<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_0003k" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>A Decade of Pluralism or Ideology?</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">The document has a title page which contains:
document title
title part</note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">Language used in quote: <foreign id="English">English</foreign></note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">1</p><p n="date">2005-05</p><p n="module title">Latin American Themes and Problems</p><p n="module code">AM101</p><p n="genre family">Essay</p><p n="discipline">Comparative American Studies</p><p n="disciplinary group">AH</p><p n="grade">M</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">4897</p><p n="number of s-units">122</p><p n="number of p">31</p><p n="number of tables">0</p><p n="number of figures">4</p><p n="number of block quotes">10</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">0</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">0</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">40.1</p><p n="average s-units per p">3.9</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">m</p><p n="year of birth">1984</p><p n="first language">Dutch</p><p n="education">OSA</p><p n="course">Comparative American Studies</p><p n="student ID">0003</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><docTitle><titlePart><hi rend="bold">A Decade of Pluralism or Ideology?</hi> <hi rend="bold"> Cultural representations of nationalism in the nineteen-thirties in Argentina, Brazil and Mexico</hi></titlePart></docTitle><titlePart>Latin American Themes and Problems<name type="student name"/>, student number <name type="student ID"/>. Word count: 4861. May 2005</titlePart></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Introduction</head><p n="p1.31"><s n="s1.7;p1.31">When we talk about the 1930s in terms of social history, we often refer to the strong emergence of ideology into the public domain. </s><s n="s2.7;p1.31">Moreover, for Latin American countries, the first half of the twentieth century marked the coming of 'modernity'.<ref target="BAWE_0003k-ftnote.001"/> Other factors, however, such as immigration and a rumbling social hierarchy in the aftermath of slavery, tended to influence society in more informal ways. </s><s n="s3.7;p1.31">Self-representation through culture was usually closest at hand for the lower classes, and often provided a colourful means of communicating a multi-faceted message. </s><s n="s4.7;p1.31">In this essay we shall look at such cultural representations in Argentina, Brazil and Mexico, and assess the extent to which they contributed to the construction of a national identity. </s><s n="s5.7;p1.31">Naturally, art forms such as dance and music were, even though powerful, not the only way of expressing one's national sentiments. </s><s n="s6.7;p1.31">The first films with sound managed to reach a mass audience and demonstrated what it was like to be a true Argentine, or Brazilian, in a light package. </s><s n="s7.7;p1.31">Moreover, the aftermath of key political events (Argentina, the 'infamous decade' after the fall of Yrigoyen; Brazil, the 1930 coup of Vargas; Mexico, the heritage of the revolution) and the subsequent split among the people brought a new literature of thinkers focussing with urgency upon 'national character and the metaphysics of the Mexican, Argentinian or Brazilian 'being''.<ref target="BAWE_0003k-ftnote.002"/> The assessment of each country's culture climate thus provides interesting insights into the attempts made at a culturally constructed nationhood. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0003k-ftnote.001"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Edwin Williamson, <hi rend="italic">The Penguin History of Latin America</hi>, (London, 1992), p. 513. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0003k-ftnote.002"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Gerald Martin, <hi rend="italic">Journeys through the Labyrinth.</hi> </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1"><hi rend="italic">Latin American Fiction in the Twentieth Century</hi>, (London/New York, 1989), p. 67. </s></p></note></div1><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="bold">Argentina: 'a land of exiles'</hi><ref target="BAWE_0003k-ftnote.003"/><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0003k-ftnote.003"><p n="pn1.1"> Jorge Luis Borges, cited in in Gabriel Nouzeilles and Graciela Montaldo (eds.), <hi rend="italic">The Argentina Reader. History, Culture, Politics</hi>, (Durham, London, 2002), p. 1.</p></note></head><p n="p2.31"><s n="s1.7;p2.31">The Argentina of the 1930s saw increasing modernisation and a changing political climate. </s><s n="s2.7;p2.31">This did not leave the notion of nationalism untouched; and, after the social positivism of the Irigoyen government that was overthrown in 1930, cultural representations of the Argentine nation became increasingly ambiguous. </s><s n="s3.7;p2.31">The 'Década Infame' brought a reconsideration of Argentine patriotism and the essence of 'Argentineness'. </s><s n="s4.7;p2.31">A new definition of the Argentine identity proved, however, not quite unproblematic. </s><s n="s5.7;p2.31">A nation of immigrants, Argentina had many faces and was, with the coming of further modernity and political maturing of the masses, thrust into a further set of cultural disparities. </s><s n="s6.7;p2.31">These were based upon dichotomies as varied as those of machismo versus feminism, the European-orientated metropolitan versus the patriotic gaucho, and that of the definition of a high culture versus that of commercially formed mass culture. </s><s n="s7.7;p2.31">Essentially, thus, the concept of <hi rend="italic">argentinidad</hi> was politically and culturally utilised in a multitude of ideological representations: 'The references to a collective ideal of the <hi rend="italic">argentinidad</hi> were continuous [...], although this ideal was defined in the most imprecise way and was basically the product of the whims and wishful thinking of the ideologues who wrote on the subject, more than an ideal that could be identified empirically as a trait of Argentina's culture'.<ref target="BAWE_0003k-ftnote.004"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0003k-ftnote.004"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Carlos Escudé, 'The Case of Argentina', <seg type="URL" n="http://www.argentina-rree.com/documentos/culture_escude.htm"/>, (2000), viewed 2 May 2005. </s></p></note><p n="p3.31"><s n="s1.2;p3.31">An early elaboration upon Argentine culture and its forms can be found in Sarmiento's <hi rend="italic">Facundo</hi> of 1845. </s><s n="s2.2;p3.31">Sarmiento, Argentina's president between 1868 and 1874, regarded the countryside, inhabited by the mestizo gaucho Argentine, as uncivilized, chaotic - even barbarous: 'dirty children covered in rags, living amid packs of dogs; men stretched out on the ground, in utter inactivity; filth and poverty everywhere'.<ref target="BAWE_0003k-ftnote.005"/> The country's biggest cities, on the contrary, contained every aspect 'that characterizes cultured people'.<ref target="BAWE_0003k-ftnote.006"/> Later, the popular poem about <hi rend="italic">Martín Fierro</hi> created a distinction between the good, heroic and patriotic gaucho, and the barbarous and violent bad gaucho.<ref target="BAWE_0003k-ftnote.007"/> The early twentieth century thereafter saw a complete rehabilitation of the gaucho icon, when it was presented as an example of <hi rend="italic">argentinidad</hi> in an increasingly immigrant-dominated society.<ref target="BAWE_0003k-ftnote.008"/> This was, however, merely a constructed and idealised identity, and the by the end of the twenties, the plurality of immigrant cultures were gaining space from more traditional social and cultural dance clubs with names like 'The Patriotic Gauchos'.<ref target="BAWE_0003k-ftnote.009"/> In its stead came a new form of dance, less courteous and more fitting in the context of the big metropolis Buenos Aires: tango. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0003k-ftnote.005"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Domingo Faustino Sarmiento, <hi rend="italic">Facundo.</hi> </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1"><hi rend="italic">Civilization and Barbarism</hi>, (London, 2003), p. 51. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0003k-ftnote.006"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid, p. 52. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0003k-ftnote.007"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">William Rowe and Vivian Schelling, <hi rend="italic">Memory and Modernity.</hi> </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1"><hi rend="italic">Popular Culture in Latin America</hi>, (London, New York, 1991), p. 34. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0003k-ftnote.008"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Leopoldo Logunes, 'National Identity in a Cosmopolitan Society' in <hi rend="italic">The Argentina Reader</hi>, p. 209. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0003k-ftnote.009"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">William Rowe and Vivian Schelling, <hi rend="italic">Memory and Modernity.</hi> </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1"><hi rend="italic">Popular Culture in Latin America</hi>, (London, New York, 1991), p. 35. </s></p></note><p n="p4.31"><s n="s1.4;p4.31">The thirties in Argentina were marked by modernising development from above and from below. </s><s n="s2.4;p4.31">The tango started its ascending popularity from below.<ref target="BAWE_0003k-ftnote.010"/> A dance of immigrants, it was originally popular in the packed, miserable and crime-ridden suburbs of Buenos Aires. </s><s n="s3.4;p4.31">Its association with knife-fighting and gangs was famously put into words in Borges' short story 'Streetcorner Man' of 1933. </s><s n="s4.4;p4.31">In it, two gang leaders head into confrontation on an illegal tango party. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0003k-ftnote.010"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid, p. 35. </s></p></note><quote lang="English">'The only reason I don't carve you up is because you sicken me,' the Butcher said to Rosendo, threatening to strike him. That same moment, La Lujanera threw her arms around the Butcher's neck, fixing those eyes of hers on him, and said in a fury, 'Let him alone - making us think he was a man.' For a minute of so [the Butcher] was bewildered. Then, wrapping his arms around La Lujanera, he called to the musicians to play loud and strong, and he ordered the rest of us to dance. <ref target="BAWE_0003k-ftnote.011"/></quote><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0003k-ftnote.011"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Jorge Luis Borges, <hi rend="italic">The Aleph and Other Stories</hi>, (London, 1973), p. 27. </s></p></note><p n="p5.31"><s n="s1.2;p5.31">These aspects - machismo, violence, illegitimacy, made dancing the tango into a rebellious act, associated with characters on the edge of society, devoid of patriotic virtue or morality.<ref target="BAWE_0003k-ftnote.012"/> This was soon to change, as the tango was brought to Europe and became popular in the salons of avant-garde Paris. </s><s n="s2.2;p5.31">Before this shift, the tango only gained marginal recognition as a truly Argentine metropolitan dance, as in the poem 'Milonga' by Oliverio Girondo. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0003k-ftnote.012"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Rowe and Schelling, <hi rend="italic">Memory and Modernity.</hi> </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1"><hi rend="italic">Popular Culture in Latin America</hi>, (London, New York, 1991), p. 36. </s></p></note><quote lang="English">Males whose bodies rupture in a ritual court, their heads sunk low between their shoulders, their lips thick with coarse remarks. Females with their nervous rumps, bits of foam at their armpits and their eyes looking much too oily.<ref target="BAWE_0003k-ftnote.013"/></quote><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0003k-ftnote.013"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Oliverio Girondo, 'Poems to Be Read on a Trolley Car' in <hi rend="italic">The Argentina Reader</hi>, p. 252-53. </s></p></note><figure id="BAWE_0003k-pic.001"><head>The tango was initially danced by men only.</head></figure><p n="p6.31"><s n="s1.3;p6.31">A second exponent of tango, nevertheless, soon found through tango a new formula for political criticism, woven into poetical lyrics. </s><s n="s2.3;p6.31">The song 'Cambalache' by Enrique Santos Discépolo, written in the early thirties, counterposed the liberal positivistic nationalism with a gloomy, destructive view of the new Argentina. </s><s n="s3.3;p6.31">'Those that don't cry don't feed', Santos sang, 'and those that don't steal are fools'.<ref target="BAWE_0003k-ftnote.014"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0003k-ftnote.014"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Enrique Santos Discépolo, 'Cambalache', in <hi rend="italic">The Argentina Reader</hi>, p. 267. </s></p></note><p n="p7.31"><s n="s1.5;p7.31">Despite this loathing with politics, the middle class adopted the tango as an aspect of the new, dynamic and modern culture that Argentina was now adopting. </s><s n="s2.5;p7.31">In this, the cinema played a big, yet not unambiguous role. </s><s n="s3.5;p7.31">Argentina was steadily adopting the Northern American cinema culture. </s><s n="s4.5;p7.31">In 1930, around a thousand film screens could be found throughout the country.<ref target="BAWE_0003k-ftnote.015"/> However, already by 1926 an estimated 95 percent of screen time was filled by films from the United States.<ref target="BAWE_0003k-ftnote.016"/> Tango reached a mass audience when sound was added to cinema films, and a number of glamorous films with appealing tunes lent this formula its great success.<ref target="BAWE_0003k-ftnote.017"/> Unfortunately this also caused tango to become a mass cultural phenomenon, alienated from its former basis of charismatic metropolitanism. </s><s n="s5.5;p7.31">By the late thirties, fifty such films were produced a year, also serving as a charming and successful export product for other Latin American countries. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0003k-ftnote.015"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">John King, <hi rend="italic">Magic Reels.</hi> </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1"><hi rend="italic">A History of Cinema in Latin America,</hi> (London, New York, 2000), p. 9. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0003k-ftnote.016"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid, p. 11. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0003k-ftnote.017"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid, p. 38. </s></p></note><p n="p8.31"><s n="s1.5;p8.31">While the metropolitan immigrant gained commercial ground and mass appeal, other cultural forces were working from above, posing questions at a more political and intellectual level. </s><s n="s2.5;p8.31"><hi rend="italic">X-Ray of the Pampa</hi> was published in 1933, melancholically referring back to inner country Argentina as a real source of Argentine national identity. </s><s n="s3.5;p8.31">In the essay, Ezequiel Martínez Estrada accused the central government in the metropolitan centre of cultivating city values at the cost of the 'countryside, which is full of truth and life'.<ref target="BAWE_0003k-ftnote.018"/> Minority immigrant groups, faced by the dominance and lack of understanding of the overwhelmingly Catholic Hispanic cultural majority, attempted to secure themselves a place within the Argentine identity. </s><s n="s4.5;p8.31">Jews, who were often particularly victim of racism, attempted, with relative success, to bring the issue to attention in the theatre. </s><s n="s5.5;p8.31">A number of Jewish playwrights wrote plays on Argentine Jewish families and their cultural problems, with strategies varying from the complete abandonment of any distinctive Jewish identity',<ref target="BAWE_0003k-ftnote.019"/> to the incorporation [...] of Argentina's many immigrant groups, their concerns and their idioms'.<ref target="BAWE_0003k-ftnote.020"/> The playwright César Tiempo in 1937 even won a prestigious theatre prize for one such play with a light-hearted tone, <hi rend="italic">Pan criollo</hi> [<hi rend="italic">Native Bread</hi>]. <ref target="BAWE_0003k-ftnote.021"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0003k-ftnote.018"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ezequiel Martínez Estrada, 'X-Ray of the Pampa' in <hi rend="italic">The Argentina Reader</hi>, p. 262. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0003k-ftnote.019"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">David William Foster, <hi rend="italic">Cultural Diversity in Latin American Literature</hi> (Albuquerque, 1994), p. 97. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0003k-ftnote.020"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Foster, <hi rend="italic">Cultural Diversity</hi>, pp. 110-11. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0003k-ftnote.021"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid, p. 111. </s></p></note><p n="p9.31"><s n="s1.4;p9.31">The literature of Jorge Luis Borges forms a totally separate category in Argentina's intellectual life of the thirties. </s><s n="s2.4;p9.31">Whilst his outlook towards nationalism was complicated and peculiar, both the political left and right came to agree 'that what the fictions display is mastery'.<ref target="BAWE_0003k-ftnote.022"/> Initially, Borges became part of the capital's avant-garde poetry circle, whose most famous representative was Oliverio Girondo, and his first published poems still breathe the excitement of metropolitan life. </s><s n="s3.4;p9.31">By the 1930s, however, Borges came to reject Martín Fierro's nativistic idea of <hi rend="italic">argentinidad</hi> as well as the avant-garde as 'infantile disorders'.<ref target="BAWE_0003k-ftnote.023"/> Perhaps due to some drastic changes in Borges' life over the second half of the thirties, among which the death of his father, a short period of serious illness and a mindless job as a librarian, Borges increasingly came to see all experiences as individual.<ref target="BAWE_0003k-ftnote.024"/> Increasingly, Borges disapproved of simplistic, mono-cultured concepts of Argentine nationalism, in which some groups were downplayed in favour of others. </s><ref target="BAWE_0003k-ftnote.025"/><s n="s4.4;p9.31">Instead, he proposed that </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0003k-ftnote.022"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Jean Franco, <hi rend="italic">Critical Passions: Selected Essays</hi> (Durham/London, 1999), p. 328. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0003k-ftnote.023"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Martin, <hi rend="italic">Journeys through the Labyrinth</hi>, p. 153. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0003k-ftnote.024"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Franco, <hi rend="italic">Critical Passions</hi>, p. 331. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0003k-ftnote.025"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Martin, <hi rend="italic">Journeys through the Labyrint</hi>, p. 153. </s></p></note><quote lang="English">we cannot limit ourselves to purely Argentine subjects in order to be Argentine; for either being Argentine is an inescapable act of fate - and in that case we shall be so in all events - or being Argentine is a mere affectation, a mask.<ref target="BAWE_0003k-ftnote.026"/></quote><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0003k-ftnote.026"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Jorge Luis Borges, cited in Martin, <hi rend="italic">Journeys through the Labyrinth</hi>, p. 155. </s></p></note><p n="p10.31"><s n="s1.1;p10.31">This deconstructionist view of <hi rend="italic">argentinidad</hi> cut short all aspirations toward an inward-looking, 'authentic' national identity, and hence, Borges later came to be regarded as an early exponent of postmodernism.<ref target="BAWE_0003k-ftnote.027"/> Throughout the 1930s, Borges was still very much in search of new values, comparing the Argentine with the Jew, whom, according to him both had no 'particular national tradition', while the entrenchment in a narrow set of national values was 'negative, or, at the very least, uncreative'.<ref target="BAWE_0003k-ftnote.028"/> Soon, he would move on to a path of displacing, often surprising literary creations,<ref target="BAWE_0003k-ftnote.029"/> revealing elements of both ironic genius as elitism. <ref target="BAWE_0003k-ftnote.030"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0003k-ftnote.027"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Franco, <hi rend="italic">Critical Passions</hi>, p. 327. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0003k-ftnote.028"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid, pp. 330-31. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0003k-ftnote.029"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Williamson, <hi rend="italic">The Penguin History</hi>, p. 516. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0003k-ftnote.030"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Martin, <hi rend="italic">Journeys through the Labyrint</hi>, p. 159. </s></p></note></div1><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="bold">Brazil: 'All hail! This samba's going to end in jail'</hi> <ref target="BAWE_0003k-ftnote.031"/><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0003k-ftnote.031"><p n="pn1.1"> Patrícia Galvão, 'Where They about Rosa Luxemburg', in <hi rend="italic">The Brazil Reader,</hi> p. 166.</p></note></head><p n="p11.31"><s n="s1.4;p11.31">The 1930s as a definable decade for Brazil started in October 1930, when a group of young army officers overthrew the long-standing São Paulo oligarchy and brought GetúlioVargas to power - a dictatorship that was to last until 1954.<ref target="BAWE_0003k-ftnote.032"/> This inaugurated an era of modernisation to the country, and a new search for a national identity. </s><s n="s2.4;p11.31">Gradually, art forms and cultural expressions of the lowest classes (in Brazil this mainly meant the former slaves) became accepted by a wider public, and eventually even representative as national symbols.<ref target="BAWE_0003k-ftnote.033"/> Dances like the <hi rend="italic">samba</hi> and <hi rend="italic">capoeira</hi> and the carnival of Rio de Janeiro - though often in commercialised and regularised forms- now became celebrated aspects of the Brazilian national identity. </s><s n="s3.4;p11.31">The film genre of the <hi rend="italic">chanchada</hi> came hereby to play an important role, as it familiarised people from the cities with the cultural life of the <hi rend="italic">favelas</hi>, the neighbourhoods of the poor black people, revealing 'its misery and at the same time its tremendous beauty'.<ref target="BAWE_0003k-ftnote.034"/> Literature and poetry, on the contrary, became increasingly politicised throughout the thirties. </s><s n="s4.4;p11.31">Already in 1931, many of the writers in the Modernist movement were aware of the ideological clash that the Vargas government was driving the cultural community into.<ref target="BAWE_0003k-ftnote.035"/> This drove a number of intellectuals to the Communists' side and often into imprisonment, as they presented a 'proletarian nation' in their work.<ref target="BAWE_0003k-ftnote.036"/> The most lasting national cultural legacy, nonetheless, comes from the <hi rend="italic">bambas</hi> of the <hi rend="italic">favelas</hi>. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0003k-ftnote.032"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Williamson, <hi rend="italic">The Penguin History</hi>, pp. 416-22. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0003k-ftnote.033"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Robert Stam, <hi rend="italic">Tropical Multiculturalism.</hi> </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1"><hi rend="italic">A Comparative History of Race in Brazilian Cinema and Culture</hi>, (London, 1997), p. 80. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0003k-ftnote.034"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid, p. 82. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0003k-ftnote.035"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Mike Gonzales and David Treece, <hi rend="italic">The Gathering of Voices.</hi> </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1"><hi rend="italic">The Twentieth-Century Poetry of Latin America</hi>, (London, New York, 1992), p. 154. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0003k-ftnote.036"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Martin, <hi rend="italic">Journeys through the Labyrinth</hi>, pp. 69-72. </s></p></note><p n="p12.31"><s n="s1.7;p12.31">While in the early decades of the twentieth century public concerts of <hi rend="italic">samba</hi> were out of question, the 1930s marked a slow shift toward toleration of the music and dance. </s><s n="s2.7;p12.31">Whereas previously lovers of <hi rend="italic">samba</hi> 'had to sing it far from the police',<ref target="BAWE_0003k-ftnote.037"/> gradually a case was being made for acceptance of "black" art forms. </s><s n="s3.7;p12.31">Amidst the still prevalent racism in Brazil, Gilberto Freyes presented his theory of 'racial democracy' in 1933 with the publishing of his book <hi rend="italic">The Masters and the Slaves</hi>. </s><s n="s4.7;p12.31">In it, Freyes argued that the contribution of Afro Brazilians added to the rich cultural mix in which Brazilian tradition was embedded.<ref target="BAWE_0003k-ftnote.038"/> It has been argued, in fact, that consumption of Afro Brazilian food and music were already prevalent among all classes in a discrete sense since the nineteenth century. </s><s n="s5.7;p12.31">However, now supported by the state, who saw in the lower classes an important element for the maintenance of the status quo, the <hi rend="italic">samba</hi> culture increasingly gained space in the public sphere.<ref target="BAWE_0003k-ftnote.039"/> The gatherings and parties held in the house of Tia Ciata have been said to serve as a microcosmic example of Brazilian society. </s><s n="s6.7;p12.31">Each room in her house had different musical genre performances, with in the front rooms -near to the street- respectable dances such as the polka, and toward the back <hi rend="italic">samba</hi> and percussive, "ethnic" rhythms.<ref target="BAWE_0003k-ftnote.040"/> Over time, as the <hi rend="italic">samba</hi> gained momentum and respectability, it started to refine and develop in a multitude of exponents. </s><s n="s7.7;p12.31">Fusing African rhythms and European tonal scales into a more accessible style, the <hi rend="italic">samba</hi> now became acceptable for the wealthier white classes. <ref target="BAWE_0003k-ftnote.041"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0003k-ftnote.037"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Stam, <hi rend="italic">Tropical Multiculturalism</hi>, p. 80. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0003k-ftnote.038"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid, p. 79. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0003k-ftnote.039"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Paul Austerlitz, 'Review of <hi rend="italic">The Mystery of Samba</hi>', <seg type="URL" n="http://www.tau.ac.il/eial/X_2/austerl.html"/>, (1999), viewed 10 May 2005. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0003k-ftnote.040"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Rowe and Schelling, <hi rend="italic">Memory and Modernity</hi>, p. 129. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0003k-ftnote.041"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Austerlitz, 'Review of <hi rend="italic">The Mystery of Samba</hi>'. </s></p></note><p n="p13.31"><s n="s1.4;p13.31">Central to the <hi rend="italic">samba</hi> scene in the <hi rend="italic">favelas</hi> were the <hi rend="italic">batuqueiros</hi>, or <hi rend="italic">bambas</hi>. </s><s n="s2.4;p13.31">These dancers performed the <hi rend="italic">capoeira</hi>, a self-defence technique disguised as a dance, which had been developed by runaway slaves.<ref target="BAWE_0003k-ftnote.042"/> In street carnivals, where performers paraded through the streets, the <hi rend="italic">bambas</hi> were singled out for their particular talent for improvised dancing. </s><s n="s3.4;p13.31">As the carnival was becoming bigger, it became also more organised. </s><s n="s4.4;p13.31">So-called <hi rend="italic">Escolas de Samba</hi> (<hi rend="italic">samba</hi> schools) started to predominate the street carnival, now participating in officially organised competitions for monetary prizes and social recognition.<ref target="BAWE_0003k-ftnote.043"/> Thus, gradually, the <hi rend="italic">samba</hi> culture came to serve as a means for increasing respectability and social mobility, with the <hi rend="italic">samba</hi> schools as benefactors of neighbourhoods, bringing education and increasing unity in Rio de Janeiro. <ref target="BAWE_0003k-ftnote.044"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0003k-ftnote.042"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Rowe and Schelling, <hi rend="italic">Memory and Modernity</hi>, p. 129. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0003k-ftnote.043"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid, p. 136. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0003k-ftnote.044"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">W.W. Norton, 'Samba: Mass Culture from the Bottom Up', <seg type="URL" n="http://www.wwnorton.com/worlds/ch10/gcd.htm"/> (2002), viewed 10 May 2005. </s></p></note><p n="p14.31"><s n="s1.3;p14.31">Whether empowering the black lower classes, or simply reducing their contribution to 'the picturesque and the folkloric',<ref target="BAWE_0003k-ftnote.045"/> sure is that <hi rend="italic">samba</hi> contributed to Brazilian nation-building as it transcended the regional differences and immensely varying dialects.<ref target="BAWE_0003k-ftnote.046"/> Over time, the <hi rend="italic">samba</hi> thus became a national symbol.<ref target="BAWE_0003k-ftnote.047"/> The production of Brazilian films brought a major contribution in the transformation of <hi rend="italic">samba</hi> into a mass culture, and thus to some extent in the emancipation of black Brazilians. </s><s n="s2.3;p14.31">With the coming of sound in films, the most popular film genre became, as had been the case in Argentina, a light story incorporating popular songs. </s><s n="s3.3;p14.31">The Brazilian version of such films was the <hi rend="italic">chanchada</hi>, which, although never entirely unambiguous, has been described in its widest sense as 'the generic name given to all the comedies and musical comedies, with popular pretensions'.<ref target="BAWE_0003k-ftnote.048"/> As could be expected, Rio de Janeiro emerged as the centre of Brazilian cinema in the 1930s,<ref target="BAWE_0003k-ftnote.049"/> closely linked to the <hi rend="italic">samba</hi> schools and the carnivals, in the sense that <hi rend="italic">chanchada</hi> films embraced similar values and were often released around the time of carnival.<ref target="BAWE_0003k-ftnote.050"/> In films such as <hi rend="italic">Alô Alô Brasil</hi> (1935), featuring Brazilian film star Carmen Miranda, and <hi rend="italic">Alô Alô Carnaval</hi> (1936), featuring her sister Aurora, blacks played minor roles as musicians in the songs.<ref target="BAWE_0003k-ftnote.051"/> The presence of blacks in <hi rend="italic">chanchadas</hi>, however marginal, were rather significant as they meant the open incorporation of "black culture" in Brazilian national culture. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0003k-ftnote.045"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Stam, <hi rend="italic">Tropical Multiculturalism</hi>, p. 80. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0003k-ftnote.046"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Norton, 'Samba: Mass Culture from the Bottom Up'. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0003k-ftnote.047"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Rowe and Schelling, <hi rend="italic">Memory and Modernity</hi>, p. 131. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0003k-ftnote.048"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">King, <hi rend="italic">Magical Reels</hi>, p. 55. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0003k-ftnote.049"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid, p. 55. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0003k-ftnote.050"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Stam, <hi rend="italic">Tropical Multiculturalism</hi>, p. 83. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0003k-ftnote.051"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid, p. 81. </s></p></note><p n="p15.31"><s n="s1.3;p15.31">The extent to which the Vargas government influenced the incorporation of <hi rend="italic">samba</hi> culture is blurred. </s><s n="s2.3;p15.31">Although Vargas showed some minor active support for the movement by founding the National Institute of Educational Film (INCE) in 1937, which was to serve national integration, this institute was actually short-lived, while the number of long feature films decreased toward the end of the decade.<ref target="BAWE_0003k-ftnote.052"/> Moreover, the culture of the <hi rend="italic">favelas</hi> brought with it the 'dialectic of <hi rend="italic">malandragem</hi>', which was a concept of using the established order for illegal interests and to avoid 'the punishment of work'. </s><s n="s3.3;p15.31"><hi rend="italic">Malandragem</hi> attempted to function alongside the order of society, thus obscuring the brisk line between order and disorder.<ref target="BAWE_0003k-ftnote.053"/> It is therefore likely that these cultural shifts were rather a wave that accompanied the emancipation of the former slave classes than a conscious attempt at nation-building for the Estado Novo. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0003k-ftnote.052"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">King, <hi rend="italic">Magical Reels</hi>, p. 56. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0003k-ftnote.053"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Rowe and Schelling, <hi rend="italic">Memory and Modernity</hi>, p. 128. </s></p></note><figure id="BAWE_0003k-pic.002"><head>Tarsila do Amaral, <hi rend="italic">Amomoeiro </hi></head></figure><p n="p16.31"><s n="s1.6;p16.31">Traditional high culture in Brazil's thirties was preoccupied with another struggle, that against the right-wing dictatorship.<ref target="BAWE_0003k-ftnote.054"/> Much of the intelligentsia and artistic scene, united in the Popular Front, chose the direction of regionalism. </s><s n="s2.6;p16.31">Upper class painter Tarsila do Amaral, after having explored aspects in Brazilian nativism in her work, now started to focus on representing traditional every-day scenes of the countryside.<ref target="BAWE_0003k-ftnote.055"/> According to Gilberto Freyes, the 'soul of Brazil' was to be sought in the rural north, which was struck by poverty and where many sugar plantations were situated.<ref target="BAWE_0003k-ftnote.056"/> The regionalist movement, however, incorporated a wide range of ideologies opposed to the Vargas regime. </s><s n="s3.6;p16.31">Raquel de Queirós, in 1930 published <hi rend="italic">Back in '15</hi>, a novel on the plight of the northern region during the famine period of 1915. </s><s n="s4.6;p16.31">In 1937 she was imprisoned for her radical Trotskyist political outlook.<ref target="BAWE_0003k-ftnote.057"/> Regionalism thus often served to point class inequalities in a radical leftist outlook of Brazilian society. </s><s n="s5.6;p16.31">A less covered ideological viewpoint is provided in Patrícia Galvão's 'proletarian novel' <hi rend="italic">Industrial Park</hi> (1933), where she focuses on the injustice of the Brazilian system. </s><s n="s6.6;p16.31">Elements of nationalism are obviously subjugated for the purpose of class struggle, as in the following passage. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0003k-ftnote.054"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Gonzales and Treece, <hi rend="italic">The Gathering of Voices</hi>, p. 152. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0003k-ftnote.055"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Carol Damian and Christina Mehrtens, 'Tarsila and the 1920s', in Robert M. Levine and John J. Crocitti (eds.), <hi rend="italic">The Brazil Reader.</hi> </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1"><hi rend="italic">History, Culture, Politics</hi>, (London, 1999) p. 315. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0003k-ftnote.056"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Martin, <hi rend="italic">Journeys through the Labyrinth</hi>, p. 66. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0003k-ftnote.057"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid, p. 69. </s></p></note><quote lang="English">Alfredo tries to like the simple and poorly prepared food. He feels happy. He doesn't find Brazil abhorrent, as before. He doesn't need to drown his individualistic irritability in any picturesque scenes, neither in the ovens of the Sahara nor in theglacial Arctic Ocean. He wants them to leave him in Braz. Eating that revolutionary food. Without longing for Cairo hotels or French wines.<ref target="BAWE_0003k-ftnote.058"/></quote><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0003k-ftnote.058"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Galvão, 'Where They about Rosa Luxemburg', in <hi rend="italic">The Brazil Reader,</hi> p. 169. </s></p></note><p n="p17.31"><s n="s1.2;p17.31">The way in which this passage points out any Brazilian national identity is clearly negative; it argues in favour of a 'simple', social Brazil instead of an internationally incorporated, capitalist nation. </s><s n="s2.2;p17.31">Elements of Brazilian grassroots national identity are ironically referred to as expressions of a repressed class: </s></p><quote lang="English"> All Hail! All Hail! This samba's Going to land in jail.<ref target="BAWE_0003k-ftnote.059"/></quote><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0003k-ftnote.059"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid, in <hi rend="italic">The Brazil Reader</hi>, p. 166. </s></p></note><p n="p18.31"><s n="s1.2;p18.31">Other poetry, although not as explicitly communist as Galvão (who, for this reason, spent four years in prison as a political prisoner), focussed on the rough and oppressive facets of the regime through from a national perspective. </s><s n="s2.2;p18.31">The liberal Mário de Andrade in his poem 'The Wagon of Misery' ridicules the regime with deliberate spelling mistakes. </s></p><quote lang="English"> Bump! The Wagon of Misery' s here From the Eyetalian carnival! Old Ma Misery is dressed in <hi rend="italic">honour</hi> The colour of the brass of our age Gathering spittle behind her. The colonil the generul the kaptin The pure the heroic the well-meaning Childrin of the Brazilyun factory Colombus's people are swinging. <ref target="BAWE_0003k-ftnote.060"/></quote><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0003k-ftnote.060"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Gonzales and Treece, <hi rend="italic">The Gathering of Voices</hi>, p. 157. </s></p></note><p n="p19.31"><s n="s1.2;p19.31">Brazilian literature and poetry of the modernist movement revealed thus revealed a highly politicised, polemic style, much embedded in the opposition of the dictatorship and united through this opposition rather than through a shared outlook of Brazilian nationalism proper. </s><s n="s2.2;p19.31">Throughout the thirties, Brazil remained still very much in search of a form of national cohesion.<ref target="BAWE_0003k-ftnote.061"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0003k-ftnote.061"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Martin, <hi rend="italic">Journeys through the Labyrinth</hi>, p. 68. </s></p></note></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Mexico: 'A dark Indian, grateful to the party'</head><p n="p20.31"><s n="s1.3;p20.31">In Mexico, the revolution proved to be the 'defining event', shaping the nation for the remainder of the century.<ref target="BAWE_0003k-ftnote.062"/> For many, the success of the 1910s revolution was the culmination of revolutionary nationalism: the yoke of a century of oppression had now been thrown off. </s><ref target="BAWE_0003k-ftnote.063"/><s n="s2.3;p20.31">In an attempt to create a "new man" and "new woman", the new government turned to art, popular culture and education to create a new sense of nationhood for the Mexicans.<ref target="BAWE_0003k-ftnote.064"/> The new Mexican nation now came to incorporate and celebrate a new group of inhabitants that had been previously been seen as passive and inferior: the Mexican Indian. </s><s n="s3.3;p20.31">The art of the 1920s and 1930s is thus marked by a fresh interest in Aztec art and architecture, and a celebration of the 'Indian race' can be found in nationalistic essays. <ref target="BAWE_0003k-ftnote.065"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0003k-ftnote.062"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Gilbert M. Joseph and Timothy J. Henderson (eds.), <hi rend="italic">The Mexico Reader.</hi> </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1"><hi rend="italic">History, Culture, Politics</hi>, (Durham, London, 2002), p. 333. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0003k-ftnote.063"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Alan Knight, 'Popular Culture and the Revolutionary State in Mexico, 1910-1940', <hi rend="italic">Hispanic American Historical Review</hi>, 74:3 (1994), p. 395. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0003k-ftnote.064"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid, p. 395. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0003k-ftnote.065"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Alexander S. Dawson, 'From Models for the Nation to Model Citizens: <hi rend="italic">Indigenismo</hi> and the 'Revindication' of the Mexican Indian, 1920-1940', <hi rend="italic">Journal of Latin American Studies</hi>, 30 (1998), p. 285. </s></p></note><p n="p21.31"><s n="s1.2;p21.31">By the thirties, a new political machine, the National Revolutionary Party, had been put in place and the work of myth-making of Mexican heroes of the revolution started. </s><s n="s2.2;p21.31">This period has been marked the post-revolutionary period, as legitimising the state, as well as instilling a paradoxical blend of conservative revolutionary sentiments in Mexicans.<ref target="BAWE_0003k-ftnote.066"/> This new ideological stream, <hi rend="italic">indigenismo</hi>, was reflected in the mural paintings of Mexico's most prominent modern artists, in the work of intellectuals and in the number of epic novels about the revolution that were published in the twenties and thirties.<ref target="BAWE_0003k-ftnote.067"/> It has, however, been held that for the government the aim was not 'to 'indigenize' Mexico, but to 'Mexicanize' the Indian'.<ref target="BAWE_0003k-ftnote.068"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0003k-ftnote.066"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Knight, 'Popular Culture and the Revolutionary State', p. 393. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0003k-ftnote.067"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Martin, <hi rend="italic">Journeys through the Labyrinth</hi>, p. 45. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0003k-ftnote.068"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Rowe and Schelling, <hi rend="italic">Memory and Modernity</hi>, p. 184. </s></p></note><p n="p22.31"><s n="s1.3;p22.31"><hi rend="italic">Indiginismo</hi> involved the reinterpretation of both the Indian and the nation.<ref target="BAWE_0003k-ftnote.069"/> It involved, on the one hand, the creation of the myth of the radically social and progressive new Mexican nation, and on the other hand, a glorification of the Mexican Indian and their past.<ref target="BAWE_0003k-ftnote.070"/> By the 1930s, however, the emphasis was shifted from race to culture.<ref target="BAWE_0003k-ftnote.071"/> An interesting example can be found in the issue of bank notes. </s><s n="s2.3;p22.31">The depiction of a 'native woman, wearing traditional costume, standing before the Aztec calendar stone' was never circulated, and instead the images of Zaragoza and Madero were preferred.<ref target="BAWE_0003k-ftnote.072"/> Now, notions of 'literacy, nationalism, notions of citizenship, sobriety, hygiene, and hard work'<ref target="BAWE_0003k-ftnote.073"/> became part of the ideological mores; the Indians were believed to possess those qualities to an exceptional extent. </s><s n="s3.3;p22.31">They were, in fact, 'rational political actors with modern sensibilities'.<ref target="BAWE_0003k-ftnote.074"/> To fit this singular representation, a new kind of Indian peasant emerged in literature: </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0003k-ftnote.069"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Dawson, '<hi rend="italic">Indigenismo</hi> and the 'Revindication' of the Mexican Indian', p. 282. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0003k-ftnote.070"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid, p. 285. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0003k-ftnote.071"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid, p. 294. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0003k-ftnote.072"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Joseph M. Galloy, 'Symbols of Identity and Nationalism in Mexican and Central-American Currency', <seg type="URL" n="http://www.chass.utoronto.ca/french/as-sa/ASSA-No9/JG2.html"/> , (2000), viewed 11 May 2005. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0003k-ftnote.073"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Knight, 'Popular Culture and the Revolutionary State', p. 395. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0003k-ftnote.074"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Dawson, '<hi rend="italic">Indigenismo</hi> and the 'Revindication' of the Mexican Indian', p. 279. </s></p></note><quote lang="English">A dark Indian dressed in white, who wants to learn to read and write in Spanish and is grateful to the party; his children are healthy and can choose whether to stay in the rancho or migrate to the new life in the cities. <ref target="BAWE_0003k-ftnote.075"/></quote><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0003k-ftnote.075"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Martin, <hi rend="italic">Journeys through the Labyrinth</hi>, p. 46. </s></p></note><p n="p23.31"><s n="s1.3;p23.31">Another aspect of this <hi rend="italic">indigenismo</hi> were the rural ballads, <hi rend="italic">corridos</hi>. </s><s n="s2.3;p23.31">They are transformed to be used on mass scale, into three-minute songs to be played on the radio Agustín Lara became the icon of this typically Mexican musical exponent.<ref target="BAWE_0003k-ftnote.076"/> Often in appraisal of revolutionary heroes, <hi rend="italic">corridos</hi> with their simple rhyme were easy to remember and thus accessible to considerable percentage of illiterate Mexicans. </s><s n="s3.3;p23.31">The following is an example of a corrido describing the death of Francisco Villa. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0003k-ftnote.076"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Rowe and Schelling, <hi rend="italic">Memory and Modernity</hi>, p. 100. </s></p></note><quote lang="English"> Poor Pancho Villa! His destiny was very sad; To die in an ambush And in the middle of the way. He went, leaving Parral handling his horse, the brave general author of "La Cucaracha" [the cockroach] [own translation] <ref target="BAWE_0003k-ftnote.077"/></quote><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0003k-ftnote.077"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Armando de Maria y Campos, <hi rend="italic">La Revolucion Mexicana a Traves de los Corridos Populares</hi>, (Mexico City 1962), p. 245. </s></p></note><p n="p24.31"><s n="s1.2;p24.31">Yet another way in which the revolutionaries were eternalised and epitomised as heroes of the Mexican nation was through the paintings of Diego Rivera, Jose Orozco and David Alfaro Siqueiros.<ref target="BAWE_0003k-ftnote.078"/> These modern artists - 'Los Tres Grandes'<ref target="BAWE_0003k-ftnote.079"/>- had started in the twenties to experiment with mural painting, a style which they thereafter used effectively for the depiction of Mexico's indigenous history, scenes of the revolution and of the modern, industrialised, progressive state. </s><s n="s2.2;p24.31">Supported and often commissioned by the government, these painters fulfilled 'the visual component of [the] need to create that Mexican citizen necessary for the survival of the post-Revolutionary state'.<ref target="BAWE_0003k-ftnote.080"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0003k-ftnote.078"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Martin, <hi rend="italic">Journeys through the Labyrinth</hi>, p. 46. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0003k-ftnote.079"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Anthony W. Lee, 'Mural Painting and Social Revolution in Mexico: 1920-1940, Art of the New Order - Review', <seg type="URL" n="http://www.findarticles.com/p/articles/mi_m0425/is_1_58/ai_54517220#continue"/>, (1999) viewed 11 May 2005. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0003k-ftnote.080"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid. </s></p></note><figure id="BAWE_0003k-pic.003"><head>Orozco, <hi rend="italic">Zapatistas</hi></head></figure><figure id="BAWE_0003k-pic.004"><head>Rivera, <hi rend="italic">Modern Industry</hi></head></figure><p n="p25.31"><s n="s1.4;p25.31">In terms of literature, the 1930s saw a continuation of the style employed in the twenties. </s><s n="s2.4;p25.31">Epic works with 'the man on horseback',<ref target="BAWE_0003k-ftnote.081"/> the archetypical revolutionary also depicted in the mural paintings of the post-revolutionaries. </s><s n="s3.4;p25.31">Where Guzmán had in 1926 recounted his memories in the revolutionary army of Villa with <hi rend="italic">The Eagle and the Serpent</hi>, Gregorio López y Fuentes in 1932 created an epic hero out of Zapata. </s><s n="s4.4;p25.31">His novel <hi rend="italic">The Land</hi> provided the sense of heroic Mexican leadership that legitimised the Mexican revolution. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0003k-ftnote.081"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Martin, <hi rend="italic">Journeys through the Labyrinth</hi>, p. 38. </s></p></note><quote lang="English"> It is passed on in whispers, in huddles, by men at the plough and women at the well. He has been seen. So it's true he's not dead... 'Do you know who saw him? Old Albina. [...] This is what she told me: "[...] I recognised him straight off. Hat pushed back, like always, them same trousers with the buttons, and that moustache you could tell a mile away. [...]" ' <ref target="BAWE_0003k-ftnote.082"/></quote><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0003k-ftnote.082"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid, p. 45. </s></p></note><p n="p26.31"><s n="s1.3;p26.31">There were, of course, also many writers opposed to this mythical image. </s><s n="s2.3;p26.31">In fact, the Mexican revolution brought no generation of poets of any significance; most of them were to be sought with the defeated reactionaries.<ref target="BAWE_0003k-ftnote.083"/> Gómez Marín, who lived in London at the time wrote in a letter: 'From here, Mexico is something dark and bloody'.<ref target="BAWE_0003k-ftnote.084"/> Moreover, the <hi rend="italic">corrido</hi>, typical Mexican icon, could naturally also be used for other purposes than the glorification of the revolution. </s><s n="s3.3;p26.31">The following extract comes from a <hi rend="italic">corrido</hi> praising the bravery of a christian Cristero rebellion. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0003k-ftnote.083"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Gonzales and Treece, <hi rend="italic">The Gathering of Voices</hi>, p. 29. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0003k-ftnote.084"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Franco, <hi rend="italic">Critical Passions</hi>, p. 456. </s></p></note><quote lang="English"> Then the general said: "I am prepared to grant you a pardon If you will tell me Where I might find the local priest." Valentín promptly answered him: "That I cannot say; I'd rather you kill me Than give up a friend."... Before they shot him, Before he went up the hill, Valentín cried: "O mother of Guadalupe! For your religion they will kill me."...<ref target="BAWE_0003k-ftnote.085"/></quote><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0003k-ftnote.085"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Anonynous, 'The Ballad of Valentín of the Sierra', in Gilbert M. Joseph and Timothy J. Henderson (eds.), <hi rend="italic">The Mexico Reader.</hi> </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1"><hi rend="italic">History, Culture, Politics</hi>, (Durham, London, 2002), p. 420. </s></p></note><p n="p27.31"><s n="s1.3;p27.31">Arguably, illiteracy rates stood in the way of effective nation-building through literature. </s><s n="s2.3;p27.31">Some have thus asserted that 'it [was] film, not writing, which create[d] [...] the 'imagined community' of the nation'.<ref target="BAWE_0003k-ftnote.086"/> Indeed, when the first film with sound was made in 1931, it was sponsored by state funds.<ref target="BAWE_0003k-ftnote.087"/> Such films, which like in the case of Argentina and Brazil, were capable of reaching as mass audience, dealt with popular themes such as destitute prostitutes (which, of course, fuelled the <hi rend="italic">macho</hi> discourse of the frail woman in need of protection) and went accompanied by popular tunes, most notably those of Agustín Lara's soundtracks.<ref target="BAWE_0003k-ftnote.088"/> The state was quite involved in the ideological message such films conveyed. </s><s n="s3.3;p27.31">Thus when the Soviet filmmaker Eisenstein, visiting Mexico, planned to make a film on the history of Mexico, the government withdrew their subsidies for fear that such a film might cause an outrage amongst the oligarchic <hi rend="italic">hacienda</hi> owners.<ref target="BAWE_0003k-ftnote.089"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0003k-ftnote.086"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">King, <hi rend="italic">Magical Reels</hi>, p. 99. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0003k-ftnote.087"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid, p. 42. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0003k-ftnote.088"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid, p. 42. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0003k-ftnote.089"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid, p. 44. </s></p></note><p n="p28.31"><s n="s1.5;p28.31">In the aftermath of the revolutionary decade (1910-1920) in Mexico, the new authorities then energetically set about constructing the archetype of a new "ideal Mexican". </s><s n="s2.5;p28.31">This was based upon a renewed enthusiasm about the Indian, who was henceforth to be considered as a part of the new Mexican state. </s><s n="s3.5;p28.31"><hi rend="italic">Indigenismo</hi> and, from the late 1920s into the thirties, revolutionary myth making played a big role in such representations. </s><s n="s4.5;p28.31">Nationalism was hence instilled through popular means: mural painting, the <hi rend="italic">corrido</hi> ballad, film, and to some extent, epic literature. </s><s n="s5.5;p28.31">By actively interfering and negotiating these art forms, the state sought to channel the multitude of opinions into a glorification of the new <hi rend="italic">Mexicanidad</hi>. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Conclusion </head><p n="p29.31"><s n="s1.9;p29.31">Nationhood is a fluid concept. </s><s n="s2.9;p29.31">It can be manipulated to incorporate whatever ideological ideas, and exclude or obscure what one does not find appropriate to it. </s><s n="s3.9;p29.31">Argentina and Brazil in the 1930s saw the beginning of a great transformation of nationhood, while Mexico had already begun that project directly after the Mexican revolution. </s><s n="s4.9;p29.31">Although often the state attempted to control cultural representations of its nationalism, intellectuals and poorer minorities did not let this happen easily. </s><s n="s5.9;p29.31">Borges refused to accept a simple, patriotic nationalism, thereby brilliantly revealing the paradoxes underlying such a concept; in Vargas' Brazil, the government was in a constant state of war with its poets and authors on the left, while former slaves of the <hi rend="italic">favelas</hi> proved to be able to provide Brazil's most uniting and lasting national identity. </s><s n="s6.9;p29.31">Perhaps the Mexican state can be said to have succeeded best at imposing an official picture of nationalism. </s><s n="s7.9;p29.31">Their <hi rend="italic">corridos</hi> and murals invoked a revolutionary-ideological <hi rend="italic">Mexicanidad</hi>, party-style; and it would only be by the 1990s that Mexican natives started to wage war on that identity. </s><s n="s8.9;p29.31">Nevertheless, the successes in Mexico also knew their limits. </s><s n="s9.9;p29.31">The Catholic religion proved impossible to curb, while student protests in the 1970s already revealed the violent antagonism underlying the picture of Mexico that the government offered its people. </s></p><p n="p30.31"><s n="s1.7;p30.31">Representations of national identity, then, are inherently linked with political ideology and power. </s><s n="s2.7;p30.31">Brazilian authors with tendencies toward communism provide the example; they employ a highly politicised image of the 'true Brazilian' proletariat. </s><s n="s3.7;p30.31">In Argentina, such representations resulted in two opposing views, the gauchoesque patriot, modelled after <hi rend="italic">Martin Fierro</hi> stood in contrast to the liberal modernist 'rational' Argentine inspired by Sarmiento's <hi rend="italic">Facundo</hi>. </s><s n="s4.7;p30.31">When tango, the voice of the minorities, and Borges came into the equation, a mono-cultured Argentine ideal became more complicated and troublesome. </s><s n="s5.7;p30.31">Similar in each of the three countries discussed, however, are the influences of 'lower' cultural forms. </s><s n="s6.7;p30.31">Tango, initially despised by all respectable layers of society, became the epitome of <hi rend="italic">Argentinidad</hi> and proud export product after its success in the Parisian salons, while the <hi rend="italic">samba</hi> of the Brazilian blacks became a national virtue. </s><s n="s7.7;p30.31">In Mexico, the <hi rend="italic">corrido</hi> and new popular film both served the ideal of praising the spiritual idealism that belonged inherently to the Mexican man and woman, as opposed to the violent pragmatism of Northern American men, and the dehumanised star beauty of the Hollywood actress. </s></p><p n="p31.31"><s n="s1.5;p31.31">Nationalism in all countries discussed, became increasingly represented in popular ways, reaching out to a mass audience. </s><s n="s2.5;p31.31">The constructors of such nationalistic forms sought to reach out to an unprecedented number of people, instilling upon them these new forms of nationalism. </s><s n="s3.5;p31.31">In Brazil, <hi rend="italic">chanchadas</hi> united the country despite its immense differences in dialect, while in Mexico the party did their best to involve nationalism in every possible cultural and educational aspect. </s><s n="s4.5;p31.31">In Argentina it culminated in the decade of Peron's popular dictatorship. </s><s n="s5.5;p31.31">It can thus be said, that across these nations, the 1930s transformed nationalism into a popular and far-reaching construct. </s></p></div1></body><back><div1 type="bibliography"><head rend="bold">Bibliography</head><p>Anonynous, 'The Ballad of Valentín of the Sierra', in Gilbert M. Joseph and Timothy J. Henderson (eds.), <hi rend="italic">The Mexico Reader. History, Culture, Politics</hi>, (Durham, London, 2002)</p><p>Austerlitz, Paul, 'Review of <hi rend="italic">The Mystery of Samba</hi>', <seg type="URL" n="http://www.tau.ac.il/eial/X_2/austerl.html"/>, (1999)</p><p>Borges, Jorge Luis, <hi rend="italic">The Aleph and Other Stories</hi>, (London, 1973)</p><p>Damian, Carol, and Mehrtens, Christina, 'Tarsila and the 1920s', in Levine, Robert M., and Crocitti, John J. (eds.), <hi rend="italic">The Brazil Reader. History, Culture, Politics</hi>, (London, 1999)</p><p>Dawson, Alexander S., 'From Models for the Nation to Model Citizens: <hi rend="italic">Indigenismo</hi> and the 'Revindication' of the Mexican Indian, 1920-1940', <hi rend="italic">Journal of Latin American Studies</hi>, 30 (1998)</p><p>Discépolo, Enrique Santos, 'Cambalache', in Nouzeilles, Gabriel, and Montaldo, Graciela (eds.), <hi rend="italic">The Argentina Reader. History, Culture, Politics</hi>, (Durham, London, 2002)</p><p>Escudé, Carlos, 'The Case of Argentina', <seg type="URL" n="http://www.argentina-rree.com/documentos/culture_escude.htm"/>, (2000)</p><p>Estrada, Ezequiel Martínez, 'X-Ray of the Pampa' in Nouzeilles, Gabriel and Montaldo, Graciela (eds.), <hi rend="italic">The Argentina Reader. History, Culture, Politics</hi>, (Durham, London, 2002)</p><p>Foster, David William, <hi rend="italic">Cultural Diversity in Latin American Literature</hi>, (Albuquerque, 1994)</p><p>Franco, Jean, <hi rend="italic">Critical Passions: Selected Essays</hi>, (Durham/London, 1999)</p><p>Galloy, Joseph M., 'Symbols of Identity and Nationalism in Mexican and Central-American Currency', <seg type="URL" n="http://www.chass.utoronto.ca/french/as-sa/ASSA-No9/JG2.html"/> , (2000)</p><p>Galvão, Patrícia, 'Where They about Rosa Luxemburg', in Levine, Robert M., and Crocitti, John J. (eds.), <hi rend="italic">The Brazil Reader. History, Culture, Politics</hi>, (London, 1999)</p><p>Girondo, Oliverio, 'Poems to Be Read on a Trolley Car' in Nouzeilles, Gabriel, and Montaldo, Graciela (eds.), <hi rend="italic">The Argentina Reader. History, Culture, Politics,</hi> (Durham, London, 2002)</p><p>Gonzales, Mike, and Treece, David, <hi rend="italic">The Gathering of Voices. The Twentieth-Century Poetry of Latin America</hi>, (London, New York, 1992)</p><p>Joseph, Gilbert M., and Henderson, Timothy J. (eds.), <hi rend="italic">The Mexico Reader. History, Culture, Politics</hi>, (Durham, London, 2002)</p><p>King, John, <hi rend="italic">Magic Reels. A History of Cinema in Latin America</hi>, (London, New York, 2000)</p><p>Knight, Alan, 'Popular Culture and the Revolutionary State in Mexico, 1910-1940', <hi rend="italic">Hispanic American Historical Review</hi>, 74:3 (1994)</p><p>Lee, Anthony W., 'Mural Painting and Social Revolution in Mexico: 1920-1940, Art of the New Order - Review', <seg type="URL" n="http://www.findarticles.com/p/articles/mi_m0425/is_1_58/ai_54517220#continue"/>, (1999)</p><p>Logunes, Leopoldo, 'National Identity in a Cosmopolitan Society' in Nouzeilles, Gabriel, and Montaldo, Graciela (eds.), <hi rend="italic">The Argentina Reader. History, Culture, Politics</hi>, (Durham, London, 2002)</p><p>Maria y Campos, Armando de, <hi rend="italic">La Revolucion Mexicana a Traves de los Corridos Populares</hi>, (Mexico City 1962)</p><p>Martin, Gerald, <hi rend="italic">Journeys through the Labyrinth. Latin American Fiction in the Twentieth Century</hi>, (London/New York, 1989)</p><p>Norton, W.W., 'Samba: Mass Culture from the Bottom Up', <seg type="URL" n="http://www.wwnorton.com/worlds/ch10/gcd.htm"/> (2002)</p><p>Rowe, William, and Schelling, Vivian, <hi rend="italic">Memory and Modernity. Popular Culture in Latin America</hi>, (London, New York, 1991)</p><p>Sarmiento, Domingo Faustino, <hi rend="italic">Facundo. Civilization and Barbarism</hi>, (London, 2003)</p><p>Stam, Robert, <hi rend="italic">Tropical Multiculturalism. A Comparative History of Race in Brazilian Cinema and Culture</hi>, (London, 1997)</p><p>Williamson, Edwin, <hi rend="italic">The Penguin History of Latin America</hi>, (London, 1992)</p></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
