<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_0003l" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Why did workers rather than communist reformers spearhead the Polish Solidarity movement of 1980-81?</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">Language used in quote: <foreign id="English">English</foreign></note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">deleted: page numbers
</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">2</p><p n="date">2006-03</p><p n="module title">Eastern Europe Since 1918</p><p n="module code">HI124</p><p n="genre family">Essay</p><p n="discipline">History</p><p n="disciplinary group">AH</p><p n="grade">M</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">2248</p><p n="number of s-units">50</p><p n="number of p">11</p><p n="number of tables">0</p><p n="number of figures">0</p><p n="number of block quotes">1</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">0</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">0</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">45.0</p><p n="average s-units per p">4.5</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">m</p><p n="year of birth">1984</p><p n="first language">Dutch</p><p n="education">OSA</p><p n="course">History</p><p n="student ID">0003</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><titlePart>Eastern Europe since 1918, Third class essay by <name type="student name"/>. March 2006 Word count: 2244.</titlePart><docTitle><titlePart rend="bold">Why did workers rather than communist reformers spearhead the Polish Solidarity movement of 1980-81? </titlePart></docTitle></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="section"><p n="p1.11"><s n="s1.4;p1.11">The advent of the Solidarity strikes and protests halfway 1980 struck a serious blow at the Polish communist regime. </s><s n="s2.4;p1.11">Whilst it provided a powerful response of workers to the repressive character and 'determination [of the Polish regime] to maintain [the political and economic] systems, whatever their human costs and lack of legitimacy',<ref target="BAWE_0003l-ftnote.001"/> an important questions comes to mind. </s><s n="s3.4;p1.11">Where from came this powerful articulation of demands, and of 'the most powerful, sophisticated and advanced working-class movement yet seen, certainly in the 'communist' sphere and perhaps anywhere in the world'?<ref target="BAWE_0003l-ftnote.002"/> To answer this question, it may be fruitful to study the emergence of new class societies in Eastern Europe,<ref target="BAWE_0003l-ftnote.003"/> paradoxical when matched with Marxist thought. </s><s n="s4.4;p1.11">Economic and political developments throughout the 1970s united with a blend of national-historical and wider Eastern European economic grievances to prepare the ferment for 'a new generation of protesting workers with a clearly different way of articulating their grievances [as] a strictly Polish phenomenon'.<ref target="BAWE_0003l-ftnote.004"/> In this essay I will have a closer look at the development of a class spirit among Polish workers, and argue that it was from their socio-economic situation that discord arose. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0003l-ftnote.001"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Walter D. Connor, 'Social Change and Stability in Eastern Europe' in <hi rend="italic">Problems of Communism</hi>, vol. 26 (1977), p. 16. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0003l-ftnote.002"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Colin Barker, <hi rend="italic">Festival of the Oppressed.</hi> </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1"><hi rend="italic">Solidarity, Reform and Revolution in Poland 1980-81</hi> (London: 1986), p. 11. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0003l-ftnote.003"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Walter D. Connor, 'Social Change and Stability in Eastern Europe' in <hi rend="italic">Problems of Communism</hi>, vol. 26 (1977), p. 29. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0003l-ftnote.004"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Jadwiga Staniszkis, <hi rend="italic">The Dynamics of the Breakthrough in Eastern Europe.</hi> </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1"><hi rend="italic">The Polish Experience</hi> (Berkeley: 1991), p. 107-8. </s></p></note><p n="p2.11"><s n="s1.3;p2.11">The prehistory of the Solidarity movement was, most importantly, sparked by an increasing crystallisation of a "class consciousness" within the ranks of the Polish work force, many of whom were becoming convinced 'that they [could only] improve their lot collectively'.<ref target="BAWE_0003l-ftnote.005"/> Despite official state rhetoric, there was an increasingly realistic attitude to the existence of a new dominant class made up of 'the intelligentsia as a whole rather than just the bureaucracy narrowly defined';<ref target="BAWE_0003l-ftnote.006"/> a class of highly educated, better-rewarded technocrats and managers, charged with the daily affairs of increasing efficiency of production and economic policy making. </s><s n="s2.3;p2.11">While official policy claimed to pursue a policy of egalitarianism, the reality behind these claims was only limited. </s><s n="s3.3;p2.11">The producing classes, those of the workers and peasants, found themselves on the same position in the material hierarchy as before, while a decrease in real standards of living were initially concealed only by the relative success of social mobility.<ref target="BAWE_0003l-ftnote.007"/> However, the stretch of social mobility had its limits and by the 1970s a new generation of workers, unfamiliar with opportunities for social mobility, many of them younger than 25 years of age, began to form an increasingly articulate and assertive sense of collective grievances.<ref target="BAWE_0003l-ftnote.008"/> While according to the orthodox theory of communism the party was the vanguard of the workers, epitomising its real interest, workers on the work floor reportedly referred to 'management in the third person, reserving "we" for themselves'.<ref target="BAWE_0003l-ftnote.009"/> This clearly meant the beginning of an independently developing working class, at odds with the intelligentsia and a regime increasingly alienated from Poland's new social reality. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0003l-ftnote.005"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Walter D. Connor, 'Social Change and Stability in Eastern Europe' in <hi rend="italic">Problems of Communism</hi>, vol. 26 (1977), p. 28. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0003l-ftnote.006"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Georg Konrád and Ivan Szelényi, <hi rend="italic">The Intellectuals on the Road to Class Power</hi> (Brighton: 1979), p. xiv-v. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0003l-ftnote.007"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Walter D. Connor, 'Social Change and Stability in Eastern Europe' in <hi rend="italic">Problems of Communism</hi>, vol. 26 (1977), p. 17. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0003l-ftnote.008"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">R.J. Crampton, <hi rend="italic">Eastern Europe in the Twentieth Century - And After</hi> (London/New York, 2005), p. 364. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0003l-ftnote.009"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Konrád and Szelényi, <hi rend="italic">The Intellectuals</hi>, p. 223. </s></p></note><p n="p3.11"><s n="s1.2;p3.11">Similar to the England of the early nineteenth century, the creation of a new Eastern European working class indeed took place within the rather short timeframe of one or two generations. </s><s n="s2.2;p3.11">Over the decades after the Second World War, an average of nearly fifty percent of the younger peasantry came 'to form the new working class, [and] to create the social drama of a new life, a new world'.<ref target="BAWE_0003l-ftnote.010"/> As their direct socio-economic interests began to reveal themselves in increasing antagonism with the state-directed economic policy, Polish workers, as a class <hi rend="italic">an sich</hi> and with an agenda different even from that of the oppositional intelligentsia, more and more often became involved in violent confrontations with the state.<ref target="BAWE_0003l-ftnote.011"/> Social discord became increasingly apparent, and ''Poles murdered by Poles, workers murdered by a 'Workers' State', became the symbol for all their accumulated grievances'.<ref target="BAWE_0003l-ftnote.012"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0003l-ftnote.010"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Connor, 'Social Change and Stability in Eastern Europe', p. 21. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0003l-ftnote.011"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid, p. 28. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0003l-ftnote.012"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Garton Ash, <hi rend="italic">The Polish Revolution</hi>, p. 12. </s></p></note><p n="p4.11"><s n="s1.5;p4.11">Timothy Garton Ash's assertion that 'December 1970 [was] the single most important date in the pre-history of Solidarity',<ref target="BAWE_0003l-ftnote.013"/> may provide further insight into the extent that Solidarity was connected to the working class. </s><s n="s2.5;p4.11">Its reaction to the government's implementation of food price increases revealed signs of a growing unity and singular purpose of action. </s><s n="s3.5;p4.11">When the government resolved to give up its policy of consistent non-unemployment 'aimed at forcing greater productivity through the use of threat of unemployment as an incentive for better and more efficient work',<ref target="BAWE_0003l-ftnote.014"/> this seemed a direct threat to workers at large. </s><s n="s4.5;p4.11">After strikes and violent confrontations throughout January 1971, the government withdrew its economic reform plans, while Gomułka was forced to step down as a consequence of his unpopular repressive measures and number of deaths as a direct consequence thereof.<ref target="BAWE_0003l-ftnote.015"/> This political outcome was seen by many protesters as a direct result of their protests, which served made workers realise where there strength lay.<ref target="BAWE_0003l-ftnote.016"/> Throughout the 1970s, many strikes followed, and although the regime 'exacted its revenge on the workers', resulting in many workers being 'sacked, arrested, beaten, jailed',<ref target="BAWE_0003l-ftnote.017"/> strikers usually got what they wanted. </s><s n="s5.5;p4.11">This, and the fact that many protests 'involved a large group which was generally representative of the worker population as a whole',<ref target="BAWE_0003l-ftnote.018"/> accounts for the growth of an awareness that the economic situation of workers was connected with, and could be influenced by, their political role as an occupational group. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0003l-ftnote.013"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid, p. 12. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0003l-ftnote.014"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Jan B. de Weydenthal, 'Poland: Workers and Politics' in Jan F. Triska and Charles Gati (eds.), <hi rend="italic">Blue-Collar Workers in Eastern Europe</hi> (London: 1981), p. 193. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0003l-ftnote.015"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Crampton, <hi rend="italic">Eastern Europe</hi>, p. 359. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0003l-ftnote.016"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Weydenthal, 'Poland: Workers and Politics', p. 194. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0003l-ftnote.017"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Barker, <hi rend="italic">Festival of the Oppressed</hi>, p. 12. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0003l-ftnote.018"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Weydenthal, 'Poland: Workers and Politics', p. 195. </s></p></note><p n="p5.11"><s n="s1.8;p5.11">Yet, what made for the timing of this growing self-awareness? </s><s n="s2.8;p5.11">Where from came the momentum that enabled workers to start attempting to influence their economic position through strikes? </s><s n="s3.8;p5.11">The Polish communist party had, from the onset, based much of its legitimacy through the reasonably successful initiation of a process of social mobility upward. </s><s n="s4.8;p5.11">Workers were recruited from among the peasant ranks, while better-educated workers were needed to support the growing bureaucratic apparatus.<ref target="BAWE_0003l-ftnote.019"/> These developments enabled many to enter new realities that were hitherto undreamed of, creating a sense of greater equality, if not of material wealth, then of opportunity. </s><s n="s5.8;p5.11">It also sparked, however, another process, which would later develop into one of the primary reasons for the antagonism between the workers and the intelligentsia as a whole. </s><s n="s6.8;p5.11">The quick development of industries created a culture of technocracy, in which economic status became more directly related to 'a hierarchy of statuses based on diplomas, irrespective of the actual amount of work done'. </s><s n="s7.8;p5.11">This put pressures on access to higher education as a direct way of material advancement,<ref target="BAWE_0003l-ftnote.020"/> as the intelligentsia were protective of their traditionally advantaged position. </s><s n="s8.8;p5.11">The attitude of this "red bourgeoisie" was becoming an assertion '[t]hat they do and <hi rend="italic">should</hi> live better than workers'.<ref target="BAWE_0003l-ftnote.021"/> This, however, created tension, as these 'unequal patterns of allocation of social rewards' were legitimised by the class that benefited from it, 'despite the traditional systemic commitment to egalitarianism'.<ref target="BAWE_0003l-ftnote.022"/> With the decreasing flexibility in the Polish labour market, most economists and sociologists began to note a shift from 'phases of system-building to the tasks of system-maintenance'.<ref target="BAWE_0003l-ftnote.023"/> The loss of revolutionary economic appeal for the masses, however, eventually began to cost the Party members as well; 'between October 1980 and March 1981 the Party lost 216,000 members, bringing total membership below three million'.<ref target="BAWE_0003l-ftnote.024"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0003l-ftnote.019"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Connor, 'Social Change and Stability in Eastern Europe', p. 24. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0003l-ftnote.020"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Konrád and Szelényi, <hi rend="italic">The Intellectuals</hi>, p. 228. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0003l-ftnote.021"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Connor, 'Social Change and Stability in Eastern Europe', p. 26. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0003l-ftnote.022"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Weydenthal, 'Poland: Workers and Politics', p. 191. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0003l-ftnote.023"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Connor, 'Social Change and Stability in Eastern Europe', p. 25. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0003l-ftnote.024"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Garton Ash, <hi rend="italic">The Polish Revolution</hi>, p. 170. </s></p></note><p n="p6.11"><s n="s1.5;p6.11">The stagnation of social mobility can be said to have a two-sided effect. </s><s n="s2.5;p6.11">While, one the one hand, it formed a ferment for discontent because the state failed to meet the workers' expectations of equality, Eastern European 'regimes [had to], in a sense, deal with the workers they have'.<ref target="BAWE_0003l-ftnote.025"/> While the legitimating narrative came out of redistribution, 'the technocrats, like the ruling elite itself, [had] an interest in keeping labor in a dispositive position',<ref target="BAWE_0003l-ftnote.026"/> which entailed maintenance of the status quo. </s><s n="s3.5;p6.11">A further source of frustration was found in the fact that, despite repeated pledges for reform from the party leadership, very little change was noticed, while concessions were repeatedly watered down.<ref target="BAWE_0003l-ftnote.027"/> This was particularly hard to swallow since continually facts were coming to light revealing the decadent and privileged world that the small number of the party and administrative élite'<ref target="BAWE_0003l-ftnote.028"/> had created for themselves. </s><s n="s4.5;p6.11">Contradictions were experienced very starkly when any kind of protest was followed by measures on a worker's economic privileges and 'any sign of active solidarity' was immediately called 'political conspiracy'.<ref target="BAWE_0003l-ftnote.029"/> Gradually, workers began to connect their economic discontent with a wider, social picture, which thoroughly undermined the legitimacy of the state. </s><s n="s5.5;p6.11">As now the argument of economic prosperity was no longer something Gierek could count on, the social and political situation became something of a ticking bomb. <ref target="BAWE_0003l-ftnote.030"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0003l-ftnote.025"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Connor, 'Social Change and Stability in Eastern Europe', p. 29. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0003l-ftnote.026"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Konrád and Szelényi, <hi rend="italic">The Intellectuals</hi>, p. 225. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0003l-ftnote.027"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Weydenthal, 'Poland: Workers and Politics', p. 190. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0003l-ftnote.028"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Crampton, <hi rend="italic">Eastern Europe</hi>, p. 362. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0003l-ftnote.029"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Konrád and Szelényi, <hi rend="italic">The Intellectuals</hi>, p. 227. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0003l-ftnote.030"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Connor, 'Social Change and Stability in Eastern Europe', p. 32. </s></p></note><p n="p7.11"><s n="s1.3;p7.11">The decade running up to the strikes of saw an increasingly untenable paradoxical situation. </s><s n="s2.3;p7.11">According to Marxist thinking, communism provided the means to stop the alienation of the workers; yet, they were becoming increasingly alienated. </s><s n="s3.3;p7.11">This was clearly demonstrated by the slow production process of inferior quality produce.<ref target="BAWE_0003l-ftnote.031"/> By the 1980s, an observer described "the Polish situation as 'the emergence of workers as a distinct, albeit unorganized, political force and the inability of institutionalized leadership groups to integrate the workers into the existing pattern of systematic operations'.<ref target="BAWE_0003l-ftnote.032"/> It is important to note, that the origins of this alienation were, to a great extent, class-originated, coming from the specific economic grievances of the workers. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0003l-ftnote.031"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Konrád and Szelényi, <hi rend="italic">The Intellectuals</hi>, p. 226. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0003l-ftnote.032"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Weydenthal, 'Poland: Workers and Politics', p. 187. </s></p></note><p n="p8.11"><s n="s1.4;p8.11">Economic alienation eventually meant political alienation, which then began to organise itself. </s><s n="s2.4;p8.11">The strikers of 1980 were no longer easily reintegrated. </s><s n="s3.4;p8.11">They were 'far more disciplined; they were not committed to socialism or the party'<ref target="BAWE_0003l-ftnote.033"/> any longer, whereas large sections of Poland's industrial workers in 1970 were still prepared to give the regime another chance, in 1980 Lech Wałęsa bitterly reminded his co-workers of how little had been done with the workers' trust and support.<ref target="BAWE_0003l-ftnote.034"/> If the Party was not prepared to listen to their grievances anymore, the workers would organise themselves outside the state.<ref target="BAWE_0003l-ftnote.035"/> This essentially foreboded the inability to continue any profitable form of communism. </s><s n="s4.4;p8.11">As R.J. Crampton observed, </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0003l-ftnote.033"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Crampton, <hi rend="italic">Eastern Europe</hi>, p. 367. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0003l-ftnote.034"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Garton Ash, <hi rend="italic">The Polish Revolution</hi>, p. 13. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0003l-ftnote.035"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Konrád and Szelényi, <hi rend="italic">The Intellectuals</hi>, p. 227. </s></p></note><quote lang="English">'Solidarity had shown the bankruptcy of east European communism because the bulk of communism's chosen people, the workers, had looked outside the party for redress of their social grievances'.<ref target="BAWE_0003l-ftnote.036"/></quote><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0003l-ftnote.036"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Crampton, <hi rend="italic">Eastern Europe</hi>, p. 376. </s></p></note><p n="p9.11"><s n="s1.3;p9.11">We have observed that the regime became increasingly inapt to rally the support of the workers for the socialist cause, or to reasonably incorporate them within a plan economy. </s><s n="s2.3;p9.11">It is, nonetheless, important to have a closer look at the reasons that caused the process to assume such a radical working class character. </s><s n="s3.3;p9.11">Surely, there existed a strong section of "critical intelligentsia", yet their position was precarious: whereas they assumed a role as the voice of the working class, they were also 'part of the intellectual class, from which neither its structural position nor its value-system [allowed] it to secede'.<ref target="BAWE_0003l-ftnote.037"/> It is said, moreover, that moral decay could be observed across the intelligentsia - so much so, that one sociologist spoke of 'the 'semi-feudalisation' of Polish society'.<ref target="BAWE_0003l-ftnote.038"/> The success propaganda of communist society that western historians are quite familiar with, also seemed to have blinded the regime, rendering it numb to criticism or alternative ideas.<ref target="BAWE_0003l-ftnote.039"/> This hostile view, however, is only useful to a certain extent, and it is more likely that many members of the intelligentsia simply still '[had] a stake in the status quo and, therefore, support[ed] it'.<ref target="BAWE_0003l-ftnote.040"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0003l-ftnote.037"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Konrád and Szelényi, <hi rend="italic">The Intellectuals</hi>, p. 221. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0003l-ftnote.038"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Barker, <hi rend="italic">Festival of the Oppressed.</hi> </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">, p. 13. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0003l-ftnote.039"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid, p. 12. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0003l-ftnote.040"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Connor, 'Social Change and Stability in Eastern Europe', p. 27. </s></p></note><p n="p10.11"><s n="s1.1;p10.11">There were, however, also initiatives from the intelligentsia within broad daylight of the Party's political sphere, which provided powerful criticism of the way in which the state treated dissident workers.<ref target="BAWE_0003l-ftnote.041"/> And while many intellectuals desiring reform continued to trap themselves in 'an iron cage' of 'the limits of possible reform',<ref target="BAWE_0003l-ftnote.042"/> organisations such as the Committee in Defence of the Workers (KOR) set out in a number of semi-legal ways to create a bond of solidarity between workers and intellectuals, an number of them eventually becoming involved in Solidarity.<ref target="BAWE_0003l-ftnote.043"/> Examples of selfless and risk-taking initiatives are not hard to find; intellectuals such as Miroslaw Chojecki lost their jobs, continuously spent time in jail and got beaten up, in the meanwhile enabling the publication of 150 illegal books.<ref target="BAWE_0003l-ftnote.044"/> The problem of intellectualism and political involvement, however, would eventually cause problems by 1989, when, during the round table talks intellectualism gave the negotiations an air of secrecy and 'institutional horse trading'. <ref target="BAWE_0003l-ftnote.045"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0003l-ftnote.041"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Crampton, <hi rend="italic">Eastern Europe</hi>, p. 364. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0003l-ftnote.042"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Barker, <hi rend="italic">Festival of the Oppressed</hi>, p. 16. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0003l-ftnote.043"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Garton Ash, <hi rend="italic">The Polish Revolution</hi>, p. 18. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0003l-ftnote.044"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Barker, <hi rend="italic">Festival of the Oppressed</hi>, p. 15. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0003l-ftnote.045"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Jadwiga Staniszkis, <hi rend="italic">The Dynamics of the Breakthrough in Eastern Europe.</hi> </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1"><hi rend="italic">The Polish Experience</hi> (Berkeley: 1991), p. 143. </s></p></note><p n="p11.11"><s n="s1.12;p11.11">By 1970, n increasing awareness of the existence of social class was observed in Polish society. </s><s n="s2.12;p11.11">This classification was not so much based upon political affiliation as upon material wealth. </s><s n="s3.12;p11.11">Rapid industrialisation since World War Two had brought new realities urban workers, a large number of them of young age, in a setting of narrowly confined economic possibilities. </s><s n="s4.12;p11.11">When rapid economic and industrial development began to slow down and the initial success story of social mobility began to lose its stretch, problems became observable. </s><s n="s5.12;p11.11">The popular official state narrative of egalitarianism became increasingly exposed, whereas the state had little means to provide alternative justifications. </s><s n="s6.12;p11.11">In a situation that was becoming more and more complicated, the workers soon discovered the power of strike and protest, something which the regime was rather fearful of. </s><s n="s7.12;p11.11">With no alternative means of political participation, the working class was rapidly becoming self-aware and radical, while the regime, with a large number of critical intellectuals torn between the rigor of party policy and the difficulty of reform, proved unable to control economic decline and the social outcry against party elitism and decadence. </s><s n="s8.12;p11.11">A state that claimed to hold the interests of workers as its highest principle was rapidly losing support from just that group. </s><s n="s9.12;p11.11">The strikers of Solidarity were no longer easily drawn back into the folds of socialist society which had, according to them, structurally failed to improve itself. </s><s n="s10.12;p11.11">A number of critical intellectuals, however, come to the aid of the workers. </s><s n="s11.12;p11.11">The KOR created effective means of communication between different workers' groups, and bridged the gap of solidarity between intellectuals and workers. </s><s n="s12.12;p11.11">Nonetheless, the development of Solidarity must be viewed as a broad expression of workers' grievances with the sympathy and support of a number of critical intellectuals. </s></p></div1></body><back><div1 type="bibliography"><head rend="bold">Bibliography</head><p>Barker, Colin, <hi rend="italic">Festival of the Oppressed. Solidarity, Reform and Revolution in Poland 1980-81</hi> (London: 1986)</p><p>Connor, Walter D., 'Social Change and Stability in Eastern Europe' in <hi rend="italic">Problems of Communism</hi>, vol. 26 (1977)</p><p>Crampton, R.J., <hi rend="italic">Eastern Europe in the Twentieth Century - And After</hi> (London/New York, 2005)</p><p>Garton Ash, Timothy, <hi rend="italic">The Polish Revolution. Solidarity 1980-82</hi> (London: 1983)</p><p>Konrád, Georg, and Szelényi, Ivan, <hi rend="italic">The Intellectuals on the Road to Class Power</hi> (Brighton: 1979)</p><p>Staniszkis, Jadwiga, <hi rend="italic">The Dynamics of the Breakthrough in Eastern Europe. The Polish Experience</hi> (Berkeley: 1991), p. 107-8.</p><p>Weydenthal, Jan B. de, 'Poland: Workers and Politics' in Triska, Jan F., and Gati, Charles (eds.), <hi rend="italic">Blue-Collar Workers in Eastern Europe</hi> (London: 1981)</p></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
