<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_0003j" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Is Rousseau's Social Contract more convincingly seen as a text of liberal, or of totalitarian democracy?</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note/></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">1</p><p n="date">2005-05</p><p n="module title">Making of the Modern World</p><p n="module code">HI153</p><p n="genre family">Essay</p><p n="discipline">History</p><p n="disciplinary group">AH</p><p n="grade">M</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">1929</p><p n="number of s-units">42</p><p n="number of p">9</p><p n="number of tables">0</p><p n="number of figures">0</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">0</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">0</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">45.9</p><p n="average s-units per p">4.7</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">m</p><p n="year of birth">1984</p><p n="first language">Dutch</p><p n="education">OSA</p><p n="course">History</p><p n="student ID">0003</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><titlePart>Making of the Modern World Third essay (skills)<name type="student name"/> (<name type="student ID"/>) Term 3, May 2005 Word count: 1928.</titlePart><docTitle><titlePart rend="bold">Is Rousseau's Social Contract more convincingly seen as a text of liberal, or of totalitarian democracy? </titlePart></docTitle></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="section"><p n="p1.9"><s n="s1.3;p1.9">Rousseau has always been typified as an intellectual outsider; it was, however, only in the twentieth century that his socio-political theory came to be seen as a threat to the individual's liberty.<ref target="BAWE_0003j-ftnote.001"/> Emphasis thereby is often laid on his concept of a 'general will', through which personal liberty is handed over to the collective. </s><s n="s2.3;p1.9">'The citizens having but one interest', Rousseau argues, 'the people [have] but a single will'.<ref target="BAWE_0003j-ftnote.002"/> And although Rousseau favours the ballot vote, he argues for the infallibility of its ruling: 'when the opinion contrary to my own prevails, it proves nothing more than that I made a mistake, and that what I took to be the general will was not'.<ref target="BAWE_0003j-ftnote.003"/> From the point of view of Rousseau, most importantly protection should be rendered against the emergence of a minority rule, or 'particular will', rather than against the state, which, after all, represents the sovereignty of the lawgiver as it corresponds with the community's best interest, the general will. </s><s n="s3.3;p1.9">The question I will look at here is thus to what extent the critical assertion holds truth that 'the more safeguards he established against despotism, the more weapons he forged for tyranny',<ref target="BAWE_0003j-ftnote.004"/> within Rousseau's system of the social contract. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0003j-ftnote.001"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Iain Hampsher-Monk, 'Rousseau and totalitarianism: with hindsight?' in Robert Wokler (ed), <hi rend="italic">Rousseau and Liberty</hi> (Manchester/New York, 1995), p. 268. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0003j-ftnote.002"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Jean-Jacques Rousseau, <hi rend="italic">The Social Contract and Discourses</hi> (London/New York, 1952), p. 87. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0003j-ftnote.003"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Christopher Bertram, <hi rend="italic">Routledge Philosophy Guidebook to Rousseau and The Social Contract</hi> (London, 2004), p. 120. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0003j-ftnote.004"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Hampsher-Monk, 'Rousseau and totalitarianism: with hindsight?', p. 271. </s></p></note><p n="p2.9"><s n="s1.3;p2.9">Recent criticism has argued that the Cold War split has caused intellectuals to make an over-simplified distinction between 'individualistic liberalism and state collectivism', stating that Rousseau was on the totalitarian side of the argument.<ref target="BAWE_0003j-ftnote.005"/> Rousseau, however, from the outset entertains an awareness of the problem of new forms of subjugation that hide behind a powerful state, and thus sets out to construct a model for a 'form of association [...] in which each, while uniting himself with all, may still obey himself alone, and remain free as before'.<ref target="BAWE_0003j-ftnote.006"/> In this sense, Rousseau undertakes to find a form in which freedom can be exercised on a public, political level.<ref target="BAWE_0003j-ftnote.007"/> The important distinction that has to be made here though, is the type of freedom at stake. </s><s n="s2.3;p2.9">Arguing that pre-modern, pre-social man exercised an individual sovereignty free from social obligation or commitment, knew a natural, brutal kind of liberty.<ref target="BAWE_0003j-ftnote.008"/> When people come to regular interaction, they become interdependent, which goes accompanied by fierce passions.<ref target="BAWE_0003j-ftnote.009"/> It is only within society that morality comes to exist, through virtue and <hi rend="italic">pitié</hi>, a form of compassion which counters man's corruption by society.<ref target="BAWE_0003j-ftnote.010"/> What is then needed is the construction of an association in which passions are tempered and virtue is encouraged. </s><s n="s3.3;p2.9">In this sense, envisaging a social contract is merely a theoretical exercise, to find a form in which such an exercise of sovereignty can be best expressed, in other words, 'Rousseau's purpose is to discover a <hi rend="italic">rule</hi> which has <hi rend="italic">moral validity</hi>'.<ref target="BAWE_0003j-ftnote.011"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0003j-ftnote.005"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Hampsher-Monk, 'Rousseau and totalitarianism: with hindsight?', p. 268. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0003j-ftnote.006"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Rousseau, <hi rend="italic">The Social Contract</hi>, p. 12. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0003j-ftnote.007"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Patrick Neal, <hi rend="italic">Liberalism and Its Discontents</hi> (London, 1997), p. 61. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0003j-ftnote.008"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Rousseau, <hi rend="italic">The Social Contract</hi>, p. 5. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0003j-ftnote.009"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Maurizio Viroli, <hi rend="italic">Jean-Jacques Rousseau and the 'well-ordered society'</hi> (Cambridge, 1988), p. 132. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0003j-ftnote.010"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Christopher Bertram, <hi rend="italic">Routledge Philosophy Guidebook to Rousseau and The Social Contract</hi> (London, 2004), p. 19. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0003j-ftnote.011"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Viroli, <hi rend="italic">The 'well-ordered society'</hi>, p. 121. </s></p></note><p n="p3.9"><s n="s1.5;p3.9">Another point of view insists on the juxtaposition of democracy and liberalism, positioning Rousseau in a radically democratic framework.<ref target="BAWE_0003j-ftnote.012"/> Certainly, this view depends greatly on the view one takes of liberalism. </s><s n="s2.5;p3.9">Liberalism can be taken at an individual level, stressing the removal of any constraint on human action (negative liberty), and placing theory in wider context, that of the body politic (positive liberty).<ref target="BAWE_0003j-ftnote.013"/> Rousseau is quite explicit about what form of liberty we are to seek. </s><s n="s3.5;p3.9">'Man is born free; and everywhere he is in chains', he argues, 'One thinks himself the master of others, and still remains a greater slave than they'.<ref target="BAWE_0003j-ftnote.014"/> It is therefore clear that Rousseau seeks a wider answer to the question of liberty, one for which 'it is necessary to ensure that the conditions in which [people] live do not pose a threat to their survival'.<ref target="BAWE_0003j-ftnote.015"/> This condition can be brought about by the realisation that it is the best interest of all citizens to care for other's interest and well-being. </s><s n="s4.5;p3.9">Here we find the distinction that Rousseau makes between a narrow form of personal interest and a wider, more coherent form of enlightened interest, being the best for the community, and thus, indirectly, each citizen's actual will, as it secures the best-considered proposal and enjoys general support of the citizenry. </s><s n="s5.5;p3.9">Subordination to the law subsequently only becomes an exercise of one's liberty.<ref target="BAWE_0003j-ftnote.016"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0003j-ftnote.012"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Carol Blum, <hi rend="italic">Rousseau and the Republic of Virtue.</hi> </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1"><hi rend="italic">The Language of Politics in the French Revolution</hi> (Ithaca/London, 1986), p. 32. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0003j-ftnote.013"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Hampsher-Monk, 'Rousseau and totalitarianism: with hindsight?', p. 271. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0003j-ftnote.014"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Rousseau, <hi rend="italic">The Social Contract</hi>, p. 3. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0003j-ftnote.015"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Viroli, <hi rend="italic">The 'well-ordered society'</hi>, p. 112. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0003j-ftnote.016"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Bertram, <hi rend="italic">Rousseau and The Social Contract</hi>, p. 44. </s></p></note><p n="p4.9"><s n="s1.5;p4.9">Exercising one's freedom through abiding by the law is only reasonable if lawgiver and subject are the same person. </s><s n="s2.5;p4.9">This is where Rousseau takes a radically democratic stance, criticising Kant's very open assertion that law can still be legitimate only by the requirement that the requirement 'that the proposal <hi rend="italic">could</hi> have been agreed to <hi rend="italic">had</hi> the citizens been consulted and <hi rend="italic">were</hi> they fully rational'.<ref target="BAWE_0003j-ftnote.017"/> Hence Rousseau's claim that 'power indeed may be transmitted, but not the will':<ref target="BAWE_0003j-ftnote.018"/> for the general will to function, it requires the individual standpoints of each citizen. </s><s n="s3.5;p4.9">Unanimity is thereby not needed; it is in fact a sign of an unhealthy body politic. </s><s n="s4.5;p4.9">The only law that requires unanimity of all citizens is the social pact, since by this each individual hands over their individual sovereignty to the higher expression of the community.<ref target="BAWE_0003j-ftnote.019"/> Within the body politic, the general will aims to protect rather than to attack its participants, and 'it is not', therefore, 'to be assumed that any of the parties then expects to get hanged'.<ref target="BAWE_0003j-ftnote.020"/> Likewise, peace with neighbouring communities is required by natural law. </s><ref target="BAWE_0003j-ftnote.021"/><s n="s5.5;p4.9">It has therefore been claimed that the general will represents a model for the well-being of all, and thus reflects 'each individual's good or real will'.<ref target="BAWE_0003j-ftnote.022"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0003j-ftnote.017"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Neal, <hi rend="italic">Liberalism</hi>, p. 63. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0003j-ftnote.018"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Rousseau, <hi rend="italic">The Social Contract</hi>, p. 20. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0003j-ftnote.019"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid, pp. 87-88. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0003j-ftnote.020"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid, p. 28. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0003j-ftnote.021"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Hampsher-Monk, 'Rousseau and totalitarianism: with hindsight?', p. 270. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0003j-ftnote.022"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid, p. 270. </s></p></note><p n="p5.9"><s n="s1.4;p5.9">The emphasis that Rousseau lays on the collective, however, is today regarded with mistrust. </s><s n="s2.4;p5.9">After all, the functioning of the general will depends entirely upon the full dedication of the citizenry to the social contract, and we find 'no restriction of principle on what it may command in that form'.<ref target="BAWE_0003j-ftnote.023"/> It appears at times as though Rousseau puts all individual risks at right for an ideologically unified community. </s><s n="s3.4;p5.9">As soon as all sovereignty passes from the individual to the state, a greater power comes to exist which '[man] cannot use without the help of others'.<ref target="BAWE_0003j-ftnote.024"/> Contrarily, there is no 'safeguards for the individual against the state'.<ref target="BAWE_0003j-ftnote.025"/> The Rousseauean state results in collective socialisation, only rendered legitimate through the consent of its participants. </s><s n="s4.4;p5.9">In a wider interpretation of the social contract as merely a thought experiment, this socialisation obtains a somewhat enforced character. <ref target="BAWE_0003j-ftnote.026"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0003j-ftnote.023"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Bertram, <hi rend="italic">Rousseau and The Social Contract</hi>, p. 193. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0003j-ftnote.024"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Blum, <hi rend="italic">Republic of Virtue</hi>, p. 111. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0003j-ftnote.025"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Hampsher-Monk, 'Rousseau and totalitarianism: with hindsight?', p. 272. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0003j-ftnote.026"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid, p. 268. </s></p></note><p n="p6.9"><s n="s1.4;p6.9">One form of criticism of the general will draws parallels with the Jacobin rule during the French revolution. </s><s n="s2.4;p6.9">Both reveal traces of absolutist totalitarianism: 'It is absolutely necessary that evil come from others and from them alone'.<ref target="BAWE_0003j-ftnote.027"/> Despite the validity of a critique of Rousseau's reassertion that the general will is infallible (which indeed shows traces of a majority intolerance), it is difficult if not altogether impossible to find examples of the Rousseauean state in practice. </s><s n="s3.4;p6.9">Eastern block socialism, which has been suggested as imposing some for of a state-directed will upon its citizens, has been severely criticised.<ref target="BAWE_0003j-ftnote.028"/> Also the Jacobin adoption of Rousseau's general will has been seen as of symbolic value rather than a precise influence of his thought. </s><s n="s4.4;p6.9">Lacking everywhere has been the binding together of lawgiver and subject, which according to Rousseau results only in the imposition a particular will of a state governed by a political elite. <ref target="BAWE_0003j-ftnote.029"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0003j-ftnote.027"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Jean Starobinski, 'La Mise en accusation de la Société', cited in Carol Blum, <hi rend="italic">Rousseau and the Republic of Virtue.</hi> </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1"><hi rend="italic">The Language of Politics in the French Revolution</hi> (Ithaca/London, 1986), p. 218. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0003j-ftnote.028"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Blum, <hi rend="italic">Republic of Virtue</hi>, p. 32. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0003j-ftnote.029"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Hampsher-Monk, 'Rousseau and totalitarianism: with hindsight?', p. 272. </s></p></note><p n="p7.9"><s n="s1.3;p7.9">It is true that Rousseau is most concerned with the organisation of social order based upon the exercise of virtue, rather than on preserving the individual's relative freedom of action.<ref target="BAWE_0003j-ftnote.030"/> It is therefore perhaps surprising that Rousseau leans entirely on the exercise of a general will in ensuring the best for all citizens. </s><s n="s2.3;p7.9">Through this construct, Rousseau categorically denies the individual any sovereignty except for a participatory role in the community. </s><s n="s3.3;p7.9">Effectively, the state attains a strongly fortified position in which ' [t]he more the natural strengths are dead and destroyed, the more the acquired ones are great and durable, and the more solid and perfect this institution is'.<ref target="BAWE_0003j-ftnote.031"/> Such a radical step toward an active, creative form of liberalism challenges liberals into the debate of the equalisation of the citizenry, since 'serious economic inequalities destroy liberty'.<ref target="BAWE_0003j-ftnote.032"/> Nonetheless, it does not suffice to, as a consequence of this conclusion, leave all individual property and grounds for action within the confines of the community's sovereignty. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0003j-ftnote.030"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Viroli, <hi rend="italic">The 'well-ordered society'</hi>, p. 113. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0003j-ftnote.031"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Blum, <hi rend="italic">Republic of Virtue</hi>, p. 111. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0003j-ftnote.032"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Hampsher-Monk, 'Rousseau and totalitarianism: with hindsight?', p. 275. </s></p></note><p n="p8.9"><s n="s1.5;p8.9">One of Rousseau's ideas of human nature was that the strongest of human passions was <hi rend="italic">amour the soi</hi> (love of self), of which virtue and <hi rend="italic">piti é</hi>were manifestations within society.<ref target="BAWE_0003j-ftnote.033"/> 'No-one has any interest in making them [the conditions of association] burdensome to others'<ref target="BAWE_0003j-ftnote.034"/> This may be seen as a problem for the protection of the individual's rights: Rousseau does not expect the intrusion of state into the individual's life and thus includes no precautions to safeguard certain domains of private life. </s><s n="s2.5;p8.9">'If this leads to intervention in 'areas which are perceived as illiberal, such as the social and economic conditions of citizen's lives and with their beliefs and values', this is seen by Rousseau as a decision of the general will in order to secure the necessary conditions for socio-political liberty.<ref target="BAWE_0003j-ftnote.035"/> To some extent the modern welfare state can be seen as a moderate outcome of Rousseau's general will, be it on a representative basis. </s><s n="s3.5;p8.9">Executive and lawmaking government of the welfare state is now generally expected to create policy that benefits the community in a broad social sense. </s><s n="s4.5;p8.9">Taxation, health security and economic intervention are put in place to equalise conditions and ensure a minimum standard of welfare for each citizen, whereas participation in elections for government positions is open to each citizen. </s><s n="s5.5;p8.9">This form of moderate liberal welfare state, however, fails to pass the test, since in this model the law does not come from all.<ref target="BAWE_0003j-ftnote.036"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0003j-ftnote.033"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Bertram, <hi rend="italic">Rousseau and The Social Contract</hi>, p. 24. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0003j-ftnote.034"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Hampsher-Monk, 'Rousseau and totalitarianism: with hindsight?', p. 281. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0003j-ftnote.035"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid, p, 275. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0003j-ftnote.036"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Bertram, <hi rend="italic">Rousseau and The Social Contract</hi>, p. 157. </s></p></note><p n="p9.9"><s n="s1.10;p9.9">The dichotomy between modern, individualist liberalism and the Rousseauean state lies predominantly in their different interpretations of liberty. </s><s n="s2.10;p9.9">Whereas the former stress the lack of protection for the individual in Rousseau's social contract, Rousseau in turn entertains concerns with the crude, unsocial kind of liberty that individualists profess. </s><s n="s3.10;p9.9">Rather does he see liberty in a community best exercised at the highest level, thus enhancing liberty in an ordered way.<ref target="BAWE_0003j-ftnote.037"/> For order to exist, there needs to be unity based on a reasonable principle; the social contract offers just that. </s><s n="s4.10;p9.9">As liberty exercised only on the most individual, narrow level only furthers contradiction in interests, Rousseau proposes the pursuit of community interest, which, if carried out fully, secures the welfare and safety of all its citizens. </s><s n="s5.10;p9.9">What Rousseau does not display enough attention to, however, was the fact that 'there is never a perfect fit between moral requirements of our rational nature and requirements of citizenship'.<ref target="BAWE_0003j-ftnote.038"/> This results in a lack of consideration of the nature of the general will, and its proper domain. </s><s n="s6.10;p9.9">Rousseau, on the contrary, believes in the stabilising role of the general will, and the inalienability of the will in general.<ref target="BAWE_0003j-ftnote.039"/> As the general will represent the only genuine method of determining the sovereign will of the citizenry, parallels drawn between totalitarian ideological states and Rousseau's general will are, strictly theoretical, incorrect. </s><s n="s7.10;p9.9">The problem, nonetheless, lies with the radical solution Rousseau's general will poses. </s><s n="s8.10;p9.9">Asserting that '[t]o be governed by appetite alone is slavery, while obedience to a law one prescribes to oneself is freedom',<ref target="BAWE_0003j-ftnote.040"/> leaves very little space for individual action. </s><s n="s9.10;p9.9">Thus, a community taking its legislative task to the extreme, might indeed force its citizens into abide by the law. </s><ref target="BAWE_0003j-ftnote.041"/><s n="s10.10;p9.9">The question becomes, then, not to what extent Rousseau can be used for totalitarian ends, which he explicitly sets out to prevent, but rather how a feasible system may be envisaged in which particular interpretations of the general good can obtain a stable construct in which the individual is both more protected and better positioned to criticise the state's pursuit of the general good. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0003j-ftnote.037"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Viroli, <hi rend="italic">The 'well-ordered society'</hi>, p. 38. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0003j-ftnote.038"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Christopher Bertram, <hi rend="italic">Routledge Philosophy Guidebook to Rousseau and The Social Contract</hi> (London, 2004), p. 33. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0003j-ftnote.039"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Rousseau, <hi rend="italic">The Social Contract</hi>, p. 20. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0003j-ftnote.040"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Neal, <hi rend="italic">Liberalism</hi>, p. 60. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0003j-ftnote.041"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Christopher Bertram, <hi rend="italic">Routledge Philosophy Guidebook to Rousseau and The Social Contract</hi> (London, 2004), p. 194. </s></p></note></div1></body><back><div1 type="bibliography"><head rend="underlined">Bibliography</head><p>Blum, Carol, <hi rend="italic">Rousseau and the Republic of Virtue. The Language of Politics in the French Revolution</hi> (Ithaca/London, 1986)</p><p>Bertram, Christopher, <hi rend="italic">Routledge Philosophy Guidebook to Rousseau and The Social Contract</hi> (London, 2004).</p><p>Hampsher-Monk, Iain, 'Rousseau and totalitarianism: with hindsight?' in Robert Wokler (ed), <hi rend="italic">Rousseau and Liberty</hi> (Manchester/New York, 1995).</p><p>Neal, Patrick, <hi rend="italic">Liberalism and Its Discontents</hi> (London, 1997).</p><p>Rousseau, Jean-Jacques, <hi rend="italic">The Social Contract and Discourses</hi> (London/New York, 1952).</p><p>Viroli, Maurizio, <hi rend="italic">Jean-Jacques Rousseau and the 'well-ordered society'</hi> (Cambridge, 1988).</p></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
