<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_0003i" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Analyze and assess the relationship between revolution and democracy in the works and deeds of Karl Marx / Friedrich Engels, Vladimir I. Lenin and Joseph Stalin.</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">The document has a title page which contains:
document title
title part</note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">deleted: page numbers
</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">1</p><p n="date">2005-01</p><p n="module title">Making of the Modern World</p><p n="module code">HI153</p><p n="genre family">Essay</p><p n="discipline">History</p><p n="disciplinary group">AH</p><p n="grade">M</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">1739</p><p n="number of s-units">54</p><p n="number of p">14</p><p n="number of tables">0</p><p n="number of figures">0</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">0</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">0</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">32.2</p><p n="average s-units per p">3.9</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">m</p><p n="year of birth">1984</p><p n="first language">Dutch</p><p n="education">OSA</p><p n="course">History</p><p n="student ID">0003</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><titlePart><hi rend="bold">Making of the Modern World</hi> Second Class Essay January 2005 Student no.: <name type="student ID"/></titlePart><docTitle><titlePart rend="bold">Analyze and assess the relationship between revolution and democracy in the works and deeds of Karl Marx / Friedrich Engels, Vladimir I. Lenin and Joseph Stalin. </titlePart></docTitle><titlePart>Second Class Essay for Making of the Modern World, January 2005. Student no. <name type="student ID"/></titlePart><docTitle><titlePart rend="bold">Analyze and assess the relationship between revolution and democracy in the works and deeds of Karl Marx / Friedrich Engels, Vladimir I. Lenin and Joseph Stalin. </titlePart></docTitle></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="section"><p n="p1.14"><s n="s1.1;p1.14">The first meeting of Marx and Engels in Paris in 1844 marked the starting point of a legendary friendship and cooperation of two thinkers<ref target="BAWE_0003i-ftnote.001"/> who left an enormous mark on political development in the twentieth century and whose influence, in the words of a critic, can only be compared to that of Jesus or Mohammed.<ref target="BAWE_0003i-ftnote.002"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0003i-ftnote.001"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">V.I. Lenin, 'Karl Marx', in <hi rend="italic">Marx - Engels - Marxism</hi> (Moscow, 1951), p. 17. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0003i-ftnote.002"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Peter Singer, <hi rend="italic">Marx</hi> (Rotterdam, 1999), p. 10. </s></p></note><p n="p2.14"><s n="s1.3;p2.14">As the <hi rend="italic">philosophes</hi> of the enlightenment had posed a theory of a developing and progressing world, Marx and Engels concerned themselves with applying this model of development to society. </s><s n="s2.3;p2.14">Marx placed all history in terms of classes struggling through their relation to material welfare and the means of production. </s><s n="s3.3;p2.14">As atheistic followers of Hegel, Marx and Engels thus came to believe that 'the struggle against existing wrong and prevalent evil, is also rooted in the universal law of eternal development'.<ref target="BAWE_0003i-ftnote.003"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0003i-ftnote.003"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">V.I. Lenin, 'Frederick Engels' in <hi rend="italic">Marx - Engels - Marxism</hi>, p. 58. </s></p></note><p n="p3.14"><s n="s1.3;p3.14">Marx and Engels lived at a time in which rapid industrialisation brought about exceeding disparities between the property-owning class (the bourgeoisie) and the working class (the proletariat). </s><s n="s2.3;p3.14">Believing capitalism to be only another step toward a society without class antagonisms, Marx turned to studying history and economics, while Engels in 1845 published <hi rend="italic">The Condition of the Working Class in England</hi>. </s><s n="s3.3;p3.14">In this work, Engels drew from direct experience and a wide range of sources, arguing that the working class was becoming increasingly conscious of its place and relation to the bourgeoisie, which would in the end inevitably lead to a proletarian revolution.<ref target="BAWE_0003i-ftnote.004"/> Marx and Engels were deeply impressed when, in 1844, factory workers revolted in Silesia and Bohemia.<ref target="BAWE_0003i-ftnote.005"/> They observed unrest all over Europe, and thus became convinced of the revolutionary potential of the proletariat; a potential which would eventually carry humanity into the next stage of socialism. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0003i-ftnote.004"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Lenin, 'Frederick Engels', p. 60. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0003i-ftnote.005"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Victor Kiernan, 'History', in David McLellan (ed.), <hi rend="italic">Marx: The First Hundred Years</hi> (Oxford, 1983), p. 60. </s></p></note><p n="p4.14"><s n="s1.3;p4.14">From circumstance and experience, Marx and Engels were not so much concerned with democracy, but rather with the greater concept of freedom and creating a freer society, in which, they argued, the state would cease to be necessary.<ref target="BAWE_0003i-ftnote.006"/> Parliamentary democracy, in the eyes of Marx and Engel, was nothing more than the crystallisation of the contradictory interests between the bourgeoisie and the proletariat, and could not be different. </s><s n="s2.3;p4.14">Moreover, by separating the government from civil society, 'the bourgeois state and its attendant ideas of political rights and common national interests functioned, like religion, as an opium, an illusory compensation and thus a support for the injustices of civil society'.<ref target="BAWE_0003i-ftnote.007"/> A radical change was needed for the advance at first of the proletariat and eventually of society as a whole. </s><s n="s3.3;p4.14">In their own words 'Not criticism but revolution is the driving force of history'.<ref target="BAWE_0003i-ftnote.008"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0003i-ftnote.006"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Singer, <hi rend="italic">Marx</hi>, p. 104. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0003i-ftnote.007"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">David McLellan, 'Politics', in David McLellan (ed.), <hi rend="italic">Marx: The First Hundred Years</hi> (Oxford, 1983), pp. 145-46. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0003i-ftnote.008"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Kiernan, 'History', p. 62. </s></p></note><p n="p5.14"><s n="s1.4;p5.14">Marx and Engels became convinced that they had discovered a scientific model of society and its inevitable future. </s><s n="s2.4;p5.14">Marx's drive to act upon theory soon brought him into international communist circles. </s><s n="s3.4;p5.14">After heated debate at a congress in London in 1847, Marx and Engels were commissioned to write a political programme for the Communist League. </s><s n="s4.4;p5.14">Its result, the <hi rend="italic">Communist Manifesto</hi>, can be regarded as Marx's and Engels' most outspoken vision on class struggle and the predestined faith of the proletariat.<ref target="BAWE_0003i-ftnote.009"/> 'The proletariat', the <hi rend="italic">Communist Manifesto</hi> stated confidently, 'goes through various stages of development'.<ref target="BAWE_0003i-ftnote.010"/> Then, the manifesto goes on to speak in deterministic terms that the proletarian 'mission is to destroy all previous securities for, and insurances of, individual property'. <ref target="BAWE_0003i-ftnote.011"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0003i-ftnote.009"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Singer, <hi rend="italic">Marx</hi>, pp. 14-15. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0003i-ftnote.010"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Karl Marx and Friedrich Engels, <hi rend="italic">The Communist Manifesto</hi>, cited in University of Warwick Insite, Department of History (20 November 2003), <seg type="URL" n="http://www2.warwick.ac.uk/fac/arts/history/undergrad/modules/hi153/bibliography/week_10/marxmanifesto/"/> (21 December 2004). </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0003i-ftnote.011"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid. </s></p></note><p n="p6.14"><s n="s1.7;p6.14">If this scenario were to be the inevitable course of events, the logical question would be: why? </s><s n="s2.7;p6.14">Analysing history, Marx and Engels had discovered a continuous struggle for power between a powerful minority and a weak majority. </s><s n="s3.7;p6.14">They noted that 'All previous historical movements were movements of minorities, or in the interest of minorities'. </s><s n="s4.7;p6.14">However, it seemed that the proletariat would be able to break through this tendency. </s><s n="s5.7;p6.14">'The proletarian movement is the self-conscious, independent movement of the immense majority, in the interest of the immense majority'<ref target="BAWE_0003i-ftnote.012"/>. </s><s n="s6.7;p6.14">In this sense, it can be argued that for Marx and Engels, a primitive idea of democratic, or majority, rights served to justify a complex social theory of inevitable revolutionary struggle. </s><s n="s7.7;p6.14">Convinced about the power and improvement value of the theory of class struggle, 'His [Engels'] and Marx's historical vision was optimistic about the future, tragic when it turned to the past, as a record so dreadfully bad that any sacrifice was worth while to get away from it'. <ref target="BAWE_0003i-ftnote.013"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0003i-ftnote.012"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0003i-ftnote.013"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Kiernan, 'History', p. 72. </s></p></note><p n="p7.14"><s n="s1.4;p7.14">When Lenin became leader of the Bolsheviks in the early twentieth century, a debate among Marxists had been around for nearly fifteen years concerning the best way to bring about communism. </s><s n="s2.4;p7.14">One section of the Second International of 1889, under the leadership of Bernstein, had come to embrace the idea of social democracy, and of participation in parliamentary politics. </s><s n="s3.4;p7.14">Where Marx had been careful in his wording, or more abstract in his discussion of the democracy question, Lenin was more articulate in his discussion of the matter. </s><s n="s4.4;p7.14">He briefly defined the state as 'a special organization of force: it is an organization of violence for the suppression of some class'.<ref target="BAWE_0003i-ftnote.014"/> Therefore, he argued, a revolution was the necessary agent for the transition from capitalism to socialism. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0003i-ftnote.014"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">McLellan, 'Politics', p. 167. </s></p></note><p n="p8.14"><s n="s1.5;p8.14">In 1905 Lenin wrote <hi rend="italic">Two Tactics</hi>, an article discussing the political direction Russia should take after the revolution. </s><s n="s2.5;p8.14">In this article he advocated a 'revolutionary democratic dictatorship of the proletariat and peasantry',<ref target="BAWE_0003i-ftnote.015"/> a term that Marx had used only once, in a letter to a friend. </s><ref target="BAWE_0003i-ftnote.016"/><s n="s3.5;p8.14">What contrasted the Bolsheviks from the anarchists, Lenin argued, was that Bolsheviks thought it necessary to establish a transitory government to place the proletariat firm in the seat of power. </s><s n="s4.5;p8.14">However, months before the October revolution, in April 1917, he wrote that this would be 'a state <hi rend="italic">without</hi> a standing army, <hi rend="italic">without</hi> a police opposed to the people, <hi rend="italic">without</hi> an officialdom placed above the people',<ref target="BAWE_0003i-ftnote.017"/> based on Marx's example of his view of the Paris Commune. </s><s n="s5.5;p8.14">Eventually, in Engels' words, the government would slowly 'wither away' because it would become unnecessary.<ref target="BAWE_0003i-ftnote.018"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0003i-ftnote.015"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid, p. 161. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0003i-ftnote.016"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid, pp. 154-55. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0003i-ftnote.017"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">V.I. Lenin, 'Letters on Tactics' in <hi rend="italic">Marx - Engels - Marxism</hi>, p. 58. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0003i-ftnote.018"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">McLellan, 'Politics', p. 168 </s></p></note><p n="p9.14"><s n="s1.2;p9.14">Some of Lenin's writing, though, already revealed some of the authoritarian traces that were to characterise the Bolsheviks' policy and the Soviet Union's later political development. </s><s n="s2.2;p9.14">Convinced, like Marx, of the inevitability of a proletarian revolution, he remarked: 'I said that there <hi rend="italic">can be no</hi> government (apart from a bourgeois government) in Russia <hi rend="italic">other than</hi> a government of the Soviets of Workers', Agricultural Labourers', Soldiers' and Peasants' Deputies'.<ref target="BAWE_0003i-ftnote.019"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0003i-ftnote.019"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Lenin, 'Letters on Tactics', pp. 389-90. </s></p></note><p n="p10.14"><s n="s1.5;p10.14">By 1917, Lenin observed that the key conditions were fulfilled in Russia for a proletarian revolution to take place. </s><s n="s2.5;p10.14">An imperialist war was raging over Europe, according to Marxist theory calling in the culmination of capitalism.<ref target="BAWE_0003i-ftnote.020"/> Conditions in Russia, he argued, were peculiar, as the country had already seen a revolution in February 1917. </s><s n="s3.5;p10.14">'We have existing side by side, together, simultaneously, <hi rend="italic">both</hi> the rule of the bourgeoisie [...] <hi rend="italic">and</hi> a revolutionary-democratic dictatorship of the proletariat and the peasantry, which is <hi rend="italic">voluntarily</hi> ceding power to the bourgeoisie, voluntarily transforming itself into an appendage of the bourgeoisie'.<ref target="BAWE_0003i-ftnote.021"/> According to Lenin, the masses had 'been confused, led astray and deceived' by the temporary government of Lvov and Kerensky. </s><s n="s4.5;p10.14">He adopted Trotsky's idea of 'permanent revolution', arguing that the proletariat could not stop after overthrowing the bourgeois government. </s><s n="s5.5;p10.14">By not completing the dictatorship of the proletariat, the government itself had gone over to the side of the bourgeoisie. <ref target="BAWE_0003i-ftnote.022"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0003i-ftnote.020"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Columbia Encyclopedia, 'Vladimir Ilych Lenin: Theoretician and Revolutionary', Encyclopedia.com (2004), <seg type="URL" n="http://www.encyclopedia.com/html/section/Lenin-Vl_TheoreticianandRevolutionary.asp"/> (27 December 2004). </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0003i-ftnote.021"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Lenin, 'Letters on Tactics', p. 386. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0003i-ftnote.022"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">V.I. Lenin, 'The Task of the Proletariat in Our Revolution' in <hi rend="italic">Marx - Engels - Marxism</hi>, p. 380. </s></p></note><p n="p11.14"><s n="s1.6;p11.14">In practice, much of Lenin's writing at the dawn of the October revolution appears to excuse the Bolsheviks' grasp for power and subsequent policy. </s><s n="s2.6;p11.14">Eventually, Bolshevik rule directly after the revolution proved to be highly undemocratic. </s><s n="s3.6;p11.14">In 1918, all political parties that did not support the Bolsheviks were systematically suppressed;<ref target="BAWE_0003i-ftnote.023"/> while a temporary oligarchic, highly centralised government was formed, taking in members by co-option rather than by democratic elections.<ref target="BAWE_0003i-ftnote.024"/> Rosa Luxemburg was among the prominent critics of Lenin's post-revolution, oppressive policy. </s><s n="s4.6;p11.14">'The negative, the tearing down, can be decreed; the building up, the positive cannot', she argued. </s><s n="s5.6;p11.14">According to her, Lenin was standing in the way of a democratic learning process of the proletariat. </s><s n="s6.6;p11.14">'The broadest democracy was needed', otherwise 'socialism will be decreed from behind a few official desks by a dozen intellectuals'.<ref target="BAWE_0003i-ftnote.025"/> Although Lenin argued that such policy was needed in 'defence against counterrevolution and the actual elimination of everything that contradicted the sovereignty of the people',<ref target="BAWE_0003i-ftnote.026"/> this, according to Luxemburg, was 'not the dictatorship of the proletariat, [...] but only the dictatorship of a handful of politicians'.<ref target="BAWE_0003i-ftnote.027"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0003i-ftnote.023"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">McLellan, 'Politics', p. 170. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0003i-ftnote.024"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid, p. 163. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0003i-ftnote.025"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Rosa Luxemburg, <hi rend="italic">The Russian Revolution and Leninism or Marxism?</hi> </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">, cited in University of Warwick Insite, Department of History (20 November 2003), <seg type="URL" n="http://www2.warwick.ac.uk/fac/arts/history/undergrad/modules/hi153/bibliography/week_10/rosa.marxism"/> (27 December 2004). </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0003i-ftnote.026"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">V.I. Lenin, 'Two Tactics of Social Democracy in the Democratic Revolution' in <hi rend="italic">Marx - Engels - Marxism</hi>, p. 177. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0003i-ftnote.027"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Rosa Luxemburg, <hi rend="italic">The Russian Revolution</hi>. </s></p></note><p n="p12.14"><s n="s1.1;p12.14">By 1921, Lenin described the Soviet Union as 'a workers' state with bureaucratic distortion'.<ref target="BAWE_0003i-ftnote.028"/> Trotsky actually became regretful, stating in a meeting that 'things are heading towards ruin'.<ref target="BAWE_0003i-ftnote.029"/> Stalin, however, asserted in 1918 that at the time, the 'Bolsheviks did not doubt that bourgeois parliamentarism and the bourgeois-democratic republic represented a past stage of the revolution'.<ref target="BAWE_0003i-ftnote.030"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0003i-ftnote.028"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">McLellan, 'Politics', p. 171. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0003i-ftnote.029"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Joseph Stalin, <hi rend="italic">The October Revolution</hi> (London, 1936), p. 168. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0003i-ftnote.030"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Stalin, <hi rend="italic">The October Revolution</hi>, p. 22. </s></p></note><p n="p13.14"><s n="s1.6;p13.14">It is hard to place Stalin's policy in an unmitigated Marxist light. </s><s n="s2.6;p13.14">Despite its rhetoric, the Soviet Union of Stalin appeared to many something other than socialism.<ref target="BAWE_0003i-ftnote.031"/> Theory was increasingly not matching policy. </s><s n="s3.6;p13.14">The state did not wither away, instead, a status quo of power was developing; one in which all lines came together in Moscow. </s><s n="s4.6;p13.14">An elite of scientifically based professional revolutionaries would 'show the way, formulating the program and policies, educating the people, and working out the strategy and tactics'.<ref target="BAWE_0003i-ftnote.032"/> The character of the government had changed since the October revolution. </s><s n="s5.6;p13.14">Stalin's biographer, Deutscher, wrote: 'It has assumed office as a government of the people, by the people and for the people [...][now,] it ceases to be government by the people'.<ref target="BAWE_0003i-ftnote.033"/> Indeed, it is arguable that the rapid industrialisation and agricultural reforms represented some elevated aspiration of the proletariat and peasants, however, the price of these reforms (The 1936 Great Terror and show trials) was disproportionate and tragic. </s><s n="s6.6;p13.14">Moreover, they revealed a highly undemocratic and unrepresentative government that stood separate from the masses.<ref target="BAWE_0003i-ftnote.034"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0003i-ftnote.031"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">McLellan, 'Politics', p.173. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0003i-ftnote.032"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Albert Weisbord, 'Bolshevism, Fraudulent Practice Of Democratic Centralism' cited in Weisbord.org (November/December 1976), <seg type="URL" n="http://www.weisbord.org/Fraudulent.htm"/> (28 December 2004). </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0003i-ftnote.033"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">I. Deutscher, <hi rend="italic">Stalin: A Political Biography</hi> (Oxford, 1950), p. 175. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0003i-ftnote.034"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">McLellan, 'Politics', p. 173. </s></p></note><p n="p14.14"><s n="s1.4;p14.14">The approximately hundred-year period over which the intellectual and political activity of Marx, Engels, Lenin and Stalin spread has seen the emergence of an immense social and political experiment of revolution and the move toward a communist state. </s><s n="s2.4;p14.14">The concept of democracy has over this time been much debated and scrutinised in order to deprive it of its 'bourgeois' elements. </s><s n="s3.4;p14.14">However, in the theories of Marx and Engels, there has been too little space left open for a pluralistic approach to state organisation.<ref target="BAWE_0003i-ftnote.035"/> Likewise, Lenin and Stalin never achieved the 'withering away of the state' into a 'revolutionary-democratic dictatorship of the proletariat' upon the gap that fell after the October revolution of 1917. </s><s n="s4.4;p14.14">Communism, or some pure form of democracy within society's organisation has never been achieved. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0003i-ftnote.035"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Singer, <hi rend="italic">Marx</hi>, p. 103. </s></p></note></div1></body><back><div1 type="bibliography"><head rend="underlined">Bibliography</head><p>Columbia Encyclopedia, 'Vladimir Ilych Lenin: Theoretician and Revolutionary', Encyclopedia.com (2004), <seg type="URL" n="http://www.encyclopedia.com/html/section/Lenin-Vl_TheoreticianandRevolutionary.asp"/> (27 December 2004).</p><p>Deutscher, I, Stalin: A Political Biography (Oxford, 1950)</p><p>Kiernan, Victor, 'History', in David McLellan (ed.), <hi rend="italic">Marx: The First Hundred Years</hi> (Oxford, 1983)</p><p>Lenin, V.I., 'Frederick Engels' in <hi rend="italic">Marx - Engels - Marxism</hi> (Moscow, 1951)</p><p>Lenin, V.I., 'Karl Marx', in <hi rend="italic">Marx - Engels - Marxism</hi> (Moscow, 1951)</p><p>Lenin, V.I., 'Letters on Tactics' in <hi rend="italic">Marx - Engels - Marxism</hi> (Moscow 1951)</p><p>Lenin, V.I., 'The Task of the Proletariat in Our Revolution' in <hi rend="italic">Marx - Engels - Marxism</hi> (Moscow 1951)</p><p>Lenin, V.I., 'Two Tactics of Social Democracy in the Democratic Revolution', in <hi rend="italic">Marx - Engels - Marxism</hi> (Moscow, 1951)</p><p>Luxemburg, Rosa, <hi rend="italic">The Russian Revolution and Leninism or Marxism?</hi>, cited in University of <name type="university"/> Insite, Department of History (20 November 2003), <seg type="URL" n="http://www2"/>.<name type="university"/>.ac.uk/fac/arts/history/undergrad/modules/hi153/bibliography/week_10/rosa.marxism (27 December 2004). </p><p>Marx, Karl and Engels, Friedrich, <hi rend="italic">The Communist Manifesto</hi>, University of <name type="university"/> Insite, Department of History (20 November 2003), <seg type="URL" n="http://www2"/>.<name type="university"/>.ac.uk/fac/arts/history/undergrad/modules/hi153/bibliography/week_10/marxmanifesto/ (21 December 2004).</p><p>McLellan, David 'Politics', in David McLellan (ed.), <hi rend="italic">Marx: The First Hundred Years</hi> (Oxford, 1983)</p><p>Singer, Peter, <hi rend="italic">Marx</hi> (Rotterdam, 1999)</p><p>Stalin, Joseph, <hi rend="italic">The October Revolution</hi> (London, 1936)</p><p>Weisbord, Albert, 'Bolshevism, Fraudulent Practice Of Democratic Centralism' cited in Weisbord.org (November/December 1976), <seg type="URL" n="http://www.weisbord.org/Fraudulent.htm"/> (28 December 2004).</p></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
