<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_0005c" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Vehicle of Propaganda or Agent of Subversion? Cold War Hollywood Bomb Cinema 1950-1963.</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">deleted: 5,070
figures are posters and stills from films
</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">4</p><p n="date">2004-01</p><p n="module title">Rethinking Cold War Cultures</p><p n="module code">HI940</p><p n="genre family">Essay</p><p n="discipline">History</p><p n="disciplinary group">AH</p><p n="grade">D</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">5147</p><p n="number of s-units">171</p><p n="number of p">24</p><p n="number of tables">0</p><p n="number of figures">3</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">0</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">0</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">30.1</p><p n="average s-units per p">7.1</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">m</p><p n="year of birth">1982</p><p n="first language">English</p><p n="education">UKA</p><p n="course">History</p><p n="student ID">0005</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><titlePart><name type="student name"/>. The University of <name type="university"/>.</titlePart><docTitle><titlePart rend="underlined bold">Vehicle of Propaganda or Agent of Subversion? Cold War Hollywood Bomb Cinema 1950-1963. </titlePart></docTitle></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="section"><p n="p1.24"><s n="s1.7;p1.24">For too long the history of the Cold War has been written from a 'top-down' perspective examining elites and decision-makers. </s><s n="s2.7;p1.24">Whilst political scientists have become mired in using rational International Relations models, historians have rarely cast their net beyond realpolitik, frequently falling foul of detailed narrative around contingencies which often never occurred. </s><s n="s3.7;p1.24">The fall of the Berlin Wall in 1989 and the end of the 30-year rule for many documents in the West, which both led to a spate of archival-based sources available to historians, cemented this diplomatic and empirical approach. </s><s n="s4.7;p1.24">Moreover, archival work alone is a dangerous place from which to survey the Cold War, since both sides of the Iron Curtain employed 'newspeak' rather than rational discourse, even behind closed doors. </s><s n="s5.7;p1.24">In short, this 'New Cold War history' can become overly narrative driven and blind to broader analysis. </s><s n="s6.7;p1.24">However, as a result of the growing interest in cultural history following the 1980s 'linguistic turn', recent study, particularly in the so called 'Constructivist' school, has challenged Cold War historians to spread their wings methodologically, and explore the culture of the conflict. </s><s n="s7.7;p1.24">In spite of noteworthy 'hot' episodes, such as Vietnam, the Cold War was in most part a conflict of words and images delivered to an audience soaked in its products. </s></p><p n="p2.24"><s n="s1.6;p2.24">One unmined area of Cold War culture is Hollywood Bomb Cinema. </s><s n="s2.6;p2.24">Bomb Cinema denotes films where the nuclear bomb is an explicit part of the theme or narrative and includes a body of films, widely forgotten, from classics such as <hi rend="italic">Dr Strangelove</hi> (1963) to off-beat cult favourites like <hi rend="italic">Them</hi> (1954).<ref target="BAWE_0005c-ftnote.001"/> However, Bomb Cinema remains predominantly the preserve of film departments and media journalists who examine issues such as plot synopsis and entertainment value. </s><s n="s3.6;p2.24">Working under Freud's avowal that a cigar is sometimes only a cigar, their inquiry is devoid of any attempt to unearth hidden realities. </s><s n="s4.6;p2.24">Apocryphal moments are not examined for anything more than meaningless and pleasurable fantasy. </s><s n="s5.6;p2.24">For example, in reviewing <hi rend="italic">Strangelove</hi>, <hi rend="italic">The Times</hi> film critic simply called it a 'farcical comedy about the end of the world' and paid most attention to the 'remarkable performances by Mr Peter Sellers and Mr George. </s><s n="s6.6;p2.24">C. Scott'. <ref target="BAWE_0005c-ftnote.002"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0005c-ftnote.001"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1"><hi rend="italic">Dr Strangelove</hi> will be referred to as <hi rend="italic"> Strangelove</hi> from this point onwards. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0005c-ftnote.002"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Film Critic, 'Film Comedy about the End of the World', <hi rend="italic">The Times</hi>, 30 January 1964, p. 16. </s></p></note><p n="p3.24"><s n="s1.9;p3.24">So why should historians concern themselves about films with images of the bomb? </s><s n="s2.9;p3.24">Put simply, the sheer number of these films reveal how deeply concerned Americans were about the bomb. </s><s n="s3.9;p3.24">Paul Boyer has argued that the bomb itself is a virtual Kantian category - an internal filter - that shapes our very understanding of the world.<ref target="BAWE_0005c-ftnote.003"/> Taking a psychoanalytic perspective, the bomb is indicative of a repressed dread in US society, concerned about survival, morality, and rebirth. </s><s n="s4.9;p3.24">Thinking about the function of these films, Hayden White argues that historical and fictional discourses have common aspects in narratives and transmit messages about shared reality. </s><s n="s5.9;p3.24">Accordingly, at any given historical point, there exists a common pool of narratives that every culture disposes for its members who might wish to draw upon them for the transmission of messages.<ref target="BAWE_0005c-ftnote.004"/> As a statistically proven part of the filmgoer's diet - indeed <hi rend="italic">The Times</hi> reported in February 1964 that 'demand to see <hi rend="italic">Strangelove</hi> has been so great...it has been decided to put on special late night showings' - Bomb Cinema is one amongst many narratives available to society in order to understand the bomb.<ref target="BAWE_0005c-ftnote.005"/> Certainly, from an early stage, the significance of the intersection between the cinema and the bomb was recognised by policymakers. </s><s n="s6.9;p3.24">For example, the Supreme Command Allied Powers (SCAP) censored references to Hiroshima and Nagasaki in films made during the occupation of Japan. </s><s n="s7.9;p3.24">Jacques Derrida, in his work on the 'nuclear subject', has argued that since the terrifying reality of nuclear war can only be the signified referent and never the real referent of a discourse, the view of fictitious projects, such as Bomb Cinema, occupy a space equal to the views of 'experts'.<ref target="BAWE_0005c-ftnote.006"/> Furthermore, in its satirical fashioning or 'black comedy', as apparent in <hi rend="italic">Strangelove</hi>, Bomb Cinema is increasingly about the workings of power. </s><s n="s8.9;p3.24">By giving a privileged opportunity to laugh at those in authority, Bomb Cinema can afford the individual the bitter-sweet illusion of panoptical power on the inside, by stripping away his real Cold War position of powerlessness on the outside. </s><s n="s9.9;p3.24">Seen in this way, the term subversion is synonymous with liberated power for the individual. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0005c-ftnote.003"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Paul Boyer, <hi rend="italic">By the Bomb's Early Light: American Thought and Culture at the Dawn of the Atomic Age</hi> (Raleigh, 1994). </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0005c-ftnote.004"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Hayden White, <hi rend="italic">The Content of the Form: Narrative Discourse and Historical Representation</hi> (Baltimore, 1990). </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0005c-ftnote.005"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Own Correspondent, 'Late Night Showings at Columbia Cinema', <hi rend="italic">The Times</hi>, 10 October 1963, p.6. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0005c-ftnote.006"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Nicholas Royle, <hi rend="italic">Jacques Derrida</hi> (Oxford, 2003). </s></p></note><p n="p4.24"><s n="s1.9;p4.24">By deconstructing key bomb films, it will be argued that by 1963 and <hi rend="italic"> Strangelove</hi>, Bomb Cinema had become an agent of subversion. </s><s n="s2.9;p4.24">The state sponsored <hi rend="italic">Strategic Air Command 1955 (SAC)</hi>, which projected a halcyon era of acquiescence and all-pervasive Cold War conformity, stands as the archetypal propaganda film for point of comparison. </s><s n="s3.9;p4.24"><hi rend="italic">Strangelove</hi> exploded absolutely the state led propaganda line. </s><s n="s4.9;p4.24">However, far from heralding the first cataclysmic step outside of the propaganda paradigm, <hi rend="italic">Strangelove</hi> is best seen as an umbrella for earlier subversive messages emerging in certain 1950s bomb films. </s><s n="s5.9;p4.24">Working under the constant eye of the House Un-American Activities Committee (HUAC), the distinctly science fiction wing of Bomb Cinema used covert images to depict the anxieties that accompanied life with the bomb.<ref target="BAWE_0005c-ftnote.007"/> Indeed, Stanley Kubrick was an avid watcher of 1950s SF, and <hi rend="italic">Strangelove</hi> can be seen as consciously linking disparate aspects of a genre. </s><s n="s6.9;p4.24">Part of the so-called 'Cold War camp', SF films like <hi rend="italic">The Thing</hi> (1951), <hi rend="italic">The Day The Earth Stood Still</hi> (1951), <hi rend="italic">Them</hi>,<hi rend="italic"> Forbidden Planet</hi> (1956) and <hi rend="italic">The Incredible Shrinking Man</hi> (1957) were intentionally self-parodic, utilising 'grand guignol' horror techniques of invasions of predatory insects and plants, in order to appeal to a generation of rebels without a cause, plagued by fears of isolation. </s><s n="s7.9;p4.24">Yet, as Peter Biskind recognises, these films were very rarely in universal agreement and did have varying degrees of departure from the propaganda paradigm.<ref target="BAWE_0005c-ftnote.008"/> My methodology is interdisciplinary and borrows from the recent Cold War Cultures School in history, including my supervisor, Dr. Patrick Major, requiring the socio-political contextualisation of films, as well as the production and reception history. </s><s n="s8.9;p4.24">Thus, this paper uses not only the films themselves but also draft scripts, biographies and newspaper reviews and articles of the period. </s><s n="s9.9;p4.24">The issues examined here - nuclear proliferation, Organisation Man, scientists and technology - are the most prevalent in Bomb films. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0005c-ftnote.007"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">For brevity, I will refer to Science Fiction as SF from now onwards. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0005c-ftnote.008"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Peter Biskind, <hi rend="italic">Seeing is Believing: How Hollywood Taught us to Stop Worrying and Love the Fifties</hi> (New York, 1983). </s></p></note><p n="p5.24"><s n="s1.13;p5.24">Nuclear proliferation is the most obvious theme in bomb films. </s><s n="s2.13;p5.24">In our period, the nuclear powers exponentially increased their arsenals of destructive potential, within the prevailing and public strategy of Mutually Assured Destruction (MAD). </s><s n="s3.13;p5.24">Ex-US Defense Secretary (1961-68), and architect of MAD, Robert McNamara later called proliferation 'the foundation of stable deterrence in a nuclear world...resting on the understanding that if either side initiates the use of nuclear weapons, the other side will respond with sufficient power to inflict unacceptable damage'.<ref target="BAWE_0005c-ftnote.009"/> World War II laid a precedent for the state taking a manipulative role in fashioning Hollywood films. </s><s n="s4.13;p5.24"><hi rend="italic">SAC</hi> - aided in its making by the US Air Force, who allowed the B-36 bomber to be filmed - defends the arms race completely. </s><s n="s5.13;p5.24">It depicts the bomber force as a safeguard to protect Americans from the bomb. </s><s n="s6.13;p5.24">Real SAC imagery is always at work, such as the billboard sign at the base entrance, 'the nation and your security are at stake', and the Command's motto, 'Peace is our Profession'. </s><s n="s7.13;p5.24">The dialogue supports this argument too with Rusty asserting 'we're the only thing that keeps the peace'.<ref target="BAWE_0005c-ftnote.010"/> In the hands of trustworthy fellows, such as Dutch, nuclear weapons are seen as banal and manageable. </s><s n="s8.13;p5.24">However, the main function of the film was to ingrain in citizens the moral resolve needed to live in the Cold War. </s><s n="s9.13;p5.24">Security officials knew it would have been impossible to protect Americans from nuclear attack. </s><s n="s10.13;p5.24">For example, Millard Caldwell - head of the Federal Civil Defense Administration 1950-52 - believed that 'when a situation is utterly hopeless, it may be better not to say so. </s><s n="s11.13;p5.24">The doctors often conclude against telling the hopeless cancer patient what the situation is'.<ref target="BAWE_0005c-ftnote.011"/> By cultivating an image of safety, <hi rend="italic">SAC</hi> hoped not only to curb the problem of panic, the invisible fifth column at home, but to ensure continued support for the policy of deterrence. </s><s n="s12.13;p5.24">It is worth remembering that, at the time of the film's release, the Alert America campaigns were in full swing, and the gospel of self-help was the new mantra of civil defence planners. </s><s n="s13.13;p5.24">By showing reluctant cold warriors, and their even more reluctant wives, subordinating their civilian lives to the demands of the state, <hi rend="italic">SAC</hi> urges civilians both to accept the secrecy of the Military Industrial Complex (MIC) and even buy into it. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0005c-ftnote.009"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Robert McNamara, 'CNN Interactive: Episode 12 MAD. Interview with Robert McNamara', 1995. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1"><seg type="URL" n="http://www.cnn.com/SPECIALS/cold.war/episodes/12/interviews/mcnamara/"/> (1 December 2003). </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0005c-ftnote.010"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1"><hi rend="italic">Strategic Air Command</hi> (Anthony Mann, 1955). </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0005c-ftnote.011"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Cited in Guy Oakes, <hi rend="italic">The Imaginary War: Civil Defence and American Cold War Culture</hi> (Oxford, 1994), p. 147. </s></p></note><p n="p6.24"><s n="s1.4;p6.24">Subversive bomb cinema exploded the propaganda line of the security of American defence. </s><s n="s2.4;p6.24"><hi rend="italic">The Day the Earth Stood Still</hi> challenged the safety of placing the world under the nuclear sword of Damocles. </s><s n="s3.4;p6.24">Sending a clear signal about the illusory security of America, the alien spaceship lands in Washington, despite being monitored by security forces, and proves immune to human weaponry. </s><s n="s4.4;p6.24">Indeed, Cold War power is shown in the most microcosmic terms when the alien Klaatu makes the earth stand still, and declares that 'at the first sign of violence, your earth will be reduced to a burned out cinder'. <ref target="BAWE_0005c-ftnote.012"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0005c-ftnote.012"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1"><hi rend="italic">The Day the Earth Stood Still</hi> (Robert Wise, 1951). </s></p></note><figure id="BAWE_0005c-pic.001"><head>Illustration 1: Promotional poster for <hi rend="italic">The Day the Earth Stood Still</hi> illustrating the dangers of proliferation, 1951. &lt;<hi rend="italic"><seg type="URL" n="http://www.geocites.co.jp/Hollywood15710/day-earth.jpg"/>></hi> (3 January 2004)</head></figure><p n="p7.24"><s n="s1.8;p7.24">Released in 1951, the film presents a direct challenge to the pursuit of the fusion bomb, which, when developed, would make nuclear holocaust possible. </s><s n="s2.8;p7.24">This message on arms control is poignantly captured when Klaatu charges 'live in peace or face obliteration'.<ref target="BAWE_0005c-ftnote.013"/> Moreover, it is worth noting that Klaatu threatens to destroy the entire Earth, in spite of proliferation clearly emerging from the nationalism of the US State Department. </s><s n="s3.8;p7.24">The arms race is thus presented as an international problem which the United Nations must solve. </s><s n="s4.8;p7.24"><hi rend="italic">The Thing</hi>, despite an over-arching propagandist rubric in which the Russians are suspected of wrongdoing, contains a subversive message on proliferation. </s><s n="s5.8;p7.24">The film ends on the thought that American power could not prevent annihilation, with Scotty lamenting 'I bring you warning... </s><s n="s6.8;p7.24">Watch the skies. </s><s n="s7.8;p7.24">Everywhere... </s><s n="s8.8;p7.24">Keep watching the skies'.<ref target="BAWE_0005c-ftnote.014"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0005c-ftnote.013"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0005c-ftnote.014"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1"><hi rend="italic">The Thing</hi> (Christopher Nyby and Howard Hanks, 1951). </s></p></note><p n="p8.24"><s n="s1.6;p8.24"><hi rend="italic">Them</hi> also looks despairingly at proliferation and examines the harmful effects of radioactive fallout; an issue particularly prevalent at the time of the film's release given the alarming implications of the Bikini test shots and the 1954 Lucky Dragon incident. </s><s n="s2.6;p8.24">According to Allan Winkler, fallout focused public fears because it threatened a less violent form of extinction and presented the danger of both psychological, as well as physical deformity.<ref target="BAWE_0005c-ftnote.015"/> Learning that the radioactive man-eating ants crawled out of a New Mexico test site, <hi rend="italic">Them</hi> rejects the safety of atmospheric testing, and the ability of statesmen to keep a lid on the nuclear Pandora's box. </s><s n="s3.6;p8.24">Indeed, one character questions 'if these monsters got started as a result of the first atomic bomb in 1945, what about all the others that have been exploded since then?' <ref target="BAWE_0005c-ftnote.016"/><hi rend="italic">Them</hi> reflects the anxiety with the all or nothing policy of MAD. By showing the military unable to use its major weapons against the ants, since it was fighting on American soil, <hi rend="italic">Them</hi> champions the search for a flexible and limited response policy. </s><s n="s4.6;p8.24">Yet <hi rend="italic">Them</hi> maintains certain propaganda messages. </s><s n="s5.6;p8.24">Like <hi rend="italic">The Thing</hi>, the monsters act as a metaphor for Communists. </s><s n="s6.6;p8.24">When Dr Medford laments, in clearly Biblical terms, 'and there shall be destruction... and the Beasts shall reign over the earth', the likeness is just discernible.<ref target="BAWE_0005c-ftnote.017"/> Despite casting a shadow over the defence establishment's blithe acceptance of the arms race, in contrast with <hi rend="italic">The Thing</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Them</hi> maintains the legitimacy of state authority, illustrating the measure of divergence within SF. Loudspeakers advise that 'your personal safety...depend(s) on your full co-operation with the military authorities'.<ref target="BAWE_0005c-ftnote.018"/> Reconciling audiences to the knowledge that the Military Scientific Complex (MSC) was there to protect them, even if the threat was produced by it in the first instance, the ants are defeated by the MSC. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0005c-ftnote.015"><p n="pn1.2"><s n="s1.1;pn1.2">Allan Winkler, <hi rend="italic">Life Under a Cloud: American Anxiety About the Atom</hi> (New York, 1993), p. 108. </s></p><p n="pn2.2"><s n="s1.1;pn2.2"><hi rend="sup">15</hi> <hi rend="italic">Them</hi> (Gordon Douglas, 1954). </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0005c-ftnote.016"/><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0005c-ftnote.017"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0005c-ftnote.018"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid. </s></p></note><p n="p9.24"><s n="s1.7;p9.24">The black comedy ending of <hi rend="italic">Strangelove</hi>, with its mushroom clouds and musical serenade of 'We'll meet again', tapped the belief that the superpowers were so caught up in the arms race that nuclear holocaust had become inevitable. </s><s n="s2.7;p9.24">For Kubrick, the logical result of Soviets 'lofting satellites as easily as Americans dunked baskets' and bomb shelters proliferating like greenhouses, was nuclear Armageddon.<ref target="BAWE_0005c-ftnote.019"/> This ending would have appeared more real given the recent Cuban Missile Crisis and brinksmanship in practice. </s><s n="s3.7;p9.24">Cynically rejecting the safeguards projected in <hi rend="italic">SAC</hi>, we witness a pitched battle between US contingents at Burpleson Air Force Base, under the 'Peace is our Profession' billboard. </s><s n="s4.7;p9.24">When General Turgidson argues for 'catching them with their pants down', in a pre-emptive first strike, <hi rend="italic">Strangelove</hi> questions the willingness of policymakers to stay within the confines of MAD.<ref target="BAWE_0005c-ftnote.020"/> Pre-emptive first strike formulations, and its idea that a massive nuclear attack could swiftly paralyse the enemy by destroying its retaliatory forces, had been growing in the light of technological advances made with Anti-Ballistic Missiles and the stockpiling of US nuclear weapons. </s><s n="s5.7;p9.24">Turgidson's insane proposal is no different from the calls by Air Force chief General Curtis LeMay to give them 'Sunday punch'. </s><s n="s6.7;p9.24">Recent findings support Kubrick's observation on the instability of the arms race. </s><s n="s7.7;p9.24">We now know that the military had developed the 'Single Integrated Operations Plan', which worked on the assumption that America would have been willing to be the first to use nuclear weapons.<ref target="BAWE_0005c-ftnote.021"/> This replaced Operation DROPSHOT, written in 1947, which assumed a long period of conventional war between NATO and the Soviet Union before any nuclear weapons would be employed by both sides. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0005c-ftnote.019"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Biskind, <hi rend="italic">Seeing is Believing</hi>, p.337. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0005c-ftnote.020"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1"><hi rend="italic">Dr Strangelove</hi> (Stanley Kubrick, 1963). </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0005c-ftnote.021"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Cited in Sven Lindquist, <hi rend="italic">A History of Bombing</hi> (London, 2001), Section. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">312. </s></p></note><p n="p10.24"><s n="s1.5;p10.24">Military critics derided <hi rend="italic">Strangelove</hi> for its inaccuracy and, unlike <hi rend="italic">SAC,</hi> the Air Force did not co-operate in the making of the film, refusing Kubrick permission to film with the B-52 bomber. </s><s n="s2.5;p10.24">Indeed, Kubrick famously created the interior of his B-52 based on pictures in an old flight manual. </s><s n="s3.5;p10.24">There was also a forced Air Force disclaimer that 'safeguards would prevent the occurrence of events depicted in this film', as the military had always maintained that no attack could be launched without 'civilian authority'.<ref target="BAWE_0005c-ftnote.022"/> However, exposing one of the Cold War's deepest secrets, Bill Barr of Washington's National Security Archive states that 'top military commanders had presidential authorised instructions providing advance authority to use nuclear weapons under specified conditions'.<ref target="BAWE_0005c-ftnote.023"/> Thus, General Ripper's exploitation of a putative retaliatory safeguard, which allows him to launch a nuclear strike, suggests that Kubrick's anxiety in the wisdom of the arms race was not unfounded. </s><s n="s4.5;p10.24">Indeed, LeMay was known for goading the Soviet Union with unauthorised reconnaissance flights. </s><s n="s5.5;p10.24">By 1964, missions had resulted in 26 planes being shot down over the Soviet Union. <ref target="BAWE_0005c-ftnote.024"/><hi rend="italic">Strangelove</hi> thus shows that the delicate nuclear balance could all too easily be disturbed. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0005c-ftnote.022"><p n="pn1.3"><s n="s1.1;pn1.3"><hi rend="italic">Dr Strangelove</hi> (Stanley Kubrick, 1963). </s></p><p n="pn2.3"><s n="s1.1;pn2.3"><hi rend="sup">22</hi> Cited in Paul Lashmar, 'Dr Strangelove's Secrets: Terrifying Truths about the Cold War Period are Leaking out from Archives Around the World', <hi rend="italic">Independent</hi>, 8 September 1998. </s></p><p n="pn3.3"><s n="s1.1;pn3.3"><hi rend="sup">23</hi> Cited in Bruce Franklin, <hi rend="italic">War Stars: The Superweapon and the American Imagination</hi> (Oxford, 1988), p. 185. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0005c-ftnote.023"/><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0005c-ftnote.024"/><p n="p11.24"><s n="s1.9;p11.24">Beyond the proliferation issue, there were other recurring themes in Bomb Cinema. </s><s n="s2.9;p11.24">The next of these is the impact of the organization on man. </s><s n="s3.9;p11.24">In <hi rend="italic">The Organization Man</hi> (1956), William Whyte observed that 'man exists as a unit of society. </s><s n="s4.9;p11.24">Of himself, he isolated, meaningless...by sublimating himself in the group, he helps produce a whole that is greater than the sum of its parts'.<ref target="BAWE_0005c-ftnote.025"/> Whyte showed that under late capitalism, every aspect of life had become regimented and scheduled. </s><s n="s5.9;p11.24"><hi rend="italic">SAC</hi> supports this triumph of conformity. </s><s n="s6.9;p11.24">Even the role of husband and father has to take a back seat to the organization, as Dutch declares 'we can't schedule the flights according to the birth schedule'.<ref target="BAWE_0005c-ftnote.026"/> The Air Force is the natural habitat for the organization man, with General Hawkes educating Dutch about the importance of the group. </s><s n="s7.9;p11.24">When Dutch falls prey on mission to an injury he has failed to disclose, the crew takes over and saves the day. </s><s n="s8.9;p11.24">He is subsequently denounced for jeopardising the lives of his team-mates and the health of the organization. </s><s n="s9.9;p11.24">Echoing Whyte's comment that 'the man of the future is not the individualist but the man who works through others for others', <hi rend="italic">SAC</hi> shows that the day of the daring pilot striving for personal glory - an image built up with maverick stereotypes of World War II pilots - had been replaced by the corporate '9 to 5' aviator. <ref target="BAWE_0005c-ftnote.027"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0005c-ftnote.025"><p n="pn1.3"><s n="s1.1;pn1.3">William Whyte, <hi rend="italic">The Organization Man</hi> (New York, 1956), p. 12. </s></p><p n="pn2.3"><s n="s1.1;pn2.3"><hi rend="sup">25</hi> <hi rend="italic">Strategic Air Command</hi> (Anthony Mann, 1955). </s></p><p n="pn3.3"><s n="s1.1;pn3.3"><hi rend="sup">26</hi> Whyte, <hi rend="italic">The Organization Man</hi>, p. 22. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0005c-ftnote.026"/><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0005c-ftnote.027"/><p n="p12.24"><s n="s1.9;p12.24">However, most subversive bomb cinema showed that the growing regimentation of corporate culture made man bereft of any genuine individual identity and sense of accomplishment. </s><s n="s2.9;p12.24">The most pertinent statement in <hi rend="italic"> The Incredible Shrinking Man</hi> is the lead character's existential condition. </s><s n="s3.9;p12.24">Living in suburbia, 'the dormitory of the new generation of organization men', and working as a reluctant organization man in his brother's firm, Robert Carey finds little achievement in his life.<ref target="BAWE_0005c-ftnote.028"/> His shrinking is thus symbolic of a broader personal turmoil. </s><s n="s4.9;p12.24">In his ritual killing of the spider, Carey loses his fear of alienation from the group, experiencing a psychological transformation. </s><s n="s5.9;p12.24">In revealing, 'and then I meant something too... </s><s n="s6.9;p12.24">To God there is no zero', Carey asks the audience to embrace his liberation. <ref target="BAWE_0005c-ftnote.029"/><hi rend="italic">The Incredible Shrinking Man</hi> is thus a covert attack on the psychological ramifications of organization fetishism. </s><s n="s7.9;p12.24">In addition, the film shows that the famous sentence in the Communist Manifesto stating that the proletariat has nothing to lose but its chains has little relevance for the organization man. </s><s n="s8.9;p12.24">Robert Carey has something to lose conjecturally - his standard of living. </s><s n="s9.9;p12.24">Carey represents a wider metonym for contemporary American middle-class families who, having run up large debts, became trapped in the net of the bourgeois milieu. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0005c-ftnote.028"><p n="pn1.3"><s n="s1.1;pn1.3">Whyte, <hi rend="italic">The Organization Man</hi>, p. 14. </s></p><p n="pn2.3"><s n="s1.1;pn2.3"><hi rend="sup">29</hi> <hi rend="italic">The Incredible Shrinking Man</hi> (Jack Arnold, 1957). </s></p><p n="pn3.3"><s n="s1.1;pn3.3"><hi rend="sup">30</hi> <hi rend="italic">The Thing</hi> (Christopher Nyby and Howard Hanks, 1951). </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0005c-ftnote.029"/><p n="p13.24"><s n="s1.11;p13.24"><hi rend="italic">The Thing</hi>, in its depiction of Air Force Captain Pat Hendry, directs its subversive message more towards the everyday practicalities of organization man. </s><s n="s2.11;p13.24">Asserting 'I'm not working for the world. </s><s n="s3.11;p13.24">I'm working for the Air Force', Hendry begins as the archetypal wheel-in-machine conformist, who cannot blow his nose without clearing it first with Headquarters. <ref target="BAWE_0005c-ftnote.030"/><hi rend="italic">The Thing</hi> serves as a critique of the absurdity of 'going by the book'. </s><s n="s4.11;p13.24">For example, using standard procedure to free an alien ship, Hendry accidentally blows it up. </s><s n="s5.11;p13.24">Hendry is actually immobilised by bureaucracy, stating 'until I receive my instructions from my superior officers, we'll have to mark time'.<ref target="BAWE_0005c-ftnote.031"/> Hendry's idleness testifies to Whyte's argument, that 'in further institutionalising the great power of the majority, we are making the individual distrust himself'.<ref target="BAWE_0005c-ftnote.032"/> When orders arrive to avoid injuring the monster, he has to break free of the parameters of the organization and kill it, in order to stay alive. </s><s n="s6.11;p13.24">However, as we have shown, SF films were anything but unanimous in agreement. </s><s n="s7.11;p13.24"><hi rend="italic">Them</hi>, in contrast to <hi rend="italic">The Thing</hi>, was not subversive in this regard. </s><s n="s8.11;p13.24">It argues that society should embrace the organization man culture and posits that to leave the group is to be beyond the safe parameters of society. </s><s n="s9.11;p13.24">All the victims succumb when they leave the confines of the group. </s><s n="s10.11;p13.24">Furthermore, it takes a consortium of scientists, police and soldiers to defeat the ants. </s><s n="s11.11;p13.24"><hi rend="italic">Them</hi> is indicative that the line of demarcation between films of propaganda and subversion can often be blurred. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0005c-ftnote.030"/><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0005c-ftnote.031"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1"><hi rend="italic">The Thing</hi> (Christopher Nyby and Howard Hanks, 1951). </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0005c-ftnote.032"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Whyte, <hi rend="italic">The Organization Man</hi>, p. 59. </s></p></note><p n="p14.24"><s n="s1.6;p14.24">The role of scientists manifests itself in Bomb Cinema. </s><s n="s2.6;p14.24">Social critic Bertrand Russell argued that 'we are perhaps living in the last age of man, and, if so, it is to science that we will owe this extinction'.<ref target="BAWE_0005c-ftnote.033"/> In Russell's eyes, scientists had become Devil Gods, violating the delicate boundary between conquering nature for the benefit of mankind and conquering nature at the expense of man's survival. </s><s n="s3.6;p14.24">In its portrayal of the nefarious Dr Carrington, <hi rend="italic">The Thing</hi> shows the scientist twisting the dragon's tail. </s><s n="s4.6;p14.24">Admiring the creature, Carrington helps it reproduce itself, and interferes with attempts on its life. </s><s n="s5.6;p14.24">The scientist inherent in Carrington is the extremist head-over-heart zealot, assiduously pursuing his parochial interests and immune to the fact that he might, in the process, be fomenting Armageddon. </s><s n="s6.6;p14.24">For example, Carrington's morally blind quest for advancement is made explicitly clear when he states 'knowledge is more important than life'.<ref target="BAWE_0005c-ftnote.034"/> Indeed, Carrington represents a wider public concern, following the defeat of scientific internationalism and its idea that knowledge should be universally shared, that science was working increasingly behind the closed doors of the MIC. These fears were particularly acute at the time of the film's release, following the public disclosure of the secret Hydrogen bomb project. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0005c-ftnote.033"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Cited in Robert Jungk, <hi rend="italic">Brighter than a Thousand Suns: A Personal History of the Atomic Scientists</hi> (1956), p. 70. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0005c-ftnote.034"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1"><hi rend="italic">The Thing</hi> (Christopher Nyby and Howard Hanks, 1951). </s></p></note><p n="p15.24"><s n="s1.3;p15.24">Scientists, however, were both reviled and revered. </s><s n="s2.3;p15.24">In <hi rend="italic">Flash Effect</hi>, David Tietge argues that in a campaign to promote science in American consciousness, many scientists were symbolised as both father figures and as saviours, working in an environment that celebrated the technological objects of their labour.<ref target="BAWE_0005c-ftnote.035"/> Certain SF bomb films portray the benevolent and wise scientist. </s><s n="s3.3;p15.24">In contrast to Carrington, Dr Medford, in <hi rend="italic">Them,</hi> is presented as an avuncular intellectual. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0005c-ftnote.035"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">David Tietge, <hi rend="italic">Flash Effect: Science and the Rhetorical Origins of Cold War America</hi> (Ohio, 2002). </s></p></note><figure id="BAWE_0005c-pic.002"><head>Illustration 2: Still of the good scientist from <hi rend="italic">Them</hi> , 1954. <hi rend="italic"><seg type="URL" n="http://www.filmposters.com/images/posters/6091.jpg"/> </hi></head></figure><p n="p16.24"><s n="s1.6;p16.24">In his closing statement, 'We've opened the door into another world. </s><s n="s2.6;p16.24">What we'll eventually find nobody can predict', Medford echoes the concerns of Robert Oppenheimer, and recognises the dangers of using the test tube to tamper with nature.<ref target="BAWE_0005c-ftnote.036"/> Echoing Eisenhower's 'Atoms for Peace' programme and his imminent formation of The 'Technological Capabilities Panel', <hi rend="italic">Them</hi> embraces the idea that in a nuclear age, science and politics should no longer inhabit separate spheres. </s><s n="s3.6;p16.24">We see scientists working at the kernel of government policy. </s><s n="s4.6;p16.24">Medford lectures public officials, commands the resources of the state and devises the plan to destroy the menace. </s><s n="s5.6;p16.24">Indeed, Medford sees his elevated role as a 'scientist's dream'.<ref target="BAWE_0005c-ftnote.037"/> The cachet of science becomes so strong it distorts the traditional hierarchy of gender roles. </s><s n="s6.6;p16.24">When his daughter insists on joining the men in a dangerous trip, Agent Graham remarks 'it's no place for you or any other woman'.<ref target="BAWE_0005c-ftnote.038"/> However, she demands that he treat her as a scientist first and a woman second, asserting 'somebody with scientific knowledge, a trained observer, has to go'.<ref target="BAWE_0005c-ftnote.039"/> Released in the wake of the arrest of the British physicist, Klaus Fuchs, for communicating atomic research to the Russians, and the subsequent executions of Julius and Ethel Rosenberg in June 1953 for their involvement in the spy ring, <hi rend="italic">Them</hi> attempts to rehabilitate the image of the good and trustworthy scientist. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0005c-ftnote.036"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1"><hi rend="italic">Them</hi> (Gordon Douglas, 1954) </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0005c-ftnote.037"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0005c-ftnote.038"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0005c-ftnote.039"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid. </s></p></note><p n="p17.24"><s n="s1.6;p17.24">During his terms in office, Eisenhower did more than any previous President to integrate science into the state. </s><s n="s2.6;p17.24">Yet, in his farewell address he exhibited more than a powerful note of irony, warning that 'we must be alert to the...danger that policy could become the captive of a scientific-technological elite'. <ref target="BAWE_0005c-ftnote.040"/><hi rend="italic">Strangelove</hi> shares Eisenhower's concern. </s><s n="s3.6;p17.24">As the premier authority on the Doomsday Machine, Dr Strangelove - struggling with his 'Heil-Hitler' hand and speaking in a terse German accent, which denotes his Nazi affiliations - is devoid of love for anything except the bomb. </s><s n="s4.6;p17.24">Despite his mental deterioration, the leadership cede all power to him by the end, as they are completely distracted by his plans to continue the human race. </s><s n="s5.6;p17.24">Dr Strangelove can be seen as a parody of the Hydrogen Bomb scientist Dr Edward Teller. </s><s n="s6.6;p17.24">Repudiated by many of his scientific colleagues for testifying against Robert Oppenheimer, who called for nuclear restraint and internationalism, Teller ran with a more military crowd, becoming the darling of conservative thinkers for his advocacy of American scientific supremacy. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0005c-ftnote.040"><p n="pn1.2"><s n="s1.1;pn1.2">John McAdams, 'Dwight Eisenhower :Farewell Address to the Nation 17 January 1961', 1995. &lt;<hi rend="italic"><seg type="URL" n="http://mcadams.posc.mu.edu/ike.htm"/>></hi> (1 December 2003). </s></p><p n="pn2.2"><s n="s1.1;pn2.2"><hi rend="sup">41</hi> <hi rend="italic">Strategic Air Command</hi> (Anthony Mann, 1955) </s></p></note><p n="p18.24"><s n="s1.5;p18.24">The final area of this paper addresses a theme unique to the films of subversion. </s><s n="s2.5;p18.24">All subversive films involve some measure of destruction and they question how this is allowed to happen. </s><s n="s3.5;p18.24">On Judgement Day who, or what, is at fault; the nature of man and his failings to control events or unrestrained technology growth? </s><s n="s4.5;p18.24">Witnessing no destruction, <hi rend="italic">SAC</hi> sits outside of this question, reflective of the fact that the Air Force aided making of the film. </s><s n="s5.5;p18.24">The characters exhibit no militant anticommunist hysteria, preferring not even to name the enemy, and simply refer to him as 'the other fella'.<ref target="BAWE_0005c-ftnote.041"/> Although recognising the contemporary problem of peacetime mobilisation for war - indeed Dutch states 'there is a new kind of war', one where 'we've got to stay ready to fight without fighting' - the men are portrayed as hard-working, reluctant cold warriors, charged with a mission others neither admired nor would accept.<ref target="BAWE_0005c-ftnote.042"/> Unlike the characters in <hi rend="italic">Strangelove</hi>, who flaunt the bomb aggressively, the dedicated public servants of <hi rend="italic">SAC</hi> present man as no apocalyptic threat and consider the bomb only as the gun behind the door. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0005c-ftnote.041"/><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0005c-ftnote.042"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid. </s></p></note><p n="p19.24"><s n="s1.7;p19.24"><hi rend="italic">The Day the Earth Stood Still</hi> presents man as the threat. </s><s n="s2.7;p19.24">This supports Stanley Kauffman's argument that 'ban the bomb and they'll find another way. </s><s n="s3.7;p19.24">The real Doomsday machine is men'.<ref target="BAWE_0005c-ftnote.043"/> The film suggests that Cold War suspicion in America had overwhelmed all reason. </s><s n="s4.7;p19.24">Unable to attain an audience with the world's leaders, given the bipolar tensions of the time, Klaatu complains to the President, 'I'm not concerned...with the internal affairs of your planet...my people have learned to live without [such stupidity]'. </s><ref target="BAWE_0005c-ftnote.044"/><s n="s5.7;p19.24">The President responds 'I'm afraid my people haven't'.<ref target="BAWE_0005c-ftnote.045"/> When the peaceful Klaatu escapes from prison, the entire nation is unrelenting in its bellicosity towards him. </s><s n="s6.7;p19.24">One man calls him 'a wild animal'.<ref target="BAWE_0005c-ftnote.046"/> The film illustrates man's dangerous lack of control as exemplified when Klaatu is shot by a trigger-happy soldier while delivering the greeting 'we have come to visit you in peace'.<ref target="BAWE_0005c-ftnote.047"/> Moreover, the film suggests that, in the right hands, technology is far from an apocalyptic threat but instead a possible path to utopia. </s><s n="s7.7;p19.24">Learning that the alien spacecraft is nuclear, Bobby exposes man's ignorance by stating 'I thought that was only for bombs'.<ref target="BAWE_0005c-ftnote.048"/> The film thus echoes Einstein's statement that 'the atomic bomb has changed everything except the nature of man'.<ref target="BAWE_0005c-ftnote.049"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0005c-ftnote.043"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Stanley Kauffman, 'Dean Swift in the Twentieth Century', <hi rend="italic">The New Republic</hi>, 150:5 (1964), p. 24. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0005c-ftnote.044"><p n="pn1.5"><s n="s1.1;pn1.5"><hi rend="italic">The Day the Earth Stood Still</hi> (Robert Wise, 1951) </s></p><p n="pn2.5"><s n="s1.1;pn2.5"><hi rend="sup">45</hi> Ibid. </s></p><p n="pn3.5"><s n="s1.1;pn3.5"><hi rend="sup">46</hi> Ibid. </s></p><p n="pn4.5"><s n="s1.1;pn4.5"><hi rend="sup">47</hi> Ibid. </s></p><p n="pn5.5"><s n="s1.1;pn5.5"><hi rend="sup">48</hi> Ibid. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0005c-ftnote.045"/><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0005c-ftnote.046"/><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0005c-ftnote.047"/><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0005c-ftnote.048"/><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0005c-ftnote.049"><p n="pn1.3"><s n="s1.1;pn1.3">Cited in Margot Henriksen, <hi rend="italic">Dr Strangelove's America: Society and Culture in the Atomic Age</hi> (Berkeley, 1997), p. xvi. </s></p><p n="pn2.3"><s n="s1.1;pn2.3"><hi rend="sup">50</hi> <hi rend="italic">The Forbidden Planet</hi> (Fred Wilcox, 1956). </s></p><p n="pn3.3"><s n="s1.1;pn3.3"><hi rend="sup">51</hi> Cited in Franklin, <hi rend="italic">War Stars</hi>, p. 4. </s></p></note><p n="p20.24"><s n="s1.9;p20.24">The custodians of the bomb are dealt a particularly vicious blow in subversive Bomb Cinema. </s><s n="s2.9;p20.24">Driven by virulent anti-communism, the American leadership is shown as nothing more than a group of modern Prometheans, morally blind to the implications of military conflagration. </s><s n="s3.9;p20.24"><hi rend="italic">Strangelove</hi> harnesses the idea by admitting that nuclear war is absurd, but understands that its absurdity only makes it more likely because of the world's propensity for producing psychotic individuals and elevating them into positions of power. </s><s n="s4.9;p20.24">Supposedly working for the 'good' of the people, these men are presented as captivated by deadly technology and oblivious to the destructive nature of their policies. </s><s n="s5.9;p20.24">It is Ripper who orchestrates the attack and Turgidson's remark, 'the human element seems to have failed us here', clearly illustrates the chasm between man's scientific skill and his political ineptitude.<ref target="BAWE_0005c-ftnote.050"/> Major Kong serves as the perfect metaphor for the failure of man to recognise how nuclear weapons have fundamentally changed the nature of war. </s><s n="s6.9;p20.24">In his pep talk - 'the folks back home is a-countin' on you and, by golly, we ain't about to let-em down'<ref target="BAWE_0005c-ftnote.051"/> - Kong is blind to the severity of the task he is being asked to do. </s><s n="s7.9;p20.24">Wearing a cowboy hat, which connects him to the frontier tradition and with the patriotic war song 'Johnny Comes Marching Home' providing music, Kong is presented as the dangerous short-sighted hero riding the bomb. </s><s n="s8.9;p20.24">Kubrick was not a lone voice in his negative treatment of the American leadership. </s><s n="s9.9;p20.24">For example, in his expressive Cold War jeremiad 'Gentleman: You are Mad', social commentator Lewis Mumford asserted that 'madmen govern our affairs in the name of security'.<ref target="BAWE_0005c-ftnote.052"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0005c-ftnote.050"/><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0005c-ftnote.051"><p n="pn1.2"><s n="s1.1;pn1.2"><hi rend="sup">52</hi> <hi rend="italic">Dr Strangelove</hi> (Stanley Kubrick, 1963). </s></p><p n="pn2.2"><s n="s1.1;pn2.2"><hi rend="sup">53</hi> Ibid. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0005c-ftnote.052"/><figure id="BAWE_0005c-pic.003"><head>Illustration 3: Shot illustrating the short-sighted hero from <hi rend="italic">Dr Strangelove</hi> , 1964. <seg type="URL" n="http://www.www.cnn.com/SHOWBIZ/movies/9903/08/Kubrick.obit/strangelove.jpg"/> (3 January 2004).</head></figure><p n="p21.24"><s n="s1.2;p21.24">Another aspect of the 'madmen' character explored in <hi rend="italic">Strangelove</hi> is the triumph of the radical right-wing cold warrior in America, exposed in the insanity of General Ripper. </s><s n="s2.2;p21.24">Echoing Senator Joseph McCarthy, who spoke of the 'communist with a razor blade poised over the jugular vein of this nation', Ripper manifests similar obsessive anti-communism by asserting, 'I can no longer sit back and allow...the international communist conspiracy to impurify all of our bodily fluids'.<ref target="BAWE_0005c-ftnote.053"/> Ripper's willingness to annihilate the world because of fluoridation illustrates that the nature of man is at fault again. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0005c-ftnote.053"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Cited in Henriksen, <hi rend="italic">Dr Strangelove's America</hi>, p. 47.;<hi rend="underlined italic"> Dr Strangelove</hi> (Stanley Kubrick, 1963). </s></p></note><p n="p22.24"><s n="s1.6;p22.24">Civilians are equally culpable. </s><s n="s2.6;p22.24">President Muffley is presented as the ineffectual Liberal who is unable to halt the madness around him. </s><s n="s3.6;p22.24">By arguing with Premier Kissof over who is sorrier for imminent global holocaust, Muffley not only exhibits the preposterous nature of Cold War tensions but also appears to see the event as no more than a social faux pas. </s><s n="s4.6;p22.24">Although, 'relentlessly perceptive of human beings to the point of inhumanity', <hi rend="italic">Strangelove</hi> is also tinged with technophobia.<ref target="BAWE_0005c-ftnote.054"/> The Doomsday Machine, 'that rules out human meddling', signals the ultimate triumph of destructive technology.<ref target="BAWE_0005c-ftnote.055"/> It is ironic that the machines of destruction, such as the Doomsday Machine, work with great efficiency, whilst more humane machines, such as telephones, are ineffectual. </s><s n="s5.6;p22.24">It is worth remembering that since 1945 delivery system advances had grown considerably, resulting in the land based missile, which is impervious to any recall signal. </s><s n="s6.6;p22.24">In part then, <hi rend="italic">Strangelove</hi> shows that developing more sophisticated defence systems will lead to technology manipulating man and ultimately annihilation. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0005c-ftnote.054"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Stanley Kauffman, 'Dean Swift in the Twentieth Century', <hi rend="italic">The New Republic</hi>, 150:5 (1964), p. 24. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">56 <hi rend="italic">Dr Strangelove</hi> (Stanley Kubrick, 1963). </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0005c-ftnote.055"/><p n="p23.24"><s n="s1.7;p23.24">In conclusion, Bomb Cinema between 1950 and 1964 revealed two cultural personalities in conflict. </s><s n="s2.7;p23.24">Under the surface of <hi rend="italic">SAC</hi>, which sat at the high-table of state propaganda, there existed films subverting the portrayal of a benign nuclear age. </s><s n="s3.7;p23.24">These reached their climax with <hi rend="italic">Strangelove</hi>. </s><s n="s4.7;p23.24">Lewis Mumford stated in 1964 that <hi rend="italic">Strangelove</hi> represented 'the first break in the catatonic Cold War trance that had so long held our country in its rigid grip'.<ref target="BAWE_0005c-ftnote.056"/> However, by deconstructing 1950s SF films, <hi rend="italic">Strangelove</hi> is best seen as the culmination of creeping subversion, rather than first explosion.1950s SF films had the freedom for subversive statements, because they appeared so thoroughly removed from reality. </s><s n="s5.7;p23.24">Lost on Film Studies scholars and reviewers, these films, even in their most apocryphal moments, were brimming with surreptitious statements on the atomic age. </s><s n="s6.7;p23.24">In our efforts to excavate the hidden and the not so hidden, we have also proved that within SF there existed a network of competing ideologues and measures of departure from the overriding propaganda paradigm. </s><s n="s7.7;p23.24"><hi rend="italic">Them</hi>, despite its abhorrence to proliferation, maintains the legitimacy of state power and support for the organization. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0005c-ftnote.056"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Cited in Charles Maland, 'Dr Strangelove: A Nightmare Comedy and the Ideology of the Liberal Consensus', <hi rend="italic">American Quarterly</hi> 31:5 (1979), p. 716. </s></p></note><p n="p24.24"><s n="s1.11;p24.24">Yet, the importance of <hi rend="italic">Strangelove</hi> cannot be underplayed. </s><s n="s2.11;p24.24">Arguably <hi rend="italic">Strangelove</hi> tells us something about the constantly renegotiated nature of hegemonic apparatuses. </s><s n="s3.11;p24.24">Gramsci argued that culture is a non-coercive means whereby the ruling-classes maintain their dominance by securing the consent of subordinate groups. </s><s n="s4.11;p24.24">Moreover, hegemony operates by allowing <hi rend="italic">mild</hi> concessions to groups who do not pose a threat to the framework of domination. </s><s n="s5.11;p24.24">Thus, it is not surprising that we find in certain 1950s SF bomb films moments of divergence from the dominant paradigm. </s><s n="s6.11;p24.24">Here is concession at work. </s><s n="s7.11;p24.24">What <hi rend="italic">Strangelove</hi> does is reverse the dialectic to make the previous mild concessions the now prevailing hegemony and signifies the moment when previously unthreatening groups rose to prominence. </s><s n="s8.11;p24.24">It also signifies the decisive moment when audiences are no longer able to watch the nuclear subject straight. </s><s n="s9.11;p24.24">Kubrick originally had intended a straight adaptation of Peter George's novel <hi rend="italic">Red Alert,</hi> but it dawned on him that the most truthful elements of scenes were absurd, and so he transformed the story into a nightmare comedy. </s><s n="s10.11;p24.24">Released shortly after <hi rend="italic">Strangelove</hi> in 1964, the straight-laced <hi rend="italic">Fail-Safe,</hi> positing a similar end of the world scenario, was a box office disaster. </s><s n="s11.11;p24.24"><hi rend="italic">Strangelove's</hi> 'horrible grin' of black humour had become the only means by which society could learn to stop worrying and love the bomb. </s></p></div1></body><back><div1 type="bibliography"><head rend="underlined bold">BIBLIOGRAPHY</head><div2 type="bibliography"><head rend="underlined bold">Films</head><p><hi rend="italic">Dr Strangelove</hi> (Stanley Kubrick, 1963).</p><p><hi rend="italic">Strategic Air Command</hi> (Anthony Mann, 1955).</p><p><hi rend="italic">The Day the Earth Stood Still</hi> (Robert Wise, 1951).</p><p><hi rend="italic">The Forbidden Planet</hi> (Fred Wilcox, 1956).</p><p><hi rend="italic">The Incredible Shrinking Man</hi> (Jack Arnold, 1957).</p><p><hi rend="italic">The Thing</hi> (Christopher Nyby and Howard Hanks, 1951).</p><p><hi rend="italic">Them</hi> (Gordon Douglas, 1954).</p></div2><div2 type="bibliography"><head rend="underlined bold">Newspapers and Contemporary Articles</head><p>Kauffman, Stanley, 'Dean Swift in the Twentieth Century', <hi rend="italic">The New Republic</hi>, 150:5 (1964), p. 24.</p><p>Film Critic, 'Film Comedy about the End of the World', <hi rend="italic">The Times</hi>, 30 January 1964, p. 16.</p><p>Lashmar, 'Dr Strangelove's Secrets: Terrifying Truths About the Cold War Period are Leaking Out from Archives Around the World', <hi rend="italic">Independent</hi>, 8 September 1998.</p><p>Maland, Charles, 'Dr Strangelove: A Nightmare Comedy and the Ideology of the Liberal Consensus', <hi rend="italic">American Quarterly</hi> 31:5 (1979), p. 716.</p><p>Own Correspondent, 'Late Night Showings at Columbia Cinema', <hi rend="italic">The Times</hi>, 10 October 1963, p.6.</p></div2><div2 type="bibliography"><head rend="underlined bold">Websites</head><p>John McAdams, 'Dwight Eisenhower :Farewell Address to the Nation 17 January 1961', 1995. &lt;<hi rend="italic"><seg type="URL" n="http://mcadams.posc.mu.edu/ike.htm"/>></hi> (1 December 2003). </p><p>Robert McNamara, 'CNN Interactive: Episode 12 MAD. Interview with Robert McNamara', 1995. <seg type="URL" n="http://www.cnn.com/SPECIALS/cold.war/episodes/12/interviews/mcnamara/"/> (1 December 2003). </p></div2><div2 type="bibliography"><head rend="underlined bold">Illustrations</head><p>Illustration 1: Promotional poster for <hi rend="italic">The Day the Earth Stood Still</hi> illustrating the dangers of proliferation, 1951. &lt;<hi rend="italic"><seg type="URL" n="http://www.geocites.co.jp/Hollywood15710/day-earth.jpg"/>></hi></p><p>(3 January 2004)</p><p>Illustration 2: Still of the good scientist from <hi rend="italic">Them</hi>, 1954. <seg type="URL" n="http://www.filmposters.com/images/posters/6091.jpg"/></p><p>(3 January 2004).</p><p>Illustration 3: Shot illustrating the shortsighted hero from <hi rend="italic">Dr Strangelove</hi>, 1964. <seg type="URL" n="http://www.www.cnn.com/SHOWBIZ/movies/9903/08/Kubrick.obit/strangelove.jpg"/></p><p>(3 January 2004).</p></div2><div2 type="bibliography"><head rend="underlined bold">Published Secondary Sources</head><p>Biskind, Peter, <hi rend="italic">Seeing is Believing: How Hollywood Taught us to Stop Worrying and Love the Fifties</hi> (New York, 1983).</p><p>Boyer, Paul, <hi rend="italic">By the Bomb's Early Light: American Thought and Culture at the Dawn of the Atomic Age</hi> (Raleigh, 1994).</p><p>Franklin, Bruce, <hi rend="italic">War Stars: The Superweapon and the American Imagination</hi> (Oxford, 1988).</p><p>Jungk, Robert, <hi rend="italic">Brighter than a Thousand Suns: A Personal History of the Atomic Scientists</hi> (1956).</p><p>Lindquist, Sven, <hi rend="italic">A History of Bombing</hi> (London, 2001).</p><p>Oakes, Guy, <hi rend="italic">The Imaginary War: Civil Defence and American Cold War</hi> Culture (Oxford, 1994).</p><p>Royle, Nicholas, <hi rend="italic">Jacques Derrida</hi> (Oxford, 2003).</p><p>Tietge, David, <hi rend="italic">Flash Effect: Science and the Rhetorical Origins of Cold War America</hi> (Ohio, 2002).</p><p>White, Hayden, <hi rend="italic">The Content of the Form: Narrative Discourse and Historical Representation</hi> (Baltimore, 1990).</p><p>Whyte, William, <hi rend="italic">The Organization Man</hi> (New York, 1956).</p><p>Winkler, Allan, <hi rend="italic">Life Under a Cloud: American Anxiety About the Atom</hi> (New York, 1993).</p></div2></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
