<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_0018b" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Report</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">deleted: page numbers</note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">Evaluated as candidate compound assignment. Assigned to S1b: collection of reports: compound.</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">2</p><p n="date">2004-04</p><p n="module title">Materials for Mechanical Engineers</p><p n="module code">ES22A</p><p n="genre family">Methodology recount</p><p n="discipline">Engineering</p><p n="disciplinary group">PS</p><p n="grade">D</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">2202</p><p n="number of s-units">95</p><p n="number of p">16</p><p n="number of tables">0</p><p n="number of figures">0</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">4</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">0</p><p n="abstract present">abstract present</p><p n="average words per s-unit">23.2</p><p n="average s-units per p">5.9</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">compound assignment consisting of 3 parts (see notesStmt for details)</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">m</p><p n="year of birth">1982</p><p n="first language">Chinese Cantonese</p><p n="education">UK7</p><p n="course">Mechanical Engineering</p><p n="student ID">0018</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front/><body><div1 type="abstract"><head rend="underlined bold">SUMMARY:</head><p n="p1.16"><s n="s1.6;p1.16">In Assignment 1, Part A was demonstrated the material selection for the fresh-water heat exchanger tubes. </s><s n="s2.6;p1.16">In Part B, material and process were selected for column spacers under a varying compressive load. </s><s n="s3.6;p1.16">Finally, the structural section was selected for a beam in Assignment 2. </s><s n="s4.6;p1.16">Cambridge Engineering Selector was mainly used in those cases to select the best suitable results. </s><s n="s5.6;p1.16">In conclusion, "Higher Conductivity Copper" was chosen for fresh-water heat exchanger tubes in Assignment 1 Part A. Secondly, "Silicon" was selected for column spacers and "Fine Grinding (Automated)" and "Polishing (Automated)" processes were selected to use in manufacturing in Assignment 1 Part B. Finally, "Hot Fin. </s><s n="s6.6;p1.16">Steel (Y.S.355MPa) Circular Hollow-(194×5.0)" was chosen for the optimum structural section. </s></p></div1><div1 type="front-back-matter"><head rend="underlined bold">CONTENT: PAGE</head><p/></div1><div1 type="text"><head rend="bold">PART A - Material selection for fresh-water heat exchanger tubes</head><div2><head rend="underlined bold">Introduction:</head><p n="p2.16"><s n="s1.5;p2.16">In this part, a material was selected and used to manufacture a set of tubes in heat exchangers by using the CES Selector Materials Package. </s><s n="s2.5;p2.16">The material needed to conduct heat well, had a maximum operating temperature above the operating temperature of the device, not corrode in the fluid and have adequate ductility. </s><s n="s3.5;p2.16">Two stages (Graphical stages) were created to identify a subset of materials that met the criteria. </s><s n="s4.5;p2.16">On the other hand, some other material characteristics which might influence the choice were also considered before a suitable material was chosen. </s><s n="s5.5;p2.16">The Specification for particular heat exchanger was given below: </s></p><list type="bulleted"><item>Maximum service temperature 150°(which is equal to 423K)</item><item>Elongation >20%</item><item>Corrosion resistance in fresh water Very good</item><item>Thermal conductivity As large as possible</item></list></div2><div2><head rend="underlined bold">Method:</head><p n="p3.16"><s n="s1.7;p3.16">First of all, a graphic stage was created by pressing the "New graphic stage" button on the standard toolbar in the CES window, "Fresh water" was selected from attributes list box on the x-axis tab and "Ductility" was selected on the y-axis tab. </s><s n="s2.7;p3.16">A graph was shown to indicate the ductility of materials against the corrosion resistance in fresh water. </s><s n="s3.7;p3.16">"Box selection" button on the Project toolbar was pressed afterwards for selecting materials within a property range. </s><s n="s4.7;p3.16">The mouse was clicked near the point (Very good, 0.2), the button was held down and the cursor was drag near to the point (Very good, 9.3(Max.)). </s><s n="s5.7;p3.16">The limits were refined by opening "Stage properties" window in the "Project" menu and the exact value was entered in the "Selection" tab. </s><s n="s6.7;p3.16">Total number of 155 different materials met the specification in this stage. </s><s n="s7.7;p3.16">(Figure 1.1) Failed materials were hidden by pressing "Hide failed record" box in "Stage properties" window. </s></p><p n="p4.16"><s n="s1.5;p4.16">Secondly, another graphic stage was created in the same method as the one above. </s><s n="s2.5;p4.16">But "Maximum service temperature" and "Thermal conductivity" were selected on the x-axis and y-axis tab respectively. </s><s n="s3.5;p4.16">A graph (Figure 1.2) was shown again to indicate the maximum service temperature against the thermal conductivity for different materials. </s><s n="s4.5;p4.16">Again, "Box selection" button was pressed and limits were refined to 423K to 3800K (Max.) on the x-axis and refined to 200W/m.K to 422W/m.K (Max.) on the y-axis, using the same method as stage one. </s><s n="s5.5;p4.16">At the end, 21 different materials met the specification in this stage. </s></p><p n="p5.16"><s n="s1.3;p5.16">Finally, materials that superimposed were found out by pressing the "Result intersection" toggle on the standard toolbar. </s><s n="s2.3;p5.16">Results could be viewed by clicking on "Results Window" button, in this case there were 11 materials which met both specifications; a list of results was shown in Figure 1.3. </s><s n="s3.3;p5.16">A clearer view for stage 1 and 2 after intersection were shown in Figure 1.4 and 1.5 respectively. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined bold">Evaluation:</head><p n="p6.16"><s n="s1.5;p6.16">In fact some characteristics were also important and might influence the choice, therefore a careful consideration was needed, e.g. lower price was important in large number of manufacturing processes, higher endurance limit was helpful for long-term usage and the relevant replacement cost could be minimized, lower specific heat lowered the amount of heat required to heat up the fluid. </s><s n="s2.5;p6.16">Although "Silver, Commercial Purity" (Figure 1.6) was the best material after intersection, it was too expensive. </s><s n="s3.5;p6.16">Both "Brass" (Figure 1.7) and "High Conductivity Copper" (Figure 1.8) had a lower price and a similar specific heat, "High Conductivity Copper" had a higher endurance limit and "Higher Conductivity Copper" had a higher thermal conductivity. </s><s n="s4.5;p6.16">But the heat exchanger tubes with high thermal conductivity were more important than one with a high endurance limit. </s><s n="s5.5;p6.16">So in conclusion, "Higher Conductivity Copper" was chosen for fresh-water heat exchanger tubes. </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="text"><head rend="bold">PART B - Selection for column spacers under a varying compressive load</head><div2><head rend="underlined bold">Introduction:</head><p n="p7.16"><s n="s1.4;p7.16">This part included selection for column spacers in a precision instrument. </s><s n="s2.4;p7.16">The instrument incorporated two stiff plates between which a fluid flowed. </s><s n="s3.4;p7.16">They were held apart by a set of seven spacers, which were to be solid bars of circular cross-section. </s><s n="s4.4;p7.16">Periodically changing compressive load was applied axially on the plates. </s></p><list type="bulleted"><head>Specification for the instrument:</head><item>Spacers length 2.65±0.015 mm</item><item>Diameter of plates 55 mm (0.055m)</item><item>Maximum compressive load 10 <hi rend="sup">5</hi>N (0.1MN)</item><item>Selling price £80,000</item><item>Number of selling each year 25</item><item>Expected tooling cost £2500-3000</item></list><list type="bulleted"><head>Principal criteria for choice:</head><item>Spacers should not fail under the load.</item><item>Material should be essentially an electrical insulator.</item><item>Thermal distortion should be as low as possible.</item><item>Resistance to water and organic solvents should be very good and resistance to acids should be good.</item></list><p n="p8.16"><s n="s1.1;p8.16">In theory, thermal distortion could be minimized by selecting materials with large values of the index M= λ/α, where λ is thermal conductivity and α is thermal expansion. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined bold">Methods:</head><p n="p9.16"><s n="s1.14;p9.16">For material selection, "Materials" was selected in project setting window. </s><s n="s2.14;p9.16">Actually 3 stages (a limit stage and 2 graphic stages) were created for selection of materials. </s><s n="s3.14;p9.16">A limit stage was created in stage one and the environmental resistance were adjusted to "Very good" for "Fresh Water" and "Organic Solvents", and "Good" for "Weak Acid" (Figure 2.1). </s><s n="s4.14;p9.16">Total number of 1007 different materials met the specification in this stage. </s><s n="s5.14;p9.16">Secondly, a graphical stage was created in stage 2, "Compressive Strength" and "Resistivity" were selected on x and y-axis respectively. </s><s n="s6.14;p9.16">Formula σ=F/A was used to find out the maximum compressive strength, where σ was compressive strength, F was compressive load applied and A was cross sectional area. </s><s n="s7.14;p9.16">In this case, σ=0.1/ [π× (0.055/2)<hi rend="sup">2</hi>] MPa, which was equal to 42.0906MPa. </s><s n="s8.14;p9.16">"Box selection" button was pressed and limits were refined to 42.0906MPa to 3850MPa (Max.) on the x-axis and refined to 100×10 <hi rend="sup">-8</hi> ohm.m to (1e+010) ×10 <hi rend="sup">-8</hi> ohm.m (Max.) on the y-axis. </s><s n="s9.14;p9.16">At the end, 166 different materials met the specification in this stage (Figure 2.2). </s><s n="s10.14;p9.16">Again, failed materials were hidden by pressing "Hide failed record" box in "Stage properties" window. </s><s n="s11.14;p9.16">For stage 3, another graphical stage was created, "Thermal Expansion" was selected on the x-axis and "Thermal Conductivity" was selected on the y-axis, a gradient-line with a slope of 1 was added to the graph by pressing the "Gradient-Line Selection" button. </s><s n="s12.14;p9.16">The line was placed to a desired level after held and dragged from any point on the graph. </s><s n="s13.14;p9.16">Materials with high index M (λ/α) were indicated by clicking once on a point above line with hand cursor. </s><s n="s14.14;p9.16">There are total number of 953 materials met the specification in stage 3 (Figure 2.3). </s></p><p n="p10.16"><s n="s1.4;p10.16">Finally the materials that met the specification in all 3 stages could be viewed on the graph by clicking on "Result intersection" toggle at each graphical stage. </s><s n="s2.4;p10.16">A list of results could be view by clicking on "Results Window" button on standard toolbar. </s><s n="s3.4;p10.16">A total number of 9 materials met all the specifications and a list of results was shown in Figure 2.4. </s><s n="s4.4;p10.16">A clearer view for stage 2 and 3 after intersection were shown in Figure 2.5 and 2.6 respectively. </s></p><p n="p11.16"><s n="s1.10;p11.16">For process selection, "Process" was selected in project setting window from project menu, 2 stages were created for selection of processes. </s><s n="s2.10;p11.16">A graphical stage was created in stage 1, advanced button was pressed in graph stage wizard and an expression builder appeared. </s><s n="s3.10;p11.16">"Shape" folder in left hand pane was clicked, "Prismatic" folder was expanded in right hand pane by clicking the "Plus sign" next to it. </s><s n="s4.10;p11.16">Similarly the "Axisymmetric" folder was expanded followed by the "Solid" folder, "Plain" was selected by double clicking on the folder. </s><s n="s5.10;p11.16">On the y-axis, "Tolerance" was selected. </s><s n="s6.10;p11.16">Precision of 2.65±0.015 mm was given. </s><s n="s7.10;p11.16">Therefore "Box selection" button was pressed and the limit of tolerance was set to 1e-003mm (Min.) to 0.015mm on the "Selection" tab (Figure 2.7). </s><s n="s8.10;p11.16">The tooling cost was expected to be £2500-3000, so a limit stage was created in stage 2 and the limit was entered in "Tooling cost" boxes (Figure 2.8). </s><s n="s9.10;p11.16">"Result intersection" toggle was clicked in stage 2 and 8 different processes were met the specification (Figure 2.9). </s><s n="s10.10;p11.16">A short list was shown in Figure 2.10. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined bold">Evaluation:</head><p n="p12.16"><s n="s1.6;p12.16">Both "Silicon" (Figure 2.11) and "Germanium" (Figure 2.12) had a outstanding good result, but the compressive strength and thermal distortion of "Silicon" was slightly higher and lower respectively than "Germanium", also the price of "Silicon" is much lower than "Germanium". </s><s n="s2.6;p12.16">Therefore, "Silicon" was chosen to manufacture the spacers. </s><s n="s3.6;p12.16">On the other hand, "Fine Grinding (Automated)" (Figure 2.13) and "Polishing (Automated)"(Figure 2.14) were selected for "Machining" and "Finishing" process respectively. </s><s n="s4.6;p12.16">A better precision and surface finish of spacers could be obtained using the "Fine Grinding (Automated)" even the capital cost was very high. </s><s n="s5.6;p12.16">Precisions and surface of the spacers could be improved using the "Polishing (Automated)" process; the capital cost was similar to the "Fine Grinding (Automated)" process. </s><s n="s6.6;p12.16">In conclusion, "Silicon" was selected for column spacers, "Fine Grinding (Automated)" and "Polishing (Automated)" processes were used for machining and polishing the spacer respectively. </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="front-back-matter"><head rend="underlined bold">Reference:</head><p>
1). 
Ashby, M.F., Materials Selection in Mechanical Design, 1 <hi rend="sup">st</hi> Edition, Pergamon Press, 1993, p119-122; p167-207. 
</p></div1><div1 type="text"><head rend="underlined bold">Assignment 2 - Shape selection: Selection of structural section for a beam</head><div2><head rend="underlined bold">Introduction:</head><p n="p13.16"><s n="s1.4;p13.16">In this section, the best standard structural section was chosen for a roof member. </s><s n="s2.4;p13.16">The interior space was intended to be divided with glass curtain walls and the roof was a pedestrian area. </s><s n="s3.4;p13.16">Because of the poor deflection tolerance of the glass, minimal deflection was the primary design consideration. </s><s n="s4.4;p13.16">Lateral torsional buckling problems were avoided by maximizing the torsional rigidity of the members and the environmental impact was also minimized. </s></p><list type="bulleted"><head>Specification for choice:</head><item>Considered clear span = 10m</item><item>Absolute maximum deflection = 1/400 span = 25mm = 0.025m</item><item>Maximum capacity of lifting equipment = 500lb = 226.796kg</item><item>Live roof load (including safety factor) = 50kg/m ~ 500N/m</item><item>Maximum deflection was given by: </item><item>δ<hi rend="sub">max</hi> = (5qL <hi rend="sup">4</hi>)/ (384EI)</item><item> q = load in N/m, L = length and EI = flexural stiffness.</item></list><p n="p14.16"><s n="s1.1;p14.16">In this case, δ<hi rend="sub">max</hi> = (5×500×10 <hi rend="sup">4</hi>)/ (384EI) </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined bold">Method:</head><p n="p15.16"><s n="s1.12;p15.16">First of all, "Shape" was selected in selection table after opening the "Project Setting" window form "Project" menu. </s><s n="s2.12;p15.16">"Structural Sections" filters and forms were selected in shape table. </s><s n="s3.12;p15.16">Two stages were created - A graphical stage and a limit stage. </s><s n="s4.12;p15.16">In stage 1, graphical stage was created and "Deflection" was plotted on the x-axis. </s><s n="s5.12;p15.16">"Deflection" was created from expression builder window and an expression of (5×500×10 <hi rend="sup">4</hi>)/ (384EI) was built. </s><s n="s6.12;p15.16">On the y-axis, the "Optimal secondary design parameter" (M) was plotted using the expression builder again and an expression of [Torsional Stiffness] × [Recycle Fraction] / [Energy Content] was selected and pasted. </s><s n="s7.12;p15.16">"Box selection" button was pressed and limits were refined to 4.01878e-005m (Min.) to 0.025m on the x-axis and refined to 100 to 9.6096e+006 (Max.) on the y-axis. </s><s n="s8.12;p15.16">Failed materials were hidden by pressing "Hide failed record" box in "Stage properties" window (Figure 3.1). </s><s n="s9.12;p15.16">On the other hand, limit stage was created and limit for "Mass per unit length" was filled in stage 2. </s><s n="s10.12;p15.16">The length of beam was 10m and the maximum capacity of lifting equipment was 226.796kg, so an amount of 22.6796kg/m was entered into the maximum mass per unit length box (Figure 3.2). </s><s n="s11.12;p15.16">After that the "Result intersection" toggle was clicked and a total number of 11 passed sections were shown in Figure 3.3. </s><s n="s12.12;p15.16">A clearer view for stage 1 after intersection was shown in Figure 3.4. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined bold">Evaluation:</head><p n="p16.16"><s n="s1.8;p16.16">"Hot Rolled Steel (Y.S.355MPa) Universal Beam-(305×102×25)" (Figure 3.5) was the best section that satisfied the minimum deflection. </s><s n="s2.8;p16.16">On the other hand, "Hot Fin. </s><s n="s3.8;p16.16">Steel (Y.S.355MPa) Circular Hollow - (194×5.0)" (Figure 3.6) was the best section that satisfied the maximum value of M. Anyway, "Glulam Softwood rectangular section - (495×65×16.11)" (Figure 3.7) was the best section that satisfied both consideration. </s><s n="s4.8;p16.16">Actually, economical factor was also needed to be considered so that a new expression [Torsional Stiffness] × [Recycle Fraction] × [Price] / [Energy Content] was formed for the value of M. The range of M was adjusted to 100 to 8.12613e+006 (Max.) and adjusted to 100 to 9.6096e+006 (Max.) on the y-axis, a new graph was shown in Figure 3.8. </s><s n="s5.8;p16.16">"Hot Fin. </s><s n="s6.8;p16.16">Steel (Y.S.355MPa) Circular Hollow - (194×5.0)" and "Glulam Softwood rectangular section - (495×65×16.11)" were also appeared in the graph. </s><s n="s7.8;p16.16">By the way, in conclusion, "Hot Fin. </s><s n="s8.8;p16.16">Steel (Y.S.355MPa) Circular Hollow-(194×5.0)" was chosen for the beam because a high torsional stiffness and a low price could be found from this section. </s></p></div2></div1></body><back><div1 type="bibliography"><head rend="underlined bold">Reference:</head><p>1). Ashby, M.F., Materials Selection in Mechanical Design, 1<hi rend="sup">st</hi> Edition, Pergamon Press, 1993, p132-165.</p></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
