<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_0023d" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Pipe Flow Experiment</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">The document has a title page which contains:
document title
title part</note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">figures and tables appear to be in (absent) appendix
deleted: footer giving page number</note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">Running text contains reference to external or missing appendix.
</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">2</p><p n="date">2004-04</p><p n="module title">Fluid Mechanics</p><p n="module code">ES252</p><p n="genre family">Methodology recount</p><p n="discipline">Engineering</p><p n="disciplinary group">PS</p><p n="grade">D</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">3497</p><p n="number of s-units">280</p><p n="number of p">182</p><p n="number of tables">0</p><p n="number of figures">0</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">106</p><p n="number of lists">10</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">37</p><p n="abstract present">abstract present</p><p n="average words per s-unit">12.5</p><p n="average s-units per p">1.5</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">m</p><p n="year of birth">1984</p><p n="first language">English</p><p n="education">UKA</p><p n="course">Engineering Design and Appropiate Technology</p><p n="student ID">0023</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><titlePart>ES252 FLUID MECHANICS</titlePart><docTitle><titlePart>Pipe Flow Experiment</titlePart></docTitle><titlePart rend="italic">Laboratory report</titlePart><titlePart><name type="student ID"/> Second Year EDAT Undergraduate I002</titlePart><docTitle><titlePart rend="underlined">Experiment 4: Pipe Flow Experiment</titlePart></docTitle></titlePage><div1 type="toc" n="1"><head rend="underlined">Table of Contents</head><p/></div1></front><body><div1 type="abstract"><head rend="underlined">Summary</head><p n="p1.182"><s n="s1.1;p1.182">In this experiment it was found: </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p2.182"><s n="s1.1;p2.182">Pipe flow will have different flow friction characteristics dependant on whether it is laminar or turbulent. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p3.182"><s n="s1.1;p3.182">At high Reynolds numbers in turbulent flow, the roughness value of the material begins to seriously affect the friction factor, and hence its relationship with <hi rend="italic">Re</hi>. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p4.182"><s n="s1.1;p4.182">From this roughness value, we can determine the likely material used by comparing it with known values for different materials, i.e. wood, steel, gold, etc. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p5.182"><s n="s1.1;p5.182">The friction factor of a pipe at low <hi rend="italic">Re</hi> depends largely on the wall shear stress inherent in the flow. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p6.182"><s n="s1.1;p6.182">In turbulent flow, other stresses additional turbulent stresses slow the fluid down further. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p7.182"><s n="s1.1;p7.182">These stresses influence the value of <hi rend="italic">Cf</hi> and hence should be taken out when calculating <hi rend="italic">Cf</hi>, otherwise the obtained results will not correspond to data on the Moody chart. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p8.182"><s n="s1.1;p8.182">Because of these additional shear stresses, the head loss in the pipe is greater as the fluid moves along it, resulting in the reduced flow velocity. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p9.182"><s n="s1.1;p9.182">In laminar flow, the only stress slowing the fluid is the wall shear stress. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p10.182"><s n="s1.1;p10.182">At low Reynolds numbers, i.e. in the transitional region, the friction factor <hi rend="italic">Cf</hi> in turbulent flow follows the same line as laminar flow, being logarithmically inversely proportional to <hi rend="italic">Re</hi>, as shown on the Moody chart. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p11.182"><s n="s1.2;p11.182">Turbulent flow takes a lot longer to build up a parabolic velocity profile due to the boundary layer going turbulent early on. </s><s n="s2.2;p11.182">The laminar flow forms a parabolic velocity profile faster. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p12.182"><s n="s1.1;p12.182">Building up the velocity profile creates a positive pressure gradient travelling along the pipe, as the fluid close to the pipe wall slows down, leaving positive pressure behind it. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined">Introduction</head><p n="p13.182"><s n="s1.4;p13.182">This experiment investigates the frictional forces inherent in laminar and turbulent pipe flow. </s><s n="s2.4;p13.182">By measuring the pressure drop and flow rate through a pipe, an estimate of the coefficient of friction (friction factor) can be obtained. </s><s n="s3.4;p13.182">Two different flow situations are studied, laminar flow and turbulent flow. </s><s n="s4.4;p13.182">The experimentally obtained values of the coefficient of friction are compared with established results by plotting them on the Moody chart. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined">Background</head><div2><head rend="underlined italic">Laminar Pipe Flow</head><p n="p14.182"><s n="s1.9;p14.182">Flow in a pipe is known as Poiseuille flow (Hagen-Poiseuille in the interest of historical accuracy). </s><s n="s2.9;p14.182">Figure 1<ref target="BAWE_0023d-endnote.001"/> shows the cross-section of a pipe. </s><s n="s3.9;p14.182">Let's assume that the fluid is incompressible. </s><s n="s4.9;p14.182">It is known that the liquid immediately in contact with the wall of the pipe is stationary (the no-slip condition), and that velocity <hi rend="italic">u</hi> is a function of <hi rend="italic">r</hi>, radius, i.e. flow velocity increases as we move away from the wall. </s><s n="s5.9;p14.182">This function of <hi rend="italic">r</hi> and <hi rend="italic">u</hi>,<hi rend="italic"> u</hi>(<hi rend="italic">r</hi>) is known as the velocity profile. </s><s n="s6.9;p14.182">This is independent of flow direction distance, <hi rend="italic">x</hi>. </s><s n="s7.9;p14.182">We consider the shaded element<formula notation="" id="BAWE_0023d-form.001"/> in Figure 1, which has length<formula notation="" id="BAWE_0023d-form.002"/> in the <hi rend="italic">x</hi> direction. </s><s n="s8.9;p14.182">The viscous forces on the faces of this element vary because of the different velocity gradients (one is closer to the wall than the other) and areas (dependant on<formula notation="" id="BAWE_0023d-form.003"/>). </s><s n="s9.9;p14.182">Therefore, the force on one face is </s></p><note place="end" id="BAWE_0023d-endnote.001"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">FIG 2.4, P11, Physical Fluid Dynamics - Tritton </s></p></note><p rend="ordered" n="p15.182"><s n="s1.1;p15.182"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0023d-form.004"/> (1) </s></p><p n="p16.182"><s n="s1.2;p16.182">where<formula notation="" id="BAWE_0023d-form.005"/> is the (constant) coefficient of viscosity of the fluid. </s><s n="s2.2;p16.182">The net viscous for on the element is therefore </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p17.182"><s n="s1.1;p17.182"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0023d-form.006"/> (2) </s></p><p n="p18.182"><s n="s1.1;p18.182">The pressure on one end of the element is </s></p><p n="p19.182"><s n="s1.1;p19.182"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0023d-form.007"/> </s></p><p n="p20.182"><s n="s1.1;p20.182">and the net pressure force is </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p21.182"><s n="s1.1;p21.182"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0023d-form.008"/> (3) </s></p><p n="p22.182"><s n="s1.3;p22.182">The partial derivative may be replaced with a total derivative<formula notation="" id="BAWE_0023d-form.009"/> as <hi rend="italic">p</hi> varies <hi rend="underlined">only</hi> with <hi rend="italic">x</hi>. </s><s n="s2.3;p22.182">Also, as the velocity profile remains unchanged as we move down the pipe, the pressure gradient (pressure per unit volume) must be independent of <hi rend="italic">x</hi>. </s><s n="s3.3;p22.182">Therefore </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p23.182"><s n="s1.1;p23.182"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0023d-form.010"/> (4) </s></p><p n="p24.182"><s n="s1.1;p24.182">where <hi rend="italic">l</hi> is the length of pipe. </s></p><p n="p25.182"><s n="s1.2;p25.182">As we move down the pipe, the momentum of the element<formula notation="" id="BAWE_0023d-form.011"/> is not changing, each particle of fluid moves at the same distance from the pipe wall all the way down the stream, and so with constant speed. </s><s n="s2.2;p25.182">Hence, the total force acting must be zero, from (2) and (3): </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p26.182"><s n="s1.1;p26.182"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0023d-form.012"/> (5) </s></p><p n="p27.182"><s n="s1.1;p27.182">Combining (4) and (5) obtains </s></p><p n="p28.182"><s n="s1.1;p28.182"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0023d-form.013"/> </s></p><p n="p29.182"><s n="s1.1;p29.182">Integrating gives </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p30.182"><s n="s1.1;p30.182"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0023d-form.014"/> (6) </s></p><p n="p31.182"><s n="s1.2;p31.182">To find <hi rend="italic">A</hi> and <hi rend="italic">B</hi>, we look at the boundary conditions, i.e. the no-slip condition where <hi rend="italic">u</hi>=0. </s><s n="s2.2;p31.182">This is at the wall, <hi rend="italic">r</hi>=<hi rend="italic">a</hi>, giving </s></p><p n="p32.182"><s n="s1.1;p32.182"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0023d-form.015"/> </s></p><p n="p33.182"><s n="s1.1;p33.182">Therefore the velocity profile is a parabola with a maximum speed of </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p34.182"><s n="s1.2;p34.182"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0023d-form.016"/> . </s><s n="s2.2;p34.182">(7) </s></p><p n="p35.182"><s n="s1.1;p35.182">The average speed of flow, or mass per unit time, passing through the pipe is </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p36.182"><s n="s1.1;p36.182"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0023d-form.017"/> (8) </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined italic">Reynolds Number</head><p n="p37.182"><s n="s1.2;p37.182">The Reynolds number is a dimensionless number which relates inertial forces and viscous forces in flow. </s><s n="s2.2;p37.182">Its general definition is </s></p><p n="p38.182"><s n="s1.1;p38.182"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0023d-form.018"/> </s></p><p n="p39.182"><s n="s1.1;p39.182">where </s></p><list type="simple"><item><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0023d-form.019"/> is the density of the fluid </item><item><hi rend="italic">U</hi> is the velocity scale </item><item><hi rend="italic">L</hi> is the length scale </item><item><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0023d-form.020"/> is the coefficient of viscosity of the fluid.</item></list><p n="p40.182"><s n="s1.1;p40.182">For pipe flows, the configuration is similar: </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p41.182"><s n="s1.1;p41.182"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0023d-form.021"/> (9) </s></p><p n="p42.182"><s n="s1.1;p42.182">where </s></p><list type="simple"><item><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0023d-form.022"/> is the average velocity across... </item><item><hi rend="italic">d</hi>, the pipe diameter.</item></list></div2><div2><head rend="underlined italic">Entry Region</head><p n="p43.182"><s n="s1.8;p43.182">This Poiseuille flow theory only works with Reynolds numbers less than ~30. </s><s n="s2.8;p43.182">After that, the there is no parabolic velocity profile. </s><s n="s3.8;p43.182">Indeed there is, but it only materialises a distance down the pipe. </s><s n="s4.8;p43.182">This is because the fluid enters the pipe from a reservoir 'pretty' square on, and so the speed across the pipe diameter is the same at the entry point. </s><s n="s5.8;p43.182">Instantly, the fluid at the pipe wall slows down due to no-slip conditions, and then adjacent fluid is frictionally slowed until the parabolic feature is formed. </s><s n="s6.8;p43.182">(It could also be viewed that as the outer wall fluid slows and stops, the rest of the fluid has to speed up to conserve mass). </s><s n="s7.8;p43.182">The length needed until the parabola is formed is called the Entry Length, after which the Poiseuille flow theory applies. </s><s n="s8.8;p43.182">A diagram of laminar velocity profiles in pipe entry length, base on average of various experimental and theoretical profiles, is given in Figure 2<ref target="BAWE_0023d-endnote.002"/>. </s></p><note place="end" id="BAWE_0023d-endnote.002"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">FIG 2.5, P15, Physical Fluid Dynamics - Tritton </s></p></note><p n="p44.182"><s n="s1.1;p44.182">We can illustrate the dependence of the entry length on the Reynolds number by looking at how long we have to travel in the pipe until<formula notation="" id="BAWE_0023d-form.023"/> at the centre of the pipe is within 5% of its calculated Poiseuille value, with relatively high (<formula notation="" id="BAWE_0023d-form.024"/>) Reynolds numbers using </s></p><p n="p45.182"><s n="s1.1;p45.182"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0023d-form.025"/> </s></p><p n="p46.182"><s n="s1.1;p46.182">where </s></p><list type="simple"><item><hi rend="italic">X</hi> is the distance along the pipe from entry </item><item><hi rend="italic">d</hi> is the pipe diameter.</item></list><p n="p47.182"><s n="s1.2;p47.182">For turbulent flow, the entry region starts off laminar as with laminar pipe flow. </s><s n="s2.2;p47.182">However, above a certain boundary layer thickness, because of the high Reynolds number, the flow becomes turbulent and vortices occur, leaving a laminar region right near the wall only a small magnitude of a millimetre deep. </s></p><p n="p48.182"><s n="s1.3;p48.182">Entry region is also affected by the pipe start. </s><s n="s2.3;p48.182">Because of the change in profile of the flow region, as the fluid enters the pipe down a cone-shape, head loss can occur at the entry region because of turbulence, which gives rise to pressure losses. </s><s n="s3.3;p48.182">Pressure gains are apparent while a velocity profile is developing because the pressure at the pipe wall increases as the fluid slows down, because fluid ahead of that point is travelling slower, i.e. </s></p><p n="p49.182"><s n="s1.1;p49.182">At entry point </s></p><list type="simple"><item> wall speed = 2m/s (say)</item><item> mid pipe speed = 2m/s (say)</item></list><p n="p50.182"><s n="s1.1;p50.182">then, </s></p><p n="p51.182"><s n="s1.1;p51.182">Along pipe </s></p><list type="simple"><item> wall speed = 1m/s (say)</item><item> mid pipe speed = 4m/s (say)</item></list><p n="p52.182"><s n="s1.2;p52.182">to conserve mass. </s><s n="s2.2;p52.182">As the velocity profile takes longer to develop in turbulent flow, this effect will be less apparent. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined italic">Turbulent Flow</head><p n="p53.182"><s n="s1.4;p53.182">From Reynolds experimental data, he found that laminar flow is limited to roughly<formula notation="" id="BAWE_0023d-form.026"/>, after which the flow goes turbulent. </s><s n="s2.4;p53.182">In turbulent flow the flow velocity and movement becomes very random. </s><s n="s3.4;p53.182">A typical plot of velocity in turbulent flow is shown in Figure 3<ref target="BAWE_0023d-endnote.003"/>. </s><s n="s4.4;p53.182">In terms of pressure gradient versus the flow rate, Figure 4<ref target="BAWE_0023d-endnote.004"/> shows that for a given flow rate, the pressure difference needed to produce said flow rate is greater than in laminar flow. </s></p><note place="end" id="BAWE_0023d-endnote.003"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">FIG 2.6, P16, Physical Fluid Dynamics - Tritton </s></p></note><note place="end" id="BAWE_0023d-endnote.004"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">FIG 2.11, P19, Physical Fluid Dynamics - Tritton </s></p></note></div2><div2><head rend="underlined italic">Laminar pipe flow and wall shear stress</head><p n="p54.182"><s n="s1.3;p54.182">Using Figure 4, we can balance shear forces (in the <hi rend="italic">x</hi>-direction), similar to (5). </s><s n="s2.3;p54.182">No acceleration in the fluid means that all forces are balanced. </s><s n="s3.3;p54.182">Thus </s></p><p n="p55.182"><s n="s1.1;p55.182"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0023d-form.027"/> </s></p><p n="p56.182"><s n="s1.1;p56.182">Re-arranging gives shear stress in the limit <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0023d-form.028"/> </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p57.182"><s n="s1.1;p57.182"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0023d-form.029"/> (10) </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined italic">Friction Coefficient (Friction Factor)</head><p n="p58.182"><s n="s1.1;p58.182">This is a dimensionless wall shear stress, <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0023d-form.030"/> </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p59.182"><s n="s1.1;p59.182"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0023d-form.031"/> (11) </s></p><p n="p60.182"><s n="s1.1;p60.182">where<formula notation="" id="BAWE_0023d-form.032"/> from (8), mean flow speed of the fluid. </s></p><p n="p61.182"><s n="s1.1;p61.182">By combining (10) and (11), it can be shown that </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p62.182"><s n="s1.1;p62.182"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0023d-form.033"/> (12) </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined italic">Wall Shear Stress</head><p n="p63.182"><s n="s1.3;p63.182">The wall shear stress can be derived by using (10) and substituting <hi rend="italic">R</hi> as <hi rend="italic">r</hi>. </s><s n="s2.3;p63.182">We then use equation (8) to substitute for the pressure gradient, <hi rend="italic">G</hi>. </s><s n="s3.3;p63.182">This gives </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p64.182"><s n="s1.1;p64.182"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0023d-form.034"/> (13) </s></p><p n="p65.182"><s n="s1.2;p65.182">This shows that mean flow speed is directly proportional to friction. </s><s n="s2.2;p65.182">Substituting (13) into (11) reveals </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p66.182"><s n="s1.1;p66.182"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0023d-form.035"/> (14) </s></p><p n="p67.182"><s n="s1.1;p67.182">where<formula notation="" id="BAWE_0023d-form.036"/> in pipes. </s></p><p n="p68.182"><s n="s1.2;p68.182">In turbulent flow, the products of turbulent fluctuations,<formula notation="" id="BAWE_0023d-form.037"/> gives rise to additional shear stresses. </s><s n="s2.2;p68.182">These turbulent shear stresses, </s></p><p n="p69.182"><s n="s1.1;p69.182"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0023d-form.038"/> </s></p><p n="p70.182"><s n="s1.1;p70.182">are called Reynolds stresses. </s></p><p n="p71.182"><s n="s1.1;p71.182">Therefore the total shear stress in a turbulent fluid can be expressed as </s></p><p n="p72.182"><s n="s1.1;p72.182"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0023d-form.039"/> </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined italic">Effects of surface roughness</head><p n="p73.182"><s n="s1.3;p73.182">Most calculations and analysis are done under the assumption that the pipe surface is smooth. </s><s n="s2.3;p73.182">In real situations however, this is not true. </s><s n="s3.3;p73.182">For laminar flows, however, flow is unaffected as the flow merely passes over these protrusions. </s></p><p n="p74.182"><s n="s1.5;p74.182">In turbulent flow, even the smallest roughness can have a major effect. </s><s n="s2.5;p74.182">Looking at the turbulent boundary layer, if the protrusions are so small as to lie within the viscous sub-layer, the flow is unaffected, and the surface is said to be hydraulically smooth. </s><s n="s3.5;p74.182">However, if the protrusions are large enough then they reach fully into the turbulent core. </s><s n="s4.5;p74.182">This causes the viscosity to become irrelevant and so Reynolds number plays no part in the flow, which is now determined by the size of the roughness elements. </s><s n="s5.5;p74.182">If the protrusions extend only into the buffer lawyer, the flow is dependant on both roughness size and Reynolds number. </s></p><p n="p75.182"><s n="s1.4;p75.182">Nikuradse (1933) carried out experiments using different roughness of sand to determine surface roughness. </s><s n="s2.4;p75.182">Thus the wall friction coefficient <hi rend="italic">Cf</hi> can be found for various grain sizes, <hi rend="italic">ks</hi>. </s><s n="s3.4;p75.182">He found the following three regimes of roughness, using a non-dimensional value of roughness height,<formula notation="" id="BAWE_0023d-form.040"/>. </s><s n="s4.4;p75.182">Where<formula notation="" id="BAWE_0023d-form.041"/> and<formula notation="" id="BAWE_0023d-form.042"/> </s></p><list type="ordered"><item>Hydraulically smooth:<formula notation="" id="BAWE_0023d-form.043"/><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0023d-form.044"/>Viscous dependence only</item><item>Transition roughness:<formula notation="" id="BAWE_0023d-form.045"/><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0023d-form.046"/>Viscous and roughness dependence</item><item>Completely rough:<formula notation="" id="BAWE_0023d-form.047"/></item></list></div2><div2><head rend="underlined italic">The Moody Chart</head><p n="p76.182"><s n="s1.6;p76.182">At high enough Reynolds numbers, the friction factor of many pipes becomes independent of <hi rend="italic">Re</hi>, whereas with lower Reynolds numbers the friction factor varies greatly with <hi rend="italic">Re</hi>, as the irregularities of the material protrude through the viscous sub-layer at different <hi rend="italic">Re</hi> values. </s><s n="s2.6;p76.182">Under these conditions the Nikuradse equations and graphs cannot be used. </s><s n="s3.6;p76.182">An equivalent grain size for large values of Re can be specified for the pipe. </s><s n="s4.6;p76.182">These roughness values (in mm) cannot be measured, however using current observed roughness values, American engineer Lewis F. Moody (1880 - 1953) prepared a diagram which can be used with commercial pipes, based on results obtained by C. F. </s><s n="s5.6;p76.182">Colebrook. </s><s n="s6.6;p76.182">It allows engineers to find the friction factor of a pipe with given roughness <hi rend="italic">k</hi>, from a calculation Reynolds number <hi rend="italic">Re</hi>, therefore determining whether the fluid is in Laminar or Turbulent flow, or a transition value. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined italic">Pipe Pressure Measurement</head><p n="p77.182"><s n="s1.7;p77.182">Pipe pressure measurement is achieved using a manometer. </s><s n="s2.7;p77.182">In it's simplest form a manometer is a device consisting of columns of liquid in a U-tube set in a vertical plane, with one end connected to what is being measures, and the other end to the atmosphere. </s><s n="s3.7;p77.182">A denser liquid, which is immiscible to what is being measured, is used in the U-tube. </s><s n="s4.7;p77.182">From measurements of the height difference of this liquid between one length of the tube and another, a pressure difference between <hi rend="italic">p</hi> and <hi rend="italic">patm</hi> can be found. </s><s n="s5.7;p77.182">To measure the pressure between two points, the manometer can take the form of Figure 5<ref target="BAWE_0023d-endnote.005"/>. </s><s n="s6.7;p77.182">Because the mercury is incompressible, and points A and B are connected, they have to have the same pressure. </s><s n="s7.7;p77.182">Therefore </s></p><note place="end" id="BAWE_0023d-endnote.005"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">PJT/NGS/MC - February 1998 </s></p></note><p n="p78.182"><s n="s1.1;p78.182"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0023d-form.048"/> </s></p><p n="p79.182"><s n="s1.1;p79.182">From Bernoulli's equation </s></p><p n="p80.182"><s n="s1.1;p80.182"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0023d-form.049"/>, </s></p><p n="p81.182"><s n="s1.1;p81.182">where </s></p><list type="simple"><item><hi rend="italic">V</hi> velocity averaged over cross-section (m/s) </item><item><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0023d-form.050"/> density (kg/m³) </item><item><hi rend="italic">g</hi> acceleration due to gravity (m/s²) </item><item><hi rend="italic">z</hi> distance (m),</item></list><p n="p82.182"><s n="s1.1;p82.182">it can be shown that </s></p><p n="p83.182"><s n="s1.1;p83.182"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0023d-form.051"/> </s></p><p n="p84.182"><s n="s1.1;p84.182">Therefore </s></p><p n="p85.182"><s n="s1.1;p85.182"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0023d-form.052"/>, </s></p><p n="p86.182"><s n="s1.1;p86.182">Likewise <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0023d-form.053"/>. </s></p><p n="p87.182"><s n="s1.1;p87.182">Subtracting: </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p88.182"><s n="s1.2;p88.182"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0023d-form.054"/>. </s><s n="s2.2;p88.182">(15) </s></p><p n="p89.182"><s n="s1.1;p89.182"><hi rend="italic">p</hi><hi rend="sub">1</hi><hi rend="italic">−p</hi><hi rend="sub">2</hi> represents the pressure drop between points 1 and 2. </s></p><p n="p90.182"><s n="s1.1;p90.182"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0023d-form.055"/> </s></p><p n="p91.182"><s n="s1.1;p91.182">therefore <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0023d-form.056"/> </s></p><p n="p92.182"><s n="s1.1;p92.182">Finally, divide through by<formula notation="" id="BAWE_0023d-form.057"/>, giving </s></p><p n="p93.182"><s n="s1.1;p93.182"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0023d-form.058"/> </s></p><p n="p94.182"><s n="s1.1;p94.182">so <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0023d-form.059"/>, </s></p><p n="p95.182"><s n="s1.1;p95.182">where <hi rend="italic">hs</hi>, <hi rend="italic">h</hi><hi rend="sub">1</hi> and <hi rend="italic">h</hi><hi rend="sub">2</hi> are all in metres. </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined">Apparatus</head><p n="p96.182"><s n="s1.3;p96.182">Figure 6 shows the flow diagram of the system. </s><s n="s2.3;p96.182">Table 1 shows where pressure is measured relative to the end face of the pipe. </s><s n="s3.3;p96.182">Figure 7 is a detailed view of the pipe tappings, intake and outlet. </s></p><p n="p97.182"><s n="s1.6;p97.182">The apparatus consists of a horizontal pipe with tappings along the length of it. </s><s n="s2.6;p97.182">One end of the pipe is connected to a fluid reservoir which is filled from a pump. </s><s n="s3.6;p97.182">The pump takes its intake from a second pipe which runs from a reservoir at the outlet of the first pipe. </s><s n="s4.6;p97.182">This reservoir is balanced on weighing scales and a valve controls whether flow is allowed out of it. </s><s n="s5.6;p97.182">The pipe work is set up so that the Reynolds number is at a transition stage somewhere between laminar and turbulent flow, i.e.<formula notation="" id="BAWE_0023d-form.060"/>. </s><s n="s6.6;p97.182">A plunger at the start of the pipe can be used to disturb the laminar flow and turn it to turbulent. </s></p><p n="p98.182"><s n="s1.2;p98.182">The pipe tappings are connected to a manometer similar to that shown in Figure 5. </s><s n="s2.2;p98.182">Mercury is used in the pipes as it is more dense than the oil and to aid reading the levels. </s></p><list type="simple"><head>Data:</head><item> Absolute viscosity of oil μ = 0.01743 Ns/m²</item><item> Density of oil ρ<hi rend="sub">oil</hi> = 861 kg/m³</item><item> Density of mercury ρ<hi rend="sub">Hg</hi> = 13530 kg/m³, at a temperature of 300K.</item><item> internal diameter of pipe d = 0.019 m.</item></list></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined">Experimental Procedure</head><p n="p99.182"><s n="s1.2;p99.182">Two runs - one for LAMINAR flow and one for TURBULENT flow. </s><s n="s2.2;p99.182">In both cases: </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p100.182"><s n="s1.1;p100.182">Measure the mass flow rate and therefore<formula notation="" id="BAWE_0023d-form.061"/> in<formula notation="" id="BAWE_0023d-form.062"/>. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p101.182"><s n="s1.2;p101.182">Pressure at various points along the pipe using the static holes and manometer. </s><s n="s2.2;p101.182">These results can be plotted on a graph to determine the pressure gradient <hi rend="italic">G</hi>, as<formula notation="" id="BAWE_0023d-form.063"/>, using the identity<formula notation="" id="BAWE_0023d-form.064"/>. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p102.182"><s n="s1.1;p102.182">Find <hi rend="italic">Cf</hi> (11) and <hi rend="italic">Red</hi>. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p103.182"><s n="s1.1;p103.182">Compare values with Moody chart and comment. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined">Hypothesis</head><p n="p104.182"><s n="s1.2;p104.182">The entry region for both the laminar and turbulent flows should form a parabolic velocity profile a short distance down the pipe. </s><s n="s2.2;p104.182">This can be calculated for the laminar flow using </s></p><p n="p105.182"><s n="s1.1;p105.182"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0023d-form.065"/> </s></p><p n="p106.182"><s n="s1.3;p106.182">For laminar flow, the entry region should see a slight head drop for part way along the pipe due to adverse pressure gradients forming as the profile decreases. </s><s n="s2.3;p106.182">However, the first tapping should be too far down the pipe for this to be observable. </s><s n="s3.3;p106.182">This will not occur in turbulent flow because the flow is already turbulent! </s></p><p n="p107.182"><s n="s1.6;p107.182">Figure 4 shows that for a given flow rate, the pressure difference needed to produce said flow rate is greater than in laminar flow. </s><s n="s2.6;p107.182">There should be a similar correlation in this experiment, with a deeper pressure gradient in turbulent compared with laminar, flow. </s><s n="s3.6;p107.182">To achieve this higher pressure difference, the flow needs to slow down, as was determined for laminar flow in (8). </s><s n="s4.6;p107.182">Because of the transition to turbulent,<formula notation="" id="BAWE_0023d-form.066"/> isn't the only thing which determines flow speed and pressure gradient. </s><s n="s5.6;p107.182">There are additional shear stresses,<formula notation="" id="BAWE_0023d-form.067"/>, inherent in the flow which slow the fluid down and increase pressure gradient, as reviewed in "<hi rend="italic">Wall Shear stress</hi>". </s><s n="s6.6;p107.182">These additional stresses hence increase the <hi rend="italic">Cf</hi> value when using equation (12). </s></p><p n="p108.182"><s n="s1.2;p108.182">Because the flow has been tripped to turbulent in the turbulent flow, one would assume that it's Reynolds number is less that that for laminar flow. </s><s n="s2.2;p108.182">However this is not the case as the apparatus is in a transitional stage and therefore the Reynolds numbers should be similar for both procedures. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined">Observations and Results</head><div2><head rend="underlined italic">Laminar Flow</head><p n="p109.182"><s n="s1.1;p109.182">For <hi rend="italic">Cf</hi> [equation (12)], two unknowns need to be found. <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0023d-form.068"/> can be found by measuring the amount of time taken to fill the reservoir with 80lbs of oil: </s></p><list type="simple"><item>Start Weight:- 81.5lbs</item><item>Finish Weight:- 161.5lbs</item><item>Time:- 60secs</item><item>Mass Flow:- 80lbs</item><item> 36.29kg</item></list><p n="p110.182"><s n="s1.1;p110.182">From here mass flow rate was found: </s></p><p n="p111.182"><s n="s1.1;p111.182"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0023d-form.069"/>, </s></p><p n="p112.182"><s n="s1.1;p112.182">the volumetric flow rate, </s></p><p n="p113.182"><s n="s1.1;p113.182"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0023d-form.070"/>, </s></p><p n="p114.182"><s n="s1.1;p114.182">and hence the speed of flow, </s></p><p n="p115.182"><s n="s1.1;p115.182"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0023d-form.071"/>, </s></p><p n="p116.182"><s n="s1.1;p116.182">where <hi rend="italic">A</hi> is the cross-sectional area of the pipe. </s></p><p n="p117.182"><s n="s1.3;p117.182">Results from the manometer readings are given in Table 2. </s><s n="s2.3;p117.182">These are compiled into a chart against the length of the tapping from the pipe end face on Graph 1. </s><s n="s3.3;p117.182">From the equation of the graph we can we can determine (say), </s></p><p n="p118.182"><s n="s1.1;p118.182"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0023d-form.072"/> </s></p><p n="p119.182"><s n="s1.1;p119.182"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0023d-form.073"/> </s></p><p n="p120.182"><s n="s1.1;p120.182">Equation (15) can be re-arranged to give </s></p><p n="p121.182"><s n="s1.1;p121.182"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0023d-form.074"/> </s></p><p n="p122.182"><s n="s1.1;p122.182">Therefore, </s></p><p n="p123.182"><s n="s1.1;p123.182"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0023d-form.075"/>, </s></p><p n="p124.182"><s n="s1.1;p124.182">and </s></p><p n="p125.182"><s n="s1.1;p125.182"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0023d-form.076"/>. </s></p><p n="p126.182"><s n="s1.1;p126.182">Substituting into (12) reveals </s></p><p n="p127.182"><s n="s1.1;p127.182"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0023d-form.077"/>. </s></p><p n="p128.182"><s n="s1.1;p128.182">Again, to find Reynolds number using (9), with<formula notation="" id="BAWE_0023d-form.078"/>: </s></p><p n="p129.182"><s n="s1.1;p129.182"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0023d-form.079"/>. </s></p><p n="p130.182"><s n="s1.1;p130.182">These two values are plotted on the moody chart, Chart 1. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined italic">Turbulent Flow</head><p n="p131.182"><s n="s1.1;p131.182">For <hi rend="italic">Cf</hi> [equation (12)], two unknowns need to be found. <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0023d-form.080"/> can be found by measuring the amount of time taken to fill the reservoir with 80lbs of oil: </s></p><list type="simple"><item>Start Weight:- 81.5lbs</item><item>Finish Weight:- 161.5lbs</item><item>Time:- 68secs</item><item>Mass Flow:- 80lbs</item><item> 36.29kg</item></list><p n="p132.182"><s n="s1.1;p132.182">From here mass flow rate was found: </s></p><p n="p133.182"><s n="s1.1;p133.182"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0023d-form.081"/>, </s></p><p n="p134.182"><s n="s1.1;p134.182">the volumetric flow rate, </s></p><p n="p135.182"><s n="s1.1;p135.182"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0023d-form.082"/>, </s></p><p n="p136.182"><s n="s1.1;p136.182">and hence the speed of flow, </s></p><p n="p137.182"><s n="s1.1;p137.182"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0023d-form.083"/>, </s></p><p n="p138.182"><s n="s1.1;p138.182">where <hi rend="italic">A</hi> is the cross-sectional area of the pipe. </s></p><p n="p139.182"><s n="s1.3;p139.182">Results from the manometer readings are given in Table 3. </s><s n="s2.3;p139.182">These are compiled into a chart against the length of the tapping from the pipe end face on Graph 2. </s><s n="s3.3;p139.182">From the equation of the graph we can we can determine (say), </s></p><p n="p140.182"><s n="s1.1;p140.182"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0023d-form.084"/> </s></p><p n="p141.182"><s n="s1.1;p141.182"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0023d-form.085"/>. </s></p><p n="p142.182"><s n="s1.1;p142.182">Equation (15) can be re-arranged to give </s></p><p n="p143.182"><s n="s1.1;p143.182"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0023d-form.086"/>. </s></p><p n="p144.182"><s n="s1.1;p144.182">Therefore, </s></p><p n="p145.182"><s n="s1.1;p145.182"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0023d-form.087"/>, </s></p><p n="p146.182"><s n="s1.1;p146.182">and </s></p><p n="p147.182"><s n="s1.1;p147.182"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0023d-form.088"/>. </s></p><p n="p148.182"><s n="s1.1;p148.182">Substituting into (12) reveals </s></p><p n="p149.182"><s n="s1.1;p149.182"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0023d-form.089"/>. </s></p><p n="p150.182"><s n="s1.1;p150.182">Again, to find Reynolds number using (9), with<formula notation="" id="BAWE_0023d-form.090"/>. </s></p><p n="p151.182"><s n="s1.1;p151.182"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0023d-form.091"/>. </s></p><p n="p152.182"><s n="s1.1;p152.182">These two values are plotted on the moody chart, Chart 1. </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined">Analysis and Discussion of Results</head><p n="p153.182"><s n="s1.6;p153.182">The velocity is reduced when going from turbulent to laminar flow due to additional wall shear stress,<formula notation="" id="BAWE_0023d-form.092"/>, from the fluctuations in the fluid. </s><s n="s2.6;p153.182">Flow speed is also reduced because of the effects of surface roughness. </s><s n="s3.6;p153.182">Whether this surface roughness is dependant on Reynolds number or not can now be deduced from the results. </s><s n="s4.6;p153.182">Earlier we found that<formula notation="" id="BAWE_0023d-form.093"/>. </s><s n="s5.6;p153.182">Where<formula notation="" id="BAWE_0023d-form.094"/> and<formula notation="" id="BAWE_0023d-form.095"/>. </s><s n="s6.6;p153.182">Using values found in the results and equation (13), we determine that </s></p><p n="p154.182"><s n="s1.1;p154.182"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0023d-form.096"/>, </s></p><p n="p155.182"><s n="s1.1;p155.182"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0023d-form.097"/>, </s></p><p n="p156.182"><s n="s1.1;p156.182"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0023d-form.098"/>, </s></p><p n="p157.182"><s n="s1.1;p157.182">hence <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0023d-form.099"/>. </s></p><p n="p158.182"><s n="s1.2;p158.182">Therefore the Friction Factor is dependant only on the Reynolds number, not the surface roughness. </s><s n="s2.2;p158.182">Hence the point for friction factor against Reynolds number lies along the (straight) laminar flow line of the Moody chart, as has been shown. </s></p><p n="p159.182"><s n="s1.1;p159.182">We can determine the value of the additional shear stresses by comparing the values obtained by (11) and (12) using the shear stress obtained here. </s></p><p n="p160.182"><s n="s1.1;p160.182">Looking at (11) </s></p><p n="p161.182"><s n="s1.1;p161.182"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0023d-form.100"/>, </s></p><p n="p162.182"><s n="s1.1;p162.182">and (12) </s></p><p n="p163.182"><s n="s1.1;p163.182"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0023d-form.101"/>. </s></p><p n="p164.182"><s n="s1.2;p164.182">Therefore it can be seen that the additional shear stresses add an extra 0.0025 onto the friction factor value. </s><s n="s2.2;p164.182">Both of these values have been added to the Moody chart (Chart 1) to show how excluding the additional forces<formula notation="" id="BAWE_0023d-form.102"/> produces a result closer to the analytical result. </s></p><p n="p165.182"><s n="s1.1;p165.182">As<formula notation="" id="BAWE_0023d-form.103"/> is not the only factor that influences the value of<formula notation="" id="BAWE_0023d-form.104"/>, and hence the point on the Moody Chart, the result against the Reynolds number is slightly out on ideal values when using equation (12), and the pressure gradient obtained from results. </s></p><p n="p166.182"><s n="s1.2;p166.182">As with figure 4, a greater pressure gradient is required to produce the flow rate in turbulent flow. </s><s n="s2.2;p166.182">Hence the pressure gradient increases as the flow turns turbulent, and the speed decreases, as expected, a pattern contrary to what would have happened if the two flows had been laminar (see equation (8)), where flow speed is proportional to pressure gradient </s></p><p n="p167.182"><s n="s1.2;p167.182">Both flows have a velocity profile development region. </s><s n="s2.2;p167.182">The development region for the laminar flow experiment can be calculated now using </s></p><p n="p168.182"><s n="s1.1;p168.182"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0023d-form.105"/>. </s></p><p n="p169.182"><s n="s1.1;p169.182">Therefore </s></p><p n="p170.182"><s n="s1.1;p170.182"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0023d-form.106"/>. </s></p><p n="p171.182"><s n="s1.4;p171.182">Hence roughly 1.5m should have been needed for a parabolic velocity profile to develop. </s><s n="s2.4;p171.182">However, looking at Graph 1, we see that the flow has fully developed, i.e. there are no more adverse pressure gradients, from roughly 0.5m down the pipe. </s><s n="s3.4;p171.182">Therefore this result is flawed. </s><s n="s4.4;p171.182">In the case of turbulent flow, the velocity profile took a lot longer to develop, hence the effects cannot be seen that greatly. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined">Recommendations for Future Work</head><p n="p172.182"><s n="s1.2;p172.182">For a more accurate estimation of flow in this pipe, one might want to look at the pipe roughness value in turbulent flow by taking the Reynolds number a lot higher. </s><s n="s2.2;p172.182">For different (high) values of Reynolds number, these can be compared on the Moody chart to find the roughness value <hi rend="italic">k</hi> of the pipe and hence it's likely material. </s></p><p n="p173.182"><s n="s1.2;p173.182">These results however could only be obtained by changing the set-up of the equipment to give different Reynolds numbers. </s><s n="s2.2;p173.182">This would involve changing the geometry of the pipe work or, better, changing the pump speed to increase <hi rend="italic">Re</hi>. </s></p><p n="p174.182"><s n="s1.1;p174.182">A way to get the turbulent results to correspond on the Moody chart better would be to include the additional stresses in the evaluation of the friction factor and Reynolds number in the experimental procedure. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined">Conclusions</head><p n="p175.182"><s n="s1.1;p175.182">In conclusion it is found: </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p176.182"><s n="s1.1;p176.182">The friction factor of a pipe depends largely on the wall shear stress inherent in the flow. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p177.182"><s n="s1.1;p177.182">In turbulent flow, other stresses additional turbulent stresses slow the fluid down further. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p178.182"><s n="s1.1;p178.182">These stresses influence the value of <hi rend="italic">Cf</hi> and hence should be taken out when calculating <hi rend="italic">Cf</hi>, otherwise the obtained results will not correspond to data on the Moody chart. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p179.182"><s n="s1.1;p179.182">Because of these additional shear stresses, the head loss in the pipe is greater as the fluid moves along it, resulting in the reduced flow velocity. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p180.182"><s n="s1.1;p180.182">In laminar flow, the only stress slowing the fluid is the wall shear stress. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p181.182"><s n="s1.1;p181.182">At low Reynolds numbers, i.e. in the transitional region, the friction factor <hi rend="italic">Cf</hi> in turbulent flow follows the same line as laminar flow, being logarithmically inversely proportional to <hi rend="italic">Re</hi>, as shown on the Moody chart. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p182.182"><s n="s1.2;p182.182">Turbulent flow takes a lot longer to build up a parabolic velocity profile due to the boundary layer going turbulent early on. </s><s n="s2.2;p182.182">The laminar flow forms a parabolic velocity profile faster. </s></p></div1></body><back><div1 type="bibliography"><head rend="underlined">Bibliography</head><p/></div1><div1 type="missing or external appendix"><p/></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
