<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_0023a" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Case Study 2:Midland Metro</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">The document has a title page which contains:
title part</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">1</p><p n="date">2002-12</p><p n="module title">Professional Studies</p><p n="module code">ES156</p><p n="genre family">Design specification</p><p n="discipline">Engineering</p><p n="disciplinary group">PS</p><p n="grade">D</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">1901</p><p n="number of s-units">93</p><p n="number of p">29</p><p n="number of tables">4</p><p n="number of figures">1</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">6</p><p n="number of lists">1</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">0</p><p n="abstract present">abstract present</p><p n="average words per s-unit">20.4</p><p n="average s-units per p">3.2</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">m</p><p n="year of birth">1984</p><p n="first language">English</p><p n="education">UKA</p><p n="course">Engineering Design and Appropiate Technology</p><p n="student ID">0023</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><titlePart><hi rend="underlined">ES 156 PROFESSIONAL</hi> <hi rend="underlined">STUDIES</hi></titlePart><titlePart>Case Study 2: Midland Metro</titlePart><titlePart rend="italic">Written Assignment 2</titlePart><titlePart><name type="student ID"/> A060 First Year General Engineering Undergraduate</titlePart><titlePart>05/12/2002</titlePart><docTitle><titlePart rend="underlined">Electrical Aspects of Pantograph Design</titlePart></docTitle></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="abstract"><head rend="underlined">Summary</head><p n="p1.29"><s n="s1.6;p1.29">The pantograph will have a wire traversing down the side of middle of one of it's supporting members. </s><s n="s2.6;p1.29">The power could have been sent through the frame itself, however this creates problems with insulating the up/down mechanism on the pantograph and the tram body. </s><s n="s3.6;p1.29">Here I have looked at whether to use AC or DC through the pantograph and advantages and disadvantages for each. </s><s n="s4.6;p1.29">I have also looked at the conductor used in the pantograph and how that's going to be insulated. </s><s n="s5.6;p1.29">In looking at the conductor I have seen how the resistivity of the wire affects the cross-sectional area of wire required and it's shape. </s><s n="s6.6;p1.29">Lastly, I have looked at how to join the wiring on the pantograph to limit corrosion and benefit maintenance. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined">Current through wire</head><div2><head rend="underlined">AC vs. DC through Pantograph</head><table id="BAWE_0023a-tab.001"><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p2.29"><s n="s1.1;p2.29">Although there are many more disadvantages to DC than to AC, I have decided the best choice of current would be DC because the disadvantages are less significant than those of AC. For example, even though there will be more losses through the wire with DC current as it can't be transformed to a high voltage, there will be less losses in the motor as you won't be limited to alternating the motor speed using resistors, which will carry a much higher resistance and therefore loose much more current than in any piece of wire in getting there. </s></p><p n="p3.29"><s n="s1.2;p3.29">Because DC can't be transformed, we'll have to use lower voltage all the way through. </s><s n="s2.2;p3.29">This means the gap between any conductor and insulated frame need not be bigger than a few millimetres, although the static and passing gaps formed by the Heath and Safety Executive enforce 75mm and 25mm gaps respectively, for a voltage up to 750v. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">Voltage Level</head><p n="p4.29"><s n="s1.2;p4.29">We need to come up with a voltage that will be suitable for traversing down a length of wire without too much power loss, and then power a DC motor of similar voltage. </s><s n="s2.2;p4.29">Looking at the equation </s></p><p n="p5.29"><s n="s1.1;p5.29"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0023a-form.001"/> </s></p><p n="p6.29"><s n="s1.4;p6.29">we can see that V is directly proportional to I, with the resistance in the wire, R, as a constant. </s><s n="s2.4;p6.29">Therefore with a large voltage as opposed to a large current, you can have a larger resistance with less loss. </s><s n="s3.4;p6.29">If you have a small voltage however, you will be limited to a small current if R is large to balance both sides of the equation: therefore losses are high. </s><s n="s4.4;p6.29">To optimise the lower losses and limit the need for higher levels of safety standard therefore, we much choose a voltage of 750v, with commercial motor characteristics determining the exact figure. </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined">Conductor</head><p n="p7.29"><s n="s1.1;p7.29">To work out the resistance of any conductor travelling down the pantograph, I will use the equation </s></p><p n="p8.29"><s n="s1.1;p8.29"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0023a-form.002"/> </s></p><p n="p9.29"><s n="s1.1;p9.29">where R is the overall resistance of the conductor, ρ is the resistivity of the material in Ωm, l is the length of the in meters used, and A is it's cross-sectional area in m². </s></p><p n="p10.29"><s n="s1.7;p10.29">Say we wanted to get a R, and we already knew the length of the wire l. </s><s n="s2.7;p10.29">Ideally therefore, we would need to make ρ as small as possible so that we don't need as large value of A, thereby making the wire thinner. </s><s n="s3.7;p10.29">With thinner wire material, comes increased ductility, as the cable is not putting as much compression and tension on the inside and outside respectively, of a bend. </s><s n="s4.7;p10.29">We need to make a compromise therefore between cost and cross-sectional area; as generally speaking, the price of a conductor goes up with a lower resistivity. </s><s n="s5.7;p10.29">Plus this may not be a linear correlation. </s><s n="s6.7;p10.29">Some metals may have a high purity and therefore low resistivity only after taking it through an expensive refinement process several times. </s><s n="s7.7;p10.29">Each time the metal is refined, it may incur a half-life by which the difference in resistivity before and after refinement becomes less each time, making the cost less practical. </s></p><p n="p11.29"><s n="s1.3;p11.29">In the search for a good low-cost conductor, one could easily choose copper and be done with it. </s><s n="s2.3;p11.29">After all, copper is one of the cheapest metals to form because it is so malleable and, for it's electrical characteristics, is of excellent value for money. </s><s n="s3.3;p11.29">Copper has many alloys associated with it, the uses of which are shown below. </s></p><table id="BAWE_0023a-tab.002"><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p12.29"><s n="s1.2;p12.29">As you can see, the only alloy commonly used as an electrical conductor is copper or pure copper. </s><s n="s2.2;p12.29">This is probably due to the higher cost of manufacturing the alloys, as although they might have better electrical characteristics, we could use thicker ordinary copper and still make a saving over the thinner alloys. </s></p><p n="p13.29"><s n="s1.4;p13.29">Times change however. </s><s n="s2.4;p13.29">Copper is not longer as plentiful as it use to be and now the price of the raw material is steadily rising. </s><s n="s3.4;p13.29">Therefore, other materials such as aluminium, which is steadily being caught by copper price wise, have to be taken into consideration. </s><s n="s4.4;p13.29">A table of a few conductors and there association with copper is shown below. </s></p><table id="BAWE_0023a-tab.003"><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p14.29"><s n="s1.3;p14.29">As you can see, copper still wins on conductivity, but if weight was a critical factor, aluminium would win, having 214% of the conductivity of copper per unit mass. </s><s n="s2.3;p14.29">The only point where steel alloy would be useful is it's high tensile strength, however this is not a deciding factor as the wire is simply traversing the frame of the pantograph, therefore it is not in any tension, so strength is largely irrelevant. </s><s n="s3.3;p14.29">Also, weight is not a critical factor because the material is small in quantity compared to the weight of the frame. </s></p><p n="p15.29"><s n="s1.5;p15.29">Lets look therefore at a typical example. </s><s n="s2.5;p15.29">A tram may weigh 30 tonnes, that's 30 000kg, and carry 150 passengers with an average weight of 80kg (12 tonnes in total). </s><s n="s3.5;p15.29">The tram could have an average speed of 50km/h, or 14m/s. </s><s n="s4.5;p15.29">Acceleration will be no more than 1.4m/s². </s><s n="s5.5;p15.29">Therefore </s></p><p n="p16.29"><s n="s1.1;p16.29"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0023a-form.003"/> </s></p><p n="p17.29"><s n="s1.1;p17.29"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0023a-form.004"/> </s></p><p n="p18.29"><s n="s1.1;p18.29"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0023a-form.005"/> </s></p><p n="p19.29"><s n="s1.5;p19.29">Using P = V.I , we can obtain a current value for a tolerance 748.5V voltage as being 1100A, which sounds about right for a tram of this sort. </s><s n="s2.5;p19.29">To completely traverse the frame of the pantograph,, we will need not more than 3m of cable. </s><s n="s3.5;p19.29">Because we want to keep losses to a minimum, we want no more than 0.2% voltage drop and to keep the motor within tolerances. </s><s n="s4.5;p19.29">Using R = V/I , this equated to a resistance of 0.013Ω. </s><s n="s5.5;p19.29">To test this I have used a simple circuit with a potential divider to calculate V <hi rend="sub">S</hi> again with the values I found out. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0023a-pic.001"/><p n="p20.29"><s n="s1.1;p20.29">I can now apply this resistance to the equation </s></p><p n="p21.29"><s n="s1.1;p21.29"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0023a-form.006"/> </s></p><p n="p22.29"><s n="s1.7;p22.29">with ρ as 1.673*10 <hi rend="sup">-7 </hi>Ωm, and l as 3m. </s><s n="s2.7;p22.29">This gives a cross-sectional area requirement of 3.7cm². </s><s n="s3.7;p22.29">This cross-sectional area of wire will have to be split up into several stands to make sure that minimum tension and compression is being applied to the outside and inside of the wire, which would be significant if using solid core wire. </s><s n="s4.7;p22.29">If the wire is constantly being bent, i.e. tensioned and compressed too much, then the metal will harden and snap. </s><s n="s5.7;p22.29">This is another reason for using copper, as it's ductility will delay this happening. </s><s n="s6.7;p22.29">Another alternative to the arrangement of strands other than a circular cross-section would be a flat wire. </s><s n="s7.7;p22.29">This will reduce stress in the wire more still, prolonging the life of the wire for maintenance purposes. </s></p><p n="p23.29"><s n="s1.3;p23.29">Another reason of choosing between different materials is their resistance to corrosion. </s><s n="s2.3;p23.29">A list of metals and how they stand in the corrosion hierarchy is listed below. </s><s n="s3.3;p23.29">The metals most prone to corrosion are at the top of the list. </s></p><list type="simple"><item>Magnesium.Aluminium.Duralumin.Zinc.Cadmium.Iron.Chromium iron (active).Chromium-nickel-iron (active).Soft solder.Tin.Lead.Nickel.Brasses.Bronzes.Monel.Copper.Chromium iron (passive).Silver solder.Silver.Gold.Platinum.</item></list><p n="p24.29"><s n="s1.5;p24.29">Looking at the two main choices, aluminium and copper, both create a stable oxide on their surface once exposed to the elements. </s><s n="s2.5;p24.29">The oxides are stable at constant temperature. </s><s n="s3.5;p24.29">However, copper oxides grow if the copper is heated. </s><s n="s4.5;p24.29">If the copper is heated for a lengthy amount of time, then eventually the metal will harden and break. </s><s n="s5.5;p24.29">This is why it is especially important to make sure the copper has a good connection, therefore higher tolerances in the joining processes need to be observed. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined">Connections</head><p n="p25.29"><s n="s1.3;p25.29">The oxidising problem in copper would be particularly prudent in pressure connections where the metal is pressed again another as opposed to forging the metals together. </s><s n="s2.3;p25.29">When pressure connections are used, it is imperative that the right sorts of metals are joined together; otherwise the oxides of the metals will react and create a high resistance at the joint. </s><s n="s3.3;p25.29">A table of suitable connectors for different copper and aluminium alloys is shown below. </s></p><table id="BAWE_0023a-tab.004"><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p26.29"><s n="s1.6;p26.29">The methods for fusion joining are brazing, welding and soldering. </s><s n="s2.6;p26.29">Brazing would be a good choice in this application because of the lower temperature requirements and that is uses brass rod, which is a copper alloy, though a low corrosion silver solder may also be used. </s><s n="s3.6;p26.29">The high temperatures of 650°C - 700°C may still be enough to damage insulation and anneal the conductor though. </s><s n="s4.6;p26.29">A better solution would be to solder the conductors. </s><s n="s5.6;p26.29">This method uses a lead/tin alloy in a ratio of about 40/60. </s><s n="s6.6;p26.29">Solder can melt at a low 200°C, making it more than ideal for this application. </s></p><p n="p27.29"><s n="s1.2;p27.29">For maintenance purposes, however, the best solution would be pressure joints with bolted clamps at either end holding the cables in place. </s><s n="s2.2;p27.29">This way the clamp is re-usable as opposed to bending a flap of metal over to clamp the cable, which would become brittle at the bend as you tried to bend it back. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined">Insulation</head><p n="p28.29"><s n="s1.5;p28.29">Because the voltage is fairly low, only a small gap between live conductors and any exposed metal need be maintained. </s><s n="s2.5;p28.29">At 75mm in open air, this can be done by using durable rubber insulation between the surfaces. </s><s n="s3.5;p28.29">Through my research, I have discovered that the most commonly used and durable insulator is silicon-based rubber, having a high resistance to weathering and high breakdown voltages. </s><s n="s4.5;p28.29">Because neither the copper nor aluminium will adhere to the rubber, adhesives will have to be used, except that rubber which is wrapped around the wire. </s><s n="s5.5;p28.29">The rubber is also flexible, as is crucial when the pantograph is raised or lowered, as it's frame angles adjust as it travels up and down. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined">Conclusions</head><p n="p29.29"><s n="s1.9;p29.29">I have decided the pantograph should run a relatively high voltage of 750v, which is at the top of the scale of the HSE's guidelines without requiring further insulation. </s><s n="s2.9;p29.29">I've decided higher voltage is better because of the reduced losses. </s><s n="s3.9;p29.29">The current drawn will be DC, because the motor will be easier to control that way with fewer losses that resistors in an AC motor. </s><s n="s4.9;p29.29">Also DC doesn't produce inductance in the wire, though this may not be such an issue in this application, even with AC. Insulation will be limited to silicon rubber strips because of the small gaps required between live wire and earthed frame. </s><s n="s5.9;p29.29">The material is both safe and durable and will withstand bad weather. </s><s n="s6.9;p29.29">I have chosen copper as the main conductor because it is cheap at the moment and have good conductivity and ductility. </s><s n="s7.9;p29.29">Aluminium may be considered at a later stage if the price of copper goes up. </s><s n="s8.9;p29.29">Multithread, flat copper wire would be best to stop breakages and give extra flexibility. </s><s n="s9.9;p29.29">Clamp connectors will be used to join wires together, but conductive paste may have to be used to keep contacts clean when operating. </s></p></div1></body><back><div1 type="bibliography"><head rend="underlined">Bibliography</head><p>Tables of conductors and electrical connections, and corrosion list of metals from </p><p><seg type="URL" n="http://www.usbr.gov/power/data/fist/fist3~3/"/></p><p>Table of copper alloy uses from <seg type="URL" n="http://www.knight-group.co.uk/w_copper.htm"/></p></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
