<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_0023e" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Gearbox Design</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">The document has a title page which contains:
document title
title part</note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">deleted: Word count: 4022
deleted: footer giving page number</note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">Running text contains reference to external or missing appendix.
</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">3</p><p n="date">2005-06</p><p n="module title">Design of Machines</p><p n="module code">ES388</p><p n="genre family">Design specification</p><p n="discipline">Engineering</p><p n="disciplinary group">PS</p><p n="grade">D</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">3912</p><p n="number of s-units">255</p><p n="number of p">122</p><p n="number of tables">2</p><p n="number of figures">15</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">54</p><p n="number of lists">3</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">10</p><p n="abstract present">abstract present</p><p n="average words per s-unit">15.3</p><p n="average s-units per p">2.1</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">m</p><p n="year of birth">1984</p><p n="first language">English</p><p n="education">UKA</p><p n="course">Engineering Design and Appropiate Technology</p><p n="student ID">0023</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><titlePart>ES368 DESIGN OF MACHINES</titlePart><docTitle><titlePart>Gearbox Design Assignment</titlePart></docTitle><titlePart><name type="student ID"/> Third Year EDAT Undergraduate O002</titlePart></titlePage><div1 type="toc" n="2"><head rend="underlined">Contents Page</head><p/></div1></front><body><div1 type="abstract"><head rend="underlined">Summary</head><p n="p1.122"><s n="s1.13;p1.122">A compact gearbox design is required to use in an electric drill to produce a 25:1 speed reduction from a motor developing 36W at 9000rpm. </s><s n="s2.13;p1.122">The gearbox arrangement decided is an epicyclic two-stage reduction, each of 5:1 reduction. </s><s n="s3.13;p1.122">A DOS-based analysis tool was used for the analysis of the second stage reduction. </s><s n="s4.13;p1.122">Using a minimum recommended sun gear of 16 teeth, and a module of 1.0, a compact design of epicyclic reduction has been designed, using phosphor bronze material. </s><s n="s5.13;p1.122">The first stage of the reduction uses nylon gears. </s><s n="s6.13;p1.122">This will cut costs compared with metal gears. </s><s n="s7.13;p1.122">The same module and sun gear teeth number has been selected as the second reduction stage. </s><s n="s8.13;p1.122">Rubbing bearings hold the input and output shafts in position while a roller thrust bearing restrains the force acted on the gearbox case by the operator. </s><s n="s9.13;p1.122">The gearbox casing accommodates the gears and bearings. </s><s n="s10.13;p1.122">Seals are places and the front and rear of the gearbox. </s><s n="s11.13;p1.122">The gearbox consists of two identical halves which are located together by means of two M6 fixing screws. </s><s n="s12.13;p1.122">Comparisons with other gearboxes suggest the design is comparable with other gearboxes used in similar applications. </s><s n="s13.13;p1.122">Therefore it is believed that the gearbox is a cost-effective design which makes economic use of available space. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined">Introduction</head><p n="p2.122"><s n="s1.6;p2.122">A battery-powered drill is driven by a 36W electric motor running at 9000 rev/min. </s><s n="s2.6;p2.122">The drill speed is to be about 360 rev/min. </s><s n="s3.6;p2.122">This reduction could be carried out in two identical stages (e.g. two epicyclic gear stages). </s><s n="s4.6;p2.122">Design the speed reduction for the drill and the bearing arrangement to carry the thrust load axially along the drill. </s><s n="s5.6;p2.122">The maximum thrust is what a user can exert onto the drill. </s><s n="s6.6;p2.122">Consider the use of plastic gears for one stage of speed reduction. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined">Theory</head><div2><head rend="underlined italic">Basic gear design theory</head><p n="p3.122"><s n="s1.3;p3.122">The basic force on a gear determine the stress in the teeth and on the gear shaft. </s><s n="s2.3;p3.122">The tangential load <hi rend="italic">F</hi> along the pressure line is dependant on the pitch circle diameter <hi rend="italic">r</hi> and the torque <hi rend="italic">T</hi>. </s><s n="s3.3;p3.122">Hence simply </s></p><p n="p4.122"><s n="s1.1;p4.122"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0023e-form.001"/>. </s></p><p n="p5.122"><s n="s1.2;p5.122">The overall force on the gear <hi rend="italic">F</hi> is a function of the tangential force and the angle upon which the opposing gears act upon each other, the pressure angle<formula notation="" id="BAWE_0023e-form.002"/>. </s><s n="s2.2;p5.122">Now </s></p><p n="p6.122"><s n="s1.1;p6.122"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0023e-form.003"/>. </s></p><p n="p7.122"><s n="s1.2;p7.122">The bending moment <hi rend="italic">M</hi> in the tooth can be calculated simply by modelling the tooth as a cantilever with angle<formula notation="" id="BAWE_0023e-form.004"/> being the angle of <hi rend="italic">F</hi> to the centreline of the tooth. </s><s n="s2.2;p7.122">This is then </s></p><p n="p8.122"><s n="s1.1;p8.122"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0023e-form.005"/>. </s></p><p n="p9.122"><s n="s1.1;p9.122">In a similar manner the stress <hi rend="italic">σb</hi> is determined by the second moment of area <hi rend="italic">M</hi> and tooth thickness <hi rend="italic">t</hi>: </s></p><p n="p10.122"><s n="s1.1;p10.122"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0023e-form.006"/>. </s></p><p n="p11.122"><s n="s1.3;p11.122">where <hi rend="italic">kb</hi> is the stress concentration. </s><s n="s2.3;p11.122">It is inversely proportional to the fillet radius <hi rend="italic">rf</hi>. </s><s n="s3.3;p11.122">The stress may be simplified to </s></p><p n="p12.122"><s n="s1.1;p12.122"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0023e-form.007"/>, where the Lewis Form Factor<formula notation="" id="BAWE_0023e-form.008"/>. </s></p><p n="p13.122"><s n="s1.1;p13.122">To reduce bending stresses therefore make module <hi rend="italic">m</hi> and flank width <hi rend="italic">b</hi> as large as possible. </s></p><p n="p14.122"><s n="s1.2;p14.122">The contact force is transmitted on a line on the flank face of the tooth. </s><s n="s2.2;p14.122">For gears of the same material with a Poisson ratio of 0.3, the contact stress is </s></p><p n="p15.122"><s n="s1.2;p15.122"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0023e-form.009"/>, where<formula notation="" id="BAWE_0023e-form.010"/>. </s><s n="s2.2;p15.122"><hi rend="italic">E</hi> is in MPa. </s></p><p n="p16.122"><s n="s1.3;p16.122">This can be modified for a pair of gears. </s><s n="s2.3;p16.122">For the "rollers" (cylinders) above the radii of curvature for each up to the contact point are ρ<hi rend="sub">1</hi> and ρ<hi rend="sub">2</hi>. </s><s n="s3.3;p16.122">For a gear ratio of U these are modified to </s></p><p n="p17.122"><s n="s1.1;p17.122"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0023e-form.011"/> and<formula notation="" id="BAWE_0023e-form.012"/>. </s></p><p n="p18.122"><s n="s1.1;p18.122">Also, since<formula notation="" id="BAWE_0023e-form.013"/>, </s></p><p n="p19.122"><s n="s1.1;p19.122"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0023e-form.014"/>. </s></p><p n="p20.122"><s n="s1.1;p20.122">Modifying this with a velocity factor<formula notation="" id="BAWE_0023e-form.015"/>, where <hi rend="italic">V</hi> = peripheral speed, yields </s></p><p n="p21.122"><s n="s1.1;p21.122"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0023e-form.016"/>. </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined">Analysis</head><p n="p22.122"><s n="s1.1;p22.122">The ratio for this gearbox will be </s></p><p n="p23.122"><s n="s1.1;p23.122"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0023e-form.017"/>, or 25:1. </s></p><p n="p24.122"><s n="s1.2;p24.122">This would be too high for a single stage reduction; hence the suggestion of a double reduction should be carried out. </s><s n="s2.2;p24.122">Quite simply this could be done using two identical reductions of 5:1. </s></p><p n="p25.122"><s n="s1.2;p25.122">Faigure 1 shows different combination of gear arrangement and gear trains possible. </s><s n="s2.2;p25.122">Gearbox boundaries are indicated by dotted lines and crosses mark bearing points. </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p26.122"><s n="s1.3;p26.122">A compound train system with two reduction stages. </s><s n="s2.3;p26.122">6 bearing are required, with one on the output shaft being a thrust bearing. </s><s n="s3.3;p26.122">This design is simple and effective but would be bulky as it requires extra space for positioning of the layshaft. </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p27.122"><s n="s1.3;p27.122">An inline planetary gearing system with two epicyclic gears. </s><s n="s2.3;p27.122">The inputs are attached to the sun gear and the planets are attached to the gearbox output. </s><s n="s3.3;p27.122">The ring gear remains stationary. </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p28.122"><s n="s1.2;p28.122">A combined planetary and bevel gear arrangement for the possibility of incorporating the drill motor into the handle of the drill casing. </s><s n="s2.2;p28.122">Again the thrust bearing may have to be incorporated into the planetary gear housing. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0023e-pic.001"><head>Figure 1: Different layout and gear combinations</head></figure><p n="p29.122"><s n="s1.2;p29.122">This report will be based upon design (b). </s><s n="s2.2;p29.122">The main reasons for choosing this type of design are: </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p30.122"><s n="s1.2;p30.122">Motor is mounted in axially to chuck. </s><s n="s2.2;p30.122">As this is a battery-powered drill there will likely be little residual space in the handle considering the size of battery packs usually placed at the base. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p31.122"><s n="s1.1;p31.122">Mounting the motor in line with the chuck reduces friction losses compared to the 90degree motion rotation experienced in (c). </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p32.122"><s n="s1.1;p32.122">3 planets means less stress on gears as torque is split three ways. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p33.122"><s n="s1.1;p33.122">Gear train need only be fixed at four points as planets provide bearing for sun gear. </s></p><div2><head rend="underlined italic">Initial manual calculation</head><p n="p34.122"><s n="s1.2;p34.122">The gear ratio in an epicyclic gear is not equivalent to the inverse of the teeth ratio as in a compound gear train. </s><s n="s2.2;p34.122">The gear ratio in a planetary system is </s></p><p n="p35.122"><s n="s1.1;p35.122"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0023e-form.018"/>, </s></p><p n="p36.122"><s n="s1.1;p36.122">where <hi rend="italic">Ns</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Np</hi> are the number of teeth on the sun and planet gears respectively. </s></p><p n="p37.122"><s n="s1.1;p37.122">Hence for a reduction of 5 and a sun with 15 teeth, </s></p><p n="p38.122"><s n="s1.1;p38.122"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0023e-form.019"/>, rearranging gives </s></p><p n="p39.122"><s n="s1.1;p39.122"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0023e-form.020"/>. </s></p><p n="p40.122"><s n="s1.4;p40.122">Obviously a gear of 22.5 teeth is impractical, hence rounding to 23 would produce a gearing ratio of 5.07 which is near enough. </s><s n="s2.4;p40.122">In the calculation which follows, a module of 1.0mm will be used with a material with a of Young's modulus of 210 GPa. </s><s n="s3.4;p40.122">Tooth thickness is 2.0mm. </s><s n="s4.4;p40.122">The ratio of the sun to the planet gear is 1.53. </s></p><p n="p41.122"><s n="s1.1;p41.122">For pinion, pitch circle diameter </s></p><p n="p42.122"><s n="s1.1;p42.122"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0023e-form.021"/>. </s></p><p n="p43.122"><s n="s1.1;p43.122">Lewis form factor is </s></p><p n="p44.122"><s n="s1.1;p44.122"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0023e-form.022"/> </s></p><p n="p45.122"><s n="s1.1;p45.122">Torque <hi rend="italic">T</hi> transmitted </s></p><p n="p46.122"><s n="s1.1;p46.122"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0023e-form.023"/>. </s></p><p n="p47.122"><s n="s1.1;p47.122">Therefore bending stress </s></p><p n="p48.122"><s n="s1.1;p48.122"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0023e-form.024"/>. </s></p><p n="p49.122"><s n="s1.1;p49.122">The contact stress in unmodified Hertzian form is </s></p><p n="p50.122"><s n="s1.1;p50.122"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0023e-form.025"/> </s></p><p n="p51.122"><s n="s1.1;p51.122"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0023e-form.026"/> </s></p><p n="p52.122"><s n="s1.1;p52.122"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0023e-form.027"/>. </s></p><p n="p53.122"><s n="s1.1;p53.122">The velocity factor </s></p><p n="p54.122"><s n="s1.1;p54.122"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0023e-form.028"/>. </s></p><p n="p55.122"><s n="s1.1;p55.122">Therefore modified contact stress </s></p><p n="p56.122"><s n="s1.1;p56.122"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0023e-form.029"/>. </s></p><p n="p57.122"><s n="s1.2;p57.122">All stress values therefore fall below the stress limits for the material. </s><s n="s2.2;p57.122">Not forgetting however that the stress values will likely be a third of that calculated because the planetary system uses three planet gears which each take load from the sun gear. </s></p><p n="p58.122"><s n="s1.2;p58.122">The above calculation is for the first planetary system only. </s><s n="s2.2;p58.122">A separate but similar calculation would be performed on the second planetary system. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined italic">Computer analysis and optimisation</head><p n="p59.122"><s n="s1.4;p59.122">Figure 2 shows the initial run for the first gear train of the gearbox. </s><s n="s2.4;p59.122">The points of interest have been highlighted. </s><s n="s3.4;p59.122">Firstly, upon calculating the program found that the face width was too low for the program parameters. </s><s n="s4.4;p59.122">While this does not affect the result, it means that there may have to be a boss on the gear to allow greater contact length between shaft and gear. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0023e-pic.002"><head>Figure 2: Initial gear program run output</head></figure><p n="p60.122"><s n="s1.2;p60.122">To check that the values in Figure 2 are being calculated accurately by the program, the programs calculations should be performed manually. </s><s n="s2.2;p60.122">The program computes the gear dimensions to BS436, so a few of the input figures have been rounded up to meet that specification, such as the pinion gear tooth number. </s></p><p n="p61.122"><s n="s1.2;p61.122">The chosen modulus for the gear design is 1.0. </s><s n="s2.2;p61.122">Therefore the pitch diameters for the gear <hi rend="italic">DG</hi> and the pinion <hi rend="italic">Dp</hi> can be calculated as </s></p><p n="p62.122"><s n="s1.1;p62.122"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0023e-form.030"/> </s></p><p n="p63.122"><s n="s1.1;p63.122">and <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0023e-form.031"/>, </s></p><p n="p64.122"><s n="s1.2;p64.122">which match the figures presented in the figure. </s><s n="s2.2;p64.122">The centre distance can be similarly calculated as </s></p><p n="p65.122"><s n="s1.1;p65.122"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0023e-form.032"/>. </s></p><p n="p66.122"><s n="s1.1;p66.122">The pitch line speed is </s></p><p n="p67.122"><s n="s1.1;p67.122"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0023e-form.033"/>. </s></p><p n="p68.122"><s n="s1.2;p68.122">Again these results are consistent with those in Figure 2, suggesting the program is doing as suggested. </s><s n="s2.2;p68.122">The face width limits are set at </s></p><p n="p69.122"><s n="s1.1;p69.122"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0023e-form.034"/>. </s></p><p n="p70.122"><s n="s1.2;p70.122">The program computes the ideal face width based on the material properties. </s><s n="s2.2;p70.122">The contact stress on the teeth in the pinion gear is </s></p><p n="p71.122"><s n="s1.1;p71.122"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0023e-form.035"/>. </s></p><p n="p72.122"><s n="s1.1;p72.122">The bending stress is </s></p><p n="p73.122"><s n="s1.1;p73.122"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0023e-form.036"/> </s></p><p n="p74.122"><s n="s1.1;p74.122"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0023e-form.037"/>, </s></p><p n="p75.122"><s n="s1.4;p75.122">where<formula notation="" id="BAWE_0023e-form.038"/> has been calculated based on the assumption that<formula notation="" id="BAWE_0023e-form.039"/>. </s><s n="s2.4;p75.122">Thereby we have a factor of safety of 120 compared with the ultimate tensile strength of the material of 500MPa, based on a<formula notation="" id="BAWE_0023e-form.040"/> of 60 degrees. </s><s n="s3.4;p75.122">Basing the value on an angle of 60 degrees does have its risks though as this value seems pretty high, however based on the bending model described using the Lewis Form Factor this is the nearest approximation to the 120 bending stress factor used in the calculation. </s><s n="s4.4;p75.122">Being as the contact stress is considerably lower than the bending stress, the bending stress is the one that takes priority when calculating face width. </s></p><p n="p76.122"><s n="s1.2;p76.122">It will be best to try to use plastic gears for the first speed reduction ratio. </s><s n="s2.2;p76.122">There are many reasons why plastic gears may be superior to metal ones, including: </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p77.122"><s n="s1.3;p77.122"><hi rend="bold">Suitability for applications where gears are dry running</hi>It is likely that the drill would be designed to be maintenance-free. </s><s n="s2.3;p77.122">Therefore there will be no facility to lubricate the gears or bearings once assembled. </s><s n="s3.3;p77.122">Another advantage is that if the gear does break down slightly because of neglect or dirt ingress, the cascade affect which afflicts metal gears, where shards of flaked gear start to wear other components and more of the gear itself, is not an issue. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p78.122"><s n="s1.3;p78.122"><hi rend="bold">Suitable for use in harsh climates</hi>Plastic gears by their nature are not affected by environmental factors. </s><s n="s2.3;p78.122">They do not corrode such as metal ones would, which is an important factor to consider when designing an electric drill as they are likely to be used in harsh conditions where they may get damp and corrode. </s><s n="s3.3;p78.122">The only disadvantage is that plastics tend to become brittle at low temperatures (<formula notation="" id="BAWE_0023e-form.041"/>). </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p79.122"><s n="s1.2;p79.122"><hi rend="bold">Cost</hi>Although the raw materials for plastic gears may be more expensive than for metal gears, the machining costs are much reduced because of the relative softness of the materials. </s><s n="s2.2;p79.122">The materials are also less abrasive to cutting tools and other parts of the machinery, reducing tooling costs. </s></p><p n="p80.122"><s n="s1.3;p80.122">Unfortunately the gears program cannot model plastic gears, but instead the calculations can be produced easily enough by hand or spreadsheet. </s><s n="s2.3;p80.122">The program can be used for calculating most dimensional values apart from the face width. </s><s n="s3.3;p80.122">A report published by Polypenco Limited, (see Appendix) a plastic gear train manufacturer, indicates design principles for plastic gear design. </s></p><p n="p81.122"><s n="s1.1;p81.122">A standard bending stress calculation for plastic gears is </s></p><p n="p82.122"><s n="s1.1;p82.122"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0023e-form.042"/>. </s></p><p n="p83.122"><s n="s1.3;p83.122">This can be used to design a gear with the necessary stress life. </s><s n="s2.3;p83.122">Designing for the pinion gear, it was found that using the same dimensions as a metal gear used in the program would produce a gear that would not support the stress loads placed upon it. </s><s n="s3.3;p83.122">Instead, increasing the face width to the minimum acceptable level and decreasing the module to 0.8mm, gave a stress level of </s></p><p n="p84.122"><s n="s1.1;p84.122"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0023e-form.043"/>. </s></p><p n="p85.122"><s n="s1.3;p85.122">This value is can be compared to the graph of FIG3 on page 8 of Appendix which shows the stress cycles for nylon gears with these dimensions to be much above the maximum shown stress cycles. </s><s n="s2.3;p85.122">This will likely be reduced further in this epicyclic system as the stress placed on the tooth will be one third of the total stress. </s><s n="s3.3;p85.122">However this also means that the gear goes through three times as many stress cycles per revolution. </s></p><p n="p86.122"><s n="s1.1;p86.122">A reference for the formulae used in the plastic gear calculation is included as an Appendix. </s></p><p n="p87.122"><s n="s1.2;p87.122">The second gear reduction can easily be accommodated with the gearbox program as the use of plastic gears would be unsuitable. </s><s n="s2.2;p87.122">The input torque thus for the second reduction is </s></p><p n="p88.122"><s n="s1.1;p88.122"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0023e-form.044"/>, </s></p><p n="p89.122"><s n="s1.1;p89.122">i.e. five times the torque input of the first reduction, at a speed of </s></p><p n="p90.122"><s n="s1.1;p90.122"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0023e-form.045"/>. </s></p><p n="p91.122"><s n="s1.4;p91.122">Again, the <hi rend="italic">gear</hi> reduction will be 1.53, and besides from this it is only the torque which has changes. </s><s n="s2.4;p91.122">Putting these values into the program again produces the results in Figure 1. </s><s n="s3.4;p91.122">Again, the program computes a face width below the minimum recommendation, as highlighted. </s><s n="s4.4;p91.122">This is double the face width calculated for the first reduction, because torque is doubled and hence stresses on the teeth are doubled also. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0023e-pic.003"><head>Figure 1: First program run for second speed reduction</head></figure><p n="p92.122"><s n="s1.7;p92.122">The face width could be increased and the rest of the parameters left as they are, however this would mean that a material of superior quality was being used in a gear train which had higher material quantity than necessary. </s><s n="s2.7;p92.122">The program recommends either decreasing the material quality, module or centre distance. </s><s n="s3.7;p92.122">Preferred values for module size start at 0.3mm. </s><s n="s4.7;p92.122">However, it is felt that a module size below the 1.0mm already specified would not be suitable for this application, especially in an environment where dust ingress is likely. </s><s n="s5.7;p92.122">Another possibility would be to reduce the centre distance, whereby contact stress would increase. </s><s n="s6.7;p92.122">This would have the effect of decreasing the number of teeth, which are already at 15, the recommended minimum. </s><s n="s7.7;p92.122">The only way to reduce centre distance in reality would be to decrease the module, however as mentioned previously this is not impossible but would be problematic in this application where vibration and dust are present. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0023e-pic.004"><head>Figure 2: Output for second reduction using phosphor bronze material</head></figure><p n="p93.122"><s n="s1.7;p93.122">Changing the material properties however will hopefully require the program to increase the face width to a point where it becomes acceptable. </s><s n="s2.7;p93.122">Figure 2 shows a run of the program with phosphor bronze chosen as the material. </s><s n="s3.7;p93.122">Although the material is 20 times as expensive as other materials, the lower ultimate strength is much lower than other materials such as cast iron or mild steel. </s><s n="s4.7;p93.122">This means that it would likely be easier to machine. </s><s n="s5.7;p93.122">Also, bronze has a lower melting temperature than other metals, meaning it would be easily cast if machining was deemed unsuitable. </s><s n="s6.7;p93.122">A softer material would also likely be quieter running without introducing helical gears. </s><s n="s7.7;p93.122">Choosing this material means that face width is increased to within limits, being 10mm. </s></p><p n="p94.122"><s n="s1.9;p94.122">With these values and values of stresses in mind, the layout of the shafts can be designed. </s><s n="s2.9;p94.122">Overall there are two shafts, all of which carry the 36W power at various speeds. </s><s n="s3.9;p94.122">Only the final shaft carries an axial load, from the drill bit. </s><s n="s4.9;p94.122">It is assumed that the average person operating the drill would weigh about 80kg, and could feasibly apply 50% of this body weight to the drill if they were drilling downwards. </s><s n="s5.9;p94.122">It is unlikely though that anyone could apply his or her full body weight to the drill, as this would unbalance him or her. </s><s n="s6.9;p94.122">Although the shaft and thrust bearings are being designed to take 50% body weight, it is unlikely that this will be thrust onto the drill in its lifetime. </s><s n="s7.9;p94.122">In any case the maximum thrust load will likely be applied in short bursts if the drill was being use properly in order to minimise damage caused by overheating of the bit. </s><s n="s8.9;p94.122">The drill bearings may have to be redesigned if the drill was of the hammer action type, in which case there was be a repeated load/unloading condition on the shaft and gears, though there will likely be a joint before the gearbox to take the axial movement of the shaft. </s><s n="s9.9;p94.122">The static force placed by a person on the drill is </s></p><p n="p95.122"><s n="s1.1;p95.122"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0023e-form.046"/>, </s></p><p n="p96.122"><s n="s1.1;p96.122">remembering that this calculation is approximate so it would best be to round the answer to 400N. </s></p><p n="p97.122"><s n="s1.1;p97.122">There is no tangential force on either shaft as the gearing is epicyclic. </s></p><p n="p98.122"><s n="s1.4;p98.122">As indicated by the screenshot in Figure 3, the shafts program models point loads and distributed loads on a shaft with stepped diameter. </s><s n="s2.4;p98.122">It does not model steady torsion of the beam. </s><s n="s3.4;p98.122">Therefore the program is unsuitable for this application. </s><s n="s4.4;p98.122">Instead, manual methods can be applied. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0023e-pic.005"><head>Figure 3: 'Shaft' program splash screen</head></figure><p n="p99.122"><s n="s1.1;p99.122">For a shaft of diameter <hi rend="italic">d</hi> subjected to a torque <hi rend="italic">T</hi>, the maximum shear stress is </s></p><p n="p100.122"><s n="s1.1;p100.122"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0023e-form.047"/>, </s></p><p n="p101.122"><s n="s1.1;p101.122">where <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0023e-form.048"/>. </s></p><p n="p102.122"><s n="s1.1;p102.122">There are three shafts in total carrying four loads: </s></p><list type="bulleted"><item><hi rend="bold">Shaft from motor</hi><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0023e-form.049"/>.</item><item><hi rend="bold">Shaft from first reduction</hi><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0023e-form.050"/>.</item><item><hi rend="bold">Shaft from second reduction</hi><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0023e-form.051"/>,<formula notation="" id="BAWE_0023e-form.052"/>.</item></list><p n="p103.122"><s n="s1.1;p103.122">The relationship for the torsion of a round shaft is </s></p><p n="p104.122"><s n="s1.1;p104.122"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0023e-form.053"/>. </s></p><p n="p105.122"><s n="s1.1;p105.122">Rearranging, the calculated required diameter of the shaft is </s></p><p n="p106.122"><s n="s1.1;p106.122"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0023e-form.054"/>. </s></p><p n="p107.122"><s n="s1.1;p107.122">Therefore a spreadsheet calculation of torsion and displacement can be produced as </s></p><table id="BAWE_0023e-tab.001"><head>Figure 4: Spreadsheet calculation for shafts</head><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p108.122"><s n="s1.3;p108.122">Using this 'model' the ideal solid shaft diameters can be calculated. </s><s n="s2.3;p108.122">The material chosen is a medium carbon steel 080-M46 to BS970, with a yield strength of 280MPa. </s><s n="s3.3;p108.122">The shaft diameters for each shaft therefore, assuming a shaft length of 10mm between gears (50mm for second reduction), and a bending limit of 1 degree of 0.009 rads, are: </s></p><list type="bulleted"><item><hi rend="bold">Shaft from motor,</hi>6.39mm.</item><item><hi rend="bold">Shaft from first reduction,</hi>9.56mm.</item><item><hi rend="bold">Shaft from second reduction,</hi>21.09mm.</item></list><p n="p109.122"><s n="s1.2;p109.122">Each shaft diameter produces a factor of safety which is quite high compared to the material yield strength. </s><s n="s2.2;p109.122">The second reduction stage shaft is increased further by the need to design in a 50mm shaft length to accommodate the thrust bearing. </s></p><p n="p110.122"><s n="s1.7;p110.122">The thrust bearing itself, as mentioned, has to hold a load of 400N. It is best placed toward the end of the shaft to reduce the chance of strut buckling. </s><s n="s2.7;p110.122">Looking at Figure 5, the desired bearing can be selected by checking the lines to find a suitable bearing type. </s><s n="s3.7;p110.122">Looking at the graph, it appears that rubbing bearings are just outside their operating range. </s><s n="s4.7;p110.122">Therefore the alternatives are oil impregnated porous metal bearings or roller bearings. </s><s n="s5.7;p110.122">Out of the two, roller bearings would probably be best as they are easier to fit and require no maintenance. </s><s n="s6.7;p110.122">Although the porous metal bearings would probably have a longer life and have a higher stiffness, although stiffness is not required in this situation. </s><s n="s7.7;p110.122">By Figure 5 the bearing should have a diameter of 6mm, which is fine in this situation where a shaft of 21.9mm diameter is required anyway to limit torsion. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0023e-pic.006"><head><hi rend="bold">Figure 5: General guide to bearing type</hi><ref target="BAWE_0023e-endnote.001"/><note place="end" id="BAWE_0023e-endnote.001"><p n="pn1.1"> X. Ping Liu. <hi rend="italic">Design of Machines - ES388</hi> [lecture notes]. Page 33.</p></note></head></figure><p n="p111.122"><s n="s1.2;p111.122">All other bearings are to run at high speed but unloaded. </s><s n="s2.2;p111.122">In which case rubbing bearings, being the cheapest option, are no doubt suitable. </s></p><p n="p112.122"><s n="s1.1;p112.122">Therefore the components of the gearbox are: </s></p><list type="bulleted"><item>1 shaft, 6.39mm diameter by 10mm length</item><item>1 shaft, 9.56mm diameter by 10mm length</item><item>1 shaft, 21.09mm diameter by 50mm length</item><item>2 rubbing bearings, shaft diameter</item><item>1 roller thrust bearing, shaft diameter</item><item>1 sun gear, 15mm diameter, 9mm deep, nylon</item><item>3 planet gears, 23mm diameter, 9mm deep, nylon</item><item>1 sun gear, 15mm diameter, 10mm deep, phosphor bronze</item><item>3 planet gears, 23mm diameter, 10mm deep, phosphor bronze</item><item>1 ring gear, 61mm diameter, 9mm deep, nylon</item><item>1 ring gear, 61mm diameter, 10mm deep, phosphor bronze.</item></list></div2><div2><head rend="underlined italic">Gearbox design and assembly</head><p n="p113.122"><s n="s1.1;p113.122">Figure 6 below shows an internal view of the gearbox based on the specification given above. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0023e-pic.007"><head rend="bold">Figure 6: Gearbox internals from design variables</head></figure><p n="p114.122"><s n="s1.1;p114.122">Appendix A shows a cross-sectional view of the gearbox, with labelled items as per Figure 7. </s></p><table id="BAWE_0023e-tab.002"><head rend="bold">Figure 7: Cross-referenced descriptions as per Appendix A</head><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p115.122"><s n="s1.8;p115.122">Figure 8 shows a 3-dimentional view of the gearbox with one half of the case removed. </s><s n="s2.8;p115.122">The gearbox seals are not shown. </s><s n="s3.8;p115.122">Holes are indicated for joining the two case halves. </s><s n="s4.8;p115.122">These have been drilled to 6mm to accommodate M6 bolts. </s><s n="s5.8;p115.122">A gasket material cut to the shape of the mating flange provides sealing for the two gearbox halves. </s><s n="s6.8;p115.122">An interference fit between the case and the ring gear inhibits slipping of the ring gear in the casing. </s><s n="s7.8;p115.122">A bonding glue would be used in this situation where appropriate. </s><s n="s8.8;p115.122">Dimensions for the gearbox casing are included in Appendix B. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0023e-pic.008"><head rend="bold">Figure 8: Half-view of gearbox </head></figure></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined">Comparisons against other gearboxes</head><p n="p116.122"><s n="s1.1;p116.122">In order to begin drawing conclusions from the gearbox design, it shall be compared with other gearboxes from similar commercial units. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0023e-pic.009"><head><hi rend="bold">Figure 9: A cut-away of a commercially available corded hand-held drill</hi><ref target="BAWE_0023e-endnote.002"/><note place="end" id="BAWE_0023e-endnote.002"><p n="pn1.1"> Enigma Industries. <hi rend="italic">Harbor Freight 9.6V drill</hi> [online]. <seg type="URL" n="http://www.enigmaindustries.com/Motors/Harbor_Freight_45935.htm"/> [Access 18/04/2005].</p></note></head></figure><p n="p117.122"><s n="s1.5;p117.122">The drill gearbox has been designed for use in a drill assembly, such as that in Figure 9. </s><s n="s2.5;p117.122">This unit, like that in the design drawn up, has both motor and gearbox mounted in-line in the drill casing. </s><s n="s3.5;p117.122">The gearbox is mounted ahead of the motor and disappears under the torque adjuster. </s><s n="s4.5;p117.122">The similarity of this drill to the one designed shows is a good indication that it is a good design. </s><s n="s5.5;p117.122">However, is more appropriate to compare the internals of the gearboxes: this will aid an understanding that the correct mechanism and mechanical arrangement was chosen. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0023e-pic.010"><head><hi rend="bold">Figure 10: Gearbox A cross-section</hi><ref target="BAWE_0023e-endnote.003"/><note place="end" id="BAWE_0023e-endnote.003"><p n="pn1.1"> European Patent Office. <hi rend="italic">epa@cenet home page</hi> [online]. <seg type="URL" n="http://ep.espacenet.com"/> [Accessed 18/04/2005].</p></note></head></figure><figure id="BAWE_0023e-pic.011"><head><hi rend="bold">Figure 11: Gearbox A exterior view</hi> iii</head></figure><p n="p118.122"><s n="s1.10;p118.122">Gearbox A is a cordless handheld drill with a variable speed controller. </s><s n="s2.10;p118.122">Figure 10 and Figure 11 show cross-sectional and exterior views of the gearbox respectively. </s><s n="s3.10;p118.122">Although no descriptive text is available for the gearbox, it appears that, from Figure 10, the gearbox is driven from a motor in a handle via a straight-cut gear on the end of input shaft (17) onto a bevel gear (19). </s><s n="s4.10;p118.122">This provides the first speed reduction of approximately 16:1. </s><s n="s5.10;p118.122">There are three choices of speed reduction, therefore there should be three methods of speed selection. </s><s n="s6.10;p118.122">It appears that the input shaft (16) on which the bevel gear (19) is fixed has a spur gear attached or machined at its left hand end which engages a layshaft (29). </s><s n="s7.10;p118.122">It appears that the speed is selected by a number of dog clutches (14), probably by the use of selector forks. </s><s n="s8.10;p118.122">Thus power is then transmitted either through spur gear (30) or (30`). </s><s n="s9.10;p118.122">The selectors (14) is most likely located on a splined section of the output shaft and can hence slide along there. </s><s n="s10.10;p118.122">The third speed reduction may well be electronic. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0023e-pic.012"><head><hi rend="bold">Figure 12: Gearbox B exploded internal view</hi> iii</head></figure><figure id="BAWE_0023e-pic.013"><head><hi rend="bold">Figure 13: Gearbox B internal view</hi> iii</head></figure><p n="p119.122"><s n="s1.3;p119.122">Figure 12 and Figure 13 show an exploded and non-exploded internal view respectively, of a second gearbox drawing. </s><s n="s2.3;p119.122">The gearbox (12) is a 'floating' design on a spring 26 to restrain its movement during hammer operating. </s><s n="s3.3;p119.122">The gearbox houses a planetary system consisting of a ring gear (34), planet gear carrier (29), sun gear (11) and planet gears (not shown). </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0023e-pic.014"><head><hi rend="bold">Figure 14: Gearbox C cross sectional view of drill</hi> iii</head></figure><figure id="BAWE_0023e-pic.015"><head><hi rend="bold">Figure 15: Gearbox C cross-sectional gearbox view</hi> iii</head></figure><p n="p120.122"><s n="s1.3;p120.122">Figure 14 and Figure 15 show a cross-sectional view of the complete drill assembly and gearbox assembly respectively. </s><s n="s2.3;p120.122">Again, the gearbox is driven from a motor in the handle providing a speed reduction of around 16:1. </s><s n="s3.3;p120.122">From Figure 15, it appears that the output is driven by two epicyclic gear reductions: through planet gears (21) and (33); planet gear carriers (25) and (36). </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined">Conclusions</head><p n="p121.122"><s n="s1.6;p121.122">Using the analysis programs and manual analysis techniques, a gearbox design consisting of two epicyclic gear arrangements can be produced, with the specifications and details described in previous sections. </s><s n="s2.6;p121.122">It is expected that the gearbox should be sufficient and cost effective enough to provide a ground point for the development of a gearbox for the situation required. </s><s n="s3.6;p121.122">The gearbox is made from a combination of nylon and phosphor bronze gears for the 1 <hi rend="sup">st</hi> and 2 <hi rend="sup">nd</hi> reduction stages respectively. </s><s n="s4.6;p121.122">The choice of nylon gears for the 1 <hi rend="sup">st</hi> reduction will hopefully allow a cost-effective solution to the gearbox problem. </s><s n="s5.6;p121.122">A suitable factor of safety has been included for both reduction stages. </s><s n="s6.6;p121.122">The gearbox casing allows the accommodation of the gears and suitable seals and bearings. </s></p><p n="p122.122"><s n="s1.3;p122.122">In comparing the design in this report to other drill gearbox designs, it is concluded that the layout and size of the gearbox is comparable to designs of other handheld drill gearboxes. </s><s n="s2.3;p122.122">However, it may prove suitable, upon selection of a driving motor, to place said motor in the handle of the drill, and hence create a reduction, by bevel or worm gear, from the motor to the gearbox. </s><s n="s3.3;p122.122">The choice of epicyclic gears, as demonstrated, facilitates the inclusion of speed reduction techniques by rotating the ring gear by a variable amount to vary the ratio. </s></p></div1></body><back><div1 type="bibliography"><head rend="underlined">References</head><p/></div1><div1 type="missing or external appendix"><p/></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
