<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_0025a" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Instrumentation</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">The document has a title page which contains:
document title
title part
abstract</note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">deleted: page numbers
</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">2</p><p n="date">2005-01</p><p n="module title">Design of Measurement Systems</p><p n="module code">ES21Q</p><p n="genre family">Methodology recount</p><p n="discipline">Engineering</p><p n="disciplinary group">PS</p><p n="grade">D</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">2592</p><p n="number of s-units">141</p><p n="number of p">85</p><p n="number of tables">1</p><p n="number of figures">5</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">49</p><p n="number of lists">1</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">24</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">18.4</p><p n="average s-units per p">1.7</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">f</p><p n="year of birth">1984</p><p n="first language">Chinese Mandarin</p><p n="education">UK4</p><p n="course">Electronic and Communication Engineering</p><p n="student ID">0025</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><titlePart>University of <name type="university"/> School of Engineering</titlePart><titlePart rend="underlined bold">ES21Q - Design of Measurement System</titlePart><docTitle><titlePart rend="underlined bold">Assignment 1: Instrumentation</titlePart></docTitle><titlePart>Student ID: <name type="student ID"/> Date: 31/01/2005</titlePart></titlePage><div1 type="abstract"><head rend="bold">Summary</head><p>The purpose of this experiment is to understand the method of force measurement. There are several ways of sensing force, as for this experiment, strain gauges are used to do the measurement. As applying an external force to a balanced system, the strain of the strain gauges is changed results in the resistance changes, then output voltage changes due to the change of the resistance. As a result, the relationship between the applied force and the system output can be found out.</p><p>The force sensor which is going to be measured and tested consists of three parts. They are a cantilever rig, a Wheatstone bridge circuit and an amplifier. The cantilever rig and the Wheatstone bridge form an analogue experimental transducer. Two strain gauges which are bonded onto the cantilever beam are part of the bridge circuit. After adding forces to the transducer, the output voltage signal is very small therefore the amplifier is used to increase the output.</p><p>The experiment is mainly divided into five steps. First of all, the force range can be applied has to be determined to make sure the system will not be damaged. Secondly, a Wheatstone deflection bridge circuit is designed and built in order to convert the change in resistance of the two strain gauges to an output voltage. Thirdly, an amplifier is designed and built in order to amplify the output to an appropriate level. Fourthly, the complete force sensor system can be tested so that the relationship between the output and loading force can be found out and plotted on a graph, in this process, all signals are in analogue format, therefore it can be considered as an analogue test. Lastly, analogue signals can be converted into digital format by computer software in order to do some further processes.</p><p>The relationship between the system output and applied force is expected to be a straight line. However, in practice, the result is not linear as there are some factors affecting the system such as temperature effect and measurement misplays. On the digital analysis part, the output waveform against time can be seen from the computer. For further testing, the system outputs with and without applied force are compared. Also, a feedback capacitor produces a significant effect to the output.</p></div1><div1 type="toc" n="1"><head rend="bold">Table of Contents</head><p/></div1></front><body><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Introduction</head><p n="p1.85"><s n="s1.2;p1.85">The main objective of this experiment is to use the strain gauge to measure the strain produced due to applied force. </s><s n="s2.2;p1.85">The experiment is designed only for low-level force measurement as can be seen from the experiment apparatus. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Theory</head><div2><head rend="underlined">Strain and Strain gauge:</head><p n="p2.85"><s n="s1.3;p2.85">"A strain is the amount of deformation of a body due to an applied force." </s><s n="s2.3;p2.85">(From web National Instrument-Measuring strain with strain gauges) It can be measured by a stain gauge since the gauge resistance changes proportional to the strain. </s><s n="s3.3;p2.85">The strain can be tensile or compressive; the two stain gauges used in this experiment are boned on the top and bottom surfaces of the cantilever beam which produce tensile and compressive stains. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0025a-pic.001"><head>(Figure 1)</head></figure></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">Wheatstone bridge circuit:</head><p n="p3.85"><s n="s1.5;p3.85">In this experiment, an important theory that has to be understood is the balance condition of the Wheatstone bridge circuit. </s><s n="s2.5;p3.85">The circuit is used to measure a small change in resistance, and then convert the resistance signal to an output voltage. </s><s n="s3.5;p3.85">It consists of four resistors which connect together to form a quadrilateral. </s><s n="s4.5;p3.85">From Figure 1 on the right, a DC source voltage Vs connected across one of the diagonals AC, and the output voltage Vo connected across the other diagonal BD. The top and bottom part of the bridge can be treated as individual voltage dividers. </s><s n="s5.5;p3.85">Therefore Vo is actually determined by measuring the difference between the outputs of two voltage dividers. </s></p><p n="p4.85"><s n="s1.1;p4.85">Since<formula notation="" id="BAWE_0025a-form.001"/> and<formula notation="" id="BAWE_0025a-form.002"/> </s></p><p n="p5.85"><s n="s1.1;p5.85">then the output voltage Vo of the circuit is<formula notation="" id="BAWE_0025a-form.003"/> </s></p><p n="p6.85"><s n="s1.1;p6.85">or<formula notation="" id="BAWE_0025a-form.004"/>. </s></p><p n="p7.85"><s n="s1.1;p7.85">When bridge circuit is in balance, both potential dividers are equal, thus the potential difference between them which is the output voltage Vo is zero. </s></p><p n="p8.85"><s n="s1.1;p8.85">Then R1R3-R2R4 on the numerator of the equation equals zero :- R1R3=R2R4 </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">Non-inverting amplifier:</head><p n="p9.85"><s n="s1.1;p9.85">This part of knowledge has already been taught in Year one, the voltage gain of a non-inverting amplifier is<formula notation="" id="BAWE_0025a-form.005"/>. </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Apparatus and Methods</head><div2><head rend="underlined bold">Apparatus:</head><figure id="BAWE_0025a-pic.002"><head>(Figure 2)</head></figure><p rend="bulleted" n="p10.85"><s n="s1.3;p10.85"><hi rend="underlined">A cantilever rig</hi> =(Figure 2): it consists of a cantilever beam with two strain gauges bonded to the top and bottom surfaces of the beam. </s><s n="s2.3;p10.85">There is a nylon screw attached at the free end of the beam for adding forces. </s><s n="s3.3;p10.85">On the other side of the transducer, there is a Wheatstone bridge circuit contains a 9V DC source supply, a balance potentiometer and the two strain gauges on the beam. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p11.85"><s n="s1.4;p11.85"><hi rend="underlined">An electrocircuit board</hi>: it contains an 8 pin layout op-amp 741 in the middle of the board. </s><s n="s2.4;p11.85">It is used to design and build an amplifier using the 741 to amplify output voltage to an appropriate level. </s><s n="s3.4;p11.85">Two resistor values are chosen to form a non-inverting amplifier. </s><s n="s4.4;p11.85">Additionally, the use of a capacitor crossing the feedback resistor of the amplifier is to form a simple low-pass filter to cut off the high frequency noise caused by high gain in the circuit. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p12.85"><s n="s1.1;p12.85">Other equipments: DC power supply, digital voltmeter and oscilloscope. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined bold">Methods:</head><p rend="ordered" n="p13.85"><s n="s1.1;p13.85">Determine the force range which can be applied to the mechanical system: </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p14.85"><s n="s1.1;p14.85">The way to calculate the maximum loading force is by measuring the geometrical dimensions of the cantilever and location of the strain gauges, then substituted these values into the equation of the strain produced in terms of F. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0025a-pic.003"><head>(Figure 3)</head></figure><p n="p15.85"><s n="s1.1;p15.85">Since<formula notation="" id="BAWE_0025a-form.006"/> </s></p><p n="p16.85"><s n="s1.1;p16.85">As shown left (Figure 3), x, l, w and t are the required measurements, where l is the length of the beam, x is the length from the starting side to the middle of the strain gauges on the beam, w is the width and t is the thickness of the beam. </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p17.85"><s n="s1.1;p17.85">Design and build a Wheatstone bridge circuit: </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p18.85"><s n="s1.2;p18.85">The circuit diagram and use have already been explained in the theory part of the report. </s><s n="s2.2;p18.85">In this procedure, the circuit needs to be adjusted at zero by the potentiometer. </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p19.85"><s n="s1.1;p19.85">Design and build an amplifier: </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p20.85"><s n="s1.4;p20.85">The gain of the amplifier is preferred to be a value of 1000 as the system output is small, usually in millivolts; the amplifier can amplify the output voltage to about 1V. After the circuit is complete, the amplifier's working status has to be tested before connect it to the bridge circuit. </s><s n="s2.4;p20.85">This procedure is mainly to check to noise status caused by the high gain of the amplifier. </s><s n="s3.4;p20.85">Therefore connect the amplifier output to the oscilloscope to see the fluctuation. </s><s n="s4.4;p20.85">After this, a capacitor is considered to connect across the feedback resistor of the amplifier to reduce the noise level. </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p21.85"><s n="s1.1;p21.85">Test the complete force sensor which consists of the cantilever, bridge circuit and amplifier: </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p22.85"><s n="s1.2;p22.85">In this step, the relationship between the system output and the applied force can be found out by recording the output voltage values when adding washers on the nylon strew. </s><s n="s2.2;p22.85">Then plot a graph according to the records. </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p23.85"><s n="s1.1;p23.85">After testing the force sensor by an analogue device, those analogue signals can be converted into digital format for further test. </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p24.85"><s n="s1.2;p24.85">A computer software with cards either 6023E or 6024E installed is used to do the digital test of the system. </s><s n="s2.2;p24.85">In this procedure, the noise levels are compared for four situations, which are with feedback capacitor with tap, with feedback capacitor without tap, without feedback capacitor without tap and without feedback capacitor with tap. </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Observations and Results</head><p rend="ordered" n="p25.85"><s n="s1.1;p25.85">To derive the stain produced at the strain gauges in terms of F: </s></p><p n="p26.85"><s n="s1.1;p26.85">The stain and stress relationship is<formula notation="" id="BAWE_0025a-form.007"/>, </s></p><p n="p27.85"><s n="s1.1;p27.85">and from the stress and force relationship:<formula notation="" id="BAWE_0025a-form.008"/> </s></p><p n="p28.85"><s n="s1.1;p28.85">where<formula notation="" id="BAWE_0025a-form.009"/> is from databook. </s></p><p n="p29.85"><s n="s1.1;p29.85">then get<formula notation="" id="BAWE_0025a-form.010"/>. </s></p><p n="p30.85"><s n="s1.1;p30.85">The sensitivity of the mechanical system can be expressed by the equation below: </s></p><p n="p31.85"><s n="s1.3;p31.85"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0025a-form.011"/>, as can be seen, the sensitivity is determined by the geometrical dimensions of the system, which are the values of l, x, w and t. </s><s n="s2.3;p31.85">In this experiment, the measurement is imprecise since the lengths are measured by a ruler. </s><s n="s3.3;p31.85">As a result, to consider the sensitivity of the system, those factors which affect the geometrical dimensions measurement of the system should be taken into account, such as temperature, measurement misplay, etc. </s></p><p n="p32.85"><s n="s1.1;p32.85">Additionally, it is found out that only small dimensions can be used and measured in this mechanical system, since the lengths are measured by a ruler, the larger the dimension is, the more imprecise the measurement is. </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p33.85"><s n="s1.1;p33.85">Rearrange the equation above then get<formula notation="" id="BAWE_0025a-form.012"/> </s></p><list type="simple"><item>l=14.8cm=0.148m, </item><item>x=4.8cm=0.048m, </item><item>w=1.3cm=0.013m, </item><item>t=0.5mm=0.0005m,</item><item><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0025a-form.013"/>=540MPa=540*1000000Pa</item></list><p n="p34.85"><s n="s1.1;p34.85">then<formula notation="" id="BAWE_0025a-form.014"/>=<formula notation="" id="BAWE_0025a-form.015"/>=<formula notation="" id="BAWE_0025a-form.016"/>=<formula notation="" id="BAWE_0025a-form.017"/> </s></p><p n="p35.85"><s n="s1.1;p35.85">this means the maximum force can be applied to the system is 2.93N. If a greater force is applied then the cantilever will be damaged. </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p36.85"><s n="s1.2;p36.85">The theoretical balance condition of the Wheatstone bridge circuit has already been explained in the theory part, that is when Vo=0, R1R3=R2R4. </s><s n="s2.2;p36.85">The two strain gauges both have values of<formula notation="" id="BAWE_0025a-form.018"/>, and the rest two resistors in the bridge circuit also have magnitudes of <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0025a-form.019"/> </s></p><p n="p37.85"><s n="s1.1;p37.85">then, R1=R2=R3=R4=R=<formula notation="" id="BAWE_0025a-form.020"/> </s></p><p n="p38.85"><s n="s1.3;p38.85">The factor may affect this condition is the temperature as it may affect the measurement. </s><s n="s2.3;p38.85">As we know that the resistance is determined by the resistivity, the length and the cross-section area of the material,<formula notation="" id="BAWE_0025a-form.021"/>, the three factors are all affected by temperature, therefore the value of resistance will changed with temperature. </s><s n="s3.3;p38.85">So the resistance of strain gauge is not dependent on the strain produced but also the temperature. </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p39.85"><s n="s1.5;p39.85">As above, under the balance condition, R1R3=R2R4. </s><s n="s2.5;p39.85">However, when force is applied to the system, the two active strain gauges will be changed. </s><s n="s3.5;p39.85">This is because the strain is determined by the geometric dimensions and force F,<formula notation="" id="BAWE_0025a-form.022"/>. </s><s n="s4.5;p39.85">At the beginning, no applied force, no strain. </s><s n="s5.5;p39.85">But after applying force to the system, the strain changes, then resistance of the strain gauge changes, then output voltage changes. </s></p><p n="p40.85"><s n="s1.2;p40.85">As one of the strain gauge is on the top surface of the beam and the other one is on the bottom surface, the bending of the beam causes a tensile strain on the first gauge but a compressive strain on the second gauge. </s><s n="s2.2;p40.85">(From theory) </s></p><p n="p41.85"><s n="s1.1;p41.85"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0025a-form.023"/> </s></p><p n="p42.85"><s n="s1.1;p42.85"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0025a-form.024"/> </s></p><p n="p43.85"><s n="s1.1;p43.85">then bridge output can be expressed by the following: </s></p><p n="p44.85"><s n="s1.1;p44.85"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0025a-form.025"/> </s></p><p n="p45.85"><s n="s1.1;p45.85">since R1=R2=R3=R4=R, R can be substituted into the above equation, then get </s></p><p n="p46.85"><s n="s1.1;p46.85"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0025a-form.026"/> </s></p><p n="p47.85"><s n="s1.1;p47.85">therefore the bridge output and the relative resistance change of the strain gauge gives a linear relationship in the form y=kx. </s></p><p n="p48.85"><s n="s1.1;p48.85">Here, Vs=9V, so<formula notation="" id="BAWE_0025a-form.027"/>. </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p49.85"><s n="s1.2;p49.85">A non-inverting amplifier is preferred to use in this experiment rather than an inverting amplifier. </s><s n="s2.2;p49.85">The reason is that in comparison, the non-inverting amplifier has higher impedance, smaller input current and higher voltage gain than the inverting amplifier. </s></p><p n="p50.85"><s n="s1.1;p50.85">The gain of the non-inverting amplifier is determined as 1000 rather than other values since lower gain will not amplify the output enough, and higher gain will cause higher noise level. </s></p><p n="p51.85"><s n="s1.1;p51.85">Therefore for the non-inverting amplifier,<formula notation="" id="BAWE_0025a-form.028"/>, </s></p><p n="p52.85"><s n="s1.1;p52.85">so R1+R2 =1000R2 :- R1=999R2 :- R1=1000R2 </s></p><p n="p53.85"><s n="s1.1;p53.85">so if R1=<formula notation="" id="BAWE_0025a-form.029"/>, then R2=<formula notation="" id="BAWE_0025a-form.030"/> </s></p><p n="p54.85"><s n="s1.4;p54.85">Before connect to the bridge circuit, the amplifier needs to be tested to see the noise level. </s><s n="s2.4;p54.85">Due to the high gain and the electromagnetic interference, a noise around 50HZ is formed. </s><s n="s3.4;p54.85">In order to reduce the noise, a simple low-pass filter is considered to use by connecting a capacitor across the feedback resistor. </s><s n="s4.4;p54.85">The time constant t=RC=0.1sec is given, feedback R1=<formula notation="" id="BAWE_0025a-form.031"/>, so that C=0.1/1000=100uF. </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p55.85"><s n="s1.2;p55.85">The table below shows the records of the loading force Fl with system output voltage Vo. </s><s n="s2.2;p55.85">The relationship between the two physical quantities can be found out by plotting these data on the graph. </s></p><table id="BAWE_0025a-tab.001"><head>(Table 1)</head><row><cell/></row></table><figure id="BAWE_0025a-fig.001"><head>(Figure 4)</head></figure><p n="p56.85"><s n="s1.3;p56.85">As shown from Figure 4, there are two lines shown on the graph. </s><s n="s2.3;p56.85">The blue line represents system theoretical output which is a straight line. </s><s n="s3.3;p56.85">The red line represents system output in practice which is not linear. </s></p><p n="p57.85"><s n="s1.1;p57.85">The sensitivity of the force sensor is determined by the slope of the graph, which is the system output divided by the loading force,<formula notation="" id="BAWE_0025a-form.032"/>,the detailed explanation of this force sensor system sensitivity is shown in the analysis part of the report. </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p58.85"><s n="s1.1;p58.85">After converting analogue signals into digital signals, data can be collected from the computer. </s></p><p n="p59.85"><s n="s1.1;p59.85">First of all, compare the system output without and with feedback capacitor when there is no applied force to the system, which is without taping the nylon screw. </s></p><p n="p60.85"><s n="s1.1;p60.85">The graph below shows the output waveform against time without feedback capacitor without taping. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0025a-fig.002"><head>(Figure 5)</head></figure><p n="p61.85"><s n="s1.1;p61.85">The graph below shows the output waveform against time with feedback capacitor without taping. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0025a-fig.003"><head>(Figure 6)</head></figure><p n="p62.85"><s n="s1.2;p62.85">From Figure 5 and 6, the amplitude of both the waveforms is small since there is no applied force. </s><s n="s2.2;p62.85">However, Figure 5 shows much higher frequency noise than Figure 6, this is because the noise level is reduced by the feedback capacitor in the amplifier circuit. </s></p><p n="p63.85"><s n="s1.1;p63.85">Secondly, compare the system output without and with feedback capacitor when there is a force added to the system. </s></p><p n="p64.85"><s n="s1.1;p64.85">The graph below shows the system output without feedback capacitor with taping. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0025a-fig.004"><head>(Figure 7)</head></figure><p n="p65.85"><s n="s1.1;p65.85">The graph below shows the system output with feedback capacitor with tapping. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0025a-fig.005"><head>(Figure 8)</head></figure><p n="p66.85"><s n="s1.2;p66.85">From Figure 7 and 8, the amplitude of both the waveforms is increased compared with Figure 5 and 6 since there is the applied force to the system. </s><s n="s2.2;p66.85">On the other hand, only a small force applied to the system since the beam is taped very slightly, so the time need for stabilizing the output after it is disturbed can be found out from the graph. </s></p><p n="p67.85"><s n="s1.1;p67.85">Record from the laboratory result, the time needs to stabilize the system output without feedback capacitor is about 1 second, but only about 0.5 second when there is the capacitor. </s></p><p n="p68.85"><s n="s1.1;p68.85">Additionally, without the capacitor, the system gives the resonant frequency since there is no damping effect, so the resonant frequency can be worked out by: </s></p><p n="p69.85"><s n="s1.1;p69.85">The system needs 1 second to stabilize, and there are 10 oscillation periods, so 1 period needs 0.1 second, the resonant frequency is 1/0.1=10HZ. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Analysis of Results</head><p n="p70.85"><s n="s1.1;p70.85">Under the balance condition,:-, as Vs is constant (9V), the equation gives a linear relationship between the output voltage<formula notation="" id="BAWE_0025a-form.033"/> and the variation of resistance of strain gauges<formula notation="" id="BAWE_0025a-form.034"/>. </s></p><p n="p71.85"><s n="s1.3;p71.85">Additionally,<formula notation="" id="BAWE_0025a-form.035"/> is defined as Gauge factor G or sensitivity of the strain gauge. </s><s n="s2.3;p71.85">So<formula notation="" id="BAWE_0025a-form.036"/>. </s><s n="s3.3;p71.85">Then substitute<formula notation="" id="BAWE_0025a-form.037"/> into<formula notation="" id="BAWE_0025a-form.038"/> can get:<formula notation="" id="BAWE_0025a-form.039"/> also,<formula notation="" id="BAWE_0025a-form.040"/> is known, after substituting,<formula notation="" id="BAWE_0025a-form.041"/>:-<formula notation="" id="BAWE_0025a-form.042"/> </s></p><p n="p72.85"><s n="s1.2;p72.85">therefore, the output voltage and the applied force is in a linear relationship since<formula notation="" id="BAWE_0025a-form.043"/> is a constant value. </s><s n="s2.2;p72.85">This is the theoretical result, </s></p><p n="p73.85"><s n="s1.1;p73.85">so<formula notation="" id="BAWE_0025a-form.044"/> =<formula notation="" id="BAWE_0025a-form.045"/>. </s></p><p n="p74.85"><s n="s1.4;p74.85">The sensitivity of the system is dependent on the following factors: the geometrical dimensions, Young's modulus, the DC power supply and the gauge factor. </s><s n="s2.4;p74.85">For this experiment, the gauge factor is 2.1, so it can be determined as a metallic strain gauge. </s><s n="s3.4;p74.85">However, there are other types of strain gauges with different gauge factors, such as semiconductor strain gauge. </s><s n="s4.4;p74.85">The Young's modulus E depends on the equation<formula notation="" id="BAWE_0025a-form.046"/>, therefore the system is also dependent on strain and stress. </s></p><p n="p75.85"><s n="s1.1;p75.85">On the other hand, from Figure 4, since the graph is almost a straight line, the gradient of it can be calculated by the equation:<formula notation="" id="BAWE_0025a-form.047"/>, substitute two values from table 1 into the equation then get:<formula notation="" id="BAWE_0025a-form.048"/>=12.2 </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Discussion</head><p n="p76.85"><s n="s1.2;p76.85">Usually, a typical change in resistance of the strain gauge might be 1% of the nominal resistance value; as a result, how to measure such a small change in resistance accurately is a main problem for the experiment. </s><s n="s2.2;p76.85">In order to solve this problem, the following statements have to be considered and paid attention to: </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p77.85"><s n="s1.1;p77.85">When using the strain gauges, it is very important to make sure that they are properly mounted onto the cantilever beam surfaces so that the strain can be accurately and completely transferred from the surfaces. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p78.85"><s n="s1.1;p78.85">The resistive elements in the strain gauge are not only sensitive to the strain produced but also they are responding to other physical quantities such as temperature and light, for the experiment, the thermal induced change is <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0025a-form.049"/> which is acceptable. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p79.85"><s n="s1.3;p79.85">In order to reduce the thermal sensitivity of the system, a good method is to use four strain gauges on the cantilever beam instead of two. </s><s n="s2.3;p79.85">So the sensitivity of the circuit is doubled and also the arrangement can further compensate any variation caused by temperature. </s><s n="s3.3;p79.85">This is called the full-bridge configuration. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p80.85"><s n="s1.2;p80.85">Lead wire resistances will also affect the system and reduce the accuracy of the result. </s><s n="s2.2;p80.85">Even when the system is balanced, the wire resistances changes with temperature will also result in errors. </s></p><p n="p81.85"><s n="s1.2;p81.85">A more precise apparatus can be chosen to measure the lengths of the cantilever rig since the sensitivity of the mechanical system is dependent on the geometrical dimensions of the rig. </s><s n="s2.2;p81.85">Especially t in the denominator should be recorded carefully otherwise it will give a big difference in result since it is inverse squared. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Conclusion</head><p n="p82.85"><s n="s1.2;p82.85">The system is configured to measure a low-level force since the geometrical dimensions are small. </s><s n="s2.2;p82.85">The dimensions of the cantilever rig gives an applied force range is small, only a few Newton. </s></p><p n="p83.85"><s n="s1.4;p83.85">For the strain gauge, the change of resistance is only expected to vary with the strain produced as adding forces to the system. </s><s n="s2.4;p83.85">However, the resistance is not only responding to the strain but also temperature changes. </s><s n="s3.4;p83.85">A half-bridge circuit configuration used in this experiment which is to use two active strain gauges can reduce the temperature effect. </s><s n="s4.4;p83.85">And an even better solution is use the full-bridge circuit configuration hence the temperature effect can be minimized. </s></p><p n="p84.85"><s n="s1.2;p84.85">For the amplifier used in the experiment, the gain is chosen as 1000 since higher gain will produced a considerable noise level, but the lower gain will probably not amplify the output to an expect level to observe. </s><s n="s2.2;p84.85">A low-pass filter is widely used to cut off the high noise frequency of the system. </s></p><p n="p85.85"><s n="s1.4;p85.85">The output voltage and applied force give an approximately linear relationship in this experiment. </s><s n="s2.4;p85.85">However, the result is expected to be a straight line. </s><s n="s3.4;p85.85">The errors produced in the result due to many factors such as temperature effect and measurement misplay. </s><s n="s4.4;p85.85">Those errors can be reduced manually however they can not be eliminated. </s></p></div1></body><back><div1 type="bibliography"><head rend="bold">Bibliographies</head><p>From Website - National Instrument - "Measuring Strain with Strain Gauges"</p><p>From Website - National Instrument - "How is Temperature Affecting Your Strain Measurement Accuracy"</p><p><seg type="URL" n="http://zone.ni.com/devzone/conceptd.nsf/webmain"/></p></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
