<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_0030a" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Was India enriched or impoverished by British colonial rule?</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">deleted: WORD COUNT: 2,199
</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">1</p><p n="date">2003-12</p><p n="module title">Making of the Modern World</p><p n="module code">HI153</p><p n="genre family">Essay</p><p n="discipline">History</p><p n="disciplinary group">AH</p><p n="grade">M</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">2232</p><p n="number of s-units">105</p><p n="number of p">16</p><p n="number of tables">0</p><p n="number of figures">0</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">0</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">0</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">21.3</p><p n="average s-units per p">6.6</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">m</p><p n="year of birth">1983</p><p n="first language">English</p><p n="education">UKA</p><p n="course">History</p><p n="student ID">0030</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><docTitle><titlePart rend="bold">Was India enriched or impoverished by British colonial rule? </titlePart></docTitle><titlePart><name type="student name"/></titlePart></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="section"><p n="p1.16"><s n="s1.6;p1.16">The Far East has always provided an attraction for European powers. </s><s n="s2.6;p1.16">It was often perceived as an exotic area, rich in luxury goods, none less so than India. </s><s n="s3.6;p1.16">The pre-Colonial Indian economy relied, almost entirely on tribal, subsistence agriculture, a typical attribute of any developing country. </s><s n="s4.6;p1.16">Indeed, Neil Charlesworth saw India as 'an important and populous less developed country...[with] low levels of output but possessing a tradition of high quality handicraft production and merchant enterprise." </s><ref target="BAWE_0030a-ftnote.001"/><s n="s5.6;p1.16">The British sought to modernize India, politically, socially and economically: they wanted to create a colony worthy of being part of their expansive empire. </s><s n="s6.6;p1.16">This process effectively saw Britain incorporate India, and take full responsibility for its governing. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0030a-ftnote.001"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Neil Charlesworth, <hi rend="italic">British Rule and the Indian Economy 1800-1914</hi> (London, 1990), p. 11. </s></p></note><p n="p2.16"><s n="s1.1;p2.16">Gramscian theory of colonial rule often falls into two categories: colonies are ruled either by coercion, in which case they are dominated by force, or by consent, which is representative of a hegemonic colonial power.<ref target="BAWE_0030a-ftnote.002"/> The British were keen to have a legitimate presence in India as 'after 1858...they knew they were a long-term government...with no interest in ruining agriculture for the sake of a temporary quick money return.'<ref target="BAWE_0030a-ftnote.003"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0030a-ftnote.002"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Burton Stein, <hi rend="italic">The Making of Agrarian Policy in British India 1770 - 1900</hi> (Oxford, 1992), p. 147. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0030a-ftnote.003"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">M. E. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">Chamberlain, <hi rend="italic">Britain and India: The Interaction of Two Peoples</hi> (Newton Abbot, 1974), p. 125. </s></p></note><p n="p3.16"><s n="s1.5;p3.16">To assess whether British presence was positive or negative, it is necessary to examine what the British brought to the colony and whether or not it ultimately benefited the Indians. </s><s n="s2.5;p3.16">Typically there are two schools of thought on British rule in India. </s><s n="s3.5;p3.16">Karl Marx believed that 'England has broken down the entire framework of Indian society'<ref target="BAWE_0030a-ftnote.004"/> while Sir Percival Griffiths saw British rule as a 'powerful, positive force for modernisation." </s><ref target="BAWE_0030a-ftnote.005"/><s n="s4.5;p3.16">Key to modernisation was a movement away from an agriculturally dependent economy and the creation of state infrastructure such as railways, canals and irrigation. </s><s n="s5.5;p3.16">These advancements would also, it was hoped, help deal with famine which had increasingly become a problem in India. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0030a-ftnote.004"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Avineri Shlomo, <hi rend="italic">Karl Marx on Colonisation and Modernisation</hi> (New York, 1969), p. 90. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0030a-ftnote.005"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Sir Percival Griffiths, <hi rend="italic">The British Impact on India</hi> (London, 1952). </s></p></note><p n="p4.16"><s n="s1.9;p4.16">The creation of infrastructure was highly important for the British in order to develop India's economy. </s><s n="s2.9;p4.16">Marx believed that 'the railway system will...become, in India, truly the forerunner of modern industry." </s><ref target="BAWE_0030a-ftnote.006"/><s n="s3.9;p4.16">This was certainly represented in its uptake, with nearly 7,000 miles of track being laid between 1858 and 1878.<ref target="BAWE_0030a-ftnote.007"/> The railways network created was strategic, providing routes to and from ports, as well as following 'ancient and obvious lines of communication'<ref target="BAWE_0030a-ftnote.008"/>. </s><s n="s4.9;p4.16">While the creation of these routes was important for industry, a secondary objective was to counter famine problems by allowing the movement of any surplus food to impoverished areas. </s><s n="s5.9;p4.16">Irrigation too was constructed with the idea of providing water outside of the rainy season. </s><s n="s6.9;p4.16">As with railways, the uptake of irrigation was quite spectacular: 'by World War two, over 32 million acres...was irrigated from state irrigation schemes, the largest in any country in the world." </s><ref target="BAWE_0030a-ftnote.009"/><s n="s7.9;p4.16">Despite this philanthropic nature of these schemes, the British were harshly criticized over the provision of revenue for development. </s><s n="s8.9;p4.16">The British government was of the opinion that if the schemes were to benefit Indians, then Indians should pay for them. </s><s n="s9.9;p4.16">Even during times of famine, when the Indians could not afford to feed themselves, revenue still had to be met. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0030a-ftnote.006"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Avineri Shlomo, <hi rend="italic">Karl Marx on Colonisation and Modernisation</hi> (New York, 1969), p. 136. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0030a-ftnote.007"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">H. M. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">Hyndman, <hi rend="italic">The Bankruptcy of India</hi> (London, 1886), p. 36. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0030a-ftnote.008"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Chamberlain, <hi rend="italic">Britain and India: The Interaction of Two Peoples</hi>, p. 121. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0030a-ftnote.009"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid, p. 124. </s></p></note><p n="p5.16"><s n="s1.10;p5.16">The agriculture industry was also modernised by the British, with positive and negative outcomes. </s><s n="s2.10;p5.16">The introduction of large scale cash crops such as cotton, jute, indigo and tea allowed India greater scope for export and therefore competition in the world's markets. </s><s n="s3.10;p5.16">Such a transformation obviously could not happen overnight, but the foundations were certainly laid. </s><s n="s4.10;p5.16">However, with agricultural reform came the addition of land tax. </s><s n="s5.10;p5.16">All land needed to be officially owned by a person and this tax could only be paid in currency.<ref target="BAWE_0030a-ftnote.010"/> The result was the destruction of previous tribal work ethics, where often several people shared and worked the land together. </s><s n="s6.10;p5.16">The concept of value on land was also alien to Indians. </s><s n="s7.10;p5.16">Certainly, this was another way for the British to make money but there were further repercussions. </s><s n="s8.10;p5.16">If, for example, a land owner was had suffered a poor harvest and could not afford the land tax, then he would have to sell land in order to pay. </s><s n="s9.10;p5.16">The missing income from his poor harvest would also affect his crop growing ability the following year as well as imminent food supply. </s><s n="s10.10;p5.16">A vicious circle was created and also 'economic and social stratification'<ref target="BAWE_0030a-ftnote.011"/> of the peasants: a divide between the richer, land owning peasants and the poorer land workers. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0030a-ftnote.010"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Chamberlain, <hi rend="italic">Britain and India: The Interaction of Two Peoples</hi>, p. 125. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0030a-ftnote.011"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Charlesworth, <hi rend="italic">British Rule and the Indian Economy</hi>, pp. 30-1. </s></p></note><p n="p6.16"><s n="s1.5;p6.16">Britain's exploitative management of the Indian economy, both domestically and internationally was highlighted by R. C. Dutt<ref target="BAWE_0030a-ftnote.012"/> in three stages: firstly, tariffs, or lack of them, were used to favour British industrialists at Indian expense. </s><s n="s2.5;p6.16">Secondly, the aforementioned land tax forced the peasants into a subsistent lifestyle as most surpluses had to be sold to meet the tax. </s><s n="s3.5;p6.16">Thirdly, the 'tribute' tax, a massive drain on the economy. </s><s n="s4.5;p6.16">R. P. Dutt added a forth stage: 'British capital invested in India was in reality first raised in India from the plunder of the Indian people, and then written down as debt owed to India by Britain, on which she had henceforward to pay interest and dividends." </s><ref target="BAWE_0030a-ftnote.013"/><s n="s5.5;p6.16">R. P. Dutt also suggested that money coming out of Bengal financed the British Industrial Revolution<ref target="BAWE_0030a-ftnote.014"/>. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0030a-ftnote.012"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">R. C. Dutt, <hi rend="italic">The Economic History of India: 2, in the Victorian Age</hi> (1968), ch. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">5-9. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0030a-ftnote.013"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">R. P. Dutt, <hi rend="italic">India Today</hi> (London, 1940), pp. 106, 139. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0030a-ftnote.014"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Chamberlain, <hi rend="italic">Britain and India: The Interaction of Two Peoples</hi>, p. 112. </s></p></note><p n="p7.16"><s n="s1.4;p7.16">The lack of any Indian tariffs gave no protection to the Indian markets. </s><s n="s2.4;p7.16">For example, 'Indian goods were driven out of the British market (Lancashire goods were protected by British tariffs)...[but] Lancashire goods now began to drive Indian goods out of their home markets." </s><ref target="BAWE_0030a-ftnote.015"/><s n="s3.4;p7.16">No attempt was made to reverse this. </s><s n="s4.4;p7.16">In mitigation, it was British policy to allow free trade, and there was a belief that 'markets would find their own levels'<ref target="BAWE_0030a-ftnote.016"/>. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0030a-ftnote.015"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid, p. 115. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0030a-ftnote.016"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid, p. 116. </s></p></note><p n="p8.16"><s n="s1.16;p8.16">Perhaps the most controversial measure was that of the tribute tax. </s><s n="s2.16;p8.16">The payment of the tribute or 'home charge' was seen as the primary drain on the Indian economy. </s><s n="s3.16;p8.16">This included paying pensions and salaries of the administrators of India. </s><s n="s4.16;p8.16">The government felt it inappropriate to charge the British tax payer and subsequently billed any related expense to the colony. </s><s n="s5.16;p8.16">This stretched as far as the offices based in London. </s><s n="s6.16;p8.16">If this money had gone to Indians then at least it would have stayed in the Indian economy, but as it was paid to expatriate Britons, the money left the country. </s><s n="s7.16;p8.16">Revenue not spent on India was either used in public work schemes or paid to the shareholders of the East Indian Company, who collected a 10.5 per cent dividend. </s><s n="s8.16;p8.16">Even when the company ceased trading in 1834, this dividend still had to be paid. </s><s n="s9.16;p8.16">The Indians obviously could not afford this tax so a loan was created. </s><s n="s10.16;p8.16">This loan, however, still had to be serviced with interest payments. </s><s n="s11.16;p8.16">The East Indian Company surrendered its rights to the Crown who, despite the huge Indian debt, paid absolutely nothing for it. </s><s n="s12.16;p8.16">Whenever the tribute could not cover the cost of any expenditure, the amount was simply added to the loan. </s><s n="s13.16;p8.16">This obviously had a snowballing effect, with increased debt leading to increased interest payments. </s><s n="s14.16;p8.16">Military expenditure was obligatory, and effectively, 'Britain was...able to maintain a considerable army overseas at someone else's expense." </s><ref target="BAWE_0030a-ftnote.017"/><s n="s15.16;p8.16">The Afghan war added £40 million to the debt, and military overseas operations in Abyssinia in 1868 and Egypt in 1882 which aided Indian interest were added to the account. </s><s n="s16.16;p8.16">It is questionable how this could come about when some of the areas of the nation were in the poverty trap.<ref target="BAWE_0030a-ftnote.018"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0030a-ftnote.017"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Chamberlain, <hi rend="italic">Britain and India: The Interaction of Two Peoples</hi>, p. 129. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0030a-ftnote.018"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid, pp. 128-30. </s></p></note><p n="p9.16"><s n="s1.3;p9.16">In 1857, 'home charges...amounted...under the East Indian Company's rule to about £3 million pounds." </s><ref target="BAWE_0030a-ftnote.019"/><s n="s2.3;p9.16">However, 'In the 20 years from 1857... </s><s n="s3.3;p9.16">India paid home charges to the amount of £270 million at the very lowest estimate.'<ref target="BAWE_0030a-ftnote.020"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0030a-ftnote.019"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Hyndman, <hi rend="italic">The Bankruptcy of India</hi>, p. 53. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0030a-ftnote.020"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid. </s></p></note><p n="p10.16"><s n="s1.11;p10.16">The Crown also tagged public works expenditure to the account. </s><s n="s2.11;p10.16">This, as well as security, effectively were the only tangible product of the tribute and accumulating interest. </s><s n="s3.11;p10.16">Even in times of famine, the government showed no compassion. </s><s n="s4.11;p10.16">Hyndman describes how, for a typical Indian, 'the first thing to be met is the revenue and local charges, the next the soucar's usurious interest; the provision of food for men and animals comes after." </s><ref target="BAWE_0030a-ftnote.021"/><s n="s5.11;p10.16">He also describes the death of three hundred thousand people, despite food being exported that year. </s><s n="s6.11;p10.16">Yet still work on railways and irrigation continued: 'public works...are the greatest official panacea for famine." </s><ref target="BAWE_0030a-ftnote.022"/><s n="s7.11;p10.16">The problem is that railways did not produce wealth themselves. </s><s n="s8.11;p10.16">It is more likely that the creation of railway routes was maintained as it acted as an employer for British workers. </s><s n="s9.11;p10.16">In fact, India had to pay rent of £8 million to shareholders for the use of railways. </s><s n="s10.11;p10.16">On top of this was the bill for construction: 'up to 1877...a grand total of over £130 million [was spent on railways]...at the rate of £21,000 a mile." </s><ref target="BAWE_0030a-ftnote.023"/><s n="s11.11;p10.16">Irrigation too was criticised, as it would not make water run up hill or produce water in times of drought.<ref target="BAWE_0030a-ftnote.024"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0030a-ftnote.021"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Hyndman, <hi rend="italic">The Bankruptcy of India</hi>, p. 60. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0030a-ftnote.022"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid, p. 64. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0030a-ftnote.023"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid, p. 65. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0030a-ftnote.024"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid, pp. 65-7, 193-4. </s></p></note><p n="p11.16"><s n="s1.8;p11.16">Taxation perpetualised famine in India. </s><s n="s2.8;p11.16">The British insistence on building the railways and irrigation channels saw money being used in a way that didn't help the starving Indians. </s><s n="s3.8;p11.16">The revenue used was not even disposable capital: the Government accumulated deficit of £16 million in the three years between 1876-9. </s><s n="s4.8;p11.16">This was despite stationary revenue from India.<ref target="BAWE_0030a-ftnote.025"/> Predictably those suffering could not see the benefit of such expenditure. </s><s n="s5.8;p11.16">Furthermore, Sir John Strachey believed that the poor and only the poor should provide revenue for relief. </s><s n="s6.8;p11.16">The wealthier obviously did not require relief, and so Strachey placed the burden of revenue entirely on the poor, despite it being a time of famine and scarcity.<ref target="BAWE_0030a-ftnote.026"/> Lord Salisbury questioned the nature of this heavy taxation at a speech in Bradford in 1877. </s><s n="s7.8;p11.16">His idea was that the money spent on India should come from the savings of light taxation, rather than heavy taxation and loans. </s><s n="s8.8;p11.16">This saving idea was extended to the people: the only 'true remedy of famine and scarcity is the frugality of the people.'<ref target="BAWE_0030a-ftnote.027"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0030a-ftnote.025"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid, pp. 68-9. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0030a-ftnote.026"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid, pp. 69-70. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0030a-ftnote.027"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Hyndman, <hi rend="italic">The Bankruptcy of India</hi>, p. 67. </s></p></note><p n="p12.16"><s n="s1.7;p12.16">British policy in India was not destructive. </s><s n="s2.7;p12.16">It would be illogical for Britain to pump huge amounts of capital into India if this was the case. </s><s n="s3.7;p12.16">What is was possible to see was the Europeanization of India, with an European occupational army, a land policy of absenteeism and the employment of Europeans to work the state infrastructure and industry.<ref target="BAWE_0030a-ftnote.028"/> The public work schemes provided a source of controversy; they were not ineffective more overdone. </s><s n="s4.7;p12.16">The Europeanization of agriculture too was prevalent. </s><s n="s5.7;p12.16">There was the change from subsistence farming, to surplus cash crops. </s><s n="s6.7;p12.16">While creating a market for export, it also had great effect on the land. </s><s n="s7.7;p12.16">Land was not allowed to be fallow, and often was overworked. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0030a-ftnote.028"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid, pp. 98-9. </s></p></note><p n="p13.16"><s n="s1.4;p13.16">The greatest controversy during India rule, taxation, had its proponents. </s><s n="s2.4;p13.16">Sir Theodore Martin in 1911 countered the 'drain of India' argument, stipulating that 'British connection had enabled Indians to borrow capital for public works at substantially below the figure exacted from the Japanese for similar enterprises...and argued that this in itself was enough to wipe out the so-called tribute." </s><ref target="BAWE_0030a-ftnote.029"/><s n="s3.4;p13.16">Indeed, 'by the end of the century, both canals and railways were making a profit and beginning to contribute to the Indian revenues." </s><ref target="BAWE_0030a-ftnote.030"/><s n="s4.4;p13.16">Regarding the payment for an occupational army, it was argued that all nations must pay for defence, and Britain was keeping 'other powers out during the competitive days of the nineteenth century and...[providing] naval cover.'<ref target="BAWE_0030a-ftnote.031"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0030a-ftnote.029"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Chamberlain, <hi rend="italic">Britain and India: The Interaction of Two Peoples</hi>, p. 130. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0030a-ftnote.030"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid, p. 130. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0030a-ftnote.031"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Chamberlain, <hi rend="italic">Britain and India: The Interaction of Two Peoples</hi>, p. 130. </s></p></note><p n="p14.16"><s n="s1.9;p14.16">In terms of industry, there was a certain pick up by the twentieth century: 'by 1914 India was certainly not an industrial desert." </s><ref target="BAWE_0030a-ftnote.032"/><s n="s2.9;p14.16">In 1914, India had become the world's fourth greatest cotton manufacturing nation in the world, and produced three times as much as Japan. </s><s n="s3.9;p14.16">Such a transformation would not have been possible without the machinery and knowledge of Lancashire. </s><s n="s4.9;p14.16">The Tata iron and steel works had also been created, and by 1907, they were the largest in the British Empire and sixth largest in the world. </s><s n="s5.9;p14.16">In 1910, the same family had also branched out into hydroelectric power.<ref target="BAWE_0030a-ftnote.033"/> Such progression would not have been possible without the knowledge, technology and capital of Britain. </s><s n="s6.9;p14.16">While it is true to say that the public works were not always area specific and directly beneficial to all, the modernizing of the Indian state through establishment of infrastructure and industry only had a positive effect. </s><s n="s7.9;p14.16">It would perhaps seem uncompassionate that capital was being driven into the modernizing of the Indian state while the Indians themselves suffered. </s><s n="s8.9;p14.16">However, as Charlesworth points out, 'the imperial state was always at its most exploitative during its early stages." </s><ref target="BAWE_0030a-ftnote.034"/><s n="s9.9;p14.16">When industry and infrastructure was established and functional, India's economy improved which, in turn, increased quality of life for those involved. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0030a-ftnote.032"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid, p. 131. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0030a-ftnote.033"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0030a-ftnote.034"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Charlesworth, <hi rend="italic">British Rule and the Indian Economy</hi>, p. 68. </s></p></note><p n="p15.16"><s n="s1.4;p15.16">Perhaps those that suffered greatest were the agricultural underclass. </s><s n="s2.4;p15.16">These impoverished people paid for their own relief even in times of famine and hardship. </s><s n="s3.4;p15.16">There was a lack of technological advance in agriculture, even by 1951 'wooden ploughs...outnumbered iron ones by a factor of thirty to one." </s><ref target="BAWE_0030a-ftnote.035"/><s n="s4.4;p15.16">Agriculture was an area which did not experience a revolution. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0030a-ftnote.035"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Charlesworth, <hi rend="italic">British Rule and the Indian Economy</hi>, p. 22. </s></p></note><p n="p16.16"><s n="s1.3;p16.16">In the first instance, British colonisation economically exploited India, with a substantial drain on the economy. </s><s n="s2.3;p16.16">Colonies have the primary function that they are a source of wealth for the colonisers, but the British wanted to create an example, they wanted India to be the jewel in the Crown of British Empire. </s><s n="s3.3;p16.16">This meant heavy investment and modernisation of industry and infrastructure resulting in the enrichment of the society on the whole. </s></p></div1></body><back><div1 type="bibliography"><head rend="bold">Bibliography</head><p>Charlesworth, Neil, <hi rend="italic">British Rule and the Indian Economy 1800-1914</hi> (London, 1990).</p><p>Chamberlain, M. E., <hi rend="italic">Britain and India: The Interaction of Two Peoples</hi> (Newton Abbot, 1974).</p><p>Dutt, R. C., <hi rend="italic">The Economic History of India: 2, in the Victorian Age</hi> (1968).</p><p>Dutt, R. P., <hi rend="italic">India Today</hi> (London, 1940).</p><p>Hyndman, H. M., <hi rend="italic">The Bankruptcy of India</hi> (London, 1886).</p><p>Shlomo, Avineri, <hi rend="italic">Karl Marx on Colonisation and Modernisation</hi> (New York, 1969).</p><p>Stein, Burton, <hi rend="italic">The Making of Agrarian Policy in British India 1770 - 1900</hi> (Oxford, 1992).</p></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
