<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_0032b" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Subcellular Distribution of Succinate Dehydrogenase</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">deleted: header and footer giving student name and page numbers
</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">1</p><p n="date">2005-01</p><p n="module title">Biochemistry Laboratories and Assessed Work</p><p n="module code">BS120</p><p n="genre family">Methodology recount</p><p n="discipline">Biological Sciences</p><p n="disciplinary group">LS</p><p n="grade">D</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">496</p><p n="number of s-units">25</p><p n="number of p">8</p><p n="number of tables">0</p><p n="number of figures">2</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">1</p><p n="number of lists">0</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">0</p><p n="abstract present">abstract present</p><p n="average words per s-unit">19.8</p><p n="average s-units per p">3.1</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">m</p><p n="year of birth">1985</p><p n="first language">English</p><p n="education">UKA</p><p n="course">Biochemistry</p><p n="student ID">0032</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><docTitle><titlePart rend="bold">Experiment 10: Subcellular Distribution of Succinate Dehydrogenase</titlePart></docTitle></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="abstract"><head rend="bold">Abstract &amp; Aims</head><p n="p1.8"><s n="s1.3;p1.8">The aims of the experiment are to investigate the distribution of the enzyme succinate dehydrogenase in three subcellular compartments, the nucleus, the cytosol and the mitochondria, isolated from a preparation of cells from rat liver. </s><s n="s2.3;p1.8">The enzyme succinate dehydrogenase is found in the mitochondrial membrane, and so was most prevalent in the mitochondrial fraction. </s><s n="s3.3;p1.8">The cystolic fraction contained the highest percentage of protein due to the cytoskeletal material usually found in the cystol. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Introduction</head><p n="p2.8"><s n="s1.5;p2.8">Cells show a high degree of structure and organisation through the localisation of metabolic pathways and the related enzymes into distinct subcellular compartments. </s><s n="s2.5;p2.8">By disrupting the plasma membrane of the cell and separating the subcellular compartments it is possible to examine the metabolic pathways. </s><s n="s3.5;p2.8">Differential centrifugation is a common method for this separation procedure, which is known as fractionation. </s><s n="s4.5;p2.8">Successive centrifugations are carried out at increasing speeds, which pellets the larger particles first and smaller particles last, leaving cytosol as the supernatant. </s><s n="s5.5;p2.8">Typically around 90% of each fraction consists of one particular subcellular compartment. </s></p><p n="p3.8"><s n="s1.2;p3.8">The activity of succinate dehydrogenase acts as a marker for the location of the mitochondrial membrane where it is found. </s><s n="s2.2;p3.8">This enzyme catalyses the following reaction from the citric acid cycle. </s></p><p n="p4.8"><s n="s1.1;p4.8"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0032b-form.001"/> </s></p><p n="p5.8"><s n="s1.1;p5.8">Finding the subcellular location of any enzyme would have commercial applications as a prelude to purification of the enzyme, as only the fractions containing the highest amount of protein would be used. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Method</head><p n="p6.8"><s n="s1.2;p6.8">The method followed was as described in the laboratory manual. </s><s n="s2.2;p6.8">For the determination of protein content of the liver homogenate fractions biorad was used to blank the spectrophotometer. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Results</head><figure id="BAWE_0032b-fig.001"><head rend="underlined">Figure 1: Percentage of protein against percentage of enzyme in each fraction</head></figure><figure id="BAWE_0032b-fig.002"><head rend="underlined">Figure 2: Specific activity of the enzyme in each fraction</head></figure><p n="p7.8"/></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Discussion</head><p n="p8.8"><s n="s1.11;p8.8">Figure 1 shows the percentage content of protein and enzyme in each fraction. </s><s n="s2.11;p8.8">Fractions N and M contained fairly small percentages of protein. </s><s n="s3.11;p8.8">Fraction S however, contained nearly 45% protein. </s><s n="s4.11;p8.8">Fractions N and S contained small percentages of enzyme, while fraction M contained around 85% enzyme. </s><s n="s5.11;p8.8">Figure 2 shows the specific activity of the protein in each fraction, which is the purity of the enzyme with respect to other proteins. </s><s n="s6.11;p8.8">Fraction M has by far the greatest specific activity value of the four fractions. </s><s n="s7.11;p8.8">This fact concurs with the fact that fraction M had a high percentage content of enzyme, as a high percentage content in turn means a lower content of other cell parts and so a relatively high purity of the enzyme. </s><s n="s8.11;p8.8">Fraction M was the mitochondrial fraction, as such, a high concentration of enzyme was expected in this fraction because in a cell succinate dehydrogenase is located within the inner mitochondrial membrane. </s><s n="s9.11;p8.8">Both figures show that fraction M was not entirely enzyme, and that the fractionation left each fraction contaminated with the other fractions. </s><s n="s10.11;p8.8">Fraction S was the cytosol fraction, this contained the largest percentage of protein. </s><s n="s11.11;p8.8">This is due to the contents of a cell's cytosol being cytoskeletal material such as keratin, actin and spectrin. </s></p></div1></body><back><div1 type="appendix"><head rend="bold">Appendix</head><p/></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
