<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_0035a" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Eukaryotic Genetics: "Model Genetics as tools to understand gene function: Saccharomyces cerevisiae &amp; Drosophila"</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">deleted: header: student name and number and name of lab partner</note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">Evaluated as candidate compound assignment. Assigned to S1b: collection of reports: compound.</note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">deleted: tutor's comments at end</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">2</p><p n="date">2005-03</p><p n="module title">BS/MB/VIR/CB laboratories</p><p n="module code">BS215</p><p n="genre family">Methodology recount</p><p n="discipline">Biological Sciences</p><p n="disciplinary group">LS</p><p n="grade">M</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">2754</p><p n="number of s-units">130</p><p n="number of p">75</p><p n="number of tables">10</p><p n="number of figures">5</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">6</p><p n="number of lists">1</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">0</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">21.2</p><p n="average s-units per p">1.7</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">compound assignment consisting of 2 parts (see notesStmt for details)</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">f</p><p n="year of birth">1984</p><p n="first language">English</p><p n="education">UKA</p><p n="course">Biological Sciences</p><p n="student ID">0035</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><docTitle><titlePart rend="underlined bold">Eukaryotic Genetics Practical: Model Genetics as tools to understand gene function</titlePart></docTitle></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="text"><head rend="bold italic">Saccharomyces cerevisiae</head><p n="p1.75"/></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">Introduction</head><p n="p2.75"><s n="s1.2;p2.75">Saccharomyces cerevisiae is the yeast used by bakers and brewers. </s><s n="s2.2;p2.75">Its ~13Mb genome has been sequenced, and this along with its similarity to higher organisms in terms of basic biological processes (including biosynthetic pathways, DNA replication and repair, signal transduction, and cell cycle repair), and its ease of genetic manipulation makes it a good experimental organism. </s></p><p n="p3.75"><s n="s1.3;p3.75">This investigation uses three proteins: p53, SV40 and lamin put into 2 categories, bait and prey. </s><s n="s2.3;p3.75">The bait is put with both of the prey, to see which it will interact with. </s><s n="s3.3;p3.75">Figure 1 shows how these three proteins are used in this experiment in a yeast-2-hybrid screen, where the 2 haploid cells mate to form a diploid. </s></p><p n="p4.75"><s n="s1.1;p4.75">The yeast strains used are Y187 (mating type α) and AH109 (mating type <hi rend="bold">a</hi>). </s></p><p n="p5.75"><s n="s1.1;p5.75">The yeast's preferred state is as a diploid, therefore it will always attempt to mate to become a diploid if it's in its haploid state, insuring mating without any artificial intervention required. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0035a-fig.001"><head rend="italic">Figure 1. Life cycle of S. cerevisiae</head></figure><p n="p6.75"><s n="s1.5;p6.75">SV40 (simian virus 40), has a large T antigen, which is the protein used in this experiment as part of the "bait" construct. </s><s n="s2.5;p6.75">It is a DNA binding protein with high affinity for segments of the viral genome, where it works to prevent apoptosis of the host, ensuring its survival. It is tested here to see whether it binds to the proteins lamin or p53. </s><s n="s3.5;p6.75">The bait construct also contains the LEU2 gene, a nutritional marker that allows transformed yeast to grow without leucine. </s><s n="s4.5;p6.75">(This is important as the yeast strains used: AH109 and Y187 cannot grow naturally in the absence of leucine, tryptophan, uracil or histidine). </s><s n="s5.5;p6.75">LEU2 and the T antigen of SV40 are on a plasmid in AH109 (diagram on page 26 of manual). </s></p><p n="p7.75"><s n="s1.3;p7.75">P53 and lamin are the "prey" of the experiment. p53 is the product of a tumour suppressor gene, and is involved in regulating the activity of some other genes and prevents cells entering cell division. </s><s n="s2.3;p7.75">Lamin are structural components found in most multicellular organisms. </s><s n="s3.3;p7.75">Either lamin or p53, along with the TRP1 nutritional marker (allows growth in the absence of tryptophan) are inserted into a plasmid in Y187 (diagram page 25 of manual) and used as pray. </s></p><p n="p8.75"><s n="s1.1;p8.75">The interaction between one of the prey and the bait, will be shown by the production of the reporter genes by the activation of the upstream activation sequence (which can only occur in the diploid cell, not haploid) </s></p><div2><head rend="underlined bold">Materials and Methods</head><p n="p9.75"><s n="s1.1;p9.75">Growing and harvesting the yeast cultures (stages 1 and 2, page 14 of lab manual) was carried out by the demonstrators to save time. </s></p><p n="p10.75"><s n="s1.3;p10.75">Transformation of the bait and prey DNA constructs was carried out as described in the manual on pages 14 and 15. </s><s n="s2.3;p10.75">The first alteration made, was the second 30 <hi rend="sup">o</hi>C incubation detailed in steps 12 and 15 was shortened to 30 minutes from 50 minutes, as this was sufficient. </s><s n="s3.3;p10.75">The second alteration was that the centrifugation of step 16 was increased from 1000rpm to 2000 rpm, as the lower speed did not give the extent of pelleting required. </s></p><p n="p11.75"><s n="s1.1;p11.75">The mating of the transformed haploid yeast strains and the calculation of the transformation efficiency was followed exactly as described in the lab manual on page 18. </s></p><p n="p12.75"><s n="s1.1;p12.75">Testing diploid cultures for the reporter gene was carried out as described on page 20 of the manual, using 16 rather than 36 squares. </s></p><p n="p13.75"><s n="s1.1;p13.75">Quantification of interactors was done as explained in the manual on pages 23 and 24. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined bold">Results</head><p n="p14.75"><s n="s1.1;p14.75">The transformation efficiency of the haploid yeast strains were calculated (as described in the manual on page 18) to be as follows: AH019-p53 =2008 cfu/µg DNA, AH109-lamin = 1716 cfu/µg DNA, Y187-SV40 = 10 cfu/µg DNA. It can be seen that the most efficient was p53 and the least efficient SV40. </s></p><p n="p15.75"><s n="s1.1;p15.75">The number of diploid colonies per transformation mating plate was 220 for Y187-SV40 mated with AH109-p53, and 26 for Y187-SV40 mated with AH109-lamin. </s></p><p n="p16.75"><s n="s1.4;p16.75">Figure 2 shows a photograph of an X-a plate. </s><s n="s2.4;p16.75">It can be seen that there was very little p53 growth at all, but on what there is blue can be seen. </s><s n="s3.4;p16.75">There is much more lamin growth, showing more diploids were produced and blue can be seen here also. </s><s n="s4.4;p16.75">This implies that the reporter gene MEL-1 (produces -galactosidase) was expressed in both p53 and lamin, and therefore interaction occurred between the proteins in both pairs. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0035a-pic.001"><head><hi rend="underlined">Photograph of Plate showing protein interactions</hi><hi rend="italic">Figure 2. Photograph of X-a gal plate</hi></head></figure><p n="p17.75"><s n="s1.3;p17.75">The values in figure 3 show that a greater amount of ONPG is hydrolysed to o-nitrophenyl and D-Galactose per minute per cell in the case of p53 than lamin. </s><s n="s2.3;p17.75">This implies that the interaction between Y187-SV40 and AH109-p53, is much greater than that between Y187-SV40 and AH109-lamin. </s><s n="s3.3;p17.75">This contradicts with the results in figure 3, which implied more interactions with lamin. </s></p><table id="BAWE_0035a-tab.001"><head><hi rend="underlined">Table indicating the level of β-galactosidase produced for each protein pair.</hi> <hi rend="italic">Figure 3. Table of β-galactosidase units</hi></head><row><cell/></row></table></div2><div2><head rend="bold">Discussion</head><p n="p18.75"><s n="s1.3;p18.75">The transformation efficiency of the three proteins into the haploid yeast strains varies enormously. </s><s n="s2.3;p18.75">This could be is because of the effectiveness of the different plasmids at incorporating into the yeast. </s><s n="s3.3;p18.75">Here both of the prey plasmids transformed with far higher efficiency than the bait plasmids. </s></p><p n="p19.75"><s n="s1.2;p19.75">Following transformation, the plasmids were maintained in the yeast strains by being plated onto plates that ensured that they had to synthesize the amino acid missing on the plate, which the yeast were only able to do in the presence of the plasmid. </s><s n="s2.2;p19.75">The AH109-lamin and AH109-p53 were grown in the absence of tryptophan, and Y187-SV40 in the absence of leucine. </s></p><p n="p20.75"><s n="s1.2;p20.75">The method of transformation used here was lithium acetate, which acts by punching holes in the membrane of the yeast. </s><s n="s2.2;p20.75">Other methods that could have been used include electroporation, where the shock of electricity makes the membranes more permeable. </s></p><p n="p21.75"><s n="s1.4;p21.75">It would have been expected that the p53 would turn blue, and not the lamin, as other groups in the laboratory were able to show. </s><s n="s2.4;p21.75">This is because p53 it would express Mel-1, and therefore produce α-galactosidase, which would hydrolyse X-α Gal causing the yeast to turn blue. </s><s n="s3.4;p21.75">This did happen to small extent, but the blue of the lamin also needs to be accounted for. </s><s n="s4.4;p21.75">Lamin does contain some (much less that p53) Mel-1, which must have been released as they died, causing the blue yeast. </s></p><p n="p22.75"><s n="s1.3;p22.75">The quantification results, as shown in figure 3 support the above theory that the blue colouring shown for lamin interactions was due to released Mel-1 already in the lamin, rather than being caused by protein interactions. </s><s n="s2.3;p22.75">It supports this as it shows there to be a greater amount of β-galactosidase units for p53 interactions, by over 10 times greater. </s><s n="s3.3;p22.75">For the reporter gene, LacZ (which encodes β-galactosidase) to be expressed, protein interaction must have occurred and therefore for there to be so many more β-galactosidase units for p53 than lamin, it must be p53 that interacts with SV40. </s></p><p n="p23.75"><s n="s1.4;p23.75">Rather than using the reporter genes lacZ or MEL-1 ADE2 could have been used. </s><s n="s2.4;p23.75">ADE-2 contains a nutritional marker, meaning it could have been selected for on plates lacking adenine, in a similar we to trp- and leu- plates were used here. </s><s n="s3.4;p23.75">The marker on the plates if ADE-2 was used would have been red signalling protein interaction. </s><s n="s4.4;p23.75">The result expected in this instance would have been activation by interaction of the p53 protein. </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="front-back-matter"><head rend="bold">References</head><p><seg type="URL" n="www.yeastgenome.org/VL-yeast.html"/> 
</p><p><seg type="URL" n="www.pdg.cnb.uam.es/UniPub/iHOP/gg/34478.html"/> 
</p></div1><div1 type="text"><head><hi rend="underlined bold">Eukaryotic Genetics Practical: Model Genetics as tools to understand gene function</hi><hi rend="underlined bold">Drosophila</hi></head><div2><head rend="underlined bold">Introduction </head><p n="p24.75"><s n="s1.2;p24.75">P-elements are of high biological interest due to their horizontal transfer from various species to <hi rend="italic">Drosophila melanogaster</hi>, and the subsequent spread between <hi rend="italic">Drosophila</hi>. </s><s n="s2.2;p24.75">They also have a large number of technical applications that make them a very useful tool in manipulating the genome of drosophila. </s></p><p n="p25.75"><s n="s1.4;p25.75"><hi rend="italic">Drosophila melanogaster</hi> is a fruit fly, of approximately 3mm long. </s><s n="s2.4;p25.75">It has been used as a model organism for research for almost a century, due to its ease to handle, well understood, a short life cycle of about 2 weeks, and cheap to handle, and its entire genome is now sequenced. </s><s n="s3.4;p25.75">It has 4 pairs of chromosomes, 1 XY pair and three autosome pairs (2,3 and 4). </s><s n="s4.4;p25.75">We will be looking at pairs 1 2 and 3, as the fourth is so tiny. </s></p><p n="p26.75"><s n="s1.2;p26.75">Transposition is when a donor element (P-element) is excised from the donor, and reinserted into a recipient, creating an exact replication. </s><s n="s2.2;p26.75">Transposase is encoded by P-elements and binds to subterminal regions at both ends of the element and represses transcription. </s></p><p n="p27.75"><s n="s1.1;p27.75">Transposition is thought to be an important factor in evolution, due to the mutations it causes, and the selective benefits these may have caused on the species and then been selected for. </s></p><p n="p28.75"><s n="s1.1;p28.75">In this experiment P-elements and drosophila are used to study different genetic techniques. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined bold">Materials and Methods</head><p n="p29.75"><s n="s1.1;p29.75">All materials and processes were carried as explained in the manual with the following details: </s></p><div3><head rend="bold italic">Experiment 1</head><p n="p30.75"><s n="s1.1;p30.75">The following flies were crossed: </s></p><table id="BAWE_0035a-tab.002"><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p31.75"><s n="s1.2;p31.75">They both carry the white mutations, and the males also carry a transposon marker with a stubble mutation. </s><s n="s2.2;p31.75">The females have a P-element. </s></p><p n="p32.75"><s n="s1.1;p32.75">The P element used is as shown in figure 1 </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0035a-fig.002"><head rend="italic">Figure 1: P-elementGAL4 dependent promoter, torp4a only expressed when he fly produces GAL4 protein. White+ makes the fly's eye red; it's a marker. </head></figure></div3><div3><head rend="bold italic">Experiment 2</head><p n="p33.75"><s n="s1.1;p33.75">The following flies were crossed: </s></p><table id="BAWE_0035a-tab.003"><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p34.75"><s n="s1.2;p34.75">Here both the males and females have a Y chromosome demonstrating that the presence of a Y chromosome does not determine a male phenotype. </s><s n="s2.2;p34.75">Instead, in the case of drosophila, it is the ratio of X chromosomes to autosomes, and in this example the female has almost 2 complete X chromosomes. </s></p><p n="p35.75"><s n="s1.2;p35.75">The males here are wild type, and the females carry 8 insertions of a P element marked by a mini-white+ gene mutation, and carrying a <hi rend="italic">lacZ</hi> gene, and a transposase marked by a dominant stubble mutation. </s><s n="s2.2;p35.75">The females also have an attached X chromosome, which is nearly 2 complete copies of the X chromosome. </s></p><p n="p36.75"><s n="s1.1;p36.75">The P element used is as shown in figure 2 </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0035a-fig.003"><head rend="italic">Figure 2: P-elementPoor promoter, requires enhancer activity to make lacZ mRNA</head></figure></div3><div3><head rend="bold italic">Experiment 3</head><p n="p37.75"><s n="s1.1;p37.75">The following flies were crossed: </s></p><table id="BAWE_0035a-tab.004"><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p38.75"><s n="s1.1;p38.75">The P element used is that shown in figure 1. </s></p></div3><div3><head rend="bold italic">Experiment 4</head><p n="p39.75"><s n="s1.1;p39.75">The following flies were crossed: </s></p><table id="BAWE_0035a-tab.005"><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p40.75"><s n="s1.1;p40.75">The males have UAS-<hi rend="italic">aru</hi> transgenes with the mini-white mutation, and carry the transposase characterised by the stubble mutation </s></p><p n="p41.75"><s n="s1.1;p41.75">The females have a strong ubiquitous eye-specific GAL4 driver, with the mini-white mutation. </s></p><p n="p42.75"><s n="s1.1;p42.75">The P element used on the male is shown in figure 3. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0035a-fig.004"><head rend="italic">Figure 3: P-elementGAL4 dependent promoter, producing mRNA for inverted copy of the arouser gene. </head></figure></div3></div2><div2><head rend="underlined bold">Results</head><div3><head rend="bold italic">Experiment 1</head><p n="p43.75"><s n="s1.1;p43.75">Male offspring with both the transposon and the P-element will have the genotype: </s></p><p n="p44.75"><s n="s1.1;p44.75"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0035a-form.001"/> </s></p><p n="p45.75"><s n="s1.1;p45.75">Males with curly wings and red eyes and the following genotype, are saved for experiment 3. </s></p><p n="p46.75"><s n="s1.1;p46.75"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0035a-form.002"/> </s></p><p n="p47.75"><s n="s1.1;p47.75">From cross 1, 4 red eyed, straight winged males with stubble were obtained. </s></p><p n="p48.75"><s n="s1.2;p48.75">Some of the eyes were observed to have mosaic eyes, examples shown in figure 4. </s><s n="s2.2;p48.75">Those with masaic eyes must have the genotype: </s></p><p n="p49.75"><s n="s1.1;p49.75"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0035a-form.003"/> </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0035a-pic.002"><head rend="italic">Figure 4: A drosophila eye with mosaic effect</head></figure></div3><div3><head rend="bold italic">Experiment 2</head><p n="p50.75"><s n="s1.1;p50.75">Only 25% of the crosses in the class survived. </s></p><p n="p51.75"><s n="s1.1;p51.75">The class results were as follows: </s></p><table id="BAWE_0035a-tab.006"><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p52.75"><s n="s1.1;p52.75">Δ<hi rend="sup">w+</hi> shows the moved P element carrying in the w+ gene. </s></p><p n="p53.75"><s n="s1.1;p53.75">As can be seen, there were approximately 10 times more white eyed males, than red. </s></p></div3><div3><head rend="bold italic">Experiment 3</head><p n="p54.75"><s n="s1.3;p54.75">36 curly winged and 5 straight winged flies were counted by us. </s><s n="s2.3;p54.75">That is a ratio of 36:5 or 7.2:1. </s><s n="s3.3;p54.75">The class results were 140:44 or 3.2:1, slightly lower than ours. </s></p><div4><head rend="bold italic">Experiment 4</head><p n="p55.75"><s n="s1.3;p55.75">Of the 9 flies we screened they all died. </s><s n="s2.3;p55.75">Using the results of SC and WC, 11 flies were screened, and none had rough eyes. </s><s n="s3.3;p55.75">In the class 1342 flies were screened and only 6 rough eyes discovered. </s></p></div4></div3><div3><head rend="bold italic">Experiment 5</head><p n="p56.75"><s n="s1.2;p56.75">Upon staining of the imaginal discs and brains of the third instar larvae, staining was observed in the brain and central nerve chord, centre of antennal, 2 of the 3 sensory neurons on the wing, the mechanosensory on the wing: this forms a line of bristles on the wing, and the tissue between the brain and eye (which are muscle precursors). </s><s n="s2.2;p56.75">This staining can be seen in figures 5 and 6. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0035a-pic.003"><head rend="italic">Figure 5 Staining of 3rd instar larvae Figure 6. Staining of 3rd instar larvae wing</head></figure></div3></div2><div2><head rend="underlined bold">Discussion </head><div3><head rend="bold italic">Experiment 1</head><p n="p57.75"><s n="s1.1;p57.75">The flies obtained with the transposon and the P-element (both required for transposition), must have had the genotype: </s></p><p n="p58.75"><s n="s1.1;p58.75"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0035a-form.004"/> </s></p><p n="p59.75"><s n="s1.5;p59.75">Flies with mosaic and white eyes (figure 4) demonstrate the occurrence of somatic transposition. </s><s n="s2.5;p59.75">(The P elements used have a Δ2-3 aloowing somatic transposition). </s><s n="s3.5;p59.75">The transposase on the 3 <hi rend="sup">rd</hi> male chromosome has acted on the transposon on the 2 <hi rend="sup">nd</hi> female chromosome, making it move or leave the chromosome. </s><s n="s4.5;p59.75">Where it has completely left the chromosome, the flies have white eyes as the mini-white+ gene encoding red is lost. </s><s n="s5.5;p59.75">The mosaic eye occurs when the P element has moved, the red being in cells where it has landed, and the different shades demonstrating different levels of expression of the w+ gene (rarely as strong from the wild type). </s></p></div3><div3><head rend="bold italic">Experiment 2</head><p n="p60.75"><s n="s1.2;p60.75">Only 25% of the crosses in the class survived because the females were sick. </s><s n="s2.2;p60.75">It is known that insertions were in the germline as the progeny have the insertion in all of their cells (i.e. the eyes were not mosaic). </s></p><p n="p61.75"><s n="s1.1;p61.75">Flies with the transposase gene are recognised by their stubble, with the original P inserts by mosaic eyes(P element didn't move in germline), with neither the original or new P inserts or a transposase have white eyes, no stubble and will have one of the genotypes: </s></p><p n="p62.75"><s n="s1.1;p62.75"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0035a-form.005"/><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0035a-form.006"/> </s></p><p n="p63.75"><s n="s1.1;p63.75">Flies without the original P inserts nor transposase, but with a new transposase have eyes of one smooth red colour. </s></p><p n="p64.75"><s n="s1.1;p64.75">The possible progeny are shown in figure 7. </s></p><p n="p65.75"><s n="s1.1;p65.75">We obtained: </s></p><table id="BAWE_0035a-tab.007"><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p66.75"><s n="s1.1;p66.75">The 10 white+ males show a new P insertion has occurred. </s></p><table id="BAWE_0035a-tab.008"><head rend="italic">Figure 7. The genotype and phenotype of the possible progeny</head><row><cell/></row></table></div3><div3><head rend="bold italic">Experiment 3</head><figure id="BAWE_0035a-pic.004"><head><hi rend="bold italic">Figures 8 and 9.</hi> <hi rend="italic">8: Wild type wing structure (Cy) 9: Cy+ wing structure</hi></head></figure><p n="p67.75"><s n="s1.3;p67.75">By comparison of Cy+ and Cy wings (example shown in figure 9 from JL and ECS) a gap is seen where the vein is interrupted before reaching the edge of the wing (circled in figure 9). </s><s n="s2.3;p67.75">This occurs because the introduced dsRNA that corresponds to part of the ORF binds, causing the target mRNA to be broken down so that it can't be translated. </s><s n="s3.3;p67.75">The transgene must have corresponded to the part of mRNA for this part of wing vein, hence it could not be translated. </s></p><p n="p68.75"><s n="s1.1;p68.75">The possible progeny looking at the 2 <hi rend="sup">nd</hi> chromosome were: </s></p><table id="BAWE_0035a-tab.009"><row><cell/></row></table><table id="BAWE_0035a-tab.010"><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p69.75"><s n="s1.1;p69.75">The expected ratio of curly: straight is therefore 2:1 </s></p><p n="p70.75"><s n="s1.1;p70.75">Observed ratio 7.2:1 </s></p><p n="p71.75"><s n="s1.1;p71.75">Class observed ratio 3.2:1 </s></p><p n="p72.75"><s n="s1.3;p72.75">Chi squared for our results is 8.3. </s><s n="s2.3;p72.75">This is greater than the tabulated value for n-1 degrees of freedom at p=0.05, showing a significant difference between the observed and expected ratios, and that the difference is 0.95 likely not to be due to chance. </s><s n="s3.3;p72.75">Chi squared for the class results is 7.3; still greater than the tabulated value, but closer to the value meaning it is less likely to be due to chance, and closer to the expected ratio. </s></p></div3><div3><head rend="bold italic">Experiment 4</head><p n="p73.75"><s n="s1.4;p73.75">No rough eyes were screened by us as they all died. </s><s n="s2.4;p73.75">SC and WC screened 11 flies, but none were rough eye, however these are rare events occurring only weakly when the complete UAS-<hi rend="italic">aru</hi> is expressed. </s><s n="s3.4;p73.75">It is likely for SC and WC that the transposase induced events such as deletions, inversions, and duplications in the P element, giving near precise or imprecise excision, but not the precise excision of the P element that gives rise to rough eye. </s><s n="s4.4;p73.75">In rough eye flies there will be a white patch in the eye, as the marker is completely removed with the P element (figure 10). </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0035a-pic.005"><head rend="italic">Figure 10, A rough eyed fly. It can be identified by the altered morphology and the imperfect pattern, due to the aru gene being expressed in the eye causing subtle deformation</head></figure></div3><div3><head rend="bold italic">Experiment 5</head><p n="p74.75"><s n="s1.3;p74.75">The staining seen in figures 5 and 6 is the result of where the transposon has landed. </s><s n="s2.3;p74.75">When the transposon lands near to the enhancer or in the X gene it can enhance the usually poor promoter of <hi rend="italic">lacZ</hi>. </s><s n="s3.3;p74.75">Staining occurs due to the staining of β-galactosidase, which is the product of translation of <hi rend="italic">lacZ</hi>. </s></p><p n="p75.75"><s n="s1.1;p75.75">The fly would likely die, as it has mutation to the brain, but if it were to live, speculations of its phenotype would include: </s></p><list type="bulleted"><item>Inability to fly </item><item>Brain damage </item><item>Blind </item><item>Painless (bumps into things)</item></list></div3></div2></div1></body><back/></text></TEI.2>
