<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_0035b" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Plant Molecular Development: "The mechanisms of higher plants and algae to concentrate CO2 at the site of photosynthetic carbon fixation, and their significance in relation to the environments in which they live"</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">deleted: header giving student number
</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">2</p><p n="date">2005-03</p><p n="module title">BS/MB/VIR/CB assessments</p><p n="module code">BS241</p><p n="genre family">Explanation</p><p n="discipline">Biological Sciences</p><p n="disciplinary group">LS</p><p n="grade">M</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">3859</p><p n="number of s-units">152</p><p n="number of p">51</p><p n="number of tables">3</p><p n="number of figures">3</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">0</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">8</p><p n="abstract present">abstract present</p><p n="average words per s-unit">25.4</p><p n="average s-units per p">3.0</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">f</p><p n="year of birth">1984</p><p n="first language">English</p><p n="education">UKA</p><p n="course">Biological Sciences</p><p n="student ID">0035</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><docTitle><titlePart rend="underlined bold">Plant Molecular Development The mechanisms of higher plants and algae to concentrate CO2 at the site of photosynthetic carbon fixation, and their significance in relation to the environments in which they live</titlePart></docTitle></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="abstract"><head rend="underlined bold">Abstract</head><p n="p1.51"><s n="s1.4;p1.51">Higher plants and algae use various mechanisms to concentrate CO <hi rend="sub">2</hi> at the site of Rubisco. </s><s n="s2.4;p1.51">The three key concentrating mechanisms C <hi rend="sub">4</hi> photosynthetic carbon fixation, crassulacean acid metabolism (CAM) and internal concentration of CO <hi rend="sub">2</hi> each exploit the features of the plant type including the structure, the light sensing machinery, the regulatory elements and enzymes. </s><s n="s3.4;p1.51">The mechanisms relate directly to the environment in which they live: C <hi rend="sub">4</hi> plants coping with high temperatures and dryness, CAM with drought and algae with minimal light in the water depths. </s><s n="s4.4;p1.51">Each has evolved over time in various species each with the environmental conditions in common. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">Introduction</head><p n="p2.51"><s n="s1.7;p2.51">Rubisco has poor affinity for CO <hi rend="sub">2</hi>, probably due to its evolution in CO <hi rend="sub">2</hi> levels much higher than today. </s><s n="s2.7;p2.51">In normal atmospheric conditions Rubisco operates at below 30% of its capacity. </s><s n="s3.7;p2.51">To improve this C <hi rend="sub">3</hi> plants contain high amounts of Rubisco. </s><s n="s4.7;p2.51">O <hi rend="sub">2</hi> competes with CO <hi rend="sub">2</hi> as Rubisco's substrate, and O <hi rend="sub">2</hi> from the atmosphere accounts for 30% of the reactions catalysed by Rubisco. </s><s n="s5.7;p2.51">It is therefore vital that plants can increase the concentration of CO <hi rend="sub">2</hi> at the site of Rubisco to increase the amount of CO <hi rend="sub">2</hi> fixation, and decrease the amount of oxygenation reactions. </s><s n="s6.7;p2.51">This essay will look at the mechanisms and significance in relation to the environment of three plant groups that use varying methods of this CO <hi rend="sub">2</hi> concentrating mechanism. </s><s n="s7.7;p2.51">The three mechanisms are C <hi rend="sub">4</hi> photosynthetic carbon fixation, Crassulacean acid metabolism (CAM) and internal concentration of CO <hi rend="sub">2</hi> used by C <hi rend="sub">4</hi>, CAM, and algal and cyanobacterial cells respectively. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">C4 photosynthetic carbon fixation</head><p n="p3.51"><s n="s1.2;p3.51">C <hi rend="sub">4</hi> plants have spatial separation of enzymes: PEP carboxylase in the mesophyll cells, and Rubisco in the bundle sheath cells. </s><s n="s2.2;p3.51">They concentrate CO <hi rend="sub">2</hi> at the site of Rubisco by combining the C <hi rend="sub">4</hi> cycle with the Calvin cycle, as shown in figure 1, a process summarised into four stages (2): </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p4.51"><s rend="bold" n="s1.1;p4.51">CO2 fixation. </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p5.51"><s n="s1.4;p5.51">Phosphoenolpyruvate (PEP) is carboxylated in the mesophyll cells to form oxaloacetate, which is converted to a C <hi rend="sub">4</hi> acid (malate and/or Aspartate). </s><s n="s2.4;p5.51">Atmospheric CO <hi rend="sub">2</hi> is not used directly, but rather converted to HCO <hi rend="sub">3</hi>- first by carbonic anhydrase (CA) because PEP carboxylase has a high affinity for HCO <hi rend="sub">3</hi>-, and is insensitive to O <hi rend="sub">2</hi>, unlike Rubisco. </s><s n="s3.4;p5.51">Rubisco does not interfere because of the spatial separation of it in the bundle sheath cells. </s><s n="s4.4;p5.51">PEP carboxylase is not unique to C <hi rend="sub">4</hi> plants but its activity can be up to 100-fold more than in the leaves of C <hi rend="sub">3</hi> plants. </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p6.51"><s rend="bold" n="s1.1;p6.51">C4 acid transported to bundle sheath cells </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p7.51"><s n="s1.2;p7.51">This detected CO <hi rend="sub">2</hi> movement demonstrates the action of the C <hi rend="sub">4</hi> cycle. </s><s n="s2.2;p7.51">It moves compartment via an ATP-driven carbon dioxide pump in which two ATP molecules are transferred per CO2 </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p8.51"><s rend="bold" n="s1.1;p8.51">C4 acid decarboxylation </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p9.51"><s n="s1.2;p9.51">If the C4 acid is malate, this is carried out my malic enzyme, generating a C <hi rend="sub">3</hi> acid (pyruvate or alanine) and CO <hi rend="sub">2</hi>, which is reduced to carbohydrates by the Calvin cycle. </s><s n="s2.2;p9.51">In the Calvin cycle Ribulose uses CO <hi rend="sub">2</hi> and ribulose-1.5-bisphosphate to form two molecules of 3-phosophoglycerate </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p10.51"><s n="s1.1;p10.51"><hi rend="bold">C3 acid is transported to the mesophyll cells, and the CO2 acceptor PEP is regenerated</hi>. </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p11.51"><s n="s1.1;p11.51">PEP regeneration, and therefore the autocatalytic nature of the process is only possible because the two cycles are involved, the C <hi rend="sub">4</hi> cycle alone would not facilitate this. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0035b-fig.001"><head rend="italic">Figure 1. A summary of the C4 photosynthetic system, consisting if the C4 and Calvin-Benson cycles. </head></figure><p n="p12.51"><s n="s1.3;p12.51">PEP regeneration consumes two ATP equivalents per CO <hi rend="sub">2</hi> transported. </s><s n="s2.3;p12.51">The total energy required to fix one CO <hi rend="sub">2</hi> molecule is 4ATP plus two NADPH (2). </s><s n="s3.3;p12.51">This is a higher energy demand than required by C <hi rend="sub">3</hi> plants, but due to the mechanisms avoiding photorespiration in varying environmental conditions the quantum requirement of C <hi rend="sub">4</hi> plants remains relatively constant. </s></p><div2><head rend="bold italic">Leaf anatomy</head><p n="p13.51"><s n="s1.2;p13.51">The major difference between C <hi rend="sub">3</hi> and C <hi rend="sub">4</hi> plants is that C <hi rend="sub">4</hi> plants contain chloroplasts in two cell types: the mesophyll and the bundle sheath, rather than only the mesophyll. </s><s n="s2.2;p13.51">This C <hi rend="sub">4</hi> leaf anatomy is known as Kranz anatomy, as shown in figure 2. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0035b-pic.001"><head rend="italic">Figure 2. Kranz anatomy of a C4 plant showing the chloroplast containing mesophyll and single bundle sheath cells. (20)</head></figure><p n="p14.51"><s n="s1.5;p14.51">The bundle sheath can be single or double, and as shown in figure 2 have thin-walled mesophyll (which contact the intercellular air spaces) radiating out from them in various arrangements but never more than two or three cells away. </s><s n="s2.5;p14.51">Bundle sheath cell walls are thick, and often contain suberin, which contributes to the barrier to water, solute and gas movement. </s><s n="s3.5;p14.51">It also allows CO <hi rend="sub">2</hi> to concentrate, with little leakage (10-40% of total transfer depending on the species (1)) therefore preventing photorespiration. </s><s n="s4.5;p14.51">This low permeability has been proven by mutants of <hi rend="italic">Amaranthus edulis</hi>, a C <hi rend="sub">4</hi> plant, without PEP carboxylase that only grow in very high CO <hi rend="sub">2</hi> concentrations, as they are incapable of CO <hi rend="sub">2</hi> concentration to the level required for the carboxylation of Rubisco. </s><s n="s5.5;p14.51">However, desired movement of metabolites is possible via the many plasmodesmata to the mesophyll cells, allowing cell-to-cell communication. </s></p><p n="p15.51"><s n="s1.1;p15.51">CO <hi rend="sub">2</hi> concentration in the bundle sheath in C <hi rend="sub">4</hi> plants is significantly higher than in C <hi rend="sub">3</hi> plants at an estimated 20-60M compared to 7-8M for C <hi rend="sub">3</hi> leaves in pH's 7.5 and 8 respectively (1). </s></p><p n="p16.51"><s n="s1.3;p16.51">Despite most C <hi rend="sub">4</hi> plants having Kranz anatomy, it has been shown to not be essential (5) as Magnin et al. were able to successfully induce C <hi rend="sub">4</hi> photosynthesis on the submersed monocot <hi rend="italic">Hydrilla verticillata,</hi> which has an ancient structure not resembling Kranz anatomy. </s><s n="s2.3;p16.51">However Leegood decided it to be unlikely to successfully introduce single cell CO <hi rend="sub">2</hi>-concentrating mechanisms into modern non-C <hi rend="sub">4</hi> cells without also introducing some of the structural characteristics. </s><s n="s3.3;p16.51">(12) </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold italic">Transport</head><p n="p17.51"><s n="s1.2;p17.51">Metabolite movement between the cell types is facilitated by selective plasmodesmata (molecules less than 800 Da (1)) and diffusion is induced by concentration gradients. </s><s n="s2.2;p17.51">Within the cells specialised translocaters, and again concentration gradients regulate movement over the chloroplast envelopes. </s></p><p n="p18.51"><s n="s1.2;p18.51">The movement rate of metabolites from the C <hi rend="sub">4</hi> cycle such as malate must be equal to the rates of CO <hi rend="sub">2</hi> assimilation. </s><s n="s2.2;p18.51">In illuminated leaves, the concentration gradients of e.g. malate have been seen to build up to a greater contrast than required for diffusion to occur at a rate sufficient to support the photosynthesis rate observed (1). </s></p><p n="p19.51"><s n="s1.1;p19.51">It is due to the effective transport of CO <hi rend="sub">2</hi>, and its concentration in the bundle sheath being of a higher concentration than it would be in equilibrium with the atmosphere (2), that suppression of the oxygenation of ribulose-1,5-bisphosphate by Rubisco, and therefore of photorespiration occurs. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold italic">Variations</head><p n="p20.51"><s n="s1.2;p20.51">The basic C <hi rend="sub">4</hi> pathway has three variations (shown in figure 3), which differ mainly in the C <hi rend="sub">4</hi> acid (malate or Aspartate) and the enzymes involved in their decarboxylation (2). </s><s n="s2.2;p20.51">In variation 3, NAD+-malic enzyme provides NADH, which is oxidised generating ATP, which is necessary for the operation of PEP carboxykinase (1). </s></p><table id="BAWE_0035b-tab.001"><head rend="italic">Figure 3. The differences between the 3 variations of C4 plants. </head><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p21.51"><s n="s1.3;p21.51">Whether the plant produces malate or aspartate is important, as aspartate does not have the ability to carry reductants from mesophyll to bundle sheath as malate does. </s><s n="s2.3;p21.51">These instead require the otherwise absent photosystem II in the bundle sheath to generate this reductant for carbon assimilation. </s><s n="s3.3;p21.51">This deficiency in photosystem II of variation 1 is beneficial in that it maintains the high CO <hi rend="sub">2</hi> to O <hi rend="sub">2</hi> ratio, further reducing the possibility of photorespiration occurring in the bundle sheath (1). </s></p><p n="p22.51"><s n="s1.1;p22.51">There are further distinctions between the types including the direction of the chloroplasts and the presence of single or double sheaths, but the significance of these differences is unknown. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold italic">Regulation</head><p n="p23.51"><s n="s1.5;p23.51">Light regulates the activity of the key enzymes including PEP carboxylase and pyruvate P <hi rend="sub">i</hi> dikinase, as shown in Figure 4. </s><s n="s2.5;p23.51">In illuminated leaves (in its phosphorylated, active form), PEP carboxylase is less sensitive to malate inhibition than in dark leaves. </s><s n="s3.5;p23.51">It is the protein kinase that undergoes diurnal changes in activity. </s><s n="s4.5;p23.51">Cytosolic pH, [Ca <hi rend="sup">2+</hi>] and metabolites, such as glycerate 3-phosohate may also contribute to the activity/synthesis of the kinase (1). </s><s n="s5.5;p23.51">Pyruvate P <hi rend="sub">i</hi> dikinase is also regulated by reversible phosphorylation. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0035b-fig.002"><head><hi rend="italic">Figure 4. Regulation of PEP carboxylase</hi> <hi rend="italic">by metabolites providing communication between the C4 cycle, and the Benson-Calvin cycle</hi></head></figure><p n="p24.51"><s n="s1.2;p24.51">Regulation of the C <hi rend="sub">4</hi> acid decarboxylases is partly by substrate supply. </s><s n="s2.2;p24.51">Other factors involved include pH, Mg+, products of the Benson-Calvin cycle </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">Significance in relation to environment</head><p n="p25.51"><s n="s1.9;p25.51">The C <hi rend="sub">4</hi> mechanism is thought to have evolved between 7 and 30 million years ago in response to a decrease in atmospheric CO <hi rend="sub">2</hi> concentration. </s><s n="s2.9;p25.51">It was discovered in tropical grasses (2) and is now known to consist of 17 higher family plants, and includes many important crop species including maize and sugarcane (both Graminae) (1). </s><s n="s3.9;p25.51">The plants vary considerably and indicate that the mechanism evolved multiple times in different species. </s><s n="s4.9;p25.51">They are found primarily in hot, dry environments and predominate in tropical grasslands covering 15% of the earth's vegetated surface, and, despite the small number of species are responsible for about 18% of the global terrestrial photosynthesis (1). </s><s n="s5.9;p25.51">They predominate in these locations as the process minimises water loss and photorespiration compared to that in C <hi rend="sub">3</hi> plants. </s><s n="s6.9;p25.51">Photorespiration rate is shown to be low unless the intercellular [CO <hi rend="sub">2</hi>] is severely limited by stress (8). </s><s n="s7.9;p25.51">Both of these factors enable C <hi rend="sub">4</hi> plants to photosynthesise more efficiently at higher temperatures than C <hi rend="sub">3</hi> plants (2). </s><s n="s8.9;p25.51">Because of the high activity of PEP carboxylase, C <hi rend="sub">4</hi> plants can reduce the stomatal size reducing water loss without reducing the CO <hi rend="sub">2</hi> fixation rate, which is important in their environments. </s><s n="s9.9;p25.51">The suppression of photorespiration by the high concentration of CO <hi rend="sub">2</hi> is also beneficial as it means, the enzymes can be used for the CO <hi rend="sub">2</hi> reactions. </s></p><p n="p26.51"><s n="s1.1;p26.51">Some plants have been observed to have properties between those of C3 and C4 plants depending on their natural environments (2). </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">Crassulacean acid metabolism (CAM)</head><p n="p27.51"><s n="s1.3;p27.51">Many plants that exist in environments with a short water supply undergo Crassulacean Acid Metabolism, which is a CO <hi rend="sub">2</hi> concentrating mechanism that induces increased water-use efficiency (WUE). </s><s n="s2.3;p27.51">The first recognition of CAM was that succulent plants tasted more bitter (malic acid) in the morning then the evening (15), initially by the Romans, and formally described in the early nineteenth century by de Saussure (16), and Heyne (whom it was named after(13))(17). </s><s n="s3.3;p27.51">The diversity of these drought exposed species from the common Cactaceae and Euphorbiaceae, and tropical epiphytes to the two ferns suggests that, like the C <hi rend="sub">4</hi> mechanism it has evolved many times throughout evolution. </s></p><div2><head rend="bold italic">Mechanism</head><p n="p28.51"><s n="s1.3;p28.51">CAM is similar to C <hi rend="sub">4</hi> metabolism but uses temporal rather than spatial separation of carbon fixation (13). </s><s n="s2.3;p28.51">This process is shown in figure 5, and can be divided in to night-time and day-time reactions, and further more, into 4 phases, as shown in figure 6. </s><s n="s3.3;p28.51">These phases can be suppressed in severe drought as water saving becomes more important than carbon gain. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0035b-fig.003"><head rend="italic">Figure 5, The Crassulacean Acid Metabolism, showing the distribution of dark and light reactions (14)</head></figure><div3><head rend="bold">Night (Stages 4 and 1):</head><p n="p29.51"><s n="s1.9;p29.51">The fixation of CO <hi rend="sub">2</hi> rapidly converts carbohydrate (mostly starch and sucrose) to oxaloacetate, which is reduced to malate. </s><s n="s2.9;p29.51">This is indicated by the inverse relationship between carbohydrate in the leaves the amount of malate, and the absence of CO <hi rend="sub">2</hi> completely inhibiting starch degradation (1). </s><s n="s3.9;p29.51">CO <hi rend="sub">2</hi> fixation is carried out by phosphoenolpyruvate carboxylase (PEPC) in the cytosol. </s><s n="s4.9;p29.51">Stomata are opened at night when the temperature and hence the water loss are at their lowest. </s><s n="s5.9;p29.51">Malate (or an alternative C <hi rend="sub">4</hi> organic acid) is actively transported and stored in the vacuole until light. </s><s n="s6.9;p29.51">The malate movement is via ATP dependent and pyrophosphate (Ppi)-dependent, H+ transport. </s><s n="s7.9;p29.51">When CAM is induced into <hi rend="italic">Mesembryanthemum crystallinum</hi> it leads to activation of the ATPase alone, indicating it to be the more important of the two. </s><s n="s8.9;p29.51">It is the acidification of the vacuole by malate at the start of the dark period that activates both of these pumps. </s><s n="s9.9;p29.51">Consideration of pH and the amount of malate stored indicates the majority of malate in a cell to be in the vacuole, where it is protected from further metabolism, prevents excessive acidification of the cytosol and inhibition of PEP carboxylase (1). </s></p></div3><div3><head rend="bold">Light (stages 2 and 3):</head><p n="p30.51"><s n="s1.5;p30.51">Malate is transported from the vacuole to the cytosol, by what is thought to be a passive, yet regulated process across the tonoplast by a yet unfound carrier (1). </s><s n="s2.5;p30.51">Diffusion is thought to only occur when the lowest vacuolar pH is reached at the end of the night, and sets an upper limit on the amount of malate that can be stored in the vacuole. </s><s n="s3.5;p30.51">It is then decarboxylated (phase 3) behind closed stomata (so water cannot be lost) creating a high internal CO <hi rend="sub">2</hi> concentration (about 1% compared to 0.03% in the atmosphere), which is close to and therefore reassimilated by Rubisco (13). </s><s n="s4.5;p30.51">The high CO <hi rend="sub">2</hi> concentration suppresses the oxygenase activity of Rubisco therefore greatly reduces photorespiration. </s><s n="s5.5;p30.51">CO <hi rend="sub">2</hi> is re-fixed in the Benson-Calvin cycle generating triose phosphate, which is then converted to sucrose or starch regenerating the original carbon acceptor (2). </s></p><table id="BAWE_0035b-tab.002"><head rend="italic">Figure 6. The four stages of gas exchange and CAM metabolism </head><row><cell/></row></table></div3></div2><div2><head rend="bold italic">Two groups</head><p n="p31.51"><s n="s1.4;p31.51">The catalyst of malate decarboxylation separates CAM plants into 2 groups, as shown in figure 7. </s><s n="s2.4;p31.51">The group does not seem to correspond with whether the plant stores starch or soluble sugars (1) and the precursor of these carbohydrates, triose phosphate is not converted equally to each carbohydrate type, but is influenced by the amount of glycerate-3-phosphate generated. </s><s n="s3.4;p31.51">High concentrations of glycerate-3-phosphate activate ADP-glucose pyrophosphorylase, which favours starch synthesis. </s><s n="s4.4;p31.51">The cell reserves are first restored, and carbohydrates for export are then synthesised. </s></p><table id="BAWE_0035b-tab.003"><head rend="italic">Figure 7 The two groups CAM plants</head><row><cell/></row></table></div2><div2><head rend="bold italic">Regulation</head><p n="p32.51"><s n="s1.4;p32.51">Regulation in CAM plants is important, as cycles of carboxylation and decarboxylation, and malate storage and release, can easily occur with no advantage to the plant at the cost of ATP. PEP carboxylase, Pyruvate kinase, and Pyruvate phosphate dikinase are three key enzymes that have to be regulated. </s><s n="s2.4;p32.51">PEP carboxylase is regulated so that when CO <hi rend="sub">2</hi> is released by malate decarboxylation it is not immediately refixed. </s><s n="s3.4;p32.51">Pyruvate kinase must be regulated in the dark so that it does not compete with PEP carboxylase for the available PEP and pyruvate phosphate dikinase is regulated by light and contributes to regulation in NAD(P)+-malic enzyme type plants (1). </s><s n="s4.4;p32.51">The regulation of PEP carboxylase and Rubisco is in time rather than space as they are found in all chloroplast containing cells; PEP carboxylase is active only in the dark, and Rubisco active only in the light. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold italic">Significance in relation to environment</head><p n="p33.51"><s n="s1.1;p33.51">CAM is very typical of plants in environments exposed to droughts such as semi-deserts, shallow soils or in the epiphytic environment in tropical forests (1) as it has the ability to minimise water loss. </s></p><p n="p34.51"><s n="s1.4;p34.51">The succulent property of many of these plants enables their survival as the large vacuoles and low surface area to volume ratio acts improves water storage. </s><s n="s2.4;p34.51">The water-use efficiency is also increased by the leaves taking in CO <hi rend="sub">2</hi> for fixation at night whilst the temperatures and vapour pressure deficit of the air compared to the leaf are much lower, therefore minimising transpiration. </s><s n="s3.4;p34.51">For example <hi rend="italic">Agave desertii</hi> has a water vapour concentration difference of 7 times greater at 20 <hi rend="sup">o</hi>C than 5 <hi rend="sup">o</hi>C (1). </s><s n="s4.4;p34.51">Anatomical features minimising water loss in CAM plants include think cuticles and reduced stomata size and frequency compared to C <hi rend="sub">3</hi> or C <hi rend="sub">4</hi> plants (3). </s></p><p n="p35.51"><s n="s1.2;p35.51">Thanks to the water conserving properties, CAM plants lose 50-100g of water per gram of CO <hi rend="sub">2</hi> gained, compared to 400-500g for C <hi rend="sub">3</hi> plants. </s><s n="s2.2;p35.51">C <hi rend="sub">4</hi> plants are better at water conservation than C <hi rend="sub">3</hi> plants losing 250-300g but CAM are by far the most efficient in this respect (2). </s></p><p n="p36.51"><s n="s1.6;p36.51">CAM plants are able to adjust their CO <hi rend="sub">2</hi> uptake according to the changing environmental conditions. </s><s n="s2.6;p36.51">For example the ice plant <hi rend="italic">Mesembryanthemum crystallinum</hi> can convert to CAM from C <hi rend="sub">3</hi> in response to stress signals such as heat, water or salt stress. </s><s n="s3.6;p36.51">This requires the regulation and expression of several CAM genes (18, 19). </s><s n="s4.6;p36.51">Other species are able to alter their metabolism to take in CO <hi rend="sub">2</hi> in the daytime if sufficient water is available to maximise carbon gain without forfeiting water. </s><s n="s5.6;p36.51">Many plants demonstrate facultative CAM, and all are C <hi rend="sub">3</hi> as seedlings. </s><s n="s6.6;p36.51">Some CAM plants, such as the Aizoaceae <hi rend="italic">, Mesembryanthemum crystallinum</hi> germinate in the early part of the year when water is plentiful, and CAM is onset in the dry seasons that follow (1). </s></p><p n="p37.51"><s n="s1.3;p37.51">Some CAM plants react to prolonged drought very severely, by sealing the stomata and shedding the roots. </s><s n="s2.3;p37.51">This prevents gas exchange, but the internal cycling of CO <hi rend="sub">2</hi> continues. </s><s n="s3.3;p37.51">In this state photoinhibition is prevented and the plant can respond immediately to water availability (2). </s></p><p n="p38.51"><s n="s1.3;p38.51">CAM is found in aquatic vascular plants, which is at first thought to be strange as they do not require water saving mechanisms. </s><s n="s2.3;p38.51">However this is because daytime CO <hi rend="sub">2</hi> availability (caused by water conserving closing of the stomata) becomes rate limiting for photosynthesis, caused either by high diffusional resistances limiting access to CO <hi rend="sub">2</hi> or competition from other species (13). </s><s n="s3.3;p38.51">This is a second similarity between most CAM plants. </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">Internal CO2 concentrating mechanism (CCM) </head><p n="p39.51"><s n="s1.2;p39.51">In cyanobacteria and microalgae, Rubisco has a particularly low affinity for CO <hi rend="sub">2,</hi> therefore operating far below its maximal specific activity (1) and the K <hi rend="sub">m</hi>(CO <hi rend="sub">2</hi>) can be greater than 200 µM, which is high compared to C <hi rend="sub">4</hi> plants. </s><s n="s2.2;p39.51">To increase the CO <hi rend="sub">2</hi> concentration at the site of Rubisco and to try to out compete the high levels of atmospheric O <hi rend="sub">2</hi>, they concentrate CO <hi rend="sub">2</hi> internally by the use of CO <hi rend="sub">2</hi> and HCO <hi rend="sub">3</hi>- pumps at the plasma membrane. </s></p><p n="p40.51"><s n="s1.2;p40.51">Microalgae cannot stop the CO <hi rend="sub">2</hi> escaping by thickened cell walls as C <hi rend="sub">4</hi> plants do as they consist of one to a few cells, each of which can easily access the environment. </s><s n="s2.2;p40.51">They need therefore to have cell walls that can prevent the leakage of CO <hi rend="sub">2</hi>, whist allowing the entry of other nutrients. </s></p><p n="p41.51"><s n="s1.6;p41.51">To do this, firstly these organisms accumulate HCO <hi rend="sub">3</hi>- (as well as CO <hi rend="sub">2</hi>) which being charged has a greater diffusion resistance and therefore diffuses out through the membranes more slowly than CO <hi rend="sub">2</hi>. </s><s n="s2.6;p41.51">The cells take up both CO <hi rend="sub">2</hi> and HCO <hi rend="sub">3</hi>- by active uptake driven by ATP derived from light reactions (2). </s><s n="s3.6;p41.51">The HCO <hi rend="sub">3</hi>- must be converted back to CO <hi rend="sub">2</hi> to be used as the substrate for Rubisco. </s><s n="s4.6;p41.51">It is thought that Rubisco is packaged into the cell at a specific location within the chloroplast of the cell, and the action of carbonic anhydrase then quickly generates higher CO <hi rend="sub">2</hi> levels from bicarbonate in the chloroplast than elsewhere, a process favoured in the plastid stroma alkaline conditions in the light. </s><s n="s5.6;p41.51">This has been observed by an increase in CA activity in multiple compartments upon induction of CCM. This specific chloroplast location is the pyrenoid, which is a structure specific to the chloroplasts of certain algae and hornworts (6). </s><s n="s6.6;p41.51">The CO <hi rend="sub">2</hi> can then be used by Rubisco and consequently the Calvin cycle, before it diffuses out of the cell or is out competed by O <hi rend="sub">2</hi> (4). </s></p><p n="p42.51"><s n="s1.2;p42.51">Secondly cyanobacteria and microalgae are effective at scavenging CO <hi rend="sub">2</hi> that is leaking out from both the chloroplast to the cytoplasm, and the cell to periplasmic space (6). </s><s n="s2.2;p42.51">It is thought that the peculiar internal structure of microalgae such as the localization of rubisco in the pyrenoid, the starch envelope and the concentric thylakoid membranes contribute to the effective CCM and low amount of CO <hi rend="sub">2</hi> loss (6). </s></p><p n="p43.51"><s n="s1.1;p43.51">The gene responsible for the transcription factor controlling this apparatus is only induced in low CO <hi rend="sub">2</hi> conditions so as not to be wasteful in the cells' energy by expressing genes that are not required (1). </s></p><p n="p44.51"><s n="s1.2;p44.51">The result of this CO <hi rend="sub">2</hi> concentration mechanism in low CO2 conditions for the cells is that oxygenation of Rubisco is suppressed and therefore so is photorespiration. </s><s n="s2.2;p44.51">It also costs the cell one extra ATP molecule (1). </s></p><div2><head rend="bold italic">Significance in relation to environment</head><p n="p45.51"><s n="s1.4;p45.51">Cyanobacteria are unicellular aquatic organisms of more than 3.5 billion years. </s><s n="s2.4;p45.51">Microalgae are the most primitive form of plants and are also aquatic organisms. </s><s n="s3.4;p45.51">Because they grow in aqueous suspension, they have more efficient access to water, CO <hi rend="sub">2</hi>, and other nutrients than non-aqueous plants. </s><s n="s4.4;p45.51">However the CO <hi rend="sub">2</hi> concentration in their environment is often low, making the internal CO <hi rend="sub">2</hi> concentrating mechanism vital for their survival. </s></p><p n="p46.51"><s n="s1.6;p46.51">Many environmental factors affect the capacity and activity of the CCM (7). </s><s n="s2.6;p46.51">The main constraints of the environment are DIC (dissolved inorganic carbon), light and temperature, but others such as pH, O <hi rend="sub">2</hi> and mineral nutrients are also important (9). </s><s n="s3.6;p46.51">Light is responsible for the energy required for transport, and along with the other parameters, in general when in short supply reduces the level of CO <hi rend="sub">2</hi> accumulation. </s><s n="s4.6;p46.51">It is not a simple process however, and the parameter supply to level of CO <hi rend="sub">2</hi> accumulation is not a linear relationship. </s><s n="s5.6;p46.51">The rate of supply and the form of some of the nutrients affects the interactions. </s><s n="s6.6;p46.51">High levels of CO <hi rend="sub">2</hi> or pH also have to ability to repress the CCM, so therefore there is an optimum condition. </s></p><p n="p47.51"><s n="s1.2;p47.51">These organisms are often characterised by low photosynthetic rates, low light requirements and high K <hi rend="sub">m</hi>(CO <hi rend="sub">2</hi>/HCO <hi rend="sub">3</hi>-) values, which are caused mainly by low DIC diffusion rates (9). </s><s n="s2.2;p47.51">They are also characteristics that enable the organisms to survive in the aquatic conditions, where the light is minimal, especially under surface growth. </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">Conclusion</head><p n="p48.51"><s n="s1.2;p48.51">It can be seen be looking at three major mechanisms how plants overcome the problem of Rubisco having a low affinity to CO <hi rend="sub">2</hi>, the competitor O <hi rend="sub">2</hi>, and the leakage of already accumulated CO <hi rend="sub">2</hi>. </s><s n="s2.2;p48.51">All three of the mechanisms work to concentrate CO <hi rend="sub">2</hi> at the site of Rubisco in slightly different ways, and it can be concluded that the mechanism varies according to the environment in which they live, and that further variations exist within each type discussed. </s></p><p n="p49.51"><s n="s1.4;p49.51">The structure is vital to each type of mechanism. </s><s n="s2.4;p49.51">In C <hi rend="sub">4</hi> plants spatial separation of the enzymes is used, enabled by the complex Kranz anatomy. </s><s n="s3.4;p49.51">CAM plants have features supporting the mechanism but they not as characterised as Kranz anatomy. </s><s n="s4.4;p49.51">Algal and cyanobacterial cells are yet more simplistic in structure, but the plasma membrane pumps and unique chloroplast structure are vital for the mechanism to exist. </s></p><p n="p50.51"><s n="s1.2;p50.51">C <hi rend="sub">4</hi> and CAM plants have evolved independently in a vast range of species indicating that it has been vital for the survival in the changing atmospheric conditions through evolution. </s><s n="s2.2;p50.51">The internal concentration of CO <hi rend="sub">2</hi> is present in a narrower range of species. </s></p><p n="p51.51"><s n="s1.2;p51.51">Each of the processes exists in a specific environment, C <hi rend="sub">4</hi> in hot dry environments, CAM in areas of drought, and internal concentration of CO <hi rend="sub">2</hi> in aquatic organisms. </s><s n="s2.2;p51.51">CAM plants and algal and cyanobacterial cells can exploit times when the environment is not as harsh by the turning on and off of the CO <hi rend="sub">2</hi> concentrating mechanisms. </s></p></div1></body><back><div1 type="bibliography"><head rend="underlined bold">References</head><div2 type="bibliography"><p>1.</p><p>Leegood, R.C. (1999) Carbon Dioxide - concentrating mechanisms: C<hi rend="sub">4</hi> photosynthesisand Crassulacean acid metabolism. <hi rend="italic">Plant Biochemistry and Molecular Biology</hi>. Lee and Leegood eds. Wiley</p><p>2.</p><p>Taitz and Zeiger. <hi rend="italic">Plant Physiology</hi> 3<hi rend="sup">rd</hi> ed, Sinauer (2002)</p><p>3.</p><p>Lara, M V., Casati, P. and Andreo, C.S. (2002) CO<hi rend="sub">2</hi>-concentrating mechanisms in <hi rend="italic">Egeria densa</hi>, a submersed aquatic plant. <hi rend="italic">Physiologia Plantarum</hi><hi rend="bold"> 115,</hi> 487-495.</p><p>4.</p><p>Moroney, J. V., and Somanchi, A. (1999) How Do Algae Concentrate CO2 to Increase the Efficiency of Photosynthetic Carbon Fixation? Plant Physiology, <hi rend="bold">119</hi>, 9-16</p><p>5.</p><p>Magnin, N. C., Cooley, B. A., Reiskind J. B. and Bowes, G. (1981-1989) Regulation and Localization of Key Enzymes during the Induction of Kranz-Less, C4-Type Photosynthesis in Hydrilla verticillata. <hi rend="italic">Plant Physiology </hi><hi rend="bold">115</hi>, 1681-1689.</p><p>6.</p><p>Fridlyand L.E. (1997) Models of CO<hi rend="sub">2</hi> concentrating mechanisms in microalgae taking into account cell and chloroplast structure. <hi rend="italic">Biosystems </hi><hi rend="bold">44</hi>, 41-57</p><p>7.</p><p>Beardall, J., Johnston, A., and Raven, J. (1998) <hi rend="bold">Environmental</hi> regulation of CO<hi rend="sub">2</hi>-concentrating mechanisms in microalgae. <hi rend="italic">Canadian Journal of Botany </hi><hi rend="bold">76</hi>, 1010-1017 </p><p>8.</p><p>Dai, Z., Ku, MSB., and Edwards G. E. (1993) C4 Photosynthesis (The CO2-Concentrating Mechanism and Photorespiration). <hi rend="italic">Plant Physiology </hi><hi rend="bold">103</hi> 83-90 </p><p>9.</p><p>Bowes, G., Salvucci, M. E. (1989) Plasticity in the photosynthetic carbon metabolism of submersed aquatic macrophytes. <hi rend="italic">Aquatic Botany </hi><hi rend="bold">34</hi> 233-266</p><p>10.</p><p>Aizawa, K. and Miyachi, S., 1986. Carbonic anhydrase and CO<hi rend="sub">2</hi> concentrating mechanisms in microalgae and cyanobacteria. <hi rend="italic">Federation of European Microbiological Societies. Rev. </hi><hi rend="bold">39</hi>, 215 - 233. Cited in (6).</p><p>11.</p><p>Xiang, Y., Zhang, J., and Weeks, D.P. (2001). The <hi rend="italic">Cia5</hi> gene controls formation of the carbon concentrating mechanism in <hi rend="italic">Chlamydomonas reinhardtii</hi>. <hi rend="italic">Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences </hi><hi rend="bold">98,</hi> 5341 - 5346. Cited in (6)</p><p>12.</p><p>Leegood, R.C. (2002) C<hi rend="sub">4</hi> photosynthesis: principles of CO<hi rend="sub">2</hi> concentration and prospects for its introduction into C<hi rend="sub">3</hi> plants. <hi rend="italic">Journal of Experimental Botany</hi>. <hi rend="bold">53</hi>, 581-590 </p><p>13. Cushman J. C. (2001) Crassulacean Acid Metabolism. A Plastic Photosynthetic Adaptation to Arid Environments. <hi rend="italic">Plant Physiology</hi><hi rend="bold"> 127,</hi> 1439-1448</p><p>14.</p><p>Figure taken from University of Newcastle web page.</p><p><seg type="URL" n="www.ncl.ac.uk"/></p><p>Project "Investigating the effects of oxidative stress on the facultative CAM plant <hi rend="italic">Mesembryanthemum crystallinum</hi>." By Stewart Elliott</p><p>15.</p><p>Rowley G (1978) The Illustrated Encyclopedia of Succulents. Salamander, London. Cited in (13).</p><p>16.</p><p>de Saussure, T. (1804) Recherches chimiques sur la végétation. Chez la V.<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Nyon, Paris. Cited in (13).</p><p>17.</p><p>Heyne, B. (1815) On the deoxidation of the leaves of <hi rend="italic">Coltyledon calycina</hi>. Trans Linn Soc Lond <hi rend="bold">11:</hi> 213-215. Cited in (13).</p><p>18.</p><p>Adams P, Nelson DE, Yamada S, Chmara W, Jensen RG, Bohnert HJ, Girffiths H (1998) Tansley Review No. 97 - Growth and development of Mesembryanthemum crysallinum (Aizoaceae). <hi rend="italic">New Phytologist </hi><hi rend="bold">138</hi>: 171-19. Cited in (2)</p><p>19.</p><p>Cushman, J. C. (2001) Crassulacean Acid Metabolism. A Plastic Photosynthetic Adaptation to Arid Environments. <hi rend="italic">Plant Physiology </hi><hi rend="bold">127:</hi> 1439-1448. Cited in (2)</p><p>20.</p><p><seg type="URL" n="http://gemini.oscs.montana.edu/~mlavin/b434/graphic/Leafc4m.jpg"/></p></div2><div2 type="bibliography"><head rend="underlined bold">General Sources</head><p>Leegood, R.C. (1999) Carbon Dioxide - concentrating mechanisms: C<hi rend="sub">4</hi> photosynthesisand Crassulacean acid metabolism. <hi rend="italic">Plant Biochemistry and Molecular Biology</hi>. Lee and Leegood eds. Wiley</p><p>Taitz and Zeiger. <hi rend="italic">Plant Physiology</hi> 3<hi rend="sup">rd</hi> ed, Sinauer (2002)</p></div2></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
