<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_0039e" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Was European Imperialism a violation or an integral component of liberal ideology?</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">deleted: header: course and student name; footer: page numbers
deleted: Word Count: 1,649
</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">1</p><p n="date">2003-11</p><p n="module title">Making of the Modern World</p><p n="module code">HI153</p><p n="genre family">Essay</p><p n="discipline">History</p><p n="disciplinary group">AH</p><p n="grade">M</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">1636</p><p n="number of s-units">43</p><p n="number of p">7</p><p n="number of tables">0</p><p n="number of figures">0</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">0</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">0</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">38.0</p><p n="average s-units per p">6.1</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">m</p><p n="year of birth">1985</p><p n="first language">English</p><p n="education">UKA</p><p n="course">History &amp; Politics</p><p n="student ID">0039</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><docTitle><titlePart rend="underlined bold">Was European Imperialism a violation or an integral component of liberal ideology? </titlePart></docTitle></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="section"><p n="p1.7"><s n="s1.7;p1.7">European imperialism in the pre-World War era appears aggressive, coercive and plainly exploitative. </s><s n="s2.7;p1.7">Indeed, it seems antithetical to liberalism that is embedded on the principles of self-determination, autonomy and individual freedom. </s><s n="s3.7;p1.7">However, this incongruity between nineteenth century European metropolitan theory and non-European colonialisation has been accurately accounted for by neo-Marxists such as Lenin. </s><s n="s4.7;p1.7">The 'Highest stage of capitalism'<ref target="BAWE_0039e-ftnote.001"/> theory emphasises that the annexation of exotic territory was influenced purely by economic needs, as imperialism was essential for the very survival of capitalism; the acquisition of materials such as rubber, copper, sugar, tea and diamonds would elevate the income of the rising bourgeois and the proletariat and keep domestic public discontent down to a minimum, an idea amplified by advocates of the social imperialism theory. </s><s n="s5.7;p1.7">Interestingly, this interpretation is suggestive of a crucial point: that imperialism is not a direct contradiction of liberalism but liberalism itself is paradoxical. </s><s n="s6.7;p1.7">As Raymond Williams highlights, it is a 'doctrine based on individualist theories of man and society'<ref target="BAWE_0039e-ftnote.002"/> and thus implies that individuals are politically equal, but have the freedom to be economically dissimilar; theoretically, a strange blend of universality and differentiation. </s><s n="s7.7;p1.7">This mixture is also the bedrock of imperialism; the phenomena was not just driven by economic self-interest, as Marxist interpretations would lead us to believe, but also by ideology that intended to 'provide the natives with the guarantees essential to the good distribution of justice and lead them prudently and consistently to a higher level of civilisation'<ref target="BAWE_0039e-ftnote.003"/>. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0039e-ftnote.001"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">V.I.Lenin, <hi rend="italic">Imperialism: The Highest Stage of Capitalism: A popular outline</hi>, (13th edn., Moscow, 1966) </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0039e-ftnote.002"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Raymond Williams, <hi rend="italic">Keywords: A vocabulary of culture and society</hi>, (Great Britain, 1976), p.181. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0039e-ftnote.003"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">A.P. Ansom, <hi rend="italic">Note Pour le Ministre</hi>, Letter written 15 July 1903. </s></p></note><p n="p2.7"><s n="s1.6;p2.7">This universalism, in the form of importing <hi rend="italic">liberte</hi>, <hi rend="italic">egalite</hi> and <hi rend="italic">fraternite</hi>, combined with racialism, in the sense that the French believed they had a right to adopt coercive and violent measures against the colonised for the sake of manufacturing a liberal society simply because they perceived themselves to be morally and materialistically superior, is criticised by Alice Conklin, who exemplifies Frances's <hi rend="italic">mission civillastrice</hi> in West Africa. </s><s n="s2.6;p2.7">She shows that although the French abolished the slave trade in 1905, introduced the <hi rend="italic">politique des races</hi> between 1908 and 1914- an exhaustive attempt to attack the 'continuing institution of aristocratic rule in the form of hereditary chiefs'<ref target="BAWE_0039e-ftnote.004"/>- and established an education system which all Africans could infiltrate, not just children of the old elite, so 'a society in which careers would be... open to talent rather than based on privilege'<ref target="BAWE_0039e-ftnote.005"/> would be created, they failed to follow these principles themselves. </s><s n="s3.6;p2.7">Fascinatingly, all West Africans were treated as subjects and not citizens, although France was viciously anti-monarchical. </s><s n="s4.6;p2.7">Notably, France concealed this by passing the 1907 naturalisation law which allowed worthy natives to rise to equal citizenship with the French; accordingly, this diverted attention from the large majority that actually remained subjects. </s><s n="s5.6;p2.7">Disguise was also used by the British who 'displayed submissive maharajahs in jewelled robes- freely loyal rather than captive'<ref target="BAWE_0039e-ftnote.006"/> at royal jubilees and coronations. </s><s n="s6.6;p2.7">Apparently, supposed liberal ends justified illiberal imperial practices and resultantly the colonisers 'managed to obscure the fundamental contradiction between democracy and the forcible acquisition of an empire'<ref target="BAWE_0039e-ftnote.007"/>. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0039e-ftnote.004"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Alice L.Conklin, 'Colonialism and human rights, a contradiction in terms? </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">The case of France and West Africa, 1875-1914', <hi rend="italic">American Historical Review</hi>, 103 (1998), p.426. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0039e-ftnote.005"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Conklin, 'Colonialism and human rights', p. 430. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0039e-ftnote.006"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Eric Hobsbawm, <hi rend="italic">The Age of Empire, 1875-1914</hi>, (England, 1987), p. 71. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0039e-ftnote.007"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Alice L. Conklin, <hi rend="italic">A mission to civilize: The Republican Idea of Empire in France and West Africa, 1895-1930</hi>, (USA, 1997), p. 2. </s></p></note><p n="p3.7"><s n="s1.3;p3.7">However, the detachment of imperialism with liberalism denies firstly that civilisation was not seen as a peaceful construction born from the willingness and education of Africans, and secondly that the beginning of superior Europe was 'characterised by struggle, conflict, and crisis'<ref target="BAWE_0039e-ftnote.008"/>. </s><s n="s2.3;p3.7">Significantly, Hardt and Negri elevate the paradox of liberal ideology: 'A contradiction that runs throughout European modernity...the immanent forces of desire and association, the love of the community, and on the other, the strong hand of an overarching authority that imposes and enforces an order on the social field'<ref target="BAWE_0039e-ftnote.009"/>. </s><s n="s3.3;p3.7">Chiefly, just as an enlightened and educated few had to guide the French masses in the post-Revolution period to ensure an 'achieved condition of refinement and order'<ref target="BAWE_0039e-ftnote.010"/>, namely civilisation, the European superpowers now perceived themselves as having a duty to elevate the backward and irrational natives to a higher standard of living: 'Colonial subjects...were not just barbarians, they were barbarians capable of, and in the process of receiving, civilisation understood in the most democratic and universal sense'<ref target="BAWE_0039e-ftnote.011"/>. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0039e-ftnote.008"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Michael Hardt and Antonio Negri, <hi rend="italic">Empire</hi>, (USA, 2000), p.70. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0039e-ftnote.009"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Hardt and Negri, <hi rend="italic">Empire</hi>, p.69. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0039e-ftnote.010"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Williams, <hi rend="italic">Keywords</hi>, p.58. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0039e-ftnote.011"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Conklin, 'Colonialism and human rights', p.433. </s></p></note><p n="p4.7"><s n="s1.6;p4.7">But, illiberal means to a liberal end being central to European liberalism is questionable as in the 1906 British general election, the Liberal Party in Britain achieved a landslide victory principally because of its anti-imperialistic message: it was against the existence of Chinese slavery in South Africa. </s><s n="s2.6;p4.7">Moreover, liberal philosopher J.A. Hobson condemned imperialism, believing a minority of business elites who perverted true capitalism and exercised illegitimate and undemocratic influence over government and mass opinion controlled it<ref target="BAWE_0039e-ftnote.012"/>. </s><s n="s3.6;p4.7">This is exemplified by the fact that approximately forty-five percent of Britain's cotton exports went to India; a plausible reason for creating formal colonies- namely Egypt and South Africa- which would guarantee trade access to the 'the brightest jewel in the imperial crown'<ref target="BAWE_0039e-ftnote.013"/>. </s><s n="s4.6;p4.7">Additionally, Schumpeter detached imperialism from liberalism, offering an alternative interpretation of it being a feature of the old pre-capitalist autocratic and militaristic elite trying to hold on to some form of influence by flying the imperialist flag with liberal colours<ref target="BAWE_0039e-ftnote.014"/>. </s><s n="s5.6;p4.7">Nevertheless, Hobson and Schumpeter seem to deny that nineteenth-century classical liberalism is a two-headed monster; an inherent part of the ideology is uncontrolled economic advancement and the establishment of an authority that guarantees security. </s><s n="s6.6;p4.7">Indeed, 'the anarchic organisation of the international system of states'<ref target="BAWE_0039e-ftnote.015"/> was repaired by the epoch of empire between 1875 and 1914. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0039e-ftnote.012"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Bernard Porter, <hi rend="italic">Critics of Empire: British radical attitudes to colonialism in Africa, 1895-1914</hi>, (London, 1968), p.258. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0039e-ftnote.013"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Hobsbawm, <hi rend="italic">The Age of Empire</hi>, p.69. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0039e-ftnote.014"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Norman Etherington, <hi rend="italic">Theories of Imperialism.</hi> </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1"><hi rend="italic">War, Conquest and Capital</hi>, (Beckenham, 1984), p.58. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0039e-ftnote.015"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Benjamin Cohen, <hi rend="italic">The Question of Imperialism: The Political Economy of Dominance and Dependence</hi>, (New York and London, 1974), p.245. </s></p></note><p n="p5.7"><s n="s1.8;p5.7">The notion that imperialism is a perversion of liberalism is elaborated by the observations of Eric Hobsbawm; the impulse for imperialism, the very act of imperialism itself, and the intended outcome were far from being liberal, apart from in an economic sense. </s><s n="s2.8;p5.7">Certainly, Australia, New Zealand and Argentina all had developed labour and radical democratic parties and systems of public social welfare and security before any of the European superpowers. </s><s n="s3.8;p5.7">Furthermore, the New Colonialism of the latter part of the nineteenth century was mainly a 'by-product of an era of economic and political rivalry between competing national economies'<ref target="BAWE_0039e-ftnote.016"/>; the acquisition of colonies became a status symbol and declaration of power- surely, Italy did not have liberal tendencies when it conquered undesirable stretches of African desert and mountain- and also often a disguise for militaristic and demographic inferiority, as was the case with France. </s><s n="s4.8;p5.7">This search for supremacy also explains the fact that racism was rampant in the metropolis: Italian workers called strike-breakers <hi rend="italic">crumiri</hi>, after a North African tribe, and the French called criminal gangs <hi rend="italic">Caids</hi>, originally the name of indigenous chiefs. </s><s n="s5.8;p5.7">Ultimately, this shows that imperialism was merely a last struggle by government to achieve some degree of rule as their own countries slipped into the unconquerable system of democracy where all member of societies were treated as equal, confirmed by the mounting consideration and eventual implementation of universal male franchise in 1918. </s><s n="s6.8;p5.7">The view of imperialism being utterly illiberal and demonstrative of pre-democratic practices, for the French even mirroring the conduct of the detested <hi rend="italic">ancien regime</hi>, is substantiated by the fear amongst some imperialists of colonial self-rule: 'Europe will shift the burden of physical toil...on to the coloured races, and itself be content with the role of rentier, and this way... pave the way for the economic and...political emancipation of the coloured races'<ref target="BAWE_0039e-ftnote.017"/>. </s><s n="s7.8;p5.7">This is demonstrated in the Irish campaign for self-rule, a country that is seemingly educated, civilised and Western enough to govern themselves; the Conservative and Irish Unionist Party opposed the proposal staunchly between 1910 and 1913, even at the cost of igniting civil war. </s><s n="s8.8;p5.7">To Hobsbawm, the creation of liberal institutions in the colonies was merely a clever 'rationalisation of empire'<ref target="BAWE_0039e-ftnote.018"/> and a deterrent of the real, unimpeded liberation of the subjugated natives. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0039e-ftnote.016"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Hobsbawm, <hi rend="italic">The Age of Empire</hi>, p.76. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0039e-ftnote.017"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">H.G.V.Schulze-Gaevernitiz, <hi rend="italic">Britischer Imperialismus und englischer Freihandel zu Beginn des 20.</hi> </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1"><hi rend="italic">Jahrunderts</hi>, (Leipzig, 1906) </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0039e-ftnote.018"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Conklin, 'Colonialism and human rights', p.421. </s></p></note><p n="p6.7"><s n="s1.6;p6.7">However, this interpretation denies the expensive and exhaustive attempt of the colonisers to improve their colonies economically and socially. </s><s n="s2.6;p6.7">In 1870, for example, there was two hundred thousand kilometres of railway worldwide. </s><s n="s3.6;p6.7">By 1914, there was just over one million. </s><s n="s4.6;p6.7">India flourished because of this: by 1913, it was second only to Britain in the world as a supplier of cotton yarn<ref target="BAWE_0039e-ftnote.019"/>, and because of the development of a 'sensitive inter-regional crop failure grain trade'<ref target="BAWE_0039e-ftnote.020"/>, the United Provinces of Northern India, for example, was able to import roughly 725, 000 tons of grain to lessen the catastrophic effects of a severe famine in 1907. </s><s n="s5.6;p6.7">Moreover, in West Africa, the French eradicated only four traditional African institutions: indigenous languages, slavery, barbaric customary law and feudal chieftaincies<ref target="BAWE_0039e-ftnote.021"/>. </s><s n="s6.6;p6.7">Unquestionably, to claim that imperialism was not rooted by any degree of social liberal theory, but instead solely on the seeking of power and increase in material, is to neglect the genuine post-Enlightenment humanitarian urge to intervene beyond Europe to better the circumstances of non-Europeans<ref target="BAWE_0039e-ftnote.022"/>. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0039e-ftnote.019"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">B.R.Tomlinson, <hi rend="italic">The political economy of the Raj, 1914-1947</hi>, (London, 1979), p.1. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0039e-ftnote.020"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">I.D.Derbyshire, 'Economic change and the Railways in North India, 1860-1914', <hi rend="italic">Modern Asian Studies</hi>, vol.21, issue 3, (1987), p.539. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0039e-ftnote.021"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Conklin, <hi rend="italic">A mission to civilize</hi>, p.6. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0039e-ftnote.022"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Andrew Porter, <hi rend="italic">European Imperialism, 1860-1914</hi>, (Malaysia, 1994), p.20. </s></p></note><p n="p7.7"><s n="s1.7;p7.7">To adopt a wholly cynical, Marxist view of imperialism- that there is an immediate link between monopoly capitalism and colonialism<ref target="BAWE_0039e-ftnote.023"/>- is to still agree that the phenomenon is a branch of economic liberalism. </s><s n="s2.7;p7.7">However, this rejects an additional dimension to imperialism that perhaps makes formal imperialism more liberal then informal imperialism, which is conventionally thought of as the symbol of 'the free-trading and freely competing liberal world of the mid-century'<ref target="BAWE_0039e-ftnote.024"/>: the creation of a wider society based on the principles of equality, individual freedom and rational not backward or supernatural thought. </s><s n="s3.7;p7.7">Just as informal imperialism is regarded as the economic high point of capitalism, formal imperialism was the high point of social universalism. </s><s n="s4.7;p7.7">Here, we have met the crux of this argument: that universal civilisation and equality, according to imperialists, was a manufactured state, not a natural one. </s><s n="s5.7;p7.7">The colonisers, therefore, had a right to ensure the natives attained a higher state of society through undemocratic and often violent methods. </s><s n="s6.7;p7.7">It is a contemporary fashion to be sceptical of imperialism if you believe in such liberal values as human rights, autonomy and freedom. </s><s n="s7.7;p7.7">But one must examine more closely the contradictory nature of liberalism in the nineteenth century to understand why imperialism originated from and was part of this ideology. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0039e-ftnote.023"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Anthony Brewer, <hi rend="italic">Marxist Theories of Imperialism; A critical survey</hi>, (2nd edn., England, 1990), p.1-9. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0039e-ftnote.024"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Hobsbawm, <hi rend="italic">The Age of Empire</hi>, p.59. </s></p></note></div1></body><back><div1 type="bibliography"><head rend="underlined bold">Bibliography and Word Count</head><p>Ansom, A.P., <hi rend="italic">Note Pour le Ministre</hi>, Letter written 15 July 1903.</p><p>Brewer, Anthony, <hi rend="italic">Marxist Theories of Imperialism; A critical survey</hi>, (2<hi rend="sup">nd</hi> edn., England, 1990)</p><p>Cohen, Benjamin, <hi rend="italic">The Question of Imperialism: The Political Economy of Dominance and Dependence</hi>, (New York and London, 1974)</p><p>Conklin, Alice L., <hi rend="italic">A mission to civilize: The Republican Idea of Empire in France and West Africa, 1895-1930</hi>, (USA, 1997)</p><p>Conklin, Alice L., 'Colonialism and human rights, a contradiction in terms? The case of France and West Africa, 1875-1914', <hi rend="italic">American Historical Review</hi>, 103 (1998), pp.419-442.</p><p>Derbyshire, I.D. 'Economic change and the Railways in North India, 1860-1914', <hi rend="italic">Modern Asian Studies</hi>, vol.21, issue 3, (1987), pp.521-545.</p><p>Etherington, Norman, <hi rend="italic">Theories of Imperialism. War, Conquest and Capital</hi>, (Beckenham, 1984)</p><p>Hardt, Michael and Negri, Antonio, <hi rend="italic">Empire</hi>, (USA, 2000)</p><p>Hobsbawm, Eric, <hi rend="italic">The Age of Empire, 1875-1914</hi>, (England, 1987)</p><p>Lenin, V.I., <hi rend="italic">Imperialism: The Highest Stage of Capitalism: A popular outline</hi>, (13<hi rend="sup">th</hi> edn., Moscow, 1966)</p><p>Porter, Andrew, <hi rend="italic">European Imperialism, 1860-1914</hi>, (Malaysia, 1994),</p><p>Porter, Bernard, <hi rend="italic">Critics of Empire: British radical attitudes to colonialism in Africa, 1895-1914</hi>, (London, 1968)</p><p>Schulze-Gaevernitiz, H.G.V., <hi rend="italic">Britischer Imperialismus und englischer Freihandel zu Beginn des 20. Jahrunderts</hi>, (Leipzig, 1906)</p><p>Tomlinson, B.R., <hi rend="italic">The political economy of the Raj, 1914-1947</hi>, (London, 1979)</p><p>Williams, Raymond, <hi rend="italic">Keywords: A vocabulary of culture and society</hi>, (Great Britain, 1976)</p></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
