<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_0039a" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>How successfully did the Church impose its moral values on society in the period 1560-1640?</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">deleted: module, assignment and student name
deleted: Number of words:	1,980</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">2</p><p n="date">2004-12</p><p n="module title">Social History of England, 1500-1700</p><p n="module code">HI209</p><p n="genre family">Essay</p><p n="discipline">History</p><p n="disciplinary group">AH</p><p n="grade">M</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">1863</p><p n="number of s-units">56</p><p n="number of p">8</p><p n="number of tables">0</p><p n="number of figures">0</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">0</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">0</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">33.3</p><p n="average s-units per p">7.0</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">m</p><p n="year of birth">1985</p><p n="first language">English</p><p n="education">UKA</p><p n="course">History &amp; Politics</p><p n="student ID">0039</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><docTitle><titlePart rend="underlined bold">How successfully did the Church impose its moral values on society in the period 1560-1640? </titlePart></docTitle></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="section"><p n="p1.8"><s n="s1.11;p1.8">During the transformation from the Elizabethan times to the early Stuart era, the Church of England increasingly intervened in society; supposedly, this prompted a greater compliance to its moral values. </s><s n="s2.11;p1.8">A range of sources, particularly the records of the ecclesiastical courts, indicate that a better educated and more godly ministry, alongside newly found grammar schools that inculcated "right religion in the young"<ref target="BAWE_0039a-ftnote.001"/>, were ostensibly triumphant at elevating moral standards. </s><s n="s3.11;p1.8">For example, the medium-sized rural parish of Terling, the changes it went through allegedly a representation of "national or even supra-national developments"<ref target="BAWE_0039a-ftnote.002"/>, had an infant illegitimacy ratio of nine percent in the first decade of the seventeenth century; by the 1630s, this had reduced to only two percent<ref target="BAWE_0039a-ftnote.003"/>. </s><s n="s4.11;p1.8">Nevertheless, the records historians utilise to measure the effect of the Church on everyday lives are limited; they may show an increase in moral standards, but fail to signify the motives for conformity. </s><s n="s5.11;p1.8">Villagers may have displayed compliance to the Church- three in four attending the 1603 Easter communion in the diocese of Lincoln<ref target="BAWE_0039a-ftnote.004"/>- but probably for alternative reasons to religious conviction, such as avoidance of punishment like "fines, whipping, or imprisonment in the house of correction"<ref target="BAWE_0039a-ftnote.005"/>. </s><s n="s6.11;p1.8">Whether you believed the new ideas of the reformed church or not, conforming just to avoid publicly apologising to the whole parish in a white gown, holding a white candle, seems a prudent decision. </s><s n="s7.11;p1.8">Reports of churchwardens on their parishes are another unreliable source; a conclusion of <hi rend="italic">omnia bene</hi> ('all is well') is normally reached, probably in an attempt to show that the job is being done properly. </s><s n="s8.11;p1.8">This is clearly a distortion of actuality, as proved by the activities the young of the parishes engaged in; they were notoriously promiscuous, Keith Thomas highlighting the attractiveness of bachelors to adopt "the role of seducer"<ref target="BAWE_0039a-ftnote.006"/>. </s><s n="s9.11;p1.8">From this, one could articulate the notion that the Church was only able to penetrate a narrow strand of society: the elderly and the literate- the latter because Protestantism was primarily concerned with the words of the Bible. </s><s n="s10.11;p1.8">Nevertheless, even the orthodoxy of this narrow band of society was more than likely motivated by the need to maintain their status- they could not "afford to remain excommunicate from one Easter to the next"<ref target="BAWE_0039a-ftnote.007"/>- and convince workers that "idleness and waste"<ref target="BAWE_0039a-ftnote.008"/> in the alehouse, truthfully bad for productivity, was irreligious. </s><s n="s11.11;p1.8">Consequently, this essay will argue that only a relatively small number of people progressively conformed to the moral values of the Church in this period; yet their reasons were mostly different to deep conviction in what the Church was amplifying. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0039a-ftnote.001"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">J.A.Sharpe (ed.), <hi rend="italic">Early Modern England: A Social History 1550-1760</hi> (New York, 1997), 2, p.246. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0039a-ftnote.002"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Martin Ingram, 'Religion, Communities and Moral Discipline in Late Sixteenth and Early Seventeenth-Century England', in K.Von Greyerz (ed.), <hi rend="italic">Religion and Society in Early Modern Europe</hi> (London, 1984), p.177. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0039a-ftnote.003"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid., pp.177-193. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0039a-ftnote.004"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Judith Maltby, <hi rend="italic">Prayer Book and People in Elizabethan and Early Stuart England</hi> (Cambridge, 1998), p.32. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0039a-ftnote.005"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Keith Wrightson and David Levine, <hi rend="italic">Poverty and Piety in an English Village: Terling, 1525-1700</hi> (New York, 1979), p.113. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0039a-ftnote.006"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Keith Thomas, 'The Double Standard', <hi rend="italic">Journal of the History of Ideas</hi>, 20 (1959), p.196. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0039a-ftnote.007"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Patrick Collinson, <hi rend="italic">The Religion of Protestants: The Church in English Society 1559-1625</hi> (Oxford, 1982), p.228. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0039a-ftnote.008"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ingram, 'Religion, Communities and Moral Discipline', p.180. </s></p></note><p n="p2.8"><s n="s1.8;p2.8">The efforts made to assert the dominance of Anglicanism in England- notably the demands by Archbishop Grindal of York that "the Churchwardens shall see that in their churches and chapels all altars be utterly taken down, and clean removed even unto the foundations"<ref target="BAWE_0039a-ftnote.009"/>- were often so meticulous and overpowering that parishes were converted into eager supporters of Church principles. </s><s n="s2.8;p2.8">Certainly, the growth of prosecutions by the laity against non-conforming ministers illustrates this. </s><s n="s3.8;p2.8">In particularly fervent villages, there were complaints against clergymen who did not read prayers at the usual time and those who deliberately delayed the ringing of the bell signifying the beginning of a prayer reading- this being emblematic of a vicar with Catholic tendencies, as they were obviously trying to sabotage common prayers, preferring the traditional stratified readings. </s><s n="s4.8;p2.8">Interestingly, J.A.Sharpe has argued that a non-conforming clergy surely emblemises the lack of control the Church had over local parishes. </s><s n="s5.8;p2.8">Indeed, Lancashire was reported to have only six of twenty-five justices favourable of the established church in 1564<ref target="BAWE_0039a-ftnote.010"/>. </s><s n="s6.8;p2.8">How can people be even aware of the central Church's moral values when their ministers were overwhelmingly non-Protestant? </s><s n="s7.8;p2.8">Nonetheless, measuring the conformity of the clergy does not give a full indication of how successful the church was; they are people more likely to maintain their beliefs whatever social controls are imposed upon them. </s><s n="s8.8;p2.8">Focusing on the laity, however, and their high levels of conformity, apparently symbolises the triumph of the Church in permeating society at a local level. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0039a-ftnote.009"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Edmund Grindal, 'Iniunctions given by the most reuerende father in Christ, Edmund Grindal in his metropoliticall visitation of the prouince of York' (London, 1571) in David Cressy and Lori Anne Ferrell (eds.) <hi rend="italic">Religion and Society in Early Modern England: A Sourcebook</hi> (London, 1996), p.91. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0039a-ftnote.010"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Sharpe (ed.), <hi rend="italic">Early Modern England</hi>, pp.241-242. </s></p></note><p n="p3.8"><s n="s1.4;p3.8">Interestingly, some parishes campaigned for a rise in the number of services throughout the week and, in Lincoln particularly, for proper observance of saint's days. </s><s n="s2.4;p3.8">Unquestionably, there was a deep commitment to the Book of Common Prayer; contrary to the beliefs of Martin Ingram who highlights that support of the Established church was possibly for ulterior motives such as guaranteeing the poor were using their time productively, the willingness of people to engage in "time consuming"<ref target="BAWE_0039a-ftnote.011"/> battles to settle disputes with rebellious ministers shows a society deeply dedicated to the values advanced by the Church. </s><s n="s3.4;p3.8">Furthermore, the conception that Protestantism only really affected the literate, privileged classes is disproved by the broad cross-section of society, "from a 'Mr' Thockmorton to the labourer Margaret Gates"<ref target="BAWE_0039a-ftnote.012"/>, that criticised non-conforming ministers; out of the thirteen parishioners who denounced Anthony Armitage of Ellington, two were labourers- one of them a women- and eight made only marks, a possible indication of illiteracy, when signing the denunciation document<ref target="BAWE_0039a-ftnote.013"/>. </s><s n="s4.4;p3.8">Indisputably, empirical evidence indicates that the church not only victoriously imposed its values on, but also indoctrinated, a diverse range of society: "Conformity had a fairly wide appeal socially and drew supporters from both the humble and the substantial"<ref target="BAWE_0039a-ftnote.014"/>. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0039a-ftnote.011"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Maltby, <hi rend="italic">Prayer Book and People</hi>, p.45. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0039a-ftnote.012"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid., p.44. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0039a-ftnote.013"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid., p.80. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0039a-ftnote.014"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid., p.80. </s></p></note><p n="p4.8"><s n="s1.5;p4.8">Nevertheless, these examples of staunch moral values amongst a wide range of people were questionably isolated occurrences, rather than a general trend. </s><s n="s2.5;p4.8">Indeed, the research of Judith Maltby, which amplifies the eagerness of people to have proper church conduct, is restricted to the study of only a handful of parishes. </s><s n="s3.5;p4.8">Elsewhere, people were debatably unaffected; conservative villagers were sceptical to the new ideas of the church, as it was a "challenge to the traditional, less austere, system of belief"<ref target="BAWE_0039a-ftnote.015"/>. </s><s n="s4.5;p4.8">Excluding specific hotspots of religious observance such as Fenstanton and Hilton in Huntingdonshire, spreading God's word was difficult to organise, since educated clergymen were not attracted by the low wages of working in parishes. </s><s n="s5.5;p4.8">Thus, early modern England was a patchwork of religious conformity, the church varying in its success on imposing moral values depending on the village, consequently equalling- by the second half of the sixteenth century- a "half-Christianised"<ref target="BAWE_0039a-ftnote.016"/> society. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0039a-ftnote.015"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Sharpe (ed.), <hi rend="italic">Early Modern England</hi>, p.243. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0039a-ftnote.016"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid., p.243. </s></p></note><p n="p5.8"><s n="s1.8;p5.8">Similarly, the achievement of the church relied not only on geographical location, but also on the age and social status of a particular member of society. </s><s n="s2.8;p5.8">The young, composing a sizeable proportion of society as "half the population may have been under twenty years of age"<ref target="BAWE_0039a-ftnote.017"/>, were largely disinterested and openly rebellious to Church demands; teenage servants had notoriously low attendance at sermons. </s><s n="s3.8;p5.8">Additionally, the Evening prayer was often subordinated for such events as football; in Nottingham 1608, thirty-five men were put before the court for such an offence<ref target="BAWE_0039a-ftnote.018"/>. </s><s n="s4.8;p5.8">The youth maintained their lewd and ungodly culture, the Church unable to mould this large section of society into conformers: "The 'bawdy court', was powerless to force the youth of the parish into 'towardliness'"<ref target="BAWE_0039a-ftnote.019"/>. </s><s n="s5.8;p5.8">The church also failed to impose its values on another substantial portion of society. </s><s n="s6.8;p5.8">In the Early Stuart period especially, there was a clampdown on adultery, yet the lower class's "tradition of promiscuity"<ref target="BAWE_0039a-ftnote.020"/> remained strong. </s><s n="s7.8;p5.8">Essentially, the post-Reformation church was a "more exclusive religion than pre-Reformation Catholicism had been"<ref target="BAWE_0039a-ftnote.021"/>, flawed by its appeal to only a narrow strand of society- the literate, middling sort. </s><s n="s8.8;p5.8">As a result, these people were the only ones really affected by the strict moral values amplified; the Church failed to effectively infiltrate other, probably larger, sections of early modern English society. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0039a-ftnote.017"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Collinson, <hi rend="italic">The Religion of Protestants</hi>, p.229. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0039a-ftnote.018"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Paul Hair (ed.), <hi rend="italic">Before the Bawdy Court</hi> (Great Britain, 1972), p.36. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0039a-ftnote.019"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Collinson, <hi rend="italic">The Religion of Protestants</hi>, p.228. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0039a-ftnote.020"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Thomas, 'The Double Standard', p.206. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0039a-ftnote.021"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Sharpe (ed.), <hi rend="italic">Early Modern England</hi>, p.247. </s></p></note><p n="p6.8"><s n="s1.5;p6.8">Contrastingly, Sharpe describes the entire of Elizabethan and early Stuart society as a "population...very unconvinced about the advantages of Protestantism"<ref target="BAWE_0039a-ftnote.022"/>; thus, the reasons for conformity amongst the literate, middling sort were probably not due to religious conviction. </s><s n="s2.5;p6.8">Fascinatingly, the parishioners of Ellington requested Antony Armitage announce upcoming holy days; evidently not in tune with the Church calendar, the primary concern of these people was an avoidance of penalties. </s><s n="s3.5;p6.8">Furthermore, Ingram points to the fact that the arrest of fifteen men between 1624-25 in Keevil for drunkenness is closely linked with a time of economic distress<ref target="BAWE_0039a-ftnote.023"/>; yeoman supposedly utilised religious morals to defend their demands for an increase in work and cut-back on leisure time. </s><s n="s4.5;p6.8">Still, these examples symbolise that religious moral values were assumed by society. </s><s n="s5.5;p6.8">However, they weren't accepted primarily because of firm conviction in the Church. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0039a-ftnote.022"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid., p.238. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0039a-ftnote.023"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ingram, 'Religion, Communities and Moral Discipline', pp.177-193. </s></p></note><p n="p7.8"><s n="s1.6;p7.8">Yet, there were people who continued to break the rules, risking fines and other forms of punishment. </s><s n="s2.6;p7.8">Philip Stubbes, author of <hi rend="italic">The Anatomie of Abuses</hi>, hints at a widespread lack of adherence to the requirements of the Church on a Sunday: villagers regularly did piping, carding and tennis-playing, and others spent "the Sabbath day (for the most part)...in bear-baiting, cock-fighting, hawking, hunting, and such like"<ref target="BAWE_0039a-ftnote.024"/>. </s><s n="s3.6;p7.8">The variety of sport mentioned, ranging from ones most members of society engaged in to ones probably only a privileged elite played, is indicative of how all levels of society, not just the young and poor, had not had strict moral values instructed into, or at least heavily imposed upon, them. </s><s n="s4.6;p7.8">This conception of prevalent non-conformity is elaborated by Patrick Collinson; he verbalises that the culture in villages was unreflective of the strict, pious archetype the Church aspired to install, Ideally, divorce and adultery were to be taboo issues; yet people explicitly resolved differences based on sexual infidelity in open courts: "This was not the kind of 'honour and shame' society in which sexual licence was unthinkable and sexual behaviour literally worse than death"<ref target="BAWE_0039a-ftnote.025"/>. </s><s n="s5.6;p7.8">Apparently, the restraints established were not sufficient to guarantee consistent and ardent conformity. </s><s n="s6.6;p7.8">Nevertheless, it must be observed that the Church may have failed to harness sport and customs in specific areas of England, but more pressing issues were heavily condemned and the majority listened: throughout the period outlined, the quantity of bridal pregnancies in Keevil rapidly decreased, confined to only a few poorer couples by the 1620s<ref target="BAWE_0039a-ftnote.026"/>. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0039a-ftnote.024"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Philip Stubbes, <hi rend="italic">The Anatomie of Abuses</hi> (London, 1583), p.105. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0039a-ftnote.025"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Collinson, <hi rend="italic">The Religion of Protestants</hi>, p.227. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0039a-ftnote.026"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ingram, 'Religion, Communities and Moral Discipline', pp.177-193. </s></p></note><p n="p8.8"><s n="s1.9;p8.8">Undeniably, the Church imposed its moral values thoroughly in some regions of the country; the "increase in... </s><s n="s2.9;p8.8">Church court prosecutions relating to religious observance and personal morality"<ref target="BAWE_0039a-ftnote.027"/> forced parishioners to conform. </s><s n="s3.9;p8.8">This is highlighted by the growth in demand for additional sermons and the healthier attendance of prayer readings. </s><s n="s4.9;p8.8">Yet, in some areas where Clergymen were lacking and conservative tendencies reigned, traditional 'ungodly' activities continued, villagers indulging in Sunday sports and unspeakable sexual infidelity. </s><s n="s5.9;p8.8">As a result, the success of the church fluctuated from village to village. </s><s n="s6.9;p8.8">Other variables included the age and social standing of members of the parish; unquestionably, the poor and young were largely unaffected by the crackdown on sexual activity and marital expectations. </s><s n="s7.9;p8.8">But even the literate elders, their belief in the established Church supposedly reinforced by the invention of the printing press and consequent spread of religious material, more than likely had hidden intentions for conforming, based mainly on the upholding of their status. </s><s n="s8.9;p8.8">Certainly, public penance and temporary excommunication were effective constraints on those who wished to deviate from expected moral standards. </s><s n="s9.9;p8.8">Ultimately therefore, the success of the church seems to be largely limited to merely preventing deviance from strict moral values, rather than getting people to actually believe in them; even this small accomplishment however, was confined to particular villages and members of society. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0039a-ftnote.027"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid., p.182. </s></p></note></div1></body><back><div1 type="bibliography"><head rend="underlined bold">Bibliography and Word Count</head><p>Collinson, Patrick, <hi rend="italic">The Religion of Protestants: The Church in English Society 1559-1625</hi> (Oxford, 1982)</p><p>Cressy, David and Ferrell, Lori Anne (eds.) <hi rend="italic">Religion and Society in Early Modern England: A Sourcebook</hi> (London, 1996)</p><p>Hair, Paul, (ed.) <hi rend="italic">Before the Bawdy Court</hi> (Great Britain, 1972)</p><p>Ingram, Martin, 'Religion, Communities and Moral Discipline in Late Sixteenth and Early Seventeenth-Century England', in Greyerz, K.Von, (ed.), <hi rend="italic">Religion and Society in Early Modern Europe</hi> (London, 1984), pp.177-193</p><p>Maltby, Judith, <hi rend="italic">Prayer Book and People in Elizabethan and Early Stuart England</hi> (Cambridge, 1998)</p><p>Sharpe, J.A., (ed.) <hi rend="italic">Early Modern England: A Social History 1550-1760</hi> (New York, 1997)</p><p>Stubbes, Philip, <hi rend="italic">The Anatomie of Abuses</hi> (London, 1583)</p><p>Thomas, Keith, 'The Double Standard', <hi rend="italic">Journal of the History of Ideas</hi>, 20 (1959), </p><p>pp.195-216</p><p>Wrightson, Keith and Levine, David,<hi rend="italic"> Poverty and Piety in an English Village: Terling, 1525-1700</hi> (New York, 1979)</p></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
