<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_0042d" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Do Western understandings of Asia continue to be informed by Orientalist assumptions?</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">The document has a title page which contains:
document title
title part</note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">deleted: header: course and assignment name; footer: page numbers
deleted: Word Limit- 2,000; Word Count- 2,089
</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">3</p><p n="date">2006-03</p><p n="module title">Historiography</p><p n="module code">HI323</p><p n="genre family">Essay</p><p n="discipline">History</p><p n="disciplinary group">AH</p><p n="grade">M</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">2100</p><p n="number of s-units">48</p><p n="number of p">10</p><p n="number of tables">0</p><p n="number of figures">0</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">0</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">0</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">43.8</p><p n="average s-units per p">4.8</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">m</p><p n="year of birth">1985</p><p n="first language">Hindi</p><p n="education">UK2</p><p n="course">History &amp; Politics</p><p n="student ID">0042</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><docTitle><titlePart rend="bold">Do Western understandings of Asia continue to be informed by Orientalist assumptions? </titlePart></docTitle><titlePart><name type="student name"/> Tutor- <name type="tutor name"/></titlePart></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="section"><p n="p1.10"><s n="s1.4;p1.10">The most lasting legacy of Edward Said's <hi rend="italic">Orientalism</hi> (1978) - it has been argued- has been the "dislocation of the modern West", bringing down the "body of knowledge" that signified Orientalist writings about the East from their "Olympian heights".<ref target="BAWE_0042d-ftnote.001"/> Said's key argument revolved around the various representations of the Orient- focussing on <hi rend="italic">what</hi> the Orientalist wrote- not <hi rend="italic">how</hi>- about an 'other' which was essentially created by bypassing any dialogue between the different cultures, and operating within a very specific context of imperialism and hegemony.<ref target="BAWE_0042d-ftnote.002"/> Said's work had been preceded by considerable postcolonial writings, and it reinvigorated the debate subsequently in the 1980s with the creation of the <hi rend="italic">Subaltern Studies</hi> group of historians. </s><s n="s2.4;p1.10">After providing a glimpse of the major facets of Orientalism, and the responses it generated, this paper will argue that understandings and discussions of the East- focussing here particularly on India- continue to be influenced by the fundamental feature of Orientalism. </s><s n="s3.4;p1.10">The articulation of that feature is credited to Ronald Inden, who argued that Orientalism's deepest influence was denying "human agency" to the East, and providing universalising "models of how people ought to or must act." </s><ref target="BAWE_0042d-ftnote.003"/><s n="s4.4;p1.10">Explicitly or inadvertently, both Orientalists as well as postcolonial critiques of all ideological spectres have failed to counter this highest level of hegemony. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0042d-ftnote.001"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Gyan Prakash, "Orientalism Now", <hi rend="underlined">History and Theory</hi> 34:3 (1995), pp. 199, 211; Gyan Prakash, "Writing Post-Orientalist Histories of the Third World: Perspectives from Indian Historiography", <hi rend="underlined">Comparative Studies in Society and History</hi> 32:2 (1990), p. 384 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0042d-ftnote.002"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Edward Said, <hi rend="italic">Orientalism: Western Conceptions of the Orient</hi> (London: Penguin, 1995), pp. 5, 21, 27 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0042d-ftnote.003"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ronald Inden, <hi rend="italic">Imagining India</hi> (Oxford: Basil Blackwell, 1990), pp. 1-2 </s></p></note><p n="p2.10"><s n="s1.6;p2.10">In many ways, the 'classical' Orientalism of the 19 <hi rend="sup">th</hi> century continued to influence much of the 20 <hi rend="sup">th</hi> century understandings of India, both in the writings of the Cambridge School, as well as their critiques who failed to move out of the broad generalisations thus created, and merely responded <hi rend="italic">to</hi> them. </s><s n="s2.6;p2.10">Firstly, Richard King has identified a broad distinguishing discourse, whereby society, science, rationality and masculinity are solely attributed to the Enlightenment. </s><s n="s3.6;p2.10">Conversely, religiosity, irrationality, mysticism and femininity are considered exclusive characteristics of the Orient.<ref target="BAWE_0042d-ftnote.004"/> Secondly, contemporary debates in linguistic studies as well as ancient history continue to pertain to the traditional Oriental discourse of "constructing the 'self' through the 'other'".<ref target="BAWE_0042d-ftnote.005"/> For example, Max Muller's search for Europe's "childhood" in the Sanskrit language and the Aryan race continues to be espoused, with the 'other' (in this case India) labelled "the eternal child", underlying its supposedly static nature.<ref target="BAWE_0042d-ftnote.006"/> Third, just as Arthur Balfour argued in 1910 that the Orient "...exists in a sense, as we know it", legacies of Hegel and James Mill's <hi rend="italic">History of India</hi> (1817) continue to survive, commenting on the disunity of the Orient.<ref target="BAWE_0042d-ftnote.007"/> This can be seen in Vincent Smith's writing- "In political institutions, no evolution took place. </s><s n="s4.6;p2.10">No sovereign arose endowed with commanding abilities and capable of wielding together the jarring members of the body politic." </s><ref target="BAWE_0042d-ftnote.008"/><s n="s5.6;p2.10">While colonial and postcolonial nationalist historiography has responded by referring to the 'golden age' of the Maurya and Gupta empires, the crucial question of whether a centralised Westphalian state is the minimum requirement to prevent colonisation has been largely unexplored. </s><s n="s6.6;p2.10">Herein lies the continual hold of Orientalist knowledge that Said wrote of. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0042d-ftnote.004"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Richard King, <hi rend="italic">Orientalism and Religion: Postcolonial Theory, India and the "Mystic East"</hi> (London: Routledge, 1999), p. 13 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0042d-ftnote.005"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Bill Ashcroft and Pal Ahluwalia, <hi rend="italic">Edward Said: The Paradox of Identity</hi> (London: Routledge, 1999), p. 58 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0042d-ftnote.006"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Gyan Prakash, op cit, p. 386 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0042d-ftnote.007"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ashcroft and Ahluwalia, op cit, p. 64 and Ronald Inden, op cit, p. 8 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0042d-ftnote.008"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ronald Inden, op cit </s></p></note><p n="p3.10"><s n="s1.7;p3.10">Said's work sparked off defensive reactions across academic disciplines to what was considered "Western tradition", and rebuttals by contemporary Orientalists like Dennis Porter and Bernard Lewis. </s><ref target="BAWE_0042d-ftnote.009"/><s n="s2.7;p3.10">However, the problem- as Gyan Prakash has pointed out- remains in what is taken to be the representation of the West, and invariably this is determined by Orientalism in the first place.<ref target="BAWE_0042d-ftnote.010"/> This digresses into a discourse that could be termed 'Occidentalism'. </s><s n="s3.7;p3.10">Such reverse essentialism was considered a part of Said's <hi rend="italic">Orientalism</hi> and criticised by James Clifford. </s><s n="s4.7;p3.10">Moreover, such discourses often deny the autonomy of the historical actors themselves. </s><s n="s5.7;p3.10">In <hi rend="italic">Orientalism</hi>, Said himself cited the writing of Flaubert, who spoke of the Egyptian woman who was always represented by her husband, a societal trait the writer took to be "typically Oriental".<ref target="BAWE_0042d-ftnote.011"/> An illustration is the debate around the <hi rend="italic">sati</hi> tradition (widow burning), which was uprooted during the 19 <hi rend="sup">th</hi> century by colonial officers and some members of the Hindu elite. </s><s n="s6.7;p3.10">While some contemporary writers sought justification of the tradition from Hindu texts, Orientalists denounced it as an example of 'Oriental despotism' and took it upon themselves to "civilise" the natives. </s><s n="s7.7;p3.10">What goes unnoticed in the debate- as Gayatri Chakravorty Spivak has argued- is the "silencing of the subaltern woman", whose history is presented by two contesting frameworks detached from her own agency. <ref target="BAWE_0042d-ftnote.012"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0042d-ftnote.009"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ashcroft and Ahluwalia, op cit, pp. 74-6 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0042d-ftnote.010"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Gyan Prakash, op cit, p. 408 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0042d-ftnote.011"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Edward Said, op cit., p. 6 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0042d-ftnote.012"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Gyan Prakash, "Subaltern Studies as Postcolonial Criticism", <hi rend="underlined">The American Historical Review</hi> 99:5 (1994), p. 1488 </s></p></note><p n="p4.10"><s n="s1.3;p4.10">To fill the void generated by Orientalist and nationalist historiography, a group of historians came together in the 1980s to establish <hi rend="italic">Subaltern Studies</hi>. </s><s n="s2.3;p4.10">The founding editor- Ranajit Guha- argued that their aim was to write the histories of the "demographic difference" between the total population of India and those groups they considered to be 'elite'.<ref target="BAWE_0042d-ftnote.013"/> While Jawaharlal Nehru had written his <hi rend="italic">Discovery of India</hi> (1946) largely to rescue Indian nationalism from being hijacked by narrow sectarian interests, <hi rend="italic">Subaltern Studies</hi> focussed instead on the heterogeneity of the 'mainstream', pointing out groups that had been essentialised not only by the Orientalists, but also by the nationalists. </s><s n="s3.3;p4.10">More fundamentally, the group- Partha Chatterjee in particular- has focussed on the "marginalisation of the 'other' forms of knowledge".<ref target="BAWE_0042d-ftnote.014"/> This tradition has influenced postmodernist and Marxist writers too, as works by Romila Thapar (1978) and Bernard Cohn (1987) on the social constructs of the Orientalists and nationalists vis-à-vis the "real" Orient of the subaltern groups demonstrates. <ref target="BAWE_0042d-ftnote.015"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0042d-ftnote.013"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Richard King, op cit, p. 190 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0042d-ftnote.014"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Gyan Prakash, op cit, p. 1483 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0042d-ftnote.015"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Gyan Prakash, op cit, pp. 400-1 </s></p></note><p n="p5.10"><s n="s1.3;p5.10">This approach, however, often fails to break the 'self-other' dichotomy between the elites and the marginalised groups, besides falling into the familiar trap of essentialising the supposedly non-essentialising characteristics- "appropriation of subalternity", according to Chatterjee- of these groups.<ref target="BAWE_0042d-ftnote.016"/> Moreover, the poststructuralist methodology has been criticised for "privileging particular informants", particularly when the localised writers were often writing in their own imperial and/or social contexts.<ref target="BAWE_0042d-ftnote.017"/> Gyan Prakash attempts to present a defence by arguing for the need to question the traditional labels such as "native" and "woman" (in the aforementioned <hi rend="italic">sati</hi> example), and explore new categories such as "native woman" with this relativist approach.<ref target="BAWE_0042d-ftnote.018"/> However, it is difficult to avoid the irony that much of the Orientalist writing- produced by colonial officers working in different parts of the empire- drew on precisely the <hi rend="italic">same</hi> technique- that of producing particularistic pictures of the localised Orient. </s><s n="s2.3;p5.10">Finally, as recent work in psychology has shown, individual actions are often subconsciously 'automated' by their external environment.<ref target="BAWE_0042d-ftnote.019"/> Therefore, the Foucauldian discourse Said drew on in <hi rend="italic">Orientalism</hi> acted on the localised agents of the subaltern groups in the same manner as it would have on the colonial writers, especially if these groups were in fact 'subaltern', thereby limiting their own power to shape the discourse. </s><s n="s3.3;p5.10">This reverts back to the problem many critics feel is inherent in <hi rend="italic">Orientalism</hi> where Said problematically espouses Gramsican counter-hegemony in a Foucauldian discourse.<ref target="BAWE_0042d-ftnote.020"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0042d-ftnote.016"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Gyan Prakash, op cit., p. 1481 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0042d-ftnote.017"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Rosalind O'Hanlon and David Washbrook, "After Orientalism: Culture, Criticism, and Politics in the Third World", <hi rend="underlined">Comparative Studies in Society and History</hi> 34:1 (1992), pp. 161/2 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0042d-ftnote.018"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Gyan Prakash, "Can the "Subaltern" Ride? </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">A Reply to O'Hanlon and Washbrook", <hi rend="underlined">Comparative Studies in Society and History</hi> 34:1 (1992), p. 183 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0042d-ftnote.019"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">John Bargh and Tanya Chartrand, "The Unbearable Automaticity of Being", <hi rend="underlined">American Psychologist</hi> 54:7 (1999), pp. 462-479 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0042d-ftnote.020"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Akeel Bilgrami, "Interpreting a Distinction" in Homi Bhabha and W.J.T. Mitchell (eds.), <hi rend="italic">Edward Said: Continuing the Conversation</hi> (Chicago: University of Chicago Press, 2005), p. 29 </s></p></note><p n="p6.10"><s n="s1.6;p6.10">Said, in <hi rend="italic">Orientalism</hi>, differed from the Foucauldian view of "inescapability of relations of power and domination" within a discourse.<ref target="BAWE_0042d-ftnote.021"/> The failure of the postcolonial critiques of Orientalism has been in creating a genuine alternative discourse. </s><s n="s2.6;p6.10">Nationalist and Marxist critiques of Orientalism failed to break out of Eurocentric discourses. </s><s n="s3.6;p6.10">Nationalism staked a claim to "reason and progress instituted <hi rend="italic">by</hi> colonialism", while Marxism "universalised Europe's historical experiences". <ref target="BAWE_0042d-ftnote.022"/><hi rend="italic">Subaltern Studies</hi> has successfully avoided the nationalist claims to appropriate the "real Orient", but it has not been able to reverse the "normalisation of 'other' forms of knowledge", something championed by Orientalism.<ref target="BAWE_0042d-ftnote.023"/> As Dipesh Chakrabarty argues, "themes of historical transition" are prominent in non-Western histories. </s><s n="s4.6;p6.10">Such transitions emphasise Europe's position <hi rend="italic">as</hi> history, reason and progress, rendering all other forms of people as subaltern, and their histories as subsidiaries of the "established" history that is Europe. </s><s n="s5.6;p6.10">Citing the example of jute worker movements in Bengal, he argues that class based analysis (Marxist) or the absence of a "liberty tree" (E P Thompson) is grossly inadequate, given the importance of caste and religion. </s><s n="s6.6;p6.10">Traditional Marxist responses would assert that the Indian workers 'weren't <hi rend="italic">there</hi> yet' in their stage of development.<ref target="BAWE_0042d-ftnote.024"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0042d-ftnote.021"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Rosalind O'Hanlon and David Washbrook, op cit., pp. 149-50 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0042d-ftnote.022"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Gyan Prakash, op cit., p. 1475 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0042d-ftnote.023"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Gyan Prakash, op cit., p. 399 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0042d-ftnote.024"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Gyan Prakash, op cit., pp. 1484-5 </s></p></note><p n="p7.10"><s n="s1.5;p7.10">Broadly speaking, Orientalism has created two discourses- the 'self-other' discourse which underlines the essential differences between Europe and the Orient, and the response that it has provoked from writers aiming to <hi rend="italic">reOrient</hi>, conceding Europe's supposed qualities as catalysts for progress, and denying their absence in the Orient. </s><s n="s2.5;p7.10">It is curious to note that both- while supposedly opposed discourses- accept the universality of Europe's values and ideas. </s><s n="s3.5;p7.10">Peter Heehs thus considers the responses to Orientalism as mere components of the homogenising discourse. </s><s n="s4.5;p7.10">He has classified postcolonial writings into critical (1950s and 60s), reductive (1970s and 80s) and reactionary (1990s) approaches.<ref target="BAWE_0042d-ftnote.025"/> While the critical approach reduces itself to examining empirical issues through Western frameworks, the reductive method fails to present an autonomous Indian agency. </s><s n="s5.5;p7.10">Reactionary writing has been the most vociferous (especially in the 1990s with the ascent of the Hindutva movement) in arguing for "re-Indianising" the discourse to trace the "imagined community" of India, but it not only borrows crucial aspects of colonial Orientalism (such as the idea of a united and centralised India), but continuously finds- as Sudipta Kaviraj has argued- an 'other' to the Indian 'self' (Muslims, Europeans, etc.).<ref target="BAWE_0042d-ftnote.026"/> They are all, therefore, located within the straitjacket of Orientalism. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0042d-ftnote.025"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Peter Heehs, "Shades of Orientalism: Paradoxes and Problems in Indian Historiography", <hi rend="underlined">History and Theory</hi> 42:2 (2003), pp. 172-5 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0042d-ftnote.026"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid., pp. 178-195 </s></p></note><p n="p8.10"><s n="s1.4;p8.10">An example of an academic debate ought to illustrate the point. </s><s n="s2.4;p8.10">Writing from a traditional Eurocentric perspective, David Landes has argued that Europe for the past millennia has possessed conducive socio-political-economic institutions, coupled with a temperate climate, entrepreneurial zeal and a lack of Malthusian pressure on resources, which made it the natural birthplace of the Industrial Revolution in the 19 <hi rend="sup">th</hi> century.<ref target="BAWE_0042d-ftnote.027"/> In responding to his argument, Kenneth Pomeranz has systematically gone through all the aspects of pre-Industrial Europe mentioned by Landes, and argued that Asia possessed similar, if not advanced characteristics during the 18 <hi rend="sup">th</hi> century.<ref target="BAWE_0042d-ftnote.028"/> While attributing Europe's industrialisation to accidents of geography (proximity to coal in Britain) and colonisation, he tacitly accepts the Eurocentric recipe for a modern industrial society. </s><s n="s3.4;p8.10">Crucially, he acknowledges the existence of a linear notion of progress, from which Asia- for whatever reasons- digressed. </s><s n="s4.4;p8.10">This is a classic case of non-European histories being reduced to mere 'accessories' of the meta narrative that is Europe's history, as Chakrabarty's earlier argument goes. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0042d-ftnote.027"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">David Landes, <hi rend="italic">The Wealth and Poverty of Nations</hi> (London: Little, Brown and Company, 1998), p. xxi </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0042d-ftnote.028"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Kenneth Pomeranz, <hi rend="italic">The Great Divergence</hi> (Princeton: Princeton University Press, 2000), p. 70 </s></p></note><p n="p9.10"><s n="s1.5;p9.10">The problem in Oriental historiography- as Ronald Inden argues- is with the rather inflexible usage of universalised terms such as free market, liberalism, democracy, welfare state, etc. </s><s n="s2.5;p9.10">I would even argue that narratives of non-European societies through a Western framework (without tacit acknowledgement of its thus limitation) "presents itself as a form of knowledge that is both different from, and superior to" the Orientals' knowledge about themselves- in essence, an Orientalist discourse.<ref target="BAWE_0042d-ftnote.029"/> Most writings pertaining to the Orient take Europe as the only "knowable" entity (since the structures of knowledge are European), viewing the Orient as merely an empirical study to be conducted through this skeleton.<ref target="BAWE_0042d-ftnote.030"/> It has also been argued that this entails that <hi rend="italic">all</hi> subsequent writings about the Orient (at least as long as Western political and intellectual hegemony does not recede) will continue to be classified as Orientalist, in one way or another. </s><s n="s3.5;p9.10">O'Hanlon and Washbrook question postcolonial critiques how the Oriental can refute Western discourses without understanding them, and how he can understand them without engaging them, and how, therefore, can he avoid being drawn into the discourse and avoid "totalising abstraction" and "endless relativism" of postmodernism at the same time.<ref target="BAWE_0042d-ftnote.031"/> Prakash offers a partial response, arguing that Oriental historiography must engage itself in a discourse "not determined" by Western conquest.<ref target="BAWE_0042d-ftnote.032"/> This seems inadequate, because Orientalist writings about India have often taken place <hi rend="italic">without</hi> an imperial context (in the case of French and German Orientalism). </s><s n="s4.5;p9.10">Perhaps what is required is a discourse not impacted upon by Western systems of knowledge- in essence, studying the Orient <hi rend="italic">on its own terms</hi>. </s><s n="s5.5;p9.10">For example, Indian political philosophy, despite being extremely rich, has been prevented from analysing Indian history on the grounds of "being tainted with theological assumptions".<ref target="BAWE_0042d-ftnote.033"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0042d-ftnote.029"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ronald Inden, op cit., pp. 18, 37 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0042d-ftnote.030"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Aamir Mufti, "Global Comparativism" in Bhabha and Mitchell (eds.), op cit., p. 111 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0042d-ftnote.031"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Rosalind O'Hanlon and David Washbrook, op cit., pp. 149-50 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0042d-ftnote.032"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Gyan Prakash, op cit., p. 184 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0042d-ftnote.033"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Richard King, op cit., p. 28 </s></p></note><p n="p10.10"><s n="s1.5;p10.10">Whether one looks at "the clash of civilisations" or the "axis of evil", essentialisations about the Orient are rife in contemporary Western- and consequently global- discourses. </s><s n="s2.5;p10.10">These not only reinforce the traditional Orientalist definitions of the 'self' (the West), it prompts the Orient to defend its own 'self' as defined by its 'other' (the West), thereby indirectly accepting the initial generalisation. </s><s n="s3.5;p10.10">Postcolonial Oriental historiography- in this case Indian- has failed to live up to Said's "fundamental human and intellectual obligation"- to reconcile a humanist method of writing history with the ideas of a Foucauldian discourse.<ref target="BAWE_0042d-ftnote.034"/> The alternative which I have proposed- creating an Oriental discourse based on its own value systems- is yet to be explored. </s><s n="s4.5;p10.10">Consequently, writings about the East continue to bear- with varying degrees and often implicitly- the characteristics of the Orientalism of the 19 <hi rend="sup">th</hi> century. </s><s n="s5.5;p10.10">The ghost of James Mill's <hi rend="italic">History of India</hi>, in short, has not been buried. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0042d-ftnote.034"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Rosalind O'Hanlon and David Washbrook, op cit., p. 156 </s></p></note></div1></body><back><div1 type="bibliography"><head rend="bold">Bibliography</head><p>Ashcroft, Bill; Ahluwalia, Pal: <hi rend="italic">Edward Said: The Paradox of Identity</hi> (London: Routledge, 1999)</p><p>Bargh, John; Chartrand, Tanya: "The Unbearable Automaticity of Being", <hi rend="underlined">American Psychologist</hi> 54:7 (1999), pp. 462-479</p><p>Bhabha, Homi; Mitchell, W.J.T. (eds.): <hi rend="italic">Edward Said: Continuing the Conversation</hi> (Chicago: University of Chicago Press, 2005)</p><p>Heehs, Peter: "Shades of Orientalism: Paradoxes and Problems in Indian Historiography", <hi rend="underlined">History and Theory</hi> 42:2 (2003), pp. 169-195</p><p>Inden, Ronald: <hi rend="italic">Imagining India</hi> (Oxford: Basil Blackwell, 1990)</p><p>King, Richard: <hi rend="italic">Orientalism and Religion: Postcolonial Theory, India and the "Mystic East"</hi> (London: Routledge, 1999)</p><p>Landes, David: <hi rend="italic">The Wealth and Poverty of Nations: Why some are so rich and some so poor</hi> (London: Little, Brown and Company, 1998)</p><p>Pomeranz, Kenneth: <hi rend="italic">The Great Divergence: Europe, China, and the Making of the Modern World Economy</hi> (Princeton: Princeton University Press, 2000)</p><p>Prakash, Gyan: "Can the Subaltern Ride?" A Reply to O'Hanlon and Washbrook", <hi rend="underlined">Comparative Studies in Society and History</hi> 34:1 (1992), pp. 168-184</p><p>Prakash, Gyan: "Orientalism Now", <hi rend="underlined">History and Theory</hi> 34:3 (1995), pp. 199-212</p><p>Prakash, Gyan: "Subaltern Studies as Postcolonial Criticism", <hi rend="underlined">The American Historical Review</hi> 99:5 (1994), pp. 1475-90</p><p>Prakash, Gyan: "Writing Post-Orientalist Histories of the Third World: Perspectives from Indian Historiography", <hi rend="underlined">Comparative Studies in Society and History</hi> 32:2 (1990), pp. 383-408</p><p>Said, Edward: <hi rend="italic">Orientalism: Western Conceptions of the Orient</hi> (London: Penguin, 1995)</p><p>Washbrook, David; O'Hanlon, Rosalind: "After Orientalism: Culture, Criticism, and Politics in the Third World", <hi rend="underlined">Comparative Studies in Society and History</hi> 34:1 (1992), pp. 141-167</p></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
