<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_0043a" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Determination of the Function and Structure of Monoclonal Antibodies &amp; Immunoglobin</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note/></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">4</p><p n="date">2005-01</p><p n="module title">Data Acquisition I: Biophysical Techniques &amp; Instrumentation Design</p><p n="module code">MOAC2</p><p n="genre family">Explanation</p><p n="discipline">Biological Sciences</p><p n="disciplinary group">LS</p><p n="grade">D</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">1767</p><p n="number of s-units">60</p><p n="number of p">22</p><p n="number of tables">0</p><p n="number of figures">1</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">0</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">0</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">29.4</p><p n="average s-units per p">2.7</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">m</p><p n="year of birth">1978</p><p n="first language">English</p><p n="education">UKA</p><p n="course">Mathematical Biology and Biophysical Chemistry</p><p n="student ID">0043</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><docTitle><titlePart>Determination of the Function and Structure of Monoclonal Antibodies &amp; Immunoglobin</titlePart></docTitle><titlePart><hi rend="italic"><name type="student name"/></hi> University of <name type="university"/>, UK.</titlePart><titlePart rend="bold">19th January 2005</titlePart></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="section"><p n="p1.22"><s n="s1.2;p1.22">Antibodies are glycoprotein molecules which are found in the blood and tissue of many living beings. </s><s n="s2.2;p1.22">Antibody molecules are created by the immune system in white blood cells known as B lymphocytes upon recognition of a toxin or potentially threatening entity; the foreign bodies whose presence cause the generation of antibodies are known as antigens - as they generate the production of antibodies. </s></p><p n="p2.22"><s n="s1.1;p2.22">Antibodies provide the major defense against pathogens, toxins and extracellular bacteria; they are therefore essential in immunology and drug design. </s></p><p n="p3.22"><s n="s1.2;p3.22">Normally in the body, B-lymphocyte cells produce different antibodies with slightly different properties. </s><s n="s2.2;p3.22">Monoclonal antibodies on the other hand are such that they all originate from a single clone of cells - thus they are all identical, they are typically produced by immunizing a mouse or rat, with an antigen, the B cells from the immunized animal are then fused with B cells that do not produce their own immunoglobin. </s></p><p n="p4.22"><s n="s1.3;p4.22">The procedure undertaken to produce monoclonal antibodies (mAbs) was discovered in 1975, much of the literature relating to the structure and function of antibodies and immunoglobin dates from the mid to late 70's and 1980's, however in recent years mAbs have found a unique and important place in molecular biology and the development and design of drugs as they can provide information about the role of a specific molecule in disease, and also form the basis of new treatments. </s><s n="s2.3;p4.22">In this essay the function in structure of antibodies in general will be discussed and the importance of monoclonal antibodies will be considered. </s><s n="s3.3;p4.22">In addition to this, the biophysical techniques used to discern the structure are addressed. </s></p><p n="p5.22"><s n="s1.1;p5.22">The determination of the structure of a biological molecule such as an antibody can be achieved using a number of experimental techniques in conjunction with post-experimental computational methods - such as molecular replacement software. </s></p><p n="p6.22"><s n="s1.1;p6.22">In order to make sense of much of the literature pertaining to antibody structure it is useful to be familiar with the terminology and nomenclature used to refer to different elements of the antibody. </s></p><p n="p7.22"><s n="s1.1;p7.22">There is a common structure shared by all antibody molecules - this common structure loosely resembles a capital letter Y and this is known to comprise four distinct protein subunits. </s></p><p n="p8.22"><s n="s1.1;p8.22">The following figure shows a schematic of the shape of a typical antibody molecule showing the principle regions and features. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0043a-pic.001"><head>Figure 1: Schematic of a typical antibody [Courtesy of Wikipedia Encylopedia]</head></figure><p n="p9.22"><s n="s1.4;p9.22">For any given antibody molecule there are two heavy chains (shown dark blue in Figure 1 ) which are typically 50-70kDa in size and are usually identical to each other. </s><s n="s2.4;p9.22">The two light chains (shown pale blue in Figure 1) are typically around 23kDa in size and will also be identical to each other - meaning that the antibody has a high level of axial symmetry. </s><s n="s3.4;p9.22">Different antibodies have different heavy and light chains and these differences make the antibody bind specifically to different antigens. </s><s n="s4.4;p9.22">The antibody's specificity is defined in the 'arms' of the Y-shape and the variable regions determining which antigen is bound to is called the complementarity determining region (CDR). </s></p><p n="p10.22"><s n="s1.2;p10.22">The protein domains of the antibody are named in relation to which of the chains they belong to and whether they belong to the constant or the variable region (this variability relates to the amino acid sequence). </s><s n="s2.2;p10.22">For example the domain C <hi rend="sub">H4</hi> belongs to the heavy chain in the constant region, similarly the domain V <hi rend="sub">L</hi> describes the domain of the variable region of the light chain. </s></p><p n="p11.22"><s n="s1.1;p11.22">The region of the antibody connecting the two light chain-containing proteins is often referred to as the hinge as this is a region of high flexibility. </s></p><p n="p12.22"><s n="s1.4;p12.22">Another commonly used nomenclature to describe the generic structure of antibodies originates from the fact the molecules can be cleaved using proteases forming fragments of the original molecule. </s><s n="s2.4;p12.22">These regions are called Fab and Fc. </s><s n="s3.4;p12.22">The Fab region (Fragment antigen binding) describes the two arms and the hinge of the antibody. </s><s n="s4.4;p12.22">The Fc region (Fragment crystallisable) describes the stem of the antibody - so-called due to its propensity to crystallize upon being cleaved. </s></p><p n="p13.22"><s n="s1.5;p13.22">As previously stated, antibodies play a crucial role in the immune system, defending the body against toxins that enter the bloodstream and countering disease threat posed by microbes and viruses. </s><s n="s2.5;p13.22">The primary function of antibodies is that of binding to antigens. </s><s n="s3.5;p13.22">The CDR region of the antibody binds specifically to one or a small number of closely related antigens. </s><s n="s4.5;p13.22">The result of this biding is that the effect of the toxin in irradicated and the host is protected. </s><s n="s5.5;p13.22">It is sometimes the case that there is no immediate effect of the antibody binding to the antigen, but the presence of the antibody - antigen complex causes biological activity thus protecting the host from the threat - this is called an 'Effector Function' of the antibody. </s></p><p n="p14.22"><s n="s1.2;p14.22">There is a wealth of examples in the literature of the research undertaken to determine the structure of monoclonal antibodies using a number of biophysical techniques such as X-ray diffraction, NMR, EM and mass spectrometry. </s><s n="s2.2;p14.22">Herein, a number of examples have been selected chosen so as to show the range of techniques and to display how combining the information from these different techniques can aid in the formation of an overall description of the structure and function of antibodies. </s></p><p n="p15.22"><s n="s1.5;p15.22">Electron microscopy was the first technique to be used to image antibodies [2] it predates the use of NMR or X-ray techniques by over a decade and is still used in a reduced capacity to address some specific questions of function and structure. </s><s n="s2.5;p15.22">There is an upper limit on the resolution that can be achieved using electron microscopy due the physical limitation associated with accelerating the electrons and thus reducing the wavelength. </s><s n="s3.5;p15.22">This problem does not exist with x-rays as they are of sufficiently small wavelength to be able to produce images of macromolecules at the atomic level. </s><s n="s4.5;p15.22">However X-ray crystallography is not without its own challenges. </s><s n="s5.5;p15.22">The crystal sample needs to be pure, concentrated, stable and conformationally inflexible and there are often problems associated with obtaining a crystal of antibodies largely due to the oligosaccharides found on the CH domains. </s></p><p n="p16.22"><s n="s1.4;p16.22">In the process of X-ray crystallography x-rays are fired at the crystal where they undergo diffraction through the lattice formed by the molecules, the diffracted x-rays are then detected, typically by a CCD. A larger magnitude of the angular deviation of the x-ray corresponds to a higher resolution of the structure. </s><s n="s2.4;p16.22">The data collected during this process then undergoes post-processing such that the maximal amount of information can be extracted. </s><s n="s3.4;p16.22">The nature of this processing can vary and there are a number of mathematical tricks that can sharpen resolution, eliminate clutter and provide error correction. </s><s n="s4.4;p16.22">However at its most basic the processing involves performing a Fourier transform on the location of the maximal intensities found - from this the structure of the crystal and be inferred and thus the shape of the molecule. </s></p><p n="p17.22"><s n="s1.3;p17.22">In their 1975 paper Poljak et al [3] describe the use of X-ray crystallographic techniques to discern the structure of the Fab' fragment of a human myeloma (IgG1) protein to a resolution of 0.2 nm. </s><s n="s2.3;p17.22">The paper describes the finding of two irregular beta sheets in both the light and heavy polypeptide chains which are roughly parallel and surround a tightly packed interior of hydrophobic side chains. </s><s n="s3.3;p17.22">The research was also able to identify the spatial location of the hypervariable portions of both the light and heavy chains - and to speculate as to the role these hypervariable portion have in defining the function of the immunoglobin. </s></p><p n="p18.22"><s n="s1.3;p18.22">In the paper '<hi rend="italic">Refined structure of an intact IgG2a monoclonal antibody'</hi> [4] Harris et al describe their X-ray crystallographic data. </s><s n="s2.3;p18.22">It is interesting to compare these two papers [3] and [4] and to regard how the understanding and technology has progress in the intervening two decades. </s><s n="s3.3;p18.22">For example, in the Harris et al paper, which is concerned with the imaging of the monoclonal antibody Mab231, much is made of the computing techniques to obtain the images, and the resolution obtained between 3 and 20A, at least two orders of magnitude greater than that obtained by Poljak et al. </s></p><p n="p19.22"><s n="s1.5;p19.22">The principle of NMR relies on the quantum mechanical affect of the intrinsic spin of nuclei. </s><s n="s2.5;p19.22">The intrinsic spin is perturbed using a magnetic field and then a resonant field is applied usually in the form of the magnetic component of radio frequency electromagnetic radiation. </s><s n="s3.5;p19.22">This mobility and resonance can be detected using the principle of electromagnetic induction. </s><s n="s4.5;p19.22">What characterizes the sample is its ability to recover from the resonance and this gives information regarding the structure of the sample. </s><s n="s5.5;p19.22">NMR can be used to obtain information about different levels of the structure of the proteins (primary, secondary and tertiary) for example use of techniques like NOESY to discern the primary structure (amino acid sequence) of the proteins. </s></p><p n="p20.22"><s n="s1.3;p20.22">The use of NMR to discern aspects of the antibody structure and function are found in references [5] and [6]. </s><s n="s2.3;p20.22">Anglister et al [5] used NMR to probe the nature of antibody - antigen combining sites and obtain spectra from the cleaved Fab fragment of a monoclonal anti-spin-label antibody using deuterated amino acids to form the proteins of the antibody. </s><s n="s3.3;p20.22">Anglister et al go on to postulate that the combining-site structures must be almost identical to the native structures. </s></p><p n="p21.22"><s n="s1.5;p21.22">A major difference between crystallographic techniques and NMR is that the specimen can be viewed close to their natural states when NMR is the probing technique. </s><s n="s2.5;p21.22">Furthermore dynamical structural information can be found with NMR - of course this cannot be the case with crystallography as the molecule needs to be tightly bound in the crystal lattice. </s><s n="s3.5;p21.22">Kim et al use NMR for the study of the dynamical properties of the hinge region of IgG. The hinge region is typically mobile and is therefore a prime target for dynamical imaging. </s><s n="s4.5;p21.22">It was concluded that the hinge region of the mouse IgG2a molecule has a mosaic structure with heterogeneous nature of flexibility with the rigid core part flanked by upper and lower hinges, which are highly flexible peptide segments. </s><s n="s5.5;p21.22">It was suggested that the rigidity in the N-terminal side of the upper hinge is due to the interaction with a CH domain of the antibody. </s></p><p n="p22.22"><s n="s1.2;p22.22">The examples presented here are among many which have gone to aid the understanding of the structure and function of monoclonal antibodies and immunoglobin in general. </s><s n="s2.2;p22.22">The growth of this pool of knowledge will aid in the increased use of monoclonal antibodies as a therapy for diseases and ailments such as arthritis and cancers. </s></p></div1></body><back><div1 type="bibliography"><head>References</head><p>[1] - <hi rend="bold">Huber R</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Spatial structure of immunoglobulin molecules.</hi> Klin Wochenschr 1980 Nov 17;58(22):1217-31.</p><p>[2] - <hi rend="bold">Kenneth H. Roux</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Immunoglobulin Structure and Function as Revealed by Electron Microscop,y</hi> International Archives of Allergy and Immunology 1999;120:85-99 </p><p>[3] - <hi rend="bold">Poljak RJ, Amzel LM, Chen BL, Phizackerley RP, Saul F</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Structure and specificity of antibody molecules</hi>. Philos Trans R Soc Lond B Biol Sci 1975 Nov 6;272(915):43-51</p><p>[4] - <hi rend="bold">Harris LJ, Larson SB, Hasel KW, McPherson A</hi>. <hi rend="italic">Refined structure of an intact IgG2a monoclonal antibody.</hi> Biochemistry. 1997 Feb 18;36(7):1581-97.</p><p>[5] - <hi rend="bold">Anglister J, Frey T, McConnell HM</hi>, <hi rend="italic">NMR technique for assessing contributions of heavy and light chains to an antibody combining site</hi>. Nature 1985 May 2-8; 315 (6014) : 65-7.</p><p>[6] - <hi rend="bold">Kim H, Matsunaga C, Yoshino A, Kato K, Arata Y. </hi><hi rend="italic">Dynamical structure of the hinge region of immunoglobulin G as studied by 13C nuclear magnetic resonance spectroscopy</hi>, J Mol Biol. 1994 Feb 11;236(1):300-9. </p></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
