<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_0043c" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Description of an Experiment on the Chemotaxis of Bacteria</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">deleted: page numbers
</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">4</p><p n="date">2005-02</p><p n="module title">Networks &amp; Pathways in Cells</p><p n="module code">MOAC8</p><p n="genre family">Methodology recount</p><p n="discipline">Biological Sciences</p><p n="disciplinary group">LS</p><p n="grade">D</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">1815</p><p n="number of s-units">76</p><p n="number of p">22</p><p n="number of tables">1</p><p n="number of figures">4</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">0</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">0</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">23.9</p><p n="average s-units per p">3.5</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">m</p><p n="year of birth">1978</p><p n="first language">English</p><p n="education">UKA</p><p n="course">Mathematical Biology and Biophysical Chemistry</p><p n="student ID">0043</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><docTitle><titlePart>MOAC Module 8 Laboratory Report; Description of an Experiment on the Chemotaxis of Bacteria</titlePart></docTitle><titlePart><name type="student name"/></titlePart><titlePart>February 22, 2005</titlePart></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="section"><head>1 Introduction</head><div2><head rend="bold">1.1 Overview</head><p n="p1.22"><s n="s1.3;p1.22">In this report an experiment is described in which the chemotaxis of two strains of bacteria are investigated. </s><s n="s2.3;p1.22">The motivation behind the design of the experiment is described in detail identifying the reasons and the rationale behind all of the decisions made during the design of the experiment. </s><s n="s3.3;p1.22">The expectations underlying the anticipated results of the experiment are described which in many cases provided the driving force of the rationale behind the design of the experiment. </s></p><p n="p2.22"><s n="s1.2;p2.22">After the description of the design of the experiment there follows a brief summary of the procedure and conduct of the experiment. </s><s n="s2.2;p2.22">Finally there are a number of suggestions as to how the experiment could be improved continued or amended if undertaken again. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">1.2 Scope and Limitations</head><p n="p3.22"><s n="s1.2;p3.22">The goal of this exercise was to design and carry out an experiment which would show a feature of the motile behaviour of bacteria. </s><s n="s2.2;p3.22">There were two bacteria available for use (Myxococcus Xanthus and Echerichea Coli) and a number of chemicals were made available, these chemicals could have been chemo-attractors, chemo-repellors or they could have had no eect whatsoever on the bacteria in question. </s></p><p n="p4.22"><s n="s1.3;p4.22">There were many factors which could have been investigated during this experiment, many degrees of freedom which could have been varied to discover something about the nature of chemotaxis in bacteria. </s><s n="s2.3;p4.22">The experiment described herein was designed to extract quantitative data which could be used to extract some law or property of the bacteria movement. </s><s n="s3.3;p4.22">This was conducted in a rigorous and methodical fashion - however the price of this rigour is that the scope of the experiment was perhaps more limited than other experiments. </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head>2 Design of the Experiment</head><p n="p5.22"><s n="s1.3;p5.22">A decision was made to attempt to obtain quantitative data regarding the chemotaxis behaviour of the bacteria under analysis. </s><s n="s2.3;p5.22">In addition to the analysis of the motile behaviour of the bacteria, attepts were made to discern the effect of a chemical to the motility; the chemical under scrutiny was succinic acid. </s><s n="s3.3;p5.22">The motile behaviour of both M. Xanthus and E.coli were be observed and recorded and compared. </s></p><p n="p6.22"><s n="s1.1;p6.22">The experiments designed fall distinctly into two categories; macroscopic experiments conducted on agar plates whereby the bulk motion of bacteria can be observed and microscopic experiments where bacteria are placed on a microscope slide and observed under an optical microscope to discern the behaviour and motility of individual bacterium. </s></p><div2><head rend="bold">2.1 Macroscopic Plate Experiments</head><p n="p7.22"><s n="s1.3;p7.22">A constraint that was considered during this aspect of the experiment is that was only enough agar to make approximately ten plates. </s><s n="s2.3;p7.22">This meant that that scope the macroscopic experiments were designed with this in mind. </s><s n="s3.3;p7.22">The table </s></p><table id="BAWE_0043c-tab.001"><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p8.22"><s n="s1.4;p8.22">shows the content of the plates in the experiment. </s><s n="s2.4;p8.22">The reasoning behind the each plate will now be described. </s><s n="s3.4;p8.22">Plates 0 and 1 were the control plates for the M. Xanthus and E. coli cultures respectively. </s><s n="s4.4;p8.22">Figure 1 shows a schematic of the control plates (0 and 1). </s></p><p n="p9.22"><s n="s1.2;p9.22">The control plates consisted of agar with no succinic acid and would thus provide information regarding the motile behaviour of the bacteria in the absence of any chemicals. </s><s n="s2.2;p9.22">The control plates consisted of a streak and a spot of </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0043c-pic.001"><head>Figure 1: Schematic of the Agar Plate for plates 0 and 1</head></figure><p n="p10.22"><s n="s1.1;p10.22">the bacteria, providing the information required to act as the control for all the subsequent plates. </s></p><p n="p11.22"><s n="s1.2;p11.22">Figure 2 shows a schematic diagram of how the gradient of the chemical was obtained. </s><s n="s2.2;p11.22">In each of the gradient experiments (plates 2-5) a streak of the bacteria was applied to the plate in the direction of the gradient (from low to high). </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0043c-pic.002"><head>Figure 2: Schematic of the Agar Plate for plates 2,3,4 and 5</head></figure><p n="p12.22"><s n="s1.2;p12.22">The shallow gradient (plates 2 and 3) was created using agar with a 5 mM concentration succinic acid allowed to set at an angle, having set - the plate was filled using agar with no succinic acid, the idea being that the gradient would be formed where there is more succcinic acid. </s><s n="s2.2;p12.22">The steeper gradient was created for plates 4 and 5 in the same way and using succinic acid with a concentration of 10 mM. Comparison of plates 0, 2 and 4 would show the effect of the differing concentrations of succinic acid to M. Xanthus and comparison of plate 1, 3, and 5 would show the effect of the different concentrations of succinic acid to E. Coli. </s></p><p n="p13.22"><s n="s1.1;p13.22">The purpose of the gradient-type experiments was to show that if succinic acid was a chemoattractor, there would be increased activity in the regions of higher concentration of the chemical and a net migration towards the high concentration regions, whereas if succinic acid were found to be a repellant, then the reverse would be found, with net migration away from the high concentration regions. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0043c-pic.003"><head>Figure 3: Schematic of the Agar Plate for plates 6,7,8, 9 and 10</head></figure><p n="p14.22"><s n="s1.14;p14.22">Figure 3 shows how the plates were constructed for plates 6 - 10. </s><s n="s2.14;p14.22">In these experiments the concentration of succinic acid was gradually increased in subsequent plates to show the effect of the chemical on the bacteria in a homogenous environment. </s><s n="s3.14;p14.22">Comparison and of each of the spots after a given time would show the effect of the differing effect of the chemical, furthermore, measurement of the swarming of the bacteria would allow quantification of the motility of the bacteria. </s><s n="s4.14;p14.22">For example it was anticipated that a graph of average distance moved versus concentration of the succinic acid could be constructed. </s><s n="s5.14;p14.22">Unlike the gradient experiments, the homogenous plate experiments were specifically designed to enable quantification of the motility. </s><s n="s6.14;p14.22">The idea behind this experiment was to show that with no chemo-attractors present E. Coli exhibits a type of random walk with two phases of motion. </s><s n="s7.14;p14.22">A translation which corresponds to anticlockwise flaggella motion, this translation is then followed by a tumbling phase where the bacterium rotates due to clockwise flagella rotation. </s><s n="s8.14;p14.22">This tumbling reorientates the bacterium thus when the tranlaton phase is entered again the bacterium is facing in a random direction. </s><s n="s9.14;p14.22">Having measured the bacterial motion in the absence of chemicals, a succinic acid gradient would be added and the random walk would be measured in the presence of the chemical. </s><s n="s10.14;p14.22">The measurements would be taken by observing a bacterium in the tumbling phase the then wait until it entered the translation phase. </s><s n="s11.14;p14.22">The direction of the translation and the time spent in the translation phase would be recorded. </s><s n="s12.14;p14.22">Figure 4 shows a schematic diagram of the view through the microscope. </s><s n="s13.14;p14.22">The viewing area would be split into eight imaginary regions thus enabling the direction of the motion to be roughly quantised. </s><s n="s14.14;p14.22">A stop watch would be used to measure the length of time spent in the translation phase. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">2.2 Microscope Experiments</head><p n="p15.22"><s n="s1.2;p15.22">The second aspect of the experiment was to observe the two bacteria under a microscope, then to somehow quantify the motion seen. </s><s n="s2.2;p15.22">The challenge in this experiment was precisely how to perform this quantification </s></p><p n="p16.22"><s n="s1.2;p16.22">It was hoped that the data collected in this experiment in the absence of any chemicals would be used to show that the motion of the bacteria is described by Brownian motion, thus a diffusion coefficent could be ascribed to the motion. </s><s n="s2.2;p16.22">Futhermore in the presence of a succinic acid chemical gradient, it was hoped that the motion would statistically described by a biased random walk, therefore </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0043c-pic.004"><head>Figure 4: Schematic of microscope view</head></figure><p n="p17.22"><s n="s1.1;p17.22">the diffusion would be non-homogenous and the diffusion coefficient would be different in different directions. </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head>3 Results &amp; Conclusions</head><p n="p18.22"><s n="s1.1;p18.22">In this section the results of the experiment are summarised with some suggestions for improvement and how the experiments would be changed if performed again. </s></p><div2><head rend="bold">3.1 Macroscopic Plate Experiments</head><p n="p19.22"><s n="s1.12;p19.22">The M. Xanthus displayed no apparent motion in any of the plates observed. </s><s n="s2.12;p19.22">This could be for a number of reasons. </s><s n="s3.12;p19.22">The way in which M. Xanthus moves may not be efficient on the agar medium, or it could be that the bacteria were well fed and therefore had no impetus to be motile in the search for food. </s><s n="s4.12;p19.22">As no motility was observed in the M. Xanthus no conclusions could drawn regarding its reaction to the succinic acid. </s><s n="s5.12;p19.22">The E. coli did display some motion. </s><s n="s6.12;p19.22">The control (plate 1) showed the the bacteria had swarmed over 6 mm non uniformly around the single spot. </s><s n="s7.12;p19.22">The control streak also displayed some motion away from the original place. </s><s n="s8.12;p19.22">The control streak moved as much as 3 mm roughly uniformly. </s><s n="s9.12;p19.22">Comparison of plates 3 and 5 showed the effect of the gradient on the motility. </s><s n="s10.12;p19.22">It was apparent that the motion on plate 3 was less than on the control and the motion on plate 5 was less than on plate 3. </s><s n="s11.12;p19.22">The motion on both E. Coli plates was a roughly uniform. </s><s n="s12.12;p19.22">This implies that motility decreases with increased concentrations of succinic acid, and as no gradient effects were observed it also implies that the gradient became less apparent due to diffusion. </s></p><p n="p20.22"><s n="s1.2;p20.22">Plates 6 - 10 showed that the E-coli did move as much as 1.5 mm in some cases. </s><s n="s2.2;p20.22">Although no quantitative data was recorded comparison between the plates showed that there was less motion in the plates with higher concentrations of succinic acid. </s></p><p n="p21.22"><s n="s1.4;p21.22">This implies that succinic acid suppresses the motility of the E. Coli. </s><s n="s2.4;p21.22">However to draw firmer conclusions more experiments should take place. </s><s n="s3.4;p21.22">If the experiment were conducted again more spots would be placed on each plate, thus giving more data, also observations would be made at regular time intervals and for a longer complete time. </s><s n="s4.4;p21.22">Tests should also be conducted to ensure that the bacteria are starved and are likely to form flagella. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">3.2 Microscope Experiments</head><p n="p22.22"><s n="s1.9;p22.22">The grand designs of the experiment were made with little experience of actually handling the equipment, however both M. Xanthus and E. Coli were successfully observed under the microscope. </s><s n="s2.9;p22.22">The E. Coli were particularly impressive in that they occasionally displayed the tumbling behaviour. </s><s n="s3.9;p22.22">However it became apparent that the E. Coli were well fed and therefore had no need to grow the flagella. </s><s n="s4.9;p22.22">More experiments were conducted using starved bacteria - and these were more successful in that the transitions between the tumbling phase and the translation phase could clearly be observed for individual bacterium. </s><s n="s5.9;p22.22">Indeed had more time been available quantitative data may have been obtained in the manner described in the previous section. </s><s n="s6.9;p22.22">The recording of data was complicated immensely by fluid effects. </s><s n="s7.9;p22.22">By far the overwhelming motion of the bacteria is due to a drift cause by fluid motion and pressure gradients under the cover slip. </s><s n="s8.9;p22.22">The fluid effects are quite drastic when another fluid (such as succinic acid)is added to the sample. </s><s n="s9.9;p22.22">Although quantitive data could be collected in this fashion - fluid drift effects could have to be accounted for in the analysis, or a way to counter the flow should be designed into the experiments. </s></p></div2></div1></body><back/></text></TEI.2>
