<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_0043b" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Comment and Analysis of the Molecular Simulation on Phospholipid Bilayers.</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note/></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">4</p><p n="date">2005-03</p><p n="module title">Computation II: Molecular Modelling</p><p n="module code">MOAC7</p><p n="genre family">Critique</p><p n="discipline">Biological Sciences</p><p n="disciplinary group">LS</p><p n="grade">D</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">2028</p><p n="number of s-units">78</p><p n="number of p">23</p><p n="number of tables">0</p><p n="number of figures">2</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">9</p><p n="number of lists">1</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">0</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">26.0</p><p n="average s-units per p">3.4</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">m</p><p n="year of birth">1978</p><p n="first language">English</p><p n="education">UKA</p><p n="course">Mathematical Biology and Biophysical Chemistry</p><p n="student ID">0043</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><docTitle><titlePart rend="bold">Comment and Analysis of the Molecular Simulation on Phospholipid Bilayers. </titlePart></docTitle><titlePart rend="bold"><name type="student name"/></titlePart><titlePart rend="bold">MOAC Module 7: 5th March 2005-03-05</titlePart><titlePart>Analysis of the 2003 paper entitled "<hi rend="italic">Molecular Dynamics Simulation of the Formation, Structure and Dynamics of Small Phospholipid Vesicles</hi>" by Siewert J Marrink and Alan E Mark.</titlePart></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold italic">Introduction</head><p n="p1.23"><s n="s1.7;p1.23">The paper "<hi rend="italic">Molecular Dynamics Simulation of the Formation, Structure and Dynamics of Small Phospholipid Vesicles</hi>" documents the work carried out by Marrink and Mark to simulate the dynamics of phospholipids in solution. </s><s n="s2.7;p1.23">This study adds to the already considerable body of literature pertaining to the modelling of lipid bilayers. </s><s n="s3.7;p1.23">The interest in these systems is due to bilayers being the main constituent of typical cell membranes. </s><s n="s4.7;p1.23">The authors claim that the method described in this paper represents an improvement on the accuracy and fidelity of results compared with previous simulations. </s><s n="s5.7;p1.23">Other studies have shown how phospholipids can form vesicles, liposomes and closed structures due to the hydrophobic nature of the tails and the desire to minimise free energy. </s><s n="s6.7;p1.23">Marrink and Mark confirm the formation of these closed structure vesicles and go on to analyse the structure of the vesicles and dynamics within them. </s><s n="s7.7;p1.23">Furthermore they analyse the effect of having different types of phospholipids within the vesicle structure. </s></p><p n="p2.23"><s n="s1.1;p2.23">The method used in this study was a course graining technique where functional elements of the phospholipids were bunched together and treated as single entities. </s></p><p n="p3.23"><s n="s1.4;p3.23">A total of 10 individual simulations were conducted. </s><s n="s2.4;p3.23">In each of the simulations the phospholipid dipalmitoylphosphatidylcholine (DPPC) was present. </s><s n="s3.4;p3.23">DPPC is a phospholipid which is found in cellular membranes and the properties are well documented both experimentally and through simulations. </s><s n="s4.4;p3.23">In addition to using DPPC in some of the later simulations other phospholipids were added and the interactions between the different elements of the bilayers were observed. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold italic">Simulation and Techniques</head><p n="p4.23"><s n="s1.2;p4.23">The course graining technique employed for this study is a step towards a fully atomised approach where each of the atoms present in the molecules would be considered in the simulation. </s><s n="s2.2;p4.23">The molecules within this simulation are modelled as a collection of 'atoms', where each atom represents a chemically and spatially functional group within the real molecule. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0043b-pic.001"><head rend="bold">Figure 1: Schematic of the course graining</head></figure><p n="p5.23"><s n="s1.5;p5.23">Figure 1 shows how the course graining was performed in the simulations. </s><s n="s2.5;p5.23">Two 'atoms' were used to represent the head group of the DPPC, when DPPE was introduced to the simulations the NC3 atom was replaced by a NH3 atom. </s><s n="s3.5;p5.23">Two atoms were used to represent the glycorol groups and four atoms were used to represent each chain of the hydrophobic tail. </s><s n="s4.5;p5.23">When lysolipids are introduced into the simulation, these were modelling as in Figure 1 with only one tail chain. </s><s n="s5.5;p5.23">The lipids are solvated in water which in this course grained model are represented by a WAT atom which represents four individual water molecules. </s></p><p n="p6.23"><s n="s1.6;p6.23">Each type of atom is ascribed a level of hydrophilia: the WAT, NC3 and NH3 groups are all hydrophilic, the GLYC (glycerol) groups are slightly hydrophilic and the TAIL groups are hydrophobic. </s><s n="s2.6;p6.23">The interactions of between the molecules in the simulation are governed by Lennard-Jones potentials which accounts for the relative hydrophilia of the groups in a pair wise fashion; the Coulomb interactions due to charges are also accounted for. </s><s n="s3.6;p6.23">Both the Lennard Jones and the Coulomb interactions are only considered for short ranges, the cut-off distance being 1.2 nm. </s><s n="s4.6;p6.23">In addition to these potentials being considered individual bonds between the atoms are considered and modelled as a simple spring obeying Hooke's law, both the spring constant and the equilibrium distance are given parameters. </s><s n="s5.6;p6.23">Angles between the atoms were also included in the simulations using a cosine rule with the equilibrium being at 180 <hi rend="sup">0</hi>. </s><s n="s6.6;p6.23">During the simulations the atoms move and vibrate due the interactions and thermal energy in the defined force field and within the given constraints, throughout all the simulations the temperature was assumed to be 323K, which is roughly human body temperature. </s></p><p n="p7.23"><s n="s1.1;p7.23">This model of the phospholipids agrees well with experiment - where the area per head group is used as a metric. </s></p><p n="p8.23"><s n="s1.2;p8.23">During this study a total of ten simulations were run. </s><s n="s2.2;p8.23">These were as follows: </s></p><list type="ordered"><item>RANDOM I : 1500 DPPC molecules simulated for <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0043b-form.001"/>.</item><item>RANDOM II: 1500 DPPC molecules simulated for <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0043b-form.002"/>.</item><item>RANDOM III: 1500 DPPC molecules simulated for <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0043b-form.003"/>.</item><item>RANDOM IV: 2500 DPPC molecules simulated for <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0043b-form.004"/>.</item><item>BICEL I: 877 DPPC molecules simulated for <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0043b-form.005"/>.</item><item>BICEL II: 877 DPPC molecules simulated for <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0043b-form.006"/>.</item><item>BICEL III: 877 DPPC molecules simulated for <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0043b-form.007"/>.</item><item>BICEL - PE I: DPPE added to the simulation</item><item>BICEL - PE II: DPPE added to the simulation</item><item>BICEL - lysoPC: lysolipids added to Bicelle</item></list><p n="p9.23"><s n="s1.6;p9.23">The first four of these had a random initial configuration of phospholipids. </s><s n="s2.6;p9.23">The runs RANDOM I, RANDOM II and RANDOM III had 1500 lipid molecules solvated in 400,000 WAT molecules (corresponding to 1.6 million water molecules.) </s><s n="s3.6;p9.23">Run RANDOM IV had 2500 lipid molecules. </s><s n="s4.6;p9.23">The remaining six simulations took an intermediate stage (called the Bicelle) of one of the random runs as a starting point. </s><s n="s5.6;p9.23">Runs BICEL I, BICEL II and BICEL III, used pure DPPC and could therefore be seen as continuation of the random simulations. </s><s n="s6.6;p9.23">The remaining runs other phospholipids were added to the DPPC such that the effect of these other molecules could be assessed. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold italic">Formation of the Vesicles</head><p n="p10.23"><s n="s1.2;p10.23">In each of the random simulations the formation of a closed vesicle was observed. </s><s n="s2.2;p10.23">It appears as though the dynamics of the formation is not sensitive to the starting structure - and in each of the simulations the vesicles formed within 200 - 300 ns. </s></p><p n="p11.23"><s n="s1.1;p11.23">The longest simulations showed that once formed the vesicles are stable structures and remain relatively unchanged for the duration of the simulation. </s></p><p n="p12.23"><s n="s1.1;p12.23">The simulation progresses through a number of structural stages to arrive at the formation of the closed vesicles, these stages appear to be universal in that they are observed in each of the simulations. </s></p><p n="p13.23"><s n="s1.3;p13.23">Starting in a random configuration the phospholipids rapidly form micellular structures which coalesce to form threadlike structures - referred to as interconnected worms. </s><s n="s2.3;p13.23">The next phase is the formation of single structure called a bicelle - this is an open structure consisting of a curved bilayer of phospholipids, with the head groups exposed and the hydrophobic tails concealed from the water. </s><s n="s3.3;p13.23">The next phase is a recognisable vesicle with a pore allowing the passage of water - finally the pore closes leaving the closed vesicle structure. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0043b-pic.002"><head rend="bold">Figure 2 Cross Section of a vesicle forming - showing the closing of the pore</head></figure><p n="p14.23"><s n="s1.3;p14.23">Figure 2 shows a cross section through the vesicle showing the pore closing. </s><s n="s2.3;p14.23">The pore is hourglass shaped. </s><s n="s3.3;p14.23">In these simulations the vesicle with a pore was not a stable state - and it was quickly closed. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold italic">Structure of the Vesicles</head><p n="p15.23"><s n="s1.2;p15.23">Not all the lipids in the simulation formed vesicles - some remain in micelles or are found in smaller 'dry' vesicles. </s><s n="s2.2;p15.23">Once the main vesicle has formed those lipid remaining outside the main structure stayed outside and in the timescales were not observed to fuse with the main structure. </s></p><p n="p16.23"><s n="s1.5;p16.23">In all of the simulations which contained just DPPC the formation a vesicle was observed, the vesicles in all simulations were all very similar to one another being roughly spherical and containing similar number of lipids both on the outer and inner layers. </s><s n="s2.5;p16.23">The exception to this was the vesicle formed in run RANDOM IV; in this run there were many more phospholipid molecules present (2500 as opposed to 1500 in other random runs) and a structure called a hemifused vesicle formed. </s><s n="s3.5;p16.23">This structure resembled two smaller vesicles stuck together sharing a joining wall. </s><s n="s4.5;p16.23">It is thought that this structure is actually an intermediate state of the fusion process - where the rupture of the joining wall would form a larger single vesicle. </s><s n="s5.5;p16.23">However this rupture was not seen in the timescales of the simulation. </s></p><p n="p17.23"><s n="s1.5;p17.23">The paper documents the average densities of the different atoms as a function of the distance from the centre of the vesicle - this analysis is elegantly presented as a graph (RDF) and clearly shows the difference between the inner and outer layers of the vesicle. </s><s n="s2.5;p17.23">For example the average area per head group is less for the inner layer - this is due to the inner layer having a greater curvature than the outer layer. </s><s n="s3.5;p17.23">This analysis also reveals the level to which water molecules penetrate the bilayer. </s><s n="s4.5;p17.23">The hydrophilic nature of the head groups means that water permeation into the head region is common place - whereas there are very few water molecules found in the hydrophobic tail region. </s><s n="s5.5;p17.23">Furthermore - the level of penetration of water in the outer layer head region is greater than the penetration into the head group of the inner layer. </s></p><p n="p18.23"><s n="s1.3;p18.23">Structurally the inner and outer layers are very different - this difference arises from the nature of the curvature - and the asymmetry of the molecules. </s><s n="s2.3;p18.23">In the outer layer the tail groups points toward the centre of curvature whereas with the inner layer the head groups point toward the centre of curvature. </s><s n="s3.3;p18.23">Marrink and Mark touch on the topology of the simulations and discuss Minkowski topological measures and means of assessing the curvature of the structures. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold italic">Mixed Vesicles</head><p n="p19.23"><s n="s1.8;p19.23">The final three simulations consisted of vesicles with mixed phospholipid components. </s><s n="s2.8;p19.23">BICEL PE I and BICEL PE II had 25% of the DPPC replaced by DPPE and BICEL lyso PC had 25% of the DPPC replaced by the single tailed lyso-lipid. </s><s n="s3.8;p19.23">The starting point of these simulations is the point at which the bicelle-like structure have formed and crude simple structure. </s><s n="s4.8;p19.23">As with the pure DPPC the most elucidating analysis was that of the density of the species from the centre of the vesicle. </s><s n="s5.8;p19.23">This analysis showed that the DPPE was more likely to be found in the inner layer of the vesicle. </s><s n="s6.8;p19.23">This is due to the species favouring the negative curvature conditions in this region due to it having a smaller head group and its ability to form hydrogen bonds with other DPPE molecules. </s><s n="s7.8;p19.23">One of the DPPE simulations resulted in the formation of a much larger vesicle than in any of the other simulations. </s><s n="s8.8;p19.23">Although no explicit explanation of this behaviour is offered - it is speculated that it may be due to the relative differences in the curvature between the outer and the inner layers being less in a larger structure. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold italic">Dynamics within the Vesicles</head><p n="p20.23"><s n="s1.5;p20.23">In all of the simulations there was no change in the bulk shape of the vesicle once it had formed, there was however diffusion of the lipids across the surface of the layers. </s><s n="s2.5;p20.23">By observation of individual molecules, the diffusion coefficients in the outer and inner layers were measured. </s><s n="s3.5;p20.23">The diffusion coefficient in the upper was found to be<formula notation="" id="BAWE_0043b-form.008"/> and the diffusion coefficient for the inner layers was calculated as<formula notation="" id="BAWE_0043b-form.009"/>. </s><s n="s4.5;p20.23">This shows that the diffusion across the outer layer of the vesicles to be nearly twice as fast for the inner layers. </s><s n="s5.5;p20.23">Given that in the calculation of the diffusion coefficient the curvature has been accounted for - the difference in the speed of diffusion is probably due to the greater density in the inner layers. </s></p><p n="p21.23"><s n="s1.1;p21.23">The simulation revealed that there was no so-called flip-flop behaviour of the phospholipids - meaning that once the pore had closed then they remained in the same layer for the duration of the simulation. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold italic">Conclusions and Observations</head><p n="p22.23"><s n="s1.2;p22.23">The course graining techniques employed in this study have offered an elucidating means to analyse the structure and dynamics of the vesicle formation. </s><s n="s2.2;p22.23">However due the course graining the results imply that the action occurs at faster timescales than would be expected experimentally, for this reason the results, at least those relating to timescales, should be treated qualitatively rather than quantitatively. </s></p><p n="p23.23"><s n="s1.3;p23.23">There are a number of ways in which these simulations could be improved, the course graining provides a model which is near atomic - for a more complete picture more 'atoms' should be included in the model. </s><s n="s2.3;p23.23">Also this simulation although large in terms of <hi rend="italic">in-silico</hi> simulations is still smaller than the smallest known naturally occurring vesicle - an obvious further step would be to increase the size of the simulations to better represent reality. </s><s n="s3.3;p23.23">Although this would be computationally intensive a possible solution could be to utilise the spherical symmetry of the simulation - starting at a mature state of vesicle development and introducing periodic boundary conditions such that the vesicle element modelled would form a sphere. </s></p></div1></body><back/></text></TEI.2>
