<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_0047d" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Thromboembolic Event</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">document consists of pro forma table giving section headings, along with notes detailing the expected contents of each section
</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">4</p><p n="date">2005-10</p><p n="module title">General Clinical Education</p><p n="module code">unknown</p><p n="genre family">Case study</p><p n="discipline">Medicine</p><p n="disciplinary group">LS</p><p n="grade">D</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">2681</p><p n="number of s-units">126</p><p n="number of p">48</p><p n="number of tables">2</p><p n="number of figures">1</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">10</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">21</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">21.3</p><p n="average s-units per p">2.6</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">m</p><p n="year of birth">1981</p><p n="first language">English</p><p n="education">UKA</p><p n="course">Medicine</p><p n="student ID">0047</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><titlePart>PORTFOLIO CASE N <hi rend="sup underlined">o</hi>: <hi rend="bold">12</hi> Patient Initials: <name type="other"/> Hospital Number: Kept on separate list Age: 63 (<name type="date"/>) Gender: M </titlePart><docTitle><titlePart>Portfolio Case presentation number: 12</titlePart></docTitle></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="section"><head>Referral information</head><p n="p1.48"><s n="s1.1;p1.48">Mr <name type="other"/> was referred to the accident and emergency department after presenting at an NHS walk-in clinic. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head>History</head><div2><head rend="underlined bold">PC:</head><p n="p2.48"><s n="s1.1;p2.48">Mr <name type="other"/> presented with acute pain and paraesthesiae in the right ankle. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined bold">HPC:</head><p n="p3.48"><s n="s1.7;p3.48">Mr <name type="other"/> awoke from sleep yesterday morning with pain and paraesthesiae in the right ankle. </s><s n="s2.7;p3.48">The pain was described as a sharp, constant stabbing pain that was aggravated by movement and weight bearing. </s><s n="s3.7;p3.48">He was fit and well the previous day. </s><s n="s4.7;p3.48">There was no history of swelling or bruising. </s><s n="s5.7;p3.48">No chest pain, dyspnoea or pyrexia. </s><s n="s6.7;p3.48">No history of hypertension or claudication. </s><s n="s7.7;p3.48">No recent travel or localised trauma. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined bold">PMH:</head><list type="bulleted"><head>Mr <name type="other"/>'s previous medical history includes:</head><item>Rheumatic fever (<name type="date"/>)</item><item>Venous stripping for varicose veins in the right leg (<name type="date"/>)</item><item>Gastro-oesophageal reflux disease (<name type="date"/>) - treated with a short course of PPI</item></list><p n="p4.48"><s n="s1.1;p4.48">No history of MI, CVA, TIA, COPD, DM or epilepsy </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined bold">DH:</head><list type="bulleted"><item>No regular medication. </item><item>NKDA</item><item>Occasional alcohol.</item><item>Smokes 12/day. Previously smoked 25/day for 50 years (62 pack years).</item></list><p n="p5.48"/></div2><div2><head rend="underlined bold">SH:</head><p n="p6.48"><s n="s1.4;p6.48">Mr <name type="other"/> works as a painter and decorator. </s><s n="s2.4;p6.48">He currently lives in a privately owned house with his wife. </s><s n="s3.4;p6.48">He also has two daughters and a son. </s><s n="s4.4;p6.48">He doesn't have any mobility problems and takes regular recreational walks. </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head>Analysis of history</head><p n="p7.48"><s n="s1.4;p7.48">Given the history of acute onset pain and paraesthesiae in an extremity, the most likely cause for <name type="other"/>'s presentation is acute limb ischaemia. </s><s n="s2.4;p7.48">This condition typically presents with six classic features (6P's), which include pain, paraesthesiae, pallor, pulselessness, perishingly cold and paralysis (due to nerve damage) and therefore additional signs should be sought upon physical examination. </s><s n="s3.4;p7.48">Acute ischaemia occurs due to sudden arterial occlusion and can arise as a result of thrombosis in situ, embolism, graft occlusion or occasionally trauma. </s><s n="s4.4;p7.48">Some of the conditions which may lead to emboli or thrombus formation are shown below (McLatchie and Leaper al, 2002): </s></p><list type="bulleted"><item>AF</item><item>Post MI thrombus (mural thrombus)</item><item>Atherosclerotic heart disease (e.g. Abdominal aorta, iliac, femoral, popliteal arteries)</item><item>Rheumatic valvular disease</item><item>Artheromatous plaques</item><item>Aneurysms </item><item>Paradoxical emboli (if PFO is present)</item><item>Iatrogenic (following interventional radiological procedures)</item></list><p n="p8.48"><s n="s1.6;p8.48">In the case of Mr <name type="other"/> there were several important features elicited from the history which may have predisposed him to vascular disease. </s><s n="s2.6;p8.48">These included a history of smoking, rheumatic fever and previous vascular disease. </s><s n="s3.6;p8.48">A history of intermittent claudication is also common in patients presenting with acute ischaemia, however its absence does not impact upon the diagnosis. </s><s n="s4.6;p8.48">There were no features in the history to suggest additional causes of acute onset pain such as trauma or a DVT. DVT is unlikely given that there was no history of swelling, recent surgery/travel, fever, redness or tachycardia. </s><s n="s5.6;p8.48">There were no features in the history to suggest a recent myocardial infarction. </s><s n="s6.6;p8.48">There was no history of Raynaud's syndrome. </s></p><p n="p9.48"><s n="s1.2;p9.48">Given the history of previous vascular problems, the physical examination will focus upon the peripheral vascular system. </s><s n="s2.2;p9.48">A general examination will also be performed in order to elicit any systemic signs which may indicate cardiovascular disease. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head>Physical examination and mental state examination</head><p n="p10.48"><s n="s1.1;p10.48">Obtained from admission notes: </s></p><div2><head rend="underlined bold">General</head><list type="simple"><item>Patient was alert. <hi rend="underlined">Severe pain in right foot. MEWS=4</hi></item><item rend="underlined">HR64. Sinus rhythm </item><item>BP 123/81</item><item rend="underlined">34.0c</item><item>RR21</item><item>99% on air</item><item>No JACCOLTG</item></list><p n="p11.48"/></div2><div2><head rend="underlined bold">Peripheral vascular</head><list type="simple"><item><list type="bulleted"><head>Inspection:</head><item rend="underlined">No swelling or redness</item><item rend="underlined">Both feet pale</item><item rend="underlined">Blue discolouration in right foot</item><item><hi rend="underlined">Dilated peripheral small veins in right foot</hi> (have been present since the venous stripping last year) </item></list></item><item><list type="bulleted"><head>Palpation:</head><item>Abdomen was soft and tender. No masses or AAA</item><item rend="underlined">Both feet were cold</item><item>Capillary refill in feet: Left- 4sec. <hi rend="underlined">Right-6sec</hi></item><item rend="underlined">Radial, brachial and femoral pulse present bilaterally. No radio-femoral delay. </item><item rend="underlined">Popliteal, posterior tibial and dorsali pedis pulses absent on right. </item><figure id="BAWE_0047d-fig.001"/><item rend="underlined">Intact motor function in legs. </item></list></item><item>Auscultation:</item><item>Detection of carotid, subclavian, aortic, renal and femoral bruits - not performed. </item></list><p n="p12.48"/></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head>Analysis of history and examination</head><p n="p13.48"><s n="s1.5;p13.48">Further signs indicating acute ischaemia were elicited upon physical examination such as cool extremities, pallor and the absence of distal peripheral pulses in the right leg. </s><s n="s2.5;p13.48">There was also delayed capillary refill on the right suggesting poor peripheral perfusion. </s><s n="s3.5;p13.48">Given that the right popliteal pulse was absent and there was no radio-femoral delay, the most likely most position for the arterial obstruction is in the superior femoral artery. </s><s n="s4.5;p13.48">Although clinically it is difficult to determine the precise cause for a thrombo-embolic event, some features of the history can be used to help differentiate between embolism and thrombosis. </s><s n="s5.5;p13.48">These are summarised below with significant findings highlighted in bold (Handa et al, 2000): </s></p><table id="BAWE_0047d-tab.001"><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p14.48"><s n="s1.3;p14.48">The above guidelines therefore suggest that Mr <name type="other"/>'s ischaemia was most likely due to an embolic event. </s><s n="s2.3;p14.48">The fact that capillary refill occurred, albeit delayed, in the right foot suggests that either the obstruction was incomplete or that some collaterals were available in order to maintain perfusion. </s><s n="s3.3;p14.48">Although it is impossible to determine the precise cause of the emboli without further investigation, there was no evidence to suggest the presence of atrial fibrillation or an abdominal aortic aneurysm. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head>Formulation of the patient's problem(s)</head><p n="p15.48"><s n="s1.5;p15.48">Mr <name type="other"/> is suffering from acute limb ischaemia as a result of a thrombo-embolic event. </s><s n="s2.5;p15.48">This condition represents an acute medical emergency which may require urgent angioplasty, embolectomy (using a fogarty catheter) or open surgery, and as a result Mr <name type="other"/> is likely to be placed under a considerable amount of stress. </s><s n="s3.5;p15.48">In addition, there is also the danger that amputation may be required if the limb is not viable or becomes gangrenous. </s><s n="s4.5;p15.48">Given this scenario, there would obviously be the potential for significant psychological and social issues to arise. </s><s n="s5.5;p15.48">For example amputation may have a substantial impact upon his mental health, his ability to maintain previous social interactions and employment. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head>Management</head><div2><head rend="underlined bold">Investigations</head><p rend="bulleted" n="p16.48"><s n="s1.2;p16.48">Prompt treatment is required for this condition and therefore diagnosis is usually based on clinical findings rather than extensive investigations. </s><s n="s2.2;p16.48">However if in doubt, an urgent arteriogram or Doppler USS should be performed to confirm the diagnosis. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p17.48"><s n="s1.2;p17.48">Following the initial treatment (see below) further investigations should be performed in order to help determine the underlying cause and to differentiate embolism from thrombosis. </s><s n="s2.2;p17.48">These investigations are outlined below along with some results for <name type="other"/> where available. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p18.48"><s n="s1.2;p18.48">FBC and clotting screen. </s><s n="s2.2;p18.48">LFT, D-dimers and cholesterol levels may also be desirable. </s></p><table id="BAWE_0047d-tab.002"><head>No abnormal results</head><row><cell/></row></table><list type="simple"><head>Duplex scan (Right leg):</head><item>Aorta - Clear and normal size</item><item>Iliacs, CFA, profunda origin and SFA - Clear</item><item>Popliteal - Occluded 1.3cm diameter aneurysm just above knee. </item><item>Below knee popliteal - Fairly clear.</item><item>Tibioperoneal trunk - Fairly clear. </item><item>PT - occluded just above the ankle distally</item><item>AT - Occluded in mid calf, but patent distal calf.</item><item>DP - Short 85% stenosis distally. </item></list><p n="p19.48"><s n="s1.1;p19.48">Following this report the most likely cause for this patient's localised pain in the dorsal region of the foot was obstruction of the posterior tibial, secondary to an embolus derived from within the popliteal aneurysm. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p20.48"><s n="s1.1;p20.48">CXR: Normal </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p21.48"><s n="s1.1;p21.48">Angiography (Not performed) </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p22.48"><s n="s1.1;p22.48">ECG (Results not available). </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined bold">Reassurance and explanation</head><p n="p23.48"><s n="s1.8;p23.48">"You are suffering from acute limb ischaemia, which basically means the blood supply to your leg has been interrupted. </s><s n="s2.8;p23.48">As a result the tissues have not been getting enough oxygen which has resulted in pain. </s><s n="s3.8;p23.48">This obstruction is probably due to a blood clot which has travelled down and blocked the arteries supplying your foot. </s><s n="s4.8;p23.48">We believe that the clot may have originated from an enlarged blood vessel further up, behind your knee. </s><s n="s5.8;p23.48">In order help restore the blood supply, we will place you on a heparin infusion which will thin your blood and prevent the clot from growing any larger. </s><s n="s6.8;p23.48">We may also need to do an operation to remove the clot depending on the severity of the obstruction. </s><s n="s7.8;p23.48">It is important that you appreciate that this is quite a serious situation which occasionally results in severe consequences especially as the tissues in your leg may have been starved of oxygen for too long. </s><s n="s8.8;p23.48">Do you have any questions?" </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined bold">Prescription/medical intervention</head><div3><head rend="underlined">Immediate intervention:</head><p rend="bulleted" n="p24.48"><s n="s1.3;p24.48">Patients who present with limb ischaemia are potentially seriously ill therefore remember ABC of resuscitation. </s><s n="s2.3;p24.48">Give 100% oxygen. </s><s n="s3.3;p24.48">Get senior help ASAP. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p25.48"><s n="s1.1;p25.48">Get venous access and start slow IVI of normal saline (one litre over 8 hours, unless the patient is very dehydrated in which case it should be faster). </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p26.48"><s n="s1.2;p26.48">Prescribe heparin to prevent propagation of the thrombus (loading dose of 5000 units followed by continuous infusion of 15 - 25 units/kg/hour). </s><s n="s2.2;p26.48">Be cautious of contra-indications such as aortic dissection, head injury, multiple trauma or recent surgery. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p27.48"><s n="s1.1;p27.48">Prescribe opiate analgesia if the patient is in severe pain </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p28.48"><s n="s1.2;p28.48">FBC, U+E, BM, LFT, cardiac enzymes, clotting, and group and save. </s><s n="s2.2;p28.48">A thrombophilia screen and lipid profile should also be considered. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p29.48"><s n="s1.1;p29.48">CXR and ECG, and if the patient is in AF arrange for cardiac monitoring. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p30.48"><s n="s1.1;p30.48">Insert a urinary catheter to monitor resuscitation if the patient is dehydrated. </s></p></div3><div3><head rend="underlined">Subsequent intervention: </head><p rend="bulleted" n="p31.48"><s n="s1.2;p31.48">Assess the severity of the ischaemia. </s><s n="s2.2;p31.48">There are three broad categories and this should be carried out by an experienced surgeon: </s></p><list type="ordered"><item>Irreversible with a non-salvageable limb. </item><item>Complete with an acutely threatened limb (At risk group)</item><item>Incomplete with a viable limb </item></list><p n="p32.48"><s n="s1.3;p32.48">In category one, amputation is inevitable and should be carried out promptly as delay may result in death from the systemic sequelae of muscle necrosis which include hyperkalaemia, acidosis, acute renal failure and sepsis. </s><s n="s2.3;p32.48">Patients in categories 2 and 3 should be continued on IVI heparin and the activated partial thromboplastin time (APTT) should be checked after 4-6 hours, with the aim of achieving a time twice the normal range (25 - 35secs). </s><s n="s3.3;p32.48">Mr <name type="other"/> exhibited some degree of perfusion as indicated by the presence of capillary refill and therefore he would have been placed in category 3, as the ischaemia was incomplete. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p33.48"><s n="s1.2;p33.48">In the acutely threatened group (i.e. </s><s n="s2.2;p33.48">2) vascular input may be required to treat the cause of obstruction e.g. </s></p><list type="ordered"><item>Embolic disease - Embolectomy (Fogarty balloon catheters used to retrieve thrombus) or Intra-arterial thrombolysis (e.g. Streptokinase, urokinase or TPA)</item><item>Thrombotic disease → intra-arterial thrombolysis, angioplasty or arterial bypass surgery</item></list></div3></div2><div2><head rend="underlined bold">Observation</head><p n="p34.48"><s n="s1.2;p34.48">Mr <name type="other"/> should be closely observed and regularly re-assessed until the underlying cause of the ischaemia has been treated, in order to ensure that the limb doesn't become non-viable. </s><s n="s2.2;p34.48">There are several occur complications which should be watched for: </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p35.48"><s n="s1.2;p35.48">Gangrene. </s><s n="s2.2;p35.48">If this develops, amputation is obviously necessary. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p36.48"><s n="s1.2;p36.48">Reperfusion injury. </s><s n="s2.2;p36.48">This may cause more damage than the initial ischaemia and can arise due to various causes e.g. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p37.48"><s n="s1.1;p37.48">Neutrophils suddenly migrate into the reperfused tissue causing enzymatic injury </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p38.48"><s n="s1.1;p38.48">There is an increase in capillary permeability therefore limb swelling may cause a compartment syndrome </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p39.48"><s n="s1.1;p39.48">Dead and damaged cells may leak causing acidosis, hyperkalaemia (leading to cardiac arrhythmias) and myoglobinaemia (leading to acute tubular necrosis). </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p40.48"><s n="s1.2;p40.48">Chronic pain syndrome. </s><s n="s2.2;p40.48">If complete ischaemia occurs it may cause permanent peripheral nerve injury. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined bold">Referral and team working</head><p n="p41.48"><s n="s1.3;p41.48">Referral to, or advice from an experienced general or vascular surgeon should be obtained as soon as the possible so that the limb and degree of ischaemia can be properly assessed. </s><s n="s2.3;p41.48">Follow-up with a vascular surgeon should be arranged, even if recannalization is achieved using heparin or thrombolysis, as further revascularization surgery is usually required later. </s><s n="s3.3;p41.48">Additional psychological or social support may be required, especially if amputation is necessary. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined bold">Advice and Prevention</head><p n="p42.48"><s n="s1.9;p42.48">Prevention is aimed at reducing factors for arterial disease. </s><s n="s2.9;p42.48">In particular, smoking should be stopped as it encourages the progression of the disease. </s><s n="s3.9;p42.48">Although they are not currently present, Mr <name type="other"/> should be regularly monitored for diabetes mellitus, hypertension and obesity, as these are likely to co-exist in many patients. </s><s n="s4.9;p42.48">A lipid profile should be obtained and hypercholesterolaemia treated appropriately with statins, to reduce disease progression. </s><s n="s5.9;p42.48">Advice regarding foot care should be provided to help avoid infection and trauma of the feet as patients will be prone to poor wound healing. </s><s n="s6.9;p42.48">Mr <name type="other"/> should be encouraged to continue his regular exercise programme, as this would also be beneficial and help maintain his quality of life. </s><s n="s7.9;p42.48">Low-dose aspirin should be given to reduce the risk of myocardial infarction and stroke. </s><s n="s8.9;p42.48">Aspirin may also help reduce the rate of re-occlusion. </s><s n="s9.9;p42.48">Long-term anticoagulants are not believed to be of significant benefit (Kumar &amp; Clarke, 2002). </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head>Outcome</head><p n="p43.48"><s n="s1.8;p43.48">Following admission Mr <name type="other"/> remained in hospital for eight days under observation. </s><s n="s2.8;p43.48">During this time he continued on IVI heparin for several days, until being transferred to oral warfarin. </s><s n="s3.8;p43.48">No immediate surgical intervention was necessary and there were no signs to indicate that his foot had suffered any irreversible damage as a result of the ischaemia. </s><s n="s4.8;p43.48">Mr <name type="other"/> reported that he had not suffered from any pain or paraesthesiae since the heparin was started and his OBS had been stable through his admission. </s><s n="s5.8;p43.48">After being transferred to warfarin his INR, APTT and PT levels were closely monitored until appropriate levels for discharge had been achieved. </s><s n="s6.8;p43.48">Prior to discharge levels of INR = 2.0, PT = 21 and APTTR = 1.2 were achieved indicating a stable anti-coagulated state. </s><s n="s7.8;p43.48">Although there is still some debate as to whether long-term anticoagulation is beneficial in these patients, it would be important to keep Mr <name type="other"/> on warfarin in the short-term, at least until he can be reviewed in clinic. </s><s n="s8.8;p43.48">At this stage further decisions could be made regarding the need for elective surgery to improve the arterial supply. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head>Evidence based care and issues for research</head><p n="p44.48"><s n="s1.5;p44.48">A recent Cochrane review compared the use of surgery with thrombolysis to determine the best initial management for acute limb ischaemia. </s><s n="s2.5;p44.48">It found that there was not enough evidence to support initial thrombolysis rather than initial surgery. </s><s n="s3.5;p44.48">It did however highlight the fact that thrombolysis may be associated with a higher risk of continued limb ischaemia and haemorrhagic complications (i.e. stroke), but then this risk of complications must be balanced against risks of surgery in individuals. </s><s n="s4.5;p44.48">In addition, there was no overall difference in the rates of limb salvage or death at one year between initial surgery and initial thrombolysis. </s><s n="s5.5;p44.48">The report therefore concluded that universal guidelines for initial treatment with either surgery or thrombolysis cannot be advocated based on the available evidence. </s></p><p n="p45.48"><s n="s1.3;p45.48">Following successful reperfusion, there is still some debate regarding whether long-term anticoagulation is beneficial in patients such as <name type="other"/> who are not suffering from AF. For example Campbell et al (2000) suggest that long-term oral anticoagulation is associated with reduced risk of recurrent limb ischaemia and amputation, however they admit that more research is needed to define the specific benefits and risks. </s><s n="s2.3;p45.48">In contrast, a further report suggested that patients without AF or a cardiac thrombus may not be at the same risk for recurrent events as those with these risk factors, and that therefore long-term anticoagulant therapy may not be as necessary in this group (Forbes et al, 2003). </s><s n="s3.3;p45.48">It therefore appears that the choice to use of long-term anticoagulants remains at discretion of treating physician. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head>Commentary</head><p n="p46.48"><s n="s1.1;p46.48">The prevalence of acute leg ischaemia is approximately 1 in 12,000 patients per year (Tidy, 2004). </s></p><p n="p47.48"><s n="s1.6;p47.48">In England and Wales approximately 5000 patients present each year, and the associated mortality is at least 20%, with a limb loss rate of 40%. </s><s n="s2.6;p47.48">Mortality is generally higher in patients presenting with embolic causes, while limb loss is higher in those with thrombosis. </s><s n="s3.6;p47.48">The majority of acute limb ischaemia is caused by acute thrombosis in a vessel with pre-existing atherosclerosis (60%) whilst embolism accounts for a further 30% of acutely ischaemic limbs. </s><s n="s4.6;p47.48">Most emboli (80%) have a cardiac cause and arise from the left atrium in patients with atrial fibrillation or following acute myocardial infarction. </s><s n="s5.6;p47.48">Less common cardiac sources include prosthetic valves, valve vegetations in endocarditis, "paradoxical" embolus and atrial myxoma. </s><s n="s6.6;p47.48">Arterial aneurysms account for a further 10% of emboli and may be in the aortic, iliac, femoral, popliteal, or subclavian arteries (Hickey et al, 1990). </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head>Impact on your learning</head><p n="p48.48"><s n="s1.4;p48.48">This case has provided to the opportunity to review the typical presentation and treatment of an acutely ischaemic limb. </s><s n="s2.4;p48.48">It has also highlighted the severity of the situation and the importance of prompt diagnosis and treatment in order to avoid the need for amputation. </s><s n="s3.4;p48.48">Speed is essential as complete acute limb ischaemia will lead to irreversible tissue damage within 6 hours unless the limb is revascularised, therefore it is also important that senior help is called for early on as this may lead to improved limb salvage and survival. </s><s n="s4.4;p48.48">It allowed the various types of surgical intervention, such embolectomy, to be studied. </s></p></div1></body><back><div1 type="bibliography"><head rend="underlined bold">References:</head><p>Campbell, W., Ridler, B. and Szymanska, T. (2000) Two-year follow-up after acute thromboembolic limb ischaemia: the importance of anticoagulation. <hi rend="italic">Eur J Vasc Endovasc Surg</hi>. 19(2):169-73</p><p>Forbes, T., DeRose, G. and Harris, K. (2002) Is long-term anticoagulation after acute thromboembolic limb ischemia always necessary? <hi rend="italic">Can J Surg</hi>. 45(5):337-40.</p><p>Handa, A., Turner, K. and Jones, A. (2000). Surgical Emergency: Acute ischaemic limb. <seg type="URL" n="http://www.studentbmj.com/issues/00/07/education/226.php"/>. Last accessed 21/9/2005.</p><p>Hickey, N., Crowson, M. and Simms, M. (1990) Emergency arterial reconstruction for acute ischaemia. <hi rend="italic">Br J Surg</hi> 77:680-1.</p><p>Kumar, P and Clark, M. (2002). 'Chapter 14: Respiratory disease' In Clinical Medicine (5<hi rend="sup">th</hi> edition). Saunders publishing </p><p>McLatchie, G. and Leaper, D. (2002). Oxford Handbook of Clinical Surgery (2<hi rend="sup">nd</hi> edition). Oxford University Press. New York. </p><p>Tidy, C. (2004). 'Limb Embolism And Ischaemia' on patient plus website. <seg type="URL" n="http://www.patient.co.uk/showdoc/40000242/"/>. Last accessed 22/9/2005.</p></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
