<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_0047f" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Subacute Infective Endocarditis</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">document consists of pro forma table giving section headings, along with notes detailing the expected contents of each section
</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">4</p><p n="date">2005-10</p><p n="module title">General Clinical Education</p><p n="module code">unknown</p><p n="genre family">Case study</p><p n="discipline">Medicine</p><p n="disciplinary group">LS</p><p n="grade">D</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">3574</p><p n="number of s-units">145</p><p n="number of p">48</p><p n="number of tables">0</p><p n="number of figures">4</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">14</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">0</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">24.6</p><p n="average s-units per p">3.0</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">m</p><p n="year of birth">1981</p><p n="first language">English</p><p n="education">UKA</p><p n="course">Medicine</p><p n="student ID">0047</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><titlePart>PORTFOLIO CASE N <hi rend="sup underlined">o</hi>: <hi rend="bold">7</hi> Patient Initials: <name type="other"/> Hospital Number: <name type="other"/> Age: 81 (<name type="date"/>) Gender: MALE</titlePart><docTitle><titlePart>Portfolio Case presentation number: 7</titlePart></docTitle></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="section"><head>Referral information</head><p n="p1.48"><s n="s1.2;p1.48">Mr <name type="other"/> arrived at <name type="other"/> hospital accident and emergency department by ambulance following a 999 call. </s><s n="s2.2;p1.48">He was subsequently transferred to a cardiology ward. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head>History</head><div2><head rend="underlined bold">PC</head><p n="p2.48"><s n="s1.5;p2.48">Mr <name type="other"/> was a pleasant 81 year old male who presented four days ago with a 6-week history of tiredness, low mood and occasional neck and shoulder pain. </s><s n="s2.5;p2.48">He complained of feeling generally "run down" during this period and had been struggling with his usual daily activities such as shopping. </s><s n="s3.5;p2.48">For a few days prior to his admission he also reported a cold sensation running across top of his back and shoulders and some occasional discomfort in left loin region. </s><s n="s4.5;p2.48">He did not report any pyrexia or additional symptoms to suggest an infection occurring in the last few months. </s><s n="s5.5;p2.48">Interestingly however he reported he couldn't remember a single time since childhood when he's had a temperature associated with an illness. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined bold">HPC</head><p n="p3.48"><s n="s1.4;p3.48">Six weeks ago, Mr <name type="other"/> was admitted to hospital whilst on holiday in <name type="other"/> after experiencing some acute chest pain. </s><s n="s2.4;p3.48">The pain was described by Mr <name type="other"/> as an "angina-like" central crushing chest pain. </s><s n="s3.4;p3.48">Upon admission no significant clinical signs or ECG abnormities were detected, however during his four day stay he was found to be anaemic (Hb 11.5g/dl, RBC 4.26x10 <hi rend="sup">12</hi>, PCV 36%) and suffering from a low platelet count (141x10 <hi rend="sup">9</hi>/L). </s><s n="s4.4;p3.48">As a result he was given 2 units of blood and discharged without further action. </s></p><p n="p4.48"><s n="s1.4;p4.48">His recent admission arose due to the concern of his relatives during a family gathering. </s><s n="s2.4;p4.48">Mr <name type="other"/> is generally a fairly active man who usually enjoys playing with his grandchildren when they visit. </s><s n="s3.4;p4.48">On the day of admission, he was unable to play with them and complained of exhaustion even at rest. </s><s n="s4.4;p4.48">Although his condition on this occasion had not increased in severity or differed from that of the previous 6 weeks, Mr <name type="other"/> had become notably more anxious his continuing state and his son decided enough was enough and called the paramedics. </s></p><p n="p5.48"><s n="s1.4;p5.48">In the past he has suffered from occasional angina, which is particularly exacerbated by cold windy weather and sudden exertion. </s><s n="s2.4;p5.48">Mr <name type="other"/> described these episodes as few and far between, as knows what triggers to avoid. </s><s n="s3.4;p5.48">As a result he doesn't usually suffer from any reduced exercise tolerance as long as he takes his time and rests when necessary. </s><s n="s4.4;p5.48">He even reported doing 10-20 minutes of light stretching everyday to keep fit. </s></p><p n="p6.48"><s n="s1.2;p6.48">When the pain does it occur it usually subsides within 5 minutes anyway and therefore he rarely uses his GTN spray. </s><s n="s2.2;p6.48">There has never been any associated breathlessness, PND, palpitations, dizziness or pedal oedema. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined bold">PMH</head><list type="bulleted"><head>Previous medical history includes the following:</head><item>Diphtheria during childhood</item><item>Malaria along with pneumonia and a lung abscess (<name type="date"/>) </item><item>Right potts fracture (<name type="date"/>)</item><item>Gout (<name type="date"/>) which has been mainly asymptomatic for 30-35years, although occasional flare-ups </item><item>Myocardial infarctions (<name type="date"/>, <name type="date"/> and <name type="date"/>)</item><item>Hypertension (since <name type="date"/>)</item><item>Bronchiectasis for which he receives daily postural drainage by his wife in order to prevent symptoms</item><item>Hard of hearing</item><item>No history of CVA, diabetes, asthma or rheumatic fever. No significant family history</item><item>Recently ceased using acetylcysteine and latanoprost eye drops as an earlier diagnosis of glaucoma was dismissed in March.</item></list><p n="p7.48"><s n="s1.1;p7.48">Previous surgery includes three coronary artery bypass grafts (<name type="date"/>, <name type="date"/> and <name type="date"/>) and cardioversion (<name type="date"/>). </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined bold">DH</head><p n="p8.48"><s n="s1.4;p8.48">NKDA although he strictly avoids oranges and grapefruit as they exacerbate his gout. </s><s n="s2.4;p8.48">He is an ex-smoker who quit 44yrs ago, after smoking 80/day for 20yrs. </s><s n="s3.4;p8.48">He only consumes occasional alcohol at present. </s><s n="s4.4;p8.48">No history of IV drug use. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined bold">Current Medication</head><list type="simple"><item>Frusemide 40mg PO od (Loop diuretic)</item><item>Bendroflumethiazide 2.5mg PO od (Thiazide diuretic)</item><item>Lisinopril 40mg PO od (ACE inhibitor)</item><item>Allopurinol 300mg PO bd (xanthine-oxidase inhibitor)</item><item>Ferrous sulphate 200mg PO bd</item><item>Nicorandil 10mg PO bd (potassium-channel activator)</item><item>Carvedilol 6.25mg PO bd (beta-blocker with arteriolar vasodilating action)</item><item>Simvastatin 20mg PO od (Lipid lowering drug)</item><item>Warfarin PO od - as per INR</item><item>Aspirin 75mg PO od</item><item>Paracetamol 1g PO PRN</item></list><list type="simple"><head>Additional drugs: GTN 300mcg PRN</head></list><p n="p9.48"/></div2><div2><head rend="underlined bold">SH</head><p n="p10.48"><s n="s1.8;p10.48">Mr <name type="other"/> retired as a pub owner at the age of 46, although he continued working part-time as a gardener and ambulance driver until his late sixties. </s><s n="s2.8;p10.48">He also served in the Australian special forces during the war, working in indo-china for the most part. </s><s n="s3.8;p10.48">Five weeks ago he travelled to the artic circle with some fellow war veterans. </s><s n="s4.8;p10.48">He currently lives with his wife in a privately owned bungalow. </s><s n="s5.8;p10.48">His wife is fit and healthy. </s><s n="s6.8;p10.48">Mr <name type="other"/> is usually independent and mobile, and therefore doesn't require any assistance with daily activities. </s><s n="s7.8;p10.48">He currently drives, although his exercise tolerance is apparently not an issue. </s><s n="s8.8;p10.48">They have a son (aged 45) who lives locally and visits 2-3 times a week with their two grandchildren. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined bold">Systems review</head><list type="simple"><item>No pedal oedema, PND or Orthopnea</item><item>No weight loss, loss of appetite, altered bowel habits, diarrhoea, vomiting, dysuria or haematuria</item><item>No SOB, cough or haemopytsis </item><item>No history of recent infection</item><item>Dental procedure 2 months ago</item></list><p n="p11.48"/></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head>Analysis of history</head><p n="p12.48"><s n="s1.4;p12.48">There are several salient features of the history which indicate infective endocarditis (IE) as the most likely cause for Mr <name type="other"/>'s symptoms. </s><s n="s2.4;p12.48">Although the majority of his symptoms (i.e. malaise, lethargy, rigors and anaemia) are non-specific, the fact that he has a history of cardiac disease and underwent a dental procedure just prior to the onset of symptoms should raise suspicion of IE. In addition, the onset of loin pain may be due to splenomegaly or immune-complex deposition which is commonly seen in IE. Given his current drug regime and history of heart disease, Mr <name type="other"/> is obviously suffering from a minor degree of heart failure (New York classification I). </s><s n="s3.4;p12.48">Fortunately however there was nothing to suggest that this had been exacerbated by the recent events, for example as a result of valve destruction. </s><s n="s4.4;p12.48">There was also nothing to suggest the occurrence of an infarction (e.g. arterial, pulmonary, coronary or cerebral) as a result of vegetation emboli. </s></p><p n="p13.48"><s n="s1.5;p13.48">When considering differential diagnoses at this stage, there are numerous conditions which could explain his main symptoms of malaise, lethargy and rigors and the association with a dental procedure may just be incidental. </s><s n="s2.5;p13.48">Following his recent hospital admission, anaemia would have to be a possible reason, especially if no underlying cause was previously determined. </s><s n="s3.5;p13.48">Secondly, despite the lack of pyrexia and cough, a LRTI may present in this way and given his bronchiectasis, Mr <name type="other"/> would have an increased susceptibility to such infections. </s><s n="s4.5;p13.48">Elderly patients are also prone to UTI's which can often present with non-specific systemic symptoms. </s><s n="s5.5;p13.48">Other conditions such as SLE, sickle cell disease and atrial myxoma (primary cardiac tumour) can also mimic IE. </s></p><p n="p14.48"><s n="s1.1;p14.48">During the physical examination it would be necessary to assess the cardiovascular, respiratory and abdominal systems as well as searching for more specific clinical signs which indicate IE. Important clinical signs of IE include the following: </s></p><list type="bulleted"><item>Finger clubbing</item><item>New cardiac murmurs</item><item>Splinter haemorrhages</item><item>Janeway lesions (Flat, non-tender, blanchable red spots found on palms and soles - shown below)</item><item>Osler's nodes (Tender, erythematous, pea-sized nodules seen in the pulp of the fingers - shown below)</item><item>Petechiae on skin, palate and conjunctiva</item><item>Splenomegaly</item><item>Roth spots upon fundoscopy</item></list><figure id="BAWE_0047f-pic.001"/><figure id="BAWE_0047f-pic.002"/><figure id="BAWE_0047f-pic.003"/><p n="p15.48"><s n="s1.1;p15.48">The admission notes from A+E will also be obtained in order to provide an insight into Mr <name type="other"/>'s condition upon arrival. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head>Physical examination and mental state examination</head><div2><head rend="underlined bold">Upon arrival</head><list type="simple"><item>Temp 39.7c, BP 131/65, RR16, O2 sat = 96%</item><item>Very cold to touch, GCS = 15</item><item>Right basal crepitations with no wheeze.</item></list><p n="p16.48"/></div2><div2><head><hi rend="underlined bold">General Examination</hi> (on day 4)</head><list type="simple"><item>Temp 35.7 <hi rend="sup">o</hi>c, BP 100/60, RR 15</item><item>Pale conjunctiva and nail beds indicating anaemia</item><item>Splinter haemorrhages present</item><item>No Jaundice, clubbing, cyanosis, oedema, lymphadenopathy or tremor</item><item>No Janeway lesions or Oslers nodes</item><item>No fundoscope was available</item></list><p n="p17.48"/></div2><div2><head rend="underlined bold">CVS</head><p n="p18.48"><s n="s1.1;p18.48">HS 1 + 2 + ejection systolic murmur </s></p><p n="p19.48"><s n="s1.2;p19.48">Murmur was loudest in mitral region, but heard throughout precordium. </s><s n="s2.2;p19.48">Indicating mitral regurgitation. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined bold">RS</head><p n="p20.48"><s n="s1.3;p20.48">Few left basal crepitations but there was no percussive irritability. </s><s n="s2.3;p20.48">No other significant signs. </s><s n="s3.3;p20.48">AP CXR revealed slightly large heart and lower left zone shadowing </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined bold">GI </head><p n="p21.48"><s n="s1.4;p21.48">Abdomen soft and non-tender. </s><s n="s2.4;p21.48">No masses felt. </s><s n="s3.4;p21.48">Bowel sounds present. </s><s n="s4.4;p21.48">No hepatosplenomegaly. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined bold">CNS</head><p n="p22.48"><s n="s1.2;p22.48">Not formally assessed. </s><s n="s2.2;p22.48">All limbs moving </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head>Analysis of history and examination</head><p n="p23.48"><s n="s1.5;p23.48">The admission notes revealed that Mr <name type="other"/> was pyrexic (39.7c) on arrival. </s><s n="s2.5;p23.48">He also had cold peripheries and a reduced oxygen saturation which may indicate a degree of anaemia. </s><s n="s3.5;p23.48">Significant findings from the systems examinations included splinter haemorrhages, anaemia and the detection of a previously undocumented MR murmur. </s><s n="s4.5;p23.48">These all point towards a diagnosis of IE as previously suggested by the history. </s><s n="s5.5;p23.48">Although some basal lung crepitations were heard indicating consolidation, Mr <name type="other"/> was not suffering from any specific respiratory symptoms and therefore they were assumed to be due to some minor mucus collection as would be expected in bronchiectasis - There was nothing to suggest it was infected at present. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head>Formulation of the patient's problem(s)</head><p n="p24.48"><s n="s1.5;p24.48">Mr <name type="other"/> appears to be suffering from infective endocarditis, which has presented in an atypical fashion due to the absence of pyrexia. </s><s n="s2.5;p24.48">In addition to the physical diagnosis, it is important to consider the psychosocial implications this condition may have upon Mr <name type="other"/>. </s><s n="s3.5;p24.48">Despite his history of cardiac disease, Mr <name type="other"/> exhibits remarkably good health for his age, which allows him to lead a fully independent life and even participate in a daily exercise routine. </s><s n="s4.5;p24.48">His reported anxiety and low mood during the past 6 weeks obviously highlights his concern for his health, and therefore it would be important to consider the impact a complication such as severe heart failure would have upon his lifestyle and mental health. </s><s n="s5.5;p24.48">Fortunately however there does appear to be significant family support network available to care for him in the event of chronic complications. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head>Management</head><div2><head rend="underlined bold">Investigations</head><p n="p25.48"><s n="s1.3;p25.48">In suspected cases of infective endocarditis, further investigation is essential in order to confirm the diagnosis. </s><s n="s2.3;p25.48">Some of the necessary investigations are described below, along with actual results obtained from Mr <name type="other"/> where available. </s><s n="s3.3;p25.48">It is however important to remember that the majority of these investigations (with the exception of Echo and ECG) are non-specific, and are instead used to confirm the presence of sepsis rather than IE itself. </s></p><div3><head rend="underlined">Blood tests</head><p n="p26.48"><s n="s1.4;p26.48">A normochromic, normocytic anaemia is common in IE and both CRP and ESR levels are usually increased. </s><s n="s2.4;p26.48">A polymorphonuclear leucocytosis is also common and thrombocytopenia can occasionally occur. </s><s n="s3.4;p26.48"><hi rend="bold">No ESR level was available for Mr <name type="other"/>, however anaemia (Hb 9.3g/dl, MCV 83.7fl), leucocytosis (WCC 60) and thrombocytopenia (PLT 135x109/l) were all present along with a raised CRP (44mg/l)</hi>. </s><s n="s4.4;p26.48">It is also worth noting that his INR was 1.3, which indicates that his anti-coagulation medication should be increased in order to achieve a suitable therapeutic level. </s></p><p n="p27.48"><s n="s1.6;p27.48">Despite these results, the single most important test for diagnosing endocarditis is a blood culture. </s><s n="s2.6;p27.48">Three sets of blood should be taken at different times over 24 hours from different sites. </s><s n="s3.6;p27.48">Endocarditis is most commonly caused by bacteria such as streptococcus viridans (35-50%), staphylococcus aureus or enterococci although it may also arise as a result of fungal infections (e.g. </s><s n="s4.6;p27.48">Candida, Aspergillus, Histoplasma) or due to rarer causes such as malignancy and SLE (Libman-Sacks endocarditis). </s><s rend="bold" n="s5.6;p27.48">In the case of Mr <name type="other"/> his initial blood culture revealed the presence of streptococcus bacteria, most likely to be S.viridans. </s><s rend="bold" n="s6.6;p27.48">This was later confirmed in two additional cultures. </s></p></div3><div3><head rend="underlined">Biochemistry Screen </head><p n="p28.48"><s n="s1.5;p28.48">Liver biochemistry is often mildly disturbed. </s><s n="s2.5;p28.48">In particular, serum alkaline phosphatase is usually raised. </s><s n="s3.5;p28.48"><hi rend="bold">Mr <name type="other"/>'s bilirubin (22umol/l) and AST (45iu/l) were slightly raised whilst his ALP level (242iu/l) was significantly increased</hi>. </s><s n="s4.5;p28.48">Albumin (34g/l) was also slightly below the normal reference range, although this is a common finding in many acute and chronic illnesses. </s><s n="s5.5;p28.48">His urea (13.3mmol/l) was raised as well, although his creatinine (132umol/l), K+ (3.8mmol/l) and Na (138mmol/l) were normal. </s></p></div3><div3><head rend="underlined">Immunoglobulins and complement </head><p n="p29.48"><s n="s1.2;p29.48">Serum immunoglobulins are increased, but total complement and C3 complement are decreased owing to immune complex formation. </s><s n="s2.2;p29.48">Circulating immune complexes are present in more than 70% of cases but are not routinely measured as in this case. </s></p></div3><div3><head rend="underlined">Urine </head><p n="p30.48"><s n="s1.2;p30.48">Proteinuria may occur and microscopic haematuria is nearly always present. </s><s n="s2.2;p30.48"><hi rend="bold">Mr <name type="other"/>'s urine revealed blood (+++) and protein (+)</hi>, but was negative for nitrates and leucocytes, therefore dismissing the earlier differential of a UTI. </s></p></div3><div3><head rend="underlined">Echocardiogram and ECG</head><p n="p31.48"><s n="s1.7;p31.48">Echocardiography can be used in suspected endocarditis to demonstrate bacterial vegetations, however a negative echo will not necessary exclude endocarditis as vegetations less than 3-4mm are unlikely to be visible. </s><s n="s2.7;p31.48">Furthermore all the leaflets of the aortic, pulmonary and tricuspid valves may not be visualised in every patient. </s><s n="s3.7;p31.48"><hi rend="bold">Mr <name type="other"/>'s echo didn't reveal any obvious bacterial vegetations, however it did show slight dilation of all chambers and the presence of slow AF</hi>. </s><s n="s4.7;p31.48">The AF was also confirmed on the ECG which revealed a HR of 61 and irregularly irregular <name type="other"/>S complexes with absent P waves. </s><s n="s5.7;p31.48">Given the high suspicion of endocarditis, it would be beneficial to carry out a Trans-oesophageal echocardiogram (TOE) which is more sensitive and is generally better for visualising mitral lesions and aortic root abscesses. </s><s n="s6.7;p31.48">The echo also revealed mild to moderate regurgitation in all four valves, mild septal impairment with otherwise fairly well preserved systolic function and no hypertrophy. </s><s n="s7.7;p31.48">There was no evidence of RVH. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0047f-pic.004"/><p n="p32.48"><s n="s1.4;p32.48">The majority of the results obtained from the further investigations were consistent with a diagnosis of IE, in particular the positive blood culture which demonstrated growth of Streptococcus viridans. </s><s n="s2.4;p32.48">As a result of these investigations it is possible to determine a definitive diagnosis of endocarditis by using the <hi rend="bold">Duke Criteria</hi> which are outlined below (Longmore et al., 2004). </s><s n="s3.4;p32.48">A diagnosis of infective endocarditis can be concluded when either 2 major, 1 major + 3 minor, or 5 minor criteria are present. </s><s n="s4.4;p32.48">In the case of Mr <name type="other"/> he fulfils both major criteria (i.e. having a positive culture and new murmur) as well as some of the minor criteria (i.e. temp of 39.7 on admission and vascular signs such as splinter haemorrhages). </s></p><list type="ordered"><head>Major criteria </head><item>Positive blood culture demonstrating a typical organism in 2 separate cultures or, three persistently positive blood cultures at 12hrs apart </item><item>Endocardium involvement: Therefore either a positive echocardiogram (i.e. vegetation or an abscess) or a new valvular regurgitation </item></list><list type="ordered"><head>Minor criteria</head><item>Fever >38c</item><item>Predisposition (Known cardiac valve lesion, IV drug user)</item><item>Vascular/immunological signs</item><item>Positive blood culture not meeting major criteria</item><item>Positive echocardiogram not meeting major criteria</item></list><p n="p33.48"><s n="s1.3;p33.48">Despite the diagnosis, it will be important to carry out repeat cultures, blood tests and biochemical screens during the course of his treatment in order to ensure the correct response to therapy. </s><s n="s2.3;p33.48">Given the presence of some basal lung shadowing, a repeat CXR would also be desirable to monitor progress. </s><s n="s3.3;p33.48">A TOE should also be carried out ASAP to allow visualisation of the mitral valve, especially considering the MR murmur detected clinically. </s></p></div3></div2><div2><head rend="underlined bold">Reassurance and explanation</head><p n="p34.48"><s n="s1.9;p34.48">"We believe that your symptoms are the result of a condition known as infective endocarditis. </s><s n="s2.9;p34.48">Endocarditis is an infection of the innermost lining of the heart - the endothelium. </s><s n="s3.9;p34.48">This occurs when bacteria get into your blood stream and are able to colonise and grow on the heart tissue. </s><s n="s4.9;p34.48">Not everyone who gets bacteria in the blood develops endocarditis, however those that do develop it often have a cardiac abnormality that makes it easier for bacteria to invade the endothelium of the heart. </s><s n="s5.9;p34.48">Endocarditis can result in damage to the heart valves, the rings of connective tissue that surround the valves, as well as the inner linings of the heart chambers themselves. </s><s n="s6.9;p34.48">This is the reason we have been using the ultrasound machine in order to examine them. </s><s n="s7.9;p34.48">From the blood tests, we have been able to identify the type of bacteria which is causing your problems and have therefore started you on antibiotics which will hopefully fight the infection. </s><s n="s8.9;p34.48">At this stage it is difficult to predict the outcome of the infection, and whether or not there will be any long-term complications associated with it. </s><s n="s9.9;p34.48">However as we have now identified the cause we can continue to target it using the appropriate antibiotics." </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined bold">Prescription/medical intervention</head><p n="p35.48"><s n="s1.2;p35.48">As soon as infective endocarditis is suspected it is important to initiate empirical treatment whilst awaiting the blood culture results. </s><s n="s2.2;p35.48">The treatment of choice is as follows: </s></p><list type="bulleted"><item rend="bold">Gentamicin 80mg/12h IV (Aminoglycoside)</item><item rend="bold">Benzylpenicillin 1.2g/4hr IV (Penicillin)</item><item rend="bold">Flucloxacillin 2g/6h IV should also be included in severely ill patients to cover staphlococci</item></list><p n="p36.48"><s n="s1.1;p36.48">Once streptococcus has been confirmed as the infective agent, the drug regime should be changed to the following: </s></p><list type="bulleted"><item rend="bold">Benzylpenicillin 1.2g/4hr IV for 2-4 weeks</item><item rend="bold">Amoxicillin 1g/8h PO for 2 weeks</item><item rend="bold">It may also be necessary to add gentamicin 80mg/12h IV if the MIC>0.01ng/ml</item></list><p n="p37.48"><s n="s1.1;p37.48">It may also be necessary to treat Mr <name type="other"/>'s anaemia with a further transfusion if his anaemia is still evident following treatment of the bacteraemia, or should he begin to develop chest pain, dizziness or shortness of breath. </s></p><p n="p38.48"><s n="s1.1;p38.48">In some cases cardiac surgery may be indicated should any of the following occur: </s></p><list type="bulleted"><item>Heart failure</item><item>Valvular obstruction</item><item>Repeated emboli</item><item>Positive blood cultures or relapse after several days of the best available antibiotic therapy indicates the need for a valve replacement</item><item>Valve ring or myocardial abscesses will require surgical drainage</item><item>Patients with aortic valve endocarditis who develop 2 <hi rend="sup">nd</hi> or 3 <hi rend="sup">rd</hi> degree heart block will require valve replacement</item><item>Unstable infected prosthetic valves require replacement </item><item>(Baliga, 2003; Longmore et al, 2004)</item></list></div2><div2><head rend="underlined bold">Observation</head><p n="p39.48"><s n="s1.3;p39.48">In patients requiring gentamicin for prolonged periods, regular monitoring of serum levels will be required in order to avoid toxic concentration levels. </s><s n="s2.3;p39.48">Serum levels should not exceed 5-10mg/l at peak (one hour post dose) or drop below 2mg/l (trough). </s><s n="s3.3;p39.48">Clinical signs of gentamicin toxicity include tinnitius, deafness, nystagmus, vertigo and renal failure. </s></p><p n="p40.48"><s n="s1.6;p40.48">As previously mentioned there are various complications of IE which should be observed for. </s><s n="s2.6;p40.48">Firstly, destruction of the heart valves can result in congestive heart failure. </s><s n="s3.6;p40.48">Secondly, small emboli composed of bacteria or fungus, as well as platelets and fibrin can flick off the valves and cause various systemic problems such as strokes, kidney failure, MI and damage to the gastrointestinal organs. </s><s n="s4.6;p40.48">Septic emboli may also result in distal infections such as brain abscesses. </s><s n="s5.6;p40.48">Endocarditis can also lead to heart arrhythmias or result in heart abscesses which typically prove very hard to treat. </s><s n="s6.6;p40.48">Glomerulonephritis may also arise and is associated with low complement levels and immune complexes. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined bold">Referral and team working</head><p n="p41.48"><s n="s1.2;p41.48">Mr <name type="other"/> was referred to the <name type="other"/> hospital for his TOE. The results were not available at the time. </s><s n="s2.2;p41.48">It is important to liaise with a microbiologist when carrying out the repeat blood cultures for IE in order to ensure that appropriate therapeutic concentrations of antibiotics are being provided when targeting the bacteraemia. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined bold">Advice and Prevention</head><p n="p42.48"><s n="s1.2;p42.48">Mr <name type="other"/> should be informed that prophylactic antibiotics should be used in future whenever he undergoes a medical procedure with a high probability of introducing bacteria into the blood. </s><s n="s2.2;p42.48">For example, dental procedures, bronchoscopy, upper respiratory tract surgery, urinary tract procedures and gastrointestinal procedures all confer an increased risk of bacteraemia and therefore, an increased risk of infective endocarditis in those individuals with predisposing cardiac lesions. </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head>Outcome</head><p n="p43.48"><s n="s1.2;p43.48">Six days after being admitted and starting the antibiotics, Mr <name type="other"/> reported a significant improvement in his health. </s><s n="s2.2;p43.48">As shown above, his temperature had fallen significantly over the first four days, and his blood results from day 6 also started to show some improvement particularly his WCC. </s></p><list type="simple"><item rend="bold">Hb 10.8g/dl</item><item rend="bold">PLT 149 x109/L</item><item>WCC 5.6 x10 <hi rend="sup">9</hi>/L</item><item rend="bold">ALP 207iu/L </item><item>K+ 3.8mmol/L </item><item>Na 138mmol/L </item><item>Creatinine 110umol/L</item><item rend="bold">Urea 10.6</item></list><p n="p44.48"><s n="s1.3;p44.48">With regard to prognosis, the mortality rate in patients with sensitive streptococcus infections is 6%. </s><s n="s2.3;p44.48">This is considerably better than the 30+% rate observed in patients with staphylococcus, enterococci or fungal infections. </s><s n="s3.3;p44.48">There are however a few additional factors which have a detrimental effect upon prognosis including: </s></p><list type="bulleted"><item>Heart failure (No symptoms present in this case)</item><item>Infected prosthetic valves (N/A)</item><item>Elderly patients</item><item>The presence of a valve ring or myocardial abscess (No indication from TTE, awaiting TOE)</item></list><p n="p45.48"><s n="s1.2;p45.48">Given that Mr <name type="other"/> is in a relatively good physical condition for his age, with limited co-morbidity, and the fact that he has shown a significant improvement since starting treatment, there appears to be a good prognosis for him. </s><s n="s2.2;p45.48">However, further follow up was not possible at the time. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head>Evidence based care and issues for research</head><p n="p46.48"><s n="s1.3;p46.48">Murtagh B et al (2003) highlighted the difficulties associated with diagnosing infective endocarditis and the important role the Duke criteria has assumed over the past decade in allowing early detection of this often occult disease. </s><s n="s2.3;p46.48">In addition they also described the increasing importance of echocardiography, in particular TOE which is much more sensitive and specific than transthoracic echocardiography (TTE) at detecting vegetations less than 10 mm in diameter. </s><s n="s3.3;p46.48">This is of great value considering that it is vegetations >10mm in diameter which are thought to be at the greatest risk of embolising. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head>Commentary</head><p n="p47.48"><s n="s1.1;p47.48">Infective endocarditis is three times more common in males than in females, and although it may occur in a people of any age, the frequency is increased in elderly individuals, with 25-50% of cases occurring in those older than 60 years (Brusch, 2005). </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head>Impact on your learning</head><p n="p48.48"><s n="s1.4;p48.48">This case has provided an opportunity to study infective endocarditis in much greater detail. </s><s n="s2.4;p48.48">In particular it has highlighted the difficulties which may arise in diagnosing the condition due to its diverse and non-specific clinical presentation. </s><s n="s3.4;p48.48">The value of the Duke criteria when trying to confirm a diagnosis has also been exemplified. </s><s n="s4.4;p48.48">Furthermore it has allowed the management and possible complications to be studied. </s></p></div1></body><back><div1 type="bibliography"><head rend="underlined bold">References</head><p>Baliga, R. (2003). 250 Cases in clinical medicine (3<hi rend="sup">rd</hi> Edition). W. B. Saunders limited. London </p><p>Brusch, J. (2005). Infective Endocarditis. <seg type="URL" n="http://www.emedicine.com/med/topic671.htm"/>. Accessed on 12/7/2005</p><p>Longmore, M., Wilkinson, I. and Rajagopalan (2004). Oxford Handbook of Clinical Medicine (6<hi rend="sup">th</hi> Edition). Oxford University Press. New York</p><p>Murtagh, B., Frazier, O. and Letsou, G. (2003) Diagnosis and management of bacterial endocarditis. Current Opinions in Cardiology. 18: 106-10</p></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
