<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_0047b" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Asthma</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">document consists of pro forma table giving section headings, along with notes detailing the expected contents of each section
</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">4</p><p n="date">2005-10</p><p n="module title">General Clinical Education</p><p n="module code">unknown</p><p n="genre family">Case study</p><p n="discipline">Medicine</p><p n="disciplinary group">LS</p><p n="grade">D</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">2551</p><p n="number of s-units">107</p><p n="number of p">33</p><p n="number of tables">1</p><p n="number of figures">0</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">14</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">0</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">23.8</p><p n="average s-units per p">3.2</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">m</p><p n="year of birth">1981</p><p n="first language">English</p><p n="education">UKA</p><p n="course">Medicine</p><p n="student ID">0047</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><titlePart>PORTFOLIO CASE N <hi rend="sup underlined">o</hi>: <hi rend="bold">9</hi> Patient Initials: <name type="other"/> Hospital Number: Kept on separate list Age: 48 (<name type="date"/>) Gender: M</titlePart><docTitle><titlePart>Portfolio Case presentation number: 9</titlePart></docTitle></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="section"><head>Referral information</head><p n="p1.33"><s n="s1.1;p1.33"><name type="other"/> was on an emergency referral SOS list with his respiratory physician, and was therefore admitted directly to the respiratory ward following self-referral. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head>History</head><div2><head rend="underlined bold">PC: </head><p n="p2.33"><s n="s1.1;p2.33">Mr <name type="other"/> presented with breathlessness, wheezing and a significantly reduced PEF. He was unable speak and was using accessory muscles to aid breathing. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined bold">HPC: </head><p n="p3.33"><s n="s1.7;p3.33">Mr <name type="other"/> had been suffering from a mild chest infection for approximately ten days, producing about a tablespoon of sputum daily. </s><s n="s2.7;p3.33">He is a known asthmatic and had been taking 20mg prednisolone daily during this period in order to maintain control of his asthma. </s><s n="s3.7;p3.33">He reported that he had been becoming increasingly breathless over the two days prior to his admission. </s><s n="s4.7;p3.33">The night before his admission he was woken from sleeping by extreme breathlessness and wheezing. </s><s n="s5.7;p3.33">He tried using nebulised salbutamol several times throughout the night, however this had little effect and his PEFR fell to 250. </s><s n="s6.7;p3.33">A PEFR of 250 represented a significant reduction over his usual documented PEFR which was reported 550-600, and as high as 700 "on a good day". </s><s n="s7.7;p3.33">He contacted the respiratory unit and was subsequently admitted directly to the ward. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined bold">PMH: </head><p n="p4.33"><s n="s1.7;p4.33"><name type="other"/> has a well-documented history of ongoing asthma since the age of three. </s><s n="s2.7;p4.33">Throughout his childhood he suffered from very severe asthma, which resulted in near continuous admission between October and March as well as several additional admissions. </s><s n="s3.7;p4.33">Despite a comparatively moderate period during his late teens and early twenties, his asthma became problematic again once he reached thirty. </s><s n="s4.7;p4.33">His last hospital admission was in May 2004. </s><s n="s5.7;p4.33">This was one of three hospital admissions related to his asthma last year, one of which resulted in a 3-week stay. </s><s n="s6.7;p4.33">In recent years, he has required hospital admission on average once a year, however this used to be as much as 3-5/year. </s><s n="s7.7;p4.33">In 1999 and 2002 he required admission to ICU. </s></p><p n="p5.33"><s n="s1.2;p5.33">His exercise tolerance varies daily, ranging from no limitation to a few metres on a bad day. </s><s n="s2.2;p5.33">Mr <name type="other"/> is a particularly fragile asthmatic who is allergic to numerous allergens, however he suggested southern and foreign air were relieving factors. </s></p><p n="p6.33"><s n="s1.3;p6.33">Mr <name type="other"/> reported that he has learned to control his asthma appropriately. </s><s n="s2.3;p6.33">Whenever necessary he will increase the dose of his home medication to control his symptoms and initiate prednisolone if needed. </s><s n="s3.3;p6.33">If such measures prove unsuccessful and he feels like he is losing control, he will contact the hospital for additional support. </s></p><p n="p7.33"><s n="s1.5;p7.33">His additional medical history includes osteoporosis (which has resulted in 3-4 wedge fractures) and osteoarthritis (hips, knees, shoulder) which had occurred secondary to his history of frequent steroid use. </s><s n="s2.5;p7.33">He previously used 5-10mg prednisolone for over 15years. </s><s n="s3.5;p7.33">He also suffers from BPH and frequent UTI's. </s><s n="s4.5;p7.33">There is no history of hayfever or eczema. </s><s n="s5.5;p7.33">Previous surgery includes arthroscopy (both knees, shoulder) and cleft palate correction. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined bold">Drugs and allergies: </head><p n="p8.33"><s n="s1.4;p8.33"><name type="other"/> is a non-smoker who consumes 10-12units of alcohol per week. </s><s n="s2.4;p8.33">Known drug allergy to erythromycin. </s><s n="s3.4;p8.33">He has allergies to all animals and has had a positive reaction to all allergens used during skin prick testing. </s><s n="s4.4;p8.33">There was no recollection of exposure to known allergens prior to this acute episode, however obviously his degree of hypersensitivity would make identifying such triggers difficult. </s></p><list type="simple"><head>His regular medication includes:</head><item>Alendronate sodium 70mg once weekly (bisphosphonate for bone protection)</item><item>Ventolin acuhaler PRN</item><item>Seretide 500 acuhaler 2 puffs bd (one puff contains 500mcg Fluticasone and 50mcg salmeterol)</item><item>Flixonase 2 sprays (100mcg) each nostril bd</item><item>Trimethoprim 200mg od (UTI prophylaxis)</item><item>Tamsulonsin 400mcg od (alpha blocker for BPH)</item><item>Lansoprazole 30mg od (PPI)</item><item>Theophylline (Dose depends on brand - brand unknown) - MUST MONITOR BLOOD LEVELS due to narrow therapeutic margin. Optimum plasma concentration is 10-20mg/litre </item><item>Co-dydramol 10/500 qds (Dihydrocodeine and paracetamol for arthritis)</item><item>Home nebs - salbutamol 5mg and saline PRN</item><item>No home oxygen</item></list></div2><div2><head rend="underlined bold">SH: </head><p n="p9.33"><s n="s1.6;p9.33"><name type="other"/> works as a marketing director. </s><s n="s2.6;p9.33">He lives in a privately owned house with his wife and son. </s><s n="s3.6;p9.33">His 15-year-old son also suffers from asthma, although it is well controlled. </s><s n="s4.6;p9.33">His wife works for a department store. </s><s n="s5.6;p9.33">As she usually works from home, she is able to visit <name type="other"/> frequently when he is admitted. </s><s n="s6.6;p9.33">There was no history of recent travel. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined bold">FH:</head><p n="p10.33"><s n="s1.1;p10.33">Mother died aged 78 from CCF </s></p><p n="p11.33"><s n="s1.1;p11.33">Father died of oesophageal cancer aged 78 </s></p><p n="p12.33"><s n="s1.1;p12.33">Grandfather died of MI </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head>Analysis of history</head><p n="p13.33"><s n="s1.11;p13.33">The presenting symptoms (i.e. wheezing, breathlessness, reduced PEFR) are typical of an acute asthma attack and given Mr <name type="other"/>'s history of chronic asthma, this is the most likely diagnosis. </s><s n="s2.11;p13.33">The onset of breathlessness at night also points towards asthma. </s><s n="s3.11;p13.33">As <name type="other"/> appears to be a particularly fragile asthmatic, it is likely that his recent infection has precipitated this acute attack. </s><s n="s4.11;p13.33">On admission <name type="other"/> was unable to complete sentences and his PEFR was significantly reduced (38% of normal) indicating an acute severe attack. </s><s n="s5.11;p13.33">A PEFR between 33%-50% usually suggests a severe attack, whilst &lt;38% is regarded as life-threatening. </s><s n="s6.11;p13.33">On examination, the respiratory and cardiovascular systems should be examined. </s><s n="s7.11;p13.33">Specific signs should be sought in order to allow the severity to be assessed further. </s><s n="s8.11;p13.33">For example an increased respiratory rate (>25/min) and tachycardia (>110/min) would be expected in a severe attack. </s><s n="s9.11;p13.33">However bradycardia, hypotension and a reduced respiratory effort (or silent chest) may develop as the episode increases in severity and becomes life threatening. </s><s n="s10.11;p13.33">Other signs associated with hypoxia may also occur in life-threatening attack such as cyanosis, exhaustion and confusion. </s><s n="s11.11;p13.33">ABG values are also important for assessing the severity therefore results will be obtained if available. </s></p><p n="p14.33"><s n="s1.5;p14.33">Important differential diagnoses to exclude would include an acute infective exacerbation of COPD, pulmonary oedema (cardiac asthma), URTI, PE, pneumothorax, anaphylactic shock and airway obstruction by a foreign body or tumour. </s><s n="s2.5;p14.33">Most of these are unlikely given his history. </s><s n="s3.5;p14.33">For example Mr <name type="other"/> has no history of COPD, has never smoked and has not travelled recently. </s><s n="s4.5;p14.33">On admission, a CXR would be performed and therefore allow pneumothorax, pleural oedema and infection to be ruled out. </s><s n="s5.5;p14.33">The recent chest infection however may have exacerbated his asthma leading to this acute attack therefore signs of infection should be sought on the CXR. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head>Physical examination and mental state examination</head><div2><head rend="underlined bold">On admission:</head><list type="simple"><item>BP 150/65</item><item rend="underlined">pO2 100% on 28% O2</item><item>HR 75/min</item><item>Apyrexial</item><item rend="underlined">RR 25</item><item rend="underlined">Wheeze in upper zones</item><item rend="underlined">Silent chest in lower zones</item><item rend="underlined">ABG</item><item>pH 7.39</item><item>pO <hi rend="sub">2</hi> 16.9</item><item>pCO <hi rend="sub">2</hi> 4.9</item><item>HCO <hi rend="sub">3</hi> 21.7mmol/L</item><item>BE 2.6mmol/L</item></list><p n="p15.33"/></div2><div2><head rend="underlined bold">Review following initial treatment:</head><list type="simple"><head rend="underlined">RESP</head><item>RR 16</item><item>Symmetrical chest expansion </item><item rend="underlined">Dull percussion at left base</item><item rend="underlined">Reduced BS in bases. Bilateral scattered expiratory wheeze </item><item rend="underlined">Left basal course crackles with reduced vocal fremitus</item><item>CXR not available</item></list><list type="simple"><head rend="underlined">CVS</head><item>Apex not displaced</item><item>HS 1+2+0 </item></list><p n="p16.33"/></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head>Analysis of history and examination</head><p n="p17.33"><s n="s1.7;p17.33">A PEFR of 38%, RR>25 and the inability to complete sentences all correlate with a acute severe attack as outlined in the BTS guidelines for asthma management. </s><s n="s2.7;p17.33">Although Mr <name type="other"/> also exhibited a silent chest in the lower zones, there were no additional signs to suggest a life-threatening attack. </s><s n="s3.7;p17.33">For example SpO <hi rend="sub">2</hi>=100%, PaO <hi rend="sub">2</hi>=16.9O and there was no evidence of hypotension, bradycardia or cyanosis. </s><s n="s4.7;p17.33">Physical examination also revealed evidence to suggest a lower respiratory tract infection, particularly in the left lung. </s><s n="s5.7;p17.33">However a chest x-ray was not available to allow radiological confirmation. </s><s n="s6.7;p17.33">It is proposed that the silent lower lobes initially detected may have been due to partially collapsed lobes arising due to the LRTI, however again this would radiological confirmation. </s><s n="s7.7;p17.33">Following examination therefore the most likely diagnosis is an acute severe asthma attack secondary to the recent LRTI. There was no evidence to suggest a cardiac origin for the breathlessness and no ABG abnormalities were detected. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head>Formulation of the patient's problem(s)</head><p n="p18.33"><s n="s1.4;p18.33">Mr <name type="other"/> is suffering from an acute severe asthma attack and a LRTI. As <name type="other"/> is an intelligent patient who understands his condition well and knows when to approach the hospital for additional treatment, this recent attack is unlikely to have any psychological implications upon his health. </s><s n="s2.4;p18.33">However it is important to consider that <name type="other"/> may be concerned about the possibility of requiring admission to ICU or another prolonged stay. </s><s n="s3.4;p18.33">In particular the implications a prolonged stay would have upon his family and employment. </s><s n="s4.4;p18.33">Fortunately <name type="other"/> reported having an extremely supportive family and employer, however these are undoubtedly important issues to consider in asthmatic patients especially as emotion stress is itself a proven trigger factor. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head>Management</head><div2><head rend="underlined bold">Investigations</head><p n="p19.33"><s n="s1.2;p19.33">In addition to the PEF, ABG and CXR mentioned above, further investigations such as FBC, U&amp;E and sputum MC&amp;S should be performed on asthmatics suffering from an acute exacerbation. </s><s n="s2.2;p19.33">Although these investigations were requested, no results were available at the time. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined bold">Reassurance and explanation</head><p n="p20.33"><s n="s1.4;p20.33">"Although you correctly started high dose prednisolone as soon as you noticed you were becoming ill, it appears that the recent infection has upset the finite control of your asthma. </s><s n="s2.4;p20.33">Therefore we will need to admit you to the respiratory ward so that your symptoms can be monitored and treated appropriately until they become stable. </s><s n="s3.4;p20.33">Whilst you're in hospital we will treat the infection with antibiotics and alter your medication appropriately so that control of your asthma can be regained. </s><s n="s4.4;p20.33">Do you have any questions?" </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined bold">Prescription/medical intervention</head><p n="p21.33"><s n="s1.2;p21.33">When presented with a suspected asthma attack, treatment should be started immediately before any investigations are initiated. </s><s n="s2.2;p21.33">An outline of how to manage acute asthma is shown below: </s></p><list type="bulleted"><head>1) Immediate treatment:</head><item>Sit patient up and give high dose O <hi rend="sub">2</hi></item><item>Nebulised β<hi rend="sub">2</hi> agonist bronchodilator e.g. salbutamol 5mg plus ipratropium bromide 0.5mg</item><item>Hydrocortisone 100mg IV or prednisolone 30mg PO (both if severe)</item><item>CXR to exclude pneumothorax</item></list><list type="bulleted"><head>1b) And if life threatening add:</head><item>Inform ITU</item><item>Magnesium sulphate 1.2-2g IV over 20mins</item><item>Nebulised salbutamol every 15mins, or 10mg/hr continuously</item></list><list type="bulleted"><head>2) If improving:</head><item>40-60% O <hi rend="sub">2 </hi></item><item>Prednisolone 30-60mg/24hr PO</item><item>Nebulised salbutamol 4hourly</item><item>Monitor PEF and PaO <hi rend="sub">2</hi></item></list><list type="bulleted"><head>2b) If not improving after 15-30mins:</head><item>Continue 100% O <hi rend="sub">2</hi></item><item>Nebulised salbutamol every 15mins, or 10mg/hr continuously</item><item>Continue ipratropium 0.5mg every 4-6hr</item></list><list type="bulleted"><head>3) If still not improving: </head><item>Discuss transfer to ITU</item><item>Repeat salbutamol nebuliser every 15mins</item><item>MgSO <hi rend="sub">4</hi> if not already given</item><item>If not on theophylline already, Aminophylline 5mg/kg IVI over 20mins (loading dose)</item></list><list type="bulleted"><head>When administering treatment, the effects should be carefully monitored:</head><item>PEF if possible 15-30mins after treatment then at frequent intervals</item><item>Pulse oximetry - maintain above 92</item><item>Recheck ABG especially if initial abnormalities were detected</item></list><list type="bulleted"><head>In the case of <name type="other"/>, the following medication was administered: </head><item>Nebulised salbutamol 5mg</item><item>Hydrocortisone 200mg IV</item><item>Nebulised ipratropium bromide 0.5g (phosphodiesterase inhibitor)</item><item>Aminophylline 350mg IVI over 20mins (despite frequent theophylline use) </item><item>Magnesium sulphate 2g/50ml saline IVI over 50mins</item></list><p n="p22.33"><s n="s1.1;p22.33">After his initially symptoms had been stabilised, he was placed on prednisolone 40mg PO od as well as amoxycillin 500mg PO tds to fight the LRTI. His regular out patient medication was also resumed in order to prevent further disruption of his asthma maintenance. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined bold">Observation</head><p n="p23.33"><s n="s1.2;p23.33">It would be important to monitor <name type="other"/>'s PEFR whilst he remains an in-patient, in order to assess his lung function and response to therapy. </s><s n="s2.2;p23.33">The results are shown below: </s></p><table id="BAWE_0047b-tab.001"><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p24.33"><s n="s1.3;p24.33">The measurements show an obvious improvement his PEF since admission. </s><s n="s2.3;p24.33">As <name type="other"/> usually records a PEF of 550-600 this would be the desirable level to achieve before considering discharge. </s><s n="s3.3;p24.33">It would also be important to ensure that he was stable on his TTO medication prior to discharge. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined bold">Referral and team working</head><p n="p25.33"><s n="s1.3;p25.33"><name type="other"/>'s GP should be notified of the admission and any alterations made to his regular medication. </s><s n="s2.3;p25.33">All patients admitted with severe asthma should also be followed up by a respiratory specialist for one year as per the british thoracic society (BTS) guidelines. </s><s n="s3.3;p25.33">An initial clinic follow-up at two weeks was arranged for <name type="other"/>. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined bold">Advice and Prevention</head><p n="p26.33"><s n="s1.3;p26.33"><name type="other"/> was provided with home oxygen prior to discharge in order to provide symptomatic relief in case of further episodes of acute dyspnoea. </s><s n="s2.3;p26.33">He already understands the need to initiate prednisolone therapy during times when asthma control becomes challenging and regularly receives the necessary influenza vaccinations. </s><s n="s3.3;p26.33">Although there are numerous non-pharmaceutical measures which could be suggested for managing asthma, the majority of these are unproven and not recommended by the BTS. They are therefore unlikely to beneficial to <name type="other"/> especially considering his experience living with the disease. </s></p><p n="p27.33"><s n="s1.1;p27.33">For general reference some of the suggested recommendations are shown below: </s></p><list type="bulleted"><head>Primary prevention:</head><item>Encourage breast feeding</item><item>Smoking cessation should be encouraged in parents and parents-to-be</item></list><list type="bulleted"><head>Secondary prevention:</head><item>Reducing levels of house dust mites may help in committed families who use multiple approaches, however the BTS asthma guidelines suggest there is no evidence indicating that single interventions are sufficient to help those with asthma.</item><item>Removal of pets when a recognisable allergy is detected</item><item>Encourage smoking cessation</item></list><list type="bulleted"><head>Dietary manipulation</head><item>Weight control is recommended for obese patients</item></list><p n="p28.33"><s n="s1.1;p28.33">Complementary therapy </s></p><p n="p29.33"><s n="s1.2;p29.33">A recent Cochrane review (Yorke &amp; Shuldham, updated 2005) indicated that family therapy may have a role alongside pharmacotherapy in the treatment of difficult childhood asthma. </s><s n="s2.2;p29.33">Although this recommendation was subsequently adopted by the BTS in its guidelines, the studies upon which they were based appear to be limited by extremely small study sizes (55 children) and therefore further studies are obviously required. </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head>Outcome</head><p n="p30.33"><s n="s1.5;p30.33"><name type="other"/> was followed-up as an in-patient two days after admission. </s><s n="s2.5;p30.33">On examination he was sat up comfortably and could easily talk without becoming breathless (RR=11). </s><s n="s3.5;p30.33">His PEFR was stable at around 380. </s><s n="s4.5;p30.33">Two weeks later at clinic, he reported a stable PEFR of around 450-500 and despite one incidence of dyspnoea, which required the use of home oxygen (for ~1.5hrs) he was generally well. </s><s n="s5.5;p30.33">No further fixed follow-up was therefore arranged. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head>Evidence based care and issues for research</head><p n="p31.33"><s n="s1.3;p31.33">As a result of the high prevalence of asthma within the general population, a vast amount of information exists within the literature. </s><s n="s2.3;p31.33">Fortunately the british thoracic society has published guidelines to aid physicians with the diagnosis and treatment of asthma based upon the best available evidence. </s><s n="s3.3;p31.33">The 'British guideline on the management of asthma' therefore provides a valuable resource when treating asthmatics (British Thoracic Society, 2003). </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head>Commentary</head><div2><head rend="underlined bold">Epidemiology</head><p n="p32.33"><s n="s1.4;p32.33">Asthma is increasing in prevalence, particularly in the Western world, where approximately 5-15% of the population may be symptomatic and receiving treatment. </s><s n="s2.4;p32.33">However despite improvements in treatment, mortality rates have also been decreasing and asthma accounts for almost 1500 deaths per year in the UK. Interestingly there is also a geographical variation, with the condition being more common in developed countries such UK, New Zealand and Australia where some of the highest rates can be found. </s><s n="s3.4;p32.33">In contrast, asthma is much more rare in Africa, Central Europe and Far Eastern countries such as China and Malaysia. </s><s n="s4.4;p32.33">Studies investigating this variation have shown a correlation with 'Westernised' life-styles that include living conditions that favour house-dust mites and atmospheric pollution (Ward et al, 2002). </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head>Impact on your learning</head><p n="p33.33"><s n="s1.5;p33.33">This case has highlighted the importance of rapidly diagnosing and initiating treatment in patients with a suspected asthma attack. </s><s n="s2.5;p33.33">In a case such as this it is essential that appropriate therapy is given immediately with a view to regaining control of the asthma, no matter what the cause of the attack. </s><s n="s3.5;p33.33">These patients should be closely supervised and subsequent re-assessment should be carried out frequently to ensure that any further deterioration is detected and addressed appropriately. </s><s n="s4.5;p33.33">Once the patient has been stabilised, further investigations should be performed to identify potential causes for the acute exacerbation (e.g. infection, recent change in medication). </s><s n="s5.5;p33.33">This case has also highlighted the importance of patient education and the need to consider psychosocial factors such as unemployment when treating chronic asthmatics. </s></p></div1></body><back><div1 type="bibliography"><head rend="underlined bold">References:</head><p>British guideline on the management of asthma - Quick reference guide. 2003. British Thoracic Society. <seg type="URL" n="www.brit-thoracic.org.uk"/>. Last accessed 3/8/2005 </p><p>Kumar, P and Clark, M. (2002). 'Chapter 14: Respiratory disease' In Clinical Medicine (5<hi rend="sup">th</hi> edition). Saunders publishing </p><p>Longmore, M., Wilkinson, I. and Rajagopalan (2004). Oxford Handbook of Clinical Medicine (6<hi rend="sup">th</hi> Edition). Oxford University Press. New York</p><p>Ward, J., Ward, J., Wiener, C. &amp; Leach, R. (2002). 'Chapter 21: Asthma' In The Respiratory system at a glance. Blackwell publishing </p><p>Yorke, J. and Shuldham, C. (2005) Family therapy for chronic asthma in children. Cochrane Database Syst Rev. 99900089</p></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
