<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_0047g" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Diabetes Insipidus</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">document consists of pro forma table giving section headings, along with notes detailing the expected contents of each section
</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">4</p><p n="date">2005-10</p><p n="module title">General Clinical Education</p><p n="module code">unknown</p><p n="genre family">Case study</p><p n="discipline">Medicine</p><p n="disciplinary group">LS</p><p n="grade">D</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">2843</p><p n="number of s-units">148</p><p n="number of p">58</p><p n="number of tables">2</p><p n="number of figures">0</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">3</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">10</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">19.2</p><p n="average s-units per p">2.6</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">m</p><p n="year of birth">1981</p><p n="first language">English</p><p n="education">UKA</p><p n="course">Medicine</p><p n="student ID">0047</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><titlePart>PORTFOLIO CASE N <hi rend="sup underlined">o</hi>: <hi rend="bold">6</hi> Patient Initials: <name type="other"/> Hospital Number: Kept on separate list Age: 24 (<name type="date"/>) Gender: FEMALE</titlePart><docTitle><titlePart>Portfolio Case presentation number: 6</titlePart></docTitle></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="section"><head>Referral information</head><p n="p1.58"><s n="s1.1;p1.58">Miss <name type="other"/> arrived at <name type="other"/> hospital's accident and emergency department by ambulance following a road traffic accident </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head>History</head><div2><head rend="underlined bold">PC</head><p n="p2.58"><s n="s1.2;p2.58"><name type="other"/> arrived in the A+E department three weeks ago following an RTA. She was unconscious with a GCS of 6 and was suffering from multiple lacerations to her face and feet. </s><s n="s2.2;p2.58">Later whilst recovering she was found to have polyuria. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined bold">HPC</head><p n="p3.58"><s n="s1.8;p3.58"><name type="other"/> was walking along a country lane at approximately 23.30hrs when she was hit by a van. </s><s n="s2.8;p3.58">When the paramedics arrived at the scene, she was able to maintain her own airway but had a GCS of 6 (E2,M3,V1). </s><s n="s3.8;p3.58">A classic 'bullseye' impact was noted on the windscreen indicating a head impact. </s><s n="s4.8;p3.58">Upon arrival at the A+E department, rapid sequence induction was administered in order to allow intubation and ventilation. <name type="other"/> was haemodynamically stable and arterial blood gases were normal. </s><s n="s5.8;p3.58">Her chest was clear and the pelvis was stable. </s><s n="s6.8;p3.58">A laceration to her right scalp was sutured. </s><s n="s7.8;p3.58">X-ray images of her chest, pelvis, c-spine and feet were obtained along with CT scans of her head and c-spine. </s><s n="s8.8;p3.58">The following abnormalities were detected: </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p4.58"><s n="s1.1;p4.58">Displaced # left distal phalanx of hallux (along with wound flap to plantar aspect) </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p5.58"><s n="s1.1;p5.58">Undisplaced # left proximal phalanx of 2 <hi rend="sup">nd</hi>, 3 <hi rend="sup">rd</hi>, 4 <hi rend="sup">th</hi> and 5 <hi rend="sup">th</hi> toes </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p6.58"><s n="s1.1;p6.58"># C7 spinous process </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p7.58"><s n="s1.3;p7.58">Head CT revealed widespread haemorrhagic 'dot' contusions in all corners of cortex and the brainstem. </s><s n="s2.3;p7.58">These characteristics are consistent with diffuse axonal injury (DAI). </s><s n="s3.3;p7.58">DAI is typically associated with shearing injuries which occur due to when sudden acceleration/deceleration or rotational forces are placed upon the brain (i.e. shearing of axons, rather than contra-coup injury). </s></p><p n="p8.58"><s n="s1.5;p8.58">A left backslab plaster was placed on left leg to stabilise the multiple fractures following an orthopaedic consult. </s><s n="s2.5;p8.58">Several hours after her initial assessment at the A+E department, <name type="other"/> was transferred to the ICU at <name type="other"/> Hospital with a GCS = 9 and placed on an intracranial pressure (ICP) monitor. </s><s n="s3.5;p8.58">While in ICU she became haemodynamically unstable with her haemoglobin dropping below 7g/dl with no obvious cause, therefore an explorative laparotomy was carried out. </s><s n="s4.5;p8.58">The surgery didn't reveal any abnormalities. </s><s n="s5.5;p8.58">After 4 days in ICU, <name type="other"/> was moved onto the wards with a GCS = 12. </s></p><p n="p9.58"><s n="s1.6;p9.58">Fifteen days following the accident, <name type="other"/> had a GCS = 15 with intermittent confusion. </s><s n="s2.6;p9.58">She was afebrile, BP was 120/70 and her blood glucose levels was stable. </s><s n="s3.6;p9.58">She was documented to have shown a marked improvement in speech, mobility and general condition. </s><s n="s4.6;p9.58">Once her NG tube was removed, she began eating 3 meals per day although she required help with feeding and washing. </s><s n="s5.6;p9.58">She had also begun to mobilise slowly. </s><s n="s6.6;p9.58">It was at this stage that she was noticed to be producing an excessive amount of urine (>3L/day). </s></p><p n="p10.58"><s n="s1.3;p10.58">When assessed today (Day 21) <name type="other"/> was conscious, alert and her speech was intelligent, although she was clearly suffering from a mild degree of confusion. </s><s n="s2.3;p10.58">She could only provide a limited history with regard to her presenting complaint due to some anteriograde amnesia (i.e. she had no recollection of why she was in hospital or how she came to be there). </s><s n="s3.3;p10.58">She was however able to provide detailed information regarding her current symptoms, PMH, DH and SH. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined bold">PMH</head><list type="bulleted"><head>Previous medical history includes the following:</head><item>Bulimia and anorexia (since aged 18)</item><item>Reported having always suffered from a degree of hypotension </item><item>No other significant medical conditions or surgery</item></list><p n="p11.58"/></div2><div2><head rend="underlined bold">DH</head><p n="p12.58"><s n="s1.1;p12.58"><name type="other"/> smokes tobacco (5-10/day) and drinks occasional alcohol. </s></p><p n="p13.58"><s n="s1.1;p13.58">NKDA. Current medication includes enoxaparin 20mg SC od (LMW heparin). </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined bold">SH</head><p n="p14.58"><s n="s1.1;p14.58"><name type="other"/> is currently unemployed living with her parents. </s></p><p n="p15.58"><s n="s1.1;p15.58">Previously graduated from Anglia Polytechnic University in Cambridge. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined bold">SR</head><div3><head>CNS:</head><list type="simple"><item>Occasional blurred vision associated with waking and rising from supine position - no diplopia</item><item>No history of headaches, visual loss, flashes or vertigo </item><item>No peripheral weakness or loss of sensation</item><item>No dysphagia, dysarthria or dysphasia</item></list><p n="p16.58"/></div3><div3><head>GI:</head><list type="simple"><item>Polyuria and polydipsia. No increase in urinary frequency</item><item>Occasional urinary incontinence, bowels ok</item><item>Complained of occasional "tingling" sensation in abdomen</item></list><p n="p17.58"/></div3><div3><head>Functional status:</head><p n="p18.58"><s n="s1.1;p18.58">Gradually increasing mobility - able to walk with assistance but stated that a 'limp' resulting from the physical presence of the backslab was the main hindrance </s></p></div3></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head>Analysis of history</head><p n="p19.58"><s n="s1.2;p19.58">Despite the extent of this young lady's initial injuries following the RTA, she is fortunately continuing to make a steady and progressive recovery. </s><s n="s2.2;p19.58">With regard to further analysis and diagnosis, this case will therefore focus upon the excessive urinary output and polydipsia which was detected during her recovery phase, as this provides a valuable opportunity to discuss the investigation and management of acute polyuria. </s></p><div2><head rend="underlined">Background</head><p n="p20.58"><s n="s1.6;p20.58">Under normal physiological conditions thirst and water regulation are largely controlled by anti-diuretic hormone (ADH, or vasopressin), which is synthesized in the hypothalamus. </s><s n="s2.6;p20.58">ADH then migrates in neurosecretory granules along axonal pathways to the posterior pituitary. </s><s n="s3.6;p20.58">Pituitary disease alone without hypothalamic involvement therefore does not lead to ADH deficiency as the hormone can still 'leak' from the damaged end of the intact axon. </s><s n="s4.6;p20.58">At normal concentrations the kidney is the predominant site of action of ADH. ADH acts via two receptors known as V1 and V2. </s><s n="s5.6;p20.58">Stimulation of the V2 receptors allows the collecting tubule to become permeable to water, thus permitting reabsorption of hypotonic luminal fluid. </s><s n="s6.6;p20.58">ACH therefore reduces diuresis and results in overall retention of water. </s></p><p n="p21.58"><s n="s1.5;p21.58">Release of ADH is controlled by osmoreceptors in the anterior hypothalamus which sense changes in plasma osmolarity. </s><s n="s2.5;p21.58">ADH secretion is suppressed at levels below 280 mOsm/kg, thus allowing maximal water diuresis. </s><s n="s3.5;p21.58">When plasma osmolarity rises above this level, ADH release occurs in direct proportion to plasma osmolarity in order to promote appropriate retention of water. </s><s n="s4.5;p21.58">Maximum ADH release occurs when the plasma osmolarity reaches 295 mOsm/kg. </s><s n="s5.5;p21.58">This represents the upper limit of normal plasma osmolarity, after which the sensation of thirst is experienced (usually at about 298 mOsm/kg) </s></p><p n="p22.58"><s n="s1.1;p22.58">Acquired polyuria can therefore arise due to either: </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p23.58"><s n="s1.1;p23.58">Lack of ADH production: resulting from hypothalamic disease (Cranial diabetes insipidus) </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p24.58"><s n="s1.1;p24.58">Lack of response of kidneys to ADH: renal tubules are insensitive to vasopressin due to abnormal receptors (Nephrogenic diabetes insipidus) </s></p><p n="p25.58"><s n="s1.5;p25.58">Both these conditions, however, are comparatively rare and it is therefore important that commoner causes of polyuria are ruled out prior to further investigation. </s><s n="s2.5;p25.58">Diabetes mellitus is an extremely common cause of polyuria, due the osmotic diuresis it induces. </s><s n="s3.5;p25.58">DM should therefore be excluded first by testing blood glucose levels. </s><s n="s4.5;p25.58">Secondly, a full medication history should be obtained to exclude the use of any therapeutic diuretic agents or excessive IV fluids. </s><s n="s5.5;p25.58">A full biochemical screen should also be carried out as renal tubular function may be impaired by electrolyte abnormalities, such as hypokalaemia or hypercalcaemia. </s></p><p n="p26.58"><s n="s1.1;p26.58">Once these causes have been excluded it is then possible to consider some specific causes of DI. A list of differentials is outlined below (Adapted from Longmore et al, 2004) </s></p><table id="BAWE_0047g-tab.001"><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p27.58"><s n="s1.6;p27.58">In the case of <name type="other"/>, her blood glucose and electrolyte levels were within the normal range and her only medication was LMW heparin. </s><s n="s2.6;p27.58">This suggests that DM, drugs and electrolyte imbalances would be unlikely causes of the polyuria. </s><s n="s3.6;p27.58">Given the acute onset of symptoms and associated head injuries, causes such as malignancy would also be unlikely. </s><s n="s4.6;p27.58">The most likely cause for <name type="other"/>'s excessive urine output is cranial DI secondary to her head injuries. </s><s n="s5.6;p27.58">It is also possible that a degree of sub-clinical renal damage occurred during her recent trauma, leading to nephrogenic DI. With regard to physical examination there are no specific clinical signs which help to clarify the cause of the polyuria, although it would be important to assess whether she was significantly dehydrated. </s><s n="s6.6;p27.58">Given her history of head injuries and occasional abdominal discomfort, a full neurological examination will be performed along with an abdominal exam. </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head>Physical examination and mental state examination</head><div2><head rend="underlined bold">General examination (on day 21)</head><p n="p28.58"><s n="s1.1;p28.58">Patient was sat up in a chair, appeared comfortable and alert (GCS = 15). </s></p><p n="p29.58"><s n="s1.1;p29.58">Left leg - backslab plaster to knee </s></p><p n="p30.58"><s n="s1.1;p30.58">Skin not overtly dry, no reduced skin turgor, no postural hypotension </s></p><div3><head rend="underlined">CN Exam</head><p n="p31.58"><s n="s1.1;p31.58">No abnormalities detected </s></p><p n="p32.58"><s n="s1.1;p32.58">Fundoscopy was omitted </s></p></div3><div3><head rend="underlined">PNS exam</head><p n="p33.58"><s n="s1.1;p33.58">Normal tone, power, sensation, reflexes and co-ordination. </s></p></div3><div3><head rend="underlined">Abdo Exam</head><p n="p34.58"><s n="s1.1;p34.58">Recent laparotomy wound </s></p><p n="p35.58"><s n="s1.4;p35.58">Abdomen was soft and non-tender. </s><s n="s2.4;p35.58">No masses felt. </s><s n="s3.4;p35.58">No organomegaly. </s><s n="s4.4;p35.58">No bladder enlargement. </s></p></div3></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head>Analysis of history and examination</head><p n="p36.58"><s n="s1.3;p36.58">No significant signs were elicited during the examination, however this would be expected in the case of diabetes insipidus. </s><s n="s2.3;p36.58">In order to confirm a diagnosis of diabetes insipidus, a water deprivation test should be performed. </s><s n="s3.3;p36.58">This test would also allow differentiation between cranial and nephrogenic DI. No neurological abnormalities were detected and the abdominal tingling was most likely to be a result of the laparotomy wound. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head>Formulation of the patient's problem(s)</head><p n="p37.58"><s n="s1.9;p37.58">Miss <name type="other"/> appears to be suffering from cranial diabetes insipidus as a result of the head injuries sustained during the RTA. Confirmation of this diagnosis will however require a water deprivation test. </s><s n="s2.9;p37.58">In addition to this possible diagnosis, <name type="other"/> is still recovering from severe head injuries and multiple fractures and will require a significant period of rehabilitation. </s><s n="s3.9;p37.58">Even then a complete recovery can by no means be guaranteed. </s><s n="s4.9;p37.58">The recent events are also likely to have a significant psychological impact upon <name type="other"/>, not only will she have to deal with the psychological trauma associated with her RTA injuries but also a possible diagnosis of DI which will require life long therapy. </s><s n="s5.9;p37.58">In this case, extra support may be required in order to help her deal with the psychological issues, particularly to prevent the recurrence of eating disorders. </s><s n="s6.9;p37.58">With regard to her social situation, <name type="other"/> is fortunate enough to have a close supportive family, however her age must also be considered in the context of her head injuries. </s><s n="s7.9;p37.58">This young graduate is only 24 and previously lead a fully independent life. </s><s n="s8.9;p37.58">She is now faced with the possibility that her mobility and degree of independence may be limited in future. </s><s n="s9.9;p37.58">Fortunately diabetes insipidus wouldn't necessarily have a significant social impact if controlled appropriately. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head>Management</head><div2><head rend="underlined bold">Investigations</head><p n="p38.58"><s n="s1.2;p38.58">Confirming a diagnosis of diabetes insipidus requires the use of the water deprivation test, however the condition can easily be excluded if the osmolality of a first morning urine sample exceeds 600mosmol/kg. </s><s n="s2.2;p38.58">The procedure for the water deprivation test is outlined below: </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p39.58"><s n="s1.2;p39.58">The test should be carried out in the morning shortly after waking. </s><s n="s2.2;p39.58">Prior to the test foods, fluids, smoking and drugs such as carbamazepine (which have an ADH inducing activity) should be avoided. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p40.58"><s n="s1.1;p40.58">Then monitor serum and urine osmolality, and weight at regular intervals for up to 8 hours </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p41.58"><s n="s1.1;p41.58">Administer desmopressin if serum osmolality >300mOsm/kg and/or urine osmolality >600mOsm/kg </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p42.58"><s n="s1.1;p42.58">Stop test immediately if more than 3% of starting body weight is lost. </s></p><div3><head rend="underlined">Normal response: </head><p n="p43.58"><s n="s1.1;p43.58">Urine will become increasingly concentrated i.e. >600 mOsm/kg </s></p></div3><div3><head rend="underlined">DI response: </head><p n="p44.58"><s n="s1.1;p44.58">Urine will become abnormally dilute (&lt;400 mOsm/kg) and /or serum osmolality may rise above normal range (275-295mOsm/kg) without adequate urine concentration. </s></p><p n="p45.58"><s n="s1.1;p45.58">A response to desmopressin (i.e. increasing urine osmolality by >50%) indicates cranial DI </s></p><p n="p46.58"><s n="s1.1;p46.58">The results of the water deprivation test are shown below: </s></p><table id="BAWE_0047g-tab.002"><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p47.58"><s n="s1.4;p47.58">These results clearly show that during the water deprivation test, there was failure to concentrate the urine resulting in a decreasing urine osmolality. </s><s n="s2.4;p47.58">Although the serum osmolality remained stable, there was a significant increase in serum sodium observed. </s><s n="s3.4;p47.58">Urine osmolality returned to 561mOsm/kg an hour after desmopressin 2ug SC was administered at 12.00. </s><s n="s4.4;p47.58">A diagnosis of cranial DI was therefore confirmed. </s></p></div3></div2><div2><head rend="underlined bold">Reassurance and explanation</head><p n="p48.58"><s n="s1.8;p48.58">"We have discovered that the excessive urine you have been producing is due to a condition known as diabetes insipidus. </s><s n="s2.8;p48.58">Despite the similar names, diabetes insipidus is not related to diabetes mellitus. </s><s n="s3.8;p48.58">It occurs when a part of your brain stops producing a hormone that helps concentrate your urine. </s><s n="s4.8;p48.58">As a result, your kidneys can't concentrate urine very well; so more water is passed and you feel the need to drink more often. </s><s n="s5.8;p48.58">We believe that your body has stopped producing this hormone as a result of the head injuries you suffered. </s><s n="s6.8;p48.58">We can treat this condition by giving you a replacement for the hormone, which we will start straight away in order to reduce your symptoms. </s><s n="s7.8;p48.58">This may either be a temporary or permanent condition which has developed, however it is difficult to tell at this stage. </s><s n="s8.8;p48.58">Do you have any questions?" </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined bold">Prescription/medical intervention</head><p n="p49.58"><s n="s1.5;p49.58">Treatment for cranial DI involves replacing the ADH deficiency using a synthetic ADH analogue known as desmopressin (DDAVP). </s><s n="s2.5;p49.58">This is possible because unlike in nephrogenic DI, the kidneys are still capable of responding to the hormonal influence. </s><s n="s3.5;p49.58">Whilst an inpatient <name type="other"/> should be given <hi rend="bold">desmopressin 2ug bd SC or IM</hi>. </s><s n="s4.5;p49.58">Prior to discharge, the method of administered should be switched to either oral tablets (200ug td) or an intranasal spray (10-20ug od/bd) as these would prove more practical in future. </s><s n="s5.5;p49.58">It would be important to switch to one of these methods whilst under supervision as an inpatient so that the correct daily dose could be to be determined without risking hyponatraemia. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined bold">Observation</head><p n="p50.58"><s n="s1.5;p50.58">Dehydration is the most important complication of DI to watch for. </s><s n="s2.5;p50.58">Although electrolyte levels can be monitored, the easiest way of assessing this in a cogitative patient is to ask about the sensation of thirst. </s><s n="s3.5;p50.58">With regard to the treatment with desmopressin, nocturia and water intoxication are the must important side effects to consider. </s><s n="s4.5;p50.58">Water intoxication due to excessive ADH replacement is indicated by hyponatraemia with a urine osmolality greater than >500mmol/kg in the absence of oedema (Longmore et al, 2004). </s><s n="s5.5;p50.58">With regard to her head injuries, there would be no requirement for further CT or MRI imaging of her head, unless her condition deteriorated. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined bold">Referral and team working</head><p n="p51.58"><s n="s1.4;p51.58">Post hospitalisation follow-up visits should be arranged with an endocrinologist every 6-12 months in order to allow regular monitoring of her electrolyte levels and ensure the desmopressin dose is correct. </s><s n="s2.4;p51.58">It may also be beneficial to monitor electrolytes more frequently within the primary care setting for the first few months after discharge considering this may be a transient condition. </s><s n="s3.4;p51.58">Appropriate follow up with the physiotherapists, SALT and orthopaedic surgeons should also be arranged. </s><s n="s4.4;p51.58">Considering psychological effects she is likely to have suffered from her experience, referral to a councillor should also be offered. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined bold">Prevention and Advice</head><p n="p52.58"><s n="s1.3;p52.58">Although no specific dietary considerations exist in chronic DI, it is important that <name type="other"/> understands the need for adequate and balanced salt and water intake, in order to avoid dehydration and water intoxication. </s><s n="s2.3;p52.58">Patients with DI must also take special precautions, such as when travelling, in order to be prepared to treat vomiting or diarrhoea and to avoid dehydration with exertion or hot weather. </s><s n="s3.3;p52.58">She should be reassured that even if her condition does become poorly controlled for some reason, problems are unlikely as long as water is available and she continues to drink whenever thirsty. </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head>Outcome</head><p n="p53.58"><s n="s1.1;p53.58">25 days after RTA: </s></p><p n="p54.58"><s n="s1.9;p54.58">With regard to DI her prognosis is excellent. </s><s n="s2.9;p54.58">Since treatment with desmopressin was initiated, <name type="other"/> has been passing urine four times a day and has reported no nocturia or sensation of thirst. </s><s n="s3.9;p54.58">The occasional urinary incontinence has also stopped. </s><s n="s4.9;p54.58">She has now been switched to intranasal desmopressin 20mcg bd pending her discharge. </s><s n="s5.9;p54.58">Her mobility has continued to improve and an orthopaedic consultation had been arranged in order to discuss removal of the plaster cast. </s><s n="s6.9;p54.58">A speech and language assessment reported good communication at conversational level, although her speech remained slightly slurred but intelligible. </s><s n="s7.9;p54.58">She was orientated to time and place. </s><s n="s8.9;p54.58">There were still obvious memory problems although she was able to retrieve memories with maximum prompts. </s><s n="s9.9;p54.58">She continues to maintain a normal diet along with twice daily fortisip supplements. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head>Evidence based care and issues for research</head><p n="p55.58"><s n="s1.6;p55.58">A study by Agha et al (2004) reported that up to 21% of patients suffering moderate to severe traumatic brain injury developed DI in the immediate post-injury period. </s><s n="s2.6;p55.58">However, 6.9% patients still exhibited permanent DI at a later follow-up; a figure which is higher than traditionally thought. </s><s n="s3.6;p55.58">They stressed the importance of identifying patients with partial posttraumatic DI as appropriate treatment may reduce morbidity and optimise the potential for recovery. </s><s n="s4.6;p55.58">Yuan and Wade (1991) reported similar findings, showing cranial DI in 26% of patients. </s><s n="s5.6;p55.58">They also reported that various other post-traumatic neuroendocrine abnormalities (e.g. </s><s n="s6.6;p55.58">SIADH, Addison's disease, hyperprolactinaemia, low GH) also occur early and with high frequency in such injuries. </s></p><p n="p56.58"><s n="s1.3;p56.58">A report by Laczi and Orv (2002) stated that the diuresis associated with cranial diabetes insipidus can be most effectively decreased by vasopressin substitution. </s><s n="s2.3;p56.58">The non-vasopressin containing oral antidiuretics previously used have become outdated in the treatment of central diabetes insipidus, with the first choice compound for this purpose now being 1-desamino-8-D-arginine-vasopressin (DDAVP). </s><s n="s3.3;p56.58">Although treatment may be required immediately, most cases arising as a result of TBI recover completely, but there is an appreciable frequency of long-term DI which can be subtle and should be recognized and managed appropriately (Bondanelli et al, 2005). </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head>Commentary</head><div2><head rend="underlined">Epidemiology:</head><p n="p57.58"><s n="s1.1;p57.58">DI is relatively uncommon with a prevalence of 1 case per 25,000 people, although as previously mentioned this rises up to 26% amongst patients suffering from traumatic brain injuries. </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head>Impact on your learning</head><p n="p58.58"><s n="s1.1;p58.58">This case has provided an opportunity to examine the causes of polyuria, and in particular the diagnosis, investigation and management of cranial diabetes insipidus. </s></p></div1></body><back><div1 type="bibliography"><head rend="underlined bold">References:</head><p>Agha, A., Thornton, E., O'Kelly, P., Tormey, W., Phillips, J and Thompson, C. (2004) Posterior Pituitary Dysfunction after Traumatic Brain Injury. J Clin Endocrin Metab. 89 (12):5987-92.</p><p>Bondanelli, M., Ambrosio, M., Zatelli, M. and De Marinis, L. (2005). Hypopituitarism after traumatic brain injury. Eur J Endocrinol. 152(5):679-91. Abstract.</p><p>Laczi, F. and Orv, H. (2002) Diabetes insipidus: aetiology, diagnosis, and therapy. 143(46):2579-85 </p><p>Longmore, M., Wilkinson, I. and Rajagopalan, S. (2004). Oxford Handbook of Clinical Medicine (6<hi rend="sup">th</hi> Edition). Oxford University Press. New York</p><p>Segal-Lieberman, G., Karasik, A. and Shimon, I. (2000). Hypopituitarism following closed head injury. Pituitary. 3(3):181-4</p><p>Yuan, X. and Wade, C. (1991) Neuroendocrine abnormalities in patients with traumatic brain injury. Front Neuroendocrinol. 12(3):209-30</p></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
