<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_0047e" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Colorectal Cancer</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">document consists of pro forma table giving section headings, along with notes detailing the expected contents of each section
</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">4</p><p n="date">2005-10</p><p n="module title">General Clinical Education</p><p n="module code">unknown</p><p n="genre family">Case study</p><p n="discipline">Medicine</p><p n="disciplinary group">LS</p><p n="grade">D</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">2932</p><p n="number of s-units">150</p><p n="number of p">66</p><p n="number of tables">2</p><p n="number of figures">0</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">17</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">20</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">19.5</p><p n="average s-units per p">2.3</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">m</p><p n="year of birth">1981</p><p n="first language">English</p><p n="education">UKA</p><p n="course">Medicine</p><p n="student ID">0047</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><titlePart>PORTFOLIO CASE N <hi rend="sup underlined">o</hi>: <hi rend="bold">14</hi> Patient Initials: <name type="other"/> Hospital Number: Kept on a separate list Age: 78 (<name type="date"/>) Gender: M</titlePart><docTitle><titlePart>Portfolio Case presentation number: 14</titlePart></docTitle></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="section"><head>Referral information</head><p n="p1.66"><s n="s1.1;p1.66">Mr <name type="other"/> was initially referred to the colorectal clinic by his GP. He was met for the first time as an inpatient at the <name type="other"/> Hospital whilst awaiting elective surgery. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head>History</head><div2><head rend="underlined bold">PC: </head><p n="p2.66"><s n="s1.1;p2.66"><name type="other"/> initially presented to his GP with a two-week history of diarrhoea and rectal bleeding approximately three months ago. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined bold">HPC: </head><p n="p3.66"><s n="s1.10;p3.66">Mr <name type="other"/> initially contacted his GP after suffering from diarrhoea and rectal bleeding for a few weeks. </s><s n="s2.10;p3.66">At the time of presentation there was no history of associated abdominal pain, loss of appetite, dyspnoea or fatigue. </s><s n="s3.10;p3.66">There was no mucus in the stool, only a small amount (~1 teaspoon) of fresh blood which appeared in the pan and on the paper. </s><s n="s4.10;p3.66">No abdominal bloating or distension. </s><s n="s5.10;p3.66">No tenesmus. </s><s n="s6.10;p3.66">There was no history of recent travel or contact with infected persons. </s><s n="s7.10;p3.66">Mr <name type="other"/> was previously well. </s><s n="s8.10;p3.66">He was subsequently referred to the GI clinic. </s><s n="s9.10;p3.66">When assessed in clinic approximately a month later, he reported that he had lost about stone in weight since his initial presentation. </s><s n="s10.10;p3.66">The diarrhoea and rectal bleeding had persisted. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined bold">PMH: </head><list type="bulleted"><head>His previous medical history included:</head><item>Hypothyroidism</item><item>NIDDM (since aged 66yrs)</item><item>Possible MI (aged 74yrs)</item><item>Bilateral inguinal hernia repair (aged 60yrs)</item><item>Open surgical removal of renal calculi (Pyelolithotomy) (aged 48yrs) </item><item>No history of CVA, TIA, Rheumatic fever, COPD, asthma or epilepsy</item></list><p n="p4.66"/></div2><div2><head rend="underlined bold">Drugs and allergies: </head><list type="bulleted"><item>NKDA</item><item>Ex-smoker. Stopped aged 60yrs.</item><item>4-6units of alcohol per week</item><item><list type="bulleted"><head>Regular medication includes</head><item>Glibenclamide 5mg PO TDS (Sulphonylurea)</item><item>Metformin 500mg PO TDS (Biguanide antiglycaemic)</item><item>Levothyroxine 100mcg PO OD</item><item>Metoprolol 12.5mg PO OD (Beta-blocker)</item><item>Ramipril 2.5mg PO OD (ACE inhibitor)</item><item>Simvastatin 40mg PO OD (Lipid-lowering drug)</item><item>Clopidogrel 75mg PO OD (Anti-platelet drug)</item></list></item></list><p n="p5.66"/></div2><div2><head rend="underlined bold">FH</head><p n="p6.66"><s n="s1.2;p6.66">There was no family history of GI disorders. </s><s n="s2.2;p6.66">His father died of an MI. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined bold">SH: </head><p n="p7.66"><s n="s1.4;p7.66">Mr <name type="other"/> currently lives in a privately owned house with his wife. </s><s n="s2.4;p7.66">Prior to his retirement he worked as a factory supervisor. </s><s n="s3.4;p7.66">He has one son who is a renal physician at Guys hospital in London. </s><s n="s4.4;p7.66">Mr <name type="other"/> is usually fully independent and mobile. </s></p><div3><head rend="underlined">General examination:</head><list type="bulleted"><item>BP 146/75</item><item>HR 61</item><item rend="underlined">Weight 68kg</item><item rend="underlined">No jaundice, anaemia, cyanosis, oedema, lymphadenopathy, tremor or goitre</item><item>Clubbing was present </item></list><p n="p8.66"/></div3><div3><head rend="underlined">CVS:</head><list type="bulleted"><item>HS 1+2+0</item><item>JVP not detected</item><item>ECG: LBBB may be associated with a previous MI</item></list><p n="p9.66"/></div3><div3><head rend="underlined">RESP:</head><list type="bulleted"><item>RR 16/min</item><item>Trachea - central</item><item>Pectus excavatum</item><item>Normal breath sounds</item><item>Chest clear - No wheeze or crepitations</item></list><p n="p10.66"/></div3><div3><head>ABDO:</head><list type="bulleted"><item>Three old scars on abdomen (from pyelolithotomy and bilateral hernia repairs)</item><item>No clinical signs</item><item rend="underlined">No distension or obvious masses</item><item rend="underlined">No pain or tenderness on palpation</item><item rend="underlined">No mass detectable on PR. Some fresh blood present. </item></list><p n="p11.66"/></div3></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head>Analysis of history</head><p n="p12.66"><s n="s1.7;p12.66">Given the age of this patient and the history of PR bleeding, weight loss and a recent change of bowel habit, the most likely cause for this presentation is colorectal carcinoma. </s><s n="s2.7;p12.66">More specifically these symptoms suggest a left sided lesion. </s><s n="s3.7;p12.66">This is in contrast to the classical symptoms of a right-sided lesion which include anaemia, weight loss and a palpable mass. </s><s n="s4.7;p12.66">There was nothing in the history to suggest obstruction, perforation or fistula formation had occurred as a result. </s><s n="s5.7;p12.66">Other important differential diagnoses to consider would include chronic diverticular disease and diarrhoea resulting from infectious causes such as food poisoning (Salmonella), dysentery or viral enterocolitis. </s><s n="s6.7;p12.66">However as the symptoms, particularly PR bleeding, had persisted for nearly six weeks an infective cause seems quite unlikely. </s><s n="s7.7;p12.66">Medical causes such as excessive use of levothyroxine could also be responsible for his weight loss and diarrhoea however this would not cause rectal bleeding. </s></p><p n="p13.66"><s n="s1.4;p13.66">Upon physical examination a focused abdominal examination will be carried out to look for specific signs such as abdominal tenderness or palpable masses. </s><s n="s2.4;p13.66">A rectal exam will also be performed to confirm the PR bleeding. </s><s n="s3.4;p13.66">In addition PR masses can be detected in 60% of right sided carcinomas (Longmore et al, 2004). </s><s n="s4.4;p13.66">A general examination should also be performed to look for relevant systemic signs such as anaemia, and to allow the patient's general health to be assessed. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head>Physical examination and mental state examination</head><p n="p14.66"/></div1><div1 type="section"><head>Analysis of history and examination</head><p n="p15.66"><s n="s1.5;p15.66">The physical examination did not reveal any clinical signs which suggested that Mr <name type="other"/> was systemically unwell. </s><s n="s2.5;p15.66">There was some finger clubbing present although this may have been congenital and therefore with hindsight this should have been queried further. </s><s n="s3.5;p15.66">There was no pain or palpable masses on abdominal exam, however these symptoms rarely occur in left-sided carcinoma unless the patient presents late or obstruction has occurred. </s><s n="s4.5;p15.66">Although tenderness in the LIF is usually present in chronic diverticular disease, this still remains an important differential at this stage which would require further investigation before being excluded. </s><s n="s5.5;p15.66">However given the history of associated weight loss, left-sided colorectal carcinoma remains the most likely cause of Mr <name type="other"/>'s problems. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head>Formulation of the patient's problem(s)</head><p n="p16.66"><s n="s1.5;p16.66">Mr <name type="other"/> is a seventy-eight year old man who is most likely suffering from a left-sided colorectal carcinoma. </s><s n="s2.5;p16.66">Chronic diverticular disease still remains a possible differential diagnosis at this stage, however this could easily be clarified by performing further imaging investigations. </s><s n="s3.5;p16.66">Although Mr <name type="other"/> also suffers from NIDDM and hypothyroidism, these have both been successfully controlled by medication, therefore he is otherwise fit and well and able to maintain a fully independent lifestyle. </s><s n="s4.5;p16.66">Receiving a diagnosis of cancer may therefore have a significant impact upon his psychosocial well-being. </s><s n="s5.5;p16.66">He currently lives with his elderly wife and has no other family in the area, therefore it is important to consider that he may require additional care assistance if his health deteriorates further or his condition becomes terminal. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head>Management</head><div2><head rend="underlined bold">Investigations</head><p n="p17.66"><s n="s1.5;p17.66">Elective patients such as Mr <name type="other"/> who present with suspected colorectal carcinoma should undergo routine bloods and biochemistry in order to detect anaemia or any other metabolic disturbances. </s><s n="s2.5;p17.66">Tumours markers such as carcino-embryonic antigen (CEA) can also be measured in order to aid diagnosis, monitor the disease and assess the effectiveness of treatment. </s><s n="s3.5;p17.66">Faecal occult blood may be carried out, although it is of little practical value within the hospital setting. </s><s n="s4.5;p17.66">However, the most important investigative technique in the diagnosis of colorectal cancer is imaging. </s><s n="s5.5;p17.66">Various imaging techniques are commonly used including (Ellis et al, 2002): </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p18.66"><s n="s1.1;p18.66"><hi rend="bold">Rigid/flexible sigmoidoscopy:</hi> Helps reveal tumours in the recto-sigmoid region and allows biopsy samples to be obtained for positive diagnosis. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p19.66"><s n="s1.1;p19.66"><hi rend="bold">Colonoscopy</hi>: Enables inspection of higher aspects of the colon and is currently the gold standard for investigating colorectal cancer as it also allows biopsies and polypectomies to be performed in order to obtain specimens for histological examination. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p20.66"><s n="s1.3;p20.66"><hi rend="bold">Double contrast barium enema</hi>: Usually reveals the growth as either a stricture or a filling defect (apple-core deformity). </s><s n="s2.3;p20.66">However, it is important to remember that a negative barium enema doesn't definitely exclude the presence of a small tumour, particularly in the presence of extensive diverticulosis. </s><s n="s3.3;p20.66">This technique is likely to be superseded in the future by CT pneumocolon. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p21.66"><s n="s1.2;p21.66"><hi rend="bold">Ultrasound, CT and MRI:</hi> These techniques can be used to evaluate tumour size and local/secondary spread, including hepatic metastases. </s><s n="s2.2;p21.66">In some cases they may provide enough evidence to confirm the diagnosis and are particularly valuable in elderly patients who are unable to tolerate bowel preparations or 'invasive' procedures such as colonoscopy. </s></p><p n="p22.66"><s n="s1.2;p22.66">In this case, Mr <name type="other"/> underwent routine blood tests (FBC, UE and LFT), a sigmoidoscopy and a CT scan in order to confirm a diagnosis. </s><s n="s2.2;p22.66">The results are shown below: </s></p><div3><head rend="underlined">Blood tests:</head><p n="p23.66"><s n="s1.1;p23.66">There was no indication of anaemia or any other abnormalities. </s></p><table id="BAWE_0047e-tab.001"><row><cell/></row></table></div3><div3><head rend="underlined">Sigmoid report:</head><p n="p24.66"><s n="s1.3;p24.66">The sigmoidoscopy revealed a polypoidal circumferential tumour about 30cm from the anus. </s><s n="s2.3;p24.66">It was causing a significant luminal obstruction and prevented further passage of the sigmoidoscope. </s><s n="s3.3;p24.66">The mass was biopsied and the results showed severe dysplasia with a strong suspicion of underlying adenocarcinoma. </s></p></div3><div3><head rend="underlined">CT of chest, abdomen and pelvis:</head><p n="p25.66"><s n="s1.3;p25.66">The CT also suggested probable sigmoid carcinoma. </s><s n="s2.3;p25.66">There was no evidence of liver metastases. </s><s n="s3.3;p25.66">A 1cm irregular lung lesion was also seen on the chest CT. It was suggested that it could be focal scarring, but a small early carcinoma could not be excluded. </s></p><p n="p26.66"><s n="s1.2;p26.66">Collectively these results confirmed the presence of colon adenocarcinoma in the sigmoid region. </s><s n="s2.2;p26.66">As Mr <name type="other"/> was otherwise relatively fit and healthy, elective surgical intervention was indicated in order to remove the affected section of bowel. </s></p></div3></div2><div2><head rend="underlined bold">Surgical intervention</head><p n="p27.66"><s n="s1.3;p27.66">As the adenocarcinoma was positioned within the sigmoid colon, a left hemicolectomy was performed to resect the bowel. </s><s n="s2.3;p27.66">This involved removal of the descending and sigmoid colon and was followed by formation of an anastomosis to restore bowel function. </s><s n="s3.3;p27.66">The operation was performed through a long midline incision. </s></p><p n="p28.66"><s n="s1.2;p28.66">Mr <name type="other"/> was admitted a few days prior to the surgery and appeared well during the pre-op assessment. </s><s n="s2.2;p28.66">No cardiovascular or respiratory abnormalities were detected and his general OBS were stable (Apyrexial, BP 139/67, HR 60, RR 20, Oxygen saturation 99%, BM 6.5). </s></p><p n="p29.66"><s n="s1.5;p29.66">Mr <name type="other"/> received a general anaesthetic and an epidural (at T12/L1) prior to the surgery. </s><s n="s2.5;p29.66">As a result of the epidural, a HDU bed was arranged so that he could be closely monitored after in case of complications such as hypotension or renal failure. </s><s n="s3.5;p29.66">During surgery, the bowel was resected from the distal transverse colon to the upper rectum as the descending colon was found to be relatively ischaemic. </s><s n="s4.5;p29.66">An anastomosis was successfully formed from the remaining bowel, eliminating the need for a temporary colostomy. </s><s n="s5.5;p29.66">During surgical exploration the liver, gall bladder, stomach and small bowel all appeared normal. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined bold">Reassurance and explanation</head><p n="p30.66"><s n="s1.5;p30.66">"Unfortunately we have some bad news for you Mr <name type="other"/>. </s><s n="s2.5;p30.66">The scan and camera test both confirmed the presence of a mass in the lower part of your large bowel. </s><s n="s3.5;p30.66">During the camera test we took a piece of the mass for further examination and the results have shown that it is malignant. </s><s n="s4.5;p30.66">Due to the position of the tumour we will be able to operate to remove the affected part of bowel. </s><s n="s5.5;p30.66">Do you have any questions"? </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined bold">Prescription/medical intervention</head><p n="p31.66"><s n="s1.6;p31.66">Mr <name type="other"/> regularly uses the anti-platelet drug, clopidogrel, however it would be necessary to stop this medication seven days before the operation in order to prevent excessive bleeding. </s><s n="s2.6;p31.66">This should therefore be replaced with aspirin 75mg PO OD during this period. </s><s n="s3.6;p31.66">Whilst an inpatient Mr <name type="other"/> would require DVT prophylaxis in the form of enoxiparin, as he may be bed-bound for several days following surgery. </s><s n="s4.6;p31.66">Prior to the operation he would require either an enema or oral stimulant laxatives (e.g. </s><s n="s5.6;p31.66">Picolax) to clear the bowel. </s><s n="s6.6;p31.66">Prophylactic antibiotics such as metronidazole and gentamicin (or cephalosporin) may also be required during the peri-operative period. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined bold">Observation</head><p n="p32.66"><s n="s1.2;p32.66">Following surgery Mr <name type="other"/> should be closely monitored for signs of surgical complications. </s><s n="s2.2;p32.66">These can be divided into immediate, early and late and are summarised below (Ellis et al, 2002): </s></p><list type="bulleted"><head>Immediate (&lt;24hrs): </head><item>Unexpected reaction to anaesthesia </item><item>Asphyxiation due to inhaled vomit or obstructed airway</item><item>Primary haemorrhage</item></list><list type="bulleted"><head>Early (24hr-3wks):</head><item><list type="bulleted"><head>Local:</head><item>Paralytic ileus</item><item>Obstruction due to fibrinous adhesions</item><item>Infection </item><item>Secondary haemorrhage</item><item>Dehiscence of wound or anastomosis</item><item>Fistula formation</item></list></item><item><list type="bulleted"><head>General: </head><item>DVT</item><item>Pulmonary infection/collapse/embolus</item><item>Bed sores</item><item>Enterocolitis</item><item>Urinary retention</item></list></item></list><list type="bulleted"><head>Late (3wks+): </head><item>Obstruction due to fibrinous adhesions</item><item>Incisional hernias</item><item>Recurrence of malignancy</item><item>Malabsorption </item></list><p n="p33.66"><s n="s1.2;p33.66">Following discharge Mr <name type="other"/> should also be reviewed in clinic in case of late complications. </s><s n="s2.2;p33.66">His case was also discussed at the MDT meeting with regards to the lung lesions found on CT. It was decided that a repeat CXR should be performed in 12 months time. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined bold">Referral and team working</head><p n="p34.66"><s n="s1.2;p34.66">Mr <name type="other"/> may initially require some degree of social support or care assistance whilst recovering completely at home. </s><s n="s2.2;p34.66">Referral to an oncologist for chemo- or radiotherapy was not indicated in this case - radiotherapy is primarily reserved for unresectable rectal tumours, whilst chemotherapy would be unsuitable for a patient in his late seventies. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined bold">Prognosis</head><p n="p35.66"><s n="s1.1;p35.66">Colon carcinoma has traditionally been staged using the Dukes classification system, however moves are now being made towards using the TNM staging system which is summarised below (Kumar and Clark, 2002): </s></p><table id="BAWE_0047e-tab.002"><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p36.66"><s n="s1.3;p36.66">Although there remained some uncertainty regarding the abnormal lesion detected in Mr <name type="other"/>'s lung it was assumed to be a metastatic lesion. </s><s n="s2.3;p36.66">His tumour was therefore graded T4 N0 M0 which indicated a stage two carcinoma. </s><s n="s3.3;p36.66">His five year survival rate was therefore estimated to be in the region of 80%. </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head>Outcome</head><div2><head rend="underlined">Immediately post-op</head><p n="p37.66"><s n="s1.6;p37.66">Following his surgery Mr <name type="other"/> was transferred to the high dependency unit. </s><s n="s2.6;p37.66">FBC, UE and LFT results were normal. </s><s n="s3.6;p37.66">Whilst in HDU he became hypotensive therefore the epidural was stopped. </s><s n="s4.6;p37.66">His BP subsequently returned to 81/40 and the presence of concentrated urine indicated adequate renal perfusion. </s><s n="s5.6;p37.66">He was also given 500ml gelofusin over 2hr in order increase his BP, and IV paracetamol for the pain. </s><s n="s6.6;p37.66">The epidural was subsequently restarted to provide appropriate pain relief after his BP had stabilised. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">1 day post-op</head><p n="p38.66"><s n="s1.3;p38.66">The day after surgery Mr <name type="other"/> appeared well. </s><s n="s2.3;p38.66">His OBS were stable and his BP remained steady at 82/38. </s><s n="s3.3;p38.66">Small volumes of fluid had been drained from his wound (150ml) and rectal (10ml) drains. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">2 days post-op</head><p n="p39.66"><s n="s1.4;p39.66">His BP remained stable and there was moderate urine production. </s><s n="s2.4;p39.66">OBS were stable. </s><s n="s3.4;p39.66">Chest was clear. </s><s n="s4.4;p39.66">The epidural remained in situ and was working (i.e. there was no pain). </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">3 days post-op </head><p n="p40.66"><s n="s1.5;p40.66">On examination Mr <name type="other"/> was sat up comfortably in a chair (MEWS 0), therefore the epidural was removed and replaced with PCA (patient controlled analgesia) and IV paracetamol. </s><s n="s2.5;p40.66">He was subsequently returned to the surgical ward. </s><s n="s3.5;p40.66">He had resumed a healthy urine output (1740ml output in 12hr). </s><s n="s4.5;p40.66">There was no flatus or faeces being produced. </s><s n="s5.5;p40.66">He was instructed to increase his fluids and start a light diet. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">6 days post-op</head><p n="p41.66"><s n="s1.4;p41.66">His OBS remained stable on the surgical ward. </s><s n="s2.4;p41.66">IV fluids and the PCA were stopped. </s><s n="s3.4;p41.66">The catheter was also removed. </s><s n="s4.4;p41.66">He had started to pass flatus and was continuing his oral intake of food. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">7 days post op</head><p n="p42.66"><s n="s1.5;p42.66">Bowels opened, but some diarrhoea. </s><s n="s2.5;p42.66">This was negative for clostridium difficile toxin (EIA). </s><s n="s3.5;p42.66">No vomiting or abdominal pain was reported. </s><s n="s4.5;p42.66">The wound was healing well. </s><s n="s5.5;p42.66">The drain was still producing serous fluid. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">9 days post op</head><p n="p43.66"><s n="s1.4;p43.66">Mr <name type="other"/> appeared comfortable and well. </s><s n="s2.4;p43.66">No further diarrhoea and no additional problems. </s><s n="s3.4;p43.66">He was now passing urine and faeces regularly. </s><s n="s4.4;p43.66">Apyrexial with stable OBS. No gross abnormalities were detected on the blood results. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">10 days post-op</head><p n="p44.66"><s n="s1.3;p44.66">Mr <name type="other"/> was recovering well and had not reported any significant complications. </s><s n="s2.3;p44.66">He was therefore discharged and a clinic follow-up was arranged for six weeks time. </s><s n="s3.3;p44.66">No further follow-up has since been possible. </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head>Evidence based care and issues for research</head><p n="p45.66"><s n="s1.1;p45.66">At present there is considerable debate regarding means of preventing of colorectal carcinoma and the benefits of introducing a national screening programme. </s></p><div2><head><hi rend="underlined">Prevention:</hi> (Surgical tutor website, 2005)</head><p n="p46.66"><s n="s1.1;p46.66">A lower risk of sporadic cancer has been convincingly linked with the following, however no specific have yet been implemented: </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p47.66"><s n="s1.1;p47.66">Lifestyle: infrequent consumption of meat, matching calorie consumption to need, low dietary fat, active lifestyle, not smoking, frequent consumption of vegetables and possibly fruit, high-fibre diet. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p48.66"><s n="s1.1;p48.66">Nutritional supplements and medication: vitamin supplements containing folic acid, selenium, calcium, regular use of non-steroidal anti-inflammatory drugs, hormone replacement therapy. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">Screening:</head><p n="p49.66"><s n="s1.1;p49.66">Screening for colorectal cancer can be divided into two categories i.e. screening of high risk groups and population screening. </s></p><div3><head rend="bold">Screening of high risk groups</head><list type="bulleted"><head>This includes </head><item>Patients with family history </item><item>Sporadic adenomatous polyps (especially villous type)</item><item>Inflammatory bowel disease </item></list><p rend="bulleted" n="p50.66"><s n="s1.1;p50.66">Definition of the high risk group is difficult </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p51.66"><s n="s1.1;p51.66">High risk patients should undergo colonoscopy at approximately 50 years </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p52.66"><s n="s1.2;p52.66">Patients with a family history of inherited syndromes (e.g. </s><s n="s2.2;p52.66">FAP, HNPCC) should undergo genetic testing </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p53.66"><s n="s1.1;p53.66">If a mutation is present they should undergo intensive colonoscopic screening from adolescence </s></p></div3><div3><head rend="bold">Population screening</head><p rend="bulleted" n="p54.66"><s n="s1.1;p54.66">The role of screening is currently being investigated by either </s></p><list type="bulleted"><item>- Faecal occult blood testing </item><item>- Colonoscopy </item></list><p rend="bulleted" n="p55.66"><s n="s1.1;p55.66">Colorectal cancer usually develops in benign adenomatous polyps which are often amenable to endoscopic resection, therefore it is believed that screening may both reduce the incidence of the disease as well as improving outcome from it (Robinson and Hardcastle, 1998) </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p56.66"><s n="s1.1;p56.66">A Nottingham study has recruited over 150,000 patients </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p57.66"><s n="s1.1;p57.66">75,250 underwent biennial FOB testing </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p58.66"><s n="s1.1;p58.66">Resulted in 1774 colonoscopies </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p59.66"><s n="s1.1;p59.66">Seven complications occurred requiring operations in 6 patients </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p60.66"><s n="s1.1;p60.66">There was no difference identified in stage of presentation in screened group, however overall survival was significantly </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p61.66"><s n="s1.1;p61.66">Several other large randomized studies have demonstrated a reduction in cancer-related mortality of 15-33%. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p62.66"><s n="s1.1;p62.66">The disadvantage of screening with FOB is its relatively low sensitivity which means many unnecessary colonoscopies. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p63.66"><s n="s1.1;p63.66">Its expense, the need for full bowel preparation and sedation and the small risk of perforation obviate its use as a population screening tool at present, though trials are underway in the UK and USA. </s></p><p n="p64.66"><s n="s1.1;p64.66">In the future CT pneumocolon or 'virtual colonoscopy' and the refinement of genetic testing may contribute to screening programmes. </s></p></div3></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head>Commentary</head><list type="bulleted"><head><hi rend="underlined">Epidemiology:</hi> (Longmore et al, 2004)</head><item>2nd most common cause of cancer deaths in the UK (19,000 deaths/year) (68% Colonic, 32% Rectal)</item><item>56% occurs in patients >70yrs old</item><item>Increased prevalence in males (54/100,000 vs. 36/100,000)</item><item>3% patients present with more than one tumour </item><item>A previous colonic neoplasm increases the risk of a second tumour</item><item>Exercise, NSAIDS and HRT may have protective effect</item></list><list type="bulleted"><head rend="underlined">Predisposing factors:</head><item>Neoplastic polyps (e.g.villous adenomas)</item><item>UC and Crohns</item><item>Familial adenomatous polyposis (APC gene)</item><item>HNPCC (MSH2, MLH1 genes) </item><item>Previous history of malignancy</item><item>Low fibre diet</item></list><p n="p65.66"><s n="s1.1;p65.66">FH: No relatives 1:50, 1x 1st degree 1:17, 2x 1st degree 1:6 </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head>Impact on your learning</head><p n="p66.66"><s n="s1.1;p66.66">This case has provided an opportunity to study various aspects of colorectal cancer including: </s></p><list type="bulleted"><item>The important symptoms to consider during history taking</item><item>Specific findings to examine for upon physical assessment</item><item>The role of the imaging and biopsy in aiding diagnosis</item><item>The importance of considering the various surgical complications which may arise in the post-op period</item><item>The use of the Dukes and TMN staging criteria when considering patient prognosis </item><item>The pros and cons of introducing nation screening programmes</item><item>Increased personal awareness of the extent of colorectal carcinoma within the UK</item></list></div1></body><back><div1 type="bibliography"><head rend="underlined bold">References:</head><p>Ellis, H., Calne, R. and Watson, C. (2002). 'Chapter 24: The Colon' in Lecture notes in General surgery (10<hi rend="sup">th</hi> Edition).Blackwell publishing. Oxford.</p><p>Kumar, P and Clark, M. (2002). 'Chapter 6: The colon and the rectum' In Clinical Medicine (5<hi rend="sup">th</hi> edition). Saunders publishing </p><p>Longmore, M., Wilkinson, I. and Rajagopalan, S. (2004). 'Colorectal adenocarcinoma' in Oxford Handbook of Clinical Medicine (6<hi rend="sup">th</hi> Edition). Oxford University Press. New York.</p><p>McLatchie, G. and Leaper, D. (2002). Oxford Handbook of Clinical Surgery (2<hi rend="sup">nd</hi> edition). Oxford University Press. New York.</p><p>Robinson, M. and Hardcastle, J. (1998). Should we be screening for colorectal carcinoma? <hi rend="italic">Br Med Bull</hi>. 54(4):807-21. Review</p><p>Unknown author. 'Colorectal carcinoma' on Surgical tutor website. <seg type="URL" n="www.surgical-tutor.org.uk"/>. Last accessed on 2<hi rend="sup">nd</hi> October 2005.</p></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
