<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_0047a" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Breast Cancer</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">The document has a title page which contains:
document title
title part
figure</note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">title page consists of pro forma table
deleted: page numbers
deleted: Word Count: 8, 326 (Excluding tables and references) 
</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">4</p><p n="date">2005-02</p><p n="module title">Clinical Application Skills</p><p n="module code">MD109</p><p n="genre family">Narrative recount + Essay + Case study + Case study + Case study</p><p n="discipline">Medicine</p><p n="disciplinary group">LS</p><p n="grade">D</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">13160</p><p n="number of s-units">550</p><p n="number of p">151</p><p n="number of tables">7</p><p n="number of figures">15</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">2</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">2</p><p n="abstract present">abstract present</p><p n="average words per s-unit">23.9</p><p n="average s-units per p">3.6</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">m</p><p n="year of birth">1981</p><p n="first language">English</p><p n="education">UKA</p><p n="course">Medicine</p><p n="student ID">0047</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><titlePart rend="bold">Exam Number: <name type="student ID"/></titlePart><figure id="BAWE_0047a-fig.001"/><figure id="BAWE_0047a-fig.002"/><titlePart rend="bold"><name type="university"/> Medical School MB ChB Phase 1</titlePart><titlePart rend="bold">Clinical Applications Module Dissertation</titlePart><docTitle><titlePart>Title: Breast Cancer</titlePart></docTitle><titlePart>Mentor: <name type="tutor name"/> Date: 2 <hi rend="sup">nd</hi> February 2005</titlePart><titlePart rend="bold">Academic Session 2004/05</titlePart></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="abstract"><head rend="underlined bold">SUMMARY</head><p n="p1.151"><s n="s1.4;p1.151">When first considering an area of study for this module, numerous subjects initially came to my attention, although I had a vague familiarity with the majority as a result of my previous degree. </s><s n="s2.4;p1.151">Then it struck me that within my time at medical school, I had already met several patients with histories of breast carcinoma during other aspects of the course and yet I knew virtually nothing about this condition. </s><s n="s3.4;p1.151">Whilst discussing this with colleagues it soon became apparent that unlike most people, I had never had first hand experience of people suffering from breast cancer as fortunately I knew of no family members or friends who had undergone the trauma of a diagnosis. </s><s n="s4.4;p1.151">I found this quite surprising given the high rates of incidence, and therefore decided to use this opportunity to gain an insight into the disease. </s></p><p n="p2.151"><s n="s1.2;p2.151">Once I began investigating the condition further, it immediately struck me that I was going to have a difficult job ahead of me, purely due to the sheer volume of literature which appeared to be available. </s><s n="s2.2;p2.151">From the outset I had decided that a general overview would be most beneficial, although as I my interest grew, it became increasingly difficult to maintain this ideal as I found myself focusing upon fascinating, albeit obscure aspects of breast cancer research. </s></p><p n="p3.151"><s n="s1.3;p3.151">I feel I have gained a great deal from this module, as it has increased my clinical understanding of this condition and furthered my interest into this diverse area of medical research. </s><s n="s2.3;p3.151">In addition, it has also allowed me to gain a better appreciation of the range of emotional effects it may have upon the patients themselves. </s><s n="s3.3;p3.151">I sincerely believe that this knowledge base will be of great value in future, particularly when discussing what may be an uncomfortable topic for many patients. </s></p></div1><div1 type="front-back-matter"><head rend="underlined bold">CONTENTS </head><p/></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">1. INTRODUCTION</head><p n="p4.151"><s n="s1.4;p4.151">An estimated 1 in 3 people will develop cancer during the course of their lives, of which the four most common cancers - breast, lung, colorectal and prostate - account for over half of the 270,000 new cases of malignant cancer registered each year (1). </s><s n="s2.4;p4.151">For many years, breast cancer has been the most common cancer amongst women. </s><s n="s3.4;p4.151">With over 41,000 new cases being diagnosed each year, it accounts for one in three of all female cancer cases and the lifetime risk for developing breast cancer is estimated to be as high in one in nine. </s><s n="s4.4;p4.151">It is therefore unsurprising that breast cancer is the second biggest cause of cancer mortality in the UK, with figures suggesting that 12,000 women die of breast cancer each year (Figure 1.1) (2). </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0047a-fig.003"><head><hi rend="bold">Figure 1.1 Cancer mortality in females in 2002</hi> (2)</head></figure><p n="p5.151"><s n="s1.2;p5.151">Furthermore, an even greater number of women present to their doctor each year concerned about malignancy as a result of breast lumps, despite the fact that 90% of these symptoms arise from benign lesions (2). </s><s n="s2.2;p5.151">In addition, the success of media campaigns and advertisements over the past 20 years aimed at raising breast cancer awareness has lead to even greater levels of women seeking medical assistance (3). </s></p><p n="p6.151"><s n="s1.3;p6.151">As a result of these trends medical professionals are coming into contact with patients concerned about breast cancer more frequently. </s><s n="s2.3;p6.151">It is therefore important that practitioners are able to develop an understanding of the disease processes involved so they can competently identify possible malignancies when necessary. </s><s n="s3.3;p6.151">In addition, they must also be aware of the varied psychological implications breast disease may have upon the patients presenting to them, irrespective of whether or not their initial fear of malignancy is justified. </s></p><p n="p7.151"><s n="s1.6;p7.151">The aim of this dissertation is to provide a broad overview of the major features associated with breast cancer in women. </s><s n="s2.6;p7.151">It will start by examining the normal breast anatomy and physiology, the pathological processes involved, the clinical features of the disease and the methods by which can be detected and diagnosed. </s><s n="s3.6;p7.151">The available treatment options and prognosis will subsequently be discussed. </s><s n="s4.6;p7.151">Various social and psychological issues are also associated with breast cancer particularly with regard to screening, diagnosis and treatment. </s><s n="s5.6;p7.151">These issues will be highlighted and discussed where appropriate. </s><s n="s6.6;p7.151">Additional patient case studies will also be used to address more specific social and psychological problems which may be faced by patients. </s></p><p n="p8.151"><s n="s1.4;p8.151">It is important to appreciate at this stage that certain important omissions will unfortunately be made due to the limited coverage available. </s><s n="s2.4;p8.151">As mentioned above benign breast diseases account for a large proportion of breast masses, however these will not be discussed in further detail despite their significance. </s><s n="s3.4;p8.151">Although a comparatively rare phenomenon, carcinoma of the breast may also present in males, however given the rarity of this condition it too will not be discussed in the following dissertation. </s><s n="s4.4;p8.151">Finally, the numerous complications which may occur as a result of breast cancer, metastatic disease and the medical and surgical interventions used will not be discussed due to the extent of this topic. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">2. ANATOMY AND PHYSIOLOGY</head><p n="p9.151"><s n="s1.10;p9.151">The breast represents a down-growth of the epidermis which usually only develops significantly in females (4). </s><s n="s2.10;p9.151">The main structures contained within the breast tissue are the mammary glands which are involved in the production and expression of milk. </s><s n="s3.10;p9.151">These glands therefore represent an important accessory to reproduction in women (5). </s><s n="s4.10;p9.151">The mammary gland is attached to the dermis of the overlying skin by the suspensory ligaments of the breast. </s><s n="s5.10;p9.151">These ligaments represent thickenings in the connective tissue stroma, and are particularly prominent in superior part of the breast in order to provide support for the glandular lobules. </s><s n="s6.10;p9.151">At its posterior margin, the circular base of the breast rests on the deep pectoral fascia overlying pectoralis major and serratus anterior, there is however a loose connective tissue plane between these two structures which gives rise to the retromammary space. </s><s n="s7.10;p9.151">This is a potential space which contains a small amount of fat and therefore permits movement of the breast over the fascial layer. </s><s n="s8.10;p9.151">The base of the breast extends transversely from the lateral sternal border to the mid axillary line (MAL) and vertically from the 2 <hi rend="sup">nd</hi> to 6 <hi rend="sup">th</hi> ribs, but the gland also extends laterally towards the axilla forming the axillary tail. </s><s n="s9.10;p9.151">The mammary glands are highly vascular, being supplied by perforating branches of the subclavian and axillary arteries (Figure 2.1). </s><s n="s10.10;p9.151">In addition they also receive arterial blood from the thoracic aorta via the posterior intercostal arteries which enter the 2 <hi rend="sup">nd</hi>, 3 <hi rend="sup">rd</hi> and 4 <hi rend="sup">th</hi> intercostal spaces (6). </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0047a-pic.001"><head><hi rend="bold">Figure 2.1 Arterial supply of the breast</hi> (6) </head></figure><p n="p10.151"><s n="s1.1;p10.151">Venous drainage of the breast is primarily to the axillary vein, although the internal thoracic veins are also involved (Figure 2.2). </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0047a-pic.002"><head><hi rend="bold">Figure 2.2 Venous drainage of the breast</hi> (6)</head></figure><p n="p11.151"><s n="s1.5;p11.151">An understanding of the lymphatic supply of the breast is highly important, due to the role it plays in metastatic cancer (Figure 2.3). </s><s n="s2.5;p11.151">The subareolar lymphatic plexus receives drainage from the nipple, areola and lobules. </s><s n="s3.5;p11.151">The majority of lymph from this region originates from the lateral breast quadrants and drains into the axillary lymph nodes and accessory nodes such as the interpectoral, deltopectoral, supraclavicular or inferior deep cervical nodes. </s><s n="s4.5;p11.151">In contrast, lymph from the medial quadrants drains to either the parasternal nodes or the opposite breast. </s><s n="s5.5;p11.151">Lymph from the lower quadrants may also pass inferiorly to the phrenic (abdominal) nodes (6). </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0047a-pic.003"><head><hi rend="bold">Figure 2.3 Lymphatic drainage of the breast</hi> (6)</head></figure><p n="p12.151"><s n="s1.5;p12.151">Prior to puberty the breast lacks any form of glandular tissue, exhibiting only a few small ducts connected to the nipple. </s><s n="s2.5;p12.151">With the onset of thelarche (breast development) there is increased deposition of fat and connective tissue, and the ducts also increase in length and begin to branch, forming terminal buds. </s><s n="s3.5;p12.151">Further breast growth and glandular development occurs with the onset of menses, in response to the associated hormonal changes and continues until the age of 25. </s><s n="s4.5;p12.151">This developmental process is primarily regulated by the interaction of oestrogen, progesterone and prolactin levels, however several other hormones are also believed to have a minor role (Figure 2.4). </s><s n="s5.5;p12.151">It has been difficult to determine the precise role of each hormone since they may have both growth and secretory effects; however this process is evidently accelerated by pregnancy during this period (5). </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0047a-pic.004"><head><hi rend="bold">Figure 2.4 The action of hormones in the development of the breast</hi> (5) </head></figure><p n="p13.151"><s n="s1.7;p13.151">As a result of its role in milk production, the structure of the mammary gland is best described during pregnancy as it only during this period that the tissue is fully functional. </s><s n="s2.7;p13.151">Like most compound glands the structure of the gland can be thought to consist of lobes, lobules and ducts (Figure 2.5). </s><s n="s3.7;p13.151">Each lobe contains a branching duct system that extends into the fibroadipose tissue of the breast, terminating in groups of lobules. </s><s n="s4.7;p13.151">The lobules represent the secretory units, which contain of a variable number of acini surrounded by loose connective tissue. </s><s n="s5.7;p13.151">Each acinus is composed of epithelial cells and myoepithelial cells, which have secretory and mechanical functions respectively. </s><s n="s6.7;p13.151">The main role of the epithelial cells is secretion of milk during later pregnancy and post-partum; however they also continuously secrete various glycoproteins into the glandular lumen. </s><s n="s7.7;p13.151">In contrast the myoepithelial cells form a discontinuous layer, which surrounds the basement membrane, and contain contractile proteins which promote passage of the secretions through the duct system (5). </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0047a-pic.005"><head>Lactiferous Duct Lobe consisting of several lobules Lactiferous sinus Opening of a lactiferous sinus Stroma consisting of connective and adipose tissue Pectoralis major and minor Ribs and intercostal muscles Columnar/cuboidal epithelial cells Basement membrane Lumen of lactiferous duct <hi rend="bold">Figure 2.5</hi> <hi rend="bold">Structure of the mature female mammary gland during lactation</hi> (7)</head></figure><p n="p14.151"><s n="s1.5;p14.151">The groups of lobules associated with each lobe are connected via a series of intra and extra-lobular ducts to an individual lactiferous duct which subsequently empties onto the surface of the breast. </s><s n="s2.5;p14.151">There are approximately 15-20 lactiferous ducts, each draining a segment of the breast, which converge towards the centre of the nipple like the spokes of a bicycle wheel. </s><s n="s3.5;p14.151">Before opening at the nipple, each duct exhibits a lactiferous sinus which permits the accumulation of milk in the lactating mother. </s><s n="s4.5;p14.151">The nipple itself contains connective tissue and smooth muscle cells which allow the formation of a circular sphincter. </s><s n="s5.5;p14.151">The area surrounding the nipple, known as the areola, also contains numerous sebaceous glands which enlarge during pregnancy and secrete an oily substance to protect against irritation and chaffing which may occur when nursing (5). </s></p><p n="p15.151"><s n="s1.4;p15.151">In the non-pregnant state (i.e. when lactation is not occurring), the lactiferous ducts end in a group of blind, saccular evaginations which exhibit relatively few, if any, lobules. </s><s n="s2.4;p15.151">The most noticeable characteristic of breast tissue during pregnancy is therefore the formation of lobules and lobes. </s><s n="s3.4;p15.151">It is this development of glandular tissue along with increased fat deposition which results in the breast enlargement associated with pregnancy. </s><s n="s4.4;p15.151">Following pregnancy, further adipose tissue replaces the lobular alveolar tissue (4). </s></p><p n="p16.151"><s n="s1.6;p16.151">The breast also undergoes minor changes during each menstrual cycle, in response to the variations which occur in the circulating levels of sex steroids (Figure 2.6). </s><s n="s2.6;p16.151">During the post-ovulation secretory phase, the rising oestrogen and gonadotrophin (e.g. </s><s n="s3.6;p16.151">LH and FSH) levels cause the lobular stroma to become oedematous, resulting in breast enlargement and the sensation of tenderness that is often experienced prior to menstruation. </s><s n="s4.6;p16.151">In addition both progesterone and oestrogen promote cell division mitosis during this period, and although subsequent apoptosis ensures the overall balance is maintained, it may cause temporary lumpiness of the breast. </s><s n="s5.6;p16.151">It is important to appreciate these normal physiological changes and the times at which they occur in order to provide reassurance to concerned patients. </s><s n="s6.6;p16.151">As a result however, it is usually beneficial to examine the breasts of pre-menopausal women in the first half of the cycle (5). </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0047a-fig.004"><head><hi rend="bold">Figure 2.6 Changes in breast epithelium and stroma during the menstrual cycle</hi> (5) </head></figure><p n="p17.151"><s n="s1.4;p17.151">With increasing age, breast tissue also undergoes changes due to the altered sex steroid levels, which accompany decreasing ovarian function. </s><s n="s2.4;p17.151">For example, the connective tissue of the lobules changes from a loose to a dense structure, the basement membrane thickens and the cells lining the acini are lost (5). </s><s n="s3.4;p17.151">These changes start during the pre-menopausal period and continue past the menopause, until old age is reached by which point the breast is primarily composed of adipose tissue. </s><s n="s4.4;p17.151">Importantly these changes occur at an uneven rate which frequently results in clinically palpable lumps (8). </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">3. PATHOLOGY AND HISTOLOGY</head><p n="p18.151"><s n="s1.4;p18.151">Given the high incidence rates, it is not surprising that there has been significant research interest in the aetiological mechanisms associated with the development of breast carcinoma. </s><s n="s2.4;p18.151">As a result, numerous risk factors have been identified which correlate with an increased risk of pathogenesis. </s><s n="s3.4;p18.151">In most cases it is uncertain whether the individual factors act as initiators or promoters, due to the complex interactions between them (5). </s><s n="s4.4;p18.151">Some of these factors will be examined below. </s></p><div2><head rend="underlined bold">3.1 Risk Factors</head><div3><head rend="underlined">Gender and Age</head><p n="p19.151"><s n="s1.3;p19.151">The single biggest risk factor for developing breast carcinoma is being female, as less than 1% of carcinomas occur in males and although this aspect will not be discussed further, it is undoubtedly important to be aware of this fact especially if presented with a concerned male patient. </s><s n="s2.3;p19.151">The incidence of breast carcinoma, as with most other malignancies, increases with age. </s><s n="s3.3;p19.151">In particular there is a rapid increase which can be observed between the ages of 45-50 (5). </s></p></div3><div3><head rend="underlined">Family History of Breast Cancer</head><p n="p20.151"><s n="s1.4;p20.151">Another important risk factor is to ascertain is whether there is any evidence of breast cancer in first degree relatives for example in the mother or sisters. </s><s n="s2.4;p20.151">Particular interest should be made to relatives who developed the disease prior to the menopause, as this strongly suggests an underlying genetic basis. </s><s n="s3.4;p20.151">Approximately 10% of breast cancer is due to genetic predisposition (9). </s><s n="s4.4;p20.151">Genetic susceptibility to breast cancer is generally inherited as an autosomal dominant trait exhibiting limited penetrance, it can therefore be transmitted through either sex, although it may not necessarily manifest in the phenotype of all carriers (10). </s></p><p n="p21.151"><s n="s1.6;p21.151">Two major susceptibility genes, known as BRCA1 and BRCA2, have been identified to date. </s><s n="s2.6;p21.151">About one-third of familial cases exhibit mutations in the tumour suppressor gene BRCA1 which is located on the long arm of chromosome 17. </s><s n="s3.6;p21.151">Over 200 mutations have been described in BRCA1, some of which are associated with different risks, in particular distal mutations are almost exclusively associated with breast cancer, whilst those occurring early in the gene predispose to ovarian and breast cancer. </s><s n="s4.6;p21.151">As a result of the latter, BRCA1 is responsible for almost all families with a susceptibility to both ovarian and breast cancer. </s><s n="s5.6;p21.151">The second hereditary locus, BRCA2, is found on the long arm of chromosome 13 and is typically associated with families with early onset or male breast cancer (10). </s><s n="s6.6;p21.151">In both cases, early detection is essential as up to 90% of patients will survive if the malignancy is found at an early stage (11). </s></p><p n="p22.151"><s n="s1.5;p22.151">In addition, abnormalities in the p53 tumour suppressor gene have also been linked to malignancy. </s><s n="s2.5;p22.151">For example, up to 40% of sporadic tumours exhibit p53 mutations (9). </s><s n="s3.5;p22.151">Mutations have also been identified in rare conditions such as Li-fraumeni syndrome, in which there is an association between sarcomas, brain tumours and early onset breast cancer. </s><s n="s4.5;p22.151">Although collectively these genes account for a significant proportion of breast carcinomas, there are undoubtedly further genes conferring susceptibility which have yet to be discovered. </s><s n="s5.5;p22.151">It is also important to remember that despite the association with these individual mutations, a proportion of cancers arising in those with genetic factors are still likely to be sporadic (5). </s></p></div3><div3><head rend="underlined">Age at Key Reproductive Stages</head><p n="p23.151"><s n="s1.7;p23.151">The risk of developing breast cancer is also significantly higher amongst women experiencing either an early menarche or a late menopause, therefore attention to these elements of the reproductive history is particularly important. </s><s n="s2.7;p23.151">For example women experiencing the menopause after the age of 55, have twice the risk of developing carcinoma in comparison with those reaching it before 45. </s><s n="s3.7;p23.151">It therefore becomes apparent that extended menstrual activity can have a significant effect. </s><s n="s4.7;p23.151">Parity has also been demonstrated to be associated with breast cancer development. </s><s n="s5.7;p23.151">In general, pregnancy is believed to confer some protection, which is related to the age at which the first birth occurs. </s><s n="s6.7;p23.151">Those who delayed their pregnancy until they entered their thirties were at twice the risk compared to teenage mothers. </s><s n="s7.7;p23.151">Nulliparous women also have an increased lifetime incidence of breast cancer, however the risk is greater amongst women delaying the first birth until their mid to late thirties (5). </s></p><p n="p24.151"><s n="s1.3;p24.151">The association of breast cancer risk with menarche, menopause and first full time pregnancy indicates that hormones may have a role in development of carcinomas, however they are much more likely to be promoters than initiators. </s><s n="s2.3;p24.151">Oestrogen activity appears to be most important hormonal factor, in particular overexposure to oestrogens and under-exposure to progesterone are associated with increased risk. </s><s n="s3.3;p24.151">For example, early menarche and late menopause will both result in a greater number of menstrual cycles, which will subsequently prolong the period over which the tissue is exposed to the stimulatory oestrogen surges (5). </s></p></div3><div3><head rend="underlined">Use of Hormone Therapy</head><p n="p25.151"><s n="s1.5;p25.151">The suggested role of oestrogen in the pathogenesis of breast carcinoma obviously raises questions regarding the safety of common hormonal therapies such the oral contraceptive pill (OCP) and hormonal replacement therapy (HRT). </s><s n="s2.5;p25.151">Numerous studies have been carried out investigating the effect of the OCP, and although no definite relationship has been demonstrated, those contraceptives containing a high oestrogen content have been linked with breast carcinoma, in addition to their established role in endometrial cancer. </s><s n="s3.5;p25.151">In previous studies, high oestrogen pills have been linked to an increased risk of endometrial and possibly breast cancer (12). </s><s n="s4.5;p25.151">However recent meta-analysis of studies examining oral contraceptives and breast cancer risk show a slight increase in the relative risk of breast cancer whilst taking the OCP, which remains for up to ten years after cessation. </s><s n="s5.5;p25.151">The breast cancers occurring in women on the OCP are however, more likely to be localised to breast, rather than involving the regional nodes (13). </s></p><p n="p26.151"><s n="s1.2;p26.151">Interestingly the high progesterone and prolactin levels associated with pregnancy may have a protective role due to their inhibitory effect on oestrogen. </s><s n="s2.2;p26.151">This benefit is also believed to extend to oral contraceptives with a low oestrogen-to-progesterone ratio (5). </s></p><p n="p27.151"><s n="s1.2;p27.151">The use of postmenopausal oestrogen replacement therapy (HRT) increases the risk of breast cancer, and although this risk disappears 5 years after cessation, evidence suggests that the risk increases significantly during prolonged use, especially beyond fifteen years. </s><s n="s2.2;p27.151">Over short periods, the risk of developing cancer as a result of these preparations is offset by the prophylactic benefits they provide against osteoporosis and ischemic heart disease (14). </s></p></div3><div3><head rend="underlined">Previous Evidence of Atypical Hyperplasia</head><p n="p28.151"><s n="s1.4;p28.151">Within normal breast tissue a process known as epithelial hyperplasia may occasionally occur whereby excessive epithelial cell proliferation occurs within the acini or small ducts. </s><s n="s2.4;p28.151">This leads to solid masses, which may cause partial or complete occlusion of the duct lumen. </s><s n="s3.4;p28.151">Although these changes aren't necessarily associated with a pre-malignant stage, cells exhibiting abnormal characteristics such as nuclear pleomorphism and mitotic figures may occur, giving rise to atypical hyperplasia. </s><s n="s4.4;p28.151">Although the majority of women who experience benign breast disease, do not generally have an increased risk of breast cancer, however those who demonstrate the presence of atypical epithelial hyperplasia in subsequent biopsies will definitely exhibit a greater risk of developing future malignancies (5). </s></p></div3><div3><head rend="underlined">Additional Risk Factors </head><p n="p29.151"><s n="s1.3;p29.151">Various other aetiological factors have been proposed including alcohol consumption, smoking, viruses and whether any children were breast-fed. </s><s n="s2.3;p29.151">A recent review indicates that there is little evidence that these factors have a significant role in the direct pathogenesis of breast cancer. </s><s n="s3.3;p29.151">Further studies also suggest correlations with obesity and a high-fat diet, although these have generally been unconfirmed (15). </s></p></div3></div2><div2><head rend="underlined bold">3.2 Histological Presentation</head><p n="p30.151"><s n="s1.2;p30.151">Despite the proposed mechanisms, in practice it is often difficult to establish which factors, if any, were associated with the development of the cancer. </s><s n="s2.2;p30.151">It is however essential that the histological features of the lesion are determined as these will allow the specific type of breast cancer to be identification, and therefore provide valuable information regarding prognosis and further treatment options (16). </s></p><p n="p31.151"><s n="s1.4;p31.151">The majority of breast carcinomas are adenocarcinomas and are therefore derived from the epithelial cells lining the ducts and lobules. </s><s n="s2.4;p31.151">Of these 90% of carcinomas arise from ductal epithelium, whilst the remainder occur within the lobular alveolar-ductal epithelium (4). </s><s n="s3.4;p31.151">In either case, a carcinoma is defined as in situ if the tumour cells are localised and there is no evidence of penetration through the basement membrane into the surrounding fibrous connective tissue. </s><s n="s4.4;p31.151">It is therefore possible to classify non-invasive cancers as either ductal carcinoma in situ (DCIS) or lobular carcinoma in situ (LCIS). </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">Ductal Carcinoma in Situ</head><p n="p32.151"><s n="s1.3;p32.151">Ductal carcinoma in situ occurs in both pre-menopausal and postmenopausal women, typically in the 40 to 60 year age groups, and accounts for approximately 5% breast carcinoma diagnoses. </s><s n="s2.3;p32.151">It usually presents as a palpable mass, especially if extensive and associated with fibrosis. </s><s n="s3.3;p32.151">Involvement of the larger ducts may also lead to nipple discharge or Paget's disease of the nipple (4). </s></p><p n="p33.151"><s n="s1.3;p33.151">The lesions typically range in size from 10-100mm, and are unilateral being localized to one quadrant of the breast. </s><s n="s2.3;p33.151">DCIS is considered a precursor for invasive cancer as it commonly spreads along the duct system or into the lobules if untreated. </s><s n="s3.3;p33.151">However as it is localized, it can be totally removed surgically (5). </s></p><p n="p34.151"><s n="s1.5;p34.151">The histological appearance depends upon the architecture of the DCIS, although the ducts may be filled with either cells (solid pattern) or exhibit central necrosis (comedo pattern). </s><s n="s2.5;p34.151">In the latter, creamy necrotic material may exude from the cut surface of the breast and may allow mammographical detection if calcification has occurred. </s><s n="s3.5;p34.151">The ductal cells usually exhibit varying degrees of cytoplasmic and nuclear pleomorphism, along with frequent mitotic figures. </s><s n="s4.5;p34.151">These changes are usually found in the small or medium sized ducts, although in older women, the large ducts may also be involved. </s><s n="s5.5;p34.151">The histological features of DCIS are summarised in figure 3.1. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0047a-pic.006"><head><hi rend="bold">Figure 3.1 Typical features of DCIS</hi> (5)</head></figure><div3><head rend="underlined">Lobular Carcinoma in Situ</head><p n="p35.151"><s n="s1.5;p35.151">In contrast, LCIS primarily occurs in pre-menopausal women, although it may present later in association with an infiltrating tumour. </s><s n="s2.5;p35.151">LCIS is considerably more difficult to detect and rarely presents as a palpable lump, instead it is usually found incidentally as a result of surgical biopsies removed because of cysts or benign masses (4). </s><s n="s3.5;p35.151">It is often bilateral and may even be multifocal within one breast. </s><s n="s4.5;p35.151">Unsurprisingly there are no specific radiological or macroscopic features. </s><s n="s5.5;p35.151">The histological features of LCIS are summarised in figure 3.2. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0047a-pic.007"><head><hi rend="bold">Figure 3.2 Typical features of LCIS</hi> (5)</head></figure></div3><div3><head rend="underlined">Invasive Carcinomas</head><p n="p36.151"><s n="s1.7;p36.151">Invasive or infiltrating carcinomas by definition are tumours which have broken through the basement membrane and subsequently entered into the surrounding tissue. </s><s n="s2.7;p36.151">Although invasive carcinomas are categorised into different histological types as with localised carcinomas, the name given doesn't necessarily indicate that that the tumour arises from that site only. </s><s n="s3.7;p36.151">For example, cells at the junction of the extralobular and intralobular ducts may give rise to both invasive ductal and lobular carcinomas and therefore an invasive ductal carcinoma may develop in a patient with previous lobular carcinoma in situ. </s><s n="s4.7;p36.151">Invasive carcinomas vary in size significantly, but are typically between 20-30mm at presentation. </s><s n="s5.7;p36.151">They are usually firm on palpation and may show evidence of tethering to overlying skin or underlying muscle. </s><s n="s6.7;p36.151">Lymphatic permeation may also cause dimpling of the skin known as <hi rend="italic">peau d' orange</hi>. </s><s n="s7.7;p36.151">Nipple retraction is also commonly observed due to tethering or contraction of the intra-mammary ligaments (5). </s></p><p n="p37.151"><s n="s1.9;p37.151">The presenting features observed in each case are largely dependent upon the composition of the underlying tumour and the amount or type of stroma that they contain. </s><s n="s2.9;p37.151">As a result the macroscopic appearance of invasive carcinomas is traditionally described as scirrhous, medullary or mucinous depending upon their composition. </s><s n="s3.9;p37.151">Scirrhous implies a prominent fibrous tissue reaction, which results in a characteristic white, dense tissue. </s><s n="s4.9;p37.151">Yellow streaks may also form due to the presence of elastic tissue. </s><s n="s5.9;p37.151">The high proportion of fibrous tissue leads to the formation of irregular shaped tumour, extending into adjacent structures such as fat. </s><s n="s6.9;p37.151">It is the process of the fibrous reaction which results in skin retraction. </s><s n="s7.9;p37.151">In contrast, medullary carcinomas are very cellular with relatively little fibrous material. </s><s n="s8.9;p37.151">Necrosis is also common therefore they appear softer, rounded and more discrete than scirrhous tumours. </s><s n="s9.9;p37.151">Finally, mucinous carcinomas have a well-defined edge and contain mucin, or jelly-like material within them (5). </s></p><p n="p38.151"><s n="s1.2;p38.151">By far the commonest form of breast malignancy is the infiltrating ductal carcinoma (IDC) which accounts for over 75% of breast tumours, in both pre- and post-menopausal women (See 9.1 and 9.3). </s><s n="s2.2;p38.151">These usually exhibit a scirrhous consistency, and are formed by tumour cells arranged in clusters, cords or gland-like structures (Figure 3.3). </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0047a-pic.008"><head><hi rend="bold">Figure 3.3 Characteristic features of infiltrating ductal carcinoma</hi> (5)</head></figure><p n="p39.151"><s n="s1.3;p39.151">Unlike LCIS which predominates in pre-menopausal, infiltrating lobular carcinomas (ILC) may also occur in postmenopausal women, accounting for approximately 10% of invasive tumours (See 9.2). </s><s n="s2.3;p39.151">As a result of abundant levels of fibrous stroma, ILC tumours typically have a scirrhous macroscopic appearance and while IDC usually form at one focus in the breast, ILC can be multifocal throughout the breast. </s><s n="s3.3;p39.151">In addition the histological appearance also differs significantly, as the cells of ILC are small, uniform and dispersed singly, or in strands of one cell wide, which are known as 'Indian files', in a dense stroma (Figure 3.4). </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0047a-pic.009"><head><hi rend="bold">Figure 3.4 Typical appearance of infiltrating lobular carcinoma</hi> (5)</head></figure><p n="p40.151"><s n="s1.2;p40.151">There are also several further classifications of invasive carcinoma which are significantly less common than those described above (Table 3.1). </s><s n="s2.2;p40.151">Therefore these will not be discussed further although it is important to note that despite their relative rarity they typically have a better prognosis. </s></p><table id="BAWE_0047a-tab.001"><head><hi rend="bold">Table 3.1 Further classifications of infiltrating carcinomas</hi> (Figures from 5)</head><row><cell/></row></table></div3></div2><div2><head rend="underlined bold">3.3 Metastatic Disease</head><p n="p41.151"><s n="s1.2;p41.151">As previously mentioned, metastatic disease is a significant problem in breast cancer patients, as metastases can occur in almost any organ of the body. </s><s n="s2.2;p41.151">Tumour cells spread to further structures either by infiltrating into local tissues, or undergoing metastasis to more distant sites via lymphatics or the blood stream (Figure 3.5) </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0047a-pic.010"><head><hi rend="bold">Figure 3.5 Common sites of breast cancer metastases</hi> (5)</head></figure><p n="p42.151"><s n="s1.3;p42.151">The axillary lymph nodes represent the commonest initial site of metastasis via lymphatic spread with approximately 40-50% of malignancies exhibiting secondary tumours in this region. </s><s n="s2.3;p42.151">Metastases also commonly occur in the intramammary, supraclavicular and tracheobrachial nodes. </s><s n="s3.3;p42.151">Due to the frequency with which metastases occur it is essential that areas prone to metastases are understood and investigated thoroughly. </s></p><p n="p43.151"><s n="s1.2;p43.151">When investigating suspected axillary spread, histological examination is essential as palpation is often unreliable. </s><s n="s2.2;p43.151">Oedema may also arise following permeation of the localised lymphatic channels, resulting in the classic <hi rend="italic">peau d'orange</hi> sign associated with advanced carcinoma (8). </s></p><p n="p44.151"><s n="s1.2;p44.151">The lungs, liver, bone and brain are the commonest sites haematogenous spread of metastases. </s><s n="s2.2;p44.151">In these cases, secondary tumours frequently appear years or decades after the initial diagnosis and treatment of breast cancer, and therefore any symptoms should prompt immediate investigation (8). </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">4. SCREENING AND PREVENTION</head><p n="p45.151"><s n="s1.2;p45.151">The majority of well established risk factors which have been identified for breast cancer are non modifiable and therefore unlike the association between smoking and lung cancer, there is no single major cause which can be easily avoided. </s><s n="s2.2;p45.151">It has however been shown that the success rates for treatment are closely linked to the stage of the cancer at presentation, and as a result it is thought that a reduction in mortality from breast cancer can logically be achieved through screening processes which allow early detection (17). </s></p><p n="p46.151"><s n="s1.5;p46.151">Mammography is the favoured screening technique, because unlike clinical examination and self-breast examination, it has been shown in several randomised control trials to reduce mortality from breast cancer. </s><s n="s2.5;p46.151">For example, studies by Forest, Shapiro and Tabar showed reductions in mortality of between 20-50% in women over fifty who were screened regularly (19, 20 ,21). </s><s n="s3.5;p46.151">In contrast, there is no evidence to support population screening of women under forty who are not at increased risk of breast cancer. </s><s n="s4.5;p46.151">Instead the evidence from this group indicates that the incidence of breast cancer is significantly lower, the sensitivity of mammography is reduced and the risk of radiation-induced cancer is relatively high (22). </s><s n="s5.5;p46.151">No randomised control trials have yet been published specifically examining women between these two age groups, however subgroup analysis of RCTs including this group indicate that any benefits are outweighed by large numbers of false positives and benign biopsies, as well as the financial implications of unnecessary recall and follow-up (23). </s></p><p n="p47.151"><s n="s1.3;p47.151">Screening is defined as the application of diagnostic measures to an apparently healthy population in order to detect serious disease at an early stage when treatment is more likely to be curative than it is at a later stage. </s><s n="s2.3;p47.151">Before any screening process can be introduced, there are several criteria as proposed by the World Health Organisation (WHO) that should ideally be met. </s><s n="s3.3;p47.151">These are summarised in table 4.1 along with the evidence to support the use of mammography for breast cancer screening. </s></p><table id="BAWE_0047a-tab.002"><head><hi rend="bold">Table 4.1. Criteria for screening programmes</hi> (Information obtained from 23)</head><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p48.151"><s n="s1.2;p48.151">As table 4.1 indicates, mammography fulfils most the requirements for a screening programme and in 1988 the Forrest committee published its recommendations for introducing a National Breast Screening Programme (NHSBSP) aimed at targeting the two strongest risk factors i.e. being female and older age (19). </s><s n="s2.2;p48.151">The NHSBSP (Figure 4.1) was subsequently introduced in 1990. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0047a-fig.005"><head><hi rend="bold">Figure 4.1 An overview of the breast screening process</hi> (Adapted from 24) </head></figure><p n="p49.151"><s n="s1.2;p49.151">Since its introduction, the NHSBSP has screened than 14 million women and detected over 80,000 cancers. </s><s n="s2.2;p49.151">As a result it has lead to a significant improvement in overall survival (Figure 4.2), saving an estimated 300 lives each year (25, 26). </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0047a-fig.006"><head><hi rend="bold">Figure 4.2 Effect of the NHSBSP upon breast cancer incidence and mortality</hi> (26)</head></figure><p n="p50.151"><s n="s1.1;p50.151">Although the screening programme has been a significant success statistically, it is important to consider the psychosocial effects it may have upon those being assessed. </s></p><p n="p51.151"><s n="s1.5;p51.151">As mammography requires compression of the breast, temporary physical discomfort is often reported. </s><s n="s2.5;p51.151">More importantly it has also been shown to have adverse psychological affects (27). </s><s n="s3.5;p51.151">For example, Cockburn et al examined the emotional, social and physical functioning of women undergoing screening and reported that those recalled suffered significant dysfunction which continued for a period even after obtaining notification that there was no sign of cancer (28). </s><s n="s4.5;p51.151">Therefore given that up to 10% of women are recalled for further investigations, large numbers of women may be at risk of adverse psychological consequences. </s><s n="s5.5;p51.151">It is therefore essential that results are accurately interpreted to minimise the false positive recall rate, and that counselling services are available at recall assessment centres. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">5. INVESTIGATION</head><p n="p52.151"><s n="s1.5;p52.151">Appropriately 90% of breast cancers are discovered as a lump by the patient or their partner (2). </s><s n="s2.5;p52.151">Patients may also present with a history of pain and no mass, with breast enlargement, or with a nondescript thickening in the breast. </s><s n="s3.5;p52.151">Due to the non-specific nature of presentation a structured method of assessment is required in order to prevent cases being missed. </s><s n="s4.5;p52.151">The system used to investigate suspected breast carcinoma is generally known as the "triple assessment". </s><s n="s5.5;p52.151">Following referral to a specialist breast cancer clinic, the patient will past through three stages of investigation which are outlined below (29): </s></p><list type="ordered"><head>The Triple Assessment: 1) Clinical Assessment</head><item> 2) Imaging and Radiology</item><item> 3) Needle Biopsy</item></list><div2><head rend="underlined bold">5.1 Clinical Assessment</head><p n="p53.151"><s n="s1.5;p53.151">The initial assessment consists of a complete patient history followed by a physical examination. </s><s n="s2.5;p53.151">The ability to obtain a detailed history of the problem is important in order to determine the time scale and nature of the problem. </s><s n="s3.5;p53.151">The time since first noticed, any increases in size and any associated nipple or skin problems are all important factors to determine. </s><s n="s4.5;p53.151">Any pain should be investigated e.g. whether it is associated with the menstrual cycle or whether it affects one or both the breasts. </s><s n="s5.5;p53.151">In addition, it important is to identify any of the risk factors previously described. </s></p><p n="p54.151"><s n="s1.7;p54.151">Clinical examination of the breast initially involves observing changes in gross breast shape, size and symmetry. </s><s n="s2.7;p54.151">The breast is then palpated whilst the patient is supine starting with the normal breast to assess the natural consistency of the tissue. </s><s n="s3.7;p54.151">The typical finding is a dominant mass distinctly different from the surrounding breast tissue. </s><s n="s4.7;p54.151">The characteristics of such a lesion must be recorded for example, size, position, shape, consistency, mobility and any associated pain. </s><s n="s5.7;p54.151">Diffuse fibrotic changes in a quadrant of the breast, usually the upper outer quadrant, are usually more characteristic of benign disorders; however a slightly firmer thickening absent in the contralateral breast may be a sign of cancer. </s><s n="s6.7;p54.151">More advanced breast cancers are typically characterized by fixation of the mass to the chest wall or to overlying skin or by the presence of nodules, ulcers in the skin or <hi rend="italic">peau d'orange</hi>. </s><s n="s7.7;p54.151">Diffuse inflammation and enlargement of the breast, often in the absence of a mass, may indicate inflammatory breast cancer, which is associated with a poor prognosis (8). </s></p><p n="p55.151"><s n="s1.3;p55.151">The nipple should also be briefly examined for signs of any obvious lumps or evidence of asymmetry, inversion or discharge. </s><s n="s2.3;p55.151">The tail of the breast, the axilla and the neck are then assessed for lymphadenopathy. </s><s n="s3.3;p55.151">If any abnormalities are found it may also be necessary to examine the abdomen and spine for evidence of hepatic or bone involvement respectively (8). </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined bold">5.2 Imaging and Radiology</head><p n="p56.151"><s n="s1.1;p56.151">The second stage of the triple assessment investigation usually involves either mammography or ultrasound imaging techniques. </s></p><p n="p57.151"><s n="s1.11;p57.151">Mammography is extremely effective at showing lumps and areas of calcification within the breast, therefore in most circumstances it is possible to predict the nature of a lesion solely by its appearance on the mammogram (30). </s><s n="s2.11;p57.151">For example, benign lumps such as fibroadenomas are usually very discrete with well-defined margins on the X-ray, whilst the invasion of malignant lesions into surrounding structures results in poorly defined, irregular margins. </s><s n="s3.11;p57.151">Mammography does have its limitations though, particularly in association with nulliparous women or in those less than 35 years of age. </s><s n="s4.11;p57.151">This is due to the high percentage of connective tissue they exhibit, which promotes X-ray absorption and therefore results in a mostly opaque film. </s><s n="s5.11;p57.151">Large regions of opacities may also be seen in women over 35. </s><s n="s6.11;p57.151">These opacities appear as compression of normal breast tissue creates the appearance of apparently dense regions on the film. </s><s n="s7.11;p57.151">However as two X-ray planes are now assessed (i.e. cranio-caudal and mediolateral oblique views), any abnormalities can usually be ruled out by examining the tissue in the opposite direction. </s><s n="s8.11;p57.151">Women with large regions of opacities must therefore be reassured that they do not always mean bad news. </s><s n="s9.11;p57.151">Furthermore, the patient's age, parity and circulating hormone levels can all influence the appearance of the mammogram. </s><s n="s10.11;p57.151">In either circumstance, it can be difficult to detect abnormalities when dense tissue is present, because they do not stand out from the surrounding tissue. </s><s n="s11.11;p57.151">In such patients where mammography is of limited value ultrasound imaging may be more beneficial. </s></p><p n="p58.151"><s n="s1.4;p58.151">Another finding often seen on mammograms is micro-calcification. </s><s n="s2.4;p58.151">Tiny speckles of calcium can be seen clearly, because they do not allow X-rays to pass, so appear white on the film. </s><s n="s3.4;p58.151">It is known that a number of breast problems can cause microcalcification to occur, most of which are usually benign. </s><s n="s4.4;p58.151">However, it is important to note that calcification of the ducts is an early indicator of DCIS, which may be observed before they are clinically palpable (5). </s></p><p n="p59.151"><s n="s1.2;p59.151">Ultrasound scans (USS) are of great value in the investigation of breast lumps and cysts particularly in younger women who have dense breasts, as cysts and solid lumps have characteristic appearances which allow them to be easily identified (Figure 5.1) (31). </s><s n="s2.2;p59.151">In addition, the use of USS prevents unnecessary exposure to radiation in these populations. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0047a-pic.011"><head><hi rend="bold">Figure 5.1 Comparison of ultrasound images</hi> (31) </head></figure><p n="p60.151"><s n="s1.2;p60.151">USS is however less useful for areas of general "lumpiness" where there is no discrete abnormality to feel, as the quality of the image is restricted by the resolution of the scanner and the operator's experience (8). </s><s n="s2.2;p60.151">It is also limited in its ability to diagnose non-cystic and non-solid breast problems such as fibrocystic change where there is diffuse glandularity and lumpiness throughout the breast. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined bold">5.3 Cytology</head><p n="p61.151"><s n="s1.1;p61.151">Cytological analysis involves either Fine Needle Aspiration Cytology (FNAC) or a core needle biopsy. </s></p><p n="p62.151"><s n="s1.6;p62.151">FNAC provides a quick and relatively painless method of determining whether a lesion is solid or cystic (8). </s><s n="s2.6;p62.151">If a cyst is present, cystic fluid will be obtained and often the lump will subsequently disappear. </s><s n="s3.6;p62.151">In this way the diagnosis and treatment are achieved at the same time. </s><s n="s4.6;p62.151">Cell aspirate obtained using FNAC may also be sufficient to confirm solid tumours, although a more definitive procedure such as needle biopsy should be performed if aspirate from a suspicious lesion is negative as it is difficult to determine whether the needle entered the lesion. </s><s n="s5.6;p62.151">For example sampling from very small lumps may prove unreliable, especially in women with large breasts. </s><s n="s6.6;p62.151">Despite this caveat, FNAC is still an important technique, particularly as it may provide results within a few hours and therefore helps minimise the anxiety associated with awaiting a diagnosis (32). </s></p><p n="p63.151"><s n="s1.4;p63.151">In contrast, the tradition core needle biopsy is a more sophisticated test than FNAC and provides a great deal more information regarding the potential tumour. </s><s n="s2.4;p63.151">As mentioned above, this technique is reserved for lumps with suspicious results, although it is more frequently used to establish an exact diagnosis before planning treatment. </s><s n="s3.4;p63.151">The results generally take longer to obtain, however it does provide information regarding the type of cancer present, whether it is invasive and whether or not it is likely to respond to hormonal treatment (30). </s><s n="s4.4;p63.151">This information is of paramount importance in determining what type of surgical treatment should be performed. </s></p><p n="p64.151"><s n="s1.1;p64.151">In recent years, there has also been a move towards the use of ultrasound-guided biopsies which allow improve diagnostic accuracy. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined bold">5.4 Additional Investigations</head><div3><head rend="underlined">Oestrogen Receptors</head><p n="p65.151"><s n="s1.5;p65.151">Following biopsy, specimens are also routinely analysed for oestrogen and progesterone receptors using antigen-based immunohistochemical techniques (30). </s><s n="s2.5;p65.151">There are two types of oestrogen surface receptors,  and , both of which are believed to regulate cell growth within breast tissue (4). </s><s n="s3.5;p65.151">The relative risk of tumour development is therefore increased if cellular mutations result in abnormal receptor expression. </s><s n="s4.5;p65.151">In general about 60% of patients have an oestrogen-receptor positive (ER+) tumour, the majority of which occur in postmenopausal women and exhibit an over expression of  - receptors. </s><s n="s5.5;p65.151">It is thought that the progesterone receptor reflects a functional oestrogen receptor and therefore the presence of both receptors predicts a greater likelihood of response than the presence of oestrogen receptors alone (30). </s></p><p n="p66.151"><s n="s1.4;p66.151">It is important to determine the receptor status as ER+ tumours exhibit an improved prognosis as they are more susceptible to endocrine therapy with oestrogen receptor antagonists such as Tamoxifen, Fulvestrant and Toremifene (33, 34). </s><s n="s2.4;p66.151">Knowledge of receptor status also aids the selection of adjuvant therapeutics following excision or radiation therapy, and palliative therapy if metastatic disease develops. </s><s n="s3.4;p66.151">The tissue specimens may also be evaluated for ploidy and S-phase fraction of cells. </s><s n="s4.4;p66.151">Patients who have aneuploid tumours typically have a worse prognosis (8). </s></p></div3><div3><head rend="underlined">Herceptin Receptors</head><p n="p67.151"><s n="s1.5;p67.151">There is also been a move towards testing tumour samples for the presence of the cell surface receptor HER2 (human epidermal growth factor receptor 2) which is a key component in regulating cell growth in normal cells. </s><s n="s2.5;p67.151">In approximately 25-30% of breast cancers, tumour cells exhibit mutations which cause gene amplification of the HER2 proto-oncagene and therefore HER2 protein over-expression (35). </s><s n="s3.5;p67.151">This results in increased rates of cell division and typically a more aggressive tumour which is less responsive to standard breast cancer treatments. </s><s n="s4.5;p67.151">HER2 over-expression also correlates with several negative prognostic variables, including oestrogen receptor-negative status, aneuploidy, nodal infiltration and p53 mutations (37). </s><s n="s5.5;p67.151">The use of Herceptin (Trastuzumab), a monoclonal antibody which binds to HER2, has however been shown to be highly effective against HER+ tumours (30). </s></p></div3><div3><head rend="underlined">Tumour Markers</head><p n="p68.151"><s n="s1.4;p68.151">Although there has been significant research into tumour markers associated with breast carcinoma, the majority have been shown to be non-specific and of little clinical use (38). </s><s n="s2.4;p68.151">CA15-3 is currently the only marker in routine use; even then it is limited to monitoring patients undergoing treatment and to determining whether recurrence or a reduction in metastatic cell mass has occurred. </s><s n="s3.4;p68.151">For example, elevated levels are found in approximately 70% of patients with metastatic disease but only about 30-40% of those with non-metastasised carcinoma. </s><s n="s4.4;p68.151">However CA15-3 is still relatively non-specific as elevated levels may be found in bronchial, ovarian and colorectal tumours, and non-malignant conditions such as cirrhosis, hepatitis and benign breast disease (38). </s></p></div3></div2><div2><head rend="underlined bold">5.5 Future Investigations</head><p n="p69.151"><s n="s1.5;p69.151">The use of magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) in breast cancer is being examined in several distinct settings. </s><s n="s2.5;p69.151">Firstly, the use of MRI to screen younger women with a predisposition to <hi rend="italic">BRCA1</hi>/<hi rend="italic">BRCA2</hi> gene mutations is being investigated, as breast these cancers often occur at an early age when dense breast tissue decreases the sensitivity of mammographic screening (39). </s><s n="s3.5;p69.151">For example, a new study indicates that MRI (71%) is more sensitive than mammography (40%) for detecting cancers in women with inherited susceptibility (40). </s><s n="s4.5;p69.151">The use of MRI would also prevent unnecessary radiation exposure and allow detection of small multi-focal lesions. </s><s n="s5.5;p69.151">Despite the cost which would be associated with such an initiative, further evidence suggests that this may be a promising method to screening this high-risk population (41). </s></p><p n="p70.151"><s n="s1.2;p70.151">Further investigation of women with a clinical or mammographic abnormality could also be achieved using MRI, therefore help avoid the need to biopsy suspicious lesions. </s><s n="s2.2;p70.151">However one of the initial studies carried out suggested that although MRI had a greater positive predictive value than mammography (72.4% compared to 52.8%), this was not high enough to avoid a breast biopsy or provide justification for the routine use of MRI (42). </s></p><p n="p71.151"><s n="s1.2;p71.151">Despite the on-going research, at present MRI scans are only routinely used in breast cancer as an aid for improving the outcome of breast conserving surgery and in situations whereby mammography is unsuitable, i.e. in high risk patients who have undergone breast augmentation. </s><s n="s2.2;p71.151">However, there are obviously further benefits of using MRI scans to evaluate breast cancer; a few of these are summarised in table 5.1, along with relevant limitations. </s></p><table id="BAWE_0047a-tab.003"><head><hi rend="bold">Table 5.1 Benefits and limitations of breast MRI</hi> (43)</head><row><cell/></row></table></div2><div2><head rend="underlined bold">5.6 Staging and Grading</head><p n="p72.151"><s n="s1.2;p72.151">Once a diagnosis has been confirmed, staging of the breast cancer is carried out using the Tumour Node Metastasis (TNM) classification proposed by the American joint committee (Table 5.2) (9). </s><s n="s2.2;p72.151">This staging process dictates the most appropriate therapy and provides an indication of the likely prognosis, although within each staging group additional tumour characteristics such as ER and HER2 receptor status may also influence the prognosis (30). </s></p><table id="BAWE_0047a-tab.004"><head><hi rend="bold">Table 5.2 Summary of the TNM staging of breast cancer</hi> (Adapted from 9)</head><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p73.151"><s n="s1.2;p73.151">Grading of the biopsy sections is also carried out to determine the degree of tumour cell differentiation. </s><s n="s2.2;p73.151">Typically those which are well differentiated i.e. grade I tumours, have a much better outcome than grade III tumours (poorly differentiated) however grading does not provide an reliable prognostic measure of the tumours between these extremes and is therefore of less value than staging with regard to breast carcinoma (5). </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined bold">5.7 Differential Diagnosis</head><p n="p74.151"><s n="s1.2;p74.151">The most important lesions to consider in the differential diagnosis of breast carcinoma include the following benign conditions, in descending order of frequency: cystic disease of the breast, fibroadenoma, intraductal papilloma, lipoma and fat necrosis (30). </s><s n="s2.2;p74.151">These conditions will not be discussed further, although as previously mentioned, they account for the significant majority of breast lesions and it is therefore essential that they be excluded during any investigation. </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">6. MANAGEMENT AND TREATMENT </head><p n="p75.151"><s n="s1.1;p75.151">The treatment of breast cancer is dependent upon the stage of the disease and can broadly be classified as either early or advanced breast cancer. </s></p><div2><head rend="underlined bold">6.1 Early Breast Cancer </head><p n="p76.151"><s n="s1.6;p76.151">Breast cancers presenting relatively early, for example in clinical stage I or II are generally considered to be curable, although some stage III and inflammatory tumours may also be included in this group. </s><s n="s2.6;p76.151">The standard treatment for early cancers is surgical resection involving either wide local excision (WLE) or mastectomy. </s><s n="s3.6;p76.151">Breast conserving treatment such as WLE (lumpectomy) involves removal of the tumour and surrounding tissue, with or without local lymph nodes. </s><s n="s4.6;p76.151">In contrast, a mastectomy involves removal of all the breast tissue although the extent to which additional structures are affected depends upon the surgical approach selected. </s><s n="s5.6;p76.151">A modified radical mastectomy (total mastectomy plus axillary clearance) involves removal of all breast tissue, skin, lymph nodes and pectoralis fascia, whilst the simple (partial) mastectomy, as used in some cases of DCIS, leaves the skin and nipple intact. </s><s n="s6.6;p76.151">The underlying pectoralis major muscle is generally left untouched during mastectomy, although resection may occasionally be required (30). </s></p><p n="p77.151"><s n="s1.3;p77.151">Adjuvant radiotherapy may also be given following WLE to reduce the risk of local reoccurrence, or following mastectomy if surgical margins are inadequate. </s><s n="s2.3;p77.151">This has been shown to reduce the risk of local reoccurrence by 25% and improve survival by 3% (30). </s><s n="s3.3;p77.151">There is currently controversy regarding the timing of surgery with respect to the menstrual cycle as some studies suggest that operation during the time of unopposed oestrogen adversely affects survival, however the majority of evidence rejects these claims (44). </s></p><p n="p78.151"><s n="s1.3;p78.151">Axillary node dissection of some or all of the lymph nodes may also be necessary when treating early invasive cancers, depending upon the level of node involvement. </s><s n="s2.3;p78.151">Clearance of the axillary nodes frequently results in post-operative problems associated with lymphoedema, and moves are now being made towards the use of sentinel node biopsies in the UK for evaluating node involvement (See patient case study one). </s><s n="s3.3;p78.151">This procedure involves injecting a low-level radioactive tracer containing technetium-99 and a blue dye into the tissue surrounding the mass prior to surgery, thereby allowing the surgeons to identify the sentinel node i.e. the node most likely to contain metastatic cells (Figure 6.1) (45). </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0047a-pic.012"><head><hi rend="bold">Figure 6.1 Identification of a sentinel node</hi> (45)</head></figure><p n="p79.151"><s n="s1.5;p79.151">Breast conserving surgery with radiation is the preferred form of treatment for early tumours, particularly as numerous RCTs have shown mastectomy to have no additional effect upon survival (30). </s><s n="s2.5;p79.151">Despite this fact the standard therapy for most patients is a modified radical mastectomy. </s><s n="s3.5;p79.151">Although this may avoid the need for radiotherapy, it is more likely to affect the patient's sense of self due to their altered appearance and increase the psychological impact of the disease (46). </s><s n="s4.5;p79.151">It is therefore essential when deciding on surgery, that the rationale for the operation and any alternative forms of treatment are discussed with the patient. </s><s n="s5.5;p79.151">Studies suggest the majority of patients wish to save their breast, and therefore breast conserving surgery and irradiation should be offered whenever possible (30). </s></p><p n="p80.151"><s n="s1.2;p80.151">Following surgery and radiotherapy, adjuvant treatment with chemotherapy or hormonal therapy is advocated for patients with early breast cancer in order to eliminate the systemic metastases responsible for late reoccurrences whilst they are still microscopic and vulnerable. </s><s n="s2.2;p80.151">The use of tamoxifen can also reduce the occurrence of cancer in the contralateral breast (30). </s></p><p n="p81.151"><s n="s1.3;p81.151">CMF (Cyclophosphamide, methotrexate and 5-fluorouracil) is the most commonly used adjuvant therapy for early breast cancers and has been extensively studied (30). </s><s n="s2.3;p81.151">When used as an adjunct to surgery, it has been shown to improve both relapse-free and overall survival (47). </s><s n="s3.3;p81.151">Although numerous other chemotherapeutic regimes also exist which are effective, they are mainly variations based around the CMF programme (Table 6.1). </s></p><table id="BAWE_0047a-tab.005"><head><hi rend="bold">Table 6.1 Typical CMF adjuvant chemotherapy regime</hi> (30)</head><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p82.151"><s n="s1.3;p82.151">Tamoxifen is also commonly used in women with ER+ disease, and has been shown to reduce the death rate by as much as 25% (29). </s><s n="s2.3;p82.151">Tamoxifen is particularly favourable in patients with concomitant health problems such as the elderly as it has fewer side effects than chemotherapy. </s><s n="s3.3;p82.151">It also increases bone density and lowers lipoproteins levels providing protection from osteoporosis and coronary artery disease respectively, therefore reducing further co-morbidity. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined bold">6.2 Advanced Breast Cancer</head><p n="p83.151"><s n="s1.3;p83.151">Patients with advanced metastatic disease (i.e. stage IV) or unresectable local cancers are not suitable for surgery. </s><s n="s2.3;p83.151">Instead palliative treatment, aimed at maintaining a good quality of life for as long as possible, is the preferred course of action (30). </s><s n="s3.3;p83.151">This may involve radiotherapy, endocrine therapy or chemotherapy. </s></p><p n="p84.151"><s n="s1.4;p84.151">For patients without immediately life threatening disease, endocrine therapy is the initial treatment of choice in ER+ patients as it successfully shrinks disseminating tumours in 80% of cases (30). </s><s n="s2.4;p84.151">It is presumed these treatments work by eliminating tumour growth factors such as oestrogens, progesterone and androgens. </s><s n="s3.4;p84.151">The choice of endocrine therapy depends largely on the menopausal status of the patient, although tamoxifen is the most commonly prescribed form of hormone manipulation in both pre- and post-menopausal women, providing an average of 12 months remission. </s><s n="s4.4;p84.151">The typical treatments are summarised in table 6.2. </s></p><table id="BAWE_0047a-tab.006"><head rend="bold">Table 6.2 Approaches to hormonal manipulation in advanced breast cancer</head><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p85.151"><s n="s1.2;p85.151">When a response to endocrine therapy is considered unlikely, has been unsuccessful or a rapid response is necessary cytotoxic chemotherapy is required. </s><s n="s2.2;p85.151">Despite the possible side effects, chemotherapeutic drugs can provide a good quality of life for prolonged periods in patients with established metastatic disease (46). </s></p><p n="p86.151"><s n="s1.1;p86.151">The most effective cytotoxic drugs for the treatment of metastatic breast cancer are cyclophosphamide, doxorubicin, paclitaxel, docetaxel, navelbine, capecitabine, and mitomycin C, and most patients requiring palliative treatment with chemotherapy are initially prescribed CMF as previously mentioned, as response rates are greater when combination therapies are administered (8). </s></p><p n="p87.151"><s n="s1.4;p87.151">In addition new drugs and treatment strategies, such as biological response modifiers, may be beneficial if considered before extensive chemotherapy is given. </s><s n="s2.4;p87.151">For example, herceptin may induce remission in some patients with metastatic breast cancer and increase the value of cytotoxic therapy in others (8). </s><s n="s3.4;p87.151">Treatment with high doses of chemotherapy and bone marrow transplantation is also under study in patients with metastatic disease. </s><s n="s4.4;p87.151">Some results are promising, but whether this approach can substantially improve survival for women who do not respond to standard-dose chemotherapy is unclear (8). </s></p><p n="p88.151"><s n="s1.4;p88.151">Another option is palliative radiotherapy, which can be used, in advanced cancers to control features such as localised ulceration and pain. </s><s n="s2.4;p88.151">Although it is usually undertaken when a lesion is inoperable, it may occasionally prove curative if distant metastases are absent (30). </s><s n="s3.4;p88.151">Irradiation is also beneficial for metastatic bone or soft tissue as it helps prevent fractures and control pain. </s><s n="s4.4;p88.151">In addition, it provides an essential method of targeting isolated bone and brain metastases, and lesions causing acute spinal cord compression (8). </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">7. PROGNOSIS</head><p n="p89.151"><s n="s1.4;p89.151">Following diagnosis and treatment, questions understanably arise from patients regarding the prognosis and likelihood of cure. </s><s n="s2.4;p89.151">As with all forms of malignancy, breast cancer is an unpredictable condition however a number of factors can be used to give an indication of how successful treatment might have been (30). </s><s n="s3.4;p89.151">As previously mention the TNM staging system is the commonest method of predicting survival. </s><s n="s4.4;p89.151">The estimated lengths of survival for each stage are summarised in table 7.1. </s></p><table id="BAWE_0047a-tab.007"><head><hi rend="bold">Table 7.1 Survival of breast cancer patients according to stage</hi> (30)</head><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p90.151"><s n="s1.2;p90.151">A more established and validated model for predicting disease-specific survival in women with breast carcinoma is the Nottingham Prognostic Index (NPI), however this operates under the assumption that adjuvant therapy is not used (48). </s><s n="s2.2;p90.151">The NPI is routinely measured following tumour resection and separates women into three risk categories using a simple equation that depends on tumour size, tumour grade and lymph node status (Figure 7.1). </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0047a-fig.007"><head><hi rend="bold">Figure 7.1 Calculating NPI scores</hi> (48) </head></figure><p n="p91.151"><s n="s1.2;p91.151">Patients are subsequently classified as having either a good outcome with a high chance of a cure (&lt;3.4), a moderate chance of cure (3.4-5.4) or a poor prognosis with a smaller chance of cure (>5.4). </s><s n="s2.2;p91.151">Although the NPI is a useful guide, it is not absolutely reliable and there will always be many patients whose NPI predictions do not match the reality of their individual outcomes (48). </s></p><p n="p92.151"><s n="s1.4;p92.151">Regardless of the prognosis, it is essential that appropriate emotional and informational support is provided and accessible. </s><s n="s2.4;p92.151">Patients experiencing further recurrence and those requiring palliative care, may express an unpredictable variety of emotions ranging from relatively good adjustment to severe psychosocial morbidity. </s><s n="s3.4;p92.151">(49). </s><s n="s4.4;p92.151">It is therefore important that individual needs can be identified and the appropriate services provided as and when necessary. </s></p><p n="p93.151"><s n="s1.2;p93.151">Even though the majority of women adjust well, some survivors may also continue to experience psychological morbidity after treatment ends. </s><s n="s2.2;p93.151">Studies suggest that younger pre-menopausal women are especially vulnerable to depression and anxiety compared to their older counterparts and therefore exhibit greater psychosocial and information needs (50). </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">8. DISCUSSION</head><p n="p94.151"><s n="s1.2;p94.151">Breast cancer has been shown to be a significant cause of morbidity and mortality which affects thousands of women every year. </s><s n="s2.2;p94.151">The ability to understand this disease and initiate further investigation when necessary is therefore important quality for any clinician. </s></p><p n="p95.151"><s n="s1.4;p95.151">When investigating breast cancer it is important to be aware of the normal physiological changes which occur during pregnancy and menstruation in response to the changing hormone levels. </s><s n="s2.4;p95.151">Breast examination should therefore be carried out in the first half of the menstrual cycle in pre-menopausal women whenever possible. </s><s n="s3.4;p95.151">In post-menopausal women, abnormalities may also arise due to the changing composition of the breast tissue. </s><s n="s4.4;p95.151">The importance of understanding the breast anatomy was also highlighted due to frequency with which metastatic disease occurs in breast cancer, particular to the axillary region. </s></p><p n="p96.151"><s n="s1.4;p96.151">Various risk factors for breast cancer pathogenesis were described including the established correlations with age, gender and family history. </s><s n="s2.4;p96.151">The effects of extended exposure to unopposed oestrogen were also considered along with evidence suggesting HRT and the OCP have possible harmful effects. </s><s n="s3.4;p96.151">Furthermore, obesity may in future prove to be an important factor as a result of the oestrogen production associated with adipose cells. </s><s n="s4.4;p96.151">Additional risk factors were such as smoking, alcohol and breast feeding were also addressed and although it may be important to consider these factors during the clinical assessment, the aetiological mechanisms by which these factors influence breast cancer are still not fully understood. </s></p><p n="p97.151"><s n="s1.5;p97.151">The majority of breast adenocarcinomas arise from ductal epithelium. </s><s n="s2.5;p97.151">In situ carcinomas such as DCIS usually present as small palpable masses in women of all ages and nipple involvement may also be an associated complaint. </s><s n="s3.5;p97.151">Alternatively, LCIS frequently arises in pre-menopausal women in the absence of a detectable mass. </s><s n="s4.5;p97.151">Invasive cancers usually present with additional signs such as skin tethering, although this is dependent upon the tumour composition. </s><s n="s5.5;p97.151">IDC is typically unifocal and accounts for the majority of invasive cancers in both pre- and post-menopausal women, although the more aggressive invasive lobular carcinomas still represent about 10% of infiltrating cancers. </s></p><p n="p98.151"><s n="s1.2;p98.151">Since the NHSBSP was introduced to target breast cancer in older women, it has had a considerable impact upon the incidence rates and rates of survival; however it is not without its limitations. </s><s n="s2.2;p98.151">Studies indicated that adverse psychological effects may arise without proper support services, and an appropriate screening programme has yet to be developed for those at risk of early onset breast cancer. </s></p><p n="p99.151"><s n="s1.3;p99.151">The use of the triple assessment was also discussed along with additional investigations, which have been introduced as moves are made towards tumour specific treatments. </s><s n="s2.3;p99.151">At present mammography remains the cornerstone of screening, although technologies such as ultrasonography and MRI have an increasingly defined role in non-invasive diagnosis. </s><s n="s3.3;p99.151">The promising research supporting the use of MRI for screening was also examined and hopefully this will provide a method for assessing younger high-risk populations in the future. </s></p><p n="p100.151"><s n="s1.3;p100.151">The major surgical techniques currently used for management of breast cancer have in essence changed very little for many years, however advances in imaging and the introduction of novel techniques such as sentinel node lymphadectomy aim to improve the precision of these techniques. </s><s n="s2.3;p100.151">Although the ultimate goal of treatment remains improved survival, an increasing emphasis is now put on less morbid treatments and improved quality of life. </s><s n="s3.3;p100.151">These advances will hopefully allow less invasive procedures to be carried out, helping to minimise the physical and psychological impact of surgery. </s></p><p n="p101.151"><s n="s1.1;p101.151">In addition, the introduction of herceptin and advances towards other biological response modifiers promises to provide further tumour-specific therapies which may prove especially valuable against metastatic disease. </s></p><p n="p102.151"><s n="s1.2;p102.151">Despite the use of various prognostic measures, the ability to accurately determine the prognosis of individual patients remains difficult. </s><s n="s2.2;p102.151">However as further research is carried out, a greater understanding of the types of support particular patients require is being obtained and if appropriate support programmes are subsequently introduced, then this arguably improves the outlook for individuals whatever the prognosis. </s></p><p n="p103.151"><s n="s1.2;p103.151">In the future, prevention is expected to remain a major focus, particularly in women at high risk of developing breast cancer because of mutations in susceptibility genes. </s><s n="s2.2;p103.151">Current research is also focusing upon the possible use of mammary ductoscopy for screening and diagnosis, and the development of immunotherapy treatments and breast cancer vaccines. </s></p><p n="p104.151"><s n="s1.4;p104.151">Mammary ductoscopy (MD) is an emerging technique that allows direct visualisation of the mammary duct system. </s><s n="s2.4;p104.151">Using a sub-millimetre fibreoptic micro-endoscope inserted through the ductal opening on the nipple surface, it is possible to obtain video images as well as ductal washings for cytological analysis. </s><s n="s3.4;p104.151">There is a growing body of evidence that MD may have a role in the investigation of women with pathological nipple discharge, the guiding of breast conserving surgery and the screening of high risk women. </s><s n="s4.4;p104.151">Although research is required to confirm these potential applications and the feasibility of its use in the outpatient setting under local anaesthesia, the addition of molecular and genetic analysis of cells obtained by MD and the emergence of newer generations of microendoscopes are likely to enhance the use of this technique (51). </s></p><p n="p105.151"><s n="s1.3;p105.151">As result of the significant advances in biotechnology and immunology, research is also being carried out to investigate the possible use of vaccines to harness the power of the immune system in the fight against breast cancer. </s><s n="s2.3;p105.151">It is believed that cancer vaccines would have several therapeutic advantages over traditional breast cancer treatment therapies. </s><s n="s3.3;p105.151">For example, by targeting the anti-tumour immune response to critical tumour-specific antigens it would provide a therapy with exquisite specificity and minimal toxicity. </s></p><p n="p106.151"><s n="s1.2;p106.151">In addition, immune-mediated tumour destruction would occur by mechanisms distinct from those underlying the efficacy of chemotherapy and hormone therapy. </s><s n="s2.2;p106.151">Therefore immunotherapy would offer an approach to circumventing the intrinsic drug resistance that currently underlies therapeutic failure. </s></p><p n="p107.151"><s n="s1.3;p107.151">Finally, the phenomenon of immunologic memory also gives immunotherapy the potential to create a durable therapeutic effect that can be reactivated at the onset of disease relapse. </s><s n="s2.3;p107.151">The use of immunologic memory also underlies the potential future use of vaccines for the prevention of breast cancer. </s><s n="s3.3;p107.151">Early clinical trials have highlighted the promise of immunotherapy as an additional major therapeutic modality for breast cancer, with the potential for breast cancer prevention as well as treatment (52). </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">9. PATIENT CASE STUDIES</head><div2><head rend="underlined bold">9.1 Patient Case Study One</head><p n="p108.151"><s n="s1.1;p108.151">Hospital no. <name type="other"/> DOB: <name type="other"/> </s></p><p n="p109.151"><s n="s1.2;p109.151">Ms <name type="other"/> was a 38 year-old lady, from <name type="other"/> who presented at the <name type="other"/> hospital breast cancer clinic for a general pre-surgical assessment accompanied by a friend. </s><s n="s2.2;p109.151">She was due to undergo a right breast lumpectomy and complete axillary clearance the following day. </s></p><p n="p110.151"><s n="s1.3;p110.151">The patient initially presented to her GP four weeks ago, after finding a small lump in her right breast whilst moisturising, and she was subsequently referred to the breast clinic for an appointment the following week. </s><s n="s2.3;p110.151">Over the weekend prior to her appointment, she found a further, slightly smaller mass in the same breast. </s><s n="s3.3;p110.151">Although she found both lumps herself, she did not routinely examine her breasts. </s></p><p n="p111.151"><s n="s1.6;p111.151">At present she is otherwise fit and healthy with no other medical conditions. </s><s n="s2.6;p111.151">She has a two-year history of depression for which she under went treatment with Prozac and cognitive behavioural therapy (CBT). </s><s n="s3.6;p111.151">She finished her treatment approximately a year ago and did not wish to discuss this issue further. </s><s n="s4.6;p111.151">Her past medical history also included an operation in <name type="other"/>9 to repair a dislocated patella. </s><s n="s5.6;p111.151">She experience0d a bad reaction to the anaesthetic used during this procedure. </s><s n="s6.6;p111.151">She also delivered her twin sons six weeks early by caesarean section after developing pre-eclampsia. </s></p><p n="p112.151"><s n="s1.4;p112.151"><name type="other"/> has worked as a self-employed singer/musician for the last 18 years. </s><s n="s2.4;p112.151">She was divorced two and a half years ago, and currently she lives in a private house with her twin boys, aged six. </s><s n="s3.4;p112.151">One of her sons developed cerebral ataxia 18 months ago after contracting chickenpox. </s><s n="s4.4;p112.151">Although he has now recovered, apart from some minor learning difficulties, she acknowledged that this incident has placed her under considerable stress over the past year or so. </s></p><p n="p113.151"><s n="s1.4;p113.151">She has three brothers' currently alive, two of which live locally, although she has minimal contact with them. </s><s n="s2.4;p113.151">Her two other brothers both died following myocardial infarctions. </s><s n="s3.4;p113.151">As a result of her mother's suicide when she was five years old, her father primarily raised her, although he died of liver cancer when she was 17. </s><s n="s4.4;p113.151">She placed particular emphasis on the value of the close friendships she has maintained over the years, as she has no other family living in the area. </s></p><p n="p114.151"><s n="s1.8;p114.151">There was no history of breast or ovarian cancer in the family. </s><s n="s2.8;p114.151">She has never smoked and only drinks alcohol occasionally. </s><s n="s3.8;p114.151">Menarche took place at 15. </s><s n="s4.8;p114.151">She does however have a history of OCP use. </s><s n="s5.8;p114.151">For the last four years she has had an Implanon (etonogesterel-releasing) contraceptive implant in her left arm, although it was immediately removed following the recent cancer diagnosis. </s><s n="s6.8;p114.151">As a result she has not had a period for 4 years, and was particularly concerned about menstruating again. </s><s n="s7.8;p114.151">She also used the OCP for eight years prior to her pregnancy at the age of 31. </s><s n="s8.8;p114.151">She did not breast-feed her twins. </s></p><p n="p115.151"><s n="s1.3;p115.151"><name type="other"/> has no known allergies, apart from the previous complications she suffered with anaesthesia. </s><s n="s2.3;p115.151">She is not currently taking any medication. </s><s n="s3.3;p115.151">No further information was revealed during the systems review. </s></p><p n="p116.151"><s n="s1.4;p116.151">No abnormalities were detected during the general examination. </s><s n="s2.4;p116.151">A breast exam was also performed in the presence of a female house officer, which revealed two fixed lumps (appropriately 0.5cm and 2cm) in the right breast, although there was no evidence of tethering or other external signs (Figure 9.1). </s><s n="s3.4;p116.151">The left breast appeared normal. </s><s n="s4.4;p116.151">No masses were found in either axilla. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0047a-pic.013"><head rend="bold">Figure 9.1 Approximate size and position of the right breast lumps</head></figure><p n="p117.151"><s n="s1.3;p117.151">In addition to the lumpectomy and complete axillary clearance, <name type="other"/> had also decided to participate in a clinical trial at the <name type="other"/> Hospital, investigating the sensitivity of sentinel node biopsies (See dissertation). </s><s n="s2.3;p117.151">She therefore received an injection of radioactive dye into the tissue surrounding her breast lumps prior to surgery so that the sentinel nodes could be identified and examined, however all her axillary nodes were removed irrespective of the findings. </s><s n="s3.3;p117.151">Although the initial surgery only involved a lumpectomy and axillary clearance, she was also warned that reconstruction and possibly mastectomy would be required, should further tissue removal be required. </s></p><p n="p118.151"><s n="s1.3;p118.151">The initial surgery involving wide local excision and axillary node clearance with sentinel node biopsy of the right breast was carried out in mid October. </s><s n="s2.3;p118.151">The histology reports confirmed the presence of two firm lesions both measuring 11mm in diameter. </s><s n="s3.3;p118.151">The histological reports from these tumours are summarised below: </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p119.151"><s n="s1.4;p119.151"><hi rend="bold">Medial lesion</hi>: Invasive ductal carcinoma (within 2mm of the anterior margin and 5mm of the posterior margin). </s><s n="s2.4;p119.151">Grade II (T2, N3, M2). </s><s n="s3.4;p119.151">There was some associated DCIS which extended to within 1mm of the traumatised posterior margin and 5mm of the anterior and superior margins. </s><s n="s4.4;p119.151">All other margins were clear. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p120.151"><s n="s1.3;p120.151"><hi rend="bold">Lateral lesion</hi>: Invasive ductal carcinoma (within 2.5mm of the anterior margin and 5mm of the posterior margin). </s><s n="s2.3;p120.151">Grade III (T2, N3, M3). </s><s n="s3.3;p120.151">All other margins were clear. </s></p><p n="p121.151"><s n="s1.6;p121.151">Both tumours were oestrogen receptor positive and negative for HER 2 amplification. </s><s n="s2.6;p121.151">The NPI score was 4.22 indicating an intermediate level malignancy with a moderate chance of 'cure'. </s><s n="s3.6;p121.151">The pathologist noted that these lesions may have been two separate primaries, although the presence of DCIS in a section between the lesions indicated it was more likely to be one area of DCIS with multi focal invasive carcinomas. </s><s n="s4.6;p121.151">The whole tumour diameter was therefore in excess of 50mm. </s><s n="s5.6;p121.151">Both of the sentinel nodes were found to be benign, as were the nine other lymph nodes examined. </s><s n="s6.6;p121.151">A shaving taken from the inferio-medial cavity wall revealed an area of intermediate grade DCIS presence at the excision margin. </s></p><p n="p122.151"><s n="s1.4;p122.151">In light of the residual cells found in the cavity wall shaving, a right mastectomy was carried out in order to ensure total excision of the malignancy. </s><s n="s2.4;p122.151">The subsequent histology report stated that all margins exhibited at least 4mm clearance. </s><s n="s3.4;p122.151">At the MDT meeting held following the second operation, it was decided that <name type="other"/> would require chemotherapy followed by a course of Tamoxifen. </s><s n="s4.4;p122.151">Although radiotherapy was also discussed, it was proposed that it would have a limited role because of the full clearance margins obtained. <name type="other"/> was subsequently referred to an oncologist and scheduled for a follow up appointment in one year. </s></p><p n="p123.151"><s n="s1.1;p123.151">No further follow up contact was possible with Ms <name type="other"/>, there are however several psychosocial implications which should be considered in this case. </s></p><p n="p124.151"><s n="s1.5;p124.151">Firstly, as with most cases of breast cancer, the duration over which presentation, diagnosis and treatment occurred was particularly acute. </s><s n="s2.5;p124.151">Appropriate support must therefore be provided to allow her cope with the rapidly occurring changes in her emotions and physical appearance. </s><s n="s3.5;p124.151">This is particularly important in this case, given her history of depression and the stress resulting from her sons' recent illness. </s><s n="s4.5;p124.151">If she is willing to discuss her feelings further with a professional such as a specialist breast nurse, it may help her to develop appropriate coping strategies in order to avoid relapsing. </s><s n="s5.5;p124.151">It is also essential that she is encouraged to maintain her close friendships, as these would provide a further source of support during her recovery. </s></p><p n="p125.151"><s n="s1.2;p125.151">It is also possible that she may feel guilty for not examining her breasts more regularly, or for using oral contraceptive therapy for such a prolonged period, and therefore reassurance should be given. </s><s n="s2.2;p125.151">If requested a return referral to her psychiatrist should also be arranged. </s></p><p n="p126.151"><s n="s1.4;p126.151">In addition, it is important to consider the psychological effects a mastectomy would have on a young woman who earns a living by performing to an audience. </s><s n="s2.4;p126.151">Even if she receives a subsequent reconstruction, the experience may still have significant effects on her confidence and therefore ability to work. </s><s n="s3.4;p126.151">There are also the immediate financial implications given that she is a self-employed single mother. </s><s n="s4.4;p126.151">For example, there is the initial period of post-op recovery, and the subsequent time required for chemotherapy, along with its possible side effects. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined bold">9.2 Patient Case Study Two</head><p n="p127.151"><s n="s1.1;p127.151">Hospital no. <name type="other"/> DOB: <name type="other"/> </s></p><p n="p128.151"><s n="s1.2;p128.151">Ms <name type="other"/> was a 48 year-old lady, from <name type="other"/> who presented at the <name type="other"/> hospital breast cancer clinic for a pre-surgical assessment accompanied by her neighbour. </s><s n="s2.2;p128.151">She was due to undergo a complete left mastectomy and wide axillary clearance in three days time. </s></p><p n="p129.151"><s n="s1.8;p129.151"><name type="other"/> found the lump on her left breast whilst routinely examining her breasts, after her monthly menstrual period. </s><s n="s2.8;p129.151">Although the lump was noticed about a month ago, she only presented to her GP two weeks ago after returning from her annual holiday. </s><s n="s3.8;p129.151">She justified the delay by explaining that she "thought it would be anything but cancer". </s><s n="s4.8;p129.151">Despite the fact that the mass was large enough to see clearly, she has not experienced pain or any other associated symptoms. </s><s n="s5.8;p129.151">There were no other current or previous medical conditions reported, although she had an uncomplicated sterilisation eight years ago. </s><s n="s6.8;p129.151">Following the initial triple assessment, the ultrasound core biopsy confirmed the presence of an invasive lobular carcinoma. </s><s n="s7.8;p129.151">As a result, <name type="other"/> was advised to consider a complete left mastectomy due to the large size of the tumour (45mm) and the fact that lobular type lesions are often multifocal. </s><s n="s8.8;p129.151">She reported that she was initially upset and confused by the diagnosis, and unsure whether to continue with the mastectomy, however she agreed to the surgery following several discussions with a breast care nurse. </s></p><p n="p130.151"><s n="s1.6;p130.151"><name type="other"/> currently lives in a privately owned house that she shares with her 14 year-old son. </s><s n="s2.6;p130.151">He suffers from epilepsy and asthma, although neither is a significant problem at present. <name type="other"/> also has two older sons who live away from <name type="other"/>. </s><s n="s3.6;p130.151">She appeared to be especially grateful of the support she receives from her youngest, particularly as she works full time as a store auditor. </s><s n="s4.6;p130.151">Both her parents died relatively young (father 52, mother 66) due to cardiac problems and the rest of her family live in <name type="other"/>; however she receives support from her neighbour and other friends living in the area. </s><s n="s5.6;p130.151">She also has an active social life and enjoys dancing regularly. </s><s n="s6.6;p130.151">Following the operation she will be unable to drive for 3 weeks, and appreciated the fact that her closest friend would be so near to help her out. </s></p><p n="p131.151"><s n="s1.5;p131.151">There was no family history of breast or ovarian cancer. </s><s n="s2.5;p131.151">Her menarche occurred at the age of 14, she delivered her first child at 22 years of age and has subsequently breast-fed all her children. </s><s n="s3.5;p131.151">She has no known drug allergies and has never used the OCP. She is still having regular menstrual cycles. </s><s n="s4.5;p131.151">She has never smoked and only drinks moderate amounts when socialising. </s><s n="s5.5;p131.151">From this information there do not appear to be any significant risk factors which may have induced cancer development. </s></p><p n="p132.151"><s n="s1.3;p132.151">During the systems review she complained of a dry cough, occasional shooting pains in her left arm and recent palpitations, which she dismissed as stress related. </s><s n="s2.3;p132.151">She was otherwise healthy. </s><s n="s3.3;p132.151">She was prescribed clexane (enoxiparin) for use the night before the operation, in order to reduce the risk of DVT. </s></p><p n="p133.151"><s n="s1.4;p133.151">General examination and blood tests (FBC, urea, electrolytes, creatinine and INR) were both normal. </s><s n="s2.4;p133.151">The breast examination revealed a large area of tethering on the left breast when the arm was abducted. </s><s n="s3.4;p133.151">On palpation a large lump, approximately 4cm in diameter, was detected in this region (Figure 9.2). </s><s n="s4.4;p133.151">No masses were detectable in the right breast or in either axilla. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0047a-pic.014"><head rend="bold">Figure 9.2 Approximate size and position of the mass found in the left breast </head></figure><p n="p134.151"><s n="s1.7;p134.151">The surgery was successfully carried out and <name type="other"/> had an uneventful post-operative recovery. </s><s n="s2.7;p134.151">The histology results reported a grade III (T3, N3, M2) multifocal invasive lobular carcinoma which was ER+ and HER negative. </s><s n="s3.7;p134.151">The closest resection margin was 26mm (posterior). </s><s n="s4.7;p134.151">No axillary lymph node involvement, although one of the 13 nodes recovered from the breast tissue was positive. </s><s n="s5.7;p134.151">She was subsequently referred into the care of an oncologist in order to be consideration for chemotherapy and radiotherapy. </s><s n="s6.7;p134.151">Following any adjuvant therapy, <name type="other"/> will also be suitable for endocrine treatment due to the presence of oestrogen receptors. </s><s n="s7.7;p134.151">No further follow-up was possible. </s></p><p n="p135.151"><s n="s1.8;p135.151">During the interview, <name type="other"/> stated that she was "frightened" about what would happen exactly after the surgery. </s><s n="s2.8;p135.151">It was quite surprising to hear that these aspects of her care had not been discussed, especially given the uncertainly that she suffered when deciding whether to continue with her treatment. </s><s n="s3.8;p135.151">This therefore raises several important points regarding the support she has received. </s><s n="s4.8;p135.151">For example, the positive outcome from her initial contact with the breast nurse suggests that they had developed a good rapport. </s><s n="s5.8;p135.151">However, her recent comments indicated that she probably wasn't in a situation to approach the nurse, or medical team in general, when she desired. </s><s n="s6.8;p135.151">Although it is not known whether she failed to contact the team, or whether they had failed to provide satisfactory answers, it is clear a communication problem exists. </s><s n="s7.8;p135.151">To overcome this further effort must be made to improve access and ensure that patient concerns are addressed adequately. </s><s n="s8.8;p135.151">This could be achieved through simple measures such as supplying an out-of-hours contact number or by summarising information at the end of discussions, although in her case it may be more beneficial to encourage frequent communication with the nurse in order to build on their previous relationship. </s></p><p n="p136.151"><s n="s1.2;p136.151">Having the close support of a professional may also be desirable given her lack of family in local area, for there are likely to be personal issues which she would choose not to discuss with her son or friends, despite the care they are willing to provide. </s><s n="s2.2;p136.151">Even still it is fortunate that <name type="other"/> has a good social network of friends which are able to help with travelling and other day-to-day activities whilst she is recovering. </s></p><p n="p137.151"><s n="s1.5;p137.151">It would also be necessary to consider her home situation. </s><s n="s2.5;p137.151">It appears that her young son already provides her with a great deal of support and it is therefore possible that further pressure may be placed upon him especially if he feels obliged to assist in her care. </s><s n="s3.5;p137.151">This aspect should be addressed as it may have subsequent effects upon his physical, emotional and social well being. </s><s n="s4.5;p137.151">Although it may not be necessary to prepare specific arrangements such as the provision of social support or district nurse visits, it may if beneficial if at least the breast care nurses were to extend their offer of support to the son. </s><s n="s5.5;p137.151">At the very least, the impact of this diagnosis upon her son should be discussed with <name type="other"/>, in order to determine how she feels it may affect her son. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined bold">9.3 Patient Case Study Three</head><p n="p138.151"><s n="s1.1;p138.151">Hospital no. <name type="other"/> DOB: <name type="date"/> </s></p><p n="p139.151"><s n="s1.3;p139.151">Mrs <name type="other"/> was a pleasant 86 year-old lady, from <name type="other"/> who presented at the <name type="other"/> breast cancer clinic for a pre-surgical assessment with her daughter. </s><s n="s2.3;p139.151">She was due to undergo a right mastectomy with wide axillary node clearance in three days time. </s><s n="s3.3;p139.151">She had been admitted the previous week, however the operation was postponed when she was found to have atrial fibrillation. </s></p><p n="p140.151"><s n="s1.4;p140.151">She was initially referred to the clinic three weeks ago by her GP after reporting distortion of the right nipple to a nurse during a regular blood pressure check up. </s><s n="s2.4;p140.151">She had not experienced any pain, redness, discharge or swelling in association with the distortion. </s><s n="s3.4;p140.151">Although the complaint had been noticed whilst showering, she didn't examine her breasts regularly. </s><s n="s4.4;p140.151">In addition she reported that she had felt like her balance was going over the past two weeks, although she wasn't experiencing any dizziness. </s></p><p n="p141.151"><s n="s1.3;p141.151">At present she also suffers from a hiatus hernia which causes occasional chest pain and nausea, these symptoms are controlled with gaviscon. </s><s n="s2.3;p141.151">She also reported frequent ankle swelling which is exacerbated by warm weather. </s><s n="s3.3;p141.151">She also experiences photosensitivity of the skin, presumably a side effect of her current drug regime which includes amiodarone. </s></p><p n="p142.151"><s n="s1.4;p142.151">Her previous medical history included a stroke 10 years ago, which resulted in temporary right-sided paralysis and loss of the ability to swallow. </s><s n="s2.4;p142.151">Fortunately she rapidly recovered and successfully underwent speech therapy allowing her to regain her speech, which is now clear and fluent. </s><s n="s3.4;p142.151">Some still experiences some sensory loss in the right arm and has difficulty initiating abduction of the arm. </s><s n="s4.4;p142.151">Prior to the stroke she also reported occasional palpitations, but these have not been experienced since. </s></p><p n="p143.151"><s n="s1.4;p143.151">She currently lives alone in her own house and gets around fine, using the aid of a walking stick when necessary. </s><s n="s2.4;p143.151">Her fitness level is reported to be good as she can easily walk for half an hour before becoming breathless. </s><s n="s3.4;p143.151">She also receives a lot of support from her daughter and three sons who live locally. </s><s n="s4.4;p143.151">Before retiring at the age of 60, she worked in a paper factory for many years. </s></p><p n="p144.151"><s n="s1.2;p144.151">Her sister died of breast carcinoma at the age of 60, but there is no further family history of the disease. </s><s n="s2.2;p144.151">Her mother died of cardiac problems aged 59 following rheumatic fever, whilst her father died at 77 of diabetes complications. </s></p><p n="p145.151"><s n="s1.4;p145.151">With regard to other specific risk factors, she has never used oral contraceptives, she underwent menarche at the age of 16 and she gave birth to her first child at 30. </s><s n="s2.4;p145.151">All her children were breast-fed. </s><s n="s3.4;p145.151">Her menopause occurred at the age of 52 and she has never used HRT. She has not smoked for over fifty years and reported drinking only the occasional glass of red wine. </s><s n="s4.4;p145.151">There were no known drug or food allergies reported. </s></p><list type="simple"><head>Current medication included:</head><item>Amiodarone 200mg</item><item>Digoxin 125mg</item><item>Lansoprazole 30mg </item><item>Co-amilofruse (2.5/20) </item><item>Aspirin 75mg </item></list><p n="p146.151"><s n="s1.1;p146.151">During a thorough systems review she reported that she was otherwise in good health at the moment, apart from occasional constipation and the limitations she experiences when trying to abduct her right arm. </s></p><p n="p147.151"><s n="s1.4;p147.151">On general examination, her heart rate was slightly irregular, there was a carotid bruit, pitting oedema at the ankles and lateral displacement of the apex beat. </s><s n="s2.4;p147.151">ECG results were not available. </s><s n="s3.4;p147.151">The breast examination revealed obvious skin puckering and distortion of the right nipple. </s><s n="s4.4;p147.151">On palpation a small fixed mass was detected, approximately 1.5cm in size (Figure 9.3). </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0047a-pic.015"><head rend="bold">Figure 9.3 Approximate position of right breast lump</head></figure><p n="p148.151"><s n="s1.9;p148.151"><name type="other"/> had an uneventful post operative recovery and was released home after 5 days. </s><s n="s2.9;p148.151">The histology results reported a grade II (T2, N2/3, M1) invasive ductal carcinoma measuring 22mm in diameter. </s><s n="s3.9;p148.151">The closest resection margin was 28mm (Posterior). </s><s n="s4.9;p148.151">The tumour was moderately ER positive and negative for HER2 amplification. </s><s n="s5.9;p148.151">Her NPI score was 3.44 indicating a moderate chance of cure. </s><s n="s6.9;p148.151">There was no evidence of Paget's disease despite the close proximity to the nipple. </s><s n="s7.9;p148.151">There was no lymph node involvement. </s><s n="s8.9;p148.151">At the MDT meeting held following her surgery, it was decided that given her age she would be unsuitable for chemotherapy or radiotherapy. </s><s n="s9.9;p148.151">Instead it was agreed that tamoxifen prescribed over the next five years would be the most appropriate course of action. </s></p><p n="p149.151"><s n="s1.3;p149.151">Following the surgery, <name type="other"/> was subsequently discharged back into the care of her GP and therefore follow-up was not possible. </s><s n="s2.3;p149.151">It may be necessary for the GP to arrange a review of her medication, as she would benefit from being transferred to an anti-arrhythmic which didn't cause photosensitivity. </s><s n="s3.3;p149.151">Arrangements will also have to be made for the provision of her tamoxifen prescriptions, although the relative lack of side effects will be extremely valuable in her case. </s></p><p n="p150.151"><s n="s1.5;p150.151">From a social perspective <name type="other"/> appeared to be happy with fact that she was still able to cope for herself at home albeit with occasional assistance from her children. </s><s n="s2.5;p150.151">She mentioned that she was still able to visit the local store and even caught the bus to the GP unattended when necessary. </s><s n="s3.5;p150.151">The only problem with day-to-day living that came to light was her limited ability to abduct the right arm, and fortunately no further disability arose as a result of the axillary surgery. </s><s n="s4.5;p150.151">With this in consideration there did not appear to be any further agency involvement which would have benefited Mrs <name type="other"/> at present. </s><s n="s5.5;p150.151">In addition the diagnosis itself did not appear to have a significant impact upon her, and she seemed to except the fact that the tamoxifen wouldn't necessarily cure her cancer, merely delay its progression. </s></p><p n="p151.151"><s n="s1.2;p151.151">Although there are relatively few psychosocial issues which need to be addressed at present, it is important to consider that further problems may arise in future, particularly if her heart failure progresses or she develops breast metastases or another stroke. </s><s n="s2.2;p151.151">In that situation, her loss of mobility and increasing dependence upon others may have a substantial effect upon her especially given that she has been independent for such a long period, and clearly cherishes that freedom. </s></p></div2></div1></body><back><div1 type="bibliography"><head rend="underlined bold">10. REFERENCES</head><p>1) Cancer. Office of National Statistics. <seg type="URL" n="www.statistics.gov.uk"/>. Published 29th July 2004</p><p>2) Breast cancer care. <seg type="URL" n="www.breastcancercare.org.uk"/>. Published 4th November 2004 </p><p>3) BBC health website. <seg type="URL" n="www.bbc.co.uk/health/womens_health/issues_breastcancer"/>. Accessed 11th December 2004 </p><p>4) Kierszenbaum, A.L. Histology and cell biology - An introduction to pathology. USA. Mosby. 2002: 606-607</p><p>5) Walker, R.A. Breast. In: General and systemic pathology (3rd edition) ed. Underwood, J. London. Churchill Livingstone. 2003: 469-494</p><p>6) Moore, K. and Dalley, A. Clinically orientated anatomy (14th edition). USA. Lippencott, Williams and Wilkins. 2002: 72-76 </p><p>7) Breast cancer org. <seg type="URL" n="www.breastcancer.org/breast_anatomy.html"/>. Accessed 27th August 2004</p><p>8) Henderson, C. Breast cancer. In: The Merck manual (17th edition) eds. Beers, M. and Berkow, R. USA. 1999: 1974-1982</p><p>9) Longo, D. Breast cancer. In: Harrison's manual of medicine (15th edition) eds. Braunwald, E., Fauci, S., Kasper, D., et al. USA. McGraw Hill publishing. 2002: 286-290</p><p>10) Cameron, D. and Smyth, J. Oncology. In: Davidson's Medicine - Principles and practice (19th edition) eds. Haslett, C., Chilvers, E., Boon, N. and Colledge, N. London. Churchill Livingstone. 2002: 213-225</p><p>11) Charlotte, E. and Grayson, M. Breast cancer in young women. <seg type="URL" n="www.WebMD.com"/>. Published February 2004</p><p>12) Zografos, G., Panou, M. and Panou N. Common risk factors of breast and ovarian cancer: recent view. Int J Gynecol Cancer. 2004: 14(5):721-40</p><p>13) Breast cancer. E-medicine. <seg type="URL" n="www.emedicine.com/med/topic2808.htm"/>. Accessed 23rd June 2004</p><p>14) Staren, E., and Omer, S.. Hormone replacement therapy in postmenopausal women. Am J Surg. 2004: 188(2): 136-49. Review </p><p>15) Korde, L., Calzone, K. and Zujewski, J. Assessing breast cancer risk: genetic factors are not the whole story. Postgrad Med. 2004: 116(4): 6-8, 11-4, 19-20</p><p>16) Detailed guide to breast cancer. American Cancer Society - Cancer reference information. <seg type="URL" n="www.cancer.org"/>. Accessed 11th December 2004</p><p>17) Miller, A., To, T., Baines, C. and Wall, C. Canadian national breast screening study-2: 13-year results of a randomized trial in women aged 50-59 years. Journal of the National Cancer Institute. 2000: 92(18): 1490-1499</p><p>18) Ksters, J. and Gtzsche, P. Regular self-examination or clinical examination for early detection of breast cancer (Cochrane Review - abstract). The Cochrane database of systematic reviews. 2003; Issue 2. </p><p>19) Cancer screening programmes - When was the NHS Breast Screening Programme set up? <seg type="URL" n="www.cancerscreening.nhs.uk/breastscreen"/>. Accessed 11th December 2004 </p><p>20) Shapiro, S., Venet, W., Strax, P., Venet, L. and Roeser, R. Ten- to fourteen-year effect of screening on breast cancer mortality (Abstract). Journal of the National Cancer institute. 1982: 69(2): 349-55</p><p>21) Tabar, L., Vitak, B., Chen, H. et al. The Swedish Two-County Trial twenty years later - Updated mortality results and new insights from long-term follow-up (Abstract). Radiol Clin North Am. 2000: 38(4): 625-51</p><p>22) Lannin, D., Harris, R., Swanson, F., Edwards, M., Swanson, M. and Pories, W. Difficulties in diagnosis of carcinoma of the breast in patients less than fifty years of age. Surg Gynecol Obstet. 1993: 177(5): 457-62</p><p>23) Given-Wilson, R. Screening for breast cancer. In: Medical Therapy of Breast Cancer. eds. Rayter, Z. and Mansi, J. Cambridge University Press. 2003: 103-125</p><p>24) Given-Wilson, R. Screening process. In: Medical Therapy of Breast Cancer. eds. Rayter, Z. and Mansi, J. Cambridge University Press. 2003: 113</p><p>25) Blanks, S., Moss, M., McGahan, C., Quinn, M. and Babb, P. Effect of NHS breast screening programme on mortality from breast cancer in England and Wales, 1990-8: comparison of observed with predicted mortality. BMJ. 2000: 321: 665 - 669</p><p>26) Breast cancer. Office of National Statistics. <seg type="URL" n="www.statistics.gov.uk"/>. Published 31st October 2003</p><p>27) Asghari, A. and Nicholas, M. Pain during mammography: the role of coping strategies. Pain. 2004: 108(1-2):170-9</p><p>28) Cockburn, J., Staples, M., Hurley, S. and De Luise, T. Psychological consequences of screening mammography. J Med Screen. 1994: 1: 7-12</p><p>29) Kelsey, S.M., Gallagher, C.J. and Tate, T. Medical Oncology including haematological malignancy. In: Clinical Medicine (5th edition) ed. Kumar, P. and Clark, M. London. WB Saunders. 2002: 503-505 </p><p>30) Giuliano, A. Carcinoma of the female breast. In Current medical diagnosis and treatment (43rd edition) eds. Tierney, L, McPhee, S. and Papadakis, M. London. McGraw-Hill publishing. 2004: 672-692</p><p>31) Ultrasound Images of Breast Conditions. Imaginis: The breast health resource. <seg type="URL" n="http://imaginis.com/breasthealth/ultrasound_images.asp"/>. Accessed 16th January 2005</p><p>32) Edelman, R. The psychological costs of screening. In: Psychosocial aspects of the health care process. England. Prentice Hall. 2000: 46-50</p><p>33) Early Breast Cancer Trialists' Collaborative Group. Tamoxifen for early breast cancer (Cochrane Review - abstract). The Cochrane database of systematic reviews. 2001: Issue 1</p><p>34) Sex hormones and hormone antagonists in malignant disease. British National Formulary (48th edition). British Medical Association. 2004: 445-452 </p><p>35) Slamon, D., Godolphin, W., Jones, L., et al. Studies of the HER-2/neu proto-oncogene in human breast and ovarian cancer. Science. 1989; 244:707-712</p><p>36) Sjogren, S., Inganas, M., Lindgren, A., et al. Prognostic and predictive value of c-erbB-2 over-expression in primary breast cancer, alone and in combination with other prognostic markers. Journal of Clinical Oncology. 1998; 16:462-469</p><p>37) Emens, L. and Davidson, N. Trastuzumab in breast cancer (Abstract). Oncology (Huntington). 2004: 18(9): 1117-28</p><p>38) CA 15 - 3. <seg type="URL" n="www.thedoctorslounge.net"/>. Accessed 29th December 2004 </p><p>39) Brekelmans, C., Seynaeve, C., Bartels, C., et al. Effectiveness of breast cancer surveillance in BRCA1/2 gene mutation carriers and women with high familial risk. Journal of Clinical Oncology. 2001: 19: 924-930</p><p>40) Kriege, M., Brekelmans, C., Boetes, C., et al. Efficacy of magnetic resonance imaging and mammography for breast cancer screening in women with a familial or genetic predisposition. Obstet Gynecol Surv. 2005: 60(2): 107-109</p><p>41) Warner, E., Plewes, D., Hill K., et al. Surveillance of BRCA1 and BRCA2 mutation carriers with magnetic resonance imaging, ultrasound, mammography, and clinical breast examination. JAMA. 2004; 292:1317-1325 </p><p>42) Bluemke, D., Gatsonis, C., Chen, M., et al. Magnetic resonance imaging of the breast prior to biopsy. JAMA. 2004; 292:2735-2742</p><p>43) Magnetic Resonance Breast Imaging. Imaginis: The breast health resource. <seg type="URL" n="http://imaginis.com/breasthealth/mri.asp"/>. Accessed 16th January 2005</p><p>44) Zurrida, S., Galimberti, V., Gibelli, B. et al. Timing of breast cancer surgery in relation to the menstrual cycle: an update of developments. Critical Reviews in Oncology and Hematology. 2001: 38(3): 223-30 </p><p>45) Sentinel node biopsy. <seg type="URL" n="www.fleshandbones.com/imagebank"/>. Accessed 11th December 2004 </p><p>46) Edelman, R. The impact of chronic illness. In: Psychosocial aspects of the health care process. England. Prentice Hall. 2000: 171</p><p>47) Bonadonna, G., Moliterni, A., Zambetti, M., et al. 30 years' follow up of randomised studies of adjuvant CMF in operable breast cancer: cohort study. BMJ. 2005: 330: 217</p><p>48) Kattan, M., Giri, D., Panageas, K., et al. A tool for predicting breast carcinoma mortality in women who do not receive adjuvant therapy. <hi rend="italic">Cancer</hi>. 2004; 101:2509-15</p><p>49) Oh, S., Heflin, L., Meyerowitz, B., Desmond, K., Rowland, J. and Ganz, P. Quality of life of breast cancer survivors after a recurrence - a follow-up study. Breast Cancer Research and Treatment. 2004. 87(1): 45-57</p><p>50) Thewes, B., Butow, P., Girgis, A. and Pendlebury, S. The psychosocial needs of breast cancer survivors - a qualitative study of the shared and unique needs of younger versus older survivors. Psychooncology. 2004: 13(3): 177-89</p><p>51) Mokbel, K. and Elkak, A. The evolving role of mammary ductoscopy (Abstract). Curr Med Res Opin. 2002: 18(1): 30-2</p><p>52) Emens, L. and Jaffee, E. Toward a breast cancer vaccine: work in progress (Abstract). Oncology (Huntington). 2003: 17(9): 1200-11; discussion 1214, 1217-8. </p></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
