<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_0051a" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Flat Screen Display Technologies</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">The document has a title page which contains:
document title
title part
abstract</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">2</p><p n="date">2004-12</p><p n="module title">Physics Essay</p><p n="module code">PX221</p><p n="genre family">Explanation</p><p n="discipline">Physics</p><p n="disciplinary group">PS</p><p n="grade">D</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">3625</p><p n="number of s-units">156</p><p n="number of p">54</p><p n="number of tables">0</p><p n="number of figures">5</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">20</p><p n="number of lists">0</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">2</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">23.2</p><p n="average s-units per p">2.9</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">m</p><p n="year of birth">1984</p><p n="first language">English</p><p n="education">UKA</p><p n="course">Physics</p><p n="student ID">0051</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><docTitle><titlePart rend="bold">Flat Screen Display Technologies</titlePart></docTitle><titlePart>By <name type="student name"/><name type="student ID"/></titlePart></titlePage><div1 type="abstract"><head rend="bold">Abstract</head><p>In this report the inner workings of flat screen displays are explained and the advantages of such displays over the current market leading Cathode Ray Tube (CRT) screens are considered. The origins and principles of liquid crystal technology - one of the main areas of flat screen technology - are discussed with particular reference to the structural manipulation that such technology is based upon. The physical principles of the polarization of light and birefringence are outlined along with their uses in flat screen displays.</p></div1></front><body><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">1. Introduction</head><p n="p1.54"><s n="s1.5;p1.54">One of the main areas of technological advancement in the last thirty years has been in the area of flat screen displays. </s><s n="s2.5;p1.54">From microwaves to mobile phones and calculators to clocks, flat screens are becoming somewhat ubiquitous in society. </s><s n="s3.5;p1.54">In a world where mobility is now equally as important as quality, flat screens have made the step from industry implementations to a recreational consumer market - from the board room to the living room. </s><s n="s4.5;p1.54">Now flat screens are second only to the traditional Cathode Ray Tube (CRT) displays in the television market. </s><s n="s5.5;p1.54">Liquid crystal displays account for over 80% of the current varieties of flat screens available and so I believe it is appropriate to dedicate this report to this fundamental area of flat screen technology: the advantages, the mechanisms and the physics behind the flat screen phenomenon. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">2. Advantages</head><p n="p2.54"><s n="s1.2;p2.54">There is an ever-growing list of advantages for having a flat screen television as opposed to the conventional CRT displays. </s><s n="s2.2;p2.54">As the list grows and the price of the technology falls, this relatively new technology becomes more and more attractive. </s></p><p n="p3.54"><s n="s1.4;p3.54">The main advantage of flat screens over the standard CRT displays is mobility. </s><s n="s2.4;p3.54">CRT displays involve the use of a large electron gun situated at the read of the set which fires electrons at certain points on the phosphor-coated screen. </s><s n="s3.4;p3.54">This causes the phosphor to glow and hence light appear in that area of the screen. </s><s n="s4.4;p3.54">The colour of the particular area of phosphor that the electron is fired at determines the colour of the resultant light on the screen. </s></p><p n="p4.54"><s n="s1.4;p4.54">An LCD involves a more simplistic setup with a thin layer of liquid crystals encased between two glass plates. </s><s n="s2.4;p4.54">Behind this there is either a small backlight or alternatively a mirror to provide light for the screen to make use of to convey images. </s><s n="s3.4;p4.54">This means that the thickness of such LCD's is small enough that they are feasible for applications of any size and scale. </s><s n="s4.4;p4.54">It is for this reason that they are now widespread in small electrical devices where size is paramount. </s></p><p n="p5.54"><s n="s1.4;p5.54">Another key benefit of flat screens is that the power consumption is considerably less than that of CRT's. </s><s n="s2.4;p5.54">As mentioned above, the CRT contains an electron gun which not only takes up considerable space in the unit, but also requires a large amount of power. </s><s n="s3.4;p5.54">The two main consumers of power in an LCD are an induced electric field across the liquid crystals, which is a result of a small change in voltage and, in televisions, a backlight that is required to compensate for light intensity lost during polarization. </s><s n="s4.4;p5.54">Consequently the power usage in an LCD is considerably less. </s></p><p n="p6.54"><s n="s1.3;p6.54">Currently the only drawback of flat screen displays is the cost. </s><s n="s2.3;p6.54">However as production is increased for the ever-expanding market, the price of construction falls and so flat panel displays seem more attractive. </s><s n="s3.3;p6.54">To understand the benefits of flat screens the key principles behind the technology must be investigated. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">3. Liquid Crystal Principles</head><div2><head rend="bold">3.1 The Liquid Crystal Phase</head><p n="p7.54"><s n="s1.4;p7.54">In 1898 Friedrich Reinitzer, a botanist in Austria, was investigating cholesterol in plants when he noticed an anomaly. </s><s n="s2.4;p7.54">He was melting Cholesteryl Benzoate and found that it changed from a solid to an opaque liquid and upon further heating underwent another change and became a clear liquid. </s><s n="s3.4;p7.54">He had inadvertently discovered a fourth state of matter. </s><s n="s4.4;p7.54">This phenomenon was reported to Otto Lehmann, a German physicist, who later became an expert in this field and coined the term "liquid crystal". </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0051a-pic.001"><head rend="bold">Figure 1 - Molecular structure of a solid, liquid crystal and liquid respectively[1]</head></figure><p n="p8.54"><s n="s1.5;p8.54">This <hi rend="italic">liquid crystal phase</hi> exhibits features of both a solid and a liquid (figure 1). </s><s n="s2.5;p8.54">A solid exhibits both positional and orientational order, with the molecular positions fixed in a planar nature. </s><s n="s3.5;p8.54">A liquid exhibits no such order and the molecules are free to slide past one-another. </s><s n="s4.5;p8.54">The rod-like molecules (or <hi rend="italic">mesogens</hi> when referring to liquid crystals) in a liquid crystal do not have a rigid structure but they do have some orientational order. </s><s n="s5.5;p8.54">The rod-like mesogens are generally aligned along a common axis which is denoted by the director of the liquid crystal. </s></p><p n="p9.54"><s n="s1.1;p9.54">The degree of alignment can be defined by an order parameter, <hi rend="italic">S</hi>, a function of temperature, <hi rend="italic">T</hi>, which is given by: </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p10.54"><s n="s1.1;p10.54"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0051a-form.001"/> (Equation 1)<hi rend="sup">[2]</hi> </s></p><p n="p11.54"><s n="s1.1;p11.54">where θ is the angle by which the long axis deviates from the director and <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0051a-form.002"/> is the unit vector in the direction of the director (figure 2). </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0051a-pic.002"><head><hi rend="bold">Figure 2 -</hi> <hi rend="bold">Director Alignment[2]</hi></head></figure><p n="p12.54"><s n="s1.3;p12.54">For a solid <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0051a-form.003"/> as the temperature drops and the material exhibits features of a solid. </s><s n="s2.3;p12.54">Conversely <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0051a-form.004"/> as the temperature is increased and the material reverts to a liquid form. </s><s n="s3.3;p12.54">The order parameter for liquid crystals normally lies in the range <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0051a-form.005"/><hi rend="sup">[2]</hi>. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">3.2 Mesophases</head><p n="p13.54"><s n="s1.3;p13.54">The liquid crystal phase can be further characterised into <hi rend="italic">mesophases</hi>. </s><s n="s2.3;p13.54">These are sub-phases that exhibit different qualities depending upon which mesophase they are in. </s><s n="s3.3;p13.54">There are three mesophases: nematic, smetic and cholesteric. </s></p><p n="p14.54"><s n="s1.2;p14.54">The nematic phase exhibits basic features of a liquid crystal where there is no positional order and a rough orientational order as the mesogens align along the director. </s><s n="s2.2;p14.54">It is the lowest temperature band in which a substance is said to be in the liquid crystal phase. </s></p><p n="p15.54"><s n="s1.3;p15.54">Upon further heating the liquid crystal makes the transition into the smetic phase. </s><s n="s2.3;p15.54">The mesogens begin to form a planar structure and so now have both positional and orientational order. </s><s n="s3.3;p15.54">Motion is restricted to within these planes but the planes themselves are free to move past each other given their parallels to the liquid phase. </s></p><p n="p16.54"><s n="s1.3;p16.54">Finally they move into the cholesteric phase. </s><s n="s2.3;p16.54">Also known as the chiral nematic phase, the structure is more complex whereby the director rotates by a small angle when moving from plane to plane. </s><s n="s3.3;p16.54">This results in a helix effect when considering the crystal alignment as a function of each planar director. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0051a-pic.003"><head rend="bold">Figure 3 - Chiral nematic liquid crystal having rotated through 180° across a distance p/2[2]</head></figure><p n="p17.54"><s n="s1.3;p17.54">Figure 3 above shows a chiral nematic liquid crystal. </s><s n="s2.3;p17.54">These are the type of liquid crystal commonly used in LCD's. </s><s n="s3.3;p17.54">The structure can be described as a collection of planes of nematic mesogens where if each plane is taken in isolation it can be considered to be a nematic with a degree of rotation when moving from one plane to the next. </s></p><p n="p18.54"><s n="s1.3;p18.54">The pitch, <hi rend="italic">p</hi>, is defined as the distance it takes for the director to rotate one full turn in the helix <hi rend="sup">[2]</hi>. </s><s n="s2.3;p18.54">This pitch is prone to change since the gradual change in director orientation between layers is a function of temperature. </s><s n="s3.3;p18.54">Therefore an increase in temperature will cause a larger change in the director orientation between layers and so the pitch will decrease. </s></p><p n="p19.54"><s n="s1.5;p19.54">In an LCD the thickness of the liquid crystal between the glass plates is equal to one quarter of the pitch. </s><s n="s2.5;p19.54">This results in a rotation of the director by 90°. </s><s n="s3.5;p19.54">By adding polarizers both in front and behind this liquid crystal layer, the light passing through the structure is restricted - only a certain component of the light can pass through both polarizers if it twists with the director as it passes between planes. </s><s n="s4.5;p19.54">It is this restriction of light entering the liquid crystal that is the key to how LCD's operate. </s><s n="s5.5;p19.54">In order to understand this selective transmission and 'twisting' of light, a more in depth explanation of this light manipulation is provided in the following section. </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">4. Light Manipulation</head><p n="p20.54"><s n="s1.1;p20.54">Before understanding how specific properties of light are utilised in LCD's, ideas regarding the polarization and manipulation of light must be outlined. </s></p><div2><head rend="bold">4.1 Polarization</head><p n="p21.54"><s n="s1.2;p21.54">A polarizer is a material that allows only light with a specific angle of vibration to pass through. </s><s n="s2.2;p21.54">The direction of fluctuation passed by the polarizer is called the 'easy' axis <hi rend="sup">[2]</hi>. </s></p><p n="p22.54"><s n="s1.6;p22.54">A visual representation of these light fluctuations can be obtained by considering the light as a plane wave. </s><s n="s2.6;p22.54">The magnetic field vector is perpendicular to the electric field vector and the plane in which these vectors lie is perpendicular to the direction of propagation of the wave. </s><s n="s3.6;p22.54">Since this plane containing the two vectors is two dimensional, the electric field vector can be demonstrated as two orthogonal components: <hi rend="italic">x</hi> and <hi rend="italic">y</hi> in this plane. </s><s n="s4.6;p22.54">A 'snapshot' of the electric field can be taken by considering the resultant vector of these two components as the light wave passes through the plane. </s><s n="s5.6;p22.54">For a <hi rend="italic">simple harmonic wave</hi>, where the amplitude of the electric vector varies in a sinusoidal manner, the two components have exactly the same frequency <hi rend="sup">[3]</hi>. </s><s n="s6.6;p22.54">The light wave can therefore be considered as a function of the electric field vector (the magnetic field vector essentially stays the same and so can be ignored). </s></p><p n="p23.54"><s n="s1.2;p23.54">The two components of the electric field vector may not necessarily have the same amplitude and phase at any given time. </s><s n="s2.2;p23.54">This means that the resultant vector traces out different shapes as the plane wave passes through the plane, depending upon the combination of the magnitudes of these contributory components. </s></p><p n="p24.54"><s n="s1.4;p24.54">A good analogy for the polarization of such light is that of a rope held at both ends being oscillated. </s><s n="s2.4;p24.54">If it is unrestricted, the rope is free to oscillate horizontally, vertically and at all angles in-between. </s><s n="s3.4;p24.54">However, if the rope passes through a picket fence then the direction of oscillation is limited to the plane parallel to the shape of the aperture in the fence. </s><s n="s4.4;p24.54">This is the effect of polarizing white light which oscillates in all directions to linearly polarized light which only oscillates in one plane. </s></p><p n="p25.54"><s n="s1.5;p25.54">A visualisation of such <hi rend="italic">linearly polarized</hi> light can be achieved by considering the situation where the <hi rend="italic">x</hi> and <hi rend="italic">y</hi> components of the electric field are in phase. </s><s n="s2.5;p25.54">This results in constructive superposition of the maxima and minima and the vector sum leads to a resultant line at 45°. </s><s n="s3.5;p25.54">This light is said to be linearly polarized because the electric field vector traces out a straight line from the maximum amplitude to the minimum amplitude as the two components mutually increase and decrease (figure 4). </s><s n="s4.5;p25.54">The angle that the vector makes with the x-axis is dependant upon the ratio of the magnitudes of the two components. </s><s n="s5.5;p25.54">In this case the amplitudes are equal and so the vector is equidistant from the two axes, however a greater contribution from the amplitude of the <hi rend="italic">y</hi> component would cause the line to rotate further towards the y-axis and the same for the <hi rend="italic">x</hi> component and the x-axis. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0051a-fig.001"><head rend="bold">Figure 4 - Linearly polarized light expressed as a planar representation of the x and y components of the electric field vector[2]</head></figure><p n="p26.54"><s n="s1.1;p26.54">If there is a phase difference of <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0051a-form.006"/> between the two components then the vector sum will result in a line linearly polarized perpendicular to the previous line (the phase difference means that <hi rend="italic">x </hi>→<hi rend="italic">-x</hi> and is equivalent to a reflection in the x-axis). </s></p><p n="p27.54"><s n="s1.5;p27.54">Another situation to consider is where the phase difference <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0051a-form.007"/> (one component is at its maximum when the other is at its minimum). </s><s n="s2.5;p27.54">The magnitudes of the 2 components are no longer always the same but the sum of the resultant vector is. </s><s n="s3.5;p27.54">This leads to a change in the vector direction as the proportion of the two contributing components changes but the magnitude of the vector remains constant. </s><s n="s4.5;p27.54">The vector therefore traces out a circle in the plane. </s><s n="s5.5;p27.54">This is called <hi rend="italic">circular polarization</hi> (figure 5) and is the natural state of white light. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0051a-fig.002"><head rend="bold">Figure 5 - Circularly polarized light expressed as a planar representation of the x and y components of the electric field vector[2]</head></figure><p n="p28.54"><s n="s1.1;p28.54">When this circularly polarized light passes through a polarizer only the small component of the light that is oscillating in the plane parallel to the polarizer passes through with the rest being absorbed. </s></p><p n="p29.54"><s n="s1.6;p29.54">If <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0051a-form.008"/> is any angle other than 90° or 180°, then the <hi rend="italic">x</hi> and <hi rend="italic">y</hi> components combine in different proportions at different points in the period. </s><s n="s2.6;p29.54">This means that both the modulus and direction of the resultant vector changes as the plane wave passes through the plane. </s><s n="s3.6;p29.54">The result of this is that the vector traces out an ellipse and hence this is known as <hi rend="italic">elliptical polarization</hi>. </s><s n="s4.6;p29.54">Elliptically polarized light has a phase difference in-between those of linearly and circularly polarized light. </s><s n="s5.6;p29.54">If <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0051a-form.009"/> tends towards 90° then the minor axis increases until it has the same magnitude as the major axis and the elliptical representation becomes a circle. </s><s n="s6.6;p29.54">Similarly if <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0051a-form.010"/> tends towards 180° then the minor axis of the ellipse decreases until it becomes compressed onto a line. </s></p><p n="p30.54"><s n="s1.1;p30.54">This means that a larger component of elliptically polarized light will pass through a polarizer than circularly polarized light and as that ellipse becomes closer to a line, more of the oscillations will be in the direction allowed by the polarizer and so a greater element of the light will pass through. </s></p><p n="p31.54"><s n="s1.5;p31.54">This is one of the key principles in LCD technology. </s><s n="s2.5;p31.54">The light is linearly polarized as it enters the screen and the helix structure of the liquid crystals is used to change the polarization state of the light to the extent that by the time the light reaches the back of the screen the phase has been shifted by 180°. </s><s n="s3.5;p31.54">In effect the linearly polarized light is rotated by 90°. </s><s n="s4.5;p31.54">This allows the light to then pass through a linear polarizer at the back of the screen which is perpendicular to that which is at the front of the screen. </s><s n="s5.5;p31.54">The next section describes how this phase difference is achieved within the liquid crystal. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">4.2 Birefringence</head><p n="p32.54"><s n="s1.3;p32.54">The way that the light 'twists' with the helix of the liquid crystal to create a phase difference to allow the light to pass through the second polarizer is called <hi rend="italic">Birefringence</hi>. </s><s n="s2.3;p32.54">Birefringence depends upon the fundamental idea of <hi rend="italic">anisotropy</hi>. </s><s n="s3.3;p32.54">This is the idea that liquid crystals look different depending upon which direction they are observed from. </s></p><p n="p33.54"><s n="s1.3;p33.54">Liquid crystals have different properties depending upon how they are approached. </s><s n="s2.3;p33.54">There is a one refractive index for light entering the crystal that is polarized parallel to the director and another for light polarized perpendicularly to the director. </s><s n="s3.3;p33.54">For typical nematic liquid crystals, <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0051a-form.011"/> is approximately 1.5 and the maximum difference, <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0051a-form.012"/>, may range between 0.05 and 0.5 <hi rend="sup">[2]</hi>. </s></p><p n="p34.54"><s n="s1.3;p34.54">This means that any component of light entering the liquid crystal that is parallel to the director will have a different velocity in the medium to a component of light that is perpendicular to the director. </s><s n="s2.3;p34.54">So when light with both <hi rend="italic">x</hi> and <hi rend="italic">y</hi> components (see §# on Polarization) enters the liquid crystal it separates out into two components: the ordinary ray (<hi rend="italic">x</hi> component) and the extraordinary ray (<hi rend="italic">y</hi> component) (figure 5). </s><s n="s3.3;p34.54">This means that when the two components recombine as they exit the medium they are no longer in the same phase that they were previously - each <hi rend="italic">y</hi> component has lagged behind and recombined with a later <hi rend="italic">x</hi> component and so the phase difference has increased. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0051a-fig.003"><head><hi rend="bold">Figure 5 - Birefringence in a liquid crystal. unpolarized light separated into 2 components by the anisotropic nature of liquid crystals[2]</hi> <hi rend="bold">(the director is taken to be vertical in this diagram)</hi></head></figure><p n="p35.54"><s n="s1.1;p35.54">A formula for this phase difference can be derived: </s></p><p n="p36.54"><s n="s1.1;p36.54">The optical path of a ray of light can be defined as </s></p><p n="p37.54"><s n="s1.1;p37.54"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0051a-form.013"/> </s></p><p n="p38.54"><s n="s1.1;p38.54">where <hi rend="italic">L</hi> is the length of the medium that the ray is travelling in. </s></p><p n="p39.54"><s n="s1.1;p39.54">The difference in refractive indices is <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0051a-form.014"/> </s></p><p n="p40.54"><s n="s1.1;p40.54">Therefore the difference in optical path of the two rays, <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0051a-form.015"/> </s></p><p n="p41.54"><s n="s1.1;p41.54">To convert from a distance, <hi rend="italic">L</hi>, to a phase difference, <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0051a-form.016"/>: </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p42.54"><s n="s1.1;p42.54"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0051a-form.017"/> (Equation 2)<hi rend="sup"> [2]</hi> </s></p><p n="p43.54"><s n="s1.1;p43.54">where <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0051a-form.018"/> is the wavelength of the light in a vacuum </s></p><p n="p44.54"><s n="s1.1;p44.54">The length of liquid crystal needed to rotate the polarization state by 90° can be calculated using equation 2, depending upon the refractive indices and light used. </s></p><p n="p45.54"><s n="s1.5;p45.54">Once the light enters the display it passes through the first (vertical) polarizer and becomes linearly polarized. </s><s n="s2.5;p45.54">It then enters the first plane of nematic mesogens in the liquid crystal. </s><s n="s3.5;p45.54">Because the director of the top plane is parallel to the polarizer direction, the light has no <hi rend="italic">x</hi> component and so no separation occurs and the light remains in its current polarization state. </s><s n="s4.5;p45.54">When the light reaches the second plane the director has rotated and now there is a component of the light that is at an angle to it. </s><s n="s5.5;p45.54">This means that there is now also a small <hi rend="italic">x</hi> component of light and birefringence will occur - it will separate from the <hi rend="italic">y</hi> component and recombine to create a phase difference. </s></p><p n="p46.54"><s n="s1.4;p46.54">This process then repeats as the light passes from one plane to the next. </s><s n="s2.4;p46.54">Each small change in director alignment results in a slight decrease in the <hi rend="italic">y</hi> component and a slight increase in the <hi rend="italic">x</hi> component. </s><s n="s3.4;p46.54">This occurs until the light has travelled a distance L through the crystal and all of the y component has undergone birefringence and become the <hi rend="italic">x</hi> component - the <hi rend="italic">y</hi> component is now zero. </s><s n="s4.4;p46.54">This means that the light now passes through the second (horizontal) polarizer. </s></p><p n="p47.54"><s n="s1.4;p47.54">In most simple LCD's a mirror is used and so once the helix has been traversed the ambient light is then reflected back through the system to the observer, retracing its steps. </s><s n="s2.4;p47.54">In more complex colour displays, such as televisions and laptop screens where gradients of light are necessary, a backlight is used. </s><s n="s3.4;p47.54">This provides a higher intensity of light that compensates for the loss of half of the light due to linear polarization by ensuring that what does pass through is of a high intensity. </s><s n="s4.4;p47.54">In this case the light starts from a source at the rear of the screen and follows the twist of the helix once before exiting the display and reaching the observer. </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">5. Use of Electric Fields</head><p n="p48.54"><s n="s1.2;p48.54">The previous sections have dealt with how light is manipulated and passes through crystals with specific properties to display an image on the screen. </s><s n="s2.2;p48.54">Now using this knowledge of the structure and operation of LCD's the creation of areas on a screen with no light can be discussed. </s></p><p n="p49.54"><s n="s1.2;p49.54">When an electric field is passed through a liquid crystal the mesogens attempt to align along the field lines due to a small induced dipole moment. </s><s n="s2.2;p49.54">This is caused by the positively charged protons and negatively charged electrons moving to opposite ends of each rod-like mesogen in line with the electric field. </s></p><p n="p50.54"><s n="s1.4;p50.54">In the context of an LCD the electrodes are situated at the front and back of the display. </s><s n="s2.4;p50.54">When an electric field is applied, it causes the mesogens that originally lie parallel to the screen to tilt in an attempt to lie perpendicular to the screen and in the direction of the electric field lines that go from one electrode at the front to the other at the back of the display. </s><s n="s3.4;p50.54">This ruins the helical alignment of the mesogens that is required in order to rotate the polarization state of the light and at the extreme where the mesogens have tilted by 90°, the light that enters the screen travels straight down the long axis of each mesogen. </s><s n="s4.4;p50.54">There is no twist to enable birefringence to occur and so once the light reaches the back polarizer it has not undergone the necessary phase change in order to pass through the polarizer, so that part of the screen is devoid of light. </s></p><p n="p51.54"><s n="s1.3;p51.54">The magnitude of the induced electric field determines exactly how much the mesogens tilt and therefore how much birefringence can occur before the light reaches the back polarizer. </s><s n="s2.3;p51.54">The amount of light that passes through the liquid crystal perpendicular to the director, <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0051a-form.019"/>, is now <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0051a-form.020"/> since the plane is tilting. </s><s n="s3.3;p51.54">This means that the amount of birefringence reduces as the tilt angle increases. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0051a-fig.004"><head rend="bold">Figure 6 - Graph showing mesogen tilt angle as a result of the voltage applied[2]</head></figure><figure id="BAWE_0051a-fig.005"><head rend="bold">Figure 7 - Graph of % light transmitted when a given voltage is applied[2]</head></figure><p n="p52.54"><s n="s1.4;p52.54">Figure 6 shows the increase in tilt angle as a greater voltage is applied and so the electric field grows stronger. </s><s n="s2.4;p52.54">Figure 7 shows the percentage of light transmitted by the display decreasing as the voltage is increased and the mesogens attempt to align horizontally. </s><s n="s3.4;p52.54">The two lines signify the voltages at which the pixel is deemed to be 'on' and 'off'. </s><s n="s4.4;p52.54">The maximum transmission percentage is only 50% since linearly polarized light is used, which necessitates the use of a backlight. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">6. Addressing</head><p n="p53.54"><s n="s1.7;p53.54">LCD's are divided up into rows and columns of pixels. </s><s n="s2.7;p53.54">Each of these pixels contains all of the necessary components to allow or prevent light from passing through that small portion of the screen. </s><s n="s3.7;p53.54">Addressing is the method used to selectively turn off arbitrary pixels by passing an electric field through them. </s><s n="s4.7;p53.54">Small scale LCD's use direct addressing where each part of the display has its own drive circuit. </s><s n="s5.7;p53.54">This is not feasible for displays that involve a large number of pixels, for example in a television or laptop screen there may be thousands of pixels (and also sub-pixels for each of the 3 constituent colours) that need to be addressed. </s><s n="s6.7;p53.54">In this case multiplex addressing is used. </s><s n="s7.7;p53.54">This is where pixels are addressed by their row and column with one electrode per row and one electrode per column so that for a 10x10 display 20 drive circuits are required as opposed to 100 if direct addressing was used. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">7. Conclusion</head><p n="p54.54"><s n="s1.4;p54.54">The physical mechanisms and theoretical principles of LCD's have been discussed. </s><s n="s2.4;p54.54">Advantages over CRT screens have been argued and the fundamental ideas of liquid crystal technology and light manipulation via polarization and birefringence have been outlined. </s><s n="s3.4;p54.54">The structure of an LCD has been built up referring to the liquid crystal layer, the electrodes and the polarizers and how each layer is used in the operation of the screen. </s><s n="s4.4;p54.54">Finally the methods of addressing the pixels have been summarised for small and large scale displays. </s></p></div1></body><back><div1 type="bibliography"><div2 type="bibliography"><head rend="bold">8. References</head><p>[1] - "Chemical of the Week"</p><p><seg type="URL" n="http://scifun.chem.wisc.edu/chemweek/LiqXtal/LiqXtal.html"/></p><p>[2] - "PLC Virtual Textbook"</p><p><seg type="URL" n="http://plc.cwru.edu/tutorial/enhanced/main.htm"/></p><p>[3] - Polarization definition</p><p><seg type="URL" n="http://www.brainyencyclopedia.com/encyclopedia/p/po/polarization.html"/></p></div2><div2 type="bibliography"><head rend="bold">9. Bibliography</head><p>N.A.Platé (ed), "Liquid Crystal Polymers", Plenum Press, Oxford, 1993</p><p>R.M.A. Azzam and N.M. Bashara, "Ellipsometry and Polarized Light", North Holland Publishing, Oxford, 1977</p><p>Dept. of Physics, Case Western Reserve University, "PLC Virtual Textbook" <seg type="URL" n="http://plc.cwru.edu/tutorial/enhanced/main.htm"/></p><p>"Brainyencyclopedia.com", "Polarization definition", <seg type="URL" n="http://www.brainyencyclopedia.com/encyclopedia/p/po/polarization.html"/></p><p>Peter J. Collings and Michael Hird, "Introduction to Liquid Crystals", Taylor &amp; Francis Publishers, London, 1997</p></div2></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
