<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_0051d" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Nuclear Power - A Source of Hazardous Waste</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">deleted: header: student name and number
</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">3</p><p n="date">2005-10</p><p n="module title">Communicating Science</p><p n="module code">PX376</p><p n="genre family">Essay</p><p n="discipline">Physics</p><p n="disciplinary group">PS</p><p n="grade">M</p><p n="number of authors">2</p><p n="number of words">945</p><p n="number of s-units">39</p><p n="number of p">13</p><p n="number of tables">1</p><p n="number of figures">0</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">0</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">0</p><p n="abstract present">abstract present</p><p n="average words per s-unit">24.2</p><p n="average s-units per p">3.0</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">m</p><p n="year of birth">1984</p><p n="first language">English</p><p n="education">UKA</p><p n="course">Physics</p><p n="student ID">0051</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><docTitle><titlePart rend="underlined bold">Nuclear Power: A Source of Hazardous Waste</titlePart></docTitle></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="abstract"><head rend="bold">Abstract</head><p n="p1.13"><s n="s1.2;p1.13">With the increased interest in nuclear power as a viable source of energy, little consideration has been given to waste management. </s><s n="s2.2;p1.13">In this paper the two current methods of the disposal of high-level radioactive waste have been discussed and their associated problems critically evaluated. </s></p><p n="p2.13"><s n="s1.1;p2.13">______________________________________________________________ </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><p n="p3.13"><s n="s1.7;p3.13">With the current energy crisis and the imminent demise of fossil fuels world governments are looking for reliable energy sources. </s><s n="s2.7;p3.13">One of the more favourable solutions they have chosen is nuclear power. </s><s n="s3.7;p3.13">The main disadvantage is that the unwanted by-product of nuclear fission process is a large amount of hazardous radioactive waste. </s><s n="s4.7;p3.13">For each year that a reactor is in operation a third of its core material - around 30 tons - has to be removed and replaced. </s><s n="s5.7;p3.13">During their time within the reactor these uranium fuel rods increase in radioactivity to the extent that when they are removed they contain hundreds of radioactive chemicals that generate large amounts of heat and radiation. </s><s n="s6.7;p3.13">This is regarded as high-level waste. </s><s n="s7.7;p3.13">The equipment and tools involved in manipulating the materials is categorised as low-level waste, given its relatively short contact time with the reactor. </s></p><p n="p4.13"><s n="s1.2;p4.13">At the dawn of the nuclear age nobody foresaw any problems regarding the disposal of the radioactive waste. </s><s n="s2.2;p4.13">Whilst low-level waste is easily dealt with there are currently two ways of dealing with high-level waste, each of which has obvious disadvantages. </s></p><p n="p5.13"><s n="s1.3;p5.13">'One method preferred by Canada and the US is to bury the waste deep underground in a remote location'<hi rend="sup">[1]</hi>. </s><s n="s2.3;p5.13">This is proving increasingly difficult due to the lack of geographically suitable areas. </s><s n="s3.3;p5.13">There are also political consequences of storing dangerous nuclear waste in populated areas that will remain a threat for as long as twenty-four thousands years <hi rend="sup">[2]</hi> - longer than the recorded history of man - and at a cost of tens of millions of pounds per year <hi rend="sup">[3]</hi>. </s></p><p n="p6.13"><s n="s1.2;p6.13">The alternative approach practiced by European countries <hi rend="sup">[1]</hi> is to reprocess the spent fuel rods to extract unused uranium and plutonium, both of which are used in atomic bomb construction, an obvious unethical by-product. </s><s n="s2.2;p6.13">Of the three commercial reprocessing centres planned for construction in the United States during the 1960's, only one saw completion and it was closed down in 1972 under a cloud of controversy concerning accidental contamination at the site. </s></p><p n="p7.13"><s n="s1.3;p7.13">Although reprocessing was and still is a viable option, it merely separates the much sought after plutonium from the remaining fission products which still remain radioactive for over a millennium. </s><s n="s2.3;p7.13">Unfortunately the political situation throughout the latter twentieth century has forced laws to be passed to prevent governments from reprocessing radioactive waste. </s><s n="s3.3;p7.13">While this does remove the threat of countries obtaining nuclear missile capabilities, it also results in an increase in high-level waste being deposited at the reactor sites. </s></p><p n="p8.13"><s n="s1.1;p8.13">The untreated waste has been allowed to accumulate to the extent that today 'approximately 7000 tons of spent fuel from commercial reactors is stored on racks submerged in cooling ponds or "swimming pools" at each reactor site [in America].'<hi rend="sup">[1]</hi> This waste is highly dangerous and if left untreated can be damaging to the local environment. </s></p><p n="p9.13"><s n="s1.3;p9.13">Before understanding the severity of the radiation emitted by radioactive waste, one must understand the units and scales used. </s><s n="s2.3;p9.13">Radiation dosage is measured in <hi rend="italic">rem</hi>s with a thousand millirems constituting one rem. </s><s n="s3.3;p9.13">Table 1 shows how differing values affect the human body. </s></p><table id="BAWE_0051d-tab.001"><head rend="bold italic">Table 1 - Radiation dosages and their resultant effects on subjects</head><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p10.13"><s n="s1.1;p10.13">The reason that nuclear power plants are so low on the scale is due to heavy shielding around the reactor core, but once the waste leaves the core the radioactive emissions are far in excess of background radiation. </s></p><p n="p11.13"><s n="s1.3;p11.13">As the table shows, radiation effects are not easily observable below 50 rems. </s><s n="s2.3;p11.13">'Few low-level studies exist, not only because the results are ambiguous, but also because studies that require research and follow-up for a period of forty years are prohibitively expensive.'<hi rend="sup">[4]</hi> This makes it difficult to know what the effects of low-level radiation are over long periods of time. </s><s n="s3.3;p11.13">Cancer may not appear for decades after exposure and genetic defects may lay dormant for generations. </s></p><p n="p12.13"><s n="s1.7;p12.13">The closest scientists have come to a model for low-level radiation behaviour is to study the high-dose effects and extrapolate the information down to the low-dose range <hi rend="sup">[4]</hi>. </s><s n="s2.7;p12.13">Here lies the source of the radiation controversy. </s><s n="s3.7;p12.13">Whilst many scientists support the linear hypothesis, there is an increasing belief that more damage is caused per rem at low doses than at high ones. </s><s n="s4.7;p12.13">Their argument is that lower doses only weaken and damage cells rather than kill them. </s><s n="s5.7;p12.13">These cells then live on to damage neighbouring healthy cells - similar to a cancer. </s><s n="s6.7;p12.13">Whilst highly radioactive waste can be buried well below ground in order to minimise the resultant effects at surface level, the resultant low-level increase in the radioactivity at the surface could raise the level beyond the tolerable limit and hence cause damage to the human body that is not visible. </s><s n="s7.7;p12.13">'This may manifest itself as an increased risk of mental retardation along with other congenital malformations.'<hi rend="sup">[5]</hi> </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Conclusion</head><p n="p13.13"><s n="s1.4;p13.13">Nuclear power plants produce thousands of tons of radioactive waste each year and yet there is still no safe and efficient method of disposal. </s><s n="s2.4;p13.13">Burial is very much limited by the suitability of potential sites and even when a suitable site is found, there are still adverse effects on the surrounding environment. </s><s n="s3.4;p13.13">Reprocessing is both expensive and ineffective as it only marginally reduces the amount of radioactive constituents which then need to be buried. </s><s n="s4.4;p13.13">As such nuclear power is still very much an unethical and dangerous power source and will remain so until significant breakthroughs have been made regarding waste disposal. </s></p></div1></body><back><div1 type="bibliography"><div2 type="bibliography"><head rend="bold">References</head><p> [1] - <hi rend="italic">'Radioactive Waste Management'</hi></p><p> Uranium Information Centre, <seg type="URL" n="http://www.uic.com.au/wast.htm"/>, 2002</p><p>[2] - <hi rend="italic">'Poison Power',</hi></p><p>John W. Gofman &amp; Arthur R. Tamplin, Rodale Press, 1971</p><p>[3] - <hi rend="italic">'Radioactive Waste Management in Perspective'</hi>, </p><p>Nuclear Energy Agency, OECD, 1996</p><p>[4] - <hi rend="italic">'Nuclear Power: Both Sides',</hi></p><p>Michio Kaku PhD &amp; Jennifer Trainer, WW Norton &amp; Co., 1982</p><p>[5] - <hi rend="italic">'Report of the President's Commission on the Accident at Three Mile Island'</hi>, </p><p>L. Battist et. al, 1979</p></div2><div2 type="bibliography"><head rend="bold">Bibliography</head><p rend="italic"> 'Radioactive Waste Management'</p><p> Uranium Information Centre, <seg type="URL" n="http://www.uic.com.au/wast.htm"/>, 2002</p><p rend="italic">'Poison Power',</p><p>John W. Gofman &amp; Arthur R. Tamplin, Rodale Press, 1971</p><p><hi rend="italic">'Radioactive Waste Management in Perspective'</hi>, </p><p>Nuclear Energy Agency, OECD, 1996</p><p rend="italic">'Nuclear Power: Both Sides',</p><p>Michio Kaku PhD &amp; Jennifer Trainer, WW Norton &amp; Co., 1982</p><p rend="italic"> 'Report of the President's Commission on the Accident at Three Mile Island',</p><p>L. Battist et. al, 1979</p><p rend="italic">'Public Radiation Exposure From Nuclear Power Generation in the U.S.',</p><p>National Council on Radiation Protection, Report No. 92, 1987, 72-112</p></div2></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
