<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_0051b" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>P4 - X-ray Crystallography - Powder Diffraction</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">The document has a title page which contains:
document title
title part
abstract</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">2</p><p n="date">2004-12</p><p n="module title">Experimetal Techniques A</p><p n="module code">PX251</p><p n="genre family">Methodology recount</p><p n="discipline">Physics</p><p n="disciplinary group">PS</p><p n="grade">M</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">3274</p><p n="number of s-units">186</p><p n="number of p">124</p><p n="number of tables">1</p><p n="number of figures">7</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">109</p><p n="number of lists">0</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">6</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">17.6</p><p n="average s-units per p">1.5</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">m</p><p n="year of birth">1984</p><p n="first language">English</p><p n="education">UKA</p><p n="course">Physics</p><p n="student ID">0051</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><titlePart>University of <name type="university"/> Second Year Physics Laboratory</titlePart><docTitle><titlePart>P4 X-ray Crystallography Powder Diffraction</titlePart></docTitle><titlePart rend="bold"><name type="student name"/><name type="student ID"/></titlePart></titlePage><div1 type="abstract"><head rend="bold">Abstract</head><p>The lattice types and lattice parameters for 2 unknown samples were determined by analysis of diffraction patterns created as a result of x-ray powder diffraction. Secondly the lattice parameter for a mixed sample composed of KBr and KCl was obtained. Vegard's Law was then tested using this sample.</p><p>Sample 1 had a face-centred cubic structure and a lattice parameter of</p><p><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0051b-form.001"/></p><p>This value is higher than the accepted value and hence when it was used to identify the sample, identification was not possible.</p><p>Sample 2 had a simple cubic structure and a lattice parameter of</p><p><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0051b-form.002"/></p><p>This value is in agreement with the accepted value and the sample was identified as <hi rend="italic">sodium chlorate</hi>.</p><p>By analysing high scattering angles, a more accurate value for <hi rend="italic">a</hi> was obtained:</p><p><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0051b-form.003"/></p><p>This result contained a considerably smaller error of 0.037%</p><p>For the mixed sample the lattice parameter was</p><p><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0051b-form.004"/></p><p>This point lay on the theoretical linear plot and so supported Vegard's Law.</p></div1></front><body><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">1. Introduction</head><div2><head rend="bold">1.1 Finding the lattice parameter, <hi rend="italic">a</hi></head><p n="p1.124"><s n="s1.2;p1.124">When an x-ray beam passes through a crystalline structure, diffraction occurs because the spacing between the layers of molecules is less than the wavelength of the x-ray radiation. </s><s n="s2.2;p1.124">The angle by which the wave is diffracted,<formula notation="" id="BAWE_0051b-form.005"/>, can be modelled using Bragg's Law: </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p2.124"><s n="s1.1;p2.124"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0051b-form.006"/> (Equation 1) </s></p><p n="p3.124"><s n="s1.2;p3.124">where <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0051b-form.007"/> is the wavelength of the x-ray radiation and <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0051b-form.008"/> is the interplanar spacing of the crystal with Miller indices <hi rend="italic">h</hi>, <hi rend="italic">k</hi> and <hi rend="italic">l</hi>. </s><s n="s2.2;p3.124"><hi rend="italic">N</hi> is an integer value referring to the reading being taken at the <hi rend="italic">n</hi><hi rend="sup">th</hi> maxima. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0051b-pic.001"><head rend="bold">Figure 1 - Bragg's Law in action as a wave is diffracted when passing through a crystal[1]</head></figure><p n="p4.124"><s n="s1.1;p4.124"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0051b-form.009"/> can be expressed as </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p5.124"><s n="s1.1;p5.124"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0051b-form.010"/> (Equation 2) </s></p><p n="p6.124"><s n="s1.1;p6.124">where <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0051b-form.011"/> is the lattice parameter. </s></p><p n="p7.124"><s n="s1.1;p7.124">By combining equations 1 and 2, the following relationship can be obtained: </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p8.124"><s n="s1.1;p8.124"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0051b-form.012"/> (Equation 3) </s></p><p n="p9.124"><s n="s1.1;p9.124">A value for <hi rend="italic">a</hi> can therefore be determined from the gradient of the linear relationship between the maxima number, <hi rend="italic">N</hi>, and a function of the diffraction angle, <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0051b-form.013"/>. </s></p><p n="p10.124"><s n="s1.1;p10.124">Indexing can then be carried out, whereby the <hi rend="italic">N</hi> values are attributed to different maxima depending upon the lattice type of the crystal: <hi rend="italic">simple cubic</hi> (<hi rend="italic">P</hi>), <hi rend="italic">face-centred cubic</hi> (<hi rend="italic">F</hi>) and <hi rend="italic">body-centred cubic</hi> (<hi rend="italic">I</hi>) {refer to table in lab script[2]}. </s></p><p n="p11.124"><s n="s1.1;p11.124">When equation 3 is plotted with the appropriate set of <hi rend="italic">N</hi> values for the three different lattice types, only one will yield a linear relationship passing through the origin and so the lattice type will be evident. </s></p><p n="p12.124"><s n="s1.1;p12.124">Differentiating Bragg's Law shows that </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p13.124"><s n="s1.1;p13.124"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0051b-form.014"/> (Equation 4) </s></p><p n="p14.124"><s n="s1.2;p14.124">This shows that a small change in the lattice parameter leads to a large change in Bragg angle near back reflection. </s><s n="s2.2;p14.124">Consequently the higher order reflections are extremely sensitive to the lattice parameter and so in order to obtain <hi rend="italic">a</hi> values to a greater degree of accuracy (~0.1%), measurements are taken at large values of <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0051b-form.015"/> where such back reflection occurs. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">1.2 Identifying samples</head><p n="p15.124"><s n="s1.3;p15.124">Once accurate values for the lattice parameter are obtained, these can be used to identify the sample that the x-ray beam was being diffracted by. </s><s n="s2.3;p15.124">The American Society for Testing Materials (A.S.T.M.) index identifies a sample based on the <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0051b-form.016"/> values of its three most intense Bragg reflections. </s><s n="s3.3;p15.124">By inputting ranges for the three <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0051b-form.017"/> values and the lattice parameter, a list of possible matches is formulated, which can then be further narrowed down using other characteristics such as the lattice type and colour of the sample in order to determine the nature of the sample. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">1.3 Vegard's Law</head><p n="p16.124"><s n="s1.2;p16.124">Vegard's law states that if two crystalline materials with different lattice parameters are combined (melted together and cooled), then the lattice parameter of the new compound is expected to vary linearly with the atomic composition of the compound in question. </s><s n="s2.2;p16.124">Therefore if the proportions of two substances that make up a compound are known, then the lattice parameter will be that proportion of the way between the lattice parameters of the two substances. </s></p><p n="p17.124"><s n="s1.3;p17.124">The experiment comprises two parts - in the first section the lattice parameters and lattice types for two unknown samples were calculated. </s><s n="s2.3;p17.124">These substances were then identified using the ASTM index. </s><s n="s3.3;p17.124">In the second section a compound mixture of potassium chloride (KCl) and potassium bromide (KBr) was created and its lattice parameter and interplanar spacings were determined so as to test Vegard's Law. </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">2. Part (a)</head><div2><head rend="bold">2.1 Experimental Detail</head><p n="p18.124"><s n="s1.3;p18.124">The camera used in this experiment (see Figure 2) consisted of a centrally mounted sample aligned between two collimators. </s><s n="s2.3;p18.124">The circular nature of the camera allowed a film to be placed around the inside of the case which absorbed radiation emitted at all possible values of <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0051b-form.018"/>. </s><s n="s3.3;p18.124">For convenience the circumference of the case <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0051b-form.019"/> and so <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0051b-form.020"/>. </s></p><p n="p19.124"><s n="s1.4;p19.124">The sample was ground up and added to a capillary tube to a depth of 25mm. </s><s n="s2.4;p19.124">This was then mounted in the centre of a camera such that it was in line with the collimators so that the x-ray beam would pass directly through the sample. </s><s n="s3.4;p19.124">The tube was vertically aligned (perpendicular to the path taken by the x-ray beam through the collimators) so that when it was rotated no precession occurred. </s><s n="s4.4;p19.124">This maximised the amount of time that the sample spent in the x-ray beam. </s></p><p n="p20.124"><s n="s1.3;p20.124">The film was inserted and the camera was sealed in complete darkness and then positioned in the X-ray machine where the sample was rotated by an external motor. </s><s n="s2.3;p20.124">This utilises the isotropic nature of the crystalline structure to ensure that the effects of impurities in the sample are minimised. </s><s n="s3.3;p20.124">The sample was then exposed to the x-ray source for 7 hours. </s></p><p n="p21.124"><s n="s1.2;p21.124">The x-ray source used in this experiment was a copper source that had a wavelength of <hi rend="italic">1.5425</hi>Å. </s><s n="s2.2;p21.124">This represents a combination of the two components <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0051b-form.021"/> and <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0051b-form.022"/><hi rend="sup">[3]</hi> </s></p><p n="p22.124"><s n="s1.1;p22.124">The diffraction patterns that occurred as a result of the scattering took the form of concentric rings centred about the focus of the x-ray beam where the beam exited the camera. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0051b-pic.002"><head rend="bold">Figure 2 - Camera setup used to expose the sample to x-ray radiation and the resulting diffraction pattern</head></figure><p n="p23.124"><s n="s1.1;p23.124">The geometry of the system is such that the diameter of these rings, <hi rend="italic">D</hi>, is equivalent to <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0051b-form.023"/> (see figure 2 above). </s></p><p n="p24.124"><s n="s1.2;p24.124">This process was undertaken for both sample 1 and sample 2, with each sample exposed to the x-ray source for 7 hours. </s><s n="s2.2;p24.124">The film was then removed and developed in complete darkness. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">2.2 Results</head><div3><head rend="underlined bold">2.2.1 Sample 1</head><div4><head rend="bold">i) Finding <hi rend="italic">a</hi></head><p n="p25.124"><s n="s1.6;p25.124">The diffraction pattern as a result of x-ray diffraction through sample 1 was analysed. </s><s n="s2.6;p25.124">The diameter of each diffraction ring, <hi rend="italic">D</hi>, was measured and hence the scattering angle determined. </s><s n="s3.6;p25.124">Measurements were made for the 9 visible diffraction rings (<formula notation="" id="BAWE_0051b-form.024"/> to <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0051b-form.025"/>) and then the results were indexed. </s><s n="s4.6;p25.124">This was achieved by attributing appropriate <hi rend="italic">N</hi> values for <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0051b-form.026"/> for each of the 3 hypothetical lattice types and identifying that which satisfied the linear relationship. </s><s n="s5.6;p25.124">For example for a face-centred cubic <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0051b-form.027"/> maps onto <hi rend="italic">N</hi>=3,4,8,... </s><s n="s6.6;p25.124">24 (refer to table 1). </s></p><p n="p26.124"><s n="s1.3;p26.124">These <hi rend="italic">N</hi> and <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0051b-form.028"/> values were then substituted in <hi rend="italic">equation 3</hi> and the relationship was plotted (see <hi rend="italic">Figure 3</hi>). </s><s n="s2.3;p26.124">The linear relationship was apparent. </s><s n="s3.3;p26.124">The line passes through the origin and therefore it can be assumed that this is the correct lattice type. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0051b-fig.001"><head rend="bold">Figure 3 - Finding the lattice parameter, <hi rend="italic">a</hi>, for sample 1</head></figure><p n="p27.124"><s n="s1.1;p27.124">Using <hi rend="italic">equation 3</hi> </s></p><p n="p28.124"><s n="s1.1;p28.124"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0051b-form.029"/> </s></p><p n="p29.124"><s n="s1.1;p29.124"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0051b-form.030"/> </s></p><p n="p30.124"><s n="s1.1;p30.124">The gradient of <hi rend="italic">figure 3</hi> was found to be <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0051b-form.031"/> and <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0051b-form.032"/> </s></p><p n="p31.124"><s n="s1.1;p31.124"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0051b-form.033"/> </s></p></div4><div4><head rend="bold">ii) Error Analysis</head><p n="p32.124"><s n="s1.1;p32.124">Error in gradient, <hi rend="italic">G</hi>, taken from Origin to be <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0051b-form.034"/>Å (0.247%) </s></p><p n="p33.124"><s n="s1.1;p33.124">Error in <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0051b-form.035"/> taken to be negligible </s></p><p n="p34.124"><s n="s1.1;p34.124"><hi rend="italic">a</hi> is of the form <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0051b-form.036"/> </s></p><p n="p35.124"><s n="s1.1;p35.124"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0051b-form.037"/> </s></p></div4><div4><head rend="bold">iii) Identifying the Sample</head><p n="p36.124"><s n="s1.1;p36.124">The 3 most prominent lines were noted and these 3 <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0051b-form.038"/> values were used to determine the interplanar spacing, <hi rend="italic">d</hi>, for each ring. </s></p><p n="p37.124"><s n="s1.1;p37.124">This was achieved using <hi rend="italic">equation 1</hi>: </s></p><p n="p38.124"><s n="s1.1;p38.124">For an arbitrary maxima </s></p><p n="p39.124"><s n="s1.1;p39.124"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0051b-form.039"/> </s></p><p n="p40.124"><s n="s1.1;p40.124"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0051b-form.040"/> </s></p><p n="p41.124"><s n="s1.1;p41.124">The 3 lines with the greatest intensities were at </s></p><p n="p42.124"><s n="s1.1;p42.124"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0051b-form.041"/> </s></p><p n="p43.124"><s n="s1.1;p43.124"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0051b-form.042"/> </s></p><p n="p44.124"><s n="s1.1;p44.124"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0051b-form.043"/> </s></p><p n="p45.124"><s n="s1.2;p45.124">Using the ASTM database and inputting maximum and minimum values for d <hi rend="sub">1</hi>,d <hi rend="sub">2</hi> and d <hi rend="sub">3</hi>, a list of 128 possible substances was found. </s><s n="s2.2;p45.124">These were further filtered by the use of other parameters. </s></p><p n="p46.124"><s n="s1.2;p46.124">A visualisation is provided for each possible match showing the intensities across all <hi rend="italic">N</hi> values. </s><s n="s2.2;p46.124">From this it was possible to compare the relative intensities of the potential matches with the film for sample 1 and thus reduce the list of possible substances. </s></p><p n="p47.124"><s n="s1.1;p47.124">Features such as colour (which in sample 1's case was white), lattice type (sample 1 was face-centred cubic) and <hi rend="italic">a</hi> value (<formula notation="" id="BAWE_0051b-form.044"/>) also helped to further reduce the uncertainty in the list however the list was still too large to identify the sample. </s></p></div4></div3><div3><head rend="underlined bold">2.2.2 Sample 2</head><div4><head rend="bold">i) Finding <hi rend="italic">a</hi></head><p n="p48.124"><s n="s1.2;p48.124">The diffraction pattern was analysed for sample 2. </s><s n="s2.2;p48.124">Once again the diameter of each diffraction ring, <hi rend="italic">D</hi>, was measured and the scattering angle determined. </s></p><p n="p49.124"><s n="s1.1;p49.124">For this sample 17 diffraction rings (<formula notation="" id="BAWE_0051b-form.045"/> to <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0051b-form.046"/>) were visible and these lines were indexed. </s></p><p n="p50.124"><s n="s1.4;p50.124">These <hi rend="italic">N</hi> and <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0051b-form.047"/> values were substituted in <hi rend="italic">equation 3</hi> and the relationship was plotted (see <hi rend="italic">Figure 4</hi>). </s><s n="s2.4;p50.124">The relationship was not linear and so required adjustment to compensate for any maxima that might not have been visible on the film that may have lead to incorrectly indexed <hi rend="italic">N</hi> values. </s><s n="s3.4;p50.124">By assuming that maxima are missing from the film before <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0051b-form.048"/> and <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0051b-form.049"/> and therefore translating the <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0051b-form.050"/> values up one at these two points before mapping <hi rend="italic">N</hi> values, a linear relationship became apparent. </s><s n="s4.4;p50.124">The line passes through the origin and therefore it can be assumed that this is the correct lattice type. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0051b-fig.002"><head rend="bold">Figure 4 - finding the lattice parameter, <hi rend="italic">a</hi>, for sample 2</head></figure><p n="p51.124"><s n="s1.1;p51.124">Using <hi rend="italic">equation 3</hi> again </s></p><p n="p52.124"><s n="s1.1;p52.124"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0051b-form.051"/> </s></p><p n="p53.124"><s n="s1.1;p53.124"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0051b-form.052"/> </s></p><p n="p54.124"><s n="s1.1;p54.124">The gradient of <hi rend="italic">figure 4</hi> was <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0051b-form.053"/><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0051b-form.054"/> and <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0051b-form.055"/>. </s></p><p n="p55.124"><s n="s1.1;p55.124"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0051b-form.056"/> </s></p><p n="p56.124"><s n="s1.1;p56.124">(For error analysis refer to §2.1.2) </s></p></div4><div4><head rend="bold">ii) Identifying the Sample</head><p n="p57.124"><s n="s1.1;p57.124">The 3 lines with the greatest intensities were at </s></p><p n="p58.124"><s n="s1.1;p58.124"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0051b-form.057"/> </s></p><p n="p59.124"><s n="s1.1;p59.124"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0051b-form.058"/> </s></p><p n="p60.124"><s n="s1.1;p60.124"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0051b-form.059"/> </s></p><p n="p61.124"><s n="s1.3;p61.124">By putting the upper and lower bounds for d <hi rend="sub">1</hi>, d <hi rend="sub">2</hi> and d <hi rend="sub">3</hi> into the ASTM index a list of 5 possible substances was found. </s><s n="s2.3;p61.124">The 4 incorrect matches were filtered out by comparing the <hi rend="italic">a</hi> values as well as using the fact that the sample was a white powder with a simple cubic structure. </s><s n="s3.3;p61.124">Finally the intensities across all <hi rend="italic">N</hi> values married up and so it was possible to identify sample 2 to be <hi rend="italic">Sodium Chlorate</hi>, which has <hi rend="italic">d</hi> values of <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0051b-form.060"/>, <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0051b-form.061"/> and <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0051b-form.062"/>. </s></p></div4></div3><div3><head rend="underlined bold">2.2.3 Higher Angle Scattering</head><p n="p62.124"><s n="s1.2;p62.124">As mentioned in §1.1 measurement of the diffraction patterns for higher values of θ leads to greater accuracy (~0.1%) in the resultant lattice constant. </s><s n="s2.2;p62.124">At the high angle reflections the rings of the diffraction pattern separates into doublets with two different components, K <hi rend="sub">α1</hi> and K <hi rend="sub">α2</hi><hi rend="sup">[3]</hi> </s></p><p n="p63.124"><s n="s1.2;p63.124">Figure 5 shows the geometry of the situation. </s><s n="s2.2;p63.124">The diameter of the doublets, <hi rend="italic">D</hi>, is equivalent to the angle <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0051b-form.063"/> which is given by the following expression: </s></p><p n="p64.124"><s n="s1.1;p64.124"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0051b-form.064"/> or <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0051b-form.065"/> </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0051b-fig.003"><head rend="bold">Figure 5 - Angle relationship</head></figure><p n="p65.124"><s n="s1.3;p65.124">These theta values for all visible doublet <hi rend="italic">D</hi> measurements were plotted on a graph of <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0051b-form.066"/> against <hi rend="italic">N</hi> to find the integer <hi rend="italic">N</hi> values associated with these Bragg angles. </s><s n="s2.3;p65.124">These were then substituted into <hi rend="italic">equation 3</hi> to find <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0051b-form.067"/>. </s><s n="s3.3;p65.124">These values were then plotted on a graph of <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0051b-form.068"/> against an error function which is proportional to: </s></p><p n="p66.124"><s n="s1.1;p66.124"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0051b-form.069"/> </s></p><p n="p67.124"><s n="s1.2;p67.124">This error function tends to zero as <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0051b-form.070"/> or when <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0051b-form.071"/> where the beam is reflected back. </s><s n="s2.2;p67.124">This means that the <hi rend="italic">a</hi> value is most accurate at <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0051b-form.072"/> and so the y-intercept of the graph of <hi rend="italic">a(N)</hi> against the error function provides the most accurate value for <hi rend="italic">a</hi>. </s></p><p n="p68.124"><s n="s1.1;p68.124">The <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0051b-form.073"/> value used in equation 3 for each ring of the doublet refers to the wavelength of the wave originating from the copper source but, as mentioned above, the wave has separated into 2 components and so there are 2 corresponding <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0051b-form.074"/> values that must be used depending on whether the result in question is the outer ring or the inner ring. </s></p><p n="p69.124"><s n="s1.1;p69.124">For the copper source used in all sections of this experiment </s></p><p n="p70.124"><s n="s1.1;p70.124"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0051b-form.075"/> - very strong </s></p><p n="p71.124"><s n="s1.1;p71.124"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0051b-form.076"/> - strong <hi rend="sup">[2]</hi> </s></p><p n="p72.124"><s n="s1.2;p72.124">For doublets at higher angles the inner ring is as a result of <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0051b-form.077"/> and the outer ring is due to <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0051b-form.078"/>. </s><s n="s2.2;p72.124">This is due to Bragg's Law where <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0051b-form.079"/> is a function of <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0051b-form.080"/> and so a larger wavelength will lead to a larger diffraction angle and so the ring will be further from the exit hole; hence making it the inner of the two rings (figure 6). </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0051b-fig.004"><head rend="bold">Figure 6 - the 2 contributions to the doublet rings</head></figure><p n="p73.124"><s n="s1.1;p73.124">From figure 7 the y-intercept value was 6.579 with an error (given by Origin) of 0.037%. </s></p><p n="p74.124"><s n="s1.1;p74.124"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0051b-form.081"/> </s></p><p n="p75.124"><s n="s1.2;p75.124">which is in agreement with the value found in <hi rend="italic">§2.2.1</hi> to be <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0051b-form.082"/>. </s><s n="s2.2;p75.124">The error has also been improved from 0.219% down to 0.037%. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0051b-fig.005"><head rend="bold">Figure 7 - Finding the lattice parameter, <hi rend="italic">a</hi>, for high angle scattering</head></figure></div3></div2><div2><head rend="bold">2.3 Discussion</head><p n="p76.124"><s n="s1.2;p76.124">Sample 2 was correctly identified to the extent that when the <hi rend="italic">a</hi> value was put into the database there were very few possible matches. </s><s n="s2.2;p76.124">This may be an indication of the great deal of accuracy in determining a, although it may just be coincidence and merely that there are very few substances in the database with a values near to that of sodium chlorate. </s></p><p n="p77.124"><s n="s1.3;p77.124">The high angle indexing proved highly successful, yielding a value with a particularly small error (0.037%). </s><s n="s2.3;p77.124">This was far below the required level of 0.1% and can be accredited to the wealth of doublet lines that were visible on the film that could be analysed. </s><s n="s3.3;p77.124">This value is also in agreement with that found in §3.2.1. </s></p><p n="p78.124"><s n="s1.4;p78.124">Sample 1 was not successfully identified. </s><s n="s2.4;p78.124">The value for the lattice parameter was higher than the accepted value and so this may have lead to the inability to find the correct match in the list produced by the ASTM index. </s><s n="s3.4;p78.124">Further parameters did narrow down the list of possibilities, but not to the extent where it was possible to confidently identify the sample. </s><s n="s4.4;p78.124">This could be as a result of an unforeseen error in the calculations; leading to an underestimate of the error in <hi rend="italic">a</hi> and so the error bounds were not large enough to include the accepted value. </s></p><p n="p79.124"><s n="s1.4;p79.124">The main problem that was encountered was the lack of definition in the diffraction rings on the films. </s><s n="s2.4;p79.124">Some films were underexposed and so many of the maxima were not visible, leading to incorrect assumptions regarding the structure of the sample and problems when indexing. </s><s n="s3.4;p79.124">With the range of visible lines varying from 7 to 27 there were some instances where the structure was indeterminable and so the films had to be repeated. </s><s n="s4.4;p79.124">Other films were overexposed which then made the doublets more difficult to identify and measure. </s></p><p n="p80.124"><s n="s1.3;p80.124">Another factor that may have contributed to the intensity problems was the vertical alignment of the sample in the camera. </s><s n="s2.3;p80.124">This was done by standing the tube in a lump of 'blu-tack' and prodding it until it appeared to be vertical and central on the stand. </s><s n="s3.3;p80.124">The camera was then sealed and moved into the x-ray machine with no opportunity to check the alignment of the sample again and so some external perturbation during that time may have caused the sample to precess or even move in and out of the x-ray beam, reducing the exposure time and therefore the intensity of the resulting diffraction patterns. </s></p><p n="p81.124"><s n="s1.1;p81.124">The powdered sample may not have been sufficiently ground up and so the point at which the x-ray beam passed through the tube may have contained air gaps, which would have affected the pattern on the film and possibly lead to the larger <hi rend="italic">a</hi> value. </s></p><p n="p82.124"><s n="s1.3;p82.124">The method could be improved by using a camera with a better means of fixing the sample vertically in the centre of the beam so that the intensity was as good as possible. </s><s n="s2.3;p82.124">This would lead to a greater deal of clarity in the diffraction patters and hence provide more data to draw conclusions from. </s><s n="s3.3;p82.124">This improvement in intensity would also increase the definition of the rings, making them thinner and hence remove any possible ambiguity in where the measurement should be taken from and to. </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">3. Part (b)</head><div2><head rend="bold">3.1 Experimental Detail</head><p n="p83.124"><s n="s1.1;p83.124">A mixture of KBr and KCl was created with equal proportions with respect to their molecular masses using the following data: </s></p><p n="p84.124"><s n="s1.1;p84.124">Total Mass,<formula notation="" id="BAWE_0051b-form.083"/> </s></p><table id="BAWE_0051b-tab.001"><head rend="bold italic">Table 1 - Combining atomic masses</head><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p85.124"><s n="s1.1;p85.124">From these two values a ratio was formed: </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p86.124"><s n="s1.1;p86.124"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0051b-form.084"/> (Equation 5) </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p87.124"><s n="s1.1;p87.124"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0051b-form.085"/> (Equation 6) </s></p><p n="p88.124"><s n="s1.1;p88.124">Combining equations 5 and 6 gives </s></p><p n="p89.124"><s n="s1.1;p89.124"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0051b-form.086"/> </s></p><p n="p90.124"><s n="s1.1;p90.124"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0051b-form.087"/> </s></p><p n="p91.124"><s n="s1.1;p91.124"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0051b-form.088"/> </s></p><p n="p92.124"><s n="s1.3;p92.124">By creating a 50:50 mix then according to Vegard's law the theoretical value for the lattice parameter was set at a point half way between the value of a <hi rend="sub">KBr</hi> and a <hi rend="sub">KCl</hi>. </s><s n="s2.3;p92.124">The mixture was heated until melting to form a liquid and then cooled to form a single compound. </s><s n="s3.3;p92.124">This was then ground up, inserted into the camera and exposed to the x-ray source in the same manner as samples 1 and 2 (see §2.1). </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">3.2 Results</head><div3><head rend="underlined bold">3.2.1 Finding <hi rend="italic">a</hi></head><p n="p93.124"><s n="s1.1;p93.124">The diffraction pattern was analysed for the mixture (see <hi rend="italic">§2.2.1i</hi> for method). </s></p><p n="p94.124"><s n="s1.1;p94.124">9 diffraction rings (<formula notation="" id="BAWE_0051b-form.089"/> to <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0051b-form.090"/>) were visible and these lines were indexed. </s></p><p n="p95.124"><s n="s1.1;p95.124">Given that the two compounds that make up this mixed sample are both face-centred cubic, it is safe to assume that this sample will therefore also be a face-centred cubic structure. </s></p><p n="p96.124"><s n="s1.4;p96.124">These <hi rend="italic">N</hi> and <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0051b-form.091"/> values were substituted in <hi rend="italic">equation 3</hi> and the relationship was plotted (see <hi rend="italic">Figure 8</hi>). </s><s n="s2.4;p96.124">The relationship was not linear and so required adjustment to compensate for any maxima that might not have been visible on the film that may have lead to incorrectly indexed <hi rend="italic">N</hi> values. </s><s n="s3.4;p96.124">By assuming that maxima are missing from the film before <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0051b-form.092"/> and <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0051b-form.093"/> and therefore translating the <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0051b-form.094"/> values up one at these two points before mapping <hi rend="italic">N</hi> values, a linear relationship became apparent. </s><s n="s4.4;p96.124">The line passes through the origin and therefore it can be assumed that this is the correct lattice type. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0051b-fig.006"><head rend="bold">Figure 8 - Finding the lattice parameter, <hi rend="italic">amix</hi>, for the mixed sample</head></figure><p n="p97.124"><s n="s1.1;p97.124">Using <hi rend="italic">equation 3</hi> again </s></p><p n="p98.124"><s n="s1.1;p98.124"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0051b-form.095"/> </s></p><p n="p99.124"><s n="s1.1;p99.124"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0051b-form.096"/> </s></p><p n="p100.124"><s n="s1.1;p100.124">The gradient of <hi rend="italic">figure 8</hi> was <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0051b-form.097"/><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0051b-form.098"/> and <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0051b-form.099"/> </s></p><p n="p101.124"><s n="s1.1;p101.124"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0051b-form.100"/>. </s></p><p n="p102.124"><s n="s1.1;p102.124">(For error analysis refer to §2.1.2) </s></p></div3><div3><head rend="underlined bold">3.2.2 Testing Vegard's Law</head><p n="p103.124"><s n="s1.1;p103.124">The known values for the lattice constants of the 2 components of the mixed sample are <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0051b-form.101"/> and <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0051b-form.102"/>. </s></p><p n="p104.124"><s n="s1.1;p104.124">These two values along with the <hi rend="italic">a</hi> value of the mixed sample, a <hi rend="sub">mix</hi>, were plotted on a graph of lattice parameter against concentration of KBr in the sample (figure 9). </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0051b-fig.007"><head rend="bold">Figure 9 - Testing Vegard's law for mixed sample</head></figure><p n="p105.124"><s n="s1.1;p105.124">As shown in figure 9 the Vegard line passes through the area bound by the error bars of <hi rend="italic">amix</hi> and so Vegard's Law holds true. </s></p></div3></div2><div2><head rend="bold">3.3 Discussion</head><p n="p106.124"><s n="s1.2;p106.124">Vegard's Law has been proven. </s><s n="s2.2;p106.124">For a compound with equal proportions of its two constituent substances, the lattice parameter is half way between the lattice parameters of the two substances that make up the mixture. </s></p><p n="p107.124"><s n="s1.2;p107.124">A systematic error may have occurred in the mass measurement such as if the scales were not tared and instead under read the masses. </s><s n="s2.2;p107.124">Although this would affect all masses that were measured by adding <hi rend="italic">X</hi>grams to the each mass measured, if taken as a proportion of the mass this would mean that the composition of KBr could be greater than 50% and so would translate the a <hi rend="sub">mix</hi> point horizontally, moving it closer to the line. </s></p><p n="p108.124"><s n="s1.3;p108.124">When the substances were combined by melting them in a test tube a small element of the glass may have also melted and combined with the substances. </s><s n="s2.3;p108.124">This would create a mixed sample with more than just KBr and KCl and so the theoretical a value would not lie on the line shown in figure 9. </s><s n="s3.3;p108.124">The experimental method could be improved by melting and forming the compound in a material with a much higher melting point than both KBr and KCl and so avoid any other unwanted contributions to the sample. </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">4. Conclusion</head><p n="p109.124"><s n="s1.1;p109.124">For sample 1 the lattice type was face-centred cubic and the lattice parameter was found to be </s></p><p n="p110.124"><s n="s1.1;p110.124"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0051b-form.103"/> </s></p><p n="p111.124"><s n="s1.2;p111.124">However it was not possible to identify the sample due to the fact that the lattice parameter was higher than the agreed value and so the true match did not appear in the list of possible substances in the ASTM index. </s><s n="s2.2;p111.124">When the ranges of <hi rend="italic">as1</hi> were increased to include the accepted value, the list of possible matches became too great to narrow down, even using other parameters such as colour and intensity patterns. </s></p><p n="p112.124"><s n="s1.1;p112.124">For sample 2 the lattice type was simple cubic and the lattice parameter was found to be </s></p><p n="p113.124"><s n="s1.1;p113.124"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0051b-form.104"/> </s></p><p n="p114.124"><s n="s1.1;p114.124">which is in agreement with the accepted value. </s></p><p n="p115.124"><s n="s1.1;p115.124">The sample was identified as sodium chlorate with the three lines of greatest intensity at </s></p><p n="p116.124"><s n="s1.1;p116.124"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0051b-form.105"/> </s></p><p n="p117.124"><s n="s1.1;p117.124"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0051b-form.106"/> </s></p><p n="p118.124"><s n="s1.1;p118.124"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0051b-form.107"/> </s></p><p n="p119.124"><s n="s1.1;p119.124">By analysis of high scattering angles, a more accurate value for a was obtained: </s></p><p n="p120.124"><s n="s1.1;p120.124"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0051b-form.108"/> </s></p><p n="p121.124"><s n="s1.1;p121.124">This result contained a considerably smaller error of 0.037% </s></p><p n="p122.124"><s n="s1.1;p122.124">For the mixed sample the lattice parameter was </s></p><p n="p123.124"><s n="s1.1;p123.124"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0051b-form.109"/> </s></p><p n="p124.124"><s n="s1.1;p124.124">The line connecting the two known lattice parameters crossed the error bounds for this point and hence confirmed Vegard's Law. </s></p></div1></body><back><div1 type="bibliography"><div2 type="bibliography"><head rend="bold">5. References</head><p> [1] - <seg type="URL" n="http://hyperphysics.phy-astr.gsu.edu/hbase/quantum/bragg.html"/></p><p>[2] - "X-ray Crystallography Powder Diffraction" Second Year Lab Script</p><p>[3] - B.D. Cullity, "Elements of X-ray Diffraction", Addison-Wesley, 2<hi rend="sup">nd</hi> ed. 1978</p></div2><div2 type="bibliography"><head rend="bold">6. Bibliography</head><p> "X-ray Crystallography Powder Diffraction" Second Year Lab Script </p><p>B.D. Cullity, "Elements of X-ray Diffraction", Addison-Wesley, 2<hi rend="sup">nd</hi> ed. 1978</p><p>H. Lipson and H. Steeple, "Interpretation of X-ray Diffraction Patterns", Taylor-Francis, 1970</p><p>A.J. Walton, "Three Phases of Matter", Clarendon Press-Oxford, 2<hi rend="sup">nd</hi> ed. 1983</p></div2></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
