<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_0053c" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Econometrics assignment 1</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">deleted: header: student number; footer: page numbers</note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">Evaluated as candidate compound assignment. Assigned to S3: assignment structured by questions: non-compound</note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">appendices: Summary of descriptive statistic; Correlation Matrix; data tables</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">2</p><p n="date">2005-12</p><p n="module title">Econometrics</p><p n="module code">EC226</p><p n="genre family">Methodology recount</p><p n="discipline">Economics</p><p n="disciplinary group">SS</p><p n="grade">M</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">2313</p><p n="number of s-units">126</p><p n="number of p">63</p><p n="number of tables">0</p><p n="number of figures">0</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">59</p><p n="number of lists">0</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">0</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">18.4</p><p n="average s-units per p">2.0</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">complex but non-compound assignment (see notesStmt for details)</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">f</p><p n="year of birth">1985</p><p n="first language">English</p><p n="education">OSA</p><p n="course">Economics, Politics and International Studies</p><p n="student ID">0053</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><docTitle><titlePart rend="bold">EC226: Econometrics assignment 1</titlePart></docTitle></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">Question 1</head><p n="p1.63"><s n="s1.5;p1.63">The sample data concerns the marks of 408 students obtained in first year statistics exam (<hi rend="italic">qtmark)</hi> and a plethora of variables which might affect the marks of these students majority aged 19. </s><s n="s2.5;p1.63">A summary of descriptive statistic in Appendix 1 shows that the average marks obtained was 64.9%. </s><s n="s3.5;p1.63">The median was also 65% while the minimum and maximum were 9% and 95% respectively. </s><s n="s4.5;p1.63">A standard deviation of 13.06 implies that majority of the results vary between 51.8% and 77.9%. </s><s n="s5.5;p1.63">The correlation matrix in Appendix 1 shows that some notable variables with positive effect on exam results include ability, attendance and time spent on revision while variables like expenditure on alcohol and coming from the UK are found to have a negative impact on <hi rend="italic">qtmark.</hi> </s></p><p n="p2.63"><s n="s1.9;p2.63">Amongst all the variables, ability was found to be the most significant variable affecting qtmark as demonstrated by its high correlation of 0.37. </s><s n="s2.9;p2.63">The fact that the ability of all students is normally distributed suggests a fair and adequate sample for regression. </s><s n="s3.9;p2.63">According to Romer<ref target="BAWE_0053c-ftnote.001"/>, generally students with good attendance perform better in examinations. </s><s n="s4.9;p2.63">This concurs with the strong positive correlation of 0.28 and 0.24 between <hi rend="italic">qtmarks</hi> and attending classes (<hi rend="italic">attc</hi>) and lectures (<hi rend="italic">attl</hi>) respectively in our data set. </s><s n="s5.9;p2.63">Most of the students attended an approximate mean of 80% for both lectures and classes. </s><s n="s6.9;p2.63">There is a slight disparity in the data set because there is a weak negative correlation of 0.006 between the proportion of revision lectures attended (<hi rend="italic">attr)</hi> and the test result. </s><s n="s7.9;p2.63">This could be attributed to the low mean proportion of revision lectures attended, 47%. </s><s n="s8.9;p2.63">Nevertheless, when <hi rend="italic">attr</hi> was tested<ref target="BAWE_0053c-ftnote.002"/> it was found to have a positive impact on qtmark. </s><s n="s9.9;p2.63">For students who have been consistently working hard, as evident from the number of A-grades obtained at A-level (<hi rend="italic">alevelsa</hi>) which is also positively related (correlation of 0.22) to <hi rend="italic">qtmark</hi>, the higher positive correlation of 0.091 compared to 0.06( <hi rend="italic">hrsqt1)</hi><ref target="BAWE_0053c-ftnote.003"/> proves that more time spent on revision (<hi rend="italic">hrsqt</hi>) would result in higher marks. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0053c-ftnote.001"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Romer, 1993,pg 171-173 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0053c-ftnote.002"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Referring to the model in question 2b which included the other 2 relevant variables-<hi rend="italic">ability</hi> and <hi rend="italic">hrsqt</hi> </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0053c-ftnote.003"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Where <hi rend="italic">hrsqt1</hi> refers to the hours spent working on statistics during week before exam </s></p></note><p n="p3.63"><s n="s1.4;p3.63">Some of the data do not appear to be very convincing because of the small sample size. </s><s n="s2.4;p3.63">There are only 126 observations as to whether a student has a home computer and this is only available for the year 2004.It would have been more useful to find out in addition to owning a computer, the number of hours spent on using the computer for statistics. </s><s n="s3.4;p3.63">There does not seem to be a simple explanation for the outliers in the scatter plots in Appendix 1 for the regression of <hi rend="italic">qtmark</hi> against variables like alcohol expenditure. </s><s n="s4.4;p3.63">However, their impact on the regression is not significant. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">Question 2a</head><p n="p4.63"><s n="s1.1;p4.63"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0053c-form.001"/> </s></p><p n="p5.63"><s n="s1.5;p5.63">First, restrict the sample to those having <hi rend="italic">ability</hi> and <hi rend="italic"> hrsqt</hi> to obtain a bivariate regression for these respective students only. </s><s n="s2.5;p5.63">Table 2.1 in Appendix 2 shows that there is a positive relationship between (<hi rend="italic">qtmark</hi>) mark in first year statistic exam and the (<hi rend="italic">attr</hi>) proportion of revision lectures attended; if attr increased by one percent then qtmark would increase by 0.002263 percent. </s><s n="s3.5;p5.63">If attr were zero, qtmark would be about 64.73999%.In addition, 0.0049% of the variation in qtmark is explained by attr because the R<formula notation="" id="BAWE_0053c-form.002"/> value is about 0.000049. </s><s n="s4.5;p5.63">In a bivariate model, the R <hi rend="sup">2</hi> value is a good measure for how good of a fit the model truly is; the higher the R <hi rend="sup">2</hi> value, the better the fit for the model. </s><s n="s5.5;p5.63">In this case we can see that this regression is not the best fit. </s></p><p n="p6.63"><s n="s1.9;p6.63">Next, test the null hypothesis that there is no relationship between <hi rend="italic">qtmark</hi> and <hi rend="italic">attr</hi>, that is, the true slope coefficient β<hi rend="sub">1</hi> = 0. </s><s n="s2.9;p6.63">Holding all other variables constant, the estimated value of coefficient β<hi rend="sub">1</hi> is 0.002263. </s><s n="s3.9;p6.63">Under the null hypothesis, we observe that the <hi rend="italic">t</hi>-value is 0.129684 and the <hi rend="italic">p</hi>-value of obtaining such a <hi rend="italic">t</hi>-value is 0.8969. </s><s n="s4.9;p6.63">In other words, accept the null hypothesis that <hi rend="italic">attr</hi> has no effect on <hi rend="italic">qtmark.</hi> </s><s n="s5.9;p6.63">Under the same null hypothesis that the true slope coefficient is zero, the <hi rend="italic">F</hi>-value is 0.016818. </s><s n="s6.9;p6.63">If we square the <hi rend="italic">t</hi>-value of the slope coefficient of <hi rend="italic">attr,</hi> we will see that this will be the <hi rend="italic">F</hi>-value. </s><s n="s7.9;p6.63">This shows the close relationship between the <hi rend="italic">t</hi> and the <hi rend="italic">F</hi> statistic. </s><s n="s8.9;p6.63">This can only be true when the degree of freedom for the <hi rend="italic">F</hi>-statistic is 1, which includes this particular regression. </s><s n="s9.9;p6.63">Hence we can see that at the 5% level, we do not reject the null hypothesis. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">Question 2b</head><p n="p7.63"><s n="s1.1;p7.63"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0053c-form.003"/> </s></p><p n="p8.63"><s n="s1.11;p8.63">In (2b), the variables <hi rend="italic">hrsqt and ability</hi> are independent variables and part of the regression. </s><s n="s2.11;p8.63">However, the sample is still restricted to students having both <hi rend="italic">hrsqt and ability -</hi> the number of observations are 347 students in both regressions. </s><s n="s3.11;p8.63">This multi-variate model is assumed to be linear in parameters. </s><s n="s4.11;p8.63">The coefficients of <hi rend="italic">ability, hrsqt</hi> and <hi rend="italic">attr</hi> are called partial regression coefficients. </s><s n="s5.11;p8.63">Table 2.2 in Appendix 2 shows that there is still a positive linear relationship between <hi rend="italic">qtmark</hi> and <hi rend="italic">attr</hi> because a 1% increase in <hi rend="italic">attr</hi> will result in a 0.105959% increase in <hi rend="italic">qtmark</hi>, given that all other explanatory variables <hi rend="italic">(hrsqt and ability)</hi> are held constant. </s><s n="s6.11;p8.63">However, the intercept has changed; if <hi rend="italic">ability, hrsqt and attr</hi> all equal to zero, <hi rend="italic">qtmark</hi> will be 36.82527%. </s><s n="s7.11;p8.63">The R <hi rend="sup">2</hi> has increased to 0.221924. </s><s n="s8.11;p8.63">As R <hi rend="sup">2</hi> is bounded by zero and one, the goodness of fit for this model is still relatively low. </s><s n="s9.11;p8.63">In this three-variable model, the multiple coefficient of determination R <hi rend="sup">2</hi> is the proportion of the variation in (this case) <hi rend="italic">qtmark</hi> explained by the variables ability, hrsqt and attr. </s><s n="s10.11;p8.63">This is an extension of the two-variable model in (2a). </s><s n="s11.11;p8.63">The multiple correlation R is simply the measure of the degree of association between qtmark and all the explanatory variables jointly. </s></p><div2><head rend="underlined">Hypothesis Testing</head><p n="p9.63"><s n="s1.1;p9.63">Ho: β<hi rend="sub">1</hi> = 0 </s></p><p n="p10.63"><s n="s1.1;p10.63">H <hi rend="sub">1</hi>: β<hi rend="sub">1 </hi>≠ 0 [2-sided test as <hi rend="italic">attr</hi> can affect <hi rend="italic">qtmark</hi> either way] </s></p><p n="p11.63"><s n="s1.1;p11.63">t = 5.356408, t <hi rend="sub">0.05,343</hi> = 1.96 </s></p><p n="p12.63"><s n="s1.1;p12.63">Therefore, reject Ho and conclude that <hi rend="italic">attr</hi> does have an effect on <hi rend="italic">qtmark</hi>, holding <hi rend="italic">ability</hi> and <hi rend="italic">hrsqt</hi> variables constant. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">Test for overall significance</head><p n="p13.63"><s n="s1.1;p13.63">Ho: β<hi rend="sub">1</hi>= β<hi rend="sub">2</hi>= β<hi rend="sub">3</hi> </s></p><p n="p14.63"><s n="s1.1;p14.63">H <hi rend="sub">1</hi>: β<hi rend="sub">j </hi>≠ 0; j <hi rend="sub">=1,2, 3</hi> </s></p><p n="p15.63"><s n="s1.1;p15.63">F = 32.61029, F <hi rend="sub">2, 343</hi> = 3.00 at 5% significance level </s></p><p n="p16.63"><s n="s1.1;p16.63">Therefore, reject Ho and conclude that the three regressors <hi rend="italic">ability, hrsqt and attr</hi> have an impact on <hi rend="italic">qtmark.</hi> </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">Question 2c</head><p n="p17.63"><s n="s1.1;p17.63"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0053c-form.004"/> </s></p><p n="p18.63"><s n="s1.1;p18.63">Where <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0053c-form.005"/>; <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0053c-form.006"/>; <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0053c-form.007"/> and the default is <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0053c-form.008"/><ref target="BAWE_0053c-ftnote.004"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0053c-ftnote.004"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Reason for choice of dummy variable range: conducted 25th, 50th, 75th and 100th percentile of <hi rend="italic">hrsqt</hi> to obtain 2, 3, 5 and 30 hours respectively. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">This is to have equal variation in each range to provide more accurate results for the respective dummy variables for the regression </s></p></note><p n="p19.63"><s n="s1.1;p19.63"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0053c-form.009"/> </s></p><p n="p20.63"><s n="s1.1;p20.63"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0053c-form.010"/> </s></p><p n="p21.63"><s n="s1.1;p21.63">F statistic= <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0053c-form.011"/><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0053c-form.012"/> </s></p><p n="p22.63"><s n="s1.1;p22.63">Therefore at the 5% significant level, do not reject <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0053c-form.013"/> and conclude that the dummy variables are not jointly significant to this regression. </s></p><p n="p23.63"><s n="s1.1;p23.63">Referring to the line graph in appendix 2, conclude that there is nonlinearity in the effect of <hi rend="italic">hrsqt</hi> on <hi rend="italic">qtmark.</hi> </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">Question 3</head><p n="p24.63"><s n="s1.1;p24.63">Restricted model: <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0053c-form.014"/> </s></p><p n="p25.63"><s n="s1.1;p25.63">Unrestricted model: <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0053c-form.015"/> </s></p><div2><head><hi rend="underlined">Test for constant differences</hi><ref target="BAWE_0053c-ftnote.005"/><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0053c-ftnote.005"><p n="pn1.1"> Table 3.1 showing the results of these regressions can be found in Appendix 3</p></note></head><p n="p26.63"><s n="s1.3;p26.63">Compared with the expected value of <hi rend="italic">qtmark</hi> in 2004 (which is about 38.12 marks), the expected value of <hi rend="italic">qtmark</hi> of students of the year 2002 is about -5.2 marks, for an actual mark of about 32.92 marks. </s><s n="s2.3;p26.63">Similarly, for students of the year 2003, the expected mark was lower by 7.19 marks, for an actual mark of 30.93 marks. </s><s n="s3.3;p26.63">Hence conclude that differences in <hi rend="italic">qtmarks</hi> are not constant between the subsample of 2004 students and previous years' students. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">Interpreting coefficients</head><p n="p27.63"><s n="s1.2;p27.63">Referring to table 3.1 in Appendix 3, <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0053c-form.016"/>, <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0053c-form.017"/> and <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0053c-form.018"/> demonstrate that a one unit change in <hi rend="italic">ability</hi>, 1% change in class attendance(<hi rend="italic">attc</hi>) and one unit increase in the number of A-grades obtained(<hi rend="italic">alevelsa</hi>), will result in 0.56%, 0.16% and 1.53% increase in <hi rend="italic">qtmark</hi> respectively. </s><s n="s2.2;p27.63">Holding <hi rend="italic">ability, attc</hi> and <hi rend="italic"> alevelsa</hi> constant,<formula notation="" id="BAWE_0053c-form.019"/>(-5.2) and <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0053c-form.020"/>(-7.19) are the differential intercept coefficients and they measure the change in the expected value of <hi rend="italic">qtmark</hi> for 2002 and 2003 respondents respectively relative to 2004 respondents. </s></p></div2><div2><head><hi rend="underlined">Test for significance of dummy variables</hi><ref target="BAWE_0053c-ftnote.006"/><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0053c-ftnote.006"><p n="pn1.1"> Results for the regression can be found in table 3.1 n appendix 3</p></note></head><p n="p28.63"><s n="s1.1;p28.63"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0053c-form.021"/> </s></p><p n="p29.63"><s n="s1.1;p29.63"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0053c-form.022"/> </s></p><p n="p30.63"><s n="s1.1;p30.63">F statistic= <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0053c-form.023"/><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0053c-form.024"/> </s></p><p n="p31.63"><s n="s1.1;p31.63">Therefore at the 5% significance level, reject <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0053c-form.025"/> and conclude that the dummy variables have a significant impact on the regression. </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">Question 4</head><p n="p32.63"><s n="s1.1;p32.63"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0053c-form.026"/> </s></p><p n="p33.63"><s n="s1.3;p33.63">The results from the three regression (in Appendix 4) showed that in except in 2004, the number of A-grades obtained at A-level had the largest effect( compared to other variables like ability and proportion of class attended) on the marks obtained in first year statistics exam. </s><s n="s2.3;p33.63">The coefficient on ability was the largest in year 2002, implying that an increase in ability had the greatest effect on marks for the 2002 respondents. </s><s n="s3.3;p33.63">On the other hand, an increase in class attendance had the greatest impact on marks for the 2003 respondents. </s></p><div2><head rend="underlined">Chow test</head><p n="p34.63"><s n="s1.1;p34.63">Restricted model: <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0053c-form.027"/> </s></p><p n="p35.63"><s n="s1.1;p35.63">Unrestricted model: year 2002: <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0053c-form.028"/> </s></p><p n="p36.63"><s n="s1.1;p36.63">Year 2003: <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0053c-form.029"/> </s></p><p n="p37.63"><s n="s1.1;p37.63">Year 2004: <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0053c-form.030"/> </s></p><p n="p38.63"><s n="s1.1;p38.63"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0053c-form.031"/> </s></p><p n="p39.63"><s n="s1.1;p39.63"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0053c-form.032"/> </s></p><p n="p40.63"><s n="s1.1;p40.63">F statistic=<formula notation="" id="BAWE_0053c-form.033"/>, <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0053c-form.034"/> </s></p><p n="p41.63"><s n="s1.1;p41.63">At the 5% significance level, reject <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0053c-form.035"/> and conclude that the coefficients are not constant across the three subsamples. </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">Question 5</head><p n="p42.63"><s n="s1.1;p42.63">Restricted model<ref target="BAWE_0053c-ftnote.007"/>: <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0053c-form.036"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0053c-ftnote.007"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">In this restricted model, a pooled regression was performed </s></p></note><p n="p43.63"><s n="s1.1;p43.63">Unrestricted model: year 2002: <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0053c-form.037"/> </s></p><p n="p44.63"><s n="s1.1;p44.63">Year 2003: <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0053c-form.038"/> </s></p><p n="p45.63"><s n="s1.1;p45.63">Year 2004: <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0053c-form.039"/> </s></p><p n="p46.63"><s n="s1.1;p46.63"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0053c-form.040"/> </s></p><p n="p47.63"><s n="s1.1;p47.63"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0053c-form.041"/> </s></p><p n="p48.63"><s n="s1.1;p48.63">F statistic= <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0053c-form.042"/>, <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0053c-form.043"/> </s></p><p n="p49.63"><s n="s1.1;p49.63">Therefore at the 5% significance level, do not reject <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0053c-form.044"/> and conclude that the slope coefficients are constant across the three regression equations. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">Question 6</head><p n="p50.63"><s n="s1.7;p50.63">The attributes of a good model<ref target="BAWE_0053c-ftnote.008"/> are (i) Parsimony- a model can never completely capture the reality; some amount of abstraction or simplification is inevitable in any model building. </s><s n="s2.7;p50.63">The Occam's razor or the principle of parsimony states that a model be kept as simple as possible. (ii) </s><s n="s3.7;p50.63">Identifiabilty- for a given set of data, the estimated parameters must have unique values. (iii) </s><s n="s4.7;p50.63">Goodness of fit- Since the basic thrust of regression analysis is to explain as much of the variation in the dependent variable as possible by explanatory variables included in the model, a model is judged good if this explanation, as measured by the adjusted Ris as high as possible.(iv)Theoretical consistency- No matter how high the goodness of fit measures, a model may not be judged good if one or more coefficients have the wrong signs. </s><s n="s5.7;p50.63">In constructing a model, we need to have some theoretical underpinning to it. (v) </s><s n="s6.7;p50.63">Predictive power- Milton Friedman, the Nobel laureate notes: "the only relevant test of the validity of a hypothesis model is comparison of its prediction with experience". </s><s n="s7.7;p50.63">Taking into account the above five attributes of a good model, my statistically preferred model for <hi rend="italic">qtmark</hi> is as follows: </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0053c-ftnote.008"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Damodar Gujarati, 1999, pg406 </s></p></note><p n="p51.63"><s n="s1.1;p51.63"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0053c-form.045"/> </s></p><p n="p52.63"><s n="s1.1;p52.63">where <hi rend="italic">Mgrad</hi> is split into 4 dummy variables <hi rend="italic">: mgrad1 (default) = grade A and IB 7, mgrad2 = grade B and IB 6, mgrad3 = grade C or D and IB 5 or 4, and mgradnone = No maths/stats</hi> </s></p><div2><head rend="underlined">Justification for model</head><p n="p53.63"><s n="s1.5;p53.63">The variables <hi rend="italic"> Age, computer, printer, sch6fc, schmix, expfood, expcd, exprent, female, expalc, topb, domestic (>2 siblings and paruni=0),domestic1(siblings&lt;2 and paruni>=1), domestic2 (>2siblings or paruni=0)</hi><ref target="BAWE_0053c-ftnote.009"/>,were excluded from the model as their t statistic indicated that they are insignificant to the determination of <hi rend="italic">qtmark.</hi> </s><s n="s2.5;p53.63">Imperfect multicollinearity occurs when there is a very high correlation between two or more explanatory variables. </s><s n="s3.5;p53.63">Therefore the variables <hi rend="italic">hrsall, attc and alevels</hi> were excluded because of their high correlation with <hi rend="italic">hrsqt, attl and alevelsa</hi> respectively. </s><s n="s4.5;p53.63">With multicollinearity, our application of Ordinary least Square (OLS) to the equation is no longer BLUE. The standard error on the coefficient estimate would become increasingly larger. </s><s n="s5.5;p53.63">As a result, the t-ratios on the coefficient estimates will be smaller and we are more likely to accept any null hypothesis (whether true or not).The variable <hi rend="italic">course</hi> was excluded though it is statistically significant because when tested, its coefficient was found to be -1.39 which is inconsistent with theory as we would expect that the study of a subject related to economics to have a positive impact on marks for statistics exam. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0053c-ftnote.009"><p n="pn1.1"><s rend="sup" n="s1.1;pn1.1"> conclude that domestic factors insignificant </s></p></note></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">Interpreting results</head><p n="p54.63"><s n="s1.2;p54.63">As seen from question 2a and 2b, omission of relevant variables <hi rend="italic">ability</hi> and <hi rend="italic">hrsqt</hi> would result in a bias estimator. </s><s n="s2.2;p54.63">Our model shows a unit increase in <hi rend="italic">ability</hi> and <hi rend="italic">hrsqt</hi> increases qtmark by 0.71(<formula notation="" id="BAWE_0053c-form.046"/>) and 0.45 (<formula notation="" id="BAWE_0053c-form.047"/>) respectively. </s></p><p n="p55.63"><s n="s1.1;p55.63"><hi rend="bold">Bias</hi> = <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0053c-form.048"/> </s></p><p n="p56.63"><s n="s1.1;p56.63"><hi rend="bold">Bias</hi> = <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0053c-form.049"/> </s></p><p n="p57.63"><s n="s1.1;p57.63"><hi rend="bold">Bias</hi> = <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0053c-form.050"/> </s></p><p n="p58.63"><s n="s1.9;p58.63">Differential intercepts <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0053c-form.051"/> and <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0053c-form.052"/> are statistically significant (shown in question 3) suggesting that the average <hi rend="italic">qtmark</hi> differs across the three years. </s><s n="s2.9;p58.63">Therefore they are included to show that <hi rend="italic"> qtmark</hi> in 2002 and 2003 is lower than the default year (2004) by 3.96 and 6.69 respectively. </s><s n="s3.9;p58.63">In this regression model, it is assumed that the three regression lines are parallel regression lines, hence only the intercept and not the slope coefficient varies among the three years (this is the conclusion derived from questions 4 and 5). </s><s n="s4.9;p58.63">This implies that the other variables in the model like <hi rend="italic">ability</hi> and <hi rend="italic">attl</hi> are constant across the three years.Mgrad1 is chosen to be the default so that the coefficients of the other three dummy variables are comparable to 'smart' students in relation to <hi rend="italic">qtmark</hi>. </s><s n="s5.9;p58.63">The results in Table 6.1 in Appendix 6 show that <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0053c-form.053"/>,k <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0053c-form.054"/> and <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0053c-form.055"/> are all significant (high t-statistic) and we can conclude that students with better math/stats grades will have higher <hi rend="italic">qtmark.</hi> </s><s n="s6.9;p58.63">Devadoss and Foltz's report<ref target="BAWE_0053c-ftnote.010"/> proposes that students attending a fee paying school (<hi rend="italic">schfee</hi>) would have achieve higher results as there is a cost involved (school fees) in not studying. </s><s n="s7.9;p58.63">A possible explanation for the negative coefficient (-2.57) on <hi rend="italic">schfee</hi> could be lesser time for studying because the student has to work in order to pay the school fees. </s><s n="s8.9;p58.63">Another interesting result from this regression is that UK students are found to have lower qtmarks (<formula notation="" id="BAWE_0053c-form.056"/>). </s><s n="s9.9;p58.63">This might be because their school fees are subsidized or that they have a better aptitude for other subjects like language and literature. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0053c-ftnote.010"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Devadoss, S. and Foltz J, 1996, pg 504 </s></p></note></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">Test for overall significance</head><p n="p59.63"><s n="s1.1;p59.63"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0053c-form.057"/> </s></p><p n="p60.63"><s n="s1.1;p60.63"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0053c-form.058"/> </s></p><p n="p61.63"><s n="s1.1;p61.63">F statistic =13.56 ; F <hi rend="sub">12, 298</hi> = 1.79 at 5% significance level </s></p><p n="p62.63"><s n="s1.1;p62.63">Therefore at the 5% significance level, do not reject <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0053c-form.059"/>. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">Conclusion</head><p n="p63.63"><s n="s1.3;p63.63">When a Ramsey RESET test and White's Heteroscedasticity test was performed on the above equation (Appendix 6) it was found to show no evidence of omitted variables or incorrect functional form. </s><s n="s2.3;p63.63">Therefore this is my preferred model by estimation using the OLS method. </s><s n="s3.3;p63.63">Congruent with my personal education experience, I can conclude that in addition to ability, consistent effort plays an important role in achieving good results. </s></p></div2></div1></body><back><div1 type="appendix"><head rend="bold">Appendix 1</head><p/></div1><div1 type="bibliography"><head rend="underlined">Bibliography</head><p>Brauer wt al (1994), "Should class attendance be mandatory", <hi rend="underlined italic">Journal of Economic Perspectives,</hi> 205-15</p><p>Christopher Dougherty, "simple regression analysis", "Covariance, variance and correlation", "Dummy Variables" and "multiple regression analysis" in <hi rend="underlined italic">Introduction to Econometrics</hi>, second edition, Oxford, Oxford University Press</p><p>Damodar Gujarati, "Multiple regression: estimation and hypothesis", " Model selection: Criteria and tests" in <hi rend="underlined italic">Essentials of econometrics</hi>, second edition, London, McGraw Hill</p><p>Devadoss, S. and Foltz, J (1996), "Evaluation of factors influencing student class attendance and performance", <hi rend="underlined italic">American journal of Agricultural Economics</hi>, 18,199-507</p></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
