<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_0055f" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Assignment III</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">The document has a title page which contains:
document title
title part</note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">deleted: page border!
appendix contains extensive data tables
</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">1</p><p n="date">2005-04</p><p n="module title">Computing &amp; Data Analysis</p><p n="module code">EC125</p><p n="genre family">Methodology recount</p><p n="discipline">Economics</p><p n="disciplinary group">SS</p><p n="grade">M</p><p n="number of authors">4</p><p n="number of words">2153</p><p n="number of s-units">87</p><p n="number of p">24</p><p n="number of tables">0</p><p n="number of figures">11</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">0</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">0</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">24.7</p><p n="average s-units per p">3.6</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">f</p><p n="year of birth">1986</p><p n="first language">Turkish</p><p n="education">OSA</p><p n="course">Philosophy, Politics and Economics</p><p n="student ID">0055</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><titlePart rend="bold">UNIVERSITY OF <name type="university"/></titlePart><docTitle><titlePart rend="bold">COMPUTING AND DATA ANALYSIS Assignment III</titlePart></docTitle><titlePart rend="bold">Candidate Numbers: <name type="student ID"/>, <name type="student ID"/>, <name type="student ID"/>, <name type="student ID"/> April 22, 2005</titlePart></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Introduction</head><p n="p1.24"><s n="s1.4;p1.24">This report aims to analyze the relationship between GDP and imports of goods and services of three countries with different economic status. </s><s n="s2.4;p1.24">The countries are - United States (a developed country), India (a developing country) and Sierra Leone (a less developed country). </s><s n="s3.4;p1.24">Countries with different economic status are chosen in order to facilitate the differentiation of the variation between the characteristics of countries with different GDP levels and growth rates. </s><s n="s4.4;p1.24">For example, a developed country, the US, has much higher imports compared to a developing and less developed country, although the level of its imports constitutes only to a small part of its total GDP. This difference in imports portrays the GDP gap between a developed country and a less developed country. </s></p><p n="p2.24"><s n="s1.4;p2.24">GDP and imports are chosen as indicators of economic development. </s><s n="s2.4;p2.24">It is expected that countries with high GDP levels will also have high import levels, however not high enough to drive the country into a trade deficit. </s><s n="s3.4;p2.24">Whilst a less developed country is expected to show unstable levels of imports (because of an unstable economy and unstable exchange rates) and thus will be expected to show signs of having trade deficits. </s><s n="s4.4;p2.24">The data have been further investigated by applying correlation and regression analysis between GDP and import figures of each country. </s></p><p n="p3.24"><s n="s1.3;p3.24">The GDP and import values are ranged from 1970 to 2003, which have been acquired from the World Bank database<ref target="BAWE_0055f-ftnote.001"/>. </s><s n="s2.3;p3.24">The GDP values and import values are in US dollar 1995 constant prices, which implies that the values between 1970 and 2003 have accounted for inflation, and thus have been converted to real GDP and real import figures. </s><s n="s3.3;p3.24">Likewise, to make our data comparable with each other, the GDP and import values of all three countries are in a single currency, US dollars. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0055f-ftnote.001"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Economic and Social data Service, World Bank, <hi rend="underlined">World Development Indicators</hi> (November 2004) </s></p></note></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Economic Theory:</head><p n="p4.24"><s n="s1.6;p4.24">According to economic theory imports can depend on multiple factors such as the level and dynamics of domestic income of economic integration. </s><s n="s2.6;p4.24">However, with respect to the aim of our analysis the emphasis will merely lie on the relationship between Gross Domestic Product (GDP) and imports. </s><s n="s3.6;p4.24">By definition, GDP is seen to be a measure of aggregate output in the national income accounts equalling the sum of incomes earned domestically by both nationals and foreign citizens working in the country<ref target="BAWE_0055f-ftnote.002"/>. </s><s n="s4.6;p4.24">In relation to imports, GDP has to consider the level and dynamics of the GDP components and thus differentiate between them i.e. investment, consumption, public expenditure and exports<ref target="BAWE_0055f-ftnote.003"/>. </s><s n="s5.6;p4.24">However, economic theory - ceteris paribus - suggests that when GDP rises imports rise as well, for example because disposable income increases. </s><s n="s6.6;p4.24">In real life on the other hand, there are many exceptions to this rule. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0055f-ftnote.002"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Blanchard, Olivier. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0055f-ftnote.003"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Piana, Valentino. </s><s rend="underlined" n="s2.2;pn1.1">Imports. </s></p></note><p n="p5.24"><s n="s1.10;p5.24">Overtime the general trend GDP seems to follow is a steadily increasing one. </s><s n="s2.10;p5.24">The reasoning behind this is the following: as free market economies aim to maximize GDP they will produce at least the same output in subsequent years as they have in previous ones. </s><s n="s3.10;p5.24">In addition however they will aim to increase the level of output by improving the factors of production, i.e. the standard of the machinery by expanding industries or creating new ones. </s><s n="s4.10;p5.24">Therefore, overtime GDP will - due to the improvements that are likely to be made - increase. </s><s n="s5.10;p5.24">The extent to which this is the case varies in different economies. </s><s n="s6.10;p5.24">This reasoning however, does not apply to economies in a state of emergency such as civil wars or natural disasters (as is the case in many less developed countries i.e. </s><s n="s7.10;p5.24">Sierra Leone). </s><s n="s8.10;p5.24">This is due to the devastation of the economy. </s><s n="s9.10;p5.24">Similarly, imports can be said to generally be increasing over time. </s><s n="s10.10;p5.24">This can be justified by referring to the way that GDP determines the level of imports, meaning given that (for the above reasons) GDP increases overtime, imports must also rise overtime. </s></p><p n="p6.24"><s n="s1.3;p6.24">However, since imports have a negative effect on the current account of the balance of payments, governments often choose to impose import restrictions or protectionist measures such as the introduction of value added taxes or quotas. </s><s n="s2.3;p6.24">This coupled with the general national attitude towards foreign goods may manipulate the consumer in such a way that the above relationship does not apply. </s><s n="s3.3;p6.24">Yet, as long as free market forces operate without governmental or other intervention, it can be said that imports as well as GDP increase overtime. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Data Analysis:</head><div2><head rend="italic">U.S.A. </head><p n="p7.24"><s n="s1.1;p7.24">Investigating the relationship between GDP and imports in the US we find our expectations are realized. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0055f-fig.001"><head>Figure 1</head></figure><p n="p8.24"><s n="s1.6;p8.24">Figure 1 illustrates that in the US the relationship between GDP and imports is positive, as you would expect. </s><s n="s2.6;p8.24">Although GDP increases by larger amounts than imports, the two correlate closely. </s><s n="s3.6;p8.24">This is substantiated by a high correlation coefficient: 0.969175. </s><s n="s4.6;p8.24">By definition, the correlation coefficient is a measure of the interdependence of two variables that ranges in value from −1 to +1, indicating perfect negative correlation at −1, absence of correlation at zero, and perfect positive correlation at +1<ref target="BAWE_0055f-ftnote.004"/>. </s><s n="s5.6;p8.24">The calculated figure (0.969175) therefore illustrates that there is a causal and reciprocal relationship between imports and GDP in the US over this period. </s><s n="s6.6;p8.24">This is because as income and output increase, so does spending and therefore the demand for imports both by consumers (with more disposable income) and by firms (with a greater demand for capital and materials to invest). </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0055f-ftnote.004"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Answers.com. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1"><hi rend="underlined">Correlation Coefficient</hi>. </s></p></note><p n="p9.24"><s n="s1.2;p9.24">Further evidence of this is given by the line fit plot (see figure 2). </s><s n="s2.2;p9.24">A line fit plot will draw scatter plots of each independent variable on the x-axis, and the predicted and actual values of the dependent variable on the y axis<ref target="BAWE_0055f-ftnote.005"/>, thus showing how theory and reality are linked </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0055f-ftnote.005"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Miles, Jeremy, <hi rend="underlined">Applying Regression and Correlation: A Guide for Students and Researchers</hi> </s></p></note><figure id="BAWE_0055f-fig.002"><head>Figure 2</head></figure><p n="p10.24"><s n="s1.3;p10.24">This is further clarification that the two variables are as closely related in reality, as they are in theory, and that the relationship is positive. </s><s n="s2.3;p10.24">In order to examine the accuracy of this model further we can use the residual plot. </s><s n="s3.3;p10.24">A residual plot (see figure 3) will draw scatter plots of each independent variable on the x-axis, and the residual on the y-axis<ref target="BAWE_0055f-ftnote.006"/>, therefore showing more clearly the discrepancy between the model and reality. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0055f-ftnote.006"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">ibid </s></p></note><figure id="BAWE_0055f-fig.003"><head>Figure 3</head></figure><p n="p11.24"><s n="s1.3;p11.24">What we find is that the residuals are very small, the model fits closely, but they are not constant and neither are they equally dispersed. </s><s n="s2.3;p11.24">The reason for this may be that the line fit is exactly that, a line, in reality things are unlikely to happen in a linear manner, however this does not explain the reason we see a pattern; values below, then above, then below. </s><s n="s3.3;p11.24">There is correlation between the residuals, the goodness of fit of the last value will affect the next because they are happening over time, they will be influenced by previous events, the higher the GDP value in one year the higher the value of predicted GDP the next year </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="italic">India</head><figure id="BAWE_0055f-fig.004"><head>Figure 4</head></figure><p n="p12.24"><s n="s1.4;p12.24">In India we find a similar situation to that which we found in the US. Imports and GDP are positively correlated, in fact marginally more so with a correlation coefficient of: 0.979607. </s><s n="s2.4;p12.24">We see that the line of fit and residual plot are again substantive to this conclusion. </s><s n="s3.4;p12.24">The line of fit is closely followed by actual values and the residual plot shows small variance. </s><s n="s4.4;p12.24">It appears that once more imports and GDP are linked in the way our model predicted. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0055f-fig.005"><head>Figure 5</head></figure><figure id="BAWE_0055f-fig.006"><head>Figure 6</head></figure></div2><div2><head rend="italic">Sierra Leone</head><p n="p13.24"><s n="s1.1;p13.24">In contrast to our previous observations we find a very different situation in Sierra Leone. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0055f-fig.007"><head>Figure 7</head></figure><p n="p14.24"><s n="s1.1;p14.24">As Figure 7 portrays, there appears to be no consistent relationship between imports and GDP. The correlation coefficient is low; 0.133331 </s></p><p n="p15.24"><s n="s1.1;p15.24">The line of fit (see Figure 8) illustrates how widely dispersed predicted and actual values are, and how the relationship is only just positive (very small upward slope). </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0055f-fig.008"><head>Figure 8</head></figure><p n="p16.24"><s n="s1.5;p16.24">What is also interesting is how different the figures are in size in comparison to the other two countries we have investigated this may be the key to understanding the lack of success of our model for Sierra Leone. </s><s n="s2.5;p16.24">Sierra Leone was ranked 177 <hi rend="sup">th</hi> out of 177 countries for their HDI (Human development Index-a measure combining three dimensions of development - longevity (life expectancy at birth), knowledge (adult literacy and mean years of schooling), and income<ref target="BAWE_0055f-ftnote.007"/>. </s><s n="s3.5;p16.24">Clearly this is going to cause a severe hindrance to economic growth and development. </s><s n="s4.5;p16.24">The civil war in Sierra Leone from 1991-2002, can provide an explanation for the downturn in GDP since 1991. </s><s n="s5.5;p16.24">Together with the general hampering of economic development specifically the UN sanctions imposed on Sierra Leone in 1997 caused a 20% drop in GDP, bauxite and rutile mines (main manufacturing outputs) have been shut down by civil strife. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0055f-ftnote.007"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Canadian International Development Agency <hi rend="underlined">Definitions</hi> </s></p></note><p n="p17.24"><s n="s1.5;p17.24">The path imports has taken is less easily explained, there has been a generally steady decline in imports, after the civil war this is explained by the fall in GDP but previously other factors were at play. </s><s n="s2.5;p17.24">The essential cause of the downward trend in imports is explained by the fall in purchasing power. </s><s n="s3.5;p17.24">In order to import money is required and money is earned through exports, if exports decrease then so does your power to purchase. </s><s n="s4.5;p17.24">There has been a fall in exports over this period, this is because Sierra Leone's main export, diamonds, is increasingly exported illegally, (this trend was accelerated by the rebel occupation of the diamond production area, during the civil war) they therefore earn the country no official money, imports have, as a consequence been falling. </s><s n="s5.5;p17.24">This illustrates the importance of other factors on imports, in addition to GDP. The case of Sierra Leone is especially interesting because it is an under developed country, other factors are often weighted in their importance in these types of situations, where society and economy is unstable. </s></p></div2><div2><head>Comparison Between Nations</head><p n="p18.24"><s n="s1.6;p18.24">We are not only interested in the relationship of GDP and imports within countries but also how each country's relationships compare with each other. </s><s n="s2.6;p18.24">One of the clearest indicators of this is the difference in the countries correlation coefficient for GDP and imports. </s><s n="s3.6;p18.24">As we saw previously GDP and imports are very closely correlated in the USA and in India with correlation coefficients 0,969 and 0,979 respectively. </s><s n="s4.6;p18.24">These are in stark contrast to the correlation between the variables in Sierra Leone which stands at 0,133. </s><s n="s5.6;p18.24">This difference can be due to multiple factors, such as the stability in the economies of India and the USA compared to the unstable economy of Sierra Leone where external factors hinder the functioning of economic rationale. </s><s n="s6.6;p18.24">This suggests that in an economy where there are no adverse external factors GDP and imports will be correlated closely. </s></p><p n="p19.24"><s n="s1.1;p19.24">Comparatively the size of the GDPs which we are examining is very informative. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0055f-fig.009"><head>Figure 9 </head></figure><p n="p20.24"><s n="s1.2;p20.24">In the 2003, where the difference is at its greatest, the GDP of the USA is exceeds that of India by 8,9 trillion US$. </s><s n="s2.2;p20.24">At the same point in time the GDP of India is over half a trillion US$ greater then that of Sierra Leone. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0055f-fig.010"><head>Figure 10</head></figure><p n="p21.24"><s n="s1.7;p21.24">This emphasises the vast difference in GDP for these countries. </s><s n="s2.7;p21.24">GDP among other things is an indicator of the level of economic development experienced in a country. </s><s n="s3.7;p21.24">According to the Human Developed Index the USA is ranked 8 <hi rend="sup">th</hi>, while India holds the 127 <hi rend="sup">th</hi> place and Sierra Leone is at the bottom of the list at placing number 177<ref target="BAWE_0055f-ftnote.008"/>. </s><s n="s4.7;p21.24">Another reason for the difference in GDP is the area of the countries. </s><s n="s5.7;p21.24">The USA's area is 9,631,418 sq. km.<ref target="BAWE_0055f-ftnote.009"/> compared to India's 3,287,590 sq. km. </s><ref target="BAWE_0055f-ftnote.010"/><s n="s6.7;p21.24">and Sierra Leone's 71,740 sq km<ref target="BAWE_0055f-ftnote.011"/>. </s><s n="s7.7;p21.24">This has obvious effects on the amount of output that a country can experience and thus its GDP. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0055f-ftnote.008"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Human Development Index </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0055f-ftnote.009"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">CIA World Factbook <hi rend="underlined">United States</hi> </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0055f-ftnote.010"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">ibid </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0055f-ftnote.011"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">ibid </s></p></note><p n="p22.24"><s n="s1.1;p22.24">When examining the amount of imports for these countries we once again see differences between nations. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0055f-fig.011"><head>Figure 11 </head></figure><p n="p23.24"><s n="s1.2;p23.24">In the period of time investigated, USA's imports have increased by 1,3 trillion US$, while the imports in India have only increased by 78 thousands of million of US$ and Sierra Leone experienced a decrease in imports by 500 million US$. </s><s n="s2.2;p23.24">The great difference in these figures is partially due to the great difference in the countries GDPs but also due to the stability in the countries. </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Conclusion:</head><p n="p24.24"><s n="s1.6;p24.24">After all, our analysis makes it obvious that there is a positive relationship between the two economic figures under discussion, GDP and imports. </s><s n="s2.6;p24.24">Generally, GDP tends to increase over time, so do imports. </s><s n="s3.6;p24.24">As far as our empirical data is concerned, this is the case with respect to the USA and India. </s><s n="s4.6;p24.24">Sierra Leone however, seems to be an exception as there is no constant correlation between the two economic indicators. </s><s n="s5.6;p24.24">Therefore, in conclusion it can be said that one needs to differentiate between the state of an economy when applying economic theory. </s><s n="s6.6;p24.24">In this case, this refers to the fact that a less developed, unstable country like Sierra Leone does not follow economic theory that developed and developing countries follow. </s></p></div1></body><back><div1 type="bibliography"><head rend="bold">References:</head><p>Anderson, David R, Sweeney, Dennis J, Williams, Thomas A, <hi rend="underlined">Essentials of statistics for business and economics</hi>, South-Western, Thomson Learning. (2003) "Simple Linear Regression" Chap. 12, p.480, </p><p>Blanchard, Olivier. <hi rend="underlined">Macroeconomics</hi> 3rd edition. U.S.A.: Prentice Hall. (2003) Glossary G-4</p><p>Answers.com. <hi rend="underlined">Correlation Coefficient</hi>. (accessed 19/04/05) &lt;<seg type="URL" n="http://www.answers.com/correlation+coefficient&amp;r=67"/>></p><p>Canadian International Development Agency <hi rend="underlined">Definitions</hi> (accessed 19/04/05)</p><p>&lt;<seg type="URL" n="http://www.acdicida.gc.ca/CIDAWEB/webcountry.nsf/VLUDocEn/SierraLeone-Factsataglance#def"/>></p><p>CIA World Factbook <hi rend="underlined">United States</hi> (accessed 20/04/05) </p><p>&lt;<seg type="URL" n="http://www.cia.gov/cia/publications/factbook/geos/us.html"/>></p><p>Human Development Index (accessed 20/04/05) &lt;<seg type="URL" n="http://hdr.undp.org/reports/global/2004/pdf/hdr04_HDI.pdf"/>></p><p>Miles, Jeremy, <hi rend="underlined">Applying Regression and Correlation: A Guide for Students and Researchers</hi>, Sage. (accessed 20/04/05) &lt;<seg type="URL" n="http://www.jeremymiles.co.uk/regressionbook/extras/appendix2/excel/"/>></p><p>Piana, Valentino. <hi rend="underlined">Imports</hi> (accessed 19/04/05)</p><p>&lt;<seg type="URL" n="http://www.economicswebinstitute.org/glossary/imports.htm#determinants"/>> </p><p>World Bank, Economic and Social data Service, <hi rend="underlined">World Development Indicators</hi> (Nov 2004), (accessed 20/04/05) &lt;<seg type="URL" n="http://esds.mcc.ac.uk/wds_wb/ReportFolders/reportfolders.aspx"/>></p></div1><div1 type="appendix"><head rend="bold">APPENDIX</head><p/></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
