<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_0057f" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Thomas Nagel and the Unity of Consciousness</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note/></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">2</p><p n="date">2005-04</p><p n="module title">Philosophy of Mind I</p><p n="module code">PH240</p><p n="genre family">Essay</p><p n="discipline">Philosophy</p><p n="disciplinary group">AH</p><p n="grade">M</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">4210</p><p n="number of s-units">167</p><p n="number of p">28</p><p n="number of tables">0</p><p n="number of figures">0</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">0</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">7</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">25.2</p><p n="average s-units per p">6.0</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">m</p><p n="year of birth">1983</p><p n="first language">Swedish</p><p n="education">OSA</p><p n="course">Philosophy and Psychology</p><p n="student ID">0057</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><docTitle><titlePart>Thomas Nagel and the Unity of Consciousness</titlePart></docTitle><titlePart><name type="student name"/> April 2005</titlePart></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="section"><head>Introduction</head><p n="p1.28"><s n="s1.6;p1.28">The gradual realization that mind is reducible to brain does not just provide us with an organ that needs to be accommodated in any working theory of the mind - an increasing understanding of the brain also promises to rid us of old misconceptions about the nature of the mind. </s><s n="s2.6;p1.28">But what if a feature of the mind that is being called into question by scientific findings is so integral and intuitively certain to us that we feel disinclined to abandon it even in the face of contradictory experimental data? </s><s n="s3.6;p1.28">Thomas Nagel (1971) argues that in such an event we must consider whether we have in fact encountered evidence that the mind is <hi rend="italic">not</hi> reducible to the brain. </s><s n="s4.6;p1.28">An example will help clarify the argument: imagine that it is discovered that once every year each human nervous system on the planet temporarily shuts down, leaving the brain completely void of activity, only to return to an active state some thirty seconds later<ref target="BAWE_0057f-ftnote.001"/>. </s><s n="s5.6;p1.28">Such a discovery would come as a blessing to philosophers of a holistic disposition who fight what they consider unwarranted forms of reductionism in philosophy of mind, because here would be direct proof that the mind is irreducible to just brain processes. </s><s n="s6.6;p1.28">I shall refer to such findings as <hi rend="italic">conflicting data</hi>. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0057f-ftnote.001"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">If the specific time of the annual freeze is different for each nervous system it is not <hi rend="italic">impossible</hi> that such a phenomena is being overlooked. </s></p></note><p n="p2.28"><s n="s1.8;p2.28">The present essay is a comment on Nagel's <hi rend="italic">'Brain Bisection and the Unity of Consciousness'</hi> (1971) in which he argues that the data relating to patients who have undergone corpus callosotomy constitute conflicting data with regard to the idea of the necessary unity of consciousness of a person or mind, and of mind being something numerically absolute. </s><s n="s2.8;p2.28">Corpus callosotomy, the surgical disconnection of the cerebral hemispheres, is not a mere thought experiment like Shoemaker's 'brain zaps', or Chalmerian zombies, but was performed on patients in the 50s and 60s regarding whom there is now a substantial body of experimental and observational data. </s><s n="s3.8;p2.28">One does not have to be a philosopher to be baffled by the details of this data. </s><s n="s4.8;p2.28">In evaluating Nagel's claim I shall begin by discussing the hemispheric duality of the human brain, and how this duality is brought out to an extreme degree in the case of patients who have undergone callosotomy. </s><s n="s5.8;p2.28">I will then proceed to evaluate Nagel's argument. </s><s n="s6.8;p2.28">Nagel argues that it is impossible to properly assign personal identity and a unified conscious experience to callosotomy patients without violating the clinical and experimental data. </s><s n="s7.8;p2.28">Thus, he concludes, we must either abandon certain concepts (crucially, the necessary unity of consciousness of a person or mind), or accept that the mind is irreducible to the brain. </s><s n="s8.8;p2.28">I shall argue that by accepting that each person may have more than one mind, we can avoid most of these difficulties. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head>The bilateral brain</head><p n="p3.28"><s n="s1.4;p3.28">Like the body, the brain is to a large extent bilateral. </s><s n="s2.4;p3.28">In the midbrain and hindbrain, one side is largely a mirror image of the other, but the two sides are highly interconnected (think peanut). </s><s n="s3.4;p3.28">In the cortex however, the cerebral hemispheres only connect directly through a relatively small band of about 200 million axons called the <hi rend="italic">corpus callosum</hi>. </s><s n="s4.4;p3.28">The extent to which the hemispheres can communicate through the midbrain seems, unfortunately, to be largely unknown. </s></p><p n="p4.28"><s n="s1.13;p4.28">The midbrain and brainstem (including cerebellum) make up more than 50% of the mass of the brain. </s><s n="s2.13;p4.28">They process and relay sensory information to the cerebral hemispheres and control functions such as emotion, reward and aversion, biological rhythms and some forms of memory. </s><s n="s3.13;p4.28">The cerebral hemispheres mediate higher cognitive functions such as episodic and working memory, planning and sensory processing. </s><s n="s4.13;p4.28">The right hemisphere receives input from and controls the left side of the body and vice versa (neck and face are controlled by both). </s><s n="s5.13;p4.28">The left hemisphere, often called the dominant hemisphere, is slightly larger than the right one, and is the only one capable of producing spoken language. </s><s n="s6.13;p4.28">This difference in language ability is the only hemispheric asymmetry<ref target="BAWE_0057f-ftnote.002"/> that Nagel brings into his essay but further differences that make up what is called the cognitive style of each hemisphere will be important to the argument. </s><s n="s7.13;p4.28">Very crudely, the left hemisphere tends to work by sequential analysis: systematic, logical interpretation of information. </s><s n="s8.13;p4.28">It is superior at dealing with symbolic information: language, mathematics, abstraction and reasoning, and its memory is stored in a "language format". </s><s n="s9.13;p4.28">Conversely, the right hemisphere functions in a holistic manner, processing multi-sensory input to produce a unified picture of one's environment. </s><s n="s10.13;p4.28">It is superior at spatial orientation, mental imagery, colour discrimination, and the processing of music and emotionally significant information. </s><s n="s11.13;p4.28">Its memory is stored in sensory modalities. </s><s n="s12.13;p4.28">It is mute but can understand and produce (written) language at the level of a young child. </s><s n="s13.13;p4.28">Finally the left half of each retina (i.e. the right visual field) is connected to the visual cortex of the left hemisphere and vice versa, with only a partial overlap in the middle<ref target="BAWE_0057f-ftnote.003"/>. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0057f-ftnote.002"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">It should be pointed out that the hemispheric asymmetries described here are only found in most right-handed individuals. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">In considering the callosotomy data, remember that some people are believed to have functionally identical hemispheres (including language abilities). </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0057f-ftnote.003"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Close one eye at a time to see this overlap. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">It allows for visual information from the centre of the visual field to reach both hemispheres even in patients who have undergone callosotomy and probably accounts for a lot of their unified behaviour outside the experimental setting. </s></p></note></div1><div1 type="section"><head>What is brain bisection?</head><p n="p5.28"><s n="s1.11;p5.28">Corpus callosotomy, then, refers to a procedure where surgeons cut the corpus callosum to prevent the spread of epilepsy from one hemisphere to the other. </s><s n="s2.11;p5.28">Although the procedure is no longer performed, many patients who have undergone it are still alive and have attracted considerable attention from psychologists, philosophers and neurologists alike. </s><s n="s3.11;p5.28">Two things should be noted about these patients. </s><s n="s4.11;p5.28">In everyday life their behaviour remains largely unchanged (which, of course, is why the procedure became popular in the first place). </s><s n="s5.11;p5.28">They retain the ability to "play the piano, button their shirts, swim and... do not report any sensation of division or reduction of the visual field" (p. </s><s n="s6.11;p5.28">434)<ref target="BAWE_0057f-ftnote.004"/>. </s><s n="s7.11;p5.28">Their friends and family continue to refer to them as one and the same person. </s><s n="s8.11;p5.28">Nagel and some of his contemporary critics (e.g. </s><s n="s9.11;p5.28">Bayne, 2004) make it sound as though callosotomy leaves the patient behaviourally <hi rend="italic">completely</hi> unchanged but this is not true: callosotomy patients exhibit the symptoms of <hi rend="italic">split brain syndrome</hi>, which can include a moderate memory deficit, selective learning difficulties, inappropriate or exaggerated politeness in conversation and a slight tendency to confabulate. </s><s n="s10.11;p5.28">Also, there can be a reduction in the ability to express emotion verbally (alexithymia) and maintain motivation while reading long texts<ref target="BAWE_0057f-ftnote.005"/>. </s><s n="s11.11;p5.28">Some cases have even been reported of two disconnected hemispheres answering differently to questions such as 'what do you want to be?' and one patient repeatedly complained that when trying to hug his wife his left hand pushed her away, but such cases are very rare. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0057f-ftnote.004"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">All page references in this essay refer to Nagel's essay as reproduced in <hi rend="italic">The Nature of Mind</hi> (Rosenthal, ed. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">1991). </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0057f-ftnote.005"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">This symptom has a certain commonsensical logic to it - the effect is readily understood as the disconnection of the more verbal left and the more emotional right hemisphere. </s></p></note><p n="p6.28"><s n="s1.7;p6.28">In the experimental setting, however, a truly bewildering lack of communication can be demonstrated by separating stimuli so that it reaches each hemisphere separately (called tachistoscopic stimulation). </s><s n="s2.7;p6.28">The most common example is that a patient is shown a word; say TAXABLE, in such a way that TAX is in the left visual field and ABLE in the right. </s><s n="s3.7;p6.28">When asked to write down what word was shown the patients right hand will write TAX and his left hand (poorly) ABLE. If only ABLE is shown the patient will insist verbally that he saw nothing and express surprise at finding his left hand writing. </s><s n="s4.7;p6.28">Similarly, if asked to identify an object by touching it with his left hand he remains unable to say verbally what kind of object it is but will be able to point to it or draw a picture of it, using his left hand. </s><s n="s5.7;p6.28">Callosotomy patients are unable to compare sensory input that is processed separately by the disconnected hemispheres because without the corpus callosum, sensory processing in one hemisphere is inaccessible to the other. </s><s n="s6.7;p6.28">In Nagel's words, the observations in the experimental setting make us wonder "whether these patients have one mind, or two, or some more exotic configuration" (p. </s><s n="s7.7;p6.28">435). </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head>Conflicting data?</head><p n="p7.28"><s n="s1.3;p7.28">Nagel considers five different attempts to understand the minds of the patients following hemispheric bisection. </s><s n="s2.3;p7.28">Before we can consider these different accounts and Nagel's analysis of them we must clarify what we mean by 'mind'. </s><s n="s3.3;p7.28">What are the concepts with which the callosotomy data may be in conflict? </s></p><p n="p8.28"><s n="s1.11;p8.28">If we want to assert that a callosotomy patient has one mind, is still one person, then, because of their disunified experience, the idea of the necessary unity of consciousness of a person is challenged. </s><s n="s2.11;p8.28">The unity of consciousness is an old and influential philosophical concept that is central to thinkers such as Descartes, Leibniz, Kant, Reid and William James. </s><s n="s3.11;p8.28">The concept can be defined as the assertion that the subjective experiences of a person or a mind always occur as a whole, i.e. for me to be conscious of one object in my present experience is to be conscious of all other objects of my experience and of them as a group. </s><s n="s4.11;p8.28">A similar definition which Nagel refers to at one point (p. </s><s n="s5.11;p8.28">437) states that unity of consciousness can be understood as a mind's ability to <hi rend="italic">compare</hi> the different objects of its experience. </s><s n="s6.11;p8.28">A more Kantian definition states that experience is necessarily unified because I am (and must be) able to ascribe all aspects of my experience to my <hi rend="italic">self</hi>. </s><s n="s7.11;p8.28">(For a multitude of complex contemporary explorations and definitions of the concept, see Bayne &amp; Chalmers, 2003 or Brook, 2001.) </s><s n="s8.11;p8.28">Common to all these definitions is the quite intuitive idea that each person or mind has only one (unified) conscious experience, not many. </s><s n="s9.11;p8.28">However, the data just discussed gives strong support to the idea that a callosotomy patient does not have a unified conscious experience. </s><s n="s10.11;p8.28">Thus, if we still want to refer to one of them as an individual, as a single person or mind, then we must abandon the idea that a person's consciousness is necessarily unified. </s><s n="s11.11;p8.28">Nagel argues that abandoning this idea is probably intuitively impossible, but it is a route that is compatible with animalist theories of personhood, and has been endorsed by thinkers such as Derek Parfit, and I shall return to it. </s></p><p n="p9.28"><s n="s1.3;p9.28">More generally Nagel argues that the callosotomy data challenges the idea of mind or person being something numerically absolute. </s><s n="s2.3;p9.28">He argues that, considering the experimental evidence, it is impossible to assign the callosotomy patients <hi rend="italic">any</hi> whole number of minds. </s><s n="s3.3;p9.28">I shall argue that Nagel fails to respond to the 'two minds' hypothesis and that the callosotomy data does not necessarily contradict the idea of mind being something numerically absolute. </s></p><p n="p10.28"><s n="s1.2;p10.28">Suffice it to say then, that by 'mind' Nagel means something like a numerically absolute, single subject of a unified experience, something we normally consider ourselves and others to be<ref target="BAWE_0057f-ftnote.006"/>. </s><s n="s2.2;p10.28">Nagel considers the following five accounts of how a whole number of minds can be attributed to a callosotomy patient: </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0057f-ftnote.006"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.4;pn1.1">In his essay, Nagel refuses to ever really define concepts such as 'person', 'mind', and 'subject of a unified experience' (which he uses interchangeably). </s><s n="s2.4;pn1.1">"Instead of beginning with an analysis of the unity of mind I am going to proceed by attempting to apply the ordinary, unanalyzed conception" (p. </s><s n="s3.4;pn1.1">435). </s><s n="s4.4;pn1.1">This creates serious problems in the interpretation of Nagel's argument. </s></p></note><p rend="ordered" n="p11.28"><s n="s1.1;p11.28">1) The patient has one fairly normal mind in the hemisphere that can respond verbally, and only automatic responses in the right one. </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p12.28"><s n="s1.1;p12.28">2) The patient has one normal mind in the hemisphere that can respond verbally, and occasional "free floating" conscious experiences which do not constitute a mind in the right one. </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p13.28"><s n="s1.1;p13.28">3) The patient has two normal minds, one in each hemisphere. </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p14.28"><s n="s1.1;p14.28">4) The patient has one, rather peculiar and dissociated mind that derives from both hemispheres. </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p15.28"><s n="s1.1;p15.28">5) The patient has one normal mind most of the time while the hemispheres function normally, but two minds when stimuli is artificially separated in the experimental setting. </s></p><p n="p16.28"><s n="s1.5;p16.28">1) becomes somewhat plausible when we ask ourselves who we are in fact talking to when conversing with a callosotomy patient. </s><s n="s2.5;p16.28">In a conversation we want to believe we are conversing with an entire person, and the lack of cognitive diminution following callosotomy is hard to account for other than by saying that the right hemisphere <hi rend="italic">never</hi> has any conscious experience with which to contribute to conversation, even in an intact brain. </s><s n="s3.5;p16.28">Furthermore, we know from the experimental setting that the bisected hemispheres are curiously unaware of activity in the partner hemisphere and we know that only the left one is talking to us - so if the patient's behavior is in perfect accord with his words; if the left side of his body (controlled by the right hemisphere) is in perfect synch with the right side, need we not ask ourselves if the right hemisphere is not being completely subjugated, somehow controlled, by the dominant left one? </s><s n="s4.5;p16.28">However, separating the two hemispheres does not rid them of their common memories, desires and fears, midbrain and hindbrain, which might help to account for their synchronized behavioral output<ref target="BAWE_0057f-ftnote.007"/>. </s><s n="s5.5;p16.28">Also, we should not forget that many conversational difficulties following callosotomy <hi rend="italic">have</hi> in fact been reported (see split brain syndrome above). </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0057f-ftnote.007"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">For instance, the dopaminergic system that originates in the ventral tegmental area of the midbrain and is believed to control most of our approach behaviour pools input from both hemispheres and thus provides the hemispheres with single behavioural goals. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">Also, in the non-experimental setting most relevant stimuli reaches both hemispheres (i.e. both hear what is said to the patient, and visual stimuli that is in the centre of the visual field is processed by both). </s></p></note><p n="p17.28"><s n="s1.9;p17.28">2) is a weaker version of 1). </s><s n="s2.9;p17.28">It states that although the right hemisphere probably still has some conscious experiences, it does not have the kind of structured experience that warrants us ascribing it a mind of its own. </s><s n="s3.9;p17.28">Aptitude tests taken by the right hemisphere (not to mention its lacking Brocca's and Wernicke's areas) show that it has a limited ability to process symbolic information, i.e. language, logic, quantity and concepts. </s><s n="s4.9;p17.28">Can an experience that is to a large extent deprived of these organizing features (categories if you will) be more than something like a dream? </s><s n="s5.9;p17.28">In other words is it not at least questionable whether the experience of the right hemisphere is "mindlike"? </s><s n="s6.9;p17.28">Our evidence against this view is that the right hemisphere functions with a degree of autonomy, intentionality and intelligence which makes it difficult to deny it at least the conscious mental life of a child. </s><s n="s7.9;p17.28">The right hemisphere is "a system capable of learning, reacting emotionally, following instructions, and carrying out tasks which require the integration of diverse psychological determinants (p. </s><s n="s8.9;p17.28">435). </s><s n="s9.9;p17.28">Some specific examples of what the right hemisphere actually <hi rend="italic">can</hi> do on its own is needed here, but for the sake of argument, let us grant that the experiences of the right hemisphere may well be structured in a mindlike fashion. </s></p><p n="p18.28"><s n="s1.4;p18.28">However, let us avoid the third account which ascribes a mind to each hemisphere for now. </s><s n="s2.4;p18.28">Let us also reject 5) which states that a single mind divides into two in the "experimental setting". </s><s n="s3.4;p18.28">As Nagel points out, this account is insensitive to the fact that the experimental setting simply structures the stimuli that reaches the two hemispheres in a certain way. </s><s n="s4.4;p18.28">Such structuring (tachistoscopic stimulation) occurs every day; there is just much more of it in the experimental setting, which simply brings out a split that is continually present. </s></p><p n="p19.28"><s n="s1.12;p19.28">Let us proceed instead to 4) which asserts that the patient is one person and still has one mind, although this mind is a bit unusual and, as it were, split at the top. </s><s n="s2.12;p19.28">This is probably what we have to believe legally and in interaction with the patient. </s><s n="s3.12;p19.28">This view also avoids the difficult question of how much of the corpus callosum had to be cut for one mind to become two. </s><s n="s4.12;p19.28">But this is the account that challenges the idea that each person or mind has only one unified conscious experience. </s><s n="s5.12;p19.28">A mind that knows that it has just been shown a plastic duck say and is in the process of drawing a picture of it cannot be ascribed a single unified experience if it is at the same time unaware of having been shown a duck and is confused to find itself drawing a picture of one. </s><s n="s6.12;p19.28">The consciousness of the callosotomy patient is split. </s><s n="s7.12;p19.28">How deep is this split? </s><s n="s8.12;p19.28">It is certainly a split at the level of attention: the two hemispheres can engage in very different, conflicting tasks, but so can some people. </s><s n="s9.12;p19.28">However, it is also a split in visual, tactile and olfactory (and to some extent auditory) experience: the patients cannot compare stimuli that reach the two hemispheres separately. </s><s n="s10.12;p19.28">This is far from normal. </s><s n="s11.12;p19.28">It is furthermore an epistemological split: the patient can be convinced of an assertion (e.g. having seen a plastic duck) and its negation simultaneously. </s><s n="s12.12;p19.28">Taken together these splits amount to a disunified consciousness in a single body. </s></p><p n="p20.28"><s n="s1.9;p20.28">Still, it is not a split at the level of desires (see footnote 6), fears, levels of arousal, "instinctual" responses, and hormonal environment. </s><s n="s2.9;p20.28">It is interesting to consider the hypothetical implications of a complete brain bisection. </s><s n="s3.9;p20.28">It is unlikely that the midbrain would survive such an operation, but if it did the mental and behavioral split would certainly be much deeper. </s><s n="s4.9;p20.28">So there are still elements of unity in the case of callosotomy patients. </s><s n="s5.9;p20.28">In <hi rend="italic">Reasons and Persons</hi> (1984) Derek Parfit argues that a split brain patient can still be considered a person even though their experience is not unified. </s><s n="s6.9;p20.28">He invites us to consider a benevolent scenario where we imagine we are one of those individuals whose hemispheres are functionally identical, and have recently had a device installed such that we can easily and quickly block all transmission along the corpus callosum, and just as easily reverse the process. </s><s n="s7.9;p20.28">Using this device we could divide our attention completely in situations where we wish to do so (we could for instance listen to two different conversations and then, upon reconnection, perhaps have mnemonic access to both). </s><s n="s8.9;p20.28">However, Parfit argues, this would not mean that two new persons would have suddenly popped into existence and then somehow merged into one when the device was inactivated. </s><s n="s9.9;p20.28">Given a bit of practice we would <hi rend="italic">learn to accept</hi> the extent to which a single person's experiences can be separated. </s></p><p n="p21.28"><s n="s1.13;p21.28">The difficulty involved in this argument is that it presumes what it is trying to argue for, namely, that only one person or mind was present to begin with. </s><s n="s2.13;p21.28">But it could just as well be argued that rather than partially dividing a single mind, the device temporarily disconnects two minds that are normally intimately connected. </s><s n="s3.13;p21.28">Also, while we're discussing science fiction devices, why not imagine one such that we could connect ourselves to a third hemisphere, and a fourth. </s><s n="s4.13;p21.28">Would four connected hemispheres make one person according to Parfit's argument, or two, or four? </s><s n="s5.13;p21.28">Does it not make more sense to call each hemisphere a mind? </s><s n="s6.13;p21.28">Perhaps, but can we really call each hemisphere a <hi rend="italic">person</hi>? </s><s n="s7.13;p21.28">Although Nagel uses the terms interchangeably, mind and person are not necessarily the same thing, though we often think of them as such. </s><s n="s8.13;p21.28">One way out of these difficulties is to adopt an animalist account of personhood and argue that the callosotomy patient remains one and the same person as long as the (human) animal, i.e. the body, its behavior and appearance, and perhaps its DNA, remains intact. </s><s n="s9.13;p21.28">A person then, could have two (or more) minds, and still be one person, provided these minds could cooperate in the control of the body. </s><s n="s10.13;p21.28">I am skeptical to animalism myself, mainly because it denies the possibility of a person surviving a brain transplant into a new body. </s><s n="s11.13;p21.28">But it is certainly debatable whether Nagel is justified in equating person and mind. </s><s n="s12.13;p21.28">'Person', much more so than 'mind', carries traditional properties such as a body, a name, habits, a social security number and so on, and all these remain intact in the callosotomy patient. </s><s n="s13.13;p21.28">For now, I shall simply refrain from referring to 'person' but will instead use the term 'mind'. </s></p><p n="p22.28"><s n="s1.4;p22.28">Let us consider 3) then, the assertion that in the callosotomy patient each hemisphere has a mind of its own. </s><s n="s2.4;p22.28">In so far as there is any standard interpretation among neurologists and psychologists in this matter (e.g. </s><s n="s3.4;p22.28">Sperry, Mayer and Gazzinga - the pioneers of split brain research), this is it. </s><s n="s4.4;p22.28">As far as I can see there are two versions to this argument: </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p23.28"><s n="s1.1;p23.28">3a) Brains that have undergone callosotomy have two minds, intact brains have one. </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p24.28"><s n="s1.1;p24.28">3b) Brains that have undergone callosotomy have two minds and, though we do not normally notice it because of their extensive communication via the corpus callosum, so do intact brains. </s></p><p n="p25.28"><s n="s1.12;p25.28">Nagel rejects 3a) on the grounds that the patients' behavior is too integrated; too much like that of normal people for us to talk about two minds housed in the same body. </s><s n="s2.12;p25.28">Indeed, the two sides of the patient's body cooperate admirably and their family and friends continue to refer to them as one person. </s><s n="s3.12;p25.28">The easiest way to bring out the difficulty involved in 3a) is to consider the actual callosotomy. </s><s n="s4.12;p25.28">Patients are usually awake during brain surgery and we can ask ourselves when exactly their one mind splits in two as the surgeon slowly cuts the corpus callosum. </s><s n="s5.12;p25.28">Surely it must be a gradual decline, and what if a small strand of the corpus callosum is left intact, do we still get two minds? </s><s n="s6.12;p25.28">Consider that, on average, the corpus callosum of women is some 25% thicker than that of men. </s><s n="s7.12;p25.28">And what if, by application of a new species of neurotrophins we could initiate an increase in the number of axons connecting the two hemispheres in a healthy subject? </s><s n="s8.12;p25.28">If this operation was performed successfully, the patient would probably experience something like an <hi rend="italic">increase</hi> in the unity of his consciousness; in his ability to compare sensory information in the two hemispheres for instance. </s><s n="s9.12;p25.28">Then maybe, he would come to believe that his experience was and always had been the result of two closely connected minds. </s><s n="s10.12;p25.28">So what if we accept this view (3b), that every intact brain has two minds, and that this duality is simply brought out more clearly in callosotomy patients? </s><s n="s11.12;p25.28">Remember that the two hemispheres are to a large extent mirror images of each other, i.e. they both contain structures for processing input from all the senses and frontal and association cortices for thought, planning and integrated experience. </s><s n="s12.12;p25.28">Maybe all brains have what Sperry calls "two separate realms of conscious awareness; two sensing perceiving, thinking and remembering systems." or what Searle calls "two loci of consciousness". </s></p><p n="p26.28"><s n="s1.11;p26.28">For some reason Nagel seems unable to take this view seriously and dismisses it in a footnote. </s><s n="s2.11;p26.28">But it is the view of many researchers, including some philosophers (e.g. </s><s n="s3.11;p26.28">Ahmed, Pietsch), and it is in my opinion the most difficult one to throw aside. </s><s n="s4.11;p26.28">Nagel (footnote 11, p. 440) tries to do so by arguing that "in case anyone is inclined to embrace the conclusion that we all have two minds" they should consider that each hemisphere can be subjected to further functional disconnection, yielding "several cooperating minds with specialized capacities". </s><s n="s5.11;p26.28">But this is a misconception - it is very unlikely that, say, a disconnected visual cortex would have experiences that would warrant us ascribing it a mind. </s><s n="s6.11;p26.28">Rather, it would be a complex biological camera. </s><s n="s7.11;p26.28">Most importantly it would be disconnected from the associative white matter of the cortex where experience is integrated and the prefrontal cortex where experience is manipulated. </s><s n="s8.11;p26.28">It is unfortunate that Nagel does not take 3b) more seriously for I cannot see any further objections to it. </s><s n="s9.11;p26.28"><hi rend="italic">If</hi> we equate mind with person it is perhaps understandable why we should be reluctant to accept 3b): we do not want to refer to the callosotomy patient as two persons - the fact that they inhabit the same body and cooperate to such a considerable degree through common memories and desires etc makes this alternative implausible. </s><s n="s10.11;p26.28">But is there any reason why I cannot refer to them as two minds that have lost the direct connection that my minds have? </s><s n="s11.11;p26.28">The unified consciousness that I experience then, is the result of two <hi rend="italic">potentially</hi> separable minds. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head>Conclusion</head><p n="p27.28"><s n="s1.7;p27.28">The callosotomy data forces us to consider a duality which is present in all of us, but which we normally do not notice. </s><s n="s2.7;p27.28">In the case of callosotomy patients this duality has been brought out and can be demonstrated by careful experimentation, but their behavior remains coherent in the normal setting. </s><s n="s3.7;p27.28">It is unclear how to interpret this. </s><s n="s4.7;p27.28">Nagel argues that it is impossible to attribute personal identity to them, and to describe the unity in their experience, in a way that does not violate the experimental, observational and theoretical data. </s><s n="s5.7;p27.28">While it appears that they experience two streams of consciousness, we remain unable to refer to them as two persons in a single body. </s><s n="s6.7;p27.28">Does this mean that we must abandon the idea of the conscious experience of a person being necessarily unified? </s><s n="s7.7;p27.28">No, Nagel argues, it can just as well mean that the unity of consciousness that we experience is simply incompatible with, and irreducible to, the clinical and experimental data. </s></p><p n="p28.28"><s n="s1.6;p28.28">I have argued that the callosotomy data suggests that the unity of consciousness that each of us experiences is not absolute: our experience could be more or less unified. </s><s n="s2.6;p28.28">In the case of callosotomy patients, their anatomy is such that they can have two completely separate experiences simultaneously. </s><s n="s3.6;p28.28">Although these experiences can perhaps not be attributed to the same mind, I have argued that they can still be attributed to the same person, as long as we accept that the unity we all experience is still the result of sensory processing in two interconnected minds, and that the experience of each mind would remain unified even if the corpus callosum was cut (though it would then process less sensory input). </s><s n="s4.6;p28.28">Thus, while the necessary unity of consciousness of a <hi rend="italic">person</hi> is indeed challenged by the callosotomy data, the necessary unity of consciousness of a mind is not. </s><s n="s5.6;p28.28">In other words, the callosotomy data challenges the assumption that a person has only one mind. </s><s n="s6.6;p28.28">But I hope I have shown that this conclusion is perfectly plausible. </s></p></div1></body><back><div1 type="bibliography"><head>References</head><p>Bayne, T., 2004, "Brain Bisection and the Unity of Consciousness" <hi rend="italic">(Course description handout)</hi>, Macquarie University</p><p>[url = <seg type="URL" n="www.phil.mq.edu.au/staff/tbayne/unity_handout.pdf"/>]</p><p>Bayne, T. &amp; Chalmers, D., 2003, "What is the unity of consciousness?" Published in A. Cleeremans (ed.), <hi rend="italic">The Unity of Consciousness: Binding, Integration, Dissociation</hi> (Oxford, 2003)</p><p>[url = jamaica.u.arizona.edu/~chalmers/papers/unity.html]</p><p>Brook, A., 2001, "The Unity of Consciousness", <hi rend="italic">The Stanford Encyclopedia of Philosophy (Summer 2001 Edition)</hi>, Edward N. Zalta (ed.)</p><p>[url = plato.stanford.edu/archives/sum2001/entries/consciousness-unity]</p><p>Parfit, D., 1984 <hi rend="italic">Reasons and persons</hi>, Norfolk, Oxford university press</p><p>Passer, M. W. &amp; Smith, R. E., 2001, <hi rend="italic">Psychology Frontiers and Applications</hi>, Boston, McGraw-Hill</p><p>Zeidel, E. &amp; Zeidel, D. W. &amp; Bogen, J. E., 1998, "The Split Brain", <hi rend="italic">California Institute of Technology, Information Technology Services</hi></p><p>[url = <seg type="URL" n="http://www.its.caltech.edu/~jbogen/text/ref130.htm"/>]</p><p>Snowdon, P. F., "Persons, Animals and Bodies" as printed in Bermudez, J. L., Marcel, A. &amp; Eilan, N. (ed.) (2001) <hi rend="italic">The Body and the Self</hi>, Massachusetts, MIT Press</p></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
