<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_0057e" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Mapping the reward circuits in the human nervous system</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">The document has a title page which contains:
document title
title part</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">2</p><p n="date">2005-04</p><p n="module title">BS/MB/VIR/CB assessments</p><p n="module code">BS241</p><p n="genre family">Essay</p><p n="discipline">Biological Sciences</p><p n="disciplinary group">LS</p><p n="grade">D</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">3043</p><p n="number of s-units">110</p><p n="number of p">14</p><p n="number of tables">2</p><p n="number of figures">1</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">0</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">0</p><p n="abstract present">abstract present</p><p n="average words per s-unit">27.7</p><p n="average s-units per p">7.9</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">m</p><p n="year of birth">1983</p><p n="first language">Swedish</p><p n="education">OSA</p><p n="course">Philosophy and Psychology</p><p n="student ID">0057</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><docTitle><titlePart>Mapping the reward circuits in the human nervous system</titlePart></docTitle><titlePart><name type="student name"/></titlePart><titlePart>April 2005</titlePart></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="abstract"><head>Abstract</head><p n="p1.14"><s n="s1.9;p1.14">This essay explores the many-sided current literature on how reward is generated in the mammalian nervous system. </s><s n="s2.9;p1.14">Reward is defined the process that sustains approach behaviour in an animal. </s><s n="s3.9;p1.14">The topography of reward-relevant sites in the brain and the intracranial stimulation research that has yielded this data is described. </s><s n="s4.9;p1.14">The medial forebrain bundle is identified as crucial to reward activity, and is discussed in some detail. </s><s n="s5.9;p1.14">A number of reward-relevant sites along the medial forebrain bundle, especially the ventral tegmental area are identified and their functional anatomy discussed. </s><s n="s6.9;p1.14">It is concluded that dopamine plays a fundamental (albeit somewhat ambiguous) role in the reward process. </s><s n="s7.9;p1.14">The roles of other transmitter substances in the reward process are discussed. </s><s n="s8.9;p1.14">The role of opioids is considered in the discussion where a model of reward that distinguishes between pleasure and desire is explored. </s><s n="s9.9;p1.14">It is concluded that although the dopaminergic circuit that originates in the ventral tegmental area is neither the "pleasure centre" of the brain (as it is sometimes described) nor the only circuit involved in the reward process, it is certainly central to it. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head>Introduction</head><p n="p2.14"><s n="s1.6;p2.14">In this essay <hi rend="italic">reward</hi> refers to those processes in the nervous system, the function of which is to make an animal repeat evolutionary adaptive patterns of behaviour. </s><s n="s2.6;p2.14">Reinforcers are objects that elicit reward. </s><s n="s3.6;p2.14">Primary reinforcers, such as sweet nutrients, generate reward in an animal that has never encountered them before, while the reward value of secondary reinforcers, such as coins, has to be learnt. </s><s n="s4.6;p2.14">The reward process drives an animal to obtain reinforcers. </s><s n="s5.6;p2.14">It includes that motivating process of anticipation that occurs before and as a reinforcer is being obtained. </s><s n="s6.6;p2.14">Conversely, conscious pleasure, often equated with reward, is just one form of it. </s></p><p n="p3.14"><s n="s1.5;p3.14">What then, in neurobiological terms, is reward? </s><s n="s2.5;p3.14">A considerable amount of research has gone into the analysis of the reward-circuits of mammals since Olds and Milner's classic experiments in the 1950s (see below). </s><s n="s3.5;p3.14">The problem facing any reader of this literature is that different studies point in different, sometimes conflicting directions. </s><s n="s4.5;p3.14">At least four cortical structures, more than ten separate midbrain sites and parts of the brainstem and cerebellum have all been referred to as involved in the reward process in study or other. </s><s n="s5.5;p3.14">These sites are listed in table 1 below. </s></p><table id="BAWE_0057e-tab.001"><head>Table 1. Sites and structures implicated in the reward process in a variety of studies.</head><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p4.14"><s n="s1.6;p4.14">Moving on to reward-relevant <hi rend="italic">compounds</hi> in the brain, dopamine is very often referred to as the transmitter that mediates reward, but norepinephrine, serotonin, endogenous opiates and a multitude of chemically diverse recreational and therapeutic drugs function as powerful reinforcers of behaviour (see table 2 below). </s><s n="s2.6;p4.14">How are we to fit these pieces together? </s><s n="s3.6;p4.14">Is there a single reward system in the mammalian nervous system? </s><s n="s4.6;p4.14">If not, how can reward serve as that "common currency" which the nervous system uses to choose between different behavioural options at a given time (Philips, 2003; Grossman, 1994)? </s><s n="s5.6;p4.14">Many researchers identify the <hi rend="italic">mesolimbic dopamine pathway</hi> (MDP) as the final common mediator of reward and of pleasure in the brain, but since the 1980s this conclusion has been partly challenged by a number of studies that suggest that the MDP mediates not pleasure, but another, related emotive process; <hi rend="italic">desire</hi> (Berridge &amp; Robinson, 1998; Berridge, 2003; Philips, 2003) and that pleasure is generated elsewhere. </s><s n="s6.6;p4.14">In fact, some studies conclude that dopamine and the MDP are not necessary for reward at all (Cannon &amp; Bseikri, 2004; Grossman, 1994). </s></p><table id="BAWE_0057e-tab.002"><head>Table 2. Chemical compounds involved in reward.</head><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p5.14"><s n="s1.9;p5.14">This essay attempts to put some of these pieces together. </s><s n="s2.9;p5.14">First it considers the multitude of brain sites that have been implicated in the reward process. </s><s n="s3.9;p5.14">Most of these were first identified by their ability to sustain site-specific intracranial electrical stimulation in animals given the opportunity to self-stimulate. </s><s n="s4.9;p5.14">The value of the intracranial self-stimulation (ICSS) procedure to reward-research is considered, and the <hi rend="italic">medial forebrain bundle</hi> is identified as crucial to ICSS and its anatomy discussed. </s><s n="s5.9;p5.14">Second, the various transmitters and drugs that have been implicated in reward are considered. </s><s n="s6.9;p5.14">The idea that the reward-value of many of these compounds can be tied to each other and to dopaminergic neurons in the ventral tegmental area, sometimes called the <hi rend="italic">cascade theory of reward</hi>, is discussed. </s><s n="s7.9;p5.14">Finally, this single-system view of reward, which is the view held by many researchers, is challenged. </s><s n="s8.9;p5.14">The distinctions that have emerged in recent years between pleasure and desire, and between conscious and unconscious (or "core") aspects of these emotive processes are considered, as is their distinct functional anatomy. </s><s n="s9.9;p5.14">Hopefully, a clearer account of the complexity of reward is given. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head>Topography of reward</head><p n="p6.14"><s n="s1.18;p6.14">What sites in the mammalian nervous system mediate reward? </s><s n="s2.18;p6.14">Which sites increase their metabolic activity at the prospect of say a large cash prize <hi rend="italic">and</hi> during sex <hi rend="italic">and</hi> while preparing a meal or receiving praise for a job well done? </s><s n="s3.18;p6.14">Where are these sites? </s><s n="s4.18;p6.14">Anatomical localization of reward-relevant circuits began with a series of experiments by Olds and Milner (1954) using electrical brain stimulation. </s><s n="s5.18;p6.14">Electrical stimulation is a valuable technique for localizing function in the nervous system because only fibres passing within a fraction of a millimetre from the electrode are activated (Wise, 1998). </s><s n="s6.18;p6.14">The technique has some limitations: it is unclear how to interpret the relatively rapid extinction of behaviour that is no longer electrically reinforced. </s><s n="s7.18;p6.14">Developing measures of how rewarding electrical stimuli is, which does not depend solely on the elicited frequency of self-stimulation, can be difficult; and of course, crude electrode pulses will never reproduce the intricacies of natural reward-activity and are insensitive axon directionality and to specific transmitter systems. </s><s n="s8.18;p6.14">Still, the results of ICSS are striking. </s><s n="s9.18;p6.14">Stimulation of the septal area, a site adjacent to the hypothalamus, was the first site found to serve as a powerful reinforcer in rats. </s><s n="s10.18;p6.14">Given the opportunity to self stimulate rats would learn complex tasks and forfeit many natural reinforcers to obtain a short train of pulses through an imbedded electrode. </s><s n="s11.18;p6.14">Olds and Milner concluded that they had identified the rats' "pleasure centres". </s><s n="s12.18;p6.14">Some researchers tried to apply these findings to humans, hoping to cure a variety of ailments (e.g. </s><s n="s13.18;p6.14">Dr. Heath of Tulane University (1960) who implanted electrodes into ICSS sustaining sites in the septal area and cerebellum of over 70 human patients). </s><s n="s14.18;p6.14">Human subjects are almost but not quite as susceptible to ICSS as are rodents (Hooper &amp; Teresi, 1991). </s><s n="s15.18;p6.14">Later studies on non-human animals found a whole battery of ICSS sensitive sites throughout the midbrain and elsewhere in the nervous system (see table 1). </s><s n="s16.18;p6.14">Similarly; it was discovered that rats will quickly increase the amount of time they spend in an area that is paired with stimulation of ICSS sensitive sites (Nader et. al., 1997). </s><s n="s17.18;p6.14">Some of these sites are drive-specific and will sustain much more ICSS if, for instance, the animal is hungry (posterior lateral hypothalamus), or in the presence of a sexually receptive mate (Grossman, 1994). </s><s n="s18.18;p6.14">Especially sensitive are: the ventral tegmental area, the medial forebrain bundle and the septum (figure 1 describes self-stimulation rate by rats at these sites as a function of current intensity). </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0057e-fig.001"><head>Figure 1. Rate-intensity function for electrical self-stimulation of the brain in rats (Zigmond, 1999).</head></figure><p n="p7.14"><s n="s1.7;p7.14">Are all these ICSS-sites connected, and, if so, how? </s><s n="s2.7;p7.14">The region most sensitive to ICSS is the medial forebrain bundle (MFB), which traverses the hypothalamus and connects the brainstem and the central grey matter of the midbrain with sites in the cerebrum (see figure 2 below: the MFB originates in the ventral tegmental area). </s><s n="s3.7;p7.14">Many studies suggest that ICSS is most pronounced in sites that innervate or are innervated by the MFB and there is evidence that most ICSS sustaining sites generate activity in this area when stimulated<ref target="BAWE_0057e-ftnote.001"/> (Zigmond, 1999; Grossman, 1994). </s><s n="s4.7;p7.14">Studies by Porrino (1990) and Yadin (1983) using autoradiographic labelling support this conclusion, but also suggest partially separate circuits sustaining ICSS in the prefrontal cortex (see discussion) and in the brainstem (involved in smell and taste and centring around the tegmental pedunculopontine nucleus) (Grossman, 1994; Nader et. al., 1997; Wise &amp; Rompre, 1989a). </s><s n="s5.7;p7.14">While most investigators seem to have accepted the crucial role of the MFB in sustaining ICSS in most areas of the brain it should be pointed out that although destruction of the MFB will largely eliminate approach behaviour (e.g. feeding, mating, ICSS) in an animal, these effects are often transient, and subject to partial or complete recovery (provided the animal survives that long) (Grossman, 1994). </s><s n="s6.7;p7.14">It is not clear whether this should be understood as the result of adaptive plasticity. </s><s n="s7.7;p7.14">Also, although the MFB can be considered the major "reward artery", it and other reward-relevant sites each seem to mediate separable functional sub-components of reward (see discussion). </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0057e-ftnote.001"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">There should therefore be a roughly linear relationship between the degree to which a given site produces ICSS and its corresponding activation of the reward relevant fibres of the MFB. </s></p></note></div1><div1 type="section"><head>Neurochemistry of reward</head><p n="p8.14"><s n="s1.9;p8.14">Despite its high ICSS potential only a few of the 50 or so fibre systems that constitute the MFB seem to be reward-relevant (Wise, 1998). </s><s n="s2.9;p8.14">These include the axons of the mesolimbic and mesocortical dopamine pathways, the neurons of which have their cell bodies situated in the <hi rend="italic">ventral tegmental area</hi> (VTA) and extend ascending afferents to the nucleus accumbens, septal regions, lateral amygdala and parts of the hippocampus in the midbrain, and orbitofrontal, prefrontal and cingulate cortex in the forebrain<ref target="BAWE_0057e-ftnote.002"/> (see figure 2) (Wise, 1998; Grossman, 1994). </s><s n="s3.9;p8.14">Microdialysis studies consistently show that reward-related activity in the VTA and MFB release dopamine in these regions, especially in the nucleus accumbens and medial prefrontal cortex (Grossman, 1994, Zigmond, 1999). </s><s n="s4.9;p8.14">Animals will work extremely hard to receive direct injections of dopamine or dopamine agonists (e.g. apomorphine or cocaine) into these regions (Grossman, 1994). </s><s n="s5.9;p8.14">Similarly, systemic or local administration of dopamine antagonists (e.g. spiroperdiol) or destruction of dopaminergic terminals through local injections of 6-hydroxydopamine (particularly in the nucleus accumbens) are known to reduce or eliminate approach behaviour including ICSS (i.e. produce anhedonia, see figure 1) in experimental animals<ref target="BAWE_0057e-ftnote.003"/> (Nader et. al., 1997, Philips, 2003; Walters, 2005). </s><s n="s6.9;p8.14">For these reasons, the mesolimbic dopamine pathway is simply referred to as the "pleasure centre" by many textbooks and is the circuit most frequently examined in studies of reward and addiction. </s><s n="s7.9;p8.14">It is unclear how microinjections of dopamine antagonists at VTA target sites other than the nucleus accumbens and prefrontal cortex affect approach behaviour but few investigators deny the crucial role of dopamine in reward (especially that of the VTA-nucleus accumbens axis). </s><s n="s8.9;p8.14">At the same time however, it has become clear that dopaminergic neurons constitute just a component (albeit, perhaps, an indispensable component) of a larger reward system. </s><s n="s9.9;p8.14">This should come as no surprise considering the variety of endogenous and pharmacological compounds that produce rewarding effects (see table 2). </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0057e-ftnote.002"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">It should be pointed out that there are no dopaminergic cell bodies in any of the dopamine target areas. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">Neither do dopamine neurons innervate each other (Wise &amp; Rompre, 1989a). </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0057e-ftnote.003"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Researchers have found it difficult to clearly separate the effects of compromising dopamine transmission on reward from changes in other functions such as arousal and the initiation of motor movement, in which dopamine systems (especially the nigro-striatal pathway) also play a major role. </s></p></note><figure id="BAWE_0057e-pic.001"><head>Figure 2. Midsaggital view of a mouse brain with dopaminergic systems marked out.</head></figure><p n="p9.14"><s n="s1.2;p9.14">To begin with, refractory period estimates indicate that descending hypothalamic <hi rend="italic">cholinergic</hi> axons, not ascending dopaminergic axons, are the primary mediators of the rewarding effects of intracranial electrical stimulation to the MFB (Wise, 1998, Grossman, 1994; Esch &amp; Stefano, 2004). </s><s n="s2.2;p9.14">These cholinergic axons have cell bodies in the hypothalamus and directly or indirectly innervate the dopaminergic neurons of the VTA, and could thus perhaps carry information about reward-relevant stimuli from the hypothalamus to the VTA. The existence of cholinergic receptors in the VTA is also thought to contribute strongly to <hi rend="italic">nicotine</hi>-induced dopamine release in the nucleus accumbens, thereby facilitating the addictive potential of smoking (Miyasato, 2001; Wise, 1998). </s></p><p n="p10.14"><s n="s1.2;p10.14">Several nuclei innervate the dopaminergic neurons of the VTA. In particular, noradrenergic axons from sites such as the locus ceruleus and dorsal raphe (pons) in the brainstem synapse with dopaminergic neurons in the VTA. These two sites are ICSS sustaining and electrically stimulating them have been shown to increase the activity of dopaminergic neurons in the VTA, and to release <hi rend="italic">noradrenaline</hi> into the nucleus accumbens and sites in the medial frontal cortex (Grossman, 1994). </s><s n="s2.2;p10.14">It is therefore possible that noradrenergic neurons carry reward related information from sites downstream of the VTA. Other potentially important sources of input to the VTA include glutamatergic input from medial prefrontal cortex, amygdala and pedunculopontine tegmental nucleus (these sites are all ICSS sustaining) (Wise, 1998; Lingford-Hughes &amp; Nutt, 2003). </s></p><p n="p11.14"><s n="s1.6;p11.14">Some of the more difficult systems to accommodate in reward are the serotonergic systems. </s><s n="s2.6;p11.14">Systemic infusion of serotonin antagonists or lesions of serotonergic axons increase the reward value of dopamine agonists (such as cocaine) and of primary reinforcers (primarily sex) (Wise, 1998). </s><s n="s3.6;p11.14">Several studies (e.g. </s><s n="s4.6;p11.14">Wise, 1998) have suggested an inhibitory serotonergic influence on the VTA. On the other hand long and short term serotonin agonists have behaviourally rewarding properties, and increased concentrations of endogenous opiates (see discussion) following administration of serotonin agonists have been demonstrated (Wilson, 2003). </s><s n="s5.6;p11.14">Some researchers argue that serotonergic neurons in the hypothalamus can produce release of endorphins in the VTA (Wilson, 2003). </s><s n="s6.6;p11.14">Furthermore, it is possible that serotonin and dopamine (D2) receptors are similar enough for serotonin to act as a partial dopamine agonist. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head>Discussion: Sub-components of reward</head><p n="p12.14"><s n="s1.12;p12.14">The role of opiates in reward also complicates the analysis of reward, but for different reasons. </s><s n="s2.12;p12.14">Endogenous opiates (e.g. endorphin and enkephalin, endomorphins) and opioid receptor agonists (such as morphine) both have highly rewarding properties. </s><s n="s3.12;p12.14">Neurons containing endorphin receptors are numerous in the VTA where they exert an inhibitory influence on GABAergic neurons which otherwise inhibit the firing of the dopaminergic neurons that project along the mesolimbic and mesocortical pathways (Hooper &amp; Teresi, 1991; Wise &amp; Rompre, 1989b). </s><s n="s4.12;p12.14">But opiates also serve other functions relevant to reward: in later years it has become apparent that <hi rend="italic">pleasure</hi> might not be the right term to describe the affect generated by mesolimbic and mesocortical dopamine activity. </s><s n="s5.12;p12.14">Berridge (1996) was one of the first to discover that rats whose (reward-related) dopaminergic neurons had been destroyed would still show the correct facial expressions (i.e. hedonic, ingestive reactions to sucrose and aversive, expulsive reactions to quinine) if a liquid was infused into the mouth (Berridge &amp; Robinson, 1998; Berridge, 2003; Nader et. al., 1997). </s><s n="s6.12;p12.14">Facial expressions are a reliable way of judging the hedonic impact of a food reinforcer on many animals, including newborn humans<ref target="BAWE_0057e-ftnote.004"/>. </s><s n="s7.12;p12.14">Moreover, in human subjects dopamine agonists can increase consumption of food but do not affect how much people report liking that food (Philips, 2003). </s><s n="s8.12;p12.14">These findings have convinced many researchers that reward-relevant dopamine transmission mediates, not feelings of palatability and pleasure, but the affect <hi rend="italic">desire</hi> (this view is sometimes called the dopamine <hi rend="italic">salience attribution model</hi>). </s><s n="s9.12;p12.14">Meta-analysis of the subjective reports given by patients receiving electrical brain stimulation of the major ICSS sustaining sites support this conclusion (Berridge, 2003, Zigmond, 1999). </s><s n="s10.12;p12.14">Microdialysis studies have shown that dopamine concentrations in the nucleus accumbens rise as animals are working to complete a task and peak right <hi rend="italic">before and at the moment</hi> the reinforcer is obtained, not as the reinforcer (in the case of a food-reward) is being consumed (Lingford-Hughes &amp; Nutt, 2003). </s><s n="s11.12;p12.14">Opiate transmission on the other hand seems more closely to correlate with subjective measures of pleasure. </s><s n="s12.12;p12.14">Opiate agonists increase peoples' reported liking of reinforcers and opioid receptor antagonists (such as nalexone) reduce the palatability of food, but not feelings of hunger (Philips, 2003; Berridge, 2003). </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0057e-ftnote.004"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Despite the high reliability of facial expressions as an operational definition of hedonic impact in rodents, Berridge and others seem to be drawing surprisingly general conclusions about the physiology of "liking" from experiments that exclusively utilize sweet nutrients as reinforcers. </s></p></note><p n="p13.14"><s n="s1.12;p13.14">So where, if not in the mesolimbic and mesocortical dopamine systems is "liking" generated? </s><s n="s2.12;p13.14">Berridge attributes the ventral pallidum a central role in mediating pleasure<ref target="BAWE_0057e-ftnote.005"/> (Berridge, 2003). </s><s n="s3.12;p13.14">Many of its neurons contain opioid receptors and diffuse to ICSS sensitive sites in the medial frontal cortex (Philips, 2003). </s><s n="s4.12;p13.14">Also, lesions to the region (and similarly, to the nucleus accumbens shell) eliminate normal hedonic reactions (Philips, 2003; Berridge, 2003). </s><s n="s5.12;p13.14">The ventral pallidum receives afferents from the nucleus accumbens suggesting a definite link between the opioid and dopamine systems (and between wanting and liking as affective reactions) but also from the orbitofrontal cortex which is independent of dopamine transmission. </s><s n="s6.12;p13.14">In fact, some (not all) studies report no significant decrease in the rate of self administration of opioid agonists (morphine and heroin) following dopamine antagonist pre-treatment or destruction of dopamine receptors in the nucleus accumbens (Nader, et. al., 1997). </s><s n="s7.12;p13.14">Several researchers (including Rolls, 2001) have found that reported level of liking associated with various reinforcers (including music and faces) correlates with level of activity in the orbitofrontal cortex (Philips, 2003). </s><s n="s8.12;p13.14">Given the validity of the salience attribution model, it is still unclear what the motivational and behavioural effect of "liking" really is (or, for that matter, its evolutionary value). </s><s n="s9.12;p13.14">The partial or complete elimination of approach behaviour produced by lesions to the mesolimbic dopamine pathway suggests that "liking" is not enough to sustain goal-directed behaviour (although, again, it is difficult to demonstrate that this anhedonic effect is not due to general deficits in the initiation of motor movement). </s><s n="s10.12;p13.14">Also, as we have seen, opioid antagonists do not reduce feelings of hunger, i.e. "wanting". </s><s n="s11.12;p13.14">So it is unclear whether the "liking system" really contributes to reward (defined as producing approach behaviour). </s><s n="s12.12;p13.14">Still, there is something strongly counterintuitive in the idea that a pattern of activation could in principle be artificially generated, such that a feeling of extreme euphoria (liking) is generated, but which leaves one with no desire to repeat whatever behaviour that produced that state. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0057e-ftnote.005"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Researchers have also suggested a partially independent system for mediating gustatory pleasure located in the brainstem (including the nucleus of the solitary tract and the parabrachial nucleus) (Nader et. al., 1997, Berridge, 2003). </s></p></note><p n="p14.14"><s n="s1.7;p14.14">The liking/wanting division is not the only distinction between the possible sub-components of reward where discrete anatomical sites and functions has been suggested. </s><s n="s2.7;p14.14">The deprived/nondeprived model focuses on the role of several systems, including the brainstem tegmental pedunculopontine nucleus, orbitofrontal cortex and the VTA in modulating the reward value of reinforcers depending on whether an animal is, for instance, hungry or sated; drug-naïve or drug-dependent (Nader et. al., 1997). </s><s n="s3.7;p14.14">This model also constrains dopamine's participation in the reward process to situations where the animal is in a deprived state. </s><s n="s4.7;p14.14">Cardinalal. (2002) discuss the different roles of parts of the amygdala and of the frontal lobe in reward. </s><s n="s5.7;p14.14">Also, many affective neuroscientists advocate a distinction between unconscious, or core aspects of reward and its subjective, conscious features (Berridge, 2003). </s><s n="s6.7;p14.14">According to this view it seems as though the systems described here mediate the core aspects of reward only, and that the subjective states which we experience are generated elsewhere, some have argued in the cingulate cortex, somatosensory cortex and certain sites in the brainstem (Philips, 2003; Berridge, 2003). </s><s n="s7.7;p14.14">It is not clear whether these structures by which we are conscious of reward processes represent those core processes accurately or whether they can influence those same processes. </s></p></div1></body><back><div1 type="bibliography"><head>References</head><p>Berridge, K. C. (2003) Pleasures of the brain. <hi rend="italic">Brain and Cognition</hi> (52) p. 106-128</p><p>Berridge, K. C. &amp; Robinson, T. E. (1998) What is the role of dopamine in reward: hedonic impact, reward learning, or incentive salience? <hi rend="italic">Brain Research Review</hi> (28) p. 309-369</p><p>Cardinal, R. N., Parkinson, J. A., Hall, J., &amp; Everitt, B. J. (2002) Emotion and motivation: the role of the amygdala, ventral striatum, and prefrontal cortex. <hi rend="italic">Neuroscience and biobehavioral reviews</hi> (26) p. 321-352</p><p>Esch, T. &amp; Stefano, G. B. (2004) The neurobiology of pleasure, reward processes, addiction and their health implications. <hi rend="italic">Neuroendocrinology Letters</hi> 25(4) p. 235-251</p><p>Gagliardi, S. (ed.) (2003) <hi rend="italic">Mind Brain &amp; Behavior I</hi> coursenotes. Accessed online: <seg type="URL" n="http://courses.umassmed.edu/mbb1/2003/index.cfm"/></p><p>Grossman, S. P. (1994). <hi rend="italic">Reinforcing effects of electrical brain stimulation</hi>. Accessed online: <seg type="URL" n="http://www.wireheading.com/brainstim/"/>.</p><p>Hooper, J. &amp; Teresi, D. (1991) The Three-Pound Universe</p><p>Lingford-hughes, A. &amp; Nutt, D. (2003) Neurobiology of addiction and its implications for treatment. <hi rend="italic">British journal of psychiatry</hi> (182) p. 97-100</p><p>Joseph, R. (2000) Neuropsychiatry, Neuropsychology, Clinical Neuroscience. New York: Academic press.</p><p>McBridge, W. J., Murphy, J. M. &amp; Ikemoto, S. (1999) Localization of brain reinforcement mechanisms: intracranial self-administration and intracranial place conditioning studies. <hi rend="italic">Behavioural Brain Research</hi> (101) p. 129-152</p><p>Miyasato, K. (2001) Recent advances in research on nicotine dependence and reward mechanism. <hi rend="italic">Nippon Yakurigaku Zasshi</hi> 117(1) p. 27-34</p><p>Nader, K., Bechara, A. &amp; van der Kooy, D. (1997) Neurobiological constraints on behavioral models of motivation. <hi rend="italic">Annual Review of Psychology</hi> (48) p. 85-114</p><p>Philips, H. (2003). The pleasure seekers. <hi rend="italic">New Scientist</hi>, October 11.</p><p>Rosenzweig, M. R., Breedlove, S. M., Leiman, A. L. (2002). <hi rend="italic">Biological Psychology</hi>. Massachusetts: Sinauer Associates, Inc.</p><p>Schultz, W. (2001) Reward signalling by dopamine neurons. <hi rend="italic">Neuroscientist</hi> (7) p. 293-302</p><p>Walters, R. J. (2005) A brief guide to neurotransmitter systems. Accessed online: <seg type="URL" n="http://www.cellscience.com/CCA.htm"/>.</p><p>Wilson, J. F. (2003) <hi rend="italic">Biological Foundations of Human Behavior</hi>. Canada: Wadsworth/Thomson Learning</p><p>Wise, R. A. (1998) Drug-activation of brain reward pathways. <hi rend="italic">Drug and Alcohol Dependence</hi> (51) p. 13-22</p><p>Wise, R. A. &amp; Rompre, P. P. (1989a) Brain dopamine and reward. <hi rend="italic">Annual Review of Psychology</hi> (40) 191-225</p><p>Wise, R. A. &amp; Rompre, P. P. (1989b) Opioid-neuroleptic interaction in brainstem self stimulation. <hi rend="italic">Brain Research</hi> 477(1-2) p. 144-151</p><p>Zigmond., M., Bloom., F., Landis, S., Roberts, J. &amp; Squire, L. (1999) <hi rend="italic">Fundamental Neuroscience</hi>. Academic Press.</p></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
