<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_0058d" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Stat Lab C - Data Summaries</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">Evaluated as candidate compound assignment. Assigned to S4: set of tasks/questions/exercises: non-compound</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">1</p><p n="date">2003-12</p><p n="module title">Statistical Laboratory I</p><p n="module code">ST104</p><p n="genre family">Exercise</p><p n="discipline">Mathematics</p><p n="disciplinary group">PS</p><p n="grade">D</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">1573</p><p n="number of s-units">81</p><p n="number of p">37</p><p n="number of tables">5</p><p n="number of figures">4</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">1</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">29</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">19.4</p><p n="average s-units per p">2.2</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">complex but non-compound assignment (see notesStmt for details)</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">f</p><p n="year of birth">1984</p><p n="first language">English</p><p n="education">UKA</p><p n="course">Mathematics, Operational Research, Statistics and Economics</p><p n="student ID">0058</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><titlePart rend="bold"><name type="student name"/></titlePart><docTitle><titlePart rend="bold">Stat Lab C - Data Summaries ST104</titlePart></docTitle></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined">Report 1</head><p n="p1.37"><s n="s1.1;p1.37">Stem and Leaf Plots to show how ascorbate affects the sample survival time in days for each cancer type. </s></p><p n="p2.37"><s n="s1.1;p2.37">Key for each plot: </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p3.37"><s n="s1.2;p3.37">Stem and Leaf Plots are a square root transformation of the data. </s><s n="s2.2;p3.37">Truncation of the values of the square roots has been used. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p4.37"><s n="s1.1;p4.37">Stem is in 10's, Leaf is in 1's. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p5.37"><s n="s1.1;p5.37">Units are split: . denotes values from 0-4, * denotes values from 5-9. </s></p><table id="BAWE_0058d-tab.001"><head>STOMACH:</head><row><cell/></row></table><table id="BAWE_0058d-tab.002"><head>BRONCHUS:</head><row><cell/></row></table><table id="BAWE_0058d-tab.003"><head>COLON:</head><row><cell/></row></table><table id="BAWE_0058d-tab.004"><head>OVARY:</head><row><cell/></row></table><table id="BAWE_0058d-tab.005"><head>BREAST:</head><row><cell/></row></table><div2><head>Five figure Summaries (minimum value, lower quartile, median, upper quartile, maximum value)</head><list type="simple"><item>Stomach (25, 45.75, 124, 400, 1112)</item><item>Bronchus (20, 70, 155, 245.25, 859)</item><item>Colon (20, 186.75, 372, 523.5, 1843)</item><item>Ovary (89, 201, 406, 1234, 2970)</item><item>Breast (24, 721, 1166, 1748.25, 3808)</item></list><p n="p6.37"><s n="s1.1;p6.37">See Box Plots </s></p></div2><div2><head>Summary of Data:</head><p rend="bulleted" n="p7.37"><s n="s1.5;p7.37">Each data set seems to have similar minimum values for survival however the maximum values vary greatly. </s><s n="s2.5;p7.37">These could possibly be outliers. </s><s n="s3.5;p7.37">Therefore, it is best to compare where the majority of values in the data set fall. </s><s n="s4.5;p7.37">From this we can see that on the whole Ascorbate seems to have the greatest affect on Breast Cancer as this has one of the highest maximum values as well as a very high lower quartile. </s><s n="s5.5;p7.37">We can see from the stem and leaf plot that there are many values bunched together with high survival times compared to the other samples. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p8.37"><s n="s1.1;p8.37">From this data ascorbate seems to have the second best effect on Colon and a similar effect on Bronchus and Stomach although it seems to work slightly better on Bronchus Cancer than stomach cancer. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p9.37"><s n="s1.3;p9.37">It is hard to compare the effect on Ovarian Cancer as due to the small sample size it is hard to comment on the modality (where most of the values lie). </s><s n="s2.3;p9.37">Ascorbate appears to work very well as the minimum survival time is high and this is a feature of all the other values throughout the five figure summary. </s><s n="s3.3;p9.37">However, to gain proper conclusions we need a larger data sample.Each data set except the ovary set is positively skewed. </s></p></div2><div2><head>Constructive Criticism:</head><p rend="bulleted" n="p10.37"><s n="s1.2;p10.37">The samples are of varying sizes therefore it is difficult to compare. </s><s n="s2.2;p10.37">A larger sample size is generally more of an accurate representation than a small one as sampling variation decreases. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p11.37"><s n="s1.1;p11.37">We do not know anything about the age of the people in the sample and this may make a large difference to how ascorbate affects the cancer. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p12.37"><s n="s1.1;p12.37">Gender would also be useful to know in order to compare effectiveness although obviously the breast and ovarian cancer only affect women. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p13.37"><s n="s1.1;p13.37">In order to have a clear idea on the effectiveness of ascorbate we must compare each sample o a sample that has not been treated with ascorbate - we do not know how the treatment has actually changed the normal survival times. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p14.37"><s n="s1.2;p14.37">Although we know that the cancer in each patient was advanced we do not know their predicted survival time without taking ascorbate. </s><s n="s2.2;p14.37">It would be interesting to compare predicted to actual survival time. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p15.37"><s n="s1.2;p15.37">We do not know how each sample has been chosen - are they all patients of a particular doctor who advocates this treatment? </s><s n="s2.2;p15.37">In this case the sample is not random. </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined">Report 3</head><figure id="BAWE_0058d-fig.001"><head>Scatter diagram to compare 200m times to 100m times</head></figure><p n="p16.37"><s n="s1.2;p16.37">The coach can use the rough equation that y=0.605x - 2.036 where y= 100m time and x= 200m time. </s><s n="s2.2;p16.37">Obviously this equation can also be used to find the 200m time from the 100m time by re-arranging to x= (y+2.036)/0.605 </s></p><p n="p17.37"><s n="s1.2;p17.37">There is a positive correlation. </s><s n="s2.2;p17.37">As the length of time it takes to run 200m increases, the length of time it takes to run 100m increases. </s></p><div2><head>Constructive Criticism:</head><p rend="bulleted" n="p18.37"><s n="s1.2;p18.37">The data is based on sprinters whose best event is the 200m because to find the sprinters their 200m times had to be below 21.2 seconds. </s><s n="s2.2;p18.37">Therefore it may be acceptable to use the time of sprinters who are best at 200m to find their 100m time but not vice versa. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p19.37"><s n="s1.2;p19.37">The data is based on some of the best sprinters in the UK. This is very specific data and not representative of every athlete in UK. It is very difficult for it to represent hardly any athletes as the best athletes will obviously train much more and harder than an average person who runs for fun. </s><s n="s2.2;p19.37">The coach should be very careful who applies his predictions too. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p20.37"><s n="s1.4;p20.37">The data is specific to the year 1998. </s><s n="s2.4;p20.37">This is now 5 years ago and the data could be out of date. </s><s n="s3.4;p20.37">For example new training machines may have been brought in which could affect the relationship between the two best times. </s><s n="s4.4;p20.37">In order to gain a broader idea it would be useful to use the same data from a number of years up to the most recent year possible (2002). </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p21.37"><s n="s1.2;p21.37">The sample only contains male sprinters. </s><s n="s2.2;p21.37">The coach cannot apply the prediction to female sprinters as the relationship between their 200m time and the 100m time could be very different. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p22.37"><s n="s1.5;p22.37">A coach should be very wary over which distances he applies this predictive equation to. </s><s n="s2.5;p22.37">200m sprint and 100m sprint are relatively similar events. </s><s n="s3.5;p22.37">The equation cannot use a 200m time to predict a 1500m time and vice versa. </s><s n="s4.5;p22.37">The coach should stick to 200m and 100m predictions and carry out a similar process if he wishes to predict athletes' potential at different distances. </s><s n="s5.5;p22.37">For example use a relationship between 800m and 1500m times. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p23.37"><s n="s1.3;p23.37">We do not know the age of the sprinters involved (although it may be easy to find out). </s><s n="s2.3;p23.37">As the sample is probably made up of professional sprinters they will most likely be adults of 18 years or over. </s><s n="s3.3;p23.37">We should therefore not apply these results to children who may not have developed to their full potential yet meaning that the relationship between their best times at each distance may be different. </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined">Report 2</head><div2><head>a)</head><p rend="bulleted" n="p24.37"><s n="s1.1;p24.37">Sample Mean = x = 0.803 IgM (g/l) (to 3 decimal places) </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p25.37"><s n="s1.1;p25.37">Sample Median = x <hi rend="sub">m</hi>= 0.7 IgM (g/l) </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p26.37"><s n="s1.2;p26.37">There is not a single mode. </s><s n="s2.2;p26.37">38 children (the highest number) have 0.7 IgM (g/l) and 38 children have 0.8 IgM (g/l). </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p27.37"><s n="s1.1;p27.37">10% point of distribution = 0.4 IgM (g/l) </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p28.37"><s n="s1.1;p28.37">90% point of distribution = 1.4 IgM (g/l) </s></p></div2><div2><div3><head>b) i)</head><figure id="BAWE_0058d-fig.002"><head>Graph to show square root transformation of IgM data</head></figure><p n="p29.37"><s n="s1.3;p29.37">A square root transformation reduces the kurtosis of the distribution slightly so producing a smoother distribution. </s><s n="s2.3;p29.37">The right-hand tail is also reduced meaning that the data is slightly more symmetric than with no transformation at all. </s><s n="s3.3;p29.37">The range of variation of the IgM values is decreased. </s></p></div3><div3><head>ii)</head><figure id="BAWE_0058d-fig.003"><head>Graph to show log transformation of IgM data</head></figure><p n="p30.37"><s n="s1.3;p30.37">A log transformation produces the most symmetric distribution of the three. </s><s n="s2.3;p30.37">Kurtosis decreases and the right-hand tail is also reduced considerably more than in the square root transformation. </s><s n="s3.3;p30.37">We can see that the range of variation of the IgM values decreases and that they range from -1 to 0.65. with the maximum point at -0.1 therefore showing it is almost symmetrical. </s></p></div3><div3><head>iii)</head><figure id="BAWE_0058d-fig.004"><head>Chart to show the frequency distribution of immuniglobin (IgM) levels in children (no transformation)</head></figure><p n="p31.37"><s n="s1.2;p31.37">No transformation produces a distribution which is relatively peaked compared to the previous two we have used. </s><s n="s2.2;p31.37">The data is more heavily skewed to the right than in the log and square root transformations and obviously the range of IgM values is much larger. </s></p></div3></div2><div2><head>c) Constructive Criticism:</head><p rend="bulleted" n="p32.37"><s n="s1.2;p32.37">Although we know that the sample contains children between the ages of 6 months and 6 years the data does not show us which children are within which age categories. </s><s n="s2.2;p32.37">This may be quite useful to know in order to compare whether immunoglobin levels change with age. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p33.37"><s n="s1.3;p33.37">We do not know how the sample was chosen or what population it is supposed to represent. </s><s n="s2.3;p33.37">If it is supposed to represent the population of 6 month to 6 year olds in the UK is it a random from around the country with many different backgrounds included? </s><s n="s3.3;p33.37">The sample is relatively small for this to be the case so we must be careful who we apply our conclusions to. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p34.37"><s n="s1.4;p34.37">We must be careful of outliers. </s><s n="s2.4;p34.37">Each 0.1 level of immunoglobin up to 1.8 g/l has at least 3 children with that level. </s><s n="s3.4;p34.37">However after this the measurements become more sporadic with the higher levels having only one child with that level. </s><s n="s4.4;p34.37">4.5 g/l seems especially higher than the other measured levels. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p35.37"><s n="s1.4;p35.37">The data is from 1983. </s><s n="s2.4;p35.37">This is 20 years ago and so may not be relevant to today's 6 month to 6 year olds. </s><s n="s3.4;p35.37">Medical practices and childcare techniques will have changed over 20 years. </s><s n="s4.4;p35.37">For a more accurate representation we should use a more recent sample. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p36.37"><s n="s1.4;p36.37">We do not know whether the measurement of the immunoglobin by laser nephelometry is a reliable measurement. </s><s n="s2.4;p36.37">We have also not been told how the results have been collected. </s><s n="s3.4;p36.37">For example we do not know when, where and by whom the data was collected. </s><s n="s4.4;p36.37">More information is needed in order to gauge the accuracy of the data. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p37.37"><s n="s1.3;p37.37">We have not been told which gender the children in the sample are. </s><s n="s2.3;p37.37">It would be useful to know this in order to compare whether immunoglobin levels differ between the genders. </s><s n="s3.3;p37.37">In addition if the children sampled were only male/ female we could not apply this to all 6 month to 6 year olds. </s></p></div2></div1></body><back/></text></TEI.2>
