<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_0058b" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Stat Lab B - Simple Summaries</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">Evaluated as candidate compound assignment. Assigned to S4: set of tasks/questions/exercises: non-compound</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">1</p><p n="date">2003-12</p><p n="module title">Statistical Laboratory I</p><p n="module code">ST104</p><p n="genre family">Exercise</p><p n="discipline">Mathematics</p><p n="disciplinary group">PS</p><p n="grade">D</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">551</p><p n="number of s-units">43</p><p n="number of p">35</p><p n="number of tables">1</p><p n="number of figures">0</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">6</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">25</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">12.8</p><p n="average s-units per p">1.2</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">complex but non-compound assignment (see notesStmt for details)</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">f</p><p n="year of birth">1984</p><p n="first language">English</p><p n="education">UKA</p><p n="course">Mathematics, Operational Research, Statistics and Economics</p><p n="student ID">0058</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><docTitle><titlePart rend="bold">Stat Lab B Simple Summaries</titlePart></docTitle></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="section"><head>Stem in 100s, Leaf in 10s</head><table id="BAWE_0058b-tab.001"><row><cell/></row></table><list type="simple"><item>Min value : 39</item><item>LQ: 64</item><item>Median: 242.5</item><item>UQ: 840 </item><item>Max: 1413</item></list><p rend="bulleted" n="p1.35"><s n="s1.1;p1.35">Bimodal and asymmetric </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p2.35"><s n="s1.1;p2.35">About ½ of the time there are less than 200 reported cases </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p3.35"><s n="s1.1;p3.35">The other large amounts of reported cases of measles centred around 900-1000 </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p4.35"><s n="s1.1;p4.35">2 epidemic outbreaks - 2 extreme data points denote the peaks of the outbreaks. </s></p><p n="p5.35"><s n="s1.1;p5.35">From Scatter Graph of Data.... </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p6.35"><s n="s1.1;p6.35">Data collected at equal time intervals thus constitutes a time series </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p7.35"><s n="s1.1;p7.35">One can clearly see epidemic outbreaks </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p8.35"><s n="s1.2;p8.35">Randomness? </s><s n="s2.2;p8.35">Future observations may depend on past observations b/c future cases arise from previous ones </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p9.35"><s n="s1.1;p9.35">Scatter points above 45 degreeline refer to the times when the infection/ epidemic is rising and points below the 45 degree are times when epidemic/ infection is falling. </s></p><p n="p10.35"><s n="s1.1;p10.35">Constructive Crit: 5 points </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p11.35"><s n="s1.1;p11.35">Only reported cases- some people may have not reported </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p12.35"><s n="s1.1;p12.35">(what if someone lives in Birmingham but goes to GP outside?) </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p13.35"><s n="s1.1;p13.35">If people have measles for over fortnight are they counted twice? </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p14.35"><s n="s1.1;p14.35">Other useful info e.g. ages may have been useful </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p15.35"><s n="s1.1;p15.35">Interesting to see 20 yr data not jus 2 yr </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p16.35"><s n="s1.1;p16.35">Data may look diff if vaccination intro. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head>2. See graphs</head><list type="simple"><head>Self: </head><item>Min: 102</item><item>LQ: 130</item><item>Median: 144</item><item>UQ: 149</item><item>Max: 163</item></list><list type="simple"><head>Cross:</head><item>Min: 96</item><item>LQ: 153</item><item>Median: 172</item><item>UQ: 177</item><item>Max: 188</item></list><p n="p17.35"><s rend="bold" n="s1.1;p17.35">Summary of data: </s></p><p n="p18.35"><s n="s1.1;p18.35">See above </s></p><p n="p19.35"><s n="s1.2;p19.35">2 erroneous values where the height of the cross fertilized plant &lt; self fertilized. </s><s n="s2.2;p19.35">Both cross values are 96- has some rounding taken place? </s></p><p n="p20.35"><s rend="bold" n="s1.1;p20.35">Constructive Crit </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p21.35"><s n="s1.1;p21.35">Height associated with health but are other measures of health of a plant a good/ better indicator? </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p22.35"><s n="s1.1;p22.35">Plants that grow best in the field do not necess grow best in lab. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p23.35"><s n="s1.1;p23.35">96's- rounded? </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p24.35"><s n="s1.1;p24.35">Median diff in heights is a more appropriate comparison than the mean. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p25.35"><s n="s1.1;p25.35">2 outliers are at either end of the data set - if plants in a row could be affected disease/ pest </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p26.35"><s n="s1.1;p26.35">Any other plants included and omitted because died? </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head>3. </head><p n="p27.35"><s n="s1.1;p27.35">Five Figure Summary </s></p><list type="simple"><head>Presidents:</head><item>0, 6.25, 13.5, 21.5,36</item></list><list type="simple"><head>Popes</head><item>0, 5.75, 10.5, 18.25, 32</item></list><list type="simple"><head>Monarchs</head><item>6, 9.5,13, 29, 63</item></list><p n="p28.35"><s n="s1.1;p28.35">Draw a box plot to compare </s></p><p n="p29.35"><s n="s1.1;p29.35">Survival times appear highest for monarchs - considerably higher than for presidents and popes. </s></p><p n="p30.35"><s n="s1.1;p30.35">Constructive Crit: </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p31.35"><s n="s1.2;p31.35">Zeros: seem to be quite a few for presidents and popes- is this because no data for this specific person or did they just die less than a year after inauguration/ election? </s><s n="s2.2;p31.35">When is the time rounded to a year? </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p32.35"><s n="s1.1;p32.35">Do not have the same sample size for each set - difficult to compare? </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p33.35"><s n="s1.4;p33.35">Working off very large time period- 1690-1990. </s><s n="s2.4;p33.35">Life expectancy has changed a lot in these years and do not have the data close to hand as when each of these people lived. </s><s n="s3.4;p33.35">Is difficult to compare a pope living in 1990 to a monarch living in 1700 etc. </s><s n="s4.4;p33.35">Would be good to group them all into categories. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p34.35"><s n="s1.3;p34.35">How have these been selected? </s><s n="s2.3;p34.35">Are they all of the popes/ presidents/ monarchs? </s><s n="s3.3;p34.35">Is this a random sample or where these people simply the easiest to gain data about? </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p35.35"><s n="s1.1;p35.35">Does not include the the time in a persons life when they became pope/ president/ monarch- maybe monarchs (because it is birthright) come into office earlier than pope/ president which is why appear to survive longer after coronation than others after inauguration/ election. </s></p></div1></body><back/></text></TEI.2>
