<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_0061e" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Discuss the use of irony in Les Liaisons dangereuses</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">deleted: header: student number; footer: page numbers</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">2</p><p n="date">2003-12</p><p n="module title">Prelude to Revolution: 18th Century Literature and the Call for Social Change</p><p n="module code">FR227</p><p n="genre family">Essay</p><p n="discipline">other</p><p n="disciplinary group">AH</p><p n="grade">M</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">1458</p><p n="number of s-units">46</p><p n="number of p">8</p><p n="number of tables">0</p><p n="number of figures">0</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">0</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">0</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">31.7</p><p n="average s-units per p">5.8</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">m</p><p n="year of birth">1983</p><p n="first language">English</p><p n="education">UKA</p><p n="course">French and German</p><p n="student ID">0061</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><docTitle><titlePart rend="bold">Discuss the use of irony in <hi rend="italic">Les Liaisons dangereuses</hi></titlePart></docTitle></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="section"><p n="p1.8"><s n="s1.2;p1.8"><hi rend="italic">Les Liaisons Dangereuses</hi> is a deliberate attack on the futility and wickedness of sexual immorality and Laclos infuses the text with both blatant and subtle ironies in order to highlight the dangers of this evil. </s><s n="s2.2;p1.8">These ironical aspects are both evident in the plot and in the relationships between characters, whilst simultaneously being imbedded in the structure of the text. </s></p><p n="p2.8"><s n="s1.9;p2.8"><hi rend="italic">Les Liaisons dangereuses</hi> is written in the form of a series of letters and this status as an epistolary novel serves to immediately introduce an element of irony into the text; enabling Laclos to highlight the dichotomy between the proximity of the 'dangerous acquaintances' and the distance suggested by the form of the letter. </s><s n="s2.9;p2.8">The act of writing a letter implies an intimate and deeply personal relationship, yet this notion is subverted by Laclos, who explores the ways in which this form of expression can be corrupted and used perversely. </s><s n="s3.9;p2.8">This is apparent in la marquise de Merteuil's correspondence with Madame de Volanges, in which she advises her not to grant her daughter permission to marry Danceny on mercenary grounds, stating '<hi rend="italic">Soixante mille livres de rente dont</hi> [<hi rend="italic">Cecile</hi>]<hi rend="italic"> va jouir ne sont pas déjà tant quand on porte le nom de Danceny</hi>." </s><ref target="BAWE_0061e-ftnote.001"/><s n="s4.9;p2.8">In a letter to Valmont, however, her true feelings are revealed and her desire to destroy her confidante is exposed, writing '<hi rend="italic">faisons-en, de concert, le désespoir de sa</hi> [Cécile's]<hi rend="italic"> mère et de Gercourt</hi>'<ref target="BAWE_0061e-ftnote.002"/>. </s><s n="s5.9;p2.8">This highlights the ironic transformation of the letter from an intimate document expressing genuine emotion, into an instrument of deception. </s><s n="s6.9;p2.8">The order and time that the letters are received imbues the text with an additional source of irony. </s><s n="s7.9;p2.8">This is particularly evident in letter 126, in which Madame de Rosemonde praises la présidente de Tourvel for resisting the advances of the vicomte de Valmont. </s><s n="s8.9;p2.8">Whilst it is possible that this letter would have prevented the liaison between them, it is received by la présidente only after she has succumbed to Valmont's advances. </s><s n="s9.9;p2.8">The letter is therefore denied the ability to facilitate a change in la presidente's actions and is used by Laclos as a symbol of impotence and dramatic irony. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0061e-ftnote.001"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Laclos, C., <hi rend="italic">Les Liaisons dangereuses</hi> (Lausanne, 1960), p. 295 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0061e-ftnote.002"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid., p. 304 </s></p></note><p n="p3.8"><s n="s1.4;p3.8">One of the reasons as to why Merteuil and Valmont behave as they do towards other people is that they are jealous of each other's exploits, yet 'seek each other's admiration and plaudits." </s><ref target="BAWE_0061e-ftnote.003"/><s n="s2.4;p3.8">Letter 10 is one such example where la marquise includes a lengthy description of her satisfaction with her new lover Belleroche: '<hi rend="italic">j'</hi> <hi rend="italic">avais résolu que tout ce temps fût pour lui également délicieux</hi>'<ref target="BAWE_0061e-ftnote.004"/> this is answered with a description by Valmont of a night he spent with Émilie in letter 47. </s><s n="s3.4;p3.8">This rivalry of lovers continues throughout the novel and characterises their relationship. </s><s n="s4.4;p3.8">It is all the more ironic that, whilst they 'consider each other as the only audience whose applause is worth having, so that they depend on each other for praise which they are both equally reluctant to give'<ref target="BAWE_0061e-ftnote.005"/>, they become fierce rivals by the conclusion and succeed in destroying each other. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0061e-ftnote.003"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Davies, S., <hi rend="italic">Laclos.</hi> </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1"><hi rend="italic">Les Liaisons dangereuses</hi> (London, 1987), p. 19 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0061e-ftnote.004"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Laclos, C., op. cit., pp. 55-56 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0061e-ftnote.005"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Thody, P., <hi rend="italic">Laclos: Les Liaisons dangereuses</hi> (Scotland, 1970), p. 29 </s></p></note><p n="p4.8"><s n="s1.6;p4.8">It appears a safe assumption that Valmont is in love with la marquise and throughout the novel he constantly tries to impress and seduce her. </s><s n="s2.6;p4.8">The irony lies in the fact that Valmont, in order to be rewarded with one night with la marquise, attempts to seduce la présidente de Tourvel but ends up falling in love with her. </s><s n="s3.6;p4.8">The resulting confusion for Valmont paves the way for his downfall. </s><s n="s4.6;p4.8">The scapegrace's basic tenet is that falling in love leads to a loss of control, a langour to which he will never succomb; he and Merteuil are '<hi rend="italic">non susceptibles de passion qu'ils considèrent comme une faiblesse...</hi> </s><s rend="italic" n="s5.6;p4.8">Valmont projette de lui-même l'image du Don Juan idéal en quelque sort, celui pour qui la chair est pouvoir, mais qui garde la tête entièrement froide. </s><s n="s6.6;p4.8">'<ref target="BAWE_0061e-ftnote.006"/> This becomes all the more ironic as Valmont is destroyed at the end because of his attempt to exploit human emotions whilst attempting to remain immune to those of his own. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0061e-ftnote.006"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Therrien, M. B., <hi rend="italic">Les Liaisons dangereuses - Une Interprétation Psychologique</hi> (Paris, 1973), p. 203 </s></p></note><p n="p5.8"><s n="s1.5;p5.8">It becomes almost immediately obvious that Laclos is writing not entirely about true love but about the dangers of seduction as well. </s><s n="s2.5;p5.8">It could be contested that the sentient characters, ironically, are not bound merely by love - but almost by duty. </s><s n="s3.5;p5.8">La présidente wants to alleviate Valmont's malaise and le chevalier Danceny uses claims of distress on his beloved Cécile. </s><s n="s4.5;p5.8">In letter 77, Valmont skilfully uses reversal of reality to manipulate the truth and also la présidente thoughts, making him the victim and portraying her as the aggressor. </s><s n="s5.5;p5.8">He employs such verbs as '<hi rend="italic">punir...réfuser...détourner...abuser'</hi><ref target="BAWE_0061e-ftnote.007"/>to describe her behaviour and his sentiments include 'tendre...l'amour...l'amitié'.<ref target="BAWE_0061e-ftnote.008"/> This is an effective technique and Madame de Tourvel genuinely wrestles with her conscience and eventually capitulates which leads to her perfidy. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0061e-ftnote.007"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Laclos, C., op. cit., pp. 201-02 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0061e-ftnote.008"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid. </s></p></note><p n="p6.8"><s n="s1.5;p6.8">There are also smaller yet equally deliberate incongruities in the novel: whilst Madame de Tourvel is portrayed as completely innocent - '<hi rend="italic">différente des "autres femmes" qui se laissent séduire par la passion...</hi> </s><s n="s2.5;p6.8">[<hi rend="italic">elle est</hi>] <hi rend="italic">fière de son... système de valeurs</hi>'<ref target="BAWE_0061e-ftnote.009"/>, she arranges Valmont's actions to be watched, which is 'not an action beyond reproach'<ref target="BAWE_0061e-ftnote.010"/> and eventually commits adultery. </s><s n="s3.5;p6.8">The ironic treatment of relationships includes Danceny's assistance to Valmont in seducing his beloved Cécile, writing to persuade her that Valmont is on their side and '<hi rend="italic">la seule personne qui puisse nous</hi> [Cécile and Danceny]<hi rend="italic"> rapprocher l'un de l'autre</hi>'<ref target="BAWE_0061e-ftnote.011"/>. </s><s n="s4.5;p6.8">Perhaps the main sardonic relationship is that Cécile believes Madame de Merteuil to be her closest and most veracious confidante, whereas in la marquise's eyes Cécile is but a 'subsidiary intrigante worthy of only secondary roles... an object, a pleasure machine." </s><ref target="BAWE_0061e-ftnote.012"/><s n="s5.5;p6.8">Madame de Volanges only shows great concern when it is too late and her daughter has already been seduced by Valmont. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0061e-ftnote.009"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Therrien, M. B., op. cit., p. 207 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0061e-ftnote.010"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Davies, S., op. cit., p. 30 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0061e-ftnote.011"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Laclos, C., op. cit., p. 260 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0061e-ftnote.012"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Runte, R., <hi rend="italic">Authors and Actors: The Characters in Les Liaisons dangereuses</hi> in Free, L., ed., <hi rend="italic">Laclos - Critical Approaches to Les Liaisons dangereuses</hi> (Madrid, 1978), p. 126 </s></p></note><p n="p7.8"><s n="s1.9;p7.8">The ending of the novel and the punishment the characters receive from Laclos is ironic in itself. </s><s n="s2.9;p7.8">Although he has punished the vice of his <hi rend="italic">libertins</hi>, Laclos, paradoxically, does not reward virtue, the death of la présidente is not a moral one and in the last line of one of the final three letters in the novel Madame de Volanges explains: '<hi rend="italic">Je vois bien dans tout cela les méchants punis; mais je n'y trouve null consolation pour leurs malheureuses victimes.</hi> </s><s n="s3.9;p7.8">'<ref target="BAWE_0061e-ftnote.013"/> Indeed, considering her punishment, convention would suggest that Merteuil would not succeed; yet, ironically, she does. </s><s n="s4.9;p7.8">La marquise controls everyone in the novel, and militates even against Valmont: 'She has experimented with counterfeiting emotions and has discovered that she can mislead others." </s><ref target="BAWE_0061e-ftnote.014"/><s n="s5.9;p7.8">Whilst Valmont's egocentric image is that of complete control, shown perhaps through his self directed usage of heroic images - such as his donation to save the troubled family who gathered round him exclaiming: '<hi rend="italic">Tombons tous aux pieds de cette image de Dieu...</hi> </s><s n="s6.9;p7.8">[and Valmont thought he] <hi rend="italic">ne ressemblais</hi>[t] <hi rend="italic">pas mal au héros d'un drame</hi>'.<ref target="BAWE_0061e-ftnote.015"/> Despite this la marquise 'knows his vanity and alternately flatters and teases his delusions of grandeur to goad him into action." </s><ref target="BAWE_0061e-ftnote.016"/><s n="s7.9;p7.8">It is ironic, therefore that she succeeds at all but she does destroy Valmont - '<hi rend="italic">le seul homme qu'elle ait sans doute jamais aimé</hi>'<ref target="BAWE_0061e-ftnote.017"/> - as he faces Danceny in a duel and Gercourt never marries Cécile who is forced to take refuge in a convent. </s><s n="s8.9;p7.8">Such is human nature, the reader does not hate Merteuil or Valmont until the end of the novel as 'they appeal to an aspect of our own personality which...we feel we ought to suppress'<ref target="BAWE_0061e-ftnote.018"/>. </s><s n="s9.9;p7.8">This is ironic and Laclos here deliberately manipulates the reader's emotions to shock him with the novel's dramatic conclusion. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0061e-ftnote.013"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid., p.466 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0061e-ftnote.014"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Thelander, D., <hi rend="italic">Laclos and the Epistolary Novel</hi> (Genève, 1963), p. 159 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0061e-ftnote.015"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Laclos, C., op. cit., p. 74 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0061e-ftnote.016"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Runte, R., op. cit., p. 129 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0061e-ftnote.017"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Delmas, A., <hi rend="italic">À la recherché des Liaisons dangereuses</hi> (France, 1964), p. 303 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0061e-ftnote.018"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Thody, P., op. cit., p. 13 </s></p></note><p n="p8.8"><s n="s1.6;p8.8">It is ironic; therefore, that Merteuil is destroyed as well. </s><s n="s2.6;p8.8">By punishing her more than Valmont, Laclos stresses that she placed too much confidence in her own abilities. </s><s n="s3.6;p8.8">Losing her lawsuit and having letters 81 and 85 circulated in Paris is not enough for the author and 'physical retribution is exacted through her contraction of smallpox, and her consequent disfigurement is emblematic of her moral corruption." </s><ref target="BAWE_0061e-ftnote.019"/><s n="s4.6;p8.8">Yet more ironic is that it is her own 'act of single folly'<ref target="BAWE_0061e-ftnote.020"/> which destroys her; that of implicating Valmont to Danceny which allows Valmont revenge as he passes on to him their correspondence. </s><s n="s5.6;p8.8">Indeed it is the height of irony that one who boasts so much of her '<hi rend="italic">supériorité sur vous</hi> [Valmont]'<ref target="BAWE_0061e-ftnote.021"/>, sees herself as invincible; as larger than life and '<hi rend="italic">est la première femme qui ne soit pas soumise à l'homme...affirme son independence, revendique et exerce ses droits</hi>'<ref target="BAWE_0061e-ftnote.022"/> should '<hi rend="italic">réagit par sa jalousie, et... détruit elle-même par ses reactions impulsives le success de son enterprise.</hi> </s><s n="s6.6;p8.8">'<ref target="BAWE_0061e-ftnote.023"/> As a reader one feels also that a similar situation with Valmont could have arisen if he had only admitted to himself that he was in fact, in love with la présidente. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0061e-ftnote.019"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Davies, S., op. cit., p. 25 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0061e-ftnote.020"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Thody, P., op. cit., p. 7 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0061e-ftnote.021"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Laclos, C., op.cit., p. 215 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0061e-ftnote.022"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Delmas, A., op. cit., p. 305 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0061e-ftnote.023"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Therrien,. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">M. B., op. cit., p. 205 </s></p></note></div1></body><back><div1 type="bibliography"><head rend="bold">Bibliography</head><p>Davies, S., <hi rend="italic">Laclos. Les Liaisons dangereuses</hi> (London, 1987)</p><p>Laclos, C., <hi rend="italic">Les Liaisons dangereuses</hi> (Lausanne, 1960)</p><p>Thody, P., <hi rend="italic">Laclos: Les Liaisons dangereuses</hi> (Scotland, 1970)</p><p>Therrien, M. B., <hi rend="italic">Les Liaisons dangereuses - Une Interprétation Psychologique</hi> (Paris, 1973)</p><p>Thelander, D., <hi rend="italic">Laclos and the Epistolary Novel</hi> (Genève, 1963)</p><p>Free, L., <hi rend="italic">Laclos - Critical Approaches to Les Liaisons dangereuses</hi> (Madrid, 1978)</p><p>Delmas, A., <hi rend="italic">À la recherché des Liaisons dangereuses</hi> (France, 1964)</p><p>Messière, P., <hi rend="italic">Les Liaisons dangereuses</hi> (Paris, 1991)</p></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
