<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_0061a" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Compare the representation of war in 'Wo warst du, Adam?' and 'Die Brücke.'</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note/></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">1</p><p n="date">2002-12</p><p n="module title">Writers, Media and Society in Contemporary Germany</p><p n="module code">GE108</p><p n="genre family">Essay</p><p n="discipline">other</p><p n="disciplinary group">AH</p><p n="grade">M</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">3201</p><p n="number of s-units">116</p><p n="number of p">14</p><p n="number of tables">0</p><p n="number of figures">0</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">0</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">0</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">27.6</p><p n="average s-units per p">8.3</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">m</p><p n="year of birth">1983</p><p n="first language">English</p><p n="education">UKA</p><p n="course">French and German</p><p n="student ID">0061</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><docTitle><titlePart rend="bold"> Compare the representation of war in 'Wo warst du, Adam?' and 'Die Brücke.'</titlePart></docTitle></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="section"><p n="p1.14"><s n="s1.3;p1.14">When looking to compare the representation of war in <hi rend="italic">Wo warst du Adam?</hi> </s><s n="s2.3;p1.14">and <hi rend="italic">Die Brücke</hi>, one must firstly examine how war is portrayed in both the novel and the film before beginning to draw parallels between their representations. </s><s n="s3.3;p1.14">There are a number of concordant themes portraying war as a horrific and futile experience within both oeuvres and the purpose of this essay is to examine and compare the representations of these wartime representations thematically. </s></p><p n="p2.14"><s n="s1.12;p2.14">The paramount theme in both the novel and the film is that of futility and Böll and Wicki provide us, as a reader and a viewer, with several examples of war being pointless and meaningless. </s><s n="s2.12;p2.14">The representations of futility can be split into various groups. </s><s n="s3.12;p2.14">One example is the whole war itself being completely futile; this is seen in the very beginning of <hi rend="italic">Wo warst du, Adam?</hi> </s><s n="s4.12;p2.14">as Böll describes the appearance of a General - "<hi rend="italic">Der General sah müde aus</hi>." </s><ref target="BAWE_0061a-ftnote.001"/><s n="s5.12;p2.14">This is significant as it is a man who is high up in command in the German Army, and ergo one who should evoke confidence and enthusiasm and inspire a will for success in his soldiers, appears apathetic and resigned. </s><s n="s6.12;p2.14">In fact: "<hi rend="italic">Dieser magere, gelbe Generalshals ohne Schmuck lieβ an verlorene Schlachten denken, miβlungene Rückzüge</hi>"<ref target="BAWE_0061a-ftnote.002"/>. </s><s n="s7.12;p2.14">At the start also, Böll makes a point of showing that the soldiers are merely numbers, they are nameless, inhuman pawns with which the Officers can do what they want. </s><s n="s8.12;p2.14">The view that the entire war itself is pointless concurs with the theory of Charlotte W. Ghurye, who states that at this point in history, all German efforts are futile and Böll makes this point by emphasising the ever-present confidence of the German soldiers in the continuing success of the Nazi war machine. </s><s n="s9.12;p2.14">This is a myth yet "life goes on...in the hospital... in the school... and at the inn...in a self-assured manner as if the Germans were still victors." </s><ref target="BAWE_0061a-ftnote.003"/><s n="s10.12;p2.14">This pointlessness of war is present in <hi rend="italic">Die Brücke</hi> where the boys are sent off to train and prepare for next-day combat, but are only taught how to retreat. </s><s n="s11.12;p2.14">The point, therefore, is mirrored in the film but it is portrayed differently as there is the acceptance in the film that victory is already lost, yet Böll's characters are still completely "oblivious of the fact that their defeat will come in a matter of hours"<ref target="BAWE_0061a-ftnote.004"/>. </s><s n="s12.12;p2.14">War is portrayed by Böll, according to Bernd Balzer "<hi rend="italic">als übermächtige Sinnlosigkeit, die dem Einzelnen einen Ausweg nur in die Transzendenz gestattet."</hi><ref target="BAWE_0061a-ftnote.005"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0061a-ftnote.001"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Heinrich Böll, <hi rend="italic">Wo warst du, Adam?</hi> </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">(Munich, 1972), p.7 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0061a-ftnote.002"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Heinrich Böll, <hi rend="italic">Wo warst du, Adam?</hi> </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">(Munich, 1972), p.7 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0061a-ftnote.003"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Charlotte W. Ghurye, <hi rend="italic">The Writer and Society</hi> (1976), p.23 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0061a-ftnote.004"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Charlotte W. Ghurye, <hi rend="italic">The Writer and Society</hi> (1976), p.23 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0061a-ftnote.005"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Bernd Balzer, <hi rend="italic">Humanität als ästhetisches Prinzip - Die Romane Heinrich Bölls</hi> (Königstein, 1980), p.47 </s></p></note><p n="p3.14"><s n="s1.11;p3.14">In both <hi rend="italic">Die Brücke</hi> and <hi rend="italic"> Wo warst du, Adam?</hi> </s><s n="s2.11;p3.14">There is a great sense of needless, human sacrifice which ties into the representation of war; for example in <hi rend="italic">Wo warst du, Adam?</hi> </s><s n="s3.11;p3.14">Bressen is sent back to the front even though he is unfit to fight. </s><s n="s4.11;p3.14">His injury is dismissed as "<hi rend="italic">Eine geradezu lächerlich geringfügige Verletzung der Kopfschwarte.</hi> </s><s n="s5.11;p3.14"><hi rend="italic">War in fünf Tagen abgeheilt."</hi><ref target="BAWE_0061a-ftnote.006"/> In <hi rend="italic">Die Brücke</hi> the average age for the attack is fifteen; boys still in school and with only one day's training (which was ironically spent learning to retreat) are sent on a hopeless mission when the war is, in effect, already lost. </s><s n="s6.11;p3.14">The Officer who speaks to inspire the soldiers sounds more than a little pessimistic when he gives the soldiers only the option of "<hi rend="italic">Kampf, Zieg oder Tot!"</hi><ref target="BAWE_0061a-ftnote.007"/> It is also completely pointless for the boys to die; they are only positioned at the Bridge to keep them out of harms way after a request from their teacher to their commanding officer. </s><s n="s7.11;p3.14">The bridge itself serves no strategic purpose and is in fact to be blown up. </s><s n="s8.11;p3.14">They are fighting not only a lost but also a pointless battle. </s><s n="s9.11;p3.14">Wicki uses the boys' enthusiasm for war as a tool to help emphasise how much of a needless death it is, as, should the boys have not appeared so keen to go to war in front of their teacher, he probably wouldn't have spoken with the Officer in the way in which he did. </s><s n="s10.11;p3.14">Böll, on the other hand, makes it clear throughout that it is a needless sacrifice in <hi rend="italic">Wo warst du, Adam?</hi> </s><s n="s11.11;p3.14">- Wicki makes us think, until the confrontation with the enemy that the boys will be successfully spared. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0061a-ftnote.006"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Heinrich Böll, <hi rend="italic">Wo warst du, Adam?</hi> </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">(Munich, 1972), p.23 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0061a-ftnote.007"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Bernhard Wicki, <hi rend="italic">Die Brücke (Film)</hi> (1959) </s></p></note><p n="p4.14"><s n="s1.10;p4.14">The theme of futility extends also to the realisation that most of the deaths are caused by logistical mistakes. </s><s n="s2.10;p4.14">For example, the removal of the dud that kills Scneider in <hi rend="italic">Wo warst du, Adam?</hi> </s><s n="s3.10;p4.14">had been ordered several times and, after the explosion, the Russians begin firing for a long time, however, "<hi rend="italic">Erst später merkten sie, daβ von der anderen Seite kein einziger Schuβ fiel."</hi><ref target="BAWE_0061a-ftnote.008"/> Finck receives contradicting orders and ends up getting killed whilst attempting to save the wine he carried rather than his own life; <hi rend="italic">"Finck stirbt einen sinnlosen Tod, weil er einen Koffer voller Weinflaschen mit sich schleppte."</hi><ref target="BAWE_0061a-ftnote.009"/> Those in command cannot decide whether to keep the bridge or not and in chapter eight: <hi rend="italic">"eine Brücke wird gebaut, um sie danach zu sprengen."</hi><ref target="BAWE_0061a-ftnote.010"/> The Lieutenant who speaks with Feinhals explains that he feels there are mistakes in the logistics of the war; "<hi rend="italic">meine Ausbildung hat den Staat einige nette Einfamilienhäuser gekostet, damit ich mir jetzt als Infanterist die Hucke vollmachen lasse, meine Seele aushauche, um nach Walhall zu fahren."</hi><ref target="BAWE_0061a-ftnote.011"/> In <hi rend="italic">Die Brücke</hi> the Sergeant assigned to look after the boys is shot by a fellow German soldier even though he has a perfectly legitimate reason for being there. </s><s n="s4.10;p4.14">These examples both show how simple, but more importantly, needless mistakes (often by those in command) lead to unnecessary death. </s><s n="s5.10;p4.14"><hi rend="italic">"In einem sinnlosen Kampf fallen alle Jungen bis auf einen"</hi><ref target="BAWE_0061a-ftnote.012"/> is one interpretation of the boys' needless death. </s><s n="s6.10;p4.14">The representations differ between the book and the film as Böll prolongs the effect, that is to say the effect of the mistakes, in these instances at least, comes fairly long after the mistake itself. </s><s n="s7.10;p4.14">Wicki's effect is perhaps a little more dramatic in the sense that it is immediate. </s><s n="s8.10;p4.14">This can be put down to the fact that, as a director, Wicki, does not have the luxury of allowing his viewer time to contemplate, as Böll might have in a book, as it is a film and only occurs over a matter of hours. </s><s n="s9.10;p4.14">It is therefore necessary to keep the viewer shocked and interested. </s><s n="s10.10;p4.14">Any deep thought and consideration must come afterwards. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0061a-ftnote.008"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Heinrich Böll, <hi rend="italic">Wo warst du, Adam?</hi> </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">(Munich, 1972), p.45 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0061a-ftnote.009"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1"><seg type="URL" n="http://www.pausenhof.de/referate/refdeu/refdeub009.asp"/> </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0061a-ftnote.010"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1"><seg type="URL" n="http://www.pausenhof.de/referate/refdeu/refdeub009.asp"/> </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0061a-ftnote.011"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Heinrich Böll, <hi rend="italic">Wo warst du, Adam?</hi> </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">(Munich, 1972), p.82 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0061a-ftnote.012"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1"><seg type="URL" n="http://clubfilmothek.bjf.info/filme/2910052.htm"/> </s></p></note><p n="p5.14"><s n="s1.8;p5.14">Böll makes the point in <hi rend="italic">Wo warst du, Adam?</hi> </s><s n="s2.8;p5.14">that war is futile in that no matter who one is, the fate of death cannot be avoided. </s><s n="s3.8;p5.14">There is certainly the feeling in <hi rend="italic">Wo warst du, Adam?</hi> </s><s n="s4.8;p5.14">that a Jew dies in the concentration camps, and a German on the battle field. </s><s n="s5.8;p5.14">Böll makes the point that war is so futile that everybody dies, no matter also at what stage the war is at. </s><s n="s6.8;p5.14">C.W. Ghurye states; "What constitutes the utter absurdity is the fact that he (Feinhals) is killed when the war is practically over, seconds before he is reunited with his parents"<ref target="BAWE_0061a-ftnote.013"/>. </s><s n="s7.8;p5.14">Wicki uses the dramatic tool of the vision of the young boys' death to convey his point of everybody being killed and at the end and this point links in with the representation of the horror of war - "Einzig Mutz bleibt, verlassen und verzweifelt, am Leben." </s><ref target="BAWE_0061a-ftnote.014"/><s n="s8.8;p5.14">Böll, by contrast, at this point in the book almost makes it sound normal and routine for Feinhals to get shot at this stage; such is the futility of war. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0061a-ftnote.013"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Charlotte W. Ghurye, <hi rend="italic">The Writer and Society</hi> (1976), p.26 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0061a-ftnote.014"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Peter Zander, <hi rend="italic">Bernhard Wicki</hi> (Berlin 1994), p.21 </s></p></note><p n="p6.14"><s n="s1.7;p6.14">The portrayal of relationships in wartime differs between the two mediums, however, both Böll and Wicki agree that they are futile. </s><s n="s2.7;p6.14">In <hi rend="italic">Die Brücke,</hi> such is the excitement and enthusiasm of the boys, the relationships are portrayed in only one way; that is to say it is only the mothers of the boys - not the boys themselves - who are particularly worried about their loved ones. </s><s n="s3.7;p6.14">In <hi rend="italic">Wo warst du, Adam?</hi> </s><s n="s4.7;p6.14">it is different as the main relationship is between Ilona and Feinhals, although they have both expressed their love for each other they know they cannot be together: <hi rend="italic">"in seiner Nähe gekommen war sie noch nicht...er hätte sie gern geküβt; nur kam sie nie in seine Nähe."</hi><ref target="BAWE_0061a-ftnote.015"/> Böll underlines the fact that it is because of the situation of war, C.W. Ghurye agrees that this relationship is "essentially ironical and can only lead to a dangerous, clandestine affair." </s><ref target="BAWE_0061a-ftnote.016"/><s n="s5.7;p6.14">Frau Susan also thinks of her husband but this is useless, as she has no idea where he is. </s><s n="s6.7;p6.14">Maria is made pregnant by Peter and, under normal circumstances, they could perhaps be together but this is made impossible by the war again as Peter is moved on shortly after. </s><s n="s7.7;p6.14">Both the director and the author, therefore portray relationships as futile during the war. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0061a-ftnote.015"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Heinrich Böll, <hi rend="italic">Wo warst du, Adam?</hi> </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">(Munich, 1972), p.62 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0061a-ftnote.016"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Charlotte W. Ghurye, <hi rend="italic">The Writer and Society</hi> (1976), p.25 </s></p></note><p n="p7.14"><s n="s1.20;p7.14">Another main theme in both <hi rend="italic">Wo warst du, Adam</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Die Brücke</hi> is one of escapism. </s><s n="s2.20;p7.14">This can happen sexually in the cases of Bressen - <hi rend="italic">"Das einzige, was ihn während dieser Zeit tröstete, war die Möglichkeit, mit ihren Frauen ab und zu ein Abenteuer zu bestehen."</hi><ref target="BAWE_0061a-ftnote.017"/> and Maria and Peter in <hi rend="italic">Wo warst du, Adam?</hi> </s><s n="s3.20;p7.14">and Barbara and Karl's father in <hi rend="italic">Die Brücke,</hi> in the form of denial or the search for escape into one's memory. </s><s n="s4.20;p7.14">The boys in <hi rend="italic">Die Brücke</hi> think of war; <hi rend="italic">"halb als nationale Verpflichtung, halb als romantisches Abenteuer."</hi><ref target="BAWE_0061a-ftnote.018"/> They cannot wait to be called up for service and Wicki emphasises the naivety of the boys at this point with the scenes of jubilation when one of them receives the first letter. </s><s n="s5.20;p7.14">This is a powerful image for the viewer who is shocked at the sight of such enthusiasm for war. </s><s n="s6.20;p7.14">They cannot wait to see the bridge where a bomb was rumoured to have dropped, and casually joke about the school being bombed - "Ich werde Churchill meinen Stundenplan schicken." </s><ref target="BAWE_0061a-ftnote.019"/><s n="s7.20;p7.14">Following this, when in the classroom, the boys discuss the war tactics they would pursue should they be in charge. </s><s n="s8.20;p7.14">This image is mirrored in Wo warst du, Adam? where Feinhals calls to Ilona: "wir spielen Generalstab, ein wunderbares Spiel"<ref target="BAWE_0061a-ftnote.020"/> and Ilona later describes it "wie Relief." </s><ref target="BAWE_0061a-ftnote.021"/><s n="s9.20;p7.14">Even after the boys are called up and positioned at the bridge Wicki still portrays them as thinking that it is not quite real - it has not sunk in to them that they are involved in a real war. </s><s n="s10.20;p7.14">They show their immaturity when wanting to shoot cans on the bridge. </s><s n="s11.20;p7.14">One boy asks their Sergeant if he could be stationed in an observation post similar to one that he held when the boys used to play children's games on that very bridge. </s><s n="s12.20;p7.14">This denial extends even after they face the enemy and they show great delight at successfully shooting them. </s><s n="s13.20;p7.14">These attitudes continue all the way up arguably until Karl dies. </s><s n="s14.20;p7.14">Böll portrays Filskeit as someone who does not like killing but carries out orders scrupulously, he uses his love of art and music as a form of escapism from the horror in which he finds himself; "(daβ) er jeden Neuankömmling zum Vorsingen bestellte und seine gesangliche Leistung auf der Karteikarte mit Noten versah"<ref target="BAWE_0061a-ftnote.022"/>. </s><s n="s15.20;p7.14">Another example is found in the form of Greck who yearns for a go on the "Schiffschaukel"<ref target="BAWE_0061a-ftnote.023"/> and "Diese Vergnüngen waren ihm nicht vergönnt gewesen...so öffentlich, blöde wie ein Affe, in der Luft herumzuschaukeln." </s><ref target="BAWE_0061a-ftnote.024"/><s n="s16.20;p7.14">Both Böll and Wicki therefore, portray their characters in a certain way to evoke sympathy, as they are in a terrible situation and try to find refuge from it by means which to us as a reader or viewer may seen simple or unreal. </s><s n="s17.20;p7.14">One representation specific to Böll is the use of the past as a sanctuary from the horrors of war; his "characters were continually in search of lost innocence." </s><ref target="BAWE_0061a-ftnote.025"/><s n="s18.20;p7.14">Alan Bance agrees. </s><s n="s19.20;p7.14">Bressen is one character to use as an example for this. </s><s n="s20.20;p7.14">When he sees the picture of the shepherd he remembers "daβ er früher eine Zeitlang Nicker in einem Hotel gewesen war, in einem sehr vornehmen Restaurant"<ref target="BAWE_0061a-ftnote.026"/> - these were happy times for him. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0061a-ftnote.017"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Heinrich Böll, <hi rend="italic">Wo warst du, Adam?</hi> </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">(Munich, 1972), p.20 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0061a-ftnote.018"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1"><seg type="URL" n="http://clubfilmothek.bjf.info/filme/2910052.htm"/> </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0061a-ftnote.019"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Bernhard Wicki, <hi rend="italic">Die Brücke (Film)</hi> (1959) </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0061a-ftnote.020"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Heinrich Böll, <hi rend="italic">Wo warst du, Adam?</hi> </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">(Munich, 1972), p.63 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0061a-ftnote.021"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Heinrich Böll, <hi rend="italic">Wo warst du, Adam?</hi> </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">(Munich, 1972), p.64 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0061a-ftnote.022"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Heinrich Böll, <hi rend="italic">Wo warst du, Adam?</hi> </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">(Munich, 1972), p.96 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0061a-ftnote.023"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Heinrich Böll, <hi rend="italic">Wo warst du, Adam?</hi> </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">(Munich, 1972), p.46 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0061a-ftnote.024"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Heinrich Böll, <hi rend="italic">Wo warst du, Adam?</hi> </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">(Munich, 1972), p.46 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0061a-ftnote.025"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Alan Bance, <hi rend="italic">The German Novel 1945-1960</hi> (Stuttgart 1980), p.40 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0061a-ftnote.026"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Heinrich Böll, <hi rend="italic">Wo warst du, Adam?</hi> </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">(Munich, 1972), p.17 </s></p></note><p n="p8.14"><s n="s1.8;p8.14">Given the fact that both pieces of work portray a horrific situation (the Second World War) one would expect to find reference to the horror and the inhumanity of war. </s><s n="s2.8;p8.14">Indeed the examples of this are many. </s><s n="s3.8;p8.14">Both Böll and Wicki show that death is a very common part of wartime practice and especially in <hi rend="italic">Wo warst du, Adam?</hi> </s><s n="s4.8;p8.14">these deaths are numerous and the human loss, particularly as affects Frau Susan, is devastating. </s><s n="s5.8;p8.14">Perhaps the most horrific death is that of Ilona who is shot by Filkskeit, a man who has spared other Jews and was thought not to be able to kill. </s><s n="s6.8;p8.14">C.W Churye puts this down to envy as Ilona possess both what he desires most ("beauty, stature, religious faith, and a perfect voice"<ref target="BAWE_0061a-ftnote.027"/>) and "all the qualities that his (Filkskeit's) own cherished demagogic racial theory denies the Jews." </s><ref target="BAWE_0061a-ftnote.028"/><s n="s7.8;p8.14">Alan Bance says that "it goes without saying that war is evil"<ref target="BAWE_0061a-ftnote.029"/> and this is shown in the death of Böll's characters. </s><s n="s8.8;p8.14">The inhumane aspect in the book comes arguably in the form of Filkskeit's selection basis for who should be killed and who should not, <hi rend="italic">"In seinem Lager kommen die Juden, die gut singen können in den Chor, die anderen in das Krematorium."</hi><ref target="BAWE_0061a-ftnote.030"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0061a-ftnote.027"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Charlotte W. Ghurye, <hi rend="italic">The Writer and Society</hi> (1976), p.26 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0061a-ftnote.028"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Charlotte W. Ghurye, <hi rend="italic">The Writer and Society</hi> (1976), p.26 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0061a-ftnote.029"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Alan Bance, <hi rend="italic">The German Novel 1945-1960</hi> (Stuttgart 1980), p.66 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0061a-ftnote.030"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1"><seg type="URL" n="http://www.pausenhof.de/referate/refdeu/refdeub009.asp"/> </s></p></note><p n="p9.14"><s n="s1.8;p9.14">This inhumanity of war is represented somewhat differently in <hi rend="italic">Die Brücke;</hi> it is through the representation of the boys. </s><s n="s2.8;p9.14">Owing to their ridiculous enthusiasm the viewer is provoked into wondering why the boys hold such attitudes. </s><s n="s3.8;p9.14">Although this contemplation would perhaps come after the film, Wicki makes us think of the extent of the indoctrinated evil (probably, in this case, of the Hitler Youth or, ironically, the same English teacher who tried to persuade the Captain to spare their lives) for the boys to have such enthusiasm for war. </s><s n="s4.8;p9.14">When they hear that they will be called up <hi rend="italic">"Die Jungen sind sehr stolz darauf, endlich auch für das Vaterland kämpfen zu dürfen"</hi><ref target="BAWE_0061a-ftnote.031"/>. </s><s n="s5.8;p9.14">Even when two of them have already died and they are given the chance to surrender by the Americans they do not give up. </s><s n="s6.8;p9.14">This, however, is not a direct link towards Nazism and as Peter Zander explains: <hi rend="italic">"Der Film ist somit keine Abrechung mit dem Nazismus"</hi><ref target="BAWE_0061a-ftnote.032"/>. </s><s n="s7.8;p9.14">This is a different representation to Wo warst du, Adam? as people address and leave each other with the exclamation "Heil Hitler!" and there is a felling in the book of people upholding and staying loyal to the Nazi criteria for how one should behave. </s><s n="s8.8;p9.14">Greck is one such example, as well as worrying whether he has given the correct Nazi salute or not, he is also concerned after having sold his trousers to a Jew. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0061a-ftnote.031"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1"><seg type="URL" n="http://clubfilmothek.bjf.info/filme/2910052.htm"/> </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0061a-ftnote.032"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Peter Zander, <hi rend="italic">Bernhard Wicki</hi> (Berlin 1994), p.20 </s></p></note><p n="p10.14"><s n="s1.4;p10.14">Both oeuvres portray the role of women in wartime in much the same way, that is to say perfectly fitting with the <hi rend="italic">Kinder, Kirche, Küche</hi> Nazi ideal. </s><s n="s2.4;p10.14">In Wo warst du, Adam? this is done primarily through the representation of Frau Susan who cooks and looks after the soldiers staying with her and worries about her husband. </s><s n="s3.4;p10.14">In the film the boys' mothers worry that their sons are going off to war at such a young age. </s><s n="s4.4;p10.14">These representations are similar in that the role of women is very limited and it is the men who make all the decisions and go to fight in the war - both mediums focus on them. </s></p><p n="p11.14"><s n="s1.8;p11.14">It is undoubtedly the case that both Böll and Wicki emphasise the horror, futility and inhumanity of war. </s><s n="s2.8;p11.14">However, to ensure a balanced account is given, it is important to state that sometimes, in both cases, war is portrayed somewhat paradoxically; and is seen not to be a terrible experience, in rare circumstances. </s><s n="s3.8;p11.14">For example in <hi rend="italic">Wo warst du, Adam?</hi> </s><s n="s4.8;p11.14">when stationed at Frau Susan's house, there is a relaxed atmosphere and wartime life could almost be pleasant or at lest mirror that of the everyday: <hi rend="italic">"Dort saβ nun einer von ihnen den ganzen Tag und guckte ins Gebirge hinauf...und die anderen lungerten herum und langweilten sich."</hi><ref target="BAWE_0061a-ftnote.033"/> Likewise, earlier on, we see this in Hungary, which, according to C.W. Ghurye is "continuing its normal routine. </s><s n="s5.8;p11.14">The Hungarian civilians are eating, amusing themselves, and transacting business without concern for war." </s><ref target="BAWE_0061a-ftnote.034"/><s n="s6.8;p11.14">Böll also suggests that the war can be profitable as: "Die Soldaten waren die besten Kunden, die sie je gehabt hatte: diese acht verzehrten mehr im Monat als alle Leute zusammen, die einzeln über die Brücke gegangen waren. </s><s n="s7.8;p11.14">Die Soldaten schienen viel Geld und sehr viel Zeit zu haben." </s><ref target="BAWE_0061a-ftnote.035"/><s n="s8.8;p11.14">Although this is not directly the case in Die Brücke and people do not seem to get on as if it was their daily routine, this idea does, however, coincide with the representation of war being as a game for the boys. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0061a-ftnote.033"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Heinrich Böll, <hi rend="italic">Wo warst du, Adam?</hi> </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">(Munich, 1972), p.106 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0061a-ftnote.034"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Charlotte W. Ghurye, <hi rend="italic">The Writer and Society</hi> (1976), p.23 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0061a-ftnote.035"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Heinrich Böll, <hi rend="italic">Wo warst du, Adam?</hi> </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">(Munich, 1972), p.106 </s></p></note><p n="p12.14"><s n="s1.10;p12.14">One major difference between the representations of war in <hi rend="italic">Wo warst du, Adam?</hi> </s><s n="s2.10;p12.14">from that in <hi rend="italic"> Die Brücke</hi> is that the book refers to Jews and religion whereas the fim does not. </s><s n="s3.10;p12.14">Böll uses Ilona firstly to highlight the inconsistencies of the Nazi prejudice and to discredit the Aryan myth, and also to portray the horror and inhumanity of war, more directly, regarding the treatment of her by Filkskeit. </s><s n="s4.10;p12.14">Religion is used to illustrate the ignorance of Bressen who had no idea there were Catholics in Romania and to make the point that the Nazi claim of <hi rend="italic">Heim ins Reich</hi> is actually not valid. </s><s n="s5.10;p12.14">Although both are major themes to do with the Second World War, no reference is made to them in <hi rend="italic">Die Brücke.</hi> </s><s n="s6.10;p12.14">Similarly, there is no depiction of the enemy in <hi rend="italic">Wo warst du, Adam?</hi> </s><s n="s7.10;p12.14">- we see them at the end of <hi rend="italic"> Die Brücke</hi>, perhaps as Wicki wants to highlight the differences between the experienced, mature American opposition to the novice youths. </s><s n="s8.10;p12.14">Böll's point in not showing an enemy is one of futility, the fact that war is pointless and an enemy is not seen. </s><s n="s9.10;p12.14">This futility is mentioned by C.W. Ghurye who describes "the battles raging some 50 miles away, futile in themselves"<ref target="BAWE_0061a-ftnote.036"/> - meaning there is no point the soldiers being there as they never see combat. </s><s n="s10.10;p12.14">An ironic twist, highlighted by Ghurye is that Schniewind "shoots at his own people (Feinhals), but does not fire a single cannon at the enemy"<ref target="BAWE_0061a-ftnote.037"/>. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0061a-ftnote.036"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Charlotte W. Ghurye, <hi rend="italic">The Writer and Society</hi> (1976), p.23 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0061a-ftnote.037"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Charlotte W. Ghurye, <hi rend="italic">The Writer and Society</hi> (1976), p.26 </s></p></note><p n="p13.14"><s n="s1.3;p13.14">The representation of war between these two mediums differs mainly as, in <hi rend="italic">Die Brücke</hi> we are drawn emotionally, as a viewer, to follow the lives and fate of the characters. </s><s n="s2.3;p13.14">Böll, however, throws us in the thick of the battle and the same point is made over and over again using different examples and characters - Rainer Nägele explains: <hi rend="italic">"die Handlung ist nicht mehr auf ein Individuum hin angelegt, sondern zielt durch Parallel-Episoden auf eine gröβere Breite."</hi> </s><ref target="BAWE_0061a-ftnote.038"/><s n="s3.3;p13.14"> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0061a-ftnote.038"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Rainer Nägele, <hi rend="italic">Heinrich Böll - Einführung in das Werk und in die Forschung</hi> (Frankfurt am Main, 1976), p.126 </s></p></note><p n="p14.14"><s n="s1.4;p14.14">In conclusion, Heinrich Böll's <hi rend="italic">Wo warst du, Adam?</hi> </s><s n="s2.4;p14.14">and Bernhard Wicki's <hi rend="italic">Die Brücke</hi> both agree on several common wartime themes. </s><s n="s3.4;p14.14">The representation of these themes is often similar, yet one must consider that they are not always trying to make the same point. </s><s n="s4.4;p14.14">In some instances, therefore, the tools they use to control us as a reader or as a viewer are different. </s></p></div1></body><back><div1 type="bibliography"><div2 type="bibliography"><head rend="bold">Bibliography</head><div3 type="bibliography"><head rend="underlined">Primary Texts</head><p>Heinrich Böll, <hi rend="italic">Wo warst du, Adam?</hi> (Munich, 1972)</p></div3><div3 type="bibliography"><head rend="underlined">Secondary Literature </head><p>Alan Bance, <hi rend="italic">The German Novel 1945-1960</hi> (Stuttgart 1980)</p><p>Bernd Balzer, Humanität als ästhetisches Prinzip - Die Romane Heinrich Bölls (Königstein,1980)</p><p>Hanno Beth, <hi rend="italic">Heinrich Böll - Eine Einführung in das Gesamtwerk in Einzelinterpretationen</hi> (1980)</p><p>Charlotte W. Ghurye, <hi rend="italic">The Writer and Society</hi> (1976)</p><p>Heinrich Herlyn, <hi rend="italic">Heinrich Böll als utopischer Schriftsteller</hi> (Bern 1996)</p><p>Rainer Nägele, <hi rend="italic">Heinrich Böll - Einführung in das Werk und in die Forschung</hi> (Frankfurt am Main, 1976)</p><p>Hermann Stresau, <hi rend="italic">Heinrich Böll</hi> (Berlin 1964)</p><p>Günter Wirth, <hi rend="italic">Heinrich Böll - Religiöse und gesellschaftliche Motive im Prosawerk</hi> (Cologne,1987)</p><p>Peter Zander, <hi rend="italic">Bernhard Wicki</hi> (Berlin 1994)</p><p><seg type="URL" n="http://www.pausenhof.de/referate/refdeu/refdeub009.asp"/></p><p><seg type="URL" n="http://clubfilmothek.bjf.info/filme/2910052.htm"/></p></div3></div2><div2 type="bibliography"><head rend="bold">Filmography</head><p><hi rend="italic">Die Brücke</hi> (1959), dir. Bernhard Wicki</p></div2></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
