<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_0061i" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>The use of style indirect libre in Madame Bovary</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">deleted: header: student number; footer: page numbers</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">2</p><p n="date">2004-03</p><p n="module title">Bestsellers of the Nineteenth Century</p><p n="module code">FR233</p><p n="genre family">Essay</p><p n="discipline">other</p><p n="disciplinary group">AH</p><p n="grade">M</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">1228</p><p n="number of s-units">44</p><p n="number of p">7</p><p n="number of tables">0</p><p n="number of figures">0</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">0</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">0</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">27.9</p><p n="average s-units per p">6.3</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">m</p><p n="year of birth">1983</p><p n="first language">English</p><p n="education">UKA</p><p n="course">French and German</p><p n="student ID">0061</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><docTitle><titlePart rend="bold">The use of <hi rend="italic">style indirect libre</hi> in <hi rend="italic">Madame Bovary</hi></titlePart></docTitle></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="section"><p n="p1.7"><s n="s1.6;p1.7">Free indirect discourse or <hi rend="italic">style indirect libre</hi> is a technique used by writers to present the thoughts or utterances of a fictional character as if it were from their own point of view. </s><s n="s2.6;p1.7">This is achieved by combining grammatical and other features of the character's 'direct speech' with features of the narrator's 'indirect' report. </s><s n="s3.6;p1.7">It is a technique to allow the reader to interpret the protagonist's thoughts as the author enjoys a seemingly objective stance. </s><s n="s4.6;p1.7">Gustave Flaubert was a 'pioneer'<ref target="BAWE_0061i-ftnote.001"/> of this style and in his novel <hi rend="italic">Madame Bovary</hi>, this technique is used copiously. </s><s n="s5.6;p1.7">One advantage he enjoyed was that it enabled him to find a style 'suitable to each object, each place, each circumstance [and] each being'<ref target="BAWE_0061i-ftnote.002"/> and permitted him 'to give expression to the unexpressed thoughts of incoherent people." </s><ref target="BAWE_0061i-ftnote.003"/><s n="s6.6;p1.7">This <hi rend="italic">style indirect libre</hi> involves the reader in the narrative; there is no privation to preface the tenets of the protagonists with '<hi rend="italic">il a pensé</hi>' or - would it be direct speech - '<hi rend="italic">il me semble</hi>' as it is either deliberately apparent or indeterminate who the reference is made by and this is controlled by the author. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0061i-ftnote.001"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Brombert, V., <hi rend="italic">The Novels of Flaubert: A Study of Themes and Techniques</hi> (New Jersey, 1966), p. 76 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0061i-ftnote.002"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Faguet, É., <hi rend="italic">Flaubert</hi> (London, 1914), p. 203 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0061i-ftnote.003"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Starkie, E., <hi rend="italic">Flaubert: The Making of the Master</hi> (London, 1967), p. 313 </s></p></note><p n="p2.7"><s n="s1.7;p2.7">The reader is often told how things are seen rather than merely what is being seen. </s><s n="s2.7;p2.7">One example of this is Charles' description of Emma as he frequents Rouault's farm; she offers him a drink. </s><s n="s3.7;p2.7">Flaubert uses <hi rend="italic">style indirect libre</hi> to underline the significance of this moment to Charles. </s><s n="s4.7;p2.7">The description is, ergo, extremely detailed and it is clear that it portrays the thoughts of Monsieur Bovary. </s><s n="s5.7;p2.7">He sees Emma: '[<hi rend="italic">qui</hi>] <hi rend="italic">n'avait point de fichu, on voyait sur les épaules nues de petites gouttes de sueur</hi>." </s><ref target="BAWE_0061i-ftnote.004"/><s n="s6.7;p2.7">Flaubert manages to describe Emma in a highly suggestive way and yet manages to keep the semblance of objectivity through the <hi rend="italic">style indirect libre</hi> as it appears clear that it is Charles who sees Emma in this way and is becoming emotionally charged as '<hi rend="italic">Elle</hi> [Emma] <hi rend="italic">riait de ne rien sentir, tandis que le bout de la langue, passant entre ses dents fines, léchait à petits coups le fond du verre.</hi> </s><s n="s7.7;p2.7">'<ref target="BAWE_0061i-ftnote.005"/> He is realizing her strong erotic potential which will 'find its first symbolic awakening during the dance ritual at the <hi rend="italic">Vaubyessard</hi> ball.'<ref target="BAWE_0061i-ftnote.006"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0061i-ftnote.004"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Flaubert, G., <hi rend="italic">Madame Bovary</hi> (Paris, 1971), p. 23 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0061i-ftnote.005"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0061i-ftnote.006"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Brombert, V., op. cit., p. 46 </s></p></note><p n="p3.7"><s n="s1.8;p3.7">This <hi rend="italic">style indirect libre</hi> would initially suggest that Flaubert would sympathise with Emma as her description is through the eyes of Charles who is in awe of her. </s><s n="s2.8;p3.7">Flaubert, however, ensures his rigid objectivity as, later on in the novel, the reader will be able to judge Emma's character for himself when the <hi rend="italic">style indirect libre</hi> switches to her shared point of view, through her actions and rhetoric. </s><s n="s3.8;p3.7">The reader will see her dissatisfaction with her life and especially with Charles but 'Flaubert's <hi rend="italic">style indirect libre</hi> gives a modicum of objectivity' to this lamentation. </s><s n="s4.8;p3.7">'<hi rend="italic">Charles était là.</hi> </s><s n="s5.8;p3.7"><hi rend="italic">Il avait sa casquette enforcée sur ses sourcils...ce qui ajoutait à son visage quelque chose de stupide</hi>'<ref target="BAWE_0061i-ftnote.007"/>. </s><s n="s6.8;p3.7">It is evident that it is not the author who is making this comment but it is in Emma's thoughts. </s><s n="s7.8;p3.7">By adopting <hi rend="italic">style indirect libre</hi> Flaubert drops the real subject of the sentence and the protagonist's true thoughts are expressed. </s><s n="s8.8;p3.7">This technique also enables Flaubert to ensure that the text is impersonal while simultaneously conveying judgments of characters and events; as 'impersonality depends not on what is said but on the fact that no identifiable narrator speaks.'<ref target="BAWE_0061i-ftnote.008"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0061i-ftnote.007"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Flaubert, G., op. cit., quoted in Culler, J., <hi rend="italic">Flaubert: The Uses of Uncertainty</hi> (London, 1974), p. 140 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0061i-ftnote.008"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Culler, J., op. cit., p. 110 </s></p></note><p n="p4.7"><s n="s1.7;p4.7"><hi rend="italic">Style indirect libre</hi> combines two voices: the voice of the narrator and that of a character. </s><s n="s2.7;p4.7">It is often impossible to tell who actually is speaking as the 'speaker may be the narrator, or one of the characters, or both, or neither." </s><ref target="BAWE_0061i-ftnote.009"/><s n="s3.7;p4.7">We can see this in incidents where the distinction between character and narrator appears to disappear completely; '<hi rend="italic">Emma fut intérieurement satisfaite de se sentir arrivée du premier coup à ce rare idéal des existences pâles, où ne parviennent jamais les coeurs médiocres.</hi> </s><ref target="BAWE_0061i-ftnote.010"/><s n="s4.7;p4.7"> It is impossible to tell here whether the narrator is quoting Emma's thoughts or feelings or whether he is, in fact, expressing his own opinions.<ref target="BAWE_0061i-ftnote.011"/> The effect this has on the reading of the text is that firstly - as a result of the <hi rend="italic">style indirect libre</hi> - the reader can read Emma's thoughts, feel her feelings, and appreciate her reactions with a much greater ease as his involvement in the text is further enhanced. </s><s n="s5.7;p4.7">Secondly, this intermittent use of 'absent' narration creates an illusion of objectivity and detachment by pushing the character into the foreground as the narrator recedes into the background. </s><s n="s6.7;p4.7">Due to the fact that the source of the narration is indistinguishable and that there are not multiple narrators, nor does the narrator have 'a distinct set of characteristics'<ref target="BAWE_0061i-ftnote.012"/>, it is impossible therefore, for a narrator to be 'opposed to another narrator, or to a character." </s><ref target="BAWE_0061i-ftnote.013"/><s n="s7.7;p4.7">The sequential effect is one which underlines the authenticity and objectivity of the text. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0061i-ftnote.009"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ginsburg, M. P., <hi rend="italic">Flaubert Writing - A Study in Narrative Strategies</hi> (California, 1986), p. 101 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0061i-ftnote.010"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Flaubert, G., op. cit., p. 40 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0061i-ftnote.011"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ginsburg, M. P., op. cit. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0061i-ftnote.012"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ginsburg, M. P., op. cit., p. 103 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0061i-ftnote.013"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid. </s></p></note><p n="p5.7"><s n="s1.7;p5.7">This <hi rend="italic">style indirect libre</hi>, thus, allows Flaubert to move unobtrusively between the objective and the subjective and permits him to place stress on certain characterizations. </s><s n="s2.7;p5.7">Through <hi rend="italic">style indirect libre</hi> Flaubert ensures that we only see what is important to the protagonists and that we adopt their own idiom. </s><s n="s3.7;p5.7">We only see the characters through what they notice of each other through what they perceive of each other. </s><s n="s4.7;p5.7">Another example of this is where Emma's beauty as she lies in the hotel bed is appreciated by both Léon and the narrator: '<hi rend="italic">rien au monde n'était beau comme sa tête brune et sa peau blanche se détachant sur cette couleur pourpre, quand, par un geste de pudeur, elle fermait ses deux bras nus, en se cachant la figure dans les mains.</hi> </s><s n="s5.7;p5.7">'<ref target="BAWE_0061i-ftnote.014"/> Perhaps substantiation that Flaubert remains objective and that the descriptions are solely through the eyes of his protagonists lies in the trivial inconsistencies in the novel. </s><s n="s6.7;p5.7">Emma's eyes are such incongruities; 'on one occasion he gives Emma brown eyes; on another deep black eyes; and, on another, blue eyes. </s><s n="s7.7;p5.7">Léon...is described as having golden hair; and later as having chestnut locks.' <ref target="BAWE_0061i-ftnote.015"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0061i-ftnote.014"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Flaubert, G., op. cit., p. 270 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0061i-ftnote.015"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Starkie, E., op. cit., p. 314 </s></p></note><p n="p6.7"><s n="s1.7;p6.7">Through his use of <hi rend="italic">style indirect libre</hi> Flaubert encourages the reader to see through his character's limited point of view and the interplay between the protagonists deliberately leaves space for the reader to interpret their actions. </s><s n="s2.7;p6.7">This form of statement allows a third-person narrative to exploit a first person point of view thus facilitating a multifaceted presentation of character, allowing the possibility of both ironic and empathetic attitudes. </s><s n="s3.7;p6.7">One example of Flaubert's use of <hi rend="italic">style indirect libre</hi> to highlight the dramatic irony in the novel is Emma's excitement when she returns home from the forest after committing adultery with Rodolphe exclaiming: '<hi rend="italic">J'ai un amant!</hi> </s><s rend="italic" n="s4.7;p6.7">Un amant! </s><s n="s5.7;p6.7">'<ref target="BAWE_0061i-ftnote.016"/> This is placed in direct discourse as it is technically true. </s><s n="s6.7;p6.7">However, the passage which follows is in <hi rend="italic">style indirect libre</hi>: '<hi rend="italic">Elle allait donc posséder enfin ces joies de l'amour, cette fièvre du bonheur dont elle avait désespéré.</hi> </s><s n="s7.7;p6.7">'<ref target="BAWE_0061i-ftnote.017"/> Here Emma is disillusioned and qua reader we know this and are immediately aware of the subtle irony. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0061i-ftnote.016"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Flaubert, G., op. cit., p. 167 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0061i-ftnote.017"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid. </s></p></note><p n="p7.7"><s n="s1.2;p7.7">In conclusion Flaubert uses <hi rend="italic">style indirect libre</hi> in <hi rend="italic">Madame Bovary</hi> and proves it to be a particularly suitable vehicle for interior monologues often verbalising essentially pre-verbal sensations and states of mind. </s><s n="s2.2;p7.7">The style is also used to highlight the irony that is to be found in the text and to subtly control the reader and his reading of the text. </s></p></div1></body><back><div1 type="bibliography"><head rend="bold">Bibliography</head><p>Brombert, V., <hi rend="italic">The Novels of Flaubert: A Study of Themes and Techniques</hi> (New Jersey, 1966)</p><p>Culler, J., <hi rend="italic">Flaubert: The Uses of Uncertainty</hi> (London, 1974)</p><p>Faguet, É., <hi rend="italic">Flaubert</hi> (London, 1914)</p><p>Fairlie, A., <hi rend="italic">Flaubert: Madame Bovary</hi> (London, 1962)</p><p>Flaubert, G., <hi rend="italic">Madame Bovary</hi> (Paris, 1971)</p><p>Ginsburg, M. P., <hi rend="italic">Flaubert Writing - A Study in Narrative Strategies</hi> (California, 1986)</p><p>Starkie, E., <hi rend="italic">Flaubert: The Making of the Master</hi> (London, 1967)</p><p>Tillett, M. G., <hi rend="italic">On Reading Flaubert</hi> (London, 1961)</p></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
