<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_0062b" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Discuss with the aid of diagrams the super-secondary elements, domain structures and post-translational modifications which contribute toward the overall structure and function of the Immunoglobulin G molecule.</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">deleted: Word Count: 2935</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">2</p><p n="date">2005-03</p><p n="module title">Protein Structure and Function</p><p n="module code">BS244</p><p n="genre family">Explanation</p><p n="discipline">Biological Sciences</p><p n="disciplinary group">LS</p><p n="grade">D</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">3048</p><p n="number of s-units">102</p><p n="number of p">32</p><p n="number of tables">0</p><p n="number of figures">4</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">0</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">0</p><p n="abstract present">abstract present</p><p n="average words per s-unit">29.9</p><p n="average s-units per p">3.2</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">f</p><p n="year of birth">1983</p><p n="first language">German</p><p n="education">OSA</p><p n="course">Biochemistry</p><p n="student ID">0062</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><titlePart><name type="student ID"/> 10.03.2005</titlePart><docTitle><titlePart rend="underlined">Discuss with the aid of diagrams the super-secondary elements, domain structures and post-translational modifications which contribute toward the overall structure and function of the Immunoglobulin G molecule. </titlePart></docTitle></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="abstract"><head rend="underlined">Abstract</head><p n="p1.32"><s n="s1.2;p1.32">The domain structures of the various regions of the Immunoglobulin G molecule, as well as post-translational modifications such as glycosylation, are depicted with respect to their biological functions. </s><s n="s2.2;p1.32">Furthermore, one of the most characteristic structural elements: the immunoglobulin fold, which can be found in a multitude of other proteins, as well as the formation of an antigen-antibody complex, are discussed. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined">Introduction</head><p n="p2.32"><s n="s1.2;p2.32">Immunoglobulin proteins are an indispensable part of the humoural immune system. </s><s n="s2.2;p2.32">They are synthesised by B lymphocytes in response to the presence of an antigen and have two main functions: recognising and binding to antigens, for example a bacterial toxin in order to inhibit its action, and recruiting other components of the immune system to eliminate the pathogen. </s></p><p n="p3.32"><s n="s1.4;p3.32">The term immunoglobulin is used for all antibodies that are constructed in a similar fashion from two identical heavy and light polypeptide chains each, which contain constant and variable regions. </s><s n="s2.4;p3.32">But differences in the constant regions and functionality have given rise to five different classes of immunoglobulins in mammals, namely IgM, IgD, IgA, IgE and IgG, the latter being by far the most abundant and constituting about 75% of serum immunoglobulins. </s><s n="s3.4;p3.32">IgG is mainly involved in binding antigen during the secondary immune response, activation of the complement cascade as well as recruitment of macrophages and neutrophils. </s><s n="s4.4;p3.32">In addition it is the only immunoglobulin to cross the placenta and become secreted in breast milk since the neonatal immune system lacks fully functional antibodies. </s></p><p n="p4.32"><s n="s1.3;p4.32">IgG can be further divided into four subclasses on the basis of distinctive conformations found in the constant regions of the heavy chains and the hinge region, which also influence the antigenic properties of these subclasses. </s><s n="s2.3;p4.32">Approximately 70% of serum IgG is IgG1, which is mainly concerned with neutralising protein toxins. </s><s n="s3.3;p4.32">IgG2 constitutes about 20% and recognises mostly antigenic polysaccharides while IgG3 is mainly concerned with viruses, making up about 8% of the IgG serum concentration. </s></p><p n="p5.32"><s n="s1.5;p5.32">The fact that each B cell secretes antibodies specifically recognise one certain epitope and the massive variation needed to ensure coverage of all sorts of antigens results from immunoglobulin gene rearrangements, i.e. the recombination of the genes encoding constant and variable regions of both types of polypeptide chains. </s><s n="s2.5;p5.32">The immune system is capable of generating millions of different molecules from a large pool of variable domain alleles. </s><s n="s3.5;p5.32">Two sets of V genes encode the variable domains of immunoglobulin heavy and light chains. </s><s n="s4.5;p5.32">The two chains are produced separately, but the mechanisms by which their diversity is achieved are similar in principle. </s><s n="s5.5;p5.32">The constant domains on the other hand, do not undergo a great deal of variation, as their name implies. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined">The General Structure of IgG</head><p n="p6.32"><s n="s1.3;p6.32">IgG is a monomeric and fairly large molecule with a molecular weight of about 150 kDa resulting from the presence of two γ heavy chains weighing 50 kDa and two κ or λ light chains weighing 25 kDa each. κ and λ are apparently functionally indistinguishable and either type of light chain may be associated with any of the heavy chains. </s><s n="s2.3;p6.32">However, individual immunoglobulins are symmetrical and always contain identical light chains and identical heavy chains. </s><s n="s3.3;p6.32">As a result an antibody's antigen-binding sites are always identical, which is crucial for the cross-linking function needed to antigen-antibody clusters. </s></p><p n="p7.32"><s n="s1.8;p7.32">The structure of immunoglobulin G has been extensively studied since IgG is the simplest of all immunoglobulins, thus serving as a model for the other classes. </s><s n="s2.8;p7.32">Because X-ray crystallography of the intact molecule was difficult at the beginning of its investigation, due to its conformational flexibility in the hinge region, it was subjected to digestion by proteolytic enzymes. </s><s n="s3.8;p7.32">Treatment with papain was the most successful, and three fragments of equal molecular weight were obtained. </s><s n="s4.8;p7.32">Two of these fragments continued to display antigen binding properties, and were named Fab (ab: antigen binding) as a result. </s><s n="s5.8;p7.32">The third fragment however did not bind antigen, instead it was named Fc (c: crystallisable) because it crystallised readily. </s><s n="s6.8;p7.32">Fc expresses effector functions, such as activation of the complement cascade. </s><s n="s7.8;p7.32">From the pioneering work of Roberto Poljak and David Davies in 1973 to this day, the high-resolution structures of multiple Fab and Fc fragments have been determined, either by themselves or complexed with a multitude of antigens. </s><s n="s8.8;p7.32">Though in reality this is often not the case due to its flexible hinge region, an IgG molecule can be pictured as Y-shaped, where the Fab fragments would form the two arms and Fc the tail of the Y. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0062b-pic.001"><head><hi rend="bold">Fig. 1:</hi> (A) 3-dimensional structure of IgG. (B) Schematic diagram of IgG, showing the 12 immunoglobulin domains. Stryeral. Biochemistry</head></figure><p n="p8.32"><s n="s1.6;p8.32">As already mentioned the IgG molecule consists of four polypeptide chains connected by disulphide bonds, namely two identical heavy and two identical light chains, which can be further divided into so called immunoglobulin domains as can be seen in figure 1. </s><s n="s2.6;p8.32">The light chains consist of two domains, the variable amino-terminal domain termed VL, and the constant carboxyl-terminal domain CL. The amino-terminal domain of heavy chains exhibits sequence variations as well, hence it is called VH. The three remaining domains are constant, thus termed CH1, CH2, and CH3. </s><s n="s3.6;p8.32">Most of the amino acid sequences of these domains are remarkably conserved, even across different species, suggesting that the genes encoding the constant domains evolved from one common ancestor, and that the amino acid sequences are crucial for the molecule's tertiary structure. </s><s n="s4.6;p8.32">Also, variation in sequence and length of the variable regions is confined to three short sequences that do not contribute to the overall structure; these are called the hypervariable loops or complimentarity determining regions (CDR). </s><s n="s5.6;p8.32">These regions determine the specificity of the antigen-antibody interactions. </s><s n="s6.6;p8.32">Constant and variable domains do not share homologous sequences, yet their structures are very similar. </s></p><p n="p9.32"><s n="s1.2;p9.32">An important feature of the molecule's structure are the numerous disulphide bonds which do not only connect the Fab and Fc fragments, but also the heavy and light chains. </s><s n="s2.2;p9.32">Figure 2 illustrates these as well as the 12 immunoglobulin domains, which will be discussed in more detail shortly. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0062b-pic.002"><head><hi rend="bold">Fig. 2:</hi> Schematic diagram of the overall structure of IgG, showing the different domains and disulphide bonds. Alberts et.al.: The Cell.</head></figure></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined">The Immunoglobulin Fold</head><p n="p10.32"><s n="s1.1;p10.32">Underlying the structures of the 12 immunoglobulin domains found in IgG is a structure called the immunoglobulin fold, which shows remarkable similarity not only within the molecule itself but also across the wide range of specific antibodies produced and many other proteins such as MHC. </s></p><p n="p11.32"><s n="s1.2;p11.32">A pair of -sheets, consisting of a stable arrangement of hydrogen bonded anti-parallel -strands, and held together by a single disulphide bond, forms a barrel like structure, creating a central hydrophobic core. </s><s n="s2.2;p11.32">The amino terminus and the carboxyl terminus are at opposite ends of the barrel, so that several domains can form a chain, as is the case in the light and heavy chains of IgG and several other key molecules in the immune system. </s></p><p n="p12.32"><s n="s1.4;p12.32">In the constant domains, the barrel structure is formed by seven -strands, so that one sheet consists of four strands and the other of three. </s><s n="s2.4;p12.32">The constant domain structure of both light and heavy chains is the same and the amino acid sequence inside the barrel structure is mostly invariant, resulting in its structural stability and enabling the heavy and light chain domains to interact. </s><s n="s3.4;p12.32">The loops that connect the -strands outside the barrel are found having different sizes and conformations across the different classes of immunoglobulins (padlan), but they are constant within one class, and generally short so that most amino acid residues within a chain contribute to the barrel structure and are not "outside". </s><s n="s4.4;p12.32">It is thought that loops of the constant domains play a role in the effector functions of the antibody, but their mode of action is unknown. </s></p><p n="p13.32"><s n="s1.5;p13.32">The structure and topology of both constant and variable domains are very similar, but the variable domain, contains two additional, albeit relatively short, -strands, resulting in one -sheet containing four and the other containing five strands. </s><s n="s2.5;p13.32">The amino acid sequence of the -strands is still highly conserved within the barrel. </s><s n="s3.5;p13.32">There is a total of six interconnecting loops, and by comparing the amino acid sequences of several hundreds of variable domains, it was found that variation is especially prevalent in three of these. </s><s n="s4.5;p13.32">Namely the aforementioned complementarity determining regions (CDRs), which are found exclusively protruding out of the barrel at the amino-terminal, as one can see in fig. </s><s n="s5.5;p13.32">3, and form the antigen binding site. </s></p><p n="p14.32"><s n="s1.1;p14.32">An enormous diversity of antigen-binding sites can be generated by changing only the lengths and amino acid sequences of the hypervariable loops, thus changing their structural characteristics such as shape or polarity, while the overall three-dimensional structure necessary for antibody function remains constant since the hypervariable loops are not associated with keeping the -barrel structure stable. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0062b-pic.003"><head rend="bold italic">Fig.3: Schematic sideview of the variable domain, consisting of the beta sheets from each chain.\It is illustrated how this structure enables all CDRs to come together at the amino-terminal of IgG. Stryeral. Biochemistry</head></figure><p n="p15.32"><s n="s1.3;p15.32">Since two domains of IgG contribute to one antigen binding site each, the polypeptide chains that make up the IgG molecule must be associated with one another in a ordered fashion, particularly in the Fab fragment. </s><s n="s2.3;p15.32">The variable domains of the heavy and light chain, VH and VL interact strongly with one another, as do the constant domains CH1 and CL. Contrary to that, the variable and constant domains of the same chain are only minimally connected to one another. </s><s n="s3.3;p15.32">If one only considers one constant and one variable chain i.e. half of an intact IgG, the structural result is an elongated molecule with two globular units, with the CDRs of both chains held in close proximity of one another (4). </s></p><p n="p16.32"><s n="s1.1;p16.32">The four-stranded beta sheets of CH1 and CL interact to form the constant </s></p><p n="p17.32"><s n="s1.4;p17.32">globular unit. </s><s n="s2.4;p17.32">The sheets are layered over another in a lattice-like structure, with nearly 90° angles to each other. </s><s n="s3.4;p17.32">Picture two barrel structures put together, with the three-stranded beta sheets on the outside, and a mainly hydrophobic core where the barrels associate. </s><s n="s4.4;p17.32">This favours the stability of the molecule, since its environment is of aqueous nature. </s></p><p n="p18.32"><s n="s1.6;p18.32">The association of variable domains underlies the goal of bringing the CDRs of both chains into close proximity to form the antigen-binding site. </s><s n="s2.6;p18.32">In order to allow IgG to bind small antigenic molecules such as haptens as well as large proteins, a binding cleft for small antigens and an essentially continuous surface for larger antigens is needed. </s><s n="s3.6;p18.32">Also, since it is primarily the five-stranded -sheet of each chain whose loops contribute to the antigen-binding site, those sheets have to be fairly close to on another. </s><s n="s4.6;p18.32">This is achieved by arranging the VL and VH domains into a barrel-like structure. </s><s n="s5.6;p18.32">The five-stranded beta sheets are associated with one another but are not packed as closely as is the case in the constant domain. </s><s n="s6.6;p18.32">Instead, they form the core of the barrel, which is once again hydrophobic, whilst the four-stranded beta sheets are wrapped around the outside, and all hypervariable loops protrude from one side of the barrel (4). </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined">Antibody-Antigen Complexes</head><p n="p19.32"><s n="s1.2;p19.32">The two Fab regions are able to move relative to each other over a wide range of angles and to the Fc stem, allowing their antigen-binding sites to to display segmental flexibility. </s><s n="s2.2;p19.32">This enhances the formation of an antibody-antigen complex, by enabling a single IgG to bind a polyvalent antigen possessing multiple identical epitopes such as a bacterial cell surface, irrelevant of the distance and orientation of these epitopes relative to each other. </s></p><p n="p20.32"><s n="s1.2;p20.32">This is possible due to the so called hinge region of the heavy chain, which connects the CH1 and CH2 domains, thus providing the link between the Fab and Fc fragments of the molecule. </s><s n="s2.2;p20.32">Cysteine residues that form two disulphide bonds between the two heavy chains found in an IgG molecule and numerous proline residues, which are responsible for the flexibility of this polypeptide region are characteristics of the hinge region. </s></p><p n="p21.32"><s n="s1.1;p21.32">The reversible formation of antibody-antigen complexes is one of the fundamental functions of IgG, mediated by numerous non-covalent interactions such as hydrogen bonding, hydrophobic van-der-Waals-forces, electrostatic and ionic interactions, which take place if the antigen's epitope(s) and the antigen-binding sites are in close proximity (4). </s></p><p n="p22.32"><s n="s1.4;p22.32">A huge number of various antigens and their interactions with the Fab fragments have been analysed by X-ray crystallography and have revealed the structural aspects underlying antigen binding by residues found in the CDRs. </s><s n="s2.4;p22.32">About 15 residues from a few of the CDRs may participate in binding small molecules (haptens) such as phosphorylcholine, progesterone or digosin, which will often bind in a cleft similar to the binding of an enzyme and its substrate. </s><s n="s3.4;p22.32">Bigger antigens include oligopeptides like a nonapeptide from influenza virus hemaglutinin or a trisaccharide epitope of a branched bacterial lipopolysaccharide. </s><s n="s4.4;p22.32">Macromolecules e.g. lysozyme or HIV-I reverse transciptase are usually bound by >20 residues from all six CDRs and tend to interact with complementary protrusions and depressions of larger, flat surfaces of the IgG molecule (4). </s></p><p n="p23.32"><s n="s1.3;p23.32">Phosphorylcholine is a typical example of binding a small molecule in a cavity formed by CDR residues. </s><s n="s2.3;p23.32">In this case, two CDRs originate from the VL and three from the VH domain. </s><s n="s3.3;p23.32">The Phosphorylcholine-IgG complex is stabilised by </s></p><p n="p24.32"><s n="s1.1;p24.32">van-der-Waals forces and relies on the binding of a positively charged trimethylammonium group, which electrostatically interacts with two negatively charged IgG glutamate residues inside the cavity, as well as binding of a negatively charged phosphate group by three CDR residues, namely positively charged arginine, lysine and tyrosine. </s></p><p n="p25.32"><s n="s1.3;p25.32">The availability of both complexed and uncomplexed structures for the same antibody permits the evaluation of the possibility of conformational changes occurring upon ligand binding. </s><s n="s2.3;p25.32">In the case of phosphorylcholine or other small molecules, no conformational changes take plus. </s><s n="s3.3;p25.32">But later studies with larger ligands revealed that significant changes can occur upon binding (7). </s></p><p n="p26.32"><s n="s1.3;p26.32">Hen egg-white lysozyme, whose interactions with IgG have been extensively studied, shall serve as an example for the binding of macromolecules. </s><s n="s2.3;p26.32">There are several antibodies raised against lysozyme, and each one interacts with it in a slightly different manner, but in general IgG's amino-terminal domains do not exhibit significant conformational changes except for "opening up" a little to allow for more intimate contact with lysozyme, and all six CDRs are involved with the epitope across a region that spans about 30 x 20 Å. </s><s n="s3.3;p26.32">Lysozyme binds with a rather flat surface, except for the protrusion of a glutamine side chain into the antigen binding site, which is surrounded by three aromatic side chains and hydrogen bound to a carbonyl oxygen atom (11). </s></p><p n="p27.32"><s n="s1.5;p27.32">Formation of antibody-antigen complexes has different results depending on the type of pathogen involved. </s><s n="s2.5;p27.32">Binding certain gram-negative bacteria, leads to activation of a serum complement cascade that results in C8 and C9 drilling themselves through the bacterial membrane and causing lysis of the bacterium. </s><s n="s3.5;p27.32">In the case of gram-positive bacteria complement is activated to form a C3 and C5 complex, which in turn attracts phagocytes. </s><s n="s4.5;p27.32">Also, certain bacterial toxins can be neutralised by binding to them, as well as viral adherence sites, whose inactivation then renders the virus incapable of adhering to and penetrating a potential host cell. </s><s n="s5.5;p27.32">Experimental proof for this direct antiviral effect is that monovalent fragments of IgG, exert similar neutralization activity as the intact antibody but are - contrarily - unable to activate complement, since this function is performed by the Fc fragment (3). </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined">Glycosylation and Effector Functions</head><p n="p28.32"><s n="s1.2;p28.32">Several protein-carbohydrate interactions involving the heavy chain in Fab and Fc fragments of IgG have been discovered by X-ray crystallography. </s><s n="s2.2;p28.32">These are post-translational glycosylation sites, which are especially important in the Fc fragment of IgG. </s></p><p n="p29.32"><s n="s1.3;p29.32">The Fab fragment is also glycosylated, but it's glycosylation sites are not conserved. </s><s n="s2.3;p29.32">Three can be found on VL, but one oligosaccharide complex is also attached to an asparagine residue within CDR2 of VH, yet its composition and structure differ from the biantennary complex found in the CH2 domain, since it is of the high mannose type. </s><s n="s3.3;p29.32">The following figure illustrates which regions of the molecule become glycosylated (8): </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0062b-pic.004"><head rend="bold">Fig. 5: Schematic representation of IgG showing domain structure and location of glycosylation sites. (Adaptation from: O'Connor, S.E., and B. Imperialli. Modulation of protein structure and function by asparagine-linked glycosylation. Chem. &amp; Biol. 3: 803-812, 1996.)</head></figure><p n="p30.32"><s n="s1.7;p30.32">One conserved glycosylation site in the CH2 domain has been found in a turn-segment between two -sheets. </s><s n="s2.7;p30.32">Bound to the asparagine 297 residue is a biantennary oligosaccharide complex, roughly 3 x 4 nm in size, which consists of a number of different carbohydrates, and interacts with several amino acids in close proximity of the N-terminal of CH2. </s><s n="s3.7;p30.32">Glycosylation of the conserved site in the CH2 domain of the IgG heavy chain is essential for biological function. </s><s n="s4.7;p30.32">Lack of glycosylation of the CH2 domains does not alter tertiary structure, but does change the local conformation of the residues normally interacting with the biantennary structure, promoting lateral movements of the hinge region (9). </s><s n="s5.7;p30.32">Furthermore glycosylation is required for the effector functions of Fc and thermodynamic stability of the molecule, as was shown by investigating a number of truncated oligosaccharide chains, and their effect on Fc binding to complement C1 as well as the Fc receptors of leucocytes. </s><s n="s6.7;p30.32">All truncated oligosaccharides provided for a certain degree of functionality and stability, suggesting that effector functions can be modulated by variation of the oligosaccharide structures. </s><s n="s7.7;p30.32">It has also become clear that the N-terminal region of the CH2 domain is the part of Fc responsible for its effector functions and that its glycosylation is essential (5, 10). </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined">Conclusion</head><p n="p31.32"><s n="s1.2;p31.32">Immunoglobulin G is an excellent example of the way a protein's various structural aspects, starting with the primary structure needed to yield the appropriate secondary structures up to post-translational modifications like glycosylation, all come together in the end. </s><s n="s2.2;p31.32">As a result of evolution, there is not a single structural aspect that does not contribute to the functionality of the protein somehow, thus making it very efficient. </s></p><p n="p32.32"><s n="s1.2;p32.32">As one of the most extensively studied proteins, Immunoglobulin G serves as a model for other immunoglobulins. </s><s n="s2.2;p32.32">It also shows how genetic diversity, accommodating for the presence of a uncountable number of possible pathogens, can be generated without sacrificing its structure or functionality and with relatively little effort - what is changing about two dozen amino acid residues in a given sequence compared to the millions of possibilities arising from this small change? </s></p></div1></body><back><div1 type="bibliography"><div2 type="bibliography"><head rend="underlined">General References</head><p>Alberts, B., Johnson, A., Lewis, J., Raff, M., Roberts, K. and P. Walter. <hi rend="underlined">Molecular Biology of the Cell, 4th Ed</hi>. 2002. New York: Garland Science. </p><p>Baron S. (editor). <hi rend="underlined">Medical Microbiology, 4th Ed</hi>. 1996. Galveston: The University of Texas Medical Branch.</p><p>Berg, J.M., Clarke, N.D., Stryer, L. and J.L. Tymoczko. <hi rend="underlined">Biochemistry, 5th Ed</hi>. 2002. New York: W. H. Freeman and Company.</p><p>Branden, C. and J. Tooze. <hi rend="underlined">Introduction to Protein Structure, 2nd Ed</hi>. 1999. New York: Garland Publishing Inc.</p></div2><div2 type="bibliography"><head rend="underlined">Specific References</head><p>Ashton, R., Church, S., Dong, S., Ghirlando, P.R., Goodall, M., Jefferis, R., Lund, J., and Y. Mimura. The influence of glycosylation on the thermal stability and effector function expression of human IgG1-Fc: properties of a series of truncated glycoforms. <hi rend="italic">Mol. Immu</hi>. 37: 697-706, 2000.</p><p>Braden, B.C. and R.J. Poljak. Structural features of the reactions between antibodies and protein antigens. <hi rend="italic">FASEB J.</hi> 9: 9-16, 1995.</p><p>Davies, D.R., Padlan, E.A. and S. Sheriff. Antibody-Antigen Complexes. <hi rend="italic">J. Biol. Chem</hi>. 263: 10541-10544, 1988.</p><p>Endo, T., Kobata, A., Morrison S.L. and A. Wright. Glycosylation of the variable region of immunoglobulin G - site specific maturation of the sugar chains. <hi rend="italic">Mol. Immu</hi>. 32: 931-940, 1995.</p><p>Huber, R., Jefferis, R., Krapp, S., Mimura, Y. and P. Sondermann. Structural Analysis of Human IgG-Fc Glycoforms Reveals a Correlation Between Glycosylation and Structural Integrity. <hi rend="italic">J. Mol. Biol</hi>. 325: 979-989, 2003.</p><p>O'Connor, S.E., and B. Imperiali. Modulation of protein structure and function by asparagine-linked glycosylation. <hi rend="italic">Chem. &amp; Biol</hi>. 3: 803-812, 1996.</p><p>Padlan, E.A. Anatomy of the Antibody Molecule. <hi rend="italic">Mol. Immun</hi>. 31: 169-217, 1994.</p></div2></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
