<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_0065d" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Broken hip</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">pro forma
deleted:header: student and module name, date; footer: page numbers</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">4</p><p n="date">2004-03</p><p n="module title">General Clinical Education</p><p n="module code">unknown</p><p n="genre family">Case study</p><p n="discipline">Medicine</p><p n="disciplinary group">LS</p><p n="grade">D</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">835</p><p n="number of s-units">28</p><p n="number of p">20</p><p n="number of tables">0</p><p n="number of figures">0</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">12</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">4</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">29.8</p><p n="average s-units per p">1.4</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">m</p><p n="year of birth">1976</p><p n="first language">English</p><p n="education">UKA</p><p n="course">Medicine</p><p n="student ID">0065</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><titlePart><hi rend="bold">PORTFOLIO CASE No:</hi> Patient Initials Hospital Number Age Gender<name type="other"/> Keep separate list 89 F</titlePart><docTitle><titlePart>Portfolio Case presentation number: 23 Phase 2 course document objective(s):</titlePart></docTitle></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Referral information</head><p n="p1.20"><s n="s1.1;p1.20">Referred to A&amp;E by ambulance following incident at home </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">History</head><list type="simple"><head>PC: Fall</head></list><list type="simple"><head>HPC: </head><item>Admitted on <name type="date"/> after she slipped and fell on to left side </item><item>C/o pain in left hip with radiation to the groin</item><item>Unable to weight bear or move left lower limb</item><item>No knee pain</item></list><p n="p2.20"><s n="s1.1;p2.20">No previous history of falls </s></p><p n="p3.20"><s n="s1.1;p3.20">Could previously climb stairs </s></p><list type="simple"><head rend="underlined">Risk factors for fracture </head><item>smoke/alcohol X</item><item>Diet X</item><item>Early menopause X</item><item>Steroid medication X</item><item>Eye sight normal X</item><item>Obstacles at home X</item></list><list type="simple"><head>PMH: </head><item>Cellulitis 2 years ago</item><item>No asthma, Hypertension or IHD</item></list><list type="simple"><head>DH: </head><item>NAD</item></list><list type="simple"><head>FH: </head><item>NAD</item></list><list type="simple"><head>SH:</head><item>Lives with son in a house. He is the primary carer</item></list></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Analysis of history</head><p n="p4.20"><s n="s1.3;p4.20">Pain arising in the hip is felt mainly in the groin and in the front or inner side of the thigh. </s><s n="s2.3;p4.20">Pain is often referred also to the knee and can sometimes be the predominant feature. </s><s n="s3.3;p4.20">In contrast, the 'hip' pain that is referred from the spine is felt mainly in the gluteal region, where it often radiates down the back or outer side of the thigh. </s></p><p n="p5.20"><s n="s1.2;p5.20">True hip pain is made worse by walking, whereas gluteal pain referred from the spine is aggravated by activities such as stooping and lifting, and is often eased by walking. </s><s n="s2.2;p5.20">In this case, however, weight bearing was not possible, let alone walking or stooping. </s></p><p n="p6.20"><s n="s1.1;p6.20">Other joints to examine - Pain in the hip area may be due to pathology in the lumbar spine, sacroiliac joints, abdomen or pelvis </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Physical examination</head><list type="simple"><item>Patient uncomfortable in bed</item><item>Left leg shortened, externally rotated and adducted.</item><item>No active movement</item><item>Pain on all passive movement</item><item>Tenderness over left hip</item><item>No sensory deficit</item></list><p n="p7.20"/></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Analysis of history and examination</head><p n="p8.20"><s n="s1.1;p8.20">Examination findings of a shortened, externally rotated hip, with pain on movement and tenderness over the left hip, strongly suggest a broken hip. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Formulation of the patient's problem(s)</head><p n="p9.20"><s n="s1.4;p9.20">This 89 year old lady has suffered from a serious fall that has left her with a broken hip requiring a major operation. </s><s n="s2.4;p9.20">This has severely affected her health status and no doubt this has hugely impinged on her mobility and made her more dependent on her son in both the short term and long term. </s><s n="s3.4;p9.20">She may well need extra help from social services. </s><s n="s4.4;p9.20">The psychological distress here extends not only to Mrs <name type="other"/>, but also to her Son who is the primary carer and will also be at increased risk of developing depression and other health problems. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Management</head><div2><head rend="underlined">Investigations</head><p rend="bulleted" n="p10.20"><s n="s1.1;p10.20"><hi rend="bold">Bloods</hi> for - U&amp;E, Glucose, FBC, X-match </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p11.20"><s n="s1.5;p11.20"><hi rend="bold">X-rays</hi> - Both AP pelvis and lateral hip x-rays of the suspected side are essential. </s><s n="s2.5;p11.20">Careful scrutiny for disruption of the trabeculae, inferior or superior cortices, and abnormalities of pelvic contours (shenton's lines). </s><s n="s3.5;p11.20">Fractures of the femoral neck are not always visible on initial x-rays. </s><s n="s4.5;p11.20">Repeat x-rays, bone scanning or even MRI may be required if symptoms continue. </s><s n="s5.5;p11.20">Intracapsular neck of femur fractures may be graded radiologically according to the Garden classification. </s></p></div2><div2><head>RESULTS:</head><p rend="bulleted" n="p12.20"><s n="s1.1;p12.20">x-ray - subcapital fracture of left neck of femur + pubic rami fracture of the right hip </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p13.20"><s n="s1.1;p13.20">ECG - nil acute </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">Reassurance and explanation</head><p n="p14.20"><s n="s1.1;p14.20">Mrs <name type="other"/>, I'm afraid the x-ray findings have confirmed that you have broken your hip and will be requiring some major surgery to replace the hip joint </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">Prescription/medical intervention</head><list type="bulleted"><item>Assess vital signs. Treat with Haemaccel, but beware incipient heart failure. If present, monitor CVP. </item><item>Obtain IV access</item><item>Start IV infusion if indicated</item><item>Relieve pain - Give IV analgesia plus an antiemetic; provide all analgesia IV in small increments every few minutes until pain is controlled</item><item>X-rays - a good quality lateral is essential to make the diagnosis if there is impaction or little displacement.</item><item>Arrange admission to orthopaedic ward</item><item>Prepare for theatre: FBC, U&amp;E, CXR, ECG {to look for arrhthmias or evidence of MI}, crossmatch 2 units, consent. Tell the anesthetist about any drugs the patient is taking.</item><item>In theatre - If displacement is minimal, either multiple screw fixation, or Garden screws. (sliding nail plate units are not used for intracapsular fractures). Alternatively, the head is excised and a prosthesis is inserted. </item><item>In Mrs <name type="other"/>'s case, this was a Left hemiarthroplasty.</item></list><p n="p15.20"/></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">Observation</head><p n="p16.20"><s n="s1.1;p16.20">Check for complications: </s></p><list type="simple"><item>Ischaemic necrosis of the femoral head - supplied by the medial femoral circumflex artery</item><item>Infection</item><item>Non-union</item><item>Haematoma</item><item>PE</item><item>DVT</item><item>Post-op anaemia</item><item>CVA</item><item>MI</item></list></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">Referral and team working</head><list type="simple"><item>Occupational therapist</item><item>Social worker</item><item>Physiotherapist</item></list><p n="p17.20"/></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Outcome</head><p n="p18.20"><s n="s1.1;p18.20">Hip replacement undertaken, but developed post-op complications and has returned to hospital </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Evidence based care and issues for research</head><list type="simple"><head>Garden Classification of Intracapsular fractures:</head><item>Garden I - trabeculae angulated, but inferior cortex intact. No significant displacement.</item><item>Garden II - Trabeculae in line, but a fracture line visible from superior to inferior cortex. No significant displacement.</item><item>Garden III - Obvious complete fracture line with slight displacement and/or rotation of the femoral head</item><item>Garden IV - Gross, often complete, displacement of the femoral head - highest risk of avascular necrosis of the femoral head</item></list><p n="p19.20"/></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Commentary</head><p n="p20.20"><s n="s1.3;p20.20">Femur fractures fill 20% of all uk orthopaedic beds. </s><s n="s2.3;p20.20">The incidence is rising (~1:100/yr in females aged 75-84). </s><s n="s3.3;p20.20">Mortality is 50%. </s></p></div1></body><back/></text></TEI.2>
