<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_0066b" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Consideration is a perfectly adequate test of liability in contract, the so-called doctrine of intention to create legal relations is superfluous. Discuss this statement in the light of decided cases.</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">deleted: page numbers</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">1</p><p n="date">2004-12</p><p n="module title">Basic Techniques of Common Law in Contract &amp; Tort</p><p n="module code">LA102</p><p n="genre family">Essay</p><p n="discipline">Law</p><p n="disciplinary group">SS</p><p n="grade">M</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">1250</p><p n="number of s-units">58</p><p n="number of p">6</p><p n="number of tables">0</p><p n="number of figures">0</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">0</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">0</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">21.6</p><p n="average s-units per p">9.7</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">m</p><p n="year of birth">1984</p><p n="first language">Hindi</p><p n="education">OSA</p><p n="course">Law</p><p n="student ID">0066</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><docTitle><titlePart rend="bold">"Consideration is a perfectly adequate test of liability in contract, the so-called doctrine of intention to create legal relations is superfluous." Discuss this statement in the light of decided cases. </titlePart></docTitle></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="section"><p n="p1.6"><s n="s1.5;p1.6">"Every contract entails a free agreement, but not every agreement results in a contract." </s><ref target="BAWE_0066b-ftnote.001"/><s n="s2.5;p1.6">While both possess the elements of Offer and Acceptance, the key difference lies in the presence of 'Consideration' and 'Intention to create Legal Relations' which transforms agreements into contracts. </s><s n="s3.5;p1.6">Both these doctrines, although established concepts of English Contract Law, have their critics and supporters. </s><s n="s4.5;p1.6">While Treitel<ref target="BAWE_0066b-ftnote.002"/> and Cheshire<ref target="BAWE_0066b-ftnote.003"/> support the necessity of both doctrines, some believe that Intention to create legal relations cannot co-exist with the principle of consideration and is therefore superfluous functioning only as a 'substitute' for it<ref target="BAWE_0066b-ftnote.004"/> or assist in 'determining the boundaries of contract' where consideration does not exist as a principle (Prof. Williston- US Educationist)<ref target="BAWE_0066b-ftnote.005"/>. </s><s n="s5.5;p1.6">However, it is contended that English Contract Law can survive without consideration as Intention can perform its functions.<ref target="BAWE_0066b-ftnote.006"/> It is the purpose of this essay to examine the role of Consideration and Intention to create legal relations establishing that both form integral parts of Contract Law coexisting as independent principles essential to its functioning. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0066b-ftnote.001"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Adams, John N. &amp; Brownsword, Roger, '<hi rend="italic">Key Issues in Contract</hi>', 3rd Edition (1995), Butterworths Pg 22. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0066b-ftnote.002"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Treitel, G.H., '<hi rend="italic">The Law of Contract</hi>', Eleventh Edition (2003), Sweet &amp; Maxwell. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0066b-ftnote.003"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Cheshire, Fifoot, &amp; Furmston's '<hi rend="italic">Law of Contract</hi>', Fourteenth Edition (2001), Butterworths. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0066b-ftnote.004"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Applebey, George, '<hi rend="italic">Contract</hi> Law', (2001), Sweet &amp; Maxwell. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">Page 95 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0066b-ftnote.005"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Elliott, Catherine &amp; Quinn, Frances, '<hi rend="italic">Contract Law</hi>', 4th Edition (2003) Pearson Education Ltd. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">Page 51. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0066b-ftnote.006"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Hepple, B.A., '<hi rend="italic">Intention to Create Legal Relations'</hi>, [1970] CLJ 122-137. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">Page 122 </s></p></note><p n="p2.6"><s n="s1.10;p2.6">The doctrine of consideration is a "body of rules...the function of which is to put some limits on the enforceability of agreements in law." </s><ref target="BAWE_0066b-ftnote.007"/><s n="s2.10;p2.6">The traditional definition accrues a benefit to the promisor and a detriment to the promisee. </s><s n="s3.10;p2.6">It is also considered an 'exchange' model<ref target="BAWE_0066b-ftnote.008"/>, 'the reason for a promise'<ref target="BAWE_0066b-ftnote.009"/> or 'the price paid for one'<ref target="BAWE_0066b-ftnote.010"/>. </s><s n="s4.10;p2.6">However, in the 18 <hi rend="sup">th</hi> century, the concept of consideration was subject to criticism. </s><s n="s5.10;p2.6">Lord Mansfield believed that consideration was only a means through which one could ascertain the party's Intention to enter into a contract and this, if possible in any other way, would render it unnecessary.<ref target="BAWE_0066b-ftnote.011"/> He later modified his approach to consideration being intertwined with moral obligation, condemned by Lord Denman in <hi rend="italic">Eastwood v.</hi> </s><s n="s6.10;p2.6"><hi rend="italic">Kenyon</hi><ref target="BAWE_0066b-ftnote.012"/> as one which would 'annihilate consideration altogether'.<ref target="BAWE_0066b-ftnote.013"/> Atiyah criticizes consideration as 'artificial' and believes that its traditional meaning "no longer accords with the law actually enforced in courts"<ref target="BAWE_0066b-ftnote.014"/>. </s><s n="s7.10;p2.6">He advocates that consideration should only be a reason for a promise rather than vital to its enforcement.<ref target="BAWE_0066b-ftnote.015"/> Rigidity of consideration is another of its major drawbacks evidenced in the rule of sufficiency rather than adequacy. </s><s n="s8.10;p2.6">In <hi rend="italic">Mountford v.</hi> </s><s n="s9.10;p2.6"><hi rend="italic">Scott,</hi><ref target="BAWE_0066b-ftnote.016"/> promise to pay £1 was thought to be sufficient consideration without regard for the actual value of property. </s><s n="s10.10;p2.6">So, why despite criticism, does consideration survive as a legitimate test for contractual liability? </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0066b-ftnote.007"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Cracknell, D.G, "<hi rend="italic">Obligations: Contract Law"</hi>, Fourth Edition (2003), Old Bailey Press Page 40. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0066b-ftnote.008"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">"Fawcett (note 4 <hi rend="underlined">supra</hi>), Page 96" </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0066b-ftnote.009"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Atiyah, P.S., '<hi rend="italic">Essays on Contract</hi>' "<hi rend="underlined">Consideration: A Restatement</hi>", (1986), Clarendon Press-Oxford. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">Page 183. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0066b-ftnote.010"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">"Fawcett (note 3 <hi rend="underlined">supra</hi>), Page 82". </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0066b-ftnote.011"><p n="pn1.2"><s n="s1.1;pn1.2">"Fawcett (note 3 <hi rend="underlined">supra</hi>), Page 80". </s></p><p n="pn2.2"><s n="s1.1;pn2.2">"Fawcett (note 4 <hi rend="underlined">supra</hi>), Page 96". </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0066b-ftnote.012"><p n="pn1.1"><s rend="underlined italic" n="s1.2;pn1.1">Eastwood v. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1"><hi rend="underlined italic">Kenyon</hi> [1840] 11 A and E 438, 113 E.R. 482. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0066b-ftnote.013"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">"Fawcett (note 3 <hi rend="underlined">supra</hi>), Page 80-81". </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0066b-ftnote.014"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">"Fawcett (note 9 <hi rend="underlined">supra</hi>), Page 179. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0066b-ftnote.015"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid Page 183. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0066b-ftnote.016"><p n="pn1.1"><s rend="underlined italic" n="s1.2;pn1.1">Mountford v. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1"><hi rend="underlined italic">Scott</hi> [1975] 1 All E.R. 198 </s></p></note><p n="p3.6"><s n="s1.12;p3.6">There have been many developments in the doctrine of consideration fundamental to its survival in Contract Law. </s><s n="s2.12;p3.6">While these do not affect bilateral contracts (a promise for a promise) where consideration is easily established, they have profound influence in unilateral ones (a promise for an act) where contractual intention might come into play as consideration becomes difficult to ascertain.<ref target="BAWE_0066b-ftnote.017"/> The continuing disregard for the Benefit - Detriment Theory<ref target="BAWE_0066b-ftnote.018"/> has modified the definition of consideration. </s><s n="s3.12;p3.6">In <hi rend="italic">William v.</hi> </s><s n="s4.12;p3.6"><hi rend="italic">Roffey Bros,</hi><ref target="BAWE_0066b-ftnote.019"/> the concept of mutual benefit was favoured allowing extra payment for an already existing contractual duty to be valid consideration. </s><s n="s5.12;p3.6">If the traditional definition had been applied in this case, the claimant's action would fail, as there was no detriment to either party illustrating the flexibility of the courts with regard to consideration. </s><s n="s6.12;p3.6">Its ill effects are also taken care of by the principle of Equity. </s><s n="s7.12;p3.6">Consideration performs three main functions- dealing with the problems of evidence and establishing contracts, ensuring the enforceability of promises, and providing courts with a tool to strike out various promises based on public policy.<ref target="BAWE_0066b-ftnote.020"/> Consideration is also paramount in making and enforcing contracts. </s><s n="s8.12;p3.6">In bi-lateral commercial contracts, consideration rather than Intention is of importance. </s><s n="s9.12;p3.6">However, when considering domestic and social agreements, Intention is given priority over consideration. </s><s n="s10.12;p3.6">If there is a breach brought before a court of law, both Intention and consideration play an important role in deciding the validity of the contract. </s><s n="s11.12;p3.6">Thus, despite all criticism, consideration continues to survive as a test to ensure contractual liability. </s><s n="s12.12;p3.6">However, Intention to create legal relations is considered superfluous next to consideration despite the crucial role it plays in determining contractual liability. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0066b-ftnote.017"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Denning, A.T., "Recent Developments in the Doctrine of Consideration", [1952] 15 MLR 1, Page 1 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0066b-ftnote.018"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid Page 2 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0066b-ftnote.019"><p n="pn1.1"><s rend="underlined italic" n="s1.2;pn1.1">William v. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1"><hi rend="underlined italic">Roffey Bros and Nicholls (Contractors) Ltd</hi> [1991] 1 QB 1 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0066b-ftnote.020"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">"Fawcett (note 4 <hi rend="underlined">supra</hi>), Page 97". </s></p></note><p n="p4.6"><s n="s1.6;p4.6">Experts believe that as Intention is intertwined with consideration, its existence as an independent element is unnecessary. </s><s n="s2.6;p4.6">However, it can coexist with consideration contrary to the belief that it is only a 'good substitute' if "consideration were ever abolished"<ref target="BAWE_0066b-ftnote.021"/>. </s><s n="s3.6;p4.6">In a unilateral contract, as per Lord Denning, acceptance of an offer through action can be considered a party's Intention to create legal relations rather than consideration for the offer. <ref target="BAWE_0066b-ftnote.022"/><hi rend="italic">Carlil v.</hi> </s><s n="s4.6;p4.6"><hi rend="italic">Carbolic Smoke Ball Company</hi><ref target="BAWE_0066b-ftnote.023"/> is an important case that allows a response to an advertisement to be a valid contract and brings forth, to English Contract Law, the concept of Intention to create legal relations.<ref target="BAWE_0066b-ftnote.024"/> The promise to pay hundred pounds to who so ever caught influenza after taking the smoke balls was seen as the company's desire to create legal relations, a concept re-validated in <hi rend="italic">Bowerman v.</hi> </s><s n="s5.6;p4.6"><hi rend="italic">ABTA</hi><ref target="BAWE_0066b-ftnote.025"/> where ABTA's advertisement was held to be legally binding. </s><s n="s6.6;p4.6">The courts, therefore, began to give importance to Intention as one of the factors essential for contracts. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0066b-ftnote.021"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">"Fawcett (note 4 <hi rend="underlined">supra</hi>), Page 95". </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0066b-ftnote.022"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">"Fawcett (note 17 <hi rend="underlined">supra</hi>), Page 2". </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0066b-ftnote.023"><p n="pn1.1"><s rend="underlined italic" n="s1.3;pn1.1">Carlil v. </s><s rend="underlined italic" n="s2.3;pn1.1">Carbolic Smoke Ball Company [1893] 1 QB 256. </s><s rend="underlined" n="s3.3;pn1.1"> </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0066b-ftnote.024"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">"Fawcett (note 4 <hi rend="underlined">supra</hi>), Page 177". </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0066b-ftnote.025"><p n="pn1.1"><s rend="underlined italic" n="s1.2;pn1.1">Bowerman v ABTA Ltd. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1"> {1996} CLC 451 </s></p></note><p n="p5.6"><s n="s1.20;p5.6">Intention to create legal relations becomes essential in agreements where courts do not 'wish to have jurisdiction'<ref target="BAWE_0066b-ftnote.026"/>. </s><s n="s2.20;p5.6">These include family, social, government, and collective labour agreements. </s><s n="s3.20;p5.6">Contractual intention, although important in domestic agreements, is sometimes difficult to establish. </s><s n="s4.20;p5.6">In <hi rend="italic">Balfour v.</hi> </s><s n="s5.20;p5.6"><hi rend="italic">Balfour,</hi><ref target="BAWE_0066b-ftnote.027"/> the courts held that the parties did not intend to create legal relations as they were husband and wife at the time of agreement and such a family arrangement cannot constitute a contract. </s><s n="s6.20;p5.6">This is also evident in <hi rend="italic">Jones v.</hi> </s><s n="s7.20;p5.6"><hi rend="italic">Padavatton</hi><ref target="BAWE_0066b-ftnote.028"/> where an agreement between mother and daughter was not a contract because the parties did not intend to create legal relations. </s><s n="s8.20;p5.6">Therefore, the general presumption is against creating legal relations in family arrangements. </s><s n="s9.20;p5.6">However, in <hi rend="italic">Merritt v.</hi> </s><s n="s10.20;p5.6"><hi rend="italic">Merritt,</hi><ref target="BAWE_0066b-ftnote.029"/> since the marriage was breaking down, the agreement made between the parties was a binding contract because of their intentions. </s><s n="s11.20;p5.6">Courts also give importance to contractual intention in family business as in <hi rend="italic">Snelling v.</hi> </s><s rend="italic" n="s12.20;p5.6">John G Snelling Ltd. </s><ref target="BAWE_0066b-ftnote.030"/><s n="s13.20;p5.6">In social arrangements, contractual intentions come into play when validating contracts. </s><s n="s14.20;p5.6">In <hi rend="italic">Simpkins v.</hi> </s><s n="s15.20;p5.6"><hi rend="italic">Pays,</hi><ref target="BAWE_0066b-ftnote.031"/> an agreement between co-inhabitants was a valid contract because the nature of the agreement purported that the parties had an Intention to create legal relations.<ref target="BAWE_0066b-ftnote.032"/> However, collective labour (<hi rend="italic">Ford Motors v.</hi> </s><s n="s16.20;p5.6"><hi rend="italic">Amalgamated Union</hi><ref target="BAWE_0066b-ftnote.033"/>) and Public Service Agreements (Electric Company/Post Office) are 'promises in honour' and not legal contracts in spite of offer, acceptance, and consideration being present.<ref target="BAWE_0066b-ftnote.034"/> Although in commercial contracts Intention is assumed, it becomes important if the contract is ambiguous as in the case of <hi rend="italic">Edwards v.</hi> </s><s n="s17.20;p5.6"><hi rend="italic">Skyways</hi><ref target="BAWE_0066b-ftnote.035"/> where 'exgratia' payment was held not to rebut the presumption of contractual intention. </s><s n="s18.20;p5.6">However, this can be rebutted if e.g. an honorary clause is inserted within contracts proving that the parties did not intend to create legal relations, as in <hi rend="italic">Rose &amp; Frank v.</hi> </s><s n="s19.20;p5.6"><hi rend="italic">J.R. Crompton</hi><ref target="BAWE_0066b-ftnote.036"/>. </s><s n="s20.20;p5.6">Therefore, Intention to create legal relations is a valuable principle in Contract Law and not superfluous. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0066b-ftnote.026"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">"Fawcett (note 1 <hi rend="underlined">supra</hi>), Page 22". </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0066b-ftnote.027"><p n="pn1.1"><s rend="underlined italic" n="s1.2;pn1.1">Balfour v. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1"><hi rend="underlined italic">Balfour</hi> [1919] 2 KB 571. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0066b-ftnote.028"><p n="pn1.1"><s rend="underlined italic" n="s1.2;pn1.1">Jones v. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1"><hi rend="underlined italic">Padavatton</hi> [1969] 1 WLR 328. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0066b-ftnote.029"><p n="pn1.1"><s rend="underlined italic" n="s1.2;pn1.1">Merritt v. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1"><hi rend="underlined italic">Merritt</hi> [1970] 1 WLR 1211. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0066b-ftnote.030"><p n="pn1.1"><s rend="underlined italic" n="s1.3;pn1.1">Snelling v. </s><s rend="underlined italic" n="s2.3;pn1.1">John G Snelling Ltd. </s><s n="s3.3;pn1.1"> [1973] 1 QB 87 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0066b-ftnote.031"><p n="pn1.1"><s rend="underlined italic" n="s1.2;pn1.1">Simpkins v. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1"><hi rend="underlined italic">Pays</hi> [1955] 1 WLR 975. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0066b-ftnote.032"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">McKendrick, Ewan, '<hi rend="italic">Contract Law Text, Cases, and Materials</hi>' (2003), Oxford Univ. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">Press Page 300. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0066b-ftnote.033"><p n="pn1.1"><s rend="italic" n="s1.3;pn1.1">Ford Motors Co. </s><s rend="italic" n="s2.3;pn1.1">Ltd. v. </s><s n="s3.3;pn1.1"><hi rend="italic">Amalgamated Union of Engg. &amp; Foundry Workers</hi> [1969] 2 QB 303. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0066b-ftnote.034"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">"Fawcett (note 2 <hi rend="underlined">supra</hi>), Page 168". </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0066b-ftnote.035"><p n="pn1.1"><s rend="underlined italic" n="s1.2;pn1.1">Edwards v. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1"><hi rend="underlined italic">Skyways</hi> [1964] 1 WLR 349 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0066b-ftnote.036"><p n="pn1.1"><s rend="underlined italic" n="s1.3;pn1.1">Rose &amp; Frank Co v. </s><s rend="underlined italic" n="s2.3;pn1.1">JR Crompton &amp; Bros Ltd. </s><s n="s3.3;pn1.1"> [1923] 2 KB 261. </s></p></note><p n="p6.6"><s n="s1.5;p6.6">Both consideration and Intention to create legal relations are important principles of English Contract Law. </s><s n="s2.5;p6.6">Although sometimes overlapping, they are 'doctrinally distinct'<ref target="BAWE_0066b-ftnote.037"/>. </s><s n="s3.5;p6.6">Consideration plays a greater role in making and enforcing contracts whereas Intention is fundamental when viewing domestic, social, and some commercial agreements. </s><s n="s4.5;p6.6">It is argued that absence of consideration may provide a 'simpler' and 'more realistic explanation' than Intention; however, sometimes the later "may best capture the spirit of decision(s)"<ref target="BAWE_0066b-ftnote.038"/> (<hi rend="italic">White v.</hi> </s><s n="s5.5;p6.6"><hi rend="italic">Bluett</hi>).<ref target="BAWE_0066b-ftnote.039"/> In conclusion, both principles are fundamental to English Contract Law, as their coexistence is vital to its functioning. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0066b-ftnote.037"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">"Fawcett (note 32 <hi rend="underlined">supra</hi>), Page 299". </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0066b-ftnote.038"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid Page 299-301 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0066b-ftnote.039"><p n="pn1.1"><s rend="underlined italic" n="s1.3;pn1.1">White v. </s><s n="s2.3;pn1.1"><hi rend="underlined italic">Bluett </hi>[1853] 23 LJ Ex. </s><s n="s3.3;pn1.1">36. </s></p></note></div1></body><back><div1 type="bibliography"><div2 type="bibliography"><head rend="bold">BIBLIOGRAPHY</head><p rend="bold">Adams, John N. &amp; Brownsword, Roger, '<hi rend="italic">Key Issues in Contract</hi>', Third Edition (1995), Butterworths.</p><p rend="bold">Applebey, George, '<hi rend="italic">Contract</hi> Law', (2001), Sweet &amp; Maxwell.</p><p rend="bold">Atiyah, P.S., '<hi rend="italic">Essays on Contract</hi>', (1986), Clarendon Press-Oxford.</p><p rend="bold">Cheshire, Fifoot, &amp; Furmston's '<hi rend="italic">Law of Contract</hi>', Fourteenth Edition (2001), Butterworths.</p><p rend="bold">Cracknell, D.G.,"<hi rend="italic">Obligations: Contract Law"</hi>, Fourth Edition (2003), Old Bailey Press.</p><p rend="bold">Denning, A.T., "<hi rend="italic">Recent Developments in the Doctrine of Consideration",</hi> [1952] 15 MLR 1</p><p rend="bold">Elliott, Catherine &amp; Quinn, Frances, '<hi rend="italic">Contract Law</hi>', Fourth Edition (2003) Pearson Education Ltd.</p><p rend="bold">Hepple, B.A., '<hi rend="italic">Intention to Create Legal Relations'</hi>, [1970] CLJ 122-137.</p><p rend="bold">McKendrick, Ewan, '<hi rend="italic">Contract Law Text, Cases, and Materials</hi>' (2003), Oxford University Press.</p><p rend="bold">Treitel,G.H., '<hi rend="italic">The Law of Contract</hi>', Eleventh Edition (2003), Sweet &amp; Maxwell.</p><p rend="bold">IOLIS 2004/05 edition- Contract Law: Consideration Cases.</p></div2><div2 type="bibliography"><head rend="bold">EXTENDED BIBLIOGRAPHY</head><p rend="bold">Adams, John N. &amp; Brownsword, Roger, '<hi rend="italic">Contract, Consideration, and the Critical Path</hi>', [1990] 53 MLR 536-543.</p><p rend="bold">Adams, John N. &amp; Brownsword, Roger, '<hi rend="italic">Understanding Contract Law</hi>', Third Edition (2000), Sweet &amp; Maxwell.</p><p rend="bold">Atiyah, P.S., '<hi rend="italic">An Introduction to the Law of Contract</hi>', Fifth Edition (1995), Clarendon Press-Oxford.</p><p rend="bold">Beale, H.G, Bishop, W.D &amp; Furmston, M.P, '<hi rend="italic">Contract, Cases and Materials</hi>', Fourth Edition (2001), Butterworths.</p><p rend="bold">Beatson, J, "<hi rend="italic">Anson's Law of Contract</hi>", 28th Edition, Oxford University Press.</p><p rend="bold">Oughton, David &amp; Davis, Martin, '<hi rend="italic">Source Book on Contract Law</hi>', Second Edition (2000), Cavendish Publishing.</p><p rend="bold">Poole, Jill, '<hi rend="italic">Case Book on Contract law</hi>', Sixth Edition (2003), Oxford University Press Ltd.</p><p rend="bold">Poole, Jill, '<hi rend="italic">Textbook on Contract law</hi>', Sixth Edition (2001), Blackstone Press Ltd.</p><p rend="bold">Richards, Paul, 'Law of Contract', Fifth Edition (2002), Pearson Education Limited.</p><p rend="bold">Smith, Sir John &amp; Thomas, '<hi rend="italic">A Case Book on Contract',</hi> 11th Edition (2000), Sweet &amp; Maxwell.</p><p rend="bold">Smith, Sir John C, <hi rend="italic">'The Law of Contract',</hi> Fourth Edition (2002), Sweet &amp; Maxwell.</p></div2></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
