<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_0066a" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Analyse the decision of R (S) v Chief Constable of South Yorkshire [2004] 4 All ER 193</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">deleted: page numbers</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">1</p><p n="date">2004-12</p><p n="module title">The Modern English Legal System</p><p n="module code">LA115</p><p n="genre family">Critique</p><p n="discipline">Law</p><p n="disciplinary group">SS</p><p n="grade">M</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">1255</p><p n="number of s-units">39</p><p n="number of p">6</p><p n="number of tables">0</p><p n="number of figures">0</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">0</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">0</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">32.2</p><p n="average s-units per p">6.5</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">m</p><p n="year of birth">1984</p><p n="first language">Hindi</p><p n="education">OSA</p><p n="course">Law</p><p n="student ID">0066</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><docTitle><titlePart rend="bold">Analyse the decision of <hi rend="italic">R (S) v Chief Constable of South Yorkshire</hi> [2004] 4 All ER 193</titlePart></docTitle></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="section"><p n="p1.6"><s n="s1.9;p1.6">It is a general presumption in English Law, after the Human Rights Act 1998, that European Law gains precedence over Domestic Law. </s><s n="s2.9;p1.6">The courts have sometimes ruled Domestic Law to be incompatible when it contravenes EC Law. </s><s n="s3.9;p1.6">In the present case, <hi rend="italic">R (S) v Chief Constable of South Yorkshire</hi>,<ref target="BAWE_0066a-ftnote.001"/> this declaration of incompatibility is sought with regard to Article 64(1A) of the Police and Criminal Evidence Act 1984 (PACE) which allows Police to retain DNA samples of those arrested in connection with criminal investigation and subsequently acquitted of their charges. </s><s n="s4.9;p1.6">The Appellants argue that this contravenes Article 8(1) (Right to life) and 14 (Prohibition of Discrimination) of the European Convention of Human Rights (ECHR). </s><s n="s5.9;p1.6">However, House of Lords rejected these contentions. </s><s n="s6.9;p1.6">The Judges while formulating the ratio decidendi focus on the uniform interpretation of Convention Rights and advantages of DNA samples as a form of evidence along with their role in facilitating the detection and prevention of criminal activities. </s><s n="s7.9;p1.6">The ratio, therefore, is that interpretation of any Article of ECHR must be universal amongst all contracting States without local tradition influencing application of any particular Article of the Convention, albeit it might affect objective justification if any Article of Convention is contravened. </s><s n="s8.9;p1.6">If an Article of Domestic Law has a legitimate purpose, the practice enabled through that law, will be considered lawful rather than an abuse of official power. </s><s n="s9.9;p1.6">Since a ratio decidendi has binding force upon all lower courts, the essay discusses the reasoning behind the majority and dissenting opinions. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0066a-ftnote.001"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1"><hi rend="underlined">R (S) v Chief Constable of South Yorkshire</hi> [2004] 4 All ER 193 </s></p></note><p n="p2.6"><s n="s1.5;p2.6">Lord Steyn outlines the advantages of forensic science as having "inestimable value of cogency and objectivity...not affected by the subjective defects of testimony." </s><ref target="BAWE_0066a-ftnote.002"/><s n="s2.5;p2.6">When speaking specifically of DNA sample and other forensic science, he stresses on their advantages to the Criminal Justice System, which in cases of domestic burglary rises from 14% to 48%. </s><s n="s3.5;p2.6">It helps to exculpate the innocent and convict the guilty thereby controlling 'miscarriages of justice'.<ref target="BAWE_0066a-ftnote.003"/> Lord Brown of Eaton-Under-Heywood echoes similar views but considers the fear of misuse and stigmatization of the innocent in his judgment. </s><s n="s4.5;p2.6">They are legitimate but cannot curtail the advantages of having a large database for efficiency in dealing with crime and in the deterrence of present and future criminals.<ref target="BAWE_0066a-ftnote.004"/> With regard to stigmatization, it is important to note that sometimes samples are even taken on a voluntary basis. </s><s n="s5.5;p2.6">Privacy of individuals, although important, 'is not the only thing at stake'<ref target="BAWE_0066a-ftnote.005"/> as prevention of crime as a matter of policy is of primary concern and one of the major factors in the majority decision. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0066a-ftnote.002"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Para1 p197 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0066a-ftnote.003"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">P197-198 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0066a-ftnote.004"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Para88 p220 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0066a-ftnote.005"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Para24 p205 </s></p></note><p n="p3.6"><s n="s1.11;p3.6">The Appellants contended that Article 64(1A) of PACE is 'incompatible' with Article 8(1) and 14 of the ECHR. Even though the House majority decision did not accept this contention, they agreed that there is objective justification for breach of Conventional Rights under Article 8(2) namely to prevent and persecute crime if Article 8(1) is indeed contravened. </s><s n="s2.11;p3.6">It is important to note that the European Courts of Human Rights (ECtHR) has not yet made a decision on whether retention of samples contravenes the Convention. </s><s n="s3.11;p3.6">The European Commission in <hi rend="italic">McVeigh v UK</hi><ref target="BAWE_0066a-ftnote.006"/>, states it to be an 'open question'. </s><s n="s4.11;p3.6">However, retention of photographs and fingerprints were seen not to contravene Article 8(1) of ECHR in <hi rend="italic">Kinnunen v.</hi> </s><s n="s5.11;p3.6"><hi rend="italic">Finland</hi><ref target="BAWE_0066a-ftnote.007"/> in relation to fraud. </s><s n="s6.11;p3.6">Therefore, according to Lord Steyn the view of the Commission, as expressed in <hi rend="italic">Kinnunen v.</hi> </s><s n="s7.11;p3.6"><hi rend="italic">Finland</hi>, must be taken as the view of ECtHR.<ref target="BAWE_0066a-ftnote.008"/> Lord Rodger of Earlsferry agrees but stresses on the fact that the Court of Appeal puts much emphasis on English tradition. </s><s n="s8.11;p3.6">Such beliefs may influence parliament in changing laws but does not affect the Convention itself. </s><s n="s9.11;p3.6">He highlights the importance of looking at "equivalent Rights in the Convention" along with the "spectrum of attitudes across the contracting States." </s><ref target="BAWE_0066a-ftnote.009"/><s n="s10.11;p3.6">Lord Steyn also advocates that as the samples do not give out any personal information, their retention does not affect private lives of people thereby not engaging Article 8(1). </s><s n="s11.11;p3.6">He then stresses on the facts that fingerprints and samples have limited purpose, are useless unless have fingerprints from crime area for comparison, cannot be made public, and interference with private life is minimal in comparison with the advantages of a large database in the fight against crime.<ref target="BAWE_0066a-ftnote.010"/> Thus, Lord Steyn and the majority conclude that Article 8(1) is not engaged let alone contravened by Article 64(1A) of PACE, a conclusion even supported by Strasbourg case law. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0066a-ftnote.006"><p n="pn1.1"><s rend="underlined italic" n="s1.1;pn1.1">McVeigh v UK (1981) 25 DR 15 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0066a-ftnote.007"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1"><hi rend="underlined italic">Kinnunen v Finland App No 24950/94 </hi>(15 May 1996, unreopened) </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0066a-ftnote.008"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Para27 p207 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0066a-ftnote.009"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Para66 p215 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0066a-ftnote.010"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Para38 p209-210 </s></p></note><p n="p4.6"><s n="s1.6;p4.6">The question before the court regarding Article 14 centres on the definition of discrimination and to what extent the Appellants are discriminated against. </s><s n="s2.6;p4.6">The answers to the fundamental questions originating in <hi rend="italic">Wandsworth London BC v Michalak</hi><ref target="BAWE_0066a-ftnote.011"/> form the basis of Lord Steyn's judgment on discrimination in the current case. </s><s n="s3.6;p4.6">In ascertaining whether the Appellants are treated unjustly, he emphasises that it is unfair for them to compare themselves with people who were never required to give any samples to the police in connection with a criminal investigation. </s><s n="s4.6;p4.6">This is also supported by Lord Carswell, who stresses on the 'identical position' rather than 'same relevant situation' test when determining breach of Article 14.<ref target="BAWE_0066a-ftnote.012"/> Therefore, there has been no difference in treatment between Appellants and people in an 'identical situation'. </s><s n="s5.6;p4.6">Lord Steyn then underscores that Article 14 is 'not limitless' and going beyond the prescribed boundaries is not its goal.<ref target="BAWE_0066a-ftnote.013"/> If this is discrimination, Article 14 can be easily exploited or over used. </s><s n="s6.6;p4.6">Thus, in order to protect public interest, the majority judgment concluded that in this case even Article 14 of ECHR is not contravened by Article 64 (1A) of PACE. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0066a-ftnote.011"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1"><hi rend="underlined italic">Wandsworth London BC v Michalak</hi> [2002] EWCA Civ 271at [20], [2002 4 All ER 1136 at [20], [2003] 1 WLR 617 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0066a-ftnote.012"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Para83 p218 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0066a-ftnote.013"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Para48 p212 </s></p></note><p n="p5.6"><s n="s1.3;p5.6">However, the dissenting judgment of Baroness Hale of Richmond concluded that the retention of DNA profile and samples is an interference of Article 8(1) of ECHR. She accentuates 'informational privacy,' the concept of a person having the autonomous right and freedom to divulge any information he chooses, without which "the very basis of a civilized, free, and democratic society could be undermined" (Canadian Privacy Commissioner).<ref target="BAWE_0066a-ftnote.014"/> She exemplifies that if reading bank statement, private correspondence, and medical record is an encroachment of personal privacy then keeping/reading of DNA profile should also be treated in the same manner. </s><s n="s2.3;p5.6">Even though it is believed that the samples do not divulge information, their retention may provide access to personal information. </s><s n="s3.3;p5.6">Both ECtHR and European Commission also regard "keeping or storing of private information by State Institutions" as an interference with Article 8(1) of ECHR.<ref target="BAWE_0066a-ftnote.015"/> She fears that if Article 8(1) is not engaged in this case then neither is Article 14 and therefore the State becomes free to retain any samples without going against the Convention, increasing discrimination.<ref target="BAWE_0066a-ftnote.016"/> However, she too dismisses the appeal in favour of the advantages of retaining samples in fighting serious crimes believing there to be objective justifications for the actions of the Chief Constable under Article 8(2) of the Convention. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0066a-ftnote.014"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Para67 p215 Report on <hi rend="underlined italic">Genetic Testing and Privacy</hi> (1995) p2. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0066a-ftnote.015"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1"><hi rend="underlined italic">Leander v Sweden</hi> (1987)9 EHRR 433 at 450 (para48) </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0066a-ftnote.016"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Para77 p217 </s></p></note><p n="p6.6"><s n="s1.5;p6.6">The retention of samples by the police is an effective tool in the battle against crime. </s><s n="s2.5;p6.6">Although, there is nothing more private than genetic information, its retention does not "tarnish the innocence of the unconvicted in the eyes of the Law." </s><ref target="BAWE_0066a-ftnote.017"/><s n="s3.5;p6.6">The Lords agreed and concluded that Article 8(1) and 14 of the ECHR are not contravened in this case by Article 64(1A) of PACE whereas Her Ladyship dissented highlighting the objective justification for breach of Convention Rights. </s><s n="s4.5;p6.6">However, central to all judgements, was the 'inestimable value' of DNA analysis to eliminate suspects and incriminate the guilty. </s><s n="s5.5;p6.6">This allows for greater efficiency in law enforcement increasing accuracy in dealing with criminal activity- the primary concern of society. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0066a-ftnote.017"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Para50 p212 </s></p></note></div1></body><back/></text></TEI.2>
