<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_0067b" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>The role of maternal effect genes in the development of the nematode Caenorhabditis elegans</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">deleted: header: student name and number; footer: file name
deleted: Word count: 2,994</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">3</p><p n="date">2005-10</p><p n="module title">Development</p><p n="module code">BS301</p><p n="genre family">Explanation</p><p n="discipline">Biological Sciences</p><p n="disciplinary group">LS</p><p n="grade">D</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">3606</p><p n="number of s-units">136</p><p n="number of p">32</p><p n="number of tables">0</p><p n="number of figures">5</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">0</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">0</p><p n="abstract present">abstract present</p><p n="average words per s-unit">26.5</p><p n="average s-units per p">4.3</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">m</p><p n="year of birth">1984</p><p n="first language">English</p><p n="education">UKA</p><p n="course">Biochemistry</p><p n="student ID">0067</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><docTitle><titlePart rend="bold">The role of maternal effect genes in the development of the nematode <hi rend="italic">Caenorhabditis elegans</hi></titlePart></docTitle></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="abstract"><p n="p1.32"><s n="s1.3;p1.32">Maternally expressed genes are essential for the correct patterning and cell-fate determination in the early <hi rend="italic">Caenorhabditis elegans</hi> embryo. </s><s n="s2.3;p1.32">The PAR proteins and MEX-5/6 are responsible for initial polarisation of the zygote,<hi rend="italic"> skn-1</hi> is required to specify the EMS fate, the bifunctional protein PIE-1 is required to maintain the totipotent germ cell lineage and specification of the AB lineage involves a system homologous to Notch in <hi rend="italic">Drosophila</hi>. </s><s n="s3.3;p1.32">This review describes the current understanding of these molecular mechanisms in the specification of cell fates in the pregastrulation embryo. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Introduction</head><p n="p2.32"><s n="s1.4;p2.32">The potential of <hi rend="italic">Caenorhabditis elegans</hi> as a model organism for the study of embryology emerged in the 1970s (Brenner, 1974). </s><s n="s2.4;p2.32">This free-living soil nematode is ideal for studying in the laboratory as it has a rapid period of embryogenesis (16 hours) and each worm has an invariant cell lineage, with exactly 959 somatic cells in the adult, which can be easily traced during development through the transparent cuticle (Sulston &amp; Horvitz, 1977). </s><s n="s3.4;p2.32"><hi rend="italic">C.elegans</hi> is a small round-worm, approximately 1 mm long, that lives for 2-3 weeks and can be fed on <hi rend="italic">Escherichia coli</hi>, which allows large numbers to be conveniently raised in a Petri dish. </s><s n="s4.4;p2.32">The predominant adult form is hermaphroditic, containing both sperm and eggs and therefore reproduction is rapid, either by self-fertilization or by cross-fertilization with the rare males. </s></p><p n="p3.32"><s n="s1.7;p3.32">The genetics for <hi rend="italic">C.elegans</hi> is advancing rapidly. </s><s n="s2.7;p3.32">It has a small genome at 8 x 10 <hi rend="sup">7</hi> bp and relatively few genes for a eukaryote - around 17,500. </s><s n="s3.7;p3.32">It was the first multicellular organism for which the genome was completely sequenced (<hi rend="italic">C.elegans</hi> Sequencing Consortium 1999) and approximately 8,000 <hi rend="italic">C.elegans</hi> proteins have already been matched to homologous human gene transcripts (Lai <hi rend="italic">at al.</hi> </s><s n="s4.7;p3.32">, 2000). </s><s n="s5.7;p3.32">Specific mutants may be produced by targeted deletion through transposon insertion or mutagens. </s><s n="s6.7;p3.32">Embryos may be manipulated by transformation or injection with transgenes and marker proteins such as green fluorescent protein (GFP) are easily visualised in the transparent embryos. </s><s n="s7.7;p3.32">RNA interference (RNAi) is a particularly useful technique for studying maternal effect genes by eliminating the expression of specific maternal or zygotic genes in offspring. </s></p><div2><head rend="underlined">Reproduction</head><p n="p4.32"><s n="s1.3;p4.32">In hermaphrodite worms, fertilization occurs in the spermatheca - an organ where the sperm is stored - when mature oocytes pass from the ovary towards the vulva (Fig 1A-B). </s><s n="s2.3;p4.32">The point of sperm entry determines the posterior end of the embryo. </s><s n="s3.3;p4.32">After fertilization, a rigid, ovoid-shaped chitin eggshell called the chorion is made (Kemphues &amp; Strome, 1997) and the long axis of this ovoid is termed the anteroposterior (a/p) axis of the embryo. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0067b-pic.001"><head><hi rend="bold">Figure 1 <hi rend="italic"> Caenorhabditis elegans</hi></hi> (A) Side view of the adult hermaphrodite. (B) The gonads. Near the distal end, germ cells undergo mitosis and undergo meiosis as they move away from the distal tip. Early meioses form sperm, which are stored in the spermatheca. Later meioses form eggs, which are fertilized as they pass through the spermatheca. (C) Early development of the embryo. The P-lineage consists of stem cells that will eventually form the germ cells. (D) Abbreviated cell lineage chart. The number of derived cells refers to the 558 cells present in the newly hatched larva, some of which continue to divide to produce the 959 somatic cells of the adult. Descendent cells are named according to their positions relative to their sister cells, e.g. AB.al is the 'left-hand' daughter of the AB.a cell, which is the 'anterior' daughter of the AB cell. (From Gilbert, Developmental Biology 7 <hi rend="sup">th</hi> edn, after Pines 1992, Sulston &amp; Horvitz 1977 and Sulston <hi rend="italic">et al.</hi> 1983)</head></figure></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">Early cell lineage</head><p n="p5.32"><s n="s1.4;p5.32">Cleavage of the zygote (P0) is asymmetric, forming two different daughter cells - a larger anterior blastomere, AB, and a smaller posterior blastomere, P1, which possess different fates. </s><s n="s2.4;p5.32">The AB blastomere goes on to divide equatorially (90°C to the a/p axis; Fig 1C), eventually forming pharyngeal, hypodermal and neural tissues. </s><s n="s3.4;p5.32">This division is followed by a series of meridional (transverse), asymmetrical divisions of the P-lineage (P1, P2, P3 and P4), which consists of stem cells at the posterior end that eventually form the primordial germ cells, Z2 and Z3. </s><s n="s4.4;p5.32">These divisions also form the remaining somatic 'founder cells' (MS, E, C and D) that produce differentiated descendents (Fig 1D). </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Initial asymmetries in the embryo</head><div2><head rend="underlined">Fertilization</head><p n="p6.32"><s n="s1.4;p6.32">Goldstein and Hird (1996) showed that the sperm defines the posterior end of the zygote and therefore the a/p axis. </s><s n="s2.4;p6.32">Oocytes are arrested in prophase I of meiosis as they pass through the spermatheca. </s><s n="s3.4;p6.32">Upon fertilization, the oocyte completes meiosis and the cytoskeleton is arranged by the sperm-derived centrosomes to create cytoplasmic streams. </s><s n="s4.4;p6.32">The flow of internal cytoplasm towards the posterior end and cortical cytoplasm towards the anterior end causes migration of the oocyte pronucleus to meet the sperm pronucleus at the posterior end where they fuse before migrating back to the centre of the embryo (Gotta &amp; Ahringer, 2001; Golden, 2000). </s></p><p n="p7.32"><s n="s1.6;p7.32">During the first cleavage, the mitotic spindle becomes asymmetrically placed along the a/p axis, requiring the microtubule protein dynein, the cortical DEP protein LET-99 and GPB-1 to rotate and position the mitotic spindle towards the posterior. </s><s n="s2.6;p7.32">A number of maternal factors involved in the determination of cell fates are partitioned differentially in the first few divisions. </s><s n="s3.6;p7.32">For instance, P granules are always segregated with the P-lineage and are thought to promote the germline fate, as we will see later. </s><s n="s4.6;p7.32">Mutations in the <hi rend="italic">mes-1</hi> gene affect polarity, spindle orientation and P granule localisation in the P2 &amp; P3 blastomeres (Tenenhaus <hi rend="italic">et al.</hi> </s><s n="s5.6;p7.32">, 2001). </s><s n="s6.6;p7.32">Polarisation of the zygote is essential for the correct segregation of these components and generation of cell diversity and specialisation during development of the embryo. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">Establishment of polarity - PAR and MEX proteins</head><p n="p8.32"><s n="s1.1;p8.32">The first distinct phase of polarisation before pronuclear meeting is termed 'establishment' and involves the segregation of the cortical <hi rend="bold">PAR</hi> proteins and cytoplasmic <hi rend="bold">MEX-5/6</hi> proteins, which provide polarity information during the first cell cycle and are necessary for the proper asymmetric distribution of cell-fate regulators such as MEX-3, MEX-1, MES-1 and PIE-1. </s></p><p n="p9.32"><s n="s1.2;p9.32">Mutations of the <hi rend="italic">par</hi> genes cause early <hi rend="italic">par</hi>titioning defects including an equal first cleavage, synchronous second cleavage, mislocalisation of P granules and alterations to spindle orientation during the second cleavage. </s><s n="s2.2;p9.32">These defects lead to the variable absences of intestine and germline and excess of pharyngeal and body wall muscle. </s></p><p n="p10.32"><s n="s1.7;p10.32">Signalling between the sperm asters and the actin cytoskeleton causes PAR-1 (a serine/threonine kinase identified as Dishevelled-associated kinase in <hi rend="italic">Drosophila</hi>) and PAR-2 (a RING finger protein) to localise to the posterior cortex (Fig 2), while PAR-3 and PAR-6 localise to the anterior, in an evolutionarily conserved complex with an atypical protein kinase C called PKC-3. </s><s n="s2.7;p10.32">These proteins interact via their PDZ domains (Lyczak <hi rend="italic">et al.</hi> </s><s n="s3.7;p10.32">, 2002). </s><s n="s4.7;p10.32">PAR-4 and PAR-5 are not polarised but remain enriched throughout the cortex. </s><s n="s5.7;p10.32">PAR-5 (a 14-3-3 protein) may serve to ensure a maximal response of the PAR-3/PAR-6/PKC-3 complex to the sperm aster and prevent overlap with PAR-2. </s><s n="s6.7;p10.32">Consistent with this possibility, PAR-3 contains a predicted 14-3-3 binding motif (Morton <hi rend="italic">et al</hi>., 2002). </s><s n="s7.7;p10.32">A major function of PAR-1 is to localize the germline-specific protein, PIE-1, to the P-lineage (see below). </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0067b-pic.002"><head><hi rend="bold">Figure 2</hi> Model for polarization of the <hi rend="italic">C. elegans</hi> zygote. (A) Graphic depiction of the establishment and maintenance phases. Proteins that localize to the anterior are in blue (PAR-3, PAR-6, PKC-3 on the cortex, MEX-5 and MEX-6 in the cytoplasm). Proteins that localize to the posterior are in pink (PAR-2 and PAR-1 on the cortex, PIE-1 in the cytoplasm). Circles: pronuclei, Black lines: microtubules. (B) Sequential repression model (modified from Kemphues, (2000)). Lines with bars depict antagonistic interactions, whereas lines with arrows depict positive interactions. PAR-1 is restricted to the posterior by the anterior PARs. From Cuenca <hi rend="italic">et al.</hi> (2003).</head></figure><p n="p11.32"><s n="s1.6;p11.32">PAR polarisation is initiated by the sperm-derived microtubule organising centre (MTOC; Wallenfang &amp; Seydoux, 2000). </s><s n="s2.6;p11.32">Chemical disruption of microfilaments with cytochalasin D - or RNA interference of the non-muscle myosin II heavy chain gene, <hi rend="italic">nmy-2</hi> or myosin light chain gene, <hi rend="italic">mlc-4</hi> - eliminates the cytoplasmic flows and pseudocleavage, causing PAR-3 and PAR-6 to remain throughout the cortex (Guo &amp; Kemphues, 1996; Cuenca <hi rend="italic">et al.</hi> </s><s n="s3.6;p11.32">, 2003). </s><s n="s4.6;p11.32">Maturation of functional paternal centrosomes, however, requires the maternal gene <hi rend="italic">spd-2</hi> (O'Connell <hi rend="italic">et al.</hi> </s><s n="s5.6;p11.32">, 2000). </s><s n="s6.6;p11.32">Other genes with suggestive roles in intracellular trafficking come from <hi rend="italic">pod-1</hi> and <hi rend="italic">pod-2</hi> (polarity and osmotic defective) and <hi rend="italic">ooc-3</hi> and <hi rend="italic">ooc-5</hi> mutants (Gotta &amp; Ahringer, 2001). </s></p><p n="p12.32"><s n="s1.4;p12.32">The predominantly cytoplasmic proteins MEX-5 and MEX-6 also play a role during the establishment phase (Fig 2). </s><s n="s2.4;p12.32">Although these proteins appear not to be absolutely essential for PAR localisation, it is thought they ensure a rapid response by the PAR-3/PAR-6/PKC-3 complex to the MTOC/actin cytoskeleton signal. </s><s n="s3.4;p12.32">In a model proposed by Cuenca <hi rend="italic">et al.</hi> </s><s n="s4.4;p12.32">(2003), clearance of PAR-3/PAR-6/PKC-3 complexes, enhanced by MEX-5/6, and accumulation of PAR-1 and PAR-2 at the posterior end may constitute a feedback loop in which PAR-1 presence reduces MEX-5/6 expression (Fig 2). </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">Maintenance</head><p n="p13.32"><s n="s1.4;p13.32">Following fusion of the two pronuclei, the MTOC-dependent signal is switched off and PAR-1, PAR-2 and another protein, CDC-42 become essential for exclusion of the PAR-3/PAR-6/PKC-3 complex from the posterior of the zygote. </s><s n="s2.4;p13.32">How these proteins function together to maintain the balance between anterior and posterior PAR domains remains to be determined (Cuenca <hi rend="italic">et al.</hi> </s><s n="s3.4;p13.32">, 2003). </s><s n="s4.4;p13.32">There is also evidence that the PAR proteins are important in subsequent cell divisions (Lyczak <hi rend="italic">et al</hi>., 2002). </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Fate of the EMS blastomere: the role of <hi rend="italic">skn-1</hi></head><p n="p14.32"><s n="s1.3;p14.32">Patterning in the early embryo is a result of the complex interaction between oriented asymmetric divisions and cell-cell interactions. </s><s n="s2.3;p14.32">For example, the P1 cell is able to develop autonomously in the absence of AB, but the daughters of AB require interactions from the descendents of P1 - the EMS and P2 blastomeres. </s><s n="s3.3;p14.32">Proper development of the EMS blastomere is determined by signals from P2 (via the <hi rend="italic">Wnt</hi> pathway) as well as the autonomous, maternally expressed transcription factor <hi rend="bold">SKN-1</hi>, as described in this section. </s></p><p n="p15.32"><s n="s1.3;p15.32">SKN-1 is a predicted 61 kDa protein, largely hydrophobic, containing homologous regions to the bZIP (leucine zipper) class of transcription factors and the ant homeodomain in <hi rend="italic">Drosophila</hi> (Bowerman <hi rend="italic">et al.</hi> </s><s n="s2.3;p15.32">, 1992). </s><s n="s3.3;p15.32">Unlike the bZIP proteins, however, SKN-1 lacks a dimerisation segment and binds DNA as a monomer (Fig 3). </s></p><p n="p16.32"><s n="s1.5;p16.32">During cleavage of the zygote, SKN-1 protein is loaded unequally between the P1 and AB sister blastomeres, an effect mediated by MEX-1 and PAR-1. </s><s n="s2.5;p16.32">SKN-1 is required for differentiation of the EMS daughter of P1: in <hi rend="italic">skn-1</hi> mutant embryos, neither EMS nor its daughter E develops normally, instead of making pharyngeal and intestinal structures they produce extra hypodermal and body wall tissues. </s><s n="s3.5;p16.32"><hi rend="italic">skn-1+</hi> male sperm are unable to rescue embryos from <hi rend="italic">skn-1</hi>-/- mothers, indicating that maternal expression of the <hi rend="italic">skn-1</hi> gene is necessary for normal embryogenesis. </s><s n="s4.5;p16.32">In <hi rend="italic">mex-1</hi> mutant embryos, pharyngeal cells are produced from both AB and P1 descendents (Bowerman <hi rend="italic">et al.</hi> </s><s n="s5.5;p16.32">, 1993). </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0067b-pic.003"><head><hi rend="bold">Figure 3</hi> 3-D model of the SKN-1 protein (red/yellow) bound to DNA (green). The basic bZIP region near the carboxyl-terminal of the protein binds to the major groove of the DNA in the form of an alpha-helix, recognising the sequence GTCAT. The ant domain fits into the minor groove of the DNA at an A-T-rich region adjacent to the GTCAT signal and the rest of the protein serves to stabilise these interactions (Blackwell <hi rend="italic">et al.</hi> , 1994). Model from Sarai <hi rend="italic">et al</hi> . BioInfo Bank website (2005).</head></figure><p n="p17.32"><s n="s1.5;p17.32">SKN-1 activates the transcription of at least two genes, <hi rend="italic">med-1</hi> and <hi rend="italic">med-2</hi>, whose products are also transcription factors. </s><s n="s2.5;p17.32">The MED transcription factors appear to specify the fate of the EMS cell, since expression of the <hi rend="italic">med</hi> genes in other cells can cause non-EMS cells to become EMS, even in the absence of SKN-1. </s><s n="s3.5;p17.32">SKN-1 protein is present in the embryo from the 2-cell stage until the 12-cell stage, when it suddenly disappears. </s><s n="s4.5;p17.32">However, zygotic expression is required post-embryogenesis, for the development of intestinal cells (Maduro <hi rend="italic">et al.</hi> </s><s n="s5.5;p17.32">, 2001). </s></p><div2><head rend="underlined">Differentiation of the EMS daughter cells</head><p n="p18.32"><s n="s1.3;p18.32">Following cleavage of EMS, SKN-1 mediates the endodermal development of the E blastomere. </s><s n="s2.3;p18.32">The transcription factor <hi rend="bold">POP-1</hi> is necessary to repress SKN-1 in the MS cell, to prevent it also becoming endoderm. </s><s n="s3.3;p18.32">POP-1 in the posterior EMS daughter receives signals from MOM-1 and MOM-2 (Wnt pathway components) and a receptor tyrosine kinase from P2 to allow SKN-1 to switch on endodermal genes in that cell, which becomes E (Fig 4; Maduro </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0067b-pic.004"><head><hi rend="bold">Figure 4</hi> Cell signalling in the 4-cell embryo. P2 produces two signals: (1) APX-1 (Delta), which is bound by GLP-1 (Notch) on the ABp blastomere, promoting the posterior fate in ABp, and (2) MOM-2 (Wnt), which binds MOM-5 (Frizzled) protein on the EMS cell, promoting the endoderm fate in the E daughter. (From Gilbert, Developmental Biology 7 <hi rend="sup">th</hi> edn, after Han 1998.)<hi rend="italic">et al.</hi> , 2001).</head></figure></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">Differentiation of the C and D blastomeres</head><p n="p19.32"><s n="s1.3;p19.32">The somatic descendents of the P2 blastomere (C and D) require another putative transcription factor, <hi rend="bold">PAL-1.</hi> </s><s n="s2.3;p19.32">PAL-1 is regulated by the MEX-3 protein, which binds to <hi rend="italic">pal-1</hi> mRNA, inhibiting its translation. </s><s n="s3.3;p19.32">PAL-1 is also inhibited by SKN-1, preventing it from acting in the EMS cell (Hunter &amp; Kenyon, 1996). </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Development of the germline: gene regulation by PIE-1 and MEX-1</head><p n="p20.32"><s n="s1.6;p20.32">After the second cleavage, equal levels of SKN-1 are found in both daughters of the P1 blastomere, EMS and P2. </s><s n="s2.6;p20.32">However, only EMS produces pharyngeal cells and P2 is still able to develop into a healthy germline in <hi rend="italic">skn-</hi>1 mutant embryos. </s><s n="s3.6;p20.32">The maternal protein <hi rend="bold">PIE-1</hi> is segregated with the germ lineage and is necessary for the germline fate by inhibiting both SKN-1 and PAL-1 function in the P2 and subsequent germline cells (Mello <hi rend="italic">et al.</hi> </s><s n="s4.6;p20.32">, 1992). </s><s n="s5.6;p20.32">In embryos from <hi rend="italic">pie-1</hi> mutant mothers (<hi rend="italic">p</hi>harynx and <hi rend="italic">i</hi>ntestine in <hi rend="italic">e</hi>xcess), germline blastomeres adopt somatic fates, with the P2 cell behaving as a wildtype EMS blastomere (Fig 5; Mello <hi rend="italic">et al.</hi> </s><s n="s6.6;p20.32">, 1992). </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0067b-fig.001"><head><hi rend="bold">Figure 5</hi> Early embryonic lineage in wild-type and <hi rend="italic">pie-1</hi> mutants. This tree diagram shows the series of divisions of the zygote (P0) into somatic (AB, EMS, C, D) and germline (P1, P2, P3, P4) blastomeres, and the division of P4 into Z2 and Z3. In <hi rend="italic">pie-1</hi> mutants (no PIE-1 protein), transcription is activated in the germ lineage, and SKN-1 causes P2 descendants to adopt fates similar to those adopted by EMS descendants. Thick vertical lines: cells that produce mRNAs. Red lines: cells containing PIE-1 protein. Blue lines: cells containing SKN-1 protein. From Seydoux &amp; Strome (1999).</head></figure><div2><head rend="underlined">Transcriptional silencing of somatic genes</head><p n="p21.32"><s n="s1.7;p21.32">PIE-1 is a novel 38 kDa protein whose structure is not similar to any known transcription factors, although it contains two CCCH zinc-finger domains that have been shown to bind RNA in other proteins, implicating a role in mRNA cleavage, processing and/or turnover. </s><s n="s2.7;p21.32">However, later studies provided evidence for a role in the direct repression of zygotic transcription by RNA polymerase II (RNAPII). </s><s n="s3.7;p21.32">Firstly, PIE-1 is present in the nucleus as well as the cytoplasm (Mello <hi rend="italic">et al.</hi> </s><s n="s4.7;p21.32">, 1996). </s><s n="s5.7;p21.32">Secondly, PIE-1 disappears from the germline shortly after division of P4 into Z2 and Z3, coinciding with the onset of zygotic transcription, as determined by the appearance of the H5 phosphoepitope on the carboxyl-terminal domain of RNAPII (RNAPII-H5). </s><s n="s6.7;p21.32">Somatic blastomeres acquire the ability to transcribe new mRNA minutes after separation from the germ lineage, and furthermore, newly transcribed mRNAs are additionally detected in germline blastomeres in <hi rend="italic">pie-1</hi> mutants (Fig 5). </s><s n="s7.7;p21.32">Also, the ectopic expression of PIE-1 in somatic cells by transformation of the <hi rend="italic">pie-1</hi> gene fused to a heat shock promoter represses embryonic transcription (Seydoux &amp; Strome, 1999). </s></p><p n="p22.32"><s n="s1.9;p22.32">It is suggested that PIE-1 suppresses the action of maternally encoded transcription factors such as SKN-1 from activating zygotic genes that promote somatic fates through the general repression of mRNA transcription by RNAPII in germline blastomeres, thus protecting the germline fate. </s><s n="s2.9;p22.32"><hi rend="italic">skn-1::pie-1</hi> double mutants do not produce germ cells either, indicating that other factors are involved in germ cell determination (Mello <hi rend="italic">et al.</hi> </s><s n="s3.9;p22.32">, 1992). </s><s n="s4.9;p22.32">The mechanism of transcriptional repression has recently been dissected (Batchelder <hi rend="italic">et al.</hi> </s><s n="s5.9;p22.32">, 1999; Zhang <hi rend="italic">et al.</hi> </s><s n="s6.9;p22.32">, 2003). </s><s n="s7.9;p22.32">Unexpectedly, instead of transcriptional initiation, PIE-1 inhibits transcriptional elongation. </s><s n="s8.9;p22.32">The process of elongation requires phosphorylation by CDK9 (a cyclin-dependent kinase, associated with cyclin T in the P-TEFb complex) of the RNAPII-H5 phosphoepitope. </s><s n="s9.9;p22.32">In transfected mammalian HeLa cells, PIE-1 inhibits CDK9, through a sequence (YAPMAPT) similar to the repeated heptapepide sequence in the RNAPII C-terminal domain (YSPTSPS) and that apparently competes for CDK9 (Zhang et al., 2003; Strome, 2005). </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">Expression of maternal factors essential for germ cell development</head><p n="p23.32"><s n="s1.7;p23.32">The presence of PIE-1 also in the cytoplasm, where it is commonly found associated with P granules (Fig 6B), suggests a further role in germline development. </s><s n="s2.7;p23.32">P granules are rich in maternal mRNAs and the second zinc-finger motif (ZF2) of PIE-1 is necessary and sufficient to target it to the P granules (Tenenhaus <hi rend="italic">et al.</hi> </s><s n="s3.7;p23.32">2001). </s><s n="s4.7;p23.32">One maternal mRNA associated with P granules is <hi rend="italic">nos-2</hi> (a homolog of Nanos in <hi rend="italic">Drosophila</hi>), which is normally expressed in P4 and is required for the correct migration of Z2 and Z3 to meet the somatic gonads. </s><s n="s5.7;p23.32"><hi rend="italic">nos-2</hi> is not translated in P4 from <hi rend="italic">pie-1</hi> mutants, indicating that <hi rend="italic">pie-1</hi> also promotes the expression of maternally encoded factors essential for primordial germ cell development. </s><s n="s6.7;p23.32">This role can be genetically and functionally separated from the transcriptional silencing described above by mutations that affect either one function or the other (Tenenhaus <hi rend="italic">et al.</hi> </s><s n="s7.7;p23.32">, 2001). </s></p><p n="p24.32"><s n="s1.2;p24.32"><hi rend="bold">MEX-1</hi> is similar in structure to PIE-1 but is found only associated with P granules in the cytoplasm where it also regulates gene expression, with different targets to PIE-1. </s><s n="s2.2;p24.32"><hi rend="italic">mex-1</hi> mutations disrupt segregation of P granules, prevent formation of germ cells and cause inappropriate patterns of somatic cell differentiation. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0067b-pic.005"><head><hi rend="bold">Figure 6</hi> Distributions of embryonically transcribed RNA and PIE-1 in normal 4-cell embryos. (A) <hi rend="italic">pes-10</hi> transcripts are detected in ABa, ABp, and EMS but not in P2 (on the right). (B) PIE-1 accumulates primarily in P2, where it is concentrated in the nucleus and in P granules. From Strome (2005), provided by Seydoux G.</head></figure></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">Segregation of P granules, PIE-1 and MEX-1</head><p n="p25.32"><s n="s1.2;p25.32">MEX-1 localisation is dependent on PAR segregation and is in turn required to restrict <hi rend="italic">pie-1</hi> expression and activity to germline blastomeres. </s><s n="s2.2;p25.32">P granules are unstable in somatic cytoplasm (Hird <hi rend="italic">et al</hi>., 1996) and PIE-1 and MEX-1 are degraded in somatic lineages by interactions with ubiquitin ligase via the ZF1 domain (Spike &amp; Strome, 2003). </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Determining AB lineage fates: the <hi rend="italic">C.elegans</hi> maternal Notch system</head><p n="p26.32"><s n="s1.2;p26.32">The early Aba and Abp blastomeres are identical and exchangeable (Priess &amp; Thomson, 1987); however, in the late 4-cell stage, these two cells are committed to different fates. </s><s n="s2.2;p26.32">This determination requires the Notch-like receptor, <hi rend="bold">GLP-1</hi>, and the Delta-like membrane-bound ligand, <hi rend="bold">APX-1</hi>. </s></p><div2><head rend="underlined">4-cell stage</head><p n="p27.32"><s n="s1.3;p27.32">Maternal GLP-1 mRNA is found in oocytes and all blastomeres up to the 8-cell stage but its translation is regulated temporally and spatially such that, at the 4-cell stage GLP-1 is detected only in the AB blastomeres (Evans <hi rend="italic">et al.,</hi> 1994). </s><s n="s2.3;p27.32">A reporter RNA study identified a region of 125 bases at the 3' end of the 3' UTR of <hi rend="italic">glp-1</hi> mRNA, called the temporal control region (TCR), and a 66-base spatial control region (SCR) in the middle of the 3' UTR. The TCR is required for the suppression of translation of <hi rend="italic">glp-1</hi> mRNA in oocytes and one-cell embryos whilst the SCR suppresses translation in the posterior blastomeres (Evans <hi rend="italic">et al.</hi> </s><s n="s3.3;p27.32">, 1994). </s></p><p n="p28.32"><s n="s1.2;p28.32">The APX-1 signal in the membrane of P2 breaks the initial symmetry between ABa and Abp by stimulating GLP-1 only on the AB daughter that it touches (ABp). </s><s n="s2.2;p28.32">In doing this, the P2 blastomere initiates the dorsal/ventral axis of <hi rend="italic">C.elegans</hi> and determines the different fates of the AB descendents (Fig 4). </s></p><p n="p29.32"><s n="s1.10;p29.32">APX-1 translation is regulated by <hi rend="bold">POS-1.</hi> </s><s n="s2.10;p29.32">Maternal <hi rend="italic">apx-1</hi> mRNA is present in all early blastomeres but APX-1 is only expressed in P1 at the 2-cell stage and in EMS but mainly in the membrane of P2 in the 4-cell stage (Mickey <hi rend="italic">et al.</hi> </s><s n="s3.10;p29.32">, 1996). </s><s n="s4.10;p29.32">In <hi rend="italic">pos-1</hi> mutant embryos (lethal), APX-1 is not detected in spite of the abundant <hi rend="italic">apx-1</hi> mRNA (Tabara <hi rend="italic">et al</hi>. </s><s n="s5.10;p29.32">1999). </s><s n="s6.10;p29.32">POS-1 is another protein with two CCCH zinc finger motifs (Ogura <hi rend="italic">et al</hi>., 2003) and is observed in the posterior blastomeres as a temporary component of P granules (Tabara <hi rend="italic">et al</hi>. </s><s n="s7.10;p29.32">1999). </s><s n="s8.10;p29.32">Ogura <hi rend="italic">et al</hi>. </s><s n="s9.10;p29.32">(2003) recently show that POS-1 binds the SCR region of <hi rend="italic">glp-1</hi> mRNA via its ZF2 domain, negatively regulating its translation in posterior blastomeres. </s><s n="s10.10;p29.32">In anterior blastomeres, SPN-4 interacts with POS-1 and also binds the TCR of <hi rend="italic">glp-1</hi> mRNA via its RNP-type RNA binding domain to promote translation. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">12-cell stage</head><p n="p30.32"><s n="s1.3;p30.32">The GLP-1 receptor is also required in ABa descendents at the 12-cell stage to mediate signals from the MS blastomere that are required for pharyngeal development. </s><s n="s2.3;p30.32">Transcription of these unknown ligands is initiated by SKN-1. </s><s n="s3.3;p30.32">Asymmetric induction of the two ABa descendents forms the left-right axis. </s></p><p n="p31.32"><s n="s1.3;p31.32">The different responses to inductive signals that use a common receptor are dependent on the age of the AB descendent when the signal is received (Shelton &amp; Bowerman, 1996). </s><s n="s2.3;p31.32">In both cases, however, the pharyngeal precursor cells only are instructed to activate the <hi rend="italic">pha-4</hi> gene, encoding a transcription factor that activates almost all of the pharynx-specific genes (Mango <hi rend="italic">et al</hi>. </s><s n="s3.3;p31.32">1994, Gaudet &amp; Mango, 2002). </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Summary</head><p n="p32.32"><s n="s1.3;p32.32">Embryogenesis relies almost exclusively on maternal proteins and RNAs loaded into the oocyte during oogenesis. </s><s n="s2.3;p32.32">Patterning arises through a combination of oriented, intrinsically asymmetric cell divisions and cell-cell interactions. </s><s n="s3.3;p32.32">The PAR proteins and MEX-5/6 are responsible for initial polarisation of the zygote,<hi rend="italic"> skn-1</hi> is required to specify the EMS fate, the bifunctional protein PIE-1 is required to maintain the totipotent germ cell lineage and specification of the AB lineage involves a system homologous to Notch in <hi rend="italic">Drosophila</hi>. </s></p></div1></body><back><div1 type="bibliography"><head rend="bold">References</head><p>Batchelder C, Dunn MA, Choy B, Suh Y, Cassie C, Shim EY, Shin TH, Mello C, Seydoux G &amp; Blackwell TK (1999) Transcriptional repression by the <hi rend="italic">Caenorhabditis elegans</hi> germ-line protein PIE-1. <hi rend="italic">Genes Dev. </hi><hi rend="bold">13</hi>:202-12</p><p>Brenner, S (1974) The genetics of <hi rend="italic">Caenorhabditis elegans</hi>. <hi rend="italic">Genetics</hi>. <hi rend="bold">77</hi>:71-94</p><p>Blackwell TK, Bowerman B, Priess JR &amp; Weintraub H (1994) Formation of a monomeric DNA binding domain by Skn-1 bZIP and homeodomain elements. <hi rend="italic">Science. </hi><hi rend="bold">266(5185)</hi>:621-8</p><p>Bowerman B, Draper BW, Mello CC, Priess JR (1993) The maternal gene skn-1 encodes a protein that is distributed unequally in early C. elegans embryos. <hi rend="italic">Cell</hi>. <hi rend="bold">74(3)</hi>:443-52</p><p>Bowerman B, Eaton BA &amp; Priess JR (1992) skn-1, a maternally expressed gene required to specify the fate of ventral blastomeres in the early C.elegans embryo. <hi rend="italic">Cell</hi>. <hi rend="bold">68(6)</hi>:1061-75</p><p><hi rend="italic">C.elegans</hi> Sequencing Consortium (1999) Genome sequence of the nematode <hi rend="italic">C.elegans</hi>: A platform for investigating biology. <hi rend="italic">Science</hi>. <hi rend="bold">282</hi>:2012-8</p><p>Cuenca A, Schetter A, Aceto D, Kemphues K, Seydoux G (2003) Polarization of the <hi rend="italic">C.elegans</hi> zygote proceeds via distinct establishment and maintenance phases. <hi rend="italic">Development. </hi><hi rend="bold">130</hi>:1255-65</p><p>Evans TC, Crittenden SL, Kodoyanni V &amp; Kimble JK (1994) Translational control of maternal <hi rend="italic">glp-1</hi> mRNA establishes an asymmetry in the C. elegans embryo.<hi rend="italic"> Cell</hi>. <hi rend="bold">77</hi>:183-94</p><p>Gaudet J &amp; Mango SE (2002) Regulation of organogenesis by the <hi rend="italic">Caenorhabditis elegans</hi> FoxA protein PHA-4. <hi rend="italic">Science</hi>. <hi rend="bold">295</hi>:821-5</p><p>Gilbert SF (2003) Developmental Biology 7<hi rend="sup">th</hi> edn. <hi rend="italic">Sinauer Associates Inc.</hi></p><p>Golden A (2000) Cytoplasmic flow and the establishment of polarity in <hi rend="italic">C.elegans</hi> 1-cell embryos. <hi rend="italic">Curr. Opin. Gen. Dev. </hi><hi rend="bold">10</hi>:410-20</p><p>Goldstein B &amp; Hird HN (1996) Specification of the anteroposterior axis in <hi rend="italic">Caenorhabditis elegans</hi>. <hi rend="italic">Development</hi>. <hi rend="bold">122</hi>:1467-74</p><p>Gotta M &amp; Ahringer J (2001) Axis determination in <hi rend="italic">C.elegans</hi>: initiating and transducing polarity.<hi rend="italic"> Curr. Opin. Gen. &amp; Dev. </hi><hi rend="bold">11</hi>:367-73</p><p>Guo S &amp; Kemphues KL (1996) A non-muscle myosin required for embryonic polarity in <hi rend="italic">Caenorhabditis elegans</hi>. <hi rend="italic">Nature</hi>. <hi rend="bold">382</hi>:455-8</p><p>Han M (1998) Gut reaction to Wnt signalling in worms. <hi rend="italic">Cell</hi>. <hi rend="bold">90</hi>:581-4</p><p>Hird S, Paulsen J &amp; STrome S (1996) Segregation of germ granules in living <hi rend="italic">Caenorhabditis elegans</hi> embryos: cell-type-specific mechanisms for cytoplasmic localisation. <hi rend="italic">Development </hi><hi rend="bold">122</hi>:1303-12</p><p>Hunter CP &amp; Kenyon C (1996) Spatial and temporal controls target <hi rend="italic">pal-1</hi> blastomere-specification activity to a single blastomere in <hi rend="italic">C.elegans</hi> embryos. <hi rend="italic">Cell</hi>. <hi rend="bold">87</hi>:217-26</p><p>Kemphues KJ &amp; Strome S (1997) Fertilization and establishment of polarity in the embryo. In <hi rend="italic">C.elegans II</hi>. Edited by Riddle DL, Blumenthal T, Meyer BJ, Priess JR, Cold Spring Harbor; Laboratory Press; 335-59</p><p>Lai CH, Chou CY, Ch'ang LY, Lui CS, Lin W (2000) Identification of novel human genes evolutionarily conserved in Caenorhabditis elegans by comparative proteomics.<hi rend="italic"> Genome Res. </hi><hi rend="bold">10(5)</hi>:703-13</p><p>Lyczak R, Gomes J-E &amp; Bowerman B (2002) Heads or Tails: Cell Polarity and Axis Formation in the Early <hi rend="italic">Caenorhabditis elegans</hi> Embryo. <hi rend="italic">Developmental Cell</hi>. <hi rend="bold">3</hi>:157-66</p><p>Mickey KM, Mello CC, Montgomery MK, Fire A &amp; Priess J (1996) An inductive interaction in 4-cell stage <hi rend="italic">C.elegans</hi> embryos involves APX-1 expression in the signalling cell. <hi rend="italic">Development. </hi><hi rend="bold">122</hi>:1791-8</p><p>O'Connell KF, Maxwell KN &amp; White JG (2000) The <hi rend="italic">spd-2</hi> gene is required for polarization of the anteroposterior axis and formation of the sperm asters in the <hi rend="italic">Caenorhabditis elegans</hi> zygote. <hi rend="italic">Dev. Bio. </hi><hi rend="bold">222</hi>:55-70</p><p>Maduro MF, Meneghini MD, Bowerman B, Broitman-Maduro G &amp; Rothman JH (2001) Restriction of mesendoderm to a single blastomere by the combined action of SKN-1 and a GSK-3β homolog is mediated by MED-1 and -2 in <hi rend="italic">C.elegans. Mol. Cell</hi>. <hi rend="bold">7</hi>:475-85</p><p>Mango SE, Lambie EJ &amp; Kimble J (1994) The <hi rend="italic">pha-4</hi> gene is required to generate the pharyngeal primordium of <hi rend="italic">Caenorhabditis elegans</hi>. <hi rend="italic">Development. </hi><hi rend="bold">120</hi>:3019-31</p><p>Mello CC, Draper BW, Krause M, Weintraub H &amp; Priess JR (1992) The pie-1 and mex-1 genes and maternal control of blastomere identity in early C. elegans embryos. <hi rend="italic">Cell</hi>.<hi rend="bold"> 70(1)</hi>:163-76</p><p>Mello CC, Schubert C, Draper B, Zhang W, Lobel R &amp; Priess JR (1996) The PIE-1 protein and germline specification in <hi rend="italic">C. elegans</hi> embryos. <hi rend="italic">Nature</hi>. <hi rend="bold">382</hi>:710-2</p><p>Morton DG, Shakes DC, Nugent S, Dichoso D, Wang W, Golden A and Kemphues KJ (2002) The <hi rend="italic">Caenorhabditis elegans</hi> par-5 gene encodes a 14-3-3 protein required for cellular asymmetry in the early embryo. <hi rend="italic">Dev. Biol. </hi><hi rend="bold">241</hi>:47-58</p><p>Ogura K-I, Kishimoto N, Mitani S, Gengyo-Ando K &amp; Kohara Y (2003) Translational control of maternal <hi rend="italic">glp-1</hi> mRNA by POS-1 and its interacting protein SPN-4 in <hi rend="italic">Caenorhabditis elegans</hi>. <hi rend="italic">Development</hi>. <hi rend="bold">130</hi>:2495-503</p><p>Priess JR &amp; Thomson JN (1987) Cellular interactions in early <hi rend="italic">C.elegans</hi> embryos. <hi rend="italic">Cell</hi>. <hi rend="bold">48</hi>:241-50</p><p>Sarai A, Ahmad S, Abdulla B, Kumar S, Kitajima K &amp; Uedaira H (2005) Kyushu institute of technology. BioInfo Bank website. <seg type="URL" n="http://gibk26.bse.kyutech.ac.jp/jouhou/image/dna-protein/all/small_N1skn.gif"/></p><p>Seydoux G &amp; Dunn MA (1997) Transcriptionally repressed germ cells lack a subpopulation of phosphorylated RNA polymerase II in early embryos of <hi rend="italic">Caenorhabditis elegans</hi> and Drosophila melanogaster. <hi rend="italic">Development</hi>. <hi rend="bold">124</hi>:2191-201.</p><p>Seydoux G &amp; Strome S (1999) Launching the germline in <hi rend="italic">Caenorhabditis elegans</hi>: regulation of gene expression in early germ cells. <hi rend="italic">Development</hi>. <hi rend="bold">126</hi>,3275-83</p><p>Shelton CA &amp; Bowerman B (1996) Time-dependent responses to <hi rend="italic">glp-1</hi> mediated inductions in early <hi rend="italic">C. elegans</hi> embryos.</p><p>Spike CA &amp; Strome S (2003) Germ plasm: Protein Degredation in the Soma. <hi rend="italic">Current Biology</hi>. <hi rend="bold">13</hi>:R837-9</p><p>Strome S, Specification of the germ line (2005), <hi rend="italic">WormBook</hi>, ed. The <hi rend="italic">C. elegans</hi> Research Community,WormBook, doi/10.1895/wormbook.1.9.1, <seg type="URL" n="http://www.wormbook.org"/>.</p><p>Sulston JE &amp; Horvitz HR (1977) Postembryonic lineages of the nematode <hi rend="italic">Caenorhabditis elegans</hi>. <hi rend="italic">Dev. Biol. </hi><hi rend="bold">100</hi>:110-56</p><p>Sulston JE, Schierenberg J, White J &amp; Thomson N (1983) The embryonic cell lineage of the nematode <hi rend="italic">Caenorhabditis elegans</hi>. <hi rend="italic">Dev. Biol. </hi><hi rend="bold">100</hi>:64-119</p><p>Tabara H, Hill JR, Mello CC, Priess JR &amp; Kohara Y (1999) <hi rend="italic">pos-1</hi> encodesa cytoplasmic zinc-finger protein essential for germline specification in <hi rend="italic">C.elegans</hi>. <hi rend="italic">Development</hi>. <hi rend="bold">126</hi>:1-11</p><p>Tenenhaus C, Subramanium K, Dunn MA &amp; Seydoux G (2001) PIE-1 is a bifunctional protein that regulates maternal and zygotic gene expression in the embryonic germ line of <hi rend="italic">Caenorhabditis elegans</hi>. <hi rend="italic">Genes. Dev. </hi><hi rend="bold">15</hi>:1031-40</p><p>Wallenfang MR &amp; Seydoux G (2000) Polarization of the anterior-posterior axis of <hi rend="italic">C.elegans</hi> is a microtubule-directed process. <hi rend="italic">Nature</hi>. <hi rend="bold">408</hi>:89-92</p><p>Woodland HJ (2002) Methods of disrupting gene action to determine the function of genes. <hi rend="italic">Lecture handout</hi>.</p><p>Zhang F, Barboric M, Blackwell TK &amp; Peterlin BM (2003) A model of repression: CTD analogs and PIE-1 inhibit transcriptional elongation by P-TEFb. <hi rend="italic">Genes Dev. </hi><hi rend="bold">17</hi>:748-58</p></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
