<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_0069d" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>The development of international criminal law in the latter half of the twentieth century demonstrates that governments can no longer behave with impunity. - Discuss -</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note/></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">2</p><p n="date">2004-12</p><p n="module title">International Law</p><p n="module code">LA205</p><p n="genre family">Essay</p><p n="discipline">Law</p><p n="disciplinary group">SS</p><p n="grade">M</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">3224</p><p n="number of s-units">88</p><p n="number of p">21</p><p n="number of tables">0</p><p n="number of figures">0</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">0</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">0</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">36.6</p><p n="average s-units per p">4.2</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">m</p><p n="year of birth">1984</p><p n="first language">English</p><p n="education">UKA</p><p n="course">Law</p><p n="student ID">0069</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><titlePart>University of <name type="university"/> School of Law International Law <hi rend="underlined bold"> Assessed Essay 2004</hi></titlePart><docTitle><titlePart><hi rend="bold italic">"The development of international criminal law in the latter half of the twentieth century demonstrates that governments can no longer behave with impunity".</hi> <hi rend="bold"> - Discuss - </hi></titlePart></docTitle></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">1. Introduction </head><p n="p1.21"><s n="s1.3;p1.21">The latter half of last century saw some of the most significant developments in international criminal law. </s><s n="s2.3;p1.21">With the establishment of two <hi rend="italic">ad hoc</hi> international criminal tribunals in former Yugoslavia (ICTY) and Rwanda (ICTR), the so-called 'internationalized-courts' in East Timor, Sierra Leone and Kosovo and the permanent International Criminal Court (ICC), momentous steps have been taken to implement mechanisms, operating at an international level, to punish those responsible for the commission of the gravest breaches of international humanitarian and human rights law. </s><s n="s3.3;p1.21">As a result, we have witnessed the emergence of what has been heralded as a <hi rend="italic">"new culture of accountability"</hi><ref target="BAWE_0069d-ftnote.001"/>, replacing the previous <hi rend="italic">"culture of impunity"</hi><ref target="BAWE_0069d-ftnote.002"/> that had remained mostly unfettered throughout history. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0069d-ftnote.001"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1"><hi rend="italic">"From Sovereign Impunity to International Accountability: the Search for Justice in a World of States",</hi> edited by Ramesh Thakur and Peter Malcontent, 2004, UNU Press. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0069d-ftnote.002"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid. </s></p></note><p n="p2.21"><s n="s1.3;p2.21">However, as I shall discuss, these developments are not without their limitations. </s><s n="s2.3;p2.21">The aforementioned <hi rend="italic">"culture of impunity"</hi> had persisted throughout history for good reason; primarily, due to the unwillingness of states to sacrifice their treasured sovereignty over the <hi rend="italic">"hallowed area of criminal law"</hi><ref target="BAWE_0069d-ftnote.003"/> for fear of being subjected to international scrutiny. </s><s n="s3.3;p2.21">Such philosophy has by no means been ousted among all nations, and as we shall see, it still serves as a critical restriction on the efficacy of international criminal law, as its enforcement is so evidently dependant on the co-operation of states, on their political will and their readiness to limit their sovereignty and submit to international jurisdiction. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0069d-ftnote.003"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1"><hi rend="italic">"Lest We Fail: the Importance of Enforcement in International Criminal Law",</hi> Mary Margaret Penrose, A.U.I.L.R, 2000, 321-394, at 352 </s></p></note><p n="p3.21"><s n="s1.3;p3.21">In the following paragraphs, I will endeavour to analyse and assess these developments in international criminal law, and discuss whether they demonstrate that governments who commit the gravest breaches of international humanitarian and human rights law can no longer behave with impunity. </s><s n="s2.3;p3.21">I will focus on the operation and limitations of the two <hi rend="italic">ad hoc</hi> international criminal tribunals, and will consider the potential impact of the ICC on bringing individuals to justice. </s><s n="s3.3;p3.21">Firstly, however, it is important to establish an understanding into the history of international criminal law development, and the evolution of state's political and moral ideology, which forms the foundation of this so-called 'new era of accountability'. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">2. Historical development of international criminal law &amp; the emergence of individual accountability</head><p n="p4.21"><s n="s1.3;p4.21">International jurisdiction over the commission of international crimes by government leaders was almost non-existent prior to the twentieth century<ref target="BAWE_0069d-ftnote.004"/>. </s><s n="s2.3;p4.21">The doctrine of state sovereignty was held as sacrosanct, shielding individuals from accountability - <hi rend="italic">"virtually all governments regarded how they treated those under their control and policies they pursued as a matter exclusively within their own jurisdiction...and not subject to any outside international standards, scrutiny, criticism or interference"</hi><ref target="BAWE_0069d-ftnote.005"/>. </s><s n="s3.3;p4.21">National courts provided the only arena for punishing those responsible for the few crimes defined as 'international'<ref target="BAWE_0069d-ftnote.006"/>, but their judgements "<hi rend="italic">were and remain ineffective when those responsible for the crimes are still in power and their victims remain subjugated"</hi><ref target="BAWE_0069d-ftnote.007"/>. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0069d-ftnote.004"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">One of the very few notable exceptions to this was the trial and conviction of Peter von Hagenbach for violations of "the laws of God and man" by the Austrian, German and Swiss <hi rend="italic">ad hoc</hi> criminal tribunal in 1474. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0069d-ftnote.005"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1"><hi rend="italic">"From Impunity to Accountability: Forces of Transformation &amp; the Changing International Human Rights Context",</hi> Paul G. Lauren,op cit. <hi rend="italic">supra</hi> note 2 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0069d-ftnote.006"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">as Cassese notes: <hi rend="italic">"Initially...for a long time, only war crimes were punishable",</hi> Antonio Cassese, "<hi rend="italic">International Criminal Law</hi>", 2003, OUP, p. 16 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0069d-ftnote.007"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1"><hi rend="italic">"An Introduction to the International Criminal Court",</hi> William A. Schabas, 2nd ed., 2004, Cambridge University Press, p. 1. </s></p></note><p n="p5.21"><s n="s1.4;p5.21">By the twentieth century however, religious, philosophical and political thinking had evolved significantly, resulting in a much greater awareness of the concept of human rights and humanitarian law, and an increasing emphasis on the need to <hi rend="italic">"protect individuals from the horrors of war"</hi><ref target="BAWE_0069d-ftnote.008"/>. </s><s n="s2.4;p5.21">The unprecedented scale of the atrocities committed during World Wars I and II "shocked the conscience" of the international community leading to Allied victors pledge that "never again" would anything similar occur. </s><s n="s3.4;p5.21">While attempts were made in the aftermath of WWI to punish the leading figures responsible for the commission of war crimes<ref target="BAWE_0069d-ftnote.009"/>, these proved to be of little value in creating a substantial system of international criminal justice<ref target="BAWE_0069d-ftnote.010"/>. </s><s n="s4.4;p5.21">However, the subsequent atrocities committed during WWII demanded a more decisive reaction of the international community, resulting in the establishment of two International Military Tribunals, at Nuremburg and Tokyo. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0069d-ftnote.008"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Gustav Moynier, <hi rend="italic">"Note sur la création d'une institution judicaire internationale",</hi> Bulletin International, vol. 11, 1872. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0069d-ftnote.009"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">The Versailles Treaty, for example, had envisaged the creation of an international 'special tribunal' to try the German Emperor Kaiser Wilhelm II. However, the Netherlands' refused his extradition, no international court was set up and trials were conducted under heavily biased German jurisdiction in Leipzig. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">In the end, out of the 895 accused by the Allies, only 12 minor indictees were brought to trial </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0069d-ftnote.010"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Cassese notes: <hi rend="italic">"the attempts to establish some sort of international criminal justice ended in failure", supra</hi> note 7, p. 328 </s></p></note><p n="p6.21"><s n="s1.7;p6.21">The tribunals provided revolutionary developments in international criminal law. </s><s n="s2.7;p6.21">They established the principle and practice that individuals at the highest levels of government and military infrastructure could be prosecuted and punished<ref target="BAWE_0069d-ftnote.011"/> under international law, recognising accountability for the commission of war crimes and introduced new offences of crimes against peace and crimes against humanity. </s><s n="s3.7;p6.21">The 'monopoly' over criminal jurisdiction held by States and the 'act of state immunity' that had so often protected leaders from liability in the past were removed<ref target="BAWE_0069d-ftnote.012"/>, demonstrating that individuals could no longer hide behind the legal cover of the state. </s><s n="s4.7;p6.21">However, major criticisms were levelled against the IMTs suggesting only a 'victor's justice' had been served, and to a large extent these are inescapable. </s><s n="s5.7;p6.21">Only the vanquished were put on trial, regardless of the atrocities committed by the Allies<ref target="BAWE_0069d-ftnote.013"/> and the victors undertook the duties of both prosecutor and judge, without leaving recourse to appeal. </s><s n="s6.7;p6.21">It was obvious that this mechanism of trial and punishment, immunising some whilst sentencing others, could not serve as a legitimate system of international criminal justice in the long run. </s><s n="s7.7;p6.21">It would be unable to acquire the respect and therefore the co-operation of the international community, and would only be able to come into existence "<hi rend="italic">in the aftermath of an international conflict that had been entered into, fought and won by those wishing to implement international criminal law"</hi>. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0069d-ftnote.011"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Twenty-four individual defendants were indicted, of which 12 were sentenced to death by hanging, 3 to life imprisonment, 2 to twenty-years and 1 to 10 years imprisonment, while only 3 were released having received a verdict of 'not guilty'. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0069d-ftnote.012"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">see Articles 7 and 8 IMT Statute </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0069d-ftnote.013"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">"<hi rend="italic">Criminal Trials Before International Tribunals: Legality And Legitimacy",,</hi> Dominic McGoldrick, found in "<hi rend="italic">The Permanent International Criminal Court, Legal and Policy Issues" e</hi>dited by McGoldrick, Rowe and Donnelly, 2004, Hart Publishing, p. 21 </s></p></note><p n="p7.21"><s n="s1.3;p7.21">Nevertheless, the tribunals importantly served as a <hi rend="italic">"springboard for the development of international humanitarian and... human rights law"</hi><ref target="BAWE_0069d-ftnote.014"/> - those laws which, if breached, could now give rise to individual criminal liability. </s><s n="s2.3;p7.21">Demonstrated by the considerable efforts of the newly created United Nations, over the next few years, <hi rend="italic">"an international momentum began to build"</hi><ref target="BAWE_0069d-ftnote.015"/> towards creating a comprehensive international penal code that would promote accountability and deter violations of international law. </s><s n="s3.3;p7.21">With the rapid adoption of several momentous international agreements, in particular the Universal Declaration of Human Rights and the Genocide Convention in 1948, and the 1949 Geneva Conventions, combined with the work undertaken by the specially appointed ILC<ref target="BAWE_0069d-ftnote.016"/> to prepare a draft code of international crimes, it became evident that the international community now possessed, at least in theory, the will and capacity to hold governments accountable for the commission of international crimes. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0069d-ftnote.014"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1"><hi rend="italic">"Accountability for Human Rights Atrocities in International Law',</hi> Ratner &amp; Abrams, 2nd ed., 2001, OUP, p.7 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0069d-ftnote.015"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">see <hi rend="italic">supra</hi> note 5, p. 27 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0069d-ftnote.016"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Pursuant to a request of the UN General Assembly on 21 Nov 1947, (res. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">177/II), <hi rend="italic">"Formulation of the Principles Recognised at in the Charter of the Nuremburg Tribunal".</hi> </s></p></note><p n="p8.21"><s n="s1.4;p8.21">However, the ensuing Cold War era led the international community into a standstill. </s><s n="s2.4;p8.21">It produced a climate of political stagnation which froze foreign interference in domestic affairs and impeded the functioning of the UN<ref target="BAWE_0069d-ftnote.017"/>. </s><s n="s3.4;p8.21">Any further development of international criminal law was put on hold<ref target="BAWE_0069d-ftnote.018"/>, demonstrating a critical limitation of international criminal law - its dependence on prevailing international politics. </s><s n="s4.4;p8.21">It was not until some 40 years later, after the fall of the Iron Curtain and the collapse of the Soviet Union, that the international community regained its drive towards ending impunity, the success and limitations of which I shall now discuss </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0069d-ftnote.017"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">its members having become "<hi rend="italic">subsumed into two rival and antagonistic political blocs", "International Criminal Law",</hi> Antonio Cassese, 2003, OUP, p. 334. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0069d-ftnote.018"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">The promising work of the ILC in establishing both a codification of international crimes and a draft statute for the creation of an international criminal court, failed to come to fruition, and <hi rend="italic">"the tensions and mistrust of the Cold War stymied any possibility of creating any international mechanisms to bring [human rights] abusers to justice",</hi>op cit. <hi rend="italic">supra</hi> note 14, p. 8 </s></p></note></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">3. The International Criminal Tribunals for the former Yugoslavia (ICTY) and Rwanda (ICTR)</head><p n="p9.21"><s n="s1.5;p9.21">The end of the Cold War led to a dramatic change in geo-political power structures and attitudes. </s><s n="s2.5;p9.21">Agreement in the UN Security Council was rekindled, as was the international community's desire to establish "permanent and effective bodies to dispense international justice"<ref target="BAWE_0069d-ftnote.019"/>. </s><s n="s3.5;p9.21">The end of the Cold War also led to the removal of the forces that had been able to guarantee "a modicum of international order"<ref target="BAWE_0069d-ftnote.020"/>. </s><s n="s4.5;p9.21">This allowed religious and ethnic conflicts that had been smouldering beneath the surface to erupt into instability and conflict, leading to "gross violations of international humanitarian law, on a scale comparable to those committed during World War II"<ref target="BAWE_0069d-ftnote.021"/>. </s><s n="s5.5;p9.21">The Balkans and Rwanda saw tremendous blood-shed, involving genocide, 'ethnic cleansing' and other crimes against humanity, and it was in response to these shocking atrocities that the international community's reaction materialised with the creation of two ad hoc criminal tribunals under the auspices of the UN Security Council (SC)<ref target="BAWE_0069d-ftnote.022"/>. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0069d-ftnote.019"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Final Report of the Commission of Experts, UN Doc S/1994/674 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0069d-ftnote.020"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1"><hi rend="italic">"On the Current Trends Towards Criminal Prosecution and Punishment of Breaches of International Humanitarian Law",</hi> Antonio Cassese, European Journal of International Law, 2, 11 (1998), p.4 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0069d-ftnote.021"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid., p.4 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0069d-ftnote.022"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Under UN SC Resolutions 827 and 955 respectively </s></p></note><p n="p10.21"><s n="s1.4;p10.21">Mandated to punish individuals responsible for grave violations of international law, the ICTY and ICTR have achieved some considerable successes to that end and have contributed substantially to the development of international criminal law. </s><s n="s2.4;p10.21">The establishment of the tribunals in itself, first and foremost demonstrates the intention and capability of the international community at large to punish war criminals, and in this sense sends an important message to government leaders worldwide that there is now the potential for their being brought to justice<ref target="BAWE_0069d-ftnote.023"/>. </s><s n="s3.4;p10.21">Since coming into force, 108 accused have appeared in proceedings before the ICTY, including most importantly and for the first time, an incumbent Head-of-State<ref target="BAWE_0069d-ftnote.024"/>. </s><s n="s4.4;p10.21">The ICTR has also secured the arrest, trial and conviction of a number of high ranking officials and ministers, including a former Prime Minister<ref target="BAWE_0069d-ftnote.025"/>, Vice-President of militia<ref target="BAWE_0069d-ftnote.026"/> and Director of the Ministry of Defence<ref target="BAWE_0069d-ftnote.027"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0069d-ftnote.023"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">As Theodore Meron notes: <hi rend="italic">"No matter how many atrocities these tribunals may eventually try, their very existence sends a powerful message.</hi> </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1"><hi rend="italic">Their statutes, rules of procedure and evidence, and practice stimulate the development of the law",</hi> "The International Criminalisation of Internal Atrocities", American Journal International Law, Vol. 89, 1995, p.555 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0069d-ftnote.024"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Slobodan Miloševic </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0069d-ftnote.025"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Jean Kambanda </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0069d-ftnote.026"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Georges Rutaganda </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0069d-ftnote.027"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Théoneste Bagosora </s></p></note><p n="p11.21"><s n="s1.3;p11.21">Unlike their predecessors in Nuremburg and Tokyo, their creation by the SC means the tribunals' statutes are binding upon all UN member states and call upon all states to "<hi rend="italic">cooperate fully"</hi> with it and <hi rend="italic"> "to take any measures necessary under their domestic law to implement the provisions"</hi><ref target="BAWE_0069d-ftnote.028"/> of its statute. </s><s n="s2.3;p11.21">This origin, coming as it did from the full international community, immunises the tribunals from challenges of 'victor's justice' which had to be endured at Nuremburg and Tokyo. </s><s n="s3.3;p11.21">It was no longer the victors emerging from the aftermath of warfare that were indicting, prosecuting and judging war criminals but a body of UN-appointed and elected individuals, representative of a wide range of nations. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0069d-ftnote.028"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.3;pn1.1">S.C. Res. </s><s n="s2.3;pn1.1">827, U.N. SCOR, 48th session, U.N. Doc. </s><s n="s3.3;pn1.1">S/RES/827 (1993). </s></p></note><p n="p12.21"><s n="s1.5;p12.21">The tribunals also exert primacy over national courts<ref target="BAWE_0069d-ftnote.029"/>, meaning if it appears that the national court proceedings <hi rend="italic">"are not impartial or are designed to shield the accused from international criminal responsibility"</hi><ref target="BAWE_0069d-ftnote.030"/>, then they must be deferred to the tribunal. </s><s n="s2.5;p12.21">This tackles the aforementioned shortcomings of national enforcement of international criminal law, which had been demonstrated so blatantly at Leipzig<ref target="BAWE_0069d-ftnote.031"/>. </s><s n="s3.5;p12.21">The tribunals also have at last given effect to the numerous aforementioned conventions reached mid-century, through its judgements concerning war crimes, genocide<ref target="BAWE_0069d-ftnote.032"/> and other crimes against humanity<ref target="BAWE_0069d-ftnote.033"/>. </s><s n="s4.5;p12.21">Both tribunals have gone further in developing substantive law, incorporating sexual crimes such as rape into the context of crimes against humanity<ref target="BAWE_0069d-ftnote.034"/> and recognising new crimes such as the <hi rend="italic">employment of poisonous weapons or others calculated to cause unnecessary suffering</hi><ref target="BAWE_0069d-ftnote.035"/>. </s><s n="s5.5;p12.21">Opening a new area for tribunals of this nature, Article 4 of the ICTR statute enables the prosecution of persons who commit or order to be committed serious violations of Article 3 common to the Geneva Conventions and of Additional Protocol II during to armed conflict <hi rend="italic">not</hi> of an international character, meaning, therefore, that purely internal conflicts are no longer beyond the ambit of international criminal law. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0069d-ftnote.029"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">ICTY Statute, Article 9 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0069d-ftnote.030"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1"><hi rend="italic">"Judging War Criminals: The Politics of International Jutsice",</hi> Yves Beigbeder, 2003, Palgrave, p. 155 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0069d-ftnote.031"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">see <hi rend="italic">supra</hi> note <hi rend="italic">9.</hi> </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0069d-ftnote.032"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">The ICTR delivered the first convictions of an international tribunal for genocide in the case of <hi rend="italic">Akayesu</hi> (1998) </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0069d-ftnote.033"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">ICTY Statute, Articles 2-5. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0069d-ftnote.034"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.3;pn1.1">Ibid. Article 6. see also <hi rend="italic">Furundzija Judgement,</hi> paras. </s><s n="s2.3;pn1.1">174-186 (definition for purposes of war crime); <hi rend="italic">Celebici Judgement</hi>, paras. </s><s n="s3.3;pn1.1">475-497 (rape as act of torture). </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0069d-ftnote.035"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid. Article 3(a) </s></p></note><p n="p13.21"><s n="s1.4;p13.21">However, whilst all of this demonstrates that significant strides have indeed been taken by the world community towards ending impunity, we must of course appreciate the substantial limitations of these tribunals. </s><s n="s2.4;p13.21">Both are only <hi rend="italic">ad hoc,</hi> limited to specific individual conflicts with highly restricted <hi rend="italic">ratione personae</hi><ref target="BAWE_0069d-ftnote.036"/> and <hi rend="italic">ratione temporis</hi><ref target="BAWE_0069d-ftnote.037"/> competences, and therefore cannot possibly bring all those perpetrators of international crimes to justice. </s><s n="s3.4;p13.21">Resources (and the lack thereof) are also key to the tribunals' efficacy, and they have been a recurrent problem for both, <hi rend="italic">"limiting their ability to obtain needed equipment, conduct investigations and protect witnesses and even threatening the tribunal's very survival on occasion"</hi><ref target="BAWE_0069d-ftnote.038"/>. </s><s n="s4.4;p13.21">However, the most fundamental weakness of the tribunals relates to enforcement. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0069d-ftnote.036"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Only <hi rend="italic">natural persons</hi> may be prosecuted, not organisations, political parties, administrative entities or other legal subjects - Article 6 ICTY </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0069d-ftnote.037"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Tribunals were limited to prosecuting "<hi rend="italic">persons responsible for serious violations of international humanitarian law committed in the territory of the former Yugoslavia since 1991"</hi> (Article 1 ICTY), and those responsible for "<hi rend="italic">serious violations of international humanitarian law committed in the territory of Rwanda and Rwandan citizens responsible for such violations committed in the territory of neighbouring States between 1 January 1994 and 31 December 1994"</hi> (Article 1 ICTR) </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0069d-ftnote.038"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1"><hi rend="italic">supra note</hi> 14, p. 223. </s></p></note><p n="p14.21"><s n="s1.8;p14.21">Unlike national courts, the international criminal tribunals have no law enforcement agency akin to a police judicature<ref target="BAWE_0069d-ftnote.039"/>.They therefore rely primarily on the co-operation of national authorities to arrest and bring forward the accused, as a necessary means to begin the trial which is not permitted to take place <hi rend="italic">in absentia.</hi> </s><s n="s2.8;p14.21">There is thus the existence of a 'Catch-22' situation: for a case to commence, the co-operation of those very states in whose name the war criminals were more-often-than-not acting is required to bring indictees forward. </s><s n="s3.8;p14.21">Obviously, in a situation such as former Yugoslavia where the <hi rend="italic">"offenders retain some degree of power"</hi><ref target="BAWE_0069d-ftnote.040"/>, it is clearly not in the state's interest to submit these individuals to the tribunals for what could culminate in a damning legal report; instead, states have "protected their war criminals...and ignored the Tribunal's warrants"<ref target="BAWE_0069d-ftnote.041"/>. </s><s n="s4.8;p14.21">Whilst both tribunals' statutes<ref target="BAWE_0069d-ftnote.042"/> require full co-operation of nation-states in the enforcement of arrests and sentences, "these obligations have only been respected in a few cases...revealing all too clearly that the tribunal had no real political support from the main parties concerned"<ref target="BAWE_0069d-ftnote.043"/>. </s><s n="s5.8;p14.21">The ICTY in particular has encountered massive problems in arresting and acquiring evidence against accused individuals. </s><s n="s6.8;p14.21">Despite having been indicted nearly a decade ago, and having even appeared in public on occasions, Bosnian Serb leaders Radovan Karadžić and Ratko Mladić continue to escape arrest. </s><s n="s7.8;p14.21">Even after four years of the tribunal's creation, Republika Srpska had failed to execute any of the scores of arrest warrants addressed to it, while the Federal Republic of Yugoslavia had not even enacted legislation to enable it to cooperate with the tribunal<ref target="BAWE_0069d-ftnote.044"/>. </s><s n="s8.8;p14.21">Evidence collection has been notoriously difficult and investigators have even identified instances where state officials have led efforts to conceal<ref target="BAWE_0069d-ftnote.045"/> and destroy evidence.<ref target="BAWE_0069d-ftnote.046"/> Furthermore, Croatia's persistent refusal to supply inculpatory evidence to the ICTY in the Blaskic case<ref target="BAWE_0069d-ftnote.047"/> was not met with any effective means of coercion<ref target="BAWE_0069d-ftnote.048"/>, and illustrated both the ineffectiveness of the tribunal's attempts to enforce compliance, and the propensity of states to simply and all-too-easily refuse compliance when its nationals are deeply implicated in the conflict in question. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0069d-ftnote.039"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">As Cassese notes: <hi rend="italic">"They do not have the power to issue warrants for the seizure of evidence or the searching of premises, and to issue subpoenas or arrest warrants",</hi> "International Law", 2nd ed., 2005, OUP, p. 461. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0069d-ftnote.040"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1"><hi rend="italic">supra</hi> note 14, p. 222 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0069d-ftnote.041"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1"><hi rend="italic">supra</hi> note 29, p. 161 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0069d-ftnote.042"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Article 29 ICTY and Article 28 ICTR </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0069d-ftnote.043"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1"><hi rend="italic">supra</hi> note 29, p.160 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0069d-ftnote.044"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid. p.161 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0069d-ftnote.045"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">For example, archives containing requested evidence, relating to cases in Central Bosnia involving members of the Bosnian Croat political and military structures, were secreted out of Bosnia and Herzegovina by state authorities and concealed in Zagreb, Croatia </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0069d-ftnote.046"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">One such example was the Srebrenica investigation, in which forensic specialists, conducting exhumations at mass grave sites, discovered human remains from these sites had been removed and re-buried elsewhere, having been systematically conducted by the Army of the Republika Srpska. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0069d-ftnote.047"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">following the massacre of Muslim civilians by Bosnian Croat military forces under Tihomir Blaskic in the village of Ahmići. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0069d-ftnote.048"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">In the end, the Appeals Chamber held that when a state failed to comply with a binding order issued by the tribunal, the tribunal's President could transmit a report of non-compliance to the UN SC for rectification. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">However, the general way in which the SC has reacted in the past, to issue a new resolution or a presidential statement calling on the recalcitrant state to cooperate, has been largely ineffective, as noted by Beigbeder: <hi rend="italic">"The Council has failed to ensure such compliance",</hi>op cit. <hi rend="italic">supra</hi> note 29, p.160 </s></p></note><p n="p15.21"><s n="s1.2;p15.21">Having considered these, just some of the many problems encountered by the ICTs, it is clear that the fundamental reliance placed upon state co-operation serves as a huge obstacle to ending impunity, because <hi rend="italic">"if that co-operation is not forthcoming, the tribunals are paralysed"</hi><ref target="BAWE_0069d-ftnote.049"/>. </s><s n="s2.2;p15.21">Moving on now to consider the ICC, hailed as the most <hi rend="italic">"innovative and exciting development in international law"</hi><ref target="BAWE_0069d-ftnote.050"/>, it becomes apparent that such an obstacle remains to be overcome. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0069d-ftnote.049"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">s <hi rend="italic">upra</hi> note 38, p. 461 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0069d-ftnote.050"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1"><hi rend="italic">supra</hi> note 7, p. 25. </s></p></note></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">4. The International Criminal Court</head><p n="p16.21"><s n="s1.2;p16.21">Having fallen victim to the aforementioned institutional paralysis of the Cold War, the idea of a permanent standing international criminal court regained momentum in 1995 when the UN GA created a Preparatory Commission to carefully study the ILC's draft statute for the establishment of such a court<ref target="BAWE_0069d-ftnote.051"/>. </s><s n="s2.2;p16.21">The experiences of two <hi rend="italic">ad hoc</hi> tribunals, coupled with the continued violence and bloodshed occurring across the globe, demonstrated the need for a court with universal jurisdiction, which finally came into being on July 1, 2002. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0069d-ftnote.051"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">UN GA, Resolution 50/46, "Establishment of a Criminal Court", 11 Dec 1995 </s></p></note><p n="p17.21"><s n="s1.6;p17.21">Again, the very creation of this institution illustrates, to a far greater extent than by the <hi rend="italic">ad</hi> <hi rend="italic">hoc</hi> tribunals, that individuals committing international crimes are no longer beyond the scope of justice. </s><s n="s2.6;p17.21">To date, 139 nations are signatories to the Rome Statute and 94 have ratified it, highlighting the existence of a truly global consensus aiming to end the impunity of governments. </s><s n="s3.6;p17.21">Enshrining substantive international criminal law on a global stage, the ICC will adjudicate over individuals accused of committing war crimes, genocide and crimes against humanity<ref target="BAWE_0069d-ftnote.052"/>, which have been defined in greater detail<ref target="BAWE_0069d-ftnote.053"/> and include certain innovations flowing from the judgements of the ICTY and ICTR<ref target="BAWE_0069d-ftnote.054"/>. </s><s n="s4.6;p17.21">The Statute has ensured all of the traditional immunities enjoyed by State officials, which shield them from outside scrutiny and prosecution, are swept away<ref target="BAWE_0069d-ftnote.055"/>, while Article 12 notably enables jurisdiction over not only individuals from states party to the statute but also over crimes committed on the territory of a state party. </s><s n="s5.6;p17.21">Thus, potential war-wagers from nations seeking to escape the ICC jurisdiction may nevertheless still be brought to trial. </s><s n="s6.6;p17.21">The permanency of the court negates the logistical drawbacks of setting up continuous <hi rend="italic">ad hoc</hi> tribunals in every case and, coupled with the variety of trigger-mechanisms available to commence proceedings (particularly the power held by the Prosecutor to initiate an investigation <hi rend="italic">proprio motu</hi><ref target="BAWE_0069d-ftnote.056"/>), the expediency and efficiency of international criminal justice have been augmented<ref target="BAWE_0069d-ftnote.057"/>. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0069d-ftnote.052"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Article 5(1) Rome Statute of the ICC </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0069d-ftnote.053"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">"<hi rend="italic">One of the outstanding contributions of the ICC Statute to international criminal law is to have specified better than ever before which behaviour amounts to war crimes and crimes against humanity",</hi> Lattimer &amp; Sands, <hi rend="italic">"Justice for Crimes Against Humanity",</hi> 2003, Hart Publishing, p.358 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0069d-ftnote.054"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">for example, following on from the ICTR, jurisdiction reaches to crimes committed in purely <hi rend="italic">internal</hi> conflicts. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">Also, as Kittischaisaree notes: "<hi rend="italic">The active role played by women in the negotiations has ensured the ICC Statute and the accompanying Elements of Crimes and Rules of Procedure are gender-sensitive,"</hi> "International Criminal Law", K. Kittichaisaree, 2003, OUP, p. 326 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0069d-ftnote.055"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Antonio Cassese, "<hi rend="italic">A Big Step Forward in International Justice",</hi> Crimes of War Project - The Magazine, Dec 2003. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0069d-ftnote.056"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Article 15 Rome Statute of the ICC </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0069d-ftnote.057"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">As Dworkin notes: <hi rend="italic">"It is easier to think that an independent prosecutor might pursue a case against a citizen of a powerful country than to imagine the government of another country doing it, at the risk of economic, diplomatic or perhaps military reprisal",</hi> "<hi rend="italic">The ICC an end to impunity?",</hi> Crimes of War Project - the Magazine, Dec 2003, p.2 </s></p></note><p n="p18.21"><s n="s1.7;p18.21">However, despite this revolutionary step in international criminal law, <hi rend="italic">"we remain a long way from a universal court that can sit in judgement over all the atrocities of the world"</hi><ref target="BAWE_0069d-ftnote.058"/>. </s><s n="s2.7;p18.21">The ICC is a UN-independent, treaty-based organisation, entry to which is voluntary and dependent on the political will of states. </s><s n="s3.7;p18.21">If such will is lacking, states can choose to remain outside the court's jurisdiction and will be under no obligation to co-operate with it, thus, a severe restriction on the jurisdiction of the court exists. </s><s n="s4.7;p18.21">The choice of the USA to remain absent is particularly problematic. </s><s n="s5.7;p18.21">As the world's only remaining superpower, and "<hi rend="italic">the only member of the UN SC able to mount and sustain transcontinental military operations...the USA is highly relevant to the ICC's future efficacy"</hi>.<ref target="BAWE_0069d-ftnote.059"/> It can undermine the otherwise widely recognised treaty by withholding information and refusing to extradite criminals, without fearing coercive action against it. </s><s n="s6.7;p18.21">The failure of the League of Nations was largely attributable to the USA's absence and the UN has often been paralysed due to lack of US co-operation. </s><s n="s7.7;p18.21">The ICC therefore bears the risk of being similarly limited. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0069d-ftnote.058"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid. p.1 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0069d-ftnote.059"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">"<hi rend="italic">The International Criminal Court: An American View",</hi> Ruth Wedgewood, E.J.I.L (1999), 93-107, p. 106 </s></p></note><p n="p19.21"><s n="s1.5;p19.21">In similar vein to the ICTs, the difficulties of enforcement will also no doubt severely limit the efficacy of the ICC. Analogous to the statutes of the ad hoc tribunals, the Rome Statute obligates States to co-operate with the ICC but provides no mechanisms of enforcement to see that they do. </s><s n="s2.5;p19.21">Furthermore, one of the principle features of the ICC is that it shall be "complementary"<ref target="BAWE_0069d-ftnote.060"/> to national criminal jurisdictions, meaning it shall only pursue cases when State authorities are "unwilling or unable"<ref target="BAWE_0069d-ftnote.061"/> to do so themselves. </s><s n="s3.5;p19.21">It follows that before pronouncing on a case, the ICC must first establish that the State that <hi rend="italic">"in principle could deal with the matter in fact shuns justice or is utterly unable to dispense justice"</hi>, thereby attaching a negative label to that State. </s><s n="s4.5;p19.21">This may clearly act as a disincentive for the much-needed co-operation from that State, and thus creates a major stumbling block with which the Court will have to come to grips. </s><s n="s5.5;p19.21">Again, when the gathering of evidence and the arresting of accused is so dependent on the good-will of states, the real impotence of international criminal justice can be demonstrated<ref target="BAWE_0069d-ftnote.062"/> and impunity is likely to remain apparent. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0069d-ftnote.060"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Article 1, Rome Statute of the ICC </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0069d-ftnote.061"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Article 17, Rome Statute of the ICC </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0069d-ftnote.062"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">As Penrose notes: <hi rend="italic">"Left to their own desires and devices, nation-states will continue to pursue their own self-interests at the cost of enforcing international law",</hi>op cit. <hi rend="italic">supra</hi> note 3, p. 371 </s></p></note></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">5. Conclusion - an end to impunity? </head><p n="p20.21"><s n="s1.2;p20.21">Considering these developments in international criminal law, it is clear that governments are no longer guaranteed to behave with impunity. </s><s n="s2.2;p20.21">The legacy of individual accountability established at Nuremburg has been furthered and refined by the ICTY and ICTR, and will no doubt continue with the future operation of the ICC. The tribunals have demonstrated that individuals from even the highest levels of political and military infrastructure can be brought to justice before international courts and the creation of the ICC with its more global reach serves as a formidable warning to potential belligerents, epitomising the international community's intolerance of genocide, war crimes and crimes against humanity. </s></p><p n="p21.21"><s n="s1.5;p21.21">However, what is also clear is that international criminal justice remains escapable. </s><s n="s2.5;p21.21">While the will of the international community to put an end to impunity exists on paper, embodied in numerous treaties and conventions, their commitment and co-operation in practice has not been so forthcoming. </s><s n="s3.5;p21.21">The experiences of the <hi rend="italic">ad hoc</hi> tribunals illustrated that without state co-operation, enforcement of the law becomes exceedingly difficult, if not impossible, and <hi rend="italic">"a tribunal unable to enforce its orders and judgements becomes at best an academic exercise and at worst, a cynical setback for international law"</hi><ref target="BAWE_0069d-ftnote.063"/>. </s><s n="s4.5;p21.21">There is little reason to expect that the ICC will fare much better in this regard, meaning impunity is likely to remain the rule rather than the exception in international criminal justice. </s><s n="s5.5;p21.21">Of course, as the ICC commences its first investigations<ref target="BAWE_0069d-ftnote.064"/>, we shall see over time whether states will respect their obligations and demonstrate their commitment to the treaty they so freely entered into, but at this point in time and given the fact that the Rome Statute cannot be altered until 2009, it would appear that government impunity cannot yet be brought to an end. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0069d-ftnote.063"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1"><hi rend="italic">supra</hi> note 14, p. 222 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0069d-ftnote.064"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">in Uganda, the Democratic Republic of the Congo and most recently the Central African Republic </s></p></note></div1></body><back><div1 type="bibliography"><head rend="underlined bold">6. Bibliography</head><p><hi rend="italic">"International Law"</hi>, Antonio Cassese, 2<hi rend="sup">nd</hi> edition, 2005, OUP</p><p><hi rend="italic">"International Law",</hi> Malcolm N. Shaw, 5<hi rend="sup">th</hi> edition, 2003, Cambridge University Press</p><p><hi rend="italic">"International Criminal Law",</hi> Antonio Cassese, 2003, OUP</p><p><hi rend="italic">"International Criminal Law",</hi> Kriangsak Kittichaisaree</p><p><hi rend="italic">"Judging War Criminals: The Politics of International Justice",</hi> Yves Beigbeder, 2003, Palgrave</p><p><hi rend="italic">"From Sovereign Impunity to International Accountability: the Search for Justice in a World of States",</hi> edited by Ramesh Thakur &amp; Peter Malcontent, 2004, United Nations University Press</p><p><hi rend="italic">"Accountability for Human Rights Atrocities in International Law",</hi> Steven R. Ratner &amp; Jason S. Abrams, 2001, OUP</p><p><hi rend="italic">"An Introduction to the International Criminal Court",</hi> William A. Schabas, 2<hi rend="sup">nd</hi> edition, 2004, Cambridge University Press</p><p><hi rend="italic">"Justice for Crimes Against Humanity",</hi> edited by Mark Lattimer &amp; Philippe Sands, 2003, Oxford: Hart</p><p><hi rend="italic">"The Permanent International Criminal Court: Legal &amp; Policy Issues",</hi> edited by Dominic McGoldrick, Peter Rowe and Eric Donnelly, 2004, Oxford: Hart.</p><p><hi rend="italic">"The Major Hurdles and Accomplishments of the ICTY - what the ICC can learn from them",</hi> Claude Jorda, Journal of International Criminal Justice, <hi rend="bold">2</hi> (2004) p.572-584</p><p><hi rend="italic">"The International Criminal Court: An American View",</hi> Ruth Wedgwood, European Journal of International Law, <hi rend="bold">10</hi> (1999) p.93-107</p><p><hi rend="italic">"On the Current Trend Towards Criminal Prosecution and Punishment of Breaches of International Humanitarian Law",</hi> Antonio Cassese, </p><p><hi rend="italic">"Reaching Inside the State: International Law and Superior Liability",</hi> James Meernik, International Studies Perspectives, 2004, Vol 5, p. 356-377</p><p><hi rend="italic">"Lest We Fail: the Importance of Enforcement in International Criminal Law",</hi> Mary Margaret Penrose, A.U.I.L.R, 2000, 321-394</p><p><hi rend="italic">"The ICC: an end to impunity?",</hi> Article from "Crimes of War Project - the Magazine", Dec 2003 edition found at <seg type="URL" n="www.crimesofwar.org/icc_magazine"/></p><p><hi rend="italic">"The Statute of the ICC, some preliminary reflections",</hi> Antonio Cassese, European Journal of International Law, <hi rend="bold">10</hi> (1999) 144</p></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
