<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_0069a" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>A discussion of the potential criminal liability of Amy and Felicity arising from the given hypothetical scenario, with consideration of the scope of applicable criminal law and the principle of fair labelling.</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">deleted: header: course name, student number
</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">1</p><p n="date">2004-03</p><p n="module title">Criminal Law</p><p n="module code">LA104</p><p n="genre family">Problem question</p><p n="discipline">Law</p><p n="disciplinary group">SS</p><p n="grade">M</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">3192</p><p n="number of s-units">120</p><p n="number of p">21</p><p n="number of tables">0</p><p n="number of figures">0</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">0</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">0</p><p n="abstract present">abstract present</p><p n="average words per s-unit">26.6</p><p n="average s-units per p">5.7</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">m</p><p n="year of birth">1984</p><p n="first language">English</p><p n="education">UKA</p><p n="course">Law</p><p n="student ID">0069</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><titlePart>University of <name type="university"/> School of Law Methods and functions of Criminal Law <hi rend="underlined bold"> Assessed Essay 2004</hi></titlePart><docTitle><titlePart rend="bold">- A discussion of the potential criminal liability of Amy and Felicity arising from the given hypothetical scenario, with consideration of the scope of applicable criminal law and the principle of fair labelling. </titlePart></docTitle></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="abstract"><p n="p1.21"><s n="s1.3;p1.21">Having read the given detailed account, it can be seen that certain incidents occurring in the story could be deemed criminal offences, for which either Felicity or Amy, or both, could be potentially liable. </s><s n="s2.3;p1.21">In the following paragraphs I will endeavour to identify and explain these offences and conclude whether or not the two could indeed be made criminally liable for them, whilst considering the scope of the applicable criminal law and the principle of fair labelling. </s><s n="s3.3;p1.21">I have fragmented this essay accordingly, so as to deal with each identifiable offence in turn. </s></p><p n="p2.21"><s rend="underlined italic" n="s1.2;p2.21">N.B. - </s><s n="s2.2;p2.21">based on the given information, for the sake of this essay it seems practical to treat both defendants as co-principals in the commission of the first two offences mentioned. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">1. The Offence of Theft</head><p n="p3.21"><s n="s1.12;p3.21">Felicity and Amy were successful on two occasions in implementing their plan to steal mobile phones from train passengers. </s><s n="s2.12;p3.21">Based on the given information, it appears that both parties would be liable for the offence of theft. </s><s n="s3.12;p3.21">Turning to the relevant statutory provisions contained in the Theft Act 1968, we can see how this is so. </s><s n="s4.12;p3.21">Ashworth's useful interpretation of section 1 of the Act breaks down the statutory requirements into five elements - three relating to conduct and two to the fault requirement: there must be (i) an <hi rend="italic"> appropriation</hi>; of (ii) <hi rend="italic">property</hi>; which (iii) <hi rend="italic">belongs to another</hi>; with (iv) an <hi rend="italic">intention of</hi> <hi rend="italic">permanent deprivation</hi>; and that this be done (v) <hi rend="italic">dishonestly</hi><ref target="BAWE_0069a-ftnote.001"/>. </s><s n="s5.12;p3.21">These conduct and fault requirements should be looked at in turn in relation to the actions and intentions of the two defendants, so as to decipher their liability conclusively. </s><s n="s6.12;p3.21">Firstly, the mobile phones that Felicity and Amy targeted did not belong to them but were under the possession of others (it seems justifiable to assume this, as we are told the phones were removed from others' bags/coats - an indication of their ownership), and yet they secretly took them into their own possession, thus being <hi rend="italic">appropriated</hi> in the eyes of the law. </s><s n="s7.12;p3.21">A mobile phone clearly comes under the scope of the definition of 'property' detailed in s. </s><s n="s8.12;p3.21">4(1) of the Act as including '<hi rend="italic">money and all other property, real or personal...'</hi>. </s><s n="s9.12;p3.21">Elements (i), (ii) and (iii) are hence satisfied; the conduct is criminal. </s><s n="s10.12;p3.21">The defendants' intentions to permanently deprive can be assumed as it is highly unlikely that the appropriation was intended only to be temporary. </s><s n="s11.12;p3.21">The phones were also taken without the consent of those who owned them and it cannot be argued that any of the stipulations contained in s. </s><s n="s12.12;p3.21">2, where appropriation would not be considered dishonest, could apply (i.e. the defendants obviously did not believe they either had a <hi rend="italic">legal right</hi> to take the phones nor that they would have been given <hi rend="italic">consent</hi> if their victims had known of the circumstances - the simple fact that they were carrying rulers to mimic concealed weapons shows that this would not be the case as they foresaw the owners' objections to their acts). </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0069a-ftnote.001"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">'Principles of Criminal Law' - A. Ashworth, p. 366, 4th ed., 2003, OUP. </s></p></note><p n="p4.21"><s n="s1.2;p4.21">Felicity and Amy therefore appear to be liable for this offence; the provisions of the 1968 Act can be applied without difficulty. </s><s n="s2.2;p4.21">However, complications arise when dealing with the attempted theft of the third victim's phone, as I will now discuss. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">2. Are Felicity and Amy guilty of Attempted Theft? </head><p n="p5.21"><s n="s1.6;p5.21">The Criminal Attempts Act 1981, s. </s><s n="s2.6;p5.21">1(1) establishes that a defendant will be liable for this offence if they perform "<hi rend="italic">an act which is more than merely preparatory to the commission of the offence".</hi> </s><s n="s3.6;p5.21">Their actions clearly meet this requirement in that not only did the two <hi rend="italic">plan</hi> to thieve, they went as far as reaching into their victim's coat and looking in their pockets for the object they desired. </s><s n="s4.6;p5.21">The statute also requires <hi rend="italic">intention</hi> to commit the offence. </s><s n="s5.6;p5.21">Obviously, the girls showed such intention by secretly inspecting the Caroline's pockets in the hope of acquiring a phone. </s><s n="s6.6;p5.21">The fact that they had already stolen two phones in such a way would, if proven in court, greatly assist their prosecution also. </s></p><p n="p6.21"><s n="s1.9;p6.21">However, difficulty lies in the fact that there was actually no phone in the pockets to steal; it was impossible to commit the intended offence. </s><s n="s2.9;p6.21">In determining liability in such a situation the courts appear somewhat ambiguous. </s><s n="s3.9;p6.21">In <hi rend="italic">Partington v Williams</hi><ref target="BAWE_0069a-ftnote.002"/> it was held that there could be no liability in such cases "<hi rend="italic">because the commission of the substantive offence was, in the circumstances, impossible</hi><ref target="BAWE_0069a-ftnote.003"/>". </s><s n="s4.9;p6.21">However, contrasting this decision is the case of <hi rend="italic">Bayley and Easterbrook</hi><ref target="BAWE_0069a-ftnote.004"/> where defendants were convicted of "<hi rend="italic">attempting to steal not the actual contents but something, unidentified, that was not in the box</hi><ref target="BAWE_0069a-ftnote.005"/>". </s><s n="s5.9;p6.21">Clearly, the potential liability depends on the approach adopted by the court in each case. </s><s n="s6.9;p6.21">If an act-centred approach is taken, whereby the defendants are judged on the consequences they intended to happen, liability may be escaped. </s><s n="s7.9;p6.21">However, it appears the trend<ref target="BAWE_0069a-ftnote.006"/> is to embrace a fault-centred approach suggesting a person should be judged on facts/circumstances as they believed them to be at the time. </s><s n="s8.9;p6.21">Felicity and Amy obviously thought that there was a phone in Caroline's jacket pocket and took action based on this assumption to secretly investigate the jacket in the hope of appropriating it. </s><s n="s9.9;p6.21">If this could be proven, liability for attempted theft may be imposed. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0069a-ftnote.002"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">[1977] Crim.L.R. 609 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0069a-ftnote.003"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">'Criminal Law, Texts and Materials' - CMV Clarkson &amp; HM Keating, p.494, 5th ed., 2003, Sweet &amp; Maxwell. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0069a-ftnote.004"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">[1980] Crim.L.R. 503 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0069a-ftnote.005"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">per Smith at [1980] Crim.L.R. 504 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0069a-ftnote.006"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Law Commission's recommendation of fault-centred approach, followed by sympathetic provisions in s1(2) and (3) of Criminal Attempts Act 1981 and ultimately decision in <hi rend="italic">Shivpuri</hi> [1987] AC 1 ascertained the judging of those charged with attempt based on the facts as they believed them to be. </s></p></note><p n="p7.21"><s n="s1.4;p7.21">Another potential liability for <hi rend="italic">conspiring</hi> to commit a criminal act could be incurred if attempted theft is not. </s><s n="s2.4;p7.21">Section 1(1) of the Criminal Law Act 1977 provides that a criminal conspiracy occurs when "<hi rend="italic">a course of conduct will be pursued which, if the agreement is carried out in accordance with their intentions...will necessarily amount to or involve the commission of any offence or offences by one or more parties to the agreement".</hi> </s><s n="s3.4;p7.21">Crucially, the agreement need not be physical but a mere 'meeting of the minds'. </s><s n="s4.4;p7.21">The agreed plan between Felicity and Amy to steal mobile phones undoubtedly amounts to such an offence, although would be very difficult to prove in court. </s></p><p n="p8.21"><s n="s1.3;p8.21">Criminalisation of these inchoate offences raises potent arguments in relation to principle of fair labelling. </s><s n="s2.3;p8.21">Whilst those attempting to commit an offence may indeed have a <hi rend="italic">mens rea</hi> justifiable of punishment, (an argument advocating criminal law's preventative principles), should the fact that they fundamentally do not commit a crime protect them from being labelled a criminal, the stigma of which remains with them for life? </s><s n="s3.3;p8.21">The scope of the law in this area can be criticised, as it purports to convict those who's acts are, somewhat loosely defined, as being 'more than merely preparatory', revealing a relatively broad approach to criminalisation in this area. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">3. Wounding or infliction of G.B.H. with intent</head><p n="p9.21"><s n="s1.8;p9.21">The Offences Against the Person Act 1861, s. </s><s n="s2.8;p9.21">18 , states that "<hi rend="italic">Whoever shall unlawfully and maliciously by any means whatsoever wound or cause grievous bodily harm to any person, with intent...to do some grievous bodily harm to any person...shall be guilty of [an offence and shall be liable...to imprisonment for life]</hi><ref target="BAWE_0069a-ftnote.007"/>". </s><s n="s3.8;p9.21">Felicity's action of stabbing Caroline in the eye clearly falls under this statutory provision hence it is likely that she would be found liable for such an offence. </s><s n="s4.8;p9.21">Felicity's aggressive conduct and frame of mind satisfy the elements of the statutory requirements in terms of <hi rend="italic">actus reus</hi> and <hi rend="italic">mens rea</hi>. </s><s n="s5.8;p9.21">Case law has aided the clarification of the terms <hi rend="italic">'wound'</hi> and <hi rend="italic">'grievous bodily harm',</hi> giving guidance to the jury deciding upon their existence in each case as a matter of fact. </s><s n="s6.8;p9.21">'Wounding' occurs when the skin is completely broken<ref target="BAWE_0069a-ftnote.008"/>, and G.B.H. is somewhat broadly defined as being when the harm caused is "<hi rend="italic">really serious"</hi><ref target="BAWE_0069a-ftnote.009"/>. </s><s n="s7.8;p9.21">The Charging Standard refers to "<hi rend="italic">injuries resulting in permanent disability or loss of sensory function</hi>"<ref target="BAWE_0069a-ftnote.010"/> (amongst others) in relation to G.B.H. The penetration of an object/weapon into a victim's eye causing blindness, as in the case in question, is likely to be considered G.B.H. by a jury. </s><s n="s8.8;p9.21">It is clear that Felicity, through stabbing Caroline, directly committed the offence with assault (<hi rend="italic">battery</hi> in the sense of the word in this case) which satisfies the conduct requirement and thus further concretes the case against her. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0069a-ftnote.007"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Adaptation of statute found in 'Criminal Law, Texts and Materials' - CMV Clarkson &amp; HM Keating, p.593, 5th ed., 2003, Sweet &amp; Maxwell. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0069a-ftnote.008"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1"><hi rend="italic">Moriarty v Brooks</hi> (1834) 6 C &amp; P 684 - <hi rend="italic">"Both the dermis and epidermis must be broken".</hi> </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0069a-ftnote.009"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1"><hi rend="italic">DPP v Smith</hi> [1961] A.C. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">290 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0069a-ftnote.010"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">as cited in 'Principles of Criminal Law' - A. Ashworth, p.314, 4th ed., 2003, OUP </s></p></note><p n="p10.21"><s n="s1.4;p10.21">In terms of the requisite <hi rend="italic">mens rea</hi>, the intention to cause G.B.H. must be shown. </s><s n="s2.4;p10.21">Felicity's intention is clear in this example. </s><s n="s3.4;p10.21">It cannot be denied that her conscious act of plunging an object into another's eye amounts to direct intention to inflict G.B.H. This goes far beyond satisfaction of the currently authoritative test for intention established in <hi rend="italic">Nedrick</hi><ref target="BAWE_0069a-ftnote.011"/>, which requires that the events that cause G.B.H. were seen as <hi rend="italic">virtually certain</hi> consequences of the defendant's actions, decided subjectively by the jury. </s><s n="s4.4;p10.21">Caroline's stabbing was neither a result of any accident nor a virtually certain consequence of some other intended offence, but was certainly the product of Felicity's 'violent temper', catalysed by her frustration with failing to acquire a third mobile phone. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0069a-ftnote.011"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">(Ransford Delroy) [1986] 1 W.L.R. 1025; [1986] 3 All ER 1 </s></p></note><p n="p11.21"><s n="s1.11;p11.21">Having said this, it is worth noting that there is a potential defence available to Felicity. </s><s n="s2.11;p11.21">Caroline's sudden and unexpected return may have caused Felicity to panic, perhaps due to fear and shock of being 'caught in the act' by Caroline, and cause her to think she was in danger of immediate harm. </s><s n="s3.11;p11.21">Her defence could therefore argue she justifiably reacted in self-defence to ensure this threat did not materialise. </s><s n="s4.11;p11.21">This line of argument is however likely to fail for several reasons. </s><s n="s5.11;p11.21">The law of self-defence turns on two requirements: that "<hi rend="italic">the force must have been necessary, and it must have been reasonable"</hi><ref target="BAWE_0069a-ftnote.012"/>. </s><s n="s6.11;p11.21">We are not informed of any action taken by Caroline that could possibly necessitate the subsequent action of Felicity, and therefore she is unable to justify her reaction as being reasonable, nor necessary. </s><s n="s7.11;p11.21">However, the courts may be inclined to take a subjective view, taking into account how Felicity may have actually interpreted Caroline's return as posing an immediate threat to her. </s><s n="s8.11;p11.21">The leading case of <hi rend="italic">Palmer</hi><ref target="BAWE_0069a-ftnote.013"/> suggests that this may be the case, where Lord Morris stated<ref target="BAWE_0069a-ftnote.014"/> that it is "most potent evidence" of reasonableness that the defendant only did what they "honestly and instinctively thought necessary". </s><s n="s9.11;p11.21">A court adopting this approach would greatly benefit Felicity's defence, yet it would be very unlikely to assume such a sympathetic perspective in such a situation involving the doctrine of prior fault (i.e. the attempted theft which had induced the subsequent scene of confrontation between defendant and victim). </s><s n="s10.11;p11.21">Furthermore, the requirement that a reaction in self-defence must be proportionate to the nature of the threat would defeat Felicity's defence argument. </s><s n="s11.11;p11.21">The simple act of returning to one's seat before another expects it to happen could not be considered proportionate to being stabbed in the eye. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0069a-ftnote.012"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">'Principles of Criminal Law' - A. Ashworth, p.139, 4th ed., 2003, OUP </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0069a-ftnote.013"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">[1971] AC 814 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0069a-ftnote.014"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">at 832 </s></p></note></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">4. Murder or Involuntary Manslaughter? </head><p n="p12.21"><s n="s1.3;p12.21">The final incident to consider is Felicity's punching of Delia, that ultimately lead to the latter's death. </s><s n="s2.3;p12.21">Felicity is potentially liable for murder or involuntary manslaughter. </s><s n="s3.3;p12.21"><hi rend="italic">Voluntary</hi> manslaughter, where the defendant intended murder but successfully pleas provocation or diminished responsibility, would not be applicable here as it is clear that Felicity was neither provoked by Delia (who was merely assisting the injured Caroline), nor are we told that she was suffering from any "<hi rend="italic">disease of the mind</hi><ref target="BAWE_0069a-ftnote.015"/>" as is required for a successful plea of diminished responsibility. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0069a-ftnote.015"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">A pre-requisite for diminished responsibility established in <hi rend="italic">M'Naghten's case</hi> (1843) 10 C&amp;F, 200 </s></p></note><p n="p13.21"><s n="s1.7;p13.21">Was Delia murdered by Felicity? </s><s n="s2.7;p13.21">Difficulty lies in the fact that death was not directly caused by the punch to the face but by Delia's subsequent fall, cracking her head against a handrail. </s><s n="s3.7;p13.21">Therefore the courts must look to the relationship between the two incidents in order determine causation of the death for the sake of assessing whether Felicity satisfied the requisite <hi rend="italic">actus reus</hi> for murder - unlawful killing of another. </s><s n="s4.7;p13.21">As usual, it must also be shown that the defendant had requisite <hi rend="italic">mens rea</hi> for the offence. </s><s n="s5.7;p13.21">For murder it is defined as "<hi rend="italic">intention to kill or cause G.B.H.</hi> </s><ref target="BAWE_0069a-ftnote.016"/><s n="s6.7;p13.21">". </s><s n="s7.7;p13.21">Felicity's actual intention is seemingly unclear - did she merely mean to assault and cause in injury to Delia as part of her aforementioned fit of rage, or did she actually intend to kill? </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0069a-ftnote.016"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">According to section 1 Homicide Act 1957 </s></p></note><p n="p14.21"><s n="s1.8;p14.21">In terms of <hi rend="italic">actus reus</hi>, it seems clear that in punching Delia, Felicity commits an assault which satisfies the requirement that the action be 'unlawful'; it was neither in self-defence nor an assault justifiable in any other way. </s><s n="s2.8;p14.21">However, the causation element becomes crucial here. </s><s n="s3.8;p14.21">To impose liability, the chain of causation between unlawful act and the death of the victim must be unbroken. </s><s n="s4.8;p14.21">Application of the traditional "<hi rend="italic">but for</hi>" test<ref target="BAWE_0069a-ftnote.017"/> is justifiable here in this simplistic scenario<ref target="BAWE_0069a-ftnote.018"/> and would suggest the death would not have been caused 'but for' the initial punch, indicating causation <hi rend="italic">in fact</hi>. </s><s n="s5.8;p14.21">Causation <hi rend="italic">in law</hi> must also be considered. </s><s n="s6.8;p14.21">The key issue here is whether Delia's collision with the handrail, which caused the injury from which she died, could be a "<hi rend="italic">novus actus interveniens</hi><ref target="BAWE_0069a-ftnote.019"/>", thus breaking the chain of causation. </s><s n="s7.8;p14.21">In such a case where the intervening event is the immediate cause of death, the courts will apply the test of reasonable forseeability, to be decided objectively as a matter of fact by the jury<ref target="BAWE_0069a-ftnote.020"/>. </s><s n="s8.8;p14.21">If it decided that Delia's fall and collision after being punched was a reasonably foreseeable consequence of that punch, the chain of causation would remain in tact and the actus reus requirement satisfied. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0069a-ftnote.017"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">e.g. in <hi rend="italic">Mitchell</hi> [1983] 2 All ER 427 - held that by knocking over an elderly woman causing her to later form a blood clot in her lung and die, defendant was liable based on this 'but for' test. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0069a-ftnote.018"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.3;pn1.1">Unlike in <hi rend="italic">Cato</hi> [1976] 62 Cr. </s><s n="s2.3;pn1.1">App. </s><s n="s3.3;pn1.1">R 41 - 'but for' test considered too narrow to incorporate the somewhat tenuous link between D's conduct of injecting heroin into the victim and the latter's subsequent death. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0069a-ftnote.019"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">(A new act intervening) </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0069a-ftnote.020"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.3;pn1.1">e.g. in cases of <hi rend="italic">Roberts</hi> [1971] 56 Cr. </s><s n="s2.3;pn1.1">App. </s><s n="s3.3;pn1.1">R. 95 and </s></p></note><p n="p15.21"><s n="s1.5;p15.21">Turning to the fault requirement for murder, the Criminal Justice Act 1967 s. </s><s n="s2.5;p15.21">8(1) establishes that the test for deciphering intention should be subjective and the cases of <hi rend="italic">Nedrick</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Woollin</hi><ref target="BAWE_0069a-ftnote.021"/> have concreted this. </s><s n="s3.5;p15.21">Whilst Felicity's purpose may not have been to kill Delia, she may still be liable for murder if the jury "<hi rend="italic">feels sure that death or serious bodily harm was a virtual certainty...as a result of the defendant's actions and they the defendant appreciated that such was the case"</hi><ref target="BAWE_0069a-ftnote.022"/>. </s><s n="s4.5;p15.21">No longer is the test mere "reasonable forseeability" as it is for the causation element, but for mens rea it must be "virtual certainty" of the consequences accruing as they did. </s><s n="s5.5;p15.21">It is unlikely, therefore, that Felicity would be liable for murder as there are too many uncertainties in the scenario - whilst it may be nearly certain that someone would fall over after a punch to the face, it cannot be virtually certain that the fall would be onto a handrail and that the resulting collision would cause fatal injuries to the victim. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0069a-ftnote.021"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">[1999] AC 92 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0069a-ftnote.022"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">per Lord Steyn in <hi rend="italic">Woollin</hi> </s></p></note><p n="p16.21"><s n="s1.2;p16.21">With murder exhausted, Felicity's potential liability takes the more likely form of Unlawful and Dangerous Act Manslaughter<ref target="BAWE_0069a-ftnote.023"/>. </s><s n="s2.2;p16.21">The fault element here is not attached to proving the defendant intended to kill or cause G.B.H. but more to the commission of an unlawful and dangerous act that is so connected to the death of the victim that they should be guilty of homicide. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0069a-ftnote.023"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">(or <hi rend="italic">constructive</hi> manslaughter) </s></p></note><p n="p17.21"><s n="s1.8;p17.21">Case law again becomes most useful here in defining the law. </s><s n="s2.8;p17.21">The act<ref target="BAWE_0069a-ftnote.024"/> must firstly be "unlawful" e.g. a criminal offence. </s><s n="s3.8;p17.21">As previously mentioned, Felicity's battery against Delia satisfies this requirement. </s><s n="s4.8;p17.21">Secondly, the act must be objectively dangerous. </s><s n="s5.8;p17.21">In <hi rend="italic">Dawson</hi><ref target="BAWE_0069a-ftnote.025"/>, it was held that an unlawful act would be regarded as 'dangerous' if it was 'likely to cause physical harm'<ref target="BAWE_0069a-ftnote.026"/>. </s><s n="s6.8;p17.21">Battery of such nature as Felicity committed is a clear example of a dangerous act therefore. </s><s n="s7.8;p17.21">Lastly, the act must cause the death of the victim, and as discussed for murder, this is left to the jury to decide as matters of fact and law based on the traditional "but for" test and the objective test of reasonable forseeability of the fatal consequences. </s><s n="s8.8;p17.21">Felicity is most likely to be liable for this offence, as the unbroken chain of causation links her act to Delia's death. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0069a-ftnote.024"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">an omission cannot amount to this charge, established in e.g. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1"><hi rend="italic">Lowe</hi> [1973] QB 702 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0069a-ftnote.025"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">[1985] 81 Cr App R 150 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0069a-ftnote.026"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">'Principles of Criminal Law' - A. Ashworth, p.296, 4th ed., 2003, OUP </s></p></note><p n="p18.21"><s n="s1.3;p18.21">The courts approach in relation to involuntary manslaughter, whereby life imprisonment, the same punishment as for murder, may be ordered at the court's discretion, again raises issues of fair labelling. </s><s n="s2.3;p18.21">It is seemingly unjust for the courts to impose their most severe punishment on those who do not actually intend commit a crime meriting such a punishment, but who's intention lies merely in the commission of a common assault. </s><s n="s3.3;p18.21">Commentators have even called for its abolishment, and reform in this section of the law is under consideration. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">5. Amy's potential accomplice liability</head><p n="p19.21"><s n="s1.13;p19.21">The Accessories and Abettors Act 1861 details the threshold of participation required to impose liability on potential accomplices. </s><s n="s2.13;p19.21">A person will be liable if they are seen to '<hi rend="italic">aid, abet, counsel or procure</hi><ref target="BAWE_0069a-ftnote.027"/>' the principal offender in the commission of their offence. </s><s n="s3.13;p19.21">The courts have interpreted this statutory provision and established certain rules and guidelines through case law over time. </s><s n="s4.13;p19.21">Does Amy's participation cross the threshold in relation to these last two offences committed by Felicity? </s><s n="s5.13;p19.21">Investigating her conduct and state of mind relating to (i) aiding and abetting and (ii) counselling and procuring<ref target="BAWE_0069a-ftnote.028"/>, does not produce an altogether conclusive result. </s><s n="s6.13;p19.21">On one hand, if we are to assume based on the given information that Amy does not offer any positive encouragement to Felicity, her mere presence at the scene of the crime does not satisfy the conduct requirement for accomplice liability. </s><s n="s7.13;p19.21">Case law indicates that the defendant must make some positive acts of encouragement<ref target="BAWE_0069a-ftnote.029"/>, such as a 'pat on the back' (Gianetto<ref target="BAWE_0069a-ftnote.030"/>) or applause (Wilcox v Jeffery<ref target="BAWE_0069a-ftnote.031"/>). </s><s n="s8.13;p19.21">The attack on Caroline was not planned but was more a sudden manifestation of Felicity's rage. </s><s n="s9.13;p19.21">The two party's common intention only went so far as to commit theft, and possibly assault through intimidation of victims with rulers. </s><s n="s10.13;p19.21">It was never agreed to commit battery or manslaughter prior to Felicity's actions. </s><s n="s11.13;p19.21">This suggests that Amy's state of mind would not satisfy the mens rea requirement for liability. </s><s n="s12.13;p19.21">She must have intended to do any acts of assistance/encouragement and have been aware of her ability to do so. </s><s n="s13.13;p19.21">It seems impossible that she could have been in this frame of mind in relation to an offence that occurred so suddenly and unexpectedly. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0069a-ftnote.027"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Accessories and Abettors Act 1861, s.8 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0069a-ftnote.028"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">separation, in accordance with tradition, of the two "<hi rend="italic">time-honoured pairings" -</hi> A. Ashworth - 'Principles of Criminal Law', p. 416. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0069a-ftnote.029"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Established in cases of <hi rend="italic">Coney</hi> (1881-82) LR 8 QBD 534 and <hi rend="italic">Clarkson</hi> [1971] 1 WLR 1402 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0069a-ftnote.030"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">[1977] 1 Cr App R 1 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0069a-ftnote.031"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">[1951] 1 All ER 464 </s></p></note><p n="p20.21"><s n="s1.5;p20.21">On the other hand, importance lies in Amy's awareness of Felicity's propensity to act violently, and in her knowledge that such behaviour has made her criminally liable in the past. </s><s n="s2.5;p20.21">Amy also realised Felicity was armed with an object being wielded as if it were a weapon. </s><s n="s3.5;p20.21">It could be argued that, with this knowledge, Amy's omission is one where she had the <hi rend="italic">power to act</hi> and could thus satisfy the requisite <hi rend="italic">mens rea</hi> - just as the weigh-bride operator, who knew the incorrect weight-certificate he gave to a lorry driver would mean an offence could be committed, was liable due to his omission to act<ref target="BAWE_0069a-ftnote.032"/>. </s><s n="s4.5;p20.21">In this case it is the accomplice's awareness of what will happen in the future, and even 'reckless knowledge' i.e. </s><s n="s5.5;p20.21"><hi rend="italic">awareness of risk</hi><ref target="BAWE_0069a-ftnote.033"/> of the offence, can amount to liability. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0069a-ftnote.032"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1"><hi rend="italic">National Coal Board v Gamble</hi> [1959] 1 QB 11 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0069a-ftnote.033"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">'Accomplice Liability' - J. Hodgson, lecture notes, 2004. </s></p></note><p n="p21.21"><s n="s1.2;p21.21">Clearly, the criminalisation of accessories to the extent where they are as culpable as the principal offender generates a profound debate, bringing the principle of fair labelling into consideration once again. </s><s n="s2.2;p21.21">The courts have not been able to douse criticisms over the doctrine's propensity to unjustly convict those, whose participation in the commission of another's offence may be relatively low, and it seems as though their current test for establishing the threshold for participation is undesirably too broad. </s></p></div1></body><back/></text></TEI.2>
