<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_0069c" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>The decision of the Court in Williams v Roffey Bros [(1991) 1 QB 1, Court of Appeal] which suggests that performance of an existing (contractual) duty can constitute consideration where it results in 'practical benefit' to the promisor creates further ambiguity in the scope of consideration in eng contract law. Discuss.</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">deleted: header: course name, student number; footer:page number
</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">1</p><p n="date">2003-12</p><p n="module title">Basic Techniques of Common Law in Contract &amp; Tort</p><p n="module code">LA102</p><p n="genre family">Essay</p><p n="discipline">Law</p><p n="disciplinary group">SS</p><p n="grade">M</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">1502</p><p n="number of s-units">67</p><p n="number of p">10</p><p n="number of tables">0</p><p n="number of figures">0</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">0</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">0</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">22.4</p><p n="average s-units per p">6.7</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">m</p><p n="year of birth">1984</p><p n="first language">English</p><p n="education">UKA</p><p n="course">Law</p><p n="student ID">0069</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><titlePart><hi rend="bold">CONTRACT LAW 2003-2004</hi> First assessed essay topic</titlePart><docTitle><titlePart>"The decision of the Court in <hi rend="italic">Williams v Roffey Bros</hi> [(1991) 1 QB 1, Court of Appeal] which suggests that performance of an existing (contractual) duty can constitute consideration where it results in 'practical benefit' to the promisor creates further ambiguity in the scope of consideration in English contract law." Discuss.</titlePart></docTitle></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="section"><p n="p1.10"><s n="s1.2;p1.10">The element of consideration is a requisite component of a contract as governed by the common law principles encompassed by the English Law of Contract. </s><s n="s2.2;p1.10">It is inherent to the element of exchange through bargaining in contracts, and is needed to validate contracts when found in conjunction with a legitimate offer, acceptance and an intention of the parties to create legal relations. </s></p><p n="p2.10"><s n="s1.3;p2.10">Consideration has always been somewhat of an unclear, problematic doctrine, often being left to the courts to decipher in individual cases - a point clearly illuminated by this investigation in question. </s><s n="s2.3;p2.10">Traditionally, consideration's definition is translated into a model of mutual benefit/detriment, as expressed by Lush, J in the case of <hi rend="italic">Currie v.</hi> </s><s n="s3.3;p2.10"><hi rend="italic">Misa</hi><ref target="BAWE_0069c-ftnote.001"/>: "<hi rend="italic">A valuable consideration, in the sense of the law, may consist either in some right, interest, profit, or benefit accruing to one party, or some forbearance, detriment, loss, or responsibility, given, suffered or undertaken by the other".</hi> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0069c-ftnote.001"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">[1875] LR Ex 153, 162 </s></p></note><p n="p3.10"><s n="s1.4;p3.10">Looking at consideration in the context of the case of <hi rend="italic">Williams v.</hi> </s><s n="s2.4;p3.10"><hi rend="italic">Roffey Bros</hi><ref target="BAWE_0069c-ftnote.002"/>, the <hi rend="italic">sufficiency</hi> of consideration given by a particular party is contested by the other party over the issue that arose as to whether or not good (sufficient) consideration can be given by one party simply promising to perform their existing contractual duties. </s><s n="s3.4;p3.10">The Court of Appeal came to a significant conclusion in this case that such performance could constitute consideration when it conveys a 'practical' benefit to the promisor. </s><s n="s4.4;p3.10">This somewhat revised the orthodox legal position on the matter. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0069c-ftnote.002"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">and Nicholls (Contractors) Ltd [1991] 1 QB 1, Court of Appeal </s></p></note><p n="p4.10"><s n="s1.8;p4.10">Traditionally, the courts had maintained the rule that in situations where one contracting party, A, promises to pay an additional sum to fellow contracting party, B, provided B undertakes to perform their existing contractual obligations to A, B's return promise does not provide sufficient consideration, and that if one party promises to modify their obligations without fresh consideration being provided in return, the promise to vary the original agreement is gratuitous and hence unenforceable. </s><s n="s2.8;p4.10">The case of <hi rend="italic">Stilk v.</hi> </s><s n="s3.8;p4.10"><hi rend="italic">Myrick</hi><ref target="BAWE_0069c-ftnote.003"/> classically represents these rules. </s><s n="s4.8;p4.10">It was held that a captain was not bound by his promise to pay additional sums to his crew, after the desertion of two sailors, if they would complete their voyage as contracted, due to the court concluding that the crew offered no fresh consideration for the captain's promise. </s><s n="s5.8;p4.10">Arguably, the captain enjoyed some 'practical benefit' in the form of his crew working harder, under greater pressure due to lack of crewmen, and that this could amount to consideration. </s><s n="s6.8;p4.10">However this idea was dismissed, the court concluding that the sailors "<hi rend="italic">had sold all their services till the voyage should be completed</hi><ref target="BAWE_0069c-ftnote.004"/>". </s><s n="s7.8;p4.10">Lord Ellenborough placed the most importance on deciphering the legal obligations of the remaining crew, deciding that they had not done anything more than what they were already legally obliged to do under the contract, hence no consideration. </s><s n="s8.8;p4.10">The position of the courts was hence established, strengthening the importance of investigating benefits/detriments under contract as a matter of law, rather than as 'factual' or 'practical'. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0069c-ftnote.003"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">[1809] 2 Camp 317, 6 Esp 129 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0069c-ftnote.004"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">As quoted from Lord Ellenborough - exclusively from Campbell's report [1809] 2 Camp 318 - Campbell's report has been chosen as authority, after recognition of its distinction over the less reliable report made by Espinasse. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">Several sources induced this decision, backing Campbell's reliability over Espinasse. </s></p></note><p n="p5.10"><s n="s1.7;p5.10">The case of <hi rend="italic">Foakes v.</hi> </s><s n="s2.7;p5.10"><hi rend="italic">Beer</hi><ref target="BAWE_0069c-ftnote.005"/> furthered the authority of this rule. </s><s n="s3.7;p5.10">The courts position thus seemed unambiguous. </s><s n="s4.7;p5.10">Mrs Beer had obtained a judgement for the sum of £2090 19s to be made payable in instalments at an interest rate of 4% by Dr. Foakes. </s><s n="s5.7;p5.10">Later, at Foakes' request, a new agreement was made that prolonged the time allowed for debt-payment despite not mentioning any further requisite interest payments. </s><s n="s6.7;p5.10">Beer sought to recover this interest after Foakes refused to pay it. </s><s n="s7.7;p5.10">The House of Lords agreed that there was a one-sided benefit being obtained by the new agreement (Foakes had a longer time to pay at no added interest) and that this agreement should fail for lack of consideration from Foakes. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0069c-ftnote.005"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">[1884] 9 App Cas 605, House of Lords </s></p></note><p n="p6.10"><s n="s1.10;p6.10">How so was it then, that in <hi rend="italic">Williams v.</hi> </s><s n="s2.10;p6.10"><hi rend="italic">Roffey Bros,</hi> consideration was deemed sufficient in the form of a promise to perform existing contractual obligations? </s><s n="s3.10;p6.10">We must look at the details of the case. </s><s n="s4.10;p6.10">The plaintiff had entered into a subcontract with the defendants, who held the main building contract which itself contained a time penalty clause, to carry out carpentry work in a block of flats for an agreed price of £20,000. </s><s n="s5.10;p6.10">The plaintiff then ran into financial difficulty due to the agreed price being too low for him to operate profitably at. </s><s n="s6.10;p6.10">Consequently, a new agreement was made under which the plaintiff would be paid an additional £10,300 (£575 per completed flat). </s><s n="s7.10;p6.10">The defendants were wary of incurring the penalty clause that was likely to take effect if they were to try and find a suitable replacement for the existing carpenters. </s><s n="s8.10;p6.10">After the substantial completion of 8 more flats, Williams had only received a further £1,500. </s><s n="s9.10;p6.10">He subsequently left the site and sued for remaining payment. </s><s n="s10.10;p6.10">The Court of Appeal judges unanimously agreed to uphold the County Court decision that had awarded the plaintiff £4,600 for such substantially completed work. </s></p><p n="p7.10"><s n="s1.4;p7.10">Crucially, here the judges emphasised the importance of 'practical benefits' that accrued due to the re-negotiation of the contract - i.e. the assured avoidance of the penalty clause<ref target="BAWE_0069c-ftnote.006"/> and the mutual benefit enjoyed due to the creation of a system of payment reconciling the haphazard original agreement. </s><s n="s2.4;p7.10">It also remained largely uncontested that the original agreed amount of pay owed to the sub-contractors was too low. </s><s n="s3.4;p7.10">Lord Glidewell defined a newly revised legal position, essentially stating that in situations when one of two contracting parties runs into difficulty and is potentially unable to fully perform their contractual obligations, a new agreement can be legally binding if, through a promise to pay additional sums to the party suffering difficulty, the other party obtains some practical benefit or obviates a disbenefit. </s><s n="s4.4;p7.10">Good consideration can be in the form of such promises in these situations, provided the new agreement is not induced by fraud or economic duress. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0069c-ftnote.006"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">It should be noted that the additional sums promised to the plaintiffs were likely to be less than the agreed damages that the defendants would have to pay if substantial delays occurred - Adams and Brownsword: "Understanding Contract Law", Ch. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">5, p. 79 </s></p></note><p n="p8.10"><s n="s1.7;p8.10">It is arguable that this rouses ambiguity in the scope of consideration as it appears to contest and hence distort the traditional stance of the courts. </s><s n="s2.7;p8.10">On first appearance it seems to be in direct contrast to the ruling in <hi rend="italic">Stilk v.</hi> </s><s n="s3.7;p8.10"><hi rend="italic">Myrick</hi>. </s><s n="s4.7;p8.10">Williams was only doing what he was already contracted to do, as were the sailors in <hi rend="italic">Stilk,</hi> and yet the promise to perform his pre-existing contractual duties was construed as good consideration in the new agreement. </s><s n="s5.7;p8.10">Essentially, the court has become ambiguous in the sense that it, on the basis of <hi rend="italic">Williams v.</hi> </s><s n="s6.7;p8.10"><hi rend="italic">Roffey,</hi> it now appears to concern itself more with the realism element of the contract and the true intention of the parties - the 'practical' benefits/detriments seem more significant to the judges than those existing legally. </s><s n="s7.7;p8.10">It is a shift from the traditional, pragmatic approach, placing the law in its more modern context - "a <hi rend="italic">decision inspired by modern market-individualism</hi><ref target="BAWE_0069c-ftnote.007"/>". </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0069c-ftnote.007"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Adams and Brownsword - Understanding Contract Law, Ch. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">5, p. 80 </s></p></note><p n="p9.10"><s n="s1.13;p9.10">However, the court itself saw the decision as not to overrule the principle established in <hi rend="italic">Stilk v.</hi> </s><s n="s2.13;p9.10"><hi rend="italic">Myrick</hi> but more to "<hi rend="italic">refine and limit the application of that principle"</hi><ref target="BAWE_0069c-ftnote.008"/>. </s><s n="s3.13;p9.10">This seems fair as it is perhaps inevitable and useful that such a long-established precedent relating to such a vexed area of contract law should be placed into a modern arena to be tried and tested. </s><s n="s4.13;p9.10">The case of Williams v. </s><s n="s5.13;p9.10">Roffey was obviously very different to Stilk v. </s><s n="s6.13;p9.10">Myrick, thus it was distinguished by the court. </s><s n="s7.13;p9.10">The 'practical benefits' enjoyed by the defendants, post re-negotiation, made it unconscionable that such a contract should not be upheld for lack of consideration. </s><s n="s8.13;p9.10">Furthermore, it is worth noting that two cases from the 1950's, Ward v. </s><s n="s9.13;p9.10">Byham<ref target="BAWE_0069c-ftnote.009"/> and Williams v. </s><s n="s10.13;p9.10">Williams<ref target="BAWE_0069c-ftnote.010"/> had also established a precedent suggesting that performance of existing legal obligations can constitute good consideration in a contract<ref target="BAWE_0069c-ftnote.011"/>. </s><s n="s11.13;p9.10">In Ward, the performance of the pre-existing duty of a mother to care for her child was deemed sufficient consideration for the father's promise to pay her £1 per month to do so<ref target="BAWE_0069c-ftnote.012"/>. </s><s n="s12.13;p9.10">In Williams v. </s><s n="s13.13;p9.10">Williams, having deserted her husband, a wife's promise to 'maintain herself' (as already bound to do) during their separation was construed as being good consideration for his promise to pay £1 10s for said upkeep. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0069c-ftnote.008"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Glidewell, L.J. in reference to <hi rend="italic">Stylk v.</hi> </s><s rend="italic" n="s2.2;pn1.1">Myrick </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0069c-ftnote.009"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">[1956] 1 WLR 496, Court of Appeal </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0069c-ftnote.010"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">[1957] 1 WLR 148, Court of Appeal </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0069c-ftnote.011"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">largely thanks to the liberal approach adopted by Lord Denning </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0069c-ftnote.012"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Lord Denning: "<hi rend="italic">...a promise to perform an existing duty, or the performance of it, should be regarded as good consideration, because it is a benefit to the person to whom it is given".</hi> </s></p></note><p n="p10.10"><s n="s1.9;p10.10">To conclude the discussion, a powerful argument exists suggesting the law has become more ambiguous in relation to the scope of consideration due to the ruling in <hi rend="italic">Williams v.</hi> </s><s rend="italic" n="s2.9;p10.10">Roffey. </s><s n="s3.9;p10.10">The courts now seem unpredictable. </s><s n="s4.9;p10.10">It is still unclear as to whether they will continue to affirm the traditional approach established in <hi rend="italic">Stilk v.</hi> </s><s n="s5.9;p10.10"><hi rend="italic">Myrick</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Foakes v.</hi> </s><s n="s6.9;p10.10"><hi rend="italic">Beer</hi> and only focus on the construction of consideration from a legal benefit/detriment model (as approved in the more recent case of <hi rend="italic">Re Selectmove</hi><ref target="BAWE_0069c-ftnote.013"/>), or whether they will further embrace the modern benefit-led, policy-sensitive theory of consideration that recognises the significance of 'practical/factual' benefits/detriments accruing in contracts. </s><s n="s7.9;p10.10">However, it is also arguable that perhaps the law has not been made as much ambiguous as it has been re-defined to account for a more modern species of case, extending existing principles established in cases such as <hi rend="italic">Ward v.</hi> </s><s n="s8.9;p10.10"><hi rend="italic">Byham</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Williams v.</hi> </s><s rend="italic" n="s9.9;p10.10">Williams. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0069c-ftnote.013"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">[1995] 1 W.L.R. 474; [1995] 2 All E.R. 531, CA </s></p></note></div1></body><back/></text></TEI.2>
