<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_0077g" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Coordination of Wage Bargaining - Does it increase mark-up and generate higher prices?</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">deleted: header: student number; footer: page numbers
deleted: WORD COUNT: 938
</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">3</p><p n="date">2005-11</p><p n="module title">Economic Policy in the UK</p><p n="module code">EC307</p><p n="genre family">Essay</p><p n="discipline">Economics</p><p n="disciplinary group">SS</p><p n="grade">D</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">935</p><p n="number of s-units">40</p><p n="number of p">6</p><p n="number of tables">0</p><p n="number of figures">0</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">0</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">0</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">23.4</p><p n="average s-units per p">6.7</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">m</p><p n="year of birth">1981</p><p n="first language">Norwegian</p><p n="education">OSA</p><p n="course">Economics</p><p n="student ID">0077</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><docTitle><titlePart rend="bold">Coordination of Wage Bargaining - does it increase mark-up and generate higher prices? </titlePart></docTitle><titlePart/><titlePart><hi rend="bold">EC307 Research in Applied Economics Literature Review</hi><hi rend="bold"> 30.11.2005 Student Number <name type="student ID"/></hi></titlePart></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="section"><p n="p1.6"><s n="s1.15;p1.6">Price determination has received an increasingly important position in contemporary literature, as it is essential to our understanding of the complex issues of unemployment and inflation. </s><s n="s2.15;p1.6">The increasing attention of policymakers regarding inflation targets has necessitated further research in this field. </s><s n="s3.15;p1.6">Nevertheless, there is surprisingly little literature on both single country and cross-country price determination analysis. </s><s n="s4.15;p1.6">Still, some interest has been put in different theories of price determination, and the two most central theories are the purchasing power theory (the law of one price) and the mark-up theory. </s><s n="s5.15;p1.6">The purchasing power theory asserts that prices are determined in the long run by world competition, thus the theory emphasises the importance of import prices.<ref target="BAWE_0077g-ftnote.001"/> The mark-up theory developed by Kalecki states that producers set prices as a mark-up over average variable costs<ref target="BAWE_0077g-ftnote.002"/>, partly as an insurance against variability in input prices and partly to earn profits. </s><s n="s6.15;p1.6">Martin advocate, through his theoretical and empirical assessment of the UK economy<ref target="BAWE_0077g-ftnote.003"/>, that reality is somewhat in the middle of these two main theories. </s><s n="s7.15;p1.6">He shows that interactions between domestic and foreign actors cannot be neglected when it comes to theories of price formation, thus both domestic costs and import prices are important in determining the domestic price level. </s><s n="s8.15;p1.6">Accordingly, there is no clear view in the literature about which variables determine prices at the aggregate level. </s><s n="s9.15;p1.6">I aim to utilise the mark-up theory in my paper; however, papers that estimate the price mark-up equation is, rather unexpectedly, not very prevalent.<ref target="BAWE_0077g-ftnote.004"/> Furthermore, I attempt to investigate whether there is an omitted variable bias in the standard price determination models by including an index for the coordination of wage determination. </s><s n="s10.15;p1.6">We can think of two theoretical justifications for including coordination as an explanatory variable. </s><s n="s11.15;p1.6">First, as coordination between unions increase, firms realise that their competitors suffer from the same rise in wages; hence a higher mark-up is defendable. </s><s n="s12.15;p1.6">Second, higher coordination could create barriers of entry and could make higher mark-ups sustainable. </s><s n="s13.15;p1.6">The implications of both these theoretical justifications are that a higher degree of coordination increases the mark-up, ceteris paribus. </s><s n="s14.15;p1.6">As far as I am concerned, there has hitherto been no attempt to explicitly address this issue. </s><s n="s15.15;p1.6">Earlier studies have focused solely on the price curve dynamics of the price determination, and accordingly assumed the wage curve to be fixed. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0077g-ftnote.001"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">See Dornbusch (1992) for further details. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0077g-ftnote.002"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Kalecki (1943) and Kalecki (1971). </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0077g-ftnote.003"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Martin (1997). </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0077g-ftnote.004"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">See for example Martin (1997) and Clements and Sensier (2003). </s></p></note><p n="p2.6"><s n="s1.5;p2.6">Nunziata<ref target="BAWE_0077g-ftnote.005"/> elucidated institutional factors as highly significant in influencing wages. </s><s n="s2.5;p2.6">He estimates the determinants of labour costs in 20 OECD (Organisation of Economic Co-operation and Development) countries, and finds both a direct effect on wages, through wage pressure despite excess supply in the labour market, and an indirect effect via the matching process of unemployed individuals to available job vacancies. </s><s n="s3.5;p2.6">Furthermore, bargaining coordination, employment protection and benefit replacement ratios are significantly affecting labour costs and consequently wages. </s><s n="s4.5;p2.6">Nunziata finds that bargaining coordination is significantly decreasing wages, while employment protection and benefit replacement ratios have a significantly positive relationship to wages. </s><s n="s5.5;p2.6">Even so, it seems hard to theoretically rationalise that employment protection and benefit replacement ratios can affect prices. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0077g-ftnote.005"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Nunziata (2001). </s></p></note><p n="p3.6"><s n="s1.5;p3.6">Thus far the only article combining mark-up analysis with wage bargaining is an article by Sen and Dutt<ref target="BAWE_0077g-ftnote.006"/>. </s><s n="s2.5;p3.6">Nonetheless, the article has merely theoretically appraisal of the issue and does not present any empirical testing of the presented theory. </s><s n="s3.5;p3.6">The paper shows that the size of the mark-up does not merely depend on the product market factors, but also on the bargaining strength of the unions. </s><s n="s4.5;p3.6">Moreover, their model shows that changes in aggregate demand does not affect the money wage, real wage, price, and the mark-up. </s><s n="s5.5;p3.6">Variations in aggregate demand only change the output of firms, thus Sen and Dutt's model can be seen as a model that provides a theory of the stickiness of prices and wages. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0077g-ftnote.006"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Sen and Dutt (1995). </s></p></note><p n="p4.6"><s n="s1.6;p4.6">Ashworth et al<ref target="BAWE_0077g-ftnote.007"/> and Asteriou et al<ref target="BAWE_0077g-ftnote.008"/> both specify and estimate price equations in OECD countries, but none of the papers include elements of wage-setting coordination in their analysis. </s><s n="s2.6;p4.6">Yet, their analysis is interesting from the price determination point of view. </s><s n="s3.6;p4.6">Ashworth estimates a non-stationary panel data set for 13 OECD countries. </s><s n="s4.6;p4.6">Their findings suggest a pro-cyclical mark-up, i.e. firms charge higher prices in booms. </s><s n="s5.6;p4.6">As a proxy for intermediate goods the authors use the oil price, and estimate it to be significant and positive. </s><s n="s6.6;p4.6">The estimation puts a roughly equal weight on unit labour costs and import prices in the price equation, which correspond relatively good to other empirical studies. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0077g-ftnote.007"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ashworth et al (2003). </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0077g-ftnote.008"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Asteriou et al (2002). </s></p></note><p n="p5.6"><s n="s1.4;p5.6">Furthermore, Asteriou estimates manufacturing mark-up equations for 15 OECD countries introducing uncertainty as a new element of attention. </s><s n="s2.4;p5.6">Uncertainty is estimated to lower margins. </s><s n="s3.4;p5.6">The long-run relationships can be modelled as a variable mark-up driven by productivity, labour costs, technical progress, competitors' prices, deviations from trend output and uncertainty. </s><s n="s4.4;p5.6">Albeit these last two papers do not explicitly include coordination in their analysis, I still get an insight to the magnitudes of the coefficients in the price equation that is valuable as guidelines for my own estimation. </s></p><p n="p6.6"><s n="s1.5;p6.6">Ashworth find evidence for a pro-cyclical mark-up in his paper. </s><s n="s2.5;p6.6">Nevertheless, there is, interestingly enough, empirical support for both pro-cyclical and counter-cyclical mark-up in the literature. </s><s n="s3.5;p6.6">Some examples of counter-cyclical mark-up are Bils<ref target="BAWE_0077g-ftnote.009"/> and later Ireland<ref target="BAWE_0077g-ftnote.010"/> who argue that firms utilise booms and excess demand to capture new customers, thus lowering the mark-up during booms, which clearly implies a counter-cyclical mark-up. </s><s n="s4.5;p6.6">Some researchers, <hi rend="italic">inter alia</hi> Rotemberg et al<ref target="BAWE_0077g-ftnote.011"/>, advocate that collusion is less likely in booms, while a last case is Chevalier<ref target="BAWE_0077g-ftnote.012"/> who presents a model where imperfections in the capital markets result in a counter-cyclical mark-up. </s><s n="s5.5;p6.6">Chevalier contends that liquidity constrained firms are induced to increase mark-ups during recessions as a source of financing. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0077g-ftnote.009"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Bils (1989). </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0077g-ftnote.010"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ireland (1998). </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0077g-ftnote.011"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Rotemberg et al (1986) and Rotemberg et al (1995). </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0077g-ftnote.012"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Chevalier et al (1996). </s></p></note></div1></body><back><div1 type="bibliography"><head rend="bold">References</head><p>Ashworth P, Byrne JP (2003). <hi rend="italic">Some international evidence on price determination: a non-stationary panel approach</hi>. Economic Modelling; 20: 809-38.</p><p>Asteriou D, Lukacs P, Pain N, Price S (2002). <hi rend="italic">Manufacturing price determination in OECD countries; mark-ups, demand and uncertainty in a dynamic heterogeneous panel</hi>. City University, Department of Economics Discussion Paper no. 90.</p><p>Bils M (1989). <hi rend="italic">Pricing in a customer market</hi>. Quarterly Journal of Economics; 104: 699-718.</p><p>Chevalier JA, Scharfstein DS (1996). <hi rend="italic">Capital market imperfections and countercyclical markups: theory and evidence</hi>. American Economic Review; 86: 703-25.</p><p>Clements MP, Sensier M (2003). <hi rend="italic">Asymmetric output-gap effects in Phillips curve and mark-up pricing models: Evidence for the US and the UK</hi>. Scottish Journal of Political Economy; 50: 359-74.</p><p>Dornbusch R (1992). <hi rend="italic">Purchasing power parity</hi>. In: Newman P et al, ed: The New Palgrave Dictionary of Economics. Pp. 236-44. Stockton Press, New York.</p><p>Ireland P (1998). <hi rend="italic">Customer flows, countercyclical markups and the output effects of technology shocks</hi>. Journal of Macroeconomics; 20: 649-64.</p><p>Kalecki M (1943). <hi rend="italic">Theory of economic dynamics</hi>. George Allen and Unwin, London.</p><p>Kalecki M (1971). <hi rend="italic">Selected essays on the dynamics of the capitalist economy</hi>. Cambridge University Press.</p><p>Martin C (1997). <hi rend="italic">Price formation in an open economy: Theory and evidence for the United Kingdom, 1951-1991</hi>. The economic Journal; 107: 1391-1404.</p><p>Nunziata L (2001). <hi rend="italic">Institutions and Wage Determination: A Multi-Country Approach</hi>. Nuffield College Working Papers in Economics, no. 29. Internet: <seg type="URL" n="www.nuff.ox.ac.uk/users/nunziata/"/>.</p><p>Rotemberg JJ, Saloner G (1986). <hi rend="italic">A supergame-theoretic model of price wars during booms</hi>. American Economic Review; 76: 390-407.</p><p>Rotemberg JJ, Woodford M (1995). <hi rend="italic">Dynamic general equilibrium models with imperfectly competitive product markets</hi>. Frontiers of Business Cycle Research, editor Cooley TF. PP 243-93. Princeton University Press.</p><p>Sen A, Dutt AK (1995). <hi rend="italic">Wage bargaining, imperfect competition and the mark-up: Optimizing microfoundations</hi>. Economics Letters; 48: 15-20.</p></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
