<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_0077f" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>A Cross-sectional Analysis of Economic Growth Theory</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">The document has a title page which contains:
document title
title part</note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">deleted: footer: page numbers
appendix: data tables, charts and graphs</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">2</p><p n="date">2005-05</p><p n="module title">Econometrics</p><p n="module code">EC226</p><p n="genre family">Critique</p><p n="discipline">Economics</p><p n="disciplinary group">SS</p><p n="grade">D</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">2728</p><p n="number of s-units">114</p><p n="number of p">25</p><p n="number of tables">3</p><p n="number of figures">3</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">7</p><p n="number of lists">0</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">0</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">23.9</p><p n="average s-units per p">4.6</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">m</p><p n="year of birth">1981</p><p n="first language">Norwegian</p><p n="education">OSA</p><p n="course">Economics</p><p n="student ID">0077</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><docTitle><titlePart>a Cross-sectional analysis of Economic growth theory</titlePart></docTitle><titlePart/><titlePart>EC226 ECONOMETRICS 1</titlePart><titlePart>03 <hi rend="sup">RD</hi> May 2005 - Assignment 2</titlePart><titlePart>STUDENT NUMBER: <name type="student ID"/> IN COLLABORATION WITH:<name type="student ID"/></titlePart></titlePage><div1 type="toc" n="1"><p/></div1></front><body><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Introduction</head><p n="p1.25"><s n="s1.4;p1.25">Understanding economic growth has been central to many great economists through time. </s><s n="s2.4;p1.25">What factors determines economic growth has been fundamental particularly in development economics, a subject dating back to the Second World War. </s><s n="s3.4;p1.25">However, after been a vastly researched topic from the mid 1950s to the late 1960s, the surprising loss of interest in the field until the late 1980s was unfortunate. </s><s n="s4.4;p1.25">Nevertheless, since then considerable research has been undertaken and some interesting results have emerged in the literature. </s></p><p n="p2.25"><s n="s1.5;p2.25">In this paper I will present some of these results and different theories, including an interpretation of the different econometric tools used to test for the relevant economic theories. </s><s n="s2.5;p2.25">My starting hypothesis is that initial GDP is significant in explaining economic growth, that is to say that a poor country grows faster than a rich and well developed country. </s><s n="s3.5;p2.25">This is consistent with Solow's theory of convergence; that poor countries will exhibit a higher growth rate and eventually catch up with the richer countries. </s><s n="s4.5;p2.25">However, I will not use the original Solow model as a reference in this paper, but rather the augmented version of the model as found in Mankiw, Romer and Weil's paper on the empirics of economic growth<ref target="BAWE_0077f-ftnote.001"/>. </s><s n="s5.5;p2.25">This model seeks to explain economic growth by including human capital in the original Solow model. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0077f-ftnote.001"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Mankiwal. 1992. </s></p></note><p n="p3.25"><s n="s1.4;p3.25">To test the hypothesis that initial GDP is negatively related to economic growth, thus testing the validity of Solow's proposal of convergence, I will use a cross-sectional sample of 54 countries from 1994-2000<ref target="BAWE_0077f-ftnote.002"/>. </s><s n="s2.4;p3.25">The countries are a chosen sample of different countries throughout the world, although the selection is limited by the availability of data. </s><s n="s3.4;p3.25">The data for the dependent variable Real GDP growth per capita and the explanatory variables Investment and Initial GDP is retrieved from the Penn World Tables<ref target="BAWE_0077f-ftnote.003"/>. </s><s n="s4.4;p3.25">Furthermore, as a proxy for human capital investment we use data for secondary school enrolment, which is retrieved from the World Bank Online Databases<ref target="BAWE_0077f-ftnote.004"/>. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0077f-ftnote.002"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">The list of countries included in the sample is provided in the Appendix. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0077f-ftnote.003"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Alan Heston, Robert Summers and Bettina Aten, Penn World Table Version 6.1, Center for International Comparisons at the University of Pennsylvania (CICUP), October 2002. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0077f-ftnote.004"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1"><seg type="URL" n="http://www.worldbank.org/data/onlinedatabases/onlinedatabases.html"/> </s></p></note></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Literature Review</head><p n="p4.25"><s n="s1.4;p4.25">The starting point for modern economic growth theory is the immortal article of Ramsey<ref target="BAWE_0077f-ftnote.005"/>, a paper that was several decades ahead of its time. </s><s n="s2.4;p4.25">However, disregarding a few attempts to integrate Keynesian analysis with elements of economic growth<ref target="BAWE_0077f-ftnote.006"/>, the next and more important contributions were those of Solow and Swan<ref target="BAWE_0077f-ftnote.007"/>. </s><s n="s3.4;p4.25">In his classic 1956 article "A Contribution to the Theory of Economic Growth" in the Quarterly Journal of Economics<ref target="BAWE_0077f-ftnote.008"/> Solow proposed that economic growth can be explained by a standard neoclassical production function with decreasing returns to capital and labour. </s><s n="s4.4;p4.25">The augmented Solow model includes human capital (<hi rend="italic">H</hi>) and the Cobb-Douglas production function illustrated below is the foundation of the model: </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0077f-ftnote.005"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ramsey 1928. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0077f-ftnote.006"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">For example Harrod 1939 and Domar 1946. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0077f-ftnote.007"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Solow 1956 and Swan 1956. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0077f-ftnote.008"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Solow 1956. </s></p></note><p n="p5.25"><s n="s1.1;p5.25"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0077f-form.001"/> </s></p><p n="p6.25"><s n="s1.3;p6.25">K represents capital, L represents labour, and Y represents output while A is a residual explaining the level of technology. </s><s n="s2.3;p6.25">One problem with the Solow model is consequently that it assumes that every country exhibit the same production function. </s><s n="s3.3;p6.25">It seems that the production function works as a good estimation of the US and other industrialised countries, but in general, countries do seem to operate on different production functions. <ref target="BAWE_0077f-ftnote.009"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0077f-ftnote.009"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Gartner 2003. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">P224. </s></p></note><figure id="BAWE_0077f-fig.001"><head rend="bold">Graph 1: The Cobb-Douglas Production Function </head></figure><p n="p7.25"><s n="s1.19;p7.25">A prediction from this model is conditional convergence. </s><s n="s2.19;p7.25">The lower the starting level of GDP (the <hi rend="italic">InitialGDP</hi> variable included in our regression), relative to the steady-state position, the faster the growth rate. </s><s n="s3.19;p7.25">This property of the Solow-model is derived directly from the assumption of diminishing returns to capital; economies that have less capital per worker tend to have higher rates of return and higher growth rates. </s><s n="s4.19;p7.25">The conditional convergence hypothesis says that per capita incomes of countries that are identical in their structural characteristics converge to one another independently of their initial conditions (<hi rend="italic">InitialGDP</hi>). </s><s n="s5.19;p7.25">Supporting evidence is found in several articles<ref target="BAWE_0077f-ftnote.010"/>. </s><s n="s6.19;p7.25">It is worth mentioning, however, that this supporting evidence is to a large extent consistent with the club convergence hypothesis as well. </s><s n="s7.19;p7.25">The club convergence hypothesis requires that the initial conditions are similar too, whereas absolute convergence is the case where countries converge to one another independently of both initial conditions and structural characteristics. </s><s n="s8.19;p7.25">Barro and Sala-i-Martin studied the behaviour of US states since 1880, regions of Japan since 1930 and eight European countries since 1950<ref target="BAWE_0077f-ftnote.011"/>. </s><s n="s9.19;p7.25">Regressions showed a significant negative correlation between growth rates and initial GDP. This result is consistent with the Solow model. </s><s n="s10.19;p7.25">The speed of the convergence across the data sets is also surprisingly similar. </s><s n="s11.19;p7.25">The convergence coefficient is around 2-3 percent per year, which implies that it takes 25-35 years to eliminate one-half of an initial gap in per capita incomes. </s><s n="s12.19;p7.25">This evidence is consistent with the Solow model with a capital share (α) of around three-quarters<ref target="BAWE_0077f-ftnote.012"/>. </s><s n="s13.19;p7.25">It is important to keep in mind that the study is done on countries with relative similar structural characteristics. </s><s n="s14.19;p7.25">One of the first studies on convergence, by Baumol, included a sample of 16 industrialised countries and found evidence of perfect convergence<ref target="BAWE_0077f-ftnote.013"/>. </s><s n="s15.19;p7.25">However, De Long revised the regression properties due to what he argued was bias and measurement errors and found that there exists practically no convergence<ref target="BAWE_0077f-ftnote.014"/>. </s><s n="s16.19;p7.25">Many cross-sectional studies provide evidence of conditional convergence, but by closer examination one still finds a growing divergence between the rich and poor countries in the world. </s><s n="s17.19;p7.25">An example of this is provided by Kremer who discovered absolute divergence in the majority of developing economies<ref target="BAWE_0077f-ftnote.015"/>. </s><s n="s18.19;p7.25">Romer also shows that the average growth rate of the richest countries by far exceeds the poorest ones<ref target="BAWE_0077f-ftnote.016"/>. </s><s n="s19.19;p7.25">Mankiw<ref target="BAWE_0077f-ftnote.017"/> finds no evidence of convergence in his cross-sectional study of 102 countries (Graph 2, left), however, when estimating a regression for the OECD countries convergence as indicated by the Solow model is apparent: </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0077f-ftnote.010"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Barro 1991, Mankiw et al 1992, Sala-i-Martin 1996. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0077f-ftnote.011"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Barro et al 1991. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0077f-ftnote.012"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Barro et al 1991. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0077f-ftnote.013"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Baumol 1986. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0077f-ftnote.014"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">De Long 1988. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0077f-ftnote.015"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Kremer 1993. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0077f-ftnote.016"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Romer 1986. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0077f-ftnote.017"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Mankiw 2000. </s></p></note><figure id="BAWE_0077f-fig.002"><head rend="bold">Graph 2: Initial GDP and Growth - Convergence</head></figure><p n="p8.25"><s n="s1.4;p8.25">To test for the empirics of economic growth theory, I have chosen - as several others<ref target="BAWE_0077f-ftnote.018"/> - to use a cross-sectional sample of countries over a time period of seven years from 1994 to 2000. </s><s n="s2.4;p8.25">When testing for the determinants of economic growth I have estimated a regression of the averaged growth rates for real GDP per capita (<hi rend="italic">RealGDPGrowth</hi>) on the initial GDP value for 1994 (<hi rend="italic">InitialGDP</hi>), the averaged investment shares of GDP (<hi rend="italic">Investment</hi>) and the averaged value of secondary school enrolment over the seven years (<hi rend="italic">HumanCapital</hi>). </s><s n="s3.4;p8.25">I have chosen to estimate my regression using secondary school enrolment as a proxy for human capital investment, and since this is a flow variable I can use the average value over the chosen time period. </s><s n="s4.4;p8.25">In the literature there are examples of other proxies for human capital such as literacy rates, school expenditure and so forth; however, for the chosen countries in our sample we could only find suitable data for secondary school enrolment. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0077f-ftnote.018"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">For example Barro 1991. </s></p></note></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">An analysis of the descriptive statistics</head><p n="p9.25"><s n="s1.13;p9.25">The data in the 54 country big sample was retrieved from the Penn World Tables<ref target="BAWE_0077f-ftnote.019"/>. </s><s n="s2.13;p9.25">The time period was chosen to eliminate any business cycle influences one might get if testing for a more limited time period. </s><s n="s3.13;p9.25">However, in order to be able to retrieve data for the different variables it was also necessary to limit both the countries included in the sample and the time period chosen. </s><s n="s4.13;p9.25">The data for all the variables for the entire sample is included in the appendix at the end of this paper. </s><s n="s5.13;p9.25">As can be seen from plotting the residuals (Graph A5 in the appendix), I fail the normality test due to an outlier (Ireland). </s><s n="s6.13;p9.25">However, this is not a problem as I can apply the Central Limit Theorem having more than 30 observations in my sample. </s><s n="s7.13;p9.25">I have also tried to correct for the outlier by including an impulse dummy variable (as described in the next section). </s><s n="s8.13;p9.25">The mean real GDP per capita growth rate is 2.22 %, although the maximum growth rate is an extreme 8.48 % (Ireland). </s><s n="s9.13;p9.25">The standard deviation of the real GDP growth is relatively large (1.85), as the range of observations go from -1.87 to 8.48 %. </s><s n="s10.13;p9.25">Investment share of GDP has an average of around 19 % and is fairly equally distributed from 5-30 % over the sample range. </s><s n="s11.13;p9.25">Initial GDP also features a quite large standard deviation of 8081, giving the point estimate of the mean fairly little certainty. </s><s n="s12.13;p9.25">The distribution of school enrolment is (negatively) skewed, with most countries in the top quartile between 75 and 100 % and a mean of approximately 75 %. </s><s n="s13.13;p9.25">Initial GDP measured in 1994 has an average of just above $ 12 000 per capita and the distribution is a bit clustered around $ 5000 and between $ 18 000 and $ 24 000. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0077f-ftnote.019"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Alan Heston, Robert Summers and Bettina Aten, Penn World Table Version 6.1, Center for International Comparisons at the University of Pennsylvania (CICUP), October 2002. </s></p></note><table id="BAWE_0077f-tab.001"><head rend="bold">Table 1: Summary of descriptive statistics</head><row><cell/></row></table></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Analysis of the estimated equation and its policy implications</head><p n="p10.25"><s n="s1.2;p10.25">The variables included in my datasets were, after sorting them alphabetically and calculating averages, imported to Eviews. </s><s n="s2.2;p10.25">The estimated equation is as follows: </s></p><p n="p11.25"><s n="s1.1;p11.25"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0077f-form.002"/> </s></p><p n="p12.25"><s n="s1.1;p12.25"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0077f-form.003"/> </s></p><p n="p13.25"><s n="s1.1;p13.25"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0077f-form.004"/> </s></p><p n="p14.25"><s n="s1.1;p14.25">When regressing the averaged real GDP growth per capita over the seven years from 1994-2000 on the initial level of income in 1994, the average level of investment share of GDP and the average rate of secondary school enrolment I obtained the following estimates: </s></p><table id="BAWE_0077f-tab.002"><head rend="bold">Table 2: Regression output on the initial estimated equation</head><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p15.25"><s n="s1.5;p15.25">From the regression output I obtain some interesting results. </s><s n="s2.5;p15.25">According to growth theory the coefficient on investment (<formula notation="" id="BAWE_0077f-form.005"/>) ought to be positive, which in fact it is in my regression. </s><s n="s3.5;p15.25">It is also significant at a significance level of 5 % (which I will use for the rest of this paper). <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0077f-form.006"/>, the coefficient on secondary school enrolment, my proxy for human capital investment, is also positive and significant consistent with economic theory. </s><s n="s4.5;p15.25">In accordance with Solow's convergence theory there is signs of absolute convergence with a negative, although insignificant, coefficient (<formula notation="" id="BAWE_0077f-form.007"/>) on <hi rend="italic">InitialGDP.</hi> </s><s n="s5.5;p15.25">The intercept C would in principle imply that if all my explanatory variables were zero, there would be a negative growth rate of real GDP of around 2 %; however, I would say that it is an unrealistic interpretation in this particular case. </s></p><p n="p16.25"><s n="s1.2;p16.25">To test the validity of my estimated equation, I performed a series of diagnostic tests. </s><s n="s2.2;p16.25">The tests are summarised in Table 3 below: </s></p><table id="BAWE_0077f-tab.003"><head rend="bold">Table 3: Diagnostic Tests of the estimated equation</head><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p17.25"><s n="s1.8;p17.25">The estimated equation passes the first three diagnostic tests I have performed<ref target="BAWE_0077f-ftnote.020"/>. </s><s n="s2.8;p17.25">There is no heteroscedasticity or systematic information in the errors. </s><s n="s3.8;p17.25">There is, however, non-normality in the residuals probably caused by an outlier as mentioned before. </s><s n="s4.8;p17.25">When including an impulse dummy variable to correct for the outlier<ref target="BAWE_0077f-ftnote.021"/> I pass the normality test as shown in Graph A7 in the Appendix. </s><s n="s5.8;p17.25">However, one can also apply the Central Limit Theorem (CLT) to the initially estimated equation since the sample size is above 30. </s><s n="s6.8;p17.25">The F-statistics from the regression output illustrates that the three explanatory variables are jointly significant in explaining growth in real GDP per capita. </s><s n="s7.8;p17.25">I have plotted the actual and fitted values in Graph A6, and it is evident that the estimated equation gives a relatively good fit of the actual values. </s><s n="s8.8;p17.25">The R <hi rend="sup">2</hi> is 0.34, which is perceived to be a relatively good fit for cross-sectional data analysis. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0077f-ftnote.020"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">The exact F-statistics and test outputs are given in the Appendix. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0077f-ftnote.021"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">The corresponding regression output is given in Table A6 in the Appendix. </s></p></note><figure id="BAWE_0077f-fig.003"><head rend="bold">Graph 3: Initial GDP and Growth in my dataset:</head></figure><p n="p18.25"><s n="s1.6;p18.25">Since the coefficient for <hi rend="italic">InitialGDP</hi> was insignificant (although a fairly strong positive relationship as illustrated in Graph 3 above), I tried to estimate my equation to test for conditional convergence. </s><s n="s2.6;p18.25">To do so one has to identify the countries with the same structural characteristics. </s><s n="s3.6;p18.25">The conditional convergence hypothesis is independent of initial income, so to test for the conditional convergence hypothesis I included only the OECD countries that was in the original sample. </s><s n="s4.6;p18.25">This is a commonly used identification of countries with similar structural characteristics<ref target="BAWE_0077f-ftnote.022"/>. </s><s n="s5.6;p18.25">I did unfortunately not obtain any significant coefficient for <hi rend="italic">InitialGDP</hi> in the associated regression output<ref target="BAWE_0077f-ftnote.023"/>. </s><s n="s6.6;p18.25">Accordingly, I cannot support the hypothesis of conditional convergence consistent with Solow's model for my dataset. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0077f-ftnote.022"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">As used in for example Nonnemann et al (1996). </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0077f-ftnote.023"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">The corresponding regression output is found in Table A2 in the Appendix. </s></p></note><p n="p19.25"><s n="s1.4;p19.25">To test for club convergence, I created a dummy variable for rich countries with an initial income of over $ 18 000 in the sample with only the OECD countries (28 countries<ref target="BAWE_0077f-ftnote.024"/>). </s><s n="s2.4;p19.25">Then both of the criteria for club convergence - that initial income and structural characteristics are the same for the included countries - were met. </s><s n="s3.4;p19.25">The associated regression output shows that the coefficient is negative and, even though it still is insignificant, it is much closer to being significant<ref target="BAWE_0077f-ftnote.025"/>. </s><s n="s4.4;p19.25">Nevertheless, even though the sign of the coefficient is coherent with economic theory, there is no significant evidence of club convergence in my dataset. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0077f-ftnote.024"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">The countries are listed in the Appendix in Table A4. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0077f-ftnote.025"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">The corresponding regression output is found in Table A3 in the Appendix. </s></p></note><p n="p20.25"><s n="s1.10;p20.25">I therefore support my originally estimated equation, where I obtain significant coefficient for both <hi rend="italic">Investment</hi> and <hi rend="italic">HumanCapital</hi>. </s><s n="s2.10;p20.25">This broadly supports the theoretical work done in this field as elaborated on in Section 2. </s><s n="s3.10;p20.25">That this empirical study of a variety of countries from all over the world confirm that a high investment share of GDP is consistent with a high growth rate of GDP per capita has several important policy implications. </s><s n="s4.10;p20.25">Firstly, keeping the interest rate at a reasonably low level will encourage investment and consequently lead to economic growth as established by our regression analysis. </s><s n="s5.10;p20.25">Moreover, other and perhaps more incentive-oriented policies should be implemented to encourage investment so as to contribute to economic growth. </s><s n="s6.10;p20.25">One should also encourage Foreign Direct Investment (FDI) in developing countries to make them grow at a higher rate than they are currently experiencing. </s><s n="s7.10;p20.25">Had my null hypothesis of convergence been supported, this would also imply that the developing countries could have 'caught up' with the richer and developed countries of the world. </s><s n="s8.10;p20.25">The coefficient of a slope dummy variable for investment shows the effect of one percentage-point more investment in poor countries relatively to the rich countries of the sample<ref target="BAWE_0077f-ftnote.026"/>. </s><s n="s9.10;p20.25">The regression output shows that the coefficient for the slope dummy is significantly positive. </s><s n="s10.10;p20.25">This confirms that investment is marginally more effective in poor countries compared to rich countries, thus resources should be allocated to investment in developing countries where they could be utilised more efficiently. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0077f-ftnote.026"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">The corresponding regression output is found in Table A5 in the Appendix </s></p></note><p n="p21.25"><s n="s1.5;p21.25"><hi rend="italic">HumanCapital</hi> is significantly positive for the estimated equation for the whole sample of countries. </s><s n="s2.5;p21.25">This is also consistent with economic theory, and has apparent implications. </s><s n="s3.5;p21.25">One should always seek to maximise human capital investment, as this type of investment not only bears a higher rate of return because it cannot be divested<ref target="BAWE_0077f-ftnote.027"/>, but also since investing in the knowledge of the workforce is increasing productivity. </s><s n="s4.5;p21.25">It may also increase the welfare and well-being of the people in an economy, which may also contribute to increased efficiency and economic growth. </s><s n="s5.5;p21.25">The results in this paper that human capital is a significant determinant of economic growth for the world as a whole but not in the OECD countries specifically are consistent with what other authors have found previously<ref target="BAWE_0077f-ftnote.028"/>. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0077f-ftnote.027"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Becker 1964. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0077f-ftnote.028"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Mankiw et al 1992. </s></p></note></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Conclusion</head><p n="p22.25"><s n="s1.4;p22.25">The objective of this paper was to empirically test the theoretical growth models and specifically the determinants of economic growth. </s><s n="s2.4;p22.25">I chose the augmented Solow model as a reference for determining the factors that affect economic growth, and included the explanatory variables <hi rend="italic">InitialGDP</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Investment</hi> and <hi rend="italic">HumanCapital</hi> (by using secondary school enrolment as a proxy) in my dataset. </s><s n="s3.4;p22.25">The sample included 54 countries from the whole world, and the time period chosen was from 1994 to 2000. </s><s n="s4.4;p22.25">Although it might have been interesting to extend the time span in my cross-sectional dataset, I presumably still avoid the effect of business cycles by choosing a time period of seven years. </s></p><p n="p23.25"><s n="s1.3;p23.25">For my estimated equation I obtained significant and positive coefficients for both human capital investment and investment, implying that these determinants of economic growth should be taken into account in policy contemplations. </s><s n="s2.3;p23.25">However, I did not find any significant evidence for my null hypothesis of convergence in the sample, as the coefficient on initial GDP was negative but not significant. </s><s n="s3.3;p23.25">Even when testing for conditional and club convergence with only the OECD countries included in the estimated equation there was no empirical support of economic convergence theory. </s></p><p n="p24.25"><s n="s1.3;p24.25">When including a slope dummy variable in my estimated equation I obtained an interesting feature. </s><s n="s2.3;p24.25">With my cross-sectional dataset there was significant evidence that one percentage-point more investment in poor countries is more efficient than in rich countries, that is, it gives a higher rate of growth of real GDP per capita. </s><s n="s3.3;p24.25">The supportive evidence of human capital investment as an important determinant of economic growth has also central policy implications as discussed earlier. </s></p><p n="p25.25"><s n="s1.1;p25.25">To summarise, the empirical evidence in this paper suggests that the explanatory variables <hi rend="italic">Investment</hi>, <hi rend="italic">HumanCapital</hi> and <hi rend="italic">InitialGDP</hi> is jointly significant in determining economic growth as measured by the growth rate of real GDP per capita. </s></p></div1></body><back><div1 type="bibliography"><head rend="bold">References</head><p>Alan Heston, Robert Summers and Bettina Aten, Penn World Table Version 6.1, Center for International Comparisons at the University of Pennsylvania (CICUP), October 2002. </p><p>Barro RJ. <hi rend="italic">Economic Growth in a Cross Section of Countries</hi>. The Quarterly Journal of Economics; 106: 407-443.</p><p>Barro RJ, Sala-I-Martin XX, Blanchard OJ, Hall RE. <hi rend="italic">Convergence Across States and Regions</hi>. Brookings Papers on Economic Activity; 1991: 107-82.</p><p>Baumol W. 1986. <hi rend="italic">Productivity growth, convergence, and welfare: Comment</hi>. American Economic Review; 76: 1071-85.</p><p>Becker G. <hi rend="italic">Human Capital: A Theoretical and Empirical Analysis with Special Reference to Education</hi>. New York: National Bureau of Economic Research, 1964.</p><p>De Long JB<hi rend="italic">. Productivity growth, convergence, and welfare: Comment</hi>. American Economic Review; 78: 1138-54.</p><p>Domar ED. <hi rend="italic">Capital Expansion, Rate of Growth, and Employment</hi>. Econometrica; 14: 137-147.</p><p>Gärtner M. <hi rend="italic">Macroeconomics.</hi> Prentice-Hall 2003.</p><p>Harrod RF. <hi rend="italic">An Essay in Dynamic Theory</hi>. The Economic Journal; 49: 14-33.</p><p><seg type="URL" n="http://www.worldbank.org/data/onlinedatabases/onlinedatabases.html"/>. Retrieved on the 27th of april 2005.</p><p>Kremer, Michael. <hi rend="italic">O-ring Theory of Economic Development.</hi> The Quarterly Journal of Economics; 108: 551-75.</p><p>Mankiw NG, Romer D, Weil DN. <hi rend="italic">A contribution to the empirics of economic growth</hi>. The Quarterly Journal of Economics; 107: 407-37.</p><p>Mankiw NG. <hi rend="italic">Macroeconomics</hi>. 4<hi rend="sup">th</hi> edition. Worth Publishers 2000.</p><p>Nonnemann E, Vanhoudt P. <hi rend="italic">A further augmentation of the Solow model and the empirics of economic growth for oecd countries</hi>. The Quarterly Journal of Economics; 111: 943-53.</p><p>Ramsey FP. <hi rend="italic">A Mathematical Theory of Saving</hi>. The Economic Journal; 38: 543-59.</p><p>Sala-i-Martin XX. <hi rend="italic">The Classical Approach to Convergence Analysis</hi>. The Economic Journal; 106: 1019-36.</p><p>Solow RM<hi rend="italic">. A contribution to the Theory of Economic Growth</hi>. The Quarterly Journal of Economic; 70: 65-94.</p><p>Swan AW<hi rend="italic">. Time-Study and Statistics</hi>. OR; 7: 110-39.</p></div1><div1 type="appendix"><head rend="bold">Appendix</head><p/></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
