<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_0079b" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>The time consistency problem in Monetary Policy: How an independent Central Bank helps to reduce it</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">The document has a title page which contains:
document title
title part
abstract</note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">deleted: page numbers
footnotes converted to endnotes</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">4</p><p n="date">2004-05</p><p n="module title">Macroeconomics</p><p n="module code">EC9012</p><p n="genre family">Essay</p><p n="discipline">Economics</p><p n="disciplinary group">SS</p><p n="grade">M</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">6523</p><p n="number of s-units">279</p><p n="number of p">142</p><p n="number of tables">1</p><p n="number of figures">10</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">25</p><p n="number of lists">0</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">21</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">23.4</p><p n="average s-units per p">2.0</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">m</p><p n="year of birth">1976</p><p n="first language">Spanish</p><p n="education">OSA</p><p n="course">Economic Analysis and Policy</p><p n="student ID">0079</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><docTitle><titlePart><hi rend="bold">The time consistency problem in Monetary Policy: How an independent Central Bank</hi><hi rend="bold"> helps to reduce it</hi></titlePart></docTitle></titlePage><div1 type="abstract"><head>Abstract</head><p>The literature on monetary economics has devoted a long effort to explaining why economies may end up with positive inflation rates without any positive effect on output. After the seminal contributions of Kydland and Prescott (1977) and Barro and Gordon (1983a) the explanation has been focused on the time consistency problem (TCP) that the policymaker suffers when conducting monetary policy: the optimal inflation rate from his viewpoint is different before and after the public sets the expected inflation, even though no relevant change in the set of information occurs. The paper explains that delegating monetary policy to an independent Central Bank helps to reduce the TCP. Furthermore, the principal contribution of the essay is to show that the mechanism operates by increasing the marginal cost that the policymaker faces for generating inflation when compared to the pure discretionary case. However, addressed here is that the TCP is not fully solved unless the policymaker's aversion to inflation tends to infinite, which is not optimal since this generates a high stabilisation bias. Some empirical evidence is revised which suggests that when CBs are more independent the average inflation rate is reduced, the UK case after May 1997 being particularly analysed.</p></div1><titlePage><titlePart>Essay submitted for the module EC901 - Macroeconomics</titlePart><titlePart><name type="student name"/>x MSc in Economic Analysis and Policy Department of Economics The University of <name type="university"/><hi rend="underlined"><name type="other"/>@<name type="university"/>.ac.uk</hi></titlePart></titlePage><div1 type="toc" n="3"><head>Table of Contents</head><p/></div1></front><body><div1 type="section"><head>Introduction</head><p n="p1.142"><s n="s1.1;p1.142">A considerable effort has been made in economics in the last thirty years with the aim of answering important issues regarding monetary policy: why an economy ends up with positive inflation rates without any remarkable positive effect on output, and why it seems difficult to achieve a final outcome with zero inflation and, at least, the same output level. </s></p><p n="p2.142"><s n="s1.2;p2.142">To answer these questions the seminal papers by Kydland and Prescott (1977) and Barro and Gordon (1983a) (henceforth KP and BG, respectively) first developed an analytical framework based on the so-called time consistency problem (TCP). </s><s n="s2.2;p2.142">The policymaker faces a trade-off between unexpected inflation and output but, as the public incorporates that, the expected inflation is set at a sufficiently high level so that the government's best response is to validate this inflation and the output is not affected. </s></p><p n="p3.142"><s n="s1.4;p3.142">Many suggestions have been assessed about how to improve this suboptimal equilibrium. </s><s n="s2.4;p3.142">For instance, KP and BG highlight that by imposing strict rules on the policymaker the TCP might be eliminated. </s><s n="s3.4;p3.142">Rogoff (1985), on the other hand, points out that by delegating monetary policy to a conservative central banker the TCP is reduced. </s><s n="s4.4;p3.142">Furthermore, this framework gives analytical support to the explanation about why modern Central Banks (CB) tends to be more independent <hi rend="sup">1</hi>. </s></p><p n="p4.142"><s n="s1.1;p4.142">The paper has two main objectives: firstly, address critically the TCP in monetary policy; secondly, answer why by delegating monetary policy to an independent CB it is possible to reduce the TCP. Some evidence is also introduced to overview to what extent independent CBs have reduced the TCP from an empirical perspective with emphasis on the UK experience after 1997. </s></p><p n="p5.142"><s n="s1.3;p5.142">One of the main conclusions of the paper is that the TCP seems to arise only under institutional setups where the policymaker faces some degree of discretion. </s><s n="s2.3;p5.142">In this case, the policymaker faces a marginal benefit of generating inflation which exceeds the marginal cost when the inflation rate is announced below the equilibrium level, which may induce him to not validate such announcement. </s><s n="s3.3;p5.142">Furthermore, developing this particular insight to the problem I show that delegating monetary policy to an independent CB helps to reduce the TCP since, for a given marginal benefit, the marginal cost of generating inflation rises compared with the pure discretionary case. </s></p><p n="p6.142"><s n="s1.4;p6.142">The remaining of the paper is organized as follows. </s><s n="s2.4;p6.142">Section I critically addresses the TCP in monetary policy. </s><s n="s3.4;p6.142">Section II assesses how an independent CB helps to reduce the TCP. Section III analyses some empirical evidence emphasising the UK case after 1997. </s><s n="s4.4;p6.142">Section IV presents concluding remarks. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head>I. The time consistency problem in Monetary Policy</head><p n="p7.142"><s n="s1.2;p7.142">The TCP <hi rend="sup">2</hi> in monetary policy arises when certain decisions (forming part of an optimal plan) at an initial date are no longer optimal at a later date, even though the information set between periods has not changed (Blanchard and Fisher 1989, p. 592). </s><s n="s2.2;p7.142">Kydland and Prescott (1977) (KP) first explained the TCP the monetary authority may suffer when conducting monetary policy. </s></p><p n="p8.142"><s n="s1.2;p8.142">In particular, KP points out this problem considering a situation where the policymaker optimises a social objective function in each period, in a world where agents do not have mechanical <hi rend="italic">ad hoc</hi> expectations upon past prices (op cit., p. 478). </s><s n="s2.2;p8.142">A further refinement of this original idea was introduced by Barro and Gordon (1983a) (BG) in an attempt to include a theory of expectations formation (op cit., p. 592). </s></p><p n="p9.142"><s n="s1.1;p9.142">In the remainder of the section, a detailed and formal explanation of the TCP in monetary policy mainly based on the BG contribution will be critically addressed. </s></p><div2><head>A. Formal explanation</head><p n="p10.142"><s n="s1.1;p10.142">The notation used for the explanation is borrowed from Walsh (2003) which, in turn, slightly modifies the BG notation. </s></p><p n="p11.142"><s n="s1.4;p11.142">As suggested previously, the TCP involves the incentives the policymaker faces when deciding economic policies, the way in which the public forms expectations and their respective interactions within a particular institutional arrangement. </s><s n="s2.4;p11.142">Worthwhile emphasising is the importance of the institutional framework in which the monetary authority determines economic policies (e.g., growth rate of money supply). </s><s n="s3.4;p11.142">As will be clear later in this section, the existence of the TCP implicitly requires that the policymaker have a certain degree of discretion when conducting monetary policy. </s><s n="s4.4;p11.142">Or, put another way, an institutional arrangement which does not commit the policymaker to strictly follow particular monetary policy rules. </s></p><p n="p12.142"><s n="s1.1;p12.142">For the sake of clarity a detailed analysis of the objectives and constraints that each of these actors faces when optimising will be assessed in detail. </s></p><div3><head>A-1. The social loss function</head><p n="p13.142"><s n="s1.1;p13.142">Following Walsh (2003), the monetary authority (hereafter the Central Bank, CB) faces an objective function which coincides with society's preferences given by <hi rend="sup">3</hi> </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p14.142"><s n="s1.1;p14.142">(1) <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0079b-form.001"/> </s></p><p n="p15.142"><s n="s1.1;p15.142">In this formulation <hi rend="italic">V</hi> represents a loss function, <hi rend="italic">y</hi> and <hi rend="italic">yn</hi> are the current and natural rate of output, λ measures how costly output deviations from the natural rate relative to inflation are <hi rend="sup">4</hi>, <hi rend="italic">k</hi> indicates the existence of economic imperfections in the economy <hi rend="sup">5</hi> and π reflects the inflation rate. </s></p><p n="p16.142"><s n="s1.2;p16.142">Such a specification differs from BG in considering the output rate rather than the unemployment rate. </s><s n="s2.2;p16.142">Without any loss of generality, I decided to introduce the Walsh (2003) approach considering that the CB probably cares about economic activity in general, rather than only the unemployment rate. </s></p><p n="p17.142"><s n="s1.2;p17.142">The fact that output and inflation are introduced in (1) in a quadratic form assumes that the CB will care about the variance of both variables. </s><s n="s2.2;p17.142">I suggest that the importance of considering the variance of output and inflation affecting society's expected loss arises since not only the level but also the volatility of the main macroeconomic variables may affect economic performance <hi rend="sup">6</hi>. </s></p><p n="p18.142"><s n="s1.3;p18.142">A particular issue is related to the existence of the parameter <hi rend="italic">k</hi>. </s><s n="s2.3;p18.142">It is commonly assumed that <hi rend="italic">k</hi> reflects distortions in the economy, such as unemployment compensations (BG 1983a, p. 593), monopolistic competition in the goods market or political pressures (Walsh 2003, p. 367). </s><s n="s3.3;p18.142">In fact, the existence of such distortions gives the CB an incentive to utilise monetary policy with the desire of obtaining an output rate above the natural rate <hi rend="sup">7</hi>. </s></p><p n="p19.142"><s n="s1.4;p19.142">On the other hand, an interesting question arises around the explanation of the costs of inflation. </s><s n="s2.4;p19.142">For instance, BG (1983b, p. 104) argued that society's costs of inflation are not well explained by economists but seem to be associated with costs inherent to changing prices (i.e., menu costs). </s><s n="s3.4;p19.142">A few years after this assertion and, perhaps, after a few high inflation processes, Alesina and Summers (1993, p. 152) claimed that the costs of inflation are associated with the rise in economic distortions, rent seeking activities and interest rates. </s><s n="s4.4;p19.142">Hereafter, I will identify the costs of inflation with the broad interpretation given by Alesina and Summers. </s></p></div3><div3><head>A-2. Aggregate supply</head><p n="p20.142"><s n="s1.1;p20.142">Since KP, most of the literature on the TCP in monetary policy assumes a simple expectations augmented Phillips curve which takes the form, </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p21.142"><s n="s1.1;p21.142">(2) <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0079b-form.002"/> </s></p><p n="p22.142"><s n="s1.3;p22.142">As usual, ε represents an aggregate productive shock with mean zero and variance σ<hi rend="sup">2</hi> while the parameter <hi rend="italic">a</hi> indicates the effect of unexpected inflation on current output. </s><s n="s2.3;p22.142">Following Rogoff (1985, p. 1172) <hi rend="italic">πe</hi> could be driven by the wage rate negotiated one period ago, taking into account the expected inflation for the current period. </s><s n="s3.3;p22.142">This fact is particularly important since it gives incentive to the CB to generate unexpected inflation to increase the current output level. </s></p></div3><div3><head>A-3. Public's expectations</head><p n="p23.142"><s n="s1.3;p23.142">It will be assumed that the public has rational expectations. </s><s n="s2.3;p23.142">Moreover, it means that the expected level <hi rend="italic">πe</hi> will be such that on average it anticipates the true level of inflation (i.e., <hi rend="italic">πe</hi>=<hi rend="italic">E</hi>(π)). </s><s n="s3.3;p23.142">Implicitly, the assumption is that the public selects the value of π<hi rend="sup">e</hi> minimising the following loss function, </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p24.142"><s n="s1.1;p24.142">(3) <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0079b-form.003"/> </s></p><p n="p25.142"><s n="s1.1;p25.142">Clearly, this function is minimised when <hi rend="italic">πe</hi> is set to equate π. </s></p></div3><div3><head>A-4. Central Bank control variable</head><p n="p26.142"><s n="s1.3;p26.142">Most of the literature which discuses the TCP assumes that the CB is able to directly control the inflation rate since any source of uncertainty is omitted (Romer, 2001 p. 480). </s><s n="s2.3;p26.142">However, strictly speaking, the CB does not directly control the inflation rate, but does so indirectly through, for instance, the money supply growth rate. </s><s n="s3.3;p26.142">For this reason, I will assume that the CB manages the growth rate of money supply <hi rend="italic">∆m</hi> which, in turn, has a one-to-one effect on inflation as reflected in (4)<hi rend="sup">8</hi>. </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p27.142"><s n="s1.1;p27.142">(4) <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0079b-form.004"/> </s></p><p n="p28.142"><s n="s1.1;p28.142">Since (4) will hold through the analysis it is worth pointing out that is the same to consider that the CB directly controls π instead of <hi rend="italic">∆m9.</hi> </s></p></div3></div2><div2><head>B. Determination of equilibrium under discretion</head><p n="p29.142"><s n="s1.3;p29.142">As previously indicated, the institutional arrangement under which the CB sets monetary policy is a central issue in the analysis. </s><s n="s2.3;p29.142">Furthermore, it seems plausible to argue that the absence of an institutional arrangement which commits the CB to strictly follow its policy announcements relies on the basis of the TCP. In such a case the CB will behave with discretion <hi rend="sup">10</hi>. </s><s n="s3.3;p29.142">Under these circumstances or, in terms of KP, when the CB applies optimal control theory to determine its decisions in each period, the TCP rises and the final equilibrium will be suboptimal. </s></p><p n="p30.142"><s n="s1.2;p30.142">An important issue to understanding the final equilibrium is the timing of events. </s><s n="s2.2;p30.142">The sequence of decisions is assumed as follows: first the public determines <hi rend="bold italic">if </hi>(i.e., nominal wages are determined), then the supply shock <hi rend="bold italic">s </hi>is observed and finally the CB decides <hi rend="bold italic">n </hi>(i.e.<hi rend="italic">, Am)</hi> (see Figure 1). </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0079b-fig.001"><head><hi rend="bold">Figure 1. Timing of events under discretion</hi> Source: Based on Eijffinger and Hoeberichts (1998).</head></figure><p n="p31.142"><s n="s1.2;p31.142">It is important to note that the CB decides <hi rend="bold italic">n </hi>after observing the supply shock <hi rend="bold italic">s.</hi> </s><s n="s2.2;p31.142">This characteristic gives the CB the possibility of determining <hi rend="bold italic">n </hi>(i.e., <hi rend="italic">Am)</hi> in a discretionary way to offset the possible effects of, on economic activity. </s></p><p n="p32.142"><s n="s1.1;p32.142">The CB minimises (1) considering the supply function stated in (2) and the relation between money supply growth and inflation addressed in (4) in a period-by-period basis as follows: </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p33.142"><s n="s1.1;p33.142">(5) <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0079b-form.005"/> </s></p><p n="p34.142"><s n="s1.1;p34.142">This minimisation process, after rearranging terms, gives the following first order condition: </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p35.142"><s n="s1.1;p35.142">(6) <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0079b-form.006"/> </s></p><p n="p36.142"><s n="s1.1;p36.142">Since the public sets the expected inflation according to the rational expectation hypothesis (i.e., <hi rend="italic">E(π)= πe</hi>) and they know that the CB will determine the current period's inflation according to (6), the expected level of inflation becomes, </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p37.142"><s n="s1.1;p37.142">(7) <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0079b-form.007"/> </s></p><p n="p38.142"><s n="s1.1;p38.142">Replacing (7) in (6) yields the current inflation level under discretion </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p39.142"><s n="s1.1;p39.142">(8) </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0079b-pic.001"/><p n="p40.142"><s n="s1.1;p40.142">Equation (6) represents the reaction function of the CB. Since an equilibrium is only consistent when <hi rend="italic">πe</hi> equals π, and ignoring for simplicity the existence of supply shocks (i.e., ε = 0), the final outcome is easily understandable following Figure 2. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0079b-fig.002"><head><hi rend="bold">Figure 2. Equilibrium Inflation with Discretionary Policy</hi> Based on Cukierman (1992).</head></figure><p n="p41.142"><s n="s1.2;p41.142">Figure 2 panel (a) shows indifference contours of the loss function stated in (1) and their respective tangency with the short-run Phillips curves (for given values of <hi rend="italic">πe</hi>). </s><s n="s2.2;p41.142">It is worth noting that outcomes farther away from <hi rend="italic">B</hi> (i.e., the ideal point with <hi rend="italic">π=0</hi> and <hi rend="italic">y=yn+k)</hi> represent worse values from the CB viewpoint. </s></p><p n="p42.142"><s n="s1.5;p42.142">It is now worthwhile to ask why a TCP may arise in such a situation. </s><s n="s2.5;p42.142">To answer this question it is useful to focus on Figure 2 panel (a). </s><s n="s3.5;p42.142">Given • the CB will try to locate itself in a situation closer to the bliss point <hi rend="italic">B.</hi> </s><s n="s4.5;p42.142">For instance, when public sets <hi rend="bold italic">*e = </hi>0 the best option forthe CB is to locate itself in a point like <hi rend="italic">C</hi> which yields an inflation rate <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0079b-form.008"/> (greater than 0)<hi rend="sup">11</hi>. </s><s n="s5.5;p42.142">Since the public knows that the CB will behave in such a way (i.e., they have rational expectations) they will never set <hi rend="bold italic">if </hi>to zero even when the CB announces <hi rend="bold italic">n </hi>equals zero <hi rend="sup">12</hi>. </s></p><p n="p43.142"><s n="s1.8;p43.142">Furthermore, Figure 2 panel (b) emphasises the rational expectation assumption introduced previously. </s><s n="s2.8;p43.142">The reaction function of the CB is obtained from (6) and has a slope <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0079b-form.009"/> smaller than 1. </s><s n="s3.8;p43.142">It is clear that only for <hi rend="sub italic">e = Xak </hi>the CB validates this expectation, since the best response from the CB viewpoint is also set <hi rend="italic">π = λak</hi> (See Figure 2 panels (a) and (b)). </s><s n="s4.8;p43.142">The final outcome, denoted by <hi rend="italic">D</hi> in panel (a) and by <hi rend="italic">D'</hi> in panel (b) is a time consistent equilibrium given by the inflation rate <hi rend="italic">π = λak</hi> and <hi rend="italic">y = yn</hi>. </s><s n="s5.8;p43.142">Or, put another way, this is the Nash equilibrium of the monetary game between the government and the public. </s><s n="s6.8;p43.142">It is clear that this situation is strictly dominated by, say, <hi rend="italic">π = 0</hi> and <hi rend="italic">y = yn</hi>. </s><s n="s7.8;p43.142">Nevertheless, since the TCP arises in this case once the CB announces <hi rend="italic">π = 0</hi> and the public expects <hi rend="italic">πe = 0</hi> the optimal choice for the CB is to no longer select <hi rend="italic">π = 0,</hi> meaning that <hi rend="italic">π = 0</hi> and <hi rend="italic">y = yn</hi> is not a Nash equilibrium in this game. </s><s n="s8.8;p43.142">So, under discretion the final outcome is determined by a suboptimal equilibrium <hi rend="italic">π = λak</hi> and <hi rend="italic">y = yn</hi>. </s></p><p n="p44.142"><s n="s1.1;p44.142">Summarising, the formal framework already introduced allows us to define the TCP as a situation where the CB's best choice of π for a given period is different before and after expectations have been set (Cukierman 1992, p. 31). </s></p><p n="p45.142"><s n="s1.1;p45.142">Now I will explain another useful way of understanding the TCP. Considering the first order conditions after minimising (5) it would be convenient to rearrange terms so as to obtain (the supply shock <hi rend="bold italic">e </hi>is omitted for simplicity), </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p46.142"><s n="s1.1;p46.142">(9) <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0079b-form.010"/> </s></p><p n="p47.142"><s n="s1.2;p47.142">As usual, the left hand side represents the marginal benefit (given by the short-run Phillips curve) while the right hand side indicates the marginal cost of one additional unit of <hi rend="bold italic">x.</hi> </s><s rend="bold" n="s2.2;p47.142"> </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0079b-fig.003"><head><hi rend="bold">Figure 3. Equilibrium inflation under discretion</hi> Source: Based on Walsh (2003).</head></figure><p n="p48.142"><s n="s1.3;p48.142">Figure 3 graphically represents (9), where the fact that <hi rend="bold italic">x = xe = Xak </hi>in equilibrium has been imposed. </s><s n="s2.3;p48.142">Without loss of generality it was assumed that <hi rend="italic">ka2</hi> is smaller than 1 <hi rend="sup">13</hi>. </s><s n="s3.3;p48.142">Two marginal benefit curves have been plotted, for <hi rend="bold italic">xe = </hi>0 and <hi rend="bold italic">xe = Xak</hi><hi rend="sup">14</hi>. </s></p><p n="p49.142"><s n="s1.4;p49.142">Now, we can ask why the CB has incentives to not commit to an announcement of* = 0. </s><s n="s2.4;p49.142">Obvious from Figure 3 is that when the public sets <hi rend="bold italic">if = </hi>0, <hi rend="bold italic">n = </hi>0 is not an equilibrium since the marginal benefit that the CB faces (i.e., <hi rend="italic">Xak)</hi> is well above the marginal cost (i.e., 0). </s><s n="s3.4;p49.142">For all positive <hi rend="bold italic">if </hi>smaller than <hi rend="italic">Xak</hi> the CB will find such an incentive in not validating the expected inflation. </s><s n="s4.4;p49.142">It is worth highlighting that such an incentive increases in <hi rend="bold italic">X </hi>(i.e., the weight that the CB puts on the output objective)<hi rend="italic">, a</hi> (i.e., the effect of unexpected inflation on output) and <hi rend="italic">k</hi> (i.e., economic distortions). </s></p><p n="p50.142"><s n="s1.2;p50.142">So, from Figure 3 it is clear that only when •<hi rend="italic">= Xak</hi> will the CB reproduce this inflation (*<hi rend="italic">*= Xak)</hi> since the marginal benefit equals the marginal cost (i.e., the Nash equilibrium of the game). </s><s n="s2.2;p50.142">Thus, it is also possible to define the TCP as situations where for <hi rend="bold italic">if </hi>smaller than <hi rend="italic">k*= Xak,</hi> the CB faces the marginal benefit of additional inflation greater than the marginal cost, which induces him not to validate the expected inflation. </s></p></div2><div2><head>C. Comparison of expected loss under discretion and optimal rule</head><p n="p51.142"><s n="s1.1;p51.142">Introducing (2) in (1), replacing for the values of <hi rend="bold italic">if </hi>and <hi rend="bold italic">n </hi>obtained in (7) and (8) and considering the expected loss of the objective function (assuming <hi rend="italic">E(e)</hi> equals 0 and <hi rend="italic">E(s2)</hi> equals <hi rend="italic">a2)</hi> it is possible to obtain, </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p52.142"><s n="s1.1;p52.142">(10) <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0079b-form.011"/> </s></p><p n="p53.142"><s n="s1.2;p53.142">The first term on the right hand side of (10) could be interpreted as a dead-weight loss due to economic distortions while the second is originated in the variance of output. </s><s n="s2.2;p53.142">The third and fourth terms reflect the cost of having a positive average inflation rate and how well the CB manages to keep inflation constant, respectively (Eijffinger and Hoeberichts 1998, p. 397). </s></p><p n="p54.142"><s n="s1.1;p54.142">Rearranging terms, (10) could be expressed as, </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p55.142"><s n="s1.1;p55.142">(11) <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0079b-form.012"/> </s></p><p n="p56.142"><s n="s1.3;p56.142">To highlight the costs involved under discretion it is worthwhile to compare with an alternative regime. </s><s n="s2.3;p56.142">In particular, with one in which the TCP is completely avoided and the CB is still able to manage <hi rend="bold italic">n </hi>(i.e., <hi rend="italic">Am)</hi> to overcome the effects of aggregate shocks. </s><s n="s3.3;p56.142">The main characteristics of such a regime are briefly described as follows. </s></p><p n="p57.142"><s n="s1.5;p57.142">The CB announces <hi rend="bold italic">*(e) = be </hi>before the private sector determines <hi rend="bold italic">ne </hi>. </s><s n="s2.5;p57.142">But, in this situation, it is assumed that an institutional arrangement exists which commits the CB to following the announced rule. </s><s n="s3.5;p57.142">Since the public has full credibility in this institutional arrangement, they set <hi rend="bold italic">*e = E(n) = 0.</hi> </s><s n="s4.5;p57.142">Worth noting is that this rule is considered 'optimal' or 'contingent' since the CB will be able to modify <hi rend="bold italic">n </hi>depending on <hi rend="bold italic">e </hi>to avoid adverse effects on economic activity. </s><s n="s5.5;p57.142">The timing of events is summarised in Figure 4. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0079b-fig.004"><head><hi rend="bold">Figure 4. Timing of events under optimal rule</hi> Source: Based on Eijffinger and Hoeberichts (1998).</head></figure><p n="p58.142"><s n="s1.1;p58.142">Under this scenario, the expected loss function takes the form (since <hi rend="bold italic">* = 0 </hi>and <hi rend="bold italic">*(e)</hi> </s></p><p n="p59.142"><s rend="italic" n="s1.1;p59.142">= be) , </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p60.142"><s n="s1.1;p60.142">(12) <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0079b-form.013"/> </s></p><p n="p61.142"><s n="s1.1;p61.142">After determining the value of <hi rend="italic">b</hi> which minimises (12) (i.e.,<hi rend="italic">b</hi> =<hi rend="italic">λ a</hi> ), the </s></p><p n="p62.142"><s n="s1.1;p62.142">equilibrium inflation rate and the expected loss function under the optimal rule yields </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p63.142"><s n="s1.1;p63.142">(14) <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0079b-form.014"/> </s></p><p n="p64.142"><s n="s1.2;p64.142">Comparing (13) and (8) it is important to highlight how the average inflation bias is eliminated and thereby the loss due to this average inflation (i.e., when (14) is compared with (11)). </s><s n="s2.2;p64.142">In this optimal situation the TCP has been eliminated (since • = 0 is validated on average) and the CB is still able to accommodate <hi rend="italic">∆m</hi> to ε (i.e., to isolate economic activity from supply shocks). </s></p><p n="p65.142"><s n="s1.2;p65.142">However, as Rogoff (1985, p. 1177) among others points out, predicting the shocks that an economy may suffer in advance is, at least, a difficult task. </s><s n="s2.2;p65.142">Different institutional arrangements has been proposed to improve the discretional equilibrium, avoiding the difficulties inherent in defining all possible contingencies under the optimal rule, the objective of the next section being to discuss fully why it is possible to reduce the TCP through an independent CB. </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head>II. Reducing the time consistency problem with an Independent Central Bank</head><p n="p66.142"><s n="s1.3;p66.142">The assumption that, when delegating monetary policy to an independent CB, it is possible to reduce the TCP is mainly based on Rogoff (1985)'s seminal contribution. </s><s n="s2.3;p66.142">In this paper Rogoff explains how a conservative policymaker helps to reduce the average inflation bias present under discretion. </s><s n="s3.3;p66.142">Following this brief introduction, a question immediately arises about why an independent CB is directly associated with Rogoff's conservative policymaker. </s></p><p n="p67.142"><s n="s1.2;p67.142">In most of the literature on monetary policy (see, for example, Romer 2001, p. 489 or Walsh 2003, p. 393) it is often assumed with CBs being more independent that the people appointed as CB heads tend to be particularly averse to inflation. </s><s n="s2.2;p67.142">Moreover, behind this viewpoint remains an 'implicit' assumption that central bankers are on average less impatient (i.e., more conservative) than politicians and, when isolated from political influences, the former merely reflect this behaviour <hi rend="sup">15</hi>. </s></p><p n="p68.142"><s n="s1.4;p68.142">One may also ask if a trade-off exists between the degrees of independence and conservativeness. </s><s n="s2.4;p68.142">An interesting insight here is given by Eijffinger and Hoeberichts (1998, pp. 398-403) and Bergeral. (2001, pp. 4-6). </s><s n="s3.4;p68.142">In their analysis they sustain that different degrees between independence and conservativeness exist. </s><s n="s4.4;p68.142">Furthermore, considering this viewpoint, it is worth highlighting that Rogoff's framework might be associated with one whereby the CB is fully independent when conducting monetary policy <hi rend="sup">16</hi>. </s></p><p n="p69.142"><s n="s1.3;p69.142">Finally, it merits emphasising that in the Rogoff analysis it is assumed that the government is able to distinguish the relative inflation preferences among potential central bankers, which remain constant over time. </s><s n="s2.3;p69.142">This issue is especially criticised in Bergeral. (2001, p.7). </s><s n="s3.3;p69.142">I consider that this fact seems not to be excessively problematic from an empirical viewpoint, since different mechanisms such as a detailed analysis of the policymaker's professional experience probably reduce much of this information asymmetry. </s></p><p n="p70.142"><s n="s1.2;p70.142">The remainder of the section formally explains how a fully instrument-independent CB reduces the TCP present under the discretionary equilibrium following the Rogoff (1985) approach. </s><s n="s2.2;p70.142">As in the previous section, most of the notation is borrowed from Walsh (2003). </s></p><div2><head>A. The model</head><p n="p71.142"><s n="s1.3;p71.142">In this situation the objective function stated in equation (1) is slightly modified, since a conservative policymaker, who has greater inflation aversion than society does, will now set monetary policy. </s><s n="s2.3;p71.142">The degree by which the policymaker's weight on inflation differs from society's is given by the factor <hi rend="bold italic">S.</hi> </s><s n="s3.3;p71.142">In such a case, the loss function (1) takes the following form (where <hi rend="italic">WC</hi> refers to weight conservative, terminology introduced by Svensson (1997)), </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p72.142"><s n="s1.1;p72.142">(15) <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0079b-form.015"/> </s></p><p n="p73.142"><s n="s1.2;p73.142">It is worth noting that the sequence of events in this case is the same as under discretion: first the public determines &lt; then the supply shock <hi rend="bold italic">s </hi>is observed and finally the CB sets <hi rend="bold italic">x.</hi> </s><s rend="bold" n="s2.2;p73.142"> </s></p><p n="p74.142"><s n="s1.2;p74.142">In this case the CB minimises (15) considering the short-run Phillips curve (2) in order to obtain the optimal <hi rend="bold italic">n.</hi> </s><s n="s2.2;p74.142">In this case, the CB reaction function takes the following form, </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p75.142"><s n="s1.1;p75.142">(16) <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0079b-form.016"/> </s></p><p n="p76.142"><s n="s1.1;p76.142">Considering that the public has rational expectations (16) implies, </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p77.142"><s n="s1.1;p77.142">(17) <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0079b-form.017"/> </s></p><p n="p78.142"><s n="s1.2;p78.142">It is interesting to compare (17) with (7). </s><s n="s2.2;p78.142">With a weight conservative CB, the average inflation rate is reduced by <hi rend="italic">(1+6),</hi> a factor reflecting how costly inflation is from the CB viewpoint. </s></p><p n="p79.142"><s n="s1.1;p79.142">Replacing (17) in (16) yields the inflation rate of the conservative CB, </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p80.142"><s n="s1.1;p80.142">(18) <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0079b-form.018"/> </s></p><p n="p81.142"><s n="s1.2;p81.142">Now an interesting question related to how the conservative CB tends to reduce the TCP emerges. </s><s n="s2.2;p81.142">Figure 5 shows how the reaction function of the CB changes when a conservative central banker is appointed to conduct monetary policy (again, for simplicity the presence of the supply shock <hi rend="bold italic">s </hi>is omitted). </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0079b-fig.005"><head rend="bold">Figure 5. Effect of delegation monetary policy to a conservative policymaker</head></figure><p n="p82.142"><s n="s1.1;p82.142">Since the policy maker puts more weight on inflation than in the case of the </s></p><p n="p83.142"><s n="s1.3;p83.142">discretionary outcome, the reaction function tends to be flatter (the slope equals <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0079b-form.019"/>) with a lower intercept (see Figure 5). </s><s n="s2.3;p83.142">Worth noting is that the TCP is reduced but not eliminated <hi rend="sup">17</hi>. </s><s n="s3.3;p83.142">To clarify the analysis it is worth studying the first-order condition given by (16) as follows, </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p84.142"><s n="s1.1;p84.142">(19) <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0079b-form.020"/> </s></p><p n="p85.142"><s n="s1.2;p85.142">Comparing (19) with (9) it merits noting that the marginal cost of additional inflation (right hand side) has risen by the factor <hi rend="italic">(1+δ)</hi> while the marginal benefit remains equal (left hand side). </s><s n="s2.2;p85.142">Figure 6 illustrates the marginal benefit and cost obtained when a conservative policymaker is considered. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0079b-fig.006"><head><hi rend="bold">Figure 6. Equilibrium inflation with a conservative policymaker</hi> Source: Based on Walsh (2003).</head></figure><p n="p86.142"><s n="s1.5;p86.142">It is worth emphasising that this way of considering the effects of a conservative policymaker generates a new insight into the TCP and is not, to my knowledge, addressed in the literature on monetary policy. </s><s n="s2.5;p86.142">From Equation (19) and Figure 6 two main issues arise. </s><s n="s3.5;p86.142">First, that the way in which the TCP tends to be reduced when the CB is more independent (i.e., a more conservative CB head) is through an increase in the marginal cost that the central banker faces for generating inflation <hi rend="sup">18</hi>. </s><s n="s4.5;p86.142">Second, that the TCP is not fully solved unless the marginal cost is infinite (when δ tends to ∞, which implies an infinite inflation aversion by the policymaker). </s><s n="s5.5;p86.142">However, as Rogoff (1985, p. 1179) points out, under the presence of supply shocks, it is optimal to choose a head for the CB with δ &lt; ∞ (i.e., not to eliminate completely the TCP). </s></p><p n="p87.142"><s n="s1.4;p87.142">Intuitively, as δ increases, the economy's average inflation rate is reduced but the weight that the CB puts on inflation relative to output is altered. </s><s n="s2.4;p87.142">This fact negatively affects the optimal CB response to unanticipated shocks generating the so-called stabilisation bias. </s><s n="s3.4;p87.142">For this reason the optimal δ is smaller than ∞. </s><s n="s4.4;p87.142">This result is easy to observe after evaluating the expected loss function with society's preferences stated in (1) introducing the short-run Phillips curve and the results obtained in (17) and (18) as follows, </s></p><p n="p88.142"><s n="s1.1;p88.142"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0079b-form.021"/> </s></p><p n="p89.142"><s n="s1.1;p89.142">Calculating how the expected loss varies as <hi rend="bold italic">S </hi>increases yields, </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p90.142"><s n="s1.1;p90.142">(21) <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0079b-form.022"/>. </s></p><p n="p91.142"><s n="s1.4;p91.142">Equation (21) could be broken down in two terms. </s><s n="s2.4;p91.142">The first might be associated with the 'credibility effect' (Eijffinger and Hoeberichts 1998, p. 401), which tends to reduce the expected social loss since the average inflation is reduced. </s><s n="s3.4;p91.142">Contrarywise, the second term positively affects the expected loss function reflecting the adverse effect generated by less output stabilisation (Rogoff 1985, p. 1179). </s><s n="s4.4;p91.142">Equating (21) to zero, the optimal degree of conservativeness is given by, </s></p><p n="p92.142"><s n="s1.1;p92.142">The graphical representation of (22) (see Figure 7) helps to understand why the </s></p><p n="p93.142"><s n="s1.1;p93.142">optimal degree of conservativeness lies in the interval <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0079b-form.023"/>, which </s></p><p n="p94.142"><s n="s1.1;p94.142">implies that <hi rend="bold italic">S* </hi>will be greater than zero but strictly smaller than infinite when economic distortions and supply shocks are present in the economy. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0079b-fig.007"><head><hi rend="bold">Figure 7. Optimal degree of conservatism</hi> Source: Based on Eijffinger and Hoeberichts (1998).</head></figure><p n="p95.142"><s n="s1.3;p95.142">Summarising, it is possible to conclude that the TCP is completely solved with an independent CB only if the marginal cost that the policymaker face when generating additional inflation is infinite. </s><s n="s2.3;p95.142">Furthermore, this fact is fully associated with an infinitely conservative central banker in terms of the Rogoff (1985) model. </s><s n="s3.3;p95.142">Nevertheless, when the economy is exposed to supply shocks and certain economic distortions are presents, the optimal degree of conservativeness of the central banker will be positive but certainly not infinite, which implies that the TCP is reduced compared with the discretionary outcome but not completely solved <hi rend="sup">19</hi>. </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head>III. Empirical evidence</head><p n="p96.142"><s n="s1.3;p96.142">Shown in the previous section was that an independent CB tends to diminish the average inflation bias in the economy. </s><s n="s2.3;p96.142">Nevertheless, as Walsh (2003, p. 396) points out, a trade-off between a reduction in inflation and a rise in output variability around the natural rate seems to exist. </s><s n="s3.3;p96.142">To clarify, introducing (17) and (18) in (2) and taking variance yields, </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p97.142"><s n="s1.2;p97.142">(23) <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0079b-form.024"/>, which is increasing in <hi rend="bold italic">6.</hi> </s><s rend="bold" n="s2.2;p97.142"> </s></p><p n="p98.142"><s n="s1.2;p98.142">This analysis could be extended in order to take into account the inflation rate variability. </s><s n="s2.2;p98.142">Taking variance in (18) gives, </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p99.142"><s n="s1.2;p99.142">(24) <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0079b-form.025"/>, which is decreasing in <hi rend="bold italic">6.</hi> </s><s rend="bold" n="s2.2;p99.142"> </s></p><p n="p100.142"><s n="s1.2;p100.142">Equations (23) and (24) imply that as the conservativeness degree of the central banker increases (measured by <hi rend="bold italic">S) </hi>the volatility of output growth rises, while the inflation rate volatility decreases. </s><s n="s2.2;p100.142">On the other hand, (24) and (17) together imply that economies with highly inflation-averse central bankers (i.e., more independent CBs) should show low average inflation as well as limited inflation variability. </s></p><p n="p101.142"><s n="s1.2;p101.142">Interestingly, most of the empirical work has found that CB independence is negatively correlated with inflation but does not show correlation with output variability (see, for example, Alesina and Summers 1993, Bergeral. 2001 and Walsh 2003). </s><s n="s2.2;p101.142">Furthermore, Walsh (2003, p. 421) has argued that this evidence suggests that giving more independence to the CB is a "free lunch" process <hi rend="sup">20</hi>. </s></p><p n="p102.142"><s n="s1.4;p102.142">The results included in this section are in line with this empirical evidence and might confirm Walsh's viewpoint, in the sense that more CB independence is not associated with more output volatility. </s><s n="s2.4;p102.142">Nevertheless, one should note that measures of CB independence, since it is an unobservable theoretical concept, are constructed through legal indicators which show how the government is legally restricted to punishing the CB in certain directions (Bergeral. 2001, p. 22). </s><s n="s3.4;p102.142">For this reason, it seems to me that the empirical analysis of the impact of CB independence on economic performance should be considered an interesting insight to the problem but not, in general, conclusive. </s><s n="s4.4;p102.142">Furthermore, other arrangements could be introduced as CBs tend to be more independent (e.g., an inflation target regime) which makes isolating the effects of CB independency and the evolution of certain economic variables difficult. </s></p><p n="p103.142"><s n="s1.2;p103.142">Table 1 summarises the results obtained by Alesina and Summers (1993) (hereinafter AS) for 16 developing countries in the period 1955-88 <hi rend="sup">21</hi>. </s><s n="s2.2;p103.142">Increases in the index developed by AS signify greater CB independence. </s></p><table id="BAWE_0079b-tab.001"><head rend="bold">Table 1. CB independence and economic performance</head><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p104.142"><s n="s1.3;p104.142">Following Table 1, one can appreciate a strong negative correlation between CB independence and average inflation in line with the Rogoff (1985) model. </s><s n="s2.3;p104.142">The table also shows that the variance of inflation diminishes when CB independence increases. </s><s n="s3.3;p104.142">It is worth noting, as explained, that this correlation may not imply a causal relation since other factors that occur while the CB is becoming more independent may also affect the inflation rate <hi rend="sup">22</hi>. </s></p><p n="p105.142"><s n="s1.1;p105.142">Interestingly, as CBs become more independent there is no evidence of a negative effect on output or employment, either considering the mean or variance of the GDP growth rate and unemployment rate. </s></p><p n="p106.142"><s n="s1.1;p106.142">Since the sample date covers the period 1955-1988, it seems interesting to extend the analysis with more recent data, the study of the UK case until 2003 being the object of the next subsection. </s></p><div2><head>A. The UK case</head><p n="p107.142"><s n="s1.2;p107.142">On May 6, 1997 the UK Government gave operational independence to the Bank of England (BE) (i.e., instrument independence to determine monetary policy) as part of a new monetary arrangement introduced in the UK <hi rend="sup">23</hi>. </s><s n="s2.2;p107.142">As a consequence of this arrangement the BE has assumed the responsibility for setting interest rates to meet the Government's stated inflation target. </s></p><p n="p108.142"><s n="s1.2;p108.142">In what follows, the framework addressed in Alesina and Summers (1993) is extended to analyse the possible effects of this reform on UK economic performance. </s><s n="s2.2;p108.142">The sample data was divided in three parts: 1955-88 (AS), 1989-96 (after AS and pre-reform)<hi rend="sup">24</hi>, and 1997-03 (post-reform)<hi rend="sup">25</hi>. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0079b-fig.008"><head><hi rend="bold">Figure 8. Average and variance inflation in UK</hi> Sources: Alesina and Summers (1993) and IMF.</head></figure><p n="p109.142"><s n="s1.4;p109.142">Figure 8 shows the negative effect on average and variance inflation obtained after the BE achieved economic independence in 1997. </s><s n="s2.4;p109.142">Worth highlighting is that the reduction in inflation was also important in the period 1989-96 compared to those values reported by AS for 1955-88, which suggest that 'conservative monetary policy' had been conducted by the BE before 1997. </s><s n="s3.4;p109.142">Here, again, empirical evidence of the effects of CB independence on economic performance seems not to be conclusive since other factors may affect the final outcome. </s><s n="s4.4;p109.142">For instance, jointly with being more independent the BE also instrumented an inflation targeting regime which may help in explaining the overall reduction in inflation. </s></p><p n="p110.142"><s n="s1.2;p110.142">From Figures 9 and 10 one should note that considering neither the output growth rate nor the unemployment rate does UK economic performance seems to worsen. </s><s n="s2.2;p110.142">Furthermore, considering the mean and the variance of the output growth rate, the impact of the 1997 monetary reform seems to be highly favourable. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0079b-fig.009"><head><hi rend="bold">Figure 9. Average and variance GNP growth rate in UK26</hi> Sources: Alesina and Summers (1993) and IMF.</head></figure><figure id="BAWE_0079b-fig.010"><head><hi rend="bold">Figure 10. Average and variance unemployment rate in UK</hi> Sources: Alesina and Summers (1993) and IMF.</head></figure></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head>IV. Summary and Conclusions</head><p n="p111.142"><s n="s1.1;p111.142">This paper critically addressed the TCP that a policymaker may suffer when conducting monetary policy, defined as a situation where his optimal decision is not the same before and after the public set the expected inflation, even though the information set between periods remains equal. </s></p><p n="p112.142"><s n="s1.4;p112.142">I explained that behind the TCP remains the assumption that an institutional setup exists which allows the policymaker to behave with discretion. </s><s n="s2.4;p112.142">In other words, the policymaker is able to optimise his objective function in each period. </s><s n="s3.4;p112.142">Since he faces a trade-off between unexpected inflation and output and the public knows such incentive, the latter sets the expected inflation at a level at which the marginal benefit equals the marginal cost that the government faces for generating inflation. </s><s n="s4.4;p112.142">Thus, the economy ends up in a suboptimal equilibrium with positive average inflation without any effect on output beyond the natural rate. </s></p><p n="p113.142"><s n="s1.3;p113.142">How this suboptimal outcome could be improved was extensively addressed. </s><s n="s2.3;p113.142">First, the expected social loss under discretion was compared with that given by the 'optimal rule': a fully credible institutional framework which commits the government not to depart from the announced inflation rate while still allows it to manage monetary policy to reduce the effects of supply shocks. </s><s n="s3.3;p113.142">However, it was pointed out that such a framework could not be very useful in practice since it is difficult to anticipate the contingencies that an economy may suffer. </s></p><p n="p114.142"><s n="s1.3;p114.142">Nowadays, delegating monetary policy to an independent CB tends to be one of the most popular ways in which modern States try to overcome the TCP, analytically based on the Rogoff (1985) contribution. </s><s n="s2.3;p114.142">With a particular insight to the problem I argued that in this case the TCP is reduced since the policymaker faces a higher marginal cost of generating unexpected inflation when comparing with the pure discretionary situation. </s><s n="s3.3;p114.142">Furthermore, I explained that the TCP is not fully solved unless the inflation aversion of the central banker tends to infinite, an undesirable fact since it increases the stabilisation bias. </s></p><p n="p115.142"><s n="s1.4;p115.142">A brief insight to the empirical evidence was made, showing a negative correlation between the degree of CB independence and either the average or variance inflation, without negative effects on economic activity. </s><s n="s2.4;p115.142">An overview on the effects of the change in UK monetary arrangement after May 1997 is also in line with these results. </s><s n="s3.4;p115.142">However, I sustained that this evidence should be taken as indicative, since other factors not directly related to CB independence may affect the final outcome. </s><s n="s4.4;p115.142">Put another way, empirical evidence suggests that the TCP tends to be partially reduced with more independent CBs but the difficulties in measuring CB independence and the existence of other factors which affect the likelihood of inflation suggest that that this evidence is only indicative. </s></p><p n="p116.142"><s n="s1.3;p116.142">An interesting extension of the paper will be postponed for further research. </s><s n="s2.3;p116.142">It seems worthwhile asking if other institutional arrangements may help to reduce the TCP present under discretion without generating the stabilisation bias. </s><s n="s3.3;p116.142">A possible starting point to this insight, following the approach stated in Svensson (1997), seems to be explaining formally how an inflation targeting regime helps to overcome the TCP and to contrast the results with those obtained in this paper. </s></p><p n="p117.142"><s n="s1.1;p117.142"><hi rend="sup">1</hi> The TCP may also be reduced, for instance, when the reputation of the CB is considered, particular contracts are introduced in which the CB's compensation depends on inflation objectives or by limiting the CB's flexibility by institutional arrangements such as inflation rules (see Walsh 2003, p. 378 for a complete discussion). </s></p><p n="p118.142"><s n="s1.1;p118.142"><hi rend="sup">2</hi> The time consistency problem is also referred to in the literature as the dynamic inconsistency problem (see, for example, Blanchard and Fisher 1989, Cukierman 1992 and Romer 2001, among others). </s></p><p n="p119.142"><s n="s1.1;p119.142"><hi rend="sup">3</hi> In order to facilitate the analysis the desired level of inflation by the society is set to zero. </s></p><p n="p120.142"><s n="s1.2;p120.142"><hi rend="sup">4</hi> Barro and Gordon (1983a) utilise the parameters <hi rend="italic">a</hi> and <hi rend="italic">b</hi> to describe how costly deviations of output from the natural rate and inflation, respectively, are. </s><s n="s2.2;p120.142">Normalising the BG framework by <hi rend="italic">b</hi> and setting λ equals <hi rend="italic">a/b</hi> yields the specification stated in equation (1). </s></p><p n="p121.142"><s n="s1.1;p121.142"><hi rend="sup">5</hi> A detailed analysis of the nature of these economic imperfections will be introduced later in this section. </s></p><p n="p122.142"><s n="s1.1;p122.142"><hi rend="sup">6</hi> For instance, in the seminal work by Lucas (1973) it is possible to conclude that high volatility in money supply shocks increases volatility in output, thus negatively affecting the overall economic activity. </s></p><p n="p123.142"><s n="s1.2;p123.142"><hi rend="sup">7</hi> It is interesting to note that, as Svensson (1997, p. 109) among others claimed, the golden rule in economics should be to eliminate the distortion directly attacking the causes of the problem. </s><s n="s2.2;p123.142">For this reason, the mere fact of utilising monetary policy to solve such distortions explains why, at most, a second-best outcome would be obtained (See Svensson op cit. for a further discussion). </s></p><p n="p124.142"><s n="s1.2;p124.142"><hi rend="sup">8</hi> Walsh (2003) also introduces the existence of velocity shocks which might affect the rate of inflation. </s><s n="s2.2;p124.142">Since the main results remain equal without introducing this shock I will continue the analysis with this slightly easier version. </s></p><p n="p125.142"><s n="s1.1;p125.142"><hi rend="sup">9</hi> For the sake of clarity and to avoid excessive notation I will assume that the CB sets π rather than <hi rend="italic">∆m</hi> </s></p><p n="p126.142"><s n="s1.3;p126.142"><hi rend="sup">10</hi> It is worth highlighting that it is assumed the policymaker behaves with discretion as much as he can. </s><s n="s2.3;p126.142">Nevertheless, this assumption may not be necessarily true, as McCallum (1995, pp. 208-209) points out "(...) the inexistence of a technology for inescapably precommiting future behaviour does not imply that such behaviour is infeasible...what is needed is for the CB...to recognize that its objectives would be more fully achieved on average if it were to abstain from attempts to exploit these temporarily given expectations (...)." </s><s n="s3.3;p126.142">However, for simplicity, the abovementioned assumption will be followed throughout the analysis. </s></p><p n="p127.142"><s n="s1.1;p127.142"><hi rend="sup">11</hi> In fact, point C corresponds to the tangency of the short-run Phillips curve when <hi rend="italic">πe</hi> equals zero and the indifference curve closest to the bliss point B. </s></p><p n="p128.142"><s n="s1.2;p128.142"><hi rend="sup">12</hi> Unless an institutional arrangement commits the CB to validate this expectation. </s><s n="s2.2;p128.142">A brief description of this situation will be introduced at the end of this section. </s></p><p n="p129.142"><s n="s1.2;p129.142"><hi rend="sup">13</hi> Situations where <hi rend="italic">λa2</hi>>1 might be associated with those cases where either the CB cares much about output stabilisation (given by λ) or the CB perceives a high short-run benefit from unexpected inflation (given by <hi rend="italic">a</hi>). </s><s n="s2.2;p129.142">Since considering such cases does not modify the main results, the analysis only considers the case where <hi rend="italic">λa2</hi>&lt;1. </s></p><p n="p130.142"><s n="s1.2;p130.142"><hi rend="sup">14</hi> It is also possible to consider marginal benefit curves with <hi rend="italic">πe</hi> greater than <hi rend="italic">λak.</hi> </s><s n="s2.2;p130.142">However, since we already know that the final equilibrium will be at <hi rend="italic">πe</hi> = <hi rend="italic">π = λak</hi> and the TCP arises when the CB announces inflation levels smaller than <hi rend="italic">λak,</hi> only cases with <hi rend="italic">πe</hi> below <hi rend="italic">λak</hi> are worth analysing. </s></p><p n="p131.142"><s n="s1.3;p131.142"><hi rend="sup">15</hi> Cukierman (1992, p. 351), for instance, argued that "(...) </s><s n="s2.3;p131.142">Conservatives usually take a longer view. </s><s n="s3.3;p131.142">Hence to theextent that there is a tendency to appoint relatively conservative individuals to high office in the central bank, thebank's rate of time is likely to be lower that of the political authorities (...)." </s></p><p n="p132.142"><s n="s1.3;p132.142"><hi rend="sup">16</hi> The literature on monetary policy usually considers two different forms of independency: instrumentindependence and goal independence. </s><s n="s2.3;p132.142">While instrument independence is described as the ability of CBs to usemonetary policy instruments without restrictions, goal independence refers to the capacity of CBs to define policyobjectives without government's influence (Alesina and Summers, 1993 p. 153). </s><s n="s3.3;p132.142">In the analysis pointed out byEijffinger and Hoeberichts (1998) and Bergeral. (2001), implicitly, full instrument independence is needed inorder to obtain an objective function with the preferences of the conservative policymaker defined in the Rogoff(1985)'s model. </s></p><p n="p133.142"><s n="s1.1;p133.142"><hi rend="sup">17</hi> Unless δ is set equals to ∞, a situation which will be extensively discussed later in the paper. </s></p><p n="p134.142"><s n="s1.2;p134.142"><hi rend="sup">18</hi> Intuitively, the explanation might be associated with the fact that central bankers are on average less impatient than politicians. </s><s n="s2.2;p134.142">So, a more independent CB may perceive higher inflation today with a worse economic performance tomorrow, reflected in the higher marginal cost that he faces for increasing the inflation rate today. </s></p><p n="p135.142"><s n="s1.1;p135.142"><hi rend="sup">19</hi> In fact, due to the stabilisation bias, Svensson (1997, p. 105) points out that a weight conservative CB may achieve at best a third-best equilibrium. </s></p><p n="p136.142"><s n="s1.2;p136.142">20. </s><s n="s2.2;p136.142">Or, put another way, the mean and variance of inflation is reduced without affecting output variability. </s></p><p n="p137.142"><s n="s1.1;p137.142"><hi rend="sup">21</hi> The data corresponding to average GNP growth and variance GNP growth covers the period 1955-87. </s></p><p n="p138.142"><s n="s1.1;p138.142"><hi rend="sup">22</hi> Alesina and Summers (1993, p. 159) also highlights the possible mutual causality between inflation rates and CB independence, arguing, for instance, that the hyperinflation in Germany may have raised German public aversion to inflation and its propensity to having an independent CB. </s></p><p n="p139.142"><s n="s1.1;p139.142"><hi rend="sup">23</hi> See Bean (1998, pp. 1795-1796) for a discussion. </s></p><p n="p140.142"><s n="s1.2;p140.142"><hi rend="sup">24</hi> The only exception is in the case of the real GNP growth rate. </s><s n="s2.2;p140.142">Since Alesina and Summers (1993) only covers the period until 1987 the sample was extended from 1988 to 2003. </s></p><p n="p141.142"><s n="s1.2;p141.142"><hi rend="sup">25</hi> The year 1997 was considered post-reform, even though only after May 1997 was the monetary arrangement formally introduced. </s><s n="s2.2;p141.142">Nevertheless, since economic agents probably anticipated this reform in their decisions it seems reasonable to think that the effect on economic activity started at the beginning of the year. </s></p><p n="p142.142"><s n="s1.2;p142.142">26. </s><s n="s2.2;p142.142">For the period 1988-03 the real GDP growth rate was utilized as a proxy of the GNP growth rate. </s></p></div1></body><back><div1 type="bibliography"><head>V. References</head><p>Alesina, A., and L. Summers. 1993. "Central Bank Independence and Macroeconomic Performance: Some Comparative Evidence." <hi rend="italic">Journal of Money, Credit and Banking."</hi> 25:2, pp. 151-162.</p><p>Barro, R., and D. Gordon. 1983a. "A Positive Theory of Monetary Policy in a Natural Rate Model." <hi rend="italic">The Journal of Political Economy,</hi> 91:4, pp. 589-610.</p><p>Barro, R., and D. Gordon. 1983b. "Rules, Discretion and Reputation in a Model of Monetary Policy." <hi rend="italic">Journal of Monetary Economics,</hi> 12, pp. 101-121.</p><p>Bean, C. 1998. "The New UK Monetary Arrangements: A View From The Literature." <hi rend="italic">The Economic Journal</hi>, 108, pp. 1795-1809.</p><p>Berger, H.; J. de Haan and S. Eijffinger. 2001. "Central Bank Independence: An Update of Theory and Evidence." <hi rend="italic">Journal of Economic Surveys</hi>, 15:1, pp. 3-35.</p><p>Blanchard, O., and S. Fischer. 1989. <hi rend="italic">Lectures on Macroeconomics.</hi> Cambridge, Massachusetts: The MIT Press.</p><p>Blinder, A. 1997. "What Central Bankers Could Learn from Academics-and Vice Versa." <hi rend="italic">Journal of Economic Perspectives,</hi> pp. 3-19.</p><p>Calvo, G. 1978. "On the Time Consistency of Optimal Policy in a Monetary Economy." <hi rend="italic">Econometrica,</hi> 46:6, pp. 1411-1428.</p><p>Cukierman, A. 1992. <hi rend="italic">Central Bank Strategies, Credibility and Independence</hi>. Cambridge, Massachusetts: The MIT Press.</p><p>Eijffinger, S., and J. De Haan. 1996. "The Political Economy of Central Bank Independence." <hi rend="italic">University of Princeton,</hi> Special Papers in International Economics, No. 19.</p><p>Eijffinger, S., and M. Hoeberichts. 1998. "The trade off between central bank independence and conservativeness." <hi rend="italic">Oxford Economic Papers.</hi> 50, pp. 397-411.</p><p>Eijffinger, S.; M. Hoeberichts and E. Schaling. 2000. "Optimal central bank conservativeness in an open economy." <hi rend="italic">Public Choice,</hi> 105, pp. 339-355.</p><p>Kydland F., and E. Prescott. 1977. "Rules Rather than Discretion: The Inconsistency of Optimal Plans." <hi rend="italic">The Journal of Political Economy</hi>, 85:3, pp. 473-492.</p><p>Lucas, R. 1973. "Some International Evidence on Output-Inflation Tradeoffs." <hi rend="italic">The American Economic Review,</hi> 63:3, pp. 326-334.</p><p>McCallum, B. 1995. "Two Fallacies Concerning Central-Bank Independence." <hi rend="italic">The American Economic Review</hi>, 6:8, pp. 207-211.</p><p>Rogoff, K. 1985. "The Optimal Degree of Commitment to an Intermediate Monetary Target." <hi rend="italic">The Quarterly Journal of Economics,</hi> 100:4, pp. 1169-1189.</p><p>Romer, D. 2001. <hi rend="italic">Advanced Macroeconomics.</hi> 2<hi rend="sup">nd</hi> edn, New York: McGraw-Hill.</p><p>Svensson, L. 1997. "Optimal Inflation Targets, "Conservative" Central Banks, and Linear Inflation Contracts." <hi rend="italic">The American Economic Review,</hi> 87:1, pp. 98-114.</p><p>Walsh, C. 2003. <hi rend="italic">Monetary Theory and Policy.</hi> 2<hi rend="sup">nd</hi> edn, Cambridge, Massachusetts: The MIT Press.</p></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
