<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_0086b" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Property Relations</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">deleted: header: student number, course name and number; footer: page numbers
</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">1</p><p n="date">2006-03</p><p n="module title">Introduction to the Law of Property Relations</p><p n="module code">LA103</p><p n="genre family">Critique</p><p n="discipline">Law</p><p n="disciplinary group">SS</p><p n="grade">M</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">2494</p><p n="number of s-units">103</p><p n="number of p">30</p><p n="number of tables">0</p><p n="number of figures">0</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">3</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">6</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">24.2</p><p n="average s-units per p">3.4</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">f</p><p n="year of birth">1984</p><p n="first language">English</p><p n="education">OSA</p><p n="course">Law</p><p n="student ID">0086</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><div1 type="front-back-matter"><head rend="underlined bold">TABLE OF CASES:</head><p rend="bold italic">Lloyds Bank plc v Rosset [1991] 1 AC 107 (HL)</p><p rend="bold italic">Midland Bank plc v Cooke [1995] 4 All ER 562; [1995] 2 FLR 915</p><p rend="bold italic">Mortgage Corporation v Shaire [2001] Ch 743</p><p><hi rend="bold italic">Oxley v Hiscock </hi><hi rend="italic">[2004] EWCA Civ. 546; [2005] QB 211; [2004] 3 WLR 715</hi></p><p rend="bold italic">Re Densham [1975] 1 WLR 1519</p></div1><div1 type="front-back-matter"><head rend="underlined bold">LEGISLATIONS CITED:</head><p rend="bold italic">Insolvency Act 1986 Chapter 45 S. 335A</p><p rend="bold italic">Law of Property Act 1925 S. 53(1)(b)</p></div1></front><body><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">FACTS:</head><p n="p1.30"><s n="s1.6;p1.30">Mr. &amp; Mrs. Hurst purchased their matrimonial home in 1984, registered in their joint names and holding it as tenants in common under a constructive trust. </s><s n="s2.6;p1.30">They both signed the document, which recorded that a survivor could give a good receipt of moneys on purchase. </s><s n="s3.6;p1.30">No express declaration was made as regards the share of each person. </s><s n="s4.6;p1.30">The money for the purchase came partly from the sale of the old property jointly held by them, contribution from Mrs. Hurst's father and a mortgage in the name of Mr. &amp; Mrs. Hurst, secured on the property. </s><s n="s5.6;p1.30">A question that arose was whether the money given by Mrs. Hurst's father was intended only for Mrs. Hurst or to both of them. </s><s n="s6.6;p1.30">But the registrar, on evidence found that it was intended only for Mrs. Hurst. </s></p><p n="p2.30"><s n="s1.9;p2.30">Mr. Hurst, a solicitor was made bankrupt. </s><s n="s2.9;p2.30">He had provided information to his former partners that he had a 50% share in the property. </s><s n="s3.9;p2.30">And later, in a letter to his solicitor he claimed that he had erred and that he held a part of the 50% of his share on trust for his wife. </s><s n="s4.9;p2.30">In 2001 Mrs. Hurst made a written statement, i.e., an Individual Voluntary Agreement (IVA) stating that Mr. &amp; Mrs. Hurst shared the property on a 50/50 basis beneficially. </s><s n="s5.9;p2.30">But the IVA failed. </s><s n="s6.9;p2.30">Mr. Supperstone, trustee in bankruptcy of Mr. Hurst brought proceedings for the possession and sale of property on an equal basis. </s><s n="s7.9;p2.30">However, now Mr. Hurst argues that he is entitled to only a 15% share whereas Mrs. Hurst is entitled to an 85% beneficial share. </s><s n="s8.9;p2.30">They claimed under a resulting trust. </s><s n="s9.9;p2.30">The issue before the court is to quantify their respective shares. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">DECISION:</head><p n="p3.30"><s n="s1.1;p3.30">Dismissing the appeal, the court <hi rend="bold">Held-</hi> </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p4.30"><s n="s1.3;p4.30">Mr. &amp; Mrs. Hurst was entitled to a 50% share. </s><s n="s2.3;p4.30">In identifying the share recourse is to be had to the actual or assumed common intention at the time of purchase rather than at any later date. </s><s n="s3.3;p4.30">But recourse may be had to a conduct at a later date, which may be treated as showing what the intention at the date of purchase had been. </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p5.30"><s n="s1.2;p5.30">An additional relevant question that lies between the conclusion that the parties had an actual or presumed intention to share the beneficial ownership and the quantification of the respective shares is whether they should have imputed to them an intention to own as beneficial joint tenants as opposed to tenants in common. </s><s n="s2.2;p5.30">But the issue of quantification of shares arises only under a tenancy in common because joint tenants cannot hold in unequal shares; if the tenancy were severed they would share equally. </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p6.30"><s n="s1.1;p6.30">The too ready assumption of tenancy in common in cases of matrimonial homes begs an important prior question since joint tenancy is neither unjust nor inappropriate in cases of this nature. </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p7.30"><s n="s1.1;p7.30">The statements in the IVA did not give rise to a trust; they were mere statements made to the husband's creditors of the wife's willingness to co - operate for the sale of property and realisation of the husband's interest for the creditor's benefit. </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p8.30"><s n="s1.3;p8.30">In the absence of any actual or presumed intention, the court looks into the parties conduct both at the time of purchase of the property and subsequent to it and determines a share, which is fair and reasonable according to the situation. </s><s n="s2.3;p8.30">It is wrong to infer an intention, which the parties never intended. </s><s n="s3.3;p8.30">It would be unreal to suppose that both the spouses had the same intention at the date of purchase without any discussion to that effect. </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p9.30"><s n="s1.2;p9.30">The learned registrar in his decision used the IVA as a compelling factor in determining a fair share. </s><s n="s2.2;p9.30">It would be wrong for Mrs. Hurst to claim a share greater than 50% since she had stated in the agreement to the creditors that her husband and she had equal beneficial interest. </s></p><p n="p10.30"><s n="s1.2;p10.30">The underlying legal principle in deciding the case was the application of the fairness test whereby the parties' conduct have to be taken to decide the outcome in a way not to cause any detriment to the party claiming from the property. </s><s n="s2.2;p10.30">The parties' intention at the time of, or subsequent to the purchase has to be taken into account to determine the size of the beneficial interest. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">COMMENT:</head><p n="p11.30"><s n="s1.2;p11.30">This case mainly deals with the doctrine of constructive trusts. </s><s n="s2.2;p11.30">Although the wife's contribution was more than the husband's, the registrar reached the conclusion that they intended to share the beneficial interest equally under constructive trust instead of unequal shares under a resulting trust. </s></p><p n="p12.30"><s n="s1.3;p12.30">The case is set out to determine the shares of the parties and bring about an outcome desirable on the novel concept of fairness. </s><s n="s2.3;p12.30">In a resulting trust, no such thing can be used because the one and only factor that determines the shares is contribution to the purchase price. </s><s n="s3.3;p12.30">But under a constructive trust the court gives due consideration to the parties' intentions. </s></p><div2><head rend="underlined bold">CONSTRUCTIVE TRUST</head><p n="p13.30"><s n="s1.3;p13.30">Under constructive trusts the parties' intention is given importance. </s><s n="s2.3;p13.30">The statute<ref target="BAWE_0086b-ftnote.001"/> requires a written statement expressing the parties' intention for a constructive trust. </s><s n="s3.3;p13.30">As per the learned registrar the written statement in the IVA may satisfy this requirement. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0086b-ftnote.001"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Section 53(1)(b), Law of Property Act 1925 </s></p></note><p n="p14.30"><s n="s1.2;p14.30">In <hi rend="underlined">Midland Bank plc v Cooke</hi><ref target="BAWE_0086b-ftnote.002"/>, Waite LJ held that the intention could be inferred from the financial contributions of the parties, but the significance of the case lies in that it was held, - the intention can be justified from the parties' conduct. </s><s n="s2.2;p14.30">The court 'constructs' an intention, which the parties would have had by looking at the parties' conduct. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0086b-ftnote.002"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">[1995] 4 All ER 562 @ 574 - 576 </s></p></note><p n="p15.30"><s n="s1.6;p15.30">Both constructive and resulting trust requires some financial contribution but the difference arises during the quantification of the beneficial shares in the property. </s><s n="s2.6;p15.30">In a resulting trust the shares are calculated according to the proportionate contribution to the purchase price, there being no evidence of any other intention. </s><s n="s3.6;p15.30">But under a constructive trust the court gives effect to the parties' actual or presumed intention, which need not necessarily be proportionate to their contribution. </s><s n="s4.6;p15.30">On a reading of this case we can see that the parties did not intend holding beneficial interest proportionate to their contribution because on various occasions we find at least one of the spouse saying they have a 50% interest in the property. </s><s n="s5.6;p15.30">And, now when the case has come before the court it is wrong for the wife to claim a greater share under a resulting trust. </s><s n="s6.6;p15.30">It is only right that the deputy judge rejected the claim, if the IVA was any indication to this effect. </s></p><p n="p16.30"><s n="s1.1;p16.30">A constructive trust is inferred when, the parties have: - </s></p><list type="bulleted"><item>Any oral or written agreement at the time or subsequent to the purchase</item></list><list type="bulleted"><item>Common intention to be inferred at the time or any time subsequent to the purchase of property</item></list><list type="bulleted"><item>What the court thinks to be fair according to the dealings between the parties<ref target="BAWE_0086b-ftnote.003"/></item></list><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0086b-ftnote.003"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Chadwick LJ in <hi rend="underlined">Oxley v Hiscock</hi> [2004] EWCA Civ 546 </s></p></note></div2><div2><head rend="underlined bold">BENEFICIAL INTEREST AND QUANTIFICATION OF SHARES</head><p n="p17.30"><s n="s1.8;p17.30">The first issue is whether the parties intended to share the beneficial interest in the property. </s><s n="s2.8;p17.30">Lord Bridge in <hi rend="underlined">Lloyds Bank plc v Rosset</hi><ref target="BAWE_0086b-ftnote.004"/> lays down two tests to infer intention to share beneficial interest. </s><s n="s3.8;p17.30">First, where there is evidence of any discussion between the parties at the time of purchase, and the second is where contribution of money provides evidence of the same. </s><s n="s4.8;p17.30">The deputy judge in this case says that the case falls within Lord Bridge's first category<ref target="BAWE_0086b-ftnote.005"/>. </s><s n="s5.8;p17.30">I do not completely agree with that because the statements made in the IVA in 2001 showed the intention of the parties at that time, this does not follow that their intention was the same at the time of purchase<ref target="BAWE_0086b-ftnote.006"/>. </s><s n="s6.8;p17.30">There was no such discussion between the parties at the time of the purchase. </s><s n="s7.8;p17.30">I think the case falls under the second category of cases mentioned by Lord Bridge, i.e., the inference of intention from the financial contribution. </s><s n="s8.8;p17.30">This is because, apart from the contribution of moneys to the purchase price, there is no evidence of any other discussion. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0086b-ftnote.004"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">[1991] 1 AC 107 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0086b-ftnote.005"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1"><hi rend="underlined">Hurst v Supperstone</hi> [2005] EWHC 1309 Para 7 (under the heading Summary of Oxley v Hiscock) </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0086b-ftnote.006"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">'Property Law Update - What's a fair share? : Supperstone v Hurst' 155(Aug) NLJ 2005 No. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">7189 @ pg 1248 </s></p></note><p n="p18.30"><s n="s1.5;p18.30">Then comes the most important issue of quantification of the shares in the property. </s><s n="s2.5;p18.30">There is a difference between the declaration of trust and the determination of the amount of beneficial interest. </s><s n="s3.5;p18.30">If the parties owned as joint tenants then there is no question of determination of shares, since if there were a division then the parties would hold equally. </s><s n="s4.5;p18.30">It is only in cases of tenancies in common does the issue of quantification arise. </s><s n="s5.5;p18.30">That the parties in the present case were tenants in common was never disputed. </s></p><p n="p19.30"><s n="s1.8;p19.30">The size of the parties' shares can be determined by following the authorities in <hi rend="underlined">Midland Bank plc v Cooke</hi><ref target="BAWE_0086b-ftnote.007"/> and <hi rend="underlined">Oxley v Hiscock</hi><ref target="BAWE_0086b-ftnote.008"/> which lays down that while determining the shares, the court has to take into account "the whole course of dealing between the parties relevant to their ownership and occupation of the property". </s><s n="s2.8;p19.30">In <hi rend="italic">Midland Bank</hi><ref target="BAWE_0086b-ftnote.009"/> the court said it could take into account post - acquisition dealings to determine shares under a constructive trust<ref target="BAWE_0086b-ftnote.010"/>. </s><s n="s3.8;p19.30">This would include any statement expressing the parties' intention to share the property in a particular manner. </s><s n="s4.8;p19.30">In the present case the IVA made by the parties is very persuasive because when Mrs. Hurst signed the agreement, it gives rise to an intention that, she understood the nature of the agreement and was willing to perform the same. </s><s n="s5.8;p19.30">Hence the parties' claim that since the IVA was unsuccessful the court should completely ignore it is not too convincing. </s><s n="s6.8;p19.30">Nevertheless it has to be noted that this is not the only evidence that the court took into consideration. </s><s n="s7.8;p19.30">But it would be wrong and an unnecessary fiction to impute to the parties an intention they never had<ref target="BAWE_0086b-ftnote.011"/>. </s><s n="s8.8;p19.30">A statement made 17 ½ years later, in 2001 does not give rise to an intention that parties intended the same at the time of purchase. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0086b-ftnote.007"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">[1995] 4 All ER 562 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0086b-ftnote.008"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">[2004] EWCA Civ 546 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0086b-ftnote.009"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0086b-ftnote.010"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">'The Ebb and Flow of Trusts and Estoppel' 15(Dec) KCLJ 2004, Issue 2 @ pg. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">440. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0086b-ftnote.011"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Chadwick LJ in <hi rend="underlined">Oxley v Hiscock</hi> [2004] EWCA Civ 256 </s></p></note><p n="p20.30"><s n="s1.8;p20.30">I am under the impression that Mr. &amp; Mrs. Hurst was not sure what exactly they wanted. </s><s n="s2.8;p20.30">If they indeed wanted to share the property in the ratio of 85/15, why then did Mr. Hurst give evidence that the money given by his father - in - law was intended for the couple and not to Mrs. Hurst alone? </s><s n="s3.8;p20.30">Should that be the case, the contribution of Mr. &amp; Mrs. Hurst would be more or less equal and their claim for an 85/15 share would fail. </s><s n="s4.8;p20.30">This seems somewhat contradictory. </s><s n="s5.8;p20.30">I think these statements may also be reflective of their intention to share property equally. </s><s n="s6.8;p20.30">Also Mr. Hurst had written to his former partners that his assets included a 50% share in the net equity of the property. </s><s n="s7.8;p20.30">Denying this, he later wrote to his solicitor saying the letter was written in haste. </s><s n="s8.8;p20.30">As the registrar said Mr. Hurst was "a man who was willing to say what best suited his case at that time". <ref target="BAWE_0086b-ftnote.012"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0086b-ftnote.012"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1"><hi rend="underlined">Hurst v Supperstone</hi> [2005] EWHC 1309 Para 41 </s></p></note><p n="p21.30"><s n="s1.4;p21.30">While it was common ground that the couple were tenants in common, during the transfer of the property in their joint names they signed a deed, which gave the survivor a good receipt of capital monies on purchase. </s><s n="s2.4;p21.30">This is the principle of beneficial joint tenancy. </s><s n="s3.4;p21.30">But this issue was never addressed. </s><s n="s4.4;p21.30">If it was indeed a joint tenancy then their share would have been equal and there would be no issue of quantification. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined bold">FAIRNESS PRINCIPLE</head><p n="p22.30"><s n="s1.5;p22.30">The deputy judge came to the conclusion that the parties held beneficial interest in equal shares after analysing all the evidence of what would be fair and reasonable to the parties. </s><s n="s2.5;p22.30">The judge, at the end of the decision says had it not been the trustee who had brought the claim he might have thought that a 50/50 share would have been unjust to the wife. </s><s n="s3.5;p22.30">There is, in a way a detrimental reliance on the part of the creditors, which may also give rise to a presumption of constructive trust. </s><s n="s4.5;p22.30">The wife made a written declaration in the form of the IVA, drawn for the benefit of the creditors. </s><s n="s5.5;p22.30">Now when the issue is before the court she is claiming a greater share than that claimed under the IVA, its failure coming as an excuse to avoid her obligation to the creditors. </s></p><p n="p23.30"><s n="s1.2;p23.30">So the court applied the principle of fairness, i.e., what would be fair to the claimant under the circumstances. </s><s n="s2.2;p23.30">Under <hi rend="underlined">Section 335A of the Insolvency Act 1986</hi>, the court has to make an order in the best interest of the bankrupt's creditors, especially when the property has been the former residence of the bankrupt and consider the conduct of bankrupt's spouse. </s></p><p n="p24.30"><s n="s1.1;p24.30">The fairness principle was drawn from the case of <hi rend="underlined">Oxley v Hiscock</hi><ref target="BAWE_0086b-ftnote.013"/>, where the Court of Appeal reversed the judgement that the couple held an equal share under a constructive trust because it was unfair to the person who contributed more to the purchase price and attributed a resulting trust. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0086b-ftnote.013"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">[2004] EWCA Civ 546 </s></p></note><p n="p25.30"><s n="s1.1;p25.30">In Densham, Re<ref target="BAWE_0086b-ftnote.014"/>, it was held, had the trustee in bankruptcy not been involved in the proceedings the wife would have had a half share in the property, rather than the one-ninth share. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0086b-ftnote.014"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">[1975] 1 WLR 1519, extracted from 'Constructive trusts, Estoppel and the Family Home' Thompson, M.P, 2004 Conv 496, Westlaw UK. </s></p></note><p n="p26.30"><s n="s1.2;p26.30">This is the main principle of the case and the whole outcome was decided on what was fair according to the facts of the case, taking into account the whole course of dealings between the parties. </s><s n="s2.2;p26.30">The court cannot rely upon only the financial contribution to determine the shares. </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">CONCLUSION:</head><p n="p27.30"><s n="s1.4;p27.30">In conclusion I would like to say that I agree with the outcome of the case. </s><s n="s2.4;p27.30">It was only fair that the creditors did not lose out their interest because of Mrs. Hurst's greed in claiming a greater share than she intended to and was willing to give. </s><s n="s3.4;p27.30">The IVA, though not a conclusive proof of their intention to share the beneficial interest equally, was nevertheless a persuasive document. </s><s n="s4.4;p27.30">And the parties' conduct in general was proof of this. </s></p><p n="p28.30"><s n="s1.3;p28.30">The case, in effect is similar to the cases decided previously on the issue of constructive trusts and the deputy judge, for the most part relied on the Court of Appeal decision in <hi rend="underlined">Oxley v Hiscock</hi> in reaching the decision. </s><s n="s2.3;p28.30">The 'fairness principle' was applied very aptly in deciding the case. </s><s n="s3.3;p28.30">The deputy judge complemented the legal doctrines of constructive trusts and tenancies in common with the equitable principle of 'Fairness', which in my view is very important. </s></p><p n="p29.30"><s n="s1.3;p29.30">On a consideration of the facts, this case is different since almost all the cases that have come before the court till now have been cases of matrimonial home where the cohabitees claim interest on the breakdown of the relationship. </s><s n="s2.3;p29.30">In that sense the case may set a precedent if the House of Lords decides a similar issue in the future. </s><s n="s3.3;p29.30">The deputy judge applied the same law applied in the other cases of determining the interest although the legal title is owned jointly, saying there is no real difference in the underlying legal analysis due to this. </s></p><p n="p30.30"><s n="s1.2;p30.30">On the whole the case has brought about a desired result. </s><s n="s2.2;p30.30">And has been fair to the claimant, who would have otherwise been the weaker party. </s></p></div1></body><back><div1 type="bibliography"><head rend="underlined bold">BIBLIOGRAPHY:</head><div2 type="bibliography"><head rend="underlined bold">BOOKS:</head><p rend="bold italic">Land Law, Gray, Kevin and Gray, Susan Francis. Fourth Edition - 2006, Oxford University Press. </p><p rend="bold italic">Property Law, Smith, Roger J. Fifth Edition - 2006, Pearson - Longman Law Series. </p><p rend="bold italic">Making Sense of Land Law, Stroud, April. First Edition - 2005. Oxford University Press.</p><p rend="bold italic">Modern Land Law, Thompson, M.P. Second Edition - 2003, Oxford University Press.</p></div2><div2 type="bibliography"><head rend="underlined bold">JOURNALS:</head><p rend="bold italic">'Case Report: Supperstone v Hurst', Douglas, Gillian. 36 (Feb) 2006 Family Law, pp. 101 - 103. </p><p rend="bold italic">'Quantum in Gissing v Gissing Constructive Trusts', Gardner, Simon. 2004 L.Q.R 540, West Law UK. </p><p rend="bold italic">'Property Law Update - What's a fair share: Supperstone v Hurst', Peters, Edward. 155 (August) N.L.J. 2005, No. 7189, Pg. 1248.</p><p rend="bold italic">'Constructive Trusts, Estoppel and the Family Home', Thompson, M.P. 2004 Conv. 496, West Law UK.</p><p rend="bold italic">'The Ebb and Flow of Trusts and Estoppel', Dunn, Alison. Vol. 15 Dec. 2004 Issue 2, Kings College Law Journal pp. 436 - 445, Library E- resources, Journals. </p></div2></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
