<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_0086a" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Table of Cases</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">Language used in quote: <foreign id="English">English</foreign></note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">deleted: header: student number
</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">1</p><p n="date">2006-01</p><p n="module title">The Modern English Legal System</p><p n="module code">LA115</p><p n="genre family">Critique</p><p n="discipline">Law</p><p n="disciplinary group">SS</p><p n="grade">M</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">1242</p><p n="number of s-units">51</p><p n="number of p">26</p><p n="number of tables">0</p><p n="number of figures">0</p><p n="number of block quotes">1</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">0</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">8</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">24.4</p><p n="average s-units per p">2.0</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">f</p><p n="year of birth">1984</p><p n="first language">English</p><p n="education">OSA</p><p n="course">Law</p><p n="student ID">0086</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><div1 type="front text"><head rend="underlined bold">TABLE OF CASES</head><p rend="bold italic">Beswick v Beswick [1968] AC 58 (HL)</p><p rend="bold italic">Black Clawson International Ltd v Papierwerke Waldhof-Aschaffenburg AG [1975] AC 591(HL)</p><p rend="bold italic">Church of Scientology of California v Johnson - Smith [1972] 1 QB 522</p><p rend="bold italic">Davis v Johnson [1979] AC 264 (HL)</p><p rend="bold italic">Director of Public Prosecutions v Bull [1994] 4 All ER 411 (DC)</p><p><hi rend="bold italic">Pepper (Inspector of Taxes) v Hart and Related Appeals </hi><hi rend="italic">[1993] AC 593(HL); [1993] 1 All ER 42; [1992] 3 WLR 1032</hi></p><p rend="bold italic">R v Deegan (Desmond Garcia) [1998] 2 Cr App R 121 (CA (Crim Div))</p><p rend="bold italic">R v Secretary of State for the Environment, Transport and the Regions (Ex Parte Spath Holme Ltd) [2001] 2 WLR 15 (HL)</p><p rend="bold italic">Regina v Warwickshire County Council, Ex Parte Johnson [1993] AC 583(HL)</p><p rend="bold italic">Three Rivers District Council v Bank of England (No 2) [1996] 2 All ER 363</p><p rend="bold italic">Wilson v Secretary of State for Trade and Industry a.k.a Wilson v First County Trust Ltd (No. 2) [2004] 1 AC 816 (HL); [2003] 2 All ER 97; [2003] UKHL 40</p></div1></front><body><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">INTRODUCTION</head><p n="p1.26"><s n="s1.3;p1.26"><hi rend="underlined">Pepper v Hart</hi> - The taxpayers were teachers at Malvern College who could educate their sons at the school at one-fifth the normal fees. </s><s n="s2.3;p1.26">The question raised was the precise amount of tax to be paid for the benefit received. </s><s n="s3.3;p1.26">The Court of Appeal held the cost for the employer, i.e., school was the average cost and gave a ruling in favour of the school; and the House of Lords reversed the opinion deciding in favour of the taxpayers i.e., the cost of benefit was the marginal cost; and for doing this it relied on parliamentary debates, or <hi rend="italic">Hansard</hi>. </s></p><p n="p2.26"><s rend="bold" n="s1.1;p2.26">The ratio laid down in the case was reference to <hi rend="italic">Hansard</hi> would be permitted only under the following circumstances: </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p3.26"><s rend="bold" n="s1.1;p3.26">where there is an ambiguity or obscurity as to the meaning of the legislation or when the literal meaning leads to absurdity; and </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p4.26"><s rend="bold" n="s1.1;p4.26">the statement is the statement of a minister or other promoter of the bill; and </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p5.26"><s rend="bold" n="s1.2;p5.26">the statement relied is clear. </s><ref target="BAWE_0086a-ftnote.001"/><s n="s2.2;p5.26"> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0086a-ftnote.001"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1"><hi rend="underlined">Pepper v Hart</hi> [1993] AC 593 @ 640 </s></p></note><p n="p6.26"><s n="s1.4;p6.26">The importance of the case lies in that, the court had to decide if they could have recourse to <hi rend="italic">Hansard</hi> in deciding a case, and if did, would it infringe Art. </s><s n="s2.4;p6.26">9 of the Bill of Rights (1688), i.e., "the freedom of speech, and debates or proceedings in the Parliament, ought not to be impeached or questioned in any court or place out of Parliament." </s><ref target="BAWE_0086a-ftnote.002"/><s n="s3.4;p6.26">(The judges ruled out any infringement of Art. </s><s n="s4.4;p6.26">9) </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0086a-ftnote.002"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Taken from <hi rend="underlined">Church of Scientology of California v Johnson - Smith</hi> [1972] 1 QB 522 @ 523 </s></p></note><p n="p7.26"><s n="s1.2;p7.26"><hi rend="italic">Hansard</hi> is defined as "The name by which the Official Report of Parliamentary Debates is customarily referred to".<ref target="BAWE_0086a-ftnote.003"/> It is not the understanding of the individual Members of Parliament on the present state of law of, but the words, which provide evidence of the purpose of the legislation. </s><s n="s2.2;p7.26">It is one of the extrinsic aids to statutory interpretation, now widely considered after this famous decision. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0086a-ftnote.003"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Oxford Dictionary of Law, Fourth Edition 1997, Oxford University Press, Pg 210 </s></p></note></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">APPROACHES TO STATUTORY INTERPRETATION</head><p n="p8.26"><s n="s1.2;p8.26">Statutory interpretation is the process by which the courts attach meaning to a particular statute in a case before it. </s><s n="s2.2;p8.26">There are three rules of statutory interpretation: - </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p9.26"><s n="s1.1;p9.26"><hi rend="underlined">Literal Rule</hi> - The courts uses the actual words in the statute and gives meaning to it irrespective of the result produced. </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p10.26"><s n="s1.2;p10.26"><hi rend="underlined">Golden Rule</hi> - The courts construes the statute as a whole to give effect to the legislation. </s><s n="s2.2;p10.26">This can be used only if literal meaning leads to absurdity. </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p11.26"><s n="s1.1;p11.26"><hi rend="underlined">Mischief Rule</hi> - If there is any mischief in the common law, which the statute intended to remedy, the courts will give effect to it. </s></p><p n="p12.26"><s n="s1.2;p12.26">Though they are referred to as rules, they are only guiding principles. </s><s n="s2.2;p12.26">And they have to be used in the order of priority. </s></p><p n="p13.26"><s n="s1.1;p13.26">There are two approaches to interpretation: </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p14.26"><s n="s1.1;p14.26"><hi rend="underlined">Literal Approach</hi> - This approach suggests, the judge, unless under rare circumstances, should use only the words of the statute to give meaning to it. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p15.26"><s n="s1.1;p15.26"><hi rend="underlined">Purposive Approach</hi> - This approach suggests the judge can look at words outside the statute to give effect to the true intention of the legislature. </s></p><p n="p16.26"><s n="s1.2;p16.26">The English Law is said to use the literal approach to interpretation. </s><s n="s2.2;p16.26">But now, for matters concerning the European Community (EC) legislation and also the domestic legislation designed to implement Community legislation purposive approach is adopted.<ref target="BAWE_0086a-ftnote.004"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0086a-ftnote.004"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">The English Legal System, Slapper &amp; Kelly, Seventh Edition 2004, Pg 193 - 194. </s></p></note></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">USE OF HANSARD </head><p n="p17.26"><s n="s1.1;p17.26">The courts never permitted using <hi rend="italic">Hansard</hi> as an aid to interpretation until the 1990s as it was thought to be unreliable. </s></p><p n="p18.26"><s n="s1.1;p18.26">In the case of <hi rend="underlined">Davis v Johnson</hi><ref target="BAWE_0086a-ftnote.005"/>, Lord Denning MR, wanted to change this and dissented the view that parliamentary material should not be used and said it would throw light on the matter if used. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0086a-ftnote.005"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">[1979] AC 264 </s></p></note><p n="p19.26"><s n="s1.3;p19.26">But when the case went before the House of Lords Lord Scarman reversed the judgement and said that use of parliamentary material did not promote clarity and was unreliable and hence not to be used. </s><s n="s2.3;p19.26">This was the position on until the decision in <hi rend="underlined">Pepper v Hart</hi><ref target="BAWE_0086a-ftnote.006"/>, which allowed reference to <hi rend="italic">Hansard</hi> as an aid to interpretation. </s><s n="s3.3;p19.26">The House of Lords reversed its earlier decisions in <hi rend="underlined">Beswick v Beswick</hi><ref target="BAWE_0086a-ftnote.007"/>, <hi rend="underlined">Black-Clawson v Papierwerke Waldohf-Aschaffenburg AG</hi><ref target="BAWE_0086a-ftnote.008"/>, and <hi rend="underlined">Davis v Johnson</hi><ref target="BAWE_0086a-ftnote.009"/>. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0086a-ftnote.006"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">[1993] AC 593 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0086a-ftnote.007"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">[1968] AC 58 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0086a-ftnote.008"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">[1975] AC 591 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0086a-ftnote.009"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">[1979] AC 264 </s></p></note><p n="p20.26"><s n="s1.1;p20.26">Lord Browne- Wilkinson, delivering the leading judgement in the case said: </s></p><quote lang="English">"I suspect most, cases references to Parliamentary materials will not throw any light on the matter. But in a few cases it may emerge that the very question was considered by Parliament in passing the legislation. Why in such a case should the courts blind themselves to a clear indication of what Parliament intended in using those words?" <ref target="BAWE_0086a-ftnote.010"/></quote><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0086a-ftnote.010"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1"><hi rend="underlined">Pepper (Inspector of Taxes) v Hart and Related Appeals</hi> [1993] AC 596 @ 634 - 5 </s></p></note><p n="p21.26"><s n="s1.3;p21.26">This suggests that in case of any ambiguity, instead of giving a wrong interpretation of Parliamentary intention, the court can have recourse to parliamentary debates. </s><s n="s2.3;p21.26">The courts have, after all to give effect to the Parliament's intention. </s><s n="s3.3;p21.26">But this has to be construed very strictly and used only in the cases set out above and when the other internal aids fail to give meaning. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">ARGUMENTS AGAINST THE USE OF HANSARD</head><p n="p22.26"><s n="s1.3;p22.26">But there is one major drawback of the use of <hi rend="italic">Hansard</hi> addressed by almost all the judges and other critics time and again, which is that the use of <hi rend="italic">Hansard</hi> greatly increases the cost of litigation. </s><s n="s2.3;p22.26">While I accede to this view I feel that since parliamentary materials are to be used only in limited cases as set out in the decision it will not lead to increased costs in all cases. </s><s n="s3.3;p22.26">But this is not always true as can be seen from a multitude of cases where lawyers have tried to use <hi rend="italic">Hansard</hi> but in vain.<ref target="BAWE_0086a-ftnote.011"/> There are cases where <hi rend="italic">Hansard</hi> was used even when there was no ambiguity in construing the statute.<ref target="BAWE_0086a-ftnote.012"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0086a-ftnote.011"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">'Pepper v Hart A Re-examination', Steyn, Johan 21 Oxford Journal of Legal Studies, 2001, pg 59 @ 63 - 64 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0086a-ftnote.012"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1"><hi rend="underlined">R v Warwickshire County Council, Ex Parte Johnson</hi> [1993] AC 583 </s></p></note><p n="p23.26"><s n="s1.3;p23.26">Another drawback, as argued by the commentators is that by using the words of the ministers, they may get the power to make laws. </s><s n="s2.3;p23.26">This goes against the separation of powers between the Executive and the Judiciary. </s><s n="s3.3;p23.26">It is also thought of as encroaching upon the judicial functions. <ref target="BAWE_0086a-ftnote.013"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0086a-ftnote.013"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">'Pepper v Hart and its Constitutional Principle', Kavanagh, Aileen, Law Quarterly Review 2005 @ 102 </s></p></note></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">USE OF HANSARD AFTER PEPPER V HART</head><p n="p24.26"><s n="s1.2;p24.26">The cases where <hi rend="italic">Hansard</hi> was used were <hi rend="underlined">Warwickshire County Council, Ex Parte Johnson</hi><ref target="BAWE_0086a-ftnote.014"/>, a case that came before the House of Lords immediately after <hi rend="underlined">Pepper v Hart</hi><ref target="BAWE_0086a-ftnote.015"/>. </s><s n="s2.2;p24.26">But there were cases where <hi rend="italic">Hansard</hi> could not be used since they did not satisfy the requirements. <ref target="BAWE_0086a-ftnote.016"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0086a-ftnote.014"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">[1993] AC 583 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0086a-ftnote.015"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">[1993] AC 593 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0086a-ftnote.016"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1"><hi rend="underlined">R v Secretary of State for the Environment, Transport and the Regions (Ex Parte Spath Holme Ltd)</hi> [2001] 2 WLR 15 (HL); <hi rend="underlined">R v Deegan</hi> [1998] 2 Cr App R 121 (CA); <hi rend="underlined">Director of Public Prosecutions v Bull</hi> [1994] 4 ALL ER 411 (DC) </s></p></note><p n="p25.26"><s n="s1.4;p25.26">In <hi rend="underlined">Three Rivers District Council v Bank of England (No.2)</hi><ref target="BAWE_0086a-ftnote.017"/> it was held that the rule on <hi rend="italic">Hansard</hi> must be relaxed in order to give effect to some particular EC Directive. </s><s n="s2.4;p25.26">Held, it could be used to determine the purpose of the statute. </s><s n="s3.4;p25.26">Similarly, in the case of <hi rend="underlined">Wilson v First County Trust</hi><ref target="BAWE_0086a-ftnote.018"/>, HL considered for the first time if parliamentary material could be used to ascertain if a statutory provision was compatible with the ECHR<ref target="BAWE_0086a-ftnote.019"/>. </s><s n="s4.4;p25.26">But it was held that it was not appropriate for the court to use <hi rend="italic">Hansard</hi> here. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0086a-ftnote.017"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">[1996] 2 All ER 363 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0086a-ftnote.018"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">[2003] 4 All ER 97 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0086a-ftnote.019"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">European Convention on Human Rights </s></p></note></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">CONCLUSION</head><p n="p26.26"><s n="s1.3;p26.26">In conclusion I submit that though <hi rend="italic">Hansard</hi> as an aid to interpretation has proven itself useful, in most cases a plain reading of the statute will suffice. </s><s n="s2.3;p26.26">Another important aspect to be noted is the ministers have to now take greater care to see that what they say reflects the purpose of the Act and this involves greater time and money for the Parliament since it has to look at all the notes and see to it that it does not include unnecessary material since the court may rely upon these in future. </s><s n="s3.3;p26.26">Not only this, the use of <hi rend="italic">Hansard</hi> may not prove to be useful; and in many, in fact most occasions the courts have refused to use it since it does not shed any light on the matter. </s></p></div1></body><back><div1 type="bibliography"><head rend="underlined bold">BIBLIOGRAPHY</head><p rend="bold italic">Lecture Notes, MELS, Edmunds, Steven and Reddish, Michael. 2005</p><p rend="bold italic">Oxford Dictionary of Law, Edited by Elizabeth. A. Martin (New Edition). Fourth Edition - 1997, Oxford University Press.</p><p rend="bold italic">Smith, Bailey &amp; Gunn on The Modern English Legal System, Bailey, S.H., Ching, J.P.L., Gunn, M.J., and Ormerod, D.C. Fourth Edition - 2002, London Sweet &amp; Maxwell. </p><p rend="bold italic">The English Legal Process, Ingman, Terence. Tenth Edition - 2004, Oxford University Press.</p><p rend="bold italic">The English Legal System, Slapper, Gary and Kelly, David. Seventh Edition - 2004, Cavendish Publishing Limited.</p><p rend="bold italic">The Law Making Process, Zander, Michael. Sixth Edition - 2004, Cambridge University Press.</p><p rend="bold italic">Westlaw UK, Library E-Resources, Law Database, 'Pepper v Hart and its Constitutional Principle', Kavanagh, Aileen. Law Quarterly Review 2005</p><p rend="bold italic">Library E-Journals, Oxford Journal of Legal Studies, Pepper v Hart; A Re-examination, Steyn, Johan. Vol. 2, No.1 (2001) pp 59 - 72</p></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
