<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_0086c" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Introduction</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">deleted: header: student number, course name and number; footer: page numbers
</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">1</p><p n="date">2006-04</p><p n="module title">Introduction to Legal Theory</p><p n="module code">LA116</p><p n="genre family">Essay</p><p n="discipline">Law</p><p n="disciplinary group">SS</p><p n="grade">M</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">1240</p><p n="number of s-units">62</p><p n="number of p">12</p><p n="number of tables">0</p><p n="number of figures">0</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">0</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">0</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">20.0</p><p n="average s-units per p">5.2</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">f</p><p n="year of birth">1984</p><p n="first language">English</p><p n="education">OSA</p><p n="course">Law</p><p n="student ID">0086</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><div1 type="front-back-matter"><head rend="underlined bold">TABLE OF CASES:</head><p rend="bold italic">Alcock v Chief Constable of South Yorkshire [1991] 4 All ER 907</p><p rend="bold italic">Bourhill v Young [1943] AC 92</p><p rend="bold italic">Chadwick v British Railways Board [1967] 2 All ER 97</p><p rend="bold italic">Hedley Byrne &amp; Co Ltd. v Heller and Partners Ltd [1964] AC 465</p><p rend="bold italic">King v Phillips [1953] 1 QB 429</p><p rend="bold italic">McLoughlin v O' Brian [1983] AC 410</p><p rend="bold italic">Page v Smith [1996] 1 AC 155</p><p rend="bold italic">Rookes v Barnard [1964] AC 1129</p><p rend="bold italic">Spartan Steel &amp; Metal Alloys v Martin &amp; Co. [1972] QB 27</p><p rend="bold italic">Smith v Eric S. Bush [1990] 1 AC 831</p><p rend="bold italic">White v Chief Constable of South Yorkshire [1999] 1 All ER 1</p><p rend="bold italic">White v Jones [1995] 1 All ER 691</p></div1></front><body><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">INTRODUCTION:</head><p n="p1.12"><s n="s1.2;p1.12">Tort is a civil wrong which neither a breach of contract nor a breach of trust. </s><s n="s2.2;p1.12">The main goal of tort is to compensate for injury suffered by the victim and try to put him back to the position had the accident not occurred. </s></p><p n="p2.12"><s n="s1.1;p2.12">In this essay I would look at several areas of law which tort law delves into, its implications and what can be done to improve the law. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">AREAS OF TORT LAW:</head><p n="p3.12"><s n="s1.7;p3.12">Negligence is one of the important areas under tort law. </s><s n="s2.7;p3.12">A person owes a duty of care to several persons and would be liable if he breaches the same. </s><s n="s3.7;p3.12">There are special duties owed, e.g. in cases of nervous shock. </s><s n="s4.7;p3.12">But there is a tension as to the degree of proximity (the "neighbour principle") required to be liable under this. </s><s n="s5.7;p3.12">Until recently the 'foreseeability of injury by shock' was the basis of compensating victims of nervous shock (<hi rend="underlined italic">King v Phillips [1953] 1 QB 429)</hi><ref target="BAWE_0086c-ftnote.001"/>. </s><s n="s6.7;p3.12">Now there are 'primary victims' who are at a risk of physical damage and 'secondary victims' who are not at risk of suffering physical damage, but saw or heard the accident, which caused the shock<ref target="BAWE_0086c-ftnote.002"/>. </s><s n="s7.7;p3.12">He can only recover if he is a person of "normal fortitude" and "customary phlegm"<ref target="BAWE_0086c-ftnote.003"/>. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0086c-ftnote.001"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Tort, Hedley, Steve. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">Fourth Edition - 2004, LexisNexis Butterworths @ pg 79 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0086c-ftnote.002"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Casebook on Torts, Kidner, Richard. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">Eighth Edition - 2004, Oxford University Press. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0086c-ftnote.003"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1"><hi rend="underlined">Bourhill v Young</hi> [1943] AC 92; <hi rend="underlined">Page v Smith</hi> [1996] 1 AC 155 </s></p></note><p n="p4.12"><s n="s1.6;p4.12">In <hi rend="underlined italic">Page v Smith</hi><ref target="BAWE_0086c-ftnote.004"/> the claimant (primary victim) did not suffer any physical damage in the accident but saw a revival of chronic fatigue syndrome, which he had suffered a few years before. </s><s n="s2.6;p4.12">The defendant was held liable for psychiatric illness. </s><s n="s3.6;p4.12">It was laid down that the defendant could only be liable if the risk of psychiatric illness was reasonably foreseen or the risk of physical injury was foreseen. </s><s n="s4.6;p4.12">There was the earlier case of <hi rend="underlined italic">Bourhill v Young</hi><ref target="BAWE_0086c-ftnote.005"/> where the claimant who was just a bystander miscarried as a result of witnessing a motorcycle accident from a distance. </s><s n="s5.6;p4.12">Held, was not a foreseeable victim. </s><s n="s6.6;p4.12">The law is rather absurd because had she suffered physical injury she could have recovered for that as well as her mental trauma but since she didn't, she could not recover for anything<ref target="BAWE_0086c-ftnote.006"/>. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0086c-ftnote.004"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">[1996] 1 AC 155 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0086c-ftnote.005"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">[1943] AC 92 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0086c-ftnote.006"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.3;pn1.1">Tort, Hedley, Steve. </s><s n="s2.3;pn1.1">Fourth Edition - 2004, LexisNexis Butterworths @ pg. </s><s n="s3.3;pn1.1">80 </s></p></note><p n="p5.12"><s n="s1.14;p5.12"><hi rend="underlined italic">Alcock v Chief Constable of South Yorkshire</hi><ref target="BAWE_0086c-ftnote.007"/> was a case where the relatives and friends of Hillsborough disaster victims brought claims. </s><s n="s2.14;p5.12">It failed because there was no sufficient proximity in 'time and space'. </s><s n="s3.14;p5.12">The people did not suffer injury as a result of witnessing the incident in its "immediate aftermath". </s><s n="s4.14;p5.12">The court also held that the people who brought the claims had no close tie of love and affection. </s><s n="s5.14;p5.12">It was restricted to spouses, parent and children of victims. </s><s n="s6.14;p5.12">Psychiatric illness resulting from witnessing the incident on TV was not actionable. </s><s n="s7.14;p5.12">The judges may have had the floodgates issue at the back of their mind when they limited the persons who could bring an action for damages. </s><s n="s8.14;p5.12">In <hi rend="underlined italic">Chadwick v British Railways Board</hi><ref target="BAWE_0086c-ftnote.008"/> the claimant assisted in the Lewisham Train crash by giving injections to the injured by crawling between the two collided trains. </s><s n="s9.14;p5.12">He suffered clinical depression as a result of witnessing the incident and committed suicide. </s><s n="s10.14;p5.12">His wife could recover since rescuers were primary victims. </s><s n="s11.14;p5.12">Contrasting this is the case of <hi rend="underlined italic">White v Chief Constable of South Yorkshire</hi><ref target="BAWE_0086c-ftnote.009"/> where the policemen who had assisted the victims in the Hillsborough football disaster could not recover for the harm suffered. </s><s n="s12.14;p5.12">Held, rescuers were not primary victims or a special category of people. </s><s n="s13.14;p5.12">But Lord Steyn has said that it should not make a difference because: a rescuer is a rescuer is a rescuer<ref target="BAWE_0086c-ftnote.010"/>. </s><s n="s14.14;p5.12">In <hi rend="underlined italic">McLoughlin v O' Brian</hi><ref target="BAWE_0086c-ftnote.011"/> the House of Lords held, liability was owed only if the claimant was present at the scene of the incident, or was a person who witnessed the incident in the "immediate aftermath" and had ties of love and affection with the victim. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0086c-ftnote.007"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">[1991] 4 All ER 907 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0086c-ftnote.008"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">[1967] 2 All ER 97 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0086c-ftnote.009"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">[1999] 1 All ER 1 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0086c-ftnote.010"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">'Nervous Shock: Wider still &amp; wider?' [1997] CLJ 254 @ pg. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">255. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0086c-ftnote.011"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">[1983] AC 410 </s></p></note><p n="p6.12"><s n="s1.1;p6.12">The 'secondary victims' are to prove that close friends or relatives witnessed a 'shocking' event. </s></p><p n="p7.12"><s n="s1.6;p7.12">Another important area under tort law is Economic loss. </s><s n="s2.6;p7.12">As a principle pure economic loss is not recoverable unless it is consequential to physical loss<ref target="BAWE_0086c-ftnote.012"/>. </s><s n="s3.6;p7.12">This is an area of contract law but tort fills in for the gaps created by contract law. </s><s n="s4.6;p7.12">Here it only compensates losses, but does not restore status quo like under the other areas. </s><s n="s5.6;p7.12">It also redresses the wrongs done by contract law. </s><s n="s6.6;p7.12">Tort law provides remedies for strangers too<ref target="BAWE_0086c-ftnote.013"/>. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0086c-ftnote.012"><p n="pn1.1"><s rend="underlined" n="s1.2;pn1.1">Spartan Steel &amp; Metal Alloys v Martin &amp; Co. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">[1972] QB 27. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0086c-ftnote.013"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Duty of Care &amp; Economic Loss: A wider agenda (1991) 107 LQR 249 @ pg. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">249 </s></p></note><p n="p8.12"><s n="s1.4;p8.12"><hi rend="underlined italic">Hedley Byrne &amp; Co Ltd. v Heller and Partners Ltd</hi>.<ref target="BAWE_0086c-ftnote.014"/> is the leading case which says that a person is responsible for economic loss arising out of negligent misstatement if there is a special relationship between the parties and there is a voluntary assumption of responsibility. </s><s n="s2.4;p8.12">These restrictions are placed reduce the number of cases coming before the court, i.e., the floodgate issue. </s><s n="s3.4;p8.12">If there were a disclaimer then the person is exempt from responsibility; if someone with special skill gives any advice it is reasonably foreseeable that there would be a reliance on the statement<ref target="BAWE_0086c-ftnote.015"/>, making him liable<ref target="BAWE_0086c-ftnote.016"/>. </s><s n="s4.4;p8.12"><hi rend="underlined italic">White v Jones</hi><ref target="BAWE_0086c-ftnote.017"/> says the relationship of a solicitor and beneficiary of will is a fiduciary relationship and a special one<ref target="BAWE_0086c-ftnote.018"/>. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0086c-ftnote.014"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">[1964] AC 465 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0086c-ftnote.015"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1"><hi rend="underlined">Smith v Eric S. Bush</hi> [1990] 1 AC 831 where it could be foreseen that the purchaser would rely on the surveyor's statement even if it was not made to her directly. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0086c-ftnote.016"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Per Lord Morrison in Hedley Byrne v Heller &amp; Partners </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0086c-ftnote.017"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">[1995] 1 All ER 691 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0086c-ftnote.018"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Per Lord Browne Wilkinson in White v Jones </s></p></note><p n="p9.12"><s n="s1.3;p9.12">Another important yet rare area of tort law is awarding punitive damages (exemplary damages). </s><s n="s2.3;p9.12">These are only awarded if they are required for adequately punishing the defendant<ref target="BAWE_0086c-ftnote.019"/>. </s><s n="s3.3;p9.12"><hi rend="underlined italic">Rookes v Barnard</hi><ref target="BAWE_0086c-ftnote.020"/> is the authority on this, it says that punitive damages can only be awarded if the person was a servant of the Government at the time of commission of the tort; he committed it because he figured he would make more money than he would have to pay as damages or there is a statutory award<ref target="BAWE_0086c-ftnote.021"/>. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0086c-ftnote.019"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.3;pn1.1">Tort Law, McBride, Nicholas J &amp; Bagshaw, Roderick. </s><s n="s2.3;pn1.1">Second Edition - 2005, Pearson Longman @ pg. </s><s n="s3.3;pn1.1">673. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0086c-ftnote.020"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">[1964] AC 1129 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0086c-ftnote.021"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.3;pn1.1">Tort Law, McBride, Nicholas J &amp; Bagshaw, Roderick. </s><s n="s2.3;pn1.1">Second Edition - 2005, Pearson Longman @ pg. </s><s n="s3.3;pn1.1">676. </s></p></note></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">CONCLUSION:</head><p n="p10.12"><s n="s1.8;p10.12">Having looked at few important areas under tort law one would think that the law deals with a number of issues. </s><s n="s2.8;p10.12">If a case does not fall under any other civil law, it falls under tort. </s><s n="s3.8;p10.12">But we can see that not only does tort law deal with cases which other branches of law do not deal with but also ones that fall under categories of law, like contract law (economic loss - contractual breach). </s><s n="s4.8;p10.12">Again, the aim of tort law is not to punish people, but to compensate the party and restore status quo. </s><s n="s5.8;p10.12">The award of punitive damages falls under criminal law. </s><s n="s6.8;p10.12">These only increase the number of cases. </s><s n="s7.8;p10.12">But exemplary damages are only awarded rarely. </s><s n="s8.8;p10.12">Usually regular or special damages are awarded. </s></p><p n="p11.12"><s n="s1.2;p11.12">Tort law has been there for centuries and there cannot be a sudden change, the judges cannot say that they would only deal with particular areas and reject the rest; it is expected of them to address the claims of the injured party. </s><s n="s2.2;p11.12">Yet it would be desirable if tort law limited its scope to promote efficiency. </s></p><p n="p12.12"><s n="s1.8;p12.12">Yet another important problem under tort law is it lacks coherence. </s><s n="s2.8;p12.12">When we look at the cases above we can notice that there are conflicting decisions. </s><s n="s3.8;p12.12">Judges mostly decide cases on policy arguments than relying upon precedents. </s><s n="s4.8;p12.12">This leads to incoherence in the law. </s><s n="s5.8;p12.12">But this has been the problem prevailing since times immemorial. </s><s n="s6.8;p12.12">But it would be welcome to see tort law being more coherent, if the judges follow the 'rule of precedents', there would automatically be more coherence. </s><s n="s7.8;p12.12">And also if the law concentrates on its primary aim of compensating for the injuries suffered and tries not to extend the law, then tort law would be more certain. </s><s n="s8.8;p12.12">Extending the law would only increase the cases before it and would make the law inefficient and incoherent which is not desirable. </s></p></div1></body><back><div1 type="bibliography"><head rend="underlined bold">BIBLIOGRAPHY:</head><div2 type="bibliography"><head rend="underlined bold">BOOKS:</head><p rend="bold italic">Casebook on Torts, Kidner, Richard. Eighth Edition - 2004, Oxford University Press.</p><p rend="bold italic">Clerk &amp; Lindsell on Torts, Nineteenth Edition - 2006. Thomson Sweet &amp; Maxwell.</p><p rend="bold italic">Exploring Tort Law, Edited by Madden, Stuart. First Edition - 2005, Cambridge University Press.</p><p rend="bold italic">Tort, Hedley, Steve. Fourth Edition - 2004, LexisNexis Butterworths.</p><p rend="bold italic">Tort, Weir, Tony. First Edition - 2002, Oxford University Press.</p><p rend="bold italic">Tort Law, McBride, Nicholas J &amp; Bagshaw, Roderick. Second Edition - 2005, Pearson Longman.</p></div2><div2 type="bibliography"><head rend="underlined bold">JOURNALS:</head><p rend="bold italic">'Duty of Care &amp; Economic Loss: A Wider Agenda' (1991) 107 LQR 249.</p><p rend="bold italic">'Liability for psychiatric illness after Hillsborough' (1992) 12 OJLS 440.</p><p rend="bold italic">'Negligent misstatements, Negligent Acts &amp; Economic Loss' (1976) 92 LQR 213.</p><p rend="bold italic">'Nervous shock: Wider still &amp; wider?' [1997] CLJ 254</p></div2></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
