<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_0090a" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Post Module Assignment</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">deleted: header: assignment and department name; footer: student number, page numbers
deleted: (4,082 words)
</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">4</p><p n="date">2005-10</p><p n="module title">Context of a Business</p><p n="module code">ES952</p><p n="genre family">Proposal</p><p n="discipline">Engineering</p><p n="disciplinary group">PS</p><p n="grade">M</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">3799</p><p n="number of s-units">149</p><p n="number of p">74</p><p n="number of tables">5</p><p n="number of figures">7</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">5</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">27</p><p n="abstract present">abstract present</p><p n="average words per s-unit">25.5</p><p n="average s-units per p">2.0</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">m</p><p n="year of birth">1981</p><p n="first language">English</p><p n="education">OSA</p><p n="course">Engineering Business Management</p><p n="student ID">0090</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><titlePart><hi rend="bold">POST MODULE ASSIGNMENT</hi><hi rend="italic"> for</hi><hi rend="bold"> CONTEXT OF A BUSINESS<hi rend="italic"> Module Tutor: <name type="tutor name"/></hi></hi><hi rend="bold italic"> By: <name type="student name"/> Engineering Business Management</hi><hi rend="bold italic"> Student no. <name type="student ID"/> Context Of A Business</hi></titlePart></titlePage><div1 type="toc" n="3"><head rend="bold">CONTENTS</head><p/></div1><titlePage><docTitle><titlePart rend="bold">SYSTECH INTERNATIONAL</titlePart></docTitle></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="abstract"><head rend="bold">1 EXECUTIVE SUMMARY:</head><p n="p1.74"><s n="s1.3;p1.74"><hi rend="italic">Systech Intl.'s</hi> proposal states that it is a start - up company giving AMC 's (Annual Maintenance Contracts) and IT services. </s><s n="s2.3;p1.74">It also is an authorized service centre for Dell and IBM. The company's major services include maintaining networks, PC's, databases etc. and also giving software consultancy on mainly sale &amp; purchase of ERP software. </s><s n="s3.3;p1.74">In view of the following points taken from the proposal, modifications/further suggestions have been made in the subsequent chapters: </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p2.74"><s n="s1.2;p2.74">__The most eminent flaw seen in the proposal of Systech Intl. lied in the scope of the project. </s><s n="s2.2;p2.74">Though a substantial amount (£ 700,000) of funds were provided, the ideas and scope chosen for the service were not big or imaginative enough so as to utilize the cash reserves profitably. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p3.74"><s n="s1.1;p3.74">__Though the chosen sector of IT services holds promise, but inclusion of Annual Maintenance Contract (AMC's) services and service centres (IBM &amp; Dell) makes the project less lucrative as the chances of developing a core competency diminishes. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p4.74"><s n="s1.1;p4.74">__Out of all the services given by Systech Intl., the software services sector is the most viable but this fact is not built upon in the proposal where only a mere mention of ERP sale and purchase consultancy is given without delving on the intricacies involved. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p5.74"><s n="s1.2;p5.74">__ Systech's proposal does include some innovative ideas like the Employee Development Programme (EDP), which provides the opportunity for two of its employees for further study. </s><s n="s2.2;p5.74">The categorization of services into Club, Premier and Economy is also a good way of giving solutions to each customer according to their needs. </s></p><p n="p6.74"><s n="s1.1;p6.74">The market for the software/IT services is highly competitive so targeting the right sectors and developing partnerships is critically important for any organization even more so for a start up like Systech Intl. </s></p><p n="p7.74"><s n="s1.2;p7.74">The following chapters have considered Systech Intl. to be purely a software services company providing service to primarilary SME's. </s><s n="s2.2;p7.74">It contains analysis, reflection, suitable recommendations and modifications to Systech Intl.'s business proposal. </s></p><p n="p8.74"><s rend="italic" n="s1.1;p8.74">Note: Systech Intl. will be called SI for the remaining course of the assignment. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">2 BUSINESS DESCRIPTION</head><p n="p9.74"><s n="s1.2;p9.74">Greenley (1986) suggests that the mission statement has several aims, including: to provide the purpose for the organization; to express the philosophy that will guide the business; the articulate the vision of where the firm will be in the future; to define the business domain, i.e., the customer groups and needs, and the technology to be employed; and to motivate employees by providing them with a clear sense of purpose and direction. </s><s n="s2.2;p9.74">(Blackwell encyclopedia dictionary of marketing, 1997, p. 135) </s></p><p n="p10.74"><s n="s1.3;p10.74">A mission statement gives a sense of direction to the organisation. </s><s n="s2.3;p10.74">The vision statement of SI was good and bad in parts. </s><s n="s3.3;p10.74">Though it did capture the essence of a services company i.e. to be customer focussed, it lacked the insight required to be the driving force behind the company. </s></p><p n="p11.74"><s n="s1.1;p11.74">The following mission statement, like the previous one, captures the essence of the relationship between SI and its customers while succinctly explaining the new focus area for the company. </s></p><div2><head>2.1 Mission:</head><p rend="bulleted" n="p12.74"><s n="s1.1;p12.74">__Purpose: Systech Intl. provides fast and reliable software solutions and services to the local businesses. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p13.74"><s n="s1.1;p13.74">__Vision: By providing fast response, informed expertise and consistent high quality solutions we can develop Systech Intl. into a centre of excellence in the minds of the customers. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p14.74"><s n="s1.1;p14.74">__Mission: To be the leading provider of computer related solutions and services to the local business through our experienced people and world-class technology. </s></p></div2><div2><head>2.2 Objectives:</head><list type="bulleted"><item>__To make Systech International into a global supplier of software services to the industry.</item><item>__To turn Systech Intl. into a centre of excellence in the minds of the customers.</item><item>__To develop ingenious software along with being an excellent solutions provider in the future.</item><item>__To forge partnerships with world's leading software development companies and attain highest levels of certification in the next 2 years.</item><item>__To be an intellectual and social asset to the community and the environment.</item></list><p n="p15.74"/></div2><div2><head>2.3 Strategy:</head><p n="p16.74"><s n="s1.3;p16.74">Strategy encompasses the action plan required to achieve the mission and objectives of a company. </s><s n="s2.3;p16.74">The strategy of SI's proposed plan was very rightly based on being customer focused as this could prove to be a critical competitive advantage, specially in a sector like software services where there are both small and big companies competing for the market share. </s><s n="s3.3;p16.74">Hence the following shall be the core strategy of the company. </s></p><list type="bulleted"><item>__World-class technology - By being at the cutting edge of latest techniques and technologies.</item><item>__Building Relationships - By listening, anticipating, responding and following through with our customers, partners and each other.</item><item>__Customised Solutions - By developing and providing superior customer solutions tailor-made for every need.</item></list></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">3 BUSINESS ENVIRONMENT</head><div2><head>3.1 <hi rend="bold">Marketplace</hi></head><div3><head>3.1.1 The software vs. software services Industry</head><p n="p17.74"><s n="s1.3;p17.74">The software services providers, though being a part of the software sector have very different business models. </s><s n="s2.3;p17.74">They experience less significant economies of scale. </s><s n="s3.3;p17.74">They have a highly variable cost structure and mid-to-low gross margins (25% for system integrators, 35% for outsourcers), as their delivery model is more customised to clients' needs and more people-intensive whereas software has very significant returns to scale with relatively high gross margins (typically around 80%) (Sector Competitive Analysis Report 2004, p.6) making software development a more lucrative market to be into. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0090a-fig.001"><head rend="bold">Figure 1: Global Software &amp; Services Industry Value</head></figure><p n="p18.74"><s n="s1.3;p18.74">As evident from figure 1, that barring the slight dip in 2001-2002 the global software and services sector has been growing roughly at 10% for the past four years. </s><s n="s2.3;p18.74">Analysts expect the industry to grow at a "modest rate of 7% for 2003-2007" (Sector Competitive Analysis Report 2004, p.10). </s><s n="s3.3;p18.74">This shows that the software services sector, which anyways works on a tight margin, can expect to have even tighter margins making it a dicey proposition from a profitability perspective. </s></p><p n="p19.74"><s n="s1.1;p19.74">If we take a look at table 1 below, we clearly see that software services has the lion's share of the industry with 56.3%, but as stated above have only about 25%-35% margin making it more labour intensive. </s></p><table id="BAWE_0090a-tab.001"><head rend="bold">Table 1: Global Software &amp; services Group Segmentation</head><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p20.74"><s n="s1.1;p20.74">Thus for SI to start, survive and flourish it has to either find completely new ideas to do business or find a more niche segment to provide services for. </s></p></div3><div3><head>3.1.2 The software services sector in the UK</head><p n="p21.74"><s n="s1.3;p21.74">Globally the software services sector has revenue worth £ 292 billion, and at £32.9 billion in 2003 the U.K. software and computer services sector is the largest in Western Europe. </s><s n="s2.3;p21.74">In 2002 it represented 8% of global consumption, 3% of U.K. GDP and employed about 600,000 people. </s><s n="s3.3;p21.74">(Sector Competitive Analysis report 2004, p.5). </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0090a-fig.002"><head rend="bold">Figure 2: Computer Services Concentration in U.K</head></figure><p n="p22.74"><s n="s1.1;p22.74">From fig.2 we can clearly see that the smaller and/or lesser-known companies comprise of 52% of the sector, which is good and bad for SI. The figures reveal that there is an opportunity for SI to garner some market share but as there are lots of small companies like SI in the fray, the competition is cut throat. </s></p></div3><div3><head>3.1.3 Future of the sector</head><p n="p23.74"><s n="s1.2;p23.74">The global computer services market is maturing, with growth rates dropping from the mid teens in the late 1990s (15% CAGR 1997-2000)1 to single digits more recently (2% CAGR 2001-03), with the system integration sub-sector being more affected than the outsourcing one. </s><s n="s2.2;p23.74">(Sector Competitive Analysis Report 2004, p.6) </s></p><table id="BAWE_0090a-tab.002"><head rend="bold">Table 2: UK software market value forecast</head><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p24.74"><s n="s1.1;p24.74">As the system integration services mature during the next few years it is imperative for Systech Intl. to branch into software development and find new sectors to provide services to which again is an onerous task considering that market share, growth and profits only come after obtaining a certain level of expertise which comes usually after quite a few years. </s></p></div3><div3><head>3.1.4 Systech International's TOWS matrix analysis</head><p n="p25.74"><s n="s1.1;p25.74">A TOWS matrix analysis is an extension to the SWOT analysis whereby it gives more structured strategy to be employed in accordance with the strengths, weaknesses etc. </s></p><table id="BAWE_0090a-tab.003"><head rend="bold">Table 3: TOWS matrix</head><row><cell/></row></table><p rend="bulleted" n="p26.74"><s n="s1.1;p26.74">- The <hi rend="italic">WT</hi> strategy is aimed to minimise both weakness and threats. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p27.74"><s n="s1.1;p27.74">- The <hi rend="italic">WO</hi> strategy is aimed to minimize weakness and maximize opportunity. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p28.74"><s n="s1.1;p28.74">- The <hi rend="italic">ST</hi> strategy is based on reassessing strengths in relation to threats. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p29.74"><s n="s1.2;p29.74">- The <hi rend="italic">SO</hi> strategy, shows insight into possible actions that will build upon advantages available. </s><s n="s2.2;p29.74">(Adcock, <hi rend="italic">et al</hi> 1998, p.408) </s></p></div3></div2><div2><head>3.2 <hi rend="bold">Competition</hi></head><p n="p30.74"><s n="s1.3;p30.74">Sl can service a number of companies ranging across various sectors. </s><s n="s2.3;p30.74">The following table summarizes and analyses companies seen as competitors. </s><s n="s3.3;p30.74">This is considering that SI chooses to go into any of the top two sectors consuming software services i.e. financial services and manufacturing [see fig.4] </s></p><table id="BAWE_0090a-tab.004"><head rend="bold">Table 4: Summary of competitors</head><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p31.74"><s n="s1.3;p31.74">The competitor selection has been bearing in mind that SI is a start up hence immediate competition will be SME's. </s><s n="s2.3;p31.74">Also as SI philosophy is to have a dynamic work environment so not only annual sales are considered but management style, awards and recognitions etc. are given equal due. </s><s n="s3.3;p31.74">Hence companies like jmc.it and CHP consulting included in the times online best 100 SME's, make up the list of competitors. </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">4 MARKETING PLANS</head><div2><head rend="bold">4.1 4P's</head><p n="p32.74"><s n="s1.2;p32.74">The marketing mix or 4P's are a set of marketing tools that the firm uses to pursue its marketing objectives in the target market (Kotler 1988, p.71). </s><s n="s2.2;p32.74">For SI to grow and succeed in the market a correct mix of the P's is very important. </s></p><div3><head>4.1.1 Product</head><p n="p33.74"><s n="s1.2;p33.74">The product/service offered by SI is that of providing software services to businesses. </s><s n="s2.2;p33.74">If we look at the product life cycle below we will find that the software industry as a whole is entering the maturity stage as it is having a steady growth rate of 7% CAGR (Sector Competitive Analysis Report 2004, p.6) and so is the case with the software services industry. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0090a-fig.003"><head rend="bold">Figure 3: Product Life Cycle</head></figure><p n="p34.74"><s n="s1.1;p34.74">So to prolong the maturity period and not enter the decline stage quickly, SI has to come up with new ideas, new services, be up to date with the latest trends and technologies in the market and also be open to diversifying into newer markets with newer partners. </s></p></div3><div3><head>4.1.2 Price</head><p n="p35.74"><s n="s1.2;p35.74">Being a start up with relatively no new or extraordinary services to offer, SI has to compete on price in order to be successful in the market place. </s><s n="s2.2;p35.74">Among the various pricing strategies that can be used, two stand out for SI. </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p36.74"><s n="s1.2;p36.74">1) As services provided by the company will be more customised, a <hi rend="italic">pricing variation policy</hi> can be used to good effect. </s><s n="s2.2;p36.74">So SI can differ the prices according to time frames or according to the class of service to be given, which was the pricing idea given in the submitted business plan. </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p37.74"><s n="s1.2;p37.74">2) Another type of pricing policy that can be used by SI is that of <hi rend="italic">penetration pricing</hi>. </s><s n="s2.2;p37.74">Using penetration-pricing SI can set a low price for its services to attract a large number of customers. </s></p><p n="p38.74"><s n="s1.2;p38.74">The best price strategy for SI would be a mixture of the above two. </s><s n="s2.2;p38.74">As it will be giving customised solutions, a variation in price is but necessary and as it is a new entrant, a lower price would enable SI to service customers at a lower price. </s></p></div3><div3><head>4.1.3 Place</head><p n="p39.74"><s n="s1.4;p39.74">In the business plan submitted by SI, place in the 4P's was taken as location and it was mentioned that West Midlands will be its setting but actually place in a marketing mix means the various activities that a company undertakes to make the product easily accessible to target customers. </s><s n="s2.4;p39.74">(Kotler 1988, p.74). </s><s n="s3.4;p39.74">Taking cue we can say that for SI, Internet and web services are the biggest distribution channel of its services. </s><s n="s4.4;p39.74">As a distribution channel, the Internet performs all of marketing channels key functions like: </s></p><list type="bulleted"><item>- <hi rend="italic">Information:</hi> gathering and distributing information about forces and actors in the marketing environment.</item><item>- <hi rend="italic">Promotion:</hi> developing and spreading persuasive communications.</item><item>- <hi rend="italic">Contact:</hi> finding and communicating with prospective buyers.</item><item>- <hi rend="italic">Matching:</hi> shaping &amp; fitting to buyers needs.</item><item>- <hi rend="italic">Negotiation:</hi> reaching an agreement on price and other terms of offer.</item></list></div3><div3><head>4.1.4 Promotion</head><p n="p40.74"><s n="s1.2;p40.74">Promotion is an integral part of the marketing plan for any business and is the last of the 4P's. </s><s n="s2.2;p40.74">If we examine the SI business proposal closely, there was a lot of emphasis on promotion with a number of good ideas coming through like: </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p41.74"><s n="s1.2;p41.74">a. </s><s n="s2.2;p41.74">CCC's (Customer Contact Campaigns) - Reach out to the potential customers through forms, pamphlets and then directly mailing them. </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p42.74"><s n="s1.2;p42.74">b. </s><s n="s2.2;p42.74">Print Advertising - Print ads will be created and placed in several industry publications &amp; Yellow pages. </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p43.74"><s n="s1.2;p43.74">c. </s><s n="s2.2;p43.74">Trade Fairs - SYSTECH Intl. will participate in selected local and national fairs &amp; exhibitions, which will provide an opportunity to gain exposure and create awareness among potential clients. </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p44.74"><s n="s1.2;p44.74">d. </s><s n="s2.2;p44.74">Promotional Give-aways - Tying up with community service organizations and giving away free gifts, discounts on special occasions like for fund-raising efforts. </s></p><p n="p45.74"><s n="s1.2;p45.74">Besides these, as SI has money left in the kitty, sponsoring events can be a useful idea as it creates a buzz about the company. </s><s n="s2.2;p45.74">As SI is a software services company, sponsorship of software conferences or inviting guest speakers/experts to discuss the future of the industry can be a good start. </s></p></div3><div3><head>4.1.5 What about the other P's?</head><p n="p46.74"><s n="s1.2;p46.74">According to the extended marketing mix concept of Booms &amp; Britner, the 4P's are more useful for tangible products but the 7P's are more useful for the services industry particularly knowledge intensive ones . </s><s n="s2.2;p46.74">These three are: </s></p><list type="bulleted"><item>__People - people directly or indirectly involved in the consumption of a service.</item><item>__Process - procedure, mechanisms and flow of activities by which services are consumed.</item><item>__Physical environment - the ability and environment in which the service is delivered. (Valuebasedmanagement.net, 2005)</item></list><p n="p47.74"><s n="s1.1;p47.74">Kotler, P. gave the idea of another 4P's, that were probe (researching the market), partition (segmenting the market), prioritize (specifying markets to targets) and position (deciding a role with respect to the target market) (kogan-page.co.uk 2005) </s></p><p n="p48.74"><s n="s1.1;p48.74">There maybe more dimensions and additions to the marketing mix but getting a right balance of each and every element of the mix is important for the future success of SI. </s></p></div3></div2><div2><head rend="bold">4.2 Market segmentation</head><p n="p49.74"><s n="s1.2;p49.74">Though SI's business proposal did carry details of the market segment, the focus of that plan and this report is different as SI is only concentrating on software services now. </s><s n="s2.2;p49.74">Following is the market segment for SI to concentrate on. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0090a-fig.004"><head rend="bold">Figure 4:Computer Services Consumption by Industry</head></figure><p n="p50.74"><s n="s1.3;p50.74">There are various sectors/markets to target for SI as fig.4 shows ranging from media/comm. to financial services. </s><s n="s2.3;p50.74">The Sector competitive analysis report elucidates the difference between the two biggest consumers of the software services in UK i.e. financial services and manufacturing. </s><s n="s3.3;p50.74">It is important to compare and understand the software services needs of both as both have their own model so that SI could target the right sector. </s></p><p n="p51.74"><s n="s1.2;p51.74">In manufacturing companies, the use of software is more standardised without much customisation so system integration services tend to be more standardised and therefore lower cost (Sector Competitive Analysis Report 2004, p.64). </s><s n="s2.2;p51.74">This makes it more viable for a start up like Systech Intl. as it minimizes the vagaries &amp; risks involved. </s></p><p n="p52.74"><s n="s1.4;p52.74">The financial services on the other hand, software tends to be company-specific leading to a high level of custom application development and application integration. </s><s n="s2.4;p52.74">In addition, due to large transaction volumes, applications are developed on platforms that are complex and difficult to deploy. </s><s n="s3.4;p52.74">Thus the system integration services mix in financial services tends to command a price premium over, for example, standard ERP implementations or mid-range server farm deployments (Sector Competitive Analysis Report 2004, p.63). </s><s n="s4.4;p52.74">This makes the finance sector more profitable but also increases the risks involved in undertaking work. </s></p><p n="p53.74"><s n="s1.4;p53.74">The challenge for SI is to clearly reason out what it wants to do. </s><s n="s2.4;p53.74">Does it be safer and chose a manufacturing sector? </s><s n="s3.4;p53.74">Or does it target the more premium financial services sector and increase risks involved? </s><s n="s4.4;p53.74">Or does it make one of the industries as its base for now and move on to the other after a few years? </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">5 OPERATIONAL PLAN</head><div2><head rend="bold">5.1 Operations Strategy</head><p n="p54.74"><s n="s1.1;p54.74">The business plan of SI did not touch upon its operations strategy so following can be a model operational strategy. </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p55.74"><s n="s1.3;p55.74">1. </s><s n="s2.3;p55.74">When a deal is struck between SI and the client, a series of meetings can be held at either of the offices regarding the details of the needs of the client vis-à-vis exact solutions that SI can provide. </s><s n="s3.3;p55.74">If some need of the client is out of the SI expertise domain it can look for other companies that can carry out the service required efficiently. </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p56.74"><s n="s1.2;p56.74">2. </s><s n="s2.2;p56.74">After the initial round of meetings, an exact timeline could be mapped out detailing delivery, installation &amp; training of the softwares. </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p57.74"><s n="s1.2;p57.74">3. </s><s n="s2.2;p57.74">Depending on the length of the project series of review meetings could be planned which are weekly (for small tasks), monthly (for intermediate tasks) and bi-monthly (for overview of the project). </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p58.74"><s n="s1.2;p58.74">4. </s><s n="s2.2;p58.74">Finally after successful completion of the project, after completion checks could be carried out whereby hassle free running of the software is ensured. </s></p><p n="p59.74"><s n="s1.5;p59.74">Whether SI wants to be a part of the manufacturing or financial services sector, partnerships will be the key to company's success. </s><s n="s2.5;p59.74">So, for example, becoming reseller of AutoDesk Inc. can give SI an entry in the modelling software field. </s><s n="s3.5;p59.74">Similarly for project management software it can have a partnership with Primavera Inc., who just have one partner based in London (Primavera Inc. </s><s n="s4.5;p59.74">2005), leaving a lot of scope for potential market entry. </s><s n="s5.5;p59.74">Depending upon the type of industry Systech wants to get into, other big partners like Siebel Systems, Oracle, and Microsoft etc. can be potential partners. </s></p><p n="p60.74"><s n="s1.3;p60.74">Department of Trade &amp; Industry's Intellect campaign is an initiative to present the agenda of SME's primarily to the government and the public (Intellect campaign 2005). </s><s n="s2.3;p60.74">This will be a good idea as the future of the company lies in the future of the SME's and a campaign for the betterment for SME's will be a step in the right direction. </s><s n="s3.3;p60.74">Also being a member of the campaign will expose to industry peers and a chance for alliances could get a further boost. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">5.2 Staffing</head><figure id="BAWE_0090a-fig.005"><head rend="bold">Figure 5: Organisation Structure</head></figure><p n="p61.74"><s n="s1.2;p61.74">SI will have an initial strength of 20 employees, with 6 employees comprising the top management. </s><s n="s2.2;p61.74">The table below summarizes the key positions of the top management with their specified roles in the company. </s></p><table id="BAWE_0090a-tab.005"><head rend="bold">Table 4: Key employees, their roles and skills</head><row><cell/></row></table></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">6 INFRASTRUCTURE AND SUPPORT SYSTEM</head><p n="p62.74"><s n="s1.5;p62.74">As SI is a small software services start up company, its does not have huge infrastructure or support systems requirements, most of which will anyway be online. </s><s n="s2.5;p62.74">For the 20 employees of SI, besides the regular office infrastructure, a dynamic work environment infrastructure would be of paramount importance. </s><s n="s3.5;p62.74">E.H Schien mentioned in his book Organisational Psychology that the notion of a psychological contract implies that the individual has a variety of expectations of the organisation so taking cue; a relaxed work environment should prevail in SI. Provisions like snookering boards, gaming consoles and music rooms will be provided to the employees. </s><s n="s4.5;p62.74">Understanding the general dimensions of service organisations, SI can follow the ten dimensions of service quality - reliability, responsiveness, competence, access, coutesy, communication, credibility, security, understanding the customer, tangibles of service (like physical facilities). </s><s n="s5.5;p62.74">(Schneider and Bowen 1995, p.27) to help it attain highest levels of quality. </s></p><p n="p63.74"><s n="s1.4;p63.74">The basis of SI's growth is its relationship with its customers; hence CRM becomes its most important support system. </s><s n="s2.4;p63.74">But customer relationship is not as easy as it seem as Customer Relationship Management is not about new ways of giving discounts or a place to buy or sell cheaper but it <hi rend="italic">is</hi> about using technology like internet that has the power to change the world to build mutually profitable relationships and strengthen the bond between a business and its customers. </s><s n="s3.4;p63.74">It will be important for SI to use CRM techniques to keep customers coming back to it. </s><s n="s4.4;p63.74">The techniques could be an offer reminder service, order status change alerts and a service that remembers past orders to make reordering easy (Newell 2000, p.80). </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">7 FINANCE</head><p n="p64.74"><s n="s1.1;p64.74">The diagram below shows the allocation of funds by SI in their business plan: </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0090a-fig.006"><head rend="bold">Figure 6: Allocation of funds</head></figure><p n="p65.74"><s n="s1.1;p65.74">If we look at the allocation of the money, we find that it is a good budget as all aspects of the business have been taken care of like rent, salaries, Insurance, licensing etc. but there have been two flaws in budgeting: </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p66.74"><s n="s1.2;p66.74">1. </s><s n="s2.2;p66.74">The salaries considered have only been for six months with a logic that a substantial profit would be earned in the initial six months, leaving enough funds to pay the employees for the rest of the year. </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p67.74"><s n="s1.3;p67.74">2. </s><s n="s2.3;p67.74">Though the inclusion of corpus fund as a good idea, but the amount i.e. £ 200,000 is high. </s><s n="s3.3;p67.74">Some of the money could be utilised in sponsorships for local sporting events thereby creating a small buzz about SI. </s></p><p n="p68.74"><s n="s1.1;p68.74">Taking into account the above remarks the new budget allocation is shown below: </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0090a-fig.007"><head rend="bold">Figure 7: Allocation of funds</head></figure><p rend="ordered" n="p69.74"><s n="s1.2;p69.74">1. </s><s n="s2.2;p69.74">As figure 7 shows, most of the allocation is unchanged except salaries, which are calculated for the entire year now. </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p70.74"><s n="s1.2;p70.74">2. </s><s n="s2.2;p70.74">The Corpus Fund, which was conceived as an emergency money resource has been reduced by £ 50,000. </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p71.74"><s n="s1.2;p71.74">3. </s><s n="s2.2;p71.74">Money kept for future provisions like IPO's have been changed to being used for sponsorships as discussed in section 4.1.4, which has been allocated as £60,000. </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p72.74"><s n="s1.2;p72.74">4. </s><s n="s2.2;p72.74">The budget for marketing &amp; promotions has been increased to £ 70,000, as it is important for SI to establish itself in the minds of its target customers, which can be done by promoting the company. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">8 CONCLUSION</head><p n="p73.74"><s n="s1.3;p73.74">Through the various chapters of this report we have been trying to reason whether Systech international could establish itself in the market or fizzle out under intense competition. </s><s n="s2.3;p73.74">As we saw in the business environment chapter that the software sector is maturing and particularly the services market is highly competitive with so many small companies sweating against each other. </s><s n="s3.3;p73.74">But being a knowledge intensive industry, start ups like Systech International might be able to do really well by catching the industry unaware through an innovative way of providing service or investing in the future softwares. </s></p><p n="p74.74"><s n="s1.1;p74.74">Though lots of facts are still unknown about the company, like price strategy or demand for their services, but SYSTECH Intl. can definitely do well in the marketplace provided it: </s></p><list type="bulleted"><item>__Builds lasting partnerships with its partners.</item><item>__Remains customer focussed.</item><item>__Investing in future &amp; developing softwares.</item><item>__Diversifying within some years to the software development sector, which can give it a dedicated customer base.</item></list></div1></body><back><div1 type="bibliography"><div2 type="bibliography"><head rend="bold">9 BIBLIOGRAPHY</head><p>__Adcock, D., Halborg, A., Ross, C. (1998). <hi rend="italic">Marketing Principles &amp; Practice.</hi>4th ed.</p><p>FT Prentice Hall.</p><p>__Bowen, D.E., Schneider, B. (1995). <hi rend="italic">Winning the Service Game.</hi> Harvard</p><p>Business School Press.</p><p>__Kotler, P. (1988). <hi rend="italic">Marketing management</hi> 6th ed. Prentice Hall.</p><p>__Edited by Lewis, B.R., Littler, D. (1997). <hi rend="italic">The Blackwell Encyclopedic Dictionary of</hi></p><p><hi rend="italic">Marketing</hi>. Blackwell Publishers, Inc.</p><p>__Newell, F. (2000). <hi rend="italic">loyalty.com.</hi> McGraw Hill.</p><p>__Schien, E.H. (1988). <hi rend="italic">Organisational Psychology</hi>. Prentice Hall.</p></div2><div2 type="bibliography"><head rend="bold">10 REFERENCES</head><p>__Department of Trade &amp; Industry. (2004, June 16). <hi rend="italic">Sector Competitive Analysis</hi></p><p><hi rend="italic">Report.</hi> [Online] (URL</p><p><seg type="URL" n="http://www.dti.gov.uk/industries/software/Sector_Competitiveness_Analysis.doc"/>).</p><p>(Accessed 8 October 2005).</p><p>__<hi rend="italic">Company Information.</hi> [Online] (URL</p><p><seg type="URL" n="http://www.hoovers.com/freeuk/tools/bcl/index.xhtml"/>). (Accessed 15 October</p><p>2005).</p><p>__Value based management. (2005, September 18). <hi rend="italic">Extending Marketing Mix</hi></p><p>[Online] (URL</p><p><seg type="URL" n="http://www.valuebasedmanagement.net/methods_booms_bitner_7Ps.html"/>).</p><p>(Accessed 5 November 2005)</p><p>__Groucutt, J., Leadley, P., Forsyth, P. <hi rend="italic">Marketing - Essential Principles • New</hi></p><p><hi rend="italic">Realities.</hi> [Online]. (URL <seg type="URL" n="http://www.kogan-page.co.uk/groucutt/chapter.htm"/>).</p><p>(Accessed 5 November 2005).</p><p>__Primavera Inc. [Online]. (URL <seg type="URL" n="www.primavera.co.uk"/> ) (Accessed 31 October</p><p>2005).</p><p>__<hi rend="italic">Campaigns</hi> Intellect Campaign [Online] (URL</p><p><seg type="URL" n="http://www.intellectuk.org/campaigns/default.asp"/>) (Accessed 1 November 2005).</p><p>__Global software services Industry profile (May 2005). Reference Code- 0199-</p><p>2139.</p><p>ì</p></div2></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
