<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_0092b" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Management Accounting Assignment for non WBS students for 30 Cats</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">Evaluated as candidate compound assignment. Assigned to S4: set of tasks/questions/exercises: non-compound</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">3</p><p n="date">2005-12</p><p n="module title">Management Accounting Part 1</p><p n="module code">IB2240</p><p n="genre family">Explanation</p><p n="discipline">Business</p><p n="disciplinary group">SS</p><p n="grade">M</p><p n="number of authors">2</p><p n="number of words">704</p><p n="number of s-units">32</p><p n="number of p">13</p><p n="number of tables">0</p><p n="number of figures">2</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">0</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">8</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">22.0</p><p n="average s-units per p">2.5</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">complex but non-compound assignment (see notesStmt for details)</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">m</p><p n="year of birth">unknown</p><p n="first language">German</p><p n="education">OSA</p><p n="course">Accounting and Finance</p><p n="student ID">0092</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><docTitle><titlePart rend="underlined bold">Management Accounting Assignment for non <name type="university"/> students for 30 Cats</titlePart></docTitle><titlePart><name type="student name"/> (<name type="student ID"/>)</titlePart></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="section"><p n="p1.13"><s n="s1.2;p1.13">Both 'marginal Costing' and 'full costing' information are methods of valuing and costing stock. </s><s n="s2.2;p1.13">They differ in one conceptual respect: whether fixed manufacturing costs are 'inventoriable' cost, i.e. if they are costs associated with the acquisition and conversion of manufacturing inputs into finished goods (Horngren p.191). </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Marginal vs. Full costing</head><p n="p2.13"><s n="s1.3;p2.13"><hi rend="italic">Marginal Costing</hi> or <hi rend="italic">Variable Costing</hi> considers fixed manufacturing costs as period costs and thus assigns only manufacturing variable costs (direct labour, direct material and variable overheads) to individual products. </s><s n="s2.3;p2.13">Even though fixed overhead costs are part of manufacturing costs, the variable costing information considers them as fixed costs and adds them to the profit and Loss account directly as a lump sum, without assigning these costs to the individual finished goods. </s><s n="s3.3;p2.13">The <hi rend="italic">full costing</hi> or <hi rend="italic">absorption costing</hi> method on the other hand regards fixed manufacturing costs as product costs and allocates them to each individual product. </s></p><p n="p3.13"><s n="s1.2;p3.13">Non-manufacturing costs are considered as fixed costs in both costing methods and added directly to the profit and loss account. </s><s n="s2.2;p3.13">Tables 1 and 2 graphically show the difference between the two costing methods. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0092b-fig.001"><head>Figure 1: full costing</head></figure></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Profitability</head><p n="p4.13"><s n="s1.2;p4.13">The effect on operating profits of the two costing methods will depend on the relation between production and number of sales, because the resulting change in inventory levels is valued differently. </s><s n="s2.2;p4.13">Three scenarios can be analysed. </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p5.13"><s n="s1.3;p5.13">Production = Sales. </s><s n="s2.3;p5.13">If production levels coincide with the number of sales, the inventory will be unchanged as the closing stock will be the same as the opening stock. </s><s n="s3.3;p5.13">Hence profit levels under both methods will be identical. </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p6.13"><s n="s1.4;p6.13">Production > Sales. </s><s n="s2.4;p6.13">This would imply that inventory levels increase and the closing stock will be positive. </s><s n="s3.4;p6.13">As the costs associated with the closing stock can be deferred by one period, the overall production costs in the current period will fall under both methods. </s><s n="s4.4;p6.13">As the Absorption costing method associates fixed costs to each individual product, the deductible variable costs (including fixed overheads), will be greater than the deductible variable costs incurred under the variable costing method (excluding fixed overheads); hence profits under full costing will be larger than under variable costing. </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p7.13"><s n="s1.5;p7.13">Production &lt; Sales. </s><s n="s2.5;p7.13">In this scenario the level of production is not sufficient to face the number of sales and inventories fall. </s><s n="s3.5;p7.13">In order to cover the "higher than production" number of sales a greater amount of fixed overheads will have to be brought forward in the opening inventory than is being deducted in the closing inventory. </s><s n="s4.5;p7.13">Under the absorption costing method a larger amount of costs (including fixed overheads) are added than under the absorption costing method, inflating costs and reducing profits. </s><s n="s5.5;p7.13">Hence operating profits under marginal costing will be larger than under full costing. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0092b-fig.002"><head>Figure 2 : marginal costing</head></figure></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Advantages and disadvantages</head><p n="p8.13"><s n="s1.1;p8.13">Which method better to use is a question that can not clearly be answered and arguments for and against the different costing systems have to be considered. </s></p><div2><head>Variable Costing: </head><p rend="bulleted" n="p9.13"><s n="s1.2;p9.13">Variable Costing information is easier to use as it highlights the individual impacts of fixed and variable costs. </s><s n="s2.2;p9.13">Consequently, it is easier to make cost effective decisions. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p10.13"><s n="s1.4;p10.13">When using the absorption costing method, sales fluctuations can have strange effects on profits. </s><s n="s2.4;p10.13">Profits can fall while sales rise, even though the cost structure and selling price remain constant. </s><s n="s3.4;p10.13">This is due to the consideration of over and under absorption, i.e. the difference between the budgeted fixed overhead rate and the actual incurred fixed overheads. </s><s n="s4.4;p10.13">By only taking a lump sum as fixed overhead costs, the marginal costing information avoids any contradictory impact of sales fluctuations. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p11.13"><s n="s1.1;p11.13">In addition, the marginal costing information avoids managerial behaviour that aims at inflating inventory levels to defer costs onto latter periods. </s></p></div2><div2><head>Absorption costing:</head><p rend="bulleted" n="p12.13"><s n="s1.1;p12.13">As a result of cost deferral up to the period where the goods are sold, full costing information allows for a steady profit level in industries that are highly seasonal, instead of large losses in the period where inventories are stocked up and high profits in the period where the produced goods are sold. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p13.13"><s n="s1.2;p13.13">The absorption costing method is regarded as the international measure of company performance. </s><s n="s2.2;p13.13">Top Management might prefer their internal costing information to match their external costing measure for financial markets to have a clear idea of company performance. </s></p></div2></div1></body><back/></text></TEI.2>
