<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_0094b" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An Organisational Behaviour Essay: Critically discuss the benefits and downsides of "strong" organisational cultures.</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">The document has a title page which contains:
document title
title part</note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">Language used in quote: <foreign id="English">English</foreign></note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">deleted: header: student number; footer: page numbers
</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">1</p><p n="date">2004-11</p><p n="module title">Business Studies II: Management of Change</p><p n="module code">IB3140</p><p n="genre family">Essay</p><p n="discipline">Business</p><p n="disciplinary group">SS</p><p n="grade">M</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">1481</p><p n="number of s-units">57</p><p n="number of p">19</p><p n="number of tables">0</p><p n="number of figures">0</p><p n="number of block quotes">2</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">0</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">4</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">26.0</p><p n="average s-units per p">3.0</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">m</p><p n="year of birth">1984</p><p n="first language">Finnish</p><p n="education">OSA</p><p n="course">Business</p><p n="student ID">0094</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><docTitle><titlePart>An Organisational Behaviour Essay: <hi rend="italic">Critically discuss the benefits and downsides of "strong" organisational cultures.</hi> </titlePart></docTitle><titlePart><name type="student ID"/> Business II / OB IB3140 University of <name type="university"/> 6 <hi rend="sup">th</hi> March 2005</titlePart></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">1. Introduction</head><p n="p1.19"><s n="s1.7;p1.19">Organisational culture influences individual and group behaviour and it can be managed to facilitate success within groups and organisations. </s><s n="s2.7;p1.19">There has been academic debate whether highly integrated organisational culture, "strong" organisational culture is a key factor in success. </s><s n="s3.7;p1.19">It can be argued that stimulation of individuals within the organisation to high performance and contribution to their well-being is feasible for any organisation. </s><s n="s4.7;p1.19">Thus, finding a suitable organisational culture is important in human resources management (HRM) considerations. </s><s n="s5.7;p1.19">However, the precise nature of an appropriate organisational culture is disputable, for example the official descriptions of companies do not reflect how the life as a part of the organisation is perceived by individuals and groups. </s><s n="s6.7;p1.19">In the light of cases in organisational culture it is possible to derive support to both sides of the academic debate. </s><s n="s7.7;p1.19">Nevertheless, the extent of integration of the ideal organisational culture seems to be limited, even though there is a clear case for ensuring the element of control in a successful organisational culture. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">2. "Strong" Organisational Culture</head><p n="p2.19"><s n="s1.2;p2.19">In order to understand the scope of "strong" organisational culture, the concept of organisational culture has to be clarified. </s><s n="s2.2;p2.19">Schein defined organisational culture in his work: </s></p><quote lang="English"><hi rend="italic">"cognitive framework that consist of assumptions and values shared by organization members."</hi><ref target="BAWE_0094b-ftnote.001"/></quote><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0094b-ftnote.001"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Schein; 1992: 19 </s></p></note><p n="p3.19"><s n="s1.1;p3.19">Schein's definition is broad and it can be rather easily observed that the definition allows a wide inclusion of factors into concept of organisational culture. </s></p><p n="p4.19"><s n="s1.2;p4.19">However, "strong" organisational cultures have distinguishing characteristics. </s><s n="s2.2;p4.19">Firstly and most importantly, the vision of the organisational culture is strict in "strong" cultures, as Rosenfeld and Wilson define it: </s></p><quote lang="English"><hi rend="italic">"Anything which lies outside this predefined frame of reference is said to be counter-cultural and is to be discouraged."</hi><ref target="BAWE_0094b-ftnote.002"/></quote><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0094b-ftnote.002"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Rosenfeld et al; 1999: 271 </s></p></note><p n="p5.19"><s n="s1.4;p5.19">It must be noticed here that Wilson is a critic of so-called "excellence school" that is in favour of "strong"-culture theory. </s><s n="s2.4;p5.19">But, it is clear that the definitive characteristic of "strong" culture is the drive for integration and it discourages anything that is in contradiction of its perceived essence. </s><s n="s3.4;p5.19">Secondly, in "strong" cultures there is a certain level of control to discourage devious behaviour. </s><s n="s4.4;p5.19">Methods used to discourage particular types of behaviour are often sanctions and failures to reward. </s></p><p n="p6.19"><s n="s1.3;p6.19">The integrity in "strong" cultures must be enforced, it is arguably not self-sustaining, as sub-cultures will eventually develop and deviate from the original culture. </s><s n="s2.3;p6.19">Porter et al argued that there is an observable connection in numerous cases of a "strong" organisational culture accompanied with financial success and increased competitiveness.<ref target="BAWE_0094b-ftnote.003"/> This implies that any deviations should indeed be discouraged. </s><s n="s3.3;p6.19">Porter et al based their arguments on findings of Sorensen, who found empirical evidence of existence of a relationship between "strong" cultures and financial success. <ref target="BAWE_0094b-ftnote.004"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0094b-ftnote.003"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Porter et al; 2003: 34 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0094b-ftnote.004"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Sorensen; 2002: 71 </s></p></note><p n="p7.19"><s n="s1.1;p7.19">On the contrary, Wilson has argued already in 1992 that similar conclusion can be reached, but the underlying theoretical issues are supported by questionable empirical evidence; his argumentation was a reply to such findings by Kotter et al.<ref target="BAWE_0094b-ftnote.005"/> Wilson identified four limitations of the empirical proof: </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0094b-ftnote.005"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Wilson; 1992: 73 </s></p></note><p rend="ordered" n="p8.19"><s n="s1.1;p8.19">I) Numerous good companies fail to sustain success </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p9.19"><s n="s1.1;p9.19">II) There are alternative ways to corporate success, such as monopoly </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p10.19"><s n="s1.1;p10.19">III) Most studies have poor sampling and represent only view of top managers </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p11.19"><s n="s1.1;p11.19">IV) All industries do not provide such empirical evidence <ref target="BAWE_0094b-ftnote.006"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0094b-ftnote.006"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Adaptated from Wilson 1992 </s></p></note><p n="p12.19"><s n="s1.2;p12.19">There are clearly cases that favour his view about the limitations of empirical evidence. </s><s n="s2.2;p12.19">However, there is no explicit empirical evidence suggesting that a "strong" culture does not matter. <ref target="BAWE_0094b-ftnote.007"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0094b-ftnote.007"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Martin; 2001: 8 </s></p></note><p n="p13.19"><s n="s1.3;p13.19">In sum, it is possible to identify benefits and downsides in the organisational culture. </s><s n="s2.3;p13.19">In the light of academic debate, the uses of a "strong" organisational culture can be empirically shown, but the limitations are rather complex. </s><s n="s3.3;p13.19">Therefore, these are discussed below using case evidence. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">3. Uses and limitations of a "strong" organisational culture</head><p n="p14.19"><s n="s1.4;p14.19">Even though the cases below are primarily about the "strong" organisational culture, the three models of corporate culture and organisational performance can be identified in the cases below. </s><s n="s2.4;p14.19">In addition to "strong" culture theory, there is "culture-fit" theory, which encourages adaptation to the values of environment, but paying attention to the internal values as well. </s><s n="s3.4;p14.19">Secondly, in so-called "adaptive-culture" theory the values of the culture are seen as tools of adapting to change in the environment. </s><s n="s4.4;p14.19">The characteristics of the three theories can be overlapping as well in some cases they can be mutually inclusive, i.e. they all can be observed in a "strong" culture. </s></p><p n="p15.19"><s n="s1.4;p15.19">A classic case of a "strong" organisational culture is Ford Motor Company. </s><s n="s2.4;p15.19">The organisational culture of the car manufacturing giant was very "strong" in the early twentieth century, it did not allow deviations from the rules of the organisation.<ref target="BAWE_0094b-ftnote.008"/> They had their own "Sociological department" that enforced "aright" behaviour of the workers at work and in their free time, any failures to comply with company standards resulted in a reduced wage or expulsion.<ref target="BAWE_0094b-ftnote.009"/> Such high level of control created employee discomfort and it arguably contributed into the already large labour turnover. </s><s n="s3.4;p15.19">To illustrate, in 1913 turnover was 423% in spite of relatively high wages.<ref target="BAWE_0094b-ftnote.010"/> Individuals tend to dislike excessive control, certain extent of privacy is needed, workers are barely happy in an Orwellian<ref target="BAWE_0094b-ftnote.011"/> organisational culture. </s><s n="s4.4;p15.19">Hence, high level of control can cause negative impact on individuals and this speaks against "strong" organisational cultures. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0094b-ftnote.008"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Corbett; 1994: 123 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0094b-ftnote.009"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Corbett; 1994: 123 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0094b-ftnote.010"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Corbett; 1994: 124 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0094b-ftnote.011"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">George Orwell pictures a control society in his novel 1984 (1949) </s></p></note><p n="p16.19"><s n="s1.6;p16.19">However, there is evidence that lack of control can be harmful, as the members of organisation can act as they please. </s><s n="s2.6;p16.19">This can be depicted in the example of skin and body products retailer The Body Shop. </s><s n="s3.6;p16.19">The majority of The Body Shop's outlets are franchises and there is a very limited amount of control, the franchisees can sell their own related products and modify the store concept, which has been a key to their success.<ref target="BAWE_0094b-ftnote.012"/> However, in early 1990s a franchisee of six outlets, suffering of a mental disorder without her managers knowing of it, became hostile to the culture of the company and let her outlets to degrade, which resulted in damage to company's reputation and extensive litigation and the top management was forced to escalate the level of control.<ref target="BAWE_0094b-ftnote.013"/> On basis of The Body Shop's case, it can be argued that some level of control is needed in order to eliminate the risk of hostile deviations against the organisational culture itself. </s><s n="s4.6;p16.19">The organisational culture is a means of management and the managers should appreciate and manage it rather than to let the culture to guide themselves. </s><s n="s5.6;p16.19">Organisations such as The Body Shop claim that their success is largely based on freedoms of the franchisees and this is clearly the case. </s><s n="s6.6;p16.19">Thus, some level of control is certainly needed and this is in favour of "strong" organisational culture. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0094b-ftnote.012"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">The Body Shop International </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0094b-ftnote.013"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Corbett; 1994: 204 </s></p></note><p n="p17.19"><s n="s1.4;p17.19">The organisational culture has an impact on the groups within the organisation and their decision-making; it can be argued that role of organisational culture is larger the "stronger" the culture is. </s><s n="s2.4;p17.19">The case of Body Shop implies that freedom of the group-decision making is beneficial. </s><s n="s3.4;p17.19">However, it is not straightforward whether the bias resulting from the organisational culture is beneficial or detrimental. </s><s n="s4.4;p17.19">In conclusion, the analysis of "strong" organisational culture has to be applied on a case-by-case basis. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">4. Alternative perspective of success and failure</head><p n="p18.19"><s n="s1.5;p18.19">Assessment of the benefits and downsides of "strong" organisational cultures has limitations. </s><s n="s2.5;p18.19">It is clear that the evaluation in the academic debate is often based on solely financial factors. </s><s n="s3.5;p18.19">For example, in his work Greenberg describes Starbucks as a healthy organisational culture, due to its low turnover.<ref target="BAWE_0094b-ftnote.014"/> Indeed, the culture at Starbucks appears to ensure the employee welfare and it is characterised by integrated values.<ref target="BAWE_0094b-ftnote.015"/> But, pressure groups argue that the organisation exploits the Third World and promotes inequality in the developing countries.<ref target="BAWE_0094b-ftnote.016"/> Greenberg's view is solely finance-based, and hence limited. </s><s n="s4.5;p18.19">This implies that wider considerations of all levels, individual, group, organisational and environmental, should be made about judgement of the success of an organisational culture. </s><s n="s5.5;p18.19">Starbucks might be a profitable organisation, but the negative economic externalities sourcing from their failure to respond to the needs of their environment reduces dramatically the value of Starbucks as an example of a successful "strong" organisational culture. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0094b-ftnote.014"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Greenberg; 2005: 395 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0094b-ftnote.015"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Starbucks Career Center </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0094b-ftnote.016"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">IWW Organisation </s></p></note></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">5. Conclusion</head><p n="p19.19"><s n="s1.5;p19.19">There are cases and academic work explicitly supporting "strong" organisational cultures, but the limitations to this view do exist. </s><s n="s2.5;p19.19">Element of control seems to be the most crucial and disputable one, but there is a demand for a certain level of control in order to ensure that the employees work towards the goals agreed on by management. </s><s n="s3.5;p19.19">However, excessive control causes discomfort amongst individuals and groups leading into reduced motivation to work. </s><s n="s4.5;p19.19">Nevertheless, managers must make their choices about HRM solutions and try to adjust the organisational culture to what is most suitable for them, as it is by no means clear whether to choose "strong" culture or not. </s><s n="s5.5;p19.19">It is not likely that the academic debate will be solved in favour of one side or the other, as the real world is one of diversity and uncertainty and therefore, the power of models is restricted. </s></p></div1></body><back><div1 type="bibliography"><head rend="bold">LIST OF REFERENCES</head><div2 type="bibliography"><head rend="bold">PRINTED SOURCES</head><p>Corbett, J. M. 1994. <hi rend="italic">Critical cases in Organisational Behaviour</hi>. The Macmillan Press Ltd. Kent.</p><p>Martin, Joanne. 2001. <hi rend="italic">Organizational Culture: Mapping the Terrain.</hi> Sage Publications. London.</p><p>Porter, L. W. - Bigley, G. A. - Steers, R. M. 2003. <hi rend="italic">Motivation and Work Behavior</hi>. (7<hi rend="sup">th</hi> edition) McGraw Hill. Harvard.</p><p>Rosenfeld, Robert H. - Wilson, David C. 1999. <hi rend="italic">Managing organisations</hi>. McGraw-Hill. London.</p><p>Schein, E. H. 1992. <hi rend="italic">Organizational culture and leadership.</hi> (2<hi rend="sup">nd</hi> edition) Jossey-Bass. San Francisco.</p><p>Sorensen, J. B. 2002. <hi rend="italic">The strength of corporate culture and the reliability of firm's performance.</hi> Administrative Science Quarterly. Vol 47/Issue 1. 70-</p><p>Wilson, David C. 1992. <hi rend="italic">A strategy of change: concepts and controversies in the management of change.</hi> Routledge. London.</p></div2><div2 type="bibliography"><head rend="bold">INTERNET SOURCES</head><p>IWW Organisation. 2004. <hi rend="italic">Starbucks Baristas Go Union.</hi> <seg type="URL" n="http://www.iww.org/unions/iu660/starbucks/"/> (adapted 28-02-2005)</p><p>Starbucks Career Center. 2005.<hi rend="italic">Our success depends on your success.</hi> <seg type="URL" n="http://www.starbucks.com/aboutus/jobcenter.asp"/> (adapted 28-02-2005)</p><p>The Body Shop International. 2005. <hi rend="italic">Where do we come from?</hi> <seg type="URL" n="http://www.thebodyshopinternational.com/web/tbsgl/about_where.jsp#nineties"/> (adapted 02-03-2005)</p></div2></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
