<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_0094g" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>In what ways does the floating charge fall short of being an ideal security for credit extended to companies, especially small companies, by banks and other parties dealing with those companies?</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">The document has a title page which contains:
document title
title part</note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">Language used in quote: <foreign id="English">English</foreign></note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">deleted: header: student number; footer: page numbers</note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">deleted: Word count: 2500</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">3</p><p n="date">2007-04</p><p n="module title">The Law of Business Organisation</p><p n="module code">LA310</p><p n="genre family">Essay</p><p n="discipline">Law</p><p n="disciplinary group">SS</p><p n="grade">D</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">2499</p><p n="number of s-units">97</p><p n="number of p">26</p><p n="number of tables">0</p><p n="number of figures">0</p><p n="number of block quotes">2</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">0</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">0</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">25.8</p><p n="average s-units per p">3.7</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">m</p><p n="year of birth">1984</p><p n="first language">Finnish</p><p n="education">OSA</p><p n="course">BA Law and Business Studies</p><p n="student ID">0094</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><docTitle><titlePart>In what ways does the floating charge fall short of being an ideal security for credit extended to companies, especially small companies, by banks and other parties dealing with those companies?</titlePart></docTitle><titlePart><name type="student ID"/> Law of Business Organisations (LA 310) <name type="university"/> School of Law University of <name type="university"/> April 2007</titlePart></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="section"><head>INTRODUCTION</head><p n="p1.26"><s n="s1.8;p1.26">The floating charge is a useful security - it enables companies to raise more debt finance secured against their fluctuating assets such as trading stock. </s><s n="s2.8;p1.26">However, the recent legal developments have been to the detriment of the floating charge holders. </s><s n="s3.8;p1.26">Although the Enterprise Act (EA) 2002, the Companies Act (CA) 2006 and the House of Lords decision in <hi rend="italic">National Westminster Bank plc</hi> <hi rend="italic">v Spectrum Plus and others</hi><ref target="BAWE_0094g-ftnote.001"/> have clarified the law, the floating charges have become less lucrative to lenders. </s><s n="s4.8;p1.26">As a result of the reforms, the floating charge holders are afforded less protection and have a lower priority in insolvency situations. </s><s n="s5.8;p1.26">This is particularly problematic for small companies, because they rely heavily on the floating charge as a security for their debt. </s><s n="s6.8;p1.26">Due to the recent changes, banks and other lenders are likely to become more reluctant to give loans to companies with little or no fixed assets. </s><s n="s7.8;p1.26">Therefore, it has been argued that the reforms have undermined the benefits of the floating charge. </s><s n="s8.8;p1.26">Nevertheless, the floating charge is a beneficial security in many circumstances and therefore, it remains significant from a legal perspective. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0094g-ftnote.001"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">[2005] UKHL 41 </s></p></note></div1><div1 type="section"><head>DEVELOPMENT OF THE FLOATING CHARGE</head><p n="p2.26"><s n="s1.2;p2.26">In order to understand the uses and limitations of the floating charge, it is worthwhile to briefly investigate the legal developments regarding this exceptional security. </s><s n="s2.2;p2.26">It was created by the innovativeness of equity practitioners and has been shaped further by the judiciary and the legislature. </s></p><p n="p3.26"><s n="s1.3;p3.26">Clearly, the equitable origins of the floating charge relate to the emergence of incorporated businesses. </s><s n="s2.3;p3.26">It was developed by lawyers in private practice who helped businesses<ref target="BAWE_0094g-ftnote.002"/> to raise debt finance. </s><s n="s3.3;p3.26">The floating charge was welcomed as a beneficial instrument, and Davies implies that it still remains valuable: "The ingenuity of equity practitioners led to the evolution of an unusual but highly beneficial type of security known as floating charge." <ref target="BAWE_0094g-ftnote.003"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0094g-ftnote.002"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">The floating charge is available to companies and limited liability partnerships. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0094g-ftnote.003"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Davies, 2003: 40 </s></p></note><p n="p4.26"><s n="s1.3;p4.26">The floating charge is indeed exceptional: it creates an equitable interest over a class of assets both present and future, e.g. a company's trading stock. </s><s n="s2.3;p4.26">Once the charge has been created, the company is free to deal with the charged assets in the ordinary course of business until the occurrence of a specified event (e.g. non-payment of debt). </s><s n="s3.3;p4.26">If the specified event occurs, the floating charge is said to crystallise i.e. it turns into an equitable fixed charge over the class of assets. </s></p><p n="p5.26"><s n="s1.2;p5.26">Not surprisingly, the judiciary has been active in the development of the floating charge since <hi rend="italic">Re Panama, New Zealand and Australian Royal Mint Company</hi>,<ref target="BAWE_0094g-ftnote.004"/> where floating charge was formally tested. </s><s n="s2.2;p5.26">An authoritative description of the characteristics of the floating charge was put forward by Romer LJ in his judgment in <hi rend="italic">Re Yorkshire Woolcombers Association</hi>:<ref target="BAWE_0094g-ftnote.005"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0094g-ftnote.004"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">(1870) 5 Ch App 318 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0094g-ftnote.005"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">[1903] 2 Ch 284. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">Romer LJ emphasised that he did not attempt to define a floating charge. </s></p></note><quote lang="English">A mortgage or charge by a company which contains the three following characteristics is a "floating charge"... (1.) If it is a charge on a class of assets both present and future. (2.) If that class is one which in the ordinary course of the business of the company would be changing from time to time. (3.) If it is contemplated by the charge that, until some future step is taken by or on behalf of the mortgagee, the company may carry on its business in the ordinary way so far as concerns the particular class of assets charged.</quote><p n="p6.26"><s n="s1.1;p6.26">This statement was largely approved by Lord Millett in a recent Privy Council case <hi rend="italic">Agnew v Commissioner of Inland Revenue</hi>,<ref target="BAWE_0094g-ftnote.006"/> where he identified the third characteristic as the hallmark of a floating charge.<ref target="BAWE_0094g-ftnote.007"/> The House of Lords approved his approach in their recent decision in <hi rend="italic">Spectrum Plus</hi>.<ref target="BAWE_0094g-ftnote.008"/> This decision was important because it clarified the law that had been in a confused state about the distinction between fixed and floating charges since the decision in <hi rend="italic">Siebe Gorman &amp; Co Ltd v Barclays Bank Ltd</hi>.<ref target="BAWE_0094g-ftnote.009"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0094g-ftnote.006"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">[2001] UKPC 28 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0094g-ftnote.007"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid at [13] </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0094g-ftnote.008"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">[2005] UKHL 41 [107] per Lord Scott of Foscote </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0094g-ftnote.009"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">[1979] 2Lloyd's Rep. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">142 </s></p></note><p n="p7.26"><s n="s1.5;p7.26">The legislature too has taken action to clarify some problematic case law. </s><s n="s2.5;p7.26">The controversial decision in <hi rend="italic">Re Leyland Daf Ltd</hi><ref target="BAWE_0094g-ftnote.010"/> established that the costs of liquidation were not payable out of the assets which a debenture holder held an interest in under a floating charge. </s><s n="s3.5;p7.26">The CA 2006 repeals the decision by inserting s.176ZA to the Insolvency Act (IA) 1986 and thus weakens the position of floating charge holders. </s><s n="s4.5;p7.26">Moreover, the EA 2002 had particularly wide implications to floating charge holders as it restricted the right to block the appointment of an administrator or to appoint an administrative receiver to recover their debt.<ref target="BAWE_0094g-ftnote.011"/> This development relates to the emergence of the corporate rescue culture - the objective is to maintain the company as a going concern. </s><s n="s5.5;p7.26">Therefore, administrative receivers will have to consider the interests of <hi rend="italic">all</hi> creditors instead of mere floating charge holders. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0094g-ftnote.010"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">[2004] UKHL 9 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0094g-ftnote.011"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Applies to floating charges created on or after 15th September 2003. </s></p></note><p n="p8.26"><s n="s1.8;p8.26">In summary, the law in relation to floating charges has gone through some significant changes in recent years. </s><s n="s2.8;p8.26">Walters has argued that the changes under the EA 2002 "amount to an epochal shift in the structure of insolvency law." </s><ref target="BAWE_0094g-ftnote.012"/><s n="s3.8;p8.26">It seems that the position of a floating charge holder has been weakened by these reforms and under the new regime the collective interest of creditors is given priority. </s><s n="s4.8;p8.26">Though, the implications of the EA 2002 might not be as dramatic. </s><s n="s5.8;p8.26">Walters has argued that the receivership is merely changing its form: "[T]he Enterprise Act is a Trojan horse within which lurks a new style of receivership." </s><ref target="BAWE_0094g-ftnote.013"/><s n="s6.8;p8.26">He does not seem to think that the position of floating charge holders will be radically undermined. </s><s n="s7.8;p8.26">This view is contradicted by McCormick: "It seems [the supporters of rescue culture] really want to hurt the floating charge holder." </s><ref target="BAWE_0094g-ftnote.014"/><s n="s8.8;p8.26">Nevertheless, some considerable benefits of the floating charge seem to remain. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0094g-ftnote.012"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Walters, 2004: 1 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0094g-ftnote.013"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0094g-ftnote.014"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">McCormick, 2006: 99 </s></p></note></div1><div1 type="section"><head>ADVANTAGES OF THE FLOATING CHARGE</head><p n="p9.26"><s n="s1.2;p9.26">There are a number of incentives for lenders to accept a floating charge as a security, particularly when dealing with small companies. </s><s n="s2.2;p9.26">Although a fixed charge seems to be a superior security in general, the floating charge becomes an important security where a business does not have significant fixed assets. </s></p><p n="p10.26"><s n="s1.3;p10.26">Floating charge may well be the only type of a security that small companies are able to provide. </s><s n="s2.3;p10.26">Therefore, in such circumstances the floating charge seems to be close to an ideal security. </s><s n="s3.3;p10.26">Ferran agrees with this view: </s></p><quote lang="English">Much of the wealth of a business may be in tied up in raw materials, goods in process of being manufactured or stock in trade. The floating charge is ideally suited to unlock the potential of items such as these as a valuable source of security.<ref target="BAWE_0094g-ftnote.015"/></quote><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0094g-ftnote.015"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ferran, 1999: 508 </s></p></note><p n="p11.26"><s n="s1.1;p11.26">Clearly, a floating charge holder is better protected than an unsecured creditor. </s></p><p n="p12.26"><s n="s1.4;p12.26">Moreover, the floating charge holders may protect themselves against other lenders using negative pledges. </s><s n="s2.4;p12.26">These are clauses in the debenture restricting or prohibiting the creation of subsequent charges. </s><s n="s3.4;p12.26">In case a subsequent charge holder is deemed to have notice of the negative pledge, then the floating charge holder has priority over them in insolvency situations.<ref target="BAWE_0094g-ftnote.016"/> Interestingly, the Law Commission recommended that a notice filing system for registration of charges should be introduced.<ref target="BAWE_0094g-ftnote.017"/> It would benefit the floating charge holders by making e.g. negative pledges unnecessary. </s><s n="s4.4;p12.26">However, Chiu has suggested that this reform will not be viable in its present form.<ref target="BAWE_0094g-ftnote.018"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0094g-ftnote.016"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">See Davies, 2003: 823 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0094g-ftnote.017"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">See Law Commision, 2005: 12 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0094g-ftnote.018"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">See Chiu, 2006: 654 </s></p></note><p n="p13.26"><s n="s1.2;p13.26">Furthermore, the mere fact that the floating charge holder is able to enforce the charge gives her some control over the company.<ref target="BAWE_0094g-ftnote.019"/> Particularly for small companies, the effects of the floating charge holder enforcing their rights would be disastrous - a likely consequence is the cessation of business if the charge is turned into a fixed charge e.g. over the company's book debts, which deprives the company of its cash flow. </s><s n="s2.2;p13.26">Therefore, especially small companies have an incentive to keep the floating charge holders satisfied. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0094g-ftnote.019"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Davies makes the same observation; Davies, 2003: 823 </s></p></note><p n="p14.26"><s n="s1.2;p14.26">Consequently, many companies provide financial statements to their debenture holders.<ref target="BAWE_0094g-ftnote.020"/> Therefore, the floating charge holders are informed if the company is facing parlous times. </s><s n="s2.2;p14.26">This is advantageous as it will facilitate the floating charge holders' understanding of the risk of the debt. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0094g-ftnote.020"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">See Hannigan, 2003: 679 </s></p></note><p n="p15.26"><s n="s1.4;p15.26">From a corporate finance perspective, the increased risk arising from an imperfect security such as floating charge will justify the charging of a higher interest rate from the company. </s><s n="s2.4;p15.26">Dignam et al have also considered this view: "The lender will compensate for [the additional risk arising from a floating charge] by charging a higher rate of interest." </s><ref target="BAWE_0094g-ftnote.021"/><s n="s3.4;p15.26">Lenders who seek higher returns will have to accept a higher level of risk. </s><s n="s4.4;p15.26">Thus, the floating charge becomes an interesting security for them. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0094g-ftnote.021"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Dignam et al, 2006: 19 </s></p></note><p n="p16.26"><s n="s1.5;p16.26">Moreover, the flexibility of a floating charge is advantageous to both companies and lenders. </s><s n="s2.5;p16.26">The company will be free to deal with the assets under the floating charge. </s><s n="s3.5;p16.26">This benefit has been underlined by Davies: "[A floating charge is] a particularly valuable means whereby a business concern can raise money without removing any of its property from the business." </s><ref target="BAWE_0094g-ftnote.022"/><s n="s4.5;p16.26">The charge holders will benefit from the fact that the charge attaches to all assets in a class. </s><s n="s5.5;p16.26">Though, the risk remains that the value of assets may decrease over time. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0094g-ftnote.022"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Davies, 2003: 819 </s></p></note><p n="p17.26"><s n="s1.3;p17.26">Finally, perhaps the greatest advantage of the floating charge has been the power to appoint an administrative receiver and to block the appointment of an administrator if the company becomes insolvent. </s><s n="s2.3;p17.26">Thus, the floating charge holders have an advantage as liquidations will ensure maximum return to them. </s><s n="s3.3;p17.26">However, under the EA 2002 this applies to floating charges created before the 15 <hi rend="sup">th</hi> September 2003. </s></p><p n="p18.26"><s n="s1.2;p18.26">Overall, it seems that there are several reasons why banks and other lenders should accept a floating charge as a security. </s><s n="s2.2;p18.26">Nevertheless, there have been concerns that the recent reforms have limited the advantages of the floating charge. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head>DISADVANTAGES OF THE FLOATING CHARGE</head><p n="p19.26"><s n="s1.2;p19.26">There is much about the floating charges that makes them unsatisfactory securities for lenders. </s><s n="s2.2;p19.26">If anything, the recent legal developments have worsened the position of floating charge holders. </s></p><p n="p20.26"><s n="s1.4;p20.26">The floating charge is an uncertain instrument - it creates an interest over a fluctuating amount of assets. </s><s n="s2.4;p20.26">Therefore, the charge holder is left in doubt as to how much of her debt she can recover by realising the security. </s><s n="s3.4;p20.26">Dignam et al agree with this view: "A floating charge is a less secure type of lending because the lender has no way of knowing whether the assets left in the stockroom when the charge 'crystallises' will cover the debt owed." </s><ref target="BAWE_0094g-ftnote.023"/><s n="s4.4;p20.26">Davies too has expressed concerns: "[T]he company may dissipate the assets subject to the charge, arguably the most serious risk that the charge holder faces."<ref target="BAWE_0094g-ftnote.024"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0094g-ftnote.023"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Dignam et al, 2006: 19 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0094g-ftnote.024"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Davies, 2003: 821 </s></p></note><p n="p21.26"><s n="s1.6;p21.26">Another risk arises from the low priority given to a floating charge holder when distributing the proceeds of insolvent liquidation. </s><s n="s2.6;p21.26">The fixed charge holders have the highest claim and also the preferential creditors such as employees of the company rank higher in priority than the floating charge holders. </s><s n="s3.6;p21.26">After the EA 2002, a part of the company's property will be set aside to form a fund for the unsecured creditors before allowing the floating charge holders to collect their full claim. </s><s n="s4.6;p21.26">The EA 2002 only partially countered this deprivation of the floating charge holders' rights by removing Inland Revenue from the group of preferential creditors. </s><s n="s5.6;p21.26">Finally, the ability to appoint an administrative receiver has been restricted. </s><s n="s6.6;p21.26">Subsequently, Chiu has argued: "[T]he floating charge is weaker as the Enterprise Act 2002 does not allow floating charge holders to appoint receivers."<ref target="BAWE_0094g-ftnote.025"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0094g-ftnote.025"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Chiu, 2006: 646 </s></p></note><p n="p22.26"><s n="s1.5;p22.26">Furthermore, the CA 2006 reverses the rule in <hi rend="italic">Leyland Daf</hi> and therefore the position of floating charge holders is worsened. </s><s n="s2.5;p22.26">It has been argued that this was a necessary change that resulted in efficiency and fairness. </s><s n="s3.5;p22.26">E.g. </s><s n="s4.5;p22.26">Walters has argued: "The difficulties that <hi rend="italic">Leyland Daf</hi> may be causing insolvency practitioners and the concern that it may give them perverse incentives to conduct de facto liquidations through... administration procedure (the expenses of which have statutory priority over the floating charge) has led the Government... to seek to reverse the outcome." </s><ref target="BAWE_0094g-ftnote.026"/><s n="s5.5;p22.26">On the other hand, Fletcher is sceptical about the reform's implications to the floating charge holders: "The prospects for the floating charge holder to receive any material recovery out of the realisations from floating charge assets are [now] subject to uncertainty[.]" </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0094g-ftnote.026"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Walters, 2006: 193 </s></p></note><p n="p23.26"><s n="s1.5;p23.26">The recent reforms have also resulted in other types of vulnerabilities. </s><s n="s2.5;p23.26">Firstly, a floating charge is invalid under the s.245(2) of the Insolvency Act (IA) 1986 if it was taken by an existing unsecured creditor 12 months before the company became insolvent.<ref target="BAWE_0094g-ftnote.027"/> Such floating charge will be valid only to the extent of consideration for the creation of the floating charge as set out in s.245(2). </s><s n="s3.5;p23.26">This provision is intended to protect the unsecured creditors - otherwise an existing unsecured creditor who takes up a floating charge would be in an (unfairly) advantageous position. </s><s n="s4.5;p23.26">Secondly, the administrators have obtained the power to override the interest of a floating charge holder.<ref target="BAWE_0094g-ftnote.028"/> They can sell property that is subject to a charge which as created was a floating charge without the need to obtain a court order. </s><s n="s5.5;p23.26">According to Davies, this limitation has been offset by giving the floating charge holder the same priority to a similar property.<ref target="BAWE_0094g-ftnote.029"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0094g-ftnote.027"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">24 months for connected parties, s.245(3) of the IA 1986. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0094g-ftnote.028"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.3;pn1.1">Para. </s><s n="s2.3;pn1.1">70 of Sch. </s><s n="s3.3;pn1.1">B1, the IA 1986. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0094g-ftnote.029"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Davies, 2003: 830 </s></p></note><p n="p24.26"><s n="s1.5;p24.26">The origin of the floating charge can be a weakness, too. </s><s n="s2.5;p24.26">A floating charge takes effect in equity and therefore, it is subject to the vulnerabilities of an equitable interest. </s><s n="s3.5;p24.26">It does not bind a <hi rend="italic">bona fide</hi> purchaser for value without notice. </s><s n="s4.5;p24.26">Moreover, it has been debated whether floating charge holders have a proprietary interest at all before crystallisation. </s><s n="s5.5;p24.26">The consensus view as stated by Dignam et al emphasises that: "[T]he floating charge confers an equitable interest in favour of the chargee from the time of its creation... coupled with a licence in favour of the company to deal with assets in the ordinary course of business."<ref target="BAWE_0094g-ftnote.030"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0094g-ftnote.030"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.3;pn1.1">Dignam et al, 2006: 86. </s><s n="s2.3;pn1.1">See also Goode, 1994: 594. </s><s n="s3.3;pn1.1">For an alternative view, see Gough, 1996: 97 </s></p></note><p n="p25.26"><s n="s1.2;p25.26">It can be argued that the recent reforms have worsened the position of floating charge holders. </s><s n="s2.2;p25.26">Similarly, Walters has argued: "Taken together with the Enterprise Act and <hi rend="italic">Spectrum</hi> <hi rend="italic">Plus</hi>, the statutory reversal of <hi rend="italic">Leyland</hi> <hi rend="italic">Daf</hi> will inevitably cause lenders to reappraise their practices... [the floating charge] is becoming increasingly unattractive [.]"<ref target="BAWE_0094g-ftnote.031"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0094g-ftnote.031"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Walters, 2006: 193 </s></p></note></div1><div1 type="section"><head>CONCLUSION</head><p n="p26.26"><s n="s1.8;p26.26">In conclusion, the floating charge can be a very beneficial security. </s><s n="s2.8;p26.26">However, there are several factors that reduce the value of security that can be derived from a floating charge - it often falls short of being an ideal security for lenders. </s><s n="s3.8;p26.26">The recent legal reforms have made the floating charge less lucrative a security for lenders. </s><s n="s4.8;p26.26">Although, the past situation has been unfair to an extent, and therefore, the reforms can be justified. </s><s n="s5.8;p26.26">It can be argued that the worsened position of floating charge holders is a rather inevitable consequence of the emergence of the corporate rescue culture. </s><s n="s6.8;p26.26">The objective to maintain the company as a going concern and to ensure a better return to the unsecured creditors is likely to contradict the objective to maximise the recovered amount of debt for the floating charge holders. </s><s n="s7.8;p26.26">Nevertheless, in the cases of small companies, the floating charge is often the only option. </s><s n="s8.8;p26.26">Indeed, in such cases it is a beneficial - if not ideal - security from the perspective of both the company and the lender. </s></p></div1></body><back><div1 type="bibliography"><div2 type="bibliography"><head>BIBLIOGRAPHY</head><p>Chiu, Iris H-Y. 2006. <hi rend="italic">Replacing the Default Priority Rule for Secured Creditors - Some Reservations.</hi> Journal of Business Law, J.B.L. 2006, Oct, 644-655. Sweet &amp; Maxwell Ltd. London.</p><p>Davies, Paul L. 2003. <hi rend="italic">Gower and Davies' Principles of Modern Company Law</hi> (7<hi rend="sup">th</hi> edition). Sweet &amp; Maxwell Ltd. London.</p><p>Dignam, Alan - Lowry, John. 2006. <hi rend="italic">Company Law</hi> (4<hi rend="sup">th</hi> edition). Oxford University Press. Oxford.</p><p>Ferran, Eilís. 1999. <hi rend="italic">Company Law and Corporate Finance.</hi> Oxford University Press. Oxford.</p><p>Goode, Roy. 1994. <hi rend="italic">Charges over Book Debts: a Missed Opportunity.</hi> Law Quarterly Review, L.Q.R. 1994, 110(Oct), 592-606. Sweet &amp; Maxwell Ltd. London.</p><p>Gough, W.J. 1996. <hi rend="italic">Company Charges</hi> (2<hi rend="sup">nd</hi> edition). LexisNexis Butterworths. London.</p><p>Hannigan, Brenda. 2003. <hi rend="italic">Company Law</hi>. LexisNexis Butterworths. London.</p><p>The Law Commission. 2005. <hi rend="italic">Company Security Interests.</hi> The Stationery Office, Cm 6654. Norwich.</p><p>McCormick, Roger. 2006. <hi rend="italic">Steppin' Out With The Rescue Culture Club</hi>. Journal of International Banking and Financial Law, (2006) 3 JIBFL 99, 1 March 2006. Reed Elsevier (UK) Ltd. London.</p><p>Walters, Adrian. 2006. <hi rend="italic">Floating Charges and Liquidation Expenses: Re Leyland Daf and Beyond</hi>. Company Lawyer, Comp. Law. 2006, 27(7), 193. Sweet &amp; Maxwell Ltd. London. </p><p>Walters, Adrian. 2004. <hi rend="italic">Corporate Insolvency After the Enterprise Act 2002.</hi> Company Lawyer, Comp. Law. 2004, 25(1), 1. Sweet &amp; Maxwell Ltd. London.</p></div2><div2 type="bibliography"><head>TABLE OF STATUTES</head><p>Insolvency Act 1986; 1986, c.45</p><p>Enterprise Act 2002; 2002, c.40</p><p>Companies Act 2006; 2006, c.46</p></div2><div2 type="bibliography"><head>TABLE OF CASES </head><p><hi rend="italic">Agnew v Commissioner of Inland Revenue</hi> [2001] UKPC 28</p><p><hi rend="italic">National Westminster Bank plc v Spectrum Plus and others</hi> [2005] UKHL 41</p><p><hi rend="italic">Re Leyland Daf Ltd</hi> [2004] UKHL 9</p><p><hi rend="italic">Re Panama, New Zealand and Australian Royal Mint Company</hi> (1870) 5 Ch App 318</p><p><hi rend="italic">Re Yorkshire Woolcombers Association</hi> [1903] 2 Ch 284</p><p><hi rend="italic">Siebe Gorman &amp; Co Ltd v Barclays Bank Ltd</hi> [1979] 2Lloyd's Rep. 142</p></div2></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
