<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_0094e" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>"Explain why the long-run aggregate supply curve is vertical and the short-run aggregate supply curve is horizontal. Discuss the two economic theories associated with each curve."</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">The document has a title page which contains:
document title
title part</note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">deleted: header: student number
deleted: Word count: 2000
</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">2</p><p n="date">2006-04</p><p n="module title">Macroeconomics</p><p n="module code">EC201</p><p n="genre family">Critique</p><p n="discipline">Economics</p><p n="disciplinary group">SS</p><p n="grade">D</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">1992</p><p n="number of s-units">97</p><p n="number of p">33</p><p n="number of tables">0</p><p n="number of figures">8</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">3</p><p n="number of lists">0</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">3</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">20.5</p><p n="average s-units per p">2.9</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">m</p><p n="year of birth">1984</p><p n="first language">Finnish</p><p n="education">OSA</p><p n="course">Economics</p><p n="student ID">0094</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><docTitle><titlePart>A Macroeconomics Essay: <hi rend="italic">"Explain why the long-run aggregate supply curve is vertical and the short-run aggregate supply curve is horizontal. Discuss the two economic theories associated with each curve."</hi></titlePart></docTitle><titlePart><name type="student ID"/> Economics II EC 204 University of <name type="university"/></titlePart></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Introduction</head><p n="p1.33"><s n="s1.8;p1.33">The supply-side macroeconomic debate between Keynesians and monetarists has continued throughout our post-modern time. </s><s n="s2.8;p1.33">The extreme Keynesian views about the shape of aggregate supply (AS) curve have been challenged as a result of the emergence of monetarist and moderate Keynesian thought.<ref target="BAWE_0094e-ftnote.001"/> Most economists disagree with the extreme Keynesian view that the shape of AS curve is horizontal in the short run and vertical in the long run. </s><s n="s3.8;p1.33">This is a problem, because it would be beneficial for a government to know how the nature of AS affects the success of a chosen fiscal or monetary policy. </s><s n="s4.8;p1.33">Surprisingly, there is no absolute certainty about the shape of the short run AS curves. </s><s n="s5.8;p1.33">Moderate thinkers have tried to adjust the extreme Keynesian model of AS curve into a more empirically accurate form whereas the monetarists have challenged the fundamentals of Keynesian model. </s><s n="s6.8;p1.33">In this essay, the starting point for discussion is the extreme Keynesian view: vertical long-run aggregate supply curve (LRAS) combined with a horizontal short-run aggregate supply curve (SRAS), which can be combined into an L-shaped curve.<ref target="BAWE_0094e-ftnote.002"/> The underlying theory of such AS curves is explained below, followed by discussion of alternative views. </s><s n="s7.8;p1.33">In sum, I aim to challenge the extreme Keynesian AS model. </s><s n="s8.8;p1.33">Like all models, it is a rough representation of reality and due to its rigidity it is highly disputable. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0094e-ftnote.001"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">This debate must be distinguished from Keynesian demand-side macroeconomics, which is more agreed upon. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0094e-ftnote.002"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Adapted from Glanville; 1997: 285 </s></p></note></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Aggregate Supply Curves: Extreme Keynesian Theory Explained</head><p n="p2.33"><s n="s1.4;p2.33">According to the extreme Keynesian view, there is a vertical LRAS and a horizontal SRAS curve. </s><s n="s2.4;p2.33">The AS curve model plots the quantity of goods and services supplied in an economy at a certain price level.<ref target="BAWE_0094e-ftnote.003"/> Alongside with aggregate demand (AD) analysis, AS can be used to investigate the relationship between price level (<hi rend="italic">P</hi>) and real income (<hi rend="italic">Y</hi>). </s><ref target="BAWE_0094e-ftnote.004"/><s n="s3.4;p2.33">Hence, the AD/AS model is an important tool for economists. </s><s n="s4.4;p2.33">Not surprisingly, the absence of unambiguous empirical data about AS is the main reason for controversy in supply-side economics. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0094e-ftnote.003"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Adapted from Mankiw; 2002: 245 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0094e-ftnote.004"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid </s></p></note></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">LRAS</head><p n="p3.33"><s n="s1.2;p3.33">The vertical LRAS model was created by the classical economists; however, they were focused on explaining the long run only and not analysing short run economic fluctuations.<ref target="BAWE_0094e-ftnote.005"/> The vertical LRAS is based on an assumption that in the long run prices are flexible and the economy's output will be at its full employment level (<hi rend="italic">Y</hi>*). </s><s n="s2.2;p3.33">Clearly, this level of output can occur at various price levels (<hi rend="italic">P</hi>), as illustrated below. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0094e-ftnote.005"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid </s></p></note><figure id="BAWE_0094e-fig.001"><head rend="bold">Graph A</head></figure><p n="p4.33"><s n="s1.2;p4.33">Classical economists argue that in the long run "<hi rend="italic">amount of output produced depends on the fixed amounts of capital and [labour] and on the available technology</hi>." </s><ref target="BAWE_0094e-ftnote.006"/><s n="s2.2;p4.33">This observation can be written:<ref target="BAWE_0094e-ftnote.007"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0094e-ftnote.006"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0094e-ftnote.007"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid: 241, 245 </s></p></note><p rend="ordered" n="p5.33"><s n="s1.1;p5.33"><hi rend="bold">Equation 1 </hi><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0094e-form.001"/> </s></p><p n="p6.33"><s n="s1.2;p6.33">Where: <hi rend="underlined">Y</hi>= constant level of output, Y* = output at full employment level of resources, K = capital and L = labour. </s><s n="s2.2;p6.33">The function depends on technological process. <ref target="BAWE_0094e-ftnote.008"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0094e-ftnote.008"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Cf. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">Solow growth model </s></p></note><p n="p7.33"><s n="s1.3;p7.33">Therefore, <hi rend="italic">P</hi> is independent of <hi rend="italic">Y</hi> in the long run and <hi rend="italic">P</hi> is determined by the level of AD at Y* level. </s><s n="s2.3;p7.33">Another important implication is that the production has a physical limit set by F(K,L). </s><s n="s3.3;p7.33">Given that all prices are flexible, it follows that the prices will adjust to any changes in demand. </s></p><p n="p8.33"><s n="s1.1;p8.33">Although Keynes famously stated: "<hi rend="italic">in the long run we are all dead</hi>"<ref target="BAWE_0094e-ftnote.009"/>, Mankiw states that most economists agree with the classical long run view.<ref target="BAWE_0094e-ftnote.010"/> However, Keynesians argue that immediately adjusting totally flexible prices is too strong an assumption for the short-run analysis. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0094e-ftnote.009"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Keynes; 1923: ch.3 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0094e-ftnote.010"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Mankiw; 2002: 240 </s></p></note></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">SRAS</head><p n="p9.33"><s n="s1.2;p9.33">The Keynesians assume that the prices take time to adjust in changes in demand in the short run; <hi rend="italic">"prices are sticky</hi>".<ref target="BAWE_0094e-ftnote.011"/> I will use the assumption that all prices are fixed in the short run, which is consistent with extreme Keynesian thought. </s><s n="s2.2;p9.33">Therefore, the SRAS curve shown below is horizontal. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0094e-ftnote.011"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid: 247 </s></p></note><figure id="BAWE_0094e-fig.002"><head rend="bold">Graph B</head></figure><p n="p10.33"><s n="s1.1;p10.33">In the above model, short-run changes in demand affect <hi rend="italic">Y</hi> - the price level is fixed at <hi rend="italic">P*</hi>. <ref target="BAWE_0094e-ftnote.012"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0094e-ftnote.012"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid </s></p></note><p n="p11.33"><s n="s1.1;p11.33">Hence: </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p12.33"><s n="s1.1;p12.33"><hi rend="bold">Equation 2 </hi><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0094e-form.002"/> </s></p><p n="p13.33"><s n="s1.1;p13.33">Thus, the short-run case is the opposite of the long-run model. </s></p><p n="p14.33"><s n="s1.3;p14.33">The LRAS and SRAS models have now been explained and it was shown that in the extreme model the short run output level is affected by changes in AD, whereas the long run output is not. </s><s n="s2.3;p14.33">The antithetical nature of these two models brings along questions: what happens when we move from the short-run to the long-run? </s><s n="s3.3;p14.33">The extreme Keynesian explanation is shown below. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0094e-fig.003"><head rend="bold">Graph C</head></figure><p n="p15.33"><s n="s1.4;p15.33"><hi rend="italic">P</hi> does not respond to changes in AD until <hi rend="italic">Y*</hi>. </s><s n="s2.4;p15.33">The policy implication is that fiscal policy is effective and no complete crowding-out of private investment occurs. </s><s n="s3.4;p15.33">Hence, expansionary fiscal and monetary policies increase <hi rend="italic">Y</hi> but not <hi rend="italic">P</hi> in the short run. </s><s n="s4.4;p15.33">In Keynesian analysis, wages are important and I will briefly discuss the wage-price relation relevant to this debate. </s></p><p n="p16.33"><s n="s1.2;p16.33">Given a perfectly elastic SRAS curve, it can be observed that if AD shifts outwards from 1 to 2, <hi rend="italic">Y</hi> and wages (W) increase simultaneously. </s><s n="s2.2;p16.33">This can be clarified graphically: </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0094e-fig.004"><head rend="bold">Graph D</head></figure><p n="p17.33"><s n="s1.4;p17.33">As AD shifts from 1 to 2 in Graph C, the iso-wage curve shifts from W1 to W2 and given <hi rend="italic">P*</hi>, W/P increases. </s><s n="s2.4;p17.33">Thus, wages are procyclical. </s><s n="s3.4;p17.33">However, this observation is based on L-shaped AS curve, which is a rigid assumption. </s><s n="s4.4;p17.33">Hence I will discuss alternatives to extreme Keynesian model. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Alternative views introduced</head><p n="p18.33"><s n="s1.3;p18.33">The extreme Keynesian view is based on strong assumptions and therefore its correlation with reality is reduced. </s><s n="s2.3;p18.33">Many academics have challenged the extreme Keynesian views on the AS curves, because there is controversial empirical evidence. </s><s n="s3.3;p18.33">The extreme model was developed further by the moderate Keynesians. </s></p><div2><head>Moderate Keynesian view</head><p n="p19.33"><s n="s1.3;p19.33">The moderate Keynesian model challenges the extreme idea that <hi rend="italic">P</hi> is completely insensitive of AD up to <hi rend="italic">Y*</hi>. </s><s n="s2.3;p19.33">Moderate Keynesians developed an upward-sloping middle section to the model. </s><s n="s3.3;p19.33">They based that change on the observation that unemployment and rising prices showed strong correlation in 1950s and 1960s.<ref target="BAWE_0094e-ftnote.013"/> Nevertheless, the moderate Keynesians believe that the markets will clear in the long run and their model is illustrated below. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0094e-ftnote.013"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Glanville; 1997: 279 </s></p></note><figure id="BAWE_0094e-fig.005"><head rend="bold">Graph E</head></figure><p n="p20.33"><s n="s1.4;p20.33">Above SRAS is plotted past <hi rend="italic">Y*</hi>, right of LRAS. The underlying intuition is that in the short run the economy is able to produce at levels where e.g. all machinery is used beyond sustainable levels. </s><s n="s2.4;p20.33">In terms of wages, the model is the opposite of the extreme Keynesian model. </s><s n="s3.4;p20.33">There seems to be a trade-off between unemployment and inflation, which implies that real wages are countercyclical. </s><s n="s4.4;p20.33">If the economy booms, real wages diminish unless the economy produces at the horizontal part of the SRAS. </s></p><p n="p21.33"><s n="s1.2;p21.33">Even though moderate Keynesian model accounts for overheating of economies and unemployment-inflation trade-off, it is not without limitations. </s><s n="s2.2;p21.33">Some of these limitations are pointed out by the monetarists. </s></p></div2><div2><head>Monetarist ideas explained</head><p n="p22.33"><s n="s1.3;p22.33">The classical economists believe that the markets will clear, as explained in the LRAS section above. </s><s n="s2.3;p22.33">Unsurprisingly, the extreme monetarists argue that it is justifiable to assume that the markets will work in the short run. </s><s n="s3.3;p22.33">Hence, the SRAS curve is vertical. <ref target="BAWE_0094e-ftnote.014"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0094e-ftnote.014"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Adapted from Glanville; 1997: 285 </s></p></note><figure id="BAWE_0094e-fig.006"><head rend="bold">Graph F</head></figure><p n="p23.33"><s n="s1.4;p23.33">This model corresponds to the classical view of economics - the invisible hand makes the markets work. </s><s n="s2.4;p23.33">Policy implication is that fiscal policy will lead into inflation only, full crowding-out occurs, but, monetary policy can be used to influence <hi rend="italic">P</hi>. </s><s n="s3.4;p23.33">Changes in demand will only affect <hi rend="italic">P</hi> but not <hi rend="italic">Y</hi>. </s><s n="s4.4;p23.33">An interesting observation is that wages are acyclical (i.e. economic cycles do not matter as in the Keynesian model) - all markets clear and hence there is no unemployment. </s></p><p n="p24.33"><s n="s1.2;p24.33">Nevertheless, there is evidence to support the argument that this is not the case in the short run - the reasoning behind the Keynesian thought. </s><s n="s2.2;p24.33">Their main opposition to the monetarist model is that short run situations are significant enough to be acted upon. </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">The AS theories discussed</head><p n="p25.33"><s n="s1.4;p25.33">Empirical evidence must be considered to evaluate the models above. </s><s n="s2.4;p25.33">It is clear that there is a little if any conclusive empirical research regarding the models. </s><s n="s3.4;p25.33">Before the evaluation, the condition for long-run equilibrium is established. </s><s n="s4.4;p25.33">In his work, Mankiw sets out equilibrium requirements graphically:<ref target="BAWE_0094e-ftnote.015"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0094e-ftnote.015"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Mankiw; 2002: 251 </s></p></note><figure id="BAWE_0094e-fig.007"><head rend="bold">Graph G</head></figure><p n="p26.33"><s n="s1.5;p26.33">In all long-run equilibrium points, LRAS, SRAS and AD curve must intersect, such as in point (a) in graph G. In the graph, SRAS shifts from 1 to 2, causing an increase in price level to <hi rend="italic">P*'</hi> and reducing output below <hi rend="italic">Y*</hi> level. </s><s n="s2.5;p26.33">The new short-run equilibrium is at (b) - there is stagflation: unemployment and <hi rend="italic">P</hi> have increased. </s><s n="s3.5;p26.33">According to Mankiw, these kinds of adverse supply shocks have been empirically observed and they have been caused by e.g. oil crisis in 1970s.<ref target="BAWE_0094e-ftnote.016"/> Furthermore, Mankiw argues that a government can use fiscal and monetary policy to shift AD (in the graph from 1 to 2) and restore full employment level output at point (c).<ref target="BAWE_0094e-ftnote.017"/> Though, the result is increased <hi rend="italic">P</hi>. </s><s n="s4.5;p26.33">The policy implication is that the markets will not immediately adjust to supply shocks and the government can use demand-side policies to restore <hi rend="italic">Y*</hi>. </s><s n="s5.5;p26.33">Interestingly, the horizontal model of SRAS as set in graph B was created based on observations about the Great Depression,<ref target="BAWE_0094e-ftnote.018"/> where the markets did not adjust (rather than based on observations about 1970s crisis). </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0094e-ftnote.016"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid: 253 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0094e-ftnote.017"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0094e-ftnote.018"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid: 256 </s></p></note><p n="p27.33"><s n="s1.6;p27.33">In contrast, the monetarist ideas gained impetus during the 1970s oil crisis.<ref target="BAWE_0094e-ftnote.019"/> In several countries, government demand-side policies seemed to fail and there was widespread stagflation. </s><s n="s2.6;p27.33">Monetarist explained the phenomenon by relating it to their vertical SRAS/LRAS model (see graph F above). </s><s n="s3.6;p27.33">Government attempts to increase AD were leading to an increased <hi rend="italic">P</hi> only. </s><s n="s4.6;p27.33">In spite of widespread popularity of monetarist ideas and Milton Friedman's persuasive statement that "<hi rend="italic">inflation is always and everywhere a monetary phenomenon,"</hi><ref target="BAWE_0094e-ftnote.020"/> monetarists have failed to find conclusive evidence to support their view. </s><s n="s5.6;p27.33">The limitation to their view is that there seems to be a trade-off between inflation and unemployment. </s><s n="s6.6;p27.33">On the other hand, Friedman was content to argue that the trade-off is temporary and not permanent.<ref target="BAWE_0094e-ftnote.021"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0094e-ftnote.019"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Blanchard; 2003: 152 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0094e-ftnote.020"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Friedman; 1956: 21 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0094e-ftnote.021"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid: 23 </s></p></note><p n="p28.33"><s n="s1.2;p28.33">Moderate Keynesians argue that even if the trade-off between inflation and unemployment is temporary, it is significant enough. </s><s n="s2.2;p28.33">They believe that the adjustment process of markets takes unacceptably long - and that the short-run trade-off matters as illustrated below. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0094e-fig.008"><head rend="bold">Graph E (revisited)</head></figure><p n="p29.33"><s n="s1.3;p29.33">The upward sloping section in the model above indicates that there is a trade-off between inflation and unemployment. </s><s n="s2.3;p29.33">Movement from AD1 via AD2 to AD3 shows increasing inflation and decreasing unemployment. </s><s n="s3.3;p29.33">In his work Blanchard sets out the AS relation for upward sloping section algebraically:<ref target="BAWE_0094e-ftnote.022"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0094e-ftnote.022"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Blanchard; 2003: 136 </s></p></note><p rend="ordered" n="p30.33"><s n="s1.1;p30.33"><hi rend="bold">Equation 3 </hi><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0094e-form.003"/> </s></p><p n="p31.33"><s n="s1.1;p31.33">This model was created based upon the developments of 1950s and 1960s - empirical evidence from that time period supports the moderate Keynesian model and it was almost unchallenged until the emergence of the 1970s crisis and monetarist thought. </s></p><p n="p32.33"><s n="s1.4;p32.33">The moderate Keynesian model seems more realistic than the extreme Keynesian, for two reasons. </s><s n="s2.4;p32.33">First reason is that the horizontal SRAS curve that Keynes observed during the Great Depression is accommodated in the moderate Keynesian model. </s><s n="s3.4;p32.33">The second reason is that the extreme Keynesian model cannot explain developments in the 1950s and 1960s and hence, it is too rigid a model to reflect the reality. </s><s n="s4.4;p32.33">In conclusion, I am content to argue that because of its higher correlation with empirical evidence, the moderate Keynesian view is superior to the extreme Keynesian view. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Conclusion</head><p n="p33.33"><s n="s1.8;p33.33">It seems inevitable that the academic debate about the shape of AS curves will continue further, because of the monetarist/Keynesian division. </s><s n="s2.8;p33.33">Nevertheless, it can be stated that horizontal SRAS curve combined with vertical LRAS curve is not very realistic view compared to its alternatives. </s><s n="s3.8;p33.33">In sum, there seems to be empirical evidence to give proof to all of the three models discussed above. </s><s n="s4.8;p33.33">It is interesting to observe how after several years of research the economic schools of thought disagree on some fundamental aspects of the AS analysis. </s><s n="s5.8;p33.33">Governments find themselves in a difficult position, because the models predict e.g. wage behaviour in different ways. </s><s n="s6.8;p33.33">Nevertheless, the extreme Keynesian view has lost many supporters and the academic consensus to the moderate view. </s><s n="s7.8;p33.33">I believe it is not a great exaggeration to say that the L-shaped model of the SRAS/LRAS curve is too rigid for the present day economic thought. </s><s n="s8.8;p33.33">However, it is clear that monetarists and Keynesians disagree, and the debate will continue for the foreseeable future. </s></p></div1></body><back><div1 type="bibliography"><head rend="bold">Bibliography</head><p>Blanchard, Olivier. 2003. <hi rend="italic">Macroeconomics</hi> (third edition). Pearson Education Ltd. The United Stated of America.</p><p>Friedman, Milton. 1956. <hi rend="italic">Editor of Studies in the Quantity Theory of Money</hi>. University of Chicago Press. Chicago. The United States of America.</p><p>Glanville, Alan. 1997. <hi rend="italic">Economics from a global perspective.</hi> Alan Glanville Books. Oxford. United Kingdom.</p><p>Keynes, John Maynard. 1923. <hi rend="italic">A Tract on Monetary Reform</hi> (reprinted 2000). Prometheus Books. New York. The United States of America.</p><p>Mankiw, N. Gregory. <hi rend="italic">Macroeconomics</hi> (5<hi rend="sup">th</hi> edition). Worth Publishers. New York. The United States of America.</p></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
