<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_0094d" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>"The European Council does not play a formal role in Community decision-making and does not constitute an institution hierarchically superior to the Community Institutions." (Koen Lenaerts) Discuss.</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">The document has a title page which contains:
document title
title part</note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">Language used in quote: <foreign id="English">English</foreign></note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">deleted: header: student number
</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">2</p><p n="date">2006-01</p><p n="module title">Foundations of European Law</p><p n="module code">LA240</p><p n="genre family">Essay</p><p n="discipline">Law</p><p n="disciplinary group">SS</p><p n="grade">M</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">2488</p><p n="number of s-units">77</p><p n="number of p">30</p><p n="number of tables">0</p><p n="number of figures">0</p><p n="number of block quotes">6</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">0</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">0</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">32.3</p><p n="average s-units per p">2.6</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">m</p><p n="year of birth">1984</p><p n="first language">Finnish</p><p n="education">OSA</p><p n="course">Economics</p><p n="student ID">0094</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><docTitle><titlePart>Foundations of European Union Law Assignment: "<hi rend="italic">The European Council does not play a formal role in Community decision-making and does not constitute an institution hierarchically superior to the Community Institutions." (Koen Lenaerts) Discuss.</hi> </titlePart></docTitle><titlePart>Foundations of European Union Law LA2400 28/11/2005<name type="student ID"/> University of <name type="university"/> Word count: 2497</titlePart></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">1. Introduction</head><p n="p1.30"><s n="s1.7;p1.30">It is controversial - but probably not an exaggeration - to state that "The European Council does not play a formal role in the Community decision-making and does not constitute an institution hierarchically superior to the Community Institutions" in the light of examples from European Union law and Community decision-making. </s><s n="s2.7;p1.30">However, it is clear that the validity of the statement is limited to an extent, because there is evidence that the European Council in fact interferes with the Community decision-making process. </s><s n="s3.7;p1.30">Therefore, limitations to the statement arising from contradicting evidence are discussed with relevant Community law. </s><s n="s4.7;p1.30">Firstly, the role of the European Council is compared with the executive and administrative Community Institutions. </s><s n="s5.7;p1.30">Secondly, the related institutional hierarchy is investigated, which is, thirdly, followed by evaluation of the realities of Community decision-making processes. </s><s n="s6.7;p1.30">Finally, it is obvious that the statement has underlying political implications and these are discussed, although briefly because the emphasis is on the legal perspective, but the need for reform is dealt with in the conclusion of the essay. </s><s n="s7.7;p1.30">Hence, a critical viewpoint to the statement is established. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">2. The formal role of the European Council and the Community Institutions</head><p n="p2.30"><s n="s1.2;p2.30">The role of the European Council in the Community decision-making process is rather broadly defined in the Treaties and it is important to contrast it with those of the Community Institutions in order to form a more realistic picture. </s><s n="s2.2;p2.30">When the executive and administrative roles of authority in the EU are considered, we can limit the number of the Institutions we are dealing with: the European Commission, the Council of European Union (the Council) and the European Council.<ref target="BAWE_0094d-ftnote.001"/> Problems result from their similar areas of competence; the balance of power between them has been widely debated.<ref target="BAWE_0094d-ftnote.002"/> Now, the role of the European Council and the extent of its powers is discussed and contrasted with the other two executive and administrative Community institutions. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0094d-ftnote.001"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Adapted from Bermann et al; 2005: 1 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0094d-ftnote.002"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Craig phrases similar views (Craig; 2005: 1) </s></p></note><div2><head rend="bold">2.1 The European Council</head><p n="p3.30"><s n="s1.5;p3.30">The European Council is a formal institution recognised in the Treaties, but its origins are different from the executive Community institutions, which are defined in Treaty Establishing the European Community 1957.<ref target="BAWE_0094d-ftnote.003"/> In 1961, it was agreed in Bonn that the Heads of Government should meet regularly to decide policy issues and these summits were institutionalised at the Paris summit 1974.<ref target="BAWE_0094d-ftnote.004"/> The Single European Act 1986 included the meeting in the Treaties under the name the "European Council".<ref target="BAWE_0094d-ftnote.005"/> Furthermore, Treaty on European Union 1992 (TEU) (Art. </s><s n="s2.5;p3.30">4, first paragraph) defined the task of the European Council as "[to provide] the Union with the necessary impetus for its development" and "[set out] general political guidelines." </s><ref target="BAWE_0094d-ftnote.006"/><s n="s3.5;p3.30">It is clear that TEU Art. </s><s n="s4.5;p3.30">4 is a broad definition and allows for interpretation. </s><s n="s5.5;p3.30">Additionally, TEU conferred the responsibility over the definition of principles of Common Foreign and Security Policy (CFSP), in Title V / Article J.8 (now 18), but that is outside the sphere of competence of the Community Institutions.<ref target="BAWE_0094d-ftnote.007"/> Moreover, the Treaties of Amsterdam 1998 <ref target="BAWE_0094d-ftnote.008"/> and Nice 2000 <ref target="BAWE_0094d-ftnote.009"/> contributed to the European Council, but they did not clarify the role of the European Council. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0094d-ftnote.003"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Craig; 2002: 33 ; Title as in Article G(1) of Treaty on European Union </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0094d-ftnote.004"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Adapted from Chalmers; 1998: 113 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0094d-ftnote.005"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Lenaerts et al; 2005: 384 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0094d-ftnote.006"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0094d-ftnote.007"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Adapted from Tillotson et al; 2003: 16 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0094d-ftnote.008"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Art J.3 on CFSP </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0094d-ftnote.009"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Issues relating to expansion of the EU (Galloway; 2001; 146) </s></p></note><p n="p4.30"><s n="s1.3;p4.30">It has been argued that the institutional framework of the EC does not include the European Council to any extent: "[the Communities] operate through <hi rend="italic">a single institutional framework</hi> (i.e. </s><s n="s2.3;p4.30">Commission-Council-Parliament-Court)." </s><ref target="BAWE_0094d-ftnote.010"/><s n="s3.3;p4.30">This supports the argument that the European Council does not play a formal role in the Community decision-making. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0094d-ftnote.010"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Galloway; 2001: 15 </s></p></note></div2><div2><head rend="bold">2.2 The role of the European Council contrasted with the European Commission</head><p n="p5.30"><s n="s1.2;p5.30">In addition to the European Council, administrative and executive power in the Community decision-making process is arguably vested in the European Commission.<ref target="BAWE_0094d-ftnote.011"/> Surprisingly, there are concerns that the European Council interferes with areas the Commission's competence in Community decision-making and, the Commission identified a problem involving its overlapping role with the European Council: "[T]he Commission's own role of initiative is being 'usurped' in [the internal mechanics of the EU institutions] by the European Council.<ref target="BAWE_0094d-ftnote.012"/> The conclusion is that the European Council can interfere with the role of the Commission. </s><s n="s2.2;p5.30">Therefore, the exact division of the roles of European Council and the Commission is not clear. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0094d-ftnote.011"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Fairhurst; 2006: 36 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0094d-ftnote.012"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">European Commission; 2002: 240 </s></p></note></div2><div2><head rend="bold">2.3 Distinction between the European Council and the Council</head><p n="p6.30"><s n="s1.6;p6.30">The membership in the European Council and the Council can be overlapping, thus, identification of their comparative roles seems problematic. </s><s n="s2.6;p6.30">A distinction can be made based on the procedural considerations, which arise from the EC Treaty Arts. </s><s n="s3.6;p6.30">202 to 210 (ex Arts. </s><s n="s4.6;p6.30">145-154) that define the Council's procedures; for example, in the Council as opposed to the European Council, the President of the Commission is not allowed to take part in the decision-making.<ref target="BAWE_0094d-ftnote.013"/> On the other hand, it has been argued that: "In theory, the European Council may act as the Council, because it is composed of a representative at ministerial level of each member state." </s><ref target="BAWE_0094d-ftnote.014"/><s n="s5.6;p6.30">Hence, the distinction based on the procedural difference is not necessarily helpful. </s><s n="s6.6;p6.30">It can be concluded that the distinction of the roles of the European Council as opposed to the Council and the Commission is not clear and their hierarchical positions have to be considered. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0094d-ftnote.013"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Fairhurst; 2006: 95 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0094d-ftnote.014"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Lenaerts et al; 2005: 386 </s></p></note></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">3. Hierarchical superiority and the European Council</head><p n="p7.30"><s n="s1.2;p7.30">The hierarchical superiority of the European Council to the Community Institutions cannot be found in Treaties, but evidence suggests that a degree of political superiority exists. </s><s n="s2.2;p7.30">Not surprisingly, the hierarchical position of the European Council has provoked debate.The Commission has phrased concerns about the increasing influence of the European Council: </s></p><quote lang="English"><hi rend="italic">[T]he Lisbon decision</hi> [2000]<hi rend="italic"> to give the spring European Councilthe task of reviewing the state of progress of the Union's economic and social modernisation strategy and updating its content each yearthreatens to undermine the institutional balance between Parliament,the Commission and the Council and especially the Commission's position.</hi> <ref target="BAWE_0094d-ftnote.015"/></quote><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0094d-ftnote.015"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">European Commission; 2002: 234 </s></p></note><p n="p8.30"><s n="s1.2;p8.30">Clearly, it is not a misperception that in practice the influence of the European Council has been growing. </s><s n="s2.2;p8.30">Therefore, alterations in the balance of power may lead to superiority of the European Council. </s></p><p n="p9.30"><s n="s1.1;p9.30">In contrast it has been argued that the hierarchy of the Community Institutions excludes the European Council: </s></p><quote lang="English"><hi rend="italic">The European Council is not an institution of the Communities and [...] takes no formal part in Community decision-making. The institution of the European Council therefore does not mean that the Community Institutions are subject to a higher-ranking intergovernmental institution.</hi> <ref target="BAWE_0094d-ftnote.016"/></quote><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0094d-ftnote.016"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Lenaerts et al; 2005: 385 </s></p></note><p n="p10.30"><s n="s1.1;p10.30">This supports the statement under discussion; under legal definitions the European Council is intergovernmental organisation not directly part of the supranational framework of the Community Institutions. </s></p><p n="p11.30"><s n="s1.1;p11.30">Moreover, Jean Monnet made an observation on the Community authority: </s></p><quote lang="English"><hi rend="italic">[W]e were wrong in 1952 to think that Europe would be built on the High Authority of the Coal and Steel Community as a supranational government. What matters now is that the Heads of national governments meet together regularly in the European Council. That's where the authority is.</hi> <ref target="BAWE_0094d-ftnote.017"/></quote><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0094d-ftnote.017"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Tillotson et al; 2003: 13 </s></p></note><p n="p12.30"><s n="s1.2;p12.30">He argues that the intergovernmental European Council has the greatest authority instead of the supranational institutions. </s><s n="s2.2;p12.30">Thus, the European Council has its role of supreme authority exists in a different framework, which supports the view that the European Council does not constitute an institution hierarchically superior to the Community Institutions. </s></p><p n="p13.30"><s n="s1.2;p13.30">The importance of conception of hierarchy in the Community has been challenged by various authors. </s><s n="s2.2;p13.30">For example, Bermann and Craig have argued that the significance of unambiguous hierarchy is overstated, because it is relevant only in terms of public identity.<ref target="BAWE_0094d-ftnote.018"/> However, it is clear that public identity does matter, as lack of transparency and democratic legitimacy are arguably problems in the Community decision-making.<ref target="BAWE_0094d-ftnote.019"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0094d-ftnote.018"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Bermann; 2005: 1 , Craig; 2005: 1 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0094d-ftnote.019"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Bermann agrees with that view (Bermann; 2005: 1) </s></p></note><p n="p14.30"><s n="s1.3;p14.30">The conclusion is that from the legal perspective the European Council does not constitute an organisation hierarchically superior to the Community Institutions. </s><s n="s2.3;p14.30">The European Council has arguably acted beyond the powers that have been conferred to it in the Treaties and there have been concerns that its influence has become too wide. </s><s n="s3.3;p14.30">Therefore, the influence of the European Council in Community decision-making is discussed below. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">4. The influence of the European Council in Community decision-making</head><p n="p15.30"><s n="s1.2;p15.30">Obviously, there are examples of the European Council influencing Community decision-making process. </s><s n="s2.2;p15.30">However, according to the Treaties the European Council has no powers in Community law-making, although the decision-making process in the EC is elitist and the European Council consists of top representatives of the Member States. <ref target="BAWE_0094d-ftnote.020"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0094d-ftnote.020"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Craig agrees with this view (Craig; 2002: 33) </s></p></note><p n="p16.30"><s n="s1.1;p16.30">There is evidence that the European Council has influenced Community decision-making beyond its powers: </s></p><quote lang="English"><hi rend="italic">the European Council held in Milan on June 29, 1985 adopted by a majority vote against a minority the decision to initiate the procedure provided for in Art. 236 of the EEC Treaty and toconsult the Parliament on amending the Treaty. In so doing, it disregarded the Council's rules of procedure... However the formal decision was taken by the Council.</hi> <ref target="BAWE_0094d-ftnote.021"/></quote><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0094d-ftnote.021"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Lenaerts et al; 2005: 386 </s></p></note><p n="p17.30"><s n="s1.1;p17.30">The implication is that the European Council influences the Community decision-making processes, but it cannot do so within the powers that have been granted to it in the Treaties and hence formal decisions are taken by the other executive Community Institutions. </s></p><p n="p18.30"><s n="s1.3;p18.30">In support of this view Lenaerts et al. argued that: "in practice [the Council] only gives a legal effect to what the European Council has already decided on the political level." </s><ref target="BAWE_0094d-ftnote.022"/><s n="s2.3;p18.30">The European Council decides to an extent about the policies of the Council, which then legalises the decision. </s><s n="s3.3;p18.30">Nevertheless, the Council has no legal obligation to obey their decisions but there is a political obligation as the ministerial members are from the same governments.<ref target="BAWE_0094d-ftnote.023"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0094d-ftnote.022"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Lenaerts et al; 2005: 387 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0094d-ftnote.023"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Lenaerts et al make similar observation (Lenaerts et al; 2005: 387) </s></p></note><p n="p19.30"><s n="s1.2;p19.30">Interestingly, the Commission has suggested that: "[T]he European Council no longer serves just to provide general impetus and arbitrate on specific issues: although the Treaties do not confer on it any explicit decision-making powers, it has become a genuine political decision-maker in practice." </s><ref target="BAWE_0094d-ftnote.024"/><s n="s2.2;p19.30">This observation identifies decision-making processes in the EU which are not based on the legal powers set out in Treaties, but on political influences. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0094d-ftnote.024"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">European Commission; 2002: 234 </s></p></note><p n="p20.30"><s n="s1.1;p20.30">Furthermore, the Commission gives an example where regulations falling under the competence of the Community Institutions were agreed on by the European Council without the Community procedures, which most certainly falls under the competence of the Commission and the Council. </s></p><quote lang="English"><hi rend="italic"> The code of conduct for business taxation has no legal force but constitutes a kind of political agreement between the Member States. It relies on peerpressure and the monitoring which that involves, but does not introduce a formal system and covers only a very narrow range of taxation.</hi> <ref target="BAWE_0094d-ftnote.025"/></quote><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0094d-ftnote.025"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.3;pn1.1">European Commission; 2002: 209. </s><s n="s2.3;pn1.1">Moreover, the Code of Conduct for Business Taxation was originally discussed in conclusions of the Economic and Financial Affairs Council of 1.12.1997 Doc. </s><s n="s3.3;pn1.1">98/C 2/01, but it was not legally binding (European Commission; 2002: 209) </s></p></note><p n="p21.30"><s n="s1.2;p21.30">It might be an exaggeration to say that the Commission is trying to understate the importance of such agreement, but clearly, it can be seen that the European Council interferes with an area that is more likely within Commission's competence. </s><s n="s2.2;p21.30">Thus, there is evidence that the European Council has influence in the Community decision-making exceeding those powers defined in the Treaties. </s></p><p n="p22.30"><s n="s1.3;p22.30">Moreover, Tillotson et al. argue that: "[The European Council] is not itself normally engaged in formal Treaty legislative and political co-operation processes." </s><ref target="BAWE_0094d-ftnote.026"/><s n="s2.3;p22.30">It seems logical that the interference of the European Council in the Community decision-making process is the exception, but that should not devalue the importance of those interferences. </s><s n="s3.3;p22.30">Interestingly, Tillotson et al. clearly suggest that the European Council can take part in formal decision-making processes. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0094d-ftnote.026"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Tillotson et al; 2003: 94 </s></p></note><p n="p23.30"><s n="s1.2;p23.30">Adopting a similar view, Bast argues that: "the European Council does not adopt laws... thus its law-making (or, nominally, decision-making) is not subject to the heightened scrutiny." </s><ref target="BAWE_0094d-ftnote.027"/><s n="s2.2;p23.30">It is crucial to note here that the European Council in fact takes part in the legislative process, but it cannot be held accountable or reviewed. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0094d-ftnote.027"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Bast; 2005: 1 </s></p></note><p n="p24.30"><s n="s1.1;p24.30">Craig goes even further in his argument and has stated: </s></p><quote lang="English"><hi rend="italic">although the treaties say relatively little about the powers of the European Council, the reality is that nothing of major importance happens without its approval. It has a say in setting the legislative agenda, in setting the Union's priorities, and in deciding the pace and direction of change within the Union.</hi> <ref target="BAWE_0094d-ftnote.028"/></quote><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0094d-ftnote.028"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Craig; 2005: 1 </s></p></note><p n="p25.30"><s n="s1.1;p25.30">It has to be agreed on that the political reality is a major factor in the decision-making, not just the legal arguments. </s></p><p n="p26.30"><s n="s1.2;p26.30">In conclusion, if only legal considerations are taken into account, then the statement under discussion is valid, but the arguments above show that there is a need notice the political and practical implications. </s><s n="s2.2;p26.30">The interferences of the European Council with the Community decision-making processes are not based on Community legislation and hence give a rise to concerns, which are addressed next. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">5. The implications of the statement</head><p n="p27.30"><s n="s1.2;p27.30">The statement under discussion was phrased by Lenaerts et al. in their work <hi rend="italic">Constitutional Law of the European Union</hi><ref target="BAWE_0094d-ftnote.029"/> and it is clear that their statement is subject to limitations. </s><s n="s2.2;p27.30">Thus, there are underlying reasons to take such point of view. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0094d-ftnote.029"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Lenaerts et al; 2005: 39 </s></p></note><p n="p28.30"><s n="s1.6;p28.30">Surprisingly, it can be agreed that the acts of the European Council are not subject to judicial review in the European Court of Justice.<ref target="BAWE_0094d-ftnote.030"/> The direct implication is that the accountability of the European Council is limited, and therefore, a need for reform arises. </s><s n="s2.6;p28.30">That is relevant here because Koen Lenaerts is a judge in the European Court of Justice (ECJ) and it is likely that his motive to make the statement is to call for a reform. </s><s n="s3.6;p28.30">In support of this view, it has been argued that ECJ judges try to maintain the ECJ's institutional position and "extend the ambit of their jurisprudence".<ref target="BAWE_0094d-ftnote.031"/> This supports the view that the statement under discussion is to an extent political. </s><s n="s4.6;p28.30">The ECJ judges are concerned for interferences and the lack of accountability of the European Council, which contributes to democratic deficit. </s><s n="s5.6;p28.30">However, the approach taken by Lenaerts et al. is not necessarily right. </s><s n="s6.6;p28.30">There has been argument that legal isolation of the European Council from the decision-making processes will discourage citizens' identification with the Union.<ref target="BAWE_0094d-ftnote.032"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0094d-ftnote.030"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Adapted from Bermann et al. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0094d-ftnote.031"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Hirschl; 2005: 1 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0094d-ftnote.032"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Bogdandy; 2005: 1 </s></p></note><p n="p29.30"><s n="s1.3;p29.30">The likely purpose of the statement is to argue for reform - based on the Treaties the statement is arguably valid, but in reality it is not. </s><s n="s2.3;p29.30">The Treaty establishing a Constitution for Europe attempted to remedy some of the problems, but it is highly questionable whether the Constitution will ever be ratified. </s><s n="s3.3;p29.30">The lack of clarity remains. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">6. Conclusion</head><p n="p30.30"><s n="s1.6;p30.30">In conclusion it has been satisfied that from a legal perspective: "The European Council does not play a formal role in Community decision-making and does not constitute an institution hierarchically superior to the Community Institutions." </s><s n="s2.6;p30.30">Nevertheless, it is not straightforward to define the absolute extent of the powers of the European Council, as the various examples <hi rend="italic">supra</hi> have shown. </s><s n="s3.6;p30.30">It has been shown that there are both legal and political aspects to the role of the European Council in the Community decision-making as well as in the institutional hierarchy of the Community. </s><s n="s4.6;p30.30">However, there is no evidence in the Treaties that the European Council could play a formal role in the Community decision-making, which largely justifies the statement under discussion. </s><s n="s5.6;p30.30">When making the statement, it is likely Lenaerts et al. were calling for more clarity and reform in the Community decision-making process, but following the rejection of the Constitutional Treaty, it seems that such cohesion cannot be achieved with the present legislation. </s><s n="s6.6;p30.30">Again, an argument for reform of the Community decision-making process can be invoked. </s></p></div1></body><back><div1 type="bibliography"><div2 type="bibliography"><head>Treaties Referred to:</head><p>Treaty Establishing the European Community 1957 </p><p>Single European Act 1986</p><p>Treaty on European Union 1992</p><p>Treaty of Amsterdam 1997</p><p>Treaty of Nice 2000</p></div2><div2 type="bibliography"><head>Bibliography:</head><p>Bast, Jürgen. 1 November 2005. <hi rend="italic">The Constitutional Treaty as a Reflexive Constitution</hi>. German Law Journal (No.11(6)). Max Planck Institute for Comparative and International Law. Heidelberg.</p><p>Bermann, George A. - Gellhorn, Walter. June 2005. <hi rend="italic">Executive power in the new European constitution.</hi> International Journal of Constitutional Law (ICon 3.2(440)). Oxford University Press and New York University School of Law. </p><p>Bogdandy, Armin von. June 2005. <hi rend="italic">The European Constitution and European Identity.</hi> International Journal of Constitutional Law (ICon 3.2(295)). Oxford University Press and New York University School of Law.</p><p>Chalmers, Damian. 1998. <hi rend="italic">European Union Law Volume I: Law and EU Government.</hi> Dartmouth Publishing Limited. Hants.</p><p>Craig, Paul. June 2005. <hi rend="italic">European governance: Executive and administrative powers under the new constitutional settlement</hi>. International Journal of Constitutional Law (ICon 3.2(407)). Oxford University Press and New York University School of Law.</p><p>Craig, Paul - de Búrca, Gráinne. 2002. <hi rend="italic">EU Law: Texts, Cases and Materials</hi> (3<hi rend="sup">rd</hi> ed.). Oxford University Press. Oxford.</p><p>European Commission. 2002. <hi rend="italic">European governance: preparatory work for white paper.</hi> Office for official publications of the European Communities. Luxembourg.</p><p>Fairhurst, John. 2006. <hi rend="italic">Law of the European Union</hi> (5<hi rend="sup">th</hi> ed.). Bell&amp;Bain Limited. Glasgow.</p><p>Galloway, David. 2001. <hi rend="italic">The Treaty of Nice and Beyond: realities and illusions of power in the EU.</hi> Sheffield academic press. Sheffield.</p><p>Hirschl, Ran. June 2005. <hi rend="italic">Preserving hegemony? Assessing the political origins of the EU Constitution.</hi> International Journal of Constitutional Law (ICon 3.2(269)). Oxford University Press and New York University School of Law.</p><p>Lenaerts, Koen - Van Nuffel, Piet - Bray, Robert (editor). 2005. <hi rend="italic">Constitutional Law of the European Union</hi> (2<hi rend="sup">nd</hi> ed.). Sweet&amp;Maxwell. London.</p><p>Tillotson, John - Foster, Nigel. 2003. <hi rend="italic">Texts, cases and materials on European Union Law</hi> (4<hi rend="sup">th</hi> ed.). Cavendish Publishing Limited. London.</p></div2></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
