<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_0094c" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Economics Coursework Assignment: What factors led to the slowdown of the US economy in 2001? Have matters improved in 2004? Evaluate the risks of a downturn in 2005 if oil prices remain over $40 a barrel. What are the effects on the European and Asian economies?</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">The document has a title page which contains:
document title
title part</note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">deleted: header: student number; footer: page numbers
deleted: Word count: 1956</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">1</p><p n="date">2005-01</p><p n="module title">Economics 1</p><p n="module code">EC107</p><p n="genre family">Essay</p><p n="discipline">Economics</p><p n="disciplinary group">SS</p><p n="grade">D</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">1956</p><p n="number of s-units">67</p><p n="number of p">17</p><p n="number of tables">0</p><p n="number of figures">1</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">0</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">0</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">29.2</p><p n="average s-units per p">3.9</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">m</p><p n="year of birth">1984</p><p n="first language">Finnish</p><p n="education">OSA</p><p n="course">Economics</p><p n="student ID">0094</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><docTitle><titlePart>Economics Coursework Assignment: <hi rend="italic">What factors led to the slowdown of the US economy in 2001? Have matters improved in 2004? Evaluate the risks of a downturn in 2005 if oil prices remain over $40 a barrel. What are the effects on the European and Asian economies?</hi> </titlePart></docTitle><titlePart> Economics I EC1070 PPO5 <name type="student ID"/> University of <name type="university"/> 08-01-2005</titlePart></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">1. Introduction</head><p n="p1.17"><s n="s1.7;p1.17">The United States of America (US) is no doubt the leading market economy in the world and therefore it is clear that fluctuations in it attract interest, especially signs of slowdown. </s><s n="s2.7;p1.17">Throughout the 1990s the US was performing strong in terms of economy, but recently there has been a downturn. </s><s n="s3.7;p1.17">Especially the year 2001 was difficult, because the financial markets were suffering of lack of confidence and terrorist attacks further deepened the problem. </s><s n="s4.7;p1.17">Yet, there have not been any significant signs of recovery, even though it can be argued that there are prospects for a good economic year 2005 in the US. Nevertheless, oil price is a factor that can endanger the positive development in the economy and in can pose a problem in the trade deficit that the country struggles with. </s><s n="s5.7;p1.17">In addition, weak dollar might further deepen this difficulty. </s><s n="s6.7;p1.17">The uncertainty of the US economy is reflected on the other economies of the world, particularly on the Asian ones, but Euro Area has suffered from the fluctuations as well. </s><s n="s7.7;p1.17">Here, the main economic issues are dealt and the past, present and the future of the US economy is evaluated. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">2. Recent Economic History of the US</head><p n="p2.17"><s n="s1.4;p2.17">The 1990s was a period of growth and economic boom in the US. This result is partly related to the optimism that the end of Cold War created in the world economy. </s><s n="s2.4;p2.17">The US was growing strongly due to emergence of new technology, which became known amongst the economists as "the new economy" boom. </s><s n="s3.4;p2.17">There was a sustained increase in the growth of productivity, which was largely explained by new inventions. </s><s n="s4.4;p2.17">These inventions induced massive investment and the confidence in the financial markets was high. </s></p><p n="p3.17"><s n="s1.3;p3.17">It can be argued that between the years 1992-2000 there was a virtuous circle of economy in the US. The US gross domestic product (GDP) was growing fast and this facilitated a growth in investment, which in turn caused GDP to grow. </s><s n="s2.3;p3.17">As interest rates were low, high investment was made possible. </s><s n="s3.3;p3.17">The multiplier-accelerator action in the US was strong and the information technology (IT) industry was booming until the year 2000.<ref target="BAWE_0094c-ftnote.001"/> In that year the IT sector experienced a heavy downturn as the stocks had been overvalued and the so-called "dot.com" companies were falling one after another.<ref target="BAWE_0094c-ftnote.002"/> As the stocks of "dot.com" firms were rocketing up, it was clear that this development could not be long-lived, as there were no indications that there could be production growth in those firms could respond to the huge investment that was directed to the industry.<ref target="BAWE_0094c-ftnote.003"/> These firms were, if anything, destroying wealth rather than creating it. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0094c-ftnote.001"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Greenspan; 2000 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0094c-ftnote.002"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Goldman; 2000 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0094c-ftnote.003"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid </s></p></note><p n="p4.17"><s n="s1.1;p4.17">Moreover, the extensive growth in the US economy caused capital inflows and this resulted into a deficit in the current account in the US as its net foreign investment was negative.<ref target="BAWE_0094c-ftnote.004"/> The rapidly growing GDP increased the demand for imports.<ref target="BAWE_0094c-ftnote.005"/> The consumers had more income to spend and the purchasing power of dollar was increasing.<ref target="BAWE_0094c-ftnote.006"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0094c-ftnote.004"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Mann; 2000 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0094c-ftnote.005"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0094c-ftnote.006"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid </s></p></note><p n="p5.17"><s n="s1.5;p5.17">A factor relating to imports must be mentioned here, namely oil. </s><s n="s2.5;p5.17">The energy prices increased during the years 1999 and 2000 <ref target="BAWE_0094c-ftnote.007"/> as a result of increasing US demand. </s><s n="s3.5;p5.17">Oil price reached in real terms the levels of the 1970s Oil Crisis. </s><s n="s4.5;p5.17">This factor increased the costs of production and further widened the trade deficit. </s><s n="s5.5;p5.17">The crash of IT sector, current account deficit and increasing energy prices were inevitably leading in to a financial crisis in the US stock markets. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0094c-ftnote.007"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Meyer; 2001 </s></p></note><p n="p6.17"><s n="s1.5;p6.17">Investors were liquidating their portfolios and buying bonds. </s><s n="s2.5;p6.17">Bond prices were increasing as a result of uncertain moods in the financial markets, leading in to increasing interest rates. </s><s n="s3.5;p6.17">As interest rate, the price of money, became higher there was insufficient investment to sustain the production. </s><s n="s4.5;p6.17">Output figures fell and unemployment started to grow.<ref target="BAWE_0094c-ftnote.008"/> Though, given these facts, it was clear that high interest rates would keep inflation low. </s><s n="s5.5;p6.17">Not surprisingly falling income, increasing unemployment and high interest rates resulted in to cut in the consumer demand.<ref target="BAWE_0094c-ftnote.009"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0094c-ftnote.008"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Blanchard; 2003: 4 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0094c-ftnote.009"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Blanchard; 2003: 6 </s></p></note><p n="p7.17"><s n="s1.5;p7.17">No doubt the strong decrease of IT sector was the main reason to the financial crisis, but the virtuous circle had turned in to a vicious circle of falling investment figures and fall in confidence.<ref target="BAWE_0094c-ftnote.010"/> The consumer confidence fell with the financial markets. </s><s n="s2.5;p7.17">The US economy was stagnating in the early 2001, but there were expectations of a recovery in the year 2002.<ref target="BAWE_0094c-ftnote.011"/> As it is sadly known, the terrorist attacks against the US on September eleventh 2001 pushed the US and the world economy into a confidence crisis.<ref target="BAWE_0094c-ftnote.012"/> The attack had also some underlying impacts, as most of the people who died in the attacks were individuals in charge of major financial operations, impairing trading capacity of the markets.<ref target="BAWE_0094c-ftnote.013"/> This factor deteriorated the confidence, as the functioning of the financial markets could not be relied on. </s><s n="s3.5;p7.17">Straightforwardly, the oil prices increased and the prices have remained high ever since, but this issue was not evident in 2001. </s><s n="s4.5;p7.17">Hence, the lack of confidence and terrorist attacks caused more problems in the financial markets. </s><s n="s5.5;p7.17">In conclusion, economic year 2001 in the US was an unsuccessful one. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0094c-ftnote.010"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Greenspan agrees with this view (Greenspan; 2000) </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0094c-ftnote.011"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Meyer; 2001 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0094c-ftnote.012"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Greenspan; 2001 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0094c-ftnote.013"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Greenspan; 2001 </s></p></note></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">3. From crisis to the present day </head><p n="p8.17"><s n="s1.2;p8.17">The US government used extensive fiscal and monetary policy in order to tackle the problems of the crisis. </s><s n="s2.2;p8.17">The prevailing theme on the fiscal side was tax cuts, which was strongly advocated in public by the Bush regime.<ref target="BAWE_0094c-ftnote.014"/> On the other hand, on the monetary side interest rate controls played a crucial part. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0094c-ftnote.014"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Blanchard; 2003: 6 </s></p></note><p n="p9.17"><s n="s1.6;p9.17">The aim of fiscal policy used was straightforward. </s><s n="s2.6;p9.17">The consumer spending was to be encouraged. </s><s n="s3.6;p9.17">As consumers have more disposable income, they will spend more. </s><s n="s4.6;p9.17">This is because the marginal propensity to consume is higher than marginal propensity to save, except in some rather rare circumstances. </s><s n="s5.6;p9.17">Consumer demand has a large importance in the US. It is around 60% of the GDP <ref target="BAWE_0094c-ftnote.015"/> and is therefore the single most important factor in the US aggregate demand (AD). </s><s n="s6.6;p9.17">Consumer demand recovered during the 2002 accordingly to the use of the fiscal policy.<ref target="BAWE_0094c-ftnote.016"/> The effect of tax cut on the aggregate demand is shown on the graph below. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0094c-ftnote.015"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Federal Reserve; 2004 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0094c-ftnote.016"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Gramlich; 2002 </s></p></note><figure id="BAWE_0094c-fig.001"><head rend="bold">Graph A: Tax cut and its impact on consumption and AD </head></figure><p n="p10.17"><s n="s1.5;p10.17">In contrast, on the monetary side, the Federal Reserve Board decreased interest rate known as "Federal Funds Rate (FFR)" in order to encourage spending and investment.<ref target="BAWE_0094c-ftnote.017"/> Logically, when interest rates are low, borrowing is less expensive and consumers are encouraged to spend and investment is induced to stock markets. </s><s n="s2.5;p10.17">But this aim was arguably not easy to achieve. </s><s n="s3.5;p10.17">Throughout the latter half of 1990s, the FFR had remained flat, but from the end of the year 2000 to the end of 2001 the FFR was dropped from 6% to 1.5%.<ref target="BAWE_0094c-ftnote.018"/> There has been argument that this action was taken too late, as the effect of decreased interest rates is not visible until a considerable amount of time, say one year, has passed.<ref target="BAWE_0094c-ftnote.019"/> As a result in 2002, the negative growth in investment was losing its momentum.<ref target="BAWE_0094c-ftnote.020"/> Therefore, it can be argued that the monetary policy combined with the fiscal policy was to some extent successful. </s><s n="s4.5;p10.17">Though, there are limitations such as the investment growth was still negative. </s><s n="s5.5;p10.17">In the light of this evidence, it is clear that this was a turning point. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0094c-ftnote.017"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Blanchard; 2003: 6 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0094c-ftnote.018"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0094c-ftnote.019"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0094c-ftnote.020"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">NIESR; 2003 (Jan) </s></p></note><p n="p11.17"><s n="s1.4;p11.17">The year 2003 was a year of cautious confidence, as the US economy was performing better. </s><s n="s2.4;p11.17">Even though, it was argued that the US economy "<hi rend="italic">will underpin the global upturn with GDP growth of 2.7% in the year 2003</hi>." </s><ref target="BAWE_0094c-ftnote.021"/><s n="s3.4;p11.17">The recovery was slow, yet it was a positive sign. </s><s n="s4.4;p11.17">Nevertheless, the net trade deficit was building up during 2003.<ref target="BAWE_0094c-ftnote.022"/> In spite of otherwise smooth recovery in the year 2003, the net trade deficit is one of the main concerns today. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0094c-ftnote.021"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">NIESR; 2003 (Oct) </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0094c-ftnote.022"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid </s></p></note><p n="p12.17"><s n="s1.5;p12.17">In 2004 the US economy was still growing<ref target="BAWE_0094c-ftnote.023"/>, but the concern about the trade deficit and the restrain of high oil prices was there. </s><s n="s2.5;p12.17">The oil prices were further increasing and its impact on the world economy, and the US in particular, was increasingly important.<ref target="BAWE_0094c-ftnote.024"/> However, the long-term interest rates were falling.<ref target="BAWE_0094c-ftnote.025"/> This leads into encouraged investment, which in turn cancels part of the negative effect that high oil prices have on the output. </s><s n="s3.5;p12.17">Unemployment in the US is yet at sustainable levels, but there is risk for growing unemployment figures.<ref target="BAWE_0094c-ftnote.026"/> The US government has tried to use monetary policy in terms of increasing interest rates in order to tackle with the emerging inflation, the dollar has already weakened.<ref target="BAWE_0094c-ftnote.027"/> The trade deficit is still a problem. </s><s n="s4.5;p12.17">The increased exports to the European Union and Asia, especially to China are likely to reduce this deficit.<ref target="BAWE_0094c-ftnote.028"/> It is unclear whether the reduction in the trade gap will be sufficient. </s><s n="s5.5;p12.17">But if it is considered whether the economic situation in the US has improved since the crisis of 2001, the answer is yes. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0094c-ftnote.023"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">at 4.2% (NIESR; 2004) </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0094c-ftnote.024"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">NIESR; 2004 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0094c-ftnote.025"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0094c-ftnote.026"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Gramlich; 2004 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0094c-ftnote.027"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0094c-ftnote.028"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Federal Reserve; 2004 </s></p></note></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">4. The impact on world economy and future predictions </head><p n="p13.17"><s n="s1.2;p13.17">Thus, the world economy has an impact on the US, but the effect is mutual and the role of the US cannot be ignored when investigating the near future of the world economy. </s><s n="s2.2;p13.17">The Euro Area and the United Kingdom have suffered from the depreciating exchange rate of the dollar and the impact of uncertain US economy on Asian countries has been even greater.<ref target="BAWE_0094c-ftnote.029"/> The Euro Area is likely to grow slowly in spite of the developments in the US or the world economy, but Asian economies are vulnerable to any downturns in the world economy.<ref target="BAWE_0094c-ftnote.030"/> The Asian countries, China in particular, have to be wary of overheating, as exports grow rapidly and there are not enough resources to sustain the supply. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0094c-ftnote.029"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">NIESR; 2004 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0094c-ftnote.030"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid </s></p></note><p n="p14.17"><s n="s1.2;p14.17">Firstly, it is clear that the development of imports from the Asia to the US is likely to be high in 2005. </s><s n="s2.2;p14.17">It has negative implications, as the US trade deficit remains strong, and as mentioned, the Asian economies might suffer from overheating. </s></p><p n="p15.17"><s n="s1.2;p15.17">Secondly, as the oil prices have remained high, around $40 a barrel, the risk to the world economy is greater than for the US itself, as argued above, the decreasing long term interest rates offer protection for the US output. </s><s n="s2.2;p15.17">Hence, it can be argued that the world economy is more vulnerable to the downturn resulting from high oil prices, rather than the US. However, the US is a net exporter of oil, so it would be an exaggeration to state that the oil price is not a significant factor regarding the US GDP. </s></p><p n="p16.17"><s n="s1.2;p16.17">Thirdly, the politics must not be ignored here. </s><s n="s2.2;p16.17">Bush regime has announced that its plan is to reduce growth.<ref target="BAWE_0094c-ftnote.031"/> The implication is that the direction is downwards, but this kind of development cannot be, in my opinion, described as an economic downturn. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0094c-ftnote.031"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">NIESR; 2004 </s></p></note></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">5. Conclusion</head><p n="p17.17"><s n="s1.7;p17.17">The US economy has arguably gone through a strong boom followed by a rapid recession since the early 1990s, but there is no clear indication how the economy will perform during the year 2005. </s><s n="s2.7;p17.17">There is a cautious optimism as the US economic policy seems to work so far, but the danger posed by budget and trading deficits, weak dollar and high oil prices indicates that there are no grounds for confidence yet. </s><s n="s3.7;p17.17">The World Economy is in a volatile state and the implications that the performance of the US economy has on the world, particularly on Asia, are not clearly seen. </s><s n="s4.7;p17.17">The stock markets show uncertainty, but the consumer confidence is recovering. </s><s n="s5.7;p17.17">Much depends on the economic policy of the US government, whether they succeed in their attempts to keep inflation low and interest rates at appropriate levels. </s><s n="s6.7;p17.17">It is not clear whether the slowdown is about to end, or to get worse. </s><s n="s7.7;p17.17">The prospects for the year 2005 are still questionable and indicate in my opinion that the slowdown has not reached its end yet. </s></p></div1></body><back><div1 type="bibliography"><head rend="bold">LIST OF SOURCES</head><div2 type="bibliography"><head rend="bold">Printed sources</head><p>Blanchard, Olivier. 2003. <hi rend="italic">Macroeconomics (Third Edition)</hi>. Prentice-Hall. United States.</p><p>Greenspan, Alan. September 20, 2001. <hi rend="italic">The condition of Financial Markets.</hi> The Federal Reserve Board. Washington.</p><p>Wolf, Martin. January 5, 2005. <hi rend="italic">How to turn an upswing into sustained growth.</hi> Financial Times. London</p></div2><div2 type="bibliography"><head rend="bold">Electronic sources</head><p>Goldman, M. Corey. 2000. <hi rend="italic">It's dot.com, not dot.bomb</hi>. CNN Finance. <seg type="URL" n="http://money.cnn.com/2000/10/24/technology/dotcom/"/> (cited: 05-01-2005)</p><p>Greenspan, Alan. December 5, 2000. <hi rend="italic">Structural changes in the economy and financial markets</hi>. The Federal Reserve Board. <seg type="URL" n="http://www.federalreserve.gov/boarddocs/speeches/2000/20001205.htm"/></p><p>(cited: 04-01-2005)</p><p>Gramlich, Edward M. March 7 2002. <hi rend="italic">Macroeconomic policy in recessions - and other times</hi>. The Federal Reserve Board. <seg type="URL" n="http://www.federalreserve.gov/boarddocs/speeches/2002/20020307/default.htm"/></p><p>(cited: 06-01-2005)</p><p>Gramlich, Edward M. September 16, 2004. <hi rend="italic">Oil shocks and monetary policy</hi>. The Federal Reserve Board. <seg type="URL" n="http://www.federalreserve.gov/boarddocs/speeches/2004/20040916/default.htm"/></p><p> (cited: 06-01-2005)</p><p>Federal Reserve. July 20, 2004. <hi rend="italic">Monetary policy report to the Congress.</hi> The Federal Reserve Board. <seg type="URL" n="http://www.federalreserve.gov/pubs/bulletin/2004/summer04_mpr.pdf"/></p><p>(cited: 06-01-2005)</p><p>Mann, Catherine L. March 2000. <hi rend="italic">Is the U.S. current account deficit sustainable?</hi> Finance &amp; Development Magazine, International Monetary Fund.</p><p><seg type="URL" n="http://www.imf.org/external/pubs/ft/fandd/2000/03/mann.htm"/></p><p>(cited: 05-01-2005)</p><p>Meyer, Lawrence H. June 6, 2001. <hi rend="italic">What happened to the new economy?</hi> The Federal Reserve Board. <seg type="URL" n="http://www.federalreserve.gov/boarddocs/speeches/2001/20010606/default.htm"/></p><p>(cited: 05-01-2005)</p><p>NIESR. January 31, 2003. <hi rend="italic">National Institute Economic Review No. 183</hi>. National Institute of Economic and Social Research. <seg type="URL" n="http://www.niesr.ac.uk/review/183.pdf"/></p><p>(cited: 05-01-2005)</p><p>NIESR. October 31, 2003. <hi rend="italic">National Institute Economic Review No. 186</hi>. National Institute of Economic and Social Research. <seg type="URL" n="http://www.niesr.ac.uk/review/186.PDF"/></p><p>(cited:05-01-2005)</p><p>NIESR. October 29, 2004. <hi rend="italic">National Institute Economic Review No. 190</hi>. National Institute of Economic and Social Research. <seg type="URL" n="http://www.niesr.ac.uk/PRESS/rev1004world.pdf"/></p><p>(cited: 06-01-2005)</p></div2></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
