<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_0097a" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>The role of maternal effect genes in the development of the nematode Caenorhabditis elegans</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">deleted: Word Count = 2976</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">3</p><p n="date">2005-10</p><p n="module title">Development</p><p n="module code">BS301</p><p n="genre family">Explanation</p><p n="discipline">Biological Sciences</p><p n="disciplinary group">LS</p><p n="grade">M</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">4310</p><p n="number of s-units">108</p><p n="number of p">31</p><p n="number of tables">0</p><p n="number of figures">3</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">0</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">0</p><p n="abstract present">abstract present</p><p n="average words per s-unit">39.9</p><p n="average s-units per p">3.5</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">f</p><p n="year of birth">1985</p><p n="first language">English</p><p n="education">UKA</p><p n="course">Biochemistry</p><p n="student ID">0097</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><titlePart><name type="student ID"/></titlePart><docTitle><titlePart rend="underlined bold">The role of maternal effect genes in the development of the nematode <hi rend="italic">Caenorhabditi</hi>s <hi rend="italic">elegans</hi></titlePart></docTitle></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="abstract"><head rend="underlined bold">Abstract</head><p n="p1.31"><s n="s1.6;p1.31">Maternal effect genes are genes expressed during oogenesis in order to produce mRNAs or proteins required for early development. </s><s n="s2.6;p1.31">These genes play a vital role in producing asymmetrical divisions, cell-cell interactions and determining cell fates in the early embryo. </s><s n="s3.6;p1.31">Such genes include the <hi rend="italic">par</hi> genes, which are required to produce an asymmetrical first cleavage, and to allow for asymmetrical distributions of cell fate determinants. </s><s n="s4.6;p1.31">Maternal effect genes are involved in the early specification of cell fates, for example <hi rend="italic">skn-1</hi> encodes a transcription factor to determine EMS cell fate, and <hi rend="italic">pie-1</hi> determines germline cell fate through transcriptional repression. </s><s n="s5.6;p1.31">Early cell-cell signalling requires the <hi rend="italic">glp-1</hi> and <hi rend="italic">apx-1</hi> genes to act as ligand and receptor, in order to specify conditional cell fates. </s><s n="s6.6;p1.31">The maternal effect genes encode a variety of different proteins which together initiate complex patterns of differentiation required for <hi rend="italic">C. elegans</hi> to develop into a complete organism. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">1. Introduction </head><p n="p2.31"><s n="s1.4;p2.31"><hi rend="italic">Caenorhabditis elegans</hi> is a small soil nematode, used as a model organism in the study of development for many reasons, but one clear advantage is its invariant lineage. </s><s n="s2.4;p2.31">Cell divisions occur at the same time, in the same place in each organism, so that each cell, at each stage of development will always assume the same fate. </s><s n="s3.4;p2.31">This allows the same patterns of development to be studied in numerous individuals. </s><s n="s4.4;p2.31">The early lineages that shall be discussed in this essay can be seen in figure 1. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0097a-fig.001"><head><hi rend="bold">Figure 1 - Early <hi rend="italic">C.</hi> <hi rend="italic">elegans</hi> lineages</hi> The fertilised oocyte is termed P <hi rend="sub">0</hi> , and divides asymmetrically to produce a larger anterior AB blastomere, and a smaller posterior P <hi rend="sub">1</hi> blastomere. AB divides into ABa, which produces the anterior pharynx, hypodermis and neurons, and ABp, which produces hypodermis and neurons. P <hi rend="sub">1</hi> is a stem cell, and undergoes three more asymmetrical divisions to produce EMS, C and D lineages. EMS divides to produce E with intestinal cell fate, and MS with muscle, posterior pharynx and gonad cell fate. C produces muscle, hypodermis and neurons, and D produces muscle. The P <hi rend="sub">4</hi> stem cell divides into Z2 and Z3, which form the germ line. </head></figure><p n="p3.31"><s n="s1.5;p3.31"><hi rend="italic">C. elegans</hi> is hermaphrodite, and fertilisation occurs in a sperm storage organ. </s><s n="s2.5;p3.31">Fertilization triggers several important events, including the completion of meiosis in the oocyte arrested in prophase of meiosis I, and the production of a protective chitin eggshell, which gives the embryo an oval shape.<ref target="BAWE_0097a-endnote.001"/> The two pronuclei then fuse, and the mitotic apparatus for the first division develops along the long axis of the egg, which becomes the anterior-posterior (A-P) axis. </s><s n="s3.5;p3.31">However, the spindle becomes displaced towards the posterior pole resulting in an asymmetrical division, that gives rise to the larger anterior AB blastomere, and smaller P <hi rend="sub">1</hi> blastomere. </s><s n="s4.5;p3.31">This asymmetric division is vital in the development of the <hi rend="italic">C. elegans</hi> embryo as it means that the daughter cells will contain differing amounts of cell fate determinants. </s><s n="s5.5;p3.31">Early developmental patterning involves both asymmetric divisions and cell-cell interactions in order to correctly determine cell fates, and this not only occurs in <hi rend="italic">C. elegans</hi> development, but in the development of most organisms.<ref target="BAWE_0097a-endnote.002"/>&amp; <ref target="BAWE_0097a-endnote.003"/> </s></p><note place="end" id="BAWE_0097a-endnote.001"><p n="pn1.1"><s rend="bold" n="s1.6;pn1.1">Gotta, M. and Ahnringer, J. </s><s n="s2.6;pn1.1">Axis determination in <hi rend="italic"> C. elegans</hi>: initiating and transducing polarity <hi rend="bold">2001</hi> J. Curr. </s><s n="s3.6;pn1.1">Op. </s><s n="s4.6;pn1.1">Gen. </s><s n="s5.6;pn1.1">Devel. </s><s n="s6.6;pn1.1">11:367-373 </s></p></note><note place="end" id="BAWE_0097a-endnote.002"><p n="pn1.1"><s rend="bold" n="s1.2;pn1.1">Lyczak, R., Gomes, L. E. and Bowerman, B. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">Heads or tails: Cell polarity and axis formation in the early <hi rend="italic"> Caenorhabditis elegans</hi> embryo <hi rend="bold">2002</hi> Developmental Cell 3:157-166 </s></p></note><note place="end" id="BAWE_0097a-endnote.003"><p n="pn1.1"><s rend="bold" n="s1.5;pn1.1">Rose, L. S. and Kemphues, K. J. </s><s n="s2.5;pn1.1">Early patterning of the <hi rend="italic"> C. elegans</hi> embryo <hi rend="bold">1998</hi> Annu. </s><s n="s3.5;pn1.1">Rev. </s><s n="s4.5;pn1.1">Genet. </s><s n="s5.5;pn1.1">32:521-545 </s></p></note><p n="p4.31"><s n="s1.4;p4.31">This essay shall consider maternal effect genes, which are those genes expressed during oogenesis in order to produce mRNAs or proteins required for early development. </s><s n="s2.4;p4.31">These genes play a vital role in producing asymmetrical divisions, cell-cell interactions and determining cell fates in the early embryo. </s><s n="s3.4;p4.31">Maternal effect genes are commonly studied by looking at the development of an embryo from a mother carrying a mutation in one such gene. </s><s n="s4.4;p4.31">These mutations are known as 'maternal effect mutations,' and in this essay these embryos shall be termed 'mutant embryos,' although it is the mother who actually carries the mutation. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">2. The <hi rend="italic">par</hi> genes and setting up the initial asymmetries in the embryo</head><p n="p5.31"><s n="s1.2;p5.31">The <hi rend="italic">par</hi> genes, named for <hi rend="underlined italic">partitioning defective</hi>, are important in setting up the initial asymmetries in the embryo, leading to the asymmetrical first division. </s><s n="s2.2;p5.31">They are maternal effect genes, whose role is to provide polarity information during the first cell cycle in order for the correct asymmetrical localisation of cell fate determinants.<hi rend="sup">3</hi> </s></p><p n="p6.31"><s n="s1.2;p6.31">As the oocyte enters the spermathecum, the sperm storage organ, the pronucleus moves away from the pole of entry, and the sperm fertilises the egg at the opposite pole. </s><s n="s2.2;p6.31">As well as triggering completion of meiosis and eggshell production, sperm entry specifies the A-P axis. </s></p><p n="p7.31"><s n="s1.3;p7.31">The entry point of the sperm and the associated centrosome it brings to the oocyte, determines the posterior pole.<hi rend="sup">2</hi> The sperm pronucleus directs cytoplasmic streaming, with internal cytoplasm directed towards the posterior and cortical cytoplasm directed away to the anterior. </s><s n="s2.3;p7.31">This causes a deep invagination of the membrane, called a pseudocleavage furrow.<ref target="BAWE_0097a-endnote.004"/> The maternal pronucleus migrates towards the paternal pronucleus, and then together they migrate towards the centre, so that the first mitotic spindle forms along the A-P axis. </s><s n="s3.3;p7.31">However, the spindle becomes displaced towards the posterior pole, and this requires the PAR proteins. </s></p><note place="end" id="BAWE_0097a-endnote.004"><p n="pn1.1"><s rend="bold" n="s1.2;pn1.1">Cuenca, A. A., Schetter, A., Aceto, D., Kemphues, K. and Seydoux G. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">Polarization of the <hi rend="italic"> C. elegans</hi> zygote preceeds via distinct establishment and maintenance phases <hi rend="bold">2003</hi> Development 130:1255-1265 </s></p></note><p n="p8.31"><s n="s1.1;p8.31">Following sperm entry, PAR-1 and PAR-2 localise to the posterior cortex, and </s></p><p n="p9.31"><s n="s1.7;p9.31">PAR-3 and PAR-6 localise to the anterior cortex. </s><s n="s2.7;p9.31">PAR-4 and PAR-5 are enriched in the cortex, but are not polarised. </s><s n="s3.7;p9.31">The sperm's ability to affect PAR distribution has been found to be dependant upon an intact actin cytoskeleton, as when this is disrupted with cytochalasin D, the first division is no longer asymmetric.<hi rend="sup">2&amp;4</hi> The anterior PAR-3 and PAR-6 forms a complex with a protein kinase C, PKC-3, which in <hi rend="italic">par-2</hi> mutants becomes delocalised and found throughout the cortex. </s><s n="s4.7;p9.31">Oppositely PAR-2 is no longer restricted to the posterior in <hi rend="italic">par-3, par-6</hi> and <hi rend="italic">pkc-3</hi> mutants. </s><s n="s5.7;p9.31">Cuenca <hi rend="italic">et al</hi><hi rend="sup"> 5</hi> used GFP fusions to study the localisation patterns of the PAR proteins and proposed a model based upon two distinct phases, establishment and maintenance, involved in polarising the cortex. </s><s n="s6.7;p9.31">During establishment it is proposed that signalling events occur between the sperm asters and the actin cytoskeleton to displace the PAR-3/PAR-6/PKC-3 complex to the anterior cortex, which allows PAR-2 to accumulate in the posterior cortex. </s><s n="s7.7;p9.31">The maintenance phase then involves PAR-2 preventing the PAR-3/PAR-6/PKC-3 complex returning to the posterior domain. </s></p><p n="p10.31"><s n="s1.7;p10.31">The displacement of the first mitotic spindle requires a greater pulling force at the posterior aster than the anterior. </s><s n="s2.7;p10.31">It has been found that in <hi rend="italic">par-2</hi> mutant embryos, PAR-3 expands to the posterior and exerts a low force. </s><s n="s3.7;p10.31">In <hi rend="italic">par-3</hi> mutants, PAR-2 expands to the posterior and exerts a low force. </s><s n="s4.7;p10.31">In each case, the result is that the spindle remains central.<hi rend="sup">1&amp;2</hi> This implicates the <hi rend="italic">par-2</hi> and <hi rend="italic">par-3</hi> genes, and the correct localisation of their gene products, in having direct effect on spindle displacement. </s><s n="s5.7;p10.31">LET-99 is a protein that requires the <hi rend="italic">par</hi> genes for its correct localisation at the cortex, within a band positioned slightly posteriorly, as seen in figure 2. </s><s n="s6.7;p10.31">In <hi rend="italic">let-99</hi> mutant embryos, the displacement of the spindle is defective. </s><s n="s7.7;p10.31">It has therefore been suggested that cortical forces on microtubules are lowest where LET-99 is highest, allowing the stronger posterior forces to displace the spindle.<hi rend="sup">2</hi> This process can be seen in figure 2. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0097a-fig.002"><head><hi rend="bold">Figure 2 - Localisation of PAR-2, PAR-3 and LET-99, and the displacement of the first mitotic division spindle</hi> PAR-3 (represented in red) and the associated PAR-6 and PKC-3 localise to the posterior cortex, while PAR-2 (represented in blue) and PAR-1 localise to the anterior cortex. LET-99 (represented in orange) localises within a band located slightly towards the posterior. The cortical forces on microtubules (represented in green) that contact the cortex where LET-99 is localised are proposed to be weaker, allowing the stronger forces exerted by the posterior aster to pull the spindle towards the posterior, resulting in an asymmetrical division. Figure adapted from Lyczak <hi rend="italic">et al</hi> 2002 <hi rend="italic"> Developmental Cell</hi> 3:157-166</head></figure><p n="p11.31"><s n="s1.1;p11.31">The PAR proteins are vital in displacement of the first mitotic division spindle, and are also required for the asymmetrical localisation of cell fate determinants into P <hi rend="sub">1</hi> and AB. PAR-1 for example, restricts MEX-5 and MEX-6 to the anterior somatic blastomeres, which in turn helps to restrict PIE-1, MEX-1 and POS-1 to the posterior germ line blastomeres.<hi rend="sup">4&amp;</hi><ref target="BAWE_0097a-endnote.005"/> Overall, sperm entry causes polarisation of the PAR proteins in the cortex, and this in then converted into cytoplasmic polarity.<hi rend="sup">2</hi> </s></p><note place="end" id="BAWE_0097a-endnote.005"><p n="pn1.1"><s rend="bold" n="s1.2;pn1.1">Spike, C.A. and Strome, S. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">Germ plasm: protein degradation in the soma <hi rend="bold">2003</hi> Current Biology 13:R837-R839 </s></p></note></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">3. <hi rend="italic">skn-1</hi> and EMS development</head><p n="p12.31"><s n="s1.4;p12.31">The EMS blastomere at the four-cell stage of development, as seen in figure 3, produces pharyngeal and intestinal cells in the wild-type embryo. </s><s n="s2.4;p12.31">Bowerman <hi rend="italic">et al</hi> <ref target="BAWE_0097a-endnote.006"/> screened for mutants lacking pharyngeal cells, and found such mutants were defective in a gene called <hi rend="italic">skn-1</hi>. </s><s n="s3.4;p12.31">Normal sperm could not rescue embryos whose mothers were homozygous mutants, therefore it is the maternal expression of the gene that is required, so <hi rend="italic">skn-1</hi> is a maternal effect gene. </s><s n="s4.4;p12.31">The role of the <hi rend="italic">skn-1</hi> gene is to determine EMS cell fate. </s></p><note place="end" id="BAWE_0097a-endnote.006"><p n="pn1.1"><s rend="bold" n="s1.2;pn1.1">Bowerman, B., Eaton, B. A. and Priess, J. R. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1"><hi rend="italic">skn-1</hi>, a maternally expressed gene required to specify the fate of ventral blastomeres in the early <hi rend="italic">C. elegans</hi> embryo <hi rend="bold">1992</hi> Cell 68:1061-1075 </s></p></note><figure id="BAWE_0097a-fig.003"><head><hi rend="bold">Figure 3 - The generalised cell fates of a 4-cell stage embryo</hi> EMS divides into E, which produces intestinal cells, and MS, which produces pharyngeal and body wall muscle cells required for locomotion. The pharynx is a muscular organ used for feeding, with its anterior cells descending from ABa and those posterior from EMS. All but the EMS blastomere produce hypodermal cells, which are epithelial cells that cover the surface of the embryo. Figure adapted from Bowerman <hi rend="italic">et al.</hi> 1992 <hi rend="italic"> Cell</hi> 68:1061-1075</head></figure><p n="p13.31"><s n="s1.3;p13.31">Immunofluorescence spectroscopy shows that <hi rend="italic">skn-1</hi> mutants have less intestinal tissue when compared to the wild-type, as well as lacking both EMS and ABa derived pharyngeal cell types.<hi rend="sup">6</hi> It was also found that <hi rend="italic">skn-1</hi> mutants had extra hypodermal cells where the pharynx and intestine would be. </s><s n="s2.3;p13.31">Through laser ablation, where a laser microbeam was used to destroy all but the EMS blastomere, it was determined that the EMS blastomere produced hypodermal and body wall muscle cells in <hi rend="italic">skn-1</hi> mutants. </s><s n="s3.3;p13.31">This therefore shows that <hi rend="italic">skn-1</hi> is required to specify EMS to produce both pharyngeal and intestinal cell fates. </s></p><p n="p14.31"><s n="s1.4;p14.31">The <hi rend="italic">skn-1</hi> gene was isolated and cloned by Bowerman <hi rend="italic">et al.</hi> </s><s n="s2.4;p14.31"><hi rend="sup">6</hi> The gene was found to encode a protein with a twenty-five amino acid region with similarity to the DNA binding domain of the 'bZIP' family of transcription factors. </s><s n="s3.4;p14.31">SKN-1 however lacks a leucine zipper required for the dimerisation which permits DNA binding in bZIP transcription factors. </s><s n="s4.4;p14.31">Evidence suggests that </s></p><p n="p15.31"><s n="s1.3;p15.31">SKN-1 has an alternative DNA binding domain termed the 'SKN domain,' and that it binds to DNA as a monomer.<ref target="BAWE_0097a-endnote.007"/> This indicates that <hi rend="italic">skn-1</hi> may direct the fate of EMS through activating embryonic transcription of genes required for pharyngeal and intestinal fate. </s><s n="s2.3;p15.31">Figure 4, shows that SKN-1 localises to the nucleus, further supporting the idea of SKN-1 being involved in the regulation of embryonic transcription. </s><s n="s3.3;p15.31">Since EMS cell fates appear to be specified autonomously,<hi rend="sup">6</hi> the localisation of a transcription factor could explain this. </s></p><note place="end" id="BAWE_0097a-endnote.007"><p n="pn1.1"><s rend="bold" n="s1.2;pn1.1">Blackwell, K. T., Bowerman, B., Priess, J. R., Weintraub, H. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">Formation of a monomeric DNA binding domain by SKN-1 bZIP and homeodomain elements <hi rend="bold">1994</hi> <hi rend="italic">Science</hi> 266:621-628 </s></p></note><p n="p16.31"><s n="s1.4;p16.31">Staining for the SKN-1 protein shows there is an unequal distribution of SKN-1 from the 2-cell stage, as seen in figure 4. </s><s n="s2.4;p16.31">P <hi rend="sub">1</hi> contains much higher levels of the SKN-1 protein than AB in the wild-type embryo. </s><s n="s3.4;p16.31">The levels in AB could be assumed to be too low to induce pharyngeal cell fates. </s><s n="s4.4;p16.31">When P <hi rend="sub">1</hi> divides however, it is found that SKN-1 is equally distributed in P <hi rend="sub">2</hi> and EMS. This would suggest that other factors prevent P <hi rend="sub">2</hi> from responding to SKN-1, as P <hi rend="sub">2</hi> does not produce pharyngeal cells in the wild-type embryo. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0097a-pic.001"><head><hi rend="bold">Figure 4 - Distribution of SKN-1</hi> These fluorescence micrographs are of wild-type embryos stained for SKN-1. In A) the adult gonad containing the maturing oocyte nuclei shows no SKN-1 staining. B) shows the fertilised egg with SKN-1 staining in the male (left arrow) and female (right arrow) pronuclei. In C) the early 2-cell stage shows staining in both nuclei. D) shows an increase in the level of SKN-1 in the P <hi rend="sub">1</hi> nucleus, and when P <hi rend="sub">1</hi> and AB are dividing in E) SKN-1 appears to be distributed throughout the cytoplasm, and is not localised to the nucleus. In the early 4-cell stage embryo F) there is an equal distribution of SKN-1 in ABa and ABp at low levels, and an equal distribution in EMS and P <hi rend="sub">2</hi> , but at higher levels. In the late 4-cell stage embryo G) SKN-1 is barely detectable in ABa and ABb. SKN-1 is detectable in all P <hi rend="sub">1</hi> descendants (arrow to P <hi rend="sub">3</hi> on right) in the 8-cell stage embryo H) and in none of the AB descendants (arrow to AB descendant on left). Figure adapted from Bowerman <hi rend="italic">et al.</hi> 1993 <hi rend="italic"> Cell</hi> 74:443-452</head></figure><p n="p17.31"><s n="s1.7;p17.31">It has been found that mutations in the maternal effect gene <hi rend="italic">mex-1</hi> cause both AB and P <hi rend="sub">1</hi> to produce MS-like descendants, which have the intrinsic ability to produce pharyngeal cells,<ref target="BAWE_0097a-endnote.008"/> as discussed above. </s><s n="s2.7;p17.31">It therefore appears that MEX-1 activity is required for the restriction of SKN-1 activity to P <hi rend="sub">1</hi> at the first division. </s><s n="s3.7;p17.31">In <hi rend="italic">par-1</hi> mutants, where there is a deficiency in A-P axis establishment, AB descendants also acquire a SKN-1 dependant ability to produce pharyngeal cells, however in this case all 4 blastomeres at the 4-cell stage may produce pharyngeal cells. </s><s n="s4.7;p17.31">This indicates PAR-1's more general role in the distribution of cell fate determinants. </s><s n="s5.7;p17.31">However in both <hi rend="italic">par-1</hi> and <hi rend="italic">mex-1</hi> mutants intestinal cells are not produced.<hi rend="sup">8</hi> This indicates that another factor may interact with SKN-1 to produce intestinal cells from E. When the maternal effect gene <hi rend="italic">pie-1</hi> is mutant, P <hi rend="sub">2</hi> acquires the ability to produce pharyngeal cells. </s><s n="s6.7;p17.31">This suggests that PIE-1 is required to restrict <hi rend="italic">skn-1</hi> activity to EMS at the second cleavage. </s><s n="s7.7;p17.31">A simple diagram demonstrating these conclusions is represented in figure 5. </s></p><note place="end" id="BAWE_0097a-endnote.008"><p n="pn1.1"><s rend="bold" n="s1.2;pn1.1">Bowerman, B., Draper, B. W., Mello, C. C. and Priess, J. R. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">The maternal gene <hi rend="italic">skn-1</hi> encodes a protein that is distributed unequally in early <hi rend="italic">C. elegans</hi> embryos <hi rend="bold">1993</hi><hi rend="italic"> Cell</hi> 74:443-452 </s></p></note><figure id="BAWE_0097a-fig.004"><head><hi rend="bold">Figure 5 - A simple model SKN-1 activity restriction to EMS</hi> The arrows represent the occurrence of division, and the red circle indicates the ability of a blastomere to produce pharyngeal descendants. In <hi rend="italic">mex-1</hi> mutants, both AB and P <hi rend="sub">1</hi> descendants produce pharyngeal cells, indicating that MEX-1 plays a role in restricting the ability of SKN-1 to induce pharyngeal cell fate to P <hi rend="sub">1</hi> . In <hi rend="italic">pie-1</hi> mutants, P <hi rend="sub">2</hi> acquires the ability to produce pharyngeal descendants, indicating PIE-1 plays a role in restricting the ability of SKN-1 to induce pharyngeal cell fate to EMS. We have seen that SKN-1 is at higher levels in P <hi rend="sub">1</hi> than AB, so MEX-1 may be involved in physically segregating <hi rend="italic">skn-</hi> 1 mRNA or SKN-1 protein into P <hi rend="sub">1</hi> . However, the protein is equally distributed in EMS and P <hi rend="sub">2</hi> , so PIE-1 may somehow function to repress the action of SKN-1.</head></figure></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">4. <hi rend="italic">pie-1</hi> and <hi rend="italic">mex-1</hi> genes in germline development and transcriptional silencing</head><p n="p18.31"><s n="s1.4;p18.31">We have seen that P <hi rend="sub">2</hi>, a germline blastomere, contains the somatic differentiation factor SKN-1. </s><s n="s2.4;p18.31"><hi rend="italic">pie-1</hi> is a maternal effect gene, and its role appears to be directing differences between EMS and P <hi rend="sub">2</hi> as seen in figure 5, and it perhaps does so through preventing a germline response to SKN-1.<hi rend="sup">8&amp;</hi><ref target="BAWE_0097a-endnote.009"/> The <hi rend="italic">pie-1</hi> mRNA appears to be found in all blastomeres until the 4-cell stage, where it is degraded in somatic blastomeres, whilst being maintained in the germline blastomeres. </s><s n="s3.4;p18.31">The PIE-1 protein is first detectable at low levels in the posterior cytoplasm of P <hi rend="sub">0</hi>, and following division it is then present in both the nucleus and cytoplasm of P <hi rend="sub">1</hi>, but at low or undetectable levels in AB.<hi rend="sup">9</hi> PIE-1 is then localised to the germline blastomere in each of the cleavages that follow, and is detected in the nuclei of Z2 and Z3. </s><s n="s4.4;p18.31">The asymmetrical distribution is achieved by PIE-1 accumulating equally at each centrosome of a dividing germline blastomere, but following rotation of the mitotic spindle levels decrease rapidly at one of the centrosomes, so that only the germline daughter cell contains PIE-1 at its centrosome.<hi rend="sup">8</hi> The asymmetrical distribution of PIE-1 explains how it can prevent SKN-1 activity in P <hi rend="sub">2</hi> and not EMS. </s></p><note place="end" id="BAWE_0097a-endnote.009"><p n="pn1.1"><s rend="bold" n="s1.3;pn1.1">Mello, C. </s><s rend="bold italic" n="s2.3;pn1.1">et al. </s><s n="s3.3;pn1.1">The PIE-1 protein and germline specification in <hi rend="italic"> C. elegans</hi> embryos <hi rend="bold">1996</hi> <hi rend="italic">Nature</hi> 382:710-712 </s></p></note><p n="p19.31"><s n="s1.1;p19.31">The <hi rend="italic">pie-1</hi> gene has been cloned, and found to encode a novel nuclear protein, </s></p><p n="p20.31"><s n="s1.2;p20.31">PIE-1, which contains two zinc-finger motifs.<hi rend="sup">9</hi> PIE-1 in the cytoplasm is associated via its second zinc finger to P granules,<hi rend="sup">5</hi> germline associated particles found only in germline blastomeres.<hi rend="sup">9</hi> The first zinc finger has been proposed to function in meditating PIE-1's own degradation in somatic blastomeres. </s><s n="s2.2;p20.31">ZF1 of PIE-1 (as well as MEX-1, POS-1 and MEX-5) interacts with a protein that forms part of a ubiquitin ligase, which targets proteins for degradation in a proteasome.<hi rend="sup">5</hi> This is thought to be a mechanism of preventing the accumulation of germ plasm components in somatic blastomeres. </s></p><p n="p21.31"><s n="s1.1;p21.31">Through monitoring the transcription of a chromosomally integrated transgene it has been found that embryonically transcribed RNAs can be detected in somatic blastomeres from the 3-cell stage, but are not detected in the germline blastomeres.<ref target="BAWE_0097a-endnote.010"/> This is depedant on PIE-1, indicating it acts as a repressor of differentiated cell fates in the germline blastomeres, through general repression of transcription.<hi rend="sup">9-</hi><ref target="BAWE_0097a-endnote.011"/> Staining for an epitope of RNA polymerase II characteristic only when it is active, is not found in germline blastomeres, suggesting the mechanism of transcriptional repression by PIE-1 is to inhibit transcription directly.<hi rend="sup">11</hi> However, since PIE-1 is also found in the cytoplasm, it may play other roles. </s></p><note place="end" id="BAWE_0097a-endnote.010"><p n="pn1.1"><s rend="bold" n="s1.3;pn1.1">Seydoux, G. </s><s rend="bold" n="s2.3;pn1.1"><hi rend="italic">et al</hi>. </s><s n="s3.3;pn1.1">Repression of gene expression in the embryonic germ lineage of <hi rend="italic"> C. elegans</hi> <hi rend="bold">1996</hi><hi rend="italic"> Nature</hi> 382:713-716 </s></p></note><note place="end" id="BAWE_0097a-endnote.011"><p n="pn1.1"><s rend="bold" n="s1.2;pn1.1">Seydoux, G. and Strome, S. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">Launching the germline in <hi rend="italic"> Caenorhabditis elegans</hi>: regulation of gene expression in early germ cells <hi rend="bold">1999</hi> <hi rend="italic">Development</hi> 126:3275-3283 </s></p></note><p n="p22.31"><s n="s1.4;p22.31">The role of PIE-1 in the cytoplasm has been suggested as ensuring efficient expression of NOS-2. </s><s n="s2.4;p22.31"><hi rend="italic">nos-2</hi> is also a maternal effect gene. </s><s n="s3.4;p22.31">Its mRNA is degraded in somatic blastomeres, while being maintained in germline blastomeres, and it is involved in ensuring the primordial germ cells associate with the somatic gonad.<ref target="BAWE_0097a-endnote.012"/> PIE-1 is required to maintain <hi rend="italic">nos-2,</hi> and several other maternal mRNAs in the germline. </s><s n="s4.4;p22.31">PIE-1 is also implicated in functioning to promote NOS-2 protein expression.<hi rend="sup">12</hi> The dual functioning of PIE-1 can be seen in figure 6. </s></p><note place="end" id="BAWE_0097a-endnote.012"><p n="pn1.1"><s rend="bold" n="s1.2;pn1.1">Tenenhaus, C., Subramaniam, K., Dunn, M. A. and Seydoux, G. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">PIE-1 is a bifunction protein that regulates maternal and zygotic gene expression in the embryonic germ line of <hi rend="italic"> Caenorhabditic elegans</hi> <hi rend="bold">2003 <hi rend="italic"> Genes and Development </hi></hi>15:1031-1040 </s></p></note><figure id="BAWE_0097a-fig.005"><head><hi rend="bold">Figure 6 - The nuclear and cytoplasmic functions of PIE-1</hi> In a germline blastomere PIE-1 in the nucleus inhibits embryonic transcription. This prevents the germline from responding to somatic differentiation factors such as the transcription factor SKN-1. This explains why only EMS responds to SKN-1 to form pharyngeal descendants. Indirectly through the inhibition of transcription PIE-1 also prevents the degradation of maternal mRNAs. PIE-1 in the cytoplasm, promotes expression of maternal genes such as NOS-2, required for the localisation of primordial germ cells to the gonad. Figure adapted from Tenenhaus <hi rend="italic">et al</hi> 2003 <hi rend="italic"> Genes and Development</hi> 15:1031-1040</head></figure><p n="p23.31"><s n="s1.3;p23.31">As discussed in section 3, <hi rend="italic">mex-1</hi> mutants produce excess pharyngeal cells, in a SKN-1 dependant manner. </s><s n="s2.3;p23.31">In these mutants, all the anterior blastomeres adopt an altered cell fate, and the only change to the posterior blastomeres is failure to produce germ cells, as P blastomeres differentiate into muscle cells.<ref target="BAWE_0097a-endnote.013"/> P granules are also gradually lost from the germline, indicating MEX-1 is critical for their correct segregation. </s><s n="s3.3;p23.31">Cloning of the <hi rend="italic">mex-1</hi> gene revealed that the structure of MEX-1 is similar to that of PIE-1, in that it contains two zinc finger domains.<hi rend="sup">14</hi> Like PIE-1 it was also found to associate to P granules, however it is a cytoplasmic protein, and does not have a nuclear localisation sequence.<hi rend="sup">14</hi> It appears that MEX-1 is required to restrict PIE-1 activity to the germline, and functions in both somatic and germline differentation.<hi rend="sup">13&amp;</hi> <ref target="BAWE_0097a-endnote.014"/> </s></p><note place="end" id="BAWE_0097a-endnote.013"><p n="pn1.1"><s rend="bold" n="s1.3;pn1.1">Mello, C. </s><s rend="bold" n="s2.3;pn1.1"><hi rend="italic">et al</hi>. </s><s n="s3.3;pn1.1"><hi rend="italic">The pie-1 and mex-1 genes and maternal control of blastomere identity in Early C. elegans embryos</hi> 1992 <hi rend="italic"> Cell</hi> 70:163-176 </s></p></note><note place="end" id="BAWE_0097a-endnote.014"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1"><hi rend="bold">Guedes, S. and Priess, J. R</hi>. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">The <hi rend="italic"> C. elegans</hi> MEX-1 protein is present in germline blastomeres and is a P granule component <hi rend="bold">1997</hi> <hi rend="italic">Development</hi> 124:731-739 </s></p></note></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">5. The <hi rend="italic">glp-</hi>1 and <hi rend="italic">apx-1</hi> genes in cell-cell interactions </head><p n="p24.31"><s n="s1.2;p24.31">The maternal effect gene <hi rend="italic">glp-1</hi> encodes a Notch homologue, GLP-1, which has been identified as vital for two cell-cell interactions that help specify cell fates in early development.<ref target="BAWE_0097a-endnote.015"/> Temperature shift experiments show that <hi rend="italic">glp-1</hi> activity is required between the 4- and 12-cell stages, in order for ABp to adopt different fates from ABa. </s><s n="s2.2;p24.31">Figure 7 shows the localisation of both <hi rend="italic">glp-1</hi> mRNA and the GLP-1 protein in the early embryo. </s></p><note place="end" id="BAWE_0097a-endnote.015"><p n="pn1.1"><s rend="bold" n="s1.2;pn1.1">Evans, T.C., Crittenden, S. L., Kodotanni, V., Kimble, J. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">Translational control of maternal <hi rend="italic"> glp-1</hi> mRNA establishes asymmetry in the <hi rend="italic">C.elegans</hi> embryo <hi rend="bold">1994</hi><hi rend="italic"> Cell</hi> 77:183-194 </s></p></note><figure id="BAWE_0097a-pic.002"><head><hi rend="bold">Figure 7 - The localisation of <hi rend="italic">glp-1</hi> mRNA and GLP-1 protein</hi> A and B show <hi rend="italic">in situ</hi> hybrididation with <hi rend="italic">glp-1</hi> mRNA, in the 8- and 28-cell stages of development respectively. From the 1- to 8-cell stages, the embryos are uniformly stained. Levels decline by the 16-cell stage, and there is very little staining by the 28-cell stage. It appears that the mRNA persists longer in the posterior as seen in B. The GLP-1 protein is not present until the 4-cell stage, which is shown in C. Here it is present at the membrane borders of ABa:ABp, ABa:EMS and ABp:P <hi rend="sub">2</hi> , but not P <hi rend="sub">2</hi> to EMS. It can also be seen in the cytoplasm of the AB cells. This indicates restriction to ABa and ABp. Figure adapted from Evans <hi rend="italic">et al.</hi> 1994 <hi rend="italic"> Cell</hi> 77:183-194 and Ogura <hi rend="italic">et al.</hi> 2003 <hi rend="italic"> Development</hi> 130:2495-2503</head></figure><p n="p25.31"><s n="s1.5;p25.31">The expression of the <hi rend="italic">glp-1</hi> mRNA appears to be spatially regulated, as there is asymmetrical localisation of the GLP-1 protein, but not the mRNA in the early stages as seen in figure 7. </s><s n="s2.5;p25.31">Indeed it has been found that the 3' UTR of the <hi rend="italic">glp-1</hi> mRNA is required for translational repression, in order to restrict translation to the anterior descendants of the 2- to 28-cell stage embryo.<hi rend="sup">15</hi> Using reporter RNA experiments Evans <hi rend="italic">et al.</hi> </s><s n="s3.5;p25.31">found that the 3' UTR contained a 125 nucleotide region required to repress translation from the 2- to 4-cell stage, and a 61 nucleotide region required for repression of translation in the P <hi rend="sub">2</hi> dedendants.<hi rend="sup">15</hi> This combination of temporal and spatial control is required for the correct pattern of GLP-1 expression. </s><s n="s4.5;p25.31">The spatial control of GLP-1 expression has been shown to be dependant upon two other maternal effect genes, <hi rend="italic">pos-1</hi> and <hi rend="italic">spn-4</hi>. </s><ref target="BAWE_0097a-endnote.016"/><s n="s5.5;p25.31">A model for this mechanism of control can be seen in figure 8. </s></p><note place="end" id="BAWE_0097a-endnote.016"><p n="pn1.1"><s rend="bold" n="s1.2;pn1.1">Ogura, K., Kishimoto, N., Mitani, S., Gengyo-Ando, K. and Kohara, Y. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">Translational control of maternal <hi rend="italic"> glp-1</hi> mRNA by POS-1 and its interacting protein SPN-4 in <hi rend="italic">Caenorhabditis elegans</hi> <hi rend="bold">2003</hi><hi rend="italic"> Development</hi> 130:2495-2503 </s></p></note><figure id="BAWE_0097a-fig.006"><head><hi rend="bold">Figure 8 - A model for SPN-4 and POS-1 control of <hi rend="italic">glp-1</hi> mRNA translation</hi> POS-1 interacts specifically with the 3' UTR to repress translation by binding to the spatial control region. SPN-4, has an RNA-type RNA binding domain that binds to a sub-region of the temporal control region, and is required for translation in anterior blastomeres. POS-1 is abundant in the posterior, and here it binds to a specific region within the spatial control region, and causes repression of mRNA translation. However in the anterior, there is no POS-1 present. SPN-4 is present in the anterior and binds to cause activation of translation of the <hi rend="italic">glp-1</hi> mRNA. It may also have an inhibitory effect on the binding of POS-1. Figure adapted from Ogura <hi rend="italic">et al.</hi> 2003 <hi rend="italic">Development</hi> 130:2495-2503</head></figure><p n="p26.31"><s n="s1.3;p26.31">At the beginning of the 4-cell stage, ABa and ABp are equipotent, demonstrated by the fact that the blastomeres can be swapped in position to assume the opposite cell fates.<hi rend="sup">16</hi> However, by the end of this stage they have been committed to separate fates.<ref target="BAWE_0097a-endnote.017"/> When EMS or P2 is removed by a laser microbeam, the AB blastomeres do not develop normally, suggesting a role for these cells in specifying the AB fates.<hi rend="sup">17</hi> In a wild-type 4-cell stage embryo both ABa and ABp contact EMS, however only ABp contacts P <hi rend="sub">2</hi>. </s><s n="s2.3;p26.31">It has been shown that P <hi rend="sub">2</hi> is required to contact ABp in order for it to adopt a different cell fate to ABa.<hi rend="sup">17</hi> This indicates a signalling occurs between ABp and P <hi rend="sub">2</hi>. </s><s n="s3.3;p26.31">This signalling is dependant upon <hi rend="italic">glp-1</hi> and <hi rend="italic">apx-1</hi>,<ref target="BAWE_0097a-endnote.018"/> in a <hi rend="italic">C. elegans</hi> equivalent of the Drosophila Notch system. </s></p><note place="end" id="BAWE_0097a-endnote.017"><p n="pn1.1"><s rend="bold" n="s1.2;pn1.1">Mello, C. C., Draper, B. W. and Priess, J. R. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">The maternal genes <hi rend="italic"> apx-1</hi> and <hi rend="italic"> glp-1</hi> and establishment of dorsal-ventral polarity in the early <hi rend="italic">C. elegans</hi> embryo <hi rend="bold">1994</hi> <hi rend="italic">Cell</hi> 77:95-106 </s></p></note><note place="end" id="BAWE_0097a-endnote.018"><p n="pn1.2"><s rend="bold" n="s1.2;pn1.2">Mickey, K. M., Mello, C. C., Montgomery, M. K., Fire, A. and Priess, J. R. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.2">An inductive interaction in 4-cell stage embryos involves APX-1 expression in the signalling cell <hi rend="bold">1996 <hi rend="italic"> Development </hi></hi>122:1791-1798 </s></p><p n="pn2.2"><s n="s1.1;pn2.2">Word Count = 2976 </s></p></note><p n="p27.31"><s n="s1.1;p27.31">As we have seen GLP-1, the receptor, is localised at the membranes as in figure 7. </s></p><p n="p28.31"><s n="s1.4;p28.31">In a 4-cell stage embryo the mRNA of <hi rend="italic">apx-1</hi>, the ligand, is found in all four blastomeres, but the protein is only expressed in P <hi rend="sub">2</hi> as shown in figure 8. </s><s n="s2.4;p28.31">This confirms that P <hi rend="sub">2</hi> is the signalling cell. </s><s n="s3.4;p28.31">The asymmetric APX-1 distribution, despite equal mRNA distribution like GLP-1 implies regulation perhaps by translation control, or protein stability. </s><s n="s4.4;p28.31">POS-1 seems to be involved in its regulation of expression.<hi rend="sup">16</hi> The signalling of P <hi rend="sub">2</hi> to ABp, via APX-1 and GLP-1 means that ABp will adopt different cell fates to ABa. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0097a-pic.003"><head><hi rend="bold">Figure 8 - Localisation of APX-1 in a 4-cell stage embryo</hi> APX-1 staining occurs where P <hi rend="sub">2</hi> contacts the ABp membrane. APX-1 is not detected in ABa or ABp. At the 12-cell stage it os only found faintly in P <hi rend="sub">3</hi> , indicating APX-1 is not involved in the MS signalling event. Figure adapted from Mickey <hi rend="italic">et al.</hi> 1996 <hi rend="italic"> Development</hi> 122:1791-1798</head></figure><p n="p29.31"><s n="s1.6;p29.31">As previously discussed EMS contains determinants for autonomous development of pharyngeal and intestinal cell fates. </s><s n="s2.6;p29.31">Some ABa descendants also have a pharyngeal cell fate, however these fates do not develop autonomously, but require cell-cell signalling. </s><s n="s3.6;p29.31">It is found that pharyngeal induction does not occur if MS is destroyed, indicating that this is the signalling cell.<hi rend="sup">17</hi> This interaction is also dependant upon <hi rend="italic">glp-1,</hi> as in <hi rend="italic">glp-1</hi> mutants, no pharyngeal tissue is produced by ABa descendants. </s><s n="s4.6;p29.31">Two ABa descendants contact MS, and the signalling event occurs to induce pharyngeal cell fates in these descendants. </s><s n="s5.6;p29.31">As in the 4-cell interaction, GLP-1 is the receptor, however in this case APX-1 does not appear to be the ligand, as it is not found in the 12-cell stage signalling cell MS.<hi rend="sup">18</hi> However, the interaction has been reproduced <hi rend="italic">in vitro,</hi> and P <hi rend="sub">2</hi> has been shown as capable of initiating the required response in the ABa descendants.<hi rend="sup"> 19</hi> This shows that the identity of the signalling cell or the ligand is not important. </s><s n="s6.6;p29.31">It is the stage of development that the ABa descendants are at, and the consequent factors present at this time, that produce the required outcome.<hi rend="sup">19</hi> The ligand involved in this signalling is proposed as embryonically transcribed, since it is dependant on the SKN-1 transcription factor.<hi rend="sup">17&amp;19</hi> </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">6. Conclusion</head><p n="p30.31"><s n="s1.5;p30.31">In conclusion, maternal effect genes play vital roles in determining the early development of the <hi rend="italic">C</hi>. </s><s n="s2.5;p30.31"><hi rend="italic">elegans</hi> embryo. </s><s n="s3.5;p30.31">This is evident from the detrimental effects in the development of an embryo whose mother if mutant in a maternal effect gene. </s><s n="s4.5;p30.31">Proteins and mRNAs from maternal effect genes, such as the <hi rend="italic">par</hi> genes are present in the early embryo, and cause an asymmetrical first division, and localisation of cell fate determinants. </s><s n="s5.5;p30.31">Localised determinants such as those from the <hi rend="italic">skn-1</hi>, <hi rend="italic">pie-1</hi> and <hi rend="italic">mex-1</hi> genes, as well as genes involved in early cell-cell signalling such as <hi rend="italic">glp-1</hi> and <hi rend="italic">apx-1</hi>, initiate the complex patterns of cell differentiation required to produce a correctly developed <hi rend="italic">C. elegans</hi> organism. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">7. References</head><p n="p31.31"/></div1></body><back/></text></TEI.2>
