<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_0097b" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>How is the vertebrate limb patterned?</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">deleted: footer: page numbers
deleted: Word Count = 2986</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">3</p><p n="date">2005-11</p><p n="module title">Development</p><p n="module code">BS301</p><p n="genre family">Explanation</p><p n="discipline">Biological Sciences</p><p n="disciplinary group">LS</p><p n="grade">D</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">4962</p><p n="number of s-units">79</p><p n="number of p">30</p><p n="number of tables">0</p><p n="number of figures">3</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">0</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">0</p><p n="abstract present">abstract present</p><p n="average words per s-unit">62.8</p><p n="average s-units per p">2.6</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf) </p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">f</p><p n="year of birth">1985</p><p n="first language">English</p><p n="education">UKA</p><p n="course">Biochemistry</p><p n="student ID">0097</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><titlePart><name type="student name"/><name type="student ID"/></titlePart><docTitle><titlePart rend="underlined bold">How is the vertebrate limb patterned? </titlePart></docTitle></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="abstract"><head rend="underlined bold">Abstract</head><p n="p1.30"><s n="s1.6;p1.30">Patterning of the vertebrate limb involves the formation of three axis, D-V, Pr-D and A-P to produce complete and correct morphology. </s><s n="s2.6;p1.30">Initially a limb bud is induced via Wnt and Fgf signalling, with fore- verses hindlimb identity proposed as specified by <hi rend="italic">Tbx5</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Tbx4</hi> respectively. </s><s n="s3.6;p1.30">The AER is positioned at the dorsoventral boundary as a consequence of <hi rend="italic">R-fng</hi> expression, and through expression of <hi rend="italic">Fgf4</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Fgf8</hi> gives rise to the Pr-D patterning and outgrowth of the limb. </s><s n="s4.6;p1.30">Signalling from dorsally expressed <hi rend="italic">Wnt7a</hi> and ventrally expressed <hi rend="italic">En-1</hi> in the ectoderm gives rise to D-V patterning of the limb. </s><s n="s5.6;p1.30">The ZPA appears to mediate A-P patterning of the digits via expression of <hi rend="italic">Shh</hi>, and interacts with the AER in reciprocal regulation and maintenance. </s><s n="s6.6;p1.30">Due to evolutionary conservation, the mouse and chick examples discussed here may be applied broadly to all vertebrates, with the possibility of homologous genes performing comparable functions. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">1. Introduction</head><p n="p2.30"><s n="s1.3;p2.30">Pattern formation is defined as the "set of processes by which embryonic cells form ordered spatial arrangements of differentiated tissues." </s><ref target="BAWE_0097b-endnote.001"/><s n="s2.3;p2.30">Patterning of the limb involves the formation of three axes, the proximal-distal axis (Pr-D) from close to far from the body, the anterior-posterior (A-P) axis from thumb to little finger, and the dorsal-ventral axis (D-V), from knuckle to palm. </s><s n="s3.3;p2.30">Correct patterning leads complete formation of the proximal stylopod, the intermediate zeugopod, and the distal autopod. </s></p><note place="end" id="BAWE_0097b-endnote.001"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1"><hi rend="bold">Scott F. Gilbert</hi> Developmental Biology <hi rend="bold">2003</hi> <hi rend="italic">Sinauer Associates Inc.</hi> </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">7th Edition </s></p></note><p n="p3.30"><s n="s1.2;p3.30">The vertebrate limb is not essential to embryonic survival, so grafting experiments can be performed to understand its patterning. </s><s n="s2.2;p3.30">Classical experiments have shown that the limb does not develop when certain cells are removed, and that a limb will form when groups of cells are transplanted to an alternative location.<hi rend="sup">1</hi> These observations can be explained in terms of the limb field, seen in figure 1. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0097b-pic.001"><head><hi rend="bold">Figure 1 - The limb field</hi> The limb field is a field of cells with their general fate determined as being formation of the limb, however, individual cells within the field are not commited.<hi rend="sup">1</hi> This diagram shows the forelimb field of the salamander <hi rend="italic">Ambystoma maculatum</hi> . The central purple section gives rise to the limb itself, while the surrounding pink and green sections give rise to the peribrachial flank tissue and the shoulder girdle respectively. The outer grey section represents cells that do not usually form limb, but will if the inner sections are removed. If the whole limb field is removed, no limb will form. If it is transplanted to a new location, a limb will form. Figure adapted from <hi rend="bold">Scott F. Gilbert,</hi> Developmental Biology, 7 <hi rend="sup">th</hi> Edition</head></figure><p n="p4.30"><s n="s1.5;p4.30">Classical experiments also identified several important signalling centres involved in the patterning of the vertebrate limb, seen in figure 2. </s><s n="s2.5;p4.30">If the AER is removed, distal limb development stops,<hi rend="sup">1,</hi><ref target="BAWE_0097b-endnote.002"/>,<ref target="BAWE_0097b-endnote.003"/> so it seems the AER is vital to limb outgrowth, and Pr-D patterning. </s><s n="s3.5;p4.30">Transplantation of the ZPA to the anterior of another limb bud causes mirror-image digit duplications,<hi rend="sup">1-3</hi> suggesting its involvement in A-P patterning. </s><s n="s4.5;p4.30">When the ectoderm of the limb bud is rotated 180 <hi rend="sup">o</hi> with respect to the mesenchyme, distal elements are reversed,<hi rend="sup">1</hi> demonstrating a role in D-V patterning. </s><s n="s5.5;p4.30">This essay shall consider the how these signalling centres set up their corresponding axes and interact with each other to bring about the patterning of the vertebrate limb. </s></p><note place="end" id="BAWE_0097b-endnote.002"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1"><hi rend="bold">Tickle</hi> The contribution of chicken embryology to the understanding of vertebrate limb development <hi rend="bold">2004</hi> <hi rend="italic">Mech Dev</hi> 121:1019-1029 </s></p></note><note place="end" id="BAWE_0097b-endnote.003"><p n="pn1.1"><s rend="bold" n="s1.2;pn1.1">Niswander, L. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">Pattern formation: Old models out on a limb <hi rend="bold">2003</hi> <hi rend="italic">Nat Rev Genetics</hi> 4:133-143 </s></p></note><figure id="BAWE_0097b-pic.002"><head><hi rend="bold">Figure 2 - The limb bud</hi> The limb begins development when lateral plate mesoderm thickens, and develops into defined limb buds.<hi rend="sup">2,4</hi> The progress zone (orange) is a distal region of mesenchyme which extends the developing limb and consists of undifferentitated and highly proliferative cells. The overlying ectoderm at the tip of the limb bud is thickened and forms the apical ectodermal ridge (AER),<hi rend="sup">2</hi> shown in yellow. The zone of polarising activity (ZPA) is a small region of mesenchyme at the posterior region of the limb bud, at the body wall junction (shown in green). The epithelial ectoderm (blue) encases the limb bud. Figure adapted from the internet - Kenyon College Biology Dept Website <seg type="URL" n="http://biology.kenyon.edu/courses/biol114/Chap14/Chapter_14B.html"/></head></figure></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">2. Formation of the Limb Bud</head><p n="p5.30"><s n="s1.5;p5.30">The induction of the limb begins with formation of the limb bud, where lateral plate mesoderm (LPM) proliferates to form a circular bulge. </s><s n="s2.5;p5.30">Fgf8 was first implicated as a chick limb inducer. </s><s n="s3.5;p5.30"><hi rend="italic">Fgf8</hi> mRNA localises to the intermediate mesoderm (IM) at the level of the prospective forelimb and hindlimb territories, whilst being absent from the mesoderm of the prospective inter-limb territory, at stages 13 to 15 in chicks.<ref target="BAWE_0097b-endnote.004"/> Chick limb bud induction occurs over stages 13 to 15,<hi rend="sup">5</hi> theredore <hi rend="italic">Fgf8</hi> appears to be expressed at the right time, and in the right place to be a limb inducer. </s><s n="s4.5;p5.30">Fgf8 soaked beads induce a limb-like structure when inserted into the LPM of the inter-limb region,<hi rend="sup">5</hi> further indicating a role in limb induction. </s><s n="s5.5;p5.30"><hi rend="italic">Fgf8</hi> expression in the IM appears to induce its own expression in the overlying ectoderm of the limb bud which becomes the AER, as seen in figure 3. </s></p><note place="end" id="BAWE_0097b-endnote.004"><p n="pn1.1"><s rend="bold" n="s1.2;pn1.1">Crossley <hi rend="italic">et al.</hi> </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">Roles for FGF8 in the induction, inititation and maintenance of chick limb development <hi rend="bold">1996</hi> <hi rend="italic">Cell</hi> 84:127-136 </s></p></note><figure id="BAWE_0097b-pic.003"><head><hi rend="bold">Figure 3 - FGF8 expression in the chick limb bud</hi> Whole mount <hi rend="italic">in situ</hi> hybridisations of <hi rend="italic">Fgf8</hi> mRNA A) <hi rend="italic">Fgf8</hi> is localised to the ectoderm of prospective forelimb and hindlimb at stage 17. The arrowheads indicate the posterior boundary of expression. B) <hi rend="italic">Fgf8</hi> is localised through the length of the AER at stage 25. The arrowhead indicates the posterior limit boundary of expression. <hi rend="italic">Shh</hi> mRNA is also stained, and is detected in mesoderm underlying the posterior part of the <hi rend="italic">Fgf8</hi> expression domain (as indicated by the closed arrow) and in mesoderm proximal to the Fgf8 expression domain (as indicated by the open arrow.) The role of Shh is discussed later in this essay. Figure adapted from <hi rend="bold">Crossley <hi rend="italic">et al.</hi> 1996</hi> <hi rend="italic">Cell</hi> 84:127-136 </head></figure><p n="p6.30"><s n="s1.4;p6.30"><hi rend="italic">Fgf10</hi> has also been shown to be important in limb induction. </s><s n="s2.4;p6.30">It is initially widely expressed in the segmental plate, IM and LPM, but its expression is restricted to the LPM at stage 14 of chick development. </s><s n="s3.4;p6.30">Therefore <hi rend="italic">Fgf10</hi> is also present at the right time, in the right place. <ref target="BAWE_0097b-endnote.005"/><hi rend="italic">Fgf10</hi> expressing cells can cause ectopic limb formation when implanted into the inter-limb region,<hi rend="sup">6</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Fgf10 - / -</hi> mice show complete truncation of both fore- and hindlimbs,<ref target="BAWE_0097b-endnote.006"/> seen in figure 4. </s><s n="s4.4;p6.30">No <hi rend="italic">Fgf8</hi> expression was detected in the small limb buds formed,<hi rend="sup">7</hi> suggesting <hi rend="italic">Fgf10</hi> is upstream of <hi rend="italic">Fgf8</hi> in limb bud induction. </s></p><note place="end" id="BAWE_0097b-endnote.005"><p n="pn1.1"><s rend="bold" n="s1.2;pn1.1">Kawakami <hi rend="italic">et al</hi>. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">Wnt signals control FGF-dependant limb initiation and AER induction in the chick embryo <hi rend="bold">2001</hi> <hi rend="italic">Cell</hi> 104:891-900 </s></p></note><note place="end" id="BAWE_0097b-endnote.006"><p n="pn1.1"><s rend="bold" n="s1.2;pn1.1">Sekine <hi rend="italic">et al.</hi> </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1"> Fgf10 is essential for limb and lung formation <hi rend="bold">1999</hi> <hi rend="italic">Nature Genetics</hi> 21:138-141 </s></p></note><figure id="BAWE_0097b-pic.004"><head><hi rend="bold">Figure 4 - <hi rend="italic">Fgf10 - / -</hi> mutant mice</hi> A) Newborn pups, <hi rend="italic">Fgf10+/ -</hi> on the left and <hi rend="italic">Fgf10 - / -</hi> on the right. In the <hi rend="italic">Fgf10</hi> homozygous mutant mice there is complete truncation of both the fore- and hindlimbs. There is normal formation of the clavicle and posterior scapula, however all other limb elements are absent. It is found that the formation of limb buds is initiated, however it is severely retarded. B) and C) are tissues sections, with B) the wild-type forelimb bud, with the AER indicated by an arrowhead, and C) the homozygous mutant, with only a small limb bud formed, and no AER as indicated by the arrowhead. The ectoderm covering the small limb bud is not thickened in the mutant, and resembles ectoderm of the inter-limb region. <hi rend="italic">Shh</hi> expression, a ZPA marker, is not detected indicating that the ZPA has also not formed. Figure adapted from <hi rend="bold">Sekine <hi rend="italic">et al.</hi></hi> <hi rend="bold">1999</hi> <hi rend="italic">Nature Genetics</hi> 21:138-141</head></figure><p n="p7.30"><s n="s1.1;p7.30">Together this produces a model where Fgf-8 from the IM restricts <hi rend="italic">Fgf10</hi> expression to the LPM at the level of the prospective limbs, and then Fgf10 induces <hi rend="italic">Fgf8</hi> expression in the overlying ectoderm.<hi rend="sup">6</hi> However, limb bud initiation is seen in the <hi rend="italic">Fgf10 - / -</hi> mutant mice, so it appears expression of upstream gene or genes are required earlier on in limb bud induction. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0097b-pic.005"><head><hi rend="bold">Figure 5 - <hi rend="italic">Wnt2b</hi> expression pattern</hi><hi rend="italic">Wnt2b</hi> expression in stage 15 chick embryo. <hi rend="italic">Wnt2b</hi> is detected in the fore-limb bud region from stages 14-16, with strongest expression at stage 15. By stage 17, <hi rend="italic">Wnt2b</hi> is restricted to a small posterior mesenchymal domain, and after this no expression is detected. Figure adapted from <hi rend="bold">Kawakami <hi rend="italic">et al</hi>.</hi> <hi rend="bold">2001</hi> <hi rend="italic">Cell</hi> 104:891-900</head></figure><p n="p8.30"><s n="s1.3;p8.30">Expression of <hi rend="italic">Wnt2b</hi>, belonging to the Wnt family of secreted factors, is found in the LPM of the prospective forelimb at stage 14 in chicks,<hi rend="sup">6</hi> seen in figure 5. </s><s n="s2.3;p8.30">When <hi rend="italic">Wnt2b</hi> expressing cells are implanted into the inter-limb region, a limb bud is induced, and <hi rend="italic">Fgf10</hi> is expressed in the LPM after 8 hours, and <hi rend="italic">Fgf8</hi> induction occurs at around 20 hours.<hi rend="sup">6</hi> This suggests <hi rend="italic">Wnt2b</hi> acts upstream of <hi rend="italic">Fgf10</hi> and <hi rend="italic"> Fgf8</hi> in limb bud induction in the chick. </s><s n="s3.3;p8.30"><hi rend="italic">Wnt2b</hi> is however not detected in the prospective hindlimb region, however, <hi rend="italic">Wnt8c</hi> is expressed in the LPM of the prospective hindlimb until stage 12 in the chick, when <hi rend="italic">Fgf10</hi> expression becomes localised to the LPM of the prospective hind-limb region.<hi rend="sup">6</hi> <hi rend="italic">Wnt8c</hi> expressing cells can also induce an ectopic limb bud when implanted into the inter-limb region.<hi rend="sup">6</hi> This suggests <hi rend="italic">Wnt2b</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Wnt8c</hi> in the forelimb and hindlimb respectively, contribute to the restriction of <hi rend="italic">Fgf10</hi> expression in LPM to the prospective limb regions. </s></p><p n="p9.30"><s n="s1.1;p9.30">Some Wnt proteins, such as Wnt3a, have been shown to function via the activation of the intracellular mediator -catenin, which as part of a multiprotein complex, regulates transcription of target genes.<hi rend="sup">6</hi> Evidence in figure 6, strongly suggests that <hi rend="italic">Wnt2b</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Wnt8c</hi> signalling is mediated via -catenin activation in the fore- and hindlimb respectively. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0097b-pic.006"><head><hi rend="bold">Figure 6 - Evidence Wnt2b and Wnt8c limb initiation requires -catenin activity</hi> A)  -catenin detected in a western blot using an anti- -catenin antibody, in cytosolic and membrane-bound cellular fractions. The cytosolic fraction shows  -catenin accumulation in the positive control Wnt3a, and in Wnt2b and Wnt8c. B) <hi rend="italic">Fgf10</hi> staining in the leg field infected with a recombinant adenovirus expressing AXIN, a negative regulator of  catenin (indicted by arrow) at stage 10-12, is significantly reduced. This suggests that <hi rend="italic">Wnt2b/Wnt8c</hi> induction of <hi rend="italic">Fgf10</hi> expression, is  -catenin dependant. C) <hi rend="italic">Fgf8</hi> staining in the AER in the leg field infected with a recombinant adenovirus expressing AXIN (indicted by arrow) at stage 15 -16, is significantly reduced. <hi rend="italic">Fgf10</hi> expression is unaffected. This suggests that <hi rend="italic">Fgf10</hi> expression is already established by <hi rend="italic">Wnt2b/Wnt8c</hi> signalling at this stage. Figure adapted from <hi rend="bold">Kawakami <hi rend="italic">et al</hi>.</hi> <hi rend="bold">2001</hi> <hi rend="italic">Cell</hi> 104:891-900</head></figure><p n="p10.30"><s n="s1.2;p10.30">As discussed above, it is proposed that Fgf10 induces <hi rend="italic">Fgf8</hi> expression in the overlying surface ectoderm, which becomes the AER.<hi rend="sup">6</hi> <hi rend="italic">Wnt3a</hi> expression has been shown to be an upstream regulator of <hi rend="italic">Fgf8</hi> expression in the chick, and <hi rend="italic">Wnt3a</hi> appears to mediate its affects via activation of -catenin.<hi rend="sup">6</hi> Figure 6 shows that antagonism of -catenin at stage 15-16 does not affect <hi rend="italic">Fgf10</hi> expression, however the limbs that develop are truncated, as <hi rend="italic">Fgf8</hi> expression is down-regulated in the ectoderm, and there is disruption of AER formation.<hi rend="sup"> 6</hi> This indicates the induction of <hi rend="italic">Fgf8</hi> in the ectoderm by Fgf10 occurs via <hi rend="italic">Wnt3a</hi> and is -catenin dependant. </s><s n="s2.2;p10.30">Figure 7 summarises limb bud induction in a proposed model. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0097b-fig.001"><head><hi rend="bold">Figure 7 - A proposed model of events in limb bud induction</hi><hi rend="italic">Fgf8</hi> is expressed in the IM, and may induce or maintain Wnt expression (its specific role is as yet unclear). Wnt2b in the forelimb LPM, and Wnt8c in the hindlimb LPM, via  -catenin induce restriction of <hi rend="italic">Fgf10</hi> expression to the forelimb (FL) and hindlimb (HL) respectively. Fgf10 then signals via Wnt3a in a  -catenin dependant pathway, to induce <hi rend="italic">Fgf8</hi> expression in the overlying ectoderm. </head></figure></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">3. Identity of Fore- and Hindlimbs </head><p n="p11.30"><s n="s1.3;p11.30"><hi rend="italic">Tbx4</hi> and <hi rend="italic"> Tbx5</hi> are members of the T-box transcription factor family, and are specifically expressed in the hindlimb and forelimb respectively.<ref target="BAWE_0097b-endnote.007"/>&amp;<ref target="BAWE_0097b-endnote.008"/> When a conditional <hi rend="italic">Tbx5</hi> allele is expressed in mice, forelimbs are completely absent, while hindlimbs are unaffected,<hi rend="sup">9</hi> seen in figure 8. </s><s n="s2.3;p11.30">This demonstrates <hi rend="italic">Tbx5</hi> is vital in early limb development, and illustrates specificity to the forelimb. </s><s n="s3.3;p11.30">In <hi rend="italic">Fgf10</hi> null mice, there is expression of <hi rend="italic">Tbx4</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Tbx5,</hi> and initiation of limb bud formation,<ref target="BAWE_0097b-endnote.009"/> suggesting these genes are upstream of <hi rend="italic">Fgf10</hi>. </s></p><note place="end" id="BAWE_0097b-endnote.007"><p n="pn1.1"><s rend="bold" n="s1.2;pn1.1">Rodrigues-Esteban <hi rend="italic">et al.</hi> </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">The T-box genes <hi rend="italic">Tbx4</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Tbx5</hi> regulate limb outgrowth and identity <hi rend="bold">1999</hi> <hi rend="italic">Nature</hi> 398:814-818 </s></p></note><note place="end" id="BAWE_0097b-endnote.008"><p n="pn1.1"><s rend="bold" n="s1.2;pn1.1">Rallis <hi rend="italic">et al. </hi></s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1"><hi rend="bold italic">Tbx5</hi> is required for forelimb bud formation and continued outgrowth <hi rend="bold">2002</hi> <hi rend="italic">Development</hi> 130:2741-2751 </s></p></note><note place="end" id="BAWE_0097b-endnote.009"><p n="pn1.1"><s rend="bold" n="s1.2;pn1.1">Takeuchi <hi rend="italic">et al.</hi> </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1"> Tbx5 and Tbx4 trigger limb bud formation through activation of the Wnt/Fgf signalling cascade <hi rend="bold">2003</hi> <hi rend="italic">Development</hi> 130:2729-2739 </s></p></note><figure id="BAWE_0097b-pic.007"><head><hi rend="bold">Figure 8 - The role of Tbx5 in forelimb development</hi> A) A dorsal view of the thoracic region of a control mouse. B) A dorsal view of the thoracic region of a <hi rend="italic">Tbx5</hi> conditional mutant mouse. All elements of the forelimb and pectoral girdle are absent, suggesting <hi rend="italic">Tbx5</hi> is vital to forelimb development. C) A dorsal view of a control limb bud with whole-mount <hi rend="italic">in situ</hi> hybridisation for <hi rend="italic">Fgf8</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Shh</hi> found in the AER and ZPA respectively. D) A dorsal view of a limb bud injected with dominant negative forms of <hi rend="italic">Tbx5</hi> at stage 8. <hi rend="italic">Fgf8</hi> is not detected in the anterior of the limb, and <hi rend="italic">Shh</hi> expression is not detected in the ZPA. Figure adapted from <hi rend="bold">Rallis <hi rend="italic">et al.</hi> 2002</hi> <hi rend="italic">Development</hi> 130:2741-2751</head></figure><p n="p12.30"><s n="s1.2;p12.30">Misexpression of dominant negative <hi rend="italic">Tbx5</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Tbx4</hi> induces limb-less phenotypes, and repression of Wnt and Fgf genes, shown in figure 9, with a critical time period between stages 7 and 10 to induce the limb-less phenotype.<hi rend="sup">10</hi> This suggests <hi rend="italic">Tbx4</hi> and Tbx5 function before the Wnt and Fgf signals. </s><s n="s2.2;p12.30">This is also supported by the fact that their expression is first detected in the prospective limb mesenchyme prior to overt limb outgrowth.<hi rend="sup">9</hi> </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0097b-pic.008"><head><hi rend="bold">Figure 9 - Expression of dominant negative <hi rend="italic">Tbx4</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Tbx5</hi> induces repression of Wnt and Fgf genes</hi> A) <hi rend="italic">Tbx5</hi> dominant negative misexpression shows <hi rend="italic">Wnt2b</hi> repression 24 hours after electroporation (indicated by arrowheads). Normal expression is seen in the left forelimb region. Similar results are obtained with <hi rend="italic">Tbx4</hi> dominant misexpression showing <hi rend="italic">Wnt8c</hi> repression. B) <hi rend="italic">Tbx5</hi> dominant negative misexpression shows <hi rend="italic">Fgf8</hi> repression 24 hours after electroporation (indicated by arrowheads). Normal expression is seen in the left forelimb region. Similar results are obtained with <hi rend="italic">Tbx4</hi> dominant misexpression showing <hi rend="italic">Fgf8</hi> repression. C) Tissue section showing repression of <hi rend="italic">Fgf8</hi> in the hind-limb (indicated by arrowheads) following <hi rend="italic">Tbx4</hi> dominant negative misexpression. Similar results are obtained with <hi rend="italic">Tbx5</hi> dominant negative misexpression. Figure adapted from <hi rend="bold">Takeuchi et al.</hi> <hi rend="bold">2003</hi> <hi rend="italic">Development</hi> 130:2729-2739</head></figure><p n="p13.30"><s n="s1.3;p13.30">In chick embryos leg grafts expressing <hi rend="italic">Tbx4</hi> can develop into toe-like digits when placed into the wing,<hi rend="sup">8</hi> suggesting a role for <hi rend="italic">Tbx4</hi> in specification of the hindlimb. </s><s n="s2.3;p13.30">A recent study by Takeuchi <hi rend="italic">et al</hi><hi rend="sup">10</hi> provided significant evidence for the role of <hi rend="italic">Tbx4</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Tbx5</hi> in specification of limb identity. </s><s n="s3.3;p13.30">When <hi rend="italic">Tbx5</hi> was misexpressed in the inter-limb region, a wing-like limb formed, and <hi rend="italic">Wnt2b</hi> was expressed, and conversely with <hi rend="italic">Tbx4</hi> misexpression a leg-like limb formed, and <hi rend="italic">Wnt8c</hi> was expressed.<hi rend="sup">10</hi> It seems therefore that <hi rend="italic">Tbx4</hi> and <hi rend="italic"> Tbx5</hi> operate in the gap between the Hox genes that specify the primary A-P axis and the Wnt/Fgf network, in specification of limb identity and limb induction.<hi rend="sup">10</hi> </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">4. Induction of the Apical Ectodermal Ridge (AER)</head><p n="p14.30"><s n="s1.2;p14.30">The AER is situated at the dorsoventral limb boundary,<ref target="BAWE_0097b-endnote.010"/> and is vital for limb bud outgrowth. </s><s n="s2.2;p14.30">Rodriguez-Esteban <hi rend="italic">et al</hi><hi rend="sup">11</hi> found that chick <hi rend="italic">Radical fringe</hi> (<hi rend="italic">R-fng</hi>), homologous to the Drosophila <hi rend="italic">fng</hi> gene, encodes a secreted signalling molecule, with expression as seen in figure 10.<hi rend="sup">11</hi> Ectopic expression of <hi rend="italic">R-fng</hi> in the ventral side of the limb resulted in limb bud phenotypes lacking a defined AER, having a divided AER, having additional ventral or ventrally expanded AERs and having a lengthwise expansion of the anterior AER.<hi rend="sup">11</hi> This suggests that <hi rend="italic">R-fng</hi> functions in the normal formation of the AER. </s></p><note place="end" id="BAWE_0097b-endnote.010"><p n="pn1.1"><s rend="bold" n="s1.2;pn1.1">Rodriguez-Esteban <hi rend="italic">et al. </hi></s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1"><hi rend="bold italic">Radical fringe </hi>position the apical ectodermal ridge at the dorsoventral boundary of the vertebrate limb <hi rend="bold">1997</hi> <hi rend="italic">Nature</hi> 386:360-366 </s></p></note><figure id="BAWE_0097b-pic.009"><head><hi rend="bold">Figure 10 - Expression pattern of <hi rend="italic">Radical fringe</hi> mRNA</hi> A) <hi rend="italic">R-fng</hi> mRNA is first detected at stage 15 in the presumptive dorsal limb ectoderm, D. No <hi rend="italic">R-fng</hi> is detected in the presumptive ventral limb ectoderm, V. B) At stage 16, there is a higher concentration of <hi rend="italic">R-fng</hi> mRNA, with clear restriction to the dorsal side and at the dorsoventral boundry C) At stage 18, there is a sharp domain of <hi rend="italic">R-fng</hi> expression at the dorsoventral boundry corresponding to the AER, which remains until at least stage 27, with expression on the dorsal side of the limb remaining until stage 22-24. Figure adapted from <hi rend="bold">Rodriguez-Esteban <hi rend="italic">et al.</hi> 1997</hi> <hi rend="italic">Nature</hi> 386:360-366</head></figure><p n="p15.30"><s n="s1.2;p15.30">It appears that <hi rend="italic">R-fng</hi> requires previous establishment of the D-V axis since its expression is dorsally restricted as seen in figure 10. </s><s n="s2.2;p15.30">Dorsal misexpression of ectodermal gene </s></p><p n="p16.30"><s n="s1.1;p16.30"><hi rend="italic">En-1,</hi> results in severe truncations with AERs that are undefined, discontinuous AERs, and additional dorsal AERs.<hi rend="sup">11</hi> Therefore it is suggested that ventrally expressed <hi rend="italic">En-1</hi> in the ectoderm represses <hi rend="italic">R-fng</hi> expression, restricting it to the dorsal ectoderm, creating a '<hi rend="italic">R-fng</hi> boundary' and resulting in the formation of the AER at the dorsoventral boundary.<hi rend="sup">11</hi> </s></p><p n="p17.30"><s n="s1.4;p17.30">As seen in figure 7, Fgf10 in the LPM is proposed to induce expression of <hi rend="italic">Fgf8</hi> in the ectoderm via <hi rend="italic">Wnt3a</hi> and -catenin. </s><s n="s2.4;p17.30"><hi rend="italic">Wnt3a</hi> is detected before <hi rend="italic">Fgf8</hi> in the limb field ectoderm, and is up-regulated in cells near the dorsoventral boundary.<ref target="BAWE_0097b-endnote.011"/> Misexpression of <hi rend="italic">Wnt3a</hi> induces ectopic expression of AER-specific genes, and application of <hi rend="italic">Wnt3a</hi>-expressing cells to limbs with the AER removed induces <hi rend="italic">Fgf8</hi> expression.<hi rend="sup">12</hi> It therefore appears <hi rend="italic">Wnt3a</hi> is involved in the formation of the AER and induces AER-specific genes. </s><s n="s3.4;p17.30">As shown in figure 6, <hi rend="italic">Wnt3a</hi> signals via -catenin, which forms a complex with members of the LEF/XTCF family to activate transcription of target genes.<hi rend="sup">12</hi> A member of this family, Lef1, is strongly expressed in the AER, and misexpression of <hi rend="italic">Wnt3a</hi> enhances <hi rend="italic">Lef1</hi> expression. </s><s n="s4.4;p17.30">It therefore appears <hi rend="italic">Wnt3a</hi> requires -catenin/<hi rend="italic">Lef1</hi> signalling to induce its response. </s></p><note place="end" id="BAWE_0097b-endnote.011"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1"><hi rend="bold">Kengaku</hi> <hi rend="bold italic">et al.</hi> </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">Distinct WNT pathways regulating the AER formatio and dorsoventral polarity in the chick limb bud <hi rend="bold">1998</hi> <hi rend="italic">Science</hi> 280:1274-1277 </s></p></note></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">5. Development of the Dorsal-Ventral (D-V) Axis</head><p n="p18.30"><s n="s1.3;p18.30">The signals that regulate dorsal-ventral identity are derived from the ectoderm.<ref target="BAWE_0097b-endnote.012"/>&amp; <ref target="BAWE_0097b-endnote.013"/><hi rend="italic">Wnt7a</hi> expression is present in the ectoderm at the level of the both the presumptive fore- and hindlimb in mice, and during the initial stages of limb bud outgrowth, expression is uniform throughout the dorsal limb ectoderm.<hi rend="sup">13&amp;14</hi> It is therefore thought to be involved in determining the D-V axis. </s><s n="s2.3;p18.30"><hi rend="italic">Wnt7a - / -</hi> mice show normal ventral structures in the limbs, however many dorsal-to-ventral transformations of mesenchyme cell fates are observed.<hi rend="sup">13</hi> This phenotype is more severe in distally,<hi rend="sup">13</hi> suggesting other factors are also involved in D-V patterning. </s><s n="s3.3;p18.30">Ventrally restricted expression of genes such as <hi rend="italic">En-1</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Bmp-2</hi> remains intact, so it seems the cell fate changes observed occur to the underlying dorsal mesenchyme.<hi rend="sup">13</hi> Overall, this demonstrates that <hi rend="italic">Wnt7a</hi> is required in dorsal patterning of the limb. </s></p><note place="end" id="BAWE_0097b-endnote.012"><p n="pn1.1"><s rend="bold" n="s1.2;pn1.1">Parr, B. and McMahon, A. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">Dorsalizing signal Wnt7a required for normal polarity of D-V and A-P axes of mouse limb <hi rend="bold">1995</hi> <hi rend="italic">Nature</hi> 374:350-353 </s></p></note><note place="end" id="BAWE_0097b-endnote.013"><p n="pn1.1"><s rend="bold" n="s1.2;pn1.1">Riddle <hi rend="italic">et al.</hi> </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1"> Induction of the LIM homeobox gene <hi rend="italic">Lmx-1</hi> by WNT7a establishes dorsoventral pattern in the vertebrate limb <hi rend="bold">1995</hi> <hi rend="italic">Cell</hi> 83:631-640 </s></p></note><figure id="BAWE_0097b-pic.010"><head><hi rend="bold">Figure 11 - Expression of <hi rend="italic">Lmx1</hi></hi> A) <hi rend="italic">Lmx1</hi> staining in the dorsal, D, limb mesoderm B) <hi rend="italic">Lmx1</hi> staining following infection of the ventral ectoderm with a <hi rend="italic"> Wnt7a</hi> expressing retrovirus. Ectopic <hi rend="italic">Lmx1</hi> staining is seen in the ventral, V, limb mesoderm. Figure adapted from <hi rend="bold">Riddle <hi rend="italic">et al.</hi></hi> <hi rend="bold">1995</hi> <hi rend="italic">Cell</hi> 83:631-640 </head></figure><p n="p19.30"><s n="s1.2;p19.30"><hi rend="italic">Lmx1</hi>, belonging to the LIM homeobox gene family, is expressed in the dorsal mesoderm of the limb bud, seen in figure 11.<hi rend="sup">14</hi> It is restricted to the mesoderm adjacent to the <hi rend="italic">Wnt7a</hi> expressing ectoderm, in both the fore- and hind limb.<hi rend="sup">14</hi> Its timing of expression shows great similarity to that of <hi rend="italic">Wnt7a</hi> in the ectoderm, and ventral misexpression of <hi rend="italic">Wnt7a</hi> leads to ectopic expression of <hi rend="italic">Lmx1</hi> in the ventral limb mesoderm, seen in figure 11.<hi rend="sup">14</hi> This suggests that dorsal expression of <hi rend="italic">Wnt7a</hi> in the ectoderm induces dorsal expression of <hi rend="italic">Lmx1</hi> in the mesoderm, which gives the mesoderm dorsal identity. </s><s n="s2.2;p19.30">In the absence of surrounding ectoderm, dorsal <hi rend="italic">Lmx1</hi> expression is still detected proximally, suggesting continuous signalling from the ectoderm is not required to maintain <hi rend="italic">Lmx1</hi> expression in proximal limb mesenchyme.<hi rend="sup">14</hi> <hi rend="italic">Wnt7a</hi> appears to induce <hi rend="italic">Lmx1</hi> expression via a -catenin independent pathway.<hi rend="sup">12</hi> </s></p><p n="p20.30"><s n="s1.1;p20.30">We have seen that <hi rend="italic">En-1</hi> is expressed in the ventral ectoderm, and functions in positioning of the AER.<hi rend="sup">11</hi> <hi rend="italic">En-1</hi> is thought to be involved in specifying ventral cell fate, as misexpression of <hi rend="italic">En-1</hi> represses the expression of the dorsally restricted <hi rend="italic">Wnt7a</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Lmx1</hi> genes.<hi rend="sup">11</hi> Therefore it appears that correct spatial expression and interaction of <hi rend="italic">Wnt7a</hi> and <hi rend="italic">En-1</hi> in the ectoderm are key to D-V patterning of the limb, although other genes are also likely to be involved. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">6. Development of the Proximal-Distal (Pr-D) Axis</head><p n="p21.30"><s n="s1.2;p21.30">The progress zone is a region of proliferation of undifferentiated cells.<ref target="BAWE_0097b-endnote.014"/> Cartilage staining shows that the limb develops along the Pr-D axis, and outgrowth is thought to occur as in the progress zone (PZ) model.<hi rend="sup"> 2,3</hi> This is where cells in the progress zone are maintained in a proliferative and undifferentiated state, and their fate is dependant upon the time spent in the PZ. The longer the time spent in the PZ, the more distal the cell fate. </s><s n="s2.2;p21.30">It is thought that the AER regulates outgrowth through maintaining the undifferentiated and proliferative state of cells in the PZ. <ref target="BAWE_0097b-endnote.015"/> </s></p><note place="end" id="BAWE_0097b-endnote.014"><p n="pn1.1"><s rend="bold" n="s1.2;pn1.1">Niswander <hi rend="italic">et al.</hi> </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1"> FGF-4 replaces the apical ectodermal ridge and directs outgrowth and patterning of the limb <hi rend="bold">1993</hi> <hi rend="italic">Cell</hi> 75:579-587 </s></p></note><note place="end" id="BAWE_0097b-endnote.015"><p n="pn1.1"><s rend="bold" n="s1.2;pn1.1">Mahmood <hi rend="italic">et al.</hi> </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1"> A role for FGF8 in the initiation and maintenance of vertebrate limb bud outgrowth <hi rend="bold">1995</hi> <hi rend="italic">Current Biology</hi> 5:797-806 </s></p></note><p n="p22.30"><s n="s1.1;p22.30">Application of Fgf4 soaked beads to chick limb buds with the AER removed results in stimulation of limb bud outgrowth and almost normal proximodistal pattern and limb length, although with some abnormalities in shape, compared to truncation in the controls.<hi rend="sup">15</hi> Simultaneous application of Fgf4 beads to the apical and posterior wing bud mesenchyme following AER removal, leads to virtually complete skeletal elements of the limb, with only some digit abnormalities seen in figure 12.<hi rend="sup">15</hi> This suggests <hi rend="italic">Fgf4</hi> is involved in the stimulation of limb bud outgrowth, and for complete formation of the Pr-D axis Fgf4 may stimulate posterior mesenchyme cells to produce a signal which maintains the active progress zone.<hi rend="sup">15</hi> However, <hi rend="italic">Fgf4</hi> mRNA is restricted to the posterior part of the AER,<hi rend="sup">16</hi> and Fgfs are thought to act over only short distances, so it seems other factors are likely to be involved in Pr-D development. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0097b-pic.011"><head><hi rend="bold">Figure 12 - Skeletal pattern formation</hi> A) Skeletal pattern in a wild-type chick forelimb, with an intact AER B) Skeletal pattern in a chick forelimb when the AER is removed at stage 20, showing truncation. C) Skeletal pattern in a chick forelimb when the AER is removed at stage 20, and an Fgf4 soaked bead applied to both the posterior and apical mesenchyme. Digit 2 is readily identifiable due to its shorter metacarpal, however the posterior digits 3 and 4 are incomplete, making them difficult to be distinguished. The posterior digits are in a tight cluster. It is suggested that this incomplete development is due to lack of sufficient Fgf4 at the stage the phalanges are being specified, as the beads are only applied once. Figure adapted from <hi rend="bold">Niswander <hi rend="italic">et al.</hi></hi> <hi rend="bold">1993</hi> <hi rend="italic">Cell</hi> 75:579-587</head></figure><p n="p23.30"><s n="s1.2;p23.30">Fgf signals are transduced via Fgf receptors (Fgfr). <ref target="BAWE_0097b-endnote.016"/><hi rend="italic">Fgfr2</hi> is expressed in the LPM during limb bud initiation, and then concentrates to the surface ectoderm, and at lower levels in the adjacent mesenchyme.<hi rend="sup">17</hi> Its pattern of expression therefore overlaps the domains of <hi rend="italic">Fgf10</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Fgf8</hi> expression discussed in section 2. </s><s n="s2.2;p23.30">Xu <hi rend="italic">et al17</hi> found that mice with a deletion of a domain of Fgfr2, show failure of limb induction, with no staining for <hi rend="italic">Fgf8</hi>, and <hi rend="italic">Fgf10</hi> staining weaker than in the wild-type which gradually reduced and disappeared, in both fore- and hindlimbs.<hi rend="sup">17</hi> This suggests that Fgfr2, which is present in limb bud as two major isoforms, is involved in induction of Fgf8 by Fgf10, and in turn the maintenance of Fgf10 by Fgf8, and this reciprocal interaction is vital for limb bud formation and outgrowth.<hi rend="sup">17</hi> </s></p><note place="end" id="BAWE_0097b-endnote.016"><p n="pn1.1"><s rend="bold" n="s1.2;pn1.1">Xu <hi rend="italic">et al.</hi> </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1"> Fibroblast growth factor receptor 2 (FGFR2)-mediated reciprocal regulation loop between FGF8 and FGF10 is essential for limb induction <hi rend="bold">1998</hi><hi rend="italic"> Development</hi> 125:753-765 </s></p></note><p n="p24.30"><s n="s1.3;p24.30"><hi rend="italic">Fgf8</hi> expression induced in the ectoderm by the expression of <hi rend="italic">Fgf10,</hi> persists in the limb bud and is found to be restricted uniformly to cells of the AER, before the expression of <hi rend="italic">Fgf4</hi>.<hi rend="sup">16</hi> Mice forelimbs maintain limb bud growth after AER removal and incubation with Fgf8.<hi rend="sup">16</hi> This shows that along with Fgf4, Fgf8 may also perform most of the functions of the AER when it is removed. </s><s n="s2.3;p24.30">Conditional inactivation of <hi rend="italic">Fgf8</hi> determined that it is only absolutely required in the anterior AER, as only anterior forelimb elements were absent. <ref target="BAWE_0097b-endnote.017"/><hi rend="italic">Fgf4</hi> levels had increased, suggesting that the two are co-regulated, and <hi rend="italic">Fgf4</hi> compensates for the loss of <hi rend="italic">Fgf8.</hi> </s><s n="s3.3;p24.30">Overall it appears that both <hi rend="italic">Fgf4</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Fgf8</hi> are vital for the correct outgrowth and Pr-D patterning of the vertebrate limb. </s></p><note place="end" id="BAWE_0097b-endnote.017"><p n="pn1.1"><s rend="bold" n="s1.2;pn1.1">Moon <hi rend="italic">et al</hi>. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">FGF8 is involved for outgrowth and patterning of the limbs <hi rend="bold">2000</hi> <hi rend="italic">Nature Genetics</hi> 26:455-459 </s></p></note></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">7. Development of the Anterior-Posterior (A-P) Axis</head><p n="p25.30"><s n="s1.2;p25.30">Early experiments found that the A-P axis involved ZPA, as seen in figure 13.<ref target="BAWE_0097b-endnote.018"/> Riddle <hi rend="italic">at al</hi><hi rend="sup">19</hi> isolated a Drosophila <hi rend="italic">hedgehog</hi> homolog, <hi rend="italic">Sonic hedgehog</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Shh</hi>) and via <hi rend="italic">in situ</hi> hybridisation found that <hi rend="italic">Shh</hi> is expressed in the posterior regions of the fore- and hindlimb corresponding in both position and intensity to the polarising activity of the ZPA.<hi rend="sup">19</hi> Ectopic expression of <hi rend="italic">Shh</hi> was found to result in mirror-image digit duplications similar to those with an ectopic ZPA.<hi rend="sup">19</hi> This suggests that the polarising activity of the ZPA is mediated by <hi rend="italic">Shh.</hi> </s><s n="s2.2;p25.30">Ectopic <hi rend="italic">Shh</hi> expression in the anterior could induce mirror-image activation of <hi rend="italic">Hoxd</hi> gene expression, as occurred when the ZPA is transplanted.<hi rend="sup">19</hi> This implicates <hi rend="italic">Hoxd</hi> gene expression as a downstream target of <hi rend="italic">Shh</hi> in limb A-P patterning. </s></p><note place="end" id="BAWE_0097b-endnote.018"><p n="pn1.1"><s rend="bold" n="s1.2;pn1.1">Riddle <hi rend="italic">at al.</hi> </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1"><hi rend="italic">Sonic hedgehog</hi> mediates the polarising activity of the ZPA <hi rend="bold">1993</hi> 75:1401-1416 </s></p></note><figure id="BAWE_0097b-pic.012"><head><hi rend="bold">Figure 13 - The role of the ZPA in A-P limb patterning</hi> The ZPA is a small region of mesenchyme at the posterior region of the limb bud at the body wall junction. When grafted to the anterior of another limb, the ZPA causes mirror-image digit duplications. This is shown in schematic form in a chick forelimb. Figure adapted from <hi rend="bold">Riddle <hi rend="italic">at al.</hi></hi> <hi rend="bold">1993</hi> 75:1401-1416 </head></figure><p n="p26.30"><s n="s1.2;p26.30"><hi rend="italic">In situ</hi> hybridisation shows <hi rend="italic">Hoxb-8</hi> is expressed in the posterior of the chick forelimb, with position and intensity corresponding to the ZPA.<ref target="BAWE_0097b-endnote.019"/> It seems <hi rend="italic">Hoxb-8</hi> is involved in establishing the position of the forelimb ZPA. The expression of <hi rend="italic">Hoxb-8</hi> can be regulated in a dose-dependant response to retinoic acid (RA), suggesting RA lies upstream of <hi rend="italic">Hoxb-8</hi> in specifying the position of the ZPA according to the primary axis.<hi rend="sup">20</hi> The loss of <hi rend="italic">Hoxb-8</hi> expression at stage 18 in the chick appears to be as a result of inhibition from the ZPA and AER,<hi rend="sup">20</hi> seen in figure 14. </s><s n="s2.2;p26.30"><hi rend="italic">Hoxb-8</hi> is not expressed in the hindlimb, however, a more 5' <hi rend="italic">Hox</hi> gene, with a more posterior boundary is predicted to perform a similar function in the hindlimb.<hi rend="sup">20</hi> </s></p><note place="end" id="BAWE_0097b-endnote.019"><p n="pn1.1"><s rend="bold" n="s1.2;pn1.1">Stratford <hi rend="italic">et al.</hi> </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1"><hi rend="italic">Hoxb-8</hi> has a role in establishing early anterior-posterior polarity in chick forelimb but not hindlimb <hi rend="bold">1997</hi> <hi rend="italic">Development</hi> 124:4224-4234 </s></p></note><figure id="BAWE_0097b-fig.002"><head><hi rend="bold">Figure 14 - The regulation of <hi rend="italic">Shh</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Hoxb-8</hi> expression</hi> Hoxb-8 induces expression of <hi rend="italic">Shh</hi> in the ZPA. A signal from the AER is also required to establish the ZPA. The establishment of the ZPA leads to the down-regulation of <hi rend="italic">Hoxb-8</hi> expression. The AER is also involved in providing an inhibitory signal. This is an example of how signalling from the AER and ZPA interlinks. Figure adapted from <hi rend="bold">Stratford <hi rend="italic">et al.</hi></hi> <hi rend="bold">1997</hi> <hi rend="italic">Development</hi> 124:4224-4234 </head></figure><p n="p27.30"><s n="s1.3;p27.30"><hi rend="italic">Gli3</hi> has been suggested as a target of <hi rend="italic">Shh</hi> signalling in A-P limb patterning. </s><s n="s2.3;p27.30"><hi rend="italic">Shh - / -</hi> limbs have severe distal skeletal deficiencies, with zeugopod and autopod elements missing, fused or lacking identity. <ref target="BAWE_0097b-endnote.020"/><hi rend="italic">Gli3 - / -</hi> limbs exhibit severe polydactyly.<hi rend="sup">21</hi> <hi rend="italic">Shh - / - Gli3 - / -</hi> mice, develop virtually normal stylopod and zeugopod elements, however the autopod is polydactylous.<hi rend="sup">21</hi> This suggests the two are required for constraining the polydactylous potential of the autopod and specifying digit identity. </s><s n="s3.3;p27.30">Since the <hi rend="italic">Gli3 - / -</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Shh - / - Gli3 - / -</hi> limbs are almost indistinguishable, this would suggest <hi rend="italic">Shh</hi> has no effect in the absence of <hi rend="italic">Gli3</hi>, and <hi rend="italic">Gli3</hi> is therefore required for <hi rend="italic">Shh</hi> to function in A-P patterning.<hi rend="sup">21</hi> </s></p><note place="end" id="BAWE_0097b-endnote.020"><p n="pn1.1"><s rend="bold" n="s1.2;pn1.1">Litingtung <hi rend="italic">et al.</hi> </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1"><hi rend="italic">Shh</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Gli3</hi> are dispensible for limb skeleton formation but regulate digit number and identity <hi rend="bold">2002</hi> <hi rend="italic">Nature</hi> 418:979-983 </s></p></note><p n="p28.30"><s n="s1.3;p28.30"><hi rend="italic">Gli3</hi> is a transcription factor thought to be present in the limb in transcriptional activator (<hi rend="italic">Gli3A)</hi> and repressor <hi rend="italic">(Gli3R)</hi> forms, with a proteolytic cleavage generating the repressor form.<hi rend="sup">3,4,21</hi> <hi rend="italic">Shh</hi> is proposed to inhibit this cleavage, therefore generating the activator form, and creating an A-P gradient of <hi rend="italic">Gli3A:Gli3R</hi>.<hi rend="sup"> 3,4,21</hi> The expression of target genes then leads to the A-P patterning of digits. </s><s n="s2.3;p28.30">As reviewed by Niswander,<hi rend="sup">3</hi> early A-P patterning in the stylopod and zeugopod is thought to be a result of <hi rend="italic">Gli3</hi> expression in the anterior mesenchyme and <hi rend="italic">dHand</hi> expression in the posterior mesenchyme. </s><s n="s3.3;p28.30">The transcription factor <hi rend="italic">dHand</hi> is also thought to be required to activate <hi rend="italic">Shh</hi> expression in the ZPA. </s></p><p n="p29.30"><s n="s1.1;p29.30">The ZPA requires a signal from the AER for establishment and maintenance of <hi rend="italic">Shh</hi> expression, and it appears that the AER requires the ZPA for maintenance of <hi rend="italic">Fgf4</hi> expression.<hi rend="sup">15</hi> This has been examined by looking at <hi rend="italic">limb deformed</hi> (<hi rend="italic">ld)</hi> mutants, which show normal activation of <hi rend="italic">Shh</hi> expression, but subsequent up-regulation does not occur.<hi rend="sup">22</hi> Grafts of <hi rend="italic">Shh</hi> expressing cells in the wild-type induce ectopic <hi rend="italic">Fgf4</hi> expression, however in the <hi rend="italic">ld</hi> mutant this does not occur.<hi rend="sup">22</hi> Further evidence as seen in figure 15, has lead to a model for a proposed Shh/Fgf4 feedback loop. <ref target="BAWE_0097b-endnote.021"/><ref target="BAWE_0097b-endnote.022"/> </s></p><note place="end" id="BAWE_0097b-endnote.021"><p n="pn1.1"><s rend="bold" n="s1.2;pn1.1">Zuniga <hi rend="italic">et al.</hi> </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1"> Signal relay by BMP antagonism controls the SHH/FGF4 feedback loop in vertebrate limb buds <hi rend="bold">1999</hi> <hi rend="italic">Nature</hi> 401:598-602 </s></p></note><note place="end" id="BAWE_0097b-endnote.022"><p n="pn1.1"><s rend="bold" n="s1.2;pn1.1">Khokha <hi rend="italic">et al.</hi> </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1"> Gremlin is the BMP antagonist required for maintenance of Shh and Fgf signals during limb patterning <hi rend="bold">2003</hi> <hi rend="italic">Nature Genetics</hi> 34:303-307 </s></p></note><figure id="BAWE_0097b-fig.003"><head><hi rend="bold">Figure 15 - Shh/Fgf4 feedback loop</hi><hi rend="italic">Formin</hi> was originally thought to be required to relay <hi rend="italic">Shh</hi> signalling to the AER for <hi rend="italic">Fgf4</hi> maintenance,<hi rend="sup">22</hi> however the mutation in the <hi rend="italic">ld</hi> mutants was later suggested to map to <hi rend="italic">cis-</hi> regulatory elements of G <hi rend="italic">remlin.</hi> <hi rend="sup">23</hi> <hi rend="italic">Gremlin</hi> encodes a BMP antagonist, and is expressed in the posterior distal limb bud mesenchyme.<hi rend="sup">23</hi> In the absence of <hi rend="italic">Gremlin,</hi> <hi rend="italic">Fgf4</hi> expression is undetectable in the AER and in both fore- and hindlimbs, and <hi rend="italic">Shh</hi> expression is also significantly reduced.<hi rend="sup">23</hi> Expression of BMP signalling targets are increased, suggesting <hi rend="italic">Gremlin</hi> is required for inhibition of BMP signalling, and consequent maintenance of <hi rend="italic">Fgf4</hi> expression in the AER. The regulatory feedback loop is set up when <hi rend="italic">Shh</hi> is expressed in the ZPA, and induces expression of <hi rend="italic">Gremlin</hi> in the surrounding mesenchyme. Gremlin is a BMP antagonist, and inhibits BMP signalling. Inhibition of BMP means that expression of <hi rend="italic">Fgf4</hi> is maintained in the AER, rather than being antagonised by BMPs. In turn <hi rend="italic">Fgf4</hi> maintenance in the AER maintains <hi rend="italic">Shh</hi> expression in the ZPA. </head></figure></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">8. Conclusions</head><p n="p30.30"><s n="s1.5;p30.30">The D-V, Pr-D and A-P patterning systems are highly interlinked, with grey areas in understanding that may be clarified with future experimentation. </s><s n="s2.5;p30.30">The progress zone model of progressive Pr-D specification for example, has recently been challenged by an alternative model based on early specification of Pr-D fates in the limb bud.<hi rend="sup">3</hi> Therefore it seems questions are still to be answered concerning when specification actually occurs. </s><s n="s3.5;p30.30">The chick and mice models discussed in the essay may be related to the limb patterning in other vertebrates, due to high levels of evolutionary conservation. </s><s n="s4.5;p30.30">Parallels have also often been drawn with <hi rend="italic">Drosophila</hi>. </s><s n="s5.5;p30.30">Overall the patterning of the vertebrate limb is produced by complex and interacting signalling cascades, which set up the axes that are essential in producing complete and correct morphology. </s></p></div1></body><back><div1 type="bibliography"><head rend="underlined bold">References </head><p/></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
