<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_0099c" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Investigation of GDP per capita and Military Expenditure of 50 countries Question two: Investigation of the relative values of Euro and US Dollar.</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">The document has a title page which contains:
document title
title part</note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">deleted: header: university name, module number, student name and number; footer: word counts, page numbers</note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">Evaluated as candidate compound assignment. Assigned to S4: set of tasks/questions/exercises: non-compound</note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">deleted: Word Count: 966</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">1</p><p n="date">2006-01</p><p n="module title">Computing &amp; Data Analysis</p><p n="module code">EC125</p><p n="genre family">Exercise</p><p n="discipline">Economics</p><p n="disciplinary group">SS</p><p n="grade">D</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">1348</p><p n="number of s-units">54</p><p n="number of p">15</p><p n="number of tables">5</p><p n="number of figures">3</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">1</p><p n="number of lists">1</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">0</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">25.0</p><p n="average s-units per p">3.6</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">complex but non-compound assignment (see notesStmt for details)</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">m</p><p n="year of birth">1984</p><p n="first language">Finnish</p><p n="education">UK2</p><p n="course">Economics L100</p><p n="student ID">0099</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><docTitle><titlePart rend="bold">EC 125 Computing and Data Analysis 2004-2005 Coursework Assignment 1</titlePart></docTitle><titlePart><hi rend="bold">Investigation of GDP per capita and</hi> <hi rend="bold"> Military Expenditure of 50 countries Question two: Investigation of the</hi> <hi rend="bold"> relative values of Euro and US Dollar.</hi> </titlePart></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="section"><p n="p1.15"><s n="s1.5;p1.15">The aim of this assignment is to carry out a simple enquiry based on indicators of development, using the World Development Indicators and the statistical features of Excel. </s><s n="s2.5;p1.15">My choice of Indicators was Gross Domestic Product of random 50 countries in year 2002, and military expenditure as a percentage of the GDP in those countries in the same year. </s><s n="s3.5;p1.15">This was of particular interest for me, since in 2002 the attacks on the World Trade Centre could already have some effect on military expenditure, especially in the western world, United States and countries with similar interests in world politics. </s><s n="s4.5;p1.15">Also it would be interesting to see whether the size of GDP would have any effect on the percentage of military expenditure, one could think that the larger economy, the smaller percentage of the aggregate output is required to maintain an army. </s><s n="s5.5;p1.15">Even if a country is willing to enlarge its military power, the total share could get smaller as economy increases. </s></p><p n="p2.15"><s n="s1.1;p2.15">The countries represented in this investigation are shown in the end. </s></p><p n="p3.15"><s n="s1.1;p3.15">The frequency distribution table for GDP per capita of the 50 in 2002 countries in terms of 1995 US Dollars: </s></p><table id="BAWE_0099c-tab.001"><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p4.15"><s n="s1.7;p4.15">The frequency distribution table shows how many countries there are representing each income class. </s><s n="s2.7;p4.15">The classes work as limits, for example there are five countries in the class from 7 500 dollars to 15 000. </s><s n="s3.7;p4.15">The right side of the frequency table is the same table, just put in decreasing order. </s><s n="s4.7;p4.15">However in this case the value zero does not represent a group as such, it is just the number of countries, which did not have data of that indicator for 2002. </s><s n="s5.7;p4.15">It has to be noted, that this will affect the calculations later on, changing the summary statistics by a small factor. </s><s n="s6.7;p4.15">Out of these 50 countries the largest group of countries was of income level 0 - 7 500 Dollars per capita. </s><s n="s7.7;p4.15">The histogram formed using the above data and the summary statistics for GDP per capita: </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0099c-fig.001"><head>GDP per capita</head></figure><table id="BAWE_0099c-tab.002"><head rend="italic">Summary statistics</head><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p5.15"><s n="s1.5;p5.15">The summary statistics gives the results of the calculations made. </s><s n="s2.5;p5.15">The mean is the average and out of these 50 countries it is 11 814.58 of 1995 US Dollars. </s><s n="s3.5;p5.15">It has to be noted however, that the mean is affected by the three countries, that weren't given a value for GDP per capita. </s><s n="s4.5;p5.15">The median is the middle value of the range, it divides the data in two equal parts, 50 % of the data is to the left of median and 50% of the data is to the right. </s><s n="s5.5;p5.15">In this case median is 4478.196 of the same US Dollars. </s></p><p n="p6.15"><s n="s1.5;p6.15">The range of all the values is 45 029.42, which is the difference between the minimum and maximum values. </s><s n="s2.5;p6.15">The standard deviation is a statistic that tells you how tightly all the various examples are clustered around the mean in a set of data, It is the "mean of mean". </s><s n="s3.5;p6.15">In this case it is 13 627.34. </s><s n="s4.5;p6.15">Skewness is a measure of symmetry, negative values for the skewness indicate data that are skewed left and positive values for the skewness indicate data that are skewed right of its middle point, mean. </s><s n="s5.5;p6.15">In this case the skewness measure is positive, so the data is skewed right of the mean, meaning that the median is left from the mean. </s></p><p n="p7.15"><s n="s1.1;p7.15">The frequency distribution for military expenditure as a percentage of GDP in 2002 and the histogram produced: </s></p><table id="BAWE_0099c-tab.003"><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p8.15"><s n="s1.3;p8.15">It can be seen that for most of the countries the percentage share of military expenditure is between 1.6 and 3.2 per cent. </s><s n="s2.3;p8.15">In this variable there is quite a large number with no data, 10 in total. </s><s n="s3.3;p8.15">This will affect the following calculations. </s></p><table id="BAWE_0099c-tab.004"><head rend="italic">Summary statistics</head><row><cell/></row></table><figure id="BAWE_0099c-fig.002"><head>Military expenditure % of GDP</head></figure><p n="p9.15"><s n="s1.6;p9.15">In this case the mean is 2.419 (3DP), meaning that the average military expenditure of the 50 countries is 2.419% (3 Decimal Places). </s><s n="s2.6;p9.15">The middle value, median, is 1.9. </s><s n="s3.6;p9.15">Range is 11.2; the largest percentage of GDP in military expenditure is 11.2%, shown by Kuwait in this case. </s><s n="s4.6;p9.15">The standard deviation, <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0099c-form.001"/>, is 2.361 (Correct to 3 Decimal Places). </s><s n="s5.6;p9.15">The skewness of military expenditure is also positive, so the data is skewed to the right. </s><s n="s6.6;p9.15">In this case however, it has to emphasised, that there is some error in these calculations, due to the fact, that 10 countries did not have available data for military expenditure. </s></p><p n="p10.15"><s n="s1.1;p10.15">When plotting one variable against the other, the following result is: </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0099c-fig.003"><head>Relstionship between GDP per capita and military expenditure</head></figure><p n="p11.15"><s n="s1.2;p11.15">The trend in this diagram seems to be, that the larger the GDP per capita, the smaller the military expenditure, as a percentage of GDP. It seems reasonable to conclude, that for different countries, at least some military expenditure is required, and as wealth increases, the opportunity cost of maintaining an army gets smaller, i.e. the percentage share gets smaller. </s><s n="s2.2;p11.15">However, much care has to be taken, this is a large simplification, and does not explain everything, that could affect the need or willingness to spend money on military. </s></p><table id="BAWE_0099c-tab.005"><head rend="bold">Following countries were included in this survey:</head><row><cell/></row></table></div1><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="underlined bold">Question 2:</hi><hi rend="italic">Does the weakening of US Dollar against the Euro help US to reduce her trade deficit?</hi> </head><list type="bulleted"><head rend="bold">The web pages to be considered are:</head><item><seg type="URL" n="http://washingtontimes.com/commentary/20041130-084446-4947r.htm"/></item><item><seg type="URL" n="http://www.voanews.com/english/2004-12-01-voa3.cfm"/></item><item><seg type="URL" n="http://www.bloomberg.com/apps/news?pid=10000087&amp;sid=abIxJUVppx1A&amp;refer=top_world_news"/></item><item><seg type="URL" n="http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/business/3999825.stm"/></item><item><seg type="URL" n="http://www.boston.com/news/globe/editorial_opinion/oped/articles/2004/12/01/the_amazing_shrinking_dollar/"/></item></list><p n="p12.15"><s n="s1.6;p12.15">All the above sources seem to be reliable sources of information. </s><s n="s2.6;p12.15">The Washington Times is a known newspaper, and should contain relevant information, at least from the American point of view. </s><s n="s3.6;p12.15">BBC web page includes information from European perspective, but not from the Euro zone itself. </s><s n="s4.6;p12.15">Voice of America and Bloomberg sites are both American, pages for people interested in current issues in financial sector. </s><s n="s5.6;p12.15">All the pages, apart from BBC, were last updated on December 1 <hi rend="sup">st</hi>, and therefore all of them should have had accessed the most recent available data to write their articles. </s><s n="s6.6;p12.15">The BBC website was last updated on 10 <hi rend="sup">th</hi> November, but that particular article is still relevant to this topic, the issue of US trade deficit is not one of short term. </s></p><p n="p13.15"><s n="s1.5;p13.15">The US trade deficit exceeded 50bn USD for fourth month in a row in September.<ref target="BAWE_0099c-ftnote.001"/> About a month later Euro exceeded 1.30 Dollars, being 1.3334 Dollars on 30 <hi rend="sup">th</hi> of November. </s><s n="s2.5;p13.15">A strong euro has raised economic fears in Europe, where exporters want the dollar to stay strong to boost their international competitiveness.<ref target="BAWE_0099c-ftnote.002"/> As Euro gets more expensive in terms of Dollars, European goods will be more expensive. </s><s n="s3.5;p13.15">As a result of this the US customers will not buy as many European goods, and the US money paid abroad will get smaller, i.e. the US trade deficit gets smaller. </s><s n="s4.5;p13.15">Also weaker Dollar will make US goods cheaper for foreign markets, and as a result, US firms will collect more revenues. </s><s n="s5.5;p13.15">Raising the cost to us of foreign goods and lowering the cost of American goods to foreigners, should reduce imports and increase exports<ref target="BAWE_0099c-ftnote.003"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0099c-ftnote.001"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1"><seg type="URL" n="http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/business/3999825.stm"/> </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0099c-ftnote.002"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0099c-ftnote.003"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1"><seg type="URL" n="http://washingtontimes.com/commentary/20041130-084446-4947r.htm"/> </s></p></note><p n="p14.15"><s n="s1.2;p14.15">However, it may be that the weakening Dollar in comparison to Euro is not enough to reduce the US trade deficit, which counts to 6% of the GDP by now and is rising.<ref target="BAWE_0099c-ftnote.004"/> China keeps its currency pegged to the dollar, so a cheaper dollar doesn't improve our trade balance with the Chinese. </s><s n="s2.2;p14.15">It seems that Japanese automobile producers adjust their prices as Dollar falls in comparison to other currencies, so Japanese producers will keep their share in the US car market, using the "price to market" principle.<ref target="BAWE_0099c-ftnote.005"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0099c-ftnote.004"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1"><seg type="URL" n="http://www.voanews.com/english/2004-12-01-voa3.cfm"/> </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0099c-ftnote.005"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1"><seg type="URL" n="http://www.boston.com/news/globe/editorial_opinion/oped/articles/2004/12/01/the_amazing_shrinking_dollar/"/> </s></p></note><p n="p15.15"><s n="s1.4;p15.15">As can be seen from the data above, the decline of Dollar against Euro, will make European goods less attractive in the US market, and hence have a negative effect on the European economy and possible positive effect on US trade deficit. </s><s n="s2.4;p15.15">However, some criticism occurs against the view, that declining Dollar would solve the problem altogether. </s><s n="s3.4;p15.15">Other aspects, such as interest rates, foreign investment to US markets, and the interests paid abroad as a result of this have to be considered as well. </s><s n="s4.4;p15.15">As Dollar declines, European economy faces threat of further decline, but it is not said, that the US trade deficit would fall. </s></p></div1></body><back/></text></TEI.2>
