<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_0103a" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>The Making of a Vertebrate Limb</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">Language used in quote: <foreign id="English">English</foreign></note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">deleted: header: student and page numbers
deleted: Word count: 3000
</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">3</p><p n="date">2005-11</p><p n="module title">Development</p><p n="module code">BS301</p><p n="genre family">Explanation</p><p n="discipline">Biological Sciences</p><p n="disciplinary group">LS</p><p n="grade">D</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">5151</p><p n="number of s-units">150</p><p n="number of p">68</p><p n="number of tables">2</p><p n="number of figures">5</p><p n="number of block quotes">1</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">0</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">0</p><p n="abstract present">abstract present</p><p n="average words per s-unit">34.3</p><p n="average s-units per p">2.2</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">f</p><p n="year of birth">1985</p><p n="first language">French</p><p n="education">OSA</p><p n="course">Biological Sciences with Cell Biology</p><p n="student ID">0103</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><docTitle><titlePart rend="bold">The making of a vertebrate limb</titlePart></docTitle></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="abstract"><head rend="underlined bold">Abstract:</head><p n="p1.68"><s n="s1.1;p1.68">Formation of the vertebrate limb requires specification of cell position along 3 axes: the proximal-distal axis, the antero-posterior axis and the dorso-ventral axis. </s></p><p n="p2.68"><s n="s1.2;p2.68">These 3 axes are governed by signalling centres: the apical ectodermal ridge and the progress zone for the proximal distal elements, the polarizing activity region for the antero-posterior axis and the overlying ectoderm that determines the dorso-ventral axis. </s><s n="s2.2;p2.68">These signalling centres emanate proteins which cross-talk linking the formation of each axis to each other. </s></p><p n="p3.68"><s n="s1.3;p3.68">A decade of intensive studies has identified some signals that pattern the different axes. </s><s n="s2.3;p3.68">The apical ectodermal ridge releases Fibroblast growth fators (Fgfs) in particular Fgf- 4 and Fgf-8 which mimic it if removed. </s><s n="s3.3;p3.68">Fgf-8 is also involved in the formation of the fore and hind limb formation as it forms a feedback loop with Fgf-10 mediated by Wnt3a, which is induced by Tbx 5 and 4 via Wnt2b and Wnt8c respectively. </s></p><p n="p4.68"><s n="s1.2;p4.68">The polarizing activity region releases Sonic Hegdhog (Shh), a limb morphogen, which is induced by Gli3 a protein implicated in human Greig cephalopolysyndactyly syndrome, which forms a feedback loop (mediated by Formin, Gremlin, a Bmp antagonist and of course Bmp) with Fgf-8 and Fgf-4. </s><s n="s2.2;p4.68">Sonic Hedgehog is also induced by dHand, a transcription factor, and in the forelimb by Hoxb8. </s></p><p n="p5.68"><s n="s1.3;p5.68">However, dorso-ventral patterning is very different as it does not rely on a gradient of expression but more on an ON/OFF system. </s><s n="s2.3;p5.68">Wnt7a, another member of the Wnt family, is restricted to the dorsal region by Engrailed1 and induces the expression of <hi rend="italic">Lmx1</hi> without β-catenin dependent activity to specify the dorsal fate. </s><s n="s3.3;p5.68">It is also required for maintenance of Shh and thus Fgf signalling. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">Introduction:</head><quote lang="English"><hi rend="italic">"What can be more curious than the hand of a man, formed for grasping, that a mole for digging, the leg of a horse, the paddle of the porpoise, and the wing of the bat should all be constructed on the same pattern and should include similar bones, and in the same relative positions?"</hi> Darwin(1859).</quote><p n="p6.68"><s n="s1.3;p6.68">This quote from Charles Darwin highlights the intrigue that is the making of the vertebrate limb and how it has been conserved in evolution and between the different vertebrates. </s><s n="s2.3;p6.68">This is an extremely complex organ, which is not necessary for embryonic survival (therefore makes it a fantastic candidate for studying how structures develop in the right places in the embryo), is initiated when the vertebrate body plan is being mapped out and finished when the precise array of organised cells and tissues have been generated. </s><s n="s3.3;p6.68">The question the developmental biologists seek to answer is: how is the vertebrate limb made? </s></p><p n="p7.68"><s n="s1.2;p7.68">Limb patterning is established along 3 dimensions: the proximal-distal axis which consists in the replacement of the initial cartilage by bone and accompanied by the rises of the stylopod (humerus/femur), zeugopod (radius, ulna/ tibia and fibula) and autopod (carpal fingers/ankle and toes). </s><s n="s2.2;p7.68">The second axis is the anterior-posterior axis (thumb to little finger) and finally the third one is the dorsal-ventral axis (knuckles/palm respectively). </s></p><p n="p8.68"><s n="s1.1;p8.68">Figure 1 represents a schematic diagram of these 3 axes and a recapitulatory of all the terms and their definitions used in this review can be viewed in the end table. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0103a-pic.001"><head>Figure 1. The 3 dimensional patterns of the development of a limb. The ventral side can not be seen in this figure as it is viewed from the dorsal side. Adapted from Gilbert, 2003. </head></figure><p n="p9.68"><s n="s1.1;p9.68">In order to analyse the making of a vertebrate limb, the 3 different pattern of development must be discussed. </s></p><div2><head rend="bold">I) Generation of the proximal-distal axis in the vertebrate limb</head><div3><head rend="underlined">A) Apical ectodermal function and Fibroblast Growth Factor (FGF) roles</head><p n="p10.68"><s n="s1.4;p10.68">The proximal - distal axis is patterned through an organizing centre known as the apical ectodermal ridge (AER). </s><s n="s2.4;p10.68">This self-perpetuating structure forms at the boundary between the dorsal and ventral ectoderm (Niswander, 2003). </s><s n="s3.4;p10.68">It becomes visible as a continuous epithelial layer protruding from the distal tip of the limb bud. </s><s n="s4.4;p10.68">This structure can be viewed in figure 2. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0103a-pic.002"><head>Figure 2. Localization of the apical ectodermal ridge. Source: Niswander, 2003.</head></figure><p n="p11.68"><s n="s1.3;p11.68">AER formation involves 3 steps. </s><s n="s2.3;p11.68">Precursors are first induced; they then spread over a large area of ectoderm. </s><s n="s3.3;p11.68">Following their migration, they are concentrated at the dorso-ventral junction of the limb bud and this defines the compaction step (see section III) (Tickle, 2004; Niswander, 2003). </s></p><p n="p12.68"><s n="s1.1;p12.68">Following experiments in which the entire ridge was removed and resulted in the cessation of outgrowth and a truncated limb, it was concluded that this organization centre is critical for the developing limb and each step mentioned is mediated by key signal which will be discussed later (Mahmood <hi rend="italic">et al</hi>., 1995; Niswander <hi rend="italic">et al</hi>., 1993; Niswander, 2003). </s></p><p n="p13.68"><s n="s1.1;p13.68">Subadjacent to it is a region of mesenchyme (see end table for definition) which contains undifferentiated progenitors of the limb skeletal elements and called the progress zone. </s></p><p n="p14.68"><s n="s1.1;p14.68">Two models have been proposed to explain the specification of proximal-distal elements: the progress zone model and the early specification model. </s></p><p n="p15.68"><s n="s1.1;p15.68">A comparison of the two models is shown in figure 3. </s></p><p n="p16.68"><s n="s1.2;p16.68">Another region of mesenchyme caudal and proximal to the progress zone is the polarizing region which is the source of polarizing activity. </s><s n="s2.2;p16.68">This zone was defined following experiments which resulted in mirror image digit duplications (see figure 4 for a representation of these interacting regions). </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0103a-fig.001"><head>Figure 3. The progress zone model (at the top) versus the early specification model (at the bottom) proposed by Dudley <hi rend="italic">et al</hi> . Interaction between the AER and the progress zone was discovered through the removal of the ridge at progressive stages which resulted in more distal limbs truncation (Niswander, 2003). This observation led to the proposal of the progress zone model which states that the length of time mesenchyme cells spend in the progress zone determines the positional value they acquire, in other words distal or proximal (Niswander, 2003; Tickle, 2004). Although it is the most popular model, an alternative model has been suggested by Dudley <hi rend="italic">et al</hi> in 2002 to explain the phenotype that results from AER removal: all proximal-distal fates are already specified in the early bud and the role of AER is to promote expansion and differentiation of the different limb elements in a proximal-distal sequence. The stylopod precursor is represented in blue, the zeugopod precursor in black and the autopod precursor in red. The shaded zone represents the progress zone. Source: Torres <hi rend="italic">et al</hi> ., 2002; Tickle and Wolpert, 2002.</head></figure><figure id="BAWE_0103a-pic.003"><head>Figure 4. Organisation of the zones of interactions: Apical ectodermal ridge, progress zone and polarizing region. The progress zone is underlying the apical ectodermal ridge. The polarizing region is subadjacent to the AER. Source: adapted from Niswander <hi rend="italic">et al</hi> ., 1993.</head></figure><p n="p17.68"><s n="s1.3;p17.68">AER function is specified by the fibroblast growth factors (Fgfs). </s><s n="s2.3;p17.68">It is a gene family containing 15 known members that encode heparin-binding proteins which most of them are secreted constitutively. </s><s n="s3.3;p17.68">They are essential for the induction of the mesoderm, vascularization and maintenance of the ridge. </s></p><p n="p18.68"><s n="s1.1;p18.68">These genes were identified to encode the outgrowth signals as beads soaked in Fgf could substitute for the apical ectodermal ridge and sustain limb bud outgrowth (Niswander <hi rend="italic">et al</hi>., 1993; Tickle, 2004; Mahmood <hi rend="italic">et al</hi>., 1995). </s></p><p n="p19.68"><s n="s1.2;p19.68">Two protein members seem to be more involved than the others: Fgf-4 and Fgf-8. </s><s n="s2.2;p19.68">Although these proteins have the same overall effect, their signal transduction pathway differs greatly. </s></p><p n="p20.68"><s n="s1.2;p20.68">Fgf-8, previously identified as androgen-induced growth factor, is believed to be the most divergent member of the family since its amino acid sequence shows the least similarity than the others. </s><s n="s2.2;p20.68">It therefore probably regulates developmental processes not previously associated with Fgfs (Mahmood <hi rend="italic">et al</hi>., 1995). </s></p><p n="p21.68"><s n="s1.2;p21.68"><hi rend="italic">Fgf-8</hi> is expressed in all three germ layers and in 2 neuromeric boundary regions of the brain (Mahmood <hi rend="italic">et al</hi>., 1995). </s><s n="s2.2;p21.68">Its expression in those regions suggests that it might affect morphogenetic movements or cell adhesive processes that help to establish the initial number of cell in the early limb bud and the also play a role in spatial organization (Mahmood <hi rend="italic">et al</hi>., 1995; Niswander, 2003). </s></p><p n="p22.68"><s n="s1.1;p22.68">Interestingly, the use of whole-mount RNA in situ hybridization, has detected <hi rend="italic">Fgf-8</hi> RNA in nephrogenic mesoderm cells adjacent to the Wolfian duct prior to their differentiation, suggesting that its expression is linked to embryonic kidney development and has very important role in tubulogenesis (Crossley <hi rend="italic">et al</hi>., 1996). </s></p><p n="p23.68"><s n="s1.4;p23.68">However, the most striking role of Fgf-8 is in its involvement in AER derived mitogenic activity that regulates limb bud outgrowth (see section B). </s><s n="s2.4;p23.68">This was stated due to its presence in the ectoderm of limb bud prior to the onset of limb bud growth in both mouse and chicken embryos. </s><s n="s3.4;p23.68">However, it is not sufficient to induce a limb; it probably acts in conjunction with other determinants such as retinoic acid or other <hi rend="italic">Hox</hi> genes. </s><s n="s4.4;p23.68">It is also involved in the compaction step of the ridge formation (Niswander, 2003). </s></p><p n="p24.68"><s n="s1.4;p24.68">This protein signals through Fgfr2, which belongs to the fibroblast growth factor receptor family. </s><s n="s2.4;p24.68">This is a group of four transmembrane proteins with intrinsic tyrosine kinase activity (Xu <hi rend="italic">et al</hi>., 1998). </s><s n="s3.4;p24.68">They all share common features (they are listed in table 1 along with their role) and all have the same signalling pathway. </s><s n="s4.4;p24.68">See figure 5 for a schematic representation. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0103a-fig.002"><head>Figure 5. Schematic representation of the Fgfrs signalling. The FGFs induce formation of receptor homodimers. The dimerisation activates the receptor in each monomer, by undergoing mutual phosphorylation, (each subunit phosphorylates multiple tyrosine residues on the other subunit), which subsequently provides binding sites for target proteins such as protein phosphatases, protein tyrosine kinases and many more. These target proteins, in this case, an adaptor protein binds to the phosphorylated residues via its SH2 domain (these are independent structures found in many proteins). The adaptor protein also contains 2 SH3 domains and binds to the GEF, which activates ras (attached to the membrane through its farnesyl group). Ras then binds to MAPK3 (mitogen activate protein kinase 3), activating the MAP kinase cascade. The overall result is growth and cell differentiation. Adapted from Davey, 2005.</head></figure><p n="p25.68"><s n="s1.3;p25.68">But the most important domain is the immunoglobulin (Ig) like domain. </s><s n="s2.3;p25.68">Deletion of this domain or inactivation using a Cre recombinase uncouples the interaction between Fgf-8 and Fgf-10 (which defines the reciprocal regulation loop) resulting in limbless embryos (Xu <hi rend="italic">et al</hi>., 1998). </s><s n="s3.3;p25.68">It is therefore critical for Fgf binding and for normal Fgfr2 activity. </s></p><p n="p26.68"><s n="s1.1;p26.68">Figure 6 represents a schematic diagram of this interaction. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0103a-pic.004"><head>Figure 6. Reciprocal regulation loop during limb induction. As stated earlier on, <hi rend="italic">Fgf-10</hi> is required for limb outgrowth and its expression on the mesenchyme precedes <hi rend="italic">Fgf-8</hi> expression (Moon and Capecchi, 2000; Xu <hi rend="italic">et al</hi> ., 1998). Fgfr2IIIb, a major isoform of the receptor, is localized to the surface ectoderm and interacts with Fgf-10 (cells expressing Fgfr2IIIb proliferate due to promotion by Fgf-10) and induces <hi rend="italic">Fgf-8</hi> expression. Reduction of the expression of <hi rend="italic">Fgf-8</hi> results in a decreased <hi rend="italic">Fgf10</hi> expression in both the anterior and posterior extremes of the mesenchyme (Moon and Capecchi, 2000). This shows that Fgf-8 signalling in turn positively regulates <hi rend="italic">Fgf-10</hi> . FGF-8 does so by interacting with Fgfr2IIIc, which is expressed in the adjacent mesoderm, induces and maintains Shh (Crossley et al., 1996). However, the latter statement clashes with results from Mahmood <hi rend="italic">et al</hi> . (1995) in which addition of the protein after removal of the ridge failed to maintain <hi rend="italic">Shh</hi> expression in the posterior mesoderm. A possible explanation of this discrepancy is that different Fgf-8 isoforms have different functions in vivo (different isoforms were used in each experiments). Source: Adapted from Xu <hi rend="italic">et al</hi> ., 1998 and Niswander <hi rend="italic">et al</hi> ., 1993.<hi rend="bold">Note:</hi> Fgfr2 is not only limited to limb induction, it is also essential for placental formation. Defect in Fgfr2 results in a block in the trophoblast cell proliferation and the outcome is a failure in labyrinthine portion of placenta (Xu <hi rend="italic">et al</hi> ., 1998).</head></figure><p n="p27.68"><s n="s1.5;p27.68">A characteristic that differentiates Fgf-4 from Fgf-8 is the receptor it binds to. </s><s n="s2.5;p27.68">Fgf-4 binds to Fgfr-1, which is expressed in mesenchyme. </s><s n="s3.5;p27.68">Fgf-4 is efficiently secreted from cells and along with Fgf-9 and Fgf-17 is expressed in the posterior part of the ridge (Niswander <hi rend="italic">et al</hi>., 1993; Tickle, 2004). </s><s n="s4.5;p27.68">Fgf-4 can also substitute for the ridge but although the limb develops completely, there are a few digit abnormalities. </s><s n="s5.5;p27.68">This suggests that Fgf-4 does not perform the mechanical function of the ridge (Niswander <hi rend="italic">et al</hi>., 1993). </s></p><p n="p28.68"><s n="s1.2;p28.68"><hi rend="italic">Fgf-4</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Fgf-8</hi> do show redundancy as Fgf-4 also maintains <hi rend="italic">Shh</hi> expression (See section II). </s><s n="s2.2;p28.68">This property is also shared with Fgf-9 and Fgf-17. </s></p><p n="p29.68"><s n="s1.2;p29.68">Nonetheless, this redundancy is partial as in <hi rend="italic">Fgf-4</hi> conditional mutants, the limb forms normally showing that <hi rend="italic">Fgf-4</hi> is not essential for limb induction (Niswander, 2003). </s><s n="s2.2;p29.68">Another feature in which Fgf-8 differs from Fgf-4 is that the latter is critical for the progress zone cell proliferation (Niswander <hi rend="italic">et al</hi>., 1993). </s></p><table id="BAWE_0103a-tab.001"><head>Table 1. Concise depiction of the fibroblast growth factor receptor family. Source: Xu <hi rend="italic">et al</hi> ., 1998 and information hyperlinked protein website (<seg type="URL" n="http://www.ihop-net.org/UniPub/iHOP/gs/88210.html"/>)</head><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p30.68"><s n="s1.3;p30.68">There are 3 hypotheses that relate Fgf signalling to the proximal-distal patterning: according to the progress zone model, Fgf signalling could be related to a developmental clock based on oscillations, as cells leave the progress zone, they leave Fgf influence. </s><s n="s2.3;p30.68">Another hypothesis is that there is continuous interaction between the mesenchyme and the AER throughout limb but outgrowth, leading to increasing levels of Fgf production and that these levels specify the proximo-distal fate. </s><s n="s3.3;p30.68">And finally, a possible explanation that specifies a role of Fgfs in the Dudley <hi rend="italic">et al</hi> model is that Fgfs form a gradient, by diffusing Fgfs from the ridge, which specifies position along the proximal-distal axis (Tickle, 2004). </s></p><p n="p31.68"><s n="s1.1;p31.68">Once the Fgfs have performed their role, they are down - regulated, mesenchyme proliferation ceases and the apical ectodermal ridge regresses, returning to a flattened epithelium (Niswander, 2003). </s></p></div3><div3><head rend="underlined">B) The formation of the limb bud and the identification of the hind and forelimbs. </head><p n="p32.68"><s n="s1.3;p32.68">Limb bud induction occurs progressively and at different stages in different tetrapods. </s><s n="s2.3;p32.68">It first begins when mesenchyme cells proliferate from the somatic layer of the limb field lateral plate mesoderm and from the somites. </s><s n="s3.3;p32.68">These cells to accumulate under the ectodermal tissue to create a circular bulge: the limb bud (Gilbert, 2003). </s></p><p n="p33.68"><s n="s1.1;p33.68">Limb induction engages 3 distinct gene families: the <hi rend="italic">Fibroblast growth factor</hi> family, the <hi rend="italic">Wnt</hi> family and the <hi rend="italic">Tbx</hi> family. </s></p><p n="p34.68"><s n="s1.1;p34.68">From the <hi rend="italic">Fgf</hi> family, 2 actors impose themselves: <hi rend="italic">Fgf-10</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Ffg-8</hi> as seen above. </s></p><p n="p35.68"><s n="s1.4;p35.68">Fgf-10 protein has various roles, and is not only limited to limb bud induction: it's a brain regulator and it is required for lung formation (Sekine <hi rend="italic">et al</hi>., 1999). </s><s n="s2.4;p35.68">The latter was suggested due following <hi rend="italic">Fgf-10</hi> deficient mice that were generated using embryonic stem cells in which a targeting vector construct had replaced <hi rend="italic">Fgf-10</hi> exon. </s><s n="s3.4;p35.68">The resulting mice died shortly after birth: they were fore and hind limbness as the limb bud had been initiated but did not outgrowth and displayed pulmonary branching morphogenesis disruption (Sekine <hi rend="italic">et al</hi>., 1999). </s><s n="s4.4;p35.68">Like stated above, it has to interact with Fgf-8 in order to induce a limb. </s></p><p n="p36.68"><s n="s1.1;p36.68">Recent work has however updated the reciprocal regulation loop. </s></p><p n="p37.68"><s n="s1.1;p37.68">Three members have now emerged as to mediate the interaction between Fgf-8 and Fgf-10 as Fgfs do not diffuse very far and when a Fgf-8 soaked bead is implanted in the flank, it takes as long as 17hr to induce Fgf-10 expression in the surface ectoderm in the lateral plate mesoderm contrasting with the rapid activation of other limb genes in response to Fgf beads. </s></p><p n="p38.68"><s n="s1.3;p38.68">The first mediator is <hi rend="italic">Wnt-2b</hi>, a member of the <hi rend="italic">Wnt</hi> family , showed by whole-mount in situ hybridization of embryos to be expressed (and restricted) in the chick wing region (forelimb) and to act upstream of <hi rend="italic">Fgf-10</hi> in the lateral plate mesoderm during limb initiation (Kawakami <hi rend="italic">et al</hi>., 2001). </s><s n="s2.3;p38.68">The second mediator detected by a similar experiment is <hi rend="italic">Wnt8c</hi> which is expressed in the leg (hind limb) and acts as a regulator of <hi rend="italic">Fgf-10</hi> expression in the lateral plate mesoderm of the hind limb region (Kawakami <hi rend="italic">et al</hi>., 2001). </s><s n="s3.3;p38.68">And finally, the 3 <hi rend="sup">rd</hi> mediator appears to be implicated in the reciprocal regulation loop. </s></p><p n="p39.68"><s n="s1.1;p39.68">These intermediate factors all have activities that are β-catenin dependent: when β-catenin is blocked in both the fore and hind limbs forming regions (using axin, a negative regulator of the Wnt pathway, which was over expressed using an adenoviral vector) limb development is impaired (Tickle and Münsterberg, 2001; Kawakami <hi rend="italic">et al</hi>., 2001). </s></p><p n="p40.68"><s n="s1.1;p40.68">The third family that is critical for fore and hind limb development is the <hi rend="italic">Tbx</hi> family. </s></p><p n="p41.68"><s n="s1.4;p41.68">This family of gene encodes T-box transcription factors with the T-box domain binding DNA as a dimer (Rodriguez-Esteban <hi rend="italic">et al</hi>., 1999; Rallis <hi rend="italic">et al</hi>., 2003). </s><s n="s2.4;p41.68">Two members are specifically expressed in the hind and fore limb buds: <hi rend="italic">Tbx 5</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Tbx4</hi>. </s><s n="s3.4;p41.68">These appear to be the most upstream factors in limb initiation. </s><s n="s4.4;p41.68">This is supported by 3 lines of evidence: mice carrying a null mutation in <hi rend="italic">Tbx5</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Tbx4</hi> (using the Cre recombinase) failed to express <hi rend="italic">Fgf10</hi> in the fore limb and hind limb respectively (Takeuchi <hi rend="italic">et al</hi>., 2003; Rallis <hi rend="italic">et al</hi>., 2003), <hi rend="italic">Tbx5</hi> mutation in human causes Holt-Gram syndrome (a dominant disorder characterised by upper limb defects and heart abnormalities), and misexpression experiments using RCAS retroviral vector to produce <hi rend="italic">Tbx4</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Tbx5</hi> dominant-negative forms resulted in failure of wing and leg to form respectively (Takeuchi <hi rend="italic">et al</hi>., 2003). </s></p><p n="p42.68"><s n="s1.1;p42.68">Recent work has also shown that there is a regulatory loop between Hox9 and Tbx for both limb initiation and the wing/leg identity specification (Takeuchi <hi rend="italic">et al</hi>., 2003). </s></p><p n="p43.68"><s n="s1.1;p43.68">Figure 7 shows the expanded model of this reciprocal loop. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0103a-fig.003"><head>Figure 7: The updated version of the reciprocal loop between Fgf-10 and Fgf-8 resulting in the formation of the hind and fore limb. Adapted from Takeuchi <hi rend="italic">et al</hi> ., 2003; Gilbert, 2003; Tickle and Mü nsterberg, 2001; Kawakami <hi rend="italic">et al</hi> ., 2001, Niswander, 2003.</head></figure></div3></div2><div2><head rend="underlined bold">II) The establishment of the anterior-posterior axis</head><div3><head rend="underlined">A) Front line</head><p n="p44.68"><s n="s1.5;p44.68">Normal antero-posterior patterning in the limb depends on the zone of polarizing activity. </s><s n="s2.5;p44.68">This crucial signalling centre releases a number of signals (Niswander, 2003). </s><s n="s3.5;p44.68">The first identified signal, using whole-mount in situ hybridization is Sonic hedgehog (Shh) protein, which has the main attribute of the limb morphogen in that it acts by forming a gradient across the early bud and is diffusible (Tickle, 2004; Riddle <hi rend="italic">et al</hi>., 1993). </s><s n="s4.5;p44.68">Degenerate polymerase chain reaction primers corresponding to a sequence highly conserved between drosophila <hi rend="italic">Hedgehog</hi> (produced by a set of cells in the posterior of each segment) and mouse <hi rend="italic">desert Hedgehog</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Dhh</hi>) was used to amplify and screen an amplified cDNA library. </s><s n="s5.5;p44.68">This resulted in the isolation of a 16.6kb cDNA clone whose gene was name <hi rend="italic">Shh</hi> (Riddle <hi rend="italic">et al</hi>., 1993). </s></p><p n="p45.68"><s n="s1.4;p45.68">Its attribute as a morphogen arises from graft experiments in which small blocks of limb tissue were grafted to the anterior of host limb buds and the strength of the ZPA activity was quantified according to the degrees of digit duplication to determine the extent of correlation between the spatial and temporal pattern of ZPA activity and <hi rend="italic">Shh</hi> expression (Riddle <hi rend="italic">et al</hi>., 1993). </s><s n="s2.4;p45.68">The outcome of this experiment was that Shh signalling is pivotal in controlling both digit number and identity (Tickle, 2004). </s><s n="s3.4;p45.68">Further evidence support this statement as application of <hi rend="italic">Shh</hi> expressing cells or recombinant Shh protein to the anterior of the chick limb bud causes mirror-image digit duplications of the type: 4-3-3-4 and 4-3-2-2-3-4 (Niswander, 2003; Riddle <hi rend="italic">et al</hi>., 1993). </s><s n="s4.4;p45.68">Figure 8 shows these mirror- image duplications. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0103a-pic.005"><head>Figure 8: Mirror image duplications seen in chick embryos. A: the normal digit pattern. B and D: the 4-3-2-2-3-4 digit pattern. C: the 4-3-3-4 digit pattern. Source: Koyama <hi rend="italic">et al</hi> ., 1996</head></figure><p n="p46.68"><s n="s1.4;p46.68">The patterning effects of Shh signalling require <hi rend="italic">Gli3</hi> (Gene implicated in human Greig cephalopolysyndactyly syndrome ) (Litingtung <hi rend="italic">et al</hi>., 2002; Niswander, 2003). </s><s n="s2.4;p46.68"><hi rend="italic">Gli3</hi>-/- embryos display polydactyly (which has been attributed to ectopic <hi rend="italic">Shh</hi> expression in the early stage mesoderm of the anterior limb bud) and surprisingly <hi rend="italic">Gli3-/- Shh-/-</hi> double mutants also have numerous digits with a normal stylopod and zeugopod. </s><s n="s3.4;p46.68">This suggests that the default state of the limb is to form many digits and that those 2 genes and their transcripts repress the polydactylous capacity of the autopod. </s><s n="s4.4;p46.68">In other words, Shh and Gli3 are required for digit identity, not the formation of the limb; and the type of digit that develops in a particular position depends on the signalling strength (Lintingtung <hi rend="italic">et al</hi>., 2002; Niswander, 2003; Tickle, 2004). </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0103a-pic.006"><head>Figure 9. <hi rend="italic">Gli3</hi> -/- and <hi rend="italic">Gli3-/- Shh-/-</hi> limbs. Source: <seg type="URL" n="http://www.sciencemag.org/cgi/content/summary/298/5594/699i"/></head></figure><p n="p47.68"><s n="s1.3;p47.68">The Gli3 processed form acts as a repressor (Gli3R) and the unprocessed form acts as an activator. </s><s n="s2.3;p47.68">The relative ratio of Gli3A: Gli3R is crucial in Shh signalling (Niswander, 2003; Litingtung <hi rend="italic">et al</hi>., 2002). </s><s n="s3.3;p47.68">Defects in Shh signalling can be seen in <hi rend="italic">talpid</hi><hi rend="sup">2</hi> and <hi rend="italic">talpid</hi><hi rend="sup">3</hi> mutant which express high Gli3A:Gli3R levels across the anterior/posterior axis supporting the model described above (Tickle, 2004; Litintung <hi rend="italic">et al</hi>., 2002). </s></p><p n="p48.68"><s n="s1.4;p48.68">Upstream of <hi rend="italic">Shh</hi> lie <hi rend="italic">Hoxb8</hi> and <hi rend="italic">dHAND.Hoxb8</hi>, member of the <hi rend="italic">Hox</hi> gene family, plays an important role in specifying the antero-posterior axis (Gilbert, 2003; Stratford <hi rend="italic">et al</hi>., 1997). </s><s n="s2.4;p48.68">It appears to be induced by Retinoic acid (Retinal is oxidised to retinoic acid by retinaldehyde dehydrogenase2- Raldh2) as embryos treated with disulphiram (which inhibits RA synthesis) showed severe Hoxb8 down-regulation (Stratford <hi rend="italic">et al</hi>., 1997) within particular regions of the forelimb mesoderm and is not detected in the hind limb. </s><s n="s3.4;p48.68">Conclusion, Hoxb8 only induces Shh in the anterior forelimb. </s><s n="s4.4;p48.68">Interestingly, grafting and removal experiments showed that Hoxb8 is inhibited by the established zone of polarizing activity and by the anterior AER (figure 10). </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0103a-pic.007"><head>Figure 10. Graft experiments for activity of Hoxb8. A piece of ZPA from a stage 21 forelimb was grafted under the apical ectodermal ridge at the anterior margin (left). <hi rend="italic">Hoxb-8</hi> expression was not detectable in either the graft or the anterior mesoderm, even when retinoic acid bead was added (white arrowhead) (right). Adapted from Stratford <hi rend="italic">et al</hi> ., 1997; Tanaka <hi rend="italic">et al</hi> ., 2000.</head></figure><p n="p49.68"><s n="s1.1;p49.68">However, Shh signalling affects downstream targets as well. </s></p></div3><div3><head rend="underlined">B) Downstream of Shh</head><p n="p50.68"><s n="s1.1;p50.68">The vertebrate limb bud organizer patterns the anterior-posterior axis by generating differences through extracellular antagonism signalling (Zuñiga <hi rend="italic">et al</hi>., 1999). </s></p><p n="p51.68"><s n="s1.2;p51.68">As stated, there is a feedback loop between the ZPA region and the AER in which Fgf-4 and Shh form the reciprocal regulation loop with Shh normally maintaining Fgf-4 expression which in turns maintains Shh expression in the posterior mesenchyme (Tickle, 2003). </s><s n="s2.2;p51.68">There are 3 main mediators of this feedback loop: Formin (Fmn), Gremlin (Gre) and Bone morphogenetic proteins (Bmp). </s></p><p n="p52.68"><s n="s1.2;p52.68"><hi rend="italic">Formin</hi> was first discovered as a downstream target of sonic hedgehog as in <hi rend="italic">Shh</hi> mutants, there are no <hi rend="italic">Fmn</hi> transcripts in the limb bud and in <hi rend="italic">ld</hi> (<hi rend="italic">limb deformity</hi>) mutant mice, the gene encoding Fmn is disrupted as well as the maintenance of the ridge and the Shh-Fgf feedback loop. </s><s n="s2.2;p52.68">Furthermore, anterior grafts of <hi rend="italic">Shh</hi> expressing cells induce ectopic <hi rend="italic">Formin</hi> expression in distal limb bud mesenchyme (Zuñiga <hi rend="italic">et al</hi>., 1999, Khokha <hi rend="italic">et al</hi>., 2003). </s></p><p n="p53.68"><s n="s1.4;p53.68">Downstream of <hi rend="italic">Formin</hi> there is <hi rend="italic">Gremlin</hi>, a member of the DAN/Cerberus gene family and an extracellular Bmp antagonist absolutely required in limb patterning (Khokha <hi rend="italic">et al</hi>., 2003). </s><s n="s2.4;p53.68">This was demonstrated by producing a null allele at the <hi rend="italic">Gremlin</hi> locus by replacing the open reading frame which lies in the exon with an in-frame fusion of LacZ to the sequence encoding the first five residues of Gremlin. </s><s n="s3.4;p53.68">Homozygous displayed a very obvious disturbed skeletal phenotype and died within 48hours of birth, <hi rend="italic">Fgf-4</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Fgf-8</hi> expression were reduced (they lacked kidneys, and as discussed, Fgf-8 is linked to embryonic kidney). </s><s n="s4.4;p53.68">This supports the model in which Gremlin is sufficient to induce the Fgf-Shh feedback loop (Zuñiga <hi rend="italic">et al</hi>., 1999, Khokha <hi rend="italic">et al</hi>., 2003). </s></p><p n="p54.68"><s n="s1.1;p54.68">Figure 11 is a model representing this regulation loop. </s></p><p n="p55.68"><s n="s1.1;p55.68">However, there is an alternative pathway which involves the same protagonists, except for Shh, (and is therefore termed the Shh-independent pathway), with the instigator being an unknown posterior activity (Zuñiga <hi rend="italic">et al</hi>., 1999; Niswander, 2003). </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0103a-fig.004"><head>Figure 11. Shh dependent pathway resulting in the anterior-posterior patterning. dHand is a transcription factor in the posterior region expressed immediately before <hi rend="italic">Shh</hi> and restricts <hi rend="italic">Shh</hi> expression to the posterior mesenchyme (Gilbert, 2003, Niswander, 2003). Source: Niswander, 2003; Zuñ iga <hi rend="italic">et al</hi> ., 1999. Note: For an overview of the Shh-independent pathway replace Shh by an unknown posterior activity (PA), and it is not induced by Hoxb8.</head></figure><p n="p56.68"><s n="s1.1;p56.68">This feedback loop shows that the making of a vertebrate limb involves cross-talking between the different axes. </s></p><p n="p57.68"><s n="s1.1;p57.68">In contrast with the molecular mechanisms involved in the establishment of the other axes, the formation of the dorso-ventral dimension appears to be straightforward. </s></p></div3></div2><div2><head rend="underlined bold">III) The mechanism of Dorso-ventral axis patterning</head><p n="p58.68"><s n="s1.1;p58.68">Studies of the molecular control of the dorso-ventral patterning has so far identified 2 central characters. </s></p><p n="p59.68"><s n="s1.4;p59.68"><hi rend="italic">Wnt7a</hi>, a member of the <hi rend="italic">Wnt</hi> family is expressed in the dorsal ectoderm, suggesting that it may play a role (Parr and McMahon, 1995; Riddle <hi rend="italic">et al</hi>., 1995). </s><s n="s2.4;p59.68">Indeed, loss of <hi rend="italic">Wnt7a</hi> function in mice, using gene targeting, results in the transformation of dorsal limb structures into ventral fates (Parr and McMahon, 1995; Riddle <hi rend="italic">et al</hi>., 1995). </s><s n="s3.4;p59.68">These are particularly distinguishable in distal limb structures. </s><s n="s4.4;p59.68">In addition, ectopic expression of <hi rend="italic">Wnt7a</hi> in ventral ectoderm leads to the acquisition of dorsal properties by the ventral mesoderm (Riddle <hi rend="italic">et al</hi>., 1995). </s></p><p n="p60.68"><s n="s1.1;p60.68">Figure 12 shows some of these penetrant phenotypes. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0103a-pic.008"><head>Figure 12. Different phenotypes resulting from loss of <hi rend="italic">Wnt7a</hi> gene and ectopic expression of <hi rend="italic">Wnt7a</hi> in ventral ectoderm. The photo on the right (at the top) shows the ventral skin of wild-type digits which can be compared to the <hi rend="italic">Wnt7a</hi> mutant ventral skin 2 weeks after birth (bottom right). It is quite obvious that the ventral side is not affected. It is clear that they are furless, have no pigments and exhibit a prominent set of striations. "Vp" indicates the ventral pads. In the middle, the dorsal half of the wild-type limb can be seen. This appears pigmented, covered in fur and does not possess sesamoid. On the left hand side, (at the top), the dorsal surface of mutant digits have less hair ad more striation and the dorsal surface of mutant limbs (at the bottom) display dermal thickening representing duplication of footpads normally found ventrally). Source : Adapted from Parr and McMahon, 1995.</head></figure><p n="p61.68"><s n="s1.5;p61.68"><hi rend="italic">Wnt7a</hi> induces the expression of <hi rend="italic">Lmx1</hi> and is sufficient to maintain its expression in disto-dorsal mesenchymal cells. </s><s n="s2.5;p61.68">This is supported by the fact that expression of <hi rend="italic">Wnt7a</hi> coincides with expression of <hi rend="italic">Lmx1</hi>. </s><s n="s3.5;p61.68"><hi rend="italic">Lmx1</hi> is a member of the LIM homeobox gene family which encodes protein with a pain of cysteine-histidine rich LIM domains and a homedomain (Riddle <hi rend="italic">et al</hi>., 1995). </s><s n="s4.5;p61.68">The presence or absence of their respective proteins appears to depict the organization of the limb into dorsal and ventral domains. </s><s n="s5.5;p61.68">In other words, the default state of the limb mesenchyme is ventral and Wnt7a and Lmx1 signalling result in the emergence of a dorsal pattern (Riddle <hi rend="italic">et al</hi>., 1995). </s></p><p n="p62.68"><s n="s1.4;p62.68">It follows that Wnt7a and Lmx1 signalling is not restricted to the dorso-ventral pattern. </s><s n="s2.4;p62.68">Indeed, the removal of the dorsal ectoderm or the loss of <hi rend="italic">Wnt7a</hi> by gene targeting causes a reduction or loss of <hi rend="italic">Shh</hi> expression. </s><s n="s3.4;p62.68">Moreover, loss of posterior skeletal elements and Fgf-4 expression in <hi rend="italic">Wnt7a-/- limbs</hi> supports the view that Wnt7a is also required in conjunction with Fgfs to maintain <hi rend="italic">Shh</hi> expression and thus A-P establishment (Niswander, 2003; Parr and McMahon, 1995; Riddle <hi rend="italic">et al</hi>., 1995). </s><s n="s4.4;p62.68">Phenotypes produced by these experimental manipulations can be seen in figure 13. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0103a-pic.009"><head>Figure 13. Effect of Wnt7a and Lmx1 mutation on the anterior-posterior pattern. The wild-type forelimb displays the humerus, ulna, and the radius. Note the absence of the humerus in the <hi rend="italic">Lmx1</hi> mutant, the absence of ulna, humerus and digits in the <hi rend="italic">Wnt7a</hi> mutant and the further reduction of digit number along with fusion of the humerus and ulna in the <hi rend="italic">Wnt7a-/-;-/-lmx1</hi> double mutant. Note: mutant limbs were obtained using gene targeting. Adapted from Parr and McMahon, 1995; Chen and Johnson, 2002.</head></figure><p n="p63.68"><s n="s1.3;p63.68">Although a Wnt protein, Wnt7a is not involved in AER formation and does not have a β-catenin dependent activity (Kengaku et al., 1998). </s><s n="s2.3;p63.68">Misexpression of an activated mutant form of β-catenin limb buds stimulated the effect of Wnt3a but not of Wnt7a. </s><s n="s3.3;p63.68">Furthermore, this resulted in ectopic expression of <hi rend="italic">Fgf-8</hi> and other AER markers such as <hi rend="italic">Fgf-4</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Bmp-2</hi> but not <hi rend="italic">Lmx1</hi>, the Wnt7a target (Kengaku <hi rend="italic">et al</hi>., 1998). </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0103a-fig.005"><head>Figure 13. The involvement of Wnt7a and Lmx1 in the formation of the vertebrate limb. Dorsal ventral distinctions in the mesoderm are established prior to limb bud initiation by information contained in the mesenchyme (Niswander, 2003; Riddle et al., 1995). Prior to limb bud formation, the mesenchyme transfers this information to the overlying ectoderm: the molecular nature of this early mesenchymal signal is unknown.<hi rend="italic">Wnt7a</hi> expression is initiated very early in the flanking ectoderm even before the earliest signs of ridge formation (Parr and McMahon, 1995; Tickle, 2004) and is restricted to the dorsal ectoderm because it is repressed in the ventral ectoderm by Bmp-2 and the transcription factor Engrailed 1 (En1). It is apparently maintained in the dorsal ectoderm throughout limb bud development and into digital plate stages (Niswander, 2003; Tickle, 2004). Wnt7a induces expression of <hi rend="italic">Lmx1</hi> in the underlying dorsal mesenchyme which dorsalizes the growing limb bud. An explanation for the early expression of <hi rend="italic">Wnt7a</hi> is its implication in the patterning of the A-P axis (Parr and McMahon, 1995; Niswander, 2003). Wnt7a along with Lmx1 targets <hi rend="italic">Shh</hi> for induction in the posterior mesenchyme, resulting in the initiation of the A-P pattern and the feedback loop between Shh and Fgfs, which maintains proximo-distal outgrowth (Niswander, 2003; Parr and McMahon, 1995). Source: Adapted from Niswander, 2003.</head></figure><p n="p64.68"><s n="s1.2;p64.68">What signal specifies the dorso-ventral border? </s><s n="s2.2;p64.68">It has yet to be identified but the dorso-ventral boundary can be clearly seen due to the presence of the apical ectodermal ridge (Rodriguez-Esteban <hi rend="italic">et al</hi>., 1997). </s></p><p n="p65.68"><s n="s1.2;p65.68">A gene called <hi rend="italic">Radical fringe</hi> (<hi rend="italic">R-fng</hi>) in the chick (it also homologous to Drosophila <hi rend="italic">fng</hi> gene) appears to direct formation and positioning of the ridge (Rodriguez-Esteban <hi rend="italic">et al</hi>., 1997). </s><s n="s2.2;p65.68">It is first expressed at the dorsal limb ectoderm and then at the dorso-ventral boundary to finally be expressed in the AER. </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">Conclusion:</head><p n="p66.68"><s n="s1.1;p66.68">The last ten years of research into this field has given insight into how all three axes are mutually linked to allow co-ordinated growth and patterning of the limb. </s></p><p n="p67.68"><s n="s1.3;p67.68">Several aspects remain in the dark such as the fact that Gli3 activity is not required for expression of the genes downstream of <hi rend="italic">Shh</hi>, however these genes are not sufficient to generate posterior digit identity (posterior pattern is not generated in the <hi rend="italic">Gli3-/-</hi> limbs despite intact levels of Shh signalling as shown by expression of genes downstream of <hi rend="italic">Shh</hi>). </s><s n="s2.3;p67.68">It is possible that another Gli family member fulfils this role or a different transcription factor. </s><s n="s3.3;p67.68">Another enigma is what are the downstream targets that translate the signals from the organizing centres into skeletal pattern? </s></p><p n="p68.68"><s n="s1.1;p68.68">And the greatest question is why some of the molecules involved have been conserved between vertebrates and invertebrates whereas others have been changed within a specific developmental program? </s></p><table id="BAWE_0103a-tab.002"><head>Definition table. Data taken from Niswander, 2003; Gilbert, 2003.</head><row><cell/></row></table></div1></body><back><div1 type="bibliography"><head rend="underlined bold">Bibliography</head><p>Gilbert, S. F. (2003). The making of a tetrapod limb. <hi rend="italic">Developmental biology</hi>. Sinauer. 7<hi rend="sup">th</hi> edition, 16.</p><p>Kawakami <hi rend="italic">et al</hi>., (2001). Wnt signals control FGF-dependent limb initiation and AER induction in the chick embryo. <hi rend="italic">Cell</hi>. 104, 891-900.</p><p>Kengaku <hi rend="italic">et al.,</hi> (1998). Distinct Wnt pathways regulating formation and dorsal/ventral polarity in the chick limb bud. <hi rend="italic">Science</hi>. 208, 1274-1277.</p><p>Khokha <hi rend="italic">et al</hi>., (2003). Gremlin is the BMP antagonist required for maintenance of SHH and Fgf signals during limb patterning. <hi rend="italic">Nature Genetics</hi>. 34, 303-307.</p><p>Litingtung <hi rend="italic">et al.,</hi> (2002). Shh and Gli3 are dispensible for limb skeleton formation but regulate digit number and identity. <hi rend="italic">Nature</hi>. 418, 979-983. </p><p>Mahmood <hi rend="italic">et al.,</hi> (1995). A role for FGF-8 in the initiation and maintenance of vertebrate limb bud outgrowth. <hi rend="italic">Current biology</hi>. 5, 797-806.</p><p>Moon <hi rend="italic">et al.,</hi> (2000). FGF8 is involved for outgrowth and patterning of the limbs. <hi rend="italic">Nature Genetics</hi>. 26, 455-459. </p><p>Niswander <hi rend="italic">et al</hi>., (1993). FGF-4 replaces the apical ectodermal ridge and directs outgrowth and patterning of the limb. <hi rend="italic">Cell</hi>. 75, 579-587. </p><p>Niswander, L., (2003). Pattern formation: Old models out on a limb. <hi rend="italic">Nature review genetics</hi>. 4, 133-143.</p><p> Parr and McMahon (1995). Dorsalising signal Wnt7a required for normal polarity of D/V and A/P axes mouse limb. <hi rend="italic">Nature</hi>. 374, 350-353.</p><p>Rallis <hi rend="italic">et al</hi>., (2003). Tbx is required for forelimb bud formation and continued outgrowth. <hi rend="italic">Development</hi>. 130, 2741-2751.</p><p>Riddle <hi rend="italic">et al</hi>., (1993). Sonic hedgehog mediates the polarizing activity of the ZPA. <hi rend="italic">Cell</hi>. 75, 1401-1416. </p><p>Riddle <hi rend="italic">et al</hi>., (1995). Induction of the LIM homebox gene <hi rend="italic">Lmx1</hi> by WNT7A establishes dorsoventral pattern in the vertebrate limb. <hi rend="italic">Cell</hi>. 83, 631-640. </p><p>Rodrigues-Esteban <hi rend="italic">et al</hi>., (1997). Radical fringe the apical ectodermal ridge at the dorsoventral boundary of the vertebrate limb. <hi rend="italic">Nature</hi>. 386, 360-366.</p><p>Rodrigues-Esteban <hi rend="italic">et al</hi>., (1999). The T-box genes <hi rend="italic">Tbx4</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Tbx5</hi> regulate limb outgrowth and identity. <hi rend="italic">Nature</hi>. 398, 814-818.</p><p>Sekine <hi rend="italic">et al</hi>., (1999). Fgf10 is essential for limb and lung formation. <hi rend="italic">Nature genetics</hi>.21, 138-141.</p><p>Stratford <hi rend="italic">et al.,</hi> (1997). Hoxb-8 has a role in establishing early anterior-posterior polarity in chick forelimb but not hind limb. <hi rend="italic">Development</hi>. 124, 4225-4234. </p><p>Takeuchi <hi rend="italic">et al</hi> (2003). Tbx5 and Tbx4 trigger limb formation through activation of the Wnt/Fgf signalling cascade. <hi rend="italic">Development</hi>. 130, 2729-2739.</p><p>Tickle, (2003). Patterning systems-from one end of the limb to the other. <hi rend="italic">Developmental cell</hi>. 4, 449-458.</p><p>Tickle, (2004). The contribution of chicken embryology to the understanding of vertebrate limb development. <hi rend="italic">Development.</hi> 121, 1019-1029. </p><p>Tickle and Munsterberg, (2001). Vertebrate limb development. <hi rend="italic">Current opinion genetic development</hi>. 11, 476-481.</p><p>Xu <hi rend="italic">et al</hi>., (1998). Fibroblast growth factor receptor 2(FGFR2) mediated reciprocal regulation loop between FGF8 and FGF10 is essential for limb induction. <hi rend="italic">Development</hi>, 125, 753-765.</p><p>Zuniga <hi rend="italic">et al.,</hi> (1999). Signal relay by BMP antagonism controls the Shh/Fgf4 feedback loop in vertebrate limb buds. <hi rend="italic">Nature.</hi> 401, 598-602.</p></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
