<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_0103b" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>The role of maternal effect genes in the development of the nematode Caenorhabditis elegans.</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">deleted: header: student and page numbers
deleted: Word count: 3000 words.
</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">3</p><p n="date">2002-10</p><p n="module title">Development</p><p n="module code">BS301</p><p n="genre family">Explanation</p><p n="discipline">Biological Sciences</p><p n="disciplinary group">LS</p><p n="grade">M</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">4254</p><p n="number of s-units">160</p><p n="number of p">63</p><p n="number of tables">4</p><p n="number of figures">10</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">0</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">0</p><p n="abstract present">abstract present</p><p n="average words per s-unit">26.6</p><p n="average s-units per p">2.5</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">f</p><p n="year of birth">1985</p><p n="first language">French</p><p n="education">OSA</p><p n="course">Biological Sciences with Cell Biology</p><p n="student ID">0103</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><docTitle><titlePart rend="bold">The role of maternal effect genes in the development of the nematode Caenorhabditis elegans. </titlePart></docTitle></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="abstract"><head rend="underlined bold">Abstract: </head><p n="p1.63"><s n="s1.4;p1.63"><hi rend="italic">C. elegans</hi> is a very good model organism for developmental biology: it is small, cheap and easy to manipulate. </s><s n="s2.4;p1.63">It is extensively used for the understanding of maternal effect genes. </s><s n="s3.4;p1.63">These are genes from the mother which are inherited by the embryos and which are essential for the correct and complete development of the embryo. </s><s n="s4.4;p1.63">In <hi rend="italic">C. elegans</hi>, there are 3 major developmental pathways studied: the establishment of the anterior-posterior axis, the specification of the germline and the dorsal-ventral formation. </s></p><p n="p2.63"><s n="s1.5;p2.63">The anterior- posterior axis is set up through maternal and paternal contribution. </s><s n="s2.5;p2.63">The position of the sperm after entry into the egg specifies the posterior pole. </s><s n="s3.5;p2.63">Maternal material consists of PAR proteins which are localized at different poles through the action of centrosomes brought by the sperm. </s><s n="s4.5;p2.63">These proteins are required for maintenance of the asymmetry along with the CDC-42 G-protein. </s><s n="s5.5;p2.63">An array of other proteins such as RIC-8, LET-99, LIN-5 and others are also involved in a-p axis formation. </s></p><p n="p3.63"><s n="s1.2;p3.63">Once the egg is fertilized in undergoes a series of divisions that give rise to somatic blastomeres and germline blastomeres. </s><s n="s2.2;p3.63">Specification of the germline involves the maternal genes <hi rend="italic">pie-1</hi> and the <hi rend="italic">mex-1. pie-1</hi> encodes a protein that has dual functionality: it blocks mRNA translation in germline blastomeres and induces maternal programs involved in germ cell development. </s></p><p n="p4.63"><s n="s1.3;p4.63">Finally, the dorsal-ventral formation relies on the somatic blastomeres, in particular ABa, ABp and EMS. ABa generates the anterior pharyngeal cells through cell-cell interaction with EMS, also involving the receptor GLP-1 and an unknown ligand. </s><s n="s2.3;p4.63">EMS forms the posterior pharyngeal cells autonomously and with the help of the <hi rend="italic">skn-1</hi> gene which is distributed unequally. </s><s n="s3.3;p4.63">Finally ABp forms the rectal and valve cells through interaction between its receptor GLP-1 as well, and the ligand APX-1 signalled from P <hi rend="sub">2</hi>. </s></p><p n="p5.63"><s n="s1.1;p5.63">All these genes have homologies with other species including human, and although most of them form a complex interactive network, their analysis is vital for understanding human development. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">Introduction</head><p n="p6.63"><s n="s1.3;p6.63">The success of molecular biology is due to the existence of model systems. </s><s n="s2.3;p6.63">These are defined as extremely simple organism such as Drosophila, Arabidopsis and <hi rend="italic">Caenorhabditis elegans</hi>. </s><s n="s3.3;p6.63">The latter was introduced as model system by Dr. Sydney Brenner in 1974 (Gilbert, 2003). </s></p><p n="p7.63"><s n="s1.2;p7.63">This free living, non-parasitic soil nematode has all the characteristics of the ideal model organism: it is small, easy to manipulate, cheap, has a short life cycle and most importantly its genome (which is approximately 100 Mbp, that is to say 20 times bigger than that of <hi rend="italic">E. coli</hi> and about 1/30 of that of the human) shows 40% homology to that of the human (Gilbert, 2003). </s><s n="s2.2;p7.63">Figure 1 shows 3 nematode worms viewed under the microscope. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0103b-pic.001"><head>Figure 1. Three nematodes worm viewed under the microscope. Source: <seg type="URL" n="www.yourgenome.org/"/> intermediate/all/</head></figure><p n="p8.63"><s n="s1.7;p8.63">Moreover, this multicellular organism is a hermaphrodite. </s><s n="s2.7;p8.63">It is also transparent making the tracking of cells and following of cell lineages (which is most of the time invariant) very easy using reporter genes such as GFP (green fluorescent protein) (Gilbert, 2003). </s><s n="s3.7;p8.63">Its genome also makes it easy to mutate it: various mutagens can be used, such as EMS, to define mutants. </s><s n="s4.7;p8.63">Mutants can also be obtained using reverse genetics particularly RNA interference (RNAi) which consists of transcribing RNA in vitro from a specific target gene and injecting it into the gonad of wild type worms. </s><s n="s5.7;p8.63">It then prevents the production of the protein product of the target gene (Rose and Kemphues, 1998). </s><s n="s6.7;p8.63">The latter has been extensively used to study maternally expressed genes. </s><s n="s7.7;p8.63">Maternal effect genes are genes required for the development of the embryo. </s></p><p n="p9.63"><s n="s1.1;p9.63">Many of these appear to have a role in the development of the worm and researchers are currently analysing is their exact role. </s></p><p n="p10.63"><s n="s1.1;p10.63">Understanding such an analysis requires the discussion of how the initial asymmetries are set up in the embryo, how the cell fates and lineage are specified. </s></p><div2><head rend="underlined bold">I) The anterior-posterior (a-p) axis establishment in the nematode worm</head><div3><head rend="underlined">Determination of the position of the cell axis</head><p n="p11.63"><s n="s1.1;p11.63"><hi rend="italic">C. elegans</hi> embryogenesis begins with the entry of the sperm into the egg, a process called fertilization and resulting into the formation of a zygote P <hi rend="sub">0.</hi> </s></p><p n="p12.63"><s n="s1.2;p12.63">Just before fertilization, the <hi rend="italic">C. elegans</hi> oocyte is arrested in meiotic prophase I. The oocyte pronucleus moves away from the side contacting the spermatheca and the nuclear envelope breaks down (Gotta and Ahringer, 2001). </s><s n="s2.2;p12.63">It is only then that the sperm enters. </s></p><p n="p13.63"><s n="s1.1;p13.63">Sperm entry triggers 3 events: completion of meiosis with extrusion of 2 polar bodies, formation of a protective eggshell (its rigidity forces the embryo into an ovoid shape) and finally the arrangement of the a-p axis (Lyczak et al., 2002; Gotta and Arhinger, 2001; Rose and Kemphues, 1998). </s></p><p n="p14.63"><s n="s1.2;p14.63">The position of the sperm appears to polarize the zygote (it defines the posterior end and the a-p axis which is the long axis of the egg) bringing along centrosomes. </s><s n="s2.2;p14.63">Meanwhile, the embryo undergoes a process known as pseudocleavage (Lyczak et al., 2002; Cowan and Hyman, 2004) (see figure 2 for a detailed schematic diagram of this process). </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0103b-pic.002"><head>Figure 2a: <hi rend="italic">C. elegans</hi> embryo during pseudocleavage. White dots represent localization points. Source: Centre for cell dynamics, University of Washington, 2003.</head></figure><figure id="BAWE_0103b-fig.001"><head>Figure 2 b. Schematic diagram of pseudocleavage in the nematode worm. The cortex begins to ruffle (visible as abundant temporary invaginations in the cortex) followed by cortical smoothing in the area around the sperm centrosome and spreading toward the opposite end of the embryo (Cowan and Hyman, 2004). "A" stands for anterior and "P" stands for posterior. Adapted from: Cowan and Hyman, 2004.</head></figure><p n="p15.63"><s n="s1.1;p15.63">The cytoplasm is reorganised through the internal cytoplasm being moved to the posterior and the cortical cytoplasm in the opposite direction. </s></p><p n="p16.63"><s n="s1.3;p16.63">The mechanism by which the sperm contributes to the establishment of the a-p axis is not fully understood, however, the cues seem to reside in the sperm donated centrosome and associated microtubules, not in the pronucleus (Lyczak <hi rend="italic">et al</hi>., 2002; Gotta and Arhinger, 2001). </s><s n="s2.3;p16.63">This is further exemplified by the fact that sperm lacking DNA can still fertilize the oocyte and determine the polarity (Gotta and Ahringer, 2001). </s><s n="s3.3;p16.63">In addition to this, disruption of microfilaments, cytoplasmic flow and pseudocleavage by dsRNA mediated interference of <hi rend="italic">nmy-2</hi> (non muscle mysosin II heavy chain gene) results in the removal of the a-p axis, showing that an entire acto-myosin cystoskeleton is required (Lyczak <hi rend="italic">et al</hi>., 2002). </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0103b-pic.003"><head>Figure 3. Staining for actin in the <hi rend="italic">C. elegans</hi> embryo during formation of anterior posterior axis. "A" stands for anterior, "P" stands for posterior. Source: Centre for cell dynamics, University of Washington, 2003.</head></figure><p n="p17.63"><s n="s1.1;p17.63">Nevertheless, the set up of the a-p axis requires maternal signals as well. </s></p></div3><div3><head rend="underlined">B) Contribution of maternal proteins to the a-p axis formation</head><p n="p18.63"><s n="s1.2;p18.63">Analysis of maternal effect lethal mutations led to the finding of 6 genes: the <hi rend="italic">par</hi> genes (<hi rend="italic">par</hi> stands for partitioning defective). </s><s n="s2.2;p18.63">Table 1 </s></p><p n="p19.63"><s n="s1.1;p19.63">summarizes the different genes. </s></p><table id="BAWE_0103b-tab.001"><head>Table 1. The <hi rend="italic">par</hi> genes and the proteins they encode. Source: Data taken from Lyczak <hi rend="italic">et al</hi> ., 2002 and Cowan and Hyman, 2004.</head><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p20.63"><s n="s1.1;p20.63">Their mutation causes early division defects such as equal first cleavage, synchronous second cleavage, mislocalization of P granules and alterations in spindle orientation (see section II to get a full insight and understanding of these events) (Rose and Kemphues, 1998). </s></p><p n="p21.63"><s n="s1.3;p21.63">In the fertilized egg, PAR-1 and PAR-2 are found in the posterior cortex while PAR-3 and PAR-6 are found at the opposite end. </s><s n="s2.3;p21.63">The proteins also have an antagonizing effect on each other: the loss of PAR-3, PAR-6 and PKC-3 result in the uniform distribution of PAR-1 and PAR-2. </s><s n="s3.3;p21.63">Additionally, the contractile polarity coincides with the domains occupied by the PAR proteins suggesting that the 2 processes are linked. </s></p><p n="p22.63"><s n="s1.1;p22.63">This evidence puts forward the hypothesis that <hi rend="italic">par</hi> genes provide polarity information during the first cell cycle. </s></p><p n="p23.63"><s n="s1.1;p23.63">Furthermore, they are required for orientating mitotic spindles during the 2 cell stage (Lyczak and Bowerman, 2002) </s></p><p n="p24.63"><s n="s1.1;p24.63">In summary PAR proteins have emerged as key players in cortical asymmetry and their antagonizing properties may allow for maintenance of these domains resulting in anterior-posterior axis formation. </s></p><p n="p25.63"><s n="s1.1;p25.63">Nonetheless these proteins are also assisted by other proteins. </s></p></div3><div3><head rend="underlined">C) Other proteins involved in the process</head><p n="p26.63"><s n="s1.3;p26.63">As stated above, the PAR proteins do not act by themselves. </s><s n="s2.3;p26.63">They are chaperoned and aided by other proteins. </s><s n="s3.3;p26.63">These proteins include MEX-3, MEX-1 (discussed in section II), MEX-5 and MEX-6, 2 closely related CCCH finger proteins that seem to act downstream of the PAR proteins in localising asymmetrically proteins but not involved in spindle asymmetry in the zygote (Gotta and Arhinger, 2001). </s></p><p n="p27.63"><s n="s1.1;p27.63">Spindle asymmetry appears to be dictated by LIN-5. </s></p><p n="p28.63"><s n="s1.5;p28.63">So far the most striking and exciting finding concerning spindle asymmetry is the involvement of heterotrimeric G proteins. </s><s n="s2.5;p28.63">One G protein in particular, CDC-42, is vital in maintaining but not initiating polarity. </s><s n="s3.5;p28.63">This was deduced following the observation that embryos, in which CDC-42 had been inhibited by RNAi, closely resembled those that had absent or defective PAR-3, PAR-5, or PKC-3 (Gotta and Arhinger, 2001). </s><s n="s4.5;p28.63">Furthermore, two redundant Gα subunits GOA-1 and GPA-16 are required for posterior displacement of the zygote spindle (Gotta and Arhinger, 2001; Lyczak and Bowerman, 2002). </s><s n="s5.5;p28.63">In addition to this, Gβγ controls distinct MT-dependent processes and thus is involved in orientating the mitotic spindle. </s></p><p n="p29.63"><s n="s1.1;p29.63">Three other proteins are thought to interact with the G proteins subunits during spindle positioning: RIC-8, LET-99, and SPN-1 (Lyczak and Bowerman, 2002; Gotta and Arhinger, 2001). </s></p><p n="p30.63"><s n="s1.1;p30.63">And finally intracellular trafficking appears to also be important in polarity establishment, involving 2 proteins, OOC-5 and OOC-3 which are found in the endoplasmic reticulum. </s></p><p n="p31.63"><s n="s1.1;p31.63">Table 2 concisely describes the different proteins along with explaining their role, the consequence of their absence or defect on the phenotype. </s></p><table id="BAWE_0103b-tab.002"><head>Table 2. Recapitulation of the main proteins which act in conjunction or downstream of the PAR proteins in the establishment of the anterior-posterior axis (Lyczack and Bowerman, 2002; Gotta and Ahringer, 2001; Rose and Kemphues, 1998). Section II, figure 5 is essential for a better understanding of the different blastomeres mentioned in this table.</head><row><cell/></row></table><figure id="BAWE_0103b-fig.002"><head>Figure 4. The protein network involved in anterior-posterior polarity (Lyczack and Bowerman, 2002; Gotta and Ahringer, 2001; Rose and Kemphues, 1998). Source: adapted from Seydoux and Pelletieri, 2002.</head></figure></div3></div2><div2><head rend="underlined bold">II) Cell fates and lineage specification: germline development</head><div3><head rend="underlined">A) Embryonic lineage</head><p n="p32.63"><s n="s1.4;p32.63">After a series of event (stated in the first section) the egg divides and gives rise to 2 daughter cells known as AB (anterior blastomere) and P <hi rend="sub">1</hi> (posterior blastomere). </s><s n="s2.4;p32.63">This division precedes and leads to subsequent divisions producing somatic cells (soma) and germline cells (germline). </s><s n="s3.4;p32.63">To be more accurate, once the fertilized egg has given rise to AB and P <hi rend="sub">1</hi>, AB divides equally to generate somatic daughters with equivalent developmental potential (Seydoux and Strome, 1999) whereas the P <hi rend="sub">1</hi> germline blastomere divides unequally generating somatic blastomeres and germline blastomeres. </s><s n="s4.4;p32.63">The major end products of the germline cleavage are 2 primordial germ cells, Z <hi rend="sub">2</hi> and Z <hi rend="sub">3</hi>. </s></p><p n="p33.63"><s n="s1.1;p33.63">Figure 5 provides a clear and concise overview of the embryonic lineage in general and the subsequent cleavages. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0103b-fig.003"><head>Figure 5. Schematic diagram of the embryonic lineage in <hi rend="italic">C. elegans.</hi> P <hi rend="sub">0</hi> represents the fertilized egg. P <hi rend="sub">1</hi> germline blastomere divides unequally to give to P <hi rend="sub">2</hi> and EMS. P <hi rend="sub">2</hi> is the next germline blastomere, which when it divides it produces P <hi rend="sub">3</hi> , another germline blastomere, and C. P <hi rend="sub">3</hi> then produces P <hi rend="sub">4</hi> and D. P <hi rend="sub">4</hi> is a primordial germ cell and it is the progenitor of the entire germline. As for EMS, it divides into MS, which generates primarily pharyngeal cells and muscle cells, and E, which produces intestinal cells (Seydoux and Strome, 1999; Mello et al., 1992; Bowerman et al., 1992). Following a few more divisions, the primordial germ cell is divided symmetrically rather than asymmetrically and produces the 2 primordial germ cells Z <hi rend="sub">2</hi> and Z <hi rend="sub">3</hi> which are joined by 2 somatic gonadal cells (Z <hi rend="sub">1</hi> and Z <hi rend="sub">4</hi> ). The 16 cell stage may sometimes vary between 16 and 24 cells. The germ cells lineage appears in bold. Adapted from Seydoux and Strome, 1999. </head></figure><p n="p34.63"><s n="s1.1;p34.63">The germ line lineage is fully understood unlike the mechanism which differentiates the germline and the soma. </s></p></div3><div3><head><hi rend="underlined">B) Germline specification and distinction from the soma in <hi rend="italic">C. elegans</hi></hi> .</head><p n="p35.63"><s n="s1.2;p35.63">Many characteristics constitute such a difference between germline blastomeres and somatic blastomeres. </s><s n="s2.2;p35.63">The germ cells arise from totipotent cells and have a very low mitotic activity compared to somatic cells instead; they undergo meiosis and gametogenesis (Seydoux and Strome, 1999; Mello et al., 1992). </s></p><p n="p36.63"><s n="s1.1;p36.63">However, the distinction between germline and soma is more complex and involves mechanisms that are still to be fully understood. </s></p><p n="p37.63"><s n="s1.10;p37.63">One of the most striking characteristic that discriminates them is the difference in transcriptional activity. </s><s n="s2.10;p37.63">An analysis of 16 transcripts revealed the presence of newly synthesized mRNA in somatic blastomeres, but never in the germline blastomeres (Seydoux and Strome, 1999; Seydoux <hi rend="italic">et al.</hi> </s><s n="s3.10;p37.63">, 1996). </s><s n="s4.10;p37.63">These experiments resulted in the proposal of two hypotheses: either there is a block in mRNA synthesis in germline blastomeres or a decrease in its stability. </s><s n="s5.10;p37.63">Further experiments supported the first hypothesis. </s><s n="s6.10;p37.63">These were conducted by Geraldine Seydoux and Susan Strome and showed that the germline blastomeres lacked a specific phosphoepitope (H5) on the carboxyl terminal (CTD) of RNA polymerase II. Thus its activity is reduced or even absent (Seydoux and Strome, 1999; Tenehaus <hi rend="italic">et al.</hi> </s><s n="s7.10;p37.63">, 2001). </s><s n="s8.10;p37.63">It was later discovered that mRNA inhibition is in fact regulated by <hi rend="italic">pie-1</hi> (Seydoux and Strome, 1999; Tenehaus <hi rend="italic">et al.</hi> </s><s n="s9.10;p37.63">, 2001; Seydoux <hi rend="italic">et al.</hi> </s><s n="s10.10;p37.63">, 1996). </s></p><p n="p38.63"><s n="s1.4;p38.63">The <hi rend="italic">pie-1</hi> gene is believed to play an important role in germline specification. </s><s n="s2.4;p38.63">The <hi rend="italic">pie-1</hi> gene encodes a 38kDA cytoplasmic and nuclear protein called PIE-1 protein which contains two zinc fingers of the C <hi rend="sub">3</hi>H class (3 cysteines and histidine residues). </s><s n="s3.4;p38.63">It appears to be present at the right time and the right place to repress transcription in germline blastomeres. </s><s n="s4.4;p38.63">See table 3 for description of observations that led to these conclusions. </s></p><table id="BAWE_0103b-tab.003"><head>Table 3. Summary of the observations that led to the innovative conclusions.</head><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p39.63"><s n="s1.4;p39.63">It has been concluded that the inhibition of transcription might protect germline blastomeres from the activity of transcription factors that normally promote somatic development (Seydoux <hi rend="italic">et al</hi>., 1996; Seydoux and Strome, 1999). </s><s n="s2.4;p39.63">A perfect example is SKN-1 which is a transcription factor present in EMS and P <hi rend="sub">2</hi> but only functions in EMS (refer to section III for a more detailed description of this transcription factor). </s><s n="s3.4;p39.63">It specifies the fate of the former and is prevented from acting on the latter by PIE-1 (Seydoux <hi rend="italic">et al</hi>., 1996; Seydoux and Strome, 1999). </s><s n="s4.4;p39.63">However, SKN-1 is probably not the only transcription factor whose activity is repressed by PIE-1. </s></p><p n="p40.63"><s n="s1.1;p40.63">Nevertheless PIE-1 appears to have another important role in germline lineage along with another protein. </s></p></div3><div3><head rend="underlined">C) Bifunctionality of PIE-1 and regulation by MEX-1. </head><p n="p41.63"><s n="s1.5;p41.63">As stated earlier on, PIE-1 is also present in the cytoplasm of germline cells. </s><s n="s2.5;p41.63">In the cytoplasm, it is associated with P granules (Tenehaus et al., 2001). </s><s n="s3.5;p41.63">These are germline associated RNA-rich organelles believed to be involved in germ cell development (Guedes and Priess, 1997). </s><s n="s4.5;p41.63">In conjunction with its role in the nucleus, PIE-1's cytoplasmic function promotes the expression of factors that are maternally encoded and that are crucial for primordial germ cell development such as the maternally encoded Nanos homolog NOS-2 (Tenenhaus <hi rend="italic">et al.</hi> </s><s n="s5.5;p41.63">, 2001). </s></p><p n="p42.63"><s n="s1.5;p42.63">The cytoplasm found in germ cells is called germ plasm. </s><s n="s2.5;p42.63">In the zygote, by an MT- dependent manner P granules are carried to the posterior end, where they associate with the cortex (Spike and Strome, 2003). </s><s n="s3.5;p42.63">This results in most P granules being segregated to P <hi rend="sub">1</hi> (Spike and Strome, 2003). </s><s n="s4.5;p42.63">P granules also turn up to be unstable in the cytoplasm fated for the somatic blastomeres. </s><s n="s5.5;p42.63">Experiments by Caroline Spike and Susan Strome described this phenomenon as: "P granules being trapped near the anterior cortex of a P <hi rend="sub">0</hi> cell appear to be disassembled or degraded prior to cell division and the few P granules mistakenly segregated to a C or D blastomere disappear rapidly" (Spike and Strome, 2003). </s></p><p n="p43.63"><s n="s1.6;p43.63">In addition to this, it has been found that the germ plasm also contains the MEX-1 protein. </s><s n="s2.6;p43.63">MEX-1 is very similar to the PIE-1 protein (Guedes and Priess, 1997). </s><s n="s3.6;p43.63">MEX-1 is encoded by the <hi rend="italic">mex-1</hi> gene which when mutated causes the embryo to produce too many pharyngeal cells as does the pie-1gene (<hi rend="italic">pie</hi> stands for pharyngeal intestinal excess and <hi rend="italic">mex</hi> stands for muscle excess) (Mello <hi rend="italic">et al</hi>., 1992). </s><s n="s4.6;p43.63">It also has the same 2 copies of the unusual finger domain found in the PIE-1 protein (Guedes and Priess, 1997). </s><s n="s5.6;p43.63">Although MEX-1 is only present in the cytoplasm, it is a granule component which appears to be required to restrict PIE-1 expression and activity to the germline blastomere (Guedes and Priess, 1997). </s><s n="s6.6;p43.63">Figure 6 shows the effect of the absence of the 2 proteins on the germ lineage. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0103b-fig.004"/><p n="p44.63"><s n="s1.3;p44.63">The specification of the germline therefore involves 2 major proteins, PIE-1 and MEX-1. </s><s n="s2.3;p44.63">PIE-1 blocks zygotic programs that drive somatic development and activates maternal programs that drive germ cell development. </s><s n="s3.3;p44.63">As for MEX-1 it regulates PIE-1. </s></p><p n="p45.63"><s n="s1.1;p45.63">Figure 7 summarizes the role of the 2 proteins. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0103b-fig.005"><head>Figure 7: Schematic diagram of the role of the proteins. Source: Adapted from Tenenhaus <hi rend="italic">et al.</hi> , 2001</head></figure></div3></div2><div2><head rend="underlined bold">III) Somatic specification: dorsal-ventral formation</head><p n="p46.63"><s n="s1.2;p46.63">The anterior blastomeres produced at the 2 cell stage have the equal developmental potential (referred to briefly in section II). </s><s n="s2.2;p46.63">They are eventually committed to different fates: ABa progeny give rise to anterior pharyngeal cells and ABp descendants contribute to the formation of the anus and rectum. </s></p><div3><head rend="underlined">Cell-cell interaction</head><p n="p47.63"><s n="s1.3;p47.63">Specification of ABp fate requires cell-cell interaction between ABp and P <hi rend="sub">2</hi>. </s><s n="s2.3;p47.63">This was demonstrated by Shelton and Bowerman (1996) by incubating intact embryos overnight and using antibodies to distinguish the cell types normally generated by ABp. </s><s n="s3.3;p47.63">In addition, when AB and P <hi rend="sub">2</hi> are grown in isolation, they do not produce valve nor rectal cells. </s></p><p n="p48.63"><s n="s1.10;p48.63">It follows that ABp-P2 interaction engages the maternal effect gene <hi rend="italic">glp-1</hi>. </s><s n="s2.10;p48.63">This gene encodes the protein GLP-1, which is a membrane bound receptor and a homolog of the <hi rend="italic">Drosophila</hi> Notch (Shelton and Bowerman, 1996; Evans <hi rend="italic">et al</hi>., 1994; Mickey <hi rend="italic">et al</hi>., 1996). </s><s n="s3.10;p48.63">P <hi rend="sub">2</hi> seems to be the signalling cell, with the ligand being APX-1, a homolog of the <hi rend="italic">Drosophila</hi> Delta (Mickey <hi rend="italic">et al</hi>., 1996; Shelton and Bowerman, 1996). </s><s n="s4.10;p48.63">Two line s of evidence suggest this: in <hi rend="italic">apx-1</hi> embryos (produced from <hi rend="italic">apx-1</hi> mutant mothers), ABp produces pharyngeal cells (cells produced by ABa) and its sequence is very similar to that of <hi rend="italic">Drosophila</hi> Delta (Shelton and Bowerman, 1996). </s><s n="s5.10;p48.63">At the 2 cell stage, APX-1 is found in the anterior of the P <hi rend="sub">1</hi> blastomere. </s><s n="s6.10;p48.63">Moreover, it is localized in a very similar manner to that of PAR-3. </s><s n="s7.10;p48.63">It follows that the level of APX-1 increases in P <hi rend="sub">2</hi> although the mRNA is present in all the 4 cell stage blastomeres. </s><s n="s8.10;p48.63">These observations have led to the conclusion that it must be translationally regulated, membrane targeted or stabilised/destabilised. </s><s n="s9.10;p48.63">In other words, its localization could result from the same mechanism as PAR-3 or interaction with adjacent blastomeres (Mickey <hi rend="italic"> et al</hi>., 1996). </s><s n="s10.10;p48.63">Figure 8 shows a model of this localization. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0103b-fig.006"><head>Figure 8. Localization of GLP-1 and APX-1 in the blastomeres. GLP-1 is in yellow and APX-1 is in blue. At the 2 cell stage, GLP-1 is detected in the anterior blastomeres only. At the 4 cell stage, it is only detectable in the 2 sister blastomeres: ABa and ABp. APX-1 is located in the anterior region of P1 which contacts the posterior region of AB. This is maintained in the 4 cell stage (Mickey <hi rend="italic">et al</hi> ., 1996) Source: Adapted from Evans <hi rend="italic">et al</hi> ., 1994 and Mello <hi rend="italic">et al</hi> ., 1994.</head></figure><p n="p49.63"><s n="s1.3;p49.63">GLP-1 appears to be the receptor in ABa induction; however, its ligand isn't APX-1: <hi rend="italic">apx-1</hi> mutant blastomeres are still able to give rise to pharyngeal cells when induced by the appropriate cell (Shelton and Bowerman, 1996). </s><s n="s2.3;p49.63">However, the ligand has yet to be identified. </s><s n="s3.3;p49.63">EMS and its descendants are the signalling cells: removal of EMS by laser ablation greatly affects ABa descendants which failed to produce their cells (Mello <hi rend="italic">et al</hi>., 1994). </s></p><p n="p50.63"><s n="s1.1;p50.63">The question is: how can the same receptor send out 2 developmental signals with very different consequences? </s></p><p n="p51.63"><s n="s1.4;p51.63">2 models have been proposed: developmental fate either depends on the activated cell or on temporal changes in the cellular factors expressed by the responding cell. </s><s n="s2.4;p51.63">The latter has been validated as the switching of one blastomere for the other does not change the inductive response (Shelton and Bowerman, 1996). </s><s n="s3.4;p51.63">Even though <hi rend="italic">glp-1</hi> is present in all blastomeres up to the 8 cell stage, its translation is temporally and spatially regulated. </s><s n="s4.4;p51.63">A study using a reporter RNA has revealed that this regulation is controlled by the 3' untranslated region of the gene (3'UTR) (Ogura <hi rend="italic">et al</hi>., 2003). </s></p><p n="p52.63"><s n="s1.3;p52.63">Two regulatory regions have been revealed: a 61 nucleotide region in the middle known as spatial control region which represses translation in the descendants of P <hi rend="sub">1</hi> and a 125 nucleotide region initially identified as the temporal control region. </s><s n="s2.3;p52.63">However it has recently been revealed that it also contains a spatial activation region (Ogura <hi rend="italic">et al</hi>., 2003; Evans <hi rend="italic">et al</hi>., 1994). </s><s n="s3.3;p52.63">See figure 9 for a schematic diagram of this region of the gene. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0103b-fig.007"><head>Figure 9. The 3' UTR of the <hi rend="italic">glp-1</hi> gene. The red region represents the spatial control region, the green region represents the temporal inhibition region within the TCR and the purple region represents the spatial activation region. The spatial activation region was deduced following observation that deletion of the TCR disrupts spatial regulation of translation as well as temporal regulation (Ogura <hi rend="italic">et al</hi> ., 2003). Source: Adapted from Ogura <hi rend="italic">et al.</hi> 2003</head></figure><p n="p53.63"><s n="s1.3;p53.63">The presence of 2 regulatory regions indicates that glp-1 mRNA is regulated by 2 factors: POS-1 which binds to SCR and temporal regulation which is achieved by the binding of SPN-4 (has an RNA type binding domain) to the TCR which is then inactivated between the 2 and 4 cell stages (Ogura <hi rend="italic">et</hi> al., 2003; Evans <hi rend="italic">et al.</hi> </s><s n="s2.3;p53.63">, 1994). </s><s n="s3.3;p53.63">Figure 10 represents a schematic diagram which describes the regulation. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0103b-fig.008"><head>Figure 10: Translational regulation of <hi rend="italic">glp-1.</hi> In the anterior bastomere, SPN-4 binds to the spatial activation region of the TCR and represses POS-1 action which is bound to the SRC as a homomer through it second zinc finger and also present in a much smaller concentration. Since POS-1 is inactivated, the SRC is as well. In contrast, the temporal region is active between the 2 and 4 cell stages allowing expression of <hi rend="italic">glp1</hi> . On the other hand, the SRC region is active in the posterior blastomere due to POS-1 being present in much higher levels by elongating its poly-a tail) than in the anterior blastomere . It therefore dominates the SPN-4 function, resulting in the inhibition of the translation of <hi rend="italic">glp-1</hi> . Source: Ogura <hi rend="italic">et al</hi> ., 2003.</head></figure></div3><div3><head rend="underlined">Autonomous development</head><p n="p54.63"><s n="s1.3;p54.63">EMS also gives rise to pharyngeal cells although they are posterior (Bowerman <hi rend="italic">et al.</hi> </s><s n="s2.3;p54.63">, 1992). </s><s n="s3.3;p54.63">Two lines of evidence suggest that generation of pharyngeals cells by EMS is through autonomous cell specification (in other words it adopts its normal pattern of development without requiring cell-cell interaction): destruction of ABa blastomeres by laser ablation does not affect the production of cell by EMS and neither does the production of <hi rend="italic">glp-1</hi> embryos (Bowerman <hi rend="italic">et al</hi>., 1992). </s></p><p n="p55.63"><s n="s1.2;p55.63">A genetic analysis has revealed that EMS development requires the maternal gene <hi rend="italic">skn-1</hi> which stands for s <hi rend="italic">k</hi>i <hi rend="italic">n</hi> in excess (maternal because <hi rend="italic">skn-1</hi> embryos fail to be rescued by wild type male sperm and lack pharyngeal and intestinal cells) (Bowerman <hi rend="italic">et al</hi>., 1992; Rose and Kemphues, 1998). </s><s n="s2.2;p55.63">Figure 11 shows the differences between wild-type and <hi rend="italic">skn-1</hi> embryos phenotype. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0103b-fig.009"><head>Figure 11. Source: Gilbert, 2003</head></figure><p n="p56.63"><s n="s1.3;p56.63"><hi rend="italic">skn-1</hi> encodes a transcription factor that contains a basic region similar to those of basic leucine zipper proteins (bZIP). </s><s n="s2.3;p56.63">Additionally it binds as a monomer because it lacks a leucine zipper dimerization domain. </s><s n="s3.3;p56.63">This paradox has been resolved by Blackwell and coworkers in 1994 which explained that "its binding domain represents an alternative strategy for promoting binding of a basic region segment helix to a bZIP half site". </s></p><p n="p57.63"><s n="s1.1;p57.63">So how is SKN-1 localized to EMS in the first place? </s></p><p n="p58.63"><s n="s1.4;p58.63">Following fertilization and the 2 <hi rend="sup">nd</hi> division, SKN-1 appears to build up at much higher levels in P <hi rend="sub">1</hi> than in the AB blastomeres. </s><s n="s2.4;p58.63">SKN-1 is therefore localized unequally in the <hi rend="italic">C. elegans</hi> embryo. </s><s n="s3.4;p58.63">The possible mechanisms by which it amasses are: differences in distribution or translation of the mRNA or differences in the stability of the protein. </s><s n="s4.4;p58.63">A series of mutations (maternal effect mutations in <hi rend="italic">par-1</hi> and <hi rend="italic">mex-1</hi> which lead to approximately equal levels of SKN-1 in both P <hi rend="sub">1</hi> and AB) have led to the conclusion that MEX-1 and PAR-1 are required for the unequal distribution of the SKN-1 to P <hi rend="sub">1</hi> (Blackwell <hi rend="italic">et al</hi>., 1994) . </s></p><p n="p59.63"><s n="s1.2;p59.63">So why do P <hi rend="sub">2</hi> and EMS have different fates? </s><s n="s2.2;p59.63">This question is still under investigation but it looks like <hi rend="italic">pie-1 (+)</hi> activity may control the activity of SKN-1 in the EMS and its progeny (Bowerman <hi rend="italic">et al</hi>., 1993) and that an interaction between P <hi rend="sub">2</hi> and EMS is required (Rose and Kemphues, 1998). </s></p></div3></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">Conclusion:</head><p n="p60.63"><s n="s1.2;p60.63">Three different developmental pathways and so many genes! </s><s n="s2.2;p60.63">However, they are interconnected forming a complex cross-network. </s></p><p n="p61.63"><s n="s1.1;p61.63">Table 4 summarizes all the genes and proteins involved in the different pathways. </s></p><table id="BAWE_0103b-tab.004"><head>Table 4. Genes and proteins engaged in the 3 majors developmental specifications of the nematode worm.</head><row><cell/></row></table><figure id="BAWE_0103b-fig.010"><head>Figure 12. The complex cross-network between the developmental specifications. No source.</head></figure><p n="p62.63"><s n="s1.1;p62.63">Could the analysis reveal some aspect of the human development? </s></p><p n="p63.63"><s n="s1.1;p63.63">It seems that understand how this organisms and other invertebrates acquire different potentials could be a further step to understanding embryo development, finding a treatments for prenatal malformations and avoiding miscarriages. </s></p></div1></body><back><div1 type="bibliography"><head rend="underlined bold">Bibliography:</head><p>Bowerman, B. <hi rend="italic">et al</hi>., (1992). <hi rend="italic">Skn-1 a maternally expressed gene required to specify the fate of ventral blastomeres in the early C. elegans embryo</hi>. Cell. 68, 1061-1075.</p><p>Bowerman, B. <hi rend="italic">et al</hi>., (1993). <hi rend="italic">The maternal gene skn-1 encodes a protein that is distributed unequally in early C. elegans embryo</hi>. Cell. 74, 443-452.</p><p>Cowan, C. R. and Hyman, A. A., (2004). <hi rend="italic">Asymmetric cell division in C. elegans: Cortical Polarity and Spindle Positioning.</hi> Annual Review of Cell and Developmental Biology. 20,427-453.</p><p>Evans, T. C, Crittenden, S. L. Kodoyanni. V. and Kimble, J. K., (1994). <hi rend="italic">Translational control of maternal glp-1 mRNA establishes an asymmetry in the C. elegans embryo</hi>. Cell. 77, 183-194.</p><p>Gilbert, S. F. (2003). <hi rend="italic">Developmental biology</hi>. Sinauer editions. p 254-255.</p><p>Gotta, M., and Ahringer, J., (2001). <hi rend="italic">Axis determination in C. elegans: initiating and transducing polarity</hi>. Journal of current genetic development. 11, 367-373.</p><p>Guedes, S. and Priess, J. R., (1997). <hi rend="italic">Cloning of the pie-1 gene</hi>. Development. 124, 731-739.</p><p>Mello, C.C. <hi rend="italic">et al</hi>., (1992). <hi rend="italic">The pie-1 and mex-1 genes and maternal control of blastomere identity in early C. elegans embryos</hi>. Cell. 70, 163-176. </p><p>Lyczak, R., Gomes, J. E. and Bowerman, B., (2002). <hi rend="italic">Heads or tails: cell polarity and axis formation in the early Caenorhabditis elegans embryo</hi>. Developmental cell. 3, 157-166.</p><p>Mello, C. C et al., (1994). <hi rend="italic">The maternal genes apx-1 and glp-1 and establishment of dorsal ventral polarity in the early C. elegans embryo</hi>. Cell. 77, 95-106.</p><p>Mickey et al., (1996). An inductive interaction in 4-cell stage embryo involves APX-1 expression in the signalling cell. Development. 122, 1791-1798.</p><p>Ogura, K., Kishimoto, N., Mitani, S., Gengyo-Ando, K. and Kohara, Y., (2003). Translational control of maternal glp-1 mRNA by POS- 1 and its interacting protein SPN-4 in Caenorhabditis elegans. Development. 130, 2495-2503.</p><p>Rose, L.S and Kemphues, K. J., (1998). <hi rend="italic">Early patterning of the C.elegans embryo</hi>. Annual review of genetics. 32, 521-545.</p><p>Seydoux, G. and Strome, S. (1999). <hi rend="italic">Launching the germline in Caenorhabditis elegans: regulation of gene expression in early germ cell</hi>. Development. 126, 3275-3283. </p><p>Shelton, C. A. and Bowerman, B., (1996). <hi rend="italic">Time-dependant responses to glp-1 mediated inductions in early C. elegans embryos</hi>. Development. 122, 2043-2050.</p><p>Spikes, C. A and Strome, S. (2003). <hi rend="italic">Germ plasm: Protein degradation in the soma</hi>. Current Biology. 13, R837-R839.</p><p>Tenenhaus, C., Subramaniam, K. M., Dunn, M. A and Seydoux, G., (2001). <hi rend="italic">PIE-1 is a bifunctional protein that regulates maternal and zygotic gene expression in the embryonic germ line of Caernorhabditis elegans</hi>. Genes and Development. 15, 1031-1040.</p></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
