<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_0103d" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Stem Cells; their origin, properties and medical potential</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">deleted: header: student and page numbers
deleted: Word count: 2972 words
</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">2</p><p n="date">2005-03</p><p n="module title">BS/MB/VIR/CB assessments</p><p n="module code">BS241</p><p n="genre family">Explanation</p><p n="discipline">Biological Sciences</p><p n="disciplinary group">LS</p><p n="grade">M</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">3590</p><p n="number of s-units">139</p><p n="number of p">48</p><p n="number of tables">1</p><p n="number of figures">4</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">0</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">0</p><p n="abstract present">abstract present</p><p n="average words per s-unit">25.8</p><p n="average s-units per p">2.9</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">f</p><p n="year of birth">1985</p><p n="first language">French</p><p n="education">OSA</p><p n="course">Biological Sciences with Cell Biology</p><p n="student ID">0103</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><docTitle><titlePart rend="bold">Stem cells: their origin, properties and medical potential</titlePart></docTitle></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="abstract"><head rend="underlined bold">Abstract:</head><p n="p1.48"><s n="s1.8;p1.48">Stem cells are undifferentiated cells that can give rise to specialized cells. </s><s n="s2.8;p1.48">There are different types of stem cells, but those that are thoroughly studied at the present time are pluripotent stem cells. </s><s n="s3.8;p1.48">These cells in theory can give rise to any cells in the body. </s><s n="s4.8;p1.48">There are 3 kinds of pluripotent stem cells: embryonal carcinoma stem cells which are derived from teratocarcinomas and primordial germ cells, embryonic germ cells derived from primordial germ cell as well and embryonic stem cell derived from the inner cell mass cells and the primitive ectoderm. </s><s n="s5.8;p1.48">Each of those cells exhibit markers that define their state as undifferentiated and they also require growth factors. </s><s n="s6.8;p1.48">This leads to one of their properties: self-renewal. </s><s n="s7.8;p1.48">When kept in their niches, these stem cells can divide symmetrically giving rise to 2 identical daughter cells which in turn will give rise to 2 identical daughter cells each. </s><s n="s8.8;p1.48">Pluripotent stem cells also possess 2 other properties, they can undergo differentiation (which is correlated with their exit from their niche, secreted factors and a clock mechanism) and they are capable of plasticity. </s></p><p n="p2.48"><s n="s1.1;p2.48">These cells are of great importance as they can be used in cell-based therapies to treat diseases and injuries but their use also raises many concerns, morally and ethically. </s></p><p n="p3.48"><s n="s1.2;p3.48">Stem cells may be the answer to a new medical generation and era. </s><s n="s2.2;p3.48">The analysis of their origin, properties and medical potential are therefore primordial. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">Introduction:</head><p n="p4.48"><s n="s1.9;p4.48">The aim of researchers has always been to find a way of treating diseases caused by damaged or non-functional cells. </s><s n="s2.9;p4.48">In their years of investigation, a new class of cells has been discovered: stem cells. </s><s n="s3.9;p4.48">Stem cells are a special kind of cells that are unique. </s><s n="s4.9;p4.48">They are undifferentiated cells, which under certain conditions are capable of self-renewal and maintenance and are also capable of differentiating into specialized tissue-forming cells (The official national institutes of health resource for stem cell research; Donovan and Gearhart, 2001). </s><s n="s5.9;p4.48">Some cells will only give rise to one particular cell type, others will give rise to many. </s><s n="s6.9;p4.48">And it is this characteristic that has differentiated them from each other. </s><s n="s7.9;p4.48">Many stem cells have now been discovered: adult stem cells, embryonic stem cells, pluripotent stem cells and many more. </s><s n="s8.9;p4.48">But scientists have focused on pluripotent stem cells. </s><s n="s9.9;p4.48">These cells possess the ability to give rise to every cell type and tissues in the animal body and are derived from embryonic tissues (Musina <hi rend="italic">et al</hi>, 2003). </s></p><p n="p5.48"><s n="s1.1;p5.48">The investigation of biologists have been based on one question: what is the origin, properties and medical potential of these particular cells? </s></p><p n="p6.48"><s n="s1.1;p6.48">To understand why researchers have focused on them, a full understanding of these cells is primordial and their origin, properties and medical potential must be reviewed individually and concisely. </s></p><div2><head rend="underlined bold">I) The origin of pluripotent stem cells</head><p n="p7.48"><s n="s1.1;p7.48">Three types of pluripotent stem cells have been isolated and studied: embryonal carcinoma (EC) stem cells, embryonic stem (ES) cells derived from pre-implantation embryos and embryonic germ cells derived from primordial germ cells (PGCs) of the post-implantation embryo. </s></p><div3><head rend="underlined">A) Embryonal carcinoma stem cells</head><p n="p8.48"><s n="s1.2;p8.48">Embryonal carcinoma stem cells have been investigated for decades (since the 1980s) and they were, in fact, the first pluripotent stem cells to be identified (Donovan and Gearhart, 2001; Przyborski, <hi rend="italic">et al</hi>, 2004). </s><s n="s2.2;p8.48">These are stem cells derived from tumours know as teratocarcinomas (see figure 1). </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0103d-pic.001"><head>Figure 1. Tight colony of embryonal carcinoma cells Source: Przyborski, <hi rend="italic">et al</hi> , 2004. Stem cell and Development, 13, 400-408. </head></figure><p n="p9.48"><s n="s1.1;p9.48">Teratocarcinomas, also called testicular teratomas, are highly bizarre gonadal tumours containing a wide array of tissues which are derivatives of the 3 primary germ layers (endoderm, ectoderm and mesoderm). </s></p><p n="p10.48"><s n="s1.3;p10.48">However, other studies have suggested that EC cells are also derived from primordial germ cells (PGCs) (Donovan and de Miguel, 2003). </s><s n="s2.3;p10.48">This was first noted by Roy Stevens who described "vesicles like structures that resemble embryonic ectoderm, mesoderm and endoderm" that had differentiated after rupturing the seminiferous tubules and entering the interstitial space in mice developing teratocarcinomas (Donovan and de Miguel, 2003). </s><s n="s3.3;p10.48">The primordial germ cells are diploid germ cell precursors that transiently exist in the embryo before entering into close association with the somatic cells of the gonad and specialize into haploid gametes (<seg type="URL" n="www.brown.edu/courses/BI0032/embgerm/pgc.html"/>). </s></p><p n="p11.48"><s n="s1.3;p11.48">The PGCs from which EC cells are derived in this case are termed nullipotent. </s><s n="s2.3;p11.48">This is because when tested in assays of development potency, they can not give rise to any other cell types. </s><s n="s3.3;p11.48">The question researchers have been trying to resolve is how these nullipotent primordial germ cells actually give rise to EC cells. </s></p><p n="p12.48"><s n="s1.3;p12.48">Genetic approaches have determined several germ sell tumour loci in both mice (located on chromosome 19 and chromosome 13), humans (located on chromosome 12) and the markers they express such as the POU-domain transcription factor Oct4 (common to the 3 types of pluripotent stem cells), the tissues non-specific alkaline phosphatase (TNAP) (Donovan and de Miguel, 2003). </s><s n="s2.3;p12.48">Somehow, the conversion of PGCs into EC cells remains to be clarified and understood. </s><s n="s3.3;p12.48">It is believed to be linked in some way with their deregulated proliferation. </s></p><p n="p13.48"><s n="s1.1;p13.48">The study of embryonal carcinoma cells and their derivation from PGCs also lead to the discovery and analysis of embryonic germ cells derived from PGCs. </s></p></div3><div3><head rend="underlined">B) Embryonic germ cells derived from PGCs of the post-implantation embryo. </head><p n="p14.48"><s n="s1.1;p14.48">Embryonic germ (EG) cells were first discovered in 1998 and like the EC cells, they are derived from a nullipotent PGC and are capable of forming the 3 germ layers that make all the specific organs of the body (see figure 2) (Donovan and Gearhart, 2001). </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0103d-pic.002"><head>Figure 2. Embryonic germ cells Source: <seg type="URL" n="www.labs.roslin.ac.uk/"/>.../ established_eg.jpg</head></figure><p n="p15.48"><s n="s1.2;p15.48">EG cells formation is believed to be related in some way to PGC mitotic status. </s><s n="s2.2;p15.48">This is based on 3 facts: PGCs isolated from young embryos make EG cells readily, loss of the tumour suppressor PTEN increases PGC proliferation and EG cell formation competence and PGCs isolated from the embryonic gonad will in the presence of serum and certain growth factors (such as KL or Kit ligand, leukaemia inhibitory factor also know as LIF and basic fibroblast growth factor designated bFGF) will grow into EG cells (Donovan and de Miguel, 2003). </s></p><p n="p16.48"><s n="s1.1;p16.48">bFGF is believed to be the key to the conversion of PGC into embryonic germ cells (demonstrated by the addition of KL and LIF alone, which did not cause the conversion), along with the Oct4 POU domain transcription factor, the STAT3 transcription activator, the HMG-box protein SOX2, the forkhead transcriptional regulator Fox D3 and finally, the recently described Nanog protein (Donovan and de Miguel, 2003). </s></p><p n="p17.48"><s n="s1.1;p17.48">The exact role of these factors remains unclear, as does the genetic pathway which declenches the proliferation and differentiation of the nullipotent PGC, however it is believed to be similar to nuclear reprogramming. </s></p></div3><div3><head rend="underlined">C) Embryonic stem (ES) cells derived from pre-implantation embryos. </head><p n="p18.48"><s n="s1.4;p18.48">In contrast with the 2 other types of stem cells reviewed above, embryonic stem cells are derived by the culture of the pluripotent inner cell mass (ICM) cells of the pre-implantation embryo (Wert and Mummery, 2003; Donovan and Gearhart, 2001). </s><s n="s2.4;p18.48">The inner cell mass is the second lineage of the early embryo that is located inside the blastocyst and that gives rise to all cell types of the adult body (Zwaka and Thomson, 2005). </s><s n="s3.4;p18.48">As a result, they are often mistaken as to be the equivalent of ICM cells. </s><s n="s4.4;p18.48">Figure 3 shows where the embryonic stem cells have originated. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0103d-pic.003"><head>Figure 3. Inner cell mass (in the dark, in the centre) from which embryonic stem cells are generated (left) and a diagram of it on the right. Sources: http:// pub.ucsf.edu/today/ print.php?news_id=200209176 and <seg type="URL" n="http://users.rcn.com/jkimball.ma.ultranet/BiologyPages/S/Stem_Cells.html"/></head></figure><p n="p19.48"><s n="s1.1;p19.48">They are said to be totipotent. </s></p><p n="p20.48"><s n="s1.3;p20.48">However, the isolation of the primitive ectoderm also called epiblast or embryonic ectoderm, (the remaining ICM tissue formed during the second differentiation event of embryonic development), from the mouse readily produces ES cell lines compared to isolated ICM (Zwaka, and Thomson, 2005). </s><s n="s2.3;p20.48">In addition to this, ES cell lines can be derived from single, isolated, mouse primitive ectodermal cells, which is impossible with ICM cells (Zwaka and Thomson, 2005). </s><s n="s3.3;p20.48">These experiments suggested that embryonic stem cells can also originate from the primitive ectoderm, but only a minority of those cells will undergo the full transition. </s></p><p n="p21.48"><s n="s1.1;p21.48">Biologists have been trying to determine what triggers the proliferation and differentiation of the inner cell mass cells and primitive ectodermal cells into embryonic stem cells. </s></p><p n="p22.48"><s n="s1.3;p22.48">The classical markers such as alkaline phosphatase isozymes and some cell surface markers including GCCM-2, TRA-1-60, SSEA-4 and SSE-3 are currently been studied. </s><s n="s2.3;p22.48">The cell surface markers display an epitope which is recognised by highly specific antibodies (Pera, <hi rend="italic">et al</hi>, 2000). </s><s n="s3.3;p22.48">Their exact physiological role in the conversion of the precursor cells remains in the dark, but scientists have been able to elucidate the roles of 2: Oct 4 which appears to maintain the totipotency of the cells derived from the inner cell mass cells, and Fgf5 or fibroblast growth factor which indicates that embryonic stem cells obtained are derived from the primitive ectodermal cell population (Musina, <hi rend="italic">et al</hi>, 2003; Zwaka and Thomson, 2005). </s></p><p n="p23.48"><s n="s1.1;p23.48">Three different pluripotent cells and four different origins, however they are linked to one another somehow (see figure 4) and share many properties. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0103d-fig.001"><head>Figure 4. Origins and derivation of pluripotent stem cells. The 3 types all give rise to the 3 germ layers: ectoderm, mesoderm and endoderm.</head></figure></div3></div2><div2><head rend="underlined bold">II) Properties of stem cells</head><p n="p24.48"><s n="s1.2;p24.48">As mentioned above, one of the fundamental properties of stem cells is that they are unspecialized. </s><s n="s2.2;p24.48">However they are capable of dividing and renewing themselves (for short and long periods) and can give rise to specialized cells. </s></p><div3><head rend="underlined">A) Division and self-maintenance</head><p n="p25.48"><s n="s1.8;p25.48">Unlike the other "ordinary" cells, stem cells may replicate many times, over and over again. </s><s n="s2.8;p25.48">This process is defined as proliferation. </s><s n="s3.8;p25.48">During proliferation, they will divide asymmetrically, or symmetrically (Watt, and Hogan, 2000). </s><s n="s4.8;p25.48">In asymmetric division, a stem cell gives rise to one stem daughter and one daughter that undergoes differentiation (this applies to unicellular organism and invertebrates), or a stem cell gives rise to daughter cells that have a limited probability of being either stem cells or allocated progenitors (this applies to most mammalian tissues) (Watt, and Hogan, 2000). </s><s n="s5.8;p25.48">However, pluripotent stem cells divide symmetrically (in culture) and give rise to 2 daughter cells (Donovan and Gearhart, 2001). </s><s n="s6.8;p25.48">These cells are exact copies of one another. </s><s n="s7.8;p25.48">When symmetrical division goes on for a certain period of time, the cells are said to show long-term self renewal. </s><s n="s8.8;p25.48">Figure 5 shows the process of self renewal. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0103d-fig.002"><head>Figure 5. Pattern of division. The pluripotent stem cell divides and gives rise to 2 identical daughters which in turn give rise to 2 other identical daughter cells each. Source: <seg type="URL" n="http://www.isscr.org/images/Self-Renewal.jpg"/></head></figure><p n="p26.48"><s n="s1.8;p26.48">The state of long-term self-renewal is controlled by extrinsic and intrinsic factors (Watt, and Hogan, 2000). </s><s n="s2.8;p26.48">It is believed that the intrinsic factors make up the stem cell niche. </s><s n="s3.8;p26.48">A niche is defined as the combination of the cellular microenvironment and extra-cellular matrix that serves as a "shelter" for an indefinitely long period of time (Musina, <hi rend="italic">et al</hi>, 2003). </s><s n="s4.8;p26.48">It produces various factors promoting the survival of the stem cells and the maintenance of their undifferentiated state. </s><s n="s5.8;p26.48">The specific factors and conditions of this niche are of great interest to researchers; but, unfortunately, few factors are known for pluripotent stem cells. </s><s n="s6.8;p26.48">These factors are believed to be secreted factors and they are the same factors associated with the cells that have just been derived from their precursors (LIF, STAT 3, bFGF, SSEA4, SSEA3) (Donovan and Gearhart, 2001). </s><s n="s7.8;p26.48">This discovery (which took 20 years of trial and error) allowed pluripotent stem cells to be expanded in culture before any induction of differentiation. </s><s n="s8.8;p26.48">For example, human ES cells rely on embryonic fibroblast feeders to maintain their undifferentiated phenotype (Przyborski, <hi rend="italic">et al</hi>, 2004). </s></p><p n="p27.48"><s n="s1.3;p27.48">It is also believed that the self-renewal process requires cell to cell contact mediated by integral membrane proteins (e.g. the receptor Notch and its ligand Delta) and integrins adhering to the extra cellular matrix (they keep the stem cells in their niche and can directly activate growth factor receptors) (Watt, and Hogan, 2000). </s><s n="s2.3;p27.48">However, these last 2 concepts have only been demonstrated in stem cells other than the pluripotent. </s><s n="s3.3;p27.48">Figure 6 shows a schematic diagram of the differentiation process. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0103d-fig.003"><head>Figure 6. Differentiation process of pluripotent stem cells. Source: <seg type="URL" n="www.bioethics.gov/images/"/> sc_4_differentiation.jpg</head></figure><p n="p28.48"><s n="s1.1;p28.48">The exit from their niche (in vivo) or the removal of those factors (in vitro) is correlated to the transition to irreversible differentiation (Musina, <hi rend="italic">et al</hi>, 2003). </s></p></div3><div3><head rend="underlined">B) Differentiation</head><p n="p29.48"><s n="s1.2;p29.48">It is not known whether it is the exit from their niche that sets off the differentiation or whether it is the spontaneous differentiation that causes the exit. </s><s n="s2.2;p29.48">This relationship has been investigated in laboratories, primarily using mice and by testing with 3 independent assays (carried out by Gearhart and Donovan): in vitro differentiation in a Petri dish, differentiation into teratomas when placed in histocompatible mice and finally, in vivo differentiation when introduced in the blastocoel cavity of a pre-implantation embryo (Donovan and Gearhart, 2001). </s></p><p n="p30.48"><s n="s1.4;p30.48">These experiments have shown that all the pluripotent stem cells can differentiate in vitro and give rise to specialized cells, which represent the 3 primary germ layers in the embryo. </s><s n="s2.4;p30.48">During their differentiation, a decreased level of the markers and increased level of new markers were noticeable (Przyborski, <hi rend="italic">et al</hi>, 2004). </s><s n="s3.4;p30.48">It is also believed that the differentiation is dependant on chemicals secreted by other cells. </s><s n="s4.4;p30.48">For example, cultures of EC stem cells exposed to retinoic acid or HMBA lose their cell surface markers SSEA3, SSEA4, and TRA-1-60 and simultaneously acquire a variety of new antigens (Przyborski, <hi rend="italic">et al</hi>, 2004). </s></p><p n="p31.48"><s n="s1.2;p31.48">The stem cells are also believed to emit internal signals controlled by specific genes which are interspersed across the DNA strands. </s><s n="s2.2;p31.48">These genes still remain to be determined. </s></p><p n="p32.48"><s n="s1.4;p32.48">Another factor that is believed to play a role is a clock mechanism. </s><s n="s2.4;p32.48">It is believed that intracellular clocks control changes in the level of cell cycle promoters or inhibitors and the length of the telomere. </s><s n="s3.4;p32.48">Telomerase activity is very low in humans and its progressive shortening could act as a mitotic clock counting off the divisions until a particular number has been reached. </s><s n="s4.4;p32.48">Once this number has been reached, differentiation can be initiated (Watt, and Hogan, 2000). </s></p><p n="p33.48"><s n="s1.6;p33.48">However, recent published studies have launched a debate and divided scientist into to 2 groups. </s><s n="s2.6;p33.48">These studies suggest that stem cells can give rise to the cells of given tissue which in turn differentiate into cells of other unrelated tissues (Musina, <hi rend="italic">et al</hi>, 2003). </s><s n="s3.6;p33.48">This ability is called plasticity and the process described is termed transdifferentiation or transdetermination. </s><s n="s4.6;p33.48">Not all stem cells have shown this capacity and scientist have come to the conclusion that these stem cells show plasticity in the case of transplantation, organ or tissue injury (Watt and Hogan, 2000). </s><s n="s5.6;p33.48">In the case of transplant, these cells may undergo transdifferentiation when established in a new and suitable stem cell niche. </s><s n="s6.6;p33.48">This property is intensively being analysed in the hematopoietic stem cells but are assumed to be a feature of pluripotent stem cells. </s></p><p n="p34.48"><s n="s1.1;p34.48">These amazing assets could lead to the treatment of devastating diseases. </s></p></div3></div2><div2><head rend="underlined bold">III) Medical potentials and ethical issues </head><div3><head rend="underlined">A) Medical applications </head><p n="p35.48"><s n="s1.4;p35.48">The properties of stem cells open a new window to researchers in their quest against diseases and injuries. </s><s n="s2.4;p35.48">Stem cells have been discovered to have many medical applications. </s><s n="s3.4;p35.48">They can be use dot understand the causes of early pregnancy loss, toxic effects of new drugs on early embryonic cells (which are more sensitive than adult cells) but their most important use is their transplant to treat diseases and injuries (Wert and Mummery, 2003). </s><s n="s4.4;p35.48">Examples of those are neurodegenerative disorders (Alzheimer's disease, Parkinson's disease), spinal cord injury, liver cell damage, hematopoeitic diseases (leukemias and lymphomas), stroke and arthritis (Gearhart, 1998; Wert and Mummery, 2003; Musina, <hi rend="italic">et al</hi>, 2003). </s></p><p n="p36.48"><s n="s1.3;p36.48">Many experiments with mice have demonstrated success in mice: neuronal cells derived from human EC cells after treatment with retinoic acid have improved motor and cognitive deficits in rats with stroke. </s><s n="s2.3;p36.48">Most of the diseases (with the exception of stroke and blood diseases) are the targets of embryonic stem cells. </s><s n="s3.3;p36.48">Embryonic stem cells appear to be very prospective in regenerative medicine (Gearhart, 1998; Wert and Mummery, 2003; Musina, <hi rend="italic">et al</hi>, 2003). </s></p><p n="p37.48"><s n="s1.2;p37.48">The use of embryonic stem cells must be both safe and effective. </s><s n="s2.2;p37.48">Three key safety issues have been considered: derived cells must be histocompatible with every individual to avoid the problem of tissue rejection during transplantation due to the polymorphism of human populations; derived cells and transplanted cells must not form tumours in the host; and pluripotent stem cells derived from embryos and culture on feeders layers containing serum must be infectious agents free (Donovan and Gearhart, 2001). </s></p><p n="p38.48"><s n="s1.5;p38.48">The first key issue can be followed be using 2 methods: therapeutic cloning and genetic modification. </s><s n="s2.5;p38.48">Therapeutic cloning also known as somatic cell nuclear transfer (SCNT) involves the nucleus from an adult, mature donor cell to be introduced into the cytoplasm of an enucleated oocyte to create a cloned embryo (Hochedlinger and Jaenisch, 2003; Fischbach and Fischbach, 2004). </s><s n="s3.5;p38.48">Stem cells derived will be derived from that embryo and are genetically similar to the cells of the donor. </s><s n="s4.5;p38.48">It is therefore less likely that the proteins produced will be recognized as foreign and trigger an immune response in the host (Fischbach and Fischbach, (2004). </s><s n="s5.5;p38.48">Figure 7 shows the different steps of this method. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0103d-pic.004"><head>Figure.7. Different step of therapeutic cloning and its clinical application. Source: Fischbach and Fischbach, 2004. The Journal of Clinical Investigation. 114 (10), 1364-1370.</head></figure><p n="p39.48"><s n="s1.2;p39.48">Genetic modification involves homologous recombination of existing stem lines to create a compatible stem cell to the patient. </s><s n="s2.2;p39.48">However, these techniques are very difficult (SCNT requires many attempts since most embryo created by SCNT are malformed and die in utero and the length of time between reprogramming and the start of zygotic transcription must be considered (Fischbach and Fischbach, 2004; Hochedlinger and Jaenisch, 2003). </s></p><p n="p40.48"><s n="s1.3;p40.48">The second key issue has been raised by the ability of EC, ES, and EG cells to form tumours in histocompatible organisms. </s><s n="s2.3;p40.48">It has therefore been suggested to use differentiated cells rather than non-differentiated stem cells for transplantation. </s><s n="s3.3;p40.48">Research is therefore required on how to deliver cells to the appropriate site in the patient, to ensure they survive, to integrate in the host tissues and adopt appropriate function (Wert and Mummery; Donovan and Gearhart, 2001). </s></p><p n="p41.48"><s n="s1.1;p41.48">The third key safety issue requires development in human stem cells in defined, serum-free medium with purified recombinant growth factors and on defined extracellular matrix (Donovan and Gearhart, 2001). </s></p><p n="p42.48"><s n="s1.6;p42.48">These methods also require sources of human ES cells. </s><s n="s2.6;p42.48">There are various sources at the moment (e.g. spare IVF embryos) but what happens when these sources are depleted? </s><s n="s3.6;p42.48">Should embryos be created just for cloning purposes? </s><s n="s4.6;p42.48">When does life begin? </s><s n="s5.6;p42.48">What are the regulations around the use of hES cells? </s><s n="s6.6;p42.48">All these questions show another aspect of the stem cells which are the ethical issues arising. </s></p></div3><div3><head rend="underlined">B) Policy and ethics</head><p n="p43.48"><s n="s1.1;p43.48">The questions that are currently being debated are: when does life begin and is it justified to create embryos for cloning purposes? </s></p><p n="p44.48"><s n="s1.2;p44.48">The beginning of life can be defined as the moment of conception but this relies on an assumption about the value of a potential life (Fischbach and Fischbach, 2004). </s><s n="s2.2;p44.48">The argument scientists are giving is that at 14 days, the blastocyst has no central nervous system; therefore it has no feelings whatsoever (Fischbach and Fischbach, 2004). </s></p><p n="p45.48"><s n="s1.5;p45.48">Several commissions (National Bioethics advisory commission, the national academy of sciences advisory committee) have been exploring the ethical issues surrounding this matter. </s><s n="s2.5;p45.48">They have to consider 2 perspectives: a fetalist perspective and a feminist perspective (Wert and Mummery, 2003). </s><s n="s3.5;p45.48">These 2 perspectives underlie the same problem: the use of a potential life and women purely as instruments with no benefit at all for them. </s><s n="s4.5;p45.48">But can this be justified, in the case of the depletion of the current sources of embryos, they could treat many diseases that are fatal and save lives. </s><s n="s5.5;p45.48">However, the commissions are concerned that if the creation of embryos is permitted (which would mean destroying an organism that has the potential to develop into a human being), then it may open doors to more destructive acts (Fischbach and Fischbach, 2004). </s></p><p n="p46.48"><s n="s1.2;p46.48">To date, the use of stem cell derived from created embryos as well as embryos stored frozen in IVF clinics is forbidden by article 18 of the European convention on human rights and biomedicine (Wert and Mummery, 2003; Fischbach and Fischbach, 2004). </s><s n="s2.2;p46.48">Nevertheless, the ban of the derivation of stem cell from embryos through governmental sponsorship (public law 107-78, section 513a) has lead to the research being sponsored through private and corporate funding (Gearhart, 1998). </s></p></div3></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">Conclusion:</head><p n="p47.48"><s n="s1.3;p47.48">Stem cells, especially pluripotent stem cells are of great interest in the research field. </s><s n="s2.3;p47.48">These cells although very different from one another and derived from different origins are connected by their amazing properties and medical potential. </s><s n="s3.3;p47.48">Table 1 summarizes the different and important aspects reviewed. </s></p><table id="BAWE_0103d-tab.001"><head>Table 1. Summary table of the aspects of pluripotent stem cells in humans.</head><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p48.48"><s n="s1.5;p48.48">The importance and great potential of pluripotent stem cells has been recognized amongst the different communities (scientific, clergy, governmental) but have also raised concerns about their sources and use. </s><s n="s2.5;p48.48">If the creation of embryos for the derivation of pluripotent stem cells is reconsidered and allowed, what criteria will be used for cell-based therapies? </s><s n="s3.5;p48.48">Could the use of embryo be just allowed for therapeutic cloning? </s><s n="s4.5;p48.48">Adult stem cells might be the answer as there are less ethical issues surrounding them. </s><s n="s5.5;p48.48">But biologists are still trying to find ways to grow them in cell culture and manipulate them to generate specific cell types. </s></p></div1></body><back><div1 type="bibliography"><head rend="underlined bold">Bibliography</head><div2 type="bibliography"><head rend="bold">Journals</head><p>Donovan, P.J. and Gearhart, J., (2001). The end of the beginning for pluripotent stem cells. Nature. 414, 92-97.</p><p>Donovan, P.J. and de Miguel, M.P., (2003). Turning germ cells into stem cells. Current opinion in genetics and development. 13, 463-471.</p><p>Fischbach, G. D. and Fischbach, R. L., (2004). Stem cells: science, policy and ethics. The journal of clinical investigation. 114 (10), 1364-1370. </p><p>Gearhart, J., (1998). New potential for human embryonic stem cells. Cell biology. 282 (5391), 1061-1062.</p><p>Hochedlinger, K. and Jaenisch, R., (2003). Nuclear transplantation, embryonic stem cells and the potential for cell therapy. The New England journal of medicine. 349 (3), 275-286.</p><p>Musina, R.A., Yegorov, Y.Y., and Belyavsky, A.V., (2003).Stem cells: properties and prospective medical applications. Molecular biology. 38 (4), 563-577.</p><p>Pera, M.F, Reubinoff, B., and Trouson, A., (2000). Human embryonic stem cells. Journal of cell science. 113, 5-10.</p><p>Przyborski, S. A., Chrislie, V.B. Hayman, M.W., Stewart, R., and Horrocks, G.M, (2004). Human embryonal carcinoma stem cells: Models of embryonic development in humans. Stem cells and development. 13, 400-408.</p><p>Wert, G. and Mummery, C., (2003). Human embryonic stem cells: research, ethics and policy. Human reproduction. 18 (4), 672-682.</p><p>Watt, F. M. and Hogan, B. L. M., (2000). Out of Eden: Stem cells and their niches. Science.287 (5457), 1427-1431.</p><p>Zwaka, T.P. and Thomson, J. A., (2005). A germ cell origin of embryonic stem cells? Development.132, 227-233.</p></div2><div2 type="bibliography"><head rend="bold">Websites</head><p>The official national institutes of health resource for stem cell research. <seg type="URL" n="http://stemcells.nih.gov/info/basics/basics2.asp"/></p></div2></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
