<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_0109b" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Report on the measurement of g, the ratio of specific heats, for different gases. (Experiment M4)</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note/></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">1</p><p n="date">unknown</p><p n="module title">Physics Laboratory</p><p n="module code">PX110</p><p n="genre family">Methodology recount</p><p n="discipline">Physics</p><p n="disciplinary group">PS</p><p n="grade">M</p><p n="number of authors">unknown</p><p n="number of words">3103</p><p n="number of s-units">137</p><p n="number of p">59</p><p n="number of tables">3</p><p n="number of figures">1</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">19</p><p n="number of lists">0</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">13</p><p n="abstract present">abstract present</p><p n="average words per s-unit">22.6</p><p n="average s-units per p">2.3</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">m</p><p n="year of birth">1985</p><p n="first language">English</p><p n="education">UKA</p><p n="course">Mphysics</p><p n="student ID">0109</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><docTitle><titlePart rend="bold">Report on the measurement of (, the ratio of specific heats, for different gases. (Experiment M4)</titlePart></docTitle><titlePart rend="italic"><name type="student name"/></titlePart></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="abstract"><head>Abstract</head><p n="p1.59"><s rend="bold" n="s1.4;p1.59">The ratio of specific heat at constant pressure to the specific heat at constant volume was measured using a variation on the Rüchardt method (Rüchardt 1929). </s><s rend="bold" n="s2.4;p1.59">Values where measured for Air (1.608 ( 0.021 / 1.433 ( 0.023), Nitrogen (1.503 ( 0.020) and Argon (1.866 ( 0.024). </s><s rend="bold" n="s3.4;p1.59">Apart from one of the values calculated for Air these results disagree with accepted values for these gases, and their corresponding theoretical values, which are 1.4, 1.4 and 1.667 respectively. </s><s rend="bold" n="s4.4;p1.59">The errors in these results are discussed, and suggestions are made to improve the experimental setup. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head>1. Introduction</head><p n="p2.59"><s n="s1.3;p2.59">The specific heat of a gas (c) is defined as the amount of heat required in order to change a unit mass, or a unit quantity (i.e. a mole), of a substance by one degree in temperature. </s><s n="s2.3;p2.59">Specific heat can therefore be defined as a proportionality constant between the amount of heat added to a system (Q) and the consequent temperature change (t). </s><s n="s3.3;p2.59">Specific heat is an intensive variable, for a mass (m) it can be found by: </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p3.59"><s n="s1.1;p3.59"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0109b-form.001"/> (1) </s></p><p n="p4.59"><s n="s1.2;p4.59">For any gas there is effectively an infinite number of specific heats, depending on what external variables are held constant, however two notable ones are the value at constant pressure (C <hi rend="sub">p</hi>) and that at constant volume (C <hi rend="sub">v</hi>). </s><s n="s2.2;p4.59">The ratio of specific heats is then defined as: </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p5.59"><s n="s1.1;p5.59"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0109b-form.002"/> (2) </s></p><p n="p6.59"><s n="s1.2;p6.59">This value is an important thermodynamic quantity that gives an insight into the structure of the gas molecules for which it was calculated. </s><s n="s2.2;p6.59">For instance appears in the pressure-volume relation of an adiabatic process, and also in formulas that describe the efficiency of cyclic processes i.e. an internal combustion engine. </s></p><p n="p7.59"><s n="s1.2;p7.59">In principle may be obtained by independently measuring C <hi rend="sub">p</hi> and C <hi rend="sub">v,</hi> however in practice this method is very time consuming. </s><s n="s2.2;p7.59">Instead the value for a gas can be determined from a study of any adiabatic process in which the gas is involved. </s></p><p n="p8.59"><s n="s1.1;p8.59">The earliest recorded method used to calculate is that of Clément-Desormes (Clément-Desormes 1819), which involves the relationship between the pressure of air in a bottle before quickly removing and replacing a bung, the atmospheric pressure, and then the pressure in the bottle once the air returns to the original starting temperature. </s></p><p n="p9.59"><s n="s1.2;p9.59">The method employed in this experiment is the study of adiabatic changes caused by an oscillating piston in a trapped mass of a gas in a tube. </s><s n="s2.2;p9.59">This is a variation on the Rüchardt method (Rüchardt 1929), where was calculated from the period of oscillations of a metal sphere in a glass tube supported by an "air spring", effectively a given volume of air attached to the glass tube in a bottle. </s></p><p n="p10.59"><s n="s1.4;p10.59">In this experiment a cylindrical metal piston, placed between two columns of the same gas, is driven into oscillation by a magnetic coil. </s><s n="s2.4;p10.59">Using a frequency generator the piston is made to oscillate over a range of frequencies. </s><s n="s3.4;p10.59">The frequency at which the piston oscillates with the largest amplitude is recorded, this is known as the resonant frequency. </s><s n="s4.4;p10.59">A value for can then be derived from a simple calculation that includes the resonant frequency, and the parameters of the experiment. </s></p><p n="p11.59"><s n="s1.2;p11.59">In this report I present the values obtained experimentally for three different gases, Air, Nitrogen and Argon. </s><s n="s2.2;p11.59">These values are compared to those predicted by theory, and values obtained from other experiments. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head>2. Theory</head><div2><head rend="bold">2.1 The internal energy of an ideal gas</head><p n="p12.59"><s n="s1.5;p12.59">The addition of heat results in an increase in a substances internal molecular energy. </s><s n="s2.5;p12.59">This molecular energy comprises a variety of different kinetic energies associated with the motion of the individual molecules. </s><s n="s3.5;p12.59">Depending on the type of molecule these kinetic energies can be divided into velocity components in translational, rotational and vibrational directions. </s><s n="s4.5;p12.59">The number of velocity components needed to describe the complete motion of a molecule is called the number of degrees of freedom (n). </s><s n="s5.5;p12.59">According to the principle of equipartition of energy each degree of freedom (either linear or angular) has on average an associated kinetic energy per molecule (U <hi rend="sub">n</hi>) of: </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p13.59"><s n="s1.1;p13.59"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0109b-form.003"/> (3) </s></p><p n="p14.59"><s n="s1.1;p14.59">where k is the Boltzmann constant and T is the absolute temperature. </s></p><p n="p15.59"><s n="s1.2;p15.59">For a monatomic gas at constant volume all added heat energy goes into an increase in random translational molecular kinetic energy. </s><s n="s2.2;p15.59">Monatomic gases therefore have three degrees of freedom (n=3), with velocity components V <hi rend="sub">x</hi>, V <hi rend="sub">y</hi> and V <hi rend="sub">z</hi> in the translational direction. </s></p><p n="p16.59"><s n="s1.3;p16.59">For a diatomic gas, however, additional heat is required to supply the increased vibrational and rotational energies as well as the translational energies. </s><s n="s2.3;p16.59">Diatomic gases therefore possess the three degrees of translational motion, as well as two degrees of rotational motion, corresponding to rotations about two mutually perpendicular axes, and two degrees pf vibrational freedom, corresponding to vibration of the atoms along the inter-nuclear axes. </s><s n="s3.3;p16.59">Results from quantum theory show that the degrees of freedom associated with vibration are not operative at room temperature or below, meaning for this experiment a diatomic gas can be thought of as having five degrees of freedom (n=5). </s></p><p n="p17.59"><s n="s1.1;p17.59">The ratio of specific heats can be found by theory using this relation: </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p18.59"><s n="s1.1;p18.59"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0109b-form.004"/> (4) </s></p><p n="p19.59"><s n="s1.5;p19.59">When a system experiences a temperature increase, but remains at a constant volume, the system does no work on its surroundings. </s><s n="s2.5;p19.59">The change in internal energy (U) of the system is equal to the heat added (Q). </s><s n="s3.5;p19.59">If the system undergoes a temperature increase, but remains at a constant temperature, then the volume must increase. </s><s n="s4.5;p19.59">This means the system does work on its surroundings, and the change in internal energy (U) is equal to the heat added (Q) plus the work done (W). </s><s n="s5.5;p19.59">This is also known as the first law of thermodynamics: </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p20.59"><s n="s1.1;p20.59"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0109b-form.005"/> (5) </s></p><p n="p21.59"><s n="s1.3;p21.59">Equation (5) shows that the heat input for a constant pressure process must therefore be greater than that for a constant volume process, in order to get the same change in internal energy. </s><s n="s2.3;p21.59">This is because additional energy must be supplied to account for the work done (W) during the expansion. </s><s n="s3.3;p21.59">It is for this reason that the value for C <hi rend="sub">v</hi> and C <hi rend="sub">p</hi> are different, the relationship between these two variables (), as we have shown, tells us a lot about the system it describes. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">2.2 The Rüchardt Method</head><p n="p22.59"><s n="s1.2;p22.59">To find for a given gas using the Rüchardt method, we must apply Newton's II law to the vibrating piston of mass (m) inside the glass tube. </s><s n="s2.2;p22.59">The force involved in the pistons oscillation has two components, a hydrodynamic component resulting from displacement of gas by the moving piston (K), as well as the component on one side of the piston due to the magnetic and gravitational forces (K <hi rend="sub">s</hi>). </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p23.59"><s n="s1.1;p23.59"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0109b-form.006"/> (6) </s></p><p n="p24.59"><s n="s1.1;p24.59">If we consider only small pressure and volume changes then we can assume this adiabatic process is reversible and therefore obeys the Poisson equation: </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p25.59"><s n="s1.1;p25.59"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0109b-form.007"/> (7) </s></p><p n="p26.59"><s n="s1.2;p26.59">where p is the pressure and V is the volume of the gas. </s><s n="s2.2;p26.59">Differentiating this equation shows that for a quasi-static adiabatic change: </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p27.59"><s n="s1.1;p27.59"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0109b-form.008"/> (8) </s></p><p n="p28.59"><s n="s1.1;p28.59">The force F acting on the piston due to the change in pressure P can be written: </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p29.59"><s n="s1.1;p29.59"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0109b-form.009"/> (9) </s></p><p n="p30.59"><s n="s1.1;p30.59">This force is quasi-elastic, in the form F=-kz with a spring constant: </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p31.59"><s n="s1.1;p31.59"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0109b-form.010"/> (10) </s></p><p n="p32.59"><s n="s1.1;p32.59">If we assume that the frictional damping is negligible then the resonant frequency f of the system is given by: </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p33.59"><s n="s1.1;p33.59"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0109b-form.011"/> (11) </s></p><p n="p34.59"><s n="s1.3;p34.59">For the situation where both bungs are in place we use the substitution <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0109b-form.012"/>, and likewise if both bungs are removed then <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0109b-form.013"/>. </s><s n="s2.3;p34.59">Finally if only one bung is present <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0109b-form.014"/>. </s><s n="s3.3;p34.59">The following solutions for gamma can then be derived: </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p35.59"><s n="s1.1;p35.59"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0109b-form.015"/> (12) </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p36.59"><s n="s1.1;p36.59"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0109b-form.016"/> (13) </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head>3. Experimental Details</head><figure id="BAWE_0109b-pic.001"><head rend="italic">Figure 1 - A schematic diagram of the equipment used in the experiment. </head></figure><p n="p37.59"><s n="s1.4;p37.59">The metal piston was placed equidistant from either end of the glass tube, between the encircling magnetic coils. </s><s n="s2.4;p37.59">An A.C. current was driven through the coil forcing the piston to oscillate. </s><s n="s3.4;p37.59">A frequency generator, which controlled the A.C. current through the magnetic coil, was used to alter the oscillation frequency of the piston. </s><s n="s4.4;p37.59">At the natural frequency of the system clear amplitude resonance is observed, this frequency value is recorded. </s></p><p n="p38.59"><s n="s1.2;p38.59">The metal piston was fitted snugly into the tube, in order to prevent leakage of gas from one side of the cylinder to the other, and was aligned correctly so that it oscillated freely in the tube with no resistance to motion. </s><s n="s2.2;p38.59">A sliding sleeve placed around the tube was used to mark the amplitude of oscillation at different frequencies. </s></p><p n="p39.59"><s n="s1.2;p39.59">The resonant frequency for air was determined with two bungs in place (f <hi rend="sub">2</hi>), one bung at one end (f <hi rend="sub">1</hi>), and with both ends empty (f <hi rend="sub">0</hi>). </s><s n="s2.2;p39.59">The tube is then filled with Argon, and later Nitrogen, using a gas filling system and (f <hi rend="sub">2</hi>) is found for these two gases. </s></p><p n="p40.59"><s n="s1.3;p40.59">It is noted that the response time between adjusting the frequency generator value, and observing the requested change in oscillation of the piston was of the order of a couple of seconds. </s><s n="s2.3;p40.59">The delay was significant enough to hinder the determination of the resonant frequency value (f <hi rend="sub">0</hi>) for air. </s><s n="s3.3;p40.59">This was because the response was sporadic, and the frequency produced by the generator appeared to oscillate of its own accord. </s></p><p n="p41.59"><s n="s1.3;p41.59">The gas filling system involved pumping the gas into each end of the tube separately, using the gas flow to push the piston to the extremities of the respective end of the tube, thus replacing the air in the tube with the chosen gas. </s><s n="s2.3;p41.59">This process was repeated for each end alternately, opening the bung on the end of the tube sufficiently to allow the air to exit. </s><s n="s3.3;p41.59">It is noted that the use of this system means it is unlikely that the tube is filled completely with the chosen gas. </s></p><p n="p42.59"><s n="s1.4;p42.59">The length of each gas column was measure using a ruler. </s><s n="s2.4;p42.59">The cross-sectional area (A) of the tube was assumed to be that of the piston, this assumption is valid if the piston has a snug fit, and was therefore derived using the diameter of the piston, which is measured using vernier calipers. </s><s n="s3.4;p42.59">The half volume of the tube (V) is then calculated using the cross-sectional area, and the length of the tube (the volume of the piston is allowed for). </s><s n="s4.4;p42.59">The mass of the piston (m) is taken using scales and the temperature and pressure (p) in the lab are noted regularly during the day. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head>4. Results</head><p n="p43.59"><s n="s1.2;p43.59">Three runs were taken for each frequency value, and the average was then calculated. </s><s n="s2.2;p43.59">The values for f <hi rend="sub">0</hi> and f <hi rend="sub">1</hi> were only taken for air, since measurements without a bung in place were impossible to take with this equipment for any other gas. </s></p><p n="p44.59"><s n="s1.3;p44.59">The value for Air, Nitrogen and Argon, was calculated using equation (12) and equation (13). </s><s n="s2.3;p44.59">The value for air was calculated twice, with f <hi rend="sub">2</hi> &amp; f <hi rend="sub">0</hi> and then f <hi rend="sub">2</hi> &amp; f <hi rend="sub">1</hi>, while for Nitrogen and Argon is obtained only using the f <hi rend="sub">2</hi> value for the respective gas, and the f <hi rend="sub">0</hi> value for air. </s><s n="s3.3;p44.59">The results are shown in Table 1. </s></p><table id="BAWE_0109b-tab.001"><head rend="italic">Table 1 - Summary of the Experimental Results</head><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p45.59"><s n="s1.1;p45.59">The expected values are taken from Kaye and Laby's "Tables of Physical &amp; Chemical Constants"(see Table 3), and the theoretical values are derived using equation (4), assuming that for the diatomic gases Air and Nitrogen, n = 5, and for the monatomic gas Argon, n = 3. </s></p><p n="p46.59"><s n="s1.2;p46.59">The error quoted for the experimental value was based on the precision errors of the instruments used in the experiment (see Table 2). </s><s n="s2.2;p46.59">This error was calculated using the standard techniques for manipulating errors. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head>5. Discussions</head><p n="p47.59"><s n="s1.4;p47.59">The experimental values calculated for do not agree with the expected value or theoretical value quoted for in Table 1. </s><s n="s2.4;p47.59">In general the experimental results are larger than expected by <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0109b-form.017"/>, except for the value for Air calculated using f <hi rend="sub">2</hi> &amp; f <hi rend="sub">1</hi>, which is very close to both the expected and theoretical value. </s><s n="s3.4;p47.59">It is noted that the value found for Air is very close to that found for Nitrogen. </s><s n="s4.4;p47.59">This is because Air is composed mostly of Nitrogen, a value of around 77%. </s></p><p n="p48.59"><s n="s1.5;p48.59">The error bounds stated in Table 1 are only precision errors. </s><s n="s2.5;p48.59">It is suggested that the error in these measurements is actually a lot larger than stated, since some errors have not been quantified and used in the error analysis. </s><s n="s3.5;p48.59">For example, these include the human judgment error of which frequency is the resonant frequency of the piston, and in the case of measurements in the gases Argon and Nitrogen, the assumption that the tube is filled completely with the gas and that all remnants of air have been expelled, which is unlikely to be true. </s><s n="s4.5;p48.59">The errors in are more likely to be of the order <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0109b-form.018"/>. </s><s n="s5.5;p48.59">This would bring the value for Air using f <hi rend="sub">2</hi> and f <hi rend="sub">1</hi> to be within the range of the values suggested by theory. </s></p><p n="p49.59"><s n="s1.6;p49.59">The values calculated using the value of f <hi rend="sub">0</hi> for Air remain in disagreement with those values predicted by theory. </s><s n="s2.6;p49.59">It was mentioned earlier in Section 3 that there were experimental problems in determining the value f <hi rend="sub">0</hi> for Air. </s><s n="s3.6;p49.59">It is likely that there is a large error in this value. </s><s n="s4.6;p49.59">This may be due to the piston not being placed correctly in the tube, which would mean the piston would be subjected to friction from the side of the tube, changing the resonant frequency. </s><s n="s5.6;p49.59">Under these circumstances air would also be able to pass from one side of the piston to the other, thus not satisfying the conditions for the experimental theory to be applied. </s><s n="s6.6;p49.59">In this case the force due to the displacement of the gas would be significantly reduced. </s></p><p n="p50.59"><s n="s1.3;p50.59">A possible explanation for the discrepancy in the values of for Nitrogen and Argon is therefore that the calculations for these gases are based on the value f <hi rend="sub">0</hi> for Air. </s><s n="s2.3;p50.59">It has already been suggested that there is a large error in this value, however in an ideal situation it would be the resonant frequency of the actual gas, Argon or Nitrogen, with no bungs in the tube that would be used as opposed to that of Air. </s><s n="s3.3;p50.59">This is one of the limitations of using this experimental setup; it is impossible to find the resonant frequency of the piston for Argon and Nitrogen when a bung is removed from the tube. </s></p><p n="p51.59"><s n="s1.2;p51.59">To analyze the discrepancy in f <hi rend="sub">0</hi> further the ratio of calculated for Air from f <hi rend="sub">2</hi> and f <hi rend="sub">1</hi>, and the calculated for Air from f <hi rend="sub">2</hi> and f <hi rend="sub">0</hi> was taken to try and find a scaling factor that could be used to adjust the values calculated for Argon and Nitrogen. </s><s n="s2.2;p51.59">This would be applicable since these values use the value of f <hi rend="sub">0</hi> for Air in their calculation: </s></p><p n="p52.59"><s n="s1.1;p52.59"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0109b-form.019"/> </s></p><p n="p53.59"><s n="s1.3;p53.59">This ratio gives altered values of = 1.339 for Nitrogen and = 1.663 for Argon. </s><s n="s2.3;p53.59">These values are much closer to those predicted by theory and those taken as accepted values. </s><s n="s3.3;p53.59">This indicates that there is, as suggested, a significant error in the value taken for f <hi rend="sub">0</hi>, and it is likely that this has affected the values derived for Nitrogen and Argon. </s></p><p n="p54.59"><s n="s1.4;p54.59">It is also noted that for Nitrogen and Argon the pressure value used in the calculations was the atmospheric pressure in the lab. </s><s n="s2.4;p54.59">This would have introduced an error in the result, since the pressure in the tube would actually be different to this value, after having had the gas pumped in. </s><s n="s3.4;p54.59">Before drawing conclusions between the accepted value of for Argon, and the experimental value it must also be noted that the accepted value for Argon is given at a temperature of 0C (Table 3), whereas the experimental value was derived for Argon at a temperature of 24C (Table 2). </s><s n="s4.4;p54.59">However, in comparison with some of the other errors discussed in this situation, this temperature difference is likely to have had a negligible effect on the result. </s></p><p n="p55.59"><s n="s1.4;p55.59">In the light of this discussion, it is useful to suggest improvements to the experimental method. </s><s n="s2.4;p55.59">The error in could be significantly reduced for Nitrogen and Argon if a value for f <hi rend="sub">0</hi> could be determined for these gases. </s><s n="s3.4;p55.59">This would require the experiment to be conducted in a chamber filled completely with these gases. </s><s n="s4.4;p55.59">This is not possible with the current laboratory set up. </s></p><p n="p56.59"><s n="s1.2;p56.59">A more easily implemented change would be to measure the pressure inside the tube when Nitrogen or Argon has been pumped in. </s><s n="s2.2;p56.59">This could be done if a gauge was installed on the gas filling system. </s></p><p n="p57.59"><s n="s1.4;p57.59">Torzoal. (2001) suggested a new version of the Rüchardt method to measure the ratio of specific heat of a gas. </s><s n="s2.4;p57.59">A portable microcomputer-based laboratory based on a graphic calculator, an interface, two commercial sensors (sonar and barometric) along with a homemade temperature sensor were used to record the time evolution of temperature, pressure and volume, oscillating around an equilibrium value. </s><s n="s3.4;p57.59">The value is then calculated using the slope of a graph plotting the measured relative changes in pressure against the measured relative changes in volume, and substituting this into equation (8). </s><s n="s4.4;p57.59">It is likely that this alternative method would find experimental results that closer to the predicted values than found in this experiment. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head>6. Conclusion</head><p n="p58.59"><s n="s1.7;p58.59">The ratio of specific heat was measured for Air, Nitrogen and Argon using the Rüchardt apparatus. </s><s n="s2.7;p58.59">The experimental value of found for Air, when calculated using values based on the tube having both or one of the bungs in place, agreed with the value predicted from theory and a referenced accepted value. </s><s n="s3.7;p58.59">However this was only after having re-assessed the significance of errors in the experiment. </s><s n="s4.7;p58.59">The value for obtained for Nitrogen and Argon, as well as the value for Air when based upon the piston oscillating with no bungs in the tube, contained large discrepancies with the values predicted by theory. </s><s n="s5.7;p58.59">Analysis of the ratio between the two values found for Air suggests that there is an error in the measurement of f <hi rend="sub">0</hi>, the resonant frequency of the piston with no bungs in place. </s><s n="s6.7;p58.59">It is also noted that the lack of measurement of the pressure inside the tube for Argon and Nitrogen, and the inability to measure f <hi rend="sub">0</hi> for these gases may have contributed to the error in the result for the ratio of specific heat of these gases. </s><s n="s7.7;p58.59">Amendments to the experimental set-up that addressed these errors were discussed. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head>7. Data Tables</head><table id="BAWE_0109b-tab.002"><head>Table 2 - Experimental values obtained. Note error quoted is the precision error of the instrument used in the measurement of the value.</head><row><cell/></row></table><table id="BAWE_0109b-tab.003"><head>Table 3 - values quoted from Kaye and Laby, and the temperature values for which they apply.</head><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p59.59"/></div1></body><back><div1 type="bibliography"><head>8. References</head><p>Young H.D., &amp; Freedman R.A., Sears and Zemansky's university physics: with modern physics - 11<hi rend="sup">th</hi> ed.</p><p>Clément-Desormes N., 1819, Physics, 89, 321, 428</p><p>Kaye G.W.C., &amp; Laby T.H., "Tables of Physical &amp; Chemical Constants", page 15, Longman Scientific and Technical, Edition 15 </p><p>Rüchardt E., 1929, "Eine Einfache Methode zur Bestimmung von C<hi rend="sub">p</hi> / C<hi rend="sub">v</hi>", Phys. Z. 30, 58-59 </p><p>Torzo G., Delfitto G., Pecori B., Scatturin P., 2001, Am., J., Phys., 69, 11</p></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
