<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_0112b" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Organisation of Centromeric Chromatin in Mammals</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">deleted: page numbers
deleted: Word Count = 2843 </note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">2</p><p n="date">2004-03</p><p n="module title">BS/MB/VIR/CB assessments</p><p n="module code">BS241</p><p n="genre family">Explanation</p><p n="discipline">Biological Sciences</p><p n="disciplinary group">LS</p><p n="grade">M</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">3484</p><p n="number of s-units">133</p><p n="number of p">34</p><p n="number of tables">1</p><p n="number of figures">6</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">0</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">0</p><p n="abstract present">abstract present</p><p n="average words per s-unit">26.2</p><p n="average s-units per p">3.9</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">f</p><p n="year of birth">1984</p><p n="first language">English</p><p n="education">UKA</p><p n="course">Biological Sciences with Molecular Genetics</p><p n="student ID">0112</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><docTitle><titlePart rend="underlined">Organisation of Centromeric Chromatin in Mammals</titlePart></docTitle><titlePart rend="underlined">University number <name type="student ID"/></titlePart></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="abstract"><head rend="underlined">Abstract</head><p n="p1.34"><s n="s1.4;p1.34">Within eukaryotic cells the DNA is not sited in the nucleus on its own, inside the nucleus the DNA is associated with various proteins and RNA forming a complex structure called chromatin. </s><s n="s2.4;p1.34">The total length of pure DNA that composes a chromosome is much greater than the actual measured length of a chromosome found in mitotic cells. </s><s n="s3.4;p1.34">This means the DNA must be condensed and pack to convert it from a long narrow structure to a dense thick rod, it is the chromatin proteins that cause this DNA packing. </s><s n="s4.4;p1.34">The structure of chromatin varies across species and across individual chromosomes; this essay aims to address the organisation centromeric chromatin in mammals. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined">Introduction</head><p n="p2.34"><s n="s1.5;p2.34">The proteins associated with DNA in the nucleus are all positively charged and can be divided into two simple groups: histone and non-histone protein. </s><s n="s2.5;p2.34">Histones are essential for the structural packing of DNA and carry a large positive charge. </s><s n="s3.5;p2.34">This is achieved by the high percentage of lysine and arginine residues present and allows the protein to bond electrostatically to negatively charged phosphate groups located on the DNA backbone. </s><s n="s4.5;p2.34">X-ray diffraction studies show that chromatin produces regularly spaced diffraction rings suggesting a repeating structure of histone-DNA complexes; this diffraction pattern dissipates when the histones are removed. </s><s n="s5.5;p2.34">There are five main variations of the histone protein. </s></p><table id="BAWE_0112b-tab.001"><head rend="italic">Table 1: Types of histone protein</head><row><cell/></row></table><figure id="BAWE_0112b-fig.001"><head rend="italic">Figure 1: The Nucleosome. Histone octamer shown in green, DNA shown in pink and spacer histone in purple. Sourced from: Cummings, M. R. Klug, W. S. "Concepts of genetics" Prentice Hall, seventh edition, chapter 11 page 285</head></figure><p n="p3.34"><s n="s1.9;p3.34">The histones H2A and H2B pair up to form the tetramer (H2A)<hi rend="sub">2</hi> . </s><s n="s2.9;p3.34">(H2B)<hi rend="sub">2</hi> as do H3 and H4 forming (H3)<hi rend="sub">2</hi> . </s><s n="s3.9;p3.34">(H4)<hi rend="sub">2</hi>. </s><s n="s4.9;p3.34">These two tetramers then join up to form an octamer structure called the nucleosome. </s><s n="s5.9;p3.34">The nucleosome is in the form of a flattened disk measuring 6nm by 11nm, this shape is deigned to be the structural basis for the coiling of DNA (figure 1). </s><s n="s6.9;p3.34">A total of 146 base pairs of DNA can be warped around each nucleosome in a 1.75 left-handed superhelical resolution (Krude <hi rend="italic">et al</hi> 1999), reducing the length of the DNA strand by a third of its original length. </s><s n="s7.9;p3.34">The function of histone H1 is as a spacer molecule that binds to the linker DNA between the lengths of DNA that are wrapped around the histones octamer. </s><s n="s8.9;p3.34">Figure 2 shows an electron micrograph of this first level of DNA condensation. </s><s n="s9.9;p3.34">If this structure is treated with micrococcal nuclease only the linker regions of DNA are available to be cleaved because the nucleosomes protect the DNA that is coiled round them. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0112b-pic.001"><head rend="italic">Figure 2: Dark field electron micrograph of nucleosomes present in chromatin derived from chicken erythrocyte nucleus. Sourced from: Cummings, M. R. Klug, W. S. "Concepts of genetics " Prentice Hall, seventh edition, chapter 11, page 284</head></figure><p n="p4.34"><s n="s1.2;p4.34">When the salt conditions are high the nucleosome bead structure (figure 2) assumes a coiled form called a solenoid. </s><s n="s2.2;p4.34">This structure is 30nm in diameter and is stabilized by the H1 histone which runs down its centre (figure 3). </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0112b-fig.002"><head rend="italic">Figure 3: Solenoid structure: Histone octamers shown in green, DNA shown in pink and spacer histone in purple. Sourced from: Cummings, M. R. Klug, W. S. "Concepts of genetics" Prentice Hall, seventh edition, chapter 11 page 285 </head></figure><p n="p5.34"><s n="s1.3;p5.34">There is still a third level of packing required to form the mitotic chromosome. </s><s n="s2.3;p5.34">The 30nm solenoid forms a series of looped domains that condenses the DNA further into a 300nm wide fibre. </s><s n="s3.3;p5.34">The fibre is then coiled into the chromosome arms that constitute a chromatid. </s></p><p n="p6.34"><s n="s1.6;p6.34">Fine detail structure studies have shown that the histone protein is not all tightly structured; several of the proteins possess tails which can act as sites for histone modification. </s><s n="s2.6;p6.34">H3 and H2B have tails that protrude through the minor grove channels of the DNA helix; H4 has a tail that forms a connection with adjacent histone molecules. </s><s n="s3.6;p6.34">The first of the modification and most common is acetylation by the enzyme acetyltransferase (HAT). </s><s n="s4.6;p6.34">This enzyme adds an acetyl group to lysine residues which neutralises its positive chare therefore altering the net charge of the protein. </s><s n="s5.6;p6.34">This action appears to open up the chromatin fibre and possibly altering gene expression. </s><s n="s6.6;p6.34">Methylation can occur to both lysine and arginine residues and phosphorylation of serine and histidine residues, both are thought to alter gene expression and the levels of phosphorylation seem to characterise different stages of the cell cycle. </s></p><p n="p7.34"><s n="s1.5;p7.34">The chromatin structure is not uniformed over the entire chromosome, observation during interphase show that some areas of chromatin remain condensed while others uncoil. </s><s n="s2.5;p7.34">It is these uncoiled regions that's possess the transcriptionaly active parts of the genome (protein coding regions) and has been given the term euchromatin. </s><s n="s3.5;p7.34">There is another form of chromatin that remains condensed during interphase, this is heterochromatin. </s><s n="s4.5;p7.34">It is located at the telomeres and in the centromeres and shows little or no transcription regions. </s><s n="s5.5;p7.34">This type of chromatin is believed to play a mechanical role in chromosome structure and to aid the segregation of the chromosomes during cell division. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined">Centromere</head><p n="p8.34"><s n="s1.5;p8.34">Centromeres are highly complex chromosomal substructures involved in essential aspects of chromosome transmission during cell division. </s><s n="s2.5;p8.34">The centromere/kinetochore complex is responsible for directing chromosome movements in mitosis and for progression of mitotic events at the transition between metaphase and anaphase. </s><s n="s3.5;p8.34">For accurate chromosome segregation interactions must occur between the centromere/kinetochore complex and the spindle apparatus. </s><s n="s4.5;p8.34">In most organisms the centromere appears as a constitutively functioning structure that exists at a defined position of a monocentric chromosome. </s><s n="s5.5;p8.34">In some eukaryotic organisms (not mammals) centromere activities are distributed throughout the entire length of the chromosome forming a holocentric structure (Choo <hi rend="italic">et al</hi> 2001). </s></p><p n="p9.34"><s n="s1.8;p9.34">During cell division centromeric DNA attaches to spindle microtubules through a proteinaceous structure, this is the kinetochore. </s><s n="s2.8;p9.34">The outer region of the kinetochore assembles when the chromosome condenses to allow the microtubules to attach, and will dissociate again after chromosome segregation. </s><s n="s3.8;p9.34">The inner kinetochore is present in the DNA at all points of the cell cycle and is formed by special centromeric chromatin and associated foundation proteins (Henikoft <hi rend="italic">et al</hi> 2005). </s><s n="s4.8;p9.34">Despite the conserved function of centromeres across species they lack any conserved DNA sequence, but most centromeres do show a particular similarity. </s><s n="s5.8;p9.34">That is that they comprise of long stretches of short tandem repeats called "satellite DNA sequences" that are only found in the centromere and the surrounding pericentric heterochromatin. </s><s n="s6.8;p9.34">In humans this repeat is knows as α-satellite DNA and this 171 base pair monomer is arranged in a large head-to-tail tandem array. </s><s n="s7.8;p9.34">Although this sequence is found in all normal human centromeres it is not the deciding factor of centromere location. </s><s n="s8.8;p9.34">In stable 'dicentric' chromosomes where due to rearrangement, a chromosome contains two centromeres, the centromeric function is often lost from one of the two α-satellite repeats (Amor <hi rend="italic">et al</hi> 2004). </s></p><p n="p10.34"><s n="s1.7;p10.34">The second piece of evidence to support the theory that DNA sequence is not determining factor for centromere location is the presence of neocentromeres. </s><s n="s2.7;p10.34">These are ectopic centromeres that originate from normal noncentromeric regions of a chromosome and therefore do not contain the α-satellite repeat (Choo <hi rend="italic">et al</hi> 2001). </s><s n="s3.7;p10.34">A neocentromere shows an ability to function like a true centromere, and there have been a small number of documented cases to prove it. </s><s n="s4.7;p10.34">A Neocentromere may take on the role of a centromere when the true centromere has been removed from the chromosome. </s><s n="s5.7;p10.34">This is possible due to rearrangement and breakage of the chromosome, leaving a dicentric chromosome and a centromere devoid chromosome. </s><s n="s6.7;p10.34">However due to a lack of α-satellite repeat the formation of the centromere must take place via a method not linked to DNA sequence. </s><s n="s7.7;p10.34">Epigenetic factors must play a role. </s></p><p n="p11.34"><s n="s1.3;p11.34">Thirdly the presence of heterochromatin does not define the centromere, it is known that heterochromatin is present around the centromere but it is also found at chromosome telomeres. </s><s n="s2.3;p11.34">If heterochromatin is the deciding factor in centromere development then telomeres would demonstrate some of there activity. </s><s n="s3.3;p11.34">This confirmed that merely the presence of heterochromatin does not create a centromere. </s></p><p n="p12.34"><s n="s1.2;p12.34">This evidence shows that the location and function of the centromere is dependant upon more than just a DNA sequence and general chromatin type, the molecules that comprise the centromeres chromatin must give the centromere its function. </s><s n="s2.2;p12.34">Centromeric chromatin must be different on a molecular level to that of normal chromatin. </s></p><p n="p13.34"><s n="s1.9;p13.34">Centromere location is determined by a collection of at least six kinetochore foundation proteins that assemble in a hierarchical and co-dependant fashion. </s><s n="s2.9;p13.34">The kinetochore is a densely staining fibrillar region with the centromere, to which spindle microtubules attach during meiosis or mitosis. </s><s n="s3.9;p13.34">The kinetochore proteins bind to both the DNA and the heterochromatin that is located either side of the core centromere region. </s><s n="s4.9;p13.34">In humans the kinetochore assembles on the α-I subfamily of α-satellite DNA repeats. </s><s n="s5.9;p13.34">These six proteins are CENP-A, CENP-B, CENP-C, CENP-H, CENP-I and the most recent addition hMis12. </s><s n="s6.9;p13.34">The first three are thought to associate with centromeric DNA therefore directly forming the centromere chromatin (Politi <hi rend="italic">et al</hi> 2002), CENP-H, CENP-I and hMis12 are thought to form part of the kinetochore structure. </s><s n="s7.9;p13.34">The α-I satellite DNA repeats contain a 17 base pair CENP-B box motif, to which this protein will bind. </s><s n="s8.9;p13.34">These six proteins (excluding CENP-B) are essential for centromere activity and are also found at neocentromeres. </s><s n="s9.9;p13.34">This demonstrates that this chromatin protein is more of a deciding factor for centromere location then DNA sequence. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined">CENP-A</head><p n="p14.34"><s n="s1.4;p14.34">CENP-A a 17kDa protein is present in humans and similar homologues exist in mice and in all other eukaryotic organisms studied (Sullivan <hi rend="italic">et al</hi> 2001). </s><s n="s2.4;p14.34">The protein contains a histone folding domain at the C-terminus that is 62% identical to H3 C-terminal and with a variable N-terminus. </s><s n="s3.4;p14.34">Loss of the protein in mice leads to the mis-localisation of some kinetochore proteins and over expression causes no functional kinetochore to be produced (Amor <hi rend="italic">et al</hi> 2004). </s><s n="s4.4;p14.34">It is now widely accepted that CENP-A replaces histone 3 within chromatin nucleosomes. </s></p><p n="p15.34"><s n="s1.1;p15.34">A study by Blower <hi rend="italic">et al</hi> 2002 demonstrated that not all H3 is replace by the CENP-A protein in centromeres (figure 4) but appears that H3 and CENP-A are found in alternately nucleosomes. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0112b-fig.003"><head><hi rend="italic">Figure 4:</hi> <hi rend="italic">Human CENP-A (green) and H3 (red) are interspersed with infrequent overlap. Top line: Both H3 and CENP-A staining, second line: only H3 stained, bottom line: only CENP-A staining. Scale bar is 10 microns.</hi> Sourced from: Blower <hi rend="italic">et al</hi> 2002</head></figure><p n="p16.34"><s n="s1.2;p16.34">The number of CENP-A spots varies greatly across human chromosomes which suggest that CENP-A containing regions or the amount CENP-A nucleosomes varies widely. </s><s n="s2.2;p16.34">When Blower <hi rend="italic"> et al</hi> 2002 completed there staining experiment they discovered that only two thirds of the α-satellite DNA repeats were stained, leaving the possibility that not all α-satellites are involved in kinetochore formation. </s></p><p n="p17.34"><s n="s1.2;p17.34">CENP-A synthesis appears to be linked to centromere replication during mid-S phase to early G <hi rend="sub">2</hi> phase. </s><s n="s2.2;p17.34">When the protein is expressed under the H3 promoter it does not associate to the centromere suggesting that CENP-A is involved in the packaging of centromeric chromatin and that it may provide an early epigenetic marker for centromere formation (Fowler <hi rend="italic">et al</hi> 2000). </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined">CENP-B</head><p n="p18.34"><s n="s1.4;p18.34">CENP-B is an 80kDa protein that will bind to the centromere independently of other proteins. </s><s n="s2.4;p18.34">This is because it is the only protein with its own specific DNA binding domain, a 17 base pair sequence knows as the CENP-B box. </s><s n="s3.4;p18.34">This box is found only in α-I satellite DNA in humans and minor satellites in mice. </s><s n="s4.4;p18.34">The role of CENP-B is still under debate due to it nonessential nature as is it not found in mammalian Y chromosomes, in human neocentromeres and CENP-B knock out mice show normal viability and normal kinetochore formation (Amor <hi rend="italic">et al</hi> 2004). </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined">CENP-C</head><p n="p19.34"><s n="s1.5;p19.34">CENP-C is a 140kDa protein which is totally dependant on other proteins for its localisation. </s><s n="s2.5;p19.34">This protein will bind directly to DNA but with no sequence specificity, in humans for successful localisation the protein CENP-A must be present. </s><s n="s3.5;p19.34">CENP-C also appears to network with CENP-B an interaction shown by the yeast two-hybrid experiment of Suzuki <hi rend="italic">et al</hi> 2004. </s><s n="s4.5;p19.34">The loss of the CENP-C protein in knock out mice causes lethality at 3.5 day from post conception (Amor <hi rend="italic">et al</hi> 2004). </s><s n="s5.5;p19.34">These interactions suggest that the CENP-A, B and C protein together form the identifying features of centromeric chromatin. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined">hMis12</head><p n="p20.34"><s n="s1.3;p20.34">The hMis2 protein is found in humans and yeasts and homologues of it can be located in most other mammals. </s><s n="s2.3;p20.34">The protein localises to the centromere independently of CENP-A and is present through out the entire cell cycle. </s><s n="s3.3;p20.34">Removal of hMis2 from a cell leads to miss segregation of the chromosome during cell division and the loss of CENP-H and I (Amor <hi rend="italic">et al</hi> 2004). </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined">CENP-H, CENP-I </head><p n="p21.34"><s n="s1.2;p21.34">Very little is known about these proteins, one confirmed observation is that neither is required for CENP-A localisation. </s><s n="s2.2;p21.34">CENP-H does however co-localise with CENP-A, C and with CENP-I for the whole cell cycle. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined">Heterochromatin</head><p n="p22.34"><s n="s1.7;p22.34">Heterochromatin is a specialised highly condensed for a chromatin that is associated with tandem DNA repeats. </s><s n="s2.7;p22.34">It is found only in specialised chromosome locations such as flanking the centromere or at either telomeres. </s><s n="s3.7;p22.34">It forms silent stretches of DNA where not transcription takes place. </s><s n="s4.7;p22.34">The heterochromatic state is not determined only by the DNA sequence but by epigenetic factors such as histone modification. </s><s n="s5.7;p22.34">There are three modifications, first the N-terminus tails of the H3 histone are methylated two or three times at the lysine-9 residue. </s><s n="s6.7;p22.34">Second the deposition of HP1, a heterochromatin associated protein, due to the methylation of these lysine residues. </s><s n="s7.7;p22.34">And third is cytosine methylation of the DNA itself (Derijck <hi rend="italic">et al</hi> 2003) (Figure 5). </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0112b-fig.004"><head><hi rend="italic">Figure 5: The nucleosomes of pericentromeric heterochromatin are arranged into a regular array with a reduced linker length between adjacent nucleosomes. (A) This type of organisation may facilitate packaging into a structure that is highly condensed compared with silent euchromatin (B) although the details of how this structure is organised have not been determined. Pericentromeric heterochromatin is marked by the presence of tri-methyl lysine 9 and mono-methyl lysine 27 residues of histone H3. The major histone modifications in silent euchromatin are mono- and di-methyl H3 lysine 9 and mono-, di- and tri-methyl H3 lysine 27.</hi> Sourced from: Dillon <hi rend="italic">et al</hi> 2004</head></figure><p n="p23.34"><s n="s1.4;p23.34">Due to the continuous presence of heterochromatin at pericentric regions in all eukaryotic chromosomes it would appear that it is required for centromere function. </s><s n="s2.4;p23.34">In an article by Ahmad <hi rend="italic">et al</hi> 2000 it is stated that heterologous centromeric histones localise to heterochromatic regions suggesting that the heterochromatic state must facilitate localisation of centromeric proteins. </s><s n="s3.4;p23.34">The mechanism for these processes is not stated nor is the reason why centromeric proteins do not localise to all regions of heterochromatin, such as telomeres. </s><s n="s4.4;p23.34">One possible reason for the presence of heterochromatin is to provide a suitable, stable environment for the assembly of centromeric components, such as the CENP-A containing nucleosomes. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined">Centromere Structure</head><p n="p24.34"><s n="s1.3;p24.34">The basic centromeric organisation in mammals comprises of a kinetochore and its associated proteins along with a heterochromatin domain. </s><s n="s2.3;p24.34">In the human centromere there are a set of well defined domains the fibrous corona, the outer and inner kinetochore plates and the inter kinetochore plate spaces. </s><s n="s3.3;p24.34">Finally the area underlying the inner kinetochore plate is thought to consist of a heterochromatin region. </s></p><p n="p25.34"><s n="s1.1;p25.34">In a paper by Amor <hi rend="italic">et al</hi> 2004 two models of chromatin organisation were suggested, these were the linear model and the 3D model. </s></p><div2><head rend="bold">Linear Model of the Human Centromere </head><p n="p26.34"><s n="s1.2;p26.34">In the linear model the centromere nucleosomes containing the protein CENP-A are found in a series of alternating blocks associated with the α-satellite DNA repeats. </s><s n="s2.2;p26.34">These blocks of CENP-A containing nucleosomes are separated by nucleosomes conforming to the original format containing H3 (figure 6). </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0112b-fig.005"><head><hi rend="italic">Figure 6: Linear models of centromere organization. In humans, kinetochore assembly takes place on the '-I' subfamily of -satellite DNA, which is homogeneous and enriched in the 17-bp CENP-B box. Inset shows the hierarchical and co-dependent assembly of foundation kinetochore proteins in humans.</hi> Sourced from: (Amor et al 2004)</head></figure><p n="p27.34"><s n="s1.5;p27.34">There is some evidence to suggest that the clustering of CENP-A along the centromere domain is conserved among all multicellular eukaryotes partially because of if its similarity to the functional centromere of <hi rend="italic">S.pombe (</hi>Zinkowski <hi rend="italic">et al</hi> 1991). </s><s n="s2.5;p27.34">Both CENP-B and C localise to the DNA in centromeres so they must occupy a specific domain within the model (figure 6). </s><s n="s3.5;p27.34">Immuneoprecipitation studies were completed and discovered that CENP-C localises in the discontinuous domains with CENP-A upon the same nucleosome. </s><s n="s4.5;p27.34">The CENP-B protein showed a different distribution pattern, it co-localised at points with CENP-A but the majority did not. </s><s n="s5.5;p27.34">The determining factor for CENP-B position was the availability of CENP-B box motifs within the DNA, these existed both across the CENP-A and H3 containing nucleosome regions. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">3D Model of Human Centromeres</head><p n="p28.34"><s n="s1.5;p28.34">To determine the 3D organisation Amor <hi rend="italic">et al</hi> 2004 used deconvolution microscopy to examined the human centromere. </s><s n="s2.5;p28.34">The CENP-A protein was shown to hold a cylindrical form at the centromere. </s><s n="s3.5;p28.34">This structure was parallel to the axis of the chromosome at the inner kinetochore plate. </s><s n="s4.5;p28.34">CENP-C occupied a marginally different domain, but one that did overlap in regions to the CENP-A domains. </s><s n="s5.5;p28.34">It appeared to wrap around the pole-ward face of the CENP-A domain of chromatin (Figure 7). </s></p><p n="p29.34"><s n="s1.2;p29.34">Correct localisation of the proteins CENP-H, CENP-I and hMis12 has proved challenging and no firm conclusions have yet been made. </s><s n="s2.2;p29.34">Some immunofluorescent 2D analysis has highlighted the possibility that these proteins are also localised with CENP-A and CENP-C (Campbell <hi rend="italic">et al</hi> 2003). </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0112b-fig.006"><head><hi rend="italic">Figure 7:</hi> <hi rend="italic">3D organization of human centromere: Linear chromatin fibre might coil through a 3D cylindrical structure like a solenoid, which would enable the individual blocks of CENP-A-containing nucleosomes to form a single domain consisting of a series of repetitive functional subunits at the poleward face of the metaphase chromosome, where they interact with the remaining foundation kinetochore proteins. On the opposite face of the chromosome, the intervening blocks of histone H3 would also form a single domain. The extent to which this inner H3 domain is heterochromatic or euchromatic is the subject of debate and, in turn, has implications for the localization of cohesin (shown in grey in this region), which is recruited to the centromere by heterochromatin. In the left-hand coil, unique sequence DNA is shown in dark green; other repeat elements are shown in dark blue; -II satellites are shown in pink; -I satellites are shown in orange; scaffold or matrix proteins are shown in grey. In the right-hand coil, CENP-A is shown in red; CENP-B is shown in light green; CENP-C, CENP-H, hMis12 and CENP-I are shown in purple; heterochromatin is shown in yellow; euchromatin is shown in blue; and regions of uncertain heterochromatin or euchromatin status are shown in half blue and half yellow.</hi> Sourced from: Amour <hi rend="italic">et al</hi> 2004</head></figure><p n="p30.34"><s n="s1.2;p30.34">Just as with the linear model the location of CENP-B is entirely dependant upon the position of CENP-B DNA motifs to which the protein can bind and is not influenced by the presence of other centromeric proteins. </s><s n="s2.2;p30.34">Again this model showed that some CENP-B was located at the inner kinetochore plate but that most is to be found in the surrounding heterochromatin (figure 7). </s></p><p n="p31.34"><s n="s1.4;p31.34">We can be certain about one structural characteristic of the centromere, that is the regions containing CENP-A in can not form heterochromatin. </s><s n="s2.4;p31.34">This is because the structure of heterochromatin is determined by modification of H3 such as methylation of lysine residues and hypoacetylation of the H3 tail. </s><s n="s3.4;p31.34">The tail of H3 is not conserved in CENP-A so, when CENP-A replaces H3 within the nucleosome then theses modification will not take place, so heterochromatin will not be formed. </s><s n="s4.4;p31.34">A further observation proving the different between the two is the ability for gene transcription to occur in CENP-A containing chromatin and not in heterochromatin. </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined">Conclusions </head><p n="p32.34"><s n="s1.3;p32.34">The organisation of centromeric chromatin is significantly different and unusual to that of the rest of the chromosome. </s><s n="s2.3;p32.34">Difficulties in studying this structure have arisen because the chromatin changes during the cell cycle and the exact mechanisms as to how have not yet been identified. </s><s n="s3.3;p32.34">A further problem for study is the variability of centromeric chromatin across different species, the largest advances have occurred in the study of budding and fission yeasts but these organisms show certain centromeric differences to that of mammals. </s></p><p n="p33.34"><s n="s1.3;p33.34">From all the data gathered it is clear that the DNA sequence at centromeres is not the determining factor for centromere location although it clearly plays some role in centromeric protein recruitment. </s><s n="s2.3;p33.34">It seem fairly certain that epigenetic factors contribute significantly to the formation of centromeres, the most noteworthy of these is the discovery of CENP-A histone H3-like protein. </s><s n="s3.3;p33.34">This molecule creates centromeric chromatin that is structurally different to euchromatin and heterochromatin, and aids the recruitment of other key centromeric proteins such as CENP-C. </s></p><p n="p34.34"><s n="s1.1;p34.34">Further studies into the production and recruitment of CENP-A and the other proteins utilised in the centromere should provide further insight into centromeric organisation. </s></p></div1></body><back><div1 type="bibliography"><head rend="underlined">Bibliography</head><div2 type="bibliography"><head rend="underlined">Journal References</head><p>Ahmad, K. Henikoff, S. Platero, J. S. Steensel, B. V. 2000 "Heterochromatin deposition of centromeric histone H3-like proteins." <hi rend="italic">Proc Natl Acad Sci USA, Vol 97, Is 2, pp.716-721</hi></p><p>Allan, J. Gilbert, N. 2001 "Distinctive higher-order chromatin structure at mammalian centromeres" ." <hi rend="italic">Proc Natl Acad Sci USA, Vol 98, Is21, pp.11949-11954</hi></p><p>Allshire, R. Ekwall, K. Huktenby, K. Kniola, B. McIntosh, R. Mellone, B. Mengaelli, S. O'Toole, E. 2001 "The domain structure of centromeres is conserved from ision yeast to humans" <hi rend="italic">Molecular Biology of the Cell, Vol 12, pp.2767-2775</hi></p><p>Amor, D. J. Choo, K. H. A. Kalitsis, P. Summer, H. 2004 "Building the centromere: from foundation proteins to 3D structure" <hi rend="italic">Trends in Cell Biology, Vol 14, Is 7, pp.359-368</hi></p><p>Blower, M.D. Karpen, G. H. Sullivan, B.A. 2002 "Conserved organisation of Centromeric Chromatin in flies and humans" <hi rend="italic">Developmental Cell, Vol 2, Is 3, pp.319-330</hi></p><p>Campbell, M. S. Hittle, J. C. Jablonski, S. A. Liu, S. T. Yen, T. J. Yoda, K. 2003 "Human CENP-I specifies localization of CENP-F, MAD1 and MAD2 to kinetochores and is essential for mitosis" <hi rend="italic">Nature Cell Biology Vol 5, Is 4, pp.341-345</hi></p><p>Cavalli, G. 2002 "Chromatin as a eukaryotic template of genetic information" <hi rend="italic">Current Opinion in Cell Biology, Vol 14, Is 3, pp.269-278</hi></p><p>Choo, A. 2001 "Domain organization at the centromere and neocentromere" <hi rend="italic">Developental Cell, Vol 1, Is 2, pp.165-177</hi></p><p>Cummings, M. R. Klug, W. S. "Concepts of genetics " Prentice Hall, seventh edition 2003</p><p>Dalal, Y. Henikoff, S. 2005 "Centromeric Chromatin: what makes it unique?" <hi rend="italic">Current Opinion in Genetics and Development, Article in Press, Corrected proof, available on line Feb 2005</hi></p><p>Derijck, A. A. Jenuwein, T. Kohlmaier, A. Kubicek, S. Martens, J. H. Mechtler, K. Opravil, S. O'Sullivan, R. J. Perez-Burgos, L. Peters, A. Tachibana, M. 2003 "Partitioning and Plasticity of Repressive Histone Methylation States in Mammalian Chromatin" <hi rend="italic">Molecular cell, Vol 12, Is 6, pp. 1577-1589</hi></p><p>Dillon, N. 2004 "Heterochromatin structure and function, review" <hi rend="italic">Biology of the Cell, Vol 96, Is 8, pp.631-637</hi></p><p>Driel, R.V. Otte, A.P "Nuclear Organisation, Chromatin Structure and Gene Expression" Oxford University Press 1997</p><p>Fowler, K. J. Howman, E. V. Kalitsis, P. MacDonald, A. C. Newson, A. J. Redward, S. and Choo, A. 2000 "Early disruption of centromeric chromatin organisation in centromere protein A (Cenpa) null mice" <hi rend="italic">The National Academy of Science, Vol 97, pp.1148-1153</hi></p><p>Griffiths, A. Miller, J. Suzuki, D. Lewontin, R. Gelbart, W. "An introduction to genetic analysis" Freedman, seventh edition, 2003</p><p>Henikoff, S. 2002 "Near the edge of a chromosome's 'black hole'" <hi rend="italic">Trends in Genetics, Vol 18, Is 4, pp.165-167</hi></p><p>Henikoff, S. Malik, H. 2002 <hi rend="italic">"Current Opinion in Genetics and Development", Vol 12, Is 6, pp.711-718</hi></p><p>Krude, T. 1999 "Chromatin ssembly during DNA replication in somatic cells" Review article, <hi rend="italic">Eur. J. Biochem, Vol 263, pp.1-5</hi></p><p>Politi, V. 2002"CENP-C binds the <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0112b-form.001"/>-satellite DNA <hi rend="italic">in vivo</hi> at specific centromere domains." <hi rend="italic">J. Cell Sci. Vol 115 pp.2317 - 2327</hi></p><p>Sullivan, K. F. 2001 "A solid foundation: functional specialization of centromeric chromatin." <hi rend="italic">Curr. Opin. Genet. Dev. Vol 11, pp.182 - 188</hi>.</p><p>Suzuki, N. 2004 "CENP-B Interacts with CENP-C domains containing Mif2 regions responsible for centromere localization." <hi rend="italic">J. Biol. Chem. Vol 279, pp. 5934 - 5946.</hi></p><p>Zinkowski, R. P. Meyne, J. Brinkley, B. R. 1991 "The centromere-kinetochore complex: a repeat subunit model" <hi rend="italic">The Journal Of Cell Biology Vol 113, Is 5, pp.1091-1110</hi></p></div2></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
