<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_0112a" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Endosymbiotic theory - the modern, or organelle-containing eukaryotic cell evolved in steps through the stable incorporation of chemo-organotrophic and phototrophic symbionts from the domain of Bacteria.</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">deleted: page numbers
deleted: Word Count \n 2703 words
</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">1</p><p n="date">2003-03</p><p n="module title">BS/MB/VIR/CB laboratories &amp; assessed work</p><p n="module code">BS121</p><p n="genre family">Critique</p><p n="discipline">Biological Sciences</p><p n="disciplinary group">LS</p><p n="grade">D</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">2731</p><p n="number of s-units">133</p><p n="number of p">53</p><p n="number of tables">1</p><p n="number of figures">4</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">2</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">23</p><p n="abstract present">abstract present</p><p n="average words per s-unit">20.5</p><p n="average s-units per p">2.5</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">f</p><p n="year of birth">1984</p><p n="first language">English</p><p n="education">UKA</p><p n="course">Biological Sciences with Molecular Genetics</p><p n="student ID">0112</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><docTitle><titlePart rend="underlined bold">Endosymbiotic theory - the modern, or organelle-containing eukaryotic cell evolved in steps through the stable incorporation of chemo-organotrophic and phototrophic symbionts from the domain of Bacteria. </titlePart></docTitle><titlePart><hi rend="underlined bold">University No.</hi> <hi rend="bold"><name type="student ID"/></hi></titlePart></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="abstract"><head rend="underlined">Abstract </head><p n="p1.53"><s n="s1.6;p1.53">The Endosymbiotic theory was first theorised by Lynn Margulis, a biologist from the University of Boston. </s><s n="s2.6;p1.53">This essay aims to introduce this theory and review the evidence supporting it. </s><s n="s3.6;p1.53">Initially there is a look at the prokaryotic cell structure and cell abundance, followed by the modern eukaryotic cell and the organelles it contains. </s><s n="s4.6;p1.53">Then the Endosymbiotic theory and its practical process are discussed before the evidence for the theory is highlighted and explained. </s><s n="s5.6;p1.53">Practical examples of endosymbiosis from the supporting discovery of Professor Kwang Jeon and natural examples are discussed. </s><s n="s6.6;p1.53">The essay will end with arguments against the endosymbiotic theory and possible alternatives. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined">Introduction</head><p n="p2.53"><s n="s1.7;p2.53">The Endosymbiotic theory proposed by Lynn Margulis aimed to explain the evolution of eukaryotes from prokaryotes. </s><s n="s2.7;p2.53">This evolution is not though to have occurred from genetic mutations like the classical Darwin theory but, that the cells came in to being from the fusion of separate cell that had a symbiotic relationship. </s><s n="s3.7;p2.53">It does not cast the Darwin ideas aside, as this theory does explain the improvement of species through random genetic mutation and negative selection. </s><s n="s4.7;p2.53">Darwin's theory does not however explain the sudden appearance of more complex species, which need a positive process of evolution. </s><s n="s5.7;p2.53">The theory of endosymboisis does give an explanation to how species originated in the early stages of evolution. </s><s n="s6.7;p2.53">The Endosymbiotic theory states that "these organisms did not evolve by random genetic mutations as previously believed, but by a number of cell combinations"<ref target="BAWE_0112a-ftnote.001"/>. </s><s n="s7.7;p2.53">Smaller prokaryote cells merged with the larger early protists, it took up residency in the cell and provided the cell with energy in exchange for environmental protection and nutrients. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0112a-ftnote.001"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Quote from <seg type="URL" n="http://dekalb.dc.peachnet.edu/~pgore/students/w96/joshbond/"/> </s></p></note></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined">The Prokaryote cell</head><figure id="BAWE_0112a-pic.001"><head><hi rend="italic">Figure 1: A typical prokaryotic cell</hi> <ref target="BAWE_0112a-ftnote.002"/><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0112a-ftnote.002"><p n="pn1.1"> Picture from <seg type="URL" n="http://dekalb.dc.peachnet.edu/~pgore/students/w96/joshbond/"/></p></note></head></figure><p n="p3.53"><s n="s1.8;p3.53">Prokaryotes are single celled organism like Bacteria and Archaea, which are around one micrometer in length. </s><s n="s2.8;p3.53">They contain a single closed compartment surrounded by a plasma membrane; all the genetic material is concentrated in the nucleiod region where one compact (often circular) DNA molecule is located (see figure 1). </s><s n="s3.8;p3.53">Prokaryotes replicate asexually producing offspring that are almost exact genetic replicas of the parent. </s><s n="s4.8;p3.53">This form of reproduction has meant that there evolution is extremely slow so this life form has changed very little for millions of years. </s><s n="s5.8;p3.53">Prokaryotes can be aerobic such as E.coli or anaerobic such as modern cyanobacteria. </s><s n="s6.8;p3.53">As the concentration of oxygen increased in the atmosphere with the evolution of plants 2.5 billion years ago, more prokaryotes evolved the ability to utilise oxygen for energy production. </s><s n="s7.8;p3.53">Due to the small size of the prokaryotic cell and its high surface area to volume ratio it can obtain all the nutrients and gases it needs through simple diffusion, so the cell contains no complicated transport mechanisms. </s><s n="s8.8;p3.53">Prokaryotic cells are the most abundant across the earth and are found everywhere from hot sulphur springs to living inside other cells. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined">The Eukaryote cell </head><p n="p4.53"><s n="s1.2;p4.53">The eukaryotic family contains all animals, plants and fungi; the cell is around ten times the size of the prokaryotic cell, being on average 10 microns in diameter with over 1000 times greater the volume. </s><s n="s2.2;p4.53">Due to this size increase simple diffusion is not sufficient to transport chemicals round the cell so a complex system of structures are in place to aid this process. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0112a-pic.002"><head><hi rend="italic">Figure 2: Picture of an animal Eukaryotic cell</hi><ref target="BAWE_0112a-ftnote.003"/><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0112a-ftnote.003"><p n="pn1.1"> Picture from <seg type="URL" n="http://micro.magnet.fsu.edu/cells/animalcell.html"/></p></note></head></figure><p n="p5.53"><s n="s1.2;p5.53">The major difference between prokaryotic cells and eukaryotic cells is the presence of membrane bound organelles. </s><s n="s2.2;p5.53">An organelle is an independent, bound structure which performs a specific task </s></p><p n="p6.53"><s n="s1.1;p6.53">The major organelles are as follows: (see figure 2) </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p7.53"><s n="s1.2;p7.53">Nucleus - the major site of genetic material with in the cell, more than 95% of the DNA is found here. </s><s n="s2.2;p7.53">The DNA is in the form of linear chromosomes. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p8.53"><s n="s1.3;p8.53">Endoplasmic reticulum and Golgi body - the endoplasmic reticulum is a series of folds of membrane which is the building site of most of the complex molecules produced in the cell. </s><s n="s2.3;p8.53">The Golgi body and endoplasmic reticulum interact with vesicles for transport of molecules between the two structures. </s><s n="s3.3;p8.53">In the Golgi chemicals adjustments are preformed on newly produced molecules and then transported to their required site. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p9.53"><s n="s1.1;p9.53">Mitochondria and Chloroplasts - mitochondria oxidise fuel molecules e.g. carbohydrates to produced useable energy for the cell in the form of ATP. Chloroplasts produce carbohydrates to be used in respiration by harnessing light energy. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p10.53"><s n="s1.1;p10.53">Cytoskeleton - is a web of protein fibres extending through the cell providing structural support and channels for molecules to flow through. </s></p><p n="p11.53"><s n="s1.1;p11.53">Eukaryotes reproduce sexually by crossing genetic material with another cell in a process called meiosis, this allows for more rapid evolution as each offspring is genetically different to its parents. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined">Endosymbiotic Theory</head><p n="p12.53"><s n="s1.4;p12.53">The idea that the eukaryotic cell was a colony of microbes was first suggested by Ivan Wallin an American biologist working in the 1920's. </s><s n="s2.4;p12.53">The modern theory was proposed by Lynn Margulis in 1981 while working at the University of Boston. </s><s n="s3.4;p12.53">The theory postulates that mitochondria are ancestors of modern day <hi rend="italic">Rickettsia</hi> bacteria which developed an ability to respire oxygen. </s><s n="s4.4;p12.53">The chloroplast is a possible ancestor of modern day cyanobacteria which are free living photosynthetic organisms. </s></p><p n="p13.53"><s n="s1.8;p13.53">A protist is thought to be the cell the bacteria were engulfed by, it is an intermediate cell between prokaryote and eukaryote with no organelles except from a membrane bound nucleus. </s><s n="s2.8;p13.53">It is believed to resemble an archaebacterium similar to modern day Thermoplasma that can withstand high temperatures and acid condition. </s><s n="s3.8;p13.53">Margulis proposed that these bacteria were once free-living organisms and were engulfed by protists in a manner similar to phagocytosis. </s><s n="s4.8;p13.53">Once inside the cell they entered into a mutualistic relationship where one cell benefited from another. </s><s n="s5.8;p13.53">In the case of mitochondria the bacteria respired the harmful oxygen building up in the atmosphere to produce energy in the form of ATP which could be used by the host cell. </s><s n="s6.8;p13.53">Chloroplasts produce carbohydrates and sugars to be used as an energy source by the cell. </s><s n="s7.8;p13.53">In return these bacteria were provided with a safe living environment and a constant supply of nutrients. </s><s n="s8.8;p13.53">The reason for engulfing the bacteria is unknown but it is thought that the bacteria were possibly engulfed as a source of food for the protists but for some unknown reason entered into symbiotic relationship. </s></p><p n="p14.53"><s n="s1.2;p14.53">A further characteristic in eukaryotes is the whip like cilia which are not found in prokaryotes. </s><s n="s2.2;p14.53">Margulis suggested that this feature is from different free living bacteria that would resemble modern spirochetes. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined">Process of endosymboisis</head><figure id="BAWE_0112a-fig.001"><head><hi rend="italic">Figure 3: Diagram of endosymbiosis</hi><ref target="BAWE_0112a-ftnote.004"/><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0112a-ftnote.004"><p n="pn1.1"> Figure 3 from <seg type="URL" n="http://www.gwu.edu/~darwin/BiSc151/Eukaryotes/Eukaryotes.html"/></p></note></head></figure><p n="p15.53"><s n="s1.4;p15.53">A bacterium is engulfed into the protists by a process similar to phagocytosis. </s><s n="s2.4;p15.53">It remains within the membrane sac formed by the engulfing procedure. </s><s n="s3.4;p15.53">It is not digested but remains in the cell as symbionts. </s><s n="s4.4;p15.53">Interdependence eventually arises between the aerobic bacteria and host cell, the mitochondria is formed. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0112a-fig.002"/><p n="p16.53"><s n="s1.1;p16.53">The same process happened with cyanobacteria to produce chloroplasts and therefore plant cells. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined">Evidence for the Endosymbiotic theory</head><p rend="bulleted" n="p17.53"><s n="s1.2;p17.53">Both mitochondria and chloroplasts can only arise from preexisting mitochondria and chloroplasts. </s><s n="s2.2;p17.53">They cannot be formed in a cell which lacks them because the nucleus of the cell only contains some of the genes necessary to produce all the proteins they require. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p18.53"><s n="s1.1;p18.53">Both mitochondria and chloroplasts contain there own genome, a single circular molecule resembling that of prokaryote cell DNA. Eukaryotic DNA is in the form of linear chromosomes. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p19.53"><s n="s1.2;p19.53">Both mitochondria and chloroplasts are bound with a double membrane unlike other organelles. </s><s n="s2.2;p19.53">This extra membrane could be the remnants of the vesicle created when the bacteria was engulfed. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p20.53"><s n="s1.4;p20.53">Both mitochondria and chloroplasts have there own protein synthesizing machinery. </s><s n="s2.4;p20.53">Their ribosomal structure and ribosomal RNA resembles that of prokaryotic cells. </s><s n="s3.4;p20.53">Bacterial ribosomes are made up of 23s, 16s and 5s subunits, like mitochondria and chloroplasts. </s><s n="s4.4;p20.53">The eukaryotic ribosome is composed of 28s, 18s, 5.8s and 5s subunits. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p21.53"><s n="s1.2;p21.53">Mitochondria have similar respiratory chains as <hi rend="italic">Rickettsia</hi>. </s><s n="s2.2;p21.53">They take electrons from food molecules extract the energy and combine them to oxygen and protons. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p22.53"><s n="s1.2;p22.53">Chloroplasts and cyanobacteria both share a similar photosynthetic mechanism. </s><s n="s2.2;p22.53">This system used two light collecting systems, photosystem I and photosystem II which remove electrons from water molecules by light energy, give them energy and add them to organic molecules. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p23.53"><s n="s1.1;p23.53">The first amino acid of protein transcription in mitochondria and chloroplasts is fMet just like in bacteria, where as in eukaryotes it is methionine. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p24.53"><s n="s1.3;p24.53">Certain antibiotics that act by blocking protein synthesis in bacteria also work on mitochondria and chloroplasts. </s><s n="s2.3;p24.53">Such an antibiotic is Streptomycin. </s><s n="s3.3;p24.53">This antibiotic has no effect on the protein synthesis in the eukaryotic cytoplasm. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p25.53"><s n="s1.1;p25.53">Certain inhibitors of protein synthesis in eukaryotes, such as diphtheria toxin, have no effect on protein synthesis in mitochondria and chloroplasts. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p26.53"><s n="s1.2;p26.53">The antibiotic rifampicin inhibits RNA polymerase in bacteria and also in mitochondria. </s><s n="s2.2;p26.53">This antibiotic has no effect on eukaryotic RNA polymerase. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p27.53"><s n="s1.1;p27.53">Fossil evidence and the accumulation of oxygen support the theory. </s></p><p n="p28.53"><s n="s1.3;p28.53">Prokaryotes evolve 3.5 billion years ago before the oxygen build up (see figure 4). </s><s n="s2.3;p28.53">This was followed, 1 billion years later by the first eukaryote fossils. </s><s n="s3.3;p28.53">For mitochondrial like bacteria to evolve and form symbiotic relationships with other cells, there needed to be oxygen present in the atmosphere for bacteria to evolve within, before the modern eukaryote could engulf them. </s></p><table id="BAWE_0112a-tab.001"><head><hi rend="italic">Figure 4: Important dates in the Earth's history</hi><ref target="BAWE_0112a-ftnote.005"/><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0112a-ftnote.005"><p n="pn1.1"> Figure 4 from <seg type="URL" n="http://dekalb.dc.peachnet.edu/~pgore/students/w96/joshbond/"/></p></note></head><row><cell/></row></table></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined">Mitochondrial Genome</head><p n="p29.53"><s n="s1.1;p29.53">The human mitochondrial genome contains 16,569 base pairs in one circular strand molecule. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0112a-fig.003"><head><hi rend="italic">Figure 5: Diagram of human mitochondrial genome: some of the major genes are labeled</hi><ref target="BAWE_0112a-ftnote.006"/>. <note place="foot" id="BAWE_0112a-ftnote.006"><p n="pn1.1"> Figure 5 from <seg type="URL" n="http://users.rcn.com/jkimball.ma.ultranet/BiologyPages/E/Endosymbiosis.html"/></p></note></head></figure><p n="p30.53"><s n="s1.1;p30.53">The DNA contains genes to encode for: (see figure 5) </s></p><list type="bulleted"><item>Two ribosomal RNA molecules</item><item>Twenty two transfer RNA molecules (yellow bars on diagram)</item><item>Thirteen polypeptides </item><item>Seven subunits that make up the mitochondrial NADH dehydrogenase </item><item>Three subunits of cytochrome c oxidase</item><item>Two subunits of ATP synthase </item><item>Cytochrome b</item></list><p n="p31.53"><s n="s1.1;p31.53">The polypeptides encoded are used to build protein complexes that are embedded in the inner mitochondrial membrane; these are not found in the nucleus genome. </s></p><p n="p32.53"><s n="s1.1;p32.53">The mitochondrion also needs some proteins encoded by the nuclear genome, such as RNA and DNA polymerase, which are imported into the mitochondrial from the cystol. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined">Chloroplast Genome</head><p n="p33.53"><s n="s1.1;p33.53">The circular genome contains 121,024 base pairs and 128 genes which include: (see figure 6) </s></p><list type="bulleted"><item>Duplicate genes for encoding the four subunits of ribosomal RNA.</item><item>Thirty seven genes encoding all the transfer RNA molecules used in translation with the chloroplast (shown as black marks on figure 6)</item><item>Four genes encoding sum subunits of chloroplast RNA polymerase.</item><item>A gene encoding the Rubisco enzyme.</item><item>Nine genes to encode the photosystems 1 and 11.</item><item>Genes for a third of the proteins used to build up the chloroplast ribosome.</item><item>Six encoding part of the enzyme ATP synthase</item></list><figure id="BAWE_0112a-fig.004"><head><hi rend="italic">Figure</hi> 6: <hi rend="underlined italic">Diagram of a chloroplast genome</hi><ref target="BAWE_0112a-ftnote.007"/><hi rend="italic">: this genome is found in Marchantia polymorpha</hi><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0112a-ftnote.007"><p n="pn1.1"> Figure 6 from <seg type="URL" n="http://users.rcn.com/jkimball.ma.ultranet/BiologyPages/E/Endosymbiosis.html"/></p></note></head></figure><p n="p34.53"><s n="s1.2;p34.53">Like with the mitochondrion the chloroplast requires molecules and structures encoded for in the nucleus. </s><s n="s2.2;p34.53">The particles are produced in the cystol and transported in the chloroplast through the membrane. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined">Experimental Evidence</head><p n="p35.53"><s n="s1.9;p35.53">One of the major piece experimental data that supports Margulis's theory was discovered by Kwang W. Jeon, a biologist from the University of Tennessee. </s><s n="s2.9;p35.53">Jeon witnessed the symbiosis of an amoeba with unrelated bacteria, where the bacteria became completely integrated with the host amoeba cell. </s><s n="s3.9;p35.53">In 1987 Professor Jeon noticed that his collection of amoeba was developing spots due to an infection of bacteria. </s><s n="s4.9;p35.53">Initially this infection was lethal and the numbers in his amoeba collection were depleting rapidly. </s><s n="s5.9;p35.53">Some of the amoeba however did survive and appeared to now be immune to the bacteria in their culture. </s><s n="s6.9;p35.53">Immunity had been acquired because these amoebas contained nearly 40,000 living bacteria which had once infected them. </s><s n="s7.9;p35.53">The amoeba and bacteria now had a symbiotic relationship and were dependant upon each other. </s><s n="s8.9;p35.53">Jeon proved this was a true dependency by performing nuclei transplants between infected amoebas and amoebas lacking the bacteria symbionts. </s><s n="s9.9;p35.53">If left alone the hybrid amoebas (bacteria dependent nuclei in bacteria free cell) died within days, but if these amoebas were reinfected with the original (lethal) bacteria they returned to perfect health and began to grow. </s></p><p n="p36.53"><s n="s1.1;p36.53">Jeon also proved the interdependence by other methods: </s></p><p n="p37.53"><s n="s1.3;p37.53">Jeon treated the endosymbiotic bacteria with the antibiotic chloramphenicol (CAP). </s><s n="s2.3;p37.53">The antibiotic kills bacteria and reduced the number of bacteria living in the amoeba by 90%. </s><s n="s3.3;p37.53">None of the amoeba that had all there bacteria killed survived. </s></p><p n="p38.53"><s n="s1.5;p38.53">A third piece of evidence was provided when Jeon and his fellow researcher J.Y.Choi demonstrated that the amoeba no longer produced a protein which made an enzyme. </s><s n="s2.5;p38.53">This enzyme was essential for the amoebas' survival. </s><s n="s3.5;p38.53">Some enzyme was however present in half the concentration of normal amoeba. </s><s n="s4.5;p38.53">It was discovered that the bacterial endosymbiont was producing this vital enzyme instead. </s><s n="s5.5;p38.53">Also if the bacteria were removed the amoebae's nuclei were damaged due to lack of this enzyme. </s></p><p n="p39.53"><s n="s1.1;p39.53">These experiments proved that endosymboisis was a viable process and could provide a mechanism for cellular evolution and improvement. </s></p><p n="p40.53"><s n="s1.1;p40.53">There are also other examples found in nature that support the Endosymbiotic theory: </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p41.53"><s n="s1.1;p41.53"><hi rend="italic">Mixotricha paradoxa</hi> is a proctist consisting of a symbiotic colony of 5 different bacteria all living in symbiosis with the large proctist. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p42.53"><s n="s1.1;p42.53">Cnidarians are a family of multicellular organisms forming animal colonies consisting of former free living cells. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p43.53"><s n="s1.2;p43.53">Lichens are a family of Endosymbiotic organisms containing blue-green algae and a fungus. </s><s n="s2.2;p43.53">The algae provides the energy and nutrients where as the fungus provided the surrounding membrane giving moisture and protection. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined">Evidence against the Endosymbiotic Theory</head><p n="p44.53"><s n="s1.2;p44.53">There are some academics which disagree with the endosymbiotic theory due to flaws in the evidence. </s><s n="s2.2;p44.53">There are two major downfalls in the evidence: </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p45.53"><s n="s1.1;p45.53">The evidence supports the opposing theory just as well (autogenous model). </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p46.53"><s n="s1.1;p46.53">It is the wrong sort of evidence because none of these data have been shown to be synapomorphies between prokaryotes and organelles. </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p47.53"><s n="s1.1;p47.53">Organelles are the same size and shape as bacteria: the size and shape range of bacteria is so varied that it is not possible to rule that similarity appeared just by chance. </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p48.53"><s n="s1.2;p48.53">DNA in a circular loop, the DNA is very similar to that of a plasmid (super coiled, doubly covalently linked like bacterial DNA): the DNA in mitochondria is not always circular, it can be linear. </s><s n="s2.2;p48.53">Also most of the mitochondrial genes can be found in the nucleus. </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p49.53"><s n="s1.3;p49.53">The similar size of ribosomes: the size of ribosomes in the organelles is between 60s and 80s. </s><s n="s2.3;p49.53">The size of ribosomes in eukaryotic cytoplasm is between 78s and 80s. </s><s n="s3.3;p49.53">These sizes overlap. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined">The Alternate Hypothesis </head><div2><head rend="underlined">Autogenous Model</head><p n="p50.53"><s n="s1.4;p50.53">This theory states that the modern eukaryotic cell evolved from a single prokaryotic cell. </s><s n="s2.4;p50.53">The cell gained compartmentalisation functions through infolding of its plasma membrane. </s><s n="s3.4;p50.53">This model is used to explain the presence of the endoplasmic reticulum, golgi body, nuclear membrane and any other organelle bound by a single membrane. </s><s n="s4.4;p50.53">According to the autogenous model the mitochondrion and chloroplast were formed in the protists by compartmentalising plasmids (vesicles of DNA) within a pinched off invagination of the cell membrane. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">The xenogenous origin hypothesis</head><p n="p51.53"><s n="s1.3;p51.53">This theory predicts that the organelle genomes should share more synapomorphies with eubacteria than with either nuclear or archebacterial genomes. </s><s n="s2.3;p51.53">The DNA sequences were analysed of all different cell types and compared. </s><s n="s3.3;p51.53">It was shown that the chloroplast genome was most closely related to that of the cyanobacteria and the mitochondrial genome closely related to aerobic bacteria. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">The Hydrogen Theory</head><p n="p52.53"><s n="s1.4;p52.53">This theory was created by Martin and Müller in 1998. </s><s n="s2.4;p52.53">It states that the union between the protists and bacterium was not an accident but a planned union between archaebacteria, a methogen (a cell that consumed hydrogen and carbon dioxide to produce methane) and the future mitochondria that respired anaerobically making hydrogen and carbon dioxide waste products. </s><s n="s3.4;p52.53">The union was driven by the desire for the methogen to find food, the anaerobic cell was this constant source of nutrients that the methogen needed. </s><s n="s4.4;p52.53">The anaerobic bacteria eventually became an oxygen consumer as the oxygen in the atmosphere built up. </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined">Conclusion</head><p n="p53.53"><s n="s1.4;p53.53">The endosymbiosis theory was initially ridiculed but is now the most popular explanation for the eukaryotic evolution. </s><s n="s2.4;p53.53">There is strong evidence supporting the theory like ribosome size, gene structure and the presence of double membranes. </s><s n="s3.4;p53.53">The mechanism for bacteria incorporation has also been experimentally proven by Kwang W. Jeon but there is still no evidence that can prove the theory correct above all others. </s><s n="s4.4;p53.53">It is tempting to accept the theory as it is and end the speculation to how eukaryotes first came into being, but there will always be doubts because we can never go back to witness the event ourselves. </s></p></div1></body><back><div1 type="bibliography"><head rend="underlined">Bibliography</head><div2 type="bibliography"><head rend="underlined">Books</head><p>"An introduction to genetic analysis" by Griffiths publisher Freedman seventh edition</p><p>"Molecular cell biology" by Lodish publisher Freedman fifth edition </p></div2><div2 type="bibliography"><head rend="underlined">Web sites </head><p><seg type="URL" n="http://wiki.cotch.net/wiki.phtml?title=Endosymbiotic_theory"/></p><p><seg type="URL" n="http://www.geocites.com/jjmohn/endosymbiosis.htm"/></p><p><seg type="URL" n="http://users.rcn.com/jkimball.ma.ultranet/BiologyPages/E/Endosymbiosis.htlm"/></p><p><seg type="URL" n="http://dekalb.dc.peachnet.edu/~pgore/students/w96/joshbond"/></p><p><seg type="URL" n="http://www.gwu.edu/~darwin/BiSc151/Eukaryotes/Eukaryotes.html"/></p><p><seg type="URL" n="http://www.evcforum.net/ubb/Forum11/HTML/000050-3.html"/></p><p><seg type="URL" n="http://www.gate.net/~rwms/EvoEndosymbiotOrigins.html"/></p><p><seg type="URL" n="http://www.-class.uni.edu/bio201a/spring97/group61"/></p><p><seg type="URL" n="http://www.blc.arizona.edu/courses/181gh/rick/expression2/intro.htlm"/></p><p><seg type="URL" n="http://www.sidwell.edu/us/science/vlb5/Labs/Classification_Lab/Bacteria/symbiosis.html"/></p><p><seg type="URL" n="http://micro.magnet.fsu.edu/cells/animalcell.html"/></p><p><seg type="URL" n="http://www.thymos.com/science/endosymb.html"/></p><p><seg type="URL" n="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Endosymbiosis"/></p></div2></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
