<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_0112f" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Role of Maternal Effect Genes in the Development of the Nematode C. elegans</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">deleted: footer: page numbers
deleted: Word Count = 2981
</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">3</p><p n="date">2005-11</p><p n="module title">Development</p><p n="module code">BS301</p><p n="genre family">Explanation</p><p n="discipline">Biological Sciences</p><p n="disciplinary group">LS</p><p n="grade">D</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">3863</p><p n="number of s-units">118</p><p n="number of p">41</p><p n="number of tables">0</p><p n="number of figures">4</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">0</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">6</p><p n="abstract present">abstract present</p><p n="average words per s-unit">32.7</p><p n="average s-units per p">2.9</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">f</p><p n="year of birth">1984</p><p n="first language">English</p><p n="education">UKA</p><p n="course">Biological Sciences with Molecular Genetics</p><p n="student ID">0112</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><docTitle><titlePart rend="underlined">Role of Maternal Effect Genes in the Development of the Nematode <hi rend="italic">C. elegans</hi></titlePart></docTitle><titlePart>University No. <name type="student ID"/></titlePart></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="abstract"><head rend="underlined">Abstract </head><p n="p1.41"><s n="s1.3;p1.41">The initial development of <hi rend="italic">C .elegans</hi> is heavily dependant upon maternal genes and maternally loaded RNA's to identify different cell fates. </s><s n="s2.3;p1.41">These factors act in a complex and interconnected fashion providing either autonomous signals or cell to cell interaction to identify the different cell fates. </s><s n="s3.3;p1.41">This essay aims to outline the major maternal effect genes, there roles in embryo development and how there localisation is essential for the production of the correct <hi rend="italic">C .elegans</hi> body plan. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined">Introduction</head><p n="p2.41"><s n="s1.8;p2.41">The C. elegans nematode has been used by development researchers for decades; over the past two, the focus has been upon genetic analysis to understand the pattern of cell fate in the embryo. </s><s n="s2.8;p2.41">The <hi rend="italic">C. elegans</hi> organism is useful for study because of its cellular simplicity, easy maintenance of stocks, workable genetics and an accessible embryo. </s><s n="s3.8;p2.41">The early cells fates are determined by asymmetric divisions, localisation of regulatory molecules and cell to cell interactions. </s><s n="s4.8;p2.41">The cell to cell interactions come in two forms; first a cell or group of cells send a signal that alter the fate of an adjacent cell or, signals from one cell alter the polarisation of a second cell so it divides asymmetrically (Rose <hi rend="italic">et al</hi> 1998). </s><s n="s5.8;p2.41">These signals are usually produced from maternally loaded mRNA (maternal effect genes), that are positioned in the egg by the mother during the production of mature oocytes. </s><s n="s6.8;p2.41">The first axis to be produced is the anterior-posterior (AP) axis at the 1-cell stage, with the sperm-derived centrosome breaking the symmetry of the oocyte. </s><s n="s7.8;p2.41">Second, the dorso-ventral (DV) axis is formed at the transition between the 2 and 4-cell stage, with EMS defining the ventral side of the embryo. </s><s n="s8.8;p2.41">Third, the left-right (LR) axis is detectable at the transition between the 4 and 6-cell stage, by two granddaughters cells of AB (ABal and ABpl) (see figure 1) which define the left side of the embryo (Gönczy <hi rend="italic">et al</hi> 2005, Worm Book). </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0112f-fig.001"><head><hi rend="bold">Figure 1: Early embryonic cell lineage map of wild type organisms.</hi> Picture from: Seydoux <hi rend="italic">et al</hi> 1999</head></figure><p n="p3.41"><s n="s1.1;p3.41">Figure 2 shows a cell lineage diagram of the C. elegans embryo demonstrating the asymmetric division of cells, most of the early embryonic patterning events occur before the 28-cell stage at which point gastrulation begins (Rose <hi rend="italic">et al</hi> 1998). </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0112f-pic.001"><head><hi rend="bold">Figure 2. Generation of founder cells in the early embryo.</hi> Anterior: left, posterior: right, dorsal is up and ventral down. The germ-line precursors (P cells) are shown outlined with blue. Each of the founder cells generated by asymmetric division are indicated with a different color. The founder cells each display a characteristic cell cycle rate and lineage: The AB lineage produces hypodermis, neurons, anterior pharynx and other cell types; MS produces the somatic gonad, muscle, the majority of the pharynx, neurons and gland cells; E produces all intestine; C produces muscle, hypodermis and neurons; D produces muscle; P <hi rend="sub">4</hi> is the germ-line precursor. The 16-cell embryo shown in (E) is simplified and does not show the daughters of the 4 <hi rend="sup">th</hi> AB cell division, which occurs at approximately the same time as the P <hi rend="sub">3</hi> division. Picture from: Gö nczy <hi rend="italic">et al</hi> 2005</head></figure></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined">Initial Establishment of Polarity</head><p n="p4.41"><s n="s1.1;p4.41">The largest insight into the mechanisms of forming A-P cell polarity in the zygote came form the study of six maternal-effect mutants that resulted in a defective A-P polarity at the 1-cell stage. </s></p><p n="p5.41"><s n="s1.1;p5.41">Within the <hi rend="italic">C. elegans</hi> zygote polarisation occurs in two phases, the establishment phase before the pronuclear meeting and the maintenance phase after (Cuenca <hi rend="italic">et al</hi> 2003). </s></p><p n="p6.41"><s n="s1.2;p6.41">The initial polarisation is believed to emanate from the nucleation of sperm-derived microtubules around the sperm pronucleus (Wallenfang <hi rend="italic">et al</hi> 2000). </s><s n="s2.2;p6.41">The formation of this microtubule organising centre appears to correlate in space and time with the earliest signs of polarity. </s></p><p n="p7.41"><s n="s1.2;p7.41">During the nuclear migration the pronuclear-centrosomal complex rotates by 90˚ to orientate the spindles along the A-P axis (Gotta <hi rend="italic">et al</hi> 2001) a pseudocleavage furrow is formed, which later regresses allowing cytoplasmic flow to occur (see figure 3). </s><s n="s2.2;p7.41">It is during this process that the maternally loaded PAR proteins become asymmetrically distributed. </s></p><p n="p8.41"><s n="s1.3;p8.41">PAR-1, a ser/thr kinase and PAR-2, a ring finger protein are localised on the posterior side of the zygote near to the entry of the sperm asters (Cuenca <hi rend="italic">et al</hi> 2003). </s><s n="s2.3;p8.41">In a paper by Cuenca <hi rend="italic">et al,</hi> PAR-2 protein was coupled to GFP and its movement monitored shortly after fertilisation. </s><s n="s3.3;p8.41">The findings showed that it is enriched in the posterior cortex centred around the centrosome and then progresses outward towards the anterior until 50% of the egg is covered (Gönczy and Rose 2005). </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0112f-pic.002"><head><hi rend="bold">Figure 3. Establishment of the Anterior-Posterior Axis:</hi> The sperm pronuclear/centrosome complex(es) triggers cortical rearrangements and cytoplasmic flows to polarize the axis. During this phase, the cortical PAR proteins become asymmetrically distributed, the oocyte pronucleus (o) migrates to the posterior, and the germline P granules move to the posterior. Polarization culminates in posterior displacement of the spindle and an asymmetric first cleavage in which determinants are segregated to one or the other daughter. This cleavage results in a larger anterior daughter AB, and a smaller posterior daughter P <hi rend="sub">1</hi> .Diagram form Lyczak <hi rend="italic"> et al</hi> 2002</head></figure><p n="p9.41"><s n="s1.2;p9.41">PAR-4 is thought to be a ser/thr kinase and is distributed equally thought the cortex along with PAR-5 a 14-3-3 protein (Lyczak <hi rend="italic"> et al</hi> 2002). </s><s n="s2.2;p9.41">The function of PAR-5 is relatively unknown but when absent PAR-6 responds weakly, or not at all to its localising signals, suggesting that PAR-5 causing protein localisation (Cuenca <hi rend="italic">et al</hi> 2003). </s></p><p n="p10.41"><s n="s1.2;p10.41">PAR-3 and PAR-6 are PDZ-containing proteins that form a complex with an atypical protein kinase C (PCK-3) and localise at the anterior cortex (Gönczy <hi rend="italic">et al</hi> 2005). </s><s n="s2.2;p10.41">As with PAR-2, Cuenca <hi rend="italic">et al</hi> coupled PAR-6 to GFP and discovered that the complex is distributed equally throughout the cortex shortly after fertilisation (unlike PAR-2) and recedes to the anterior after centrosome rotation. </s></p><p n="p11.41"><s n="s1.6;p11.41">Mutations in the <hi rend="italic">par</hi> genes generally affect other <hi rend="italic">par</hi> genes in 2 ways: by depolarising the distribution of other PAR proteins or, blocking the peripheral localisation of PAR proteins. </s><s n="s2.6;p11.41">From these mutant studies the order of function of the genes can be predicted. </s><s n="s3.6;p11.41">Rose <hi rend="italic">et al</hi> (1998) suggested that PAR-1 maybe the only protein required for establishing polarity, however later evidence contradicts the theory, in <hi rend="italic">par</hi>-2 mutants, the PAR-1 protein is not localised yet other down-stream maternal effect genes reliant on the PAR proteins for localisation remain correctly distributed (SKN-1 and P granules). </s><s n="s4.6;p11.41">The genetic pathway was reviewed by Cuenca <hi rend="italic">et al</hi> (2003), in <hi rend="italic">par-2</hi> mutants it was found that PAR-3, PAR-6 and PKC-3 all become delocalised so were spread though the cortex. </s><s n="s5.6;p11.41">The reverse was true in the <hi rend="italic">par-3, par-6,</hi> and <hi rend="italic"> pkc-3</hi> mutants where PAR-2 was not restricted to the posterior of the embryo. </s><s n="s6.6;p11.41">Cuenca <hi rend="italic">et al</hi> (2003) came to the conclusion that the establishment of the anterior and posterior PAR domains depends upon antagonistic interactions between the PAR-3/PAR-6/PKC-3 complex in the anterior and PAR-2 at the posterior (see figure 4). </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0112f-fig.002"><head><hi rend="bold">Figure 4. Sequential relationships between AP polarity components in one-cell stage embryos.</hi> Contact between the centrosome and the cortex breaks the symmetry of the zygote and results in PAR-3/PAR-6/PKC-3 receding from the posterior in an NMY-2-dependent manner. Meanwhile, PAR-2 enrichment at the posterior occurs concomitant with that of PAR-3/PAR-6/PKC-3 at the anterior. In turn, PAR-1 prevents MEX-5/6 accumulation at the posterior. The presence of MEX-5/6 at the anterior prevents the presence of P granules and PIE-1 on that side of the embryo, and also reinforces anterior PAR-3/PAR-6/PKC-3 distribution. As a result of this sequence of interactions, P granules and PIE-1 are segregated to the posterior of one-cell stage embryos. Figure from: Gö nczy <hi rend="italic">et al</hi> 2005</head></figure><p n="p12.41"><s n="s1.3;p12.41">Once the 1-cell polarity has been established by the PAR proteins this information needs to be translated to other maternal proteins down stream that are required for determining cell fates. </s><s n="s2.3;p12.41">This process is thought to be controlled by the proteins MEX-5 and MEX-6, these are CCCH finger proteins that act downstream of the PAR proteins by establishing maternal protein asymmetry. </s><s n="s3.3;p12.41">This protein function was suggested after observations of <hi rend="italic">mex-5;mex-6</hi> mutants, where several maternal proteins were missexpressed in the anterior of the embryo, such as MEX-1, PIE-1, and SKN-1, which are usually present in the posterior of the embryo at the 1-cell stage (Schubert <hi rend="italic">et al</hi> 2000). </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined">SKN-1 in early EMS development </head><p n="p13.41"><s n="s1.4;p13.41">The maternal effect gene <hi rend="italic">skn-1</hi> is required for the formation of pharyngeal and intestinal cells and was identified through mutant screens where the zygotes lacked both these cell types. </s><s n="s2.4;p13.41">Bowerman <hi rend="italic">et al</hi> (1992) showed that only P <hi rend="sub">1</hi> cells had the ability to produce pharyngeal cell in isolation by removing them from the embryo and growing them in cell culture. </s><s n="s3.4;p13.41">This characteristic was different from the AB cell which, when removed was unable to produce pharyngeal cells. </s><s n="s4.4;p13.41">This experiment proved that that the P <hi rend="sub">1</hi> cells differentiation was pre determined by intrinsic factors, where as the AB fate was due to cell-cell interactions. </s></p><p n="p14.41"><s n="s1.4;p14.41">SKN-1 protein is not detectable in either the oocyte or sperm before fertilization takes place. </s><s n="s2.4;p14.41">Once the initial cleavage on P <hi rend="sub">0</hi> has occurred then it can be detected in both the AB and P <hi rend="sub">1</hi> nuclei equally. </s><s n="s3.4;p14.41">As the first cell cycle takes place the levels of SKN-1 increase in the P <hi rend="sub">1</hi> nucleus but not in AB, the AB and P <hi rend="sub">1</hi> cells both enter mitosis and there daughters contain equal amount of SKN-1. </s><s n="s4.4;p14.41">There is however a noticeable higher concentration in the daughters of the P <hi rend="sub">1</hi> cell compared to the AB cell (Bowerman <hi rend="italic">et al</hi> 1993). </s></p><p n="p15.41"><s n="s1.2;p15.41">SKN-1 is a transcription factor that binds to DNA as a monomer, it acts in the EMS cell to activate transcription of zygotic gene which induce somatic fates. </s><s n="s2.2;p15.41">It has an unusual DNA binding domain called the Skn domain (see figure 5) which includes a carboxyl-terminal basic region (BR), like those of dimeric basic-leucine zipper (bZIP) proteins, and a flexible amino-terminal arm resembling helix-turn-helix proteins (Thiphaphone <hi rend="italic">et al</hi> 1999). </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0112f-pic.003"><head><hi rend="bold">Figure 5: Structure of the Skn domain bound to DNA.</hi> The Skn domain backbone is shown in blue, along with the Arg 9 (Arg 457) side chain. Other side chains are not shown. The DNA backbone is orange, the GTCAT base pairs are yellow, and the AT-rich region bases are red. Green spheres indicate sugar residues. Picture from: Thiphaphone <hi rend="italic">et al</hi> 1999</head></figure><p n="p16.41"><s n="s1.1;p16.41">The distribution and activity of SKN-1 is regulated by other maternal effect genes, primarily MEX-1, PAR-1 and PIE-1 (see figure 6). </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0112f-pic.004"><head><hi rend="bold">Figure 6. Skn-1 Protein in Wild-Type Embryos and in <hi rend="italic">mex-1</hi> and <hi rend="italic">par-1</hi> Mutant Embryos</hi> Immnofluorescence micrographs of wild-type embryos (a-c) and of <hi rend="italic">mex-1</hi> (d-f) and <hi rend="italic">par-1</hi> (g-i) mutant embryos stained for Skn-1 protein. The top, middle, and bottom rows show 2-cell, 4-cell, and 8-cell embryos, respectively. Comparisons are between embryos at equivalent times in the cell cycle as determined by DAPI staining (data not shown). (c; the left arrow points to the nucleus of the ABa cell and the right arrow points to the MS cell. Picture from: Thiphaphone <hi rend="italic">et al</hi> 1999</head></figure><p n="p17.41"><s n="s1.4;p17.41">Figure 6 shows a marked difference in the SKN-1 levels between the AB and P1 daughter cells in the wild type embryos at the 4-cell stage. </s><s n="s2.4;p17.41">However in the MEX-1 and Figure 6 shows that in PAR-1 mutants all the blastomeres appear to have very similar levels of SKN-1. </s><s n="s3.4;p17.41">The AB cells have more SKN-1 than the wild type and the P1 cells less than wild type. </s><s n="s4.4;p17.41">By the 8-cell stage SKN-1 is detectable in all blastomeres of the mutant embryos and only in P1 descendants of the wildtype embryo (Thiphaphone <hi rend="italic">et al</hi> 1999). </s></p><p n="p18.41"><s n="s1.3;p18.41">Along with regulating the EMS blastomere cell fate, SKN-1 my also play a role in determining the ABa cell fate. </s><s n="s2.3;p18.41">In <hi rend="italic">skn-1</hi> mutants there is no production of ABa derived pharyngeal cells. </s><s n="s3.3;p18.41">In a paper by Shelton <hi rend="italic">et al</hi> (1996) it was identified that SKN-1 is required for MS to signal to the ABa cell, but not to allow the AB descendants to respond, causing the production of pharyngeal cells. </s></p><p n="p19.41"><s n="s1.5;p19.41">The EMS cell divides to form asymmetrical E and MS (see figure 1). </s><s n="s2.5;p19.41">This asymmetry was though to evolve autonomously but recent studies have shown that it also requires interactions between P <hi rend="sub">2</hi> and EMS via the Wnt pathway (Reviewed in Lesilee <hi rend="italic">et al</hi> 1998). </s><s n="s3.5;p19.41">Contact between P <hi rend="sub">2</hi> and EMS appears to polarise the EMS cells causing the asymmetrical division placing the daughter E adjacent to P <hi rend="sub">2</hi>. </s><s n="s4.5;p19.41">If the P <hi rend="sub">2</hi> cell is removed before this division can take place then the EMS cell divides to form two MS like cells. </s><s n="s5.5;p19.41">For P <hi rend="sub">2</hi> signaling a set of five genes called <hi rend="italic">mom</hi> genes are required, <hi rend="italic">mom</hi> mutants produce embryos with no intestinal cells but extra pharynx, P <hi rend="sub">2</hi> signalling also effects levels of maternal proteins in E like POP-1 required for posterior pharynx formation. </s></p><div2><head rend="underlined">Formation of the Germline </head><p n="p20.41"><s n="s1.2;p20.41">The germline in <hi rend="italic">C. elegans</hi> is produced at the 100cell stage when the P4 cell divides to form Z2 and Z3 cells (see figure 1). </s><s n="s2.2;p20.41">Through all previous divisions' one cell is set aside (the P cells) destined to be the germ cell. </s></p><p n="p21.41"><s n="s1.3;p21.41">The core maternally loaded RNA's responsible for the production of the germline is PIE-1 and the P granules. </s><s n="s2.3;p21.41">The <hi rend="italic">pie-1</hi> gene was identified during screens of maternal effect mutants that produce an excess of pharyngeal and intestinal cells (Mello <hi rend="italic">et al</hi> 1992). </s><s n="s3.3;p21.41">This somatic cell excess is caused by the P <hi rend="sub">2</hi> cells reverting to the EMS blastomere state through the action of SKN-1. </s></p><p n="p22.41"><s n="s1.2;p22.41">PIE-1 is a 38kDa CCCH-type zinc finger protein (2 zinc fingers). </s><s n="s2.2;p22.41">This class of proteins are known for there ability to bind to RNA or have been implicated in mRNA cleavage/processing events. </s></p><p n="p23.41"><s n="s1.1;p23.41">Several reasons lead researchers to believe that PIE-1 is a transcriptional repressor: </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p24.41"><s n="s1.1;p24.41">The protein is detected in the right place at the right time for SKN-1 repression </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p25.41"><s n="s1.1;p25.41">It is maternally loaded and segregates with germline </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p26.41"><s n="s1.3;p26.41">It disappears from germ lineage shortly after the division of P4 into Z2 and Z3. </s><s n="s2.3;p26.41">At this point new zygotic mRNA's need to be transcribed to expand the germline. </s><s n="s3.3;p26.41">(Seydoux <hi rend="italic">et al</hi> 1999) </s></p><p n="p27.41"><s n="s1.2;p27.41"><hi rend="italic">Pie-1</hi> in the nucleus acts as a transcriptional repressor that inhibits the production of several proteins, (including SKN-1) to prevent activation of zygotic genes that will promote somatic fates (Seydoux <hi rend="italic">et al</hi> 1996). </s><s n="s2.2;p27.41">This block in gene expression is essential for the formation of the germline. </s></p><p n="p28.41"><s n="s1.4;p28.41">PIE-1's cytoplasmic function is to prevent the degradation of maternal RNA's in germline blastomeres and promote the expression of maternally encoded factors that promote germline formation (Tenenhaus <hi rend="italic">et al</hi> 2001). </s><s n="s2.4;p28.41">One such factor is the <hi rend="italic"> nos-2</hi>, a maternal RNA related to <hi rend="italic">Drosophila nanos</hi> which is maintained in the cytoplasm of germline cells as a component of P granules. </s><s n="s3.4;p28.41">Studies by Tenenhaus <hi rend="italic">et al</hi> (2001) investigated the function of the two zinc fingers in PIE-1 protein, through mutation experiments by removing the function of each finger separately. </s><s n="s4.4;p28.41">When the first zinc finger is knocked out, the protein is no longer able to inhibit transcription, when the second finger is removed transcription repression still occurs but the promotion of <hi rend="italic">nos-2</hi> expression is prevented, this lead to the conclusion that these two functions are separated genetically and spatially within the protein. </s></p><p n="p29.41"><s n="s1.2;p29.41">The process of transcription elongation requires phosphorylation by CDK9 of a repeated heptapeptide in the carboxy-terminal domain (CTD) of RNAPII, this phosphoepitope is known as H5. </s><s n="s2.2;p29.41">The PIE-1 protein is able inhibit CDK9, because it contains a sequence that is very similar to the repeated heptapeptide (H5) in the CTD of RNAPII. PIE-1 competes for the CDK9 active site preventing phosphorylation and transcription (Tenenhaus <hi rend="italic">et al</hi> 2001). </s></p><p n="p30.41"><s n="s1.5;p30.41">Correct localisation of <hi rend="italic">pie-1</hi> is incredibly important because of its function and ability to repress transcription. </s><s n="s2.5;p30.41">PIE-1 protein first becomes detectable at low levels in the posterior cytoplasm of the 1-cell embryo. </s><s n="s3.5;p30.41">After first division PIE-1 is present in the nucleus and cytoplasm of the germline blastomere P <hi rend="sub">1</hi>, there is only a residual presence of the protein in the somatic AB cell. </s><s n="s4.5;p30.41">By the 4 cell stage PIE-1 is present only in the germline P <hi rend="sub">2</hi> cell and not in the EMS cell. </s><s n="s5.5;p30.41">This accurate localisation is achieved by several methods: </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p31.41"><s n="s1.3;p31.41">Localisation via the MEX-1 protein. </s><s n="s2.3;p31.41">In a study by Guedes <hi rend="italic">et al</hi> (1997) <hi rend="italic">mex-1</hi> mutant were produces and the location of PIE-1 analysed, it was discovered that in theses mutants PIE-1 was detected in several blastomeres including E and MS and that there was significant reduction in the P-granule association with PIE-1. </s><s n="s3.3;p31.41">MEX-1 protein contains two repeat finger domains suggesting that it may bind directly to posterior cortex proteins PAR-1 and PAR-2 to produce the P granule association and localisation of PIE-1. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p32.41"><s n="s1.2;p32.41">PIE-1 is removed form the somatic cell lines by an enzyme, C/CUL-2 E3 ubiquitin ligase. </s><s n="s2.2;p32.41">This is targeted to PIE-1 by a bridging protein called ZIF-1 that interacts with bother the ligase and the first zinc finger of PIE-1 (see figure 7). </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p33.41"><s n="s1.1;p33.41">The final method is associates with centromeres. </s></p><p n="p34.41"><s n="s1.7;p34.41">When germline blastomeres begin to divide, the nascent mitotic spindle complex rotates by roughly 90ْ. </s><s n="s2.7;p34.41">PIE-1 protein appears to accumulate round each centrosome of the spindle in equal quantise before rotation. </s><s n="s3.7;p34.41">At the same time the PIE-1 concentrations diminish in the nucleus, cytoplasm and even in the P-granules. </s><s n="s4.7;p34.41">After rotation the levels of PIE-1 diminish rapidly at one centromere until it becomes undetectable. </s><s n="s5.7;p34.41">This results in all the PIE-1 protein be located at one centrosome and therefore in only one daughter cell (the germ cell line). </s><s n="s6.7;p34.41">The movement of the PIE-1 protein to the centrosome maybe a translocation process (other proteins are know to do this such as NuMA). </s><s n="s7.7;p34.41">The proposed reason for the sudden loss of PIE-1 at one centrosome after rotation is that the protein is brought into a different cytoplasmic environment that affects the PIE-1 stability and it is therefore degraded (Mello <hi rend="italic">et al</hi> 1996). </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0112f-fig.003"><head><hi rend="bold">Figure 7. The hypothetical E3 ligase that targets specific zinc finger proteins for degradation in somatic cells.</hi> Core components of the E3 ligase (blue) are shown along with E1 and E2 (gray), additional factors required for the ubiquitination reaction. The substrate recruitment factor ZIF-1 (purple) interacts with Elongin C (C) via the ZIF-1 SOCS box domain (S) and recruits the zinc finger (ZF) protein PIE-1 (red) for ubiquitination. Arrows represent the movement of ubiquitin (Ub, gold) from one protein to another. Picture from: Spike <hi rend="italic">et al</hi> 2003</head></figure></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined">Determination of the AB cell line</head><p n="p35.41"><s n="s1.2;p35.41">At the 2-cell stage the AB blastomere divides to form the ABa and ABp cells who, soon after formation become committed to different fates. </s><s n="s2.2;p35.41">The ABa and ABp cells are developmentally equivalent but cell-cell interactions by the maternal gene <hi rend="italic">glp-1</hi> acting along with the <hi rend="italic">apx-1</hi> gene cause differentiation in the blastomeres fates (Evans <hi rend="italic">et al</hi> 1994). </s></p><p n="p36.41"><s n="s1.1;p36.41">The identities of the cells are determined at the 4 and 12-cell stages and isolated cells in cultured medium showed that both used the same GLP-1 receptor to respond to the signals (Shelton <hi rend="italic">et al</hi> 1996). </s></p><p n="p37.41"><s n="s1.5;p37.41">GLP-1 is a transmembrane protein from the same family as the <hi rend="italic">Drosophila</hi> NOTCH protein. </s><s n="s2.5;p37.41">It is expressed on the surface of ABa and ABp cells and their descendants from the 4 to 28-cell stage (Mickey <hi rend="italic">et al</hi> 1996). </s><s n="s3.5;p37.41">The initial difference between the two AB daughters is created by signalling from the P <hi rend="sub">2</hi> blastomere with GLP-1 receptors on the ABp surface at the 4-cell stage to from the dorsal-ventral axis. </s><s n="s4.5;p37.41">GLP-1 signalling has a second influence at the 12-cell stage where the MS blastomere signals to two of the ABa descendants, alp and ara (see figure 8) to form pharyngeal cells producing the left-right axis of the embryo (Mello <hi rend="italic">et al</hi> 1994). </s><s n="s5.5;p37.41">The fates of the AB descendants can be switched by moving them to different locations within the embryo; this experimental evidence proves that the cell fates are not intrinsically determined but a result of cell-cell contact and signalling pathways (Mello <hi rend="italic">et al</hi> 1994). </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0112f-pic.005"><head><hi rend="bold">Figure 8: Cell-Cell interactions at the 4-cell and 12-cell stages</hi> Picture from Mello <hi rend="italic">et al</hi> 1994</head></figure><p n="p38.41"><s n="s1.3;p38.41">The translation of maternal <hi rend="italic">glp-1</hi> is spatially and temporally controlled (Evans <hi rend="italic">et al</hi> 1994) thought the proteins 3' UTR, specifically two subregions: the SCR (spatial control region) and TCR (temporal control region). </s><s n="s2.3;p38.41">This control is achieved by two maternal gene products POS-1 and SPN-4, POS-1 has a negative influence on the spatial expression of <hi rend="italic">glp-1</hi> by binding to SCR region. </s><s n="s3.3;p38.41">SPN-4 interacts directly with POS-1 while bound to TCR to have a positive effect on translation (see figure 9). </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0112f-fig.004"><head><hi rend="bold">Figure 9: A model for the roles of POS-1 and SPN-4 in the <hi rend="italic">glp-1</hi> mRNA translation.</hi> (Top) SCR: the 66-base spatial control region within the <hi rend="italic">glp-1</hi> mRNA 3' UTR. TCR: the 125-base temporal control region within the <hi rend="italic">glp-1</hi> mRNA 3' UTR. In this model, POS-1 binds the SCR with its second CCCH finger. SPN-4 binds the TCR. POS-1 suppresses and SPN-4 activates the translation. SPN-4 may also inhibit the POS-1 function by direct binding. (Bottom) POS-1 is abundant in the posterior blastomere (right) but present at a much lower level in the anterior one (left), while SPN-4 is abundant in both. We propose that the translation of maternal <hi rend="italic">glp-1</hi> mRNA is suppressed in the posterior half of the embryo by the POS-1 repressor activity, while it is turned on in the anterior half, where the concentration of SPN-4 and its activating function predominates. Diagram from: Ogura <hi rend="italic">et al</hi> 2003</head></figure><p n="p39.41"><s n="s1.4;p39.41">Mutation experiment by Ogura <hi rend="italic">et al</hi> (2003) showed that POS-1 is a zinc finger protein and that its second zinc finger motif binds directly to the SCR region of <hi rend="italic">glp-1</hi> to inhibit translation in the posterior blastomeres. </s><s n="s2.4;p39.41">SPN-4 was found to contain a RNP-type RNA binding motif and is thought to bind directly to the TCR of <hi rend="italic">glp-1</hi>. </s><s n="s3.4;p39.41">POS-1 is present in high concentrations at the posterior of the embryo, and at very low levels in the anterior, SPN-4 is present in equal concentrations all over the embryo. </s><s n="s4.4;p39.41">SPN-4 acts to promote translation of <hi rend="italic">glp-1</hi> but POS-1 acts as an inhibitor and is dominant over SPN-4, preventing <hi rend="italic">glp-1</hi> expression at the posterior. </s></p><p n="p40.41"><s n="s1.3;p40.41">A second maternal effect gene required for AB lineage determination, <hi rend="italic">apx-1</hi>, a transmembrane protein homologous to the NOTCH ligand DELTA. The gene was identified through mutant screens where the mutant embryos showed defective ABp development (Mello <hi rend="italic">et al</hi> 1994); with phenotypes similar to embryos where there P <hi rend="sub">2</hi> cell had been removed. </s><s n="s2.3;p40.41">From this data it is suspected that APX-1 acts as a ligand for GLP-1 produced by P <hi rend="sub">2</hi>, during the 4-cell stage. </s><s n="s3.3;p40.41">The APX-1 ligand is required for differentiation between the ABa and ABp cells causing dorsal-ventral patterning in subsequent development (Mello <hi rend="italic">et al</hi> 1994). </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined">Conclusion</head><p n="p41.41"><s n="s1.4;p41.41">The major conclusion is that patterning in the early <hi rend="italic">C. elegans</hi> embryo is dependant on a mixture of intrinsic factors causing asymmetric division and 2 types of cell-cell interactions. </s><s n="s2.4;p41.41">The PAR proteins form the initial asymmetry via cytoskeleton and spindle positioning. </s><s n="s3.4;p41.41">SKN-1 acts autonomously to form the EMS cell line, where as PIE-1 and MEX-1 work to form the germline. </s><s n="s4.4;p41.41">GLP-1 and APX-1 act with several other maternal proteins as signals to form the AB cell line and form the major body axes, but there are also several overlaps in function adding to the complexity. </s></p></div1></body><back><div1 type="bibliography"><head rend="underlined">References</head><p><hi rend="bold">Bowerman, B. Draper, B. W. Mello, C. C. Priess. J.</hi> (1993) "The maternal gene <hi rend="italic">skn-1</hi> encodes a protein that is distributed unequally in early <hi rend="italic">C. elegans</hi> embryos" <hi rend="italic">Cell. Vol.74, 443-452</hi></p><p><hi rend="bold">Bowerman, B. Eaton, B. A. Priess, J.</hi> (1992) "<hi rend="italic">skn-1</hi>, a maternally expressed gene required to specify the fate of ventral blastomeres in the early <hi rend="italic">C. elegans</hi> embryo." <hi rend="italic">Cell. Vol.68, 1061-1075</hi></p><p><hi rend="bold">Cuenca, A. A. Seydoux, G. Schetter, A. Donato, A. Kenneth, K.</hi> (2003) "Polarization of the <hi rend="italic">C. elegans</hi> zygote proceeds via distinct establishment and maintenance phases." <hi rend="italic">Development. Vol.130, 1255-1265</hi></p><p><hi rend="bold">Evans, T. C. Crittenden, S. L. Kodoyianni, V. Kimble, J.</hi> (1994) "Translational control of maternal <hi rend="italic">glp-1</hi> mRNA established an asymmetry in the <hi rend="italic">C. elegans</hi> embryo." <hi rend="italic">Cell. Vol.77, 183-194</hi></p><p><hi rend="bold">Goldstein, Hird, S. N.</hi> (1996) "Specification of the anteroposterior axis in <hi rend="italic">Caenorhabditis elegans"</hi>. <hi rend="italic">Development. Vol.122, 1467 - 1474.</hi></p><p><hi rend="bold">Gönczy, P. Rose, L.S.</hi> (2005) "Asymmetric cell division and axis formation in the embryo." <hi rend="italic">WormBook</hi>, ed. The <hi rend="italic">C. elegans</hi> Research Community, WormBook,doi/10.1895/wormbook.1.30.1, <seg type="URL" n="http://www.wormbook.org"/></p><p><hi rend="bold">Gotta, M. Ahringer</hi>. (2001) "Axis determination in the <hi rend="italic">C. elegans</hi>: initiating and transducing polarity." <hi rend="italic">Current Opinion in Genetics and Development. Vol.11, Issue.4, 367-373</hi></p><p><hi rend="bold">Guedes, S. Priess, J.</hi> (1997) "The <hi rend="italic">C. elegans</hi> MEX-1 protein is present in germline blastomeres and is a P granule component." <hi rend="italic">Development. Vol.124, 731-739</hi></p><p><hi rend="bold">Thiphaphone, K. Carroll, A. S. Blackwell, K.</hi> (1999) "The SKN-1 amino-terminal arm is a DNA specificity segment." <hi rend="italic">Molecular and Cellular Biology. Vol.19, 3039-3035</hi></p><p><hi rend="bold">Lyczak, R. Gomes, J. E. Bowerman, B.</hi> (2002) "Heads or tails: cell polarity and axis formation in the early Caenorhabditis elegans embryo." <hi rend="italic">Developmental cell. Vol.3, Issue.2, 157-166</hi></p><p><hi rend="bold">Mello, C. C. Draper, B. W. Krause, M. Weintraub, H. Priess, J.</hi> (1992) "The <hi rend="italic">pie-1</hi> and <hi rend="italic">mex-1</hi> genes and maternal control of blastomere identity in early <hi rend="italic">C. elegans</hi> embryos." <hi rend="italic">Cell. Vol.70, 163-176</hi></p><p><hi rend="bold">Mello, C. C. Draper, B. W. Priess, J.</hi> (1994) "The maternal genes <hi rend="italic">apx-1</hi> and <hi rend="italic">glp-1</hi> and establishment of dorsal-ventral polarity in the early <hi rend="italic">C. elegans</hi> embryo." <hi rend="italic">Cell. Vol,77, 95-106</hi></p><p><hi rend="bold">Mello, C. C. Schubert, C. Draper, B. Zhang, W. Lobel, R. Priess, J.</hi> (1996) "The PIE-1 protein and germ line specification in <hi rend="italic">C. elegans</hi> embryos." Letters to Nature 22<hi rend="sup">nd</hi> August. <hi rend="italic">Nature. Vol.382</hi></p><p><hi rend="bold">Mickey, K. M. Mello, C. C. Montgomery, M. K. Fire, A. Priess, J.</hi> (1996) "An inclusive interaction in the 4-cell stage <hi rend="italic">C. elegans</hi> embryos involves APX-1 expression in the signalling cell." <hi rend="italic">Development. Vol.122, 1791-1798</hi></p><p><hi rend="bold">Ogura, K. Kishimoto, N. Mitani, S. Gengyo-Ando, K. Kohara, Y.</hi> (2003) "Translational control of maternal <hi rend="italic">glp-1</hi> mRNA by POS-1 and its interacting protein SPN-4 in <hi rend="italic">Caenorhabditis elegans</hi>." <hi rend="italic">Development. Vol.130, 2495-2503</hi></p><p><hi rend="bold">Rose, L. S. Kemphues, K. J.</hi> (1998) "Early patterning of the <hi rend="italic">C. elegans</hi> embryo." <hi rend="italic">Annual Review of Genetics. Vol.32, 521-545</hi></p><p><hi rend="bold">Schubert, C. M. Lin, R. de Vries, C. J. Plasterk, R. H. Priess, J. R.</hi> (2000) "MEX-5 and MEX-6 function to establish soma/germline asymmetry in early <hi rend="italic">C. elegans</hi> embryos". <hi rend="italic">Molecular Cell. Vol.5, 671-682</hi></p><p><hi rend="bold">Seydoux. G. Mello, C. C. Pettitt, J. Wood, W. B. Priess, J. Fire, A.</hi> (1996) "Repression of gene expression in the embryonic germ lineage of <hi rend="italic">C. elegans</hi>" Letters to Nature, 22<hi rend="sup">nd</hi> August. <hi rend="italic">Nature. Vol.382</hi></p><p><hi rend="bold">Seydoux, G. Strome, S.</hi> (1999) "Launching the germline in <hi rend="italic">Caenorhabditis elegans:</hi> regulation of a gene expression in early germline cells", Review Article. <hi rend="italic">Development. Vol.126, 3275-3283</hi></p><p><hi rend="bold">Shelton, C. A. Bowerman, B.</hi> (1996) "Time-dependant responses to the <hi rend="italic">glp-1</hi> mediated inductions in early <hi rend="italic">C. elegans</hi> embryo." <hi rend="italic">Development. Vol.122, 2043-2050</hi></p><p><hi rend="bold">Spike, C. Strome, S.</hi> (2003) "Germ plasm: protein degradation in the soma." <hi rend="italic">Current Biology. Vol.13, 837-839</hi></p><p><hi rend="bold">Strome, S</hi>. (2005) "Specification of the germ line." <hi rend="italic">WormBook</hi>, ed. The <hi rend="italic">C. elegans</hi> Research Community, WormBook, doi/10.1895/wormbook.1.9.1, <seg type="URL" n="http://www.wormbook.org"/>.</p><p><hi rend="bold">Sulston, J. Schierenberg, E. White, J. Thomson, N</hi>. (1983). "The embryonic cell lineage of the nematode <hi rend="italic">Caenorhabditis elegans"</hi>. <hi rend="italic">Developmental Biology. Vol.100, 67119</hi></p><p><hi rend="bold">Tenenhaus, C. Sumramaniam, K. Dunn, M. A. Seydoux, G.</hi> (2001) "PIE-1 is a bifunctional protein that regulates maternal and zygotic gene expression in the embryonic germ line of <hi rend="italic">Caenorhabditis elegans</hi>." <hi rend="italic">Genes and Development. Vol.15, 1031-1040</hi></p><p><hi rend="bold">Wallenfang, M. R. and Seydoux, G.</hi> (2000). "Polarization of the anterior-posterior axis of C. elegans is a microtubule-directed process." <hi rend="italic">Nature. Vol.408, 89-92</hi></p></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
