<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_0114b" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Portfolio Case No. 28</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">proforma
deleted: page numbers
</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">4</p><p n="date">2004-09</p><p n="module title">Child Health Rotation</p><p n="module code">unknown</p><p n="genre family">Case study</p><p n="discipline">Medicine</p><p n="disciplinary group">LS</p><p n="grade">D</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">2834</p><p n="number of s-units">141</p><p n="number of p">49</p><p n="number of tables">0</p><p n="number of figures">0</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">6</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">5</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">20.1</p><p n="average s-units per p">2.9</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">m</p><p n="year of birth">1979</p><p n="first language">English</p><p n="education">UKA</p><p n="course">Medicine Phase II</p><p n="student ID">0114</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><docTitle><titlePart><hi rend="bold">PORTFOLIO CASE No:</hi> 28</titlePart></docTitle><titlePart>Patient Initials Hospital Number Age Gender Mast. <name type="other"/> Keep separate list 5 years, 11 months Male</titlePart><titlePart>Portfolio Case presentation number: 2.11 Phase 2 course document objective(s): 2.9, 2.10, 2.11, 2.12.</titlePart></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="bold">Referral information</hi> Source of referral and a summary of key information</head><p n="p1.49"><s n="s1.1;p1.49">Seen in routine cystic fibrosis (CF) outpatients clinic at the <name type="other"/> and <name type="other"/> (A + B) Hospital on <name type="date"/>. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="bold">History</hi> All <hi rend="bold italic">relevant</hi> information gathered from the patient about the presenting illness, co-existing problems, and current treatment, significant past medical history and the social and family background. The patient's view of the nature of the problem and their expectations for treatment. </head><p n="p2.49"><s n="s1.5;p2.49">Describing the events that lead to <name type="other"/>'s diagnosis of cystic fibrosis, Mrs <name type="other"/> said that <name type="other"/> had been wheezy from birth and a CXR at 16/52 showed that <name type="other"/> had a R U lobe pneumonia, and was treated with antibiotics. </s><s n="s2.5;p2.49">Over the next 40/52, <name type="other"/> suffered from persistent chest infections was put on further courses of antibiotics and was also diagnosed as having 'infantile asthma'. <name type="other"/> experienced extreme difficulty in gaining weight, despite having a "tremendous appetite". </s><s n="s3.5;p2.49">Mrs <name type="other"/> was concerned as <name type="other"/> had a "very big belly, but it was all at the front, and he was really as thin as a rake." </s><s n="s4.5;p2.49">For the first year of his life, <name type="other"/> was a miserable baby who slept poorly and had bouts of inconsolable crying. </s><s n="s5.5;p2.49">Mrs <name type="other"/> said he permanently had offensive smelling, yellow stools that were uniformly bulky. </s></p><p n="p3.49"><s n="s1.5;p3.49">Neither antibiotics nor bronchodilators relieved <name type="other"/>'s wheeze, and after moving to a new GP in <name type="other"/>, <name type="other"/> was referred to the paediatricians at the <name type="other"/> Hospital. </s><s n="s2.5;p3.49">A sweat test confirmed the diagnosis of cystic fibrosis. </s><s n="s3.5;p3.49">He was transferred to the <name type="other"/> Hospital (<name type="other"/>), and admitted for 2/52 for IV antibiotics and feeding. </s><s n="s4.5;p3.49">At this time <name type="other"/>'s mother was introduced to the CF nurse, physiotherapist, dietician and social workers that were to be involved in <name type="other"/>'s subsequent care. </s><s n="s5.5;p3.49">Mrs <name type="other"/> learnt how to perform physiotherapy on <name type="other"/>; the dietician advised Mrs <name type="other"/> on the high calorie, high fat diet most suitable for <name type="other"/>. </s></p><p n="p4.49"><s n="s1.1;p4.49">Since diagnosis, both Mrs <name type="other"/> and <name type="other"/> have been attending the CF outpatient's clinic at the A + B, and biannual visits to the regional CF centre at <name type="other"/> Children's Hospital (<name type="other"/>). </s></p><p n="p5.49"><s n="s1.3;p5.49"><name type="other"/> has had "four or five" chest infections in the last year, but only one admission. </s><s n="s2.3;p5.49">Mrs <name type="other"/> takes <name type="other"/> to <name type="other"/> to have the line inserted, and then cares for <name type="other"/> at home. </s><s n="s3.3;p5.49">He does not attend school whilst the cannula is in place. <name type="other"/>'s admission to <name type="other"/> in June this year was for a severe pseudomonas chest infection. </s></p><p n="p6.49"><s n="s1.3;p6.49"><name type="other"/> also has chest physiotherapy twice daily (am and pm), with both postural drainage and deep breathing exercises. </s><s n="s2.3;p6.49">Postural drainage involves <name type="other"/> laying on his front for 20 minutes every morning, at the end of which his mother places a towel on his back, cups her hands and rather firmly beats both back and front of his chest in order to dislodge sputum from his airways. </s><s n="s3.3;p6.49">The deep breathing exercises involve <name type="other"/> blowing up a balloon as far as he can, twice or three times daily. <name type="other"/> is a very sporty young boy, and regularly plays football, cycles and plays tennis. </s></p><p n="p7.49"><s n="s1.9;p7.49">Currently, <name type="other"/> has no respiratory symptoms. <name type="other"/> Has no abdominal pain, distension, and opens his bladder regularly. </s><s n="s2.9;p7.49">He opens his bowels every day, and Mrs <name type="other"/> asks <name type="other"/> to inspect his faeces and tell her if it is difficult to flush. </s><s n="s3.9;p7.49">There is no family history of cystic fibrosis. <name type="other"/>'s diet is very high in calories and fat. </s><s n="s4.9;p7.49">Breakfast is Cocoa pops, milk, toast and butter. </s><s n="s5.9;p7.49">He then has biscuits and chocolate at break. </s><s n="s6.9;p7.49">Lunch is usually cheese sandwiches, crisps, and chocolate for dessert. <name type="other"/> has crisps when he arrives home. </s><s n="s7.9;p7.49">Dinner is commonly chips, turkey, and broccoli followed by cake. <name type="other"/> also has some biscuits before bed. </s><s n="s8.9;p7.49">Mrs <name type="other"/> also puts lots of table salt on <name type="other"/>'s food. </s><s n="s9.9;p7.49">He regularly sees his dentist to maintain his dental health. </s></p><p n="p8.49"><s n="s1.1;p8.49"><name type="other"/> has no other significant illnesses. </s></p><p n="p9.49"><s n="s1.1;p9.49">Currently he is prescribed Polycal liquid 200ml (1 bottle/day), Colomycin + NaCl 20 million units/ 5 mls, bd nebulised), Vitamins A and D (4000 IU/400 IU bd po), Pancreatin (lipase, amylase, protease, 10000/8000/600 IU od po), Co-trimoxazole 80 mg + 400 mg/5ml, 5mls bd po), Salbutamol (100g/inhalation 2 puffs bds), Vitamin E (500mg/5ml, 2mls daily), and Flucticasone (50g/inhalation, 2 puffs bds). <name type="other"/> is up to date with his vaccinations, and is going for his Influenza vaccine next week. </s></p><p n="p10.49"><s n="s1.4;p10.49">Mrs <name type="other"/> delivered <name type="other"/> vaginally following a difficult pregnancy, as she was suffering from Symphysis Pubis Dysfunction and sciatica. </s><s n="s2.4;p10.49">He weighed 8lbs 8oz. </s><s n="s3.4;p10.49">He was not admitted to the Special Care Baby Unit. </s><s n="s4.4;p10.49">He was breast fed for 3/12, before transferring to bottle milk. </s></p><p n="p11.49"><s n="s1.4;p11.49">Mrs <name type="other"/> described a normal developmental history for <name type="other"/>, although she was concerned he was nearly 2 years old before he could walk. </s><s n="s2.4;p11.49">Mrs <name type="other"/> feels <name type="other"/> is very small for his age; he is nearly 6, but wears clothes for 3-4 year olds. <name type="other"/> is doing well at school, and is comfortably "in the top half of his class"; despite <name type="other"/> missing 1-2 days/month due to illness. </s><s n="s3.4;p11.49">Mrs <name type="other"/> said the most significant problem was <name type="other"/> coughing throughout the night, and being tired the next day. </s><s n="s4.4;p11.49">Otherwise, the only issue regarding CF at school is <name type="other"/> taking his Creon tablets at lunchtimes. </s></p><p n="p12.49"><s n="s1.8;p12.49">Before <name type="other"/> was born, Mrs <name type="other"/> was a hairdresser who ran her own business. <name type="other"/>'s father works for a large car manufacturer in the Midlands. </s><s n="s2.8;p12.49">Mrs <name type="other"/> is now in receipt of a full-time carer's allowance for looking after <name type="other"/>. </s><s n="s3.8;p12.49">Mrs <name type="other"/> also receives Disability Living Allowance for <name type="other"/>, and also has a reduction in her Council Tax bill. </s><s n="s4.8;p12.49">Mr <name type="other"/> had to change his shift patterns at work so he could return home in time to look after <name type="other"/> in the evenings. </s><s n="s5.8;p12.49">Mr <name type="other"/>'s work and colleagues have been very helpful toward the family, and have raised over £4000 though various sponsored events to allow the family to go to Florida in 2006. </s><s n="s6.8;p12.49">Mrs <name type="other"/> has been in contact with the children's charity Banardo's, who helped Mrs <name type="other"/> discover which benefits she was entitled to. </s><s n="s7.8;p12.49">She is aware of various CF support groups, but chooses not to use them as she feels <name type="other"/> has a normal existence at the moment, and doesn't want to change it. </s><s n="s8.8;p12.49">Mrs <name type="other"/> is in contact with the CF specialist nurse, who she describes as "invaluable." </s></p><p n="p13.49"><s n="s1.4;p13.49">Describing her daily routine looking after <name type="other"/>, Mrs <name type="other"/> said she has to get up at 6.30am every weekday morning in order to get <name type="other"/> ready for school. </s><s n="s2.4;p13.49">She felt she could not return to work, as <name type="other"/> frequently has to come home in the middle of the day due to illness. </s><s n="s3.4;p13.49">Mrs <name type="other"/>'s grandmother is also able to perform physiotherapy on <name type="other"/> if she is not available. </s><s n="s4.4;p13.49">Mrs and Mrs <name type="other"/> were considering having more than one child; however after the issues surrounding <name type="other"/>'s care, Mr <name type="other"/> decided to have a vasectomy. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="bold">Physical examination</hi> Highlight the findings most relevant to your clinical problem solving by underlining them</head><list type="simple"><head>General- BP= 96/60 Hr= 90, regular. CRP= &lt;2 secs. O <hi rend="sub">2</hi> Sat.= 97% (Room air) Height = 104.3 cm (9 <hi rend="sup">th</hi>-25 <hi rend="sup">th</hi> centile). Weight= 16.6 kg (2 <hi rend="sup">nd</hi> centile). Appears well. Mild clubbing.</head></list><list type="simple"><item> Jaundice/anaemia/oedema/lymphadenopathy.</item></list><div2><head rend="underlined">Abdominal exam</head><list type="simple"><item> Abdomen soft and non-tender. Distension/hepatomegaly/spleomegaly/ palpable faeces in colon. BS +.</item></list><p n="p14.49"/></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">Respiratory exam</head><list type="simple"><item>Breathless at rest/cyanosis. No nasal polyps. Slight Harrison's sulcus evident. ºTracheal deviation. Expansion bilateral and symmetrical. Percussion unremarkable. Good air entry bilaterally, with a clear cough.</item></list><list type="simple"><head>Impression: Small, but well young child. Very socially engaging.</head></list><p n="p15.49"/></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="bold">Formulation of the patient's problem(s)</hi> Encapsulate this in physical, psychological and social terms (the triple diagnosis)</head><p n="p16.49"><s n="s1.6;p16.49"><name type="other"/> is a young boy who is suffering the effects of a chronic, incurable illness. </s><s n="s2.6;p16.49">Physically, he is currently well, although patients with CF are prone to becoming unwell very acutely. </s><s n="s3.6;p16.49">Ideally, <name type="other"/> should be overweight, but is only on the 2 <hi rend="sup">nd</hi> centile. </s><s n="s4.6;p16.49">Psychologically, <name type="other"/> is a bright young man who is doing well at school, but is too young to fully realise all the consequences of his illness. </s><s n="s5.6;p16.49">Socially <name type="other"/> is very popular, and engages in all the activities his peers do. </s><s n="s6.6;p16.49">He has little to do with other children with CF due to the risks of cross-infection. </s></p><p n="p17.49"><s n="s1.1;p17.49"><name type="other"/> has a close family unit who care for him well, and who have been successful in organising a much anticipated holiday for <name type="other"/>. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="bold">Management</hi> Use the framework of RAPRIOP to structure your proposed management. Refer to the guidelines to the writing of portfolio cases for the details of the issues to be addressed under each heading.</head><div2><head rend="underlined">Investigations</head><p n="p18.49"><s n="s1.2;p18.49">No tests/investigations ordered at this outpatient clinic. </s><s n="s2.2;p18.49">However, at his biannual check in <name type="other"/> next month, <name type="other"/> will have LFTs, a CXR, and liver USS. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">Reassurance and explanation</head><p n="p19.49"><s n="s1.2;p19.49">Mrs <name type="other"/> is in regular contact with the paediatricians and CF specialist nurse at <name type="other"/>. </s><s n="s2.2;p19.49">Mrs <name type="other"/> is also aware of local support groups and national groups, if she wishes to contact them. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">Prescription/medical intervention</head><div3><head rend="underlined">Dietician comments </head><p n="p20.49"><s n="s1.4;p20.49">Height between 9-25 <hi rend="sup">th</hi> centile, weight on 2 <hi rend="sup">nd</hi> centile. </s><s n="s2.4;p20.49">Currently growing well. </s><s n="s3.4;p20.49">Eating large amounts of food. </s><s n="s4.4;p20.49">Occasional cough not apparently affecting appetite. </s></p><p n="p21.49"><s n="s1.1;p21.49">. </s></p></div3><div3><head rend="underlined">Observation </head><p n="p22.49"><s n="s1.1;p22.49">6-8/52 outpatient appointments. </s></p></div3><div3><head rend="underlined">Referral and team working</head><p n="p23.49"><s n="s1.1;p23.49">At the <name type="other"/> review next month, an evaluation of the last year from a clinical point of view will be performed. <name type="other"/>'s vitamin intake will also come under scrutiny, as will his aspergillus and pseudomonas status. <name type="other"/>'s care currently involves his GP, Physiotherapist, Dietician, Social worker, Specialist CF nurse, and paediatricians at both <name type="other"/> and <name type="other"/>. </s></p></div3><div3><head rend="underlined">Advice and Prevention</head><p n="p24.49"><s n="s1.2;p24.49">CF is not easily preventable. </s><s n="s2.2;p24.49">Screening is suggested for parents of a child with CF wishing to conceive. </s></p></div3></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="bold">Evidence based medicine (EBM) and issues for research</hi> A brief consideration of the evidence base required for the diagnosis and management of the patient's problem(s)</head><p n="p25.49"><s n="s1.2;p25.49">There is very little EBM directed solely at Cystic Fibrosis. </s><s n="s2.2;p25.49">However, the following article was relevant: </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p26.49"><s rend="underlined" n="s1.1;p26.49">EBM Online: Support by another mother and a child-life specialist decreased anxiety in mothers of children with chronic illnesses </s></p><p n="p27.49"><s n="s1.3;p27.49">161 mothers of children who were 7 to 11 years of age; did not have mental retardation; and were diagnosed with diabetes, sickle cell anaemia, cystic fibrosis, or moderate-to-severe asthma (daily medication, wheezing 2 to 3 times weekly, and 1 hospital or emergency department visit in the previous 6 months). </s><s n="s2.3;p27.49">An experienced mother visited 86% of families with a child suffering form the same condition over 6 months. </s><s n="s3.3;p27.49">It found In mothers of children with chronic illnesses, support given by another experienced mother and a child-life specialist reduced anxiety [1]. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="bold">Commentary</hi> A commentary on issues of epidemiology, psycho-social, health care delivery, ethical issues or disability relevant to the patient and/or problem</head><p n="p28.49"><s n="s1.3;p28.49">Cystic fibrosis is the most common potentially lethal autosomal recessive disorder in Caucasian populations, characterised by chronic suppurative lung disease and chronic exocrine pancreatic insufficiency [2]. </s><s n="s2.3;p28.49">It affects 1 in 2500 infants from birth and the frequency of carrier heterozygotes is estimated to be 5%. </s><s n="s3.3;p28.49">It affects males and females equally. </s></p><p n="p29.49"><s n="s1.1;p29.49">CF may present from birth in a multitude of ways, including: </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p30.49"><s n="s1.1;p30.49">Meconium ileus- up to 10% of CF patients presents this way on the first day of life. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p31.49"><s n="s1.1;p31.49">Recurrent chest infections within 1 <hi rend="sup">st</hi> year of life. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p32.49"><s n="s1.1;p32.49">Failure to thrive- up to 50% of CF patients in childhood or infancy. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p33.49"><s n="s1.1;p33.49">Meconium ileus equivalent may occur in later life. </s></p><p n="p34.49"><s n="s1.4;p34.49">Clinical diagnosis of CF is strongly suggested by a meconium ileus. </s><s n="s2.4;p34.49">It presents within the first few hours of life with absolute constipation, bile-stained vomiting and abdominal distension. </s><s n="s3.4;p34.49">The secretory disorder in cystic fibrosis results in loss intestinal mucus and blockage of pancreatic ducts with loss of tryptic digestion. </s><s n="s4.4;p34.49">As a result sticky, inspissated meconium blocks the lower ileum of the foetus. </s></p><p n="p35.49"><s n="s1.6;p35.49">Formal diagnosis involves either a sweat test or immunoreactive trypsin. </s><s n="s2.6;p35.49">The sweat test is diagnostic of cystic fibrosis. </s><s n="s3.6;p35.49">It is induced by intra-dermal injection of pilocarpine. </s><s n="s4.6;p35.49">The chloride concentration if greater than 60 mmol/l and the sodium concentration is greater than 70 mmol/l. </s><s n="s5.6;p35.49">Sodium concentration is greater than chloride concentration in the sweat. </s><s n="s6.6;p35.49">The mass of sweat should be greater than 100mg for an interpretable result, and the test is difficult to perform in those under 3/52 due to an inability to produce enough sweat. </s></p><p n="p36.49"><s n="s1.3;p36.49">Infants with cystic fibrosis 1 to 2 weeks of age show increased levels of immunoreactive trypsin in the plasma in the neonatal heal-prick test. </s><s n="s2.3;p36.49">The test is positive if immunoreactive trypsin is greater than 80 mcg/litre. </s><s n="s3.3;p36.49">It currently the best screening test for cystic fibrosis but cannot be done after the first few weeks of life since it falls as pancreatic insufficiency develops [3]. </s></p><p n="p37.49"><s n="s1.6;p37.49">The aetiology and pathogenesis of CF is increasingly understood. </s><s n="s2.6;p37.49">The defective protein is a cAMP-regulated chloride channel called the cystic fibrosis transmembrane conductance regulator (CFTR) whose gene is on the long arm (q) of chromosome 7. </s><s n="s3.6;p37.49">This defective channel leads to a high concentration of sodium and a low concentration of chloride in exocrine secretions. </s><s n="s4.6;p37.49">There are many types of defect in the gene, of which the most common, a deletion of phenylalanine at position 508, accounts for about 70% of the total [4]. </s><s n="s5.6;p37.49">The clinical severity of cystic fibrosis varies between patients with the same mutation in CFTR. This suggests that there may be modulator genes that interact with CFTR. It is thought that the digenic inheritance of CF is responsible for variable severity of presentation. </s><s n="s6.6;p37.49">The phenylalanine lesion at position 508 is thought to account for the pancreatic insufficiency in CF. This causes malabsorbtion and subsequent failure to thrive. </s></p><p n="p38.49"><s n="s1.8;p38.49">Genetic mutations resulting in abnormal epithelia enable bacteria to adhere more efficiently to respiratory epithelium. </s><s n="s2.8;p38.49">Mucus cannot be cleared efficiently by abnormal cilia, resulting in mucus build up in the lower airways. </s><s n="s3.8;p38.49">Chronic bacterial infection results in mucus gland hypertrophy, hypersecretion of mucus, and further infection. </s><s n="s4.8;p38.49">The bronchial wall is damaged, resulting in bronchiectasis. </s><s n="s5.8;p38.49">When established bronchiectasis is present and mucociliary transport is compromised, then clearance of the lungs is increasingly dependent on gravity and coughing. </s><s n="s6.8;p38.49">Small areas of parenchymal consolidation and fibrosis may develop as a result of impaired clearance. </s><s n="s7.8;p38.49">Principle colonising pathogens in CF include <hi rend="italic">H. influenzae, S. aureus,</hi> and later <hi rend="italic">Pseudomonas aeruginosa</hi> and other pseudomonads. </s><s n="s8.8;p38.49">In advanced disease, there is increasing destruction of lung tissue and emphysema. </s></p><p n="p39.49"><s n="s1.1;p39.49">The underlying principles of management of cystic fibrosis are: </s></p><list type="bulleted"><item>Optimisation of physical and psychological growth </item><item>Delaying the progress of the lung disorder </item><item>Making the lifestyle of the patient and their family as normal as possible.</item></list><p n="p40.49"><s n="s1.10;p40.49">Management of the lung disorder is started early and aimed at maintenance of normal lung function for as long as possible. </s><s n="s2.10;p40.49">Bronchial clearance is attempted by vigorous daily physiotherapy and manual percussion, forced expiratory manoeuvres, and vibration in a variety of positions. </s><s n="s3.10;p40.49">There is also a role for postural drainage - laying in a variety of positions in order to drain mucus form the lower airways. </s><s n="s4.10;p40.49">There is also anecdotal evidence that vigorous aerobic exercise slows lung deterioration as it is thought to improve bronchial clearance. </s><s n="s5.10;p40.49">Antibiotic treatment can be both prophylactic and responsive. </s><s n="s6.10;p40.49">Prophylaxis is often lifelong to protect against <hi rend="italic">S. aureus</hi>, the commonest childhood pathogen, <hi rend="italic">H. inflenzae</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Pseudomonas aeruginosa</hi>. </s><s n="s7.10;p40.49">Pseudomonas becomes and increasing problem with increasing age, and is often a benchmark for severe respiratory decline. </s><s n="s8.10;p40.49">Other pharmacological intervention includes bronchodilators and steroids (oral or inhaled), which may be beneficial in patients with allergic bronchopulmonary aspergillosis. </s><s n="s9.10;p40.49">Mucolytics (DNA-ase) improve mucus expectoration- the DNA is from bacterial infection and shed epithelium. </s><s n="s10.10;p40.49">Heart-Lung transplantation is the final treatment pathway for terminal respiratory compromise. </s></p><p n="p41.49"><s n="s1.7;p41.49">Nutritional therapy in CF patients is also essential. </s><s n="s2.7;p41.49">Frequent liaison with a dietician is suggested, as CF patients are advised to be overweight; this is helpful during bouts of acute illness, when patients become anorexic. </s><s n="s3.7;p41.49">It is also thought that expectoration of sputum alone increases a CF patient's calorific requirement by 5%. </s><s n="s4.7;p41.49">The weight gain is achieved by excessive eating, Polycal fluid, or NG feeding at night. </s><s n="s5.7;p41.49">Pancreatic replacement therapy is in the form of granules or tablets. </s><s n="s6.7;p41.49">Pancreatic extract is degraded in the stomach by acid; the effectiveness of this form of treatment can be increased by administration of H2 antagonists such as cimetidine [5]. </s><s n="s7.7;p41.49">Vitamin supplements (A, D, E, K) are also prescribed. </s></p><p n="p42.49"><s n="s1.3;p42.49">Finally, there are immense psychosocial issues surrounding families and suffers of CF that need to be addressed. </s><s n="s2.3;p42.49">Parents with an affected child need to be informed that there is a 25% risk of having another child with cystic fibrosis. </s><s n="s3.3;p42.49">An unaffected child has a 66% chance of being a carrier of cystic fibrosis, and a child of an unaffected sibling has about a 1 in 80 chance of being affected by cystic fibrosis, assuming that the other parent has a population 1 in 20 chance of being a carrier for CF. </s></p><p n="p43.49"><s n="s1.3;p43.49">An offspring of an affected mother has a 1 in 40 chance of being affected by cystic fibrosis, assuming that the father has 1 in 20 chance of being a carrier. </s><s n="s2.3;p43.49">Adult males with cystic fibrosis are normally sterile, and adult females with cystic fibrosis are sub fertile. </s><s n="s3.3;p43.49">The diagnosis of CF is a life limiting one, and all members of the multi-disciplinary team should try to work together to help the sufferer cope with the feelings of anger, fear and depression that will inevitably occur. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="bold">Impact on your learning</hi> Describe what you have learnt from this case</head><p n="p44.49"><s n="s1.2;p44.49">Diagnosis, investigations and management of CF. Psycho-social consequences of living with a life-limiting illness. </s><s n="s2.2;p44.49">The importance of multi-disciplinary team working in a healthcare environment. </s></p><p n="p45.49"><s n="s1.1;p45.49"><seg type="URL" n="http://ebm.bmjjournals.com/cgi/content/full/7/1/23?maxtoshow=&amp;HITS=10&amp;hits=10&amp;RESULTFORMAT=&amp;fulltext=Cystic+Fibrosis&amp;andorexactfulltext=and&amp;searchid=1097426504060_515&amp;stored_search=&amp;FIRSTINDEX=0&amp;sortspec=relevance&amp;resourcetype=1&amp;journalcode=ebmed"/>. </s></p><p n="p46.49"><s n="s1.1;p46.49"><seg type="URL" n="http://www.gpnotebook.co.uk/simplepage.cfm?ID=919601157"/>. </s></p><p n="p47.49"><s n="s1.1;p47.49"><seg type="URL" n="http://www.gpnotebook.co.uk/simplepage.cfm?ID=1516961826&amp;linkID=49649&amp;cook=yes"/>. </s></p><p n="p48.49"><s n="s1.1;p48.49"><seg type="URL" n="http://www.gpnotebook.co.uk/simplepage.cfm?ID=1584070697&amp;linkID=11517&amp;cook=yes"/>. </s></p><p n="p49.49"><s n="s1.1;p49.49"><seg type="URL" n="http://www.gpnotebook.co.uk/simplepage.cfm?ID=-1227882478&amp;linkID=56167&amp;cook=yes"/>. </s></p></div1></body><back/></text></TEI.2>
