<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_0114e" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Portfolio Case No. 33</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">proforma
deleted: page numbers
</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">4</p><p n="date">2004-12</p><p n="module title">Other Rotations</p><p n="module code">unknown</p><p n="genre family">Case study</p><p n="discipline">Medicine</p><p n="disciplinary group">LS</p><p n="grade">D</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">2483</p><p n="number of s-units">160</p><p n="number of p">62</p><p n="number of tables">0</p><p n="number of figures">0</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">13</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">16</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">15.5</p><p n="average s-units per p">2.6</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">m</p><p n="year of birth">1979</p><p n="first language">English</p><p n="education">UKA</p><p n="course">Medicine Phase II</p><p n="student ID">0114</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><docTitle><titlePart><hi rend="bold">PORTFOLIO CASE No:</hi> <hi rend="bold">33</hi></titlePart></docTitle><titlePart>Patient Initials Hospital Number Age Gender Miss <name type="other"/> Keep separate list 28 Female</titlePart><titlePart>Portfolio Case presentation number: Phase 2 course document objective(s): </titlePart></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="bold">Referral information</hi> Source of referral and a summary of key information</head><p n="p1.62"><s n="s1.1;p1.62">Admitted as an emergency on <name type="date"/> with acute severe abdominal pain. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="bold">History</hi> All <hi rend="bold italic">relevant</hi> information gathered from the patient about the presenting illness, co-existing problems, and current treatment, significant past medical history and the social and family background. The patient's view of the nature of the problem and their expectations for treatment. </head><p n="p2.62"><s n="s1.1;p2.62">Miss <name type="other"/> was diagnosed with Crohn's Disease in 1998. </s></p><p n="p3.62"><s n="s1.5;p3.62">A severe generalised abdominal pain, "sharp and stabbing" in nature that came on in the evening, and resulted in admission 3 hours later was described. </s><s n="s2.5;p3.62">At its worst, she gave it a severity of 10/10, and felt it was constant. </s><s n="s3.5;p3.62">It was partially relieved by the oral morphine she was already prescribed, but on admission she required a further I.V bolus. </s><s n="s4.5;p3.62">There were no aggravating factors. </s><s n="s5.5;p3.62">Miss <name type="other"/> had also been vomiting prior to admission, but could not describe her vomitus as she was drowsy. </s></p><p n="p4.62"><s n="s1.2;p4.62">On the day of admission, Miss <name type="other"/> felt her bowel habit had been normal at 1/day. </s><s n="s2.2;p4.62">She had not observed her stool. </s></p><p n="p5.62"><s n="s1.6;p5.62">Miss <name type="other"/> had no problems swallowing foods or liquids. </s><s n="s2.6;p5.62">She had recently had a decreased appetite which she described as a typical prodrome to a 'flare up' of her Crohn's Disease, but felt this was not as bad as normal. </s><s n="s3.6;p5.62">She felt she had been suffering from a temperature over the previous 4 days, but had not recorded it. </s><s n="s4.6;p5.62">She had not lost any weight recently. </s><s n="s5.6;p5.62">Before admission, she stated she felt "tired all the time" before and during her 'flare ups'. </s><s n="s6.6;p5.62">Describing these exacerbations, she said she suffers from 1-2 minor episodes/year, which are usually managed by bed rest and a low dose of steroids from her GP. She has had 2 major flare ups in the past 3 years, which both required admission. </s></p><p n="p6.62"><s n="s1.1;p6.62">Miss <name type="other"/> intermittently suffers from mouth ulcers, but does not suffer from other rashes or conjunctivitis. </s></p><p n="p7.62"><s n="s1.2;p7.62">Referring to her original diagnosis, Miss <name type="other"/> had attended the Dr after losing a considerable amount of weight; when finally admitted in 1998 she was 4.5 stones, and had constant abdominal pain. </s><s n="s2.2;p7.62">Miss <name type="other"/> pays careful attention to her diet and is aware that nuts, digestive biscuits, and uncooked vegetables exacerbate her symptoms. </s></p><p n="p8.62"><s n="s1.5;p8.62">Miss <name type="other"/> had a right hemicolectomy in 2002 to resect part of her diseased colon. </s><s n="s2.5;p8.62">Unfortunately, there were pot-operative complications including septicaemia and subsequent respiratory failure requiring ITU admission. </s><s n="s3.5;p8.62">Her left knee fused as a result of septic arthritis in the joint, and that winter she fell on ice and fractured her left hip. </s><s n="s4.5;p8.62">Miss <name type="other"/> also has osteoporosis secondary to long-term steroid use. </s><s n="s5.5;p8.62">Otherwise, she has no other medical history of note. </s></p><p n="p9.62"><s n="s1.1;p9.62">There is no family history of inflammatory bowel disease, and no other relevant family history. </s></p><p n="p10.62"><s n="s1.1;p10.62">Miss <name type="other"/> is currently prescribed Mesalazine (400mg qds po) Azathioprine ( 140mg od po) Domperidone (10mg tds po), Folic acid (5mg od po) Oromorph (20 mls bd po) Co-codamol 8/500 (2 tablets qds prn) Alendronate (10mg mane po) Amytriptyline (75mg nocte po), Fluoxitine (20mg mane po). </s></p><p n="p11.62"><s n="s1.5;p11.62">Miss <name type="other"/> lives at home with her parents. </s><s n="s2.5;p11.62">She works as a receptionist; and has had to take a considerable amount of time off. </s><s n="s3.5;p11.62">Fortunately, her employer is understanding. </s><s n="s4.5;p11.62">She is a smoker with a 6 year pack history. </s><s n="s5.5;p11.62">She does not drink. </s></p><p n="p12.62"><s n="s1.1;p12.62">A systems review was unremarkable. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="bold">Analysis of history</hi> The most likely single cause of the presentation, other possible causes and reasons for these choices. </head><p n="p13.62"><s n="s1.3;p13.62">Miss <name type="other"/> is a 28 year old lady who has suffered many of the major sequalae of Crohn's disease. </s><s n="s2.3;p13.62">She had a right hemicolectomy in 2002 to remove a particularly ulcerated part of her bowel, and this had serious post-operative complication, resulting in further disability. </s><s n="s3.3;p13.62">She has a serious exacerbation of her Crohn's disease approximately every year. </s></p><p n="p14.62"><s n="s1.1;p14.62">In light of this information, this presentation of acute, severe abdominal pain which is similar in nature to previous attacks is suggestive of another symptomatic phase of Crohn's disease. </s></p><p n="p15.62"><s n="s1.1;p15.62">Other diagnoses that may have been considered include Ulcerative Colitis, Irritable Bowel Syndrome, Coeliac Disease and chronic infection (campylobacter/giardia). </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="bold">Physical examination</hi> Highlight the findings most relevant to your clinical problem solving by underlining them, highlighting them.</head><list type="simple"><head>General Obsevations:</head><item><hi rend="bold">HR 107/min</hi> <hi rend="bold">BP- 89/59 mmHg</hi> <hi rend="bold">Resp. Rate 18/min Temperature- 36.1 °C O2 Sats- 100% (room air)</hi> GCS- 15/15</item></list><p n="p16.62"><s rend="bold" n="s1.2;p16.62">Pale, ill young lady in considerable pain. </s><s n="s2.2;p16.62">°jaundice/cyanosis/oedema/lymphadenopathy. </s></p><list type="simple"><head rend="underlined">Abdominal exam</head><item><hi rend="bold">Finger clubbing, palmar erythema bilaterally and clinically anaemic. Puffy face consistent with Cushingoid appearance 2° long term steroid use. </hi>°pyoderma gangernosum/aphtous ulcers/glossitis. <hi rend="bold">Midline abdominal scar with 3 transverse incisions from previous abdominal surgery. Mild abdominal distension. Soft, tender abdomen, pain worse in left flank.</hi> °organomegaly or masses. <hi rend="bold">Bowel sounds increased.</hi> PR not performed on admission.</item></list><p n="p17.62"><s n="s1.1;p17.62">All other examinations were unremarkable. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="bold">Analysis of history and examination</hi> Construct a problem list.</head><list type="ordered"><head>Problem list:</head><item>Patient shocked.</item><item>Clinically anaemic.</item><item>May be obstructed.</item><item>Other consequences of acute exacerbation of Crohn's Disease- Pain, anorexia, fatigue.</item></list><p n="p18.62"/></div1><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="bold">Management</hi> Use the framework of RAPRIOP to structure your proposed management. Refer to the guidelines to the writing of portfolio cases for the details of the issues to be addressed under each heading. </head><div2><head rend="underlined">Investigations</head><list type="bulleted"><head>Bloods</head><item>Abnormal- FBC (Hb 7.5 g/dL (↓)), ESR (25 (↑)) CRP (0.92mg/L()), Serum Ferritin (300 ųg/ml ()).</item><item>Normal- B <hi rend="sub">12</hi>/Folate, U+Es, Ca <hi rend="sup">2+</hi>, LFTs, B-hCG.</item></list><list type="bulleted"><head>Imaging</head><item>X-rays of abdomen and chest. <hi rend="bold">Abominal X- ray showed dilated loops of small bowel in right iliac fossa.</hi> <hi rend="bold">Barium follow-through showed stricture in terminal ileum.</hi> </item><item>CT Abdomen. <hi rend="bold">Stricture in terminal ileum visualised.</hi> </item></list><p n="p19.62"/></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">Reassurance and explanation</head><p n="p20.62"><s n="s1.2;p20.62">"It is probably likely that you are suffering from another flare up of your Crohn's Disease. </s><s n="s2.2;p20.62">We are going to pass a tube down your throat to help relieve the feeling of fullness you have, and we are going to give you some drugs that have been proven to help with the symptoms of your illness. </s></p><p n="p21.62"><s n="s1.1;p21.62">You are also going to need some blood transfused, as you are very anaemic. </s></p><p n="p22.62"><s n="s1.1;p22.62">Finally, we a going to refer you to a dietician to help you consider the options you have during your outbreaks, and how we can minimise your symptoms." </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">Prescription/medical intervention</head><list type="ordered"><item>Budesamide 9mg od po.</item><item>NG tube passed.</item><item>Dietician referral.</item></list><p n="p23.62"/></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">Observation </head><p n="p24.62"><s n="s1.1;p24.62">Currently observed on ward. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">Referral and team working</head><list type="simple"><item>GP, A+E team on-call, General surgicalteam on-call. Dieticians, nurses.</item></list><p n="p25.62"/></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">Advice and Prevention</head><p n="p26.62"><s n="s1.1;p26.62">Stop smoking. </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="bold">Outcome</hi> A description of the progress of the patient as far as possible. This should include consideration of further issues to be resolved. Where appropriate you should contact by telephone patients who have been discharged home. </head><p n="p27.62"><s n="s1.3;p27.62">Progressing steadily on ward. </s><s n="s2.3;p27.62">The dietician advised a low residue diet, which was reluctantly accepted by Miss <name type="other"/>. </s><s n="s3.3;p27.62">Miss <name type="other"/> is now awaiting strictureplasty. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="bold">Evidence based care and issues for research</hi> A brief consideration of the evidence base required for the diagnosis and management of the patient's problem(s).</head><div2><head>1) Azathioprine</head><p n="p28.62"><s n="s1.4;p28.62">A review found in the Cochrane Library [1] reported that Azathioprine (1.0 to 2.5 mg/day) used among patients with non-active Crohn's disease may be effective for reducing the risk of disease recurrence over a 6 month to 2 year period. </s><s n="s2.4;p28.62">Higher doses of azathioprine (2.5 mg/day) are more effective than lower doses (1.0 or 2.0 mg/day) for preventing disease recurrence. </s><s n="s3.4;p28.62">There is also evidence that azathioprine reduces the need for steroid treatment which could help reduce steroid related side effects. </s><s n="s4.4;p28.62">However, since the studies were of short duration (6 months to 2 years) the long-term effectiveness of azathioprine is unclear. </s></p></div2><div2><head>(2) Budesonide</head><p n="p29.62"><s n="s1.3;p29.62">Research showing [2] that budesonide is effective in treating active Crohn's disease has led to trials examining the effect of budesonide on reducing disease recurrence in non-active Crohn's disease. </s><s n="s2.3;p29.62">However, the use of budesonide (3 mg and 6 mg/day) among patients with non-active Crohn's disease was not effective for reducing the risk of disease recurrence over a 12-month period. </s><s n="s3.3;p29.62">Further research is needed to investigate higher doses of budesonide, the use of budesonide in combination with other drugs and flexible dosing schedules. </s></p></div2><div2><head>(3) Corticosteriods and enteral nutrition</head><p n="p30.62"><s n="s1.3;p30.62">Evidence continues to indicate that corticosteroids are more effective than enteral nutrition (liquid food feedings into the small intestine) for treating active Crohn's disease [3]. </s><s n="s2.3;p30.62">Comparing one form of enteral nutrition to another has not shown any difference in effectiveness for treating active Crohn's disease. </s><s n="s3.3;p30.62">Further research is required. </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="bold">Commentary</hi> A commentary on issues of epidemiology, psycho-social, health care delivery, ethical issues or disability relevant to the patient and/or problem. </head><p n="p31.62"><s n="s1.2;p31.62">Crohn's Disease is a chronic inflammatory disease of the gastrointestinal tract of unknown aetiology. </s><s n="s2.2;p31.62">It can affect any part of the tract from the mouth→ anus, but most commonly affects the ileocaecal region (40%), or terminal ileum (35%). </s></p><p n="p32.62"><s n="s1.6;p32.62">Incidence in Europe and North America is 2-6/100 000/year. </s><s n="s2.6;p32.62">It is more common in the developed world, and in Europe is slightly more common in Northern Europe compared to Mediterranean countries. </s><s n="s3.6;p32.62">Prevalence in Japan is 10% of developed Northern Hemisphere countries. </s><s n="s4.6;p32.62">Incidence may have now peaked in far northern countries (Scotland, Sweden) [4]. </s><s n="s5.6;p32.62">It is slightly more common in females. </s><s n="s6.6;p32.62">Most patients present between the 3 <hi rend="sup">rd</hi>-7 <hi rend="sup">th</hi> decades of life; the disease can occur at any age, but is exceedingly rare in the very young. </s></p><p n="p33.62"><s n="s1.1;p33.62">Common clinical presentations include: </s></p><list type="bulleted"><item><hi rend="bold">Diarrhoea</hi> (70-90%).</item><item><hi rend="bold">Anal lesions</hi> (50-80%)</item><item><hi rend="bold">Weight loss</hi> (65-75%)</item><item><hi rend="bold">Abdominal pain</hi> (45-70%)</item><item><hi rend="bold">Fever</hi> (30-40%)</item><item><hi rend="bold">Fistula</hi> (8-10%)</item></list><p n="p34.62"><s n="s1.4;p34.62">Ileal disease is associated with pain and obstructive symptoms, commonly due to strictures. </s><s n="s2.4;p34.62">Features of malabsorbtion, and an inflammatory mass are also common. </s><s n="s3.4;p34.62">Colonic disease is associated with rectal bleeding, perianal disease and extra-articular manifestations of Crohn's Disease. </s><s n="s4.4;p34.62">These are either related or unrelated to disease activity: </s></p><list type="bulleted"><head>Related:</head><item>Aphthous ulceration (20%)</item><item>Erythema nodosum ( 5-10%)</item><item>Acute arthritis (6-12%)</item><item>Eye complications (conjunctivitis, episcleritis, uveitis) (3-10%)</item><item>Pyoderma gangrenosum (0.5%)</item></list><list type="bulleted"><head> Unrelated:</head><item>Sacroiliitis (18%)</item><item>Ankylosing spondylitis (75% patients are HLA-B27 +ve, and may preogress following proctocolectomy)</item></list><list type="bulleted"><head> Associated liver disease:</head><item>Primary sclerosing cholangitis.</item><item>Gallstones.</item><item>Fatty change.</item><item>Amyloidosis.</item><item>Granulomata.</item></list><p n="p35.62"><s n="s1.5;p35.62">The aetiology of Crohn's Disease is incompletely understood. </s><s n="s2.5;p35.62">15-20% of sufferers have one or more first degree relatives with the condition. </s><s n="s3.5;p35.62">Concordance with monozygotic twins is 45%; higher than that for ulcerative colitis. </s><s n="s4.5;p35.62">In an affected family, there is a remarkable degree of concordance (up to 80%) of disease type and behaviour, but offspring tend to develop the disease at a younger age than affected parents. </s><s n="s5.5;p35.62">Mutations in chromosome 6 are implicated in the disease, and also 6, 12 and 19. </s></p><p n="p36.62"><s n="s1.4;p36.62">Smoking increases the risk by 3-4 fold. </s><s n="s2.4;p36.62">It was thought that <hi rend="italic">M. paratuberculosis</hi> and the Measles virus had an infective role in Crohn's but the evidence is currently tenuous. </s><s n="s3.4;p36.62">Poor diets (high sugar, low fibre) are more common in patients before the diagnosis of Crohn's, although changing to this diet post diagnosis has no effect on disease progression over 2 years. </s><s n="s4.4;p36.62">There is evidence that the normal mechanisms for down regulating the mucosal immune responses are impaired in sufferers. </s></p><p n="p37.62"><s n="s1.4;p37.62">Pathologically, 'skip lesions' are described. </s><s n="s2.4;p37.62">These are affected segments of bowel, with normal bowel in-between. </s><s n="s3.4;p37.62">Affected bowel is usually thickened due to oedema and fibrosis. </s><s n="s4.4;p37.62">The mucosa is hyperaemic and there may be aphthous ulceration; the ulcers are usually situated over lymph tissue. </s></p><p n="p38.62"><s n="s1.3;p38.62">Histologically, there is transmural inflammation, although it is predominantly submucosal. </s><s n="s2.3;p38.62">Lymphoid aggregates are a common feature. </s><s n="s3.3;p38.62">Non-caseating granulomata occur in 50-70% patients. </s></p><p n="p39.62"><s n="s1.1;p39.62">Complications: </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p40.62"><s n="s1.4;p40.62"><hi rend="bold">Strictures</hi>. </s><s n="s2.4;p40.62">Large or small bowel. </s><s n="s3.4;p40.62">More common in small intestine. </s><s n="s4.4;p40.62">Initially asymptomatic, but can progress to obstructive symptoms. </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p41.62"><s n="s1.4;p41.62"><hi rend="bold">Fistulae</hi>. </s><s n="s2.4;p41.62">May develop between loops of bowel adjacent to bladder or vagina, and skin. </s><s n="s3.4;p41.62">Pneumaturia and recurrent UTI indicate a fistula into the bladder. </s><s n="s4.4;p41.62">Passage of flatus or faeculent discharge from the vagina indicate a vaginal fistula. </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p42.62"><s n="s1.3;p42.62"><hi rend="bold">Perianal disease</hi>. </s><s n="s2.3;p42.62">Fissures/fistulae/abscesses. </s><s n="s3.3;p42.62">Fleshy skin tags are common. </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p43.62"><s n="s1.2;p43.62"><hi rend="bold">Carcinoma</hi>. </s><s n="s2.2;p43.62">May complicate long-standing Crohn's Disease of the colon; the incidence may be similar to that of Ulcerative Colitis, with the exception of reduced incidence of 1 sclerosing cholangitis and bile duct carcinoma. </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p44.62"><s n="s1.2;p44.62"><hi rend="bold">Ileocaecal disease</hi>. </s><s n="s2.2;p44.62">May involve right ureter, leading to recurrent pyelonephritis, ureteric stenosis, and hydronephrosis. </s></p><p n="p45.62"><s n="s1.1;p45.62">Investigations include: </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p46.62"><s n="s1.2;p46.62"><hi rend="bold">Bloods</hi>- FBC, Iron and folate (anaemia), ESR and CRP. Orosomucoids (α<hi rend="sub">1</hi>- glycoproteins) are usually raised and are useful in monitoring disease activity. </s><s n="s2.2;p46.62">Serum levels of K+ and albumin are often low. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p47.62"><s n="s1.1;p47.62"><hi rend="bold">Stool examination</hi>-excludes known pathogens. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p48.62"><s n="s1.3;p48.62"><hi rend="bold">Sigmoidoscopy and biopsy</hi>- Performed in all patients. </s><s n="s2.3;p48.62">30% of those with small bowel involvement exhibit histological evidence of rectal inflammation. </s><s n="s3.3;p48.62">May show features of Crohn's Disease. </s></p><list type="bulleted"><head><hi rend="bold">Imaging</hi>-</head><item>Small bowel enema-(introduction of barium directly into small intestine via nasoduodenal tube), and also air-contrast barium enema are the best techniques for barium imaging. </item><item>CT- Often more useful than ultrasonography, and may show thickened loops of small intestine.</item><item>MRI- investigation of choice for complex perianal disease. </item></list><p n="p49.62"><s n="s1.1;p49.62">Management: </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p50.62"><s n="s1.6;p50.62"><hi rend="bold">Conservative</hi>- Diet should be well-balanced with high fibre content. </s><s n="s2.6;p50.62">Low-fat, lactose-free or low-residue diet is required in those with steatorrhoea, hypolactasia or stricture. </s><s n="s3.6;p50.62">Elemental diets (amino acids + glucose)are almost as effective as prednisilone in treating active disease, and can be useful in some patients. </s><s n="s4.6;p50.62">However they are largely unpalatable, and may induce relapse more quickly in some patients. </s><s n="s5.6;p50.62">Supplements of B <hi rend="sub">12</hi>, folate and other complexes are advised. </s><s n="s6.6;p50.62">Osteomalacia should be treated with vitamin D. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p51.62"><s n="s1.2;p51.62"><hi rend="bold">Medical</hi>. </s><s n="s2.2;p51.62">Drug therapy is indicated in symptomatic patients </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p52.62"><s rend="bold" n="s1.3;p52.62">Corticosteroids. </s><s n="s2.3;p52.62">Budesonide 9mg od po is as effective as prednisolone, but with fewer side effects. </s><s n="s3.3;p52.62">Severe disease may require IV therapy (hydrocortisone 100mg qds) </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p53.62"><s rend="bold" n="s1.2;p53.62">Sulfasaline. </s><s n="s2.2;p53.62">1g bd may be beneficial in active colonic disease, but not efficacious in maintaining remission. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p54.62"><s rend="bold" n="s1.3;p54.62">Mesalazine. </s><s n="s2.3;p54.62">Upto 4 g od. </s><s n="s3.3;p54.62">Maintenace therapy following caecal or ileocaecal resection. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p55.62"><s n="s1.2;p55.62"><hi rend="bold">Immunosupression</hi>. </s><s n="s2.2;p55.62">Azathioprine 2.5mg/kg or 6-mercaptopurine 2.0mg/kg is indicated in those who continually relapse and who are dependent on low-dose steroids for remission. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p56.62"><s n="s1.5;p56.62"><hi rend="bold">Immunotherapy</hi>. </s><s n="s2.5;p56.62">Infliximab 5mg/kg is currently the only licenced IgG chemeric antibody to TNF-α. </s><s n="s3.5;p56.62">Indicated in chronic acive disease resistant to corticosteroids and immunosupression. </s><s n="s4.5;p56.62">Closes 50% of fistulae. </s><s n="s5.5;p56.62">Single IV dose provent to be efficacious. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p57.62"><s rend="bold" n="s1.4;p57.62">Surgery. </s><s n="s2.4;p57.62">75-85% of Crohn's patients require at least one surgical intervention. </s><s n="s3.4;p57.62">Main indications are strictures causing obstruction and failure to respond to medical therapy. </s><s n="s4.4;p57.62">Commonest interventions are stricureplasty or resection. </s></p><p n="p58.62"><s n="s1.1;p58.62">Mortality is about twice that expected in age/sex matched control populations. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="bold">Impact on your learning</hi> Describe what you have learnt from this case.</head><list type="simple"><item>Presenation, management and discriminators of inflammatory bowel diease. Psycho-social consequences of younger patients living with crohnic disease.</item></list><p n="p59.62"><s n="s1.6;p59.62">1. </s><s n="s2.6;p59.62">Pearson DC, May GR, Fick G, Sutherland LR. Azathioprine for maintenance of remission in Crohn's disease. </s><s n="s3.6;p59.62"><hi rend="italic">The Cochrane Database of Systematic Reviews</hi> 1998, Issue 4. </s><s n="s4.6;p59.62">Art. </s><s n="s5.6;p59.62">No.: CD000067. </s><s n="s6.6;p59.62">DOI: 10.1002/14651858.CD000067. </s></p><p n="p60.62"><s n="s1.6;p60.62">2. </s><s n="s2.6;p60.62">Steinhart AH, Otley A. Budesonide for induction of remission in Crohn's disease. </s><s n="s3.6;p60.62"><hi rend="italic">The Cochrane Database of Systematic Reviews</hi> 1996, Issue 2. </s><s n="s4.6;p60.62">Art. </s><s n="s5.6;p60.62">No.: CD000296. </s><s n="s6.6;p60.62">DOI: 10.1002/14651858.CD000296. </s></p><p n="p61.62"><s n="s1.6;p61.62">3. </s><s n="s2.6;p61.62">Zachos M, Tondeur M, Griffiths AM. Enteral nutritional therapy for induction of remission in Crohn's disease. </s><s n="s3.6;p61.62"><hi rend="italic">The Cochrane Database of Systematic Reviews</hi> 2001, Issue 3. </s><s n="s4.6;p61.62">Art. </s><s n="s5.6;p61.62">No.: CD000542. </s><s n="s6.6;p61.62">DOI: 10.1002/14651858.CD000542. </s></p><p n="p62.62"><s n="s1.3;p62.62">4. </s><s n="s2.3;p62.62">Jewell, Derek P. Inflammatory Bowel Disease:Crohn's Disease.Medicine (Student Edition). </s><s n="s3.3;p62.62">Vol 31:2 (2003), The Medicine Publishing Company Ltd. </s></p></div1></body><back/></text></TEI.2>
