<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_0114j" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Portfolio Case No. 23</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">Language used in quote: <foreign id="English">English</foreign></note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">proforma
deleted: page numbers
</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">4</p><p n="date">2004-06</p><p n="module title">Elective</p><p n="module code">unknown</p><p n="genre family">Case study</p><p n="discipline">Medicine</p><p n="disciplinary group">LS</p><p n="grade">D</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">2038</p><p n="number of s-units">99</p><p n="number of p">44</p><p n="number of tables">0</p><p n="number of figures">0</p><p n="number of block quotes">1</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">3</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">0</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">20.6</p><p n="average s-units per p">2.3</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">m</p><p n="year of birth">1979</p><p n="first language">English</p><p n="education">UKA</p><p n="course">Medicine Phase II</p><p n="student ID">0114</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><docTitle><titlePart><hi rend="bold">PORTFOLIO CASE No:</hi> 23</titlePart></docTitle><titlePart>Patient Initials Hospital Number Age Gender Miss <name type="other"/> Keep separate list 23 Female</titlePart><titlePart>Portfolio Case presentation number: Phase 2 course document objective(s): </titlePart></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="bold">Referral information</hi> Source of referral and a summary of key information</head><p n="p1.44"><s n="s1.1;p1.44">Miss <name type="other"/> is a 23-year old receptionist who was electively admitted on <name type="date"/> with chronic pelvic pain. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="bold">History</hi> All <hi rend="bold italic">relevant</hi> information gathered from the patient about the presenting illness, co-existing problems, and current treatment, significant past medical history and the social and family background. The patient's view of the nature of the problem and their expectations for treatment. </head><p n="p2.44"><s n="s1.4;p2.44">Miss <name type="other"/> has complained of recurrent pain predominantly in the left iliac fossa, and also suprapubic area for the past seven years, which has progressively been getting worse for the last 3-4 years. </s><s n="s2.4;p2.44">She describes the pain as "sharp", grades it as 10/10 at its worst, and currently suffers the same pattern of pain on a daily basis. </s><s n="s3.4;p2.44">The pain is aggravated by lying flat, and relieved by trunk flexion. </s><s n="s4.4;p2.44">She takes no medication for the pain, it does not radiate, there are no associated factors, and it is not linked with her menstrual cycle. </s></p><p n="p3.44"><s n="s1.3;p3.44">Her cycle is currently regular with 5/5 days bleeding every 30 days. </s><s n="s2.3;p3.44">There was no intermenstrual or post-coital bleeding, and no discharge. </s><s n="s3.3;p3.44">Her cervical smears have been normal since she started on the screening programme aged 20. </s></p><p n="p4.44"><s n="s1.3;p4.44">Miss <name type="other"/> was admitted with the same complaint in 1997, and in 2000 had a diagnostic laparoscopy. </s><s n="s2.3;p4.44">Miss <name type="other"/> had a bout of oligomenorrhoea in 1996 that resolved spontaneously. </s><s n="s3.3;p4.44">She currently complains of a two-year history of dysparenuria on deep penetration. </s></p><p n="p5.44"><s n="s1.3;p5.44">Miss <name type="other"/> has had no previous pregnancies, miscarriages or abortions. </s><s n="s2.3;p5.44">She has had six previous sexual partners, and has had a stable partner for the last seven years. </s><s n="s3.3;p5.44">She does not use contraception. </s></p><p n="p6.44"><s n="s1.1;p6.44">Her past medical history is unremarkable excepting removal of a naevus from her groin aged 11, and grommets in her ears aged 4. </s></p><p n="p7.44"><s n="s1.1;p7.44">She takes no medications, and has no known allergies. </s></p><p n="p8.44"><s n="s1.3;p8.44">Socially, Miss <name type="other"/> works as a receptionist, and lives with her fiancée. </s><s n="s2.3;p8.44">She smokes 10 cigarettes/day, and takes on significant alcohol. </s><s n="s3.3;p8.44">A systems review was unremarkable. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="bold">Physical examination</hi> Highlight the findings most relevant to your clinical problem solving by underlining them</head><div2><head><hi rend="bold">General</hi> - </head><list type="simple"><item>HR- 68, regular. RR- 14/min. BP- 163/68 HS- I + II + 0 added. Temp- Afebrile. °Jaundice/anaemia/cyanosis/clubbing/oedema/lymphadenopathy. Appears well.</item></list><p n="p9.44"/></div2><div2><head rend="bold">Abdominal</head><list type="simple"><item>°organomegaly. Soft and non-tender. BS++, normal. °PR examination performed.</item></list><p n="p10.44"/></div2><div2><head rend="bold">Vaginal </head><p n="p11.44"><s n="s1.3;p11.44">There were no ulcerations, erythematous patches or signs of infection on the vulva or vaginal orifice. </s><s n="s2.3;p11.44">The cervix was closed, and the uterus a normal size. </s><s n="s3.3;p11.44">The adnexae and anterior fornix were tender on palpation. </s></p><p n="p12.44"><s n="s1.1;p12.44">All other examinations were unremarkable. </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="bold">Analysis of history and examination</hi> Reasons for your choice of the cause of the patient's problem(s) and any other cause that still needs to be considered at this stage</head><p n="p13.44"><s n="s1.4;p13.44">Considering the age, duration of complaint, and sexual history of the patient, the causes of chronic pelvic pain are limited. </s><s n="s2.4;p13.44">The most likely diagnoses at this stage are Pelvic Inflammatory Disease (PID), endometriosis, Pelvic pain syndrome (chronic pelvic pain + dysparenuria without organic cause). </s><s n="s3.4;p13.44">Less likely is irritable bowel syndrome (IBS), and other causes of pelvic masses. </s><s n="s4.4;p13.44">This may also be an atypical presentation of sub-acute appendicitis. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="bold">Formulation of the patient's problem(s)</hi> Encapsulate this in physical, psychological and social terms (the triple diagnosis)</head><p n="p14.44"><s n="s1.3;p14.44">Miss <name type="other"/> is a 23-year old lady who has been suffering from chronic, daily pelvic pain for the past 7 years. </s><s n="s2.3;p14.44">This affects her performing her daily activities, has caused her to have irregular periods, causes her pain during sexual intercourse, and has caused her worry about her fertility as she has had unprotected regular sex with the same partner for the last 7 years. </s><s n="s3.3;p14.44">Socially it has affected her as she describes being embarrassed as she suddenly "doubles up" in pain without warning. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="bold">Management</hi> Use the framework of RAPRIOP to structure your proposed management. Refer to the guidelines to the writing of portfolio cases for the details of the issues to be addressed under each heading.</head><div2><head rend="underlined">Investigations</head><list type="simple"><item>Bloods- FBC, U+Es, CRP, Group + Save.</item><item>Pregnancy test.</item><item>Laparoscopy- A laparoscopy in 2000 was reported thus:</item></list><quote lang="English">"Obvious evidence of infection within the pelvis. Multiple filmy adhesions within the omentum and sigmoid were evident, attaching mainly to the fundus of the uterus, and serosa of the fallopian tubes. Further inspection revealed tethering of the ovaries to the back of the broad ligaments. A dye salpingogram revealed a non-patent left fallopian tube, and a right fallopian tube, which filled and eventually spilled. Impression- evidence of previous pelvic infection, and blocked left fallopian tube giving an increased risk of ectopic pregnancy, and decreased chance of conceiving." </quote><p n="p15.44"><s n="s1.1;p15.44">A high vaginal was positive for <hi rend="italic">Staphylococcus aureus</hi> , and + for erythrocytes. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">Reassurance and explanation</head><p n="p16.44"><s n="s1.3;p16.44">Miss <name type="other"/> was counselled regarding the risks of general anaesthesia, and consented for a laparoscopy, laparotomy and left salpingoophrectomy. </s><s n="s2.3;p16.44">A discussion regarding future family plans also took place, and the risks and potential benefits of removal of an ovary and fallopian tube were discussed. </s><s n="s3.3;p16.44">The possibility of IVF at a later stage was also considered and explained. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">Prescription/medical intervention</head><p n="p17.44"><s n="s1.1;p17.44">Miss <name type="other"/> underwent a diagnostic laparoscopy and subsequent laparotomy and left salpingoophrectomy. </s></p><p n="p18.44"><s n="s1.2;p18.44">Post-operatively, she was prescribed IV Metronidazole (1g/8hrs) and Cefuroxime (1.5g/8hrs). </s><s n="s2.2;p18.44">She was also prescribed Co-codamol 8/500 prn. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">Observation </head><p n="p19.44"><s n="s1.1;p19.44">Post-operatively, Miss <name type="other"/> was observed on the ward for 3 days and discharged with a 6/52 Outpatient appointment. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">Referral and team working</head><p n="p20.44"><s n="s1.1;p20.44">Involved Miss <name type="other"/>'s GP, theatre staff, and the Obstetricians and Gynaecologists at Miss <name type="other"/> Hospital. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">Advice and Prevention</head><p n="p21.44"><s n="s1.2;p21.44">Excepting abstention, barrier methods of contraception are the best way to prevent chlamydial infection. </s><s n="s2.2;p21.44">The progesterone-only pill is also thought to be slightly protective due to the mucus plug formation. </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="bold">Outcome</hi> A description of the progress of the patient as far as possible. This should include consideration of further issues to be resolved. Where appropriate you should contact by telephone patients who have been discharged home.</head><p n="p22.44"><s n="s1.4;p22.44">Mrs <name type="other"/> underwent a diagnostic laparoscopy, which showed multiple adhesions from the fundus of the uterus to the peritoneum. </s><s n="s2.4;p22.44">The left ovary was covered with multiple adhesions to surrounding structures, and the right ovary also displayed adhesions to the back of the broad ligament. </s><s n="s3.4;p22.44">The right fallopian tube looked unhealthy, and the right ovary had a clubbed appearance. </s><s n="s4.4;p22.44">The adhesions were divided, and a left salpingoophrectomy was performed. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="bold">Evidence based medicine (EBM) and issues for research</hi> A brief consideration of the evidence base required for the diagnosis and management of the patient's problem(s)</head><p n="p23.44"><s n="s1.1;p23.44">'Clinical Evidence' has provided EBM on 'empirical vs. delayed treatment until the results of microbiological investigations are known' and 'how do different antimicrobial regimes compare?' </s></p><div2><head>1)<hi rend="underlined"> August 2003- Empirical antibiotic treatment</hi></head><p n="p24.44"><s n="s1.2;p24.44">No Randomised Controlled Trials comparing empirical antibiotic treatment versus treatment guided by test results [1]. </s><s n="s2.2;p24.44">However, one case control study found that delaying treatment is associated with reduced fertility [2]. </s></p></div2><div2><head>2) <hi rend="underlined">August 2003- Different antimicrobial regimes</hi></head><p n="p25.44"><s n="s1.5;p25.44">There is consensus that antibiotic treatments are more effective than no treatment for women with confirmed pelvic inflammatory disease (PID). </s><s n="s2.5;p25.44">One systematic review of observational studies and RCTs has found that several different antibiotic regimens (including parenteral clindamycin plus parenteral aminoglycoside; parenteral cephalosporin with or without probenecid plus oral doxycycline; and oral ofloxacin) are similarly effective in relieving the symptoms of PID, and achieve high rates of clinical and microbiological cure. </s><s n="s3.5;p25.44">We found no good evidence on the optimal duration of treatment. </s><s n="s4.5;p25.44">Two RCTs found no significant difference between oral ofloxacin versus parenteral cefoxitin and doxycycline. </s><s n="s5.5;p25.44">One RCT found no significant difference between outpatient treatment with intramuscular cefoxitin - probenecid and oral doxycycline versus parenteral antibiotics for outcomes of recurrence, infertility, or ectopic pregnancy at 35 months [3]. </s></p><p n="p26.44"><s n="s1.1;p26.44">In the studies reviewed, cure rates of between 88-100% were achieved [4,5]. </s></p><p n="p27.44"><s n="s1.1;p27.44">It is interesting to note that there is no EBM explicitly directed towards medical vs. surgical management of PID, and no EBM on methods of restoring tubal function post- PID. </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="bold">Commentary</hi> A commentary on issues of epidemiology, psycho-social, health care delivery, ethical issues or disability relevant to the patient and/or problem</head><p n="p28.44"><s n="s1.1;p28.44">Pelvic inflammatory disease (PID) is a spectrum of infections of the female genital tract that includes endometritis, salpingitis, tuboovarian abscess, and peritonitis. </s></p><p n="p29.44"><s n="s1.2;p29.44">PID exclusively affects women, and around 1 in 50 sexually active women in the UK develop PID each year. </s><s n="s2.2;p29.44">It is most common in women aged between 15 and 24, although sexually active women of any age may contract PID. </s></p><p n="p30.44"><s n="s1.3;p30.44">Depending on the severity of the infection, patients with PID may be minimally symptomatic or may present with toxic symptoms of fever, nausea, vomiting, and severe pain. </s><s n="s2.3;p30.44">The commonest reported symptom of PID is uni/bilateral lower abdominal pain. </s><s n="s3.3;p30.44">However, vaginal discharge, lower back pain, and irregular vaginal bleeding also commonly occur. </s></p><p n="p31.44"><s n="s1.3;p31.44">One of the commonest signs of PID is lower abdominal tenderness. </s><s n="s2.3;p31.44">Pelvic examination may reveal mucopurulent cervical discharge, cervical excitation, uterine tenderness, and/or bilateral adnexal tenderness. </s><s n="s3.3;p31.44">An adnexal mass may be found in more extensive cases, suggesting a tuboovarian abscess, or peritonitis may be present, mimicking an acute surgical abdomen. </s></p><p n="p32.44"><s n="s1.6;p32.44">PID is a worldwide phenomenon, but the commonest causative agent(s) vary with location. </s><s n="s2.6;p32.44">In the West the commonest infective agents is <hi rend="italic">Chlamydia trachomatis</hi> followed by <hi rend="italic"> Neisseria gonorrhoeae,</hi> although many Gram-negative organisms (e.g. </s><s n="s3.6;p32.44"><hi rend="italic">E. coli</hi>) and Gram-positive organisms (e.g. </s><s n="s4.6;p32.44"><hi rend="italic">Streptococci</hi> Groups B and D) are also causative agents. </s><s n="s5.6;p32.44">Anaerobes (e.g. </s><s n="s6.6;p32.44"><hi rend="italic">Bacteriodes), Mycoplasma</hi> <hi rend="italic">hominis</hi>, and <hi rend="italic">Actinomyces israelii</hi> have also been identified as causative agents in PID, although a sexually transmitted infectious organism is not recovered in a third of women with PID. Certain infectious agents have also been linked with intrauterine contraceptive devices (IUCDs). </s></p><p n="p33.44"><s n="s1.4;p33.44">The pathogenesis of PID is incompletely understood. </s><s n="s2.4;p33.44">However, mononuclear cells are one of the hallmarks of chronic inflammation. </s><s n="s3.4;p33.44">In chronically or repeatedly infected individuals, increased chlamydial hsp (heat shock protein) expression secondary to the action of gamma interferon produced by the T-helper 1 cell mediated immune response might drive persistent chlamydial infection and chronic inflammation. </s><s n="s4.4;p33.44">Chronic infection might in turn lead to the fibrosis and scarring characteristic of the severe sequelae of <hi rend="italic">C. trachomatis</hi> infection. </s></p><p n="p34.44"><s n="s1.2;p34.44">On Laparoscopy, adhesions between the ovaries, fallopian tubes peritoneum and other structures may be evident. </s><s n="s2.2;p34.44">The adhesions due to <hi rend="italic">C. trachomatis</hi> are said to have a characteristic filmy appearance, although this is not pathognomonic of <hi rend="italic">C. trachomatis infection.</hi> </s></p><p n="p35.44"><s n="s1.8;p35.44">Management of PID is either medical or surgical. </s><s n="s2.8;p35.44">Medical management must first begin with a sensitive; yet frank discussion about sexual health. </s><s n="s3.8;p35.44">Risk factors for PID include youth and sexual activity (under 25), multiple sexual partners, and not using barrier methods of contraception. </s><s n="s4.8;p35.44">The patient should be asked to bring her partner(s) in for screening to the clinic, and abstain from sexual activity with them until they have also been treated. </s><s n="s5.8;p35.44">Doxycycline 100mg bds for 7 days the current recommended outpatient regime. </s><s n="s6.8;p35.44">Side effects include possible interference with the pill, and photosensitivity. </s><s n="s7.8;p35.44">If there are doubts about compliance, 1g azithromycin may be prescribed immediately. </s><s n="s8.8;p35.44">If pregnant or lactating, erythromycin 500mg qds for 7 days may be used, although a test for cure 3 weeks later is recommended, as this method is less effective than Doxycycline. </s></p><p n="p36.44"><s n="s1.1;p36.44">Long-term sequelae of PID include infertility, chronic persistent pain, increased incidence of ectopic pregnancy, increased further risk of PID, and tuboovarian abscess. </s></p><p n="p37.44"><s n="s1.3;p37.44">Surgical management is indicated for chronic pain 2 to adhesions, and tuboovarian abscesses. </s><s n="s2.3;p37.44">The most common operation performed is salpingoophrectomy, although this has considerable effects on the woman's fertility. </s><s n="s3.3;p37.44">Appropriate counselling should be given regarding assisted conception and future family planning. </s></p><p n="p38.44"><s n="s1.1;p38.44">Up to 30% women become infertile after one episode of PID, 9% have an ectopic pregnancy, and 18% experience chronic pelvic pain. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="bold">Impact on your learning</hi> Describe what you have learnt from this case</head><p n="p39.44"><s n="s1.2;p39.44">Presentation and differential diagnosis of chronic pelvic pain. </s><s n="s2.2;p39.44">Medical and surgical management of PID. Psychological and financial consequences of infertility in young women. </s></p><p n="p40.44"><s n="s1.1;p40.44"><seg type="URL" n="http://www.clinicalevidence.com/ceweb/conditions/seh/1606/1606_I1.jsp"/> </s></p><p n="p41.44"><s n="s1.2;p41.44">Hillis SD, Joesoef R, Marchbanks PA,al. Delayed care of pelvic inflammatory disease as a risk factor for impaired fertility. </s><s n="s2.2;p41.44"><hi rend="italic">Am J Obstet Gynecol</hi> 1993;168:1503 - 1509. </s></p><p n="p42.44"><s n="s1.1;p42.44"><seg type="URL" n="http://www.clinicalevidence.com/ceweb/conditions/seh/1606/1606_I2.jsp"/> </s></p><p n="p43.44"><s n="s1.2;p43.44">Walker CK, Kahn JG, Washington AE,al. Pelvic inflammatory disease: metaanalysis of antimicrobial regimen efficacy. </s><s n="s2.2;p43.44"><hi rend="italic">J Infect Dis</hi> 1993;168:969 - 978. </s></p><p n="p44.44"><s n="s1.2;p44.44">Walker CK, Workowski KA, Washington AE,al. Anaerobes in pelvic inflammatory disease: implications for the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention's guidelines for treatment of sexually transmitted diseases. </s><s n="s2.2;p44.44"><hi rend="italic">Clin Infect Dis</hi> 1999;28(suppl):29 - 36. </s></p></div1></body><back/></text></TEI.2>
