<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_0114i" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Portfolio Case No. 20</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">proforma
deleted: page numbers
</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">4</p><p n="date">2004-02</p><p n="module title">Other Rotations</p><p n="module code">unknown</p><p n="genre family">Case study</p><p n="discipline">Medicine</p><p n="disciplinary group">LS</p><p n="grade">D</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">2146</p><p n="number of s-units">113</p><p n="number of p">51</p><p n="number of tables">0</p><p n="number of figures">0</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">9</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">3</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">19.0</p><p n="average s-units per p">2.2</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">m</p><p n="year of birth">1979</p><p n="first language">English</p><p n="education">UKA</p><p n="course">Medicine Phase II</p><p n="student ID">0114</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><docTitle><titlePart><hi rend="bold">PORTFOLIO CASE No:</hi> 20</titlePart></docTitle><titlePart>Patient Initials Hospital Number Age Gender Mrs <name type="other"/> Keep separate list 71 Female</titlePart><titlePart>Portfolio Case presentation number: Phase 2 course document objective(s): </titlePart></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="bold">Referral information</hi> Source of referral and a summary of key information</head><p n="p1.51"><s n="s1.1;p1.51">Admitted via GP on <name type="date"/> with shortness of breath (SOB) and leg pain. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="bold">History</hi> All <hi rend="bold italic">relevant</hi> information gathered from the patient about the presenting illness, co-existing problems, and current treatment, significant past medical history and the social and family background. The patient's view of the nature of the problem and their expectations for treatment. </head><p n="p2.51"><s n="s1.1;p2.51">On admission, Mrs <name type="other"/> stated she always found it had to 'catch her breath' due to her Rheumatoid Arthritis (RA), but over the 4 days preceding admission her breathlessness was becoming progressively worse since suffering from a chest infection. </s></p><p n="p3.51"><s n="s1.3;p3.51">Mrs <name type="other"/> said she had a productive cough for the previous 2 days, and was expectorating several hundred millilitres of brown/green phlegm a day. </s><s n="s2.3;p3.51">She was coughing up increasing amounts of phlegm prior to admission, and there was no diurnal variation in amount. </s><s n="s3.3;p3.51">Mrs <name type="other"/>'s exercise tolerance had decreased, as she could formerly walk 'over a 100 yards' with her frame but now could only manage 'about 10 yards'. </s></p><p n="p4.51"><s n="s1.3;p4.51">Mrs <name type="other"/> said she always suffered from a wheeze, but it was currently worse than normal. </s><s n="s2.3;p4.51">She was also suffering from a fever on admission, and described herself as being 'rather delirious'. </s><s n="s3.3;p4.51">She had also noticed an increasing hoarseness of voice over the preceding days, but could not elaborate further. </s></p><p n="p5.51"><s n="s1.2;p5.51">Mrs <name type="other"/> is a former smoker of 30 pack-years who quit 23 years ago. </s><s n="s2.2;p5.51">She had not complained of haemoptysis, chest pain or night sweats. </s></p><p n="p6.51"><s n="s1.5;p6.51">Regarding her leg pain, Mrs <name type="other"/> said it had followed a similar time course to her SOB. She indicated the pain was at its worst on her right leg about 5cm below her patella. </s><s n="s2.5;p6.51">She described it as being 'stinging' in nature, and graded the pain as being 10/10. </s><s n="s3.5;p6.51">It was aggravated by standing and weight bearing, and relieved by E45 topical cream. </s><s n="s4.5;p6.51">It had no timing associations, or was associated with anything else. </s><s n="s5.5;p6.51">Mrs <name type="other"/> felt sure she was suffering from phlebitis as she had a similar bout 35 years ago. </s></p><p n="p7.51"><s n="s1.4;p7.51">Mrs <name type="other"/>'s RA was diagnosed 20 years ago and progressed from her toes proximally to eventually involve her metatarsophalangeal joints, ankles, knees, elbows, shoulders and cervical spine (c-spine). </s><s n="s2.4;p7.51">Her most recent bout involved her c-spine where she described pain, morning stiffness, and fatigue, loss of flexion/extension / lateral movements and weakness that required a cervical collar for support. </s><s n="s3.4;p7.51">At the time of the exacerbation, she had no rash, fever, constipation, ulcers or fatigue. </s><s n="s4.4;p7.51">She did not complain of neck pain or a change in sensation down her arms. </s></p><p n="p8.51"><s n="s1.4;p8.51">Mrs <name type="other"/> said the changes in her hands due to RA resulted in her finding it very difficult to grip objects with either hand. </s><s n="s2.4;p8.51">This causes her difficulty in all areas of her life. </s><s n="s3.4;p8.51">Mrs <name type="other"/> stated she could no longer hold a cup with one hand, use a chopping board to cut vegetables or prepare food, and had to put her bra on back to front as she could not reach around her back and perform the necessary movements. </s><s n="s4.4;p8.51">She has also had to give her main hobby of knitting, which was also an incidental source of income. </s></p><p n="p9.51"><s n="s1.1;p9.51">Mrs <name type="other"/>'s other past medical history includes: </s></p><list type="simple"><item>RESP- 5 bouts of pneumonia between the ages of 3-30 </item><item>ORTHO- osteoporosis of the lower back, date of diagnosis uncertain.</item><item>CVS- Hypertension, date of diagnosis uncertain.</item></list><p n="p10.51"><s n="s1.1;p10.51">Her prescriptions on admission were: </s></p><list type="simple"><item>Co-codamol 30/500 prn, Alendronic acid 70mg weekly, Ergocalciferol 20 micrograms od, Pantoprazole 20mg od, Distamine (penicillamine) 125mg od, Flucloxacillin 250mg tds, Perindopril 4mg od, Prednisolone 7.5mg od, Salbutamol 100 micrograms inhalation prn, Beclamethasone 200mg tds.</item></list><p n="p11.51"><s n="s1.1;p11.51">There was no significant family history. </s></p><p n="p12.51"><s n="s1.3;p12.51">Mrs <name type="other"/> lives with her son in a semi-detached bungalow with no stairs. </s><s n="s2.3;p12.51">She has a strong family support network of her daughter, sister in law, and neighbours. </s><s n="s3.3;p12.51">She does not drink alcohol. </s></p><p n="p13.51"><s n="s1.1;p13.51">A systems review revealed nothing of note. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="bold">Analysis of history</hi> The most likely single cause of the presentation and other possible causes. </head><div2><head rend="underlined">Likely/ potentially dangerous</head><p n="p14.51"><s n="s1.1;p14.51">The most likely diagnosis at this stage would be a Lower Respiratory Tract Infection (LRTI) on a background of lung fibrosis 2 to RA. </s></p><p n="p15.51"><s n="s1.2;p15.51">Important, less likely causes requiring exclusion includes a pulmonary embolus (PE), pneumothorax, Cardiac failure, and valvular disease. </s><s n="s2.2;p15.51">Malignant causes are less likely, but must also be considered. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">Less likely/ dangerous</head><p n="p16.51"><s n="s1.1;p16.51">First presentation of adult onset asthma, anaemia, COPD, physical deconditioning. </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="bold">Physical examination</hi> Highlight the findings most relevant to your clinical problem solving by underlining them</head><list type="simple"><head><hi rend="underlined"><hi rend="bold">General: </hi>RR-18</hi>, HR- 92, regular. BP- 167/76, O <hi rend="sub">2</hi> Sats- 96% on 2L/min O <hi rend="sub">2.</hi> Temp. 36.2 c. Jaundice/ Anaemia/ Cyanosis/Clubbing/ Oedema/ Lymphadenopathy.</head><item><hi rend="underlined">Tachypnoeic, with obvious wheeze. Patient flushed and warm</hi>.</item></list><list type="simple"><head rend="underlined bold">Respiratory</head><item rend="underlined">Fine inspiratory crackles bilaterally at both bases, with a soft biphasic wheeze. Bronchial breath sounds at right base. </item></list><list type="simple"><head rend="underlined bold">CVS</head><item>Heart sounds I +II, none added. No murmurs or carotid bruits.</item></list><list type="simple"><head rend="underlined bold">Abdomen</head><item>Abdomen soft + non-tender. No hepatomegaly/splenomegaly.</item></list><list type="simple"><head rend="underlined bold">Legs</head><item>Tender erythematous area over right anterior medial leg below patella. <hi rend="underlined">No calf tenderness</hi>.</item></list><p n="p17.51"/></div1><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="bold">Analysis of history and examination</hi> Reasons for your choice of the cause of the patient's problem(s) and any other cause that still needs to be considered at this stage</head><p n="p18.51"><s n="s1.1;p18.51">The strong, typical history of chest infection coupled with the examination findings of tachypnoea, bilateral basal crackles, and bronchial breath sounds at the right base all further support the diagnosis of chest infection </s></p><p n="p19.51"><s n="s1.2;p19.51">superimposed on lung fibrosis 2 to RA. The wheeze may have previously been present, or a new finding. </s><s n="s2.2;p19.51">The only unexpected finding was the patient being afebrile. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="bold">Management</hi> Use the framework of RAPRIOP to structure your proposed management. Refer to the guidelines to the writing of portfolio cases for the details of the issues to be addressed under each heading.</head><div2><head rend="underlined">Investigations</head><list type="simple"><item>Bloods- FBC, U+Es, CRP.</item><item>Imaging- CXR.</item><item>Others- Peak flow measurement, ECG.</item></list><p n="p20.51"/></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">Reassurance and explanation</head><p n="p21.51"><s n="s1.1;p21.51">Mrs <name type="other"/> was well- orientated in her illness, and asked questions when she felt unsure. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">Prescription/medical intervention</head><list type="simple"><item>Co-amoxiclav 750 mg po, + 1.2g stat i.v. Increase prednisolone to 30mg.</item><item>Regular nebulisers.</item><item>Regular PEFR. Repeat ECG.</item></list><p n="p22.51"/></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">Observation </head><p n="p23.51"><s n="s1.1;p23.51">Observed on ward for 4 days. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">Referral and team working</head><p n="p24.51"><s n="s1.1;p24.51">Mrs <name type="other"/>'s care involved her GP, and the on-call team at the Hospital of <name type="other"/>, <name type="other"/>. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">Advice and Prevention</head><p n="p25.51"><s n="s1.2;p25.51">Avoid people with respiratory infections. </s><s n="s2.2;p25.51">Have Influenza inoculation. </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="bold">Outcome</hi> A description of the progress of the patient as far as possible. This should include consideration of further issues to be resolved. Where appropriate you should contact by telephone patients who have been discharged home.</head><p n="p26.51"><s n="s1.6;p26.51">Patient became febrile during the night (T= 38c). </s><s n="s2.6;p26.51">CRP was elevated. </s><s n="s3.6;p26.51">The CXR showed reticular shadowing bilaterally. </s><s n="s4.6;p26.51">The ECG was unremarkable. </s><s n="s5.6;p26.51">Peak flow was 240 ml/s. </s><s n="s6.6;p26.51">Discharged uneventfully after 4 days. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="bold">Evidence based care and issues for research</hi> A brief consideration of the evidence base required for the diagnosis and management of the patient's problem(s)</head><p n="p27.51"><s n="s1.1;p27.51">There is a reasonable amount of recent clinical evidence on RA. The most relevant summaries are presented below. </s></p><div2><head rend="underlined">Disease-modifying anti-rheumatic drugs (DMARD)</head><p n="p28.51"><s n="s1.1;p28.51">One systematic review and one additional RCT found that introducing disease modifying antirheumatic drugs early (oral gold, intramuscular gold, hydroxychloroquine, methotrexate, minocycline) significantly improved radiological progression, swollen joint counts, and quality of life scores at 12 to 60 months compared with delayed treatment. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">Antimalarials</head><p n="p29.51"><s n="s1.3;p29.51">One systematic review has found that hydroxychloroquine versus placebo reduces disease activity and joint inflammation in people with rheumatoid arthritis. </s><s n="s2.3;p29.51">We found insufficient evidence about effects on functional status. </s><s n="s3.3;p29.51">One systematic review found no consistent difference in effectiveness between antimalarials and other disease modifying antirheumatic drugs. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">Methotrexate</head><p n="p30.51"><s n="s1.2;p30.51">One systematic review has found that methotrexate is more effective than placebo in reducing joint inflammation and radiological progression, and in improving functional status in people with rheumatoid arthritis. </s><s n="s2.2;p30.51">One systematic review and subsequent RCTs have found no consistent differences in efficacy between methotrexate versus leflunomide, parenteral gold, or etanercept. </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="bold">Commentary</hi> A commentary on issues of epidemiology, psycho-social, health care delivery, ethical issues or disability relevant to the patient and/or problem</head><p n="p31.51"><s n="s1.2;p31.51">Rheumatoid arthritis may be defined as a "Chronic autoimmune inflammatory disease resulting in joint destruction. </s><s n="s2.2;p31.51">Immune complexes are formed in joints and excite an inflammatory response, termed complex mediated hypersensitivity." </s></p><p n="p32.51"><s n="s1.3;p32.51">Rheumatoid arthritis affects approximately 1% of the UK population; the commonest age of onset is between 25-55 years. </s><s n="s2.3;p32.51">The ratio of females: males is 2.5:1. </s><s n="s3.3;p32.51">Clinical manifestations may be classified as articular and extra-articular: </s></p><div2><head rend="underlined">Extra-articular</head><p n="p33.51"><s n="s1.8;p33.51">RA commonly manifests itself in the respiratory, haematological, neurological, lymphoreticular, ocular, and cardiovascular systems. </s><s n="s2.8;p33.51">Common respiratory symptoms include pleurisy, pleural effusion, and pleural fibrosis. </s><s n="s3.8;p33.51">Haematologically, RA may present with marrow depression due to folate deficiency, anaemia of chronic disease or hyperviscosity. </s><s n="s4.8;p33.51">Lymphadenopathy occurs in 50% of patients, along with Felty's syndrome (splenomegaly with neutropaenia, anaemia and thrombocytopenia). </s><s n="s5.8;p33.51">Common ocular presentations include keratoconjunctivitis sicca, episcleritis, and iritis. </s><s n="s6.8;p33.51">The sequalae of RA on the cardiovascular system may include pericarditis, pericardial effusion, and myocarditis. </s><s n="s7.8;p33.51">Cardiac nodules may form causing valvular heart disease, and conduction defects. </s><s n="s8.8;p33.51">Finally, there are also many systemic presentations of RA. These include oedema, vasculitis, osteoporosis and AA amyloidosis. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">Articular </head><p n="p34.51"><s n="s1.4;p34.51">Joints usually become involved later in the disease progression. </s><s n="s2.4;p34.51">Monoarticular, oligoarticular, and symmetrical polyarticular presentation may occur. </s><s n="s3.4;p34.51">Often the disease begins in the proximal finger joints and wrists and later spreads to the elbows, shoulders, knees, ankles and feet. </s><s n="s4.4;p34.51">Characteristic deformities occur and include: </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">Hands</head><p n="p35.51"><s n="s1.4;p35.51">Ulnar deviation of the fingers due to subluxation at the metacarpophalangeal joints. </s><s n="s2.4;p35.51">A 'swan neck deformity' is loss of finger function due to hyperextension of the PIP joints with fixed flexion of the DIP joints. </s><s n="s3.4;p35.51">A 'boutonniere' deformity is fixed flexion of the PIP joints with hyperextension of the DIP joints. </s><s n="s4.4;p35.51">A 'Z-shaped' deformity of the thumb often also accompanies the above. </s></p><p n="p36.51"><s n="s1.2;p36.51">'Dropped finger' is chronic inflammation of the extensor tendon sheaths leads to damage to, and severance of the extensor tendon(s) commonly at the wrist. </s><s n="s2.2;p36.51">This results in a finger that which cannot be actively extended. </s></p><p n="p37.51"><s n="s1.2;p37.51">Common symptoms of RA include pain, swelling and stiffness of affected joints which is often worse in the mornings and lasts for more than one hour, and joint deformity. </s><s n="s2.2;p37.51">Systemic symptoms include fever, fatigue, generalised malaise, and depression. </s></p><p n="p38.51"><s n="s1.2;p38.51">RA is less common in rural African populations, and more common in Native American populations. </s><s n="s2.2;p38.51">The reasons for this are currently unclear. </s></p><p n="p39.51"><s n="s1.3;p39.51">The aetiology of rheumatoid arthritis is multifactorial, however 60% of a population's predisposition to RA is genetically determined, with the HLA region of Ch. </s><s n="s2.3;p39.51">6 implicated. </s><s n="s3.3;p39.51">The environmental contribution is not clear although various infective agents have been proposed. </s></p><p n="p40.51"><s n="s1.5;p40.51">Pathogenically, RA is an autoimmune disease which is probably initiated by T lymphocytes. </s><s n="s2.5;p40.51">One of the first histological signs of RA is the infiltration of the synovium with T cells. </s><s n="s3.5;p40.51">The T cells then become organised into aggregates, causing microvascular disorganisation and damage to the synovial membrane. </s><s n="s4.5;p40.51">Locally stimulated T cells secrete the cytokines TNF-alpha and IL-1, which in turn cause synovium to become locally invasive (pannus), angiogenesis, and the formation of high endothelial venules (HEVs). </s><s n="s5.5;p40.51">HEVs accelerate cell infiltration secretion of inflammatory mediators and metalloproteinases by synoviocytes. </s></p><p n="p41.51"><s n="s1.1;p41.51">Management of RA may be subdivided into medical, physiotherapy, and surgical: </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">Medical</head><p n="p42.51"><s n="s1.5;p42.51">The mainstay of medical management consists of early introduction of a disease-modifying anti-rheumatic drug (DMARD). </s><s n="s2.5;p42.51">The most commonly prescribed first-line DMARD is low-dose weekly methotrexate. </s><s n="s3.5;p42.51">It has proven efficacy in slowing disease progression, is well tolerated, and has few complications when combined with folate. </s><s n="s4.5;p42.51">Analgesics, NSAIDS and steroids may be used for symptomatic relief while the DMARD is acting. </s><s n="s5.5;p42.51">Combination DMARD therapy is required when monotherapy with methotrexate or sulfasalazine is not effective. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">Physiotherapy</head><p n="p43.51"><s n="s1.4;p43.51">Inflamed joints must be rested. </s><s n="s2.4;p43.51">This is best achieved by splintage. </s><s n="s3.4;p43.51">Night-time splints can be used at any stage of the disease when required. </s><s n="s4.4;p43.51">Inflamed joints should also be put through a range of passive movements each day, and as inflammation subsides active exercise should be encouraged. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">Surgical</head><p n="p44.51"><s n="s1.2;p44.51">There are now a range of surgical interventions in RA when conservative and medical management is no longer successful. </s><s n="s2.2;p44.51">Common interventions include: </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p45.51"><s n="s1.1;p45.51">1) Tendon repair or transfer to prevent progressive deformity secondary to tendon rupture and joint instability. </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p46.51"><s n="s1.1;p46.51">2) Reconstructive surgery for advanced joint destruction, instability and deformity. </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p47.51"><s n="s1.1;p47.51">3) Synovectomy. </s></p><p n="p48.51"><s n="s1.1;p48.51">Arthrodesis, osteotomy, joint replacement and excision arthroplasty are also used. </s></p><p n="p49.51"><s n="s1.4;p49.51">The prognosis of is variable as most patients have relapses and remissions. </s><s n="s2.4;p49.51">After a 10 year period about 25% of patients have complete remission. </s><s n="s3.4;p49.51">About 40% of patients have moderate impairment. </s><s n="s4.4;p49.51">The remainder of patients will have either severe impairment (25%) or will be crippled by their disease (10%). </s></p><p n="p50.51"><s n="s1.2;p50.51">Overall, life expectancy is shortened, with a roughly two-fold increase in mortality over that expected for comparable cohorts. </s><s n="s2.2;p50.51">Some of the increased mortality is caused by gastrointestinal bleeding related to long-term use of aspirin, by infections potentiated through chronic use of steroids, and by the development of reactive amyloidosis, particularly in those with protracted severe disease. </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="bold">Impact on your learning</hi> Describe what you have learnt from this case</head><p n="p51.51"><s n="s1.1;p51.51">The bio psychosocial burden of chronic illness, common presentations of RA, common comorbidities associated with RA. </s></p></div1></body><back/></text></TEI.2>
