<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_0114f" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Portfolio Case No. 34</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">proforma
deleted: page numbers
</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">4</p><p n="date">2005-01</p><p n="module title">Other Rotations</p><p n="module code">unknown</p><p n="genre family">Case study</p><p n="discipline">Medicine</p><p n="disciplinary group">LS</p><p n="grade">D</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">1844</p><p n="number of s-units">108</p><p n="number of p">50</p><p n="number of tables">0</p><p n="number of figures">0</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">8</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">7</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">17.1</p><p n="average s-units per p">2.2</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">m</p><p n="year of birth">1979</p><p n="first language">English</p><p n="education">UKA</p><p n="course">Medicine Phase II</p><p n="student ID">0114</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><docTitle><titlePart><hi rend="bold">PORTFOLIO CASE No:</hi> 34</titlePart></docTitle><titlePart>Patient Initials Hospital Number Age Gender<name type="other"/> Keep separate list 57 Male</titlePart><titlePart>Portfolio Case presentation number: 10.5 (sensory or motor loss) Phase 2 course document objective(s): 10.20,10.23, 10.25.</titlePart></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="bold">Referral information</hi> Source of referral and a summary of key information</head><p n="p1.50"><s n="s1.1;p1.50">Routinely admitted on <name type="date"/> for operation on right sided neck lump. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="bold">History</hi> All <hi rend="bold italic">relevant</hi> information gathered from the patient about the presenting illness, co-existing problems, and current treatment, significant past medical history and the social and family background. The patient's view of the nature of the problem and their expectations for treatment. </head><p n="p2.50"><s n="s1.8;p2.50">Mr <name type="other"/> had first noticed a right sided, unilateral neck lump approximately 10 years ago. </s><s n="s2.8;p2.50">Whilst on a diving holiday in Mexico 5 years ago, he went scuba diving and experienced sudden and severe earache in his right ear. </s><s n="s3.8;p2.50">He added the pain was worst over the angle of his right jaw, and was very sharp. </s><s n="s4.8;p2.50">He graded the severity as 7/10, and said that despite surfacing, it lasted for several hours after. </s><s n="s5.8;p2.50">He did not feel anything else brought his earache on, and ascent to surface eventually relieved it. </s><s n="s6.8;p2.50">He tried no analgesia. </s><s n="s7.8;p2.50">He felt that there was a definite ache on his return flight home. </s><s n="s8.8;p2.50">Over the succeeding 5 years, Mr <name type="other"/> was not concerned about it, but he recently felt it had grown and was now "quite distinct", so went to his GP who arranged an appointment with an ENT consultant. </s></p><p n="p3.50"><s n="s1.5;p3.50">Mr <name type="other"/> reported no difficulty or pain on swallowing, change in appetite, weight loss, fever, dizziness, or dribbling from the angle of his mouth. </s><s n="s2.5;p3.50">He does not have a sore throat. </s><s n="s3.5;p3.50">He thought the lump did not move on swallowing. </s><s n="s4.5;p3.50">He has not experienced any loss of power in his muscles of facial expression. </s><s n="s5.5;p3.50">He is a former smoker with a 20 pack-year history, and drinks approximately 40 units a weekend. </s></p><p n="p4.50"><s n="s1.2;p4.50">Mr <name type="other"/> had an operation when he was younger to insert a drain into his right lacrimal punctum after he fell and superficially scarred his face. </s><s n="s2.2;p4.50">He is hypertensive, but otherwise his medical history is unremarkable. </s></p><p n="p5.50"><s n="s1.2;p5.50">On admission, he was prescribed atenolol 25mg od po. </s><s n="s2.2;p5.50">He has no food or drug allergies. </s></p><p n="p6.50"><s n="s1.2;p6.50">Mr <name type="other"/> works as a commercial property meter reader. </s><s n="s2.2;p6.50">He lives with his youngest daughter following the death of his wife to ovarian cancer. </s></p><p n="p7.50"><s n="s1.1;p7.50">A systems review was unremarkable. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="bold">Analysis of history</hi> The most likely single cause of the presentation, other possible causes and reasons for these choices. The findings to be looked for on physical examination to help decide the cause.</head><p n="p8.50"><s n="s1.2;p8.50">The history is of a unilateral, right sided neck lump that has been slowly growing for approximately 10 years. </s><s n="s2.2;p8.50">Common or serious causes of this description of a neck lump include: </s></p><list type="bulleted"><head>Superficial:</head><item rend="bold">Lipoma</item><item>Sebaceous cyst.</item><item>Dermoid cyst.</item></list><list type="bulleted"><head>Deep:</head><item><hi rend="bold">Salivary glands</hi>.</item><item><hi rend="bold">Branchial cyst</hi>.</item><item><hi rend="bold">Lymph node swelling</hi>.</item><item>Sternomastoid 'tumour'.</item></list><list type="bulleted"><head> Posterior triangle:</head><item>Subclavian artery aneurysm.</item><item>Cystic hygroma.</item></list><p n="p9.50"><s n="s1.1;p9.50">The most likely causes are emboldened. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="bold">Physical examination</hi> Highlight the findings most relevant to your clinical problem solving by underlining them</head><list type="simple"><head>General observations: well-built middle aged man. HR- 78, regular. RR- 15/min. BP- 145/85. O <hi rend="sub">2</hi> Sats.- 96% (room air).</head></list><p n="p10.50"><s n="s1.9;p10.50"><hi rend="bold">ENT</hi>- <hi rend="underlined">3X3 cm mass in right parotid area, deep below angle of mandible in anterior triangle.</hi> </s><s rend="underlined" n="s2.9;p10.50">Mobile, non-tender, non-pulsatile and firm. </s><s rend="underlined" n="s3.9;p10.50">Does not move with swallowing. </s><s n="s4.9;p10.50"><hi rend="underlined">Not tethered to underling structures</hi>. </s><s n="s5.9;p10.50">Tympanic membranes intact. </s><s n="s6.9;p10.50">Oropharynx, and nasal cavity normal. </s><s n="s7.9;p10.50">The mouth was well hydrated, and not ulcerated. </s><s n="s8.9;p10.50">Nasendoscopy showed no obvious lesion in laryngopharynx. </s><s rend="underlined" n="s9.9;p10.50">There was no cervical lymphadenopathy, and no hepatosplenomegaly. </s></p><p n="p11.50"><s n="s1.1;p11.50">Fine Needle Aspiration was performed and sent for histological diagnosis. </s></p><p n="p12.50"><s rend="bold" n="s1.1;p12.50">Neurological </s></p><p n="p13.50"><s n="s1.1;p13.50">Cranial and peripheral nervous examination was normal. </s></p><p n="p14.50"><s n="s1.1;p14.50">All other systems examinations were normal. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="bold">Analysis of history and examination</hi> Reasons for your choice of the cause of the patient's problem(s) and any other cause that still needs to be considered at this stage</head><p n="p15.50"><s n="s1.2;p15.50">The history and examination is of a slowly growing 3X3 cm mass deep in the in right parotid area. </s><s n="s2.2;p15.50">This makes the most likely cause of the neck lump to be: </s></p><list type="ordered"><item>Parotid gland lesion (benign or malignant).</item><item>Lymph gland swelling.</item><item>Branchial cyst.</item><item>Lipoma.</item></list></div1><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="bold">Formulation of the patient's problem(s)</hi> Encapsulate this in physical, psychological and social terms (the triple diagnosis)</head><p n="p16.50"><s n="s1.3;p16.50">Physically, Mr <name type="other"/> is in good health excepting the neck lump and his weekend binge drinking of alcohol. </s><s n="s2.3;p16.50">Psychologically, he is concerned about the fears and stigma associated with cancer following the death of his wife, and is concerned about any permanent side effects of the surgery. </s><s n="s3.3;p16.50">Socially, he has had to take time off work, and may be temporarily reliant on his daughter's help for the next few days after discharge. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="bold">Management</hi> Use the framework of RAPRIOP to structure your proposed management. Refer to the guidelines to the writing of portfolio cases for the details of the issues to be addressed under each heading.</head><div2><head rend="underlined">Investigations</head><list type="bulleted"><head>Blood results- </head><item>Normal- U+Es, potassium, sodium, creatinine. RBCs, MCV, Lymphocytes, Basophils, Haematocrit.</item><item>Abnormal- WBCs (3.89 X 10 <hi rend="sup">9</hi>/l (↓)), Neutrophils (1.98 X 10 <hi rend="sup">9</hi>/l (↓)), Eosinophils ( 0.03 X 10 <hi rend="sup">9</hi>/l (↓)).</item></list><p n="p17.50"><s n="s1.2;p17.50">The histology report returned the diagnosis of pleomorphic adenoma, meaning few other investigations were necessary. </s><s n="s2.2;p17.50">Other tests that may have been considered include: </s></p><list type="bulleted"><item>Bloods- ESR, Paul-Bunnell test (glandular fever), Toxoplasma screen, Mantoux test, viral titres (for cervical lymphadenopathy).</item><item>Imaging- USS (distinguish between solid/cystic swellings), CT (useful for almost any mass, especially carotid body tumours) Floor of mouth X ray (Submandibular duct calculi), Sialography (contrast study to determine possible cause and site of lesion).</item></list></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">Reassurance and explanation</head><p n="p18.50"><s n="s1.2;p18.50">"We have received back the report on the cellular basis of your neck lump, and can confirm that it is a benign growth called a pleomorphic adenoma. </s><s n="s2.2;p18.50">The recommended treatment is removal of the mass. </s></p><p n="p19.50"><s n="s1.4;p19.50">All surgery is not without risks, and the major risk in this operation is damage to a nerved called the facial nerve, which is responsible for controlling the muscles of facial expression on the right side of your face. </s><s n="s2.4;p19.50">It is also involved in allowing you to purse your lips together and close your eyes tightly. </s><s n="s3.4;p19.50">There is an approximate risk of ≈ 1% that this nerve will be permanently damaged, resulting in the problems described above. </s><s n="s4.4;p19.50">It is also probable that there will be a bruising and stretching of the nerve, which may result in temporary problems with this nerve." </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">Prescription/medical intervention</head><p n="p20.50"><s n="s1.2;p20.50">A superficial right parotidectomy was performed on <name type="date"/>05. </s><s n="s2.2;p20.50">Mr <name type="other"/> was seen 3/7 post-operatively, the results discussed in 'outcome'. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">Observation </head><p n="p21.50"><s n="s1.1;p21.50">Obseved on the ward for 4/7 post-operatively. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">Referral and team working</head><p n="p22.50"><s n="s1.1;p22.50">Mr <name type="other"/>'s care has so far involved his family doctor, the ENT team at the <name type="other"/> hospital, and physiotherapists and dieticians. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">Advice and Prevention</head><p n="p23.50"><s n="s1.1;p23.50">Not applicable. </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="bold">Outcome</hi> A description of the progress of the patient as far as possible. This should include consideration of further issues to be resolved. Where appropriate you should contact by telephone patients who have been discharged home.</head><p n="p24.50"><s n="s1.1;p24.50">Mr <name type="other"/> was seen 3/7 post-operatively, and his cranial nerve findings were: </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p25.50"><s n="s1.1;p25.50">I,II, III, IV, VI- Normal. </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p26.50"><s n="s1.2;p26.50">V- Reduced in 1 <hi rend="sup">st</hi> and 2 <hi rend="sup">nd</hi> divisions to discriminative touch. </s><s n="s2.2;p26.50">No parathesiae/numbness. </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p27.50"><s n="s1.3;p27.50">VII- Could not completely close right eye. </s><s n="s2.3;p27.50">Unable to blow cheeks out uniformly, and could only draw lip up to smile on left. </s><s n="s3.3;p27.50">Could only bare teeth on left side. </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p28.50"><s n="s1.1;p28.50">VIII, IX,X,XI,XII- Normal. </s></p><p n="p29.50"><s n="s1.4;p29.50">Mr <name type="other"/> now has a 15 cm right sided neck scar passing from below the right pinna passing medially towards thyroid cartilage. </s><s n="s2.4;p29.50">There was no cervical lymphadenopathy. </s><s n="s3.4;p29.50">There was an evident drooping from the right side of the mouth, with associated drooling. </s><s n="s4.4;p29.50">The mouth was well hydrated and not ulcerated. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="bold">Evidence based care and issues for research</hi> A brief consideration of the evidence base required for the diagnosis and management of the patient's problem(s)</head><p n="p30.50"><s n="s1.1;p30.50">A literature search of both the Cochrane Collaboration and Evidence Based Medicine Online was unhelpful [1,2]. </s></p><p n="p31.50"><s n="s1.2;p31.50">It appears that there is no evidenced based medicine comparing interventions in pleomorphic adenoma; excision of the tumour via parotidectomy is the intervention of choice [3]. </s><s n="s2.2;p31.50">Enucleation of the tumour is inadequate [4, 5]. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="bold">Commentary</hi> A commentary on issues of epidemiology, psycho-social, health care delivery, ethical issues or disability relevant to the patient and/or problem</head><p n="p32.50"><s n="s1.3;p32.50">Tumours of the salivary gland (SGT) are rather uncommon and represent 2-3% of head and neck neoplasms. </s><s n="s2.3;p32.50">The glands are divided into major and minor salivary glands. </s><s n="s3.3;p32.50">The major glands are: </s></p><list type="bulleted"><item>parotid</item><item>submandibular </item><item>sublingual. </item></list><p n="p33.50"><s n="s1.3;p33.50">The minor glands are dispersed throughout the upper aerodigestive submucosa (ie, palate, lip, pharynx, nasopharynx, larynx, parapharyngeal space) [3]. </s><s n="s2.3;p33.50">Accurate histopathological diagnosis is essential to effectively manage SGT. Generally, the larger glands have the most tumours, and also the highest percentage of benign tumours. </s><s n="s3.3;p33.50">Approximately 85% of SGT are pleomorhic adenomas (benign), Warthin tumours (adenolymphoma) make up a further 10% of SGTs. </s></p><div2><head rend="underlined">Pleomorphic adenomas (PA)</head><p n="p34.50"><s n="s1.5;p34.50">Pleomorphic adenomas are benign tumours of mixed cellular origin. </s><s n="s2.5;p34.50">They are comprised of varying degrees of epithelial and connective tissue. </s><s n="s3.5;p34.50">They are round, smooth, and freely mobile. </s><s n="s4.5;p34.50">They grow slowly, although eventually may become very large if left untreated. </s><s n="s5.5;p34.50">PAs are the commonest cause of a lump in the parotid or submandibular glands, and are a common cause of neck lumps overall. </s></p><p n="p35.50"><s n="s1.2;p35.50">Both sexes are affected, although it is believed women slightly more than men. </s><s n="s2.2;p35.50">It most commonly presents in middle age, but cases from 12 onwards have been reported. </s></p><p n="p36.50"><s n="s1.2;p36.50">Patients most frequently present with an asymptomatic, slowly growing neck lump that is painless. </s><s n="s2.2;p36.50">Any facial nerve involvement or cardinal symptoms of metastatic disease (weight loss, anorexia, fever) implies more serious pathology. </s></p><p n="p37.50"><s n="s1.5;p37.50">The aetiology of pleomorphic adenoma is not understood, and there appear to be no common precipitating factors. </s><s n="s2.5;p37.50">Columns and islands of neoplastic epithelial cells are surrounded by myoepithelial cells and separated by a myxomatous connective tissue stroma, often containing areas resembling immature cartilage. </s><s n="s3.5;p37.50">This led early pathologists to believe that the tumour contained neoplastic tissue of both epithelial and connective tissue origin, resulting in the misleading name of mixed salivary tumour. </s><s n="s4.5;p37.50">Some have no myxomatous tissue and are described as monomorphic variants [6]. </s><s n="s5.5;p37.50">Pathology occurs when the benign mass presses on nearby structures, such as blood vessels or lymph tissue. </s></p><p n="p38.50"><s n="s1.1;p38.50">Investigations should include: </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p39.50"><s n="s1.1;p39.50"><hi rend="bold">FBC, WCC</hi>- The WCC investigate for any evidence of leukocytosis and shift that might indicate evidence of an infectious process or lymphoproliferative disease. </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p40.50"><s n="s1.2;p40.50"><hi rend="bold">Imaging Studies</hi>- MRI is the most sensitive test for establishing the borders of soft tissue tumour extension. </s><s n="s2.2;p40.50">CT scan and MRI findings, in most circumstances, cannot be used to reliably differentiate benign from malignant disease. </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p41.50"><s n="s1.4;p41.50"><hi rend="bold">Diagnostic procedures</hi>- With an experienced cytologist, Fine Needle Aspiration (FNA) and Biopsy are invaluable in diagnosis of pleomorphic adenoma. </s><s n="s2.4;p41.50">It can differentiate between benign and malignant lesions. </s><s n="s3.4;p41.50">FNA findings provide evidence for preoperative diagnosis that is 70-80% accurate. </s><s n="s4.4;p41.50">The final pathologic diagnosis is always established based on findings from surgical excision. </s></p><p n="p42.50"><s n="s1.2;p42.50">Management is now accepted to be superficial parotidectomy, as it enables complete excisiob with a margin. </s><s n="s2.2;p42.50">Enucleation of the mass is no longer recommended as 'ameboid processes' may be left, allowing subsequent regrowth. </s></p><p n="p43.50"><s n="s1.1;p43.50">Excepting the small operative risk of facial nerve paralysis, prognosis is excellent, with low recurrence rates. </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="bold">Impact on your learning</hi> Describe what you have learnt from this case</head><p n="p44.50"><s n="s1.1;p44.50">History and examination of a neck lump, Common causes of neck lumps, operative complications near the facial nerve. </s></p><p n="p45.50"><s n="s1.1;p45.50"><seg type="URL" n="http://www.cochrane.de/cc_bin/mno?q=pleomorphic+adenoma&amp;m=all&amp;ul=http%3A%2F%2Fwww.cochrane.org"/> </s></p><p n="p46.50"><s n="s1.1;p46.50"><seg type="URL" n="http://ebm.bmjjournals.com/"/> </s></p><p n="p47.50"><s n="s1.1;p47.50"><seg type="URL" n="http://www.emedicine.com/med/topic2789.htm"/> </s></p><p n="p48.50"><s n="s1.1;p48.50"><seg type="URL" n="http://www.gpnotebook.co.uk/simplepage.cfm?ID=-1791688692&amp;linkID=26644&amp;cook=yes"/> </s></p><p n="p49.50"><s n="s1.1;p49.50">Personal discussion with Mr <name type="other"/>, ENT Surgeon, <name type="other"/> Hospital. </s></p><p n="p50.50"><s n="s1.1;p50.50"><seg type="URL" n="http://www.gpnotebook.co.uk/simplepage.cfm?ID=1738145815&amp;linkID=26642&amp;cook=yes"/> </s></p></div1></body><back/></text></TEI.2>
