<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_0114c" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Portfolio Case No. 29</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">Language used in quote: <foreign id="English">English</foreign></note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">proforma
deleted: page numbers
</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">4</p><p n="date">2004-09</p><p n="module title">Child Health Rotation</p><p n="module code">unknown</p><p n="genre family">Case study</p><p n="discipline">Medicine</p><p n="disciplinary group">LS</p><p n="grade">D</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">1341</p><p n="number of s-units">57</p><p n="number of p">25</p><p n="number of tables">0</p><p n="number of figures">0</p><p n="number of block quotes">1</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">1</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">0</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">23.5</p><p n="average s-units per p">2.3</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">m</p><p n="year of birth">1979</p><p n="first language">English</p><p n="education">UKA</p><p n="course">Medicine Phase II</p><p n="student ID">0114</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><docTitle><titlePart><hi rend="bold">PORTFOLIO CASE No:</hi> 29</titlePart></docTitle><titlePart>Patient Initials Hospital Number Age Gender Miss <name type="other"/> Keep separate list Six weeks Female</titlePart><titlePart>Portfolio Case presentation number: Social portfolio. Phase 2 course document objective(s): Social portfolio.</titlePart></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="bold">Referral information</hi> Source of referral and a summary of key information</head><p n="p1.25"><s n="s1.1;p1.25">Self-referral to A+E for bruising 2 to accident at home. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="bold">History</hi> All <hi rend="bold italic">relevant</hi> information gathered from the patient about the presenting illness, co-existing problems, and current treatment, significant past medical history and the social and family background. The patient's view of the nature of the problem and their expectations for treatment. </head><p n="p2.25"><s n="s1.3;p2.25">Miss <name type="other"/> stated she was at home on the morning of 20 <hi rend="sup">th</hi> Sept. this year preparing both her six-week old daughter (<name type="other"/>), and her 3-year old boy (<name type="other"/>) to go shopping. <name type="other"/> was playing with a skateboard in the hallway, and <name type="other"/> was strapped into a pushchair. </s><s n="s2.3;p2.25">She left both children temporarily as she went to the toilet. </s><s n="s3.3;p2.25">When she returned she found <name type="other"/> sprawled across the hallway floor, in some distress with the skateboard nearby. </s></p><p n="p3.25"><s n="s1.4;p3.25"><name type="other"/> was still strapped into the pushchair, which had fallen backwards onto the vinyl-covered floor of the hall. </s><s n="s2.4;p3.25">She was screaming, and had a minor graze over her right eye. <name type="other"/> was sprawled over the floor, and the skateboard was nearby. </s><s n="s3.4;p3.25">Later, <name type="other"/> explained that he had skateboarded along the hallway, lost balance and grabbed onto the handles of <name type="other"/>'s pushchair. </s><s n="s4.4;p3.25">The pushchair fell backwards and <name type="other"/> fell with it, hitting her head on the floor. </s></p><p n="p4.25"><s n="s1.3;p4.25">Miss <name type="other"/> said there was no loss of consciousness, and <name type="other"/> was not bleeding from the graze. </s><s n="s2.3;p4.25">She phoned her partner's mother, who suggested she phone the Health visitor. </s><s n="s3.3;p4.25">The Health visitor was called, and recommended that <name type="other"/> attend A+E. <name type="other"/> arrived at A+E four hours later. </s></p><p n="p5.25"><s n="s1.1;p5.25"><name type="other"/> was seen by the A+E SHO, who referred <name type="other"/> to the paediatricians. </s></p><p n="p6.25"><s n="s1.2;p6.25"><name type="other"/>'s past medical history is unremarkable, excepting an oral Candida infection post-natally. </s><s n="s2.2;p6.25">Miss <name type="other"/> said she had suffered from <hi rend="italic">Candida</hi> infections throughout her pregnancy. <name type="other"/> lives at home with her mother, half brother <name type="other"/>, and his father who is a paint sprayer. </s></p><p n="p7.25"><s n="s1.2;p7.25">She has not had all her relevant immunisations due to difficulties attending the surgery. </s><s n="s2.2;p7.25">She is not on any medications, or has any allergies. </s></p><p n="p8.25"><s n="s1.4;p8.25">Miss <name type="other"/> described a normal pregnancy, and had a normal vaginal delivery at term. </s><s n="s2.4;p8.25">Neonatal period was unremarkable. </s><s n="s3.4;p8.25">Developmentally, all appropriate milestones have been achieved. </s><s n="s4.4;p8.25">Systems review was unremarkable. </s></p><div2><head rend="underlined">Social Background</head><p n="p9.25"><s n="s1.12;p9.25"><name type="other"/>'s mother is a 19year-old partly trained hairdresser. </s><s n="s2.12;p9.25">She has had three children. </s><s n="s3.12;p9.25">They live in cramped, rented accommodation on the outskirts of <name type="other"/>. <name type="other"/> is the eldest, aged three years. </s><s n="s4.12;p9.25">He is currently on the Child Protection Register after being physically abused by his father. <name type="other"/>'s father is now in prison for unrelated assault charges, and Miss <name type="other"/> has a strained relationship with him. </s><s n="s5.12;p9.25">It was unclear when he is eligible to be released. </s><s n="s6.12;p9.25">Miss <name type="other"/> had a second child with this partner, as she "felt it'd bring us closer together". <name type="other"/> was born a year after <name type="other"/>. <name type="other"/> had an uneventful pregnancy and labour, and was delivered vaginally at term. </s><s n="s7.12;p9.25">Miss <name type="other"/> added <name type="other"/> was always a small child, and never seemed to "catch his breath easily". </s><s n="s8.12;p9.25">Unexpectedly, <name type="other"/> was found dead in his cot one morning. </s><s n="s9.12;p9.25">He was 10 months old. </s><s n="s10.12;p9.25">Briefly describing the events around this difficult period, Miss <name type="other"/> said she was perennially confused and unable to concentrate, and just felt "my head was spinning" all the time. <name type="other"/>'s unexpected death did little for Miss <name type="other"/>'s relationship. </s><s n="s11.12;p9.25">Elaborating further, Miss <name type="other"/> said "That when he started drinking, and began hitting me." </s><s n="s12.12;p9.25">Miss <name type="other"/> eventually left him, and he was imprisoned on unrelated assault charges. </s></p><p n="p10.25"><s n="s1.2;p10.25">Miss <name type="other"/> found a new partner, and quickly fell pregnant with <name type="other"/>. <name type="other"/>'s father works full-time as a trainee paint-sprayer at a local car factory. </s><s n="s2.2;p10.25">He feels he doesn't spend as much time with <name type="other"/> as he would like, but has to work all available overtime. </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="bold">Physical examination</hi> Highlight the findings most relevant to your clinical problem solving by underlining them</head><p n="p11.25"><s n="s1.3;p11.25">Unremarkable. </s><s n="s2.3;p11.25">There was a minor graze over <name type="other"/>'s right eye that was not evident by the time of discharge. <name type="other"/> was on the 75 <hi rend="sup">th</hi> centile for weight and length, and on the 50 <hi rend="sup">th</hi> centile for head circumference. </s><s n="s3.3;p11.25">Otherwise, <name type="other"/> is a happy, active young baby making appropriate social contact with her mother, and fully interacting with the environment. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="bold">Formulation of the patient's problem(s)</hi> Encapsulate this in physical, psychological and social terms (the triple diagnosis)</head><p n="p12.25"><s n="s1.3;p12.25"><name type="other"/>'s presentation is eminently suitable for examination using a biopsychosocial approach. </s><s n="s2.3;p12.25">Biologically, there is actually very little wrong with <name type="other"/>. </s><s n="s3.3;p12.25">She is at least average compared to her peers; she has not 'fallen off' any of her centiles regarding physical progress, and appears to be a happy and contented 6-week-old girl. </s></p><p n="p13.25"><s n="s1.2;p13.25">However, This apparent biomedical well-being disguises the considerable psychological stressors and social depravation the family is living in. </s><s n="s2.2;p13.25">The salient points are outlined below: </s></p><list type="ordered"><item>Domestic violence. </item><item>Personal grief and depression.</item><item>Social isolation.</item><item>Interpersonal difficulties with family members.</item><item>Financial poverty.</item><item>Difficult relationship with authority.</item></list></div1><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="bold">Management</hi> Use the framework of RAPRIOP to structure your proposed management. Refer to the guidelines to the writing of portfolio cases for the details of the issues to be addressed under each heading.</head><div2><head rend="underlined">Investigations</head><p n="p14.25"><s n="s1.1;p14.25">None performed. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">Prescription/medical intervention</head><p n="p15.25"><s n="s1.2;p15.25">No prescription. </s><s n="s2.2;p15.25">Miss <name type="other"/> was given advice regarding appropriate transport for infants, and put in contact with a social worker regarding relevant benefits for lone parents, and possible funding for more appropriate ambulatory equipment. </s></p><p n="p16.25"><s n="s1.1;p16.25">. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">Observation </head><p n="p17.25"><s n="s1.1;p17.25">Observed on ward for several hours. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">Referral and team working</head><p n="p18.25"><s n="s1.2;p18.25">Acutely, <name type="other"/>'s care involved the A+E team at <name type="other"/> Hospital, and the on-call paediatricians at <name type="other"/> Hospital. </s><s n="s2.2;p18.25">The on-call social worker was also consulted. </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="bold">Outcome</hi> A description of the progress of the patient as far as possible. This should include consideration of further issues to be resolved. Where appropriate you should contact by telephone patients who have been discharged home.</head><p n="p19.25"><s n="s1.1;p19.25">After being observed on the ward, <name type="other"/> was discharged uneventfully the same evening. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="bold">Evidence based care (EBC) and issues for research</hi> A brief consideration of the evidence base required for the diagnosis and management of the patient's problem(s)</head><p n="p20.25"><s n="s1.2;p20.25">There was little evidence based care regarding Non-Accidental Injuries to infants on the internet. </s><s n="s2.2;p20.25">However, some relevant EBC on domestic violence was found: </s></p><quote lang="English">What are the effects of interventions initiated by healthcare professionals, aimed at female victims of domestic violence? Individual, couple, or group counselling Two controlled trials and one comparative cohort study found no effect of counselling compared with no treatment on medical care utilisation rates, reported exposure to violence and threats of violence, or depression, state anxiety, and self esteem. One controlled trial found that grief resolution orientated counselling improved self-esteem and self-efficacy from baseline, whereas feminist orientated counselling did not. However, the study did not directly compare effects of interventions. Similarly, one controlled trial found that cognitive behaviour orientated therapy improved women's assertiveness and reduced exposure to abuse from baseline, whereas non-specific support did not. One RCT and one non-randomised controlled trial reported that gender specific or couple therapy reduced subsequent exposure to violence among couples from baseline, but found no significant differences between these two types of counselling [1]. Advocacy One RCT and one non-randomised controlled trial found that advocacy reduced reabuse compared with no treatment. The RCT also found an improvement in women's quality of life with advocacy compared with no treatment. One controlled trial in pregnant Hispanic women found no significant difference in rates of reabuse between combined counselling plus mentoring (similar to advocacy) and a resource card, but found that counselling plus mentoring slightly reduced rates of reabuse compared with unlimited counselling [2]. Shelters We found no reliable controlled trials. One cohort study found a reduced incidence of violence in the weeks after shelter stay for women choosing to use the shelter when they were also engaged in other types of help seeking behaviour compared with women not choosing to stay at the shelter. Women choosing to stay at the shelter who had not sought help elsewhere experienced an increase in violence [3]. Peer support groups We found no systematic reviews, RCTs, non-randomised controlled trials, or cohort studies of peer support groups in women experiencing domestic violence [4].</quote></div1><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="bold">Impact on your learning</hi> Describe what you have learnt from this case</head><p n="p21.25"><s n="s1.1;p21.25">The varied presentations of a possible non-accidental injury; the complex psychosocial arrangements affecting families in 'pockets of depravation' , family and peer pressure in bringing up children. </s></p><p n="p22.25"><s n="s1.1;p22.25">1. <seg type="URL" n="http://www.clinicalevidence.com/ceweb/conditions/woh/1013/1013_I1.jsp"/>. </s></p><p n="p23.25"><s n="s1.1;p23.25">2. <seg type="URL" n="http://www.clinicalevidence.com/ceweb/conditions/woh/1013/1013_I2.jsp"/> </s></p><p n="p24.25"><s n="s1.1;p24.25">3. <seg type="URL" n="http://www.clinicalevidence.com/ceweb/conditions/woh/1013/1013_I3.jsp"/>. </s></p><p n="p25.25"><s n="s1.1;p25.25">4. <seg type="URL" n="http://www.clinicalevidence.com/ceweb/conditions/woh/1013/1013_I4.jsp"/> </s></p></div1></body><back/></text></TEI.2>
