<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_0114h" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Portfolio Case No. 18</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">proforma
deleted: page numbers
</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">4</p><p n="date">2003-10</p><p n="module title">Other Rotations</p><p n="module code">unknown</p><p n="genre family">Case study</p><p n="discipline">Medicine</p><p n="disciplinary group">LS</p><p n="grade">D</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">2626</p><p n="number of s-units">141</p><p n="number of p">52</p><p n="number of tables">2</p><p n="number of figures">0</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">4</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">0</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">18.6</p><p n="average s-units per p">2.7</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">m</p><p n="year of birth">1979</p><p n="first language">English</p><p n="education">UKA</p><p n="course">Medicine Phase II</p><p n="student ID">0114</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><docTitle><titlePart><hi rend="bold">PORTFOLIO CASE No:</hi> 18</titlePart></docTitle><titlePart>Patient Initials Hospital Number Age Gender<name type="other"/> Keep separate list 59 Male</titlePart><titlePart>Portfolio Case presentation number: Phase 2 course document objective(s): </titlePart></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="bold">Referral information</hi> Source of referral and a summary of key information</head><p n="p1.52"><s n="s1.2;p1.52">Presented to A+E at the <name type="other"/><name type="other"/> Hospital, <name type="other"/>, on <name type="date"/> with bilateral pedal oedema. </s><s n="s2.2;p1.52">Delusional, and therefore referred and informally admitted to the <name type="other"/> Clinic, <name type="other"/>. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="bold">History</hi> All <hi rend="bold italic">relevant</hi> information gathered from the patient about the presenting illness, co-existing problems, and current treatment, significant past medical history and the social and family background. The patient's view of the nature of the problem and their expectations for treatment. </head><p n="p2.52"><s n="s1.2;p2.52">Mr <name type="other"/> is an unemployed single 59-year old who owns his own semi-detached house in <name type="other"/>. </s><s n="s2.2;p2.52">He is an unmarried Catholic. </s></p><p n="p3.52"><s n="s1.7;p3.52">When asked why he was currently in hospital, Mr <name type="other"/> said it was a "safe place for me." </s><s n="s2.7;p3.52">Mr <name type="other"/> stated that sunlight, laser beams, ionised particles, the internet and fibre optic communication were "making (his) life difficult". </s><s n="s3.7;p3.52">He described himself as feeling like James Bond in the film 'Goldfinger' in the scene were Auric Goldfinger ties James Bond to a steel slab and proceeds to try to burn him in two with a laser. </s><s n="s4.7;p3.52">Mr <name type="other"/> believed he had been admitted after "laser heart massage" on himself and demanded an explanation as to how this procedure worked. </s><s n="s5.7;p3.52">Mr <name type="other"/> said his father (who died of an M.I.) saw flashing lights as he was having his heart attack, and therefore lights unduly worry him. </s><s n="s6.7;p3.52">Mr <name type="other"/> was also worried about cars killing him, and especially concerned about the attitude of drivers in the road. </s><s n="s7.7;p3.52">There appeared to be no precipitating factors to this episode of delusions. </s></p><p n="p4.52"><s n="s1.4;p4.52">Mr <name type="other"/> also described gustatory, visual and several auditory hallucinations. </s><s n="s2.4;p4.52">He said he had tasted bromine in his tea, and for this reason went to the café over the road rather than drink the tea provided. </s><s n="s3.4;p4.52">He felt the bromine was added to decrease his sex drive. </s><s n="s4.4;p4.52">He also described intermittently seeing a "bloke with red eyes who looks like Frankie Lane", although could not elaborate any further on the significance of this. </s></p><p n="p5.52"><s n="s1.5;p5.52">Mr <name type="other"/> added he heard female voices that talked to him to "remove me from dangerous situations". </s><s n="s2.5;p5.52">They gave him instructions that he couldn't remember, and said he doesn't have to do what they say, but chose to obey them anyway. </s><s n="s3.5;p5.52">The voices "looked after" him, and he considered that he worked in partnership with them. </s><s n="s4.5;p5.52">They have been with him intermittently since 1977, and the only way he can make them go away is if he smokes. </s><s n="s5.5;p5.52">He also felt that the early songs of Cliff Richard directly told him to "cheer up, enjoy myself and get married." </s></p><p n="p6.52"><s n="s1.4;p6.52">Mr <name type="other"/> described thought insertion as he said "someone or something" suddenly tells him to pray and worship. </s><s n="s2.4;p6.52">This all started when he had his tonsils out and was given a "pill wrapped in strawberry jam" that christened him and intermittently controlled his thoughts. </s><s n="s3.4;p6.52">Mr <name type="other"/> he only owned the thoughts he manages to write down on paper, otherwise "they're lost forever (to space invaders)". </s><s n="s4.4;p6.52">He stopped writing his thoughts down when it "got out of hand" but could not elaborate on this. </s></p><p n="p7.52"><s n="s1.2;p7.52">When asked if he thought he controlled himself, Mr <name type="other"/> said he was. </s><s n="s2.2;p7.52">However, he elaborated on this by saying an external force was "telling me to go into the sun." </s></p><p n="p8.52"><s n="s1.5;p8.52">Mr <name type="other"/>'s biological symptoms include early morning wakening which has become "force of habit". </s><s n="s2.5;p8.52">He also cries when he feels he's "on an unlucky streak and has done something wrong." </s><s n="s3.5;p8.52">He also feels guilty irrationally, and feels blamed when "it's not your fault. </s><s n="s4.5;p8.52">A cloud follows me about." </s><s n="s5.5;p8.52">The major significant negatives are lack of 3 <hi rend="sup">rd</hi> person auditory hallucinations, echoed thoughts, and catatonic symptoms. </s></p><p n="p9.52"><s n="s1.5;p9.52">Mr <name type="other"/> first presented to psychiatric services in 1994 aged 47, complaining that he had been suffering from "his nerves", and had felt troubled for 17 years. </s><s n="s2.5;p9.52">It is unclear why Mr <name type="other"/> presented at this time and why he had remained able to function in the community for so long. </s><s n="s3.5;p9.52">However, at that time he lived with his mother and it is felt she exerted a strong controlling influence on him. </s><s n="s4.5;p9.52">Since then, Mr <name type="other"/> has been admitted under the care of his psychiatrist as an informal admission on 4 occasions, all for either delusions or hallucinations and has had 6 monthly OP appointments. </s><s n="s5.5;p9.52">In 1997, he had his driving licence revoked by the DVLA. His most recent admission, earlier in 2003 was because of a morbid association that when people say "goodbye" they are referring to his imminent death. </s></p><list type="simple"><head>Mr <name type="other"/>'s PMHx includes:</head><item>ENT- tonsillectomy, 1952.</item><item>CVS- 1998, DVT. 2003, Bilateral leg oedema 2º to diabetes.</item><item>Metabolic- 1999, Diabetes (Type II). </item></list><p n="p10.52"><s n="s1.7;p10.52">Mr <name type="other"/> described a normal birth and early childhood, although he stated he "couldn't keep my feet" and took up athletics to increase his overall health. </s><s n="s2.7;p10.52">He described occasional period of feeling faint, but attributed this to "malnutrition". <name type="other"/> said he "loved" school because of the pleasant teaching staff and friendly atmosphere. </s><s n="s3.7;p10.52">He did very well academically, obtaining 11 GCEs and 'A' levels in History and English. </s><s n="s4.7;p10.52">He then went to Nottingham Trent Polytechnic to read English, History and Law but dropped out after a year as he got "writer's block" in the exam. </s><s n="s5.7;p10.52">He then worked for <name type="other"/> Council for about twelve years before he started "struggling and was pensioned off". </s><s n="s6.7;p10.52">Socially, he was a keen advocate of the Boy Scout movement but he eventually also found this too much to cope with. </s><s n="s7.7;p10.52">He has never been married, and never had children. </s></p><p n="p11.52"><s n="s1.4;p11.52">Mr <name type="other"/>'s current hobbies include listening to music (folk, Gilbert and Sullivan), reading (geographical, adventure stories), and films. </s><s n="s2.4;p11.52">He claims to smoke 20 cigarettes/day and has a pack history of 20 p-y. </s><s n="s3.4;p11.52">He drinks occasionally. </s><s n="s4.4;p11.52">He has never tried any street drugs. </s></p><p n="p12.52"><s n="s1.7;p12.52"><name type="other"/>'s Mother died aged 74 in 1999. </s><s n="s2.7;p12.52">She was a housewife for most of her life, and lived with <name type="other"/> until her death. <name type="other"/> had a very close relationship with his mother, and cried for several months after her death. </s><s n="s3.7;p12.52">His father was a retired metallurgist who died aged 73 in 1992. </s><s n="s4.7;p12.52">He also had a good relationship with him. <name type="other"/>'s elder brother, <name type="other"/>, is a teacher in <name type="other"/>, and is now his recognised next of kin. <name type="other"/> described him as "a fellow monk who hears his confessions". </s><s n="s5.7;p12.52">He has a younger brother, <name type="other"/>, who is in the Navy. </s><s n="s6.7;p12.52">They also get along well. </s><s n="s7.7;p12.52">There is no history of psychiatric illness. </s></p><p n="p13.52"><s n="s1.1;p13.52">Mr <name type="other"/> is currently prescribed </s></p><list type="simple"><item>Lorazepam (a benzodiazepine anxiolytic, 1mg od), Procyclidine (Antimuscarinic 5mg BD), Haloperidol (Antipsychotic 10mg tds) Zopiclone (a hypnotic 7.5mg nocte) Ciprofibrate (antifibrinolytic, 100mg od) Metformin (oral anti-diabetic biguanide 500mg w/ meals) Amisulpride (antipsychotic 400mg bd) Escitalopram (SSRI, 10mg od) Gliclazide (Sulphonylurea 80mg w/ meals) and Risperidone depot (atypical antipsychotic 37.5 mg 2/52).</item></list><p n="p14.52"><s n="s1.1;p14.52">It was not possible to ascertain if Mr <name type="other"/> had a pre-morbid personality due to lack of insight and lack of other contributors. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Mental state examination </head><div2><head rend="underlined">Appearance</head><p n="p15.52"><s n="s1.3;p15.52">Mr <name type="other"/> is a 59-year-old overweight Caucasian male who appears age-appropriate. </s><s n="s2.3;p15.52">He looked slightly dishevelled and was wearing a t-shirt, trousers and shoes. </s><s n="s3.3;p15.52">He had no jewellery on. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">Behaviour</head><p n="p16.52"><s n="s1.5;p16.52">Mr <name type="other"/> was largely pleasant and cooperative throughout, except for the occasions when he thought we were recording him, and that we were from the FBI. At this point, he requested to terminate the interview for a cigarette, and returned later. </s><s n="s2.5;p16.52">Mr <name type="other"/>'s posture was normal, although he kept looking to the corners of the room and muttering to himself. </s><s n="s3.5;p16.52">He rocked on the chair slightly for the duration of the interview. </s><s n="s4.5;p16.52">Eye contact was reduced. </s><s n="s5.5;p16.52">A reasonable rapport was achieved, excepting the FBI incident. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">Speech</head><p n="p17.52"><s n="s1.3;p17.52">Rate and rhythm were reduced. </s><s n="s2.3;p17.52">Volume and tone were normal. </s><s n="s3.3;p17.52">Towards the end of the interview, the speech became increasingly slurred. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">Thought</head><p n="p18.52"><s n="s1.4;p18.52">Formal thought disorder was evident. </s><s n="s2.4;p18.52">Insertions and deletions were apparent. </s><s n="s3.4;p18.52">There was thought derailment, rambling, tangentality, loose associations, which occasionally deteriorated into word salad. </s><s n="s4.4;p18.52">Flight of ideas was also obvious. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">Mood</head><list type="simple"><item>Subjective - "fine"</item><item>Objective - euthymic.</item></list><p n="p19.52"><s n="s1.1;p19.52">Did complain of unreasonable guilt. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">Affect</head><p n="p20.52"><s n="s1.1;p20.52">Flattened. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">Perceptions</head><p n="p21.52"><s n="s1.2;p21.52">Hallucinations and illusions were evident. </s><s n="s2.2;p21.52">Described in 'History' above. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">Cognition</head><p n="p22.52"><s n="s1.1;p22.52">Not formally assessed due to time constraints. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">Biological features</head><p n="p23.52"><s n="s1.2;p23.52">Suffered from middle insomnia. </s><s n="s2.2;p23.52">No appetite or weight change. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">Insight</head><p n="p24.52"><s n="s1.3;p24.52">When asked, Mr <name type="other"/> stated that he had a mental illness, and was a paranoid psychotic. </s><s n="s2.3;p24.52">He did not know whether his illness was treatable, but was willing to take medication. </s><s n="s3.3;p24.52">He had no objections to being informally admitted. </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="bold">Physical examination</hi> Highlight the findings most relevant to your clinical problem solving by underlining them</head><p n="p25.52"><s n="s1.1;p25.52">Not performed on request of patient. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="bold">Analysis of history and examination</hi> Reasons for your choice of the cause of the patient's problem(s) and any other cause that still needs to be considered at this stage</head><div2><head rend="underlined bold">F20. Schizophrenia</head><p n="p26.52"><s n="s1.2;p26.52">Mr <name type="other"/> has several of the positive features of schizophrenia- Delusions, hallucinations, and disorganised thoughts. </s><s n="s2.2;p26.52">He also has several negative features, including- a flat affect and loss of directed behaviour and motivation. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined bold">F20.0 Schizophrenia (Paranoid)</head><p n="p27.52"><s n="s1.2;p27.52">As above, but Mr <name type="other"/>'s delusions/ hallucinations frequently have a paranoid flavour. </s><s n="s2.2;p27.52">No negative indications for this diagnosis. </s></p></div2><div2><head><hi rend="bold">Formulation of the patient's problem(s)</hi> Encapsulate this in physical, psychological and social terms (the triple diagnosis)</head><table id="BAWE_0114h-tab.001"><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p28.52"/></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="bold">Management</hi> Use the framework of RAPRIOP to structure your proposed management. Refer to the guidelines to the writing of portfolio cases for the details of the issues to be addressed under each heading.</head><div2><head rend="underlined">Immediate</head><p n="p29.52"><s n="s1.4;p29.52">Rule out organic and drug causes of confusion/delusions/illusions. </s><s n="s2.4;p29.52">Admit and establish if medication has been taken. </s><s n="s3.4;p29.52">Review medication and perform full physical examination. </s><s n="s4.4;p29.52">Treat leg oedema, and investigate complications of diabetes. </s></p><list type="simple"><head>Bloods - HBA1c, TFTs, LFTs, FBC.</head></list></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">Long-term</head><p n="p30.52"><s n="s1.5;p30.52">This is Mr <name type="other"/>'s 4 <hi rend="sup">th</hi> admittal after community-based care. </s><s n="s2.5;p30.52">Even with the highest levels of support from the Community Mental Health Team (CMHT), Mr <name type="other"/> has been unable to cope living on his own. </s><s n="s3.5;p30.52">He is afraid of his neighbours, and the children playing near his house. </s><s n="s4.5;p30.52">Ideally, he needs transferring to appropriate sheltered housing scheme. </s><s n="s5.5;p30.52">This was offered in Shrewsbury, but Mr <name type="other"/> wants to retain a sense of independence by living in Warwickshire. </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="bold">Outcome</hi> A description of the progress of the patient as far as possible. This should include consideration of further issues to be resolved. Where appropriate you should contact by telephone patients who have been discharged home.</head><p n="p31.52"><s n="s1.2;p31.52">Mr <name type="other"/> is still informally admitted to the <name type="other"/> Clinic. </s><s n="s2.2;p31.52">He is a lot happier, and feels much more secure than living in the community. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="bold">Evidence based care and issues for research</hi> A brief consideration of the evidence base required for the diagnosis and management of the patient's problem(s)</head><div2><head rend="underlined bold">Drugs</head><p n="p32.52"><s n="s1.2;p32.52">One systematic review has found that compared with placebo, chlorpromazine reduces the proportion of people who have no improvement, or marked/worse severity of illness at 6 months on a psychiatrist rated scale. </s><s n="s2.2;p32.52">The review found that chlorpromazine caused more adverse effects, such as sedation, acute dystonia, and parkinsonism than a placebo. </s></p><p n="p33.52"><s n="s1.1;p33.52">One systematic review has found that haloperidol increases the proportion of people with psychiatrist rated global improvement at 6 and 24 weeks compared with placebo, but is associated with acute dystonia, akathisia, and parkinsonism. </s></p><p n="p34.52"><s n="s1.1;p34.52">One systematic review has found that thioridazine improves global mental state over 3 - 12 months compared with placebo. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined bold">Psycho-educational and family interventions</head><p n="p35.52"><s n="s1.2;p35.52">Evidence for non-pharmacological treatment of schizophrenia is very limited. </s><s n="s2.2;p35.52">However one systematic review has found that psycho-education reduces relapse rates at 9 - 18 months compared with usual care. </s></p><p n="p36.52"><s n="s1.1;p36.52">One systematic review found that multiple session family interventions reduced relapse rates at 12 months compared with usual care, single session family interventions, or psycho-educational interventions. </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="bold">Commentary</hi> A commentary on issues of epidemiology, psycho-social, health care delivery, ethical issues or disability relevant to the patient and/or problem</head><p n="p37.52"><s n="s1.2;p37.52">Schizophrenia was first approximately described by Emil Kraepelin in 1899, and may currently be defined as "A mental disorder characterised by disintegration of the process of thought, contact with reality, and progressive loss of emotional responsiveness." </s><s n="s2.2;p37.52">It is commonly assumed that schizophrenia means 'split personality,' but the name actually refers to the splitting and disintegration of an individual's thinking and feeling processes, rather than having two personalities. </s></p><p n="p38.52"><s n="s1.1;p38.52">Considering the important positive and negative symptoms listed below makes the clinical diagnosis: </s></p><table id="BAWE_0114h-tab.002"><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p39.52"><s n="s1.2;p39.52">The prevalence of schizophrenia is moderately high, with figures ranging between 0.6-1.4%, and incidence of 11 per 100,000. </s><s n="s2.2;p39.52">Age of onset is usually between 15-30, with males presenting typically 5 years before females. </s></p><p n="p40.52"><s n="s1.2;p40.52">The disease is higher in Afro-Caribbean males, leading to a 'migrant' theory that schizophrenia is higher amongst individuals isolated from their original ethnic community. </s><s n="s2.2;p40.52">However, this argument is partially flawed, as levels of schizophrenia are lower amongst Asian women who have migrated. </s></p><p n="p41.52"><s n="s1.2;p41.52">The aetiology of schizophrenia is controversial. </s><s n="s2.2;p41.52">There are two main theories: </s></p><div2><head rend="underlined">Genetic</head><p n="p42.52"><s n="s1.2;p42.52">Family, twin and adoption studies have suggested that genetics play a major role in the transmission of schizophrenia. </s><s n="s2.2;p42.52">Irwing Gottesman compiled over 40 studies in order to work out the risks of developing schizophrenia of people with different familial relationships to the schizophrenic person. </s></p><p n="p43.52"><s n="s1.3;p43.52">Two classes of relatives have especially high risks of developing schizophrenia. </s><s n="s2.3;p43.52">These are the offspring of two schizophrenic parents and a monozygotic (MZ) co-twin of a schizophrenic. </s><s n="s3.3;p43.52">Apparently, people who share the greatest number of genes with the people who have schizophrenia, have an increased risk of developing schizophrenia themselves. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">Environmental</head><p n="p44.52"><s n="s1.5;p44.52">Environmental factors could influence the development of schizophrenia but adoption studies support the genetic theory of transmission. </s><s n="s2.5;p44.52">In 1994, a study looked at schizophrenia in the biological and adoptive relatives of schizophrenic adoptees, and compared this to a demographically matched group of control adoptees. </s><s n="s3.5;p44.52">In the sample of adoptees with chronic schizophrenia, the disorder was found exclusively in their biological relatives and not their adoptive relatives. </s><s n="s4.5;p44.52">The prevalence of the disorder was 10 times higher in the biological relatives of the schizophrenic adoptees than in the biological relatives of the control group. </s><s n="s5.5;p44.52">These studies make a clear case for the involvement of genetics in schizophrenia. </s></p><p n="p45.52"><s n="s1.2;p45.52">Gross histological brain changes have been identified in schizophrenia. </s><s n="s2.2;p45.52">These include increased lateral and third ventricular volume compared to controls, changes in glial cell populations and diminution in neuronal size in the anterior cingulate cortex, and also reductions in specific inhibitory neuronal populations. </s></p><p n="p46.52"><s n="s1.2;p46.52">Management of schizophrenia should encompass both psychosocial and pharmacological interventions. </s><s n="s2.2;p46.52">Psychosocial interventions include assessment and support; explanation and education; building concentration; reinforcement of reality and help with relationships. </s></p><p n="p47.52"><s n="s1.2;p47.52">Communication skills and treatment of non-psychotic symptoms such as anxiety and mood disturbance dealing with challenging behaviours should be addressed, structuring to the day should be encouraged, and attention should be paid to improving daily living skills. </s><s n="s2.2;p47.52">Families should also be involved with the process of managing schizophrenia, as high levels of criticism, hostility and over-involvement predispose to relapse. </s></p><p n="p48.52"><s n="s1.3;p48.52">Antipsychotic drugs relieve florid psychotic symptoms such as thought disorder, hallucinations, and delusions, and prevent relapse. </s><s n="s2.3;p48.52">Although they are usually less effective in apathetic withdrawn patients, they sometimes appear to have an activating influence. </s><s n="s3.3;p48.52">Patients with acute schizophrenia generally respond better than those with chronic symptoms. </s></p><p n="p49.52"><s n="s1.2;p49.52">They are considered to act by interfering with dopaminergic transmission in the brain by blocking dopamine D2 receptors, which may give rise to the extrapyramidal effects, and also to hyperprolactinaemia. </s><s n="s2.2;p49.52">Antipsychotic drugs may also affect cholinergic, alpha-adrenergic, histaminergic, and serotonergic receptors. </s></p><p n="p50.52"><s n="s1.3;p50.52">They are classified as either being <hi rend="italic">typical</hi> or <hi rend="italic">atypical</hi> depending on age and mode of action. </s><s n="s2.3;p50.52">They both seem to be of similar efficacy, but the atypicals have fewer extra-pyramidal side effects and are thought to be more effective on negative symptoms. </s><s n="s3.3;p50.52">Clozapine is used for schizophrenia when other antipsychotics are ineffective or not tolerated. </s></p><p n="p51.52"><s n="s1.3;p51.52">Most people with schizophrenia continue to suffer chronically or episodically throughout their lives. </s><s n="s2.3;p51.52">Even between bouts of active illness, lost opportunities for careers and relationships, stigma, residual symptoms, and medication side effects often plague those with the illness. </s><s n="s3.3;p51.52">One in 10 people with schizophrenia eventually commit suicide. </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="bold">Impact on your learning</hi> Describe what you have learnt from this case</head><p n="p52.52"><s n="s1.1;p52.52">Presentation, diagnosis and short and long-term management of schizophrenia. </s></p></div1></body><back/></text></TEI.2>
