<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_0116d" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>The Impact of Drama on High School Students' English Learning and Self-Confidence</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">The document has a title page which contains:
document title
title part</note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">Language used in quote: <foreign id="English">English</foreign></note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">4</p><p n="date">2005-04</p><p n="module title">Researching Drama in the Classroom</p><p n="module code">IE670</p><p n="genre family">Research report</p><p n="discipline">other</p><p n="disciplinary group">SS</p><p n="grade">D</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">4096</p><p n="number of s-units">164</p><p n="number of p">32</p><p n="number of tables">1</p><p n="number of figures">3</p><p n="number of block quotes">11</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">2</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">3</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">25.0</p><p n="average s-units per p">5.1</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">f</p><p n="year of birth">1971</p><p n="first language">Chinese unspecified</p><p n="education">OSA</p><p n="course">Drama and Theatre Education</p><p n="student ID">0116</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><titlePart>Name: <name type="student name"/> Student No.: <name type="student ID"/> Date: 30 April 2005 Grade: 77 (A)</titlePart><docTitle><titlePart rend="bold">The Impact of Drama on High School Students' English Learning and Self-Confidence</titlePart></docTitle><titlePart>Course: Researching Drama in the Classroom (IE670)</titlePart><titlePart>Tutor: <name type="tutor name"/></titlePart><figure id="BAWE_0116d-pic.001"/><titlePart>Name: <name type="student name"/> Student No.: <name type="student ID"/></titlePart><docTitle><titlePart><hi rend="bold">The Impact of Drama on High School Students'</hi> <hi rend="bold"> English Learning and Self-Confidence</hi></titlePart></docTitle><epigraph><p>I hear and I forget,</p><p>I listen and I remember,</p><p>I do and I understand.</p></epigraph></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Introduction</head><p n="p1.32"><s n="s1.9;p1.32">In 2003, the university I was working for was sponsored by the Ministry of Education in Taiwan to organize a five-day English summer camp. </s><s n="s2.9;p1.32">It aimed to help the suburban senior high students improve their English ability and bridge the knowledge gap between students in city and country. </s><s n="s3.9;p1.32">As an organizer and also instructor of the summer camp, I was aware that it was almost unlikely to make the participants progress significantly in terms of their English ability within such a limited time span of five days. </s><s n="s4.9;p1.32">Besides, coming from disadvantaged schools, these students were usually short of confidence and motivation in learning, which turned the whole task more challenging. Therefore, instead of focusing on the students' learning product, I wanted to put more emphasis on their learning process. </s><s n="s5.9;p1.32">What I was intended to do was to lower the participants' anxiety level, break down their defensive walls of inhibitions they set to protect their fragile language ego, and build up their confidence in using English. </s><s n="s6.9;p1.32">I set myself a goal of creating an encouraging and supportive learning atmosphere in the summer camp where the participants could use English for real communication, take a role of active learner, and feel dauntless with trial and error when using English. </s><s n="s7.9;p1.32">But the question was what teaching method and course design could turn them on to English. </s><s n="s8.9;p1.32">It seemed to me that the combination of drama and English teaching might be a practical solution. </s><s n="s9.9;p1.32">So this study sets out to develop an integrated English and drama course for the disadvantaged students and reports the findings of how educational drama methodology can be used to create a meaningful context for English communication, boost the students' self-confidence, promote social cooperation, and enhance learner autonomy. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Literature Review</head><p n="p2.32"><s n="s1.2;p2.32">The framework of the course design was based on the principles of cooperative learning, and the students' affective factors were also important considerations. </s><s n="s2.2;p2.32">In the following discussion, I am to provide a clear picture of the underlying rationale of this study and illuminate the benefits that drama can bring to the students' English learning. </s></p><div2><head rend="bold">Affective Factors vs. Foreign Language Learning</head><p n="p3.32"><s n="s1.6;p3.32">In the past two decades, research on the relationship between foreign language learning and affective domain has proliferated. </s><s n="s2.6;p3.32">One's cognitive development cannot be separated from his/her affectivity. </s><s n="s3.6;p3.32">According to Stern (1983), "the affective component contributes at least as much as and often more to language learning than the cognitive skills" (p. </s><s n="s4.6;p3.32">386). </s><s n="s5.6;p3.32">That is to say, there will be a serious flaw in any second language acquisition theory or teaching methodology if it is based only on cognitive considerations because it leaves out "the most fundamental side of human behavior" (Brown, 1987, p. 99). </s><s n="s6.6;p3.32">This fundamental side of human behavior can be unfolded with following classification: self-esteem, inhibition, making mistakes and anxiety. </s></p><div3><head rend="bold">Self-esteem and Self-confidence</head><p n="p4.32"><s n="s1.4;p4.32">Self-esteem is one of the pivotal predictors of achievement. </s><s n="s2.4;p4.32">Brown highlights the predictor, arguing, "no successful cognitive or affective activity can be carried out without some degree of self-esteem, self-confidence, knowledge of yourself, and belief in your own capabilities for that activity" (1987, p. 101). </s><s n="s3.4;p4.32">With accumulated self-confidence, one can bring all potentials into full play. </s><s n="s4.4;p4.32">Self-esteem can be nourished by teaching in which learners' self-assessment of their own learning is encouraged, both alone and with peers in cooperative learning groups (Kohonen, in Nunan, 1992, p. 15). </s></p></div3><div3><head rend="bold">Inhibition</head><p n="p5.32"><s n="s1.5;p5.32">People have an inclination to build "sets of defenses to protect the ego" (Brown, 1987, p. 103). </s><s n="s2.5;p5.32">This psychological inhibition usually causes hindrance to one's mastery of a foreign language. </s><s n="s3.5;p5.32">An experiment conducted by Guiora et al. in 1972 shows that there is a close relationship between ego boundaries and pronunciation ability in a second language. </s><s n="s4.5;p5.32">Learning a foreign language, as Brumfit has suggested, is "a question of overcoming psychological inhibitions and emotional problems" (1983, p. 85). </s><s n="s5.5;p5.32">In order to facilitate students' acquisition of a foreign language, a teacher should create a classroom in which the learners can lower their interpersonal ego barriers by engaging in unfettered and meaningful communication. </s></p></div3><div3><head rend="bold">Making Mistakes</head><p n="p6.32"><s n="s1.5;p6.32">It is believed that people learn to master a language by trial and error. </s><s n="s2.5;p6.32">Learners should be allowed to make errors so that they can develop their language ability for real communication. </s><s n="s3.5;p6.32">Linguistic errors, however, can deflate the learner's ego because of the teacher's punitive attitude to them. </s><s n="s4.5;p6.32">Consequently, students' curiosity of testing out their hypotheses about language usually dwindles with their teacher's negative attitude. </s><s n="s5.5;p6.32">If a class is set up for facilitating language learning, students should be able to feel free from the fear of making linguistic mistakes and the teacher should "incorporate many more exercises and activities in which success is judged less in terms of linguistic norms and more in terms of the total efficacy with which tasks using language are performed" (Brumfit, 1983, p. 87). </s></p></div3><div3><head rend="bold">Anxiety</head><p n="p7.32"><s n="s1.5;p7.32">Brown (1987) classifies anxiety into two types: debilitative and facilitative. </s><s n="s2.5;p7.32">Debilitative anxiety, viewed as a negative factor, can bring people too much pressure which prevents them from performing well. </s><s n="s3.5;p7.32">Facilitative anxiety, on the other hand, is a positive factor that can work as a critical push to one's successful performance. </s><s n="s4.5;p7.32">With "some concern--some apprehension over a task to be accomplished" (Brown, 1987, p. 105), one may feel an appropriate amount of nervousness to get things done. </s><s n="s5.5;p7.32">To pave the way for efficient language learning, the teacher should provide suitable activities to eliminate students' debilitative anxiety and, at the same time, set up tasks with enough tension to keep them on their toes and stimulate them to further efforts. </s></p></div3></div2><div2><head rend="bold">Cooperative Learning </head><p n="p8.32"><s n="s1.5;p8.32">Research has shown that cooperative learning is significantly conducive to students' achievement (Bejarano 1987; Nunan 1992; Slavin, 1995). </s><s n="s2.5;p8.32">Different from the traditional instruction featuring competitiveness, independent work and passive listening, cooperative learning encourages students to work in heterogeneous groups to complete a task or a shared goal and benefit from the interactions with others. </s><s n="s3.5;p8.32">It is a matter of "sinking or swimming together". </s><s n="s4.5;p8.32">Hence, everyone in the group should actively contribute their knowledge to the assigned task and actually get down to "doing" something. </s><s n="s5.5;p8.32">What's more, only through the concrete experience and active experimentation can one transform abstract concepts into his/her frame of reference. </s></p><p n="p9.32"><s n="s1.3;p9.32">In well-functioning cooperative groups, students' inhibitions and anxiety levels are lowered and self-confidence is enhanced with peers' support and positive encouragement of risk-taking. </s><s n="s2.3;p9.32">It is important for teachers to incorporate more cooperative learning into their teaching because it provides students with fail-safe climate allowing the development of learner autonomous, personal growth and social skills. </s><s n="s3.3;p9.32">To make cooperative learning work, the teacher should construct a classroom setting on the basis of five pillars: positive interdependence, individual accountability, abundant verbal, face-to-face interaction, sufficient social skills, and team reflection (Kohonen, in Nunan, 1992, p. 35). </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">Drama vs. Language Learning </head><p n="p10.32"><s n="s1.2;p10.32">After summing up the above analysis, a conclusion about foreign language teaching and learning can be made: For successful language learning experience to happen in class, the teacher should take account of the learner's affectivity and design tasks in which students are able to try out the target language for real communication with support from peers in the cooperative groups. </s><s n="s2.2;p10.32">Now let's turn to take a look at what role drama can play in this scenario. </s></p><p n="p11.32"><s n="s1.11;p11.32">What is drama? </s><s n="s2.11;p11.32">Why can drama facilitate language learning? </s><s n="s3.11;p11.32">Simply put, "drama is doing. </s><s n="s4.11;p11.32">Drama is being" (Wessels, 1987, p. 7). </s><s n="s5.11;p11.32">Through drama, learners can engage in language exploration with hands-on experiences. </s><s n="s6.11;p11.32">This actual "doing" and "being" in a meaningful context of language learning is the key to acquiring a second language. </s><s n="s7.11;p11.32">In her book about drama and language teaching Wessels gave a superb example to justify her claim of using drama in English teaching. </s><s n="s8.11;p11.32">When asked, "What is a blind person?", an English teacher can offer a simple explanation such as "A blind person cannot see" and the student may walk away with understanding of its literal meaning. </s><s n="s9.11;p11.32">But if the teacher asks the student to close his eyes and try to find his pen on the desk in front of him, the teacher is inviting this student to enter the world of the blind people. </s><s n="s10.11;p11.32">This direct experience of "doing" and "being" is more likely to help him internalize the meaning of "blind". </s><s n="s11.11;p11.32">Too often, the teacher is obsessed with feeding students with descriptive knowledge about the target language, forgetting the importance of giving them sufficient chances to "feel" the meaning of words and put language into real use in context. </s></p><p n="p12.32"><s n="s1.3;p12.32">With recent innovation in English language teaching, more and more attention is drawn to communicative competence and affective domain. </s><s n="s2.3;p12.32">From this perspective, drama is the best companion of language teaching because drama activities bear the characteristics mentioned above. </s><s n="s3.3;p12.32">The potential benefits of combining drama and language teaching can be summarized as follows: </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p13.32"><s n="s1.7;p13.32"><hi rend="italic">To create a meaningful context for communication</hi>: In real life, it may not be easy for learners to observe how language functions in different contexts. </s><s n="s2.7;p13.32">In drama, however, it is possible to set up various dramatic contexts in which learners can take on roles to try out language use. </s><s n="s3.7;p13.32">Drama, as Maley and Duff (1978) points out, "can help considerably by ensuring that language is used in an appropriate context" (p. </s><s n="s4.7;p13.32">9). </s><s n="s5.7;p13.32">What's more, by taking roles, the learners can "use and evaluate discourses and language registers they would not otherwise use" (Bunyan, 2003, p. 29). </s><s n="s6.7;p13.32">Another crucial element of successful communication is the need for communication and it is usually overlooked in the language classroom. </s><s n="s7.7;p13.32">In a well-designed dramatic situation constituted with conflicts and roles, the learners' need for communication tends to overcome their fear of inadequacy of language so that they are able to make the best use of the language skills they already possess (Somers, 1994, p. 139). </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p14.32"><s n="s1.3;p14.32"><hi rend="italic">To arouse awareness of non-verbal elements of language</hi>: Hayes once suggests, "drama techniques can directly engage the learner's feelings and makes him aware that meaning is not conveyed just through words alone" (1984, p. 9). </s><s n="s2.3;p14.32">To be more specific, "much of what we communicate comes from the visual and aural signals - facial expressions, gesture, tone of voice - that accompany our words" (Winston, 2004, p. 18). </s><s n="s3.3;p14.32">For those who are linguistically weak, learning how to express themselves by using facial expressions and body language is helpful to remove their inhibitions in communicating in a foreign language and make themselves better understood. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p15.32"><s n="s1.6;p15.32"><hi rend="italic">To increase self-confidence</hi>: Building self-confidence requires an accepting, non-threatening environment in which the learners are encouraged to take risks. </s><s n="s2.6;p15.32">Winston reminds us that drama is playful--"at the heart of drama is the human spirit of playfulness" (2004, p. 9). </s><s n="s3.6;p15.32">The playful nature of drama can lower one's anxiety level and free one's creativity and imagination. </s><s n="s4.6;p15.32">Drama is a highly socialization tool that demands cooperation and collaboration. </s><s n="s5.6;p15.32">The learners need to work with other people in most drama activities. </s><s n="s6.6;p15.32">If a positive and supportive working atmosphere is created among the group members, the group bonds can help break down the psychological barriers. </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">The Case Study</head><div2><head rend="bold">Subjects </head><p n="p16.32"><s n="s1.5;p16.32">The subjects of this case study were twenty senior high school students (at ages of 16-17 years) who came from marginalized areas in Northern Taiwan. </s><s n="s2.5;p16.32">Generally speaking, the students from suburban district tend to have a feeling of self-doubt and devaluation about their academic abilities. </s><s n="s3.5;p16.32">Moreover, it is common to find fear of failure and the undesirability of testing one's limits among them. </s><s n="s4.5;p16.32">The participants' responses to the questionnaire also validated the presupposition. </s><s n="s5.5;p16.32">Most students claimed that they did not feel confident in communicating in English and considered themselves low-achievers in terms of academic performance. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">Case Study Design</head><p n="p17.32"><s n="s1.9;p17.32">This case study was conducted in a five-day summer camp, aiming at facilitating the students' English learning through drama. </s><s n="s2.9;p17.32">In the summer camp, the participants all lived and at meals together on campus in order to extend their interactions beyond the scheduled teaching hours. </s><s n="s3.9;p17.32">They took three-hour English classes in the morning and had drama classes for another three hours in the afternoon. </s><s n="s4.9;p17.32">The morning English sessions, conducted by the researcher, functioned as language and cultural inputs. </s><s n="s5.9;p17.32">The teaching content was theme-based, including simplified script of Romeo and Juliet, two movies - <hi rend="italic">Shakespeare in Love</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Romeo + Juliet</hi> (directed by Baz Luhrmann), an animation of Romeo and Juliet produced by BBC, and an English love song about Montague and Capulet. </s><s n="s6.9;p17.32">The students were asked to respond to each other on certain issues orally or in written form by taking roles of the characters in the story of Romeo and Juliet (see fig. </s><s n="s7.9;p17.32">1). </s><s n="s8.9;p17.32">In the fictional context, "role-players give and receive (write and read) each other messages simultaneously... </s><s n="s9.9;p17.32">This immediacy prompts new understandings and uses of language as a direct result of the active experiencing of the fiction" (Neelands, 1992, p. 6). </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0116d-pic.002"><head>Fig. 1. Students in role as Juliet writing a letter to her friends</head></figure><p n="p18.32"><s n="s1.12;p18.32">The afternoon drama classes were designed and taught by an experienced high school teacher with an MA degree in Applied Drama. </s><s n="s2.12;p18.32">Her teaching goals were to arouse the students' awareness in the use of body language, stimulate their imagination, enhance their self-confidence, introduce drama elements and help create a cooperative atmosphere among groups. </s><s n="s3.12;p18.32">On the first day, the students started from developing body awareness and spatial perception through a series of warm-up activities. </s><s n="s4.12;p18.32">Then the teacher used some dramatic activities to introduce the students to the concept of roles and scenes. </s><s n="s5.12;p18.32">They also learned to develop stories by using pictures, narration and still image. </s><s n="s6.12;p18.32">On the second day, the students were taught to create simple improvisations based on personal experience and imagination. In addition, they learned how to develop characters via describing objects and defining the space. </s><s n="s7.12;p18.32">Conflict, an important element of drama, was brought in with improvisation. </s><s n="s8.12;p18.32">Role-play was the main activity on the third day. </s><s n="s9.12;p18.32">The students were given English role cards to read and to work in pairs to "develop a solidity of characterization which can be sustained within the improvisation" (Somers, 1994, p. 18). </s><s n="s10.12;p18.32">Through this activity, the students could gain a better understanding of empathy and "become sensitive to the way in which our built-in views of our own roles and those of others are defined and clarified through language" (Maley and Duff, 1978, p. 10). </s><s n="s11.12;p18.32">On the following day, the teacher had the students improvise a short English play with different acting styles and in various space and time frames (see fig. </s><s n="s12.12;p18.32">2). </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0116d-pic.003"><head>Fig. 2 An improvised English short play </head></figure><p n="p19.32"><s n="s1.7;p19.32">An English drama competition was held on the last day of the summer camp. </s><s n="s2.7;p19.32">The students started to work on the creation of a dramatic production since the second day and based their short play on the improvisation in the drama classes. </s><s n="s3.7;p19.32">As Wessels claims, discussing and planning the different stages in the drama project satisfies Krashen's theory of language acquisition - acquiring a language requires meaningful interaction in the target language (1991, pp. 12-13). </s><s n="s4.7;p19.32">When participating in creating a drama piece, the students focused mainly on communication and getting meaning across rather than form. </s><s n="s5.7;p19.32">By so doing, they were able to improve their fluency in target language production. </s><s n="s6.7;p19.32">Besides, the atmosphere of competition can form facilitative anxiety serving as enough tension to help bring out the students' successful performance. </s><s n="s7.7;p19.32">At the same time, the completion of the drama project is conducive to boosting the students' self-esteem and self-confidence. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">Data Gathering </head><p n="p20.32"><s n="s1.2;p20.32">A good case study should include as many sources of evidence as possible. </s><s n="s2.2;p20.32">Hence this case study relied on a variety of sources as Yin suggests (2003, p. 85): </s></p><list type="ordered"><item>Archival records: the teacher's lesson plans and the researcher's field notes</item><item>Interviews: surveys of the students, the summer camp assistants and the teacher</item><item>Direct observations: the use of multiple observers including the researcher and four camp assistants with videotaping </item><item>Participant-observation: the researcher's actual participation in the case study situation by teaching the English classes</item><item>Physical artifacts: the students' final dramatic pieces of work with which the researcher was "able to develop a more precise understanding of the classroom applications" (Yin, 2003, p. 96)</item></list><p n="p21.32"><s n="s1.3;p21.32">A questionnaire was distributed to the participants at the end of the summer camp to investigate their opinions about the curriculum. </s><s n="s2.3;p21.32">Before setting about to write this research paper, the researcher emailed another questionnaire with open-ended questions to the students, the teacher and the camp assistants to have a further exploration on the influences of the drama classes and competition. </s><s n="s3.3;p21.32">Video clips and digital photos of the summer camp were attached to the email to refresh the surveyees' memories. </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Data Analysis</head><p n="p22.32"><s n="s1.3;p22.32">According to the gathered data, the researcher found positive evidence showing that the drama curriculum and drama competition successfully enhanced the participants' self-esteem and self-confidence. </s><s n="s2.3;p22.32">Their anxiety levels were lowered with support from the cooperative learning group and they were more willing to take risk in trying out language use. </s><s n="s3.3;p22.32">The findings will be presented quantitatively and qualitatively as follows. </s></p><div2><head rend="bold">Drama is a facilitating tool for English learning. </head><p n="p23.32"><s n="s1.2;p23.32">The students were asked to respond to the statement: <hi rend="italic">I think the drama classes were helpful to my English learning</hi> on a four-point Likert scale. </s><s n="s2.2;p23.32">All of them held a positive attitude towards the efficacy of drama. </s></p><table id="BAWE_0116d-tab.001"><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p24.32"><s n="s1.9;p24.32">Some students enjoyed learning English through drama because drama provided a meaningful context for them to communicate in the target language. </s><s n="s2.9;p24.32">They could have more interaction with each other. </s><s n="s3.9;p24.32">A student complained about the English at school and said, "the school class is so boring. </s><s n="s4.9;p24.32">The teacher always puts you into sleep". </s><s n="s5.9;p24.32">Another student made a very interesting comment on the differences between traditional English learning and learning English through drama by stating, "The dramatic activities in the summer camp were fun and had so much variety and interaction. </s><s n="s6.9;p24.32">The English classes in my school are boring. </s><s n="s7.9;p24.32">There is no interaction at all. </s><s n="s8.9;p24.32">And sitting on the chair all the time hurts my buttocks! </s><s n="s9.9;p24.32">Learning with more interaction is much more fun." </s></p><p n="p25.32"><s n="s1.5;p25.32">Some students liked learning English through drama because their imagination and creativity were allowed to thrive in the dramatic world. </s><s n="s2.5;p25.32">A student pointed out, "It was more lively here. </s><s n="s3.5;p25.32">We could add in our own creativity and ideas. </s><s n="s4.5;p25.32">Every group's presentation had its distinguishing characteristics but they were all clearly presented". </s><s n="s5.5;p25.32">Another student confidently expressed her point-of view in English: </s></p><quote lang="English">'They [the English teachers] just translate everything on the textbook, and explain the grammar. Drama camp is so much better. It gives us the space to create and develop our own stuff. We don't just learn the language, but we also build the language. I like that. It's nice that you [the researcher] want to bring this in our education system.</quote><p n="p26.32"><s n="s1.2;p26.32">Drama also helped the students to comprehend English by actual doing and being. </s><s n="s2.2;p26.32">"Through drama, I learned to experience and comprehend language with my body, which motivated me to speak English more" - a statement made by a participant coincided with Wessels' claim of using drama in English teaching. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">Experiences in drama increase the students' self-confidence in using English. </head><p n="p27.32"><s n="s1.2;p27.32">According to the questionnaire, the majority of the participants (75%) lacked confidence in their English abilities before attending the summer camp. </s><s n="s2.2;p27.32">The reasons for their lack of confidence were listed as: </s></p><list type="ordered"><item>fear of speaking English</item><item>deficiency of English language competence </item><item>having no opportunities to speak English in the daily life</item><item>feeling embarrassed about making mistakes in English grammar and pronunciation</item></list><p n="p28.32"><s n="s1.2;p28.32">However, the drama classes broke down their psychological inhibition and made all of them feel confident. </s><s n="s2.2;p28.32">The following is some comments made by the students: </s></p><quote lang="English">"I did notice some of my partners became more confident in using English after attending those drama class. It worked!"</quote><quote lang="English">"The dramatic activities enlivened English learning. It was like playing games, which made speaking English an easier thing to do."</quote><quote lang="English">"The summer camp was like a stage for practicing English. We had opportunities to use English whether we were on stage or off stage."</quote><p n="p29.32"><s n="s1.1;p29.32">The camp assistants also observed the increase of self-confidence among the students: </s></p><quote lang="English">Assistant K: "Some students who considered themselves as low-achievers in English learning said, 'I just couldn't believe that I was able to act in English!' And lots of students shared the same thought.... On the one hand, the dramatic activities indeed lowered their anxiety about speaking English. On the other hand, drama also increased their interest in learning English."</quote><quote lang="English">Assistant S: "It's impossible for their English to improve too much within only five days, but I think they have gained a lot of self-confidence.</quote><quote lang="English">Assistant L: "At the beginning, they were afraid of speaking English because they thought their English was not good enough. However, after a couple of days, they were able to make a short play by combining simple sentences. At the final rehearsal, all of them had the courage to speak out even though there were still some grammatical mistakes and misuse of vocabulary. I think they have already crossed the hurdle of speaking English." </quote><quote lang="English">Assistant P: "On the first day, very few students responded to me in English.... However, they became totally different on the last day. I was surprised by the concentration and self-confidence they showed when acting and speaking English on the stage."</quote></div2><div2><head rend="bold">Drama activities necessitate cooperative learning. </head><p n="p30.32"><s n="s1.11;p30.32">Ninety percent of the participants agreed that learning how to work as a team was what they benefited the most from participating in the dramatic activities. </s><s n="s2.11;p30.32">The students considered the drama competition as a catalyst to encourage cooperation among members. </s><s n="s3.11;p30.32">As Nunan notes, "collaboration and competition can coexist in the same classroom; for example, when learners work collaboratively with some learners in a small group, but competitively against other learners in other groups" (1992, p. 3). </s><s n="s4.11;p30.32">The researcher stayed with the participants till midnight for a couple of days and saw them having spirited discussions about how to present their play. </s><s n="s5.11;p30.32">There were certainly some heated arguments during the discussion but they could always find a way to reach a consensus. </s><s n="s6.11;p30.32">Moreover, the participants were transformed from passive, low-motivated students into autonomous learners who were willing to sort out problems on their own initiative. </s><s n="s7.11;p30.32">They tried every possible way to make their play a better one - calling their friends for help, asking camp assistants to see them rehearse, consulting the teachers about the English usage. </s><s n="s8.11;p30.32">This kind of autonomy is rarely seen in the traditional classroom setting. </s><s n="s9.11;p30.32">With the support from peers and teachers, those who said they would never go on stage on the first day all volunteered to give a short speech about themselves in English in the drama competition. </s><s n="s10.11;p30.32">Even though only a few groups could win the prize at the end of the competition, the result did not overshadow the students' joy of accomplishment. </s><s n="s11.11;p30.32">Some students commented: </s></p><quote lang="English">"We didn't win the prize but the process is more important than the result. And the most important thing is we all did our best!"</quote><quote lang="English">"I like the drama competition. It exhausted me but also gave me a sense of achievement. It was more rewarding than getting high scores in exams."</quote><quote lang="English">"We all worked very hard in discussion, making props and participation. We even rehearsed till midnight the day before the competition but our performance was really an unforgettable one!"</quote></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Conclusion</head><p n="p31.32"><s n="s1.8;p31.32">Drama has the potential to develop communication abilities, increase English learning and promote a positive self-concept in an interactive, fun way. </s><s n="s2.8;p31.32">Successful language learning requires the whole person to reach out in an integrated way - intellectual, physical, and affective. </s><s n="s3.8;p31.32">However, most English teachers in Taiwan rely mainly on grammar-translation-oriented teaching methods, in which English is taught in a vacuum as a set of language skills without immediate utility and only students' mental effort is called for. </s><s n="s4.8;p31.32">While some students can survive in this learning scenario by performing well on discrete-point tests, most of them are overwhelmed by the fear of using English as a communication tool and even lose their confidence. </s><s n="s5.8;p31.32">Drama offers the students a chance to rethink the way they learn English. </s><s n="s6.8;p31.32">Through drama, they can experiment not only with verbal aspects of language but also non-verbal communicative aspects. </s><s n="s7.8;p31.32">By working in a cooperative group, they gain confidence to interact. </s><s n="s8.8;p31.32">In the dramatic context, they are able to feel the language rather than memorizing it mechanically. </s></p><p n="p32.32"><s n="s1.5;p32.32">The summer camp ended two years ago but its influence is still felt today. </s><s n="s2.5;p32.32">In February 2005, a student formed an online community for the members of the summer camp and most of the participants have joined in. </s><s n="s3.5;p32.32">Two students emailed me about their decisions of applying for the drama department in university. </s><s n="s4.5;p32.32">One student has already entered university, majoring in English. </s><s n="s5.5;p32.32">Drama has yielded fruitful results beyond what I expected when designing the curriculum for the summer camp. </s></p></div1></body><back><div1 type="bibliography"><head rend="bold">References</head><p>Bejarano, Y. (1987) 'A Cooperative Small-group Methodology in the Language Classroom', <hi rend="underlined">TESOL Quarterly 21</hi> (3).</p><p>Brown, H. D. (1987) <hi rend="underlined">Principles of Language Learning and Teaching</hi>, 2<hi rend="sup">nd</hi> ed, New Jersey, Prentice-Hall, Inc. </p><p>Brumfit, C. J. &amp; Roberts, J. T. (1983) <hi rend="underlined">An Introduction to Language and Language Teaching</hi>, London, Batsford Academic and Educational Ltd.</p><p>Bunyan, P. (2003) 'Critical Contexts: A Rationale for the Inclusion of Drama in the Critical Development of Pupils From the Age of 10 to the Age of 12', <hi rend="underlined">NJ: Drama Australia journal,</hi> Vol. 27, No.2. pp. 27-35. </p><p>Hayes, S. K. (1984) <hi rend="underlined">Drama as a Second Language: A Practical Handbook for Language Teachers</hi>, Cambridge: National Extension College.</p><p>Maley, A. &amp; Duff, A. (1987) <hi rend="underlined">Drama Techniques in Language Learning: A Resource Book of Communication Activities for Language Teachers</hi>, Cambridge, Cambridge University Press.</p><p>Neelands, J (1992) <hi rend="underlined">Learning Through Imagined Experience</hi>, London, Hodder &amp; Stoughton.</p><p>Nunan, D. (Ed) (1992) Collaborative Language Learning and Teaching, New York: CUP.</p><p>Slavin, R. E. (1995) <hi rend="underlined">Cooperative Learning: Theory, Research, and Practice,</hi> 2<hi rend="sup">nd</hi> ed, Boston: Allyn and Bacon. </p><p>Somers, J. (1994) <hi rend="underlined">Drama in the Curriculum</hi>, London, Cassell.</p><p>Stern, H. H. (1983) <hi rend="underlined">Fundamental Concepts of Language Teaching</hi>, Oxford: Oxford University Press.</p><p>Wessels, C. (1987) <hi rend="underlined">Drama</hi>, Oxford, Oxford University Press.</p><p>Winston, J. (2004) <hi rend="underlined">Drama and English at the Heart of the Curriculum: Primary and Middle Years</hi>, London, David Fulton Publishers.</p><p>Yin, R. K. (2003) <hi rend="underlined">Case Study Research: Design and Methods</hi>, 3<hi rend="sup">rd</hi> Ed, London, Sage Publications, Inc.</p></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
