<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_0119g" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Crime and the Sanctioning Process Assessment</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">deleted: page numbers
</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">2</p><p n="date">2004-12</p><p n="module title">Crime and the Sanctioning Process</p><p n="module code">LA207</p><p n="genre family">Essay</p><p n="discipline">Law</p><p n="disciplinary group">SS</p><p n="grade">M</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">3535</p><p n="number of s-units">178</p><p n="number of p">38</p><p n="number of tables">0</p><p n="number of figures">0</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">0</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">0</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">19.9</p><p n="average s-units per p">4.7</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">f</p><p n="year of birth">1985</p><p n="first language">English</p><p n="education">UKA</p><p n="course">LLB</p><p n="student ID">0119</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><titlePart rend="underlined bold">Crime and the Sanctioning Process Assessment</titlePart><docTitle><titlePart rend="italic">"The Police and Criminal Evidence Act 1984, with its amended Codes of Practice, have finally eradicated the false confession." Discuss. </titlePart></docTitle></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="section"><p n="p1.38"><s n="s1.1;p1.38">This paper will consider research findings into the causes of false confessions before turning to discuss whether PACE provisions address these concerns and eliminate the problem. </s></p><p n="p2.38"><s n="s1.5;p2.38">Research identifies three types of false confessions. </s><s n="s2.5;p2.38">Voluntary confessions are obtained without interrogative pressure. </s><s n="s3.5;p2.38">Gudjonsson identified a pathological desire for notoriety and attention as the cause for Henry Lee Lucas's false confessions to over 600 murders<ref target="BAWE_0119g-ftnote.001"/>. </s><s n="s4.5;p2.38">Other psychological explanations are delusional beliefs or self-punishment for previous behaviour<ref target="BAWE_0119g-ftnote.002"/>. </s><s n="s5.5;p2.38">Psychologically 'normal' people may falsely confess to protect the real perpetrator, or for other personal reasons, for example, to cover up an extramarital affair<ref target="BAWE_0119g-ftnote.003"/>. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0119g-ftnote.001"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">p. 21, Conti, Richard P., 'The Psychology of False Confessions' </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0119g-ftnote.002"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">p. 49, Kassin, Saul. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">M. and Gudjonsson, Gisli, 'The Psychology of False Confessions: A Review of the Literature and Issues' </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0119g-ftnote.003"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Radelet, M. I., Bedau, H.A., &amp; Putnam, C.E. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">(1992), 'In Spite of Innocence: Erroneous Convictions in Capital cases', Boston: North-eastern University Press; cited p. 49 Kassin and Gudjonsson, <hi rend="italic">op. cit.</hi> </s></p></note><p n="p3.38"><s n="s1.4;p3.38">'Coerced-compliant' confessions occur where, although suspects know that they are innocent, the custodial process induces a confession. </s><s n="s2.4;p3.38">Social impact theory explains that suspects make this type of confession where they perceive the short-term benefits to outweigh the long-term costs<ref target="BAWE_0119g-ftnote.004"/>. </s><s n="s3.4;p3.38">They may be induced by threats, explicit promises or implicit rewards, which attach preferable consequences to a confession<ref target="BAWE_0119g-ftnote.005"/>. </s><s n="s4.4;p3.38">Certain personality traits are particularly vulnerable to coercion. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0119g-ftnote.004"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">p. 45, Kassin and Gudjonsson, <hi rend="italic">op. cit.</hi> </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0119g-ftnote.005"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">P. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">49 <hi rend="italic">ibid.</hi> </s></p></note><p n="p4.38"><s n="s1.4;p4.38">The last category of confessions are 'coerced internalised' confessions, whereby innocent suspects "actually come to believe that they committed the crime"<ref target="BAWE_0119g-ftnote.006"/>. </s><s n="s2.4;p4.38">Research reveals that some suspects even create false details consistent with their guilt through a process of 'confabulation'<ref target="BAWE_0119g-ftnote.007"/>. </s><s n="s3.4;p4.38">The interrogation process distorts reality through social isolation, imagination exercises, the presence of an authority figure, or false conclusive evidence of guilt<ref target="BAWE_0119g-ftnote.008"/>. </s><s n="s4.4;p4.38">Another factor linked to this type of confession is vulnerability caused by suggestibility, youth and naivety, fatigue, stress, or the influence of drugs or alcohol<ref target="BAWE_0119g-ftnote.009"/>. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0119g-ftnote.006"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">p. 22, Conti, Richard P., <hi rend="italic">op. cit.</hi> </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0119g-ftnote.007"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">p. 54, Kassin and Gudjonsson, <hi rend="italic">op. cit.</hi> </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0119g-ftnote.008"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">p. 50-54, <hi rend="italic">ibid.</hi> </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0119g-ftnote.009"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">p. 23, Conti, Richard P., <hi rend="italic">op. cit.</hi> </s></p></note><p n="p5.38"><s n="s1.1;p5.38">These three categories explain psychological factors and coercive interrogation techniques as two principal causes of false confessions; it is often a combination of both. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined">Psychological Factors</head><p n="p6.38"><s n="s1.3;p6.38">Psychological vulnerabilities divide into three further categories: mental disorders; those induced to a mentally abnormal state by severe anxiety, phobic reaction to the confinement or drug withdrawal; and thirdly, those prone to give unreliable accounts due to personality characteristics of compliance, suggestibility and inability to handle pressure<ref target="BAWE_0119g-ftnote.010"/>. </s><s n="s2.3;p6.38">Juveniles are particularly suggestible and compliant, and primarily concerned with their immediate predicament rather than long-term consequences<ref target="BAWE_0119g-ftnote.011"/>; therefore the risk of false confessions is significantly higher. </s><s n="s3.3;p6.38">Kassin's laboratory experiment<ref target="BAWE_0119g-ftnote.012"/> showed the incidence of false confessions rose from 59% amongst adults to 78% amongst 12 to 13 year-olds. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0119g-ftnote.010"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">p. 1278, Gudjonsson, G. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">'The Psychology of False Confessions' </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0119g-ftnote.011"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">p. 45, Kassin. and Gudjonsson, <hi rend="italic">op. cit.</hi> </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0119g-ftnote.012"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">p. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">52-53, <hi rend="italic">ibid.</hi> </s></p></note><p n="p7.38"><s n="s1.2;p7.38">Compliance is brought about by an eagerness to please, and a desire to avoid confrontation and conflict with others<ref target="BAWE_0119g-ftnote.013"/>. </s><s n="s2.2;p7.38">Gudjonsson devised a test to measure compliance<ref target="BAWE_0119g-ftnote.014"/>, finding a positive correlation between confessions and high compliance scores. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0119g-ftnote.013"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">p. 51, <hi rend="italic">ibid.</hi> </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0119g-ftnote.014"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">p. 51, <hi rend="italic">ibid.</hi> </s></p></note><p n="p8.38"><s n="s1.6;p8.38">Interrogative suggestibility is "the extent to which within a closed social interaction, people come to accept messages communicated during formal questioning, as a result of which their subsequent behavioural response is affected"<ref target="BAWE_0119g-ftnote.015"/>. </s><s n="s2.6;p8.38">Gudjonsson found that people shift their memory in response to misleading questions and negative feedback<ref target="BAWE_0119g-ftnote.016"/>. </s><s n="s3.6;p8.38">Higher suggestibility scores were linked to sleep deprivation, poor memory, high levels of anxiety and low self-esteem<ref target="BAWE_0119g-ftnote.017"/>. </s><s n="s4.6;p8.38">Suggestibility was highest amongst internalised false confessions. </s><s n="s5.6;p8.38">Eysenck found that introverts were particularly suggestible<ref target="BAWE_0119g-ftnote.018"/>. </s><s n="s6.6;p8.38">As methods of interrogation are devised to deal with typically extrovert criminals, introverts are put under considerable pressure<ref target="BAWE_0119g-ftnote.019"/>. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0119g-ftnote.015"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Gudjonsson, G. H, p. 280 (1991) 'The application of interrrogative suggestibility to police intervention'; cited p. 24, Conti, Richard P.,<hi rend="italic"> op. cit.</hi> </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0119g-ftnote.016"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">p.303, Baxter, J., 'Managing Interrogative Pressure in Police Interviews' </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0119g-ftnote.017"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">p. 52, Kassin. and Gudjonsson, <hi rend="italic">op. cit.</hi> </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0119g-ftnote.018"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Eysenck, H. J., (1964) 'Crime and Personality', London: Routledge; cited p. 25 Conti, Richard P., <hi rend="italic">op. cit.</hi> </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0119g-ftnote.019"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">p. 25, Conti, Richard P., <hi rend="italic">op. cit.</hi> </s></p></note></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined">Situational Factors</head><p n="p9.38"><s n="s1.4;p9.38">Features of the interrogation process exacerbate individual vulnerabilities, rendering unreliable and false confessions more likely. </s><s n="s2.4;p9.38">Physical isolation heightens anxiety, and lengthy periods of detention increase the need for escape<ref target="BAWE_0119g-ftnote.020"/>. </s><s n="s3.4;p9.38">Uncertainty about the future and lack of autonomy increase anxiety<ref target="BAWE_0119g-ftnote.021"/>. </s><s n="s4.4;p9.38">Fatigue and sleep deprivation impair decision-making abilities and heighten susceptibility to influence<ref target="BAWE_0119g-ftnote.022"/>. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0119g-ftnote.020"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">p. 53, Kassin. and Gudjonsson, <hi rend="italic">op. cit.</hi> </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0119g-ftnote.021"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">p. 60, <hi rend="italic">ibid.</hi> </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0119g-ftnote.022"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">p. 53, <hi rend="italic">ibid.</hi> </s></p></note><p n="p10.38"><s n="s1.3;p10.38">The adversarial structure of interrogation instils a sense of helplessness. </s><s n="s2.3;p10.38">Interview tactics, such as disputing alibis, interrupting explanations, and presenting ostensibly incontrovertible evidence of guilt, convey a sense of inevitability of conviction<ref target="BAWE_0119g-ftnote.023"/>. </s><s n="s3.3;p10.38">Another tactic is minimisation, providing excuse or justification or downplaying the seriousness of the crime to encourage confessions by implying that lenient sentencing will ensue<ref target="BAWE_0119g-ftnote.024"/>. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0119g-ftnote.023"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">p. 54, <hi rend="italic">ibid.</hi> </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0119g-ftnote.024"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">p. 55, <hi rend="italic">ibid.</hi> </s></p></note></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined">PACE</head><p n="p11.38"><s n="s1.3;p11.38">PACE has codified and expanded upon Judges' Rules and Administrative Directions previously governing police behaviour. </s><s n="s2.3;p11.38">The provisions carry greater force because they have parliamentary endorsement. </s><s n="s3.3;p11.38">Additionally, PACE enacted provisions dealing explicitly with the admissibility of confession evidence. </s></p><p n="p12.38"><s n="s1.10;p12.38">Section 56 entitles an arrestee to inform someone of their arrest and whereabouts. </s><s n="s2.10;p12.38">This may "lessen the psychological pressures associated with isolated confinement"<ref target="BAWE_0119g-ftnote.025"/>. </s><s n="s3.10;p12.38">Section 58 provides for access to legal advice. </s><s n="s4.10;p12.38">This includes free independent legal advice from duty solicitor<ref target="BAWE_0119g-ftnote.026"/>. </s><s n="s5.10;p12.38">A legal representative "brings reassurance and emotional support to suspects who may be frightened or disorientated", as well as supervising the conduct of an interview<ref target="BAWE_0119g-ftnote.027"/>. </s><s n="s6.10;p12.38">These benefits may be removed where legal advice is delayed pursuant to subsection (8). </s><s n="s7.10;p12.38">However, this is arguably "very, very rarely used"<ref target="BAWE_0119g-ftnote.028"/>. </s><s n="s8.10;p12.38">Its impact is almost negligible when judged in light of the key source of an absent legal adviser: the detainees deciding themselves not to exercise their right to legal advice. </s><s n="s9.10;p12.38">Zander and Henderson found only 53-56 % exercised this right<ref target="BAWE_0119g-ftnote.029"/>, much lower than the 80% estimated by Dean. </s><s n="s10.10;p12.38">This reduces the scope of section 58 for tackling false confessions. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0119g-ftnote.025"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">p.400, Roberts and Zuckerman, 'Criminal Evidence' </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0119g-ftnote.026"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Paragraph 6.1, Code C </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0119g-ftnote.027"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">p. 431, Roberts and Zuckerman, <hi rend="italic">op. cit.</hi> </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0119g-ftnote.028"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Interview Question 2 (Appendix) </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0119g-ftnote.029"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Zander and Henderson, Crown Court Study, RCCJ, Research Study No. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">19 (HMSO, 1993); cited p. 434 Roberts and Zuckerman, <hi rend="italic">op. cit.</hi> </s></p></note><p n="p13.38"><s n="s1.5;p13.38">Another reason for the low take-up could be "various ploys" devised by police officers to delay or avoid legal advice<ref target="BAWE_0119g-ftnote.030"/>. </s><s n="s2.5;p13.38">This is inconsistent with Dean's claim that "coercion tricks can't happen now with PACE"<ref target="BAWE_0119g-ftnote.031"/>. </s><s n="s3.5;p13.38">Dean's positive outlook on the availability of legal advice can be contrasted with Roberts and Zuckerman, who criticise the proficiency of duty solicitors when they are called upon<ref target="BAWE_0119g-ftnote.032"/>. </s><s n="s4.5;p13.38">This questions whether the presence of a solicitor really does much to diminish pressure and safeguard against improper interview conduct. </s><s n="s5.5;p13.38">In the case of FC, the presence of a solicitor did not protect his client's interrogators from coercing a false confession<ref target="BAWE_0119g-ftnote.033"/>. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0119g-ftnote.030"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">p. 434, Roberts and Zuckerman, <hi rend="italic">op. cit.</hi> </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0119g-ftnote.031"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Interview Question 13 (Appendix) </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0119g-ftnote.032"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">p. 435, Roberts and Zuckerman, <hi rend="italic">op. cit.</hi> </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0119g-ftnote.033"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Gudjonsson and MacKeith, 'False Confession', p. 330-334 </s></p></note><p n="p14.38"><s n="s1.7;p14.38">Failure to inform a suspect of his right to legal advice has nevertheless led to a confession being inadmissible. </s><s n="s2.7;p14.38">This contributed to the quashing of a conviction based on an unreliable confession in <hi rend="italic">Blackburn</hi><ref target="BAWE_0119g-ftnote.034"/>. </s><s n="s3.7;p14.38">In <hi rend="italic">Samuel</hi><ref target="BAWE_0119g-ftnote.035"/>, access to legal advice was refused prior to several interviews, one in which the defendant confessed to burglary. </s><s n="s4.7;p14.38">The confession was excluded on grounds of fairness under section 78, since a solicitor would have advised the defendant to remain silent. </s><s n="s5.7;p14.38">In <hi rend="italic">Alladice</hi><ref target="BAWE_0119g-ftnote.036"/>, the defendant was familiar with the criminal justice system. </s><s n="s6.7;p14.38">Absence of a legal adviser did not deprive him of his right to silence since he was already aware of this right; therefore his confession was admissible. </s><s n="s7.7;p14.38"><hi rend="italic">Alladice</hi> demonstrates that the right to legal advice is not absolute. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0119g-ftnote.034"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.3;pn1.1">[2005] 2 Cr. </s><s n="s2.3;pn1.1">App. </s><s n="s3.3;pn1.1">R. 30 at 440 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0119g-ftnote.035"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">[1988] 1 Q.B. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">615 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0119g-ftnote.036"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.4;pn1.1">(1988) </s><s n="s2.4;pn1.1">87 Cr. </s><s n="s3.4;pn1.1">App. </s><s n="s4.4;pn1.1">R. 380 </s></p></note><p n="p15.38"><s n="s1.4;p15.38">Code C provides guidance for 'Detention, Treatment and Questioning of Persons by Police Officers'. </s><s n="s2.4;p15.38">Codes of Practice must be readily available in police stations for detainees to consult their rights<ref target="BAWE_0119g-ftnote.037"/>. </s><s n="s3.4;p15.38">A poster advertising the right to legal advice must be displayed prominently in the charging area of every police station<ref target="BAWE_0119g-ftnote.038"/>. </s><s n="s4.4;p15.38">The increased awareness of legal rights will help alleviate pressure and feelings of helplessness which lead to coerced compliance. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0119g-ftnote.037"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Para. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">1.2 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0119g-ftnote.038"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Para. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">6.3 </s></p></note><p n="p16.38"><s n="s1.5;p16.38">An 'appropriate adult' must be present for juveniles and the mentally ill<ref target="BAWE_0119g-ftnote.039"/>. </s><s n="s2.5;p16.38">A rebuttable presumption in favour of assignment of an appropriate adult arises where an officer is told in good faith "that a person may be mentally disordered or otherwise mentally vulnerable", or where suspicion arises<ref target="BAWE_0119g-ftnote.040"/>. </s><s n="s3.5;p16.38">Failure to observe these formalities can render confessions inadmissible. </s><s n="s4.5;p16.38">An independent GP assigned the role of police surgeon may be called to examine interviewees suspected of suffering from psychological vulnerabilities. </s><s n="s5.5;p16.38">Extensive risk assessment, including the checking of medical databases, provides further methods of identifying this<ref target="BAWE_0119g-ftnote.041"/>. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0119g-ftnote.039"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Para. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">1.7 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0119g-ftnote.040"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Para. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">1.4 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0119g-ftnote.041"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Interview Question 8 (Appendix) </s></p></note><p n="p17.38"><s n="s1.5;p17.38">Section 77 imposes a judicial obligation to caution the jury where a case relies wholly or substantially on a confession of a mentally handicapped person which was not made in the presence of an independent person. </s><s n="s2.5;p17.38">This prevents disproportionate weight being attached to their confessions by the fact-finder. </s><s n="s3.5;p17.38">Section 77 can be criticised for conferring discretion on the court to act where "appropriate to do so", and for not extending to other psychological vulnerabilities. </s><s n="s4.5;p17.38">However, Dean describes police practice of routinely appointing appropriate adults for all psychologically vulnerable suspects. </s><s n="s5.5;p17.38">An independent adult will often be legally inexperienced and unfamiliar with the interrogation process; therefore it is doubtful whether they can adequately safeguard against manipulation of suggestibility and compliance. </s></p><p n="p18.38"><s n="s1.7;p18.38">Paragraph 1.1 outlines a general objective: "All persons in custody must be dealt with expeditiously". </s><s n="s2.7;p18.38">A continuous 8 hour period of rest must be provided in any period of 24 hours<ref target="BAWE_0119g-ftnote.042"/>, subject to limited exceptions. </s><s n="s3.7;p18.38">Cells must be adequately heated, cleaned, ventilated and lit<ref target="BAWE_0119g-ftnote.043"/>, and the same applies to interview rooms<ref target="BAWE_0119g-ftnote.044"/>. </s><s n="s4.7;p18.38">Seating must be provided<ref target="BAWE_0119g-ftnote.045"/> and refreshment breaks at two hourly intervals as well as breaks for recognised meal times<ref target="BAWE_0119g-ftnote.046"/>. </s><s n="s5.7;p18.38">These guidelines improve situational factors which contribute to interrogative pressure. </s><s n="s6.7;p18.38">Making detention as free from trauma as possible reduces its coercive effect. </s><s n="s7.7;p18.38">The provision for 8 hours rest alleviates the side-effects of high levels of suggestibility as a result of sleep deprivation, particularly problematic for internalised false confessions. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0119g-ftnote.042"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Paragraph 12.2 Code C PACE </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0119g-ftnote.043"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Para 8.2 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0119g-ftnote.044"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Para 12.4 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0119g-ftnote.045"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Para. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">12.6 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0119g-ftnote.046"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Para 12.8 </s></p></note><p n="p19.38"><s n="s1.7;p19.38">The length of detention is another contributor to coerced-compliant confessions: "the longer a person is detained, the less reliance can be placed on any confession, and the greater the oppression, because of the very fact of being detained in the unpleasant surroundings of a police cell"<ref target="BAWE_0119g-ftnote.047"/>. </s><s n="s2.7;p19.38">A number of PACE provisions are directed towards expediting the investigation process and limiting the period for which suspects can be lawfully detained. </s><s n="s3.7;p19.38">The custody officer must review the detention of the suspect after the initial 6 hour period<ref target="BAWE_0119g-ftnote.048"/>, and subsequently at intervals of no less than 9 hours<ref target="BAWE_0119g-ftnote.049"/>. </s><s n="s4.7;p19.38">PACE permits up to 24 hours' detention without charge<ref target="BAWE_0119g-ftnote.050"/>; this can be extended to 36 hours, where circumstances permit, by an officer of the rank of superintendent or above<ref target="BAWE_0119g-ftnote.051"/>. </s><s n="s5.7;p19.38">Detention beyond 36 hours must be authorised by a magistrates' court<ref target="BAWE_0119g-ftnote.052"/>, the maximum period curtailed at 96 hours from arrival at the station<ref target="BAWE_0119g-ftnote.053"/>. </s><s n="s6.7;p19.38">However, these provisions may not prevent unreliable confessions being obtained, given that the mean interrogation time for inducing false confessions is 16.3 hours<ref target="BAWE_0119g-ftnote.054"/>. </s><s n="s7.7;p19.38">Even a 24 hour detention may be sufficient to provoke the mentality associated with false confessions. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0119g-ftnote.047"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">David Ashby, 'Safeguarding the Suspect'; p. 187 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0119g-ftnote.048"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Section 40(3)(a) </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0119g-ftnote.049"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Section 40(3)(b) </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0119g-ftnote.050"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Section 41(1) </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0119g-ftnote.051"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Section 42 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0119g-ftnote.052"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Section 43 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0119g-ftnote.053"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Section 44(3) </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0119g-ftnote.054"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Drizin S. A., &amp; Leo R. A. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">(2004), 'The Problem of False Confessions in the Post-DNA World', North Carolina Law Review, 82, 891-1007; cited at p. 54, Kassinand Gudjonsson, <hi rend="italic">op. cit.</hi> </s></p></note><p n="p20.38"><s n="s1.4;p20.38">Paragraph 11.5 provides that "no interviewer shall indicate, except to answer a direct question, what action will be taken by the police if the person being questioned answers questions, makes a statement or refuses to do either". </s><s n="s2.4;p20.38">This controls interrogation tactics, prohibiting the use of inducement or promises to elicit a confession. </s><s n="s3.4;p20.38">However, proscription does not altogether eliminate the practice. </s><s n="s4.4;p20.38">In <hi rend="italic">Barry,</hi><ref target="BAWE_0119g-ftnote.055"/> Code C was breached by the offer of assistance with requesting bail if the suspect complied. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0119g-ftnote.055"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.3;pn1.1">(1991) 95 Cr. </s><s n="s2.3;pn1.1">App. </s><s n="s3.3;pn1.1">R 384; cited in Zander, Michael, 'The Police and Criminal Evidence Act 1984' </s></p></note><p n="p21.38"><s n="s1.5;p21.38">Code C does not preclude all tactics conducive to false confessions. </s><s n="s2.5;p21.38">Some tactics described by Dean adhere to PACE yet they increase pressure on the defendant, inconsistent with confessions being entirely voluntary. </s><s n="s3.5;p21.38">The 'five Ws', make the interviewee "feel obliged to give an explanation"<ref target="BAWE_0119g-ftnote.056"/>. </s><s n="s4.5;p21.38">Requiring suspects to give an exhaustive account before confronting them with a bundle of inconsistencies, refuting their alibis and attacking their memory carry strong assertions of guilt which contribute to coerced-compliance<ref target="BAWE_0119g-ftnote.057"/>. </s><s n="s5.5;p21.38">PACE does not adequately address the full extent of the research on psychological vulnerabilities and the effect of different interrogation techniques. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0119g-ftnote.056"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Interview Question 12 (Appendix) </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0119g-ftnote.057"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">p. 53, Kassin and Gudjonsson, <hi rend="italic">op. cit.</hi> </s></p></note><p n="p22.38"><s n="s1.7;p22.38">Section 36 provides for the presence of a custody officer at designated police stations. </s><s n="s2.7;p22.38">A fundamental role is to ensure compliance with PACE. This includes asking the detainee if they would like legal advice or to inform someone of their detention, and determining whether an appropriate adult or medical treatment is necessary<ref target="BAWE_0119g-ftnote.058"/>. </s><s n="s3.7;p22.38">The custody officer is entrusted with the task of determining whether there is sufficient evidence for the suspect to be charged with the offence and detained<ref target="BAWE_0119g-ftnote.059"/>. </s><s n="s4.7;p22.38">Additional evidence must corroborate any confession, representing a further obstacle against reliance on false confessions<ref target="BAWE_0119g-ftnote.060"/>. </s><s n="s5.7;p22.38">He must also ensure that all matters required to be recorded are entered on the custody record<ref target="BAWE_0119g-ftnote.061"/>. </s><s n="s6.7;p22.38">This makes coercion more easily detectable, thus deterring behaviour likely to induce a false confession. </s><s n="s7.7;p22.38">The custody officer will be held accountable for any breach of his duties<ref target="BAWE_0119g-ftnote.062"/>; Dean asserts that this provides an effective means of enforcing PACE. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0119g-ftnote.058"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Paragraph 3.5 Code C </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0119g-ftnote.059"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Section 37 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0119g-ftnote.060"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Interview Question 10 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0119g-ftnote.061"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Section 39(1)(b) </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0119g-ftnote.062"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Interview Question 7 (Appendix) </s></p></note><p n="p23.38"><s n="s1.4;p23.38">McConville's article reveals complicity between custody officers and the police, which questions the independence<ref target="BAWE_0119g-ftnote.063"/>. </s><s n="s2.4;p23.38">The custody officer breached his duty to record all interactions between the police and suspect, facilitating deviations from PACE. Consequently, this impedes the subsequent proof of such inducements<ref target="BAWE_0119g-ftnote.064"/>. </s><s n="s3.4;p23.38">This seems far from Buck's ambitious expectation of the role as "that of a quasi-independent guardian for the care and treatment of all detained persons, and indeed the protection of individual police officers"<ref target="BAWE_0119g-ftnote.065"/>. </s><s n="s4.4;p23.38">It appears that the custody officer's position is defective in protecting against false confessions. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0119g-ftnote.063"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">p. 532-548, McConville, Mike, 'Videotaping Interrogations: police behaviour on and off camera' </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0119g-ftnote.064"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">p. 545, <hi rend="italic">ibid.</hi> </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0119g-ftnote.065"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">p. 152, Maurice Buck, 'Questioning the Suspect' </s></p></note><p n="p24.38"><s n="s1.12;p24.38">Section 60 introduced mandatory tape recording of formal interviews. </s><s n="s2.12;p24.38">Recordings must be "carried out openly to instil confidence in their reliability as an impartial and accurate evidence of the interview"<ref target="BAWE_0119g-ftnote.066"/>. </s><s n="s3.12;p24.38">The analysis of recordings can confirm or reject allegations of inducement or threats. </s><s n="s4.12;p24.38">Tape recording does not altogether eliminate oppression; however, it has enabled oppression to be more easily detected and therefore deter such behaviour. </s><s n="s5.12;p24.38">The practice is not without criticism. </s><s n="s6.12;p24.38">McConville conveys the discrepancies between on and off-camera communication between a suspect and a police officer<ref target="BAWE_0119g-ftnote.067"/>. </s><s n="s7.12;p24.38">The recorded interview depicts gentle questioning producing an entirely voluntary confession. </s><s n="s8.12;p24.38">This masks the previously unrecorded abusive language, aggressive tone, and the use of bail as an inducement<ref target="BAWE_0119g-ftnote.068"/>. </s><s n="s9.12;p24.38">Dean concedes that the chance for off-tape coercion arises, but asserts that this will be detectable in the taped interview, and the possibility of cross-examination deters any manipulation<ref target="BAWE_0119g-ftnote.069"/>. </s><s n="s10.12;p24.38">However, it does not appear to effectively deter officers in the videotaping experiment. </s><s n="s11.12;p24.38">Furthermore, contrived pleas only became apparent by covert filming. </s><s n="s12.12;p24.38">If video evidence can mask prior coercion or inducements, it follows that tape recording will be an even less effective safeguard against oppression, because non-audio cues are absent. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0119g-ftnote.066"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Para 2.1 Code E </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0119g-ftnote.067"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">p. 537, McConville, <hi rend="italic">op. cit.</hi> </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0119g-ftnote.068"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">p. 539-40, McConville, <hi rend="italic">op. cit</hi> </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0119g-ftnote.069"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Interview Question 5. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">(Appendix) </s></p></note><p n="p25.38"><s n="s1.2;p25.38">McConville concluded from the videotaping experiment that "the elaborate system of internal supervision and accountability introduced by PACE and its attendant Codes of Practice have failed to penetrate police working practices and relationships"<ref target="BAWE_0119g-ftnote.070"/>. </s><s n="s2.2;p25.38">This conflicts with Dean's contention that, "there is no room for manoeuvre under PACE"<ref target="BAWE_0119g-ftnote.071"/>. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0119g-ftnote.070"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">p.545, McConville, <hi rend="italic">op. cit</hi> </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0119g-ftnote.071"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Interview Question 14 (Appendix) </s></p></note><p n="p26.38"><s n="s1.9;p26.38">The above discussion shows that PACE has instilled values into police practice which improve the reliability of evidence. </s><s n="s2.9;p26.38">However, its success depends upon police compliance. </s><s n="s3.9;p26.38">McConville demonstrates how police-generated 'working rules' may be adopted if it is thought that the job "cannot be done by the book" <ref target="BAWE_0119g-ftnote.072"/>. </s><s n="s4.9;p26.38">If police can bend the rules, adherence must depend on the integrity of the individual officer<ref target="BAWE_0119g-ftnote.073"/>. </s><s n="s5.9;p26.38">There are inadequate methods of enforcement of PACE and accountability for breach. </s><s n="s6.9;p26.38">The Codes of Practice are only taken into consideration where they are relevant to any question arising in proceedings<ref target="BAWE_0119g-ftnote.074"/>. </s><s n="s7.9;p26.38">A breach does not necessarily lead to inadmissibility of evidence. </s><s n="s8.9;p26.38">Disciplinary actions were possible under section 67(8); however this was subsequently repealed<ref target="BAWE_0119g-ftnote.075"/> because proceedings were rarely instigated<ref target="BAWE_0119g-ftnote.076"/>. </s><s n="s9.9;p26.38">Now, breach of the Codes can only lead to criminal or civil proceedings if they are also a breach of the criminal or civil law<ref target="BAWE_0119g-ftnote.077"/>. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0119g-ftnote.072"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">p. 535, McConville, <hi rend="italic">op. cit</hi> </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0119g-ftnote.073"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">p. 186-7, McConville, Sanders and Leng (1991) 'The Case for the Prosecution' </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0119g-ftnote.074"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Section 67(11) </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0119g-ftnote.075"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">s. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">37(a) Police and Magistrates' Court Act 1994 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0119g-ftnote.076"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Report of the Runciman Royal Commission on Criminal Justice, 1993, Report, p. 48, para. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">102; cited p. 242 Zander, <hi rend="italic">op. cit</hi> </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0119g-ftnote.077"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">p.290, Zander, <hi rend="italic">op. cit</hi> </s></p></note><p n="p27.38"><s n="s1.2;p27.38">Section 76, 77 and 78 deal with the consequences of a breach of PACE upon confession evidence. </s><s n="s2.2;p27.38">These reinforce that false or unreliable confessions continue under the law of PACE. </s></p><p n="p28.38"><s n="s1.3;p28.38">Where section 76 is raised by the defence or by the court of its own motion<ref target="BAWE_0119g-ftnote.078"/>, the burden of proof shifts to the prosecution to prove beyond reasonable doubt that the confession is obtained by oppression, or by circumstances rendering a confession unreliable. </s><s n="s2.3;p28.38">This is disputed away from the jury in a 'voire dire' hearing. </s><s n="s3.3;p28.38">Roberts and Zuckerman expose the overlap between the two grounds: meal breaks, sleep and adequate cell conditions are necessary requirements for safeguarding against oppression as well as ensuring reliability, since poor conditions would make detainees more prone to making false confessions<ref target="BAWE_0119g-ftnote.079"/>. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0119g-ftnote.078"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">s. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">76(2) and (3) </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0119g-ftnote.079"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">p. 456, Roberts and Zuckerman </s></p></note><p n="p29.38"><s n="s1.2;p29.38">Section 76(2)(a) adumbrates the first ground for exclusion, where it is represented that the confession "was or may have been obtained... by oppression". </s><s n="s2.2;p29.38">Oppression is defined to include "torture, inhuman or degrading treatment, and the use or threat of violence"<ref target="BAWE_0119g-ftnote.080"/>. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0119g-ftnote.080"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Section 76(8) </s></p></note><p n="p30.38"><s n="s1.6;p30.38"><hi rend="italic">Fulling</hi><ref target="BAWE_0119g-ftnote.081"/> is widely cited as leading authority on the concept of oppression. </s><s n="s2.6;p30.38">Notwithstanding the definition provided by section 76(8), the Court of Appeal selected the test of "exercise of authority or power in a burdensome, harsh, or wrongful manner; unjust or cruel treatment of subjects..." </s><ref target="BAWE_0119g-ftnote.082"/><s n="s3.6;p30.38">from one of six of the Oxford English Dictionary definitions of oppression<ref target="BAWE_0119g-ftnote.083"/>. </s><s n="s4.6;p30.38">Upon this definition, it rejected the defence contention that telling the accused of her partner's affair with a woman held in the adjacent cell amounted to oppression. </s><s n="s5.6;p30.38">Lord Lane expressed that it would be difficult to conceive of an incident of oppression which "[did] not entail impropriety on the part of the interrogator"<ref target="BAWE_0119g-ftnote.084"/>. </s><s n="s6.6;p30.38">This high threshold test indicates a restrictive approach for finding oppression. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0119g-ftnote.081"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1"><hi rend="italic">R v Fulling</hi> [1987] QB 426 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0119g-ftnote.082"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">[1987] QB 426 <hi rend="italic">per</hi>Lord Lane at 432 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0119g-ftnote.083"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">p. 107, Munday, Roderick, 'The Court, the Dictionary, and the True Meaning of "Oppression": A Neo-Socratic Dialogue on the English Legal Method' </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0119g-ftnote.084"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">[1987] QB 426 <hi rend="italic">per</hi>Lord Lane at 432; cited at p. 317, Zander, <hi rend="italic">op. cit.</hi> </s></p></note><p n="p31.38"><s n="s1.4;p31.38">Conduct triggering hallucinations in a paranoid schizophrenic<ref target="BAWE_0119g-ftnote.085"/>, and shouting and swearing<ref target="BAWE_0119g-ftnote.086"/> have been held not to be oppressive. </s><s n="s2.4;p31.38">Nevertheless, in another case, vigorous, loud interruptions, and use of obscenities to indicate that the defendant was lying were sufficient to fulfil section 76(2)(a) and render the confession inadmissible<ref target="BAWE_0119g-ftnote.087"/>. </s><s n="s3.4;p31.38">In a pre-PACE case<ref target="BAWE_0119g-ftnote.088"/>, Miller, a borderline mentally ill, was "bullied and hectored"<ref target="BAWE_0119g-ftnote.089"/> through repetitive accusations by police until a confession was elicited after more than 300 denials. </s><s n="s4.4;p31.38">This conduct was held to amount to oppression and rebuked by the court: "Short of physical violence, it hard to conceive a more hostile and intimidating approach to a suspect". </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0119g-ftnote.085"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1"><hi rend="italic">R v Miller</hi> [1986] 1 WLR 1191, cited at p. 316, Zander, <hi rend="italic">op. cit.</hi> </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0119g-ftnote.086"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.3;pn1.1"><hi rend="italic">R v Emmerson</hi> (1991) 92 Cr. </s><s n="s2.3;pn1.1">App. </s><s n="s3.3;pn1.1">R. 284, cited p. 317, Zander , <hi rend="italic">op. cit.</hi> </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0119g-ftnote.087"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1"><hi rend="italic">Timothy John West</hi>, Gloucester Crown Court, April 22, 1988, cited p. 317-18, Zander </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0119g-ftnote.088"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.3;pn1.1"><hi rend="italic">Paris, Abdullai and Miller</hi> (1993) 97 Cr. </s><s n="s2.3;pn1.1">App. </s><s n="s3.3;pn1.1">R. 99 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0119g-ftnote.089"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.4;pn1.1">(1993) 97 Cr. </s><s n="s2.4;pn1.1">App. </s><s n="s3.4;pn1.1">R. 99 at para. </s><s n="s4.4;pn1.1">103 </s></p></note><p n="p32.38"><s n="s1.4;p32.38">There is a grey area falling between behaviour regarded as proper, and that which is perceived as oppressive. </s><s n="s2.4;p32.38">This was emphasised by Mitchell J in <hi rend="italic">Heron</hi><ref target="BAWE_0119g-ftnote.090"/> in which police were held to have acted oppressively: "Persistence must not, however, develop into bullying; robustness must not develop into gratuitously demeaning questions, nor must robustness be an acceptable label for what, in truth, is no more than a repetitive verbal pounding alleging the certainty of a suspect's guilt"<ref target="BAWE_0119g-ftnote.091"/>. </s><s n="s3.4;p32.38">This uncertainty could conceivably deter police actions which venture into this grey area. </s><s n="s4.4;p32.38">Conversely, it could have the opposite effect, making police think they can get away with borderline oppressive behaviour. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0119g-ftnote.090"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1"><hi rend="italic">R v Heron,</hi> Leeds Crown Court, November 1, 1993; cited p. 319 Zander, <hi rend="italic">op. cit.</hi> </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0119g-ftnote.091"><p n="pn1.1"><s rend="italic" n="s1.1;pn1.1">ibid. </s></p></note><p n="p33.38"><s n="s1.2;p33.38">Section 76(2)(b) provides a hypothetical test of unreliability resulting from "anything said or done", irrespective of the actual veracity of the statement. </s><s n="s2.2;p33.38">Although this may lead to acquittals of defendants making truthful confessions<ref target="BAWE_0119g-ftnote.092"/>, it promotes adherence to the Codes of Practice in future cases, thus enhancing the overall reliability of confession evidence<ref target="BAWE_0119g-ftnote.093"/>. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0119g-ftnote.092"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">For example <hi rend="italic">R v Cox [1991]</hi> Crim. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">LR 276 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0119g-ftnote.093"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">p. 456, Roberts and Zuckerman, <hi rend="italic">op. cit.</hi> </s></p></note><p n="p34.38"><s n="s1.6;p34.38">Personal characteristics of the accused are relevant to the test, incorporating a subjective analysis<ref target="BAWE_0119g-ftnote.094"/>. </s><s n="s2.6;p34.38">"Circumstances existing at the time" has been interpreted to include suggestibility or mental abnormalities<ref target="BAWE_0119g-ftnote.095"/>. </s><s n="s3.6;p34.38">Where safeguards devised to protect vulnerable suspects have been breached, the court has been prepared to interpret this as something "said or done which was likely...to render any confession unreliable". </s><s n="s4.6;p34.38">In <hi rend="italic">DPP v Blake</hi><ref target="BAWE_0119g-ftnote.096"/>, a child's confession was excluded because her estranged father could not fulfil the duties of an appropriate adult. </s><s n="s5.6;p34.38">In <hi rend="italic">Trussler</hi><ref target="BAWE_0119g-ftnote.097"/>, failure to permit the prescribed rest periods to a drug addict in custody sufficed to exclude the subsequent confession under section 76(2)(b). </s><s n="s6.6;p34.38">These cases recognise the effect of psychological vulnerabilities upon on the reliability of confessions for persons not suffering from mental illness, but who are particularly suggestible or compliant, or induced to a mentally abnormal state. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0119g-ftnote.094"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">p. 322 ,Zander, <hi rend="italic">op. cit.</hi> </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0119g-ftnote.095"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1"><hi rend="italic">R v Everett</hi> [1988] Crim. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">LR 826, cited p. 323 Zander, <hi rend="italic">op. cit.</hi> </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0119g-ftnote.096"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">[1989] 1 WLR 432 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0119g-ftnote.097"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">[1988] Crim. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">LR 446 </s></p></note><p n="p35.38"><s n="s1.3;p35.38">"Anything said or done" has been interpreted to refer to police misconduct, rather than interpreting the concept of reliability independently from fault. </s><s n="s2.3;p35.38">In <hi rend="italic">R v Crampton</hi><ref target="BAWE_0119g-ftnote.098"/>, drug withdrawal influenced the suspect to make a confession, yet the police-initiated interview was held insufficient to meet the threshold of section 76(2)(b). </s><s n="s3.3;p35.38">This leaves unaddressed confessions rendered unreliable, not by coercion, but as a consequence of situational factors attributed to the interrogation process when coupled with vulnerability factors. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0119g-ftnote.098"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.3;pn1.1">(1991) 92 Cr. </s><s n="s2.3;pn1.1">App. </s><s n="s3.3;pn1.1">R 369 </s></p></note><p n="p36.38"><s n="s1.6;p36.38">Section 78 provides a general residuary exclusionary discretion that applies to all prosecution evidence which has "such an adverse effect on the fairness of the proceedings that the court ought not to admit it". </s><s n="s2.6;p36.38">This provides an additional safeguard against confession evidence. </s><s n="s3.6;p36.38">Section 78 has been successfully invoked to acquit the defendant where police have failed to observe interview formalities<ref target="BAWE_0119g-ftnote.099"/>, to allow access to legal advice<ref target="BAWE_0119g-ftnote.100"/>, and to provide an appropriate adult<ref target="BAWE_0119g-ftnote.101"/>. </s><s n="s4.6;p36.38">However, these same factors have been rejected under section 78 in other cases, showing that each decision is fact-specific. </s><s n="s5.6;p36.38">Zander acknowledges that "there remains - and will always remain - a significant and irreducible degree of pure discretion left to the court, which, by definition, means that it could go either way."<ref target="BAWE_0119g-ftnote.102"/>. </s><s n="s6.6;p36.38">Evidence may be admissible notwithstanding a breach; this undermines the deterrent effect of PACE. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0119g-ftnote.099"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">[1988] Crim. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">LR 747; cited p. 336 Zander, <hi rend="italic">op. cit.</hi> </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0119g-ftnote.100"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1"><hi rend="italic">R v Samuel</hi> [1988] 1 Q.B. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">615 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0119g-ftnote.101"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.5;pn1.1"><hi rend="italic">Weekes</hi> [1993] Crim. </s><s n="s2.5;pn1.1">LR 211; <hi rend="italic">Glaves</hi> [1993] Crim. </s><s n="s3.5;pn1.1">LR 685; <hi rend="italic">Aspinall</hi> [1999] 2 Cr. </s><s n="s4.5;pn1.1">App. </s><s n="s5.5;pn1.1">R. 115; all cited p.336 Zander, <hi rend="italic">op. cit.</hi> </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0119g-ftnote.102"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">p.335, Zander, <hi rend="italic">op. cit.</hi> </s></p></note><p n="p37.38"><s n="s1.3;p37.38">The court has discretion also in relation to section 76: in <hi rend="italic">Barry</hi><ref target="BAWE_0119g-ftnote.103"/>, the inducement of assisting with the suspect's request for bail resulted in exclusion of admissions under section 76(2)(b). </s><s n="s2.3;p37.38">However, in <hi rend="italic">Howden-Simpson</hi><ref target="BAWE_0119g-ftnote.104"/>, police threats of bringing more than two charges against a suspect if he did not confess did not render the confession unreliable. </s><s n="s3.3;p37.38">Dean believes that the risk of having a case dismissed after the "endless paperwork" is a sufficient deterrent; however, where this consequence will not inevitably follow a breach, the risk is somewhat reduced. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0119g-ftnote.103"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.3;pn1.1">(1991) 95 Cr. </s><s n="s2.3;pn1.1">App. </s><s n="s3.3;pn1.1">R 384 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0119g-ftnote.104"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">1991 WL 839597 </s></p></note></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined">Conclusion</head><p n="p38.38"><s n="s1.8;p38.38">As conceded by Dean, false confessions will still occur, but PACE should limit these to voluntary confessions<ref target="BAWE_0119g-ftnote.105"/>. </s><s n="s2.8;p38.38">PACE lays down numerous safeguards which reduce situational factors conducive to coerced confessions. </s><s n="s3.8;p38.38">PACE also addresses psychological contributors by reducing interrogative pressure. </s><s n="s4.8;p38.38">However, there is need for increased recognition of the types of psychological vulnerabilities particularly conducive to unreliable evidence. </s><s n="s5.8;p38.38">The lack of accountability for breaches of PACE could impede its success. </s><s n="s6.8;p38.38">The prevalence of cases invoking section 76 and 78 highlight that it has not altogether eradicated coerced false confessions. </s><s n="s7.8;p38.38">Furthermore, the uncertain approach taken by the judiciary is likely to undermine the deterrent effect of having a case dismissed. </s><s n="s8.8;p38.38">PACE is often contingent upon 'working rules' and the integrity of the individual officer, ultimately leaving the level of interrogative pressure to the interviewer to decide<ref target="BAWE_0119g-ftnote.106"/>. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0119g-ftnote.105"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Interview Question 16 (Appendix) </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0119g-ftnote.106"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">p.303, Baxter, J., <hi rend="italic">op. cit.</hi> </s></p></note></div1></body><back/></text></TEI.2>
