<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_0120c" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>The law on corporate manslaughter</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">deleted: header: student number; footer: page numbers
deleted: [2505 words]</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">1</p><p n="date">2005-03</p><p n="module title">Criminal Law</p><p n="module code">LA104</p><p n="genre family">Critique</p><p n="discipline">Law</p><p n="disciplinary group">SS</p><p n="grade">M</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">2492</p><p n="number of s-units">97</p><p n="number of p">15</p><p n="number of tables">0</p><p n="number of figures">0</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">0</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">0</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">25.7</p><p n="average s-units per p">6.5</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">f</p><p n="year of birth">1985</p><p n="first language">French</p><p n="education">OSA</p><p n="course">LLB</p><p n="student ID">0120</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front/><body><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Introduction</head><p n="p1.15"><s n="s1.4;p1.15">The law on corporate manslaughter is undoubtedly an area in our present system which is subject to much criticism especially with the increasing number of death occurring in the workplace. </s><s n="s2.4;p1.15">According to an article by the Professional Health and Safety Consultants, "<hi rend="italic">there are still around 300 avoidable deaths in the workplace every year</hi>"<ref target="BAWE_0120c-ftnote.001"/>. </s><s n="s3.4;p1.15">Indeed, this makes us ponder about the effectiveness of our present law especially that some recent statistics (as at 10 January 2004) showed that only seven companies have been convicted of manslaughter so far<ref target="BAWE_0120c-ftnote.002"/>. </s><s n="s4.4;p1.15">As we shall see, the debate is mainly about how to attribute fault to a corporation and how effectively the law has overcome this problem or is there any scope for reform of the law. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0120c-ftnote.001"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1"><seg type="URL" n="http://www.healthandsafety.co.uk/Corporate_Killing_Notes.doc"/>. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">1 April 2005 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0120c-ftnote.002"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1"><seg type="URL" n="http://www.corporateaccountability.org/manslaughter/cases/convictions.htm"/>. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">1 April 2005 </s></p></note></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">The Present Law</head><p n="p2.15"><s n="s1.5;p2.15">According to the present law on corporate manslaughter, the only way of convicting a corporation is through the identification principle. </s><s n="s2.5;p2.15">Under this technique, those who control the company are considered as embodying the company so that their mind can be imputed to the company itself. </s><s n="s3.5;p2.15">It is a question for the jury to decide who can be regarded as the directing and controlling mind of a company. </s><s n="s4.5;p2.15">In brief, the main issue for the courts is how to attribute to a company the acts and states of mind of its employees for corporate criminal liability to arise, provided that these acts and states of mind satisfy the prerequisites for manslaughter. </s><s n="s5.5;p2.15">When a corporation is found guilty, the punishment is in the form of a fine because a corporation as such is not physical and thus, cannot be imprisoned. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Liability for manslaughter under the Present Law</head><p n="p3.15"><s n="s1.3;p3.15">We shall now consider whether BloggsBuild Ltd or any individual might be guilty of manslaughter under the present law. </s><s n="s2.3;p3.15">The first step is to assess whether each employee might be individually liable, then consider whether their act and state of mind could be imputed to the corporation. </s><s n="s3.3;p3.15">It is important to bear in mind that the death resulted from the acts of various individuals so that it is also necessary to consider issues of causation. </s></p><p n="p4.15"><s n="s1.4;p4.15">Criminal liability for the individuals will be one of gross negligence manslaughter because there is no 'malice aforethought' and the single test devised by the Court in <hi rend="underlined italic">Adamako</hi><ref target="BAWE_0120c-ftnote.003"/> will be used. </s><s n="s2.4;p4.15">First there is the need to establish whether the defendant was in breach of a duty of care towards the victim. </s><s n="s3.4;p4.15">Then, the next step is to see whether that breach of duty was the cause of the defendant's death and finally, the last step is whether that breach of duty amounted to gross negligence. </s><s n="s4.4;p4.15">The test for gross negligence as per <hi rend="italic">Lord Mackay LC</hi> in the same case will be "<hi rend="italic">whether, having regard to the risk of death involved, the conduct of the defendant was so bad in all circumstances as to amount in the jury's judgment to a criminal act or omission</hi>"<ref target="BAWE_0120c-ftnote.004"/>. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0120c-ftnote.003"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">[1995] 1 AC 171. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0120c-ftnote.004"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid at 187, Andrew Ashworth, Principles of Criminal Law, 4th edition, 2003 at pg 299. </s></p></note><p n="p5.15"><s n="s1.6;p5.15">Considering Sid's case, the question for the courts might be whether as a scaffolder he had the duty towards any eventual user of the scaffolding to ensure its stability and safety. </s><s n="s2.6;p5.15">On the assumption that Sid was in breach of a duty of care towards the victim, his case might fail on causation purposes since Colin's swinging the jib of the crane into the scaffolding might be regarded as a novus actus interveniens. . </s><s n="s3.6;p5.15">Thus, Sid's conduct may not in the first place satisfy the actus rea for manslaughter. </s><s n="s4.6;p5.15">As for the mens rea of manslaughter, he may not have the required knowledge about safety standards such that the risk of danger would have been obvious to him. </s><s n="s5.6;p5.15">In conclusion the courts might not find his conduct so gross as to amount to a criminal act. </s><s n="s6.6;p5.15">It can rather be said that it is Malcolm who had the responsibility of ensuring that the scaffolding complied with the safety regulations since it is his signature which is required on the form. </s></p><p n="p6.15"><s n="s1.10;p6.15">As for Colin, it can be argued in his favour that since he did not have the duty to operate the crane in the first place, he could not owe a duty of care. </s><s n="s2.10;p6.15">However, it can be counter-argued that by volunteering to do the job, he has also voluntarily assumed the responsibility<ref target="BAWE_0120c-ftnote.005"/> of driving the crane in a safe manner. </s><s n="s3.10;p6.15">Hence, a legal duty of care arises. </s><s n="s4.10;p6.15">But though he might be in breach of a duty of care which caused the death, his inexperience might pose a problem for the courts to establish whether his conduct was grossly negligent. </s><s n="s5.10;p6.15">Being inexperienced, he cannot be expected to perform the job like one who is trained and experienced. </s><s n="s6.10;p6.15">In the case of the death of Lee James Smith in November 1999, two farm owners were convicted of manslaughter for leaving a JCB potato loader in the control of a trainee, who was crushed to death after the equipment was hit by a lorry. </s><s n="s7.10;p6.15">The "<hi rend="italic">Birmingham Crown Court heard that</hi> "<hi rend="italic">the JCB should not have been under the control of an untrained 16 year old with very limited experience of operating such a large, potentially dangerous piece of equipment</hi>""<ref target="BAWE_0120c-ftnote.006"/>. </s><s n="s8.10;p6.15">Indeed, it is Malcolm's fault for failing to check Colin's qualifications. </s><s n="s9.10;p6.15">Besides, it should have been obvious to him that Colin may not have the required skill for the latter is only an apprentice carpenter. </s><s n="s10.10;p6.15">Moreover, being inexperienced might mean that Colin was unconscious as to the fact that he was manipulating the crane in a dangerous way, and therefore any risk of harm might not have been obvious to him. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0120c-ftnote.005"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1"><hi rend="underlined italic">Stone and Dobinson</hi> [1977] QB 354. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0120c-ftnote.006"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1"><seg type="URL" n="http://www.corporateaccountability.org/manslaughter/cases/convictions.htm#Smith"/>. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">4 April 2005. </s></p></note><p n="p7.15"><s n="s1.8;p7.15">On all grounds, Malcolm seems to be at fault. </s><s n="s2.8;p7.15">Based on his relationship with the victim as the site manager supervising his activities, a breach of duty of care can be established. </s><s n="s3.8;p7.15">He owes a duty of care towards Vince, just as any other worker, to ensure his safety and health, and has undoubtedly failed to do so. </s><s n="s4.8;p7.15">He had knowledge that there were insufficient clamps and nevertheless instructed the scaffolder to carry on with the work. </s><s n="s5.8;p7.15">He even gave his approval that the scaffolding complied with the safety regulations without even inspecting it. </s><s n="s6.8;p7.15">Moreover, he omitted to check Colin's qualification and did not take any action when other workers reported to him the way in which the crane was being dangerously operated in a very unpredictable manner. </s><s n="s7.8;p7.15">This clearly shows his indifference to the risk of harm in the workplace. </s><s n="s8.8;p7.15">His conduct clearly falls far below what is expected of him as a site manager making him individually liable. </s></p><p n="p8.15"><s n="s1.6;p8.15">Since Malcolm's conduct can potentially satisfy the prerequisites for gross negligence manslaughter, it is now necessary to consider the possibility of whether his conduct might be attributed to the corporation. </s><s n="s2.6;p8.15">Being the site manager, he is obviously well placed in the hierarchy of the company. </s><s n="s3.6;p8.15">In <hi rend="underlined italic">Tesco Supermarkets Ltd v Natrass</hi><ref target="BAWE_0120c-ftnote.007"/>, it was held that the 'branch manager' was "<hi rend="italic">not part of the "mind" of the company</hi>"<ref target="BAWE_0120c-ftnote.008"/> because supervision of the details of operations in a retail shop is not part of the function of higher management<ref target="BAWE_0120c-ftnote.009"/>.This defence could be potentially applied to a 'site manager' case. </s><s n="s4.6;p8.15">Besides, there is clearly the existence of an obvious individual within the company against whom proceedings can be brought<ref target="BAWE_0120c-ftnote.010"/>. </s><s n="s5.6;p8.15">The court will be reluctant to find corporate fault as the act was committed by another person. </s><s n="s6.6;p8.15">Indeed, Malcolm is the one who negligently failed to supervise the work properly and should therefore be solely liable. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0120c-ftnote.007"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">[1972] AC 153. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0120c-ftnote.008"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Law Com No 237 (1996), para 6.32 at pg 76. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0120c-ftnote.009"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Lord Pearson in <hi rend="underlined italic">Tesco Supermarkets Ltd v Natrass </hi>[1972] AC 153, Law Com No 237 (1996), para 6.37 at pg 78. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0120c-ftnote.010"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1"><hi rend="underlined">Birmingham &amp; Gloucester Railway.Co</hi> [1842] 3 QB 223, Law Com No 237 (1996), para 6.11 at pg 70. </s></p></note><p n="p9.15"><s n="s1.6;p9.15">As far as the managing director is concerned, it is unlikely that the courts will find him liable because his conduct may not satisfy the prerequisites for manslaughter. </s><s n="s2.6;p9.15">First of all, he had no knowledge of what was happening on the building site though he visited it on three occasions. </s><s n="s3.6;p9.15">His site manager failed to report him any of the problems occurring in the workplace. </s><s n="s4.6;p9.15">For corporate criminal liability to arise, the managing director must also be guilty because he is the directing and controlling mind of the company. </s><s n="s5.6;p9.15">As <hi rend="italic">Bingham LJ</hi> said in the case of <hi rend="underlined italic">R v HM Coroner for East Kent, ex p Spooner</hi><ref target="BAWE_0120c-ftnote.011"/>, "<hi rend="italic">it is required that the mens rea and actus rea of manslaughter should be established not against those who acted for or in the name of the company but against those who were to be identified as the embodiment of the company itself</hi>"<ref target="BAWE_0120c-ftnote.012"/>. </s><s n="s6.6;p9.15">Since, it is unlikely that Bloggs will be found guilty, corporate liability in this circumstance may not arise. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0120c-ftnote.011"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">[1989] 88 Cr App R 10, Law Com No 237 (1996), para 6.34 at pg 77. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0120c-ftnote.012"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid note 11. </s></p></note></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Critics of the Present Law</head><p n="p10.15"><s n="s1.7;p10.15">The identification principle has been greatly criticised for being narrow in its scope as seen through its application in <hi rend="underlined italic">Tesco Supermarkets Ltd v Natrass</hi><ref target="BAWE_0120c-ftnote.013"/>. </s><s n="s2.7;p10.15">It first depends on fault to be found at the individual level, and then even if a blameworthy individual can be identified, he/she must be the controlling mind of the company for corporate liability to arise. </s><s n="s3.7;p10.15">Besides, the more complex the management and the bigger the company is, the greater the difficulty to apply the principle. </s><s n="s4.7;p10.15">Indeed, the first case where prosecution for manslaughter resulted in the conviction of a company was in the case of <hi rend="underlined italic">Kite and OLL Ltd</hi><ref target="BAWE_0120c-ftnote.014"/> which was a one-man company. </s><s n="s5.7;p10.15">Although the limited scope of the identification principle can somewhat be said to be partially supplemented by prosecutions for breach under the Health and Safety at Work Act 1974, the problem is that the Health and Safety Executives (HSE) would only press charges in extreme cases that they believe represent a blatant breach of the Act. </s><s n="s6.7;p10.15">And consequently only 20% of workplace deaths resulted into company prosecutions<ref target="BAWE_0120c-ftnote.015"/>. </s><s n="s7.7;p10.15">These are the main reasons that led to Government proposals to introduce a new offence of Corporate Killing. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0120c-ftnote.013"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">[1972] AC 153. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0120c-ftnote.014"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Winchester Crown Court, 8 December 1994, unreported. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0120c-ftnote.015"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">CMV Clarkson &amp; HM Keating, Criminal Law Text and Materials, 5th edition, 2003 at pg 255. </s></p></note></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Recommendations</head><p n="p11.15"><s n="s1.4;p11.15">The Law Commission recommended the creation of a special offence of corporate killing similar to the offence of killing by gross carelessness. </s><s n="s2.4;p11.15">Its main idea is to adapt the test for killing by gross carelessness to corporations. </s><s n="s3.4;p11.15">Thus, under the new proposals, emphasis will be laid on "<hi rend="italic">management failure</hi>"<ref target="BAWE_0120c-ftnote.016"/> and on how the company's conduct fell far below what could be reasonably expected<ref target="BAWE_0120c-ftnote.017"/>. </s><s n="s4.4;p11.15">For the new corporate offence, it is not required that the risk should have been obvious to the defendant or that he was capable of appreciating the risk (unlike the individual offence). </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0120c-ftnote.016"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Law Com No 237 (1996), para 8.19 at pg 105. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0120c-ftnote.017"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid, para 8.35 at pg 110. </s></p></note></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Liability for manslaughter under the new proposals</head><p n="p12.15"><s n="s1.13;p12.15">Under our circumstances, the courts may find concurrent liability- on one hand, the site manager and on the other, the corporation. </s><s n="s2.13;p12.15">Malcolm would be guilty of the individual offence for the reasons already mentioned before<ref target="BAWE_0120c-ftnote.018"/>. </s><s n="s3.13;p12.15">As for the corporation, the crucial question would be whether there has been a failure to ensure safety in the management/organisation of the activities of the company<ref target="BAWE_0120c-ftnote.019"/>. </s><s n="s4.13;p12.15">Some of the points that the courts may take into consideration while answering this question might be whether there was an adequate system of checks and control on the building site. </s><s n="s5.13;p12.15">Malcolm's negligence might be unintentional due to excessive workload. </s><s n="s6.13;p12.15">The company should have perhaps employed additional supervisors, each responsible for a group of tasks. </s><s n="s7.13;p12.15">In this way, inadequate clamps could have been anticipated for if there has been someone monitoring the stock of materials. </s><s n="s8.13;p12.15">Moreover, the courts might consider the provision of substitute/replacement workers in case of absence or illness. </s><s n="s9.13;p12.15">In our case, there seems to be only one crane driver so that his absence will temporarily slow down the activities. </s><s n="s10.13;p12.15">The company should have taken measures beforehand for such eventualities. </s><s n="s11.13;p12.15">The courts might also take into account the provision of safety belts or safety nets for users of the scaffolding. </s><s n="s12.13;p12.15">It is likely that BloggsBuilt Ltd may be found guilty for not providing such equipment. </s><s n="s13.13;p12.15">Therefore, under the new offence, the courts will look at how safely and properly the activities of the company are being conducted as a whole rather than, as at present, try to pinpoint a blameworthy individual whose conduct can be attributed to the corporation. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0120c-ftnote.018"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Refer to pg 3. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0120c-ftnote.019"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Law Com No 237 (1996), para 8.19 at pg 105. </s></p></note></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Evaluation of the new proposals </head><p n="p13.15"><s n="s1.9;p13.15">As it can be seen, the new proposals are greatly advantageous in the way that it avoids the difficulty encountered with the identification principle. </s><s n="s2.9;p13.15">It focuses on corporate fault through its test of management failure falling far below the appropriate standard rather than finding individual fault which can be attributed to the corporation. </s><s n="s3.9;p13.15">Since a lot of emphasis is stressed on management failure, this may encourage companies to devote more financial resources to provide a safer working environment than they normally would. </s><s n="s4.9;p13.15">Another merit is that these proposals may discourage companies from shielding behind individual employees whose conduct caused the harm by putting all the blame on them. </s><s n="s5.9;p13.15">This is illustrated by the Law Commission in its hypothetical example of the lorry driver who causes death by dangerously driving in the course of company's business. </s><s n="s6.9;p13.15">The act in itself does not involve management failure. </s><s n="s7.9;p13.15">But under the new proposals, the corporate may nevertheless be liable if the driver was required to work excessively long hours or was doing so to earn overtime, and consequently was overtired, and the company has failed to provide a monitoring system to ensure that this does not happen<ref target="BAWE_0120c-ftnote.020"/>. </s><s n="s8.9;p13.15">Indeed, the new recommendations make it easier to convict corporations. </s><s n="s9.9;p13.15">As it has been criticised by the GMB Union in the case of the collapse of the Avonmouth Bridge platform in September 1999 killing four men, "<hi rend="italic">the current state of the corporate killing law hampered the member's families fight for justice</hi>"<ref target="BAWE_0120c-ftnote.021"/>. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0120c-ftnote.020"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Law Com No 237 (1996), para 8.21 at pg 106. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0120c-ftnote.021"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1"><hi rend="underlined">http:</hi><seg type="URL" n="www.thompsons-scotland.co.uk/article_view.html?id=195"/>. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">5 April 2005. </s></p></note><p n="p14.15"><s n="s1.6;p14.15">However, one might question the fact that the new proposals might be too harsh on companies. </s><s n="s2.6;p14.15">They do not guarantee that companies will escape liability even if all the necessary precautions and measures have been taken to ensure safety in the workplace because nothing is being said about what the appropriate standard expected of the company should consist of. </s><s n="s3.6;p14.15">This is a jury question and all will depend on how they interpret the words. </s><s n="s4.6;p14.15">Moreover, corporations might be forced to devote huge amounts of financial resources beyond their capacity to cater for all possible eventuality of danger in the workplace, and this is not realistic. </s><s n="s5.6;p14.15">The harshness of the new law might discourage the formation of new companies or even lead to closure of existing ones. </s><s n="s6.6;p14.15">Consequently, in the long run this may have a huge impact on the economy. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Conclusion</head><p n="p15.15"><s n="s1.6;p15.15">Therefore, even if the Government is attempting to rectify the loopholes of the present law, it can be seen that the new proposals also engender new problems. </s><s n="s2.6;p15.15">Hence, at times it is necessary to ask ourselves whether corporations should be in the first place capable of being liable for manslaughter. </s><s n="s3.6;p15.15">Besides, if companies are found guilty, they will only be required to pay large fines to the victims' families. </s><s n="s4.6;p15.15">Perhaps, it is better to have corporations liable for only a breach of duty of care towards its employees to ensure their safety and health in the workplace and consequently pay damages to those affected by the breach. </s><s n="s5.6;p15.15">The result will afterall be the same. </s><s n="s6.6;p15.15">In this respect, the law of tort might be more appropriate to deal with corporate harm-doing than the criminal law. </s></p></div1></body><back><div1 type="bibliography"><head rend="bold">Bibliography</head><div2 type="bibliography"><head rend="underlined bold italic">Text books:</head><p>Andrew Ashworth, Principles of Criminal Law, 4<hi rend="sup">th</hi> edition, 2003.</p><p>CMV Clarkson &amp; HM Keating, Criminal Law Text and Materials, 5<hi rend="sup">th</hi> edition, 2003.</p></div2><div2 type="bibliography"><head rend="underlined bold italic">Websites:</head><p>Law Commission Report 237 (1996)- <hi rend="underlined">http://<name type="other"/>.lawcom.gov.uk/files/lc237.pdf</hi></p><p>Centre for Corporate Accountability- <seg type="URL" n="http://www.corporateaccountability.org/index.htm"/></p><p>Thompsons Scotland- <seg type="URL" n="http://www.thompsons-scotland.co.uk"/></p><p>Professional Health and Safety Consultants- <seg type="URL" n="http://www.healthandsafety.co.uk"/></p></div2></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
