<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_0120e" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>"The European Council does not play a formal role in Community decision-making and does not constitute an institution hierarchically superior to the Community Institutions." (Koen Lenaerts). Discuss.</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">deleted: page numbers
deleted: [2583 words]</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">1</p><p n="date">2006-11</p><p n="module title">Foundations of European Law</p><p n="module code">LA240</p><p n="genre family">Essay</p><p n="discipline">Law</p><p n="disciplinary group">SS</p><p n="grade">M</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">2484</p><p n="number of s-units">89</p><p n="number of p">27</p><p n="number of tables">0</p><p n="number of figures">0</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">0</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">2</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">27.9</p><p n="average s-units per p">3.3</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">f</p><p n="year of birth">1985</p><p n="first language">French</p><p n="education">OSA</p><p n="course">LLB</p><p n="student ID">0120</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><docTitle><titlePart><hi rend="bold">"The European Council does not play a formal role in Community decision-making and does not constitute an institution hierarchically superior to the Community Institutions." (Koen Lenaerts)</hi> <hi rend="bold italic"> Discuss. </hi></titlePart></docTitle></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">INTRODUCTION</head><p n="p1.27"><s n="s1.5;p1.27">The European Council is an organ which did not exist when the Communities were first created. </s><s n="s2.5;p1.27">It originates from the existing Summit Conferences of the Heads of States which have been held since 1969. </s><s n="s3.5;p1.27">It was created in 1974 as a response to a growing feeling by European leaders that the European Economic Community needed stronger leadership to overcome the stagnation in Community legislation and, the financial crises of the early seventies, which showed that "<hi rend="italic">the Western currencies were so closely intertwined such that national governments could no longer preserve their national economic autonomy</hi>"<ref target="BAWE_0120e-ftnote.001"/>. </s><s n="s4.5;p1.27">The urgency to reaffirm the position of Western Europe in an increasingly economically interdependent world confirmed the critical importance of the European Council in shaping Community legislation in a clearer direction. </s><s n="s5.5;p1.27">The question, however, is how far-reaching is the scope of the activities of the European Council in the formal Community decision-making process and, what is its position <hi rend="italic">vis-à-vis</hi> the institutional framework of the Community. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0120e-ftnote.001"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">"<hi rend="italic">The European Council</hi>", Jan Werts (1992), Elsevier Science Publishers B.V, at pg 60. </s></p></note></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">I. Does the European Council play a formal role in Community decision-making? </head><p n="p2.27"><s n="s1.1;p2.27">We shall discuss three interrelated aspects of the European Council namely: its role within the Union, the status of its decisions and their impact on Community law. </s></p><div2><head rend="bold italic">A. Role of the European Council</head><p n="p3.27"><s n="s1.6;p3.27">At the European Council meeting in London on the 29 <hi rend="sup">th</hi>-30 <hi rend="sup">th</hi> June 1977, it drew up a list of tasks for itself in the so-called London Declaration, which in brief outlined that it should have "<hi rend="bold italic">informal exchanges of view of a wide-ranging nature held in the greatest privacy and not designed to lead to formal decisions or public statements</hi>"<ref target="BAWE_0120e-ftnote.002"/>. </s><s n="s2.6;p3.27">It was also acknowledged that it should have "<hi rend="italic">discussions which are designed to produce decisions, settle guidelines for future action or lead to the issue of public statements expressing the agreed view of the European Council</hi>",<ref target="BAWE_0120e-ftnote.003"/> suggesting that it is also engaged in a formal role: that of defining broad policy guidelines for the Community. </s><s n="s3.6;p3.27">Moreover, it was given a legal basis and brought within the framework of the Community law by virtue of Article 2 of the Single European Act (SEA) 1986. </s><s n="s4.6;p3.27">Its formal legal existence was later confirmed in the Treaty on European Union (Maastricht Treaty) in 1992. </s><s n="s5.6;p3.27">Article D TEU describes the role of the European Council as being to "<hi rend="italic">provide the Union with the necessary impetus for its development</hi>... [and to]... </s><s n="s6.6;p3.27"><hi rend="italic">define the general political guidelines thereof</hi>"<ref target="BAWE_0120e-ftnote.004"/>. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0120e-ftnote.002"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">"<hi rend="italic">Institutional developments - European policy: European Council</hi>", dans Bulletin of the European Communities (1977), No.6, at pg 83, MCE European Navigator- <seg type="URL" n="http://www.ena.lu/mce.cfm"/>, 26 November 2005. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0120e-ftnote.003"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1"><hi rend="italic">Ibid</hi>. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0120e-ftnote.004"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">"<hi rend="italic">Text, Cases and Materials on European Union Law</hi>", Jon Tillotson &amp; Nigel Foster (2003), 4th edition, Cavendish Publishing, at pg 94. </s></p></note><p n="p4.27"><s n="s1.1;p4.27">Hence, the European Council seems to have shifted from the informal chats to a key political forum for resolving matters of the EU, thus undertaking a more formal role within the Union. </s></p><p n="p5.27"><s n="s1.2;p5.27">However the real issue is whether it has a formal role in Community decision-making. </s><s n="s2.2;p5.27">This requires a more detailed analysis of the nature of its decisions and an assessment of their impact on Community law. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold italic">B. Nature of the European Council's decisions</head><p n="p6.27"><s n="s1.7;p6.27">According to Article 202 EC Treaty, <hi rend="bold">only</hi> the Council of Ministers (the Council) has the power to take decisions. </s><s n="s2.7;p6.27">Thus, legally speaking, the decisions of the European Council do not have any binding effect. </s><s n="s3.7;p6.27">Besides, until the SEA came into force, the European Council had no foundation in the Community's constitution i.e, the Treaties. </s><s n="s4.7;p6.27">As such, it was not regarded as an institution of the Union to which any decision-making authority based on law was attributed<ref target="BAWE_0120e-ftnote.005"/>. </s><s n="s5.7;p6.27">It was created outside the Community's institutional framework and as such did not participate in the formal decision-making process. </s><s n="s6.7;p6.27">Moreover, its decisions do not meet any of the decision-making requirements applying to the Council such as the initiation of discussions based on proposals from the Commission, the consulting of the Parliament for opinion, the publication of the conclusions in the Official Journal. </s><s n="s7.7;p6.27">Hence, they are political in nature rather than legal, implying that they are not part of the formal Community decision-making. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0120e-ftnote.005"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1"><hi rend="italic">Op.cit</hi>, note 1, at pg 110. </s></p></note><p n="p7.27"><s n="s1.4;p7.27">Nevertheless, there are particular circumstances where the decisions of the European Council are seen as legally binding. </s><s n="s2.4;p7.27">This is the view of those who regard the European Council as a special formation of the Council, thus "<hi rend="italic">wielding the legislative authority of the latter</hi>"<ref target="BAWE_0120e-ftnote.006"/>. </s><s n="s3.4;p7.27">Indeed in a report by the "<hi rend="italic">Three Wise Men</hi>" (Barend Bushevel, Edmund Dell and Robert Marjolin), it was advised that the European Council should not allow regular decision-making to dominate its agenda lest it becomes merely "<hi rend="italic">an extension of the Council of Ministers</hi>"<ref target="BAWE_0120e-ftnote.007"/>. </s><s n="s4.4;p7.27">But for the decisions of the European Council to be in fact the decisions of the Council, two conditions have to be satisfied: </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0120e-ftnote.006"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1"><hi rend="italic">Ibid</hi>, at pg 108. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0120e-ftnote.007"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1"><hi rend="italic">Report of the Three Wise Men</hi> <hi rend="italic">(1979)</hi>, pages 16-17, "<hi rend="italic">Ever Closer Union</hi>", Desmond Dinan (1999), 2nd edition, Macmillan, at pg 251. </s></p></note><p rend="ordered" n="p8.27"><s n="s1.1;p8.27">(a) that the Heads of Government are accompanied by a member of his government e.g, a Minister (which is certainly the case because of European Council's composition<ref target="BAWE_0120e-ftnote.008"/>) and, that a decision taken can also be attributed to the members of the Council<ref target="BAWE_0120e-ftnote.009"/>; </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0120e-ftnote.008"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Article D TEU states that the "<hi rend="italic">European Council shall bring together the Heads of State or of Government of the Member States and the President of the Commission.</hi> </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1"><hi rend="italic">They shall be assisted by the Ministers for Foreign Affairs of the Member States and by a member of the Commission</hi>". </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0120e-ftnote.009"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">The Council needs only to consist of members of the governments who are authorised to commit their government to the Union and Ministers satisfy this condition. </s></p></note><p rend="ordered" n="p9.27"><s n="s1.1;p9.27">(b) that the series of procedural requirements in the Treaties for such decision-making are complied with<ref target="BAWE_0120e-ftnote.010"/>. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0120e-ftnote.010"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1"><hi rend="italic">Op.cit</hi>, note 6. </s></p></note><p n="p10.27"><s n="s1.1;p10.27">Besides, in the Stuttgart Solemn Declaration on EU (1983), the European Council clearly stated that when it acts in matters within the scope of the European Communities, it does so in its capacity as the Council within the meaning of the Treaties<ref target="BAWE_0120e-ftnote.011"/>. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0120e-ftnote.011"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">"<hi rend="italic">Introduction to the Law of the European Communities</hi>", P.J.G Kapteyn and P.VerLoren Van Thermaat, 3rd edition, Kluwer Law International, at pg 184. </s></p></note><p n="p11.27"><s n="s1.9;p11.27">Akin to this idea, is the view of the European Council acting as a Court of Appeal for the Council to resolve the highly technical, complex and politically hot problems that were left outstanding from discussions at the lower level. </s><s n="s2.9;p11.27">Some examples are the annual budget, the introduction of milk-quotas in the Community or the creation of a common fisherie policy<ref target="BAWE_0120e-ftnote.012"/>. </s><s n="s3.9;p11.27">This function of the European Council was also recognised in the London Declaration. </s><s n="s4.9;p11.27">But in this case, the European Council stated that "<hi rend="italic">in dealing with matters of Community competence...</hi> </s><s n="s5.9;p11.27">[it]<hi rend="italic">... will conform to the appropriate procedures laid down in the Community Treaties and other agreement</hi>"<ref target="BAWE_0120e-ftnote.013"/>. </s><s n="s6.9;p11.27">This struck a rather different note from the Stuttgart Declaration. </s><s n="s7.9;p11.27">Here the European Council is acting in its own capacity and not as a special formation of the Council. </s><s n="s8.9;p11.27">Although the European Council will conform to the decision-making requirements, there is some doubt as to whether the decisions are legally binding. </s><s n="s9.9;p11.27">The TEU clearly distinguishes between the European Council as an organ for providing the necessary impetus, and the Council meeting in the special composition of the Heads of State- implying that the European Council as such cannot exercise the powers of the Council<ref target="BAWE_0120e-ftnote.014"/>. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0120e-ftnote.012"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1"><hi rend="italic">Op.cit</hi>, note 1, at pg 164. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0120e-ftnote.013"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1"><hi rend="italic">Op.cit</hi>, note 2. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0120e-ftnote.014"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1"><hi rend="italic">Op.cit</hi>, note 11, at pg 185. </s></p></note><p n="p12.27"><s n="s1.1;p12.27">Nevertheless, whether it is acting in its own capacity or acting as a special formation of the Council, the European Council has indeed a direct and formal role in Community decision-making. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold italic">C. Impact of the decisions on Community Law</head><p n="p13.27"><s n="s1.2;p13.27">In the circumstances described above, the decisions of the European Council will indubitably have a direct impact on Community legislation. </s><s n="s2.2;p13.27">Hence under this section, we will rather focus on the impact of the unenforceable decisions, in others words those which are of a purely political nature. </s></p><p n="p14.27"><s n="s1.6;p14.27">The decisions of the European Council are not isolated events but are seen as a very essential part in the process of Community decision-making. </s><s n="s2.6;p14.27">Indeed the high political stakes and intergovernmental nature of some matters in the EU ensure a key role for the European Council, for example the setting of the annual budgetary framework, the setting of the agenda for integration, the European and Monetary Union (EMU), the negotiating of treaty reforms<ref target="BAWE_0120e-ftnote.015"/>. </s><s n="s3.6;p14.27">Their highly political sensitivity ensures that no other EU body apart from the European Council can deal with them<ref target="BAWE_0120e-ftnote.016"/>. </s><s n="s4.6;p14.27">Thus, the shape of the legislation on these matters will be heavily dependent on the pronouncements of the European Council. </s><s n="s5.6;p14.27">Some examples are the Maastricht Summit (1991) which led to the agreement on the TEU, the Luxembourg Summit (1997) where a decisive policy was taken towards accession of ten new Member States, the Brussels Summit (1998) where the single currency was launched thus paving the way for the third stage of the EMU to become operative. </s><s n="s6.6;p14.27">This partial list of historical landmarks in the EU history indicates the political importance of these Summits<ref target="BAWE_0120e-ftnote.017"/>. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0120e-ftnote.015"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">"<hi rend="italic">Ever Closer Union</hi>", Desmond Dinan (1999), 2nd edition, Macmillan, at pg 250-251. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0120e-ftnote.016"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1"><hi rend="italic">Ibid</hi>, at pg 251. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0120e-ftnote.017"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1"><hi rend="italic">Ibid</hi>, at pg 237. </s></p></note><p n="p15.27"><s n="s1.2;p15.27">According to Wellens and Borchardt, the decisions of the European Council "<hi rend="italic">find themselves on the legally non-binding level but which according to their drafters have to be awarded legal scope</hi> [and, that they are directed at the Community's legal order and as a result] <hi rend="italic">influence the conduct of the Member States, Institutions, undertakings and individuals...</hi> </s><s n="s2.2;p15.27">"<ref target="BAWE_0120e-ftnote.018"/> Thus, they are temporarily unenforceable political policies which expect legal compliance and implementation by the institutions. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0120e-ftnote.018"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">WELLENS and BORCHARD, l.c, 285, <hi rend="italic">Opcit</hi>, note 1, at pg 125. </s></p></note><p n="p16.27"><s n="s1.2;p16.27">Therefore, the European Council has at numerous times approached the boundary between decision-making in the political sense and in the legal sense. </s><s n="s2.2;p16.27">The fact that it has been able to reach this limit suggests that it is deeply encroached in Community matters. </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">II. Does the European constitute an institution which is hierarchically superior to the other Community institutions? </head><div2><head rend="bold italic">D. Is it an institution of the EU? </head><p n="p17.27"><s n="s1.8;p17.27">The European Council is undoubtedly a leading organ in the Community but it is not an institution of the Community in the sense of Article D TEU. Although the TEU codified its composition and the number of annual meetings, it failed to formalise its institutional status. </s><s n="s2.8;p17.27">As for the SEA, it merely recognised its existence- it neither specifies the functions of the European Council nor does it lay down its relationship with the other institutions. </s><s n="s3.8;p17.27">These are indeed the two basic requirements which need to be fulfilled before one can speak of an institution<ref target="BAWE_0120e-ftnote.019"/>. </s><s n="s4.8;p17.27">Thus, in the three sets of treaty amendments (the SEA, TEU and the Treaty of Amsterdam) since its creation in 1974, the European Council never received the status of an official institution<ref target="BAWE_0120e-ftnote.020"/>. </s><s n="s5.8;p17.27">Therefore, only in the capacity of the European Council to act as the Council that it is an institution of the Community. </s><s n="s6.8;p17.27">But the Heads of State will in practice never meet in that composition because of their unwillingness to be bound by Treaty rules. </s><s n="s7.8;p17.27">In any other circumstances, the European Council is a separate organ operating outside the Community's institutional framework. </s><s n="s8.8;p17.27">It is worth mentioning that if the Constitutional Treaty is eventually ratified, it will for the first time treat the European Council as a full institution of the EU on its own right<ref target="BAWE_0120e-ftnote.021"/>. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0120e-ftnote.019"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1"><hi rend="italic">Op.cit</hi>, note 1, at pg 173. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0120e-ftnote.020"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1"><hi rend="italic">Op.cit</hi>, note 15, at pg248. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0120e-ftnote.021"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Article I-19 Constitutional Treaty, "<hi rend="italic">Law of the European Union</hi>", John Fairhurst (2006), 5th edition, Pearson Longman, at pg 94. </s></p></note><p n="p18.27"><s n="s1.2;p18.27">Therefore, strictly speaking the European Council is not an institution of the EU, although as it will be discussed below the European Council is closely related to the other institutions and has often usurped some of their functions. </s><s n="s2.2;p18.27">Hence, on these grounds one can almost speak of the European Council as an institution of the EU. Besides, the fact that it will be officially institutionalised in the Constitutional Treaty suggests that in the eyes of many, it is already considered as such. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold italic">E. The hierarchy of institutions in the EU</head><p n="p19.27"><s n="s1.1;p19.27">The fact that legally speaking the European Council is not an institution of the EU does not exclude the possibility of it being hierarchically superior to the other institutions. </s></p><p n="p20.27"><s n="s1.3;p20.27">According to Francis Snyder, the use of the European Council conclusions as strong political guidelines (although having no legal force in theory) suggests that they derive their force from the European Council's position in the hierarchy of the EU institutions<ref target="BAWE_0120e-ftnote.022"/>. </s><s n="s2.3;p20.27">The European Council being a stronger EU political institution facilitates the adoption of measures. </s><s n="s3.3;p20.27">This is further supported by the point of view that the strength of the European Council lies in its informality<ref target="BAWE_0120e-ftnote.023"/>: the fact that it is not bound by any Treaty rules, that its scope of activities is far-reaching since it can discuss about everything inside and outside the Treaties' boundary and, that the consensus method used to arrive at conclusions ensures that no State on its own can stand against these decisions<ref target="BAWE_0120e-ftnote.024"/>. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0120e-ftnote.022"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">"<hi rend="italic">The Evolution of EU Law</hi>", Paul Craig and Grainne de Burca (1999), Oxford University Press, at pg 471. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0120e-ftnote.023"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">"<hi rend="italic">Law of the EU</hi>", Jo Shaw (2000), 3rd edition, Palgrave Law Masters, at pg 130. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0120e-ftnote.024"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1"><hi rend="italic">Op.cit</hi>, note 1, at pg 130. </s></p></note><p n="p21.27"><s n="s1.2;p21.27">Moreover, the TEU officially recognises it as "<hi rend="italic">the motor of European integration, constituting the apex of the Council hierarchy for all areas of EU activity, both supranational and intergovernmental</hi>"<ref target="BAWE_0120e-ftnote.025"/>. </s><s n="s2.2;p21.27">Thus, the European Council is the main source of impetus for the development of the EU. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0120e-ftnote.025"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">"<hi rend="italic">Policy-making in the EU</hi>", Helen Wallace and William Wallace, 4th edition, Oxford University Press, at pg 24. </s></p></note><p n="p22.27"><s n="s1.5;p22.27">Furthermore, in relation to the Commission, the European Council has eroded its initiative-taking powers. </s><s n="s2.5;p22.27">The latter often triggers debates before the former has even started its own process of developing the same project<ref target="BAWE_0120e-ftnote.026"/>. </s><s n="s3.5;p22.27">After the emergence of the European Council, the Commission even acknowledged that it would have to adapt its modus operandi "<hi rend="italic">to the new system in which ideas will come from the top</hi>"<ref target="BAWE_0120e-ftnote.027"/>. </s><s n="s4.5;p22.27">Besides, the Commission also follows at any rate the request of the European Council since it knows that the Council is politically constraint by the ideas of the European Council. </s><s n="s5.5;p22.27">This suggests that "<hi rend="italic">the Commission has been overshadowed by the European Council as the authoritative institution</hi>"<ref target="BAWE_0120e-ftnote.028"/>. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0120e-ftnote.026"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1"><hi rend="italic">Op.cit</hi>, note 1, at pg 145. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0120e-ftnote.027"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Eighth General Report (1974), p XII, <hi rend="italic">Opcit</hi>, note 1 at pg 149. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0120e-ftnote.028"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1"><hi rend="italic">Op.cit</hi>, note 1, at pg 145. </s></p></note><p n="p23.27"><s n="s1.3;p23.27">The creation of the European Council has greatly marginalised the role of the Parliament. </s><s n="s2.3;p23.27">The former often reaches agreement on the basis of communications from the Commission before Parliament has been consulted for opinion. </s><s n="s3.3;p23.27">Thus the latter has lost its consultative powers<ref target="BAWE_0120e-ftnote.029"/>. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0120e-ftnote.029"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1"><hi rend="italic">Op.cit</hi>, note 1, at pg 157. </s></p></note><p n="p24.27"><s n="s1.2;p24.27">Concerning the Council, the practice of passing some of the complex matters up the hierarchy, shows that "<hi rend="italic">the Council has lost some of its primacy as the central political decision-making institution</hi>"<ref target="BAWE_0120e-ftnote.030"/> and reflects its ineffectiveness. </s><s n="s2.2;p24.27">The Heads of State have effectively created outside the Council a politically higher-ranking European Council<ref target="BAWE_0120e-ftnote.031"/>. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0120e-ftnote.030"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1"><hi rend="italic">Op.cit</hi>, note 1, at pg 162. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0120e-ftnote.031"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1"><hi rend="italic">Ibid</hi>. </s></p></note><p n="p25.27"><s n="s1.3;p25.27">As for the Court of Justice, the European Council remains outside the ambit of its jurisdiction unless the latter decides to act as a special formation of the Council. </s><s n="s2.3;p25.27">Indeed in <hi rend="underlined italic">Roujansky v European Council</hi><ref target="BAWE_0120e-ftnote.032"/>, the Court of Justice held that since the European Council is not an institution, its acts cannot be annulled. </s><s n="s3.3;p25.27">This demonstrates that the European Council is the utmost form of authority since its decisions can never be challenged. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0120e-ftnote.032"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1"><hi rend="italic">Case T- 584/93,</hi> <hi rend="italic">[1994] ECR II- 585</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Op.cit</hi>, note 23. </s></p></note><p n="p26.27"><s n="s1.3;p26.27">Therefore all these arguments suggest that the European Council is hierarchically superior to the other Community institutions. </s><s n="s2.3;p26.27">But it is worth noting that though it enjoys such an elevated rank in the hierarchy, it is powerless to take legally binding decisions. </s><s n="s3.3;p26.27">There is also a weakness of implementation: for the measures to produce legal effect they depend on whether the other institutions of the EU have an obligation to translate them into Community law. </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">CONCLUSION</head><p n="p27.27"><s n="s1.6;p27.27">In a nutshell, views about the European Council vary from some seeing it as conferences of government reaching unenforceable political compromises, to some seeing it as playing a formal role as the main political dynamo of the Community and, to others who consider it as the decision-making, initiative-taking and even proposal-creating body enjoying the highest authority. </s><s n="s2.6;p27.27">For most, it is already considered to be an institution of the EU owing to its deep involvement in Community matters, although legally speaking it is not. </s><s n="s3.6;p27.27">Last but not least, from a political perspective, the European Council is at the top of the hierarchical ladder as the key political forum. </s><s n="s4.6;p27.27">From a legal perspective though, the European Council shares the power with the other institutions, particularly the Council. </s><s n="s5.6;p27.27">Although it defines the broad policies of the EU, it cannot be denied that it is dependent upon the Community institutions to give them a legal status. </s><s n="s6.6;p27.27">With the possible ratification of the Constitutional Treaty, some views are likely to be altered since the European Council will be finally institutionalised. </s></p></div1></body><back><div1 type="bibliography"><head rend="underlined bold italic">Bibliography</head><div2 type="bibliography"><head rend="bold italic">Primary Sources:</head><p>"<hi rend="italic">The European Council</hi>", Jan Werts (1992), Elsevier Science Publishers B.V.</p><p>"<hi rend="italic">Text, Cases and Materials on European Union Law</hi>", Jon Tillotson &amp; Nigel Foster (2003), 4<hi rend="sup">th</hi> edition, Cavendish Publishing.</p><p>"<hi rend="italic">Ever Closer Union</hi>", Desmond Dinan (1999), 2<hi rend="sup">nd</hi> edition, Macmillan.</p><p>"<hi rend="italic">Introduction to the Law of the European Communities</hi>", P.J.G Kapteyn and P.VerLoren Van Thermaat, 3<hi rend="sup">rd</hi> edition, Kluwer Law International.</p><p>"<hi rend="italic">Law of the European Union</hi>", John Fairhurst (2006), 5<hi rend="sup">th</hi> edition, Pearson Longman.</p><p>"<hi rend="italic">The Evolution of EU Law</hi>", Paul Craig and Grainne de Burca (1999), Oxford University Press.</p><p>"<hi rend="italic">Law of the EU</hi>", Jo Shaw (2000), 3<hi rend="sup">rd</hi> edition, Palgrave Law Masters.</p><p>"<hi rend="italic">Policy-making in the EU</hi>", Helen Wallace and William Wallace, 4<hi rend="sup">th</hi> edition, Oxford University Press.</p></div2><div2 type="bibliography"><head rend="bold italic">Secondary Sources:</head><p>"<hi rend="italic">Developments in the EU</hi>", Laura Cram, Desmond Dinan and Nigel Nugent (1999), Macmillan.</p><p>"<hi rend="italic">Politics in the European Union</hi>", Stephen George and Ian Bache (2001), Oxford University Press.</p></div2><div2 type="bibliography"><head rend="bold italic">Websites:</head><p>MCE European Navigator- <seg type="URL" n="http://www.ena.lu/mce.cfm"/>, 26 November 2005- <hi rend="italic">(printout appended)</hi>.</p></div2></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
