<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_0127d" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Microbiology Tutorial</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">deleted: header: student name, course code, date; footer: page numbers
</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">2</p><p n="date">2004-04</p><p n="module title">Assessments for Microbiology/Virology</p><p n="module code">BS241</p><p n="genre family">Exercise</p><p n="discipline">Biological Sciences</p><p n="disciplinary group">LS</p><p n="grade">D</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">1068</p><p n="number of s-units">60</p><p n="number of p">30</p><p n="number of tables">0</p><p n="number of figures">0</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">0</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">0</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">17.8</p><p n="average s-units per p">2.0</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">f</p><p n="year of birth">1983</p><p n="first language">English</p><p n="education">UKA</p><p n="course">Microbiology and Virology</p><p n="student ID">0127</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><docTitle><titlePart rend="bold">Microbiology Tutorial</titlePart></docTitle></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">Strain Construction in <hi rend="italic">Bacillus azureus</hi></head><p n="p1.30"><s n="s1.3;p1.30">Strain construction involves the transfer of specific alleles or mutations of a gene from one cell to another. </s><s n="s2.3;p1.30">There are four main selection approaches to constructing a new strain of bacteria. </s><s n="s3.3;p1.30">These are direct selection, co-transduction, transposon tagging and penicillin enrichment. </s></p><p n="p2.30"><s n="s1.1;p2.30">Direct selection is where if a cell is an auxotroph, you are able to select for the prototroph or drug resistance in other situations. </s></p><p n="p3.30"><s n="s1.3;p3.30">Co-transduction is the simultaneous transfer of two genetic markers by transduction. </s><s n="s2.3;p3.30">Transposon tagging is where you can select for the transfer of a selectable marker if a transposon is next to it. </s><s n="s3.3;p3.30">Finally penicillin enrichment is a relatively ineffective technique for increasing the proportion of auxotrophic mutants. </s></p><p n="p4.30"><s n="s1.3;p4.30">The five strains of bacteria available for strain construction all have mutations in a variety of genes. </s><s n="s2.3;p4.30">The information provided concerning the mutated gene <hi rend="italic">endA</hi>4 does not explain how this mutation can be isolated. </s><s n="s3.3;p4.30">Strain UWB103 has the <hi rend="italic">endA</hi>4 mutation rendering it EndA- which the desired strain must be. </s></p><p n="p5.30"><s n="s1.1;p5.30">As such UWB103 will be chosen as the starting strain. </s></p><p n="p6.30"><s n="s1.4;p6.30">The phenotypic requirements of the desired new strain must be Trp- Met- Amz- EndA-. </s><s n="s2.4;p6.30">It does not matter if drug resistance markers or transposons are present in the final strain. </s><s n="s3.4;p6.30">Technically the order in which the desired strain can be constructed does not matter. </s><s n="s4.4;p6.30">I have chosen to construct the strain the following way for ease of explanation. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">Construction of the Trp- phenotype</head><p n="p7.30"><s n="s1.2;p7.30">This mutation cannot be directly selected for. </s><s n="s2.2;p7.30">The <hi rend="italic">trp</hi> genes are co-transducible with the <hi rend="italic">rspL</hi>63 marker which encodes streptomycin resistance. </s></p><p n="p8.30"><s n="s1.1;p8.30">Co-transduction can therefore be used to introduce the trp- phenotype into strain UWB103. </s></p><p n="p9.30"><s n="s1.2;p9.30">Strain UWB104 contains the <hi rend="italic">rspL</hi>63 marker and the wild type <hi rend="italic">trp</hi> genes. </s><s n="s2.2;p9.30">When bacteriophage BAZ is grown on strain UWB104, a proportion of the bacteria will incorporate the <hi rend="italic">rspL</hi>63 and <hi rend="italic">trp</hi> genes onto their capsids. </s></p><p n="p10.30"><s n="s1.3;p10.30">The resulting lysate should be grown with strain UWB101 on minimal media with streptomycin, glucose and tryptophan. </s><s n="s2.3;p10.30">The streptomycin selects for those colonies where the <hi rend="italic">rspL</hi>63 gene has been transferred and the tryptophan is to enable those colonies with mutations in the <hi rend="italic">trp</hi> genes to survive. </s><s n="s3.3;p10.30">A proportion of the colonies will have had the <hi rend="italic">rspL</hi>63 gene transferred next to <hi rend="italic">trpA</hi>2 mutated gene. </s></p><p n="p11.30"><s n="s1.3;p11.30">When fresh bacteriophage BAZ is grown on these colonies, some of the bacteriophage will incorporate the <hi rend="italic">rspL</hi>63 and <hi rend="italic">trpA</hi>2 mutated genes into their capsids. </s><s n="s2.3;p11.30">The resulting lysate should be grown with strain UWB103 and plated on minimal media with streptomycin, glucose and tryptophan. </s><s n="s3.3;p11.30">A proportion of the cells will have had the <hi rend="italic">rspL</hi>63 and <hi rend="italic">trpA</hi>2 gene co-transduced into their genome. </s></p><p n="p12.30"><s n="s1.3;p12.30">In distinguish between cells which are tryptophan auxotrophs and the prototrophs, replica plating should be performed onto minimal media with glucose and tryptophan and minimal media with glucose. </s><s n="s2.3;p12.30">Streptomycin is not required as the transduction of gene <hi rend="italic">rspL</hi>63 has previously been selected for. </s><s n="s3.3;p12.30">Colonies which only grow on the minimal media with glucose and tryptophan are the required colonies. </s></p><p n="p13.30"><s n="s1.2;p13.30">These colonies should be re-plated onto minimal media with glucose and tryptophan and designated UWB106. </s><s n="s2.2;p13.30">This strain is <hi rend="italic">endA</hi>4 <hi rend="italic">sacB</hi>6 <hi rend="italic">amzC</hi>45 <hi rend="italic">rspL</hi>63 <hi rend="italic">trpA</hi>2. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">Construction of the Met- phenotype</head><p n="p14.30"><s n="s1.2;p14.30">This mutation cannot be directly selected for, however, the <hi rend="italic">met</hi> and <hi rend="italic">sac</hi> genes are co-transducible. </s><s n="s2.2;p14.30">Co-transduction should therefore be used to introduce the <hi rend="italic">met</hi>- phenotype into strain UWB106. </s></p><p n="p15.30"><s n="s1.1;p15.30">Strain UWB102 contains a <hi rend="italic">metA</hi>7 gene, indicating that it is unable to synthesise methionine but strain UWB102 is able to utilize sucrose which strain UWB106 is unable to do, providing a simple means of selection. </s></p><p n="p16.30"><s n="s1.1;p16.30">Bacteriophage BAZ should be grown on strain UWB102 and a proportion of bacteriophage will incorporate the wild type <hi rend="italic">sac</hi> gene and the <hi rend="italic">metA</hi>7 gene into their capsids. </s></p><p n="p17.30"><s n="s1.2;p17.30">The resulting lysate should be grown with strain UWB106 and plated on minimal media with sucrose, tryptophan and methionine. </s><s n="s2.2;p17.30">Any cells where the <hi rend="italic">met</hi> genes were not transferred will be unable to utilize sucrose and as such be unable to grow. </s></p><p n="p18.30"><s n="s1.2;p18.30">To ensure the mutated <hi rend="italic">metA</hi>7 genes has been incorporated into strain UWB106, replica plating onto minimal media with sucrose tryptophan and methionine and minimal media with sucrose and tryptophan media. </s><s n="s2.2;p18.30">All of the colonies should be technically only grow on minimal media with sucrose tryptophan and methionine. </s></p><p n="p19.30"><s n="s1.2;p19.30">Such colonies should be picked and re-plated onto fresh minimal media with sucrose, tryptophan and methionine. </s><s n="s2.2;p19.30">This strain will be designated UWB107 and is <hi rend="italic">endA</hi>4 <hi rend="italic">amzC</hi>45 <hi rend="italic">rspL</hi>63 <hi rend="italic">trpA</hi>2 <hi rend="italic">metA</hi>7. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">Construction of the Amz+ phenotype</head><p n="p20.30"><s n="s1.1;p20.30">Strain UWB105 contains a pool of insertions of transposon Tn <hi rend="italic">917</hi> which encodes erythromycin resistance. </s></p><p n="p21.30"><s n="s1.2;p21.30">Some of the bacterial cells in strain UWB105 will have a transposon inserted next to the <hi rend="italic">amzD</hi>46 gene. </s><s n="s2.2;p21.30">When bacteriophage BAZ is grown with UWB105, a proportion of the bacteriophage will incorporate the transposon and <hi rend="italic">amzD</hi>46 gene incorporated into their capsids. </s></p><p n="p22.30"><s n="s1.2;p22.30">The resulting lysates should be grown with strain UWB104 as it is the only strain which does not contain a mutation in <hi rend="italic">amz</hi> gene cluster. </s><s n="s2.2;p22.30">The lysate and UWB104 cells should be plated out on nutrient agar with erythromycin. </s></p><p n="p23.30"><s n="s1.1;p23.30">The resulting colonies indicate that Tn <hi rend="italic">917</hi> encoding erythromycin resistance has been transferred onto the bacterial chromosome of strain UWB104. </s></p><p n="p24.30"><s n="s1.1;p24.30">The resulting blue colonies indicate that the transposon has 'hopped' onto the genome of the bacteria but has not transferred the mutated <hi rend="italic">amzD</hi>46 gene into the <hi rend="italic">amz</hi> gene cluster. </s></p><p n="p25.30"><s n="s1.2;p25.30">White colonies indicate that the transposon was inserted near the <hi rend="italic">amzD</hi>46 gene and caused its transference onto strain UWB104 genome. </s><s n="s2.2;p25.30">These colonies will be designated strain UWB108. </s></p><p n="p26.30"><s n="s1.2;p26.30">The final strain must be able to produce amazin. </s><s n="s2.2;p26.30">In order to convert UWB107 into an amazin producing strain, a back cross on strain UWB108 must be performed. </s></p><p n="p27.30"><s n="s1.2;p27.30">Bacteriophage BAZ should be grown on strain UWB108. </s><s n="s2.2;p27.30">As all the transposons will be located in the <hi rend="italic">amz</hi> gene cluster, a proportion of Tn <hi rend="italic">917</hi> will have inserted near the wild type <hi rend="italic">amzC</hi> gene. </s></p><p n="p28.30"><s n="s1.2;p28.30">The resulting lysate should be grown with strain UWB107 and plated onto nutrient agar and erythromycin. </s><s n="s2.2;p28.30">Any resulting white colonies indicate that the Tn <hi rend="italic">917</hi> transposon had not inserted near the wild type <hi rend="italic">amzC</hi> gene and as such did not transfer the gene to strain UWB107. </s></p><p n="p29.30"><s n="s1.1;p29.30">The resulting blue colonies indicate that the wild type <hi rend="italic">amzC</hi> gene was transferred. </s></p><p n="p30.30"><s n="s1.3;p30.30">A blue colony should be picked and re-plated onto minimal media with sucrose, tryptophan and methionine and designated strain UWB109. </s><s n="s2.3;p30.30">This strain is <hi rend="italic">endA</hi>4 <hi rend="italic">metA</hi>7 <hi rend="italic">trpA</hi>7 <hi rend="italic">rspL</hi>63 Tn <hi rend="italic">917</hi> and therefore the strain has a Trp- Met- Amz+ EndA- StrR EryR phenotype. </s><s n="s3.3;p30.30">Figure 1 illustrated this process. </s></p></div1></body><back/></text></TEI.2>
