<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_0127e" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>The Growth Cycle of Bovine Enterovirus</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">deleted: header: student and course name, date; footer: page numbers
</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">2</p><p n="date">2004-01</p><p n="module title">Laboratories for Microbiology/Virology</p><p n="module code">BS215</p><p n="genre family">Methodology recount</p><p n="discipline">Biological Sciences</p><p n="disciplinary group">LS</p><p n="grade">M</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">4027</p><p n="number of s-units">148</p><p n="number of p">69</p><p n="number of tables">6</p><p n="number of figures">2</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">0</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">0</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">27.2</p><p n="average s-units per p">2.1</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">f</p><p n="year of birth">1983</p><p n="first language">English</p><p n="education">UKA</p><p n="course">Microbiology and Virology</p><p n="student ID">0127</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><docTitle><titlePart rend="bold">The Growth Cycle of Bovine Enterovirus</titlePart></docTitle></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Introduction</head><p n="p1.69"><s n="s1.1;p1.69">The picornaviridae family comprises of a wide range of human and animal pathogens which are classified by their physio-chemical properties. </s></p><p n="p2.69"><s n="s1.2;p2.69">Bovine Enterovirus, as illustrated below by figure 1 is a picornavirus which is endemic in cattle populations. </s><s n="s2.2;p2.69">It is a member of the Enterovirus group of picornavirus and is non-pathogenic to its natural host and humans. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0127e-pic.001"><head>Figure 1, Bovine Enterovirus</head></figure><p n="p3.69"><s n="s1.3;p3.69">BEV is a class four virus with a single stranded positive sense RNA genome. </s><s n="s2.3;p3.69">BEV exhibits a very wide tissue tropism for cell types <hi rend="italic">in vitro</hi> which has hampered efforts to determine the cell surface receptor to which its Vp1 capsid protein attaches. </s><s n="s3.3;p3.69">The Vp1 protein locks to the receptor and becomes exposed producing a channel enabling its RNA genome to pass into the cell. </s></p><p n="p4.69"><s n="s1.3;p4.69">In the cytoplasm, the genome is replicated by continually by a gene encoded RNA polymerase. </s><s n="s2.3;p4.69">Many RNA polymerase molecules are able to attach to the 3' end of the genome which forms a double stranded intermediate. </s><s n="s3.3;p4.69">As continuous replication of the genome occurs the RNA is half away from the genome and newly synthesized RNA by proteins which enables up to five replication complexes to occur at any one time. </s></p><p n="p5.69"><s n="s1.3;p5.69">The positive sense RNA genome can be translated by host mechanisms to produce a polyprotein which is processed by proteolytic cleavage to yield structural and non structural polypeptides. </s><s n="s2.3;p5.69">These then form a 5S structural unit which associates into groups of five to form a 14S pentemer. </s><s n="s3.3;p5.69">Twelve of these associate to form a 75S empty capsids into which RNA genomes are packaged. </s></p><p n="p6.69"><s n="s1.1;p6.69">The capsid and genome are not infectious until VP0 is cleaved to VP2 and VP4 forming an infectious particle which leaves the cell by lysis. </s></p><p n="p7.69"><s n="s1.1;p7.69">BEV has been shown to be an oncolytic virus (M. Smyth, A. Symonds, S. Brazinova, J. Martin: International Journal of Molecular Medicine 10 49-53 2002) and is therefore being studies to determine its effectiveness as an anti-tumor agent. </s></p><p n="p8.69"><s n="s1.2;p8.69">When BEV was inoculated into U937 histiocytic lymphoma monocyte-like cells and ZR-75-1 human breast cancer cell lines, it was observed that the virus demonstrated a cytopathic effect around seven hours post infection. </s><s n="s2.2;p8.69">Such work described in this paper indicates that BEV should be included for cancer therapy research in the future. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Aims</head><p n="p9.69"><s n="s1.1;p9.69">The aim of the experiment is to measure the infectious progeny, intracellular viral RNA and RNA polymerase activity with the view to characterize the progress of BEV infection in BHK21 cells. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Method</head><p n="p10.69"><s n="s1.2;p10.69">The method followed for this experiment was followed exactly as stated in the laboratory manual. </s><s n="s2.2;p10.69">However, the draining of the RNA dot plot on 3MM filter paper was not performed for logistic reasons. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Results</head><div2><head rend="underlined">RNA polymerase activity</head><p n="p11.69"><s n="s1.3;p11.69">RNA synthesis in infected and control cells can be monitored by pulse - labeling with small amounts of <hi rend="sup">3</hi>H-uridine. </s><s n="s2.3;p11.69">The RNA polymerase will incorporate uridine instead of thymine into the growing mRNA chains and therefore macromolecules. </s><s n="s3.3;p11.69">The incorporation can be determined by counting large molecules on filter paper. </s></p><p n="p12.69"><s n="s1.1;p12.69">Actinomycin D was added to cell lines to inhibit transcription and therefore RNA polymerase activity allowing viral and host cell transcription to be distinguished. </s></p><p n="p13.69"><s n="s1.1;p13.69">The mock infected cells did not contain BEV DNA and therefore any RNA polymerase activity present in the mock infected cells is host RNA polymerase activity. </s></p><p n="p14.69"><s n="s1.2;p14.69">The BEV infected cells will contain both viral and host RNA as BEV mRNA contains a VPg protein covalently attached to the 5' end which causes translation to switch to cap independent translation so the genome encoded polymerase can be translated. </s><s n="s2.2;p14.69">The viral RNA polymerase will then replicate the genome using a replication intermediate. </s></p><p n="p15.69"><s n="s1.2;p15.69">The determinations of RNA polymerase activity can therefore be manipulated to remove 'background' RNA polymerase activity from the count results. </s><s n="s2.2;p15.69">If actinomycin D inhibits RNA polymerase, these values can be subtracted from the count data to give levels of actual RNA polymerase activity in normal cell conditions. </s></p><p n="p16.69"><s n="s1.1;p16.69">As the determinations of activity were performed in duplicate, average results for each cell culture can be determined. </s></p><table id="BAWE_0127e-tab.001"><head>Table 1 below demonstrates the primary data for the determination of RNA polymerase activity and average values over the time course of the experiment. </head><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p17.69"><s n="s1.1;p17.69">The percentage of BEV infected RNA polymerase activity values can be plotted graphically as demonstrated by figure 2. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">Intracellular viral RNA</head><p n="p18.69"><s n="s1.5;p18.69">The BEV genome can be used to directly translate protein therefore new mRNA need not be for translation to occur. </s><s n="s2.5;p18.69">New RNA is only produced when the BEV genome is replicated. </s><s n="s3.5;p18.69">Once the polymerase enzyme and the poly-binding proteins have been synthesized, the genome forms a replicative intermediate. </s><s n="s4.5;p18.69">Up to five replication complexes and therefore polymerase enzymes can move along the replication templates at one time which are held apart by the polyprotein. </s><s n="s5.5;p18.69">New single stranded positive sense mRNA genomes can then be used for further replication and translation or be packaged in virion particles. </s></p><p n="p19.69"><s n="s1.1;p19.69">Upon processing of the RNA dot-blot, a photographic copy of the RNA was produced as illustrated by figure . </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0127e-pic.002"><head>Figure 3, the results for the RNA dot-blot</head></figure><p n="p20.69"><s n="s1.4;p20.69">Where the film has turned dark compared to the background it indicates that RNA is present on the filter. </s><s n="s2.4;p20.69">A labeled prove became bound to the RNA which can be identified when an antibody binds to it. </s><s n="s3.4;p20.69">A second antibody carries an enzyme which generates light from a chemiluminescent substrate. </s><s n="s4.4;p20.69">The second antibody binds to the first antibody and therefore the more exposed the film is the more bound RNA is therefore present. </s></p><p n="p21.69"><s n="s1.1;p21.69">Table 2, demonstrates the results interpreted from figure 3. </s></p><table id="BAWE_0127e-tab.002"><head>Table 2, the percentage concentration estimated from the RNA dot-blot</head><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p22.69"><s n="s1.1;p22.69">The results above are expressed as percentage concentration of RNA but for purposes of graphical representation log values are more appropriate. </s></p><p n="p23.69"><s n="s1.1;p23.69">Therefore the end point dilutions for the time points are demonstrated below. </s></p><table id="BAWE_0127e-tab.003"><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p24.69"><s n="s1.1;p24.69">The logged values can now be plotted graphically as shown by figure 4. </s></p><table id="BAWE_0127e-tab.004"><head>Table 3, the percentage concentration estimated from the RNA dot-blot for data set B</head><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p25.69"><s n="s1.1;p25.69">The results above are expressed as percentage concentration of RNA but for purposes of graphical representation log values are more appropriate. </s></p><p n="p26.69"><s n="s1.1;p26.69">Therefore the end point dilution for the time points are demonstrated below. </s></p><table id="BAWE_0127e-tab.005"><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p27.69"><s n="s1.1;p27.69">The logged values can now be plotted graphically as shown by figure 4. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">Infectious virus</head><p n="p28.69"><s n="s1.2;p28.69">Upon translation of viral structural proteins and replication of the BEV genome to produce progeny genomes, BEV can begin to assemble new virion particles. </s><s n="s2.2;p28.69">The polyprotein is cleaved to Vp0, Vp3 and Vp1 which can forma 5S structural unit which upon association with other units eventually forms a 75S empty capsid. </s></p><p n="p29.69"><s n="s1.2;p29.69">BEV genome associated with the Vpg protein can be packaged into the capsid. </s><s n="s2.2;p29.69">Once Vp0 is cleaved to Vp2 and Vp4, the BEV particle becomes infectious and leaves the cell by lysis. </s></p><p n="p30.69"><s n="s1.1;p30.69">Table 4 illustrates the end point for the TCID <hi rend="sub">50</hi> assay for BEV virus. </s></p><table id="BAWE_0127e-tab.006"><head>Table 4, TCID <hi rend="sub">50</hi> assay end point results with log values</head><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p31.69"><s n="s1.1;p31.69">The titre of virus stock in TCID <hi rend="sub">50</hi> units can be calculated by multiplying the TCID <hi rend="sub">50</hi> value by twenty to convert the virus into TCID <hi rend="sub">50</hi> units/ml. </s></p><p n="p32.69"><s n="s1.1;p32.69">These values can now be plotted graphically as shown by figure 5. </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Discussion</head><div2><head rend="underlined">RNA polymerase activity</head><p n="p33.69"><s n="s1.1;p33.69">RNA polymerase activity is a measure of genome replication within a host cell, be it for the BEV genome or host genome replication. </s></p><p n="p34.69"><s n="s1.2;p34.69">Actinomycin D will inhibit transcription if the genome forms a double stranded DNA template. </s><s n="s2.2;p34.69">As BEV uses a double stranded RNA template to replicate its genome, BEV RNA polymerase will not be inhibited. </s></p><p n="p35.69"><s n="s1.2;p35.69">Figure 2 illustrates the percentage activity of RNA polymerase in BEV infected BHK21 cells during the time course of the experiment. </s><s n="s2.2;p35.69">The graph demonstrated that when BEV infected cell RNA polymerase is compared to its mock infected cell equivalent, RNA polymerase activity generally increases overtime. </s></p><p n="p36.69"><s n="s1.3;p36.69">For both BEV infected cell lines whether actinomycin D is present or absent, two peaks in RNA polymerase activity are apparent. </s><s n="s2.3;p36.69">The first peak at four hours is due to primary replication of the BEV. The lag time between initial infection and the peak at four hours is due to the need for RNA polymerase to be synthesized by BEV using host translational mechanisms such as ribosomes. </s><s n="s3.3;p36.69">The first peak is therefore smaller than the second peak, which is due to secondary replication of BEV genome; at ten hours as only initial BEV genomes will be present in the cells causing a higher percentage of RNA polymerase activity to be evident at ten hours. </s></p><p n="p37.69"><s n="s1.2;p37.69">Both BEV infected cell samples also exhibit a decrease in RNA polymerase activity at six hours into the experiment. </s><s n="s2.2;p37.69">The results obtained for the RNA polymerase activity at six hours may be anomalous because as the experiment progresses, RNA polymerase activity is likely to increase rather then decrease as more BEV genome and polyproteins become available for replication. </s></p><p n="p38.69"><s n="s1.6;p38.69">There are two possible reasons as to why this may have occurred. </s><s n="s2.6;p38.69">The first may be due to the how effective the BHK21 cells were at producing the BEV progeny. </s><s n="s3.6;p38.69">Usually, BEV production reaches a peak at around five hours into an experiment, yet figure 2 demonstrates that two cycles of genome replication and therefore two cycles of BEV growth are apparent during the time course of the experiment. </s><s n="s4.6;p38.69">As a high multiplicity of infection was used, all of the cells should have been infected initially and therefore only a single BEV growth cycle should be apparent. </s><s n="s5.6;p38.69">Therefore it is possible that some of the BHK21 cells were more efficient at replicating BEV genome than other BHK21 cells. </s><s n="s6.6;p38.69">Some BHK21 cells may have been able to replicate BEV more efficiently as they were perhaps about to divide themselves and therefore translation of proteins and abundance of nucleotides would be optimal and favor BEV replication. </s></p><p n="p39.69"><s n="s1.3;p39.69">The second reason as to why a decrease in RNA polymerase activity occurs at six hours could be due to the technique used to obtain these results. </s><s n="s2.3;p39.69">During one phase of this experiment the cell extract was spotted onto Whatman No1 filter paper circles and then washed in trichloroacetic acid and ethanol. </s><s n="s3.3;p39.69">These discs were then incubated in order to dry them therefore if these discs were not completely dry when the final stage of this procedure was carried out, it is possible that some RNA polymerase may have been washed away leading to lower than expected results. </s></p><p n="p40.69"><s n="s1.2;p40.69">From observing figure 2, there is a difference in the percentage activity of RNA polymerase between the BEV infected cells with actinomycin D present and those with actinomycin D absent. </s><s n="s2.2;p40.69">BEV infected cells with actinomycin D absent have a lower percentage RNA polymerase activity than the BEV infected cells with actinomycin D present. </s></p><p n="p41.69"><s n="s1.3;p41.69">As actinomycin D does not inhibit the viral RNA polymerase there should theoretically be little difference between the percentage activity of RNA polymerase of both the BEV infected cell lines. </s><s n="s2.3;p41.69">However, because both BEV infected cell lines follow a similar trend of a peak of RNA polymerase activity at four and ten hours and a decrease at six hours a possible difference between the data sets may again be due too the efficiency of the cells at producing BEV. It may be possible that BHK21 cells infected with BEV and actinomycin D were more efficient at translation therefore producing more RNA polymerase causing the enzymes activity to be higher in this cell line the BEV infected cells where actinomycin D was absent. </s><s n="s3.3;p41.69">The cells which were infected with BEV alone may have required BEV to stimulate translation of mRNA molecules to a higher intensity which may have taken more time to achieve and as such accounting for the lag in RNA polymerase activity and sudden increase in RNA polymerase activity seen in BEV infected cells without actinomycin D over the time course of the experiment. </s></p><p n="p42.69"><s n="s1.2;p42.69">Another possible reason for this occurrence may be due to the presence and absence of the actinomycin D. initially, the BEV infected cells with actinomycin D present have a higher percentage of RNA polymerase activity then the BEV infected cells with actinomycin D absent. </s><s n="s2.2;p42.69">It is therefore possible that the BEV infected cells where actinomycin D was present were inhibited at a faster rate, enabling the host cells energy and components to be directed towards BEV progeny synthesis and a faster and more effective rate, leading to the general higher levels of RNA polymerase activity in BEV infected cells with actinomycin D present. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">Intracellular viral RNA</head><p n="p43.69"><s n="s1.1;p43.69">Figure 4, demonstrates the log of the dilution end points of intracellular viral RNA over the time course of the experiment. </s></p><p n="p44.69"><s n="s1.2;p44.69">For data set A, there appears to be two peaks of intracellular viral RNA. One peak is at four hours and the other at eight hours with a general trend of increasing intracellular viral RNA over the period of the experiment. </s><s n="s2.2;p44.69">There may also be the beginnings of a third peak at fourteen hours although as no further data was collect this hypothesis cannot be confirmed. </s></p><p n="p45.69"><s n="s1.1;p45.69">For data set B, there appears to be three peaks of intracellular viral RNA at four hours, seven hours and fourteen hours, which is very similar to the trend exhibited by data set A for BEV intracellular RNA. </s></p><p n="p46.69"><s n="s1.3;p46.69">It is evident that BEV RNA increases during the experiment. </s><s n="s2.3;p46.69">The first peak at four hours for both data sets is possibly due to the synthesis of new RNA genomes as translation can occur directly from the BEV genome. </s><s n="s3.3;p46.69">The newly synthesized genomes can then in turn be used to translate polyprotein and replicate to produce more BEV genomes. </s></p><p n="p47.69"><s n="s1.2;p47.69">The second peak at seven hours for data set B and eight hours for data set A signifies the second cycle of genome replication. </s><s n="s2.2;p47.69">The amount of intracellular viral RNA will be higher at the eight hour peak than the four hour peak as the primary replicated genomes can now be used as templates for further genome replication. </s></p><p n="p48.69"><s n="s1.1;p48.69">A lag period is evident between both the primary genome replication event and the secondary genome replication event as proteins such as polyprotein C and the RNA polymerase enzyme need to be synthesized in order for replication to occur. </s></p><p n="p49.69"><s n="s1.3;p49.69">A dramatic decrease in the intracellular viral RNA is present at roughly seven hours for both data sets and again between eight and ten hours for data set B. Such a decrease in viral RNA may be due to the degradation of the replicative intermediate molecule which is also RNA. New BEV genomes cannot be directly synthesized from genomic RNA as no enzyme exists in the host cell or the BEV genome which can perform such a reaction. </s><s n="s2.3;p49.69">Therefore a negative sense RNA molecule is synthesized and acts as a template so viral RNA polymerase may make more BEV genomes. </s><s n="s3.3;p49.69">As the negative sense RNA is only required for genome replication, it is degraded after sufficient genome replication has been completed, effectively leading to a decrease in intracellular viral RNA as shown by figure 4. </s></p><p n="p50.69"><s n="s1.4;p50.69">The beginnings of a third peak for data set A at fourteen hours and the third peak at the same time period for data set B may be possibly due to a third cycle of genome replication, although if this were the case, the end point dilution for intracellular viral RNA should be higher as more BEV genomes would be available as templates for replication to occur. </s><s n="s2.4;p50.69">There are therefore two possible reasons why this trend has occurred. </s><s n="s3.4;p50.69">The first is that the third peak is indeed the beginnings of a third peak but as no further samples of intracellular viral RNA were taken from other time points it is unknown how the data for both sets would continue. </s><s n="s4.4;p50.69">Another possible reason is that different BHK21 cells were able to replicate the BEV genomes at a more efficient rate and the possible beginnings of a third genome replication cycle at fourteen hours may be due to the inefficient cells beginning a delayed cycle of genome replication. </s></p><p n="p51.69"><s n="s1.3;p51.69">It is evident from observing figure 4 that intracellular viral RNA levels for data set B is, on average, higher than those for data set A. The cells sampled to provide data set B may have been more efficient at the replication of the BEV genome, possibly as some BHK21 cells infected with BEV were more efficient at translation. </s><s n="s2.3;p51.69">Therefore more RNA polymerase enzymes and polyproteins could be produced, enabling the replication intermediate of the genome to be produced at a higher efficiency hence causing intracellular viral RNA levels to increase. </s><s n="s3.3;p51.69">These cells may have also contained higher levels of nucleotides important for the replication of the genome enabling the process to occur more efficiently therefore producing more intracellular RNA at a faster rate. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">Infectious virus</head><p n="p52.69"><s n="s1.1;p52.69">Figure 5 demonstrates the log of the TCID <hi rend="sub">50</hi> titres of BEV infectious virus over the time course of the experiment. </s></p><p n="p53.69"><s n="s1.1;p53.69">For data set A, there appears to be two peaks of infectious virus, one at eight hours and another at eighteen hours with a general trend of increasing amounts of infectious virus over the time course of the experiment. </s></p><p n="p54.69"><s n="s1.2;p54.69">Data set B follows a similar pattern although only two peaks of infectious virus, one at four hours and another at seven hours are apparent. </s><s n="s2.2;p54.69">For the remaining eleven hours of the experiment the titre of infectious virus decreases to zero. </s></p><p n="p55.69"><s n="s1.2;p55.69">The peaks in infectious virus demonstrate that the BHK21 cells have enabled BEV to replicate and produce infectious progeny. </s><s n="s2.2;p55.69">Both data sets show peaks in infectious virus at seven to eight hours at these time points and therefore BEV has successfully translated structural proteins to produce empty capsids and replicated its RNA genome enabling infectious progeny to be produced. </s></p><p n="p56.69"><s n="s1.2;p56.69">After this time period data set A shows further increases in infectious virus. </s><s n="s2.2;p56.69">BEV produces a single step growth curve so further increases in infectious progeny could be due to anomalous results. </s></p><p n="p57.69"><s n="s1.3;p57.69">I believe that the data value for eighteen hours for data set A is anomalous as it is unlikely that a high proportion of the BHK21 cells were so inefficient at producing BEV progeny that infectious virus levels peaked at eighteen hours. </s><s n="s2.3;p57.69">An initial high multiplicity of infection would have prevented a secondary infection wave of BEV into uninfected cells to produce a two step growth curve. </s><s n="s3.3;p57.69">As such, a possible reason as to why this result is so high may be due to contamination from another virus causing the infectious virus levels to become very high or due to error in determining the TCID <hi rend="sub">50</hi> value which was open to individual interpretation and therefore subjected to miscalculation leading to a higher than expected result. </s></p><p n="p58.69"><s n="s1.3;p58.69">As figures two and four have both shown secondary peaks for RNA polymerase activity and intracellular RNA respectively, a conclusion can be drawn that some of the BHK21 cells were better at producing virus. </s><s n="s2.3;p58.69">An initial high multiplicity of infection would have prevented viral progeny infecting current uninfected cells. </s><s n="s3.3;p58.69">As such, the more efficient BHK21 cells produced viral progeny around the seven to eight hours time points and the inefficient BHK21 cells produced viral progeny at lower levels from eight to fourteen hours with a dramatic increase at eighteen hours. </s></p><p n="p59.69"><s n="s1.3;p59.69">For data set B a similar pattern can be observed on figure 5. </s><s n="s2.3;p59.69">Efficient infectious BEV producing cells were lysed at even hours. </s><s n="s3.3;p59.69">Less efficient cells then produced infectious BEV for six hours until all cells were lysed at eighteen hours. </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Conclusion</head><p n="p60.69"><s n="s1.2;p60.69">Figures 2, 4 and 5 demonstrate the lifecycle of Bovine Enterovirus. </s><s n="s2.2;p60.69">From observing these graphs some conclusions can be drawn concerning the BEV lifecycle. </s></p><p n="p61.69"><s n="s1.4;p61.69">Between zero and one hours after infection, BEV attaches and enters the host cell. </s><s n="s2.4;p61.69">This phase is known as the absorption and penetration phase. </s><s n="s3.4;p61.69">During these time points, little RNA polymerase activity, intracellular viral RNA and no infectious progeny are present. </s><s n="s4.4;p61.69">As intracellular viral RNA begins to increase after one hour into infection, it can be assumed that these phases last roughly an hour long. </s></p><p n="p62.69"><s n="s1.3;p62.69">There is a time lag between the presence of intracellular viral RNA and the first peak of RNA polymerase activity at four hours as demonstrated by figures 4 and 2 respectively. </s><s n="s2.3;p62.69">At approximately four hours, BEV has penetrated the cell and has undergone translation using host cellular components to produce the genome encoded RNA polymerase enzyme and the polyproteins required for effective replication. </s><s n="s3.3;p62.69">As such, a peak of intracellular viral RNA and RNA polymerase activity at four hours signifies the initial cycle of BEV genome replication. </s></p><p n="p63.69"><s n="s1.2;p63.69">Figure 2 demonstrates a second peak in RNA polymerase activity around ten hours into the infection of BHK21 cells but figures 4 and 5 do not demonstrate corresponding peaks at this time period. </s><s n="s2.2;p63.69">A possible reason as to why a conflicting result may have occurred is also a possible limitation and therefore source of error for the experiment which will be discussed shortly. </s></p><p n="p64.69"><s n="s1.3;p64.69">Between four and six hours the amount of intracellular viral RNA decreases within the cells and corresponds to an increase in infectious virus as demonstrated by figure 5. </s><s n="s2.3;p64.69">Therefore between four and six hours, the newly synthesized BEV genomes are packaged into empty capsids formed from viral structural proteins translated previously. </s><s n="s3.3;p64.69">This would correspond to a decrease in intracellular viral RNA as it would become contained in the capsid which would mature to form infectious progeny. </s></p><p n="p65.69"><s n="s1.1;p65.69">After six hours into the infection, the BHK21 cells will lyse and release the infectious progeny into the surrounding lysate. </s></p><p n="p66.69"><s n="s1.4;p66.69">Figure 4 demonstrates a second peak of intracellular RNA is present at seven hours for data set B and eight hours for data set A. A possible explanation for this occurrence is that some BHK21 cells are more efficient at producing BEV progeny and therefore infectious progeny will peak at seven to eight hours for most of the BHK21 cells. </s><s n="s2.4;p66.69">The third peak of intracellular viral RNA at ten hours into infection is due to the inefficient BHK21 cells finally enabling BEV genomic replication to occur. </s><s n="s3.4;p66.69">This explanation corresponds to the data demonstrated by figure 5. </s><s n="s4.4;p66.69">Most of the infectious progeny are released at seven to eight hours into the experiment but infectious virus is still present up to fourteen hours into the experiment for both data sets A and B. As such, although most of the BHK21 cells will be efficient at producing BEV progeny, those which are not will continue to produce infectious progeny releasing them steadily for the remaining time course of the experiment until all the cells are lysed. </s></p><p n="p67.69"><s n="s1.5;p67.69">A possible reason as to why a second peak of RNA polymerase activity is evident at ten hours, the value for TCID <hi rend="sub">50</hi> titers at eighteen hours for data set A and a major limitation of the experiment is that different cell lines were used for each of the sampling procedures. </s><s n="s2.5;p67.69">Due to time limitations, the experiment was unable to run continuously over an eighteen hour period using the same batch of BHK21 cells. </s><s n="s3.5;p67.69">As such, the RNA polymerase activity, intracellular viral RNA and infectious virus data were collected on different days from different batches of BHK21 cells. </s><s n="s4.5;p67.69">This in itself will produce errors in terms of the similarity of the BHK21 cells. </s><s n="s5.5;p67.69">The cells may have been at different stages of growth, some may have been more able to grow and obtain energy from the surrounding medium at a more efficient rate and possible contamination with other viruses may have occurred. </s></p><p n="p68.69"><s n="s1.2;p68.69">If this investigation were to be repeated, ideally all data samples should be collected during the same time frame to prevent discontinuity between the BHK21 cells. </s><s n="s2.2;p68.69">If such a procedure is difficult, the same BHK21 cells should be used in the remainder of the experiment. </s></p><p n="p69.69"><s n="s1.5;p69.69">Another possible source of error in the experiment is that the RNA polymerase activity for BEV in BHK21 cells was not sampled for longer. </s><s n="s2.5;p69.69">Although this would have been logistically difficult within the time frame of the experimental days, such data may have helped to explain the second peaks at eight hours for intracellular viral RNA for both data sets. </s><s n="s3.5;p69.69">A further source of error is that the TCID <hi rend="sub">50</hi> of infectious virus and the data for intracellular RNA was not carried out in duplicate. </s><s n="s4.5;p69.69">As such, any anomalous results will not be accounted for as no averages will be taken. </s><s n="s5.5;p69.69">Therefore if the experiment were to be repeated, all procedures should be ideally be carried out in duplicate. </s></p></div1></body><back/></text></TEI.2>
