<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_0129d" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Was it racism or economic factors that caused the enslavement of Africans in colonial North America?</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">The document has a title page which contains:
document title
title part</note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">Language used in quote: <foreign id="English">English</foreign></note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">deleted: page numbers
deleted: WORD COUNT: 2,061
</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">1</p><p n="date">2005-01</p><p n="module title">North America: Themes and Problems</p><p n="module code">AM102</p><p n="genre family">Essay</p><p n="discipline">Comparative American Studies</p><p n="disciplinary group">AH</p><p n="grade">D</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">2063</p><p n="number of s-units">71</p><p n="number of p">18</p><p n="number of tables">0</p><p n="number of figures">0</p><p n="number of block quotes">1</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">0</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">0</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">29.1</p><p n="average s-units per p">3.9</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">f</p><p n="year of birth">1986</p><p n="first language">English</p><p n="education">UKA</p><p n="course">Comparative American Studies</p><p n="student ID">0129</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><docTitle><titlePart rend="underlined bold">Was it racism or economic factors that caused the enslavement of Africans in colonial North America? </titlePart></docTitle><titlePart rend="underlined bold">Term 2 - January 2005</titlePart><titlePart><name type="student name"/></titlePart><docTitle><titlePart rend="underlined bold">Was it racism or economic factors that caused the enslavement of Africans in colonial North America? </titlePart></docTitle></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="section"><p n="p1.18"><s n="s1.1;p1.18">The racial and economic factors, which were the principal contributors to the enslavement of Africans in colonial North America, are intertwined in a complex relationship as they overlap considerably. </s></p><p n="p2.18"><s n="s1.2;p2.18">The function of racism in enslavement <hi rend="italic">alone</hi> is an overtly intricate concept, as highlighted by the widespread and multifaceted debate regarding the 'chicken-or-egg'<ref target="BAWE_0129d-ftnote.001"/> problem of which came first: racism or slavery. </s><s n="s2.2;p2.18">This has been a hotly contested topic on which there has been such extensive indecision and disagreement that a firm conclusion is unlikely to be arrived at. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0129d-ftnote.001"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Carl N. Degler, 'Slavery and the Genesis of American Race Prejudice', in Betty Wood, <hi rend="italic">The Origins of American Slaver: Freedom and Bondage in the English Colonies</hi> (New York, 1997), p.42 </s></p></note><p n="p3.18"><s n="s1.1;p3.18">Consequently, this has played a role in the rise of enquiries concerning the precise <hi rend="italic">dating</hi> of the institution of slavery, which embodies two vastly conflicting theories: firstly, that Africans were brought to North America <hi rend="italic">as</hi> slaves, owing to <hi rend="italic">existing</hi> economic strife and <hi rend="italic">preconceived</hi> opinions on race, and secondly, that it was actually a <hi rend="italic">result</hi> of economic and racial factors transpiring <hi rend="italic">subsequent</hi> to the initial arrival of Africans that slavery was established. </s></p><p n="p4.18"><s n="s1.1;p4.18">These two separate debates are central to discussions on the enslavement of Africans in colonial North America, in relation to its racial and economic origins, and thus in ascertaining the most significant causal factor. </s></p><p n="p5.18"><s n="s1.2;p5.18">Economic factors were of indisputable importance in the enslavement of Africans in colonial North America. </s><s n="s2.2;p5.18">'Progressivism'<ref target="BAWE_0129d-ftnote.002"/>, which emphasises an economic stance regarding enslavement, has been the dominant force in American historiography since the turn of the century, alluding to slavery as an 'economic institution'<ref target="BAWE_0129d-ftnote.003"/>, which was 'created primarily for economic reasons.'<ref target="BAWE_0129d-ftnote.004"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0129d-ftnote.002"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Wood, <hi rend="italic">The Origins of American Slavery</hi>, p.v </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0129d-ftnote.003"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Eric Williams, 'Capitalism and Slavery', in Wood, <hi rend="italic">The Origins of American Slavery,</hi> p.5 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0129d-ftnote.004"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Wood, <hi rend="italic">The Origins of American Slavery,</hi> p.viii </s></p></note><p n="p6.18"><s n="s1.5;p6.18">As stressed by Winthrop D. Jordan, 'it may be taken as given that there would have been no enslavement without economic need." </s><ref target="BAWE_0129d-ftnote.005"/><s n="s2.5;p6.18">Such economic necessities in North America included, most importantly, an overwhelming requirement for agricultural labour as a result of the 'high land-to-population ratio." </s><ref target="BAWE_0129d-ftnote.006"/><s n="s3.5;p6.18">This was specifically true of the plantations of the underpopulated colonies that, in a quest to maximise their profits, desired to take advantage of the opportunities offered by escalating European demand. </s><s n="s4.5;p6.18">They 'called for some sort of bound, controlled labour'<ref target="BAWE_0129d-ftnote.007"/>, which was created by enslaving Africans. </s><s n="s5.5;p6.18">Peter Kolchin argues firmly that 'shortage of labour <hi rend="italic">was</hi> the most basic element'<ref target="BAWE_0129d-ftnote.008"/>, alluding to the utmost significance of economic strains as a primary factor for enslavement. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0129d-ftnote.005"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Winthrop D. Jordan, <hi rend="italic">White Over Black.</hi> </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1"><hi rend="italic">American Attitudes Toward the Negro, 1550-1812</hi> (United States, 1968), p.91 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0129d-ftnote.006"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Peter Kolchin, <hi rend="italic">Unfree Labour.</hi> </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1"><hi rend="italic">American Slavery and Russian Serfdom</hi> (Cambridge, Massachusetts, 1987), p.17 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0129d-ftnote.007"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Jordan, <hi rend="italic">White Over Black,</hi> p.61 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0129d-ftnote.008"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Kolchin, <hi rend="italic">Unfree Labour,</hi> p. 19 </s></p></note><p n="p7.18"><s n="s1.6;p7.18">The familiarity of Africans with the rice crop, as cultivated in their homeland, was of significant interest to North American colonists who wanted to establish it as a staple crop. </s><s n="s2.6;p7.18">The prior knowledge that Africans bought with them across the Atlantic would aid the economy and thus was an additional incitement for their enslavement. </s><s n="s3.6;p7.18">'This would help to explain the joint growth of slavery and rice production in South Carolina between the 1690s and 1720s'<ref target="BAWE_0129d-ftnote.009"/>, and therefore stands out as an important economic factor of enslavement. </s><s n="s4.6;p7.18">However, it must be taken into account, as has been noted by Philip D. Morgan<ref target="BAWE_0129d-ftnote.010"/>, that the Africans supplied to South Carolina were predominantly males from coastal regions where rice was not grown, and women primarily undertook the cultivation where it was. </s><s n="s5.6;p7.18">Therefore, the economic advantage of having Africans with existing skills of rice cultivation could <hi rend="italic">not</hi> have been a leading impetus for enslavement. </s><s n="s6.6;p7.18">However, if it were the case that such skills were versatile and could be transferred to another area of cultivation, such as cotton or tobacco, then African slaves would still be economically advantageous. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0129d-ftnote.009"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Kenneth Morgan, <hi rend="italic">Slavery and Servitude in North America, 1607-1800</hi> (Edinburgh, 2000), p.42 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0129d-ftnote.010"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Philip D. Morgan, cited in Morgan, <hi rend="italic">Slavery and Servitude</hi>, p.42 </s></p></note><p n="p8.18"><s n="s1.7;p8.18">On the other hand, 'the Atlantic slave trade cannot be explained by the demand for these crops'<ref target="BAWE_0129d-ftnote.011"/>, cotton and tobacco, thus it was not these economic factors <hi rend="italic">alone</hi> that caused the enslavement of Africans. </s><s n="s2.7;p8.18">The importation of eighty percent of all slaves was carried out between 1451 and 1810.<ref target="BAWE_0129d-ftnote.012"/> However, the early nineteenth century was a period in which the cotton industry was still in its very early years of production, consequently not requiring the vast numbers of slave workers previously brought into North America. </s><s n="s3.7;p8.18">This is particularly true of New England where there did not exist a staple crop that required such an economic need and 'compelling demand for Negroes'<ref target="BAWE_0129d-ftnote.013"/>, yet, as early as 1638, there existed a slave trade. </s><s n="s4.7;p8.18">Even though this has been viewed as merely 'weakly rooted'<ref target="BAWE_0129d-ftnote.014"/>, slavery was not <hi rend="italic">at all</hi> essential for the colony. </s><s n="s5.7;p8.18">In an explicit contrast, in Virginia and Maryland slavery became a 'vitally important institution'<ref target="BAWE_0129d-ftnote.015"/>, once legally established in 1660 following the initial arrival of Africans as indentured servants in 1619, signifying regional variation across the colonies of North America. </s><s n="s6.7;p8.18">A further example of regional disparity is seen in the fact that 'slavery became the backbone of the economies in some colonies while in others it made little or no advance." </s><ref target="BAWE_0129d-ftnote.016"/><s n="s7.7;p8.18">It can be inferred, therefore, that slavery existed in some areas where there had <hi rend="italic">not</hi> been an overwhelmingly economic motive for enslavement. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0129d-ftnote.011"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Robert William Fogel and Stanley L. Engerman, <hi rend="italic">Time on the Cross.</hi> </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1"><hi rend="italic">The Economics of American Negro Slavery</hi> (London, 1974), p.15 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0129d-ftnote.012"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Fogel and Engerman, <hi rend="italic">Time on the Cross,</hi> p.15 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0129d-ftnote.013"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Jordan, <hi rend="italic">White Over Black,</hi> p.66 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0129d-ftnote.014"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Jordan, <hi rend="italic">White Over Black,</hi> p.66 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0129d-ftnote.015"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Jordan, <hi rend="italic">White Over Black,</hi> p.72 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0129d-ftnote.016"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Kolchin, <hi rend="italic">Unfree Labour</hi>, p.20 </s></p></note><p n="p9.18"><s n="s1.6;p9.18">In comparison to the exigencies of the cotton crop, there was ever-increasing demand for tobacco and hence for labour, which was to be infinitely available, 'cheap but not temporary, mobile but not independent, and tireless rather than skilled." </s><ref target="BAWE_0129d-ftnote.017"/><s n="s2.6;p9.18">This contributed to the enslavement of Africans who adequately fulfilled such criteria, although slaves on tobacco plantations only accounted for a 'miniscule fraction of the six million slave imports during the same period." </s><ref target="BAWE_0129d-ftnote.018"/><s n="s3.6;p9.18">Therefore, it can be surmised that they were being <hi rend="italic">distributed</hi> elsewhere. </s><s n="s4.6;p9.18">Nevertheless, economic motives still prevailed as it was the sugar plantations, producing the most popular consumable in Europe from colonial America, which soaked up between sixty and seventy percent<ref target="BAWE_0129d-ftnote.019"/> of Africans brought into America. </s><s n="s5.6;p9.18">This underlines the role of major features of the economy in enslavement. </s><s n="s6.6;p9.18">It is apparent that, having begun to move away from the declining labour of Indians and white indentured servants, 'the eventual solution to the supply for North American plantations lay via the Atlantic slave trade'<ref target="BAWE_0129d-ftnote.020"/>, which has been estimated as accounting for the trafficking of between twelve million<ref target="BAWE_0129d-ftnote.021"/> and fifteen million Africans. <ref target="BAWE_0129d-ftnote.022"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0129d-ftnote.017"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Jordan, <hi rend="italic">White Over Black,</hi> p.72 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0129d-ftnote.018"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Fogel and Engerman, <hi rend="italic">Time on the Cross,</hi> p.15 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0129d-ftnote.019"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Fogel and Engerman, <hi rend="italic">Time on the Cross,</hi> p.16 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0129d-ftnote.020"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Morgan, <hi rend="italic">Slavery and Servitude</hi>, p.29 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0129d-ftnote.021"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Morgan, <hi rend="italic">Slavery and Servitude</hi>, p.29 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0129d-ftnote.022"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">John White, <hi rend="italic">Slavery in the American South</hi> (Bristol, 1970), p.8 </s></p></note><p n="p10.18"><s n="s1.7;p10.18">The relationship between <hi rend="italic">capitalism</hi> in the economy and slavery is 'complicated'<ref target="BAWE_0129d-ftnote.023"/> yet, nonetheless, draws attention to a further economic factors contributing to enslavement. </s><s n="s2.7;p10.18">Even though the view that 'the roots of slavery are found in capitalism'<ref target="BAWE_0129d-ftnote.024"/> has been contended as being somewhat <hi rend="italic">extreme</hi>, it is undeniable that 'the Negro played a major role in the development of the New World and in the growth of commercial capitalism." </s><ref target="BAWE_0129d-ftnote.025"/><s n="s3.7;p10.18">It was the expanding desire of colonies in North America to accumulate wealth through the exportation of staples, which required the labour of ever-more people, namely Africans. </s><s n="s4.7;p10.18">Their diversity also enabled these slaves to be used in industrial work. </s><s n="s5.7;p10.18">The development of North America with the export of manufactured goods, in the nineteenth century, was primarily owing to the toils of enslaved Africans. </s><s n="s6.7;p10.18">George Fredrickson<ref target="BAWE_0129d-ftnote.026"/> has criticised Robert Fogel and Stanley Engerman<ref target="BAWE_0129d-ftnote.027"/> for their 'controversial claim that slaves were willing collaborators in this economic miracle as well as beneficiaries of it'<ref target="BAWE_0129d-ftnote.028"/>, for which there is a lack of evidence. </s><s n="s7.7;p10.18">It has been suggested that 'Negroes were relatively helpless in the face of European aggressiveness and technology'<ref target="BAWE_0129d-ftnote.029"/>, and vulnerable to the economic policies of North American colonists. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0129d-ftnote.023"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">James Oakes, <hi rend="italic">The Ruling Race.</hi> </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1"><hi rend="italic">A History of American Slaveholders</hi> (New York, 1998), p.xii </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0129d-ftnote.024"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Williams, 'Capitalism and Slavery', in Wood, <hi rend="italic">The Origins of American Slavery,</hi> p.3 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0129d-ftnote.025"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">White, <hi rend="italic">Slavery in the American South</hi>, p.8 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0129d-ftnote.026"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">George Fredrickson, <hi rend="italic">The Arrogance of Race.</hi> </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1"><hi rend="italic">Historical Perspectives on Slavery, Racism and Social Inequality</hi> (New England, 1988) </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0129d-ftnote.027"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Fogel and Engerman, <hi rend="italic">Time on the Cross.</hi> </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0129d-ftnote.028"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Fredrickson, <hi rend="italic">The Arrogance of</hi> Race, p.115 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0129d-ftnote.029"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Jordan, <hi rend="italic">White Over Black,</hi> p.91 </s></p></note><p n="p11.18"><s n="s1.1;p11.18">Thus economic factors, comprising of labour requirements, managing demand, diverse transferable skills, and increased capital, reflect that 'American Negro slavery was created for expressly economic purposes.'<ref target="BAWE_0129d-ftnote.030"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0129d-ftnote.030"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Wood, <hi rend="italic">The Origins of American</hi> Slavery, p.vi </s></p></note><p n="p12.18"><s n="s1.10;p12.18">On the other hand, the controversy over the origins of slavery has 'elicited much new consideration'<ref target="BAWE_0129d-ftnote.031"/> over the last half a century, as the acceptability of contemporary racism provoked concerns. </s><s n="s2.10;p12.18">The development involved the incorporation of a new element into the debate on slavery, where 'the burden of proof rests with... those who suggest racial rather than economic foundations." </s><ref target="BAWE_0129d-ftnote.032"/><s n="s3.10;p12.18">This added a complex dimension and a 'racial twist... to what is basically an economic phenomenon." </s><ref target="BAWE_0129d-ftnote.033"/><s n="s4.10;p12.18">It was Carl Degler whom first challenged this orthodox economic interpretation of slavery. </s><s n="s5.10;p12.18">He suggested that 'the American idea of the racial inferiority of Africans has roots deeper than the labour needs of early colonists'<ref target="BAWE_0129d-ftnote.034"/>, thus racism is seen as having stood above economic factors in the enslavement of Africans. </s><s n="s6.10;p12.18">This theory carries with it his proposal that racial prejudice and discrimination came <hi rend="italic">before</hi> slavery, hence initiating (and outliving) it, and therefore was not a <hi rend="italic">product</hi> of it. </s><s n="s7.10;p12.18">The Handlins' strongly argue the case of the latter, citing that chattel slavery was established long after the original arrival of Africans who were, at first, indentured servants. </s><s n="s8.10;p12.18">This ensued in heated conflicts with Degler, who maintained 'that racism existed from the moment that blacks stepped ashore." </s><ref target="BAWE_0129d-ftnote.035"/><s n="s9.10;p12.18">On the other hand, Jordan takes the safer middle-road with his view that 'the two probably evolved at the same time'<ref target="BAWE_0129d-ftnote.036"/> by generating one another, whilst J. H. </s><s n="s10.10;p12.18">Plumb asserts that 'racism is merely a justification for slavery'<ref target="BAWE_0129d-ftnote.037"/> although, overall, it is a controversy that remains universally unresolved. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0129d-ftnote.031"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Winthrop D. Jordan, 'Modern Tensions and the Origins of American Slavery', in Wood, <hi rend="italic">The Origins of American Slavery,</hi> p.67 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0129d-ftnote.032"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Wood, <hi rend="italic">The Origins of American Slavery,</hi> p.x </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0129d-ftnote.033"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Williams, 'Capitalism and Slavery', in Wood, <hi rend="italic">The Origins of American Slavery,</hi> p.5 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0129d-ftnote.034"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Degler, 'Slavery', in Wood, <hi rend="italic">The Origins of American Slavery,</hi> p.41 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0129d-ftnote.035"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Morgan, <hi rend="italic">Slavery and Servitude</hi>, p.35 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0129d-ftnote.036"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Jordan, 'Modern Tensions', in Wood, <hi rend="italic">The Origins of American Slavery,</hi> p.68 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0129d-ftnote.037"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">J. H. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">Plumb, 'Does Race Prejudice Cause Slavery?', in Wood, <hi rend="italic">The Origins of American Slavery,</hi> p.151 </s></p></note><p n="p13.18"><s n="s1.3;p13.18">'Something about Negroes... set them apart for drastic exploitation, oppression, and degradation." </s><ref target="BAWE_0129d-ftnote.038"/><s n="s2.3;p13.18">It is evident that Africans were rendered different from Europeans due to their differences such as their physiognomy, level of civilisation, religion, strange language, and skin colour. </s><s n="s3.3;p13.18">This caused exhibitions of racism against Africans. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0129d-ftnote.038"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Jordan, <hi rend="italic">White Over Black,</hi> p.85-6 </s></p></note><p n="p14.18"><s n="s1.5;p14.18">Englishmen were predisposed to stereotype blackness with disdainful and negative connotations such as Satan, savagery, barbarism, magic and heathenism, even prior to their first contact with Africans. </s><s n="s2.5;p14.18">They carried these attitudes across the Atlantic, which then combined with early examples of 'ethnocentrism and xenophobia'<ref target="BAWE_0129d-ftnote.039"/> and 'invited pejorative feelings'<ref target="BAWE_0129d-ftnote.040"/> towards Africans. </s><s n="s3.5;p14.18">Therefore, when the <hi rend="italic">already</hi> stigmatised Africans arrived there, they were 'treated as somehow deserving a life and status different from English and other European settlers." </s><ref target="BAWE_0129d-ftnote.041"/><s n="s4.5;p14.18">This instigated the debasement of Africans as slaves in an attempt to control, subordinate and dehumanise them, which is a highly illuminating example of racism. </s><s n="s5.5;p14.18">It is inferable that, due to the <hi rend="italic">pre-existing</hi> antipathy of Englishmen towards Africans, 'it would seem logical that racial prejudice preceded and probably caused the enslavement of the Negro'<ref target="BAWE_0129d-ftnote.042"/>, which explicitly underlines the function of racism. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0129d-ftnote.039"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Morgan, <hi rend="italic">Slavery and Servitude</hi>, p.31 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0129d-ftnote.040"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Jordan, <hi rend="italic">White Over Black,</hi> p.97 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0129d-ftnote.041"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Jordan, <hi rend="italic">White Over Black,</hi> p.44 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0129d-ftnote.042"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Wood, <hi rend="italic">The Origins of American Slavery,</hi> p.x </s></p></note><p n="p15.18"><s n="s1.3;p15.18">Also, 'various passages in Scripture condoned the existence of slave societies'<ref target="BAWE_0129d-ftnote.043"/> and, as the practice had already been widely accepted since ancient times, North American colonists had little moral qualms when enslaving Africans. </s><s n="s2.3;p15.18">Furthermore, their lack of moral consciousness was a result of the accepted belief in the inferiority of Africans because of their skin-colour. </s><s n="s3.3;p15.18">There was undoubtedly a 'causal connection between the institution of slavery and the colour prejudice of Americans'<ref target="BAWE_0129d-ftnote.044"/>, which highlights the role of racism in enslavement; that 'American slavery was racial slavery.'<ref target="BAWE_0129d-ftnote.045"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0129d-ftnote.043"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Morgan, <hi rend="italic">Slavery and Servitude</hi>, p.42 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0129d-ftnote.044"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Degler, 'Slavery', in Wood, <hi rend="italic">The Origins of American Slavery,</hi> p.42 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0129d-ftnote.045"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">White, <hi rend="italic">Slavery in the American South</hi>, p.21 </s></p></note><p n="p16.18"><s n="s1.4;p16.18">On the other hand, Kenneth Stampp has 'noted that there was no prejudice or racial discrimination against the African before he was enslaved." </s><ref target="BAWE_0129d-ftnote.046"/><s n="s2.4;p16.18">Such a surmise is comparable to the Handlins', which harps back to the unsolved chicken-or-egg dispute of which came first. </s><s n="s3.4;p16.18">In relation to this, an important question has been put forward: 'Does the mere fact that racism existed prior to slavery prove that racism caused the institution?" </s><ref target="BAWE_0129d-ftnote.047"/><s n="s4.4;p16.18">The implication is that, even though racism existed, it may not have necessarily been the only influence on the enslavement of Africans, although it was undoubtedly a contributory factor of enslavement: </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0129d-ftnote.046"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Kenneth Stampp, cited in Wood, <hi rend="italic">The Origins of American Slavery,</hi> p.viii </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0129d-ftnote.047"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Plumb, 'Does Race Prejudice Cause Slavery?', in Wood, <hi rend="italic">The Origins of American Slavery,</hi> p.151 </s></p></note><quote lang="English">'It is difficult to believe that racial prejudice did not play a significant part in enslaving Africans... But to suggest that a widespread number of those purchased slaves were necessarily imbued with a deep-seated racial prejudice, and that this was their predominant motive for acquiring enslaved black workers, cannot be proven.'<ref target="BAWE_0129d-ftnote.048"/></quote><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0129d-ftnote.048"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Morgan, <hi rend="italic">Slavery and Servitude</hi>, p.35 </s></p></note><p n="p17.18"><s n="s1.3;p17.18">The many different and conflicting views postulated regarding the role of racism as a factor must be taken into equal consideration, including the opinion that 'racism does not create slavery. </s><s n="s2.3;p17.18">It is an excuse for it." </s><ref target="BAWE_0129d-ftnote.049"/><s n="s3.3;p17.18">This proposes that racism played its role as a <hi rend="italic">justification</hi> for slavery as opposed to being directly involved in its formation, implying that there were other factors that caused it, which includes economic ones. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0129d-ftnote.049"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Plumb, 'Does Race Prejudice Cause Slavery?', in Wood, <hi rend="italic">The Origins of American Slavery,</hi> p.151 </s></p></note><p n="p18.18"><s n="s1.4;p18.18">To conclude, there was a multiplicity of factors, both economic and racial, which led to the enslavement of Africans in colonial North America. </s><s n="s2.4;p18.18">Many historians argue for either one or the other, such as Williams who firmly states that 'the reason was economic not racial'<ref target="BAWE_0129d-ftnote.050"/> and Degler who asserts that 'the racial inferiority of Africans'<ref target="BAWE_0129d-ftnote.051"/> caused their enslavement. </s><s n="s3.4;p18.18">However, it can be contended that it was neither of these factors <hi rend="italic">in isolation</hi> but a <hi rend="italic">combination</hi> of both of them that led to the enslavement of Africans. </s><s n="s4.4;p18.18">Although it was largely economic requirements that instigated the need for extra plantation workers, it was only as a result of already engrained racial prejudices regarding Africans that it was they, in particular, whom were considered appropriate candidates as slaves for the colonies of North America. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0129d-ftnote.050"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Williams, 'Capitalism and Slavery', in Wood, <hi rend="italic">The Origins of American Slavery,</hi> p.16 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0129d-ftnote.051"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Degler, 'Slavery', in Wood, <hi rend="italic">The Origins of American Slavery,</hi> p.41 </s></p></note></div1></body><back/></text></TEI.2>
