<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_0129a" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Assess the similarities and differences between the early eng settlements of North America and those of the Spanish colonisers.</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">The document has a title page which contains:
document title
title part</note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">Language used in quote: <foreign id="English">English</foreign></note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">deleted: page numbers
deleted: WORD COUNT: 2,181 
</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">1</p><p n="date">2004-11</p><p n="module title">North America: Themes and Problems</p><p n="module code">AM102</p><p n="genre family">Essay</p><p n="discipline">Comparative American Studies</p><p n="disciplinary group">AH</p><p n="grade">M</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">2194</p><p n="number of s-units">75</p><p n="number of p">17</p><p n="number of tables">0</p><p n="number of figures">0</p><p n="number of block quotes">1</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">0</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">0</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">29.3</p><p n="average s-units per p">4.4</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">f</p><p n="year of birth">1986</p><p n="first language">English</p><p n="education">UKA</p><p n="course">Comparative American Studies</p><p n="student ID">0129</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><docTitle><titlePart rend="underlined bold">Assess the similarities and differences between the early English settlements of North America and those of the Spanish colonisers. </titlePart></docTitle><titlePart rend="underlined bold">November 2004. </titlePart><titlePart><name type="student name"/></titlePart><docTitle><titlePart rend="underlined bold">Assess the similarities and differences between the early English settlements of North America and those of the Spanish colonisers. </titlePart></docTitle></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="section"><p n="p1.17"><s n="s1.6;p1.17">The voyage of Christopher Columbus, in the late fifteenth century, motivated subsequent European explorations of North America, for example John Cabot of England in 1497, and Juan Ponce de Leon of Spain in 1513. </s><s n="s2.6;p1.17">Whereas the failure of Cabot's voyage led to an abandonment of exploration until the late sixteenth century, the Spanish continued to explore throughout the era. </s><s n="s3.6;p1.17">Spanish expeditions along the North American coast were led by Hernando de Soto between 1539 and 1543, and inland missions under Tristan de Luna between 1559 and 1561, then by Juan Padro between 1566 and 1581. </s><s n="s4.6;p1.17">The discovery of the <hi rend="italic">new world</hi> 'transformed Spain into a world power, the envy of other European monarchs... inevitably motivated to emulate Spain's success." </s><ref target="BAWE_0129a-ftnote.001"/><s n="s5.6;p1.17">As a result, both England and Spain founded early coastal settlements in North America in the late sixteenth century and throughout the seventeenth century. </s><s n="s6.6;p1.17">Although English and Spanish colonies each had their own distinctive 'colonial identity'<ref target="BAWE_0129a-ftnote.002"/> and 'would come to perceive themselves as distinct and different peoples'<ref target="BAWE_0129a-ftnote.003"/>, partly as a result of their motherland and characteristics of their settlements, they also exhibited some similarities. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0129a-ftnote.001"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Alan Taylor, <hi rend="italic">American Colonies.</hi> </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1"><hi rend="italic">A Penguin History of the United States</hi> (New York, 2001), p.6 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0129a-ftnote.002"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">N. Canny and A. Pagden (eds.), <hi rend="italic">Colonial Identity in the Atlantic World, 1500-1800</hi> (New Jersey, 1987), p.3 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0129a-ftnote.003"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Canny and Pagden (eds.), <hi rend="italic">Colonial Identity</hi>, p.95 </s></p></note><p n="p2.17"><s n="s1.4;p2.17">Both countries' settlements attracted migrants by offering a geographical extension of the search for employment and stability, when all opportunities in their motherland had been exhausted. </s><s n="s2.4;p2.17">On the other hand, Bailyn asserts that it is not known <hi rend="italic">how</hi> this transition came about in England, however in Spain it was because 'impoverished Andalusian farmworkers and the idle <hi rend="italic">hidalgos</hi> and tradesman of the overcrowded cities'<ref target="BAWE_0129a-ftnote.004"/> favoured overseas migration as somewhat of a escape. </s><s n="s3.4;p2.17">On the other hand, many Spaniards were 'forced to leave profitable positions and become soldiers." </s><ref target="BAWE_0129a-ftnote.005"/><s n="s4.4;p2.17">This is comparable to English convicts who were sent to North America, often as servants. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0129a-ftnote.004"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Bernard Bailyn, <hi rend="italic">The Peopling of British North America.</hi> </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1"><hi rend="italic">An Introduction</hi> (New York, 1988), p.27 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0129a-ftnote.005"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Theodore Corbett, 'Migration to a Spanish Imperial Frontier in the Seventeenth and Eighteenth Centuries: St. Augustine', <hi rend="italic">The Hispanic American Historical Review,</hi> Vol. 54, No. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">3 (August 1974), p.427 </s></p></note><p n="p3.17"><s n="s1.9;p3.17">The earliest successful Spanish settlement in North America was in Florida's capital, St. Augustine, which was established under Pedro Menendez de Aviles in 1565. </s><s n="s2.9;p3.17">Although trading outposts had already been established earlier in the century, for example in Columbia, St. Augustine's was destined to be a military outpost from where the Spanish could defend their trade routes and treasure from privateers sanctioned by the English government (until the 1604 Peace Treaty). </s><s n="s3.9;p3.17">The majority of the small Spanish population in Florida were <hi rend="italic">hidalgos</hi>, most of whom were single young men engaged in Government service. </s><s n="s4.9;p3.17">Thus, there were few families, and those that did exist were often hybrid as a result of intermarriages, with their children being identified as <hi rend="italic">mestizos.</hi> </s><s n="s5.9;p3.17">English settlements were not so complex as their 'Northern American societies saw less racial mixture." </s><ref target="BAWE_0129a-ftnote.006"/><s n="s6.9;p3.17">The complex stratification of the Spanish is further enhanced by the variations between Hispanic immigrants in St. Augustine, including divisions between <hi rend="italic">peninsulares</hi> of the Iberian Peninsula, and Spanish-American <hi rend="italic">criollo</hi>, as focused upon in Corbett's article.<ref target="BAWE_0129a-ftnote.007"/> Among the <hi rend="italic">peninsulares</hi> there were additional differences, much more intricate than those between, for example, the English and the Scottish. </s><s n="s7.9;p3.17">As a result, St. Augustine has accurately been illustrated as 'a melting pot of ethnic groups, loosely bound together by... the Spanish Crown." </s><ref target="BAWE_0129a-ftnote.008"/><s n="s8.9;p3.17">Corbett significantly observes that the source of migration to St. Augustine, during the period of 1671 to 1691, was actually from Spanish Mexico, highlighting internal migration from colonies of New Spain. </s><s n="s9.9;p3.17">English settlements also contained people derived from varying ancestries, as a result of internal movements, particularly in the middle colonies of New York and Pennsylvania. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0129a-ftnote.006"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Anthony McFarlane, <hi rend="italic">The British in the Americas 1480-1815</hi> (New York, 1992), p.182 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0129a-ftnote.007"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Corbett, 'Migration to a Spanish Imperial Frontier', p.414-430 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0129a-ftnote.008"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Corbett, 'Migration to a Spanish Imperial Frontier', p.414 </s></p></note><p n="p4.17"><s n="s1.6;p4.17">The earliest English colonists 'preferred to search for precious metals, in emulation of the Spanish conquistadores." </s><ref target="BAWE_0129a-ftnote.009"/><s n="s2.6;p4.17">However, in direct contrast to early Spanish incentives for North American colonies as military bases, the result of the three English missions to Roanoke in the 1580s, despite <hi rend="italic">initially</hi> being a military expedition, was the discovery of the value of the land for cultivation. </s><s n="s3.6;p4.17">Consequently, the English decided to establish a permanent self-sustaining settlement there and in 1587, under Sir Walter Raleigh, 'the first English families to settle in the Americas'<ref target="BAWE_0129a-ftnote.010"/> arrived at Roanoke. </s><s n="s4.6;p4.17">However, its success was minimal as it had been mysteriously abandoned by the 1590s. </s><s n="s5.6;p4.17">This differs significantly with St. Augustine, which, although being burnt down in 1586 and rebuilt, remained a permanent settlement for two hundred years. </s><s n="s6.6;p4.17">It is ironic that St. Augustine's was not originally intended as a permanent colony yet persisted as one nonetheless, despite never significantly increasing in terms of population, whereas Roanoke's <hi rend="italic">eventual</hi> overall purpose was as a lasting agricultural settlement yet it perished within a few years. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0129a-ftnote.009"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Richard Middleton, <hi rend="italic">Colonial America.</hi> </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1"><hi rend="italic">A History, 1607-1760</hi> (Oxford, 1992), p.6 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0129a-ftnote.010"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Taylor, <hi rend="italic">American Colonies,</hi> p.124 </s></p></note><p n="p5.17"><s n="s1.5;p5.17">Predominant similarities of both English and American settlements were some of the reasons for the founding of, and migration to them. </s><s n="s2.5;p5.17">Trade and profit through the exploitation of the New World were key motivational factors. </s><s n="s3.5;p5.17">This was particularly true of the English who wished to break the Spanish monopoly over North America, consequently leading them to a greater share in the American wealth. </s><s n="s4.5;p5.17">Thus internal competition and rivalry for prestige and prosperity was stimulated. </s><s n="s5.5;p5.17">However, the English were unsuccessful in their formation of the economic settlement of Jamestown, at Virginia's Chesapeake Bay in 1607, as it was built by a malarial swamp that led to the death of the majority of the migrants. </s></p><p n="p6.17"><s n="s1.2;p6.17">The principal reason for the proceeding English settlements in New England were based upon a diverse religious vision of a pure colony, as opposed to financial importance, incited by the Pilgrims in 1620, and followed by the migration of the Puritans the following decade. </s><s n="s2.2;p6.17">Unfortunately, 'New England ultimately failed as a "city upon a hill"'<ref target="BAWE_0129a-ftnote.011"/> although it sustained 'an especially diverse and complex economy'<ref target="BAWE_0129a-ftnote.012"/>, which was ultimately beneficial. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0129a-ftnote.011"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Taylor, <hi rend="italic">American Colonies</hi>, p.185 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0129a-ftnote.012"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Taylor, <hi rend="italic">American Colonies</hi>, p.186 </s></p></note><p n="p7.17"><s n="s1.5;p7.17">McFarlane distinguishes between religion in both Spanish and English settlements. </s><s n="s2.5;p7.17">Although it had initially played a similar role in the formation of both sets of settlements, it went on to adopt varying and separate roles in the social element of each. </s><s n="s3.5;p7.17">Their religious structures differ considerably in terms of relationship with political and social life. </s><s n="s4.5;p7.17">For example, 'English... colonies remained without a formal nobility, even on the small scale that the Spaniards created in their colonial realms." </s><ref target="BAWE_0129a-ftnote.013"/><s n="s5.5;p7.17">However, New England suffered fewer problems, arguably as a result of their religious attitudes and hence the establishment of a good relationship with the Native Indians. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0129a-ftnote.013"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">McFarlane, <hi rend="italic">The British in the Americas,</hi> p.182 </s></p></note><p n="p8.17"><s n="s1.2;p8.17">The pattern of migrants settling in Virginia represented the English population, mostly consisting of 'middling sorts,'<ref target="BAWE_0129a-ftnote.014"/> similarly to the predominating middle class in Spanish settlements. </s><s n="s2.2;p8.17">As in St. Augustine, many early English settlements contained few women or families, which were significant as the stable 'foundation of colonial society'.<ref target="BAWE_0129a-ftnote.015"/> The structure of New England was, in contrast to both Virginia and St. Augustine, more cohesive as 'family units of the English population were moving essentially intact'.<ref target="BAWE_0129a-ftnote.016"/> Sometimes even entire communities migrated, cited by Bailyn as being either <hi rend="italic">metropolitan</hi> (primarily from London) or <hi rend="italic">provincial</hi>, depending on the area of England from whence they came which subsequently determined where they migrated.<ref target="BAWE_0129a-ftnote.017"/> For example, indentured servitude was a 'major characteristic of the "metropolitan" migration... overwhelmingly dominant in the flows to Maryland, Pennsylvania, and Virginia'<ref target="BAWE_0129a-ftnote.018"/>, the central colonies. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0129a-ftnote.014"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Taylor, <hi rend="italic">American Colonies</hi>, p.159 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0129a-ftnote.015"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Middleton, <hi rend="italic">Colonial America,</hi> p.214 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0129a-ftnote.016"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Bailyn, <hi rend="italic">The Peopling of British North America,</hi> p.14 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0129a-ftnote.017"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Bailyn, <hi rend="italic">The Peopling of British North America,</hi> p.15 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0129a-ftnote.018"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Bernard Bailyn, <hi rend="italic">Voyagers to the West: emigration from Britain to America on the Eve of the Revolution</hi> (London, 1987), p.208 </s></p></note><p n="p9.17"><s n="s1.11;p9.17">Maryland, founded by the English in Virginia in 1634, was a relatively successful settlement as they accommodated the Native Indians to a greater extent than the English in the Chesapeake, who had not formed a good relationship with them. </s><s n="s2.11;p9.17">However, both England and Spain westernised the Indians, with alcohol, guns and ammunition. </s><s n="s3.11;p9.17">Moreover, both were notorious for brutalising and terrorising the Indians. </s><s n="s4.11;p9.17">As Taylor surmises, the English promoters of migration depicted the Spanish as 'uniquely brutal colonizers... the Indians of Virginia would welcome the English as their liberators'.<ref target="BAWE_0129a-ftnote.019"/> However, 'Spanish and English mariners sometimes kidnapped or killed Natives',<ref target="BAWE_0129a-ftnote.020"/> often the Spanish being increasingly more brutal, reflecting that the English were far from liberating. </s><s n="s5.11;p9.17">On the other hand, 'the Cusabo welcomed the English...as a welcome alternative to ineffectual Spanish'<ref target="BAWE_0129a-ftnote.021"/> signifying an overriding difference in their colonies in that the Indians showed a preference for the English. </s><s n="s6.11;p9.17">Such differences are emphasised by Taylor: 'the Spanish were uniquely more cruel and far more brutal and destructive than other Europeans in their treatment of the Indians'<ref target="BAWE_0129a-ftnote.022"/>, representing an ultimate difference between their settlements. </s><s n="s7.11;p9.17">Furthermore, with regard to the concept of converting the Indians to Christianity through missionaries, 'the English refusal to convert slaves diverged sharply from the practice of the... </s><s n="s8.11;p9.17">Spanish... masters." </s><ref target="BAWE_0129a-ftnote.023"/><s n="s9.11;p9.17">Their foremost concern was to assimilate them as economic inferiors. </s><s n="s10.11;p9.17">Overall, the English and Spanish settlements shared the overwhelming similarity that they both desired to keep the Indians under control and thus 'the first and essential step was to oblige the mobile Indians to settle down in permanent and delimited communities." </s><ref target="BAWE_0129a-ftnote.024"/><s n="s11.11;p9.17">This had the additional benefit of making a greater expanse of land available for more settlements. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0129a-ftnote.019"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Taylor, <hi rend="italic">American Colonies</hi>, p.122 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0129a-ftnote.020"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Taylor, <hi rend="italic">American Colonies</hi>, p.128 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0129a-ftnote.021"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Taylor, <hi rend="italic">American Colonies</hi>, p.232 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0129a-ftnote.022"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Taylor, <hi rend="italic">American Colonies</hi>, p.51 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0129a-ftnote.023"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Taylor, <hi rend="italic">American Colonies</hi>, p.214 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0129a-ftnote.024"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Taylor, <hi rend="italic">American Colonies</hi>, p.197 </s></p></note><p n="p10.17"><s n="s1.3;p10.17">In addition to both settlements' government's attitude towards Indians, they also differed with regard to their own 'planter elite." </s><ref target="BAWE_0129a-ftnote.025"/><s n="s2.3;p10.17">'The English monarch exercised little power over his colonists'<ref target="BAWE_0129a-ftnote.026"/> which explains why they had a share in the power of the colony. </s><s n="s3.3;p10.17">On the other hand, Spanish colonies 'permitted neither elected neither assemblies nor individual liberties'<ref target="BAWE_0129a-ftnote.027"/> and 'unlike... the English... possessed a distinctive set of political aspirations'<ref target="BAWE_0129a-ftnote.028"/>, offering an explanation for their varying governmental structures. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0129a-ftnote.025"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Taylor, <hi rend="italic">American Colonies</hi>, p.140 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0129a-ftnote.026"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Taylor, <hi rend="italic">American Colonies</hi>, p.246 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0129a-ftnote.027"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Taylor, <hi rend="italic">American Colonies</hi>, p.140 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0129a-ftnote.028"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Canny and Pagden (eds.), <hi rend="italic">Colonial Identity</hi>, p.52 </s></p></note><p n="p11.17"><s n="s1.6;p11.17">In the mid-seventeenth century English settlements were developing in the West Indies and became 'crown jewels of the English colonial empire'<ref target="BAWE_0129a-ftnote.029"/> due to their valuable sugar plantations, particularly in Barbados. </s><s n="s2.6;p11.17">The escalating population of the West Indies highlighted their importance as settlements, for example, by 1650 more colonists lived there than the Chesapeake and New England settlements combined, totalling 44,000.<ref target="BAWE_0129a-ftnote.030"/> The principal migrants were ambitious young men 'heading for the islands to make their fortunes." </s><ref target="BAWE_0129a-ftnote.031"/><s n="s3.6;p11.17">By the early eighteenth century Jamaica had become 'the wealthiest and most important colony in the English empire." </s><ref target="BAWE_0129a-ftnote.032"/><s n="s4.6;p11.17">On the other hand, it was not until 1616 that English colonists discovered the wealth that could be wrought from tabacco plantations, long after the Spanish. </s><s n="s5.6;p11.17">Despite this, 'plantation settlements in... </s><s n="s6.6;p11.17">Virginia, or in parts of Spanish America... had more in common with each other than with the mother country'<ref target="BAWE_0129a-ftnote.033"/> which is significant as it shows how both sets of settlements grew equally distinct from their homeland. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0129a-ftnote.029"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Taylor, <hi rend="italic">American Colonies</hi>, p.205 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0129a-ftnote.030"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Taylor, <hi rend="italic">American Colonies</hi>, p.206 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0129a-ftnote.031"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Bernard Bailyn, <hi rend="italic">Voyagers to the West</hi>, p.251 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0129a-ftnote.032"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Taylor, <hi rend="italic">American Colonies</hi>, p.220 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0129a-ftnote.033"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Canny and Pagden (eds.), <hi rend="italic">Colonial Identity</hi>, p7 </s></p></note><p n="p12.17"><s n="s1.2;p12.17">Regarding the significance of the Lesser Antilles of the Caribbean, English and Spanish opinions differed considerably. </s><s n="s2.2;p12.17">The English viewed them as important due to their proximity to Spanish ports, whereas the Spanish 'disdained the islands as too small to bother with'<ref target="BAWE_0129a-ftnote.034"/> as they were trying to colonise Hispaniola, Jamaica, Cuba and Puerto Rico. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0129a-ftnote.034"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Taylor, <hi rend="italic">American Colonies</hi>, p.206 </s></p></note><p n="p13.17"><s n="s1.3;p13.17">Taylor indicates how England was 'emerging as an important power as Spain grew weaker'<ref target="BAWE_0129a-ftnote.035"/>, represented by the English colony of Carolina which was founded in 1670 defiantly close to Spain's St. Augustine on the border of Florida. </s><s n="s2.3;p13.17">However, this had significant repercussions as 'fugitive slaves fled the English colonies to establish themselves in St. Augustine'<ref target="BAWE_0129a-ftnote.036"/> and the Spanish 'crown favoured encouragement of runaways as part of a policy of hostility to the Carolina settlement." </s><ref target="BAWE_0129a-ftnote.037"/><s n="s3.3;p13.17">This represents the differences between the settlements and, moreover, the antagonism transpiring between them. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0129a-ftnote.035"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Taylor, <hi rend="italic">American Colonies</hi>, p.224 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0129a-ftnote.036"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Corbett, 'Migration to a Spanish Imperial Frontier', p.429 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0129a-ftnote.037"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Corbett, 'Migration to a Spanish Imperial Frontier', p.429 </s></p></note><p n="p14.17"><s n="s1.1;p14.17">There is a remarkable distinction between migration to English and Spanish settlements as highlighted by Bailyn: </s></p><quote lang="English">By 1700 the overall population of Britons or their descendants in the Western Hemisphere was approximately 250,000, which is double the number of peninsular Spaniards... known to be in Spanish America. <ref target="BAWE_0129a-ftnote.038"/></quote><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0129a-ftnote.038"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Bernard Bailyn, <hi rend="italic">Voyagers to the West</hi>, pp.24-5 </s></p></note><p n="p15.17"><s n="s1.1;p15.17">This is contested by Taylor who claims that, in the sixteenth century alone, there were 250,000 Spanish migrants in North America.<ref target="BAWE_0129a-ftnote.039"/> However, it can still be inferred from Bailyn that there was a greater percentage of English migrants than Spanish, represented by the population of England's thirteen colonies being 700,000 by 1760.<ref target="BAWE_0129a-ftnote.040"/> This difference in population is supported by the fact that the population of Spanish Florida was a mere three thousand, half that of English Georgia's population, and compared to New England homogenous population of 500,000 in 1760. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0129a-ftnote.039"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Taylor, <hi rend="italic">American Colonies</hi>, p.61 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0129a-ftnote.040"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Bernard Bailyn, <hi rend="italic">Voyagers to the West</hi>, p.25 </s></p></note><p n="p16.17"><s n="s1.7;p16.17">Since the populations of English settlements were demographically self-sustaining and thus growing continuously, increasingly more than the Spanish, their societies emerged within a more stratified and viable social and economic framework, which encouraged permanency. </s><s n="s2.7;p16.17">Alongside differences between European colonies, within each of their settlements 'communities differed... the distinctions among them, more than their similarities, shaped the ways in which new arrivals were absorbed into the society." </s><ref target="BAWE_0129a-ftnote.041"/><s n="s3.7;p16.17">As a result of their large and diverse population, English settlements were consistently more dynamic than the Spanish and, moreover, further developed as highlighted by their colonial expansion inland. </s><s n="s4.7;p16.17">At first, the English settlements were 'clustered on a coastal strip'<ref target="BAWE_0129a-ftnote.042"/>, for example, 'Nova Scotia and the Floridas... were <hi rend="italic">coastal</hi> frontiers." </s><ref target="BAWE_0129a-ftnote.043"/><s n="s5.7;p16.17">These were initially English and Spanish settlements but by the mid-seventeenth century both were in English hands and were distinguishable from other regions because these settlements were convenient for Atlantic trade. </s><s n="s6.7;p16.17">Eventually, the 'English secured a lucrative, dynamic, and expansive base on the North American continent'<ref target="BAWE_0129a-ftnote.044"/>, partly due to the beneficial position of their settlements. </s><s n="s7.7;p16.17">On the other hand, in Spanish New Mexico imports were only allowed through Vera Cruz, which resulted in economic stagnation. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0129a-ftnote.041"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Bailyn, <hi rend="italic">The Peopling of British North America,</hi> p.53 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0129a-ftnote.042"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">McFarlane, <hi rend="italic">The British in the Americas,</hi> p.154 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0129a-ftnote.043"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Bernard Bailyn, <hi rend="italic">Voyagers to the West</hi>, p.358 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0129a-ftnote.044"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Taylor, <hi rend="italic">American Colonies</hi>, p.61 </s></p></note><p n="p17.17"><s n="s1.2;p17.17">In conclusion, the early English and Spanish settlements in North America shared both similarities and differences in terms of their trade, demographical structures, religious beliefs, their nature towards Native Indians and their geographical location. </s><s n="s2.2;p17.17">Although some of these similarities and differences were implicit, many were explicit, as seen specifically with regard to their purpose and religion. </s></p></div1></body><back/></text></TEI.2>
