<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_0129e" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>To what extent did the Romantic Movement pave the way for modern environmentalism?</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">The document has a title page which contains:
document title
title part</note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">deleted: page numbers
deleted: WORD COUNT: 2,165
</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">1</p><p n="date">2005-02</p><p n="module title">The Making of the Modern World</p><p n="module code">HI153</p><p n="genre family">Essay</p><p n="discipline">History</p><p n="disciplinary group">AH</p><p n="grade">M</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">2164</p><p n="number of s-units">73</p><p n="number of p">21</p><p n="number of tables">0</p><p n="number of figures">0</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">0</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">0</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">29.6</p><p n="average s-units per p">3.5</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">f</p><p n="year of birth">1986</p><p n="first language">English</p><p n="education">UKA</p><p n="course">History</p><p n="student ID">0129</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><docTitle><titlePart rend="underlined bold">To what extent did the Romantic Movement pave the way for modern environmentalism? </titlePart></docTitle><titlePart rend="underlined bold">February 2005. </titlePart><titlePart><name type="student name"/></titlePart><docTitle><titlePart rend="underlined bold">To what extent did the Romantic Movement pave the way for modern environmentalism? </titlePart></docTitle></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="section"><p n="p1.21"><s n="s1.2;p1.21">The epoch of the Romantic Movement has been a topic of notable discussion, however it is generally postulated that it spanned the period between the mid-eighteenth and mid-nineteenth century, triumphing particularly in its later years. </s><s n="s2.2;p1.21">The Romantic Movement symbolised a momentous reaction against the degrading material and environmental changes stimulated by the centuries' industrial and agricultural revolutions, alongside a rejection of the rational dogmas of the Enlightenment. </s></p><p n="p2.21"><s n="s1.2;p2.21">The principal characteristics of the Romantic Movement included an overpowering yet troubled love of nature, sympathy and nostalgia for a golden past, and enthusiasm for a simple rural life. </s><s n="s2.2;p2.21">A combination of these elements provided the impetus in paving the way for modern environmentalism, because of their connection to the supreme force of Mother Nature and endeavours to protect her dominion. </s></p><p n="p3.21"><s n="s1.4;p3.21">Although it is 'difficult to place the commencement of modern concerns about the environment to any specific date'<ref target="BAWE_0129e-ftnote.001"/>, <hi rend="italic">modern</hi> environmentalism evolved as a mass movement since Earth Day, in 1970. </s><s n="s2.4;p3.21">Although an understanding of environmental issues had been accumulating throughout the century, this national celebration underlined the fact that <hi rend="italic">modern</hi> society was growing <hi rend="italic">increasingly</hi> conscious of the threat posed by the profound environmental problems that stemmed from adverse developments in the economy. </s><s n="s3.4;p3.21">Such extensive awareness harped back to the eighteenth and nineteenth centuries, where 'an impending global shortage of timber resources'<ref target="BAWE_0129e-ftnote.002"/> had given rise to schemes for forest protection, and preservation reserves were established owing to wildlife depletion at the hands of hunters. </s><s n="s4.4;p3.21">Modern environmentalism could be deemed part of a 'romantic resurgence'<ref target="BAWE_0129e-ftnote.003"/>, as it similarly endorsed the ideal that humans 'should behave with more peaceful and harmonious intentions towards nature'<ref target="BAWE_0129e-ftnote.004"/>, as opposed to the degrading and exploiting it. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0129e-ftnote.001"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">David Pepper, <hi rend="italic">Roots of Modern Environmentalism</hi>, (London, 1989), p.14 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0129e-ftnote.002"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Richard Grove, <hi rend="italic">Green Imperialism: Colonial Expansion, Tropical Island Edens and the Origins of Environmentalism, 1600-1860,</hi> (Cambridge, 1995), p.309 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0129e-ftnote.003"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Pepper, <hi rend="italic">Roots</hi>, p.87 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0129e-ftnote.004"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Pepper, <hi rend="italic">Roots</hi>, p.13 </s></p></note><p n="p4.21"><s n="s1.5;p4.21">David Pepper declared that 'modern ecological environmentalism... has particular affinities with 19 <hi rend="sup">th</hi>-century romanticism." </s><ref target="BAWE_0129e-ftnote.005"/><s n="s2.5;p4.21">An early illustration of the extent to which the Romantic Movement paved the way for modern environmentalism can be seen in the studies of Gilbert White. </s><s n="s3.5;p4.21">His emphasis on the natural harmony of Selbourne eulogised the ideals of simplicity, the sublime landscape, unity with a palpable nature, and Pantheism, all of which were key concepts in the philosophy of the Romantic Movement. </s><s n="s4.5;p4.21">The latter was particularly central, as 'it seemed that to find God one must find 'unspoiled' nature, his creation'<ref target="BAWE_0129e-ftnote.006"/>, thus, because of the manifestation of God in nature, they saw it as a deity. </s><s n="s5.5;p4.21">White omitted citing the agricultural revolution in his book, <hi rend="italic">The Natural History of Selbourne</hi> (1789), despite the fact that it had irrevocably distorted the rustic simplicity of his life into an anachronism. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0129e-ftnote.005"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Pepper, <hi rend="italic">Roots</hi>, p.68 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0129e-ftnote.006"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">David Pepper, <hi rend="italic">Modern Environmentalism: An Introduction</hi>, (London, 1996), p.200 </s></p></note><p n="p5.21"><s n="s1.3;p5.21">In nineteenth-century Massachusetts, the transcendentalist Henry David Thoreau expressed the ideals of the Romantic Movement and veneration of nature in an American context. </s><s n="s2.3;p5.21">He exercised remarkable austerity in his immersion into nature and in his response to intensive farming and the rapid depletion of forests; he 'saw trees as God's temples." </s><ref target="BAWE_0129e-ftnote.007"/><s n="s3.3;p5.21">Thoreau's condemnation of extensive deforestation can be compared to forest protection schemes, implying that the modern environmentalism embodied much of the ethos of the Romantic Movement. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0129e-ftnote.007"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Pepper, <hi rend="italic">Roots</hi>, p.72 </s></p></note><p n="p6.21"><s n="s1.3;p6.21">Modern environmental theories were rooted in desires to return to the Golden Age of the pre-industrial era and capitulating oneself to nature, following the path laid down by the Romantic Movement. </s><s n="s2.3;p6.21">In their struggle to preserve the dynamics of nature, 'the ecocentric very much restates the ideas of the transcendentalists. </s><s n="s3.3;p6.21">They, in turn, took on the European romantic's ideas'<ref target="BAWE_0129e-ftnote.008"/>, identifying that modern environmentalism inherited ideas of Romantics. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0129e-ftnote.008"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Pepper, <hi rend="italic">Roots</hi>, p.81 </s></p></note><p n="p7.21"><s n="s1.5;p7.21">Romantics expressed their deep disillusionment with the rise of deplorable industry and agricultural innovations, which vandalised nature. </s><s n="s2.5;p7.21">This was due to the adverse impact they had upon the landscape and wider environment; 'Romantics hated how industrialisation made previously beautiful places ugly." </s><ref target="BAWE_0129e-ftnote.009"/><s n="s3.5;p7.21">Those involved in modern environmental movements similarly articulated their concerns about the destruction and gross exploitation of the landscape owing to modern industry and progressive agricultural technology. </s><s n="s4.5;p7.21">'Over the last 10,000 years human activities have brought about major changes in the ecosystems of the world." </s><ref target="BAWE_0129e-ftnote.010"/><s n="s5.5;p7.21">Such activities led modern environmentalists to advocate the balance of humanity and nature, emulating the romantic inspiration to transcend notions of human superiority, signifying the extent to which the Romantic Movement impacted modern environmentalism. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0129e-ftnote.009"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Pepper, <hi rend="italic">Modern Environmentalism</hi>, pp.189-90 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0129e-ftnote.010"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Clive Ponting, <hi rend="italic">A Green History of the World.</hi> </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1"><hi rend="italic">The Environment and the Collapse of Great Civilisations</hi>, (London, 1993), p.161 </s></p></note><p n="p8.21"><s n="s1.5;p8.21">A prime characteristic of modern environmentalism was an endeavour to conserve exhaustible sources of energy by conducting searches for safe, renewable sources. </s><s n="s2.5;p8.21">Such initiatives stemmed from Romantic reactions to widespread beliefs of the era in the <hi rend="italic">inexhaustibility</hi> of natural resources. </s><s n="s3.5;p8.21">Modern environmentalists were 'romantic followers'<ref target="BAWE_0129e-ftnote.011"/>, as they shared the same lack of empathy towards industrialisation which 'created areas of concentrated pollution'<ref target="BAWE_0129e-ftnote.012"/>, regarding it as a profanity corrupting society. </s><s n="s4.5;p8.21">Industrial centres were viewed as transforming a <hi rend="italic">natural</hi> man into a sullied man encumbered by possessions and estranged from the dynamics of nature. </s><s n="s5.5;p8.21">This clearly represents how modern environmentalism adapted qualities from the path set down by the Romantic Movement as both encouraged the return of man to nature. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0129e-ftnote.011"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Pepper, <hi rend="italic">Modern Environmentalism</hi>, p.169 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0129e-ftnote.012"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ponting, <hi rend="italic">A Green</hi> History, p.361 </s></p></note><p n="p9.21"><s n="s1.3;p9.21">It was the amalgamation of a myriad of environmental concerns that broadened the constituency of the modern environmental movement in the 1970s, underscoring a new phase in environmentalism. </s><s n="s2.3;p9.21">The plethora of modern environmental problems could be deemed cataclysmic, as they included the acute growth of modern metropolises, pollution, acid rain, extinction of various species of wildlife and entire natural ecosystems, global warming and ozone depletion, mineral depletion, deforestation, and the exhaustion of natural resources. </s><s n="s3.3;p9.21">The 'pioneers of modern environmentalism'<ref target="BAWE_0129e-ftnote.013"/> sought to limit, if not rectify, these problems by establishing numerous protective schemes, for example to conserve forests by placing strict controls upon the cutting of trees. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0129e-ftnote.013"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Pepper, <hi rend="italic">Modern Environmentalism</hi>, p.169 </s></p></note><p n="p10.21"><s n="s1.7;p10.21">However, some initial government policies to combat deforestation were autocratic and had detrimental effects, particularly for Native American Indians who were displaced from their forest dwellings. </s><s n="s2.7;p10.21">This was also a consequence of the revolutionary establishment of wildlife sanctuaries, which required the indigenous forest communities to relocate. </s><s n="s3.7;p10.21">The first of these special reserves, Yellowstone National Park in America, was founded for recreational purposes in 1872. </s><s n="s4.7;p10.21">It predominantly promoted 'escapism, as well as the more positive romantic desire for spiritual regeneration'<ref target="BAWE_0129e-ftnote.014"/> for the urban middle-class. </s><s n="s5.7;p10.21">The Romantic Movement had paved the way for this sense of a <hi rend="italic">retreat</hi> back to the solace of nature, as it presented an opportunity for those who had become estranged from nature to withdraw back into it, away from the distortions and corruptions of heavy industry, consumerism, and city life. </s><s n="s6.7;p10.21">However, the dislocation of the Natives, in order to establish National Parks, went against ideals of the Romantic Movement, which exalted the 'noble savage'<ref target="BAWE_0129e-ftnote.015"/> and the way they lived in harmony with nature. </s><s n="s7.7;p10.21">This indicates an area of environmentalism that did not wholly follow the path set down by the Romantic Movement. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0129e-ftnote.014"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Pepper, <hi rend="italic">Roots</hi>, p.88 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0129e-ftnote.015"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Pepper, <hi rend="italic">Modern Environmentalism</hi>, p.192 </s></p></note><p n="p11.21"><s n="s1.1;p11.21">The modern environmental movement was rooted in these early attempts to recapture the romantic essence and vital force of nature and regenerate aspects that had descended into a state of melancholy and introspection. </s></p><p n="p12.21"><s n="s1.5;p12.21">David Pepper proposes that 'within the environmental movement there is a host of ideologies and cross-currents'<ref target="BAWE_0129e-ftnote.016"/>, and furthermore, that some factions altered the path of their campaigning in synonymy with contemporary environmental concerns. </s><s n="s2.5;p12.21">For instance, in 1972, the Club of Rome sponsored <hi rend="italic"> The Limits of Growth</hi>, which instigated the debate over the potential consequences of the continued exhaustion of energy supplies, even though their own predictions proved to be unsubstantiated. </s><s n="s3.5;p12.21">Consequently, following the oil crisis of 1973, there arose a search for alternative energy sources. </s><s n="s4.5;p12.21">However, by the early 1980s emphasis had turned to the issue of pollution caused by those alternative mineral resources. </s><s n="s5.5;p12.21">Although these sectors in isolation were originally concerned with energy resources, the ideology of the latter can be see to alter to a concern for an associated environmental problem. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0129e-ftnote.016"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Pepper, <hi rend="italic">Roots</hi>, p.13 </s></p></note><p n="p13.21"><s n="s1.3;p13.21">Tendencies to echo the ideals of the Romantic Movement are visible in Fritz Schumacher's 'deeply influential'<ref target="BAWE_0129e-ftnote.017"/> concepts in <hi rend="italic">Small in Beautiful</hi>, in which he underlines the preference for small-scale appropriate industry, which was judged more beneficial to society and the environment. </s><s n="s2.3;p13.21">By advocating this theory, Third World environmentalists achieved substantial successes, such as the construction of dams. </s><s n="s3.3;p13.21">In the 1970 the passing of the Environmental Protection Agency and Clean Air and Clean Water Acts similarly represented successes of modern environmentalists, which sought to safeguard nature as the Romantics had stressed. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0129e-ftnote.017"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Pepper, <hi rend="italic">Roots</hi>, p.22 </s></p></note><p n="p14.21"><s n="s1.3;p14.21">Arcadian sensibilities, accentuating the idea of an <hi rend="italic">ordered</hi> nature, had emerged prior to the Romantic Movement, yet were imbued with many of the same sentiments For example, both celebrated the primitive and pastoral harmony with nature that had been experienced in the unspoiled period of the Golden Age, notably expressed by French Enlightenment philosophe, and first of the Romantics, Jean-Jacques Rousseau. </s><s n="s2.3;p14.21">However, Arcadianism did not share the same revolutionary and turbulent spirit as the Romantic Movement, which rejoiced in the disordered wilderness and irrational side of nature. </s><s n="s3.3;p14.21">Nevertheless, Arcadian critiques also played a role in paving the way for modern environmentalism to a certain extent, highlighted by Donald Worster in <hi rend="italic">Nature's Economy: A History of Ecological Ideas</hi> (1985), because of its emphasis on co-existence with nature as opposed to the self-appointed, egotistical superiority and domination by humans. </s></p><p n="p15.21"><s n="s1.6;p15.21">The work of Charles Darwin, from the 1830s, did not elaborate upon this aspect of co-existence. </s><s n="s2.6;p15.21">Conversely, Darwin deployed a pessimistic and darker view of nature, which revolved around the process of natural selection and the survival of the fittest, to a much greater extent. </s><s n="s3.6;p15.21">It was not until the later nineteenth century that he reverted his ideals back to the concept of harmony and oneness with nature, reminiscing about Arcadian and Romantic notions of respect for Mother Nature. </s><s n="s4.6;p15.21">However, Darwin's theories had already been used in a perverse manner to justify the violence of science and the exploitation of nature for the common good of <hi rend="italic">superior</hi> humanity. </s><s n="s5.6;p15.21">Romantics were highly critical of such superficial forms of modern science and the violence it often entailed, for example in animal and plant research where it was employed in order to construct, to some degree superfluous, systems of classification. </s><s n="s6.6;p15.21">Thus the framework of modern environmentalism can be seen as originating in the doctrines that renounced the rigorous manipulation of nature by modern science, which burgeoned in the Romantic Movement. </s></p><p n="p16.21"><s n="s1.3;p16.21">However, as well as the Romantic Movement, other 'scientific'<ref target="BAWE_0129e-ftnote.018"/> roots, which stemmed from 'empiricism and rational thinking in biology and ecology'<ref target="BAWE_0129e-ftnote.019"/>, had paved the way for modern environmentalism, for example the ideas of Charles Darwin and Thomas Malthus. </s><s n="s2.3;p16.21">The latter, and his 'modern limits to growth argument'<ref target="BAWE_0129e-ftnote.020"/>, can be seen as pre-empting debates about the extent of progression in modern society, and the extent to which the environment could cater for the surging population of humanity. </s><s n="s3.3;p16.21">The motivation of some actions of modern environmentalists was simply 'the need, as human numbers have steadily increased, to feed, clothe and house them'<ref target="BAWE_0129e-ftnote.021"/>, by utilising nature. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0129e-ftnote.018"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Pepper, <hi rend="italic">Roots</hi>, p.68 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0129e-ftnote.019"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Pepper, <hi rend="italic">Modern Environmentalism,</hi> p.169 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0129e-ftnote.020"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Pepper, <hi rend="italic">Modern Environmentalism</hi>, p.173 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0129e-ftnote.021"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ponting, <hi rend="italic">A Green History</hi>, p.141 </s></p></note><p n="p17.21"><s n="s1.2;p17.21">Darwin, as previously discussed, had affiliations with the Romantic Movement in his later years, yet he was a 'towering nineteenth-century figure whose ideas form... the scientific strand in modern ecocentrism." </s><ref target="BAWE_0129e-ftnote.022"/><s n="s2.2;p17.21">This was because he opened up areas of observations that paved the way for modern environmentalism and its regard for diversity, although to how great an extent he did so remains 'ambiguous.' <ref target="BAWE_0129e-ftnote.023"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0129e-ftnote.022"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Pepper, <hi rend="italic">Modern Environmentalism</hi>, p.180 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0129e-ftnote.023"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Pepper, <hi rend="italic">Modern Environmentalism</hi>, p.183 </s></p></note><p n="p18.21"><s n="s1.1;p18.21">On the other hand, it is considered by Anna Bramwell<ref target="BAWE_0129e-ftnote.024"/> that it was essentially Ernst Haeckel whom 'created the scientific root of ecologism, giving credence and scientific legitimacy to romantics who were alienated by the effects and values of industrial capitalism'<ref target="BAWE_0129e-ftnote.025"/>, which further implies that the Romantic Movement was not singularly responsible for paving the way for modern environmentalism. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0129e-ftnote.024"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Anna Bramwell, <hi rend="italic">Ecology in the Twentieth Century: a History,</hi> (London, 1989) </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0129e-ftnote.025"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Pepper, <hi rend="italic">Modern Environmentalism</hi>, p.185 </s></p></note><p n="p19.21"><s n="s1.5;p19.21">There existed chasms between the Romantics and the scientific study of nature, as the former maintained that 'science was inadequate to explain all the phenomena with which humans are confronted." </s><ref target="BAWE_0129e-ftnote.026"/><s n="s2.5;p19.21">Conversely, Romanticism was 'attacked by champions of scientific rationalism." </s><ref target="BAWE_0129e-ftnote.027"/><s n="s3.5;p19.21">However, it is important to bear in mind that 'the scientist and the Romantic pursue their different paths in the same spirit toward to same goal'<ref target="BAWE_0129e-ftnote.028"/> - the preservation of the environment via modern environmentalism. </s><s n="s4.5;p19.21">Nonetheless, 'the dividing line between scientific and artistic tastes was a shadowy one." </s><ref target="BAWE_0129e-ftnote.029"/><s n="s5.5;p19.21">Consequently, it is difficult to determine which paved the way to the greater extent as both scientific 'rationalism and romanticism intertwine in... environmental history.' <ref target="BAWE_0129e-ftnote.030"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0129e-ftnote.026"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Pepper, <hi rend="italic">Modern Environmentalism</hi>, p.191 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0129e-ftnote.027"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Pepper, <hi rend="italic">Modern Environmentalism</hi>, p.190 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0129e-ftnote.028"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ernest Berbaum, <hi rend="italic">Guide Through the Romantic Movement</hi>, (New York, 1949), p.309 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0129e-ftnote.029"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Grove, <hi rend="italic">Green Imperialism</hi>, p.355 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0129e-ftnote.030"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Pepper, <hi rend="italic">Modern Environmentalism</hi>, p.219 </s></p></note><p n="p20.21"><s n="s1.2;p20.21">In conclusion, I would surmise that the Romantic Movement had the most superior influence because it embodied numerous factions and ideals, which ultimately paved the path for modern environmentalism. </s><s n="s2.2;p20.21">Although science and environmental theories played a role in the path to modern environmentalism, it was more limited, and could possibly be seen as having been influenced by the Romantic Movement to some extent. </s></p><p n="p21.21"><s n="s1.3;p21.21">As Pepper has asserted: 'the Romantic Movement has strong and direct historical links into modern ecocentrism'<ref target="BAWE_0129e-ftnote.031"/>. </s><s n="s2.3;p21.21">Furthermore, Erisman<ref target="BAWE_0129e-ftnote.032"/> 'concludes that modern... environmentalists are 'not the <hi rend="italic">avant-garde</hi> of a new, but only the most recent manifestations of an old, romantic tradition''<ref target="BAWE_0129e-ftnote.033"/>, clearly demonstrating the belief that modern environmentalism can be seen as a <hi rend="italic">continuation</hi> of the Romantic Movement. </s><s n="s3.3;p21.21">I strongly agree with this view and maintain that the Romantic Movement undoubtedly paved the way to modern environmentalism to a significant extent, primarily due to its emphasis upon the preservation of nature in all her forms. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0129e-ftnote.031"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Pepper, <hi rend="italic">Modern Environmentalism</hi>, p.189 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0129e-ftnote.032"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">F. Erisman, 'The environmental crisis and present-day romanticism: the persistence of an idea', <hi rend="italic">Rocky Mountain Social Science Journal</hi>, Vol. 10, (1973), pp.7-14 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0129e-ftnote.033"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Pepper, <hi rend="italic">Roots</hi>, p.90 </s></p></note></div1></body><back/></text></TEI.2>
