<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_0132a" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Analysis of Pepper vs Hart</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note/></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">1</p><p n="date">2005-12</p><p n="module title">The Modern English Legal System</p><p n="module code">LA115</p><p n="genre family">Critique</p><p n="discipline">Law</p><p n="disciplinary group">SS</p><p n="grade">M</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">1235</p><p n="number of s-units">52</p><p n="number of p">11</p><p n="number of tables">0</p><p n="number of figures">0</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">0</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">0</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">23.8</p><p n="average s-units per p">4.7</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">f</p><p n="year of birth">1986</p><p n="first language">Chinese Cantonese</p><p n="education">OSA</p><p n="course">LLB</p><p n="student ID">0132</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><docTitle><titlePart rend="underlined bold">ANALYSIS OF PEPPER v HART</titlePart></docTitle></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="section"><p n="p1.11"><s n="s1.4;p1.11">This case, <hi rend="italic">Pepper v Hart</hi> <hi rend="italic">and others</hi><ref target="BAWE_0132a-ftnote.001"/>, just like <hi rend="italic">Donoghue v Stevenson</hi><ref target="BAWE_0132a-ftnote.002"/> and <hi rend="italic">Carlill v Carbolic Smoke Ball Co</hi>.<ref target="BAWE_0132a-ftnote.003"/>, has brought up important issues and laid down important rules. </s><s n="s2.4;p1.11">In this case, constitutional issues were raised. </s><s n="s3.4;p1.11">Questions to be answered are whether parliamentary materials, such as Hansard, are admissible in construing Acts of Parliament and if yes, will the rights under Article 9 of the Bill of Rights Act 1998 and the privileges of members of the Parliament be infringed. </s><s n="s4.4;p1.11">Now, I will consider the relevant issues individually, starting off with this instant case. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0132a-ftnote.001"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">[1993] A.C. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">593 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0132a-ftnote.002"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">[1932] A.C. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">562 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0132a-ftnote.003"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">[1893] 1 Q.B. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">256 </s></p></note></div1><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="underlined bold">Pepper v Hart 's facts and decision </hi><ref target="BAWE_0132a-ftnote.004"/><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0132a-ftnote.004"><p n="pn1.1"><hi rend="italic">Pepper</hi> (n 1) at 619D (Lord Griffiths), at 620F (Lord Oliver), at 643C(Lord Browne-Wilkinson)</p></note></head><p n="p2.11"><s n="s1.9;p2.11"><hi rend="italic">Pepper v Hart</hi> involved a dispute between the taxpayers and the Inland Revenue. </s><s n="s2.9;p2.11">The taxpayers, who are members of the staff in Malvern College, had the benefit of educating their sons in the school under a concessionary fees' scheme. </s><s n="s3.9;p2.11">The taxpayers argued that the cost of the benefit is the marginal cost of the employer of providing the benefit. </s><s n="s4.9;p2.11">The Special Commissioner accepted and held in favour of the taxpayers. </s><s n="s5.9;p2.11">The Crown then appealed arguing that under section 63(2) of the Finance Act 1976, the cost of benefit was <hi rend="italic">the amount of any expense incurred or in connection with its provision including a proper proportion of any expense relating partly to the benefit and partly to other matters</hi>. </s><s n="s6.9;p2.11">Vinelott J allowed the appeal and his decision was upheld by the Court of Appeal. </s><s n="s7.9;p2.11">The taxpayers appealed. </s><s n="s8.9;p2.11">In the first hearing of the House of Lords, the appeal was dismissed.<ref target="BAWE_0132a-ftnote.005"/> However, a rehearing was listed before a panel of seven Law Lords. </s><s n="s9.9;p2.11">In this rehearing, the parties are invited to present their arguments on the question whether parliamentary debates can be referenced in construing the relevant statute, which in this case, section 63(2). </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0132a-ftnote.005"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid. </s></p></note><p n="p3.11"><s n="s1.9;p3.11">In the rehearing, the Lordships, except Lord Mackay of Clashfern LC, allowed the appeal. </s><s n="s2.9;p3.11">The Lordships reached this outcome based on a number of reasons. </s><s n="s3.9;p3.11">Firstly, Lord Browne-Wilkinson stated 'that courts have a duty to give effect to the intention of the Parliament. </s><s n="s4.9;p3.11">In most cases, reference to parliamentary materials will not throw any light on the matter of dispute. </s><s n="s5.9;p3.11">However, in a few cases, where the Parliament has considered the very problem will give a clear indication of their intentions. </s><s n="s6.9;p3.11">Therefore, in this kind of situations, the courts should not turn a blind eye and construe words in the way that they cannot bear.' </s><s n="s7.9;p3.11">He then laid down three criteria which are to be fulfilled in order to permit reference to Hansard. </s><s n="s8.9;p3.11">They are where 1) legislation is ambiguous or obscure, or leads to an absurdity; 2) the material relied on consists of one or more statements by a minister or other promoter of the Bill together if necessary with such other parliamentary material as is necessary to understand such statements and their effect; and 3) the statements relied on are clear. </s><s n="s9.9;p3.11">The present case met these three criteria. </s></p><p n="p4.11"><s n="s1.2;p4.11">Secondly, Article 9 of the Bill of rights Act 1998 was not infringed on the grounds that, as per Lord Browne-Wilkinson, 'the plain meaning of Article 9 was to ensure that members of Parliament were not subjected to any penalty, civil or criminal for what they said. </s><s n="s2.2;p4.11">The purpose of looking into Hansard is not to construe or criticise the words used by the ministers but to give effect to the words used as long as they are clear.' </s></p><p n="p5.11"><s n="s1.1;p5.11">Lastly, Lord Browne-Wilkinson held that parliamentary privileges do not exist in this case in absence of a claim of any privilege extending beyond that protected by the Bills of Rights from the Clerk of Commons or the Attorney General. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">Statutory Interpretation and Use of Hansard</head><p n="p6.11"><s n="s1.4;p6.11">'The constitutional role of the judiciary is applying and interprets the law'.<ref target="BAWE_0132a-ftnote.006"/> The basic rules of statutory interpretation are the enactment is to be construed in accordance with the interpretative criteria laid down in Interpretation Act 1978, which generally guides to the intention and where these conflicts, the problem is to be resolved by weighing and balancing the factors concerned.<ref target="BAWE_0132a-ftnote.007"/> There are two different approaches to statutory interpretation. </s><s n="s2.4;p6.11">Firstly, the literal approach where 'courts adopt a strict constructionist view of interpretation which required them to adopt the literal meaning of the language'.<ref target="BAWE_0132a-ftnote.008"/> Then, the purposive approach which the courts adopt now 'which seeks to give effect to the true purpose of the legislation and are prepared to look at much extraneous material'.<ref target="BAWE_0132a-ftnote.009"/> There are three rules in statutory interpretation. </s><s n="s3.4;p6.11">They are the literal, golden and mischief rule. </s><s n="s4.4;p6.11">Besides that, secondary aids to construction are also available. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0132a-ftnote.006"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Slapper and Kelly,<hi rend="italic"> The English Legal System</hi>,( Cavendish Publishing, 2004), p. 192 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0132a-ftnote.007"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Lord Hailsham <hi rend="italic">, Halsbury's Law of England</hi>, Volume 44(1), 4th edition, (Butterworths, 2004) para. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">1376, p.837 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0132a-ftnote.008"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1"><hi rend="italic">Pepper (Inspector of Taxes) v Hart</hi> [1993] A.C. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">593 Lord Griffiths </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0132a-ftnote.009"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">As above </s></p></note><p n="p7.11"><s n="s1.5;p7.11">Hansard, as an aid to construction, was not allowed before this case. </s><s n="s2.5;p7.11">This 'exclusionary rule' was established in the <hi rend="italic">Miller v Taylor</hi> where it stated that ' the sense and meaning of an Act of Parliament must be collected from what it says, not from the history of changes it underwent in the House where it took its rise'.<ref target="BAWE_0132a-ftnote.010"/> In 1840s, reports by commissioners were admissible.<ref target="BAWE_0132a-ftnote.011"/> However, in 1989, Hansard had been allowed in <hi rend="italic">Pickstone v Freeman</hi> <hi rend="italic">plc.</hi> </s><ref target="BAWE_0132a-ftnote.012"/><s n="s3.5;p7.11">This case did not have any large consequences. </s><s n="s4.5;p7.11">Now, in <hi rend="italic">Pepper v Hart</hi>, Hansard is permitted to be referenced if the three criterion set down by Lord Browne-Wilkinson are met. </s><s n="s5.5;p7.11">In another tax case<ref target="BAWE_0132a-ftnote.013"/>, Lord Browne-Wilkinson added the fourth criterion which says that only statements directed to the specific provision under consideration are admissible. <ref target="BAWE_0132a-ftnote.014"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0132a-ftnote.010"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1"><hi rend="italic">Miller v Taylor</hi> [1769] 4 Burr 2303 at 2332 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0132a-ftnote.011"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1"><hi rend="italic">Re Dean of York</hi> [1841] 2 QB 1 at 34 Lord Denman CJ; Stefan Vogenauer, 'A retreat from Pepper v Hart?', <hi rend="italic">Oxford Journal of Legal Studies Advance Access</hi>, 7 September 2005, p. 2 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0132a-ftnote.012"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">[1989] A.C. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">66 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0132a-ftnote.013"><p n="pn1.1"><s rend="italic" n="s1.4;pn1.1">Melluish vBMI (No. </s><s rend="italic" n="s2.4;pn1.1">3) Ltd. </s><s n="s3.4;pn1.1">[1996] 1 A.C. </s><s n="s4.4;pn1.1">454 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0132a-ftnote.014"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Guy Holborn, <hi rend="italic">Legal Research Guide,</hi> 2nd edition, (Butterworths, 2001) Chapter 4, pp. 123-160 </s></p></note><p n="p8.11"><s n="s1.4;p8.11"><hi rend="italic">Pepper v Hart</hi>, in my understanding, shows that the courts are moving towards the purposive approach in interpreting statutes. </s><s n="s2.4;p8.11">The judges, in the best way, interpret which shows what mischief the Parliament intended to cure. </s><s n="s3.4;p8.11">However, use of Hansard or parliamentary materials is still open to criticisms. </s><s n="s4.4;p8.11">Lord Steyn stated that 'some cases reference to Hansard proved to be a damp squib'.<ref target="BAWE_0132a-ftnote.015"/> Turning now to the way courts have chosen to apply, refine or distinguish the decision in subsequent cases. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0132a-ftnote.015"><p n="pn1.1"><s rend="italic" n="s1.2;pn1.1">Re Bishopgate Investment Ltd. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">[1993] Ch 452 </s></p></note></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">Cases following Pepper v Hart</head><p n="p9.11"><s n="s1.8;p9.11">In <hi rend="italic">Rees-Mogg</hi>,<ref target="BAWE_0132a-ftnote.016"/> an issue of ministerial pronouncements was raised. </s><s n="s2.8;p9.11">David Pannick QC contended that 'ministerial statement relied upon the Crown was wrong'. </s><s n="s3.8;p9.11">The court held that it did not matter. </s><s n="s4.8;p9.11">The point of citation was to show what Parliament intended. </s><ref target="BAWE_0132a-ftnote.017"/><s n="s5.8;p9.11">Two years later, Clarke J held that Hansard is permissible in cases of construing a statute as a whole<ref target="BAWE_0132a-ftnote.018"/>. </s><s n="s6.8;p9.11">This show the courts are now taking a more flexible approach. </s><s n="s7.8;p9.11">In contrast, the third case of <hi rend="italic">Spath Holme</hi><ref target="BAWE_0132a-ftnote.019"/>, House of Lords narrowed the construction of <hi rend="italic">Pepper</hi> and held that in cases where interpretation of a scope of statutory power, Hansard is not admissible. </s><s n="s8.8;p9.11">Following by the case of <hi rend="italic">Beckett</hi><ref target="BAWE_0132a-ftnote.020"/>, the narrower construction was applied. <ref target="BAWE_0132a-ftnote.021"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0132a-ftnote.016"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1"><hi rend="italic">R v Secretary of State for Foreign and Commonwealth Affairs, ex p Rees-Mogg</hi> [1994] 1 All ER 457 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0132a-ftnote.017"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Geoffrey Marshall, 'Hansard and Interpretation of statutes' in Dawn Oliver and Gavin Drewry , <hi rend="italic">The Law and Parliament</hi>, (Butterworths, 1998), p. 148 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0132a-ftnote.018"><p n="pn1.1"><s rend="italic" n="s1.2;pn1.1">Three Rivers District Council v Bank of England (No. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1"><hi rend="italic">2),</hi> [1996] 2 ALL ER 363 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0132a-ftnote.019"><p n="pn1.1"><s rend="italic" n="s1.2;pn1.1">R v Secretary of State for the Environment, Transport and the Regions, ex p Spath Holme Ltd. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">[2001] 2 WLR 15 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0132a-ftnote.020"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1"><hi rend="italic">A E Beckett &amp; Sons (Lyndons) Ltd v Midland Electricity plc</hi> [2001] 1 WLR 281 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0132a-ftnote.021"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Stefan Vogenauer, 'A retreat from Pepper v Hart?', <hi rend="italic">Oxford Journal of Legal Studies Advance Access</hi>, 7 September 2005, p. 20 </s></p></note><p n="p10.11"><s n="s1.1;p10.11">Today, the scope of the ruling has been narrowed in five respects: 1) Purpose of statutory interpretation, 2) House of Lord argued even in ordinary cases involving statutory interpretation with exceptions, Hansard is not admissible, 3) statements relied on must be by government of the day, 4) no reference to Hansard if such materials are not regarded as an aid of construction and 5) Hansard not admissible if penal statute is to be construed.<ref target="BAWE_0132a-ftnote.022"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0132a-ftnote.022"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid. pp.25-26 </s></p></note><p n="p11.11"><s n="s1.5;p11.11">In conclusion, the use of Hansard or parliamentary material is allowed in very limited circumstances. </s><s n="s2.5;p11.11">Furthermore, judges especially Lord Steyn and other commentators have expressed their disagreement with the reference to such materials. </s><s n="s3.5;p11.11">In my understanding, courts are now adopting the narrowed construction and slowly departing from <hi rend="italic">Pepper</hi>. </s><s n="s4.5;p11.11">Hence, departing from purposive approach. </s><s n="s5.5;p11.11">Finally, in order to do justice, the courts, in my opinion, should find a balance between justice and preserving the parliamentary materials. </s></p></div1></body><back><div1 type="bibliography"><head rend="underlined bold">TABLE OF CASES</head><p>A E Beckett &amp; Sons (Lyndons) Ltd v Midland Electricity plc [2001] 1 WLR 281</p><p>Carlill v Carbolic Smoke Ball Co. [1893] 1 Q.B. 256</p><p>Donoghue v Stevenson [1932] A.C. 562</p><p>Pepper v Hart [1993] A.C. 593</p><p>Pickstone v Freeman Plc [1989] A.C. 66</p><p>Melluish vBMI (No. 3) Ltd. [1996] 1 A.C. 454</p><p>Miller v Taylor [1769] 4 Burr 2303 </p><p>Re Bishopgate Investment Ltd. [1993] Ch 452</p><p>Re Dean of York [1841] 2 QB 1</p><p>R v Secretary of State for Foreign and Commonwealth Affairs, ex p Rees-Mogg [1994] 1 All ER 457</p><p>R v Secretary of State for the Environment, Transport and the Regions, ex p Spath Holme Ltd. [2001] 2 WLR 15</p><p>Three Rivers District Council v Bank of England (No. 2), [1996] 2 ALL ER 363</p></div1><div1 type="bibliography"><head rend="underlined bold">Bibliography</head><p>Boone, Kevin, '<hi rend="italic">Kevin's English Law Glossary: Pepper v Hart (1993)</hi>' April 2002 </p><p><seg type="URL" n="http://www.kevinboone.com/PF_lawglos_Pepper_v_Hart_(1993).html"/></p><p>Holborn, Guy, <hi rend="italic">Legal Research Guide,</hi> 2<hi rend="sup">nd</hi> Edition, 2001</p><p>Lord Hailsham of St. Marylebone, <hi rend="italic">Halsbury's Laws of England, Volume 44(1</hi>), 4<hi rend="sup">th</hi> Edition 1995 Butterworths</p><p>Lord Steyn, '<hi rend="italic">Pepper v Hart: a re-</hi>examination' 21 Oxford Journal of Legal Studies 2001 </p><p>Marshall, Geoffrey, '<hi rend="italic">Hansard and interpretation of statutes</hi>' in </p><p>Oliver, Dawn and Drewry, Gavin, <hi rend="italic">The Law and Parliament</hi>, 1998 Butterworths</p><p>Slapper, Gary and Kelly, David, <hi rend="italic">The English legal System,</hi> 7<hi rend="sup">th</hi> Edition, 2004</p><p>Statutory Interpretation, Hansard, </p><p><seg type="URL" n="http://www.richinstyle.com/masterclass/smallerblack/interpretation.html"/></p><p>Vogenauer, Stefan, '<hi rend="italic">A retreat from Pepper v Hart?'</hi> Oxford Journal of Legal Studies Advance Access, 7 September 2005</p></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
