<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_0137m" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>"Threat of Islam or threat to Islam?" Critically assess the conflict between Islam and the West.</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">deleted: header: student number, word coumt, modue name and number, assessment title, date; footer: page numbers</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">3</p><p n="date">2007-04</p><p n="module title">Middle East Regional Relations</p><p n="module code">PO365</p><p n="genre family">Essay</p><p n="discipline">Politics</p><p n="disciplinary group">SS</p><p n="grade">M</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">5445</p><p n="number of s-units">182</p><p n="number of p">40</p><p n="number of tables">0</p><p n="number of figures">0</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">0</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">0</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">29.9</p><p n="average s-units per p">4.5</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">f</p><p n="year of birth">1985</p><p n="first language">English</p><p n="education">OSA</p><p n="course">Politics</p><p n="student ID">0137</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><docTitle><titlePart rend="bold">"Threat of Islam or threat to Islam?" Critically assess the conflict between Islam and the West. </titlePart></docTitle></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="section"><p n="p1.40"><s n="s1.4;p1.40">Any scholar embarking on the ambitious voyage to examine "Islam" in its entirety will have to first acknowledge the complexity of this field. </s><s n="s2.4;p1.40">The ideologically-loaded word, "Islam" in itself, denotes "more than fourteen centuries of history, a billion and a third people and a religious and cultural tradition of enormous diversity"<ref target="BAWE_0137m-ftnote.001"/>. </s><s n="s3.4;p1.40">Many have devoted their time and effort to examine "Islam" in its totality however it is clearly out of a question to attempt that comprehensive endeavour here. </s><s n="s4.4;p1.40">On this note, the essay will attempt to provide a sufficient and useful account of the perceived and real conflicts between "Islam" and the "West"; stringing together various perspectives and arguments, finally coming to terms that the perceived threat of "Islam" brings a greater backlash of Islamism. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0137m-ftnote.001"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Bernard Lewis, <hi rend="italic">The Crisis of Islam: Holy war and Unholy Terror</hi> (New York: The Random House Publishing Group, 2003), pp. 3. </s></p></note><p n="p2.40"><s n="s1.2;p2.40">The centrality of this essay will reject the idea that the conflict of "Islam" and the "West" is and should be taken as a given, based on some arguments that are divided into three parts. </s><s n="s2.2;p2.40">Firstly, the </s></p><p n="p3.40"><s n="s1.6;p3.40">Islamic threat has been based upon some unjust and myopic scholarly perspectives, of which the essay hopes to address from the start. </s><s n="s2.6;p3.40">Following that, the essay will reiterate the view that "Islam" has always been perceived wrongly as a threat in itself, which becomes a self fulfilling prophecy. </s><s n="s3.6;p3.40">With that, the threat of "Islam" stems not from "Islam" per se but originates from socio-economic and political factors that have radicalized it from its religious roots. </s><s n="s4.6;p3.40">The last section will examine facets of the Islamist threat, manifested in various dimensions beyond the radical Islamic component. </s><s n="s5.6;p3.40">Moving on, the essay will also illustrate that the Islamic threat is not a coherent threat and it faces more threat from within than it poses to the "West". </s><s n="s6.6;p3.40">The essay will conclude by reviewing the implications of a perceived Islamic threat and a real Islamist threat on policy making and conflict management. </s></p><p n="p4.40"><s n="s1.2;p4.40">Having established the argumentative scope, it is also crucial to lay the definitional parameters of the essay. </s><s n="s2.2;p4.40">It should be forewarned that generic terms like "Islam" and the "West" will be used in quotation marks as there is no Islam or the West per se that can be treated as "a single cohesive, coherent comprehensible monolithic entity"<ref target="BAWE_0137m-ftnote.002"/>. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0137m-ftnote.002"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Graham E Fuller and Ian O Lesser, <hi rend="italic">A Sense of Siege: the Geopolitics of Islam and the West</hi> (Colorado: Westview Press, 1995), pp. 2. </s></p></note><p n="p5.40"><s n="s1.6;p5.40">To begin with, "Islam" will be the most common word in this essay and yet also the hardest word to define. </s><s n="s2.6;p5.40">Edward Said asserted rightly that the term "Islam" is also unjustly overused and is an 'unreliable index' of the phenomena that we are trying to comprehend" <ref target="BAWE_0137m-ftnote.003"/>. </s><s n="s3.6;p5.40">Therefore, there has to be a distinction drawn between "Islam" as a religion and "Islam" as a contemporary political phenomenon. </s><s n="s4.6;p5.40">If taken at face value, the former usage of the term "Islam" denotes a "monotheistic religion in existence for more than 1400 years"<ref target="BAWE_0137m-ftnote.004"/> and the civilisation that "flourished under the aegis of that religion" <ref target="BAWE_0137m-ftnote.005"/>. </s><s n="s5.6;p5.40">Its core beliefs are based on the <hi rend="italic">Qur' an</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Sunna</hi> of the Prophet Muhammad, believed to be the messenger of God.<ref target="BAWE_0137m-ftnote.006"/> Strictly speaking, religious "Islam" itself cannot be translated into a real threat against the "West" as it is detached from politics and does not resist the supremacy of the "West" in international political and economic realms.<ref target="BAWE_0137m-ftnote.007"/> Instead, the focus of the essay will be on political "Islam", more appropriately coined as Islamism. </s><s n="s6.6;p5.40">It is a discourse that tries to centre "Islam" within the political order and also refers to modern political movements that are based on Islamist principles.<ref target="BAWE_0137m-ftnote.008"/> In all, it consists of a set of varied ideologies that aspire to adopt <hi rend="italic">Shari' a</hi> or Islamic law to its full extent and reject secular forms of governments.<ref target="BAWE_0137m-ftnote.009"/> Within this strand of "Islam", fundamentalist Islamism will be the radicalized branch of Islamism, when set in practice, could potentially pose a threat to the "West" or to "Islam" itself. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0137m-ftnote.003"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">S. Sayyid, <hi rend="italic">A Fundamental Fear: Eurocentrism and the Emergence of Islamism</hi>, (London: Zed Books Ltd, 2003), pp.36. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0137m-ftnote.004"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">B.A. Roberson, eds., <hi rend="italic">Shaping the Current Islamic Reformation</hi> (London: Frank Cass Publishers), the glossary section. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0137m-ftnote.005"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Lewis, <hi rend="italic">The Crisis of Islam: Holy War and Unholy Terror</hi>, pp. 13. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0137m-ftnote.006"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Roberson, <hi rend="italic">Shaping the Current Islamic,</hi> the glossary section. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0137m-ftnote.007"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Shireen T. Hunter, <hi rend="italic">The Future of Islam and the West: Clash of Civilizations or Peaceful Coexistence</hi> (Westport: Praeger Publishers, 1998), pp. 14. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0137m-ftnote.008"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Fuller and Lesser, <hi rend="italic">A Sense of Siege: the Geopolitics of Islam and the West</hi>, pp. 6. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0137m-ftnote.009"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Roberson, <hi rend="italic">Shaping the Current Islamic,</hi> the glossary section. </s></p></note><p n="p6.40"><s n="s1.5;p6.40">On the other side of the spectrum, the coherence of the "West" as a single entity also continues to be contested as it can be taken differently in different contexts from different perspectives. </s><s n="s2.5;p6.40">Historically, the "West" can refer to "all former colonial nations which have conquered and dominated most of the Muslim World at some point in history"<ref target="BAWE_0137m-ftnote.010"/> or it can refer to "the entire industrialized world including Japan"<ref target="BAWE_0137m-ftnote.011"/> in an economic sense. </s><s n="s3.5;p6.40">Despite the diversity in its meanings, the consistency lies in that the "West" refers not so much to a geographic location, rather as a symbol of a way of life or values which threatens or stands in stark contrast with certain segments of the Muslim population. </s><ref target="BAWE_0137m-ftnote.012"/><s n="s4.5;p6.40">In this essay, the "West" will refer to a set of cultural values that are embodied within more or less liberal and democratic regimes based on the "sovereignty" of the people" rather than "God's right to control all aspects of human individual and collective life." </s><ref target="BAWE_0137m-ftnote.013"/><s n="s5.5;p6.40">It is a belief system synonymous with a secular political system and a capitalist economic system embedded within a globalized arena, with the United States as the de facto trend setter and leader. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0137m-ftnote.010"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Fuller and Lesser, <hi rend="italic">A Sense of Siege: the Geopolitics of Islam and the West</hi>, pp. 7. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0137m-ftnote.011"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid., pp. 7. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0137m-ftnote.012"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ron Greaves and Theodore Gabriel, "Introduction", in Ron Greaves, Theodore Gabriel, Yvonne Haddad and Jane Idleman Smith, eds., <hi rend="italic">Islam &amp; the West Post 9/11</hi> (Aldershot: Ashgate Publishing Limited, 2004), pp. 1. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0137m-ftnote.013"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid., pp. 1. </s></p></note></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">The Threat of "Islam" as a Myth </head><p n="p7.40"><s n="s1.4;p7.40">The origins of the Islamic threat as a perceived reality must be examined within the contemporary context of post-September 11 <hi rend="sup">th</hi> events. </s><s n="s2.4;p7.40">Since then, there has been a wholesale branding of all Muslims as fundamental Islamists and events in the world project the image of Muslims as the "new enemy of the West" <ref target="BAWE_0137m-ftnote.014"/>. </s><s n="s3.4;p7.40">It is debatable what the Islamic threat is as it is not one of political analysis rather one of belief. </s><ref target="BAWE_0137m-ftnote.015"/><s n="s4.4;p7.40">Hence, it is important in academic scholarship that we take a step backwards and examine how "Islam" came to be unjustly perceived as a direct threat to the "West" which became nothing more than an established myth. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0137m-ftnote.014"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Greaves and Gabriel,<hi rend="italic"> Islam &amp; the West Post 9/11</hi>, pp. 4. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0137m-ftnote.015"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Jochen Hippler and Andrea Lueg, "Conclusion: Dealing with Islam" in Jochen Hippler and Andrea Lueg, eds.,<hi rend="italic">The Next Threat: Western Perceptions of Islam</hi> (London: Plato Press, 1995), pp. 154. </s></p></note><div2><head rend="bold">I. Myopic Academic Approaches to "Islam"</head><p n="p8.40"><s n="s1.6;p8.40">There are a number of methodological flaws when examining "Islam" which leads to limitations in its findings and conclusions. </s><s n="s2.6;p8.40">Firstly, we often view "Islam" and events in the Muslim world through the "prism of violence and terrorism" <ref target="BAWE_0137m-ftnote.016"/> which has led to a failure to see beyond the "breadth and depth of contemporary Islam"<ref target="BAWE_0137m-ftnote.017"/>. </s><s n="s3.6;p8.40">It is true that the Middle East region has consistently appeared to be the most unstable and strategically volatile region in the whole Third World, and incidents such as the Suez Crisis, Arab-Israeli wars, Iranian Revolution, Iran-Iraq war of 1980-88, Gulf war of 1990-91 are sufficient to affirm the fact. </s><s n="s4.6;p8.40">Even if the Middle East is a volatile region, the threats it posed are more political than religious. </s><s n="s5.6;p8.40">Basing these political crises on "Islam" seems to advocate that "Islam" as a religion is to be directly blamed for advocating such inhumane acts of violence and terrorism. </s><s n="s6.6;p8.40">It is crucial that we distinguish between a religious or Islamic challenge and a direct political Islamism threat which "requires walking the fine line between myth and reality" <ref target="BAWE_0137m-ftnote.018"/>. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0137m-ftnote.016"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">John L. Esposito, <hi rend="italic">The Islamic Threat: Myth or Reality</hi> (Oxford: Oxford University Press, 1992), pp. 199. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0137m-ftnote.017"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid., pp. 199. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0137m-ftnote.018"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid., pp. 5. </s></p></note><p n="p9.40"><s n="s1.5;p9.40">Secondly, most academic accounts of "Islam" tend to view it from an Orientalist approach. </s><s n="s2.5;p9.40">It seems as though it is a given that the behaviours of Islamic, Muslim or Middle Eastern societies should be analyzed through the lens of "Islam", neglecting other socioeconomic and political factors. </s><ref target="BAWE_0137m-ftnote.019"/><s n="s3.5;p9.40">In line with Edward Said's anti-Orientalist approach, the development of the region's politics and the Islamist threat have to be analyzed within specific frameworks of time and space with their unique circumstances, geopolitics, socioeconomic and political dimensions. </s><s n="s4.5;p9.40">"Islam" as a socio- political system has to be contextualized in order to be made concrete ,<ref target="BAWE_0137m-ftnote.020"/> and cannot be solely explained in reference to a fixated set of religious doctrines. </s><ref target="BAWE_0137m-ftnote.021"/><s n="s5.5;p9.40">Hence, the threat of "Islam" cannot be a threat in itself as there is nothing within the religious doctrines of "Islam" that sets it on a collision path with the "West". </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0137m-ftnote.019"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Fred Halliday, <hi rend="italic">Islam and the Myth of Confrontation</hi> (London: I.B. Tauris, 2003), pp.13. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0137m-ftnote.020"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Halliday, <hi rend="italic">Islam and the Myth of Confrontation</hi>, pp. 2. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0137m-ftnote.021"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid., pp. 42. </s></p></note><p n="p10.40"><s n="s1.7;p10.40">Moreover, many have envisioned a potential threat of "Islam" based on a historical perspective. </s><s n="s2.7;p10.40">This view rests on the complex and long standing tension between the Islamic world and a predominantly Christian and secular Europe. </s><s n="s3.7;p10.40">This brings to mind, the rise of "Islam" in the late 7 <hi rend="sup">th</hi> century which was halted by the medieval wars of the Christian Crusaders that followed on with the collapse of the Ottoman Empire and finally ended when "European states subjugated the Muslim world to their political and economic domination"<ref target="BAWE_0137m-ftnote.022"/>. </s><s n="s4.7;p10.40">It is easy to base the contemporary conflict of "Islam" and the "West" based on this historical incompatibility between "Islam" and Christendom yet this is to deny the fact that "Islam" is a socio-political system capable of evolution and adaptation. </s><s n="s5.7;p10.40">This also alludes to the fact that "Islam" is inherently in conflict with the "West" which is an oversight on our part to envision prospects for cooperation and compromise in the modern context. </s><s n="s6.7;p10.40">After all, the United States' invasion of Iraq in 2003 was not based on what happened centuries ago between Christendom and the Ottoman Empire, rather it was based on current geopolitical issues and security fears. </s><s n="s7.7;p10.40">It would be more practical if we operate this discussion of the threat between "Islam" and the "West" on more functional lines than on an abstract level of a clash of civilisation. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0137m-ftnote.022"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Steve Niva, "Between Clash and Co-optation: US Foreign Policy and the Specter of Islam", <hi rend="italic">Middle East Report</hi>, 208(1998), pp.29. </s></p></note><p n="p11.40"><s n="s1.5;p11.40">Lastly, it is evident that most scholarship on "Islam" and Islamic societies stem from a secular Westernized perspective. </s><s n="s2.5;p11.40">Indeed, most scholars are schooled with a secular academic bias and lack an insider perspective in Islamic societies. </s><s n="s3.5;p11.40">John Esposito also commented on the limitations of secular work as "secular presuppositions have been a major obstacle to reduce "Islam" to fundamentalism and fundamentalism to religious extremism"<ref target="BAWE_0137m-ftnote.023"/>. </s><s n="s4.5;p11.40">Furthermore, most scholars have analyzed the issue from a top down approach and tend to focus on governments and elites. </s><s n="s5.5;p11.40">This results in a lack of understanding of the totality of the threat of "Islam" in all its dimensions, especially in "understanding the nature of populist movements in general and Islamic movements in particular."<ref target="BAWE_0137m-ftnote.024"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0137m-ftnote.023"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Esposito, <hi rend="italic">The Islamic Threat: Myth or Reality</hi>, pp. 200. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0137m-ftnote.024"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid., pp. 206. </s></p></note></div2><div2><head rend="bold">II. Unjust Public Portrayals of "Islam"</head><p n="p12.40"><s n="s1.2;p12.40">Apart from academic short-sightedness, skewed media portrayals and coverage of political events will lead to a limited understanding of the real issues beneath the explosive events in the Islamic world. </s><s n="s2.2;p12.40">A view espoused by John Esposito stated clearly that a range of selective presentation and analysis of "Islam" and events "fails to tell the whole story... while it sheds some light, it is a partial light that obscures and distorts the full picture." <ref target="BAWE_0137m-ftnote.025"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0137m-ftnote.025"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Andrea Lueg, "The Perception of Islam in Western Debate", in Jochen Hippler and Andrea Lueg, eds., <hi rend="italic">The Next Threat: Western Perceptions of Islam</hi> (London: Plato Press, 1995), pp. 7. </s></p></note><p n="p13.40"><s n="s1.3;p13.40">More often than not, we are focusing on a perceived threat that has been manipulated and hijacked for the wrong reasons. </s><s n="s2.3;p13.40">The threat of "Islam" often depends on how the "West" portrays "Islam" which also arises from focusing on the wrong dimensions. </s><s n="s3.3;p13.40">It is evident how the western media has played along the religious lines, by echoing public's fears of "The Sword of Islam", "The Islamic Threat" or "The Green Peril" - after the media has discovered the market value of this theme and how politicians have exaggerated external threats to divert attention from national issues. </s></p><p n="p14.40"><s n="s1.5;p14.40">Clearly, the threat of "Islam" is more of a perceived threat than a real threat. </s><s n="s2.5;p14.40">And the costs for thinking this way will be burdened on the "West". </s><s n="s3.5;p14.40">As Patrick Bannerman, a former diplomat and analyst for the British Foreign Office observed in his book <hi rend="italic">Islam in Perspective</hi>, "how non-Muslims think of Islam conditions the manner in which they deal with Muslims, which in turn conditions how Muslims think of and deal with non-Muslims" <ref target="BAWE_0137m-ftnote.026"/>. </s><s n="s4.5;p14.40">A related example comes from the Cold War experience; it was fuelled based on mutual misperceptions and distrust. </s><s n="s5.5;p14.40">Essentially, the intensification of the fear and demonizing of the enemy blinded many to the true and limited extent of the Soviet threat during the Cold War.<ref target="BAWE_0137m-ftnote.027"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0137m-ftnote.026"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Esposito, <hi rend="italic">The Islamic Threat: Myth or Reality</hi>, pp. 169. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0137m-ftnote.027"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid., pp. 168. </s></p></note><p n="p15.40"><s n="s1.6;p15.40">With that, it is safe to assert that the perceived threat of "Islam" may be a self fulfilling prophecy. </s><s n="s2.6;p15.40">This backlash arises when we placed all fundamentalist ideologies, movements and groups under the same branch of "Islam" and perceived it as a threat in its totality. </s><s n="s3.6;p15.40">This serves to alienate even the most moderate Islamist groups, such as the Muslim Brotherhood which aspires to reform society according to Islamic laws with a just cause without infringing on the rights of others. </s><s n="s4.6;p15.40">In effect, seeing "Islam" as a threat accentuates the "bloody borders" <ref target="BAWE_0137m-ftnote.028"/> between the "West" and "Islam" more evidently. </s><s n="s5.6;p15.40">Hence, our short-sightedness ironically achieves what it fears most; the intensification of Islamist tendencies and their radicalization. </s><s n="s6.6;p15.40">It is also negligence on our part to focus on the symptoms of the problems rather than eradicate the root causes of the problems that have radicalized or materialized "Islam" into militant Islamism. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0137m-ftnote.028"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Manus I. Midlarsky, "Democracy and Islam: Implications for Civilizational Conflict and the Democratic Peace", <hi rend="italic">International Studies Quarterly</hi>, 42 (1998), pp. 489. </s></p></note></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">Rise of the Islamist Threat</head><p n="p16.40"><s n="s1.2;p16.40">Thus far, it has been established that "Islam" as a threat remains a myth; hence the threat of "Islam" is an unlikely notion. </s><s n="s2.2;p16.40">However, this is not to deny that fundamentalist Islamism can be hijacked and exploited to further other means which could be a threat to the "West". </s></p><p n="p17.40"><s n="s1.7;p17.40">Firstly, it is radical Islamism, a strand of "Islam" that seems diabolically opposed to the "West". </s><s n="s2.7;p17.40">Examined in its religious context, "Islam" is neither opposed to the "West", much less inevitably in conflict with the "West". </s><s n="s3.7;p17.40">Proponents of the threat of "Islam" often allude to the violence and conflicts that are encouraged by an Islamic principle, <hi rend="italic">Jihad</hi> (holy war), which is mentioned in the <hi rend="italic">Qur'an.</hi> </s><s n="s4.7;p17.40">In a strict Islamic sense, <hi rend="italic">Jihad</hi>, literally means striving or struggle for a defensive cause to protect the cause of God, <hi rend="italic">Allah</hi>. </s><s n="s5.7;p17.40">It is waged against oppression of the faith and the faith community. </s><s n="s6.7;p17.40">In theory, <hi rend="italic">Jihad</hi> is only legitimate when it is used in a constructive and defensive sense. </s><s n="s7.7;p17.40">In reality, this Islamic belief has often been abused for the wrong cause. </s></p><p n="p18.40"><s n="s1.5;p18.40">In the Islamic world, radical leaders like Saddam Hussein, has called for a <hi rend="italic">Jihad</hi> in the Gulf war to legitimize his aggressive policies. </s><s n="s2.5;p18.40">Al Qaeda, the Islamist militant group behind the 9/11 attacks has also recruited members based on the extreme version of the duty of Jihad, reinforced by videos that show Muslims being killed in Chechnya, Iraq, Kashmir and Lebanon.<ref target="BAWE_0137m-ftnote.029"/> In the western media, it is often the radicalized version of <hi rend="italic"> jihad</hi> that is predominant. </s><s n="s3.5;p18.40">In an article in a time magazine, it is written that "guns and prayer go together in the fundamentalist battle" <ref target="BAWE_0137m-ftnote.030"/>. </s><s n="s4.5;p18.40">This skewed view of Islamism neglects the reality that extremism is no more the monopoly of "Islam" than it is the monopoly of other religions, including Christianity. </s><s n="s5.5;p18.40">In actuality, radical "Islam" is certainly not advocated from its religious base, rather from "secular radical ideologies exogenous to Islam and the Islamic world" <ref target="BAWE_0137m-ftnote.031"/>. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0137m-ftnote.029"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Joseph S. Nye, Jr., "Just don't mention the War on Terrorism", International Herald Tribune, 8 February 2007, pp. 1. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0137m-ftnote.030"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Lueg, <hi rend="italic">The Next Threat: Western Perceptions of Islam,</hi> pp. 12. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0137m-ftnote.031"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Hunter, <hi rend="italic">The Future of Islam and the West: Clash of Civilizations or Peaceful Coexistence,</hi> pp. 71. </s></p></note><p n="p19.40"><s n="s1.4;p19.40">Most evidently, the manifestation of the Islamist threat is the rise of radical Islamist militant groups. </s><s n="s2.4;p19.40">The "West" and Islamic states have every reason to fear radical Islamist movements that operate independently of governments as they are often more mobile on attacks and also more harder to pinpoint - states are answerable, movements are not. </s><ref target="BAWE_0137m-ftnote.032"/><s n="s3.4;p19.40">Furthermore, the success of one group may lend moral, material and ideological support to other radical movements on the world scene. </s><ref target="BAWE_0137m-ftnote.033"/><s n="s4.4;p19.40">Recognizing this threat, it would be futile to try and resolve the problem without addressing the underlying factors that radicalized Islamism into its militant form.<ref target="BAWE_0137m-ftnote.034"/> It is important to note that even the terrorist group, Al Qaeda that has depended on "Islam" to justify their actions, are in actuality, occupied with "contemporary political concerns and convenience rather than any generic loyalty to a religion".<ref target="BAWE_0137m-ftnote.035"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0137m-ftnote.032"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Fuller and Lesser, <hi rend="italic">A Sense of Siege: the Geopolitics of Islam and the West</hi>, pp. 118. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0137m-ftnote.033"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid., pp. 118. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0137m-ftnote.034"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Khashan, "The New World Order and the Tempo of Militant Islam", pp. 21. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0137m-ftnote.035"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Halliday, <hi rend="italic">Islam and the Myth of Confrontation</hi>, pp. X of Preface. </s></p></note><p n="p20.40"><s n="s1.4;p20.40">Situating this Islamist threat in time and place, it is vital that states are aware of some generic factors that could possibly lead to the rise of militant Islamism. </s><s n="s2.4;p20.40">As the French scholar Gilles Kepel reiterated in his book, <hi rend="italic">Jihad: the Trail of Political Islam,</hi> there are a mixture of factors that unify two core social groups; the "urban poor" and the "pious middle classes", behind such radical Islamist movements.<ref target="BAWE_0137m-ftnote.036"/> These factors include the failure of secular nationalist elites to meet the hopes and aspirations of their people, the failure to incorporate Islamist participation in the political arena, the uneven economic development and wealth distribution, lastly, the erosion of cultural and religious norms and values that define the Islamic faith. </s><s n="s3.4;p20.40">More often, geopolitical events added fuel to the fire. </s><s n="s4.4;p20.40">For example, the oil revolution of the 1970s and the ensuing oil wealth enabled Saudi Arabia to propagate its Islamic movement, Wahhabism "which provided fertile ground for the growth and maturation of militant Islamic tendencies" <ref target="BAWE_0137m-ftnote.037"/> More notably, the Iranian Revolution in 1979 provided the blueprint for the success of radical Islamism in contemporary politics. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0137m-ftnote.036"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Gilles Kepel, <hi rend="italic">Jihad : The Trail of Political Islam</hi> (London : I.B. Tauris, 2002), pp. 67. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0137m-ftnote.037"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Hunter, <hi rend="italic">The Future of Islam and the West: Clash of Civilizations or Peaceful Coexistence,</hi> pp. 108. </s></p></note><p n="p21.40"><s n="s1.6;p21.40">Indeed, the "West" fears Islamism for its link to Islamic terrorism which has manifested itself all over the world in different forms. </s><s n="s2.6;p21.40">It is a legitimate threat yet it is naïve for us to deem "terrorism as an authentic expression of the predominant values of Islam"<ref target="BAWE_0137m-ftnote.038"/>. </s><s n="s3.6;p21.40">Terrorism is essentially a political struggle fought in the name of religion by those who feel powerless seeking to undermine the perceived power of a targeted group. </s><s n="s4.6;p21.40">Therefore, the West's containment of radical Islamism or contemporary terrorism is legitimate only to the extent that it also respects and recognizes the benign elements of other Islamist groups which are all part of this widespread revivalist trend. </s><s n="s5.6;p21.40">Many other moderate Islamist movements have emphasized change through non violent channels; the political and social transformation of society. </s><s n="s6.6;p21.40">Opting for a military confrontation without understanding the diversity of Islamism will only carry the "risk of politicizing hence radicalizing - increasing the numbers of the pacifist Islamic multitude"<ref target="BAWE_0137m-ftnote.039"/>. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0137m-ftnote.038"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Khaled Abou El Fadl, "Islam and the Theology of Power", <hi rend="italic">Middle East Report</hi>, 221(2001), pp. 28. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0137m-ftnote.039"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Khashan, "The New World Order and the Tempo of Militant Islam", pp. 23. </s></p></note><p n="p22.40"><s n="s1.2;p22.40">At this junction, it is evident that the only direct threat Islamism poses is in the rise of radical Islamist groups. </s><s n="s2.2;p22.40">There are also other indirect manifestations of Islamist threats which are threats posed by Islamic states, societies and communities. </s></p><p n="p23.40"><s n="s1.4;p23.40">Firstly, there are socio developments in Islamic states that may have detrimental spill over effects on the "West". </s><s n="s2.4;p23.40">This is epitomized by an impending demographic threat caused by population explosions in Middle Eastern countries which are spilling into the United States or Europe through refugee movements and migration. </s><s n="s3.4;p23.40">There are problems of integration, assimilation and racism with regards to the large inflow of Muslims into countries such as Great Britain and France which puts strain on the social fabric. </s><ref target="BAWE_0137m-ftnote.040"/><s n="s4.4;p23.40">The migration policies and treatment of Muslim residents will also play a substantial role affecting the nature of relations between "Islam" and the "West".<ref target="BAWE_0137m-ftnote.041"/> This is illustrated through European unease at the prospect of Turkey's entry into the European Union as it would bring about potentially unrestricted migration of about 60 million Muslims into the European countries.<ref target="BAWE_0137m-ftnote.042"/> More examples would include the controversies over the "headscarf affair" in France where Muslims girls were suspended from school for wearing headscarves and the backlash against Denmark's diplomatic relations with Islamic states when the Danish newspaper <hi rend="italic">Jyllands-Posten</hi> published a dozen mockery cartoons of the prophet Muhammad. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0137m-ftnote.040"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Esposito, <hi rend="italic">The Islamic Threat: Myth or Reality</hi>, pp. 176. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0137m-ftnote.041"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Fuller and Lesser, <hi rend="italic">A Sense of Siege: the Geopolitics of Islam and the West</hi>, pp. 53. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0137m-ftnote.042"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid., pp. 51. </s></p></note><p n="p24.40"><s n="s1.7;p24.40">Next, there are also sensitive strategic issues which would threaten Western interests if they are not addressed appropriately. </s><s n="s2.7;p24.40">More specifically, such issues include strategic military threats; the role of states on the borderlands between Islamic and Western spheres; pressures and consequences of Western military or humanitarian intervention in the Islamic world.<ref target="BAWE_0137m-ftnote.043"/> Predominantly, the fear and focus has been centred on the development and use of weapons of mass destruction and carrier systems such as missiles. </s><s n="s3.7;p24.40">This fear is heightened when nuclear weapons are produced or stockpiled in a volatile region such as the Middle East. </s><s n="s4.7;p24.40">Such fears have perhaps resulted in direct Western military interventions into "rogue states" such as Iraq and predictably Iran in the near future. </s><s n="s5.7;p24.40">Furthermore, western's strategic alignment with Israel will continue to be a barrier to diplomatic relations with anti-Israel Islamic countries. </s><s n="s6.7;p24.40">With that, western interests will always be threatened as Israel is constantly engulfed by wars waged against Lebanon, fears of an Iranian nuclear threat and the escalation of the Palestinian problem. </s><s n="s7.7;p24.40">With all these issues and fears, it is evident that it is neither the religious character, nor cultural tradition of "Islam" that threatens Western foreign policy but conflicting Islamic interests and actions that may threaten Western interests. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0137m-ftnote.043"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid., pp. 151. </s></p></note></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">From a Threatened "Islam" to a Threat of "Islam"</head><p n="p25.40"><s n="s1.3;p25.40">Till this stage, the contemporary coinage of the threat of "Islam" should be more accurately termed as the threat of radical Islamism. </s><s n="s2.3;p25.40">Even so, most Islamist movements are more concerned with the internal conflicts within the Islamic world than with the outside world. </s><s n="s3.3;p25.40">It is worth noting that Ayatollah Khomeini's rhetoric before and after coming to power was a cry of concern: "Islam is in danger". <ref target="BAWE_0137m-ftnote.044"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0137m-ftnote.044"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Halliday, <hi rend="italic">Islam and the Myth of Confrontation</hi>, pp. 120. </s></p></note><p n="p26.40"><s n="s1.8;p26.40">Reiterating Khomeini's concern on "Islam", it is apparent that "Islam" does not constitute a coherent monolithic threat fundamentally because "Islam" is a fragmented religion in itself. </s><s n="s2.8;p26.40">The multitude of Islamic movements, sects, belief systems that are prevalent within "Islam" is a reflection of this centrifugal pattern.<ref target="BAWE_0137m-ftnote.045"/> Added to that, the fragmentation within "Islam" is compounded by religious, national, linguistic and political differences. </s><s n="s3.8;p26.40">State implementation of "Islam" has also varied markedly in terms of its forms of governments, domestic and foreign policies. </s><s n="s4.8;p26.40">State systems are as diverse as "Saudi Arabia's conservative monarchy, Libya's populist socialist state, Iran's clerical republic and Sudan's military regime" <ref target="BAWE_0137m-ftnote.046"/>. </s><s n="s5.8;p26.40">As a result, external relations between "West" and Muslim states will always be of an uneven nature - a number of Western countries will still have strained relations with some Muslim states while other Western and Muslim states will enjoy cooperative and even cordial ties.<ref target="BAWE_0137m-ftnote.047"/> While "Islam" can influence a Muslim nation's attitude towards the "West", in most cases, the overriding determinant will be national interests.<ref target="BAWE_0137m-ftnote.048"/> This is reflected through the diverse Islamic states' support for and against Al Qaeda's operations. </s><s n="s6.8;p26.40">Iran, Syria and Libya, all countries at odds with the "West", nonetheless denounced what Osama bin Laden and his associates were doing. </s><s n="s7.8;p26.40">Another manifestation of the lack of a coherent Islamic threat is through the fragmentation of radical Islamist movements. </s><s n="s8.8;p26.40">The bloody confrontations among Afghanistan's fundamentalist groups also reinforce this point. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0137m-ftnote.045"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid., pp. 121. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0137m-ftnote.046"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Esposito, <hi rend="italic">The Islamic Threat: Myth or Reality</hi>, pp. 116. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0137m-ftnote.047"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Hunter, <hi rend="italic">The Future of Islam and the West: Clash of Civilizations or Peaceful Coexistence,</hi> pp. 169. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0137m-ftnote.048"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Esposito, <hi rend="italic">The Islamic Threat: Myth or Reality</hi>, pp. 117. </s></p></note><p n="p27.40"><s n="s1.6;p27.40">Additionally, the "Islamic threat" has in recent years come to acquire a more "inward-looking" <ref target="BAWE_0137m-ftnote.049"/> aspect. </s><s n="s2.6;p27.40">The enemy has shifted to not so much the "West" but directed against Muslims within Western and other non-Muslim societies who have "adopted western ways and departed from the comprehensive way of life revealed by God known as Islam"<ref target="BAWE_0137m-ftnote.050"/>. </s><s n="s3.6;p27.40">Islamic communities that have emerged in Britain, France, Germany, and Sweden are religiously, nationally, linguistically and politically diverse. </s><s n="s4.6;p27.40">On top of religious differences, the Muslims of Western Europe who appear homogenous to the non-Islamic world also come from a variety of national backgrounds. </s><s n="s5.6;p27.40">There are predominantly Pakistanis, Indians and Turkish Cypriots in Britain, while France has a variety of Algerians, Moroccans and Tunisians. </s><s n="s6.6;p27.40">Fred Halliday emphasized this diversity when he acknowledged that, "even these national labels conceal local and linguistic divisions - between Kurds and Turks, Algerian Arabs and Kabyles ... "<ref target="BAWE_0137m-ftnote.051"/>. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0137m-ftnote.049"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Halliday, <hi rend="italic">Islam and the Myth of Confrontation</hi>, pp. 160. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0137m-ftnote.050"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid., pp. 160. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0137m-ftnote.051"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid., pp. 112. </s></p></note><p n="p28.40"><s n="s1.5;p28.40">Linked to the above, the spread of "Islamophobia" in Europe also poses a direct threat to "Islam" itself. </s><s n="s2.5;p28.40">A recent report published in May 2002 by the European Monitoring Centre on Racism and Xenophobia (EUMC) which focused on 'Islamophobia' in Europe after September 11 <hi rend="sup">th</hi>, established that the spread of "Islamophobia" and anti-Muslim feelings have became so virulent in the post 9/11 era that it "permeated many levels of understanding: from the most basic of discourse at street level to the rhetoric and politicizing in the hierarchies of national and pan-European governance"<ref target="BAWE_0137m-ftnote.052"/>. </s><s n="s3.5;p28.40">Over the years, a number of sensitized Islamic issues have emerged that have not only fuelled hostility towards the Muslim immigrants, but also strained the social fabric of European communities. </s><s n="s4.5;p28.40">Such include the Islamic protests against Salman Rushdie's <hi rend="italic">The Satanic Verses</hi> and the prominence of Turks as targets of racism in Germany. </s><ref target="BAWE_0137m-ftnote.053"/><s n="s5.5;p28.40">The spread of such anti-Muslimism sentiment is taking place in a broader context of xenophobia that poses a direct threat to "Islam" itself. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0137m-ftnote.052"><p n="pn1.2"><s n="s1.2;pn1.2">Christopher Allen, "Endemically European or a European Epidemic? </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.2">Islamophobia in a post 9/11 Europe", in Ron Greaves, Theodore Gabriel, Yvonne Haddad and Jane Idleman Smith, eds., <hi rend="italic">Islam &amp; the West Post 9/11</hi> (Aldershot: </s></p><p n="pn2.2"><s n="s1.1;pn2.2">Ashgate Publishing Limited, 2004), pp. 134. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0137m-ftnote.053"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Halliday, <hi rend="italic">Islam and the Myth of Confrontation</hi>, pp. 185. </s></p></note><p n="p29.40"><s n="s1.7;p29.40">Lastly, "Islam" with its Islamic communities and states may feel more threatened by the "West" in vital political, cultural, social, military and economic realms more so than "Islam" can be a coherent threat to the "West". </s><s n="s2.7;p29.40">In the political arena, such fears would include political pressures from the "West" to resolve the Arab-Israeli conflict and western alliances with Israel against the Arabic states. </s><s n="s3.7;p29.40">Economically, the oil issue naturally comes to mind, as Muslim states have only in the last two decades "wrested from the West the right to fully possess and control their resources." </s><ref target="BAWE_0137m-ftnote.054"/><s n="s4.7;p29.40">For most of the century, these oil resources were viewed as indispensable to Western economies that Muslim governments had very little control over the use of their own resources. </s><s n="s5.7;p29.40">More so, the economies of the developing Muslim world are also perceived to be deeply connected to the Western economy and its institutions that this dependency translates into a potential vulnerability. </s><s n="s6.7;p29.40">There is often a clash between the financial requirements of the World Bank or International Monetary Fund (IMF) and the socio-economic interests of the Islamic society. </s><s n="s7.7;p29.40">Lastly, with a higher number of peacekeeping, military and humanitarian forces in the Middle East, Islamic societies fear more direct intervention by the "West" in their internal affairs. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0137m-ftnote.054"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Fuller and Lesser, <hi rend="italic">A Sense of Siege: the Geopolitics of Islam and the West</hi>, pp. 83. </s></p></note><p n="p30.40"><s n="s1.4;p30.40">From all these perspectives, "Islam" is fundamentally under threat. </s><s n="s2.4;p30.40">What appears to be a conflict between "Islam" and the external non-Islamic world is above all, a reflection of a conflict within the Islamic world. </s><s n="s3.4;p30.40">Essentially, the threat to "Islam" is as real as the Islamist threat to the "West". </s><s n="s4.4;p30.40">Muslim paranoia is indeed growing in conjunction with a Western's paranoia of "Islam". </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">Managing the Myth, Moderating the Threat</head><p n="p31.40"><s n="s1.2;p31.40">The foremost important task for any policy maker is to separate myth from reality; to separate the real, material, specific and secular threats faced and posed by both Islamic and Western societies from their confused religious expressions; then address these difficulties themselves. </s><s n="s2.2;p31.40">By recognizing that "Islam" per se is not responsible as a strategic threat to the West's vital regional interests in the region; this perspective calls for a new approach to Islamism within the foreign policy establishment. </s></p><p n="p32.40"><s n="s1.3;p32.40">The complexity of the bilateral threat issue between the two spheres requires a flexible mixture of hard and soft approaches to tackle the underlying causes for the rise of radical Islamism. </s><s n="s2.3;p32.40">At the generic level, we must realize that every threat is manifested in different ways and is critical to varying degrees; hence a mixture of hard confrontation and soft engagement will have to be deployed in various cases over time depending on the nature and severity of the situation. </s><s n="s3.3;p32.40">This is epitomized during United States' President Clinton's administration when it applied its "rogue state" doctrine of containment to radically Islamist states such as Iran and Sudan while steadfastly supporting Egypt and Tunisia in their brutal repression of all shades of Islamic activism in the name of eradicating "terrorism".<ref target="BAWE_0137m-ftnote.055"/> On the other hand, it also urged "the military regime in Algeria to initiate a dialogue with "moderate" Islamists and to include them in democratic elections under international supervision" <ref target="BAWE_0137m-ftnote.056"/>. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0137m-ftnote.055"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Niva, "Between Clash and Co-optation: US Foreign Policy and the Specter of Islam", pp.26. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0137m-ftnote.056"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid., pp. 26. </s></p></note><p n="p33.40"><s n="s1.4;p33.40">Onto a more contemporary example, Britain has recently banned the catchphrase "war on terrorism".<ref target="BAWE_0137m-ftnote.057"/> This marked a turning point in British political thinking and foreign policy making. </s><s n="s2.4;p33.40">In a speech delivered by Britain's Prime Minister, Tony Blair, to the Los Angeles World Affairs Council in August 2006, he called for a "complete renaissance"<ref target="BAWE_0137m-ftnote.058"/> on foreign policy to combat "reactionary Islam".<ref target="BAWE_0137m-ftnote.059"/> More strikingly, he encapsulated the idea of fighting the hard battle with a soft approach by stating that "we will not win the battle against this global extremism unless we win it at the level of values as much as force..." </s><ref target="BAWE_0137m-ftnote.060"/><s n="s3.4;p33.40">Indeed, a larger effort should be devoted to the longer generational struggle of winning the hearts and minds of mainstream Muslims. </s><s n="s4.4;p33.40">On this line of thought, while states should condemn and prevent the rise of radical Islamist groups, states should also facilitate the development of Islamic moderates by supporting their inclusion in political processes which would ultimately subject them to mechanisms of social control thus conforming and transforming them in accordance with the demands of a modern liberal state.<ref target="BAWE_0137m-ftnote.061"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0137m-ftnote.057"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Nye, "Just don't mention the War on Terrorism", pp. 1 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0137m-ftnote.058"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Paul Reynolds, "Blair disputes Bush's Global Tactics", BBC News Website, 2 August 2006, <seg type="URL" n="http://news.bbc.co.uk/go/pr/fr/-/1/hi/uk_politics/5238050.stm"/>. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">Accessed on 1 May 2007. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0137m-ftnote.059"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0137m-ftnote.060"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0137m-ftnote.061"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Niva, "Between Clash and Co-optation: US Foreign Policy and the Specter of Islam", pp. 28. </s></p></note><p n="p34.40"><s n="s1.5;p34.40">In addition, it is important to note the underlying reasons for the rise of radical Islamist groups. </s><s n="s2.5;p34.40">Until the internal problems of these countries are reduced or resolved, Islamism will still emerge as an attractive force against the backdrop of failed secular political system and dire economic status. </s><s n="s3.5;p34.40">Furthermore, the Islamist threat does not stand alone and the "West" will have to assess the consequences of its own actions too. </s><s n="s4.5;p34.40">On one hand, the "West" will have to develop a greater recognition and hostility towards the racism and general ethnic-religious prejudice that is directed against Muslim immigrants in Western societies and Islamic countries. </s><s n="s5.5;p34.40">There must also be a humble recognition on the West's part in acknowledging its failure in preventing the oppression of Islamic peoples whether in Palestine or in Bosnia. </s></p><p n="p35.40"><s n="s1.5;p35.40">With all the above considerations in mind, the "West" should be prepared for new threats manifested in new dimensions. </s><s n="s2.5;p35.40">The future resurgence of "Islam" in Muslim politics will be inevitable, and will be far more indigenously rooted. </s><s n="s3.5;p35.40">Secular institutions may soon be complemented or challenged by Islamic schools, clinics, banks and social services. </s><s n="s4.5;p35.40">More considerably, the emergence of an alternative class of modern educated yet Islamically-oriented elite may challenge "the Western, secular presuppositions and life styles of many in the establishment"<ref target="BAWE_0137m-ftnote.062"/>. </s><s n="s5.5;p35.40">This could be a greater challenge to address as radical Islamism will be camouflaged as a more subtle hue of Islamism which be hard to track, much less tackle. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0137m-ftnote.062"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Esposito, <hi rend="italic">The Islamic Threat: Myth or Reality</hi>, pp. 210. </s></p></note></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">Conclusion</head><p n="p36.40"><s n="s1.1;p36.40">To conclude, there are various tenets encapsulated in this single argument for the threat of "Islamism" as opposed to the threat of "Islam". </s></p><p n="p37.40"><s n="s1.6;p37.40">The subject at hand is that the threat of "Islam" does not and cannot exist. </s><s n="s2.6;p37.40">It does not exist because it is merely a myth that is fabricated from both inaccurate scholarly perceptions and unjust media portrayals that have adopted contemporary Islamic-related events around the world at face value. </s><s n="s3.6;p37.40">More importantly, the notion cannot exist in practice because of the realities of the external and internal struggles that "Islam" is facing today. </s><s n="s4.6;p37.40">"Islam" is neither a real nor a coherent threat in itself. </s><s n="s5.6;p37.40">Dismantling this construct of the stereotyped "enemy" does not signify a lack of criticism; rather it is a prerequisite for more serious critique of the methodologies adopted in constructing it in the first place. </s><s n="s6.6;p37.40">After all, it is realities that should be analyzed, not fantasies. </s></p><p n="p38.40"><s n="s1.3;p38.40">While it is established that the notion of the threat of "Islam" does not and cannot exist, the threat of Islamism is possibly the most accurate concept that forms the basis of a conflict with the "West". </s><s n="s2.3;p38.40">More importantly, the essay has reiterated that the fundamental threat against the "West" comes from the radicalized notion of Islamism which is also militant fundamentalism. </s><s n="s3.3;p38.40">This acknowledges the multifaceted dimensions of an Islamic threat; between the supposed unity of "Islam" and the diversity of its multiple and complex manifestations in the world today, taking shape in various realms - from geopolitics to socio-economics. </s></p><p n="p39.40"><s n="s1.6;p39.40">In approaching this subject at hand, the methodologies adopted must also be critically assessed. </s><s n="s2.6;p39.40">Fundamentally, we should not be accused of double standards when assessing the threat of "Islam" from predominantly a secular or outsider perspective. </s><s n="s3.6;p39.40">According to Jurgen Liminski, we should not seek to impose our own standards on what "Islam" should be as most Islamic countries in the Middle East "live according to a world of associations which cannot be comprehended or judged by European standards"<ref target="BAWE_0137m-ftnote.063"/>. </s><s n="s4.6;p39.40">Ultimately, we are also guilty of "misogyny, aggression, fanaticism and irrationality"<ref target="BAWE_0137m-ftnote.064"/> which are not exclusive to the Islamic world. </s><s n="s5.6;p39.40">It is natural that we adopt completely different standards when we confront the same or different phenomena in other cultures, especially Islamic ones, but it is not an excuse for us to dismiss this biasness of ours. </s><s n="s6.6;p39.40">Contemporary "Islam" challenges the "West" to appreciate the diversity of the Muslim experience and perhaps challenge the "West" to stand by the democratic values it embodies to recognize the right of people and states to determine their way of life and nature of their governments, leaderships and societies.<ref target="BAWE_0137m-ftnote.065"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0137m-ftnote.063"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Lueg, <hi rend="italic">The Next Threat: Western Perceptions of Islam,</hi> pp. 20. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0137m-ftnote.064"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid., pp. 24. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0137m-ftnote.065"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Esposito, <hi rend="italic">The Islamic Threat: Myth or Reality</hi>, pp. 207. </s></p></note><p n="p40.40"><s n="s1.5;p40.40">On this note, it is indeed a challenge to conceive "Islam" in a totally different light, contrary to what we have historically and traditionally perceived without a doubt. </s><s n="s2.5;p40.40">Perhaps the softer side of "Islam" does exist; nevertheless it will also be accompanied by the darker side. </s><s n="s3.5;p40.40">The reality is that there will be newer and more intensified fault lines between "Islam" and the "West" as the two will inevitably meet, yet this does not necessarily translate to an inevitable conflict simply because "the need for the two to live and work together in our increasingly interdependent world has never been greater"<ref target="BAWE_0137m-ftnote.066"/>. </s><s n="s4.5;p40.40">With this realistic picture in mind, Michel Foucault has so aptly reminded us that "the question of "Islam" as a political force is a vital question of our times and will be for several years to come. </s><s n="s5.5;p40.40">The precondition for its treatment with a minimum of intelligence is probably not to start from a platform of hatred". <ref target="BAWE_0137m-ftnote.067"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0137m-ftnote.066"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">H.R.H The Prince of Wales, ''Islam and the West, <hi rend="italic">Arab Law Quarterly</hi>, 9 (1994), pp. 135. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0137m-ftnote.067"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Francois Burgat, <hi rend="italic">Face to Face with Political</hi> Islam (London: I.B. Tauris &amp; Co Ltd, 2003), pp. 117. </s></p></note></div1></body><back><div1 type="bibliography"><head rend="underlined bold">Bibliography</head><div2 type="bibliography"><head rend="underlined bold">Books:</head><p>Allen, Christopher, "Endemically European or a European Epidemic? Islamophobia in a post 9/11 Europe", in Ron Greaves, Theodore Gabriel, Yvonne Haddad and Jane Idleman Smith, eds., <hi rend="italic">Islam &amp; the West Post 9/11</hi>. Aldershot: Ashgate Publishing Limited, 2004, pp. 130 - 146.</p><p>Andrea Lueg, "The Perception of Islam in Western Debate", in Jochen Hippler and Andrea Lueg, eds., <hi rend="italic">The Next Threat: Western Perceptions of Islam</hi> (London: Plato Press, 1995), pp. 7 - 32.</p><p>Burgat, Francois, <hi rend="italic">Face to Face with Political Islam</hi>. London: I.B. Tauris &amp; Co Ltd, 2003.</p><p>Esposito, L. John, <hi rend="italic">The Islamic Threat: Myth or Reality</hi>. Oxford: Oxford University Press, 1992.</p><p>Fuller, E. Graham and Lesser, O. Ian, <hi rend="italic">A Sense of Siege: The Geopolitics of Islam and the West</hi>. Colorado: Westview Press, 1995.</p><p>Greaves, Ron and Gabriel, Theodore, "Introduction", in Ron Greaves, Theodore Gabriel, Yvonne Haddad and Jane Idleman Smith, eds., <hi rend="italic">Islam &amp; the West Post 9/11</hi>. Aldershot: Ashgate Publishing Limited, 2004, pp. 1 -13.</p><p>Halliday, Fred, <hi rend="italic">Islam and the Myth of Confrontation</hi>. London: I.B. Tauris, 2003.</p><p>Hippler, Jochen and Lueg, Andrea, "Conclusion: Dealing with Islam" in Jochen Hippler and Andrea Lueg, eds., <hi rend="italic">The Next Threat: Western Perceptions of Islam.</hi> London: Plato Press, 1995, pp. 154 -159.</p><p>Hunter, T. Shireen, <hi rend="italic">The Future of Islam and the West: Clash of Civilizations or Peaceful Coexistence</hi>. Westport: Praeger Publishers, 1998. </p><p>Kepel, Gilles, <hi rend="italic">Jihad: The Trail of Political Islam.</hi> London : I.B. Tauris, 2002.</p><p>Lewis, Bernand, <hi rend="italic">The Crisis of Islam: Holy war and Unholy Terror</hi>. New York: The Random House Publishing Group, 2003. </p><p>Roberson, B.A., <hi rend="italic">Shaping the Current Islamic Reformation.</hi> London: Frank Cass Publishers, 2003.</p><p>Sayyid, S., <hi rend="italic">A Fundamental Fear: Eurocentrism and the Emergence of Islamism</hi>, London: Zed Books Ltd, 2003. </p></div2><div2 type="bibliography"><head rend="underlined bold">Electronic Journals:</head><p>Fadl, Abou El, Khaled, "Islam and the Theology of Power", <hi rend="italic">Middle East Report</hi>, 221(2001), pp. 28-33.</p><p>H.R.H, The Prince of Wales, "Islam and the West", <hi rend="italic">Arab Law Quarterly</hi>, 9 (1994), pp. 135 -143.</p><p>Midlarsky, I. Manus, "Democracy and Islam: Implications for Civilisational Conflict and The Democratic Peace", <hi rend="italic">International Studies Quarterly</hi>, 42 (1998), pp. 485-511.</p><p>Niva, Steve, "Between Clash and Co-optation: US Foreign Policy and the Specter of Islam", <hi rend="italic">Middle East Report</hi>, 208 (1998), pp. 26-29.</p><p>Khashan, Hilal, "The New World Order and the Tempo of Militant Islam", <hi rend="italic">British Journal of Middle Eastern Studies</hi>, 24 (1997), pp. 5-24.</p></div2><div2 type="bibliography"><head rend="underlined bold">Newspaper Articles:</head><p>Joseph S. Nye, Jr., "Just don't mention the War on Terrorism", <hi rend="italic">International Herald Tribune</hi>, 8 February 2007, pp. 1 -3</p></div2><div2 type="bibliography"><head rend="underlined bold">Websites:</head><p>Paul Reynolds, "Blair disputes Bush's Global Tactics", BBC News Website, 2 August 2006, <seg type="URL" n="http://news.bbc.co.uk/go/pr/fr/-/1/hi/uk_politics/5238050.stm"/>. Accessed on 1 May 2007.</p></div2></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
