<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_0137j" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>What is the more convincing hypothesis - the "China Threat" or the "Peaceful rise of China"?</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">deleted: page numbers</note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">deleted: Word Count: 5485</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">2</p><p n="date">2006-06</p><p n="module title">Politics of Contemporary China</p><p n="module code">PO222</p><p n="genre family">Essay</p><p n="discipline">Politics</p><p n="disciplinary group">SS</p><p n="grade">M</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">5522</p><p n="number of s-units">173</p><p n="number of p">64</p><p n="number of tables">0</p><p n="number of figures">1</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">0</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">0</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">31.9</p><p n="average s-units per p">2.7</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">f</p><p n="year of birth">1985</p><p n="first language">English</p><p n="education">OSA</p><p n="course">Politics</p><p n="student ID">0137</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><titlePart>Student Identification Number: <name type="student ID"/></titlePart><docTitle><titlePart>What is the more convincing hypothesis - the "China Threat" or the "Peaceful rise of China"?</titlePart></docTitle></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined">As China rises, must others bow? </head><p n="p1.64"><s n="s1.2;p1.64">With the 2008 Beijing Olympics in the making, it adds to the global recognition that China is fast emerging and will potentially emerge as the next global power as well as a regional powerhouse in South East Asia. </s><s n="s2.2;p1.64">To account for how and when it emerged in the international limelight is as controversial as the debate on the implications of its rise. </s></p><p n="p2.64"><s n="s1.1;p2.64">The essay rests on a fundamental acknowledgement of China's rise as an on-going dynamic process in an evolving global context and the crux of the essay lies more importantly with the implications of its rise for the major status quo powers, set within the parameters of a global and regional Asia-Pacific context. </s></p><p n="p3.64"><s n="s1.5;p3.64">In essence, there are many accompanying questions that fuel the debate between "the China Threat" and the "Peaceful rise of China"; will China be a satisfied mature power or an insecure defensive nouveau riche power? </s><s n="s2.5;p3.64">Will it flex its muscles or will they atrophy? </s><s n="s3.5;p3.64">Will Beijing seek regional hegemony or peaceful coexistence with its neighbours?<ref target="BAWE_0137j-ftnote.001"/> Such will be the major issues that the essay will focus on and attempt to address. </s><s n="s4.5;p3.64">With such thematic issues in mind, the essay will also flow systematically from the initial definitional to the argumentative and finally to the conclusive section all directed towards the analysis of the implications of China's possession and use of power. </s><s n="s5.5;p3.64">In relation, the entire essay is also metaphorically stringed up by a central theme of the "Great Wall" of China which accompanies and reinforces the current debate on China's strengths and weaknesses seen from outside and within, whether such metaphorical and real walls of fortresses translates to aggressive threat or defensive gestures. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0137j-ftnote.001"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Shambaugh, D. (1996) "Containment or Engagement of China", <hi rend="underlined">International Security</hi> Vol. 21:p. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">181. </s></p></note></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined">Re-emergence of China</head><p n="p4.64"><s n="s1.1;p4.64">The debate on the global implications of China's rise is clearly divided into two separatist camps; the realist conception of the "China Threat" and the liberalist notion of the "Peaceful rise of China". </s></p><p n="p5.64"><s n="s1.2;p5.64">The origins of the "China Threat" thesis arose in the early 1990s when China's economy posted exceptional growth which conveniently translated into a potential military and economic threat in the eyes of western advocates. </s><s n="s2.2;p5.64">Recently, it has been revived with United States' fear of a rising dragon in the Asia Pacific region. <ref target="BAWE_0137j-ftnote.002"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0137j-ftnote.002"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">"Peaceful Rise" <hi rend="underlined">The Economist Print Edition Online,</hi> 24th June 2004. </s></p></note><p n="p6.64"><s n="s1.3;p6.64">As the "China Threat" theory became a common currency, the term "Peaceful Rise" was invented as an important counterweight to the prevalent "China Threat" or "China Collapse" theories in the West. </s><s n="s2.3;p6.64">One of its central tenets is that China will never seek hegemony and asserting it was a skilful diplomatic move to assure others concerned about China's growing economic and military strength. </s><s n="s3.3;p6.64">Yet ironically, the term has also played into the hands of China's critics, some of the more strident of whom "shudder at the mere mention of the word 'rise' in connection with China"<ref target="BAWE_0137j-ftnote.003"/> for it draws parallels with the rise of Germany and Japan. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0137j-ftnote.003"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">"Peaceful Rise" <hi rend="underlined">The Economist Print Edition Online,</hi> 24th June 2004. </s></p></note><p n="p7.64"><s n="s1.4;p7.64">With that in mind, it is more accurate to coin China's rise as a "re-emergence". </s><s n="s2.4;p7.64">As Joseph Nye reinforced rightly that, "China rise is somewhat of a misidentification; it is more of a return to power. </s><s n="s3.4;p7.64">China dominated the Asia-Pacific region from 500 to 1500 and now seeks to restore itself as a great regional power." </s><ref target="BAWE_0137j-ftnote.004"/><s n="s4.4;p7.64">This will set the start of the essay on an unbiased footing which examines the "Peaceful re-emergence of China" vis-à-vis the "China Threat" theory, drawing no parallels with the rise of other previous antagonistic world powers. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0137j-ftnote.004"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Broomfield, E.V. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">(2003) "Perceptions of Danger: the China Threat Theory" <hi rend="underlined">Journal of Contemporary China</hi> Vol. 12: p. 267. </s></p></note></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined">A real fortress? </head><p n="p8.64"><s n="s1.1;p8.64">Before we embark on establishing the implication of its re-emergence, it is also pivotal to establish the qualitative and quantitative indicators that established its re-emergence on the world's scale. </s></p><p n="p9.64"><s n="s1.2;p9.64">Clearly, measuring Chinese real capabilities and intentions at this critical junction in world history "is all the more complicated by the profound domestic social, economic and ecological transformation that China is experiencing even as the global system in which it is now embedded undergoes a structural and political metamorphosis." </s><ref target="BAWE_0137j-ftnote.005"/><s n="s2.2;p9.64">Hence we can only fall back on indicators that are the building blocks of international influence giving rise to "estimated power". </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0137j-ftnote.005"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.3;pn1.1">Kim, S.S. </s><s n="s2.3;pn1.1">(1995) "China in the Post Cold War World", in Harris, S. &amp; Klintworth, G. et al (eds.) <hi rend="underlined">China as a Great Power: Myths, Realities and Challenges in the Asia Pacific Region.</hi> </s><s n="s3.3;pn1.1">Melbourne: Addison Wesley Longman Pty Ltd, p.46. </s></p></note><p n="p10.64"><s n="s1.4;p10.64">The first and most important indicator will be economic statistics. </s><s n="s2.4;p10.64">Its re-emergence has been marked by economics, with growth rates of 8 to 9 percent per year that have led to a tripling of its GNP in less than two decades. </s><s n="s3.4;p10.64">At a more sustainable rate of growth of 6 percent per head, China would reach $10,000-per-person income in thirty years and its economy would then total about $16 trillion, or twice the size of the current American economy.<ref target="BAWE_0137j-ftnote.006"/> Furthermore, it is an economic power by the "nature of the world's economic stake in China." </s><ref target="BAWE_0137j-ftnote.007"/><s n="s4.4;p10.64">The continued growth of the Chinese economy is a sustaining force for the world economy. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0137j-ftnote.006"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Kim, S.S. (ed.) (1998) <hi rend="underlined">China and the World: Chinese foreign policy faces the new millennium.</hi> </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">Colorado: Westview Press, p. 7. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0137j-ftnote.007"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.3;pn1.1">Nathan, A. J. &amp; Ross, R. S. </s><s n="s2.3;pn1.1">(1997) <hi rend="underlined">The Great Wall and the Empty Fortress.</hi> </s><s n="s3.3;pn1.1">London: W.W. Norton &amp; Company, p. 174 </s></p></note><p n="p11.64"><s n="s1.1;p11.64">Militarily, it was only in the late 1990s that China implemented a modernization program that increasingly emphasized the importance of "limited war under high-technology conditions".<ref target="BAWE_0137j-ftnote.008"/> At the same time, the continuing strength of the Chinese economy and the availability of advanced armaments from an economically strapped Russian military industry provided them the opportunities to act on these motivations.<ref target="BAWE_0137j-ftnote.009"/> The result was the emergence of "pockets of excellence" within the ground, air and naval forces of the PLA. <ref target="BAWE_0137j-ftnote.010"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0137j-ftnote.008"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.3;pn1.1">Goldstein, A. </s><s n="s2.3;pn1.1">(2000) "Great Expectations: Interpreting China's Arrival", in Brown, M. E., Cote, O.R, Lynn-Jones, S. M. &amp; Miller, S. E. et al (eds.) <hi rend="underlined">The Rise of China.</hi> </s><s n="s3.3;pn1.1">Massachusetts: MIT Press, p. 10. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0137j-ftnote.009"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Brown, M. E., Cote, O.R, Lynn-Jones, S. M. &amp; Miller, S. E., <hi rend="underlined">The Rise of China.</hi> </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">p. 10. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0137j-ftnote.010"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Brown, M. E., Cote, O.R, Lynn-Jones, S. M. &amp; Miller, S. E., <hi rend="underlined">The Rise of China.</hi> </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">p. 11. </s></p></note><p n="p12.64"><s n="s1.2;p12.64">To top it off, an external catalytic event seemed to reinforce perceptions of China's international standing and likely future role. </s><s n="s2.2;p12.64">The International Monetary Fund's (IMF) decision in 1993 to switch its method of calculating national wealth from one based on currency exchange rates to one relied on purchasing power parity (PPP) resulted in new results of China's GDP that was actually four times larger than previously thought which advanced China to the third place from the tenth. <ref target="BAWE_0137j-ftnote.011"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0137j-ftnote.011"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Goldstein, A., <hi rend="underlined">The Rise of China.</hi> </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">p. 23. </s></p></note></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined">A benign or malign giant behind the Great Wall? </head><p n="p13.64"><s n="s1.3;p13.64">While China seems to showcase its might to the world, the more important issue lies not in how much power China possesses but its intention in its use or abuse of power. </s><s n="s2.3;p13.64">Conceptions of power, threat and peace are all normative concepts in international relations. </s><s n="s3.3;p13.64">Whether we adhere to the "China Threat" theory or the "Peaceful re-emergence" hypothesis, it is evident that the proponents of both schools of thought derived their validness from their own respective domestic and international security concerns yet whether one holds more validity than the other in the current context will depend on the criterion assessment and definition of a threat defined by China as well as the rest of the world. </s></p><p n="p14.64"><s n="s1.2;p14.64">To begin with, theories that focus on the dynamics of changing power relations in the international system all gear favourably towards the "China Threat" thesis. </s><s n="s2.2;p14.64">Theories such as the "hegemonic instability theory" and "balance of power theory" highlight the incongruity between a rising power's growing capabilities and its continued subordinate status in an international political system dominated by a hegemon (United States) that will result in inevitable conflicts. </s></p><p n="p15.64"><s n="s1.3;p15.64">Likewise, historical precedence has shown that nations in economic transition tend to be externally assertive and that accommodating a rising power into the established order has proved difficult and disruptive. </s><s n="s2.3;p15.64">After all, violent conflict followed the rise of Athens and Rome in classical times, Habsburg Empire in 16 <hi rend="sup">th</hi> century, France in the 17 <hi rend="sup">th</hi> century, England in the 18 <hi rend="sup">th</hi> century Germany in the 19 <hi rend="sup">th</hi> and 20 <hi rend="sup">th</hi> century and Japan and Soviet Union in the 20 <hi rend="sup">th</hi> century. </s><s n="s3.3;p15.64">There is no reason to think that China would depart from this norm. </s></p><p n="p16.64"><s n="s1.1;p16.64">Although it would be an intellectual oversight and oversimplification to examine China's re-emergence in merely these historical and theoretical contexts for the translation of strength to threat is not as straightforward as theorists hypothesized; instead there are some "hard and soft"<ref target="BAWE_0137j-ftnote.012"/> arguments which state that the "China Threat" thesis is over-exaggerated and out of sync with reality and it is more apt to align China's re-emergence with the peaceful hypothesis, yet keeping in mind that this hypothesis is also conditional. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0137j-ftnote.012"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Roy, D. (1996) "The China Threat Issue: Major Arguments", <hi rend="underlined">Asian Survey.</hi> </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">Vol. 36: p. 767. </s></p></note><p n="p17.64"><s n="s1.1;p17.64">The following assessment on the implications of China's re-emergence will be examined systematically below, starting with the hard arguments, which centre on outcomes that are logically derived from objective circumstances, dealing with capabilities or anticipated but not unintended consequences. <ref target="BAWE_0137j-ftnote.013"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0137j-ftnote.013"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Roy, D. (1996) "The China Threat Issue: Major Arguments", <hi rend="underlined">Asian Survey.</hi> </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">Vol. 36: p. 767. </s></p></note><div2><head>Disposition as a world power and its foreign policy</head><p n="p18.64"><s n="s1.2;p18.64">Whether China falls into the category of a threat depends on whether it is a risk-acceptant or risk averse, a revolutionary or limited-aims revisionist power and the extent and nature of its revisionist demands as spelt out in its foreign policy. </s><s n="s2.2;p18.64">The formulation and conduct of foreign policy determines China's relations with other nations and hence how China is received or perceived by others. </s></p><p n="p19.64"><s n="s1.2;p19.64">Drawn from the Chinese Defense White Paper of July 1998, there are five concepts which underlay their foreign policy and comprises a "new concept of security" for China: (1) salience of 'comprehensive security' as opposed to 'military security' (2) security as a 'mutual' rather than 'zero-sum' dynamic (3) emphasis on cooperation and dialogue (4) importance of confidence building measures (5) gradual acceptance of the concept of 'transparency'. </s><s n="s2.2;p19.64">In all, its disposition as a world power and the core values underlying its foreign policy is largely crouched in peaceful and defensive terms. </s></p><p n="p20.64"><s n="s1.1;p20.64">Rhetorically, China has aimed to appease the world that it is a "peaceful, cooperative, and responsible great power" but what that self identification entails can only be affirmed by its conduct in international relations and that can only be examined in line with how China have acted in the past and will behave in the present. </s></p></div2><div2><head>Application of power </head><p n="p21.64"><s n="s1.2;p21.64">Even if China professed to be a "peaceful" power as epitomized in its foreign policy values, uncertainties still exist about the use to which China will put its increased power and influence in the region in the future. </s><s n="s2.2;p21.64">The most reliable way to assess whether its present re-emergence translates into future threat or opportunity will be to base it on how China has responded thus far, is responding to changes in the international environment and subsequently derive conclusions on its future responses. </s></p><p n="p22.64"><s n="s1.1;p22.64">China has extended peaceful gestures diplomatically even in the midst of increased militarization. </s></p><p n="p23.64"><s n="s1.2;p23.64">In June 2001, China has promoted a new security forum, the Shanghai Cooperation Organisation which aimed at strengthening border security and countering Islamic extremism. </s><s n="s2.2;p23.64">Since taking up their posts, Mr. Wen Jiabao, China's Premier and President Hu Jintao have been busy trying to present China as a benign emerging nation that is ready to co-operate with others to solve international problems.<ref target="BAWE_0137j-ftnote.014"/> In late 2003, China signed a "treaty of amity and co-operation" with the ten-member Association of South-East Asian Nations: the first non-South-East Asian country to do so. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0137j-ftnote.014"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">"Peaceful Rise" <hi rend="underlined">The Economist Print Edition Online,</hi> 24th June 2004. </s></p></note><p n="p24.64"><s n="s1.4;p24.64">Since its 1979 attack on Vietnam, China has largely been a reactive power, striving not to alter but to adapt to regional patterns of power. </s><s n="s2.4;p24.64">Its diplomacy has been in support of its status quo, aiming not to undermine but to join international regimes.<ref target="BAWE_0137j-ftnote.015"/> China's policies towards Russia, the new Central Asia republics, India, the two Koreas, Japan and the countries of Indochina have sought to consolidate bilateral relationships. </s><s n="s3.4;p24.64">Its military threats against Taiwan were aimed at deterring Taiwan from upsetting the status quo rather than at compelling it to accelerate the pace of reunification. </s><s n="s4.4;p24.64">In the South China Sea, China has acted to maintain historical claims when others challenged them, rather than to extend new claims. <ref target="BAWE_0137j-ftnote.016"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0137j-ftnote.015"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Nathan, A. J. &amp; Ross, R. S., <hi rend="underlined">The Great Wall and the Empty Fortress.</hi> </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">p. 230. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0137j-ftnote.016"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Nathan, A. J. &amp; Ross, R. S., <hi rend="underlined">The Great Wall and the Empty Fortress.</hi> </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">p. 230. </s></p></note><p n="p25.64"><s n="s1.1;p25.64">In essence, from this analysis, it is apparent that China may have the power to pose a threat but lacks the will and incentive to do so. </s></p></div2><div2><head>Potential as a powerful threat </head><p n="p26.64"><s n="s1.1;p26.64">Up to this point, the essay has examined threat in its general form and this section seeks to establish the extent to which the "China Threat" could fall into the various dimensions; economic, military and ideological. </s></p><p n="p27.64"><s n="s1.3;p27.64">As an emerging economic giant, there are legitimate causes for concern from the perspectives of its trading partners, particularly the United States. </s><s n="s2.3;p27.64">China poses a threat because of its infiltration into the US capital market resulting in a deficit crisis. </s><s n="s3.3;p27.64">According to the Center for Security Policy, "communist China is utilizing much of the huge trade surplus that it enjoys thanks to this privileged trading status [MFN] to mount a strategic threat to the United States and its vital interests in Asia, the Middle East and beyond".<ref target="BAWE_0137j-ftnote.017"/> In a similar light, China has been accused of adopting the mercantilist approach to trade, like Japan's model of economic growth of which export led growth has been fueled by 'aggressive guided capitalism'. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0137j-ftnote.017"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Broomfield, E.V. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">(2003) "Perceptions of Danger: the China Threat Theory" <hi rend="underlined">Journal of Contemporary China</hi> Vol. 12: p. 272. </s></p></note><p n="p28.64"><s n="s1.5;p28.64">Yet such concerns may be over-exaggerated as China's primary priority is economic modernization and development, a goal which stresses cooperation with its neighbors rather than conflict. </s><s n="s2.5;p28.64">It also fails to factor in the fact that China's continued growth will be dependent on its growing engagement with and dependence on the capitalist world economic system which also translates into greater vulnerability and sensitivity than into greater power. </s><s n="s3.5;p28.64">Access to the China market makes a contribution to the economies of the United States, Europe and Northeast Asia, but these markets are more important to China than China's market is to them. </s><s n="s4.5;p28.64">China has frequently been compelled to compromise its policies to maintain access to these markets.<ref target="BAWE_0137j-ftnote.018"/> Most importantly, if we take into account mounting environmental pressures and environmental deficit financing<ref target="BAWE_0137j-ftnote.019"/>, China's impressive growth of 12.15per cent per annum in 1992-1996 drops down to almost zero growth. </s><s n="s5.5;p28.64">Hence, economic statistics alone do not account accurately for China's power and by extension, its economic threat should not be exaggerated. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0137j-ftnote.018"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Nathan, A. J. &amp; Ross, R. S., <hi rend="underlined">The Great Wall and the Empty Fortress.</hi> </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">p. 229. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0137j-ftnote.019"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Economic costs of China's air and water pollution alone have been estimated at 3-8 percent of GDP yearly, not to mention 289 000 deaths a year that could have been avoided if air pollution alone had been reduced to comply with Chinese government standards. </s></p></note><p n="p29.64"><s n="s1.4;p29.64">From a military perspective, it is also hard to reject the "China Threat" thesis, especially in the eyes of the Americans. </s><s n="s2.4;p29.64">America's Defence Secretary, Donald Rumsfeld, raised red flags on 4 <hi rend="sup">th</hi> June 2005 when he accused China of increasing its military expenditures at a time when it faces no serious military threats and raised doubts about its future intentions.<ref target="BAWE_0137j-ftnote.020"/> China's military modernization appears to be acquiring weapon systems that boost the People's Liberation Army's (PLA) capability to project power beyond China's shores - Russian Su-27s, Russian Kilo class submarines, in-flight refueling technology and a continuing interest to buy one or more aircraft carriers. </s><s n="s3.4;p29.64">A greater fear is that China's participation in the US market and its growing trade surplus will be used to finance a military built up of the PLA which will be an economic threat to the United States. </s><s n="s4.4;p29.64">It has been observed that "state owned enterprises, 'red chips', have infiltrated the American market by establishing companies on the West Coast and buying up firms already operating in America to increase profits and facilitate technology transfers". <ref target="BAWE_0137j-ftnote.021"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0137j-ftnote.020"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">"Casus Belli" <hi rend="underlined">The Economist Print Edition Online,</hi> 9th June 2005. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0137j-ftnote.021"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Broomfield, E.V. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">(2003) "Perceptions of Danger: the China Threat Theory" <hi rend="underlined">Journal of Contemporary China</hi> Vol. 12: p. 276. </s></p></note><p n="p30.64"><s n="s1.2;p30.64">While their fears may be understandable, yet military figures are usually one-sided. </s><s n="s2.2;p30.64">David Shambaugh, an analyst of the Chinese armed forces, argues that "the recent hype in the media and by those in the American political system about the so-called Chinese threat is grossly overblown, not empirically grounded, irresponsible and politically dangerous."<ref target="BAWE_0137j-ftnote.022"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0137j-ftnote.022"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">"As China rises, Must others bow?" </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1"><hi rend="underlined">The Economist Print Edition Online</hi>, 25th June 1998. </s></p></note><p n="p31.64"><s n="s1.4;p31.64">Firstly, it is important not to confuse the existence of a military power with the intent to use that power against other nations. </s><s n="s2.4;p31.64">And PLA's growth must be kept in perspective: it is a "routine, moderate and long-overdue modernisation." </s><ref target="BAWE_0137j-ftnote.023"/><s n="s3.4;p31.64">China still spends far less per capita on its military budget than the US, even prior to 11 September when the US military was in a non-combat state of readiness. </s><s n="s4.4;p31.64">And analyses of its military expenditures must be on a relative basis; China has spent a vast sum on the PLA's budget over the past decade because it has a lot of catching up to do. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0137j-ftnote.023"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Roy, D. (1996) "The China Threat Issue: Major Arguments", <hi rend="underlined">Asian Survey.</hi> </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">Vol. 36: p. 764. </s></p></note><p n="p32.64"><s n="s1.2;p32.64">The East-West Centre in Hawaii argues that China's military modernisation is still far from meeting its defence needs; "military expenditures have been very low, especially when considered against the size of the country... </s><s n="s2.2;p32.64">China's low military spending reflects a clear-cut policy choice; that military modernisation is subordinated to and supportive of national economic reconstruction".<ref target="BAWE_0137j-ftnote.024"/> Recent geopolitical events also affirmed this; in the aftermath of the tsunami of December 2004, when, "in contrast to America's highly visible military-backed role in the relief work, China's presence was marginal".<ref target="BAWE_0137j-ftnote.025"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0137j-ftnote.024"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">"As China rises, Must others bow?" </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1"><hi rend="underlined">The Economist Print Edition Online</hi>, 25th June 1998. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0137j-ftnote.025"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">"Aphorisms and Suspicions" <hi rend="underlined">The Economist Print Edition Online</hi>, 17th November 2005. </s></p></note><p n="p33.64"><s n="s1.1;p33.64">In other words, the rise of Chinese military power, similar to the rise of its economic power, must be taken seriously but not in an exaggerated form for China is not likely to be a global challenger to the United States, nor will it be able to exercise regional hegemony so long as the United States stays involved in East Asia.<ref target="BAWE_0137j-ftnote.026"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0137j-ftnote.026"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">"As China rises, Must others bow?" </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1"><hi rend="underlined">The Economist Print Edition Online</hi>, 25th June 1998. </s></p></note><p n="p34.64"><s n="s1.2;p34.64">Proponents of the "China Threat" encroached in ideological terms have also been deeply mistaken. </s><s n="s2.2;p34.64">It is inaccurate to perceive China to be the new ideological leader of what is left of communism and thus an ideological competitor of the United States as China has embraced the market system which differentiates it from the "the missionary-like zeal of Soviet communism that once sought to battle the US on ideological grounds around the globe". <ref target="BAWE_0137j-ftnote.027"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0137j-ftnote.027"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Broomfield, E.V. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">(2003) "Perceptions of Danger: the China Threat Theory" <hi rend="underlined">Journal of Contemporary China</hi> Vol. 12: p. 278. </s></p></note><p n="p35.64"><s n="s1.1;p35.64">Henceforth, with all the above arguments established, the hypothesis of a "China Threat" as seen in the above dimensions does not stand. </s></p></div2><div2><head>Engagement with multilateral institutions</head><p n="p36.64"><s n="s1.2;p36.64">Thus far, we have firmly established that the "China Threat" may not materialize and may simply be a perceived threat. </s><s n="s2.2;p36.64">Yet to ensure that such a potential threat will not become a real threat will also depend on the extent to which multilateral institutions engage China constructively and vice versa. </s></p><p n="p37.64"><s n="s1.3;p37.64">International security institutions such as Council on Security Cooperation in the Asia Pacific (CSCAP) created in 1993 and the ASEAN Regional Forum (ARF) created in 1994 were established with the aim of engaging China. </s><s n="s2.3;p37.64">Effectively, China's continual involvement in such institutions can be useful for developing "a reputation for responsibility and cooperation"<ref target="BAWE_0137j-ftnote.028"/> and leads to constraints on action which increases the chances that "China will act as a responsible regional power".<ref target="BAWE_0137j-ftnote.029"/> Such is evident in the increased participation rates of the China; from 1982 to 1996, the total number of possible treaties increased from nine to fourteen, an increase of 55 percent. </s><s n="s3.3;p37.64">China's accessions increased from two to twelve, a jump of 500 percent. <ref target="BAWE_0137j-ftnote.030"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0137j-ftnote.028"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.3;pn1.1">Johnston A.I. &amp; Evans, P. </s><s n="s2.3;pn1.1">(1999) "China's Engagement with Multilateral Security Institutions", in Johnston, A.I. &amp; Ross, R.S. et al (eds.) <hi rend="underlined">Engaging China: The Management of an Emerging Power.</hi> </s><s n="s3.3;pn1.1">London: Routledge, p. 237. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0137j-ftnote.029"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Johnston A.I. &amp; Evans, P., <hi rend="underlined">Engaging China: The Management of an Emerging Power.</hi> </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">p. 257. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0137j-ftnote.030"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Johnston A.I. &amp; Evans, P., <hi rend="underlined">Engaging China: The Management of an Emerging Power.</hi> </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">p. 257. </s></p></note><p n="p38.64"><s n="s1.5;p38.64">Similarly, multilateral economic institutions have responded to China's re-emergence in a constructive manner. </s><s n="s2.5;p38.64">Such institutions include the World Bank, International Monetary Fund, the General Agreement on Tariffs and Trade and its successor, the World Trade Organisation which have been successful at engaging China to commit to the norms of the system and participate more fully in the international trade and investment arena. </s><s n="s3.5;p38.64">In an important sense, China's rapidly growing presence in international markets has been viewed less as a threat to the global economic system than as an opportunity to bring China into the global economy on favourable terms.<ref target="BAWE_0137j-ftnote.031"/> Perhaps, "in major (if incomplete) ways, China has adopted the rules of the international game".<ref target="BAWE_0137j-ftnote.032"/> More evidence lies in the government initiatives to implement numerous additional policy changes that would bring it into line with GATT/WTO standards for international trade. </s><s n="s4.5;p38.64">For example, direct subsidies for exports have been largely phased out. </s><s n="s5.5;p38.64">Tariff reductions on merchandise goods as well as in agricultural products and services were also announced in 1993 and 1995.<ref target="BAWE_0137j-ftnote.033"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0137j-ftnote.031"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.3;pn1.1">Pearson, M. M. </s><s n="s2.3;pn1.1">(1999) "The Major Multilateral Economic Institutions Engage China", in Johnston, A.I. &amp; Ross, R.S. et al (eds.) <hi rend="underlined">Engaging China: The Management of an Emerging Power.</hi> </s><s n="s3.3;pn1.1">London: Routledge, p. 210. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0137j-ftnote.032"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Pearson, M. M., <hi rend="underlined">Engaging China: The Management of an Emerging Power.</hi> </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">p. 217. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0137j-ftnote.033"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Pearson, M. M., <hi rend="underlined">Engaging China: The Management of an Emerging Power.</hi> </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">p. 218. </s></p></note></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined">Perspectives from outside</head><p n="p39.64"><s n="s1.2;p39.64">In conjunction with all the above analysis, a relative assessment of threat must stem from a multidirectional approach; evaluating Chinese capabilities relative to others and the extent of threat it poses to each significant adversary. </s><s n="s2.2;p39.64">Surely, China cannot be equally 'powerful' in all issue areas (structural power) and in all relationships (relational power). <ref target="BAWE_0137j-ftnote.034"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0137j-ftnote.034"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Kim, S.S., <hi rend="underlined">China and the World: Chinese foreign policy faces the new millennium</hi>. p. 8. </s></p></note><p n="p40.64"><s n="s1.1;p40.64">Additionally, it is overly simplistic to classify its re-emergence in its totality as a threat or opportunity, for its re-emergence inevitably presents the established powers with both threats and opportunities; some stand to benefit by its emergence, others fear that they will be disadvantaged. </s></p><p n="p41.64"><s n="s1.1;p41.64">In this case, it is not possible to describe China's relations with every entity of the world; hence the essay will examine its relations with countries such as Japan, United States and Taiwan to the extent that it gives a sufficient and just overview of China's impact on the world. </s></p><div2><head>China and United States</head><p n="p42.64"><s n="s1.2;p42.64">This is the key relationship for China as the United States is the dominant power in the world and in the Asia-Pacific region. </s><s n="s2.2;p42.64">China's threat to the world may depend on this Sino-American relationship and its tilt towards cooperation, competition or confrontation. </s></p><p n="p43.64"><s n="s1.4;p43.64">Firstly, there is a web of mutual interdependency between the United States and China. </s><s n="s2.4;p43.64">The Chinese government requires foreign investment and access to Western markets to sustain its economic growth to maintain itself in power. </s><s n="s3.4;p43.64">To these ends, it requires a stable peaceful international environment and the US is the key element in ensuring that both conditions are available to China. </s><s n="s4.4;p43.64">Similarly, the US fear a weak China for it will destabilize the East Asian regime. </s></p><p n="p44.64"><s n="s1.4;p44.64">There is always room for cooperation. </s><s n="s2.4;p44.64">China supported Pakistan's efforts to cooperate with the US to oppose Bin Laden and the Taliban regime of Afghanistan, and provided the US with intelligence information it had on terrorist networks and activities in the region. </s><s n="s3.4;p44.64">It also agreed to US's request to use the Shanghai APEC Summit platform to promote the anti-terrorist cause. </s><s n="s4.4;p44.64">Contrary to the expectations of some Americans hostile to China, China did all this without attaching any conditions.<ref target="BAWE_0137j-ftnote.035"/> More recently, in response to US domestic pressures on the Bush Administration to address the trade deficit problem with China, "the Chinese Government has sent several delegations to the US to make significant purchases of US airplanes, cars and agricultural produce and made significant concessions in the recent negotiation on phasing out tax benefits to computer chip makers in China".<ref target="BAWE_0137j-ftnote.036"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0137j-ftnote.035"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Qingquo, J. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">(2005) "Learning to live with the Hegemon: Evolution of China's policy towards the US since the end of the Cold War", <hi rend="underlined">Journal of Contemporary China</hi> Vol. 14: p. 403. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0137j-ftnote.036"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Qingquo, J. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">(2005) "Learning to live with the Hegemon: Evolution of China's policy towards the US since the end of the Cold War", <hi rend="underlined">Journal of Contemporary China</hi> Vol. 14: p. 403. </s></p></note><p n="p45.64"><s n="s1.5;p45.64">Despite the hopeful optimism invested in the relationship, it is a shaky and fragile one. </s><s n="s2.5;p45.64">Washington takes interest in issues such as human rights, Taiwan and Tibet that Beijing considers domestic matters.<ref target="BAWE_0137j-ftnote.037"/> Beijing is very much wary of being encircled by a string of American bases around Asia (see illustration one) and an enhancement in recent years of American security ties with Japan and Taiwan.<ref target="BAWE_0137j-ftnote.038"/> The Taiwan Relations Act (TRA) established in 1979 could also drive the wedge between the two countries. </s><s n="s3.5;p45.64">Lastly, another potent issue lies in the struggle for oil resources. </s><s n="s4.5;p45.64">According to the Department of Energy, Chinese oil consumption is projected to reach 12 million barrels per day in 2020, of which 9 million barrels will have to be obtained abroad. </s><s n="s5.5;p45.64">The United States will also need more imports in 2020 and if there is no credible research on alternative energy resources, the stage is set for an intense struggle for the world's petroleum supplies.<ref target="BAWE_0137j-ftnote.039"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0137j-ftnote.037"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Kim, S.S., <hi rend="underlined">China and the World: Chinese foreign policy faces the new millennium</hi>. p. 93. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0137j-ftnote.038"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">"Aphorisms and suspicions" <hi rend="underlined">The Economist Print Edition Online</hi>, 17th November 2005. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0137j-ftnote.039"><p n="pn1.2"><s n="s1.2;pn1.2">Klare, T.M. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.2">(2005) "Revving up the China Threat: New Stage in US China Policy" <hi rend="underlined">The Nation</hi>, 24th October 2005 </s></p><p n="pn2.2"><s n="s1.2;pn2.2">on the website <hi rend="underlined"><seg type="URL" n="http://japanfocus.org/article.asp?id=419"/>.</hi> </s><s n="s2.2;pn2.2">Accessed 14 <hi rend="sup">th</hi> April 2006 </s></p></note><p n="p46.64"><s n="s1.5;p46.64">With such disruptive obstacles in mind, even if the United States does not outrightly declare China as a threat, it does not dismiss such a possibility entirely. </s><s n="s2.5;p46.64">Yet the crucial issue resides in the mutual understanding of the complexity and interdependency of their relationship which stresses for the management and maintenance of just political and economic ties. </s><s n="s3.5;p46.64">To label China as a threat is an exaggeration of areas of tension in the Sino - American relationship and ignorance of many realities and positive externalities. </s><s n="s4.5;p46.64">This viewpoint also reflects "irresponsibility on the part of such thinkers and such continued rhetoric will only push China away from the ideals and goals of the United States". </s><ref target="BAWE_0137j-ftnote.040"/><s n="s5.5;p46.64">After all, it is not American's position to impose its will on China for it will merely uplift the American threat and downplay the "China Threat". </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0137j-ftnote.040"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Broomfield, E.V. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">(2003) "Perceptions of Danger: the China Threat Theory" <hi rend="underlined">Journal of Contemporary China</hi> Vol. 12: p. 284. </s></p></note></div2><div2><head>China and Japan</head><p n="p47.64"><s n="s1.6;p47.64">Comparable to the Sino-US relation, a delicate peace prevails between China and Japan. </s><s n="s2.6;p47.64">There are areas of dependency; both share complementary economies as China has many natural resources that Japan needs while Japan has the technology and money to assist China and a rich market for Chinese goods. </s><s n="s3.6;p47.64">In 1995, China exported far more textile products to Japan than to any other country. </s><s n="s4.6;p47.64">It ranked third in the export of electrical machinery to Japan and fourth in the export of chemicals. </s><s n="s5.6;p47.64">In terms of imports, China bought nearly $18 billion worth of Japanese machinery and electronic products in 1996.<ref target="BAWE_0137j-ftnote.041"/> China is also the top recipient of Japan's official development assistance. </s><s n="s6.6;p47.64">During the 1993-1995 periods, it received annual funds ranging from $1.4 to $1.5 billion.<ref target="BAWE_0137j-ftnote.042"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0137j-ftnote.041"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Kim, S.S., <hi rend="underlined">China and the World: Chinese foreign policy faces the new millennium</hi>. p. 138. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0137j-ftnote.042"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Kim, S.S., <hi rend="underlined">China and the World: Chinese foreign policy faces the new millennium</hi>. p. 139. </s></p></note><p n="p48.64"><s n="s1.6;p48.64">Yet there are possibilities for conflict and Japan's view of China as a threat is not dismissed. </s><s n="s2.6;p48.64">The legacy of the Pacific war reinforces the security dilemma between both countries, causing each to view all military activities by the other as offensive threats. </s><s n="s3.6;p48.64">They also have competing strategic interests in the South China Sea of which China seeks to stake claims on. </s><s n="s4.6;p48.64">It is the route most traveled by ships bearing some 90 percent of the oil the Japanese consume. </s><s n="s5.6;p48.64">Perhaps the most potentially explosive issue in Sino-Japanese relations concerns the linkage of the US - Japan security treaty and the "two China" issue. </s><s n="s6.6;p48.64">In Chinese eyes, the worst scenario was aptly described as "the prospect of American and Japanese forces cooperating under the umbrella of the US - Japan alliance in response to use of force by [China]...to prevent Taiwan from becoming independent." <ref target="BAWE_0137j-ftnote.043"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0137j-ftnote.043"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Kim, S.S., <hi rend="underlined">China and the World: Chinese foreign policy faces the new millennium</hi>. p. 143. </s></p></note><p n="p49.64"><s n="s1.4;p49.64">In the absence of an ideal solution, continuing to abet China's growth while hoping defensive balancing will not be necessary is the least problematic option for Japan. </s><s n="s2.4;p49.64">Continued and unrestrained economic engagement conveys implicit acquiescence to the possibility of an economically and militarily powerful China, with all its attendant risks. </s><s n="s3.4;p49.64">But this approach has its positive externalities as well; it is the least threatening from China's perspective. </s><s n="s4.4;p49.64">Therefore, the way Japan defines China as a threat also determines how China views Japan in the same way. </s></p></div2><div2><head>China and Taiwan</head><p n="p50.64"><s n="s1.3;p50.64">Taiwan is perhaps one adversary who sees the "China Threat" as the most persistent. </s><s n="s2.3;p50.64">Taiwan-mainland relations are dominated by a dilemma of mutual vulnerability. </s><s n="s3.3;p50.64">Each side is potentially able to do vital damage to the security of the other and in trying to improve its own security; each increases the sense of threat on the other side. </s></p><p n="p51.64"><s n="s1.5;p51.64">Economically, the Taiwanese economy is very much dependent on the Chinese economy as evident by early 1999, where investments on the mainland by Taiwan companies had grown to more than US$30 billion. </s><s n="s2.5;p51.64">Approximately 40 percent of the island's total foreign investment was PRC-bound. </s><ref target="BAWE_0137j-ftnote.044"/><s n="s3.5;p51.64">However, such optimistic growth were perceived as potential threats as they are seen as increased leverage of which Beijing could use to increase demands for movement in cross-strait relations. </s><s n="s4.5;p51.64">As one military intelligence official puts it, the mainland's strategy aimed "at carrying out a united front campaign against Taiwan through economic and trade activities".<ref target="BAWE_0137j-ftnote.045"/> Furthermore, both sides remain divided over the meaning of "one China". </s><s n="s5.5;p51.64">While the mainland meant it to relegate Taiwan to subordinate status within a China ruled from Beijing, Taipei insisted on recognition of its own sovereignty and equality vis-à-vis the mainland. <ref target="BAWE_0137j-ftnote.046"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0137j-ftnote.044"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.3;pn1.1">Goldstein, S.M. </s><s n="s2.3;pn1.1">(1999) "Terms of Engagement: Taiwan's mainland policy", in Johnston, A.I. &amp; Ross, R.S. et al (eds.) <hi rend="underlined">Engaging China: The Management of an Emerging Power.</hi> </s><s n="s3.3;pn1.1">London: Routledge, p. 64. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0137j-ftnote.045"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Goldstein, S.M., <hi rend="underlined">Engaging China: The Management of an Emerging Power.</hi> </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">p. 67. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0137j-ftnote.046"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Goldstein, S.M., <hi rend="underlined">Engaging China: The Management of an Emerging Power.</hi> </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">p. 70. </s></p></note><p n="p52.64"><s n="s1.4;p52.64">Although it is vital to note that the stakes for invading Taiwan by force is too high for China and the opportunity costs far outweigh the benefits. </s><s n="s2.4;p52.64">Presently, it is far more important for China to improve its standing in the world and maintain political stability at home. </s><s n="s3.4;p52.64">In the eyes of Taiwan, the "China Threat" is real and legitimate for ultimately the final decision for conflict or compromise lies in Beijing though it may not materialize. </s><s n="s4.4;p52.64">Besides, the catalyst for that decision may be the interaction of domestic policies and foreign policy on Taiwan as there is responsibility on all parties (United States and Japan), including Taiwan, to act responsibly to preserve peace in the Taiwan Strait.<ref target="BAWE_0137j-ftnote.047"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0137j-ftnote.047"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Kim, S.S., <hi rend="underlined">China and the World: Chinese foreign policy faces the new millennium</hi>. p. 306. </s></p></note><p n="p53.64"><s n="s1.1;p53.64">Stringing all the perspectives together, it is evident that the "China Threat" is more persistent to some than to others, although most have sought to deal with it as a manageable re-emergence together with the potential threats and benefits it could possibly bring. </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined">Perspective from within</head><p n="p54.64"><s n="s1.2;p54.64">Many China watchers would agree with the assertion that "China's intentions are perhaps even more important than its capabilities." </s><ref target="BAWE_0137j-ftnote.048"/><s n="s2.2;p54.64">This "soft" argument approach highlights the intentions of the Chinese in relation to that of their adversaries; whether it is a threat or not depends on their malign or benign intentions. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0137j-ftnote.048"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Roy, D. (1996) "The China Threat Issue: Major Arguments", <hi rend="underlined">Asian Survey.</hi> </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">Vol. 36: p. 767. </s></p></note><p n="p55.64"><s n="s1.3;p55.64">It is unfair to judge China's actions purely from an outsider's point of view: its intentions may be defensive even if they appear aggressive. </s><s n="s2.3;p55.64">Its behaviour is often misunderstood because China's strategic situation is so different from that of the other major powers, and because the Chinese feel safer in hiding the logic of their actions than in explaining them. </s><s n="s3.3;p55.64">"Such misunderstanding can be dangerous for friends and even more so for rivals". <ref target="BAWE_0137j-ftnote.049"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0137j-ftnote.049"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Nathan, A. J. &amp; Ross, R. S., <hi rend="underlined">The Great Wall and the Empty Fortress.</hi> </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">p. 15 of foreword. </s></p></note><p n="p56.64"><s n="s1.3;p56.64">It may appear threatening but its posture stems from defensive security concerns. </s><s n="s2.3;p56.64">For a country that has weathered civil wars and periods of disunity lasting for centuries, no other country can comprehend the intensity of its security concerns. </s><s n="s3.3;p56.64">In particular, the United States is separated from Asia and Europe by oceans and shares borders with two much weaker countries, which are allies, on the contrary, China sits in the middle of the Asian continent, bordered by potential foes. </s></p><p n="p57.64"><s n="s1.1;p57.64">Besides it sees itself being more threatened than being a threat: "the problem of the strong state thesis embedded in the rise-of-China global chorus today is that it does not sufficiently take into account deepening legitimation and ecological crisis".<ref target="BAWE_0137j-ftnote.050"/> China's external impressive economic growth camouflages a multitude of domestic problems such as increasing disparities between rich and poor, rampant corruption and capricious party rule. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0137j-ftnote.050"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Kim, S.S., <hi rend="underlined">China as a Great Power: Myths, Realities and Challenges in the Asia Pacific Region.</hi> </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">p.60. </s></p></note><p n="p58.64"><s n="s1.2;p58.64">In consequence, its behaviour begins to make sense only if one looks at where it is located in the world, what assets and liabilities it brings to the defense of its own security and how its leaders see their country's vulnerabilities. </s><ref target="BAWE_0137j-ftnote.051"/><s n="s2.2;p58.64">Understanding its causes and consequences should help Western policymakers accommodate China when they should, persuade China when they can and resist China when they must.<ref target="BAWE_0137j-ftnote.052"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0137j-ftnote.051"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Nathan, A. J. &amp; Ross, R. S., <hi rend="underlined">The Great Wall and the Empty Fortress.</hi> </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">p. 4. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0137j-ftnote.052"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Nathan, A. J. &amp; Ross, R. S., <hi rend="underlined">The Great Wall and the Empty Fortress.</hi> </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">p. 237. </s></p></note></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined">Future realities depend on current responses </head><p n="p59.64"><s n="s1.3;p59.64">The question of whether particular apprehensions about China's role in the future are justified is exercising many minds in the region. </s><s n="s2.3;p59.64">But what is important is not just that the answer to that question remains open but China's future regional posture and policies are not and have not yet been determined but are open to the influence of the international community. </s><s n="s3.3;p59.64">Hence there is a proactive part that the global community can play in fostering the kind of China that we expect and hope to receive even with its limitations. </s></p><p n="p60.64"><s n="s1.4;p60.64">Since this essay establishes that China should be received with caution but not alarm, the most appropriate line of action will be "engagement" rather than "containment" which will sustain a "Peaceful re-emergence of China" over time. </s><s n="s2.4;p60.64">Engagement employs economic incentives and disincentives to exact desirable behaviour, banking on hard bargaining and low coercion. </s><s n="s3.4;p60.64">It should not be the policy goal rather it is a process and a vehicle to the ultimate goal of integrating China into the existing rule-based, institutionalized and normative international system. </s><s n="s4.4;p60.64">Even if we engage china, there is no guarantee of friendship, but at least there will be a reasonable prospect and perhaps minimize the chances of strength translating to threat. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined">Conclusion</head><p n="p61.64"><s n="s1.2;p61.64">China re-emergence is troubling for its global and regional implications are uncertain. </s><s n="s2.2;p61.64">Coupled with the lack of knowledge about Chinese policy making that is still very much hidden behind great walls, there is a great concern as to whether its rising strength translates into threat. </s></p><p n="p62.64"><s n="s1.4;p62.64">The essay started on the premise that its strength has been inaccurately portrayed if we define power in purely economic and military terms and if we include more extensive assessment criterions, we would be aware of China's internal insecurities, domestic concerns and defensive posture which may not even translate to real strength. </s><s n="s2.4;p62.64">Even with its supposed strength, this would not translate into a contemporary threat if we are aware of its peaceful and defensive disposition. </s><s n="s3.4;p62.64">In addition, if China projects its power with the global consequences in mind, it is very much tied down by 'world governance' - multilateral security and economic institutions to refine and define China's actions. </s><s n="s4.4;p62.64">With all these open possibilities in an evolving era, we should not outrightly equate strength to threat. </s></p><p n="p63.64"><s n="s1.3;p63.64">Above all, it must be stressed that neither hypothesis, be it the "China Threat" or "Peaceful re-emergence of China" is substantial to account for such a complex phenomenon with its far ranging impact on so many actors and regions over time. </s><s n="s2.3;p63.64">China is a big enough power that its choice is not merely between obeying the world's rules or flouting them, hence upholding peace or posing threat respectively. </s><s n="s3.3;p63.64">Though, it has been argued that China is more inclined to peace than threat. </s></p><p n="p64.64"><s n="s1.5;p64.64">Even then, the applicability of this "peaceful re-emergence" hypothesis over time is conditional. </s><s n="s2.5;p64.64">It will depend on how China defines and implements its foreign and domestic policies, how others relate and respond to China and how China will reciprocate accordingly. </s><s n="s3.5;p64.64">As such, it calls for shared responsibility to shoulder a potential "China Threat"; China needs to be more persuasive in its actions than just rhetoric and there is a need for a western policy that reflects an understanding of and sensitivity to the factors that motivate Chinese policies and responses. </s><s n="s4.5;p64.64">With mutual understanding between China and the world, the "China Threat" may not snowball into a real threat and remains purely a myth even if it is a misguided one. </s><s n="s5.5;p64.64">In all, let us embrace the awakened dragon with optimism accompanied by caution and vigilance. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0137j-pic.001"><head>Illustration one: Map showing US presence around China. From "Aphorisms and Suspicions", <hi rend="underlined">The Economist Print Edition Online,</hi> 17 <hi rend="sup">th</hi> November 2005.</head></figure></div1></body><back><div1 type="bibliography"><head>Bibliography:</head><div2 type="bibliography"><head>Online resources:</head><p>"Through China's eyes" <hi rend="underlined">The Economist Print Edition Online</hi>, 6<hi rend="sup">th</hi> March 1997.</p><p> "If China rises, must others bow?" <hi rend="underlined">The Economist Print Edition Online</hi>, 25<hi rend="sup">th</hi> June 1998.</p><p>"The not-so-great power" <hi rend="underlined">The Economist Print Edition Online</hi>, 13th February 2003.</p><p> "Peaceful Rise" <hi rend="underlined">The Economist Print Edition Online</hi>, 24<hi rend="sup">th</hi> June 2004.</p><p> "Casus Belli" <hi rend="underlined">The Economist Print Edition Online</hi>, 9<hi rend="sup">th</hi> June 2005.</p><p>"China and the key to Asian Peace" <hi rend="underlined">The Economist Print Edition Online</hi>, 23<hi rend="sup">rd</hi> March 2005.</p><p> "Aphorisms and Suspicions" <hi rend="underlined">The Economist Print Edition Online</hi>, 17<hi rend="sup">th</hi> November 2005.</p><p>"Meeting the superpower" <hi rend="underlined">The Economist Print Edition Online</hi>, 17<hi rend="sup">th</hi> November 2005.</p><p>Klare, T.M. (2005) "Revving up the China Threat: New Stage in US China Policy" <hi rend="underlined">The Nation</hi>, 24<hi rend="sup">th</hi> October 2005 on the website <seg type="URL" n="http://japanfocus.org/article.asp?id=419"/>. Accessed 14<hi rend="sup">th</hi> April 2006.</p></div2><div2 type="bibliography"><head>Electronic articles:</head><p>Yan, X. (2001) "The Rise of China in Chinese Eyes", <hi rend="underlined">Journal of Contemporary China</hi> Vol. 10: p. 33-39. </p><p>Roy, D. (1996) "The China 'Threat' Issue: Major Arguments", <hi rend="underlined">Asian Survey</hi> Vol. 36: p.758-771.</p><p>Osius, T. (2001) "Discussion of 'the Rise of China in Chinese eyes'", <hi rend="underlined">Journal of Contemporary China</hi> Vol.10: p. 41 - 44.</p><p>Deng, Y. &amp; Gray, S. (2001) "Introduction: Growing Pains - China debates its international future", <hi rend="underlined">Journal of Contemporary China</hi> Vol.10: p. 5 - 16.</p><p>Broomfield, E.V. (2003) "Perceptions of Danger: the China threat theory", <hi rend="underlined">Journal of Contemporary China</hi> Vol.12: p. 265 -284.</p><p>Jia, Q. (2005) "Learning to live with the Hegemon: Evolution of China's policy toward the US since the end of the Cold War" <hi rend="underlined">Journal of Contemporary China</hi> Vol.14:p. 395 - 407.</p><p>Gill, B. (2001) "Discussion of the article of China as a responsible great power", <hi rend="underlined">Journal of Contemporary China</hi> Vol. 10: p. 27 - 32.</p><p>Wu, X. (2001) "Four contradictions constraining China's behaviour", <hi rend="underlined">Journal of Contemporary China</hi> Vol. 10: p. 293 - 301.</p><p>Yahuda, M. (1999) "China's Foreign Relations: the Long March, Future Uncertain", <hi rend="underlined">The China Quarterly</hi> Vol.159: p. 650-659.</p><p>Ding, X. (1991) "Managing Sino-American relations in a changing world", <hi rend="underlined">Asian Survey</hi> Vol.31: p. 1155-1169.</p><p>Roy, D. (1994) "Hegemon on the Horizon, Threat to East Asian Security", <hi rend="underlined">International Security</hi> Vol. 19: p. 149-168.</p><p>Economy, E. (2005) "China's rise in South East Asia: implications for the United States", <hi rend="underlined">Journal of Contemporary China</hi> Vol. 14: p. 409-425.</p><p>Shambaugh, D. (1993) "Emergence of a Greater China", <hi rend="underlined">The China Quarterly</hi> Vol. 136: p. 653-659.</p><p>Shambaugh, D. (1996) "Containment or Engagement of China", <hi rend="underlined">International Security</hi> Vol.21: p. 180-209.</p><p>Yahuda, M. (2003) "Chinese dilemmas in thinking about regional security architecture", <hi rend="underlined">The Pacific Review</hi>, Vol. 16: p. 189 - 206.</p><p> Cable, V. &amp; Ferdinand, P. (1994) "China as an Economic Giant: Threat or Opportunity?", <hi rend="underlined">International Affairs</hi> Vol.70: p. 243-261.</p></div2><div2 type="bibliography"><head>Books:</head><p>Brown, M. E., Cote, O.R, Lynn-Jones, S. M. &amp; Miller, S. E. (ed.) (2000) <hi rend="underlined">The Rise of China.</hi> Massachusetts: MIT Press. </p><p>Harris, S. &amp; Klintworth, G. (ed.) (1995) <hi rend="underlined">China as a Great Power: Myths, Realities and Challenges in the Asia Pacific Region.</hi> Melbourne: Addison Wesley Longman Pty Ltd.</p><p>Kim, S.S. (ed.) (1998) <hi rend="underlined">China and the World: Chinese foreign policy faces the new millennium.</hi> Colorado: Westview Press.</p><p>Nathan, A. J. &amp; Ross, R. S. (1997) <hi rend="underlined">The Great Wall and the Empty Fortress.</hi> London: W.W. Norton &amp; Company.</p><p>Johnston, A.I. &amp; Ross, R.S. (ed.) (1999) <hi rend="underlined">Engaging China: The Management of an Emerging Power.</hi> London: Routledge.</p></div2></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
