<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_0138d" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>The Feminist Contribution to Political Thought: A Ground-Breaking Challenge</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">The document has a title page which contains:
document title
title part</note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">header: student name and number
footer: page numbers</note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">deleted: Word count: 1,608
</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">1</p><p n="date">2005-11</p><p n="module title">Introduction to Politics</p><p n="module code">PO107</p><p n="genre family">Essay</p><p n="discipline">Politics</p><p n="disciplinary group">SS</p><p n="grade">D</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">1577</p><p n="number of s-units">56</p><p n="number of p">7</p><p n="number of tables">0</p><p n="number of figures">0</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">0</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">0</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">28.2</p><p n="average s-units per p">8.0</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">f</p><p n="year of birth">1987</p><p n="first language">French</p><p n="education">OSA</p><p n="course">EPAIS</p><p n="student ID">0138</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><titlePart>The Feminist Contribution to Political Thought: A Ground-Breaking Challenge</titlePart><titlePart><name type="student name"/>, <name type="student ID"/><name type="student name"/>@<name type="university"/>.ac.uk</titlePart><docTitle><titlePart> Introduction to Politics (PO 107) Essay 3, Question 1: <hi rend="italic">In what ways have feminists challenged conventional thinking about politics?</hi> </titlePart></docTitle><titlePart>Tutor: <name type="tutor name"/> Module Director: <name type="tutor name"/> Date: 02 / 03 / 2006</titlePart></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="section"><p n="p1.7"><s n="s1.6;p1.7">The past centuries have witnessed an "ongoing struggle between and amongst political ideologies"<ref target="BAWE_0138d-ftnote.001"/> as liberals, socialists, conservatives, nationalists and others have proposed rival interpretations of political reality. </s><s n="s2.6;p1.7">In spite of their many differences, however, the mainstream approaches have all ignored the political significance of sexual divisions. </s><s n="s3.6;p1.7">It is only with the nineteenth-century emergence of the women's movement, and more powerfully with the rise of 'second-wave' feminism the 1960's, that the issue of gender was "raised . . . as a major challenge to the discipline [of political science]." </s><ref target="BAWE_0138d-ftnote.002"/><s n="s4.6;p1.7">By forcing the customarily public scope of politics to embrace the private sphere, by exposing the patriarchal assumptions underlying conventional political theory, and by drawing attention to the fundamental role of gender in shaping all aspects of life, feminism puts the dominant institutions of political thought into serious question. </s><s n="s5.6;p1.7">The core feminist themes reveal that the traditional ideologies, and in particular liberalism, provide a highly biased and male-oriented interpretation of reality - they may consequently be "inadequate vehicles for advancing the social role of women"<ref target="BAWE_0138d-ftnote.003"/>. </s><s n="s6.6;p1.7">The emergence of feminism as a distinctive political ideology challenges mainstream theorists to reconsider their understanding of the political world. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0138d-ftnote.001"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Heywood, Andrew, <hi rend="underlined">Political Ideologies: An Introduction</hi>, Palgrave Macmillan (2003), p6 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0138d-ftnote.002"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Carver, Terrel, 'Gender and Feminism in International Relations'. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1"><hi rend="italic">International Studies Review</hi> Vol 5, No 2, (2003), p289 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0138d-ftnote.003"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Heywood 2003, p238 </s></p></note><p n="p2.7"><s n="s1.11;p2.7">Conventional political theories have long ignored the issue of gender divisions. </s><s n="s2.11;p2.7">Feminism, by contrast, argues that gender is the deepest and most significant of political rifts, and claims that mainstream political ideology has "neglected analyses of sex and gender to its own detriment"<ref target="BAWE_0138d-ftnote.004"/>. </s><s n="s3.11;p2.7">The feminist view of gender is based on a clear distinction between sex, understood as the biological, immutable differences between males and females, and gender, the more malleable, socially constructed male and female identities. </s><s n="s4.11;p2.7">Sex is a common pretext for female oppression; the traditional view that women are destined to domestic work as an inescapable result of their biological function as mothers, for example, often bars women from political participation. </s><s n="s5.11;p2.7">Likewise, most societies uphold a conception of gender that diminishes women and highlights male superiority through "socially learnt and culturally variable"<ref target="BAWE_0138d-ftnote.005"/> processes of 'engenderment'<ref target="BAWE_0138d-ftnote.006"/>. </s><s n="s6.11;p2.7">Feminists question both modes of discrimination. </s><s n="s7.11;p2.7">They argue that as sex is an unchangeable characteristic, "existing independently of [mankind's] representations of it"<ref target="BAWE_0138d-ftnote.007"/>, it should not serve to justify differential attitudes towards males and females. </s><s n="s8.11;p2.7">Furthermore, feminists hope to reconstruct the current understanding of gender; their primary political project is to attain a notion of genderless 'personhood' in which individuals are no longer categorised according to sex<ref target="BAWE_0138d-ftnote.008"/>. </s><s n="s9.11;p2.7">The feminist aspiration to abolish gender boundaries is criticised by difference feminists, who stress that there are essential differences between men and women, and that social norms must value and preserve both distinct 'manly' and 'womanly' qualities<ref target="BAWE_0138d-ftnote.009"/>. </s><s n="s10.11;p2.7">Yet whatever their conflicting agendas may be, all feminists identify gender as a crucial analytical category, something that the more conventional political ideologies fail to do. </s><s n="s11.11;p2.7">By bringing the notion of gender to the attention of political scholars and practitioners, therefore, "feminist scholars have pointed out numerous flaws . . . in mainstream political theory"<ref target="BAWE_0138d-ftnote.010"/>. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0138d-ftnote.004"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Kinsella, Helen, 'For a Careful Reading: The Conservativism of Gender Constructivism' in Carver, Terrel, 'Gender and Feminism in International Relations'. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1"><hi rend="italic">International Studies Review</hi> Vol 5, No 2, (2003), p296 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0138d-ftnote.005"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.3;pn1.1">Youngs, Gillian, 'Feminist International Relations: a contradiction in terms? </s><s n="s2.3;pn1.1">Or: why women and gender are essential to understanding the world 'we' live in'. </s><s n="s3.3;pn1.1"><hi rend="italic">International Affairs</hi> Vol 80, No 1, (2004), p88 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0138d-ftnote.006"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Heywood 2003, 246 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0138d-ftnote.007"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Kinsella 2003, p295 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0138d-ftnote.008"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Heywood 2003, p246 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0138d-ftnote.009"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Heywood 2003, p247 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0138d-ftnote.010"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Moller Okin, Susan, 'Gender, the Public, and the Private', Chapter 5 in Phillips, Anne (ed), <hi rend="underlined">Feminism and Politics</hi>. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">Oxford : Oxford University Press (1998), p122 </s></p></note><p n="p3.7"><s n="s1.7;p3.7">In addition to attacking the social construction of gender, feminism makes the controversial claim that "the personal is political"<ref target="BAWE_0138d-ftnote.011"/>. </s><s n="s2.7;p3.7">Mainstream ideologies regard politics as activity confined to the 'public' sphere of government and believe that, in the interest of protecting the natural rights and freedoms of individuals, this field should be clearly separated from an apolitical private realm<ref target="BAWE_0138d-ftnote.012"/>. </s><s n="s3.7;p3.7">However, the same schools of thought have traditionally ascribed men to the public areas of "non-domestic, economic, and political life"<ref target="BAWE_0138d-ftnote.013"/> while seeing women as better suited to private life. </s><s n="s4.7;p3.7">This leads feminists to argue that restricting politics to the public sphere is a "strategy of depoliticisation": not only does it normalise and legitimate male domination, but it also silences any potential opposition to this status quo by entirely excluding women from political debate<ref target="BAWE_0138d-ftnote.014"/>. </s><s n="s5.7;p3.7">Feminists contend instead that politics exists wherever social conflict or "power-structured relationships"<ref target="BAWE_0138d-ftnote.015"/> of domination are found, and that "neither the realm of domestic, personal life, nor that of non-domestic . . . life, can be understood or interpreted in isolation from the other"<ref target="BAWE_0138d-ftnote.016"/>. </s><s n="s6.7;p3.7">In the 1970s, for example, Milett's <hi rend="underlined">Sexual Politics</hi> and Germaine Greer's <hi rend="underlined">The Female Eunuch</hi> eroded the borders of the 'political' by addressing the psychological and sexual aspects of gender imbalances within the home<ref target="BAWE_0138d-ftnote.017"/>. </s><s n="s7.7;p3.7">By striving to bring private power relations into traditional political considerations, feminists have considerably destabilised conventional understandings of politics and "entailed the remarking of its boundaries"<ref target="BAWE_0138d-ftnote.018"/>. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0138d-ftnote.011"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.4;pn1.1">" 'The Personal is Political': Origins of the Phrase". </s><s n="s2.4;pn1.1">WMST-L. Internet. </s><s n="s3.4;pn1.1">Accessed on 01 / 03 / 2005. </s><s n="s4.4;pn1.1">Accessed at: <seg type="URL" n="http://research.umbc.edu/~korenman/wmst/pisp.html"/> </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0138d-ftnote.012"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Squires, Judith, 'Politics Beyond Boundaries: A Feminist Perspective', in A. Leftwich (ed.), <hi rend="underlined">What is Politics?</hi> </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">Oxford : Blackwell (2004), p120 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0138d-ftnote.013"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Moller Okin 1998, p124 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0138d-ftnote.014"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Squires 2004, p122 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0138d-ftnote.015"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Millet 1970, in Heywood 2003, p239 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0138d-ftnote.016"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Moller Okin 1998, p124 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0138d-ftnote.017"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Heywood 2003, p242 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0138d-ftnote.018"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Squires 2004, p119 </s></p></note><p n="p4.7"><s n="s1.9;p4.7">The public-private divide upheld by conventional political theory, feminists maintain, is only one of numerous ideological concepts perpetuating female oppression. </s><s n="s2.9;p4.7">Indeed, feminism perceives political reality itself as a social construction and claims that most political outcomes can be explained by examining the ideas - and especially the beliefs about sexual difference - underlying them<ref target="BAWE_0138d-ftnote.019"/>. </s><s n="s3.9;p4.7">In particular, radical feminists such as Miller have identified 'patriarchy' as the main belief system that pervades political, social, and economic structures in every society to ensure a "systematic, institutionalised and pervasive process of gender oppression"<ref target="BAWE_0138d-ftnote.020"/>. </s><s n="s4.9;p4.7">In patriarchal systems, all power relationships between men and women replicate the father's initial dominance within the family unit. </s><s n="s5.9;p4.7">Patriarchal paradigms have a gender-biased influence on most political arrangements, including on the structure of legal frameworks. </s><s n="s6.9;p4.7">The French Code Civil, for instance, Europe's first codification of private law, explicitly describes strength ("puissance") as a characteristic of the husband, while identifying dependency ("incapacité") as a trait typical of the wife. </s><s n="s7.9;p4.7">This formally establishes the marital relationship as one of domination<ref target="BAWE_0138d-ftnote.021"/>. </s><s n="s8.9;p4.7">For liberal feminists, patriarchy continues to shape socio-political outcomes today, contributing to the under-representation of women in politics, professions, and public life. </s><s n="s9.9;p4.7">The concept of patriarchy thus issues a significant challenge to existing political thought: as stated by Carole Pateman, "almost all political theorists have in fact, explicitly or tacitly, upheld patriarchal right"<ref target="BAWE_0138d-ftnote.022"/>. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0138d-ftnote.019"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Carpenter 2003, p299 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0138d-ftnote.020"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Heywood 2003, p243 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0138d-ftnote.021"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Vogel, Ursula, Chapter 3 in Randall, Vicky, and Waylen, Georgina, (eds), <hi rend="underlined">Gender, Politics and the State</hi>. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">London : Routledge, (1998), p34 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0138d-ftnote.022"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Pateman, Carole, <hi rend="underlined">The Sexual Contract</hi>. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">Cambridge : Polity (1988), p19 </s></p></note><p n="p5.7"><s n="s1.9;p5.7">Indeed, the feminist critique of traditional political thought can be carried further still to reveal "mainstream political theory as one of the very discourses that help perpetuate men's power of control"<ref target="BAWE_0138d-ftnote.023"/>. </s><s n="s2.9;p5.7">It would seem that even liberalism, which theoretically promises both men and women freedom and equality, in fact rests upon highly patriarchal assumptions<ref target="BAWE_0138d-ftnote.024"/>. </s><s n="s3.9;p5.7">Liberalism is founded upon the notion of individualism: it sees securing the individual's freedom as the principal priority of political interactions. </s><s n="s4.9;p5.7">The key trait of the liberal 'individual' is that he is rational, capable of making decisions in his best interest. </s><s n="s5.9;p5.7">These characteristics contrast remarkably to those of the archetypical woman, who has long been perceived as weak and emotional, characterised not by her mind but by her body. </s><s n="s6.9;p5.7">Indeed, Mary Wollstonecraft's claim that women were capable of rational thought caused an uproar in the 1760s, and, according to Carole Pateman, women's lack of rationality is still seen to be a 'natural' difference between the sexes today<ref target="BAWE_0138d-ftnote.025"/>. </s><s n="s7.9;p5.7">Liberalism's rational conception of the individual, combined with its belief that autonomous reasoning is an exclusively male attribute, dismisses women as unfit for political life and "not properly deserving of the rights granted to individuals by the state." </s><ref target="BAWE_0138d-ftnote.026"/><s n="s8.9;p5.7">It may be that liberalism, far from adopting a neutral conception of gender, is a key discourse of patriarchy. </s><s n="s9.9;p5.7">As expressed by Pateman, "Locke's 'individual' is masculine"<ref target="BAWE_0138d-ftnote.027"/>. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0138d-ftnote.023"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Youngs 2004, p77 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0138d-ftnote.024"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Pateman 1988, p97 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0138d-ftnote.025"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Pateman 1988, p107 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0138d-ftnote.026"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Squires 2004, p126 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0138d-ftnote.027"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Pateman 1998, p21 </s></p></note><p n="p6.7"><s n="s1.8;p6.7">The feminist challenge to liberalism also questions this ideology's second founding principle, that of the social contract. </s><s n="s2.8;p6.7">In the words of Judith Squires, "the social contract that generates liberal politics and establishes the political freedom of individuals simultaneously entails the sexual subordination of women in marriage"<ref target="BAWE_0138d-ftnote.028"/>. </s><s n="s3.8;p6.7">Indeed, Pateman argues that the social contract hides within it an oppressive 'sexual contract', a mechanism whereby men formalise their rights over women in a secure civil framework<ref target="BAWE_0138d-ftnote.029"/>. </s><s n="s4.8;p6.7">This structure is best illustrated by capitalism, which, socialist feminists argue, confines women to the domestic sphere through a marital contract specifically designed to meet certain economic interests<ref target="BAWE_0138d-ftnote.030"/>. </s><s n="s5.8;p6.7">As housewives, women serve to raise children into a disciplined new work force; they enhance men's productivity in paid labour by relieving them of the task of child-rearing; they provide an incentive for men to be productive and earn wages to support their families; and they can become a 'reserve army of labour' that is employed at no cost in times of need. </s><s n="s6.8;p6.7">In this way, the recent Western development of capitalism may have transformed the wife into being "her husband's economic dependent." </s><ref target="BAWE_0138d-ftnote.031"/><s n="s7.8;p6.7">The growth of capitalist industry in England, for example, saw the economic, legal and marital status of women decline dramatically from the seventeenth to nineteenth centuries, until their "economic dependence upon, and subordination to, their husbands was virtually complete"<ref target="BAWE_0138d-ftnote.032"/>. </s><s n="s8.8;p6.7">Women thus "constitute a permanent embarrassment and problem for liberal political theory"<ref target="BAWE_0138d-ftnote.033"/>: they reveal that this school of thought, far from promoting freedom and equality, may be a major patriarchal tool. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0138d-ftnote.028"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Squires 2004, p198 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0138d-ftnote.029"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Pateman 1988, p1 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0138d-ftnote.030"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Heywood 2003, p250 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0138d-ftnote.031"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Squires 2004, p109 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0138d-ftnote.032"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Squires 2004, p109 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0138d-ftnote.033"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Brennan, Teresa, and Pateman, Carole, ''Mere Auxiliaries to the Commonwealth': Women and the Origins of Liberalism', Chapter 4 in Phillips, Anne (ed), <hi rend="underlined">Feminism and Politics</hi>. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">Oxford : Oxford University Press (1998), p93 </s></p></note><p n="p7.7"><s n="s1.6;p7.7">Since feminism's inception, skeptics have attacked the ideology with claims that it "lacks the depth and strength of other kinds of scholarly analyses, especially those favored by the mainstream"<ref target="BAWE_0138d-ftnote.034"/>. </s><s n="s2.6;p7.7">However, such criticism is misguided: rather than suffering from a lack of analytical purchase, feminism has generated insightful new concepts that are unsettling the bases of conventional political theories. </s><s n="s3.6;p7.7">By tackling gender as a fundamental political divide, feminists highlight power relationships and social constructions hitherto ignored by mainstream thinkers. </s><s n="s4.6;p7.7">By stressing the significance of the private sphere of activity, they broaden the traditionally restricted and institutionalist scope of political analysis. </s><s n="s5.6;p7.7">By revealing the existence of a universal paradigm of patriarchy, they suggest that the dominant ideologies encourage a distorted, gender-biased interpretation of political reality. </s><s n="s6.6;p7.7">To quote Gillian Youngs,"mainstream concepts of [politics] have been traditionally constrained by masculinist blinkers" <ref target="BAWE_0138d-ftnote.035"/>- it is time for feminism to overthrow the dominant patriarchal paradigms and reveal political reality for what it truly is. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0138d-ftnote.034"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Zalewski, Marysia, ' "Women's Troubles" Again in IR', in Carver, Terrel, 'Gender and Feminism in International Relations'. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1"><hi rend="italic">International Studies Review</hi> Vol 5, No 2, (2003), p292 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0138d-ftnote.035"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Youngs 2004, p83 </s></p></note></div1></body><back><div1 type="bibliography"><head>Bibliography</head><p>Brennan, Teresa, and Pateman, Carole, ''Mere Auxiliaries to the Commonwealth': Women and the Origins of Liberalism', Chapter 4 in Phillips, Anne (ed), <hi rend="underlined">Feminism and Politics</hi>. Oxford : Oxford University Press (1998).</p><p>Carpenter, R. Charli, 'Stirring Gender into the Mainstream: Constructivism, Feminism and the Uses of IR Theory' <hi rend="italic">International Studies Review</hi> Vol 5, No 2, (2003) pp:287-302</p><p>Carver, Terrel, 'Gender and Feminism in International Relations'. <hi rend="italic">International Studies Review</hi> Vol 5, No 2, (2003) pp: 287-302</p><p>Heywood, Andrew, <hi rend="underlined">Political Ideologies: An Introduction</hi>, Palgrave Macmillan (2003) </p><p>Kinsella, Helen, 'For a Careful Reading: The Conservativism of Gender Constructivism' in Carver, Terrel, 'Gender and Feminism in International Relations'. <hi rend="italic">International Studies Review</hi> Vol 5, No 2, (2003) pp: 287-302</p><p>Moller Okin, Susan, 'Gender, the Public, and the Private', Chapter 5 in Phillips, Anne (ed), <hi rend="underlined">Feminism and Politics</hi>. Oxford : Oxford University Press (1998).</p><p>Pateman, Carole, <hi rend="underlined">The Sexual Contract</hi>. Cambridge : Polity (1988).</p><p>Squires, Judith, 'Politics Beyond Boundaries: A Feminist Perspective', in A. Leftwich (ed.), <hi rend="underlined">What is Politics?</hi> Oxford : Blackwell (2004), pp. 119-134.</p><p>Vogel, Ursula, Chapter 3 in Randall, Vicky, and Waylen, Georgina, (eds), <hi rend="underlined">Gender, Politics and the State</hi>. London : Routledge, (1998)</p><p>WMST-L, 'The Personal is Political': Origins of the Phrase". WMST-L. Internet. Accessed on 01 / 03 / 2005. Accessed at: <seg type="URL" n="http://research.umbc.edu/~korenman/wmst/pisp.html"/></p><p>Youngs, Gillian, 'Feminist International Relations: a contradiction in terms? Or: why women and gender are essential to understanding the world 'we' live in'. <hi rend="italic">International Affairs</hi> Vol 80, No 1, (2004) pp: 75-87.</p><p>Zalewski, Marysia, ' "Women's Troubles" Again in IR', in Carver, Terrel, 'Gender and Feminism in International Relations'. <hi rend="italic">International Studies Review</hi> Vol 5, No 2, (2003) pp: 287-302</p></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
