<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_0138h" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>The Transformation of the Music Industry: A Move to Technology and Perfect Competition</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">The document has a title page which contains:
document title
title part</note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">deleted: page numbers</note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">deleted: Word count: 1,954</note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">deleted: [word count: 1,954]</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">1</p><p n="date">2006-01</p><p n="module title">Economics 1</p><p n="module code">EC107</p><p n="genre family">Essay</p><p n="discipline">Economics</p><p n="disciplinary group">SS</p><p n="grade">D</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">1988</p><p n="number of s-units">82</p><p n="number of p">15</p><p n="number of tables">0</p><p n="number of figures">6</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">0</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">0</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">24.2</p><p n="average s-units per p">5.5</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">f</p><p n="year of birth">1987</p><p n="first language">French</p><p n="education">OSA</p><p n="course">EPAIS</p><p n="student ID">0138</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><docTitle><titlePart>The Transformation of the Music Industry: A Move to Technology and Perfect Competition</titlePart></docTitle><titlePart><name type="student name"/>, <name type="student ID"/></titlePart><titlePart>Economics 1 (EC 107) Micro-Economics Personal Essay Tutor: <name type="other"/> Module Director: <name type="tutor name"/> Date: 18 / 12 / 2005</titlePart></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="section"><p n="p1.15"><s n="s1.5;p1.15">Over recent years, the music industry has undergone "dramatic shocks": while the industry grew at a healthy rate of 8% per year between 1988 and 1996, it has shrunk by a total17% since then<ref target="BAWE_0138h-ftnote.001"/>. </s><s n="s2.5;p1.15">The decline of the physical market for music has been triggered by a revolutionary technological change: the development of the internet. </s><s n="s3.5;p1.15">Indeed, the RIAA<ref target="BAWE_0138h-ftnote.002"/> upholds that the current slump in physical record sales is a direct result of illegal online music sharing and piracy<ref target="BAWE_0138h-ftnote.003"/>. </s><s n="s4.5;p1.15">Yet the most credible challenge to the existing music industry is posed by an emerging legal digital market, which is expanding and may constitute 33% of all music sales by 2008<ref target="BAWE_0138h-ftnote.004"/>. </s><s n="s5.5;p1.15">The shift from a physical industry led by a small number of producers to a more accessible online production may fundamentally alter the structure of the global music market. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0138h-ftnote.001"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.3;pn1.1">"Industry brief: Music recording", Oligopoly Watch, Internet. </s><s n="s2.3;pn1.1">28 / 06 / 2003. </s><s n="s3.3;pn1.1">Accessed at: <seg type="URL" n="http://www.oligopolywatch.com/2003/06/28.html"/> </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0138h-ftnote.002"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Recording Industry Association of America </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0138h-ftnote.003"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.4;pn1.1">Peitz, Martin and Waelbroeck, Patrick, "The Effect of Internet Piracy on Music Sales: Cross-Section Evidence". </s><s n="s2.4;pn1.1">Review of Economic Research on Copyright Issues, 2004, vol. 1(2), pp. 71-79. </s><s n="s3.4;pn1.1">Internet. </s><s n="s4.4;pn1.1">Accessed at: <seg type="URL" n="http://www.serci.org/docs_1_2/waelbroeck.pdf"/> </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0138h-ftnote.004"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.5;pn1.1">McCarthy, Michael, "Record Industry lowers prices". </s><s n="s2.5;pn1.1">Internet. </s><s n="s3.5;pn1.1">USA Today. </s><s n="s4.5;pn1.1">08 / 12 / 2003. </s><s n="s5.5;pn1.1">Accessed at: <seg type="URL" n="http://www.boycott-riaa.com/article/9385"/> </s></p></note><p n="p2.15"><s n="s1.8;p2.15">The ongoing transformation of the music industry is likely to have a significant impact on its market structure. </s><s n="s2.8;p2.15">The industry is currently dominated by four record companies each controlling formidable market shares, while independent labels have little room in the market<ref target="BAWE_0138h-ftnote.005"/>. </s><s n="s3.8;p2.15">In this oligopolistic market structure<ref target="BAWE_0138h-ftnote.006"/>, firms are price makers, having some control over price and quantity. </s><s n="s4.8;p2.15">If they were to compete in price (Bertrand competition), oligopolists could near productive efficiency<ref target="BAWE_0138h-ftnote.007"/>. </s><s n="s5.8;p2.15">In Fig1, competitors would undercut each-others' prices until price equaled average cost, and the perfect competition price (Pc) and output (Xc) would be reached. </s><s n="s6.8;p2.15">However, the firms in the music industry more often vie to increase their market shares. </s><s n="s7.8;p2.15">They compete in terms of quantity (Cournot competition), which means that price is higher than Pc at Po, and quantity is below Xc at Xo. </s><s n="s8.8;p2.15">Producers make abnormal profits , and consumers are harmed, paying higher prices for less output. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0138h-ftnote.005"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Universal 25.5%, Sony BMG 21.5%, EMI 13.4%, Warner 11.3%, Independent - 24.8% - Oligopoly Watch </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0138h-ftnote.006"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">A market where there are many consumers but few producers each with a large market share </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0138h-ftnote.007"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">The maximum output is produced from the minimum number of inputs </s></p></note><figure id="BAWE_0138h-fig.001"><head>FIG1</head></figure><p n="p3.15"><s n="s1.5;p3.15">The major record labels have maintained their oligopoly by erecting high barriers to entry into the market. </s><s n="s2.5;p3.15">They have undergone vertical integration by taking possession of industries throughout the music supply chain, including distribution companies, retail sale of recordings, and manufacturing; this places high start-up costs on incoming firms. </s><s n="s3.5;p3.15">The oligopolists also have rigid control of the radio media, so that new firms face high marketing barriers. </s><s n="s4.5;p3.15">Due to their size, the "big four" further enjoy economies of scale and can fend off decreasing returns to scale for longer than independent labels. </s><s n="s5.5;p3.15">This situation discourages smaller firms from competing in the existing music market and explains the oligopolistic structure of the industry. </s></p><p n="p4.15"><s n="s1.8;p4.15">Worryingly for consumers, the oligopolists are beginning to consolidate. </s><s n="s2.8;p4.15">After a Polygram and MCA merger in 2000<ref target="BAWE_0138h-ftnote.008"/>, the EU allowed Sony and BMG to merge in 2004<ref target="BAWE_0138h-ftnote.009"/>, and EMI, Warner Music, Sony and Bertelsmann are currently seeking approval for new planned mergers.<ref target="BAWE_0138h-ftnote.010"/> If the four firms merge, they may transform the music industry into a monopoly, with only one producer of records. </s><s n="s3.8;p4.15">This could reduce production costs due to increased economies of scale: indeed, EMI estimates that it could save 360 million pounds annually by merging with Warner<ref target="BAWE_0138h-ftnote.011"/>. </s><s n="s4.8;p4.15">However, the creation of a monopoly may also be a danger for the industry. </s><s n="s5.8;p4.15">In a monopoly, the price-making firm chooses to produce at the profit-maximising output where its marginal cost equals its marginal revenue. </s><s n="s6.8;p4.15">In Fig2, prices are therefore pushed up to Pm, far above the productively efficient price Pc, and quantity falls from Xc to Xm. </s><s n="s7.8;p4.15">Price is yet higher than in an oligopolistic structure, with a lower level of output, and the monopolist enjoys abnormal profits . </s><s n="s8.8;p4.15">The quality of the product could also drop: unmotivated by competition, the monopolist need not invest in finding new artists, and could offer consumers a reduced choice of music. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0138h-ftnote.008"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">"Industry brief: Music recording", Oligopoly Watch </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0138h-ftnote.009"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">"Music's Brighter Future", The Economist, 30 October 2004, p.92 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0138h-ftnote.010"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.3;pn1.1">Matheson, Clare, "Mixing Up the Music Industry". </s><s n="s2.3;pn1.1">BBC. Internet. </s><s n="s3.3;pn1.1">Accessed at: <seg type="URL" n="http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/business/3264083.stm"/> </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0138h-ftnote.011"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Matheson, Clare, "Mixing Up..." </s></p></note><p n="p5.15"><s n="s1.5;p5.15">In addition, the monopoly causes a netba welfare loss. </s><s n="s2.5;p5.15">In perfect competition, consumer surplus<ref target="BAWE_0138h-ftnote.012"/> is represented by the area of the triangle a-b-Pc; as there is no producer surplus<ref target="BAWE_0138h-ftnote.013"/>, a-b-Pc also represents total welfare. </s><s n="s3.5;p5.15">In a monopoly, however, consumer surplus shrinks to the area , and producer surplus is the abnormal profits . </s><s n="s4.5;p5.15">In addition to this welfare transfer from consumer to monopolist, there is a total welfare loss of . </s><s n="s5.5;p5.15">The development of a monopoly in the music industry could benefit producers to the expense of consumers, and considerably reduce the market's efficiency and creativity. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0138h-ftnote.012"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">The difference between the price one is prepared to pay for a good and the market price </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0138h-ftnote.013"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">DEFINE!!! </s></p></note><figure id="BAWE_0138h-fig.002"><head>FIG2</head></figure><p n="p6.15"><s n="s1.7;p6.15">However, the attempts of the "big four" to join forces may be "desperation merger[s]"<ref target="BAWE_0138h-ftnote.014"/>, short-run solutions that cannot long rival the emerging digital music market. </s><s n="s2.7;p6.15">With independent labels "fighting to stop further consolidation among the majors"<ref target="BAWE_0138h-ftnote.015"/>, the music industry's transition to a monopoly is improbable. </s><s n="s3.7;p6.15">Instead, a legal digital music market is developing via the internet: over 180 legal download services were launched globally in 2004<ref target="BAWE_0138h-ftnote.016"/>. </s><s n="s4.7;p6.15">The digital market is eroding barriers to entry into the music industry. </s><s n="s5.7;p6.15">While the major record labels have controlled CD distribution in the past, this distribution can now occur freely online; manufacturing and production costs are also lowered by internet technology<ref target="BAWE_0138h-ftnote.017"/>, and the capital costs that restrict entry to the physical market are therefore considerably reduced in the digital scene. </s><s n="s6.7;p6.15">The internet is also an effective marketing tool that has allowed artists to bypass the major record labels despite these firms' tight control of the media<ref target="BAWE_0138h-ftnote.018"/>. </s><s n="s7.7;p6.15">The legal digital market is consequently easy to enter, and should foster more competition in this industry. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0138h-ftnote.014"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.3;pn1.1">"A Desperation Merger in a Fading Industry," The Economist. </s><s n="s2.3;pn1.1">Internet. </s><s n="s3.3;pn1.1">Accessed at: <seg type="URL" n="http://www.economist.com/background/displaystory.cfm?story_id=2216946"/> CHECK! </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0138h-ftnote.015"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">"Music's Brighter Future", The Economist </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0138h-ftnote.016"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.4;pn1.1">International Record Industry Organisation, "IFPI Releases Definitive Statistics on Global Market for Recorded Music". </s><s n="s2.4;pn1.1">IFPI. Internet. </s><s rend="italic" n="s3.4;pn1.1">London, August 2, 2005. </s><s n="s4.4;pn1.1"><hi rend="italic">Accessed at:</hi> <seg type="URL" n="http://www.ifpi.org/"/> </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0138h-ftnote.017"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Bockstedt et al, "The Move to Artist-Led..." </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0138h-ftnote.018"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.3;pn1.1">Bockstedt, Jesse C., Kauffman, Robert J., and Riggins, Frederick J., "The Move To Artist-Led Online Music Distribution: Explaining Structural Changes In The Digital Music Market". </s><s n="s2.3;pn1.1">Internet. </s><s n="s3.3;pn1.1">Accessed at: <seg type="URL" n="http://misrc.umn.edu/workingpapers/abstracts/0422.aspx"/> </s></p></note><p n="p7.15"><s n="s1.4;p7.15">This new market with numerous buyers and sellers and low barriers to entry hence presents traits of a perfectly competitive industry. </s><s n="s2.4;p7.15">Indeed, prices are standardised throughout the market, with all firms selling songs at 99 US cents each<ref target="BAWE_0138h-ftnote.019"/>. </s><s n="s3.4;p7.15">The benefits of perfect competition are substantial. </s><s n="s4.4;p7.15">The internet facilitates the flow of information between producers and consumers, fostering perfect knowledge and allowing consumers to enjoy a more elastic PED<ref target="BAWE_0138h-ftnote.020"/>. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0138h-ftnote.019"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Bockstedt et al, "The Move to Artist-Led..." </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0138h-ftnote.020"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Price Elasticity of Demand: the responsiveness of quantity demanded of a good to changes in price. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">The more elastic the PED, the more easily consumers can adjust consumption habits to changes in price. </s></p></note><figure id="BAWE_0138h-fig.003"><head>FIG3</head></figure><p n="p8.15"><s n="s1.2;p8.15">Furthermore, firms cannot make abnormal profits (as new firms can easily join the market), and production therefore occurs at price Pc and output Xc, where productive efficiency is reached and where welfare is of in Fig3. </s><s n="s2.2;p8.15">If it were to keep growing, the legal digital market would increase productivity, lower costs, and increase welfare - this transformation would cause beneficial changes in the music industry. </s></p><p n="p9.15"><s n="s1.10;p9.15">However, the physical music industry has fought the development of the digital market, as the internet also creates an illegal market for music. </s><s n="s2.10;p9.15">The major record companies argue that internet piracy "plays a significant role in the decline in music sales"<ref target="BAWE_0138h-ftnote.021"/>. </s><s n="s3.10;p9.15">Illegal file sharing has mushroomed over recent years, with over three million individuals sharing more than half a billion music files simultaneously on just a single network in 2003<ref target="BAWE_0138h-ftnote.022"/>. </s><s n="s4.10;p9.15">By providing consumers with substitutes<ref target="BAWE_0138h-ftnote.023"/> to recorded CD's, digital downloads may lower demand for physical records. </s><s n="s5.10;p9.15">Digital music offers consumers similar utility to CD's, as there is no loss in quality through the downloading process<ref target="BAWE_0138h-ftnote.024"/>. </s><s n="s6.10;p9.15">While file sharing places a high opportunity cost on users due to its illegality, it is free, and certain consumers may choose to substitute illegal downloads for physical records. </s><s n="s7.10;p9.15">Graphically, when the price of illegal digital music decreases relative to that of CD's, a consumer's budget constraint rotates outwards (E to E'). </s><s n="s8.10;p9.15">A consumer initially at equilibrium <hi rend="italic">a</hi> on indifference curve IC can now maximize utility at <hi rend="italic">b</hi> on a new indifference curve, IC', where he consumes less CD's (y falls to y') and more digital music (x increases to x'). </s><s n="s9.10;p9.15">This substitution effect is represented by the distance <hi rend="italic">s</hi>. </s><s n="s10.10;p9.15">Based on such an analysis, Pietz and Waelbroeck claim that downloading is responsible for a 20% drop in global music sales from 1998 to 2002<ref target="BAWE_0138h-ftnote.025"/>. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0138h-ftnote.021"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Peitz and Waelbroeck, "The Effect of Internet Piracy..." </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0138h-ftnote.022"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.4;pn1.1">Oberholzer, Felix, and Strumpf, Koleman, "The Effect of File Sharing on Record Sales: an Empirical Analysis", Harvard Business School. </s><s n="s2.4;pn1.1">Internet. </s><s n="s3.4;pn1.1">March 2004. </s><s n="s4.4;pn1.1">Accessed at: <seg type="URL" n="http://www.unc.edu/~cigar/papers/FileSharing_March2004.pdf"/> </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0138h-ftnote.023"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Goods with a similar utility </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0138h-ftnote.024"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Bockstedt et al, "The Move to Artist-Led..." </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0138h-ftnote.025"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Peitz and Waelbroeck, "The Effect of Internet Piracy..." </s></p></note><figure id="BAWE_0138h-fig.004"><head>FIG4</head></figure><p n="p10.15"><s n="s1.3;p10.15">However, a study by Oberholzer and Strumpf finds that file sharing has no such effect on record sales; indeed, they argue that 5,000 downloads are needed to displace the sale of a single album<ref target="BAWE_0138h-ftnote.026"/>. </s><s n="s2.3;p10.15">This finding can be explained if illegal music is considered to be an inferior good<ref target="BAWE_0138h-ftnote.027"/>. </s><s n="s3.3;p10.15">When the budget constraint in Fig5 rotates outwards (E to E') due to a drop in the price of digital music, a consumer may move to indifference curve IC'', where the new equilibrium point <hi rend="italic">c</hi> lies level with the initial equilibrium <hi rend="italic">a</hi>. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0138h-ftnote.026"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Oberholzer and Strumpf, "The Effect of File Sharing..." </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0138h-ftnote.027"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">A good for which quantity demanded falls as consumer income rises. </s></p></note><figure id="BAWE_0138h-fig.005"><head>FIG5</head></figure><p n="p11.15"><s n="s1.4;p11.15">Here, physical record consumption remains unchanged at y. </s><s n="s2.4;p11.15">File sharing could even have a positive effect on CD sales: if the new indifference curve on E' is located at IC''', with equilibrium <hi rend="italic">d</hi> lying to the left of <hi rend="italic">a</hi>, the individual consumes more physical records than previously (y increases to y'''). </s><s n="s3.4;p11.15">In the move from IC to IC''', the substitution effect <hi rend="italic">s</hi> is cancelled by the income effect <hi rend="italic">i</hi>, which works in the opposite direction. </s><s n="s4.4;p11.15">(As illegal music is an inferior good, the price consumption curves in both scenarios are no longer downwards-sloping as in Fig4, but flat (PPC'') and upwards-sloping (PPC''')). </s></p><p n="p12.15"><s n="s1.4;p12.15">Oberholzer and Strumpf offer an alternative explanation for the positive impact of piracy on CD sales. </s><s n="s2.4;p12.15">They find that 60% of file sharers use downloading to sample music, which leads to them buying at least one CD<ref target="BAWE_0138h-ftnote.028"/>. </s><s n="s3.4;p12.15">One must also note that pirated music is not the only available substitute for CD's; other forms of entertainment, such as DVD's and gaming, may also draw consumers away from records. </s><s n="s4.4;p12.15">Thus, the decline of the physical music market cannot be attributed entirely to piracy. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0138h-ftnote.028"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Oberholzer and Strumpf, "The Effect of File Sharing..." </s></p></note><p n="p13.15"><s n="s1.7;p13.15">Factors such as changes in consumer income may also explain the fall in sales. </s><s n="s2.7;p13.15">When income increases, the consumer's budget constraint shifts outwards (E to E' in Fig6), and one would expect the quantity demanded of most goods to rise (the consumer moves from <hi rend="italic">a</hi> on IC to <hi rend="italic">c</hi> on IC'', where the quantity consumed of CD's has risen from X to X''). </s><s n="s3.7;p13.15">Indeed, a "strong positive effect of income on CD purchases" has been observed in Europe<ref target="BAWE_0138h-ftnote.029"/>. </s><s n="s4.7;p13.15">However, the opposite relationship exists in the United States, where falling sales have been accompanied by annual 3% growth in GDP<ref target="BAWE_0138h-ftnote.030"/>. </s><s n="s5.7;p13.15">In this case, the consumer shifts to equilibrium <hi rend="italic">b</hi> on IC' to the left of <hi rend="italic">a</hi>, and the rise in income causes a drop in CD consumption (from X to X'). </s><s n="s6.7;p13.15">This means that while CD's are normal goods<ref target="BAWE_0138h-ftnote.031"/> for European consumers (the income consumption curve ICC'' is downwards-sloping), they are considered inferior in the United States (ICC' slopes upwards). </s><s n="s7.7;p13.15">Consumer constraints alone cannot explain the drop in CD sales, and variations in consumer preferences must therefore also be taken into account. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0138h-ftnote.029"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Peitz and Waelbroeck, "The Effect of Internet Piracy..." </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0138h-ftnote.030"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.4;pn1.1">Gold, Michael, "The CD Sales Slump: Not Simply because of MP3". </s><s n="s2.4;pn1.1">Internet. </s><s n="s3.4;pn1.1">16 / 06 / 2002. </s><s n="s4.4;pn1.1">Accessed at: <seg type="URL" n="http://www.sric-bi.com/DF/DFnews/2002-07-16.shtml"/> </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0138h-ftnote.031"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Goods for which there is a positive relationship between consumer income and quantity demanded </s></p></note><figure id="BAWE_0138h-fig.006"><head>FIG6</head></figure><p n="p14.15"><s n="s1.4;p14.15">In the music industry, consumer preferences are greatly influenced by age: Boorstin (2004) finds that areas in the United States where most of the population is older than 24 have high CD sales, while those with a majority of younger inhabitants suffer from "significantly decrease[d]" sales.<ref target="BAWE_0138h-ftnote.032"/> There indeed seems to be a "graying of the music audience"<ref target="BAWE_0138h-ftnote.033"/> as younger individuals turn to digital music substitutes. </s><s n="s2.4;p14.15">While the median age of music buyers was approximately 23 in 1989, it was almost 32 by 2000; moreover, consumers above 40 years of age account for most purchases in the over-32 group<ref target="BAWE_0138h-ftnote.034"/>. </s><s n="s3.4;p14.15">Although there is a negative relationship between consumer age and CD purchasing, however, record companies continue to focus their releases on younger consumers - this miscalculation may account, at least in part, for the decline of the music industry. </s><s n="s4.4;p14.15">Demand factors "appear to play at least as great role in the current slump as do[es] . . . the Internet"<ref target="BAWE_0138h-ftnote.035"/>. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0138h-ftnote.032"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Peitz and Waelbroeck, "The Effect of Internet Piracy..." </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0138h-ftnote.033"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Gold, Michael, "The CD Sales Slump..." </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0138h-ftnote.034"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Gold, Michael, "The CD Sales Slump..." </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0138h-ftnote.035"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Gold, Michael, "The CD Sales Slump..." </s></p></note><p n="p15.15"><s n="s1.6;p15.15">The record companies dominating the current physical music industry are therefore misled in their analysis of the problem facing them. </s><s n="s2.6;p15.15">Attributing their falling sales entirely to the illegal online market, the "big four" have directed much energy into suing file sharing sites and users. </s><s n="s3.6;p15.15">However, by carrying out over 2,100 new legal cases against individuals in 2005, organizations such as the RIAA may simply discourage potential consumers who may use downloads to sample music prior to purchasing<ref target="BAWE_0138h-ftnote.036"/>. </s><s n="s4.6;p15.15">Moreover, the oligopolists' focus on piracy has left other problems, such as changing demand factors and the emergence of substitute goods, unattended. </s><s n="s5.6;p15.15">Most importantly, rather than attempting to stifle online music, major record labels must accept that "the internet and digital technology will define the industry's future"<ref target="BAWE_0138h-ftnote.037"/>. </s><s n="s6.6;p15.15">If the current music producers can embrace the expanding digital market and adjust to its technology, a more competitive and productive music industry will flourish. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0138h-ftnote.036"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.3;pn1.1">International Record Industry Organisation, "Biggest Wave of Actions Yet Announced Against Illegal File-Sharing". </s><s n="s2.3;pn1.1">IFPI. Internet. </s><s n="s3.3;pn1.1">Accessed at: <seg type="URL" n="http://www.ifpi.org/site-content/press/20051115.html"/> </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0138h-ftnote.037"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">"Music's Brighter Future", The Economist </s></p></note></div1></body><back><div1 type="bibliography"><head>Bibliography</head><p>"A Desperation Merger in a Fading Industry," The Economist. Internet. Accessed at: <seg type="URL" n="http://www.economist.com/background/displaystory.cfm?story_id=2216946"/> - CHECK!</p><p>Bockstedt, Jesse C., Kauffman, Robert J., and Riggins, Frederick J., "The Move To Artist-Led Online Music Distribution: Explaining Structural Changes In The Digital Music Market". Internet. Accessed at: <seg type="URL" n="http://misrc.umn.edu/workingpapers/abstracts/0422.aspx"/></p><p>Gold, Michael, "The CD Sales Slump: Not Simply because of MP3". Internet. 16 / 06 / 2002. Accessed at: <seg type="URL" n="http://www.sric-bi.com/DF/DFnews/2002-07-16.shtml"/></p><p>"Industry brief: Music recording", Oligopoly Watch, Internet. 28 / 06 / 2003. Accessed at: <seg type="URL" n="http://www.oligopolywatch.com/2003/06/28.html"/></p><p>International Record Industry Organisation, "Biggest Wave of Actions Yet Announced Against Illegal File-Sharing". IFPI. Internet. Accessed at: <seg type="URL" n="http://www.ifpi.org/site-content/press/20051115.html"/></p><p>International Record Industry Organisation, "IFPI Releases Definitive Statistics on Global Market for Recorded Music". IFPI. Internet. <hi rend="italic">London, August 2, 2005. Accessed at:</hi> <seg type="URL" n="http://www.ifpi.org/"/> </p><p>McCarthy, Michael, "Record Industry lowers prices". Internet. USA Today. 08 / 12 / 2003. Accessed at: <seg type="URL" n="http://www.boycott-riaa.com/article/9385"/></p><p>Oberholzer, Felix, and Strumpf, Koleman, "The Effect of File Sharing on Record Sales: an Empirical Analysis", Harvard Business School. Internet. March 2004. Accessed at: <seg type="URL" n="http://www.unc.edu/~cigar/papers/FileSharing_March2004.pdf"/></p><p>"Music's Brighter Future", The Economist, 30 October 2004, p.92</p><p>Peitz, Martin and Waelbroeck, Patrick, "The Effect of Internet Piracy on Music Sales: Cross-Section Evidence". Review of Economic Research on Copyright Issues, 2004, vol. 1(2), pp. 71-79. Internet. Accessed at: <seg type="URL" n="http://www.serci.org/docs_1_2/waelbroeck.pdf"/></p></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
