<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_0138b" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>European Press Coverage of the Merkel-Schroeder Struggle: Striving to Widen the Scope of Media Analysis</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">deleted: [word count: 1,444]
</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">1</p><p n="date">2005-10</p><p n="module title">Introduction to Politics</p><p n="module code">PO107</p><p n="genre family">Essay</p><p n="discipline">Politics</p><p n="disciplinary group">SS</p><p n="grade">D</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">1429</p><p n="number of s-units">47</p><p n="number of p">9</p><p n="number of tables">0</p><p n="number of figures">0</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">0</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">0</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">30.4</p><p n="average s-units per p">5.2</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">f</p><p n="year of birth">1987</p><p n="first language">French</p><p n="education">OSA</p><p n="course">EPAIS</p><p n="student ID">0138</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><titlePart><name type="student name"/><name type="student ID"/> Introduction to Politics 16 / 10 / 2005</titlePart><docTitle><titlePart>European Press Coverage of the Merkel-Schroeder Struggle: Striving to Widen the Scope of Media Analysis</titlePart></docTitle></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="section"><p n="p1.9"><s n="s1.4;p1.9">On September 18 <hi rend="sup">th</hi> 2005, in the wake of a heated political race, German citizens voted to elect their Chancellor. </s><s n="s2.4;p1.9">For weeks leading up to the elections, the rivalry between leader of the Christian Democratic Union (CDU) Angela Merkel and the existing Social Democrat (SPD) Chancellor, Gerhard Schroeder, received immense media coverage. </s><s n="s3.4;p1.9">Despite the fact that the outcome of these elections could have "radically alter[ed] the face of Europe"<ref target="BAWE_0138b-ftnote.001"/>, however, the European media outside Germany seems to have communicated the two parties' race to the overseas EU public in a largely inaccurate manner. </s><s n="s4.4;p1.9">By comparing press treatment of the pre-election period to the examination that might be carried out by a political analyst, one realizes that our media may need to make significant improvements in its coverage of political issues. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0138b-ftnote.001"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.6;pn1.1">Horsley, William, "What German Poll Means for Europe". </s><s n="s2.6;pn1.1">BBC News. </s><s n="s3.6;pn1.1">Internet. </s><s n="s4.6;pn1.1">08 / 09 / 2005. </s><s n="s5.6;pn1.1">Accessed on 05 / 10 / 2005. </s><s n="s6.6;pn1.1">Accessed at: <seg type="URL" n="http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/world/europe/4226802.stm"/> </s></p></note><p n="p2.9"><s n="s1.5;p2.9">Throughout the German campaign, one of the focal points of European newspapers has been to contrast the CDU and SPD candidates on a personal basis. </s><s n="s2.5;p2.9">In certain publications, such as the Spanish 'El mundo', this comparison is limited to describing Schroeder as "combative", by juxtaposition to a Merkel "with tears in her eyes" at one of her rallies<ref target="BAWE_0138b-ftnote.002"/>. </s><s n="s3.5;p2.9">However, 'The Guardian' goes further, labeling Merkel as "dull [and] uninspiring" and depicting her rival as "the charming and roguish Schroeder"<ref target="BAWE_0138b-ftnote.003"/>. </s><s n="s4.5;p2.9">Similarly, the BBC claims that one of Merkel's key challenges will be, "struggl[ing] to match the famous charisma of Mr Schroeder"<ref target="BAWE_0138b-ftnote.004"/>. In a further attempt to spark readers' interest, England's 'Expatica' bases articles wholly on an exchange of venomous words between the candidates during a television debate. </s><s n="s5.5;p2.9">This narrow focus on the two politicians' personalities, while helping journalists to better interest and manipulate a politically unaware audience, poorly informs readers; nevertheless, it dominates pre-election articles in major European publications. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0138b-ftnote.002"><p n="pn1.2"><s n="s1.1;pn1.2">EFE, "Un combativo Gerhard Schröder y una convencida Angela Merkel cierran sus </s></p><p n="pn2.2"><s n="s1.6;pn2.2">campañas en Alemania". </s><s n="s2.6;pn2.2">El mundo. </s><s n="s3.6;pn2.2">Internet. </s><s n="s4.6;pn2.2">16 / 09 / 2005. </s><s n="s5.6;pn2.2">Accessed on 14 / 10 / 2005. </s><s n="s6.6;pn2.2">Accessed at: <seg type="URL" n="http://www.elmundo.es/elmundo/2005/09/16/internacional/1126905330.html"/> </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0138b-ftnote.003"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.6;pn1.1">The Observer, "Germany in flux as 48pc can't decide how to vote". </s><s n="s2.6;pn1.1">Internet. </s><s n="s3.6;pn1.1">28 / 08 / 2005. </s><s n="s4.6;pn1.1">Guardian Unlimited. </s><s n="s5.6;pn1.1">Accessed on 08 / 09 / 2005. </s><s n="s6.6;pn1.1">Accessed at <seg type="URL" n="http://www.guardian.co.uk/germany/article/0,,1558099,00.html"/> </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0138b-ftnote.004"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.6;pn1.1">Murphy, Clare, "Merkel's Bumpy Road to Polls". </s><s n="s2.6;pn1.1">BBC News. </s><s n="s3.6;pn1.1">Internet. </s><s n="s4.6;pn1.1">16 / 09 / 2005. </s><s n="s5.6;pn1.1">Accessed on 05 / 10 / 2005. </s><s n="s6.6;pn1.1">Accessed at: <seg type="URL" n="http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/world/europe/4251572.stm"/> </s></p></note><p n="p3.9"><s n="s1.5;p3.9">From a political analyst's perspective, this style of coverage does have some validity: if one accepts the individual level of analysis, whereby individuals are key political actors in international relations, the personality of a leader may be seen to have some bearing on his or her decision-making. </s><s n="s2.5;p3.9">Indeed, the processual assumption states that politics exist in all spheres of life and may often occur on a personal basis. </s><s n="s3.5;p3.9">Trying to target the EU public by appealing to readers' psychology also illustrates a voluntarist approach to political thought: individuals are more than self-interested rational actors, and they have volition to take decisions based on factors other than a straightforward ordering of preferences. </s><s n="s4.5;p3.9">Despite this theoretical backing, however, the individual level of analysis is rather restricted. </s><s n="s5.5;p3.9">In order to arrive at a more conclusive study, a political analyst may seek to broaden the scope of his or her investigation.<ref target="BAWE_0138b-ftnote.005"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0138b-ftnote.005"><p n="pn1.3"><s n="s1.1;pn1.3">Axford, Barrie; Browning, Gary K.; Huggins, Richard; and Rosamond, Ben, "Chapter 1: </s></p><p n="pn2.3"><s n="s1.3;pn2.3">Individuals: is Politics Really about People?". </s><s n="s2.3;pn2.3"><hi rend="underlined">Politics: An Introduction</hi>. </s><s n="s3.3;pn2.3">2 <hi rend="sup">nd</hi> edition, Routledge, 2002. </s></p><p n="pn3.3"><s n="s1.4;pn3.3">Leftwitch, Adrian, "Thinking Politically: On the Politics of Politics". </s><s rend="underlined" n="s2.4;pn3.3">What is Politics? </s><s n="s3.4;pn3.3">. </s><s n="s4.4;pn3.3">2 <hi rend="sup">nd</hi> edition, 2004. </s></p></note><p n="p4.9"><s n="s1.6;p4.9">Indeed, much as they make individual scrutiny a main point of interest, most European newspapers do proceed onto a domestic level of analysis in their evaluation of Germany's two candidates. </s><s n="s2.6;p4.9">Particularly, the Spanish press concentrates on how the SPD plans to rally the support of different interest groups. </s><s n="s3.6;p4.9">Schroeder's party satisfies the working class by guaranteeing that the German economy will "continue being productive without destroying . . . workers' rights"; it appeals to ecologists with the argument that economic development will not sacrifice ecological sensitivity, and finally vows to "peacefully resolve world conflicts", thus gaining the backing of pacifists as well<ref target="BAWE_0138b-ftnote.006"/>. </s><s n="s4.6;p4.9">Similarly, the UK's 'Expatica' writes that the SPD's economic plans are, "beloved by unions and hated by most business leaders"<ref target="BAWE_0138b-ftnote.007"/>. </s><s n="s5.6;p4.9">In France, 'Nord Eclair' examines how the election of Merkel as Germany's first female Chancellor would impact female voters<ref target="BAWE_0138b-ftnote.008"/>. </s><s n="s6.6;p4.9">By evaluating each party's assets and shortcomings in the eyes of Germany's interest groups, these publications prove slightly more informative for the non-German European reader. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0138b-ftnote.006"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.6;pn1.1">EFE, "Un combativo Gerhard Schröder y una convencida Angela Merkel cierran sus campañas en Alemania". </s><s n="s2.6;pn1.1">El mundo. </s><s n="s3.6;pn1.1">Internet. </s><s n="s4.6;pn1.1">16 / 09 / 2005. </s><s n="s5.6;pn1.1">Accessed on 14 / 10 / 2005. </s><s n="s6.6;pn1.1">Accessed at: <seg type="URL" n="http://www.elmundo.es/elmundo/2005/09/16/internacional/1126905330.html"/> </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0138b-ftnote.007"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.6;pn1.1">DPA, "Schroeder fires up party for last stretch of campaign". </s><s n="s2.6;pn1.1">Expatica. </s><s n="s3.6;pn1.1">Internet. </s><s n="s4.6;pn1.1">31 / 08 /2005. </s><s n="s5.6;pn1.1">Accessed on 14 / 10 / 2005. </s><s n="s6.6;pn1.1">Accessed at: <seg type="URL" n="http://www.expatica.com/source/site_article.asp?channel_id=2&amp;story_id=23259"/> </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0138b-ftnote.008"><p n="pn1.3"><s n="s1.2;pn1.3">Clauwaert, Jules, "Nord Eclair", "Revue de presse: les elections allemandes". </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.3">Le Nouvel </s></p><p n="pn2.3"><s n="s1.5;pn2.3">Observateur. </s><s n="s2.5;pn2.3">Internet. </s><s n="s3.5;pn2.3">17 / 09 / 2005. </s><s n="s4.5;pn2.3">Accessed on 14 / 10 / 2005. </s><s n="s5.5;pn2.3">Accessed at: </s></p><p n="pn3.3"><s n="s1.1;pn3.3"><seg type="URL" n="http://archquo.nouvelobs.com/cgi/articles?ad=societe/20050917.OBS9452.html"/> </s></p></note><p n="p5.9"><s n="s1.6;p5.9">Certain newspapers widen the domestic level of analysis by comparing the CDU and SPD in terms of domestic German policy. </s><s n="s2.6;p5.9">Thus, both 'The Guardian' (UK) and 'El mundo' (Spain) give an overview of Schroeder's plans to cut down on unemployment benefits, and outline Merkel's goal of a "complete political change"<ref target="BAWE_0138b-ftnote.009"/>. </s><s n="s3.6;p5.9">Readers learn that, while the SPD would ensure free university education and raise the top rate of tax, for example, the CDU instead proposes to "increase VAT from 16 to 18 per cent" and to introduce tuition fees for students<ref target="BAWE_0138b-ftnote.010"/>. </s><s n="s4.6;p5.9">In France, 'Le Nouvel Observateur' calls attention to the "tactical uncertainty" of Merkel's aims, which it sees as too vague<ref target="BAWE_0138b-ftnote.011"/>. </s><s n="s5.6;p5.9">While carried out by a restricted sample of publications, the investigation of domestic policy proves to be a conclusive and empirical manner of contrasting the two rival parties. </s><s n="s6.6;p5.9">Indeed, a somewhat similar evaluation may be gleaned from considering the political expert's viewpoint. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0138b-ftnote.009"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.6;pn1.1">The Observer, "Germans buy Merkel's miracle". </s><s n="s2.6;pn1.1">Internet. </s><s n="s3.6;pn1.1">04 / 09 / 2005. </s><s n="s4.6;pn1.1">Guardian Unlimited. </s><s n="s5.6;pn1.1">Accessed on 08 / 09 / 2005. </s><s n="s6.6;pn1.1">Accessed at: <seg type="URL" n="http://www.guardian.co.uk/germany/article/0,,1562459,00.html"/> </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0138b-ftnote.010"><p n="pn1.2"><s n="s1.6;pn1.2">The Observer, "Germans buy Merkel's miracle". </s><s n="s2.6;pn1.2">Internet. </s><s n="s3.6;pn1.2">04 / 09 / 2005. </s><s n="s4.6;pn1.2">Guardian Unlimited. </s><s n="s5.6;pn1.2">Accessed on 08 / 09 / 2005. </s><s n="s6.6;pn1.2">Accessed at: <seg type="URL" n="http://www.guardian.co.uk/germany/article/0,,1562459,00.html"/> </s></p><p n="pn2.2"><s n="s1.6;pn2.2">EFE, "Un combativo Gerhard Schröder y una convencida Angela Merkel cierran sus campañas en Alemania". </s><s n="s2.6;pn2.2">El mundo. </s><s n="s3.6;pn2.2">Internet. </s><s n="s4.6;pn2.2">16 / 09 / 2005. </s><s n="s5.6;pn2.2">Accessed on 14 / 10 / 2005. </s><s n="s6.6;pn2.2">Accessed at: <seg type="URL" n="http://www.elmundo.es/elmundo/2005/09/16/internacional/1126905330.html"/> </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0138b-ftnote.011"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.6;pn1.1">"Legislatives Allemandes: Angela Merkel, Chretienne-Democrate". </s><s n="s2.6;pn1.1">Le Nouvel Observateur. </s><s n="s3.6;pn1.1">Internet. </s><s n="s4.6;pn1.1">16 / 09 / 2005. </s><s n="s5.6;pn1.1">Accessed on 14 / 10 / 2005. </s><s n="s6.6;pn1.1">Accessed at: <seg type="URL" n="http://archquo.nouvelobs.com/"/> </s></p></note><p n="p6.9"><s n="s1.8;p6.9">As with the individual level of analysis, the domestic scrutiny of the CDU and SPD is rooted in political theory. </s><s n="s2.8;p6.9">By considering the formal institutions and ideologies that Merkel and Schroeder represent, the media could be seen to consider the two candidates from an arena approach. </s><s n="s3.8;p6.9">This coverage is additionally consistent with institutional analysis, which focuses on the rules, norms and values shaping political exchanges; such norms determine what economic or political reforms CDU or SPD leaders can envisage. </s><s n="s4.8;p6.9">Thus, to understand why Merkel's feminist arguments have an influential impact on female voters, one must be aware that, in Germany, "the traditional image of the woman entirely committed to her "three K's" (Kinder, children, Kirche, church, and Küche, cooking) has lost its popularity"<ref target="BAWE_0138b-ftnote.012"/>. </s><s n="s5.8;p6.9">Some of the CDU's shortcomings can also be explained through the lens of culture and institutions. </s><s n="s6.8;p6.9">If Merkel has lost some support through "seeking an "elbow society" driven by egoism"<ref target="BAWE_0138b-ftnote.013"/>, this can be attributed to German socialist past: citizens are firmly embedded in cultural structures of their society (communitarianism), and are reluctant to see their collectivist values change. </s><s n="s7.8;p6.9">By contrast, an analyst concerned with the scientific aspect of politics may consider the importance of interest groups and economic reforms in the Merkel and Schroeder campaigns to be evidence of Rational Choice Theory; individuals make political decisions such as voting based on an empirical cost-benefit analysis, by simply selecting the party most likely to satisfy the needs of one's own interest group. </s><s n="s8.8;p6.9">In this way, the press's occasional presentation of a domestic level of analysis can be seen to lead to a more comprehensive discussion of the CDU and SPD campaigns.<ref target="BAWE_0138b-ftnote.014"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0138b-ftnote.012"><p n="pn1.2"><s n="s1.6;pn1.2">Clauwaert, Jules, "Nord Eclair", "Revue de presse: les elections allemandes". </s><s n="s2.6;pn1.2">Le Nouvel Observateur. </s><s n="s3.6;pn1.2">Internet. </s><s n="s4.6;pn1.2">17 / 09 / 2005. </s><s n="s5.6;pn1.2">Accessed on 14 / 10 / 2005. </s><s n="s6.6;pn1.2">Accessed at: </s></p><p n="pn2.2"><s n="s1.1;pn2.2"><seg type="URL" n="http://archquo.nouvelobs.com/cgi/articles?ad=societe/20050917.OBS9452.html"/> </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0138b-ftnote.013"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.6;pn1.1">DPA, "Schroeder fires up party for last stretch of campaign". </s><s n="s2.6;pn1.1">Expatica. </s><s n="s3.6;pn1.1">Internet. </s><s n="s4.6;pn1.1">31 / 08 /2005. </s><s n="s5.6;pn1.1">Accessed on 14 / 10 / 2005. </s><s n="s6.6;pn1.1">Accessed at: <seg type="URL" n="http://www.expatica.com/source/site_article.asp?channel_id=2&amp;story_id=23259"/> </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0138b-ftnote.014"><p n="pn1.3"><s n="s1.1;pn1.3">Axford, Barrie; Browning, Gary K.; Huggins, Richard; and Rosamond, Ben, "Chapter 1: </s></p><p n="pn2.3"><s n="s1.3;pn2.3">Individuals: is Politics Really about People?". </s><s n="s2.3;pn2.3"><hi rend="underlined">Politics: An Introduction</hi>. </s><s n="s3.3;pn2.3">2 <hi rend="sup">nd</hi> edition, Routledge, 2002. </s></p><p n="pn3.3"><s n="s1.4;pn3.3">Leftwitch, Adrian, "Thinking Politically: On the Politics of Politics". </s><s rend="underlined" n="s2.4;pn3.3">What is Politics? </s><s n="s3.4;pn3.3">. </s><s n="s4.4;pn3.3">2 <hi rend="sup">nd</hi> edition, 2004. </s></p></note><p n="p7.9"><s n="s1.5;p7.9">After progressing from an individual investigation to a domestic one, some publications broaden the scope of their evaluation yet more. </s><s n="s2.5;p7.9">Such is the case of the BBC's William Horsley, who considers the effect that the election outcomes may have at a global level. </s><s n="s3.5;p7.9">He explains that a CDU win could forge a "three-way understanding among Berlin, Paris and London", which might be able to resolve European problems such as the breakdown of the EU constitution<ref target="BAWE_0138b-ftnote.015"/>; furthermore, the impact of a possible friendship between Germany and the United States under Merkel's leadership is explored. </s><s n="s4.5;p7.9">In France, 'L'Humanite' adopts an equally wide span by speculating on the fate of European socialism as a result of the elections, just as 'Liberation'(France) analyses the German situation by drawing parallels to the current relationship between French socialist and conservative parties<ref target="BAWE_0138b-ftnote.016"/>. </s><s n="s5.5;p7.9">Given that, "in the EU, the behaviour of Europe's "Big Three" - Germany, France and Britain - is often decisive"<ref target="BAWE_0138b-ftnote.017"/>, it is such far-ranging evaluation that proves of most direct import to non-German European readers. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0138b-ftnote.015"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.6;pn1.1">Horsley, William, "What German Poll Means for Europe". </s><s n="s2.6;pn1.1">BBC News. </s><s n="s3.6;pn1.1">Internet. </s><s n="s4.6;pn1.1">08 / 09 / 2005. </s><s n="s5.6;pn1.1">Accessed on 05 / 10 / 2005. </s><s n="s6.6;pn1.1">Accessed at: <seg type="URL" n="http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/world/europe/4226802.stm"/> </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0138b-ftnote.016"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.6;pn1.1">Sabatier, Patrick, "Liberation", "Revue de presse: les elections allemandes". </s><s n="s2.6;pn1.1">Le Nouvel Observateur. </s><s n="s3.6;pn1.1">Internet. </s><s n="s4.6;pn1.1">17 / 09 / 2005. </s><s n="s5.6;pn1.1">Accessed on 14 / 10 / 2005. </s><s n="s6.6;pn1.1">Accessed at: <seg type="URL" n="http://archquo.nouvelobs.com/cgi/articles?ad=societe/20050917.OBS9452.html"/> </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0138b-ftnote.017"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.6;pn1.1">Horsley, William, "What German Poll Means for Europe". </s><s n="s2.6;pn1.1">BBC News. </s><s n="s3.6;pn1.1">Internet. </s><s n="s4.6;pn1.1">08 / 09 / 2005. </s><s n="s5.6;pn1.1">Accessed on 05 / 10 / 2005. </s><s n="s6.6;pn1.1">Accessed at: <seg type="URL" n="http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/world/europe/4226802.stm"/> </s></p></note><p n="p8.9"><s n="s1.5;p8.9">Indeed, for certain political experts, a global or interstate level of analysis may be considered more conducive to understanding the complexities of the international system. </s><s n="s2.5;p8.9">The Marxist and Interpretive approaches, for example, both argue that human behaviour is guided by underlying structures that repeat over the ages, but that are unobservable from empirical evidence - one must take a necessary distance from events in order to comprehend their workings. </s><s n="s3.5;p8.9">Similarly, if they are to convey the wider implications of the CDU-SPD election outcomes to readers, European newspapers cannot restrict their study to individual or domestic levels. </s><s n="s4.5;p8.9">A broader investigation generates not just descriptive knowledge applicable at a single point in time, but also theoretical knowledge that can help to identify global trends in politics. </s><s n="s5.5;p8.9">Unfortunately, only a minority of newspapers considers the German elections from such an ample perspective. <ref target="BAWE_0138b-ftnote.018"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0138b-ftnote.018"><p n="pn1.3"><s n="s1.1;pn1.3">Axford, Barrie; Browning, Gary K.; Huggins, Richard; and Rosamond, Ben, "Chapter 1: </s></p><p n="pn2.3"><s n="s1.3;pn2.3">Individuals: is Politics Really about People?". </s><s n="s2.3;pn2.3"><hi rend="underlined">Politics: An Introduction</hi>. </s><s n="s3.3;pn2.3">2 <hi rend="sup">nd</hi> edition, Routledge, 2002. </s></p><p n="pn3.3"><s n="s1.4;pn3.3">Leftwitch, Adrian, "Thinking Politically: On the Politics of Politics". </s><s rend="underlined" n="s2.4;pn3.3">What is Politics? </s><s n="s3.4;pn3.3">. </s><s n="s4.4;pn3.3">2 <hi rend="sup">nd</hi> edition, 2004. </s></p></note><p n="p9.9"><s n="s1.3;p9.9">In conclusion, while the September 18 <hi rend="sup">th</hi> elections generated extensive attention from European media outside Germany, the coverage of this issue leaves much to be desired. </s><s n="s2.3;p9.9">Due to the narrowness of political analysis undertaken by the majority of pre-election newspapers consulted, the average European citizen received little access to concrete information regarding the importance of the CDU-SPD power struggle. </s><s n="s3.3;p9.9">Yet political theory suggests a solution to this dilemma: by moving away from a restrictive level of analysis and into a more global realm, the media may soon offer readers a more enriching understanding of contemporary political issues. </s></p></div1></body><back><div1 type="bibliography"><head>Bibliography</head><p>Axford, Barrie; Browning, Gary K.; Huggins, Richard; and Rosamond, Ben, "Chapter 1:</p><p>Individuals: is Politics Really about People?". <hi rend="underlined">Politics: An Introduction</hi>. 2<hi rend="sup">nd</hi></p><p>edition, Routledge, 2002.</p><p>Clauwaert, Jules, "Nord Eclair", "Revue de presse: les elections allemandes". Le Nouvel</p><p>Observateur. Internet. 17 / 09 / 2005. Accessed on 14 / 10 / 2005. Accessed at:</p><p><seg type="URL" n="http://archquo.nouvelobs.com/cgi/articles?ad=societe/20050917.OBS9452.html"/></p><p>DPA, "Merkel to Schroeder - "You're lying, Chancellor!". Expatica. Internet. 07 / 09 / 2005. Accessed on 14 / 10 / 2005. Accessed at:<seg type="URL" n="http://www.expatica.com/source/site_article.asp?channel_id=4&amp;story_id=23471"/></p><p>DPA, "Schroeder fires up party for last stretch of campaign". Expatica. Internet. 31 / 08 / 2005. Accessed on 14 / 10 / 2005. Accessed at:<seg type="URL" n="http://www.expatica.com/source/site_article.asp?channel_id=2&amp;story_id=23259"/></p><p>EFE, "Un combativo Gerhard Schröder y una convencida Angela Merkel cierran sus</p><p>campañas en Alemania". El mundo. Internet. 16 / 09 / 2005. Accessed on 14 / 10 /</p><p>2005. Accessed at: <seg type="URL" n="http://www.elmundo.es/elmundo/2005/09/16/internacional/1126905330.html"/></p><p>Furlong, Ray, "German Election Tension Mounts". BBC News. Internet. 02 / 09 / 2005. Accessed on 05 / 10 / 2005. Accessed at:<seg type="URL" n="http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/world/europe/4207842.stm"/></p><p>Horsley, William, "What German Poll Means for Europe". BBC News. Internet. 08 / 09 / 2005. Accessed on 05 / 10 / 2005. Accessed at:<seg type="URL" n="http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/world/europe/4226802.stm"/></p><p>Laurent, Pierre, "L'Humanite", "Revue de presse: les elections allemandes". Le Nouvel</p><p>Observateur. Internet. 17 / 09 / 2005. Accessed on 14 / 10 / 2005. Accessed at:</p><p><seg type="URL" n="http://archquo.nouvelobs.com/cgi/articles?ad=societe/20050917.OBS9452.html"/></p><p>"Legislatives Allemandes: Angela Merkel, Chretienne-Democrate". Le Nouvel</p><p>Observateur. Internet. 16 / 09 / 2005. Accessed on 14 / 10 / 2005. Accessed at: <seg type="URL" n="http://archquo.nouvelobs.com/"/></p><p>Leftwitch, Adrian, "Thinking Politically: On the Politics of Politics". <hi rend="underlined">What is Politics?</hi>.</p><p>2<hi rend="sup">nd</hi> edition, 2004.</p><p>Martin, Natalia, "Último día en Alemania de una campaña electoral marcada por la</p><p>mejora de Schröder frente a Merkel". El mundo. Internet. 16 / 09 / 2005.</p><p>Accessed on 14 / 10 / 2005. Accessed at: <seg type="URL" n="http://www.elmundo.es/elmundo/2005/09/16/internacional/1126869165.html"/></p><p>Murphy, Clare, "Merkel's Bumpy Road to Polls". BBC News. Internet. 16 / 09 / 2005.</p><p>Accessed on 05 / 10 / 2005. Accessed at:</p><p><seg type="URL" n="http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/world/europe/4251572.stm"/></p><p>Noblet, Charlotte, "Angela Merkel, portrait d'une candidate sur la défensive." L'Humanite. Internet. 15 / 09 / 2005. Accessed on 14 / 10 / 2005. Accessed at:<seg type="URL" n="http://www.humanite.fr/journal/2005-09-15/2005-09-15-814056"/></p><p>The Observer, "Germans buy Merkel's miracle". Guardian Unlimited. Internet. 04 / 09 / 2005. Accessed on 08 / 09 / 2005. Accessed at:<seg type="URL" n="http://www.guardian.co.uk/germany/article/0,,1562459,00.html"/></p><p>The Observer, "Germany in flux as 48pc can't decide how to vote". Guardian Unlimited.</p><p>Internet. 28 / 08 / 2005. Accessed on 08 / 09 / 2005. Accessed at:<seg type="URL" n="http://www.guardian.co.uk/germany/article/0,,1558099,00.html"/></p><p>Odent, Bruno, "Balises." L'Humanite. Internet. 10 / 08 / 2005. Accessed on 14 / 10 /</p><p>2005. Accessed at: <seg type="URL" n="http://www.humanite.fr/journal/2005-10-08/2005-10-08-815582"/></p><p>Sabatier, Patrick, "Liberation", "Revue de presse: les elections allemandes". Le Nouvel</p><p>Observateur. Internet. 17 / 09 / 2005. Accessed on 14 / 10 / 2005. Accessed at:</p><p><seg type="URL" n="http://archquo.nouvelobs.com/cgi/articles?ad=societe/20050917.OBS9452.html"/></p></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
