<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_0138e" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>The Rise of Transnational Actors: Towards the Creation of a "New World Order"?</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">The document has a title page which contains:
document title
title part</note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">header: student name and number
footer: page numbers</note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">deleted: Word count: 2, 438
</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">1</p><p n="date">2006-02</p><p n="module title">World Politics</p><p n="module code">PO131</p><p n="genre family">Essay</p><p n="discipline">Politics</p><p n="disciplinary group">SS</p><p n="grade">M</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">2404</p><p n="number of s-units">78</p><p n="number of p">12</p><p n="number of tables">0</p><p n="number of figures">0</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">0</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">0</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">30.8</p><p n="average s-units per p">6.5</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">f</p><p n="year of birth">1987</p><p n="first language">French</p><p n="education">OSA</p><p n="course">EPAIS</p><p n="student ID">0138</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><titlePart>The Rise of Transnational Actors: Towards the Creation of a "New World Order"?</titlePart><titlePart><name type="student name"/>, <name type="student ID"/><name type="student name"/>@<name type="university"/>.ac.uk</titlePart><docTitle><titlePart>World Politics (PO 131)<hi rend="italic"> Essay 2, Question 6: "How can transnational actors affect world politics?"</hi></titlePart></docTitle><titlePart>Tutor: <name type="tutor name"/> Module Director: <name type="tutor name"/> Date: 06 / 02 / 2006</titlePart></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="section"><p n="p1.12"><s n="s1.6;p1.12">For Francis Fukuyama, John Ruggie, and other reputed international relations experts, the end of the Cold War heralded the emergence of a "new world order"<ref target="BAWE_0138e-ftnote.001"/>. </s><s n="s2.6;p1.12">The shift away from a bipolar distribution of power that these analysts have in mind, however, is only one aspect of this transformation; perhaps more importantly, the stage of world politics has recently been invaded by a host of transnational actors. </s><s n="s3.6;p1.12">As transnational cooperations, non-governmental organisations and superstate institutions gain influence in global debate, they may "call into question the primacy of states" by challenging their sovereignty<ref target="BAWE_0138e-ftnote.002"/>. </s><s n="s4.6;p1.12">Some even warn that international organisations can be used by powerful states as tools to secure their hegemony<ref target="BAWE_0138e-ftnote.003"/>. </s><s n="s5.6;p1.12">These somewhat pessimistic forecasts may be exaggerated, however; if transnational actors can be made accountable to civil society, they will more likely reform rather than annihilate the Westphalian system. </s><s n="s6.6;p1.12">Through the emergence of "global governance"<ref target="BAWE_0138e-ftnote.004"/>, transnational actors can become a positive force for change in today's world order. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0138e-ftnote.001"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ruggie p554 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0138e-ftnote.002"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Kaldor p583 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0138e-ftnote.003"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Cronin p103 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0138e-ftnote.004"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Barnett </s></p></note><p n="p2.12"><s n="s1.10;p2.12">In popular belief, some of the most powerful and potentially threatening actors of the current international stage may be transnational coorperations (TNCs), firms which hold branches, subsidiaries and production facilities outside their own country. </s><s n="s2.10;p2.12">These have proliferated in recent years, emerging even in developing countries<ref target="BAWE_0138e-ftnote.005"/>. </s><s n="s3.10;p2.12">According to Peter Willetts, their growth and the scale of their activities leaves "the sovereignty of most governments . . . significantly reduced"<ref target="BAWE_0138e-ftnote.006"/>. </s><s n="s4.10;p2.12">As TNCs have highly mobile production facilities, they can easily move out of a host country if its policy is no longer attractive to them. </s><s n="s5.10;p2.12">Due to such 'regulatory arbitrage', host governments must compete for a firm's presence by lowering taxes, relaxing regulation, or improving particular infrastructures ; major aspects of state policy thus become dictated by the needs of the TNC. In Indonesia, for instance, the government has voluntarily relaxed environmental laws in order to accommodate the American mining company Freeport-McMoRan Copper &amp; Gold. </s><s n="s6.10;p2.12">This firm's "importance to Indonesia's treasury . . . ha[s] helped secure it against challenges from local people [and] environmental groups" <ref target="BAWE_0138e-ftnote.007"/> in spite of the considerable environmental damage that it causes in the Papuan region. </s><s n="s7.10;p2.12">Morevoer, TNC's can cause states to lose control not only of policy, but also of currency and foreign trade, as the bulk of financial flows generated by these companies leads to considerable fluctuations in a currency's exchange rate and in a country's current account. </s><s n="s8.10;p2.12">Furthermore, companies can occasionally evade state supervision altogether, for example by transfer pricing, where TNC's transfer their funds from one country to another to avoid taxation. </s><s n="s9.10;p2.12">In cases where firms follow directives from extraterritorial headquarters, domestic branches may be subject to the policy of a foreign government and may disregard domestic regulation<ref target="BAWE_0138e-ftnote.008"/>. </s><s n="s10.10;p2.12">TNCs can indeed pose very real threats to state sovereignty. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0138e-ftnote.005"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Willetts p363 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0138e-ftnote.006"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Willetts p363 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0138e-ftnote.007"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Perlez and Raymond </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0138e-ftnote.008"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Willetts pp363 - 365 </s></p></note><p n="p3.12"><s n="s1.8;p3.12">Beyond the impact of TNCs, the growth of transnational actors also worries states by fostering the development of a "global civil society"<ref target="BAWE_0138e-ftnote.009"/>. </s><s n="s2.8;p3.12">Modern voluntary associations seek to shape social rules by gaining independence from the state, engaging in transnational public debate, and becoming globally connected<ref target="BAWE_0138e-ftnote.010"/>. </s><s n="s3.8;p3.12">In particular, the number of Non-Governmental Organisations (NGOs) is "skyrocketing worldwide"<ref target="BAWE_0138e-ftnote.011"/> thanks to improved communications technology and higher levels of education. </s><s n="s4.8;p3.12">NGOs are generally seen as potentially destabilising activist movements that have been 'tamed' and institutionalised<ref target="BAWE_0138e-ftnote.012"/>, yet it is this "formalised part of this civil society"<ref target="BAWE_0138e-ftnote.013"/> that governments most fear. </s><s n="s5.8;p3.12">As legally recognised entities or 'insiders' to the political process, NGOs have acquired considerable influence and autonomy in decision-making processes. </s><s n="s6.8;p3.12">Transparency International, for instance, builds public pressure against corruption, lobbies individual governments to advocate policy reform, and monitors the compliance of states to multilateral conventions<ref target="BAWE_0138e-ftnote.014"/>. </s><s n="s7.8;p3.12">Submitting NGOs to a state's domestic regulations may consequently be difficult, leading governments to extreme measures: the United States government, for instance, recently launched an NGO-monitoring project threatening certain organisations with loss of funding if they did not adhere to its policies<ref target="BAWE_0138e-ftnote.015"/>. </s><s n="s8.8;p3.12">Such antagonism suggests that today's transnational civil society can limit the sovereignty of even the most dominant states. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0138e-ftnote.009"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Kaldor p583 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0138e-ftnote.010"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Kaldor p585 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0138e-ftnote.011"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Florini p72 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0138e-ftnote.012"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Kaldor p585 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0138e-ftnote.013"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Florini p72 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0138e-ftnote.014"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Transparency International </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0138e-ftnote.015"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Florini p73 </s></p></note><p n="p4.12"><s n="s1.5;p4.12">A similar power struggle pits states against a third form of transnational actor: International Organisations (IOs). </s><s n="s2.5;p4.12">The majority of international organisations - such as the United Nations or the International Monetary Fund - have states as their constituent membership and operate within formal procedures. </s><s n="s3.5;p4.12">Nonetheless, these bodies can act with a degree of autonomy from states. </s><s n="s4.5;p4.12">According to Abbott and Snidal, this independence gives IOs considerable power to "modify the political, normative, and intellectual context of state interactions"<ref target="BAWE_0138e-ftnote.016"/>: thus, the UN Commission on Latin America was the source of many of the economic development concepts that influenced the formation of the Group of 77.<ref target="BAWE_0138e-ftnote.017"/> Additionally, by centralising different states' interests, IOs can alter states' perceptions of their conflicts and hence influence the terms and outcomes of their interactions. </s><s n="s5.5;p4.12">By shaping the norms, values and preferences of member states, International Organisations acquire significant power over the decision-making processes in the international system. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0138e-ftnote.016"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Abbot and Snidal p17 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0138e-ftnote.017"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Abbot and Snidal p17 </s></p></note><p n="p5.12"><s n="s1.5;p5.12">Indeed, the influence that IOs exert on state policy can directly "challenge the state's monopoly on decision-making authority at the global level"<ref target="BAWE_0138e-ftnote.018"/>. </s><s n="s2.5;p5.12">IOs regularly serve as "managers of enforcement" in ensuring that governments comply with international commitments; by threatening to withhold their benefits or to apply sanctions if states renege from these obligations, IOs truly diminish the extent to which states are sovereign to choose their own courses of action. </s><s n="s3.5;p5.12">Moreover, certain political figures propose to strengthen the role of IOs in areas linked still more closely to state sovereignty, such as security. </s><s n="s4.5;p5.12">The previous UN Secretary-General Boutros Boutros-Ghali, for example, advocated the creation of a UN standing army, arguing that issues of domestic security were a "legitimate concern of the United Nations because [they] ha[d] the potential to undermine regional security." </s><ref target="BAWE_0138e-ftnote.019"/><s n="s5.5;p5.12">Likewise, the 1993 Australian foreign minister Gareth Evans called for a greater use of sanctions by the UN, which would enable this organisation to establish international regimes for peace enforcement.<ref target="BAWE_0138e-ftnote.020"/> Such changes would allow transnational actors to infringe traditional aspects of state sovereignty to an even greater degree. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0138e-ftnote.018"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Abbott and Snidal p18 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0138e-ftnote.019"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Boutros-Boutros Ghali (1995), <hi rend="italic">Agenda for Peace</hi>, in Barnett </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0138e-ftnote.020"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Gareth Evans (1993), <hi rend="italic">Cooperating for Peace</hi>, in Barnett </s></p></note><p n="p6.12"><s n="s1.5;p6.12">Not all political theorists see transnational actors strictly as threats to state power, however. </s><s n="s2.5;p6.12">Alternative interpretations suggest that NGOs, IOs and even TNCs could be tools by which dominant states of the international system would reflect and promote their personal interests. </s><s n="s3.5;p6.12">Some thus suspect certain TNCs of promoting the hegemonic ideology of dominant countries - in this fashion, both Coca-Cola and MacDonald's can be perceived as part of an apparatus by which the United States disperses capitalism to the developing world. </s><s n="s4.5;p6.12">Similarly, NGOs could also be used by states to voice their own concerns through a smokescreen of democratic consultation; as critics have expressed it, "these unelected guardians of the public good . . . claim to speak for the world but in fact speak only for themselves." </s><ref target="BAWE_0138e-ftnote.021"/><s n="s5.5;p6.12">Indeed, the neoliberal view of civil society sees NGOs as key agents in disseminating capitalist ideology, in particular by facilitating market reform and promoting parliamentary democracy.<ref target="BAWE_0138e-ftnote.022"/> Rather than reversing the logic of the Westphalian system, transnational actors may instead fortify existing power balances and reinforce, rather than deplete, a hegemon's sovereignty. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0138e-ftnote.021"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Florini p75 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0138e-ftnote.022"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Kaldor p586 </s></p></note><p n="p7.12"><s n="s1.7;p7.12">For many, however, such claims rest on isolated examples of partisanship, and NGOs and TNCs alike are generally accountable organisms.<ref target="BAWE_0138e-ftnote.023"/> The case for the use of International Organisations as tools of hegemonic influence, on the other hand, is a truly convincing one. </s><s n="s2.7;p7.12">Numerous theories of international relations suggest that IOs can provide "continuing utility . . . as instruments . . . for regime and rule creation." </s><ref target="BAWE_0138e-ftnote.024"/><s n="s3.7;p7.12">For realists, powerful states form IOs to allow weaker states to participate in the furthering of their own interests - thus, by creating the Council for Mutual Economic Assistance at the zenith of its Cold War supremacy, the Soviet Union could share the burden of its economy with satellite states<ref target="BAWE_0138e-ftnote.025"/>. </s><s n="s4.7;p7.12">Constructivist theory argues that IOs may help states to legitimise their prevailing ideas by setting codes of conduct that encourage certain activities.<ref target="BAWE_0138e-ftnote.026"/> For example, Michael Barnett sees the United Nations as a norm-setter dedicated to "expand[ing] the number of actors who are committed to a liberal political order"<ref target="BAWE_0138e-ftnote.027"/>: the UN's peace-keeping operations may be a pretext to spread the US neoliberal ideology by introducing principles of democracy and human rights in turbulent states. </s><s n="s5.7;p7.12">As shown by the use of the veto in the United Nations Security Council, voting procedures in IOs can establish a certain balance of power that endows dominant states with disproportionate influence on decision-making. </s><s n="s6.7;p7.12">Additionally, the UN, the WTO and the IMF alike serve as forums that allows weaker states to voice their grievances, thus legitimising the status quo and limiting any challenges existing neoliberal international system. </s><s n="s7.7;p7.12">IOs can therefore promote a hegemon's interests by creating structures that stabilise world politics and encourage member states to adhere to the hegemon's rules. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0138e-ftnote.023"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Scholte p231 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0138e-ftnote.024"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Karns and Mingst 1990, in Abbott and Snidal p29 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0138e-ftnote.025"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Abbott and Snidal p30 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0138e-ftnote.026"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Abbott and Snidal p30 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0138e-ftnote.027"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Barnett </s></p></note><p n="p8.12"><s n="s1.8;p8.12">The predominant threat that transnational actors pose to states today thus resides in the proliferation of IOs. </s><s n="s2.8;p8.12">These bodies can fragilise the sovereignty of member states, or they may even pursue policies that favour one state at the expense of other members. </s><s n="s3.8;p8.12">At present, IOs suffer from a scarcity of democratic accountability mechanisms: their leadership is not appointed through direct elections, they lack elected legislative bodies to balance the power of their executive components, they cannot be tried in court, and they are not subject to the control of external formal policy evaluation devices<ref target="BAWE_0138e-ftnote.028"/>. </s><s n="s4.8;p8.12">Yet, according to Scholte, the accountability of these 'global governance arrangements' could be restored if civil society was to take an active role in regulating international organisations.<ref target="BAWE_0138e-ftnote.029"/> In particular, NGOs can increase the transparency of IO operations, as was the case in 1998 when voluntary organisations in Canada and France forced the OECD to publicly release the text of the secret Multilateral Agreement on Investment which it was debating<ref target="BAWE_0138e-ftnote.030"/>. </s><s n="s5.8;p8.12">NGOs can also monitor global policies and seek redress in court for errors that are committed in these policies' implementation. </s><s n="s6.8;p8.12">Civil society can also promote the creation of formal accountability mechanisms to control IOs, as was done with the 1994 formation of an Inspection Panel for the World Bank.<ref target="BAWE_0138e-ftnote.031"/> More recently, NGOs have also attempted to implement 'corporate social responsibility' (CSR) devices to ensure the accountability of TNCs. </s><s n="s7.8;p8.12">For example, Christian Aid is currently lobbying for the establishment of international, legally binding regulation of TNCs that would impose minimum human rights and environmental standards on these firms<ref target="BAWE_0138e-ftnote.032"/>. </s><s n="s8.8;p8.12">With the necessary resources and networking, and with the support of progressive political attitudes and culture, "civil society associations [can] offer significant possibilities to increase global regulatory arrangement"<ref target="BAWE_0138e-ftnote.033"/> - the threats posed to state sovereignty by transnational actors, and especially by IOs, may be reduced. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0138e-ftnote.028"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Scholte p212 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0138e-ftnote.029"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Scholte p212 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0138e-ftnote.030"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Scholte p220 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0138e-ftnote.031"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Scholte p224 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0138e-ftnote.032"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Christian Aid </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0138e-ftnote.033"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Scholte p231 </s></p></note><p n="p9.12"><s n="s1.5;p9.12">If International Organisations can be monitored and controlled by other transnational actors, then, rather than endangering global stability, they may become "an important supplement to the decentralised cooperation of the international system." </s><ref target="BAWE_0138e-ftnote.034"/><s n="s2.5;p9.12">Decentralised cooperation theory holds that IOs centralise the interests of different states through stable organisational structures which significantly enhance interstate cooperation. </s><s n="s3.5;p9.12">IOs provide institutions that increase the efficiency of collective activities by pooling the assets and activities of members. </s><s n="s4.5;p9.12">This enables burden sharing between nations and reduces the risks of individual states, solving coordination problems and facilitating the otherwise contentious production of collective goods<ref target="BAWE_0138e-ftnote.035"/>. </s><s n="s5.5;p9.12">Moreover, Keohane (1984) stresses that IOs can play a crucial role in intergovernmental bargaining: international regimes reduce the transaction costs of negotiations, improve the flow of information between states, and make any violations of multilateral agreements more costly.<ref target="BAWE_0138e-ftnote.036"/> In this way, far from being the most threatening of transnational actors for the established international system, IOs may instead foster its proper functioning and steadiness. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0138e-ftnote.034"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Abbott and Snidal p31 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0138e-ftnote.035"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Abbott and Snidal p17 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0138e-ftnote.036"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Abbott and Snidal p20 </s></p></note><p n="p10.12"><s n="s1.9;p10.12">Yet, for many, the growing involvement of transnational actors in world politics is of little value if its only effect is to uphold the existing status quo. </s><s n="s2.9;p10.12">Rather, international relations theorists such as Snidal argue that International Organisations "often represent deliberate decisions by states to change their mutually consisted environments, and thus, themselves"<ref target="BAWE_0138e-ftnote.037"/>: IOs can and should become forces for positive change in the international system. </s><s n="s3.9;p10.12">One way in which IOs can foster such reform is through their role as sources of information. </s><s n="s4.9;p10.12">According to Alexandru Grigorescu, state interaction with IOs can lead to increased governmental transparency<ref target="BAWE_0138e-ftnote.038"/>. </s><s n="s5.9;p10.12">Through their various activities, International Organizations collect large amounts of information from member states; as they release previously concealed and potentially disparaging information about a government to societal actors, the regime concerned may face a 'trust crisis' from its citizens. </s><s n="s6.9;p10.12">In order to prove its credibility to a society, it will tend to adopt laws that increase transparency and free flow of information. </s><s n="s7.9;p10.12">Based on empirical evidence, Grigorescu finds that IO-led growth in external information does precede the advent of democratic transparency in many countries<ref target="BAWE_0138e-ftnote.039"/>. </s><s n="s8.9;p10.12">In turn, this transparency enhances interstate cooperation and makes collective action more effective. </s><s n="s9.9;p10.12">A strong civil society can therefore have a beneficial impact on the workings of domestic and international politics. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0138e-ftnote.037"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Abbott and Snidal p25 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0138e-ftnote.038"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Grigorescu p643 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0138e-ftnote.039"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Grigorescu p665 </s></p></note><p n="p11.12"><s n="s1.5;p11.12">The constructive role that IOs can play in improving interstate cooperation is best exemplified by the tasks currently ascribed to the United Nations. </s><s n="s2.5;p11.12">Reports composed by UN enthusiasts circa 1995 maintain that the globalizing world order needs international organizations that can mitigate the negative side-effects of modernization and resolve interstate conflicts resulting from interdependence and collective burden-sharing. </s><s n="s3.5;p11.12">IOs are believed to build confidence and transparency between members, in particular through creating monitoring mechanisms that guarantee that states will respect their commitments to international agreements. </s><s n="s4.5;p11.12">Finally, rather than endangering the stability of states, such organizations may provide states with what United Nations Secretary-General Perez de Cueller expressed as a "final confirmation of independence, nationhood, and sovereignty"<ref target="BAWE_0138e-ftnote.040"/>. </s><s n="s5.5;p11.12">International Organisations can therefore create a more peaceful international order capable of reforming the obsolete realism of the Westphalian system without endangering the states that comprise it. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0138e-ftnote.040"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Barnett </s></p></note><p n="p12.12"><s n="s1.5;p12.12">In the last few decades, states have witnessed the appearance of a great number of transnational actors in the international relations arena. </s><s n="s2.5;p12.12">The growing influence of Transnational Corporations, Non-Governmental Organisations and especially International Organisations in world politics may have ground-shaking consequences for the structure of the international system. </s><s n="s3.5;p12.12">While these new actors may not altogether dethrone the statist world order, they are introducing a "system of global governance . . . in which states will continue to be sovereign, but sovereignty will be much more conditional than before." </s><ref target="BAWE_0138e-ftnote.041"/><s n="s4.5;p12.12">In particular, a growing global civil society can hold states domestically accountable to their citizens, and international bodies such as the United Nations can facilitate state cooperation and ensure that governments fulfil their commitments to the world community. </s><s n="s5.5;p12.12">The end of the Cold War has indeed marked the emergence of a "new world order" - one in which the rise of transnational actors is of ever-increasing importance. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0138e-ftnote.041"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Kaldor p584 </s></p></note></div1></body><back><div1 type="bibliography"><head>Bibliography</head><p>Abbott, Kenneth W. and Snidal, Duncan, "Why States Act through Formal International Organisations." <hi rend="italic">The Journal of Conflict Resolution,</hi> Vol. 42, No.1 (1998), pp. 3-32.</p><p>Barnett, Michael, "Bringing in the New World Order: Liberalism, Legitimacy, and the United Nations." <hi rend="italic">World Politics,</hi> Vol 49 No 4 (1997): 526-551.</p><p>Boutros-Boutros Ghali (1995), <hi rend="italic">Agenda for Peace</hi>, in Barnett, Michael, "Bringing in the New World Order: Liberalism, Legitimacy, and the United Nations." <hi rend="italic">World Politics,</hi> Vol 49 No 4 (1997): 526-551.</p><p>Bonner, Raymond, and Perlez, Jane, "Below a Mountain of Wealth, a River of Waste".</p><p><hi rend="italic">New York Times</hi>. Internet. December 27, 2005. Accessed at: <seg type="URL" n="http://www.globalpolicy.org/socecon/tncs/2005/1227gold.htm"/></p><p>Christian Aid, "The need for legally binding regulation of Transnational Corporations". Christian Aid. Internet. February 2002. Accessed at: <seg type="URL" n="http://www.christianaid.org.uk/indepth/0202tnc/transc.htm"/></p><p>Cronin, Bruce, "The Paradox of Hegemony: America's Ambiguous Relationship with the United Nations." <hi rend="italic">European Journal of International Relations</hi>, Vol 7 No 1 (2001) pp: 103-129.</p><p>Evans, Gareth (1993), <hi rend="italic">Cooperating for Peace</hi>, in Barnett, Michael, "Bringing in the New World Order: Liberalism, Legitimacy, and the United Nations." <hi rend="italic">World Politics,</hi> Vol 49 No 4 (1997): 526-551.</p><p>Florini, Ann, "Is Global Civil Society a Good Thing?" <hi rend="italic">New Perspectives Quarterly,</hi> Vol 21, No 2 (2004) pp: 72-76</p><p>Grigorescu, Alexandru, "International Organizations and Government Transparency: Linking the International and Domestic Realms." <hi rend="italic">International Studies Quarterly</hi>, Vol 47, No 4, (2003) pp: 643-667.</p><p>Kaldor, Mary, "The idea of global civil society." <hi rend="italic">International Affairs,</hi> Vol 79, No 3, (2003) pp: 583-593.</p><p>Ruggie, John Gerard, "Third Try at World Order? America and Multilateralism after the Cold War", <hi rend="italic">Political Science Quarterly</hi>, Vol. 109, No4 (Autumn, 1994), pp553-570.</p><p>Scholte, Jan Aart, "Civil Society and Democratically Accountable Global Governance." <hi rend="italic">Government and Opposition,</hi> Vol 39, No 2, (2004) pp: 211-233</p><p>Transparency International website, accessed at <seg type="URL" n="www.transparency.org"/> </p><p>Willetts, Peter, "Transnational Actors and International Organisations in Global Politics." Chapter 17 in John Baylis and Steve Smith, <hi rend="underlined">The Globalization of World Politics: An Introduction to International Relations</hi>. Oxford: Oxford University Press, 2005 (2<hi rend="sup">nd</hi> edition).</p></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
