<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_0139a" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>The Essence of Political Power</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">The document has a title page which contains:
document title
title part</note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">header: student name and number</note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">deleted: Word count: 1, 639
</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">1</p><p n="date">2006-01</p><p n="module title">Introduction to Politics</p><p n="module code">PO107</p><p n="genre family">Essay</p><p n="discipline">Politics</p><p n="disciplinary group">SS</p><p n="grade">D</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">1618</p><p n="number of s-units">54</p><p n="number of p">8</p><p n="number of tables">0</p><p n="number of figures">0</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">0</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">0</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">30.0</p><p n="average s-units per p">6.8</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">f</p><p n="year of birth">1987</p><p n="first language">French</p><p n="education">OSA</p><p n="course">EPAIS</p><p n="student ID">0139</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><titlePart>The Essence of Political Power<name type="student name"/>, <name type="student ID"/><hi rend="underlined"><name type="student name"/>@<name type="university"/>.ac.uk</hi></titlePart><docTitle><titlePart>Introduction to Politics (PO 107) Essay 2, Question 3: '<hi rend="italic">A gets B to do something that he or she would not otherwise do'. Does this sum up the essence of political power?</hi> </titlePart></docTitle><titlePart>Tutor: <name type="tutor name"/> Module Director: <name type="tutor name"/> Date: 17 / 01 / 2006</titlePart></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="section"><p n="p1.8"><s n="s1.5;p1.8">In his 1968 pluralist thesis, Robert Dahl describes politics as the analysis of the nature, exercise and distribution of power<ref target="BAWE_0139a-ftnote.001"/>; accordingly, a precise understanding of power is vital to all political study. </s><s n="s2.5;p1.8">Scholars and philosophers have struggled with the concept of power since Antiquity; debate has focused over whether power can be exercised responsibly, on how it should be distributed, and on whether power can be possessed as an attribute, or rather manifested purely as an activity, in the production of intended results. </s><s n="s3.5;p1.8">Theorists further question <hi rend="italic">why</hi> people exercise power - while Nietzsche claims that humans possess a fundamental "will to power", for Hobbes power struggles are merely fuelled by the scarcity of resources<ref target="BAWE_0139a-ftnote.002"/>. </s><s n="s4.5;p1.8">The complexity of these views suggests that claims that 'politics is power' and that political power exists only within governments are oversimplified. </s><s n="s5.5;p1.8">So as to truly gain insight into today's political world, we must carefully reconsider the nature, uses and effects of power. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0139a-ftnote.001"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.5;pn1.1">Dahl, Robert. </s><s rend="underlined" n="s2.5;pn1.1">Who Governs? </s><s n="s3.5;pn1.1"><hi rend="underlined">Democracy and Power in an American City</hi>. </s><s n="s4.5;pn1.1">Pg. </s><s n="s5.5;pn1.1">12. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0139a-ftnote.002"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.4;pn1.1">Goodwin, Barbara. </s><s n="s2.4;pn1.1"><hi rend="underlined">Using Political Ideas</hi>. </s><s n="s3.4;pn1.1">Pg. </s><s n="s4.4;pn1.1">305. </s></p></note><p n="p2.8"><s n="s1.7;p2.8">Firstly, what is power? </s><s n="s2.7;p2.8">For Dahl and other pluralists, "A has power over B to the extent that he can get B to do something B would not otherwise have done", particularly when B is aware that the modified behaviour is contrary to his interests<ref target="BAWE_0139a-ftnote.003"/>. </s><s n="s3.7;p2.8">Such power abounds in international politics, where developing states are often forced to counter their national interests and to comply with transnational companies' potentially harmful requests due to these agencies' superior financial and political status. </s><s n="s4.7;p2.8">The Cola-Cola company, for instance, wields unquestionable power over the Indian government, which has granted it subsidized water and land despite the grave environmental damage caused by Coca-Cola's production processes<ref target="BAWE_0139a-ftnote.004"/>. </s><s n="s5.7;p2.8">Power is here understood in terms of its <hi rend="italic">effects</hi>, and is seen as an attribute of individuals or groups; it is a behavioural phenomenon, associated with domination more than merely with the capacity to influence outcomes. </s><s n="s6.7;p2.8">Power relationships are accordingly 'zero-sum games', which must deprive B of something if A is to benefit<ref target="BAWE_0139a-ftnote.005"/>. </s><s n="s7.7;p2.8">Dahl thus provides a very precise and quantifiable definition of political power. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0139a-ftnote.003"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.4;pn1.1">Hay, C. </s><s n="s2.4;pn1.1"><hi rend="underlined">Political Analysis</hi>. </s><s n="s3.4;pn1.1">Pg. </s><s n="s4.4;pn1.1">171 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0139a-ftnote.004"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.4;pn1.1">Srivastava, Amit. </s><s n="s2.4;pn1.1">"Communities Reject Coca-Cola in India". </s><s n="s3.4;pn1.1">India Resource Center. </s><s n="s4.4;pn1.1">Accessed at: <seg type="URL" n="http://www.corpwatch.org/article.php?id=7508"/> </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0139a-ftnote.005"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.4;pn1.1">Goodwin, Barbara. </s><s n="s2.4;pn1.1"><hi rend="underlined">Using Political Ideas</hi>. </s><s n="s3.4;pn1.1">Pg. </s><s n="s4.4;pn1.1">308. </s></p></note><p n="p3.8"><s n="s1.9;p3.8">This explanation may be over-simplistic, however: it unrealistically assumes that actors possess perfect knowledge, knowing exactly where their interests lie in the power game. </s><s n="s2.9;p3.8">Furthermore, in measuring A's power over B in terms of the decisions that A makes at B's expense, Dahl's theory does not weigh these decisions' importance. </s><s n="s3.9;p3.8">Peter Bachrach and Morton Baratz additionally criticize the pluralist approach for insufficiently differentiating power over <hi rend="italic">people</hi> and power over <hi rend="italic">matter</hi>. </s><s n="s4.9;p3.8">They also argue that the possession of instruments of power (such as Coca-Cola's significant funds in the above example) is merely <hi rend="italic">latent</hi> power, which can only really be defined as power <hi rend="italic">if A's threat is found credible by B</hi> (or if the Indian government is convinced that Coca-Cola will withdraw its investment if environmental regulations are reinforced)<ref target="BAWE_0139a-ftnote.006"/>. </s><s n="s5.9;p3.8">Most importantly, these scholars move beyond Dahl's definition of power as decision-making, claiming instead that individuals exert power primarily by <hi rend="italic">setting the agenda</hi> for political decisions. </s><s n="s6.9;p3.8">In this view, A has power over B if it can "limit the scope of the political process to public consideration of only those issues which are comparatively innocuous to A"<ref target="BAWE_0139a-ftnote.007"/>. </s><s n="s7.9;p3.8">This theory, dubbed the 'second face' of political power, finds support in the Camp David Peace Accords, for instance, where the United States obtained Israeli-Palestinian consent to demilitarization of the Sinai Peninsula by formulating 'yesable propositions', in which the discussion of highly disputed issues was deliberately minimized<ref target="BAWE_0139a-ftnote.008"/>. </s><s n="s8.9;p3.8">Bachrach and Baratz theory also point to <hi rend="italic">non-decision making</hi> as an indication of power: they suggest that B may bend to A's power by choosing <hi rend="italic">not</hi> to act against a violation of its own interests<ref target="BAWE_0139a-ftnote.009"/> - as the Security Council's permanent members did by avoiding vetoing the United States' 2002 resolution on Iraq. </s><s n="s9.9;p3.8">Agenda-setting and non-decisions, both overlooked by Dahl's 'first face of power', are therefore clearly important indications of political power. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0139a-ftnote.006"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.4;pn1.1">Bachrach, Peter and Baratz, Morton. </s><s n="s2.4;pn1.1"><hi rend="underlined">Power and Poverty: Theory and Practice</hi>. </s><s n="s3.4;pn1.1">Pg. </s><s n="s4.4;pn1.1">4. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0139a-ftnote.007"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.4;pn1.1">Goodwin, Barbara. </s><s n="s2.4;pn1.1"><hi rend="underlined">Using Political Ideas</hi>. </s><s n="s3.4;pn1.1">Pg. </s><s n="s4.4;pn1.1">309. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0139a-ftnote.008"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.4;pn1.1">Fisher, Roger. </s><s n="s2.4;pn1.1"><hi rend="underlined">International Conflict for Beginners</hi>. </s><s n="s3.4;pn1.1">Pg. </s><s n="s4.4;pn1.1">16. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0139a-ftnote.009"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.4;pn1.1">Bachrach, Peter and Baratz, Morton. </s><s n="s2.4;pn1.1"><hi rend="underlined">Power and Poverty: Theory and Practice</hi>. </s><s n="s3.4;pn1.1">Pg. </s><s n="s4.4;pn1.1">5. </s></p></note><p n="p4.8"><s n="s1.5;p4.8">In attempting to combine the pluralist definition of power with Bachrach's and Baratz's explanation, a 'third face of power' has emerged: neo-elitism. </s><s n="s2.5;p4.8">This view extends the scope of power to <hi rend="italic">preference-shaping</hi>, in which A exerts power over B <hi rend="italic"> unbeknownst to B</hi>, by manipulating B's idea of his own preferences. </s><s n="s3.5;p4.8">Steven Lukes warns that such power is widespread in everyday society, as social institutions "prevent people from having grievances by shaping their perceptions... in such a way that they accept their role in the existing order of things"<ref target="BAWE_0139a-ftnote.010"/>. </s><s n="s4.5;p4.8">Such manipulation was illustrated by the USSR's communist regime, which partially convinced citizens that their individual interests coincided exactly with those of the state<ref target="BAWE_0139a-ftnote.011"/>. </s><s n="s5.5;p4.8">This "institutionalized persuasion"<ref target="BAWE_0139a-ftnote.012"/> is key to the neo-elitist theory of power, diverging from the above two 'faces' in that it demonstrates power <hi rend="italic">over</hi> and not only power <hi rend="italic">to</hi>: rather than simply bringing about desired outcomes, this more virulent form of power allows player A to change player B's incentive structure to achieve its goals. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0139a-ftnote.010"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.4;pn1.1">Goodwin, Barbara. </s><s n="s2.4;pn1.1"><hi rend="underlined">Using Political Ideas</hi>. </s><s n="s3.4;pn1.1">Pg. </s><s n="s4.4;pn1.1">311. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0139a-ftnote.011"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.3;pn1.1">Schattschneider, E.E. </s><s n="s2.3;pn1.1"><hi rend="underlined">The Semi-Sovereign People</hi>. </s><s n="s3.3;pn1.1">1960. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0139a-ftnote.012"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.4;pn1.1">Goodwin, Barbara. </s><s n="s2.4;pn1.1"><hi rend="underlined">Using Political Ideas</hi>. </s><s n="s3.4;pn1.1">Pg. </s><s n="s4.4;pn1.1">311 </s></p></note><p n="p5.8"><s n="s1.6;p5.8">To better assess the accuracy of these three definitions (power as decision making, agenda-setting, and ideational restructuring) they should be compared to common archetypes of political power. </s><s n="s2.6;p5.8">These include: authority (power attached to offices); coercion (power to make others act and to legally punish them if they refuse); force (the rule-free use of coercion by a politically identifiable group); and violence (a "coercive and destructive act by unauthorized people in orderly situations")<ref target="BAWE_0139a-ftnote.013"/>. </s><s n="s3.6;p5.8">Traditionally, power has been equated with these archetypes; as political theorists refine their definitions of the concept, however, this is no longer the case. </s><s n="s4.6;p5.8">Force, for instance, was previously seen by Robert Bierstedt as "manifest power"<ref target="BAWE_0139a-ftnote.014"/>; Bachrach and Baratz, though, distinguish force from power by remarking that A does not achieve B's <hi rend="italic">compliance</hi> when implementing force. </s><s n="s5.6;p5.8">Lack of compliance implies that A's use of force may expose it to deprivation as well as B. The application of force in the Gestapo's executions of civilian hostages in World War II, for instance, inadvertently fueled rather than inhibited European underground movements<ref target="BAWE_0139a-ftnote.015"/>. </s><s n="s6.6;p5.8">Contrarily to conventional belief, therefore, force is perhaps not synonymous of political power; rather, in the words of Bachrach and Baratz, "the application of sanctions [or of force] is an <hi rend="italic">admission of defeat</hi> by the would-be wielder of power"<ref target="BAWE_0139a-ftnote.016"/>. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0139a-ftnote.013"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.4;pn1.1">Goodwin, Barbara. </s><s n="s2.4;pn1.1"><hi rend="underlined">Using Political Ideas</hi>. </s><s n="s3.4;pn1.1">Pg. </s><s n="s4.4;pn1.1">306 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0139a-ftnote.014"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.4;pn1.1">Bachrach, Peter and Baratz, Morton. </s><s n="s2.4;pn1.1"><hi rend="underlined">Power and Poverty: Theory and Practice</hi>. </s><s n="s3.4;pn1.1">Pg. </s><s n="s4.4;pn1.1">17. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0139a-ftnote.015"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.4;pn1.1">Bachrach, Peter and Baratz, Morton. </s><s n="s2.4;pn1.1"><hi rend="underlined">Power and Poverty: Theory and Practice</hi>. </s><s n="s3.4;pn1.1">Pg. </s><s n="s4.4;pn1.1">20. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0139a-ftnote.016"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.4;pn1.1">Bachrach, Peter and Baratz, Morton. </s><s n="s2.4;pn1.1"><hi rend="underlined">Power and Poverty: Theory and Practice</hi>. </s><s n="s3.4;pn1.1">Pg. </s><s n="s4.4;pn1.1">20. </s></p></note><p n="p6.8"><s n="s1.11;p6.8">Similar ambiguities surround the relationship between power and authority. </s><s n="s2.11;p6.8">Whereas Hobbes claims that authority is not vital to state power (as people will obey coercion out fear of anarchy)<ref target="BAWE_0139a-ftnote.017"/>, for most theorists power is meaningless without authority. </s><s n="s3.11;p6.8">On the psychological level, the 1963 Milgram Experiments demonstrated that an individual's perception of another's authority (the authority of a recognized scientist, in this case) prompted him to obey that individual's orders even when these provoked intense moral dilemmas (such as the belief that one was subjecting others to excruciating pain)<ref target="BAWE_0139a-ftnote.018"/>. </s><s n="s4.11;p6.8">On a more political level, Plamenatz argues that, "no man has power unless his right to command is acknowledged by some of those who obey him"<ref target="BAWE_0139a-ftnote.019"/>. </s><s n="s5.11;p6.8">Likewise, for Locke, a government devoid of authority is pre-social and cannot achieve the cooperation of its people. </s><s n="s6.11;p6.8">The UK's 1688 Glorious Revolution thus preserved most elements of the system it was theoretically 'replacing' to ensure its citizens' loyalty and to preserve its authority<ref target="BAWE_0139a-ftnote.020"/>. </s><s n="s7.11;p6.8">Currently, states wielding somewhat unjustified power over minority regions - such as India over Kashmir or Russia over Chechnya - are losing their grip on these territories precisely due to their insufficient legitimacy<ref target="BAWE_0139a-ftnote.021"/>; as put by Ivo Daalder, "legitimacy is not a luxury for the powerful and a necessity of the weak - it is what is necessary to translate power into success"<ref target="BAWE_0139a-ftnote.022"/>. </s><s n="s8.11;p6.8">Bachrach and Baratz do not share such views, however. </s><s n="s9.11;p6.8">Whilst they accept that authority and power are mutually reinforcing, these theorists reject definitions of authority as "institutionalized power" and insist that the two are <hi rend="italic">not</hi> synonymous. </s><s n="s10.11;p6.8">In their view, authority involves B complying to A because A's command is <hi rend="italic">reasonable in terms of his values</hi>; as such a relationship no longer contains any <hi rend="italic">conflict</hi> in values, it cannot be labeled as power<ref target="BAWE_0139a-ftnote.023"/>. </s><s n="s11.11;p6.8">These scholars thus warn us that associations between authority, force and power must be discarded if one is to obtain an accurate understanding of political power. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0139a-ftnote.017"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.4;pn1.1">Goodwin, Barbara. </s><s n="s2.4;pn1.1"><hi rend="underlined">Using Political Ideas</hi>. </s><s n="s3.4;pn1.1">Pg. </s><s n="s4.4;pn1.1">311 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0139a-ftnote.018"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.5;pn1.1">Milgram, Stanley. </s><s n="s2.5;pn1.1">"Behavioral Study of Obedience." </s><s n="s3.5;pn1.1"><hi rend="italic">Journal of Abnormal and Social Psychology</hi>. </s><s n="s4.5;pn1.1">Pg. </s><s n="s5.5;pn1.1">371. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0139a-ftnote.019"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.4;pn1.1">Goodwin, Barbara. </s><s n="s2.4;pn1.1"><hi rend="underlined">Using Political Ideas</hi>. </s><s n="s3.4;pn1.1">Pg. </s><s n="s4.4;pn1.1">313 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0139a-ftnote.020"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.4;pn1.1">Goodwin, Barbara. </s><s n="s2.4;pn1.1"><hi rend="underlined">Using Political Ideas</hi>. </s><s n="s3.4;pn1.1">Pg. </s><s n="s4.4;pn1.1">313 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0139a-ftnote.021"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.3;pn1.1">Shah, Mowahid. </s><s n="s2.3;pn1.1">"The Power of Moral Legitimacy", August 27, 2004. </s><s n="s3.3;pn1.1">Accessed at: <seg type="URL" n="http://www.pakistanlink.com/mowahid/08272004.html"/> </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0139a-ftnote.022"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.3;pn1.1">Daalder, Ivo H."Why Legitimacy In Iraq Matters". </s><s n="s2.3;pn1.1">Center for American Progress. </s><s n="s3.3;pn1.1">Accessed at: <seg type="URL" n="http://www.americanprogress.org/site/pp.asp?c=biJRJ8OVF&amp;b=24723"/> </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0139a-ftnote.023"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.4;pn1.1">Bachrach, Peter and Baratz, Morton. </s><s n="s2.4;pn1.1">Power and Poverty: Theory and Practice. </s><s n="s3.4;pn1.1">Pg. </s><s n="s4.4;pn1.1">32 </s></p></note><p n="p7.8"><s n="s1.7;p7.8">Such an understanding would be incomplete without some comprehension of <hi rend="italic">where</hi> power lies in society. </s><s n="s2.7;p7.8">Is political power (especially power over state actions) only available to influential groups, or can it be possessed by individuals? </s><s n="s3.7;p7.8">The pluralist view of the state claims that individuals and interest groups possess the majority of political power<ref target="BAWE_0139a-ftnote.024"/>. </s><s n="s4.7;p7.8">In the 2005 Iraqi elections, for instance, the Sunni minority's needs were particularly heeded, as "the temporary government feared that [this group] would not participate in the elections" otherwise<ref target="BAWE_0139a-ftnote.025"/>. </s><s n="s5.7;p7.8">Extreme pluralists argue that even groups that are <hi rend="italic">devoid</hi> of resources possess power, as governments respect their interests out of fear that their very deprivation may otherwise spark rebellion<ref target="BAWE_0139a-ftnote.026"/>. </s><s n="s6.7;p7.8">Contradicting these views, elitists however hold that power lies not in individuals but in a society's elite, whether this comprises large businesses in corporatist states or kinship ties in nepotistic regimes<ref target="BAWE_0139a-ftnote.027"/>. </s><s n="s7.7;p7.8">Power, consequently, may exist both within civil society and in strictly governmental circles - depending on whether one adheres to pluralism or elitism, and on the type of regime concerned. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0139a-ftnote.024"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.4;pn1.1">Axford, Barrie, Browning, Gary, Huggins, Richard, &amp; Rosamond, Ben. </s><s n="s2.4;pn1.1"><hi rend="underlined">Politics: an introduction</hi>. </s><s n="s3.4;pn1.1">Pg. </s><s n="s4.4;pn1.1">35 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0139a-ftnote.025"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.3;pn1.1">Johnson, Bill, Peterson, Katherine, Vaswani, Nikhil, and Gentry, Zach. </s><s n="s2.3;pn1.1">"2005 Iraq Elections: Analysis of Minority Participation". </s><s n="s3.3;pn1.1">Accessed at: <seg type="URL" n="http://faculty.haas.berkeley.edu/rjmorgan/MBA217/Playaz_Iraq%20final.doc"/> </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0139a-ftnote.026"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.4;pn1.1">Bachrach, Peter and Baratz, Morton. </s><s n="s2.4;pn1.1">Power and Poverty: Theory and Practice. </s><s n="s3.4;pn1.1">Pg. </s><s n="s4.4;pn1.1">5 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0139a-ftnote.027"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.4;pn1.1">Axford, Barrie, Browning, Gary, Huggins, Richard, &amp; Rosamond, Ben. </s><s n="s2.4;pn1.1"><hi rend="underlined">Politics: an introduction</hi>. </s><s n="s3.4;pn1.1">Pg. </s><s n="s4.4;pn1.1">38 </s></p></note><p n="p8.8"><s n="s1.4;p8.8">Having explored the differing definitions and locations of power in society, we can conclude that political power involves more than "A get[ting] B to do something that he or she would not otherwise do". </s><s n="s2.4;p8.8">Power implicates domination, agenda-setting, and preference-shaping, and is accessible to individuals as well as to elites in a community, depending on the social strata in which that power exists. </s><s n="s3.4;p8.8">When faced by such variability, the most important question for political theorists to answer concerning power may actually be, where <hi rend="italic">should</hi> power lie? </s><s n="s4.4;p8.8">If we can access a truly accurate definition of power, our next task may be to seriously challenge its distribution in our own societies, no longer in theory, but in practice. </s></p></div1></body><back><div1 type="bibliography"><head>BIBLIOGRAPHY</head><p>Axford, Barrie, Browning, Gary, Huggins, Richard, &amp; Rosamond, Ben. <hi rend="underlined">Politics: an introduction</hi>. 2nd Ed. 2002. Routledge Publishers, London.</p><p>Bachrach, Peter and Baratz, Morton S. <hi rend="underlined">Power and Poverty: Theory and Practice</hi>. New York: Oxford University Press, 1970.</p><p>Daalder, Ivo H."Why Legitimacy In Iraq Matters". Center for American Progress. January 27, 2004, Internet. Accessed at: <seg type="URL" n="http://www.americanprogress.org/site/pp.asp?c=biJRJ8OVF&amp;b=24723"/></p><p>Dahl, Robert. <hi rend="underlined">Who Governs? Democracy and Power in an American City</hi>. New Haven: Yale University Press, 1961. </p><p>Fisher, Roger. <hi rend="underlined">International Conflict for Beginners</hi>. New York: Harper and Row, 1970.</p><p>Goodwin, Barbara. <hi rend="underlined">Using Political Ideas</hi>. John Wiley &amp; Sons, 4th edition, 2000.</p><p>Hay, Colin. Political Analysis: A Critical Introduction. London: Palgrave, 2002.</p><p>Johnson, Bill, Peterson, Katherine, Vaswani, Nikhil, and Gentry, Zach. "2005 Iraq Elections: Analysis of Minority Participation". March 8, 2005, Internet. Accessed at: <seg type="URL" n="http://faculty.haas.berkeley.edu/rjmorgan/MBA217/Playaz_Iraq%20final.doc"/></p><p>Milgram, Stanley. "Behavioral Study of Obedience." <hi rend="italic">Journal of Abnormal and Social Psychology</hi>, 1963. </p><p>Schattschneider, Elmer Eric. <hi rend="underlined">The Semisovereign People: A Realist's View of Democracy in America.</hi> Harcourt Brace College Publishers, 1960.</p><p>Shah, Mowahid. "The Power of Moral Legitimacy", August 27, 2004. Accessed at: <seg type="URL" n="http://www.pakistanlink.com/mowahid/08272004.html"/></p><p>Srivastava, Amit. "Communities Reject Coca-Cola in India". India Resource Center. July 10th, 2003, Internet. Accessed at: <seg type="URL" n="http://www.corpwatch.org/article.php?id=7508"/></p></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
