<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_0139i" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Douglass North's Theory of Institutions: Key to Understanding Underdevelopment Today?</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">The document has a title page which contains:
document title
title part</note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">deleted: header: student name and number; footer: page numbers</note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">deleted: Word count: 1, 564</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">1</p><p n="date">2005-11</p><p n="module title">World Economy: History &amp; Theory</p><p n="module code">EC104</p><p n="genre family">Essay</p><p n="discipline">Economics</p><p n="disciplinary group">SS</p><p n="grade">D</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">1560</p><p n="number of s-units">53</p><p n="number of p">7</p><p n="number of tables">0</p><p n="number of figures">0</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">0</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">0</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">29.4</p><p n="average s-units per p">7.6</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">f</p><p n="year of birth">1987</p><p n="first language">French</p><p n="education">OSA</p><p n="course">EPAIS</p><p n="student ID">0139</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><docTitle><titlePart>Douglass North's Theory of Institutions: Key to Understanding Underdevelopment Today?</titlePart></docTitle><titlePart><name type="student name"/>, <name type="student ID"/></titlePart><titlePart>World Economy (EC 104) Question 2</titlePart><titlePart>Tutor: <name type="other"/> Module Director: <name type="tutor name"/> Date: 21 / 11 / 2005</titlePart></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="section"><p n="p1.7"><s n="s1.9;p1.7">Today's world is fraught with economic inequality: the breach between the incomes of 'Northern' countries and those of poorer 'Southern' countries is relentlessly widening. </s><s n="s2.9;p1.7">What explains such a trend? </s><s n="s3.9;p1.7">Why do some countries accumulate so much wealth while others become so radically poorer? </s><s n="s4.9;p1.7">Traditional economic theory has attributed underdevelopment to differences in resource endowments between rich and poor nations, or to Western exploitation of less developed states. </s><s n="s5.9;p1.7">Such theories, however, do not satisfactorily explain why underdevelopment <hi rend="italic">persists</hi> in poor countries in spite of the guidance which more successful 'model' countries provide them with. </s><s n="s6.9;p1.7">Only recently has the persistence of underdevelopment been seriously considered; in particular, theorists such as Douglass North have looked to the role of institutions in shaping countries' economic performance. </s><s n="s7.9;p1.7">These scholars argue that institutions, when efficient, are vital to achieving modern economic growth; inefficient institutions based on incomplete information, however, irremediably harm economies' long-term development. </s><s n="s8.9;p1.7">Such claims can be investigated by looking into the role played by institutions in governmental structures, in long-distance trade, and in economic change throughout history. </s><s n="s9.9;p1.7">By comparing the institutions which led to the rise of the "European Miracle" in the post-Renaissance period to those present in third-world countries at that time, one can assess the extent to which North's institutional theories promote a modern understanding of the persistence of underdevelopment today. </s></p><p n="p2.7"><s n="s1.7;p2.7">How far can institutions be considered relevant to economic performance? </s><s n="s2.7;p2.7">For North, institutions are "the rules of the game in society"<ref target="BAWE_0139i-ftnote.001"/>, which structure incentives in human exchanges and reduce social uncertainty by defining and limiting individuals' choices. </s><s n="s3.7;p2.7">As Kuznets demonstrates by including institutional change (or changes in society's structure and ideology) in his six characteristics of modern economic growth, efficient institutions will therefore develop incentives conducive to growth<ref target="BAWE_0139i-ftnote.002"/>. </s><s n="s4.7;p2.7">Changes in Britain's institutional framework, for instance (in particular, the temporary establishment of a republic and of a House of Lords) enabled the government to credibly uphold property rights and patent laws, thus fostering the technological innovation and market-led growth that culminated in the 1688 Glorious Revolution<ref target="BAWE_0139i-ftnote.003"/>. </s><s n="s5.7;p2.7">This in turn stimulated the development of public finance and parliamentary systems unique to Europe at the time<ref target="BAWE_0139i-ftnote.004"/>. </s><s n="s6.7;p2.7">Likewise, the Netherlands' push for modern economic growth in the 17 <hi rend="sup">th</hi> Century was enhanced by its development of commercial institutions modeled on those of earlier Italian city states<ref target="BAWE_0139i-ftnote.005"/>. </s><s n="s7.7;p2.7">Institutions, when they provide society with the appropriate incentives, can thus be an important source of economic stimulation. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0139i-ftnote.001"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">North, D.C. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">(1991), <hi rend="italic">Institutions, Institutional Change and Economic Performance</hi>, Cambridge: Cambridge University Press. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0139i-ftnote.002"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Kuznets, S. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">(1974), Population, Capital and Economic Growth: Selected Essays, London: Heinemann. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0139i-ftnote.003"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">North, D.G. and Weingast, B.R. (1989), "Constitutions and Commitment: The Evolution of Institutions Governing Public Choice in Seventeenth-Century England" </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0139i-ftnote.004"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">North, D.C. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">(1991), <hi rend="italic">Institutions, Institutional Change and Economic Performance</hi> </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0139i-ftnote.005"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Maddison, A. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">(2001), The World Economy: A Millennial Perspective, Paris:OECD. </s></p></note><p n="p3.7"><s n="s1.5;p3.7">Institutions are considered vital to economic development not only because of the incentives that they provide, however, but because of the constraints they impose on members of society. </s><s n="s2.5;p3.7">As noted by North, if humans were to interact in a system devoid of rules, due to the "noncoincidence of wealth-maximising behaviour and of socially cooperative outcomes" the common good would be sacrificed to individual gain. </s><s n="s3.5;p3.7">Such a dilemma is reflected in society's inherent 'fundamental problem of exchange', by which trade, even when potentially profitable, is forgone because actors have no means of ensuring that their counterparts will pay for traded goods, rather than 'reneging' and illegally holding onto them. </s><s n="s4.5;p3.7">Greif claims that, "for individuals to enter mutually beneficial relationships they have to recognize them as such and have to be able to fulfill their contractual obligations". </s><s n="s5.5;p3.7">In this light, institutional constraints are key to enabling trade and profitable economic exchange, as they mitigate the FPOE by providing "rules" to the "game". <ref target="BAWE_0139i-ftnote.006"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0139i-ftnote.006"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">North, D.C. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">(1991), <hi rend="italic">Institutions, Institutional Change and Economic Performance</hi> </s></p></note><p n="p4.7"><s n="s1.10;p4.7">Different types of institutions - both governmental and private-order - have thus been formed throughout history to counter the FPOE. In Medieval Europe abuse of foreign merchants by local rulers was widespread - as noted by England's Edward I in 1923, as a result "many merchants [were] put off coming to the land with their merchandise"<ref target="BAWE_0139i-ftnote.007"/>. </s><s n="s2.10;p4.7">Institutions employing multilateral reputation mechanisms consequently evolved to constrain rulers' actions: a large subgroup of merchants would cease trade with a ruler if one of their members was abused. </s><s n="s3.10;p4.7">However, traders themselves did not always comply with the rules set by their organizations - in imposing an embargo on Norway in 1294, for instance, German towns had to post ships in the Danish straits so as to intercept any defecting German traders<ref target="BAWE_0139i-ftnote.008"/>. </s><s n="s4.10;p4.7">Such costly means of enforcement were gradually countered by the establishment of merchant guilds, more complex institutions that heavily ostracized defecting traders as well as conditioning future trade with rulers on past protection. </s><s n="s5.10;p4.7">Inter-city organizations such as the German Hansa, or the subdivision of city administrations in Italian city-states, thus succeeded in mitigating the FPOE at both the ruler and inter-merchant level through their use of institutional constraints<ref target="BAWE_0139i-ftnote.009"/>. </s><s n="s6.10;p4.7">As trade grew in scale, institutions had to further be formed at the global level, to govern relations between merchants and overseas agents. </s><s n="s7.10;p4.7">Such institutional frameworks are found in 11 <hi rend="sup">th</hi> Century trading on both sides of the Mediterranean: in the collectivistic agency relationships among Maghribi traders, and in the individualistic systems employed by Genoese merchants. </s><s n="s8.10;p4.7">These traders again reduced the problem of trust by imposing constraints on each-other through third-party enforcement (fear of collective punishment through the Maghribis' extended kinship networks ensured agents' honesty in trading, whilst the more individualistic Genoese system necessitated government enforcement and the creation of legal contracts to stabilise trade)<ref target="BAWE_0139i-ftnote.010"/>. </s><s n="s9.10;p4.7">In both long-distance and intra-European trade, therefore, institutions have been vital means of mitigating the FPOE, and of thus enabling capitalist gains through comparative advantage, division of labour, technological innovation, and specialization<ref target="BAWE_0139i-ftnote.011"/>. </s><s n="s10.10;p4.7">North's insistence on the importance of institutions to economic development therefore seems well-justified. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0139i-ftnote.007"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Greif, A. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">(2000), "The Fundamental Problem of Exchange a research agenda in historical institutional analysis", <hi rend="italic">European Review of Economic History</hi>. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0139i-ftnote.008"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Greif, A. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">"The Fundamental Problem of Exchange: a research agenda in historical institutional analysis" </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0139i-ftnote.009"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">North, D.C. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">(1991), <hi rend="italic">Institutions, Institutional Change and Economic Performance</hi> </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0139i-ftnote.010"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Greif, A. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">"The Fundamental Problem of Exchange: a research agenda in historical institutional analysis" </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0139i-ftnote.011"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">North, D.C. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">(1991), <hi rend="italic">Institutions, Institutional Change and Economic Performance</hi> </s></p></note><p n="p5.7"><s n="s1.9;p5.7">While such a focus explains the development of certain economies, however, what does it contribute to our understanding of <hi rend="italic">underdevelopment</hi>? </s><s n="s2.9;p5.7">According to Greif, "once an institution has evolved in a society to mitigate FPOE, it can cause that society to evolve along a particular trajectory and in the long run explain distinct economic performances"<ref target="BAWE_0139i-ftnote.012"/>. </s><s n="s3.9;p5.7">In this light, just as efficient institutions can trigger growth, inefficient ones can trap their users in detrimental economic habits; this is particularly dangerous because institutional change is a difficult and highly incremental process, due to the informal constraints - including deep-rooted cultural and ideological customs - underlying them<ref target="BAWE_0139i-ftnote.013"/>. </s><s n="s4.9;p5.7">Such 'lock-in' problems can be observed by comparing Chinese and European institutional frameworks in the post-Renaissance period, as these may have fostered much of the difference that now lies between the Eastern and Western worlds. </s><s n="s5.9;p5.7">The Chinese institutional framework promoted agricultural development and best-practice in the first millennium due to its highly efficient bureaucratic elite; in the second millennium, however, China's institutions failed to keep up with the global expansion of trade and technology and became detrimental to their economy: the bureaucracy's monopoly restricted the emergence of an independent class of commercial bourgeoisie, thus forbidding potentially profitable trade and entrepreneurship. </s><s n="s6.9;p5.7">This bureaucracy furthermore promoted an ethnocentric outlook, thus rendering China impermeable to Western scientific development and trade<ref target="BAWE_0139i-ftnote.014"/>. </s><s n="s7.9;p5.7">As put by Deng, such "deeply engrained attitudes" prevented China's dynamic growth in the 18 <hi rend="sup">th</hi> century, and may continue to do so today<ref target="BAWE_0139i-ftnote.015"/>. </s><s n="s8.9;p5.7">By contrast, the institutional and governmental structures behind the 'European miracle' countries were all particularly permissive at this time - Venice provided merchants with securitising legal frameworks, Portugal welcomed Jewish merchants and scholars driven out of Spain by the Inquisition, and the Dutch republic's tolerance drew many merchants from Antwerp to Amsterdam - thus highly promoting innovation. </s><s n="s9.9;p5.7">This comparison suggests that institutions can explain both economic backwardness and economic growth. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0139i-ftnote.012"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Greif, A. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">"The Fundamental Problem of Exchange: a research agenda in historical institutional analysis" </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0139i-ftnote.013"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">North, D.C. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">(1991), <hi rend="italic">Institutions, Institutional Change and Economic Performance</hi> </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0139i-ftnote.014"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Maddison, A. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">(1998), Chinese Economic Performance in the Long Run, Paris:OECD. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0139i-ftnote.015"><p n="pn1.2"><s n="s1.2;pn1.2">Deng, K.G. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.2">(2000), "A Critical Survey of Recent Research in Chinese Economic </s></p><p n="pn2.2"><s n="s1.1;pn2.2">History", <hi rend="italic">Economic History Review</hi>. </s></p></note><p n="p6.7"><s n="s1.9;p6.7">But do solutions to these institutional problems exist? </s><s n="s2.9;p6.7">Can faulty mechanisms be modified so as to increase chances of growth? </s><s n="s3.9;p6.7">For North, such change is possible within an institutional context that "makes new compromises between players possible"<ref target="BAWE_0139i-ftnote.016"/>. </s><s n="s4.9;p6.7">Oppressive institutions as were found in China must therefore evolve to grant their members greater intellectual and ideological freedom. </s><s n="s5.9;p6.7">Such freedom, according to Mancur Olson, is far more prevalent in democracies than in autocracies - consequently, democracies allow economies to "reap all possible gains from investment and long-term transactions"<ref target="BAWE_0139i-ftnote.017"/>. </s><s n="s6.9;p6.7">How feasible, then, is a transition from autocratic to democratic governance in underdeveloped countries? </s><s n="s7.9;p6.7">In the past century Africa has seen over 52 governments transit from neopatrimonial rule to 'democracy'; most of these countries' economies, however, have not significantly improved since the change<ref target="BAWE_0139i-ftnote.018"/>. </s><s n="s8.9;p6.7">Karen Remmer notes that, even in these apparently democratic states, "contemporary political changes are conditioned by mechanisms of rule [or institutions] embedded in the ancient regime"<ref target="BAWE_0139i-ftnote.019"/>. </s><s n="s9.9;p6.7">Even in the context of modified institutional frameworks, therefore, the 'lock-in' or 'path dependence' problem fundamental to North's theory continues to apply. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0139i-ftnote.016"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">North, D.C. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">(1991), <hi rend="italic">Institutions, Institutional Change and Economic Performance</hi> </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0139i-ftnote.017"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Olson, M. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">(1993), "Dictatorship, Democracy and Development", <hi rend="italic">American Political Science Review</hi>. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0139i-ftnote.018"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Bratton </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0139i-ftnote.019"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Bratton </s></p></note><p n="p7.7"><s n="s1.4;p7.7">In the year 2000 the United States economy was nine times the size of China's, and over 1,000 times that of Ethiopia's<ref target="BAWE_0139i-ftnote.020"/>; clearly, such a trend cannot simply be attributed to factor endowment discrepancies amongst countries. </s><s n="s2.4;p7.7">Backed by evidence throughout history - from Maghribi and Genoese long-distance trade, to the 17 <hi rend="sup">th</hi> Century's "European Miracle", to the demise of China's bureaucratic system - Douglass North's theory of institutions provides a more satisfactory explanation of the persistence of underdevelopment in today's world. </s><s n="s3.4;p7.7">Today institutions fundamentally explain not only economic discrepancies between countries, but also, according to Plamenatz, the securing of power in societies<ref target="BAWE_0139i-ftnote.021"/>; on a wider scale, liberal institutionalists consider the role of institutions in determining interstate relations and the future of the world order. </s><s n="s4.4;p7.7">Since they were first analysed by North in the 1980s, institutions have thus adopted an increasingly international scope; in today's globalizing world, we can thus expect them to contribute to an ever broader understanding of the persistence of underdevelopment. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0139i-ftnote.020"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Baylis, John and Smith, Steve. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1"><hi rend="underlined">The Globalization of World Politics: A introduction to international relations</hi> (Oxford: Oxford University Press, 2005 (2nd edition)). </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0139i-ftnote.021"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Baylis, John and Smith, Steve. </s><s rend="underlined" n="s2.2;pn1.1">The Globalization of World Politics </s></p></note></div1></body><back><div1 type="bibliography"><head>BIBLIOGRAPHY</head><p>Baylis, John and Smith, Steve. <hi rend="underlined">The Globalization of World Politics: A introduction to</hi></p><p><hi rend="underlined">international relations</hi> (Oxford: Oxford University Press, 2005 (2<hi rend="sup">nd</hi> edition)).</p><p>Bratton, Michael and Van de Walle, Nicolas. "Neopatrimonial Regimes and Political</p><p>Transitions in Africa". Internet. Accessed on 15<hi rend="sup">th</hi> Oct. 2005. Available at: <hi rend="underlined"><seg type="URL" n="http://www.jstor.org/view/00438871/di982458/98p0274b/1?frame=noframe&amp;userID=89cd1b87"/>@<name type="university"/>.ac.uk/01cce4403500501a64c85&amp;dpi=3&amp;config=jstor</hi></p><p>Deng, K.G. (2000), "A Critical Survey of Recent Research in Chinese Economic</p><p>History", <hi rend="italic">Economic History Review</hi>, 53, 1-28. </p><p>Greif, A. (2000), "The Fundamental Problem of Exchange: A Research Agenda in</p><p>Historical Institutional Analysis", <hi rend="italic">European Review of Economic History,</hi>. 4, 251-284. </p><p>Kuznets, S. (1974), <hi rend="italic">Population, Capital and Economic Growth: Selected Essays</hi>,</p><p>London: Heinemann.</p><p>Maddison, A. (1998), <hi rend="italic">Chinese Economic Performance in the Long Run</hi>, Paris:OECD.</p><p>Maddison, A. (2001), <hi rend="italic">The World Economy: A Millennial Perspective</hi>, Paris:OECD.</p><p>North, D.C. (1991), <hi rend="italic">Institutions, Institutional Change and Economic Performance</hi>,</p><p>Cambridge: Cambridge University Press.</p><p>North, D.G. and Weingast, B.R. (1989), "Constitutions and Commitment: The</p><p>Evolution of Institutions Governing Public Choice in Seventeenth-Century</p><p>England", <hi rend="italic">Journal of Economic History</hi>. Internet. Accessed on 16<hi rend="sup">th</hi> Nov. 2005.</p><p>Available at: <hi rend="underlined">http://0</hi></p><p rend="underlined"><seg type="URL" n="www.jstor.org.pugwash.lib"/>.<name type="university"/>.ac.uk/browse/00220507/.41</p><p rend="underlined">.50?frame=noframe&amp;userID=89cdc814@<name type="university"/>.ac.uk/01cce4403500501aa94</p><p rend="underlined">6&amp;dpi=3&amp;config=jstor</p><p>Olson, M. (1993), "Dictatorship, Democracy and Development", <hi rend="italic">American Political</hi></p><p><hi rend="italic">Science Review,</hi> 87, 567-576.</p></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
