<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_0139c" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Press Coverage of the Japan-China Conflict: Deepening the Countries' Mutual Hostilities?</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">footer: page numbers</note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">deleted: [word count: 1,610]</note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">appendix: 16 newspaper articles (in separate file)</note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">Running text contains reference to external or missing appendix.
</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">1</p><p n="date">2005-10</p><p n="module title">Introduction to Politics</p><p n="module code">PO107</p><p n="genre family">Essay</p><p n="discipline">Politics</p><p n="disciplinary group">SS</p><p n="grade">D</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">1597</p><p n="number of s-units">46</p><p n="number of p">7</p><p n="number of tables">0</p><p n="number of figures">0</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">0</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">0</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">34.7</p><p n="average s-units per p">6.6</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">f</p><p n="year of birth">1987</p><p n="first language">French</p><p n="education">OSA</p><p n="course">EPAIS</p><p n="student ID">0139</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><titlePart><name type="student name"/> Introduction to Politics Newspaper Project 25 <hi rend="sup">th</hi> October 2005</titlePart><docTitle><titlePart>Press Coverage of the Japan-China Conflict: Deepening the Countries' Mutual Hostilities?</titlePart></docTitle></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="section"><p n="p1.7"><s n="s1.9;p1.7">In an increasingly globalizing environment, the written press is gaining power worldwide. </s><s n="s2.9;p1.7">In Asia today, this is particularly visible in the relationships between Japan and China. </s><s n="s3.9;p1.7">Due to these countries' oppositions during World War II, Sino-Japanese ties have never been serene<ref target="BAWE_0139c-ftnote.001"/>; nonetheless, economic prospects have significantly bonded China and Japan throughout the late twentieth century. </s><s n="s4.9;p1.7">Today, however, tensions between these countries are resurfacing at a worrying pace. </s><s n="s5.9;p1.7">2005 has seen the mobilization of over 400,000 Chinese signing online petitions to oppose Japan's bid for a permanent seat on the U.N. Security Council; mass anti-Japan protests opposing the publication of a text-book said to "gloss over Japan's wartime atrocities"; and high Sino-Japanese discord over the control of gas exploitation in the East China Sea<ref target="BAWE_0139c-ftnote.002"/>. </s><s n="s6.9;p1.7">Many point towards the media as the source of such sudden hostility. </s><s n="s7.9;p1.7">Hokkaido University professor Kiyoshi Takai claims that "biased reports [are] breeding misunderstanding and hatred" between these countries<ref target="BAWE_0139c-ftnote.003"/>. </s><s n="s8.9;p1.7">In particular, the controversial history textbooks published in Japan have provoked countless articles in the Sino-Japanese press. </s><s n="s9.9;p1.7">By analyzing these countries' newspapers' treatment of this issue, and by comparing these views to those of the international press and to a more political analysis of the situation, one may evaluate the media's role in shaping readers' minds - not only in Japan and China, but worldwide. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0139c-ftnote.001"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">"International Herald Tribune", 12 February 2002 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0139c-ftnote.002"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">"The Japan Times", 18 April 2005 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0139c-ftnote.003"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Chung-Yan, "China &amp; Japan - superficial, biased reporting hurting ties between nations" </s></p></note><p n="p2.7"><s n="s1.11;p2.7">Articles covering the textbook issue in the Sino-Japanese press show an evident reporting bias; as noted by Kiyoshi Takai, "for the Chinese media, Japan-bashing has become an obsession"<ref target="BAWE_0139c-ftnote.004"/>. </s><s n="s2.11;p2.7">Excerpts from China's "The People's Daily" are mostly written in an objective style: the author seldom offers personal judgement, and facts are quantitatively presented. </s><s n="s3.11;p2.7">In subtext, however, these articles often appeal to anti-Japan sentiments. </s><s n="s4.11;p2.7">Article 1 describes Chinese president Hu Jintao's recent speech, in which Japanese are described as, "arch criminals who . . . had their hands blotted with the blood of the people around the world", and who "wantonly trampled underfoot the beautiful land of China" <ref target="BAWE_0139c-ftnote.005"/>. </s><s n="s5.11;p2.7">Despite the article's carefully detached style here, by exclusively citing such quotations it becomes clearly biased. </s><s n="s6.11;p2.7">Likewise, behind A.2's apparently objective description of anti-Japan protests in China, the author adopts an individual focus and introduces readers to "an old man who experienced the World War II [and who] said the war had broken his family up", stirring resentment in his readers<ref target="BAWE_0139c-ftnote.006"/>. </s><s n="s7.11;p2.7">Insisting on such individual focus particularly strongly, A.3 appeals to readers' emotions by detailing the wartime hardships of a Shanghai farmer, who "lost his mother in a Japanese bombing attack", whose father and brother "were stabbed to death by Japanese soldiers" and whose grandmother "died in prison . . . after she was forced to eat human flesh" <ref target="BAWE_0139c-ftnote.007"/>. </s><s n="s8.11;p2.7">The Chinese media thus starkly differs from the approach that political scientists may take to explore the textbook situation: these articles adopt an individual focus often avoided by political analysis for objectivity's sake, and only really return to discussing the textbook issue itself in their last lines. </s><s n="s9.11;p2.7">Nonetheless, this approach may be aimed not at igniting anti-Japanese sentiments in readers, but perhaps simply at securing commercial gains. </s><s n="s10.11;p2.7">As put by Chinese journalists, "tabloids want to use provocative reports to sell newspapers . . . positive stories [on Japan] would not be used"<ref target="BAWE_0139c-ftnote.008"/>. </s><s n="s11.11;p2.7">While the press augments Chinese nationalism, therefore, the nature of the Chinese public itself influences the media's level of bias. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0139c-ftnote.004"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Chung-Yan, "China &amp; Japan - superficial, biased reporting hurting ties between nations" </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0139c-ftnote.005"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">"The People's Daily", 3rd September 2005 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0139c-ftnote.006"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">"The People's Daily", 18th April 2005 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0139c-ftnote.007"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">"The People's Daily", 16th August 2005 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0139c-ftnote.008"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Chung-Yan, "China &amp; Japan - superficial, biased reporting hurting ties between nations" </s></p></note><p n="p3.7"><s n="s1.6;p3.7">Unsurprisingly, the Japanese press is equally subjective in its presentation of the textbook issue; rather than exploring the controversy at the individual level, however, journalists more frequently blame it on the Chinese government and education system. </s><s n="s2.6;p3.7">Reporting on the anti-Japan protests in China, A.4 attributes Chinese hostility to "anti-Japanese instruction that Chinese schools have delivered since the 1980s"<ref target="BAWE_0139c-ftnote.009"/>; it furthermore condemns the Chinese government's refusal to apologise for the protests, as well as its provocative attempts at gas exploitation in the East China Sea. </s><s n="s3.6;p3.7">Hu Jintao's government comes under further attack in A.5: as in many Chinese articles, the author's objective tone here is offset by his exclusive citing of claims that the Chinese protesters were "controlled" <ref target="BAWE_0139c-ftnote.010"/> by the government. </s><s n="s4.6;p3.7">A.6 likewise states that, "police watched the protesters but didn't stop them" and that, "Beijing should have prevented the violence" <ref target="BAWE_0139c-ftnote.011"/>. </s><s n="s5.6;p3.7">Contrarily to Chinese articles, which frequently analyse the textbook controversy on what political scientists would call the individual level (adopting an 'extensive view' of politics in which daily individual interactions influence a country's political stance), Japanese articles thus apply the domestic level of analysis to the issue, focusing primarily on government actions through a 'limited view'. </s><s n="s6.6;p3.7">Despite such differences, Sino-Japanese press are nevertheless both highly subjective in their coverage. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0139c-ftnote.009"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">"The Japan Times", 18th April 2005 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0139c-ftnote.010"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">"The Japan Times", 18th April 2005 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0139c-ftnote.011"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">"The Japan Times", 17th April 2005 </s></p></note><p n="p4.7"><s n="s1.4;p4.7">Such bias is not present in all Chinese and Japanese articles, however: some journalists in fact fully recognize their own country's share of responsibility in the ongoing friction. </s><s n="s2.4;p4.7">In reporting intervening political figures' speeches, A.7 differs from previously-cited articles - it includes quotations that are both favourable towards China's government and critical of it: the article refers both to the Chinese Foreign Minister's claim that, "the Chinese government has never done anything that wronged the Japanese people," and to his Japanese counterpart's request for the Chinese government to "sincerely handle [the] matter under international regulations"<ref target="BAWE_0139c-ftnote.012"/>. </s><s n="s3.4;p4.7">Correspondingly, A.8 looks not towards Japan as a cause of April's violent protests, but towards Chinese education - while the author argues that, "Chinese students learn in their history lessons to love their country but not to hate Japan", he nonetheless acknowledges that, "58 million Chinese teens study the Japanese occupation of China . . . as part of regular Chinese history courses"<ref target="BAWE_0139c-ftnote.013"/>. </s><s n="s4.4;p4.7">Visibly, not all articles dealing with the textbook issue in the Chinese press are overly biased; by adopting a stance more akin to that of political scientists and analyzing the conflict based on its cultural and sociological antecedents, some authors offer readers a more comprehensive investigation of today's tensions. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0139c-ftnote.012"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">"CBS News", 17 April 2005 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0139c-ftnote.013"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">"The People's Daily", 22 April 2005 </s></p></note><p n="p5.7"><s n="s1.5;p5.7">Similarly, Japanese articles do not exclusively blame China for the current controversy; some, like A.9, indeed recognize that the textbooks may be "nationalistic and a whitewash of Japan's wartime aggression" <ref target="BAWE_0139c-ftnote.014"/>, and acknowledge the protests that have resulted in not only in China, but also in South Korea and in parts of Japan. </s><s n="s2.5;p5.7">A.10 likewise provides a dichotomous view of the situation: despite reproving China's refusal to apologise for the April protests, its author reports the Chinese Foreign Minister's statement that, "the responsibility for the current situation falls on the Japanese side"<ref target="BAWE_0139c-ftnote.015"/>. </s><s n="s3.5;p5.7">Some authors take a particularly extreme stance, at times fully blaming Japan for the conflict - A.11 asserts that, despite the widespread conviction that Japan has apologized to China for its wartime atrocities (a belief that largely contributes to Japan's self-righteousness vis-à-vis China), there is in fact "no indication that [the Japanese Foreign Minister] had made such an apology". </s><s n="s4.5;p5.7">A.12 inculpates Japan even further, affirming that, "the Japanese assault [during WWII ] was merciless", and backing this claim with horrifying details of Japanese war crimes; by then contrasting such descriptions to news that, "while [Japanese president] Koizumi was apologizing for the war, at least one member of his Cabinet . . . visited Yasukuni Shrine, which honors war criminals"<ref target="BAWE_0139c-ftnote.016"/>, the author clearly condemns not only his country's violent past, but also its current actions. </s><s n="s5.5;p5.7">Though isolated, therefore, some articles do indeed limit the amount of nationalistic bias prevalent in the Sino-Japanese press - perhaps so as to cater to more objective readers' tastes. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0139c-ftnote.014"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">"The Japan Times", 27 August 2005 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0139c-ftnote.015"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">"The Japan Times", 19 April 2005 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0139c-ftnote.016"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">"The Japan Times", 4 August 2005 </s></p></note><p n="p6.7"><s n="s1.8;p6.7">Despite these more balanced viewpoints, there however remains a clear distinction between Sino-Japanese articles and those of the international press: while the former restrict political analysis of the textbook issue to mostly anecdotic accounts of recent protests and diplomatic blotches, the latter delve into the causes of current hostilities at a broader socio-economic level. </s><s n="s2.8;p6.7">A.13 recognises that, "it is not the demonstrations that should be the central issue between these two countries, but rather the underlying causes that created this firestorm"<ref target="BAWE_0139c-ftnote.017"/>. </s><s n="s3.8;p6.7">The author relates the "firestorm" to Sino-Japanese disputes concerning the East China Sea's gas fields and Taiwan's future status. </s><s n="s4.8;p6.7">A.14, meanwhile, claims that the Japanese president's deliberately reactionary attitude towards China "is due in no small measure to the support he has received from the Bush administration"<ref target="BAWE_0139c-ftnote.018"/>. </s><s n="s5.8;p6.7">A.15 attributes the anti-Japan protests in April to "China's state-controlled media [which] sustain[s] the belief that Japan has indeed never apologized [for its war crimes]"<ref target="BAWE_0139c-ftnote.019"/>. </s><s n="s6.8;p6.7">Yet other international papers link Sino-Japanese hostility to overly nationalistic education in China - A.16 points out that, despite the controversy existing over the Japanese history books, "China's corresponding textbook . . . appears to have gaps of its own"<ref target="BAWE_0139c-ftnote.020"/>. </s><s n="s7.8;p6.7">In investigating Sino-Japanese conflicts, the international press considers issues mostly ignored by the implicated countries' media. </s><s n="s8.8;p6.7">Perhaps due to the intellectual expectations of their readers or to the more culturally-detached perspective of their authors, these articles cover the ongoing tensions in a manner more typical of political scientists: adopting a structuralist view, they analyse not only the individual behaviour of actors involved in the conflict, but their society's role in shaping these actions. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0139c-ftnote.017"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">"Japan Today", 16 May 2005 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0139c-ftnote.018"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">"World Socialist News", 25 April 2005 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0139c-ftnote.019"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">"The New York Times", 21 April 2005 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0139c-ftnote.020"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">"The Financial Times", 11 May 2005 </s></p></note><p n="p7.7"><s n="s1.3;p7.7">Through analyzing the impact of the textbook issue's media coverage on Sino-Japanese relations, one can conclude that the international press, by adopting a more extensive and global approach to the controversy, comes closer to solving these tensions than the local press does with its often provocative individual focus. </s><s n="s2.3;p7.7">Overall, public interest seems to influence the level of bias and political analysis offered by the media just as much as the press in turn impacts reader's opinions. </s><s n="s3.3;p7.7">In a world where "media now play[s] an unprecedented role in shaping bilateral relationship[s]", the press and its readers may have to grow apart if politically-relevant coverage is to be achieved. </s></p></div1></body><back><div1 type="missing or external appendix"><p/></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
