<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_0139j" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>"Divergence Big Time" in Twentieth Century Economic Growth: Dooming Neoclassical Predictions of Future Convergence?</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">The document has a title page which contains:
document title
title part</note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">deleted: header: student name and number; footer: page numbers</note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">deleted: Word count: 1, 649</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">1</p><p n="date">2006-02</p><p n="module title">World Economy: History &amp; Theory</p><p n="module code">EC104</p><p n="genre family">Essay</p><p n="discipline">Economics</p><p n="disciplinary group">SS</p><p n="grade">D</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">1677</p><p n="number of s-units">67</p><p n="number of p">9</p><p n="number of tables">0</p><p n="number of figures">0</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">0</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">0</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">25.0</p><p n="average s-units per p">7.4</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">f</p><p n="year of birth">1987</p><p n="first language">French</p><p n="education">OSA</p><p n="course">EPAIS</p><p n="student ID">0139</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><docTitle><titlePart>"Divergence Big Time" in Twentieth Century Economic Growth: Dooming Neoclassical Predictions of Future Convergence?</titlePart></docTitle><titlePart><name type="student name"/>, <name type="student ID"/></titlePart><titlePart>World Economy (EC 104)</titlePart><titlePart>Question 3: <hi rend="italic">Why was the experience of economic growth in the 20th century one of 'divergence big time'? What light does your answer shed on the assumptions of the Solow growth model?</hi> </titlePart><titlePart>Tutor: <name type="other"/> Module Director: <name type="tutor name"/> Date: 21 / 02 / 2006</titlePart></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="section"><p n="p1.9"><s n="s1.10;p1.9">Today's world is one of rapidly growing inequality. </s><s n="s2.10;p1.9">In 1960, the average income of the world population's richest 20% was 30 times higher than that of the poorest 20%; by 1995, this had risen to 82 times<ref target="BAWE_0139j-ftnote.001"/>. </s><s n="s3.10;p1.9">What causes such tremendous disparities? </s><s n="s4.10;p1.9">Why are the neoclassical predictions of the Solow model - which foretells long-term income <hi rend="italic">convergence</hi> - collapsing? </s><s n="s5.10;p1.9">Economic historians attribute this "divergence big time" to differences in economies' total factor productivity, which is affected primarily by countries' institutional quality and geography. </s><s n="s6.10;p1.9">Institutions and geographical endowments are often unchangeable, however, or at least extremely difficult to improve rapidly. </s><s n="s7.10;p1.9">Will convergence and international equality therefore remain unobtainable even throughout the 21 <hi rend="sup">st</hi> Century? </s><s n="s8.10;p1.9">Perhaps not: other indications of living standards, such as poverty levels or Human Development Indices, are converging. </s><s n="s9.10;p1.9">This suggests that, while the assumptions guiding neoclassical predictions are seriously flawed, global convergence remains achievable. </s><s n="s10.10;p1.9">The extent to which developing countries' institutions and social infrastructures are bettered in coming decades will determine whether the 21 <hi rend="sup">st</hi> Century can escape the predicament of "divergence big time". </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0139j-ftnote.001"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.3;pn1.1">Vanaik, Achin. </s><s n="s2.3;pn1.1">"Unequal Gains". </s><s n="s3.3;pn1.1"><hi rend="italic">Telegraph,</hi> December 2005. Accessed at: <seg type="URL" n="http://www.globalpolicy.org/socecon/inequal/2005/1222inequgains.htm"/> </s></p></note><p n="p2.9"><s n="s1.9;p2.9">In the 1980s neoclassicalists such as Robert Solow and Robert Lucas predicted the natural convergence of world income. </s><s n="s2.9;p2.9">The Solow model claims that when an economy's labour force is low, its per-capita savings are high, increasing its output, but that this rise eventually converges to a situation of 'steady state growth' as per-capita savings are superseded by a growing population<ref target="BAWE_0139j-ftnote.002"/>. </s><s n="s3.9;p2.9">In the long run, therefore, all economies will grow at the same rate. </s><s n="s4.9;p2.9">Correspondingly, Robert Lucas argues that later-starting countries will have faster initial growth ('β-convergence'), and then experience growth proportional to their income gap with the world's leading country, until this gap diminishes to zero ('σ-convergence') <ref target="BAWE_0139j-ftnote.003"/>. </s><s n="s5.9;p2.9">Lucas bases this convergence on cross-border equalizations of capital-to-labour ratios and total factor productivity, attributed to globalisation's 'spillovers'. </s><s n="s6.9;p2.9">Human capital spillover should provide developing countries with imitable models of Western countries' more efficient institutions. </s><s n="s7.9;p2.9">Financial liberalization should grant poor nations access to richer ones' savings, enabling them to invest beyond domestic savings constraints. </s><s n="s8.9;p2.9">Lastly, high wages in successful economies should generate capital flows to weaker economies, increasing the latter's income levels.<ref target="BAWE_0139j-ftnote.004"/> Like the Solow model, Lucas's model predicts that "sooner or later . . . all economies will grow at the rate common to the wealthiest economies, and differences in income levels will disappear"<ref target="BAWE_0139j-ftnote.005"/>. </s><s n="s9.9;p2.9">Expectations of international income convergence form the core of neoclassical growth theory. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0139j-ftnote.002"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.5;pn1.1">Jones, Hywel G. </s><s n="s2.5;pn1.1"><hi rend="underlined">An Introduction to Modern Theories of Economic Growth</hi>. </s><s n="s3.5;pn1.1">London, Thomas Nelson and Sons, 1975. </s><s n="s4.5;pn1.1">Pg. </s><s n="s5.5;pn1.1">84. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0139j-ftnote.003"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.6;pn1.1">Lucas, Robert. </s><s n="s2.6;pn1.1">"Some macroeconomics for the 21st century". </s><s n="s3.6;pn1.1"><hi rend="underlined">Journal of Economic Perspectives</hi>. </s><s n="s4.6;pn1.1">Vol.14, Issue 1. </s><s n="s5.6;pn1.1">Pg. </s><s n="s6.6;pn1.1">160. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0139j-ftnote.004"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.5;pn1.1">Lucas, Robert. </s><s n="s2.5;pn1.1">"Some macroeconomics for the 21st century". </s><s n="s3.5;pn1.1"><hi rend="underlined">Journal of Economic Perspectives</hi>. </s><s n="s4.5;pn1.1">Pg. </s><s n="s5.5;pn1.1">165. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0139j-ftnote.005"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.5;pn1.1">Lucas, Robert. </s><s n="s2.5;pn1.1">"Some macroeconomics for the 21st century". </s><s n="s3.5;pn1.1"><hi rend="underlined">Journal of Economic Perspectives</hi>. </s><s n="s4.5;pn1.1">Pg. </s><s n="s5.5;pn1.1">170. </s></p></note><p n="p3.9"><s n="s1.5;p3.9">Empirical investigations contradict these predictions, however. </s><s n="s2.5;p3.9">Since the Industrial Revolution the West has far outgrown of the rest of the world in per-capita income. </s><s n="s3.5;p3.9">Whilst in 1970 the per-capita GDP gap between the world's richest country and its poorest was of 88:1, in 2000 it had widened to 267:1<ref target="BAWE_0139j-ftnote.006"/>. </s><s n="s4.5;p3.9">Lucas's predictions of faster catch-up growth by 'late-starters' have collapsed, as most developing countries continue to grow much slower than the West (Africa's per capita income has thus dropped from 9.4% of US levels in 1950 to 5.2% in 2000, indicating significantly lagging growth<ref target="BAWE_0139j-ftnote.007"/>). </s><s n="s5.5;p3.9">20 <hi rend="sup">th</hi> Century "divergence big time" drastically contradicts the neoclassical forecast of convergence - as put by Fagerberg, "it is rare to see a prediction that is so completely rejected by the evidence as this one is"<ref target="BAWE_0139j-ftnote.008"/>. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0139j-ftnote.006"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.3;pn1.1">Vanaik, Achin. </s><s n="s2.3;pn1.1">"Unequal Gains". </s><s n="s3.3;pn1.1"><hi rend="italic">Telegraph,</hi> December 2005. Accessed at: <seg type="URL" n="http://www.globalpolicy.org/socecon/inequal/2005/1222inequgains.htm"/> </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0139j-ftnote.007"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.6;pn1.1">Maddison, Angus. </s><s n="s2.6;pn1.1"><hi rend="underlined">The World Economy: A Millennial Perspective</hi>. </s><s n="s3.6;pn1.1">2003. </s><s n="s4.6;pn1.1">Organization for Economic Cooperation &amp; Development. </s><s n="s5.6;pn1.1">Pg. </s><s n="s6.6;pn1.1">500. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0139j-ftnote.008"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.4;pn1.1">Jones, Hywel. </s><s n="s2.4;pn1.1"><hi rend="underlined">An Introduction to Modern Theories of Economic Growth</hi>. </s><s n="s3.4;pn1.1">Thomas Nelson &amp; Sons, Pg. </s><s n="s4.4;pn1.1">86. </s></p></note><p n="p4.9"><s n="s1.8;p4.9">What explains this divergence? </s><s n="s2.8;p4.9">Many economists attribute economic growth primarily to the productivity of a country's labour force. </s><s n="s3.8;p4.9">Output per worker varies widely across countries: the USA's 1988levels were 35 times higher than Niger's, meaning that ten days' worth of American worker's production was only matched by a Nigerian after a year<ref target="BAWE_0139j-ftnote.009"/>. </s><s n="s4.8;p4.9">Hall and Jones relate such disparities to the level of countries' human capital inputs, such as education investment (a lack of the latter may explain France's and the UK's lag on the USA) and, in poorer countries, to economies' total factor productivity - which reflects both the state of their technology and how efficiently their capital and labour are utilized<ref target="BAWE_0139j-ftnote.010"/>. </s><s n="s5.8;p4.9">Hall and Jones claim that TFP and human capital inputs are "fundamentally related to differences in [economies'] social infrastructures"<ref target="BAWE_0139j-ftnote.011"/>, or to the institutions and policies that determine the economic environment of individual and firm actions. </s><s n="s6.8;p4.9">As social infrastructures can provide incentives for productivity just as they can inhibit innovation by encouraging inefficiency and corruption, they heavily impact economic growth. </s><s n="s7.8;p4.9">Indeed, policy modifications in China (which greatly reformed its agricultural incentive structures since 1978<ref target="BAWE_0139j-ftnote.012"/>) and India coincide with much stronger TFP growth in Asia than in Africa<ref target="BAWE_0139j-ftnote.013"/>. </s><s n="s8.8;p4.9">Countering the Solow model's assumption of constant TFP growth worldwide, Hall and Jones demonstrate that today's divergence is largely impacted by TFP disparities and by the quality of countries' social infrastructures. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0139j-ftnote.009"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.6;pn1.1">Hall, R.E. and Jones, C.I.. </s><s n="s2.6;pn1.1">"Why Do Some Countries Produce So Much More Output Per Worker Than Others?" </s><s n="s3.6;pn1.1"><hi rend="italic">Quarterly Journal of Economics</hi>, 114. </s><s n="s4.6;pn1.1">Pg. </s><s n="s5.6;pn1.1">84. </s><s n="s6.6;pn1.1">Accessed at: <hi rend="underlined"><seg type="URL" n="http://0-ejournals.ebsco.com.pugwash.lib.warwick.ac.uk"/>:80/direct.asp?ArticleID=7T7Y3XPNAEJUW3LJ3C8W</hi> </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0139j-ftnote.010"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.5;pn1.1">Hall, R.E. and Jones, C.I.. </s><s n="s2.5;pn1.1">"Why Do Some Countries Produce So Much More Output Per Worker Than Others?" </s><s n="s3.5;pn1.1"><hi rend="italic">Quarterly Journal of Economics</hi>, 114. </s><s n="s4.5;pn1.1">Pg. </s><s n="s5.5;pn1.1">82. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0139j-ftnote.011"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.6;pn1.1">Hall, R.E. and Jones, C.I.. </s><s n="s2.6;pn1.1">"Why Do Some Countries Produce So Much More Output Per Worker Than Others?" </s><s n="s3.6;pn1.1"><hi rend="italic">Quarterly Journal of Economics</hi>, 114. </s><s n="s4.6;pn1.1">Pg. </s><s n="s5.6;pn1.1">84. </s><s n="s6.6;pn1.1">Accessed at: <hi rend="underlined"><seg type="URL" n="http://0-ejournals.ebsco.com.pugwash.lib.warwick.ac.uk"/>:80/direct.asp?ArticleID=7T7Y3XPNAEJUW3LJ3C8W</hi> </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0139j-ftnote.012"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.4;pn1.1">Deng, K.G. </s><s n="s2.4;pn1.1">(2000), "A Critical Survey of Recent Research in Chinese Economic History", Economic History Review, 53. </s><s n="s3.4;pn1.1">Pg. </s><s n="s4.4;pn1.1">11. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0139j-ftnote.013"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.4;pn1.1">Bosworth, B.P. and Collins, S.M. </s><s n="s2.4;pn1.1">"The Empirics of Growth: An Update". </s><s n="s3.4;pn1.1"><hi rend="underlined">Brookings Papers on Economic Activity</hi>. </s><s n="s4.4;pn1.1">Washington: 2003 Iss.2; pg.116. </s></p></note><p n="p5.9"><s n="s1.8;p5.9">What determines such "social capability"? </s><s n="s2.8;p5.9">New Institutional Economic Historians claim that <hi rend="italic">institutions</hi> play a vital role in structuring social growth incentives. </s><s n="s3.8;p5.9">In particular, the strength of institutions in limiting government power and in enforcing contracts determines the appropriability of an economy's returns, and therefore its investment levels. </s><s n="s4.8;p5.9">Acemoglu and Johnson demonstrate that institutional efficiency differs greatly across countries, depending particularly on the antiquity of an economy's state, on its government's democratic accountability, and, in former colonies, on the legal systems inherited from colonizers<ref target="BAWE_0139j-ftnote.014"/>. </s><s n="s5.8;p5.9">These variations significantly impact economic growth. </s><s n="s6.8;p5.9">An economy's adherence to the rule of law (or the extent to which agents have confidence in and abide by society's rules and institutions) for instance strongly correlates with productivity - Africa's and Latin America's low productivity levels thus coincide with poor RoL scores (-0.81 and -0.41 respectively)<ref target="BAWE_0139j-ftnote.015"/>. </s><s n="s7.8;p5.9">By contrast, accession countries having undergone institutional reform under EU conditionality boast high RoL scores and improving growth rates<ref target="BAWE_0139j-ftnote.016"/>. </s><s n="s8.8;p5.9">Such evidence suggests that variations in institutional quality highly influence economic growth, and may explain much of 20 <hi rend="sup">th</hi> Century divergence. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0139j-ftnote.014"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.7;pn1.1">Bardhan, Pranab. </s><s n="s2.7;pn1.1">"Institutions matter, but which ones?" </s><s n="s3.7;pn1.1"><hi rend="underlined">Economics of Transition</hi>, Volume 13, No. </s><s n="s4.7;pn1.1">3. </s><s n="s5.7;pn1.1">July 2005. </s><s n="s6.7;pn1.1">Pg. </s><s n="s7.7;pn1.1">501. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0139j-ftnote.015"><p n="pn1.2"><s n="s1.3;pn1.2">Kaufman, Daniel, Aart Kraay, and Massimo Mastruzzi. </s><s n="s2.3;pn1.2">2003. </s><s n="s3.3;pn1.2">"Governance Matters III: </s></p><p n="pn2.2"><s n="s1.4;pn2.2">Governance Indicators for 1996-2002." </s><s n="s2.4;pn2.2"><hi rend="underlined">World Bank Policy Research Working Paper 3106</hi>. </s><s n="s3.4;pn2.2">Pg. </s><s n="s4.4;pn2.2">4. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0139j-ftnote.016"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.4;pn1.1">Crafts, Nicholas &amp; Kaiser, Kai, 2004. </s><s n="s2.4;pn1.1">"Long-term growth prospects in transition economies: a reappraisal." </s><s n="s3.4;pn1.1"><hi rend="underlined">Structural Change and Economic Dynamics</hi>, Vol. 15(1), Pg. </s><s n="s4.4;pn1.1">110. </s></p></note><p n="p6.9"><s n="s1.6;p6.9">This implies that countries with inadequate institutions may be doomed to perpetual underdevelopment and divergence, as institutional change is extremely difficult to achieve. </s><s n="s2.6;p6.9">Douglass North argues that inefficient institutions persist because they rest on vested interests in society which oppose changes to the status quo; furthermore, institutions develop from and reinforce informal social rules which "cause [a] society to evolve along a particular trajectory and in the long run explain distinct economic performances"<ref target="BAWE_0139j-ftnote.017"/>. </s><s n="s3.6;p6.9">Institutions are therefore subject to path-dependency: whilst efficient ones trigger growth, inefficient ones can trap their users in detrimental habits. </s><s n="s4.6;p6.9">Being impermeable to top-down reform, informal institutions (such as trust or cultural values) are particularly problematic in this respect. </s><s n="s5.6;p6.9">These nonetheless remain vital to economic growth - Knack and Keefer suggest that a 10% increase in a country's trust can raise its growth rate by 0.8%<ref target="BAWE_0139j-ftnote.018"/>. </s><s n="s6.6;p6.9">Trust levels, like the stability of formal institutions, vary highly internationally; weak institutions in countries may therefore not only explain their current income discrepancies, but may also obstruct future convergence. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0139j-ftnote.017"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.3;pn1.1">North, D.G. and Weingast, B.R. (1989), "Constitutions and Commitment: The Evolution of Institutions Governing Public Choice in Seventeenth-Century England", <hi rend="italic">Journal of Economic History.</hi> </s><s n="s2.3;pn1.1">Pg. </s><s n="s3.3;pn1.1">13. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0139j-ftnote.018"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.5;pn1.1">Knack, S, and Keefer, P. </s><s n="s2.5;pn1.1">(1997) "Does social capital have an economic payoff?" </s><s n="s3.5;pn1.1"><hi rend="underlined">Quarterly Journal of Economics</hi>. </s><s n="s4.5;pn1.1">Pg. </s><s n="s5.5;pn1.1">53. </s></p></note><p n="p7.9"><s n="s1.6;p7.9">Outside of institutional frameworks, economic historians also focus on <hi rend="italic">geography</hi>'s impact on economic growth incentives. </s><s n="s2.6;p7.9">For Jeffrey Sachs, oil- and mineral-exporting countries face a "natural resource curse", as their production of primary resources entails the neglect of other economic sectors (the so-called 'Dutch disease') and discourages modernization, as elites profiting from the resources develop vested interests in the economy's status quo<ref target="BAWE_0139j-ftnote.019"/>. </s><s n="s3.6;p7.9">The corruption and mistrust often bred by such lucrative resources cripple countries' institutions and exacerbate income inequalities - whilst Nigerian oil exports for instance totaled $350 billion between 1965 and 2000, in this period the proportion of Nigerians living on less than $1 a day grew from 36% to 70%<ref target="BAWE_0139j-ftnote.020"/>. </s><s n="s4.6;p7.9">Geographical <hi rend="italic">location</hi> may also explain 20 <hi rend="sup">th</hi> Century divergence: Redding and Venables argue that, the further a country is from the locus of global economic activity, the higher its transport and importation costs are and the less competitive its exports become. </s><s n="s5.6;p7.9">They thus attribute two-thirds of cross-country income variations to distance from markets, arguing that moving a country 50% closer to its trading partners would raise its income by 25%<ref target="BAWE_0139j-ftnote.021"/>. </s><s n="s6.6;p7.9">As Nicholas Crafts concludes, "the world economy is not quite the level playing field of neoclassical economics"<ref target="BAWE_0139j-ftnote.022"/>: if countries possess poor geographical or institutional structures, their chances of catch-up growth and convergence may be permanently jeopardized. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0139j-ftnote.019"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.6;pn1.1">Sachs, J.D. and Warner, A.M. </s><s n="s2.6;pn1.1">1995. </s><s n="s3.6;pn1.1">"Natural Resource Abundance and Economic Growth". </s><s rend="underlined" n="s4.6;pn1.1">Harvard Institute for International Development. </s><s n="s5.6;pn1.1">Pg. </s><s n="s6.6;pn1.1">71. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0139j-ftnote.020"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.6;pn1.1">Sachs, J.D. and Warner, A.M. </s><s n="s2.6;pn1.1">1995. </s><s n="s3.6;pn1.1">"Natural Resource Abundance and Economic Growth". </s><s rend="underlined" n="s4.6;pn1.1">Harvard Institute for International Development. </s><s n="s5.6;pn1.1">Pg. </s><s n="s6.6;pn1.1">76. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0139j-ftnote.021"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.6;pn1.1">Redding, Stephen and Venables, Anthony. </s><s n="s2.6;pn1.1">2002. </s><s n="s3.6;pn1.1">"The economics of isolation and distance". </s><s n="s4.6;pn1.1"><hi rend="underlined">Nordic Journal of Political Economy</hi>, (Conference Issue), 28. </s><s n="s5.6;pn1.1">Pg. </s><s n="s6.6;pn1.1">96. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0139j-ftnote.022"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.4;pn1.1">Crafts, Nicholas &amp; Kaiser, Kai, 2004. </s><s n="s2.4;pn1.1">"Long-term growth prospects in transition economies: a reappraisal." </s><s n="s3.4;pn1.1"><hi rend="underlined">Structural Change and Economic Dynamics</hi>, Vol. 15(1), Pg. </s><s n="s4.4;pn1.1">109. </s></p></note><p n="p8.9"><s n="s1.7;p8.9">Is such pessimism justified? </s><s n="s2.7;p8.9">Is world income convergence truly vital to equalizing global living standards? </s><s n="s3.7;p8.9">Economic theorists increasingly argue that per-capita income does not accurately measure quality of life. </s><s n="s4.7;p8.9">Despite income divergence over the past century, non-income determinants of living standards such as poverty and literacy levels are effectively converging. </s><s n="s5.7;p8.9">Life expectancy is equalizing with countries' facilitated access to health-care technologies, and improvements in developing nations' educational standards has pushed global literacy up from 52% to 81% between 1950 and 1999. </s><s n="s6.7;p8.9">In these years the coefficients for global life expectancy and literacy variations have dropped from 0.26 to 0.11 and from 0.73 to 0.22 respectively, and the UN's Human Development Index has also shown convergence. </s><s n="s7.7;p8.9">These figures imply that underdevelopment results more from a lack of basic capabilities than from insufficient income, and that, whilst prospects of income convergence remain bleak for this century, potential for <hi rend="italic">development</hi> may be at its highest. </s></p><p n="p9.9"><s n="s1.8;p9.9">In terms of income, the 20 <hi rend="sup">th</hi> Century has been one of "divergence big time", resulting from variations in countries' institutional frameworks as well as from their cultural and geographical differences. </s><s n="s2.8;p9.9">In terms of living standards, however, the gap between the West and developing countries is shrinking. </s><s n="s3.8;p9.9">What, therefore, are the prospects for equality in coming years? </s><s n="s4.8;p9.9">Lucas claims that "the restoration of inter-society income equality will be one of the major economic events of th[is] century"<ref target="BAWE_0139j-ftnote.023"/>, and that, despite their past failures, neoclassical predictions of convergence will ultimately prevail. </s><s n="s5.8;p9.9">20 <hi rend="sup">th</hi> Century divergence nonetheless challenges the Solow model's applicability to today's world. </s><s n="s6.8;p9.9">This model's assumptions of perfectly mobile factors of production and of universal total factor productivity are flawed; capital-to-labour ratios and income will not naturally converge while countries remain bound to inappropriate institutional frameworks. </s><s n="s7.8;p9.9">Institutional change may however be possible: Alexander Gerschenkron recommends that developing countries cultivate 'substitutes for prerequisites for growth' - that they develop institutions based not on Western models, but on more culturally-specific criteria<ref target="BAWE_0139j-ftnote.024"/>. </s><s n="s8.8;p9.9">If North's institutional 'lock-in' problem can be mitigated by nurturing such 'substitutes' or through concerted international efforts, convergence may still be possible in the 21 <hi rend="sup">st</hi> Century. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0139j-ftnote.023"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.6;pn1.1">Lucas, Robert. </s><s n="s2.6;pn1.1">"Some macroeconomics for the 21st century". </s><s n="s3.6;pn1.1"><hi rend="underlined">Journal of Economic Perspectives</hi>. </s><s n="s4.6;pn1.1">Vol.14, Issue 1. </s><s n="s5.6;pn1.1">Pg. </s><s n="s6.6;pn1.1">166. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0139j-ftnote.024"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.3;pn1.1">Crafts, Nicholas &amp; Kaiser, Kai, 2004. </s><s n="s2.3;pn1.1">"Long-term growth prospects in transition economies: a reappraisal." </s><s n="s3.3;pn1.1"><hi rend="underlined">Structural Change and Economic Dynamics</hi>, Vol. 15(1). </s></p></note></div1></body><back><div1 type="bibliography"><head>BIBLIOGRAPHY</head><p>Vanaik, Achin. "Unequal Gains". <hi rend="italic">Telegraph,</hi> December 2005. Accessed at: <seg type="URL" n="http://www.globalpolicy.org/socecon/inequal/2005/1222inequgains.htm"/> </p><p>Jones, Hywel G. <hi rend="underlined">An Introduction to Modern Theories of Economic Growth</hi>. London, Thomas Nelson and Sons, 1975. </p><p>Lucas, Robert. "Some macroeconomics for the 21st century". <hi rend="underlined">Journal of Economic Perspectives</hi>. Vol.14, Issue 1. </p><p>Maddison, Angus. <hi rend="underlined">The World Economy: A Millennial Perspective</hi>. 2003. Organization for Economic Cooperation &amp; Development. </p><p>Hall, R.E. and Jones, C.I.. "Why Do Some Countries Produce So Much More Output Per Worker Than Others?" <hi rend="italic">Quarterly Journal of Economics</hi>, 114. </p><p>Deng, K.G. (2000), "A Critical Survey of Recent Research in Chinese Economic History", Economic History Review, 53.</p><p>Bosworth, B.P. and Collins, S.M. "The Empirics of Growth: An Update". <hi rend="underlined">Brookings Papers on Economic Activity</hi>. Washington: 2003 Iss.2.</p><p>Bardhan, Pranab. "Institutions matter, but which ones?" Economics of Transition, Volume 13, No. 3. July 2005. </p><p>Kaufman, Daniel, Aart Kraay, and Massimo Mastruzzi. 2003. "Governance Matters III:</p><p>Governance Indicators for 1996-2002." <hi rend="underlined">World Bank Policy Research Working Paper 3106</hi>. </p><p>Crafts, Nicholas &amp; Kaiser, Kai, 2004. "Long-term growth prospects in transition economies: a reappraisal." Structural Change and Economic Dynamics, Vol. 15(1).</p><p>North, D.G. and Weingast, B.R. (1989), "Constitutions and Commitment: The</p><p>Evolution of Institutions Governing Public Choice in Seventeenth-Century England", <hi rend="italic">Journal of Economic History</hi>. </p><p>Knack, S, and Keefer, P. (1997) "Does social capital have an economic payoff?" <hi rend="underlined">Quarterly Journal of Economics</hi>.</p><p>Sachs, J.D. and Warner, A.M. 1995. "Natural Resource Abundance and Economic Growth". <hi rend="underlined">Harvard Institute for International Development.</hi></p><p>Redding, Stephen and Venables, Anthony. 2002. "The economics of isolation and distance". <hi rend="underlined">Nordic Journal of Political Economy</hi>, (Conference Issue), 28.</p></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
