<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_0141d" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Photosynthetic electron transport in isolated chloroplasts using the oxygen electrode</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">footer: page numbers</note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">appendix: calculations, data tables and graphs
</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">2</p><p n="date">2004-02</p><p n="module title">Biochemistry Laboratories and Assessed Work</p><p n="module code">BS240</p><p n="genre family">Methodology recount</p><p n="discipline">Biological Sciences</p><p n="disciplinary group">LS</p><p n="grade">D</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">1443</p><p n="number of s-units">73</p><p n="number of p">30</p><p n="number of tables">2</p><p n="number of figures">2</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">2</p><p n="number of lists">0</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">0</p><p n="abstract present">abstract present</p><p n="average words per s-unit">19.8</p><p n="average s-units per p">2.4</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">f</p><p n="year of birth">1984</p><p n="first language">English</p><p n="education">OSA</p><p n="course">Biochemistry</p><p n="student ID">0141</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><titlePart>09.02.2004<name type="student name"/> Lab partner: <name type="student name"/></titlePart><docTitle><titlePart><hi rend="underlined">Bioenergetics Experiment 1.</hi> <hi rend="underlined">Photosynthetic electron transport in isolated chloroplasts using the</hi> <hi rend="underlined"> oxygen electrode</hi></titlePart></docTitle></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="abstract"><head>Abstract:</head><p n="p1.30"><s n="s1.9;p1.30">The aim of this experiment was to obtain measurements of photosynthetic activity in isolated chloroplasts using an oxygen electrode. </s><s n="s2.9;p1.30">Oxygen evolution was measured for samples in various conditions and then the rate of oxygen evolution was calculated. </s><s n="s3.9;p1.30">The rate of oxygen evolution in control conditions was determined to be 62.2μmol of O <hi rend="sub">2</hi> / mg chlorophyll / hour. </s><s n="s4.9;p1.30">It was discovered that when in presence of DCMU there was no evolution of oxygen. </s><s n="s5.9;p1.30">Upon addition of ADP with potassium phosphate, the rate increased to 117μmol of O <hi rend="sub">2</hi> / mg chlorophyll / hour. </s><s n="s6.9;p1.30">However, without a source of phosphate the rate remained the same as the control. </s><s n="s7.9;p1.30">A limiting amount of ferricyanide also revealed to keep the rate of oxygen evolution constant. </s><s n="s8.9;p1.30">Upon addition of ammonium chloride rate increased over three fold, and subsequent addition of ADP did not change the value of 206μmol of O <hi rend="sub">2</hi> / mg chlorophyll / hour. </s><s n="s9.9;p1.30">Finally with double the concentration of chlorophyll, rate calculated as μmol of O <hi rend="sub">2</hi> / hour also doubled. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head>Introduction:</head><p n="p2.30"><s n="s1.3;p2.30">This experiment was concerned with the electron transport chain of pea seedling photosynthesis and its relationship to ATP synthesis. </s><s n="s2.3;p2.30">The "light reaction" of photosynthesis (photophosphorylation) was studied in osmotically shocked chloroplasts so that hydrophilic reagents such as electron acceptors have access to the thylakoid membrane. </s><s n="s3.3;p2.30">Then CO <hi rend="sub">2</hi> fixation (also known as the "dark reaction") was driven by electron transport and photophosphorylation. </s></p><p n="p3.30"><s n="s1.7;p3.30">The electrode used consists of a platinum cathode and silver anodes. </s><s n="s2.7;p3.30">A thin membrane is stretched over the electrode which separates the electrode elements bathed in an electrolyte of saturated KCl from the reaction solution in the sample chamber. </s><s n="s3.7;p3.30">The membrane is permeable to gases including oxygen which then can come into contact with the surface of the platinum cathode. </s><s n="s4.7;p3.30">If a voltage of about 0.6V is applied across the cell, oxygen is reduced at the cathode. </s><s n="s5.7;p3.30">Hence the current flowing through the electrode system is directly proportional to the amount of oxygen passing through the membrane. </s><s n="s6.7;p3.30">According to the laws of diffusion, the rate of oxygen flowing through the membrane depends on the concentration of dissolved oxygen in sample. </s><s n="s7.7;p3.30">Therefore the extent of the current flow in the electrode is directly related to the concentration of dissolved oxygen. </s></p><p n="p4.30"><s n="s1.3;p4.30">Hill reaction was demonstrated using the oxygen electrode with potassium ferricyanide as the Hill oxidant. </s><s n="s2.3;p4.30">In the 1930s, Robin Hill demonstrated that the light reaction of photosynthesis is an electron transfer reaction by showing that isolated chloroplasts will evolve oxygen in the light as long as it is provided with a suitable electron acceptor, known as a Hill oxidant. </s><s n="s3.3;p4.30">The oxygen evolved in photosynthesis comes from the oxidation of water, which is coupled to the reduction of the Hill oxidant (A). </s></p><p n="p5.30"><s n="s1.2;p5.30">Photosynthetic phosphorylation is direct synthesis of ATP coupled to electron transport, and non-cyclic photophosphorylation is ATP synthesis driven by non-cyclic electron transport like that involved in the Hill reaction. </s><s n="s2.2;p5.30">Cyclic photophosphorylation is driven by cyclic electron transport and no net oxidation reduction or oxygen evolution occurs. </s></p><p n="p6.30"><s n="s1.1;p6.30">Below show the differences between cyclic and non-cyclic phosphorylation </s></p><div2><head><hi rend="underlined">Cyclic phosphorylation</hi> : </head><p n="p7.30"><s n="s1.1;p7.30"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0141d-form.001"/> </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">Non-cyclic phosphorylation:</head><p n="p8.30"><s n="s1.1;p8.30"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0141d-form.002"/> </s></p><p n="p9.30"><s n="s1.2;p9.30">The value of n, the P:2e- or P:O ratio, is a still debated topic. </s><s n="s2.2;p9.30">However, it is usually said that if n &lt; 1.5, then not enough ATP per molecule of NADPH will be made by non-cyclic photophosphorylation alone to satisfy demands of the Calvin cycle, and hence cyclic phosphorylation would need to compensate. </s></p><p n="p10.30"><s n="s1.1;p10.30">(All above information from the laboratory manual) </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head>Method:</head><p n="p11.30"><s n="s1.2;p11.30">The method described in the laboratory manual was followed. </s><s n="s2.2;p11.30">No changes were made to the set procedure. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head>Results:</head><p n="p12.30"><s n="s1.1;p12.30">Raw data and calculations can be found in the appendix (p.6~9) </s></p><p n="p13.30"><s n="s1.1;p13.30">The table below shows the various conditions studied and the values obtained for the rate of oxygen evolution. </s></p><table id="BAWE_0141d-tab.001"><head><hi rend="underlined">Table 1.</hi> <hi rend="underlined">Effect of different conditions on the rate of oxygen evolution in isolated chloroplasts.</hi> </head><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p14.30"><s n="s1.1;p14.30">As can be seen from the results above, when DCMU, a herbicide, is added, there is no evolution of oxygen. </s></p><p n="p15.30"><s n="s1.3;p15.30">When ADP and potassium phosphate is added in the reaction medium, the rate of oxygen evolution increases. </s><s n="s2.3;p15.30">The increase is almost double the value obtained in the control when 30μl of 20mM ADP is added. </s><s n="s3.3;p15.30">However, when ADP alone is added without a source of phosphate, there is no change in rate. </s></p><p n="p16.30"><s n="s1.2;p16.30">Addition of ammonium chloride, an uncoupler, also has the effect of increasing the rate, by over three times when 30μl of 0.5M ammonium chloride is added. </s><s n="s2.2;p16.30">When ADP is added subsequently, there is no change observed, the rate remains very high. </s></p><p n="p17.30"><s n="s1.2;p17.30">Limiting amounts of ferricyanide appears to have no effect in changing the rate of oxygen evolution. </s><s n="s2.2;p17.30">This could be used to confirm the calibration of the electrode, as shown in the appendix on page 7. </s></p><p n="p18.30"><s n="s1.2;p18.30">Doubling the amount of chlorophyll in the reaction sample has no effect in the rate of oxygen evolution because the units used are μmol of O <hi rend="sub">2</hi> / mg chlorophyll / hour. </s><s n="s2.2;p18.30">However, calculating the rate of oxygen evolution as μmol of O <hi rend="sub">2</hi> / hour shows the following: </s></p><table id="BAWE_0141d-tab.002"><head><hi rend="underlined">Table 2.</hi> <hi rend="underlined">Effect of doubling the chlorophyll concentration</hi></head><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p19.30"><s n="s1.2;p19.30">This shows that the rate of oxygen evolution doubles when the concentration of chlorophyll doubles. </s><s n="s2.2;p19.30">Hence the concentration of chlorophyll and rate of oxygen evolution are directly proportional. </s></p><p n="p20.30"><s n="s1.1;p20.30">Possible reasons for the outcome of these experiments will now be discussed in the next section. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head>Discussion: </head><div2><head rend="underlined">In the presence of DCMU</head><p n="p21.30"><s n="s1.4;p21.30">With the addition of DCMU, the evolution of oxygen stops. </s><s n="s2.4;p21.30">This is because DCMU is a herbicide which acts as an electron transport inhibitor between the two plastoquinone molecules Q <hi rend="sub">A</hi> and Q <hi rend="sub">B</hi> on the acceptor side of the reaction centre of photosystem II. However, because an artificial electron acceptor, ferricyanide is present, DCMU should not have any effect. </s><s n="s3.4;p21.30">This does not agree with the results obtained. </s><s n="s4.4;p21.30">Possibly at the point DCMU was added, there were no unreduced ferricyanide left. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">With the addition of ADP, with and without potassium phosphate</head><p n="p22.30"><s n="s1.6;p22.30">Addition of ADP with a source of phosphate was demonstrated to produce an increase in the rate of oxygen evolution. </s><s n="s2.6;p22.30">Prior to the addition of ADP and the phosphate, there is a build up of protons in the thylakoid lumen. </s><s n="s3.6;p22.30">Once ADP and phosphate are added ATP synthase can begin to produce ATP using the proton motive force. </s><s n="s4.6;p22.30">As protons are used up, the rate of electron transport will increase to maintain the proton gradient, and thus increasing the rate of oxygen production as a consequence. </s><s n="s5.6;p22.30">Usually, the electron transport will slow down with the accumulation of protons. </s><s n="s6.6;p22.30">Nevertheless, the rate will return to the initial value after the ADP is used up. </s></p><p n="p23.30"><s n="s1.2;p23.30">The value of n, the P:2e- or P:O ratio, was calculated to be 3.22. </s><s n="s2.2;p23.30">Because it is greater than 1.5, there is enough ATP per molecule of NADPH made by non cyclic photophosphorylation alone to satisfy demands of the Calvin cycle. </s></p><p n="p24.30"><s n="s1.1;p24.30">However, with no potassium phosphate, the rate of oxygen evolution was shown not to change after the addition of ADP. This is because phosphate is necessary as well as ADP to produce ATP by proton motive force driven ATP synthase. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0141d-fig.001"><head><hi rend="underlined">Figure 2.</hi> <hi rend="underlined">Simple schematic diagram of the light reaction of photosynthesis.</hi> </head></figure><p n="p25.30"><s n="s1.1;p25.30">In the case of the Hill reaction, electrons flow through photosystem II directly to ferricyanide. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">With the addition of ammonium chloride</head><p n="p26.30"><s n="s1.5;p26.30">Upon addition of ammonium chloride, there is an approximately 3 fold increase in the rate of oxygen evolution. </s><s n="s2.5;p26.30">Ammonium chloride, an uncoupler, has the effect of "mopping" up protons. </s><s n="s3.5;p26.30">As a consequence, electron transport does not slow down as there is no accumulation of protons. </s><s n="s4.5;p26.30">Hence, the rate of oxygen evolution increases. </s><s n="s5.5;p26.30">The diagram below (Figure 1.) describes the effect of ammonium chloride schematically. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0141d-fig.002"><head><hi rend="underlined">Figure 1.</hi> <hi rend="underlined">Effect of ammonium chloride.</hi> </head></figure><p n="p27.30"><s n="s1.1;p27.30">O <hi rend="sub">2</hi> evolution remains at 206 μmol of O <hi rend="sub">2</hi> / mg chlorophyll / hour after addition of ADP. This is because electron transport is probably occurring at the maximum and so the rate of oxygen evolution is also at the highest and will remain the same too. </s></p><p n="p28.30"><s n="s1.1;p28.30">What effect has ammonium chloride had on the P/2e- ratio? </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">With limiting amounts of ferricyanide</head><p n="p29.30"><s n="s1.3;p29.30">Limiting amounts of ferricyanide appears to have no effect in changing the rate of oxygen evolution. </s><s n="s2.3;p29.30">This is probably because the endogenous electron acceptors are still present and are able to be oxidised just like the Hill oxidant, ferricyanide. </s><s n="s3.3;p29.30">Hence photophosphorylation continues and oxygen is evolved. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">With double the concentration of chlorophyll</head><p n="p30.30"><s n="s1.2;p30.30">Calculating the rate of oxygen evolution as μmol of O <hi rend="sub">2</hi> / hour shows that the rate of oxygen evolution doubles when the concentration of chlorophyll doubles. </s><s n="s2.2;p30.30">The concentration of chlorophyll and rate of oxygen evolution are directly proportional, because with more chlorophyll, the more electron transport can occur. </s></p></div2></div1></body><back><div1 type="appendix"><head rend="underlined">Appendix</head><p/></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
