<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_0141a" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Compare and contrast electron transport in respiration by mitochondria and bacteria, illustrating the diversity of the bacterial respiration system.</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">footer: page numbers</note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">deleted: Word count: 2571
</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">1</p><p n="date">2003-04</p><p n="module title">Biochemistry Laboratories and Assessed Work</p><p n="module code">BS120</p><p n="genre family">Explanation</p><p n="discipline">Biological Sciences</p><p n="disciplinary group">LS</p><p n="grade">M</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">2764</p><p n="number of s-units">143</p><p n="number of p">25</p><p n="number of tables">0</p><p n="number of figures">10</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">0</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">3</p><p n="abstract present">abstract present</p><p n="average words per s-unit">19.3</p><p n="average s-units per p">5.7</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">f</p><p n="year of birth">1984</p><p n="first language">English</p><p n="education">OSA</p><p n="course">Biochemistry</p><p n="student ID">0141</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><titlePart><name type="student ID"/></titlePart><docTitle><titlePart rend="italic">Compare and contrast electron transport in respiration by mitochondria and bacteria, illustrating the diversity of the bacterial respiration system. </titlePart></docTitle><titlePart rend="underlined">Similarities and differences of electron transport in respiration by mitochondria and bacteria</titlePart></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="abstract"><head rend="underlined">Abstract</head><p n="p1.25"><s n="s1.3;p1.25">This paper describes and compares electron transport by mitochondria in eukaryotes with electron transport by various different bacteria. </s><s n="s2.3;p1.25">From studying these various forms of electron transport in respiration, it was concluded that electron transport in bacteria and in mitochondria are similar in the following respects: the electron carriers are arranged in an order of increasingly more positive reduction potential and the energy released in electron transport is utilised to generate a proton motive force, used to synthesise ATP. </s><s n="s3.3;p1.25">(Madiganal. 126-127) However, differences are present in the numbers and types of electron carriers used and likewise the complexes pumping protons. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined">Introduction</head><p n="p2.25"><s n="s1.5;p2.25">The electron transport in respiration is a process by which electrons are transferred from an electron donor, such as NADH, to an electron acceptor, for example oxygen, through a sequence of membrane-associated electron carriers. </s><s n="s2.5;p2.25">This transfer releases energy, allowing for the pumping of protons across the cell membrane, creating an electrochemical gradient. </s><s n="s3.5;p2.25">The resulting proton motive force allows for the synthesis of ATP from ADP and inorganic phosphate. </s><s n="s4.5;p2.25">Although details such as electron carriers used differ, this general process is present in all eukaryotes and prokaryotes as a form of producing ATP. For example, bacteria that have electron transport chains very similar to mitochondria's include <hi rend="italic">Rickettsia</hi> <hi rend="italic">prowazekii</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Paracoccus</hi> <hi rend="italic">denitrificans</hi>. </s><s n="s5.5;p2.25">As will be subsequently described, the former is considered to be descendant of the bacterium that was incorporated into the eukaryotic cell, now a mitochondrion. </s></p><p n="p3.25"><s n="s1.3;p3.25">Bacteria that have electron transport chains less similar to the mitochondrial electron transport chain, for example those using different electron donors including hydrogen oxidising bacteria and sulfur oxidising bacteria, are also considered in this essay among others. </s><s n="s2.3;p3.25">In addition, anaerobic respiration in bacteria, with nitrate and sulfur as a final electron acceptors are also described, including comparison with the electron transport chain in mitochondria. </s><s n="s3.3;p3.25">Finally, a bacterium that does not use an electron transport chain is briefly described to illustrate the diversity found in the bacterial respiration system and that an electron transport chain is not essential for ATP synthesis. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined">Eukaryotes, <hi rend="italic">Rickettsia</hi> <hi rend="italic">prowazekii</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Paracoccus</hi> <hi rend="italic">denitrificans</hi></head><p n="p4.25"><s n="s1.6;p4.25">In Eukaryotes, electron transport occurs within large proteins present in the inner mitochondrial membrane. </s><s n="s2.6;p4.25">Electrons are transported by these protein complexes from NADH (or FADH <hi rend="sub">2</hi>) to oxygen, the final electron acceptor in aerobic respiration. </s><s n="s3.6;p4.25">NADH is a high energy molecule due to the high transfer potential of electrons, produced by carbon fuels oxidised in the Krebs cycle. </s><s n="s4.6;p4.25">This electron motive force is converted into a proton motive force by three electron driven proton pumps in the inner mitochondrial membrane: NADH-Q oxidoreductase, Q-cytochrome c oxidoreductase and cytochrome c oxidase. </s><s n="s5.6;p4.25">These protein complexes contain several redox centres, including quinones, flavins, iron-sulfur clusters, hemes and copper ions. </s><s n="s6.6;p4.25">(Bergal. 492) </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0141a-pic.001"><head>Fig. 1 Typical electron transport chain Electron transport chains and their relation to reduction potential.</head></figure><p n="p5.25"><s n="s1.11;p5.25">Fig. </s><s n="s2.11;p5.25">1 on the left shows the electron transport system where electrons are transferred from substrates to oxygen. </s><s n="s3.11;p5.25">This is a scheme typical of mitochondria. </s><s n="s4.11;p5.25">In addition to the three proton pumps mentioned above, the mitochondrial electron transport chain consists of another complex called succinate-Q reductase, which links the transport chain to the Krebs cycle. </s><s n="s5.11;p5.25">Fig. </s><s n="s6.11;p5.25">2 on the right represents the membrane, showing the location of these key electron carriers, whose redox centres are outlined in Fig. </s><s n="s7.11;p5.25">1. </s><s n="s8.11;p5.25">(Madiganal. 127) Fig. </s><s n="s9.11;p5.25">2 is a diagram of the membrane of <hi rend="italic">Paracoccus denitrificans</hi>, but it could be likewise the inner membrane of the mitochondria. </s><s n="s10.11;p5.25">A mitochondrion and this bacterium contain the same transporter protein because the mitochondrion was originally a free-living bacterium, which was incorporated into the cell by an endosymbiotic event. </s><s n="s11.11;p5.25">(Bergal. 492) The bacterium that is said to be the most closely related to mitochondria is <hi rend="italic">Rickettsia</hi> <hi rend="italic">prowazekii</hi>. </s></p><p n="p6.25"><s n="s1.4;p6.25">Analysis of the genes in the bacterium in contrast with the mitochondrion's has allowed for this conclusion to be reached. (<hi rend="italic">Nature</hi>, 1998) </s><s n="s2.4;p6.25">Hence, <hi rend="italic">R. prowazekii</hi> also has the same electron carriers as mitochondria. </s><s n="s3.4;p6.25">The only obvious difference between them is that in the mitochondrion hydrogen ions are pumped into the intermembrane space, whereas in the bacterium protons are pumped into the environment. </s><s n="s4.4;p6.25">The second membrane around mitochondria appeared when the ancestor of the bacterium <hi rend="italic">R. prowazekii</hi> was engulfed by the eukaryotic cell. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0141a-pic.002"><head>Fig. 2 Electron transport chain of <hi rend="italic">Paracoccus</hi> <hi rend="italic">denitrificans</hi> . Complex I: NADH-Q oxidoreductase, complex III: Q-cytochrome c oxidoreductase, complex IV: cytochrome c oxidase. FMN: flavoprotein, Q: quinone, Cyt: cytochrome. (Complex II: succinate-Q reductase is not included in the scheme for simplicity.)</head></figure><p n="p7.25"><s n="s1.4;p7.25">Although the electron transport chain of these two bacteria show close similarities to that of the mitochondria, many other bacteria have different electron transport chains. </s><s n="s2.4;p7.25">While the basic mechanism, in which a proton motive force is obtained leading to the synthesis of ATP is very similar, the numbers and types of electron carriers involved are different. </s><s n="s3.4;p7.25">For example, in <hi rend="italic">Escherichia coli</hi>, cytochromes c and aa <hi rend="sub">3</hi> are not present and the electrons instead go directly from cytochrome b to o or d. </s><s n="s4.4;p7.25">(Madiganal. 126) </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined">Hydrogen Oxidation</head><p n="p8.25"><s n="s1.12;p8.25">Chemolithotrophs are organisms that use inorganic electron donors. </s><s n="s2.12;p8.25">A number of these organisms use hydrogen as an electron donor. </s><s n="s3.12;p8.25">In aerobic hydrogen oxidising bacteria, hydrogen is oxidised by oxygen, a reaction catalysed by an enzyme called hydrogenase. </s><s n="s4.12;p8.25">Electrons are transferred from hydrogen to a quinone acceptor and then through a sequence of cytochromes until ultimately oxygen is reduced to water. </s><s n="s5.12;p8.25">As in all electron transport chains, this process results with the formation of a proton motive force. </s><s n="s6.12;p8.25">Fig. </s><s n="s7.12;p8.25">3 illustrates the electron transport chain of a hydrogen oxidising bacteria, such as <hi rend="italic">Ralstonia</hi> <hi rend="italic">eutropha</hi> that contain two hydrogenases. </s><s n="s8.12;p8.25">As can be seen in the diagram, one hydrogenase is membrane associated and the other is soluble. </s><s n="s9.12;p8.25">The membrane bound hydrogenase is the one that is involved in electron transport. </s><s n="s10.12;p8.25">(Madiganal. 568) Unlike the electron transport chain in mitochondria, it is a H <hi rend="sub">2</hi> molecule that is immediately involved in the electron transport chain, not carried by NAD+. </s><s n="s11.12;p8.25">Also, the chain in hydrogen oxidising bacteria lack flavoproteins and iron-sulfur proteins. </s><s n="s12.12;p8.25">However, the general structure and mechanism by which the proton motive force is reached is remarkably similar to the mitochondria's. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0141a-pic.003"><head>Fig. 3 Electron transport chain of <hi rend="italic">Ralstonia eutropha</hi> . The membrane associated hydrogenase is involved in the electron transport chain. The cytoplasmic hydrogenase makes NADH for the Calvin cycle. H <hi rend="sub">2</hi> ase: hydrogenase, Q: quinone, Cyt: cytochrome.</head></figure></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined">Oxidation of Reduced Sulfur Compounds</head><p n="p9.25"><s n="s1.8;p9.25">Reduced sulfur compounds can also be used as electron donors. </s><s n="s2.8;p9.25">Most common of these are hydrogen sulfide, elemental sulfur and thiosulfate. </s><s n="s3.8;p9.25">The diagram overleaf, Fig. </s><s n="s4.8;p9.25">4, describes an electron transport chain of a sulfur oxidising bacteria. </s><s n="s5.8;p9.25">Electrons from sulfur compounds enter the electron transport chain at flavoprotein, which then flow to quinone, cytochrome b, cytochrome c, cytochrome aa <hi rend="sub">3</hi> and then to the final electron acceptor, oxygen. </s><s n="s6.8;p9.25">H+ is pumped out of the cell at two points of the chain, at the quinone and cytochrome aa <hi rend="sub">3</hi>. </s><s n="s7.8;p9.25">If the electron donor used is thiosulfate or elemental sulfur, electrons enter the chain at cytochrome c. </s><s n="s8.8;p9.25">(Madiganal. 570) Again, like the electron transport chain of the hydrogen oxidising bacteria, an iron-sulfur protein is missing, compared to the mitochondrial electron transport chain. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0141a-pic.004"><head>Fig. 4 Electron transport chain of a sulfur oxidising bacteria. FP: flavoprotein, Q: quinone, Cyt: cytochrome.</head></figure></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined">Iron oxidation</head><p n="p10.25"><s n="s1.4;p10.25">Aerobic oxidation of iron from ferrous (Fe <hi rend="sup">2+</hi>) to ferric (Fe <hi rend="sup">3+</hi>) state is made use in a few bacteria such as <hi rend="italic">Thiobacillus ferrooxidans</hi>. </s><s n="s2.4;p10.25">The respiratory chain of <hi rend="italic">T. ferrooxidans</hi> contains cytochrome c and cytochrome a and a periplasmic protein containing copper, called rusticyanin. </s><s n="s3.4;p10.25">(Madiganal. 572) In the transport chain, the ferrous iron is oxidised to Fe <hi rend="sup">3+</hi> by rusticyanin. </s><s n="s4.4;p10.25">The electron is then transferred to cytochrome c and subsequently cytochrome a is reduced. </s></p><p n="p11.25"><s n="s1.6;p11.25">Since respiration is aerobic, the final electron acceptor is again oxygen, which is reduced to water when it accepts the two electrons from cytochrome a. </s><s n="s2.6;p11.25">Again the key cytochromes, c and a, are present as shown in Fig. </s><s n="s3.6;p11.25">5. </s><s n="s4.6;p11.25">Compared with electron transport in mitochondria, and the transport chains studied thus far, quinone is not present. </s><s n="s5.6;p11.25">Also, flavoproteins are missing. </s><s n="s6.6;p11.25">Both iron oxidising bacteria and sulfur oxidising bacteria do not contain any iron-sulfur proteins since these elements are used as electron donors and the electron transporters should be present in increasing reduction potential. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0141a-pic.005"><head>Fig. 5 Electron transport chain of <hi rend="italic">Thiobacillus ferrooxidans</hi> . Rusticyanin is the immediate electron acceptor from Fe <hi rend="sup">2+</hi> . Cyt: cytochrome.</head></figure></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined">Ammonia and nitrite oxidation</head><figure id="BAWE_0141a-pic.006"><head>Fig. 6 Electron transport chain of an ammonia oxidising bacteria. AMO: ammonia monooxygenase, HAO: hydroxlamine oxidoreductase</head></figure><p n="p12.25"><s n="s1.18;p12.25">Some bacteria use inorganic nitrogen compounds such as ammonia and nitrite as electron donors. </s><s n="s2.18;p12.25">These compounds are oxidised aerobically by chemolithotrophic nitrifying bacteria. </s><s n="s3.18;p12.25">These bacteria can be classified roughly in two groups: one oxidising NH <hi rend="sub">3</hi> to NO <hi rend="sub">2</hi>- and the other oxidising NO <hi rend="sub">2</hi>- to NO <hi rend="sub">3</hi>-. </s><s n="s4.18;p12.25">Fig. </s><s n="s5.18;p12.25">6 shows an electron transport chain of an ammonia oxidising bacteria. </s><s n="s6.18;p12.25">First, ammonia is oxidised by ammonia monooxygenase (AMO), producing hydroxylamine (NH <hi rend="sub">2</hi>OH) and water. </s><s n="s7.18;p12.25">Then another enzyme called hydroxylamine oxidoreductase (HAO) oxidises NH <hi rend="sub">2</hi>OH to NO <hi rend="sub">2</hi>-, removing four electrons. </s><s n="s8.18;p12.25">Two of these electrons and two protons are used to reduce one atom of oxygen into water. </s><s n="s9.18;p12.25">As shown in the diagram (Fig. </s><s n="s10.18;p12.25">6), two electrons from oxidation of NH <hi rend="sub">2</hi>OH are transferred from HAO to AMO through cytochrome c and ubiquinone (Q). </s><s n="s11.18;p12.25">Therefore, only two of the four electrons produced form the oxidation of ammonia to nitrite reaches cytochrome aa <hi rend="sub">3</hi>, the last electron transporter in the chain. </s><s n="s12.18;p12.25">So the differences of this electron transport chain from that of the mitochondria are as follows: there are no flavoproteins or iron-sulfur proteins present, and NAD+ is not used an electron donor. </s><s n="s13.18;p12.25">There are also two types of cytochrome c, one in the membrane and the other in the periplasm, whereas in the mitochondrial electron transport there is cytochrome bc <hi rend="sub">1</hi>, which is membrane associated. </s><s n="s14.18;p12.25">Nitrite oxidising bacteria, however, use an enzyme called nitrite oxidoreductase (NOR in Fig. </s><s n="s15.18;p12.25">7) to oxidise NH <hi rend="sub">2</hi>- to NH <hi rend="sub">3</hi>-. </s><s n="s16.18;p12.25">This electron transport chain is much simpler compared to that of the ammonia oxidising bacteria. </s><s n="s17.18;p12.25">Electrons are transferred to cytochrome c and then to cytochrome aa <hi rend="sub">3</hi> and finally oxygen, the terminal electron acceptor, is reduced. </s><s n="s18.18;p12.25">(Madiganal. 574) </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0141a-pic.007"><head>Fig. 7 Electron transport chain of a nitrite oxidising bacteria. (NOR: nitrite oxidoreductase)</head></figure></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined">Anaerobic respiration:</head><div2><head rend="underlined">Nitrate as a final electron acceptor</head><p n="p13.25"><s n="s1.11;p13.25">In anaerobic respiration, a final electron acceptor other than oxygen is used. </s><s n="s2.11;p13.25">Common electron acceptors in anaerobic respiration are inorganic nitrogen compounds. </s><s n="s3.11;p13.25">The case considered below (Fig. </s><s n="s4.11;p13.25">8(b)) is NO <hi rend="sub">3</hi>- as an electron acceptor in <hi rend="italic">Escherichia coli</hi>. </s><s n="s5.11;p13.25">On the right, Fig. </s><s n="s6.11;p13.25">8(a), aerobic respiration is shown for comparison. </s><s n="s7.11;p13.25">In both cases, NADH+H+ donates two electrons, which is transferred to flavoprotein (Fp). </s><s n="s8.11;p13.25">At this point two protons are pumped out of the cell. </s><s n="s9.11;p13.25">Next, electrons are transferred to an iron-sulfur protein, which is subsequently oxidised by ubiquinone (Q). </s><s n="s10.11;p13.25">Again H+ is pumped out of the cell. </s><s n="s11.11;p13.25">Thus far electron transporters involved in both anaerobic and aerobic respiration in <hi rend="italic">E. coli</hi> are the same as those found in the mitochondria. </s></p><p n="p14.25"><s n="s1.5;p14.25">However, in anaerobic respiration of <hi rend="italic">E. coli</hi>, the two electrons are then transferred from ubiquinone to cytochrome b <hi rend="sub">556</hi>. </s><s n="s2.5;p14.25">Subsequently, an enzyme called nitrate reductase accepts electrons from cytochrome b <hi rend="sub">556</hi>. </s><s n="s3.5;p14.25">The final step is the reduction of NO <hi rend="sub">3</hi>- to NO <hi rend="sub">2</hi>-. </s><s n="s4.5;p14.25">However, in the aerobic respiration of <hi rend="italic">E. coli</hi>, there are two cytochrome bs involved, cyt b <hi rend="sub">556</hi> and cyt b <hi rend="sub">562</hi>. </s><s n="s5.5;p14.25">The electrons are then transferred to cytochrome o, one that is not present in anaerobic respiration in <hi rend="italic">E. coli</hi> or in the electron transport chain in the mitochondria. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0141a-pic.008"><head>Fig. 8 Aerobic (a) and anaerobic (b) respiration in <hi rend="italic">Escherichia coli</hi> . Fp: Flavoprotein, Q: quinone, Cyt: cytochrome</head></figure><p n="p15.25"><s rend="underlined" n="s1.1;p15.25">Sulfate as a final electron acceptor </s></p><p n="p16.25"><s n="s1.18;p16.25">Another common electron acceptor used in bacteria respiring anaerobically are inorganic sulfur compounds. </s><s n="s2.18;p16.25">Of these the most common is sulfate, like the final electron acceptor in the electron transport chain overleaf. </s><s n="s3.18;p16.25">(Fig. </s><s n="s4.18;p16.25">9) The difference of this electron transport chain from the ones studied so far is that a membrane associated protein called Hmc is present. </s><s n="s5.18;p16.25">This protein complex transfers electrons from hydrogenase across the cell membrane. </s><s n="s6.18;p16.25">The electron transport system considered in Fig. </s><s n="s7.18;p16.25">9 uses an organic compound, lactate, as an electron donor. </s><s n="s8.18;p16.25">Lactate is converted into pyruvate, by LDH, whereby 2H are transported across to hydrogenase. </s><s n="s9.18;p16.25">This is the single point at which H+ are produced to generate a proton motive force. </s><s n="s10.18;p16.25">Then electrons are transferred to cytochrome c <hi rend="sub">3</hi> and then Hmc, a cytochrome complex which, as mentioned previously, transports electrons across the membrane to the iron-sulfur protein. </s><s n="s11.18;p16.25">Finally the electrons are accepted by a sulfite to produce sulfide. </s><s n="s12.18;p16.25">Looking at Fig. </s><s n="s13.18;p16.25">9, it seems that sulfate is not directly involved and APS is accepting the two electrons from the iron-sulfur protein. </s><s n="s14.18;p16.25">What actually is happens is ATP gains a sulfur moiety along with the loss of two phosphates. </s><s n="s15.18;p16.25">Then with the gain of two electrons AMP and sulfite is produced. </s><s n="s16.18;p16.25">The next six electrons from the iron-sulfur protein reduces sulfite to sulfide. </s><s n="s17.18;p16.25">(Madiganal. 580) Apart from the iron-sulfur protein and a cytochrome c, this electron transport chain comprise of electron carriers that are not present in mitochondrial electron transport. </s><s n="s18.18;p16.25">Also, hydrogen ions are only pumped out by a hydrogenase in this sulfate reducing bacteria, unlike mitochondria which has three proton pumps. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0141a-pic.009"><head>Fig. 9 Anaerobic respiration in a sulfate reducing bacteria. Hmc: cytochrome complex, APS: adenosine 5'-phosphosulfate, LDH: lactate dehydrogenase.</head></figure></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">ATP production without electron transport</head><p n="p17.25"><s n="s1.3;p17.25">An unusual fermentation is carried out by <hi rend="italic">Propionigenium modestum</hi>, a bacterium that ferments succinate. </s><s n="s2.3;p17.25">This bacterium is very specialised to fermenting its particular substrate, and only a very restricted group carry it out. </s><s n="s3.3;p17.25">It is interesting to compare the process of ATP formation of <hi rend="italic">P. modestum</hi> with that of the mitochondria, since due to such specialisation, it is expected that it will be very different. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0141a-pic.010"><head>Fig. 10 ATP production in <hi rend="italic">Propionigenium</hi> <hi rend="italic">modestum</hi> .<hi rend="italic">Propionigenium modestum</hi> is a bacterium that does not use an electron transport chain to obtain an electrochemical gradient for ATP synthesis.</head></figure><p n="p18.25"><s n="s1.7;p18.25">As expected, the process of ATP formation is completely unlike the mitochondria's. </s><s n="s2.7;p18.25">What is surprising is that not even electron transport occurs. </s><s n="s3.7;p18.25">However, ATP is formed like in mitochondria, due to an electrochemical gradient, although it is produced by sodium ions and not protons. </s><s n="s4.7;p18.25">Sodium ions are pumped out of the cell (Fig. </s><s n="s5.7;p18.25">10) using the energy produced by decarboxylating succinate. </s><s n="s6.7;p18.25">This then creates an accumulation of sodium ions outside the cell, which can be used by the Na+ ATPase to form ATP. </s><s n="s7.7;p18.25">(Madiganal. 594) Hence due to specialisation, this bacterium can be so different from mitochondria and other common bacteria to have no electron transport chain. </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined">Conclusion</head><p n="p19.25"><s n="s1.1;p19.25">Although only a fraction of bacteria have been considered in this essay, it has allowed for the diversity of processes which exist to produce ATP to be illustrated, from bacteria that have electron transport chains very similar to mitochondrial electron transport such as in <hi rend="italic">R. prowazekii</hi> and <hi rend="italic">P. denitrificans</hi> to those that have a very different electron transport chain, such as a sulfur reducing bacterium. </s></p><p n="p20.25"><s n="s1.1;p20.25">According to <hi rend="underlined">Brock's Biology of Microorganisms</hi>: "several features are characteristic of all electron transport chains and can be summarized as follows: </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p21.25"><s n="s1.1;p21.25">The presence of a series of membrane-associated electron carriers arranged in order of increasingly more positive E <hi rend="sub">0</hi>'. </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p22.25"><s n="s1.1;p22.25">An alternation in the chain of electron-only and hydrogen-atom only carriers </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p23.25"><s n="s1.2;p23.25">Generation of a proton motive force as a result of charge separation across the membrane, acidic outside and alkaline inside." </s><s n="s2.2;p23.25">(126~127) </s></p><p n="p24.25"><s n="s1.5;p24.25">However, if the few types electron transport chains studied in this essay are to be considered, it can be said that many of the bacterial electron transport chain have some common electron carriers with mitochondria. </s><s n="s2.5;p24.25">For example, flavoproteins are not only present in mitochondria but also in <hi rend="italic">E. coli</hi> and some hydrogen oxidising bacteria. </s><s n="s3.5;p24.25">Moreover, in <hi rend="italic">E. coli</hi>, iron sulfur proteins are also present. </s><s n="s4.5;p24.25">However, by far the most common electron transporter was cytochrome c. </s><s n="s5.5;p24.25">All the electron transport chains considered in this essay contained some form of a cytochrome. </s></p><p n="p25.25"><s n="s1.3;p25.25">It was surprising to discover that there is an organism that does not use an electron transport chain. </s><s n="s2.3;p25.25">The electron transport chain was possibly lost through evolution, where using a certain substrate meant that it was more efficient to use another method of ATP formation than the usual electron transport chain to produce a proton motive force. </s><s n="s3.3;p25.25">Nevertheless, the similarities of electron transport chain between all other bacteria suggest that the electron transport chain of the bacteria studied and indeed the mitochondria have a common lineage, but due to selective pressures, such as availability of various oxidation and reduction agents, certain changes have been favoured over others. </s></p></div1></body><back><div1 type="bibliography"><div2 type="bibliography"><head rend="underlined">Bibliography:</head><p>Andresson, Siv G.E., et al. "The genome sequence of <hi rend="italic">Rickettsia prowazekii</hi> and the</p><p>origin of mitochondria." <hi rend="underlined">Nature</hi> Nov. 1998: 133-140. &lt;<seg type="URL" n="http://www.nature"/>.</p><p>com/genomics/papers/r_prowazekii.html></p><p>Berg, Jeremy M., John L.Tymoczko, and Lubert Stryer. <hi rend="underlined">Biochemistry</hi>. 5th ed. New </p><p>York: W. H. Freeman and Company, 2002.</p><p>Lodish, Harvey, et al. <hi rend="underlined">Molecular Cell Biology</hi>. 4th ed. New York: W. H. Freeman </p><p> and Company, 2000.</p><p>Madigan, Michael T., John M. Martinko, and Jack Parker. <hi rend="underlined">Brock: Biology of</hi></p><p><hi rend="underlined">Microorganisms</hi>. 10th ed. New Jersey: Pearson Education, 2003.</p><p>"MICR 425: Physiology &amp; Biochemistry of Microorgansims: Electron Transport </p><p>Chain." Aug. 1999. SIUC, College of Science 10 April 2003 &lt;<seg type="URL" n="http://www.science.siu.edu/microbiology/micr425/425Notes/07-Respire.html"/>></p><p>Thain, Michael and Hickman, Michael. <hi rend="underlined">The Penguin Dictionary of Biology</hi>. 10th ed. </p><p> London: Penguin Group, 2000.</p></div2><div2 type="bibliography"><head rend="underlined">Diagrams used:</head><p>Fig. 1 (Madigan et al. p.126, Figure 5.19)</p><p>Fig. 2 (Madigan et al. p.127, Figure 5.20)</p><p>Fig. 3 (Madigan et al. p.568, Figure 17.25)</p><p>Fig. 4 (Madigan et al. p.570, Figure 17.27)</p><p>Fig. 5 (Madigan et al. p.572, Figure 17.30)</p><p>Fig. 6 (Madigan et al. p.574, Figure 17.32)</p><p>Fig. 7 (Madigan et al. p.574, Figure 17.33)</p><p>Fig. 8 (Madigan et al. p.578, Figure 17.37)</p><p>Fig. 9 (Madigan et al. p.581, Figure 17.39)</p><p>Fig. 10 (Madigan et al. p.594, Figure 17.52)</p></div2></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
