<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_0141b" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Properties of enzymes and the kinetics of enzyme action</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">footer: page numbers</note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">appendix: data tables
</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">1</p><p n="date">2003-02</p><p n="module title">Biochemistry Laboratories and Assessed Work</p><p n="module code">BS120</p><p n="genre family">Methodology recount</p><p n="discipline">Biological Sciences</p><p n="disciplinary group">LS</p><p n="grade">D</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">1378</p><p n="number of s-units">70</p><p n="number of p">22</p><p n="number of tables">0</p><p n="number of figures">6</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">2</p><p n="number of lists">0</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">0</p><p n="abstract present">abstract present</p><p n="average words per s-unit">19.7</p><p n="average s-units per p">3.2</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">f</p><p n="year of birth">1984</p><p n="first language">English</p><p n="education">OSA</p><p n="course">Biochemistry</p><p n="student ID">0141</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><titlePart>07.02.2003<name type="student name"/> Lab partner: <name type="student name"/></titlePart><docTitle><titlePart rend="underlined">Properties of enzymes and the kinetics of enzyme action</titlePart></docTitle></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="abstract"><head>Abstract:</head><p n="p1.22"><s n="s1.7;p1.22">This experiment involved studying the kinetics of the reaction catalysed by alkaline phosphatase. </s><s n="s2.7;p1.22">First, the responses of the enzyme to differing pH and temperature were examined. </s><s n="s3.7;p1.22">Optimum pH and temperature were determined to be 9.5 and 44°C respectively. </s><s n="s4.7;p1.22">Then, the Michaelis Menten constant was determined by plotting a Lineweaver Burk and Eadie Hofstee plot from the results obtained of enzyme action at differing substrate concentrations. </s><s n="s5.7;p1.22">K <hi rend="sub">M</hi> was calculated to be approximately 1mmoldm <hi rend="sup">-3</hi>. </s><s n="s6.7;p1.22">The product inhibition of alkaline phosphatase by inorganic phosphate was also examined, and it was established that the lowest phosphate concentration to produce marked change to enzyme activity was 20mmoldm <hi rend="sup">-3</hi>. </s><s n="s7.7;p1.22">This is much above the product produced in the other assays, ensuring that no product inhibition occurred during the rest of the experiment. </s></p><p n="p2.22"><s n="s1.1;p2.22">Finally the order of reaction was confirmed to be first order; the rate of the reaction catalysed by alkaline phosphatase is proportional to the concentration of p-nitrophenyl phosphate at concentrations where enzyme is not saturated with substrate. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head>Introduction:</head><p n="p3.22"><s n="s1.1;p3.22">The enzyme used in this experiment was alkaline phosphatase, catalysing the hydrolysis of p-nitrophenyl phosphate to p-nitrophenol and inorganic phosphate. </s></p><p n="p4.22"><s n="s1.1;p4.22"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0141b-form.001"/> </s></p><p n="p5.22"><s n="s1.2;p5.22">This reaction is particularly easy to assay due to the fact that the product of the reaction, p-nitrophenol is a coloured compound at low pH. This means that its concentration can be determined simply by measuring absorption at 410nm. </s><s n="s2.2;p5.22">The low pH is achieved by addition of a strong base, NaOH <hi rend="sub">(aq)</hi>, which also causes the denaturing of the enzyme, hence stopping the reaction at the required time. </s></p><p n="p6.22"><s n="s1.6;p6.22">For this first order enzyme catalysed reaction, at low substrate concentrations the rate of reaction is proportional to the concentration of the substrate. </s><s n="s2.6;p6.22">However, at higher concentrations the rate reaches a maximum, V <hi rend="sub">max</hi>. </s><s n="s3.6;p6.22">This is when the enzyme is saturated. </s><s n="s4.6;p6.22">The Michaelis-Menten constant (K <hi rend="sub">M</hi>), is the substrate concentration when the rate of reaction is ½ V <hi rend="sub">max</hi>. </s><s n="s5.6;p6.22">K <hi rend="sub">M</hi> is always the same for a particular enzyme with a particular substrate. </s><s n="s6.6;p6.22">Its value can be a useful to compare different enzymes catalysing the same reaction as it will indicate which enzyme can function efficiently at low substrate concentrations. (ie. the enzyme with lower K <hi rend="sub">M</hi> value) </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head>Method:</head><p n="p7.22"><s n="s1.6;p7.22">For the effects of pH and temperature on enzyme activity, the method in sections 11.4.2 of the laboratory manual was followed. </s><s n="s2.6;p7.22">For the determination of the Michaelis-Menten constant, the tubes were set up as shown in table 3. in the appendix (p.8). </s><s n="s3.6;p7.22">To each of these tubes, 1cm <hi rend="sup">3</hi> of buffer was added to make up 3cm <hi rend="sup">3</hi> volumes. </s><s n="s4.6;p7.22">The blank for the spectrophotometer was prepared by eliminating the substrate, but making sure to make up the 3cm <hi rend="sup">3</hi> volumes. </s><s n="s5.6;p7.22">The reaction was started by the addition of 1cm <hi rend="sup">3</hi> of the enzyme, alkaline phosphatase. </s><s n="s6.6;p7.22">Then the steps in 11.4.2 (ii), (iii) and (iv) were carried out. </s></p><p n="p8.22"><s n="s1.3;p8.22">The experiment analysing product inhibition of enzyme action required tubes with varying concentration of phosphate (Table 7., appendix p. 10) to be prepared. </s><s n="s2.3;p8.22">The blank for the spectrophotometer did not include any substrate. </s><s n="s3.3;p8.22">The reaction was started and terminated as explained in the laboratory manual. </s></p><p n="p9.22"><s n="s1.4;p9.22">Finally, the time course assay of the enzyme reaction was carry out by preparing 11 test tubes each containing 2cm <hi rend="sup">3</hi> p-nitrophenyl phosphate (5mM in 0,05M glycine buffer, pH9.5) and 1cm <hi rend="sup">3</hi> buffer. </s><s n="s2.4;p9.22">The reaction was started upon addition of 1cm <hi rend="sup">3</hi> of enzyme. </s><s n="s3.4;p9.22">Then, the reaction was stopped with addition of NaOH <hi rend="sub">(aq)</hi> at 0, 0.5, 1.0, 1.5, 2.0 min and then at 2 min intervals until 20 min. </s><s n="s4.4;p9.22">The amount of p-nitrophenol produced was determined by measuring A <hi rend="sub">410</hi>. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head>Results: </head><div2><head rend="underlined">Effect of pH on enzyme activity</head><p n="p10.22"><s n="s1.4;p10.22">The results obtained from the experiment show that pH affects the activity of the enzyme. </s><s n="s2.4;p10.22">As can be seen in graph 1. below, when pH increases, the enzyme activity increases. </s><s n="s3.4;p10.22">The highest enzyme activity is around pH 9.0~9.5 where most p-nitrophenol is produced. </s><s n="s4.4;p10.22">However, at more alkaline pH, enzyme activity decreases again. pH 9.0~9.5 is the optimum pH for the enzyme alkaline phosphatase. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0141b-fig.001"><head>Graph 1. p-nitrophenol produced at different pH </head></figure></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">Effect of temperature of enzyme activity</head><p n="p11.22"><s n="s1.4;p11.22">As temperature increase, the activity of the enzyme gradually increases at a fairly constant rate. </s><s n="s2.4;p11.22">(Graph 2. below) </s><s n="s3.4;p11.22">However, at around 45°C, enzyme activity drops quite rapidly. </s><s n="s4.4;p11.22">According to the results, optimum temperature for the enzyme is 44°C. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0141b-fig.002"><head>Graph 2. p-nitrophenol produced at different temperature</head></figure></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">Determination of Michaelis-Menten constant</head><p n="p12.22"><s n="s1.7;p12.22">Graph 3 and 4 (p. </s><s n="s2.7;p12.22">4) are two methods of calculating the Michaelis-Menten constant, K <hi rend="sub">M</hi>, the Lineweaver Burk plot and Eadie Hofstee plot respectively. </s><s n="s3.7;p12.22">Since the Lineweaver Burk plot is 1/V <hi rend="sub">0</hi> against 1/[S], the x-intercept of the line is equal to -1/K <hi rend="sub">M</hi>. </s><s n="s4.7;p12.22">Hence, K <hi rend="sub">M</hi> was calculated to be 1.00mmoldm <hi rend="sup">-3</hi>. </s><s n="s5.7;p12.22">(Calculations can be found in the appendix, p. 9) For the Eadie Hofstee plot, the gradient of the line is equal to - K <hi rend="sub">M</hi> because the graph is a graph of V <hi rend="sub">0</hi> against V <hi rend="sub">0</hi>/[S]. </s><s n="s6.7;p12.22">From this plot, it K <hi rend="sub">M</hi> was calculated to be 0.93mmoldm <hi rend="sup">-3</hi>. (p. </s><s n="s7.7;p12.22">10) </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0141b-fig.003"><head>Graph 3. Lineweaver Burk Plot of hydrolysis of p-nitrophenyl phosphate catalysed by alkaline phosphatase</head></figure><figure id="BAWE_0141b-fig.004"><head>Graph 4. Eadie Hofstee Plot of hydrolysis of p-nitrophenyl phosphate catalysed by alkaline phosphatase </head></figure></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">Product inhibition of enzyme action</head><p n="p13.22"><s n="s1.2;p13.22">As shown in the graph 5. below, as the concentration of phosphate, one of the products of the reaction catalysed by alkaline phosphatase, increases the amount of p-nitrophenol produced decreases, showing that the product inhibits the action of the enzyme. </s><s n="s2.2;p13.22">It continually decreases until about 20mmoldm <hi rend="sup">-3</hi> of phosphate is added, when amount of p-nitrophenol produced becomes constant. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0141b-fig.005"><head> Graph 5. Product inhibition of enzyme action </head></figure></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">Order of reaction</head><p n="p14.22"><s n="s1.3;p14.22">Graph 6. is a graph of the log(a/(a-x)) against time. </s><s n="s2.3;p14.22">Since the resulting plot is linear, the reaction is first order. </s><s n="s3.3;p14.22">This means that the rate of the reaction is proportional to the concentration of the substrate, p-nitrophenyl phosphate. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0141b-fig.006"><head>Graph 6. Order of the hydrolysis reaction of p-nitrophenyl phenol catalysed by alkaline phosphatase</head></figure></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head>Conclusion: </head><div2><head rend="underlined">Effect of pH on enzyme activity</head><p n="p15.22"><s n="s1.3;p15.22">pH affects the rate of enzyme catalysed reaction because at different pH values, the charges of various amino acid residues in the enzyme change. </s><s n="s2.3;p15.22">This affects electrostatic interactions between amino acids, altering tertiary structure and hence activity of the enzyme. </s><s n="s3.3;p15.22">The optimum pH value determined from the experiment for alkaline phosphatase is about pH 9.5. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">Effect of temperature on enzyme activity</head><p n="p16.22"><s n="s1.2;p16.22">Increasing the temperature initially increases the rate of enzyme catalysed reactions because more of the reactants posses the minimum activation energy, leading to more successful collisions of substrate and enzyme resulting in reaction. </s><s n="s2.2;p16.22">The optimum temperature for alkaline phosphatase determined from this experiment is 44°C. Above this temperature, rate of reaction decreases because the enzyme becomes denatured as the hydrogen bonds holding the tertiary structure of the enzyme breaks. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">Michaelis-Menten constant</head><p n="p17.22"><s n="s1.3;p17.22">The Michaelis-Menten constant is the substrate concentration when the rate of reaction is half the maximum velocity that can be obtained. </s><s n="s2.3;p17.22">For alkaline phosphatase, the K <hi rend="sub">M</hi> is about 1mmoldm <hi rend="sup">-3</hi>. </s><s n="s3.3;p17.22">That is, when there is 1mmoldm <hi rend="sup">-3</hi> of p-nitrophenyl phosphate, the rate of reaction is half the V <hi rend="sub">0max</hi>. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">Product inhibition of enzyme action</head><p n="p18.22"><s n="s1.2;p18.22">According to the graph, the lowest molarity of phosphate which markedly inhibits alkaline phosphatase is at 20mmoldm <hi rend="sup">-3</hi>. </s><s n="s2.2;p18.22">Since amounts of phosphate produced in all the previous reactions have been much lower than this (not more than 5mM) it would have been insufficient to begin inhibiting the enzyme. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">Order of reaction</head><p n="p19.22"><s n="s1.4;p19.22">From the results obtained the order of this reaction is first order with respect to the substrate, p-nitrophenyl phosphate. </s><s n="s2.4;p19.22">This means that the rate of the reaction is proportional to the concentration of the substrate. </s><s n="s3.4;p19.22">However, this is only true for low substrate concentrations because at higher concentrations the enzyme will become saturated with substrate. </s><s n="s4.4;p19.22">Although from the reaction: </s></p><p n="p20.22"><s n="s1.1;p20.22"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0141b-form.002"/> </s></p><p n="p21.22"><s n="s1.2;p21.22">it can be seen that water is also a reactant, the reaction is first order because the concentration of water is so high it does not change significantly. </s><s n="s2.2;p21.22">Hence concentration of H <hi rend="sub">2</hi>O is negligible and the reaction is first order. </s></p><p n="p22.22"><s n="s1.2;p22.22">From the graph the rate constant, K is equal to 0.011min <hi rend="sup">-1</hi>. </s><s n="s2.2;p22.22">(Calculations can be found in the appendix, p. +) </s></p></div2></div1></body><back><div1 type="appendix"><head rend="underlined">Appendix</head><p/></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
