<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_0141h" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Analysing a 5kb fragment of a bacteriophage DNA sequence</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">footer: page numbers
</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">2</p><p n="date">2004-04</p><p n="module title">Bioinformatics</p><p n="module code">BS250</p><p n="genre family">Methodology recount</p><p n="discipline">Biological Sciences</p><p n="disciplinary group">LS</p><p n="grade">M</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">1595</p><p n="number of s-units">70</p><p n="number of p">40</p><p n="number of tables">15</p><p n="number of figures">2</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">6</p><p n="number of lists">0</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">0</p><p n="abstract present">abstract present</p><p n="average words per s-unit">22.8</p><p n="average s-units per p">1.8</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">f</p><p n="year of birth">1984</p><p n="first language">English</p><p n="education">OSA</p><p n="course">Biochemistry</p><p n="student ID">0141</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><titlePart>06.04.2004 University Number: <name type="student ID"/> Biochemistry Undergraduate, 2 <hi rend="sup">nd</hi> year</titlePart><docTitle><titlePart rend="underlined">Bioinformatics Assignment Analysing a 5kb fragment of a bacteriophage DNA sequence </titlePart></docTitle></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="abstract"><head rend="underlined">Abstract</head><p n="p1.40"><s n="s1.10;p1.40">A DNA sequence of approximately 5 kilobases derived from a bacteriophage which infects marine cyanobacteria of the genus <hi rend="italic">Synechococcus</hi> was analysed. </s><s n="s2.10;p1.40">The 4246 base pair (bp) sequence contained 14 potential open reading frames (ORF) when searching for ORFs with a length of over 100bp. </s><s n="s3.10;p1.40">Of these, three of the largest ORFs were studied in further detail. </s><s n="s4.10;p1.40">These genes were mostly similar to the genes found in enterobacteria phage T4 and were similar to gene products (gp) 13, 14 and 15. </s><s n="s5.10;p1.40">Pairwise similarity to the T4 phage was calculated to be: 28%, 28% and 35% respectively. </s><s n="s6.10;p1.40">The Gp13 and gp14 are genes for neck proteins of the phage and gp15 is a terminal capping protein of the tail sheath. </s><s n="s7.10;p1.40">The proteins were analysed and it was revealed that as expected, all three were globular proteins. </s><s n="s8.10;p1.40">The three proteins also contained common motifs that are also found in the T4 phage gp13, 14 and 15. </s><s n="s9.10;p1.40">This supports the fact that probably the enterobacteria phage T4 and the marine cyanobacteria infecting bacteriophage are related. </s><s n="s10.10;p1.40">The secondary structures were also predicted and can be viewed in the results section. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined">Introduction</head><p n="p2.40"><s n="s1.4;p2.40">Viruses come in a variety of forms, however, the head-tail structure (as seen in Figure 1.) is unique to bacterial viruses. </s><s n="s2.4;p2.40">(Dimmock <hi rend="italic">et al</hi>., 2001) The figure below shows the T4 bacteriophage, which has a relatively complex structure consisting of an icosahedral head that contains the nucleic acid, the neck structure including whiskers, a tail with an external contractile sheath and a tail core that usually has helical symmetry and is non contractile. </s><s n="s3.4;p2.40">The tail ends with a baseplate with tail pins and tail fibres. </s><s n="s4.4;p2.40">These different structures of the bacteriophage interact during the infection of a bacterium. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0141h-pic.001"><head rend="underlined">Figure 1. Structural components of the T4 particle</head></figure><p n="p3.40"><s n="s1.5;p3.40">The infection of the bacterium usually occurs by the phage attaching to the host's cell wall. </s><s n="s2.5;p3.40">In the case of a bacteriophage like T4, tail fibres attach to the receptor on the bacterial cell wall, allowing the phage to be brought closer to the cell surface. </s><s n="s3.5;p3.40">This happens so that contact can be made with the tail pins on the phage's base plate. </s><s n="s4.5;p3.40">Once the phage tail pins are in contact with the cell wall, the tail sheath can contract and the tail core penetrates the wall. </s><s n="s5.5;p3.40">As a consequence, nucleic acid can pass through the tail </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined">Materials &amp; Methods</head><p n="p4.40"><s n="s1.8;p4.40">Firstly, the 4246bp sequence was pasted into the ORF Finder<ref target="BAWE_0141h-ftnote.001"/> to search for potential ORFs of a minimum size of 100bp, using the standard genetic code. </s><s n="s2.8;p4.40">The ORFs were searched for homologues using BLASTP<ref target="BAWE_0141h-ftnote.002"/> using the non-redundant peptide sequence databases. </s><s n="s3.8;p4.40">This did not give very specific results, many of the sequences found being unknown environmental sequences. </s><s n="s4.8;p4.40">However, a few of the ORFs had similarities with other bacteriophage genes. </s><s n="s5.8;p4.40">These were: gp13 neck protein, gp15 tail sheath, gp14 neck protein and gp24. </s><s n="s6.8;p4.40">Whether these were of any significance was uncertain, and hence another method of aligning sequences was necessary. </s><s n="s7.8;p4.40">That is, multiple sequence alignment, which involves placing "residues in columns that derive from a common ancestral residue by substitutions. </s><s n="s8.8;p4.40">The most successful alignment is the one that most closely represents the evolutionary history of the sequences." </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0141h-ftnote.001"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1"><seg type="URL" n="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/gorf/gorf.html"/> </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0141h-ftnote.002"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1"><seg type="URL" n="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/BLAST/"/> </s></p></note><p n="p5.40"><s n="s1.3;p5.40">ORFs translated into amino acid sequences were examined using PredictProtein<ref target="BAWE_0141h-ftnote.003"/> which analyses and predicts the structure of the protein sequence. </s><s n="s2.3;p5.40">This was carried out for the three largest ORFs, namely the ones that show similarity to the enterobacteria phage T4 gp13, gp14 and gp15. </s><s n="s3.3;p5.40">These three were not only chosen because they were the largest genes but because all three showed similarity to structural proteins important for attachment of the tail to the phage head. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0141h-ftnote.003"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1"><seg type="URL" n="http://www.predictprotein.org"/> </s></p></note><p n="p6.40"><s n="s1.5;p6.40">With PredictProtein the sequence underwent a number of different analyses: the databases searched for homologues include SWISS-PROT, TrEMBL, PDB and BIG. Then, alignment was undergone by BLASTP, PSIblast and MaxHom, the latter being the multiple sequence alignment program. </s><s n="s2.5;p6.40">In addition, there were a number of sequence motif searching methods and a prediction of protein structure. </s><s n="s3.5;p6.40">The outcome of PredictProtein which were thought to be significant in the analysis of these three ORFs are tabulated in the results section. </s><s n="s4.5;p6.40">Due to the fact that the format of the secondary structure predicted by PHD and PROF in PredictProtein was difficult to reproduce in this document, NNPREDICT was used to produce a prediction of the secondary structure. </s><s n="s5.5;p6.40">However, this prediction is less accurate than that made by PHD or PROF as these two latter servers expect the input to an alignment of multiple sequences. </s></p><p n="p7.40"><s n="s1.3;p7.40">CPHmodels, a homology modelling server, was used to try and build a model of the proteins encoded by each of the three largest genes. </s><s n="s2.3;p7.40">However, as no suitable template was found, the server was unable to build a model. </s><s n="s3.3;p7.40">This was also the case with SWISS-MODEL. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined">Results</head><div2><head rend="underlined bold">ORFs found</head><p n="p8.40"><s n="s1.1;p8.40">Below shows the sequence with highlighted parts which are potential ORFs that are over 100bp in size, which was generated by the ORF Finder <hi rend="sup">1</hi>. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0141h-fig.001"><head>Figure 2. ORFs found</head></figure></div2><div2><head rend="underlined bold">Predict Protein</head><div3><head rend="underlined">1. Gene encoding sequence of <hi rend="bold">276</hi> amino acid residues </head><div4><head>·<hi rend="underlined">PSI-BLAST</hi></head><table id="BAWE_0141h-tab.001"><head>Table 1. The first three hits found </head><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p9.40"/></div4><div4><head>·<hi rend="underlined">Motifs found by PROSITE</hi></head><table id="BAWE_0141h-tab.002"><head>Table 2. All functional motifs found in sequence </head><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p10.40"/></div4><div4><head>·<hi rend="underlined">MAXHOM alignment</hi></head><table id="BAWE_0141h-tab.003"><head>Table 3. </head><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p11.40"/></div4><div4><head>·<hi rend="underlined">CYSPRED prediction</hi></head><p n="p12.40"><s n="s1.1;p12.40">No bonded cysteines found </s></p></div4><div4><head>·<hi rend="underlined">Prediction of secondary structure (PHDsec and PROF)</hi></head><table id="BAWE_0141h-tab.004"><head>Table 4. Percentage of secondary structure type in protein </head><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p13.40"/></div4><div4><head>·<hi rend="underlined">Prediction of solvent accessibility (PHDacc and PROF)</hi></head><table id="BAWE_0141h-tab.005"><head>Table 5. </head><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p14.40"/></div4><div4><head>·<hi rend="underlined">GLOBE prediction of globularity</hi></head><p n="p15.40"><s n="s1.1;p15.40">Protein appears as compact, as a globular domain </s></p></div4></div3><div3><head rend="underlined">2. Gene encoding sequence of <hi rend="bold">292</hi> amino acid residues </head><div4><head>·<hi rend="underlined">PSI-BLAST</hi></head><table id="BAWE_0141h-tab.006"><head>Table 6. The first three hits found </head><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p16.40"/></div4><div4><head>·<hi rend="underlined">Motifs found by PROSITE</hi></head><table id="BAWE_0141h-tab.007"><head>Table 7. All functional proteins found in sequence </head><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p17.40"/></div4><div4><head>·<hi rend="underlined">MAXHOM alignment</hi></head><table id="BAWE_0141h-tab.008"><head>Table 8. </head><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p18.40"/></div4><div4><head>·<hi rend="underlined">CYSPRED prediction</hi></head><p n="p19.40"><s n="s1.1;p19.40">No bonded cysteines found </s></p></div4><div4><head>·<hi rend="underlined">Prediction of secondary structure (PHDsec and PROF)</hi></head><table id="BAWE_0141h-tab.009"><head>Table 9. Percentage of secondary structure type in protein </head><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p20.40"/></div4><div4><head>·<hi rend="underlined">Prediction of solvent accessibility (PHDacc and PROF)</hi></head><table id="BAWE_0141h-tab.010"><head>Table 10. </head><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p21.40"/></div4><div4><head>·<hi rend="underlined">GLOBE prediction of globularity</hi></head><p n="p22.40"><s n="s1.1;p22.40">Protein appears as compact, as a globular domain </s></p></div4></div3><div3><head rend="underlined">3. Gene encoding sequence of <hi rend="bold">266</hi> amino acid residues </head><div4><head>·<hi rend="underlined">PSI-BLAST</hi></head><table id="BAWE_0141h-tab.011"><head>Table 11. The first three hits found </head><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p23.40"/></div4><div4><head>·<hi rend="underlined">Motifs found by PROSITE</hi></head><table id="BAWE_0141h-tab.012"><head>Table 12. All functional proteins found in sequence </head><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p24.40"/></div4><div4><head>·<hi rend="underlined">MAXHOM alignment</hi></head><table id="BAWE_0141h-tab.013"><head>Table 13. </head><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p25.40"/></div4><div4><head>·<hi rend="underlined">CYSPRED prediction</hi></head><p n="p26.40"><s n="s1.1;p26.40">No bonded cysteines found </s></p></div4><div4><head>·<hi rend="underlined">Prediction of secondary structure (PHDsec and PROF)</hi></head><table id="BAWE_0141h-tab.014"><head>Table 14. Percentage of secondary structure type in protein </head><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p27.40"/></div4><div4><head>·<hi rend="underlined">Prediction of solvent accessibility (PHDacc and PROF)</hi></head><table id="BAWE_0141h-tab.015"><head>Table 15. </head><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p28.40"/></div4><div4><head>·<hi rend="underlined">GLOBE prediction of globularity</hi></head><p n="p29.40"><s n="s1.1;p29.40">Protein appears as compact, as a globular domain </s></p></div4></div3></div2><div2><head rend="underlined bold">NNPREDICT</head><p n="p30.40"><s n="s1.1;p30.40"><hi rend="bold">Sequence</hi> <hi rend="bold italic">gp13</hi> (276 amino acids):<formula notation="" id="BAWE_0141h-form.001"/> </s></p><p n="p31.40"><s n="s1.1;p31.40"><hi rend="bold">Secondary structure prediction <hi rend="italic">(H = helix, E = strand, - = no prediction)</hi>:</hi><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0141h-form.002"/> </s></p><p n="p32.40"><s n="s1.1;p32.40"><hi rend="bold">Sequence</hi> <hi rend="bold italic">gp14</hi> (292 amino acids)<formula notation="" id="BAWE_0141h-form.003"/> </s></p><p n="p33.40"><s n="s1.1;p33.40"><hi rend="bold">Secondary structure prediction <hi rend="italic">(H = helix, E = strand, - = no prediction)</hi>:</hi><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0141h-form.004"/> </s></p><p n="p34.40"><s n="s1.1;p34.40"><hi rend="bold">Sequence</hi> <hi rend="bold italic">gp15</hi> (266 amino acids)<formula notation="" id="BAWE_0141h-form.005"/> </s></p><p n="p35.40"><s n="s1.1;p35.40"><hi rend="bold">Secondary structure prediction <hi rend="italic">(H = helix, E = strand, - = no prediction)</hi>:</hi><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0141h-form.006"/> </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined">Discussion</head><div2><head rend="underlined">Genes expressing neck and tail sheath protein</head><p n="p36.40"><s n="s1.6;p36.40">Many phages have tails attached to the phage head. </s><s n="s2.6;p36.40">In this bacteriophage infecting marine cyanobacteria, a gene encoding a tail sheath protein of 266 amino acid length was discovered. </s><s n="s3.6;p36.40">There was 35% pairwise sequence identity to the enterobacteria phage T4 protein (SwissProt accession number: P11112). </s><s n="s4.6;p36.40">In these phages, the tail is surrounded by a contractile sheath which contracts during infection of the bacterium. </s><s n="s5.6;p36.40">This is an important structure when penetrating the host bacterial cell to inject its DNA. The gp15 tail sheath in fact forms a connector which enables the tail to bind to the head and is an important component in completing the assembly of the bacteriophage tail. </s><s n="s6.6;p36.40">(Zhao <hi rend="italic">et al</hi>., 2003) </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0141h-fig.002"><head rend="underlined">Figure 3. Model of the head-to-tail interface in bacteriophage T4</head></figure><p n="p37.40"><s n="s1.7;p37.40">The two other genes studied were discovered to be neck proteins and these are involved in the structural part separating the phage head. </s><s n="s2.7;p37.40">(Figure 3.) </s><s n="s3.7;p37.40">The neck protein is a knob-like structure on top of the tail (Coombs et al., 1977) and is thought to be required for the tail to bind to the head. </s><s n="s4.7;p37.40">The first of the neck proteins analysed from the phage sequence showed similarity to the T4 phage gp13 neck protein (SwissProt accession number: P11110) and gp14 neck protein (SwissProt accession number: P11111) According to the works of Stahl <hi rend="italic">et al</hi>., the genes 13, 14 and 15 in T4 phage are co-transcribed and that the clustering of genes indicate "interaction and cooperative functions of the gene products they encode". </s><s n="s5.7;p37.40">This is exactly what was found to be the case for this DNA fragment of this cyanobacteria infecting phage. </s><s n="s6.7;p37.40">The genes 13, 14, 15 were established to be co-transcribed on the fragment and the genes were very close together. </s><s n="s7.7;p37.40">Moreover, these three genes all code for structural proteins that are important for the attachment of the tail to the phage head. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">Secondary structure of the proteins</head><p n="p38.40"><s n="s1.3;p38.40">From the analyses by PredictProtein, all three of the gene product studied have predominantly loops in their secondary structure. </s><s n="s2.3;p38.40">In the proteins similar to T4 phage gp14 and gp15, the protein structure was predicted to contain more β sheets than α helices. </s><s n="s3.3;p38.40">However, for the other protein, the prediction included slightly more helices. </s></p><p n="p39.40"><s n="s1.1;p39.40">As expected for structural components of the bacteriophage, all three proteins were predicted to be compact and globular proteins where approximately half the amino acid residues are exposed with more than 16% of their surface. </s></p><p n="p40.40"><s n="s1.2;p40.40">Analyses of the protein motifs contained in each of the gene products revealed that all three consistently contain three common motifs: protein kinase C and casein kinase II phosphorylation sites and N-myristoylation sites. </s><s n="s2.2;p40.40">Studying enterobacteria phage T4 gp13 (SwissProt accession number: P11110) revealed that this protein also contains the same motifs (this study not shown in results section), again supporting the fact that this gp13 of the T4 and the gene in the studied cyanobacteria infecting phage are related. </s></p></div2></div1></body><back><div1 type="bibliography"><head rend="underlined">References</head><div2 type="bibliography"><head rend="underlined">Journals</head><p>Chen, F. and Lu, J. Genomic Sequence and Evolution of Marine Cyanophage P60: a New</p><p>Insight on Lytic and Lysogenic Phages. <hi rend="italic">Applied and Environmental Microbiology</hi>. <hi rend="bold">68</hi>: 5 2589-2594 (2002)</p><p>Coombs, D.H. <hi rend="italic">et al</hi>., <hi rend="italic">Mol. Biol</hi>. <hi rend="bold">116</hi>: 375-405 (1977), cited in Zhao, L., Kanamaru, S., </p><p>Chaidirek, C. and Arisaka, F. P15 and P3, the Tail Completion Proteins of Bacteriophage T4, Both Form Hexameric Rings. <hi rend="italic">Journal of Bacteriology</hi>. <hi rend="bold">185</hi>: 5, 1693-1700 (2003).</p><p>Mayer, G. Medical Microbiology, MBIM, University of South Carolina.</p><p> (<seg type="URL" n="http://www.med.sc.edu"/>:85/mayer/phage.htm)</p><p>Stahl, F.W. et al., <hi rend="italic">Genectics</hi>. <hi rend="bold">64</hi>, 157-170 (1970), cited in Zhao, L., Kanamaru, S., Chaidirek, </p><p>C. and Arisaka, F. P15 and P3, the Tail Completion Proteins of Bacteriophage T4, Both Form Hexameric Rings. <hi rend="italic">Journal of Bacteriology</hi>. <hi rend="bold">185</hi>: 5, 1693-1700 (2003).</p><p>Selivanov, N.A., Prilipov, A.G. and Mesyanzhinov, V.V. Nucleotide sequences of bacteriophage T4 genes 13, 14 and 15. <hi rend="italic">Nucleic Acids Research</hi>. <hi rend="bold">17</hi>:9, 3583 (1989)</p><p>Zhao, L., Kanamaru, S., Chaidirek, C. and Arisaka, F. P15 and P3, the Tail Completion </p><p>Proteins of Bacteriophage T4, Both Form Hexameric Rings. <hi rend="italic">Journal of Bacteriology</hi>. <hi rend="bold">185</hi>: 5, 1693-1700 (2003)</p></div2><div2 type="bibliography"><head rend="underlined">Servers</head><p>CYSPRED: Fariselli, P., Riccobelli, P. and Casadio, R. <hi rend="italic">Proteins</hi>. <hi rend="bold">36</hi>: 340-346 (1999)</p><p>URL: <seg type="URL" n="http://prion.biocomp.unibo.it/cyspred.html"/></p><p>GLOBE: Rost, B. (1998) Unpublished.</p><p>URL: <seg type="URL" n="http://cubic.bioc.columbia.edu"/></p><p>MaxHom: Sander, C. and Schneider, R. <hi rend="italic">Proteins</hi>. <hi rend="bold">9</hi>: 56-68 (1991)</p><p>PHD: Rost, B. <hi rend="italic">Methods in Enzymology</hi>. <hi rend="bold">266</hi>: 525-539 (1996)</p><p>URL: <seg type="URL" n="http://cubic.bioc.columbia.edu"/></p><p>PHDacc: Rost, B. and Sander, C. <hi rend="italic">Proteins</hi>. <hi rend="bold">20</hi>: 216-226 (1994)</p><p>URL: <seg type="URL" n="http://cubic.bioc.columbia.edu"/></p><p>PHDsec: Rost, B. and Sander, C. <hi rend="italic">J Mol Biol</hi>. <hi rend="bold">232</hi>: 584-599 (1993)</p><p>URL: <seg type="URL" n="http://cubic.bioc.columbia.edu"/></p><p>PredictProtein: Rost, B and Liu, J. <hi rend="italic">Nucleic Acids Research</hi>. <hi rend="bold">31</hi>:13 3300-3304 (2003)</p><p>URL: <seg type="URL" n="http://cubic.bioc.columbia.edu"/></p><p>PROF: Rost, B. and Sander, C. <hi rend="italic">J Mol Biol</hi>. <hi rend="bold">232</hi>: 584-599 (1993)</p><p>PROFsec: Rost, B. <hi rend="italic">Meth. Mol. Biol</hi>. Submitted (2004)</p><p>URL: <seg type="URL" n="http://cubic.bioc.columbia.edu"/></p><p>PROSITE: Bairoch, A. Bucher, P. and Hofmann, K. <hi rend="italic">Nucleic Acids Research</hi>. <hi rend="bold">25</hi>: 217-221 </p><p>(1997) URL: <seg type="URL" n="http://cubic.bioc.columbia.edu"/></p></div2><div2 type="bibliography"><head rend="underlined">Figures</head><p>Figure 1. and 3. were taken from Miller, E.S., Kutter, E., Mosig, G., Arisaka, F., Kunisawa, T and Rüger, W. Bacteriophage T4 Genome. <hi rend="italic">Microbiology and Molecular Biology Reviews</hi>. <hi rend="bold">67</hi>:1, 86-156 (2003).</p></div2></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
