<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_0142a" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Explain the importance of the case of DONOGHUE V STEVENSON 1932 AC 562 in the development of the law of negligence.</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">header: student and 'seminar group' number
footer: date, assignment name, page numbers</note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">appendix: list of cited cases
</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">1</p><p n="date">2006-01</p><p n="module title">Introduction to Business Law</p><p n="module code">IB1100</p><p n="genre family">Critique</p><p n="discipline">Business</p><p n="disciplinary group">SS</p><p n="grade">M</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">1446</p><p n="number of s-units">96</p><p n="number of p">11</p><p n="number of tables">0</p><p n="number of figures">0</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">0</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">0</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">15.1</p><p n="average s-units per p">8.7</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">f</p><p n="year of birth">1985</p><p n="first language">Chinese Cantonese</p><p n="education">UK1</p><p n="course">Accounting and Finance</p><p n="student ID">0142</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><docTitle><titlePart rend="bold">Question: Explain the importance of the case of DONOGHUE V STEVENSON 1932 AC 562 in the development of the law of negligence. </titlePart></docTitle></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="section"><p n="p1.11"><s n="s1.5;p1.11">The history of English law is long standing and well established. </s><s n="s2.5;p1.11">As stated in Keeton's (1984:7) book, 'the doctrine of precedent inherently brings legal history to bear upon current judicial decisions.' </s><s n="s3.5;p1.11">Due to the distinctive nature of precedents, the specificity of cases had been coloured by its uniqueness and independence. </s><s n="s4.5;p1.11">Every verdict in individual cases had imposed a remarkable influence on the development of the law of tort. </s><s n="s5.5;p1.11">Many reasoning as well as rulings had even been extended into modern days. </s></p><p n="p2.11"><s n="s1.7;p2.11">According to Keeton's (1984) investigation, in early nineteenth century, the common practice of the society was politically incorrect. </s><s n="s2.7;p2.11">The concern over how to identify the problem of proximity had created a loud noise. </s><s n="s3.7;p2.11">Meanwhile, the whole system was still at embryo stage. </s><s n="s4.7;p2.11">Some might argue that when goods were sold from the manufacturer to distributors, those products were then expected to be resold to other retailers and eventually reaching the hands of consumers. </s><s n="s5.7;p2.11">Because of the unknown size of the public being involved behind, the society tended not to burden the manufacturers and sellers with too much pressure. </s><s n="s6.7;p2.11">Hence, it was generally accepted that the responsibility should not be passed onto their shoulders. </s><s n="s7.7;p2.11">Yet, a gleam of hope shined in this apparently desperate situation, lightened the darkness. </s></p><p n="p3.11"><s n="s1.7;p3.11">Originally, in <hi rend="italic"> Heaven v.</hi> </s><s n="s2.7;p3.11"><hi rend="italic">Pender</hi><ref target="BAWE_0142a-ftnote.001"/>, the concept of negligence was not approved by Cotton and Bowen L.JJ.<ref target="BAWE_0142a-ftnote.002"/>. </s><s n="s3.7;p3.11">After years and years of criticism, the importance of the duty of care had been stressed. </s><s n="s4.7;p3.11">And in law's term, a number of previous judges had tried to work out a formula to define the duty of care. </s><s n="s5.7;p3.11">Firstly, Brett M.R. provided a statement with a relatively wide meaning. </s><s n="s6.7;p3.11">He, became Lord Esher in later time, amended his idea by saying it in a less vague way. </s><s n="s7.7;p3.11">Then with Lords Atkin, Thankerton and Macmillan coming next, their comments given those days had inaugurated a new era in law of negligence. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0142a-ftnote.001"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">[1883] 11 Q.B.D. 503 509 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0142a-ftnote.002"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Only if physical harm was caused, the ground for accounting negligence was possibly formed. </s></p></note><p n="p4.11"><s n="s1.11;p4.11">At that time, the relevant law can be applied purely relied on the law of contract. </s><s n="s2.11;p4.11">It covered a very limited area as the linkage was being built up in between buyers and sellers only which had made it more difficult to make the manufacturer of defective products liable to third parties. </s><s n="s3.11;p4.11">The problem then came up, Mrs. Donoghue did not purchase the ginger beer in person (Adams, 2003). </s><s n="s4.11;p4.11">In this case, the right of making a claim was restricted to Mrs. Donoghue's friend (buyer) only. </s><s n="s5.11;p4.11">But, her friend did not suffer much. </s><s n="s6.11;p4.11">So, even if she had decided to engage in a lawsuit, the compensation could have been a pretty small amount which was insufficient to recover Mrs. Donoghue's harm, her physical illness and mental impact. </s><s n="s7.11;p4.11">However, as a third person, the bargaining counter of Mrs. Donoghue is very weak since she had no direct relationship with the seller. </s><s n="s8.11;p4.11">Moreover, the seller is just one of the retailers. </s><s n="s9.11;p4.11">To make it meaningful, the plaintiff had made up her mind to sue Stevenson, the manufacturer. </s><s n="s10.11;p4.11">And the final outcome had written a new page in tort law and case law. </s><s n="s11.11;p4.11">The results boosted popular morale and encouraged same type of cases being put to court. </s></p><p n="p5.11"><s n="s1.9;p5.11">The past experience shadowed a lot on tort law. </s><s n="s2.9;p5.11">It was always difficult to fit in several standard frameworks. </s><s n="s3.9;p5.11">In order to raise a practical claim, the plaintiff would need to look for particular pattern to follow under the spirit of common law. </s><s n="s4.9;p5.11">The winning of the case <hi rend="italic">Donoghue v.</hi> </s><s n="s5.9;p5.11"><hi rend="italic">Stevenson</hi><ref target="BAWE_0142a-ftnote.003"/> had examined the association in between a general public sentiment of wrongdoing and its responsibility. </s><s n="s6.9;p5.11">It had shown that the liability for negligence did exist, successfully opposing the general rule<ref target="BAWE_0142a-ftnote.004"/>. </s><s n="s7.9;p5.11">Furthermore, the interpretation of Lord Macmillan had emphasized on the last few lines, "The grounds of action may be as various and manifold as human errancy; and the conception of legal responsibility may develop in adaptation to altering social conditions and standards. </s><s n="s8.9;p5.11">The criterion of judgment must adjust and adapt itself to the changing circumstances of life. </s><s n="s9.9;p5.11">The categories of negligence are never closed." </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0142a-ftnote.003"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">[1936] A.C. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">562 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0142a-ftnote.004"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Derived from the holding of Winterbottom v. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">Wright. </s></p></note><p n="p6.11"><s n="s1.10;p6.11">On the other hand, the dictum made by Lord Atkin had put forward a relatively concrete guideline for the posterity to follow. </s><s n="s2.10;p6.11">This valuable notion introduced was the "neighbour" principle. </s><s n="s3.10;p6.11">"The rule that you are to love your neighbour becomes in law, you must not injure your neighbour; and the lawyer's question, Who is my meighbour? </s><s n="s4.10;p6.11">Receives a restricted reply. </s><s n="s5.10;p6.11">You must take reasonable care to avoid acts or omissions which you can reasonably foresee would be likely to injure your neighbour. </s><s n="s6.10;p6.11">Who, then, in law is my neightbour? </s><s n="s7.10;p6.11">The answer seems to be - persons who are so closely and directly affected by my act that I ought reasonably to have them in contemplation as being so affected when I am directing my mind to the acts or omissions which are called in question" addressed by Lord Atkin. </s><s n="s8.10;p6.11">Some sort of duty of care had been recognized to an outsider with whom it had no contract at all. </s><s n="s9.10;p6.11">It is also a fateful event to determine that a manufacturer did owe a duty of care to the ultimate consumer, not just buyers and sellers. </s><s n="s10.10;p6.11">Other than evidently outlined the method should be adopted to define the vicinity or proximity within reasonable range, the decision could never make it any clearer that the existing precedents was no longer an obstacle in developing the tort of negligence. </s></p><p n="p7.11"><s n="s1.8;p7.11">In handling <hi rend="italic">Home Office v.</hi> </s><s rend="italic" n="s2.8;p7.11">Dorset Yacht Co. </s><ref target="BAWE_0142a-ftnote.005"/><s n="s3.8;p7.11">, Lord Ried further agreed with Lord Atkin's speech. </s><s n="s4.8;p7.11">Thus he expressed his interest to regard <hi rend="italic">Donoghue v.</hi> </s><s n="s5.8;p7.11"><hi rend="italic">Stevenson</hi><ref target="BAWE_0142a-ftnote.006"/> as a milestone (Goldstein, 1987). </s><s n="s6.8;p7.11">Despite the fact that it was not belonged to part of a statute, still, the explanation was valid in many scenarios. </s><s n="s7.8;p7.11">In addition, the opinions mentioned above and by Lord Macmillan<ref target="BAWE_0142a-ftnote.007"/> had turned into an extremely strong persuasive precedent. </s><s n="s8.8;p7.11">Although not compulsorily binding, they had been cited for hundreds time so as to support different convictions. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0142a-ftnote.005"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">[1970] A.C. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">1004, 1027. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0142a-ftnote.006"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">[1936] A.C. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">562 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0142a-ftnote.007"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">'In the daily contacts of social and business life, human beings are thrown into, or place themselves in, an infinite variety of relations with their fellows; and the law can refer only to the standards of the reasonable man in order to determine whether any particular relation gives to a duty to take care, as between those who stand in that relation to each other.' </s></p></note><p n="p8.11"><s n="s1.9;p8.11">One point worthwhile to discuss was Lord Buckmaster's dissent in <hi rend="italic">Donoghue v.</hi> </s><s n="s2.9;p8.11"><hi rend="italic">Stevenson</hi>. </s><s n="s3.9;p8.11">The quoting of Cardozo's judgment in <hi rend="italic">MacPhersonv.</hi> </s><s rend="italic" n="s4.9;p8.11">Buick Motor Co. </s><ref target="BAWE_0142a-ftnote.008"/><s n="s5.9;p8.11"> It had definitely set up an example beforehand. </s><s n="s6.9;p8.11">This would probably be in favour of Mrs. Donoghue's condition. </s><s n="s7.9;p8.11">Yes, this was the point where it starts to differentiate. </s><s n="s8.9;p8.11">Lord Buckmaster denied the citation as appropriate since that was assumed only to 'dangerous articles'. </s><s n="s9.9;p8.11">Items like beer were well beneath the relevant topic. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0142a-ftnote.008"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.3;pn1.1">[1916] 217 N.Y. </s><s n="s2.3;pn1.1">382, 111 N.E. </s><s n="s3.3;pn1.1">1050 </s></p></note><p n="p9.11"><s n="s1.3;p9.11">Heading with this case's triumph, the court gradually extended the contractual guarantee to protect not only the eventual buyer, but also persons (e.g. family, friends and others) held close relationship with them (neighbouring effect). </s><s n="s2.3;p9.11">The USA had allowed the claimant to go on a direct claim against the manufacturer, provided that the skipping of procedures could allocate resources like time and money properly (Gerven et al 1998). </s><s n="s3.3;p9.11">It was not until the establishment of The UK Consumer Protection Act 1987 to obtain the similar outcome with USA. Referring to this victorious case, the general 'proximity' involved was totally granted on relationship and should not be confused with 'proximate cause<ref target="BAWE_0142a-ftnote.009"/>' (Gerven et al 1998). </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0142a-ftnote.009"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">It associated with the determination of remoteness upon consequences of defendant's actions in the context of causation. </s></p></note><p n="p10.11"><s n="s1.19;p10.11">To begin with <hi rend="italic">Donoghue v.</hi> </s><s n="s2.19;p10.11"><hi rend="italic">Stevenson</hi>, other cases continued putting to law might not be confined to physical injury, but starting to expand to aspects like mental damage, nervous shock, emotional distress and even financial loss. </s><s n="s3.19;p10.11">The consequential chain joined up all those cases progressively. </s><s n="s4.19;p10.11">For instance, <hi rend="italic">Hedley Byrne &amp; Co.</hi> </s><s rend="italic" n="s5.19;p10.11">Ltd v. </s><s rend="italic" n="s6.19;p10.11">Heller &amp; Partners Ltd. </s><ref target="BAWE_0142a-ftnote.010"/><s rend="italic" n="s7.19;p10.11">, Smith v. </s><s n="s8.19;p10.11"><hi rend="italic">Eric S. Bush</hi><ref target="BAWE_0142a-ftnote.011"/> coupled with T v. </s><s n="s9.19;p10.11">Surrey County Council<ref target="BAWE_0142a-ftnote.012"/> (Percy, 1977). </s><s n="s10.19;p10.11">Implied in later case, Stennett v. </s><s n="s11.19;p10.11">Hancock<ref target="BAWE_0142a-ftnote.013"/>, there is no any kind of formal or direct relationship in between the claimant and the defendant. </s><s n="s12.19;p10.11">Yet, by taking the neighbour test into account, the garage was found to owe a duty of care. </s><s n="s13.19;p10.11">The same applies in Grant v. </s><s n="s14.19;p10.11">Australian Knitting Mills Ltd<ref target="BAWE_0142a-ftnote.014"/>. </s><s n="s15.19;p10.11">Tort seemed to have acted as an alternative way-out or route to seek indemnification. </s><s n="s16.19;p10.11">Last but not least, in impressive titles such as Malfroot v. </s><s n="s17.19;p10.11">Noxal Ltd.<ref target="BAWE_0142a-ftnote.015"/> and Brown v. </s><s n="s18.19;p10.11">Cotterill<ref target="BAWE_0142a-ftnote.016"/>, Lewis J. and Lawrence J. applied the principles being found in Donoghue v. </s><s n="s19.19;p10.11">Stevenson respectively, revealing the existence of duty of care (Percy, 1977). </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0142a-ftnote.010"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">[1963] A.C. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">465, HL </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0142a-ftnote.011"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">[1989] 2 WLR 790, HL, </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0142a-ftnote.012"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">[1994] 4 All ER </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0142a-ftnote.013"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">[1939] 2 All ER 578 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0142a-ftnote.014"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">[1936] A.C. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">85 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0142a-ftnote.015"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">[1935] 51 T.L.R. 551: a sidecar parted from the motor-cycle while climbing a gradient injured the passenger. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0142a-ftnote.016"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">[1934] 51 T.L.R. 21: a tombstone in a churchyard was erected causing the monument fell upon the plaintiff. </s></p></note><p n="p11.11"><s n="s1.8;p11.11">With respect to the principles of UK law, the court usually exerted creative power in establishing case law (Adams, 2003). </s><s n="s2.8;p11.11">Even though common law had not been decreed by statute, it is influential to cases which would appear afterwards. </s><s n="s3.8;p11.11">To certain extent, those lengthy views done by judges were served as guidelines. </s><s n="s4.8;p11.11">Conclusively, before the hearing of <hi rend="italic">Donoghue v.</hi> </s><s n="s5.8;p11.11"><hi rend="italic">Stevenson</hi>, the fundamentals of the law of negligence had always been questioned. </s><s n="s6.8;p11.11">How to prove the existence of the duty of care? </s><s n="s7.8;p11.11">What were the requirements and limits? </s><s n="s8.8;p11.11">The prominent decision definitely answered all these exclamation marks. </s></p></div1></body><back><div1 type="appendix"><head rend="underlined bold">Appendices</head><p/></div1><div1 type="bibliography"><head rend="underlined bold">Bibliography</head><p rend="underlined">Textbook:</p><p> Adams, A., 2003. <hi rend="underlined">Law for Business Students</hi> 3<hi rend="sup">rd</hi> Edition, UK: Pearson Education Limited.</p><p> Gerven, W.V., Lever, J., Larouche, P., &amp; et al 1998. <hi rend="underlined">Tort Law, Scope of Protection</hi> Oxford: Hart Publishing</p><p> Goldstein, L., 1987. <hi rend="underlined">Precedent in Law</hi> United States: Oxford University Press, New York.</p><p> Harper, F.V., 1956. <hi rend="underlined">The Law of Torts</hi> Volume 1, Canada: Little, Brown &amp; Company Limited. </p><p> Keeton, W.P., Dobbs, D.B., &amp; Owen, D.G.,1984. <hi rend="underlined">Prosser and Keeton on Torts</hi> 5<hi rend="sup">th</hi> Edition, United States of America: West Group.</p><p> Percy, R.A., 1977. <hi rend="underlined">The Charlesworth on Negligence</hi> 6<hi rend="sup">th</hi> Edition, London: Sweet &amp; Maxwell Limited. </p></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
