<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_0143h" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>REPORT ON THE IMPLEMENTATION OF THE UNCRC IN THE RUSSIAN FEDERATION.</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">The document has a title page which contains:
document title</note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">header: student number, module name, date
footer: page numbers</note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">deleted: 2480 words.
</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">3</p><p n="date">2005-04</p><p n="module title">International Issues in Child Law</p><p n="module code">LA350</p><p n="genre family">Critique</p><p n="discipline">Law</p><p n="disciplinary group">SS</p><p n="grade">M</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">2609</p><p n="number of s-units">98</p><p n="number of p">24</p><p n="number of tables">1</p><p n="number of figures">1</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">1</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">0</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">26.6</p><p n="average s-units per p">4.1</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">f</p><p n="year of birth">1985</p><p n="first language">English</p><p n="education">UKA</p><p n="course">LLB</p><p n="student ID">0143</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><docTitle><titlePart><hi rend="bold">REPORT ON THE IMPLEMENTATION OF THE UNCRC IN THE RUSSIAN FEDERATION.</hi> <hi rend="bold"> April, 2005.</hi> </titlePart></docTitle><docTitle><titlePart><hi rend="bold">REPORT ON THE IMPLEMENTATION OF THE UNCRC IN THE RUSSIAN FEDERATION.</hi> <hi rend="bold"> April, 2005.</hi> </titlePart></docTitle></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">1. FOCUS. </head><p n="p1.24"><s n="s1.4;p1.24">Due to the wide scope of the United Nations Convention on the Rights of the Child, to write a report covering all aspects of its implementation in the Russian Federation would be unsuitable. </s><s n="s2.4;p1.24">This report shall therefore concentrate upon one of the issues that has emerged as particularly pressing within Russia. </s><s n="s3.4;p1.24">This matter is the state care children receive when they are left with no parental care. </s><s n="s4.4;p1.24">The relevant Convention articles shall be divulged and explained throughout the course of the report. </s></p><p n="p2.24"><s n="s1.2;p2.24">The aforementioned concern that this report will concentrate on was brought to the fore by various sources. </s><s n="s2.2;p2.24">Non-Government Organisations, as well as United Nations Committee on the Rights of the Child, highlight this issue as especially problematic within the Russian Federation, as does the considerable amount of international media coverage of this concern. </s></p><p n="p3.24"><s n="s1.2;p3.24">The Russian Federation itself has recognised that this problem needs urgent State attention and has subsequently begun to take some of the necessary action. </s><s n="s2.2;p3.24">As this report will reveal however, this considerable problem will require lengthy, expensive State involvement. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="bold">2. INTRODUCTION TO THE RUSSIAN FEDERATION</hi><ref target="BAWE_0143h-ftnote.001"/>.<note place="foot" id="BAWE_0143h-ftnote.001"><p n="pn1.1"> Map from <seg type="URL" n="http://www.unicef.org/infobycountry/russia.html"/> .</p></note></head><div2><list type="simple"><item><hi rend="bold">POPULATION:</hi> 143.8 million (July 2004) <ref target="BAWE_0143h-ftnote.002"/></item><item><hi rend="bold">AVERAGE AGE:</hi> 34.7 years (2004)</item><item><hi rend="bold">NUMBER OF UNDER 18s:</hi> 35 million (2004)</item><item><hi rend="bold">NUMBER OF UNDER 5s:</hi> 7.3 million (2004</item><item><hi rend="bold">LITERACY:</hi> 99.5% literacy among the over 10s (2002)</item><item><hi rend="bold">UNEMPLOYMENT:</hi> 8.6%<ref target="BAWE_0143h-ftnote.003"/></item></list><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0143h-ftnote.002"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1"><seg type="URL" n="www.mongabay.com/reference/country_profiles/2004-2005.Russia.html"/> </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0143h-ftnote.003"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Figures quoted by ECPAT.net </s></p></note><figure id="BAWE_0143h-pic.001"/><p n="p4.24"><s n="s1.8;p4.24">The Russian Federation has undergone significant social and economic change since the early 1990s. </s><s n="s2.8;p4.24">The fall of Communism in 1992 has led to the introduction of an unpredictable free-market economy that has led to persistently fluctuating wages, increasing poverty and a widening of the gaps between rich and poor and urban and rural areas. </s><s n="s3.8;p4.24">1997 saw the start of the most recent economic crisis, which by August 1998 had led to price increases, and subsequently a fall in income and living standards<ref target="BAWE_0143h-ftnote.004"/>. </s><s n="s4.8;p4.24">The population of Russia is also steadily declining, meaning that the population is gradually ageing. </s><s n="s5.8;p4.24">The federal system in place in Russia means that most issues are dealt with at a regional level, on advice from the central government. </s><s n="s6.8;p4.24">This structure of governance has led to wide diversity between different regions of the Federation in all areas, not just that of the rights of children. </s><s n="s7.8;p4.24">Disparity of funding between regions is a significant obstacle facing the Russian central government. </s><s n="s8.8;p4.24">All of these prominent issues have had an obvious effect on Russia's ability to ensure the rights of children are maximised. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0143h-ftnote.004"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">CRC/C/125/Add.5 15/11/2004 </s></p></note></div2><div2><head rend="bold">RUSSIA AND THE UNCRC. </head><p n="p5.24"><s n="s1.2;p5.24">Russia signed the United Nations Convention on the Rights of the Child on the 26 <hi rend="sup">th</hi> January 1990 making no reservations or declarations, and this entered into force on the 15 <hi rend="sup">th</hi> September of the same year, before Communism fell. </s><s n="s2.2;p5.24">Unsurprisingly, little was done to implement the Convention until democracy was restored to the nation in 1992. </s></p><p n="p6.24"><s n="s1.4;p6.24">In 1993, the Constitution of the Russian Federation was adopted, bringing with it guarantees that motherhood, childhood and the family would be protected by the State<ref target="BAWE_0143h-ftnote.005"/>. </s><s n="s2.4;p6.24">Since this most important of developments, various other pieces of legislation have been drafted to coincide with the Convention, including in 1995 by the Family Code of the Russian Federation. </s><s n="s3.4;p6.24">The Family Code was especially created to ensure all of Russian family law coincided with the principles and provisions of the UNCRC. The Federal Law on the Fundamentals of the System for the Prevention of Neglect and Violations Against Minors, adopted in June 1999, is, the Russian government claim, the 'fundamental law in this sphere'<ref target="BAWE_0143h-ftnote.006"/>, as it contains legal and social guarantees to ensure the protection of the rights, legal interests and security of minors. </s><s n="s4.4;p6.24">Compulsory free education for nine school years and the guarantee of free secondary education have also been introduced through the use of the Constitution and the State Education Act. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0143h-ftnote.005"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">CRC/C/65Add.5, paragraph 31. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0143h-ftnote.006"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Implementation of the Convention on the Rights of the Child: Commentary by NGOs, September 10th 1999, question one. </s></p></note><p n="p7.24"><s n="s1.3;p7.24">One of the most important national developments in relation to the implementation of the Convention was the 1997 introduction of the post of Commissioner for Human Rights in the Russian Federation, and later the addition of a Commission and an Ombudsman, all charged with the same task. </s><s n="s2.3;p7.24">This, in theory is to provide state protection for all civil rights and freedoms, including those of children<ref target="BAWE_0143h-ftnote.007"/>. </s><s n="s3.3;p7.24">The effectiveness of these posts however, will be questioned later. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0143h-ftnote.007"><p n="pn1.1"><s rend="italic" n="s1.2;pn1.1">Ibid. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">paragraph 44. </s></p></note><p n="p8.24"><s n="s1.9;p8.24">Official statistics would suggest that the state of the children of Russia has improved since ratification. </s><s n="s2.9;p8.24">Infant mortality is gradually falling (down from 17.2 per thousand in 1997 to 16 for 2003<ref target="BAWE_0143h-ftnote.008"/>), and vaccination rates are increasing, improving the children's Article 6 right to life. </s><s n="s3.9;p8.24">Other statistics however, tell a very different story. </s><s n="s4.9;p8.24">As a direct result of the 1998 economic crisis, various regions had to reduce payments to families with children, or limit them to families living below the poverty line only<ref target="BAWE_0143h-ftnote.009"/>. </s><s n="s5.9;p8.24">The Committee on the Rights of the Child has heard criticism of the newly reformed education system from Russian NGOs, stating that approximately 2.5million children still do not study anywhere<ref target="BAWE_0143h-ftnote.010"/>. </s><s n="s6.9;p8.24">In Russia as a whole, something like 50,000 children run away from home each year<ref target="BAWE_0143h-ftnote.011"/>. </s><s n="s7.9;p8.24">In 2003, 27% of the Russian population were living below the internationally recognised subsistence level of $73 per month<ref target="BAWE_0143h-ftnote.012"/>. </s><s n="s8.9;p8.24">These figures are merely a sample of a collection of damning evidence that NGOs are always ready to cite to 'prove' Russia's failings in the field of the rights of children. </s><s n="s9.9;p8.24">As will be explained below however, there have been some improvements, and there are some mechanisms in place to ensure other areas are developed also. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0143h-ftnote.008"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1"><seg type="URL" n="http://www.unicef.org/infobycountry/russia.html"/> </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0143h-ftnote.009"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">CRC/C/SR/565, paragraph 3. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0143h-ftnote.010"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Committee on the Rights of the Child, Day of General Discussion, "State Violence Against Children", Submission by Russian NGOs. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0143h-ftnote.011"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1"><seg type="URL" n="http://pangaea.org/street_children/russia/russia2.htm"/> Nikalai Trubilin and Vadim Saitsey. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">'World Health Forum', 1996 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0143h-ftnote.012"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1"><seg type="URL" n="www.mongabay.com/reference/country_profiles/2004-2005.Russia.html"/> </s></p></note></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">3. STATE CARE OF CHILDREN LEFT WITH NO PARENTAL CARE. </head><div2><head rend="bold">STEPS TAKEN BY THE STATE. </head><p n="p9.24"><s n="s1.6;p9.24">The Russian Federation recognised that the way it dealt with children left with no parental care was unacceptable. </s><s n="s2.6;p9.24">The number of children left like this is persistently increasing, and at the end of 2001 reached 685,132<ref target="BAWE_0143h-ftnote.013"/>, a 10% increase since 1998. </s><s n="s3.6;p9.24">The common estimate of the number of 'social orphans', that is, those with at least one living parent, is 95% of this number<ref target="BAWE_0143h-ftnote.014"/>. </s><s n="s4.6;p9.24">The reasons for this ever increasing number of children abandoned are numerous, but invariably lead back to the economic crisis facing their families. </s><s n="s5.6;p9.24">Wages are falling and prices are increasing, leaving families with not enough money to feed and clothe their children. </s><s n="s6.6;p9.24">200,000 children were placed in State orphanages and boarding institutions in 1999, the rest with either close relatives, or adoptive or foster families. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0143h-ftnote.013"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">CRC/C/125/Add.5, paragraph 146. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0143h-ftnote.014"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Committee on the Rights of the Child, Day of General Discussion, "State Violence Against Children", Submission by Russian NGOs. </s></p></note><p n="p10.24"><s n="s1.4;p10.24">The 1995 Family Code of the Russian Federation established arrangements for children left with no parental care that are in line with the UNCRC. This Code states that adoption will always be the favoured way of raising children, followed by the fostering of child, and then temporary placement with a receiving family. </s><s n="s2.4;p10.24">Institutional care is a last resort only. </s><s n="s3.4;p10.24">These changes have been made in line with Article 20 UNCRC, which states that children 'temporarily or permanently deprived of his or her family environment' should receive special state attention, and if possible state care should include foster placement or adoption, 'or if necessary placement in suitable institutions for the care of children'<ref target="BAWE_0143h-ftnote.015"/>. </s><s n="s4.4;p10.24">In 2001, a State databank was set up to monitor the care received by children left with no parental care. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0143h-ftnote.015"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">UNCRC Article 20.3 </s></p></note><p n="p11.24"><s n="s1.2;p11.24">The Russian Government realises that the large boarding establishments that exist to house abandoned children are unacceptable and against a child's Article 27 right to an adequate standard of living, and their Article 3 right to have their best interests promoted wherever possible. </s><s n="s2.2;p11.24">They have therefore begun to break these institutions up into smaller units, to make them more like the family environment that these children are lacking<ref target="BAWE_0143h-ftnote.016"/>. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0143h-ftnote.016"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">CRC/C/125/Add.5, paragraph 150. </s></p></note><p n="p12.24"><s n="s1.5;p12.24">The introduction of foster care and the concept of 'receiving families' in 1996 into Russian family law are both direct results of the Convention. </s><s n="s2.5;p12.24">Russia has realised that children do not advance to their full potential in large, crowded institutions, and that this contravenes their Article 6 right to development. </s><s n="s3.5;p12.24">One of the focuses of the current government, under President Putin, in relation to the rights of deserted children has therefore become the progression of the State systems of care within families. </s><s n="s4.5;p12.24">The Government is proud that the numbers of children being adopted and fostered are rising steadily. </s><s n="s5.5;p12.24">The chart below comes from Russia's 2001 report to the Committee<ref target="BAWE_0143h-ftnote.017"/>. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0143h-ftnote.017"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">CRC/C/125/Add.5, paragraph 146. </s></p></note><table id="BAWE_0143h-tab.001"><row><cell/></row></table></div2><div2><head rend="bold">CONTINUING PROBLEMS. </head><p n="p13.24"><s n="s1.2;p13.24">The obvious continuing problem in relation to Russian orphans is the ever-increasing number of them. </s><s n="s2.2;p13.24">Until the State economy becomes stable, and enables both the federal and regional governments to make permanent commitments to the funding of the family welfare system, then families will continually be left with such a scarcity of money that they feel it necessary to take the most severe of steps: the abandonment of their babies and children to the state. </s></p><p n="p14.24"><s n="s1.6;p14.24">The Government admitted in 1999<ref target="BAWE_0143h-ftnote.018"/> that any furthering of the fostering scheme was being held back substantially by the lack of national and regional funding. </s><s n="s2.6;p14.24">Any country in economic crisis has to prioritise funding, and the Russian Federation is seemingly reluctant to finance the much needed change to their system for the State care of children. </s><s n="s3.6;p14.24">Russian NGOs claim that the above figures quoted by the State do not reflect the fact that the majority of adoptive and foster families are actually close relatives of the child involved. </s><s n="s4.6;p14.24">They claim therefore, that the Russian system is not as successful as State reports to the Committee have claimed<ref target="BAWE_0143h-ftnote.019"/>. </s><s n="s5.6;p14.24">It is also claimed in the same report that more money is spent by the regional governments of Russia on funding the current unacceptable institutions, than implementing the changes needed to bring the State to a standard tolerable under the Convention. </s><s n="s6.6;p14.24">(There is no official data to prove this fact however). </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0143h-ftnote.018"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Implementation of the Convention on the Rights of the Child: Commentary by NGOs, September 10th 1999. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0143h-ftnote.019"><p n="pn1.1"><s rend="italic" n="s1.2;pn1.1">Ibid. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">at question seventeen. </s></p></note><p n="p15.24"><s n="s1.3;p15.24">Another continuing problem is the structure of the Russian methods for protection of the rights of children. </s><s n="s2.3;p15.24">After the creation of both the Commission for Human Rights, and the later implementation of an Ombudsman for Human Rights, it was expected that children would have various routes open to them to complain about the State care they were receiving. </s><s n="s3.3;p15.24">This would then, in theory lead to an improvement of the care given. </s></p><p n="p16.24"><s n="s1.3;p16.24">If a report by Human Rights Watch in 1998 is to be taken at face value however, children left to the care of State institutions are receiving ever worsening levels of care<ref target="BAWE_0143h-ftnote.020"/>. </s><s n="s2.3;p16.24">This report details children being subjected to 'cruel, inhuman and degrading treatment by institution staff', a possible signal that the recently created State support system may not be working as adequately as it should be. </s><s n="s3.3;p16.24">This treatment is a blatant violation of the children's Article 19 right to protection from 'all forms of physical or mental violence, injury or abuse, neglect or negligent treatment, maltreatment or exploitation', and is also evidence that the current 'safeguards' for the rights of children in state care are not functioning properly, if at all. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0143h-ftnote.020"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">"Children Abandoned to the Russian State: Cruelty and Neglect in Russian Orphanages", Report prepared for the UN Committee on the Rights of the Child by Human Rights Watch, October 1998. </s></p></note><p n="p17.24"><s n="s1.3;p17.24">Press reports from all over the world describe the dire conditions inside 'Dom Rebyonkas' (Russian baby-houses). </s><s n="s2.3;p17.24">One story states that the biggest problem facing them is lack of funding to provide anything but the bare necessities of food and shelter to the children<ref target="BAWE_0143h-ftnote.021"/>. </s><s n="s3.3;p17.24">Lack of funding is not something that is easily solved, and some possible solutions to this problem are detailed below. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0143h-ftnote.021"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">"<hi rend="italic">Russian orphans rarely overcome their dim future",</hi> Mike Thompson, Detroit Free Press <seg type="URL" n="www.freep.com"/>, 7th September 2004. </s></p></note></div2><div2><head rend="bold">POSSIBLE SOLUTIONS. </head><p n="p18.24"><s n="s1.4;p18.24">With regard to children orphaned or abandoned, there seems to be a great need for new systems to guard their rights. </s><s n="s2.4;p18.24">If the NGO and press reports are accurate, then there are horrendous violations occurring all over Russia that are simply not acceptable. </s><s n="s3.4;p18.24">Funding need not be an issue- all the children require is a safe environment in which to begin to develop both physically and socially. </s><s n="s4.4;p18.24">This setting should include all the education and health care that a child would receive if they were being brought up in a family, in compliance with the Article 2 right to non-discrimination. </s></p><p n="p19.24"><s n="s1.3;p19.24">As Russia becomes more financially able to do so, additions can be made to the system as and when they are deemed necessary. </s><s n="s2.3;p19.24">It is obvious though that the Commission and the Ombudsman are not working, and need re-evaluating. </s><s n="s3.3;p19.24">A team of independent inspectors and an improved system through which children can make complaints about their treatment should be the main priority of the Russian government. </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">4. THE FUTURE OF THE CONVENTION IN RUSSIA. </head><p n="p20.24"><s n="s1.3;p20.24">It is obvious from even a basic study into the workings of the UNCRC in the Russian Federation that there are still some serious flaws in its implementation. </s><s n="s2.3;p20.24">These defects seem to be due to the lack of funding available to help the State improve the implementation of this Convention. </s><s n="s3.3;p20.24">There is serious consideration needed surrounding most areas of children's rights, as is evidenced from the Committee on the Rights of the Child's reports regarding Russia. </s></p><p n="p21.24"><s n="s1.6;p21.24">The Committee has recommended that Russia strengthens its links with non-governmental organizations. </s><s n="s2.6;p21.24">The NGOs themselves, in their commentary of 1999<ref target="BAWE_0143h-ftnote.022"/> stated that NGOs were being deprived of government support due to the Law on Social Contracts not being passed. </s><s n="s3.6;p21.24">By 2002 however, 120 organisations with international or inter-Russian status whose basic work involved children's rights were registered with the Russian Ministry of Justice<ref target="BAWE_0143h-ftnote.023"/>. </s><s n="s4.6;p21.24">Further evidence of NGO involvement in implementation was the First All-Russian Conference of NGOs, "Civil Society for the Children of Russia"<ref target="BAWE_0143h-ftnote.024"/> which took place in March 2001. </s><s n="s5.6;p21.24">Here, more than 100 organisations from all over Russia congregated to discuss the rights f children in their nation. </s><s n="s6.6;p21.24">This shows that the status of NGOs in Russia is improving, giving the Russian Government opportunity to allow these organizations to take some responsibility for implementing and monitoring the UNCRC. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0143h-ftnote.022"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Implementation of the Convention on the Rights of the Child: Commentary by NGOs, September 10th 1999, question five. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0143h-ftnote.023"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">CRC/C/125/Add.5. paragraph 49 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0143h-ftnote.024"><p n="pn1.1"><s rend="italic" n="s1.1;pn1.1">ibid. </s></p></note><p n="p22.24"><s n="s1.3;p22.24">Public education about the rights of children is also a vital part of implementation (Article 42 of the Convention encourages wide dissemination of the rights given by it). </s><s n="s2.3;p22.24">2001 was the Russian Year of the Child<ref target="BAWE_0143h-ftnote.025"/>, and the volunteer movement in relation to children is growing rapidly<ref target="BAWE_0143h-ftnote.026"/>. </s><s n="s3.3;p22.24">This would indicate that the public of Russia is gradually coming to appreciate that their children deserve to have their rights realized, and that action needs to be taken to achieve this. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0143h-ftnote.025"><p n="pn1.1"><s rend="italic" n="s1.2;pn1.1">ibid. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">paragraph 44 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0143h-ftnote.026"><p n="pn1.1"><s rend="italic" n="s1.2;pn1.1">ibid. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">paragraph 51 </s></p></note><p n="p23.24"><s n="s1.7;p23.24">Perhaps the biggest issue surrounding Russian implementation of the Convention as a whole is funding. </s><s n="s2.7;p23.24">Although there are not necessarily State funds available to spend on children (and it is inappropriate to discuss the complicated economic issues surrounding this in this report), there are international lending organizations that would be able to help. </s><s n="s3.7;p23.24">The World Bank is already financing various medical and educational programs, and the Committee has stated that it would be suitable for other agencies to help in a similar manner<ref target="BAWE_0143h-ftnote.027"/>. </s><s n="s4.7;p23.24">This would allow Russia to fund any schemes necessary to ensure the rights of its children. </s><s n="s5.7;p23.24">It would also however, require the Federation to succumb to large amounts of debt that would need to be repaid as soon as the economy became more stable. </s><s n="s6.7;p23.24">Any loan would also enable Russia to tackle its main problem in relation to children, that of families living in poverty. </s><s n="s7.7;p23.24">Child benefit payments are currently in heavy arrears<ref target="BAWE_0143h-ftnote.028"/>, and this needs to be resolved to ensure that family life is as fulfilling as it can be for children. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0143h-ftnote.027"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">CRC/C/SR.564 paragraph 42. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0143h-ftnote.028"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Implementation of the Convention on the Rights of the Child: Commentary by NGOs, September 10th 1999, question eleven. </s></p></note><p n="p24.24"><s n="s1.4;p24.24">Overall, Russia has come some way to improving its implementation of the Convention in the 13 years since it ratified. </s><s n="s2.4;p24.24">These improvements however, are not enough, and various sources of evidence suggest that children are still not being afforded all their rights. </s><s n="s3.4;p24.24">Article 4 of the Convention recognises that it may not always be economically possible for a State to implement all of the Articles immediately, but it also states that this should be done as soon as possible. </s><s n="s4.4;p24.24">Russia therefore needs to re-evaluate its systems and take heed of all recommendations made by the committee, not just for care of orphans, but for all of the areas covered by the Convention. </s></p></div1></body><back><div1 type="bibliography"><head rend="bold">SOURCES OF INFORMATION:</head><div2 type="bibliography"><head rend="bold">WRITTEN RESOURCES:</head><p>Conway H L. <hi rend="italic">"Family Law Key Facts."</hi> Hodder and Stoughton, edition one, 2004. </p><p>Cretney S M, Masson J M &amp; Bailey-Harris R. <hi rend="italic">"Principles of Family Law."</hi> Thomson, Sweet and Maxwell, seventh edition, 2002.</p><p>Hale B, Pearl D, Cooke E &amp; Bates P. <hi rend="italic">"The Family, Law and Society- Cases and Materials."</hi> Butterworths Lexis Nexis, fifth edition, 2002.</p><p>Probert, R. "<hi rend="italic">Cretney's Family Law."</hi> Thomson, Sweet and Maxwell, 2003. Fifth Edition.</p></div2><div2 type="bibliography"><head rend="bold">INTERNET-BASED RESOURCES:</head><div3 type="bibliography"><head rend="bold">United Nations Documentation: </head><p><seg type="URL" n="http://www.crin.org/docs/resources/treaties/crc.25/russngos.pdf"/> - Committee on the Rights of the child, day of general discussion. 22<hi rend="sup">nd</hi> September 2000, submission by Russian NGOs.</p><p><seg type="URL" n="http://www.unhchr.ch/tbs/doc.nsf/(Symbol)/d71205c3fb86454f8025670d0053ef48?Opendocument"/> - Periodic reports of States parties due in 1997: Russian Federation. 20/11/98. CRC/C/65/Add.5. Accessed April 2005. Committee on the Rights of the Child.</p><p><seg type="URL" n="http://www.unhchr.ch/tbs/doc.nsf/(Symbol)/7e6d42bb52bcdcf180256804004d41e0?Opendocument"/> - Summary record of the 565th meeting: Russian Federation. 30/09/99. CRC/C/SR.565. Accessed April 2005. Committee on the Rights of the Child.</p><p><seg type="URL" n="http://www.unhchr.ch/tbs/doc.nsf/(Symbol)/58142ba0ac006af0802568240034ec2f?Opendocument"/> - Summary record of the 564th meeting: Russian Federation. 25/10/99. CRC/C/SR.564. Accessed April 2005. Committee on the Rights of the Child.</p><p><seg type="URL" n="http://www.unhchr.ch/tbs/doc.nsf/(Symbol)/f60a0928c30f787980256811003b8d5d?Opendocument"/> - Concluding Observations of the Committee on the Rights of the Child: Russian Federation. 10/11/99. CRC/C/15/Add.110. Accessed April 2005. Committee on the Rights of the Child.</p><p><seg type="URL" n="http://www.unhchr.ch/tbs/doc.nsf/(Symbol)/bb8eec5d7497ba60c1256fdc0052adcb?Opendocument"/> - Committee on the Rights of the Child- Consideration of Reports Submitted by States Parties Under Article 44 of the Convention - Third periodic reports of States parties due in 2001, CRC/C/125/Add.5, 15 November 2004. Accessed April 2005.</p><p><seg type="URL" n="http://www.unhchr.ch/tbs/doc.nsf"/> - Committee on the Rights of the Child homepage - Accessed April 2005.</p></div3><div3 type="bibliography"><head rend="bold">Non-Government Organisations:</head><p><seg type="URL" n="http://www.yapi.org/uncrc/"/> - Youth Advocate Program International, 'The United Nations Convention on the Rights of the Child - Issue Summary'. Accessed March 2005.</p><p><seg type="URL" n="http://www.unicef.org/infobycountry/russia.html"/> - "At a Glance: Russian Federation." ©UNICEF 2004. Accessed April 2005.</p><p><seg type="URL" n="http://www.ecpat.net/eng/Ecpat_inter/projects/monitoring/online_database/countries.asp?arrCountryID=143&amp;CountryProfile=facts&amp;CSEC=Overview,Prostitution,Pronography,trafficking&amp;Implement=Coordination_cooperation,Recovery&amp;Nationalplans=&amp;DisplayBy=optDisplayCountry"/> - ECPAT International Russia Homepage. Accessed April 2005.</p><p><seg type="URL" n="http://www.russianorphan.org/orphan_facts/orphan_facts.htm"/> - Russian Orphan Aid Foundation. "Orphan Facts and Statistics." ©2004 Ascent Russian Orphan Aid Foundation. Accessed March 2004.</p><p><seg type="URL" n="http://www.crin.org/docs/resources/treaties/cdrom1/russiacrc-engngocomment.doc"/> - <hi rend="italic">'Implementation of the United Nations Convention on the Rights of the Child: Commentary by Non-Governmental Organizations'</hi>, Boris Altshuter, Lyubov Kushnir and Anatoly Severny, 10 September 1999. Accessed April 2005.</p><p><seg type="URL" n="http://pangaea.org/street_children/russia/russia2.htm"/> - <hi rend="italic">'World Health Forum'</hi>, Nikalai Trubilin, and Vadim Saitsey, 1996. Accessed April 2005. </p></div3><div3 type="bibliography"><head rend="bold">Media Representation:</head><p><seg type="URL" n="http://www.mosnews.com/news/2004/11/15/prospersh.shtml"/> - The Moscow News, "Russia's Children Go On Sale- The Law Enforcers", 15<hi rend="sup">th</hi> November 2004, </p><p><seg type="URL" n="http://www.freep.com/voices/columnists/emike7_20040907.htm"/> - Detroit Free Press, "Russian Orphans Rarely Overcome Their Dim Future", Mike Thompson, September 7<hi rend="sup">th</hi> 2004.</p><p><seg type="URL" n="http://www.guardian.co.uk/germany/article/0,2763,1285401,00.html"/> - The Guardian, "Schroder Adopts Russian Orphan" Ben Aris, August 18<hi rend="sup">th</hi> 2004.</p></div3></div2></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
