<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_0143a" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>In reference to Cutter v. Eagle Star Insurance Co. Ltd [1998] 4 All ER 417, HL, please address the following points:</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">header: date, module name, student number
footer: page numbers</note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">deleted: WORDS: 1,113
</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">1</p><p n="date">2003-12</p><p n="module title">The Modern English Legal System</p><p n="module code">LA115</p><p n="genre family">Critique</p><p n="discipline">Law</p><p n="disciplinary group">SS</p><p n="grade">M</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">1065</p><p n="number of s-units">44</p><p n="number of p">11</p><p n="number of tables">0</p><p n="number of figures">0</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">0</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">0</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">24.2</p><p n="average s-units per p">4.0</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">f</p><p n="year of birth">1985</p><p n="first language">English</p><p n="education">UKA</p><p n="course">LLB</p><p n="student ID">0143</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><docTitle><titlePart><hi rend="bold">In reference to <hi rend="italic">Cutter v. Eagle Star Insurance Co. Ltd [1998] 4 All ER 417, HL</hi>, please address the following points: What are the material facts of the case?</hi> <hi rend="bold"> Which point of statutory interpretation arose in the case?</hi> <hi rend="bold"> Which rule of statutory interpretation was applied in the case and why?</hi> </titlePart></docTitle></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="section"><p n="p1.11"><s n="s1.7;p1.11">When <hi rend="italic">Cutter v.</hi> </s><s rend="italic" n="s2.7;p1.11">Eagle Star Insurance Co. </s><s n="s3.7;p1.11"><hi rend="italic">Ltd [1998]</hi> came to the House of Lords, the material facts of the case had already been established during its process through both the County Court and the Court of Appeal. </s><s n="s4.7;p1.11">These were that Mr Cutter had been injured when some leaking gas had ignited in the car in which he was positioned in the passenger seat. </s><s n="s5.7;p1.11">These basic facts were not what were under dispute in the House of Lords; Mr Cutter had received damages from the driver of the car (who had lit the cigarette that ultimately led to the explosion) in separate proceedings. </s><s n="s6.7;p1.11">What <hi rend="bold">was</hi> on dispute was whether the insurance company should pay Mr Cutter or not. </s><s n="s7.7;p1.11">The point of disagreement between the parties arose because the car had been parked in a multi-storey car-park, and the relevant statutory provisions provided that Eagle Star was liable to insure any person injured through 'the use of a vehicle on a road'<ref target="BAWE_0143a-ftnote.001"/>. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0143a-ftnote.001"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Section 145 (3) (a) of the Road Traffic Act 1988 </s></p></note><p n="p2.11"><s n="s1.2;p2.11">The phrase 'on a road' therefore, was the point of argument between the parties; did a multi-storey car-park qualify as a road? </s><s n="s2.2;p2.11">Or, as the County Court and Court of Appeal had previously decided, did it not? </s></p><p n="p3.11"><s n="s1.2;p3.11">This phrase was consequently also the point of statutory interpretation which the Lords had to deal with. </s><s n="s2.2;p3.11">The basic principle of statutory interpretation is for the judiciary to discover the will of Parliament; to ask themselves the question, 'What would Parliament have wanted the outcome of this case to be?'. </s></p><p n="p4.11"><s n="s1.9;p4.11">In this case, the Lords used the literal approach to statutory interpretation. </s><s n="s2.9;p4.11">Using this method, they look, as the name may suggest, at the literal meaning of the words of a statute, and apply them. </s><s n="s3.9;p4.11">Had this caused 'inconsistency, absurdity or inconvenience'<ref target="BAWE_0143a-ftnote.002"/>, then the judges may have gone on to apply the golden rule. </s><s n="s4.9;p4.11">This is only ever applied where use of the literal rule would create an unjust or illogical outcome. </s><s n="s5.9;p4.11">Through this approach, judges can either choose between two conflicting definitions, as used in <hi rend="italic">Adler v.</hi> </s><s n="s6.9;p4.11"><hi rend="italic">George [1964]</hi> or simply apply the legislation in a way, although contrary to the written statute, that they believe Parliament would prefer to the literal application, as used in <hi rend="italic">Re Sigsworth [1935]</hi>. </s><s n="s7.9;p4.11">In very rare cases, the mischief rule can be applied. </s><s n="s8.9;p4.11">This is where the judiciary can use existing common law rules alongside the rules established in <hi rend="italic">Haydon's Case [1584]</hi> to decide what new statutory legislation was intended to do. </s><s n="s9.9;p4.11">This approach however, also had no place in the Eagle Star case because it was obvious to the Lords what the legislation was intended to do: ensure insurance companies paid out to those who deserved compensating. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0143a-ftnote.002"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Lord Blackburn, <hi rend="italic">River Wear Commissioners v.</hi> </s><s rend="italic" n="s2.2;pn1.1">Adamson[1877] </s></p></note><p n="p5.11"><s n="s1.7;p5.11">The Lords themselves defined the point of interpretation as, "...the construction and application of the word 'road' in section 145 (3) (a) of the Road Traffic Act 1988." </s><s n="s2.7;p5.11">Their first point of reference was the intrinsic definition of the word 'road'. </s><s n="s3.7;p5.11">They stated that, "For England and Wales it [road] means 'any highway and any other road to which the public has access..." </s><ref target="BAWE_0143a-ftnote.003"/><s n="s4.7;p5.11">The Lords also looked upon the decision made in the Court of Appeal, and the references that Kilner Brown J. had made during that hearing. </s><s n="s5.7;p5.11">They took into consideration his citation of <hi rend="italic">Oxford v.</hi> </s><s rend="italic" n="s6.7;p5.11">Austin [1981] R.T.R. 416 at pg. </s><s n="s7.7;p5.11"><hi rend="italic">418</hi>, and the quotation to which he referred that defined a road as, "...a definable was over which vehicles may pass which in plain common sense qualifies as a road." </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0143a-ftnote.003"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Section 192, Road Traffic Act 1988 </s></p></note><p n="p6.11"><s n="s1.4;p6.11">Other sources upon which they looked were other sections of the Road Traffic Act 1988 itself, and also various other cases where the meaning of the word 'road' was put into dispute. </s><s n="s2.4;p6.11">The 1988 Act provided a very helpful phrase that suggested that Parliament intended to distinguish between roads and parking places. </s><s n="s3.4;p6.11">Section 25<ref target="BAWE_0143a-ftnote.004"/> starts with the words, "If, while a motor vehicle is on a road or on a parking place..." </s><s n="s4.4;p6.11">They also refer to the Road Traffic Regulation Act 1984, because this Act also recognises the difference between parking places for vehicles and roads. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0143a-ftnote.004"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Section 25 refers to the offence of tampering with a vehicle. </s></p></note><p n="p7.11"><s n="s1.2;p7.11">Their use of the 1984 Act aided their overall intention which, ultimately, was to find what Parliament would want to be construed from the word 'road'. </s><s n="s2.2;p7.11">They recognised that Parliament's distinction between a road a parking place can be found in the provisions forming Part IV of the 1984 Act, and that section 57 (1) (b) in particular suggests that Parliament would not intend for a parking place to be viewed as a road. </s></p><p n="p8.11"><s n="s1.3;p8.11">As well as using both intrinsic and extrinsic aides to their interpretation, the Lords also took into consideration the 'physical character and function' of a normal road. </s><s n="s2.3;p8.11">Through doing this, they became closer still to finding an exact literal meaning to the word 'road'. </s><s n="s3.3;p8.11">They came to the conclusion that a road usually has obvious limits and boundaries and serves as a 'means of access', whereas the primary function of a car park is to enable vehicles to 'stand and wait'. </s></p><p n="p9.11"><s n="s1.2;p9.11">Consequently, the Lords recognised that to give the 'road' and 'parking place' the same meaning would take the language of the Act 'beyond the literal meaning of the word[s]' and would be 'stretching the language'<ref target="BAWE_0143a-ftnote.005"/>, and therefore allowed the appeal of Eagle Star Insurance Co. </s><s n="s2.2;p9.11">Ltd. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0143a-ftnote.005"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Lord Clyde, Cutter v. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">Eagle Star </s></p></note><p n="p10.11"><s n="s1.4;p10.11">In his final summing up, Lord Clyde expressed his feelings on the decision that he and his colleagues clearly had to reach. </s><s n="s2.4;p10.11">He stated that he felt 'sympathy' for the victims (Cutter was heard with another case<ref target="BAWE_0143a-ftnote.006"/>), but that it was up to Parliament to decide how people in these circumstances should be compensated in the future. </s><s n="s3.4;p10.11">This point had been raised earlier in Clyde's speech when he stated that if the Act needed extending or amending, then that was a 'matter for Parliament to achieve'. </s><s n="s4.4;p10.11">This is evidence that although the judiciary invariably follow the rules of statutory interpretation to ensure that just outcomes are achieved, they often realise that Parliament has not legislated as fully as it could to achieve the maximum justice it could in our legal system. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0143a-ftnote.006"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Cutter was heard with Clarke v. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">Kato, Smith and General Accident Fire and Life Assurance Corporation Plc. </s></p></note><p n="p11.11"><s n="s1.2;p11.11">The point of law which the decision of this case turned upon was whether or not a car-park should be included under the heading of a 'road'. </s><s n="s2.2;p11.11">The ratio decidendi therefore, was that it did not, and that only when victims were injured on roads were insurance companies obliged to compensate them. </s></p></div1></body><back><div1 type="bibliography"><head rend="bold">BIBLIOGRAPHY</head><p>Cutter v Eagle Star Insurance Co. Ltd. [1198] 4 All ER 417, HL</p><p>"<hi rend="italic">The</hi> English Legal System" 6<hi rend="sup">th</hi> Ed. Gary Slapper and David Kelly, Cavendish Publishing Ltd, 2003.</p></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
