<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_0144d" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>'Braudel betrayed the Annales tradition.' Discuss.</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">Language used in quote: <foreign id="English">English</foreign></note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">header: student name
footer: page numbers</note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">deleted: Word Count, 2,265.
</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">3</p><p n="date">2006-02</p><p n="module title">Historiography</p><p n="module code">HI323</p><p n="genre family">Essay</p><p n="discipline">History</p><p n="disciplinary group">AH</p><p n="grade">M</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">2288</p><p n="number of s-units">53</p><p n="number of p">13</p><p n="number of tables">0</p><p n="number of figures">0</p><p n="number of block quotes">4</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">0</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">0</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">43.2</p><p n="average s-units per p">4.1</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">m</p><p n="year of birth">1984</p><p n="first language">English</p><p n="education">UKA</p><p n="course">History</p><p n="student ID">0144</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><docTitle><titlePart rend="bold">'Braudel betrayed the <hi rend="italic">Annales</hi> tradition.' Discuss. </titlePart></docTitle></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="section"><p n="p1.13"><s n="s1.4;p1.13">The foundations of the group of historians now known as the <hi rend="italic">Annales</hi> 'school' were laid when in 1929 Marc Bloch and Lucien Febvre published the journal <hi rend="italic">Annales d'histoire économique et sociale</hi>. </s><s n="s2.4;p1.13">Since this pivotal moment, the <hi rend="italic">Annales</hi> have been credited with undermining the positivist definition of historical fact, destroying the taboo on unwritten evidence, imposing a dialogue with other disciplines, discrediting the history of events, and rejecting the primacy of political history.<ref target="BAWE_0144d-ftnote.001"/> Importantly, this tradition cannot be attributed to a single historian, nor has it employed a 'clear-cut' paradigm.<ref target="BAWE_0144d-ftnote.002"/> 'Their work is united, however, in terms of theoretical and methodological principles embodied in the journal <hi rend="italic">Annales: Économies, Sociétés, Civilisations</hi> whence their name derives." </s><ref target="BAWE_0144d-ftnote.003"/><s n="s3.4;p1.13">Trevor-Roper helpfully captures these elements of unity, emphasising their attempts to grasp the totality and cohesion of every historical period, their conviction that history is at least partly determined by forces which are external to man, and their determination to reduce areas of incomprehension by rigorous statistical analysis.<ref target="BAWE_0144d-ftnote.004"/> Fernand Braudel's contribution to the <hi rend="italic">Annales</hi> tradition, although significant, should be therefore, placed within a wider tradition of conjectural fluidity and development. </s><s n="s4.4;p1.13">Far from betraying this tradition, we can credit Braudel with furthering the principle for which the <hi rend="italic">Annales</hi> stood most, promulgating an ideal of <hi rend="italic">histoire totale.</hi> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0144d-ftnote.001"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Jean Glénisson, 'France', in Georg G. Iggers and Harold T. Parker (eds), <hi rend="italic">International Handbook of Historical Studies: Contemporary Research and Theory</hi> (Connecticut, 1979), p. 176, cited in Anna Green and Kathleen Troup (eds),<hi rend="italic"> The Houses of History</hi> (Manchester, 1999), p. 87. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0144d-ftnote.002"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Anna Green and Kathleen Troup (eds),<hi rend="italic"> The Houses of History</hi> (Manchester, 1999), p. 87. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0144d-ftnote.003"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0144d-ftnote.004"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.3;pn1.1">H. R. Trevor-Roper, 'Fernand Braudel, the <hi rend="italic">Annales,</hi> and the Mediterranean', <hi rend="italic">The Journal of Modern History,</hi> vol. 44, no. </s><s n="s2.3;pn1.1">4. </s><s n="s3.3;pn1.1">(Dec., 1972), pp. 470-1. </s></p></note><p n="p2.13"><s n="s1.8;p2.13">Braudel led the <hi rend="italic">Annales</hi> group of historians from 1956 to the early 1970s. </s><s n="s2.8;p2.13"><hi rend="italic">La Méditerranée et le monde Méditerranéen à l'époque de Philippe II,</hi> published in 1949 and proclaimed as Braudel's most profound and influential work, epitomises his method of historical investigation and writing. </s><s n="s3.8;p2.13">Indeed, Trevor-Roper affirms, 'no single book so amply and vividly illustrates, in its practice, the whole philosophy of the <hi rend="italic">Annales</hi> school." </s><ref target="BAWE_0144d-ftnote.005"/><s n="s4.8;p2.13">However, as Febvre himself notes, <hi rend="italic">La Méditerranée</hi> 'gave us an entirely new dimension and one which, in a sense, is revolutionary. </s><s n="s5.8;p2.13">The book is a manifesto, a sign. </s><s n="s6.8;p2.13">And, I have no hesitation in saying so, it is a milestone." </s><ref target="BAWE_0144d-ftnote.006"/><s n="s7.8;p2.13">For Braudel did not follow the newer approaches to economic and social history embodied by Bloch's and Febvre's work, choosing not to refer to Bloch's innovative analyses of agricultural patterns of production, nor employing Febvre's idea that religious, literary, and cultural activity is coerced and guided by 'mental tools' characteristic of a given period.<ref target="BAWE_0144d-ftnote.007"/> Instead, Braudel envisaged three layers of historical time, each moving at a different speed, and each aligned with different historical topics. </s><s n="s8.8;p2.13">Anna Green and Kathleen Troup provide us with a useful synopsis, </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0144d-ftnote.005"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid., p. 472. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0144d-ftnote.006"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Lucien Febvre, 'A New Kind of History', in <hi rend="italic">A New Kind of History: From the Writings of Lucien Febvre</hi> (ed. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">Peter Burke, London, 1973), p. 37. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0144d-ftnote.007"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.3;pn1.1">Samuel Kinser, 'Annaliste Paradism? </s><s n="s2.3;pn1.1">The Geohistorical Structuralism of Fernand Braudel', <hi rend="italic">The American Historical Review,</hi> vol. 86, no. </s><s n="s3.3;pn1.1">1 (Feb., 1981), p. 66. </s></p></note><quote lang="English">The slowest moving, 'man in his relationship to the environment', was geographical time, the 'almost imperceptible' shifting of geology and climate, entailing examination of communications and limits of production. The <hi rend="italic">longue durée</hi> moved in slow cycles of hundreds of years or more. The medium <hi rend="italic">durée,</hi> or <hi rend="italic">conjunctures,</hi> was equivalent to the 'swelling currents' with 'slow but perceptible rhythms', and revolved in ten to fifty year cycles. This middle layer comprised economic cycles, trade, population fluctuations, and prices. His third aspect of time Braudel called <hi rend="italic">histoire événementielle,</hi> 'the ephemera of history', 'crests of foam that the tides of history carry on their strong backs'.<ref target="BAWE_0144d-ftnote.008"/></quote><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0144d-ftnote.008"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Green and Troup, <hi rend="italic">The Houses of History,</hi> p.89. </s></p></note><p n="p3.13"><s n="s1.1;p3.13">Although Braudel thus ignored what seemed to many historians in the 1940s to be the most significant achievements of the first two editors of the <hi rend="italic">Annales,</hi> he echoed and extended their most signal ideological directives, the synthesising of history with other social sciences, the use of statistical analysis, and the attempt to capture <hi rend="italic">histoire totale</hi>.<ref target="BAWE_0144d-ftnote.009"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0144d-ftnote.009"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Kinser, 'Annaliste Paradism?', p. 66. </s></p></note><p n="p4.13"><s n="s1.4;p4.13">Febvre and Bloch rejected the near-monopoly of French history by political and diplomatic topics, an approach they condemned as 'sterile'; instead, they wanted to break down the boundaries between the human sciences, with historians incorporating as many of these disciplines as possible in their work.<ref target="BAWE_0144d-ftnote.010"/> Bloch, arguing in <hi rend="italic">The Historian's Craft,</hi> affirms that 'we have no other remedy than to substitute, in place of the multiple skills of a single man, the pooling of the techniques practiced by different scholars." </s><ref target="BAWE_0144d-ftnote.011"/><s n="s2.4;p4.13">Using a metaphor of a searchlight, Bloch affirms that 'danger threatens only when each searchlight operator claims to see everything by himself, when each canton of learning pretends to national sovereignty." </s><ref target="BAWE_0144d-ftnote.012"/><s n="s3.4;p4.13">Such a metaphor propagates interdisciplinary collaboration. </s><s n="s4.4;p4.13">Febvre, furthermore, is in agreement, </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0144d-ftnote.010"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Green and Troup, <hi rend="italic">The Houses of History,</hi> p.87. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0144d-ftnote.011"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Marc Bloch, <hi rend="italic">The Historian's Craft</hi> (Manchester, 1998), p. 57. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0144d-ftnote.012"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid., p. 124. </s></p></note><quote lang="English">For my part I think we shall need more learning in the future, more intelligence, imagination and breadth of mind, in a word we shall have to approach things on a far larger scale, in order to ask questions which were always badly put in the past, and, particularly to ask, for the first time, questions which no one has yet put and which are extremely vital both to our understanding of the present by means of the past, and of the past by means of the present.<ref target="BAWE_0144d-ftnote.013"/></quote><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0144d-ftnote.013"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Febvre, 'A New Kind of History', p. 33. </s></p></note><p n="p5.13"><s n="s1.4;p5.13">For Febvre, collaboration therefore allowed the added benefits of scale and efficiency, the ability to approach questions and topics previously denied by their complexity, a solution to the task of writing <hi rend="italic">histoire totale</hi>. </s><s n="s2.4;p5.13">Braudel, far from contradicting such a proposition, is in full agreement, arguing that 'each science encroaches on its neighbours, all the while believing it is staying in its own domain... but the crucial thing now is to get together." </s><ref target="BAWE_0144d-ftnote.014"/><s n="s3.4;p5.13">'I would hope that the social sciences, at least provisionally, would suspend their constant border disputes over what is or is not a social science... rather let them try to trace those lines across our research, and make possible the first stages of some sort of coming together." </s><ref target="BAWE_0144d-ftnote.015"/><s n="s4.4;p5.13">The coming together of the different social sciences, sociology, history, and economics, therefore provides a unifying methodological approach to the <hi rend="italic">Annales</hi> tradition, propagated collectively by Bloch, Febvre, and indeed, Braudel. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0144d-ftnote.014"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Fernand Braudel, <hi rend="italic">On History</hi> (Chicago, 1980), p. 25. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0144d-ftnote.015"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid., p. 52. </s></p></note><p n="p6.13"><s n="s1.5;p6.13">Although sometimes mocked and ridiculed for their overuse of quantification, statistical analysis and graphical representation, the <hi rend="italic">Annales</hi> group of historians avidly employ such methods to help construct their <hi rend="italic">histoire totale.</hi> </s><ref target="BAWE_0144d-ftnote.016"/><s n="s2.5;p6.13"> Bloch, writing in <hi rend="italic">The Historian's Craft,</hi> propagates the use of scientific modes and methods of investigation, 'to conform to a sort of pan-scientific ideal." </s><ref target="BAWE_0144d-ftnote.017"/><s n="s3.5;p6.13">With the belief that history is 'vastly indebted' to 'this great scientific effort', Bloch concludes that 'it has taught us to analyse more profoundly, to grasp our problems more firmly, and even, I dare to say, to think less shoddily." </s><ref target="BAWE_0144d-ftnote.018"/><s n="s4.5;p6.13">Indeed, Braudel is in agreement, and has helped to initiate a strong focus on quantitive history among the historians influenced by him.<ref target="BAWE_0144d-ftnote.019"/> Samuel Kinser, in fact attributes the use graphical representation to represent historical change as one of <hi rend="italic">La Méditerranée's</hi> chief attractions, Braudel proving 'unusually adept at presenting immense bodies of documentation in summary visual form." </s><ref target="BAWE_0144d-ftnote.020"/><s n="s5.5;p6.13">Braudel, by readily employing the <hi rend="italic">Annales</hi> statistical methodology, seems far from contradicting the <hi rend="italic">Annales</hi> tradition. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0144d-ftnote.016"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.3;pn1.1">An example of this mockery is provided by J. H. </s><s n="s2.3;pn1.1">Hexter, see J.H. Hexter, 'Fernand Braudel and the Monde Braudellien...', <hi rend="italic">The Journal of Modern History,</hi> vol. 44, no. </s><s n="s3.3;pn1.1">4 (Dec., 1972), pp. 480-539. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0144d-ftnote.017"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Bloch, <hi rend="italic">The Historian's Craft,</hi> p. 12. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0144d-ftnote.018"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0144d-ftnote.019"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Green and Troup, <hi rend="italic">The Houses of History,</hi> p.87. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0144d-ftnote.020"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Kinser, 'Annaliste Paradism?', p. 90. </s></p></note><p n="p7.13"><s n="s1.2;p7.13">Although criticised for its omissions, such as culture, agriculture, law and religion, Braudel's <hi rend="italic">La Méditerranée</hi> converges with Febvre's and Bloch's aim of writing a total history.<ref target="BAWE_0144d-ftnote.021"/> Bloch, arguing in <hi rend="italic">The Historian's Craft,</hi> outlines his struggle to 'penetrate beneath the mere surface of actions, rejecting not only the temptations of legend and rhetoric, but the still more dangerous modern poisons of routine learning and empiricism parading as common sense." </s><ref target="BAWE_0144d-ftnote.022"/><s n="s2.2;p7.13">Braudel, writing some years later, agrees with this notion, </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0144d-ftnote.021"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Green and Troup, <hi rend="italic">The Houses of History,</hi> p.90. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0144d-ftnote.022"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Bloch, <hi rend="italic">The Historian's Craft,</hi> p. 11. </s></p></note><quote lang="English">We do not believe in this cult of demigods, or to put it even more simply, we are against Treitschke's proud and unilateral declaration: 'Men make history.' No, history also makes men and fashions their destiny - anonymous history, working in the depths and most often in silence, whose domain, immense and uncertain as it is, we must now approach.<ref target="BAWE_0144d-ftnote.023"/></quote><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0144d-ftnote.023"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Braudel, <hi rend="italic">On History</hi>, p.10. </s></p></note><p n="p8.13"><s n="s1.6;p8.13">It is this sense of purpose that provides the <hi rend="italic">Annales</hi> with an enduring tradition, rather than a clear single paradigm. </s><s n="s2.6;p8.13">Braudel, writing his in his <hi rend="italic">Personal Testimony</hi>, affirms that the <hi rend="italic">Annales, '</hi>despite their vivacity, never constituted a school in the strict sense, that is to say, a pattern though closed in upon itself. </s><s n="s3.6;p8.13">On the contrary. </s><s n="s4.6;p8.13">The password for the <hi rend="italic">Annales</hi> was nothing more than passion for the past - but that is a great deal." </s><ref target="BAWE_0144d-ftnote.024"/><s n="s5.6;p8.13">Furthermore, Braudel adds, 'and joined with that passion there was the search for <hi rend="italic">all</hi> the new possibilities, a readiness to accept changes in the way problems were put, according to the requirements and logic of the hour.'<ref target="BAWE_0144d-ftnote.025"/><hi rend="italic"> La Méditerranée</hi> is not, therefore, in the narrow sense a paradigm, nor has it been literally imitated by anyone, because it offers an image of <hi rend="italic">Annaliste</hi> history more than a method.<ref target="BAWE_0144d-ftnote.026"/> Braudel's work, then, gave to the <hi rend="italic">Annales</hi> group of historians something more than a model, he offered to them, and to all of his readers, 'what may be called an inspiring suggestiveness." </s><ref target="BAWE_0144d-ftnote.027"/><s n="s6.6;p8.13">And it is with this that we must judge Braudel's contribution to the <hi rend="italic">Annales</hi> tradition, a tradition built upon a specific context, reasoning and purpose. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0144d-ftnote.024"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Fernand Braudel, 'Personal Testimony', <hi rend="italic">The Journal of Modern History,</hi> vol. 44, no. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">4 (Dec., 1972), p. 467. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0144d-ftnote.025"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0144d-ftnote.026"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Kinser, 'Annaliste Paradism?, p. 104. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0144d-ftnote.027"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid. </s></p></note><p n="p9.13"><s n="s1.6;p9.13">Trevor-Roper contends, 'French in origin, French in inspiration." </s><ref target="BAWE_0144d-ftnote.028"/><s n="s2.6;p9.13">Braudel, by asking 'is it by chance that Henri Berr, Lucien Febvre, March Bloch, and myself all four came from eastern France? </s><s n="s3.6;p9.13">That the <hi rend="italic">Annales</hi> began at Strasbourg, next door to Germany and to German historical thought?' shares this sentiment.<ref target="BAWE_0144d-ftnote.029"/> The political context of the 1920s, the inherent anti-Germanic feelings, the destruction of the First World War, and the embarrassment of invasion and occupation, provide numerous explanations to help account for the <hi rend="italic">Annales</hi> conception. </s><s n="s4.6;p9.13">Bryce Lyon asserts, their 'reaction is easy to explain... their memories of the Franco-Prussian War and of the German annexation of Alsace plus their involvement in the war of 1914-18 made them little receptive to German historical ideas." </s><ref target="BAWE_0144d-ftnote.030"/><s n="s5.6;p9.13">Their distinctive 'Frenchness' can therefore be explained by the context in which the <hi rend="italic">Annales</hi> began, and what they were reacting to. </s><s n="s6.6;p9.13">With the belief that they study of history in France was in the doldrums, lagging far behind such study in Germany, England, and the United States, the <hi rend="italic">Annales</hi> set out to bring France to the forefront of international research and investigation.<ref target="BAWE_0144d-ftnote.031"/> Hexter affirms, </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0144d-ftnote.028"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Trevor-Roper, 'Fernand Braudel, the <hi rend="italic">Annales,</hi> and the Mediterranean', p. 468. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0144d-ftnote.029"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Braudel, 'Personal Testimony', p. 467. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0144d-ftnote.030"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Bryce Lyon, 'Marc Bloch: did he repudiate <hi rend="italic">Annales</hi> history?', <hi rend="italic">Journal of Medieval History</hi> 11 (1985), p.184. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0144d-ftnote.031"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Hexter, 'Fernand Braudel and the Monde Braudellien...', p. 482. </s></p></note><quote lang="English">What they saw as the retardation of historical work in France they ascribed to an institution, an attitude, and a deficiency. The institution was the Faculty of Letters of the University of Paris, or more precisely the dominant historians of that faculty. In the interest of the advance of historical studies he [Febvre] felt it must be crushed. Febvre regarded the attitude of the <hi rend="italic">Sorbonnistes</hi> as a symptom of the shrinking timidity of France that emerged in spiritual disarray both from the debacle of 1870 and from the pyrrhic victory of 1914-18.<ref target="BAWE_0144d-ftnote.032"/></quote><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0144d-ftnote.032"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid., p. 483. </s></p></note><p n="p10.13"><s n="s1.1;p10.13">The goal of the <hi rend="italic">Annales</hi> from the outset, therefore, was to undo the work of the <hi rend="italic">Sorbonnistes,</hi> to turn French historians away from the narrowly political and the narrowly diplomatic, to turn them toward the new studies in history, especially toward social and economic history.<ref target="BAWE_0144d-ftnote.033"/> Braudel, in sharing this outlook and sense of mission, thus conformed to the <hi rend="italic">Annales</hi> tradition, helping to make 'history one of the most important subjects in French academia, and, as institutional and pedagogical leader of the <hi rend="italic">Annales</hi> group of historians... provided intellectual and financial support for a burgeoning French historical profession.'<ref target="BAWE_0144d-ftnote.034"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0144d-ftnote.033"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0144d-ftnote.034"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Green and Troup, <hi rend="italic">The Houses of History,</hi> p. 91. </s></p></note><p n="p11.13"><s n="s1.2;p11.13">Structurally, much of the <hi rend="italic">Annales</hi> also remained consistent throughout Braudel's period of leadership. </s><s n="s2.2;p11.13">The Sixiême Section of the École Pratique des Haute Études, founded in 1947, continued to promote a variety of <hi rend="italic">Annales</hi> research.<ref target="BAWE_0144d-ftnote.035"/> The VI <hi rend="sup">e</hi> Section's structure, rules, and methods of recruitment remained flexible, and free from the regulations and obligations of the French university system.<ref target="BAWE_0144d-ftnote.036"/> Braudel did much to help further propagate <hi rend="italic">Annales</hi> research, establishing the Centre de recherches historiques, and another dozen research teams and laboratories attached to the VI <hi rend="sup">e</hi> Section.<ref target="BAWE_0144d-ftnote.037"/> Braudel's tangible legacy, those belonging to the 'third generation' of the <hi rend="italic">Annales</hi> group of historians, although focusing largely on statistical aspects of investigation, seizing upon the use of the computer as a tool, continued to pursue the totality of history, adding emphasis on the <hi rend="italic">mentalités</hi> of past societies to the already formidable range of new topics.<ref target="BAWE_0144d-ftnote.038"/> Braudel, therefore, did much to remain consistent with the <hi rend="italic">Annales</hi> tradition. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0144d-ftnote.035"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid., p. 88. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0144d-ftnote.036"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Hexter, 'Fernand Braudel and the Monde Braudellien...', p. 484. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0144d-ftnote.037"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0144d-ftnote.038"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Green and Troup, <hi rend="italic">The Houses of History,</hi> p. 91. </s></p></note><p n="p12.13"><s n="s1.5;p12.13">Interestingly, Lyon has recently asserted that had Bloch survived the Second World War, he would probably have repudiated the kind of history he had embraced between 1919-1939.<ref target="BAWE_0144d-ftnote.039"/> Lyon affirms, that Bloch, having fought on the losing side and living in a defeated and partly occupied nation, solemn about the 'shortcomings and failures of both himself and all Frenchmen', regretted that he and other individuals did not act.<ref target="BAWE_0144d-ftnote.040"/> Lyon concludes, 'living daily amidst unpleasant realities, he had to admit that the individual in history cannot be ignored, that human frailties and strengths influence the course of history, and that chance, destiny, and the unforeseen must be taken into account." </s><ref target="BAWE_0144d-ftnote.041"/><s n="s2.5;p12.13">Although it is difficult for us to satisfactorily investigate such an assertion, it does raise a number of important points. </s><s n="s3.5;p12.13">Firstly, if Bloch was willing to challenge his theoretical interpretations due to changing circumstance and personal experience, then context must be seen as an important factor governing the <hi rend="italic">Annales</hi> tradition. </s><s n="s4.5;p12.13">Secondly, flexibility, fluidity, and development are permitted attributes of the <hi rend="italic">Annales</hi> method of history. </s><s n="s5.5;p12.13">And thirdly, a clear goal and sense of purpose must be seen as driving the <hi rend="italic">Annales</hi> theoretical and methodological principles. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0144d-ftnote.039"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Lyon, 'Marc Bloch: did he repudiate <hi rend="italic">Annales</hi> history?', p. 184. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0144d-ftnote.040"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid., p. 185. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0144d-ftnote.041"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid., p. 190. </s></p></note><p n="p13.13"><s n="s1.5;p13.13">In conclusion, we can therefore reject the notion that Braudel betrayed the <hi rend="italic">Annales</hi> tradition. </s><s n="s2.5;p13.13">Although we should credit the <hi rend="italic">Annales</hi> group of historians with employing a distinctive theoretical method in which to record and investigate the past, these distinctive elements cannot be attributed to a single historian, nor contained within a clear-cut paradigm. </s><s n="s3.5;p13.13">Rather, the <hi rend="italic">Annales</hi> 'tradition' rests upon its place within the journal <hi rend="italic">Annales: Économies, Sociétés, Civilisations,</hi> a unifying embodiment of its guiding principles. </s><s n="s4.5;p13.13">Braudel's contribution to this 'tradition', although significant, and somewhat revolutionary, ought therefore, be placed within this wider tradition of conjectural fluidity and development. </s><s n="s5.5;p13.13">Far from betraying this tradition, we can credit Braudel with furthering one of the <hi rend="italic">Annales</hi> foremost important principles, promulgating the attempt to capture history in its totality through methodical innovation and continued historical investigation. </s></p></div1></body><back><div1 type="bibliography"><head rend="underlined">Bibliography:</head><p>Bloch, Marc, <hi rend="italic">The Historian's Craft</hi> (Manchester, 1998).</p><p>Braudel, Fernand, 'Personal Testimony', <hi rend="italic">The Journal of Modern History,</hi> vol. 44, no. 4 (Dec., 1972), pp. 448-467.</p><p>Braudel, Fernand, <hi rend="italic">On History</hi> (Chicago, 1980).</p><p>Green, Anna and K. Troup (eds),<hi rend="italic"> The Houses of History</hi> (Manchester, 1999).</p><p>Febvre, Lucien, 'A New Kind of History', in <hi rend="italic">A New Kind of History: From the Writings of Lucien Febvre</hi> (ed. Peter Burke, London, 1973), pp. 27-43.</p><p>Hexter, J. H., 'Fernand Braudel and the Monde Braudellien...', <hi rend="italic">The Journal of Modern History,</hi> vol. 44, no. 4 (Dec., 1972), pp. 480-539.</p><p>Kinser, Samuel, 'Annaliste Paradism? The Geohistorical Structuralism of Fernand Braudel', <hi rend="italic">The American Historical Review,</hi> vol. 86, no. 1 (Feb., 1981), pp. 63-105.</p><p>Lyon, Bryce, 'Marc Bloch: did he repudiate <hi rend="italic">Annales</hi> history?', <hi rend="italic">Journal of Medieval History</hi> 11 (1985), 182-92</p><p>Trevor-Roper, H. R., 'Fernand Braudel, the <hi rend="italic">Annales,</hi> and the Mediterranean', <hi rend="italic">The Journal of Modern History,</hi> vol. 44, no. 4. (Dec., 1972), pp. 468-479.</p></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
