<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_0146d" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Radstone Finances Assignment</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">Language used in quote: <foreign id="English">English</foreign></note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">header: student and module number
footer: date and page numbers</note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">deleted: Word count:
4,994 words. Not including Contents and References/Bibliography. Does include all data for future performance presented.</note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">deleted: markers comments:
[Net margin???]
[In days???]
[Some good points, some confusion on gross margin.]
[The cash flow S/M p24 shows that the decrease in stock &amp; debtors did contribute to cash inflow but then main source is operating profit.]
</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">4</p><p n="date">2004-02</p><p n="module title">Finance and Accounting</p><p n="module code">ES379</p><p n="genre family">Case study</p><p n="discipline">Engineering</p><p n="disciplinary group">PS</p><p n="grade">D</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">5009</p><p n="number of s-units">191</p><p n="number of p">80</p><p n="number of tables">1</p><p n="number of figures">4</p><p n="number of block quotes">18</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">4</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">5</p><p n="abstract present">abstract present</p><p n="average words per s-unit">26.2</p><p n="average s-units per p">2.4</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">m</p><p n="year of birth">1983</p><p n="first language">English</p><p n="education">UKA</p><p n="course">Electronics &amp; Communications</p><p n="student ID">0146</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><div1 type="toc" n="2"><head rend="underlined bold">CONTENTS</head><p/></div1></front><body><div1 type="abstract"><head rend="underlined bold">EXECUTIVE SUMMARY</head><list type="bulleted"><head rend="bold">Objectives:</head><item>To become familiar with contents of Radstone's annual report.</item><item>To learn how to calculate and interpret financial ratios.</item><item>To evaluate the past performance of Radstone over one financial year based on information contained within the annual report and on information provided by peers.</item><item>To assess the potential future performance of Radstone over the next financial year based on the annual report and other publicly available information.</item></list><list type="bulleted"><head rend="bold">Report covers:</head><item>Evaluation of Radstone's past performance from the perspective of an ordinary shareholder.</item><item><list type="bulleted"><item>Evaluate performance using a maximum of 10 performance indicators</item><item>Assessment of reliability of the report.</item><item>Recommendation to ordinary shareholder on 1 <hi rend="sup">st</hi> April 2003.</item></list></item><item>Assessment of potential future performance of Radstone over the next financial year.</item></list><p n="p1.80"><s rend="bold" n="s1.1;p1.80">Key findings and conclusions </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p2.80"><s n="s1.2;p2.80">It was found that Radstone's annual report does provide a 'true and fair view' of the company's performance. </s><s n="s2.2;p2.80">The optimistic outlook is backed up by the company's consistent improvement in performance over the last 5 years. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p3.80"><s n="s1.4;p3.80">The annual report is a good indicator of past performance. </s><s n="s2.4;p3.80">The profit margin has increased from 4.86% (1999) to 12.63% (2003) and as a result the basic earnings per share have increased from 4.38p to 17.98p over the same period. </s><s n="s3.4;p3.80">The company has become more efficient and its liquidity is improved also. </s><s n="s4.4;p3.80">They have reduced the gearing from 21.63% to 12.43 % as a result of clearing long-term debts while maintaining a high stock turnover. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p4.80"><s n="s1.3;p4.80">For future performance the annual report is good for long-term indication of growth on any potential investment. </s><s n="s2.3;p4.80">The information I found from public sources about plans to close a plant in Wales and the acquisition of a specialist technology company in Canada, are certainly justifiable from information in the annual report. </s><s n="s3.3;p4.80">The acquisition in particular has increased market share price. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">INTRODUCTION</head><p n="p5.80"><s n="s1.1;p5.80">The evaluations and conclusions for past and future performance have been kept separate with Conclusion sections after each separate evaluation. </s></p><p n="p6.80"><s n="s1.2;p6.80">All the financial figures relating to Radstone's performance have been taken from the Fame database, Fame (2003), unless otherwise stated. </s><s n="s2.2;p6.80">(For example, A.R. means the 2003 Radstone annual report). </s></p><p n="p7.80"><s n="s1.2;p7.80">For the research on the past performance the annual report itself was used including the notes to the financial statements (that make up the majority of the report), the Fame file in Excel format and the Radstone-Best file in Excel format. </s><s n="s2.2;p7.80">The class produced ratios and explanations are used as well as the Dyson book to help choose the performance indicators and then relate them to the given task of the assignment. </s></p><p n="p8.80"><s n="s1.2;p8.80">For the future performance the Factiva database is mainly used, but also the interim report for the 6 months to 30 <hi rend="sup">th</hi> September. </s><s n="s2.2;p8.80">The format for this section is to present the data, some of which was paraphrased for shortness, then evaluated and compared to the annual report before the conclusions are presented. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">(1.) PAST PERFORMANCE FROM PERSPECTIVE OF ORDINARY SHAREHOLDER. </head><div2><head rend="underlined bold italic">Choice of performance indicators</head><p n="p9.80"><s n="s1.1;p9.80">The type of financial information shareholders are interested in is </s></p><list type="bulleted"><item>Profits and Investment.</item><item>Assets (what company owns and what is owed to it, from balance sheet. Looking for increase in assets, are assets increasing return?) and Liabilities (what the company owes).</item><item>Effectiveness of directors.</item></list><p n="p10.80"><s n="s1.5;p10.80">For profits the majority of information will come from the profit and loss account since it can tell what profit the business has made. </s><s n="s2.5;p10.80">By using ratios and/or making comparisons across the last five years (using data in the Fame database, which originally will have come from annual reports) it should be possible to put this profit information into context. </s><s n="s3.5;p10.80">That is, to remove the effects of company size and inflation for example. </s><s n="s4.5;p10.80">Specifically the chosen ratios are: Return on shareholders funds, Capital Gearing and Basic earnings per share. </s><s n="s5.5;p10.80">Also, Gross Profit Margin will be used as an indicator of performance. </s></p><p n="p11.80"><s n="s1.3;p11.80">For Assets and Liabilities mostly the balance sheet is used but to find what state the business is in requires also looking at the efficiency of the entity (ability to turn stocks into profit) and movement of cash in the entity, to see what the entity can afford to do and judge the effectiveness of the directors. </s><s n="s2.3;p11.80">Hence the ratios to be used here are Fixed assets turnover, Stock turnover and Current Ratio. </s><s n="s3.3;p11.80">The Average working capital÷sales (A.R. p1) is also to be used as a performance indicator. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined bold italic">Data</head><table id="BAWE_0146d-tab.001"><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p12.80"/></div2><div2><head rend="underlined bold italic">Findings </head><div3><head rend="underlined italic">Return on shareholders funds</head><p n="p13.80"><s n="s1.5;p13.80">The return on shareholders funds gives a good idea of the profit in relation to the funds contributed by the shareholders rather than just the figure of the profit. </s><s n="s2.5;p13.80">Overall it has increased over the last 5 years showing that the performance of the company has increased. </s><s n="s3.5;p13.80">However, since 2001 it has only increased a little perhaps indicating that it may not increase further without expansion. </s><s n="s4.5;p13.80">Indeed expansion would mean issuing more shares to raise the funds, which is only possible when this ratio is high, but the act of which may reduce the ratio anyway assuming the profit initially stays the same. </s><s n="s5.5;p13.80">So it is best if this ratio remains high and does not decrease over a longer period of time. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0146d-fig.001"/><p n="p14.80"><s n="s1.1;p14.80">[by <name type="student ID"/>] </s></p></div3><div3><head rend="underlined italic">Capital Gearing</head><p n="p15.80"><s n="s1.6;p15.80">The Capital Gearing shows what proportion of capital comes from long term loans. </s><s n="s2.6;p15.80">It is very important for investors since it can show how much of a risk investing in the entity may be. </s><s n="s3.6;p15.80">If there are many long term loans then the interest rate on these loans may affect the entity severely. </s><s n="s4.6;p15.80">Profits need to be sufficiently high to guarantee that the interest rates do not affect it. </s><s n="s5.6;p15.80">Radstone has neither a typically high or low capital gearing but it has been steadily decreasing over the last few years representing an inviting investment. </s><s n="s6.6;p15.80">This is due to the steady repayment of long term loans, combined with increasing profit the risk to investors is reduced; if the company went into liquidation at least there would be something left over for the shareholders after loans were paid back. </s></p></div3><div3><head rend="underlined italic">Basic earnings per share</head><p n="p16.80"><s n="s1.4;p16.80">The basic earnings per share are taken from the annual report. </s><s n="s2.4;p16.80">There has been a significant increase in this over the years which is good news for share holders since it means there is investment growth and stability. </s><s n="s3.4;p16.80">Radstone see this figure <hi rend="italic">as "...indicative of underlying performance..."</hi> </s><s n="s4.4;p16.80">(Annual report, page 11) which may be true, but is certainly of more use to potential investors when deciding whether to invest in the entity. </s></p></div3><div3><head rend="underlined italic">Gross profit margin</head><p n="p17.80"><s n="s1.8;p17.80">The gross profit margin in Fame is the same as the, "profit margin" or "net profit ratio" calculated in the Radstone-best file. </s><s n="s2.8;p17.80">They are the same here though, because the numerator, net profit, has had the interest deducted before tax, which is gross profit (the denominator is turnover). </s><s n="s3.8;p17.80">It relates profit to sales irrespective of entity size. </s><s n="s4.8;p17.80">It seems that while both the profit and turnover have increased over the last 5 years, the profit has increased more rapidly resulting in an overall increase in this ratio. </s><s n="s5.8;p17.80">Typically a high value at 12.63% currently indicates Radstone are in a strong position to choose the pricing of their products. </s><s n="s6.8;p17.80">In the annual report on page 7 it talks about the increasing profit margin in its Embedded Computing business due to its "rugged" computer products which may represent a niche market the business is settling in. </s><s n="s7.8;p17.80">On pages 4, 7, 8, 10 and 11 of the annual report it is learned that while the Embedded computing business has enjoyed increases in profit margins the other of Radstone groups businesses, EMS (Electronic Manufacturing Service), has suffered profit margin losses. </s><s n="s8.8;p17.80">Still, overall the group profit margins have climbed and look good for shareholders. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0146d-fig.002"/><p n="p18.80"><s n="s1.1;p18.80">[by <name type="student ID"/>] </s></p><p n="p19.80"><s n="s1.2;p19.80">Moving on now to the indicators more of how the company is run efficiently, or isn't, and not just purely concerned with profit and investment issues. </s><s n="s2.2;p19.80">These indicators should indicate stability of Radstone which is important for any shareholder looking for a long term investment. </s></p></div3><div3><head rend="underlined italic">Fixed assets turnover</head><p n="p20.80"><s n="s1.5;p20.80">The fixed assets turnover ratio (Profit from sales (turnover) ÷ Total fixed assets) shows how efficiently the entity produces goods. </s><s n="s2.5;p20.80">It is best used as a comparison between alternative years. </s><s n="s3.5;p20.80">For Radstone there is a considerable reduction (>50%) of this ratio from 1999 to 2000. </s><s n="s4.5;p20.80">This could represent the purchasing of a large piece of machinery or perhaps upgrading, since the profit from sales has remained similar or at least not changed enough to more than half this ratio. </s><s n="s5.5;p20.80">Since 1999 the ratio has slowly climbed indicating that the efficiency of the company is increasing. </s></p><quote lang="English"><hi rend="italic">"Development work aimed at reducing the cost and lead times of our Systems products made good progress during the year, creating the potential to extend their use into previously inaccessible application areas with substantial production volumes."</hi> (From page 7, Operations Review, Embedded Computing)</quote><p n="p21.80"><s n="s1.2;p21.80">This example shows where Radstone have managed to reduce lead times and thereby increase efficiency. </s><s n="s2.2;p21.80">This is important for shareholders especially when new shares are issued as the newly invested money will be spent on fixed assets as part of growth and expansion. </s></p></div3><div3><head rend="underlined italic">Stock turnover</head><p n="p22.80"><s n="s1.4;p22.80">Stock turnover has also increased since 1999 although there is a noticeable drop in 2002. </s><s n="s2.4;p22.80">It is stated in the annual report (page 8) that 2002 was a difficult year for the EMS business. </s><s n="s3.4;p22.80">Radstone secured a short term contract in 2003 which is no doubt how the stock turnover has increased greatly this year. </s><s n="s4.4;p22.80">Using this indicator it appears that the efficiency of the company is at least stabilizing or indeed increasing which is what the shareholders will be looking for. </s></p></div3><div3><head rend="underlined italic">Current ratio</head><p n="p23.80"><s n="s1.6;p23.80">Current ratio has doubled since 1999 showing Radstone has doubled how quickly they can turn assets into cash. </s><s n="s2.6;p23.80">The ratio uses the current liabilities as the denominator and so can also tell how able the company is to meet financial commitments. </s><s n="s3.6;p23.80">Hence, it is a liquidity ratio, reflective of the effectiveness of the directors. </s><s n="s4.6;p23.80">The financial health of Radstone appears to be good based on this ratio and the large increase from 2002 and 2003 as in the Chairman's statement is likely due to the large one-off contract that was won. </s><s n="s5.6;p23.80">Perhaps such an increase could be worrying as it may mean not enough working capital is been used. </s><s n="s6.6;p23.80">The next indicator looks at this though. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0146d-fig.003"/><p n="p24.80"><s n="s1.1;p24.80">[by <name type="student ID"/>] </s></p></div3><div3><head rend="underlined italic">Average working capital÷sales</head><p n="p25.80"><s n="s1.5;p25.80">Average working capital÷sales is from the annual report. </s><s n="s2.5;p25.80">Looking at the working capital in relation to sales puts it into perspective and this is a good idea. </s><s n="s3.5;p25.80">In 2002 the working capital seemed to jump massively but it was probably actually due to lower sales in 2002 which was known to be a "difficult" year. </s><s n="s4.5;p25.80">The fact that they have reduced this percentage in 2003 is indicative of increased sales but more importantly that the working capital is not too low when compared to sales. </s><s n="s5.5;p25.80">So they seem to be bouncing back from 2002, recovering from a bad year and hopefully stabilising in this percentage. </s></p></div3><div3><head rend="underlined bold italic">Is the information in the annual report reliable? </head><p n="p26.80"><s n="s1.6;p26.80">The annual report is very optimistic but does admit that 2002 was a difficult year. </s><s n="s2.6;p26.80">There is also mention of the one-off contract that was won. </s><s n="s3.6;p26.80">Without this would the apparent continuous increase in performance of the company have held? </s><s n="s4.6;p26.80">This is hard to answer at any rate but they are making the most of the good times by paying off long term debts and producing good earnings on invested money. </s><s n="s5.6;p26.80">This is what the shareholder wants to know, is there going to be a good return on the investment and is the entity a going concern? </s><s n="s6.6;p26.80">Yes, Radstone is profitable, the annual report shows no signs of failing business and other indicators show that the efficiency is at least stable if not increasing in the long-term. </s></p></div3><div3><head rend="underlined bold italic">Two examples of accounting adjustments and their impact on reported profit</head><p rend="ordered" n="p27.80"><s n="s1.5;p27.80">The inclusion of accruals in the profit and loss account, detailed in the notes to the financial statements in the (p35 of annual report). </s><s n="s2.5;p27.80">If accruals increase, cash increases. </s><s n="s3.5;p27.80">This can be seen in the notes to the financial statements (Note 17, p35 of annual report). </s><s n="s4.5;p27.80">In fame the data goes back further showing the amount of accruals has been increasing since 1999. </s><s n="s5.5;p27.80">This means that the reported profit increases.<hi rend="italic"> - [No.]</hi> </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p28.80"><s n="s1.2;p28.80">Stocks decrease, cash increase. </s><s n="s2.2;p28.80">This makes the companies cash position stronger and is indeed how they paid for the new building recently.-<hi rend="italic">[reference.]</hi> This will increase the apparent profit of Radstone since less cash is tied up in current assets. </s></p></div3><div3><head rend="underlined bold italic">Evidence in annual report indicating financial accounting standards have been applied to produce a 'true and fair view'. </head><p n="p29.80"><s n="s1.2;p29.80">The most obvious place this is true is the section in the annual report, the first section of notes to the financial statements, describes how this has been done. </s><s n="s2.2;p29.80">The best example is the goodwill which is stated to have, in accordance with FRS10, been capitalised and amortised over its estimated useful life. </s></p><p n="p30.80"><s n="s1.3;p30.80">Modified historic cost has been used to put value to land and buildings while other tangible assets are stated at purchase price. </s><s n="s2.3;p30.80">Depreciation with straight-line approach was used to charge these to the accounts. </s><s n="s3.3;p30.80">The estimated useful life is different for freehold buildings, 45 years, whereas it is 3-10 years for other assets. </s></p><p n="p31.80"><s n="s1.4;p31.80">It states the value put to stocks is cost or net realisable value, whichever is lower. </s><s n="s2.4;p31.80">This will make the company look good since it is not desirable to be seen to have lots of high-value stock. </s><s n="s3.4;p31.80">It is worth noting that the net realisable cost has been set to include the cost of realisation so I cannot see how it would ever be less than the cost, except for obsolete and defective stocks. </s><s n="s4.4;p31.80">So this is an area for perhaps slight concern, although the difference is small they are certainly not using prudence here. </s></p><p n="p32.80"><s n="s1.2;p32.80">There is a case where Radstone have reported a loss due to currency changes. </s><s n="s2.2;p32.80">This makes their profit lower but they have stuck with it. </s></p><p n="p33.80"><s n="s1.1;p33.80">FRS19 - Deferred Tax has been used with the Tax charge. </s></p></div3></div2><div2><head rend="underlined bold">CONCLUSIONS</head><div3><head rend="underlined">(QA.)Does the annual report provide a 'true and fair view' of Radstone's performance? </head><p n="p34.80"><s n="s1.4;p34.80">I believe that the annual report does provide a 'true and fair view' of Radstone's performance. </s><s n="s2.4;p34.80">They have consistently had improving performance except for in 2002 but this has been explained in the annual report. </s><s n="s3.4;p34.80">They admit to landing a good contract which will not necessarily happen again but their past performance would seem to suggest that this will not be a problem to them. </s><s n="s4.4;p34.80">They are in a strong financial position as pointed out in the annual report and this is certainly what I found when looking at the performance indicators and explaining what it means for investors. </s></p></div3><div3><head rend="underlined">(QB.)How reliable is this report to an ordinary shareholder as an indicator past performance? </head><p n="p35.80"><s n="s1.5;p35.80">The annual report is more than reliable to an ordinary shareholder as an indicator of past performance. </s><s n="s2.5;p35.80">Radstone is growing; they would not be buying bigger premises and continuing to increase investment in research and development if they did not have the funds available. </s><s n="s3.5;p35.80">This is possible because of the past performance which the annual report shows has improved year to year. </s><s n="s4.5;p35.80">The directors are succeeding in making Radstone more efficient and improving its liquidity which provide long term stability. </s><s n="s5.5;p35.80">The shareholder is interested in making money from the shares in the long-term and the profitability indicators have shown this to be the case for the last five years with no sign of stopping now. </s></p></div3><div3><head rend="underlined bold">Should an ordinary shareholder on 1st April 2003 have held, sold or bought more shares? </head><p n="p36.80"><s n="s1.5;p36.80">Linking back to the capital gearing it is fairly certain that buying more shares in Radstone is a safe bet. </s><s n="s2.5;p36.80">So my recommendation is that the shareholder should have bought some more shares. </s><s n="s3.5;p36.80">For the next few years I expect the share price to increase. </s><s n="s4.5;p36.80">Even if Radstone does come into difficulty the shares will either still be of moderate value at the end or it will be delayed because of the low debt and strong finance. </s><s n="s5.5;p36.80">As long as they keep up the same level of honesty there would be time to sell the shares and so make a handsome profit if a rough patch was too much worry for the shareholder. </s></p></div3></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">(2.) FUTURE PERFORMANCE</head><div2><head rend="underlined bold">Data from Factiva published since annual report (paraphrased in non-italics)</head><p n="p37.80"><s n="s1.1;p37.80">25/11/2003, The Liverpool Daily Post &amp; Echo Ltd, 2003, CARL BUTLER </s></p><p n="p38.80"><s n="s1.3;p38.80">60 jobs under threat at Radstone site in Wales. </s><s n="s2.3;p38.80">If the business is not sold by February it will be closed. </s><s n="s3.3;p38.80">This site makes the complex circuit boards, a niche market, but there is little demand for this type of manufacturing at the moment. </s></p><p n="p39.80"><s n="s1.1;p39.80">25/11/2003, The Ottawa Citizen </s></p><p n="p40.80"><s n="s1.1;p40.80">Manufacturing services are to be concentrated at Radstone's main manufacturing facility in Milton Keynes. </s></p><p n="p41.80"><s n="s1.1;p41.80">25/11/2003, Birmingham Post &amp; Mail Ltd </s></p><p n="p42.80"><s n="s1.1;p42.80">If the facility in Wales is not sold there will be a charge of £2.9 million of goodwill and a one-off charge of approximately £600,000 to cover redundancy and closure costs. </s></p><p n="p43.80"><s n="s1.1;p43.80">The cash impact would be approximately £250,000 in the current year and £150,000 thereafter. </s></p><p n="p44.80"><s n="s1.1;p44.80">24/11/2003, AFX UK Focus </s></p><quote lang="English" rend="italic">"The board believes that this move will strengthen this important component of the Radstone Group with a consequential improvement in its overall earnings," it said in a statement. </quote><p n="p45.80"><s n="s1.1;p45.80">17/11/2003, Citywire </s></p><quote lang="English" rend="italic">"Radstone Technologies (RST) advanced 7.3% to 358.5p as a 74% leap in half-year pre-tax profits to £1.2 million gave it cause to resume dividend payments. A surge in demand for its computer products, which are designed to withstand the rigours of combat situations, fuelled the jump in profits for the computer hardware group."</quote><p n="p46.80"><s n="s1.1;p46.80">17/11/2003, DAVID BLACKWELL, Financial Times </s></p><quote lang="English"><hi rend="italic">"Western military demand for electronics is growing, good news to investors in Radstone.</hi> <hi rend="italic"> Last week, it paid its first interim dividend since 1995 as profits jumped from £675,000 to £1.18m.</hi> <hi rend="italic"> However, in spite of the war in Iraq, sales were only just ahead at £18.5m, including a £1.3m contribution from Interactive Circuits and Systems (ICS), a Canadian radio software specialist acquired at the beginning of September.</hi> <hi rend="italic"> BAE Avionics for the Eurofighter worth £14 million over 3 years, production not due to start until 2006."</hi></quote><p n="p47.80"><s n="s1.2;p47.80">The problem with Radstone is that they need the EMS business to secure their own supplies for the Embedded business. </s><s n="s2.2;p47.80">EMS business is not doing so well and not expected to improve, 80% of its sales go to 3rd party. </s></p><p n="p48.80"><s n="s1.1;p48.80">Analysts are sure of good long-term success from Radstone because of the rugged computer products. </s></p><p n="p49.80"><s n="s1.1;p49.80">ICS's software radio can be used with existing military tried and tested hardware to improve compatibility and avoid "friendly fire" incidents. </s></p><p n="p50.80"><s n="s1.1;p50.80">11/11/2003, Bert Hill, The Ottawa Citizen </s></p><p n="p51.80"><s n="s1.1;p51.80">Acquisition of ICS already paying off for Radstone. </s></p><quote lang="English" rend="italic">"The deal cost Radstone $38 million U.S. but profits in the six months ending Sept. 30 rose 65 per cent to $1.3 million U.S." </quote><p n="p52.80"><s n="s1.3;p52.80">This has made Radstone appear to be doing better than they perhaps are. </s><s n="s2.3;p52.80">It is because of the timing of shipments from ICS and when Radstone reports its interim profits. </s><s n="s3.3;p52.80">Radstone warn investors not to expect big leaps in profit like this again but are confident of sales in the next 6 months. </s></p><quote lang="English" rend="italic">"As in previous years, trading in this part of the business is expected to be heavily weighted towards the second half and we are confident of a resulting strong performance in this period."</quote><p n="p53.80"><s n="s1.1;p53.80">11/11/2003 The Independent - London, by Liz Vaughan-Adams. </s></p><quote lang="English" rend="italic">"Jeff Perrin, the company's managing director, said the company remained confident of a 'strong' performance from its main embedded computing business in the second half of the year."</quote><p n="p54.80"><s n="s1.1;p54.80">10/11/2003, Citywire </s></p><quote lang="English"><hi rend="italic">"Order intake at embedded computing rose by 52% in the first half boosted by two large multi-year contracts, one of which is worth £14 million for work on the Eurofighter project, although this does not begin until 2006. The overall order book for future delivery stood at £74.3 million at the end of September running for up to five years.</hi> <hi rend="italic"> In contrast the UK-oriented Electronic Manufacturing Services (EMS) division continues to suffer with order intake slumping 37% to £5.6 million largely as the result of the completion of a one-off contract from last year."</hi></quote><p n="p55.80"><s n="s1.1;p55.80">7/11/2003 The Ottawa Citizen, by Jeff Buckstein </s></p><quote lang="English"><hi rend="italic">"In August, Radstone Technology PLC of Towcester, England, a leading vendor of intelligent, reconfigurable military radio networks, acquired ICS in a deal worth $37.5 million, mostly in cash.</hi> <hi rend="italic"> The transaction officially closed Sept. 3, 2003."</hi></quote><p n="p56.80"><s n="s1.1;p56.80">Radstone managing director Peter Cavill sees potential market of intelligent radio networks as motivation for acquiring ICS. </s></p><p n="p57.80"><s n="s1.1;p57.80">15/11/2003 The Times, by Nick Hasell </s></p><quote lang="English" rend="italic">"Radstone Technology rose 10p at 358p on talk its integration of Canada's ICS was proceeding well."</quote><p n="p58.80"><s n="s1.1;p58.80">11/09/2003 The Canadian Press </s></p><quote lang="English"><hi rend="italic">"Radstone will pay $37.5 million, plus $10 million over the next two years if profit targets are met, Integrated Partners, the private equity division of Integrated Asset Management, said Thursday.</hi> <hi rend="italic"> Radstone Technology PLC said trading in the first five months of the year was in line with expectations, but sales in the period were 12.6 million stg, down 9 pct, hit by some short-term variations in delivery requirements."</hi></quote><p n="p59.80"><s n="s1.1;p59.80">10/09/2003, AFX UK Focus </s></p><quote lang="English"><hi rend="italic">"Radstone Technology PLC said trading in the first five months of the year was in line with expectations, but sales in the period were 12.6 million stg, down 9 pct, hit by some short-term variations in delivery requirements.</hi> <hi rend="italic"> Cash generation continues to be strong, with net cash of 1.8 million stg, compared to 0.6 million at the year-end. New orders totalled 24.1 million, some 34 pct ahead of the same period last year."</hi></quote><p n="p60.80"><s n="s1.1;p60.80">12/06/2003, Reuters News </s></p><quote lang="English"><hi rend="italic">"WARNING FROM RADSTONE SENDS SHARES INTO RETREAT.</hi> <hi rend="italic"> ...warned that short-term sales could be affected by the end of the war in Iraq. It reported a 34 percent rise in full-year pre-tax profit, but shares dropped 15p to 270p on the warning."</hi></quote><p n="p61.80"><s n="s1.1;p61.80">12/06/2003, The Independent - London </s></p><quote lang="English"><hi rend="italic">"But the company concedes that it may now be affected by short-term fluctuations in orders - implying that life can get more tricky both during and after conflicts.</hi> <hi rend="italic"> Analysts point out that the uncertainty created by war can mean defence programmes get pulled forward, reprioritised and cancelled - leaving Radstone exposed because it is still a relatively small business, dependant on a small number of programmes. Order book down 15% on last year."</hi></quote></div2><div2><head rend="underlined bold">Data from Radstone interim report</head><p n="p62.80"><s n="s1.2;p62.80">Most of the information in the interim report has been covered already in the various reports found in the Factiva database. </s><s n="s2.2;p62.80">There a few additional pieces of information however: </s></p><p n="p63.80"><s n="s1.2;p63.80">Sales in the first half of year were down 6%. </s><s n="s2.2;p63.80">More than two thirds of this decline is due to weakness of the U.S. dollar. </s></p><p n="p64.80"><s n="s1.1;p64.80">Basic earnings per share were 3.15p (2002: 1.96p). </s></p><p n="p65.80"><s n="s1.1;p65.80">EMS business: 8% lower 3 <hi rend="sup">rd</hi> party sales. </s></p><quote lang="English"><hi rend="italic">"Operating cash inflow for the half-year continues to be very strong at £5,480,000 (2002: £4,871,000), reflecting continued strong management of working capital." "Gearing was 20% at 30 September 2003 compared to 26% at 30 September 2002 and net cash of £563,000 at the end of last year."</hi><hi rend="italic"> "As in previous years, trading in this part of the business is expected to be heavily weighted towards the second half and your board is confident of a resulting strong performance in this period."</hi></quote></div2><div2><head rend="underlined bold">Data from London Stock Exchange on Radstone share price</head><figure id="BAWE_0146d-fig.004"/><p n="p66.80"/></div2><div2><head rend="underlined bold">Read annual report to identify any info on potential future performance of company</head><quote lang="English"><hi rend="italic">"Radstone may continue to be affected by short-term programme fluctuations, but our long-term prospects have never been stronger."</hi> (page 5, Chairman's statement)</quote><p n="p67.80"><s n="s1.1;p67.80">The fact that the values for almost everything in the financial summary are increasing is an indicator that they are likely to continue increasing in the future indicating good future performance. </s></p><quote lang="English"><hi rend="italic">"We enjoyed excellent cash flow, with £12,676,000 generated from operations in the year, further enhancing our strong financial position."</hi> (page 4, Chairman's statement)</quote><p n="p68.80"><s n="s1.1;p68.80">If Radstone have good cash flow then they can afford to do more in the future. </s></p><p n="p69.80"><s n="s1.2;p69.80">They are paying a dividend and the annual report states there is the intention to pay an interim dividend also. </s><s n="s2.2;p69.80">The payment of these dividends and the high level of dividend cover show that the company is very profitable at the moment and expecting continuing profits. </s></p><quote lang="English"><hi rend="italic">"The proposed dividend is covered 8.9 times compared to 13.1 times last year."</hi> (page 13, Financial Review, Liquidity)</quote><p n="p70.80"><s n="s1.1;p70.80">The EMS business is not expected to experience growth in the 2003/2004 financial year. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined bold">Compare data from public sources TO info in A.R. </head><p n="p71.80"><s n="s1.3;p71.80">Profit increased 74%: This was largely due to the acquisition of ICS as was realised in the public sources of information. </s><s n="s2.3;p71.80">There is no information in the annual report to suggest a profit increase of this size. </s><s n="s3.3;p71.80">However, the intention of paying an interim dividend and later on carrying this out suggest that at the time of writing the annual report they knew they would still be making great profit. </s></p><p n="p72.80"><s n="s1.3;p72.80">Expecting strong performance of the Embedded business enhanced by performance of newly acquired ICS: Usually more orders for the Embedded business in second half. </s><s n="s2.3;p72.80">Although the reported profit for the 6 months was an increase of 74% it is recognised this is largely due to lots of deliveries from the newly acquired ICS in the last month of the 6 months after the annual report. </s><s n="s3.3;p72.80">The annual report mentions no intention of acquisition but it is known from Radstone's strong cash flow and low level of debt that they can more than afford this kind of venture. </s></p><p n="p73.80"><s n="s1.4;p73.80">Closure/ sale of plant in Wales (Integration into main UK manufacturing site): Need EMS to secure its own supplies for the Embedded business although the Embedded business counts for only 20% of orders for EMS, 80% being 3rd party. </s><s n="s2.4;p73.80">Needs 3rd party sales to make scale of economy so it is feasible to make their own supplies for the Embedded business. </s><s n="s3.4;p73.80">The annual report of course mentions nothing of intending to close a plant but they do recognise that in the annual report the EMS business is somewhat floundering or at least showing nothing like the performance of the Embedded Computing business. </s><s n="s4.4;p73.80">This then seems to be Radstone's way of dealing with it, concentrating its manufacturing to improve performance. </s></p><p n="p74.80"><s n="s1.2;p74.80">Weakness of the US dollar is reducing profits continuously, order book reduced by £2.3 million because of this also. </s><s n="s2.2;p74.80">This point is stressed in the annual report and is still affecting Radstone. </s></p><p n="p75.80"><s n="s1.4;p75.80">Recoil of Iraq War: Caught up in short term fluctuation of military spending on defence electronics. </s><s n="s2.4;p75.80">This had the effect of making Radstone's orders very high in the months leading up to the war and then a "thinning" of orders afterwards. </s><s n="s3.4;p75.80">However, as we have seen since, Radstone we're quite right not to worry too much about this in the annual report. </s><s n="s4.4;p75.80">They expected more orders in the second half of the year and especially with ICS acquired, this is indeed what happened. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined bold">CONCLUSIONS</head><div3><head rend="underlined bold">Future position of company over next financial year. 1st Apr 2003 to 31st Mar 2004. </head><p n="p76.80"><s n="s1.3;p76.80">I expect the share price to jump considerably when they are rid of the plant in Wales. </s><s n="s2.3;p76.80">The Embedded business should have also moved into its new location and it was the hope in the annual report that <hi rend="italic">"...the new laboratory and office facilities will enable the Group to work more efficiently and provide a platform for future growth."</hi> </s><s n="s3.3;p76.80">(page 5, Chairman's statement) This will certainly inspire the employees to work harder, but it seems key to Radstone that they must secure orders. </s></p><p n="p77.80"><s n="s1.2;p77.80">The demand for Radstone's products is still high and, as they are accustomed to, the majority of orders are now happening in the second half of the financial year. </s><s n="s2.2;p77.80">So there is no decline in the niche market that Radstone are in and definitely leaders. </s></p><p n="p78.80"><s n="s1.3;p78.80">The share price has continued to rise as Radstone have experienced growth and secured some long term contracts. </s><s n="s2.3;p78.80">I expect that when they dispose of the plant in Wales one way or another that there will be a noticeable increase in share price since this will increase Radstone's profitability further by reducing their operating costs considerably. </s><s n="s3.3;p78.80">The rise in share price also proves that my recommendation in the first part of this report was correct. </s></p></div3><div3><head rend="underlined bold">Discuss whether A.R. gave any useful info about future performance. </head><p n="p79.80"><s n="s1.4;p79.80">I think that the annual report did give useful information about future performance. </s><s n="s2.4;p79.80">This is all assuming the information in the annual report is accurate and true; so far this seems to have been the case with Radstone. </s><s n="s3.4;p79.80">They say they are improving performance; the share price, performance history and their future plans for growth seem to reflect this. </s><s n="s4.4;p79.80">So it is my opinion that the annual report is reasonably reliable to an ordinary shareholder as an indicator of future performance. </s></p><p n="p80.80"><s n="s1.7;p80.80">It shows trends of increasing performance but in Radstone's ever-changing market with one-off deals and acquisitions the future performance seemed to be better than the annual report could have told. </s><s n="s2.7;p80.80">Without these would the performance have lived up to the annual reports expectations? </s><s n="s3.7;p80.80">It is hard to say, but I think that there are helpful clues in the annual report. </s><s n="s4.7;p80.80">For instance it talks about future growth but not how this will be implemented as well as excellent cash flow, low debts. </s><s n="s5.7;p80.80">Then, they are buying a business that helps boost their performance and get some more share of the market they are in. </s><s n="s6.7;p80.80">Obviously an acquisition of this nature will increase share prices at least for the short term so it would seem the annual report is a better indicator of long-term prospects. </s><s n="s7.7;p80.80">This is after all what most shareholders are interested in; seeing an investment grow. </s></p></div3></div2></div1></body><back><div1 type="bibliography"><div2 type="bibliography"><head rend="underlined bold">LIST OF REFERENCES</head><p>The Radstone-best.xls file from the ratios that everyone in the class calculated and provided detailed information about. (<seg type="URL" n="http://www.eng"/>.<name type="university"/>.ac.uk/local/ug-office/students/notes/es379/Radstone-best.xls, accessed 23<hi rend="sup">rd</hi> December 2003)</p><p>Annual report (<seg type="URL" n="http://www.radstone.co.uk/pdfs/ar&amp;a_current.pdf"/>, accessed 23<hi rend="sup">rd</hi> December)</p><p>Interim report (<seg type="URL" n="http://www.radstone.co.uk/pdfs/interim_current.pdf"/>, accessed 23<hi rend="sup">rd</hi> December 2003)</p><p>Factiva database results (Library electronic resources)</p><p>London Stock Exchange Website (<seg type="URL" n="http://www.londonstockexchange.com/landmark/midlands/company_midlands.asp?sedol=0720483&amp;landmark=True&amp;landmarksource=/landmark/midlands/trigger_midlands.asp"/>, accessed 23<hi rend="sup">rd</hi> December 2003)</p></div2><div2 type="bibliography"><head rend="underlined bold">BIBLIOGRAPHY</head><p>J.R. Dyson, Accounting for Non-Accounting students. </p></div2></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
