<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_0147a" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>What part did the discovery of a sea passage to Asia play in explaining the decline of the Ottoman Empire?</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">Language used in quote: <foreign id="English">English</foreign></note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">2</p><p n="date">2005-11</p><p n="module title">Galleons and Caravans</p><p n="module code">HI163</p><p n="genre family">Essay</p><p n="discipline">History</p><p n="disciplinary group">AH</p><p n="grade">M</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">1879</p><p n="number of s-units">65</p><p n="number of p">13</p><p n="number of tables">0</p><p n="number of figures">0</p><p n="number of block quotes">1</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">0</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">0</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">28.9</p><p n="average s-units per p">5.0</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">m</p><p n="year of birth">1986</p><p n="first language">German</p><p n="education">OSA</p><p n="course">History &amp; Politics</p><p n="student ID">0147</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><titlePart rend="italic"><name type="student name"/> 25 November 2005</titlePart><titlePart rend="underlined bold">Galleons and Caravans - Essay One</titlePart><docTitle><titlePart rend="italic">What part did the discovery of a sea passage to Asia play in explaining the decline of the Ottoman Empire? </titlePart></docTitle></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="section"><p n="p1.13"><s n="s1.8;p1.13">The discovery of a sea passage to Asia was not a chief cause for the Ottoman Empire's decline. </s><s n="s2.8;p1.13">To assume that the loss of European transit trade was a key factor in the decline is an assumption tainted by an orientalist discourse. </s><s n="s3.8;p1.13">More pressing causes for the withering away of the Ottoman state were the incompetence of the Ottoman administration to adapt to changing conditions. </s><s n="s4.8;p1.13">Hence, the decline should be attributed to incompetent administrative and economic policies. </s><s n="s5.8;p1.13">In addition, failed military adventures contributed to an ever declining central authority. </s><s n="s6.8;p1.13">The Dutch Vice-Consul de Willem in Aleppo aptly summarizes this argument - "it is not just one pillar that is broken or weakened, but all four pillars of State: religion, justice, politics and finances." </s><ref target="BAWE_0147a-ftnote.001"/><s n="s7.8;p1.13">Therefore, to assume that external trade was a major aspect of its decline lends too great of an emphasis to the impact of European trade and the underlying orientalist assumptions. </s><s n="s8.8;p1.13">This essay will show that the Ottoman Empire crumbled from within and will attempt to disarm those who accentuate the loss of the transit trade as decisive in the Empire's downfall. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0147a-ftnote.001"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">1626. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">Cited in Niels Steensgaard, <hi rend="italic">The Asian Trade Revolution of the Seventeenth Century</hi> (London, 1973), p.75 </s></p></note><p n="p2.13"><s n="s1.5;p2.13">It is necessary to acknowledge that there was a decrease in transit trade due to internal and external developments. </s><s n="s2.5;p2.13">Middle Eastern trade is traditionally regarded as consistent of peddlers, with little central organization and barely any 'advance knowledge of their target market'.<ref target="BAWE_0147a-ftnote.002"/> Hence, this negated the political force of the merchant class, as they were individuals rather than an entity. </s><s n="s3.5;p2.13">Thus, they were not able to counter unjust rapacity by custom's officials. </s><s n="s4.5;p2.13">As Niels Steensgaard points out, 'the caravans [...] had to pass through many towns and countries, and everywhere the Turkish rulers demanded heavy duties over and above the customary ones'.<ref target="BAWE_0147a-ftnote.003"/> This culture of squeeze also affected the volume of trade going through Ottoman ports. </s><s n="s5.5;p2.13">For instance, after the establishment of the East India Company the British preferred to acquire pepper from India rather than from Ottoman ports as customs duties were approximately 'three times as high in near-eastern ports'.<ref target="BAWE_0147a-ftnote.004"/> Therefore, the inability by the central administration to regulate duty collection formed part of the grounds for a loss in transit trade. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0147a-ftnote.002"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Suraiya Faroqhi, <hi rend="underlined">Crisis and Change</hi> in Suraiya Faroqhi, et.al., (eds.), <hi rend="italic">An Economic and Social History of the Ottoman Empire</hi>, Vol. 2, (Cambridge, 1994) , p.477 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0147a-ftnote.003"><p n="pn1.1"><s rend="italic" n="s1.2;pn1.1">Op.Cit. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">, Steensgaard, p.179 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0147a-ftnote.004"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">H. Wood, <hi rend="italic">A History of the Levant Company</hi> (London, 1935), p.37 </s></p></note><p n="p3.13"><s n="s1.4;p3.13">On another part, the discovery of the sea passage to Asia was a contributing factor to the decline of the transit trade. </s><s n="s2.4;p3.13">Yet, it was the subsequent Ottoman failure to realize the opportunity of sea-borne commercial expansion that led to the decrease of the trade flow. </s><s n="s3.4;p3.13">Although the Ottoman's were able to prevent the Portuguese from gaining maritime control the superior ships of the Dutch and English managed to gain firm dominion over the Indian Ocean.<ref target="BAWE_0147a-ftnote.005"/> In this way, the European navies with their newly developed frigate class, the <hi rend="italic">Bertone</hi><ref target="BAWE_0147a-ftnote.006"/>, were able to wrestle maritime control away from the Levant who could not scramble a navy powerful enough to counter the 'combined navies of the Christian Mediterranean states'.<ref target="BAWE_0147a-ftnote.007"/> Likewise, there was little protection on both the Black and Red Sea and this further discouraged trade that would have benefited the Empire. </s><s n="s4.4;p3.13">Hence, the administration was merely unable to control the trade flows on the oceans and were thus excluded from the benefits of far eastern trade. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0147a-ftnote.005"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Halil Inalcik, <hi rend="italic">The Ottoman Empire The Classical Age 1300-1600</hi> (London, 1973), p.44 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0147a-ftnote.006"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Daniel Goffman, <hi rend="italic">The Ottoman Empire and Early Modern Europe</hi> (Cambridge, 2002), p.194 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0147a-ftnote.007"><p n="pn1.1"><s rend="italic" n="s1.2;pn1.1">Op.Cit. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">, Inalcik, p.44 </s></p></note><p n="p4.13"><s n="s1.3;p4.13">Nevertheless, there are numerous indications that trade within the Empire was flourishing. </s><s n="s2.3;p4.13">A Venetian Consul reports that although the Venetian transit trade was decreasing, "the trade in Aleppo is as flourishing as ever".<ref target="BAWE_0147a-ftnote.008"/> This increased trade manifested itself in the emergence of a large merchant class in trading centers. </s><s n="s3.3;p4.13">In this sense, Suraiya Faroqhi argues that in merchant cities such as Ankara and Bursa the internal trade 'led to a significant amount of social differentiation and capital accumulation'.<ref target="BAWE_0147a-ftnote.009"/> Furthermore, inter-province trade was complemented by the commercial relationship between the cities and their hinterland, which flourished especially during times of urban growth. <ref target="BAWE_0147a-ftnote.010"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0147a-ftnote.008"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.3;pn1.1">1612-1615. </s><s n="s2.3;pn1.1">Cited in <hi rend="italic">Op.Cit.</hi> </s><s n="s3.3;pn1.1">, Steensgaard, p.181 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0147a-ftnote.009"><p n="pn1.1"><s rend="italic" n="s1.2;pn1.1">Op.Cit. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">, Faroqhi, p.474 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0147a-ftnote.010"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Metin Kunt and Christine Woodhead, <hi rend="italic">Suleyman the magnificent and his age</hi> (London, 1995), p.99 </s></p></note><p n="p5.13"><s n="s1.3;p5.13">Unfortunately, there is scarce reliable data to suitably determine the various internal commercial links. </s><s n="s2.3;p5.13">Research into this area has long been 'overshadowed by the study of international maritime activities'.<ref target="BAWE_0147a-ftnote.011"/> In this way an orientalist view of the Ottomans as the <hi rend="italic">Other</hi> contributed to the neglect of the study of interior trade patterns. </s><s n="s3.3;p5.13">However, the very existence of tangible links illustrate that financial loss due to the diversion of transit trade could have easily been recovered through the adjustment of local economies to the domestic market.<ref target="BAWE_0147a-ftnote.012"/> In this fashion Steensgaard notes that it was 'the publicans and thieves who suffered the greatest losses [...] their investments could not so easily be transferred to other fields'.<ref target="BAWE_0147a-ftnote.013"/> Thus, the argument that the opening of the sea passage to Asia was a considerable cause of the decline of the Ottoman Empire is perhaps somewhat exaggerated. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0147a-ftnote.011"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Daniel Panzac, <hi rend="underlined">International and Domestic Maritime Trade in the Ottoman Empire during the 18th Century</hi>, <hi rend="italic">International Journal of Middle East Studies</hi>, Vol. 24, No. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">2 (1992), p.189 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0147a-ftnote.012"><p n="pn1.1"><s rend="italic" n="s1.2;pn1.1">Op.Cit. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">, Goffman, p.193 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0147a-ftnote.013"><p n="pn1.1"><s rend="italic" n="s1.2;pn1.1">Op.Cit. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">, Steensgaard, p.175 </s></p></note><p n="p6.13"><s n="s1.4;p6.13">Much more significant to the decline of the Ottoman Empire was the incompetence of the ruling class and their inadequate response to change. </s><s n="s2.4;p6.13">The <hi rend="italic">timar</hi> system was central to the decline of central authority. </s><s n="s3.4;p6.13"><hi rend="italic">Timars</hi> were plots of land allocated to men who in return would provide military support to the Empire. </s><s n="s4.4;p6.13">Yet, irregular inflation began to affect many <hi rend="italic">timar</hi> holders who did not receive state supplements to their income.<ref target="BAWE_0147a-ftnote.014"/> Subsequently, many <hi rend="italic">timar</hi> plots were vacated and snatched up by administrative or palace officials, depriving the army of its backbone.<ref target="BAWE_0147a-ftnote.015"/> This shortage of soldiers was alleviated by the recruitment of <hi rend="italic">janissaries</hi>, who according to Andrina Stiles were undisciplined and resembled a part-time militia as opposed to a professional army.<ref target="BAWE_0147a-ftnote.016"/> Hence, an inefficient army that was ridden with corruption fostered instability within the Empire. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0147a-ftnote.014"><p n="pn1.1"><s rend="italic" n="s1.2;pn1.1">Op.Cit. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">, Inalcik, p.47 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0147a-ftnote.015"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Andrina Stiles, <hi rend="italic">The Ottoman Empire 1450-1700</hi> (Kent, 1989), p.121 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0147a-ftnote.016"><p n="pn1.1"><s rend="italic" n="s1.2;pn1.1">Ibid. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">, pp.122-123 </s></p></note><p n="p7.13"><s n="s1.6;p7.13">The ineptitude of officials to regulate an army is mirrored in the civil service's propensity to corruption. </s><s n="s2.6;p7.13">Koja Beg's analysis succinctly summarizes this situation, "undeserving people can procure a fief or a salary by means of bribes [...and...] many who have been put down on the army pay lists simply draw their salaries without ever dreaming of serving in a war".<ref target="BAWE_0147a-ftnote.017"/> A good indicator for this is the amount of land that government lost to the private market. </s><s n="s3.6;p7.13">In 1610 royal land amounted to 9 per cent of the 1560 value. </s><s n="s4.6;p7.13">Land was taken up by officials and courtiers and thus the government lost a significant amount of revenue. </s><s n="s5.6;p7.13">Compounding this issue were the sultans of which the 'majority were incompetent, pleasure living spendthrifts, who no longer controlled government decisions'.<ref target="BAWE_0147a-ftnote.018"/> A society that is prone to corruption and furthermore lacks political authority is bound to disintegrate. </s><s n="s6.6;p7.13">Indeed, in light of the internal problems facing the Empire the issue of the loss of transit trade seems small in comparison. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0147a-ftnote.017"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">From <hi rend="italic">Op.Cit.</hi> </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">, Steensgaard, p.76 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0147a-ftnote.018"><p n="pn1.1"><s rend="italic" n="s1.2;pn1.1">Op.Cit. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">, Stiles, p.119 </s></p></note><p n="p8.13"><s n="s1.7;p8.13">The fiscal policy of the Ottoman Empire further added to the decline. </s><s n="s2.7;p8.13">Inflation caused by the influx of silver from the New World led to severe financial difficulties within the Empire. </s><s n="s3.7;p8.13">Most taxes were levied in <hi rend="italic">akce</hi> and not in silver. </s><s n="s4.7;p8.13">Therefore in 1591 the central treasury income was only worth half of what it was in 1534.<ref target="BAWE_0147a-ftnote.019"/> This issue was compounded by a worldwide trend of inflation that Murat Cizakca terms as 'price revolution'.<ref target="BAWE_0147a-ftnote.020"/> The failure to implement required fiscal regulation to counter the silver threat and subsequent inflation is largely ascribed to the Ottoman mentality of supplying abundant commodities to the home market. </s><s n="s5.7;p8.13">This subjected the external trade of the empire to free trade by agreeing to numerous capitulations with Western powers.<ref target="BAWE_0147a-ftnote.021"/> This stood in contrast to the European mercantilist political economy of the time. </s><s n="s6.7;p8.13">Hence, the belief in economical self-regulation hindered the development of vital fiscal measures to control the effects of inflation. </s><s n="s7.7;p8.13">In the midst of this financial crisis the English Ambassador to Istanbul remarked that "as far as I can see, the Turkish Empire was in great decline, almost ruined". <ref target="BAWE_0147a-ftnote.022"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0147a-ftnote.019"><p n="pn1.1"><s rend="italic" n="s1.2;pn1.1">Op.Cit. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">, Inalcik, p.49 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0147a-ftnote.020"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Murat Cizakca, <hi rend="underlined">Price History and the Bursa Silk Industry: A Study in Ottoman Industrial Decline 1550-1650</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Journal of Economic History</hi>, Vol. 40, No. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">3 (1980), p.533 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0147a-ftnote.021"><p n="pn1.1"><s rend="italic" n="s1.2;pn1.1">Op.Cit. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">, Inalcik, p.51 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0147a-ftnote.022"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.3;pn1.1">1607. </s><s n="s2.3;pn1.1">Cited in <hi rend="italic">Ibid.</hi> </s><s n="s3.3;pn1.1">, p.51 </s></p></note><p n="p9.13"><s n="s1.5;p9.13">The Ottoman concept of the circle of equity and the firm belief in it hindered the prospects for reform that could have potentially reversed the decline. </s><s n="s2.5;p9.13">The circle of equity prescribed the function of each class within the state and the relations between them. </s><s n="s3.5;p9.13">Hence, advisors and commentators 'were hampered by the tenets of High Islam, which bound them to the circle of equity hypothesis and restricted their suggestions for action almost entirely to the traditional approach'.<ref target="BAWE_0147a-ftnote.023"/> In this way, the decline was remarked upon in scholarship. </s><s n="s4.5;p9.13">However, solutions were sought merely in relation to reinforcing the old order. </s><s n="s5.5;p9.13">Therefore, it is apparent that the decline of the Ottoman Empire was largely due to incompetent administrative management that failed to respond to external and internal change. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0147a-ftnote.023"><p n="pn1.1"><s rend="italic" n="s1.2;pn1.1">Op.Cit. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">, Stiles, p.130 </s></p></note><p n="p10.13"><s n="s1.4;p10.13">The extent of the Ottoman Empire was greater in the 1620s than it had been a century before.<ref target="BAWE_0147a-ftnote.024"/> However, this figure should not be mistaken for the Ottoman's military might during that period. </s><s n="s2.4;p10.13">Indeed, their withdrawal from Malta in 1565 signaled the halt of territorial expansion into Europe and the Mediterranean.<ref target="BAWE_0147a-ftnote.025"/> Nonetheless, futile campaigns against the Habsburgs and the Persians were exhausting and their continued military failure contributed to an ever declining Ottoman state. </s><s n="s3.4;p10.13">In this way, increased amounts of state spending were diverted towards the military cause without any tangible benefits from the annexations of territory. </s><s n="s4.4;p10.13">As Colin Imber notes, 'it is unlikely that the tax yield of the new provinces covered the cost of their garrisons'.<ref target="BAWE_0147a-ftnote.026"/> The internal causes somewhat overshadow the significance of the discovery of a sea passage to Asia in the decline of the Ottoman Empire. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0147a-ftnote.024"><p n="pn1.1"><s rend="italic" n="s1.2;pn1.1">Op.Cit. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">, Steensgaard, p.75 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0147a-ftnote.025"><p n="pn1.1"><s rend="italic" n="s1.2;pn1.1">Op.Cit. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">, Inalcik, p.41 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0147a-ftnote.026"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Colin Imber, <hi rend="italic">The Ottoman Empire</hi> (New York, 2002), p.67 </s></p></note><p n="p11.13"><s n="s1.3;p11.13">At this juncture it is important to make a few points about the orientalist discourse and its relevance to the discussion of the decline of the Ottoman Empire. </s><s n="s2.3;p11.13">It is extremely difficult to produce a work about the Orient without forming part of the highly-criticized orientalist discourse. </s><s n="s3.3;p11.13">Edward Said argues continuously that, </s></p><quote lang="English">'the Orient is itself a constituted entity and that the notion that there are geographical spaces with indigenous radically different inhabitants who can be defined on the basis of some religion, culture or racial essence proper to that geographical space is [...] a highly debatable idea.'<ref target="BAWE_0147a-ftnote.027"/></quote><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0147a-ftnote.027"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Edward Said, <hi rend="italic">Orientalism</hi> (New York, 1979), p.322 </s></p></note><p n="p12.13"><s n="s1.4;p12.13">Filters through which the Ottoman Empire is seen are inevitably tainted by the assumptions of norms. </s><s n="s2.4;p12.13">Western socio-economic and political institutions dictate the underlying assumptions about the analysis of all things that represent an <hi rend="italic">Other</hi>.<ref target="BAWE_0147a-ftnote.028"/> In this sense for instance this essay is perhaps itself guilty of using orientalist constructions. </s><s n="s3.4;p12.13">However, it has attempted to distance itself from a Eurocentric approach that places large emphasis on external trade routes. </s><s n="s4.4;p12.13">Instead, there has been a great effort to demonstrate that the Empire's causes for decline came largely from within. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0147a-ftnote.028"><p n="pn1.1"><s rend="italic" n="s1.2;pn1.1">Ibid. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">, pp.6-7 </s></p></note><p n="p13.13"><s n="s1.9;p13.13">Hence, in conclusion, the discovery of the sea passage to Asia was not a key factor in the decline of the Ottoman Empire. </s><s n="s2.9;p13.13">Much more prominent are internal causes such as corruption and inefficient fiscal policies. </s><s n="s3.9;p13.13">The effects of the loss of transit trade on the Ottoman Empire were minimal as local merchants could easily redirect their investments towards the flourishing interior trade. </s><s n="s4.9;p13.13">The drive for territorial expansion further lent a destabilizing element to Ottoman society. </s><s n="s5.9;p13.13">Therefore, the foundations of the empire crumbled as the old social structures and institutions ceased to adapt to a modern changing society. </s><s n="s6.9;p13.13">The overarching topic of the Orient is inevitably seen through the filter of an orientalist discourse. </s><s n="s7.9;p13.13">However, a solely post-modern approach to the study of the Ottoman Empire would not be feasible. </s><s n="s8.9;p13.13">Hence, some assumptions made in this essay, even though orientalist, contribute to a greater understanding of the decline. </s><s n="s9.9;p13.13">In all, the discovery of the sea passage to Asia played little part in the decline of the Ottoman Empire. </s></p></div1></body><back><div1 type="bibliography"><head rend="underlined bold">Bibliography</head><p>Cizakca, Murat. <hi rend="underlined">Price History and the Bursa Silk Industry: A Study in Ottoman Industrial Decline 1550-1650</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Journal of Economic History</hi>, Vol. 40, No. 3 (1980)</p><p>Faroqhi, Suraiya; McGowan, Bruce; Quataertm, Donald; Pamuk, Sevket. (eds.), <hi rend="italic">An Economic and Social History of the Ottoman Empire</hi>, Vol. 2, Cambridge University Press (Cambridge, 1994) </p><p>Goffman, Daniel. <hi rend="italic">The Ottoman Empire and Early Modern Europe</hi>, Cambridge University Press (Cambridge, 2002)</p><p>Imber, Colin. <hi rend="italic">The Ottoman Empire</hi>, Palgrave (New York, 2002)</p><p>Inalcik, Halil. <hi rend="italic">The Ottoman Empire The Classical Age 1300-1600</hi>, Weidenfeld and Nicolson (London, 1973)</p><p>Kunt, Metin; Woodhead, Christine. <hi rend="italic">Suleyman the magnificent and his age</hi>, Longman (London, 1995)</p><p>Panzac, Daniel. International <hi rend="underlined">and Domestic Maritime Trade in the Ottoman Empire during the 18th Century</hi>, <hi rend="italic">International Journal of Middle East Studies</hi>, Vol. 24, No. 2 (1992)</p><p>Said, Edward. <hi rend="italic">Orientalism</hi>, Vintage Books (New York, 1979)</p><p>Steensgaard, Niels. <hi rend="italic">The Asian Trade Revolution of the Seventeenth Century</hi>, University of Chicago Press (London, 1973)</p><p>Stiles, Andrina. <hi rend="italic">The Ottoman Empire 1450-1700</hi>, Hodder and Stoughton (Kent, 1989)</p><p>Wood, H. <hi rend="italic">A History of the Levant Company</hi> (London, 1935)</p></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
