<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_0148b" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Analyse the Decision In Pepper v Hart [1993] AC 593</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">Language used in quote: <foreign id="English">English</foreign></note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">deleted: header: student and page numbers</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">1</p><p n="date">2006-01</p><p n="module title">The Modern English Legal System</p><p n="module code">LA115</p><p n="genre family">Critique</p><p n="discipline">Law</p><p n="disciplinary group">SS</p><p n="grade">M</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">1260</p><p n="number of s-units">54</p><p n="number of p">10</p><p n="number of tables">0</p><p n="number of figures">0</p><p n="number of block quotes">1</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">0</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">0</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">23.3</p><p n="average s-units per p">5.4</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">f</p><p n="year of birth">1986</p><p n="first language">English</p><p n="education">UKA</p><p n="course">LLB</p><p n="student ID">0148</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><docTitle><titlePart>Analyse the Decision In <hi rend="italic">Pepper v Hart</hi> [1993] AC 593</titlePart></docTitle></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="section"><p n="p1.10"><s n="s1.5;p1.10">The landmark decision in <hi rend="italic">Pepper v Hart</hi><ref target="BAWE_0148b-ftnote.001"/> to relax the exclusionary rule regarding the use of Hansard has received much comment and criticism. </s><s n="s2.5;p1.10">One must consider the advantages of using parliamentary material as an aid to statutory construction as it allows the courts to "give effect to...the intentions of parliament." </s><ref target="BAWE_0148b-ftnote.002"/><s n="s3.5;p1.10">Yet on the other hand there are huge concerns regarding the constitutional implications of the decision<ref target="BAWE_0148b-ftnote.003"/> and it's affect on the concept of the separation of powers. </s><s n="s4.5;p1.10">Furthermore one must consider the financial and practical implications of the decision; increased time and expense inevitably linked with using Hansard is a disadvantage<ref target="BAWE_0148b-ftnote.004"/>. </s><s n="s5.5;p1.10">One must therefore decide whether the advantages of using Hansard outweigh practical and political objections. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0148b-ftnote.001"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1"><hi rend="italic">Pepper (Inspector of taxes) v Hart</hi> [1993] AC 593 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0148b-ftnote.002"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1"><hi rend="italic">Pepper (Inspector of taxes) v Hart</hi> [1993] AC 593 at p. 22 per Lord Browne-Wilkinson </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0148b-ftnote.003"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Steyn, J., 'Pepper v Hart; a Re-Examination' 21 (59) <hi rend="italic">Oxford Journal of Legal Studies,</hi> March 2001 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0148b-ftnote.004"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">See White, 'Hansard's up' (1992) 136 <hi rend="italic">Solicitors Journal</hi> 1224 and Davenport, 'Perfection but at what cost? </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">(1993) 109 <hi rend="italic">Law Quarterly Review</hi>149 </s></p></note><p n="p2.10"><s n="s1.8;p2.10"><hi rend="italic">Pepper v Hart</hi><ref target="BAWE_0148b-ftnote.005"/> involved school masters from Malvern College who partook in a concessionary scheme which meant their sons were educated at one fifth of the normal fees. </s><s n="s2.8;p2.10">It was not disputed that the fees were a taxable benefit under s.61 of The Finance Act 1976. </s><s n="s3.8;p2.10">However, the issue was "what is the cash equivalent of the benefit?" </s><s n="s4.8;p2.10">This Phrase was defined in section 63 of the 1976 Act. </s><s n="s5.8;p2.10">The school masters argued the "cost of the benefit was the marginal cost to the employer providing the benefit"<ref target="BAWE_0148b-ftnote.006"/> and was therefore nil. </s><s n="s6.8;p2.10">It was originally held as correct, yet the crown contended this and argued that the expense incurred in educating the taxpayer's sons was the same as a fee-paying member of the public. </s><s n="s7.8;p2.10">Their appeal was allowed. </s><s n="s8.8;p2.10">The issue was therefore placed before the House of Lords. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0148b-ftnote.005"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1"><hi rend="italic">Pepper (Inspector of taxes) v Hart</hi> [1993] AC 593 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0148b-ftnote.006"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1"><hi rend="italic">Pepper (Inspector of taxes) v Hart</hi> [1993] AC 593 p.1 </s></p></note><p n="p3.10"><s n="s1.2;p3.10">The point of law presented to the House of Lords was whether or not the courts should relax the exclusionary rule and be permitted to examine the proceedings in parliament prior to the enactment of s 63 in order to firmly establish their true intentions. </s><s n="s2.2;p3.10">Seven Law Lords decided, in a 6:1 majority<ref target="BAWE_0148b-ftnote.007"/>, that </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0148b-ftnote.007"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Lord Mackay dissenting </s></p></note><quote lang="English"> "The exclusionary rule should be relaxed so as to permit reference to Parliamentary materials where: Legislation is ambiguous or obscure, or leads to an absurdity The material relied on consists of one or more statements by a minister or other promoter of the bill and The statements relied on are clear" <ref target="BAWE_0148b-ftnote.008"/></quote><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0148b-ftnote.008"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1"><hi rend="italic">Pepper (Inspector of taxes) v Hart</hi> [1993] AC 593 p.27-28 per Lord Browne-Wilkinson </s></p></note><p n="p4.10"><s n="s1.2;p4.10">This decision has been both commended and criticised. </s><s n="s2.2;p4.10">It changed the role of the courts with regard to statutory interpretation and it is therefore important to study subsequent cases to examine its application. </s></p><p n="p5.10"><s n="s1.7;p5.10">The decision in <hi rend="italic">Pepper</hi><ref target="BAWE_0148b-ftnote.009"/> has been applied in a number of subsequent cases such as <hi rend="italic">R v Warwickshire County Council.</hi> </s><ref target="BAWE_0148b-ftnote.010"/><s n="s2.7;p5.10"> This case concerned the interpretation of s 20 (1) of The Consumer Protection Act 1987 where the words "any business of his" were scrutinised. </s><s n="s3.7;p5.10">The court allowed reference to Hansard which clarified these words. </s><s n="s4.7;p5.10">This case and others<ref target="BAWE_0148b-ftnote.011"/>, highlight the way in which the House of Lords intended Hansard to be used: It shows that the decision has placed the courts in a position to more accurately interpret the intentions of parliament. </s><s n="s5.7;p5.10">In <hi rend="italic">Beckett v Midland electricity</hi><ref target="BAWE_0148b-ftnote.012"/> Lord Phillips stated that using Hansard "immediately made clear what had previously been obscure." </s><ref target="BAWE_0148b-ftnote.013"/><s n="s6.7;p5.10">Holland supports the use of Hansard stating that "there are certainly undoubted advantages in making use of all relevant materials to interpret a statute." </s><ref target="BAWE_0148b-ftnote.014"/><s n="s7.7;p5.10">Therefore both case law and academic writing highlight that there is support for the argument that the courts should not "blind themselves to a clear indication of what parliament intended." <ref target="BAWE_0148b-ftnote.015"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0148b-ftnote.009"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1"><hi rend="italic">Pepper (Inspector of taxes) v Hart</hi> [1993] AC 593 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0148b-ftnote.010"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1"><hi rend="italic">R v Warwickshire County Council, ex parte Johnson</hi> [1993] 2 WLR 1 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0148b-ftnote.011"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">See <hi rend="italic">Stubbings v Webb</hi> [1993] 2 WLR 120, <hi rend="italic">Chief Adjudication Officer v Foster</hi> [1992] 2 WLR 292 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0148b-ftnote.012"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1"><hi rend="italic">A.E. Beckett and sons Ltd v Midland Electricity plc</hi> [2001] 1 WLR 281 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0148b-ftnote.013"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1"><hi rend="italic">A.E. Beckett and sons Ltd v Midland Electricity plc</hi> [2001] 1 WLR 281 p.34 per Lord Phillips MR </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0148b-ftnote.014"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Holland, J., Webb, J., <hi rend="italic">Learning Legal rules,</hi> 5th Edition, Oxford university Press, 2003 p.230 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0148b-ftnote.015"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1"><hi rend="italic">Pepper (Inspector of taxes) v Hart</hi> [1993] AC 593 p.23 per Lord Browne-Wilkinson </s></p></note><p n="p6.10"><s n="s1.1;p6.10">However, subsequent cases have also questioned and refined the decision. </s></p><p n="p7.10"><s n="s1.5;p7.10">There have been questions raised as to exactly when reference to Hansard should be permitted, what an ambiguity is and how clear the explanatory ministerial statement must be.<ref target="BAWE_0148b-ftnote.016"/> In <hi rend="italic">R v Secretary of state</hi><ref target="BAWE_0148b-ftnote.017"/> their lordships refined the rule, agreeing that "resort to Hansard as an aid to interpretation is the exception rather than the rule." </s><ref target="BAWE_0148b-ftnote.018"/><s n="s2.5;p7.10">Peacock,J who refers to the judgement of Lord Browne-Wilkinson as "deeply flawed"<ref target="BAWE_0148b-ftnote.019"/> supports this approach, stating that the courts should "treat the development in <hi rend="italic">Pepper</hi> as a limited exception to the rule." </s><ref target="BAWE_0148b-ftnote.020"/><s n="s3.5;p7.10">This cautious approach is extended further by Lord Browne-Wilkinson who refined his own decision in <hi rend="italic">Melluish v BMI</hi><ref target="BAWE_0148b-ftnote.021"/> warning against over-use of Hansard and stating that the ministerial statement must be "directed at the very point of litigation." </s><ref target="BAWE_0148b-ftnote.022"/><s n="s4.5;p7.10">It was the case of <hi rend="italic">Wilson</hi><ref target="BAWE_0148b-ftnote.023"/> which most "tamed and muted"<ref target="BAWE_0148b-ftnote.024"/> the decision in <hi rend="italic">Pepper</hi><ref target="BAWE_0148b-ftnote.025"/>. </s><s n="s5.5;p7.10">This case refined the decision so that it is now to be read in a narrow way; it essentially accepts that the parliamentary context of the legislation is of use, but direct ministerial statements should not be accepted as law. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0148b-ftnote.016"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">See <hi rend="italic">Sheppard v</hi> <hi rend="italic">Commissioners of Inland Revenue,</hi> [1993] Lexis Transcript per Aldous J </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0148b-ftnote.017"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1"><hi rend="italic">R v Secretary of State for the Environment, Transport and the regions (ex parte Spath Holme Ltd)</hi> [2001] 2 WLR 15, HL </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0148b-ftnote.018"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ingman, T., <hi rend="italic">The English Legal Process,</hi> 10th Edition, Oxford university Press, 2004 p 294 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0148b-ftnote.019"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Peacock, J., 'Flawed decision - the basis of the decision in Pepper v Hart' 90.43 (20), <hi rend="italic">Law Society Gazette</hi> 24 November 1993 p.2 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0148b-ftnote.020"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Peacock, J., 'Flawed decision - 'The second instalment of an analysis of Pepper v Hart examining the future for using Hansard as an aid to statutory construction' 90.46 (26), <hi rend="italic">Law Society Gazette</hi> 17 December 1993 p.3 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0148b-ftnote.021"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1"><hi rend="italic">Melluish (Inspector of Taxes) v BMI</hi> [1995] 3 WLR 630 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0148b-ftnote.022"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1"><hi rend="italic">Melluish (Inspector of Taxes) v BMI</hi> [1995] 3 WLR 630 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0148b-ftnote.023"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1"><hi rend="italic">Wilson v First County Trust Ltd</hi> [2004]1 AC 816 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0148b-ftnote.024"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Kavanagh, A., 'Pepper v Hart and matters of Constitutional Principle' <hi rend="italic">Law Quarterly Review</hi> 2005, 121, 98-122 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0148b-ftnote.025"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1"><hi rend="italic">Pepper (Inspector of taxes) v Hart</hi> [1993] AC 593 </s></p></note><p n="p8.10"><s n="s1.8;p8.10">It has been argued by some that the decision to relax the exclusionary rule raises "serious constitutional objections." </s><ref target="BAWE_0148b-ftnote.026"/><s n="s2.8;p8.10">Lord Steyn suggests that an individual's statement cannot "represent the intentions of parliament i.e. both houses." </s><ref target="BAWE_0148b-ftnote.027"/><s n="s3.8;p8.10">This is an important point to consider. </s><s n="s4.8;p8.10">It has been taken to a further extent, some arguing that ministers may make deliberate statements which can be referred to in later litigation.<ref target="BAWE_0148b-ftnote.028"/> Lord Steyn describes this as "a constitutional shift in power from parliament to ministers." </s><ref target="BAWE_0148b-ftnote.029"/><s n="s5.8;p8.10">This has serious implications as parliament are the supreme law making body in the UK and if individual ministers are able to use the relaxation of the exclusionary rule to have more influence over the law then the constitution is threatened. </s><s n="s6.8;p8.10">The decision in <hi rend="italic">Pepper</hi> blurs the lines between parliament and the judiciary, thus disturbing Montesquieu's concept of the separation of powers. </s><s n="s7.8;p8.10">Kavanagh is deeply critical of this effect has on the constitution and commends the decision in <hi rend="italic">Wilson.</hi> </s><ref target="BAWE_0148b-ftnote.030"/><s n="s8.8;p8.10"> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0148b-ftnote.026"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Steyn, J., 'Pepper v Hart; a Re-Examination' 21 (59) <hi rend="italic">Oxford Journal of Legal Studies,</hi> March 2001 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0148b-ftnote.027"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Steyn, J., 'Pepper v Hart; a Re-Examination' 21 (59) <hi rend="italic">Oxford Journal of Legal Studies,</hi> March 2001 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0148b-ftnote.028"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Marshall, G., 'Hansard and the Interpretation of statutes' in Oliver, D., and Drewry, G., <hi rend="italic">The Law and Parliament,</hi> Butterworths, 1998 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0148b-ftnote.029"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Steyn, J., 'Pepper v Hart; a Re-Examination' 21 (59) <hi rend="italic">Oxford Journal of Legal Studies,</hi> March 2001 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0148b-ftnote.030"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1"><hi rend="italic">Wilson v First County Trust Ltd</hi> [2004]1 AC 816 </s></p></note><p n="p9.10"><s n="s1.10;p9.10">One must also consider that use of Hansard may result in "an immense increase in...cost of litigation." </s><ref target="BAWE_0148b-ftnote.031"/><s n="s2.10;p9.10">It is clear that using Hansard makes litigation a more lengthy and consequently more expensive process. </s><s n="s3.10;p9.10">This has social implications which may restrict access to justice to those who cannot afford the cost of lengthy litigation. </s><s n="s4.10;p9.10">Davenport points out that "The cost of legal services is largely governed by the length of time occupied in providing them. </s><s n="s5.10;p9.10">Will clients really have confidence in the legal system if they see such items on their bill?" </s><ref target="BAWE_0148b-ftnote.032"/><s n="s6.10;p9.10">The accessibility of Hansard must also be considered: White suggests that "apart from those in London, it is highly unlikely that Hansard will be readily available." </s><ref target="BAWE_0148b-ftnote.033"/><s n="s7.10;p9.10">Therefore, the decision in <hi rend="italic">Pepper</hi><ref target="BAWE_0148b-ftnote.034"/> has social implications. </s><s n="s8.10;p9.10">If use of Hansard is to be limited by access and cost of litigation it does not deliver the justice it is supposed to. </s><s n="s9.10;p9.10">Lord Steyn refers to use of Hansard as an "expensive luxury"<ref target="BAWE_0148b-ftnote.035"/> which "has substantially increased the cost of litigation to very little advantage." </s><ref target="BAWE_0148b-ftnote.036"/><s n="s10.10;p9.10">Therefore, the use of Hansard in finding justice must be juxtaposed against the practical problems it creates. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0148b-ftnote.031"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1"><hi rend="italic">Pepper (Inspector of taxes) v Hart</hi> [1993] AC 593 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0148b-ftnote.032"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Davenport 'perfection but at what cost?' </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">1993 109 LQR 149 at 154-155 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0148b-ftnote.033"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">White, 'Hansard's up' (1992) 136 <hi rend="italic">Solicitors Journal</hi> 1224 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0148b-ftnote.034"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1"><hi rend="italic">Pepper (Inspector of taxes) v Hart</hi> [1993] AC 593 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0148b-ftnote.035"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Steyn, J., 'Pepper v Hart; a Re-Examination' 21 (59) <hi rend="italic">Oxford Journal of Legal Studies,</hi> March 2001 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0148b-ftnote.036"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Steyn, J., 'Pepper v Hart; a Re-Examination' 21 (59) <hi rend="italic">Oxford Journal of Legal Studies,</hi> March 2001 </s></p></note><p n="p10.10"><s n="s1.6;p10.10">In conclusion, there are advantages of using Hansard. </s><s n="s2.6;p10.10">It is beneficial for a court to place itself in a position of clarity with regard to the intentions of parliament. </s><s n="s3.6;p10.10">One must however consider political objections to the relaxation of the exclusionary rule, which question the effect the rule may have on the constitution and the concept of separation of powers. </s><s n="s4.6;p10.10">The practical and financial disadvantages of the rule are also of some substance; increasing the cost of litigation may create the paradox that a rule designed to increase justice may actually prevent a part of society from accessing it. </s><s n="s5.6;p10.10">Whether we should follow Lord Steyn's advice to fully re-examine the case remains to be seen. </s><s n="s6.6;p10.10">For the instance therefore, we must trust the courts to use their discretion, as shown in cases such as <hi rend="italic">Wilson</hi><ref target="BAWE_0148b-ftnote.037"/>, ensuring that the rule is not taken too far. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0148b-ftnote.037"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1"><hi rend="italic">Wilson v First County Trust Ltd</hi> [2004]1 AC 816 </s></p></note></div1></body><back><div1 type="bibliography"><head>Bibliography</head><div2 type="bibliography"><head rend="underlined bold">Books</head><p>Holland, J., Webb, J., <hi rend="italic">Learning Legal rules,</hi> 5<hi rend="sup">th</hi> Edition, Oxford University Press, 2003</p><p>Ingman, T., <hi rend="italic">The English Legal Process,</hi> 10<hi rend="sup">th</hi> Edition, Oxford university Press, 2004</p><p>Manchester, C., Salter, D., Moodie, P. &amp; Lynch., <hi rend="italic">Exploring the Law</hi>, 2<hi rend="sup">nd</hi> Edition, London: Sweet and Maxwell, 2000</p><p>Oliver, D., Drewry, G., <hi rend="italic">The Law and Parliament,</hi> Butterworths, 1998</p><p>Slapper, G., Kelly, D., <hi rend="italic">The English Legal System,</hi> 7<hi rend="sup">th</hi> Edition, Cavendish Publishing, 2004</p></div2><div2 type="bibliography"><head rend="underlined bold">Articles</head><p>Davenport, 'Perfection but at what cost? (1993) 109 <hi rend="italic">Law Quarterly Review</hi>149</p><p>Kavanagh, A., 'Pepper v Hart and matters of Constitutional Principle' <hi rend="italic">Law Quarterly Review</hi> 2005, 121, 98-122</p><p>Peacock, J., 'Flawed decision - the basis of the decision in Pepper v Hart' (1993) 90.43 (20), <hi rend="italic">Law Society Gazette</hi></p><p>Peacock, J., 'Flawed decision - 'The second instalment of an analysis of Pepper v Hart examining the future for using Hansard as an aid to statutory construction' (1993) 90.46 (26), <hi rend="italic">Law Society Gazette</hi></p><p>Steyn, J., 'Pepper v Hart; a Re-Examination' (2001) 21 (59) <hi rend="italic">Oxford Journal of Legal Studies</hi></p><p>Tunkel, V., 'Research after Pepper v Hart' (1993) 90.18 (17), <hi rend="italic">Law Society Gazette,</hi></p><p>White, 'Hansard's up' (1992) 136 <hi rend="italic">Solicitors Journal</hi> 1224</p></div2><div2 type="bibliography"><head>Table of Cases</head><p><hi rend="italic">A.E. Beckett and sons Ltd v Midland Electricity plc</hi> [2001] 1 WLR 281</p><p><hi rend="italic">Chief Adjudication Officer v Foster</hi> [1992] 2 WLR 292</p><p><hi rend="italic">Melluish (Inspector of Taxes) v BMI</hi> [1995] 3 WLR 630</p><p><hi rend="italic">Pepper (Inspector of taxes) v Hart</hi> [1993] AC 593</p><p rend="italic">R v Secretary of State for the Environment, Transport and the regions (ex parte Spath</p><p><hi rend="italic">Holme Ltd)</hi> [2001] 2 WLR 15, HL </p><p><hi rend="italic">R v Warwickshire County Council, ex parte Johnson</hi> [1993] 2 WLR 1</p><p><hi rend="italic">Sheppard v Commissioners of Inland Revenue,</hi> [1993] Lexis Transcript</p><p><hi rend="italic">Stubbings v Webb</hi> [1993] 2 WLR 120</p><p><hi rend="italic">Wilson v First County Trust Ltd</hi> [2004]1 AC 816</p></div2><div2 type="bibliography"><head>Table of Statutes</head><p>The Finance Act 1976 s.61</p><p> s.63</p><p>Consumer Protection Act 1987 s. 20</p></div2></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
