<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_0148a" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Critically assess the doctrine of intention to create legal relations in the light of the above statement and relevant legal developments.</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">deleted: header: student and page numbers</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">1</p><p n="date">2006-01</p><p n="module title">Basic Techniques of Common Law in Contract &amp; Tort</p><p n="module code">LA102</p><p n="genre family">Essay</p><p n="discipline">Law</p><p n="disciplinary group">SS</p><p n="grade">M</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">1271</p><p n="number of s-units">57</p><p n="number of p">9</p><p n="number of tables">0</p><p n="number of figures">0</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">0</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">0</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">22.3</p><p n="average s-units per p">6.3</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">f</p><p n="year of birth">1986</p><p n="first language">English</p><p n="education">UKA</p><p n="course">LLB</p><p n="student ID">0148</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><epigraph><p>"In cases where the issue is litigated, it seems likely that one party intended a legal agreement and the other wanted the agreement to be merely morally binding. This contradiction removes any possibility of justifying the limits of contracts on the basis of the joint intent of the parties. We are forced to the conclusion that the courts must rely on hidden policy considerations when determining the intentions of the parties" [Collins, H (2003) <hi rend="italic">The Law of Contract</hi> pp.104-105]</p></epigraph><docTitle><titlePart>Critically assess the doctrine of intention to create legal relations in the light of the above statement and relevant legal developments.</titlePart></docTitle></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">Introduction</head><p n="p1.9"><s n="s1.7;p1.9">In order to find a valid contract the courts must be satisfied that both parties intended to create legal relations. </s><s n="s2.7;p1.9">It is therefore their role to objectively examine both the context of the agreement and the behaviour of the parties and to draw reasonable inferences from this. </s><s n="s3.7;p1.9">Where there is no express statement of contractual intent, the courts must examine "hidden policy considerations." </s><ref target="BAWE_0148a-ftnote.001"/><s n="s4.7;p1.9">The main aspect of these considerations is the context in which the agreement is made. </s><s n="s5.7;p1.9">The courts apply presumptions according to whether the agreement was made in a commercial or domestic environment to draw conclusions regarding contractual intent. </s><s n="s6.7;p1.9">There are other considerations which may rebut these presumptions. </s><s n="s7.7;p1.9">This doctrine and approach has been supported and criticised, I therefore aim to explore and balance these arguments in order to provide my own analysis of the doctrine. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0148a-ftnote.001"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Collins, H <hi rend="italic">The Law of Contract,</hi> Butterworths, 2003 p.104-105 </s></p></note><p n="p2.9"><s n="s1.5;p2.9">The doctrine of Intention to create legal relations is an essential aspect of any contract; in addition to finding offer, acceptance and consideration, "an agreement will not constitute a binding contract unless it is one which can be reasonably regarded to have been made in contemplation of legal consequences." </s><ref target="BAWE_0148a-ftnote.002"/><s n="s2.5;p2.9">Collins' Statement concerns the objective way in which the courts interpret the '<hi rend="italic">animus contrahendi'</hi><ref target="BAWE_0148a-ftnote.003"/>. </s><s n="s3.5;p2.9">The parties cannot state what they believed their intentions to be; it is for the court to decide this based upon the concept that "if a reasonable person would consider there was intention to contract...the promisor will be bound." </s><ref target="BAWE_0148a-ftnote.004"/><s n="s4.5;p2.9">The courts examine the intentions of the parties through hidden policy considerations such as "the language they use and the circumstances in which they use it." </s><ref target="BAWE_0148a-ftnote.005"/><s n="s5.5;p2.9">They consider the context and apply a presumption as to the intent of the parties. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0148a-ftnote.002"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Beatson, J., <hi rend="italic">Anson's Law of Contract,</hi> 28th Edition, Oxford University Press, 2002 p. 69 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0148a-ftnote.003"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Meaning Intention to create contractual relations, <hi rend="italic">Heilbut, Symons and Co v Buckleton</hi> [1913] AC 30 p.47 per Lord Moulton </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0148a-ftnote.004"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Beatson, J., <hi rend="italic">Anson's Law of Contract,</hi> 28th Edition, Oxford University Press, 2002 p. 71 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0148a-ftnote.005"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1"><hi rend="italic">Parker v Clark</hi> [1960] 1 WLR 286 </s></p></note></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">Domestic and Social agreements</head><p n="p3.9"><s n="s1.10;p3.9">One must first consider domestic and social agreements; it is usually in this context that "one party intended a legal agreement and the other wanted the agreement to be merely morally binding." </s><ref target="BAWE_0148a-ftnote.006"/><s n="s2.10;p3.9">The presumption in a domestic context is that there is no intention to create legal relations. </s><s n="s3.10;p3.9">Case law highlights how the courts use "hidden policy considerations" of context to exclude domestic agreements from contract law. </s><s n="s4.10;p3.9">The leading case is <hi rend="italic">Balfour v Balfour</hi><ref target="BAWE_0148a-ftnote.007"/>; a husband, living in Ceylon promised to pay his wife, living England, £30 in expenses. </s><s n="s5.10;p3.9">They separated and the wife attempted to enforce the agreement. </s><s n="s6.10;p3.9">Finding that the agreement was not an enforceable contract, Lord Atkin essentially excluded domestic agreements from the ambit of contract law. </s><s n="s7.10;p3.9">He examined hidden policy considerations, concluding that because the agreement was made in the domestic environment "they did not intend that they should be attended by legal consequences." </s><ref target="BAWE_0148a-ftnote.008"/><s n="s8.10;p3.9">The decision in that "every house is a domain in which the King's writ does not seek to run"<ref target="BAWE_0148a-ftnote.009"/> is supported by <hi rend="italic">Jones v Padavatton</hi><ref target="BAWE_0148a-ftnote.010"/> where the court refused to uphold a contract between mother and child. </s><s n="s9.10;p3.9">This extends the concept of excluding domestic agreements from contract law. </s><s n="s10.10;p3.9">Other instances of application<ref target="BAWE_0148a-ftnote.011"/> show that the courts infer intent from the relationship of the parties and context of the agreement. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0148a-ftnote.006"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Collins H <hi rend="italic">The Law of Contract,</hi> Butterworths, 2003 p.104-105 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0148a-ftnote.007"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1"><hi rend="italic">Balfour v Balfour</hi> [1919] 2 KB 571 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0148a-ftnote.008"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1"><hi rend="italic">Balfour v Balfour</hi> [1919] 2 KB 571 per Lord Atkin </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0148a-ftnote.009"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1"><hi rend="italic">Balfour v Balfour</hi> [1919] 2 KB 571 per Lord Atkin </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0148a-ftnote.010"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1"><hi rend="italic">Jones v Padavatton</hi> [1969] 1 WLR 328 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0148a-ftnote.011"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">E.g. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1"><hi rend="italic">Spellman v Spellman</hi> [1961] 1 WLR 921 </s></p></note><p n="p4.9"><s n="s1.6;p4.9">It has been argued that the domestic presumption is one of public policy aiming to keep agreements made in the environment of "love and affection"<ref target="BAWE_0148a-ftnote.012"/> outside the jurisdiction of the "cold courts." </s><ref target="BAWE_0148a-ftnote.013"/><s n="s2.6;p4.9">Appleby argues this is "a policy decision leaving various types of agreement outside the ambit of the law." </s><ref target="BAWE_0148a-ftnote.014"/><s n="s3.6;p4.9">The divisions put in place are a matter of public policy, aiming to protect the privacy of family life. </s><s n="s4.6;p4.9">Atiyah supports this view stating that the decision in <hi rend="italic">Balfour</hi><ref target="BAWE_0148a-ftnote.015"/> depends on "the courts view that it would be unseemly distressing to allow husbands and wives...to use the court as an arbiter for their matrimonial differences." </s><ref target="BAWE_0148a-ftnote.016"/><s n="s5.6;p4.9">One must question whether this approach is incongruous with today's society. </s><s n="s6.6;p4.9">Freeman argues that the decision in <hi rend="italic">Balfour,</hi><ref target="BAWE_0148a-ftnote.017"/> a Victorian marriage, is outdated thus the approach taken by the courts to establish intent "no longer reflects realities nor is it inline with the developments taking place within family law." <ref target="BAWE_0148a-ftnote.018"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0148a-ftnote.012"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1"><hi rend="italic">Balfour v Balfour</hi> [1919] 2 KB 571 per Lord Atkin </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0148a-ftnote.013"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1"><hi rend="italic">Balfour v Balfour</hi> [1919] 2 KB 571 per Lord Atkin p.579 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0148a-ftnote.014"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Appleby, G., <hi rend="italic">Contract Law,</hi> Sweet and Maxwell, 2001 p. 178 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0148a-ftnote.015"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1"><hi rend="italic">Balfour v Balfour</hi> [1919] 2 KB 571 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0148a-ftnote.016"><p n="pn1.2"><s n="s1.1;pn1.2">Atiyah, PS., <hi rend="italic">An Introduction to the Law of Contract,</hi> 5th Edition, Oxford University Press, 1995 </s></p><p n="pn2.2"><s n="s1.2;pn2.2">p. </s><s n="s2.2;pn2.2">156 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0148a-ftnote.017"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1"><hi rend="italic">Balfour v Balfour</hi> [1919] 2 KB 571 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0148a-ftnote.018"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Freeman, M., 'Contracting in the Haven: <hi rend="italic">Balfour v Balfour</hi> Revisited' </s></p></note><p n="p5.9"><s n="s1.6;p5.9">However, the courts apply other hidden policy considerations in determining contractual intent; it is possible for the presumption to be rebutted. </s><s n="s2.6;p5.9">If the relationship is at "breaking point" when the agreement is made the courts may rebut the presumption, such as in <hi rend="italic">Merritt v Merritt.</hi> </s><ref target="BAWE_0148a-ftnote.019"/><s n="s3.6;p5.9"> The contract was agreed when the couple had separated and were therefore not living 'in amity." </s><ref target="BAWE_0148a-ftnote.020"/><s n="s4.6;p5.9">The courts upheld the contract stating that 'they do not rely on honourable understandings...they intend to create legal relations." </s><ref target="BAWE_0148a-ftnote.021"/><s n="s5.6;p5.9">In cases such as <hi rend="italic">Parker v Clark</hi><ref target="BAWE_0148a-ftnote.022"/>, intent was established from detriment incurred. </s><s n="s6.6;p5.9">The courts therefore objectively assess the relationship between the parties; these too are 'hidden policy considerations.' </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0148a-ftnote.019"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1"><hi rend="italic">Merritt v Merritt</hi> [1970] 1 WLR 1211 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0148a-ftnote.020"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1"><hi rend="italic">Merritt v Merritt</hi> [1970] 1 WLR 1211 p. 1213 per Lord Denning </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0148a-ftnote.021"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1"><hi rend="italic">Merritt v Merritt</hi> [1970] 1 WLR 1211 p. 1213 per Lord Denning </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0148a-ftnote.022"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1"><hi rend="italic">Parker v Clark</hi> [1960] 1 WLR 286 </s></p></note></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">Commercial context</head><p n="p6.9"><s n="s1.7;p6.9">Within the commercial context the presumption is that there is intention to create legal relations. </s><s n="s2.7;p6.9">This presumption is difficult to rebut; the onus "is on the party who asserts that no legal effect is intended...the onus is a heavy one." </s><ref target="BAWE_0148a-ftnote.023"/><s n="s3.7;p6.9">Cases such as <hi rend="italic">Esso v Commissioners of Customs,</hi><ref target="BAWE_0148a-ftnote.024"/> where <hi rend="italic">Esso</hi> ran a campaign giving a world cup coin to motorists who bought petrol, highlight the difficulties of rebutting the presumption. </s><s n="s4.7;p6.9">Lord Simon stated "the whole transaction took place in the setting of business relations." </s><ref target="BAWE_0148a-ftnote.025"/><s n="s5.7;p6.9">His examination of the context led him to conclude that there was contractual intent. </s><s n="s6.7;p6.9">This indicates the courts' unwillingness to examine any further hidden policy considerations within the commercial context. </s><s n="s7.7;p6.9">One could argue that this is a sensible approach as it allows for certainty within the commercial world. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0148a-ftnote.023"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1"><hi rend="italic">Edwards v Skyways Ltd</hi> [1964] 1 WLR 349 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0148a-ftnote.024"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1"><hi rend="italic">Esso Petroleum Ltd v Commissioners of Customs and Excise</hi> [1976] 1 WLR 1 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0148a-ftnote.025"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1"><hi rend="italic">Esso Petroleum Ltd v Commissioners of Customs and Excise</hi> [1976] 1 WLR 1 pp 5-6 per Lord Simon </s></p></note><p n="p7.9"><s n="s1.7;p7.9">It is however possible to rebut the presumption. </s><s n="s2.7;p7.9">One way to do this is the use of honour clauses such as in <hi rend="italic">Rose and Frank v JR Crompton</hi><ref target="BAWE_0148a-ftnote.026"/> which stated that the parties "honourably pledge themselves...with mutual loyalty and friendly cooperation." </s><ref target="BAWE_0148a-ftnote.027"/><s n="s3.7;p7.9">Similarly in <hi rend="italic">Appleson v Littlewoods</hi><ref target="BAWE_0148a-ftnote.028"/> it was stated that a competition was not to be "legally enforceable or be subject of litigation." </s><ref target="BAWE_0148a-ftnote.029"/><s n="s4.7;p7.9">In both instances the statements were held to negate contractual intention. </s><s n="s5.7;p7.9">These are express statements that there was no contractual intent. </s><s n="s6.7;p7.9">In a commercial context the courts will apply a presumption that there was intent to create legal relations. </s><s n="s7.7;p7.9">This is essentially the only hidden policy consideration; successful rebuttals are usually express statements. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0148a-ftnote.026"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1"><hi rend="italic">Rose and Frank Co v JR Crompton and Brothers Ltd</hi> [1925] AC 445 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0148a-ftnote.027"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1"><hi rend="italic">Rose and Frank Co v JR Crompton and Brothers Ltd</hi> [1925] AC 445 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0148a-ftnote.028"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1"><hi rend="italic">Appleson v Littlewood Ltd</hi> [1939] 1 All ER 464 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0148a-ftnote.029"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1"><hi rend="italic">Appleson v Littlewood Ltd</hi> [1939] 1 All ER 464 </s></p></note></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">Further arguments</head><p n="p8.9"><s n="s1.4;p8.9">It has been argued that the doctrine of intent to contract is unnecessary.<ref target="BAWE_0148a-ftnote.030"/> Hepple states that 'the fact that they have cast their arrangement into the form of a bargain...provides an extremely practical test of...intention." </s><ref target="BAWE_0148a-ftnote.031"/><s n="s2.4;p8.9">This critical analysis is supported by M Furmston who points out that 'A proposal cannot properly be regarded as an offer unless it indicates an intention to undertake legal obligation." </s><ref target="BAWE_0148a-ftnote.032"/><s n="s3.4;p8.9">This suggests that it is unnecessary to find intent through hidden policy considerations; it could be found through the presence of the other aspects of a contract. </s><s n="s4.4;p8.9">It is true that the law of contract existed without the doctrine until the nineteenth century<ref target="BAWE_0148a-ftnote.033"/> but its removal now would create a far more complex situation. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0148a-ftnote.030"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Hepple, B., 'Intention to Create Legal Relations.' (1970) <hi rend="italic">Cambridge Law Journal</hi> 122 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0148a-ftnote.031"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Hepple, B., 'Intention to Create Legal Relations.' (1970) <hi rend="italic">Cambridge Law Journal</hi> 122 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0148a-ftnote.032"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Furmston, M. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1"><hi rend="italic">Butterworths Common Law Series: The Law of Contract</hi>, Butterworths 1999 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0148a-ftnote.033"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1"><hi rend="italic">Carlill v Carbolic Smoke Company Ltd</hi> [1892] 2 QB 484 </s></p></note></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">Conclusion</head><p n="p9.9"><s n="s1.5;p9.9">In conclusion, the courts rely on hidden policy considerations to help them establish the presence of intention to create legal relations. </s><s n="s2.5;p9.9">These hidden policy considerations are the behaviour of the parties and context of the agreement. </s><s n="s3.5;p9.9">Where intent is not expressly stated the courts take an objective approach, considering all the factors of the agreement. </s><s n="s4.5;p9.9">The context of the agreement is the most powerful influence on the court's decision, but other considerations can be taken in to account to rebut the initial presumption. </s><s n="s5.5;p9.9">I therefore agree with Collins that the most appropriate way for the courts to establish intention is studying the wider scope of the agreement. </s></p></div1></body><back><div1 type="bibliography"><head>Bibliography</head><div2 type="bibliography"><head rend="underlined bold">Books</head><p>Adams, J., Bronsword, R., <hi rend="italic">Understanding Contract Law,</hi> 4<hi rend="sup">th</hi> Edition, Sweet and Maxwell, 2004</p><p>Appleby, G., <hi rend="italic">Contract Law,</hi> Sweet and Maxwell, 2001</p><p>Atiyah, PS., <hi rend="italic">An Introduction to the Law of Contract,</hi> 5<hi rend="sup">th</hi> Edition, Oxford University Press, 1995</p><p>Beatson, J., <hi rend="italic">Anson's Law of Contract,</hi> 28<hi rend="sup">th</hi> Edition, Oxford University Press, 2002</p><p>Chitty, J., <hi rend="italic">Chitty on contract</hi> 29<hi rend="sup">th</hi> Edition, London Sweet and Maxwell 2004</p><p>Furmston, M. <hi rend="italic">Butterworths Common Law Series: The Law of Contract</hi>, Butterworths 1999</p><p>Mc Kendrick, E., <hi rend="italic">Contract Law text, cases and materials,</hi> Oxford University Press, 2003</p><p>Poole, J., <hi rend="italic">Casebook on Contract Law,</hi> 7<hi rend="sup">th</hi> Edition, Oxford University Press, 2003</p><p>Smith, J.C., <hi rend="italic">The Law of Contract,</hi> 4<hi rend="sup">th</hi> Edition, Sweet and Maxwell, 2002</p><p>Upex, R., Bennet, G., <hi rend="italic">Davies on Contract,</hi> 9<hi rend="sup">th</hi> Edition, Sweet and Maxwell, 2004</p></div2><div2 type="bibliography"><head rend="underlined bold">Articles</head><p>Hedley, S., 'Keeping Contract in its place: Balfour v Balfour and the enforceability of Informal agreements.' (1985) 5 <hi rend="italic">Oxford Journal of Legal Studies</hi> 391</p><p>Hepple, B., 'Intention to Create Legal Relations.' (1970) <hi rend="italic">Cambridge Law Journal</hi> 122</p><p>Freeman, M., 'Contracting in the Haven: <hi rend="italic">Balfour v Balfour</hi> Revisited'</p></div2><div2 type="bibliography"><head>Table of Cases</head><p><hi rend="italic">Appleson v Littlewood Ltd</hi> [1939] 1 All ER 464</p><p><hi rend="italic">Balfour v Balfour</hi> [1919] 2 KB 571</p><p><hi rend="italic">Carlill v Carbolic Smoke Company Ltd</hi> [1892] 2 QB 484</p><p><hi rend="italic">Edwards v Skyways Ltd</hi> [1964] 1 WLR 349</p><p><hi rend="italic">Esso Petroleum Ltd v Commissioners of Customs and Excise</hi> [1976] 1 WLR 1</p><p><hi rend="italic">Jones v Padavatton</hi> [1969] 1 WLR 328</p><p><hi rend="italic">Merritt v Merritt</hi> [1970] 1 WLR 1211</p><p><hi rend="italic">Parker v Clark</hi> [1960] 1 WLR 286</p><p><hi rend="italic">Rose and Frank Co v JR Crompton and Brothers Ltd</hi> [1925] AC 445</p><p><hi rend="italic">Spellman v Spellman</hi> [1961] 1 WLR 921</p></div2></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
