<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_0152b" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Culture in International Business</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">header: student and module number, assignment name
footer: page numbers
</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">2</p><p n="date">2005-02</p><p n="module title">International Environment of Business</p><p n="module code">IB2180</p><p n="genre family">Critique</p><p n="discipline">Business</p><p n="disciplinary group">SS</p><p n="grade">M</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">626</p><p n="number of s-units">27</p><p n="number of p">7</p><p n="number of tables">0</p><p n="number of figures">0</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">0</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">0</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">23.2</p><p n="average s-units per p">3.9</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">f</p><p n="year of birth">1983</p><p n="first language">Malay</p><p n="education">OSA</p><p n="course">Business</p><p n="student ID">0152</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><docTitle><titlePart rend="bold">Culture in International Business</titlePart></docTitle></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="section"><p n="p1.7"><s n="s1.4;p1.7">Recently, the importance of culture in International Business was discussed and it had definitely broadened my view on the concept of culture. </s><s n="s2.4;p1.7">Learning that culture has a significant influence on business strategy, brands, and marketing activities is to me, stimulating. </s><s n="s3.4;p1.7">For instance it is interesting to observe its applications to various marketing issues such as differences in consumption behaviour, differences in levels of consumer responses to advertising, management practices in various cultural settings and so forth. </s><s n="s4.4;p1.7">This piece shall look at the most apparent arguments relating to Hofstede's 5 Cultural Dimensions framework which was used as a model in grasping the essentials of the topic. </s></p><p n="p2.7"><s n="s1.2;p2.7">To begin analysing Hofstede's framework, one must be aware that his framework aimed at systematically understanding cultural similarities and differences around the world by measuring particular cultural values<ref target="BAWE_0152b-ftnote.001"/>. </s><s n="s2.2;p2.7">This means the ratings were based on the whole population, thus the framework should not be used to measure individual cultural preferences. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0152b-ftnote.001"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Clark, Terry, Culture's Consequences: Comparing Values, Behaviours, Instititutions and Organizations Across Nations </s></p></note><p n="p3.7"><s n="s1.5;p3.7">One of the main advantages of this framework is that it is comprehensive. </s><s n="s2.5;p3.7">The research, careful and quantitative, covered a great number of questionnaires from at least 50 countries, ensuring the reliability of the final scores. </s><s n="s3.5;p3.7">Users of the framework can be confident that it is representative of a particular country's culture. </s><s n="s4.5;p3.7">Gooderham and Nordhaug (2001) believe that for comparative purposes involving many countries Hofstede's survey-based approach is highly efficient. </s><s n="s5.5;p3.7">The fact that the research was conducted within a multinational firm shows that the findings can be applied to businesses in general<ref target="BAWE_0152b-ftnote.002"/>. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0152b-ftnote.002"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Bing, John W., 'Hofstede's consequences: The impact of his work on consulting and business practices' </s></p></note><p n="p4.7"><s n="s1.3;p4.7">This framework can be used to assist firms in understanding the culture of a particular emerging country when weighing the possibilities of investing in that country. </s><s n="s2.3;p4.7">For example a high Power Distance score could mean that there is preference towards an autocratic type of management. </s><s n="s3.3;p4.7">It also means that there is greater centralisation and tall organisational pyramids within the society's culture and the firm needs to take that into account. </s></p><p n="p5.7"><s n="s1.4;p5.7">However, the scores of the countries could be argued to be of less relevance today as they were derived some 30 years ago. </s><s n="s2.4;p5.7">For example, recent studies show that Japanese and Koreans are often more individualistic and less collectivistic than Americans, which contradicts the culture scores developed by Hofstede<ref target="BAWE_0152b-ftnote.003"/>. </s><s n="s3.4;p5.7">Significant events that have happened in the last three decades such as the industrialisation of under-developed countries and globalisation of leading corporations are said to have played a major role in modifying national cultures. </s><s n="s4.4;p5.7">Another recent study by Gooderham and Nordhaug (2001) based on a sample of students at leading European business schools, shows that there could even be a decline in the importance of national culture as their findings suggested a number of significant differences between male and female students. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0152b-ftnote.003"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Yoo, Boonghee; Donthu, Naveen, Culture's Consequences: Comparing Values, Behaviours, Instititutions and Organizations Across Nations. </s></p></note><p n="p6.7"><s n="s1.5;p6.7">Hofstede's dimensions are believed to be insufficient to represent the dynamism and complexity of culture. </s><s n="s2.5;p6.7">For instance, the existence of subcultures in societies and cultural borrowings were not considered. </s><s n="s3.5;p6.7">Other important aspects of culture such as language, values and beliefs were also ignored. </s><s n="s4.5;p6.7">Many social scientists contend that there is no such thing as national culture because subcultures in a country can vary greatly in their values and beliefs<ref target="BAWE_0152b-ftnote.004"/>. </s><s n="s5.5;p6.7">Hence Hofstede's framework may only be appropriate for business analysis. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0152b-ftnote.004"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Clark, Terry, Culture's Consequences: Comparing Values, Behaviours, Instititutions and Organizations Across Nations. </s></p></note><p n="p7.7"><s n="s1.4;p7.7">Nevertheless it cannot be denied that Hofstede's framework has been immensely influential in the social sciences. </s><s n="s2.4;p7.7">His framework has been widely used and has played a massive role in providing a good starting point for further research in many fields. </s><s n="s3.4;p7.7">At the same time, I support the view that culture is something which needs to be understood from a personal point-of-view that is through active involvement. </s><s n="s4.4;p7.7">Nevertheless regarding international business, firms seeking to invest abroad must firstly be introduced to the notion of cultural differences before going any further and I feel that Hofstede's framework works well to achieve this. </s></p></div1></body><back><div1 type="bibliography"><head rend="bold">BIBLIOGRAPHY</head><p>1. Bing, John W., Hofstede's Consequences: The Impact of His Work on Consulting and Business Practices, Academy of Management Executive, 2004, Vol. 18, No.1.</p><p>2. Clark, Terry, Culture's Consequences: Comparing Values, Behaviours, Instititutions and Organizations Across Nations, Journal of Marketing; Apr 2003, Vol. 67, Issue 2.</p><p>3. Hoppe, Michael H., Introduction: Geert Hofstede's Culture's Consequences: International Differences in Work-Related Values, Academy of Management Executive, 2004, Vol. 18, No.1.</p><p>4. Triandis, Harry C., The Many Dimensions of Culture, Academy of Management Executive, 2004, Vol. 18, No.1.</p><p>5. Yoo, Boonghee; Donthu, Naveen, Culture's Consequences: Comparing Values, Behaviours, Instititutions and Organizations Across Nations, Journal of Marketing Research, Aug 2002, Vol. 39, Issue 3.</p><p>6. <hi rend="underlined"><seg type="URL" n="http://www.ebfonline.com/main_feat/in_depth/in_depth.asp?id=267"/></hi></p><p>7. <seg type="URL" n="http://www.geert-hofstede.com/"/></p></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
