<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_0153b" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Tort of negligence</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">deleted: header: student number and module name
</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">1</p><p n="date">2003-12</p><p n="module title">Introduction to Business Law</p><p n="module code">IB1100</p><p n="genre family">Problem question</p><p n="discipline">Business</p><p n="disciplinary group">SS</p><p n="grade">M</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">1252</p><p n="number of s-units">54</p><p n="number of p">7</p><p n="number of tables">0</p><p n="number of figures">0</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">0</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">0</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">23.2</p><p n="average s-units per p">7.7</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">f</p><p n="year of birth">1983</p><p n="first language">Malay</p><p n="education">OSA</p><p n="course">Business</p><p n="student ID">0153</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front/><body><div1 type="section"><p n="p1.7"><s n="s1.3;p1.7">Tort of negligence is important as it covers so many areas of our daily lives. </s><s n="s2.3;p1.7">In order to prove that a defendant is negligent, the claimant must prove three crucial elements; that the defendant owed him a duty of care, that the defendant was in breach of that duty of care and that the claimant suffered damage as a result. </s><s n="s3.3;p1.7">Duty of care is said to exist when there is proximity between the parties, the harm suffered is reasonably foreseeable and the imposition of duty must be just and reasonable. </s></p><p n="p2.7"><s n="s1.13;p2.7">In the first case, it is crucial to see whether or not Barry owes duty of care towards Albert for the advice given. </s><s n="s2.13;p2.7">With regard to proximity, parties must have been brought sufficiently into a close relationship with each other<ref target="BAWE_0153b-ftnote.001"/>. </s><s n="s3.13;p2.7">Albert was in close contact with Barry as the advice was given directly to him, face to face during the luncheon. </s><s n="s4.13;p2.7">Apart from that, it is reasonably foreseeable that the advice given by Barry is reliable. </s><s n="s5.13;p2.7">This is so because Barry is the Director of the company and is deemed to have vast knowledge about the company, making him the expert of Dunmore Limited. </s><s n="s6.13;p2.7">Based on the points above, it is likely that Barry owes duty of care towards Albert. </s><s n="s7.13;p2.7">However, it is unlikely that the duty is owed due to the circumstance in which the advice was given. </s><s n="s8.13;p2.7">The advice was communicated during lunch, which is a social occasion. </s><s n="s9.13;p2.7">In the <hi rend="italic">Hedley Byrne v Heller, 1963,</hi> it was held that specialist advice cannot reasonably be relied on when given off the cuff, or on a purely social occasion. </s><s n="s10.13;p2.7">Even if given in a business context, it may not be reasonable to rely on it if it is given without proper checks on relevant data<ref target="BAWE_0153b-ftnote.002"/>. </s><s n="s11.13;p2.7">Therefore, Albert bears the responsibility of doing his own research on any data of the company before deciding to invest and not relying purely on Barry's advice. </s><s n="s12.13;p2.7">Referring to <hi rend="italic">Caparo v Dickman (1990)</hi>, House of Lords held that the defendant must reasonably have anticipated that the advice would be acted upon without the claimant seeking further clarification or independent advice<ref target="BAWE_0153b-ftnote.003"/>. </s><s n="s13.13;p2.7">Barry's advice may be impromptu and he could have not reasonably foreseen that Albert will be following his advice. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0153b-ftnote.001"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Alix Adam, Law for Business Students, Second Edition, Pearson Education, pp140. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0153b-ftnote.002"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid, pp141. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0153b-ftnote.003"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid. </s></p></note><p n="p3.7"><s n="s1.5;p3.7">Due to the reasons above, Barry do not owe Albert duty of care. </s><s n="s2.5;p3.7">Hence, I advice Albert not to proceed with the claim. </s><s n="s3.5;p3.7">However, this case can be viewed from another angle in which Barry can be accused of negligent misrepresentation. </s><s n="s4.5;p3.7">Barry in a way had acted as a representative of the company and had enticed Albert in buying the shares. </s><s n="s5.5;p3.7">In this case, Albert could claim against the company but since the company has gone into liquidation, the claim would be dismissed. </s></p><p n="p4.7"><s n="s1.10;p4.7">In the case of Mrs. Smith and Jim, duty of care could be owed to Mrs. Smith as it is crystal clear that Mrs. Smith voluntarily went to seek for advice at the Centre and it is likely that any advice given from the Centre would be acted upon. </s><s n="s2.10;p4.7">The advice given by Jim was required for a purpose and Jim knew that his advice is communicated to Mrs. Smith and would be acted upon. </s><s n="s3.10;p4.7">Mrs. Smith then followed the advice to her detriment. </s><s n="s4.10;p4.7">Those four conditions were laid down by Lord Oliver from <hi rend="italic">Hedley Byrne v Heller (1963)</hi><ref target="BAWE_0153b-ftnote.004"/> and as the conditions are satisfied, Jim owed duty of care towards Mrs. Smith. </s><s n="s5.10;p4.7">Moreover, based on the <hi rend="italic">Esso Petroleum Co.</hi> </s><s n="s6.10;p4.7"><hi rend="italic">Ltd v Mardon (CA, 1976)</hi><ref target="BAWE_0153b-ftnote.005"/>, a duty of care is said to exist. </s><s n="s7.10;p4.7">Since Jim knew that his advice would be relied upon, he owes duty of care towards Mrs. Smith. </s><s n="s8.10;p4.7">Also, Jim is said to have voluntarily assume the responsibility of giving the advice. </s><s n="s9.10;p4.7">This is one of the criteria in determining that the defendant has been brought into close proximity with the claimant<ref target="BAWE_0153b-ftnote.006"/>. </s><s n="s10.10;p4.7">Thus, in this case, Jim was asked by the student, whom is the third party to give advice at the centre and since Jim had assumed that responsibility, he was also responsible for giving the right advice. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0153b-ftnote.004"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">(1)the advice is required for a purpose, whether particularly specified of generally described, which is made known, either actually or inferentially, to the adviser at the time when the advice is given; (2) the adviser knows, either actually or inferentially , that his advice will be communicated to the advisee, either specifically or as a member of an ascertainable class, in order that it should be used by the advisee for that purpose; (3) it is known either actually or inferentially, that the advice so communicated is likely to be acted upon by the advisee for that purpose without independent inquiry, and (4) it is so acted upon by the advisee to his detriment. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0153b-ftnote.005"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">A duty of care is said to exist whenever a businessman, in the course of his business gave information to a person who let it be known that he was seeking considered advice upon which he intended to act. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0153b-ftnote.006"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">In <hi rend="italic">White v Jones (1995, HL),</hi> it is said that when the defendant is asked by a third party to do something which affects the well-being of a claimant, who is unaware of the request, the claimant cannot realistically be said to be placing reliance on the defendant. </s></p></note><p n="p5.7"><s n="s1.9;p5.7">In proving breach of duty, it is essential to look at what other average professional academicians such as Jim would have done in this situation. </s><s n="s2.9;p5.7">As a law lecturer, whose scope of job is limited to only dispersing knowledge to students in the university, it may be possible for Jim to not keep himself up - to-date with the law. </s><s n="s3.9;p5.7">However, since he has the capacity of actually conducting the conference and the fact that he had assume responsibility at the Centre, it would be crucial that he prepared himself well in order to carry out his additional duty effectively. </s><s n="s4.9;p5.7">Hence, whether or not Mrs. Smith could make civil suit against Jim would depend upon what other average professional academicians would do. </s><s n="s5.9;p5.7">If their action would be not to keep themselves informed of the changes in law, Jim is possible to not have breached the duty. </s><s n="s6.9;p5.7">However, it is more likely that Jim has breached the duty of care and I would advise Mrs. Smith to go on with the suit. </s><s n="s7.9;p5.7">Nevertheless, the type of loss that Mrs. Smith suffers from would be uncertain. </s><s n="s8.9;p5.7">She may be suffering from financial loss, which is recoverable in which she had lost her money by not being able to claim on her insurance policy. </s><s n="s9.9;p5.7">Anyhow, the Court could also decide that she suffers from pure economic loss; she was deprived from the opportunity of getting the money back, i.e. the money is merely for her own benefit. </s></p><p n="p6.7"><s n="s1.11;p6.7">In the last case, by applying the 'neighbour test'<ref target="BAWE_0153b-ftnote.007"/>, George is said to owe duty of care towards Percy. </s><s n="s2.11;p6.7">However, the difficult part of this case is in proving breach of duty. </s><s n="s3.11;p6.7">If Percy wants to make a claim against George, he has to prove that George was driving negligently at that time. </s><s n="s4.11;p6.7">Negligent driving then can be determined by what other average reasonable driver would do on the road. </s><s n="s5.11;p6.7">George may not be in breach of that duty if the accident occurred was due to other factors such as sudden puncture of the tanker's tyre. </s><s n="s6.11;p6.7">If the breach of duty is proven, Percy would be able to recover from the cost of his spoilt crops and also claim for the proceeds which would have been made from the damaged crops and not for the loss that should be incurred due to his inability to plant and sell further field of crops<ref target="BAWE_0153b-ftnote.008"/> i.e. pure economic loss. </s><s n="s7.11;p6.7">However, the Court may also consider the argument that Percy suffered from pure economic loss as a result of property damage and it is possible for him to recover the losses. </s><s n="s8.11;p6.7">Unfortunately, other factors such as the weather factor could also be the cause to his inability to make future profit, but this would be too remote a damage. </s><s n="s9.11;p6.7">It is also important to note here that George is an employee and hence his employer could be vicariously liable for any of his negligent actions. </s><s n="s10.11;p6.7">Percy could sue George, George's employer or both if it is proven that George has acted negligently during the course of his employment, in this case, negligent in driving. </s><s n="s11.11;p6.7">Thus, it is important for Percy to firstly prove that George was negligent. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0153b-ftnote.007"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.3;pn1.1">Lord Atkin : ".... </s><s n="s2.3;pn1.1">Who then in law is my neighbour? </s><s n="s3.3;pn1.1">The answer seems to be those persons who are so closely affected y my act that I ought reasonably to have them in my contemplations as being so affected when I am directing my mind to the acts or omissions which are called into question." </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0153b-ftnote.008"><p n="pn1.1"><s rend="italic" n="s1.4;pn1.1">Spartan Steel v Alloys Ltd v Martin &amp; Co. </s><s n="s2.4;pn1.1"><hi rend="italic">1973</hi>. </s><s n="s3.4;pn1.1">Court held : The claimant could recover for the damage of the metal in the furnace for the damage of property loss and also for the loss of profit on the sale of that melt because although it was economic loss, it was caused by property loss and so it is consequential loss. </s><s n="s4.4;pn1.1">They could not, however, recover for the loss of profit caused by the power cut because these were not directly consequential upon any damage done and so are purely economic loss. </s></p></note><p n="p7.7"><s n="s1.3;p7.7">Before deciding to settle a case in the Court, it is essential that each party consider all the costs involved. </s><s n="s2.3;p7.7">The Woolf Reforms 1999 suggested that every party should opt for early settlement or settlement out of court. </s><s n="s3.3;p7.7">This saves time, money and energy. </s></p></div1></body><back/></text></TEI.2>
