<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_0155a" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Assignment 1</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">deleted: header: module name and number, assignment title, student number; footer: page numbers</note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">Evaluated as candidate compound assignment. Assigned to S3: assignment structured by questions: non-compound</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">3</p><p n="date">2006-01</p><p n="module title">Econometrics</p><p n="module code">EC226</p><p n="genre family">Problem question</p><p n="discipline">Economics</p><p n="disciplinary group">SS</p><p n="grade">D</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">3277</p><p n="number of s-units">174</p><p n="number of p">104</p><p n="number of tables">0</p><p n="number of figures">0</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">19</p><p n="number of lists">2</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">28</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">18.8</p><p n="average s-units per p">1.7</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">complex but non-compound assignment (see notesStmt for details)</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">m</p><p n="year of birth">1983</p><p n="first language">Chinese unspecified</p><p n="education">UK2.5</p><p n="course">Economics</p><p n="student ID">0155</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><docTitle><titlePart>EC 226 ECONOMETRICS I Assignment I <name type="student ID"/></titlePart></docTitle></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Introduction</head><p n="p1.104"><s n="s1.2;p1.104">The objective of this report is to formulate a model to determine the variables which affect the exam performance in the first year module Quantitative Techniques. </s><s n="s2.2;p1.104">The performance is measured by the marks students got for this module each year from 2002 to 2004. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold italic">Main features of the data</head><div2><head rend="bold">The outliers</head><p n="p2.104"><s n="s1.7;p2.104">It is notable that the minimum of QTMARK is 9, which is extremely lower than what a normal student should get. </s><s n="s2.7;p2.104">However I decided to include this figure in the dataset as the student did also get 3 As in A-levels. </s><s n="s3.7;p2.104">However, the highest value in ALEVELSA, 17, is identified as an outlier and excluded as student who took 8 subjects in A-Level would never have obtained 17 As. </s><s n="s4.7;p2.104">It is suspected that there maybe some typing error in the data provided about this student. </s><s n="s5.7;p2.104">There are also some students whose QTMARK are missing. </s><s n="s6.7;p2.104">The entire data sets for the students were deleted to avoid modelling error. </s><s n="s7.7;p2.104">I assume that the valid dataset is normally distributed with 388 observations. </s></p></div2><div2><head><hi rend="bold">Descriptive statistics</hi><ref target="BAWE_0155a-ftnote.001"/><hi rend="bold">( the variables of interest)</hi><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0155a-ftnote.001"><p n="pn1.1"> Refer to the "Descriptive Statistics for some quantitative variables" in the Appendix.</p></note></head><p n="p3.104"><s n="s1.2;p3.104">The average QTMARK is 64.9, with a standard deviation of 13.1. </s><s n="s2.2;p3.104">It is also calculated that around 98.7% of the students who attended the exam have passed the benchmark 40, which indicates the high quality of students. </s></p><p n="p4.104"><s n="s1.1;p4.104">Most of the students enrolled with this module got 3 <hi rend="bold">A</hi>s in their A-level, which demonstrates their good learning ability. </s></p><p n="p5.104"><s n="s1.1;p5.104">Attendance for lectures and classes are high, at around 80.9% and 82.4% respectively. </s></p><p n="p6.104"><s n="s1.2;p6.104">Students doing this module spent £27.0 on alcohol averagely. </s><s n="s2.2;p6.104">About 6.5% of the students spent more than £70 on alcohol weekly. </s></p><p n="p7.104"><s n="s1.2;p7.104">The average amount of hours students spent working on this module every week is 3.6. </s><s n="s2.2;p7.104">The most hard-working student spent 30 hours per week, while some none at all. </s></p><p n="p8.104"><s n="s1.1;p8.104">Students doing this module attended TopB for 37.7 times on average in their first year. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">Comparisons of data across various groups</head><p n="p9.104"><s n="s1.1;p9.104"><hi rend="bold">Pure Economics degree vs. non pure Economics degree:</hi> Students doing pure Economics degree scored 66.23 on average, while students doing a mixed-Economics degree scored 61.68. (very significant) </s></p><p n="p10.104"><s rend="bold" n="s1.2;p10.104">Female vs. </s><s n="s2.2;p10.104"><hi rend="bold">Male:</hi> The average female students got 63.8, compared to 65.4 for male students. </s></p><p n="p11.104"><s n="s1.1;p11.104"><hi rend="bold">UK students vs. non-UK students:</hi> On average, UK students gained 64.63 while non-UK students gained 66.38. </s></p><p n="p12.104"><s n="s1.1;p12.104"><hi rend="bold">Number of parents who attended university:</hi> Those students whose parents never attended university achieved 64.12 on average, those with one parent attended university achieved 64.99 averagely, and those with both parents attended university achieved 65.59 on average. </s></p><p n="p13.104"><s rend="bold" n="s1.3;p13.104">Students with at least one parent works in economics or maths or science field vs. </s><s n="s2.3;p13.104"><hi rend="bold">Students with parents working in other fields:</hi> Students whose parents both working in economics or maths field achieved 80 on average, but there are only two of them. </s><s n="s3.3;p13.104">Students with one parent working in this field got 65.64, compared to those whose parents working on other areas getting 63.85. </s></p><p n="p14.104"><s rend="bold" n="s1.2;p14.104">Students who had A-level Mathematics or Statistics vs. </s><s n="s2.2;p14.104"><hi rend="bold">Students who did not:</hi> Students who passed A-level Mathematics or Statistics got 65.97 on average while students who did not have it got 59.88 averagely. (very significant) </s></p><p n="p15.104"><s rend="bold" n="s1.3;p15.104">Students who got As in A-level Mathematics vs. </s><s n="s2.3;p15.104"><hi rend="bold">Students who did not:</hi> Students who got As in A-level Mathematics scored 67.00 averagely, while others scored 61.75. </s><s n="s3.3;p15.104">The gap between these two groups demonstrates that students, who are good at Mathematics or Statistics, generally could get a higher mark on this module. (very significant) </s></p><p n="p16.104"><s n="s1.1;p16.104"><hi rend="bold">School fee vs. non school fee:</hi> Students who went to fee-paying school obtained 63.99 on average, while students who went to other schools got 65.73. </s></p><p n="p17.104"><s n="s1.1;p17.104"><hi rend="bold">Students from mixed-school vs. otherwise</hi>: Students from mixed school scored 65.12 while others scored 64.99. </s></p><p n="p18.104"><s rend="bold" n="s1.4;p18.104">Year 2002 vs. </s><s rend="bold" n="s2.4;p18.104">Year 2003 vs. </s><s n="s3.4;p18.104"><hi rend="bold">Year 2004:</hi> The average mark for 2002, 2003 and 2004 students are 63.96, 61.70 and 69.19 respectively. </s><s n="s4.4;p18.104">Students in 2004 did better than Year 2002 and 2003. </s></p><p n="p19.104"><s rend="bold" n="s1.1;p19.104">These qualitative variables would have some impacts on the QTMARK, but whether they are statistically significant will be investigated later. </s></p></div2><div2><head><hi rend="bold">Correlation matrices</hi> <ref target="BAWE_0155a-ftnote.002"/><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0155a-ftnote.002"><p n="pn1.1"> Refer to "Correlation matrices for those quantitative variables" in the Appendix.</p></note></head><p rend="bulleted" n="p20.104"><s n="s1.1;p20.104">It is found that QTMARK has strong POSITIVE relationships with variables ABILITY, ALEVELSA, ATTC, ATTL and strong <hi rend="bold">NEGATIVE</hi> relationships with variables EXPALC and TOPB. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p21.104"><s n="s1.2;p21.104">The correlations between ATTC, ATTL and ATTR are very high. </s><s n="s2.2;p21.104">Therefore, <hi rend="bold">multi-collinearity</hi> is an issue needed to think about later on. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p22.104"><s n="s1.2;p22.104">EXPALC has strong <hi rend="bold">negative</hi> relationships with ATTC, ATTR and ATTL and strong <hi rend="bold">positive</hi> relationships with TOPB. It could be explained that students who got drunk can not get up easily to attend the lectures and classes. </s><s n="s2.2;p22.104">The more TOPB they attended, the more money they spent on alcohol. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p23.104"><s n="s1.2;p23.104">Generally, HRSQT has strong <hi rend="bold">positive</hi> relationship with ALEVELS and ALEVELSA, while strong <hi rend="bold">negative</hi> relationship with ABILITY and TOPB. This could be explained that the more TopB students went for, the fewer hours they spent on studying and the higher ability a student has the less hour of study is required for him/her. </s><s n="s2.2;p23.104">On the other hand, students having a good A-level record maintained their hard working attitude. </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold italic">Bivariate Regression and Multivariate Regression</head><div2><head rend="bold"> (a) Bivariate Regression </head><p n="p24.104"><s n="s1.1;p24.104"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0155a-form.001"/> </s></p><p n="p25.104"><s n="s1.1;p25.104">The following results are obtained after running the bivariate regressions in EViews<ref target="BAWE_0155a-ftnote.003"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0155a-ftnote.003"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Refer to the Appendix for the Bivariate regression results tables. </s></p></note><p n="p26.104"><s n="s1.1;p26.104"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0155a-form.002"/> </s></p><div3><head rend="bold">Interpretation for the regression results:</head><p rend="bulleted" n="p27.104"><s n="s1.1;p27.104">The intercept 64.97 means that even students did not attend any revision lecture, they could get 64.97 in the exam, which may not make much economic sense as revision lectures are designed to boost a student's exam marks. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p28.104"><s n="s1.4;p28.104">Slope coefficient of -0.0022 shows an inverse relationship between the attendance of revision lecture and exams performance. </s><s n="s2.4;p28.104">It means that 1% increase in the proportion of revision lecture attendance would decrease students' mark by 0.0022 in the exam. </s><s n="s3.4;p28.104">Economic interpretation of this could be that students who attended revision lectures would spend more time revising topics mentioned in the revision lecture and ignoring other topics. </s><s n="s4.4;p28.104">However as the coefficient is small, we could nearly omit its effect. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p29.104"><s n="s1.1;p29.104"><hi rend="bold">R-squared</hi> value of about 0.000047 means that only 0.0047% of the variation in QTMARK is explained by ATTR. Therefore it could be concluded that ATTR has such a trivial effect on exam performance that <hi rend="bold">it could even be omitted.</hi> </s></p><p n="p30.104"><s rend="bold" n="s1.1;p30.104">Two-tailed t-test for the significance of the slope ¹ </s></p><p n="p31.104"><s rend="bold italic" n="s1.1;p31.104">H0: ¹= 0 (Proportion of revision lecture attended does not affect exam performance) </s></p><p n="p32.104"><s rend="bold italic" n="s1.1;p32.104">H1: ¹≠ 0 (Proportion of revision lecture attended does affect exam performance) </s></p><p n="p33.104"><s n="s1.1;p33.104">Since the calculated t-value -0.13 is lower than the critical value of t-test at 5% significance level with 370 d.o.f, we fail to reject H0 in this case and the conclusion is that <hi rend="bold">revision lecture attendance does not affect exam performance.</hi> </s></p></div3></div2><div2><head rend="bold"> (b) Multivariate Regression</head><p n="p34.104"><s n="s1.1;p34.104"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0155a-form.003"/> </s></p><p n="p35.104"><s n="s1.1;p35.104">Modelling by OLS<ref target="BAWE_0155a-ftnote.004"/>, we get: </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0155a-ftnote.004"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Refer to the Appendix to find out the Multivariate regression results table. </s></p></note><p n="p36.104"><s n="s1.1;p36.104"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0155a-form.004"/> </s></p><div3><head rend="bold">Interpretation of the regression results:</head><p rend="bulleted" n="p37.104"><s n="s1.3;p37.104">The intercept means that even for students who did not go to any revision lecture, did not spend any time working on statistics during the year and had 0 on ability, they could get 36.83 in the exam. </s><s n="s2.3;p37.104">This makes sense as students are meant to fail if they fail to have the capability, attend lectures and study. </s><s n="s3.3;p37.104">However, it is surprising that the mark is only a marginal fail which can possibly be explained by the <hi rend="bold">absence of other variables such as attendances of lecture and class in the model as explanatory variables</hi>. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p38.104"><s n="s1.1;p38.104">If the students increase their attendance to revision lectures, ability and hours of studying by 1%, they could score 0.106, 0.850 and 0.418 extra marks respectively in the exam. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p39.104"><s n="s1.2;p39.104">R-squared value increased significantly to 0.222, which means that 22.2% of the variation in QTMARK is explained by the joint effect of ATTR, ABILITY AND HRSQT. Therefore, <hi rend="bold">there must be more factors that affect students' exam performance.</hi> </s><s n="s2.2;p39.104">This is consistent with my first finding and is a valuable point to investigate at a later stage. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p40.104"><s n="s1.2;p40.104">The coefficient of ATTR increased significantly from -0.0022 to 0.11 as ABILITY and HRSQT are included forming a model with more explanatory power as explained previously. </s><s n="s2.2;p40.104"><hi rend="bold">This result is now consistent with the findings of correlations in the first question, that QTMARK and ATTR have a positive correlation</hi><ref target="BAWE_0155a-ftnote.005"/>. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0155a-ftnote.005"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Refer to the Correlation matrices for Q1. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">The correlation between QTMARK and ATTR is 0.0249. </s></p></note></div3><div3><head rend="bold">F-test for overall significance of the regression</head><p n="p41.104"><s rend="bold italic" n="s1.1;p41.104">H0: = = =0 (attendance to revision lectures, hours of study and student's ability do not have impact on exam performance) </s></p><p n="p42.104"><s rend="bold italic" n="s1.1;p42.104">H1: i ≠0 (i= 1 or 2 or 3) (these three variables do matter.) </s></p><p n="p43.104"><s n="s1.1;p43.104"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0155a-form.005"/> </s></p><p n="p44.104"><s n="s1.2;p44.104">The calculated F-test value 32.62 is higher than the critical value with the same d.o.f at 5% significance level. </s><s n="s2.2;p44.104">So we reject <hi rend="bold italic">H0</hi> and conclude that: <hi rend="bold">revision lecture attendance, student's ability and hours of working <hi rend="italic">jointly</hi> have a <hi rend="italic">significant impact</hi> on exam performance.</hi> </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p45.104"><s n="s1.1;p45.104"><hi rend="bold">t-test for the significance of the slope coefficient ¹ of ATTR</hi><ref target="BAWE_0155a-ftnote.006"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0155a-ftnote.006"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Refer to the Appendix to find out t-test values for individual coefficient in the Multivariate regression. </s></p></note><p n="p46.104"><s rend="bold italic" n="s1.1;p46.104">H0: ¹= 0 (Proportion of revision lecture attended does not affect exam performance) </s></p><p n="p47.104"><s rend="bold italic" n="s1.1;p47.104">H1: ¹≠ 0 (Proportion of revision lecture attended does affect exam performance) </s></p><p n="p48.104"><s n="s1.2;p48.104">As t-test value of 5.36 is higher than the critical value with the same d.o.f. at 5% significance level, I reject H0 and conclude that <hi rend="bold">revision lecture attendance affects exam performance.</hi> </s><s n="s2.2;p48.104"><hi rend="bold">Hence</hi> <hi rend="bold">ATTR should be included as the explanatory variables for the exam performance</hi>. </s></p></div3></div2><div2><head rend="bold">(c) Defining dummy variables </head><p n="p49.104"><s n="s1.1;p49.104"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0155a-form.006"/> </s></p><list type="simple"><item>D1=1 if the student spent at most 1 hours per week on studying statistics and 0 otherwise</item><item>D3=1 if the student spent 1 - 3 hours per week on studying statistics and 0 otherwise</item><item>D10=1 if the student spent 3 - 10 hours per week on studying statistics and 0 otherwise</item><item>D20=1 if the student spent 10 - 20 hours per week on studying statistics and 0 otherwise</item><item>D30=1 if the student spent 20 - 30 hours per week on studying statistics and 0 otherwise</item></list><p n="p50.104"><s n="s1.1;p50.104">Modelling by OLS<ref target="BAWE_0155a-ftnote.007"/>: <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0155a-form.007"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0155a-ftnote.007"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Refer to the Appendix to find out the regression results table. </s></p></note><div3><head rend="bold">Interpretation of the regression results:</head><p rend="bulleted" n="p51.104"><s n="s1.1;p51.104">The effect of HRSQT on QTMARK is very different for different sub-group of HRSQT. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p52.104"><s n="s1.4;p52.104">Students with studying hour between 1-3 achieved 1.24 marks less than average whereas those who study for less than 1 hour per week would achieve 0.49 less in the exam. </s><s n="s2.4;p52.104">This can be possibly explained that it acquires considerable amount of time for one to grasp the subject. </s><s n="s3.4;p52.104">Hence, until that amount of time is spent, more study could cause the student more confusion, i.e. reduction in mark. </s><s n="s4.4;p52.104">It appears that there is nonlinearity. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p53.104"><s n="s1.3;p53.104">On the other hand, students who study between 3-10 hours a week would achieve 2.73 marks higher in exam. </s><s n="s2.3;p53.104">This figure continues to increase as the hour of study increases. </s><s n="s3.3;p53.104">This is explained by the fact that the more a student put in the subject the bigger the marginal effect is, as he/she would find it easier to explore in depth of the subject. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p54.104"><s n="s1.2;p54.104">The effect of HRSQT on QTMARK hence appears not to be a linear relationship. </s><s n="s2.2;p54.104">However as t-values are not significant at 5% level, it can not be concluded that students with less than 1 studying hour achieve better marks than student with 1-3 studying hours. </s></p></div3><div3><head rend="bold">Interpretation of the regression coefficients:</head><p n="p55.104"><s n="s1.1;p55.104">Holding others constant, if the student got one extra A in his/her A-level study, he/she would get 1.53 extra marks in the exam; if the student went for 1% extra more classes, he/she would get 0.16 extra mark; and if the student has 1% more ability, he/she would get 0.56 extra mark. </s></p><p n="p56.104"><s n="s1.2;p56.104">The coefficients for the dummy variables mean that Year 2002 and 2003 students on average scored 5.20 and 7.20 lower than the marks of Year 2004 students <hi rend="bold">.</hi> </s><s rend="bold" n="s2.2;p56.104">It might be explained by a possible change of admission requirement in 2004 or simply easier exam paper in 2004. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p57.104"><s rend="bold" n="s1.1;p57.104">F-test for the joint explanatory power of the dummy variables as a group </s></p><p n="p58.104"><s rend="bold" n="s1.1;p58.104"><hi rend="italic">H0:</hi> D02 = D03 = 0 </s></p><p n="p59.104"><s rend="bold" n="s1.1;p59.104"><hi rend="italic">H1:</hi> Di ≠ 0 ( i= 02 or 03) at least one of the is different from 0. </s></p><p n="p60.104"><s n="s1.1;p60.104">We have to regress QTMARK on ATTL and ALEVELSA to get RSS <hi rend="sup">R</hi>. </s></p><p n="p61.104"><s n="s1.1;p61.104"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0155a-form.009"/> </s></p><p n="p62.104"><s n="s1.2;p62.104">F (2, 356)<ref target="BAWE_0155a-ftnote.008"/> = 11.18, higher than the critical value of same d.o.f at 5% significance level. </s><s n="s2.2;p62.104">So we reject <hi rend="bold italic">H0 </hi>here and conclude that <hi rend="bold">there are some differences in the performance between the 2004 students and previous years' students.</hi> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0155a-ftnote.008"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Refer to Appendix to find out the calculation of F-test. </s></p></note></div3><div3><head rend="bold">t-test for individual dummy variable</head><p n="p63.104"><s n="s1.3;p63.104">The t-test values for D02 and D03 are -3.79 and -4.39, which indicates that at 1% of significance level, we reject null-hypothesis D02=0 and D03=0. </s><s n="s2.3;p63.104"><hi rend="bold">We conclude that the difference in performance between 2004 and previous years' students is caused by both students enrolled in 2002 and 2003,</hi> with similar reasons as above. </s><s n="s3.3;p63.104">Other factors could be as such that lecturer for this module in 2004 got better lecturing skills or the exam paper were more difficult in 2002 and 2003 than it was in 2004. </s></p></div3><div3><head rend="bold">Chow test for coefficient constancy across the three sub-samples</head><p n="p64.104"><s rend="bold" n="s1.1;p64.104"><hi rend="italic">H0: </hi> = == === == </s></p><p n="p65.104"><s rend="bold" n="s1.1;p65.104"><hi rend="italic">H1:</hi> not all the coefficients in the sub-samples are constant. </s></p><p n="p66.104"><s n="s1.3;p66.104">F-test<ref target="BAWE_0155a-ftnote.010"/> value is 4.25, higher than the critical value with the same d.o.f. at 1% significance level. </s><s n="s2.3;p66.104">So we reject <hi rend="bold italic">H0</hi>. </s><s n="s3.3;p66.104"><hi rend="bold">The conclusion is that the coefficients vary across the three sub-samples</hi>. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0155a-ftnote.010"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Refer to the Appendix to find out the detail for the F-test. </s></p></note></div3></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold italic">Test for exam performance between the 2004 students and previous years' students. </head><p n="p67.104"><s n="s1.1;p67.104">Set the sub-sample of 2004 students as the reference category and define 2 dummy variables D02 and D03. </s></p><list type="simple"><item>D02 = 1 if the student is in the 2002 students sub-sample</item><item>D02 = 0 if the student is not in the 2002 students sub-sample</item><item>D03 = 1 if the student is in the 2003 students sub-sample</item><item>D03 = 0 if the student is not in the 2003 students sub-sample</item></list><p n="p68.104"><s n="s1.1;p68.104">The regression model now is: </s></p><p n="p69.104"><s n="s1.1;p69.104"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0155a-form.008"/> </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold italic">Separate regression for 2002, 2003 and 2004 exam performance</head><p n="p70.104"><s n="s1.1;p70.104">Regression models for performances of year 2002, 2003 and 2004 students respectively: </s></p><p n="p71.104"><s n="s1.1;p71.104"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0155a-form.010"/> </s></p><p n="p72.104"><s n="s1.1;p72.104"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0155a-form.011"/> </s></p><p n="p73.104"><s n="s1.1;p73.104"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0155a-form.012"/> </s></p><p n="p74.104"><s n="s1.1;p74.104">Using OLS, we get<ref target="BAWE_0155a-ftnote.009"/>: </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0155a-ftnote.009"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Refer to the Appendix to find out the regression results tables. </s></p></note><p n="p75.104"><s n="s1.1;p75.104"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0155a-form.013"/> </s></p><p n="p76.104"><s n="s1.1;p76.104"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0155a-form.014"/> </s></p><p n="p77.104"><s n="s1.1;p77.104"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0155a-form.015"/> </s></p><p n="p78.104"><s rend="bold" n="s1.1;p78.104">Comparison of the three regression equations: </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p79.104"><s n="s1.2;p79.104">The intercept in 2004, 41.71, is much higher than any other year, which shows that even if year 2004 students do not go for lecture, they could obtain an average higher mark than previous years' student. </s><s n="s2.2;p79.104">This is possibly due to the same reason as mentioned in Q3. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p80.104"><s n="s1.1;p80.104">Class attendance in 2003 could make a bigger impact on the exam performance when compared to it in 2002 and 2004 </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p81.104"><s n="s1.2;p81.104">Students' ability in 2002 could make the biggest impact on exam performance when compared with 2003 and 2004. </s><s n="s2.2;p81.104"><hi rend="bold">This is in consistence with the finding that attendance in 2002 had the least impact on exam performance among 3 years</hi>, as higher ability students often find what is done in class can also be achieved on their own, so the attendance of class had less impact on their exam performance. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p82.104"><s n="s1.3;p82.104">Number of A-grades at A-level seems to have almost five times as much impact on exam performance in 2002 and 2003 while compared to 2004. </s><s n="s2.3;p82.104">Possible reason is the same as in the first point. </s><s n="s3.3;p82.104">Other reasons can be students' qualities are similar in 2004 with same number of A-levels so one's A-level performance is less influential. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold italic">Test for slope coefficients</head><p n="p83.104"><s n="s1.1;p83.104">The restricted model is: <hi rend="bold">QTMARK = </hi> </s></p><p n="p84.104"><s n="s1.1;p84.104">The unrestricted model is: </s></p><p n="p85.104"><s n="s1.1;p85.104"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0155a-form.016"/> </s></p><p n="p86.104"><s n="s1.1;p86.104"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0155a-form.017"/> </s></p><p n="p87.104"><s n="s1.1;p87.104"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0155a-form.018"/> </s></p><p n="p88.104"><s rend="bold" n="s1.1;p88.104"><hi rend="italic">H0:</hi>====== </s></p><p n="p89.104"><s rend="bold" n="s1.1;p89.104"><hi rend="italic">H1:</hi> Not all the slope coefficients in the sub-samples are constant </s></p><p n="p90.104"><s n="s1.2;p90.104">F-test value<ref target="BAWE_0155a-ftnote.011"/> is 1.91, higher than the critical value at 10% but lower than it at 1%. </s><s n="s2.2;p90.104">Therefore, we fail to reject <hi rend="bold italic">H0 </hi>at 1% significance level and conclude that <hi rend="bold">the slope coefficients are constant in the sub-samples</hi>. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0155a-ftnote.011"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Refer to the Appendix to find out the detail for the F-test. </s></p></note></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold italic">Model Estimation</head><p n="p91.104"><s n="s1.1;p91.104">The steps to formulate the model are: </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p92.104"><s n="s1.1;p92.104">Using correlation matrix<ref target="BAWE_0155a-ftnote.012"/> to pick up the quantitative variables which have high correlations with QTMARK. They are ABILITY(0.30), ALEVELSA(0.13), ATTC(0.30), ATTL (0.40), EXPALC (-0.31) and TOPB (-0.29). </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0155a-ftnote.012"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Refer to Appendix to find out Correlation Matrix under Q1 </s></p></note><p n="p93.104"><ref target="BAWE_0155a-ftnote.013"/><s n="s1.4;p93.104">Using two-tailed t-test<ref target="BAWE_0155a-ftnote.014"/>, coefficients for ABILITY, ALEVELSA, ATTTC and EXPALC are statistically significant. </s><s n="s2.4;p93.104">Due to <hi rend="bold">multi-collinearity</hi> between ATTL and ATTC mentioned in Q1, the standard error of ATTL has increased, thus its t-statistic is not significant. </s><s n="s3.4;p93.104">Therefore, I decided to remain only one of them instead of two. </s><s n="s4.4;p93.104">With a t-value of 0.35 and 0.70 respectively, TOPB and ATTL are dropped. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0155a-ftnote.013"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Refer to the Appendix to find out the statistic table for the regression. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0155a-ftnote.014"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">The reason for us to use one-tailed test is that in Q1, we have found that they are both negatively correlated, so basically, we could exclude the possibility that they are positively correlated with QTMARK. </s></p></note><p rend="bulleted" n="p94.104"><s n="s1.4;p94.104">Next, considering all the answers to previous questions, I decided to include the variable ATTR even though it did not show a significant correlation with QTMARK in our correlation matrix. </s><s n="s2.4;p94.104">Its significance on QTMARK is already tested in Q2b). </s><s n="s3.4;p94.104">Moreover as seen also in Q2b), variable HRSQT have significant coefficient and outstanding t-statistics. </s><s n="s4.4;p94.104">Hence both variables are included. </s></p><p n="p95.104"><ref target="BAWE_0155a-ftnote.015"/><s n="s1.2;p95.104">From the regression, I could see that ATTR and HRSQT both have an outstanding t-value of 3.12, 1.70 respectively. </s><s n="s2.2;p95.104">Furthermore, the R-squared value has increase from 0.255 to 0.273 which means the new model could explain more variation in QTMARK. This further confirmed the inclusion of these two variables as explanatory variables in the model. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0155a-ftnote.015"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Refer to the Appendix to find out the statistic table for the regression. </s></p></note><p rend="bulleted" n="p96.104"><s n="s1.2;p96.104">Based on the conclusion I have got from Q4 and Q5, I <hi rend="bold">deduced that intercepts should be allowed to vary for different sub-groups</hi>, but their slope coefficients are constant. </s><s n="s2.2;p96.104">Therefore, I need to add dummy variables D02 and D03 to the final model. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p97.104"><s n="s1.1;p97.104">Based on my comparison in Q1 between different groups<ref target="BAWE_0155a-ftnote.016"/>, we add another three dummy variables, DCOURSE, DMPASS and DMATHA<ref target="BAWE_0155a-ftnote.017"/>, all of which presented a significant impact on QTMARK in my initial analysis on the data. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0155a-ftnote.016"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Refer to the Appendix to find out the Comparison between different sub-groups. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0155a-ftnote.017"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Refer to the Appendix to find out the statistic table for the regression. </s></p></note><p n="p98.104"><s n="s1.5;p98.104">From the regression result<ref target="BAWE_0155a-ftnote.018"/>, using the t-tests for the coefficients of the variables, I have decided to drop variable DMATHA, as it is not statistically significant with t-value of 0.52. </s><s n="s2.5;p98.104">DMPASS will still be included as I believe <hi rend="bold">a high level of mathematics such as an A grade at A-Levels is necessary in order for a student to perform well in QT, but student must pass A-Level mathematics to obtain the basic quantitative skills</hi>. </s><s n="s3.5;p98.104">This is consistent with my finding in Q1, that s <hi rend="bold">tudents who had A-level Mathematics or Statistics achieved on average 6 marks higher</hi> than students who did not. </s><s n="s4.5;p98.104">Moreover, the coefficient of DMPASS is 1.57, among the highest coefficients. </s><s n="s5.5;p98.104">In addition, Due to collinearity between DMAPSS and DMATHA, I also expect the coefficient of DMAPSS to increase as I drop DMATHA. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0155a-ftnote.018"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Refer to the Appendix to find out the statistic table for the regression. </s></p></note><p rend="bulleted" n="p99.104"><s n="s1.2;p99.104">Regress QTMARK on the selected variables now<ref target="BAWE_0155a-ftnote.019"/>. </s><s n="s2.2;p99.104">I am now satisfied with the variables I have considered for the model: ABILITY, ALEVELSA, ATTC, EXPALC, ATTR, HRSQT, D02, D03, DCOURSE and DMPASS. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0155a-ftnote.019"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Refer to the Appendix to find out the statistic table for the regression. </s></p></note><p n="p100.104"><s n="s1.2;p100.104">The <hi rend="bold">R-squared</hi> valued now stands at <hi rend="bold">0.3462</hi>, which is my best figure so far. </s><s n="s2.2;p100.104">The coefficient of DMAPSS also increases, as expected, from 1.57 to 2.12. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p101.104"><s n="s1.3;p101.104">I think we may better specify the model by considering these variables but in different functional forms. </s><s n="s2.3;p101.104">I begin with taking the logs of all the quantitative variables (not dummy variables)<ref target="BAWE_0155a-ftnote.020"/>. </s><s n="s3.3;p101.104">R-square has decreased from 0.3462 to 0.2739, which means log function of quantitative variables could not explain more variations in QTMARK. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0155a-ftnote.020"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Refer to the Appendix to find out the statistic table for the regression. </s></p></note><p rend="bulleted" n="p102.104"><s n="s1.4;p102.104">Now I try two different functional forms, one is squaring all the quantitative variables; the other one is taking the square-root of all the quantitative variables. </s><s n="s2.4;p102.104">In both cases, R-square decreases. </s><s n="s3.4;p102.104">Hence, given the trial and error effort, I am concluding to the best of my ability, that the optimal function should be of a linear form. </s><s n="s4.4;p102.104">My best effort has resulted in the following model specification: </s></p><p n="p103.104"><s n="s1.1;p103.104"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0155a-form.019"/> </s></p><div2><head rend="bold italic">Comments on the model:</head><p n="p104.104"><s n="s1.4;p104.104">The F-test value of this model<ref target="BAWE_0155a-ftnote.021"/> is 14.34, highly significant, which demonstrated the overall significant explanatory power. </s><s n="s2.4;p104.104">Except DMPASS, all the other coefficients are statistically significant (t-test). </s><s n="s3.4;p104.104">Interactive dummy variables are not added as slope coefficients are constant based on Q5. </s><s n="s4.4;p104.104">The low R-square means that other factors affect the exam performance as well, such as interests in the subjects, a motivation factor scored by tutor and researching skills (e.g. understanding of the use of software and library resources). </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0155a-ftnote.021"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Refer to the Appendix to find out the detail for the F-test. </s></p></note></div2></div1></body><back/></text></TEI.2>
