<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_0155b" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>SWOT</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">deleted: header: module name and number, student number; footer: page numbers</note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">Evaluated as candidate compound assignment. Assigned to A3b: essay + reflection: non-compound</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">3</p><p n="date">2005-12</p><p n="module title">International Environment of Business</p><p n="module code">IB2180</p><p n="genre family">Critique</p><p n="discipline">Business</p><p n="disciplinary group">SS</p><p n="grade">M</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">713</p><p n="number of s-units">46</p><p n="number of p">37</p><p n="number of tables">1</p><p n="number of figures">0</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">0</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">28</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">15.5</p><p n="average s-units per p">1.2</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">complex but non-compound assignment (see notesStmt for details)</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">m</p><p n="year of birth">1983</p><p n="first language">Chinese unspecified</p><p n="education">UK2.5</p><p n="course">Accounting and Finance</p><p n="student ID">0155</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><docTitle><titlePart rend="bold italic">Matching Resources to Context</titlePart></docTitle></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="section"><p rend="bulleted" n="p1.37"><s n="s1.1;p1.37">Strategy as a response to external <hi rend="bold italic">Opportunities</hi> and <hi rend="bold italic">Threats </hi>and to internal <hi rend="bold italic">Strengths </hi>and <hi rend="bold italic">Weaknesses </hi>as a means of achieving competitive advantage (de Wit&amp;Meyer, 1998) </s></p><p n="p2.37"><s n="s1.1;p2.37">This view of strategy is what underlies <hi rend="bold">SWOT</hi> analysis as a modern analytical approach used to support the search for a favorable competitive position. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p3.37"><s n="s1.2;p3.37">It is the simplest form of presentation that is of practical value for describing a business and its environment. </s><s n="s2.2;p3.37">(Houlden, 1996) </s></p><table id="BAWE_0155b-tab.001"><row><cell/></row></table><p rend="ordered" n="p4.37"><s rend="bold" n="s1.2;p4.37">I. </s><s n="s2.2;p4.37">Real opportunity - the strengths enable it to pursue opportunities successfully. </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p5.37"><s rend="bold" n="s1.2;p5.37">II. </s><s n="s2.2;p5.37">If the weaknesses significantly lower its performance, decision-maker must consider actions to overcome the weakness. </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p6.37"><s rend="bold" n="s1.2;p6.37">III. </s><s n="s2.2;p6.37">Real threat - it is not equipped to deal with the threat. </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p7.37"><s rend="bold" n="s1.2;p7.37">IV. </s><s n="s2.2;p7.37">Strength can help overcome such threat. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold italic">Some Limitations of SWOT</head><p rend="bulleted" n="p8.37"><s n="s1.1;p8.37"><hi rend="bold">No weightings</hi> of factors </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p9.37"><s n="s1.1;p9.37">Difficult to determine which factors are the most important at the present time/ the most relevant for the firm? </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p10.37"><s n="s1.1;p10.37"><hi rend="bold">Arbitrary classification</hi> on factors as weakness/threat or strength/opportunity </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p11.37"><s n="s1.1;p11.37">Iraq opening oil sector: <hi rend="italic">threat</hi> - potential expansion of supplies, rising oil price </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p12.37"><s n="s1.1;p12.37"><hi rend="italic">opportunity</hi> - profitable investment for giants such as Exxon </s></p><p n="p13.37"><s n="s1.1;p13.37"><hi rend="bold">More important</hi> is to have a careful identification of these external and internal factors followed by an <hi rend="bold">appraisal</hi> of their <hi rend="bold">implications</hi> (Grant, 2005) </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p14.37"><s n="s1.1;p14.37">Strength versus <hi rend="bold">distinctive competence</hi> </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p15.37"><s n="s1.1;p15.37">Strong capacity of a firm is not necessarily the unique competence <hi rend="bold">in comparison to rivals</hi>. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p16.37"><s n="s1.1;p16.37"><hi rend="bold">Static</hi> and <hi rend="bold"> not forward looking</hi> </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p17.37"><s n="s1.1;p17.37">Can only be done once, no point of review </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p18.37"><s rend="bold" n="s1.1;p18.37">Over-Simplification </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p19.37"><s n="s1.1;p19.37">Not good at dealing with a complex and often paradoxical world (Broklesby&amp;Cummings) - <hi rend="bold">Icarus Paradox</hi> - strengths potentially being weakness. </s></p><p n="p20.37"><s rend="underlined italic" n="s1.1;p20.37">However, while SWOT is more appropriate for smaller businesses, its nature also leads to its wide application, from project to nation, where a relatively quick analysis is needed </s></p><p n="p21.37"><s n="s1.1;p21.37">. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p22.37"><s n="s1.1;p22.37">Absence of <hi rend="bold">ethical aspect</hi> and <hi rend="bold">personal motive</hi> in strategic planning </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p23.37"><s n="s1.2;p23.37">- Certain industries such as mining must consider the degree of risk the society might entail. </s><s n="s2.2;p23.37">They may be examined against the standards of responsiveness to the expectations of society the strategist elects. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p24.37"><s n="s1.1;p24.37">- What the executives <hi rend="italic">want to do</hi> also forms an element of strategic decision. </s></p><p n="p25.37"><s rend="italic" n="s1.1;p25.37">Of all the components of strategic choice, the combination of resources and competence is most crucial to success. (de Wit&amp;Meyer, 1998) </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p26.37"><s n="s1.1;p26.37">Provides <hi rend="bold">little guidance to managers</hi> </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p27.37"><s n="s1.1;p27.37">Planners are left without indication as to where to <hi rend="bold">search</hi> for such variables, or what to do after finding them in terms of how best to <hi rend="bold">incorporate</hi> them in strategy formulation. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p28.37"><s n="s1.2;p28.37">SWOT remains rooted in <hi rend="bold">vagueness</hi>, relies on an <hi rend="bold">over-simplified process</hi>. </s><s n="s2.2;p28.37">(Panagiotou, 2003) </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p29.37"><s n="s1.1;p29.37">It is an <hi rend="bold">atheoretical framework</hi>, of limited prescriptive power for practice and minor significance for research (Dess, 1999) </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold italic">SWOT from More Angles, More Customization</head><p rend="bulleted" n="p30.37"><s n="s1.2;p30.37">Duncan, Ginter&amp;Swayne (1998) suggested a four step model for assessing internal strengths and weaknesses<ref target="BAWE_0155b-ftnote.001"/>. </s><s n="s2.2;p30.37">After initial survey of both strengths and weaknesses, the focus turned to <hi rend="bold">resources and capabilities</hi> that can be used to <hi rend="bold">build</hi> a potential competitive advantage. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0155b-ftnote.001"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Their four steps include surveying, categorising, investigation, and evaluating. </s></p></note><p rend="bulleted" n="p31.37"><s n="s1.1;p31.37">SWOT's <hi rend="bold">focus on the strengths</hi> rather than the weaknesses when evaluating a firm's internal capabilities is also used by Barney (1995) in his VRIO<ref target="BAWE_0155b-ftnote.002"/> model. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0155b-ftnote.002"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">In this model, a firm would assess their capabilities based on their value(V), rareness(R), imitability(I), and organisation(O). </s></p></note><p rend="bulleted" n="p32.37"><s n="s1.1;p32.37">SWOT serves as a stepping stone towards the implementation of the Balance Score Card and Strategy Formulation<ref target="BAWE_0155b-ftnote.003"/> (Lee&amp;Ko). </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0155b-ftnote.003"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">SWOT is implemented to develop the key performance indicators (KPI) with four main perspectives of BSC. </s></p></note><p rend="bulleted" n="p33.37"><s n="s1.1;p33.37">Combination of SWOT and Maxwell's six dimensions of quality (Storr&amp;Hurst) </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold italic">Learning Process</head><p n="p34.37"><s n="s1.2;p34.37">I have briefly learnt the framework before but was initially not confident if there would be enough to say about this simple model due to its limited content in both lecture handout and seminar presentation. </s><s n="s2.2;p34.37">However, by <hi rend="bold">discussing</hi> with people with more subject knowledge and <hi rend="bold">learning independently</hi>, especially via <hi rend="bold">e-resources</hi>, I have realized there are much more insights to explore. </s></p><p n="p35.37"><s n="s1.1;p35.37">During the research of this assignment, one of the questions that I have found intriguing is that <hi rend="italic">whether</hi> strategic analyses such as SWOT a <hi rend="bold">creative interpretation</hi> of a problem situation (de Wit&amp;Meyer, 1998), whose evaluation depends on the <hi rend="bold"> idiosyncratic</hi> views held by strategists <hi rend="italic">or</hi> a <hi rend="bold"> logical analysis</hi> with which business managers could assess their competitive positions, hence choose the action from <hi rend="bold">a variety of options</hi> that brings the best chances of success. </s></p><p n="p36.37"><s n="s1.1;p36.37">This assignment has left me with a genuine interest in the area of international strategies and strategic thinking, which I would like to explore further. </s></p><p n="p37.37"><s n="s1.1;p37.37">I have found this form of assignment both enjoyable and intellectually stimulating and would definitely put in more time into reading relevant literatures for my next reflective piece on Governance. </s></p></div1></body><back><div1 type="bibliography"><head rend="bold italic">Bibliography</head><p>Houlden, Brian (1996) <hi rend="underlined italic">Understanding Company Strategy: An Introduction to Analysis and Implementation</hi>, Second Edition, Blackwell Publishers, UK</p><p>Grant, Robert M. (2005) <hi rend="underlined italic">Contemporary Strategy Analysis</hi>, Fifth Edition, Blackwell Publishing, UK</p><p>Bob de Wit &amp; Ron Meyer (1998) <hi rend="underlined italic">Strategy: Process, Content, Context</hi>, Second Edition, International Thomson Business Press, UK</p><p>Johnson &amp; Scholes (2002) <hi rend="underlined italic">Exploring Corporate Strategy</hi>, 6th Edition, Financial Times/Prentice Hall, UK</p><p>Stephen Cummings &amp; David Wilson (2003) <hi rend="underlined italic">Images of Strategy</hi>, Blackwell Publishing, UK</p><p>S.F. Lee, Andrew Sai On Ko <hi rend="underlined italic">Building balanced scorecard with SWOT analysis, and implementing ``Sun Tzu's The Art of Business Management Strategies'' on QFD methodology</hi>, Managerial Auditing Journal, Vol. 15, Numbers 1-2 (2000) P68-76 </p><p>William A. Drago and Cathleen A. Folker, <hi rend="underlined italic">Achilles Revisited: The Impact of Incompetencies on Firm Performance</hi>, Management Research News, Vol. 22, Number 8 (August 1999) P18 - 25</p><p>Lorna Storr and Keith Hurst <hi rend="underlined italic">Developing a quality assurance framework for in-service training and development</hi> Quantity Assurance in Education, Vol.9 Number 3 (July 25, 2001) P132 - 138</p><p>Gina Grandy and Albert J. Mills <hi rend="underlined italic">Strategy as Simulacra? A Radical Reflexive Look at</hi></p><p><hi rend="underlined italic">the Discipline and Practice of Strategy</hi>, Journal of Management Studies 41:7 November 2004 0022-2380</p><p>George Panagiotou, <hi rend="underlined italic">Bringing SWOT into focus</hi>, Business Strategy Review, 2003, Volume 14 Issue 2 pp 8-10</p><p>Milorad M. Novicevic, Michael Harvey, Chad W. Autry and Edward U. Bond III <hi rend="underlined italic">Dual-perspective SWOT: a synthes is of marketing intelligence and planning</hi>, Marketing Intelligence &amp; Planning Vol. 22 No. 1, 2004 pp. 84-94</p><p>Demetris Vrontis, Claudio Vignali <hi rend="underlined italic">Dairy Milk in France: A marketing investigation of the situational environment</hi>, British Food Journal, Vol. 103, Number 4 (2001) P291-296</p><p>Julia A. Smith<hi rend="italic"> The Behaviour and Performance of Young Micro Firms: Evidence from Businesses in Scotland</hi>, Small Business Economics, Vol.13, Number 3 (November 1999) P185 - 200</p><p>Andrew Sai On Ko, S.F. Lee<hi rend="underlined italic"> Implementing the strategic formulation framework for the banking industry of Hong Kong</hi>, Managerial Auditing Journal, Vol. 15, Number 9 (2000) P469 - 477</p><p>Dess, G.G. (1999) <hi rend="underlined italic">Creating competitive (dis)advantage: learning from Food Lion's freefall</hi> Academy of Management Executive, Vol. 13 No. 3, pp. 97-112.</p></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
