<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_0162b" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Module 2 Laboratory Report</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">appendices: data tables
</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">4</p><p n="date">2006-02</p><p n="module title">Data Acquisition I: Biophysical Techniques &amp; Instrumentation Design</p><p n="module code">MOAC2</p><p n="genre family">Methodology recount</p><p n="discipline">Biological Sciences</p><p n="disciplinary group">LS</p><p n="grade">D</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">2040</p><p n="number of s-units">88</p><p n="number of p">46</p><p n="number of tables">3</p><p n="number of figures">7</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">5</p><p n="number of lists">0</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">0</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">23.2</p><p n="average s-units per p">1.9</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">f</p><p n="year of birth">1983</p><p n="first language">Chinese unspecified</p><p n="education">OSA</p><p n="course">Mathematical Biology and Biophysical Chemistry</p><p n="student ID">0162</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><docTitle><titlePart rend="bold">Module 2 Laboratory Report</titlePart></docTitle><titlePart><name type="student name"/></titlePart></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Introduction</head><p n="p1.46"><s n="s1.2;p1.46">There are variety ways to determine protein and DNA properties for biological samples with modern techniques. </s><s n="s2.2;p1.46">This laboratory used absorbance and BCA method to determine concentration of protein solution, circular dichrosim (CD) for protein secondary structure determination, and fluorescence spectroscopy to find the DNA and ligand equilibrium binding constant. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Background</head><p n="p2.46"><s n="s1.1;p2.46">The principle behind the absorbance method is based on the relation </s></p><p n="p3.46"><s n="s1.1;p3.46"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0162b-form.001"/> </s></p><p n="p4.46"><s n="s1.1;p4.46">where <hi rend="italic">A</hi> is the absorbance of the sample solution, <hi rend="italic">Io</hi> is the intensity coming in, <hi rend="italic">I</hi> the intensity coming out, ε the extinction coefficient, c the concentration, and l the path length. </s></p><p n="p5.46"><s n="s1.2;p5.46">BCA method is based on the principle of linear relation between the absorbance and the protein solution. </s><s n="s2.2;p5.46">The unknown protein concentration is determined by comparing the absorbance value with the standard solution. </s></p><p n="p6.46"><s n="s1.2;p6.46">If the structure is not symmetric, CD spectroscopy can measure the differences in the absorbance of left-handed polarized light versus the right-hand polarized light. </s><s n="s2.2;p6.46">CD spectroscopy can be applied to determine protein secondary structure in far-UV region (190-260nm). Α-helix, β-sheet and random coil structure can give a characteristic shape of CD spectrum. </s></p><p n="p7.46"><s n="s1.3;p7.46">Fluorescence occurs when a molecule absorbs a high-energy photon, and re-emits it as a lower-energy photon with a longer wavelength. </s><s n="s2.3;p7.46">Fluorescence is more sensitive than absorbance, and it is sensitive to environment, too. </s><s n="s3.3;p7.46">Fluorescence signal is proportional to concentration of a particular fluorophore in a given environment, so it can be used to determine <hi rend="italic"> Lf+Sf=Lb</hi> equilibrium binding constant by the formula </s></p><p n="p8.46"><s n="s1.1;p8.46"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0162b-form.002"/> </s></p><p n="p9.46"><s n="s1.1;p9.46">Where <hi rend="italic">Lf</hi> represent ligand free,<hi rend="italic"> Sf</hi> site free, and <hi rend="italic">Lb</hi> ligand bind. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Methods and Materials</head><div2><head rend="bold">DNA and protein sample preparation</head><p n="p10.46"><s n="s1.1;p10.46">A DNA solution sample with approximate concentration 1400μM is made up from mixing 2.310mg calf thymus DNA, weighted by a 4-figure balance, and 4mL water measured by a 1000μL pipette. </s></p><p n="p11.46"><s n="s1.1;p11.46">The protein sample (unknown protein, referred as U) used here is myoglobin, and the protein stock (US) is made up to be around 1mg/mL. A total volume of 3.5mL protein is prepared with 3.5mg myoglobin weighted by the balance hydrating into 3.5mL distilled water. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">Estimation of protein concentration with Absorbance and BCA methods</head><div3><head>Absorbance at 280nm</head><p n="p12.46"><s n="s1.2;p12.46">A 2mL sample was made up with 1mL US and 1mL water in quartz cuvette. </s><s n="s2.2;p12.46">The absorbance is measured from 200-700nm and data are stored in a floppy disk. </s></p></div3><div3><head>BCA method</head><p n="p13.46"><s n="s1.2;p13.46">Total 8 samples are prepared to determine US concentration by measuring four absorbance at 562nm of the standard solution (BSA, bovine serum albumin) corresponding to four different concentration. </s><s n="s2.2;p13.46">The standard solution BSA is 2.00mg/mL, US approximate concentration should be 1mg/mL, and the values of US concentration to be determined are chosen as 300μg/mL and 200μg/mL. The 8 samples are prepared by mixing up the following chemicals listed in the table below: </s></p><table id="BAWE_0162b-tab.001"><head>*the mixture is made from 16.5mL BCA reagent and 228μ L 4% CuSO <hi rend="sub">4.</hi> </head><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p14.46"><s n="s1.2;p14.46">All those samples are incubated in 37۫C for 30 minutes. </s><s n="s2.2;p14.46">After the tubes cooled down to room temperature, the samples are transferred to the cuvettes and the absorbance are measured for each sample. </s></p></div3></div2><div2><head rend="bold">Protein secondary structure determination by circular dichroism</head><p n="p15.46"><s n="s1.2;p15.46">0.1mg/mL solution of US is put into a 1mm quarz cuvette and CD spectrum is collected from 260-190nm. </s><s n="s2.2;p15.46">After the measurement, the cuvette is washed with water for 3 times and acetone 3 times, and dried with a nitrogen line. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">Equilibrium binding constant determination by fluorescence spectroscopy</head><p n="p16.46"><s n="s1.5;p16.46">First of all, a 2mL 100μM DNA solution is obtained by adding 140μL stock solution (approx. </s><s n="s2.5;p16.46">1400μM) into 1860μL distilled water. </s><s n="s3.5;p16.46">Secondly, the absorbance at 260 is measured for this DNA solution from 320-200nm. </s><s n="s4.5;p16.46">By applying Beer Lambert Law, the original DNA sample concentration turned out to be 2140μM/L. The concentration of Ru is calculated to be 166.8μM according to the values given at A <hi rend="sub">445</hi>=0.2835 and ε<hi rend="sub">Ru,445</hi>=17,000cm <hi rend="sup">-1</hi>mol <hi rend="sup">-1</hi>dm3, <hi rend="italic">l</hi>=1mm. </s><s n="s5.5;p16.46">Seven samples for fluorescence spectra is prepared from the original DNA sample and Ru sample provided, containing different concentration of DNA and Ru , listed in the following table: </s></p><table id="BAWE_0162b-tab.002"><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p17.46"><s n="s1.2;p17.46">Then, fluorescence spectra are measured for six samples, with the first water sample zeroing the scale. </s><s n="s2.2;p17.46">The data are stored in the floppy disk. </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Results</head><div2><head rend="bold">Estimation of protein concentration with two methods</head><div3><head>Absorbance at 280nm</head><p n="p18.46"><s n="s1.4;p18.46">From the absorbance value measured from 200-700nm, we found A <hi rend="sub">280</hi>=0.8728. (see figure 1.) </s><s n="s2.4;p18.46">A 1cm cuvette is used in the measurement thus the path length <hi rend="italic">l</hi>=1cm. </s><s n="s3.4;p18.46">The coefficient of extinction of myoglobin at 280nm ε=11000M <hi rend="sup">-1</hi>cm <hi rend="sup">-1</hi> is obtained from online database (<seg type="URL" n="http://us.expasy.org/tools/protparam.html"/>, by choosing description as myoglobin, primary accession number P14393, entry name GLB_APLJU). </s><s n="s4.4;p18.46">Also, the molecular weight of this myoglobin turned out to be 15015.8 g/mol. (see appendix I) </s></p><p n="p19.46"><s n="s1.1;p19.46">Then, according to Beer Lambert Law, the molar or mass concentration of the US is </s></p><p n="p20.46"><s n="s1.1;p20.46"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0162b-form.003"/> </s></p><p n="p21.46"><s n="s1.1;p21.46">or <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0162b-form.004"/> </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0162b-fig.001"><head><hi rend="bold">Figure 1</hi> . absorbance from 200 to 700 for US</head></figure></div3><div3><head>BCA method</head><p n="p22.46"><s n="s1.3;p22.46">Figure 2. shows the values of BSA concentration and the corresponding absorbance (denoted by *), the two different absorbance corresponding to different concentration with repeated observation for the US are also indicated in the graph (shown in two dash line for each concentration). </s><s n="s2.3;p22.46">The straight line is obtained from the data set in the sense of least square. </s><s n="s3.3;p22.46">A hand drawing plot is also provided as attachment of this report. </s></p><p n="p23.46"><s n="s1.3;p23.46">From the value obtained from the graph, we can see the absorbance for the US concentration at approximately 300μg/mL is measured as 0.289 and 0.318, which correspond to concentration values as 262.7 and 289.1. </s><s n="s2.3;p23.46">Similarly, for 200μg/mL, the corresponding value is 182.7 and 193.6. </s><s n="s3.3;p23.46">By taking the mean value, the concentration found in the graph is 276μg/mL and 188μg/mL, which correspond to original US concentration to be 0.92 mg/mL and 0.94mg/mL, respectively. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0162b-fig.002"><head><hi rend="bold">Figure 2.</hi> Absorbance versus BSA concentration with linear regression of the least square for US concentration determination</head></figure></div3></div2><div2><head rend="bold">Protein secondary structure determination by circular dichroism</head><p n="p24.46"><s n="s1.1;p24.46">By subtracting the baseline provided from the CD spectrum, we get the following diagram (figure 3.): </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0162b-fig.003"><head>Figure 3. CD spectrum with the baseline subtracted.</head></figure><p n="p25.46"><s n="s1.2;p25.46">With no available CDsstr software for protein structure determination, I use DICHROWEB as the tool to do the myoglobin protein secondary structure analysis. </s><s n="s2.2;p25.46">By setting mean residue weight as 105, protein concentration as 0.1mg/mL, and path length as 0.1cm, we get the percent of α-helices is 4.715 with average length 10.505nm, and strand 2.624% with average length 4.167nm. (see appendix II) </s></p><p n="p26.46"><s n="s1.2;p26.46">Figure 4 shows the relationship experimental data with expected data. </s><s n="s2.2;p26.46">At the wavelength 222, 208, we can see clearly negative peaks occurred, which means the existence of α-helices. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0162b-fig.004"><head><hi rend="bold">Figure 4.</hi> CD spectrum from DICHROWEB.</head></figure></div2><div2><head rend="bold">Equilibrium binding constant determination by fluorescence spectroscopy</head><p n="p27.46"><s n="s1.5;p27.46">The fluorescence spectra are presented as below ( figure 5). </s><s n="s2.5;p27.46">The first peaks of each curve should be ignored since this is the light from the lamp of the fluorescence machine. </s><s n="s3.5;p27.46">The second peaks are studies. </s><s n="s4.5;p27.46">Those peaks represent the intensity of fluorescence light the molecule made. </s><s n="s5.5;p27.46">By taking the value of fluorescence intensity at wavelength 580nm, and use the mean value of 10 data points around this wavelength, we obtain seven fluorescence intensities values </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0162b-fig.005"><head>Figure 5. fluorescence spectra from 440nm to 650 nm with different with different DNA concentration and Ru ligand.</head></figure><figure id="BAWE_0162b-fig.006"><head><hi rend="bold">Figure 6.</hi> fluorescence intensity at 580nm versus DNA concentration</head></figure><p n="p28.46"><s n="s1.3;p28.46">as -0.0267, 409.7130, 461.4506, 496.7539, 554.4751, 573.3974, and 740.6843, respectively. </s><s n="s2.3;p28.46">Plot these fluorescent intensity versus DNA concentration (0 10 20 40 80 300) ( see figure 6). </s><s n="s3.3;p28.46">The first fluorescence intensity value (the blue curve at the bottom of figure 5) is neglected since it is only a zero scale for the other fluorescence. </s></p><p n="p29.46"><s n="s1.2;p29.46">According to the lecture notes, we can construct a table to calculate the value of L <hi rend="sub">b</hi>, L <hi rend="sub">f</hi>, r and r/L <hi rend="sub">f</hi>, where L <hi rend="sub">f</hi> stands for the concentration of ligand Ru free and L <hi rend="sub">b</hi> for bind. </s><s n="s2.2;p29.46">Here, we use the fluorescence intensity at [DNA]=300μM as F <hi rend="sub">b</hi>, and fluorescence intensity at [DNA]=0μM as F <hi rend="sub">f</hi>. </s></p><table id="BAWE_0162b-tab.003"><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p30.46"><s n="s1.2;p30.46">Since the first and last rows do not contain useful information, we just simply neglect it. </s><s n="s2.2;p30.46">However, maybe due to some problem, the second last row data did not follow the trend of the previous values, and I have to neglect it in order to obtain the Scatchard plots (figure 7), with the binding constant K=-0.022. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0162b-fig.007"><head><hi rend="bold">Figure 7.</hi> Scatchard plot</head></figure></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Discussion </head><div2><head rend="bold">Protein concentration determination with absorbance and BCA method</head><div3><head>1. Absorbance at 280nm</head><p n="p31.46"><s n="s1.3;p31.46">Ideally, 1mg/mL protein solution should have absorbance of 1. </s><s n="s2.3;p31.46">However, I got the absorbance at 280nm as 0.8728, which is slightly lower than 1, and the calculated protein concentration as 1.19mg/mL, which is a bit higher than 1mg/mL. The difference may due to the protein sample, the measurement error, and the environment situation. </s><s n="s3.3;p31.46">The assumption underlying this method is based on the following condition: no contribution from light scattering, no other chromphore in the protein, and no other absorbing contaminant, etc. </s></p><p n="p32.46"><s n="s1.1;p32.46">If we use another way to calculate the concentration of protein, </s></p><p n="p33.46"><s n="s1.1;p33.46"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0162b-form.005"/> </s></p><p n="p34.46"><s n="s1.3;p34.46">We get a slightly lower protein concentration than the ideal one 1mg/mL, and the value calculated from the absorbance at 280 directly. </s><s n="s2.3;p34.46">The above formula is used in the case when the protein solution is not so pure, containing a significant amounts of nuclei acid ( as a few percent). </s><s n="s3.3;p34.46">In this case, we should also determine the absorbance at 260 nm to correct the presence of nuclei acids. </s></p><p n="p35.46"><s n="s1.1;p35.46">Exercise answer: </s></p><p n="p36.46"><s n="s1.1;p36.46">If we know that the molecular weight of lysozyme is 14314, n <hi rend="sub">W</hi>=6, n <hi rend="sub">Y</hi>=3, n <hi rend="sub">C</hi>=8, ε<hi rend="sub">280</hi>(C)=300 cm <hi rend="sup">-1</hi>dm <hi rend="sup">3</hi>mol <hi rend="sup">-1</hi>, ε<hi rend="sub">280</hi>(W)=5700 cm <hi rend="sup">-1</hi>dm <hi rend="sup">3</hi>mol <hi rend="sup">-1</hi>, and ε<hi rend="sub">280</hi>(Y)=1300 cm <hi rend="sup">-1</hi>dm <hi rend="sup">3</hi>mol <hi rend="sup">-1</hi>, we can determine the extinction coefficient ε for lysozyme by: </s></p><p n="p37.46"><s n="s1.1;p37.46">ε<hi rend="sub">280</hi>=n <hi rend="sub">W</hi>*ε<hi rend="sub">280</hi>(W)+n <hi rend="sub">Y</hi>*ε<hi rend="sub">280</hi>(Y)+n <hi rend="sub">C</hi>*ε<hi rend="sub">280</hi> (C)= 6*5700+3*1300+8*300=40500 </s></p><p n="p38.46"><s n="s1.1;p38.46">which is not so far away from the experimental value of ε280 = 37932 cm <hi rend="sup">-1</hi>dm <hi rend="sup">3</hi>mol <hi rend="sup">-1</hi>. </s></p><p n="p39.46"><s n="s1.1;p39.46">Similar for chymotrysinogen, according to the value of its molecular weight 25670, n <hi rend="sub">W</hi>=8, n <hi rend="sub">Y</hi>=4, n <hi rend="sub">C</hi>=10, and the calculated extinction coefficient turns out to be 53800 cm <hi rend="sup">-1</hi>dm <hi rend="sup">3</hi>mol <hi rend="sup">-1</hi>, compared with the experimental value 51340 cm <hi rend="sup">-1</hi>dm <hi rend="sup">3</hi>mol <hi rend="sup">-1</hi>. </s></p><p n="p40.46"><s n="s1.2;p40.46">For near UV (240-290nm), absorbance can be used to determine aromatic side chains, which present especially in Tyrosine, Tryptophan, Phenyl alanine, and Cystine. </s><s n="s2.2;p40.46">Proteins that contain aromatic side chains can use the above formula to determine the extinction coefficient, such as lysozyme and chymotrysinogen. </s></p></div3><div3><head>2. BCA method</head><p n="p41.46"><s n="s1.2;p41.46">The absorbance and the protein concentration should be linear relation in an ideal case. </s><s n="s2.2;p41.46">However, due to measurement error and environmental influencing factors, the observed absorbance did not fall exactly on a line, which requires using regression to connect each data set in the least square error sense. </s></p><p n="p42.46"><s n="s1.1;p42.46">By comparing the absorbance method and BCA method, the results obtained by both methods are consistent with 1mg/mL. However, the concentration determined by absorbance is a bit larger while the value from BCA is slightly smaller. </s></p></div3></div2><div2><head rend="bold">Protein secondary structure determination by circular dichroism</head><p n="p43.46"><s n="s1.2;p43.46">CD signal reflects an average of the entire molecular population. </s><s n="s2.2;p43.46">So, CD can only determine the percentage of the α-helix of a protein but not the specific residues involved in the α-helix portion. </s></p><p n="p44.46"><s n="s1.1;p44.46">With the help of the online website ( <seg type="URL" n="http://www.biochem.ucl.ac.uk/bsm/pdbsum"/>), I can find the myoglobin protein structure with the PDB code 2FAL. However, no percentage of α-helices is given in the website, thus no comparison can be made. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">Equilibrium binding constant determination by fluorescence spectroscopy</head><p n="p45.46"><s n="s1.3;p45.46">The Scatchard plots did not work so well in this case, due to the data value obtained from the fluorescence machine at DNA concentration 40μM and 80 μM with no significant difference. </s><s n="s2.3;p45.46">This problem caused here is probably due to the unpurified DNA sample or manipulate error. </s><s n="s3.3;p45.46">I have tried twice for this measurement, and the data used here is the value of the second time since the first time those two curves looks identical. </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Conclusion</head><p n="p46.46"><s n="s1.3;p46.46">In this laboratory, we determined the protein concentration with two methods - absorbance and BCA method, with consistent but slightly different results. </s><s n="s2.3;p46.46">CD spectroscopy can determine the protein secondary structure by telling the percent of α-helices, as approximate 4.7%. </s><s n="s3.3;p46.46">Fluorescence spectra is measured to determine the binding constant for DNA and Ru at different concentration. </s></p></div1></body><back><div1 type="bibliography"><head rend="bold">References</head><p>[1] <seg type="URL" n="http://www2"/>.<name type="university"/>.ac.uk/fac/sci/moac/msc_modules/module2/practical/</p><p>[2] <seg type="URL" n="www.cryst.bbk.ac.uk/cdweb"/></p><p>[3] <seg type="URL" n="http://us.expasy.org/srs5"/></p><p>[4] <seg type="URL" n="http://us.expasy.org/tools/protparam.html"/></p><p>[5] <seg type="URL" n="http://www.biochem.ucl.ac.uk/bsm/pdbsum/"/></p></div1><div1 type="appendix"><head rend="bold">Appendix I: </head><p/></div1><div1 type="appendix"><head rend="bold">Appendix II: </head><p/></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
