<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_0162a" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>DNA Melting Exercise</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note/></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">4</p><p n="date">2005-12</p><p n="module title">Data Acquisition I: Biophysical Techniques &amp; Instrumentation Design</p><p n="module code">MOAC2</p><p n="genre family">Explanation</p><p n="discipline">Biological Sciences</p><p n="disciplinary group">LS</p><p n="grade">D</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">933</p><p n="number of s-units">45</p><p n="number of p">30</p><p n="number of tables">0</p><p n="number of figures">6</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">8</p><p n="number of lists">0</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">0</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">20.7</p><p n="average s-units per p">1.5</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">f</p><p n="year of birth">1983</p><p n="first language">Chinese unspecified</p><p n="education">OSA</p><p n="course">Mathematical Biology and Biophysical Chemistry</p><p n="student ID">0162</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><docTitle><titlePart rend="bold">DNA Melting Exercise</titlePart></docTitle><titlePart rend="italic"><name type="student name"/></titlePart></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="section"><p n="p1.30"><s n="s1.4;p1.30">Usually DNA exists as a double helix with two polymers held by hydrogen bonds between the bases on each strand. </s><s n="s2.4;p1.30">However, the double stranded DNA helices would separate into single stranded components if heated up gradually.<hi rend="italic"> Tm</hi>, called as melting temperature of a DNA helix, is defined to be the temperature at which half of the DNA base pairs have broken their hydrogen bonds. </s><s n="s3.4;p1.30">This transition is measured by the absorbance of a DNA sample as a function of temperature. </s><s n="s4.4;p1.30">The following is the diagram showing the relevant properties of the DNA melting curve versus temperature. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Determination of Tm with the plot of the Absorbance versus Temperature. </head><p n="p2.30"><s n="s1.2;p2.30">Figure 1 shows the plot of the DNA absorbance as the temperature goes up. </s><s n="s2.2;p2.30">The absorbance curve keeps constant at the beginning, from 20 to 60 degree centigrade ( οC), and goes up dramatically in the range between 60 and 85οC. Finally, the curve levels off after 80οC. </s></p><p n="p3.30"><s n="s1.3;p3.30">From the data given, we can find that the maximum absorbance is 1.2498, and the minimum one is 0.9933. </s><s n="s2.3;p3.30">Thus, the estimated <hi rend="italic">Tm</hi> can be determined by the point half way between the low DNA melting curve and the high curve, which has the value A <hi rend="sub italic">m</hi>=1.1215. </s><s n="s3.3;p3.30">This value corresponds to <hi rend="italic">Tm</hi>=68οC approximately, since the baseline of the curve is not flat. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0162a-fig.001"><head>Figure 1. DNA melting curve: absorbance versus temperature.</head></figure></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Determination of <hi rend="italic">Tm</hi> with the derivative of absorbance </head><p n="p4.30"><s n="s1.2;p4.30">Figure 2 is plot of the derivative of the absorbance curve with respect to the temperature versus the temperature. </s><s n="s2.2;p4.30">The peak occurs at the temperature of approximately 66οC, which can be another estimate value of <hi rend="italic">Tm.</hi> </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0162a-fig.002"><head>Figure 2. Differentiation of A with respect to T.</head></figure></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">3. The baseline that approximates the temperature dependence of the unmelted DNA absorbance. </head><p n="p5.30"><s n="s1.2;p5.30">Using the first 15 data points, we can find a straight line that approximates the temperature dependence of the unmelted DNA absorbance (see figure 3). </s><s n="s2.2;p5.30">The equation of this baseline worked out turns out to be: </s></p><p n="p6.30"><s n="s1.1;p6.30"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0162a-form.001"/>. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0162a-fig.003"><head>Figure 3. DNA melting curve and unmelted DNA absorbance curve.</head></figure></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">4. Evaluation of the final absorbance and α</head><p n="p7.30"><s n="s1.1;p7.30">The final absorbance on the melting curve plot is 1.2498. </s></p><p n="p8.30"><s n="s1.2;p8.30">Let <hi rend="italic">x</hi> be the difference between the final absorbance of the unfolded DNA (<hi rend="italic">A</hi><hi rend="sub">final</hi>=1.2498) and the absorbance at a given temperature (<hi rend="italic">A</hi>), and <hi rend="italic">y</hi> be the difference in absorbance between the temperature dependent absorbance (<hi rend="italic">A</hi>) and the baseline (<hi rend="italic">A</hi>=1.0007) of the figure 3 plot. </s><s n="s2.2;p8.30">Then, </s></p><p n="p9.30"><s n="s1.1;p9.30"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0162a-form.002"/> </s></p><p n="p10.30"><s n="s1.1;p10.30">is a function of temperature. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">5. Determination of <hi rend="italic">Tm</hi> with the plot of α versus absolute temperature <hi rend="italic">Tabs</hi>. </head><p n="p11.30"><s n="s1.1;p11.30">We transform the centigrade temperature <hi rend="italic">T</hi> into the absolute temperature <hi rend="italic">Tabs</hi> by the following equation: </s></p><p n="p12.30"><s n="s1.1;p12.30"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0162a-form.003"/> </s></p><p n="p13.30"><s n="s1.2;p13.30">since the absolute temperature <hi rend="italic">Tabs</hi> in Kelvin is the degree centigrade plus 273.15. </s><s n="s2.2;p13.30">The plot of α versus the inverse of the absolute temperature <hi rend="italic">1/Tabs</hi> in Kelvin is shown in figure 4: </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0162a-fig.004"><head>Figure 4. α versus the inverse of the absolute temperature in Kelvin.</head></figure><p n="p14.30"><s n="s1.2;p14.30">The midpoint of α, i.e. the melting temperature at which half of the DNA is melted, is α = 0.5143, and the corresponding <hi rend="italic"> 1/Tab</hi><hi rend="sub">s</hi> =0.00294, or <hi rend="italic">Tabs</hi> = 340.14 in Kelvin. </s><s n="s2.2;p14.30">That is, <hi rend="italic">Tm</hi> = 340.14 - 273.15 = 66.99οC </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">6. Plot of the derivative of α versus <hi rend="italic">Tabs</hi> and evaluation of van't Hoff transition enthalpy</head><p n="p15.30"><s n="s1.1;p15.30">Figure 5 is the plot of the derivative of α with respect to the inverse of the absolute temperature <hi rend="italic">1/Tabs</hi> versus the absolute temperature T <hi rend="sub">abs</hi>, since <hi rend="italic">T</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Tabs</hi> is just a shift of scale, and they are equivalent. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0162a-fig.005"><head>Figure 5. plot of derivative of α versus <hi rend="italic">Tabs</hi> .</head></figure><p n="p16.30"><s n="s1.1;p16.30">From figure 5, we can see that the absolute temperature of the maximum of the derivative curve is <hi rend="italic">Tmax =</hi> 339.66 K, while the absolute temperature of the high temperature half height of the curve turns out to be <hi rend="italic">T2</hi> = 345 K. </s></p><p n="p17.30"><s n="s1.1;p17.30">Thus, Van't Hoff transition enthalpy of the transition can be determined by the following formula: </s></p><p n="p18.30"><s n="s1.1;p18.30"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0162a-form.004"/> </s></p><p n="p19.30"><s n="s1.1;p19.30">where B' = - 4.38 cal K <hi rend="sup">-1</hi> mol <hi rend="sup">-1</hi> = - 4.38 cal K <hi rend="sup">-1</hi> mol <hi rend="sup">-1 </hi>× 4.1868 J/cal = -18.34 J K <hi rend="sup">-1</hi> mol <hi rend="sup">-1</hi>. </s></p><p n="p20.30"><s n="s1.1;p20.30">So, <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0162a-form.005"/>. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">7. Entropy determination</head><p n="p21.30"><s n="s1.2;p21.30">According to the previous steps, we have found three <hi rend="italic">Tm</hi> value as 68οC, 66οC, and 66.99οC respectively. </s><s n="s2.2;p21.30">Thus, we take the mean of these three, and <hi rend="italic">Tm =</hi> 67οC, approximately, or 340.15 K in absolute temperature. </s></p><p n="p22.30"><s n="s1.1;p22.30">The entropy change of the transition can be determined by using </s></p><p n="p23.30"><s n="s1.1;p23.30"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0162a-form.006"/>, </s></p><p n="p24.30"><s n="s1.1;p24.30">So, <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0162a-form.007"/>. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">8. Gibbs free energy determination and some comment. </head><p n="p25.30"><s n="s1.1;p25.30">Gibbs free energy of the transition is determined by </s></p><p n="p26.30"><s n="s1.1;p26.30"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0162a-form.008"/>. </s></p><p n="p27.30"><s n="s1.1;p27.30">Figure 6 can show the linear relationship between the change of Gibbs free energy and the absolute temperature: </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0162a-fig.006"><head>Figure 6. Gibbs free energy of the transition versus the absolute temperature.</head></figure><p n="p28.30"><s n="s1.3;p28.30">From the figure, we can see that the Gibbs free energy would be zero if the temperature is taken at the value <hi rend="italic"> Tm</hi>. </s><s n="s2.3;p28.30">The absolute value of Gibbs free energy decrease as the temperature increase from the beginning to <hi rend="italic">Tm,</hi> and increase again after <hi rend="italic">Tm</hi>. </s><s n="s3.3;p28.30">From the absolute magnitude of Gibbs free energy, we can see that it is high in the system of double stranded DNA and a bit lower when all double stranded become single stranded. </s></p><p n="p29.30"><s n="s1.1;p29.30">Then van't Hoff transition enthalpy of the transition is -402460 J/mol, which is the maximum amount of thermal energy derivable to a thermodynamic process of DNA melting when the pressure is held constant. </s></p><p n="p30.30"><s n="s1.2;p30.30">The change of entropy is -1183.2 J K <hi rend="sup">-1</hi> mol <hi rend="sup">-1</hi>. </s><s n="s2.2;p30.30">This is a measure of the amount of energy that cannot be sued to do work in this double stranded and single stranded DNA system. </s></p></div1></body><back/></text></TEI.2>
