<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_0162c" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Monoclonal Antibody Structure and Function Determination with Biophysical Techniques</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note/></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">4</p><p n="date">2006-02</p><p n="module title">Data Acquisition I: Biophysical Techniques &amp; Instrumentation Design</p><p n="module code">MOAC2</p><p n="genre family">Explanation</p><p n="discipline">Biological Sciences</p><p n="disciplinary group">LS</p><p n="grade">M</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">2454</p><p n="number of s-units">88</p><p n="number of p">23</p><p n="number of tables">0</p><p n="number of figures">10</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">0</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">0</p><p n="abstract present">abstract present</p><p n="average words per s-unit">27.9</p><p n="average s-units per p">3.8</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">f</p><p n="year of birth">1983</p><p n="first language">Chinese unspecified</p><p n="education">OSA</p><p n="course">Mathematical Biology and Biophysical Chemistry</p><p n="student ID">0162</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><docTitle><titlePart>Monoclonal Antibody Structure and Function Determination with Biophysical Techniques</titlePart></docTitle><titlePart rend="italic"><name type="student name"/></titlePart><titlePart>MOAC, Senate House, University of <name type="university"/>, <name type="other"/>, UK</titlePart></titlePage><div1 type="front text"><p><name type="other"/></p></div1></front><body><div1 type="abstract"><head rend="bold">Abstract:</head><p n="p1.23"><s n="s1.2;p1.23">This essay discussed the structure of antibody，the discovery and the importance of monoclonal antibodies. </s><s n="s2.2;p1.23">Different modern technique, such as NMR, absorbance spectroscopy, X-ray crystallography and mass spectrometry, are used to study the structure and function of some proteins in the monoclonal antibody. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Introduction to monoclonal antibody</head><p n="p2.23"><s n="s1.3;p2.23">Antibody is a kind of protein that is related to immune system. </s><s n="s2.3;p2.23">It belongs to the family of immunoglobulins, whose duty is to bind a specific antigen in order to remove it from the body. </s><s n="s3.3;p2.23">Antibody are synthesised from B-lymphocytes, with a different amino acid sequence and a specific binding site for different kinds of antigen, which is called antigenic determinant or epitope. </s></p><p n="p3.23"><s n="s1.3;p3.23">The structure of antibody is very interesting. </s><s n="s2.3;p3.23">Each antibody consists of four polypeptides - two heavy chains and two light chains. </s><s n="s3.3;p3.23">They join together to form a "Y" shaped molecule. (see figure 1). </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0162c-pic.001"><head>Figure 1. Y-shape structure of an antibody</head></figure><p n="p4.23"><s n="s1.2;p4.23">Different kinds of antibodies have different amino acid sequence in the tips of the "Y", which give the antibody its specificity to bind antigen. </s><s n="s2.2;p4.23">This variable region is composed of 110-130 amino acids, including the ends of both the light and heavy chains. </s></p><p n="p5.23"><s n="s1.3;p5.23">The variable region can be further subdivided into hypervariable and framework regions. </s><s n="s2.3;p5.23">Hypervariable regions have a high ratio of different amino acid in a given position, which is relative to the most common amino acid in that position. </s><s n="s3.3;p5.23">For framework regions, they have more stable amino acids sequences separating the hypervariable regions. </s></p><p n="p6.23"><s n="s1.2;p6.23">The constant region, on the other hand, determines the mechanism used to destroy antigen. </s><s n="s2.2;p6.23">Antibodies are divided into five major classes, IgM, IgG, IgA, IgD, and IgE, depending on their constant region structure and immune functions. </s></p><p n="p7.23"><s n="s1.4;p7.23">The antibody recognition of antigen is mainly based on the antigen-binding specificity. </s><s n="s2.4;p7.23">It is the basis for the ability of the immune system to recognize virtually a foreign antigen. </s><s n="s3.4;p7.23">The structural is illustrated in figure 2. </s><s n="s4.4;p7.23">V <hi rend="sub">L</hi> and V <hi rend="sub">H</hi> amino-terminal domain lie at each tip of the branches of the immunoglobulin. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0162c-pic.002"><head>Figure 2. The four-chain structure of an antibody molecule. The basic unit is composed of two identical light chains (L) and two identical heavy chains (H), which are held together by disulfide bonds to form a flexible Y shape. Each chain is composed of a variable region (H) and a constant region (C).</head></figure><p n="p8.23"><s n="s1.3;p8.23">Monoclonal antibodies are the antibodies that are identical, since they are produced by one type of immune cell. </s><s n="s2.3;p8.23">All clones are from a single parent cell. </s><s n="s3.3;p8.23">Thus, monoclonal antibodies can specifically bind to a specific substance. </s></p><p n="p9.23"><s n="s1.5;p9.23">The discovery of monoclonal antibodies can be cast back to 1970s, when the B-cell cancer myeloma was first known, and understood as cancerous B-cell all producing a single type of antibody. </s><s n="s2.5;p9.23">This discovery was applied to the study of the structure of antibodies. </s><s n="s3.5;p9.23">However, it was not possible to produce the identical antibodies specific to a given antigen. </s><s n="s4.5;p9.23">It was not until 1975 that the process of producing monoclonal antibodies was invented, and given by Nobel Prize in Physiology or Medicine in 1984 for the discovery. </s><s n="s5.5;p9.23">The key idea for the invention of monoclonal antibodies was the use a line of myeloma cells, which had already lost their ability to secrete antibodies. </s></p><p n="p10.23"><s n="s1.2;p10.23">The monoclonal antibodies can be produced artificially by some genetic technique, which is one of the most important techniques of biotechnology during the last century. </s><s n="s2.2;p10.23">The circulating B-cell would multiply to form a clone of plasma cells, secreting identical immunoglobulin molecules, when activated by an antigen. </s></p><p n="p11.23"><s n="s1.4;p11.23">Monoclonal antibody have many applications. </s><s n="s2.4;p11.23">It can be used to detect for the presence and quantity of its corresponding substance. </s><s n="s3.4;p11.23">It can also be used to purify a substance with techniques called immunoprecipitation and affinity chromatography. </s><s n="s4.4;p11.23">This is an important tool in biochemistry, molecular biology and medicine. </s></p><p n="p12.23"><s n="s1.2;p12.23">Monoclonal antibody is very important in biological studies and medical application. </s><s n="s2.2;p12.23">The structure and function of monoclonal antibody is researched a lot by a variety kinds of biophysical techniques, such as Nuclear Magnetic Resonance (NMR), absorbance spectroscopy, X-ray crystallography and mass spectrometry. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Biophysical techniques </head><div2><head rend="bold">Nuclear Magnetic Resonance</head><p n="p13.23"><s n="s1.4;p13.23">Nuclear magnetic resonance (NMR) spectroscopy is one of the few modern techniques that are capable of determining the structure of biological macromolecules, like protein and nuclei acids at atomic resolution. </s><s n="s2.4;p13.23">The NMR data can be recorded either in solution, where most protein molecule perform their physiological functions, or in solid. </s><s n="s3.4;p13.23">NMR can also be used to study protein denaturation if the solution is in nonphysiolgical condition, or dynamic features of molecular structures. </s><s n="s4.4;p13.23">Also, molecular recognition, protein folding, and thermodynamics and kinetics aspects of interactions between proteins and other solution components, such as ligands, can also be studied by NMR. </s></p><p n="p14.23"><s n="s1.4;p14.23">Developments in biochemical methods allow simple and fast preparation of protein samples for NMR spectroscopy studies. </s><s n="s2.4;p14.23">Heternuclei, like <hi rend="sup">15</hi>N, <hi rend="sup">13</hi>C and <hi rend="sup">2</hi>H, can be incorporated in proteins by uniformly or selective isotopic labelling. </s><s n="s3.4;p14.23">Spectra from these samples can be very simple but gives clear information of the protein 3D structure. </s><s n="s4.4;p14.23">Nowadays, modern developments on NMR can determine structure of proteins with the mass up to 30 k Da. </s></p><p n="p15.23"><s n="s1.5;p15.23">One example is the determination of tertiary structure and epitopes of MD-2-related lipid-recognition (ML) proteins of monoclonal antibody by NMR ([1]). </s><s n="s2.5;p15.23">The ligands and biological functions of Group 2 major mite allergens Der f 2 and Der p 2 are analyzed by a high-quality NMR structure. </s><s n="s3.5;p15.23">It is found that it is more similar to the crystal structure of NPC2, a distant homologue, than to that of Der p 2, in terms of the separation and angle between the two major β-sheets. </s><s n="s4.5;p15.23">This discovery indicates that ML proteins undergo clamshell-like motions that change the sizes of ligand-binding spaces inside their immunoglobulin-fold β-sandwich to accommodate lipid molecules. </s><s n="s5.5;p15.23">With NMR, conformational epitopes for monoclonal antibodies 15E11 and 13A4 are detected as two separate surfaces patches (see figure 3, 4). </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0162c-pic.003"><head>Figure 3. Refined tertiary structure of Der f 2. (a) Best fit superposition of the backbone atoms (N, Cα , C′ ) of the 10 final structures of Der f 2. (b) Ribbon diagrams of the mean structure of Der f 2. Disulfide bonds are colored yellow. (c) A close-up for T47, the only threonine residue whose hydroxyl proton Hγ 1 was observed. Some carbon, nitrogen and oxygen atoms are shown as black, blue and red spheres, respectively.</head></figure><figure id="BAWE_0162c-pic.004"><head>Figure 4. Structural comparison of ML proteins. Ribbon diagrams are shown, with views related by 90° rotation. (a) Der f 2; (b) Der p 2 in crystal; (c) NPC2; (d) GM2-activator. </head></figure></div2><div2><head rend="bold">Absorbance spectroscopy</head><p n="p16.23"><s n="s1.5;p16.23">Absorbance spectroscopy can probe electronic transitions of molecules as they absorb lights in the UV and visible region of spectrum. </s><s n="s2.5;p16.23">Typically, proteins have a maximum around 280 nm wavelengths from aromatics side chains, especially tryptophan. </s><s n="s3.5;p16.23">The aromatic absorbance is also the key in protein fluorescence and circular dichroism measurements. </s><s n="s4.5;p16.23">Larger protein has around 205 nm from amide bond. </s><s n="s5.5;p16.23">This is useful to determine total protein concentration, protein structure, and ligand binding. </s></p><p n="p17.23"><s n="s1.5;p17.23">Since no relevant information of ML protein of monoclonal antibody can be found regarding absorbance spectroscopy technique for structure determination, I focus on the binding site architecture instead for absorbance spectroscopy ([2]). </s><s n="s2.5;p17.23">Monoclonal antibody NC6.8 binds the superpotent sweetener ligand N-(p- cyanophenyl)-N'-(diphenylmethyl) guanidineacetic acid with high affinity. </s><s n="s3.5;p17.23">Using absorbance spectroscopy, the structure of the variable domain fragment Fv can be predicted, and the key residues in the combining site of the antibody are identified. </s><s n="s4.5;p17.23">Also, nine specific amino acids, which are involved in ligand recognition and complexation, are identified. </s><s n="s5.5;p17.23">These modeling predictions were made before the solution of high-resolution structures. (see figure 5, 6) </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0162c-fig.001"><head>Figure 5. (A) Absorption spectra of 0.7 mM of mAb NC6.8 in the presence of 0.0, 0.004, 0.012, 0.33, 0.48, 0.90, 1.6, and 2.7 mM of ligand. No increased absorption is observed in the 300-360-nm range. (B) Absorption spectra of 1.4 mM of a different mAb (clone NC10.8) in the presence of 0.0, 0.002, 0.05, 0.46, 1.24, 1.95, 2.86, 3.98, and 5.38 mM ligand. The observed increase in absorbance near 260 and 280 nm for both mAb is due to the mAb-ligand complex and free ligand. The increased absorbance in the 300-360-nm range (arrow) is due to a charge-transfer complex in NC10.8, which is not present in NC6.8.</head></figure><figure id="BAWE_0162c-pic.005"><head>Figure 6. (A) Face stereo rendering of the charges at the van der Waals surface for NC6.8. The colors are coded according to the Coulombic charges at the van der Waals surface, with blue representing the positively charged potentials and red representing negatively charged potentials; other colors render the gradient between these two extremes. (B) Fface stereo view of the peptide backbone of NC6.8. The CDR are colored as CDRL1 in blue, CDRL2 in pink, CDRL3 in purple, CDRH1 in red, CDRH2 in green, and CDRH3 in orange.</head></figure></div2><div2><head rend="bold">X-ray crystallography</head><p n="p18.23"><s n="s1.2;p18.23">X-ray crystallography is the experimental technique in which patterns produced by diffraction of X-ray through atoms in a crystal is recorded and analyzed to reveal the 3D structure of substance, such as protein and DNA. Today, crystallography is also used in pharmaceutical area to determine specifically how drug lead compounds interact with their protein targets. </s><s n="s2.2;p18.23">In biology, X-ray crystallography contributes to most of protein structures solved. </s></p><p n="p19.23"><s n="s1.7;p19.23">The working principle of X-ray crystallography is simple. </s><s n="s2.7;p19.23">The precise conformation and orientation of each atom in a molecule can be only determined when the molecule is formed into a perfect crystal. </s><s n="s3.7;p19.23">When X-ray hit the crystals of purified molecule, the rays are deflected by the atoms of molecules in diffraction patterns. </s><s n="s4.7;p19.23">The number of electrons in the atom determines the intensity of the scattering of X-rays. </s><s n="s5.7;p19.23">Heavier atoms scatter more effectively than light ones. </s><s n="s6.7;p19.23">A series of diffraction pattern are taken from several angles, and these patterns can provide the organization information of the components of the molecules. </s><s n="s7.7;p19.23">Computers can be used to mathematically interpret this pattern and reconstruct the positions of the atoms. </s></p><p n="p20.23"><s n="s1.8;p20.23">One example of using X-ray crystallography is the determination of the structure for an anti-tumor antibody ([3]). </s><s n="s2.8;p20.23">CH2-domain-deleted CC49 (HuCC49DCH2) is a recombinant humanized antibody that recognizes the TAG-72 antigen, which is expressed on a variety of human carcinomas. </s><s n="s3.8;p20.23">HuCC49DCH2 can be crystallized from sodium formate. </s><s n="s4.8;p20.23">X-ray diffraction data were collected on a single cryo-cooled crystal and the structure was solved by molecular replacement. </s><s n="s5.8;p20.23">The antibodies pack in the crystal around crystallographic 2-fold axes as tetramers with approximate 222 symmetries. </s><s n="s6.8;p20.23">The tetramer is composed of two rings, back-to-back, with a thickness of 83A. The CH3 domain is inverted with respect to the Fabs when compared to the usual orientation found in conventional antibodies. </s><s n="s7.8;p20.23">The antigen combining site of HuCC49DCH2 is similar but not identical. </s><s n="s8.8;p20.23">The combining site consists of a deep cleft, heavily lined with aromatic amino acid side-chains but bounded by numerous charged groups. (see figure 7, 8, 9 10) </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0162c-pic.006"><head>Figure 7. Stereo diagram of a portion of the polypeptide of HuCC49DCH2, residues 87 through 100 of light chain A, superimposed upon its corresponding electron density.</head></figure><figure id="BAWE_0162c-pic.007"><head>Figure 8. (a) is a stereo diagram of one HuCC49DCH2 antibody of the four comprising a toroidal complex. The Fab domains have a parallel orientation and the CH3 domain is inverted. In (b) and (c), a dimer of two antibodies, formed by interactions of their CDR loops, creates a ring. The ring is seen in the face in (b) and on edge in (c).</head></figure><figure id="BAWE_0162c-pic.008"><head>Figure 9. <hi rend="bold">Left</hi> : The toroidal complex formed by two antibody rings. An exact 2-fold axis is seen viewed along the toroidal axis in (a) and orthogonal to that axis in (b). There is an open channel along the axis of the toroid, which itself exhibits pseudo 222 symmetry, with one axis an exact crystallographic dyad. <hi rend="bold">Right:</hi> Toroidal complexes of four HuCC49DCH2 antibodies are shown as they are packed in the crystal. In (a) the view is along the crystallographic a-axis, and in (b) along the c-axis.</head></figure><figure id="BAWE_0162c-pic.009"><head>Figure 10. The polypeptide backbones for the Fab domains of antibody B72.3 and HuCC49DCH2 are shown here in a stereo diagrams. In (a) only the variable domains are shown while in (b) both constant and variable domains joined by elbow polypeptides are shown.</head></figure></div2><div2><head rend="bold">Mass spectrometry</head><p n="p21.23"><s n="s1.5;p21.23">Mass spectrometer is an analytical tool used for measuring the molecular weight of a sample, with no limitation on the range of molecular mass. </s><s n="s2.5;p21.23">It uses the difference in mass-to-charge ration (m/z) of ionized atoms or molecules to separate them from each other. </s><s n="s3.5;p21.23">For large samples such as biomolecules, molecular weights can be measured with high accuracy, which is sufficient to allow minor mass changes to be detected. </s><s n="s4.5;p21.23">Mass spectrometry nowadays plays a central role in chemistry and in biomedical sciences. </s><s n="s5.5;p21.23">The technique is extremely sensitive and is used in many analytical applications. </s></p><p n="p22.23"><s n="s1.3;p22.23">In recent years soft ionization methods like electrospray (ESI) and matrix assisted laser ionisation (MALDI) have been developed as powerful tools for the elucidation of protein structure. </s><s n="s2.3;p22.23">Mass spectrometry is useful for quantization atoms or molecules and also for determining chemical and structural information about molecules. </s><s n="s3.3;p22.23">Structural information can be generated with some certain types of mass spectrometers, achieved by fragmentation the sample and analyzing the product generated. </s></p><p n="p23.23"><s n="s1.5;p23.23">The following example shows how mass spectrometry is used in structural characterization of the maytansinoid - monoclonal antibody ([5]). </s><s n="s2.5;p23.23">The immunoconjugate, huN901 - DM1, composed of the humanized monoclonal IgG1 antibody, huN901, and the maytansinoid drug, DM1, is being tested in clinical trials to treat a small cell lung carcinoma (SCLC). huN901 - DM1 contains an average of three to four DM1 drug molecules per huN901 antibody molecule. </s><s n="s3.5;p23.23">The drug distribution profile of N901 - DM1 by electrospray time-of-flight mass spectrometry (ESI-TOFMS) showed that one to six DM1 drug molecules were attached to an antibody molecule. </s><s n="s4.5;p23.23">With respect to Asp-N digestion, modified peptides were identified by observing a mass increase corresponding to the modification. </s><s n="s5.5;p23.23">Using structural models of human IgG1, it was found that modified lysine residues were on the surface in areas of structural flexibility and had large solvent accessibility. (see figure 11, 12) </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0162c-fig.002"><head>Figure 11. <hi rend="bold">Left</hi> : ESI-TOFMS spectra of deglycosylated huN901 - DM1. (A) Raw MS data; (B) deconvoluted MS spectrum. <hi rend="bold">Right:</hi> EICs and corresponding ESIMS spectra of the Asp-N heavy chain peptide, HD8, modified with zero (A), one (B), and two (C) linkers derived from the LC/MS analysis of conjugate heavy-chain digest.</head></figure><figure id="BAWE_0162c-pic.010"><head>Figure 12. Cartoon plots of the crystal structures of human IgG1 Fab (A) and Fc (B). The two chains are in cyan and yellow and the carbohydrate moieties are in gray. Modified lysine residues in huN901 - DM1 aremapped to the corresponding residues in huIgG1 and are shown in red. In the Fc fragment, the modified lysine residues are only labeled in one chain.</head></figure></div2></div1></body><back><div1 type="bibliography"><head rend="bold">References: </head><p>1. Viswanathan, M.; Anchin, J. M.; Droupadi, P. R.; Mandal, C.; Linthicum, D.S.; and Subramaniam, S. Structural predictions of the binding site architecture for monoclonal antibody NC6.8 using computer-aided molecular modeling, ligand binding, and spectroscopy. <hi rend="bold">1995</hi>.<hi rend="italic"> Biophysical Journal, 69,</hi> 741-753</p><p>2. Ichikawa, S.; Takai, T.; Inoue, T.; Yuuki, T.; Okumura, Y.; Ogura, K.; Inagaki, F.; and Hatanaka, H. NMR Study on the Major Mite Allergen Der f 2: Its Refined Tertiary Structure, Epitopes for Monoclonal Antibodies and Characteristics Shared by ML Protein Group Members. <hi rend="bold">2005</hi>. <hi rend="italic">J. Biochem. 137</hi>, 255-263</p><p>4. Larson, S. B.; Day, J. S.; Claser, S.; Braslawsky, G.; and McPherson A. The Structure of an Antitumor CH2-domain-deleted Humanized Antibody. <hi rend="bold">2005. </hi><hi rend="italic">J. Mol. Biol. 348,</hi> 1177-1190. </p><p>4. Wang, L.; Amphlett, G.; Blattler, W. A.; Lambert, J. M.; and Zhang, W. Structural characterization of the maytansinoid - monoclonal antibody immunoconjugate, huN901 - DM1, by mass spectrometry. <hi rend="bold">2005</hi>. <hi rend="italic">Protein Sci. 14</hi>, 2436-2446.</p></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
