<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_0169a" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Report on A-Z Cloth UK</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">appendix: tables, algorithms and outputs
</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">1</p><p n="date">2004-03</p><p n="module title">Quantitive Methods of Analysis</p><p n="module code">IB1020</p><p n="genre family">Case study</p><p n="discipline">Business</p><p n="disciplinary group">SS</p><p n="grade">M</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">1008</p><p n="number of s-units">43</p><p n="number of p">21</p><p n="number of tables">0</p><p n="number of figures">0</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">0</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">10</p><p n="abstract present">abstract present</p><p n="average words per s-unit">23.4</p><p n="average s-units per p">2.0</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">m</p><p n="year of birth">1984</p><p n="first language">English</p><p n="education">UKA</p><p n="course">Management Science</p><p n="student ID">0169</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><docTitle><titlePart rend="underlined bold">Report on A-Z Cloth UK</titlePart></docTitle></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="abstract"><head rend="bold">Summary and Recommendations</head><p n="p1.21"><s n="s1.1;p1.21">After solving the problem using Microsoft Excel and analysing possible future changes the following recommendations can be made. </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p2.21"><s n="s1.1;p2.21">At current costs and internal capacities, the cost of supplying the customer with 500m of cloth is £8580.00, or £17.16 per metre. </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p3.21"><s n="s1.1;p3.21">Introducing a new product requiring only 700 hours of vat time a week would not require an increase in production capacity. </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p4.21"><s n="s1.1;p4.21">When the cost of producing yarn is cheaper that buying yarn in, 80 extra hours of carding and combing capacity should be purchased at a price according to other costs and amounts of bought in yarn purchased. </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p5.21"><s n="s1.1;p5.21">If the cost of buying in yarn becomes less costly than producing yarn internally, it may be prudent to relax the constraint on supplying cloth made from a minimum of 50% internally produced yarn. </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p6.21"><s n="s1.2;p6.21">The department should look to negotiate a 20% discount with the current external suppliers of yarn as this will help reduce overall costs. </s><s n="s2.2;p6.21">The department should be cautious of an unreliable supplier, and weigh up a 30% discount with the possibility of delays in supplying customers and the financial implications this may have. </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p7.21"><s n="s1.1;p7.21">The amount of cloth supplied to the customer can be increased to a maximum of 680m, but profit margins per metre are decreased </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Introduction</head><p n="p8.21"><s n="s1.2;p8.21">A-Z Cloth UK has agreed to supply a customer at least 500 metres of cloth per week using yarn produced internally and bought in. </s><s n="s2.2;p8.21">The minimum cost of supplying this contract is required. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Method</head><p n="p9.21"><s n="s1.2;p9.21">The problem has been simulated as a linear programming problem and solved using Solver, with Microsoft Excel. </s><s n="s2.2;p9.21">Details are contained within the appendix. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Situations</head><p n="p10.21"><s n="s1.2;p10.21">NB: - Situations will be referred to in the text by their number. </s><s n="s2.2;p10.21">Refer to Table 1 in the appendix for details of each situation. </s></p><div2><head rend="bold">A. Present Situation</head><p n="p11.21"><s n="s1.2;p11.21">At the current prices, vat hour allowances, carding and combing allowances and twisting allowances, the cost of meeting the contract is £8580.00. </s><s n="s2.2;p11.21">This is situation <hi rend="bold">1</hi>. </s></p><p n="p12.21"><s n="s1.3;p12.21">500m of cloth is produced with 320m made from internally produced yarn and 180m from bought in yarn, all at a cost of £17.16 per metre. </s><s n="s2.3;p12.21">The amount of time using vat A and vat B should be 320 hours respectively. </s><s n="s3.3;p12.21">1280 hours should be allotted to carding and combing, and 1600 hours allotted to twisting. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">B. Extra Product Introduced</head><p n="p13.21"><s n="s1.3;p13.21">The <hi rend="bold">Answer Report 1</hi> shows that there is slack (hours of spare capacity) of 280 hours for vat A and 480 hours for vat B for production under the Current Situation, a total of 760 slack hours. </s><s n="s2.3;p13.21">If a new product was introduced there would be enough spare hours per week to accommodate such a product. </s><s n="s3.3;p13.21">There would be 60 slack hours left over per week. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">C. Spare Carding and Combing Machine Capacity </head><p n="p14.21"><s n="s1.5;p14.21">In situation <hi rend="bold">1</hi>, 1600, of the available 1700 twisting hours are used. </s><s n="s2.5;p14.21">A 100 hour increase in twisting (a process that takes 5 hours) would produce enough yarn to make 20m of cloth. </s><s n="s3.5;p14.21">Therefore only enough carding and combing capacity to make 20m of cloth should be purchased. </s><s n="s4.5;p14.21">As the carding and combing process takes 4 hours, a maximum of 80 hours of carding and combing capacity should be purchased. </s><s n="s5.5;p14.21">Table 3 shows that in situations <hi rend="bold">2,</hi> <hi rend="bold">4, 6</hi> and <hi rend="bold">8</hi>, no more than £120, £36, £100 and £16 should be paid in each situation for the 80 hours of carding and combing respectively. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">D. Bought in Yarn Cost Reduction</head><p n="p15.21"><s n="s1.4;p15.21">Situation <hi rend="bold">3</hi> shows that a 20% discount in the cost of bought in yarn reduces the overall costs by £756 and that sufficient bought in yarn to produce 180m of cloth per week is required. </s><s n="s2.4;p15.21">Situation <hi rend="bold">9</hi> shows that if a new supplier can supply yarn at 30% cheaper than the existing supplier, 500m of cloth should be supplied to the customer using equal amounts of internally produced and bought in yarn. </s><s n="s3.4;p15.21">This combination represents a decrease in costs of £1155. </s><s n="s4.4;p15.21">However, this supplier is known to be less reliable than the existing supplier so A-Z Cloth UK should proceed with caution and research this supplier before considering switching. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">E. Rises in Fibre Costs</head><p n="p16.21"><s n="s1.3;p16.21">Assuming that the cost of buying in yarn stays at £21 to produce 1m of cloth, a rise in fibre costs of £1 will have no effect on the amount of yarn produced internally. </s><s n="s2.3;p16.21">The overall cost of supplying 500m of cloth would increase to £8900. </s><s n="s3.3;p16.21">Table 1 shows that situations <hi rend="bold">6, 7, 8</hi> and <hi rend="bold">10</hi> also incorporate an increase in fibre costs, and thus increased overall costs of supplying 500m of cloth. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">F. Increasing the Amount Supplied to the Customer</head><p n="p17.21"><s n="s1.5;p17.21">Situations <hi rend="bold">11</hi> from table 1 shows that 640m of cloth can be supplied to the customer, 320m from internal yarn and 320m from bought in yarn, at a cost of £11,520 or £18.00 per metre of cloth. </s><s n="s2.5;p17.21">Supplying 500m of cloth at the same costs (situation <hi rend="bold">1</hi>) equates to £17.16 per metre. </s><s n="s3.5;p17.21">Assuming that A-Z Cloth charges the same price per metre of cloth, profit will be 84p less per metre when supplying 640m compared to 500m. </s><s n="s4.5;p17.21">Situation <hi rend="bold">12</hi> shows that 640m of cloth could be supplied at a cost of £15.90 per metre compared to situation <hi rend="bold">3</hi> where 500m is supplied at a cost of £15.65 per metre. </s><s n="s5.5;p17.21">Situation <hi rend="bold">13</hi> shows that a maximum of 680m of cloth can be supplied at £18.00 per metre but this excludes the cost of acquiring the extra carding and combing capacity. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">G. Observations and Advice</head><p rend="bulleted" n="p18.21"><s n="s1.1;p18.21">When increasing the amount of yarn produced internally through increased carding and combing capacity the department should realise any possible overtime costs related to overtime required to increase output, into the price paid for extra carding and combing capacity. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p19.21"><s n="s1.1;p19.21">Throughout the report it has been assumed that hours available in Vat A and Vat B are interchangeable. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p20.21"><s n="s1.1;p20.21">Only information provided has been considered, implications on staffing and other business areas should be considered by the department. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p21.21"><s n="s1.1;p21.21">No recommendations have been made on the price that the A-Z Cloth UK should charge the customer. </s></p></div2></div1></body><back><div1 type="appendix"><head rend="bold">Appendix</head><p/></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
