<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_0169c" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Marketing Analysis 2004-2005</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">The document has a title page which contains:
document title
title part</note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">Language used in quote: <foreign id="English">English</foreign></note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">deleted: footer: page numbers</note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">deleted: Word Count = 2,998 </note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">appendix: graphs and calculations</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">2</p><p n="date">2005-02</p><p n="module title">Marketing Analysis</p><p n="module code">IB3850</p><p n="genre family">Case study</p><p n="discipline">Business</p><p n="disciplinary group">SS</p><p n="grade">M</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">3198</p><p n="number of s-units">151</p><p n="number of p">51</p><p n="number of tables">4</p><p n="number of figures">7</p><p n="number of block quotes">3</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">6</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">0</p><p n="abstract present">abstract present</p><p n="average words per s-unit">21.2</p><p n="average s-units per p">3.0</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">m</p><p n="year of birth">1984</p><p n="first language">English</p><p n="education">UKA</p><p n="course">Management Science</p><p n="student ID">0169</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><titlePart rend="bold">Marketing Analysis 2004-2005 (IB3850 &amp; IB2090) Spring Term Assessment</titlePart><docTitle><titlePart rend="bold">Report for the attention of company Chief Executive Office (CEO)</titlePart></docTitle><titlePart><hi rend="bold">Prepared by: Student ID - </hi><name type="student ID"/><hi rend="bold"> Industry - Conquest Team - U </hi></titlePart></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="abstract"><head rend="bold">EXECUTIVE SUMMARY</head><p n="p1.51"><s n="s1.2;p1.51">Company U's aim was to achieve sufficient sales in the Sonite market during the initial periods to produce 2 Vodites as quickly as possible. </s><s n="s2.2;p1.51">We aimed to be first to market with a Vodite product to benefit from the advantages of this policy; "A sometimes insurmountable advantage gained by the first significant company to move into a new market"<ref target="BAWE_0169c-ftnote.001"/> Our Sonite products were not ideally targeted to any segments and thus other factors of the marketing mix where to used to drive sales. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0169c-ftnote.001"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1"><seg type="URL" n="http://www.marketingterms.com/dictionary/first_mover_advantage/"/> [accessed February 7th 2005] </s></p></note></div1><div1 type="front-back-matter"><head rend="bold">CONTENTS</head><p/></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold"> CURRENT COMPANY POSITION</head><p n="p2.51"><s n="s1.1;p2.51">The company position will be analysed mainly on the basis of 4 Key Performance Indicators; Market Share, Retail Sales, Contribution and Shareholder Value (SPI and ROI). </s></p><div2><head rend="underlined bold italic">Financial</head><p n="p3.51"><s n="s1.3;p3.51">Share Price Index (SPI) is considered the most important financial measure and is currently 2,286, placing the firm 2 <hi rend="sup">nd</hi>. </s><s n="s2.3;p3.51">Figure 1 shows how company U had the highest SPI until period 6. </s><s n="s3.3;p3.51">A high SPI in period 4 and 5 (peak of 3153) was due to 100% dominance in the Vodite market. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0169c-fig.001"><head><hi rend="italic">Figure 1:</hi> SPI over time</head></figure><p n="p4.51"><s n="s1.3;p4.51">Return on Investment (ROI) has grown 54.7% from period 0 (4.27) but is half of the leading company (E - 8.24). </s><s n="s2.3;p4.51">Cumulative Net Contribution is the highest in the industry at $420,151,000 but mainly due to significant earlier success. $75,721,000 was generated in period 7. </s><s n="s3.3;p4.51">Figure 2 show that contribution by brand has increased over 7 periods, and the current level of $15,144,000 is up 100.8% from period 1. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0169c-fig.002"><head><hi rend="italic">Figure 2:</hi> Net contribution by brand over time</head></figure></div2><div2><head rend="underlined bold italic">Market</head><p n="p5.51"><s n="s1.1;p5.51">Overall market share is currently 25.4%, up 14.4% from period 0 and figure 3 shows how we sit roughly equal distance from the market leader, and the other companies. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0169c-fig.003"><head><hi rend="italic">Figure 3:</hi> Firms market share by retail sales</head></figure><p n="p6.51"><s n="s1.3;p6.51">The total market grew 256.9% but growth of Total retail sales was 309.4% from $69,757,000 in period 0 to $285,609,000 in period 7. </s><s n="s2.3;p6.51">Figure 4 shows 4 brands are in growth segments but range from strong to weak positions. </s><s n="s3.3;p6.51">SULI sits favourably in an ageing segment. </s></p><table id="BAWE_0169c-tab.001"><head><hi rend="italic">Figure</hi> 4 D Little business profile matrix (Chisnall)</head><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p7.51"><s n="s1.8;p7.51">Graph 1 in the appendix shows that VULI, VUDU and SULI are the main contributors to company profits. </s><s n="s2.8;p7.51">Using Levitt's<ref target="BAWE_0169c-ftnote.002"/> ideas of product classification SUSI is 'yesterday's winner' (now contributing little to corporate earnings). </s><s n="s3.8;p7.51">SULI and VULI are 'today's providers' (backbone of corporate profitability). </s><s n="s4.8;p7.51">VUSI is 'tomorrow's hopeful' (sales performance suggest good future profitability) and VUDU is a combination of both. </s><s n="s5.8;p7.51">The BCG Matrix (figure 5) shows that SULI and SUSI show 'dog' characteristics, low market share in low growth segments. </s><s n="s6.8;p7.51">Vodites in the Followers segment show 'problem child' characteristics, having relatively low market share but targeting a high growth segment. </s><s n="s7.8;p7.51">VULI and VUDU in the Adopters and Innovators segments show characteristics of both 'dogs' and 'problem children'. </s><s n="s8.8;p7.51">It would desirable to have products in the 'star performer' and then 'cash cow' segments. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0169c-ftnote.002"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Chisnall, Peter M, <hi rend="italic">Strategic Business Marketing 3rd Edition pg 187</hi> </s></p></note><figure id="BAWE_0169c-fig.004"><head><hi rend="italic">Figure 5:</hi> Boston Consulting Growth Share Matrix. Source: Markstrat3</head></figure><div3><head rend="bold italic">1) Sonites</head><p n="p8.51"><s n="s1.5;p8.51">There are 5 segments; Buffs, Singles, Professionals, HiEarners and Others. </s><s n="s2.5;p8.51">Current retail market is share 8.2%, down from period 0 by 22.2%. </s><s n="s3.5;p8.51">Retail sales have decreased 22.1% $54,373,000. </s><s n="s4.5;p8.51">Graph 2 (appendix) shows how contributions of SULI and SUSI increased until period 3 when the resources were allocated to the launch of Vodites, and hence sales suffered. </s><s n="s5.5;p8.51">The net contribution is currently $15,116,000. </s></p><div4><head rend="bold">SUSI</head><p n="p9.51"><s n="s1.8;p9.51">Retail market share is at a low of 0.8% equating to retail sales of $5,018,000. </s><s n="s2.8;p9.51">Net contribution has been positive apart from period 5, currently standing at $53,000 down 97.5% from period 0. </s><s n="s3.8;p9.51">The performance of SUSI has been disappointing over the 7 periods as it wasn't ideally suited to either of its target segments, Singles and Others. </s><s n="s4.8;p9.51">The Singles segment is estimated at 776,000 and will be approximately 831,000 in 1 period's time. </s><s n="s5.8;p9.51">The Others segment is slightly larger at 781,000 and is due to grow to 885,000 by the next period. </s><s n="s6.8;p9.51">SUSI competes with SAFE and SEXY (segment market leader) in the Singles market, and SAMA, SIII (segment market leader) and SONG in the Others market but has lower market shares. </s><s n="s7.8;p9.51">SUSI has 3.1% of the Others market, 0.4% of the Buffs, Singles and HiEarners and 0.1% of the Professionals market. </s><s n="s8.8;p9.51">In period 0 SUSI had 16.3% and 7.6% of the Others and Singles markets. </s></p></div4><div4><head rend="bold">b) SULI</head><p n="p10.51"><s n="s1.8;p10.51">SULI has performed better than SUSI, but badly compared with rival brands. </s><s n="s2.8;p10.51">Retail market share is 7.4% down 18.5% from period 0. </s><s n="s3.8;p10.51">This equates to retail sales of $49,355,000, down from period 0 by 14.9%. </s><s n="s4.8;p10.51">As graph 2 (appendix) shows, the net contribution was particularly strong in periods 2 and 3 and is currently $15,063,000, an increase of 14.0% from period 0. </s><s n="s5.8;p10.51">SULI showed initial signs of growth in the early periods but sales have since declined as resources were concentrated on the launch of Vodites. </s><s n="s6.8;p10.51">SULI's targeted at Professionals (segment, 293,000) and HiEarners (segment, 221,000). </s><s n="s7.8;p10.51">Brand awareness for both these segments has decreased over the previous 4 periods and stands at 69.1% for Professionals and 75.7% for HiEarners. </s><s n="s8.8;p10.51">In the Professionals segment market share is 14.3% where it competes with SEMI (segment leader) and SOLD. In the HiEarners segment SULI's main competition is SOUL (segment leader), SOLD and SEMI. SULI has 24.3% market share here. </s></p></div4></div3><div3><head rend="bold">2) <hi rend="italic">Vodites</hi></head><p n="p11.51"><s n="s1.4;p11.51">There are 3 segments; Innovators, Adopters and Followers. </s><s n="s2.4;p11.51">Retail sales are $231,256,000, a market share of 50.0%. </s><s n="s3.4;p11.51">Although market share has decreased from period 4 retail sales have 113.0%. </s><s n="s4.4;p11.51">The market is estimated to grow 67.0% to 1,129,000 by period 8. </s></p><div4><head rend="bold">a) VUSI</head><p n="p12.51"><s n="s1.8;p12.51">Since period 4, unit sales have increased 140.5% to 43,286. </s><s n="s2.8;p12.51">Retail sales have also increased, by 98.6% to $24,504,000. </s><s n="s3.8;p12.51">By unit sales market share is 6.4% and retail market share is 5.3%. </s><s n="s4.8;p12.51">Net contribution was initially negative but has increased to $2,352,000. </s><s n="s5.8;p12.51">The number of sales force has roughly doubled to 35 in a drive to dominate the embryonic market. </s><s n="s6.8;p12.51">VUSI is targeted at Followers in a segment size of 232,000. </s><s n="s7.8;p12.51">Brand awareness here has increased 115.8% since period 4 to 39.5%. </s><s n="s8.8;p12.51">VUSI competes with VENA (segment leader), VIRA, VULI and VUDU and has 17.2% of the follower segment. </s></p></div4><div4><head rend="bold">VULI</head><p n="p13.51"><s n="s1.9;p13.51">From period 4, retail sales have only increased 0.9% to $97,092,000. </s><s n="s2.9;p13.51">Greatest sales were in period 5 when we monopolised the market. </s><s n="s3.9;p13.51">Market share is 21.0% by retail sales. </s><s n="s4.9;p13.51">Net contribution has stayed positive in all periods but has decreased 8.2% from period 4 to $30,566,000. </s><s n="s5.9;p13.51">Although targeted at Innovators and Adopters, sales in the Followers segment have been impressive. </s><s n="s6.9;p13.51">Market share in these 3 segments is 26.1%, 18.0% and 20.9%. </s><s n="s7.9;p13.51">Brand awareness is fairly even across the 3 segments although slightly higher in the Followers segment, 63.0%. </s><s n="s8.9;p13.51">Adopters brand awareness increased most since period 4, 303.4%. </s><s n="s9.9;p13.51">VULI's 2 main competitors are VENA (segment leader) and VUDU. </s></p></div4><div4><head rend="bold">VUDU</head><p n="p14.51"><s n="s1.3;p14.51">Period 7 was a successful first period, but production was not sufficient to meet demand. </s><s n="s2.3;p14.51">By being more tailored to particular segments and enjoying a considerable advertising budget and sales force retail sales was $109,659,000. </s><s n="s3.3;p14.51">Targeted at Innovators and Adopters, VUDU achieved higher levels of brand awareness (36.3% and 33.6 respectively) than any other Vodite in its first period. </s></p></div4></div3></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">FUTURE MARKETING STRATEGY </head><p n="p15.51"><s n="s1.4;p15.51">Porter stated that 'The essence of formulating competitive strategy is relating a company to its environment'<ref target="BAWE_0169c-ftnote.003"/>. </s><s n="s2.4;p15.51">Marketing strategy can also be defined as "one that encompasses the selection and analysis of a target market and the creation and maintenance of an appropriate marketing mix that will satisfy those people in the target market"<ref target="BAWE_0169c-ftnote.004"/>. </s><s n="s3.4;p15.51">What stage products are in the product life cycle, the financial resources available, strength competition and market position both short and long term are important considerations<ref target="BAWE_0169c-ftnote.005"/>. </s><s n="s4.4;p15.51">A SWOT analysis of Company U is useful starting block. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0169c-ftnote.003"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Porter, M. E. , <hi rend="italic">Competitive Strategy,</hi> Macmillan, New York, 1980 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0169c-ftnote.004"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Dibb, Simkin, Pride and Ferrell, <hi rend="italic"> Marketing; Concepts and Strategies</hi> pg 16 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0169c-ftnote.005"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Chisnall, Peter M. , <hi rend="italic">Strategic Business Marketing</hi>, pg 177 </s></p></note><list type="bulleted"><head rend="italic">Strengths</head><item>The largest budget for the next period</item><item>A large presence in the Vodite market</item><item>Recently launched Vodite that is well tailored to its target segment</item></list><list type="bulleted"><head rend="italic">Weaknesses</head><item>Relatively low purchase intentions of Vodite products </item><item>Characteristics of Sonites </item><item>High VULI inventory </item><item>SULI is targeted at 2 shrinking segments</item></list><list type="bulleted"><head rend="italic">Opportunities</head><item>The Innovators and Adopters market for VUDU sales</item><item>Growing Singles and Others markets for SUSI (once modified)</item></list><list type="bulleted"><head rend="italic">Threats</head><item>Well tailored and financed VENA brand </item><item>VIRA's more desirable maximum frequency for the followers segment</item></list><p n="p16.51"><s n="s1.2;p16.51">SWOT analysis tells us that a strategy is required that will improve the saleability of Sonites and guard against threats in the Vodite market. </s><s n="s2.2;p16.51">The 'marketing mix' popularly known as the 4 P's; product, price, promotion and place, will be the framework for strategy development. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0169c-fig.005"><head><hi rend="italic">Figure 7:</hi> Facets of marketing strategy. Source, Chisnall</head></figure><div2><head>1.<hi rend="italic"> Product Range Strategy</hi></head><p n="p17.51"><s n="s1.2;p17.51">We aim to develop new products, eliminate unprofitable products and improve existing products to give better satisfaction to customers. </s><s n="s2.2;p17.51">2 frameworks that aid this process are the product/market matrix and product life cycle (PLC). </s></p><p n="p18.51"><s n="s1.1;p18.51">Ansoff's<ref target="BAWE_0169c-ftnote.006"/> matrix (figure 8) enables companies to assess their market situation and decide on a future strategy for products. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0169c-ftnote.006"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Ansoff, H. Igor, <hi rend="italic">Strategies for diversification,</hi> Harvard Business Review, vol. 35, no. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">5, 1957 </s></p></note><table id="BAWE_0169c-tab.002"><head><hi rend="italic">Figure 8:</hi> Product/market matrix (Source: Chisnall</head><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p19.51"><s n="s1.1;p19.51">Applying this framework, a company may do the following: </s></p><list type="ordered"><item>1) Market penetration </item><item>2) Market development </item><item>3) Product development </item><item>4) Diversification</item></list><p n="p20.51"><s n="s1.1;p20.51">What stage a product life is in the product life cycle (figure 9) is important when determining strategy for that product. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0169c-fig.006"><head><hi rend="italic">Figure 9:</hi> The Product Life Cycle (source: Dibb et al)</head></figure><quote lang="English">"The long-term health of an organisation depends on having some products that generate cash and provide acceptable profits, plus others that use cash to support growth." <ref target="BAWE_0169c-ftnote.007"/></quote><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0169c-ftnote.007"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Dibb, Simkin, Pride, Ferrell., <hi rend="italic">Marketing; Concepts and Strategies</hi> p.674 </s></p></note><p n="p21.51"><s n="s1.1;p21.51">Thus having products at different stages in the product life cycle is essential for the long-term success. </s></p><p n="p22.51"><s n="s1.3;p22.51">Figure X Product Life Cycle. </s><s n="s2.3;p22.51">Source: Dibb et alSUSI sales have declined each period since period 2 so is in the decline stage of the product life cycle<ref target="BAWE_0169c-ftnote.008"/>. </s><s n="s3.3;p22.51">Faced with a failing product there management may make 3 choices.<ref target="BAWE_0169c-ftnote.009"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0169c-ftnote.008"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Dibb, Simkin, Pride and Ferrell, <hi rend="italic"> Marketing; Concepts and Strategies</hi> pg 256 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0169c-ftnote.009"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Baker, M J <hi rend="italic">Marketing Strategy and Management</hi> p.109 </s></p></note><list type="ordered"><item>a) Abandon - withdraw the product</item><item>b) Withdrawal - slowly phase the product out </item><item>c) Resuscitation - revive the product through modifications</item></list><p n="p23.51"><s n="s1.3;p23.51">As SUSI isn't well suited to either of its target segments, it is suggested the product be withdrawn next period, and new Sonite, SUDU introduced. </s><s n="s2.3;p23.51">A R&amp;D project PSUDU is currently underway. </s><s n="s3.3;p23.51">SUDU will be solely targeted at Others as part of a 'niche' strategy. </s></p><p n="p24.51"><s n="s1.4;p24.51">SULI is in the decline stage of the product life cycle but makes a healthy contribution. </s><s n="s2.4;p24.51">Its target segments are in decline and are the 3 <hi rend="sup">rd</hi> and 4 <hi rend="sup">th</hi> largest segments. </s><s n="s3.4;p24.51">A niche market strategy should be adopted to modify SULI so it appeals to just Professionals as it has values that are more desirable them and is a greater segment size now, and long term. </s><s n="s4.4;p24.51">If modification is unfeasible a defensive strategy should be adopted to protect market share by manipulation of non-product elements of the marketing mix. </s></p><p n="p25.51"><s n="s1.4;p25.51">VULI and VUSI are in the growth stage of the product life cycle. </s><s n="s2.4;p25.51">However modifying these products may increase their appeal to their target segments. </s><s n="s3.4;p25.51">For example VUSI has a maximum frequency of 7 (the characteristic ranked second most important after price by Followers) but the value that gives Followers the greatest utility is 12. </s><s n="s4.4;p25.51">VULI should be modified to suit Innovators. </s></p><p n="p26.51"><s n="s1.2;p26.51">VUDU is in the introduction stage of the product life cycle and hence needs time to settle before any modifications are made. </s><s n="s2.2;p26.51">VUDU values hold appeal to Innovators and Early Adopters. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="italic">2. Pricing Strategy</head><quote lang="English">"Pricing is a critical element in the overall marketing strategy: it is one of the most difficult tasks facing management." <ref target="BAWE_0169c-ftnote.010"/></quote><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0169c-ftnote.010"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Chisnall, Peter M, <hi rend="italic">Strategic Business Marketing,</hi> pg 188 </s></p></note><p n="p27.51"><s n="s1.1;p27.51">Figure 10 shows that is not necessarily the lowest priced product that achieves greatest market share. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0169c-fig.007"><head rend="italic">Figure 10</head></figure><p n="p28.51"><s n="s1.2;p28.51">Strategy will be based on 'contribution pricing'<ref target="BAWE_0169c-ftnote.011"/> with sensitivity to marketing studies (e.g. conjoint analysis). </s><s n="s2.2;p28.51">We shall bear in mind that "Care should be taken not to make price the overriding Competitive Factor"<ref target="BAWE_0169c-ftnote.012"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0169c-ftnote.011"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Chisnall, Peter M, <hi rend="italic">Strategic Business Marketing,</hi> pg 191 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0169c-ftnote.012"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Lancaster, G. Massingham, L. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">(1997) Essentials of Marketing 2nd ed pg 213 </s></p></note><p n="p29.51"><s n="s1.3;p29.51">SUSI is to be withdrawn next period and replaced by SUDU. A 'penetration pricing' strategy would be initially appropriate to obtain enough market share to justify production. </s><s n="s2.3;p29.51">Pricing analysis in the appendix shows that a RRP of $205 should be set for its first period of production. </s><s n="s3.3;p29.51">Long term sales would have to increase so that the product makes a significant positive contribution. </s></p><p n="p30.51"><s n="s1.2;p30.51">SULI's RRP should be increased to $490 so it appeals more to Professionals as part of the niche strategy to concentrate on one target segment. </s><s n="s2.2;p30.51">It will also sell at the 'going rate' (competitive parity), which is considered a prudent strategy. </s></p><p n="p31.51"><s n="s1.2;p31.51">Messages from production indicate the VUSI sales weren't maximised in period 7 and thus lowering the RRP by $20 (to make the product more appealing to Followers) should not have an adverse affect on revenues. </s><s n="s2.2;p31.51">Pricing analysis (appendix) shows that were sales to increase to 50,000units next period, the average selling price must be $325 for the product to breakeven. </s></p><p n="p32.51"><s n="s1.2;p32.51">VULI and VUDU should have different RRPs so that 'cannibalisation', whereby "brand sales are being achieved at the expense of another brand"<ref target="BAWE_0169c-ftnote.013"/> does not occur. </s><s n="s2.2;p32.51">Pricing analysis (appendix) shows VULI must have a minimum average selling price of $212 ceteris paribus<ref target="BAWE_0169c-ftnote.014"/> for net contribution to stay positive. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0169c-ftnote.013"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Stapleton, J. Hart, N. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">(1987) Glossary of Marketing Terms 3rd ed pg 30 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0169c-ftnote.014"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">"All other influencing factors are held constant". </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">Source, <seg type="URL" n="http://www.bized.ac.uk/cgi-bin/glossarydb/browse.pl?glostopic=0&amp;glosid=58"/> </s></p></note><p n="p33.51"><s n="s1.4;p33.51">If VUDU sales increase e.g. to 160,000 the minimum average selling price could be $288. </s><s n="s2.4;p33.51">VUDU's RRP should be decreased over the next 3 periods by roughly $50 to make it more appealing to Innovators, to which it is better suited. </s><s n="s3.4;p33.51">VULI's RRP should also be decreased over the next 3 periods by approximately $50 thus making it more appealing to Early Adopters. </s><s n="s4.4;p33.51">This would avoid product 'cannibalisation' and is a positioning policy of 'competitive pricing'. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="italic">3. Promotional Strategy</head><p n="p34.51"><s n="s1.1;p34.51">Empirical observations suggest firms should base a promotional budget on 5 characteristics; percentage sales, competitive parity, budget, fixed sum per unit and objectives.<ref target="BAWE_0169c-ftnote.015"/> Our strategy is to remain competitive with our rivals and to use the budget effectively while maximising ROI. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0169c-ftnote.015"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Baker, J. Michael. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">(2000) <hi rend="italic">Marketing Strategy and Management 3rd edition,</hi> Macmillan pg 425 </s></p></note><p n="p35.51"><s n="s1.3;p35.51">Advertising expenditures should be kept constant for SULI as the advertising experiment in the market studies shows no discernible increase in market share as a result of increased spending. </s><s n="s2.3;p35.51">However once product modification has occurred, SULI should receive an increase in advertising expenditure to increase brand awareness and create brand loyalty. </s><s n="s3.3;p35.51">Once SUDU is launched it should benefit from a similar advertising expenditure to SIII ($2.2m) which is also targeted at Others. </s></p><p n="p36.51"><s n="s1.2;p36.51">An aggressive promotional strategy to increase brand awareness across target segments and create brand loyalty should be adopted in the Vodite market to stimulate primary demand for and secondary demand for VULI, VUSI and VUDU. The advertising budgets should be increased 20% for the next period and 10% for the following 2 periods if this is economically viable and is seen to be increasing sales. </s><s n="s2.2;p36.51">This should help to offset competitor actions and promote Vodite brands<ref target="BAWE_0169c-ftnote.016"/>. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0169c-ftnote.016"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">adapted from Dibb et al (2000) </s></p></note></div2><div2><head rend="italic">4. Selling and Distribution Strategy (Place)</head><quote lang="English">"Consumption is a function of availability"<ref target="BAWE_0169c-ftnote.017"/>. </quote><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0169c-ftnote.017"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Baker, J Michael, <hi rend="italic">Marketing Strategy and Management,</hi> pg 395 </s></p></note><p n="p37.51"><s n="s1.1;p37.51">Making sure that production is sufficient for demand and supply is distributed through the correct channels is important for success over the next 3 periods. </s></p><p n="p38.51"><s n="s1.4;p38.51">Half of the 40 SUDU sales force should be distributed to mass merchandising as this is where 52% of Others sales occur. </s><s n="s2.4;p38.51">35% and 15% in department and speciality stores respectively. </s><s n="s3.4;p38.51">The targeted segments should be 80% for Others and 5% for all other segments. </s><s n="s4.4;p38.51">Assuming 15% of the Others segment can be taken in SUDU's first period, 130,000 units should be produced. </s></p><p n="p39.51"><s n="s1.4;p39.51">SULI production needs monitoring to make sure inventory does not exist if the product is to be modified. </s><s n="s2.4;p39.51">SULI sales force effort should show bias towards distribution channels favoured by Professionals. </s><s n="s3.4;p39.51">Numbers should be increased in Mass Merchandising stores were shopping habits is over 30%. </s><s n="s4.4;p39.51">Sales force figures should be increased by 10 across each channel over 3 periods, as suggested by the sales force experiment. </s></p><p n="p40.51"><s n="s1.2;p40.51">For VULI to target the Innovators, it should be distributed mainly through Speciality Stores with a transfer of 10 staff from Mass Merchandise to increase the sales force figures here. </s><s n="s2.2;p40.51">The sales force experiment also suggests that increasing sales force figures across each distribution by 10 and this should be done over 3 periods. </s></p><p n="p41.51"><s n="s1.1;p41.51">Followers show a tendency to Mass Merchandise in their shopping habits and thus sales force effort should be greatest here for VUSI. Over half of Early Adopters shop in Speciality stores and this should be represented by the VUDU sales force figures here. </s></p><p n="p42.51"><s n="s1.1;p42.51">A summary of current sales force numbers and what is desired is figure 11 below. </s></p><table id="BAWE_0169c-tab.003"><head><hi rend="italic">Figure 11:</hi> Sales force distributions * SUSI to be withdrawn</head><row><cell/></row></table></div2><div2><head rend="bold">Period 8 Budget </head><p n="p43.51"><s n="s1.1;p43.51">Period 8 budget calculations (appendix) shows that the desired spending increases are feasible. </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">LESSONS LEARNED</head><p n="p44.51"><s n="s1.2;p44.51">Our behaviour and rationale for decisions evolved as we further understood the tools at our disposal and enhanced our knowledge of effective marketing. </s><s n="s2.2;p44.51">The following lessons were learned. </s></p><div2><head rend="italic">1. First to market</head><p n="p45.51"><s n="s1.2;p45.51">Being first to market with a Vodite product was crucial in building strong sales and a position to compete with new entrants. </s><s n="s2.2;p45.51">Vodite sales make an important contribution to the overall position. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="italic">2. Anticipating competitors</head><p n="p46.51"><s n="s1.3;p46.51">2 periods of unchallenged Vodite sales led to complacency in our pricing strategy and lack of anticipation of new entrants. </s><s n="s2.3;p46.51">Thus we lost significant Vodite market share. </s><s n="s3.3;p46.51">One cannot stand still in the marketing world as competitors are always trying to stay one step ahead </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="italic">3. Using marketing information</head><p n="p47.51"><s n="s1.2;p47.51">It was soon realised that buying market studies must be justified otherwise they were an inefficient use of funds. </s><s n="s2.2;p47.51">Conversely maximising the benefits of purchased studies was crucial in staying ahead of competition and making brand decisions e.g. product modifications, pricing etc. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="italic">4. Flexibility to market changes</head><p n="p48.51"><s n="s1.4;p48.51">Reacting quickly and effectively to changes in the market was crucial to maintain the market position. </s><s n="s2.4;p48.51">For example when forecasts show rapid segment growth, ensuring you have sufficient production to meet demand. </s><s n="s3.4;p48.51">Occasionally production levels of Vodites were not sufficient to meet demand. </s><s n="s4.4;p48.51">Flexibility to change is also linked with the effective use of market information. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="italic">5. Facets of advertising</head><p n="p49.51"><s n="s1.1;p49.51">It was learned that throwing money at advertising will not always increase sales and that other facets such as brand reputation, type of communication and relationships with customers are important methods of gaining sales. </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">CONCLUSIONS </head><p n="p50.51"><s n="s1.6;p50.51">By retail market share we started as the 3 <hi rend="sup">rd</hi> ranked company and finished as the 2 <hi rend="sup">nd</hi> ranked. </s><s n="s2.6;p50.51">We aimed to be first to market for Vodites with the knowledge that "To lead the market you must take risks and make competitors follow"<ref target="BAWE_0169c-ftnote.018"/>. </s><s n="s3.6;p50.51">By concentrating efforts on Vodites, Sonite sales suffered. </s><s n="s4.6;p50.51">We have a strategy improve Sonite sales through better segment targeting (a new product) and product modification. </s><s n="s5.6;p50.51">We aim to ensure that the marketing mix we deploy is continually up-dated in order to serve customers' changing needs and differing growth rates of target segments. </s><s n="s6.6;p50.51">Figure 12 shows our aim of better market segmentation. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0169c-ftnote.018"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Davidson, H (1997) <hi rend="italic">Even More Offensive Marketing</hi> , London: Penguin, pg 109 </s></p></note><table id="BAWE_0169c-tab.004"><head><hi rend="italic">Figure 11:</hi> Targeted segments</head><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p51.51"><s n="s1.1;p51.51">I would like to thank my project team for their excellent work and thank our shareholders for their continued support in our company. </s></p></div1></body><back><div1 type="bibliography"><head rend="bold">BIBLIOGRAPHY</head><div2 type="bibliography"><head rend="bold">Books</head><p>Baker, M J., (2000) <hi rend="italic">Marketing Strategy and Management 3rd Edition,</hi> Macmillan</p><p>Chisnall, Peter M, (1995), <hi rend="italic">Strategic Business Marketing 3rd Edition,</hi> Prentice Hall</p><p>Davidson, H, (1997), <hi rend="italic">Even More Offensive Marketing,</hi> London: Penguin</p><p>Dibb, Simkin, Pride, Ferrell, (2001) <hi rend="italic">Marketing; Concepts and Strategies 4th European Edition,</hi> Houghton Mifflin </p><p>Financial Times, (1999), <hi rend="italic">Mastering Marketing</hi>, Prentice Hall</p><p>Gatignon, Hubert and Larreche, Jean-Claude, <hi rend="italic">Markstrat3,</hi> StratX </p><p>Lancaster, Geoff and Massingham, Lester, (1993), <hi rend="italic">Essentials of Marketing</hi>, McGraw Hill</p><p>Stapleton, J. Hart, N. (1987), <hi rend="italic">Glossary of Marketing Terms 3rd Edition,</hi></p><p>Walker, Boyd, Larreche, (1996) <hi rend="italic">Marketing Strategy: planning and implementation,</hi> Irwin</p></div2><div2 type="bibliography"><head rend="bold">Journals</head><p>Goldsmith, Ronald E, (1999), The personalised marketplace: beyond the 4Ps, <hi rend="italic">Marketing Intelligence &amp; Planning</hi> [online], 17 (4), pg 178-185. Available from <seg type="URL" n="http://0-hermia.emeraldinsight.com.pugwash.lib"/>.<name type="university"/>.ac.uk/vl=7706474/cl=28/nw=1/rpsv/~1179/v17n4/s1/p178 [Accessed on 5th February 2005]</p><p>Greenley, Gordon E, (1989), An Understanding of Marketing Strategy<hi rend="italic">, European Journal of Marketing</hi> [online], 23 (8). Available from <seg type="URL" n="http://0-thesius.emeraldinsight.com.pugwash.lib"/>.<name type="university"/>.ac.uk/vl=9010729/cl=33/nw=1/rpsv/~1168/v23n8/s3/p0 [Accessed 5th February 2005]</p><p>Piercy, Nigel F. (2002), Market-Led Strategic Change: New Marketing for New Realities, <hi rend="italic">The Marketing Review,</hi> 2, pages 383-404</p></div2><div2 type="bibliography"><head rend="bold">Websites</head><p><seg type="URL" n="http://www.marketingterms.com/dictionary/"/> [accessed February 7<hi rend="sup">th</hi>-15<hi rend="sup">th</hi> 2005]</p><p><seg type="URL" n="http://www.market-modelling.co.uk/"/> [accessed February 8<hi rend="sup">th</hi> 2005]</p><p><seg type="URL" n="http://www.bized.ac.uk/cgi-bin/glossarydb/browse.pl?glostopic=0&amp;glosid=58"/> [accessed February 14<hi rend="sup">th</hi> 2005]</p></div2></div1><div1 type="appendix"><head rend="bold">APPENDIX</head><p/></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
