<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_0169g" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>A structured introduction to Costcutter: performance objectives and operational design.</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">deleted: footer: page numbers
</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">2</p><p n="date">2005-04</p><p n="module title">Operations Management</p><p n="module code">IB3410</p><p n="genre family">Critique</p><p n="discipline">Business</p><p n="disciplinary group">SS</p><p n="grade">D</p><p n="number of authors">6</p><p n="number of words">3335</p><p n="number of s-units">139</p><p n="number of p">23</p><p n="number of tables">0</p><p n="number of figures">1</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">0</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">0</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">24.0</p><p n="average s-units per p">6.0</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">m</p><p n="year of birth">1984</p><p n="first language">English</p><p n="education">UKA</p><p n="course">Management Science</p><p n="student ID">0169</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front/><body><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">Part 1 - A structured introduction to Costcutter: performance objectives and operational design. </head><p n="p1.23"><s n="s1.8;p1.23">Costcutter Supermarkets Group Ltd was founded in 1986 and is a group that operates franchises of small supermarkets. </s><s n="s2.8;p1.23">It has 1200 stores across the UK, one of which is The University of <name type="university"/> campus store (the focus of this assignment and from now referred to as 'the store'). </s><s n="s3.8;p1.23">The store was opened in 1998, employs 30 staff in total with 2 full time managers and has a yearly turnover of £4.1million. </s><s n="s4.8;p1.23">It occupies a space of 5000sqft, with further storage of 500sqft. </s><s n="s5.8;p1.23">The university provides a target market of 15,536 students and 4,354 staff during term time<ref target="BAWE_0169g-ftnote.001"/>, with conference delegates and staff the target market out of term time. </s><s n="s6.8;p1.23">The store supplies household names in conjunction with 270 own brand Costcutter lines, a total of 5,297 product lines. </s><s n="s7.8;p1.23">It operates by outsourcing 56% of product lines through its strategic alliance with Nisa Today's, the UK's largest buying group for independent retail and wholesale companies. </s><s n="s8.8;p1.23">The other 44% of product lines come from 48 small suppliers with whom Costcutter have developed individual relationships. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0169g-ftnote.001"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">From <seg type="URL" n="http://www2.warwick.ac.uk/about/profile/people/"/> [accessed April 7, 2005] </s></p></note><p n="p2.23"><s n="s1.3;p2.23">The 'corporate strategy' is based on four principles. </s><s n="s2.3;p2.23">They aim to provide grocery-led neighbourhood stores, adopt a competitive pricing policy, a strong promotional programme and a product range that includes a substantial grocery provision.<ref target="BAWE_0169g-ftnote.002"/> The 'business strategy' for the store adopts these principles but adapts them to fit in with location specific factors, such as varying levels of demand, a large ethnic population and high competition from nearby stores. </s><s n="s3.3;p2.23">It does not compete directly with companies such as Tesco (at the nearby Cannon Park Shopping Centre) on price, but aims to offer availability of products at key times, with niche items such as Halal products and food items from many ethnic origins. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0169g-ftnote.002"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">From <seg type="URL" n="http://www.costcutter.com/cgrowthset.htm"/> [accessed April 7, 2005] </s></p></note><p n="p3.23"><s n="s1.3;p3.23">All operations require a tightly defined set of objectives that relate specifically to the simple aim of satisfying customer needs. </s><s n="s2.3;p3.23">The five performance objectives are; cost, dependability, flexibility, quality. </s><s n="s3.3;p3.23">For operations to excel a company must assess their relative importance; a polar diagram of the store's performance objectives is shown right. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0169g-fig.001"><head rend="italic">Figure 1: Polar diagram of the store's performance objectives</head></figure><p n="p4.23"><s n="s1.11;p4.23"><hi rend="bold"> Dependability</hi> is doing things on time for customers in line with their expectations. </s><s n="s2.11;p4.23">From interviews with the store manager this was the most important performance objective to Costcutter. </s><s n="s3.11;p4.23">Specifically this means that products should be on the shelves, not sat in storage, and are available at times when demand is particularly high (e.g. lunch time and straight after lectures). </s><s n="s4.11;p4.23">To Costcutter dependability is an 'order winning factor' as it "directly and significantly contributes to winning business"<ref target="BAWE_0169g-ftnote.003"/>. </s><s n="s5.11;p4.23">The location of the operation to its market is a sustainable competitive advantage over its rivals but to maximise this, products must be in stock to satisfy demand. </s><s n="s6.11;p4.23">The store assesses this issue through the staff job design, where it is emphasized that all staff should constantly review the availability of products on shelves and take responsibility for ensuring shelves are always stocked. </s><s n="s7.11;p4.23">Management endeavour to ensure that the store doesn't run out of stock, so that products are readily available. </s><s n="s8.11;p4.23">This is all possible due to a flexible ordering system where the majority of products are ordered from Nisa Today's via an automated IT ordering system on a daily basis. </s><s n="s9.11;p4.23">This uses check-out data to calculate the amount of new stock needed to replenish stock levels back to the threshold level set by the manager. </s><s n="s10.11;p4.23">The manager may alternate these levels according to demand variation. </s><s n="s11.11;p4.23">Stock levels of products from smaller are monitored manually and staff are encouraged to make the manager aware when levels are running low, all contributing to more reliability of stock on the shelves, thus increased dependability. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0169g-ftnote.003"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Slack et al, (2004), <hi rend="italic">Operations Management</hi>, pg 72 </s></p></note><p n="p5.23"><s n="s1.7;p5.23">The stock system is heavily reliant on the suppliers to deliver their own service effectively and last year a fire at the warehouse of the bread supplier resulted in no bread being available at the store for two days. </s><s n="s2.7;p5.23">A better contingency plan must be considered in light of that incident. </s><s n="s3.7;p5.23">The store must also deliver their service in a competitive time, ensuring products are easy to find and queuing times do not detract customers. </s><s n="s4.7;p5.23">Finally, dependability meant having regular and reliable opening hours so customers could depend on and trust the store to provide goods for them consistently. </s><s n="s5.7;p5.23">Although different for term time and vacation time, a reflection of the change in demand, the opening hours stay consistent and the store remains open 52 weeks a year. </s><s n="s6.7;p5.23">The design of the store, with such small storage facilities drives the dependability as the key performance objective. </s><s n="s7.7;p5.23">From an 'operations resources perspective' it is not seen as a 'resource constraint' but a capability to drive more efficient performance<ref target="BAWE_0169g-ftnote.004"/>. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0169g-ftnote.004"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Slack et al, (2004), <hi rend="italic">Operations Management</hi>, pg 78-79 </s></p></note><p n="p6.23"><s n="s1.12;p6.23"><hi rend="bold">Quality</hi> was the next most important objective and the store manager emphasised the need to provide a safe and clean environment within the store, well trained and helpful staff and high quality consumer goods that meet expectations. </s><s n="s2.12;p6.23">Quality can be considered a 'qualifying factor' as the performance in this objective must be above a threshold for customers to consider the store. </s><s n="s3.12;p6.23">By stocking branded products they offer a standardised quality which customer will have experienced before e.g. </s><s n="s4.12;p6.23">Hovis bread. </s><s n="s5.12;p6.23">Annual assessments of the store's image and décor, along with daily stock checks (especially of the perishable goods) and regular cleaning of floors allow the store to meet these environmental objectives. </s><s n="s6.12;p6.23">Fridge equipment is hired from a local contractor and this gives the store a clear contingency plan when equipment fails; they can just get the contractor to deliver a new piece of equipment (under the contract) rather than have to invest heavily themselves and so frozen and chilled products are always in good condition. </s><s n="s7.12;p6.23">An internal staff training program allows the manager to ensure the staff quality is high and they deal with customers in a courteous and efficient manner. </s><s n="s8.12;p6.23">Meeting customers' product quality expectations depends heavily upon the allegiances with suppliers. </s><s n="s9.12;p6.23">Through the store's allegiance and developed relationships with smaller suppliers they stock quality products at a competitive price. </s><s n="s10.12;p6.23">Finally, unlike a lot of businesses the store doesn't have a direct way of monitoring customer satisfaction (e.g. </s><s n="s11.12;p6.23">Feedback Form). </s><s n="s12.12;p6.23">Instead the manager monitors the level of complaints made and asses each complaint individually, allowing him to highlight areas for improvement. </s></p><p n="p7.23"><s n="s1.10;p7.23"><hi rend="bold">Flexibility</hi> is being able to change some aspect of the operation in some manner, perhaps how it operates or when it operates. </s><s n="s2.10;p7.23">By taking a 'market perspective' of strategy and understanding its customers, the store performs 'mix flexibility' in providing Halal, and products from ethnic sources to satisfy a mixed ethnic market. </s><s n="s3.10;p7.23">The store performs 'volume flexibility' by stocking in anticipation of demand e.g. increasing levels of alcoholic beverages in the last few weeks of term 3 once exams have finished. </s><s n="s4.10;p7.23">This flexibility requires primary support from its suppliers (Nisa Today's and a series of smaller suppliers) and through its flexible re-stocking system and Supply Chain Management (SCM). </s><s n="s5.10;p7.23">The store is flexible in 3 other ways; price setting, supplier relationships and storage/stock. </s><s n="s6.10;p7.23">Prices are high enough to cover costs and run the store at the profit, but by matching the 'business strategy' to the 'corporate strategy' prices change as part of a strong promotional programme. </s><s n="s7.10;p7.23">The restricted storage space makes a daily delivery system with Nisa Today's and the smaller suppliers very important in meeting demand. </s><s n="s8.10;p7.23">This gives the store great flexibility in meeting their overall objective of providing product range that includes a substantial grocery provision, while giving them scope to vary product ranges when consumer tastes change. </s><s n="s9.10;p7.23">Finally the flexible re-stocking system (discussed in the dependability section) allows the store to cut down stock levels in the vacation periods when demand lowers, in order to cut down on overall costs and wastage levels. </s><s n="s10.10;p7.23">Flexibility can be seen as a 'less important factor' by its worth to the store's competitiveness, good performance in flexibility supports dependability which is an order winning factor. </s></p><p n="p8.23"><s n="s1.11;p8.23"><hi rend="bold">Speed</hi> is the time between customers requesting products or services and when they are received. </s><s n="s2.11;p8.23">For the store, it is in terms of customers getting in the store, selecting products and buying them. </s><s n="s3.11;p8.23">Simply put the more customers Costcutter can get through the store per hour the more revenue they will generate. </s><s n="s4.11;p8.23">If customers expect a short time to get in and out of the store, it makes the experience of shopping easier and more enjoyable. </s><s n="s5.11;p8.23">By reducing the throughput time of each customer flow is increased, blockages and bottlenecks are reduced and queues decrease. </s><s n="s6.11;p8.23">Using 'business intelligence' Costcutter know that the average spend is £5 and consists of mainly snack purchases, thus the design of the store is such to aid speed. </s><s n="s7.11;p8.23">Large areas are devoted to sandwiches, drinks and confectionary away from tills where queues may appear, thus increasing flow and reducing speed. </s><s n="s8.11;p8.23">Clear signage indicates what is in each aisle so a customer is able to select their desired items swiftly. </s><s n="s9.11;p8.23">The creation of two more tills and guidelines as to when opening a new till is appropriate facilitate a quick service was available. </s><s n="s10.11;p8.23">The store has the necessary equipment to process orders using debit or credit cards quickly making rush hour surges easier to cope with. </s><s n="s11.11;p8.23">The layout of the store also aims to provide the customer with easy access routes to enable their visit to the store to be hassle free. </s></p><p n="p9.23"><s n="s1.7;p9.23"><hi rend="bold">Cost</hi> objective is maybe the least important in relative terms to the store but remains essential. </s><s n="s2.7;p9.23">Cost is a 'qualifying factor' because despite the convenient location, charging high prices may make customer travel the extra distance to local rivals Tesco. </s><s n="s3.7;p9.23">Management appreciate that they cannot adopt a 'cost leadership' strategy but they achieve reasonable prices through its supplier network and by setting a recommended retail price it maintains reasonable sales volume and profit margins. </s><s n="s4.7;p9.23">Trying to compete on price may put the store under more pressure at rush hour times, ultimately resulting in a negative outcome. </s><s n="s5.7;p9.23">The highest cost associated with the operation is staffing and it is important that there is a balance made between the physical benefits of having extra staff working and the financial sacrifices made to obtain them. </s><s n="s6.7;p9.23">At the moment, with many students acting as part-time staff members, the manager has created a flexible workforce to meet the physical and financial demands of the store. </s><s n="s7.7;p9.23">Considering the outlay on the new till system, the store is under pressure in the short run to make it worthwhile through improved service levels given to the customer (e.g. reduced queuing times). </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><div2><head rend="underlined bold">Part 2 - Section 1: Capacity Management</head><p n="p10.23"><s n="s1.5;p10.23">Capacity is "the amount of resource inputs available relative to output requirements over a particular period of time"<ref target="BAWE_0169g-ftnote.005"/>. </s><s n="s2.5;p10.23">Essentially, this is the maximum degree of <hi rend="italic">value added</hi> activity that can be achieved when operating under normal conditions. </s><s n="s3.5;p10.23">It is therefore of great importance to the store because it addresses the balance between demand for their services and the supply of capacity. </s><s n="s4.5;p10.23">Providing the capability to satisfy current and future demand is a "fundamental responsibility of operations management"<ref target="BAWE_0169g-ftnote.006"/>, and this is directly related to capacity planning. </s><s n="s5.5;p10.23">Firstly, demand must be forecasted. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0169g-ftnote.005"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.3;pn1.1">Chase, Aquilano, Jacobs, '<hi rend="italic">Production &amp; Operations Management.</hi> </s><s n="s2.3;pn1.1"><hi rend="italic">Manufacturing and Services' 8th Edn</hi>. </s><s n="s3.3;pn1.1">Irwin Mcgraw-Hill. page 305 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0169g-ftnote.006"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Slack et al. page P 357 </s></p></note><div3><head rend="bold">1.1. Demand Forecasting:</head><p n="p11.23"><s n="s1.15;p11.23">To satisfy demand, it is important to accurately forecast demand fluctuations in the short and long term in order to make effective capacity planning decisions. </s><s n="s2.15;p11.23">Demand forecasting is important due to its consequences for both stock control and staff management factors. </s><s n="s3.15;p11.23">Inaccurate forecasts that differ from the actual demand can lead to too little or too much: stock purchased and/or staff employed. </s><s n="s4.15;p11.23">This could lead to empty shelves (loss of revenue), poor service and unsatisfied customers or wasted stock and unnecessary costs. </s><s n="s5.15;p11.23">At the store, forecasting is primarily based on managerial experience and examining demand statistics. </s><s n="s6.15;p11.23">Causes of Seasonality: <hi rend="bold">Political:</hi> Educational services. </s><s n="s7.15;p11.23">Whilst some people remain on campus during the 22 weeks a year of vacation time (downtime) and a number of conferences take place, the bulk of the store's sales are made during the 30 weeks of term time. </s><s n="s8.15;p11.23">Within the term times there are demand fluctuations such as: increased demand for stationery and basic cooking goods at the start of term <hi rend="bold">(behavioral)</hi> and greater demand for alcohol at the end of term, particularly after exams <hi rend="bold"> (festive)</hi>. </s><s n="s9.15;p11.23"><hi rend="bold">Behavioral:</hi> There is a small amount of custom in the morning prior to 11.00am, with individuals buying newspapers/ breakfast. </s><s n="s10.15;p11.23">Every hour past this there is a peak on the hour when lectures finish, particularly around 1.00pm, when the store operates at 100% capacity utilisation. </s><s n="s11.15;p11.23">This lunchtime demand falls only to build up again for the early evening rush as people employed on campus finish work and students shop for their dinner. </s><s n="s12.15;p11.23">Demand finally falls again at the end of the day. </s><s n="s13.15;p11.23"><hi rend="bold">Climatic:</hi> Further to this, demand for certain products can also be forecast. </s><s n="s14.15;p11.23">For instance, ice creams and drinks have more demand over the summer term. </s><s n="s15.15;p11.23"><hi rend="bold">Financial:</hi> The promotional strategies of the store with also affect product demand. </s></p><p n="p12.23"><s n="s1.6;p12.23">In the case of the store, demand is quite simple to monitor. </s><s n="s2.6;p12.23">Once this demand is forecasted for the short and long term, the capability of the operation's resources should be calculated. </s><s n="s3.6;p12.23">This finds answers to questions such as: What are the operation's capacity constraints/ bottlenecks (i.e. parts of the store that slow down the rest) - <hi rend="bold">see layout &amp; design section??</hi> </s><s n="s4.6;p12.23">The input measure of the store's capacity could be the sales floor area and number of staff. </s><s n="s5.6;p12.23">The output capacity measure could be the number of items sold per day. </s><s n="s6.6;p12.23">The management must provide the appropriate amount of capacity to: satisfy demand, to minimize costs and maximize: revenue, working capital and the service level. </s></p></div3><div3><head rend="bold">1.2. Capacity Plans:</head><p n="p13.23"><s n="s1.7;p13.23">The store employs a 'Chase demand plan' to utilise its capacity. </s><s n="s2.7;p13.23">This plan attempts to closely adjust capacity to the varying levels of forecast demand, which minimises stock levels. </s><s n="s3.7;p13.23">By minimizing stock, lower holding costs and more working capital are gained. </s><s n="s4.7;p13.23">Additionally, low stock levels make it easier to maintain the stock and to identify problems such as shortages. </s><s n="s5.7;p13.23">There is also the added benefit of more floor space, leading to more stock and variety achieving the dependability and mix flexibility performance objective. </s><s n="s6.7;p13.23">A chase demand plan also helps reduce stock wastage and excess staff that can occur with a level capacity plan by, whilst it also aims to satisfy customer demand. </s><s n="s7.7;p13.23">This is particularly suitable to the store because: it has high variations in demand, perishable goods, a flexible workforce (see section 1.3.1.) and a limited storage capacity (section 1.3.2.) - "A pure chase demand plan is more usually adopted by operations which cannot store their output "<hi rend="sup">3</hi>. </s></p></div3><div3><head rend="bold">1.3. Capacity Utilisation:</head><p n="p14.23"><s n="s1.1;p14.23">This section answers: How the store efficiently allocates its resources over time and changes its capacity according to forecasted demand changes? </s></p><div4><head rend="bold">1.3.1. Flexible workforce:</head><p n="p15.23"><s n="s1.7;p15.23">To efficiently address capacity management, the store employs students as temporary staff to work during term time to cope with the extra demand. </s><s n="s2.7;p15.23">This flexible workforce also has multiple skills and the ability to switch easily from one task to another. </s><s n="s3.7;p15.23">The staff have broad training in job enlargement and rotation so they know how to restock shelves, clean, use the tills, assist in the storage room and do stock checking. </s><s n="s4.7;p15.23">The store also controls staff at peak times by using an 'overlap' system. </s><s n="s5.7;p15.23">Since the store is open 14 hours a day, the employees work shifts instead of full days. </s><s n="s6.7;p15.23">If organised correctly this can mean an overlap of staff at lunchtime meaning that the extra staff needed are available solely for the busiest time of the day. </s><s n="s7.7;p15.23">When the store is quiet, staff engaging in other activities such as cleaning or maintenance can limit 'idle time'. </s></p></div4><div4><head rend="bold">1.3.2. Storage Capacity:</head><p n="p16.23"><s n="s1.5;p16.23">The limited storage capacity affects inventory management by restricting the quantity of stock held and the quantities ordered. </s><s n="s2.5;p16.23">The store manages with such limited space because they outsource their warehousing and a significant part of its sourcing and supply chain management activities to a service provider: Nisa. </s><s n="s3.5;p16.23">With almost a delivery every day and managers who are experienced in demand fluctuations, the store has the flexibility to order 'just-in-time,' each evening, to meet its precise needs so it can adjust itself to demand. </s><s n="s4.5;p16.23">This system is vital to achieving the important quality objective of stocking fresh food. </s><s n="s5.5;p16.23">This means that socks must be managed according to their perishable nature as well as their demand structure. </s></p><p n="p17.23"><s n="s1.4;p17.23">However, during our research we found that the stock room capacity is not entirely utilized because of its disorder, which causes problems and leads to under-utilisation of resources <hi rend="sup">4</hi>. </s><s n="s2.4;p17.23">We also discovered that the management want a larger stock room, to give a larger safety margin (or buffer stock) for highly demand goods that sell quickly, so the chance of having stock-outs is reduced. </s><s n="s3.4;p17.23">This is possible that the store makes use of a buffer inventory system for certain products because "its purpose is to compensate for unexpected fluctuations in supply and demand."<hi rend="sup">5</hi> A larger stock room also helps ensure that revenue opportunities such as gaining bulk-buying discounts by ordering large quantities from the small suppliers are not missed. </s><s n="s4.4;p17.23">Although a larger stock room would be hard to obtain, it is expensive and it may lead to more wastage, especially of perishable goods. </s></p></div4></div3></div2><div2><head rend="underlined bold">Part 2 - Section 2: Layout and Flow</head><p n="p18.23"><s n="s1.2;p18.23">Layout is a key consideration for any operation to ensure there are not overlong or confused flow patterns, long process times, customer queues or high costs. </s><s n="s2.2;p18.23">As mentioned in part one, cost is not a key performance objective to Costcutter yet, because it is a supermarket, it is vital to have a layout which maximises revenue and contribution per square metre, but minimises operating costs. </s></p><p n="p19.23"><s n="s1.4;p19.23">The layout type is based on the process type in the organisation; as Costcutter is a service shop, there are two suitable layout types out of the four: process and cell rather than product or fixed position. </s><s n="s2.4;p19.23">In a process layout, "the needs and convenience of the transforming resources dominate the layout decision"<ref target="BAWE_0169g-ftnote.007"/> as customers flow freely through Costcutter according to their purchasing requirements. </s><s n="s3.4;p19.23">Conversely, a cell layout comprises all transforming resources necessary for completion of the process located in one area of the organisation, resulting in a fast throughput of transformed resources. </s><s n="s4.4;p19.23">Costcutter is an example of a process layout, as can be seen from the diagram below. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0169g-ftnote.007"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Slack et al, p208 </s></p></note><p n="p20.23"><s n="s1.2;p20.23">Process layout allows free movement of transformed resources (customers) around the store. </s><s n="s2.2;p20.23">In process layout, similar products are located together: in Costcutter, all fruit and vegetables are at the rear of the store, with frozen items on aisle..... and all alcoholic beverages located in the far left hand corner. </s></p><p n="p21.23"><s n="s1.5;p21.23">The volume-variety characteristics of an organisation determine the importance of flow within it. </s><s n="s2.5;p21.23">Costcutter has high volume of customers and a high variety of goods, flow is going to be very difficult to determine because there is such free movement between activities. </s><s n="s3.5;p21.23">Thus, the management of Costcutter use their discretion to determine the layout that will inconvenience the least number of people whilst also ensuring that security issues are addressed. </s><s n="s4.5;p21.23">During our visit, meat, coffee and toiletries were located near security cameras whilst other products were located according to consumer tastes. </s><s n="s5.5;p21.23">If there is a small variety of products grouped together to form a distinct category with similar requirements, a cell could be appropriate. </s></p><p n="p22.23"><s n="s1.2;p22.23">In order to realise the speed objective, Costcutter must ensure that there are no bottlenecks which constrain the flow within the organisation. </s><s n="s2.2;p22.23">In Costcutter this is particularly relevant at its peak time, lunch time when the layout is insufficiently flexible to adapt to increased demand. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0169g-pic.001"/></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined">Recommendations</head><p n="p23.23"><s n="s1.2;p23.23">In order to increase flexibility and the throughput time in peak periods, Costcutter should adopt a more mixed approach by introducing cells into its layout. </s><s n="s2.2;p23.23">As lunchtime is the key peak period, all sandwiches and lunchtime snacks and drinks should be located together with a specific till at the disposal of lunchtime customers, in essence making the sandwich area a "shop-within-a-shop". </s></p></div1></body><back><div1 type="bibliography"><head rend="bold">Bibliography</head><p>Johnston, R. "Service Operations Management" Prentice Hall (2001)</p><p>Kimball, G. "Decision Theory: Operations Research In management, Advanced Management" Vol.20, No.12 (Dec 1954)</p><p>Laufer, A. "Operations Management" (1979)</p><p>Ruch, A, Fearon, H. "Fundamentals of Production/Operations Management" Fifth Edition (1992)</p><p>Slack, N. "Operations Management" Fourth Edition, Prentice Hall (2004)</p></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
