<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_0179e" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>In what sense might Hobbes' Leviathan be considered as a modern state?</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">Language used in quote: <foreign id="English">English</foreign></note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">deleted: footer: student number, page numbers</note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">deleted: 1789 Words 
</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">2</p><p n="date">2004-11</p><p n="module title">Sociology of the Modern State</p><p n="module code">SO213</p><p n="genre family">Essay</p><p n="discipline">Sociology</p><p n="disciplinary group">SS</p><p n="grade">M</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">1689</p><p n="number of s-units">71</p><p n="number of p">14</p><p n="number of tables">0</p><p n="number of figures">0</p><p n="number of block quotes">9</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">0</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">0</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">23.8</p><p n="average s-units per p">5.1</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">m</p><p n="year of birth">1983</p><p n="first language">English</p><p n="education">UKA</p><p n="course">Sociology</p><p n="student ID">0179</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><docTitle><titlePart rend="bold">In what sense might Hobbes' Leviathan be considered as a modern state? </titlePart></docTitle></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="section"><p n="p1.14"><s n="s1.10;p1.14">It appears strange to talk about a state thought up in 1651 could be in any sense modern. </s><s n="s2.10;p1.14">Just several years after the Treaty of Westphalia, which is generally agreed to be the birth of the modern nation state, was Hobbes theorising and legitimising this state already? </s><s n="s3.10;p1.14">There are of course many different versions of the 'modern state' and no single one can claim to be true. </s><s n="s4.10;p1.14">This does not, however, stop us from appraising 'Leviathan' in terms of its modernity. </s><s n="s5.10;p1.14">There is a constant struggle in the latter half of 'Of Man' and the early chapters of 'The Commonwealth' between rights as an individual and sovereignty and power of the state. </s><s n="s6.10;p1.14">These questions are still relevant today, and political theory since Hobbes has challenged and sought to expound the problems between 'liberties' and 'obligations'. </s><s n="s7.10;p1.14">I shall begin this essay by offering a summary of Hobbes' account of the state and then examine the possibility of 'Leviathan' being a modern state, particularly by comparing it with the political writings of Max Weber. </s><s n="s8.10;p1.14">I shall then look at differing views of the modern state that refute Leviathan as modern. </s><s n="s9.10;p1.14">My conclusion will be that there are concepts within Leviathan that are uniquely modern, and how the social contract tradition was vital in the formation of modern states. </s><s n="s10.10;p1.14">Having said that there are modern ideas in Hobbes, this does not mean that his end result is a modern state. </s></p><p n="p2.14"><s n="s1.1;p2.14">Hobbes conducts a thought experiment in which he places all men<ref target="BAWE_0179e-ftnote.001"/> in a 'state of nature'. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0179e-ftnote.001"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">I will be referring only to men throughout this essay as Hobbes makes is plain that is only men that can occupy any public sphere, though I believe it to be a flaw of his work, I shall remain true to the context in which he wrote </s></p></note><quote lang="English">"Nature hath made me so equal in the faculties of body and mind; as that though there may be found one man sometimes manifestly stronger in body, or of quicker mind than another; yet when all is reckoned together, the difference between man, and man is not so considerable,"<ref target="BAWE_0179e-ftnote.002"/></quote><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0179e-ftnote.002"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Page 82 Thomas Hobbes <hi rend="italic">'Leviathan'</hi> 1651 edited my J C A Gaskin 1996, Oxford, Oxford University Press </s></p></note><p n="p3.14"><s n="s1.6;p3.14">In this state all men are equal, in the sense that they are equal in their fear of one another and their insecurity. </s><s n="s2.6;p3.14">Even the weakest can use some 'secret machination' and kill the strongest in his sleep. </s><s n="s3.6;p3.14">Men are all equal in their hopes, desires and passions, that is not to say that all men share the same dreams, but they have and equal opportunity of obtaining them. </s><s n="s4.6;p3.14">In the 'state of nature' men may do what they see fit to procure the ends they desire for the "preservation of his own nature"<ref target="BAWE_0179e-ftnote.003"/>. </s><s n="s5.6;p3.14">But he may also seek power and glory either as a means to obtain more pleasure and security, or as an ends in themselves. </s><s n="s6.6;p3.14">Because of this constant competition and fear, men are in a constant state of war: </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0179e-ftnote.003"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Page 86 Thomas Hobbes <hi rend="italic">'Leviathan'</hi> </s></p></note><quote lang="English">"For war, consisteth not in battle only, or the act of fighting; but in the tract of time, wherein the will to contend is sufficiently known,"<ref target="BAWE_0179e-ftnote.004"/></quote><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0179e-ftnote.004"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Page 84 Thomas Hobbes <hi rend="italic">'Leviathan'</hi> </s></p></note><p n="p4.14"><s n="s1.5;p4.14">In this state of war there will be no culture, no art and life will be generally nasty and short. </s><s n="s2.5;p4.14">Despite this rather grim outlook men have a chance to gain the peace that they inherently desire<ref target="BAWE_0179e-ftnote.005"/>. </s><s n="s3.5;p4.14">Men can renounce their natural rights to a sovereign in return for a protection. </s><s n="s4.5;p4.14">This is the basis of the social contract. </s><s n="s5.5;p4.14">Rights are given up and replaced with obligations and obedience to the sovereign. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0179e-ftnote.005"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Chapter XV Thomas Hobbes <hi rend="italic">'Leviathan'</hi> </s></p></note><quote lang="English">"<hi rend="italic">I authorize and give up my right of governing myself, to this man, or to this assembly of men, on this condition, that thou give up thy right to him, and authorize all his actions in like manner</hi>"<ref target="BAWE_0179e-ftnote.006"/></quote><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0179e-ftnote.006"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Page 114 Thomas Hobbes <hi rend="italic">'Leviathan'</hi> </s></p></note><p n="p5.14"><s n="s1.4;p5.14">This sovereign offers assurance to those entering into covenants, and allows men to live in peace and carry out the laws of nature as stated in Chapter XV 'in foro externo'. </s><s n="s2.4;p5.14">Hobbes' sovereign has absolute power, as he still retains all the liberties that he had in a state of nature. </s><s n="s3.4;p5.14">The sovereign is not answerable to the people, and can make laws and arbitrate in accordance with the laws of nature as he sees fit<ref target="BAWE_0179e-ftnote.007"/>. </s><s n="s4.4;p5.14">The sovereign is to be the punisher of those who break covenants, of which codified law is a part, and protect individuals from harm and injury from others. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0179e-ftnote.007"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Chapter XVIII Thomas Hobbes <hi rend="italic">'Leviathan'</hi> </s></p></note><p n="p6.14"><s n="s1.9;p6.14">This although an all too brief account of arguably the most important sections of 'Leviathan' is nonetheless useful as it highlights key areas of examination. </s><s n="s2.9;p6.14">Firstly Hobbes' conception of human nature is way ahead of his time; his idea of man as in competition for scarce goods is not fully examined for another hundred years when Adam Smith talks of the 'invisible hand of the market'. </s><s n="s3.9;p6.14">Secondly his description of a state of war, aptly describe the international situation from Hobbes' time to the contemporary global system. </s><s n="s4.9;p6.14">Thirdly the social contract has been used since Hobbes to justify modern political institutions. </s><s n="s5.9;p6.14">Fourthly the sovereigns power as absolute and over-arching. </s><s n="s6.9;p6.14">This is an especially salient point as when Hobbes was writing Feudalism was declining. </s><s n="s7.9;p6.14">This links in with the fifth point of the scientific and legal rationality of this process. </s><s n="s8.9;p6.14">Power is legitimised through rational methods and upheld through codified laws rather than through customs and divinity. </s><s n="s9.9;p6.14">Although the first two points are extremely interesting and deserving of attention, it is latter three that are key to this question. </s></p><p n="p7.14"><s n="s1.4;p7.14">The notion of the social contract is a myth that has been propagated to justify the existence of the modern state. </s><s n="s2.4;p7.14">It acknowledges that humans have natural rights, and that these have been given up in greater or lesser degrees in return for the state providing governance. </s><s n="s3.4;p7.14">This at least on the surface implies some kind or interaction between the rulers and the ruled. </s><s n="s4.4;p7.14">It also suggests a hierarchy of rights, and these of course are integral to the values of a society. </s></p><quote lang="English">"[Hobbes'] position is at one with all those who argue for the importance of government by consent... and reject the authority of tradition"<ref target="BAWE_0179e-ftnote.008"/></quote><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0179e-ftnote.008"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Page 35 David Held <hi rend="italic">'Central Perspectives on the Modern State'</hi> in <hi rend="italic">'The idea of the Modern State'</hi> edited by Mclennon, Held and Hall, 1984, Milton Keynes, Open University Press </s></p></note><p n="p8.14"><s n="s1.5;p8.14">This idea of representation is a distinctively modern concept. </s><s n="s2.5;p8.14">In pre-modernity, social order was preordained by God or by blood. </s><s n="s3.5;p8.14">Hobbes' 'state of nature' and the process of social contract gives everyone rights, something which we take for granted in a modern era. </s><s n="s4.5;p8.14">This pluralistic view of politics and power is more associated with liberal democracy rather than the monarchies of the 17 <hi rend="sup">th</hi> century. </s><s n="s5.5;p8.14">However, to believe that Hobbes was advocating some kind of direct or representative democracy would be to take his words out of context: </s></p><quote lang="English">"[Hobbes'] conclusions run wholly counter to those who often take such an argument to imply the necessity of some kind of popular sovereignty"<ref target="BAWE_0179e-ftnote.009"/></quote><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0179e-ftnote.009"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Page 35 David Held <hi rend="italic">'Central Perspectives on the Modern State'</hi> </s></p></note><p n="p9.14"><s n="s1.1;p9.14">Hobbes sovereign is "unpunishable by the subject"<ref target="BAWE_0179e-ftnote.010"/>. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0179e-ftnote.010"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Page 118 Thomas Hobbes <hi rend="italic">'Leviathan'</hi> 1651 </s></p></note><quote lang="English">"Since rulers do not participate in the contract, they do not stand in a contractual relationship with their people and, therefore, there is no basis for governmental accountability"<ref target="BAWE_0179e-ftnote.011"/></quote><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0179e-ftnote.011"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Page 174 Deborah Baumgold, Chapter 10 in <hi rend="italic">'Political thinkers: From Socrates to the present'</hi> edited by D Boucher and P Kelly, 2003, Oxford, Oxford University Press </s></p></note><p n="p10.14"><s n="s1.5;p10.14">This lack of citizenship excludes Leviathan from being a modern state. </s><s n="s2.5;p10.14">A modern state is a nation state. </s><s n="s3.5;p10.14">For people to belong to a nation that can call on them; they require that the state gives up some of its rights in order to procure their services. </s><s n="s4.5;p10.14">A modern government must have authority, not simply power, where authority is legitimate power. </s><s n="s5.5;p10.14">Without some kind of representation this legitimacy would not exist in a modern state. </s></p><p n="p11.14"><s n="s1.1;p11.14">Legitimacy has a central role in state building: </s></p><quote lang="English">"A state is that human community which successfully lays claim to the monopoly of legitimate violence within a certain territory"<ref target="BAWE_0179e-ftnote.012"/></quote><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0179e-ftnote.012"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Page 310 Max Weber <hi rend="italic">'The Profession and Vocation of Politics'</hi> 1919 in <hi rend="italic">'Weber: Political Writings'</hi> edited by P Lassman, Cambridge, Cambridge University Press </s></p></note><p n="p12.14"><s n="s1.8;p12.14">This is Max Weber's basis for the foundation of a modern state: that it is the only source of violence in a given area. </s><s n="s2.8;p12.14">This is modern for two reasons. </s><s n="s3.8;p12.14">Firstly that it is bound to a piece of land, pre-modernity there were no borders but frontiers, which competing groups laid claim to. </s><s n="s4.8;p12.14">Secondly there is only one source of violence that is legitimate in a modern society. </s><s n="s5.8;p12.14">In pre-modern societies feudal lords, local courts and local customs could punish individuals. </s><s n="s6.8;p12.14">'Leviathan' sits quite happily alongside this definition of a modern state. </s><s n="s7.8;p12.14">Implicit within his writing is the fact that the sovereign is linked to a given area; namely over those that have renounced their right to the sovereign and over no more and no less. </s><s n="s8.8;p12.14">Secondly the Hobbesian state is the only source of violence in society: </s></p><quote lang="English">"Eleventhly, to the sovereign is committed the power of rewarding with riches, or honour; and of punishing with corporal, or pecuniary punishment, or with ignominy every subject according to the law he hath made"<ref target="BAWE_0179e-ftnote.013"/></quote><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0179e-ftnote.013"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Page 120 Thomas Hobbes <hi rend="italic">'Leviathan'</hi> 1651 </s></p></note><p n="p13.14"><s n="s1.4;p13.14">This codification of laws also is modern. </s><s n="s2.4;p13.14">Weber calls this the 'legal rational' domination or "rule by virtue of legality"<ref target="BAWE_0179e-ftnote.014"/> If we accept Hobbes judgements on people to be true, then it is merely a consequence of the definitions that, scientifically, we are lead to the creation of the all powerful sovereign. </s><s n="s3.4;p13.14">Using logic rather than custom and religion to define government is another fundamental building block of the modern state. </s><s n="s4.4;p13.14">Again we may not agree with where Hobbes actually ends up following his logic, but the methodology is that of modernity. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0179e-ftnote.014"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Page 312 Max Weber <hi rend="italic">'The Profession and Vocation of Politics'</hi> 1919 </s></p></note><p n="p14.14"><s n="s1.8;p14.14">In conclusion it is difficult to juxtapose Hobbes complete work with modernity. </s><s n="s2.8;p14.14">We must remember that he is writing in a time of civil war and is motivated by finding a solution that would give peace. </s><s n="s3.8;p14.14">And maybe this context confined Hobbes from truly exploring the revolutionary ideas within his own work. </s><s n="s4.8;p14.14">However it is possible to find links to the modern state: the monopoly of power within the state, the methodology of rationality and logic, the codification of law. </s><s n="s5.8;p14.14">But most importantly Hobbes gives us the language of the social contract, without which it would be impossible to theorise about any kind of modern state. </s><s n="s6.8;p14.14">The idea that there is some give and take between the state and society; even the omnipotent sovereign is restrained by the laws of nature. </s><s n="s7.8;p14.14">The language of rights and responsibilities is as pertinent as ever in today's contemporary world. </s><s n="s8.8;p14.14">But crucially Hobbes fails to create the citizen, underestimates the power of the 'state of nature' and the freedom that modernity is constantly striving for and this is perhaps why we find it so difficult to accept his 'Mortal God' as anything remotely modern: </s></p><quote lang="English">"Why would men take care to avoid what mischief's may be done to them pole-cats or foxes...think it safety to be devoured by lions"<ref target="BAWE_0179e-ftnote.015"/></quote><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0179e-ftnote.015"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Locke cited on page 37 David Held <hi rend="italic">'Central Perspectives on the Modern State'</hi> </s></p></note></div1></body><back><div1 type="bibliography"><head rend="underlined bold">References</head><p>Baumgold Deborah, Chapter 10 in <hi rend="italic">'Political thinkers: From Socrates to the present'</hi> edited by D Boucher and P Kelly, 2003, Oxford, Oxford University Press</p><p>Held David <hi rend="italic">'Central Perspectives on the Modern State'</hi> in <hi rend="italic">'The idea of the Modern State'</hi> edited by Mclennon, Held and Hall, 1984, Milton Keynes, Open University Press</p><p>Hobbes Thomas <hi rend="italic">'Leviathan'</hi> 1651 edited my J C A Gaskin 1996, Oxford, Oxford University Press</p><p>Weber, Max <hi rend="italic">'The Profession and Vocation of Politics'</hi> 1919 in <hi rend="italic">'Weber: Political Writings'</hi> edited by P Lassman, Cambridge, Cambridge University Press</p></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
