<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_0183d" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Microsensors, MEMS &amp; Smart Devices. Assignment 1: Asseessed Work</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">deleted: page numbers
</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">4</p><p n="date">2005-11</p><p n="module title">Logistics &amp; Operations Management</p><p n="module code">ES961</p><p n="genre family">Exercise</p><p n="discipline">Engineering</p><p n="disciplinary group">PS</p><p n="grade">M</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">1484</p><p n="number of s-units">65</p><p n="number of p">36</p><p n="number of tables">0</p><p n="number of figures">4</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">8</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">20</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">22.8</p><p n="average s-units per p">1.8</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">m</p><p n="year of birth">1980</p><p n="first language">English</p><p n="education">OSA</p><p n="course">MSc Advanced Mechanical Engineering</p><p n="student ID">0183</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><docTitle><titlePart rend="bold">ES916: Microsensors, MEMS &amp; Smart Devices Assignment 1: Assessed Work</titlePart></docTitle></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="section"><head>1.1State the principal forms of signal energy that may be used to classify the different types of sensors. Give two examples of sensors in each class.<hi rend="bold">Solution 1.1 </hi></head><p n="p1.36"><s n="s1.2;p1.36">Signal is a form of energy and sensors can be classified according to the type of energy they detect. </s><s n="s2.2;p1.36">There are six primary energy domains and their associated symbols are as follows: </s></p><list type="simple"><item>Electrical E</item><item>Thermal T</item><item>Radiation R</item><item>Mechanical Me</item><item>Magnetic M</item><item>Bio (chemical) C</item></list><div2><head>Electrical Sensors</head><p n="p2.36"><s n="s1.1;p2.36">These are names according to the electrical property that is changed or the electrical signal that is recorded. </s></p><list type="simple"><item>Property-Resistance, R Example of Sensor - magnetoresistor</item><item>Signal-Voltage, V Example of Sensor-thermocouple</item></list></div2><div2><head>Thermal sensors</head><p n="p3.36"><s n="s1.1;p3.36">Thermal sensors are sensors that measure a primary thermal quantity, such as temperature, heat flow, or thermal conductivity. </s></p><list type="simple"><head>Examples of sensor-thermistor, thermocouple</head></list></div2><div2><head>Radiation sensors</head><p n="p4.36"><s n="s1.1;p4.36">Radiation sensors detect electromagnetic radiation with energies or wavelengths from the ultraviolet-to-near-infrared (UV-NIR) which includes visible, through the NIR and thermal-infrared region and into the microwave and radio regions. </s></p><list type="ordered"><head>Examples of radiation sensors: (a) CdS photoconductive cell; (b) p-n silicon photodiode.</head></list></div2><div2><head>Mechanical sensors</head><p n="p5.36"><s n="s1.2;p5.36">Mechanical microsensors are perhaps the most important class of microsensors because of both the large variety of different mechanical measurands and their successful application in mass markets. </s><s n="s2.2;p5.36">The main measurands of mechanical microsensors are acceleration/deceleration, displacement, flow rate, force/torque, position/angle and pressure/stress. </s></p><list type="ordered"><head>Examples of mechanical sensors: (a) pressure microsensors; (b) microaccelerometers</head></list></div2><div2><head>Magnetic sensors</head><p n="p6.36"><s n="s1.1;p6.36">Magnetic sensors are classified according to the form of output signal rather than the energy domain of the input signal used earlier. </s></p><list type="ordered"><head>Examples of magnetic sensors: (a) magnetoresistor; (b) magnetodiode</head></list></div2><div2><head>Bio (chemical) sensors</head><p n="p7.36"><s n="s1.2;p7.36">It comprises of chemically sensitive layer interfaced to a sensing transducer. </s><s n="s2.2;p7.36">The analyte molecules interact with the chemically sensitive layer and produce a physical change that is detected by the transducer and are converted electrical signal output. </s></p><list type="ordered"><head>Examples of chemical sensors: (a) metal oxide gas sensor; (b) pellistor</head></list></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head>1.2 Briefly describe the ideal characteristics of a sensor. Explain why you think these characteristics are ideal and desirable in engineering applications.<hi rend="bold">Solution 1.2</hi></head><p n="p8.36"><s n="s1.1;p8.36">The ideal characteristics of a sensor are as follows: </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p9.36"><s n="s1.2;p9.36">High sensitivity- The sensitivity of the sensor is defined as the minimum input of physical parameter that will create a detectable output change. </s><s n="s2.2;p9.36">Hence the higher the sensitivity the better the response. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p10.36"><s n="s1.1;p10.36">Fast and linear response- It is the time at which the output reaches some percentage of its final value in response to a step change in the measurand. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p11.36"><s n="s1.1;p11.36">Fully reversible behaviour-it is the ability of the sensing mechanism to follow the variations in the environment. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p12.36"><s n="s1.2;p12.36">High reliability-The ability of a sensor to perform a required function under stated conditions for a stated period. </s><s n="s2.2;p12.36">Hence sensors should be highly reliable despite the environmental conditions. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p13.36"><s n="s1.1;p13.36">Selectivity- can be defined as the capacity of a sensor to be sensitive to a specific compound. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p14.36"><s n="s1.1;p14.36">Compact- the smaller the sensor the more easily it can be built into hand held devices. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p15.36"><s n="s1.2;p15.36">High signal-to-noise ratio-It is the power ratio between signal (meaningful information) and the background noise. </s><s n="s2.2;p15.36">In general higher signal to noise is better. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p16.36"><s n="s1.1;p16.36">Insensitive to surrounding environmental conditions. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p17.36"><s n="s1.1;p17.36">Easy to calibrate. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p18.36"><s n="s1.1;p18.36">Low cost-Price is a critical factor for mass production. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p19.36"><s n="s1.1;p19.36">No moving parts that can suffer from wear mechanisms. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head>2.1 Briefly describe the processing steps that are involved in the wet etching of a cavity in single-crystal silicon.<hi rend="bold">Solution 2.1</hi></head><p n="p20.36"><s n="s1.5;p20.36">Etching is a chemical process wherein material is removed by a chemical reaction between the etchants and the material to be etched. </s><s n="s2.5;p20.36">The etchant may be chemical solution or plasma. </s><s n="s3.5;p20.36">If the etchant is a chemical solution, the etching process is called wet chemical etching. </s><s n="s4.5;p20.36">There are two types of wet etching, one is isotropic etching where the etch rate is constant in all directions and the other one is anisotropic etching, where the etch rate depends upon orientation to crystalline planes. </s><s n="s5.5;p20.36">In anisotropic etching the lateral etch rate can be much smaller or larger than the vertical etch rate. </s></p><p n="p21.36"><s n="s1.1;p21.36">The steps involved in wet etching of a single crystal of silicon are as follows: </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p22.36"><s n="s1.3;p22.36">To grow SiO <hi rend="sub">2</hi> at 1000°C in dry oxygen on the layer on which the process is to be carried out. </s><s n="s2.3;p22.36">The oxide is patterned using optical lithography. </s><s n="s3.3;p22.36">This forms the channels which holds the chemicals and forms the shape of the cavity. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p23.36"><s n="s1.4;p23.36">This is followed by immersing the masked silicon crystal in the etching solution. </s><s n="s2.4;p23.36">The choice of etching solution depends on the type of wet etching, i.e. isotropic or anisotropic. </s><s n="s3.4;p23.36">For isotropic etching the etching solutions used are HF, HF: HN <hi rend="sub">4</hi>F, and for anisotropic etching KOH, NaOH, EDP etc. are used. </s><s n="s4.4;p23.36">The etching solution only removes the film on the exposed areas. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p24.36"><s n="s1.1;p24.36">The products are transferred from the surface of the silicon crystal and the etching solution is changed to increase the etch rate. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p25.36"><s n="s1.2;p25.36">Finally when the desired shape is reached, the chemical reaction has to be stopped. </s><s n="s2.2;p25.36">To achieve this different etch stop techniques are used, such as anisotropic etch stop layers, electrochemical etch stop, etc. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0183d-pic.001"/></div1><div1 type="section"><head>2.2 Sketch out the ideal shapes that would be etched out of a single crystal silicon using square, triangular and cross-shaped masks after various times.<hi rend="bold">Solution 2.2</hi></head><figure id="BAWE_0183d-pic.002"><head>Triangular shaped mask </head></figure><figure id="BAWE_0183d-pic.003"><head>Cross shaped mask</head></figure><figure id="BAWE_0183d-pic.004"><head>Square shaped mask </head></figure><p n="p26.36"/></div1><div1 type="section"><head>3.1 Are chemical microsensors in general linear or non-linear sensors? Explain the underlying principle or principles that led you to your conclusion.<hi rend="bold">Solution 3.1</hi></head><p n="p27.36"><s n="s1.11;p27.36">In an ideal situation, the output signal of a sensor is directly proportional to the measured property. </s><s n="s2.11;p27.36">For example, if a sensor measures temperature and has a voltage output, the gain is a constant with the unit (V/K).If the gain is not constant there is non-linearity. </s><s n="s3.11;p27.36">However in case of chemical sensors the sensor response depends on the temperature of the chemical reaction taking place. </s><s n="s4.11;p27.36">Let us consider the response of a Tin oxide gas sensor in terms of its conductance in air. </s><s n="s5.11;p27.36">The device is operated at high temperature because the chemical reaction is more specific at higher temperatures, the device responds in just a few seconds. </s><s n="s6.11;p27.36">Finally, also operating the device at higher temperatures ameliorates the effects of humidity upon its response a critical factor for chemical sensors. </s><s n="s7.11;p27.36">When the sensor is operated at higher temperatures the vacant sites within the nonstoichiometric tin oxide lattice react with the atmospheric oxygen to abstract electrons out of the conduction band of the tin oxide chemisorbed oxygen sites such as O- , O <hi rend="sub">2</hi>- and so on. </s><s n="s8.11;p27.36">This reversible reaction is disturbed when the analyte molecule X reacts with the chemisorbed oxygen species to release electrons and promulgate further reactions. </s><s n="s9.11;p27.36">In simple physical description, the tin oxide behaves like a n-type semiconductor and therefore, there is an increase in electron carrier density, and hence the electrical conductivity of the material with increase gas concentration. </s><s n="s10.11;p27.36">This leads to decrease in response time as the temperature increases. </s><s n="s11.11;p27.36">Hence we can conclude that chemical microsensors are nonlinear. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head>3.2 Why do you think chemical microsensors have not enjoys the same commercial success of the other class of microsensors. How might these deficiencies be overcome? Are there any exceptions to this general rule? If so, name them.<hi rend="bold">Solution 3.2</hi></head><p n="p28.36"><s n="s1.1;p28.36">Chemical sensor technology is poorly developed and suffers from a number of complications and hence has never had the same commercial success as </s></p><p n="p29.36"><s n="s1.2;p29.36">other class of microsensors. </s><s n="s2.2;p29.36">Some of the deficiencies are as follows: </s></p><list type="bulleted"><item>• Lack of compatibility between sensor operation and integrated circuit operation.</item><item>• Inherent vulnerability to changes in the sensing environment such as humidity.</item><item>• Poisoning from the sensor environment due to irreversible reactions with some chemicals.</item><item>• High degree of mismatch among sensors due to the nature of reactions on the sensor surface.</item><item>• Poor selectivity in the sensors themselves.</item><item>• Long response times (on the order of tens of seconds) of individual sensors.</item><item>• Reproducibility problems resulting from sensor drift over the lifetime of the sensor.</item><item>Operating range is restricted</item></list><p n="p30.36"><s n="s1.1;p30.36">The above issues are addressed in building signal processing architectures that are well suited to chemical sensing microsystems: </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p31.36"><s n="s1.1;p31.36">• Relationships between heterogeneous and homogeneous array structures in optimizing a hybrid array for subsequent signal processing. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p32.36"><s n="s1.1;p32.36">• Making Pre-processing suitable to minimizing random errors among operational sensors (e.g. mismatch) and preventing poisoned sensors from providing input to subsequent signal processing. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p33.36"><s n="s1.1;p33.36">• Normalization of sensor outputs to improve selectivity (discrimination) capability and to minimize the systematic effects of drift and concentration changes on the discrimination capability of the overall chemical sensing system. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p34.36"><s n="s1.1;p34.36">• Improvement of response time through signal processing of transient signals. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p35.36"><s n="s1.1;p35.36">• Determination of a suitable framework for integrating these signal processing architectures and actual sensor arrays. </s></p><p n="p36.36"><s n="s1.4;p36.36">However there is an exception to the rule. </s><s n="s2.4;p36.36">To date the greatest commercial success of a polymeric potentiometric device has been in the field of biosenors. </s><s n="s3.4;p36.36">The device consists of an enzyme, such as glucose oxidase, which is attached to an electrode and senses potentiometrically, amperometrically, or impedimetrically. </s><s n="s4.4;p36.36">Perhaps the most successful device has been the glucose detector. </s></p></div1></body><back><div1 type="bibliography"><head rend="bold">References</head><p>Gardner, J.W., Vardan, V.K. and Awadelkarim, O.O. (2002). Microsensors MEMS and Smart Devices, JOHN WILEY &amp; SONS, LTD.</p><p><seg type="URL" n="www.ee.washington.edu/research/"/> /PhD/denise/www/Lab/publications chapter1.pdf [Online].</p><p>3. <seg type="URL" n="http://www.inapg.inra.fr/ens_rech/siab/asteq/elba/elba_index.htm"/> [Online]</p></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
