<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_0188j" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>A kinetic study of the hydrolysis of crystal violet</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">deleted: header: university, student number, module code and date</note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">appendix contains tables of experimental results
</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">3</p><p n="date">2006-05</p><p n="module title">Extended Laboratory Work</p><p n="module code">CH3C6</p><p n="genre family">Research report</p><p n="discipline">Chemistry</p><p n="disciplinary group">PS</p><p n="grade">D</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">2859</p><p n="number of s-units">130</p><p n="number of p">87</p><p n="number of tables">6</p><p n="number of figures">11</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">15</p><p n="number of lists">0</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">15</p><p n="abstract present">abstract present</p><p n="average words per s-unit">22.0</p><p n="average s-units per p">1.5</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">m</p><p n="year of birth">1984</p><p n="first language">English</p><p n="education">UKA</p><p n="course">Chemistry</p><p n="student ID">0188</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><div1 type="front text"><p rend="bold">A kinetic study of the hydrolysis of crystal violet</p></div1><div1 type="front text"><p rend="bold"><name type="student name"/></p></div1><div1 type="front text"><p rend="bold"><hi rend="italic">Receipt Date:</hi> 22 May 2006</p></div1></front><body><div1 type="abstract"><p n="p1.87"><s n="s1.4;p1.87">Crystal violet undergoes readily hydrolysis to its carbinol form. </s><s n="s2.4;p1.87">The order of reaction with respect to crystal violet and sodium hydroxide have been found to be both one. </s><s n="s3.4;p1.87">The rate constant for the reaction has been measured at different temperatures and the activation energy calculated. </s><s n="s4.4;p1.87">The effect of adding inert salts KNO <hi rend="sub">3</hi> and CaCl <hi rend="sub">2</hi> to the system has been shown to slow down the rate of reaction, and the mixing of acetone or methanol into the reaction as solvents have shown ambiguous results as to what reaction pathways are possible. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">1. Introduction</head><p n="p2.87"><s n="s1.2;p2.87">Crystal violet (CV) <hi rend="bold">1</hi> is a large polyaromatic structure that undergoes hydrolysis to form a carbinol compound <hi rend="bold">2</hi>. </s><s n="s2.2;p2.87">Crystal violet in aqueous solution is violet, but the carbinol derivative is colourless, thus making the rate of reaction ideal for study in UV-Visible spectrometry. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0188j-fig.001"/><p n="p3.87"><s n="s1.1;p3.87">Many studies have already been conducted on this reaction, finding the order with respect to CV and hydroxide ion alongside more complicated factors affecting kinetics such as: varying the inert salt present in solution and varying the solvent the experiment is conducted in. </s></p><p n="p4.87"><s n="s1.1;p4.87">The aim of this brief study was to determine the order of reaction with respect to CV, NaOH, look at the effect of adding inert salts CaCl <hi rend="sub">2</hi> and KNO <hi rend="sub">3</hi> on the rate of reaction, and the effect of different solvent mixtures acetone: water, methanol: water on the rate of reaction. </s></p><p n="p5.87"><s n="s1.1;p5.87">The underlying premise of the kinetic studies is Beer-Lambert Law: </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p6.87"><s n="s1.1;p6.87"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0188j-form.001"/> (1) </s></p><p n="p7.87"><s n="s1.1;p7.87">Where <hi rend="italic">A</hi> is the absorbance, <hi rend="italic">c</hi> is the concentration of solution (mol dm <hi rend="sup">-3</hi>), <hi rend="italic">l</hi> is the path length of the cuvette (cm <hi rend="sup">3</hi>), and is the molar extinction coefficient in mol <hi rend="sup">-1</hi> dm <hi rend="sup">3</hi> cm <hi rend="sup">-3</hi>. </s></p><p n="p8.87"><s n="s1.1;p8.87">By using a UV-Visible spectrometer to measure the absorbance vs time, concentrations can be calculated at time t, and thus the rate of reaction calculated. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">2. Experimental</head><div2><head rend="bold">2.1 Standard Proceedure</head><p n="p9.87"><s n="s1.2;p9.87">The wavelength at which the absorbance of CV in water was determined by performing a scan between 400-700 nm to find <hi rend="sub">max</hi>. </s><s n="s2.2;p9.87">This was found to be 586.54nm, see figure 1. </s></p><p n="p10.87"><s n="s1.1;p10.87">The extinction coefficient at this wavelength is 359 415 mol <hi rend="sup">-1</hi> dm <hi rend="sup">3</hi> cm <hi rend="sup">-3</hi> [1]. </s></p><p n="p11.87"><s n="s1.2;p11.87">Previous experiments used concentrations between 1 x 10 <hi rend="sup">-6</hi> - 5.5 x 10 <hi rend="sup">-6</hi> mol dm <hi rend="sup">-3</hi> [2], and therefore with a stock solution of 2.209 x 10 <hi rend="sup">-4</hi> mol dm <hi rend="sup">-3</hi> it was necessary to dilute the solution by a factor of 100. </s><s n="s2.2;p11.87">The low concentration is necessary due to the poor solubility of the product [3]. </s></p><p n="p12.87"><s n="s1.2;p12.87">The concentration of stock solution provided was questioned when the absorbance read at the beginning of the reaction 0.056 instead of the expected (using Beer-Lambert Law) ~0.6. </s><s n="s2.2;p12.87">Using (1) and the extinction coefficient, it was calculated that the stock solution was of concentration 7.0726 x 10 <hi rend="sup">-5</hi> mol dm <hi rend="sup">-3</hi> and as such only required dilution by a factor of 10. </s></p><p n="p13.87"><s n="s1.2;p13.87">The experiments were conducted in a thermally equilibrated UV-Visible spectrometer. </s><s n="s2.2;p13.87">The solutions of NaOH (0.025 mol dm <hi rend="sup">-3</hi>), water, CV (7.073 x 10 <hi rend="sup">-6</hi> mol dm <hi rend="sup">-3</hi>) were all held to rest in the water bath for 20 minutes prior to a run. </s></p><p n="p14.87"><s n="s1.2;p14.87">Water and crystal violet were added to a cuvette first, then the sodium hydroxide. </s><s n="s2.2;p14.87">The cuvette was then inverted twice to ensure good mixing, and then placed in the UV-Visible spectrometer where the absorbance was measured. </s></p><p n="p15.87"><s n="s1.2;p15.87">Experiments were run between temperature range 273-307K, and the dependence of the hydroxide ion and CV determined by varying the concentration of NaOH between 0.0025 mol dm <hi rend="sup">-3</hi> and 0.01 mol dm <hi rend="sup">-3</hi>. </s><s n="s2.2;p15.87">Results were repeated and then gradients of the graphs averaged. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">2.2 Kinetic Salt Effect</head><p n="p16.87"><s n="s1.2;p16.87">Standardised solutions of 1.006 mol dm <hi rend="sup">-3</hi> CaCl <hi rend="sub">2</hi> and 1.00 mol dm <hi rend="sup">-3</hi> KNO <hi rend="sub">3</hi> were prepared. </s><s n="s2.2;p16.87">Concentrations of 0.001- 0.8 mol dm <hi rend="sup">-3</hi> were added to set concentrations of CV and OH- at 298K and experiments run as described in 2.1. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">2.3 Solvent Effects</head><p n="p17.87"><s n="s1.2;p17.87">Instead of using 100% water in cuvettes; a 50:50 ratio of acetone: water and a 50:50 ratio of methanol: water mixtures were used, carrying out the same experiment as outlined in section 2.1 at different temperatures ranging from 298-331K. Quartz cuvettes were used since acetone dissolves standard plastic cuvettes. </s><s n="s2.2;p17.87">The cuvettes were cleaned and dried with air before use every time to ensure clean. </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">3. Theory</head><div2><head rend="bold">3.1 Orders of reaction with respect to OH- and CV</head><p n="p18.87"><s n="s1.1;p18.87">The rate of reaction is thought to be dependant upon the concentration of OH- and CV: </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p19.87"><s n="s1.1;p19.87">Rate of reaction = <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0188j-form.002"/> (2) </s></p><p n="p20.87"><s n="s1.1;p20.87">Where a and b are the orders of reaction with respect to OH- and CV respectively and the rate of reaction can be thought as the rate of consumption of CV: </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p21.87"><s n="s1.1;p21.87"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0188j-form.003"/> (3) </s></p><p n="p22.87"><s n="s1.1;p22.87">Thus by measuring the reaction as a function of absorbance over time, we can calculate the concentration of CV at that time, and thus by various plots work out the rate constant.By putting OH- in vast excess of CV it can as such be treated as constant: </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p23.87"><s n="s1.1;p23.87"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0188j-form.004"/> (4) </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p24.87"><s n="s1.1;p24.87"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0188j-form.005"/> (5) </s></p><p n="p25.87"><s n="s1.2;p25.87">If the reaction is zeroth order with respect to CV then a plot of Absorbance vs time should be a straight line. </s><s n="s2.2;p25.87">If a plot of -ln(Absorbance) vs time is straight then that means it is first order with respect to CV, and if a plot of 1/Absorbance vs time means that CV is second order with respect to CV. </s></p><p n="p26.87"><s n="s1.1;p26.87">This is due to the different integrated rate laws; first order rate law: </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p27.87"><s n="s1.1;p27.87"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0188j-form.006"/> (6) </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p28.87"><s n="s1.1;p28.87"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0188j-form.007"/> (7) </s></p><p n="p29.87"><s n="s1.1;p29.87">Second order rate law: </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p30.87"><s n="s1.1;p30.87"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0188j-form.008"/> (8) </s></p><p n="p31.87"><s n="s1.1;p31.87">To determine the order of reaction with respect to OH-, the logarithm of (5) can be taken to give: </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p32.87"><s n="s1.1;p32.87"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0188j-form.009"/> (9) </s></p><p n="p33.87"><s n="s1.1;p33.87">Thus by plotting log <hi rend="italic">kobs</hi> vs different [OH-], will yield a graph with gradient <hi rend="italic">b</hi>. </s></p><p n="p34.87"><s n="s1.1;p34.87">From the rate constants at different temperatures by use of the Arrhenius equation, the Activation Energy (<hi rend="italic">Ea</hi>) can be determined: </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p35.87"><s n="s1.1;p35.87"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0188j-form.010"/> (10) </s></p><p n="p36.87"><s n="s1.1;p36.87">Where <hi rend="italic">R</hi> is the molar gas constant (8.315 J mol <hi rend="sup">-1</hi> K <hi rend="sup">-1</hi>), <hi rend="italic">T</hi> is the temperature in Kelvin and <hi rend="italic">A</hi> is a pre-multiplicative constant. </s></p><p n="p37.87"><s n="s1.2;p37.87">By plotting ln <hi rend="italic">k</hi> vs. </s><s n="s2.2;p37.87">1/<hi rend="italic">T</hi>, -<hi rend="italic">Ea/R</hi> is found to be the gradient. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">3.2 Kinetic Salt Effect</head><p n="p38.87"><s n="s1.1;p38.87">The kinetic salt effect is based on the principle that by adding inert salt to a system it will change the rate of reaction but play no part in the reaction itself. </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p39.87"><s n="s1.1;p39.87"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0188j-form.011"/> (11) </s></p><p n="p40.87"><s n="s1.1;p40.87">If the two reactive species coming (A and B) together to form reactive complex have like charges, adding inert salt increases the rate of the reaction, whereas if the two reactive species have different charges adding inert salt decreases the rate of reaction. </s></p><p n="p41.87"><s n="s1.1;p41.87">The formation of a single, highly charged ionic complex from two less highly charged ions is favoured by high ionic strength because the new ion has a denser ionic atmosphere and interacts more strongly, and as such the reactive intermediate complex is more stable than if it were in the solution without inert salt and thus increases the rate of reaction. </s></p><p n="p42.87"><s n="s1.1;p42.87">For ions of opposite charge coming together to form reactive complex intermediate- the charges on the complex cancel and as such the higher the ionic strength of the solution- the less favourable the interactions with the solution and decreases the rate of reaction. [4] </s></p><p n="p43.87"><s n="s1.1;p43.87">This is the theory behind in the kinetic salt equation: </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p44.87"><s n="s1.1;p44.87"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0188j-form.012"/> (12) </s></p><p n="p45.87"><s n="s1.2;p45.87">Where <hi rend="italic">A</hi>= 0.50, <hi rend="italic">zA</hi> and <hi rend="italic">zB</hi> are the charges on ions A and B respectively. </s><s n="s2.2;p45.87"><hi rend="italic">I</hi> is the ionic strength of the solution: </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p46.87"><s n="s1.1;p46.87"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0188j-form.013"/> (13) </s></p><p n="p47.87"><s n="s1.1;p47.87">Where <hi rend="italic">ci</hi> is the individual concentration of the constituent ions, <hi rend="italic">zi</hi> is the charge on those constituent ions. </s></p><p n="p48.87"><s n="s1.3;p48.87">Within the Debye-Hückel limiting law, this allows the elucidation of the charges on the reactive species that come together to form the reactive intermediate by plotting log <hi rend="italic">kobs/k</hi><hi rend="sub">(<hi rend="italic">I=0</hi>)</hi> vs. </s><s n="s2.3;p48.87"><hi rend="italic">I</hi><hi rend="sup">1/2</hi>. </s><s n="s3.3;p48.87">The gradient gives 2 <hi rend="italic">A</hi> <hi rend="italic">zA zB</hi>. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">3.3 Solvent Effects</head><p n="p49.87"><s n="s1.2;p49.87">The interaction between solvent and solute is key and critical to determining kinetics of a reaction in organic chemistry especially- such as the stabilisation of carbocation intermediates by an electron rich donor solvent, or the competition of two nucleophiles. </s><s n="s2.2;p49.87">Also the solute-solute interactions also have a part to play on this effect. </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">4. Results and Discussion</head><div2><head rend="bold">4.1 Order of reaction with respect to CV and OH-</head><p n="p50.87"><s n="s1.1;p50.87">Linear plots of -ln (Absorbance) vs time were obtained, establishing the order with respect to CV from integrated rate laws is first; <hi rend="italic">a</hi>= 1- see figure 2. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0188j-fig.002"><head><hi rend="bold">Fig. 2</hi> - First order plot shows linearity with respect to CV.</head></figure><p n="p51.87"><s n="s1.1;p51.87">Values of <hi rend="italic">kobs</hi> were calculated by using (7), at different concentrations of OH- were obtained and tabulated in table 1. </s></p><table id="BAWE_0188j-tab.001"><head><hi rend="bold">Table 1.</hi> Values of <hi rend="italic">kobs</hi> and corresponding concentrations of hydroxide ion.</head><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p52.87"><s n="s1.1;p52.87">(6) shows that a plot of log <hi rend="italic">kob</hi> vs log [OH-] (see figure 3) will yield the gradient <hi rend="italic">b</hi> - the order of reaction with respect to OH-. </s></p><p n="p53.87"><s n="s1.1;p53.87">Microcal Origin software calculated the gradient as 1.026- rounding to the nearest integer means the order with respect to OH- is one also. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0188j-fig.003"><head><hi rend="bold">Fig. 3</hi> - Plot shows first order dependance with respect to hydroxide.</head></figure><p n="p54.87"><s n="s1.1;p54.87">Thus equation (2) can be updated to: </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p55.87"><s n="s1.1;p55.87">Rate of reaction = <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0188j-form.014"/> (14) </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">4.2 Calculation of Activation Energy</head><p n="p56.87"><s n="s1.2;p56.87">The observed rate constants were found at different temperatures and tabulated in table 2. </s><s n="s2.2;p56.87">As expected the rate constant increased with temperature due to the more internal energy in the system, making it a lot easier to cross energetic barrier from reactants to products. </s></p><table id="BAWE_0188j-tab.002"><head><hi rend="bold">Table 2.</hi> Values of <hi rend="italic">kobs</hi> at different temperatures.</head><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p57.87"><s n="s1.1;p57.87">Using (10), figure 4 was obtained: </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0188j-fig.004"><head><hi rend="bold">Fig. 4</hi> - Calculation of Activation Energy of reaction.</head></figure><p n="p58.87"><s n="s1.4;p58.87">The gradient was calculated using microcal origin to be -6641.6 = -<hi rend="italic">Ea</hi>/<hi rend="italic">R</hi>. </s><s n="s2.4;p58.87">Thus, by multiplication of <hi rend="italic"> - R</hi>; <hi rend="italic">Ea</hi> = 55.21 kJ mol <hi rend="sup">-1</hi>. </s><s n="s3.4;p58.87">The intercept was 20.97 = ln <hi rend="italic">A</hi>. </s><s n="s4.4;p58.87">Thus A = 127 9800 mol <hi rend="sup">-1</hi> dm <hi rend="sup">3</hi> s <hi rend="sup">-1</hi>. </s></p><p n="p59.87"><s n="s1.1;p59.87">By manipulating the Eyring equation into a different form: </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p60.87"><s n="s1.1;p60.87"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0188j-form.015"/> (15) </s></p><p n="p61.87"><s n="s1.1;p61.87">As such at 298 K <hi rend="italic">H</hi>‡ = 52.7 kJ mol <hi rend="sup">-1</hi>, and [2] states it to be 61 kJ mol <hi rend="sup">-1</hi>, thus within 14% of literature value. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">4.3 Kinetic Salt Effect</head><p n="p62.87"><s n="s1.3;p62.87">By adding CaCl <hi rend="sub">2</hi> to reaction it was found that it slowed the reaction down quite considerably (<hi rend="italic">k</hi><hi rend="sub">0</hi>= 0.2693 mol <hi rend="sup">-1</hi> dm <hi rend="sup">3</hi> s <hi rend="sup">-1</hi>) as can be seen tabulated in table 3. </s><s n="s2.3;p62.87">This consistent with predictions that the two reactive species are the same magnitude and of opposite charge. </s><s n="s3.3;p62.87">Thus expect gradient =-1. (<hi rend="italic">zA zB</hi> = -1 x 1 = -1). </s></p><table id="BAWE_0188j-tab.003"><head><hi rend="bold">Table 3.</hi> Values of k at different ionic strengths of CaCl <hi rend="sub">2</hi> .</head><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p63.87"><s n="s1.1;p63.87">Using (12) figure 5 was obtained: </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0188j-fig.005"><head><hi rend="bold">Fig. 5</hi> - Effect of inert salt CaCl <hi rend="sub">2</hi> on rate of reaction.</head></figure><p n="p64.87"><s n="s1.3;p64.87">Microcal origin calculated the gradient to be -0.670. </s><s n="s2.3;p64.87">Thus in line with predictions however the magnitude infers that it is not purely a case of the two species CV and OH- coming together to react. </s><s n="s3.3;p64.87">And that perhaps there is an alternative reaction pathway competing as mentioned in [2]. </s></p><p n="p65.87"><s n="s1.2;p65.87">By adding KNO <hi rend="sub">3</hi> to reaction it was found that it slowed the reaction down quite considerably as can be seen tabulated in table 4 (<hi rend="italic">k</hi><hi rend="sub">0</hi>= 0.2386 mol <hi rend="sup">-1</hi> dm <hi rend="sup">3</hi> s <hi rend="sup">-1</hi>), this is in line with the prediction that the two reactive species are of the same magnitude and opposite charge. </s><s n="s2.2;p65.87">Thus predict gradient =-1. (<hi rend="italic">zA zB</hi> = -1 x 1 = -1). </s></p><table id="BAWE_0188j-tab.004"><head><hi rend="bold">Table 4.</hi> Values of k at different ionic strengths of KNO <hi rend="sub">3</hi> .</head><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p66.87"><s n="s1.1;p66.87">Using (12) figure 6 was obtained: </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0188j-fig.006"><head><hi rend="bold">Fig. 6</hi> - Effect of inert salt KNO <hi rend="sub">3</hi> on rate of reaction.</head></figure><p n="p67.87"><s n="s1.3;p67.87">However microcal origin calculated the gradient to be -0.640. </s><s n="s2.3;p67.87">Thus the sign is correct, but as with CaCl <hi rend="sub">2</hi>, the magnitude is wrong. </s><s n="s3.3;p67.87">The two inert salts should have the same effect on the rate of reaction- just providing a stronger background ion atmosphere. </s></p><p n="p68.87"><s n="s1.2;p68.87">The results here are inconclusive and go against what expectations. </s><s n="s2.2;p68.87">As such, the only the explanation in [2] that there is a competing reverse reaction (going from <hi rend="bold">2</hi> to <hi rend="bold">1</hi>) contributing to these anomalies. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">4.4 Solent Effects</head><p n="p69.87"><s n="s1.1;p69.87">As in 4.2, the calculation of the activation energy can elaborate any change of kinetics by comparing to original results. </s></p><p n="p70.87"><s n="s1.2;p70.87">Here an acetone: water 50:50 mixture was used, and the following rate constants obtained. </s><s n="s2.2;p70.87">The rates increased in comparison to pure water solution. </s></p><table id="BAWE_0188j-tab.005"><head><hi rend="bold">Table 5.</hi> Values of <hi rend="italic">k</hi> at different temperatures.</head><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p71.87"><s n="s1.1;p71.87">Using (12) the figure 7 was plotted: </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0188j-fig.007"><head><hi rend="bold">Fig. 7</hi> - Calculation of Activation Energy of reaction.</head></figure><p n="p72.87"><s n="s1.3;p72.87">However microcal origin calculated the gradient to be -8897.7. </s><s n="s2.3;p72.87">Thus <hi rend="italic">Ea</hi> = 73.98 kJ mol <hi rend="sup">-1</hi>. </s><s n="s3.3;p72.87">Using (15) at 298K, <hi rend="italic">H</hi>‡ = 71.5 kJ mol <hi rend="sup">-1</hi>. </s></p><p n="p73.87"><s n="s1.2;p73.87">The fact the rate increases however the activation energy is also larger is against expectation. </s><s n="s2.2;p73.87">However is in line with literature values; the rate constant at 298K for a 50:50 water: acetone mixture is 0.329 mol <hi rend="sup">-1</hi> dm <hi rend="sup">3</hi> s <hi rend="sup">-1</hi> [3], and these experiments calculate it to be 0.355 mol <hi rend="sup">-1</hi> dm <hi rend="sup">3</hi> s <hi rend="sup">-1</hi>. </s></p><p n="p74.87"><s n="s1.1;p74.87">The discrepancies in activation energy and rate can be explained by the fact that acetone is a more polar solvent than water, and as such can help donate electron density to the unstable carbocation of crystal violet, as such this would increase the rate of reaction, however the activation energy is now higher due to the incoming nucleophile having to break the stronger- Van der Waals forces between the substrate and the solvent. </s></p><p n="p75.87"><s n="s1.2;p75.87">A second mixture was used; methanol: water in a 50:50 ratio. </s><s n="s2.2;p75.87">This yielded a rapid exponential decay curve of Absorbance vs time graph (see figure 8). </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0188j-fig.008"><head><hi rend="bold">Fig. 8</hi> - Rapid exponential decay curve.</head></figure><p n="p76.87"><s n="s1.1;p76.87">When trying to apply the first order integrated rate law, a non-linear graph was produced (see figure 9.) </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0188j-fig.009"><head><hi rend="bold">Fig. 9</hi> - First order plot showing does not apply to methanol.</head></figure><p n="p77.87"><s n="s1.1;p77.87">It was evident that the reaction was occurring at a much larger rate and was almost over in the first 100 s; thus a 2 <hi rend="sup">nd</hi> order plot using (8) was applied yielding a linear plot. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0188j-fig.010"><head><hi rend="bold">Fig. 10</hi> - Second order plot over the first 100s of reaction</head></figure><p n="p78.87"><s n="s1.1;p78.87">More data was complied thus over a range of temperatures in table 5. </s></p><table id="BAWE_0188j-tab.006"><head><hi rend="bold">Table 6.</hi> Values of k at different temperatures.</head><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p79.87"><s n="s1.1;p79.87">Using the Arrhenius equation this yielded figure 11 </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0188j-fig.011"><head><hi rend="bold">Fig. 11</hi> - Calculation of Activation Energy of reaction.</head></figure><p n="p80.87"><s n="s1.1;p80.87">Which microcal origin calculated the gradient as: -4760.7, thus the activation energy is a lot lower and 39.6 kJ mol-1. </s></p><p n="p81.87"><s n="s1.1;p81.87">Methanol is a competing nucleophile, and as such changes the whole kinetics of the reaction to include the two nucleophiles and as such is little interest or sense to this study. </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">5. Conclusions</head><p n="p82.87"><s n="s1.2;p82.87">The results of the experiments have shown many important factors that affect the kinetics of the hydrolysis of crystal violet. </s><s n="s2.2;p82.87">Such as the order of reaction with respect to OH- and CV are both first, but the effect of adding an inert salt to the solution proved that there is perhaps a secondary pathway of the reaction taking place also- which is also eluded to in [5]. </s></p><p n="p83.87"><s n="s1.3;p83.87">The solvent effects were unexpected; methanol especially exhibiting second order reaction kinetics. </s><s n="s2.3;p83.87">Thus a competing nucleophilic attack, rather than a solvent effect- and as such a poor illustrator of the effects of solvent on the reaction kinetics. </s><s n="s3.3;p83.87">However the acetone results were good, and in line with literature data- and implying that the acetone stabilises the carbocation more readily than water (increase in rate), but the OH- nucleophile has more difficulty displacing the acetone due to the stronger Van der Waals interaction occurring between CV and acetone and this is seen in a larger activation energy (compared to water solvent). </s></p><p n="p84.87"><s n="s1.3;p84.87">The accuracy obtained here when compared (to the few experimental results available), shows that for a limited undergraduate set up the results are quite good. </s><s n="s2.3;p84.87">Ideally the reaction would be carried out in an inert nitrogen atmosphere, and all solvents properly degassed before used as well as crystal violet solid being prepared from scratch and re-crystallised before being made into a solution to increase purity of reagents. </s><s n="s3.3;p84.87">Alongside all experiments being repeated- to decrease the errors, however this would require more time than the three days provided. </s></p><p n="p85.87"><s n="s1.3;p85.87">For the ionic salt effect, more results would need to be obtained to be more conclusive about another reaction pathway; especially at very low ionic strength. </s><s n="s2.3;p85.87">Some of the higher ionic strength experiments conducted here were probably out of the Debye-Hückel limiting laws and as such are unreliable. </s><s n="s3.3;p85.87">Also a larger range of salts could also be used to look at the effect. </s></p><p n="p86.87"><s n="s1.1;p86.87">For the solvents, a wider range of solvents could be used to investigate solvent effects, however caution has to be applied when choosing a solvent; since methanol was a competing nucleophile to hydroxide and change the whole kinetics of the situation. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">6. Acknowledgements</head><p n="p87.87"><s n="s1.2;p87.87">I would like to acknowledge and thank my laboratory partner Richard Johnson for the joint experimental results we obtained; Robert Davies and Louise Sims for sharing their data on acetone: water solvent mixtures and KNO <hi rend="sub">3</hi> ionic salt reactions. </s><s n="s2.2;p87.87">Also the demonstrators present in the laboratory for on hand assistance. </s></p></div1></body><back><div1 type="bibliography"><head rend="bold">7. References</head><p>[1] Du H.; Fuh R. A.; Li J.; Corkan A.; Lindsey J. S. PhotochemCAD: A computer-aided design and research tool in photochemistry. <hi rend="italic">Photochemistry and Photobiology,</hi> 1998, <hi rend="bold">68</hi>, 141-142. </p><p>[2] Beach S. F.; Hepworth J. D.; Mason M.; Swarbrick E. A. A kinetic study of the hydrolysis of crystal violet and some terminal bridged anaolgues. <hi rend="italic">Dyes and Pigments</hi>, 1999, <hi rend="bold">42</hi>, 71-77.</p><p>[3] Turgeon J. C.; LaMer V. K. The Kinetics of the Formation of the Carbinol of Crystal Violet. <hi rend="italic">Journal American Chemical Society</hi>, 1952,<hi rend="bold"> 74</hi>, 5988-5995.</p><p>[4] Atkins P.W.; de Paula J. <hi rend="italic">Physical Chemistry</hi>, 7<hi rend="sup">th</hi> ed,; Oxford University Press: Oxford; 2002; p. 962.</p><p>[5] Ritchie C.D.; Skinner G.A.; Badding V.G; Solvent Effects on the Reactions of Stabilized Carbonium Ions with Nucleophiles. <hi rend="italic">Journal American Chemical Society</hi>, 1967, <hi rend="bold">89</hi>, 2063-2071</p></div1><div1 type="appendix"><head rend="bold">8. Appendix</head><p/></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
