<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_0188f" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Answer sheet for Session 4</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note/></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">3</p><p n="date">2006-03</p><p n="module title">Applications of Theoretical Chemistry</p><p n="module code">CH3D5</p><p n="genre family">Exercise</p><p n="discipline">Chemistry</p><p n="disciplinary group">PS</p><p n="grade">D</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">2112</p><p n="number of s-units">84</p><p n="number of p">51</p><p n="number of tables">11</p><p n="number of figures">5</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">69</p><p n="number of lists">16</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">0</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">25.1</p><p n="average s-units per p">1.6</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">m</p><p n="year of birth">1984</p><p n="first language">English</p><p n="education">UKA</p><p n="course">Chemistry</p><p n="student ID">0188</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><docTitle><titlePart rend="bold">CH3D5 Answer sheet for Session 4 Name: <name type="student name"/>, <name type="tutor name"/> and <name type="tutor name"/></titlePart></docTitle></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">Part I</head><div2><head rend="underlined bold">H2O</head><div3><head rend="bold">Why do we need a doublet state for the OH calculation? </head><p n="p1.51"><s n="s1.2;p1.51">OH is a radical, thus has one unpaired electron. </s><s n="s2.2;p1.51">S=1/2 spin multiplicity =2(1/2)+1 = 2 => doublet. </s></p></div3><div3><head rend="bold">Do you need to do more than Hartree-Fock for the H atom? Why/why not? </head><p n="p2.51"><s n="s1.1;p2.51">No, H is a 1 electron system, as such does not require any electron correlation or exchange terms- thus post Hartree-Fock theories offer no advantage other than to take longer in terms of computation time to reach the same answer. </s></p><list type="simple"><head><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0188f-form.001"/></head><item><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0188f-form.002"/></item><item><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0188f-form.003"/></item><item><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0188f-form.004"/></item></list></div3><div3><head rend="bold">Show your working to calculate the bond energy. </head><p n="p3.51"><s n="s1.1;p3.51"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0188f-form.005"/> </s></p><p n="p4.51"><s n="s1.1;p4.51"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0188f-form.006"/> </s></p><p n="p5.51"><s n="s1.1;p5.51"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0188f-form.007"/> </s></p><list type="simple"><head><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0188f-form.008"/></head><item><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0188f-form.009"/></item><item><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0188f-form.010"/></item><item><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0188f-form.011"/></item></list></div3><div3><head rend="bold">Show your working to calculate the bond energy. </head><p n="p6.51"><s n="s1.1;p6.51"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0188f-form.012"/> </s></p><p n="p7.51"><s n="s1.1;p7.51"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0188f-form.013"/> </s></p><p n="p8.51"><s n="s1.1;p8.51"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0188f-form.014"/> </s></p></div3><div3><head rend="bold">What do you think are the main sources of error in your computed CCSD(T) result? </head><p n="p9.51"><s n="s1.1;p9.51">The sources of error underlying computational calculations are 1) the level of theory used (high level meaning it has few or very good approximations, and low level meaning it has many or not very good approximations), 2) The basis set used for geometry optimisation and energy calculation, 3) The geometry optimisation (dependant upon the level of theory used and basis set). </s></p><p n="p10.51"><s n="s1.2;p10.51">Here the two levels of theory used are post HF theories- which include CI terms that help correct electron correlation in HF theory. </s><s n="s2.2;p10.51">Post HF theory is quite high thus I expect it not to be a large source of error here. </s></p><p n="p11.51"><s n="s1.2;p11.51">The geometry was optimised at the same level of theory and the same basis set as the energy calculation. </s><s n="s2.2;p11.51">Thus since the level of theory is high, it is likely that the errors here are dependant upon the basis set. </s></p><p n="p12.51"><s n="s1.3;p12.51">The size of the basis set is essential in calculations, since it affects the geometry optimisation and the energy calculation of the geometry optimisation. </s><s n="s2.3;p12.51">Fundamentally if a insufficient basis set is chosen, then the calculation is flawed. </s><s n="s3.3;p12.51">Here a slightly larger than normal basis set is employed, however to make CI term better in calculation, more heavy atoms could be added and polarisable functions to the basis set. </s></p></div3></div2><div2><head rend="underlined bold">CH2 radical</head><list type="simple"><head><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0188f-form.015"/></head><item><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0188f-form.016"/></item><item><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0188f-form.017"/></item></list><div3><head rend="bold">Which electronic state is lower and by how much? </head><p n="p13.51"><s n="s1.1;p13.51">The triplet state lies lower in energy than the singlet and by: </s></p><p n="p14.51"><s n="s1.1;p14.51"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0188f-form.018"/> </s></p><list type="simple"><head><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0188f-form.019"/></head><item><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0188f-form.020"/></item><item><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0188f-form.021"/></item></list></div3><div3><head rend="bold">Which electronic state is lower and by how much? </head><p n="p15.51"><s n="s1.1;p15.51">The triplet state lies lower in energy than the singlet and by: </s></p><p n="p16.51"><s n="s1.1;p16.51"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0188f-form.022"/> </s></p><list type="simple"><head><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0188f-form.023"/></head><item><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0188f-form.024"/></item></list></div3><div3><head rend="bold">Which electronic state is lower and by how much? </head><p n="p17.51"><s n="s1.1;p17.51">The triplet state lies lower in energy than the singlet and by: </s></p><p n="p18.51"><s n="s1.1;p18.51"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0188f-form.025"/> </s></p></div3><div3><head rend="bold">Comment on the likely sources of error in your calculations. </head><p n="p19.51"><s n="s1.5;p19.51">Again as stated earlier, the error in the calculations of energy is dependant upon 1) the level of theory, 2) the basis set and 3) the geometry optimisation . </s><s n="s2.5;p19.51">There are two different types of theory at use here: DFT and post HF theory. </s><s n="s3.5;p19.51">The post HF calculations are very consistent within each other: within ~0.05% of each other and 0.5% consistent with DFT calculations. </s><s n="s4.5;p19.51">The geometry was optimised at the same level as the energy was calculated at. </s><s n="s5.5;p19.51">Thus the main source of error here is the level of theory used is insufficient to deal with the triplet states, or the size of the basis set is not large enough. </s></p></div3></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">Part II</head><div2><head rend="underlined bold">Decomposition of methanal</head><list type="ordered"><head><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0188f-form.026"/> calculations:</head><item><hi rend="bold">What is ETS?</hi> <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0188f-form.027"/></item><item><hi rend="bold">What is Emethanal?</hi> <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0188f-form.028"/></item><item><hi rend="bold">What is EH2?</hi> <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0188f-form.029"/></item><item><hi rend="bold">What is ECO?</hi> <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0188f-form.030"/></item><item><hi rend="bold">What is Eproducts?</hi> <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0188f-form.031"/></item><item><hi rend="bold">What is the height of the barrier between reactants and transition state (in kJ/mol) at the MP2/aug-cc-pVDZ// HF/6-31G level of theory?</hi> <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0188f-form.032"/> = <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0188f-form.033"/> = <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0188f-form.034"/> = <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0188f-form.035"/></item><item><hi rend="bold">What is the reverse barrier (kJ/mol)?</hi> <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0188f-form.036"/> = <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0188f-form.037"/> = <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0188f-form.038"/> = <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0188f-form.039"/></item></list><div3><head rend="bold">Compare your MP2-based results with your previous calculations and best theoretical estimates from the literature. </head><table id="BAWE_0188f-tab.001"><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p20.51"><s n="s1.3;p20.51">Here the MP2 based results are the best calculations I have performed in terms of accuracy of forward (within 13% of experiment) and reverse barrier (within 1% of experiment). </s><s n="s2.3;p20.51">However DFT-PBEPBE is the best I have calculated for the forward barrier. </s><s n="s3.3;p20.51">The best theoretical estimates from literature are better than my forward barrier calculations, and are within 3% of experiment (and correctly predict the forward barrier is lower than the reverse barrier, with MP2 they are the wrong way around!) </s></p></div3></div2><div2><head rend="underlined bold">Hydrogen fluoride dimer</head><div3><head rend="bold">Do you think the Hartree-Fock geometry of the HF dimer is suitable for use in SPE calculations? Why/why not? How did the corresponding Hartree-Fock interaction energy compare with experiment? </head><table id="BAWE_0188f-tab.002"><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p21.51"><s n="s1.3;p21.51">The interaction energy HF calculations provided compared to experiment was poor (62% away from experiment), however the geometry it provided was relatively good. </s><s n="s2.3;p21.51">R within 0.1 Å. α and β within 3˚ of experimental values. </s><s n="s3.3;p21.51">Thus it is a valid to use the Hartree-Fock dimer geometry and calculate a SPE using MP2. </s></p><list type="simple"><head rend="underlined">MP2/aug-cc-pVDZ//HF/6-31G SPE calculations:</head><item><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0188f-form.040"/></item><item><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0188f-form.041"/></item></list></div3><div3><head rend="bold">Show your working to obtain the interaction energy:</head><list type="simple"><item><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0188f-form.042"/></item><item><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0188f-form.043"/></item><item><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0188f-form.044"/></item><item><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0188f-form.045"/></item></list><p n="p22.51"/></div3><div3><head rend="bold">Is the interaction energy calculated at the MP2/aug-cc-pVDZ//HF-6-31G level of theory an improvement over your HF and DFT estimates? Make a brief comment on your result. </head><table id="BAWE_0188f-tab.003"><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p23.51"><s n="s1.4;p23.51">The interaction energy calculated at MP2/aug-cc-pVDZ//HF-6-31G level is within 6.0% of experiment, whereas the HF/6-31+G(d,p) calculation is within 6.5% of experiment and LSDA/6-31+G(d,p) is within 95.6% of experiment! </s><s n="s2.4;p23.51">Thus it is a slight improvement compared to the HF/6-31+G(d,p) level, but is a lot better than the LSDA/6-31+G(d,p) estimate of interaction energy. </s><s n="s3.4;p23.51">However in terms of bond angles it is the same if not slightly further away from experiment than HF/6-31+G(d,p) level, but gives a hugely better estimate of R: 0.6% within experiment, instead of 3.2% at the HF/6-31+G(d,p) level. </s><s n="s4.4;p23.51">Thus the improvement is not vast compared to the HF method previously employed, but it is noticeable. </s></p><list type="simple"><head rend="underlined">MP2/aug-cc-pVDZ//MP2/6-31G SPE calculations:</head><item><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0188f-form.046"/></item><item><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0188f-form.047"/></item></list></div3><div3><head rend="bold">Show your working to obtain the interaction energy:</head><list type="simple"><item><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0188f-form.048"/></item><item><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0188f-form.049"/></item><item><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0188f-form.050"/></item><item><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0188f-form.051"/></item></list><p n="p24.51"/></div3><div3><head rend="bold">Give brief comments on whether re-optimising at the MP2/6-31G level has made a substantial improvement to your SPE calculations. </head><p n="p25.51"><s n="s1.3;p25.51">Re-optimising at MP2/6-31G level has decreased the error with respect to experiment from 6.0% to 0%. </s><s n="s2.3;p25.51">This is a substantial improvement in calculation, however the previous result was probably within the experimental error, and thus sufficient. </s><s n="s3.3;p25.51">However it is very pleasing to get "the" answer! </s></p></div3><div3><head rend="bold">Give a brief comment on the balance between resource required (such as computing time) vs. quality of results, using these two SPE calculations as examples. </head><p n="p26.51"><s n="s1.3;p26.51">It is always the aim of any calculation or experiment to gain the highest level of accuracy possible, however this has to be balanced by the resources required to achieve this. </s><s n="s2.3;p26.51">Here both results are perfectly acceptable (when compared to experiment and errors associated), one result however is better in quality than the other. </s><s n="s3.3;p26.51">However in larger systems, when computing time will be large anyway, there could be a significant argument for using SPE calculations instead of MP2//MP2 calculations due to the extra time it would require to calculate the results. </s></p></div3></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">Part 3</head><div2><head rend="underlined bold">H2O... HF complex</head><div3><head rend="underlined bold">Methodology</head><list type="ordered"><item>1) Search Literature for Experimental evidence of structure</item><item>2) Ideas for structures based on Dipole Moments and literature</item><item>3) "Low-level" preliminary calculations of possible structures</item><item>4) Chose best structure and calculate at higher levels of theory</item><item>5) Compare to experimental results/literature calculations</item></list><p n="p27.51"/></div3><div3><head rend="underlined bold">1) Literature Search</head><p n="p28.51"><s n="s1.1;p28.51">Literature searching yielded a paper published in 1992: "The nature of the Hydrogen Bond to Water in the Gas Phase" (<ref target="BAWE_0188f-ftnote.001"/>) This showed the main isomer and also gave experimental values for O-F bond lengths to compare calculations to: </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0188f-ftnote.001"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.5;pn1.1">A. C. </s><s n="s2.5;pn1.1">Legon, D. J. Millen, <hi rend="italic">Chem.</hi> </s><s rend="italic" n="s3.5;pn1.1">Soc. </s><s rend="italic" n="s4.5;pn1.1">Rev. </s><s n="s5.5;pn1.1">, <hi rend="bold">1</hi>, 71 (1992) </s></p></note></div3><div3><head rend="underlined bold">2) Ideas, Dipole Moments, Van Der Waals Interactions</head><p n="p29.51"><s n="s1.1;p29.51">Water obviously has a dipole moment, due to the very electronegative Oxygen atom drawing electron density towards itself, and away from the two hydrogens inducing a permanent dipole moment: </s></p><p n="p30.51"><s n="s1.1;p30.51">This was calculated to be <hi rend="underlined">2.235 Debyes</hi> at HF/6-31+G(d,p) level. </s></p><p n="p31.51"><s n="s1.1;p31.51">Hydrogen fluoride similarly has a permanent dipole moment, due to the very electronegative fluorine atom dragging electron density towards itself, creating a permanent dipole. </s></p><p n="p32.51"><s n="s1.1;p32.51">This was calculated to be <hi rend="underlined">2.042 Debyes</hi> at HF/6-31+G(d,p) level. </s></p><p n="p33.51"><s n="s1.1;p33.51">Based on this dipole moments and the prior calculations performed on HF dimer, there are some obvious possible structures for the dimer: </s></p><p n="p34.51"><s n="s1.1;p34.51">Dimer 2 corresponds to that proposed in literature <hi rend="sup bold">(3)</hi> </s></p></div3><div3><head rend="underlined bold">3) "Low-level" preliminary calculations of possible structures </head><p n="p35.51"><s n="s1.3;p35.51">In previous long range weekly bonded interactions (methane, hydrogen fluoride dimer) calculations; DFT-LSDA performed poorly with the H-F dimers however HF/6-31G and HF/6-31+G(d,p) provided reasonable results. </s><s n="s2.3;p35.51">From this premise, I decided that it would be best to do "low" level calculations with Hartree-Fock instead of a DFT theory (however a DFT theory at high level may provide a good answer for the weak interaction). </s><s n="s3.3;p35.51">Since the comparative computation time on these similar systems between HF/6-31G and a larger basis of 6-31+G(d,p) has been small, I decided there was no reason not to use the larger basis set- which in previous weak interaction calculations has been very good. </s></p></div3></div2><div2><head rend="underlined bold">Monomer Geometry and Energies optimised at HF/6-31+G(d,p):</head><table id="BAWE_0188f-tab.004"><row><cell/></row></table><div3><head rend="underlined bold">Dimer 1</head><p n="p36.51"><s n="s1.1;p36.51">Dimer 1's structure and energy was found by optimising to the same level of theory as monomers, the structure can be seen below: </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0188f-fig.001"/><table id="BAWE_0188f-tab.005"><row><cell/></row></table><list type="simple"><item><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0188f-form.052"/></item><item><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0188f-form.053"/></item><item><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0188f-form.054"/></item><item><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0188f-form.055"/></item></list><p n="p37.51"><s n="s1.1;p37.51">The energy is at a true localised minima or minimum since all the vibrational frequencies are a) real and b) positive. </s></p></div3><div3><head rend="underlined bold">Dimer 2</head><p n="p38.51"><s n="s1.1;p38.51">Dimer 2's structure and energy was found by optimising to the same level of theory as monomers, the structure can be seen below: </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0188f-fig.002"/><p n="p39.51"><s n="s1.1;p39.51">This is the same geometry as outlined in <hi rend="sup bold">(3)</hi>, which coincides with the notion that the Hydrogen on HF is bonding to a lone pair on the Oxygen, and thus leads to this pseudo-tetrahedral angle. </s></p><table id="BAWE_0188f-tab.006"><row><cell/></row></table><list type="simple"><item><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0188f-form.056"/></item><item><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0188f-form.057"/></item><item><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0188f-form.058"/></item><item><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0188f-form.059"/></item></list><p n="p40.51"><s n="s1.1;p40.51">The energy is at a true localised minima or minimum since all the vibrational frequencies are a) real and b) positive. </s></p></div3><div3><head rend="underlined bold">Dimer 3</head><p n="p41.51"><s n="s1.1;p41.51">Dimer 3's structure and energy was found by optimising to the same level of theory as monomers, the structure can be seen below: </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0188f-fig.003"/><table id="BAWE_0188f-tab.007"><row><cell/></row></table><list type="simple"><item><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0188f-form.060"/></item><item><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0188f-form.061"/></item><item><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0188f-form.062"/></item><item><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0188f-form.063"/></item></list><p n="p42.51"><s n="s1.1;p42.51">The energy is at a true localised minima or minimum since all the vibrational frequencies are a) real and b) positive. </s></p></div3><div3><head rend="underlined bold">4) Best Structure</head><p n="p43.51"><s n="s1.5;p43.51">Dimer 2 is the best structure in terms that it provides the largest interaction energy, however the interaction energy is lower than the experimental energy! </s><s n="s2.5;p43.51">Dimer 1 has a similarly low energy. </s><s n="s3.5;p43.51">Geometrically Dimer 2 better- marginally better O-F distance, and structure is inline with predicted non-planar structure (~60°). </s><s n="s4.5;p43.51">Thus making Dimer 1 a local minima, and Dimer 2 likely the global minima. </s><s n="s5.5;p43.51">Dimer 3 however as predicted earlier is not the global minima, and has a very small energy interaction. </s></p><p n="p44.51"><s n="s1.3;p44.51">Dimer 2 was selected as the best structure, and re-optimised at a higher level of theory. </s><s n="s2.3;p44.51">MP2 was chosen for this task, since it appeared to outperform other theoretical calculations when looking at the hydrogen fluoride dimer. </s><s n="s3.3;p44.51">Also it should outperform HF calculations, due to the extra CI terms which correct correlation. </s></p><p n="p45.51"><s n="s1.1;p45.51">The geometry of the system was optimised at the same level as the energy was to be calculated, as earlier in this lab this yielded the best results, and with negligible extra computation time (compared to SPE). </s></p><table id="BAWE_0188f-tab.008"><head rend="bold">Monomer geometries were optimised at MP2/aug-cc-pVDZ level:</head><row><cell/></row></table><div4><head rend="underlined bold">H2O--HF MP2/aug-cc-pVDZ dimer results:</head><figure id="BAWE_0188f-fig.004"/><table id="BAWE_0188f-tab.009"><row><cell/></row></table><list type="simple"><item><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0188f-form.064"/></item><item><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0188f-form.065"/></item><item><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0188f-form.066"/></item></list><p n="p46.51"><s n="s1.2;p46.51">The interaction energy here is even larger than at the HF/6-31+G(d,p) level! </s><s n="s2.2;p46.51">However the r(O-F) distance is substantially better and the angle too. </s></p><p n="p47.51"><s n="s1.2;p47.51">Surprised by this I decided to revert back to Hartree-Fock theory, using a larger basis set since they were very reliable last time. </s><s n="s2.2;p47.51">Again since the system is small, and led to better results last time, I used the same level of theory and basis set for the monomer geometry optimisation as well as the dimer energy calculation. </s></p><table id="BAWE_0188f-tab.010"><head rend="bold">Monomer geometries were optimised at HF/6-311++G(2df,2pd) level:</head><row><cell/></row></table></div4><div4><head rend="underlined bold">H2O--HF HF/6-311++G(2df,2pd) dimer results:</head><figure id="BAWE_0188f-fig.005"/><table id="BAWE_0188f-tab.011"><row><cell/></row></table><list type="simple"><item><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0188f-form.067"/></item><item><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0188f-form.068"/></item><item><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0188f-form.069"/></item></list><p n="p48.51"><s n="s1.2;p48.51">This calculation is far closer to experimental values than before in terms of geometric and energetically. </s><s n="s2.2;p48.51">It appears to have modelled the interaction well and without the need for CI- implying that correlation is not important in this dimer situation? </s></p></div4></div3><div3><head rend="underlined bold">5) Comparison to Experimental Results and Conclusions</head><p n="p49.51"><s n="s1.4;p49.51">Comparing the two high level calculations. </s><s n="s2.4;p49.51">They both over estimate the interaction energy, however the MP2 by 26% and the HF only by 4.5%. </s><s n="s3.4;p49.51">Also the angle - deviation from the planar structure is better in the HF calculation than the MP2 and better than previously calculated when compared with experimental data. </s><s n="s4.4;p49.51">However the O-F distance is better with MP2 than with HF calculations- 0.2% instead of 2% within experiment. </s></p><p n="p50.51"><s n="s1.3;p50.51">I suspected the post-HF interaction energy calculations would be better than the high level HF calculations. </s><s n="s2.3;p50.51">Here I was wrong, when comparing to experimental data. </s><s n="s3.3;p50.51">On the whole however the increase in basis set size has helped to estimate better interaction energies and geometric parameters of the dimer. </s></p><p n="p51.51"><s n="s1.1;p51.51">I would have been interested to have performed a high level DFT calculation (perhaps PBEPBE with a large basis set), to see how well that performed comparatively to the methods examined here. </s></p></div3></div2></div1></body><back/></text></TEI.2>
