<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_0188a" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Experiment Two: Rates of Reaction I</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">The document has a title page which contains:
document title
title part</note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">Language used in quote: <foreign id="English">English</foreign></note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">deleted: page numbers
</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">1</p><p n="date">2004-02</p><p n="module title">Chemistry Laboratory and Assessed Work</p><p n="module code">CH155</p><p n="genre family">Methodology recount</p><p n="discipline">Chemistry</p><p n="disciplinary group">PS</p><p n="grade">D</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">1905</p><p n="number of s-units">128</p><p n="number of p">98</p><p n="number of tables">7</p><p n="number of figures">2</p><p n="number of block quotes">1</p><p n="number of formulae">32</p><p n="number of lists">0</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">6</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">14.9</p><p n="average s-units per p">1.3</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">m</p><p n="year of birth">1984</p><p n="first language">English</p><p n="education">UKA</p><p n="course">Mchem/Chem</p><p n="student ID">0188</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><titlePart>YEAR ONE PHYSICAL CHEMISTRY FORMAL LABORATORY REPORT</titlePart><docTitle><titlePart>EXPERIMENT TWO: RATES OF REACTION I</titlePart></docTitle><titlePart>BY <name type="student name"/></titlePart><titlePart>20 <hi rend="sup">TH</hi> FEBRUARY 2004</titlePart><titlePart>LAB PARTNER: <name type="other"/></titlePart></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">1. Introduction</head><p n="p1.98"><s n="s1.2;p1.98">The aim of this experiment is to investigate the rate of a chemical reaction, and see how this is dependant on the temperature. </s><s n="s2.2;p1.98">The reaction to be studied is the oxidation of benzyl alcohol in an acid permanganate solution: </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p2.98"><s n="s1.1;p2.98"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0188a-form.001"/> </s></p><p n="p3.98"><s n="s1.2;p3.98">In this experiment benzyl alcohol and the acid ion are present in large excess, and therefore their concentrations can be assumed to remain constant. </s><s n="s2.2;p3.98">Thus the only measurable concentration is that of MnO <hi rend="sub">4</hi>-, and the rate of its disappearance can be measured to ultimately form a rate equation for this reaction. </s></p><p n="p4.98"><s n="s1.3;p4.98">The rate of disappearance of MnO <hi rend="sub">4</hi>- can be found by taking aliquots of the mixture at regular time intervals and adding potassium iodide to the mixture. </s><s n="s2.3;p4.98">This will remove all permanganate, and thus stop the oxidation of benzyl alcohol. </s><s n="s3.3;p4.98">This will liberate a proportional quantity of iodine: </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p5.98"><s n="s1.1;p5.98"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0188a-form.002"/> </s></p><p n="p6.98"><s n="s1.1;p6.98">The number of moles of liberated Iodine can be found by titrating the solution against a solution of standardised sodium thiosulphate. </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p7.98"><s n="s1.1;p7.98"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0188a-form.003"/> </s></p><p n="p8.98"><s n="s1.1;p8.98">The concentration of MnO <hi rend="sub">4</hi>- is thus known for a given value of time, and hence the order of reaction with respect to MnO <hi rend="sub">4</hi>- can be found. </s></p><p n="p9.98"><s n="s1.3;p9.98">When the concentration of MnO <hi rend="sub">4</hi>- is plotted against time, we can see the reaction proceed as a function of time. </s><s n="s2.3;p9.98">If the reaction is first order with respect to permanganate then when examining the graph with a "half-life" method it is found that consecutive half lives are the same, this is only true for a first order reaction. </s><s n="s3.3;p9.98">If the graph is a straight line, then this means the rate of reaction is zeroth order with respect to permanganate ion. </s></p><p n="p10.98"><s n="s1.1;p10.98">The overall rate equation can be written as: </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p11.98"><s n="s1.1;p11.98"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0188a-form.004"/> </s></p><p n="p12.98"><s n="s1.1;p12.98">Where a, b and c are orders of reaction with respect to their respective reagent and intergers to be determined. k is the equilibrium constant also to be determined. </s></p><p n="p13.98"><s n="s1.1;p13.98">In this experiment, the concentrations of benzyl alcohol and permanganate are in excess, and can be assumed to be constant, thus what is observed is first order-pseudo rate equation: </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p14.98"><s n="s1.1;p14.98"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0188a-form.005"/> </s></p><p n="p15.98"><s n="s1.1;p15.98">K <hi rend="sub">obs</hi> and c can be found by integrating the appropriate order rate equation, and plotting the relevant values. </s></p><p n="p16.98"><s n="s1.2;p16.98">The order with respect to benzyl alcohol, and the acid are found from examining the results of different experiments. </s><s n="s2.2;p16.98">Once this has been done, the rate constant for the rate equation can be found by equating equations (4) and (5). </s></p><p n="p17.98"><s n="s1.1;p17.98">There is a variation of k with temperature, Arrhenius in 1889 found a relationship that governs this whole concept: </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p18.98"><s n="s1.1;p18.98"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0188a-form.006"/> </s></p><p n="p19.98"><s n="s1.1;p19.98">where A is the pre-exponential (frequency) factor, E is the activation energy and R the molar gas constant. </s></p><p n="p20.98"><s n="s1.1;p20.98">By manipulating this equation, it is possible (with different sets of values of T and k), to find A and E, by graphical means. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">2. Safety Procedures</head><p n="p21.98"><s rend="underlined bold" n="s1.1;p21.98">b </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">3. Method</head><p n="p22.98"><s n="s1.3;p22.98">180.0 cm <hi rend="sup">3</hi> of benzyl alcohol solution (2.33 x 10 <hi rend="sup">-3</hi> mol dm <hi rend="sup">-3</hi> benzyl alcohol, 0.68 mol dm <hi rend="sup">-3</hi> sulphuric acid, 20% acetic acid, with dilution factor 180/200), was dispensed from a burette into a 500 cm <hi rend="sup">3</hi> conical flask. </s><s n="s2.3;p22.98">20.0 cm <hi rend="sup">3</hi> of potassium permanganate (4.06 x 10 <hi rend="sup">-3</hi> mol dm <hi rend="sup">-3</hi>) solution was pipetted into a separate conical flask. </s><s n="s3.3;p22.98">These two conical flasks were placed into a thermostat bath (at 32.5°C), and left to reach equilibrium for fifteen minutes. </s></p><p n="p23.98"><s n="s1.5;p23.98">The potassium permanganate solution was then added to the benzyl alcohol solution. </s><s n="s2.5;p23.98">The stop clock was started immediately as these two solutions were mixed. </s><s n="s3.5;p23.98">A 10.0 cm <hi rend="sup">3</hi> aliquot of the solution was taken from the mixture at t = 0 s. </s><s n="s4.5;p23.98">To which 10 cm <hi rend="sup">3</hi> of 10% potassium iodide solution was added. </s><s n="s5.5;p23.98">This was then titrated against standard sodium thiosulphate (1.953 x 10 <hi rend="sup">-3</hi> mol dm <hi rend="sup">-3</hi>). </s></p><p n="p24.98"><s n="s1.1;p24.98">This procedure was repeated every ten minutes, until the permanganate concentration decreased to 25% of starting concentration (≈ 2.5 cm <hi rend="sup">3</hi> of sodium thiosulphate titre). </s></p><p n="p25.98"><s n="s1.1;p25.98">This experiment was then repeated for a thermostat bath at 27.5°C. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">4.0 Results - 32.5°C</head><div2><head rend="bold">4.01 Determining the order with respect to permanganate</head><p n="p26.98"><s n="s1.1;p26.98">The titration results for this experiment are recorded in table 1. </s></p><table id="BAWE_0188a-tab.001"><head rend="bold">Table 1</head><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p27.98"><s n="s1.1;p27.98">From this data, the molarity of remaining MnO4- was calculated, by using equations (2) and (3): </s></p><p n="p28.98"><s n="s1.1;p28.98"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0188a-form.007"/> </s></p><p n="p29.98"><s n="s1.1;p29.98">The number moles of MnO <hi rend="sub">4</hi>- = No moles of <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0188a-form.008"/> </s></p><p n="p30.98"><s n="s1.1;p30.98">The molarity of MnO <hi rend="sub">4</hi>- = no moles of <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0188a-form.009"/> </s></p><p n="p31.98"><s n="s1.1;p31.98">Example calculation (for t=0); </s></p><p n="p32.98"><s n="s1.1;p32.98"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0188a-form.010"/> </s></p><p n="p33.98"><s n="s1.1;p33.98"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0188a-form.011"/> </s></p><p n="p34.98"><s n="s1.1;p34.98"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0188a-form.012"/> </s></p><p n="p35.98"><s n="s1.1;p35.98">The complete calculations for all of these titrations are summarised in table 2. </s></p><table id="BAWE_0188a-tab.002"><head rend="bold">Table 2</head><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p36.98"><s n="s1.2;p36.98">Plotting the concentration of permanganate against time, gives an exponential curve (see graph 1). </s><s n="s2.2;p36.98">This is characteristic of a first or second order reaction. </s></p><p n="p37.98"><s n="s1.2;p37.98">Examining the graph using the half life method, the time from t <hi rend="sub">0</hi> to t <hi rend="sub">1/2</hi> is 2750s, and the time taken from t <hi rend="sub">1/2</hi> to t <hi rend="sub">3/4</hi> is 3000s. </s><s n="s2.2;p37.98">These consecutive half-lives are roughly the same, and this indicates the reaction is first order with respect to MnO <hi rend="sub">4</hi>-. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">4.02 Determining Pseudo Rate Constant</head><p n="p38.98"><s n="s1.1;p38.98">The rate equation for this reaction can be written as: </s></p><p n="p39.98"><s n="s1.1;p39.98"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0188a-form.013"/> </s></p><p n="p40.98"><s n="s1.1;p40.98">Where a, b and c are integers, and c has already been deduced to be = 1. </s></p><p n="p41.98"><s n="s1.1;p41.98">The concentrations of acid and benzyl alcohol are in excess, and therefore can be assumed to remain constant throughout the reaction giving a pseudo first order rate equation, which will have an effective rate constant k <hi rend="sub">obs</hi>, this gives a rate equation as follows: </s></p><p n="p42.98"><s n="s1.1;p42.98"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0188a-form.014"/> </s></p><p n="p43.98"><s n="s1.3;p43.98">By manipulating the first order rate equation (7), a linear graph can be plotted. </s><s n="s2.3;p43.98">This will find the effective rate constant k <hi rend="sub">obs</hi>. </s><s n="s3.3;p43.98">This is shown below: </s></p><p n="p44.98"><s n="s1.1;p44.98"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0188a-form.015"/> </s></p><p n="p45.98"><s n="s1.1;p45.98">Integrating with respect to t equation (7) on both sides gives (8): </s></p><p n="p46.98"><s n="s1.1;p46.98"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0188a-form.016"/> </s></p><p n="p47.98"><s n="s1.1;p47.98">Equation (8) is of the form: y = c - mx, and thus the gradient of the graph is = -k <hi rend="sub">obs</hi>. </s></p><p n="p48.98"><s n="s1.1;p48.98">To obtain k <hi rend="sub">obs</hi> a graph of ln[MnO4-] vs time was plotted, using the manipulated data from table 3: </s></p><table id="BAWE_0188a-tab.003"><head rend="bold">Table 3</head><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p49.98"><s n="s1.1;p49.98">The equation of the line of best fit from graph 2 was: </s></p><p n="p50.98"><s n="s1.1;p50.98"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0188a-form.017"/> </s></p><p n="p51.98"><s n="s1.1;p51.98">Thus determining the k <hi rend="sub">obs</hi> = 0.000254 </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">4.03 Determining the Rate Constant</head><p n="p52.98"><s n="s1.1;p52.98">The rate with respect to MnO <hi rend="sub">4</hi>- has been deduced, but those with respect to H+ and C <hi rend="sub">6</hi>H <hi rend="sub">5</hi>CH <hi rend="sub">2</hi>OH have yet to be. </s></p><p n="p53.98"><s n="s1.2;p53.98">K <hi rend="sub">obs</hi> is the observed rate of reaction with respect to MnO <hi rend="sub">4</hi>-. </s><s n="s2.2;p53.98">To deduce the rate of reaction for benzyl alcohol and acid, it is important to consider the following information: </s></p><quote lang="English">"If the concentration of benzyl alcohol is doubled, it is found the half life of MnO4- is halved." "If the concentration of benzyl alcohol is doubled while that of the acid is halved, the overall rate of reaction is unchanged."</quote><p n="p54.98"><s n="s1.2;p54.98">From (i) it is deduced that order of reaction with respect to benzyl alcohol is first. </s><s n="s2.2;p54.98">The knowledge of (i) implies that from (ii) the order with respect to the acid is also first. </s></p><p n="p55.98"><s n="s1.1;p55.98">Thus a = 1, b = 1, and c = 1 in equation (4). </s></p><p n="p56.98"><s n="s1.1;p56.98">The rate constant for this reaction can then be found, from combining equations (4) and (5), using the starting concentrations of reagents. </s></p><p n="p57.98"><s n="s1.1;p57.98"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0188a-form.018"/> </s></p><p n="p58.98"><s n="s1.1;p58.98">substituting the following values will give rate constant k at 32.5°C: </s></p><p n="p59.98"><s n="s1.1;p59.98"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0188a-form.019"/> </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">4.1 Results - 27.5°C</head><div2><head rend="bold">4.11 Determining The Order With Respect To Permanganate</head><p n="p60.98"><s n="s1.1;p60.98">The titration results for this experiment are recorded in table 4. </s></p><table id="BAWE_0188a-tab.004"><head rend="bold">Table 4</head><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p61.98"><s n="s1.2;p61.98">From these results the concentration of remaining permanganate was found as previously state in section 4.01 using equations (2) and (3). </s><s n="s2.2;p61.98">These results are tabulated in table 5. </s></p><table id="BAWE_0188a-tab.005"><head rend="bold">Table 5</head><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p62.98"><s n="s1.3;p62.98">From this, the concentration of permanganate can be plotted as a function of time (graph 3), which is exponential. </s><s n="s2.3;p62.98">The time taken from t <hi rend="sub">0</hi> to t <hi rend="sub">1/2</hi> is 4000s, and time taken from t <hi rend="sub">1/2</hi> to t <hi rend="sub">3/4</hi> is 8000s. </s><s n="s3.3;p62.98">These consecutive half lives are precisely the same, indicating the reaction is first order with respect to MnO4-. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">4.12 Determining Pseudo Rate Constant</head><p n="p63.98"><s n="s1.1;p63.98">The pseudo rate constant can be found as in section 4.02, by taking natural logarithm of the concentration of MnO4- (as calculated in table 6), and plotting against time. </s></p><table id="BAWE_0188a-tab.006"><head rend="bold">Table 6</head><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p64.98"><s n="s1.1;p64.98">The equation of line of best fit from graph 4 is: </s></p><p n="p65.98"><s n="s1.1;p65.98"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0188a-form.020"/> </s></p><p n="p66.98"><s n="s1.1;p66.98">Thus the gradient of the graph is = -0.000178, hence: </s></p><p n="p67.98"><s n="s1.1;p67.98"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0188a-form.021"/> </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">4.13 Determining the Rate Constant</head><p n="p68.98"><s n="s1.1;p68.98">We know that the rate equation is: </s></p><p n="p69.98"><s n="s1.1;p69.98"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0188a-form.022"/> </s></p><p n="p70.98"><s n="s1.1;p70.98">As discussed earlier a, b and c are all equal to 1. </s></p><p n="p71.98"><s n="s1.1;p71.98">Also from combining equations (4) and (5) the rate constant for the reaction temperature can be found. </s></p><p n="p72.98"><s n="s1.1;p72.98"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0188a-form.023"/> </s></p><p n="p73.98"><s n="s1.1;p73.98">substituting the following values gives k at 25.5°C: </s></p><p n="p74.98"><s n="s1.1;p74.98"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0188a-form.024"/> </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">4.2 - Variation of the Rate Constant with Temperature</head><p n="p75.98"><s n="s1.1;p75.98">Using Arrgenius' equation (6) it is possible to obtain the activation energy and pre-exponential factor of the reaction. </s></p><p n="p76.98"><s n="s1.1;p76.98"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0188a-form.025"/> </s></p><p n="p77.98"><s n="s1.1;p77.98">Data from other groups were collected, so that as many values of K and T could be used to calculate accurate values of A and E. </s></p><p n="p78.98"><s n="s1.1;p78.98">By taking natural logarithms of both sides of equation (6) gives: </s></p><p n="p79.98"><s n="s1.1;p79.98"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0188a-form.026"/> </s></p><p n="p80.98"><s n="s1.1;p80.98">The natural logarithm of each k value was calculated, as was 1/T. This would thus give a straight line graph, with gradient = E/R and intercept = lnA. </s></p><p n="p81.98"><s n="s1.1;p81.98">The values of k and T were manipulated so graph 5 could be plotted; these results are seen in table 7. </s></p><table id="BAWE_0188a-tab.007"><head rend="bold">Table 7</head><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p82.98"><s n="s1.1;p82.98">The equation generated from graph 5: </s></p><p n="p83.98"><s n="s1.1;p83.98"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0188a-form.027"/> </s></p><p n="p84.98"><s n="s1.1;p84.98">This means <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0188a-form.028"/> </s></p><p n="p85.98"><s n="s1.1;p85.98">Also <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0188a-form.029"/> </s></p><p n="p86.98"><s n="s1.1;p86.98">Thus <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0188a-form.030"/> </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">5. Mechanism</head><p n="p87.98"><s n="s1.2;p87.98">From the rate of the reaction, it is known that one molecule of acid, one molecule of benzyl alcohol, and one molecule of permanganate are involved in the mechanism of this reaction. </s><s n="s2.2;p87.98">Also the rate determining step is said to involve the breaking of a C-H bond. </s></p><p n="p88.98"><s n="s1.1;p88.98">The proposed mechanism is shown below: </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0188a-fig.001"/><p n="p89.98"><s n="s1.1;p89.98">Although Mn <hi rend="sup">2+</hi> is not formed from this mechanism, it is believe it is formed with further reduced by oxidation of benzyl alcohol. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">6. Conclusions and Summary</head><p n="p90.98"><s n="s1.1;p90.98">In this experiment two values for a rate constant at different temperatures have been found; 0.000254 mol <hi rend="sup">-2</hi> dm <hi rend="sup">6</hi> s <hi rend="sup">-1</hi> and 0.1034 mol <hi rend="sup">-2</hi> dm <hi rend="sup">6</hi> s <hi rend="sup">-1</hi> at 305.5 K and 300.5 K respectively for the following reaction: </s></p><p n="p91.98"><s n="s1.1;p91.98"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0188a-form.031"/> </s></p><p n="p92.98"><s n="s1.1;p92.98">The overall rate equation was deduced to be: </s></p><p n="p93.98"><s n="s1.1;p93.98"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0188a-form.032"/> </s></p><p n="p94.98"><s n="s1.3;p94.98">This reaction is overall third order, and first order with respect to acid, benzyl alcohol and permanganate. </s><s n="s2.3;p94.98">This lead to the conclusion that one of all these species was involved in the mechanism, instead as the stiochiometry equation (1) would lead us to believe. </s><s n="s3.3;p94.98">The proposed mechanism has the rate determining step breaking a C-H bond: </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0188a-fig.002"/><p n="p95.98"><s n="s1.2;p95.98">Some sets of K and T data were collated and produced a graph to find A and E using Arrhenius's equation (6). </s><s n="s2.2;p95.98">The values of A and E were found to be 248.152 and 20.08 KJ mol <hi rend="sup">-1</hi> respectively. </s></p><p n="p96.98"><s n="s1.2;p96.98">The values of k obtained experimentally, appear to be quite low since it is said they should be between 0.1 - 0.4. </s><s n="s2.2;p96.98">This may be due to inaccuracy in the experiment, or poor experimental practise. </s></p><p n="p97.98"><s n="s1.3;p97.98">The major inaccuracy in this experiment may be due to the reagents (such as benzyl alcohol) are prone to breaking down over a period of time when heated. </s><s n="s2.3;p97.98">Thus the titration results could have been affected by this. </s><s n="s3.3;p97.98">The temperature of the thermostat baths were monitored for every titration and were completely consistent. </s></p><p n="p98.98"><s n="s1.2;p98.98">Also the graph generated by manipulating Arrhenius' equation is very unclear and the plots are very spatially distributed. </s><s n="s2.2;p98.98">Thus the equation of best fit is an estimate at best, implying results for A and E are inaccurate. </s></p></div1></body><back/></text></TEI.2>
