<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_0193b" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>With reference to Porter's Diamond of Advantage framework list some of the sources of competitive advantages and disadvantages of Chinese firms. What kinds of threats and opportunities do these represent for Western multinationals?</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">Language used in quote: <foreign id="English">English</foreign></note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">deleted: header: student number, word count
</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">2</p><p n="date">2005-04</p><p n="module title">International Environment of Business</p><p n="module code">IB2180</p><p n="genre family">Critique</p><p n="discipline">Business</p><p n="disciplinary group">SS</p><p n="grade">M</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">631</p><p n="number of s-units">29</p><p n="number of p">11</p><p n="number of tables">0</p><p n="number of figures">1</p><p n="number of block quotes">1</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">0</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">4</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">21.8</p><p n="average s-units per p">2.6</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">m</p><p n="year of birth">1983</p><p n="first language">English</p><p n="education">UKA</p><p n="course">Management Science</p><p n="student ID">0193</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><titlePart rend="underlined bold">IEoB Summer Term Assignment - Reflective Piece 2</titlePart><docTitle><titlePart rend="bold">3.2 - With reference to Porter's Diamond of Advantage framework list some of the sources of competitive advantages and disadvantages of Chinese firms. What kinds of threats and opportunities do these represent for Western multinationals? </titlePart></docTitle></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="section"><p n="p1.11"><s n="s1.2;p1.11">The presentation was given by Group C and outlined advantages and disadvantages available to Chinese firms and their effect on western multi-nationals. </s><s n="s2.2;p1.11">The model used to illustrate this business dynamic was 'Porter's Diamond of National Advantage' shown below. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0193b-fig.001"/><quote lang="English">"Michael E. Porter argued that a nation can create new advanced factor endowments such as skilled labour, a strong technology and knowledge base, government support, and culture. Porter used a diamond shaped diagram as the basis of a framework to illustrate the determinants of national advantage."<ref target="BAWE_0193b-ftnote.001"/></quote><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0193b-ftnote.001"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1"><seg type="URL" n="http://www.quickmba.oom/strategy/global/diamond"/> </s></p></note><p n="p2.11"><s n="s1.1;p2.11">The four corners of the diamond are aspects that can lead to a national competitive advantage and can be explained as follows: </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p3.11"><s n="s1.2;p3.11">Factor conditions - A country creates its own factors such as skills and technology. </s><s n="s2.2;p3.11">Lack of these factors forces innovation ultimately leading to a national competitive advantage. </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p4.11"><s n="s1.2;p4.11">Demand Conditions - A stronger and more demanding local market helps local firms anticipate global trends. </s><s n="s2.2;p4.11">When local demand is greater than in foreign markets, local firms devote more attention to it leading to an advantage when exporting that product. </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p5.11"><s n="s1.1;p5.11">Related and Supporting industries - When supporting industries are competitive more cost effective and innovative inputs are available </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p6.11"><s n="s1.2;p6.11">Firm Strategy, Structure, and Rivalry - Strategy and structure helps determine in which industry a country may excel. </s><s n="s2.2;p6.11">Low rivalry can make a firm attractive, however increased rivalry can lead to improvement and innovation to provide an advantage. </s></p><p n="p7.11"><s n="s1.4;p7.11">Traditional theories implied there were five factors that gave a region a 'comparative advantage'; Land, Location, Natural Resources, Labour and Population Size. </s><s n="s2.4;p7.11">These 'Factor Endowments' are difficult to influence and as a result, Porter believes they are inadequate. </s><s n="s3.4;p7.11">He argued that sustained growth has rarely been built on these inherent factors and that they may even impede a nation's drive to innovate. </s><s n="s4.4;p7.11">The diamond model is best used as a tool to help understand a nation's competitive position in global competition. </s></p><p n="p8.11"><s n="s1.5;p8.11">The presentation focused on sources of advantages and disadvantages to China but also developed explainations of how these may threaten western firms. </s><s n="s2.5;p8.11">To this effect the Diamond Model is useful and well used by the group. </s><s n="s3.5;p8.11">However, both the model itself and the group failed to give any indication as to the impact of Foreign Direct Investment on the region in question. </s><s n="s4.5;p8.11">Benefits of internationalisation of production seem to be over looked and it seems to be assumed that only outward FDI is useful in creating a competitive advantage. </s><s n="s5.5;p8.11">In short, the model seems to place too much emphasis on domestic determinants. </s></p><p n="p9.11"><s n="s1.2;p9.11">The concepts raised in the presentation helped provide me with an insight not just in how a given nation can seek to innovate but also how, as a rival nation, threats and opportunities can be identified. </s><s n="s2.2;p9.11">Taking into account the question answered in the presentation it seems that Porter's model ties in particularly well with the SWOT analysis tool to assess a region's credentials. </s></p><p n="p10.11"><s n="s1.5;p10.11">Despite being heavily used in teaching, a number of Porter's models have been heavily criticised in recent years. </s><s n="s2.5;p10.11">Questions have been raised as to its applicability, as it was derived from case studies into 10 major industrialised economies. </s><s n="s3.5;p10.11">This means its application is best suited to developed economies. </s><s n="s4.5;p10.11">Porter's Diamond also seems to over emphasise micro-factors and tends to disregard factors such as exchange or interest rates. </s><s n="s5.5;p10.11">Given his acknowledgement of the role of the government, it seems to me that these semi-controllable influences are of a significant importance. </s></p><p n="p11.11"><s n="s1.3;p11.11">This reflection has helped me clarify the models highlighted in the 'Internationalisation &amp; China' lecture of Term 2. </s><s n="s2.3;p11.11">I now realise that the models applied during the seminar presentations are best understood when used in conjunction with a prior understanding of their context. </s><s n="s3.3;p11.11">I will therefore seek to research the concepts employed before the next seminar so that the subjects explored are more easily recognisable. </s></p></div1></body><back><div1 type="bibliography"><head rend="underlined bold">Bibliography</head><p>'The Competitive Advantage of Nations' (1990) - Michael E. Porter</p><p><seg type="URL" n="http://www.quickmba.com/strategy/global/diamond"/> [Accessed 22/04/05]</p><p><seg type="URL" n="http://pacific.commerce.ubc.ca/ruckman/competitiveadvofnations.htm"/> [Accessed 24/04/05]</p><p><seg type="URL" n="http://www.valuebasedmanagement.net/methods_porter_diamond_model.html"/> [Accessed 24/04/05]</p></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
