<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_0193e" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Report on A-Z Cloth UK - Yarn Production Costs</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">deleted: header: student number</note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">appendix: tables of results, complete with workings
</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">1</p><p n="date">2004-02</p><p n="module title">Quantitive Methods of Analysis</p><p n="module code">IB1020</p><p n="genre family">Case study</p><p n="discipline">Business</p><p n="disciplinary group">SS</p><p n="grade">M</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">1225</p><p n="number of s-units">58</p><p n="number of p">19</p><p n="number of tables">0</p><p n="number of figures">0</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">0</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">5</p><p n="abstract present">abstract present</p><p n="average words per s-unit">21.1</p><p n="average s-units per p">3.1</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">m</p><p n="year of birth">1983</p><p n="first language">English</p><p n="education">UKA</p><p n="course">Management Science</p><p n="student ID">0193</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><docTitle><titlePart rend="underlined bold">Report on A-Z Cloth UK - Yarn Production Costs</titlePart></docTitle></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="abstract"><head rend="bold">Summary and Recommendations</head><p rend="bulleted" n="p1.19"><s n="s1.1;p1.19">Given the basic resources, the contract can be met at a cost of £8580. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p2.19"><s n="s1.1;p2.19">There is no affect on production if the future plan using 700 hours of the Vats comes into being. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p3.19"><s n="s1.3;p3.19">With the basic resources, it would be beneficial to purchase 80 hours at a cost of no more than £120. </s><s n="s2.3;p3.19">The decision about whether or not to purchase the extra Carding machine capacity will depend on the other variables mentioned. </s><s n="s3.3;p3.19">The price paid for this is also dependant on these factors.(see Table 2). </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p4.19"><s n="s1.1;p4.19">A 30% reduction in the cost of buying in yarn would cause it to be cheaper than producing it, but if the supplier's reliability is questionable, it may be more sensible to try and gain a 20% reduction from the current supplier. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p5.19"><s n="s1.1;p5.19">A £1 increase in cost of producing yarn will boost the cost of fulfilling the contract but will have no effect on production quantities. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Introduction</head><p n="p6.19"><s n="s1.2;p6.19">Using the information supplied, I have simulated the problem &amp; calculated production costs and quantities necessary to fulfil the contract. </s><s n="s2.2;p6.19">I have also calculated these factors given the possible changes you mentioned may be available in the future. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Method</head><p n="p7.19"><s n="s1.4;p7.19">To calculate these results I used Microsoft Excel's Linear Programming Solver. </s><s n="s2.4;p7.19">This is a statistical tool which provides the optimum quantities of resources needed given the criteria and restrictions specified. </s><s n="s3.4;p7.19">From these, I have calculated the relevant costs of the project. </s><s n="s4.4;p7.19">I have assumed that the Vats are interchangeable and as such have combined their total usage for the sake of my calculation. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Fulfilling the Contract</head><div2><head rend="underlined">1) Given the basic resources available &amp; ignoring any future cost or quantity changes. </head><p n="p8.19"><s n="s1.2;p8.19">Figure 1 of the appendix shows that enough fibre can be produced to make 320 metres of yarn. </s><s n="s2.2;p8.19">It also outlines the quantities of each resource used &amp; the relevant costs. </s></p><p n="p9.19"><s n="s1.1;p9.19">No more than this can be made because the maximum number of hours available with the Carding machine is 1280 and all these have been used. </s></p><p n="p10.19"><s n="s1.2;p10.19">Since the contract requires 500 metres to be supplied, 180 metres must be bought in from external suppliers. </s><s n="s2.2;p10.19">The total cost of the contract is:(320x£15)+(180x£21)=£8580 </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">2) If 700 hours of use of the Vats is used for another project as discussed, with all other resources remaining the same. </head><p n="p11.19"><s n="s1.3;p11.19">Figure 2 of the appendix highlights the spare capacity available with each machine given the quantities needed to fulfil the contract (as calculated in figure 1). </s><s n="s2.3;p11.19">We can see from this that there are 760 spare hours available in a combination of Vat's A + B. Therefore if 700 hours are used in this other project, there are still 60 hours spare. </s><s n="s3.3;p11.19">This means that if the other project comes to fruition, the production levels of yarn for your customer will not be affected. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">3) If extra capacity of the carding and combing machine can be obtained. </head><p n="p12.19"><s n="s1.9;p12.19">Figure 2 shows us that there is no spare capacity for the Carding + Combing machine (C+C) given the levels needed to fulfil the contract. </s><s n="s2.9;p12.19">This means that an increase in available capacity will enable more yarn to be produced. </s><s n="s3.9;p12.19">Figure 3 shows what will happen if the C+C machine's capacity is no longer a restriction. </s><s n="s4.9;p12.19">340m of yarn can now be produced before all the hours available on the Twisting machine have been exhausted. </s><s n="s5.9;p12.19">Since it takes 4 hours on the C + C machine to produce enough fibre for 20m of yarn, it would be sensible to purchase 80 hours capacity if this much is available. </s><s n="s6.9;p12.19">The new cost would therefore be (340x 15)+(160x£21)=£8460. </s><s n="s7.9;p12.19">Since this is a saving of £120 it would be unwise to spend more than this on the purchase of the additional capacity. </s><s n="s8.9;p12.19">The result of this action would be the same regardless of whether or not the future plan requiring 700 hours of use of the Vats comes into being. </s><s n="s9.9;p12.19">There would still be 60 hours available with only 40 needing to be used. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">4) If the cost of bought in yarn is reduced</head><p n="p13.19"><s n="s1.7;p13.19">Table 1 shows that if the cost of bought in yarn is reduced by 20% there is no change in the level of resources used but the total cost is reduced. </s><s n="s2.7;p13.19">This is also the case if the extra C+C capacity is purchased. </s><s n="s3.7;p13.19">Table 2 shows that no more than £36 should be spent on this. </s><s n="s4.7;p13.19">With a reduction of 30%, the cost of buying in yarn becomes £14.70 p/m ie. less than the cost to produce it. </s><s n="s5.7;p13.19">The only restriction now becomes the fact that 50% must be produced internally. </s><s n="s6.7;p13.19">However, even at this level of production the cost has been reduced by £1155 to £7425. </s><s n="s7.7;p13.19">Since this level of production can be achieved with the original resources, it is unnecessary to purchase the extra C + C capacity. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">5) If the cost of fibre rises by £1 per metre of yarn</head><p n="p14.19"><s n="s1.3;p14.19">Using the original resources there will be no effect on the amount of yarn produced and as such the amount of resources needed if the price of production rises to £16 per metre. </s><s n="s2.3;p14.19">This is because the cost of buying in yarn will still be greater than the cost of producing it internally. </s><s n="s3.3;p14.19">The only difference will be the increase in total cost to £8900. </s></p><p n="p15.19"><s n="s1.4;p15.19">If you choose to purchase the extra C + C capacity then the production level will still increase to 340m. </s><s n="s2.4;p15.19">The total cost now becomes £8800, which is a saving of only £100. </s><s n="s3.4;p15.19">If we then factor in the reduction in cost of bought in yarn by 20% then the difference in total cost is reduced to £16 (see Table 2). </s><s n="s4.4;p15.19">It would therefore be unwise to spend more than these amounts respectively on the purchase of the additional capacity. </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Future considerations</head><p n="p16.19"><s n="s1.5;p16.19">If we consider extending and increasing the contract beyond 6 months there are a number of issues that have to be taken into consideration. </s><s n="s2.5;p16.19">Based on the original resources the contract could be increased to 640m. </s><s n="s3.5;p16.19">This would include 320m produced internally and 320m bought in. </s><s n="s4.5;p16.19">The problem with this is that it would increase the cost from £17.16 per metre(to complete the basic contract) to £18 p/m to supply 640m. </s><s n="s5.5;p16.19">The terms of the increased contract would have to reflect this. </s></p><p n="p17.19"><s n="s1.5;p17.19">There are 2 plausible alternatives to this. </s><s n="s2.5;p17.19">(1)The policy regarding only buying in 50% could be reviewed. </s><s n="s3.5;p17.19">If this is increased then more yarn could be supplied. </s><s n="s4.5;p17.19">(2) The capacity of all areas of the factory could be extended to facilitate increased production. </s><s n="s5.5;p17.19">You would of course have to look into the cost of such investments and weigh up the gains and losses involved before deciding whether or not to proceed. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Conclusion</head><p n="p18.19"><s n="s1.1;p18.19">I have assumed that more then one of the possible future plans can come to be and as such have included combinations of events in my analysis. </s></p><p n="p19.19"><s n="s1.3;p19.19">I have made no assumptions about the value of the contract, but as long as the fee is greater than the total cost mentioned above, the department is capable of satisfying the contract. </s><s n="s2.3;p19.19">I have suggested increasing the percentage that can be bought in as long as the fee per metre is greater than its purchase price. </s><s n="s3.3;p19.19">My findings are based purely on the figures and as such, implications on staffing and other areas of the business must be considered. </s></p></div1></body><back><div1 type="appendix"><head rend="underlined bold">Appendix</head><p/></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
