<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_0194e" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>No15 Pseudogout AG</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">deleted: header: student name; footer: page numbers</note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">Proforma
</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">4</p><p n="date">2005-03</p><p n="module title">Rheumotology Block</p><p n="module code">unknown</p><p n="genre family">Case study</p><p n="discipline">Medicine</p><p n="disciplinary group">LS</p><p n="grade">D</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">2146</p><p n="number of s-units">111</p><p n="number of p">60</p><p n="number of tables">0</p><p n="number of figures">0</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">26</p><p n="number of lists">3</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">17</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">19.3</p><p n="average s-units per p">1.9</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">f</p><p n="year of birth">1974</p><p n="first language">English</p><p n="education">UKA</p><p n="course">Medicine</p><p n="student ID">0194</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><docTitle><titlePart><hi rend="bold">PORTFOLIO CASE No:</hi> 15</titlePart></docTitle><titlePart>Patient Initials<name type="other"/> Hospital Number Keep separate list Age 48 Gender M</titlePart><titlePart>Portfolio Case presentation number: 7.4 Hypertension Phase 2 course document objective(s): 7.8 Arrhythmias Has the patient's permission, including for follow up contact by telephone, been sought and recorded in the case notes? Yes</titlePart></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="bold">Referral information</hi> Source of referral and a summary of key information</head><p n="p1.60"><s n="s1.1;p1.60">48 year old gentleman admitted on <name type="date"/> for an elective day-case angiogram due to a 16 month history of palpitations and feeling 'not-quite-right'. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="bold">History</hi> All <hi rend="bold italic">relevant</hi> information gathered from the patient about the presenting illness, co-existing problems, current treatment, significant past medical history and the social and family background. The patient's view of the nature of the problem and their expectations for treatment. </head><div2><head rend="underlined">Presenting complaint:</head><p n="p2.60"><s n="s1.1;p2.60">Palpitations and a general feeling of being 'not quite right'. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">History of presenting complaint:</head><p n="p3.60"><s n="s1.8;p3.60">The palpitations started 16 months ago and occurred early morning, soon after getting up. </s><s n="s2.8;p3.60">The palpitations were felt in the left upper sternal area and lasted for approximately 30 seconds to a minute. </s><s n="s3.8;p3.60">During these episodes, the patient is distressed because he is aware of what he described as feeling like someone is drilling into his chest. </s><s n="s4.8;p3.60">There is a preceding feeling of faintness, but there is no associated chest pain or dyspnoea with these episodes and they occur during exercise and at rest. </s><s n="s5.8;p3.60">The patient has been able to associate excessive alcohol the previous night as a trigger for these episodes. </s><s n="s6.8;p3.60">These palpitations had started to become more frequent until this July the patient went to the hospital due to feelings of dreadfulness, he could not explain these further apart from stating he had felt tired all the time just prior to this episode. </s><s n="s7.8;p3.60">This visit to the hospital triggered further investigations, which included a 24-hour ECG, and echocardiogram both of which did not show any evidence of an arrhythmia. </s><s n="s8.8;p3.60">However, the patient then did an exercise tolerance test, which had to be stopped at stage II due to superventricular tachycardia. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">Past medical history:</head><p rend="bulleted" n="p4.60"><s n="s1.1;p4.60">Previous investigations revealed Mr <name type="other"/> has hypercholestrolaemia and hypertension </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p5.60"><s n="s1.1;p5.60">No previous history of an MI, CVA, diabetes, RF, asthma or epilepsy </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p6.60"><s n="s1.1;p6.60">The patient does suffer from certain food and stress-induced migraines </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p7.60"><s n="s1.1;p7.60">Appendectomy at age 11 </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">Family history:</head><p rend="bulleted" n="p8.60"><s n="s1.1;p8.60">Father had 2 MI's at the age of 59, still alive </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p9.60"><s n="s1.1;p9.60">Brother died at age 40 from an MI </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p10.60"><s n="s1.1;p10.60">Mum suffers from migraines </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">Drug history and allergies:</head><list type="bulleted"><head>NKDA</head><item>Aspirin 75mg OD - anti-platelet</item><item>Simvastatin 20mg OD - HMG-CoA inhibitor</item><item>Bisoprolol 2.5mg OD - β blocker</item><item>Ramipril 2.5mg OD - ACE inhibitor</item></list><p n="p11.60"/></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">Social history:</head><p n="p12.60"><s n="s1.4;p12.60">Mr <name type="other"/> is a material scientist. </s><s n="s2.4;p12.60">He is separated from his wife and has a partner who lives in <name type="other"/>. </s><s n="s3.4;p12.60">He has one daughter who lives in <name type="other"/>. </s><s n="s4.4;p12.60">The patient until recently has been very active and goes hill-walking regularly. </s></p><p n="p13.60"><s n="s1.2;p13.60">In the recent past Mr <name type="other"/> consumed upwards of 60 units of alcohol a week, recently this has been cut down to 21 units a week. </s><s n="s2.2;p13.60">He is an ex-smoker who stopped last year and has a 8 pack-year history due to smoking 5 cigars a day from the age of 18 - 47 </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">Systems review:</head><p n="p14.60"><s n="s1.1;p14.60">A systems review revealed nothing of note. </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="bold">Analysis of history</hi> The most likely single cause of the presentation, other possible causes and reasons for these choices. The findings to be looked for on physical examination to help decide the cause.</head><p rend="bulleted" n="p15.60"><s n="s1.1;p15.60">Hyperthyroidism can cause palpitations, however, this cause would have been already identified in earlier admissions if this was the cause. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p16.60"><s n="s1.1;p16.60">Anaemia can cause ventricular ectopics, again this would have already been identified. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p17.60"><s n="s1.1;p17.60">Psychological element; Mr <name type="other"/> stated that he does suffer from stress and this can cause palpitations and could be exacerbating the current situation. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p18.60"><s n="s1.2;p18.60">Electrolyte imbalance (low serum K+ or Mg+) can cause ventricular tachycardia and needs to be looked at further. </s><s n="s2.2;p18.60">There is no recent history of vomiting or diarrhoea, which makes this diagnosis less likely. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p19.60"><s n="s1.2;p19.60">Excess caffeine/alcohol can cause either or junctional tachycardias/ventricular ectopics/alcoholic cardiomyopathy. </s><s n="s2.2;p19.60">The reported alcohol intake by Mr <name type="other"/> and reported trigger of excess alcohol the preceding evening, would indicate that alcohol could be a cause for this presentation. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p20.60"><s n="s1.1;p20.60">Dilated cardiomyopathy can cause tachycardia, ventricular ectopic beats and AF. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p21.60"><s n="s1.2;p21.60">Arrhythmogenic right ventricular dysplasia (ARVD) - A rare form of cardiomyopathy, which can cause ventricular tachycardia and can be the presenting feature. </s><s n="s2.2;p21.60">Diagnosis of ARVD can often be difficult and the diagnosis is based on investigations including ECG, echo, myocardial biopsy and the gold standard investigation an MRI scan [1]. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="bold">Physical examination</hi> Highlight the findings most relevant to your clinical problem solving by underlining them</head><p n="p22.60"><s n="s1.1;p22.60">A slim man who was sitting comfortably on the bed </s></p><p n="p23.60"><s n="s1.1;p23.60">No evidence of clubbing, peripheral cyanosis, splinter haemorrhages, xanthomata, palmar erythema or dupuytren's contracture on his hands. </s></p><p n="p24.60"><s n="s1.1;p24.60">Pulse = 60 bpm and irregularly irregular, BP 122/70, RR = 16, O <hi rend="sub">2</hi> sats = 100% on air, apyrexial </s></p><p n="p25.60"><s n="s1.1;p25.60">No evidence of jaundice, anaemia, central cyanosis, oedema or lymphadenopathy </s></p><p n="p26.60"><s n="s1.1;p26.60">JVP was not raised </s></p><p n="p27.60"><s n="s1.1;p27.60">On examination of the chest there were 4 spider naevi evident superior to the nipples, nothing else of note. </s></p><div2><head><hi rend="underlined">Palpation</hi> :</head><p n="p28.60"><s n="s1.2;p28.60">No left or right parasternal heaves or palpable thrills. </s><s n="s2.2;p28.60">The apex beat was located in the 5 <hi rend="sup">th</hi> ICS MCL. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">Auscultation:</head><p n="p29.60"><s n="s1.1;p29.60">Heart sound I + II heard with no added sounds </s></p><p n="p30.60"><s n="s1.1;p30.60">Respiratory - vesicular breathing evident in all areas with no added sounds. </s></p><p n="p31.60"><s n="s1.3;p31.60">Abdominal examination - the abdomen was soft and non-tender on soft and deep palpation. </s><s n="s2.3;p31.60">There was no evidence of masses, organomegaly or ascites. </s><s n="s3.3;p31.60">On auscultation there were bowel sounds present in all four quadrants. </s></p><p n="p32.60"><s n="s1.1;p32.60">Neurological - no abnormalities found on gross examination. </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="bold">Analysis of history and examination</hi> Reasons for your choice of the cause of the patient's problem(s) and any other cause that still needs to be considered at this stage</head><p n="p33.60"><s n="s1.1;p33.60">There was no evidence of hyperthyroidism, anaemia or dehydration on examination, which makes hyperthyroidsim, anaemia, and low K+ or Mg+ less likely as the primary cause of the episodes of VT. However, these conditions could exacerbate the primary cause and TSH, T3/T4, FBC and electrolyte levels need to be checked on routine blood tests. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p34.60"><s n="s1.2;p34.60">Excess caffeine/alcohol can cause either or junctional tachycardias/ventricular ectopics/alcoholic cardiomyopathy. </s><s n="s2.2;p34.60">The reported alcohol intake by Mr <name type="other"/> and the admission that these events occur the morning after a heavy night, still indicate that alcohol could be the primary cause for this presentation. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p35.60"><s n="s1.1;p35.60">Dilated cardiomyopathy can cause tachycardia, ventricular ectopic beats and AF, an echocardiogram will be able to assess the likelihood of this diagnosis. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p36.60"><s n="s1.1;p36.60">ARVD cannot be ruled out at this stage as diagnosis is based on investigations not on clinical examination of the patient. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="bold">Formulation of the patient's problem(s)</hi> Encapsulate this in physical, psychological and social terms (the triple diagnosis)</head><p n="p37.60"><s n="s1.3;p37.60">The patient was quite an anxious man who has had a history of alcohol abuse, which was probably higher than he stated. </s><s n="s2.3;p37.60">His partner, who was present during the history, intimated that the estimate of 60 units per week was a conservative one. </s><s n="s3.3;p37.60">This history of alcohol abuse and recent need to cut down his alcohol intake will be impacting on him socially, psychologically and physically, if the reason for his presentation is due to alcohol. </s></p><p n="p38.60"><s n="s1.2;p38.60">The episodes of severe palpitations that he has been experiencing has been upsetting to him and he has stated that he is an anxious man and these episodes of uncontrollable palpitations will be increasing his anxiety levels, which in turn could increase the number of episodes he experiences. </s><s n="s2.2;p38.60">This vicious cycle and general feeling of not being in control of his body will have a global impact on his lifestyle. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="bold">Management</hi> Use the framework of RAPRIOP to structure your proposed management. Refer to the guidelines to the writing of portfolio cases for the details of the issues to be addressed under each heading.</head><div2><head rend="underlined">Investigations</head><div3><head><hi rend="underlined">24 hour tape (<name type="date"/>)</hi> :</head><p n="p39.60"><s n="s1.3;p39.60">Sinus rhythm throughout the recording, average HR 66-113 bpm. </s><s n="s2.3;p39.60">Very frequent unifocal ventricular ectopics seen in isolation and occasional couplets and triplets. </s><s n="s3.3;p39.60">Frequently sustained episodes of ventricular bigeminy and occasional episodes of trigeminy. </s></p></div3><div3><head><hi rend="underlined">Echocardiogram results</hi> :</head><p n="p40.60"><s n="s1.2;p40.60">Good left and right ventricular function with no significant valvular or structural abnormalities detected. </s><s n="s2.2;p40.60">Ventricular ectopics in ratio of 3:1 </s></p></div3><div3><head><hi rend="underlined">ETT (<name type="date"/>)</hi> :</head><p n="p41.60"><s n="s1.4;p41.60">ST changes - ST depression upsloping. </s><s n="s2.4;p41.60">Exercised for 3 min 51 sec (stage 2) of the Bruce protocol. </s><s n="s3.4;p41.60">Some light-headedness, no chest pain, no SOB. Terminated because of ventricular tachycardia. </s><s n="s4.4;p41.60">Recovered fully in recovery period. </s></p></div3><div3><head><hi rend="underlined">Bloods (<name type="date"/>)</hi> :</head><list type="simple"><item><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0194e-form.001"/></item><item><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0194e-form.002"/></item><item><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0194e-form.003"/></item><item><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0194e-form.004"/></item><item><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0194e-form.005"/></item><item><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0194e-form.006"/></item><item><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0194e-form.007"/></item><item><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0194e-form.008"/></item><item><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0194e-form.009"/></item><item><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0194e-form.010"/></item><item><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0194e-form.011"/></item><item><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0194e-form.012"/></item><item><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0194e-form.013"/></item><item><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0194e-form.014"/></item><item><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0194e-form.015"/></item><item><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0194e-form.016"/></item><item><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0194e-form.017"/></item><item><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0194e-form.018"/></item><item><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0194e-form.019"/></item><item><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0194e-form.020"/></item><item><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0194e-form.021"/></item><item><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0194e-form.022"/></item><item><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0194e-form.023"/></item><item><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0194e-form.024"/></item><item><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0194e-form.025"/></item><item><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0194e-form.026"/></item></list><p n="p42.60"/></div3></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">Reassurance and explanation</head><p n="p43.60"><s n="s1.5;p43.60">Each test that Mr <name type="other"/> had was explained to him in full as to what the test involves and the reason for the test. </s><s n="s2.5;p43.60">After each investigation, the results were explained to him. </s><s n="s3.5;p43.60">The results of the ETT were explained immediately after the test and before the angiogram. </s><s n="s4.5;p43.60">Possible reasons for the episodes of VT as well as why the angiogram was being carried out were explained. </s><s n="s5.5;p43.60">Mr <name type="other"/> knew the angiogram was to highlight any underlying coronary artery disease, which could be stented that would explain the episodes of VT. Especially with the strong positive family history, past history of smoking, high cholesterol/triglycerides and hypertension. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">Prescription/medical intervention</head><p n="p44.60"><s n="s1.3;p44.60">Mr <name type="other"/> is already on the medications recommended to reduce ischaemic coronary episodes. </s><s n="s2.3;p44.60">Additional anti-arrhythmic drugs might be necessary if the episodes of VT continue. </s><s n="s3.3;p44.60">An implantable cardioverter defibrillator might be indicated if further episodes of VT are difficult to manage medically. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">Observation</head><p n="p45.60"><s n="s1.1;p45.60">Mr <name type="other"/> was observed and monitored on an ECG while on CCU pre- and post- angiogram to ensure no further episodes of VT occurred. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">Referral and team working</head><p n="p46.60"><s n="s1.1;p46.60">The referral involved A&amp;E, Consultant cardiologist and team, cardiac investigations technicians, radiograghers, specialist nurses, HCAs, pharmacist, GP </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">Advice and prevention</head><p n="p47.60"><s n="s1.4;p47.60">Mr <name type="other"/> was told that the most likely reason for his episodes of palpitations were due to his excess alcohol consumption. </s><s n="s2.4;p47.60">He was strongly advised to cut down with the intention of stopping. </s><s n="s3.4;p47.60">This measure would stop any further alcoholic cardiomyopathy and progression of the problem. </s><s n="s4.4;p47.60">He was told to seek advice/help from his GP if he experienced further episodes. </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Outcome</head><p n="p48.60"><s n="s1.3;p48.60">A description of the progress of the patient as far as possible. </s><s n="s2.3;p48.60">This should include consideration of further issues to be resolved. </s><s n="s3.3;p48.60">Where appropriate you should contact by telephone patients who have been discharged home. </s></p><p n="p49.60"><s n="s1.3;p49.60">The prognosis of the patient will very much depend on how well he is able to curb his drinking habits. </s><s n="s2.3;p49.60">The management is one of watching and waiting with appropriate advice to the patient if a further episode occurs. </s><s n="s3.3;p49.60">If these episodes do not diminish with reduced alcohol intake then further medical or surgical management may need to be considered in the guise of anti-arrhythmic drugs or an implantable cardioverter defibrillator. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Evidence based care and issues for research</head><p n="p50.60"><s n="s1.1;p50.60">A brief consideration of the evidence base required for the diagnosis and management of the patient's problem(s) </s></p><p n="p51.60"><s n="s1.3;p51.60">One study has shown that patients with alcoholic cardiomyopathy, who abstain from alcohol, or control their drinking to less than 60g of ethanol per day (four standard drinks), improved their cardiac function [5]. </s><s n="s2.3;p51.60">Individuals with mild manifestations of cardiac dysfunction who stop all alcohol consumption can markedly improve their prognosis and even return to normal cardiac function [6]. </s><s n="s3.3;p51.60">However, caution has to be made with withdrawal of alcohol as atrial arrhythmias have been shown to occur during the early ethanol withdrawal phase in patients without other clinical evidence of heart disease [7]. </s></p><p n="p52.60"><s n="s1.2;p52.60">There are few papers in the literature regarding the diagnosis and management of SVT due to alcoholic cardiomyopathy. </s><s n="s2.2;p52.60">It Mr <name type="other"/> does not stop having these episodes of ectopics and SVT with his abstention from alcohol, then other possible causes need to be investigated. </s></p><p n="p53.60"><s n="s1.5;p53.60">An interesting recent paper on the use of radiofrequency catheter ablation for a tachycardiomyopathy on a 26 year old female, described the successful treatment on a phenomenon that is rarely diagnosed. </s><s n="s2.5;p53.60">This female presented with an incessant supraventricular tachycardia, which was not reversible with electrical cardioversion. </s><s n="s3.5;p53.60">Echocardiogram showed a severe LV systolic and diastolic dysfunction. </s><s n="s4.5;p53.60">After ablation her left ventricular function returned to normal. </s><s n="s5.5;p53.60">This case shows that early treatment for tachycardiomyopathy - considered the most frequently unrecognised curable cause of heart failure - can prevent irreversible structural cardiac damage [8]. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Commentary</head><p n="p54.60"><s n="s1.1;p54.60">A commentary on issues of epidemiology, psycho-social, health care delivery, ethical issues or disability relevant to the patient and/or problem </s></p><p n="p55.60"><s n="s1.3;p55.60">Ventricular tachycardia is associated with underlying coronary, ischaemic, or hypertension, as well as, cardiomyopathies (dilated, hypertrophic, restrictive) [2]. </s><s n="s2.3;p55.60">The underlying mechanism is thought to be enhanced automaticity, leading to re-entry circuit as in other tachycardias. </s><s n="s3.3;p55.60">In VT there is a group of ischaemic or electrically non-homogeneous cells. </s></p><p n="p56.60"><s n="s1.2;p56.60">Excessive alcohol consumption is one of the commonest causes of dilated cardiomyopathy in the Western world. </s><s n="s2.2;p56.60">Myocardial damage may arise by three basic mechanisms: </s></p><list type="ordered"><item>Direct toxic effects of alcohol</item><item>Nutritional deficiencies, particularly thiamine deficiency</item><item>Toxic effects of additives (e.g. cobalt) in alcoholic beverages</item></list><p n="p57.60"><s n="s1.1;p57.60">Stopping alcohol consumption can halt the progression of the disease and in some cases can improve ventricular function [3]. </s></p><p n="p58.60"><s n="s1.1;p58.60">Medical management of VT is most commonly with amiodarone or ß blockers. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Impact on your learning</head><p n="p59.60"><s n="s1.1;p59.60">Describe what you have learnt from this case </s></p><p n="p60.60"><s n="s1.4;p60.60">Presentation, differential diagnosis, subsequent investigations and management of tachyarrhythmias. </s><s n="s2.4;p60.60">The impact of alcohol on the myocardium. </s><s n="s3.4;p60.60">Arrhythmogenic right ventricular dysplasia. </s><s n="s4.4;p60.60">Witnessing the wiring up of a 24-hour ECG monitor, watching an echocardiogram and ETT. </s></p></div1></body><back><div1 type="bibliography"><head rend="underlined">References:</head><p>Julian D G, Cowan J C, McLenachan J M. Cardiology. Eighth Ed. Elsevier Saunders, 2005</p><p>Kendall G, Shiu K Y, Johnston S L.Medicine and Surgery: A Concise Textbook. Blackwell Publishing 2005</p><p>Gray H H, Dawkins K D, Morgan J M <hi rend="italic">et al</hi>., Lecture notes on cardiology. Fourth Ed. Blackwell Publishing 2002</p><p>Kumar P, Clark MClinical Mecicine.5th Ed. WB Saunders, 2002</p><p>Nicolas J M , Fernandez-Sola J, Estruch R et al.,The Effect of Controlled Drinking in Alcoholic Cardiomyopathy. Annals of Internal Medicine 2002; 136(3):192 - 200</p><p>G Kouvaras, Cokkinos D. Effects of alcohol on the heart: current views. Angiology. 1986 Aug;37(8): 592 - 600</p><p>Fabrizio L, Regan TJ.Alcoholic cardiomyopathy. Cardiovasc Drugs Ther. 1994 Feb;8(1):89 - 94 </p><p>V M Salemi, E Arteaga, C MadyRecovery of systolic and diastolic function after ablation of incessant supraventricular tachycardia. Eur J Heart Fail. 2005 Dec;7(7):1177 - 1179 </p></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
