<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_0194d" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>No14 GS SVT</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">deleted: header: student name; footer: page numbers</note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">Proforma
</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">4</p><p n="date">2005-12</p><p n="module title">Cardiovascular Block</p><p n="module code">unknown</p><p n="genre family">Case study</p><p n="discipline">Medicine</p><p n="disciplinary group">LS</p><p n="grade">D</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">2248</p><p n="number of s-units">112</p><p n="number of p">55</p><p n="number of tables">0</p><p n="number of figures">0</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">5</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">10</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">20.1</p><p n="average s-units per p">2.0</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">f</p><p n="year of birth">1974</p><p n="first language">English</p><p n="education">UKA</p><p n="course">Medicine</p><p n="student ID">0194</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><docTitle><titlePart><hi rend="bold">PORTFOLIO CASE No:</hi> 14</titlePart></docTitle><titlePart>Patient Initials<name type="other"/> Hospital Number Keep separate list Age 66 Gender M</titlePart><titlePart>Portfolio Case presentation number: 7.2 Chronic recurrent central chest pain Phase 2 course document objective(s): 7.3 Angina pectoris, 7.4 Acute myocardial infarction, 3.17 Insulin-dependent diabetes, 3.19 Long term complications Has the patient's permission, including for follow up contact by telephone, been sought and recorded in the case notes? Yes</titlePart></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="bold">Referral information</hi> Source of referral and a summary of key information</head><p n="p1.55"><s n="s1.3;p1.55">Mr <name type="other"/> came to hospital with his wife on a Saturday morning due to a discomfort in his chest, which he had been experiencing for a week prior to presentation. </s><s n="s2.3;p1.55">This sensation had kept him awake the preceding Friday night and spread to a feeling of pain/heaviness in his left arm. </s><s n="s3.3;p1.55">He rang the out-of-hours GP service who advised him to go to hospital for further tests, where he was admitted on <name type="date"/>. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="bold">History</hi> All <hi rend="bold italic">relevant</hi> information gathered from the patient about the presenting illness, co-existing problems, current treatment, significant past medical history and the social and family background. The patient's view of the nature of the problem and their expectations for treatment. </head><div2><head><hi rend="underlined">Presenting complaint:</hi> Chest pain.</head><p n="p2.55"/></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">History of presenting complaint:</head><p n="p3.55"><s n="s1.14;p3.55">Mr <name type="other"/> had been complaining of a vague tingling in his left infra-mammary region of his chest for a week prior to admission to hospital. </s><s n="s2.14;p3.55">This sensation came and went when he was doing activity, such as working in his allotment. </s><s n="s3.14;p3.55">It never came on at rest. </s><s n="s4.14;p3.55">The pain did not stop him form doing any activities and he rated it as 2-3/10 in intensity. </s><s n="s5.14;p3.55">The night before admission the pain was constant and radiated to his left arm, which prevented him from sleeping, as lying down made the pain worse. </s><s n="s6.14;p3.55">GTN spray did not relieve the pain. </s><s n="s7.14;p3.55">Early Saturday morning he tried some co-codamol which 'knocked him out' for a couple of hours. </s><s n="s8.14;p3.55">Before this current event Mr <name type="other"/> experienced three years ago three episodes over one weekend of sudden shortness of breath during exertion. </s><s n="s9.14;p3.55">He visited his GP who prescribed GTN spray, which he had not used until the Friday night pre-admission. </s><s n="s10.14;p3.55">Mr <name type="other"/> had not suffered from dyspnoea since the previous three episodes. </s><s n="s11.14;p3.55">He does complain of swollen ankles, which he puts down to his diabetes, which was diagnosed in 1991. </s><s n="s12.14;p3.55">He does not suffer from orthopnoea, PND, intermittent claudication or palpitations. </s><s n="s13.14;p3.55">He does complain of a dry intermittent cough, however, he is on an ACE inhibitor, which could explain this cough. </s><s n="s14.14;p3.55">He has never previously had an MI or CVA, he does suffer from hypertension and hypercholestrolaemia. </s></p><p n="p4.55"><s n="s1.2;p4.55">During his admission at <name type="other"/> hospital he had an ECG, which confirmed he had had an MI, he also had an echocardiogram to assess the function and integrity of the heart. </s><s n="s2.2;p4.55">The results from these investigations indicated that Mr <name type="other"/> needed to be transferred to the <name type="other"/> hospital for an angiogram. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">Past medical history:</head><list type="simple"><item>2000 - Bilateral cataracts operation</item><item>1991 - Diabetes</item><item>1988 - Hernia repair (umbilical and right inguinal hernia)</item><item>Nil else of note</item></list><p n="p5.55"/></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">Family history:</head><p n="p6.55"><s n="s1.1;p6.55">Father died of a stroke at the age of 74, nil else of note. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">Drug history and allergies:</head><list type="bulleted"><head>NKDA</head><item>Insulin Humulin M3 (AM and PM)</item><item>Simvastatin 40 mg OD - HMG CoA inhibitor</item><item>Aspirin 75mg - anti-platelet</item><item>Bisoprolol 1.25 mg OD - β blocker</item><item>Perindopril 4mg OD - ACE Inhibitor</item></list><list type="bulleted"><head>Post-angiogram:</head><item>Clopidogrel 75mg OD - anti-platelet (prescribed for 12 months post-angiogram to reduce the risk of stent-induced clots)</item></list><p n="p7.55"/></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">Social history:</head><p n="p8.55"><s n="s1.3;p8.55">Mr <name type="other"/> was a foundry worker who was forced to take early retirement (full pension) at 55 due to peripheral neuropathy secondary to his diabetes. </s><s n="s2.3;p8.55">He lives in a house in <name type="other"/> with his wife who is fit and well. </s><s n="s3.3;p8.55">He has one son who lives in <name type="other"/>. </s></p><p n="p9.55"><s n="s1.1;p9.55">Mr <name type="other"/> has never smoked </s></p><p n="p10.55"><s n="s1.1;p10.55">He drinks about 6 units of alcohol a week </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">Systems review:</head><p n="p11.55"><s n="s1.3;p11.55">Neurological - Mr <name type="other"/> described some odd sensation/numbness on his anterior leg and medial side of foot. </s><s n="s2.3;p11.55">He stated he often felt quite unsteady on his feet because of this sensation. </s><s n="s3.3;p11.55">He has never suffered from any faints, fits or funny turns, headaches, weakness or dizziness. </s></p><p n="p12.55"><s n="s1.1;p12.55">There was nil of note from specific questions regarding the respiratory, gastrointestinal or locomotor systems. </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="bold">Analysis of history</hi> The most likely single cause of the presentation, other possible causes and reasons for these choices. The findings to be looked for on physical examination to help decide the cause.</head><p rend="bulleted" n="p13.55"><s n="s1.2;p13.55">NSTEMI - the intensity of the pain described by the patient would more likely point towards this diagnosis. </s><s n="s2.2;p13.55">However, the patient is a diabetic with evidence of microvascular diabetic neuropathy, which could indicate that the chest pain was not so extreme because of his reduced pain receptor sensitivity. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p14.55"><s n="s1.1;p14.55">STEMI - the length of the pain on the preceding Friday could point towards this diagnosis as the pain was persistent and was not relieved with GTN. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p15.55"><s n="s1.2;p15.55">Musculoskeletal - this is a possible diagnosis as the pain was described as 2 - 3/10 in intensity and co-codamol helped to relieve the pain while GTN spray did not. </s><s n="s2.2;p15.55">However, the pain was not elicited with movement, which would make this diagnosis slightly less likely. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p16.55"><s n="s1.2;p16.55">Dypepsia - this is also a possible diagnosis as the pain was fairly low in intensity and was made worse on lying down. </s><s n="s2.2;p16.55">The positive negatives of the pain radiating to the left arm and no sensations of acid regurgitation would make this diagnosis less likely. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p17.55"><s n="s1.1;p17.55">It is unlikely to be respiratory in nature as the pain was not made worse on respiration, he was not breathless, the patient did have a cough but it was not productive and the patient did not feel like he had a fever, making this diagnosis unlikely. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="bold">Physical examination</hi> Highlight the findings most relevant to your clinical problem solving by underlining them</head><p n="p18.55"><s n="s1.1;p18.55">A slightly overweight gentleman who was sitting comfortably in the chair </s></p><p n="p19.55"><s n="s1.2;p19.55">No clubbing, peripheral cyanosis, tremour, splinter haemorrhages or xanthomata on his hands. </s><s n="s2.2;p19.55">There were bilateral dupuytren's contracture and his right wrist was bandaged due to post-angiogram access to radial artery. </s></p><p n="p20.55"><s n="s1.1;p20.55">Pulse = 96 bpm, regular and weak in character, BP 112/73, RR = 18, O <hi rend="sub">2</hi> sats = 99% on air, apyrexial </s></p><p n="p21.55"><s n="s1.2;p21.55">No evidence of jaundice, anaemia, corneal arcus or xanthelasma in his eyes. </s><s n="s2.2;p21.55">No central cyanosis, oedema or lymphadenopathy </s></p><p n="p22.55"><s n="s1.1;p22.55">JVP was not raised </s></p><p n="p23.55"><s n="s1.1;p23.55">His chest, on examination, was symmetrical with no evidence of scars or asymmetry. </s></p><div2><head><hi rend="underlined">Palpation</hi> :</head><p n="p24.55"><s n="s1.3;p24.55">There were no sternal heaves on palpation. </s><s n="s2.3;p24.55">The apex beat was not palpable. </s><s n="s3.3;p24.55">No pain was elicited on palpation of the area the patient had felt the pain the previous Friday. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">Auscultation:</head><p n="p25.55"><s n="s1.1;p25.55">Heart sounds were present in all areas, no added sounds were evident </s></p><p n="p26.55"><s n="s1.1;p26.55">Respiratory - the lung fields had vesicular breathing with no added sounds in all areas. </s></p><p n="p27.55"><s n="s1.3;p27.55">Abdominal examination - the bowel was soft and non-tender on palpation. </s><s n="s2.3;p27.55">No evidence of masses, organomegaly or ascites. </s><s n="s3.3;p27.55">On auscultation there were bowel sounds present in all four quadrants. </s></p><p n="p28.55"><s n="s1.2;p28.55">Neurological - evidence of reduced light touch and vibration sense to mid-calf bilaterally. </s><s n="s2.2;p28.55">Nil else of note. </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="bold">Analysis of history and examination</hi> Reasons for your choice of the cause of the patient's problem(s) and any other cause that still needs to be considered at this stage</head><p n="p29.55"><s n="s1.3;p29.55">The history and examination cannot rule out an NSTEMI or STEMI. However, the patient was non-tender on palpation and there was no evidence of consolidation on auscultation of the lungs, which makes a musculoskeletal or respiratory cause very unlikely. </s><s n="s2.3;p29.55">Dyspepsia cannot be ruled out at this stage, even though the patient was non-tender in the epigastric area. </s><s n="s3.3;p29.55">This diagnosis will need to be looked at further if the ECG shows no abnormalities at rest or on exertion. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="bold">Formulation of the patient's problem(s)</hi> Encapsulate this in physical, psychological and social terms (the triple diagnosis)</head><p n="p30.55"><s n="s1.5;p30.55">Mr <name type="other"/>'s symptoms although minor showed that he had in fact had a severe ischaemic event, which to his pain perception was not severe in nature. </s><s n="s2.5;p30.55">Mr <name type="other"/> will need to be educated as to how his diabetes might have effected his pain receptors and if he should feel a similar persistent chest pain to present at the hospital quickly for assessment. </s><s n="s3.5;p30.55">His diabetes is showing levels of systemic complications with peripheral neuropathy, this will effect him socially as his walking and mobility will be compromised by reduced sensation. </s><s n="s4.5;p30.55">Mr <name type="other"/> appeared psychologically well balanced, he had a good understanding of his diabetes and subsequent chest pain. </s><s n="s5.5;p30.55">However, any person who experiences a life threatening event such as an NSTEMI/STEMI will have psychological repercussions, as it is a reminder of ones own mortality. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="bold">Management</hi> Use the framework of RAPRIOP to structure your proposed management. Refer to the guidelines to the writing of portfolio cases for the details of the issues to be addressed under each heading.</head><div2><head rend="underlined">Investigations</head><p n="p31.55"><s n="s1.1;p31.55"><name type="date"/>: </s></p><p n="p32.55"><s n="s1.1;p32.55">ECG - showed biphasic T waves anterolaterally an indication of acute coronary syndrome. </s></p><p n="p33.55"><s n="s1.1;p33.55">Troponin I levels = 7.68, Creatine kinase = 769. </s></p><p n="p34.55"><s n="s1.1;p34.55">Blood results from <name type="date"/>: </s></p><p n="p35.55"><s n="s1.1;p35.55">FBC - HGB = 11.6, PLT = 247 and WCC = 10.26 </s></p><p n="p36.55"><s n="s1.4;p36.55">Monday <name type="date"/> Mr <name type="other"/> had an angiogram. </s><s n="s2.4;p36.55">Arterial access was first performed at the right radial artery, however, this artery went into spasm preventing access. </s><s n="s3.4;p36.55">Therefore, the right femoral artery was used. </s><s n="s4.4;p36.55">Mr <name type="other"/>had a coronary angiogram and left ventriculogram. </s></p><p n="p37.55"><s n="s1.1;p37.55">Angiogram results: </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p38.55"><s n="s1.1;p38.55">Severe LAD disease, 2 stents were inserted </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p39.55"><s n="s1.1;p39.55">RCA was small and non-dominant with moderate disease </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p40.55"><s n="s1.1;p40.55">Circumflex had mild disease </s></p><p n="p41.55"><s n="s1.1;p41.55">The ventriculogram showed good left ventricular systolic function with mild anterior and apical hypokinesia. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">Reassurance and explanation</head><p n="p42.55"><s n="s1.2;p42.55">The events leading up to his admission and subsequent tests while in hospital were explained to him. </s><s n="s2.2;p42.55">He was given many opportunities to ask any questions, he was given all relevant literature to read and refer to when at home. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">Prescription/medical intervention</head><p n="p43.55"><s n="s1.2;p43.55">Mr <name type="other"/> was already on all medication recommended post NSTEMI to help reduce the risk of further cardiovascular events. </s><s n="s2.2;p43.55">His angiogram and subsequent stenting will help to reduce similar events occurring in the future. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">Observation</head><p n="p44.55"><s n="s1.3;p44.55">Mr <name type="other"/> will be reviewed by his GP and a cardiologist post-angiogram. </s><s n="s2.3;p44.55">An ETT will need to be carried out to ensure there is no severe T wave inversion. </s><s n="s3.3;p44.55">His GP will manage Mr <name type="other"/>'s diabetes and any other issues that may arise which could increase the risk of future events, such as an increase in blood pressure/cholesterol. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">Referral and team working</head><p n="p45.55"><s n="s1.1;p45.55">The referral involved out-of-hours on-call GP service, A&amp;E, Consultant cardiologist and team (at <name type="other"/> and <name type="other"/>), ECG technicians, radiograghers, specialist nurses, HCAs </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">Advice and prevention</head><p n="p46.55"><s n="s1.4;p46.55">Mr <name type="other"/> was told to continue as he would do normally. </s><s n="s2.4;p46.55">Advice on diet, exercise and his diabetes was given. </s><s n="s3.4;p46.55">He was advised to see his GP if he has any new developments of chest pain, palpitations or shortness of breath. </s><s n="s4.4;p46.55">He was given a routine follow-up appointment with the cardiology team to review progress. </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="bold">Outcome</hi> A description of the progress of the patient as far as possible. This should include consideration of further issues to be resolved. Where appropriate you should contact by telephone patients who have been discharged home.</head><p n="p47.55"><s n="s1.3;p47.55">Mr <name type="other"/>was transferred back to <name type="other"/> hospital later the same day as his angiogram. </s><s n="s2.3;p47.55">The post-procedural complication was a right femoral artery haematoma. </s><s n="s3.3;p47.55">There were no other complications. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="bold">Evidence based care and issues for research</hi> A brief consideration of the evidence base required for the diagnosis and management of the patient's problem(s)</head><div2><head><hi rend="underlined">Routine early cardiac catheterisation and revascularisation</hi> :</head><p n="p48.55"><s n="s1.1;p48.55">There have been a number of RCTs comparing early routine angiography versus medical treatment alone [1,2]. </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p49.55"><s n="s1.3;p49.55">1) An RCT compared invasive treatment within the first 7 days versus non-invasive treatment plus planned coronary angiography. </s><s n="s2.3;p49.55">Results showed that invasive treatment significantly reduced the combined outcome of death and myocardial infarction rate compared with non-invasive treatment after 6 months. </s><s n="s3.3;p49.55">They did however; find that early invasive treatment increased major bleeding, but not stroke, compared with non-invasive treatment [1]. </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p50.55"><s n="s1.3;p50.55">2) An RCT compared cardiac catheterisation at 4 - 48 hours and revascularisation versus standard treatment. </s><s n="s2.3;p50.55">Results showed that cardiac catheterisation reduced MIs and readmission for unstable angina after 6 months. </s><s n="s3.3;p50.55">This RCT also found that cardiac catheterisation increased bleeding compared with standard treatment [2]. </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="bold">Commentary</hi> A commentary on issues of epidemiology, psycho-social, health care delivery, ethical issues or disability relevant to the patient and/or problem</head><div2><head><hi rend="underlined">Incidence and prevalence</hi> :</head><p n="p51.55"><s n="s1.3;p51.55">Cororanry artery disease (CAD) is the leading cause of mortality in developed countries and in the developing countries it is becoming a major cause of morbidity and mortality. </s><s n="s2.3;p51.55">Death rates vary from nation and region. </s><s n="s3.3;p51.55">In the USA, for instance, the prevalence of CAD is nearly 4% [3]. </s></p><p n="p52.55"><s n="s1.1;p52.55">Risk factors for ischaemic heart disease can either be fixed or modifiable: </s></p><list type="simple"><head>Fixed - age (risk increases with age), male sex, positive family history</head></list><list type="simple"><head>Modifiable - smoking, hypertension, diabetes, LDL and total cholesterol levels [4].</head></list></div2><div2><head><hi rend="underlined">Acute Coronary Syndrome</hi> :</head><p n="p53.55"><s n="s1.2;p53.55">Is an umbrella term for ischaemic cardiac chest pain of recent origin and includes: unstable angina, NSTEMI, or an acute, evolving or recent MI. The latter has to show features of varying levels of cardiac markers, as well as the patient exhibiting either; ischaemic symptoms, development of pathological Q waves on the ECG, ischaemic ECG changes e.g. </s><s n="s2.2;p53.55">ST elevation or depression or following coronary artery intervention such as an angiogram/plasty [4,5,6,7]. </s></p><p n="p54.55"><s n="s1.3;p54.55">These various events occur due to the rupture of an atherosclerotic plaque and subsequent thrombosis. </s><s n="s2.3;p54.55">A plaque may rupture and re-seal several times causing recurrent episodes of pain. </s><s n="s3.3;p54.55">The severity and type of the acute coronary syndrome will be determined by the severity and duration of the occlusion, the vessel affected and the presence of collateral blood supply [2,3]. </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="bold">Impact on your learning</hi> Describe what you have learnt from this case</head><p n="p55.55"><s n="s1.4;p55.55">Different ways chest pain can present to A&amp;E, different differentials for chest pain. </s><s n="s2.4;p55.55">To remember that an NSYTEMI/STEMI does not always present typically i.e. intense central crushing chest pain, impending doom, sweating, nausea. </s><s n="s3.4;p55.55">In atypical presentations to remember to include Troponin T in the routine blood tests. </s><s n="s4.4;p55.55">Acute coronary syndromes - what are they, how are they classified. </s></p></div1></body><back><div1 type="bibliography"><head rend="bold">References:</head><p>FRISC II Investigators. Invasive compared with non-invasive treatment in unstable coronary-artery disease: FRISC II prospective randomised multicentre study. Fragmin and Fast Revascularisation during Instability in Coronary artery disease Investigators. <hi rend="italic">Lancet</hi> 1999;354:708 - 715. </p><p>Cannon C P, Weintraub W S, Demopoulos L A, <hi rend="italic">et al</hi>., Comparison of early invasive and conservative strategies in patients with unstable coronary syndromes treated with the glycoprotein IIb/IIIa inhibitor tirofiban. <hi rend="italic">N Engl J Med</hi> 2001;344:1879 - 1887. </p><p><seg type="URL" n="http://www.clinicalevidence.com/ceweb/conditions/cvd/0209/0209_background.jsp#incidence"/> accessed on 27/11/05</p><p>Kendall G, Shiu K Y, Johnston S L.Medicine and Surgery: A Concise Textbook. Blackwell Publishing 2005:36</p><p>Julian D G, Cowan J C, McLenachan J M. Cardiology. Eighth Ed. Elsevier Saunders, 2005:105</p><p>Gray H H, Dawkins K D, Morgan J M <hi rend="italic">et al</hi>., Lecture notes on cardiology. Fourth Ed. Blackwell Publishing 2002:100</p><p>Kumar P, Clark MClinical Mecicine.5<hi rend="sup">th</hi> Ed. WB Saunders, 2002</p></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
