<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_0194c" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>No WD &amp; IHD diabetes</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">Proforma
</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">4</p><p n="date">2005-12</p><p n="module title">General Medical Block</p><p n="module code">unknown</p><p n="genre family">Case study</p><p n="discipline">Medicine</p><p n="disciplinary group">LS</p><p n="grade">D</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">1418</p><p n="number of s-units">73</p><p n="number of p">63</p><p n="number of tables">1</p><p n="number of figures">0</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">12</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">6</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">19.4</p><p n="average s-units per p">1.2</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">f</p><p n="year of birth">1974</p><p n="first language">English</p><p n="education">UKA</p><p n="course">Medicine</p><p n="student ID">0194</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><docTitle><titlePart rend="bold">PORTFOLIO CASE No: </titlePart></docTitle><titlePart>Patient Initials<name type="other"/> Hospital Number Keep separate list (<name type="other"/>) Age 74 Gender M</titlePart><titlePart>Portfolio Case presentation number: Phase 2 course document objective(s): Has the patient's permission, including for follow up contact by telephone, been sought and recorded in the case notes? Yes</titlePart></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="bold">Referral information</hi> Source of referral and a summary of key information</head><p n="p1.63"><s n="s1.6;p1.63">Suddenly over night developed severe pain in his knees in feet, which was so bad he couldn't out pressure on his feet. </s><s n="s2.6;p1.63">GP was called out who prescribed him painkillers, he said he couldn't do anything else without blood tests. </s><s n="s3.6;p1.63">Patient went to the <name type="other"/> to get some bloods taken. </s><s n="s4.6;p1.63">Stayed on the floor of the living room the next night as couldn't get up the stairs. </s><s n="s5.6;p1.63">Came into A&amp;E via ambulance as an emergency to the <name type="other"/> on the <name type="date"/> as the pain had not subsided and he was unable to walk to the toilet or upstairs. </s><s n="s6.6;p1.63">Drs in A&amp;E admitted him. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="bold">History</hi> All <hi rend="bold italic">relevant</hi> information gathered from the patient about the presenting illness, co-existing problems, current treatment, <hi rend="italic">significant</hi> past medical history and the social and family background. The patient's view of the nature of the problem and their expectations for treatment. </head><div2><head rend="underlined">Presenting complaint:</head><p n="p2.63"><s n="s1.1;p2.63">Severe pain in knees and feet </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">History of presenting complaint:</head><p n="p3.63"><s n="s1.2;p3.63">Couldn't get feet on the floor, couldn't climb the stairs. </s><s n="s2.2;p3.63">Slept on the floor. </s></p><p n="p4.63"><s n="s1.8;p4.63">Pain in feet was all over an agonising burning/achy pain. </s><s n="s2.8;p4.63">It was v tender/sore to the touch, the point were he couldn't bear anything to touch his legs, not even clothing. </s><s n="s3.8;p4.63">The pain as bout 8=9 out of 10 on the pains scale. </s><s n="s4.8;p4.63">Nothing really made the pain any better. </s><s n="s5.8;p4.63">The tramadol he was prescribed didn't do much good, seems to be working now. </s><s n="s6.8;p4.63">Movement and pressure seems to make it worse. </s><s n="s7.8;p4.63">He thinks a similar thing happened on his right foot after he had an arthroscopy 12 months ago. </s><s n="s8.8;p4.63">But nothing as bad as this current episode. </s></p><p n="p5.63"><s n="s1.2;p5.63">Knees and feet were swollen, red and every hot to the touch. </s><s n="s2.2;p5.63">No other joints were effected. </s></p><p n="p6.63"><s n="s1.2;p6.63">His bowels have stayed the same apart from the tramadol giving him some constipation more recently. </s><s n="s2.2;p6.63">No problems with his waterworks. </s></p><p n="p7.63"><s n="s1.2;p7.63">He was generally feeling well prior to this episode, no fever, not feeling run down. </s><s n="s2.2;p7.63">Hadn't been eating large amounts of offal, protein or drinking lots of alcohol before this admission. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">Past medical history:</head><p n="p8.63"><s n="s1.1;p8.63">Some arthritic knee pain over the last 5 years and niggling right thumb pain </s></p><p n="p9.63"><s n="s1.1;p9.63">Had viral pneumonia at age of 41 </s></p><p n="p10.63"><s n="s1.1;p10.63">Type II diabetes, controlled on diet and tablets, was diagnosed about 6 years ago. </s></p><p n="p11.63"><s n="s1.1;p11.63">12 months ago had an investigative arthroscopy on right knee </s></p><p n="p12.63"><s n="s1.2;p12.63">Never had a MI, stroke, epilepsy. </s><s n="s2.2;p12.63">RF. Does have slightly raised cholesterol and blood pressure. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">Family history:</head><p n="p13.63"><s n="s1.1;p13.63">His mother had arthritis, but he doesn't think she was treated for it. </s></p><p n="p14.63"><s n="s1.2;p14.63">He thinks his brother had a similar problem with his hand, where his hand was so tender he didn't want clothes on it, but he is not sure what the diagnosis was. </s><s n="s2.2;p14.63">His other brother is fine. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">Drug history and allergies:</head><list type="simple"><item>NKDA</item><item>Aspirin 75mg OD PO</item><item>Pravastatin 40mg OD PO</item><item>Glimitizide 2mg OD PO</item><item>Felodipine 10mg OD PO</item><item>Doxazosin 8mg OD PO</item><item>Thyroxine 100 micrograms OD PO</item><item>Colchicine 500 micrograms OD PO</item><item>Tramadol 50 mg BD PO</item><item>Lactulose 10mls TDS PO</item><item>PRN:</item><item>Tramadol 50mg (maximum dose 100mg and maximum per 24 hours = 400 mg)</item></list><p n="p15.63"/></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">Social history:</head><p n="p16.63"><s n="s1.1;p16.63">Lives in <name type="other"/> with his wife who has an arthritic hip and neck, both can manage the stairs and ADLs </s></p><p n="p17.63"><s n="s1.1;p17.63">He has 3 daughters and 2 sons all are well. </s></p><p n="p18.63"><s n="s1.1;p18.63">Ex-smoker, gave up when he was 41 </s></p><p n="p19.63"><s n="s1.2;p19.63">Drinks no more than 5 units of alcohol a week. </s><s n="s2.2;p19.63">Drinks red wine occasionally. </s></p><p n="p20.63"><s n="s1.1;p20.63">A retired mechanic, used to work at <name type="other"/> for 26 years before they made him redundant, then he worked at <name type="other"/> for 5 years until he was 61 years old. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">Systems review:</head><list type="simple"><head><hi rend="bold">Cardiovascular</hi> - dyspnoea, PND, chest pain, palpitations, intermittent claudication, oedema</head></list><list type="simple"><head><hi rend="bold">Respiratory</hi> - cough, haemoptysis, sputum, wheeze</head></list><list type="simple"><head><hi rend="bold">Gastrointestinal</hi> - appetite, weight, heartburn, dysphagia, abdominal pain, nausea, vomiting, bowel habits changed, melaena</head></list><list type="simple"><head><hi rend="bold">Neurological</hi> - the patient has never had any of the following: parasthesiae, faints, fits or funny turns, headaches, weakness, dizziness</head></list><list type="simple"><head><hi rend="bold">Locomotor</hi> - joint pain, stiffness, back pain</head></list><p n="p21.63"/></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="bold">Analysis of history</hi> The most likely single cause of the presentation, other possible causes and reasons for these choices. The findings to be looked for on physical examination to help decide the cause.</head><p n="p22.63"/></div1><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="bold">Physical examination</hi> Highlight the findings most relevant to your clinical problem solving by underlining them</head><p n="p23.63"><s n="s1.2;p23.63">Hands - clear (small scar on thenar eminence right hand) No clubbing. </s><s n="s2.2;p23.63">Hands no signs of RA or OA, normal full movement without pain </s></p><list type="simple"><item>Pulse - 96bpm and regular</item><item>Blood pressure - 140/80</item><item>Eyes - no jaundice, some pallor in conjunctiva</item><item>Tongue - quite dry and furry, no central cyanosis</item><item>No lymphadenopathy</item><item>Slight ankle oedema??</item></list><p n="p24.63"><s n="s1.1;p24.63">Ankles: </s></p><list type="simple"><head rend="bold">Right</head><item>Swollen (oedema?)</item><item>No pain</item><item>Some pain in the front of ankle on dorsiflexion</item><item>No redness</item><item>Not hot</item></list><list type="simple"><head rend="bold">Left</head><item>Normal</item><item>No pain</item><item>No pain on movement</item><item>No redness</item><item>Not hot</item></list><p n="p25.63"><s n="s1.1;p25.63">Knees: </s></p><list type="simple"><head rend="bold">Right</head><item>No pain</item><item>Normal temp</item><item>Deformity</item><item>Muscle wasting of quads</item><item>Flexion to 70 degrees</item><item>Some creptius</item><item>No pain on rotation</item><item>No fluid</item><item>No fixed flexion of knee</item></list><list type="simple"><head rend="bold">Left</head><item>No pain</item><item>Normal temp</item><item>No deformity</item><item>Muscle wasting of quads</item><item>Flexion to 75 degrees</item><item>Some crepitus</item><item>No pain on rotation</item><item>No fluid</item><item>No fixed flexion of knee</item></list><p n="p26.63"><s n="s1.1;p26.63"><hi rend="underlined">Look</hi>: </s></p><p n="p27.63"><s rend="underlined" n="s1.1;p27.63">Feel: </s></p><p n="p28.63"><s rend="underlined" n="s1.1;p28.63">Move: </s></p><p n="p29.63"><s n="s1.1;p29.63">Heart - S1 and S2 heard, no added sounds </s></p><p n="p30.63"><s n="s1.1;p30.63">Chest - lungs clear </s></p><p n="p31.63"><s n="s1.1;p31.63">Abdomen - bowel sounds heard and non tender on light and deep palpation </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="bold">Analysis of history and examination</hi> Reasons for your choice of the cause of the patient's problem(s) and any other cause that still needs to be considered at this stage</head><p n="p32.63"><s n="s1.1;p32.63">From notes: </s></p><p n="p33.63"><s n="s1.1;p33.63">Kidney problems CRF? </s></p><table id="BAWE_0194c-tab.001"><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p34.63"><s n="s1.1;p34.63">MCV = 90 </s></p><p n="p35.63"><s n="s1.1;p35.63">Ca2+ = normal </s></p><p n="p36.63"><s n="s1.1;p36.63">Xray results - right knee shows osteophytes ++, OA. Knee xr NAD </s></p><p n="p37.63"><s n="s1.1;p37.63">Arthroscopy showed grade IV OA on right knee, patient having total knee replacement in august </s></p><p n="p38.63"><s n="s1.1;p38.63">Both knees aspirated the aspirate contained calcium pyrophosphate crystals </s></p><p n="p39.63"><s n="s1.1;p39.63">Diagnosis = polyarticular crystal arthropathy or polyarticualr septic joints, the latter is less likely. </s></p><p n="p40.63"><s n="s1.2;p40.63">Why anaemia? </s><s n="s2.2;p40.63">Why lymphocytes going down? </s></p><p n="p41.63"><s n="s1.1;p41.63">B12, folate and ferritin all normal </s></p><p n="p42.63"><s n="s1.1;p42.63">Urate = 640 </s></p><p n="p43.63"><s n="s1.1;p43.63">Diagnosis is pseudo gout </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="bold">Formulation of the patient's problem(s)</hi> Encapsulate this in physical, psychological and social terms (the triple diagnosis)</head><p n="p44.63"><s n="s1.1;p44.63">This usually asymptomatic condition of the elderly is due to deposition of calcium pyrophosphate dihydrate (CPPD) crystals in large joints, most commonly the knee. </s></p><p n="p45.63"><s n="s1.2;p45.63">The crystals are initially deposited in the cartilage - chondrocalcinosis - where they are associated with degenerative changes. </s><s n="s2.2;p45.63">The shedding of the crystals into the joint space results in an acute synovitis and a clinical picture that is similar to that seen in gout. </s></p><p n="p46.63"><s n="s1.1;p46.63">This condition is more common in men (ratio of 1.5:1). </s></p><list type="bulleted"><head>pseudogout: </head><item>usually presents as an acute synovitis often affecting the knee </item><item>radiology shows calcification of articular cartilage and, if the knee is involved, of the menisci </item><item>CPPD crystals are demonstrable in aspirated synovial fluid</item></list><p rend="bulleted" n="p47.63"><s n="s1.1;p47.63">gout - occurs generally in patients over 40 years old; affects small joints, especially the great toe; clinical features include severe joint pain and swelling, hyperuricaemia; radiological features include soft-tissue swelling; there is uric acid crystal deposition in affected joints; treatment measures include rest and non-steroidal anti-inflammatory drugs e.g. diclofenac, in chronic gout allopurinol prophylaxis </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p48.63"><s n="s1.1;p48.63">pseudogout - usually affects the elderly; large joints generally involved (especially the knee joint); clinical features include moderate joint pain and swelling; radiology reveals calcification of articular cartilage menisci; calcium pyrophosphate crystals are deposited in affected joints; possible treatment measures include rest, non-steroidal anti-inflammatory drugs and joint aspiration </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p49.63"><s n="s1.1;p49.63">radiology - reveals linear opacification of articular cartilage </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p50.63"><s n="s1.1;p50.63">examination of synovial fluid - shows positively birefringent crystals </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p51.63"><s n="s1.1;p51.63">arthroscopy - 'microtophi' on the synovial membrane </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p52.63"><s n="s1.1;p52.63">tests to investigate associated conditions </s></p><p n="p53.63"><s n="s1.2;p53.63">Treatment consists of the well tried combination of rest and NSAID's. </s><s n="s2.2;p53.63">Intra-articular injection of corticosteroids or joint aspiration may be used in more severe cases. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="bold">Management</hi> Use the framework of RAPRIOP to structure your proposed management. Refer to the guidelines to the writing of portfolio cases for the details of the issues to be addressed under each heading.</head><div2><head rend="underlined">Investigations</head><p n="p54.63"/></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">Reassurance and explanation</head><p n="p55.63"/></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">Prescription/medical intervention</head><p n="p56.63"/></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">Observation</head><p n="p57.63"/></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">Referral and team working</head><p n="p58.63"/></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">Advice and Prevention</head><p n="p59.63"/></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="bold">Outcome</hi> A description of the progress of the patient as far as possible. This should include consideration of further issues to be resolved. Where appropriate you should contact by telephone patients who have been discharged home.</head><p n="p60.63"/></div1><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="bold">Evidence based care and issues for research</hi> A brief consideration of the evidence base required for the diagnosis and management of the patient's problem(s)</head><p n="p61.63"/></div1><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="bold">Commentary</hi> A commentary on issues of epidemiology, psycho-social, health care delivery, ethical issues or disability relevant to the patient and/or problem</head><p n="p62.63"/></div1><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="bold">Impact on your learning</hi> Describe what you have learnt from this case</head><p n="p63.63"/></div1></body><back/></text></TEI.2>
