<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_0194h" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>No18 Pleuraleffusion MT CTS decompression</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">deleted: header: student name; footer: page numbers</note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">Proforma
</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">4</p><p n="date">2005-11</p><p n="module title">General Medical Block</p><p n="module code">unknown</p><p n="genre family">Case study</p><p n="discipline">Medicine</p><p n="disciplinary group">LS</p><p n="grade">D</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">2914</p><p n="number of s-units">171</p><p n="number of p">96</p><p n="number of tables">0</p><p n="number of figures">1</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">4</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">39</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">17.0</p><p n="average s-units per p">1.8</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">f</p><p n="year of birth">1974</p><p n="first language">English</p><p n="education">UKA</p><p n="course">Medicine</p><p n="student ID">0194</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><docTitle><titlePart><hi rend="bold">PORTFOLIO CASE No:</hi> 18</titlePart></docTitle><titlePart>Patient Initials<name type="other"/> Hospital Number Keep separate list Age 76 Gender M</titlePart><titlePart>Portfolio Case presentation number: 7.2 Chronic recurrent central chest pain, 7.8 progressive breathlessness Phase 2 course document objective(s): 7.14 Pleural disease, 7.2 Investigations Has the patient's permission, including for follow up contact by telephone, been sought and recorded in the case notes? Yes</titlePart></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="bold">Referral information</hi> Source of referral and a summary of key information</head><p n="p1.96"><s n="s1.2;p1.96">Right-sided chest pain for the past 6 months, recent increase in pain levels, preventing patient from sleeping. </s><s n="s2.2;p1.96">Mr <name type="other"/> was having regular reviews with his GP who referred him to A&amp;E after assessment of a CXR taken on <name type="date"/> showing a right-sided pleural effusion. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="bold">History</hi> All <hi rend="bold italic">relevant</hi> information gathered from the patient about the presenting illness, co-existing problems, current treatment, <hi rend="italic">significant</hi> past medical history and the social and family background. The patient's view of the nature of the problem and their expectations for treatment. </head><div2><head rend="underlined">Presenting complaint:</head><p n="p2.96"><s n="s1.1;p2.96">Right-sided chest pain </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">History of presenting complaint:</head><p n="p3.96"><s n="s1.15;p3.96">The pain started 6 months ago. </s><s n="s2.15;p3.96">It was 'gnawing' in nature (like a low-lying headache) and radiated around the chest wall from anterior to posterior on the right side. </s><s n="s3.15;p3.96">This pain was constantly present. </s><s n="s4.15;p3.96">Recently the pain had increased in intensity and was stopping Mr <name type="other"/> from sleeping. </s><s n="s5.15;p3.96">This was due to the discomfort; rather than orthopnoea or PND. It was painful to take a deep breath or sneeze. </s><s n="s6.15;p3.96">The pain would momentarily get better on moving to a different position, but would quickly come back again. </s><s n="s7.15;p3.96">Co-codamol did not relieve the pain but unfortunately made him constipated, which is being treated with senna. </s><s n="s8.15;p3.96">Since the use of co-codamol he has been getting bright red blood PR, which he believes is due to the combination of constipation, straining at stool and haemorrhoids. </s><s n="s9.15;p3.96">Recently he has noticed that he was getting SOBOE and was tired after walking the dog. </s><s n="s10.15;p3.96">Mr <name type="other"/> did not suffer from palpitations, intermittent claudication or leg oedema. </s><s n="s11.15;p3.96">Mr <name type="other"/> had a cough on admission, which was persistent and would 'leave him gasping for air' but the sputum was clear, no blood or green/yellow coloration and he didn't think he had a temperature. </s><s n="s12.15;p3.96">He has not had a wheeze or any other chest pain. </s><s n="s13.15;p3.96">His dyspepsia has not worsened and believes the pain is different in nature; he has had no nausea, vomiting, or dysphagia. </s><s n="s14.15;p3.96">On <name type="date"/> he went to the GP, who was initially treating him for a muscular sprain, as no other clinical evidence of lung pathology was evident. </s><s n="s15.15;p3.96">On this day he sent Mr <name type="other"/> for a CXR, as his chest was dull to percussion on the right hand side, the results of which precipitated the GP to send Mr <name type="other"/> to A&amp;E for review. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">Past medical history:</head><p rend="bulleted" n="p4.96"><s n="s1.1;p4.96">No history of hypertension, high cholesterol, diabetes, asthma, CVA, RF </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p5.96"><s n="s1.2;p5.96">Longstanding problems with indigestion and acid reflux. </s><s n="s2.2;p5.96">OGD revealed a hiatus hernia </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p6.96"><s n="s1.2;p6.96"><name type="date"/> 2005 - Collapse, but didn't go to hospital as wife had an MI about an hour later, while the paramedics were present. </s><s n="s2.2;p6.96">Subsequent nail infection and cellulitis caused an admission for i.v. antibiotics </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p7.96"><s n="s1.1;p7.96">Right inguinal herniorrhaphy, he currently has a LIH, which doesn't cause him any trouble. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p8.96"><s n="s1.1;p8.96">1973 - myocardial infarction </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p9.96"><s n="s1.1;p9.96">Lost left index finger in an industrial accident </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p10.96"><s n="s1.1;p10.96">Appendectomy in childhood </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">Family history:</head><p n="p11.96"><s n="s1.1;p11.96">Elder brother had RF, but has not had any heart problems since </s></p><p n="p12.96"><s n="s1.1;p12.96">Nil of note </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">Drug history and allergies:</head><list type="bulleted"><item>Ranitidine 150mg BD - antacid, H <hi rend="sub">2</hi>-receptor antagonist</item><item>Senna TT OD - stimulant laxative</item><item>Diclofenac 50mg TDS - NSAID, anti-inflammatory and analgesic </item><item>Paracetamol 1g TDS - non-opioid analgesic </item><item>Codeine Phosphate 30 - 60mg PRN - opioid analgesic</item></list><p n="p13.96"><s n="s1.1;p13.96">Patient thinks he might be allergic to penicillin, as it upsets his stomach at high doses. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">Social history:</head><p rend="bulleted" n="p14.96"><s n="s1.4;p14.96">Retired car mechanic. </s><s n="s2.4;p14.96">Lives with his wife in a bungalow in <name type="other"/>. </s><s n="s3.4;p14.96">His wife is diabetic and has had a CVA, which caused her to become partially sighted and confused. </s><s n="s4.4;p14.96">Recently she has had an MI, which was treated with coronary artery stenting and insertion of a pacemaker. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p15.96"><s n="s1.1;p15.96">He walks his dog daily </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p16.96"><s n="s1.2;p16.96">Mr <name type="other"/>is an ex-smoker, who gave up in 1973. </s><s n="s2.2;p16.96">He started smoking at the age of 18 and smoked about 10 - 15 a day (16 - 20 pack year history). </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p17.96"><s n="s1.1;p17.96">Mr <name type="other"/> used to drink alcohol in moderation as a young man but now he is teetotal </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p18.96"><s n="s1.1;p18.96">He was intermittently exposed to asbestos during the replacement of car brakes as a mechanic </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p19.96"><s n="s1.1;p19.96">He doesn't own any birds or pigeons </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p20.96"><s n="s1.1;p20.96">He has 3 sons and one daughter </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p21.96"><s n="s1.1;p21.96">His daughter has had breast cancer, a thyroidectomy and spondylitis </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p22.96"><s n="s1.2;p22.96">One son has osteogenesis imperfecta (lives with his brother), as does his granddaughter (lives in specialist accommodation) both in wheel chairs now. </s><s n="s2.2;p22.96">Both were looked after by Mr <name type="other"/> and his wife but it became too much for them to properly care for them, too heavy to lift etc. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">Systems review:</head><p n="p23.96"><s n="s1.4;p23.96">He hadn't thought he had unintentionally lost weight, however, his family had said that he looked thinner in the face and his trousers were falling down. </s><s n="s2.4;p23.96">He was wondering whether the weight of the fluid in his chest was masking any weight loss. </s><s n="s3.4;p23.96">He mentioned that he had dysuria and described micturition syncope. </s><s n="s4.4;p23.96">There was nil of note on neurological or locomtor systems review. </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="bold">Analysis of history</hi> The most likely single cause of the presentation, other possible causes and reasons for these choices. The findings to be looked for on physical examination to help decide the cause.</head><p n="p24.96"><s n="s1.1;p24.96">Differential diagnosis will be dictated by whether the effusion is unilateral or bilateral, if it is an exudate or transudate, the latter cannot be ascertained at this point. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p25.96"><s n="s1.1;p25.96">Exudative effusions are more commonly unilateral, which would make a diagnosis from the following list more likely: </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p26.96"><s n="s1.1;p26.96">Carcinoma (primarily bronchial or secondary), this is likely because of the smoking history, the comments from his family that he is losing weight and his age. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p27.96"><s n="s1.1;p27.96">Mesothelioma, this is also likely due to his age and past history of exposure to asbestos at work. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p28.96"><s n="s1.2;p28.96">Pancreatitis or a sub-phrenic abscess are unlikely as the description of the pain is atypical for both of these presentations. </s><s n="s2.2;p28.96">They cannot however, be ruled out until further tests are done. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p29.96"><s n="s1.1;p29.96">Autoimmune disease this is less likely as the patient is more likely to feel systemically unwell and to present with multiple systemic problems. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p30.96"><s n="s1.1;p30.96">Bacterial pneumonia or TB are an unlikely cause due to the patient not suffering from a temperature or green sputum and the long time-course of the problem (6 months). </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p31.96"><s n="s1.1;p31.96">Haemothorax is unlikely as there is no history of trauma. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p32.96"><s n="s1.1;p32.96">Chylothroax, due to a leaking thoracic duct, this is unlikely as this occurs on the left hand side of the pleura and is caused by trauma or surgery. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p33.96"><s n="s1.2;p33.96">Yellow nail syndrome, caused by abnormal lymph drainage leading to yellow nails (onycholysis), pleural effusion and lymphoedema. </s><s n="s2.2;p33.96">There is no history of palpable cervical lymph nodes or yellowing of the nails. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p34.96"><s n="s1.2;p34.96">Transudative effusions are often bilateral which would make this a less likely diagnosis in this case. </s><s n="s2.2;p34.96">Common causes of bilateral effusion include: </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p35.96"><s n="s1.1;p35.96">Cardiac failure, nephrotic syndrome, hepatic cirrhosis, hypoalbuninaemia (malnutrition, chronic disease, malabsorption) </s></p><p n="p36.96"><s n="s1.1;p36.96">Unusual causes include: </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p37.96"><s n="s1.1;p37.96">Pericardial constriction and myxoedema [1,2] </s></p><p n="p38.96"><s n="s1.2;p38.96">On examination, it is important to take notice of any additional signs that might point towards a less common cause of unilateral pleural effusion. </s><s n="s2.2;p38.96">Many of these diagnoses will only be ruled out by blood tests, pleural aspirate tests etc., to narrow down the right diagnosis for Mr <name type="other"/>. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="bold">Physical examination</hi> Highlight the findings most relevant to your clinical problem solving by underlining them</head><p n="p39.96"><s n="s1.1;p39.96">A slim gentleman who was sitting comfortably in the chair </s></p><p n="p40.96"><s n="s1.3;p40.96">No clubbing, peripheral cyanosis or asterixis. </s><s n="s2.3;p40.96">Nails were normal. </s><s n="s3.3;p40.96">He did not have a left index finger due to amputation. </s></p><list type="simple"><item>Pulse = 87 bpm, regular and normal character; BP 140/85; RR = 20; O <hi rend="sub">2</hi> sats = 94% on air; apyrexial.</item></list><p n="p41.96"><s n="s1.1;p41.96">No evidence of jaundice, anaemia, horner's syndrome (unilateral ptosis, miosis and anhydrosis) central cyanosis, oedema or lymphadenopathy. </s></p><p n="p42.96"><s n="s1.1;p42.96">JVP was not raised. </s></p><p n="p43.96"><s n="s1.1;p43.96">His chest, on examination (anteriorly and posteriorly), was symmetrical with no evidence of scars, asymmetry, or musculoskeletal abnormality e.g. scoliosis. </s></p><div2><head><hi rend="underlined">Palpation</hi> :</head><p n="p44.96"><s n="s1.3;p44.96">The trachea was not deviated. </s><s n="s2.3;p44.96">The chest expanded equally on both sides. </s><s n="s3.3;p44.96">The apex beat was palpable in the 5 <hi rend="sup">th</hi> ICS MCL. No pain was elicited on palpation of the chest. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">Percussion:</head><p n="p45.96"><s n="s1.2;p45.96">Normal percussion on the left side of the chest. </s><s n="s2.2;p45.96">Stony dull to percussion on the right hand side, anteriorly from the 3 <hi rend="sup">rd</hi> ICS and posteriorly from mid-scapular. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">Auscultation:</head><p n="p46.96"><s n="s1.2;p46.96">On the left hand side of the chest, normal vesicular breathing with no added sounds was heard. </s><s n="s2.2;p46.96">Decreased air entry and reduced vocal resonance on the right hand side, consistent with the area that was dull to percussion. </s></p><p n="p47.96"><s n="s1.1;p47.96">Cardiovascular, abdominal and neurological examination was unremarkable. </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="bold">Analysis of history and examination</hi> Reasons for your choice of the cause of the patient's problem(s) and any other cause that still needs to be considered at this stage</head><p n="p48.96"><s n="s1.1;p48.96">As the effusion is unilateral and there was little to no evidence of cardiac failure, nephrotic syndrome or hepatic cirrhosis in the history or examination it is very unlikely to be any of these causes. </s></p><p n="p49.96"><s n="s1.1;p49.96">This means that the most likely cause is one of the following: </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p50.96"><s n="s1.1;p50.96">Carcinoma (primarily bronchial / secondary or mesothelioma) is a likely diagnosis and cannot be ruled out until further tests are carried out. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p51.96"><s n="s1.1;p51.96">Bacterial pneumonia or TB are unlikely causes due to the patient not suffering from a temperature or green sputum and the long time-course of the problem (6 months) </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p52.96"><s n="s1.3;p52.96">Pancreatitis or a sub-phrenic abscess are also unlikely, as there were no palpable masses or pain elicited on abdominal examination. </s><s n="s2.3;p52.96">In addition, the description of the pain is atypical for both of these presentations. </s><s n="s3.3;p52.96">However, they cannot be ruled out until further tests are done. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p53.96"><s n="s1.2;p53.96">Autoimmune disease is again less likely as the patient is more likely to feel systemically unwell and to present with multiple systemic problems. </s><s n="s2.2;p53.96">There were no abnormalities in other systems, which indicate that this diagnosis is less likely. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="bold">Formulation of the patient's problem(s)</hi> Encapsulate this in physical, psychological and social terms (the triple diagnosis)</head><p n="p54.96"><s n="s1.6;p54.96">Mr <name type="other"/> and his wife have had a bad year in regards to their health. </s><s n="s2.6;p54.96">Both of them have had a number of problems this year, taking their toll both physically and psychologically. </s><s n="s3.6;p54.96">In addition, the worry that the reason for the pleural effusion could be due to cancer is another concern. </s><s n="s4.6;p54.96">On a social front Mr <name type="other"/> has had an unlucky time since retirement. </s><s n="s5.6;p54.96">He and his wife moved to <name type="other"/> with his son and granddaughter, however, they fell into problems with their house developers, lost all their money, which forced them to come back to the <name type="other"/>. </s><s n="s6.6;p54.96">This means that they now live in a rented council house, their son and granddaughter can no longer live with them due to monetary as well as physical constraints. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="bold">Management</hi> Use the framework of RAPRIOP to structure your proposed management. Refer to the guidelines to the writing of portfolio cases for the details of the issues to be addressed under each heading.</head><div2><head rend="underlined">Investigations:</head><div3><head><name type="date"/></head><p n="p55.96"><s n="s1.1;p55.96">ECG - normal trace, sinus tachycardia </s></p></div3><div3><head><name type="date"/></head><p n="p56.96"><s n="s1.1;p56.96">CXR - Pleural effusion to 3 <hi rend="sup">rd</hi> ICS RHS </s></p></div3><div3><head><name type="date"/></head><p n="p57.96"><s n="s1.2;p57.96">Drained 3.2 litres from chest cavity. </s><s n="s2.2;p57.96">Chest drain came out causing surgical emphysema </s></p><p n="p58.96"><s n="s1.2;p58.96">CXR - chest drain and therapeutic tap, fluid in lower zone. </s><s n="s2.2;p58.96">Costo-phrenic angle obscured </s></p><p n="p59.96"><s n="s1.1;p59.96">Microbiology results showed no growth after 48 hours and no acid fast bacilli </s></p><list type="simple"><head><hi rend="underlined">Pleural fluid results</hi>:</head><item>Total protein = 45 g/L Fluid LDH = 523 U/L Fluid glucose = 47 mmol/L</item></list><p n="p60.96"><s n="s1.1;p60.96">These results indicate that the effusion is an exudate </s></p></div3><div3><head><name type="date"/></head><p n="p61.96"><s n="s1.1;p61.96">CXR - surgical emphysema due to chest drain falling out </s></p><list type="simple"><head><hi rend="underlined">Blood results</hi>:</head><item>Na+ = 139</item><item>HGB = 12.6 (<hi rend="bold">L</hi>)</item><item>PLT = 338</item><item>BASO = 0.02</item><item>K = 4.4 </item><item>RBC = 4.07 (<hi rend="bold">L</hi>)</item><item>NEUT = 8.63 (<hi rend="bold">H</hi>)</item><item>LYMP = 1.91</item><item>Urea = 6.1 </item><item>MCV = 93.4</item><item>WBC = 11.22 (<hi rend="bold">H</hi>)</item><item>MONO = 0.47</item><item>Cr = 112</item><item>HCT = 0.380 (<hi rend="bold">L</hi>)</item><item>CRP = 122(<hi rend="bold">H</hi>)</item><item>EOS = 0.19</item><item>MCHC = 33.2 </item></list><p n="p62.96"><s n="s1.2;p62.96">These results indicate there is an inflammatory reaction occurring somewhere in the body. </s><s n="s2.2;p62.96">Mr <name type="other"/> also shows normocytic anaemia which would indicate a cause of acute blood loss, a chronic disease, infection, inflammation or malignancy </s></p></div3><div3><head><name type="date"/></head><p n="p63.96"><s n="s1.1;p63.96">CXR - surgical emphysema due to chest drain falling out </s></p><p n="p64.96"><s n="s1.1;p64.96">Right-sided pneumothorax </s></p></div3><div3><head><name type="date"/></head><p n="p65.96"><s n="s1.1;p65.96">CXR - hydropneumothorax - lower and mid zones RHS </s></p></div3><div3><head><name type="date"/></head><p n="p66.96"><s n="s1.2;p66.96">Pleural fluid cytology - no malignant cells. </s><s n="s2.2;p66.96">Lymphocytes and mesothelial cells seen. </s></p></div3><div3><head><name type="date"/></head><p n="p67.96"><s n="s1.1;p67.96"><hi rend="underlined">Plan</hi>: </s></p><p n="p68.96"><s n="s1.1;p68.96">Awaiting histology and CT scan thorax </s></p><p n="p69.96"><s n="s1.2;p69.96">If biopsy negative do diagnostic tap for cytology. </s><s n="s2.2;p69.96">Consider VATS (video assisted lung and chest surgery) key-hole surgery in chest looking for smaller tumours) </s></p></div3><div3><head><name type="date"/></head><p n="p70.96"><s n="s1.2;p70.96">Referred to Mr <name type="other"/>'s team to discuss possibility of VATS, as biopsy equivocal. </s><s n="s2.2;p70.96">Need to repeat biopsy or VATS </s></p><p n="p71.96"><s n="s1.1;p71.96">CXR - hydropneumothorax - lower and mid zones RHS (similar to admission CXR, patient asymptomatic) </s></p></div3><div3><head><name type="date"/></head><p n="p72.96"><s n="s1.1;p72.96">Patient discussed at the lung multi-disciplinary meeting </s></p><p n="p73.96"><s n="s1.6;p73.96"><hi rend="underlined">CT Chest results</hi>: Large subcutaneous emphysema over the right chest. </s><s n="s2.6;p73.96">Right-sided hydropneumothorax. </s><s n="s3.6;p73.96">Partial collapse right lower lobe. </s><s n="s4.6;p73.96">No signs to suggest malignancy. </s><s n="s5.6;p73.96">Left lung multiple emphysematous bullae formation at the periphery. </s><s n="s6.6;p73.96">CT abdomen NAD. ?Right kidney malignancy. </s></p></div3><div3><head><name type="date"/></head><p n="p74.96"><s n="s1.1;p74.96">Right VAT for pleural biopsy and pleurodesis with talc; pleural deposits suggestive of mesothelioma </s></p></div3><div3><head><name type="date"/></head><p n="p75.96"><s n="s1.1;p75.96">CXR - clear (post-operative x-ray) </s></p></div3><div3><head>To date</head><p n="p76.96"><s n="s1.1;p76.96">Histology pending </s></p></div3></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">Reassurance and explanation</head><p n="p77.96"><s n="s1.3;p77.96">It has been well documented in the notes that the patient has been fully informed at each stage of the management. </s><s n="s2.3;p77.96">Issues concerning the reason for the tests and what could be the possible cause have been discussed. </s><s n="s3.3;p77.96">The patient is fully aware that the primary concern is a malignancy, in the sense of a diagnosis that needs to ruled-out if possible. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">Prescription/medical intervention</head><p n="p78.96"><s n="s1.4;p78.96">The main concern for the patient is optimum pain control. </s><s n="s2.4;p78.96">He has not had many problems with dyspnoea, since the 3.2 litres were initially drained at the beginning of his admission. </s><s n="s3.4;p78.96">A possible way to control his pain without causing constipation is a difficult one. </s><s n="s4.4;p78.96">Issues concerning this have needed to be addressed as they have appeared. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">Observation</head><p n="p79.96"><s n="s1.2;p79.96">Mr <name type="other"/> has been regularly observed on the respiratory ward. </s><s n="s2.2;p79.96">Since transfer to the cardiothoracic unit he has been in HDU post-operation to ensure that the maximum care is available during his post-operative recovery. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">Referral and team working</head><p n="p80.96"><s n="s1.1;p80.96">The staff that have been involved with his care include: A&amp;E staff, respiratory consultant and team, cardiothoracic surgeon and team, nurses, HCAs </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">Advice and prevention</head><p n="p81.96"><s n="s1.1;p81.96">The diagnosis for Mr <name type="other"/> is still not known, therefore, advice and prevention cannot be covered. </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="bold">Outcome</hi> A description of the progress of the patient as far as possible. This should include consideration of further issues to be resolved. Where appropriate you should contact by telephone patients who have been discharged home.</head><p n="p82.96"><s n="s1.3;p82.96">Histology from the VATS on the <name type="date"/> is still pending. </s><s n="s2.3;p82.96">The pleurodesis until this point had been successful. </s><s n="s3.3;p82.96">Mr <name type="other"/> was recovering on the HDU ward after a successful operation. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="bold">Evidence based care and issues for research</hi> A brief consideration of the evidence base required for the diagnosis and management of the patient's problem(s)</head><p n="p83.96"><s n="s1.4;p83.96">Patients who undergo video assisted thoracic surgery (VATS) rather than thoracotomy tend to experience less pain and shorter hospital stays [3, 4]. </s><s n="s2.4;p83.96">Lung biopsies for parenchymal lung disease or excision biopsies at the periphery of the lung can be performed relatively easily; it is believed that it makes inspection and biopsy of the pleura easier. </s><s n="s3.4;p83.96">A systematic review of the evidence from randomised trials has not been done assessing the relative advantages compared with open surgery. </s><s n="s4.4;p83.96">Therefore, it is not possible to make recommendations for best practice [3]. </s></p><p n="p84.96"><s n="s1.4;p84.96">One paper reviewed 325 VATS chemical pleurodesis performed over 4 years for malignant pleural effusions (MPE). </s><s n="s2.4;p84.96">They concluded that VATS chemical pleurodesis for oncological pleural effusion management is a safe and versatile procedure. </s><s n="s3.4;p84.96">In addition, they found that the use of talc rather than alcohol significantly increased the therapeutic success rate [4]. </s><s n="s4.4;p84.96">A further two papers also believe that VATS should be the method of choice and that talc poudrage is safe and effective in obtaining pleurodesis [5,6]. </s></p><p n="p85.96"><s n="s1.2;p85.96">Another study evaluated the outcomes, safety, and efficacy of an indwelling pleural drainage catheter (PDC) system compared with VATS. </s><s n="s2.2;p85.96">41 consecutive patients with symptomatic MPE between 2000 and 2002 and concluded that the PDC system is an efficacious treatment of patients with MPEs [7]. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Commentary</head><p n="p86.96"><s n="s1.2;p86.96">Pleural effusion, is not a diagnosis in itself and is defined as an abnormal accumulation of fluid in the pleural space. </s><s n="s2.2;p86.96">Excess fluid results from the disruption of the equilibrium that exists across the parietal and visceral pleural membranes. </s></p><p n="p87.96"><s n="s1.3;p87.96">The relative annual incidence of pleural effusion is estimated to be 320/100,000 people in the western world. </s><s n="s2.3;p87.96">Congestive heart failure, pneumonia, malignancy, and pulmonary emboli account for most of these pleural effusions. </s><s n="s3.3;p87.96">Morbidity and mortality of pleural effusions are directly related to cause, stage of disease at the time of presentation, and biochemical findings in the pleural fluid. </s></p><p n="p88.96"><s n="s1.1;p88.96">The following mechanisms play a role in the formation of pleural effusion: </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p89.96"><s n="s1.1;p89.96">Altered permeability of the pleural membranes e.g. inflammatory process, neoplastic disease </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p90.96"><s n="s1.1;p90.96">Reduction in intravascular oncotic pressure e.g. hypoalbuminemia, hepatic cirrhosis </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p91.96"><s n="s1.1;p91.96">Increased capillary permeability or vascular disruption e.g. trauma, neoplastic disease, inflammatory process, infection, pulmonary infarction, drug hypersensitivity, pancreatitis </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p92.96"><s n="s1.1;p92.96">Increased capillary hydrostatic pressure in the systemic and/or pulmonary circulation e.g. congestive heart failure, superior vena caval syndrome </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p93.96"><s n="s1.1;p93.96">Reduction of pressure in pleural space and/or the lung unable to expand e.g. extensive atelectasis, mesothelioma </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p94.96"><s n="s1.1;p94.96">Decreased lymphatic drainage or complete blockage, including thoracic duct obstruction or rupture e.g. malignancy, trauma </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p95.96"><s n="s1.1;p95.96">Increased fluid in peritoneal cavity, with migration across the diaphragm via the lymphatics e.g. hepatic cirrhosis, peritoneal dialysis [8] </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0194h-pic.001"><head>Fig 1: Diagram of video-assisted thoracic surgery (VATS) [9]</head></figure></div1><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="bold">Impact on your learning</hi> Describe what you have learnt from this case</head><p n="p96.96"><s n="s1.4;p96.96">Pleural effusions - what can be the cause, what to look for on the history and examination. </s><s n="s2.4;p96.96">The clinical signs that can be elicited on examination. </s><s n="s3.4;p96.96">Surgical emphysema. </s><s n="s4.4;p96.96">VATS and pleurodesis. </s></p></div1></body><back><div1 type="bibliography"><head><hi rend="underlined">References</hi> :</head><p>Kumar P, Clark MClinical Mecicine.5<hi rend="sup">th</hi> Ed. WB Saunders, 2002</p><p>Kendall G, Shiu K Y, Johnston S L.Medicine and Surgery: A Concise Textbook. Blackwell Publishing 2005</p><p>Sedrakyan A, van der Meulen J, Lewsey J <hi rend="italic">et al</hi>.,Video assisted thoracic surgery for treatment of pneumothorax and lung resections: systematic review of randomised clinical trials. <hi rend="italic">Br Med J</hi>. 2004;329:1008 </p><p>Brega-Massone P P, Conti B, Magnani B <hi rend="italic">et al</hi>.,Minimally invasive thoracic surgery for diagnostic assessment and palliative treatment in recurrent neoplastic pleural effusion. <hi rend="italic">Thorac cardiobvasc Surg</hi>. 2004 Aug;52(4):191 - 5.</p><p>Cardillo G, Faccido F, Carbone L. <hi rend="italic">et al</hi>.,Long-term follow-up of video-assisted talc pleurodesis in malignant recurrent pleural effusions. <hi rend="italic">Eur J Cardiothorac Surg</hi>. 2002 Feb;21(2):302 - 5</p><p>Schulze M, Boehle A S, Kurdow R <hi rend="italic">et al</hi>., Effective treatment of malignant pleural effusion by minimal invasive thoracic surgery: thoracoscopic talc pleurodesis and pleuroperitoneal shunts in 101 patients. <hi rend="italic">Ann Thorac Surg</hi>. 2001 Jun;71(6):1809 - 12</p><p>Ohm C, Park D, Vogen M <hi rend="italic">et al</hi>.,Use of an indwelling pleural catheter compared with thorascopic talc pleurodesis in the management of malignant pleural effusions. <hi rend="italic">Am Surg</hi>. 2003 Mar;69(3):198 - 202</p><p><seg type="URL" n="http://www.emedicine.com/emerg/topic462.htm"/> accessed on 10/12/05</p><p>Landreneau R J, Mack M J, Dowling R D <hi rend="italic">et al</hi>.,The role of thoracoscopy in lung cancer management. <hi rend="italic">Chest</hi> 1998; 113: 6S-12S</p></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
