<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_0194f" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>No16 GR CLL &amp; HF</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">deleted: header: student name; footer: page numbers</note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">Proforma
</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">4</p><p n="date">2005-12</p><p n="module title">Cardiovascular Block</p><p n="module code">unknown</p><p n="genre family">Case study</p><p n="discipline">Medicine</p><p n="disciplinary group">LS</p><p n="grade">D</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">2658</p><p n="number of s-units">143</p><p n="number of p">100</p><p n="number of tables">2</p><p n="number of figures">0</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">9</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">35</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">18.6</p><p n="average s-units per p">1.4</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">f</p><p n="year of birth">1974</p><p n="first language">English</p><p n="education">UKA</p><p n="course">Medicine</p><p n="student ID">0194</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><docTitle><titlePart><hi rend="bold">PORTFOLIO CASE No:</hi> 16</titlePart></docTitle><titlePart>Patient Initials<name type="other"/> Hospital Number Keep separate list Age 83 Gender M</titlePart><titlePart>Portfolio Case presentation number: 7.3 Left ventricular failure, 6.3 Haematological malignancy, 7.10 Weight loss and progressive breathlessness Phase 2 course document objective(s): 7.6 Heart failure, 6.3 Haematological malignancy, 3.22 Thyroid disorders Has the patient's permission, including for follow up contact by telephone, been sought and recorded in the case notes? Yes</titlePart></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="bold">Referral information</hi> Source of referral and a summary of key information</head><p n="p1.100"><s n="s1.2;p1.100">Mr <name type="other"/>, with a 30-year history of CLL (Stage C), had had a three-day history of insomnia with associated low mood, shortness of breath and swollen legs. </s><s n="s2.2;p1.100">He went to the haematology department who advised him to go to A&amp;E where he was subsequently admitted on <name type="date"/>. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="bold">History</hi> All <hi rend="bold italic">relevant</hi> information gathered from the patient about the presenting illness, co-existing problems, current treatment, significant past medical history and the social and family background. The patient's view of the nature of the problem and their expectations for treatment. </head><div2><head rend="underlined">Presenting complaint:</head><p n="p2.100"><s n="s1.1;p2.100">Three-day history of insomnia with low mood, shortness of breath and swollen legs. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">History of presenting complaint:</head><p n="p3.100"><s n="s1.5;p3.100">Mr <name type="other"/> had been feeling 'depressed' for the past month, with a three-day history of insomnia. </s><s n="s2.5;p3.100">He can currently only walk a few steps on the flat before getting short of breath, this sudden change occurred about one week prior to admission. </s><s n="s3.5;p3.100">Prior to this he had been getting progressively short of breath over the last 6 months. </s><s n="s4.5;p3.100">He has had problems with his legs swelling in the past, but this had resolved. </s><s n="s5.5;p3.100">The current leg oedema started about a month ago and has progressively worsened. </s></p><p n="p4.100"><s n="s1.2;p4.100">Mr <name type="other"/> does suffer with orthopneoa and needs 4 pillows at night time to sleep comfortably, he doesn't suffer from PND, chest pain, intermittent claudication. </s><s n="s2.2;p4.100">He has also reported recent feelings of intermittent palpitations. </s></p><p n="p5.100"><s n="s1.5;p5.100">Has had a productive cough for the last 4 years, which was white, but has recently changed to brown sputum. </s><s n="s2.5;p5.100">He doesn't suffer from any pleuritic chest pain, haemoptysis or wheeze. </s><s n="s3.5;p5.100">He has been more constipated recently and has lost about 4 - 5 stones in the last 2 years. </s><s n="s4.5;p5.100">He is regularly reviewed by a dietician who prescribes food supplements (Pro-Cal®). </s><s n="s5.5;p5.100">In addition, he bruises very easily (caused by CLL and low platelet count) and recently has been getting very intolerant to heat. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">Past medical history:</head><list type="bulleted"><item>No history of asthma, MI, CVA, diabetes, RF, epilepsy </item><item>1946 - peritonitis following ruptured appendix</item><item>1975 - diagnosed with CLL (currently stage C), associated spleno- and hepatomegaly and pancytopaenia</item><item>1975 - blind in right eye</item><item>1985 - cataract left eye</item><item>Atrial fibrillation </item><item>Suffers with back and rib pain</item></list><p n="p6.100"/></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">Family history:</head><p n="p7.100"><s n="s1.1;p7.100">Nil of note </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">Drug history and allergies:</head><p n="p8.100"><s n="s1.1;p8.100">NKDA </s></p><list type="bulleted"><head>Management of CLL:</head><item>Vigam i.v. injection every 3/52 - infection prevention (normal immunoglobulin)</item><item>Blood transfusion every 6/52</item><item>He is put on a course of steroids for 10 days in between his blood transfusion dates (reduce haemolysis risk)</item></list><list type="bulleted"><item>Codeine phosphate 60mg PO QDS - opioid analgesic</item><item>Paracetamol 1g - non-opioid analgesic</item><item>Temazepam 10mg nocte - short-acting hypnotic, used to treat insomnia </item></list></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">Social history:</head><p rend="bulleted" n="p9.100"><s n="s1.1;p9.100">He retired at 65, during the latter part of his working life he was self-employed and owned two DIY shops </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p10.100"><s n="s1.1;p10.100">Lives with his wife in a house in <name type="other"/> </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p11.100"><s n="s1.1;p11.100">They have adapted the house, building a toilet downstairs so that he doesn't have to climb the stairs </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p12.100"><s n="s1.1;p12.100">Has a son and a daughter who both live near-by </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p13.100"><s n="s1.1;p13.100">Teetotal - CLL medication dictates he should not drink </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p14.100"><s n="s1.1;p14.100">Ex-smoker, gave up 60 years ago after the war, started at the age of 14 on 40/day (18 pack year history) </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">Systems review:</head><p rend="bulleted" n="p15.100"><s n="s1.1;p15.100">Gastrointestinal - nil of note </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p16.100"><s n="s1.1;p16.100">Neurological - Mr <name type="other"/> has not suffered from parasthesiae, faints, fits or funny turns, headaches, weakness or dizziness </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p17.100"><s n="s1.1;p17.100">Locomotor - he does not suffer from joint pain, stiffness, back pain </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="bold">Analysis of history</hi> The most likely single cause of the presentation, other possible causes and reasons for these choices. The findings to be looked for on physical examination to help decide the cause.</head><p rend="bulleted" n="p18.100"><s n="s1.1;p18.100">Heart failure (RHF or CHF), due to the evidence of dyspnoea, orthopnea and peripheral oedema </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p19.100"><s n="s1.1;p19.100">Dyspnoea and general lethargy secondary to anaemia due to his CLL </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p20.100"><s n="s1.2;p20.100">Malnutrition - Mr <name type="other"/> has stated that his nutrition is a problem, due to a reduced appetite and receives advice from the dietician. </s><s n="s2.2;p20.100">He states he does eat the drinks he is prescribed, which should combat any protein deficits in his body, making this diagnosis less likely. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p21.100"><s n="s1.1;p21.100">Liver failure due to heptao-splenomegaly </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p22.100"><s n="s1.1;p22.100">Nephrotic syndrome/renal failure </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p23.100"><s n="s1.1;p23.100">Insomnia due to depression coupled with the orthopnea and dyspnoea </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p24.100"><s n="s1.1;p24.100">Hypothyroidism can cause constipation, intolerance of heat and insomnia - evidence of a goitre and thyroid disease need to be assessed on examination. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="bold">Physical examination</hi> Highlight the findings most relevant to your clinical problem solving by underlining them</head><p n="p25.100"><s n="s1.2;p25.100">Mr <name type="other"/> was a cachexic man sitting comfortably in the chair. </s><s n="s2.2;p25.100">His ribs were clearly visible </s></p><p n="p26.100"><s n="s1.3;p26.100">His hands were warm and dry. </s><s n="s2.3;p26.100">There was palmar erythema bilaterally and a resting tremour. </s><s n="s3.3;p26.100">No evidence of clubbing, peripheral cyanosis, splinter haemorrhages, xanthomata or dupuytren's contracture on his hands. </s></p><p n="p27.100"><s n="s1.1;p27.100">There was extensive bruising on his hands and forearms. </s></p><p n="p28.100"><s n="s1.1;p28.100">Pulse = 115 bpm and irregularly irregular, BP 102/52, temp 37.4 <hi rend="sup">O</hi>C, RR = 20, O <hi rend="sub">2</hi> sats 96% on air </s></p><p n="p29.100"><s n="s1.2;p29.100">Conjunctiva was pale, there was no evidence of jaundice, corneal arcus or xanthelasma in his eyes. </s><s n="s2.2;p29.100">No central cyanosis, lymphadenopathy or goitre. </s></p><p n="p30.100"><s n="s1.1;p30.100">JVP raised above 4cm at 45 degrees </s></p><p n="p31.100"><s n="s1.1;p31.100">Bilateral pitting oedema up to knees </s></p><p n="p32.100"><s n="s1.1;p32.100">Mr <name type="other"/>'s chest, on examination, was symmetrical with significant muscle wasting, revealing his ribs and sternum. </s></p><div2><head><hi rend="underlined">Cardiovascular examination</hi> :</head><p rend="bulleted" n="p33.100"><s n="s1.2;p33.100">Palpation: Apex beat was sustained and non-displaced. </s><s n="s2.2;p33.100">No evidence of heaves or thrills. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p34.100"><s n="s1.2;p34.100">Auscultation: HI + HII + no extra or additional heart sounds. </s><s n="s2.2;p34.100">Evidence of a grade 3 pansystolic murmur heard in all 4 areas, loudest at the apex. </s></p><p n="p35.100"><s n="s1.1;p35.100">No carotid bruits </s></p></div2><div2><head><hi rend="underlined">Respiratory examination</hi> :</head><p rend="bulleted" n="p36.100"><s n="s1.1;p36.100">Palpation: Trachea non-deviated, expansion normal </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p37.100"><s n="s1.1;p37.100">Percussion: Dullness to percussion at both lung bases, posteriorly </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p38.100"><s n="s1.2;p38.100">Auscultation: Bilateral expiratory crackles, heard most clearly in the left lower base. </s><s n="s2.2;p38.100">Generalised wheeze. </s></p></div2><div2><head><hi rend="underlined">Abdominal examination</hi> :</head><p rend="bulleted" n="p39.100"><s n="s1.1;p39.100">Both the spleen and liver were easily visible when the patient was supine </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p40.100"><s n="s1.2;p40.100">Palpation: Liver was palpable five fingers breadth below the subcostal marginSpleen was palpable to the umbilicusNo other masses felt. </s><s n="s2.2;p40.100">Kidneys not palpable. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p41.100"><s n="s1.2;p41.100">Percussion: Liver was percussed two ICS superiorly. </s><s n="s2.2;p41.100">Shifting dullness elicited. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p42.100"><s n="s1.2;p42.100">Auscultation: No liver or splenic bruits heard. </s><s n="s2.2;p42.100">Bowel sounds present. </s></p></div2><div2><head><hi rend="underlined">Neurological examination</hi> : </head><p n="p43.100"><s n="s1.1;p43.100">no abnormalities found on gross examination. </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="bold">Analysis of history and examination</hi> Reasons for your choice of the cause of the patient's problem(s) and any other cause that still needs to be considered at this stage</head><p n="p44.100"><s n="s1.1;p44.100">The evidence from the history and examination would indicate that the most likely cause of Mr <name type="other"/>'s current problems would be: </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p45.100"><s n="s1.1;p45.100">Heart failure (RHF or CHF), this is a likely diagnosis due to dyspnoea, orthopnea and peripheral oedema; as well as, the evidence of a systolic murmur on auscultation, which would add additional strain on the heart; and bilateral basal lung crackles, indicating pulmonary oedema. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p46.100"><s n="s1.1;p46.100">Anaemia could be an additional complication, exacerbating the heart failure and subsequent dyspnoea, as there was evidence of pallor in the conjunctiva. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p47.100"><s n="s1.1;p47.100">Liver failure cannot be ruled out due to marked hepatomegaly and ascites. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p48.100"><s n="s1.2;p48.100">It is less likely to be renal failure; although there was ascites, there was no loin tenderness or palpable kidneys. </s><s n="s2.2;p48.100">Again, this diagnosis cannot be ruled out and blood test will help to understand current renal function. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p49.100"><s n="s1.1;p49.100">In the history, Mr <name type="other"/> stated that he had been feeling depressed which can exacerbate current physical problems. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p50.100"><s n="s1.1;p50.100">Apart from a resting tremor, there was no evidence of thyroid disease on examination, blood results will give the definitive diagnosis. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="bold">Formulation of the patient's problem(s)</hi> Encapsulate this in physical, psychological and social terms (the triple diagnosis)</head><p n="p51.100"><s n="s1.4;p51.100">Mr <name type="other"/> has a number of health problems, which need to be managed in a co-ordinated fashion to ensure that he receives the best possible care. </s><s n="s2.4;p51.100">He appears to understand his CLL very well and the treatment he has for this and why he has it. </s><s n="s3.4;p51.100">His main complaint for this admission is his insomnia and rapid degeneration of his breathing. </s><s n="s4.4;p51.100">Psychologically he states that he is low in mood, this will need to be addressed, as any feelings of depression will exacerbate his physical condition, which is already a delicate one. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="bold">Management</hi> Use the framework of RAPRIOP to structure your proposed management. Refer to the guidelines to the writing of portfolio cases for the details of the issues to be addressed under each heading.</head><div2><head rend="underlined">Investigations</head><div3><head rend="bold"><name type="date"/></head><list type="simple"><item>Na+ = 132(L), K+ = 5, Urea = 7.9(H), Creatinine = 93, Ca2+ =2.14, Albumin = 40, ALP = 110(H), Cholesterol = 3.7, TSH = 10.50(H), PLT = 29(L), WCC = 294(H), HB = 12.2</item></list><list type="simple"><item>BP 16/10/05 lying = 100/31, standing = 94/54</item></list><p n="p52.100"/></div3><div3><head rend="bold"><name type="date"/></head><p n="p53.100"><s n="s1.1;p53.100">HB = 12.2(L) - had been given 3 units on <name type="date"/> - WCC = 294.37(H), PLT = 29(L) </s></p></div3><div3><head rend="bold"><name type="date"/></head><list type="simple"><head>BP readings: lying 100/31; standing 94/54</head></list><p n="p54.100"/></div3><div3><head rend="bold"><name type="date"/></head><p n="p55.100"><s n="s1.4;p55.100"><hi rend="underlined">Echocardiogram</hi>: Biventricular failure with dilated LA/LV/RV. Non-symptomatic valve disease. </s><s n="s2.4;p55.100">Global moderate pericardial effusion about 1.8 - 2cm. </s><s n="s3.4;p55.100">No evidence of diastolic RV collapse. </s><s n="s4.4;p55.100">IVC non-dilated. </s></p><p n="p56.100"><s n="s1.2;p56.100"><hi rend="underlined">Impression</hi>: Biventricular failure, not cardiac tamponade. </s><s n="s2.2;p56.100">Severe tricuspid regurge and mild aortic stenosis. </s></p><p n="p57.100"><s n="s1.1;p57.100"><hi rend="underlined">Plan</hi>: continue with enalopril and frusemide, if BP falls reduce enalopril </s></p><p n="p58.100"><s n="s1.2;p58.100">Pericardial effusion can be caused by CCF and hypothyroidism. </s><s n="s2.2;p58.100">Both of these need to be treated to help reduce the pericardial effusion. </s></p></div3><div3><head rend="bold"><name type="date"/></head><p n="p59.100"><s n="s1.1;p59.100">TSH = 14.18, thyroxine increased to 100 micrograms. </s></p></div3><div3><head rend="bold"><name type="date"/></head><p n="p60.100"><s n="s1.1;p60.100">Spiking temperature; septic screen and chest x-ray organised (NAD) </s></p><p n="p61.100"><s n="s1.1;p61.100"><hi rend="underlined">Plan</hi>: Transfer to B3 under care of cardiology. </s></p></div3><div3><head rend="bold"><name type="date"/></head><p n="p62.100"><s n="s1.1;p62.100">Transferred to care of Dr <name type="other"/>, Consultant Cardiologist </s></p><p n="p63.100"><s n="s1.1;p63.100">Frusemide increased to 40mg BD </s></p></div3><div3><head rend="bold"><name type="date"/></head><list type="simple"><item>HGB = 10.7(L), WBC = 323 (H), PLT = 35 (L), Na+ = 142, K+ = 4.3, Urea = 15.9(H), Creatinine = 117</item></list><p n="p64.100"><s n="s1.2;p64.100">Evidence of his CLL with anaemia, increased WBC count and reduced platelets. </s><s n="s2.2;p64.100">There is also evidence of dehydration, with some possible renal failure, as although the number is within the normal range, Mr <name type="other"/> has little muscle mass, to explain this level of creatinine. </s></p></div3><div3><head rend="bold"><name type="date"/></head><list type="bulleted"><head><hi rend="underlined">Plan</hi>: </head><item>Started on i.v. frusemide 40mg BD</item><item>Digoxin 125 mgms OD</item><item>Fluid and salt restriction, daily weights, low blood pressure 84/64</item></list><p n="p65.100"/></div3><div3><head rend="bold"><name type="date"/></head><p n="p66.100"><s rend="underlined" n="s1.1;p66.100">Repeat echo: </s></p><p n="p67.100"><s n="s1.1;p67.100">Pericardial effusion 2.0 cm posteriorly and 1.7 cm laterally. </s></p><p n="p68.100"><s n="s1.2;p68.100">A pericardiocentesis would be difficult due to the size and position of the effusion. </s><s n="s2.2;p68.100">Would need to transfuse platelets before the procedure to reduce bleeding risk. </s></p></div3><div3><head rend="bold"><name type="date"/></head><p n="p69.100"><s rend="underlined" n="s1.1;p69.100">Haematology review: </s></p><p n="p70.100"><s n="s1.2;p70.100">Consider blood transfusion. </s><s n="s2.2;p70.100">Need to make sure the patient is not fluid overloaded (which would exacerbate the current heart failure), however, it may improve O <hi rend="sub">2</hi> sats, cardiac and respiratory function. </s></p></div3><div3><head rend="bold"><name type="date"/></head><p n="p71.100"><s n="s1.1;p71.100">Blood transfusion </s></p></div3><div3><head rend="bold"><name type="date"/></head><p n="p72.100"><s rend="underlined" n="s1.1;p72.100">Bedside echo </s></p><p n="p73.100"><s n="s1.2;p73.100">Global pericardial effusion mainly seen posteriolaterally. </s><s n="s2.2;p73.100">1.8-2.86cm posteriorly and 1.05cm anteriorly to RV free wall </s></p><list type="simple"><head rend="underlined">Bloods post-transfusion:</head><item>HGB = 11.4(L), PLT = 27(L), RBC = 3.28, MCV = 113.7(H), HCT = 0.373(L), MCHC = 30.6(L), WBC = 93.10 (H), NEUT = 1.49, LYMP = 90.68 </item></list></div3><div3><head rend="bold"><name type="date"/></head><p n="p74.100"><s n="s1.1;p74.100">Seen by heart failure nurse, who will arrange a home visit post-discharge </s></p><p n="p75.100"><s n="s1.1;p75.100"><hi rend="underlined">Discharged</hi> - Plan: </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p76.100"><s n="s1.1;p76.100">Repeat echo shows no new changes; as the pericardial effusion is mostly around the LV posteriorly it would be difficult to drain, as little fluid present subcostally </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p77.100"><s n="s1.1;p77.100">Review in heart failure clinic in 2/12 </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p78.100"><s n="s1.1;p78.100">Outpatient echo prior to the clinic appointment to review progress </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p79.100"><s n="s1.1;p79.100">Heart failure nurse home visit </s></p></div3></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">Reassurance and explanation</head><p n="p80.100"><s n="s1.2;p80.100">At each step of Mr <name type="other"/>'s hospital admission, the investigations and results were explained and discussed with him. </s><s n="s2.2;p80.100">At each stage the reasons for his different symptoms and what was being done were explained. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">Prescription/medical intervention</head><p n="p81.100"><s n="s1.2;p81.100">Mr <name type="other"/> is a difficult case as he has many different dimensions to his care. </s><s n="s2.2;p81.100">The most acute problem, his heart failure, was the most important thing to control/improve, while keeping an eye on his CLL and hypothyroidism. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">Observation</head><p n="p82.100"><s n="s1.1;p82.100">Throughout his stay he had daily weights, lying and standing BP readings (as his BP was consistently low and needed to be monitored, especially with the vigorous diuretic use for his heart failure, which could reduce his blood pressure further), repeat echocardiogram carried out to monitor the progression of the pericardial effusion and heart failure. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">Referral and team working</head><p n="p83.100"><s n="s1.1;p83.100">Haematology Consultant and team, A&amp;E staff, Clinical Pharmacologist/General Medicine Consultant and team, nurses, HCAs, Consultant Cardiologist and team, radiologist, echo-specialist nurse, heart failure nurse, heart failure clinic </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">Advice and prevention</head><p n="p84.100"><s n="s1.1;p84.100">Advice given and maintained by the haematologist, cardiologist and heart failure nurse </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="bold">Outcome</hi> A description of the progress of the patient as far as possible. This should include consideration of further issues to be resolved. Where appropriate you should contact by telephone patients who have been discharged home.</head><p n="p85.100"><s n="s1.1;p85.100">Mr <name type="other"/> was discharged on the <name type="date"/>, with follow-up as recorded in the final line of results/investigations box above. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="bold">Evidence-based care and issues for research</hi> A brief consideration of the evidence base required for the diagnosis and management of the patient's problem(s)</head><p n="p86.100"><s n="s1.1;p86.100">There is good evidence-based research for the treatment of heart failure with angiotensin converting enzyme (ACE) inhibitors, angiotensin II receptor blockers (ARBs), -blockers and digoxin [1]. </s></p><div2><head><hi rend="underlined">ACE inhibitors</hi> :</head><p n="p87.100"><s n="s1.1;p87.100">A number of trials have shown that ACE inhibitors reduced ischaemic events, mortality and hospital admission for heart failure compared with placebo [2, 3]. </s></p></div2><div2><head><hi rend="underlined">ARBs</hi> :</head><p n="p88.100"><s n="s1.1;p88.100">Published evidence has shown that ARBs reduced mortality and admission for heart failure compared with placebo in people with New York Heart Association (NYHA) heart failure class II - IV. It was also shown to be an effective alternative for patients who were intolerant to ACE inhibitors [4,5]. </s></p></div2><div2><head><hi rend="underlined">(-blockers</hi> :</head><p n="p89.100"><s n="s1.1;p89.100">There has been strong evidence that adding a -blocker with an ACE inhibitor decreased mortality and hospital admission in symptomatic people with heart failure of any NYHA class [6,7]. </s></p></div2><div2><head><hi rend="underlined">Digoxin</hi> :</head><p n="p90.100"><s n="s1.1;p90.100">One large RCT showed that people receiving diuretics, ACE inhibitors and digoxin had reduced levels of admission to hospital due to worsening heart failure at 37 months compared with placebo, but there was no significant difference in mortality rates [8]. </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="bold">Commentary</hi> A commentary on issues of epidemiology, psycho-social, health care delivery, ethical issues or disability relevant to the patient and/or problem</head><p n="p91.100"><s n="s1.2;p91.100">Mr <name type="other"/> is a very complicated patient with many different health problems. </s><s n="s2.2;p91.100">Due to space limitation, I will focus on heart failure and CLL. </s></p><div2><head><hi rend="underlined">Heart failure</hi> :</head><div3><head><hi rend="underlined">Definition</hi> :</head><p n="p92.100"><s n="s1.3;p92.100">Heart failure is the inability of the heart to meet the demands of the body with normal perfusion pressures. </s><s n="s2.3;p92.100">It is characterised clinically by dyspnoea, effort intolerance, fluid retention, and poor survival. </s><s n="s3.3;p92.100">Heart failure can be due to systolic or diastolic dysfunction and is associated with elevated levels of brain natiuretic peptide (BNP) and pro-NT BNP [9,10]. </s></p></div3><div3><head><hi rend="underlined">Incidence and prevalence</hi> :</head><p n="p93.100"><s n="s1.1;p93.100">U.S. and European studies have shown an incidence rate [11]: </s></p><table id="BAWE_0194f-tab.001"><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p94.100"><s n="s1.1;p94.100">Fewer than 15% of people with heart failure under 65 years have normal systolic function, whereas the prevalence is about 40% in people over 65 years [12]. </s></p></div3><div3><head><hi rend="underlined">Aetiology and risk factors</hi> :</head><p n="p95.100"><s n="s1.2;p95.100">The commonest cause of heart failure is coronary artery disease; other causes include hypertension, cardiomyopathy and valvular heart disease [9]. </s><s n="s2.2;p95.100">Risk factors include LVH, cigarette smoking, hyperlipidaemia, and diabetes. </s></p></div3><div3><head><hi rend="underlined">Prognosis</hi> :</head><p n="p96.100"><s n="s1.3;p96.100">The 5-year mortality rate ranges from 26 - 75% [10]. </s><s n="s2.3;p96.100">Re-admission rates of 16% within 6 months of first admission have been recorded. </s><s n="s3.3;p96.100">The most common cause of death is due to ventricular arrhythmias and is responsible for 25 - 50% of all deaths [9]. </s></p></div3></div2><div2><head><hi rend="underlined">Chronic lymphocytic leukaemia (CLL)</hi> :</head><p n="p97.100"><s n="s1.6;p97.100">CLL is the uncontrolled proliferation and accumulation of mature B lymphocytes. </s><s n="s2.6;p97.100">The symptoms of the disease are due to bone marrow failure and subsequent immunosuppression. </s><s n="s3.6;p97.100">Patients with CLL suffer from anaemia, infection and bleeding, due to pancytopaenia. </s><s n="s4.6;p97.100">The disease can normally be kept under control for about 10 years. </s><s n="s5.6;p97.100">Patients can often die from infection or it can evolve into a high-grade large-cell non-Hodgkin's lymphoma 'Richter's transformation', which is more aggressive and difficult to treat. </s><s n="s6.6;p97.100">There are two different staging classifications (helps with prognosis), Mr <name type="other"/>'s classification is using the Rai staging system: </s></p><table id="BAWE_0194f-tab.002"><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p98.100"><s n="s1.1;p98.100">*Progression = weight loss, fatigue, massive organomegaly and a rapidly increasing lymphocyte count. </s></p><p n="p99.100"><s n="s1.1;p99.100">Diagnosis is made by evidence of small lymphocytes on blood film and is confirmed by immunophenotyping, showing co-expression of CD5 and CD19 antigen [13]. </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="bold">Impact on your learning</hi> Describe what you have learnt from this case</head><p n="p100.100"><s n="s1.1;p100.100">CCF (presentations, management and evidence-based trials for treatment of heart failure); echocardiograms (what are they used for, what is measured and why, how are they done); CLL (what is it, how is it managed). </s></p></div1></body><back><div1 type="bibliography"><head><hi rend="underlined">References</hi> :</head><p><seg type="URL" n="http://www.clinicalevidence.com/ceweb/conditions/cvd/0204/0204.jsp"/> accessed on 11/12/05</p><p>SOLVD Investigators. Effect of enalapril on survival in patients with reduced left ventricular ejection fractions and congestive heart failure. <hi rend="italic">N Engl J Med</hi> 1991;325:293 - 302</p><p>Garg R, Yusuf S, for the Collaborative Group on ACE Inhibitor Trials. Overview of randomised trials of angiotensin-converting enzyme inhibitors on mortality and morbidity in patients with heart failure. <hi rend="italic">JAMA</hi> 1995;273:1450 - 1456</p><p>Jong P, Demers C, McKelvie R S, <hi rend="italic">et al</hi>,. Angiotensin receptor blockers in heart failure: meta-analysis of randomized controlled trials. <hi rend="italic">J Am Coll Cardiol</hi> 2002;39:463 - 470. Search date 2001; primary sources Medline, Embase, Biological Abstracts, International Pharmaceutical Abstracts, Cochrane Controlled Trials Database, McMaster Cardiovascular Randomized Clinical Trial Registry, and Science Citation Index. </p><p>Granger C B, McMurray J J, Yusuf S, <hi rend="italic">et al</hi>., Effects of candesartan in patients with chronic heart failure and reduced left-ventricular systolic function intolerant to angiotensin-converting-enzyme inhibitors: the CHARM-Alternative trial. <hi rend="italic">Lancet</hi> 2003;362:772 - 776</p><p>Packer M, Fowler M B, Roecker E B, <hi rend="italic">et al</hi>., Effect of carvedilol on the morbidity of patients with severe chronic heart failure: results of the carvedilol prospective randomised cumulative survival (COPERNICUS) study. <hi rend="italic">Circulation</hi> 2002;106:2194 - 2199</p><p>Krum H, Roecker E B, Mohacsi P, <hi rend="italic">et al</hi>., Effects of initiating carvedilol in patients with severe chronic heart failure: results from the COPERNICUS Study. <hi rend="italic">JAMA</hi> 2003;289:712 - 718</p><p>Digitalis Investigation Group. The effect of digoxin on mortality and morbidity in patients with heart failure. <hi rend="italic">N Engl J Med</hi> 1997;336:525 - 533 </p><p>Julian D G, Cowan J C, McLenachan J M. Cardiology. Eighth Ed. Elsevier Saunders, 2005</p><p>Gray H H, Dawkins K D, Morgan J M et al., Lecture notes on cardiology. Fourth Ed. Blackwell Publishing 2002</p><p>Cowie M R, Mosterd A, Wood D A, <hi rend="italic">et al</hi>., The epidemiology of heart failure. <hi rend="italic">Eur Heart J</hi> 1997;18:208 - 225</p><p>Vasan R S, Benjamin E J, Levy D. Congestive heart failure with normal left ventricular systolic function. <hi rend="italic">Arch Intern Med</hi> 1996;156:146 - 157</p><p>Kumar P, Clark MClinical Medicine.5th Ed. WB Saunders, 2002 494 - 495 </p></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
