<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_0194a" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>No5 dysphagia</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">Proforma
</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">4</p><p n="date">2005-02</p><p n="module title">Gastrointenstinal Rotation</p><p n="module code">unknown</p><p n="genre family">Case study</p><p n="discipline">Medicine</p><p n="disciplinary group">LS</p><p n="grade">D</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">1009</p><p n="number of s-units">49</p><p n="number of p">42</p><p n="number of tables">0</p><p n="number of figures">0</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">5</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">0</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">20.6</p><p n="average s-units per p">1.2</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">f</p><p n="year of birth">1974</p><p n="first language">English</p><p n="education">UKA</p><p n="course">Medicine</p><p n="student ID">0194</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><docTitle><titlePart><hi rend="bold">PORTFOLIO CASE No:</hi> 5</titlePart></docTitle><titlePart>Patient Initials<name type="other"/> Hospital Number Keep separate list (<name type="other"/>) Age 67 Gender M</titlePart><titlePart>Portfolio Case presentation number: Phase 2 course document objective(s): Has the patient's permission, including for follow up contact by telephone, been sought and recorded in the case notes? Yes</titlePart></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="bold">Referral information</hi> Source of referral and a summary of key information</head><p n="p1.42"><s n="s1.4;p1.42">Referred by GP to Dr <name type="other"/> outpatients clinic, the patient was having persistent problems with eating, chronic vomiting and abdominal pain since October 2004. </s><s n="s2.4;p1.42">Treatment with paracetamol, then PPIs prescribed by his GP did not relieve the symptoms. </s><s n="s3.4;p1.42">On the third visit to his GP he was referred on the 2 week urgent dysphagia referral list for further endoscopic investigation. </s><s n="s4.4;p1.42">The patient was attending Dr <name type="other"/> outpatients clinic 10 days after the endoscopy to find out the results from the endoscopy. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="bold">History</hi> All <hi rend="bold italic">relevant</hi> information gathered from the patient about the presenting illness, co-existing problems, current treatment, <hi rend="italic">significant</hi> past medical history and the social and family background. The patient's view of the nature of the problem and their expectations for treatment. </head><div2><head><hi rend="underlined">Presenting complaint:</hi> Problems with eating, continuous vomiting and stomach pains</head><p n="p2.42"/></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">History of presenting complaint:</head><p n="p3.42"><s n="s1.15;p3.42">The problems with eating, stomach pains and chronic vomitjng started in October 2004 and the symptoms have not changed in character since this time. </s><s n="s2.15;p3.42">The patient says he vomits after eating, he hasn't been able to keep anything down for more than an hour and a half since xmas. </s><s n="s3.15;p3.42">When he is sick the food is undigested. </s><s n="s4.15;p3.42">He feels that the food is sitting at the top of his gullet/stomach and not going any further. </s><s n="s5.15;p3.42">The epigastric pain is central and moves to the right upper quadrant. </s><s n="s6.15;p3.42">The pain was described like a dead ache that goes away after he has vomited. </s><s n="s7.15;p3.42">It is aggravated by lying on his back on right side and not eating makes the pain better. </s><s n="s8.15;p3.42">The patient has lost 2 stone since January. </s><s n="s9.15;p3.42">He feels tired and sick all the time. </s><s n="s10.15;p3.42">Since this his bowels have changed and now he only goes once a week and the stools are 'just like water', he used to be as regular as clockwork once a day. </s><s n="s11.15;p3.42">His urine has nit changed in frequency, character and is non painful. </s><s n="s12.15;p3.42">The patient commented that he is continually starving and cannot satisfy himself. </s><s n="s13.15;p3.42">Since January he has also suffered from visual symptoms where is eyesight glazes over for about 10 minutes and he cannot focus his vision, like seeing through a mist. </s><s n="s14.15;p3.42">This has happened 4-5 times since January. </s><s n="s15.15;p3.42">He has not travelled abroad in over 10 years. </s></p><p n="p4.42"><s n="s1.1;p4.42">He has never had a heart attack, stroke, diabetes, rheumatic fever or asthma </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">Past medical history:</head><p n="p5.42"><s n="s1.1;p5.42">He suffered with stomach ulcers in the 60s/70s and the symptoms he suffered from then were nothing like the current symptoms. </s></p><p n="p6.42"><s n="s1.1;p6.42">He has no other significant medical history </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">Family history:</head><p n="p7.42"><s n="s1.1;p7.42">There is no-ojne in the family who has suffered from similar symptoms, or had peptic ulcers </s></p><p n="p8.42"><s n="s1.1;p8.42">There is a history of TB in the family where three of his family have been affected from it </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">Drug history and allergies:</head><p n="p9.42"><s n="s1.1;p9.42">Omeprazole 40 mg - proton pump inhibtor, anti-acid </s></p><p n="p10.42"><s n="s1.1;p10.42">Omezartan 10mg - anti-hypertensive, ARB? </s></p><p n="p11.42"><s n="s1.1;p11.42">He has never taken NSAIDs on a prolonged basis </s></p><p n="p12.42"><s n="s1.1;p12.42">He does not have any drug allergies </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">Social history:</head><p n="p13.42"><s n="s1.3;p13.42">He lives alone in a house in <name type="other"/>. </s><s n="s2.3;p13.42">He is divorced and has 6 children who live all over the country. </s><s n="s3.3;p13.42">One of his daughters, who accompoanied him to the clinic lives close-by. </s></p><p n="p14.42"><s n="s1.1;p14.42">He smokes a pipe about 12.5 grams of tobacco a day which equates to 6-8 pipes a day. </s></p><p n="p15.42"><s n="s1.1;p15.42">He is an occasional drinker but binge drinks when he does drink. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">Systems review:</head><list type="simple"><head><hi rend="bold">Cardiovascular</hi> - dyspnoea, PND, chest pain, palpitations, intermittent claudication, oedema</head></list><list type="simple"><head><hi rend="bold">Respiratory</hi> - cough, haemoptysis, sputum, wheeze</head></list><list type="simple"><head><hi rend="bold">Gastrointestinal</hi> - appetite, weight, heartburn, dysphagia, abdominal pain, nausea, vomiting, bowel habits changed, melaena</head></list><list type="simple"><head><hi rend="bold">Neurological</hi> - he has never suffered from faints, fits or funny turns, headaches, weakness, dizziness parasthesiae</head></list><list type="simple"><head><hi rend="bold">Locomotor</hi> - joint pain, stiffness, back pain</head></list><p n="p16.42"/></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="bold">Analysis of history</hi> The most likely single cause of the presentation, other possible causes and reasons for these choices. The findings to be looked for on physical examination to help decide the cause.</head><p n="p17.42"/></div1><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="bold">Physical examination</hi> Highlight the findings most relevant to your clinical problem solving by underlining them</head><p n="p18.42"><s n="s1.2;p18.42">He was a slim gentleman who was fully mobile. </s><s n="s2.2;p18.42">He had bad dentition </s></p><p n="p19.42"><s n="s1.1;p19.42">Hands - the patient had a dupuytren's contracture on his left hand, apart from that he did not have any visible liver related hand signs, such as, palmar erythema, leuconychia, koilonychia, finger clubbing </s></p><p n="p20.42"><s n="s1.1;p20.42">He did not have a visible tremour or liver flap </s></p><p n="p21.42"><s n="s1.1;p21.42">His pulse was 80 bpm and regular </s></p><p n="p22.42"><s n="s1.1;p22.42">Respiration rate of 14/minute </s></p><p n="p23.42"><s n="s1.1;p23.42">I was not able to measure his blood pressure </s></p><p n="p24.42"><s n="s1.1;p24.42">He had no signs of jaundice, anaemia or central cyanosis </s></p><p n="p25.42"><s n="s1.1;p25.42">He did not have any lymphadenopathy </s></p><p n="p26.42"><s n="s1.1;p26.42">His chest and abdomen was symmetrical, no evidence of scars and he was laying comfortably without discomfort </s></p><div2><head rend="underlined">Palpation:</head><p n="p27.42"><s n="s1.2;p27.42">The patient was tender on light palpation in the epigastric area. </s><s n="s2.2;p27.42">There was no evidence of hepatosplenomegaly or abdominal masses </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">Percussion:</head><p n="p28.42"><s n="s1.1;p28.42">No evidence of ascites </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">Auscultation:</head><p n="p29.42"><s n="s1.2;p29.42">Bowel sounds were heard in al four quadrants. </s><s n="s2.2;p29.42">No liver or splenic bruits were heard. </s></p><p n="p30.42"><s n="s1.1;p30.42">No evidence of pedal oedema </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="bold">Analysis of history and examination</hi> Reasons for your choice of the cause of the patient's problem(s) and any other cause that still needs to be considered at this stage</head><p n="p31.42"/></div1><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="bold">Formulation of the patient's problem(s)</hi> Encapsulate this in physical, psychological and social terms (the triple diagnosis)</head><p n="p32.42"/></div1><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="bold">Management</hi> Use the framework of RAPRIOP to structure your proposed management. Refer to the guidelines to the writing of portfolio cases for the details of the issues to be addressed under each heading.</head><div2><head rend="underlined">Investigations</head><p n="p33.42"/></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">Reassurance and explanation</head><p n="p34.42"/></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">Prescription/medical intervention</head><p n="p35.42"/></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">Observation</head><p n="p36.42"/></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">Referral and team working</head><p n="p37.42"/></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">Advice and Prevention</head><p n="p38.42"/></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="bold">Outcome</hi> A description of the progress of the patient as far as possible. This should include consideration of further issues to be resolved. Where appropriate you should contact by telephone patients who have been discharged home.</head><p n="p39.42"/></div1><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="bold">Evidence based care and issues for research</hi> A brief consideration of the evidence base required for the diagnosis and management of the patient's problem(s)</head><p n="p40.42"/></div1><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="bold">Commentary</hi> A commentary on issues of epidemiology, psycho-social, health care delivery, ethical issues or disability relevant to the patient and/or problem</head><p n="p41.42"/></div1><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="bold">Impact on your learning</hi> Describe what you have learnt from this case</head><p n="p42.42"/></div1></body><back/></text></TEI.2>
