<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_0194b" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>No6 RA &amp; OA</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">Proforma
</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">4</p><p n="date">2005-03</p><p n="module title">Rheumotology Block</p><p n="module code">unknown</p><p n="genre family">Case study</p><p n="discipline">Medicine</p><p n="disciplinary group">LS</p><p n="grade">D</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">1242</p><p n="number of s-units">87</p><p n="number of p">84</p><p n="number of tables">0</p><p n="number of figures">0</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">6</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">0</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">14.3</p><p n="average s-units per p">1.0</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">f</p><p n="year of birth">1974</p><p n="first language">English</p><p n="education">UKA</p><p n="course">Medicine</p><p n="student ID">0194</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><docTitle><titlePart><hi rend="bold">PORTFOLIO CASE No:</hi> 6</titlePart></docTitle><titlePart>Patient Initials<name type="other"/> Hospital Number Keep separate list (<name type="other"/>) Age 67 Gender M</titlePart><titlePart>Portfolio Case presentation number: Phase 2 course document objective(s): Has the patient's permission, including for follow up contact by telephone, been sought and recorded in the case notes? Yes</titlePart></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="bold">Referral information</hi> Source of referral and a summary of key information</head><p n="p1.84"><s n="s1.3;p1.84">Initially seen in outpatients clinic on <name type="date"/>. </s><s n="s2.3;p1.84">Patient was wheelchair bound due to the pain he was getting from his knees due to osteoarthritis. </s><s n="s3.3;p1.84">Admitted to <name type="other"/> ward on <name type="date"/> for assessment, treatment and rehabilitation of his osteoarthritis. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="bold">History</hi> All <hi rend="bold italic">relevant</hi> information gathered from the patient about the presenting illness, co-existing problems, current treatment, <hi rend="italic">significant</hi> past medical history and the social and family background. The patient's view of the nature of the problem and their expectations for treatment. </head><div2><head rend="underlined">Presenting complaint:</head><p n="p2.84"><s n="s1.1;p2.84">Patient declared that he had 'ground to halt' from the pain in his knees and ankles due to his osteoarthritis. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">History of presenting complaint:</head><p n="p3.84"><s n="s1.7;p3.84">The pain in his knees, particularly his right knee had been getting worse over the last 12 months and 8 months ago the pain was so bad he didn't like to weight bear on them. </s><s n="s2.7;p3.84">The pain was such a sharp strong pain it made him feel nauseous. </s><s n="s3.7;p3.84">He didn't get any pain when he was sitting and with his legs raised. </s><s n="s4.7;p3.84">Prescribed pain killers also took the pain away. </s><s n="s5.7;p3.84">The pain is worse in the mornings and it used to take him the first couple of hours to get washed, dressed and fed. </s><s n="s6.7;p3.84">The pain never woke him up from sleep unless he moved his legs very suddenly, which didn't happen very often. </s><s n="s7.7;p3.84">Before admission the patient was sleeping on the recliner chair rather than going upstairs to bed. </s></p><p n="p4.84"><s n="s1.2;p4.84">The patient said that he noticed difficulty from his OA about 2 years ago when he started getting pain from his right knee causing him to limp. </s><s n="s2.2;p4.84">Since this time many of his joints are effected including his elbows, shoulders, occasionally his hips (which he says is more to do with his bad knees), his wrists and hands. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">Past medical history:</head><p n="p5.84"><s n="s1.1;p5.84">1986 excision of a seborrhoeic keratotic skin lesion </s></p><p n="p6.84"><s n="s1.1;p6.84">Inferior MI <name type="date"/> when he was 56/7 </s></p><p n="p7.84"><s n="s1.1;p7.84">Angina </s></p><p n="p8.84"><s n="s1.1;p8.84">1997 Essential hypertension </s></p><p n="p9.84"><s n="s1.1;p9.84"><name type="date"/> haematemesis they performed an OGD which revealed a small hiatus hernia, no evidence of active bleeding or oesophagitis </s></p><p n="p10.84"><s n="s1.1;p10.84">The notes state he has had OA since at least 01 </s></p><p n="p11.84"><s n="s1.1;p11.84">Chronic anaemia </s></p><p n="p12.84"><s n="s1.1;p12.84">Currently has a right inguinal hernia </s></p><p n="p13.84"><s n="s1.1;p13.84"><name type="date"/> 2004 had an operation on his right carpal tunnel due to median nerve entrapment </s></p><p n="p14.84"><s n="s1.1;p14.84">Anaemia which has been investigated with an endoscopy and colonoscopy. </s></p><p n="p15.84"><s n="s1.1;p15.84">He has never had a stroke, diabetes or family history of diabetes, cholesterol he believes is normal, never had rheumatic fever or asthma </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">Family history:</head><p n="p16.84"><s n="s1.1;p16.84">Father had RA and eldest sister had RA </s></p><p n="p17.84"><s n="s1.1;p17.84">No other significant family history </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">Drug History:</head><p n="p18.84"><s n="s1.1;p18.84">The patient does not suffer from any drug allergies or any other kind of allergies </s></p><p n="p19.84"><s n="s1.1;p19.84">The patient is currently on the following medication: </s></p><list type="bulleted"><item>Diltiazem MR 600mg PO BD</item><item>Fybogel PO OD</item><item>Co-amilofruse PO 5/40 OD</item><item>Ferrous sulphate 200mg PO BD</item><item>Aspirin 75mg PO OD</item><item>Lanzoprazole 15mg PO OD</item><item>Lactulose 15ml PO BD</item><item>Fortisip PO TDS</item><item>Co-codamol 30/500 PO QDS</item><item>Predinisilone EC 7.5mg PO OD</item><item>Calcichew D3 Forte PO OD</item><item>GTN S/C PRN</item><item>Microlax enema PR PRN</item><item>Tramadol 50-100mg PO/IV/IM PRN Maximum QDS</item></list></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">Social history:</head><p n="p20.84"><s n="s1.1;p20.84">Lives in <name type="other"/> in <name type="other"/>, in an end of terrace house </s></p><p n="p21.84"><s n="s1.1;p21.84">He is retired initially he worked as a coal miner for 20 years and then became a driving instructor which he did for 6 years until he had his heart attack </s></p><p n="p22.84"><s n="s1.1;p22.84">Wife passed away 6 years ago, she had late onset diabetes </s></p><p n="p23.84"><s n="s1.2;p23.84">Eldest son currently lives with him, he is a computer analyst, he has suffered with a frozen shoulder and a steroid injection cured the problem. </s><s n="s2.2;p23.84">He has 2 sons and a daughter. </s></p><p n="p24.84"><s n="s1.2;p24.84">He can go up the stairs if he uses the handrail. </s><s n="s2.2;p24.84">He can prepare his meals but it takes longer because of his hands. </s></p><p n="p25.84"><s n="s1.1;p25.84">He smokes 35 cigarettes a day and has done since he was 14 years old ???pack year history </s></p><p n="p26.84"><s n="s1.1;p26.84">He doesn't drink alcohol </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">Systems review:</head><p n="p27.84"><s n="s1.1;p27.84">No breathing probelms </s></p><list type="simple"><head><hi rend="bold">Cardiovascular</hi> - dyspnoea, PND, chest pain, palpitations, intermittent claudication, oedema</head></list><list type="simple"><head><hi rend="bold">Respiratory</hi> - cough, haemoptysis, sputum, wheeze, never had TB, no COAD</head></list><list type="simple"><head><hi rend="bold">Gastrointestinal</hi> - appetite, has lost 3 stone in the past 12 months, but thinks he has been eating less as cannot prepare food because of pain, heartburn, dysphagia, abdominal pain, nausea, vomiting, bowel habits changed, melaena</head></list><list type="simple"><head><hi rend="bold">Neurological</hi> - parasthesiae, faints, fits or funny turns, headaches, weakness, dizziness, epilepsy</head></list><list type="simple"><head><hi rend="bold">Locomotor</hi> - joint pain, stiffness, back pain</head></list></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="bold">Analysis of history</hi> The most likely single cause of the presentation, other possible causes and reasons for these choices. The findings to be looked for on physical examination to help decide the cause.</head><p n="p28.84"/></div1><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="bold">Physical examination</hi> Highlight the findings most relevant to your clinical problem solving by underlining them</head><p n="p29.84"><s n="s1.4;p29.84">Hands - MCP joints less swollen. </s><s n="s2.4;p29.84">Ulna deviation of fners in both hands, knuckles swollen. </s><s n="s3.4;p29.84">All fingers not the thumbs are stuck in a flexed postion (OT equipment) Some muscle wasting on the back of the hands. </s><s n="s4.4;p29.84">No pain at rest at the the moment, movement ok, right hand worse than the left </s></p><p n="p30.84"><s n="s1.1;p30.84">Looked comfy </s></p><p n="p31.84"><s n="s1.1;p31.84">Signs ?clubbing </s></p><p n="p32.84"><s n="s1.1;p32.84">Pulse 72 bpm and regular </s></p><p n="p33.84"><s n="s1.1;p33.84">Respiratory rate: </s></p><p n="p34.84"><s n="s1.1;p34.84">Eyes - clear </s></p><p n="p35.84"><s n="s1.1;p35.84">Tongue - clear' </s></p><p n="p36.84"><s n="s1.1;p36.84">Lips fine </s></p><p n="p37.84"><s n="s1.1;p37.84">No lymphadenopathy no oedema </s></p><p n="p38.84"><s n="s1.1;p38.84">Look: </s></p><p n="p39.84"><s n="s1.1;p39.84">Swollen, not red </s></p><p n="p40.84"><s n="s1.1;p40.84">Feel: </s></p><p n="p41.84"><s n="s1.1;p41.84">Right and left knee - Painful to touch, Crepitus </s></p><p n="p42.84"><s n="s1.1;p42.84">Move: Knees </s></p><p n="p43.84"><s n="s1.1;p43.84">Right - flex to 45 degrees </s></p><p n="p44.84"><s n="s1.1;p44.84">Left flex to 40 </s></p><p n="p45.84"><s n="s1.1;p45.84">Hips flex to 85 on right </s></p><p n="p46.84"><s n="s1.1;p46.84">Flex to 80 on left </s></p><p n="p47.84"><s n="s1.2;p47.84">Hip rotation no pain on right or left leg. </s><s n="s2.2;p47.84">Internal and external rotation normal </s></p><p n="p48.84"><s n="s1.1;p48.84"><name type="date"/> HB = 8, CRP = 63, ESR = 49 </s></p><p n="p49.84"><s n="s1.1;p49.84">Suffered from OA for at least 5 years </s></p><p n="p50.84"><s n="s1.1;p50.84"><name type="date"/> diagnosed with RA and OA with increased ESR/CRP, MCP joints boggy and ulnar deviation </s></p><p n="p51.84"><s n="s1.1;p51.84"><name type="date"/> Bilateral knee injection depomedrone </s></p><p n="p52.84"><s n="s1.1;p52.84">Microcytic anaemia </s></p><p n="p53.84"><s n="s1.1;p53.84">Peripheral oedema to the knees </s></p><p n="p54.84"><s n="s1.1;p54.84">Xray of hands and feet </s></p><p n="p55.84"><s n="s1.1;p55.84">OGD and FOS </s></p><p n="p56.84"><s n="s1.1;p56.84">PR </s></p><p n="p57.84"><s n="s1.1;p57.84">Analgeisa </s></p><p n="p58.84"><s n="s1.1;p58.84">Physio and OT </s></p><p n="p59.84"><s n="s1.1;p59.84">Arrange a DEXA scan </s></p><p n="p60.84"><s n="s1.1;p60.84">Dietician </s></p><p n="p61.84"><s n="s1.1;p61.84">Dipstick urine </s></p><p n="p62.84"><s n="s1.1;p62.84">FBC </s></p><p n="p63.84"><s n="s1.1;p63.84"><name type="date"/> BP = 155/75 </s></p><p n="p64.84"><s n="s1.1;p64.84">pulse rate 90 bpm </s></p><p n="p65.84"><s n="s1.1;p65.84">Apyrexial </s></p><p n="p66.84"><s n="s1.1;p66.84">Bloods on <name type="date"/>: </s></p><p n="p67.84"><s n="s1.1;p67.84">ESR 51, UREA = 93, Albumin = 33, WCC = 11.45, HGB = 8, Creatinine = 128, MCV = 75.1, plt = 589, CRP = 52 == Microcytic anaemia </s></p><p n="p68.84"><s n="s1.1;p68.84">On <name type="date"/> HGB improved to 9.6, hands improved, swelling reduced on hands </s></p><p n="p69.84"><s n="s1.1;p69.84">Start on bisphosphonates if no oesophagitis </s></p><p n="p70.84"><s n="s1.1;p70.84">BP 158/72 </s></p><p n="p71.84"><s n="s1.2;p71.84">Results of OGD = 09/05 Oesophagus and duodenum normal. </s><s n="s2.2;p71.84">Stomach = mild linear erosive gastritis in prepyloric region evident </s></p><p n="p72.84"><s n="s1.1;p72.84">Sigmoidoscopy = porr bowel preparation instrument only insewrted to rectum </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="bold">Analysis of history and examination</hi> Reasons for your choice of the cause of the patient's problem(s) and any other cause that still needs to be considered at this stage</head><p n="p73.84"/></div1><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="bold">Formulation of the patient's problem(s)</hi> Encapsulate this in physical, psychological and social terms (the triple diagnosis)</head><p n="p74.84"/></div1><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="bold">Management</hi> Use the framework of RAPRIOP to structure your proposed management. Refer to the guidelines to the writing of portfolio cases for the details of the issues to be addressed under each heading.</head><div2><head rend="underlined">Investigations</head><p n="p75.84"/></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">Reassurance and explanation</head><p n="p76.84"/></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">Prescription/medical intervention</head><p n="p77.84"/></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">Observation</head><p n="p78.84"/></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">Referral and team working</head><p n="p79.84"/></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">Advice and Prevention</head><p n="p80.84"/></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="bold">Outcome</hi> A description of the progress of the patient as far as possible. This should include consideration of further issues to be resolved. Where appropriate you should contact by telephone patients who have been discharged home.</head><p n="p81.84"/></div1><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="bold">Evidence based care and issues for research</hi> A brief consideration of the evidence base required for the diagnosis and management of the patient's problem(s)</head><p n="p82.84"/></div1><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="bold">Commentary</hi> A commentary on issues of epidemiology, psycho-social, health care delivery, ethical issues or disability relevant to the patient and/or problem</head><p n="p83.84"/></div1><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="bold">Impact on your learning</hi> Describe what you have learnt from this case</head><p n="p84.84"/></div1></body><back/></text></TEI.2>
