<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_0194i" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>No19 MT CTS decompression</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">deleted: header: student name; footer: page numbers</note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">Proforma
</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">4</p><p n="date">2006-03</p><p n="module title">Orthopaedics Block</p><p n="module code">unknown</p><p n="genre family">Case study</p><p n="discipline">Medicine</p><p n="disciplinary group">LS</p><p n="grade">D</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">1959</p><p n="number of s-units">88</p><p n="number of p">54</p><p n="number of tables">0</p><p n="number of figures">1</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">4</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">8</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">22.3</p><p n="average s-units per p">1.6</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">f</p><p n="year of birth">1974</p><p n="first language">English</p><p n="education">UKA</p><p n="course">Medicine</p><p n="student ID">0194</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><docTitle><titlePart><hi rend="bold">PORTFOLIO CASE No:</hi> 19</titlePart></docTitle><titlePart>Patient Initials<name type="other"/> Hospital Number Keep separate list Age 58 Gender F</titlePart><titlePart>Portfolio Case presentation number: Nerve decompression Phase 2 course document objective(s): 4.1 Joint and soft tissue disease, 4.9 Limb Injuries, 4.18 Nerve compression Has the patient's permission, including for follow up contact by telephone, been sought and recorded in the case notes? Yes</titlePart></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="bold">Referral information</hi> Source of referral and a summary of key information</head><p n="p1.54"><s n="s1.1;p1.54">Mrs <name type="other"/> was referred to orthopaedic services by her GP, due to tingling pains and numbness in both hands; she was seen in the outpatient department at the <name type="other"/> Hospital in <name type="date"/> and had her surgical day unit operation under local anaesthetic on <name type="date"/>. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="bold">History</hi> All <hi rend="bold italic">relevant</hi> information gathered from the patient about the presenting illness, co-existing problems, current treatment, significant past medical history and the social and family background. The patient's view of the nature of the problem and their expectations for treatment. </head><div2><head rend="underlined">Presenting complaint:</head><p n="p2.54"><s n="s1.2;p2.54">Tingling pains and numbness in both her hands. </s><s n="s2.2;p2.54">Her right hand being more troublesome </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">History of presenting complaint:</head><p n="p3.54"><s n="s1.2;p3.54">Mrs <name type="other"/> has been suffering with symptoms bilaterally, although worse in her right hand for over 6 months. </s><s n="s2.2;p3.54">These have gradually been increasing in severity, forcing her to consult her GP, two months ago. </s></p><p n="p4.54"><s n="s1.1;p4.54">Mrs <name type="other"/> describes the pain as: </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p5.54"><s n="s1.1;p5.54">Located across the medial surfaces of the palmer surfaces of both hands </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p6.54"><s n="s1.1;p6.54">Feels like pins and needles and is sometimes 'burning' in nature </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p7.54"><s n="s1.1;p7.54">She describes it as 'niggling pain' and rates it as 5/10 in severity </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p8.54"><s n="s1.1;p8.54">The pain is not constant, but present up to 10 - 15 times/day, it is nearly always present at night and disturbs her sleep </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p9.54"><s n="s1.1;p9.54">It is not aggravated by anything in particular, but some relief can be gained by hanging the arm over the side of the bed </s></p><p n="p10.54"><s n="s1.1;p10.54">The pins and needles in Mrs <name type="other"/>'s hands are accompanied by: </s></p><list type="bulleted"><item>Loss of grip power causing her to drop things</item><item>Loss of dexterity making it harder for her to do up her buttons on clothing</item><item>Loss of sensation across both of her index fingers (right worse than her left)</item></list></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">Past medical history:</head><p n="p11.54"><s n="s1.1;p11.54">No major illnesses or operations </s></p><p n="p12.54"><s n="s1.1;p12.54">No history of MI, CVA, asthma, diabetes, hypertension, hypothyroidsim, gout or rheumatoid arthritis </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">Family history:</head><p n="p13.54"><s n="s1.1;p13.54">Nil of note </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">Drug history and allergies:</head><p n="p14.54"><s n="s1.1;p14.54">Mrs <name type="other"/> does not take any regular medications and takes glucosamine over-the-counter tablets </s></p><p n="p15.54"><s n="s1.1;p15.54">NKDA </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">Social history:</head><p n="p16.54"><s n="s1.1;p16.54">Mrs <name type="other"/> is a part-time receptionist and is finding these current symptoms are impinging on her work. </s></p><p n="p17.54"><s n="s1.1;p17.54">She is a non-smoker and occasionally drinks alcohol </s></p><p n="p18.54"><s n="s1.1;p18.54">Mrs <name type="other"/> lives with her husband and has two grown up children. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">Systems review:</head><p n="p19.54"><s n="s1.1;p19.54">A systems review revealed nothing of note. </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="bold">Analysis of history</hi> The most likely single cause of the presentation, other possible causes and reasons for these choices. The findings to be looked for on physical examination to help decide the cause.</head><p n="p20.54"><s n="s1.1;p20.54">Mrs <name type="other"/>'s story is classical of carpal tunnel syndrome, the features of which are as follows: </s></p><list type="bulleted"><item>Pain and parasthesia in the distribution of the median nerve in the hand. (See commentary)</item><item>Pain being burning or tingling in quality</item><item>Pain waking the patient at night</item><item>Relief of symptoms by hanging the arm over the bed or shaking the hand</item><item>Clumsiness and weakness with tasks requiring fine manipulation [1]</item></list><p n="p21.54"><s n="s1.2;p21.54">Mrs <name type="other"/> presents with all of these features, they arise because there is very little extra space in the carpal tunnel. </s><s n="s2.2;p21.54">Once it is occupied, by the flexor tendons and median nerve any swelling of that tunnel results in compression and ischaemia of the nerve causing the above symptoms. </s></p><p n="p22.54"><s n="s1.1;p22.54">To confirm the diagnosis a clinical examination of the hand will be performed, including the special tests for carpal tunnel syndrome. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="bold">Physical examination</hi> Highlight the findings most relevant to your clinical problem solving by underlining them</head><p n="p23.54"><s n="s1.1;p23.54">Mrs <name type="other"/> was sitting comfortably in the chair a full general examination was not performed. </s></p><div2><head rend="underlined">Examination of the Hand</head><div3><head rend="underlined">Look:</head><p n="p24.54"><s n="s1.2;p24.54">No palmar erythema, muscle atrophy, rashes or scars. </s><s n="s2.2;p24.54">There was no obvious swellings or deformity. </s></p></div3><div3><head rend="underlined">Feel:</head><p n="p25.54"><s n="s1.1;p25.54">No tenderness on palpation </s></p><p n="p26.54"><s n="s1.1;p26.54">Reduced sensation across the left index finger bilaterally. </s></p></div3><div3><head rend="underlined">Move:</head><p n="p27.54"><s n="s1.1;p27.54">No limitation to any hand or thumb movements </s></p><p n="p28.54"><s n="s1.1;p28.54">Grip strength weakened bilaterally </s></p></div3><div3><head rend="underlined">Specific carpal tunnel tests:</head><p n="p29.54"><s n="s1.1;p29.54">Phalen's Test - Positive bilaterally </s></p><p n="p30.54"><s n="s1.1;p30.54">Tinel's Test - Negative bilaterally </s></p><p n="p31.54"><s n="s1.1;p31.54">Direct Pressure Test - Positive bilaterally </s></p><p n="p32.54"><s n="s1.1;p32.54">Test of abductor pollicus brevis - Slightly weakened bilaterally, slightly worse on the right </s></p></div3></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="bold">Analysis of history and examination</hi> Reasons for your choice of the cause of the patient's problem(s) and any other cause that still needs to be considered at this stage</head><p n="p33.54"><s n="s1.1;p33.54">The examination of Mrs <name type="other"/>'s hands has strongly indicated that she has bilateral carpal tunnel syndrome. </s></p><p n="p34.54"><s n="s1.2;p34.54">Three of the four specific carpal tunnel tests were positive, indicating median nerve compression. </s><s n="s2.2;p34.54">In addition, she demonstrated numbness across the index finger, which is supplied by the median nerve (sensory), and reduced grip strength bilaterally worse on the right than the left. </s></p><p n="p35.54"><s n="s1.5;p35.54">The specific carpal tunnel tests are designed to reproduce the symptoms the patient experiences, as all of them compress the carpal tunnel space. </s><s n="s2.5;p35.54">Phalen's test involves flexing the wrist for up to 3 minutes, and is positive if symptoms occur. </s><s n="s3.5;p35.54">Tinel's test is less reliable than phalens and involves tapping over the flexor retinaculum to aggravate the median nerve and reproduce symptoms. </s><s n="s4.5;p35.54">The direct pressure test involves pressing directly over the flexor retinaculum to reproduce symptoms. </s><s n="s5.5;p35.54">Mrs <name type="other"/> had slightly weakened abductor pollicis brevis muscles in both hands, the median nerve supplies this muscle and so a weakness in this muscle indicates median nerve compression. </s></p><p n="p36.54"><s n="s1.3;p36.54">Although Mrs <name type="other"/>'s symptoms and examination strongly indicate carpal tunnel syndrome cervical spondylosis may produce similar symptoms and confuse the diagnosis. </s><s n="s2.3;p36.54">It is therefore necessary to perform an examination of the cervical spine. </s><s n="s3.3;p36.54">Mrs <name type="other"/> had normal cervical spine movements. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="bold">Formulation of the patient's problem(s)</hi> Encapsulate this in physical, psychological and social terms (the triple diagnosis)</head><p n="p37.54"><s n="s1.4;p37.54">Mrs <name type="other"/> is a 58 year old female, who presents with a twelve-month history of bilateral pain and parasthesia in her hands. </s><s n="s2.4;p37.54">Her symptoms and examination findings are classical of carpal tunnel syndrome. </s><s n="s3.4;p37.54">It is important that she receive treatment for this as it is affecting her job and ability to perform every day tasks. </s><s n="s4.4;p37.54">If the carpal tunnel is not decompressed the median nerve can be affected further and muscle atrophy of the hypothenar eminence can occur and later carpal tunnel decompression will not always successfully fully reverse the sensory and motor losses. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="bold">Management</hi> Use the framework of RAPRIOP to structure your proposed management. Refer to the guidelines to the writing of portfolio cases for the details of the issues to be addressed under each heading.</head><div2><head rend="underlined">Investigations:</head><div3><head rend="underlined">Electrodiagnostic tests</head><p n="p38.54"><s n="s1.2;p38.54">These are used to scientifically confirm the diagnosis by showing the slowing of nerve conduction between the forearm and fingers. </s><s n="s2.2;p38.54">This test is nearly always performed before surgery. </s></p><p n="p39.54"><s n="s1.1;p39.54">If there is a query about whether cervical spondylosis is the cause of the symptoms, then an X-ray of the cervical spine should be obtained. </s></p></div3></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">Reassurance and explanation:</head><p n="p40.54"><s n="s1.4;p40.54">The symptoms she was experiencing were explained to her, in terms of the anatomy of the hand and reasons for her symptoms. </s><s n="s2.4;p40.54">She was told that there were a few options available to her, with surgery being the gold standard treatment and only one that gives long-term resolution. </s><s n="s3.4;p40.54">She was told that the operation was a routine one that can be carried out as a day case under local anaesthetic. </s><s n="s4.4;p40.54">The complications were discussed, which include; infection; accidental injury to the palmer cutaneuous branch of the median nerve and thenar motor branches of the median nerve, which may leave the patient with some superficial numbness over the palm of the hand and weakness of thumb movements; and finally incomplete cure of her current symptoms. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">Prescription/medical intervention</head><p n="p41.54"><s n="s1.1;p41.54">The following options are available for managing carpal tunnel syndrome: </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p42.54"><s n="s1.1;p42.54">Light wrist splints - these can limit flexion and provide temporary relief of symptoms particularly at night, and can be useful during pregnancy. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p43.54"><s n="s1.2;p43.54">Corticosteroid injections into the carpal canal - this provides effective but only temporary relief of symptoms, which inevitably return. </s><s n="s2.2;p43.54">However if the symptoms are mild or the patient is unfit for surgery, it can be useful. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p44.54"><s n="s1.2;p44.54">Surgical carpal tunnel release is the gold standard treatment - this involves dividing the transverse carpal ligaments to relieve the pressure on the median nerve. </s><s n="s2.2;p44.54">It is a relatively quick and simple operation and can be performed either endoscopically or by open surgery. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">Observation</head><p n="p45.54"><s n="s1.1;p45.54">The procedure was carried out as a day case; observation of post-operative recovery and rehabilitation with the physiotherapists should be carried out with a follow-up out-patient appointment. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">Referral and team work:</head><p n="p46.54"><s n="s1.2;p46.54">Mrs <name type="other"/> should be referred to the physiotherapy department for post-operative rehabilitation. </s><s n="s2.2;p46.54">They will gradually increase movement of the hand with structured exercises. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">Advice and prevention:</head><p n="p47.54"><s n="s1.2;p47.54">Carpal tunnel syndrome is more common during the menopause, in rheumatoid arthritis, pregnancy and myxoedema. </s><s n="s2.2;p47.54">It is not possible to predict exactly who will suffer with the condition or prevent the condition from occurring. </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="bold">Outcome</hi> A description of the progress of the patient as far as possible. This should include consideration of further issues to be resolved. Where appropriate you should contact by telephone patients who have been discharged home.</head><p n="p48.54"><s n="s1.2;p48.54">Mrs <name type="other"/> came to clinic on <name type="date"/> post right carpal tunnel decompression. </s><s n="s2.2;p48.54">She was very happy with the results and wished to be placed on the surgical day unit list for decompression of her left carpal tunnel in the near future. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="bold">Evidence based care and issues for research</hi> A brief consideration of the evidence base required for the diagnosis and management of the patient's problem(s)</head><p n="p49.54"><s n="s1.1;p49.54">Evidence-based studies looking at whether surgical or non-surgical treatments offer the most effective symptom relief. </s></p><div2><head rend="underlined">Efficacy of corticosteroid injection:</head><p n="p50.54"><s n="s1.5;p50.54">A systematic review looked at the clinical improvement of symptoms with local steroid injection, placebo injection or other non-surgical interventions. </s><s n="s2.5;p50.54">The results suggest that local corticosteroid injection provides clinical improvement in symptoms at one-month post injection compared to placebo. </s><s n="s3.5;p50.54">However continued symptom relief could not be demonstrated after one month [2]. </s><s n="s4.5;p50.54">This study would indicate that steroid injections have a place as a temporary solution, when surgery is not indicated, i.e. pregnancy. </s><s n="s5.5;p50.54">It may also have a place for mild symptoms that do not warrant immediate surgery. </s></p></div2><div2><head><hi rend="underlined">Surgical treatment versus non- treatment</hi> :</head><p n="p51.54"><s n="s1.4;p51.54">One RCT compared the effectiveness of surgical release of the carpal tunnel and non-surgical splinting of the wrist, for clinical improvement. </s><s n="s2.4;p51.54">The results showed that at three month follow up, 71% of patients receiving surgery had a significant treatment success, compared with 51.6% who underwent splinting. </s><s n="s3.4;p51.54">As well as being more effective at three months, the patients who underwent surgery had a much lower risk of needing re-operation, unlike the majority of the non-surgical patients who needed surgery at a later date [3]. </s><s n="s4.4;p51.54">This study highlights that although splints may provide some relief, particularly for mild symptoms; in the long-run surgery is the definitive treatment to achieve significant clinical improvement. </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="bold">Commentary</hi> A commentary on issues of epidemiology, psycho-social, health care delivery, ethical issues or disability relevant to the patient and/or problem</head><p n="p52.54"><s n="s1.3;p52.54">Carpal tunnel syndrome is the most common compressive neuropathy in the upper limb. </s><s n="s2.3;p52.54">Lifetime incidence is 6% in women and 0.6% in men. </s><s n="s3.3;p52.54">It is most common between the ages of 40 - 60 years [4]. </s></p><p n="p53.54"><s n="s1.2;p53.54">The carpal tunnel is a narrow fibro-osseous canal, rigidly bound by the carpal bones and roofed by the transverse carpal ligament. </s><s n="s2.2;p53.54">It contains the median nerve and the nine extrinsic flexors of the fingers and thumb with their synovial sheath [5]. </s></p><list type="simple"><head rend="underlined">Causes of carpal tunnel syndrome</head><item><hi rend="bold">P</hi>regnancy</item><item><hi rend="bold">R</hi>heumatoid arthritis</item><item><hi rend="bold">A</hi>rthritis (degenerative)</item><item><hi rend="bold">G</hi>rowth hormone abnormalities (acromegaly)</item><item><hi rend="bold">M</hi>etabolic (hypothyroidism, gout, diabetes mellitus)</item><item><hi rend="bold">A</hi>lcoholism</item><item><hi rend="bold">T</hi>umours</item><item><hi rend="bold">I</hi>diopathic</item><item><hi rend="bold">C</hi>onnective tissue disorders (amyloidosis) [5]</item></list><list type="simple"><head rend="underlined">Supply of median nerve in the hand</head><item>-Sensory innervation of the thumb, and fingers except the last 1½ digits. (See below)</item><item>-Thenar muscles at the base of the thumb</item><item>-Two radial lumbrical muscles [1]</item></list><figure id="BAWE_0194i-pic.001"><head><hi rend="underlined">Diagram illustrating the sensory supply of the median nerve</hi> [6]</head></figure></div1><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="bold">Impact on your learning</hi> Describe what you have learnt from this case</head><p n="p54.54"><s n="s1.2;p54.54">This case has taught me the symptoms and what to look out for on the history, as well as, how to perform the special tests used for diagnosing carpal tunnel syndrome. </s><s n="s2.2;p54.54">I have also learnt how these patients are surgically managed. </s></p></div1></body><back><div1 type="bibliography"><head><hi rend="underlined">References</hi> :</head><p>Solomon L, Warwick D J, Nayagam S Apley's system of orthopaedics and fractures. 8th Edition. 2001. Arnold. London. Pages 247 - 248</p><p>Marshall S, Tardif G, Ashworth N Local corticosteroid injection for carpal tunnel syndrome. The cochrane database of systematic reviews. 2002. Issue 4.</p><p>Gerritsen A A M, de Vet H C W, Scholten R J P M et al., Splinting versus surgery in the treatment of carpal tunnel syndrome, a randomised controlled trial. J Am Med Ass. 2002:288 (10) 1245 - 51</p><p>Davey P Medicine at a glance. 1st Edition. 2002. Blackwell Science. Oxford 371</p><p>Brown D E, Neumann R D Orthopaedic secrets. 3rd Edition. 2004. Hanley &amp; Belfus. Philadelphia. Pages 204 - 205</p><p><seg type="URL" n="http://www.neuro.wustl.edu/neuromuscular/nanatomy/median.htm"/> accessed on 30/01/06</p></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
