<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_0196b" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>PEPPER v HART What does the decision mean?</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">The document has a title page which contains:
document title
title part</note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">deleted: page numbers
</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">1</p><p n="date">2005-03</p><p n="module title">The Modern English Legal System</p><p n="module code">LA115</p><p n="genre family">Critique</p><p n="discipline">Law</p><p n="disciplinary group">SS</p><p n="grade">D</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">1186</p><p n="number of s-units">47</p><p n="number of p">21</p><p n="number of tables">0</p><p n="number of figures">0</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">0</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">0</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">25.2</p><p n="average s-units per p">2.2</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">m</p><p n="year of birth">1983</p><p n="first language">German</p><p n="education">OSA</p><p n="course">Law</p><p n="student ID">0196</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><docTitle><titlePart><hi rend="bold italic">PEPPER v HART</hi> What does the decision mean?</titlePart></docTitle><titlePart>By <hi rend="bold"><name type="student name"/></hi> University of <name type="university"/> - School of Law - 2005</titlePart><docTitle><titlePart>Pepper v Hart - What does the decision mean? </titlePart></docTitle></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="section"><head>a. Introduction</head><p n="p1.21"><s n="s1.3;p1.21">Judges have the important role of interpreting statutes. </s><s n="s2.3;p1.21">Sometimes there is ambiguity in a statute's meaning, either because words have several interpretations, dispute over its purpose, or the development of a new unforeseen situation not covered by the law. </s><s n="s3.3;p1.21">Literature identifies three different aids, or so-called rules of construction, the used to interpret statute: the Literal, the Golden or the Mischief Rule. </s></p><p n="p2.21"><s n="s1.3;p2.21">According to the Literal Rule words are given their 'plain, ordinary or literal meaning'. </s><s n="s2.3;p2.21">The Golden Rule modifies the Literal rule by seeking to avoid any absurdity. </s><s n="s3.3;p2.21">The Mischief rule on the other hand suggests a purposive approach and allows the judge to consult working papers in order to find out the mischief that the statute was intended to remedy.<ref target="BAWE_0196b-ftnote.001"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0196b-ftnote.001"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">(McEldowney 2002:72) </s></p></note><p n="p3.21"><s n="s1.2;p3.21">However, these 'rules are merely guidelines' as there 'is no external control on the judges.' </s><s n="s2.2;p3.21">Reddish calls this the 'all powerful judiciary.'<ref target="BAWE_0196b-ftnote.002"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0196b-ftnote.002"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">(Reddish 2005:1) </s></p></note><p n="p4.21"><s n="s1.2;p4.21">Judges can refer to external sources, dictionaries, textbooks, earlier statutes or even working papers as aids. </s><s n="s2.2;p4.21">In recent years we can observe a slight change in the extent parliamentary material can be considered. </s></p><p n="p5.21"><s n="s1.2;p5.21">The famous decision of <hi rend="italic">Pepper v Hart</hi><ref target="BAWE_0196b-ftnote.003"/> overturned the rule that <hi rend="italic">travaux préperatoires</hi> cannot be taken into consideration by the judges. </s><s n="s2.2;p5.21">This essay provides a brief analysis of the decision and its impact on statutory interpretation to this day. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0196b-ftnote.003"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Pepper v Hart, [1993] A.C. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">593. </s></p></note></div1><div1 type="section"><head>b. The Facts of Pepper v Hart</head><p n="p6.21"><s n="s1.3;p6.21">A group of teachers at an independent public school brought this case to the courts. </s><s n="s2.3;p6.21">They were only paying one fifth of the normal fees on the grounds that their children filled up places that the school was unable to fill. </s><s n="s3.3;p6.21">The tax office argued that taxes should be paid on the average cost of the benefit and that the teachers should contribute to the general costs of the school, whereas the teachers argued the tuition fee should be the tax basis, which was considerably lower.<ref target="BAWE_0196b-ftnote.004"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0196b-ftnote.004"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">(Newspapers:1-3) </s></p></note><p n="p7.21"><s n="s1.1;p7.21">This case was of constitutional importance as it raised the question of the permissibility of judicial reference to parliamentary debates. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head>c. Ratio decidendi</head><p n="p8.21"><s n="s1.2;p8.21">The ratio decidendi of <hi rend="italic">Pepper v Hart</hi> is that reference to parliamentary discourse, for example, through <hi rend="italic">Hansard</hi>, the official report of the proceedings and debates of the Houses of Parliament<ref target="BAWE_0196b-ftnote.005"/>, is permitted under certain circumstances. </s><s n="s2.2;p8.21">First, <hi rend="italic">Lord Browne-Wilkinson</hi> states, the legislation must be either ambiguous, obscure, or following its literal meaning would lead to an obscurity.<ref target="BAWE_0196b-ftnote.006"/> Secondly, the material relied on must consist of statements made by a minister or other promoter of the Bill, and finally the statements relied on must be clear. <ref target="BAWE_0196b-ftnote.007"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0196b-ftnote.005"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">(OED 1989) </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0196b-ftnote.006"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">(<hi rend="italic">P v H</hi>, p. 640) </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0196b-ftnote.007"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">(Ingman 2004:292) </s></p></note></div1><div1 type="section"><head>d. The impact of the decision</head><p n="p9.21"><s n="s1.2;p9.21">The actual difference made by <hi rend="italic">Hansard</hi> access in judicial statutory interpretation is unknown. </s><s n="s2.2;p9.21">There is 'no substantial empirical study' available.<ref target="BAWE_0196b-ftnote.008"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0196b-ftnote.008"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">(Zander 2004:173) </s></p></note><p n="p10.21"><s n="s1.2;p10.21">In the following years the decision was referred to in several cases (WestlawUk delivers 30 cases decided by senior courts in which <hi rend="italic">P v H</hi> has been cited) and it has been debated in literature.<hi rend="italic"> Steyn</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Vogenauer</hi> have re-examined the decision itself and noticed a retreat from <hi rend="italic">P v H</hi>.<ref target="BAWE_0196b-ftnote.009"/> In opposition to Steyn, who strongly criticized the decision, Vogenauer confirms the decision and even pleads for a reversal of the retreat he could observe<ref target="BAWE_0196b-ftnote.010"/>. </s><s n="s2.2;p10.21">Lord <hi rend="italic">Steyn</hi> has concerns about the constitutionality of <hi rend="italic">P v H</hi> because ministerial statements could be given same status as law.<ref target="BAWE_0196b-ftnote.011"/> According to him <hi rend="italic"> P v H</hi> 'also substantially increased the cost of litigation to very little advantage.'<ref target="BAWE_0196b-ftnote.012"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0196b-ftnote.009"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">(Steyn 2001:79) </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0196b-ftnote.010"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">(Vogenauer 2005:46) </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0196b-ftnote.011"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">(Lynch 2003:647) </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0196b-ftnote.012"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">(Steyn 2001:60) </s></p></note><p n="p11.21"><s n="s1.2;p11.21">Both support their view with <hi rend="italic">R v Secretary of State for the Environment, Transport and the Regions and another, ex parte Spath Holme</hi><ref target="BAWE_0196b-ftnote.013"/> or <hi rend="italic">Melluish v BMI (No.3) Ltd</hi><ref target="BAWE_0196b-ftnote.014"/> where access to Hansard was denied. </s><s n="s2.2;p11.21">In the Spath decision it was held that resort to Hansard as an aid to interpretation should be the exception rather than the rule.<ref target="BAWE_0196b-ftnote.015"/> The Melluish decision excluded statements that have been subsequently made by a minister.<ref target="BAWE_0196b-ftnote.016"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0196b-ftnote.013"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">2 WLR 15, 33 HLR 301 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0196b-ftnote.014"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Melluish v BMI (No.3) Ltd, [1995] 4 All ER 453 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0196b-ftnote.015"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">(Ingman 2004:294) </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0196b-ftnote.016"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">(Slapper &amp; Kelly 2004:204) </s></p></note><p n="p12.21"><s n="s1.2;p12.21">In <hi rend="italic"> Robinson v Secretary of State for Northern Ireland</hi><ref target="BAWE_0196b-ftnote.017"/> the premises of <hi rend="italic">P v H</hi> were undoubtedly approved. </s><s n="s2.2;p12.21">Admission of ministerial statements as an aid to statutory construction was declined because they were unclear and inconclusive. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0196b-ftnote.017"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Robinson v Secretary of State for Northern Ireland, [2002] UKHL 32 </s></p></note><p n="p13.21"><s n="s1.2;p13.21"><hi rend="italic">Zander</hi> in contrast to <hi rend="italic">Steyn</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Vogenauer</hi> states that the following decisions show that the 'strict conditions [of <hi rend="italic">P v H</hi>] have frequently been ignored' and refers to <hi rend="italic">Warwickshire County Council v Johnson</hi><ref target="BAWE_0196b-ftnote.018"/> where there seemed to be no ambiguity in the statute and access was still allowed. </s><s n="s2.2;p13.21">Similarly the House of Lords 'referred to <hi rend="italic">Hansard</hi> to confirm interpretations that would have been adopted anyway.'<ref target="BAWE_0196b-ftnote.019"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0196b-ftnote.018"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Warwickshire County Council v Johnson, [1993] 1 ALL ER 299 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0196b-ftnote.019"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">(Zander 2004:171) </s></p></note><p n="p14.21"><s n="s1.2;p14.21">He fortifies his opinion with the decision <hi rend="italic">Wilson v First County Trust</hi><ref target="BAWE_0196b-ftnote.020"/> where the interpretation of rights under the ECHR 'opens the parliamentary materials door very wide." </s><ref target="BAWE_0196b-ftnote.021"/><s n="s2.2;p14.21">This would suggest that the rules defined in <hi rend="italic">P v H</hi> have been relaxed. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0196b-ftnote.020"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Wilson v Secretary of State for Trade and Industry, [2003] 3 W.L.R. 568 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0196b-ftnote.021"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">(Zander 2004:172) </s></p></note><p n="p15.21"><s n="s1.1;p15.21">But according to <hi rend="italic">Aileen Kavanagh</hi> we find 'much more agreement ... on the general issue ... [than] disagreement in the application of <hi rend="italic">Pepper v Hart</hi> to the particular facts of the cases. </s></p><p n="p16.21"><s n="s1.1;p16.21">She refers to the <hi rend="italic">Spath Holme</hi> decision where 'four out of the five members of the House of Lords stressed that the conditions laid down in that case for the admissibility of <hi rend="italic">Hansard</hi> should be strictly insisted upon.'<ref target="BAWE_0196b-ftnote.022"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0196b-ftnote.022"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">(Kavanagh 2005:110) </s></p></note></div1><div1 type="section"><head>e. Conclusion </head><p n="p17.21"><s n="s1.4;p17.21">As we can see there is diverse opinion of how <hi rend="italic">P v H</hi> was treated in subsequent cases. </s><s n="s2.4;p17.21">Often the authors even argue with the same cases. </s><s n="s3.4;p17.21">What we can reason from this that there was no real change in the application of <hi rend="italic">P v H</hi>; it was neither overruled nor left inapplicable. </s><s n="s4.4;p17.21">I think the application of P <hi rend="italic"> v H</hi> in the succeeding cases points up that UK jurisprudence has intensified a purposive approach towards statutory interpretation and in the same breath given up the historical literal approach. </s></p><p n="p18.21"><s n="s1.5;p18.21">Allowing judges to use Hansard as an aid to understanding statutes can be seen positively, since if it helps them implement the Legislature's purpose. </s><s n="s2.5;p18.21">It reinforces the judicial role as upholders of the law and not lawmakers. </s><s n="s3.5;p18.21"><hi rend="italic">Three Rivers District Council v Bank of England (No.2)</hi><ref target="BAWE_0196b-ftnote.023"/> highlights the importance of a purposive interpretation in the European dimension. </s><s n="s4.5;p18.21">The court held that reference to Hansard should be permissible in order to find out the actual purpose of a statute 'to give effect to some particular EC directive." </s><ref target="BAWE_0196b-ftnote.024"/><s n="s5.5;p18.21">In <hi rend="italic">Three Rivers</hi> the legislation was not ambiguous in itself. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0196b-ftnote.023"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Three Rivers District Council v Bank of England, [1996] 2 All ER 363 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0196b-ftnote.024"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">(Slapper &amp; Kelly 2004:204) </s></p></note><p n="p19.21"><s n="s1.4;p19.21"><hi rend="italic">Carby-Hall</hi> outlines perfectly the significant change of policy of statute interpretation in British courts: 'The British principles of interpretation are not suited to the interpretation of European laws. </s><s n="s2.4;p19.21">The European Union style of drafting legislation is different from the British style for in the former case broad principles are laid down leaving the gaps to be filled in by judges who are required to apply the spirit or purpose of the legislation. </s><s n="s3.4;p19.21">In the latter case, every detail is provided for by legislation. </s><s n="s4.4;p19.21">A fundamental change of policy had therefore to take place!'<ref target="BAWE_0196b-ftnote.025"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0196b-ftnote.025"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">(Carby-Hall 2002:8) </s></p></note><p n="p20.21"><s n="s1.1;p20.21">We can see a change 'from the purely British "purist" approach to a "purposive" approach.' <ref target="BAWE_0196b-ftnote.026"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0196b-ftnote.026"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">(ibid 2002:8) </s></p></note><p n="p21.21"><s n="s1.1;p21.21">Maybe there was some truth in Celsus´ words '<hi rend="italic">SCIRE LEGES NON HOC EST VERBA EARUM TENERE SED VIM AC POTESTATEM - To know the law is not merely to understand the words, but as well their force and effect</hi>.' <ref target="BAWE_0196b-ftnote.027"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0196b-ftnote.027"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">(Dig.1.3.17) </s></p></note></div1></body><back><div1 type="bibliography"><head rend="underlined bold">Bibliography:</head><div2 type="bibliography"><head rend="italic">Books, articles etc.</head><p>Carby-Hall, Jo <hi rend="bold italic">The judge and social law: Jurisprudential policies in interpreting and making laws</hi>, Managerial Law Patrington 44, No. 3; (2002)</p><p>Celsus in Justinian <hi rend="bold italic">Digest</hi>, Book 1, Title 3, 17</p><p>Ingman, Terence <hi rend="bold italic">The English Legal Process</hi>, 10th edition, Oxford University Press (2004)</p><p>Kavanagh, Aileen <hi rend="bold"><hi rend="italic">Pepper v Hart and matters of constitutional principle</hi>,</hi> L.Q.R 121 (2005)</p><p>Lynch, Marie <hi rend="bold italic">Robinson v Secretary of State for Northern Ireland:Interpreting constitutional legislation</hi>, LY P.L., WIN (2003)</p><p>McEldowney, John F. <hi rend="bold italic">Public law</hi>, 3rd edition, Sweet &amp; Maxwell, London (2002)</p><p>Slapper, Gary &amp; <hi rend="bold italic">The English Legal System</hi>, 7th edition, Cavendish, London. (2004)</p><p>Kelly, David</p><p>Steyn, Johan <hi rend="bold italic">Pepper v Hart - A Re-examination</hi>, Oxford Journal of Legal Studies (2001)</p><p>Vogenauer, Stefan <hi rend="bold"><hi rend="italic"> A Retreat from Pepper v Hart? A Reply to Lord Steyn</hi>,</hi> Oxford Journal of Legal Studies (2005)</p><p>Zander, Michael <hi rend="bold italic">The Law-Making Process,</hi> 6th edition, Cambridge University Press (2004)</p></div2><div2 type="bibliography"><head rend="italic">Newspaper articles</head><p>The Times <hi rend="bold italic">Lords to hear legal battle over tax case</hi>, June 8, 1992</p><p>The Guardian (London) <hi rend="bold italic">Teachers set a crucial tax test,</hi> June 6, 1992, page 32</p><p>Financial Times (London) <hi rend="bold italic">Digest of Michaelmas term cases</hi>, January 9, 1991, p. 8 </p></div2><div2 type="bibliography"><head rend="italic">Cases</head><p><hi rend="italic">Melluish v BMI (No.3) Ltd </hi> [1995] 4 All ER 453.</p><p><hi rend="italic">Pepper v Hart</hi> [1993] A.C. 593.</p><p rend="italic">R v Secretary of State for the Environment,</p><p rend="italic">Transport and the Regions and another,</p><p><hi rend="italic">Ex parte Spath Holme Ltd, HL,</hi> [2001] 2 WLR 15, 33 HLR 301.</p><p><hi rend="italic">Robinson v Secretary of State for Northern Ireland</hi> [2002] UKHL 32.</p><p><hi rend="italic">Three Rivers District Council v Bank of England</hi> [1996] 2 All ER 363.</p><p><hi rend="italic">Warwickshire County Council v Johnson</hi> [1993] 1 ALL ER 299.</p><p><hi rend="italic">Wilson v Secretary of State for Trade and Industry</hi> [2003] 3 W.L.R. 568.</p></div2><div2 type="bibliography"><head rend="italic">Legislation:</head><p>Finance Act 1976</p></div2><div2 type="bibliography"><head rend="italic">Lectures:</head><p>Reddish, Michael (2005 December 2); Lecture presented in Modern English Legal System at University of <name type="university"/>, UK</p></div2><div2 type="bibliography"><head rend="italic">Databases:</head><p>WestlawUK</p><p>Lexis Nexis</p></div2><div2 type="bibliography"><head rend="italic">Encyclopedia:</head><p>Oxford English Dictionary On-line Version, 2<hi rend="sup">nd</hi> edition, 1989. (<seg type="URL" n="http://dictionary.oed.com/"/>) Oxford University Press 2005. [Last accessed on December 10, 2005]</p><p>Wikipedia: The Free Encyclopedia. December 10, 2005. Wikimedia Foundation. &lt;<seg type="URL" n="http://en.wikipedia.org"/>>. [Last accessed on December 14, 2005]</p></div2></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
