<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_0197a" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Outline a version of the "first generation" or the "second generation" speculative attack model. Discuss the empirical evidence in support of the model you outlined. Briefly discuss the limitations and the extensions of the model.</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">Language used in quote: <foreign id="English">English</foreign></note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">appendix: graphs</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">3</p><p n="date">unknown</p><p n="module title">Topics in Financial Economics</p><p n="module code">EC332</p><p n="genre family">Critique</p><p n="discipline">Economics</p><p n="disciplinary group">SS</p><p n="grade">unknown</p><p n="number of authors">unknown</p><p n="number of words">2597</p><p n="number of s-units">143</p><p n="number of p">71</p><p n="number of tables">0</p><p n="number of figures">0</p><p n="number of block quotes">3</p><p n="number of formulae">57</p><p n="number of lists">1</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">19</p><p n="abstract present">abstract present</p><p n="average words per s-unit">18.2</p><p n="average s-units per p">2.0</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">f</p><p n="year of birth">1983</p><p n="first language">Chinese unspecified</p><p n="education">OSA</p><p n="course">Economics</p><p n="student ID">0197</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><docTitle><titlePart>Topic: Outline a version of the "first generation" or the "second generation" speculative attack model. Discuss the empirical evidence in support of the model you outlined. Briefly discuss the limitations and the extensions of the model. </titlePart></docTitle></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="abstract"><p n="p1.71"><s n="s1.7;p1.71">A stable and healthy-performing currency market is always beneficial for government and country as a whole. </s><s n="s2.7;p1.71">Being a crucial element in currency market, exchange rate is pegged by country, if it is possible. </s><s n="s3.7;p1.71">In today's developing nations, a country may decide to peg its currency to create a stable atmosphere for foreign investment. </s><s n="s4.7;p1.71">In the world economy history, the global exchange rates used to be fixed under "gold standard" (between 1870 and 1914) and "Bretton Woods System" (from post War World II to 1971). </s><s n="s5.7;p1.71">Eventually, all attempts to move back to global exchange rate peg were abandoned in 1985<ref target="BAWE_0197a-ftnote.001"/>. </s><s n="s6.7;p1.71">Krugman develops First Generation Speculative Attack Model in his work (1979) to analyse this issue, that is, the collapse of fixed exchange rate regime. </s><s n="s7.7;p1.71">The following essay consists of three sections, the first section illustrates the frame and main ideas of the first generation model; empirical examples are provided in part two and the limitations and possible extensions of this model are discussed in the last section of this essay. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0197a-ftnote.001"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Reem Heakal, February 6, 2003, <hi rend="italic">Floating And Fixed Exchange Rates</hi>, <seg type="URL" n="http://www.investopedia.com/articles/03/020603.asp"/> </s></p></note></div1><div1 type="section"><div2><head rend="underlined">Section 1.1 Target of the model</head><p n="p2.71"><s n="s1.1;p2.71">Let Krugman's word (1979) be the threshold of the first section: </s></p><quote lang="English"><hi rend="bold">"A government can peg the exchange value of its currency in a variety of [instruments] ...... But all of these instruments are subject to limits. A government attempting to keep its currency from depreciating may find its foreign reserves exhausted and its borrowing approaching a limit."</hi> <ref target="BAWE_0197a-ftnote.002"/></quote><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0197a-ftnote.002"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Paul Krugman, <hi rend="italic">A Model of Balance-of-Payment Crisis</hi>, Journal of Money, Credit and Banking, Vol.11, No. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">3 (Aug., 1979), 311-325 </s></p></note><p n="p3.71"><s n="s1.2;p3.71">The main target of this model is to find out the timing of collapse of fixed exchange rate regime. </s><s n="s2.2;p3.71">Krugman's word indicates that he would like to find out the timing of exhaustion of such instruments and hence obtain the timing of collapse. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">Section 1.2 Underlying assumptions</head><p n="p4.71"><s n="s1.1;p4.71">Several assumptions will be made before establishment of the model: </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p5.71"><s n="s1.1;p5.71">(1) Purchasing price parity (PPP) is hold in this model: </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p6.71"><s n="s1.1;p6.71"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0197a-form.001"/> ------ (1) </s></p><p n="p7.71"><s n="s1.1;p7.71">where Pt and Pt* are respectively the logs of current (say, time t) domestic and foreign price, and et stands for the exchange rate at the same stage. </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p8.71"><s n="s1.2;p8.71">(2) The government runs budget deficit, which is financed by "domestic credit"(that is, the bond owned by central bank) and "public bonds". </s><s n="s2.2;p8.71">This model also assumes that the borrowing capacity from public is exhausted. </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p9.71"><s n="s1.2;p9.71">(3) The government is willing to peg the exchange rate as long as reserves are not exhausted. </s><s n="s2.2;p9.71">This assumption excludes uncertainty for the model. </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p10.71"><s n="s1.1;p10.71">(4) All agents are assumed to be completely rational. </s></p><p n="p11.71"><s n="s1.2;p11.71">In addition to above assumptions, it is necessary to give a short introduction of the motive of speculative attack. </s><s n="s2.2;p11.71">Ross W. Jordan (2003) defines it as follows: </s></p><quote lang="English"><hi rend="bold">"The speculative motive is the need to hold cash in order to be able to take advantage of, for example, bargain purchases that might raise, attractive interest rates, and (in the case of international firms) favourable exchange rate fluctuations."</hi><ref target="BAWE_0197a-ftnote.003"/></quote><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0197a-ftnote.003"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ross W. Jordan, 2003, <hi rend="italic">Fundamentals of Corporate Finance</hi>, 6th Edition, McGraw-Hill Higher Education, p.673 </s></p></note><p n="p12.71"><s n="s1.1;p12.71">Since those speculators intend to save money to obtain benefits from "favourable exchange rate fluctuations", the speculative attack should not be a graduate process, but rapid and aggressive. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">Section 1.3 Monetary approach </head><p n="p13.71"><s n="s1.3;p13.71">This section is going to discuss the corresponding monetary policy with respect to government's target exchange rate. </s><s n="s2.3;p13.71">The so-called monetary approach is used. </s><s n="s3.3;p13.71">Besides PPP, Uncovered Interest Rate Parity Condition (UIRP) and Money Demand Equation are needed: </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p14.71"><s n="s1.1;p14.71"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0197a-form.002"/> (2), URIP </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p15.71"><s n="s1.1;p15.71"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0197a-form.003"/> (3), Money Demand Equation </s></p><p n="p16.71"><s n="s1.3;p16.71">where i and i* are domestic and foreign interest rates and <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0197a-form.004"/> is the change in exchange rate. </s><s n="s2.3;p16.71">In equation (3), Mt and Yt are money supply and domestic income respectively and all variables are in logarithm form. </s><s n="s3.3;p16.71">Substitute (2) and (3) to (1) and obtain: </s></p><p n="p17.71"><s n="s1.1;p17.71"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0197a-form.005"/> </s></p><p n="p18.71"><s n="s1.1;p18.71"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0197a-form.006"/> </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p19.71"><s n="s1.1;p19.71"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0197a-form.007"/> (4) </s></p><p n="p20.71"><s n="s1.2;p20.71">Then assume all exogenous variables to zero, i.e. <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0197a-form.008"/>. </s><s n="s2.2;p20.71">Therefore: </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p21.71"><s n="s1.1;p21.71"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0197a-form.009"/> (5) </s></p><p n="p22.71"><s n="s1.1;p22.71">given rational expectations and no uncertainty in future, residents are able to correctly estimate the exchange rate in t+1, that is: </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p23.71"><s n="s1.1;p23.71"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0197a-form.010"/> (6) </s></p><p n="p24.71"><s n="s1.1;p24.71">then substitute (6) to (5): </s></p><p n="p25.71"><s n="s1.1;p25.71"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0197a-form.011"/> </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p26.71"><s n="s1.1;p26.71"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0197a-form.012"/> (7) </s></p><p n="p27.71"><s n="s1.2;p27.71">Since this model assumes that government is pegging exchange rate, therefore <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0197a-form.013"/>. </s><s n="s2.2;p27.71">Denote this exchange rate as <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0197a-form.014"/> and substitute it to equation (7): </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p28.71"><s n="s1.1;p28.71"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0197a-form.015"/> (8) </s></p><p n="p29.71"><s n="s1.1;p29.71">Therefore the monetary policy is constant if the government plans to peg the exchange rate at <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0197a-form.016"/>. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">Section 1.4 The reserves stock</head><p n="p30.71"><s n="s1.2;p30.71">It is time to explore how foreign reserve falls under conditions above. </s><s n="s2.2;p30.71">First break down the money supply as follows: </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p31.71"><s n="s1.1;p31.71"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0197a-form.017"/> ------(9) </s></p><p n="p32.71"><s n="s1.2;p32.71">In which D and R represent domestic credit and foreign reserves. </s><s n="s2.2;p32.71">Furthermore, according to assumption (2), the relation between the budget deficit and domestic credit and public bond is: </s></p><p n="p33.71"><s n="s1.1;p33.71"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0197a-form.018"/> </s></p><p n="p34.71"><s n="s1.2;p34.71">where G stands for government spending and T is the tax revenue. </s><s n="s2.2;p34.71">G and T are in real terms therefore the increments of D and B are discounted by price level P. As indicated in assumption (2) that the borrowing capacity from public has already achieved its maximum level, B is not growing anymore and hence <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0197a-form.019"/>. </s></p><p n="p35.71"><s n="s1.2;p35.71">Now, because of <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0197a-form.020"/> and <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0197a-form.021"/>, <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0197a-form.022"/>. </s><s n="s2.2;p35.71">Assume that the rate of domestic credit expansion is equal to<formula notation="" id="BAWE_0197a-form.023"/>, which means <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0197a-form.024"/> and hence <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0197a-form.025"/>. </s></p><p n="p36.71"><s n="s1.3;p36.71">Recall the equation (8), if the government wants to peg the exchange rate at its long run equilibrium level, <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0197a-form.026"/>, it will have to hold the money supply at level of <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0197a-form.027"/>, therefore <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0197a-form.028"/>. </s><s n="s2.3;p36.71">Since M = D + R, it can be obtained that: <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0197a-form.029"/>. </s><s n="s3.3;p36.71">Now substitute <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0197a-form.030"/> to <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0197a-form.031"/>, it gives the reduction rate of reserves: </s></p><p n="p37.71"><s n="s1.1;p37.71"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0197a-form.032"/> </s></p><p n="p38.71"><s n="s1.1;p38.71">Based on this result, the country's reserves will be exhausted sooner or later and hence its currency will be forced to devalue. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">Section 1.5 Timing of collapse and the collapsing bubble</head><p n="p39.71"><s n="s1.3;p39.71">After the discussion in foregoing sections, it is time to investigate the most important part of this model: the timing of the collapse of regime. </s><s n="s2.3;p39.71">For simplicity, Flood and Garber (1984) solves this problem by introducing the concept of "shadow exchange rate". </s><s n="s3.3;p39.71">Copeland (2000) defines this term as follows: </s></p><quote lang="English"><hi rend="bold">" ...... [It is] the exchange rate which would be established if there were no intervention in the currency markets, for a given level of the basic fundamentals. In order words, exchange rate would float freely to S (the shadow exchange rate) if the authorities allowed it to do so".</hi> <ref target="BAWE_0197a-ftnote.004"/></quote><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0197a-ftnote.004"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Laurence S. Copeland, 2000, <hi rend="italic">Exchange Rate and International Finance</hi>, 3rd Edition, Pearson Education Ltd, p.437 </s></p></note><p n="p40.71"><s n="s1.1;p40.71">"S" is essentially equal to: </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p41.71"><s n="s1.1;p41.71"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0197a-form.033"/> (10) </s></p><p n="p42.71"><s n="s1.1;p42.71">where <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0197a-form.034"/> </s></p><p n="p43.71"><s n="s1.3;p43.71">Kt is the so-called "basic fundamental", in which <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0197a-form.035"/> represents the foreign money supply, <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0197a-form.036"/> is the real income relative to the foreign country and <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0197a-form.037"/> is the foreign interest rate. </s><s n="s2.3;p43.71">In this model, <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0197a-form.038"/> is set to be constant. </s><s n="s3.3;p43.71">For the equation (10), <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0197a-form.039"/> is the expected change in exchange rate in next period. </s></p><p n="p44.71"><s n="s1.2;p44.71">Now denote the timing of collapse as <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0197a-form.040"/>, and post-collapse period as <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0197a-form.041"/>. </s><s n="s2.2;p44.71">Under the condition of rational expectation, speculators have perfect prediction of exchange rate in <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0197a-form.042"/>, therefore: <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0197a-form.043"/>, and hence </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p45.71"><s n="s1.1;p45.71"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0197a-form.044"/> (11) </s></p><p n="p46.71"><s n="s1.1;p46.71">Also, because reserves are exhausted as soon as the collapse, money supply in post-collapse period would only consist of domestic credit, which implies: </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p47.71"><s n="s1.1;p47.71"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0197a-form.045"/> (12) </s></p><p n="p48.71"><s n="s1.3;p48.71">where<formula notation="" id="BAWE_0197a-form.046"/> is the starting domestic credit level and <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0197a-form.047"/> is also the growth rate of <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0197a-form.048"/>. </s><s n="s2.3;p48.71">Also, recap the idea of equation (8) that: <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0197a-form.049"/>, which implies: <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0197a-form.050"/>. </s><s n="s3.3;p48.71">Since now <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0197a-form.051"/>, therefore </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p49.71"><s n="s1.1;p49.71"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0197a-form.052"/> (13) </s></p><p n="p50.71"><s n="s1.1;p50.71">Now substitute equation (13) and (12) to (11): </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p51.71"><s n="s1.1;p51.71"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0197a-form.053"/> (14) </s></p><p n="p52.71"><s n="s1.3;p52.71">Eventually, it is time to answer the crucial question of this model: the timing of collapse. </s><s n="s2.3;p52.71">According to Copeland (2000): "the crisis will occur when the shadow exchange rate is the same as the fixed rate." </s><s n="s3.3;p52.71">As both of the variables are ready, the timing can be derived as follows: </s></p><p n="p53.71"><s n="s1.1;p53.71"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0197a-form.054"/> </s></p><p n="p54.71"><s n="s1.1;p54.71"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0197a-form.055"/> </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p55.71"><s n="s1.1;p55.71"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0197a-form.056"/> (15) </s></p><p n="p56.71"><s n="s1.2;p56.71">However, this is not the end of story. </s><s n="s2.2;p56.71">A term of "collapsing bubble" needs to be introduced to equation (15) and hence this equation is finalized: </s></p><p n="p57.71"><s n="s1.1;p57.71"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0197a-form.057"/> </s></p><p n="p58.71"><s n="s1.2;p58.71">Why this term is necessary? </s><s n="s2.2;p58.71">Because speculators will not wait until government has run out reserves; instead, they tend to attack the financial market when reserves have fallen to a certain low point, this "bubble" term implies that collapsing point is always earlier than that reserves are exhausted. </s></p><p n="p59.71"><s n="s1.1;p59.71">In the next section of essay, some empirical evidences are given. </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><div2><head rend="underlined">Section 2.1 Empirical evidence ------ The devaluation of the pound in 1967</head><p n="p60.71"><s n="s1.4;p60.71">Two examples are discussed in this section. </s><s n="s2.4;p60.71">First comes the devaluation of the pound in 1967: On the night of 18 <hi rend="sup">th</hi> November, 1967, the British government announced that it was lowering the exchange rate so the pound was worth 2.40$, down from 2.80$, a cut over 14%. </s><s n="s3.4;p60.71">This decision followed weeks of increasingly feverish speculation and a day in which the Bank of England spent £200m trying to shore up the pound from its gold and dollar reserves.<ref target="BAWE_0197a-ftnote.005"/> The Prime Minister at that time, Harold Wilson, indicated that the only alternative was to borrow heavily from foreign governments. </s><s n="s4.4;p60.71">However, the only loans on offer were short-term ones. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0197a-ftnote.005"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1"><hi rend="italic">On this day, 19 November, 1967,</hi> <hi rend="italic">Wilson defends 'pound in your pocket</hi>, <seg type="URL" n="http://news.bbc.co.uk/onthisday/hi/dates/stories/november/19/newsid_3208000/3208396.stm"/> </s></p></note><p n="p61.71"><s n="s1.2;p61.71">The devaluation of British pound in 1967 is considered to be a classical evidence of first generation speculative attack model, as it almost showed all the elements in this model. </s><s n="s2.2;p61.71">First of all, the British government was running an £800m budget deficit at that time; second, speculators had correct foresight: they knew the pound was weak and they decided to attack it; third, there was not any other choice for government but only buying pounds with its reserves; finally, the government could not hold the pound any longer and the currency depreciated. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">Section 2.2 Empirical evidence ------ The depreciating dollar in the end of Bretton Woods System</head><p n="p62.71"><s n="s1.5;p62.71">Bretton Woods System was based on Bretton Woods Agreement, which was signed by 44 nations during the first three weeks of July in 1944. </s><s n="s2.5;p62.71">The U.S dollar was set to be in a core position in this system: it is the standard to which every other currency was pegged and it was the only currency directly convertible into gold for official purposes. </s><s n="s3.5;p62.71">The benchmark of gold price referred to the rate on 1 <hi rend="sup">st</hi> July, 1944, which is $35 per ounce. </s><s n="s4.5;p62.71">Therefore, as the Bretton Woods system evolved, the reserves of most countries became a combination of gold and dollars. </s><s n="s5.5;p62.71">US dollar became increasingly more important. </s></p><p n="p63.71"><s n="s1.2;p63.71">However, during the period 1958-1971, the US experienced a persistent deficit in its balance of payments. </s><s n="s2.2;p63.71">The causes of these chronic deficits include: </s></p><list type="ordered"><item>A higher rate of return r* > r, which results in capital outflow;</item><item>Military commitments; </item><item>The Vietnam War also caused inflation in the US.<ref target="BAWE_0197a-ftnote.006"/></item></list><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0197a-ftnote.006"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">E.Kwan Choi, 1996, <seg type="URL" n="http://www.econ.iastate.edu/classes/econ355/choi/bre.htm"/>, <hi rend="italic">The Bretton Woods System</hi> </s></p></note><p n="p64.71"><s n="s1.5;p64.71">In addition to this, the U.S currency market was facing two more problems. </s><s n="s2.5;p64.71">The first one was the combination of its reserves. </s><s n="s3.5;p64.71">At the beginning of 1958, US reserve assets included foreign currencies such as Yen, DM and British pound at first. </s><s n="s4.5;p64.71">However, by the end of the 1960s, the US international reserve consisted of mainly gold. </s><s n="s5.5;p64.71">Reserve is volatile if it mainly consists of a particular currency (it is gold in this case): when this kind of foreign currency suddenly depreciates, the real value of reserves will decrease. </s></p><p n="p65.71"><s n="s1.8;p65.71">The second problem faced by the U.S government was the dramatic increase in liabilities to foreign central banks. </s><s n="s2.8;p65.71">According to Choi (1996), by 1963, the US gold reserve still roughly covered liabilities to foreign central banks; and by 1970 the gold coverage had fallen to 55%, by 1971 22%. </s><s n="s3.8;p65.71">From the perspective of the U.S government, this fall in gold is equivalent to the fall in foreign reserves. </s><s n="s4.8;p65.71">In fact, from 1963, foreign central banks had tried to convert their dollar reserves into gold, eventually the US was forced to abandon gold convertibility, which is symbolised by President Richard Nixon's indication on August 15, 1971, hence the eliminated the Bretton Woods System. </s><s n="s5.8;p65.71">Actually the post-collapse movements of exchange rate in some major countries (including the U.S) would enable this collapse to be a supporting evidence of first generation model. </s><s n="s6.8;p65.71">Choi (1996) gives the following figures: Yen appreciated 17%, Mark 13.5 %, Pound 9%, French Franc 9%; moreover, the gold price rose from $35 per oz to $38 per oz, which was equivalent to a dollar devaluation of 8.57%. </s><s n="s7.8;p65.71">The quarterly data of Yen / Dollar, Mark / Dollar and Dollar / Pound from 1971 to 1973 are plotted in Figures 1, 2 and 3 in appendix. </s><s n="s8.8;p65.71">It can be noticed that for Japan and Germany, exchange rates against Dollar gradually fell during 1971 and 1972, followed by a dramatic reduction in early 1973; performance in pound / dollar was different, but still, dollar depreciated more than 10% against British pound from 1971 till the first quarter in 1972. </s></p><p n="p66.71"><s n="s1.2;p66.71">Different from the first example, foreign countries somehow performed the role of speculator against the U.S in the collapse of Bretton Woods. </s><s n="s2.2;p66.71">The decreasing willingness of holding dollar directly forces foreign countries absorbed gold stock in the U.S. When the U.S had exhausted its gold reserves, the fixed exchange rate regime collapsed. </s></p><p n="p67.71"><s n="s1.2;p67.71">However, the financial crisis occurred in the 1990s, namely collapse of ERM in1992 and Asian Financial Crisis in 1997-99, can not be fully explained by this model as its inherent limitations. </s><s n="s2.2;p67.71">This would be discussed in section 3. </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined">Section 3 Limitations and extensions of the first generation model</head><p n="p68.71"><s n="s1.6;p68.71">This model offers formal description of speculative attacks in currency markets and analyses the timing of collapse of fixed exchange rate regime from the perspective of balance-of-payment. </s><s n="s2.6;p68.71">Nonetheless, the model has two theoretical limitations, which are caused by the assumptions imposed. </s><s n="s3.6;p68.71">The first one is that this model wipes out all uncertainty in government's policy. </s><s n="s4.6;p68.71">The government is assumed to abandon the fixed rate regime only if reserves are exhausted. </s><s n="s5.6;p68.71">This is the very reason why this model is inappropriate to explain the collapse of ERM in 1992, where, according to W. Aklia (1998), "the temptation to leave the ERM was high for the U.K. The same held true for many other struggling European economies like Italy, Spain and Portugal as well as for countries like Sweden and Finland to break off their fixed exchange rate system." </s><ref target="BAWE_0197a-ftnote.007"/><s n="s6.6;p68.71">This indication implies that by introducing uncertainty to government's and speculators' decision making, speculators are not 100% committing attack and the government is not certainly holding the regime. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0197a-ftnote.007"><p n="pn1.2"><s n="s1.1;pn1.2">Weerapana, Akila (1998): <hi rend="italic">The Performance of Simple Monetary Policy Rules in a</hi> </s></p><p n="pn2.2"><s n="s1.1;pn2.2"><hi rend="italic">Large Open Economy</hi>, Wellesley College, unpublished. </s></p></note><p n="p69.71"><s n="s1.3;p69.71">The second limitation is that this model only focuses on circumstances with budget deficit and accordingly unable to explain those speculative attack cases without apparent problems in balance-of-payment. </s><s n="s2.3;p69.71">For example, countries involved in 1997-99 Asian Financial Crisis were not having large budget deficits and some of them even enjoyed surplus, but speculators still attacked their currencies. </s><s n="s3.3;p69.71">Based on this reason, Copeland (2000) also argues: "this model (the first generation model) seemed to be no help in explaining the Asian Crisis." <ref target="BAWE_0197a-ftnote.008"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0197a-ftnote.008"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Laurence S. Copeland, 2000, <hi rend="italic">Exchange Rate and International Finance</hi>, 3rd Edition, Pearson Education Ltd, p. 464 </s></p></note><p n="p70.71"><s n="s1.5;p70.71">Essentially the extensions of this model are derived from the limitations, therefore introducing uncertainty is a sensible one. </s><s n="s2.5;p70.71">As claimed in foregoing paragraphs, neither of ERM Crisis nor Asian Financial Crisis can be explained by this model, as paradoxes exist in both cases according to the assumptions of the model. </s><s n="s3.5;p70.71">Another possible extension for this model could be the removal of those limitations on government's options of cutting budget deficit. </s><s n="s4.5;p70.71">Besides using foreign reserves, issuing Treasury bill to foreign banks is also a possible solution; even the emergency bonds could delay the timing of collapse and probably change the result. </s><s n="s5.5;p70.71">Therefore extensions can be introduced to such two aspects. </s></p><p n="p71.71"><s n="s1.7;p71.71">In conclusion, this essay outlines a version of the first generation speculative attack model. </s><s n="s2.7;p71.71">The target of this model is to find out the timing of collapse of fixed exchange rate regime in an economy. </s><s n="s3.7;p71.71">Based on several assumptions, this model offers formally describes concept of speculative attack and answers the timing question by numerical method. </s><s n="s4.7;p71.71">Empirical evidences of the devaluation of the pound in 1967 and the depreciated dollar in the end of Bretton Woods System are discussed in section 2. </s><s n="s5.7;p71.71">Because of the limitations inside, this model is not appropriate to analyse the ERM Crisis in 1992 and the Asian Financial Crisis in 1997-99. </s><s n="s6.7;p71.71">The final section not only discusses the limitations, but also the possible extension for this model. </s><s n="s7.7;p71.71">This paper argues that the introduction of uncertainty will enable this model to be more realistic and more effective. </s></p></div1></body><back><div1 type="bibliography"><head rend="bold">Bibliography</head><p>Weerapana, Akila (1998): <hi rend="italic">The Performance of Simple Monetary Policy Rules in a Large Open Economy</hi>, Wellesley College, unpublished.</p><p>E.Kwan Choi, 1996, <seg type="URL" n="http://www.econ.iastate.edu/classes/econ355/choi/bre.htm"/>, <hi rend="italic">The Bretton Woods System</hi></p><p>Laurence S. Copeland, 2000, <hi rend="italic">Exchange Rate and International Finance</hi>, 3<hi rend="sup">rd</hi> Edition, Pearson Education Ltd</p><p>Reem Heakal, February 6, 2003, <hi rend="italic">Floating And Fixed Exchange Rates</hi>, <seg type="URL" n="http://www.investopedia.com/articles/03/020603.asp"/></p><p>Ross W. Jordan, 2003, <hi rend="italic">Fundamentals of Corporate Finance</hi>, 6<hi rend="sup">th</hi> Edition, McGraw-Hill Higher Education, </p><p>Paul Krugman, <hi rend="italic">A Model of Balance-of-Payment Crisis</hi>, Journal of Money, Credit and Banking, Vol.11, No. 3 (Aug., 1979), 311-325 </p><p>Paul Krugman, 1995, <hi rend="italic">Currencies and Crisis</hi>, 1<hi rend="sup">st</hi> Edition, Asco Trade Typesetting Ltd, Hong Kong</p><p><hi rend="italic">On this day, 19 November, 1967, Wilson defends pound in your pocket</hi>, <seg type="URL" n="http://news.bbc.co.uk/onthisday/hi/dates/stories/november/19/newsid_3208000/3208396.stm"/></p></div1><div1 type="appendix"><head rend="bold">Appendix</head><p/></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
