<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_0199b" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Experiment 16: Induction of ?-galactosidase in Escherichia coli</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">deleted: header: student name and number, date; footer: page numbers</note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">appendices: results and calculations</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">1</p><p n="date">2006-03</p><p n="module title">Laboratories &amp; Assessed Work</p><p n="module code">BS121</p><p n="genre family">Methodology recount</p><p n="discipline">Biological Sciences</p><p n="disciplinary group">LS</p><p n="grade">D</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">1033</p><p n="number of s-units">52</p><p n="number of p">15</p><p n="number of tables">0</p><p n="number of figures">1</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">0</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">1</p><p n="abstract present">abstract present</p><p n="average words per s-unit">19.9</p><p n="average s-units per p">3.5</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">f</p><p n="year of birth">1987</p><p n="first language">English</p><p n="education">UKA</p><p n="course">Computational Biology</p><p n="student ID">0199</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><docTitle><titlePart rend="underlined">Experiment 16: Induction of β-galactosidase in <hi rend="italic">Escherichia coli</hi></titlePart></docTitle></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="abstract"><head rend="underlined">Abstract</head><p n="p1.15"><s n="s1.4;p1.15">The aim of this experiment was to examine the induction of β-galactosidase in <hi rend="italic">E. coli</hi> at different temperatures. </s><s n="s2.4;p1.15">This was done by assaying for enzyme activity by addition of toluene and oNPG to samples of <hi rend="italic">E. coli</hi>. </s><s n="s3.4;p1.15">The results show that induction does not occur at 15°C due to decreased enzyme activity. </s><s n="s4.4;p1.15">Induction occurs fully at 30°C and 37°C, as this is the optimum range for the enzyme, and translation and transcription occur. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined">Introduction</head><p n="p2.15"><s n="s1.7;p2.15">The <hi rend="italic">lac</hi> operon encodes three enzymes <hi rend="sup">1</hi> required for lactose degradation: β-galactosidase, lactose permease and thiogalactoside transacetylase <hi rend="sup">2</hi>. </s><s n="s2.7;p2.15">These genes are adjacent to each other in the operon. </s><s n="s3.7;p2.15">Before these genes there is a region which regulates the lactose metabolic genes: this region contains the regulator, promoter and operator. </s><s n="s4.7;p2.15">The regulator gene encodes a repressor protein which can bind to the operator site <hi rend="sup">3</hi>. </s><s n="s5.7;p2.15">This repressor is a tetrameric protein. </s><s n="s6.7;p2.15">The promoter contains a binding site for RNA polymerase, and directs the polymerase towards the correct transcription initiation site. </s><s n="s7.7;p2.15">In addition to this promoter in the operon, a second promoter is present in front of the regulator gene, which drives the synthesis of the regulator. </s></p><p n="p3.15"><s n="s1.4;p3.15">The primary carbon source of <hi rend="italic">E. coli</hi> is glucose, but other carbon sources, such as lactose (a sugar present in milk) can be metabolised using the genes of the <hi rend="italic">lac</hi> operon. </s><s n="s2.4;p3.15">In the absence of lactose, the transcription of the lac structural genes is blocked by the repressor. </s><s n="s3.4;p3.15">The <hi rend="italic">lac</hi> repressor binds DNA by inserting an α-helix into the major groove of DNA. The edges of the base pairs and the phosphodiester backbone also make contact with the repressor. </s><s n="s4.4;p3.15">Very little, if any, β-galactosidase, permease or transacetylase is produced. </s></p><p n="p4.15"><s n="s1.5;p4.15">When lactose is present it is converted to allolactose, a combination of galactose and glucose with an α-1,6 linkage, which is the correct inducer of the operon. </s><s n="s2.5;p4.15">Allolactose binds in the centre of the large domain in each monomer in the <hi rend="italic">lac</hi> operon and the repressor's affinity for operator DNA is reduced. </s><s n="s3.5;p4.15">This is done by a conformational change being induced in the interface with the DNA-binding domains. </s><s n="s4.5;p4.15">The domains cannot easily contact DNA now, which leads to the DNA-binding affinity being reduced dramatically. </s><s n="s5.5;p4.15">The proteins encoded by the structural gene are transcribed, and lactose is utilised. </s></p><p n="p5.15"><s n="s1.4;p5.15">DNA-binding proteins can stimulate transcription. </s><s n="s2.4;p5.15">An example is the catabolite activator protein (CAP), or the cAMP response protein (CRP). </s><s n="s3.4;p5.15">When CAP is bound to cAMP, the transcription of lactose and arabinose catabolising genes is stimulated. </s><s n="s4.4;p5.15">The CAP-cAMP complex stimulates the initiation of transcription by a factor of 50. </s></p><p n="p6.15"><s n="s1.2;p6.15">Within the laboratory, induction can be achieved by adding iso-propylthiogalactoside (IPTG), as IPTG is not catabolised by the cell and does not act as a carbon source, so it is described as a 'gratuitous' inducer. </s><s n="s2.2;p6.15">This is because, within the laboratory, the cells can be grown in a defined medium with glycerol as the carbon source: the expression of the <hi rend="italic">lac</hi> operon is neither induced nor repressed. </s></p><p n="p7.15"><s n="s1.1;p7.15">The aim of this experiment was: </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p8.15"><s n="s1.1;p8.15">To examine the induction of β-galactosidase in <hi rend="italic">E. coli</hi> at different temperatures </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined">Materials and Methods</head><p n="p9.15"><s n="s1.1;p9.15">Refer to manual, pg 60-62, and reference section 30 for materials and methods </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined">Results</head><div2><head rend="underlined">30.2: Assay for β-galactosidase</head><figure id="BAWE_0199b-fig.001"><head>Figure 1: Induction of Beta-galactosidase activity at four different temperatures.</head></figure><p n="p10.15"><s n="s1.4;p10.15">Figure 1 shows that for all four temperatures, the amount of o-nitrophenol (oNP) released in nM increases from zero. </s><s n="s2.4;p10.15">For 37°C, the amount of oNP released increases from 0nM to 155.9nM over 30 minutes, and then the amount released plateaus and remains constant at 157.42nM. For 30°C, the amount of oNP released increases from 0nM to 197.23nM over 30 minutes, and then remains constant for the remaining 20 minutes. </s><s n="s3.4;p10.15">At 25°C, the amount of oNP released increases from 0nM to 94.07nM at 50 minutes, and then remains constant at 95.36. </s><s n="s4.4;p10.15">At 15°C, the amount of oNP released was 0nM for 35 minutes, until the amount released increased to 13.75 at 60 minutes, an increase of 36.4%. </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined">Discussion</head><p n="p11.15"><s n="s1.5;p11.15">At 15°C leaky repression occurs. </s><s n="s2.5;p11.15">No induction occurs at this temperature, so translation and transcription also do not occur. </s><s n="s3.5;p11.15">At this temperature a little oNP is released, although there is a slight increase between 40 and 60 minutes (see Figure 1), indicating that the induction of β-galactosidase does not occur. </s><s n="s4.5;p11.15">This is due to the decreased enzyme activity as the enzyme and substrate has little kinetic energy. </s><s n="s5.5;p11.15">The release of a little oNP must therefore be due to leaky repression of the genes. </s></p><p n="p12.15"><s n="s1.4;p12.15">At 25°C, little oNP is released (see Figure 1), indicating that the β-galactosidase gene is not fully induced at this temperature. </s><s n="s2.4;p12.15">Due to the low temperature, translation and transcription occur at a low rate due to the low temperature, which allows product inhibition to occur very rapidly. </s><s n="s3.4;p12.15">The rate of β-galactosidase synthesis equals the rate of destruction, so the activity remains at a constant rate. </s><s n="s4.4;p12.15">The plateau at this temperature, and also for 30°C and 37°C, is caused by product inhibition of β-galactosidase, which creates the constant level. </s></p><p n="p13.15"><s n="s1.4;p13.15">The results from 30°C and 37°C are very similar: at these temperatures, induction of β-galactosidase occurs, and this is the optimum temperature for the enzyme. </s><s n="s2.4;p13.15">The increase in the release of oNP (see Figure 1) indicates the translation and transcription are occurring at a high rate, and that β-galactosidase synthesis is greater than the rate of destruction. </s><s n="s3.4;p13.15">The turnover number is high at these temperatures. </s><s n="s4.4;p13.15">The plateau, as explained above, is due to product inhibition. </s></p><p n="p14.15"><s n="s1.2;p14.15">The amount of oNP released at 37°C is less at 25 minutes and onwards, than at 30°C. This is because at 37°C, the enzyme starts to thermally denature and becomes unstable. </s><s n="s2.2;p14.15">Therefore, fewer enzymes (β-galactosidase) will be available, and transcription and translation will slow down. </s></p><p n="p15.15"><s n="s1.4;p15.15">The reason for the plateau at different levels of oNP may be due to a ratio between the amount of β-galactosidase and product. </s><s n="s2.4;p15.15">When the amount of product reaches a certain level in relation to the enzyme, the product inhibits the enzyme and production plateaus. </s><s n="s3.4;p15.15">There is a more rapid rate of induction for 37°C, due to the high temperature, which causes a rapid build up and a lower plateau. </s><s n="s4.4;p15.15">Therefore, product inhibition occurs more quickly. </s></p></div1></body><back><div1 type="bibliography"><head rend="underlined">References</head><p>Molecular Cell Biology: Lodish, Berk, Matsudaira, Kaiser, Kreiger, Scott, Zipursky, Darnell; Freeman Publ.; 5<hi rend="sup">th</hi> Edition; pg 115<hi rend="sup">1</hi></p><p><seg type="URL" n="http://web.mit.edu/esgbio/www/pge/lac.html2"/></p><p>Biochemistry: Stryer, Berg, Tymoczko; Freeman Publ,; 5<hi rend="sup">th</hi> Edition; pg 869<hi rend="sup">3</hi></p></div1><div1 type="appendix"><head rend="underlined">Appendices</head><p/></div1><div1 type="appendix"><head rend="underlined">Appendix 1</head><p/></div1><div1 type="appendix"><head rend="underlined">Appendix 2</head><p/></div1><div1 type="appendix"><head rend="underlined">Appendix 3</head><p/></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
