<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_0199a" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Experiment 17: Virus Haemagglutination Assay</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">deleted: header: student name and number, date; footer: page numbers</note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">appendices: results and calculations</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">1</p><p n="date">2006-04</p><p n="module title">Laboratories &amp; Assessed Work</p><p n="module code">BS121</p><p n="genre family">Methodology recount</p><p n="discipline">Biological Sciences</p><p n="disciplinary group">LS</p><p n="grade">D</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">852</p><p n="number of s-units">37</p><p n="number of p">14</p><p n="number of tables">0</p><p n="number of figures">0</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">1</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">0</p><p n="abstract present">abstract present</p><p n="average words per s-unit">23.0</p><p n="average s-units per p">2.6</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">f</p><p n="year of birth">1987</p><p n="first language">English</p><p n="education">UKA</p><p n="course">Computational Biology</p><p n="student ID">0199</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><docTitle><titlePart rend="underlined">Experiment 17: Virus Haemagglutination Assay</titlePart></docTitle></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="abstract"><head rend="underlined">Abstract</head><p n="p1.14"><s n="s1.4;p1.14">The aim of this experiment was to determine the HA titre of a virus stock and the HI titre of an antibody stock. </s><s n="s2.4;p1.14">This was done by setting up HA and HI assays using an unknown virus. </s><s n="s3.4;p1.14">The results show that the HA titre of the virus was 3200HA per ml, which gives 1.44x10 <hi rend="sup">10</hi> virions. </s><s n="s4.4;p1.14">Also, the HI titre of antibody was 1600HI per ml, and the virus was identified to be Influenza A subtype H1. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined">Introduction</head><p n="p2.14"><s n="s1.6;p2.14">In order to replicate and produce progeny, a virus needs to gain entry into a host cell. </s><s n="s2.6;p2.14">This is because they cannot generate ATP on their own and need to acquire ATP from the host cell for reproduction. </s><s n="s3.6;p2.14">In the early events of the replication cycle, the virus particle (virion) adsorbs <hi rend="sup">1</hi> onto the host cell and attaches to receptors on the cell surface. </s><s n="s4.6;p2.14">This is known as attachment. </s><s n="s5.6;p2.14">Commonly, the receptors on the host cell surface are glycoproteins or glycolipids, and the virus has evolved to bind to these molecules. </s><s n="s6.6;p2.14">The virus does not bind to the whole molecule, but rather domains within the molecule. </s></p><p n="p3.14"><s n="s1.4;p3.14">Some viruses have a property called haemagglutination, where cell surface binding structures on the virion can bind to the surface of red blood cells due to the viral protein called haemagglutinin (HA). </s><s n="s2.4;p3.14">This is a laboratory phenomenon, where the red blood cells create a lattice. </s><s n="s3.4;p3.14">Usually, only viruses which bind to simple carbohydrate motifs on the cell surface have this property. </s><s n="s4.4;p3.14">This phenomenon can be used to determine the HA titre. </s></p><p n="p4.14"><s n="s1.2;p4.14">The HA of the virus can be a primary target of the immune system, so specific antibodies can be raised against it. </s><s n="s2.2;p4.14">This property can be used in the haemagglutination inhibition (HI) assay, where an unknown virus can be identified and the HI titre can be defined. </s></p><p n="p5.14"><s n="s1.1;p5.14">The aims of this experiment were: </s></p><list type="bulleted"><item>To determine the HA titre of a stock of virus</item><item>To identify that virus on the basis of reactivity with known antisera</item><item>To determine the HI titre of the specificity reactive serum using HA and HI assays</item></list></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined">Materials and Methods</head><p n="p6.14"><s n="s1.1;p6.14">Refer to manual, pg 63 and 64, and reference sections 31 and 32 for materials and methods. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined">Results</head><div2><head rend="underlined">Virus Haemagglutination Assay</head><p n="p7.14"><s n="s1.2;p7.14">The HA titre of virus was found to be 3200 per ml, as the dilution at which the end point was seen was at 1/320. </s><s n="s2.2;p7.14">From this, the number of virus particles could be calculated, which was 1.44x10 <hi rend="sup">10</hi> virions. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">Haemagglutination Inhibition Assay</head><p n="p8.14"><s n="s1.1;p8.14">The end point was seen at a dilution of 1/160, which gives a HI titre of antibody at 1600HI per ml. </s></p><p n="p9.14"><s n="s1.2;p9.14">Only the X antibody affected the agglutination property of the virus. </s><s n="s2.2;p9.14">The X antibody binds to Influenza A subtype H1. </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined">Discussion</head><div2><head rend="underlined">Virus Haemagglutination Assay</head><p n="p10.14"><s n="s1.2;p10.14">For the controls, no agglutination was expected to be seen, as there was no virus added to the PBS and red blood cells solution. </s><s n="s2.2;p10.14">Therefore, as there was no virus to agglutinate the blood cells, the cells create a pellet at the bottom of the well. </s></p><p n="p11.14"><s n="s1.3;p11.14">For the first five dilutions of the assay (refer to Appendix 1, table 1), there was sufficient virus to create a lattice of red blood cells, and 100% of the red blood cells were agglutinated. </s><s n="s2.3;p11.14">In Well 6, which was a 1/320 dilution, the 50% end point was reached, which gave the last positive haemagglutination: this is where 50% of the red blood cells have virus particles attached to the cell surface, and 50% of the red blood cells do not have red blood cells attached to the cell surface. </s><s n="s3.3;p11.14">This was because the virus was not in sufficient quantity to bind to all of the red blood cells due to the dilution. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">Haemagglutination Inhibition Assay</head><p n="p12.14"><s n="s1.2;p12.14">For the controls, no agglutination was expected to be seen in samples one to six, as no virus was added to the solution (refer to Appendix 1, table 2 for the materials added), so agglutination could not occur. </s><s n="s2.2;p12.14">Agglutination was expected in samples 7 to 12, as virus was added to the sample, so the virus could bind to specific receptors on the red blood cell surface and create a lattice of red blood cells. </s></p><p n="p13.14"><s n="s1.5;p13.14">Referring to Appendix 1, Table 2, it can be seen that in samples two to four for the X antibody that the red blood cells did not agglutinate and formed a pellet. </s><s n="s2.5;p13.14">This was because the antibody was at a sufficient high concentration to bind to the virus particles. </s><s n="s3.5;p13.14">This prevented the virus binding to the surface of the red blood cells, and so the cells formed a pellet. </s><s n="s4.5;p13.14">In samples 5 to 12, the antibody was not in a sufficient quantity to bind to all of the virus particles, so the virions bound to the red blood cells, causing agglutination. </s><s n="s5.5;p13.14">This was because the antibody had been diluted. </s></p><p n="p14.14"><s n="s1.2;p14.14">For antibody Y, agglutination occurred in all of the samples, as the antibody is not specific for the virus, so the antibody did not bind to the virus. </s><s n="s2.2;p14.14">Therefore, the virus attached to the receptors on the red blood cell surface, causing agglutination. </s></p></div2></div1></body><back><div1 type="bibliography"><head rend="underlined">References</head><p>Introductory Virology: Prof A.J. Easton</p></div1><div1 type="appendix"><head rend="underlined">Appendices</head><p/></div1><div1 type="appendix"><head rend="underlined">Appendix 1</head><p/></div1><div1 type="appendix"><head rend="underlined">Appendix 2</head><p/></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
