<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_0200b" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>A-Z Cloth Management Report on the Costs and Quantities of Yarn Produced</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">deleted: header: student and module number, date</note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">appendix: Microsoft Excel output tables
</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">1</p><p n="date">2004-02</p><p n="module title">Quantitive Methods of Analysis</p><p n="module code">IB1020</p><p n="genre family">Case study</p><p n="discipline">Business</p><p n="disciplinary group">SS</p><p n="grade">M</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">1341</p><p n="number of s-units">64</p><p n="number of p">24</p><p n="number of tables">1</p><p n="number of figures">1</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">0</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">9</p><p n="abstract present">abstract present</p><p n="average words per s-unit">21.0</p><p n="average s-units per p">2.7</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">f</p><p n="year of birth">1985</p><p n="first language">English</p><p n="education">UKA</p><p n="course">Management Science</p><p n="student ID">0200</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><docTitle><titlePart rend="underlined bold">A-Z Cloth Management Report on the Costs and Quantities of Yarn Produced</titlePart></docTitle></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="abstract"><head rend="underlined bold">Overall Summary and the Main Recommendations</head><p rend="bulleted" n="p1.24"><s n="s1.1;p1.24">To minimise costs, 320 metres of cloth should be made internally and 180 metres externally. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p2.24"><s n="s1.1;p2.24">I recommend purchasing 80 hours of carding and combing time each week from another division for a maximum of £120, to enable internal production to increase to 520 metres per week. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p3.24"><s n="s1.2;p3.24">Gaining the 20% cost negotiation would save a substantial £756 per week or enable external production to increase by 45 meters. </s><s n="s2.2;p3.24">However, it would not change the optimal output solution. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p4.24"><s n="s1.2;p4.24">I would <hi rend="italic">not</hi> recommend switching suppliers for a 30% reduction if the 20% negotiation is gained, because of their unreliability. </s><s n="s2.2;p4.24">Although, depending on their performance, this reduction could be more beneficial due to the price competitiveness of the industry than none whatsoever. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">Introduction</head><p n="p5.24"><s n="s1.1;p5.24">The current and possible future costs and resources were analysed using solver in Excel to find the best method to minimise production costs for the yarn manufacturing division, run by Amanda Zellerman. </s></p><div2><head rend="underlined bold">A. The present cost of meeting the contract and resources to be used. </head><p n="p6.24"><s n="s1.2;p6.24">The main objective is to minimise the total costs of production (i.e. </s><s n="s2.2;p6.24">Minimise £15.I + £21.E). </s></p><p n="p7.24"><s rend="underlined" n="s1.1;p7.24">The decision variables are: </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p8.24"><s n="s1.1;p8.24">I = The number of metres of standard width cloth produced internally per week. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p9.24"><s n="s1.1;p9.24">E = The number of metres of standard width cloth produced externally per week. </s></p><p n="p10.24"><s rend="underlined" n="s1.1;p10.24">The objective is subject to the following constraints: </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p11.24"><s n="s1.2;p11.24">Internal production must be at least half of the total amount supplied, (i.e. </s><s n="s2.2;p11.24">I - E >= 0, so, I >= E). </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p12.24"><s n="s1.2;p12.24">The total output supplied must be at least 500 metres per week, (i.e. </s><s n="s2.2;p12.24">I + E >= 500). </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p13.24"><s n="s1.1;p13.24">The 3 machines are all constrained to the amount of hours available for their use (these three constraints are shown in the table below, taken from an Excel sheet). </s></p><p n="p14.24"><s n="s1.1;p14.24">Assume 'non-negativity' (as you cannot produce negative amounts) and a 'linear model.' </s></p><p n="p15.24"><s n="s1.1;p15.24">Assume vat A and vat B are used as one machine, as they both perform the same, identical task. </s></p><table id="BAWE_0200b-tab.001"><row><cell/></row></table></div2><div2><head rend="underlined bold">B. The effect of using the extra 700 hours of the vats for another product. </head><p n="p16.24"><s n="s1.3;p16.24">If the available time for the vat machines A and B decreases by 700 hours, the resources available (hrs) for the vats would exactly halve. </s><s n="s2.3;p16.24">The reports show that both the slack and the allowable increase would reduce by 700 hours, and the status is still not binding. </s><s n="s3.3;p16.24">This would not cause any major effects, but if vat use wanted to increase in future by more than 30 metres per week, there would be a lack of vat capacity. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined bold">C. Should the spare machine capacity be bought for carding &amp; combing? </head><p n="p17.24"><s n="s1.9;p17.24">At present, the resources for carding and combing (C&amp;C) have no spare capacity (or no slack), making it a binding constraint. </s><s n="s2.9;p17.24">This lack of machinery is minimising internal production to 320 metres per week, since the other two machinery types have spare capacity. </s><s n="s3.9;p17.24">Therefore, more capacity should be bought in. </s><s n="s4.9;p17.24">Since the twisting machine has a slack of 100 hours, 20 extra metres of cloth can be made internally per week. </s><s n="s5.9;p17.24">This will enable 80 hours of C&amp;C time to be bought in, so the twisting machine has no spare capacity and production can increase. </s><s n="s6.9;p17.24">(The allowable increase of the twisting and C&amp;C machines are infinite hours and 80 hours, so the non-zero decision variables (I and E) will not be affected, making this capacity increase possible). </s><s n="s7.9;p17.24">The shadow price tells us that an additional hour of C&amp;C time will improve (decrease) total production costs by £1.50. </s><s n="s8.9;p17.24">Hence, pay a maximum of £1.50 for each extra hour of capacity. </s><s n="s9.9;p17.24">Therefore, if C&amp;C capacity rises by 80 hours, the total cost should be at most £120. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined bold">D1. Implications of the 20% cost reduction of bought in yarn with the current supplier. </head><p n="p18.24"><s n="s1.5;p18.24">Assume the 20% cost negotiation with A-Z Cloth's original supplier succeeds, assuming all other things constant. </s><s n="s2.5;p18.24">This cost reduction will enable the quantity of bought in yarn to increase up to the amount that would make 45 metres of cloth, (if it is decided that production should increase after the six month review). </s><s n="s3.5;p18.24">Or cost savings of £756 could be gained, if production remained at 500 metres per week. </s><s n="s4.5;p18.24">Still, the quantity of bought in yarn should minimised because it is £1.80 per metre more expensive than producing cloth internally, so I and E remain at the same quantities. </s><s n="s5.5;p18.24">Even if the cost of fibre increases by £1 per metre, it would still be cost effective to minimise the amount bought in. </s></p><p n="p19.24"><s n="s1.1;p19.24">The shadow price of the C&amp;C constraint had increased to -0.45, (providing the C&amp;C capacity does not increase by more than 80 hours), implicating that for an 80 hour capacity increase, a maximum of £36 should be paid to the other division. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined bold">D2. Implications of the 30% cost reduction of bought in yarn with the alternative supplier. </head><p n="p20.24"><s n="s1.5;p20.24">There will be more implications if the new supplier is appointed, since the 30% reduction will mean that it is £0.30 cheaper to buy in the yarn than to make it. </s><s n="s2.5;p20.24">Thus, to be cost effective, as much yarn as possible should be bought in. </s><s n="s3.5;p20.24">If half of the total amount made is bought in (i.e. enough yarn for 250 metres of cloth is bought in), substantial cost savings of £1,155 would be gained. </s><s n="s4.5;p20.24">Since 70 metres more cloth would be produced externally, there is the spare capacity to increase internal production by 70 meters per week if production increased after the six month review. </s><s n="s5.5;p20.24">Hence, no extra C&amp;C machine capacity is required saving £36 per week if the 20% negotiation is achieved or a maximum of £120 if it is not. </s></p><p n="p21.24"><s n="s1.8;p21.24">However, the reliability of the alternative supplier should be looked up from their past behaviour. </s><s n="s2.8;p21.24">To what extent are they unreliable? </s><s n="s3.8;p21.24">Does this unpredictability of supplies cancel out the cost reduction offered? </s><s n="s4.8;p21.24">What is the quality of the yarn they supply? </s><s n="s5.8;p21.24">What are the administrative costs and the effects on the workforce of switching suppliers? </s><s n="s6.8;p21.24">Is the new supplier based locally? </s><s n="s7.8;p21.24">Are there any hidden, extra costs involved such as a delivery charge? </s><s n="s8.8;p21.24">Qualitative and quantitative factors must be considered. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined bold">E. Recommendations if the cost of fibre rises by £1 per standard width metre. </head><p n="p22.24"><s n="s1.4;p22.24">It is assumed that the increase of £1 per standard metre of cloth only applies to A-Z Cloth and not the suppliers. </s><s n="s2.4;p22.24">If the 30% reduction is gained by switching suppliers, it would be cost effective (saving £1.30 each metre) for the company policy regarding the proportion of bought in cloth to be changed, to enable more yarn to be bought in. </s><s n="s3.4;p22.24">However, any unused machine capacity would create an opportunity cost. </s><s n="s4.4;p22.24">The possibility to rent out spare machinery would reduce this opportunity cost. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined bold">F. Increasing the amount supplied under the contract in six months time. </head><p n="p23.24"><s n="s1.7;p23.24">In part A, B, C and E: the shadow price of the total output constraint is £21. </s><s n="s2.7;p23.24">Internal production cannot increase without buying extra capacity. </s><s n="s3.7;p23.24">External production can increase by up to 140 metres per week (except for C where the allowable increase is 180 metres), adding £21 to the total costs of production each time one extra metre of cloth is bought in. </s><s n="s4.7;p23.24">In part D1: if the 20% reduction is negotiated, an additional bought in metre would cost £16.80. </s><s n="s5.7;p23.24">In part D2: the 30% reduction from switching suppliers creates a good opportunity to increase internal production <hi rend="italic">as</hi> 70m extra could be made per week. </s><s n="s6.7;p23.24">If 80 hours of C&amp;C time is bought from another division (pay as less as possible for this as external production is now cheaper then internal production), then internal production can increase by a maximum of 90metres per week. </s><s n="s7.7;p23.24">This increase in I is also still feasible if the 700hours of vat use is required in the future. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0200b-fig.001"><head rend="underlined bold">Cost Implications of Increasing the Amount Supplied</head></figure></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">A limitation of solver:</head><p n="p24.24"><s n="s1.2;p24.24">Only one coefficient can change at any one time in the linear programming model. </s><s n="s2.2;p24.24">The linear program must be reformulated and solved again if multiple changes are required. </s></p></div1></body><back><div1 type="appendix"><head rend="underlined bold">Appendix</head><p/></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
