<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_0200d" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Introduction to Cultural Dynamics</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note/></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">2</p><p n="date">2005-05</p><p n="module title">International Environment of Business</p><p n="module code">IB2180</p><p n="genre family">Critique</p><p n="discipline">Business</p><p n="disciplinary group">SS</p><p n="grade">D</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">822</p><p n="number of s-units">59</p><p n="number of p">28</p><p n="number of tables">0</p><p n="number of figures">1</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">0</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">9</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">13.9</p><p n="average s-units per p">2.1</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">f</p><p n="year of birth">1985</p><p n="first language">English</p><p n="education">UKA</p><p n="course">Management Science</p><p n="student ID">0200</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front/><body><div1 type="section"><head>1. Introduction to Cultural Dynamics </head><p n="p1.28"><s n="s1.2;p1.28">I observed a presentation that analysed the elements of culture and how they influence how brands and products are communicated into different markets. </s><s n="s2.2;p1.28">One of the frameworks used to study culture was T.C. Melewar's 'five dimensions' (figure 1.1). </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0200d-fig.001"><head>Figure 1.1</head></figure><p n="p2.28"><s n="s1.2;p2.28">Culture is complex and dynamic with many definitions such as '<hi rend="italic">a collective programming of the mind which distinguishes the members of one category of people from another'</hi> (Hofstede 1994). </s><s n="s2.2;p2.28">This is why such frameworks seek to simplify culture's intricacy. </s></p><div2><head>2. Uses &amp; Insights provided by the '5 Dimensions' </head><p n="p3.28"/></div2><div2><head rend="bold">Studies Potential of Foreign Markets </head><p n="p4.28"><s n="s1.3;p4.28">Some firms fail to recognise the importance of the external marketing environment when launching/repositioning brands/products internationally. </s><s n="s2.3;p4.28">Marketing analysis should be used to assess the market potential for their brand, e.g. political changes and demand structure. </s><s n="s3.3;p4.28">However, marketing analysis fails to consider the cultural dimensions of markets, e.g. social behaviour, traditions and how promotional messages are received. </s></p><p n="p5.28"><s n="s1.1;p5.28">Hence, the 'five dimensions' can be used by firms alongside general marketing analysis to more accurately analyse the potential of the market they propose to enter to help ensure success of their brand/product. </s></p><p n="p6.28"><s n="s1.1;p6.28">Hofstede's <hi rend="italic">'Cultural Typology'</hi> model (1980) describes 6 dimensions of culture that also studies foreign market potential by discovering the cultural differences between markets. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">Other Uses of the Framework </head><p rend="ordered" n="p7.28"><s n="s1.3;p7.28">Highlights the considerations needed before moving into a new, foreign market. </s><s n="s2.3;p7.28">E.g. </s><s n="s3.3;p7.28">'Material Culture' highlights different countries' level of technological advancement and economic situation. </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p8.28"><s n="s1.1;p8.28">'Language', 'Aesthetics' and 'Humans &amp; the Universe' are useful to help organisations communicate a product/brand successfully to new markets. </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p9.28"><s n="s1.1;p9.28">It emphasises the need for market research (brand/ product perceptions, nature of foreign markets, etc.) </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p10.28"><s n="s1.2;p10.28">Aids marketer's evaluation of the marketing mix (distribution, means of production, etc), target market, etc. </s><s n="s2.2;p10.28">I.e. evaluates the elements of the marketing plan. </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p11.28"><s n="s1.1;p11.28">Acts as a frame of reference. </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head> 3. Disadvantages of the Framework as a Tool</head><p rend="ordered" n="p12.28"><s n="s1.3;p12.28">More 'prescriptive' models can be found that help the organisation adapt to cultural issues to have a successful brand and product in a foreign market. </s><s n="s2.3;p12.28">E.g. </s><s n="s3.3;p12.28">Dong and Helms brand-name translation model aids the 'Language' dimension. </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p13.28"><s n="s1.2;p13.28">This extra guidance may be needed because of the difficulty in putting cultural understandings into actions effectively. </s><s n="s2.2;p13.28">E.g. difficult to put the 'Social Institutions' affect on brand communication into practice. </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p14.28"><s n="s1.4;p14.28">Subjective nature of dimensions, much can be classified as interpretive knowledge. </s><s n="s2.4;p14.28">E.g. </s><s n="s3.4;p14.28">Aesthetics' is especially case sensitive and interpretive knowledge may create a barrier to entry. </s><s n="s4.4;p14.28">Marketers should be case sensitive when entering different markets and also be aware of existing sub-cultures. </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p15.28"><s n="s1.6;p15.28">Models simplify culture by splitting it into dimensions. </s><s n="s2.6;p15.28">This made me consider: 'can culture be segregated into 5 dimensions?' </s><s n="s3.6;p15.28">Yes, but there's a risk of oversimplification, missing out elements and overlooking relationships between dimensions. </s><s n="s4.6;p15.28">Consequently, dimensions must be viewed together. </s><s n="s5.6;p15.28">E.g. </s><s n="s6.6;p15.28">'Humans &amp; the Universe' cannot be viewed alone as it is affected by other dimensions, such as 'Social Institutions', especially politics, which dramatically effects beliefs and perceptions. </s></p><p n="p16.28"><s n="s1.2;p16.28">All dimensions are required for a cultural understanding. </s><s n="s2.2;p16.28">It's hard to put emphasis on any dimension, some are more important to some cultures. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head> 4. Conclusion</head><p n="p17.28"><s n="s1.4;p17.28">Cultural dynamics is highly important in international marketing, because cultures strongly influence the marketing plan and a lack of understanding of local markets often leads to brand failure. </s><s n="s2.4;p17.28">Not only must the firm understand the market, but it must adapt its strategy to the market's needs in coherence with its corporate strategy. </s><s n="s3.4;p17.28">Therefore, frameworks such as Hofstede's and T.C. Melewar's dimensions are beneficial as a preliminary point in the process of global brand building because they make you consider all elements of culture, which may not have been considered unaided. </s><s n="s4.4;p17.28">Cultural dimensions also change so the learning process should be continuously updated via research and strategies modified to match the changes. </s></p><p n="p18.28"><s n="s1.3;p18.28">The 'five dimensions' is a beneficial way to aid cultural understanding. </s><s n="s2.3;p18.28">Why? </s><s n="s3.3;p18.28">By understanding cultural differences, the marketing mix will better match the target market, messages will be received well and communication improved, leading to more effective international marketing. </s></p><p n="p19.28"><s n="s1.3;p19.28">Looking critically at my own learning process I judge that next time I plan to reflect on the lecture as well as the seminar and note how my learning evolved. </s><s n="s2.3;p19.28">I shall endeavour to reflect further go into more depth with my critique. </s><s n="s3.3;p19.28">This reflection has helped me clarify the overall use of the framework in reality and to consider who uses it. </s></p><p n="p20.28"><s n="s1.2;p20.28">5. </s><s n="s2.2;p20.28">Bibliography </s></p><p n="p21.28"><s n="s1.1;p21.28"><seg type="URL" n="www.webofculture.com"/> </s></p><p n="p22.28"><s n="s1.1;p22.28"><seg type="URL" n="www.wsu.edu"/>:8001/vcwsu/commons/topics/culture/culture-index </s></p><p n="p23.28"><s n="s1.1;p23.28"><seg type="URL" n="www.amanda.com/resources/hfweb2000/hfweb00.marcus"/> </s></p><p n="p24.28"><s n="s1.3;p24.28">E-resource: Academy of Management Executive, 2004, February, Vol. 18. </s><s n="s2.3;p24.28">No. </s><s n="s3.3;p24.28">1 </s></p><p n="p25.28"><s rend="underlined" n="s1.1;p25.28">The following academic papers: </s></p><p n="p26.28"><s n="s1.2;p26.28">Global corporate brand building: guidelines and case studies (2002). </s><s n="s2.2;p26.28">T.C. Melewar &amp; C.M. Walker </s></p><p n="p27.28"><s n="s1.2;p27.28">The influence of culture on brand building in the Chinese market: a brief insight. </s><s n="s2.2;p27.28">(2003) T.C. Melewar, M. Meadows, W. Zheng &amp; R. Rickards </s></p><p n="p28.28"><s n="s1.2;p28.28">The complexities of communicating to customers in emerging markets (2001). </s><s n="s2.2;p28.28">R. Fletcher &amp; T.C. Melewar. </s></p></div1></body><back/></text></TEI.2>
