<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_0203g" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Portfolio Case presentation number: 9 knee replacement</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">proforma</note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">appendices: 	ASPECTS OF CASE AS RECORDED IN SUMMARY OF PORTFOLIO CASES, PORTFOLIO COMPLETION CERTIFICATE</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">4</p><p n="date">2005-05</p><p n="module title">Other rotations</p><p n="module code">unknown</p><p n="genre family">Case study</p><p n="discipline">Medicine</p><p n="disciplinary group">LS</p><p n="grade">D</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">4396</p><p n="number of s-units">208</p><p n="number of p">99</p><p n="number of tables">2</p><p n="number of figures">2</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">15</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">15</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">21.1</p><p n="average s-units per p">2.1</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">f</p><p n="year of birth">1979</p><p n="first language">English</p><p n="education">UKA</p><p n="course">Medicine</p><p n="student ID">0203</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><docTitle><titlePart rend="bold">PORTFOLIO CASE No:</titlePart></docTitle><titlePart>Patient Initials<name type="other"/> Hospital Number Age 76 Gender Female</titlePart><titlePart>Portfolio Case presentation number: 9 Phase 2 course document objectives(s) 4.1, 4.13, P4.11 Has the patient' permission, including for follow up contact by telephone, been sought and recorded in the case notes?</titlePart></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="bold">Referral information</hi> Source of referral and a summary of key information</head><p n="p1.99"><s n="s1.1;p1.99"><name type="other"/> was admitted to <name type="other"/> hospital on the <name type="date"/> for a right elective total knee replacement carried out on the <name type="date"/>. <name type="other"/> has suffered with osteoarthritis of the right knee for approximately 10 years but stated that the she has been experiencing increased pain in her right knee over the past 3-4months. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="bold">History</hi> All <hi rend="bold italic">relevant</hi> information gathered from the patient about the presenting illness, co-existing problems, current treatment, <hi rend="italic">significant</hi> past medical history and the social and family background. The patient's view of the nature of the problem and their expectations for treatment.</head><div2><head rend="underlined bold">Presenting Complaint</head><p n="p2.99"><s n="s1.1;p2.99">Pain in the right knee which has increased in severity over the past 3-4 months and decreased mobility. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined bold">History of presenting complaint</head><p n="p3.99"><s n="s1.7;p3.99"><name type="other"/> stated that she has suffered with pain in the right knee from arthritis for approximately ten years and uses a walking stick to mobilise. <name type="other"/> stated that until recently she has been able to cope with the pain. </s><s n="s2.7;p3.99">The pain was described as being a dull aching pain which has increased in severity over the past 3-4 months with occasional sharp shooting pains. <name type="other"/> rated the pain at 6/10 (10 being the worst pain) with occasional episodes of increased severity. </s><s n="s3.7;p3.99">The pain is situated on the medial aspect of the right knee and does not radiate. </s><s n="s4.7;p3.99">There is no associated morning stiffness and the pain does not wake <name type="other"/> during the night. <name type="other"/> did not report any locking of the knee or giving way. <name type="other"/> reported that the knee feels stiff after sitting and that mobilising aggravates the pain. <name type="other"/> is unable to walk comfortably on the flat despite the use of a walking stick. </s><s n="s5.7;p3.99">The pain is most severe when walking up stairs or an incline. </s><s n="s6.7;p3.99">There is occasional swelling of the right knee and <name type="other"/> feels unable to put weight onto the knee due to the pain. <name type="other"/> has used analgesic cream in an effort to relieve the pain but stated that this only had a mild effect. </s><s n="s7.7;p3.99">In <name type="date"/> 2004 she had a Depo Medrone injection to her right knee, which was unsuccessful in relieving the pain. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined bold">Past Medical History</head><list type="bulleted"><head rend="bold">Medical</head><item>Angina</item><item>Atrial Fibrillation (paroxysmal)</item><item>Polymyalgia Rheumatica</item><item>Osteoarthritis right knee and shoulder joint</item><item>Hypertension</item><item>Mild mitral regurge</item><item>Restless leg syndrome (Right)</item><item>High Cholesterol</item><item>No epilepsy</item><item>No DVT/PE</item><item>No MI</item><item>No Stroke</item></list><list type="bulleted"><head rend="bold">Surgical</head><item>Right thyroid lobectomy 1990</item><item>Varicose Vein stripping 1994</item><item>SVT Cardioversion</item><item>Previous post operative nausea and vomiting</item></list><list type="bulleted"><head rend="underlined bold">Allergies</head><item>Penicillin</item><item>Codeine (violently sick)</item><item rend="bold">Cannot take aspirin based medication due to Warfarin use</item></list><list type="simple"><head rend="underlined bold">Medication</head><item>Spironolactone 25mg OD Potassium sparing diuretic used for the treatment of <name type="other"/>'s oedema</item><item>Atorvastatin 10 mg OD Statin (HMG CoA Reductase inhibitor) prescribed for <name type="other"/>'s high cholesterol</item><item>Propafenone 300 mg TDS Anti arrhythmic used for <name type="other"/>'s paroxysmal atrial fibrillation</item><item>Ramipril 5 mg OD ACE Inhibitor used to treat <name type="other"/>'s hypertension</item><item>Prednisolone 2.5 mg OD Corticosteroid used for <name type="other"/>'s Polymyalgia Rheumatica</item><item>Prednisolone 5 mg OD Corticosteroid used for <name type="other"/>'s Polymyalgia Rheumatica</item><item>Paracetamol 1g QDS Non-opioid analgesic, used in the treatment of mild to moderate pain</item><item>Warfarin Anti coagulant used for emboli prophylaxis due to <name type="other"/>'s atrial fibrillation</item><item>GTN spray PRN Nitrate used for the treatment of <name type="other"/>'s angina</item></list><p n="p4.99"/></div2><div2><head rend="underlined bold">Social History</head><p n="p5.99"><s n="s1.3;p5.99"><name type="other"/> is a retired cleaner who lives on her own in a bungalow. <name type="other"/> has two daughters who live nearby. <name type="other"/> is self-caring in terms of managing her personal hygiene and general cooking. </s><s n="s2.3;p5.99">However her current mobility status means that she is unable to shop for herself and she requires the assistance of her daughter for such activities. </s><s n="s3.3;p5.99">However, <name type="other"/> stated that both of her daughters now have their own families and she does not like to bother them with such tasks. <name type="other"/> has never smoked and does not consume alcohol. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined bold">Family History</head><p n="p6.99"><s n="s1.1;p6.99">No significant family history </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined bold">Systems Review</head><p n="p7.99"><s rend="bold" n="s1.1;p7.99">Cardiovascular System </s></p><p n="p8.99"><s n="s1.2;p8.99"><name type="other"/> has angina for which she uses a GTN spray and hypertension. </s><s n="s2.2;p8.99">No orthopnoea or PND. Occasional oedema </s></p><p n="p9.99"><s rend="bold" n="s1.1;p9.99">Respiratory System </s></p><p n="p10.99"><s n="s1.2;p10.99">No shortness of breath or cough. </s><s n="s2.2;p10.99">No wheeze or haemoptysis. </s></p><p n="p11.99"><s rend="bold" n="s1.1;p11.99">Gastrointestinal System </s></p><p n="p12.99"><s n="s1.1;p12.99">No nausea, vomiting or significant weight loss. <name type="other"/> suffers from constipation and has taken medication which has had no effect. </s></p><p n="p13.99"><s rend="bold" n="s1.1;p13.99">Genitourinary System </s></p><p n="p14.99"><s n="s1.1;p14.99">No change in urinary frequency, no incontinence. </s></p><p n="p15.99"><s rend="bold" n="s1.1;p15.99">Central Nervous System </s></p><p n="p16.99"><s n="s1.1;p16.99">No headaches, blackouts or visual disturbances. </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="bold">Analysis of history</hi> The most likely single cause of the presentation, other possible causes and reasons for these choices. The findings to be looked for on physical examination to help decide the cause.</head><p n="p17.99"><s n="s1.4;p17.99">The most likely cause of <name type="other"/>'s right knee pain is osteoarthritis (and this was indeed her diagnosis). </s><s n="s2.4;p17.99">Osteoarthritis is a disease of the synovial joints characterised by loss of articular cartilage and periarticular bone response (osteophytes, bone cysts, subchondral bone sclerosis). </s><s n="s3.4;p17.99">By the age of 40 90% of all people have some degenerative changes in the weight bearing joints [1] and the prevalence of OA increases with age. </s><s n="s4.4;p17.99">OA can affect many joints with the hip and knee being the major cause of disability. </s></p><list type="bulleted"><head>Symptoms of OA include:</head><item rend="bold">Joint pain</item><item rend="bold">Gelling (stiffening and pain after immobility)</item><item>Joint instability</item><item rend="bold">Loss of function</item></list><p n="p18.99"><s n="s1.1;p18.99"><name type="other"/> described three of the above characteristic symptoms of OA (highlighted) supporting such a diagnosis. <name type="other"/>' symptoms have been getting progressively worse and this is another salient feature of OA. Symptoms of OA are generally worse in one knee although both knee joints can be affected. </s></p><p n="p19.99"><s n="s1.4;p19.99">Signs to look for on examination to support a diagnosis of OA are tenderness on palpation of the right knee joint, crepitus of the patellofemoral joint on movement and a limitation of the range of movement. </s><s n="s2.4;p19.99">The knee joint may also be unstable with evidence of effusion and wasting of the quadriceps muscles. </s><s n="s3.4;p19.99">Palpation of osteophytes along the joint line may be possible. </s><s n="s4.4;p19.99">There may also be a varus deformity of the leg depending on which compartment of the knee joint if most affected by the arthritis. </s></p><p n="p20.99"><s n="s1.1;p20.99">Differential Diagnoses: </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p21.99"><s n="s1.2;p21.99"><hi rend="bold">Referred pain from the hip joint</hi> - Although <name type="other"/> describes the pain she feels as being related to the knee it is vital that the hips are examined. </s><s n="s2.2;p21.99">Pain from the hip joint can radiate to the knee as both joints have the same nerve supply. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p22.99"><s rend="bold" n="s1.7;p22.99">Inflammatory Arthritis e.g. </s><s n="s2.7;p22.99"><hi rend="bold">Rheumatoid arthritis (RA)</hi> - RA is a systemic inflammatory arthritis involving small and large joints. </s><s n="s3.7;p22.99">Pain and stiffness is worse in the morning and can last for several hours compared to OA where the post rest pain is of shorter duration. </s><s n="s4.7;p22.99">On examination the knees are painful, swollen (due to synovial thickening) and warm to the touch. </s><s n="s5.7;p22.99">Bow-leg, knock knee, or flexion deformity may occur. <name type="other"/> did not report pain in any other joints making this a less likely diagnosis. </s><s n="s6.7;p22.99">On x-ray the bone appears osteopaenic compared to OA where the bone is sclerosed. <name type="other"/> does not report any non articular manifestations associated with RA e.g. - </s><s n="s7.7;p22.99">scleritis, vasculitis, subcutaneous nodules </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p23.99"><s n="s1.5;p23.99"><hi rend="bold">Gout and Pseudogout</hi> - gout is characterised by recurrent attacks of acute synovitis. </s><s n="s2.5;p23.99">It affects mainly the peripheral joints e.g. toes, ankle and small joints of the hand but can affect the larger joints such as the knee. </s><s n="s3.5;p23.99">Signs to look for on examination are redness, a hot joint on palpation, swelling and gouty tophi around the joints (especially the olecranon and in the pinna of the ear). </s><s n="s4.5;p23.99">In an acute attack, the onset is very sudden and so this is an unlikely diagnosis in <name type="other"/> who has had symptoms for a number of years. </s><s n="s5.5;p23.99">Pseudogout more commonly affects the knee but is usually asymptomatic and therefore an unlikely diagnosis in <name type="other"/>. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p24.99"><s n="s1.3;p24.99"><hi rend="bold">Polymyalgia Rheumatica</hi> - Form of giant cell arteritis causing postrest stiffness and weakness. </s><s n="s2.3;p24.99">The pain is usually most severe around the pelvic and pectoral girdles with the tenderness arising from the muscles rather than the joints making this an unlikely diagnosis for <name type="other"/>. </s><s n="s3.3;p24.99">However, she has been diagnosed with this condition and so it should still be considered as a possible cause for her pain. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p25.99"><s n="s1.1;p25.99"><hi rend="bold">Trauma</hi> - fracture or damage to the ligament or cartilage of the knee joint - This is an unlikely diagnosis for <name type="other"/> as there was no history of trauma and <name type="other"/>'s pain has been chronic and progressive in nature. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="bold">Physical examination</hi> Highlight the findings most relevant to your clinical problem solving by underlining them</head><div2><head rend="underlined bold">General Examination </head><p n="p26.99"><s n="s1.4;p26.99">On examination <name type="other"/> was lying on the bed and looked comfortable and alert at rest. </s><s n="s2.4;p26.99">There was a single walking stick at the bedside. </s><s n="s3.4;p26.99">There was no finger clubbing, jaundice, anaemia, clubbing, cyanosis, oedema or lymphadenopathy. </s><s n="s4.4;p26.99">No evidence of gouty tophi or rheumatic nodules. </s></p><list type="bulleted"><head rend="bold">General Observations</head><item>Pulse - 83 regular</item><item>Blood Pressure - 145/77</item><item>Respiratory Rate - 18 pm</item><item>Temperature 36.1 C</item></list><list type="simple"><head rend="underlined">CVS:</head><item>No scars or deformities. HS I + II + 0 </item><item>JVP →</item><item>Palpable peripheral pulses bilaterally</item><item>No peripheral or central cyanosis</item></list><list type="simple"><head rend="underlined">RS:</head><item>Trachea central </item><item>Clear vesicular breath sounds with equal expansion </item><item>No chest wall deformities</item></list><list type="simple"><head rend="underlined">GI:</head><item>Abdomen soft and non tender </item><item>Resonant Percussion</item><item>Bowel sounds normal</item><item>No masses or organomegaly</item></list><p n="p27.99"><s rend="underlined" n="s1.1;p27.99">CNS </s></p><p n="p28.99"><s n="s1.1;p28.99">GCS 15/15 </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined bold">Musculoskeletal Examination</head><div3><head>Examination of knee joints</head><p n="p29.99"><s n="s1.3;p29.99"><hi rend="bold">Look:</hi> The right knee appeared to be swollen when compared to the left knee. </s><s n="s2.3;p29.99">There was a varus deformity of the right leg. </s><s n="s3.3;p29.99">There was no obvious muscle wasting, bruising or other skin discolouration. </s></p><p n="p30.99"><s n="s1.3;p30.99"><hi rend="bold">Feel:</hi> On palpation there was no temperature difference between the 2 knees and there was no palpable effusion on either knee. </s><s n="s2.3;p30.99">There was tenderness over the medial joint line of the right knee and some tenderness over the inferior pole of the patella. </s><s n="s3.3;p30.99">No loss of sensation or evidence of ischaemia to either leg. </s></p><p n="p31.99"><s rend="bold" n="s1.1;p31.99">Move: </s></p><p n="p32.99"><s rend="underlined" n="s1.1;p32.99">Right Knee </s></p><p n="p33.99"><s n="s1.3;p33.99">Flexion approx 60 degrees, no hyperextension, palpable crepitus and pain on movement. </s><s n="s2.3;p33.99">Tight medial collateral ligaments. </s><s n="s3.3;p33.99">Anterior and Posterior cruciate ligaments intact. </s></p><p n="p34.99"><s rend="underlined" n="s1.1;p34.99">Left Knee </s></p><p n="p35.99"><s n="s1.2;p35.99">Flexion approx 80 degrees, no hyperextension. </s><s n="s2.2;p35.99">No pain or crepitus on movement, collateral and cruciate ligaments intact. </s></p></div3><div3><head>Examination of right Hip joint</head><p n="p36.99"><s n="s1.1;p36.99"><hi rend="bold">Look:</hi> No obvious swellings, deformities, bruising or scars </s></p><p n="p37.99"><s n="s1.2;p37.99"><hi rend="bold">Feel:</hi> No temperature difference compared to left hip joint. </s><s n="s2.2;p37.99">No tenderness on palpation </s></p><p n="p38.99"><s n="s1.1;p38.99"><hi rend="bold">Move:</hi> Good range of movement with no pain elicited. </s></p></div3><div3><head>Gait</head><p n="p39.99"><s n="s1.1;p39.99"><name type="other"/> displayed an antalgic gait, reducing the stance phase duration for the right leg. </s></p></div3></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="bold">Analysis of history and examination</hi> Reasons for your choice of the cause of the patient's problem(s) and any other cause that still needs to be considered at this stage</head><p n="p40.99"><s n="s1.3;p40.99">The examination supports a working diagnosis of osteoarthritis in <name type="other"/>'s right knee. </s><s n="s2.3;p40.99">Classical signs of OA were elicited on examination - joint line tenderness on palpation with crepitus and pain on movement, varus deformity of right leg. </s><s n="s3.3;p40.99">Flexion was also limited in the right knee. <name type="other"/> displayed an antalgic gait due to the pain she experiences on walking. </s></p><p n="p41.99"><s n="s1.3;p41.99">On examination there was no redness or swelling of any other joints and no temperature difference between the 2 knees. </s><s n="s2.3;p41.99">There were no gouty tophi or rheumatic nodules present on examination and there is no known family history of such conditions. </s><s n="s3.3;p41.99">Such findings make the diagnosis of gout or rheumatoid arthritis less likely. </s></p><p n="p42.99"><s n="s1.2;p42.99">No abnormality could be found in <name type="other"/>'s hips ruling out the possibility of referred pain from the hip joint. </s><s n="s2.2;p42.99">There is no recent or past history of trauma as a possible cause of pain in the knee. </s></p><p n="p43.99"><s n="s1.1;p43.99">Radiological examination will confirm the working diagnosis of OA. Classic signs to look for are: </s></p><list type="bulleted"><item>Loss of joint space</item><item>Osteophytes</item><item>Bone cysts</item><item>Subarticular sclerosis</item></list><p n="p44.99"><s n="s1.1;p44.99">Osteoarthritis can be graded according to the severity of cartilage damage, however this is only possible during arthroscopy or at the time of surgery: </s></p><p n="p45.99"><s n="s1.1;p45.99">Grade 1 - Softening </s></p><p n="p46.99"><s n="s1.1;p46.99">Grade 2 - Fibrillation </s></p><p n="p47.99"><s n="s1.1;p47.99">Grade 3 - Fissures </s></p><p n="p48.99"><s n="s1.1;p48.99">Grade 4 - Denuding </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="bold">Formulation of the patient's problem(s)</hi> Encapsulate this in physical, psychological and social terms (the triple diagnosis)</head><p n="p49.99"><s n="s1.1;p49.99"><name type="other"/> is an elderly lady who has been admitted for an elective total right knee replacement. <name type="other"/> is slightly anxious about the surgery but is keen to have the operation in order to reduce her pain and improve her mobility. </s></p><p n="p50.99"><s n="s1.2;p50.99">Physical - <name type="other"/>'s independence is limited by the pain she experiences from her right knee. </s><s n="s2.2;p50.99">Despite <name type="other"/> having a stick to assist with walking and the pain being most severe when climbing the stairs, she feels unable to walk comfortably on the flat for fear of aggravating the pain. </s></p><p n="p51.99"><s n="s1.2;p51.99">Social - <name type="other"/> is close to both of her daughters and sees them as often as possible. </s><s n="s2.2;p51.99">The decrease in <name type="other"/>'s mobility has meant that she has had to rely on her daughters for help with shopping etc. </s></p><p n="p52.99"><s n="s1.3;p52.99">Psychological - <name type="other"/> has suffered with pain from her right knee for over 10 years. </s><s n="s2.3;p52.99">Until recently, <name type="other"/> stated that the pain was bearable. </s><s n="s3.3;p52.99">However over the last 3-4 months the pain has increased in severity and <name type="other"/> was obviously concerned over the effects on her mobility. <name type="other"/> also stated that she can feel low on occasion as she feels like a burden to her daughters who both have their own family commitments. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="bold">Management</hi> Use the framework of RAPRIOP to structure your proposed management. Refer to the guidelines to the writing of portfolio cases for the details of the issues to be addressed under each heading.</head><div2><head rend="underlined">Investigations</head><table id="BAWE_0203g-tab.001"><head>Blood tests (<name type="date"/> )</head><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p53.99"><s n="s1.4;p53.99"><hi rend="bold">Comment</hi>: The Prothrombin time and INR are increased in <name type="other"/>'s results due to her warfarin use at the time of blood tests. </s><s n="s2.4;p53.99">The INR was repeated prior to the operation after her Warfarin had been stopped and was found to be acceptable at 1.1 (normal range = 0.9-1.2). </s><s n="s3.4;p53.99">The low INR is a concern not only for the surgeon but also for the anaesthetist as it can influence the type of anaesthetic to use e.g. </s><s n="s4.4;p53.99">There would be an increased risk from using an epidural/spinal anaesthetic due to the increased risk of bleeding if the vasculature around the spinal canal was damaged during administration. </s></p><table id="BAWE_0203g-tab.002"><head>Biochemistry results (<name type="date"/> )</head><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p54.99"><s n="s1.1;p54.99"><name type="date"/>: Infection Screen nose and groin - <hi rend="bold">no MRSA</hi> </s></p><p n="p55.99"><s n="s1.1;p55.99"><name type="date"/>: Urine microscopy and culture - <hi rend="bold">no growth</hi> </s></p><p n="p56.99"><s rend="bold" n="s1.1;p56.99">X-Rays: </s></p><p n="p57.99"><s n="s1.1;p57.99">Both knees, chest, c spine and right shoulder </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0203g-pic.001"><head rend="bold">Right knee - weight bearing</head></figure><figure id="BAWE_0203g-pic.002"><head rend="bold">Left knee - weight bearing</head></figure><p n="p58.99"><s n="s1.2;p58.99">The x-rays showed that <name type="other"/> has osteoarthritis affecting her right knee and right shoulder. </s><s n="s2.2;p58.99">An x-ray of the c spine was taken to rule out pathology here which could have affected the anaesthetic. </s></p><p n="p59.99"><s n="s1.2;p59.99">Knee - the x-ray clearly shows a loss of joint space in the medial compartment of the right knee with bone sclerosis and osteophyte formation. </s><s n="s2.2;p59.99">Early arthritic changes are also visible in the left knee. </s></p><p n="p60.99"><s n="s1.1;p60.99">ECG: No significant findings </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">Reassurance and explanation</head><p n="p61.99"><s n="s1.5;p61.99"><name type="other"/> the x-rays that we took show that you have osteoarthritis of the right knee and shoulder. </s><s n="s2.5;p61.99">Osteoarthritis is a degenerative disease of the synovial joints in your body. </s><s n="s3.5;p61.99">Normally, the ends of the bones are covered in a layer of cartilage which stops them from rubbing together. </s><s n="s4.5;p61.99">In osteoarthritis, the cartilage begins to wear away, this process can be likened to Teflon in a pan, in the initial stages of the disease, the 'Teflon' or cartilage begins to soften, after a while it starts to flake off, it then starts to crack and finally wears away completely. </s><s n="s5.5;p61.99">This wearing of the cartilage means that the ends of the bones rub against each other causing the pain that you are experiencing. </s></p><p n="p62.99"><s n="s1.7;p62.99">The initial treatment for osteoarthritis consists of weight loss to reduce the load on your joints, gentle exercise, heat treatment and anti-inflammatory drugs such as ibuprofen. </s><s n="s2.7;p62.99">If these methods fail, the next step is to inject steroid into the joint. </s><s n="s3.7;p62.99">However, you have found that these methods of treatment are no longer relieving the pain and that your mobility has decreased. </s><s n="s4.7;p62.99">This indicates that your osteoarthritis is quite advanced (and your x-rays confirm this) making you a suitable candidate for a total knee replacement. </s><s n="s5.7;p62.99">This will involve us replacing your joint with a stainless steel and plastic prostheses with the aim of improving your mobility and relieving your pain. </s><s n="s6.7;p62.99">After the operation we will see you in the outpatient clinic to monitor the range of movement you have and the function of the joint. </s><s n="s7.7;p62.99">As with all surgery there are risks involved but I will explain these all to you should you decide to go ahead with the operation. </s></p><p n="p63.99"><s n="s1.1;p63.99">Are there any questions? </s></p><p n="p64.99"><s n="s1.1;p64.99">Comment: Risks of surgery - infection, bleeding, scaring, poor wound healing, damage to surrounding structures, DVT/PE, rejection of the prosthesis leading to fibrosis and anaesthetic complications. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">Prescription/medical intervention</head><p n="p65.99"><s rend="bold" n="s1.1;p65.99">ACG Right Total Knee Replacement </s></p><div3><head rend="bold">Pre-Op</head><p n="p66.99"><s n="s1.4;p66.99">IV antibiotics with induction of General Anaesthetic, Local anaesthetic and Femoral Nerve block. </s><s n="s2.4;p66.99">Pre prep in anaesthetic room, tourniquet used to minimise blood loss during procedure - 300mmHg. </s><s n="s3.4;p66.99">A medial parapatellar approach with an anterior midline incision was used to access the right knee joint. </s><s n="s4.4;p66.99">Osteoarthritis was evident in all three compartments of the knee: </s></p><list type="bulleted"><item>Medial Compartment Grade IV</item><item>Patella Grade III</item><item>Lateral Compartment Grade II</item></list><p n="p67.99"><s n="s1.4;p67.99">The PCL was intact and retained. </s><s n="s2.4;p67.99">A 60mm femoral component, 63x10 tibial component and a small patella prosthesis were used. </s><s n="s3.4;p67.99">Neutral alignment was achieved with 0-130º range of movement and normal patella tracking. </s><s n="s4.4;p67.99">The tourniquet was released after 70 min and homeostasis was achieved. </s></p></div3><div3><head rend="bold">Post-Op</head><list type="bulleted"><head>Routine observations </head><item>Pulse - 73 regular</item><item>Blood Pressure - 136/68</item><item>Respiratory Rate - 16 pm</item><item>Temperature 35.0 C</item><item>Oxygen saturation - 99% on 4L/O <hi rend="sub">2</hi></item></list><list type="bulleted"><head>Post Operative medication: </head><item>PCA - Morphine Sulphate (100mg in 50 ml)</item><item>Stemetil 12.5 mg - Phenothiazine used prophylactically for post operative nausea and vomiting </item><item>Cefuroxime 750mg IV - second generation cephalosporin for prophylaxis of post operative infection.</item></list><list type="simple"><item>Routine Mobilisation</item><item>Recommence Warfarin <name type="date"/> PM</item><item>Drain out in 24 hours</item><item>Routine bloods and X-Rays tomorrow</item></list><p n="p68.99"/></div3></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">Observation</head><p n="p69.99"><s n="s1.6;p69.99"><name type="other"/> was transferred to recovery and then back to the orthopaedic ward where she received regular monitoring of her oxygen saturation, heart rate, BP, RR, temperature. </s><s n="s2.6;p69.99">The drain was also checked and contained 500ml at 18.15pm on day of operation. </s><s n="s3.6;p69.99">During surgery the urine output may be decreased due to the release of hormones such as ADH (for water conservation). </s><s n="s4.6;p69.99">Monitoring of <name type="other"/>'s urine output following surgery is a good indicator of recovery. <name type="other"/> appeared to be a well-nourished lady and should not require any dietary supplementation. </s><s n="s5.6;p69.99">It is important to observe the wound site for any signs of infection following surgery or any indication of dehiscence so that prompt action can be taken. </s><s n="s6.6;p69.99">It is vital that <name type="other"/>'s Warfarin is restarted on the night of the operation to prevent any complications from her atrial fibrillation e.g. atrial thrombus. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">Referral and team working</head><p n="p70.99"><s n="s1.1;p70.99">Physiotherapist - to encourage early mobilisation </s></p><p n="p71.99"><s n="s1.1;p71.99">GP - details of operation and monitoring on discharge </s></p><p n="p72.99"><s n="s1.1;p72.99">Orthopaedic outpatients - for review on discharge </s></p><p n="p73.99"><s n="s1.1;p73.99">Social Services - post operative home help as <name type="other"/> is self caring, possibility of meals on wheels during <name type="other"/>'s recovery period </s></p><p n="p74.99"><s n="s1.1;p74.99">District Nurses - to redress the wound if needed and monitor for signs of infection, bed sores etc. </s></p><p n="p75.99"><s n="s1.1;p75.99">Occupational therapist - <name type="other"/> may require further walking aids to assist with her mobility in the immediate postoperative period. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">Advice and Prevention</head><p rend="bulleted" n="p76.99"><s n="s1.1;p76.99">Follow the advice of the physiotherapists </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p77.99"><s n="s1.1;p77.99">On discharge from hospital exercise the knee gently - try not to remain seated for long periods of time </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p78.99"><s n="s1.1;p78.99">If the wound becomes red or swollen or begins to weep contact your GP </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="bold">Outcome</hi> A description of the progress of the patient as far as possible. This should include consideration of further issues to be resolved. Where appropriate you should contact by telephone patients who have been discharged home.</head><p n="p79.99"><s n="s1.1;p79.99"><name type="other"/> is recovering on the orthopaedic ward of <name type="other"/> hospital </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="bold">Evidence based care and issues for research</hi> A brief consideration of the evidence base required for the diagnosis and management of the patient's problem(s)</head><p n="p80.99"><s n="s1.3;p80.99">The knee joint is one of the commonest causes of disability from OA with the medial compartment most commonly affected. </s><s n="s2.3;p80.99">The pain and limited movement experienced by patients with OA imposes a huge physical disability to the individual. </s><s n="s3.3;p80.99">This can reduce a patient's quality of life and lead to further morbidity. </s></p><p n="p81.99"><s n="s1.2;p81.99">The main principle in the treatment of OA is to treat the patients symptoms and disability and not the radiological appearance of the OA. The aim should be to alleviate pain, improve function and decrease disability. </s><s n="s2.2;p81.99">The patient should also be educated about OA and its management. </s></p><p n="p82.99"><s n="s1.1;p82.99">Treatment: </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p83.99"><s n="s1.3;p83.99"><hi rend="bold">Non-pharmacological</hi> - Initially management is focused at weight loss with strengthening and exercise of the muscles surrounding the knee joint. </s><s n="s2.3;p83.99">This helps to improve the stability of the joint and reduce the pressure placed on it. </s><s n="s3.3;p83.99">Pressure on the joint can also be relived through the use of walking aids. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p84.99"><s n="s1.10;p84.99"><hi rend="bold">Pharmacological</hi> - Initially, simple analgesia should be prescribed to reduce the pain associated with OA. Once these prove to be ineffective, NSAIDS should be used intermittently. </s><s n="s2.10;p84.99">If the pain is still severe, intra articular corticosteroid injections can produce short-term improvement in joint pain [2]. </s><s n="s3.10;p84.99">A gradual decrease in the effectiveness of such injections indicates an increase in severity of the disease. </s><s n="s4.10;p84.99">Limited evidence has shown that intra articular glucocorticoid injections into the joint reduced pain for 1-4 weeks compared with placebo [3]. </s><s n="s5.10;p84.99">However, studies have also shown that overuse of corticosteroids can lead to progression of the disease [1]. </s><s n="s6.10;p84.99">Hyaluronic Acid injections may offer a longer more durable response with improvement in pain and function when compared to Corticosteroids [2]. </s><s n="s7.10;p84.99">The public sector has been overwhelmed with publicity regarding the effectiveness of Glucosamine in the treatment and prevention of osteoarthritis. </s><s n="s8.10;p84.99">Previous reviews have shown that Glucosamine taken for 6 weeks decreased pain and improved function in people with OA [4]. </s><s n="s9.10;p84.99">However, poor quality of trials and publication bias has questioned the reliability of such information. </s><s n="s10.10;p84.99">Further research and clarification in this area is needed and may help to optimise future management of OA. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p85.99"><s n="s1.1;p85.99"><hi rend="bold">Surgery</hi> - is indicated in patients who are not gaining any benefit from non operative management. </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p86.99"><s n="s1.3;p86.99">1) Tibial Osteotomy - can correct the varus deformity of medical compartment OA and adjust the line of weight bearing so that the healthy compartment takes more weight. </s><s n="s2.3;p86.99">The operation is not always effective and the patient normally requires a TKR at a later date [5]. </s><s n="s3.3;p86.99">This option was not indicated for <name type="other"/> due to the presence of OA in the lateral compartment of her knee (even though at present this was not the main source of her pain). </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p87.99"><s n="s1.1;p87.99">2) Low Femoral osteotomy - for patients with a valgus deformity of > 10 degrees and wearing of the lateral compartment. </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p88.99"><s n="s1.1;p88.99">3) Hemi arthroplasty - Lateral and Medial components of the knee joint are replaced (femoral and tibial surfaces). </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p89.99"><s n="s1.3;p89.99">4) TKR - All three compartments of the knee (medial, lateral and patella) are replaced. </s><s n="s2.3;p89.99">The articulating surfaces are replaced with metal and plastic prostheses to provide a low friction interface. </s><s n="s3.3;p89.99">Evidence has shown that TKR provides patients with pain relief, increased function and an improvement in quality of life [6]. </s></p><p n="p90.99"><s n="s1.6;p90.99">The surgery performed on <name type="other"/> was a tricompartmental TKR. A review of tricompartmental prostheses identified 154 studies of 37 different prostheses in 9879 people [8]. </s><s n="s2.6;p90.99">Good or excellent outcomes were reported in 89% of these people [7]. </s><s n="s3.6;p90.99">The pain <name type="other"/> felt was primarily due to osteoarthritic changes in the medial compartment of her right knee. </s><s n="s4.6;p90.99">Unicompartmental knee replacements are possible, indeed one RCT found that unicompartmental knee replacements were more effective than tricompartmental replacement at 5 years follow up [8]. </s><s n="s5.6;p90.99">However, <name type="other"/>'s x-rays showed osteoarthritic changes both at the patella and the lateral compartment of the right knee. </s><s n="s6.6;p90.99">A total knee replacement was therefore more suitable for <name type="other"/> in order to prevent the need for future surgery to the remaining degenerative parts of the knee. </s></p><p n="p91.99"><s n="s1.4;p91.99">In the healthy knee, the Posterior Cruciate Ligament acts as an anterior constraint for movement of the femur on the tibia providing the knee joint with posterior stability. </s><s n="s2.4;p91.99">A total knee replacement aims to reproduce movements of the knee and the stability of the joint, therefore retaining the PCL will obviously assist with this. </s><s n="s3.4;p91.99">At present the decision to retain the PCL depends on its degenerative status, the type of implant used or just personal preference [9]. </s><s n="s4.4;p91.99">A possible area for research would be to investigate the advantages/disadvantages of retaining or sacrificing the PCL in a total knee replacement. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="bold">Commentary</hi> A commentary on issues of health care delivery, ethical issues or disability relevant to the patient and/or problem</head><p n="p92.99"><s n="s1.3;p92.99">Approximately 30,000 TKR are carried out in England and Wales each year and it is estimated that the need for all joint replacements will increase by approx 40% over the next 30 years [10]. </s><s n="s2.3;p92.99">One of the main reasons for the prospected increase is the growing size of the ageing population. </s><s n="s3.3;p92.99">It is thought that the average total knee replacement lasts for approximately 15 years, however this depends on a number of factors relating to the patient including their age, level of activity and weight. </s></p><p n="p93.99"><s n="s1.4;p93.99">Knee arthritis is slightly more common than hip arthritis, in women over the age of 74 the incidence is 43 per 1000 [11]. </s><s n="s2.4;p93.99">It is estimated that 20 per 1000 people in the general population would benefit from total knee replacement, however many of these individuals are not referred for surgery despite 4 per 1000 having extreme disability [11]. </s><s n="s3.4;p93.99">The management of waiting lists is major political issue; current thinking suggests that a standardised priority assessment criterion for common elective procedures such as total knee replacement should be introduced [11]. </s><s n="s4.4;p93.99">Patients will be prioritised according to a clinical scoring system, which will prioritise patients according to the pain and disability associated with their knee arthritis [10]. </s></p><p n="p94.99"><s n="s1.1;p94.99">Complications of total knee replacement are as for all forms of surgery but also include: </s></p><p n="p95.99"><s n="s1.2;p95.99"><hi rend="bold">Patellofemoral complications</hi> - including patellofemoral instability, fracture patella, failure of patella component, patella clunk syndrome, and extensor mechanism tendon rupture. </s><s n="s2.2;p95.99">These are some of the most common reasons for re operation. </s></p><p n="p96.99"><s n="s1.2;p96.99"><hi rend="bold">Aseptic loosening</hi> - Loosening of the prosthesis occurs at a rate of approx 5-10% of patients at 10-15 years. </s><s n="s2.2;p96.99">The aetiology is not fully understood, loosening of the prostheses leads to mechanical instability and ultimately failure of the prosthesis. </s></p><p n="p97.99"><s n="s1.4;p97.99"><hi rend="bold">Arthrofibrosis</hi> - excessive scar tissue formation causing restriction of knee movement. </s><s n="s2.4;p97.99">This occurs in less than 1% of patients and the aetiology is unknown. </s><s n="s3.4;p97.99">Conservative management includes anti-inflammatory medication, physiotherapy, and reassurance. </s><s n="s4.4;p97.99">In severe cases the joint may need to be replaced and if this fails the joint may need to be fused [12]. </s></p><p n="p98.99"><s n="s1.2;p98.99">It is therefore important that patients are informed of the possible complications of surgery so that they are able to make an appropriate informed decision. </s><s n="s2.2;p98.99">Surgery poses risks at any ages but in the case of <name type="other"/> who also has significant co morbidity, the risks are increased and it is important that <name type="other"/> understands this. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="bold">Impact on your learning</hi> Describe what you have learnt from this case</head><list type="bulleted"><item>Examination of the knee joint</item><item>Pathology and presentation of osteoarthritis</item><item>Radiological features of Osteoarthritis</item><item>Management of knee osteoarthritis</item><item>Scrubbed for theatre</item><item>Sizing prosthesis according to x-ray</item></list><p n="p99.99"/></div1></body><back><div1 type="bibliography"><div2 type="bibliography"><head rend="bold">References</head><p>[1] Brown DE and Neumann RD. Orthopaedics secrets. 2<hi rend="sup">nd</hi> edition. Hanley and Belfus 1999</p><p>[2] Bellamy N, Campbell J, Robinson V, Gee T, Bourne r, Wells T. Intra articular corticosteroid for treatment of osteoarthritis of the knee (review). The Cochrane Library 2005 Issue 3.</p><p>[3] Ravaud P, Moulinier L, Giraudeau B et al. Effects of joint lavage and steroid injection in patients with osteoarthritis of the knee: results of a multicenter, randomised controlled trial. Arthritis Rheum. 1999:42:475-482</p><p>[4] Towhead TE, Maxwell L, Anastassiades TP, Shea B, Houpt J, Robinson V, Hochberg MC, Wells G. Glucosamine therapy for treating osteoarthritis (Review) Cochrane Library 2005 Issue 3</p><p>[5] Dandy DJ and Edwards DJ.Essential Orthopaedics and trauma. 3<hi rend="sup">rd</hi> edition. Churchill Livingstone 1998</p><p>[6] Hawker G, Wright J, Coyte P et al. Health related quality of life after knee replacement. J Bone Joint Surg. 1998:80:163-173</p><p>[7] Callahan CM, Drake BG, Heck DA Et Al. Patient outcomes following unicompartmental or bicompartmental knee arthroplasty: a meta analysis. J Arthroplasty 1995;10:141-150:</p><p>[8] Newman JH, Ackroyd CE, Shah NA. Unicompartmental or total knee replacement? Five year results of a prospective randomised trial of 102 osteoarthritic knees with unicompartmental arthritis. J Bone Joint Surg. 1998;80:862-865</p><p>[9] Jacobs W, Anderson P, Clements D, Wymenga A. retention v's sacrifice of the posterior cruciate ligament in total knee replacement for the treatment of osteoarthritis and rheumatoid arthritis (Protocol). The Cochrane Library 2005 Issue 3</p><p>[10] Woolhead DM, Donovan JL, Dieppe PA. Outcomes of total knee replacement: a qualitative study. Rheumatology 2005:44:1032-1037</p><p>[11] Palmer SH. Total Knee Arthroplasty. - <seg type="URL" n="http://www.emedicine.com/orthoped/topic347.htm"/></p><p>[12] Moran CG and Morton TC. Total knee replacement: the joint of the decade. BMJ 2000;320:820</p></div2><div2 type="bibliography"><head rend="bold">References not cited</head><p>Apley AG and Solomon L. Orthopaedics and Fractures. 2<hi rend="sup">nd</hi> edition. Butterworth Heinemann Ltd 1994</p><p>Dandy DJ and Edwards DJ.Essential Orthopaedics and trauma. 3<hi rend="sup">rd</hi> edition. Churchill Livingstone 1998</p><p>BNF September 2004 BMA</p></div2></div1><div1 type="appendix"><head rend="bold">ASPECTS OF CASE AS RECORDED IN SUMMARY OF PORTFOLIO CASES•</head><p/></div1><div1 type="appendix"><head rend="bold">PORTFOLIO COMPLETION CERTIFICATE</head><p/></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
