<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_0203b" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Portfolio Case presentation number: 3 Left Carotid Endartectomy.</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">proforma</note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">page numbers</note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">appendices: 	ASPECTS OF CASE AS RECORDED IN SUMMARY OF PORTFOLIO CASES, PORTFOLIO COMPLETION CERTIFICATE</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">4</p><p n="date">2005-04</p><p n="module title">Other rotations</p><p n="module code">unknown</p><p n="genre family">Case study</p><p n="discipline">Medicine</p><p n="disciplinary group">LS</p><p n="grade">D</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">2978</p><p n="number of s-units">135</p><p n="number of p">82</p><p n="number of tables">0</p><p n="number of figures">2</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">10</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">11</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">22.1</p><p n="average s-units per p">1.6</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">f</p><p n="year of birth">1979</p><p n="first language">English</p><p n="education">UKA</p><p n="course">Medicine</p><p n="student ID">0203</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><docTitle><titlePart rend="bold">PORTFOLIO CASE No: </titlePart></docTitle><titlePart>Patient Initials<name type="other"/> Hospital Number<name type="other"/> Age 84 Gender female</titlePart><titlePart>Portfolio Case presentation number: 3 Phase 2 course document objective(s): 7.9 Has the patient's permission, including for follow up contact by telephone, been sought and recorded in the case notes?</titlePart></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="bold">Referral information</hi> Source of referral and a summary of key information</head><p n="p1.82"><s n="s1.1;p1.82"><name type="other"/> was admitted to hospital on <name type="date"/> for an <hi rend="bold">elective</hi> left carotid endarterectomy </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="bold">History</hi> All <hi rend="bold italic">relevant</hi> information gathered from the patient about the presenting illness, co-existing problems, current treatment, <hi rend="italic">significant</hi> past medical history and the social and family background. The patient's view of the nature of the problem and their expectations for treatment. </head><div2><head rend="underlined bold">Presenting Complaint and History of Presenting Complaint</head><p n="p2.82"><s n="s1.2;p2.82"><name type="other"/> has a history of recurrent Transient Ischaemic Attacks having had approximately 7 TIA's over a 5 year period. </s><s n="s2.2;p2.82">Each attack leaves <name type="other"/> with <hi rend="bold">right arm weakness and expressive dysphasia</hi> which lasts for approximately 10 minutes and then returns to normal. <name type="other"/> was referred to Mr <name type="other"/> in 2003 by her GP and has been under his care since. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined bold">Past Medical History</head><list type="bulleted"><head rend="bold">Medical</head><item>Scoliosis</item><item rend="bold">Hypertension - diagnosed 1977</item><item rend="bold">Heart Murmur</item><item rend="bold">High Cholesterol</item><item>? Rheumatic Fever as child</item><item>No hx MI</item><item>No Asthma</item><item>No Diabetes</item><item>No hx of stroke or angina</item><item>No hx of DVT/pulmonary embolism</item><item>No hx of Tuberculosis </item></list><list type="bulleted"><head rend="bold">Surgical</head><item>Appendicectomy approx - 1935</item><item>Excision of skin lesion from face and neck (cancer) - 2001</item></list><p n="p3.82"/></div2><div2><head rend="underlined bold">Social History</head><p n="p4.82"><s n="s1.2;p4.82"><name type="other"/> lives alone in warden controlled accommodation in <name type="other"/> and has a call alarm in case of emergency. <name type="other"/> receives home help once a week to help with the house work and has her shopping delivered to her. <name type="other"/> requires a <hi rend="bold">stick for walking and has an electric scooter</hi> for town shopping. <name type="other"/> is a retired school teacher. <name type="other"/> started smoking approx age 15 and stopped smoking at age 70 and has a <hi rend="bold">27 year pack history.</hi> </s><s n="s2.2;p4.82"><name type="other"/> stated that she will drink one glass of wine approximately 5 times week. <name type="other"/> is hard of hearing. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined bold">Allergies</head><p n="p5.82"><s n="s1.1;p5.82">NKDA </s></p><p n="p6.82"><s n="s1.1;p6.82">Allergy to fish </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined bold">Medication</head><list type="simple"><item><hi rend="bold">Perindopril</hi> 4 mg OD</item><item><hi rend="bold">Indapamide</hi> 1.5 mg OD</item><item><hi rend="bold">Simvastatin</hi> 40mg OD</item><item>Clopidogrel - antiplatelet 75 mg OD</item><item>Clexane 20 mg OD</item></list><p n="p7.82"/></div2><div2><head rend="underlined bold">Family History</head><p n="p8.82"><s n="s1.1;p8.82"><name type="other"/>'s sister had Parkinsons Disease </s></p><p n="p9.82"><s n="s1.1;p9.82">No other significant family history </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined bold">Systems Review</head><p n="p10.82"><s rend="bold" n="s1.1;p10.82">Cardiovascular system </s></p><p n="p11.82"><s n="s1.1;p11.82">Systolic Murmur radiating to the carotids - Aortic Stenosis </s></p><p n="p12.82"><s rend="bold" n="s1.1;p12.82">Respiratory System </s></p><p n="p13.82"><s n="s1.1;p13.82">No significant findings </s></p><p n="p14.82"><s rend="bold" n="s1.1;p14.82">Gastrointestinal System </s></p><p n="p15.82"><s n="s1.1;p15.82">No significant findings </s></p><p n="p16.82"><s rend="bold" n="s1.1;p16.82">Genitourinary System </s></p><p n="p17.82"><s n="s1.1;p17.82">Mild incontinence and increase in frequency of micturition especially during the night - <name type="other"/> attributes this to old age and said that it was not a significant change. </s></p><p n="p18.82"><s rend="bold" n="s1.1;p18.82">Central Nervous System </s></p><p n="p19.82"><s n="s1.1;p19.82"><name type="other"/> stated that she often feels <hi rend="bold">dizzy first thing in the morning</hi> but that this dizziness improves throughout the day. </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="bold">Analysis of history</hi> The most likely single cause of the presentation, other possible causes and reasons for these choices. The findings to be looked for on physical examination to help decide the cause.</head><p n="p20.82"><s n="s1.7;p20.82">Transient Ischaemic Attacks are usually caused by the passage of emboli through the cerebral circulation which interrupts blood flow to the brain. </s><s n="s2.7;p20.82">TIA's may also be caused by a fall in cerebral perfusion due to dysrhythmia or decreased flow through stenosed carotid arteries due to atheroma formation. </s><s n="s3.7;p20.82">Signs to look for on examination would be an irregular heart beat and a bruit over the carotid arteries. </s><s n="s4.7;p20.82">If a carotid bruit is heard it is an unreliable guide to the severity of the stenosis. </s><s n="s5.7;p20.82">The main sources of emboli to the brain are thrombi and atheromatous plaques within the carotid or vertebral arteries or in the heart. </s><s n="s6.7;p20.82">Cardiac thrombi can occur due to atrial fibrillation which often occurs secondary to valvular heart disease. </s><s n="s7.7;p20.82">The patient may therefore have atrial fibrillation or auscultation may reveal signs of a heart murmur. </s></p><p n="p21.82"><s n="s1.2;p21.82">Transient Ischaemic attacks cause sudden loss of function (i.e. within seconds) and last for approximately 8-14 mins (> 24 hours treated as a stroke). </s><s n="s2.2;p21.82">Hemiparesis and dysphasia are the two most common presenting symptoms of TIA's, </s></p><p n="p22.82"><s n="s1.1;p22.82">others include: </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p23.82"><s n="s1.1;p23.82">Amaurosis Fugax - a sudden transient loss of vision in on eye due to the passage of emboli through the retinal arteries. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p24.82"><s n="s1.1;p24.82">Transient Global Amnesia - episodes of amnesia lasting for several hours (presumed to be caused by posterior circulation ischaemia) </s></p><p n="p25.82"><s n="s1.1;p25.82">Differential causes for transient episodes could be syncope, postural hypotension (as a side effect of the medication <name type="other"/> takes for her hypertension although this is unlikely as the transient episodes would occur more frequently and would not be associated with hemiparesis or dysphagia), migraine, anaemia, focal epilepsy or hypoglycaemic attacks etc. </s></p><p n="p26.82"><s n="s1.1;p26.82"><name type="other"/> also has many of the risk factors applicable to carotid artery disease - raised cholesterol, hypertension, previous history of smoking, old age and limited mobility. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="bold">Physical examination</hi> Highlight the findings most relevant to your clinical problem solving by underlining them</head><div2><head rend="underlined bold">General Examination </head><p n="p27.82"><s n="s1.4;p27.82">On examination <name type="other"/> was sitting in a chair and looked comfortable and alert. <name type="other"/> had a walking stick by the side of the bed, there was no sputum pot or urine pot. </s><s n="s2.4;p27.82">There was no finger clubbing, palmar erythema, cyanosis of the fingers, leuchonychia or koilonychias. </s><s n="s3.4;p27.82">No mouth ulcerations, central cyanosis and no evidence of vitamin deficiencies. </s><s n="s4.4;p27.82">No lymphadenopathy. </s></p><list type="bulleted"><head rend="bold">General Observations</head><item>Pulse - 80 bpm regular</item><item>Blood Pressure - 140/75 (previous reading - 154/72)</item><item>Respiratory Rate - 16 pm</item><item>Temperature 36.5 C</item></list><p n="p28.82"><s n="s1.1;p28.82">Systems examination - information obtained from notes (patient requested not to be examined) </s></p><list type="simple"><head rend="underlined">CVS:</head><item>HS I + II + <hi rend="bold">loud systolic murmur which radiated to the carotids</hi></item><item>JVP →</item><item>No ankle oedema</item></list><list type="simple"><head rend="underlined">RS:</head><item>Clear vesicular breath sounds</item><item>Equal expansion</item><item>No added breath sounds</item><item>Air entry equal</item></list><list type="simple"><head rend="underlined">GI:</head><item>Abdomen soft and non-tender, no distension. Bowel sounds normal.</item><item>No masses or organomegaly.</item></list><list type="simple"><head rend="underlined">CNS </head><item>GCS 15/15</item><item>Grossly intact</item></list></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="bold">Analysis of history and examination</hi> Reasons for your choice of the cause of the patient's problem(s) and any other cause that still needs to be considered at this stage</head><p n="p29.82"><s n="s1.6;p29.82">From the history we know that the cause of <name type="other"/>'s TIA's is due to carotid artery stenosis. </s><s n="s2.6;p29.82">As previously mentioned, <name type="other"/> has many of the risk factors applicable to carotid artery disease and atheromatous plaque formation i.e. hypertension, history of smoking. </s><s n="s3.6;p29.82">Observations showed that <name type="other"/>'s blood pressure was stable at 140/75. <name type="other"/>'s heart rate was 80 bpm and regular no signs of atrial fibrillation as a possible cause of emboli. </s><s n="s4.6;p29.82">There was no evidence of anaemia from the general examination. </s><s n="s5.6;p29.82">Auscultation of the heart revealed an aortic stenosis which radiated to the carotid arteries. </s><s n="s6.6;p29.82">This is a possible site for cause of emboli, however mitral regurge is more commonly associated with production of emboli. <name type="other"/> was on statins indicating that she had a high cholesterol level - a risk factor for carotid artery disease. </s></p><p n="p30.82"><s n="s1.2;p30.82">Carotid artery stenosis can be exacerbated by co morbid conditions such as chronic lung and cardiac disease. </s><s n="s2.2;p30.82">This is because the physiological changes associated with such conditions can also limit oxygenation to the brain and can result in cerebral ischaemia in patients who would otherwise tolerate even high-grade carotid stenosis [1]. <name type="other"/>'s aortic stenosis may therefore be exacerbating her carotid artery stenosis. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="bold">Formulation of the patient's problem(s)</hi> Encapsulate this in physical, psychological and social terms (the triple diagnosis)</head><p n="p31.82"><s n="s1.4;p31.82"><name type="other"/> is an independent 84 year old lady who has been admitted for an elective Left Carotid Endartectomy. <name type="other"/> is a symptomatic case in the fact that she suffers from recurrent TIA's due to emboli produced from the stenosed carotid. <name type="other"/> has expressed a definite desire not to be resuscitated if the need should arise during the operation. <name type="other"/> is not concerned about the operation but feels that if she arrests it is her time to go. <name type="other"/> understands why the operation is needed and is aware of the possible risks and benefits. </s><s n="s2.4;p31.82">Although the emboli produced from the carotid have not yet left <name type="other"/> with any permanent physical abnormality (the weakness in her right arm has always recovered after her TIA) she is aware that there is risk of such an event occurring. </s><s n="s3.4;p31.82">Socially, <name type="other"/> may need extra help during her recovery period as she currently lives alone e.g. </s><s n="s4.4;p31.82">Daily home help or intermediate care may be required after discharge from the <name type="other"/> to assist <name type="other"/> with personal activities of daily living. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="bold">Management</hi> Use the framework of RAPRIOP to structure your proposed management. Refer to the guidelines to the writing of portfolio cases for the details of the issues to be addressed under each heading.</head><div2><head rend="underlined">Reassurance and explanation</head><p n="p32.82"><s n="s1.1;p32.82">Reassure the patient - <name type="other"/> was advised that the operation would be performed on her left carotid artery even though this had less of a stenosis as this was the side responsible for her symptoms. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">Investigations</head><list type="simple"><head rend="bold">Blood Tests (<name type="date"/>)</head><item>ESR 16, K 3.8, <hi rend="underlined">urea 9.3 (</hi>, Na 141, <hi rend="underlined">Creatinine 126 (,</hi> Prot 67, Alb 38, ALP 64, ALT 20, Glob 29, CRP &lt;4, Adj Ca 2.35, WBC 6.24, Neut 4.41, <hi rend="underlined">Hb 10.6 ↓</hi>, MCV 80.7, Plt 263</item></list><p n="p33.82"><s n="s1.1;p33.82">Comment - Raised creatinine and urea indicating reduced renal function or dehydration, Hb low indicating anaemia </s></p><p n="p34.82"><s n="s1.1;p34.82">Pre left carotid endartectomy check scan: </s></p><p n="p35.82"><s rend="bold" n="s1.1;p35.82">Transcranial Doppler Assessment and Carotid Ultrasound (<name type="date"/>) </s></p><p n="p36.82"><s n="s1.1;p36.82">Left Internal Carotid artery - moderate 2cm long plaque with <hi rend="bold">58% stenosis</hi> </s></p><p n="p37.82"><s n="s1.1;p37.82">Right Internal Carotid artery - moderate to severe 2cm long plaque with <hi rend="bold">68% stenosis</hi> </s></p><p n="p38.82"><s n="s1.1;p38.82">Pre operatively the left siphon was monitored transorbitally for 30 minutes with no emboli detected. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0203b-pic.001"><head><name type="other"/> Carotid Doppler</head></figure><figure id="BAWE_0203b-pic.002"/><p n="p39.82"><s n="s1.1;p39.82"><hi rend="bold">Comment</hi> : Although the right internal carotid artery showed a more significant stenosis than the left internal carotid artery, the decision was made to perform the endartectomy on the left artery as this was the side producing the emboli responsible for <name type="other"/>'s TIA's. <name type="other"/> was informed about the results of her Doppler assessment and understood the reasons for performing the operation on the left side rather than the right. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">Prescription/medical intervention</head><p n="p40.82"><s n="s1.1;p40.82">Operative <name type="date"/>: </s></p><p n="p41.82"><s rend="bold" n="s1.1;p41.82">Left Carotid Endarterectomy </s></p><p n="p42.82"><s n="s1.3;p42.82">Local anaesthetic - patient did not tolerate clamps to carotid and immediately lost consciousness when arteries were clamped. </s><s n="s2.3;p42.82">Consciousness returned on unclamping and operation therefore proceeded under general anaesthetic with a shunt sited in approximately 90 seconds. </s><s n="s3.3;p42.82">10 cm incision was made and an atheromatous plaque was removed. </s></p><list type="simple"><head>Post Op Plan:</head><item>Drain out tomorrow if not draining blood</item><item>Analgesia</item><item>Eat and drink tomorrow</item></list><p n="p43.82"><s n="s1.1;p43.82">Post operative: </s></p><p n="p44.82"><s n="s1.1;p44.82"><hi rend="bold">Post Operative Trans cranial Doppler -</hi> No emboli 30 minutes post op </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">Observation</head><p n="p45.82"><s rend="bold" n="s1.1;p45.82">PACU (post analgesic care unit): </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p46.82"><s n="s1.2;p46.82">(<name type="date"/>) <name type="other"/> had an episode of fainting and produced a small amount of vomit whilst in PACU. BP decreased but returned to 168/62. </s><s n="s2.2;p46.82">When on bed <name type="other"/> was awake and responsive. <name type="other"/> had a nasal cannula and face mask supplying oxygen. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p47.82"><s n="s1.1;p47.82">Fluid In 1500 </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p48.82"><s n="s1.1;p48.82">Fluid out 27 </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p49.82"><s n="s1.1;p49.82">Total Fluid +1230 </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p50.82"><s n="s1.2;p50.82">(<name type="date"/>) <name type="other"/> had a comfortable night. </s><s n="s2.2;p50.82">The nasal cannula and face mask were removed </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p51.82"><s n="s1.1;p51.82">O <hi rend="sub">2</hi> sats = 96-98% on air </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p52.82"><s n="s1.1;p52.82">BP 165/130 </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p53.82"><s n="s1.1;p53.82">HR 62-78 BPM </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p54.82"><s n="s1.1;p54.82">RR 11-15 PM </s></p><p n="p55.82"><s n="s1.3;p55.82">There was no oozing from the wound, <name type="other"/> had a redivac drain in situ and 50ml of blood had been drained from the wound. </s><s n="s2.3;p55.82">In the morning <name type="other"/> had a strip wash during which she went pale and said that she felt weak. <name type="other"/> then lost consciousness, her carotid pulses were assessed and her HR was found to be bradycardic. <name type="other"/> was seen by Mr <name type="other"/>. </s><s n="s3.3;p55.82">When <name type="other"/> returned to bed her BP was 190/60 and her HR was 50 BPM. <name type="other"/> was administered 12.5 mg Stemetil (IM) for nausea and vomiting. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">Referral and team working</head><p n="p56.82"><s n="s1.1;p56.82"><name type="other"/> was discharged from PACU to B2W for recovery and monitoring </s></p><p n="p57.82"><s n="s1.1;p57.82"><name type="date"/> </s></p><p n="p58.82"><s n="s1.1;p58.82"><name type="other"/> said that she felt well in herself although she had had an episode of dizziness. </s></p><p n="p59.82"><s n="s1.1;p59.82">BP 185/95, Mr <name type="other"/> advised to monitor over the weekend </s></p><p n="p60.82"><s n="s1.1;p60.82"><name type="date"/> </s></p><p n="p61.82"><s n="s1.2;p61.82"><name type="other"/> fainted again this morning - ? bruising to the carotid sinus during surgery. </s><s n="s2.2;p61.82">However, <name type="other"/> has had problems fainting in the past and so these episodes are probably not a result of the surgery. </s></p><p n="p62.82"><s n="s1.1;p62.82">Plan - lying and standing blood pressures to determine if the problem is postural hypotension </s></p><p n="p63.82"><s n="s1.1;p63.82"><name type="date"/> </s></p><p n="p64.82"><s n="s1.1;p64.82">General Observations: </s></p><p n="p65.82"><s n="s1.1;p65.82">Lying BP = 135/65, Standing BP = 79/45 </s></p><p n="p66.82"><s n="s1.2;p66.82">Comment - normally the blood pressure rises when standing up as a result of increased venous return due to venoconstriction to maintain cerebral perfusion. <name type="other"/>'s BP dropped significantly on standing, indicating that her dizziness is due to postural hypotension. </s><s n="s2.2;p66.82">This may be a side effect of her medication for hypertension and will require monitoring by her GP. </s></p><p n="p67.82"><s n="s1.1;p67.82">Temp 37.0, HR 90bpm, <name type="other"/> stated that was suffering from constipation and so lactulose and senna were prescribed. </s></p><p n="p68.82"><s n="s1.1;p68.82">Plan - Encourage <name type="other"/> to eat and drink, contact cardiologist to review <name type="other"/> </s></p><p n="p69.82"><s n="s1.1;p69.82"><name type="date"/> </s></p><p n="p70.82"><s n="s1.2;p70.82"><name type="other"/> seen by cardiologist who suggested that <name type="other"/> had idiopathic postural hypotension. </s><s n="s2.2;p70.82">It was suggested that <name type="other"/>'s hypertensive medication be stopped and that <name type="other"/> should be kept under observation. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">Advice and Prevention</head><p n="p71.82"><s n="s1.1;p71.82"><name type="other"/> was provided with TED stockings to prevent DVT formation. <name type="other"/> was informed about her discharge plan and was initially reluctant to accept the idea of extra assistance when she returns home, however she quickly changed her mind about this and was pleased that staff were trying to arrange an intermediate care bed assessment for her initial discharge. <name type="other"/>'s relative had managed to organise 1 week's respite care in a local nursing home and <name type="other"/> was discharged from the <name type="other"/>. </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="bold">Outcome</hi> A description of the progress of the patient as far as possible. This should include consideration of further issues to be resolved. Where appropriate you should contact by telephone patients who have been discharged home.</head><p n="p72.82"><s n="s1.6;p72.82"><name type="other"/> has now been discharged from the <name type="other"/> and is due to be reviewed by Mr <name type="other"/> at his outpatient clinic in <name type="other"/> in 4-6 weeks. <name type="other"/>'s GP has been informed about her postural hypotension and will review <name type="other"/> in the first week of discharge. </s><s n="s2.6;p72.82">Clips were removed day 8 post op (<name type="other"/>). </s><s n="s3.6;p72.82">The carotid ultrasound on <name type="date"/> showed that the right asymptomatic carotid artery had a greater stenosis than the left symptomatic carotid artery. </s><s n="s4.6;p72.82">Future issues for consideration point at the need to operate on the right carotid artery. <name type="other"/> is an old lady who has suffered with post operative morbidity due to problems with her blood pressure. </s><s n="s5.6;p72.82">Surgery on an asymptomatic carotid artery is therefore not advised in <name type="other"/>'s current physical condition. <name type="other"/> herself is also not keen to have further surgery. </s><s n="s6.6;p72.82">The stenosis will be monitored through Mr <name type="other"/>'s clinic and should <name type="other"/> suffer with any symptoms from her right carotid artery then it is likely that surgery will be indicated. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="bold">Evidence based care and issues for research</hi> A brief consideration of the evidence base required for the diagnosis and management of the patient's problem(s)</head><p n="p73.82"><s n="s1.3;p73.82">Major studies have shown the benefits of carotid endarterectomy as compared to medical therapy in symptomatic patients with a carotid artery stenosis of 70% or greater - with only eight carotid endarterectomies needed to prevent one stroke in symptomatic patients. </s><s n="s2.3;p73.82">Carotid endarterectomy has been shown to reduce the risk of disabling stroke or death in patients with stenosis exceeding 70% (ECST) or 50% (NASCET) [1]. </s><s n="s3.3;p73.82">However, this result is only applicable to surgically-fit patients operated on by surgeons with low complication rates (less than 6%) (Cochrane). </s></p><p n="p74.82"><s n="s1.4;p74.82">The optimum time for surgery in these patients is 2 weeks after the patients last symptoms, however, the chance of a patient being admitted for theatre within this time period is minimal. </s><s n="s2.4;p74.82">Trans cranial Doppler is used to assess microemboli, a high load of which is associated with early carotid thrombosis and increased risk of stroke. </s><s n="s3.4;p74.82">The <name type="other"/> hospital cardiovascular unit has pioneered a treatment for recurrent TIA's which involves the administration of trans-cranial directed anti platelet drugs to control the number of micro emboli. </s><s n="s4.4;p74.82">This treatment aims to reduce the risk of stroke until the patient can be treated safely on the next surgical elective list [2]. </s></p><p n="p75.82"><s n="s1.8;p75.82">Initially <name type="other"/>'s operation was performed under local anaesthetic, unfortunately this had to be changed to general anaesthetic as <name type="other"/> lost consciousness once the arteries were clamped. </s><s n="s2.8;p75.82">Local anesthesia has the advantage of allowing direct evaluation of the patient's neurologic status without sophisticated monitoring. </s><s n="s3.8;p75.82">This enables the surgeon to operate on the majority of patients without the need for a shunt which may pose an increased risk of stroke to the patient. </s><s n="s4.8;p75.82">General anaesthesia has the advantage of improved airway control and patient comfort during prolonged operations. </s><s n="s5.8;p75.82">However, it does require the use of routine or selected shunting, and selective shunting requires the use of some form of cerebral monitoring to assess the need for a shunt i.e. transcranial Doppler. </s><s n="s6.8;p75.82">There is insufficient evidence from randomised controlled trials comparing carotid endarterectomy performed under local and general anaesthetic [3]. </s><s n="s7.8;p75.82">Evidence from non-randomised studies suggests potential benefits with the use of local anaesthetic. </s><s n="s8.8;p75.82">This is a potential area for future research and randomised studies [3]. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="bold">Commentary</hi> A commentary on issues of epidemiology, psycho-social, health care delivery, ethical issues or disability relevant to the patient and/or problem</head><p n="p76.82"><s n="s1.3;p76.82">Epidemiology - There are approximately 130,000 strokes per year in England and Wales of which approximately 15-25% are caused by an abnormally narrow carotid artery [2]. </s><s n="s2.3;p76.82">It is estimated that approx 10% of people > 80 years &amp; 5/1000 aged 50-60 yrs have a carotid artery stenosis > than 50% [4]. </s><s n="s3.3;p76.82">The more severe the stenosis the greater the risk of a stroke and permanent disability for the patient [4]. </s></p><p n="p77.82"><s n="s1.2;p77.82">The risk factors associated with carotid artery disease have been mentioned previously. </s><s n="s2.2;p77.82">Patients with high risk factors should be encouraged to reduce their risk factors e.g. through smoking cessation programs and dietary advice. </s></p><p n="p78.82"><s n="s1.4;p78.82">In <name type="other"/>'s case, the right internal carotid artery showed a more significant stenosis than the left internal carotid artery. </s><s n="s2.4;p78.82">However, the decision was made to perform the endartectomy on the left as this was the side producing the emboli responsible for <name type="other"/>'s TIA's. </s><s n="s3.4;p78.82">The left artery posed a greater problem for <name type="other"/> in terms of future disability as there was a greater risk of stroke from this side. </s><s n="s4.4;p78.82">It is important that patients receive adequate explanation and reassurance as to the reasons for surgery particularly if as in <name type="other"/>'s case there are differing degrees of stenosis. </s></p><p n="p79.82"><s n="s1.3;p79.82">Ethical issues of non resuscitation - <name type="other"/> requested not to be resuscitated if the need arose during the operation. </s><s n="s2.3;p79.82">Patient requests for non resuscitation should always be documented in the patient's notes. </s><s n="s3.3;p79.82">The patient may already have an advance directive a copy of which will need to be obtained. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="bold">Impact on your learning</hi> Describe what you have learnt from this case</head><p n="p80.82"><s n="s1.1;p80.82">Indications for surgery - asymptomatic and symptomatic patients </s></p><p n="p81.82"><s n="s1.1;p81.82">Use of transcranial Doppler ultrasound as a means of monitoring emboli production from the atheromatous plaque, pre, peri and post operatively. </s></p><p n="p82.82"><s n="s1.1;p82.82">Use of long term medical management of a patient with a symptomatic carotid artery stenosis. </s></p></div1></body><back><div1 type="bibliography"><head>References</head><p>[1] Rerkasem K, Bond R, Rothwell PM. Local versus general anaesthesia for carotid endarterectomy. The Cochrane Database of Systematic Reviews 2004, Issue 2.</p><p>[2] <seg type="URL" n="http://www.christopherimray.co.uk/arterialsurgery/carotidarterydisease.htm"/></p><p>[3] Rerkasem K, Bond R, Rothwell PM. Local versus general anaesthesia for carotid endarterectomy. The Cochrane Database of Systematic Reviews 2004, Issue 2.</p><p>[4] eMedicine-Carotid Artery Stenosis: Lennard A Nadalo, <hi rend="bold">http</hi>://<seg type="URL" n="www.emedicine.com/radio/topic133.htm"/></p></div1><div1 type="appendix"><head rend="bold">ASPECTS OF CASE AS RECORDED IN SUMMARY OF PORTFOLIO CASES•</head><p/></div1><div1 type="appendix"><head rend="bold">PORTFOLIO COMPLETION CERTIFICATE</head><p/></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
