<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_0203i" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Portfolio Case presentation number: Crohns Disease</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">proforma</note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">appendices: 	ASPECTS OF CASE AS RECORDED IN SUMMARY OF PORTFOLIO CASES, PORTFOLIO COMPLETION CERTIFICATE</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">4</p><p n="date">2005-10</p><p n="module title">Other rotations</p><p n="module code">unknown</p><p n="genre family">Case study</p><p n="discipline">Medicine</p><p n="disciplinary group">LS</p><p n="grade">D</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">3683</p><p n="number of s-units">186</p><p n="number of p">96</p><p n="number of tables">1</p><p n="number of figures">0</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">12</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">9</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">19.8</p><p n="average s-units per p">1.9</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">f</p><p n="year of birth">1979</p><p n="first language">English</p><p n="education">UKA</p><p n="course">Medicine</p><p n="student ID">0203</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><docTitle><titlePart rend="bold">PORTFOLIO CASE No:</titlePart></docTitle><titlePart>Patient Initials<name type="other"/> Hospital Number Age 23 Gender Female</titlePart><titlePart>Portfolio Case presentation number: Phase 2 course document objectives(s) Has the patient' permission, including for follow up contact by telephone, been sought and recorded in the case notes?</titlePart></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="bold">Referral information</hi> Source of referral and a summary of key information</head><p n="p1.96"><s n="s1.1;p1.96">Elective admission on <name type="date"/>, <name type="other"/> is known to have Crohns Disease </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="bold">History</hi> All <hi rend="bold italic">relevant</hi> information gathered from the patient about the presenting illness, co-existing problems, current treatment, <hi rend="italic">significant</hi> past medical history and the social and family background. The patient's view of the nature of the problem and their expectations for treatment.</head><div2><head rend="underlined bold">Presenting Complaint</head><p rend="bulleted" n="p2.96"><s n="s1.1;p2.96"><name type="other"/> is known to have Crohns Disease, she was admitted to B1W electively with a 2 week history of diarrhoea and abdominal pain </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined bold">History of presenting complaint</head><p n="p3.96"><s n="s1.2;p3.96"><name type="other"/> was diagnosed with Crohns Disease in 1989. <name type="other"/>'s symptoms are normally well controlled by her medication, however, over the past 12 months her symptoms have been getting progressively worse and she has been having an increase in flare ups of her Crohns disease, her last admission was in <name type="date"/> 2005 when she was placed on steroids. </s><s n="s2.2;p3.96">Over the past 2 weeks, <name type="other"/> has experienced: </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p4.96"><s n="s1.2;p4.96">Abdominal pain - <name type="other"/> described the pain as being sharp and localised to the LIF and RUQ. The pain was rated at 6/10 for intensity. </s><s n="s2.2;p4.96">The pain was not constant lasting for only a few seconds and <name type="other"/> did not take anything to relieve the pain. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p5.96"><s n="s1.2;p5.96">Diarrhoea - Increased frequency (5-6 times day), no malaena or rectal bleeding. </s><s n="s2.2;p5.96">Stools are loose, contain mucous and are of normal colour, they do not float and are not foul smelling. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p6.96"><s n="s1.1;p6.96">Lethargy - <name type="other"/> felt she has had approx 60% of her normal energy levels over the past 2 weeks. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p7.96"><s n="s1.1;p7.96">Loss of appetite and weight loss - <name type="other"/> has lost one stone in weight over the past 2-3 months </s></p><p n="p8.96"><s n="s1.4;p8.96">There has been occasional vomiting of bile and food mainly in the evening. </s><s n="s2.4;p8.96">There is no dysphagia. </s><s n="s3.4;p8.96">There is no arthralgia, no skin or eye symptoms and no mouth ulcers. </s><s n="s4.4;p8.96">There has been no recent foreign travel no identifiable dietary triggers and no exposure to anyone with similar symptoms. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined bold">Past Medical History</head><list type="bulleted"><head rend="bold">Medical</head><item>No Asthma</item><item>No Diabetes Mellitus</item><item>No angina</item><item>No hypertension</item><item>No epilepsy</item><item>No DVT/PE</item></list><p n="p9.96"><s rend="bold" n="s1.1;p9.96">Surgical </s></p><p n="p10.96"><s n="s1.1;p10.96">Mole removed from neck </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined bold">Social History</head><p n="p11.96"><s n="s1.1;p11.96"><name type="other"/> is a 23 year old lady who works as a project administrator. <name type="other"/> has never smoked and drinks alcohol occasionally. <name type="other"/> has 1 sister who is 18 months younger, they both live with their parents. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined bold">Allergies</head><p n="p12.96"><s n="s1.1;p12.96">NKA </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined bold">Medication</head><p n="p13.96"><s n="s1.1;p13.96">Azathioprine 50 mg OD Immunosuppressant, modifies lymphocyte and plasma cell function </s></p><p n="p14.96"><s n="s1.1;p14.96">Mesalazine 400 mg PO BD Aminosalicylate - stimulates prostaglandins and inhibits leukotrienes, scavenges free radicals and inhibits Interleukin 1 release </s></p><p n="p15.96"><s n="s1.1;p15.96">Infliximab every 2 months Chimeric Antibody, has anti TNF alpha action </s></p><p n="p16.96"><s n="s1.1;p16.96">Metronidazole 400 mg PO BD </s></p><p n="p17.96"><s n="s1.1;p17.96">Antibiotic used in the treatment of inflammation in active Crohns (also used for treatment of perianal involvement at lower dose 0.6-1.5g) </s></p><p n="p18.96"><s n="s1.1;p18.96">Side Effect = peripheral neuropathy </s></p><p n="p19.96"><s n="s1.1;p19.96">Ciprofloxacin 500 mg PO BD Antibiotic used in the treatment of inflammation in active Crohns </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined bold">Family History</head><p n="p20.96"><s n="s1.1;p20.96">No significant family history </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined bold">Systems Review</head><p n="p21.96"><s rend="bold" n="s1.1;p21.96">Cardiovascular system </s></p><p n="p22.96"><s n="s1.1;p22.96">No chest pain, orthopnoea or PND. No peripheral oedema. </s></p><p n="p23.96"><s rend="bold" n="s1.1;p23.96">Respiratory System </s></p><p n="p24.96"><s n="s1.2;p24.96">No shortness of breath or wheeze. </s><s n="s2.2;p24.96">No cough or haemoptysis. </s></p><p n="p25.96"><s rend="bold" n="s1.1;p25.96">Gastrointestinal System </s></p><p n="p26.96"><s n="s1.1;p26.96">As history of presenting complaint, <name type="other"/> maintains a low fibre diet. </s></p><p n="p27.96"><s rend="bold" n="s1.1;p27.96">Genitourinary System </s></p><p n="p28.96"><s n="s1.2;p28.96">No change in urinary frequency, no incontinence (stress/urge). </s><s n="s2.2;p28.96">No change to menstrual cycle. </s></p><p n="p29.96"><s rend="bold" n="s1.1;p29.96">Central Nervous System </s></p><p n="p30.96"><s n="s1.1;p30.96">No headaches, blackouts or visual disturbances. </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="bold">Analysis of history</hi> The most likely single cause of the presentation, other possible causes and reasons for these choices. The findings to be looked for on physical examination to help decide the cause.</head><p n="p31.96"><s n="s1.3;p31.96">Impression - <name type="other"/> is a 23 year old lady who was diagnosed with Crohns Disease at the age of 7. </s><s n="s2.3;p31.96">Her symptoms have been well controlled by the medication. </s><s n="s3.3;p31.96">However over the past 12 months, <name type="other"/> has noticed that her symptoms have become progressively worse with a marked increase in severity over the past 2 weeks. <name type="other"/> presented with classic signs of exacerbation of her Crohns; 2 week history of diarrhoea, abdominal pain in the RIF and LUQ and weight loss. </s></p><p n="p32.96"><s n="s1.2;p32.96">The abdominal pain may be caused by inflammation and spasm of the small/large intestine during an acute exacerbation of Crohns. </s><s n="s2.2;p32.96">It may also be due to stricture formation as seen in chronic disease. </s></p><p n="p33.96"><s n="s1.1;p33.96">The diarrhoea <name type="other"/> is experiencing may be due to a number of factors linked with her Crohns: </s></p><list type="bulleted"><item>Bacterial overgrowth (due to obstructive stricture/fistula)</item><item>Proctitis - impaired sphincter function and frequent passage of watery stools with mucous</item><item>Decreased water absorption due to colonic involvement</item><item>Decreased bile acid absorption in the terminal ileum</item><item>Stenosis e.g. rectal - causing constipation with overflow diarrhoea</item></list><p n="p34.96"><s n="s1.1;p34.96">Drug induced and infective causes of diarrhoea must also be excluded in patients with Crohns Disease. </s></p><p n="p35.96"><s n="s1.4;p35.96"><hi rend="bold">Infective -</hi> There are many infective causes for diarrhoea e.g. </s><s n="s2.4;p35.96">S. Aureus, E Coli and Salmonella, Rotavirus and Norwalk virus. </s><s n="s3.4;p35.96">Most infective causes of diarrhoea are acute and symptoms tend to resolve within 72 hours. </s><s n="s4.4;p35.96">Signs to look for on examination include: </s></p><list type="bulleted"><item>signs of dehydration - dry mucosa, decreased skin turgor</item><item>tachycardia</item><item>fever</item></list><p n="p36.96"><s n="s1.5;p36.96"><hi rend="bold">Drug Induced (pseudomembranous colitis)</hi> - antibiotics e.g. </s><s n="s2.5;p36.96">Penicillins, Clindomycin and aminoglycosides can reduce the normal flora of the gut. </s><s n="s3.5;p36.96">This enables normal gut organisms such as Clostridium Difficile to grow. </s><s n="s4.5;p36.96">C Difficile produces a toxin which causes inflammation and necrosis of colonic mucosa resulting in diarrhoea. <name type="other"/> had no evidence of such drug use in the past month from her history. </s><s n="s5.5;p36.96">Signs to look for on examination include distended abdomen with generalised tenderness. </s></p><p n="p37.96"><s n="s1.1;p37.96">There are three main subgroups of Crohns Disease: </s></p><list type="bulleted"><item>Fistula pattern</item><item>Stricture pattern</item><item>Diarrhoea pattern</item></list><p n="p38.96"><s n="s1.3;p38.96">The fistula pattern of presentation leads to formation of penetrating sinuses with fistula or abscess formation. </s><s n="s2.3;p38.96">The types of fistula that can form are: entero-enteric (between adjacent lops of bowel), enterogastric (between bowel and stomach), enterovesical (between bowel and bladder), enterocutaneous (between bowel and skin). </s><s n="s3.3;p38.96">The stricture pattern produces postprandial abdominal pain with constipation. </s></p><p n="p39.96"><s n="s1.3;p39.96">The locations of the abdominal pain point to pathology in the colon, <name type="other"/> may have developed strictures in these regions. </s><s n="s2.3;p39.96">Stricture formation may also explain the occasional vomiting that <name type="other"/> has experienced and the colicky abdominal pain. </s><s n="s3.3;p39.96">However one of the main symptoms <name type="other"/> experiences is diarrhoea. </s></p><div2><head rend="underlined">Differential Diagnoses for presenting symptoms:</head><p n="p40.96"><s n="s1.3;p40.96"><hi rend="bold">Inflammatory Bowel Disease -</hi> There are 2 main types of Inflammatory Bowel Disease - Crohns and Ulcerative Colitis (UC). </s><s n="s2.3;p40.96">Signs to look for on examination include markers of chronic disease e.g. clubbing, koilonychia, leukonychia, mouth ulcers, weight loss etc. </s><s n="s3.3;p40.96">Inflammatory bowel disease is also associated with systemic manifestations e.g. rashes, arthralgia, conjunctivitis etc and so these should also be looked for on examination. <name type="other"/> did not report any blood in her stools which is more indicative of Crohns rather than Ulcerative Colitis which is associated with bloody diarrhoea. </s></p><p n="p41.96"><s n="s1.4;p41.96"><hi rend="bold">Infective -</hi> There are many infective causes for diarrhoea e.g. </s><s n="s2.4;p41.96">S. Aureus, E Coli and Salmonella, Rotavirus and Norwalk virus. </s><s n="s3.4;p41.96">Most infective causes of diarrhoea are acute and symptoms tend to resolve within 72 hours. </s><s n="s4.4;p41.96">Signs to look for on examination include: </s></p><list type="bulleted"><item>signs of dehydration - dry mucosa, decreased skin turgor</item><item>tachycardia</item><item>fever</item></list><p n="p42.96"><s n="s1.5;p42.96"><hi rend="bold">Drug Induced (pseudomembranous colitis)</hi> - antibiotics e.g. </s><s n="s2.5;p42.96">Penicillins, Clindomycin and aminoglycosides can reduce the normal flora of the gut. </s><s n="s3.5;p42.96">This enables normal gut organisms such as Clostridium Difficile to grow. </s><s n="s4.5;p42.96">C. Difficile produces a toxin which causes inflammation and necrosis of colonic mucosa resulting in diarrhoea. <name type="other"/> had no evidence of such drug use in the past month from her history. </s><s n="s5.5;p42.96">Signs to look for on examination include distended abdomen with generalised tenderness. </s></p><p n="p43.96"><s rend="bold" n="s1.1;p43.96">Malabsorption - </s></p><p n="p44.96"><s n="s1.1;p44.96">Coeliac Disease - inflammation of the mucosa of the small bowel due to gluten intolerance abdo pain, nausea and vomiting, steatorrhoea, </s></p><p n="p45.96"><s n="s1.3;p45.96"><hi rend="bold">Endocrine</hi> - Diarrhoea can be a symptom of some endocrine disorders e.g. hyperthryoidism, Diabetes. </s><s n="s2.3;p45.96">It is therefore important to look further symptoms associated with these disorders in order to exclude them as a differential e.g. </s><s n="s3.3;p45.96">Hyperthyroidism - sweaty palm, exopthalmus, fine tremor, goitre </s></p><p n="p46.96"><s rend="bold" n="s1.1;p46.96">Irritable Bowel Syndrome </s></p><p n="p47.96"><s n="s1.3;p47.96">This is the most common functional bowel disorder. </s><s n="s2.3;p47.96">Criteria for diagnosis state that ' in the past 12 months there should be at least 12 weeks of abdominal discomfort/pain with 2 out of 3 of the following - relieved with defaecation, onset associated with change in stool freq, onset associated with change in stool form'. </s><s n="s3.3;p47.96">If no other explanation can be found for this patients symptoms, patient follow up will determine whether they suffer from this condition. </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="bold">Physical examination</hi> Highlight the findings most relevant to your clinical problem solving by underlining them</head><div2><head>Examination on admission:</head><list type="bulleted"><head rend="underlined bold">General Observations</head><item>Pulse - 100 bpm</item><item>Blood Pressure - 85/55</item><item>Respiratory Rate - 20 pm</item><item>Temperature 35.0 C</item></list><p n="p48.96"><s n="s1.1;p48.96">Weight - 40Kg Height - 162.56cm BMI - 15.27 (underweight) </s></p><p n="p49.96"><s rend="underlined" n="s1.1;p49.96">General Examination </s></p><p n="p50.96"><s n="s1.1;p50.96"><name type="other"/> appeared pale and underweight </s></p><p n="p51.96"><s rend="underlined" n="s1.1;p51.96">GI: </s></p><p n="p52.96"><s n="s1.3;p52.96">The abdomen was soft and non-tender. </s><s n="s2.3;p52.96">There was no guarding or rebound tenderness. </s><s n="s3.3;p52.96">Bowel sounds present. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined"><hi rend="bold">General Examination</hi> <hi rend="bold"><name type="date"/></hi></head><p n="p53.96"><s n="s1.3;p53.96">On examination <name type="other"/> was comfortable and alert at rest. </s><s n="s2.3;p53.96">There was no jaundice or anaemia, there was no cervical lymphadenopathy and no palpable supraclavicular nodes. </s><s n="s3.3;p53.96">There was no clubbing or koilonychias and no signs of dehydration. <name type="other"/> appeared to have a 'moon face' consistent with Cushings syndrome. </s></p><list type="bulleted"><head rend="bold">General Observations</head><item>Pulse - 65 bpm</item><item>Blood Pressure - 110/75</item><item>Respiratory Rate - 14 pm</item><item>Temperature 35.0 C</item></list><p n="p54.96"><s rend="underlined" n="s1.1;p54.96">GI: </s></p><p n="p55.96"><s n="s1.3;p55.96">Inspection - The abdomen moved with respiration. </s><s n="s2.3;p55.96">There were no obvious scars, masses or visible peristalsis. </s><s n="s3.3;p55.96">The abdomen was not distended. </s></p><p n="p56.96"><s n="s1.2;p56.96">Palpation - The abdomen was soft and non-tender. </s><s n="s2.2;p56.96">There was no guarding or peritonism and there were no palpable masses or organomegaly </s></p><p n="p57.96"><s n="s1.1;p57.96">Percussion - resonant </s></p><p n="p58.96"><s n="s1.1;p58.96">Auscultation - bowel sounds present </s></p><list type="simple"><head rend="underlined">CVS:</head><item>No scars or deformities. HS I + II + 0 </item><item>JVP →</item><item>CRT &lt; 2 secs</item></list><list type="simple"><head rend="underlined">RS:</head><item>Clear vesicular breath sounds</item><item>Expansion R = L</item></list><p n="p59.96"><s rend="underlined" n="s1.1;p59.96">CNS </s></p><p n="p60.96"><s n="s1.1;p60.96">GCS 15/15 </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="bold">Analysis of history and examination</hi> Reasons for your choice of the cause of the patient's problem(s) and any other cause that still needs to be considered at this stage</head><p n="p61.96"><s n="s1.3;p61.96">There were no significant findings on examination. </s><s n="s2.3;p61.96">Given the history, the most likely diagnosis is a flare up of <name type="other"/>'s Crohns. </s><s n="s3.3;p61.96">The presence of inflammation, obstruction, abscess, and fistula should be investigated to determine the type of Crohns that <name type="other"/> has i.e. is there any stricture formation as a cause of <name type="other"/>'s nausea and colicky abdominal pain, as this will help to tailor her management. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="bold">Formulation of the patient's problem(s)</hi> Encapsulate this in physical, psychological and social terms (the triple diagnosis)</head><div2><head><hi rend="underlined">Physically</hi> - </head><p n="p62.96"><s n="s1.4;p62.96"><hi rend="italic">Short Term:</hi> Over the past 2 weeks <name type="other"/> has experienced a loss of appetite and consequent weight loss and lethargy. <name type="other"/> will benefit from nutritional supplements to improve her energy levels and may require intravenous fluids if she is dehydrated due to the diarrhoea. </s><s n="s2.4;p62.96">Pain relief is difficult in patients with inflammatory bowel disease, NSAIDS can themselves cause gastric irritation and colitis, opioid analgesics can cause constipation with a risk of obstruction. </s><s n="s3.4;p62.96">If pain cannot be managed with paracetamol, Tramadol displays fewer opioid side effects and is less likely to cause constipation. </s><s n="s4.4;p62.96">Patients who are placed on such medication should be closely monitored for signs of constipation. </s></p><p n="p63.96"><s n="s1.2;p63.96"><hi rend="italic">Long Term:</hi> It appears that medical therapy is no longer controlling <name type="other"/>'s symptoms and so there may be an indication for surgery, this could be in the form of a stricturoplasty to widen any strictures, closure of any fistula's or resection of the affected part of the bowel. </s><s n="s2.2;p63.96">Also the continual use of steroids to control <name type="other"/>'s flare ups increases her risk of oseteoporosis and proximal myopathy, she is also at risk of Cushings syndrome (moon face, striae, acne, thin skin, bruising, buffalo hump, poor wound healing). </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">Psychologically </head><p n="p64.96"><s n="s1.5;p64.96">Psychologically <name type="other"/> appeared to be in good spirits. </s><s n="s2.5;p64.96">Crohns Disease is a chronic condition with a relapsing/remitting nature. </s><s n="s3.5;p64.96">Such illnesses pose a threat to an individual's quality of life, their physical and emotional well being, social functioning and self-esteem. </s><s n="s4.5;p64.96">It is important that doctors listen to their patients concerns so that their condition can be managed appropriately. </s><s n="s5.5;p64.96">The option of surgery was mentioned approximately 6 months prior to admission, however, <name type="other"/> opted to try and control her symptoms with medication to avoid the need for surgery. <name type="other"/> is now keen to discuss surgery as she feels the medication is no longer controlling her symptoms. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">Socially </head><p n="p65.96"><s n="s1.2;p65.96">If surgery is discussed it is important that <name type="other"/> understands the implications of the proposed procedure. <name type="other"/> may require a stoma post surgery and she will require time off work for recovery. </s><s n="s2.2;p65.96">Referral to a stoma nurse and inflammatory bowel nurse specialist should also be made. </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="bold">Management</hi> Use the framework of RAPRIOP to structure your proposed management. Refer to the guidelines to the writing of portfolio cases for the details of the issues to be addressed under each heading.</head><div2><head rend="underlined">Investigations:</head><div3><head rend="bold">Blood Tests</head><list type="bulleted"><head>Why</head><item>FBC - for Iron deficiency anaemia - B12, Folate or Iron deficiency (microcytic), Normochromic normocytic (anaemia of chronic disease). Hypoalbuminaemia in severe illness. Platelets</item><item>Urea and Electrolytes - for raised Urea and low Na due to dehydration and loss of NaHCO3 from the diarrhoea. </item><item>ESR - inflammatory marker may be raised if there is inflammation </item><item>CRP - may be raised if the cause of her diarrhoea is infection</item></list><table id="BAWE_0203i-tab.001"><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p66.96"><s n="s1.3;p66.96">The blood results show that <name type="other"/> has hypochromic anaemia, which is associated with chronic disease. <name type="other"/> also has low total protein and albumin indicating that she is malnourished, probably due to the decrease in appetite and the history of diarrhoea. </s><s n="s2.3;p66.96">The CRP and ESR are also raised indicating an inflammatory process. </s><s n="s3.3;p66.96">ESR is more likely to be raised in Crohns colitis. </s></p></div3><div3><head rend="bold">Rectal Examination</head><p n="p67.96"><s n="s1.1;p67.96">Why - for presence of blood - unlikely as <name type="other"/> is diagnosed with Crohns Disease and Ulcerative Colitis if more commonly associated with bloody diarrhoea. </s></p></div3><div3><head rend="bold">Stool Culture and Microscopy </head><p n="p68.96"><s n="s1.2;p68.96">Why - presence of bacterial pathogens, cysts, ova and parasites as infective causes. </s><s n="s2.2;p68.96">Presence of leukocytes to indicate inflammatory cause. </s></p></div3><div3><head rend="bold">Abdominal X-ray</head><p n="p69.96"><s n="s1.1;p69.96">Why - to look for evidence of a dilated colon which is a medical emergency as there is risk of perforation </s></p></div3><div3><head rend="bold">Flexible Sigmoidoscopy</head><p n="p70.96"><s n="s1.1;p70.96">Why - To look for evidence of disease activity. </s></p></div3><div3><head rend="bold">Barium Follow Through</head><p n="p71.96"><s n="s1.1;p71.96">Why - used to evaluate the extent and severity of the disease in the small bowel indicated by e.g. rose thorn ulceration, cobblestone pattern (transverse and longitudinal ulceration separating oedematous areas of mucosa), thickened separated loops of oedematous bowel, skip lesions (fissuring with intervening normal mucosa), stricture and fistula. </s></p></div3><div3><head rend="bold">Colonoscopy</head><p n="p72.96"><s n="s1.2;p72.96">Why - Visualise the mucosa and look for presence of strictures, ulceration. </s><s n="s2.2;p72.96">Colonoscopy is more invasive than flexible sigmoidoscopy and so is only used in patients where the extent of the disease is unknown or in patients who are at increased risk of carcinoma. </s></p></div3></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">Results</head><p n="p73.96"><s n="s1.1;p73.96">Barium Follow Through <name type="date"/>: Normal small intestine </s></p><p n="p74.96"><s n="s1.2;p74.96">Colonoscopy Report <name type="date"/>: Crohns disease affecting large intestine from caecum to the rectum. </s><s n="s2.2;p74.96">Colonic <hi rend="bold">strictures</hi> identified and dilated at colonoscopy. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">Reassurance and explanation</head><p n="p75.96"><s n="s1.8;p75.96"><name type="other"/> as you aware your Crohns disease is becoming difficult to manage with medication. </s><s n="s2.8;p75.96">The frequency of your flare-ups has increased indicating that your current treatment regime is not controlling your Crohns. </s><s n="s3.8;p75.96">Colonoscopy also showed that some strictures have formed in your colon as a result of your Crohns Disease and these are the most likely cause of the recent pain you have been experiencing. </s><s n="s4.8;p75.96">We were able to dilate the strictures during the procedure so that your bowel contents were able to pass through more easily. </s><s n="s5.8;p75.96">However, given your current symptoms, it is likely that these strictures have reformed. </s><s n="s6.8;p75.96">We have discussed the option of surgery previously and you were keen to try and control you symptoms with medication. </s><s n="s7.8;p75.96">It appears that you are no longer responding to the treatment that we can offer to you and the current level of activity of your Crohns is resulting in you being malnourished. </s><s n="s8.8;p75.96">We therefore feel that it is appropriate to offer you the option of surgery. </s></p><p n="p76.96"><s n="s1.5;p76.96">Surgery would involve removing the affected part of your colon, one end of your bowel would be brought out onto the skin of the abdominal wall. </s><s n="s2.5;p76.96">This is called a colostomy and the opening of the bowel is known as a stoma. </s><s n="s3.5;p76.96">Your bowel motions would pass through the stoma into a colostomy bag which is worn over the stoma. </s><s n="s4.5;p76.96">If we need to remove a large amount of your bowel the colostomy may be permanent. </s><s n="s5.5;p76.96">We can ask the stoma nurses to come and see you before the operation to talk through this with you in more detail. </s></p><p n="p77.96"><s n="s1.1;p77.96">Are there any questions? </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">Prescription/medical intervention </head><p rend="bulleted" n="p78.96"><s n="s1.1;p78.96">Anaemia - <name type="other"/> had 3 units of blood transfused to correct her low Hb </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p79.96"><s n="s1.1;p79.96">Nutrition - <name type="other"/> had been maintaining a low fibre diet, she was referred to a dietician who prescribed Fortijuice 200ml TDS to help with her malnourishment and to correct her low albumin and protein levels </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p80.96"><s n="s1.1;p80.96">Commenced on Oral Prednisolone 30 mg OD </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p81.96"><s n="s1.1;p81.96">Listed for surgery </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">Observation</head><p n="p82.96"><s n="s1.1;p82.96"><name type="other"/> was eating and drinking well during admission. </s></p><p n="p83.96"><s n="s1.1;p83.96">Normal daily observations were made (blood pressure, temperature, pulse, respiratory rate) </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">Referral and team working</head><list type="bulleted"><item>Surgeons</item><item>Dieticians</item><item>Stoma nurse</item><item>Inflammatory bowel nurse specialist</item></list><p n="p84.96"/></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="bold">Outcome</hi> A description of the progress of the patient as far as possible. This should include consideration of further issues to be resolved. Where appropriate you should contact by telephone patients who have been discharged home.</head><p n="p85.96"><s n="s1.1;p85.96"><name type="other"/> had a subtotal colectomy, she recovered well from the operation and was coping with the stoma. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="bold">Evidence based care and issues for research</hi> A brief consideration of the evidence base required for the diagnosis and management of the patient's problem(s)</head><p n="p86.96"><s n="s1.3;p86.96">Crohns disease is a chronic condition that requires repeated treatment either medical or surgical. </s><s n="s2.3;p86.96">The main role of all treatment is to minimise symptoms and delay or prevent relapse. </s><s n="s3.3;p86.96">Due to the relapsing nature of the disease, the effect of treatment on the patients quality of life is an important factor in deciding on acute alterations to medical treatment or surgical intervention. </s></p><p n="p87.96"><s n="s1.8;p87.96">Current medical therapy involves the use of steroids which still provide the quickest and most reliable response to active Crohns. </s><s n="s2.8;p87.96">However, due to the relapsing nature of the disease many patients can become steroid dependent leading to an increased risk of the adverse side effects of steroids e.g. </s><s n="s3.8;p87.96">Cushings syndrome. </s><s n="s4.8;p87.96">Recent studies have shown that TNF alpha blocking agents are effective in inducing remission in Crohns Disease [1]. </s><s n="s5.8;p87.96">This may in turn decrease the dependency for steroids. </s><s n="s6.8;p87.96">NICE guidelines 2002, recommended the use of Infliximab for the treatment of severe active Crohns when treatment with immunomodulating drugs and corticosteroids has failed or is no tolerated and when surgery is inappropriate [2]. </s><s n="s7.8;p87.96">The approved dose is 5mg/Kg given as IV infusion preferably at 0, 2 and 6 weeks [3]. </s><s n="s8.8;p87.96">Research has now moved past the benefits of Infliximab and onto agents that inhibit leukocyte recruitment and block molecules such as IL-2 in the inflammatory pathway [3]. </s></p><p n="p88.96"><s n="s1.1;p88.96">In contrast with ulcerative colitis approximately 50% of patients with moderately active Crohn's colitis were shown to respond to oral metronidazole for up to 3 months [4]. </s></p><p n="p89.96"><s n="s1.4;p89.96">The average age of onset for patients with Crohns Disease is in the early decades of life, but the average life expectancy is the same as the general population [5]. </s><s n="s2.4;p89.96">Unfortunately the cost of treatment forms a major part of discussion in all aspects of health care delivery and Crohns Disease is no exception. </s><s n="s3.4;p89.96">Hospitalisation for surgery consumes a large portion of the total cost of treatment for Crohns [5}. </s><s n="s4.4;p89.96">Indeed one paper commented that therapy, which decreases the number of surgical hospitalisations for Crohns, would reduce the overall costs of caring for patients with the disease [5]. </s></p><p n="p90.96"><s n="s1.3;p90.96"><name type="other"/> appears to be having no significant response to medical therapy and the option of surgery was discussed. </s><s n="s2.3;p90.96">Research has shown that quality of life improved 30 days post surgery in patients with Crohns Disease and that this improvement was unrelated to patient characteristics, nature of disease or intervention performed [6]. </s><s n="s3.3;p90.96">Indeed many patients who underwent surgery for Crohns Disease in the study felt that surgery had helped them and felt they would undergo surgery again [6]. </s></p><p n="p91.96"><s n="s1.4;p91.96">Surgery is usually indicated for patients whose disease fails to respond to drug or dietary therapy. </s><s n="s2.4;p91.96">Resection is not curative and there is a 50% chance of recurrence that will require further surgery at 10 years [7]. </s><s n="s3.4;p91.96">Some patients prefer to opt for surgery at presentation rather than pharmacological or nutritional treatment of unknown duration. </s><s n="s4.4;p91.96">Unfortunately, there is no controlled data to confirm the best approach for patients [7]. </s></p><p n="p92.96"><s n="s1.4;p92.96">There is a well-known association between ulcerative colitis and an increased risk of colorectal cancer, and patients with Crohns disease are believed to be at increased risk of cancer of the small intestine. </s><s n="s2.4;p92.96">Studies have shown that the relative risk of colorectal cancer in patients with Crohn's colitis is approximately 5.6 and should raise the same concerns as in patients with ulcerative colitis [8]. </s><s n="s3.4;p92.96">Surveillance should begin 8 - 10 years after disease onset for pancolitis and 15 - 20 years after onset for disease affecting the left side of the colon [8]. </s><s n="s4.4;p92.96">At the time of admission, <name type="other"/>'s colon only was affected by Crohns, she was diagnosed at the age of 7 and so regular surveillance to identify any dysplasia within the colon would have been indicated according to this paper. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="bold">Commentary</hi> A commentary on issues of health care delivery, ethical issues or disability relevant to the patient and/or problem</head><p n="p93.96"><s n="s1.2;p93.96">Crohns disease affects between 30,000 and 60,000 people in the UK, (approximately 1 in 1200) with between 3,000 and 6,000 new cases diagnosed each year. </s><s n="s2.2;p93.96">Research shows that the number of people with Crohn's Disease has been rising steadily, particularly among young people [9]. </s></p><p n="p94.96"><s n="s1.2;p94.96">The most effective prophylactic measure in patients with Crohns Disease is to refrain from smoking, the risk of relapse in non smokers at 3 years is approximately 30% lower than in smokers [1]. </s><s n="s2.2;p94.96">It is vital that the care of patients with Crohns disease includes advice on such lifestyle habits to prevent future exacerbations of the disease. </s></p><p n="p95.96"><s n="s1.2;p95.96">With the advances in research and the variety of treatment options available it is essential that the patient remains at the focus of the decision making process so that they are fully informed on all available treatment therapies. </s><s n="s2.2;p95.96">This will ensure that the most appropriate management plan is developed for the patient. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="bold">Impact on your learning</hi> Describe what you have learnt from this case</head><list type="bulleted"><item>Presenting symptoms associated with Crohns</item><item>Differential diagnoses for patients presenting with acute diarrhoea and appropriate investigations</item><item>Management of patients with Crohns Disease</item><item>Differences between Crohns and Ulcerative Colitis</item></list><p n="p96.96"/></div1></body><back><div1 type="bibliography"><div2 type="bibliography"><head rend="bold">References</head><p>1 Akobeng AK, Zachos M. Tumour necrosis factor alpha antibody for induction of remission in Crohns disease (Review). The cochrane database of systematic reviews 2003 Issue 4</p><p>2 Nice Guidelines</p><p>3 Panaccione R, Ferraz J, Beck P. Advances in medical therapy of inflammatory bowel disease. Current opinion in Pharmacology. 2005 5: 1-7</p><p>4 Hanauer SB, Meyers S. Management of Crohn's disease in adults. Am J Gastroenterol 1997; 92: 559-566</p><p>5 Cohen RD et al. The cost of hospitalisation in Crohns Disease. The American Journal of Gastroenterology. 2000 95:2</p><p>6 Delaney CP et al. Quality of life improves within 30 days of surgery for Crohns disease. Journal of American Colorectal surgery 2003. 196 (5)</p><p>7 Rampton DS. Management of Crohn's disease Clinical review Regular review BMJ 1999;319:1480-1485</p><p>8 Eaden J Review article: colorectal carcinoma and inflammatory bowel disease. Aliment Pharmacol Ther. 2004 Oct;20 Suppl 4:24-30.</p><p>9 <seg type="URL" n="http://www.nacc.org.uk/content/ibd.asp"/></p></div2><div2 type="bibliography"><head rend="bold">References not cited:</head><p>Kumar P and Clark M. Clinical Medicine 5<hi rend="sup">th</hi> edition</p><p>Longmore M, Wilkinson I, Torok E. Oxford Handbook of Clinical Medicine. 5<hi rend="sup">th</hi> edition</p><p>BNF September 2004 BMA</p></div2></div1><div1 type="appendix"><head rend="bold">ASPECTS OF CASE AS RECORDED IN SUMMARY OF PORTFOLIO CASES•</head><p/></div1><div1 type="appendix"><head rend="bold">PORTFOLIO COMPLETION CERTIFICATE</head><p/></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
