<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_0203d" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Portfolio Case presentation number: 6 schizophrenia</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">proforma</note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">appendices: 	ASPECTS OF CASE AS RECORDED IN SUMMARY OF PORTFOLIO CASES, PORTFOLIO COMPLETION CERTIFICATE</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">4</p><p n="date">2005-04</p><p n="module title">Other rotations</p><p n="module code">unknown</p><p n="genre family">Case study</p><p n="discipline">Medicine</p><p n="disciplinary group">LS</p><p n="grade">D</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">4524</p><p n="number of s-units">172</p><p n="number of p">74</p><p n="number of tables">2</p><p n="number of figures">0</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">1</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">16</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">26.3</p><p n="average s-units per p">2.3</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">f</p><p n="year of birth">1979</p><p n="first language">English</p><p n="education">UKA</p><p n="course">Medicine</p><p n="student ID">0203</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><docTitle><titlePart rend="bold">PORTFOLIO CASE No: 03W372</titlePart></docTitle><titlePart>Patient Initials<name type="other"/> Age 46 Gender Male</titlePart><titlePart>Portfolio Case presentation number: 6 Phase 2 course document objectives 12.1, 12.2, 12.3, 12.5, Has the patient' permission, including for follow up contact by telephone, been sought and recorded in the case notes? YES</titlePart></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Referral information</head><p n="p1.74"><s n="s1.1;p1.74">On <name type="date"/> , <name type="other"/> was taken to his sisters house by 2 policemen on a section 136, he was then brought to <name type="other"/> by his sister and was admitted informally. <name type="other"/> is known to have schizophrenia. <name type="other"/> was interviewed on <name type="other"/> Ward on <name type="date"/>. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">History</head><div2><head rend="underlined bold">Presenting Complaint</head><p n="p2.74"><s n="s1.1;p2.74"><name type="other"/> was brought to <name type="other"/> by his sister as she was concerned about his mental state and safety. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined bold">History of Presenting Complaint </head><p n="p3.74"><s n="s1.1;p3.74"><name type="other"/> was involved in an argument and <hi rend="bold">fight</hi> at a local club and had consequently been removed from the premises by 2 security staff. <name type="other"/> had been talking to a friend and his wife who then started to shout at him for no apparent reason, he asked them to stop shouting and to leave him alone. <name type="other"/> was reluctant to come into hospital initially as he <hi rend="bold">didn't feel he had done anything wrong</hi>. <name type="other"/> felt angry and let down by his friends who had '<hi rend="bold">backstabbed' him</hi>. <name type="other"/> was taken to his sister's house by two policemen on a <hi rend="bold">section 136</hi>, he was then brought to <name type="other"/> by his sister and was admitted informally. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined bold">Symptoms</head><p n="p4.74"><s n="s1.2;p4.74"><name type="other"/> stated that he had been feeling <hi rend="bold">low</hi> over the past few weeks. <name type="other"/> complains of having a <hi rend="bold">poor appetite</hi> and <hi rend="bold">waking during the night</hi>. </s><s n="s2.2;p4.74">For the past few months, <name type="other"/> has had <hi rend="bold">no motivation to eat or care for himself</hi> (showering/brushing hair). <name type="other"/> feels slightly <hi rend="bold">anxious</hi> at the moment and is <hi rend="bold">worried</hi> about himself - he doesn't know why he feels quiet but knows that it will get better with time. <name type="other"/> said that he feels <hi rend="bold">shy</hi> and wants to <hi rend="bold">spend time alone in his room.</hi> </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined bold">Past Psychiatric History</head><p n="p5.74"><s n="s1.3;p5.74"><name type="other"/> was diagnosed with <hi rend="bold">severe depression</hi> in 1976 and was admitted to hospital in <name type="other"/> during this time. <name type="other"/> described things as <hi rend="bold">"being bad"</hi> and stated that his family were 'crying all the time' but would not elaborate on this. <name type="other"/> recalled <hi rend="bold">hearing derogatory voices</hi> at the age of 21 but was unable to describe whether the voice was male, female, single or multiple voices. </s><s n="s2.3;p5.74">The voices told him to kill himself and consequently <name type="other"/> set fire to his pyjamas. <name type="other"/> described himself as being "<hi rend="bold">brain dead"</hi> at the time and wanting to 'end it all' but is glad that he didn't succeed now. <name type="other"/> has not heard the voices since this time. </s><s n="s3.3;p5.74">In 1985 <name type="other"/> was diagnosed with <hi rend="bold">Schizophrenia</hi> and described himself as having a "<hi rend="bold">problem with his brain"</hi>. <name type="other"/> was unable to describe the changes in his mood etc that occurred around this time. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined bold">Past Medical History</head><p n="p6.74"><s n="s1.2;p6.74"><name type="other"/> described himself as having a healthy body but a <hi rend="bold">"problem with his brain".</hi> </s><s n="s2.2;p6.74"><name type="other"/> had a skin graft on his right leg in 1979 after setting fire to his pyjamas but described no other health problems. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined bold">Family History</head><p n="p7.74"><s n="s1.3;p7.74"><name type="other"/> stated that his parents had a good relationship and were happily married for 50 years. <name type="other"/>'s father died on <name type="date"/> and his mother died on <name type="date"/> of stomach cancer. <name type="other"/> stated that his dad was sometimes protective over him - 'in a good way'. <name type="other"/><hi rend="bold">misses his parents</hi> and thinks about them a lot. </s><s n="s2.3;p7.74">There was no history of abuse or neglect. <name type="other"/> has 5 brothers and 2 sisters who are all married: <name type="other"/> 52, <name type="other"/> 50, <name type="other"/> 44, <name type="other"/> 42, <name type="other"/> 39, <name type="other"/> 38, <name type="other"/> 32. <name type="other"/> stated that he <hi rend="bold">gets on well with all of his brothers and sisters</hi>, especially <name type="other"/> who tries to help him and encourages him to get better - "Come on <name type="other"/>****". <name type="other"/> and <name type="other"/> assist with <name type="other"/>'s activities of daily living and help him to manage his finances. <name type="other"/> stated that his brothers and sisters understand his problems but his nieces and nephews don't. </s><s n="s3.3;p7.74">There is no family history of contact with the mental health services. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined bold">Personal History</head><p n="p8.74"><s n="s1.1;p8.74">There are no known pregnancy or birth problems although <name type="other"/> stated that he was an 'early baby' (premature). <name type="other"/> did not recall any problems with his early milestones and stated that he had a 'good time' at home as a child. </s></p><p n="p9.74"><s n="s1.1;p9.74"><name type="other"/> enjoyed his time at infants school but was bullied at Junior school when he was approx 6 or 7 years. <name type="other"/> described being 'kicked in the stomach' and 'pushed into a brick wall' and believed this was because people were <hi rend="bold">jealous</hi> of him. <name type="other"/> had a good relationship with his teachers and friends and described himself as being a quiet, average student. <name type="other"/> left school at the age of 15 to work in a local dairy, whilst there he was bullied and described being 'clipped round the head' by people he didn't know. <name type="other"/> thinks that his "problems" started at the dairy and described himself as being '<hi rend="bold">shy'</hi> during this time. <name type="other"/> left the job at the dairy and has been delivering papers for many years, this position ended 2 months ago "due to a fight". <name type="other"/> was unable to give accurate dates or reasons for leaving employment and appeared to be confused when recalling this information. <name type="other"/> stated that he enjoys work but <hi rend="bold">doesn't think he could cope with working</hi> at the moment and said, <hi rend="bold">"my brain is stopping me".</hi> </s></p></div2><div2><head>Relationships /sexual history </head><p n="p10.74"><s n="s1.2;p10.74"><name type="other"/> stated that he has 'lots of friends' and has had a few relationships with ladies but is currently single and described himself as "<hi rend="bold">not being a lover</hi>". </s><s n="s2.2;p10.74">In 1998, <name type="other"/> had a relationship with a lady (<name type="other"/>), which ended in 2000. <name type="other"/> described this as being a happy relationship but stated that he 'never took her home' and simply '<hi rend="bold">liked her company'</hi>. <name type="other"/> could not say why the relationship ended. <name type="other"/> currently has a "good relationship" with a lady who he met at the <name type="other"/> day centre and has known for 12/13 years. <name type="other"/> stated that he "loves her" and looks forward to her visits, he was disappointed that she hadn't been to see him at <name type="other"/>. <name type="other"/> stated that he did not want any children. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">Systems Review</head><p n="p11.74"><s n="s1.1;p11.74">Gastrointestinal System - loss of appetite, no changes in bowel habits (no constipation) </s></p><p n="p12.74"><s n="s1.1;p12.74">Other systems - no significant findings </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined bold">Social History</head><p n="p13.74"><s n="s1.2;p13.74"><name type="other"/> smokes approx 15 cigarettes/day and could not remember how long he had smoked for. <name type="other"/> stated that he has the occasional shandy but avoids alcohol as it 'messes with his tablets'. <name type="other"/> currently <hi rend="bold">lives alone</hi> in a 1 bedroom council owned flat, he is able to prepare a meal for himself but his sister does all of his shopping, cleaning and pays the bills. <name type="other"/> stated that he has no financial problems and likes to "<hi rend="bold">splash out"</hi> with his money on friends in the pub. <name type="other"/> stated that his brother says "people are taking me for a mug". </s><s n="s2.2;p13.74">There is no history of or current illicit drug use as <name type="other"/> believes it will mess with his medication. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined bold">Forensic History</head><p n="p14.74"><s n="s1.1;p14.74">Nil </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined bold">Pre-morbid personality</head><p n="p15.74"><s n="s1.2;p15.74"><name type="other"/> describes himself as having a "nice personality" and being a "real good friend". <name type="other"/> enjoys watching "flying birds" and reading about them in books, but said that he <hi rend="bold">doesn't enjoy this as much at the moment</hi>. <name type="other"/> used to be a rambler and enjoyed walking stating that he had 'walked the earth'. <name type="other"/>'s religion is <name type="other"/> but he only attends church for weddings and funerals. <name type="other"/> stated that he is not himself at the moment, that he is usually 'ever so friendly and polite' and stated that 'nobody knows him at the moment'. </s><s n="s2.2;p15.74">If things are getting on top of him he copes by "just trying to breathe". </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined bold">Medication</head><p n="p16.74"><s n="s1.1;p16.74">There are no known allergies. </s></p><p n="p17.74"><s n="s1.1;p17.74"><name type="other"/> was aware that he was taking medication but could not recall the names. <name type="other"/> stated that his medication was in the form of injections and tablets and that he had been taking them for years and did not mind taking them as they "keep him alive". </s></p></div2><div2><head><hi rend="bold">Suicidal Ideation</hi> - </head><p n="p18.74"><s n="s1.2;p18.74"><name type="other"/> stated that he had made a <hi rend="bold">plan</hi> to end it all and had a written a <hi rend="bold">letter</hi> to this effect. </s><s n="s2.2;p18.74">A nurse on the ward had 'talked him round' and <name type="other"/> was now trying to drive the ideas out of his mind. <name type="other"/> would not elaborate on his plans and would not say if he had put any of these into action. <name type="other"/> has never had any thoughts of harming others. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined bold">Risk Assessment: </head><p n="p19.74"><s rend="bold" n="s1.1;p19.74">to self - high </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Mental State Examination and Physical Examination </head><div2><head><hi rend="underlined">APPEARANCE</hi> :</head><p n="p20.74"><s n="s1.1;p20.74">Medium build, tall male. <name type="other"/> was casually dressed, <hi rend="bold">unshaven and unkempt</hi> with evidence of <hi rend="bold">neglect of self-care</hi>. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">BEHAVIOUR: </head><p n="p21.74"><s n="s1.3;p21.74">Polite and willing to talk, moderate rapport established. </s><s n="s2.3;p21.74">No suspicion or guarding although <name type="other"/> was unable/unwilling to elaborate on certain parts of the history. </s><s n="s3.3;p21.74">Eye contact variable with <hi rend="bold">moments when </hi><name type="other"/><hi rend="bold">'s eyes were downcast</hi>. <name type="other"/> displayed <hi rend="bold">mannerisms</hi> - repetitive crossing of legs and folding of arms and had <hi rend="bold">a slight tremor</hi> in his hands. <name type="other"/>'s low motivation tends to isolate him from the ward. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">SPEECH: </head><p n="p22.74"><s n="s1.3;p22.74">Volume and intonation normal. </s><s n="s2.3;p22.74">Speech - generally slow but episodes of <hi rend="bold">rapid speech with vagueness of content</hi> which made it difficult to grasp the meaning of what <name type="other"/> was saying. </s><s rend="bold" n="s3.3;p22.74">Often long silences before answering questions. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">MOOD/AFFECT: </head><p n="p23.74"><s n="s1.2;p23.74">Subjective - <hi rend="bold">Low, quiet and shy</hi>. </s><s n="s2.2;p23.74">Objective - <name type="other"/> appeared to be of <hi rend="bold">low mood</hi> and slightly <hi rend="bold">worried with a flattened affect</hi>. <name type="other"/> stated that he is not like this all the time - normally very friendly. <name type="other"/> felt that his mood would change but that he has to change it himself. </s></p></div2><div2><head><hi rend="underlined">THOUGHTS</hi> : </head><p n="p24.74"><s n="s1.1;p24.74"><name type="other"/> feels <hi rend="bold">angry</hi> with himself at present because he doesn't know why he feels like he does. <name type="other"/> displayed <hi rend="bold">negative thoughts of the world and himself</hi> stating that people don't understand and that nobody knows him. <name type="other"/> sometimes has <hi rend="bold">paranoid</hi> feelings that people are talking about him but does not think that people are out to hurt him. </s></p><p n="p25.74"><s n="s1.2;p25.74">Form: <hi rend="bold">Occasional loosening of associations</hi> - There was a general lack of clarity and profoundness in <name type="other"/>'s responses. </s><s n="s2.2;p25.74">Occasionally <name type="other"/> moved between topics and didn't complete thought trails before changing topic. </s></p><p n="p26.74"><s n="s1.1;p26.74">Stream: No abnormalities detected </s></p><p n="p27.74"><s n="s1.1;p27.74">Suicidal Ideation: <hi rend="bold">Present,</hi> although <name type="other"/> stated that he was glad the nurse stopped him. </s></p><p n="p28.74"><s n="s1.1;p28.74">Delusions/Grandiose Ideas: Mild - <name type="other"/> referred to himself as being a great footballer and an excellent cricketer. <name type="other"/> also feels that people are jealous of him - evidence of <hi rend="bold">self importance</hi>. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">PERCEPTIONS: </head><p n="p29.74"><s n="s1.2;p29.74">No auditory pseudohallucinations since age 21. </s><s n="s2.2;p29.74">No illusions. </s></p><p n="p30.74"><s n="s1.1;p30.74">No somatic/auditory/visual/olfactory/gustatory hallucinations. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">INSIGHT:</head><p n="p31.74"><s n="s1.1;p31.74">Moderate - <name type="other"/> is aware that he has a mental illness and states that it is a "problem with his brain". <name type="other"/> is also aware that he needs medication and does not mind taking it. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">COGNITION: </head><p n="p32.74"><s n="s1.1;p32.74"><name type="other"/> was orientated in time, place and person. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined bold">Physical Examination </head><p n="p33.74"><s n="s1.4;p33.74">Points to look for on physical examination would be signs of endocrine abnormalities e.g. hypothyroidism, which can mimic symptoms of schizophrenia and depression. </s><s n="s2.4;p33.74">As <name type="other"/> has been assessed as having a high suicide risk it is important to look for evidence of self-harm attempted suicide e.g. cuts. </s><s n="s3.4;p33.74">As <name type="other"/> has stated that he has a poor appetite it is also important to monitor his weight and to look for evidence of malnutrition. </s><s n="s4.4;p33.74">As <name type="other"/> has been on long term antipsychotics it is important to look for extra pyramidal side effects of medication on physical examination. </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">CoVBllateral History</head><div2><head><name type="other"/><hi rend="underlined bold"> status at time of admission - sister</hi></head><p rend="bulleted" n="p34.74"><s n="s1.1;p34.74">Sister was concerned about <name type="other"/>'s mental state and safety </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p35.74"><s n="s1.1;p35.74"><name type="other"/> was <hi rend="bold">wound up easily</hi>, not his usual nature </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p36.74"><s n="s1.1;p36.74">Becoming <hi rend="bold">aggressive and verbally abusive</hi> even to family members, <hi rend="bold">threatening to kill</hi> people </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p37.74"><s rend="bold" n="s1.1;p37.74">Distracted easily and agitated, not engaging with family </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p38.74"><s n="s1.1;p38.74">Perceived by others to be <hi rend="bold">hyperactive and eccentric</hi> </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined bold">Information from medical notes - MSE on admission</head><p rend="bulleted" n="p39.74"><s n="s1.1;p39.74">Pressured speech - mumbling to self, Grandiosity and self importance " I am superman", " I should be climbing buildings", Persecutory Delusions, Irritable, </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p40.74"><s n="s1.1;p40.74">Sexually Inappropriate - "I'm vagina man" </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p41.74"><s n="s1.1;p41.74">Self Harm - wanting to cut his penis off, "I'm going to burn my legs" </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p42.74"><s n="s1.1;p42.74">Has been managing well in the community for a number of years </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined bold">Report from CPN (<name type="date"/>)</head><p rend="bulleted" n="p43.74"><s n="s1.1;p43.74">Concerns re: behaviour and interaction within the community </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p44.74"><s n="s1.1;p44.74">Paranoid of people taunting him resulting in aggressive outbursts </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined bold">Medication </head><p n="p45.74"><s n="s1.1;p45.74">Prior to admission - Depixol (Flupentixol decanoate) injection 500 mg every three weeks </s></p><list type="simple"><head>Current medication (<name type="date"/>):</head><item>Haloperidol 3-5mg (once wk)</item><item>Olanzapine 20mg OD</item><item>Sertraline 50mg OD</item><item>Oxazepam 10mg BD</item><item>Flupentixol decanoate (IM) 500mg every 3 wk</item></list></div2><div2><head rend="underlined bold">Drug History</head><p n="p46.74"><s n="s1.1;p46.74">History of long term typical anti psychotic use including Haloperidol and Flupentixol decanoate. </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Analysis of history and examination</head><p n="p47.74"><s n="s1.1;p47.74">From the history and mental state examination <name type="other"/> is a 46-year-old man who was diagnosed with schizophrenia in his late twenties. <name type="other"/> is currently experiencing symptoms of depression. </s></p><div2><head rend="bold">Severe Depressive Episode (F32.2) </head><p n="p48.74"><s n="s1.6;p48.74">This is supported by the history of poor sleep and appetite, anhedonia and low mood. </s><s n="s2.6;p48.74">The severity is indicated by <name type="other"/>'s suicidal ideation and inability to perform daily tasks. <name type="other"/> may have had a recent 'stressor' in his life which has elicited these depressive symptoms. </s><s n="s3.6;p48.74">From the history, the only possible trigger to this episode is the disagreement with his friends on the night of admission and recent anniversary of his parents death. </s><s n="s4.6;p48.74">Although <name type="other"/> is displaying many of the psychological symptoms of depression - low self esteem, hopelessness and pessimism, he does not appear to have any physical symptoms (weight loss or constipation), characteristic of a depressive disorder. </s><s n="s5.6;p48.74">Many of the features of a depressive disorder are prominent in other psychiatric illnesses such as schizophrenia. </s><s n="s6.6;p48.74">It is likely that <name type="other"/>'s current symptoms are associated with his schizophrenic diagnosis. </s></p></div2><div2><head><hi rend="bold">Depression within a schizophrenic diagnosis</hi> <hi rend="bold">(F20)</hi></head><p n="p49.74"><s n="s1.4;p49.74">- Symptoms of depression that <name type="other"/> displays commonly occur in both acute and chronic schizophrenia. </s><s n="s2.4;p49.74">The "negative features" of schizophrenia have clinical similarities to the symptoms associated with depression and are often difficult to differentiate. </s><s n="s3.4;p49.74">It is therefore important to establish whether <name type="other"/> has a history of such symptoms related to his schizophrenia or whether this is a new depressive episode. </s><s n="s4.4;p49.74">Collateral information would identify the subtype of <name type="other"/>'s schizophrenic diagnosis, he occasionally has paranoid feelings (people talking about him) and this may support a diagnosis of paranoid schizophrenia. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">Post-schizophrenic depression (F20.4) </head><p n="p50.74"><s n="s1.8;p50.74">Collateral information indicates that <name type="other"/> had psychotic symptoms on admission. </s><s n="s2.8;p50.74">The depressive symptoms <name type="other"/> is displaying may be a result of him gaining insight into the psychotic events surrounding admission. </s><s n="s3.8;p50.74">This is supported by some of the symptoms <name type="other"/> displays i.e. </s><s n="s4.8;p50.74">Ideas of self-harm, disturbed sleep, poor appetite. </s><s n="s5.8;p50.74">In such a diagnosis, schizophrenic symptoms (positive or negative) must still be present. </s><s n="s6.8;p50.74">Although <name type="other"/> does not currently display any of the first rank/clear cut symptoms of schizophrenia, there is still a loosening of associations, blunted affect and deterioration in social behaviour to support this diagnosis. </s><s n="s7.8;p50.74">Again, the rejection from his friends in the nightclub or the recent anniversary of his parents death may have over stimulated <name type="other"/> and precipitated the relapse of his schizophrenia. </s><s n="s8.8;p50.74">The relapse could also be due to a change in compliance with his medication and so this would need to be investigated. </s></p></div2><div2><head><hi rend="bold">Schizoaffective Disorder</hi> <hi rend="bold">Depressive Type (F25.1</hi> ) </head><p n="p51.74"><s n="s1.6;p51.74">in which definite schizophrenic and affective symptoms are present simultaneously and are equally prominent. </s><s n="s2.6;p51.74">Changes in <name type="other"/>'s affect have been noted in the history - "feeling low, worried". </s><s n="s3.6;p51.74">Although <name type="other"/> was not currently experiencing any hallucinations or formal thought disorder ('positive' symptoms of schizophrenia) he did appear to have a flattened affect and was displaying a loosening of associations in his thought form which transcribed as vagueness in his speech. </s><s n="s4.6;p51.74">Other symptoms include social withdrawal (preferring to spend time alone in his room) and self-neglect. </s><s n="s5.6;p51.74">These 'negative' symptoms are typical of the chronic syndrome of schizophrenia which would support a diagnosis of schizoaffective disorder. </s><s n="s6.6;p51.74">However, <name type="other"/>'s depressive symptoms appear to be more prominent than his schizophrenic symptoms which does not meet the criteria for this diagnosis. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">Bipolar affective disorder, current episode severe depression without psychotic symptoms (F31.4) </head><p n="p52.74"><s n="s1.4;p52.74">- characterised by depressive episodes and at least one authenticated hypomanic/manic, episode in the past. </s><s n="s2.4;p52.74">The symptoms of depression have been identified in the history so far. <name type="other"/> stated that he likes to splash out his money on his friends - this could indicate a degree of disinhibited behaviour indicative of hypomania. </s><s n="s3.4;p52.74">There was also a minor element of self-importance in the history - jealous of me, great footballer. </s><s n="s4.4;p52.74">However, <name type="other"/>'s low mood and reduced activity levels were not characteristic of patient with mania. </s></p><p n="p53.74"><s n="s1.5;p53.74">A diagnosis of <hi rend="bold">post schizophrenic depression</hi> is the most likely choice given the collateral information at this time. </s><s n="s2.5;p53.74">However, an organic cause for the depressive symptoms cannot be ruled out. </s><s n="s3.5;p53.74">It is important to confirm that <name type="other"/> had not taken any illicit substances preceding admission e.g. amphetamines or cocaine, as these are more likely to bring on a relapse of schizophrenia and can quickly exacerbate symptoms. </s><s n="s4.5;p53.74">It is also important to consider Endocrine causes of depression such as Hypothyroidism or Diabetes. <name type="other"/>'s medication should also be investigated to rule out an iatrogenic cause for his depression through use of sedatives, steroids etc. </s><s n="s5.5;p53.74">As <name type="other"/> has not reported any sexual relationships or illicit drug use it is unlikely that his depression could be due to an infection such as HIV or syphilis. </s></p><p n="p54.74"><s n="s1.4;p54.74"><name type="other"/> has been assessed as a high suicide risk as he has recently expressed a desire to 'end it all'. </s><s n="s2.4;p54.74">The history of attempted suicide, recent plan and letter to this effect all indicate a greater risk of a further fatal attempt. </s><s n="s3.4;p54.74">During the psychotic episode, <name type="other"/> displayed ideas of harming others. </s><s n="s4.4;p54.74">However there are no current ideas to this effect and <name type="other"/> is assessed as being a low risk of harm to others. </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Formulation of the patient's problem(s)</head><div2><head rend="underlined bold">Impression </head><p n="p55.74"><s n="s1.3;p55.74"><name type="other"/> is a pleasant, placid individual with a long history of psychiatric illness. </s><s n="s2.3;p55.74">This has led to a certain level of dependency over time, initially on his two parents and now his two sisters. <name type="other"/> is an impressionable man who seems to have superficial relationships resulting in a degree of social isolation. </s><s n="s3.3;p55.74">In view of his past schizophrenic history, it is likely that the relapse of <name type="other"/>'s schizophrenia was triggered by a high level of expressed emotion and overstimulation due to recent social factors i.e. disagreement with friends, recent anniversary of parents death. </s></p><table id="BAWE_0203d-tab.001"><row><cell/></row></table></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Management</head><div2><head rend="underlined bold">Reassurance and Explanation </head><p n="p56.74"><s n="s1.4;p56.74"><name type="other"/> is aware of his diagnosis of schizophrenia but was unclear why he had been admitted to hospital and this should be explained to him. </s><s n="s2.4;p56.74">During the interview, <name type="other"/> did not mention any of the psychotic symptoms he had displayed on admission and would only describe his state as "not being himself" and a "problem with his brain". </s><s n="s3.4;p56.74">It should be explained to <name type="other"/> that the symptoms he was experiencing are a result of his illness and the reason he takes long-term medication. </s><s n="s4.4;p56.74">This may help to reduce any problems with non-compliance, increase his insight and help him to recover from the depressive symptoms he is currently experiencing. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined bold">Investigations </head><p n="p57.74"><s n="s1.1;p57.74">To exclude an organic cause for the depression or relapse of his schizophrenia: </s></p><table id="BAWE_0203d-tab.002"><row><cell/></row></table></div2><div2><head rend="underlined bold">Collateral Information</head><p n="p58.74"><s n="s1.2;p58.74">Information should be sought from medical notes regarding previous admissions, treatments and reactions to medication and to confirm the history. </s><s n="s2.2;p58.74">Confirmation of suicide attempt should also be sought from nursing staff on the ward. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined bold">Short Term Management</head><div3><head rend="bold">Biological </head><p n="p59.74"><s n="s1.8;p59.74">Before pharmacological intervention is applied, it is important to confirm that <name type="other"/> has been compliant with his medication to ensure that this was not a precipitant for his relapse. <name type="other"/>'s long-term antipsychotic medication should be maintained to prevent any further relapses of his schizophrenic symptoms. </s><s n="s2.8;p59.74">A short-term antidepressant would help to lift <name type="other"/>'s mood during his inpatient stay and relieve his depressive symptoms. </s><s n="s3.8;p59.74">As <name type="other"/> has been assessed as having a high suicide risk it is important to prescribe an antidepressant that has a low toxicity in case of attempted overdose e.g. </s><s n="s4.8;p59.74">Sertraline. </s><s n="s5.8;p59.74">Sertraline also has good anxiolytic properties, which would help with <name type="other"/>'s mild anxiety. <name type="other"/>'s disturbed sleep pattern may have been causing his lack of energy and consequent anhedonia. </s><s n="s6.8;p59.74">A short-term benzodiazepine e.g. </s><s n="s7.8;p59.74">Lorazepam, may help to alleviate this sleep disturbance but should not be considered for prolonged use due to the risk of addiction. </s><s n="s8.8;p59.74">As <name type="other"/> has been on medication for his schizophrenia for a long time and believes that it "keeps him alive", he may be apprehensive about changes and so these would need to be explained to him. </s></p></div3><div3><head rend="bold">Social and Psychological </head><p n="p60.74"><s n="s1.6;p60.74">Equally as important if not more so in the case of <name type="other"/> is intervention at a social level. </s><s n="s2.6;p60.74">During <name type="other"/>'s inpatient stay it is vital that he is encouraged to participate in activities. </s><s n="s3.6;p60.74">This will help to avoid further social isolation and time spent contemplating suicidal ideas, therefore improving his psychological well-being. </s><s n="s4.6;p60.74">It will also help to avoid a dependency on the ward and future admissions. </s><s n="s5.6;p60.74">A change in environment e.g. activities outside, should be encouraged as under stimulation can exacerbate the negative symptoms of schizophrenia. </s><s n="s6.6;p60.74">However, the amount of stimulation and expressed emotion in the hospital environment must be carefully balanced in order to avoid a relapse of his schizophrenia. </s></p></div3></div2><div2><head rend="underlined bold">Long Term Management</head><div3><head rend="bold">Biological </head><p n="p61.74"><s n="s1.5;p61.74"><name type="other"/> should continue to receive his schizophrenic depot medication to reduce the risk of a relapse. </s><s n="s2.5;p61.74">During the interview, <name type="other"/> had a slight tremor of his hands which may be a result of the long term use of typical anti psychotics. </s><s n="s3.5;p61.74">Monitoring of these side effects should be incorporated into <name type="other"/>'s long-term management plan. </s><s n="s4.5;p61.74">If the side effects reach an unacceptable level, the medication should be changed from a typical to an atypical antipsychotic [1]. </s><s n="s5.5;p61.74">Regular monitoring of blood pressure, pulse and temperature should be observed in long-term antipsychotic treatment and can be carried out as part of primary care by the GP or CPN [2]. </s></p></div3><div3><head rend="bold">Social and Psychological </head><p n="p62.74"><s n="s1.4;p62.74"><name type="other"/> has managed well in the community for a number of years with the help of the community mental health team. </s><s n="s2.4;p62.74">As <name type="other"/> has a diverse range of service requirements, a <hi rend="italic">"care program approach"</hi> would be an effective way of initiating and maintaining contact with services to ensure a high level of care. <name type="other"/> is currently living in independent accommodation and relies on his sisters to help with activities of daily living etc. <name type="other"/> may benefit from supported accommodation/friendship housing that provides 24 hour support for patients with mental health illnesses living in the community. </s><s n="s3.4;p62.74">A full assessment of <name type="other"/>'s support needs by the social worker would ensure that suitable accommodation and support could then be applied for. </s><s n="s4.4;p62.74">This would help to alleviate the pressure on his sisters so that they can spend their time with <name type="other"/> in a more recreational way. </s></p><p n="p63.74"><s n="s1.3;p63.74">The social worker would also ensure that <name type="other"/> is receiving all benefits he is entitled to which is vital now that he is unemployed. <name type="other"/> will have little to occupy his time now that he is unemployed which may exacerbate his depressive symptoms. </s><s n="s2.3;p63.74">An occupational therapist could help to organise a structured program of activity to maintain and improve <name type="other"/>'s social and occupational skills. </s><s n="s3.3;p63.74">Reorientation and rehabilitation in this form may provide a supported stepping-stone back into mainstream work, which <name type="other"/> enjoyed, and promote social inclusion. </s></p><p n="p64.74"><s n="s1.4;p64.74">Day centres run by voluntary organisations such as Rethink or SANE would provide <name type="other"/> with a ready-made social network and a range of leisure activities and general support. </s><s n="s2.4;p64.74">CBT (cognitive behavioural therapy), may help to improve <name type="other"/>'s insight and coping mechanisms when he becomes anxious by focusing on his current thoughts, feelings and behaviours. </s><s n="s3.4;p64.74">Such interventions require active participation from the patient and the probability of this would have to be assessed before a referral was made. </s><s n="s4.4;p64.74">An advance directive (agreement) should be developed and recorded in <name type="other"/>'s care program to identify the treatment he would prefer to receive if he became too unwell to look after himself. </s></p><p n="p65.74"><s n="s1.2;p65.74">It may be beneficial to refer <name type="other"/>'s family members to a carers group where experiences and coping strategies can be shared. </s><s n="s2.2;p65.74">They may also benefit from family therapy sessions which teach family members how to recognise and reduce expressed emotion, and therefore the risk of another relapse. </s></p><p n="p66.74"><s n="s1.3;p66.74">In terms of prognosis, <name type="other"/> has a very supportive family who can recognise changes in his mental state and refer him to the mental health services for acute management. </s><s n="s2.3;p66.74">They are also available to assist with his return to the community and activities of daily living. </s><s n="s3.3;p66.74">However, a multidisciplinary approach to <name type="other"/>'s care in the community must be applied in order to reduce the risk of a further relapse of his Schizophrenia. </s></p></div3></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Outcome</head><p n="p67.74"><s n="s1.3;p67.74"><name type="other"/> is still an inpatient on <name type="other"/> Ward at <name type="other"/>. <name type="other"/> is becoming more isolated, he stays in his room all day but will get up later in the evening when the other clients have gone to bed. <name type="other"/> appears to be scared of the other clients who can be very loud and 'opinionated'. <name type="other"/> is also reluctant to go out with his sister who he has a good relationship with. <name type="other"/>'s appetite is improving slightly although he now eats his meals in his room. </s><s n="s2.3;p67.74">There is no real improvement in his psychological symptoms and he has now started to develop somatic symptoms (constipation), which may indicate that his depression is becoming more severe. <name type="other"/> did venture outside to play football with members of staff and other clients and appeared to enjoy this but on return to the ward his low mood quickly returned. </s><s n="s3.3;p67.74">Unfortunately there is no opportunity at present to move <name type="other"/> to another ward where he may feel less intimated by other clients due to bed shortage. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Relevant Core Issues, Evidence Based Care and Future Research</head><p n="p68.74"><s n="s1.7;p68.74">Schizophrenia is viewed as a neurodevelopmental disorder caused by an interaction of genetic and environmental factors. </s><s n="s2.7;p68.74">The neurodevelopmental hypothesis suggests that "factors acting during gestation may increase the risk of schizophrenia through an effect on intra uterine brain development" [4]. </s><s n="s3.7;p68.74">Such factors include viral infection in utero and obstetric complications. </s><s n="s4.7;p68.74">Genetic factors are also thought to play a role in schizophrenia and several susceptibility genes have been identified [5]. </s><s n="s5.7;p68.74">Altered neurotransmission is considered to play a key role in the expression of schizophrenic symptoms. </s><s n="s6.7;p68.74">It was initially thought that a high level of dopamine transmission in the mesolimbic area of the brain, was responsible for the positive, psychotic symptoms seen in schizophrenia. </s><s n="s7.7;p68.74">Imaging and post mortem findings have led to the development of a dual hypothesis in which a reduced level of dopamine activity in the prefrontal cortex is associated with the negative and cognitive symptoms of schizophrenia [6]. </s></p><p n="p69.74"><s n="s1.8;p69.74">The course of schizophrenia varies, approx 10% of patients never recover from their first schizophrenic episode and approximately 80% do recover [6]. </s><s n="s2.8;p69.74">In most cases schizophrenia has a remitting/relapsing course and a depressive state normally follows the resolution of an acute psychotic episode. </s><s n="s3.8;p69.74">However, there is little research on the aetiology, course, prognosis or treatment of post schizophrenic depression. </s><s n="s4.8;p69.74">As depression is associated with a high risk of suicide, the management of such symptoms is an important part of improving prognosis in patients with schizophrenia. </s><s n="s5.8;p69.74">The depressive symptoms are usually treated with antidepressants, however, there is no substantial evidence to support their use [7] and further research is obviously needed in this area. <name type="other"/> was prescribed Olanzapine for his psychotic symptoms on admission. </s><s n="s6.8;p69.74">This atypical antipsychotic has also been shown to reduce depressive symptoms in patients with unipolar psychotic depression [8] and so may reduce the severity of post schizophrenic depressive symptoms. </s><s n="s7.8;p69.74">An important part of management is to reduce the risk of further relapse and it has been shown that psychoeducational approaches can help to reduce readmission rates compared with standard care [9]. </s><s n="s8.8;p69.74">A multidisciplinary team approach must be taken to ensure that all factors contributing to potential relapse are managed. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Impact on your learning</head><p rend="bulleted" n="p70.74"><s n="s1.1;p70.74">Taking a full psychiatric history and the importance of obtaining collateral information to confirm features of the history and past psychiatric illnesses etc. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p71.74"><s n="s1.1;p71.74">The difficulties in trying to diagnose a patient within the ICD 10 classification system as patients may have complex cases with symptoms applicable to a range of diagnoses. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p72.74"><s n="s1.1;p72.74">It is important to identify the most prominent symptoms in order to reach an appropriate diagnosis and develop an effective management plan. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p73.74"><s n="s1.1;p73.74">The importance of social and psychological inputs into a patient's management plan and the various methods of achieving this. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p74.74"><s n="s1.1;p74.74">The risk of patients becoming dependent on the ward </s></p></div1></body><back><div1 type="bibliography"><head rend="bold">References</head><p>1 Nice Guidelines - Schizophrenia [Internet] <seg type="URL" n="http://www.nice.org.uk/page.aspx?o=42424"/></p><p>2 British National Formulary 48. <hi rend="italic">BMA, British Pharmaceutical Company</hi>. September 2004</p><p>3 T Turner. Your Questions answered - Schizophrenia. Churchill Livingstone. 2003</p><p>4 Stevens, L and Rodin, I. Psychiatry - an illustrated colour text. Churchill Livingstone 2001</p><p>5 Harrison PJ, Owen MJ. Genes for schizophrenia? Recent findings and their pathophysiological implications. <hi rend="italic">Lancet</hi> 2003 361:417-419</p><p>6 Frangou, S and Kington J. Psychiatry Part 1. Schizophrenia. <hi rend="italic">Medicine.</hi> 32:(7) 2004</p><p>7 Whitehead C, Moss S, Cardno A, Lewis G. Antidepressants for people with both schizophrenia and depression. <hi rend="italic">The Cochrane Database of Systematic Reviews</hi> 2002, Issue 2.</p><p>8 Nelson EB, Rielage E, Welge JA, Keck PE. An open trial of olanzapine in the treatment of patients with psychotic depression. <hi rend="italic">Annals of Clinical Psychiatry</hi> 13 (3) 2001</p><p>9 Pekkala E, Merinder L. Psychoeducation for schizophrenia. <hi rend="italic">The Cochrane Database of Systematic Reviews</hi> 2002, Issue 2</p><p>Not cited:</p><p>Gelder M, Mayou R and Cowen P. Shorter Oxford Textbook of Psychiatry. Oxford University Press 2001</p><p>ICD Classification of Mental and Behavioural Disorders. <hi rend="italic">WHO</hi> 1998</p></div1><div1 type="appendix"><head rend="bold">ASPECTS OF CASE AS RECORDED IN SUMMARY OF PORTFOLIO CASES•</head><p/></div1><div1 type="appendix"><head rend="bold">PORTFOLIO COMPLETION CERTIFICATE</head><p/></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
