<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_0203h" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Portfolio Case presentation number: 10 CTS</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">proforma</note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">appendices: 	ASPECTS OF CASE AS RECORDED IN SUMMARY OF PORTFOLIO CASES, PORTFOLIO COMPLETION CERTIFICATE</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">4</p><p n="date">2005-05</p><p n="module title">Other rotations</p><p n="module code">unknown</p><p n="genre family">Case study</p><p n="discipline">Medicine</p><p n="disciplinary group">LS</p><p n="grade">D</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">2689</p><p n="number of s-units">140</p><p n="number of p">76</p><p n="number of tables">0</p><p n="number of figures">0</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">12</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">9</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">19.2</p><p n="average s-units per p">1.8</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">f</p><p n="year of birth">1979</p><p n="first language">English</p><p n="education">UKA</p><p n="course">Medicine</p><p n="student ID">0203</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><docTitle><titlePart rend="bold">PORTFOLIO CASE No:</titlePart></docTitle><titlePart>Patient Initials<name type="other"/> Hospital Number Age 53 Gender female</titlePart><titlePart>Portfolio Case presentation number: 10 Phase 2 course document objectives(s) 4.1, 4.18, Has the patient' permission, including for follow up contact by telephone, been sought and recorded in the case notes?</titlePart></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="bold">Referral information</hi> Source of referral and a summary of key information</head><p n="p1.76"><s n="s1.1;p1.76"><name type="other"/> was referred to the outpatient clinic by her GP after complaining of tingling sensations and weakness of both hands. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="bold">History</hi> All <hi rend="bold italic">relevant</hi> information gathered from the patient about the presenting illness, co-existing problems, current treatment, <hi rend="italic">significant</hi> past medical history and the social and family background. The patient's view of the nature of the problem and their expectations for treatment.</head><div2><head rend="underlined bold">Presenting Complaint</head><p n="p2.76"><s n="s1.1;p2.76">Tingling and numbness in both hands </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined bold">History of presenting complaint</head><p n="p3.76"><s n="s1.6;p3.76"><name type="other"/> is a right handed lady who attended the outpatient clinic complaining of tingling and numbness in the hands. </s><s n="s2.6;p3.76">The tingling and numbness started approximately 2 years ago in the right hand but was now also affecting the left hand. <name type="other"/> also stated that she experiences a burning pain in both hands during the night which wakes her. </s><s n="s3.6;p3.76">The pain is worse in the right hand and is relieved by shaking the hand or daggling it out of the bed. </s><s n="s4.6;p3.76">The pain can radiate to the forearm but <name type="other"/> does not like to take painkillers to relieve the pain. </s><s n="s5.6;p3.76">Over the past few months, <name type="other"/> has experienced weakness in her right hand and has found difficulty grasping objects e.g. holding a book to read. </s><s n="s6.6;p3.76">Typing at work also aggravates the symptoms. </s></p><p n="p4.76"><s n="s1.1;p4.76"><name type="other"/> has suffered with occasional neck pain since she ruptured her acromioclavicular ligament in <name type="date"/>, but did not report any limitation in the range of neck movements. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined bold">Past Medical History</head><list type="bulleted"><head rend="underlined">Medical</head><item>Rupture Acromioclavicular ligament 1992</item><item>No asthma</item><item>No angina</item><item>No epilepsy</item><item>No DVT/PE</item></list><list type="bulleted"><head rend="bold">Surgical</head><item>Hysterectomy 1997</item><item>Excision right volar ganglion</item></list><p n="p5.76"/></div2><div2><head rend="underlined bold">Social History</head><p n="p6.76"><s n="s1.2;p6.76"><name type="other"/> is an office worker who lives with her husband in <name type="other"/>. </s><s n="s2.2;p6.76">She is a non-smoker and drinks approx 2 units of alcohol/week. <name type="other"/> has 2 children. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined bold">Allergies</head><p n="p7.76"><s n="s1.1;p7.76">There are no known allergies </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined bold">Medication</head><p n="p8.76"><s n="s1.1;p8.76">No medication </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined bold">Family History</head><p n="p9.76"><s n="s1.1;p9.76">Mother suffers from Rheumatoid Arthritis </s></p><p n="p10.76"><s n="s1.1;p10.76">No other significant family history </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined bold">Systems Review</head><p n="p11.76"><s rend="bold" n="s1.1;p11.76">Cardiovascular system </s></p><p n="p12.76"><s n="s1.1;p12.76">No chest pain, orthopnoea or PND. No oedema </s></p><p n="p13.76"><s rend="bold" n="s1.1;p13.76">Respiratory System </s></p><p n="p14.76"><s n="s1.2;p14.76">No shortness of breath or cough. </s><s n="s2.2;p14.76">No wheeze or haemoptysis. </s></p><p n="p15.76"><s rend="bold" n="s1.1;p15.76">Gastrointestinal System </s></p><p n="p16.76"><s n="s1.2;p16.76">No nausea, vomiting or significant weight loss. </s><s n="s2.2;p16.76">No dysphagia, no change in bowel habits. </s></p><p n="p17.76"><s rend="bold" n="s1.1;p17.76">Genitourinary System </s></p><p n="p18.76"><s n="s1.1;p18.76">No change in urinary frequency, no incontinence. </s></p><p n="p19.76"><s rend="bold" n="s1.1;p19.76">Central Nervous System </s></p><p n="p20.76"><s n="s1.1;p20.76">No headaches, blackouts or visual disturbances. </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="bold">Analysis of history</hi> The most likely single cause of the presentation, other possible causes and reasons for these choices. The findings to be looked for on physical examination to help decide the cause.</head><p n="p21.76"><s n="s1.1;p21.76"><name type="other"/> displays the classic symptoms of Carpal Tunnel Syndrome (CTS). </s></p><p n="p22.76"><s n="s1.7;p22.76">The carpal tunnel is a narrow fibro-osseous canal bound by the carpal bones and superiorly the flexor retinaculum. </s><s n="s2.7;p22.76">The 'tunnel' contains the median nerve and the nine extrinsic flexors of the fingers and thumb with their synovial sheaths. </s><s n="s3.7;p22.76">The median nerve supplies motor innervation to the three muscles of the thenar eminence - Abductor Pollicis Brevis, Opponens Pollicis and Flexor Pollicis Brevis and the 1 <hi rend="sup">st</hi> and 2 <hi rend="sup">nd</hi> lumbricals. </s><s n="s4.7;p22.76">It also supplies sensory innervation to the thumb, medial three fingers and radial side of the ring finger. </s><s n="s5.7;p22.76">A sensory branch of the median nerve originates proximal to the carpal tunnel and provides sensation to the thenar eminence. </s><s n="s6.7;p22.76">In the normal carpal tunnel there is barely room for all of the tendons and the median nerve. </s><s n="s7.7;p22.76">If there is a decrease in the size of the canal or an increase in the volume of contents, structure will inevitably be compressed. </s></p><p n="p23.76"><s n="s1.3;p23.76">In carpal tunnel syndrome, patients present with symptoms of tingling and numbness in the hand due to compression of the median nerve. </s><s n="s2.3;p23.76">Sensation is altered in the distribution of the median nerve (the thenar eminence is spared due to the sensory branch supplying this region originating proximal to the carpal tunnel). </s><s n="s3.3;p23.76">The ulnar nerve supplies the little finger and the lateral side of the ring finger and so sensation here should also be normal on examination. </s></p><p n="p24.76"><s n="s1.1;p24.76">Specific tests for examination to support working diagnosis: </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p25.76"><s n="s1.1;p25.76">Phalens Test: Hold the wrist fully flexed for a couple of minutes - sensory symptoms may be reproduced </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p26.76"><s n="s1.1;p26.76">Tinnels Test: Percuss over the flexor retinaculum (median nerve) to elicit sensory symptoms </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p27.76"><s n="s1.1;p27.76">Positive Pressure: Apply pressure to the midpoint of the Flexor Retinaculum to elicit sensory symptoms. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p28.76"><s n="s1.1;p28.76">Weakness of thumb abduction - due to loss of innervation to the Abductor Pollicis Brevis muscle </s></p><list type="bulleted"><head>Causes:</head><item>Non specific tenosynovial proliferation (most common)</item><item><hi rend="bold">P</hi>regnancy</item><item><hi rend="bold">R</hi>heumatoid Arthritis</item><item><hi rend="bold">A</hi>rthritis (degenerative)</item><item><hi rend="bold">G</hi>rowth hormone abnormalities (acromegaly)</item><item><hi rend="bold">M</hi>etabolic (hypothyroidism, gout)</item><item><hi rend="bold">A</hi>lcoholism</item><item><hi rend="bold">T</hi>umours</item><item><hi rend="bold">I</hi>diopathic</item><item><hi rend="bold">C</hi>onnective Tissue Disorders</item></list><p n="p29.76"><s n="s1.1;p29.76">Differential diagnosis: </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p30.76"><s n="s1.1;p30.76"><hi rend="bold">Cervical Spondylosis</hi> - Compression of roots C6 and C7 can present with similar symptoms to those described in CTS. However, pain and paraesthesia at night are more commonly reported in CTS. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p31.76"><s n="s1.4;p31.76"><hi rend="bold">Proximal Medial Nerve Compression</hi> - The median nerve can be compressed beneath one of several structures around the elbow e.g. bicipital aponeurosis. </s><s n="s2.4;p31.76">Symptoms are similar to those seen in CTS, however night pain is uncommon and pain in the forearm is common. </s><s n="s3.4;p31.76">On examination, Phalens test is negative and the pain can be elicited by resisting flexion of the elbow with the arm in supination (to tighten the biciptal aponeurosis). </s><s n="s4.4;p31.76">Nerve conduction studies are used to localize the level of the compression. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p32.76"><s n="s1.4;p32.76"><hi rend="bold">Anterior Interosseous Nerve Syndrome</hi> - can be selectively compressed at the same sites as the proximal median nerve. </s><s n="s2.4;p32.76">Symptoms include motor weakness but no changes to sensation. </s><s n="s3.4;p32.76">The anterior interosseous nerve supplies flexor digitorum profundus (FDP), flexor pollicis longus (FPL) and pronator quadratus. </s><s n="s4.4;p32.76">On examination the patient is unable to make the 'ok' sign i.e. pinching with the thumb and index finger joints flexed, due to weakness of the FPL and FDP muscles. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="bold">Physical examination</hi> Highlight the findings most relevant to your clinical problem solving by underlining them</head><div2><head rend="underlined bold">General Examination </head><p n="p33.76"><s n="s1.3;p33.76">On examination <name type="other"/> was sitting in the chair and looked comfortable and alert at rest. </s><s n="s2.3;p33.76">There was no evidence of wrist splints and no finger clubbing, jaundice, anaemia, clubbing, cyanosis, oedema or lymphadenopathy. </s><s n="s3.3;p33.76">No rheumatic nodules. </s></p><list type="bulleted"><head rend="bold">General Observations</head><item>Pulse - 74 regular</item><item>Blood Pressure - 138/56</item><item>Respiratory Rate - 14 pm</item></list><list type="simple"><head rend="underlined">CVS:</head><item>No scars or deformities. HS I + II + 0 </item><item>JVP →</item></list><list type="simple"><head rend="underlined">RS:</head><item>Clear vesicular breath sounds</item></list><list type="simple"><head rend="underlined">GI:</head><item>Abdomen soft and non tender, Bowel sounds normal</item><item>No masses or organomegaly.</item></list><list type="simple"><head rend="underlined">CNS </head><item>GCS 15/15</item></list></div2><div2><head rend="underlined bold">Musculoskeletal Examination</head><div3><head>Examination of hands</head><p n="p34.76"><s rend="bold" n="s1.1;p34.76">Look </s></p><p n="p35.76"><s n="s1.4;p35.76">Right hand - Mild wasting of thenar eminence muscles. </s><s n="s2.4;p35.76">No change in colour. </s><s n="s3.4;p35.76">No guttering of dorsal web spaces (to indicate ulna nerve/ant interosseous muscle damage). </s><s n="s4.4;p35.76">Longitudinal 3cm scar over anterior part of wrist </s></p><p n="p36.76"><s n="s1.1;p36.76">Left hand - No thenar wasting, no colour change, no guttering of dorsal web spaces. </s></p><p n="p37.76"><s rend="bold" n="s1.1;p37.76">Feel </s></p><p n="p38.76"><s n="s1.4;p38.76">Right hand - No temperature difference. </s><s n="s2.4;p38.76">Reduced sensation in thumb and index finger. </s><s n="s3.4;p38.76">Sensation in little finger and lateral half ring finger intact. </s><s n="s4.4;p38.76">Tender on palpation over region of scar. </s></p><p n="p39.76"><s n="s1.2;p39.76">Left hand - No temperature difference. </s><s n="s2.2;p39.76">Reduced sensation in thumb, sensation in little finger and lateral half ring finger intact. </s></p><p n="p40.76"><s n="s1.1;p40.76">Anterior Interosseous nerve (ok sign), ulnar nerve (sensation in little and lat half ring finger) and radial nerve (resisted extension) intact bilaterally. </s></p><p n="p41.76"><s rend="bold" n="s1.1;p41.76">Move </s></p><p n="p42.76"><s n="s1.2;p42.76">Reduced strength of thumb abduction in right hand compared to left hand. </s><s n="s2.2;p42.76">Good range in all other movements. </s></p></div3><div3><head>Special Tests</head><p n="p43.76"><s n="s1.1;p43.76">Tinnels sign - negative bilaterally </s></p><p n="p44.76"><s n="s1.1;p44.76">Phalens test - positive in right hand, negative in left </s></p><p n="p45.76"><s n="s1.1;p45.76">Positive Pressure - positive in right hand, negative in left </s></p></div3><div3><head>Examination of elbow</head><p n="p46.76"><s n="s1.1;p46.76">Full range of movement, no pain elicited on resisted flexion with arm in supination. </s></p></div3><div3><head>Examination of Neck</head><p n="p47.76"><s n="s1.1;p47.76">Full range of movement with no pain elicited. </s></p></div3></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="bold">Analysis of history and examination</hi> Reasons for your choice of the cause of the patient's problem(s) and any other cause that still needs to be considered at this stage</head><p n="p48.76"><s n="s1.2;p48.76">The findings on examination support a diagnosis of Carpal Tunnel Syndrome. <name type="other"/> described her symptoms as being worse on the right hand. </s><s n="s2.2;p48.76">The examination would support this as both Phalens and the pressure test were positive in the right hand. </s></p><p n="p49.76"><s n="s1.3;p49.76">Sensation was intact bilaterally on each little finger indicating no ulnar nerve involvement. </s><s n="s2.3;p49.76">On examination the anterior interosseous nerve was also intact. </s><s n="s3.3;p49.76">No pain was elicited on resisted flexion of the elbow in supination indicating that the median nerve was not being compressed proximally. </s></p><p n="p50.76"><s n="s1.4;p50.76">The positive family history of Rheumatoid Arthritis would support this as a possible cause for <name type="other"/>'s CTS. However, <name type="other"/> had no other signs to support such a diagnosis. </s><s n="s2.4;p50.76">Another possible cause for <name type="other"/>s CTS would be inflammation of the flexor tendons/tenosynovial proliferation of the hand from overuse due to her occupation. </s><s n="s3.4;p50.76">There is no evidence of metabolic or connective tissue disorders from the history or examination as a possible cause. </s><s n="s4.4;p50.76">X-rays of the wrist may be implicated to discount a fracture, tumour or arthritis as possible causes of median nerve compression. </s></p><p n="p51.76"><s n="s1.1;p51.76">Nerve Conduction studies can be used to localise the area of nerve compression and confirm the working diagnosis, they are based on 4 principal measurements: </s></p><list type="bulleted"><item>The mean conduction velocity (motor and sensory)</item><item>Distal motor latency</item><item>Sensory action potentials</item><item>Motor action potentials</item></list></div1><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="bold">Formulation of the patient's problem(s)</hi> Encapsulate this in physical, psychological and social terms (the triple diagnosis)</head><p n="p52.76"><s n="s1.3;p52.76"><hi rend="underlined">Physically</hi> - <name type="other"/> is developing a physical disability due to her symptoms in that she is unable to grasp objects with her right dominant hand. </s><s n="s2.3;p52.76">The symptoms she experiences are also aggravated by movements she makes as part of her occupation i.e. typing. </s><s n="s3.3;p52.76">The symptoms are also affecting her ability to carry out many activities of daily living i.e. holding a brush, kettle </s></p><p n="p53.76"><s n="s1.1;p53.76"><hi rend="underlined">Psychologically</hi> - Psychologically <name type="other"/> is concerned about the progression of her symptoms and the fact that they are now affecting her work and many of the tasks she used to do around the home. <name type="other"/> is keen to receive help for her treatment and was encouraged to hear that the pain she experience during the night is likely to be reduced by painkillers. </s></p><p n="p54.76"><s n="s1.1;p54.76"><hi rend="underlined">Socially</hi> - The only leisure activity that <name type="other"/>'s symptoms are currently affecting is reading as she often finds that she is unable to hold a book for a lengthy period of time. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="bold">anagement</hi> Use the framework of RAPRIOP to structure your proposed management. Refer to the guidelines to the writing of portfolio cases for the details of the issues to be addressed under each heading.</head><div2><head rend="underlined">Investigations and observations</head><p n="p55.76"><s n="s1.1;p55.76">Nerve Conduction Studies - confirmed that <name type="other"/> is suffering from bilateral Carpal Tunnel Syndrome </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">Reassurance and explanation</head><p n="p56.76"><s n="s1.11;p56.76">Your nerve conduction studies have confirmed that the symptoms you are experiencing are due to a condition known as Carpal Tunnel Syndrome. </s><s n="s2.11;p56.76">There are a number of tendons and nerves which pass from the arm through a small tunnel formed by the structures around your wrist and into the hand. </s><s n="s3.11;p56.76">If the tunnel is too small tendons and nerves are compressed producing the symptoms you are experiencing. </s><s n="s4.11;p56.76">There are many reasons why this can occur, including pregnancy and rheumatoid arthritis. </s><s n="s5.11;p56.76">There are also a number of people who have symptoms for which a cause cannot be identified. </s><s n="s6.11;p56.76">Painkillers will help to relive the burning pain you experience during the night so do not be afraid to take these when the pain is severe. </s><s n="s7.11;p56.76">We can also refer you to the physiotherapists who can provide you with a splint to wear at night which may provide temporary relief. </s><s n="s8.11;p56.76">As your symptoms are quite severe and are affecting your activities at work I would like to offer a surgical solution to your problems. </s><s n="s9.11;p56.76">We can perform a small operation which can release the pressure in the tunnel and therefore stop the compression of the nerves and tendons. </s><s n="s10.11;p56.76">As your symptoms are most severe in your right hand, this would be the side that we would operate on initially. </s><s n="s11.11;p56.76">In the mean time I can ask your GP to prescribe some short-term medication which may provide temporary relief and enable you to continue with your work. </s></p><p n="p57.76"><s n="s1.1;p57.76">Are there any questions? </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">Prescription/medical intervention</head><p n="p58.76"><s n="s1.1;p58.76">The aims of intervention are to improve symptoms and reduce the physical signs of carpal tunnel syndrome, to prevent progression of and loss of hand function secondary to carpal tunnel syndrome and to minimise loss of time from work. </s></p><p n="p59.76"><s rend="bold" n="s1.1;p59.76">Non operative: </s></p><p n="p60.76"><s n="s1.1;p60.76">Nocturnal hand splint to reduce flexion of the wrist. </s></p><p n="p61.76"><s n="s1.1;p61.76">Short term Oral Prednisolone to try and reduce symptoms prior to surgery. </s></p><p n="p62.76"><s rend="bold" n="s1.1;p62.76">Operative: </s></p><p n="p63.76"><s n="s1.1;p63.76"><hi rend="bold">Open Surgical Division of Flexor Retinaculum</hi> - incision kept to ulnar side of thenar crease to avoid accidental injury to the palmar cutaneous and thenar motor branches of median nerve. </s></p><p n="p64.76"><s rend="bold" n="s1.1;p64.76">Endoscopic Carpal Tunnel Release </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">Referral and team working</head><p rend="bulleted" n="p65.76"><s n="s1.1;p65.76">Referral to physiotherapy for night splint </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p66.76"><s n="s1.1;p66.76">Letter to GP for short term prescription of oral Prednisolone </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="bold">Outcome</hi> A description of the progress of the patient as far as possible. This should include consideration of further issues to be resolved. Where appropriate you should contact by telephone patients who have been discharged home.</head><p n="p67.76"><s n="s1.1;p67.76"><name type="other"/> has been placed onto the waiting list for Carpal Tunnel release. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="bold">Evidence based care and issues for research</hi> A brief consideration of the evidence base required for the diagnosis and management of the patient's problem(s)</head><p n="p68.76"><s n="s1.2;p68.76">The symptoms of CTS can cause prolonged disability and time off work for many individuals. </s><s n="s2.2;p68.76">Indeed in 1999, carpal tunnel syndrome ranked the highest in respect to number of days away from work amongst work place injuries in the United States [1]. </s></p><p n="p69.76"><s n="s1.2;p69.76">Nocturnal wrist splints can be used to retain the hand in neutral alignment and prevent flexion of the wrist and therefore reduce symptoms. </s><s n="s2.2;p69.76">Evidence has shown that nocturnal splinting provides a significant improvement in symptoms compared to no treatment [2]. </s></p><p n="p70.76"><s n="s1.5;p70.76">Due to the waiting list for operations such as Carpal Tunnel release, many patients require interim treatment to enable them to continue with their occupational duties. </s><s n="s2.5;p70.76">Oral Prednisolone has been shown to significantly improve symptoms over a short time period i.e. </s><s n="s3.5;p70.76">2- 4weeks compared to placebo [3]. </s><s n="s4.5;p70.76">However, oral prednisolone should only be prescribed as an interim intervention due to the side effects produced by corticosteroids e.g. osteoporosis, cushings syndrome. </s><s n="s5.5;p70.76">Corticosteroid injections are thought to relieve symptoms over a longer time period compared to oral corticosteroids although the duration of benefit requires further research [6]. </s></p><p n="p71.76"><s n="s1.2;p71.76">For patients with severe symptoms, surgery is the most effective treatment option for relieving symptoms [4]. </s><s n="s2.2;p71.76">There are now 2 surgical options for release of the flexor retinaculum - open or endoscopic. </s></p><list type="bulleted"><head>Complications of open release are: </head><item>painful hypertrophic scar</item><item>reflex sympathetic dystrophy</item><item>prolonged wound secretion</item><item>wound infection</item><item>scar tethering and hypertrophy</item><item>loss of strength and swollen/stiff fingers [5] </item></list><list type="bulleted"><head>Complications of endoscopic release include: </head><item>partial transection of superficial palmar arch</item><item>digital nerve contusion</item><item>conversion to the open procedure</item><item>ulnar nerve paraesthesia, incomplete release</item><item>increased numbness in fingertips</item><item>loss of strength and mobility in wrist [5] </item></list><p n="p72.76"><s n="s1.3;p72.76">One RCT found that endoscopic carpal tunnel release was marginally more effective than open surgery in terms of functional status [8]. </s><s n="s2.3;p72.76">However the same article also concluded that endoscopic release was significantly more expensive than open surgical release [8]. </s><s n="s3.3;p72.76">Endoscopic release may therefore be less cost effective when compared to open surgical treatment. </s></p><p n="p73.76"><s n="s1.3;p73.76">Evidence shows that 34% of patient with idiopathic CTS had complete resolution of symptoms within 6 months of diagnosis [7]. </s><s n="s2.3;p73.76">Surgical intervention is therefore unnecessary in this group of individuals. </s><s n="s3.3;p73.76">Further research is warranted into the relative contributions of non-surgical forms of treatment and their duration of benefit. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="bold">Commentary</hi> A commentary on issues of health care delivery, ethical issues or disability relevant to the patient and/or problem</head><p n="p74.76"><s n="s1.5;p74.76">Carpal Tunnel Syndrome has been accepted as the most common entrapment neuropathy. </s><s n="s2.5;p74.76">The condition does not follow a predictable course. </s><s n="s3.5;p74.76">Some patients experience deterioration in hand function with both motor and sensory effects whilst others describe silent periods and intermittent exacerbations of symptoms. </s><s n="s4.5;p74.76">Carpal Tunnel Syndrome has an important economic impact affecting active working people, most commonly females. </s><s n="s5.5;p74.76">It may occur as a work related disorder leading to compensation claims and so effective treatment is vital. </s></p><p n="p75.76"><s n="s1.2;p75.76">Although complication rates from surgery are low, the effects of permanent weakness in the muscles of the thenar eminence may affect patients ability to continue with their occupation (which may be the case for <name type="other"/>). </s><s n="s2.2;p75.76">Therefore it is important to discuss the risks of the operation with the patient as resolution of symptoms may occur over time without intervention. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="bold">Impact on your learning</hi> Describe what you have learnt from this case</head><list type="bulleted"><item>Symptoms of CTS</item><item>Specific tests - Phalens, Tinnels, Positive pressure</item><item>Nerve Conduction Studies </item><item>Management of CTS</item></list><p n="p76.76"/></div1></body><back><div1 type="bibliography"><div2 type="bibliography"><head rend="bold">References</head><p>[1] Rider DA. Functional tests to quantify recovery following carpal tunnel release.2005 <hi rend="italic">J Hand Therapy.</hi> Jul-Sep;18(3):385-6.</p><p>[2] Manente G, Torrieri F, Di Blasio F et al. An innovative hand brace for carpal tunnel syndrome: a randomised controlled trial. <hi rend="italic">Muscle Nerve</hi> 2001:24:1020-1025</p><p>[3] Chang MH, Chiang HT, Lee SS, et al. Oral drug of choice in carpal tunnel syndrome. <hi rend="italic">Neurology</hi> 1998;51:390 - 393</p><p>[4] Verdugo RJ, Salinas RS, Castillo J, Cea JG. Surgical v's non surgical treatment for Carpal Tunnel Syndrome (Review) <hi rend="italic">Cochrane Library 2005</hi>. Issue 3</p><p>[5] Gerritsen AA, Uitdehaag BMJ, van Geldere D, et al. Systematic review of randomised clinical trials of surgical treatment for carpal tunnel syndrome. <hi rend="italic">Br J Surg</hi> 2001;88:1285 - 1295. </p><p>[6] Marshal S, Tardif G, Ashworth N.Local corticosteroid injection for Carpal Tunnel Syndrome (Review) <hi rend="italic">Cochrane Library 2005</hi> Issue 3</p><p>[7] Fatami T, Kobayashi A, Utika T etal. Carpal Tunnel Syndrome; its natural history. <hi rend="italic">Hand Surgery</hi> 1997:2:129-130</p><p>[8] Lorgelly PK, Dias JJ, Bradley MJ, Burke FD. Carpal tunnel syndrome, the search for a cost-effective surgical intervention: a randomised controlled trial. <hi rend="italic">Ann R Coll Surg Engl.</hi>2005: 87(1):36-40.</p></div2><div2 type="bibliography"><head rend="bold">References not cited</head><p>Apley AG and Solomon L. Orthopaedics and Fractures. 2<hi rend="sup">nd</hi> edition. Butterworth Heinemann Ltd 1994</p><p>Dandy DJ and Edwards DJ.Essential Orthopaedics and trauma. 3<hi rend="sup">rd</hi> edition. Churchill Livingstone 1998</p><p>Brown DE and Neumann RD. Orthopaedics secrets. 2<hi rend="sup">nd</hi> edition. Hanley and Belfus 1999</p><p>BNF September 2004 BMA</p></div2></div1><div1 type="appendix"><head rend="bold">ASPECTS OF CASE AS RECORDED IN SUMMARY OF PORTFOLIO CASES•</head><p/></div1><div1 type="appendix"><head rend="bold">PORTFOLIO COMPLETION CERTIFICATE</head><p/></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
