<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_0203j" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Portfolio Case presentation number: Shortness of breath</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">proforma</note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">appendices: 	ASPECTS OF CASE AS RECORDED IN SUMMARY OF PORTFOLIO CASES, PORTFOLIO COMPLETION CERTIFICATE</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">4</p><p n="date">2005-10</p><p n="module title">Other rotations</p><p n="module code">unknown</p><p n="genre family">Case study</p><p n="discipline">Medicine</p><p n="disciplinary group">LS</p><p n="grade">D</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">3131</p><p n="number of s-units">164</p><p n="number of p">112</p><p n="number of tables">1</p><p n="number of figures">0</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">14</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">20</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">19.1</p><p n="average s-units per p">1.5</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">f</p><p n="year of birth">1979</p><p n="first language">English</p><p n="education">UKA</p><p n="course">Medicine</p><p n="student ID">0203</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><docTitle><titlePart rend="bold">PORTFOLIO CASE No:</titlePart></docTitle><titlePart>Patient Initials<name type="other"/> Hospital Number A19610 Age<name type="date"/> Gender Female</titlePart><titlePart>Portfolio Case presentation number: Phase 2 course document objectives(s) Has the patient' permission, including for follow up contact by telephone, been sought and recorded in the case notes?</titlePart></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="bold">Referral information</hi> Source of referral and a summary of key information</head><p n="p1.112"><s n="s1.1;p1.112"><name type="other"/> was brought to A&amp;E by ambulance on <name type="date"/> at 8.00pm with shortness of breath </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="bold">History</hi> All <hi rend="bold italic">relevant</hi> information gathered from the patient about the presenting illness, co-existing problems, current treatment, <hi rend="italic">significant</hi> past medical history and the social and family background. The patient's view of the nature of the problem and their expectations for treatment.</head><div2><head rend="underlined bold">Presenting Complaint</head><p rend="bulleted" n="p2.112"><s n="s1.1;p2.112">Sudden onset of shortness of breath </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined bold">History of presenting complaint</head><p n="p3.112"><s n="s1.1;p3.112"><name type="other"/> is a known asthmatic who presented with shortness of breath which started 3 hours prior to admission. <name type="other"/> found that she suddenly became short of breath and red in the face, she was wheezing and struggling to breath and this was not relieved by her inhaler. <name type="other"/> also complained of a constant ache and tightness in her chest, which was worse on inspiration. </s></p><p n="p4.112"><s n="s1.1;p4.112"><name type="other"/> first felt unwell one week ago, she visited her GP complaining of a sore throat, shortness of breath, runny nose and a productive cough and was diagnosed as having a viral illness - no treatment was prescribed. </s></p><p n="p5.112"><s n="s1.1;p5.112"><name type="other"/> asthma is normally well controlled but is exacerbated if she has a chest infection (last asthma attack was two years ago after a chest infection for which she was hospitalised - non ITU/HDU). </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined bold">Past Medical History</head><list type="bulleted"><head rend="bold">Medical</head><item>Asthma</item><item>Mild hayfever</item><item>Right Keratoconus</item><item>No eczema</item><item>No Diabetes Mellitus</item><item>No angina</item><item>No epilepsy</item><item>No DVT/PE</item></list><list type="bulleted"><head rend="bold">Surgical</head><item>Umbilical hernia repaired as an infant</item></list><p n="p6.112"/></div2><div2><head rend="underlined bold">Social History</head><p n="p7.112"><s n="s1.2;p7.112"><name type="other"/> is an 18 year old student who lives with her parents and older brother in <name type="other"/>. </s><s n="s2.2;p7.112">She is currently studying health and social care at college. <name type="other"/> has never smoked and she drinks approximately 4 units of alcohol/week. <name type="other"/> has a cat but her asthma is no affected by it. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined bold">Allergies</head><p n="p8.112"><s n="s1.1;p8.112">Orange Squash - precipitates nausea and vomiting </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined bold">Medication</head><p n="p9.112"><s n="s1.1;p9.112">On Admission: </s></p><p n="p10.112"><s n="s1.2;p10.112">Ventolin (Salbutamol) Inhaler PRN Beta 2 receptors respond to circulating adrenaline by producing smooth muscle relaxation and bronchodilation. </s><s n="s2.2;p10.112">Salbutamol is a Beta 2 adreno receptor agonist and therefore potentiates the action of adrenaline </s></p><p n="p11.112"><s n="s1.1;p11.112">Becotide (Beclomethasone) ON Beclomethasone is a glucocorticoid which depresses the inflammatory response in bronchial mucosa and there prevents the hyper-respo-onsivenes seen in asthma. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined bold">Family History</head><p n="p12.112"><s n="s1.1;p12.112">Mother - Asthma </s></p><p n="p13.112"><s n="s1.1;p13.112">Father - Asthma and Type II Diabetes </s></p><p n="p14.112"><s n="s1.1;p14.112">Brother - Epilepsy </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined bold">Systems Review</head><p n="p15.112"><s rend="bold" n="s1.1;p15.112">Cardiovascular system </s></p><p n="p16.112"><s n="s1.2;p16.112">Chest pain associated with shortness of breath. </s><s n="s2.2;p16.112">No palpitations, orthopnoea, PND or peripheral oedema. </s></p><p n="p17.112"><s rend="bold" n="s1.1;p17.112">Respiratory System </s></p><p n="p18.112"><s n="s1.1;p18.112">Asthma is precipitated by cold weather and <name type="other"/> is occasionally short of breath in the morning </s></p><p n="p19.112"><s n="s1.1;p19.112">Wheeze when asthma is bad - normally relieved by inhaler </s></p><p n="p20.112"><s n="s1.1;p20.112">Exercise tolerance limited by asthma - swims approx 20 lengths per week </s></p><p n="p21.112"><s n="s1.1;p21.112">Shortness of breath wakes her during the night when she is ill </s></p><p n="p22.112"><s n="s1.1;p22.112">No pet allergies </s></p><p n="p23.112"><s rend="bold" n="s1.1;p23.112">Gastrointestinal System </s></p><p n="p24.112"><s n="s1.1;p24.112">No loss of appetite, no weight loss, no change in bowel habits, no dysphagia, no heartburn </s></p><p n="p25.112"><s rend="bold" n="s1.1;p25.112">Genitourinary System </s></p><p n="p26.112"><s n="s1.1;p26.112">No change in urinary frequency, Periods regular and normal </s></p><p n="p27.112"><s rend="bold" n="s1.1;p27.112">Central Nervous System </s></p><p n="p28.112"><s n="s1.2;p28.112">No headaches, blackouts or fits. </s><s n="s2.2;p28.112">Slight blurring in right vision - diagnosed right keratoconus </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="bold">Analysis of history</hi> The most likely single cause of the presentation, other possible causes and reasons for these choices. The findings to be looked for on physical examination to help decide the cause.</head><p n="p29.112"><s n="s1.1;p29.112">Impression - <name type="other"/> is an anxious 18 year old girl admitted to A&amp;E with shortness of breath on a background of a recent chest infection </s></p><div2><head rend="underlined">Differential Diagnoses</head><p n="p30.112"><s n="s1.4;p30.112"><name type="other"/> is a known asthmatic and the most likely diagnosis for her presentation is <hi rend="bold">acute exacerbation of her asthma</hi> due to her recent chest infection. </s><s n="s2.4;p30.112">Patients with asthma have airway hyper responsiveness which is exacerbated by certain triggers such as cold air, viral infections, drugs etc. </s><s n="s3.4;p30.112">The recent viral illness that <name type="other"/> has had may have exacerbated the hyper responsiveness in the airways triggering her asthma attack. </s><s n="s4.4;p30.112">The fact that her symptoms were not relieved by her normal inhalers would indicate that this is a severe attack of asthma. </s></p><p n="p31.112"><s n="s1.1;p31.112">Other possible diagnoses which should be excluded at this stage include: </s></p><p n="p32.112"><s n="s1.2;p32.112"><hi rend="bold">Pulmonary Embolism</hi> - <name type="other"/> has no risk factors for the development of a PE (e.g. obesity, Oral contraceptive pill, post surgery, smoking etc) and did not report any haemoptysis or dizziness. </s><s n="s2.2;p32.112">There was associated chest pain but this was a constant tightness rather than a sharp pleuritic pain as seen with a PE. Investigations for suspected PE: </s></p><p n="p33.112"><s n="s1.1;p33.112">Presence of D-Dimer in blood - no specific for PE but if absent excludes PE as a differential </s></p><p n="p34.112"><s n="s1.1;p34.112">V-Q perfusion scan - to assess ventilation perfusion mismatch </s></p><p n="p35.112"><s n="s1.1;p35.112">CT pulmonary angiography - to assess blood flow throughout lungs </s></p><p n="p36.112"><s n="s1.4;p36.112"><hi rend="bold">Pneumothorax -</hi> Pneumothorax can occur spontaneously or as a result of trauma. </s><s n="s2.4;p36.112">There was no history of trauma to the chest in this patient. </s><s n="s3.4;p36.112">A rare cause of a pneumothorax is asthma, patients often present with sudden onset of pleuritic pain and progressively increasing breathlessness. </s><s n="s4.4;p36.112">Physical examination may not reveal any further symptoms and this differential is excluded by chest x-ray. </s></p><p n="p37.112"><s n="s1.3;p37.112"><hi rend="bold">Anaphylaxis -</hi> There was no report of a direct precipitant to the attack of shortness of breath in the hours preceding the attack e.g. drugs, latex etc. </s><s n="s2.3;p37.112">In an acute presentation of shortness of breath, signs to look for on examination include - swelling/oedema of the tongue and lips, tachycardia and hypotension. </s><s n="s3.3;p37.112">At presentation <name type="other"/> displayed signs of wheezing and shortness of breath, which are also associated with an anaphylactoid reaction. </s></p><p n="p38.112"><s n="s1.2;p38.112"><hi rend="bold">Upper respiratory tract obstruction -</hi> This can occur due to inhalation of a foreign body, the patient may present with stridor, localised or generalised wheezing. </s><s n="s2.2;p38.112">This is an important differential as many patients may not even recall the aspirating event [1]. </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="bold">Physical examination</hi> Highlight the findings most relevant to your clinical problem solving by underlining them</head><div2><head>Examination on admission <name type="date"/> (taken from notes)</head><list type="bulleted"><item>Pulse - <hi rend="bold">105 tachycardic</hi></item><item>Saturation - 95% on air</item><item>Respiratory Rate - <hi rend="bold">22 pm</hi></item><item>Temperature 37.5 C</item><item>Blood Pressure 110/65</item></list><p n="p39.112"><s n="s1.2;p39.112"><name type="other"/> was distressed and anxious on admission, she was dyspnoeic and was unable to talk in sentences. </s><s n="s2.2;p39.112">There was an audible wheeze and she had a non-productive cough. </s></p><p n="p40.112"><s n="s1.1;p40.112">PEFR = 180 </s></p><p n="p41.112"><s n="s1.1;p41.112">(Best PEFR for <name type="other"/> = 420) </s></p></div2><div2><head>Examination <name type="date"/></head><div3><head rend="underlined bold">General Examination </head><p n="p42.112"><s n="s1.3;p42.112"><name type="other"/> was comfortable and alert at rest although she appeared to be quite anxious, she was not visibly short of breath. <name type="other"/> had nasal prongs and was on 2L of Oxygen, there was a pink venflon in the right hand and a becotide inhaler and peak flow meter at the bedside. </s><s n="s2.3;p42.112">On examination <name type="other"/> appeared pale and clammy, there was no clubbing, peripheral cyanosis, tar staining or asterexis. </s><s n="s3.3;p42.112">No anaemia, central cyanosis or cervical lymphadenopathy and no pulsus parodoxus. </s></p><list type="bulleted"><head rend="bold">General Observations</head><item>Pulse - <hi rend="bold">96 tachycardic</hi></item><item>Saturation - 99% on 2L Oxygen</item><item rend="italic">Respiratory Rate - 18 pm</item><item>Temperature 37.0 C</item><item>Blood Pressure</item></list></div3><div3><head rend="underlined">Respiratory</head><p n="p43.112"><s n="s1.2;p43.112">Inspection - No nasal flaring or obvious use of accessory muscles of respiration. </s><s n="s2.2;p43.112">No chest wall deformities or scars, symmetrical chest movement. </s></p><p n="p44.112"><s n="s1.2;p44.112">Palpation - Trachea central, symmetrical chest expansion. </s><s n="s2.2;p44.112">No vocal fremitus </s></p><p n="p45.112"><s n="s1.1;p45.112">Percussion - resonant </s></p><p n="p46.112"><s n="s1.1;p46.112">Auscultation - Vesicular breath sounds, no audible wheeze, right basal crackles </s></p><list type="simple"><head rend="underlined">CVS:</head><item>No scars or deformities. HS I + II + 0 </item><item>JVP →</item><item>CRT &lt; 2 secs</item></list><list type="simple"><head rend="underlined">CNS </head><item>GCS 15/15</item></list></div3></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="bold">Analysis of history and examination</hi> Reasons for your choice of the cause of the patient's problem(s) and any other cause that still needs to be considered at this stage</head><p n="p47.112"><s n="s1.2;p47.112"><name type="other"/> was found to be suffering from an acute asthma attack. <name type="other"/>'s PEFR on admission was 180 compared to her normal PEFR of 420. <name type="other"/> was unable to talk in complete sentences on admission, her respiratory rate was 22 and her heart rate was 105. </s><s n="s2.2;p47.112">These signs indicate that <name type="other"/>'s asthma attack was severe based on: </s></p><list type="bulleted"><item>Unable to talk in complete sentences</item><item>RR > 25/min</item><item>HR > 110/min</item><item>Peak expiratory flow rate &lt;50% of predicted or best</item></list></div1><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="bold">Formulation of the patient's problem(s)</hi> Encapsulate this in physical, psychological and social terms (the triple diagnosis)</head><p n="p48.112"><s n="s1.3;p48.112"><hi rend="underlined">Physically</hi> - <name type="other"/> did not appear to be dyspnoeic at the time of examination but appeared to be quite lethargic, this is likely to be a result of the acute asthma attack and her recent chest infection. </s><s n="s2.3;p48.112">It is therefore important that her energy/nutrition levels are maintained to promote her recovery. </s><s n="s3.3;p48.112">During management of an acute asthma attack it is important to monitor the patients pO2 and pCO2 levels to recognise the need for ventilation. </s></p><p n="p49.112"><s n="s1.2;p49.112"><hi rend="underlined">Psychologically</hi> - <name type="other"/> was frightened by the asthma attack and appeared to be anxious on examination. <name type="other"/> is not normally affected by her asthma and only uses her ventolin inhaler approx 2-3 time/week. </s><s n="s2.2;p49.112">This episode distressed her and she is concerned hat she will be unable to control her asthma on discharge from hospital. <name type="other"/> does not remember much about her state at the time of admission and this may be one of the reasons for her distress. </s></p><p n="p50.112"><s n="s1.1;p50.112"><hi rend="underlined">Socially</hi> - <name type="other"/> social activities are not greatly limited by her asthma as it is usually well controlled with her inhalers. <name type="other"/> may need to limit her physical activity over the next few weeks until she has recovered from the chest infection. <name type="other"/> should be advised on ways of limiting her exposure to triggers of her asthma at home by e.g. using an anti allergy mattress, ensuing her living space is dust free. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="bold">Management</hi> Use the framework of RAPRIOP to structure your proposed management. Refer to the guidelines to the writing of portfolio cases for the details of the issues to be addressed under each heading.</head><div2><head rend="underlined">Investigations</head><div3><head rend="bold">Oxygen Saturations</head><p n="p51.112"><s n="s1.1;p51.112">Pulse oximeter - measures percentage of Hb saturated with oxygen, provides indication of how much oxygen is required. </s></p></div3><div3><head rend="bold">Venous Blood Tests</head><p n="p52.112"><s n="s1.1;p52.112">Why? </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p53.112"><s n="s1.1;p53.112">FBC - raised WCC and neutrophils to indicate infection </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p54.112"><s n="s1.1;p54.112">Urea and Electrolytes - Urea can be raised in cases of pneumonia </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p55.112"><s n="s1.1;p55.112">ESR - inflammatory marker may be raised if there is inflammation </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p56.112"><s n="s1.1;p56.112">CRP - may be raised if she has a chest infection </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p57.112"><s n="s1.1;p57.112">Microscopy/ C+S - for evidence of infection </s></p></div3><div3><head rend="bold">Arterial blood Gases </head><p n="p58.112"><s n="s1.1;p58.112">Why? </s></p><p n="p59.112"><s n="s1.1;p59.112">To monitor the patients blood pH, pO2 and pCO2. </s></p><p n="p60.112"><s n="s1.5;p60.112">Patients who are short of breath are unable to breathe in sufficient amounts of Oxygen and so there pO2 levels fall. </s><s n="s2.5;p60.112">In order to increase their oxygen intake they begin to hyperventilate, which can also result in a fall in their pCO2. </s><s n="s3.5;p60.112">As the respiratory drive is usually increased during asthma exacerbations, a normal pCO2 indicates severe airflow obstruction and an increased risk of respiratory failure [2]. </s><s n="s4.5;p60.112">If the asthma attack is prolonged, the patient can tire and their muscles of respiration are unable to maintain the increased respiratory rate. </s><s n="s5.5;p60.112">The pCO2 levels begin to rise and can result in hypercapnia which may require the patient to be ventilated. </s></p><p n="p61.112"><s n="s1.1;p61.112">Life threatening attack is indicated by: </s></p><list type="bulleted"><item>High PCO2 >6 kPa</item><item>PO2 &lt; 8 kPa</item><item>Low and falling arterial pH</item></list><p n="p62.112"><s n="s1.1;p62.112">Blood gases should be repeated within 2 hours if: </s></p><list type="bulleted"><item>The patient is deteriorating</item><item>Initial pCO2 was normal/raised</item><item>Initial pO2 &lt; 8 kPa</item></list></div3><div3><head rend="bold">Sputum sample</head><p n="p63.112"><s n="s1.1;p63.112">Why? </s></p><p n="p64.112"><s n="s1.1;p64.112">The sputum can be cultured for evidence of infection, however this patient did not have a productive cough </s></p></div3><div3><head rend="bold">Urine Dipstick</head><p n="p65.112"><s n="s1.1;p65.112">Why? </s></p><p n="p66.112"><s n="s1.1;p66.112">If an atypical infection is suspected, legionella can be detected in the urine. </s></p><table id="BAWE_0203j-tab.001"><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p67.112"><s n="s1.2;p67.112"><name type="other"/>'s WCC was raised indicating infection. </s><s n="s2.2;p67.112">All other blood results were within normal limits, including urea which excludes pneumonia as a possible differential. </s></p></div3><div3><head rend="bold">Chest X-Ray (when stable)</head><p n="p68.112"><s n="s1.1;p68.112">Why - to exclude a pneumothorax and to look for signs of chest infection as a precipitant of the asthma attack. </s></p><p n="p69.112"><s n="s1.1;p69.112">Report: Right basal shadowing </s></p></div3></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">Reassurance and explanation</head><p n="p70.112"><s n="s1.4;p70.112"><name type="other"/>, the reason that you were admitted to hospital last night was because you had a severe asthma attack which you were unable to relieve with your own inhalers. </s><s n="s2.4;p70.112">Your chest x-ray shows that you have some shadows on the base of your right lung, which fit with your recent chest infection, and this was probably the trigger to your asthma attack. </s><s n="s3.4;p70.112">We gave you some oxygen and medication to help open up your airways so that it was easier for you to breathe. </s><s n="s4.4;p70.112">We kept you in overnight so that we could monitor your blood tests, respiratory rate and the amount of oxygen you were breathing. </s></p><p n="p71.112"><s n="s1.3;p71.112">As you know your asthma can be triggered by a number of things, therefore it is important that you avoid smoking and any animals that you are allergic to. </s><s n="s2.3;p71.112">You should also try to keep your room clean to reduce the number of dust mites and could try using an anti allergy mattress on your bed. </s><s n="s3.3;p71.112">Before you are discharged from the hospital, I would like to watch you using your inhaler so that we can be sure you are getting the maximum benefit from it, I will also provide you with some leaflets which explain how each of your inhalers works. </s></p><p n="p72.112"><s n="s1.1;p72.112">Are there any questions? </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">Prescription/medical intervention </head><p n="p73.112"><s rend="bold" n="s1.1;p73.112">Immediate management of asthma: </s></p><p n="p74.112"><s n="s1.1;p74.112">Sit patient up - 100% <hi rend="bold">O</hi>xygen via non rebreather mask </s></p><p n="p75.112"><s n="s1.1;p75.112"><hi rend="bold">S</hi>albutamol 5 mg nebulised with the Oxygen </s></p><p n="p76.112"><s n="s1.1;p76.112"><hi rend="bold">H</hi>ydrocortisone 200mg IV </s></p><p n="p77.112"><s n="s1.1;p77.112">If no improvement: </s></p><p n="p78.112"><s n="s1.1;p78.112"><hi rend="bold">I</hi>patropium Bromide - anticholinergic blocks Muscarinic receptors which when stimulated by Parasympathetic system increase bronchostrictor tone </s></p><p n="p79.112"><s n="s1.1;p79.112"><hi rend="bold">M</hi>agnesium (membrane stabiliser)/<hi rend="bold">T</hi>heophylline - Inhibits PDE = increase in cAMP = smooth muscle relaxation and bronchodilation </s></p><p n="p80.112"><s rend="bold" n="s1.1;p80.112">If Patient improves: </s></p><p n="p81.112"><s n="s1.1;p81.112">% Oxygen and Prednisolone 30-60mg/24 hours PO </s></p><p n="p82.112"><s n="s1.1;p82.112">Nebulised Salbutamol every 4 hours </s></p><p n="p83.112"><s n="s1.1;p83.112">Monitor Oxygen saturations and peak flow </s></p><p n="p84.112"><s rend="bold" n="s1.1;p84.112">Management of Chest Infection: </s></p><p n="p85.112"><s n="s1.1;p85.112"><name type="other"/> was commenced on: </s></p><list type="simple"><item>Erythromycin 300mg QDS</item><item>Amoxicillin 300 mg TDS</item></list></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">Observation</head><p n="p86.112"><s n="s1.1;p86.112">Effects of immediate treatment should be monitored: </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p87.112"><s n="s1.1;p87.112">Repeat PEFR 15-30 mins after starting treatment </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p88.112"><s n="s1.1;p88.112">Monitor pulse oximeter - maintain saturation >92% </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p89.112"><s n="s1.1;p89.112">Repeat ABG (as above) </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p90.112"><s n="s1.1;p90.112">Prior to discharge patients must have: </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p91.112"><s n="s1.1;p91.112">Been on discharge medication for >24 hours </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p92.112"><s n="s1.1;p92.112">Had inhaler technique checked </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p93.112"><s n="s1.1;p93.112">Peak flow rate >75% predicted or best </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p94.112"><s n="s1.1;p94.112">Steroid and bronchodilator therapy </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p95.112"><s n="s1.1;p95.112">Own PEF meter and management plan </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p96.112"><s n="s1.1;p96.112">GP appointment within 1 week </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">Referral and team working</head><list type="bulleted"><item>GP</item><item>ITU if severity increases</item></list><p n="p97.112"/></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="bold">Outcome</hi> A description of the progress of the patient as far as possible. This should include consideration of further issues to be resolved. Where appropriate you should contact by telephone patients who have been discharged home.</head><p n="p98.112"><s n="s1.1;p98.112"><name type="other"/> responded to first line treatment of her acute asthma attack, she was kept in hospital overnight for observations and was discharged the following day. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="bold">Evidence based care and issues for research</hi> A brief consideration of the evidence base required for the diagnosis and management of the patient's problem(s)</head><p n="p99.112"><s n="s1.7;p99.112">Asthma exacerbations are potentially life threatening with hypoxemia being an important cause of death in these patients. </s><s n="s2.7;p99.112">Hypoxemia is produced by ventilation perfusion mismatch and so administration of inspired oxygen can usually correct this. </s><s n="s3.7;p99.112">Historically the use of high flow oxygen delivered by a mask and reservoir bag has been considered the best way of delivering oxygen to patients with an acute asthma attack. </s><s n="s4.7;p99.112">However recent studies have shown that hyperoxia may be unsafe for some patients as it can worsen the patients paCO2. </s><s n="s5.7;p99.112">One RCT compared the effect of 2 oxygen concentrations on gas exchange in adult patients with severe acute asthma. </s><s n="s6.7;p99.112">The study concluded that administration of 100% oxygen for 20 minutes significantly increased paCO2 and decreased PEFR compared with administration of 27% oxygen [3]. </s><s n="s7.7;p99.112">The oxygen dose prescribed in severe acute asthma attacks should therefore be variable and based on achieving and maintaining an spO2 of 92% adults and 95% children using pulse oximetry [3]. </s></p><p n="p100.112"><s n="s1.3;p100.112">Bronchodilators (2 agonists) are used for the relief of the symptoms of asthma. </s><s n="s2.3;p100.112">Additional Aminophylline ahs also been sued in conjunction with B2 agonists but its role in additional benefit has been unclear. </s><s n="s3.3;p100.112">Indeed one review found that in acute asthma the use of Aminophylline did not result in any additional bronchodilation compared to standard care with Beta agonists [4]. </s></p><p n="p101.112"><s n="s1.4;p101.112">Many patients who are admitted to hospital with acute asthma are often prescribed antibiotics incase the cause of the exacerbation is a bacterial infection. </s><s n="s2.4;p101.112">However the cost, side effects and allergy risk associated with antibiotics call into question whether they should be prescribed in acute asthma. </s><s n="s3.4;p101.112">One systematic review found that there is insufficient evidence to support or refute the use of antibiotics in the case of acute asthma [5]. </s><s n="s4.4;p101.112">More research is required in this area to provide evidence on the efficacy of antibiotics in patients with acute asthma. </s></p><p n="p102.112"><s n="s1.3;p102.112">Corticosteroids are used routinely in the management of acute asthma although the route of administration remains controversial. </s><s n="s2.3;p102.112">Oral corticosteroids are easier to administer than IV and are potentially safer than IV corticosteroids although they take longer to reach therapeutic levels. </s><s n="s3.3;p102.112">However a research ahs shown that corticosteroids administered orally and IV had similar efficacy in the treatment of adults hospitalised with acute asthma [6]. </s></p><p n="p103.112"><s n="s1.4;p103.112">Patient education plays a vital role in the prevention of exacerbations of asthma. </s><s n="s2.4;p103.112">Indeed one systematic review found that educating patients how to self manage their asthma reduced hospital admissions, unscheduled visits to the GP and days off work [7]. </s><s n="s3.4;p103.112">A written individualised action plan enable the patient to adjust there medication in response to particular symptoms and signs. </s><s n="s4.4;p103.112">Such strategy avoids delays, prevents exacerbations and adds to the patient's sense of control over their asthma [2]. </s></p><div2><head rend="underlined">Chronic asthma</head><p n="p104.112"><s n="s1.4;p104.112">IgE plays a central role in the development of allergic diseases. </s><s n="s2.4;p104.112">People with allergies produce IgE when exposed to allergens, this causes a release of chemicals such as histamine that produce the symptoms associated with allergic diseases e.g. itching, sneezing, shortness of breath and cough. </s><s n="s3.4;p104.112">Recombinant monoclonal antibodies to IgE may play a role in the treatment of allergic diseases such as asthma. </s><s n="s4.4;p104.112">Indeed one review found that anti IgE led to a reduction in asthma exacerbations and in some cases withdrawal of regular inhaled steroid use [8]. </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="bold">Commentary</hi> A commentary on issues of health care delivery, ethical issues or disability relevant to the patient and/or problem</head><p n="p105.112"><s n="s1.3;p105.112">The prevalence of asthma is increasing worldwide with approximately 10% of people having suffered an asthma attack [9]. </s><s n="s2.3;p105.112">Exposure to certain stimuli produces inflammation and structural changes in the airways resulting in airway hyper responsiveness and obstruction to airflow. </s><s n="s3.3;p105.112">The aim of intervention is to: </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p106.112"><s n="s1.1;p106.112">minimise or eliminate symptoms </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p107.112"><s n="s1.1;p107.112">maximise lung function, prevent exacerbations </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p108.112"><s n="s1.1;p108.112">minimise the need for medication </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p109.112"><s n="s1.1;p109.112">facilitate self-management of asthma </s></p><p n="p110.112"><s n="s1.2;p110.112">Many asthmatics do not use their inhalers correctly resulting in only 10% of the medication actually reaching the patients airways. </s><s n="s2.2;p110.112">It is therefore vital that a patients inhaler technique is observed to ensure that they are gaining maximum benefit from it and to prevent their asthma treatment being inappropriately stepped up to include steroid use. </s></p><p n="p111.112"><s n="s1.1;p111.112">Upper respiratory tract infections and exposure to allergens are thought to be the most common triggers of severe asthma exacerbations. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="bold">Impact on your learning</hi> Describe what you have learnt from this case</head><list type="bulleted"><item>Management of acute asthma attack</item><item>Stepwise treatment of asthma:</item></list><list type="ordered"><item><hi rend="bold">Relief</hi> bronchodilators - short acting agonist e.g. Salbutamol</item><item>Step 1 plus <hi rend="bold">Preventer</hi> - regular inhaled steroid e.g. Beclometasone (Becotide)</item><item>Step 1 + high dose inhaled steroid or long acting agonist e.g. Salmeterol</item><item>High does inhaled steroid + long acting agonist + other bronchodilators e.g. Theophylline</item><item>Step 4 + regular oral steroid e.g. Prednisolone</item></list><list type="bulleted"><item>Differential diagnoses for a patient presenting with shortness of breath</item><item>Indications for ITU referral in severe asthma attack</item></list><p n="p112.112"/></div1></body><back><div1 type="bibliography"><div2 type="bibliography"><head rend="bold">References</head><p>1 Foreign bodies <seg type="URL" n="http://www.emedicine.com/radio/topic59.htm"/></p><p>2 Chesnutt MS. Management of asthma exacerbations. Best of clinical cornerstone. Volume 4. No.6</p><p>3 Rodrigo GJ, Verde MR, Perigalli V, Rodrigo C. Effects of short term 28% and 100% oxygen on paCO2 and peak expiratory flow rate in severe acute asthma. RCT. Chest 124 (4) Oct 2003</p><p>4 Parameswaran K, Rowe BJ. Addition of intravenous Aminophylline to Beta 2 agonists in adults with acute asthma. Review. The cochrane database of systematic reviews 2000 issue 4</p><p>5 Graham V, Lasserson TJ, Rowe BH. Antibitoics for acute asthma Review. The cochrane database of systematic reviews 2001 Issue 2</p><p>6 Cunnington D, Smith N, Steed K, Rosengarten P, Kelly AM, Teichtahl H. Oral v's IV corticosteroids in adults hospitalised with acute asthma. Pulmonary pharmacology and therapeutics. 2005, 18, 207-212</p><p>7 Gibson PG, Coughlan J, Wilson AJ et al. Self management education and regular practitioner review for adults with asthma. The Cochrane Library Issue 3, 2002.</p><p>8 Walker S, Monteil M, Phelan K, Lasserson TJ, Walters EH. Anti IgE for chronic asthma in adults and children. Review. The cochrane database of systematic reviews 2004 Issue 2</p><p>9 Clinical Evidence Issue 10 December 2003. BMJ Publishing Group</p></div2><div2 type="bibliography"><head rend="bold">References not cited:</head><p>Kumar P and Clark M. Clinical Medicine 5<hi rend="sup">th</hi> edition</p><p>Davey P. Medicine at a glance. Blackwell Science.</p><p>Longmore M, Wilkinson I, Torok E. Oxford Handbook of Clinical Medicine. 5<hi rend="sup">th</hi> edition</p><p>BNF September 2004 BMA</p></div2></div1><div1 type="appendix"><head rend="bold">ASPECTS OF CASE AS RECORDED IN SUMMARY OF PORTFOLIO CASES•</head><p/></div1><div1 type="appendix"><head rend="bold">PORTFOLIO COMPLETION CERTIFICATE</head><p/></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
