<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_0203a" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Portfolio Case presentation number: 5. Brain Tumour</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">proforma</note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">appendices: 	ASPECTS OF CASE AS RECORDED IN SUMMARY OF PORTFOLIO CASES, PORTFOLIO COMPLETION CERTIFICATE</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">4</p><p n="date">2005-03</p><p n="module title">Other rotations</p><p n="module code">unknown</p><p n="genre family">Case study</p><p n="discipline">Medicine</p><p n="disciplinary group">LS</p><p n="grade">D</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">3728</p><p n="number of s-units">178</p><p n="number of p">91</p><p n="number of tables">2</p><p n="number of figures">2</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">13</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">9</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">20.9</p><p n="average s-units per p">2.0</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">f</p><p n="year of birth">1979</p><p n="first language">English</p><p n="education">UKA</p><p n="course">Medicine</p><p n="student ID">0203</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><docTitle><titlePart rend="bold">PORTFOLIO CASE No:</titlePart></docTitle><titlePart>Patient Initials<name type="other"/> Hospital Number Age 66 Gender Female</titlePart><titlePart>Portfolio Case presentation number: 5 Phase 2 course document objectives(s) 13.9, 10.10, 10.3 Has the patient' permission, including for follow up contact by telephone, been sought and recorded in the case notes?</titlePart></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="bold">Referral information</hi> Source of referral and a summary of key information</head><p n="p1.91"><s n="s1.1;p1.91"><name type="other"/> has suffered from an intermittent speech impairment since <name type="date"/> 2005, she was referred to the neurosurgeon by Dr <name type="other"/> (Consultant neurologist) on <name type="date"/> </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="bold">History</hi> All <hi rend="bold italic">relevant</hi> information gathered from the patient about the presenting illness, co-existing problems, current treatment, <hi rend="italic">significant</hi> past medical history and the social and family background. The patient's view of the nature of the problem and their expectations for treatment.</head><div2><head rend="underlined bold">Presenting Complaint</head><p n="p2.91"><s n="s1.1;p2.91"><name type="other"/> is a 66 year old right handed female who has suffered from an intermittent speech impairment since <name type="other"/> 2005 and has recently noticed an inability to distinguish temperature in her right hand (2 weeks). </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined bold">History of presenting complaint</head><p n="p3.91"><s n="s1.6;p3.91"><name type="other"/> was on a 10 mile walk in <name type="date"/> 2005 when she found that she suddenly became unable to speak. <name type="other"/> continued to walk but then collapsed and had approximately three fits before the ambulance transferred her to <name type="other"/> hospital where she remained unconscious for the first 2/3 days. </s><s n="s2.6;p3.91">A CT scan was performed and a left sided CVA was diagnosed. <name type="other"/> recovered within 1 week and was discharged. </s><s n="s3.6;p3.91">After discharge, <name type="other"/> stated that she felt fine but would tire easily. </s><s n="s4.6;p3.91">2 weeks later, <name type="other"/> noticed that she was having intermittent problems with her speech, 'I knew what I wanted to say but couldn't say it'. </s><s n="s5.6;p3.91">Initially this only occurred when she went on long walks, it has become progressively worse and now occurs more frequently. <name type="other"/> has also had difficulty writing for the past 4 weeks stating that she has started to jumble her words. </s><s n="s6.6;p3.91">There have been no problems with her reading. <name type="other"/> has noticed that for the past 2 weeks she has been unable to feel hot things in her right hand and has noticed some tingling and numbness of the right hand and forearm. <name type="other"/> has had no headaches, no nausea or vomiting and no changes in her vision. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined bold">Past Medical History</head><list type="bulleted"><head rend="bold">Medical</head><item>Retinal vein occlusion left eye</item><item>Deaf in left ear</item><item rend="bold">Left sided CVA - <name type="date"/> 2005</item><item>No hypertension</item><item>No Asthma</item><item>No Diabetes</item><item>No hx of MI, angina</item><item>No hx of DVT/pulmonary embolism</item><item>No hx of Tuberculosis or Rheumatic Fever</item></list><list type="bulleted"><head rend="bold">Surgical</head><item>Laser surgery for macular oedema</item><item>Mastoid surgery</item></list><p n="p4.91"/></div2><div2><head rend="underlined bold">Social History</head><p n="p5.91"><s n="s1.2;p5.91"><name type="other"/> is an active, independent <hi rend="bold">66</hi> year old lady, she is retired school teacher and a widow of 20 years. <name type="other"/> currently lives alone but has 3 daughters who she sees regularly. </s><s n="s2.2;p5.91">One of <name type="other"/>'s daughters is a speech and language therapist. <name type="other"/> is a non smoker and drinks &lt; 1 unit of alcohol per week. <name type="other"/> used to do a lot of long distance walking but finds that she now tires more easily since the stroke in <name type="date"/>. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined bold">Allergies</head><p n="p6.91"><s n="s1.1;p6.91">There are no known allergies. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined bold">Medication</head><list type="simple"><item>Aspirin - used for secondary prevention of thrombotic cerebrovascular disease 75mg OD</item><item>Persantin Retard - used for the secondary prevention of ischaemic stroke and transient ischaemic attacks200mg BD</item><item>Ramipril - used for prevention of stroke 2.5mg BD</item><item>Simvastatin - stopped due to leg pain </item><item> Glucosamine </item></list><p n="p7.91"/></div2><div2><head rend="underlined bold">Family History</head><p n="p8.91"><s n="s1.1;p8.91">No significant family history </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined bold">Systems Review</head><list type="simple"><head rend="bold">Cardiovascular system</head><item>No chest pain, orthopnoea, PND or leg oedema.</item></list><list type="simple"><head rend="bold">Respiratory System</head><item>No shortness of breath or cough. No wheeze or haemoptysis.</item></list><list type="simple"><head rend="bold">Gastrointestinal System </head><item>No nausea, vomiting or significant weight loss. No dysphagia or odynophagia. No change in bowel habits. </item></list><list type="simple"><head rend="bold">Genitourinary System </head><item>No change in urinary frequency, no incontinence (stress/urge).</item></list><list type="simple"><head rend="bold">Central Nervous System</head><item>No headaches. No blackouts, dizziness or visual disturbances. Loss of temperature sensation in right hand. Numbness and tingling in right hand. No weakness of limbs reported. No dysarthria or dysphonia.</item></list><p n="p9.91"/></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="bold">Analysis of history</hi> The most likely single cause of the presentation, other possible causes and reasons for these choices. The findings to be looked for on physical examination to help decide the cause.</head><p n="p10.91"><s n="s1.14;p10.91"><name type="other"/> is a right handed lady indicating that her dominant hemisphere (i.e. that which controls language and mathematical function) is on the left. </s><s n="s2.14;p10.91">From the history it appears that <name type="other"/> is suffering from a type of dysphasia. </s><s n="s3.14;p10.91">Dysphasia is an acquired loss of production or comprehension of spoken and/or written language secondary to brain damage. </s><s n="s4.14;p10.91">There are two main types of dysphasia - Expressive or Receptive. </s><s n="s5.14;p10.91">Expressive dysphasia is characterised by non-fluent speech produced with effort and frustration. </s><s n="s6.14;p10.91">Signs to look for on examination include malformed words and impaired reading and writing. </s><s n="s7.14;p10.91">Comprehension is intact, patients understand questions and attempt to convey meaningful answers. </s><s n="s8.14;p10.91">There may be co existing right arm and facial weakness. </s><s n="s9.14;p10.91">It is caused by a lesion in the posterior part of the dominant third frontal gyrus (Brocas area). </s><s n="s10.14;p10.91">Receptive dysphasia is characterised by empty, fluent speech. </s><s n="s11.14;p10.91">The patient is oblivious of any errors, reading writing and comprehension are impaired. </s><s n="s12.14;p10.91">It is caused by a lesion in the posterior part of the first temporal gyrus (Wernickes area). </s><s n="s13.14;p10.91">The examination will therefore need to differentiate between the two types of dysphasia. </s><s n="s14.14;p10.91">The motor system will also need to be examined for any evidence of coexisting weakness. </s></p><p n="p11.91"><s n="s1.6;p11.91">Dysphasia may develop as a result of vascular, neoplastic, traumatic, infective or degenerative disease of the cerebrum. </s><s n="s2.6;p11.91">The sudden onset of <name type="other"/>'s initial episode of dysphasia in <name type="date"/> 2005 would indicate a vascular cause and this is supported by the diagnosis of a left sided CVA. However, the lack of associated weakness indicates that this was not a normal infarct affecting the motor cortex. </s><s n="s3.6;p11.91">Vascular lesions also tend to improve with time which does not fit with <name type="other"/>'s history as her dysphasia has been getting progressively worse. </s><s n="s4.6;p11.91">Cardiovascular examination will therefore be important especially blood pressure, arrhythmias and carotid bruits which may all indicate risk factors for stroke. </s><s n="s5.6;p11.91">The recurrent episodes of dysphasia could be due to a vascular cause such as transient ischaemic attacks which are temporarily reducing the blood supply to the region of brain controlling language. </s><s n="s6.6;p11.91">There has been no history of head trauma to indicate this as a relevant cause of the dysphasia. <name type="other"/> is keen to have a diagnosis for her condition as she has had no symptoms apart from those mentioned and says that she feels well in herself. </s></p><p n="p12.91"><s n="s1.7;p12.91">The episodes have increased in frequency since <name type="date"/> and have become progressively worse - this would indicate an expanding brain lesion. </s><s n="s2.7;p12.91">A space occupying lesion will lead to raised intracranial pressure depending on the size of the lesion. </s><s n="s3.7;p12.91">Signs of raised intracranial pressure include nausea and vomiting, headaches (often worse in the morning) and papilloedema, none of which <name type="other"/> reported in her history. <name type="other"/> didn't report any weight loss a sign associated with neoplasms. </s><s n="s4.7;p12.91">If the lesion is a neoplasm, the speed of onset of symptoms suggest a malignant rather than a benign neoplasm. </s><s n="s5.7;p12.91">Intracranial tumours are classified according to their tissue of origin with the most common group of primary brain tumours being gliomas. </s><s n="s6.7;p12.91">This group contains astrocytomas, glioblastoma multiforme, oligodendrogliomas and ependymomas. </s><s n="s7.7;p12.91">They commonly occur in the frontal, parietal or temporal lobe. </s></p><p n="p13.91"><s n="s1.3;p13.91">Likely diagnosis at this stage would point to either a neoplasm in <name type="other"/> dominant hemisphere. </s><s n="s2.3;p13.91">Another possible diagnosis could be recurrent TIA's due to e.g. carotid artery stenosis or valvular dysfunction as <name type="other"/> recalled the possibility that she had had rheumatic fever as a child. </s><s n="s3.3;p13.91">However from the history, <name type="other"/> does not appear to have any risk factors for atherosclerosis. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="bold">Physical examination</hi> Highlight the findings most relevant to your clinical problem solving by underlining them</head><div2><head rend="underlined"><hi rend="bold">General Examination</hi> <hi rend="bold">and higher centres</hi></head><p n="p14.91"><s n="s1.6;p14.91"><name type="other"/> is a right handed lady who was orientated in time and place. </s><s n="s2.6;p14.91">Dysphasia was apparent from taking the history. </s><s n="s3.6;p14.91">On examination <name type="other"/> was sitting in her chair reading. </s><s n="s4.6;p14.91">She was alert and comfortable at rest. </s><s n="s5.6;p14.91">There was no evidence of walking aids. </s><s n="s6.6;p14.91">No resting tremor or involuntary movements. </s></p><p n="p15.91"><s n="s1.1;p15.91">GCS 15/15 </s></p><p n="p16.91"><s n="s1.1;p16.91">PEARL </s></p><list type="bulleted"><head rend="bold">General Observations</head><item>Pulse - 80</item><item>Blood Pressure - 195/95</item><item>Respiratory Rate - 18 pm</item><item>Temperature 35.9 C</item></list><p n="p17.91"><s rend="bold" n="s1.1;p17.91">Focused examination (relevant to patients symptoms) </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p18.91"><s n="s1.1;p18.91"><name type="other"/> </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p19.91"><s n="s1.1;p19.91"><name type="other"/>'s speech was <hi rend="bold">non-fluent with mis pronunciation of words.</hi> </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p20.91"><s n="s1.1;p20.91">Naming - <name type="other"/> was able to name everyday objects - pen, watch, watch strap and watch clasp </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p21.91"><s n="s1.1;p21.91">Comprehension - <hi rend="bold"><name type="other"/> was able to understand the command 'touch your left ear with your left hand' but had difficulty carrying out the command</hi> </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p22.91"><s n="s1.1;p22.91">Repetition - <hi rend="bold"><name type="other"/> had difficulty repeating the sentence West Register Street</hi> </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p23.91"><s n="s1.1;p23.91">Writing - <name type="other"/> was able to write the sentence given to her </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p24.91"><s n="s1.1;p24.91"><name type="other"/> was able to subtract 7 from 100 but had difficulty subtracting 7 from 93 </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p25.91"><s n="s1.1;p25.91"><name type="other"/> stated that on previous examination she had had <hi rend="bold">difficulty identifying objects (with her eyes closed) placed in her hands with the right hand being worse than the left</hi> </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p26.91"><s n="s1.1;p26.91"><name type="other"/> was able to draw a complete house </s></p><table id="BAWE_0203a-tab.001"><head rend="bold">Upper Limb Peripheral Nerve Examination</head><row><cell/></row></table><table id="BAWE_0203a-tab.002"><head rend="bold">Lower Limb Peripheral Nerve Examination</head><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p27.91"><s rend="bold" n="s1.1;p27.91">Cranial Nerve Examination </s></p><p n="p28.91"><s n="s1.1;p28.91">Cranial Nerves 1-12 intact </s></p><list type="simple"><head><hi rend="underlined">CVS:</hi> HS I + II + 0, JVP →, No ankle oedema. No murmurs or carotid bruits</head></list><p n="p29.91"><s n="s1.1;p29.91"><hi rend="underlined">RS:</hi> Clear vesicular breath sounds </s></p><list type="simple"><head><hi rend="underlined">GI:</hi> Abdomen soft and non tender, Bowel sounds normal. No masses or organomegaly.</head></list></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="bold">Analysis of history and examination</hi> Reasons for your choice of the cause of the patient's problem(s) and any other cause that still needs to be considered at this stage</head><p n="p30.91"><s n="s1.3;p30.91">On examination <name type="other"/> was alert and comfortable. <name type="other"/>'s speech was non fluent and appeared to require a lot of concentration and effort. <name type="other"/> mis-pronounced words mid sentence and had to stop and think about the next work she wanted to say. <name type="other"/> had difficulty carrying out simple commands such as 'touch your left ear with your left hand and vv' indicating left-right disorientation indicating a possible lesion in the dominant (left) parietal lobe. <name type="other"/> had difficulty subtracting 7 from 93 but said that she had always had difficulty with mental arithmetic - possible degree of acalculia. </s><s n="s2.3;p30.91">On examination, <name type="other"/> was able to clearly write a sentence that was given to her. </s><s n="s3.3;p30.91">However, her diary showed evidence of dysgraphia and jumbling of words which had become progressively worse since <name type="date"/> (see attached sheets). </s></p><p n="p31.91"><s n="s1.2;p31.91">Unfortunately we were unable to examine <name type="other"/> for tactile agnosia but the patients own description of a previous examination suggests an element of astereognosis especially in the right hand supporting a possible lesion in the left parietal lobe. </s><s n="s2.2;p31.91">No evidence of special neglect as <name type="other"/> was able to draw a complete house when asked. </s></p><p n="p32.91"><s n="s1.2;p32.91">On examination of the cranial nerves, no abnormalities were detected. </s><s n="s2.2;p32.91">Examination of the upper and lower limbs showed no abnormalities although temperature sensation was not examined and <name type="other"/>'s history indicates a reduction in temperature sensation in her right hand and forearm. </s></p><p n="p33.91"><s n="s1.6;p33.91">From the history and examination it appears that <name type="other"/> is suffering from expressive dysphasia. </s><s n="s2.6;p33.91">This could be due to a space occupying lesion, or recurrent infarcts in the dominant hemisphere (Brocas area). </s><s n="s3.6;p33.91">The most likely cause of <name type="other"/>'s symptoms is a space occupying neoplasm as the symptoms have become progressively worse over a period of 3 ½ months, this makes a vascular cause less likely. </s><s n="s4.6;p33.91">If the lesion is a neoplasm, the speed of onset of symptoms suggests a malignant rather than a benign neoplasm. </s><s n="s5.6;p33.91">Diagnosis of such a lesion will require CT or MRI imaging of the brain. </s><s n="s6.6;p33.91">Location of a primary tumour should also be investigated by e.g. chest x-ray and abdominal ultrasound or CT, to determine whether the lesion is a primary or secondary brain tumour. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="bold">Formulation of the patient's problem(s)</hi> Encapsulate this in physical, psychological and social terms (the triple diagnosis)</head><p n="p34.91"><s n="s1.1;p34.91"><name type="other"/> is an independent lady who feels fit and well aside from her dysphasia symptoms. <name type="other"/> cannot understand why she has no other symptoms and feels that she may be able to train herself to improve her speech. <name type="other"/> is keen to have a diagnosis and begin any required treatment as her daughter is currently pregnant and she wants to be around for her. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="bold">Management</hi> Use the framework of RAPRIOP to structure your proposed management. Refer to the guidelines to the writing of portfolio cases for the details of the issues to be addressed under each heading.</head><div2><head rend="underlined">Investigations</head><p n="p35.91"><s n="s1.1;p35.91"><name type="date"/><hi rend="bold"> Carotid Doppler Ultrasound</hi> - to assess if there is any carotid/vertebral artery stenosis which may be causing recurrent TIA's </s></p><p n="p36.91"><s rend="italic" n="s1.1;p36.91">Report: </s></p><p n="p37.91"><s n="s1.1;p37.91">Right - Common carotid Artery clear, bulb and Internal carotid artery show mild plaque formation </s></p><p n="p38.91"><s n="s1.1;p38.91">Left - Common carotid Artery clear, bulb and internal carotid artery clear </s></p><p n="p39.91"><s n="s1.1;p39.91">Forward flow in both vertebral arteries </s></p><p n="p40.91"><s n="s1.1;p40.91">→<name type="other"/>'s periodic symptoms are therefore not due to TIA's from carotid artery stenosis. </s></p><p n="p41.91"><s n="s1.1;p41.91"><name type="date"/> </s></p><p n="p42.91"><s n="s1.1;p42.91"><hi rend="bold">Echo ordered</hi> - to assess valvular function as a possible cause of emboli and fitness for surgery </s></p><p n="p43.91"><s n="s1.1;p43.91"><name type="date"/> </s></p><p n="p44.91"><s n="s1.3;p44.91"><hi rend="bold">MRI scan</hi> <hi rend="italic">Report:</hi> MRI shows tumour in left tempo-parietal region with patchy enhancement and oedema. </s><s n="s2.3;p44.91">There appears to be effacement of the ipsilateral ventricle. </s><s n="s3.3;p44.91">Characteristics of the tumour indicate that it is most likely malignant (dark area in the centre of the lesion indicating necrosis, various signal characteristics reflecting the variable cellularity). </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0203a-pic.001"/><figure id="BAWE_0203a-pic.002"/></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">Reassurance and explanation</head><p n="p45.91"><s n="s1.4;p45.91">The results of the scan showing the brain tumour were discussed with <name type="other"/>. </s><s n="s2.4;p45.91">It was advised that the next step in the management plan should be an operation to enable a biopsy of the lesion to be taken. </s><s n="s3.4;p45.91">It was explained that this would provide a diagnosis of the character of the lesion so that a definitive treatment plan could be initiated. <name type="other"/> was aware that the report for the biopsy could take a few days. </s><s n="s4.4;p45.91">Management of the intracranial tumour will depend on its grade (benign/malignant), site (how approachable the tumour is) and type of lesion - (further surgery or conservative treatment). </s></p><p n="p46.91"><s n="s1.1;p46.91"><name type="date"/> </s></p><p n="p47.91"><s n="s1.1;p47.91">Dexamethasone 4mg QDS - prescribed to reduce any cerebral oedema caused by the lesion </s></p><p n="p48.91"><s n="s1.1;p48.91">Phenytoin 300 gm OD - to reduce the risk of any convulsions as a result of the cerebral tumour </s></p><p n="p49.91"><s n="s1.1;p49.91">Aspirin - stopped in preparation for surgery </s></p><p n="p50.91"><s n="s1.1;p50.91"><name type="date"/> </s></p><p n="p51.91"><s rend="bold" n="s1.1;p51.91">Echo </s></p><p n="p52.91"><s n="s1.2;p52.91"><hi rend="italic">Report</hi>: Left ventricle shows concentric left ventricular hypertrophy, good systolic function, trivial aortic regurge and tricuspid regurge, mild pulmonary regurge. </s><s n="s2.2;p52.91">No evidence of emboli </s></p><p n="p53.91"><s n="s1.1;p53.91">→ The echo confirms that there is no cardiac cause for <name type="other"/>'s symptoms and that her cardiac function is suitable for surgery. </s></p><p n="p54.91"><s n="s1.1;p54.91"><name type="other"/> </s></p><p n="p55.91"><s n="s1.1;p55.91"><hi rend="bold">Chest X-ray</hi> ordered - for evidence of a primary tumour </s></p><p n="p56.91"><s n="s1.1;p56.91"><hi rend="italic">Report</hi> - no hilar lymphadenopathy or evidence of a primary tumour </s></p><p n="p57.91"><s n="s1.1;p57.91"><hi rend="bold">CT Abdomen -</hi> for evidence of a primary tumour </s></p><p n="p58.91"><s n="s1.1;p58.91"><hi rend="bold">ECG ordered -</hi> fitness for surgery </s></p><p n="p59.91"><s n="s1.1;p59.91"><hi rend="italic">Report:</hi> No abnormalities detected to contraindicate surgery </s></p><p n="p60.91"><s n="s1.1;p60.91"><name type="date"/> </s></p><p n="p61.91"><s n="s1.1;p61.91"><hi rend="bold">Blood tests including Clotting Screen</hi> - to assess clotting times since aspirin had been discontinued </s></p><p n="p62.91"><s n="s1.1;p62.91">Prothrombin time 10.3 </s></p><p n="p63.91"><s n="s1.1;p63.91">INR - 0.8 </s></p><p n="p64.91"><s n="s1.1;p64.91">APTT ratio 0.7 </s></p><p n="p65.91"><s n="s1.1;p65.91">→ Values within normal range </s></p><p n="p66.91"><s n="s1.1;p66.91"><name type="date"/> </s></p><list type="bulleted"><head>Pre operative Observations</head><item>Blood Pressure - 160/100</item><item>Heart Rate 72 bpm regular</item><item>Respiratory Rate - 17 pm</item></list><list type="simple"><head>Pre Operative Medications</head><item>Ramipril 2.5 mg</item><item>Dexamethasone 4 mg - to reduce cerebral oedema</item><item>Lansoprazole 30 mg</item><item>Phenytoin 300 mg - to reduce the risk of seizures</item><item>Cefuroxime 1.5g IV - to prevent infection</item></list><p n="p67.91"><s n="s1.1;p67.91">Pre operative CT marker scan to mark the location of the lesion for surgery </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">Prescription/medical intervention </head><p n="p68.91"><s n="s1.1;p68.91"><name type="date"/> </s></p><p n="p69.91"><s n="s1.1;p69.91">Operative - Left parietal craniotomy for left parietal glioma/metastatic lesion biopsy </s></p><p n="p70.91"><s n="s1.1;p70.91">Benefits of surgery - for histopathological diagnosis of lesion for definitive treatment regime </s></p><p n="p71.91"><s n="s1.1;p71.91">Side Effects - Hemiparesis/hemiplegia, intracranial bleed, infection (risk of infection is doubled as metal clips will be used to reposition the piece of skull removed to enable access to the brain) </s></p><p n="p72.91"><s n="s1.1;p72.91">Local anaesthetic: Lignocaine (with adrenaline which acts as a vasoconstrictor to decrease bleeding from the scalp from incision) </s></p><p n="p73.91"><s n="s1.3;p73.91"><hi rend="bold">Comment:</hi> A craniotomy was chosen for this operation instead of a burr hole as the MRI scan showed that the lesion was in close proximity to the sylvian fissure which the middle cerebral artery runs through. </s><s n="s2.3;p73.91">A craniotomy also allows greater access to the brain and therefore more control should a bleed occur. </s><s n="s3.3;p73.91">In <name type="other"/> situation debulking of the tumour was contraindicated due to the location of the tumour and the risk to speech and motor function. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">Observation</head><p n="p74.91"><s n="s1.2;p74.91">Routine neurological observations were conducted on the stepdown ward. </s><s n="s2.2;p74.91">Dexamethasone 4mg was continued to reduce cerebral oedema post operatively. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">Referral and team working</head><p n="p75.91"><s n="s1.2;p75.91"><name type="other"/>'s case highlights the referral process between the consultant neurologist and the neurosurgical team. <name type="other"/> may need to be referred to the SALT post operatively to assist with her dysphasia. </s><s n="s2.2;p75.91">Future management will depend on the results of the biopsy. </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="bold">Outcome</hi> A description of the progress of the patient as far as possible. This should include consideration of further issues to be resolved. Where appropriate you should contact by telephone patients who have been discharged home.</head><p n="p76.91"><s n="s1.2;p76.91">On <name type="date"/>, <name type="other"/>'s expressive dysphasia appeared to be more pronounced. </s><s n="s2.2;p76.91">An urgent CT scan was ordered for evidence of a postoperative haematoma and <name type="other"/>'s neurological status was monitored. </s></p><p n="p77.91"><s n="s1.2;p77.91"><hi rend="bold">CT Report:</hi> The CT scan showed evidence of white matter oedema surrounding the left temporo-parietal lesion. </s><s n="s2.2;p77.91">There was no evidence of haematoma. </s></p><p n="p78.91"><s n="s1.1;p78.91">IV Dexamethasone (8mg) was prescribed to reduce the postoperative oedema and <name type="other"/>'s neurological status continues to be monitored. <name type="other"/> was informed that the symptoms should ease over the next few weeks. </s></p><p n="p79.91"><s n="s1.4;p79.91"><name type="date"/>, <name type="other"/>'s dysphasia appeared to be even more pronounced. <name type="other"/> also had slight facial drop on the right side. </s><s n="s2.4;p79.91">CT scan showed white matter oedema, midline shift and effacement of the ventricle on the ipsilateral side. </s><s n="s3.4;p79.91">There was also evidence of haematoma at the biopsy site which was not present on previous CT scan (<name type="date"/>). </s><s n="s4.4;p79.91">IV Dexamethasone 16 mg was prescribed. </s></p><p n="p80.91"><s n="s1.5;p80.91"><name type="date"/>, <name type="other"/>'s biopsy was reported as being a glioblastoma - WHO grade 4 (highest grading - most aggressive type of glioblastoma). </s><s n="s2.5;p80.91">The samples showed malignant glioma composed of highly pleiomorphic astrocytic type cells with scattered mitoses. <name type="other"/>'s future management is due to be discussed at the MDT meeting on <name type="date"/>. </s><s n="s3.5;p80.91">Once <name type="other"/>'s current symptoms have been resolved she will be discharge from the neurosurgical ward. <name type="other"/> will be referred to a consultant oncologist who will oversee her radiotherapy regime. </s><s n="s4.5;p80.91">As the glioma is of such a high grade it is likely that <name type="other"/> will receive high dose radiotherapy (20 fractions, 60 Gray) if this can be tolerated over approximately 4 weeks as an outpatient. </s><s n="s5.5;p80.91">The aim of the radiotherapy is to reduce the speed of growth of the glioblastoma and delay the speed of onset of symptoms. <name type="other"/> will be seen by the neurosurgeon approximately 6 weeks post discharge and will have a rescan approximately 6 weeks after the radiotherapy treatment has finished. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="bold">Evidence based care and issues for research</hi> A brief consideration of the evidence base required for the diagnosis and management of the patient's problem(s)</head><p n="p81.91"><s n="s1.4;p81.91">The incidence of brain tumours is 5-15 per 100,000 per year accounting for approximately 2% of deaths. </s><s n="s2.4;p81.91">The most common type of primary brain tumour is the glioma (43%) followed by meningiomas (10%) and pituitary adenomas (10%). </s><s n="s3.4;p81.91">Brain tumours may benign or histologically malignant but will rarely metastasise outside the brain. </s><s n="s4.4;p81.91">Approximately 20% of brain tumours are secondary metastases - most commonly from the lung, breast and kidney [1]. </s></p><p n="p82.91"><s n="s1.5;p82.91">Patients with presumed primary brain tumours have two surgical management options - biopsy or resection. <name type="other"/> was not displaying any signs of increased intracranial pressure and so resection of the tumour was not essential. </s><s n="s2.5;p82.91">Patients with severe raised intracranial pressure will obviously require debulking of the tumour in order to maintain adequate cerebral perfusion. </s><s n="s3.5;p82.91">Patients without signs of raised intracranial pressure or in patients where resection is impossible due to side effects of surgery, biopsy is the only option. </s><s n="s4.5;p82.91">In <name type="other"/>'s situation debulking of the tumour was contraindicated due to the location of the tumour and the risk to <name type="other"/>'s speech and motor function. </s><s n="s5.5;p82.91">Studies into the benefits of surgical resection versus biopsy for malignant gliomas are limited and it has been identified that further large multicentred RCTs are required to conclusively answer the question of whether prior to radiotherapy, resection or biopsy is superior [2]. </s></p><p n="p83.91"><s n="s1.8;p83.91">Treatment with chemotherapy has been disappointing as there is difficulty in finding a drug which will cross the blood brain barrier [1]. </s><s n="s2.8;p83.91">The benefit of chemotherapy in patients with glioblastoma is debatable. </s><s n="s3.8;p83.91">The Medical Research Council found no significant benefit in overall survival when evaluating the use of adjuvant chemotherapy in patients with glioblastoma [4]. </s><s n="s4.8;p83.91">However, recent RCT studies by the EORTC (European organisation for research and treatment of cancer) showed a statistically significant benefit to median survival of treating patients with radiotherapy and Temozolomide compared to radiotherapy alone [4]. </s><s n="s5.8;p83.91">This is obviously an area for further research. </s><s n="s6.8;p83.91">Current NICE guidance state that Temozolomide is not recommended for first-line chemotherapy treatment for patients with malignant glioma who have failed primary therapy (surgery and/or radiotherapy), except in the context of a randomised controlled trial against a standard-treatment comparator [5]. </s><s n="s7.8;p83.91">NICE are currently appraising a different type of treatment - the use of carmustine implants and Temozolomide for the treatment of newly diagnosed high-grade glioma [7]. </s><s n="s8.8;p83.91">Future treatment options for patients like <name type="other"/> may therefore be increased. </s></p><p n="p84.91"><s n="s1.4;p84.91">As stated previously, <name type="other"/> suffered from a haematoma and worsening of her dysphagia post operatively. </s><s n="s2.4;p84.91">Postoperative haematomas at the operative site occur in approx. </s><s n="s3.4;p84.91">5% of patients and a transient neurological deficit occurs in approx. </s><s n="s4.4;p84.91">10% of patients [6]. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="bold">Commentary</hi> A commentary on issues of health care delivery, ethical issues or disability relevant to the patient and/or problem</head><p n="p85.91"><s n="s1.9;p85.91">The care of patients with a brain tumour is multidisciplinary and requires the assistance of a neurosurgeon, an oncologist, a radiologist, an expert in radiation therapy and various members of the nursing team. </s><s n="s2.9;p85.91">Management varies depending on tumour location, tissue type, and co morbid conditions. </s><s n="s3.9;p85.91">Further neurosurgical treatment may involve the placement of a ventricular shunt if <name type="other"/>'s tumour produces sufficient mass effect to cause obstructive hydrocephalus. </s><s n="s4.9;p85.91">Despite the short duration of symptoms, Gliomas are often surprisingly large at the time of presentation, occupying much of a cerebral lobe. </s><s n="s5.9;p85.91">Indeed <name type="other"/>'s glioma measured approximately 3 cm on the MRI scan. </s><s n="s6.9;p85.91">The treatment of gliomas remains difficult as there are currently no curative treatments [3]. </s><s n="s7.9;p85.91">This is because by the time the tumour is detected clinically or radiographically, the tumour is beyond the reach of local control [3]. </s><s n="s8.9;p85.91">The treatment of patients with malignant gliomas is therefore palliative. </s><s n="s9.9;p85.91">The aims of surgery are to establish a pathological diagnosis, relieve mass effect, and if possible, achieve a gross total resection to facilitate adjuvant therapy [3]. <name type="other"/> is likely to suffer from the side effects of radiotherapy (nausea, hair loss, lethargy) as she is likely to receive a maximum dose due to the grading of her glioblastoma. <name type="other"/> will therefore need support and extra care during her treatment regime which can be provided by district and Macmillan nurses. <name type="other"/> will require a lot of support and encouragement during her palliative care and radiotherapy. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="bold">Impact on your learning</hi> Describe what you have learnt from this case</head><p n="p86.91"><s n="s1.1;p86.91">Focused examination for dysphasia </s></p><p n="p87.91"><s n="s1.1;p87.91">Use of medication pre and post surgery </s></p><p n="p88.91"><s n="s1.1;p88.91">Importance of post operative monitoring and imaging </s></p><p n="p89.91"><s n="s1.1;p89.91">Astereognosis - failure to distinguish objects held in the hand by touch alone - due to a dorsal column lesion originating in the contralateral parietal lobe affecting appreciation of size, shape, texture and weight </s></p><p n="p90.91"><s n="s1.1;p90.91">Complications of surgery </s></p><p n="p91.91"><s n="s1.1;p91.91">Management of brain tumours </s></p></div1></body><back><div1 type="bibliography"><head>References</head><p>[1] GP notebook - <seg type="URL" n="http://www.gpnotebook.co.uk/simplepage.cfm?ID=-852164606&amp;linkID=4664&amp;cook=yes"/></p><p>[2] Grant R, Metcalfe SE.Biopsy versus resection for malignant glioma.Cochrane Database of Syst Reviews 2000:2.</p><p>[3] <seg type="URL" n="http://www.emedicine.com/med/topic2692.htm"/></p><p>[4] Graham CA &amp; Cloughsey TF. Brain tumour treatment, chemotherapy and other new developments. Seminars in Oncology Nursing (2004) 20:4 p 260</p><p>[5] NICE Summary of Guidance issued toNSH England and Wales, Temozolomide for malignant glioma 2:29 (04.2004)</p><p>[6] Grant R. Overview, brain tumour diagnosis and management, Royal college of physician guidelines. Journal of neurology, neurosurgery and psychiatry. 2004:75, 18-23</p><p>[7] NICE Health Technology Appraisal. Carmustine implants and Temozolomide for the treatment of newly diagnosed high-grade glioma - Final Scope. February 2005</p></div1><div1 type="appendix"><head rend="bold">ASPECTS OF CASE AS RECORDED IN SUMMARY OF PORTFOLIO CASES•</head><p/></div1><div1 type="appendix"><head rend="bold">PORTFOLIO COMPLETION CERTIFICATE</head><p/></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
