<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_0203e" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Portfolio Case presentation number: 7 Severe stomach cramps</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">proforma</note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">appendices: 	ASPECTS OF CASE AS RECORDED IN SUMMARY OF PORTFOLIO CASES, PORTFOLIO COMPLETION CERTIFICATE</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">4</p><p n="date">2005-05</p><p n="module title">Other rotations</p><p n="module code">unknown</p><p n="genre family">Case study</p><p n="discipline">Medicine</p><p n="disciplinary group">LS</p><p n="grade">D</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">4241</p><p n="number of s-units">177</p><p n="number of p">96</p><p n="number of tables">2</p><p n="number of figures">0</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">1</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">27</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">24.0</p><p n="average s-units per p">1.8</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">f</p><p n="year of birth">1979</p><p n="first language">English</p><p n="education">UKA</p><p n="course">Medicine</p><p n="student ID">0203</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><docTitle><titlePart rend="bold">PORTFOLIO CASE No: 03W372</titlePart></docTitle><titlePart>Patient Initials<name type="other"/> Age 30 Gender Female</titlePart><titlePart>Portfolio Case presentation number: 7 Phase 2 course document objectives 12.1, 12.2, 12.5, Has the patient' permission, including for follow up contact by telephone, been sought and recorded in the case notes? YES</titlePart></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Referral information</head><p n="p1.96"><s n="s1.2;p1.96"><name type="other"/> was referred to the mental health services in <name type="date"/> with a history of severe stomach cramps and a long history of problems with her eating habits and weight. </s><s n="s2.2;p1.96">This was the first time that <name type="other"/> had felt ready to accept help for her eating behaviour. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">History</head><div2><head rend="underlined bold">Presenting Complaint</head><p n="p2.96"><s n="s1.1;p2.96"><name type="other"/> has continuous thoughts about food and what she is allowed and not allowed to eat. <name type="other"/> believes she is fat and exercises excessively in order to maintain her weight, she has also been making herself sick after episodes of binge eating. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined bold">History of Presenting Complaint </head><p n="p3.96"><s n="s1.2;p3.96"><name type="other"/> has a long history of problems regarding her eating behaviours and weight. <name type="other"/> is afraid of putting on weight and says that <hi rend="bold">"she feels fat".</hi> </s><s n="s2.2;p3.96"><name type="other"/> has not weighed herself since Christmas day when she weighed 58 kg (she is 1.7m in height), she says that she "daren't get on the scales as "I know I have put weight on". <name type="other"/> says that <hi rend="bold">"she feels and knows she looks good when her hip bones stick out"</hi> and she is aware of this when she weighs approx 9 stone 2-4 lb (58Kg). <name type="other"/> plans her meals and portion size out the night before and states that she often feels hungry in the afternoons, a typical days intake at present would be: </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p4.96"><s n="s1.1;p4.96">Breakfast - 2 scoops of porridge with water and a drop of skimmed milk </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p5.96"><s n="s1.1;p5.96">Lunch - tin of tuna and a spoonful of rice </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p6.96"><s n="s1.1;p6.96">Tea - small chicken portion and a portion of vegetables </s></p><p n="p7.96"><s n="s1.3;p7.96"><name type="other"/> is currently feeling <hi rend="bold">anxious</hi> as she is in the process of selling her house and says that she has been feeling <hi rend="bold">stressed</hi> over the past few weeks and waking during the night. <name type="other"/> blamed this stress for her recent <hi rend="bold">"naughty"</hi> behaviour in that she has been bingeing on "rubbish" food (black wine gums, chocolate biscuits and toast) and then <hi rend="bold">making herself sick.</hi> </s><s n="s2.3;p7.96">This behaviour occurs approximately once a day (occasionally twice) on most days for the past 1-2 weeks either in the evening at home or at work. <name type="other"/> feels that she is <hi rend="bold">"struggling"</hi> with her eating habits at the moment, occasionally she feels <hi rend="bold">"out of control"</hi> but that "on the whole it is ok". <name type="other"/> is also exercising for approx. </s><s n="s3.3;p7.96">1 ½ hours a day, 6 days a week to "burn calories and fat, become leaner and more defined", and is taking training supplements (amino acids), multivitamins and stackers (which "lift" metabolism). <name type="other"/> has a limited social life in the evening due to the time spent at the gym and does not like to eat in front of people. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined bold">Past Psychiatric History</head><p n="p8.96"><s n="s1.1;p8.96"><name type="other"/> vividly recalls <hi rend="bold">"feeling fat"</hi> at the age of five. </s></p><p n="p9.96"><s n="s1.3;p9.96"><hi rend="bold">12-15</hi> From the age of 12 <name type="other"/> became vegetarian and started to avoid certain foods in order to decrease her weight and did this successfully until the age of 15. </s><s n="s2.3;p9.96">During this time, <name type="other"/> recalls making herself sick on 2 occasions but said that this may have been because she didn't like the food she had eaten. </s><s n="s3.3;p9.96">From the age of 15 she ate mainly fruit during the day for a period of approx 6 months to 1 year and stated that <hi rend="bold">eating made her feel sick.</hi> </s></p><p n="p10.96"><s n="s1.5;p10.96"><hi rend="bold">16-17</hi> At the age of 16-17 <name type="other"/> discovered <hi rend="bold">laxatives</hi> and has been using these since (on and off) to help with weight loss. </s><s n="s2.5;p10.96">At one point, <name type="other"/> was using approximately 18 laxatives a day and drinking lots of water to help <hi rend="bold">"wash everything out of my system".</hi> </s><s n="s3.5;p10.96"><name type="other"/> recalls having to run from the classroom to the bathroom to defecate whilst at College. <name type="other"/> would wake at 6.00 in the morning and run for 3 miles before and after college, she would have an apple for breakfast, no food during the day and a slice of toast in the evening. <name type="other"/> would weigh herself in the morning, afternoon and before bed but only after she had been to the toilet, had not had anything to eat or drink and was wearing no clothes. </s><s n="s4.5;p10.96">During this time she lost approximately <hi rend="bold">3 stone (19Kg) over a period of 9 months</hi> and her weight fell to 6 stone (38 Kg). <name type="other"/> would also <hi rend="bold">induce vomiting</hi> (approx. </s><s n="s5.5;p10.96">3-4 times in 24 hours) a number of times during the week. <name type="other"/> was aware that she had a problem at this stage but did not confide in anybody, she recalls felling very low and crying on the phone to her friend saying that she could not talk about it. </s></p><p n="p11.96"><s n="s1.2;p11.96">In <name type="date"/>, <name type="other"/> was referred to the child psychologist by her teachers. </s><s n="s2.2;p11.96">This outraged <name type="other"/> and she was determined that she didn't want help and told the psychologist a "bunch of lies" during the consultation: </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p12.96"><s n="s1.1;p12.96">she felt that her mother resented her for being female as she wanted another boy after her brothers twin was stillborn </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p13.96"><s n="s1.1;p13.96">she felt uncomfortable with her body image and hated wearing dresses </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p14.96"><s n="s1.1;p14.96">sometimes she wished she was a boy </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p15.96"><s n="s1.1;p15.96">her eating behaviours were a way of coping with all of these stresses. </s></p><p n="p16.96"><s n="s1.1;p16.96"><hi rend="bold">17-20 </hi><name type="other"/> was employed during this period and feels that her job weaned her off the laxatives as she had difficulty making it to the toilet in time. <name type="other"/>'s food intake also increased as she found she could not concentrate at work and consequently her weight increased. </s></p><p n="p17.96"><s n="s1.3;p17.96"><hi rend="bold">20-25</hi> During this period, <name type="other"/>'s weight fluctuated but her behaviour towards food was consistent. <name type="other"/> would restrict her intake, binge and exercise but her use of laxatives reduced. <name type="other"/> took up karate, became more involved in her exercising and joined the local gym, she also bought a house and her weight started to increase. </s><s n="s2.3;p17.96">At 23, <name type="other"/>'s eating behaviours relapsed and she stopped eating for a period of time. <name type="other"/> would binge and purge a number of times during the week and lost approx 3 stone over a 1year period. </s><s n="s3.3;p17.96">At 25, <name type="other"/> began working at the gym in the evenings twice a week, this introduced her to a new circle of friends and her social life improved. <name type="other"/>'s dietary intake was still restricted, she would exercise excessively but there was no bingeing or induced vomiting. </s></p><p n="p18.96"><s n="s1.2;p18.96"><hi rend="bold">26 - 30</hi> At the age of 27, <name type="other"/> made a <hi rend="bold">"conscious decision"</hi> to tell a doctor about her eating behaviour and accept help. <name type="other"/> had been aware that she had a problem for some time but was not ready to accept help before this point. </s><s n="s2.2;p18.96">Over the last 4 years, <name type="other"/> describes her eating behaviour as variable. </s></p><p n="p19.96"><s n="s1.2;p19.96"><name type="other"/>'s mother suffered from depression and attempted to commit suicide by overdose several times following the separation from her husband. </s><s n="s2.2;p19.96">This annoyed <name type="other"/> and she felt bitter towards her mother. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined bold">Past Medical History</head><p rend="bulleted" n="p20.96"><s n="s1.1;p20.96">1993/1994 - Jaundice, hair loss, skin changes; exacerbation of eczema, prolonged skin healing - at time when <name type="other"/>'s weight was at its lowest </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p21.96"><s n="s1.1;p21.96">2002 - Severe abdominal pain/cramps and bloating associated with induced vomiting, hole through nasal septum </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined bold">Family History</head><p n="p22.96"><s n="s1.7;p22.96"><name type="other"/>'s mother is 54 years old and unemployed, her father is 57 years old and delivers goods for a living, they divorced when <name type="other"/> was 21 and she feels that she coped well through this, her father is currently living with a partner. <name type="other"/> described the marriage as initially being ok but said that her parents never really had much in common. </s><s n="s2.7;p22.96">The divorce came as a relief to <name type="other"/> as it <hi rend="bold">"stopped all the arguing".</hi> </s><s n="s3.7;p22.96"><name type="other"/> has one older brother age 34 who works as a plumber, he had a twin brother who was stillborn. </s><s n="s4.7;p22.96">The relationship with her parents was described as being ok although <name type="other"/> was closer to her father and her brother was closer to his mother. <name type="other"/> described her mother as being short tempered and said that they would <hi rend="bold">"rub each other up the wrong way".</hi> </s><s n="s5.7;p22.96">There is <hi rend="bold">no history of abuse or neglect.</hi> </s><s n="s6.7;p22.96"><name type="other"/> and her brother were brought up to be independent children and said that as they were growing up they never really had time for each other. <name type="other"/> doesn't see her brother as much as she would like to but said that they keep in touch on the phone. <name type="other"/> was unable to talk to her parents about her problems, her mother found out about her behaviour by accident when she caught her being sick. </s><s n="s7.7;p22.96">Prior to this there had been no comments about her weight or dietary habits. <name type="other"/>'s mother takes thyroxine for hypothyroidism. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined bold">Personal History </head><div3><head>Birth/Childhood</head><p n="p23.96"><s n="s1.2;p23.96">There are no known pregnancy or birth problems, <name type="other"/> weighed 7lb 8oz at birth. <name type="other"/> achieved her reading, writing and talking milestones at an early age. <name type="other"/> described her childhood as being 'good'. </s><s n="s2.2;p23.96">During her pre school years, she spent a lot of time in a male dominated environment, as most of the children her age were boys. <name type="other"/>'s mother was a volunteer at the nursery that she attended. </s></p></div3><div3><head>Education</head><p n="p24.96"><s n="s1.3;p24.96">At primary school she was keen on reading and had a good relationship with all of her teachers except one. <name type="other"/> described herself as being fairly quiet but said that she had many friends. </s><s n="s2.3;p24.96">During High school, <name type="other"/> had one best friend who she remained close to until they went to different colleges and "drifted" apart. <name type="other"/> hated PE lessons but was keen on hockey and running. <name type="other"/> described herself as being an average student who was "quite academic" and did a lot of studying. <name type="other"/> left high school with good GCSE grades and attended King Edwards college and studied A levels in Maths, Biology and Chemistry. </s><s n="s3.3;p24.96">Unfortunately during this time, <name type="other"/>'s eating behaviours were "at their worse" and she failed to take her A level exams. </s></p></div3><div3><head>Employment</head><p n="p25.96"><s n="s1.4;p25.96"><name type="other"/> left college and worked as a clerical administrator at a local company in <name type="other"/>. <name type="other"/> walked "13 miles" per day to work and eventually left in <name type="date"/> to work as an accountant for Unichem. </s><s n="s2.4;p25.96">In <name type="date"/>, she was given a promotion which upset some of her colleagues. </s><s n="s3.4;p25.96">The relationship between them became "<hi rend="bold">unbearable"</hi> and <name type="other"/> left after 5 years. </s><s n="s4.4;p25.96">In <name type="date"/> she was employed by the NHS as a Quality Improvement Facilitator within <name type="other"/> PCT. <name type="other"/> enjoys her work and has a good relationship with her colleagues, in <name type="date"/> she completed a certificate in Management Practice at <name type="other"/> College. </s></p></div3><div3><head>Relationships/Sexual History</head><p n="p26.96"><s n="s1.9;p26.96"><name type="other"/>'s first sexual relationship was with a good friend when she was 18 years old. </s><s n="s2.9;p26.96">The experience was "not great" and "just happened". </s><s n="s3.9;p26.96">At the age of 19 she had her first serious sexual relationship, which lasted for approximately 9 months. <name type="other"/> described her former partner as being <hi rend="bold">"rude"</hi> and stated that neither her brother nor father liked him. </s><s n="s4.9;p26.96">In <name type="date"/>, <name type="other"/> had a relationship with a male who she lived with for approx 18 months in a house that she bought. </s><s n="s5.9;p26.96">The relationship ended in <name type="date"/> as <name type="other"/> felt they had grown apart and were better as friends, her partner was never in and she <hi rend="bold">became lonely</hi>. <name type="other"/> admitted to having a brief affair with a neighbour approx 1 month before her partner moved out but justified this by saying that the relationship was over. <name type="other"/>'s father was angry at this decision and "told her off", her brother was also angry and told <name type="other"/> to <hi rend="bold">"sort yourself out you skinny bitch".</hi> </s><s n="s6.9;p26.96">After this, <name type="other"/> had an on off relationship with a partner who "<hi rend="bold">stressed her out".</hi> </s><s n="s7.9;p26.96">Her next relationship in <name type="other"/> was not great, the partner was involved in drugs and <name type="other"/> experimented with <hi rend="bold">amphetamines</hi> during this time. </s><s n="s8.9;p26.96">The relationship ended in <name type="other"/> to <name type="other"/>'s relief as she found him to be a source of constant <hi rend="bold">criticism and irritation.</hi> </s><s n="s9.9;p26.96"><name type="other"/> is happy in her current relationship and described it as being "great". <name type="other"/> has no desire to have children and stated that the thought of it makes her "feel physically sick" and that she "can't even hold babies", although she did not discount the idea as a possibility for the future. <name type="other"/> feels that her eating behaviours affect her relationships. </s></p><p n="p27.96"><s n="s1.1;p27.96"><name type="other"/> has never had any significant problems with her menstrual cycle, however, she finds that the week before her period she feels sick and her bingeing/purging behaviour tends to increase. </s></p></div3><div3><head>Social History</head><p n="p28.96"><s n="s1.1;p28.96"><name type="other"/> has recently moved into a house with her partner in <name type="other"/>. <name type="other"/> has never smoked and rarely drinks alcohol, there is no current illicit drug use. <name type="other"/> occasionally socialises with her friends from the gym. </s></p></div3></div2><div2><head rend="underlined bold">Systems Review</head><p n="p29.96"><s n="s1.1;p29.96"><hi rend="bold">CVS</hi> Palpitations </s></p><p n="p30.96"><s n="s1.1;p30.96"><hi rend="bold">RESP</hi> Nil </s></p><p n="p31.96"><s n="s1.1;p31.96"><hi rend="bold">GIT</hi> Constipation associated with induced vomiting </s></p><p n="p32.96"><s n="s1.1;p32.96"><hi rend="bold">GUT</hi> Nil </s></p><p n="p33.96"><s n="s1.1;p33.96"><hi rend="bold">CNS</hi> Headaches after she has been sick, dizziness, light headed and sudden weakness of legs when she has not eaten </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined bold">Forensic History</head><p n="p34.96"><s n="s1.1;p34.96">Nil </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined bold">Pre-morbid personality</head><p n="p35.96"><s n="s1.2;p35.96"><name type="other"/> described herself as being an anxious individual although she gets on well with people and is often referred to as being "bubbly". </s><s n="s2.2;p35.96">She is honest and open-minded and described herself as being a perfectionist who likes order. <name type="other"/> said that she can be oversensitive and take things to heart. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined bold">Medication</head><p rend="bulleted" n="p36.96"><s n="s1.1;p36.96">Allergic to penicillin </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p37.96"><s n="s1.1;p37.96">No medication at present (prefers not to take any) </s></p></div2><div2><head><hi rend="bold">Suicidal Ideation</hi> - </head><p n="p38.96"><s n="s1.1;p38.96"><name type="other"/> stated that she had a single fleeting thought of "ending it all" during college. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined bold">Risk Assessment: </head><p n="p39.96"><s rend="bold" n="s1.1;p39.96">Low </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Mental State Examination and Physical Examination </head><div2><head rend="underlined bold">Mental State Examination</head><div3><head rend="bold">Appearance: </head><p n="p40.96"><s n="s1.3;p40.96">Well-presented lady of slight build dressed in a dark suit. </s><s n="s2.3;p40.96">Relaxed with good eye contact. </s><s n="s3.3;p40.96">A good rapport was established. </s></p></div3><div3><head rend="bold">Behaviour: </head><p n="p41.96"><s n="s1.2;p41.96">Attention and concentration good. </s><s n="s2.2;p41.96">Consistent pattern of behaviour with regards to her weight maintenance: </s></p><list type="bulleted"><item>Planning meals and measuring portions</item><item>Counting calorie intake</item><item>Exercising 6 times per week</item><item>Bingeing on "rubbish" followed by purging</item><item>Occasional feeling of loss of control</item></list></div3><div3><head rend="bold">Speech: </head><p n="p42.96"><s n="s1.1;p42.96">Normal volume, tone and speed </s></p></div3><div3><head rend="bold">Mood/Affect: </head><p n="p43.96"><s n="s1.1;p43.96">Objective - "feel fine now....felt anxious before appointment". <name type="other"/> said that her mood tends to vary and when she feels unhappy or anxious she tends to binge. </s></p><p n="p44.96"><s n="s1.1;p44.96">Subjective - cheerful mood, euthymic. </s></p><p n="p45.96"><s n="s1.1;p45.96"><name type="other"/>'s sleep pattern has been disturbed for the past week, her motivation levels appeared to be normal and she was still able to carry out her normal activities. </s></p></div3><div3><head rend="bold">Thoughts: </head><p n="p46.96"><s n="s1.2;p46.96">Negative thoughts about her physical appearance, positive thoughts regarding her own ability e.g. at work. <name type="other"/> feels guilty after bingeing and when she hasn't been to the gym. </s><s n="s2.2;p46.96">Initially after being sick, <name type="other"/> feels relieved to have the food out of her body, she then feels angry and disappointed in herself for her actions. </s></p><p n="p47.96"><s n="s1.2;p47.96">Content: Preoccupied with the belief that she is fat - overvalued idea. </s><s n="s2.2;p47.96">Obsessed with dietary intake and exercise regime. </s></p><p n="p48.96"><s n="s1.1;p48.96">Form: normal </s></p><p n="p49.96"><s n="s1.1;p49.96">Stream: normal </s></p><p n="p50.96"><s n="s1.1;p50.96">Suicidal Ideation: not at present </s></p></div3><div3><head rend="bold">Perceptions: </head><p n="p51.96"><s n="s1.2;p51.96">No hallucinations or illusions. </s><s n="s2.2;p51.96">Distorted body image (believes her legs are out of proportion) </s></p></div3><div3><head rend="bold">Insight: </head><p n="p52.96"><s n="s1.2;p52.96">recognises that she has a problem and made a conscious decision to accept help, has read books on eating disorders to gain more of an insight. </s><s n="s2.2;p52.96">Worried about effects on body from vomiting. </s></p></div3><div3><head rend="bold">Cognition: </head><p n="p53.96"><s n="s1.1;p53.96">orientated in time, person and place </s></p></div3></div2><div2><head rend="underlined bold">Physical Examination </head><p n="p54.96"><s n="s1.1;p54.96"><name type="other"/>'s weight and height would have to be measured in order to calculate her BMI. Points to look for on physical examination would be: </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p55.96"><s n="s1.1;p55.96">evidence of malnutrition - pale conjunctiva, dehydration </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p56.96"><s n="s1.1;p56.96">effects of repeated vomiting e.g. loss of enamel, callus on hand from induced vomiting </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p57.96"><s n="s1.1;p57.96">postural and resting blood pressure to indicate autonomic dysfunction and dehydration </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p58.96"><s n="s1.1;p58.96">presence of laguno hair, loss of head hair and dry skin </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p59.96"><s n="s1.1;p59.96">myopathy (however this is unlikely in <name type="other"/>s case due to her exercise and weight training) </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Analysis of history and examination</head><p n="p60.96"><s n="s1.1;p60.96">From the history and mental state examination <name type="other"/> is a 30-year-old lady who is currently presenting with a diagnosis of an <hi rend="bold">Eating Disorder F50.</hi> </s></p><p n="p61.96"><s n="s1.5;p61.96">The most likely diagnosis for <name type="other"/>'s current behaviour is <hi rend="bold"> Atypical Bulimia Nervosa F50.3.</hi> </s><s n="s2.5;p61.96">This is supported by <name type="other"/>'s current binge eating behaviour of "rubbish food" and subsequent "purging" activities to control her body weight i.e. excessive exercise and induced vomiting. </s><s n="s3.5;p61.96">There is an excessive preoccupation with her body weight and eating habits to the extent that she feels it interferes with her lifestyle. <name type="other"/> also suffers from palpitations, which could be a result of the repeated vomiting and consequent electrolyte disturbance. <name type="other"/> displays some of the features of <hi rend="bold">Bulimia Nervosa F50.2</hi> but not the full clinical picture. </s><s n="s4.5;p61.96">For example, there have been no significant changes in her weight over the past 5 years, which is often characteristic of individuals with Bulimia Nervosa. </s><s n="s5.5;p61.96">Also, <name type="other"/> does not possess a "strong desire to overeat" consistently as in Bulimia Nervosa, this only occurs when she is feeling particularly anxious, stressed or low. </s></p><p n="p62.96"><s n="s1.4;p62.96"><name type="other"/> strives to maintain an "ideal weight of 58Kg" rather than deliberately trying to lose weight which is more characteristic of <hi rend="bold">Anorexia Nervosa F50.0.</hi> </s><s n="s2.4;p62.96">The last time <name type="other"/> weighed herself she was 58 Kg (although <name type="other"/> feels she has put on weight) giving her a BMI of approx 20.1 Kg/M <hi rend="sup">2</hi>. </s><s n="s3.4;p62.96">This would discount a diagnosis of Anorexia Nervosa in which the BMI is usually &lt;17.5 Kg/M <hi rend="sup">2</hi>. <name type="other"/> has not experienced any problems with her menstrual cycle which is another common feature associated with Anorexia Nervosa. <name type="other"/>'s eating behaviours appear to be exacerbated when <name type="other"/> is felling stressed or anxious. </s><s n="s4.4;p62.96">There is also a correlation with relationships, when <name type="other"/> feels settled her behaviour improves, when she feels insecure her behaviour deteriorates. </s></p><p n="p63.96"><s n="s1.4;p63.96">The history of <name type="other"/>'s eating behaviour would support a past diagnosis of <hi rend="bold">Anorexia Nervosa F50.0.</hi> </s><s n="s2.4;p63.96">When her eating behaviour was at its worse, <name type="other"/>'s weight fell to 6 stone, which would have reduced her BMI dramatically. </s><s n="s3.4;p63.96">This diagnosis is also supported by the physical problems that <name type="other"/> experienced at the time as a result of her eating behaviours - loss head hair, dry skin. </s><s n="s4.4;p63.96">A previous history of Anorexia Nervosa is a common finding in patients diagnosed with Bulimia Nervosa [1]. </s></p><p n="p64.96"><s n="s1.6;p64.96">The trigger to <name type="other"/>'s history of anorexia may have been the parental disharmony that she witnessed as a child and her mother's consequent depression and suicide attempts. <name type="other"/>'s parents separated when she was 20 years old, prior to this there had been consistent arguing between the parents during <name type="other"/>'s late teens. </s><s n="s2.6;p64.96">This correlates with the point in her life when her behavioural symptoms were at their worse and her weight decreased to 6 stone. </s><s n="s3.6;p64.96">Since this episode, <name type="other"/>'s eating behaviours appear to be related to her relationships and <name type="other"/> has recognised that her behaviour is worse when she is feeling stressed or anxious. </s><s n="s4.6;p64.96">At the time of the her parents separation, <name type="other"/>'s eating behaviour had improved although she was beginning to exercise more. </s><s n="s5.6;p64.96">This may have provided an alternative outlet for her tension and anxiety and <name type="other"/> has maintained this exercise regime since. </s><s n="s6.6;p64.96">Recent stresses with the sale of the house have precipitated "naughty" behaviour and the recurrence of her binge/purge behaviours. </s></p><p n="p65.96"><s n="s1.2;p65.96">The association between <name type="other"/>'s eating behaviours and anxiety/stress states may suggest an underlying <hi rend="bold">Generalised Anxiety Disorder F41.1.</hi> </s><s n="s2.2;p65.96">However, there are no physical symptoms relating to <name type="other"/>'s anxiety state and so this is discounted as the primary diagnosis. </s></p><p n="p66.96"><s n="s1.1;p66.96"><name type="other"/> shows symptoms indicative of an <hi rend="bold">Obsessive Compulsive Disorder F42</hi> in that she: </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p67.96"><s n="s1.1;p67.96">has obsessional thoughts about her weight and dietary intake </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p68.96"><s n="s1.1;p68.96">displays rituals regarding binge/purge behaviour </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p69.96"><s n="s1.1;p69.96">describes herself as feeling anxious </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p70.96"><s n="s1.1;p70.96">is a perfectionist who likes order </s></p><p n="p71.96"><s n="s1.2;p71.96">However, <name type="other"/> currently displays no symptoms of depression, depersonalisation or abnormal slowness associated with this diagnosis. <name type="other"/> may therefore have underlying personality traits e.g. obsessionality, low self esteem, perfectionism, which have predisposed her to develop these eating behaviours. </s><s n="s2.2;p71.96">An organic cause for <name type="other"/>'s eating behaviours is unlikely, however clinical investigations may help to eliminate e.g. an endocrine cause. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Formulation of the patient's problem(s)</head><div2><head>Impression </head><p n="p72.96"><s n="s1.1;p72.96"><name type="other"/> is an intelligent, articulate 30-year-old lady who has a long-term history of obsessions with her weight and problem eating behaviours. <name type="other"/> has good insight into her illness but could not identify anything in her life that "triggered" her behaviour. </s></p><table id="BAWE_0203e-tab.001"><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p73.96"><s n="s1.1;p73.96">Genetic factors are considered to be less important in Bulimia Nervosa compared to Anorexia Nervosa although potential genetic links have been identified [2] </s></p><p n="p74.96"><s n="s1.2;p74.96">In terms of prognosis, <name type="other"/> has identified and accepted that she has a problem and is motivated in her approach for help. </s><s n="s2.2;p74.96">However, her eating behaviour has been engraved for a long time and her treatment is likely to be prolonged because of this. </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Management</head><div2><head rend="underlined bold">Reassurance and Explanation </head><p n="p75.96"><s n="s1.2;p75.96"><name type="other"/> has acknowledged that she has a problem and has made a conscious decision to accept help. </s><s n="s2.2;p75.96">In order for her treatment to be effective, it is important that she understands that a long term approach will probably be needed. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined bold">Investigations </head><table id="BAWE_0203e-tab.002"><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p76.96"><s n="s1.1;p76.96">If an electrolyte disturbance is detected, oral supplementation should be considered to restore the balance. <name type="other"/> should also be encouraged to have a dental check due to the damage to enamel from repeated vomiting. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined bold">Short Term Management</head><p n="p77.96"><s n="s1.4;p77.96">As <name type="other"/> does not currently appear to be displaying any serious medical problems requiring treatment i.e. serious metabolic disturbance, suicide risk, she can be treated on an outpatient basis. <name type="other"/> states that she feels anxious and stressed at the moment due to the sale of her house. </s><s n="s2.4;p77.96">In the short term, she may benefit from an anxiolytic which will help to relieve the tension she is currently experiencing and the need to pursue her binge/purge behaviour in order to relieve this. </s><s n="s3.4;p77.96">Although <name type="other"/> has no symptoms of depression, an SSRI such as Fluoxetine (60mg effective dose) would help to reduce the frequency of her binge/purge behaviour, however, <name type="other"/> is reluctant to take medication as she "doesn't feel depressed". </s><s n="s4.4;p77.96">The physical consequences of induced vomiting should be explained to <name type="other"/> so that she is aware of the potential damage and long-term complications i.e. hypokalaemia - renal damage, cardiac arrythmia and sudden death. </s></p><p n="p78.96"><s n="s1.2;p78.96"><name type="other"/> appears to be in the "Determination" phase of the Trans Theoretical Model of Change [3] as she has made a conscious decision to accept help. </s><s n="s2.2;p78.96">Psychological treatment should therefore focus on support, monitoring and encouragement in order to achieve this change. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined bold">Long Term Management</head><p n="p79.96"><s n="s1.6;p79.96">A stepwise approach should be adopted in the management of <name type="other"/>'s eating behaviours due to the long waiting list for referral to a psychologist. </s><s n="s2.6;p79.96">As <name type="other"/>'s motivation to change is high, guided cognitive behavioural self-help in the form of self-help books/manuals may <name type="other"/> regain control over her eating [4]. <name type="other"/> should be encouraged to keep a diary of her food intake, episodes of vomiting and excessive exercise and attempt to identify any environmental stimuli, emotions or thoughts that precede this activity [5]. </s><s n="s3.6;p79.96">This would be monitored on an outpatient basis and if there are no significant changes then <name type="other"/> should be referred to a psychologist for Cognitive Behavioural Therapy. </s><s n="s4.6;p79.96">This would aim to change <name type="other"/>'s abnormal thoughts and behaviour and the distorted and rigid thinking patterns associated with her eating disorder. </s><s n="s5.6;p79.96">The recommended period of treatment for CBT in patients with Bulimia Nervosa is 16-20 sessions over 4-5 months [6]. <name type="other"/> would also benefit from a referral to a nutritionist who could advise <name type="other"/> on more appropriate eating regimes and diets to control her weight. </s><s n="s6.6;p79.96">If there is no improvement with CBT then Interpersonal therapy should be considered although it would have to be explained to <name type="other"/> that it can take 8-12 months to achieve results as there are 3 phases to treatment: </s></p><p n="p80.96"><s n="s1.1;p80.96">Phase 1 - analyses interpersonal context of eating disorder </s></p><p n="p81.96"><s n="s1.1;p81.96">Phase 2 - encourage interpersonal changes based on formulation of interpersonal problem area. </s></p><p n="p82.96"><s n="s1.1;p82.96">Phase 3 - analysis of progress and development of ways to handle future interpersonal difficulties. </s></p><p n="p83.96"><s n="s1.2;p83.96">As <name type="other"/>'s eating behaviours are associated with intense emotions, dialectical therapy which views the eating disorder as an attempt to control or change painful emotional states, may also be of benefit. </s><s n="s2.2;p83.96">Continuing support from the therapist is essential as most relapses occur within the first two years [7]. </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Outcome</head><p n="p84.96"><s n="s1.1;p84.96"><name type="other"/> is currently being seen in the outpatient clinic on a 3 monthly basis. <name type="other"/> has not yet been seen by a psychologist but has been actively reading self-help books to gain a greater understanding of her problems. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Relevant Core Issues , Evidence Based Care and Issues for Research</head><p n="p85.96"><s n="s1.2;p85.96">Prevalance - In community based studies, the prevalence of BN is between 0.5% and 1.0% in young women with an even social class distribution [5]. </s><s n="s2.2;p85.96">Approximately 90% of people diagnosed with BN are women [5]. </s></p><p n="p86.96"><s n="s1.2;p86.96">Prognosis - A 10 year follow up study found that 52% had fully recovered and only 9% continued to experience full symptoms of BN [5]. </s><s n="s2.2;p86.96">If the illness is identified early enough, the prognosis is good. </s></p><p n="p87.96"><s n="s1.6;p87.96">The serotonin theory for BN suggests that there is a low serotonin level in the brains of people who are irritable, depressed and anxious. </s><s n="s2.6;p87.96">If an individual binges on carbohydrate rich foods, the level of trytophan in their blood is raised. </s><s n="s3.6;p87.96">A high level of tryptohan in the blood enables some to cross the blood brain barrier and stimulate the synthesis and release of serotonin which relieves the dysphoric mood and the individual feels relaxed [5]. </s><s n="s4.6;p87.96">This theory may explain why SSRI's have been found to reduce the frequency of binge/purge behaviours in individuals with BN [8]. </s><s n="s5.6;p87.96">Research suggests that the level of vasopressin in the brain is also found to be abnormal in people with eating disorders and OCD. The hormone is normally released in response to physical and possibly emotional stress, and may therefore contribute to the obsessive behaviour seen in some patients with eating disorders [9]. </s><s n="s6.6;p87.96">The effect of the menstrual cycle and hormonal changes on eating behaviours is a possible area for future research as <name type="other"/> recognised that her eating behaviours were exaggerated on week before her period. </s></p><p n="p88.96"><s n="s1.2;p88.96">According to Lacey (1986), manipulation of eating behaviour is an individuals defence mechanism and a coping mechanism for dealing with emotional stress. </s><s n="s2.2;p88.96">Cognitive behavioural therapy focuses on the thoughts, behaviour, feeling cycle and helps to: </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p89.96"><s n="s1.1;p89.96">Eliminate behavioural patterns and develop new ones </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p90.96"><s n="s1.1;p90.96">Modify negative/irrational thoughts and beliefs </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p91.96"><s n="s1.1;p91.96">Develop adaptive responses to situations </s></p><p n="p92.96"><s n="s1.2;p92.96">CBT achieves full remission in 40% of patients with bulimia nervosa [10] and is recommended by NICE guidelines in the management of BN [9]. </s><s n="s2.2;p92.96">CBT has been shown to reduce the specific symptoms of BN and also improve non-specific symptoms such as depression [5]. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Impact on your learning</head><p rend="bulleted" n="p93.96"><s n="s1.1;p93.96">Organising a complex psychiatric history </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p94.96"><s n="s1.1;p94.96">Difference between Anorexia Nervosa and Bulimia Nervosa </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p95.96"><s n="s1.1;p95.96">Signs to look for on physical examination </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p96.96"><s n="s1.1;p96.96">Identifying a suitable diagnosis using the ICD 10 classification system as patients may have symptoms applicable to a range of diagnoses. </s></p></div1></body><back><div1 type="bibliography"><head rend="bold">References</head><p>1 ICD Classification of Mental and Behavioural Disorders. <hi rend="italic">WHO</hi> 1998</p><p>2 Treasure J. Eating Disorders - Psychiatry Part 2 of 2. <hi rend="italic">Medicine.</hi> 32(8) 2004</p><p>3 Prochaske and Di Clemente. Behaviour Change Model. <hi rend="italic">Psychology Lecture Notes</hi>. <name type="university"/> Medical School</p><p>4 J Carter, MP Olmsted, AS Kaplan, RE McCabe, JS Mills, and A Aimé, Self-Help for Bulimia Nervosa: A Randomized Controlled Trial. <hi rend="italic">Am J Psychiatry</hi> 160:973-978, May 2003</p><p>5 Clinical Evidence. BMJ Publishing Group Ltd. 2003</p><p>6 NICE Guidelines - Eating Disorders. [Internet] <seg type="URL" n="http://www.nice.org.uk/page.aspx?o=101246"/></p><p>7 Abraham S and Llewellyn Jones D. Eating Disorders - The Facts. Oxford University Press 1997</p><p>8 Bacaltchuk J, Hay P. Antidepressants versus placebo for people with Bulimia Nervosa. <hi rend="italic">The Cochrane Library Issue 1</hi> 2003.</p><p>9 Hoffman L. Eating Disorders. National Institute of Mental Health [Internet] </p><p> <seg type="URL" n="http://www.mentalhealth.com/book/p45-eat1.html"/></p><p>10 Hay PJ, Bacatchuk J. Psychotherapy for Bulimia Nervosa and bingeing - Cochrane Review. <hi rend="italic">Cochrane Database Systematic Review</hi>. 2003</p><p>Not cited:</p><p>Gelder M, Mayou R and Cowen P. Shorter Oxford Textbook of Psychiatry. Oxford University Press 2001</p></div1><div1 type="appendix"><head rend="bold">ASPECTS OF CASE AS RECORDED IN SUMMARY OF PORTFOLIO CASES•</head><p/></div1><div1 type="appendix"><head rend="bold">PORTFOLIO COMPLETION CERTIFICATE</head><p/></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
