<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_0203c" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Portfolio Case presentation number: 1 Abdominal pain</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">proforma</note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">appendices: 	ASPECTS OF CASE AS RECORDED IN SUMMARY OF PORTFOLIO CASES, PORTFOLIO COMPLETION CERTIFICATE</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">4</p><p n="date">2005-04</p><p n="module title">Other rotations</p><p n="module code">unknown</p><p n="genre family">Case study</p><p n="discipline">Medicine</p><p n="disciplinary group">LS</p><p n="grade">D</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">3287</p><p n="number of s-units">176</p><p n="number of p">98</p><p n="number of tables">0</p><p n="number of figures">1</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">13</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">8</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">18.7</p><p n="average s-units per p">1.8</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">f</p><p n="year of birth">1979</p><p n="first language">English</p><p n="education">UKA</p><p n="course">Medicine</p><p n="student ID">0203</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><docTitle><titlePart rend="bold">PORTFOLIO CASE No:</titlePart></docTitle><titlePart>Patient Initials<name type="other"/> Hospital Number Age 84 Gender Male</titlePart><titlePart>Portfolio Case presentation number: 1 Phase 2 course document objectives(s) 3.8, 3.13, 3.15, Has the patient' permission, including for follow up contact by telephone, been sought and recorded in the case notes?</titlePart></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="bold">Referral information</hi> Source of referral and a summary of key information</head><p n="p1.98"><s n="s1.1;p1.98"><name type="other"/> presented to A&amp;E on <name type="date"/> with severe abdominal pain </s></p><p n="p2.98"><s n="s1.1;p2.98">Patient was interviewed on <name type="date"/> </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="bold">History</hi> All <hi rend="bold italic">relevant</hi> information gathered from the patient about the presenting illness, co-existing problems, current treatment, <hi rend="italic">significant</hi> past medical history and the social and family background. The patient's view of the nature of the problem and their expectations for treatment.</head><div2><head rend="underlined bold">Presenting Complaint </head><p n="p3.98"><s n="s1.1;p3.98"><name type="other"/> presented to A&amp;E on <name type="date"/> with severe abdominal pain located around the umbilicus </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined bold">History of presenting complaint</head><p n="p4.98"><s n="s1.4;p4.98">The abdominal pain started on Monday after <name type="other"/> had his catheter changed and has increased in severity since then. <name type="other"/> saw his GP on Tuesday who prescribed ciprofloxacin which had no effect. </s><s n="s2.4;p4.98">The pain is now radiating into the right iliac fossa, is <hi rend="bold">colicky in nature and rated at a scale of 10 out of 10 for intensity</hi>. <name type="other"/> stated that the pain had been present constantly over the past 2 days. <name type="other"/> preferred to lie still in order to relieve the pain. </s><s n="s3.4;p4.98">The pain is associated with nausea and there has been one episode of vomiting which contained <hi rend="bold">blood and was dark brown in colour</hi>. <name type="other"/> has <hi rend="bold">not opened his bowels since Tuesday</hi> <hi rend="bold">but had been passing wind (flatus).</hi> </s><s n="s4.4;p4.98"><name type="other"/> stated that his appetite is variable but that recently he has felt bloated after eating and is unable to finish his meal approximately every other day. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined bold">Past Medical History</head><list type="bulleted"><head rend="bold">Medical</head><item>Atrial Fibrillation</item><item>Bladder Tumour 2004</item><item>Benign Prostatic Hyperplasia</item><item>Previous Stomach Ulcer</item><item>Diverticular Disease and neoplasm of sigmoid colon</item><item>Myocardial Infarction 2000</item><item>No Asthma</item><item>No Diabetes</item><item>No hx of stroke or angina</item><item>No hx of DVT/pulmonary embolism</item><item>No hx of Tuberculosis or Rheumatic Fever</item></list><list type="bulleted"><head rend="bold">Surgical</head><item>Partial gastrectomy for previous stomach ulcer</item><item>Laparotomy x2 - colonic neoplasm and obstruction of small bowel</item><item>TURBT (trans urethral resection bladder tumour)</item><item>2000 Anterior resection for colonic polyp </item></list><p n="p5.98"/></div2><div2><head rend="underlined bold">Social History</head><p n="p6.98"><s n="s1.2;p6.98"><name type="other"/> lives alone in a terraced house and is retired. </s><s n="s2.2;p6.98">His previous occupation was a long distance driver and sand and gravel pit worker. <name type="other"/> stopped smoking 20 years ago but prior to this was a heavy smoker (approximately 120 pack year history - 80/day for 30 years). <name type="other"/> is an occasional drinker. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined bold">Allergies</head><p n="p7.98"><s n="s1.1;p7.98">There are no known drug allergies </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined bold">Medication</head><list type="simple"><item>Fluvastatin 40mg</item><item>Lansoprazole 15mg OD</item><item>Frusemide 20 mg BD</item><item>Ferrous sulphate 200 mg OD</item><item>Ciprofloxacin 500 mg BD</item><item>Perindopril 4mg OD</item><item>Tamulosin 400mcg OD</item><item>Warfarin </item><item>Finasteride 5mg OD</item></list><p n="p8.98"/></div2><div2><head rend="underlined bold">Family History</head><p n="p9.98"><s n="s1.1;p9.98"><name type="other"/>'s mother had hyperthyroidism and bowel cancer. <name type="other"/>'s youngest brother died from a stroke. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined bold">Systems Review</head><p n="p10.98"><s rend="bold" n="s1.1;p10.98">Cardiovascular system </s></p><p n="p11.98"><s n="s1.1;p11.98">Atrial Fibrillation </s></p><p n="p12.98"><s rend="bold" n="s1.1;p12.98">Respiratory System </s></p><p n="p13.98"><s n="s1.1;p13.98">No significant findings </s></p><p n="p14.98"><s rend="bold" n="s1.1;p14.98">Gastrointestinal System </s></p><p n="p15.98"><s n="s1.2;p15.98"><name type="other"/> stated that his appetite is variable but that recently he has felt bloated after eating and is unable to finish his meal every other day. <name type="other"/> occasionally suffers from heartburn and is currently taking a proton pump inhibitor as he has a history of peptic ulcer disease. </s><s n="s2.2;p15.98">No weight loss. </s></p><p n="p16.98"><s rend="bold" n="s1.1;p16.98">Genitourinary System </s></p><p n="p17.98"><s n="s1.1;p17.98"><name type="other"/> has a long term catheter after a failed TWOC (trial without catheter) post TURBT </s></p><p n="p18.98"><s rend="bold" n="s1.1;p18.98">Central Nervous System </s></p><p n="p19.98"><s n="s1.1;p19.98">No significant findings </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="bold">Analysis of history</hi> The most likely single cause of the presentation, other possible causes and reasons for these choices. The findings to be looked for on physical examination to help decide the cause.</head><p n="p20.98"><s n="s1.5;p20.98">In summary <name type="other"/> presented with a 2 day history of severe abdominal pain and one episode of vomiting. <name type="other"/> described the pain as being around his umbilicus and radiating to the right iliac fossa. </s><s n="s2.5;p20.98">This indicates that the pain around the umbilicus is referred pain from the midgut (midgut structures being distal duodenum, jejunum, ileum, caecum, appendix, ascending colon and 2/3 transverse colon). <name type="other"/> also described the pain as being colicky in nature. </s><s n="s3.5;p20.98">This occurs due to the contraction of smooth muscle against resistance in e.g. ureters, intestine. </s><s n="s4.5;p20.98">The pain could therefore be referred from the small intestine. </s><s n="s5.5;p20.98">Causes of acute abdominal pain from the small intestine could be due to small bowel obstruction - the four cardinal symptoms of intestinal obstruction are: </s></p><list type="ordered"><item>Colicky abdominal pain</item><item>Vomiting</item><item>Absolute Constipation</item><item rend="bold">Distension</item></list><p n="p21.98"><s n="s1.8;p21.98">The first three symptoms have been illustrated in the history and so the <hi rend="bold">distension can be looked for on examination</hi>, however not all of these 4 features need to be present in a case of intestinal obstruction. </s><s n="s2.8;p21.98">Small bowel obstruction is commonly caused by adhesions due to scars from previous surgery. </s><s n="s3.8;p21.98">From <name type="other"/>'s history we know that he has <hi rend="bold">previously had operations on his abdomen</hi> and so this may be a potential cause for his presenting complaint. </s><s rend="bold" n="s4.8;p21.98"><name type="other"/> has also previously had a laparotomy to remove adhesions. </s><s n="s5.8;p21.98"><hi rend="bold">Bowel sounds should be auscultated</hi> to rule out a paralytic ileus (pseudo obstruction due to reduced bowel motility). </s><s n="s6.8;p21.98">However, this most commonly occurs post operatively or can be due to anticholinergic agents - none of which apply to <name type="other"/>. </s><s n="s7.8;p21.98">Bowel sounds are normally found to be tinkling in small bowel obstruction. </s><s n="s8.8;p21.98">Other causes of small bowel obstruction include; malignancy (very rare in small intestine and <name type="other"/> stated that there had been no weight loss), intersussception (common in children &lt;4 yrs), volvulus and impacted faeces. </s></p><p n="p22.98"><s n="s1.4;p22.98">The pain in the right iliac fossa could be due to a hernia and so the <hi rend="bold">hernial orifices</hi> should be palpated on examination. </s><s n="s2.4;p22.98">Small bowel obstruction could result from a strangulation of the bowel and this occurs frequently in femoral hernias as the neck of the femoral canal is narrow. </s><s n="s3.4;p22.98">It is important to identify a strangulated femoral hernia/strangulated bowel as they are associated with a high mortality rate. </s><s n="s4.4;p22.98">Features suggesting strangulation to look for on examination include; rapid pulse, pyrexia, colicky pain becoming continuous as peritonitis develops, tenderness and abdominal rigidity. </s></p><p n="p23.98"><s n="s1.6;p23.98">Midgut pain which radiates to the right iliac fossa is also indicative of appendicitis. </s><s n="s2.6;p23.98">There is often guarding over the site of the appendix (McBurneys point) on examination due to the inflammatory process spreading to involve the wall of the peritoneum producing localised intense pain which is continuous and so this should be looked for on examination. </s><s n="s3.6;p23.98">However the initial midgut pain is often dull in nature and becomes severe when the peritoneum is involved. </s><s n="s4.6;p23.98">Bowel sounds are often absent as the abdomen becomes tender and rigid. </s><s n="s5.6;p23.98">Appendicitis is also associated with vomiting which <name type="other"/> stated in his history. </s><s n="s6.6;p23.98">The patient is normally pyrexic and tachycardic and so these should also be noted on examination. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="bold">Physical examination and mental state examination</hi> Highlight the findings most relevant to your clinical problem solving by underlining them</head><div2><head rend="underlined"><hi rend="bold">General Examination</hi> (<name type="date"/>)</head><p n="p24.98"><s n="s1.5;p24.98">On examination <name type="other"/> was lieing in bed and was alert. <name type="other"/> had a nasogastric tube and catheter. <name type="other"/> did not have a walking aid and there was no sputum pot or urine pot. </s><s n="s2.5;p24.98">There was no finger clubbing, palmar erythema, cyanosis of the fingers, leuchonychia or koilonychias. </s><s n="s3.5;p24.98">No mouth ulcerations, central cyanosis and no evidence of vitamin deficiencies. </s><s n="s4.5;p24.98">No lymphadenopathy. </s><s n="s5.5;p24.98">Signs of dehydration were present: dry mucous membranes, normal skin turgor. </s></p><list type="bulleted"><head rend="bold">General Observations</head><item>Pulse - <hi rend="bold">95 bpm</hi> irregularly irregular (atrial fibrillation)</item><item>Blood Pressure - 123/61</item><item>Respiratory Rate - 20 pm</item><item>Temperature - 35.8 C</item><item>Saturations - 98% on air</item></list><list type="simple"><head rend="underlined">CVS:</head><item>HS I + II + 0</item><item>JVP →</item><item>No ankle oedema</item></list><p n="p25.98"><s rend="underlined" n="s1.1;p25.98">RS: </s></p><p n="p26.98"><s n="s1.1;p26.98">Clear vesicular breath sounds </s></p><p n="p27.98"><s rend="underlined" n="s1.1;p27.98">CNS </s></p><p n="p28.98"><s n="s1.1;p28.98">GCS 15/15 </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined bold">Abdominal Examination</head><p n="p29.98"><s rend="bold" n="s1.1;p29.98">Inspection </s></p><p n="p30.98"><s n="s1.3;p30.98">On inspection there was <hi rend="bold">mild distension of the abdomen</hi>. </s><s n="s2.3;p30.98">Scars from previous operations were noted - gastrectomy and laparotomy. </s><s n="s3.3;p30.98">No visible hernias. </s></p><p n="p31.98"><s rend="bold" n="s1.1;p31.98">Palpation </s></p><p n="p32.98"><s n="s1.1;p32.98">The abdomen was <hi rend="bold">tender to palpation especially in the right iliac fossa</hi> </s></p><p n="p33.98"><s rend="bold" n="s1.1;p33.98">Auscultation </s></p><p n="p34.98"><s n="s1.1;p34.98">Bowel sounds were present and were high pitched </s></p><p n="p35.98"><s rend="bold" n="s1.1;p35.98">Percussion </s></p><p n="p36.98"><s n="s1.1;p36.98">Percussion of the abdomen was resonant. </s></p><p n="p37.98"><s n="s1.1;p37.98"><hi rend="bold">Comment - Hernial Orifices</hi> (from notes) </s></p><p n="p38.98"><s n="s1.1;p38.98">Tender right femoral lump </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="bold">Analysis of history and examination</hi> Reasons for your choice of the cause of the patient's problem(s) and any other cause that still needs to be considered at this stage</head><p n="p39.98"><s n="s1.8;p39.98">On observation and examination the patient was apyrexial and tachycardic. </s><s n="s2.8;p39.98">A nasogastric tube was in situ for aspiration of gastric contents as <name type="other"/> had been vomiting and there appeared to be signs of dehydration as the mucous membranes were dry. </s><s n="s3.8;p39.98">The distension of the abdomen and resonance on percussion indicate that the distension is due to gas and not free fluid. </s><s n="s4.8;p39.98">Tenderness in the right iliac fossa and a palpable lump may indicate the presence of a femoral hernia. </s><s n="s5.8;p39.98">Given that bowel sounds were present (and the patient presented with pain) an ileus can be ruled out (functional obstruction due to reduced bowel motility). </s><s n="s6.8;p39.98">Appendicitis can also be ruled out as <name type="other"/>'s temperature was stable, bowel sounds were present and there was no guarding over McBurneys point on examination. </s><s n="s7.8;p39.98">Bowel sounds were also high pitched indicating obstruction of the bowel. </s><s n="s8.8;p39.98">The likely diagnosis at this point could be either an obstructed femoral hernia or obstruction due to adhesions as a result of <name type="other"/>'s previous surgery and history of adhesions. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="bold">Formulation of the patient's problem(s)</hi> Encapsulate this in physical, psychological and social terms (the triple diagnosis)</head><p n="p40.98"><s n="s1.1;p40.98"><name type="other"/> is an 84 year old man who lives alone. <name type="other"/> has a significant history of past medical problems, the treatment of which may have contributed to his presenting complaint i.e. previous abdominal surgery. <name type="other"/> has obviously been in hospital before, psychologically he stated that he was not particularly concerned about his condition but frustrated at being in hospital again and was keen to get the problem rectified so that he could return home. <name type="other"/>'s history of medical problems may also hinder his recovery post operatively i.e. recent MI and heavy smoking history. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="bold">Management</hi> Use the framework of RAPRIOP to structure your proposed management. Refer to the guidelines to the writing of portfolio cases for the details of the issues to be addressed under each heading.</head><div2><head rend="underlined">Investigations</head><p n="p41.98"><s n="s1.1;p41.98">Plain AXR (<name type="date"/>): - to look for dilatation of bowel </s></p><p n="p42.98"><s n="s1.1;p42.98">Marked dilatation of loops of small intestine. </s></p><p n="p43.98"><s n="s1.1;p43.98">Plan: </s></p><p n="p44.98"><s n="s1.1;p44.98">NBM, IV Omeprazole - proton pump inhibitor to reduce gastric acid production - used for <name type="other"/>'s reflux and history of peptic ulcer </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">Prescription/medical intervention</head><p n="p45.98"><s n="s1.1;p45.98">Operative (<name type="date"/>): </s></p><p n="p46.98"><s n="s1.1;p46.98"><hi rend="bold">High incision for exploration of right groin -</hi> risk of strangulated femoral hernia </s></p><p n="p47.98"><s n="s1.1;p47.98">Findings: </s></p><p n="p48.98"><s n="s1.2;p48.98">Nothing in femoral canal, no bile/peritoneal fluid, no dilated small bowel. </s><s n="s2.2;p48.98">Multiple adhesions to midline. </s></p><p n="p49.98"><s n="s1.1;p49.98">Blood Tests (<name type="date"/>): </s></p><p n="p50.98"><s n="s1.1;p50.98">Abnormal results - K 4.2, Na 145 (upper limit), Creatinine 144 ↑, Urea 9.2 ↑, Hb 9.7 ↓, CRP 96 ↑ </s></p><p n="p51.98"><s n="s1.1;p51.98">Comment - creatinine, Na and urea levels are raised which may indicate dehydration, Hb levels decreased indicating anaemia, raised CRP indicates inflammation. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">Reassurance and explanation</head><p n="p52.98"><s n="s1.1;p52.98">Reassuring the patient - It was explained to <name type="other"/> that during his right groin exploration multiple adhesions had been found in the abdomen and these were the most likely cause of the symptoms he was experiencing. </s></p><p n="p53.98"><s n="s1.2;p53.98">Nature of the Disease - Previous surgery has caused some of the loops of bowel which are normally separated to join together. </s><s n="s2.2;p53.98">This has caused the bowel to become obstructed. </s></p><p n="p54.98"><s n="s1.1;p54.98">Management Plan - <name type="other"/> was advised that if his condition deteriorates he may need a laparotomy to remove the adhesions and consequent bowel obstruction. <name type="other"/> would need to be advised that his condition will be monitored to see if the situation can resolve itself without the need for further surgery. </s></p><p n="p55.98"><s n="s1.1;p55.98">Ward Round (<name type="date"/>): </s></p><p n="p56.98"><s n="s1.1;p56.98">Still no bowel opening, abdomen soft and tender, tympanic bowel sounds present. <name type="other"/> was also coughing green phlegm. </s></p><p n="p57.98"><s n="s1.1;p57.98">Comment - tinkling bowel sounds indicate bowel obstruction, green phlegm indicates possible respiratory tract infection </s></p><p n="p58.98"><s n="s1.1;p58.98">Repeat AXR (<name type="date"/>): - to look for evidence of small bowel dilation </s></p><p n="p59.98"><s n="s1.1;p59.98"><hi rend="bold">Marked dilatation of loops of small intestine</hi> still present, dilatation increased compared to previous x-ray </s></p><p n="p60.98"><s n="s1.1;p60.98">CXR (<name type="date"/>) </s></p><p n="p61.98"><s n="s1.1;p61.98">Some haze on left lung base </s></p><list type="simple"><head>Plan (<name type="date"/>):</head><item>NBM, NG tube remain in place, IV access and 8 hourly IV fluids, Monitor urine output</item><item>IV Augmentin - to treat any respiratory tract infection</item></list><p n="p62.98"><s n="s1.1;p62.98">Abdominal contrast CT (<name type="date"/>) </s></p><p n="p63.98"><s n="s1.4;p63.98">Some free fluid in the pelvis. </s><s n="s2.4;p63.98"><hi rend="bold">Multiple loops of small dilated bowel,</hi> 20cm collapsed ileum in Right Iliac Fossa. </s><s n="s3.4;p63.98">Bilateral small pleural effusion with some associated passive collapse. </s><s n="s4.4;p63.98">Moderate hydronephrosis if left kidney <hi rend="bold">(explaining raised creatinine, Na and urea levels on previous blood tests),</hi> small 3.1 cm infra renal abdominal aneurysm </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0203c-pic.001"><head>Patient <name type="other"/> CT image showing fluid gas levels in small intestine</head></figure><p n="p64.98"><s n="s1.1;p64.98">Abdominal Examination SHO (11.03.2005): </s></p><p n="p65.98"><s n="s1.3;p65.98">Mild distension of abdomen. </s><s n="s2.3;p65.98">Tenderness in Left Iliac Fossa - mobile mass in left inguinal region - no cough impulse, non pulsatile/non expansile. </s><s rend="bold" n="s3.3;p65.98">High pitched bowel sounds. </s></p><list type="simple"><head>Blood results (<name type="date"/>):</head><item>ESR 39 ↑, K 3.4↓, Urea 3.2 ↓, CRP 168 ↑, Creatinine 130 ↑, Hb 10.5↓</item></list></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">Prescription/medical intervention</head><p n="p66.98"><s n="s1.1;p66.98">Operative - <name type="date"/>: </s></p><p n="p67.98"><s n="s1.1;p67.98">Anaesthesia - General anaesthetic and Epidural </s></p><p n="p68.98"><s n="s1.1;p68.98">IV Cefuroxime and Metronidazole - to prevent infection </s></p><p n="p69.98"><s rend="bold" n="s1.2;p69.98">Left groin exploration and laparotomy. </s><s rend="bold" n="s2.2;p69.98">Adhesiolysis and excision of small bowel stricture with repair of left femoral hernia </s></p><list type="ordered"><head>Findings: </head><item>left sided femoral hernia - contents extraperitoneal fat</item><item>Dense adhesions of small intestine to each other and previous scars</item><item>Ileal stricture with an adhesive band - collapse of the distal part of ileum and dilatation of proximal small intestine</item></list><p n="p70.98"><s n="s1.1;p70.98">Biopsies taken during the operation showed no evidence of neoplasia. </s></p><list type="simple"><head>Post Op:</head><item>NBM, IV Fluids, NG tube, Epidural analgesia, C2 Stepdown</item></list></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">Observation</head><list type="bulleted"><head>1 day post op:</head><item>Pulse - 70 bpm irregularly irregular (atrial fibrillation)</item><item>Blood Pressure - 92/50</item><item>Urine output 40ml/hr</item></list><p n="p71.98"/></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">Referral and team working</head><p n="p72.98"><s n="s1.1;p72.98">Pain management team, initially pain was delivered via an epidural tap, this was then changed to PCA (patient controlled analgesia). <name type="other"/> was also referred to the physiotherapists for chest exercises to help clear his respiratory infection. </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="bold">Outcome</hi> A description of the progress of the patient as far as possible. This should include consideration of further issues to be resolved. Where appropriate you should contact by telephone patients who have been discharged home.</head><p n="p73.98"><s n="s1.5;p73.98">Unfortunately, <name type="other"/> developed a chest infection approximately four days after the operation. </s><s n="s2.5;p73.98">Sputum samples were sent and treatment was advised by the microbiologist - Amoxicillin 500mg TDS for 7 days. </s><s n="s3.5;p73.98">The wound from the second operation also became infected and purulent discharge was drained. </s><s n="s4.5;p73.98">Swabs of the discharge were taken and were found to be MRSA positive. </s><s n="s5.5;p73.98">The consultant microbiologist advised the following treatment for a period of 5 days and to then review: </s></p><list type="simple"><item>Trimethoprim 200mg BD</item><item>Fusicidic acid 500mg TDS </item></list><p n="p74.98"><s n="s1.2;p74.98">A referral was made to the tissue viability nurse who advised that the wound be treated with VAC therapy. </s><s n="s2.2;p74.98">The dietician was also contacted and advised that <name type="other"/> be commenced on NG feeding as he had had a prolonged period without adequate nutrition and was at risk of re-feeding syndrome. </s></p><p n="p75.98"><s n="s1.4;p75.98">Later swabs of the infected wound were still MRSA positive - the consultant microbiologist advised that a static dose of vancomycin 1g over 90 mins should be given. </s><s n="s2.4;p75.98">It was also advised that the condition of the wound be assessed as it may be colonised with MRSA but not infected elsewhere. </s><s n="s3.4;p75.98">Assessment of the wound showed that it was colonised and so treatment was stopped. </s><s n="s4.4;p75.98">Referral to <name type="other"/> for a rehabilitation bed was organised. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="bold">Evidence based care and issues for research</hi> A brief consideration of the evidence base required for the diagnosis and management of the patient's problem(s)</head><p n="p76.98"><s n="s1.4;p76.98">Many cases of small bowel obstruction will settle on conservative treatment but in patients with an increasing temperature, raised pulse rate, increasing pain and a raised white cell count, exploratory laparotomy is needed. </s><s n="s2.4;p76.98">It is important to try and manage the obstruction conservatively through drip and suck as further surgery could increase the risk of recurrent adhesions and therefore repeat episodes of bowel obstruction. </s><s n="s3.4;p76.98">In patients with simple or partial obstruction, resolution occurs in virtually all patients with within 72 hours [1]. </s><s n="s4.4;p76.98">If the bowel is gangrenous due to strangulation then a gut resection is needed. </s></p><p n="p77.98"><s n="s1.4;p77.98">It is important to recognise a potential case of strangulated femoral hernia. </s><s n="s2.4;p77.98">Evidence has shown that if untreated, strangulated obstructions cause death in 100% of patients. </s><s n="s3.4;p77.98">If surgery is performed within 36 hours, the mortality decreases to 8%. </s><s n="s4.4;p77.98">The mortality rate is 25% if the surgery is postponed beyond 36 hours in these patients [1]. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="bold">Commentary</hi> A commentary on issues of health care delivery, ethical issues or disability relevant to the patient and/or problem</head><p n="p78.98"><s n="s1.6;p78.98">Over 80% of cases of small bowel obstruction in adults are due to adhesions [2]. </s><s n="s2.6;p78.98">Other common causes are hernias and Crohns Disease. </s><s n="s3.6;p78.98">Adhesions can occur after abdominal surgery, and can cause bowel obstruction either in the early or late postoperative period. </s><s n="s4.6;p78.98">Early postoperative adhesions are often formed of fibrin (fibrinous adhesions) and can be a transient occurrence. </s><s n="s5.6;p78.98">Adhesions that present months or years after surgery are more permanent and are formed of fibrous tissue (fibrous adhesions). </s><s n="s6.6;p78.98">Bowel obstruction caused by either fibrinous or fibrous adhesions may settle with conservative management although a laparotomy may be necessary. <name type="other"/>'s previous surgery and history of small bowel obstruction were risk factors for recurrent adhesive obstruction. </s></p><p n="p79.98"><s n="s1.3;p79.98">Obstruction of the small bowel leads to proximal dilatation of the intestine due to accumulation of GI secretions and swallowed air. </s><s n="s2.3;p79.98">This bowel dilatation stimulates cell secretory activity resulting in more fluid accumulation. </s><s n="s3.3;p79.98">This leads to increased peristalsis both above and below the obstruction with frequent loose stools and flatus early in its course. </s></p><p n="p80.98"><s n="s1.5;p80.98">Vomiting occurs if the level of obstruction is proximal. </s><s n="s2.5;p80.98">Increasing small-bowel distention leads to increased intraluminal pressures. </s><s n="s3.5;p80.98">This can cause compression of mucosal lymphatics leading to bowel wall lymphedema. </s><s n="s4.5;p80.98">With even higher intraluminal hydrostatic pressures, increased hydrostatic pressure in the capillary beds results in massive third spacing of fluid, electrolytes, and proteins into the intestinal lumen. </s><s n="s5.5;p80.98">The fluid loss and dehydration that ensue may be severe and contribute to increased morbidity and mortality [1]. </s></p><p n="p81.98"><s n="s1.2;p81.98">MRSA is a huge problem for hospitals nationwide. </s><s n="s2.2;p81.98">Immediate, effective medication is vital in order to treat the infection and prevent further wound dehisence. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="bold">Impact on your learning</hi> Describe what you have learnt from this case</head><p n="p82.98"><s n="s1.1;p82.98">Physical findings in small bowel obstruction </s></p><p n="p83.98"><s n="s1.1;p83.98">The importance of surgical history in small bowel obstruction </s></p><p n="p84.98"><s n="s1.1;p84.98">The management of small bowel obstruction - Adhesive Obstruction - initially managed conservatively </s></p><p n="p85.98"><s n="s1.2;p85.98">Suck and drip is indicated when the obstruction is one of repeated episodes due to massive intra abdominal adhesions, rendering surgery hazardous and where a short period of observation with conservative treatment is indicated. </s><s n="s2.2;p85.98">Conservative treatment is abandoned if there is increased distension, aggravation of pain, increase in abdominal tenderness or rise in pulse. </s></p><p n="p86.98"><s n="s1.2;p86.98">Use of NG tube - Nasogastric tube for gastric aspiration, aims to decompress the bowel and removes the risk of inhalation of gastric contents during induction of anaesthesia. </s><s n="s2.2;p86.98">IV fluid replacement - normal saline to replace fluid lost during vomiting </s></p><p n="p87.98"><s n="s1.5;p87.98">Refeeding syndrome - This is a syndrome of hypophosphataemia, hypomagnesaemia, hypocalcaemia and fluid retention which is seen in severely malnourished patients when they are started on enteral or parenteral nuitrition. </s><s n="s2.5;p87.98">When the patient is straved, total body loss of these minerals is compensated for by movement of ions out from the cells into plasma, to maintain near normal plasma levels. </s><s n="s3.5;p87.98">When feeding is started the increase in insulin level encourages ions to move intracellularly and plasma concentrations fall. </s><s n="s4.5;p87.98">Thiamine deficiency may also be a feature. </s><s n="s5.5;p87.98">Life-theatening dysrhythmias and congestive cardiac failure can result. </s></p><p n="p88.98"><s n="s1.2;p88.98">Vac therapy - vacuum assisted closure of wounds. </s><s n="s2.2;p88.98">The treatment pulls excess fluid and bacteria from the wound site improving blood flow to the wound bed aiding the healing process. </s></p><p n="p89.98"><s n="s1.1;p89.98">Symptoms of small bowel obstruction include: </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p90.98"><s n="s1.2;p90.98">Colicky abdominal pain, felt in mid-abdomen. </s><s n="s2.2;p90.98">Need to know site, radiation, duration and relieving factors. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p91.98"><s n="s1.1;p91.98">no flatus, constipation is present </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p92.98"><s n="s1.1;p92.98">distention, early in the course of the illness if the obstruction is high - seen as </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p93.98"><s n="s1.1;p93.98">vomiting, earlier if the obstruction is relatively proximal in the bowel </s></p><p n="p94.98"><s n="s1.1;p94.98">Signs: </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p95.98"><s n="s1.2;p95.98">dehydration due to loss of fluid from ECF when vomiting. (the gastrointestinal tract secretes 6 litres of fluid per day and during obstruction, this tends to be sequestered) </s><s n="s2.2;p95.98">Hypovolaemia may result in hypotension and tachycardia. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p96.98"><s n="s1.2;p96.98">inspection and palpation may reveal scars, distension, peristalsis, hernias, but no tenderness. </s><s n="s2.2;p96.98">If the blood supply is cut off then tenderness develops. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p97.98"><s n="s1.1;p97.98">auscultation: hyperactive - borborygmus - or ileus </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p98.98"><s n="s1.1;p98.98">rectal examination: may be empty after 24 to 48 hours of symptoms </s></p><list type="bulleted"><head>Investigations</head><item>blood urea and electrolytes </item><item>white cell count </item><item>radiology: </item><item> supine: obstructive picture of dilated small bowel </item><item> sitting: multiple air/fluid levels in obstruction [3]</item></list></div1></body><back><div1 type="bibliography"><head>References</head><p>[1] <seg type="URL" n="http://www.emedicine.com/emerg/topic66.htm"/></p><p>[2] Kumar and Clark Clinical Medicine</p><p>[3] GP notebook</p></div1><div1 type="appendix"><head rend="bold">ASPECTS OF CASE AS RECORDED IN SUMMARY OF PORTFOLIO CASES•</head><p/></div1><div1 type="appendix"><head rend="bold">PORTFOLIO COMPLETION CERTIFICATE</head><p/></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
