<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_0208d" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Management Report for Chemimix Ldt. - Designing a Production Schedule</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">deleted: page numbers</note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">appendix: Linear Programme Formulation</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">1</p><p n="date">2005-03</p><p n="module title">Quantitive Methods of Analysis</p><p n="module code">IB1020</p><p n="genre family">Case study</p><p n="discipline">Business</p><p n="disciplinary group">SS</p><p n="grade">D</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">886</p><p n="number of s-units">28</p><p n="number of p">13</p><p n="number of tables">3</p><p n="number of figures">0</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">0</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">3</p><p n="abstract present">abstract present</p><p n="average words per s-unit">31.6</p><p n="average s-units per p">2.2</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">f</p><p n="year of birth">1985</p><p n="first language">Portuguese</p><p n="education">OSA</p><p n="course">Business</p><p n="student ID">0208</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><docTitle><titlePart rend="underlined">Management Report for Chemimix Ldt.<hi rend="italic"> - Designing a Production Schedule</hi></titlePart></docTitle></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="abstract"><head rend="bold">Summary and Recommendations: </head><p n="p1.13"><s n="s1.1;p1.13">Upon concluding a study on the three options, recommendations are as follows: </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p2.13"><s n="s1.3;p2.13">It is advisable that the firm reduce the Hotel contract to 8,000 units of Detergent C. Not only will this maximize profit (generating £3800 per week), given the current constraints and available resources, but will also guarantee a certain level of sales. </s><s n="s2.3;p2.13">Sales are susceptible to changes in consumer demand, changes in competitor pricing and an array of other external factors, meaning production may not always equal sale levels. </s><s n="s3.3;p2.13">The contract provides steady and guaranteed revenue for the firm, which may not be the case for the other scenarios where many other market factors may affect sales. </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p3.13"><s n="s1.3;p3.13">It is important that management implements and employs a clear weekly production schedule, in order to have constant revenue figures and resolve problems with suppliers. </s><s n="s2.3;p3.13">This will allow a fixed re-ordering scheme to be set-up, were Chemimix may even earn bargaining power to negotiate for lower prices from the suppliers. </s><s n="s3.3;p3.13">Furthermore, this will permit a better management of the firm's assets, possibly even enabling it to benefit from future investment opportunities, as they will have some constancy in their revenue figures, and to make long-run plans. </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p4.13"><s n="s1.2;p4.13">A possibly worthwhile investment which should be studied further is the expansion of the firm's facilities, particularly the acquisition of larger storage tanks. </s><s n="s2.2;p4.13">Even a small increase in these would be significant to revenue changes, as at the suggested profit maximising production level, both of the ingredient constraints are being used to their full capacity and are inhibiting further production (see notes 1 and 2 in Appendix B). </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Introduction:</head><p n="p5.13"><s n="s1.1;p5.13">This report aims to evaluate the current production level and study the viability and advantages of undertaking two different options, namely reducing the hotel's contract from 9,000 to 8,000 units of Commercial Detergent and cancelling it altogether. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Assumptions and limitations:</head><p n="p6.13"><s n="s1.3;p6.13">Chemimix's production is currently restricted by multiple constraints. </s><s n="s2.3;p6.13">For this study, we will assume that the production facilities available are permanent, meaning the tanks holding Ingredients A and B have a set capacity. </s><s n="s3.3;p6.13">Similarly, the bottle supply for the detergents will be considered fixed and at full stock, though this may need confirming, due to possible re-ordering problems left behind from the previous management. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Option A: Maintaining the Hotel Contract (9000 units of Detergent C) </head><p n="p7.13"><s n="s1.4;p7.13">By committing to this contract, Chemimix guarantees the supply of 9,000 units of Commercial Detergent to the Hotel. </s><s n="s2.4;p7.13">As may be observed in Appendix A, the profit generated from this production schedule, consisting of producing 9,000 units of Commercial Detergent (Detergent C) and 3000 units of Household Detergent (Detergent H), is of £3150. </s><s n="s3.4;p7.13">This leaves the production of Detergent C at full capacity levels, as the bottle availability constraint forbids it from increasing. </s><s n="s4.4;p7.13">It is important to note that limited resources (namely Ingredients A and B) are here being allocated to the less profitable Detergent C, thus suppressing the production of the more profitable Detergent H. </s></p><p n="p8.13"><s n="s1.1;p8.13">Assuming the firm has a profit maximizing objective, other opportunities may prove more profitable and should be therefore studied. </s></p><p n="p9.13"><s n="s1.1;p9.13">Similarly, there is a significant slack quantity of Ingredient A (10,000 litres, as verified in the Answer Report in Appendix B) left over when undertaking this option, where the firm may not be making full use of its producing capacity. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Option B: Reducing the Hotel Contract to 8,000 bottle of Detergent C</head><p n="p10.13"><s n="s1.3;p10.13">Upon examining the advantages of reducing the current contract, we find that indeed, more financial benefits are available to the firm. </s><s n="s2.3;p10.13">A small reduction in the production levels of Detergent C from 9,000 to 8,000 units allows us to double the production of Detergent H (from 3,000 to 6,000 units), a more profitable product, yielding additional financial benefits of £650 (see Appendix B). </s><s n="s3.3;p10.13">Furthermore, no slack is left from the ingredient constraints, meaning the firm is making full use of these resources. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Option C: Cancelling the Hotel Contract</head><p n="p11.13"><s n="s1.2;p11.13">The profit maximising production mix given by the cancelling of the hotel contract, remains the same as that of reducing the hotel contract to 8,000 units. </s><s n="s2.2;p11.13">Further details confirm this in Note 1 of Appendix C. However, Option B presents additional non-financial benefits to the firm, offering extra certainty of the sale of 8,000 units of Detergent C weekly, and is therefore preferred. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Implementing the new production schedule:</head><p n="p12.13"><s n="s1.1;p12.13">Having decided on the most profitable product mix, it is important that the firm now develops a clear production schedule in order for to benefit from more constant revenues and resolve past problems regarding the irregularity of production and ordering. </s></p><p n="p13.13"><s n="s1.3;p13.13">Firstly, weekly bottle demand for both types of detergent can be reduced, to 6000 bottles for Detergent H and 8,000 bottles for Detergent C. Secondly, an order for labels will need to be placed in two weeks time, as though not yet a binding constraint currently impacting on production levels, it will soon become one as stock is depleted. </s><s n="s2.3;p13.13">The weekly re-ordering schedule for labels should be of 14,000 labels (8,000 units of Detergent C + 6,000 units of Detergent H). </s><s n="s3.3;p13.13">Find below a summary of the recommended re-ordering schedule for the production resources for this implementation period and for the future (given the initial assumption about the firm's resources being at fully-stocked levels): </s></p><table id="BAWE_0208d-tab.001"><row><cell/></row></table><table id="BAWE_0208d-tab.002"><row><cell/></row></table><table id="BAWE_0208d-tab.003"><row><cell/></row></table></div1></body><back><div1 type="appendix"><head>APPENDIX A:</head><p/></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
