<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_0208a" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Why did Brazil's GDP growth slowdown in 2001? Assess the strength of the recovery after 2002 and the prospects for 2005 in the light of oil price increases in 2004. How has the fall of the US dollar impacted the Brazilian economy? To what extent is Brazil over-dependent on the economic performance of the US?</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">deleted: page numbers</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">1</p><p n="date">2004-12</p><p n="module title">Economics 1</p><p n="module code">EC107</p><p n="genre family">Essay</p><p n="discipline">Economics</p><p n="disciplinary group">SS</p><p n="grade">M</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">1807</p><p n="number of s-units">53</p><p n="number of p">21</p><p n="number of tables">0</p><p n="number of figures">2</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">0</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">0</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">34.1</p><p n="average s-units per p">2.5</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">f</p><p n="year of birth">1985</p><p n="first language">Portuguese</p><p n="education">OSA</p><p n="course">Economics</p><p n="student ID">0208</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><titlePart><hi rend="underlined">EC1070</hi><name type="student ID"/></titlePart><docTitle><titlePart rend="bold italic">Why did Brazil's GDP growth slowdown in 2001? Assess the strength of the recovery after 2002 and the prospects for 2005 in the light of oil price increases in 2004. How has the fall of the US dollar impacted the Brazilian economy? To what extent is Brazil over-dependent on the economic performance of the US? </titlePart></docTitle></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="section"><p n="p1.21"><s n="s1.2;p1.21">By 2001, Brazil should have started to feel the full effect of the Real devaluation<ref target="BAWE_0208a-ftnote.001"/> in 1999, giving them an increased competitive advantage in the export market coupled with other government policies designed to liberalize trade and encourage investment; It was experiencing some promising growth in the areas of consumption and investment (see Appendix 1) and had reached a degree of stability largely due to the export-led recovery. </s><s n="s2.2;p1.21">However, this impact did not fully materialize as the US economy was beginning to show signs of a slowdown. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0208a-ftnote.001"><p n="pn1.2"><s n="s1.1;pn1.2">The Real was devalued to approximately US$2.07, after having been reached near an equal exchange with </s></p><p n="pn2.2"><s n="s1.1;pn2.2">the dollar. </s></p></note></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined italic">The 2001 slowdown </head><p n="p2.21"><s n="s1.3;p2.21">Brazil, being highly susceptible to external shocks due to its dependence on exports, was even more acutely affected in 2001 by the 9/11 tragedy. </s><s n="s2.3;p2.21">To begin looking at how this impacted the national economy and slowed down the GDP growth, one must quickly examine the determinants of GDP. GDP<ref target="BAWE_0208a-ftnote.002"/> can be measured by either looking at the nation's total output, its total expenditure or its total income. </s><s n="s3.3;p2.21">A change in one of these will be reflected in both other values, as the economy reaches equilibrium where output = expenditure = income. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0208a-ftnote.002"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">GDP is defined as the total flow of economic activity in an economy during a given period, usually a year. </s></p></note><p n="p3.21"><s n="s1.3;p3.21">September 11 triggered an economic slowdown in the US that had a spill-over effect on the Brazilian economy. </s><s n="s2.3;p3.21">The fear factor and an element of uncertainty about the future led to a considerable fall in consumption<ref target="BAWE_0208a-ftnote.003"/>, which is the main component of aggregate demand. </s><s n="s3.3;p3.21">This was particularly felt by Brazil as the demand for Brazilian exports decreased<ref target="BAWE_0208a-ftnote.004"/> from the end 2001, curbing some of the much needed revenue from exports, a major contributor to the growth experienced in the previous years in Brazil, as verified below. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0208a-ftnote.003"><p n="pn1.2"><s n="s1.1;pn1.2">Consumption was experiencing a considerable growth of 3.2% in 2000, compared to the fall to 0.8% in </s></p><p n="pn2.2"><s n="s1.1;pn2.2">2001 according to the National Statistic Institute (IBGE) </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0208a-ftnote.004"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Total revenues from exports fell by about US$3bn. </s></p></note><figure id="BAWE_0208a-fig.001"><head rend="bold">Trade Balance, 1995 - 2004 (Graph 1)</head></figure><p n="p4.21"><s n="s1.1;p4.21">This in turn lowers the equilibrium output of the nation (hence lowering the expenditure on these goods and thus the income from employment, which resulted on a downward multiplier effect<ref target="BAWE_0208a-ftnote.005"/>), thereby slowing down GDP growth (for values look at Appendix 1). </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0208a-ftnote.005"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">The multiplier illustrates how national income changes as a result of an initial injection. </s></p></note><p n="p5.21"><s n="s1.2;p5.21">This, coupled with oil price increases<ref target="BAWE_0208a-ftnote.006"/> had a rather detrimental impact on production costs in Brazil, and finally on prices. </s><s n="s2.2;p5.21">This not only made the exports less competitive, but posed the problem of cost-push inflation<ref target="BAWE_0208a-ftnote.007"/>. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0208a-ftnote.006"><p n="pn1.2"><s n="s1.1;pn1.2">Brent type oil, for example, for delivery in November, was up by 3,2% being negotiated at US$ 29,31 for </s></p><p n="pn2.2"><s n="s1.1;pn2.2">a barrel in London. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0208a-ftnote.007"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Cost-push inflation is defined as price increases due to a rise in factor costs. </s></p></note><p n="p6.21"><s n="s1.2;p6.21">The oil price hikes might not even have been as acutely felt by Brazilians, who were hoping to be self-sufficient with their oil demands by 2005, had it not been for an accident taking place in the Petrobrás platform P-36, a crucial oil source in Brazil. </s><s n="s2.2;p6.21">Though Brazil possesses alternative sources of energy (which it is increasingly attempting to rely on), the manufacturing and industrial sectors suffered a supply shortage and necessitated imports, causing a deterioration of Brazil's trade balance<ref target="BAWE_0208a-ftnote.008"/> Both of these, as is verified in Appendix 2, experienced the largest slowdown and were greatly responsible for the deceleration of the GDP growth. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0208a-ftnote.008"><p n="pn1.3"><s n="s1.1;pn1.3">The trade balance shifted from a US$126 million surplus in the first half of 2000 to a US$ 1.6 billion </s></p><p n="pn2.3"><s n="s1.1;pn2.3">deficit by August 2001, as strong export growth (11.9%) was outpaced by and an even stronger import </s></p><p n="pn3.3"><s n="s1.1;pn3.3">growth (15.3%) - see graph 1. </s></p></note><p n="p7.21"><s n="s1.1;p7.21">Simultaneously, a government-imposed energy rationing programme (as a result of a drought that depleted the hydropower reserves) further jeopardized the GDP growth within the industrial sector, which has been the backbone of the strong economic rebound the previous year<ref target="BAWE_0208a-ftnote.009"/>. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0208a-ftnote.009"><p n="pn1.2"><s n="s1.1;pn1.2">The industrial sector was deeply affected as its growth rate was reduced from 5% in the previous year to </s></p><p n="pn2.2"><s n="s1.1;pn2.2">-0.5%, according to the National Statistic Institute (IBGE) </s></p></note><p n="p8.21"><s n="s1.3;p8.21">Within the same time frame, the government also announced an increase in the interest rates, possibly as a measure to curb internal consumption and investment, which had been on the rise since the start of the year<ref target="BAWE_0208a-ftnote.010"/> (presenting the danger of inflation, as increased production costs are frequently passed on to the consumers. </s><s n="s2.3;p8.21">This in turn causes workers to demand higher wages, possibly triggering off a wage-price spiral), a recurring nightmare for Brazilians, particularly in light of the hyperinflation period between 1987 and 1997. </s><s n="s3.3;p8.21">More likely however, the government saw an opportunity to attract much needed foreign investment and capital inflows, to offset the downward trend in the capital account of the balance of payments (see graph in Appendix 3). </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0208a-ftnote.010"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Interest rates rose continuously from 15,25% at the start of the year, to 19% at the end of the year. </s></p></note><p n="p9.21"><s n="s1.2;p9.21">These continuous increases of the interest rate, up to about 19% (the 4 <hi rend="sup">th</hi> highest interest rate in the world at the time), were probably one of the large contributors to the significant decrease in consumption and investment in the nation<ref target="BAWE_0208a-ftnote.011"/>, as one may conclude from the graph below (also see Appendix 4 - <hi rend="italic">The IS Schedule</hi>).A slow down of domestic consumption occurs as saving becomes a more attractive alternative at high interest rates and borrowing increasingly difficult. </s><s n="s2.2;p9.21">This increased difficulty in borrowing is also mirrored in investment figures; firms are discouraged to borrow at such high costs, thereby constraining investment and slowing down the accelerator<ref target="BAWE_0208a-ftnote.012"/> process. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0208a-ftnote.011"><p n="pn1.3"><s n="s1.1;pn1.3">Consumption registered a slowdown from a 3.2% growth rate in 2000 to 0.8% in 2001. </s></p><p n="pn2.3"><s n="s1.1;pn2.3">Investment registered a slowdown from 4.5% to 1.1% in the same period - National Statistic Institute </s></p><p n="pn3.3"><s n="s1.1;pn3.3">(IBGE) </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0208a-ftnote.012"><p n="pn1.2"><s n="s1.1;pn1.2">The accelerator is a process which indicated by how much investment increases due to a rise in National </s></p><p n="pn2.2"><s n="s1.1;pn2.2">Income. </s></p></note><figure id="BAWE_0208a-fig.002"><head rend="bold">Gross Domestic Product Growth by Type of Expenditure (Graph 2) </head></figure><p n="p10.21"><s n="s1.3;p10.21">Investment decisions are very volatile and highly dependant on future expectation. </s><s n="s2.3;p10.21">The coming election of 2002 may have caused some uneasiness in the business sector, further limiting investment (see Appendix 4 - <hi rend="italic">Shifting the IS Schedule</hi>). </s><s n="s3.3;p10.21">Resulting from this pessimism and possibly predicted future wage increase demands (as a result of inflationary pressures from oil price increases), the unemployment rate rose tremendously in 2001, perhaps proving the original Phillips Curve correct, as high unemployment was unavoidable with the containment of inflation . </s></p><p n="p11.21"><s n="s1.2;p11.21">2001 was also marked by another event which may have had some probable indirect implications on Brazil's economic performance. </s><s n="s2.2;p11.21">The extent of the direct impact of the Argentinean crisis on the Brazilian economy is debatable<ref target="BAWE_0208a-ftnote.013"/>, but what was evident was that investor confidence in growing South American markets certainly suffered a blow<ref target="BAWE_0208a-ftnote.014"/>. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0208a-ftnote.013"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Argentina accounts for only about 7% of the Brazilian export market. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0208a-ftnote.014"><p n="pn1.3"><s n="s1.2;pn1.3">Investment growth slowed down from a 4.5% growth rate in 2000 to 1.1% in 2001. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.3">Similarly, the stock </s></p><p n="pn2.3"><s n="s1.1;pn2.3">market was down (Bovespa Stock Exchange falling from 151.9% to -10% in 2001) and the bond market </s></p><p n="pn3.3"><s n="s1.1;pn3.3">was up. </s></p></note><p n="p12.21"><s n="s1.3;p12.21">The trade balance disequilibrium could have had further detrimental effects for the national economy; as the value of the currency depreciated, external debt became more expensive and thus increasingly difficult to service and repay. </s><s n="s2.3;p12.21">Deterioration of the Real, coupled with high interest rates put pressure on the domestic debt burden (which reached 53.7% of GDP in August 2001), especially since an estimated 27.1% was dollar determined. </s><s n="s3.3;p12.21">Further fiscal adjustments in the form of tax hikes were necessitated to finance these additional costs, resulting in an increased downward pressure on economic activity. </s></p><div2><head rend="underlined italic">The 2002 Recovery and prospects for 2005</head><p n="p13.21"><s n="s1.4;p13.21">The various accrued factors, which cumulatively had led to the slowdown of the Brazilian economy in 2001, showed signs of subsiding in 2002, and there was evidence of the economy taking a more positive turn. </s><s n="s2.4;p13.21">The deterioration of the Real began to stabilize in the last couple of months of 2001(at around 0.423247 USD); the energy rationing scheme eased its strong grip (lowering both production costs inflationary expectations); the US economy started picking up; and a degree of investor confidence returned to Brazil, as businesses witnessed Brazil's solid fiscal performance backed by the IMF. To avoid the danger of an inflationary trend, Brazil's interest rates were not immediately lowered as a stimulus or boost in the economy, as we may have expected. </s><s n="s3.4;p13.21">This strategy contained consumption and investment for much of 2002<ref target="BAWE_0208a-ftnote.015"/> but continued to encourage large capital inflows throughout 2003 and 2004<ref target="BAWE_0208a-ftnote.016"/>. </s><s n="s4.4;p13.21">The external sector recovery also played a part in this recovery, with exports picking up and import demand falling (perhaps as a further consequence of the high interest rates and the considerable devaluation of the Real), thereby improving the trade balance. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0208a-ftnote.015"><p n="pn1.2"><s n="s1.1;pn1.2">Consumption suffered only a 0.1% increase in 2002, and investment actually suffered a negative growth </s></p><p n="pn2.2"><s n="s1.1;pn2.2">of -4.2% - National Statistic Institute (IBGE) </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0208a-ftnote.016"><p n="pn1.2"><s n="s1.1;pn1.2">Foreign direct investment increased by 1.5 billion till Nov 2004, 10.1 billion of which took place in </s></p><p n="pn2.2"><s n="s1.1;pn2.2">2003 - National Statistic Institute (IBGE) </s></p></note><p n="p14.21"><s n="s1.3;p14.21">Nonetheless, oil prices in Brazil suffered some increases in 2002 (due to the continued turmoil that afflicted the Middle East) and political instability still loomed about, which suppressed a quick economic recovery. </s><s n="s2.3;p14.21">Investors were wary of the prospect of a 'popularist's' victory, who might sacrifice sound macroeconomic policies for popularity. </s><s n="s3.3;p14.21">Only in 2003, investors were reassured as Lula promised to maintain fiscal discipline, preserve price stability and comply with contractual obligations, committing to the continuity of Cardoso's (somewhat stringent) economic policies. </s></p><p n="p15.21"><s n="s1.2;p15.21">These sound strategies further narrowed the deficit, and reached a surplus in 2003 (see Appendix 3), thereby enhancing the confidence of those who believed that Brazil was following the right path to economic prosperity. </s><s n="s2.2;p15.21">According to the FCESP<ref target="BAWE_0208a-ftnote.017"/>, in 2004, consumer confidence began slowly picking up in the form of current consumption and investment (future expectations), possibly as people were convinced that Brazil was capable of withstanding further domestic and external shocks as those experienced in 2001. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0208a-ftnote.017"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Federação do Comércio do Estado de São Paulo </s></p></note><p n="p16.21"><s n="s1.2;p16.21">The IBGE<ref target="BAWE_0208a-ftnote.018"/> also showed a downward trend in the unemployment rate, which peaked in 1999 at 9,6 and fell to 9,2 in 2003, possible also serving to boost consumption in the same year. </s><s n="s2.2;p16.21">Many believe that another important factor to the confidence build up in 2004 were the free-trade talks with America through Mercosur<ref target="BAWE_0208a-ftnote.019"/>. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0208a-ftnote.018"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Instituto Brasileiro de Geografia e Estatística </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0208a-ftnote.019"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Trading block formed by various South American countries, including Brazil. </s></p></note><p n="p17.21"><s n="s1.4;p17.21">In 2005, Brazil should look to the Far and Middle East and the emerging Eastern European markets for new export markets while the dollar recovers. </s><s n="s2.4;p17.21">Simultaneously, 2005 may see increases in government spending, as the Congress just recently increased and passed Lula's initial budget for this year (with a 13% increase from this 2004's), while keeping budget deficit at a 10 year low (2-2.45% of GDP). </s><s n="s3.4;p17.21">The government has revealed plans to invest in the country's infrastructure through a scheme of "Public and Private Partnerships", finally engaging in the improvement of the nation's infrastructure, which has long been considered a hurdle to investment in Brazil. </s><s n="s4.4;p17.21">These projects might have a further beneficial function in decreasing unemployment rates, as construction tends to have high labour demands. </s></p><p n="p18.21"><s n="s1.3;p18.21">Brazil is experiencing a supply-side bottle neck in its seaports' capacity, that is restricting export growth. </s><s n="s2.3;p18.21">These ports are currently operating at near full capacity, and finding it difficult to cope with the prospect of increasing export demand. </s><s n="s3.3;p18.21">The government, having already identified this problem, is looking into several proposals from different concessionaries. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined italic">Brazil's dependence on the US</head><p n="p19.21"><s n="s1.5;p19.21">As mentioned earlier, the Brazilian economy is largely dependant on its exports and given that the US constitutes nearly 25% of the Brazilian export market<ref target="BAWE_0208a-ftnote.020"/>, it is highly susceptible to external shocks. </s><s n="s2.5;p19.21">The persistent depreciation of the US dollar through most of 2004 may have potentially harmful effects on the Brazilian economy. </s><s n="s3.5;p19.21">As the dollar depreciates, Brazilian exports lose their competitiveness<ref target="BAWE_0208a-ftnote.021"/> in the American markets and Brazil forgoes its much needed revenue from exports. </s><s n="s4.5;p19.21">A serious threat posed is the growing competitive advantage the Chinese are gaining, particularly by having their currency fixed against the dollar. </s><s n="s5.5;p19.21">This allows their export prices to remain stable in the American markets, thereby reducing the demand for Brazilian exports. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0208a-ftnote.020"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">In 2000, exports accounted for 9.9% of GDP, 24.3% of which was directed to the US (2.6% of GDP). </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0208a-ftnote.021"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">This competitiveness is determined by three factors: domestic prices, exchange rate and the state of the foreign economy. </s></p></note><p n="p20.21"><s n="s1.2;p20.21">Similarly, the dollar depreciation may bring about a greater demand for American exports in Brazil for 2005, possibly having adverse effect in the country's balance of payments At the same time however, the loss of confidence in the dollar and the change in the demand for the dollar as a reserve currency may diminish capital flight to America in the form of direct and foreign investment (as returns will be lower when repatriated and the yield would be smaller) The loss of status as many nations' reserve currency may cause the dollar to plummet even further, making American imports in Brazil cheaper while discouraging Brazilian exports. </s><s n="s2.2;p20.21">This could result in a downturn in Brazil's Balance of Payments, reverting from a surplus to a deficit. </s></p><p n="p21.21"><s n="s1.1;p21.21">On the other side, a possible benefit is that Brazil's debt burden which is calculated in dollars will be lessened. </s></p></div2></div1></body><back/></text></TEI.2>
