<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_0209a" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Produce a critical evaluation of the impact of the judicial decisions of the late Lord Denning MR on the rights of persons in residential occupation.</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">deleted: footer: student number
</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">1</p><p n="date">2004-04</p><p n="module title">Introduction to the Law of Property Relations</p><p n="module code">LA103</p><p n="genre family">Essay</p><p n="discipline">Law</p><p n="disciplinary group">SS</p><p n="grade">D</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">2594</p><p n="number of s-units">118</p><p n="number of p">14</p><p n="number of tables">0</p><p n="number of figures">0</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">0</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">0</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">22.0</p><p n="average s-units per p">8.4</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">m</p><p n="year of birth">1985</p><p n="first language">English</p><p n="education">UKA</p><p n="course">Law LLB</p><p n="student ID">0209</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><docTitle><titlePart rend="bold italic">Produce a critical evaluation of the impact of the judicial decisions of the late Lord Denning MR on the rights of persons in residential occupation. </titlePart></docTitle></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="section"><p n="p1.14"><s n="s1.3;p1.14">Lord Denning, renowned idol of the judicial system is known for his bold creativity and unashamed disrespect for precedent. </s><s n="s2.3;p1.14">Denning chooses to "deal on principle"<ref target="BAWE_0209a-ftnote.001"/> with matters where law fails claimants, assisting the development of occupational rights in the home, using astonishingly inventive justifications. </s><s n="s3.3;p1.14">I shall examine his efforts on establishing wives equity in the home, rights for deserted wives, and proprietary estoppel, critically analysing his justification and intuitive approaches: was he right, why was such radical judicial activity necessary and were his 'achievements' really progress? </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0209a-ftnote.001"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Lord Denning, The Due Process of Law on H v H (1947) 63 TLR 645 at 646 </s></p></note><p n="p2.14"><s n="s1.12;p2.14">Denning's most memorable contribution was his gift to women: the 'deserted wife's equity,' an example of the fabled judicial law creation that Denning is so fondly renowned. </s><s n="s2.12;p2.14">When Denning was appointed, law was undergoing radical reform concerning gender equality and women's rights. </s><s n="s3.12;p2.14">Aged patriarchal values of male superiority were staging their last strive for survival, whilst law reform was typically unhurried. </s><s n="s4.12;p2.14">Women had restricted proprietary rights and the majority of title papers were in the husband's name. </s><s n="s5.12;p2.14">"Under the old common law as it existed until 70 years ago she had no rights at all apart from those of her husband. </s><s n="s6.12;p2.14">She was treated by the law more like a piece of furniture than anything else." </s><ref target="BAWE_0209a-ftnote.002"/><s n="s7.12;p2.14">When a husband deserted his wife, she had no legal right to remain in the home, Denning commenting: "I could see an injustice, it cried out for a remedy." </s><s n="s8.12;p2.14">His first reform opportunity was in H v H<ref target="BAWE_0209a-ftnote.003"/> where a deserted wife was threatened with eviction when the husband wanted to sell their matrimonial home. </s><s n="s9.12;p2.14">In an act of pure judicial creativity, Denning "did not cite a single case" and "dealt with it on principle,"<ref target="BAWE_0209a-ftnote.004"/> claiming that "at common law the husband has no right to turn the wife out of the house," and that "he has no right in law to claim possession except under S17 Married Women's Property Act 1882." </s><ref target="BAWE_0209a-ftnote.005"/><s n="s10.12;p2.14">Whilst the decision grasped the just principle it stood alone, unprecedented and heavily reliant on S17 entitling judges to "make such an order with respect to property in dispute as he thinks fit." </s><s n="s11.12;p2.14">Denning proclaimed it afforded "a free hand to do what is just." </s><s n="s12.12;p2.14">The wife was saved. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0209a-ftnote.002"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Lord Denning, The Due Process of Law </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0209a-ftnote.003"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">H v H (1947) 63 TLR 645 at 646 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0209a-ftnote.004"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Lord Denning, The Due Process of Law on H v H (1947) 63 TLR 645 at 646 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0209a-ftnote.005"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Lord Denning in H v H (1947) 63 TLR 645 at 646 as expressed in "Lord Denning, Due Process of Law" </s></p></note><p n="p3.14"><s n="s1.8;p3.14">The decision was not without legal footing: inspiration for S17's ingenious use stemmed from Goddard LJ in 1942. </s><s n="s2.8;p3.14">Shipman v Shipman<ref target="BAWE_0209a-ftnote.006"/> stated that a man cannot treat his wife as a stranger (and thus evict her). </s><s n="s3.8;p3.14">Denning questioned why the position should change if the man wronged and deserted, suggesting "it is the husbands duty to provide the woman with a roof over her head; and by providing the matrimonial home, he gives her an authority to be there" which is irrevocable. </s><s n="s4.8;p3.14">His beliefs are morally grounded, pragmatic and just, providing order in a changing society with increasing separation. </s><s n="s5.8;p3.14">Bendall v McWhirter<ref target="BAWE_0209a-ftnote.007"/> entrenches the rule, Denning this time elaborating and affording the wife an equitable right to remain in the home; believing equity must answer law's failings. </s><s n="s6.8;p3.14">This was a fictitious creation. </s><s n="s7.8;p3.14">Furthermore, Bendall exaggerates protection, the right becoming binding on successors in title; in this instance the trustee of the husbands bankruptcy, Denning deciding that "of all the creditors, she has the most crying claim of all." </s><ref target="BAWE_0209a-ftnote.008"/><s n="s8.8;p3.14">Women were therefore justly protected from eviction by mistresses, trustees, or husband/purchaser collaborations. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0209a-ftnote.006"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Shipman v Shipman (1924) 2 Ch 140 at 146, 40 TLR 483, CA </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0209a-ftnote.007"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Bendall v McWhirter (1952) 2 QB 466 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0209a-ftnote.008"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Lord Denning, The Due Process of Law </s></p></note><p n="p4.14"><s n="s1.7;p4.14">The Lords in National Provincial v Hastings<ref target="BAWE_0209a-ftnote.009"/> was unanimous in holding that deserted wives had no equity in the home, crushing Denning's principle. </s><s n="s2.7;p4.14">Denning crossed the line from judge to law maker, stating that despite absence of legal or equitable interests wives have a "licence coupled with equity,"<ref target="BAWE_0209a-ftnote.010"/> "enforceable against any successor except a purchaser for full value without notice." </s><ref target="BAWE_0209a-ftnote.011"/><s n="s3.7;p4.14">Purists and colleagues objected, the LQR<ref target="BAWE_0209a-ftnote.012"/> stating "legislation, not litigation is the only satisfactory way of delimiting the bounds of so complex subject." "Protection for the wife should... be provided by statutory amendments...rather than judicial invention." </s><ref target="BAWE_0209a-ftnote.013"/><s n="s4.7;p4.14">Judicial freedom is necessary to achieve justice, e.g. literal interpretation is notoriously unjust, yet for law to be a certain, democratic machine judges cannot be allowed free reign. </s><s n="s5.7;p4.14">The value was acknowledged, not the justification. </s><s n="s6.7;p4.14">Indeed, Formalistic theories (e.g. </s><s n="s7.7;p4.14">Dworkin) stress the importance of judicial segregation to create a cohesive, democratic system. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0209a-ftnote.009"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">National Provincial Bank v Hastings Car Mart Ltd (1964) Ch 665 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0209a-ftnote.010"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">as per Lord Denning M.R. C.A. in National Provincial Bank v Hastings Car Mart Ltd (1964) </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0209a-ftnote.011"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">as per Lord Denning M.R. C.A. in National Provincial Bank v Hastings Car Mart Ltd (1964) </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0209a-ftnote.012"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Law Quarterly Review July 1952 (68 LQR 379) by R.E. Megarry </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0209a-ftnote.013"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Law Quarterly Review July 1952 (68 LQR 379) by R.E. Megarry </s></p></note><p n="p5.14"><s n="s1.11;p5.14">Yet Denning actions were true hallmarks of justice; it was ingenious, providing practical solutions decided "on principle." </s><s n="s2.11;p5.14">It was elastic, and like his other creations it was expanded until restrained by the ever conscious Lords. </s><s n="s3.11;p5.14">Finally it afforded women the dignity and respect they deserved, illustrating the inadequacy and gender inequality of legislative provisions. </s><s n="s4.11;p5.14">Perhaps Denning was justified, a Royal Commission<ref target="BAWE_0209a-ftnote.014"/> stating "we think it is right to afford this protection to a deserted wife." </s><s n="s5.11;p5.14">Denning himself believes that it may have taken "40 years"<ref target="BAWE_0209a-ftnote.015"/> until other provisions would have been made. </s><s n="s6.11;p5.14">From Feminist perspectives the decision has immense value, acknowledging the male paradigm and deconstructing the patriarchy that subordinates women in the home. </s><s n="s7.11;p5.14">In a liberal society, where public and private spheres of life are divided, existing proprietary rights excluded women, assisting their suppression. </s><s n="s8.11;p5.14">Why should women surrender their rights, acknowledging male superiority? </s><s n="s9.11;p5.14">Denning assured law did not fail women. </s><s n="s10.11;p5.14">The ethos continued: Lady Summerskill introduced a Bill in 1964 reinstating provisions, becoming the Matrimonial Homes Act<ref target="BAWE_0209a-ftnote.016"/>. </s><s n="s11.11;p5.14">Denning was principally correct, providing temporary justice, provoking creation of suitable legislation. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0209a-ftnote.014"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Royal Commission on Marriage and Divorce (Cmnd. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">9678 (1956), p.180) Paragraph 664 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0209a-ftnote.015"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Lord Denning, The Due Process of Law </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0209a-ftnote.016"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Matrimonial Homes Act 1967 </s></p></note><p n="p6.14"><s n="s1.6;p6.14">Denning made judgements concerning proprietary estoppel; where an estate owner expressly or impliedly creates informal assurances concerning existing or future land rights, and then attempts an unconscientious withdrawal from the representation which another has relied to their detriment. </s><s n="s2.6;p6.14">Inwards v Baker<ref target="BAWE_0209a-ftnote.017"/> is a classic example, where a son built on his fathers land, and once conveyed in the will faced eviction owing to the agreements informal nature. </s><s n="s3.6;p6.14">Denning applies estoppel as it is the only plausible solution: the law disfavours informal creation of rights (no deed/registration), gratuitous promises are unenforceable (not contractual), voluntarily rendered services are not compensational and consensual occupation is not adverse possession. </s><s n="s4.6;p6.14">Denning imposed equity: it is "a licence coupled with equity"<ref target="BAWE_0209a-ftnote.018"/> and implies a promise, stating it need not fail as "the interest to be secured has not been expressly indicated . . . the court must look at the circumstances in each case to decide in what way the equity can be satisfied." </s><ref target="BAWE_0209a-ftnote.019"/><s n="s5.6;p6.14">This was just, and was expressly affirmed by the Privy Council. </s><s n="s6.6;p6.14">It was a pragmatic solution to a commonplace problem: families rarely create formal agreements; illustrating Denning as grounded and understanding: not the stereotypical judge. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0209a-ftnote.017"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Inwards v Baker (1965) 2 QB 21, CA </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0209a-ftnote.018"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Lord Denning in Inwards v Baker (1965) 2 QB 21, CA </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0209a-ftnote.019"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Lord Denning in Inwards v Baker (1965) 2 QB 21, CA </s></p></note><p n="p7.14"><s n="s1.4;p7.14">The issues were whether equity was transferable to third parties. </s><s n="s2.4;p7.14">Law appeared to limit equity as a personal interest, yet today equity is generally freely transmissible to third parties. </s><s n="s3.4;p7.14">Denning was ahead of his time, clearly supporting this transition in Ives Investment v High,<ref target="BAWE_0209a-ftnote.020"/> stating equity as "available to successors in title," reiterating his comment in Inwards. </s><s n="s4.4;p7.14">Today increasing support exists, perhaps Denning was right. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0209a-ftnote.020"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">E.R. Ives Investment Ltd. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">V High(1967) 2 QB 379 CA </s></p></note><p n="p8.14"><s n="s1.12;p8.14">A related development concerned contractual licences and the creation of equities. </s><s n="s2.12;p8.14">Traditional doctrine holds that contractual licences confer no proprietary interests upon the licensee, thus even with actual occupation or receivership of rents and profits the contractual licence never forms an overriding interest under S70(1)(g) LPA<ref target="BAWE_0209a-ftnote.021"/>. </s><s n="s3.12;p8.14">This reflects orthodox views that contracts are personal. </s><s n="s4.12;p8.14">Denning created controversy, suggesting that licences coupled with equity could affect third parties, almost akin to a proprietary right, overriding the privity of contract principle. </s><s n="s5.12;p8.14">He was the "foremost protagonist of the theory,"<ref target="BAWE_0209a-ftnote.022"/> lifting the contractual licence to a status of "virtual equitable interest." </s><ref target="BAWE_0209a-ftnote.023"/><s n="s6.12;p8.14">Denning without authority, maintained that in registered land a contractual licence coupled with actual occupation constituted an overriding interest; reiterating his own comments expressed in Errington v Errington<ref target="BAWE_0209a-ftnote.024"/> that equitable intervention afforded contractual licences a "force and validity of their own, which could bind third parties." </s><ref target="BAWE_0209a-ftnote.025"/><s n="s7.12;p8.14">Known as the Denning doctrine it was contentious because of the power it afforded the court: contractual licences could be protected against most other rights. </s><s n="s8.12;p8.14">Denning believed that equity could protect the licensee from wrongful revocation. </s><s n="s9.12;p8.14">It was applied in Binnons v Evans<ref target="BAWE_0209a-ftnote.026"/>, where the occupier of a cottage, sold from an estate at a reduced price on the contractual agreement that she could reside there rent-free for life now faced eviction from the new owners. </s><s n="s10.12;p8.14">Denning explored the possibilities. </s><s n="s11.12;p8.14">There was no tenancy at will as she could not determine the agreement, and was inconsistent with the requirements. </s><s n="s12.12;p8.14">It was not a life tenancy as she had no power of sale, and was contrary to the intentions of the parties, and it was no other form of tenancy as there was no term of years in absolute, required by Lace v Chantler.<ref target="BAWE_0209a-ftnote.027"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0209a-ftnote.021"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">S70 (1) (g) Law of Property Act 1925 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0209a-ftnote.022"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Law of Property Volume II: Property 2002 (Oxford: Hart, 2003) </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0209a-ftnote.023"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Law of Property Volume II: Property 2002 (Oxford: Hart, 2003) </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0209a-ftnote.024"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Errington v Errington and Woods (1952) 1 KB 290 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0209a-ftnote.025"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Lord Denning MR </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0209a-ftnote.026"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Binnons v Evans (1972) 1 Ch 359, Court of Appeal </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0209a-ftnote.027"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Lace v Chantler </s></p></note><p n="p9.14"><s n="s1.9;p9.14">Denning believed that it should be an equitable interest: under Foster v Robinson<ref target="BAWE_0209a-ftnote.028"/> equity will not turn out an occupier if that breaches the contract. </s><s n="s2.9;p9.14">The court gave the contract an equitable construction, imposing a constructive trust. </s><s n="s3.9;p9.14">Realistically the contractual licence became binding upon the third party where they have full notice of it. </s><s n="s4.9;p9.14">It was the just result for the case, but as a principle it attracted wide criticism. </s><s n="s5.9;p9.14">National Provincial v Hastings<ref target="BAWE_0209a-ftnote.029"/> stated contractual licences "could only ever be private arrangements," and Fox LJ named Denning's doctrine as a "far reaching statement of principle," indicating that it could not bind third parties.<ref target="BAWE_0209a-ftnote.030"/> Criticism likened the doctrine to "a cinema ticket creating a proprietary right,"<ref target="BAWE_0209a-ftnote.031"/> an extreme but natural possibility and indication of how dangerously limitless judicial creations could become. </s><s n="s6.9;p9.14">Denning was fortunately correct, perhaps justified, but today I question whether society would tolerate such undemocratic law creation. </s><s n="s7.9;p9.14">Such behaviour is potentially perilous, disrespecting the impartiality and autonomy of law establishment. </s><s n="s8.9;p9.14">Denning synthesised law, but it achieved justice despite being denounced. </s><s n="s9.9;p9.14">It was the only way to achieve the right result, so despite subsequent overruling it served its purpose: Denning's bold move out of line was entirely worthwhile. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0209a-ftnote.028"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Foster v Robinson (1951) </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0209a-ftnote.029"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">LJ Russell in Nartional Provincial Bank Ltd. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">V Hastings Car Mart </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0209a-ftnote.030"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">lJ Fox in Ashbrun Anstalt v Arnold </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0209a-ftnote.031"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Law of Property Volume II: Property 2002 (Oxford: Hart, 2003) </s></p></note><p n="p10.14"><s n="s1.6;p10.14">Denning contributed immensely to the development of women's rights in the home, akin to his work for the 'deserted wife's equity.' </s><s n="s2.6;p10.14">Where issues continued for deserted wives, normal women were gaining a right in the home despite registration in the husbands' name, with Denning at the forefront. </s><s n="s3.6;p10.14">The first achievement was establishing a share in the proceeds of sale for the wife, Denning protesting against his fellows in Hoddinott v Hoddinott<ref target="BAWE_0209a-ftnote.032"/> where the court ruled that wife's would not receive any proceeds unless contracted to do so. </s><s n="s4.6;p10.14">Denning effectively overruled this, disregarding the doctrine of precedent, and stating that "beneficial interests in the matrimonial, or furniture, belongs to one or the other absolutely, or it is clear that they intended to hold it in definite shares. </s><s n="s5.6;p10.14">The court will give effect to these intentions;" striking an accommodating approach. </s><s n="s6.6;p10.14">In Rimmer v Rimmer<ref target="BAWE_0209a-ftnote.033"/>, Denning ruled to give equal share; this was fair as she had made substantial mortgage repayments, the decision effectively giving the courts a free hand. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0209a-ftnote.032"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Hoddinott v Hoddinott (1949) 2 KB 406 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0209a-ftnote.033"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Rimmer v Rimmer </s></p></note><p n="p11.14"><s n="s1.14;p11.14">Subsequent progression established women a share in the house, however precedent was restricting: "The wife had right to the house or any share in it unless she could show a contract by the husband with her or a gift by him to her or a trust by him for her in regard to it." </s><ref target="BAWE_0209a-ftnote.034"/><s n="s2.14;p11.14">Denning disregarded this stating, "I do think that line of argument is valid today...in many cases...the intention of the parties is not clear... the court has to attribute an intention to them,"<ref target="BAWE_0209a-ftnote.035"/> again affording the judge a 'free hand.' </s><s n="s3.14;p11.14">Denning's approach is refreshingly realistic for the period, suggesting that when living together "it does not matter who does the saving or the spending or payments:" you intend to "live together for the rest of your lives." </s><s n="s4.14;p11.14">His application ensured justice in a good many cases, e.g. </s><s n="s5.14;p11.14">Rimmer v Rimmer<ref target="BAWE_0209a-ftnote.036"/> and he extended and justified the principle once again by using S17 MWPA<ref target="BAWE_0209a-ftnote.037"/> in Appleton v Appelton,<ref target="BAWE_0209a-ftnote.038"/> similar to the deserted wife's equity. </s><s n="s6.14;p11.14">He stated "... </s><s n="s7.14;p11.14">I prefer to take the simple test: What is reasonable and fair in the circumstances as they have developed, seeing that they are circumstances which no one contemplated before?" </s><s n="s8.14;p11.14">This is Denning in his element, deciding the just result, then grappling for tool to implement it: creative but mischievous. </s><s n="s9.14;p11.14">S17 affords complete discretion, ideal justification where law fails to provide adequate provisions. </s><s n="s10.14;p11.14">At this period there was radical social adjustment, women's rights markedly enlarged but law reacted lethargically, still supporting old patriarchal values: the social segregation and suppression of women. </s><s n="s11.14;p11.14">Denning was their hope, and whilst he abused his power, the greater good was worthwhile. </s><s n="s12.14;p11.14">Yet Denning moved too far, perhaps deliberately. </s><s n="s13.14;p11.14">The test was too broad and on appeal in the Lords, whilst agreeing that "the principle he sought to establish was fair in all circumstances that it had happened"<ref target="BAWE_0209a-ftnote.039"/> S17 was only procedural: the test was questioned. </s><s n="s14.14;p11.14">Yet Denning and the Appeal court continued to use it, such as in Pettitt v Pettitt<ref target="BAWE_0209a-ftnote.040"/> and later Gissing v Gissing<ref target="BAWE_0209a-ftnote.041"/> believing it "fair and just."<ref target="BAWE_0209a-ftnote.042"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0209a-ftnote.034"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Mr Tolstoy in Fribance v Fibance (1957) 1 WLR 384 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0209a-ftnote.035"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Lord Denning, The Due Process of Law </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0209a-ftnote.036"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Rimmer v Rimmer </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0209a-ftnote.037"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">S17 Married Women's Property Act 1882 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0209a-ftnote.038"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Appleton v Appleton (1965) 1 WLR 25 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0209a-ftnote.039"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">House of Lords in Appleton v Appleton </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0209a-ftnote.040"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Pettitt v Pettitt (1970) AC 777 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0209a-ftnote.041"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Gissing v Gissing (1971) AC 886 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0209a-ftnote.042"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Lord Denning, The Due Process of Law </s></p></note><p n="p12.14"><s n="s1.4;p12.14">Consequently, the Lords introduced the trust concept, Lord Diplock stating "resulting, implied or constructive trusts" could exist in Gissing on appeal. </s><s n="s2.4;p12.14">A fortnight later, Denning applied this in Falconer v Falconer,<ref target="BAWE_0209a-ftnote.043"/> where Denning himself stated his previous cases "still provide[d] good guidance." </s><ref target="BAWE_0209a-ftnote.044"/><s n="s3.4;p12.14">Denning was right. </s><s n="s4.4;p12.14">Like the deserted wife's equity the thrusts his principles intentionally, provokingly: eventually law must retaliate and find suitable legislative provisions. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0209a-ftnote.043"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Falconer v Falconer (1970) 1 WLR 1333 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0209a-ftnote.044"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Lord Denning in Falconer v Falconer (1970) 1 WLR 1333 </s></p></note><p n="p13.14"><s n="s1.9;p13.14">One inequality remained: where non-financial contributions were made. </s><s n="s2.9;p13.14">As Denning put it, why does the wife who stays at home and works for family's good not acquire a share, when the wife who goes out to work does? </s><s n="s3.9;p13.14">If Denning's broad principle had been accepted, law could easily have developed, but the Lords "slammed the door." </s><ref target="BAWE_0209a-ftnote.045"/><s n="s4.9;p13.14">If "she gives up paid work to devote herself to caring for her husband and child...she finds herself with nothing she can call her own." </s><ref target="BAWE_0209a-ftnote.046"/><s n="s5.9;p13.14">Denning remedied injustice: the 'new model' constructive trust, implemented in Falconer<ref target="BAWE_0209a-ftnote.047"/> and Hall,<ref target="BAWE_0209a-ftnote.048"/> considering non-financial contributions (e.g. home improvement). </s><s n="s6.9;p13.14">This built on Gissing,<ref target="BAWE_0209a-ftnote.049"/> women who make non-financial contributions whilst the husband pays for everything were afforded justice. </s><s n="s7.9;p13.14">It was a pragmatic reflection of life when women were still domestically based. </s><s n="s8.9;p13.14">Burns disapproved, stating "no such general power exists." </s><s n="s9.9;p13.14">It was replaced by parliamentary provision, partially embodying his principle: S37 MPPA 1970. <ref target="BAWE_0209a-ftnote.050"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0209a-ftnote.045"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Lord Denning, Due Process of Law </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0209a-ftnote.046"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Lord Morton of Henryton in The Royal Commission on Marriage and Divorce (Cmnd. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">9678) 1956 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0209a-ftnote.047"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Falconer v Falconer (1970) 3 All ER 449 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0209a-ftnote.048"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Hall v Hall (1982) 3 F.L.R. 379 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0209a-ftnote.049"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Gissing v Gissing (1970) 3 All ER 780 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0209a-ftnote.050"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Matrimonial Proceedings and Property Act 1970 </s></p></note><p n="p14.14"><s n="s1.13;p14.14">With seemingly careless disregard for precedent and legal doctrine, Denning supported the underdog. </s><s n="s2.13;p14.14">Consistently stretching law until provoking parliamentary response (e.g. deserted wife's equity), and the necessary legal reform. </s><s n="s3.13;p14.14">He was inventive (e.g. </s><s n="s4.13;p14.14">S17) and innovative, not conforming to stereotypical images of dry and conservative judges. </s><s n="s5.13;p14.14">His gifts to women, at a time when society's very structure resisted their fight for equality made him a model of morality, promoting equality and annihilating law's male paradigm. </s><s n="s6.13;p14.14">It may have been 40 years until similar provisions were made. </s><s n="s7.13;p14.14">We cannot ignore his boisterous, dangerous disregard for authority, leaving successive courts questioning the right principle to embody. </s><s n="s8.13;p14.14">Today such unconstitutional behaviour would not be tolerated, what was once named "a naked usurpation of legislative function under the thin guise of interpretation." </s><ref target="BAWE_0209a-ftnote.051"/><s n="s9.13;p14.14">But the law is no longer what it was: an obsolete, inflexible machine adhering to an aged morality. </s><s n="s10.13;p14.14">Consistently he found the natural and 'right' conclusion, perhaps the result the person in a street would state on hearing the facts. </s><s n="s11.13;p14.14">Despite tireless devotion, the Lords defeated him, but eventually they introduced measures effectively similar to his. </s><s n="s12.13;p14.14">He was no dictator; he loathed dictatorships, only abusing power out of necessity. </s><s n="s13.13;p14.14">"The silent revolution has been accomplished."<ref target="BAWE_0209a-ftnote.052"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0209a-ftnote.051"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">House of Lords on a judgement of Lord Denning's </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0209a-ftnote.052"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Lord Denning, Due Process of Law </s></p></note></div1></body><back><div1 type="bibliography"><head rend="bold">Bibliography: <hi rend="italic">Property Law Assignment</hi></head><p rend="bold">Modern Land Law, 2nd Edition by Mark P. Thompson</p><p>Oxford University Press, 2003</p><p>Pages Used: 253-305 Co-Ownership &amp; Occupation Rights</p><p rend="bold">University of <name type="university"/>, Lecture Handouts 2003-2004</p><p>Rebecca Probert, Gary Watt </p><p>Pages Used: Co-Ownership &amp; Occupation Rights</p><p rend="bold">University of <name type="university"/>, Materials 2003-2004</p><p>Rebecca Probert, Gary Watt </p><p>Pages Used: Rights of Occupation</p><p><hi rend="bold">Lexis-Nexis Professional available at:</hi> <seg type="URL" n="http://web.lexis-nexis.com/professional"/> provided by University of <name type="university"/> Law Library </p><p>Pages Used: Case Reports</p><p rend="bold">Iolis, "Innovation in Education,"</p><p>CD-ROM, Law Courseware Consortium, University of <name type="university"/>, (2003/2004), Directed by Professor Abdul Paliwala</p><p rend="bold">Due Process of Law, 1nd Edition by Rt Hon Lord Denning Master of the Rolls</p><p>Butterworths, 1980</p><p>Pages Used: 205-234 The deserted Wife's Equity</p><p> 235-251 The Trust Concept</p><p rend="bold">Denning The Closing Chapter, 1nd Edition by Rt Hon Lord Denning</p><p>Butterworths, 1983</p></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
