<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_0209b" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>To what extent have Government ambitions for the Anti-Social Behaviour Order been fulfilled, taking into account both the experience of operating this procedure nationally and also local experience</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">title in header
appendix: "Research Memorandum:" incluidng transcripts of interviews, reports of court visits, copies of web pages
</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">1</p><p n="date">2004-04</p><p n="module title">Criminal Law</p><p n="module code">LA104</p><p n="genre family">Essay</p><p n="discipline">Law</p><p n="disciplinary group">SS</p><p n="grade">D</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">1293</p><p n="number of s-units">59</p><p n="number of p">8</p><p n="number of tables">0</p><p n="number of figures">1</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">0</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">0</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">21.9</p><p n="average s-units per p">7.4</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">m</p><p n="year of birth">1985</p><p n="first language">English</p><p n="education">UKA</p><p n="course">Law LLB</p><p n="student ID">0209</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><docTitle><titlePart rend="underlined bold">To what extent have Government ambitions for the Anti-Social Behaviour Order been fulfilled, taking into account both the experience of operating this procedure nationally and also local experience</titlePart></docTitle></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="section"><p n="p1.8"><s n="s1.7;p1.8">Anti-social behaviour has increased, with 24% of people experiencing problems, especially since 1992.<ref target="BAWE_0209b-ftnote.001"/> In response, Government created ASBO's under the Crime and Disorder Act 1998. </s><s n="s2.7;p1.8">Their function and targets were revolutionary: combining criminal sanctions with civil procedures. </s><s n="s3.7;p1.8">The system was civil based aiming to achieve fast, efficient and economical hearings, whilst hearsay admissibility protected witnesses made evidence collection less problematic, as well as being reinforced with criminal sanctions. </s><s n="s4.7;p1.8">However, theoretical criticism has been huge: concerning human rights (e.g. </s><s n="s5.7;p1.8">ASBO's avoid Article 6 ECHR as it is not a criminal procedure), opportunities for the defendant to defend themselves (e.g. question hearsay evidence) and the very concept of blurring criminal and civil boundaries. </s><s n="s6.7;p1.8">In practice, many procedural problems have been found. </s><s n="s7.7;p1.8">I will consider ASBO implementation specifically through Babergh District Council (BDC) Housing Department<ref target="BAWE_0209b-ftnote.002"/> and nationally, evaluating if Government aims are met. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0209b-ftnote.001"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Figures from Office for National Statistics British Crime Survey 2000 (website - see appendix) </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0209b-ftnote.002"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Babergh District Council are based at Corks Lane, Hadleigh, Suffolk and their housing team manages several thousand properties in the Babergh area </s></p></note><p n="p2.8"><s n="s1.6;p2.8">Government publications outline that ASBO's should "protect the public from behaviour that causes or is likely to cause harassment, alarm or distress,"<ref target="BAWE_0209b-ftnote.003"/> protecting "against anti-social behaviour," e.g. "loutish and unruly conduct...verbal abuse, harassment, assault, graffiti, and excessive noise." </s><ref target="BAWE_0209b-ftnote.004"/><s n="s2.6;p2.8">They aim to remove problems at grass roots level, "encouraging communities to become actively involved in reporting crime,"<ref target="BAWE_0209b-ftnote.005"/> inviting them into the justice system so they feel served. </s><s n="s3.6;p2.8">Their purpose is to empower local authorities and police to bring prosecutions and tackle the issues directly, creating a rapid and time-saving remedy, avoiding delay through the civil system, being economically efficient, and "accessible" by being issued by civil courts or "if the defendant is convicted of an offence in the criminal courts." </s><s n="s4.6;p2.8">Government wanted witnesses protected from intimidation, and civil administration allows hearsay to be admissible, permitting professional witnesses to be used: protecting witness and encouraging evidence to be more forthcoming. </s><s n="s5.6;p2.8">ASBO's should be bespoke to a situations needs, applying to anyone older than ten, directly targeting youth problems and neighbour disputes. </s><s n="s6.6;p2.8">Co-operation and communication between local authorities, police, courts and the communities was fundamental, with a structured system using county protocols and regional officers, but has this been realised? </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0209b-ftnote.003"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">A guide to Anti-social Behaviour Orders and Good Behaviour Contract, Home Office (March 2003) </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0209b-ftnote.004"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">A guide to Anti-social Behaviour Orders and Good Behaviour Contract, Home Office (March 2003) </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0209b-ftnote.005"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Respect and Responsibility - Taking a stand against antisocial behaviour, Home Office, (2003) </s></p></note><p n="p3.8"><s n="s1.14;p3.8">BDC's experiences illustrate a disturbing picture of disorganisation. </s><s n="s2.14;p3.8">Initially very little information was received on application procedures, evidence collection and processes to bring ASBO's to court. </s><s n="s3.14;p3.8">Government materials raised initial awareness, but thereafter it has been through their own initiative that implementation of ASBO's has occurred. </s><s n="s4.14;p3.8">BDC uses ASBO's to control council tenants breaking the tenancy agreement, as an intermediate sanction before applying for a possession order (evicting the tenant), or using an intermediate ASBO to provide protection between a possession order being granted and eviction. </s><s n="s5.14;p3.8">Helen Shackleton<ref target="BAWE_0209b-ftnote.006"/> explains that three applications have been made with two successes. </s><s n="s6.14;p3.8">She suggests the process fails government's aims of being an efficient and swift remedy, being "tiresome," and requiring 18 months of preparation. </s><s n="s7.14;p3.8">It was also "confusing" and "uncertain," not because of unfamiliarity, but poor communication with the courts and inadequate Government instruction. </s><s n="s8.14;p3.8">Colleague, Tony Morris<ref target="BAWE_0209b-ftnote.007"/> estimated the process normally takes 5-6 months, adding 4-6 weeks for defendants using representation, illustrating that ASBO's are not the fast solution government suggests. </s><s n="s9.14;p3.8">The cost (£5000-£8000) was large and disproportionate, making it unfavourable and not the economically practical proposition government claims. </s><s n="s10.14;p3.8">Morris suggests the application procedure is not widely documented and authorities (including police) are uncertain, relying on costly legal advice. </s><s n="s11.14;p3.8">He made criticism after receiving initial information, the department were left to their own initiative to investigate, and were still "unfamiliar" with the requirements, particularly concerning as they are expected to function like to the CPS, bringing applications to court. </s><s n="s12.14;p3.8">Government's information for internal use is, according to Caroline Davis<ref target="BAWE_0209b-ftnote.008"/> contrary to Government guidelines, creating a judicially reviewable situation and explaining current perplexity. </s><s n="s13.14;p3.8">The findings could explain the erratic inconsistencies of application and success statistics between counties and boroughs that has emerged (Fig.1), and poor initial response e.g. by December 2002 only 177 ASBO's were made. </s><s n="s14.14;p3.8">Government aims on speed, ease of application, and costs have failed. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0209b-ftnote.006"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Tennant Services Manager at Babergh District Council (see Appendix for transcript) </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0209b-ftnote.007"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Principal Housing Officer at Babergh District Council (see Appendix for transcript) </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0209b-ftnote.008"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Solicitor at Babergh District Council (see Appendix for transcript) </s></p></note><figure id="BAWE_0209b-fig.001"/><p n="p4.8"><s n="s1.7;p4.8">Poor awareness is largely a reflection of the system. </s><s n="s2.7;p4.8">Davis, who has considerable experience with ASBO's commented on the failures of the system. </s><s n="s3.7;p4.8">BDC's experience indicates the police have been unwilling to co-operate, providing only one incident statement in relation to many incidents. </s><s n="s4.7;p4.8">She found no police-council partnership (an aim), with the police unwilling and "uninterested" in ASBO's, regarding it as a "civil matter." </s><s n="s5.7;p4.8">The government's aims for authority co-operation have failed. </s><s n="s6.7;p4.8">Furthermore, the regional protocol for anti-social behaviour has not been created, and area does not have an appointed Anti-Social Behaviour coordinator, something she blames on "poor education and initiation by government," illustrating that none of the proposed support systems have been created. </s><s n="s7.7;p4.8">She also acknowledged ASBO's were sluggish and expensive. </s></p><p n="p5.8"><s n="s1.6;p5.8">More disturbing was BDC's experiences in court. </s><s n="s2.6;p5.8">During the first application the Clerk was unaware of the procedure to create an ASBO and the ASBO system, and produced a "technicality," which when later challenged was false. </s><s n="s3.6;p5.8">The courts appear like the police: unacquainted, and alarmingly reluctant to use ASBO's. </s><s n="s4.6;p5.8">The Magistrates stated they were "nothing but a sideshow," unwilling to grant what was later considered a valid application. </s><s n="s5.6;p5.8">Davis suggests this relatively commonplace, with judiciary despondent with the civil-criminal implications, and suggests more "internal regulation and education." </s><s n="s6.6;p5.8">Davis and Morris also comment that with CASBO applications there has been no CPS co-operation, rendering the criminally based ASBO very difficult to obtain. </s></p><p n="p6.8"><s n="s1.5;p6.8">BDC's second application was successful, issued<ref target="BAWE_0209b-ftnote.009"/> against a noisy, aggressive and intimidating tenant. </s><s n="s2.5;p6.8">The advantages of hearsay admissibility were clear: previously tenants illustrated reluctance to provide evidence owing to the defendant's violent history, but here more evidence was forthcoming, illustrating the government success. </s><s n="s3.5;p6.8">Yet, Shackleton stated that despite ASBO enforcement residents felt they were "alone and open to abuse," and unprotected after providing evidence, indicating the protection the government had hoped is not completely realised. </s><s n="s4.5;p6.8">Shackleton also stressed how "pressurising," "difficult" and "unpleasant" providing professional evidence was, this presenting an unconsidered issue. </s><s n="s5.5;p6.8">Should largely inexperienced local authority workers be subject to the rigors of court work? </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0209b-ftnote.009"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">A copy of this is available in the Appendix under the Secondary Evidence Section </s></p></note><p n="p7.8"><s n="s1.8;p7.8">Shackleton considers that once enforced ASBO's are a useful tool: all defendants behaved with "no problems," believing the success is in having "very real criminal sanctions." </s><s n="s2.8;p7.8">Initial national success was poor, but Manchester Council is at the forefront, obtaining 160. </s><s n="s3.8;p7.8">Basil Curley<ref target="BAWE_0209b-ftnote.010"/> states "...evidence shows that work to curtail harmful behaviour is working," with only 30% breaching, they are acting well as deterrents. </s><s n="s4.8;p7.8">In the region residents have noticed a "real improvement." </s><s n="s5.8;p7.8">Curley welcomes the ASB Act 2003, where procedural reform, particularly to interim orders "is a huge step forward," hinting experience of problems akin to BDC. The successes are becoming more commonplace, example 1 (appendix) reveals how 70 youths "terrorised" a community but following an ASBO incidents reduced from 24 to 5 per month. </s><s n="s6.8;p7.8">Example 2 illustrates improvement in a community enduring prostitution related offences and 62% of authorities reported an improvement<ref target="BAWE_0209b-ftnote.011"/>. </s><s n="s7.8;p7.8">Manchester also held 300 warning meetings, reporting deterrence effects. </s><s n="s8.8;p7.8">ASBO's have encouraged community participation, particularly as BDC has an Anti-social behaviour surgery, this aim of government is clearly successful and frequently leads to "early resolution without need for ASBO's."<ref target="BAWE_0209b-ftnote.012"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0209b-ftnote.010"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Housing Manager at Manchester City Council Housing Department speaking in a BBC interview </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0209b-ftnote.011"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Statistic from Home Office Website, see bibliography </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0209b-ftnote.012"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Tony Morris, Principal Housing Officer at Babergh District Council </s></p></note><p n="p8.8"><s n="s1.6;p8.8">The very concept of ASBO's, once enforced works with tangible benefits, particularly considering Manchester's low breach rate of 30%, illustrating a deterrent effect, as intended. </s><s n="s2.6;p8.8">However, whilst the mechanism itself appears to work, it is the procedure which has failed to meet government criteria. </s><s n="s3.6;p8.8">It is slow, inefficient and unregulated. </s><s n="s4.6;p8.8">Information and communication is not uniform, confusion and contradiction rife, with magistrates and clerks unaware of procedures, and lacking faith in the system. </s><s n="s5.6;p8.8">The government needs to be work with the authorities to encourage partnerships. </s><s n="s6.6;p8.8">ASBO's will be successful, but government needs to support the system. </s></p></div1></body><back><div1 type="bibliography"><head rend="bold">Bibliography:</head><div2 type="bibliography"><head>Book Research:</head><p rend="bold">Housing Law and Policy, Macmillan Law Masters, 1st Edition, (1999) written by David Cowan (Series Editor Marise Cremona)</p><p>Pages used:</p><p>498-503 Issues of Anti-social Behaviour</p><p>509-510 ASBO's</p><p rend="bold">Principles of Criminal Law, Oxford University Press, 4th Edition, (2003), written by Andrew Ashworth</p><p>Pages Used:</p><p>57 - ASBO's</p><p rend="bold">A guide to Anti-social Behaviour Orders and Good Behaviour Contracts, published by the Home Office (March 2003)</p><p rend="bold">Respect and Responsibility - Taking a stand against antisocial behaviour, Published by the Home Office, (2003)</p></div2><div2 type="bibliography"><head>Internet Based Research:</head><p><hi rend="bold">Home Office Website at: </hi><seg type="URL" n="www.homeoffice.gov.uk"/></p><p>Materials Used:</p><p>Home Office Statistics on ASBO Applications at: <seg type="URL" n="http://www.crimereduction.gov.uk/asbos2.htm"/></p><p><hi rend="bold">Crime Reduction.gov.uk at: </hi><seg type="URL" n="http://www.crimereduction.gov.uk/asbos7.htm"/></p><p>Materials Used:</p><p>Case Examples of the Successes when ASBO's are in operations</p><p><hi rend="bold">British Crime Survey 2000 Website at: </hi><seg type="URL" n="http://www.homeoffice.gov.uk/rds/bcs1.html"/></p><p>Materials Used:</p><p>Statistics on Anti-social Behaviour and the British Crime Survey 2000 (follow link on site to open file).</p><p><hi rend="bold">BBC News Website, </hi><seg type="URL" n="www.bbc.co.uk"/></p><p>Materials Used: Articles: "Manchester Tackles Anti-Social Behaviour - BBC News" </p><p> "City council welcomes new ASBO Bill - and says ASBO's do work - BBC News"</p><p>These pages are now unavailable, presumably removed however a copy of the articles can be seen in Appendix 2, following the bibliography.</p></div2><div2 type="bibliography"><head>Other Materials:</head><p>Lecture Notes</p></div2></div1><div1 type="appendix"><head rend="bold">Appendix:</head><p/></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
