<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_0210e" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>CFD Laboratory Report</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">The document has a title page which contains:
document title
title part</note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">deleted: header: student number; footer: page numbers</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">1</p><p n="date">2006-03</p><p n="module title">Design for Function</p><p n="module code">ES174</p><p n="genre family">Methodology recount</p><p n="discipline">Engineering</p><p n="disciplinary group">PS</p><p n="grade">M</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">742</p><p n="number of s-units">40</p><p n="number of p">24</p><p n="number of tables">3</p><p n="number of figures">3</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">12</p><p n="number of lists">3</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">0</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">18.6</p><p n="average s-units per p">1.7</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">m</p><p n="year of birth">1986</p><p n="first language">Sinhala</p><p n="education">OSA</p><p n="course">Systems Engineering</p><p n="student ID">0210</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><titlePart><hi rend="underlined bold">The University of <name type="university"/></hi><hi rend="bold"> School Of Engineering</hi></titlePart><docTitle><titlePart rend="bold">CFD Laboratory Report</titlePart></docTitle><titlePart rend="bold">By<name type="student ID"/></titlePart><titlePart>Report reference code: (ES174A4C) Affiliation: (Year 1 Engineering) Report of laboratory performed on: 30/01/2006, (6, 13)/02/2006</titlePart><docTitle><titlePart rend="bold">CFD Laboratory Report</titlePart></docTitle></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Introduction</head><p n="p1.24"><s n="s1.3;p1.24">The basic objective of the laboratory sessions was to use Solidworks and Cosmos Floworks to design a car in a wind tunnel and to analyse the properties such as the drag coefficient and drag force. </s><s n="s2.3;p1.24">The idea behind these laboratory sessions was to gain knowledge about basic concepts of fluid dynamics and car aerodynamics. </s><s n="s3.3;p1.24">This laboratory assisted in gaining a basic idea about analysis and optimisation. </s></p><p n="p2.24"><s n="s1.2;p2.24">A car was fitted in to a wind tunnel and all the external specifications were provided. </s><s n="s2.2;p2.24">Then the car was analysed for different properties by varying the external entities. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Method used</head><p n="p3.24"><s n="s1.4;p3.24">A car and a wind tunnel is designed using Solidworks. </s><s n="s2.4;p3.24">Then he original car was mated in to a closed wind tunnel using Solidworks and then Cosmos Floworks was added in. </s><s n="s3.4;p3.24">Using a wizard available in Cosmos Floworks the external entities such as temperature and pressure were defined. </s><s n="s4.4;p3.24">Then the surfaces of the car were mentioned on which the air acts. </s></p><p n="p4.24"><s n="s1.1;p4.24">Solver was then used to calculate the X - component of force by carrying out several iterations. </s></p><p n="p5.24"><s n="s1.1;p5.24">The original car used for the initial calculations is shown below; </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0210e-pic.001"/><p n="p6.24"><s n="s1.1;p6.24">The Modified car used for the initial calculations is shown below; </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0210e-pic.002"/><p n="p7.24"><s n="s1.1;p7.24">Following data was specified before carrying out the iteration calculations; </s></p><list type="simple"><item>Heat transfer in solids: Off</item><item>Time dependent: Off</item><item>Gravitational effects: Off</item><item>Flow type: Laminar and Turbulent</item><item>High Mach number flow: Off</item><item>Default roughness: 0 micrometer</item><item>Default wall conditions: Adiabatic wall</item></list><table id="BAWE_0210e-tab.001"><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p8.24"><s n="s1.1;p8.24">The iteration calculations are carried out for six different velocities of air (10, 20, 30, 40, 50, 60 m/s) </s></p><div2><head rend="bold">Theory Used: -</head><p n="p9.24"><s n="s1.1;p9.24">The general data used for derivation and calculation of drag coefficients; </s></p><list type="simple"><item>Temperature at sea - level (<formula notation="" id="BAWE_0210e-form.001"/>)</item><item>Speed of sound: <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0210e-form.002"/></item><item>Dynamic viscosity: <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0210e-form.003"/></item><item>Density: <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0210e-form.004"/></item><item>Area of the original car <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0210e-form.005"/></item></list><p n="p10.24"><s n="s1.1;p10.24">Area of the modified car <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0210e-form.006"/> </s></p><list type="simple"><head>Equations used for the calculation of drag coefficient and drag force;</head><item>Drag force: <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0210e-form.007"/></item><item>Drag coefficient: <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0210e-form.008"/></item></list><p n="p11.24"><s n="s1.1;p11.24">(Where; <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0210e-form.009"/> = density, <hi rend="italic">V</hi> = velocity, <hi rend="italic">A=</hi>area of the car) </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Analysis and Interpretation of results</head><p n="p12.24"><s n="s1.2;p12.24">The drag forces for six values of velocity are found and using the equation shown in the "Theory used" the respective Drag coefficient is found. </s><s n="s2.2;p12.24">Then one graph is plotted for each car, with Drag coefficient against velocity. </s></p><p n="p13.24"><s n="s1.1;p13.24">Calculating the Drag coefficient; </s></p><p n="p14.24"><s n="s1.1;p14.24"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0210e-form.010"/> </s></p><p n="p15.24"><s n="s1.1;p15.24"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0210e-form.011"/> </s></p><p n="p16.24"><s n="s1.1;p16.24"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0210e-form.012"/> </s></p><p n="p17.24"><s n="s1.1;p17.24">(Above is an example calculation of a drag coefficient) </s></p><div2><head rend="bold">The results and calculations for the Original car:</head><p n="p18.24"><s n="s1.1;p18.24">The drag coefficient for each velocity is calculated and tabulated below; </s></p><table id="BAWE_0210e-tab.002"><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p19.24"><s n="s1.4;p19.24">The graph shown below is of Drag coefficient against velocity. </s><s n="s2.4;p19.24">Even though the points seem to be scattered around the plot area when the y - axis is considered all the Drag coefficients for different velocities seem to be very close to each other. </s><s n="s3.4;p19.24">All the Drag coefficients seem to lie between 0.36 and 0.41. </s><s n="s4.4;p19.24">There is a general trend line added to the graph and it is considerably horizontal and straight showing that there is no change in Drag coefficient even though the velocity of the air is changed. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0210e-fig.001"><head>Original Car</head></figure></div2><div2><head rend="bold">The results and calculations for the Modified car:</head><p n="p20.24"><s n="s1.1;p20.24">The drag coefficient for each velocity is calculated and tabulated below; </s></p><table id="BAWE_0210e-tab.003"><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p21.24"><s n="s1.5;p21.24">The graph shown below is of Drag coefficient against velocity. </s><s n="s2.5;p21.24">Even though the points seem to be scattered around the plot area when the y - axis is considered all the Drag coefficients for different velocities seem to be close to very each other. </s><s n="s3.5;p21.24">All the Drag coefficients seem to lie between 0.3 and 0.36. </s><s n="s4.5;p21.24">There is a general trend line added to the graph and it is close to being horizontal even though it is slightly slanted showing that there is only a very slight change in Drag coefficient even though the velocity of the air is changed. </s><s n="s5.5;p21.24">This slight change of coefficients could be due to the different number of iterations carried out. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0210e-fig.002"><head>Modified Car</head></figure></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Conclusion</head><p n="p22.24"><s n="s1.3;p22.24">According to the results from the two cars it could be stated that Drag coefficient is independent of the velocity of air. </s><s n="s2.3;p22.24">Since the Drag forces and drag coefficients found in the Modified car was less than the values found in the original car, it could be derived that the modified car is more aerodynamic. </s><s n="s3.3;p22.24">The modified car has less Drag forces with the different velocities and the difference between the Drag coefficients of the two cars is roughly about '0.05'. </s></p><p n="p23.24"><s n="s1.1;p23.24">Below are some additional ways of interpreting properties such as pressure; </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0210e-pic.003"/><p n="p24.24"><s n="s1.1;p24.24">Using the software used for this laboratory various other entities such as static pressure dynamic and pressure could be measured and interpreted. </s></p></div1></body><back><div1 type="bibliography"><head rend="bold">References</head><p>Additional theory and information was obtained from the web sites listed below;</p><p><seg type="URL" n="http://www.aerodyn.org/Drag/tables.html"/></p><p><seg type="URL" n="http://www.grc.nasa.gov/WWW/K-12/airplane/drageq.html"/></p><p><seg type="URL" n="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Drag_coefficient"/></p></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
