<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_0212d" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Assignment 1</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">The document has a title page which contains:
document title
title part</note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">deleted: page numbers</note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">Evaluated as candidate compound assignment. Assigned to S3: assignment structured by questions: non-compound</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">1</p><p n="date">2005-12</p><p n="module title">Computing &amp; Information Systems</p><p n="module code">IB1070</p><p n="genre family">Exercise</p><p n="discipline">Business</p><p n="disciplinary group">SS</p><p n="grade">M</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">2057</p><p n="number of s-units">117</p><p n="number of p">57</p><p n="number of tables">7</p><p n="number of figures">8</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">13</p><p n="number of lists">2</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">0</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">17.6</p><p n="average s-units per p">2.1</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">complex but non-compound assignment (see notesStmt for details)</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">m</p><p n="year of birth">1986</p><p n="first language">English</p><p n="education">UKA</p><p n="course">Business</p><p n="student ID">0212</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><docTitle><titlePart>Statistics for BUSINESS assignment 1 </titlePart></docTitle><titlePart><name type="student ID"/></titlePart></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">A) "COMPUTE THE EXPECTED NUMBER OF DOCTOR VISITS IN FIVE YEARS" </head><p n="p1.57"><s n="s1.2;p1.57">Within the last five years there were a total of 1996 visits to the doctor. </s><s n="s2.2;p1.57">The average value is 1996/100=19.96 visits per person per five years </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold"> B) "COMMENT ON THE FOLLOWING SENTENCE: 'WOMEN TEND TO VISIT THE DOCTOR MORE OFTEN THAN MEN DO'"</head><table id="BAWE_0212d-tab.001"><head>Table 1</head><row><cell/></row></table><table id="BAWE_0212d-tab.002"><head>Table 2</head><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p2.57"><s n="s1.5;p2.57">Looking at the sum (Table 1, Table 2) for each of the sexes shows an obvious result. </s><s n="s2.5;p2.57">It is clear that women outnumber visits to the doctor compared to men at a ratio of almost 5:2. </s><s n="s3.5;p2.57">However, this isn't enough to justify the claim that women visit the doctor more often than men. </s><s n="s4.5;p2.57">For example, a handful of women could have visited a number of times thereby increasing the sum. </s><s n="s5.5;p2.57">There are also more women than men in the sample of 100 meaning the use of the sum isn't justifiable. </s></p><p n="p3.57"><s n="s1.5;p3.57">The mean of visits to the doctor is larger in women. </s><s n="s2.5;p3.57">This is also true with the median. </s><s n="s3.5;p3.57">After calculating (and omitting) any outliers i.e. data outside of two standard deviation the means were 9.894 for men and 22.27 for women. </s><s n="s4.5;p3.57">There is still a large difference between the two groups of data. </s><s n="s5.5;p3.57">This data supports the claim that more women visit the doctors than men. </s></p><p n="p4.57"><s n="s1.3;p4.57">My theory is that it is possible that women do go to the doctors more often than men. </s><s n="s2.3;p4.57">However, it is a far better idea to decide why this is. </s><s n="s3.3;p4.57">I plan to investigate what affect the age of a woman or man has on the frequency of visits as it is a key factor in why people visit the doctor. </s></p><p n="p5.57"><s n="s1.4;p5.57">The mean age of each sex shows they're almost exactly the same. </s><s n="s2.4;p5.57">The men and women in the sample are approximately the same age. </s><s n="s3.4;p5.57">The measure of spread (the standard deviation in this case) shows that their dispersion is also almost equal with a difference of only 0.75 Years. </s><s n="s4.4;p5.57">The median value of 42.5 is common between each sex. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0212d-fig.001"><head>Figure 1</head></figure><figure id="BAWE_0212d-fig.002"><head>Figure 2</head></figure><p n="p6.57"><s n="s1.1;p6.57">To compare the relationship between age and frequency of visits I have produced a scatter graph for each sex </s></p><p n="p7.57"><s n="s1.3;p7.57">Regarding Figure 1 and Figure 2, although there appears to be a relationship for the male data this cannot be said for the female data. </s><s n="s2.3;p7.57">Because of this I feel it isn't justifiable to link the two data together in a relationship. </s><s n="s3.3;p7.57">Due to this I will simply focus on the frequency of visits for each sex. </s></p><p n="p8.57"><s n="s1.3;p8.57">The health of an individual of course will determine how much they visit the doctor. </s><s n="s2.3;p8.57">I believe that the only reason why an individual would visit the doctor is if they had bad health. </s><s n="s3.3;p8.57">In the data set 5/42 (or approximately 11.90%) of men were classed as having bad health compared to the female equivalent of 14/58 (or 24.13%) which is approximately double that of the male value. </s></p><p n="p9.57"><s n="s1.2;p9.57">Finally, after putting the data into a histogram it's clear that both sets of data are right skewed i.e. </s><s n="s2.2;p9.57">Mean>Media>Mode. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0212d-fig.003"><head>Figure 3</head></figure><figure id="BAWE_0212d-fig.004"><head>Figure 4</head></figure><p n="p10.57"><s n="s1.1;p10.57">By using a population of 40 million per sex (this is approximately the population of Germany, the source of data) I calculated the distributions using Poisson </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0212d-fig.005"><head rend="italic">Figure Pop 1</head></figure><figure id="BAWE_0212d-fig.006"><head rend="italic">Figure Pop 2</head></figure><p n="p11.57"><s n="s1.3;p11.57">Both populations appear to follow a normal distribution. </s><s n="s2.3;p11.57">The female data is perhaps more bell shaped and follows the standard normal distribution. </s><s n="s3.3;p11.57">However, the male data has remained skewed </s></p><div2><head rend="underlined bold">Results</head><p n="p12.57"><s n="s1.3;p12.57">The standard deviation of the female frequency, 17.93 (Table 2) is greater than the male value of 13.34 (Table 1). </s><s n="s2.3;p12.57">The range of the female data, 66 (Table 2) is again larger than the male value of 58 (Table 1). </s><s n="s3.3;p12.57">This clearly indicates that the frequencies are more spread in the women data. </s></p><p n="p13.57"><s n="s1.3;p13.57">Figure 4 further strengthens the argument that the frequency of visits of women is indeed more widely spread. </s><s n="s2.3;p13.57">Figure 3 shows that the number of visits to the doctor by the men in the sample is more concentrated. </s><s n="s3.3;p13.57">Figure 3 crucially shows that the number of visits is more highly concentrated around a lower value compared to that of the women. </s></p><p n="p14.57"><s n="s1.1;p14.57">The coefficient of variation is a measure of variability around the mean frequencies. </s></p><p n="p15.57"><s n="s1.1;p15.57">The coefficients of variation for each sex are... </s></p><list type="simple"><head rend="bold">Male</head><item>Coefficient = <hi rend="italic">Standard Deviation/Mean</hi></item><item>Coefficient = <hi rend="italic">13.34/13.59</hi></item><item>Coefficient = <hi rend="italic">0.981625</hi></item></list><list type="simple"><head rend="bold">Female</head><item>Coefficient = <hi rend="italic">Standard Deviation/Mean</hi></item><item>Coefficient = <hi rend="italic">17.93/24.56897</hi></item><item>Coefficient = <hi rend="italic">0.729854</hi></item></list><p n="p16.57"><s n="s1.1;p16.57">The lower value (0.72) of the women data indicates yet again that the women data is more spread and the male value of 0.98 indicates the opposite for the male data. </s></p><p n="p17.57"><s n="s1.3;p17.57">A final measure of the spread of each sex is the kurtosis (the measure of flatness of a sample). </s><s n="s2.3;p17.57">The female negative value of -0.24467 again re-enforces the fact that the female data is flatter and the tails, longer. </s><s n="s3.3;p17.57">Conversely the male value of 3.61 indicates a highly peaked set of data. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined bold">Conclusions</head><p n="p18.57"><s n="s1.2;p18.57">Firstly it should be noted that the number of candidates within each sex was not even. </s><s n="s2.2;p18.57">Nevertheless there does appear to be solution to whether women visit the doctors more often than men. </s></p><p n="p19.57"><s n="s1.3;p19.57">I feel that the most useful average was the mean. </s><s n="s2.3;p19.57">Although it can be affected by extreme values it also takes into account the number of candidates within the sample for each sex. </s><s n="s3.3;p19.57">Even after omitting any outliers within the samples I feel that the values for the means had a large difference between them. </s></p><p n="p20.57"><s n="s1.3;p20.57">The use of the measure of spreads indicated that women did indeed have a larger spread of data. </s><s n="s2.3;p20.57">Even after omitting the candidates' values who were outliers the standard deviations were still larger in female data (15.34 visits) compared to the male value of 6.75 visits. </s><s n="s3.3;p20.57">The kurtosis of the datasets supported these results. </s></p><p n="p21.57"><s n="s1.2;p21.57">Finally, the fact that almost double the amount of women are classed as having bad health compared to the male values indicates an obvious difference in health states between the sexes. </s><s n="s2.2;p21.57">Combining this data with the idea that sick people go to the doctors strengthens the argument of more women tending to go to the doctor more often than men. </s></p><p n="p22.57"><s n="s1.1;p22.57">I feel the comment of "Women tend to visit the doctor more often than men do" is correct </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">C) "COMMENT ON THE NUMBER OF VISITS TO THE DOCTOR BY INDIVIDUALS RECEIVING WELFARE PAYMENTS"</head><div2><head rend="underlined bold">Graph Information</head><p n="p23.57"><s n="s1.2;p23.57">To the left I have drawn up a histogram showing exactly how many times the people on welfare went to the doctor in five years. </s><s n="s2.2;p23.57">I chose the first 20 people who were not on welfare for the comparison </s></p><p n="p24.57"><s n="s1.2;p24.57">Both of the graphs appear to follow the normal distribution but the non welfare graph more so. </s><s n="s2.2;p24.57">The non welfare group is right skewed and initially, looks to have some outliers. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0212d-fig.007"><head rend="italic">Figure 5</head></figure><figure id="BAWE_0212d-fig.008"><head rend="italic">Figure 6</head></figure><table id="BAWE_0212d-tab.003"><head rend="bold italic">No Welfare Group Table 3</head><row><cell/></row></table><table id="BAWE_0212d-tab.004"><head rend="bold italic">Welfare Group Table 4</head><row><cell/></row></table></div2><div2><head rend="underlined bold">Concerning Outliers</head><p n="p25.57"><s n="s1.2;p25.57">To try and reduce the impact of extreme values on the calculation of the mean I have also calculated if any outliers were present and I recalculated the means. </s><s n="s2.2;p25.57">However, as I only identified one outlier (PIN=8) the mean of the non welfare candidates only changed slightly from 13.75 to 12. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined bold">Results</head><p n="p26.57"><s n="s1.1;p26.57">From the data I calculated that out of the welfare group candidates, 80% were women and 20% were men. </s></p><p n="p27.57"><s n="s1.2;p27.57">The figures in the tables agree with what is displayed on the graphs. </s><s n="s2.2;p27.57">The mean number of visits to the doctor if a person is not on welfare is a low 13.75 times compared to a welfare person 41.4. </s></p><p n="p28.57"><s n="s1.4;p28.57">Initially, the difference between the two groups seems worrying. </s><s n="s2.4;p28.57">This is further compounded by the median and mode values of both sets of data. </s><s n="s3.4;p28.57">The standard deviation of each group differs by only approximately 3 visits. </s><s n="s4.4;p28.57">As this standard deviation is so low the values of each group are unlikely to cross leading to a more concrete separation of each group. </s></p><p n="p29.57"><s n="s1.1;p29.57">This separation between the apparently unhealthy welfare group and the healthy non welfare group, I believe, has some clear answers </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined bold">Conclusions</head><p n="p30.57"><s n="s1.3;p30.57">The average amount of schooling for the welfare group is only 10.925 compared to 12.375 of the non welfare group. </s><s n="s2.3;p30.57">Although a rather presumptuous analysis it can be reasonable concluded that those who have had a longer education are smarter. </s><s n="s3.3;p30.57">This intelligence can be argued to include the ability to look after one's self and therefore reduce the frequency of visits to the doctor. </s></p><p n="p31.57"><s n="s1.2;p31.57">A healthy lifestyle includes physical exercise of which non welfare people get more of (9 compared to 8) Despite supporting the theory this data isn't enough alone. </s><s n="s2.2;p31.57">I don't believe the difference between the two values is enough evidence to support such a claim. </s></p><p n="p32.57"><s n="s1.2;p32.57">Non welfare people also claim to be in good health more often (13 people) than non welfare candidates (9). </s><s n="s2.2;p32.57">This supports the ideas about a healthy lifestyle stated above. </s></p><p n="p33.57"><s n="s1.9;p33.57">A possible reason as to the difference in groups is the fact that 9.523% of all the men in the sample (i.e. </s><s n="s2.9;p33.57">4/42) received benefits. </s><s n="s3.9;p33.57">Contrast this to the 27.586% of women (i.e. </s><s n="s4.9;p33.57">16/58) who are on welfare. </s><s n="s5.9;p33.57">Previously I stated that women tend to go to the doctor more often than men do. </s><s n="s6.9;p33.57">This could be due to the fact that more women are on welfare. </s><s n="s7.9;p33.57">Women are increasingly becoming working mothers and so the number of women on welfare will also increase. </s><s n="s8.9;p33.57">During this section I have detailed that people on welfare also tend to visit the doctor more often than those that do not. </s><s n="s9.9;p33.57">These two statements support one another. </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">D) "WHAT IS THE PROBABILITY OF A SINGLE MALE PERSON NEVER VISITING A DOCTOR IN FIVE YEARS?"</head><p n="p34.57"><s n="s1.1;p34.57"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0212d-form.001"/> </s></p><p n="p35.57"><s n="s1.1;p35.57"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0212d-form.002"/> </s></p><p n="p36.57"><s n="s1.1;p36.57"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0212d-form.003"/> </s></p><p n="p37.57"><s n="s1.1;p37.57"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0212d-form.004"/> </s></p><p n="p38.57"><s n="s1.1;p38.57"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0212d-form.005"/> </s></p><p n="p39.57"><s n="s1.1;p39.57"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0212d-form.006"/> </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">EI) "CALCULATE THE PROBABILITY THAT AT LEAST 20 ARE UNHEALTHY"</head><p n="p40.57"><s n="s1.1;p40.57"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0212d-form.007"/> </s></p><p n="p41.57"><s n="s1.1;p41.57"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0212d-form.008"/> </s></p><p n="p42.57"><s n="s1.1;p42.57"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0212d-form.009"/> </s></p><p n="p43.57"><s n="s1.1;p43.57"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0212d-form.010"/> </s></p><p n="p44.57"><s n="s1.1;p44.57"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0212d-form.011"/> </s></p><p n="p45.57"><s n="s1.1;p45.57"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0212d-form.012"/> </s></p><p n="p46.57"><s n="s1.1;p46.57"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0212d-form.013"/> </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">EII) "COMMENT ON THE NUMBER OF SINGLE PEOPLE IN YOUR SAMPLE"</head><p n="p47.57"><s n="s1.1;p47.57">Using my existing data I can comment on what I would expect with the new sample from the same population. </s></p><table id="BAWE_0212d-tab.005"><head rend="italic">Table 5</head><row><cell/></row></table><table id="BAWE_0212d-tab.006"><head>Table 6</head><row><cell/></row></table><table id="BAWE_0212d-tab.007"><head>Table 7</head><row><cell/></row></table><div2><head rend="underlined bold">Concerning Outliers</head><p n="p48.57"><s n="s1.3;p48.57">With the data I calculated which items were outliers and recalculated the averages. </s><s n="s2.3;p48.57">In the case of the females I removed any data above the outlier but also one item (64) when the outlier limit was 64.33. </s><s n="s3.3;p48.57">I felt this was too close to the outlier limit to ignore. </s></p><p n="p49.57"><s n="s1.1;p49.57">Similarly with the single men data with the limit of 67.9 I removed an item of 67 </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined bold">Results</head><p n="p50.57"><s n="s1.1;p50.57">The mean age of single people of both sexes is in the age group of approximately 30-35. </s></p><p n="p51.57"><s n="s1.2;p51.57">The values in Table 5 seem to support conclusions from previous exercises. </s><s n="s2.2;p51.57">Again it seems that women do tend to visit the doctor more often and are far more often in a bad state of health. </s></p><p n="p52.57"><s n="s1.1;p52.57">Single women tend to be involved in sport more then single men with 56.52% compared to the male equivalent of 35.29%. </s></p><p n="p53.57"><s n="s1.1;p53.57">The mean logarithm of monthly gross income of single people is 7.51 compared to 7.685 of people who are not single </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined bold">Conclusions</head><p n="p54.57"><s n="s1.2;p54.57">The reason for more women being involved in sport could perhaps be because the women have more of an impotence to join a local gym after a relationship in an effort, for example, to lose weight and feel better about ones self. </s><s n="s2.2;p54.57">However, with such a small difference between the values of the two sexes this is unlikely </s></p><p n="p55.57"><s n="s1.3;p55.57">The reason for people being single could be attributed to the fact that they may be focused more on their jobs. </s><s n="s2.3;p55.57">Because of this their mean logarithm of monthly gross income would be higher than that of people who aren't single. </s><s n="s3.3;p55.57">However, this isn't the case. </s></p><p n="p56.57"><s n="s1.1;p56.57">Regarding the actual number of single people in the new sample... </s></p><p n="p57.57"><s n="s1.3;p57.57">Assuming that between the ages of 30 and 34 most people have married or have a long term partner, there is a rather high number of people who are single (40%). </s><s n="s2.3;p57.57">The mean age is 31.93 Years (Table 6) or 34.14 Years (Table 7) depending on sexes. </s><s n="s3.3;p57.57">Although the modal values of 20 (Table 6) and 24 (Table 7) seem to support the idea that most common age is rather low I don't believe that the frequency of these ages (2 and 4 respectively) within the group is justifiable. </s></p></div2></div1></body><back/></text></TEI.2>
