<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_0212e" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Assignment 1</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">deleted: header: module, assignment and student number; footer: page numbers</note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">Evaluated as candidate compound assignment. Assigned to S4: set of tasks/questions/exercises: non-compound</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">1</p><p n="date">2006-04</p><p n="module title">Statistics for Business</p><p n="module code">IB1080</p><p n="genre family">Exercise</p><p n="discipline">Business</p><p n="disciplinary group">SS</p><p n="grade">D</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">788</p><p n="number of s-units">42</p><p n="number of p">15</p><p n="number of tables">0</p><p n="number of figures">0</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">0</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">0</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">18.8</p><p n="average s-units per p">2.8</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">complex but non-compound assignment (see notesStmt for details)</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">m</p><p n="year of birth">1986</p><p n="first language">English</p><p n="education">UKA</p><p n="course">Business</p><p n="student ID">0212</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><docTitle><titlePart rend="bold">IB1070 Assignment 1 Commentaries</titlePart></docTitle></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">Task 3</head><p n="p1.15"><s n="s1.4;p1.15">Holtzbrinck Publishers Holdings Limited has performed excellently with by far the highest turnover and the second highest profit amongst others companies in its peer group. </s><s n="s2.4;p1.15">Since 1999 both profit and turnover have been increasing peeking at 2003. </s><s n="s3.4;p1.15">However the latest year (2004) has not proved to be so successful with a slight dip in both profit and turnover. </s><s n="s4.4;p1.15">Growth of the company was greatest between 1999 and 2000 with an increase of turnover of approximately £60,000 </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">Task 5</head><p n="p2.15"><s n="s1.3;p2.15">Compared with its peer group, Holtzbrinck Publishers Holdings Limited is the highest performing company bar one. </s><s n="s2.3;p2.15">In 2004 the company had the joint highest Turnover (£589,237) and one of the top three Profits (£46,001). </s><s n="s3.3;p2.15">Generally, the peer group itself had wildly varying Turnover to Profit ratios ranging from 49.9 to -49.9 (to one decimal place) </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">Task 6</head><p n="p3.15"><s n="s1.5;p3.15">For each quarter worksheet (e.g. </s><s n="s2.5;p3.15">Qtr 1), "Total" is simply an addition of the three listed months and "Average" a mean average of the months. </s><s n="s3.5;p3.15">"Commission Percentage" uses the "Total" and looks up a corresponding percentage on the "Payment Scheme" Worksheet. </s><s n="s4.5;p3.15">Using this percentage and "Total" the commission is calculated in terms of value. </s><s n="s5.5;p3.15">Finally, the bonus column outputs whether or not the salesperson has exceeded or matched the Quarterly Target. </s></p><p n="p4.15"><s n="s1.5;p4.15">Each column in the Payments worksheet uses corresponding data in the quarterly sheets (i.e. </s><s n="s2.5;p4.15">Qtr1-4). </s><s n="s3.5;p4.15">Annual Total takes the Total of each quarter and adds them together. </s><s n="s4.5;p4.15">Monthly Average and Quarterly Average are simply the Annual Total divided by twelve and four respectively. </s><s n="s5.5;p4.15">Basics salary is obtained from the "Payment Scheme worksheet" </s></p><p n="p5.15"><s n="s1.2;p5.15">"Bonuses" counts how many times a salesperson is owed a bonus and outputs the value of this bonus. </s><s n="s2.2;p5.15">Additionally, it also calculated whether the salesperson is owed the additional bonus of 0.2% by matching the Annual Total of each Salesperson with the Annual Total </s></p><p n="p6.15"><s n="s1.3;p6.15">Generally, each salesperson earns between 6-7% of the total sales per annum. </s><s n="s2.3;p6.15">The highest earner through the year (excluding bonuses/commission) is Turner with 7.513% of the sales force earnings. </s><s n="s3.3;p6.15">The least effective salesperson was Liddel with 5.959% of the sales. </s></p><p n="p7.15"><s n="s1.3;p7.15">The bonus and commission system appear to be slightly unfair. </s><s n="s2.3;p7.15">For example, Patel has 0.008% greater sales than Tsiolkovsky in the entire year .Tsiolkovsky, however, received a much bigger bonus/commission of 9.45% compared to Patel's 7.108%. </s><s n="s3.3;p7.15">This shows that some salespersons could work hard in two quarters of the year and achieve large bonuses/commissions but for the remaining two quarters, perhaps ease off slightly safe in the knowledge that they have performed better than salespeople who have worked consistently throughout the year. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">Task 7</head><p n="p8.15"><s n="s1.4;p8.15">For two of the three months Group B had the highest average Sales. </s><s n="s2.4;p8.15">However, their overall sales were far lower than the other two groups. </s><s n="s3.4;p8.15">In March, for example, Group C had over 4 times the sales of Group B. Group C was continually the highest selling group but this was simply down to sheer numbers within the group. </s><s n="s4.4;p8.15">Group A was steady throughout the Quarter with an increase in performance in the last month in which they also had the highest average sales of any of the groups </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">Task 8</head><p n="p9.15"><s n="s1.1;p9.15">When the Quarterly target for quarter one is set to a low value of 85% (£361.25) it costs the company £449.0845 in bonuses and commission </s></p><p n="p10.15"><s n="s1.2;p10.15">At 100% (i.e. </s><s n="s2.2;p10.15">425) personnel bonuses/commission costs the company £387.4545 .Further more when the target is increased to 115% or £448.75 the costs to the company decrease to £360.2695 </s></p><p n="p11.15"><s n="s1.1;p11.15">If the quarterly target is decreased to 85% the company pays out £63.61 more, which is equal to a 15.9% increase on top of bonus/commission costs at 100% </s></p><p n="p12.15"><s n="s1.1;p12.15">However, if the quarterly target increases to 115% the company saves £27.185 which is a saving of approximately 7% of the cost at 100% </s></p><p n="p13.15"><s n="s1.1;p13.15">In terms of the number of salespeople who gain bonuses the situation is as follows: </s></p><p n="p14.15"><s n="s1.6;p14.15">At 85% the whole sales team are owed a bonus for the first quarter. </s><s n="s2.6;p14.15">This is of course very high practically rendering the bonus scheme (as a tool to differentiate between the quality of each salesperson) pointless. </s><s n="s3.6;p14.15">When the target is changed to 100% 7/15 are owed a bonus and 6/15 are not owed a bonus. </s><s n="s4.6;p14.15">This means only about half of the team are owed bonuses. </s><s n="s5.6;p14.15">This even split is perhaps a happy medium between the company having to pay money and the staff considering the bonus scheme still worthwhile. </s><s n="s6.6;p14.15">When the higher target of 115% is in place then only three of the team achieve the bonus (Evans, Frances and Kowolski). </s></p><p n="p15.15"><s n="s1.1;p15.15">Currency is in Thousands of Pounds </s></p></div1></body><back/></text></TEI.2>
