<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_0223d" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Introduction to Assignment</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">deleted: header: module name; footer: affiliation, page numbers</note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">Evaluated as candidate compound assignment. Assigned to S1f: collection of long tasks/questions: compound.</note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">deleted: (4,027 words)</note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">deleted: (480 words)</note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">deleted: (319 words)</note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">deleted: (258 words)</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">4</p><p n="date">2001-04</p><p n="module title">Fianancial Analysis and Control Systems</p><p n="module code">ES979</p><p n="genre family">Critique</p><p n="discipline">Engineering</p><p n="disciplinary group">PS</p><p n="grade">M</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">4690</p><p n="number of s-units">223</p><p n="number of p">84</p><p n="number of tables">16</p><p n="number of figures">13</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">1</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">0</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">21.0</p><p n="average s-units per p">2.7</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">compound assignment consisting of 3 parts (see notesStmt for details)</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">f</p><p n="year of birth">1983</p><p n="first language">Chinese unspecified</p><p n="education">OSA</p><p n="course">Supply Engineering and Logistics</p><p n="student ID">0223</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><docTitle><titlePart rend="underlined italic">Financial Analysis &amp; Control Systems</titlePart></docTitle></titlePage><div1 type="toc" n="3"><head rend="bold">CONTENTS</head><p/></div1></front><body><div1 type="text"><head rend="bold">PART ONE</head><div2><head rend="bold">Introduction</head><div3><head rend="bold italic">Introduction to assignment</head><p n="p1.84"><s n="s1.2;p1.84">This essay gives an analysis of Amersham plc's financial performance in the past four years. </s><s n="s2.2;p1.84">Details will be followed in two parts. </s></p><p n="p2.84"><s n="s1.2;p2.84">Firstly, we will give a general overview of Amersham plc's financial performance trend over last four years trading. </s><s n="s2.2;p2.84">Mainly we will talk about the changing trends in profitability, activity, liquidity, and financing ratios. </s></p><p n="p3.84"><s n="s1.2;p3.84">Secondly, we will further discuss about Amersham plc's annual report in 2003. </s><s n="s2.2;p3.84">And critical evaluation of performance will be given. </s></p><p n="p4.84"><s n="s1.1;p4.84">Finally, conclusion will be given according to the performance of Amersham plc. </s></p></div3><div3><head rend="bold italic">Brief description of the company</head><p n="p5.84"><s n="s1.2;p5.84">Amersham is a world leader in medical diagnostics and in life sciences. </s><s n="s2.2;p5.84">The company is focused on enabling molecular medicine, working through three main business areas in diagnostic imaging, protein separations and discovery systems [1]. </s></p><p n="p6.84"><s n="s1.2;p6.84">Amersham is organised in two businesses, Amersham Health(medical dialgnostics and therapy products) and Amersham Biosciences(discovery systems and protein separations). </s><s n="s2.2;p6.84">The company was formed in 1997 from the mergers of Amersham International (UK), Pharmacia Biotech (Sweden) and Nycomed (Norway) [2]. </s></p><p n="p7.84"><s n="s1.2;p7.84">Amersham has research, development and manufacturing facilities at some 30 sites in North America, Europe and Asia. </s><s n="s2.2;p7.84">Their sales organisation includes offices in more than 50 countries as well as extensive network of agents and distributors, serving hospitals, clinics, research laboratories, biotechnology firms and pharmaceutical companies across the globe [3]. </s></p></div3></div2><div2><head rend="bold">Overview of Financial Performance Trend from 2000 to 2003</head><p n="p8.84"><s n="s1.2;p8.84">Amersham plc is at a structure reforming stage. </s><s n="s2.2;p8.84">Most significant changes occurred in year 2001. the following paragraphs will identify and discuss the trends in the accompanying graph. </s></p><div3><head rend="bold italic">Overall performance</head><figure id="BAWE_0223d-fig.001"><head>Figure 1</head></figure><p n="p9.84"><s n="s1.4;p9.84">Ratios in figure 1 illustrates that Amersham experienced fluctuated business performances during the past four years. </s><s n="s2.4;p9.84">Above all, ratios of return on capital employed stood at 20.29% in 2000, rose sharply by more than 12.09% at the end of 2001, then experienced a significant drop at 16.81% in 2002 and reached the bottom of 12.45% in 2003. similar trends were seen in ratios of return on shareholder funds and return on total assets. </s><s n="s3.4;p9.84">Started at 46.95% and 13.53% respectively, ratios of return on shareholders funds and return on total assets reached peak of 53.10% and 20.78% in 2001. </s><s n="s4.4;p9.84">Followed dramatically drop in 2002 and continued their downward trend in 2003. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0223d-fig.002"><head>Figure 2</head></figure><p n="p10.84"><s n="s1.3;p10.84">Figure 2 unfolds the steady increase of turnover in the past four years. </s><s n="s2.3;p10.84">The biggest change occurred in the period of 2000 to 2001, while turnover rose from 1,282,500 to 1,515,200. </s><s n="s3.3;p10.84">After then, Amersham experienced a slight increase from 1,537,700 in 2002 and 1,570,000 in 2003. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0223d-fig.003"><head>Figure 3</head></figure><p n="p11.84"><s n="s1.4;p11.84">The line chart above reflects fluctuated performance in kinds of profit margins. </s><s n="s2.4;p11.84">The EBIT margin experienced an increase between year 2000 and year 2001, peaking at 21.99% by the end of 2001, and steady decline in the following two years, bottoming at 12.61% in the end. </s><s n="s3.4;p11.84">Profit margin has quite similar shape of figures with EBIT margin. </s><s n="s4.4;p11.84">Although gross margin experienced fluctuation also, it reached peak at 68.72% in year 2002 and declined after that. </s></p></div3><div3><head rend="bold italic">Solvency</head><figure id="BAWE_0223d-fig.004"><head>Figure 4</head></figure><p n="p12.84"><s n="s1.1;p12.84">Liquidity ratios in figure 4 disclose how far short-term lenders have provided the funds to pay for the short-term assets[4]. </s></p><p n="p13.84"><s n="s1.5;p13.84">The chart shows a continuously decline in liquidity ratio. </s><s n="s2.5;p13.84">At the first two years, the ratios are also above 1:1 which reached 1.26:1 and 1.13:1 respectively. </s><s n="s3.5;p13.84">There is a huge fall during period from 2001 to 2002. </s><s n="s4.5;p13.84">And the ratio even dropped down to 0.88:1 which was below 1:1. </s><s n="s5.5;p13.84">Ratios kept on decrease at 0.79:1 by the end of 2003. </s></p></div3><div3><head rend="bold italic">Utilization of Assets</head><figure id="BAWE_0223d-fig.005"><head>Figure 5</head></figure><p n="p14.84"><s n="s1.2;p14.84">Figure 5 reduces the fluctuation in net assets turnover and fixed assets turnover between year 2000 and 2003. </s><s n="s2.2;p14.84">Both of them rose from 1.23 times and 1.65 times respectively in 2000 to 1.47 times and 1.92 times in 2001, following a sharp decline at 0.94 times and 1.03 times and finally a slightly increase at 0.99 times and 1.05 times. </s></p></div3><div3><head rend="bold italic">Working Capital</head><figure id="BAWE_0223d-fig.006"><head>Figure 6</head></figure><p n="p15.84"><s n="s1.3;p15.84">Seen from figure 6, there is a modest increase of 27,000 per year at the beginning. </s><s n="s2.3;p15.84">Then Amersham experienced a massive increase by 46,100 per year at the end of 2002. </s><s n="s3.3;p15.84">There was a slight decline in 2003 and the turnover ended in 430,000. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0223d-fig.007"><head>Figure 7</head></figure><p n="p16.84"><s n="s1.2;p16.84">Bar chart in figure 7 indicates that Amersham most effectively managed stock in year 2001 while the stock turnover was highest among the four years. </s><s n="s2.2;p16.84">However, the ratio reached the bottom at 7.07 in year 2003. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0223d-fig.008"><head>Figure 8</head></figure><p n="p17.84"><s n="s1.4;p17.84">Figure 8 illustrates a negative financial position for Amersham. </s><s n="s2.4;p17.84">Because debtor collection days were much longer than creditors payment days. </s><s n="s3.4;p17.84">Although there was a obvious drop from 2000 to 2001, the debtor collection days were still above 70 days. </s><s n="s4.4;p17.84">On the contrary, the creditor payment days were constantly below 30 days, and the shortest payment days occurred in 2002 which was only 16.9 days. </s></p></div3><div3><head rend="bold italic">Financial Risk</head><figure id="BAWE_0223d-fig.009"><head>Figure 9</head></figure><p n="p18.84"><s n="s1.1;p18.84">Gearing in figure 9 shows the level of all forms of debt or borrowing(regarded as the high risk sources of finance) as a percentage of the equity or shareholders funds(representing a lower risk to the company)[5]. </s></p><p n="p19.84"><s n="s1.1;p19.84">There is a positive position for Amersham in terms of financial risk because their gearing dropped from 157.84% at 2000 to 38.47% at 2003 which was regarded as a desirable target level. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0223d-fig.010"><head>Figure 10</head></figure><p n="p20.84"><s n="s1.3;p20.84">Interest cover indicates the extent to which current cover the fixed financing changes the company has to meet. </s><s n="s2.3;p20.84">Figure 10 demonstrates that Amersham experienced an improvement in financial risk which could be seen from the rapidly increase in interest cover from 2000 to 2003. </s><s n="s3.3;p20.84">It stood at 11.06 at the beginning and rose dramatically to 33.00 in the end. </s></p></div3></div2><div2><head rend="bold">Critical Evaluation of Performance as detailed in 2003</head><p n="p21.84"><s n="s1.2;p21.84">The strong results in 2003 reflect unwavering focus on Amersham's business fundamentals. </s><s n="s2.2;p21.84">They continued to expand sales of their patented medical diagnostics products at an excellent rate, delivered stronger second half growth in protein separations following the slowdown seen in the first half of the year, moved discovery systems into profit, ahead of schedule, for the second half of 2003 and they delivered improved underlying margins[6]. </s></p><div3><head rend="bold italic">Business Performance</head><div4><head rend="underlined italic">Return on Capital Employed</head><p n="p22.84"><s n="s1.2;p22.84">From figure 1(see the first part), we could easily found that the ratio of return on capital employed was declined from 16.81% in 2002 to 12.45% in 2003. </s><s n="s2.2;p22.84">It was mainly due to reduce of profit before interest which was £198,000 in 2003 compared with £275,300 in 2002[7]. </s></p></div4><div4><head rend="underlined italic">Turnover</head><p n="p23.84"><s n="s1.2;p23.84">From the group profit and loss account sheet in annual report[8], the group turnover was £1,570 million at the end of 2003, which was improved £32 million compared with turnover in 2002. </s><s n="s2.2;p23.84">This improvement was due to Amersham Health sales up seven per cent, Protein Separations sales up five per cent and Discovery Systems as a result of the restructuring programme whilst maintaining growth in Amersham Health and Protein Separations[9]. </s></p><div5><head>Amersham Health-Medical Diagnostics and Therapy</head><table id="BAWE_0223d-tab.001"><head>Table 1</head><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p24.84"><s n="s1.3;p24.84">See table 1[10], it is not hart to found that sales in 2003 increased by seven per cent to £973 million with Medical Diagnostics accounting for £924 million, up nine per cent. </s><s n="s2.3;p24.84">Medical Diagnostics sales were driven by patented diagnostic products, which grew by 22 per cent to £412 million. </s><s n="s3.3;p24.84">Sales of unpatented diagnostic products grew by 2 per cent to £357 million. </s></p></div5><div5><head>Amersham Biosciences-Protein Separations and Discovery Systems</head><table id="BAWE_0223d-tab.002"><head>Table 2</head><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p25.84"><s n="s1.5;p25.84">Table 2[11] illustrates the business performance of Amersham Biosciences. </s><s n="s2.5;p25.84">In 2003 Protein Separations sales were £295 million, up five per cent, and operating profit was up nine per cent to £106 million. </s><s n="s3.5;p25.84">Following the 3% sales growth reported at the half year, sales accelerated in the second half driven by 14 per cent growth in laboratory separations and operating margins improved driven by changes in the product mix. </s><s n="s4.5;p25.84">Discovery Systems sales in 2003 grew two per cent to £384 million, with an operating loss of £9 million compared with £32 million in 2002. the business achieved profitability in the second half following a successful realignment of the cost base by reducing R&amp;D and manufacturing costs and refocusing the business portfolio on areas where there is strong long term growth potential and where Amersham has existing market leadership. </s><s n="s5.5;p25.84">Restructuring cost savings in 2003 amounted to more than £20 amounted to more than £20 million with revised expectations of annual savings running at the rate of more than £40 million by the end of 2004. </s></p></div5></div4><div4><head rend="underlined italic">Earnings Before Interest and Tax</head><table id="BAWE_0223d-tab.003"><head> Table 3</head><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p26.84"><s n="s1.7;p26.84">Table 3 indicates that although turnover increased by £32,300 in 2003, profit before interest fell down from £275,300 to £198,000. </s><s n="s2.7;p26.84">Consequently, EBIT Margin fell down from 17.90% to 12.61%. </s><s n="s3.7;p26.84">These negative positions were caused by climbing of sales costs which reduced gross profit, and the increasing of administrative expenses. </s><s n="s4.7;p26.84">R&amp;D expenditure in protein separations increased by 18 per cent. </s><s n="s5.7;p26.84">Furthermore, the most important factor which affected these declining figures was the adverse foreign exchange movements. </s><s n="s6.7;p26.84">During 2003, the results were most notably impacted by the weakening of the US dollar with an overall adverse currency impact. </s><s n="s7.7;p26.84">Table 4 [12]gives out the comparison of effect by exchange rate in 2002 and 2003. </s></p><table id="BAWE_0223d-tab.004"><head>Table 4</head><row><cell/></row></table></div4></div3><div3><head rend="bold italic">Assets Utilization</head><table id="BAWE_0223d-tab.005"><head>Table 5</head><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p27.84"><s n="s1.2;p27.84">From table 5 [13], we could see 0.05 increase in net assets turnover in 2003 compared with 2002. </s><s n="s2.2;p27.84">The increase in this figure reflects an improvement of managing total utilization of resources in Amersham. </s></p><p n="p28.84"><s n="s1.7;p28.84">It was caused by four major factors. </s><s n="s2.7;p28.84">Firstly, sales increased to £1,652 million up six per cent at constant exchange rates and excluding the impact of disposed businesses. </s><s n="s3.7;p28.84">Secondly, fixed assets increased slightly from £1,490 million to £1,498 million. </s><s n="s4.7;p28.84">Thirdly, current assets increase from £673 million to £710 million in one year time. </s><s n="s5.7;p28.84">This rose was mainly due to the increase of stocks and debtors-amounts due within one year. </s><s n="s6.7;p28.84">Finally, current liabilities also experienced a big increase which rose from £526 million to £618 million. </s><s n="s7.7;p28.84">All in all, the net assets turnover rose from 0.94 to 0.99 which means Amersham could achieve more £0.05 of sales achieved for every £ of investment in the business.(All figures mentioned above see table 6[14]) </s></p><p n="p29.84"><s n="s1.1;p29.84">* calculated by other item in the same category. </s></p><table id="BAWE_0223d-tab.006"><head> Table6 </head><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p30.84"><s n="s1.4;p30.84">Table 5 shows the fixed assets turnover which gives out the number of £s of sales achieved for every £ of long term investment in the fixed assets of the business. </s><s n="s2.4;p30.84">The fixed asset was used more effectively in 2003, as the fixed asset turnover increased from 1.03 in 2002 to 1.05 in 2003. </s><s n="s3.4;p30.84">Together with the decline from 2000 and 2001, such kind of small change can be easily accepted when happening to an international cooperation. </s><s n="s4.4;p30.84">However, for Amersham, this improvement in the use of fixed asset could be a long term trend rather than a temporary performance, because several effective strategies had been adopted in the fixed asset management. </s></p><p n="p31.84"><s n="s1.5;p31.84">Generally speaking, Amersham continued its investment in effective fixed asset. </s><s n="s2.5;p31.84">In 2003, the value of fixed asset after depreciation and amortization increased to £1,498 million, compared with £1,491 million in 2002. </s><s n="s3.5;p31.84">There were three main reasons for this kind of change. </s><s n="s4.5;p31.84">Firstly, from table 6, we could see that intangible assets declined from £751 million in 2002 to £681 million in 2003. </s><s n="s5.5;p31.84">Table 7[15] illustrates the details around the changes in intangible fixed assets. </s></p><table id="BAWE_0223d-tab.007"><head>Table 7</head><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p32.84"><s n="s1.1;p32.84">From table 7, there was a 9.3 per cent decrease in intangible fixed assets which was mainly due to the 21.3 per cent reduce in other intangibles and slightly affected by goodwill which had a 8.5 per cent drop. </s></p><table id="BAWE_0223d-tab.008"><head>Table 8</head><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p33.84"><s n="s1.3;p33.84">Secondly, table 8[16] shows us the 10.5 per cent increase in tangible fixed assets was most significantly caused by the 48.8 per cent climbing in assets under construction. </s><s n="s2.3;p33.84">It was also affected by 7.7 per cent increase in plant and machinery and slightly rose by land and buildings spending. </s><s n="s3.3;p33.84">On the contrary, fixtures, fitting, tools &amp; equipment items had an 7.8 per cent side effect on the total tangible fixed assets. </s></p><table id="BAWE_0223d-tab.009"><head>Table 9</head><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p34.84"><s n="s1.4;p34.84">Finally, as table 9[17] told us, an acceptable 10.1 per cent rose in fixed asset investment. </s><s n="s2.4;p34.84">On one side, investment in joint ventures had a 20.5 per cent rose which had the most important affect on the total fixed asset investments. </s><s n="s3.4;p34.84">While, on the other side, investment in own shares had a 37.5 per cent fall which had a strong negative effect on total investment. </s><s n="s4.4;p34.84">Investment in trade investments had a modest 10 per cent increase. </s></p></div3><div3><head rend="bold italic">Working Capital</head><p n="p35.84"><s n="s1.5;p35.84">See from figure 6(above), the working capital in 2003 was £430 million, compared with £438 million in 2002. </s><s n="s2.5;p35.84">There was a £8,500 fall in this item. </s><s n="s3.5;p35.84">Working capital is calculated by deducting the current liabilities from the current assets. </s><s n="s4.5;p35.84">It implies that short-term sources of finance contribute to the capital tied up in current assets and the difference represents the business's own investment in the current assets. </s><s n="s5.5;p35.84">The ratio of current asserts to current liabilities expresses this difference[4]. </s></p><p n="p36.84"><s n="s1.4;p36.84">From the viewpoint of capital, there were three major reasons which caused the negative result of capital in Amersham. </s><s n="s2.4;p36.84">Firstly, stock increased 6.7 per cent. </s><s n="s3.4;p36.84">Mainly due to the work in progress stocks increased 14.0 per cent in year 2003. </s><s n="s4.4;p36.84">Finished goods and goods fro resale also steadily increase 6.7 per cent(refer to figure 11).(all data came from [18]). </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0223d-fig.011"><head>Figure 18</head></figure><p n="p37.84"><s n="s1.2;p37.84">Secondly, debtors increased 6.9 per cent in 2003. </s><s n="s2.2;p37.84">See from figure 12 trade debtors had a 4.3 per cent rose and arrived at £315 million at 31 December 2003. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0223d-fig.012"><head>Figure 19</head></figure><p n="p38.84"><s n="s1.2;p38.84">Finally, the increase of creditors also make important role by the reduction of working capital in 2003. we could easily see from figure 13 that the creditors ratios increase 186.4 per cent comparing the two years. </s><s n="s2.2;p38.84">Among all the other items, unsecured loan notes made the most significant effect on the final result which experienced a 4550 per cent increase. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0223d-fig.013"><head>Figure 13</head></figure><p n="p39.84"><s n="s1.1;p39.84">In summary, table 10 below will give the overall effect of working capital movements on cash flow. </s></p><table id="BAWE_0223d-tab.010"><head>Table 10</head><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p40.84"><s n="s1.3;p40.84">Traditional accounting statements do not tell us how efficiently an entity has been managed, that is, how well its resources have been looked after. </s><s n="s2.3;p40.84">Profit may, to some extent, be used as a measure of efficiency but, as we have explained in earlier chapter, accounting profit is subject to a great many arbitrary adjustments, and it is not entirely reliable. </s><s n="s3.3;p40.84">What we need to do is to put whatever evidence we have into context, compare it with earlier accounting period and, if possible, with other similar entities[19]. </s></p><p n="p41.84"><s n="s1.1;p41.84">There are very many different types of ratios that we can use to measure the efficiency of Amersham, now we will cover three common ones. </s></p><table id="BAWE_0223d-tab.011"><head>Table 11</head><row><cell/></row></table><div4><head rend="underlined italic">Stock turnover ratio:</head><p n="p42.84"><s n="s1.4;p42.84">The result of this calculation gives the number of £s of sales achieved for every £ tied up in stock[5]. </s><s n="s2.4;p42.84">As we can see from table 11 that stock turnover in 2003 is slightly less than turnover in 2002. </s><s n="s3.4;p42.84">It told us that Amersham was less efficient in purchasing and selling goods appearance. </s><s n="s4.4;p42.84">But generally speaking, stock turnover kept above 7 times is a good performance for the inventory management of Amersham, which mean that Amersham had only 1.7 months' normal sales in stock. </s></p></div4><div4><head rend="underlined italic">Trade debtor collection period ratio:</head><p n="p43.84"><s n="s1.4;p43.84">Keeping high stock turnover is all very well, but there is not much point in generating extra sales if the customers do not pay for them. </s><s n="s2.4;p43.84">Customers might be encouraged to buy more by a combination of lower selling prices and generous credit terms. </s><s n="s3.4;p43.84">If the debtors are slow at paying, the entity might find that it was run into cash flow problems[19]. </s><s n="s4.4;p43.84">Thus is important for it to watch the trade debtor position very carefully. </s></p><p n="p44.84"><s n="s1.6;p44.84">As an acceptable median debtor collection period in United Kingdom is about 50 days. </s><s n="s2.6;p44.84">From table 11, we could conclude that Amersham does have problem in credit control procedures because the average period among two years was above 70 days. </s><s n="s3.6;p44.84">As we know that, cash is the oil for the vehicle. </s><s n="s4.6;p44.84">The worse thing is, period in 2003 is even 2 days longer than period in 2002. </s><s n="s5.6;p44.84">This was caused by poor credit control, and more potential bad debt problems. </s><s n="s6.6;p44.84">Another factor was worse performance to customer expectations leading to more queries causing payment delays. </s></p></div4><div4><head rend="underlined italic">Creditors payment period:</head><p n="p45.84"><s n="s1.3;p45.84">Table 11 shows there was an upward trend in the average lend of trade creditors because the period in 2003 is 8 days longer than period in 2002. </s><s n="s2.3;p45.84">It illustrates that Amersham was having some difficulty in finding the cash to pay its creditors. </s><s n="s3.3;p45.84">Indeed, it was a sign that Amersham was running into financial difficulties, accompanying with the delay of payments by customers. </s></p></div4></div3><div3><head rend="bold italic">Cash Position</head><p n="p46.84"><s n="s1.5;p46.84">Cash is a very significant factor for the successful operation of a business. </s><s n="s2.5;p46.84">Almost every transaction recorded by the accountant will involve cash sooner or later. </s><s n="s3.5;p46.84">A business with adequate liquid resources can pay its way and is much less risky than a business which constantly delays payment to creditors because it does not have sufficient cash resources, or the ability to draw down cash from lenders. </s><s n="s4.5;p46.84">Conversely, cash balances do not earn a profit, so some managers would consider idle cash as a sign of inefficiency. </s><s n="s5.5;p46.84">The art of cash management is to hold a liquid balance that is sufficient for the needs of the business, get not over large and wasteful of resources[4]. </s></p><table id="BAWE_0223d-tab.012"><head>Table 12</head><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p47.84"><s n="s1.3;p47.84">Table 12 reflects the cash position around Amersham in 2002 and 2003. </s><s n="s2.3;p47.84">From the table, we can positively see that there was an improvement in cash position in 2003. </s><s n="s3.3;p47.84">Following paragraphs will analyse the reason for this kind of improvement. </s></p><p n="p48.84"><s n="s1.3;p48.84">Table 13 clearly demonstrates the change in cash position for Amersham in 2003. </s><s n="s2.3;p48.84">Among all the other factors, movement in creditors had the greatest impact on the cash position, which means that Amersham took advantage of bank to improve its cash position and solve capital problem, rather than resort to encourage its operating profit or reduce its customer stage payments. </s><s n="s3.3;p48.84">It might works well for the short term to solve current financial problems, but it had potential risk for Amersham in long term. </s></p><table id="BAWE_0223d-tab.013"><head>Table 13(figures see [20]</head><row><cell/></row></table></div3><div3><head rend="bold italic">Financial Risk</head><div4><head rend="underlined italic">Loans</head><p n="p49.84"><s n="s1.1;p49.84">Besides obtaining the necessary capital from their shareholders, Amersham also borrow money in the form of debentures. </s></p><table id="BAWE_0223d-tab.014"><head>Table 14</head><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p50.84"><s n="s1.5;p50.84">Table 14 tells us the loan position in Amersham for short and long term. </s><s n="s2.5;p50.84">For short term, Amersham strongly depended on unsecured loan, which is comparably the best risk free way to obtain capital. </s><s n="s3.5;p50.84">As we know that if it is secured loan and the company cannot repay it on its due repayment date, the debenture holders may sell the secured assets and use the amount to settle the amount owing to them. </s><s n="s4.5;p50.84">But for unsecured loan, it is not the case. </s><s n="s5.5;p50.84">For the long term loan, the company only obtained 317 million from unsecured loan, and most of its loan capital came from bank loans and overdrafts. </s></p><p n="p51.84"><s n="s1.1;p51.84">Generally speaking, from Amersham's point of view, one further advantage of raising capital in the form of the debenture loans is that for taxation purposes the interest can be charged as a business expense against the profit for the year(unlike dividends paid to share holders)[19]. </s></p></div4><div4><head rend="underlined italic"> Gearing and Interest Cover</head><table id="BAWE_0223d-tab.015"><head>Table 15</head><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p52.84"><s n="s1.9;p52.84">A high level of debt capital relative to equity capital(i.e. a high level of gearing) means that the company focus a relatively high interest charge. </s><s n="s2.9;p52.84">Interest must be paid out of the store of available profits. </s><s n="s3.9;p52.84">If the interest charge soaks up most of the available profit there will be very little left over for the ordinary shareholders. </s><s n="s4.9;p52.84">Therefore, an investment in a highly geared company is usually seen as relatively risky for equity shareholders[21]. </s><s n="s5.9;p52.84">Compared year 2002 and year 2003, Amersham had made much more progress in reducing financial risk field. </s><s n="s6.9;p52.84">We could see from table 15 that gearing experienced a 5.1 per cent reduction in 2003. </s><s n="s7.9;p52.84">It was due to 54.9 per cent reduction in long-term loans[22]. </s><s n="s8.9;p52.84">Consequently, the interest cover rose to 33.00 times, which is almost 10 times increasing compared with figures in 2002. </s><s n="s9.9;p52.84">The positive appearance in financial risk management was significant for Amersham's shareholders and for Amersham to attract more potential shareholders in the coming years. </s></p></div4></div3><div3><head rend="bold italic">Assessment of Shareholders' benefits</head><table id="BAWE_0223d-tab.016"><head>Table 16</head><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p53.84"><s n="s1.3;p53.84">From the viewpoint of shareholders, it was not a happy result by the end of 2003. from the return on shareholders funds aspect, figures dropped 7.02 per cent. </s><s n="s2.3;p53.84">Also from the EPS aspect, for the increasing spending on exceptional items and goodwill amortisation, there were less shares left for EPS. Although there was slightly increase in dividends, but most of them were still in proposed progress. </s><s n="s3.3;p53.84">From all the analysis which we mentioned above, it is not hard to conclude that Amersham had not made its shareholders happy in year 2003. </s></p></div3></div2><div2><head rend="bold">Conclusion</head><p n="p54.84"><s n="s1.1;p54.84">From the above analysis of four years' financial trends and critical evaluation of performance as detailed in most recent annual report, we could finally conclude that , after the structure reforming in 2002, Amersham was getting better performance in inventory management, assets utilization, working capital management, cash position improvement and financial risk reduction, although there was slight adverse affect in shareholders' benefits. </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="front-back-matter"><head rend="bold">Reference</head><p>
[1] Amersham plc | About us | Overview 
</p><p><seg type="URL" n="http://www.amersham.com/about/index.html"/> 
</p><p>
[2] Amersham plc | About us | Overview 
</p><p><seg type="URL" n="http://www.amersham.com/about/index.html"/> 
</p><p>
[3] Amersham plc | About us | Global operations 
</p><p><seg type="URL" n="http://www.amersham.com/about/index.html"/> 
</p><p>
[4] Pizzey, A., (1998). 
<hi rend="italic">Finance and Accounting for Non-specialist Students,</hi> London: Financial Times/Pitman. 
</p><p>
[5] Tim, P. 
(2005) <hi rend="italic">Financial Analysis and Control Systems.</hi> 
Birmingham: FOCUS Business Development &amp; Training Consultancy 
</p><p>
[6] Amersham plc Annual Report 2003, pp4. 
</p><p>
[7] Amersham plc FAME pp1. 
</p><p>
[8] Amersham plc Annual Report 2003, pp31. 
</p><p>
[9] Amersham plc Annual Report 2003, pp4. 
</p><p>
[10] Amersham plc Annual Report 2003, pp4. 
</p><p>
[11] Amersham plc Annual Report 2003, pp5. 
</p><p>
[12] Amersham plc Financial Archives 2003, 'View the Amersham plc presentation 
</p><p>
[13] Amersham plc FAME pp4. 
</p><p>
[14] Amersham plc Annual Report 2003, pp33. 
</p><p>
[15] Amersham plc Annual Report 2003, pp44. 
</p><p>
[16] Amersham plc Annual Report 2003, pp45. 
</p><p>
[17] Amersham plc Annual Report 2003, pp46. 
</p><p>
[18] Amersham plc Annual Report 2003, pp47. 
</p><p>
[19] Dyson, L., R., (2004), <hi rend="italic">Accounting for Non-accounting Students.</hi> 
New York: Prentice Hall Financial Times. 
</p><p>
[20] Amersham plc Annual Report 2003, pp34.pp66. 
</p><p>
[21] Gowthorpe, C. 
(2003), <hi rend="italic">Business Accounting and Finance: for non-specialists.</hi> 
London: Thomson Learning. 
</p><p>
[22] Amersham plc Annual Report 2003, pp48. 
</p></div1><div1 type="text"><head rend="bold">PART TWO</head><div2><head rend="bold">Budgeting</head><p n="p55.84"><s n="s1.3;p55.84">Budgets are an important tool for management planning and control. </s><s n="s2.3;p55.84">This chapter considers the process of budgets, and show how budgets are applied in the business simulation "Winning Margin™". </s><s n="s3.3;p55.84">It also picks up some issues relating to my behaviours as purchasing manager in the budget preparation. </s></p><div3><head rend="bold italic">Budget process</head><p n="p56.84"><s n="s1.3;p56.84">Budgets do not exist in a vacuum; they are an integral part of a planning framework that is adopted by well-run business[1]. </s><s n="s2.3;p56.84">It is vital that business develop plans for the future. </s><s n="s3.3;p56.84">Whatever a business is trying to achieve, it is unlikely to be successful unless its managers are clear what the future direction of the business is going to be. </s></p><p n="p57.84"><s n="s1.1;p57.84">The development of plans involves five key steps: </s></p><list type="ordered"><item>Setting the aims and objectives of the business.</item><item>Identifying the options available.</item><item>Evaluating options and making a selection. </item><item>Setting detailed short-term plans or budgets.</item><item>Collecting information on performance and exercising control. </item></list></div3><div3><head rend="bold italic">Application of budgeting in "Winning Margin™"</head><p n="p58.84"><s n="s1.2;p58.84">Budgeting is such an important area for business and other organisations, which it tends to be approached in a fairly methodical and formal way. </s><s n="s2.2;p58.84">Following paragraphs will discuss and analysis about the application of budgeting in the business simulation game. </s></p><p n="p59.84"><s n="s1.1;p59.84">Step1: Establish who will take responsibility </s></p><p n="p60.84"><s n="s1.2;p60.84">There were five functional areas in our team: purchasing, production, commercial, treasurer and finance. </s><s n="s2.2;p60.84">Define which manager should take his/her own responsibility was the first thing we did. </s></p><p n="p61.84"><s n="s1.1;p61.84">Step2: Communicate budget guidelines to relevant managers </s></p><p n="p62.84"><s n="s1.2;p62.84">When we planned to draw up budgets, all managers in different functions gathered together and discussed about them. </s><s n="s2.2;p62.84">It was the responsibility of the budget committee to see that managers had all the necessary information. </s></p><p n="p63.84"><s n="s1.1;p63.84">Step3: Identify the limiting factor </s></p><p n="p64.84"><s n="s1.3;p64.84">It was important that the limiting factor was identified as capacity and all managers were informed of the restriction early in the process. </s><s n="s2.3;p64.84">The limiting factor determined the overall level of activity for the business. </s><s n="s3.3;p64.84">All managers' budget plans considered capacity at the first stage. </s></p><p n="p65.84"><s n="s1.1;p65.84">Step 5: prepare draft budgets for all other area </s></p><p n="p66.84"><s n="s1.1;p66.84">We adopted the bottom-up approach which was an effective approach allowed greater involvement among managers in the budgeting process and this, in turn, increased the level of commitment to the targets set. </s></p><p n="p67.84"><s n="s1.1;p67.84">Step6: communicate the budgets to all interest parties </s></p><p n="p68.84"><s n="s1.2;p68.84">Quite commonly, it was impossible for our capacity to fulfil all the demands. </s><s n="s2.2;p68.84">We might communicate with our competitors to negotiate a win-win method. </s></p></div3><div3><head rend="bold italic">Purchasing manager's contribution to budget</head><p n="p69.84"><s n="s1.4;p69.84">As purchasing manager, my significant contribution was request to spend 2 million for supplier development at the very beginning stage, which made a long-term benefit for the overall situation. </s><s n="s2.4;p69.84">Firstly, we saved one quarter time for transferring raw material. </s><s n="s3.4;p69.84">Secondly, we had clearer and more effective budget plan since we cut up one stage delay. </s><s n="s4.4;p69.84">Thirdly, work in progress capital had been reduced at the largest extent to release our capital and cash position. </s></p></div3></div2></div1><div1 type="front-back-matter"><head rend="bold">Reference</head><p>
[1] Mclaney, E. &amp; Atrill, P. 
(2005), <hi rend="italic">Accounting: an Introduction.</hi> 
New York: Financial Times. 
</p></div1><div1 type="text"><head rend="bold">PART THREE</head><div2><head rend="bold">Techniques</head><p n="p70.84"><s n="s1.4;p70.84">In this chapter we will talk about two kinds of techniques: activity-based costing and investment appraisal. </s><s n="s2.4;p70.84">Function and usefulness of each technique will be given at beginning. </s><s n="s3.4;p70.84">Following we will discuss the application of each in the business simulation. </s><s n="s4.4;p70.84">Also we will compare them to the real world environment. </s></p><div3><head rend="bold italic">Activity-Based Costing</head><p n="p71.84"><s n="s1.3;p71.84">This costing system seeks to understand the behaviour of certain overhead costs, and to relate them to cost units on the basis of that behaviour. </s><s n="s2.3;p71.84">Overheads are grouped for certain activities(e.g. materials handling, setting up machinery) which 'drive' or cause costs to be incurred, and these 'cost drivers' are allocated to cost units on the basis of the use which is made of the service provided. </s><s n="s3.3;p71.84">The new method is required to understand the indirect services rendered to production and the influences which drive the costs incurred. </s></p><p n="p72.84"><s n="s1.1;p72.84">The ABC system could help our decision making in four aspects: </s></p><p n="p73.84"><s n="s1.2;p73.84">Firstly, identify the overhead activities in the business which provide a service to production, and the cost incurred to provide that service. </s><s n="s2.2;p73.84">Some overheads may be related to labour cost and others related to machinery, while the demand for the service given by other activities may not be related to either of these factors. </s></p><p n="p74.84"><s n="s1.2;p74.84">Secondly, establish a cost centre for each of these service activities, and accumulate the costs to the cost centre. </s><s n="s2.2;p74.84">Cost centres might be created for purchasing, materials handling, maintenance, inspection, packing and dispatching. </s></p><p n="p75.84"><s n="s1.3;p75.84">Thirdly, after observation and consideration it will be possible to identify the cost driver which establishes the demand for each activity: for example, production scheduling may be driven by the number of set-ups, the cost of purchasing by the number of orders placed, or materials handling by the number of deliveries or requisitions. </s><s n="s2.3;p75.84">These factors affect the cost and behaviour of the activity. </s><s n="s3.3;p75.84">At this stage, some activities may be identified for which there is little demand. </s></p><p n="p76.84"><s n="s1.1;p76.84">Fourthly, relate overhead costs to production unites on the basis of the cost drives - the number of transactions which each activity generates. </s></p><p n="p77.84"><s n="s1.2;p77.84">In real world, we are more commonly use full absorption costing method. </s><s n="s2.2;p77.84">The overhead costs of production are added to the prime cost, which comprised direct materials and direct labour for each unit. </s></p></div3><div3><head rend="bold italic">Investment appraisal</head><p n="p78.84"><s n="s1.2;p78.84">A number of investment appraisal methods have been developed which can be applied according to the circumstances of the case. </s><s n="s2.2;p78.84">In this chapter, we pick up two of the most common used methods. </s></p><p n="p79.84"><s n="s1.1;p79.84">The payback method: </s></p><p n="p80.84"><s n="s1.3;p80.84">This method simply calculates the time taken by a project to pay back from its cash flow the amount of capital invested in the project. </s><s n="s2.3;p80.84">The project which pays back soonest is the preferred investment if a choice has to be made. </s><s n="s3.3;p80.84">Projects which cannot repay within a certain period are rejected. </s></p><p n="p81.84"><s n="s1.1;p81.84">The accounting rate of return(ARR) </s></p><p n="p82.84"><s n="s1.4;p82.84">This method calculates the rate of return on funds invested in the project over its full life. </s><s n="s2.4;p82.84">The company will select a 'hurdle' rate - the minimum rate for acceptance of a project - and those projects with a return in excess of that rate will be acceptable. </s><s n="s3.4;p82.84">Working capital can be included in the funds invested, but the profit disclosed by the financial accounts if often used to calculate the return. </s><s n="s4.4;p82.84">Profit can vary according to the depreciation charge and other accounting policies used. </s></p><p n="p83.84"><s n="s1.3;p83.84">At the first stage of the "Winning Margin™", our group had to decide our investment direction, which means should we choose to develop Tiger or Wolf product. </s><s n="s2.3;p83.84">If we used the payable method, as product Wolf had short pay back circle, it was better choice. </s><s n="s3.3;p83.84">But if we adopted ARR method, as product Tiger had high investment pay back, we should choose Tiger. </s></p><p n="p84.84"><s n="s1.1;p84.84">In realistic, current businesses and competitive environment also needed to be considered when we make any decision. </s></p></div3></div2></div1></body><back><div1 type="appendix"><head rend="bold">APPENDIX</head><p/></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
