<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_0223c" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An analysis of HC collaborating with CNI</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">deleted: header: module name; footer: affiliation</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">4</p><p n="date">2001-04</p><p n="module title">International Joint Venture</p><p n="module code">ES982</p><p n="genre family">Proposal</p><p n="discipline">Engineering</p><p n="disciplinary group">PS</p><p n="grade">D</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">3347</p><p n="number of s-units">203</p><p n="number of p">101</p><p n="number of tables">0</p><p n="number of figures">1</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">8</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">43</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">16.5</p><p n="average s-units per p">2.0</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">f</p><p n="year of birth">1983</p><p n="first language">Chinese unspecified</p><p n="education">OSA</p><p n="course">Supply Engineering and Logistics</p><p n="student ID">0223</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><docTitle><titlePart rend="bold">International Joint Venture</titlePart></docTitle><titlePart> --------An analysis of HC collaborating with CNI</titlePart></titlePage><div1 type="toc" n="2"><head rend="bold">CONTENT LIST</head><p/></div1></front><body><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">INTRODUCTION</head><p n="p1.101"><s n="s1.4;p1.101">International joint ventures are increasing with the globalization of industries(Chen&amp;Wilson, 2003).HC has its glorious history in the field of manufacturing specialised medical equipment in the whole world. </s><s n="s2.4;p1.101">With the fast increasing demands of products, HC experiences insufficient capacity and high cost problems. </s><s n="s3.4;p1.101">Resorting to international collaboration is the best way for HC's growth. </s><s n="s4.4;p1.101">Following is an analysis of HC's collaboration planning. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">1.STRATEGY PLANNING</head><div2><head rend="underlined">1.1 HC SWOT Analysis:</head><list type="bulleted"><head>Strength:</head><item>Long established and highly respected company</item><item>Expertise in manufacturing specialized medical equipment</item><item>Products have an excellent reputation for quality and performance</item><item>Fairly sound financial position</item><item>Abundant current book orders and potential orders from China and Mexican</item></list><list type="bulleted"><head>Weakness:</head><item>High labor/material costs which lead to high price of product</item><item>Currently very limited presence in S.A.</item><item>Insufficient final assembly and test capacity</item><item>High cost to increase capacity in Switzerland</item></list><list type="bulleted"><head>Opportunity:</head><item>Determine to enter S.A. market</item><item>Low labor/material costs in S.A.</item><item>Low cost to increase capacity in Amazonia</item><item>Possible change in import regulations in Amazonia</item><item>CNI have interest in local manufacture</item><item>CNI's previous relationship with EM probably would broken</item><item>Transfer all final assembly and test operations to S.A.</item></list><list type="bulleted"><head>Threaten:</head><item>EM is the main European competitor</item><item>Manufacturing technology is less sophisticated than EM</item><item>Product development program is constrained by EM's patents in this field which will last for another nine years</item></list><p n="p2.101"><s n="s1.7;p2.101">From HC's current booking orders and its potential orders, HC can not supply sufficient equipments as well as competitive price. </s><s n="s2.7;p2.101">For one side, HC hoping to win the order for 20 units in 2006-2009 from Mexican authorities which means HC's price must be as low as possible to compete with the USA's company. </s><s n="s3.7;p2.101">For the other side, HC already can not meet the gap in resources. </s><s n="s4.7;p2.101">How can it meet the order from China which is 15 units in 2006-2008 is still a problem. </s><s n="s5.7;p2.101">With a capacity increase of 2 units/month would requires additional investment of some £0.80m in facilities and test equipment with current technology in Switzerland. </s><s n="s6.7;p2.101">But the some amount of financial investment could increase up to 3 units/month in specialised equipment, plus cost of land and facilities in Amazonia. </s><s n="s7.7;p2.101">Furthermore, material costs in Amazonia would be only 10-15% cheaper on average comparing with Switzerland, and labour costs is just average 15% of those in Switzerland which are quite attractive factor for HC. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">1.2 HC's motivations:</head><p n="p3.101"><s n="s1.1;p3.101">Base on the present situation, the key objective and motivation of HC is: </s></p><p n="p4.101"><s n="s1.1;p4.101">To satisfy the increasing demands for the next ten years, HC should transfer its all final assembly and test operation to South American. </s></p><p n="p5.101"><s n="s1.1;p5.101">HC also makes its step-by-step plan for next five to ten years: </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0223c-fig.001"><head>Figure 1. HC's five to ten years plan</head></figure></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">1.3 CNI SWOT Analysis:</head><list type="bulleted"><head>Strength:</head><item>Largest manufacture in Amazonia</item><item>Established for 65 years</item><item>Good reputations for reliability</item><item>Excellent connections with Government</item><item>Cheap investment to increase capacity</item><item>Sufficient space available in current factory</item><item>Low material/labour cost</item></list><list type="bulleted"><head>Weakness:</head><item>Need technological assistance</item><item>Poor patent protection system in history</item><item>Previous relationship with EM might broken along with the implement of new import regulations by Government</item><item>Unstable inflation</item></list><list type="bulleted"><head>Opportunity:</head><item>Need to build a collaborative venture to maintain its market position</item><item>Government introduce local content limit</item><item>Government interest in 'foreign exchange neutral'</item><item>Partner select from EM or HC</item></list><list type="bulleted"><head>Threaten:</head><item>Authorities change the import regulations</item><item>Only one licence will be issued by government</item></list><p n="p6.101"/></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">1.4 CNI's motivations:</head><p n="p7.101"><s n="s1.2;p7.101">Because the authorities are anxious to see the maximum practicable level of local content, plus suitable offsets to conserve limited foreign exchange, CNI can no longer reply on import fully manufactured items, it have to look for a partner to get technological assistance to development itself. </s><s n="s2.2;p7.101">And hopeful CNI could collaborate with the partner to build a joint venture company in Amazonia. </s></p><p n="p8.101"><s n="s1.2;p8.101">From the above discussion about both HC and CNI, it's not hard to find that they two could match to quite a large extent. </s><s n="s2.2;p8.101">From this sense of view, HC collaborating with CNI would be a best option. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">1.5 Evaluation of the collaboration with CNI:</head><div3><head rend="bold italic">1.5.1 Benefits:</head><p rend="ordered" n="p9.101"><s n="s1.3;p9.101">Easy to access new market in South American. </s><s n="s2.3;p9.101">S.A. is a best place for HC to enter, but HC still have not got any chance to enter it not to mention set company in it. </s><s n="s3.3;p9.101">It would a good opportunity to access the green land and explore it later. </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p10.101"><s n="s1.3;p10.101">Improve economies of scale. </s><s n="s2.3;p10.101">With the increasing demand of products, HC need to enlarge its economic scale as well. </s><s n="s3.3;p10.101">Emerge need for increasing capacity pushes HC to find external help. </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p11.101"><s n="s1.2;p11.101">Increase financial resources &amp; stability. </s><s n="s2.2;p11.101">Because CNI also have strong financial background, the new relationship with CNI could make HC more powerful in financial assistance. </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p12.101"><s n="s1.4;p12.101">Low labour/material costs to low down product price. </s><s n="s2.4;p12.101">The keen price competition with USA is still on the process. </s><s n="s3.4;p12.101">HC's current price is not that competitive to win the order from the Mexican company. </s><s n="s4.4;p12.101">By collaboration with CNI, HC could lower down its product price to a large extent. </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p13.101"><s n="s1.2;p13.101">Greater influence on markets. </s><s n="s2.2;p13.101">Because CNI is also a good reputation and long established company, HC could have stronger influence on markets by collaborating with CNI. </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p14.101"><s n="s1.2;p14.101">Reduce risk. </s><s n="s2.2;p14.101">Especially from political issue, HC need an extra hand which is in local area in S.A. to solve the official problems. </s></p></div3><div3><head rend="bold italic">1.5.2 Risks:</head><p rend="ordered" n="p15.101"><s n="s1.5;p15.101">Political instability. </s><s n="s2.5;p15.101">Firstly, government could change their import regulation now which means they could also change it later. </s><s n="s3.5;p15.101">And with the changing of officer in government, rules would also differ. </s><s n="s4.5;p15.101">Secondly, inflation is not entirely under control in Amazonia which means we might got nothing with the effect of inflation. </s><s n="s5.5;p15.101">Thirdly, how could HC get money back from Amazonia is also a problem. </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p16.101"><s n="s1.3;p16.101">Quality warranty. </s><s n="s2.3;p16.101">Authorise in Amazonia limits the minimum local content and maximum local material which might lead to quality problem. </s><s n="s3.3;p16.101">After-sales service would also a negotiable issue. </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p17.101"><s n="s1.4;p17.101">Lose timing advantage. </s><s n="s2.4;p17.101">It is a long distance from Switzerland to South American. </s><s n="s3.4;p17.101">All the time which include checking, loading, shipping, unloading, checking have to be taken into consideration. </s><s n="s4.4;p17.101">Delay on one point may conduct delay in whole system. </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p18.101"><s n="s1.3;p18.101">Personnel/training implications. </s><s n="s2.3;p18.101">Once collaboration relationship with CNI been built, inevitably, HC have to face personnel/training issue. </s><s n="s3.3;p18.101">Loyalty about the persons whom HC send out in Amazonia would be doubtable later. </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p19.101"><s n="s1.2;p19.101">Translation, communications and culture issues. </s><s n="s2.2;p19.101">Different language, different cultures, different time zones, and different work approach and habit might probably incurs many barriers. </s></p></div3></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">2.TACATICAL &amp; FINANCIAL PLANNING</head><p n="p20.101"><s n="s1.1;p20.101">Attach the spreadsheet for LICENSING and two patterns of JVC. Benefits and risks analysis will be given as follows. </s></p><div2><head rend="underlined">2.1 Option One: LICENSING</head><p n="p21.101"><s n="s1.2;p21.101">Because the Amazonia government have a strict regulation which says that the local content must be above 67%. </s><s n="s2.2;p21.101">But from table 1(see appendix), we can say that no matter how to adjust internal profit figures, it is impossible to balance and satisfy all conditions. </s></p><p n="p22.101"><s n="s1.1;p22.101">Furthermore, LICENSING is more suitable for short-term relationship between partners which is not what HC wants for. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">2.2 Option Two: Joint Venture Company (Partner or Customer)</head><p n="p23.101"><s n="s1.3;p23.101">Same amount of money, different approach. </s><s n="s2.3;p23.101">From table 2.and table 3.(see appendix),it is not hard to find out that there is not many difference on total profit for either HC or CNI. But total profit is not the only factor HC need to consider about. </s><s n="s3.3;p23.101">There are many other points which HC should concern about. </s></p><div3><head rend="bold italic">2.2.1JVC profit share:</head><p n="p24.101"><s n="s1.1;p24.101">Customer: 48.2% of total profit comes from JVC profit share. </s></p><p n="p25.101"><s n="s1.1;p25.101">Partner: 32.6% of total profit comes from JVC profit share. </s></p><p n="p26.101"><s n="s1.4;p26.101">Because the JVC profit share is kind of 'afterward' money which is not that directly to get. </s><s n="s2.4;p26.101">Based on the nature of this kind of profit, HC could only get it when JVC have already earned profits. </s><s n="s3.4;p26.101">Furthermore, the profits which HC shared is put into Amazonia bank account which means there is still a way to go for the money transferring to HC's Switzerland bank account. </s><s n="s4.4;p26.101">The above figures mean the later type of JVC could have less risk on bring money back in Switzerland bank account process for the following reasons. </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p27.101"><s n="s1.3;p27.101">Inflation. </s><s n="s2.3;p27.101">From the present environment, inflation in Amazonia is not totally under control. </s><s n="s3.3;p27.101">After carefully planning and hard working, the huge money we make may become less worthy than a piece of paper due to unexpected inflation. </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p28.101"><s n="s1.3;p28.101">Government police changing. </s><s n="s2.3;p28.101">With the replacement of officials, regulations about financial may also be changed. </s><s n="s3.3;p28.101">With the regulations changing, big amount of profit might go for offset. </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p29.101"><s n="s1.4;p29.101">Exchanging rate. </s><s n="s2.4;p29.101">It is more than like stock. </s><s n="s3.4;p29.101">The value of currency fluctuates every second, £Aztecs is not an exception. </s><s n="s4.4;p29.101">The more money stays in Amazonia, the more un-prediction it is. </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p30.101"><s n="s1.5;p30.101">Potential conflict between two countries. </s><s n="s2.5;p30.101">The world never have a moment of peace. </s><s n="s3.5;p30.101">Although the current diplomatic policy among two countries is friendly enough, but nobody know what would happen tomorrow. </s><s n="s4.5;p30.101">Possibly, for diplomatic reasons, Amazonia government might freeze funds from HC's JVC share profits. </s><s n="s5.5;p30.101">What can HC do then? </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p31.101"><s n="s1.2;p31.101">Extra transfer fees arise for bank crossing and country crossing. </s><s n="s2.2;p31.101">It is obviously there would be an extra price to pay for the transferring fees among different banks and countries. </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p32.101"><s n="s1.3;p32.101">Time delay. </s><s n="s2.3;p32.101">As the saying goes, 'Time is money'. </s><s n="s3.3;p32.101">The earlier HC bring money into its own account, the better for its capital flow and enlarging plan. </s></p></div3><div3><head rend="bold italic">2.2.2Direct sales from HC:</head><p n="p33.101"><s n="s1.1;p33.101">Sales come from HC exports units to customers: </s></p><p n="p34.101"><s n="s1.1;p34.101">Customer: 0% of total profit </s></p><p n="p35.101"><s n="s1.1;p35.101">Partner: 31.2% of total profit </s></p><p n="p36.101"><s n="s1.1;p36.101">Meantime, sales come from HC selling components to JVC: </s></p><p n="p37.101"><s n="s1.1;p37.101">Customer: 27.1% </s></p><p n="p38.101"><s n="s1.1;p38.101">Partner: 10.9% </s></p><p n="p39.101"><s n="s1.1;p39.101">Plus two together, we conclude that the 'forward' profit for HC is: </s></p><p n="p40.101"><s n="s1.1;p40.101">Customer: 27.1% </s></p><p n="p41.101"><s n="s1.1;p41.101">Partner: 42.1% </s></p><p n="p42.101"><s n="s1.3;p42.101">The partner type could make one and a half times of 'forward' profits compareing with the customer type. </s><s n="s2.3;p42.101">It means that with the same amount of total profit, comparing the two, partner type could bring 1.5 times more money directly into its own bank account in Switzerland. </s><s n="s3.3;p42.101">What lovely money it is! </s></p></div3><div3><head rend="bold italic">2.2.3JVC equity:</head><p n="p43.101"><s n="s1.1;p43.101">Customer: HC share 35% </s></p><p n="p44.101"><s n="s1.1;p44.101">Partner: HC share 49% </s></p><p n="p45.101"><s n="s1.6;p45.101">What is HC's motivation for the collaboration with CNI? </s><s n="s2.6;p45.101">Only the figures from the literal bank account? considering about the long-term development of the company, HC has to transfer all its final assembly and test operation to low-cost area which means the current considering subject - Amazonia. </s><s n="s3.6;p45.101">In this sense, HC hope to share as much as it can on equity in the collaboration relationship. </s><s n="s4.6;p45.101">100% is the best choice if it is possible. </s><s n="s5.6;p45.101">But with the regulation of Amazonia government, 49% is the maximum limit for foreign company. </s><s n="s6.6;p45.101">So, HC could get 49% in partner type means it reaches the golden point. </s></p></div3><div3><head rend="bold italic">2.2.4Product price:</head><p n="p46.101"><s n="s1.1;p46.101">HC's perspective: </s></p><p n="p47.101"><s n="s1.1;p47.101">Customer: JVC export price at £250,000. (£sterling) </s></p><p n="p48.101"><s n="s1.1;p48.101">Partner: HC get price at £222,000 from JVC and then sell at £250,000 to customers. </s></p><p n="p49.101"><s n="s1.4;p49.101">HC get the same final price to customers in different approaches which indicate opportunity and flexibility for HC. For the customer type, price to customer is simple and put on the table. </s><s n="s2.4;p49.101">For the partner type, HC get a low price at £222,000 from JVC and predict to sell at £250,000 by negotiate with CNI. But once HC received the equipments and paid to JVC the price at £222,000, how much will it sell is totally depends on itself. </s><s n="s3.4;p49.101">It means that HC has entirely right to adjust price to its customer. </s><s n="s4.4;p49.101">The extra flexibility on price could probably increase HC's profits and attract more orders from other areas. </s></p><p n="p50.101"><s n="s1.1;p50.101">CNI's perspective: </s></p><p n="p51.101"><s n="s1.1;p51.101">Customer: JVC sales to Government at £275,000 </s></p><p n="p52.101"><s n="s1.1;p52.101">Partner: CNI get very competitive price from JVC at £215,000 and sells to government at £275,000. </s></p><p n="p53.101"><s n="s1.4;p53.101">£60,000 profit would be gained for CNI simply from this one aspect exclusive of the share profit from JVC. Why not CNI be happy with this proposal? </s><s n="s2.4;p53.101">CNI make a big profit here while HC have not lost any profit. </s><s n="s3.4;p53.101">What kind of win-win game it is. </s><s n="s4.4;p53.101">And HC can also make up on other aspects because CNI would feel responsible to accept those. </s></p></div3><div3><head rend="bold italic">2.2.5Royalty:</head><p n="p54.101"><s n="s1.1;p54.101">Customer: 4.5% </s></p><p n="p55.101"><s n="s1.1;p55.101">Partner: 5.5% </s></p><p n="p56.101"><s n="s1.1;p56.101">Obviously, HC could take more royalty from JVC in partner type. </s></p></div3><div3><head rend="bold italic">2.2.6Rent of premises:</head><p n="p57.101"><s n="s1.1;p57.101">Customer: £95,000 </s></p><p n="p58.101"><s n="s1.1;p58.101">Partner: £90,000 </s></p><p n="p59.101"><s n="s1.1;p59.101">Although the difference is not too much significant, HC could still pay less £5,000 to CNI at this point. </s></p><p n="p60.101"><s n="s1.1;p60.101">All in all, choosing JVC which supplies to partners only is the best choice for HC's perspective. </s></p></div3></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">3.CONTRACT ISSUES:</head><div2><head rend="underlined">3.1 Technical aspect:</head><div3><head rend="bold italic">3.1.1 Quality warranty of local material:</head><p n="p61.101"><s n="s1.4;p61.101">According to the contract, CNI would provide 36 percent of raw materials. </s><s n="s2.4;p61.101">The important thing is we need to make a quality standard to measure the level of materials which they provide. </s><s n="s3.4;p61.101">Also, the process of choosing suppliers needed be under monitor by HC. Because there might be the case is they choose the suppliers which they have close relationship with but low quality goods. </s><s n="s4.4;p61.101">They could benefit from the low prices by the material, but the quality of our final products can hard be guarantied. </s></p></div3><div3><head rend="bold italic">3.1.2 Training:</head><p n="p62.101"><s n="s1.3;p62.101">We will transfer some of our skilful employers from Switzerland to Amazonia. </s><s n="s2.3;p62.101">Meanwhile, we provide entirely training courses for the local employers in Amazonia. </s><s n="s3.3;p62.101">JVC should pay all the training fees to HC, and relative employers' wages. </s></p></div3><div3><head rend="bold italic">3.1.3 Technology fees:</head><p n="p63.101"><s n="s1.1;p63.101">As the figures says in table3, HC could get 5.5 percentage royalty from JVC. </s></p></div3></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">3.2 Commercial aspects:</head><p n="p64.101"><s n="s1.2;p64.101">Based on we only got 49 percent of equity, which means HC owns minority share in JVC, we cannot rely on voting to make any significant decisions. </s><s n="s2.2;p64.101">Instead, the decisions of the board of directors of the company and also its shareholders will be by mutual consent of the parties in the following cases: </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p65.101"><s n="s1.1;p65.101">Decisions on new undertakings, and partnership or shareholdings with any other party; </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p66.101"><s n="s1.1;p66.101">Decisions on increase of capital, issue of new shares or classification thereof, conclusion of financial agreements or loans, changes between the partners, substitutions and/or assignments; </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p67.101"><s n="s1.1;p67.101">Introduction of new business activities; </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p68.101"><s n="s1.1;p68.101">Sale, purchase, mortgaging or charging of real property above £X million; </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p69.101"><s n="s1.1;p69.101">Incurring individual liabilities in excess of £X million; </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p70.101"><s n="s1.1;p70.101">Entry into purchase agreements with a term in excess of 18 months; </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p71.101"><s n="s1.1;p71.101">Guaranteeing third party obligations over £X million in any one case; </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p72.101"><s n="s1.1;p72.101">The policy on dividend payments; </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p73.101"><s n="s1.1;p73.101">The company's ex-works sale price of products and parts and other matters relating to profit planning. </s></p><p n="p74.101"><s n="s1.1;p74.101">All £X figures need to be negotiated with both sides. </s></p><p n="p75.101"><s n="s1.1;p75.101">Other commercial issues also need to be considered: </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p76.101"><s n="s1.3;p76.101">Warranties of products. </s><s n="s2.3;p76.101">HC combines with CNI make the standards of the components and final product at the beginning of our collaboration. </s><s n="s3.3;p76.101">If the product we received is below the acceptance level, we would have right to return it and JVC pay all the costs and relative delays penalties to our customers. </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p77.101"><s n="s1.2;p77.101">Offsets: in the first five years, based on Amazonia Government's "foreign exchange neutral" police, HC still could have priority to receive products. </s><s n="s2.2;p77.101">But after five years, who has the priority should be negociated. </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p78.101"><s n="s1.1;p78.101">Markets: CNI could only sale to Amazonia market, while HC could sale to the other parts of the world except Amazonia. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">3.3 Legal aspects:</head><div3><head rend="bold italic">3.3.1 IPR:</head><p rend="bulleted" n="p79.101"><s n="s1.2;p79.101">HC owns the patents of the product. </s><s n="s2.2;p79.101">Without permission from HC, JVC or CNI do not have right to reveal the procedure of manufacturing to others. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p80.101"><s n="s1.1;p80.101">Confidential information: each part has the responsibility to prevent opponents stealing our confidential information. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p81.101"><s n="s1.1;p81.101">Trade marks: each side keep on using its own brand. </s></p></div3></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">3.4 Other aspects:</head><p rend="ordered" n="p82.101"><s n="s1.3;p82.101">Termination: ten years. </s><s n="s2.3;p82.101">During this period, each partner want to quit, it has to pay considerable amount of penalty to the other one. </s><s n="s3.3;p82.101">But if the external environment changed, and both sides feel the necessity to make any change in contract, negotiation could be issued. </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p83.101"><s n="s1.2;p83.101">Language: only English could be used as communication language. </s><s n="s2.2;p83.101">But concerning about the English level of each company's officer, contract could have an additional local language version. </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p84.101"><s n="s1.1;p84.101">Law: We both obey the Amazonia's law and the international law. </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p85.101"><s n="s1.1;p85.101">Taxation: only one tax policy. </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p86.101"><s n="s1.1;p86.101">Currency: £Sterling </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p87.101"><s n="s1.1;p87.101">Place of delivery: FOB </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">4.OPERATIONAL PLANNING:</head><div2><head rend="underlined">4.1 Organizing and networking:</head><p n="p88.101"><s n="s1.3;p88.101">HC could be responsible for supplying production machinery, supervising the manufacturing and arranging exports. </s><s n="s2.3;p88.101">CNI should be responsible for worker management and domestic sales. </s><s n="s3.3;p88.101">The position of general manager should be allocated to HC and the position of deputy general manager be allocated to CNI. To sustain the continuity in individual departments, the position of departmental chief could be allocated to CNI and that of the deputy chief be offered to HC. At the senior level of management, the joint venture should have 15 people from HC, and 35 from CNI. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">4.2 Management obligations &amp; responsibilities</head><div3><head rend="bold italic">4.2.1 HR: globalization or localization</head><p n="p89.101"><s n="s1.2;p89.101">Cross-national and cross-cultural diversity may add complexities to strategic conflict and IJVs are seen as operations where "interests do not fully overlap and are often in conflict" (Peng and Shenkar, 2002:92). </s><s n="s2.2;p89.101">In particular, IJVs are a forum where stakeholders may disagree about whether the IJV should adopt localized practices reflecting the host country(localization) or emulate an international parent's globalization or standardization(Pucik, 1985). </s></p><p n="p90.101"><s n="s1.2;p90.101">From the perspective of the "globalization", the joint venture is an extension of HC and our HRM operations. </s><s n="s2.2;p90.101">Followings are assumptions about adopting "globalization": </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p91.101"><s n="s1.1;p91.101">Our current MNE HRM practices are clearly superior to CNI's </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p92.101"><s n="s1.2;p92.101">We could hold a significant advantage in IJV industry and particularly in international sector. </s><s n="s2.2;p92.101">We could dominate the partnership regardless of equity and can control many or all management decisions. </s></p><p n="p93.101"><s n="s1.4;p93.101">These assumptions will tend to be "drivers" in the strategic actions. </s><s n="s2.4;p93.101">But in the IJV environment, disagreements between two partners may arise. </s><s n="s3.4;p93.101">Diversity in strategy and beliefs often result in "conflicting voices" which increase with cultural heterogeneity(Hoskisson et,al, 2002). </s><s n="s4.4;p93.101">In contrast to the standarsization, there are many advantages with localization: </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p94.101"><s n="s1.2;p94.101">Local HRM practices are much easier to work in the local environment because of cultural and philosophical differences. </s><s n="s2.2;p94.101">And they have better </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p95.101"><s n="s1.1;p95.101">knowledge about local constraints. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p96.101"><s n="s1.1;p96.101">The ability of local managers to control access to the labour market and product distribution channels, expertise and information may effectively stymie standardization efforts - either directly or indirectly. </s></p><p n="p97.101"><s n="s1.2;p97.101">All in all, globalization practices are much more favorable for HC in the short-term. </s><s n="s2.2;p97.101">But concerning about our long-term planning in Amazonia , we would better choose localization which is also more acceptable for CNI. </s></p></div3><div3><head rend="bold italic">4.2.2 Production；</head><p n="p98.101"><s n="s1.11;p98.101">In the next five years, we would remove CNI's current old and slow machines, and build up new advanced machines in their factory. </s><s n="s2.11;p98.101">Five years later, with the increasing demand of equipments, we could buy a new factory in Amazonia. </s><s n="s3.11;p98.101">Location of new factory need be researched and negotiated later. </s><s n="s4.11;p98.101">HC provide all the fast and advanced machines and relevant know-how skilled employees. </s><s n="s5.11;p98.101">Meanwhile, HC could continue its new product development in Switzerland. </s><s n="s6.11;p98.101">CNI has the responsibility to order 36 percent of raw material in Amazonia. </s><s n="s7.11;p98.101">And they should better develop their suppliers to provide just-in-time delivery. </s><s n="s8.11;p98.101">HC provides 64 percent of raw material and components. </s><s n="s9.11;p98.101">All of them need to be shipped from Switzerland to Amazonia. </s><s n="s10.11;p98.101">Time management would be crucial in this process. </s><s n="s11.11;p98.101">Communication and contacting with production line would be significant to smooth this step. </s></p></div3><div3><head rend="bold italic">4.2.3 Quality:</head><p n="p99.101"><s n="s1.2;p99.101">Many organizations have started outsourcing parts of their production processes to outside companies. </s><s n="s2.2;p99.101">Maintaining quality and conformity in these outsourced processes, however, isn't always easy(Zuckerman, 2005). </s></p><p n="p100.101"><s n="s1.4;p100.101">According to contract, HC makeup takes up eight percent of Total Cost. </s><s n="s2.4;p100.101">If we want to guarantee quality of final product, first thing which we need to do is making sure the eight percent makeup is core competency. </s><s n="s3.4;p100.101">We could focus on conforming assessment or product testing, and introduce total quality management(TQM) principles. </s><s n="s4.4;p100.101">Moreover, factory must pass social compliance audits to ensure that employees are treated fairly. </s></p></div3></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">CONCLUSION</head><p n="p101.101"><s n="s1.1;p101.101">Based on the analysis which mentioned above, it is not hard to conclude that, with the building up of new Joint Venture Company with CNI, and carefully planning, HC would undoubtedly have a brilliant future and more sound effects on the worldwide markets. </s></p></div1></body><back><div1 type="bibliography"><head rend="bold">REFERENCE:</head><p>Chen, S. &amp; Wilson, M. (2003). "Standardization and Localization of Human Resource Management in Sino-Foreign Joint Ventures". <hi rend="italic">Asia Pacific Journal of Management,</hi> 20,397-408.</p><p>Hoskisson, Robert, Michael Hitt, Richard Johnson, and Wayne Grossman.(2002). "Conflicting Voices: The Effects of Institutional Ownership heterogeneity and Internal Governance on Corporate Innovation Strategies." <hi rend="italic">Academy of Management Journal</hi> 45(4), 697-716</p><p>Peng, Mick W. and Oded Shankar. (2002). "Joint Venture Dissolution as Corporate Divorce." <hi rend="italic">Academy of Management Executive</hi> 16(2), 92-105</p><p>Pucik, Vladimir. (1985). "Strategic Human Resource Management in a Multinational Firm." In Heidi Vernon-Wortzel and Lwarence Wortzel (eds.), <hi rend="italic">Strategic Management of Multinational Corporations: The Essentials.</hi> New York: John Wiley.</p><p>Zuckerman, A. (2005). "Managing Quality in a Global Economy." <seg type="URL" n="http://www.qualitydigest.com/currentmag/articles/01_article.shtml"/></p></div1><div1 type="appendix"><head rend="bold">APPENDIX</head><p/></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
