<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_0225c" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Explain the importance of: HEDLEY BYRNE AND CO V HELLER AND PARTNERS LTD 1964 AC 465 in the development of the law of negligence. In your answer you should also use this to explain and illustrate how common law is created through the use of judicial precedent.</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">deleted: header: module name and number, student name; footer: page numbers</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">1</p><p n="date">2005-04</p><p n="module title">Introduction to Business Law</p><p n="module code">IB1100</p><p n="genre family">Explanation</p><p n="discipline">Business</p><p n="disciplinary group">SS</p><p n="grade">D</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">1319</p><p n="number of s-units">54</p><p n="number of p">10</p><p n="number of tables">0</p><p n="number of figures">0</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">0</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">0</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">24.4</p><p n="average s-units per p">5.4</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">f</p><p n="year of birth">1986</p><p n="first language">Spanish</p><p n="education">UKA</p><p n="course">Management Science</p><p n="student ID">0225</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><docTitle><titlePart><hi rend="bold">Explain the importance of:</hi><hi rend="italic"> HEDLEY BYRNE AND CO V HELLER AND PARTNERS LTD 1964 AC 465</hi><hi rend="bold"> in the development of the law of negligence. In your answer you should also use this to explain and illustrate how common law is created through the use of judicial precedent.</hi> </titlePart></docTitle></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="section"><p n="p1.10"><s n="s1.6;p1.10">The Hedley Byrne V Heller<ref target="BAWE_0225c-ftnote.001"/> case falls into the law of negligence within that of tort, claiming compensation for an economic loss as a consequence of a negligent statement. </s><s n="s2.6;p1.10">The case judge, McNair J held that the defendants were careless but that a duty of care was not owed. </s><s n="s3.6;p1.10">In the Court of Appeal the judgment was agreed on the same grounds and in the House of Lords it was likewise avowed yet on different grounds. </s><s n="s4.6;p1.10">A claim under negligence will be successful if it can be proven that a duty of care is owed and was breached causing damages. </s><s n="s5.6;p1.10">The fact this case reached the most Supreme Court in the English hierarchy of courts and that it created a new precedent, highlights its impact on the development of the law of negligence, in particular in cases were proximity between parties is not of contractual or fiduciary nature but akin to it. </s><s n="s6.6;p1.10">The use of judicial precedent in the creation of the common law shall be explored and a balanced critique of it shall be put forward. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0225c-ftnote.001"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Hedley Byrne and Co V Heller and Partners Ltd [1964] AC 465; [1963] 3 WLR 100; [1963] 2 All ER 575, HL </s></p></note><p n="p2.10"><s n="s1.4;p2.10">The claimants, Hedley Byrne &amp; Co, advertising agents, were approached by a client, Easipower and a contract of £100,000 annual payments on credit was settled. </s><s n="s2.4;p2.10">However before signing the contract, Hedley Byrne &amp; Co unsure about Easipower´s creditworthiness asked its bank, National Provincial Bank Ltd, for a reference regarding Easipower`s credit disposition. </s><s n="s3.4;p2.10">The bank contacted Easipower´s bank, Heller and Partners, the defendants, who agreed to provide a gratuitous reference free from any responsibility. </s><s n="s4.4;p2.10">The reference was a positive one and Hedley Byrne signed the contract, but soon lost £17,000 when Easipower went into liquidation. </s></p><p n="p3.10"><s n="s1.4;p3.10">The <hi rend="italic">Donaghue V Stevenson</hi> case in 1932 gave rise to the modern law of negligence and established the `neighbour test´ to measure legal proximity<ref target="BAWE_0225c-ftnote.002"/>. </s><s n="s2.4;p3.10">The effects of negligent statements are far more reaching and easier to commit than that of actions. </s><s n="s3.4;p3.10">They may create liability for a large amount of unidentifiable people over an indefinite time period. </s><s n="s4.4;p3.10">Hence following <hi rend="italic">Caparo V Dickman</hi> (1990), the `neighbour test´ was replaced by the three-stage approach to decide whether a duty of care was owed. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0225c-ftnote.002"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">If the claimant could prove he was a neighbour and that the harm suffered was reasonably foreseeable to be a result of the negligent acts of the defendant, then he/she was owed a duty of care </s></p></note><p n="p4.10"><s n="s1.6;p4.10">The first stage identifies whether the defendant would have reasonably foreseen that the claimant would rely on his words and voluntarily assumed responsibility for them. </s><s n="s2.6;p4.10">Although the defendant had the professional ability to provide reliable advice and that the it was provided in a professional environment, the fact that Heller and Partners Ltd choose to place a disclaimer demonstrated that the defendant did not voluntarily assume responsibility<ref target="BAWE_0225c-ftnote.003"/>. </s><s n="s3.6;p4.10">In addition the defendant must know for what purposes his/her services are required, for whom they are required and that the listener will act upon them without any further clarification. </s><s n="s4.6;p4.10">Although Heller and partners new that an advertising agent, client of the National Provincial Bank, inquired the reference, they did not know for what purpose and if it would be solely relied upon. </s><s n="s5.6;p4.10">The claimants should have considered the bank's conflicting position before relying entirely on the reference.<ref target="BAWE_0225c-ftnote.004"/> The enquiry was a quick free of charge check on Easipower´s credit potential rather than a detailed and considered advise on the matter. </s><s n="s6.6;p4.10">It is difficult to impose Heller &amp; Partners with more duty than that of being honest.<ref target="BAWE_0225c-ftnote.005"/> Given that there was no contract this disclaimer could have only served to exclude the defendants from liability for negligence. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0225c-ftnote.003"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.5;pn1.1">In the words of Lord Pearce: "<hi rend="italic">words give no immunity to a negligent answer.</hi> </s><s rend="italic" n="s2.5;pn1.1">But in any event they clearly prevent a special relationship from arising... </s><s n="s3.5;pn1.1"><hi rend="italic">If [a] part[y] say[s] expressively that there shall be no liability, I do not find it possible to say that a liability was assumed</hi>". Kidner, Richard. </s><s n="s4.5;pn1.1"><hi rend="underlined">Casebook on Torts</hi>. </s><s n="s5.5;pn1.1">(Oxford: Oxford University Press, 2004) 137. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0225c-ftnote.004"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">between being dutiful to its customer but at the same providing a fair response to the enquiry. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0225c-ftnote.005"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">especially when the reply was gratuitous and accompanied with a disclaimer of responsibility. </s></p></note><p n="p5.10"><s n="s1.4;p5.10">For a duty of care to be owed a close relationship between the parties must exist (second stage approach). </s><s n="s2.4;p5.10">In the present case as the relationship was created ad hoc it is not clearly equivalent to that of a contract. </s><s n="s3.4;p5.10">Mere hearing or reading of statements is not sufficient to create a close proximity as this would put no limits to being liable for what one says or writes. </s><s n="s4.4;p5.10">Consequently, the last stage-approach, whether it is just, fair and reasonable to impose a duty of care would also fail<ref target="BAWE_0225c-ftnote.006"/>. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0225c-ftnote.006"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.3;pn1.1">As the courts held that the harm was not reasonably foreseeable, given that responsibility was not undertaken on the part of the defendant and that a close relationship was not observable, the claim must fail under this criterion. </s><s n="s2.3;pn1.1">This is why Lord Goff states that cases similar to the present have no need to be assessed against this criterion. </s><s n="s3.3;pn1.1">Given that no duty of care was owed, breach of duty and damages cannot be discussed. </s></p></note><p n="p6.10"><s n="s1.4;p6.10">Liability for negligent statements or services which cause economic loss has for the most part been restricted and economic loss is rarely protected. </s><s n="s2.4;p6.10">Following <hi rend="italic">Hedley Byrne V Heller</hi> it was determined that in the absence of a contractual or fiduciary relationship, a `special relationship´ entailing an assumption of responsibility resembling that of a contract would establish a duty of care. </s><s n="s3.4;p6.10">Consequently, the possibility of claiming for consequential (not pure) economic loss as a result of a negligent misstatement was first was recognised. </s><s n="s4.4;p6.10">The impact of this case in the development of the law of negligence illustrates how common law is created through the use of judicial precedent. </s></p><p n="p7.10"><s n="s1.8;p7.10">The conducts and decisions taken in previous cases have served as a guideline for future application since the Norman Rule of England. </s><s n="s2.8;p7.10">The judges travelled around the country deciding major cases some of which were based on common customs. </s><s n="s3.8;p7.10">This unified the law and made it common to all. </s><s n="s4.8;p7.10">Common law was hence developed from customs and judicial decisions.<ref target="BAWE_0225c-ftnote.007"/> Judges use precedents<ref target="BAWE_0225c-ftnote.008"/>, in forming decisions for similar cases. </s><s n="s5.8;p7.10">The <hi rend="italic"> ratio decidendi</hi>, is binding on any other similar cases whilst the <hi rend="italic">obiter dicta</hi><ref target="BAWE_0225c-ftnote.009"/>, are only persuasive. </s><s n="s6.8;p7.10">Other persuasive precedents include dissenting judgements, decisions taken by lower courts, the Privy Council and by Commonwealth countries<ref target="BAWE_0225c-ftnote.010"/>. </s><s n="s7.8;p7.10">The decisions of superior courts are binding to their immediate lower court. </s><s n="s8.8;p7.10">The decisions of the European Court of Justice (EJC) are binding on all British Courts; likewise the decisions of the House of Lords are binding on all the inferior courts. <ref target="BAWE_0225c-ftnote.011"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0225c-ftnote.007"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">It was not until the 19th century, after the Council of Law Reporting and the hierarchy of courts was established that judicial consistency in decision making developed into the more solid system found today. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0225c-ftnote.008"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.3;pn1.1">A previous decision of a court. </s><s n="s2.3;pn1.1">Although parliament is becoming more involved in the creation of statutes, most law making is still judge based. </s><s n="s3.3;pn1.1">When there is no precedent for a case, the decision will form a new precedent. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0225c-ftnote.009"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1"><hi rend="italic">Ratio decidenci</hi> refer to the reasons for a decision whilst <hi rend="italic">obiter dicta</hi> are additional comments. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0225c-ftnote.010"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">For example, the law on remoteness of damages was derived from the Privy Council's decision on the Australian case <hi rend="italic">The Wagon Mound</hi> (1961). </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0225c-ftnote.011"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.4;pn1.1">In 1966 Lord Chancellor announced that the House of Lords would no longer be bound by its own precedents, in response to the failure of the law to amend unsatisfactory decisions (which could have otherwise solely been changed through new legislation) and to keep up with the rapid social changing environment. </s><s n="s2.4;pn1.1">The Court of Appeal may divert from binding precedent in specific situations, also, its Criminal Division, is more flexible where the subject's liberty is at stake. </s><s n="s3.4;pn1.1">The decisions of the Civil division of the Court of Appeal are binding by the Divisional Court which in turn is bound by the High Court; those of the Criminal Division are bound by the Queen's Bench Divisional Court, which in turn is bound by the Crown Court. </s><s n="s4.4;pn1.1">The lowest courts the County Court (civil law) and the Magistrates Court (criminal law) are bound by the High Court and the Crown Court respectively. </s></p></note><p n="p8.10"><s n="s1.4;p8.10">Precedent is used to create new law (original precedent) and to extend old principles. </s><s n="s2.4;p8.10">The rules that govern the formation of contracts owe their existence to judicial precedent. </s><s n="s3.4;p8.10">Similarly, the law of negligence has been refined by judicial law making, beginning with the aforementioned `neighbour test´ and now extended to include cases on liability for economic loss and nervous shock. </s><s n="s4.4;p8.10">As regards criminal law, judges have played a vital role in the development of the law of intention. </s></p><p n="p9.10"><s n="s1.9;p9.10">The certainty attached to judicial precedent helps lawyers advise their clients on the likely outcome of cases. </s><s n="s2.9;p9.10">It is also a consistent, fair and precise system where all cases are treated similarly with slight variations in the facts, saving time in cases where facts are similar. </s><s n="s3.9;p9.10">Nonetheless it is also true that if a case is unjustly or wrongly decided the decision will persist, until someone has the funding, time and perseverance to appeal to the House of Lords where it is thereupon considered<ref target="BAWE_0225c-ftnote.012"/>. </s><s n="s4.9;p9.10">Given that the Court of Appeal has to follow its own past decisions makes the system rigid and slowly progressing. </s><s n="s5.9;p9.10">However this inflexibility is lessened by the ability to distinguish cases<ref target="BAWE_0225c-ftnote.013"/> contributing to the detailed set of case rules that characterises common law. </s><s n="s6.9;p9.10">Yet given the vast collection of cases, distinguishing a case to avoid its past decisions may be unfounded. </s><s n="s7.9;p9.10">Searching for similar cases, even with the aid of databases, has become a complex task and precedents may be overlooked. </s><s n="s8.9;p9.10">In addition the lengthy judgments complicate the extraction of the <hi rend="italic">ratio decidendi</hi>. </s><s n="s9.9;p9.10">Judicial precedent is also criticised for creating law only when a need arises as a dog is disciplined once he has misbehaved and for the fact that a tight majority does not make the precedent any less valuable. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0225c-ftnote.012"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Only the House of Lords may overrule but few cases reach it, all appellate courts may reverse the decision within the same case. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0225c-ftnote.013"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">When there is material difference in the facts between the present case and the previous precedent. </s></p></note><p n="p10.10"><s n="s1.5;p10.10">The Hedley Byrne V Heller case gives an illustration of how the three-stage approach is applied to the facts in the law of negligence. </s><s n="s2.5;p10.10">In reaching the House of Lords, the case demonstrates the difficulties in establishing liability for economic loss. </s><s n="s3.5;p10.10">It has significantly contributed to the development of the law of negligence as it has created a new precedent, the need to prove a `special relationship´ between those in question in the absence of a contract. </s><s n="s4.5;p10.10">Besides disproving the epithet "dogs´s law", as the claim was dismissed on grounds unrelated to the established precedent, the case also illustrates the rigidity of the court system. </s><s n="s5.5;p10.10">The high degree of communication in the world of today will demand a considerable evolvement in the liability for negligent misstatements. </s></p></div1></body><back><div1 type="bibliography"><head rend="bold">Bibliography</head><p>Adams, Alix. <hi rend="underlined">Law for Business Students.</hi> Harlow: Pearson Education Limited, 2000.</p><p>Hepple, Howarth &amp; Martin Matthews. <hi rend="underlined">Tort: Cases &amp; Materials.</hi> London: Butterworths, 2000.</p><p>Keenan, Denis. <hi rend="underlined">English Law</hi>. Harlow: Pearson Education Limited. 2001.</p><p>Keenan &amp; Riches, Sarah. <hi rend="underlined">Business Law</hi>. Harlow: Pearson Education Limited, 2005.</p><p>Kidner, Richard. <hi rend="underlined">Casebook on Torts</hi>. Oxford: Oxford University Press, 2004.</p><p>Martin, Jacqueline. <hi rend="underlined">AQA Law for AS.</hi> London: Hodder &amp; Stoughton, 2002.</p><p>Weir, Tony. <hi rend="underlined">A Casebook on Tort</hi>. London: Sweet and Maxwell Limited. 2004.</p></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
