<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_0227c" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Marketing Exercise Report</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">The document has a title page which contains:
document title
title part</note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">deleted: header: assignment name; footer: page and student numbers</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">1</p><p n="date">2006-03</p><p n="module title">Marketing Industry Exercise</p><p n="module code">ES175</p><p n="genre family">Critique</p><p n="discipline">Engineering</p><p n="disciplinary group">PS</p><p n="grade">M</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">1316</p><p n="number of s-units">76</p><p n="number of p">19</p><p n="number of tables">2</p><p n="number of figures">2</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">0</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">0</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">17.3</p><p n="average s-units per p">4.0</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">m</p><p n="year of birth">1987</p><p n="first language">Sinhala</p><p n="education">OSA</p><p n="course">General Engineering</p><p n="student ID">0227</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><docTitle><titlePart rend="underlined bold">The Midlands Metro</titlePart></docTitle><titlePart>Marketing/Industry Exercise Report ES 175</titlePart><titlePart><name type="student ID"/><name type="student name"/></titlePart><titlePart><hi rend="underlined bold">Marketing Exercise Report</hi><hi rend="bold"> The Midlands Metro</hi></titlePart></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Overview of the company</head><p n="p1.19"><s n="s1.6;p1.19">The metro was the United Kingdom's first street operational light rail system which brought a new concept of public transport among people. </s><s n="s2.6;p1.19">Birmingham's commuters now use public transport to travel as opposed to their car each morning. </s><s n="s3.6;p1.19">One in five journeys are by train and a growing number are now using the Midland Metro. </s><s n="s4.6;p1.19">More than 1200 commuters arrive by tram at Snow Hill Station each morning during the peak time. </s><s n="s5.6;p1.19">Therefore they have increased the service from a tram every eight minutes to one every six minutes to help provide a more efficient service to the customers. </s><s n="s6.6;p1.19">Metro reliability for the past two years has consistently exceeded 98%. </s></p><p n="p2.19"><s n="s1.3;p2.19">Midland Metro is a transportation company one of the first in the UK. It runs between Birmingham and Wolverhampton so more people in the West Midlands can benefit from such a reliable and frequent mode of transport. </s><s n="s2.3;p2.19">It is a part of National Express Group and they pay wages to the Travel West Midlands bus drivers. </s><s n="s3.3;p2.19">The company is doing a service to the community as opposed to operating for profit. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Details about the trams</head><p n="p3.19"><s n="s1.7;p3.19">The company owns 16 vehicles. </s><s n="s2.7;p3.19">They have 23 stops. </s><s n="s3.7;p3.19">Each tram is 25m long 3.6m high and 2.4m wide. </s><s n="s4.7;p3.19">They travel all seven days of the week starting from 6 in the morning to late in the night. </s><s n="s5.7;p3.19">The company developed machines to do the ticketing in the tram instead of having conductors, reducing the wage paid to employees. </s><s n="s6.7;p3.19">Since the machines were not able to give the customers change, the company had to get the conductors to carry on with the job. </s><s n="s7.7;p3.19">The trams are washed everyday when they come back in the night to the station, where the bus driver just drives through while it gets washed and parks it until it's taken out in the morning again. </s></p><p n="p4.19"><s n="s1.4;p4.19">Each tram holds 52 people seated and 108 people standing. </s><s n="s2.4;p4.19">200 is the maximum capacity. </s><s n="s3.4;p4.19">The company started off with a staff of 100 and now has a staff of 253, there are 43 bus drivers and 43 conductors. </s><s n="s4.4;p4.19">The company has part time conductors as well. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Structure of the industry</head><p n="p5.19"><s n="s1.6;p5.19">The industry for local rail based transport is in its maturity and can be classified as a question mark. </s><s n="s2.6;p5.19">Metro transport is still in the early stages of development. </s><s n="s3.6;p5.19">Its target market is relatively small with each company averaging turnover of approx 4.927 million in 2004. </s><s n="s4.6;p5.19">Large amount of investment will be required to develop the networks so that it can compete with buses and trains. </s><s n="s5.6;p5.19">Currently the industry's position on the spectrum of competition is an oligopoly. </s><s n="s6.6;p5.19">There are 10 firms competing with each other with 63.1% of sales in 2004 made by the top 5 firms. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Typical conduct of firms in industry</head><p n="p6.19"><s n="s1.6;p6.19">Firms compete strongly on price. </s><s n="s2.6;p6.19">There is evidence of predatory price competition. </s><s n="s3.6;p6.19">GE CAPITAL RAIL SERVICES LIMITED has made a 30.73% profit margin whilst Midland Metro's profit margin was -17.94% in 2004. </s><s n="s4.6;p6.19">Demand is relatively price inelastic for metro as it is a unique form of transport on local routes in large cities. </s><s n="s5.6;p6.19">So even if the price is increased people will still continue using the service. </s><s n="s6.6;p6.19">Since each company operates different local routes there may be evidence of collusion: market sharing agreements. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Turnover of the company during the past years </head><p n="p7.19"><s n="s1.3;p7.19">Midland Metro's turnover has grown rapidly with an average year on year increase of 61.5% between 1999 and 2004. </s><s n="s2.3;p7.19">The company is unprofitable however and running at a substantial loss (see later). </s><s n="s3.3;p7.19">The table below shows the turnover. </s></p><table id="BAWE_0227c-tab.001"><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p8.19"><s n="s1.1;p8.19">Source (<seg type="URL" n="http://fame.bvdep.com/cgi/template.dll?product=1&amp;user=ipaddress"/>) </s></p><p n="p9.19"><s n="s1.2;p9.19">The rapid growth in turnover is clearly displayed by the bar chart shown below. </s><s n="s2.2;p9.19">The most marked increase was 185% between 1999 and 2000. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0227c-fig.001"><head rend="bold">Turnover</head></figure><table id="BAWE_0227c-tab.002"><head rend="bold">Profit loss of the company before taxation in the company during the past years</head><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p10.19"><s n="s1.1;p10.19">Source (<seg type="URL" n="http://fame.bvdep.com/cgi/template.dll?product=1&amp;user=ipaddress"/>) </s></p><p n="p11.19"><s n="s1.1;p11.19">The bar chart drawn below illustrates the data tabulated above: </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0227c-fig.002"/><p n="p12.19"><s n="s1.8;p12.19">By analyzing the graph we can clearly see that the company is not clearly profitable and running at a substantial loss. </s><s n="s2.8;p12.19">In 2001 Midland Metro evidently struggled with direct cost and indirect expense control as their loss increased over 3.5 times the previous year. </s><s n="s3.8;p12.19">The situation has substantially improved between 2002 and 2004 with the loss falling at an average rate of £3.5 million per year. </s><s n="s4.8;p12.19">It is worthwhile for an entrepreneur to invest in the company rather than trying to start a new company. </s><s n="s5.8;p12.19">Initial sunk costs tend to be very high and the turnover data suggests that a rapidly growing market is using Midland Metro. </s><s n="s6.8;p12.19">It would be quite hard for a new entrant to capture the market as a result of high technical and economic barriers to entry. </s><s n="s7.8;p12.19">It is advisable for an entrepreneur to invest in the company and improve its management. </s><s n="s8.8;p12.19">In the long run Midland Metro is likely to achieve economic profit if it can manage its high cost structure in the early years. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Turnover between the competing firms and the company</head><p n="p13.19"><s n="s1.5;p13.19">The turnover differentials between Midland Metro and its competitors are shown below. </s><s n="s2.5;p13.19">Midland Metro's turnover in 2004 was 9% above the median suggesting reasonable performance by the company. </s><s n="s3.5;p13.19">Rail Europe Limited led the peer group for sales with £6.893 million in 2004, 25% greater than Midland Metro. </s><s n="s4.5;p13.19">Severn Valley Railway was satisfactory despite coming last; they only underperformed the median by 24% in 2004. </s><s n="s5.5;p13.19">Turnover levels are consistent between competitors suggesting relatively equal division of market share in the industry. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0227c-fig.003"/><p n="p14.19"><s n="s1.1;p14.19">Source (<seg type="URL" n="http://fame.bvdep.com/cgi/template.dll?product=1&amp;user=ipaddress"/>) </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Return on capital employed </head><p n="p15.19"><s n="s1.6;p15.19">The bar chart below shows the return on capital employed. </s><s n="s2.6;p15.19">Looking at it we can see that Midland Metro has failed to achieve returns on the capital they have invested in development projects. </s><s n="s3.6;p15.19">Bad investment decisions have been taken and ROCE has fallen by 565% between 1999 and 2000. </s><s n="s4.6;p15.19">Average ROCE for the peer group in 2004 was a reasonable 30% but large inequalities existed between companies. </s><s n="s5.6;p15.19">Leading the way was ISLAND LINE LTD with financial market beating ROCE of 175.49% whilst Severn Valley Railways managed an insignificant level of 0.71%. </s><s n="s6.6;p15.19">Thus Midland Metro should consider changing management and taking the necessary steps to improve their investment appraisal techniques. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0227c-fig.004"/><p n="p16.19"><s n="s1.1;p16.19">Source (<seg type="URL" n="http://fame.bvdep.com/cgi/template.dll?product=1&amp;user=ipaddress"/>) </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Evaluate performance of the industry</head><p n="p17.19"><s n="s1.5;p17.19">Since the competitors in the market are providing merit goods i.e. public transport profitability is not a key objective. </s><s n="s2.5;p17.19">In 2004 the average loss made by each firm in the industry was £249,444. </s><s n="s3.5;p17.19">There is large range in profitability however: Midland Metro is well below average and made a loss of £987,000 in 2004 whilst RAIL EXPRESS SYSTEMS LIMITED made a profit of £2.2 million. </s><s n="s4.5;p17.19">Sales for Midland Metro were 5.505 million however, 11.7% greater than average for peer group. </s><s n="s5.5;p17.19">ROCE in the industry is high (2004 average - 34.3%) reflecting good investment decisions made by companies. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Most viable strategy</head><p n="p18.19"><s n="s1.5;p18.19">Since Midland Metro is already differentiated from its competitors it needs to focus via low cost to gain an advantage over its rivals. </s><s n="s2.5;p18.19">Its ability to meet its current liabilities is poor with a current ratio of just 0.77. </s><s n="s3.5;p18.19">This suggests increasing reliance on short term credit. </s><s n="s4.5;p18.19">By reducing its costs it would be able to cut its prices and compete more effectively. </s><s n="s5.5;p18.19">In the long term its market will grow if its prices are lower and it will become profitable. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Recommendation</head><p n="p19.19"><s n="s1.5;p19.19">An entrepreneur would be advised to acquire the company rather than set up a new firm. </s><s n="s2.5;p19.19">Midland Metro is well established with the 5 <hi rend="sup">th</hi> highest turnover in its peer group. </s><s n="s3.5;p19.19">They have made the large initial investment to overcome the barriers of starting up, acquiring technical knowledge and gaining economies of scale. </s><s n="s4.5;p19.19">They have managed to create a question mark product which needs better management and further investment to become profitable. </s><s n="s5.5;p19.19">Midland Metro has a powerful position in the oligopoly and the potential to become a star company. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0227c-pic.001"/><figure id="BAWE_0227c-pic.002"/></div1></body><back/></text></TEI.2>
