<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_0227a" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Inertia Report</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">The document has a title page which contains:
document title
title part
other text</note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">deleted: header: module name and number; footer: page numbers</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">1</p><p n="date">2006-02</p><p n="module title">Technological Science I</p><p n="module code">ES180</p><p n="genre family">Methodology recount</p><p n="discipline">Engineering</p><p n="disciplinary group">PS</p><p n="grade">M</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">1758</p><p n="number of s-units">130</p><p n="number of p">86</p><p n="number of tables">4</p><p n="number of figures">3</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">69</p><p n="number of lists">7</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">18</p><p n="abstract present">abstract present</p><p n="average words per s-unit">13.5</p><p n="average s-units per p">1.5</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">m</p><p n="year of birth">1987</p><p n="first language">Sinhala</p><p n="education">OSA</p><p n="course">General Engineering</p><p n="student ID">0227</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><div1 type="front text"><p>.</p></div1><titlePage><titlePart rend="bold">University of <name type="university"/> School of Engineering</titlePart><docTitle><titlePart rend="bold">Inertia Laboratory</titlePart></docTitle><titlePart><hi rend="bold">by<name type="student name"/></hi><hi rend="bold"><name type="student ID"/></hi></titlePart><titlePart>Report Reference Code: ES180L8 Affiliation: Year 1 Engineering Report of laboratory performed on: 5 <hi rend="sup">th</hi> February 2006 [date]</titlePart></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="abstract"><head rend="bold italic">Summary</head><p n="p1.86"><s n="s1.6;p1.86">The following report consists of an experiment carried out in the laboratory to find the moment of inertia of three given disks of different sizes. </s><s n="s2.6;p1.86">This was done by using different masses and by calculating the time taken by each mass to reach the table. </s><s n="s3.6;p1.86">All the readings were tabulated and graphs were plotted. </s><s n="s4.6;p1.86">The moment of inertia was calculated using the gradient of the graph. </s><s n="s5.6;p1.86">Since most of the points on the graph were going through the best fit line we can say that the value obtained for inertia is quite accurate. </s><s n="s6.6;p1.86">And since necessary precautions were taken while carrying out the experiment such as to repeat the experiment to minimize human error would have resulted in getting very accurate reading for the inertia. </s></p></div1><div1 type="front-back-matter"><head rend="bold italic">Table of Contents</head><p/></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold italic">Introduction</head><p n="p2.86"><s n="s1.4;p2.86">Newton's First Law of motion states that "An object at rest tends to stay at rest and an object in motion tends to stay in motion with the same speed and in the same direction unless acted upon by an unbalanced force." </s><s n="s2.4;p2.86">It is normal for an object to resist its change in motion. </s><s n="s3.4;p2.86">This tendency to resist changes in their state of motion is described as inertia. </s><s n="s4.4;p2.86">The lab was carried out to further analyze and understand inertia. </s></p><p n="p3.86"><s n="s1.7;p3.86">The aim of the experiment was to investigate the moment of inertia of three metals disks of different sizes which had the same axis of rotation. </s><s n="s2.7;p3.86">The experiment was carried out in the laboratory in groups of two. </s><s n="s3.7;p3.86">Where the time taken by a given weight to travel a specific distance was noted for the three metal discs provided. </s><s n="s4.7;p3.86">Multiple readings were taken when doing the experiment to make the obtained values more accurate. </s><s n="s5.7;p3.86">Having two members in the group helped out with taking readings and setting up the apparatus and doing many other different tasks simultaneously. </s><s n="s6.7;p3.86">The average time taken was calculated and graphs were drawn which made the final value for the moment of inertia accurate. </s><s n="s7.7;p3.86">The theory used is illustrated below. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold italic"> Theory</head><p n="p4.86"><s n="s1.1;p4.86">The following theories were used to do the calculations carries out and the readings that were taken. </s></p><p n="p5.86"><s n="s1.1;p5.86"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0227a-form.001"/> </s></p><p n="p6.86"><s n="s1.1;p6.86"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0227a-form.002"/> </s></p><p n="p7.86"><s n="s1.1;p7.86"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0227a-form.003"/><hi rend="italic">Circular acceleration</hi> </s></p><p n="p8.86"><s n="s1.1;p8.86"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0227a-form.004"/><hi rend="italic"> Mass used</hi> </s></p><p n="p9.86"><s n="s1.1;p9.86"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0227a-form.005"/><hi rend="italic"> Radius of the threaded metal rod</hi> </s></p><p n="p10.86"><s n="s1.1;p10.86"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0227a-form.006"/><hi rend="italic"> Distance moved by mass</hi> </s></p><p n="p11.86"><s n="s1.1;p11.86"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0227a-form.007"/><hi rend="italic"> Time taken for the mass to go the distance's'</hi> </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0227a-pic.001"/><list type="simple"><head>Equations used</head><item><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0227a-form.008"/></item><item><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0227a-form.009"/></item><item><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0227a-form.010"/></item><item><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0227a-form.011"/></item></list><list type="simple"><head>For the disk</head><item><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0227a-form.012"/></item><item><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0227a-form.013"/></item><item>and</item><item><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0227a-form.014"/></item></list><list type="simple"><head>For the mass</head><item><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0227a-form.015"/></item><item><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0227a-form.016"/></item><item><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0227a-form.017"/></item></list><list type="simple"><head>Using</head><item><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0227a-form.018"/> and <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0227a-form.019"/></item><item><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0227a-form.020"/></item><item><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0227a-form.021"/></item><item><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0227a-form.022"/></item></list><p n="p12.86"><s n="s1.1;p12.86">Since the left hand side is the same in both the equations </s></p><list type="simple"><item><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0227a-form.023"/></item><item><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0227a-form.024"/></item><item><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0227a-form.025"/></item><item><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0227a-form.026"/></item></list><div2><head rend="underlined bold italic">2.1 Assumptions Made</head><list type="bulleted"><item><hi rend="bold">Assumption 1 </hi><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0227a-form.027"/><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0227a-form.028"/><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0227a-form.029"/></item><item><hi rend="bold">Assumption 2 </hi><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0227a-form.030"/><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0227a-form.031"/><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0227a-form.032"/><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0227a-form.033"/></item></list><p n="p13.86"><s n="s1.1;p13.86">Which is in the form </s></p><p n="p14.86"><s n="s1.1;p14.86"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0227a-form.034"/> </s></p><p n="p15.86"><s n="s1.1;p15.86">Where </s></p><p n="p16.86"><s n="s1.1;p16.86"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0227a-form.035"/> </s></p><p n="p17.86"><s n="s1.1;p17.86"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0227a-form.036"/> </s></p><p n="p18.86"><s n="s1.1;p18.86"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0227a-form.037"/> </s></p><p n="p19.86"><s n="s1.2;p19.86">The equation that was derived above will be the most important equation that will be sued to calculate the moment of inertia of each disk. </s><s n="s2.2;p19.86">This will be done by plotting the appropriate graphs and then by calculating their gradient. </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold italic">Apparatus and Methods</head><div2><head rend="underlined bold italic">3.1 Apparatus</head><p n="p20.86"><s n="s1.1;p20.86">Shown below is a simplified version of the apparatus that was used when conducting the experiment at the laboratory. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0227a-pic.002"/><p n="p21.86"><s n="s1.1;p21.86">The apparatus that was given is listed below </s></p><list type="bulleted"><item>Three metal disks of different sizes and of different masses having the same thickness.</item><item>A threaded metal rod with a winder mounted on to the stand.</item><item>Masses of different weights. </item><item>A string attached to the threaded metal rod.</item><item>A mass loader attached to the other end of the string.</item><item>Electronic stop watch.</item><item>A screw nut to fix the discs to the back of the threaded metal rod.</item><item>A half meter ruler.</item></list></div2><div2><head rend="underlined bold italic">3.2 Method used</head><p n="p22.86"><s n="s1.5;p22.86">According to the equation derived <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0227a-form.038"/> to calculate the moment of inertia the values of the following should be known. </s><s n="s2.5;p22.86">The distance 's', the radius 'r' of the threaded metal rod and the time taken 't'. </s><s n="s3.5;p22.86">All of these are unknowns. </s><s n="s4.5;p22.86">The value of 'm' should take the following 0.1Kg, 0.12Kg, 0.17Kg, 0.22Kg. </s><s n="s5.5;p22.86">And the value of the universal gravitational constant 'g' was taken to be 9.81 </s></p><p n="p23.86"><s n="s1.3;p23.86">The experiment carried out included winding up the string with the mass attached to it up to the threaded metal rod. </s><s n="s2.3;p23.86">Then it was allowed to fall down under gravity from rest (initial velocity zero). </s><s n="s3.3;p23.86">And the time taken for the mass to hit the table was tabulated with the use of a stop watch. </s></p><p n="p24.86"><s n="s1.4;p24.86">The following illustrates the steps carried to measure the time 't'. </s><s n="s2.4;p24.86">It was very helpful to have two people doing the experiment. </s><s n="s3.4;p24.86">Because when one person was in charge in sending the thread around the threaded metal rod the other person was in charge in measuring the time taken for the mass to hit the table. </s><s n="s4.4;p24.86">The two members in the group kept alternating within the two tasks which made it more accurate. </s></p><p n="p25.86"><s n="s1.1;p25.86">Steps followed </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p26.86"><s n="s1.1;p26.86">The small disk was fastened on to the back of the metal disk using the metal bush and the screw nut. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p27.86"><s n="s1.1;p27.86">The mass loader was connected to the other end of the string and then it was winded until the mass loader (0.1kg) reached the threaded metal rod. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p28.86"><s n="s1.1;p28.86">Then the metal rod was released allowing the mass unwind and hit the table. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p29.86"><s n="s1.1;p29.86">The time taken for the mass to travel from top of the stand (the level of which the metal rod is at) till it hits the table was calculated using a stop watch. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p30.86"><s n="s1.2;p30.86">The experiment was repeated to take four readings. </s><s n="s2.2;p30.86">And then was again repeated with the following masses 0.12kg, 0.17kg, 0.22kg. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p31.86"><s n="s1.1;p31.86">The readings were again obtained and the experiment was repeated with the medium size disk and the large disk. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p32.86"><s n="s1.1;p32.86">And the readings were tabulated. </s></p><p n="p33.86"><s n="s1.3;p33.86">The unknown 's' of the equation was found by measuring the distance between the threaded metal rod and the table ( The distance the mass travels before coming in contact with the table) with the use of the half meter ruler provided. </s><s n="s2.3;p33.86">This was done by keeping it between the two points. </s><s n="s3.3;p33.86">The value of s=30.6 cm </s></p><p n="p34.86"><s n="s1.1;p34.86">The other unknown 'r' the radius of the threaded metal rod was calculated using the following method. </s></p><p n="p35.86"><s n="s1.3;p35.86">The thread that was given was woven around the threaded metal rod up to 5 turns. </s><s n="s2.3;p35.86">Then string was set lose and the length of the string was calculated using the meter ruler. </s><s n="s3.3;p35.86">It was repeated three times to make sure that the reading obtained was accurate. </s></p><p n="p36.86"><s n="s1.1;p36.86">The following readings were obtained 17.5, 17.3, 17.4 </s></p><p n="p37.86"><s n="s1.1;p37.86">The average length </s></p><p n="p38.86"><s n="s1.1;p38.86"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0227a-form.039"/> </s></p><p n="p39.86"><s n="s1.1;p39.86"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0227a-form.040"/> </s></p><p n="p40.86"><s n="s1.1;p40.86">Therefore the length of one turn </s></p><p n="p41.86"><s n="s1.1;p41.86"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0227a-form.041"/> </s></p><p n="p42.86"><s n="s1.1;p42.86"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0227a-form.042"/> </s></p><p n="p43.86"><s n="s1.1;p43.86"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0227a-form.043"/> </s></p><p n="p44.86"><s n="s1.1;p44.86"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0227a-form.044"/> </s></p><p n="p45.86"><s n="s1.1;p45.86"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0227a-form.045"/> </s></p><p n="p46.86"><s n="s1.1;p46.86"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0227a-form.046"/> </s></p><p n="p47.86"><s n="s1.4;p47.86">After all the readings were tabulated, the average time of each of the four readings was calculated and for each mass the value of <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0227a-form.047"/> was calculated. </s><s n="s2.4;p47.86">This was done for all three disks. </s><s n="s3.4;p47.86">Then a graph of 'm' (mass) versus <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0227a-form.048"/> was plotted for each disk. </s><s n="s4.4;p47.86">From the equation. </s></p><p n="p48.86"><s n="s1.1;p48.86"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0227a-form.049"/> </s></p><p n="p49.86"><s n="s1.1;p49.86">We can see that this is in the form of a straight line with equation </s></p><p n="p50.86"><s n="s1.1;p50.86"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0227a-form.050"/> </s></p><p n="p51.86"><s n="s1.1;p51.86">Therefore </s></p><p n="p52.86"><s n="s1.1;p52.86">The gradient of the graph <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0227a-form.051"/> </s></p><p n="p53.86"><s n="s1.1;p53.86">Therefore the moment of inertia of the disk is given by </s></p><p n="p54.86"><s n="s1.1;p54.86"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0227a-form.052"/> </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold italic">Observations Results and Possible errors</head><div2><head rend="underlined bold italic">4.1 Results</head><p rend="bulleted" n="p55.86"><s n="s1.1;p55.86">The distance <hi rend="italic">'s'</hi>, the height between the centre of the threaded metal rod and the table. (accuracy of the meter ruler used to measure this value was 0.001m) </s></p><p n="p56.86"><s n="s1.1;p56.86"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0227a-form.053"/> </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p57.86"><s n="s1.1;p57.86">The radius <hi rend="italic">'r'</hi>, radius of the threaded metal rod which was used as the axis of rotation. (accuracy of the metal ruler used was 0.0005m) </s></p><p n="p58.86"><s n="s1.1;p58.86"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0227a-form.054"/> </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p59.86"><s n="s1.1;p59.86">The time <hi rend="italic">'t'</hi>, the table below shows the results of the times taken for the masses to travel from the centre of the metal rod to the surface of the table (The accuracy of the stop watch was 0.01s) </s></p><table id="BAWE_0227a-tab.001"><row><cell/></row></table></div2><div2><head rend="underlined bold italic">4.2 Possible errors</head><p n="p60.86"><s n="s1.2;p60.86">The values that were obtained may not be accurate due to errors that would have occurred while conducting the experiment. </s><s n="s2.2;p60.86">The error that would have affected the reading are listed below. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p61.86"><s n="s1.1;p61.86">Time error - The time taken to start and stop the clock. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p62.86"><s n="s1.1;p62.86">Friction - The friction between the bearings would have also effected in the reading not being accurate. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p63.86"><s n="s1.1;p63.86">Inertia - Even though we need to calculate the inertia of the disk according to the experiment carries out we are finding the inertia of the whole system. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p64.86"><s n="s1.1;p64.86">Air Resistance - The air present around the experiment area would also affect the reading. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p65.86"><s n="s1.2;p65.86">Worn out equipment - The value of the masses may not be the value that they are supposed to be because they might be worn out due to being used consistently. </s><s n="s2.2;p65.86">There for the actual mass might be less than that stated. </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold italic"> Analysis and Discussion of Results</head><p n="p66.86"><s n="s1.3;p66.86">The value of <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0227a-form.055"/> was required to sketch the graph. </s><s n="s2.3;p66.86">The table below shows the values used to plot the graph. </s><s n="s3.3;p66.86">A graph of 'm' versus <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0227a-form.056"/> was plotted for each table the results obtained is shown below. </s></p><table id="BAWE_0227a-tab.002"><head rend="bold">For the small Disk</head><row><cell/></row></table><figure id="BAWE_0227a-fig.001"><head rend="italic">The Graph of the small disk</head></figure><table id="BAWE_0227a-tab.003"><head rend="bold">For the medium Disk</head><row><cell/></row></table><figure id="BAWE_0227a-fig.002"><head rend="italic">The Graph of the medium disk</head></figure><table id="BAWE_0227a-tab.004"><head rend="bold">For the large Disk</head><row><cell/></row></table><figure id="BAWE_0227a-fig.003"><head rend="italic">The Graph of the large disk</head></figure><div2><head rend="underlined bold italic">5.1 Calculating the Gradient</head><p n="p67.86"><s n="s1.2;p67.86">After drawing the graph in order to calculate the inertia the gradient of each line was to be calculated. </s><s n="s2.2;p67.86">This process is shown below. </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p68.86"><s n="s1.2;p68.86">1. </s><s n="s2.2;p68.86">Gradient of line of small disc: <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0227a-form.057"/> </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p69.86"><s n="s1.2;p69.86">2. </s><s n="s2.2;p69.86">Gradient of line of medium disc:<formula notation="" id="BAWE_0227a-form.058"/> </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p70.86"><s n="s1.2;p70.86">3. </s><s n="s2.2;p70.86">Gradient of line of large disc: <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0227a-form.059"/> </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined bold italic">5.2 Calculating the Moment of Inertia</head><p n="p71.86"><s n="s1.1;p71.86">The gradient of each line was found to be equal to <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0227a-form.060"/>. </s></p><p n="p72.86"><s n="s1.1;p72.86">The moment of inertia was found by substituting the values obtained for the gradient in the derived equation. </s></p><p n="p73.86"><s n="s1.1;p73.86">Gradient = <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0227a-form.061"/> </s></p><p n="p74.86"><s n="s1.1;p74.86">For the small disc: </s></p><p n="p75.86"><s n="s1.1;p75.86"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0227a-form.062"/> </s></p><p n="p76.86"><s n="s1.1;p76.86"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0227a-form.063"/> </s></p><p n="p77.86"><s n="s1.1;p77.86">For the medium disc: </s></p><p n="p78.86"><s n="s1.1;p78.86"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0227a-form.064"/> </s></p><p n="p79.86"><s n="s1.1;p79.86"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0227a-form.065"/> </s></p><p n="p80.86"><s n="s1.1;p80.86">For the large disc: </s></p><p n="p81.86"><s n="s1.1;p81.86"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0227a-form.066"/> </s></p><p n="p82.86"><s n="s1.1;p82.86"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0227a-form.067"/> </s></p><p n="p83.86"><s n="s1.1;p83.86">The calculated answers carry a certain uncertainty due to errors that would have occurred during the experiment that are mentioned under section 4.2 and due to rounding off of numerical answers. </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold italic">Recommendations</head><p n="p84.86"><s n="s1.3;p84.86">It is also recommended as a second method to pick out the minimum and maximum value of the four readings obtained by repeating the experiment. </s><s n="s2.3;p84.86">(Finding out how long the mass takes to travel from the centre of the metal rod until it comes in contact with the table), Then calculating the value of <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0227a-form.068"/> for the minimum and maximum reading of each disk and plotting a graph of the mass versus <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0227a-form.069"/> for the minimum values and the maximum values. </s><s n="s3.3;p84.86">Then by comparing the minimum and maxim graphs we can interpret the results for the inertia. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold italic">Conclusions</head><p n="p85.86"><s n="s1.2;p85.86">Since the experiment was carried out by a group all precautions were taken to make sure that the apparatus was set up in the most precise and accurate manner. </s><s n="s2.2;p85.86">Tabulations and readings were taken very carefully so as not to jeopardize the accuracy of the experiment. </s></p><p n="p86.86"><s n="s1.2;p86.86">Since almost all the points plotted are on the best fit line. </s><s n="s2.2;p86.86">And the experiment was repeated and the necessary precautions were taken, we can say that the calculated value of the moment of inertia is accurate. </s></p></div1></body><back><div1 type="bibliography"><head rend="bold italic">References</head><p><seg type="URL" n="http://www.glenbrook.k12.il.us/gbssci/phys/Class/newtlaws/u2l1b.html"/></p><p><seg type="URL" n="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Inertia"/></p></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
