<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_0227e" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Finding the coefficient of friction between brass and steel.</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">deleted: header: assignment name; footer: page and student numbers</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">1</p><p n="date">2005-11</p><p n="module title">Technological Science I</p><p n="module code">ES180</p><p n="genre family">Methodology recount</p><p n="discipline">Engineering</p><p n="disciplinary group">PS</p><p n="grade">D</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">721</p><p n="number of s-units">62</p><p n="number of p">35</p><p n="number of tables">2</p><p n="number of figures">0</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">28</p><p n="number of lists">1</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">4</p><p n="abstract present">abstract present</p><p n="average words per s-unit">11.6</p><p n="average s-units per p">1.8</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">m</p><p n="year of birth">1987</p><p n="first language">Sinhala</p><p n="education">OSA</p><p n="course">General Engineering</p><p n="student ID">0227</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><titlePart rend="underlined bold">ES 180 Introductory Laboratory Metrology</titlePart><docTitle><titlePart><hi rend="underlined bold">Finding the coefficient of friction between brass and steel</hi>.</titlePart></docTitle></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="abstract"><head rend="bold italic">Summary</head><p n="p1.35"><s n="s1.8;p1.35">The report illustrates finding the coefficient of friction between a brass pin and a moving steel surface. </s><s n="s2.8;p1.35">When the results were tabulated they tended to have a percentage uncertainty of about 1%. </s><s n="s3.8;p1.35">Due to this the experiment was repeated to obtain a more precise value. </s><s n="s4.8;p1.35">The mean value of the deflection obtained by reading the dial gauge had a mean value of 0.079 mm. </s><s n="s5.8;p1.35">The expected for the deflection was 0.068 mm since this value had a standard deviation of 0.012 mm the mean value of 0.079 is accurate. </s><s n="s6.8;p1.35">The average value of the coefficient of friction between the brass pin and moving steel surface turned out to be 0.3095. </s><s n="s7.8;p1.35">The expected value was 0.267 this had an uncertainty of 0.046. </s><s n="s8.8;p1.35">Thus the reading obtained is accurate. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold italic">Introduction</head><p n="p2.35"><s n="s1.8;p2.35">A commercial wear testing machine is driven by an alternating power supply. </s><s n="s2.8;p2.35">Which has a loading mechanism a weight of 0.5 kg is put on the loading bar and the dial gauge is used to measure the deflection of the cantilever which is related to the coefficient of friction. </s><s n="s3.8;p2.35">The expected result for the deflection which was 0.068 mm differed from the obtained mean value of 0.079 mainly due to the difficulties that arise when trying to read the deflection of the dial gauge. </s><s n="s4.8;p2.35">Which kept on moving in to either side so rapidly, at an uncertainty of about (+) or (-) 1. </s><s n="s5.8;p2.35">This would have resulted in the change in the final value obtained for the coefficient of friction. </s><s n="s6.8;p2.35">Also a number of errors occurred during the experiment would have resulted in the change in the final reading. </s><s n="s7.8;p2.35">This would have been due to the work hardening of the pin and also due to the friction in the pivots and the wasted parts of the machine. </s><s n="s8.8;p2.35">The zero error of the gauge would also result in the difference in the final reading. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold italic">Conclusions</head><p n="p3.35"><s n="s1.10;p3.35">The value obtained had a mean of be 0.3095, which is between 0 and 1 and close to 0.3 as mentioned. </s><s n="s2.10;p3.35">The gathered results from all of the participating students also seem to be of similar values with the average value working out at 0.275 with an uncertainty of 0.046. </s><s n="s3.10;p3.35">Thus the value I obtained seems sensible and realistic. </s><s n="s4.10;p3.35">The dial gauge needed to be calibrated after switching on, before placing the load to make sure there was no zero error. </s><s n="s5.10;p3.35">The machine was vibrating so vigorously it was very hard to obtain a reading. </s><s n="s6.10;p3.35">This would have effected in the spread of results. </s><s n="s7.10;p3.35">To minimize this error the experiment was repeated a couple of times. </s><s n="s8.10;p3.35">Also the brass pin wearing also would have affected in people in different groups getting different values, but comparatively I think this error is negligible. </s><s n="s9.10;p3.35">However looking at the set of results obtained we can state that the value of coefficient of friction is close to the theoretical value between the two surfaces. </s><s n="s10.10;p3.35">Therefore a conclusion can be drawn that the value obtained for the coefficient of friction between the brass pin and the moving steel is very accurate. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold italic">Steps followed to make the reading accurate</head><p rend="bulleted" n="p4.35"><s n="s1.2;p4.35">Fist I switched on the motor and set the counter to zero. </s><s n="s2.2;p4.35">I made sure it was as accurate as possible by considering where the pin seems to be most of the time during its very rapid oscillations </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p5.35"><s n="s1.1;p5.35">Then I placed the load of 0.5kg and recorded the new reading. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p6.35"><s n="s1.2;p6.35">I repeated these two steps for four times to make the value obtained more accurate. </s><s n="s2.2;p6.35">And found out that the reading was in the range of (+) or (-) 1 </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p7.35"><s n="s1.1;p7.35">The readings were tabulated in the table below, taking in to account their average values. </s></p><table id="BAWE_0227e-tab.001"><head rend="bold italic">Data given</head><row><cell/></row></table><list type="simple"><item><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0227e-form.001"/></item><item><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0227e-form.002"/></item><item><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0227e-form.003"/></item><item><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0227e-form.004"/></item><item><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0227e-form.005"/></item><item><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0227e-form.006"/></item><item><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0227e-form.007"/></item><item><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0227e-form.008"/></item></list></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold italic">Calculations</head><p n="p8.35"><s n="s1.1;p8.35">First Reading </s></p><p n="p9.35"><s n="s1.1;p9.35"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0227e-form.009"/> </s></p><p n="p10.35"><s n="s1.1;p10.35"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0227e-form.010"/> </s></p><p n="p11.35"><s n="s1.1;p11.35"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0227e-form.011"/> </s></p><p n="p12.35"><s n="s1.1;p12.35">Then </s></p><p n="p13.35"><s n="s1.1;p13.35"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0227e-form.012"/> </s></p><p n="p14.35"><s n="s1.1;p14.35"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0227e-form.013"/> </s></p><p n="p15.35"><s n="s1.1;p15.35"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0227e-form.014"/> </s></p><p n="p16.35"><s n="s1.1;p16.35"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0227e-form.015"/> </s></p><p n="p17.35"><s n="s1.2;p17.35">One reading of the meter corresponds to 0.01 mm. </s><s n="s2.2;p17.35">Therefore </s></p><p n="p18.35"><s n="s1.1;p18.35"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0227e-form.016"/> </s></p><p n="p19.35"><s n="s1.1;p19.35"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0227e-form.017"/> </s></p><p n="p20.35"><s n="s1.1;p20.35">Then </s></p><p n="p21.35"><s n="s1.1;p21.35"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0227e-form.018"/> </s></p><p n="p22.35"><s n="s1.1;p22.35"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0227e-form.019"/> </s></p><p n="p23.35"><s n="s1.1;p23.35"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0227e-form.020"/> </s></p><p n="p24.35"><s n="s1.1;p24.35"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0227e-form.021"/> </s></p><p n="p25.35"><s n="s1.1;p25.35"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0227e-form.022"/> </s></p><p n="p26.35"><s n="s1.1;p26.35"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0227e-form.023"/> </s></p><p n="p27.35"><s n="s1.1;p27.35"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0227e-form.024"/> </s></p><p n="p28.35"><s n="s1.1;p28.35">The same procedure was followed to obtain the coefficient of friction of the other two deflections. </s></p><p n="p29.35"><s n="s1.1;p29.35">When it was 8.5 </s></p><p n="p30.35"><s n="s1.1;p30.35"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0227e-form.025"/> </s></p><p n="p31.35"><s n="s1.1;p31.35">When it was 8.0 </s></p><p n="p32.35"><s n="s1.1;p32.35"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0227e-form.026"/> </s></p><p n="p33.35"><s n="s1.1;p33.35">When it was 7.5 </s></p><p n="p34.35"><s n="s1.1;p34.35"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0227e-form.027"/> </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold italic">The Summary of the experiment is shown below. </head><table id="BAWE_0227e-tab.002"><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p35.35"><s n="s1.2;p35.35">Since the coefficient of friction should lie between the range <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0227e-form.028"/> this value is reasonable. </s><s n="s2.2;p35.35">And since as mentioned in the in the briefing sheet the value is approximately 0.3 to one significant figure, therefore the value is accurate. </s></p></div1></body><back><div1 type="back text"><p rend="bold italic"><name type="student name"/></p><p rend="bold italic">Student No :- <name type="student ID"/></p></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
