<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_0228g" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Part 1 Evaluation</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">deleted: header: student number
</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">2</p><p n="date">2004-03</p><p n="module title">Computer Systems Engineering</p><p n="module code">CS213</p><p n="genre family">Critique</p><p n="discipline">Computer Science</p><p n="disciplinary group">PS</p><p n="grade">M</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">1138</p><p n="number of s-units">56</p><p n="number of p">25</p><p n="number of tables">0</p><p n="number of figures">1</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">0</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">0</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">20.3</p><p n="average s-units per p">2.2</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">m</p><p n="year of birth">1984</p><p n="first language">English</p><p n="education">UKA</p><p n="course">Computer Science</p><p n="student ID">0228</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><docTitle><titlePart>ID: <name type="student ID"/> Course: Computer Systems Engineering Name: <name type="student name"/></titlePart></docTitle></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">PART 1: EVALUATION</head><div2><head rend="underlined">Limitations</head><p n="p1.25"><s n="s1.4;p1.25">When carrying out an expert evaluation one has to realise that the expert will be biased towards their own needs and desires. </s><s n="s2.4;p1.25">The expert will know how to use all the features and may want to do more complicated things with a piece of equipment. </s><s n="s3.4;p1.25">On the other hand the regular user may not be familiar with the equipment and will really only want the simpler features. </s><s n="s4.4;p1.25">So if a piece of equipment has a good review it may be too complicated for a regular user; if a piece of equipment has a bad review it may be exactly what the user wants. </s></p><p n="p2.25"><s n="s1.1;p2.25">I feel that I am quite good at using technical equipment and personally, after reading the manual, I feel that I could quite confidently use the Honeywell Smartfit. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">Strengths</head><p n="p3.25"><s n="s1.2;p3.25">By placing all the menus, settings and buttons clearly on the front you know that all the features are accessible from that place. </s><s n="s2.2;p3.25">There will be no hidden menus or tedious menu scrolling. </s></p><p n="p4.25"><s n="s1.1;p4.25">The LCD screen is very useful and gives good feedback, indicating when heating is on or off etc. </s></p><p n="p5.25"><s n="s1.1;p5.25">The copy button is very useful if you want to make the settings for each day the same. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">Weaknesses</head><p n="p6.25"><s n="s1.2;p6.25">There are perhaps too many features on that front panel. </s><s n="s2.2;p6.25">Seeing so many sliders and buttons may seem a bit overwhelming for some people. </s></p><p n="p7.25"><s n="s1.2;p7.25">After reading the manual, there does not seem to be any audio feedback. </s><s n="s2.2;p7.25">This can be a problem because if you set the times there is nothing to say you have set them correctly. </s></p><p n="p8.25"><s n="s1.1;p8.25">There does not need to be an indication of whether the boiler is on or not, because if either heating or hot water is on then the boiler will have to be on. </s></p><p n="p9.25"><s n="s1.1;p9.25">There is barely the need to have the holiday button and the features associated with it. </s></p><p n="p10.25"><s n="s1.2;p10.25">If a person had lost the manual it would be quite difficult to change any settings. </s><s n="s2.2;p10.25">There are not any clues on the programmer to show you what you need to do. </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">PART 3: HIGH-LEVEL USABILITY IMPROVEMENTS</head><div2><head rend="underlined">Learning</head><p n="p11.25"><s n="s1.2;p11.25">Most of the more complicated features are accessed through the Main Menu. </s><s n="s2.2;p11.25">From here you will be able to select a user level - beginner or expert. </s></p><p n="p12.25"><s n="s1.2;p12.25">Then when using the beginner setting there will be a 'wizard' type use of the programmer where the system will guide the user through setting all the timings. </s><s n="s2.2;p12.25">When the beginner is confident enough they can then use the programmer in expert mode, where they can fill in the information needed much more quickly. </s></p><p n="p13.25"><s n="s1.1;p13.25">The documentation will come with screenshots of all the different menus making the programmer very easy to use for beginners while still straightforward and interesting enough for expert users to program it with out getting bored. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">Memory</head><p n="p14.25"><s n="s1.4;p14.25">Because the menus will come with step by step commands the user does not have to remember anything if they wish. </s><s n="s2.4;p14.25">If they do remember then it will speed up the process. </s><s n="s3.4;p14.25">The buttons on the front are divided so that all the buttons associated with heating are on the left and all those associated with hot water are on the left. </s><s n="s4.4;p14.25">This will help them to remember where to find a control associated with either hot water or heating. </s></p><p n="p15.25"><s n="s1.3;p15.25">E.g. </s><s n="s2.3;p15.25">To keep the heating on for an extra hour the user will remember that last time to put the heating on the pulled the slider on the left. </s><s n="s3.3;p15.25">So that will mean that the button to put the heating on for an extra hour will also be on the left. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">Ergonomics</head><p n="p16.25"><s n="s1.2;p16.25">The buttons on the front will be large and have enough space between them, so that it is relatively easy to press one button without pressing the one next to it. </s><s n="s2.2;p16.25">The buttons on the touch screen will also have the same features. </s></p><p n="p17.25"><s n="s1.1;p17.25">There will be a brightness adjuster so that if it is too bright for some people or too dull for others they can adjust the brightness to suit them. </s></p><p n="p18.25"><s n="s1.1;p18.25">The display will be quite large so that a large font can be used and people will have no problem reading it. </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">PART 4: LOW-LEVEL USABILITY IMPROVEMENTS</head><div2><head rend="underlined">Observability</head><p n="p19.25"><s n="s1.3;p19.25">There will be a large display showing you exactly what you are doing. </s><s n="s2.3;p19.25">All the buttons will be labelled, with the name of the button being on the button. </s><s n="s3.3;p19.25">There will be big label for the heating side of the unit and a label for the hot water side. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">Feedback</head><p n="p20.25"><s n="s1.1;p20.25">Apart from the central display there will be an audio feedback, with a positive sound for correct actions and a negative sound for incorrect actions (similar to those on Windows for example). </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">Forgiveness</head><p n="p21.25"><s n="s1.3;p21.25">When using the programmer in beginner mode, the user will be using a 'wizard' type system. </s><s n="s2.3;p21.25">This will mean they will have the option of going back through the menus to change anything they think is incorrect. </s><s n="s3.3;p21.25">With the expert user they will simply have to reset the values manually, in the same way as they entered them in the first place. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">Progressive Disclosure</head><p n="p22.25"><s n="s1.2;p22.25">The programmer unit shows progressive disclosure by having both a beginner and expert mode. </s><s n="s2.2;p22.25">In beginner mode there is a lot of assistance from the unit but in expert mode you will be able to carry out tasks much more quickly. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">Mapping</head><p n="p23.25"><s n="s1.3;p23.25">There are cursor controls on the programmer unit. </s><s n="s2.3;p23.25">When using the menus in expert mode it will be easier to move around the screen using the cursor keys. </s><s n="s3.3;p23.25">This shows an example of mapping because pressing left will move a highlighted box or something similar left. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">Consistency</head><p n="p24.25"><s n="s1.2;p24.25">The programmer unit shows some degree of consistency in that all the buttons for heating are on the left side and all the buttons for hot water are on the right side. </s><s n="s2.2;p24.25">The setting of times for the hot water and heating will also be similar when it comes to accessing menus. </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">PART 2: THE IMPROVED DESIGN</head><figure id="BAWE_0228g-pic.001"/><p n="p25.25"><s n="s1.9;p25.25">The design of this programmer is based on removing the clutter of all the buttons and sliders. </s><s n="s2.9;p25.25">Only the buttons which may be frequently used are placed on the front of the display. </s><s n="s3.9;p25.25">The number buttons and cursor are placed on the front because it would be inconvenient to have them placed anywhere else. </s><s n="s4.9;p25.25">The main input system of the programmer is the touch screen display. </s><s n="s5.9;p25.25">The touch screen will mean that many different buttons can be placed on the screen and removed as when needed. </s><s n="s6.9;p25.25">This will aid the user in pressing the correct buttons for the correct situation. </s><s n="s7.9;p25.25">The user will be able to change settings by accessing the main menu. </s><s n="s8.9;p25.25">All of the features from the previous programmer will be accessible through these menus. </s><s n="s9.9;p25.25">The menu system will have to be designed very well to have an effective programmer unit. </s></p></div1></body><back/></text></TEI.2>
