<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_0228d" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Electrical Systems Laboratory Report</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">The document has a title page which contains:
document title
title part</note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">deleted: page numbers</note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">appendices: graphs and briefing sheet</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">1</p><p n="date">2002-12</p><p n="module title">Electrical and Electronic Systems</p><p n="module code">ES163</p><p n="genre family">Methodology recount</p><p n="discipline">Engineering</p><p n="disciplinary group">PS</p><p n="grade">D</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">1879</p><p n="number of s-units">121</p><p n="number of p">54</p><p n="number of tables">2</p><p n="number of figures">0</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">2</p><p n="number of lists">4</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">0</p><p n="abstract present">abstract present</p><p n="average words per s-unit">15.5</p><p n="average s-units per p">2.2</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">m</p><p n="year of birth">1984</p><p n="first language">English</p><p n="education">UKA</p><p n="course">Engineering</p><p n="student ID">0228</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><titlePart rend="underlined bold">ES163A9A: Electrical and Electronic Systems</titlePart><docTitle><titlePart rend="underlined bold">Electrical Systems Laboratory Report</titlePart></docTitle><titlePart><name type="student name"/> First Year Computer Systems Engineering 6/12/02</titlePart></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="abstract"><head rend="underlined">Summary</head><p n="p1.54"><s n="s1.1;p1.54">An experiment was carried out to gain more knowledge of: </s></p><list type="simple"><item>Current, voltage and power in ac circuits</item><item> Variation of inductance of a coil with number of turns</item><item> Harmonics in waveforms</item></list><p n="p2.54"><s n="s1.2;p2.54">This was achieved by setting up a circuit which had resistance and inductance connected in series. </s><s n="s2.2;p2.54">The circuit contained a Variac (trade name) which allowed for changes to the number of turns of the coil. </s></p><p n="p3.54"><s n="s1.3;p3.54">Increase in the number of turns caused increase in inductance. </s><s n="s2.3;p3.54">This caused the current to go out of phase with voltage. </s><s n="s3.3;p3.54">This lowered the current and also lowered the power factor giving a lower total power. </s></p><p n="p4.54"><s n="s1.3;p4.54">Harmonics present on the ac mains were seen from the waveforms because there were peaks in multiples of 50. </s><s n="s2.3;p4.54">This meant that the waves were not completely sinusoidal but were close to it. </s><s n="s3.3;p4.54">Harmonics were difficult to read after the 5 <hi rend="sup">th</hi> harmonic because inductors act as low-pass filters meaning it filters out the higher frequencies. </s></p><p n="p5.54"><s n="s1.2;p5.54">To counteract the effects of the inductor a capacitor could be added to the circuit to bring the current back into phase with the voltage. </s><s n="s2.2;p5.54">This would give a higher total power output. </s></p><p n="p6.54"><s n="s1.1;p6.54">The graphs and waveforms can be viewed in the graph section in the appendix. </s></p></div1><div1 type="front-back-matter"><head rend="underlined">Contents</head><p/></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined">1.Introduction</head><p n="p7.54"><s n="s1.1;p7.54">The purpose of this experiment was to develop understanding of: </s></p><list type="simple"><item>Current, voltage and power in an ac circuit</item><item> Variation of inductance of a coil with number of turns</item><item> Harmonics in waveforms.</item></list><p n="p8.54"><s n="s1.4;p8.54">Constructing a circuit that contained resistance and inductance in series carried this out. </s><s n="s2.4;p8.54">The ac mains were used as the voltage supply. </s><s n="s3.4;p8.54">The mains were connected through a variable autotransformer (known as a 'Variac' - trade name) and an isolating transformer. </s><s n="s4.4;p8.54">The Variac provided a way of controlling alternating voltage and the isolating transformer ensures safety. </s></p><p n="p9.54"><s n="s1.5;p9.54">The main part of the circuit consisted of a coil from the motor of a food mixer. </s><s n="s2.5;p9.54">The coil was wound on a magnetic core. </s><s n="s3.5;p9.54">The coil and part of the core were placed within the test box. </s><s n="s4.5;p9.54">The rest of the core sat on top of the box. </s><s n="s5.5;p9.54">To limit the current a fixed resistor of 350 was placed in series with the coil. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined">2.Theory</head><p n="p10.54"><s n="s1.7;p10.54">An inductor consists of a coil of wire wrapped around a magnetic core. </s><s n="s2.7;p10.54">When current is passed through this coil there is a delay in the release of the charge. </s><s n="s3.7;p10.54">This causes storage of charge within the coil. </s><s n="s4.7;p10.54">This makes an inductor a storage element for charge. </s><s n="s5.7;p10.54">However placing an inductor in series with a resistor causes the current to lags in relation to the voltage. </s><s n="s6.7;p10.54">To oppose this problem placing a capacitor in parallel with the inductor will put the current back in phase with the voltage. </s><s n="s7.7;p10.54">A current-carrying coil with N-turns, length l, and cross-sectional area A wound on a ferromagnetic core, would have a voltage given by, </s></p><p n="p11.54"><s n="s1.1;p11.54"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0228d-form.001"/> </s></p><p n="p12.54"><s n="s1.1;p12.54">Whereii is the current and L is the inductance (Henry's) </s></p><p n="p13.54"><s n="s1.1;p13.54">It can be seen that inductance has a relation to current. </s></p><p n="p14.54"><s n="s1.1;p14.54">The relationship between the inductance (L) and the number of turns (N) is: </s></p><p n="p15.54"><s n="s1.1;p15.54"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0228d-form.002"/> </s></p><p n="p16.54"><s n="s1.2;p16.54">Taking logarithms gives log <hi rend="sub">10</hi><hi rend="italic">k</hi> + log <hi rend="sub">10</hi><hi rend="italic">N</hi>. </s><s n="s2.2;p16.54">In a single layered coil  = 2, however in multi-layer coils  is slightly different from this value. </s></p><p n="p17.54"><s n="s1.2;p17.54">Inductors can act as low-pass filters. </s><s n="s2.2;p17.54">This means that they only let through wavelengths of a lower frequency. </s></p><p n="p18.54"><s n="s1.3;p18.54">Harmonics can be present in circuits. </s><s n="s2.3;p18.54">Harmonics is the distortion of wavelengths and frequency. </s><s n="s3.3;p18.54">In a normal circuit the current waveform is sinusoidal, however this can be changed due to the addition of other electrical components, hence causing harmonics in the system. </s></p><p n="p19.54"><s n="s1.1;p19.54">For more theory read the appendices of the briefing sheet included in this report. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined">3.Apparatus</head><p n="p20.54"><s n="s1.1;p20.54">Variable autotransformer 0 - 275 ac (Variac, Regavolt, or equivalent) </s></p><p n="p21.54"><s n="s1.1;p21.54">Isolating transformer with connecting leads </s></p><p n="p22.54"><s n="s1.1;p22.54">Test box with inductor and switch to select number of turns (Fig 1 of briefing sheet) </s></p><p n="p23.54"><s n="s1.1;p23.54">Digital Storage Oscilloscope (Tektronix TDS 210) </s></p><p n="p24.54"><s n="s1.1;p24.54">Digital Wattmeter (Elcontrol Nanovip Plus) </s></p><p n="p25.54"><s n="s1.1;p25.54">2 connecting leads (BNC to BNC) for oscilloscope </s></p><p n="p26.54"><s n="s1.1;p26.54">3 connecting leads (4mm to 4mm) for circuit) </s></p><p n="p27.54"><s n="s1.1;p27.54">Shared access to Printer (HP DeskJet 930C) </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined">4.Method</head><div2><head>4.1. <hi rend="underlined">Preparation</hi></head><div3><head>4.1.1</head><p n="p28.54"><s n="s1.1;p28.54">The equipment was set up as shown in fig 2 of the briefing sheet. </s></p></div3><div3><head>4.1.2</head><p n="p29.54"><s n="s1.1;p29.54">The Variac was set to minimum voltage (fully anticlockwise). </s></p></div3><div3><head>4.1.3</head><p n="p30.54"><s n="s1.1;p30.54">The turns switch of the inductor box was set to 700. </s></p></div3><div3><head>4.1.4</head><p n="p31.54"><s n="s1.2;p31.54">The time base setting of the oscilloscope was set to 2.5ms/division. </s><s n="s2.2;p31.54">The Channel 1 voltage range was set to 10 Volts/division and the Channel 2 voltage range was set to 50 millivolts/division. </s></p></div3></div2><div2><head>4.2. <hi rend="underlined">Characteristics of an R-L Circuit</hi></head><div3><head>4.2.1</head><p n="p32.54"><s n="s1.1;p32.54">The wattmeter was switched on and checked to make sure that all values read zero. </s></p></div3><div3><head>4.2.2</head><p n="p33.54"><s n="s1.1;p33.54">The oscilloscope was adjusted, using the beam position controls, so that each trace formed a line across the middle of the screen. </s></p></div3><div3><head>4.2.3</head><p n="p34.54"><s n="s1.2;p34.54">The power to the Variac was switched on using the switch on the side of the box. </s><s n="s2.2;p34.54">The output voltage of the Variac was slowly increased until the voltage on the wattmeter read 20V. </s></p></div3><div3><head>4.2.4</head><p n="p35.54"><s n="s1.2;p35.54">The r.m.s voltage (in Volts), r.m.s current (in milliAmps), power (in Watts), and power factor (read from section labelled cos) were recorded from the wattmeter. </s><s n="s2.2;p35.54">The same measurements were recorded when <hi rend="italic">N</hi> (the number of turns) = 975, 1250, 1525, and 1800. </s></p></div3><div3><head>4.2.5</head><p n="p36.54"><s n="s1.8;p36.54">The turns switch was set back so that <hi rend="italic">N</hi> = 1250. </s><s n="s2.8;p36.54">The traces on the oscilloscope were lined up so that the mean values were on the centre line of the oscilloscope. </s><s n="s3.8;p36.54">The horizontal cursors were set up by pressing CURSOR then setting up VOLTAGE on the Type menu. </s><s n="s4.8;p36.54">The SOURCE was set to CH1. </s><s n="s5.8;p36.54">The cursors were placed at the top and bottom of the waveform giving the peak-to-peak voltage. </s><s n="s6.8;p36.54">This voltage was recorded and a hard copy of the trace was produced. </s><s n="s7.8;p36.54">The hard copy was obtained by pressing RUN/STOP and then HARD COPY. This SOURCE was then set to CH2. </s><s n="s8.8;p36.54">The process to produce a hard copy of the trace was then repeated. </s></p></div3><div3><head>4.2.6</head><p n="p37.54"><s n="s1.3;p37.54">The vertical cursors were then used by setting TIME on the Type menu. </s><s n="s2.3;p37.54">The cursors were lined up on the zero crossing points of the two waveforms. </s><s n="s3.3;p37.54">The time difference between these zero crossings was recorded. </s></p></div3></div2><div2><head>4.3. <hi rend="underlined">Harmonic Analysis of the Voltage and Current Waveforms</hi></head><div3><head>4.3.1</head><p n="p38.54"><s n="s1.7;p38.54">The MATH button and FFT CH1 on the oscilloscope were pressed. </s><s n="s2.7;p38.54">The sec/div control was adjusted to read 125Hz/div. </s><s n="s3.7;p38.54">The RUN/STOP button was pressed to freeze the trace. </s><s n="s4.7;p38.54">The CURSOR button was pressed and the SOURCE was set to MATH. The vertical cursors were set up setting the TYPR to FREQUENCY. The first large vertical line was checked to be at 50 HZ, the next large line at 150 Hz and the third line at 250 Hz. </s><s n="s5.7;p38.54">The horizontal cursors were then set up by setting up MAGNITUDE on the Type menu. </s><s n="s6.7;p38.54">These cursors were then used to measure the voltage at the first and fifth harmonics. </s><s n="s7.7;p38.54">A hard copy was obtained by pressing HARD COPY. </s></p></div3><div3><head>4.3.2</head><p n="p39.54"><s n="s1.5;p39.54">The RUN/STOP button was then pressed to de-freeze the trace. </s><s n="s2.5;p39.54">The MATH button and FFT CH2 on the oscilloscope were pressed. </s><s n="s3.5;p39.54">The RUN/STOP was button was pressed to freeze the trace. </s><s n="s4.5;p39.54">The current was recorded at the first and fifth harmonics as above. </s><s n="s5.5;p39.54">A hard copy was obtained in the usual manner. </s></p></div3></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined">5.Results</head><table id="BAWE_0228d-tab.001"><head rend="bold">Table 1</head><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p40.54"><s rend="italic" n="s1.1;p40.54">This table shows how the voltage, current, power and power factor changed in relation to number of turns. </s></p><p n="p41.54"><s n="s1.2;p41.54">The hard copies of the waveforms produced can be found in the graph section. </s><s n="s2.2;p41.54">The main results of the waveforms can be found here: </s></p><list type="simple"><item>Peak-to-peak voltage (CH1) = 27.2 + 27.2 = 54.4 V</item><item>Peak-to-peak voltage (CH2) = 58.0 + 58.0 = 116.0 mV </item></list><list type="simple"><item>Magnitude at 50Hz (CH1) = 25.0 dB</item><item>Magnitude at 250Hz (CH2) = -9.78 dB</item><item>Magnitude at 50Hz (CH2) = -29.0 dB</item><item>Magnitude at 250Hz (CH2) = -68.6 dB</item></list><table id="BAWE_0228d-tab.002"><head rend="bold">Table 2</head><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p42.54"><s rend="italic" n="s1.1;p42.54">The raw data for the graph of log10 Inductance against log10 N turns. </s></p><p n="p43.54"><s n="s1.1;p43.54">The method of calculation for this data can be found in the appendices of the briefing sheet included with this report. </s></p><p n="p44.54"><s n="s1.1;p44.54">was found from the gradient of the graph to be 1.915. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined">6.Analysis</head><p n="p45.54"><s n="s1.7;p45.54">The first set of data displayed in Table 1 shows that as the number of turns go up there is a decrease in current, power and power factor. </s><s n="s2.7;p45.54">The voltage stays fairly constant. </s><s n="s3.7;p45.54">Power is related to current so a decrease in current means a decrease in power. </s><s n="s4.7;p45.54">The power factor is the cosine of the phase angle between voltage and current. </s><s n="s5.7;p45.54">Looking at figure 1 in the graph section it is shown that as the number of turns increased the inductance of the system also increased. </s><s n="s6.7;p45.54">An increase in inductance gives an increase in phase angle. </s><s n="s7.7;p45.54">This is shown because the power factor goes down as inductance increases. </s></p><p n="p46.54"><s n="s1.1;p46.54">Increasing the inductance causes a decrease in current, power and power factor. </s></p><p n="p47.54"><s n="s1.4;p47.54">The peak voltage obtained from the oscilloscope was 27.2V. However this was not in r.m.s voltage. </s><s n="s2.4;p47.54">The peak voltage had to be divided by 2 to obtain the r.m.s voltage. </s><s n="s3.4;p47.54">The r.m.s voltage calculated from the waveform was 19.23V. This was quite close to the wattmeter reading of 20.2V. </s><s n="s4.4;p47.54">(Figure 2 graph section) </s></p><p n="p48.54"><s n="s1.2;p48.54">The peak current obtained from the oscilloscope was 58.0mA. The r.m.s value was calculated by dividing the peak current by 2. </s><s n="s2.2;p48.54">The r.m.s current was 41mA. This again was close to the wattmeter reading of 38.1mA. </s></p><p n="p49.54"><s n="s1.3;p49.54">The power factor calculated from the waveform was 0.71. </s><s n="s2.3;p49.54">This does not differ much from the wattmeter reading of 0.61. </s><s n="s3.3;p49.54">(Figure 3 graph section) </s></p><p n="p50.54"><s n="s1.3;p50.54">By changing the settings of the oscilloscope to produce in results in dB the magnitude of the waveforms were emphasised rather than the shape. </s><s n="s2.3;p50.54">The oscilloscope showed a voltage magnitude of 25.0dB. A voltage magnitude calculated from the waveform data (20log <hi rend="sub">10</hi> 19.23V) gave a magnitude of 25.68dB which was very close to the oscilloscope value. </s><s n="s3.3;p50.54">(Figure 4 graph section) </s></p><p n="p51.54"><s n="s1.2;p51.54">The oscilloscope showed a current magnitude - 29.0dB. The current magnitude calculated from the waveform data (20log <hi rend="sub">10</hi> 41mA) gave a magnitude of - 27.74dB which was again close to the oscilloscope value. </s><s n="s2.2;p51.54">(Figure 5 graph section) </s></p><p n="p52.54"><s n="s1.2;p52.54">The harmonics of the circuit had a period of 50Hz but were difficult to read after the 5 <hi rend="sup">th</hi> harmonic. </s><s n="s2.2;p52.54">The inductor acted as low-pass filter and filtered out the higher harmonics. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined">7.Conclusions</head><p n="p53.54"><s n="s1.5;p53.54">Increasing the number of turns on an inductor increased the inductance of the system. </s><s n="s2.5;p53.54">This in turn increased the phase angle between the current and voltage causing the current to lag further and further behind the voltage. </s><s n="s3.5;p53.54">This caused the current in the circuit to decrease. </s><s n="s4.5;p53.54">The decrease in current caused a decrease in power. </s><s n="s5.5;p53.54">Because the phase angle increases as inductance increases the power factor decreased. </s></p><p n="p54.54"><s n="s1.2;p54.54">Harmonics were present in the system and had a period of 50Hz. </s><s n="s2.2;p54.54">They were filtered out after the 5 <hi rend="sup">th</hi> harmonic because inductors act as low-pass filters. </s></p></div1></body><back><div1 type="bibliography"><head rend="underlined">8.Bibliography</head><p>1. How Stuff Works - Inductors</p><p><seg type="URL" n="http://www.howstuffworks.com/inductor.htm"/></p></div1><div1 type="appendix"><head rend="underlined">9. Appendix 1 - Graphs</head><p/></div1><div1 type="appendix"><head rend="underlined">10. Appendix 2 - Briefing Sheet</head><p/></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
