<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_0229d" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>"No, Ernest, don't talk about action. It is the last resource of those who know not how to dream." How nearly, whether obliquely or directly, does Oscar Wilde's work approach Ireland?</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">Language used in quote: <foreign id="English">English</foreign></note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">deleted: header: page and student numbers
</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">2</p><p n="date">2005-12</p><p n="module title">Anglo-Irish Literature</p><p n="module code">EN255</p><p n="genre family">Essay</p><p n="discipline">other</p><p n="disciplinary group">AH</p><p n="grade">M</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">5224</p><p n="number of s-units">125</p><p n="number of p">23</p><p n="number of tables">0</p><p n="number of figures">0</p><p n="number of block quotes">17</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">0</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">0</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">41.8</p><p n="average s-units per p">5.4</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">f</p><p n="year of birth">1983</p><p n="first language">English</p><p n="education">UKA</p><p n="course">English</p><p n="student ID">0229</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><docTitle><titlePart>"No, Ernest, don't talk about action. It is the last resource of those who know not how to dream." How nearly, whether obliquely or directly, does Oscar Wilde's work approach Ireland?</titlePart></docTitle></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="section"><p n="p1.23"><s n="s1.5;p1.23">The whole of Oscar Wilde's writing, like the man himself, is a contradiction. </s><s n="s2.5;p1.23">John Sloan, calls England Wilde's 'mother country'<ref target="BAWE_0229d-ftnote.001"/>, and his society plays are set in the upper class echelons of England, supporting the general public's view that he was a born Englishman. </s><s n="s3.5;p1.23">And yet, Wilde spent much of his life in homage to that well-known Anglo-Irish villain, Count Dracula. </s><s n="s4.5;p1.23">Like the Count, whose knowledge of English geography surpasses that of his English guest's<ref target="BAWE_0229d-ftnote.002"/>, Wilde was able to be 'more English than the English themselves'<ref target="BAWE_0229d-ftnote.003"/> due to his position as an outsider, an Irishman who said himself that he was 'not English', but 'Irish which is quite another thing'.<ref target="BAWE_0229d-ftnote.004"/> Not only did he classify himself as Irish, but also his work; as Sloan states, 'In artistic matters, Wilde consistently identified himself with a new 'Celtic School' of literature'.<ref target="BAWE_0229d-ftnote.005"/> Hence, there is clearly a paradoxical discussion occurring in the criticism concerned with Wilde's nationality, implying that an appreciation of his work and his themes cannot ignore the 'Irish Question'<ref target="BAWE_0229d-ftnote.006"/> of the man himself and the influence that his schizophrenic cultural background had on his writing. </s><s n="s5.5;p1.23">In investigating this influence, I will examine to what extent Wilde approaches Ireland, whether directly or obliquely, in the following essay. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0229d-ftnote.001"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Peter Sloan, <hi rend="underlined">Authors in Context: Oscar Wilde</hi> (Oxford: Penguin, 2003), 4. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0229d-ftnote.002"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Bram Stoker, <hi rend="underlined">Dracula</hi> (Oxford: Oxford University Press, 1998), 31. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0229d-ftnote.003"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Jerusha McCormack, ed., <hi rend="underlined">Wilde the Irishman</hi> (New Haven and London: Yale University Press, 1998), 85. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0229d-ftnote.004"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Richard Ellmann, <hi rend="underlined">Oscar Wilde</hi>, (London: Penguin, 1980), 352, quoted in Sloan 21. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0229d-ftnote.005"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Sloan, 21. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0229d-ftnote.006"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">McCormack, 2. </s></p></note><p n="p2.23"><s n="s1.20;p2.23">It is not surprising that Wilde is considered to be one of the greatest <hi rend="italic">English</hi> authors of all time. </s><s n="s2.20;p2.23">His transformation into a dandy at Oxford, along with his promotion as a typical English aristocrat by the tourist industry, have helped to sustain this myth. </s><s n="s3.20;p2.23">Moreover, there are only two direct references to Wilde's country of birth in <hi rend="underlined">The Works of Oscar Wilde</hi> (this does not include lectures or letters). </s><s n="s4.20;p2.23">Mrs Cheveley, in <hi rend="underlined">An Ideal Husband</hi>, briefly mentions her desire to 'teach the English to talk, and the Irish to listen'<ref target="BAWE_0229d-ftnote.007"/>, and the narrator of <hi rend="underlined">A Portrait of Mr. W. H.</hi> </s><s n="s5.20;p2.23">tells the reader that he has been discussing 'Macpherson, Ireland, and Chatterton'<ref target="BAWE_0229d-ftnote.008"/> of late. </s><s n="s6.20;p2.23">Yet many critics have recognised that, despite the lack of direct references to Wilde's native country, Ireland is a dominant albeit subtle theme throughout Wilde's work. </s><s n="s7.20;p2.23">This is most apparent in Wilde's indirect treatment of Anglo-Irish relations. </s><s n="s8.20;p2.23">The Great Famine took place just before Wilde was born<ref target="BAWE_0229d-ftnote.009"/>, engraving the image of his suffering fellow countrymen on the family conscience; indeed, his father wrote a report on the 'devastating effect of starvation and mass immigration'<ref target="BAWE_0229d-ftnote.010"/> on Ireland. </s><s n="s9.20;p2.23">It was the 'English insular unawareness of the realities of Irish life'<ref target="BAWE_0229d-ftnote.011"/> which proved fatal during the Famine Years, and was frequently the catalyst in Wilde's work and life to convince him to assume the 'pose of an Englishman', 'a clever strategy for challenging English prejudices about the Irish'<ref target="BAWE_0229d-ftnote.012"/>. </s><s n="s10.20;p2.23">However, in some writings, Wilde used no such pose and focused on specifically Irish themes, which one critic has described as 'anarchy and socialism, poverty and privilege, feminism and gender [and] imperialism'<ref target="BAWE_0229d-ftnote.013"/>. </s><s n="s11.20;p2.23">The theme of 'poverty' is especially apparent in the abundance of famine imagery throughout his work. </s><s n="s12.20;p2.23">Sloan mentions only one portrayal of famine in Wilde's work, saying that 'The terrifying vision of the famine in 'The Young King'... is seen to allude to Ireland during the Great Hunger'<ref target="BAWE_0229d-ftnote.014"/>. </s><s n="s13.20;p2.23">However, there are several other veiled references to this key event in Irish history. </s><s n="s14.20;p2.23">As Brecht's <hi rend="underlined">The Resistable Rise of Arturo Ui</hi> attacks contemporary German politics, thinly disguised by moving the action to America, so is Mother Russia in <hi rend="underlined">Vera</hi> 'a barely suppressed political correlative for Mother Ireland'<ref target="BAWE_0229d-ftnote.015"/>. </s><s n="s15.20;p2.23">Indeed, in revolutionary literature, the country for whose fight for freedom on is documenting is often referred to as 'Mother' (witness Brecht, again, in his poem, <hi rend="underlined">Deutschland</hi>), and nowhere is this more true than in <hi rend="underlined">Vera</hi>. </s><s n="s16.20;p2.23">Michael, one of the Nihilist revolutionaries, says, in a <hi rend="underlined">Hamlet</hi>-esque metaphor, that 'there is one who lies sick [he] would fain cure', depicting the invalid as 'Mother Russia'<ref target="BAWE_0229d-ftnote.016"/>. </s><s n="s17.20;p2.23">Russia is once again referred to as 'mother'<ref target="BAWE_0229d-ftnote.017"/> on the next page, and Alexis, the Czar's son, symbolically rejects his royal status for socialism in saying, 'I have no mother now but Russia'<ref target="BAWE_0229d-ftnote.018"/>. </s><s n="s18.20;p2.23">Nonetheless, the implied image of Ireland as the sacrificial, selfless, mother reaches its peak when Vera apostrophises Russia twice within a few lines, exclaiming, 'O crucified mother'<ref target="BAWE_0229d-ftnote.019"/>. </s><s n="s19.20;p2.23">In equating Ireland with Christ's crucifixion, Wilde elevates his native country's history, suggesting that future generations will prosper due to past sacrifices. </s><s n="s20.20;p2.23">This is supported by O' Donoghue's view that 'sacrifice as an idea pervades the Irish cultural tradition'<ref target="BAWE_0229d-ftnote.020"/>. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0229d-ftnote.007"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.3;pn1.1">Oscar Wilde, <hi rend="underlined">The Works of Oscar Wilde,</hi> ed. </s><s n="s2.3;pn1.1">J. B. </s><s n="s3.3;pn1.1">Foreman (London and Glasgow: Collins, 1948), 553. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0229d-ftnote.008"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Wilde, 1150. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0229d-ftnote.009"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Sloan, 1. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0229d-ftnote.010"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Sloan, 1. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0229d-ftnote.011"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Michael McConville, <hi rend="underlined">Ascendancy to Oblivion: The Story of the Anglo-Irish</hi> (London: Quartet Books, 1986), 228. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0229d-ftnote.012"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Sloan, 6. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0229d-ftnote.013"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Sloan, 99. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0229d-ftnote.014"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Sloan, 120. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0229d-ftnote.015"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Bernard O'Donoghue, 'The Journey to Reading Gaol: Sacrifice and Scapegoats in Irish Literature', <hi rend="underlined">Wilde the Irishman</hi>, ed. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">Jerusha McCormack (New Haven and London: Yale University Press, 1998), 110. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0229d-ftnote.016"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Wilde, 654. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0229d-ftnote.017"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Wilde, 655. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0229d-ftnote.018"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Wilde, 657. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0229d-ftnote.019"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Wilde, 681. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0229d-ftnote.020"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">O'Donoghue, 103. </s></p></note><p n="p3.23"><s n="s1.5;p3.23">These religious allusions to the suffering of the poor continue in Wilde's story, <hi rend="underlined">The Young King</hi>, which I have already mentioned with reference to Sloan. </s><s n="s2.5;p3.23">Concentrating on the eponymous character's struggle with his place in society, the theme of famine is portrayed much more literally here in his biblical-inspired dreams. </s><s n="s3.5;p3.23">In the vein of Joseph, the King dreams of 'faces pinched with famine'<ref target="BAWE_0229d-ftnote.021"/> in a weaving factory, representing the Irish, who are turned into 'slaves'<ref target="BAWE_0229d-ftnote.022"/>, wearing 'chains, though no eye beholds them'<ref target="BAWE_0229d-ftnote.023"/>, by and to the wealthy English, who could have helped the Irish much more during the Famine, had it not been for their ignorance of Ireland's out-of-date society (McConville tells us that, 'In the areas worst affected...many...had never in their lives seen money'<ref target="BAWE_0229d-ftnote.024"/>). </s><s n="s4.5;p3.23">Here is where Wilde's fine motif of greedy appetites in the upper classes, representative of capitalist England's avarice and particularly prevalent in the society plays, has its roots. </s><s n="s5.5;p3.23">In a telling example of dramatic irony, one of the workers describes the King to the King himself without knowing it. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0229d-ftnote.021"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Wilde, 226-7. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0229d-ftnote.022"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Wilde, 227. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0229d-ftnote.023"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Wilde, 227. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0229d-ftnote.024"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">McConville, 228. </s></p></note><quote lang="English">He is a man like myself. Indeed, there is but this difference between us - that he wears fine clothes while I go in rags, and that while I am weak from hunger he suffers not a little from overfeeding.<ref target="BAWE_0229d-ftnote.025"/></quote><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0229d-ftnote.025"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Wilde, 227. </s></p></note><p n="p4.23"><s n="s1.5;p4.23">Wilde's portrayal of the literal greed of the English reaches its apex in <hi rend="underlined">The Importance of Being Earnest</hi>. </s><s n="s2.5;p4.23">The character of Algy is obsessed with eating to the extent that he has a rather farcical argument with Jack about muffins, causing the latter to say to him, 'How can you sit there, calmly eating muffins when we are in this horrible trouble, I can't make out. </s><s n="s3.5;p4.23">You seem to me to be perfectly heartless." </s><ref target="BAWE_0229d-ftnote.026"/><s n="s4.5;p4.23">Many of the conversations and friendships in the play, as well as in <hi rend="underlined">The Picture of Dorian Gray</hi>, seem to revolve around the importance of dining out. </s><s n="s5.5;p4.23">This foreshadows Wilde's depiction of Lord Alfred Douglas, in <hi rend="underlined">De Profundis</hi>, as a 'coarse English aristocrat'<ref target="BAWE_0229d-ftnote.027"/> ultimately destroying Wilde, the personification of Ireland, with his taste for 'reckless dinners' at which 'too much was eaten and too much was drunk.'<ref target="BAWE_0229d-ftnote.028"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0229d-ftnote.026"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Wilde, 368. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0229d-ftnote.027"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Sloan, 148. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0229d-ftnote.028"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Wilde, 877. </s></p></note><p n="p5.23"><s n="s1.2;p5.23">On a more symbolic note, Wilde's medieval-style personification of Death and Avarice in <hi rend="underlined">The Young King</hi> approaches Ireland's negative history and future by showing the power of these abstract qualities, in the context of the numerous famines the country suffered and the yoke of English rule, to destroy Ireland at the lifting of a finger. </s><s n="s2.2;p5.23">Both emigration and an increased mortality rate dramatically reduced the Irish population, and the 'socially disgusting'<ref target="BAWE_0229d-ftnote.029"/> policies of the English in the post-Famine years, which included evicting 'thousands to raise lifestock'<ref target="BAWE_0229d-ftnote.030"/>, are reflected in the selfish attitude of Avarice, representing capitalist England, to the death of 'a third of her servants'.<ref target="BAWE_0229d-ftnote.031"/> Death's sweeping actions are ultimately shown to be only the consequence of Avarice's self-centred refusal to give Death a grain of corn, symbolic of Robert Peel's refusal, during the Great Hunger, to give corn directly to the hungry.<ref target="BAWE_0229d-ftnote.032"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0229d-ftnote.029"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">McConville, 240. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0229d-ftnote.030"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">McConville, 240. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0229d-ftnote.031"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Wilde, 229. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0229d-ftnote.032"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">McConville, 227. </s></p></note><quote lang="English">'I will not give thee anything", said Avarice, and she hid her hand in the fold of her raiment. And Death laughed, and took a cup, and dipped it into a pool of water, and out of the cup rose Ague. She passed through the great multitude, and a third of them lay dead.<ref target="BAWE_0229d-ftnote.033"/></quote><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0229d-ftnote.033"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Wilde, 229. </s></p></note><p n="p6.23"><s n="s1.9;p6.23">The phenomenon of the Big House and English absenteeism from Ireland plays a large part in Wilde's writing. </s><s n="s2.9;p6.23">Introduced in the latter half of the nineteenth century, Gladstone's Land Acts were largely inadequate, and this is reflected best of all in two of Wilde's stories, <hi rend="underlined">The Selfish Giant</hi> and <hi rend="underlined">The Canterville Ghost</hi>. </s><s n="s3.9;p6.23">In the latter, an ideal American family, comprised of a minister for a father, a 'New York Belle'<ref target="BAWE_0229d-ftnote.034"/> for a mother, one son and one daughter, descend on Canterville Hall, representative of the Big House, and become its temporary landlords. </s><s n="s4.9;p6.23">As an Irishman, Wilde has his revenge on the English by casting them in the part of the colonized, symbolized by the character of Sir Simon, but also gives England a chance to repent for its interference with Ireland by allowing them to empathise with the Irish position. </s><s n="s5.9;p6.23">Thus, Sir Simon is a representation of both the colonized and the colonizer. </s><s n="s6.9;p6.23">Presented as the personification of the Irish Question, the ghost is discussed at breakfast, an echo of my view earlier that the English merely considered Ireland, at a distance whilst appeasing their greed by eating, as a problem to solve. </s><s n="s7.9;p6.23">Sir Simon's refusal of the Rising Sun Lubricator corresponds to England's patronising, inadequate attempts to mollify Ireland, such as the Catholic Emancipation Act of 1829<ref target="BAWE_0229d-ftnote.035"/>, and is met with clear dismay by the Otis patriarch. </s><s n="s8.9;p6.23">Paradoxically, relieving Sir Simon of his chains (that is, Ireland of her total slavery to England in matters of government), which are symbolic of his prison term as a ghost, only makes him more a slave than ever, which is reminiscent of the phrase from <hi rend="underlined">The Young King</hi>, where the slaves are in 'chains, though no eye beholds them'.<ref target="BAWE_0229d-ftnote.036"/> Like Sir Simon, Ireland could only look to England for her release from her 'prison term'. </s><s n="s9.9;p6.23">In her case, she depended on England not only politically, but also financially, and, despite several bloody rebellions, independence could only truly be granted in the civilised form of a treaty. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0229d-ftnote.034"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Wilde, 194. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0229d-ftnote.035"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Roy Foster, <hi rend="underlined">Modern Ireland 1600-1972</hi> (England: Penguin, 1988), 606. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0229d-ftnote.036"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Wilde, 227. </s></p></note><quote lang="English">The next morning when the Otis family met at breakfast, they discussed the ghost at some length. The United States Minister was naturally a little annoyed to find that his present had not been accepted. "I have no wish," he said, to do the ghost any personal injury, and I must say that, considering the length of time he has been in the house, I don't think it is at all polite to throw pillows at him.... Upon the other hand," he continued, "he continued, "if he really declines to use the Rising Sun Lubricator, we shall have to take his chains from him. It would be quite impossible to sleep, with such a noise going on inside the bedrooms."<ref target="BAWE_0229d-ftnote.037"/></quote><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0229d-ftnote.037"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Wilde, 198. </s></p></note><p n="p7.23"><s n="s1.3;p7.23">The spirit of Sir Simon, however, proves to be invincible. </s><s n="s2.3;p7.23">His spirit is, in turn, a pun signifying the spirit of Ireland - that is, the unassailable determination of the Irish people whose rebellions eventually resulted in their independence from England. </s><s n="s3.3;p7.23">Resolved to scare away the Otis family, representing the English, Sir Simon betrays the Irish love of spectacle, teasingly asking for the reader's permission to speak of the theatre rather than supernatural mysteries. </s></p><quote lang="English">It was, however, an extremely difficult "make-up", if I may use such a theatrical expression in connection with one of the greatest mysteries of the supernatural...<ref target="BAWE_0229d-ftnote.038"/></quote><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0229d-ftnote.038"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Wilde, 203. </s></p></note><quote lang="English"> ...he went over his most celebrated performances, and...recalled to mind his last appearance as "Red Ruben, or the Strangled Babe", [and] his <hi rend="italic">debut</hi> as "Gaunt Gibeon, the Blood-sucker of Bexley Moor.<ref target="BAWE_0229d-ftnote.039"/></quote><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0229d-ftnote.039"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Wilde, 197-98. </s></p></note><p n="p8.23"><s n="s1.15;p8.23">As Owen Dudley Edwards says, ''The Selfish Giant' in particular suggests...the Giant as owner of the Big House with the little children as peasants and, presumably, Catholics." </s><ref target="BAWE_0229d-ftnote.040"/><s n="s2.15;p8.23">Denying the children permission to play in his garden, a place which evokes the idea of the 'Garden of England', Wilde pokes fun at the bureaucratic English government's creation of laws concerned with Ireland by building a 'high wall'<ref target="BAWE_0229d-ftnote.041"/> around the Giant's garden and erecting a sign stating, 'TRESPASSERS WILL BE PROSECUTED'<ref target="BAWE_0229d-ftnote.042"/>. </s><s n="s3.15;p8.23">Soon, however, a Utopia is created in which the children play happily in the Giant's garden with his permission, reminiscent of Wilde's suggestion that 'England [should] adopt some Irish qualities while shedding Irish territories." </s><ref target="BAWE_0229d-ftnote.043"/><s n="s4.15;p8.23">Only when the 'high wall', which perhaps foreshadows the tyrannical grip of the Soviets on Berlin, is knocked down with a 'great axe'<ref target="BAWE_0229d-ftnote.044"/> can the children play in beautiful surroundings. </s><s n="s5.15;p8.23">This mirrors Wilde's views on revolution in Ireland, implying that he supports violence as a means of gaining freedom for the next generation. </s><s n="s6.15;p8.23">On the one hand, this contradicts the quote in the title, and therefore the romantic image of the eternally-struggling, socially inferior Celt, epitomised in Wilde's aphorism, 'we are in all the gutter, but some of us are looking at the stars'<ref target="BAWE_0229d-ftnote.045"/>. </s><s n="s7.15;p8.23">On the other hand, however, it is important to remember that there have been not one, but eight Irish rebellions in less than four hundred years, the Easter Uprising of 1916 leading to the Anglo-Irish War of 1919-1921, resulting in the creation of the Irish Free State in 1922. </s><s n="s8.15;p8.23">In other words, Wilde may have said that, 'The creative instinct is strong in the Celt, and it is the Celt who leads in art'<ref target="BAWE_0229d-ftnote.046"/>, but he also acknowledged the necessary release of the Irish violent streak in order to achieve independence. </s><s n="s9.15;p8.23">This is clear in his <hi rend="underlined">The Soul of Man Under Socialism</hi>, in which he says, 'It is through disobedience that progress has been made, through disobedience and through rebellion'<ref target="BAWE_0229d-ftnote.047"/> and that , 'The very violence of a revolution may make the public grand and splendid for a moment'<ref target="BAWE_0229d-ftnote.048"/>. </s><s n="s10.15;p8.23">However, his defence of revolution, unsurprisingly, is most apparent in <hi rend="underlined">Vera</hi>, his play about revolution. </s><s n="s11.15;p8.23">The literal translation of the Nihilists' J.K. Rowlingesque Latin password, 'Per sanguinem ad libertatem'<ref target="BAWE_0229d-ftnote.049"/>, epitomises this defence. </s><s n="s12.15;p8.23">Moreover, pre-empting Theodor Adorno, who said that, 'After Auschwitz, writing poetry is barbaric'<ref target="BAWE_0229d-ftnote.050"/>, Wilde ironically rejects the idea that art can ever be useful (as he says in the preface to <hi rend="underlined">The Picture of Dorian Gray</hi>, 'All art is quite useless'<ref target="BAWE_0229d-ftnote.051"/>). </s><s n="s13.15;p8.23">Reading can only ever be 'a rehearsal for revolution'<ref target="BAWE_0229d-ftnote.052"/>, never a revolution in itself. </s><s n="s14.15;p8.23">For he states, implicitly referring to Ireland's future, that action is the one true weapon: 'I think little of pen and paper in revolution. </s><s n="s15.15;p8.23">One dagger will do more than a hundred epigrams'<ref target="BAWE_0229d-ftnote.053"/>. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0229d-ftnote.040"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Owen Dudley Edwards, "Impressions of an Irish Sphinx", <hi rend="underlined">Wilde the Irishman</hi>, ed. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">Jerusha McCormack (New Haven and London: Yale University Press, 1998), 59. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0229d-ftnote.041"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Wilde, 297. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0229d-ftnote.042"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Wilde, 297. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0229d-ftnote.043"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Kiberd, <hi rend="underlined">Wilde the Irishman</hi>, 21. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0229d-ftnote.044"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Wilde, 299. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0229d-ftnote.045"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Wilde, 417. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0229d-ftnote.046"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Wilde, 1050. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0229d-ftnote.047"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Wilde, 1082. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0229d-ftnote.048"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Wilde, 1094. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0229d-ftnote.049"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Wilde, 652. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">'Through blood to liberty.' </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0229d-ftnote.050"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Theodor Adorno, quoted <seg type="URL" n="http://www.ivrit.org/html/literary/alhashehitah.htm"/>, Tuesday 3rd Jan 2006, 19:13. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0229d-ftnote.051"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Wilde, 17. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0229d-ftnote.052"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Kiberd, <hi rend="underlined">Inventing Ireland</hi>, 280. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0229d-ftnote.053"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Wilde, 654. </s></p></note><p n="p9.23"><s n="s1.4;p9.23">On the subject of revolution, Wilde's writing promotes not only physical, but also vocal violence. </s><s n="s2.4;p9.23">His characters often engage in verbal duels designed to display the Irish love of talk for talk's sake; as I mentioned previously, Mrs Cheveley notes in <hi rend="underlined">An Ideal Husband</hi> that the Irish need to learn 'to listen'<ref target="BAWE_0229d-ftnote.054"/>, implying that their loquaciousness is both a curse as well as a blessing. </s><s n="s3.4;p9.23">Humorously mocking the Irish 'gift of the gab', Wilde tells us of the Selfish Giant's 'visit [to] his friend the Cornish ogre', noting the fact that he 'stayed with him for seven years' and that 'After the seven years were over, he had said all that he had to say, for his conversation was limited'.<ref target="BAWE_0229d-ftnote.055"/> In addition, two of the most comic battles are the muffin quarrel, which I have already discussed, in <hi rend="underlined">The Importance of Being Earnest</hi>, and the oral tennis between the Rocket and the Frog in <hi rend="underlined">The Remarkable Rocket</hi>. </s><s n="s4.4;p9.23">Their farewell conversation both sends up the English stereotype of the talkative Irishman and reveals the egotism of the aristocratic Englishman dominant throughout Wilde's work. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0229d-ftnote.054"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Wilde, 553. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0229d-ftnote.055"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Wilde, 297. </s></p></note><quote lang="English">Well, good-bye; I have enjoyed our conversation very much, I assure you. Conversation, indeed! said the Rocket. You have talked the whole time yourself. That is not conversation. Somebody must listen, answered the Frog, and I like to do all the talking myself. It saves time, and prevents arguments.<ref target="BAWE_0229d-ftnote.056"/></quote><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0229d-ftnote.056"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Wilde, 315. </s></p></note><p n="p10.23"><s n="s1.1;p10.23">This satirical episode anticipates Kiberd's view that Wilde 'question[s] the assumption that, just because the English are one thing, the Irish must be its opposite'<ref target="BAWE_0229d-ftnote.057"/> and introduces the major theme of the double in Wilde's work, a topic to which I shall return later. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0229d-ftnote.057"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Kiberd, 11. </s></p></note><p n="p11.23"><s n="s1.5;p11.23">For a writer whom Joseph O'Connor considers to be a 'revolutionary socialist'<ref target="BAWE_0229d-ftnote.058"/>, style over content is one of Wilde's paramount concerns. </s><s n="s2.5;p11.23">In contrast to his declaration in <hi rend="underlined">Vera</hi> that 'One dagger will do more than a hundred epigrams'<ref target="BAWE_0229d-ftnote.059"/>, Deirdre Toomey notes that 'Wilde's love of the aphorism (and his elevation of aphorism above narrative in <hi rend="italic">The Picture of Dorian Gray</hi>) is also typical of the oral mode'.<ref target="BAWE_0229d-ftnote.060"/> Furthermore, Wilde's multi-layered stories, many of which are, in fact, stories within stories, reflect the fact that storytellers had 'trudged the countryside for twenty five centuries'<ref target="BAWE_0229d-ftnote.061"/> in Ireland. </s><s n="s3.5;p11.23">For example, the Sparrow in <hi rend="underlined">The Happy Prince</hi> narrates his adventures to the eponymous character, as do the Soul and the Mermaid in <hi rend="underlined">The Fisherman and His Soul</hi>. </s><s n="s4.5;p11.23">He even goes as far as giving advice to the prospective <hi rend="italic">seanchai</hi> (Irish storyteller), saying that 'Every good storyteller nowadays starts with the end, and then goes onto the beginning, and concludes with the middle." </s><ref target="BAWE_0229d-ftnote.062"/><s n="s5.5;p11.23">His repetition of phrases is reminiscent of Frank Delaney's storyteller, who theatricalises storytelling and performs his own particular ritual at the beginning of a tale. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0229d-ftnote.058"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Joseph O'Connor, <hi rend="underlined">The Secret World of the Irish Male</hi> (London: Vintage, 1998), 148. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0229d-ftnote.059"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Wilde, 654. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0229d-ftnote.060"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Deirdre Toomey, <hi rend="underlined">Wilde the Irishman</hi>, 28. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0229d-ftnote.061"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Frank Delaney, <hi rend="underlined">Ireland: A Novel</hi> (London: Time Warner Books, 2004), 5. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0229d-ftnote.062"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Wilde, 303. </s></p></note><quote lang="English">And after a year was over the Soul came down to the shore of the sea and called to the young Fisherman, and he rose out of the deep, and said, Why dost thou call to me?<ref target="BAWE_0229d-ftnote.063"/></quote><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0229d-ftnote.063"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Wilde, 257. </s></p></note><quote lang="English">And after the second year was over, the Soul came down to the shore of the sea, and called to the young Fisherman and he rose out of the deep and said, Why dost thou call to me?<ref target="BAWE_0229d-ftnote.064"/></quote><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0229d-ftnote.064"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Wilde, 260. </s></p></note><quote lang="English">I'll be with you in a minute, he said to the audience, fixing the hat, the pipe, the opening out of the coat, the settling back in the chair, the surveying. Finally, with the pipe lighting, the matches on the small table beside his chair, he cleared his throat. <ref target="BAWE_0229d-ftnote.065"/></quote><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0229d-ftnote.065"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Delaney, 438. </s></p></note><quote lang="English">He lit his pipe. But that is an understatement: he performed the lighting of a pipe. From the filling of the tobacco to the lighting of the match must have lasted three or four minutes but no one in the theatre took their eyes off him.<ref target="BAWE_0229d-ftnote.066"/></quote><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0229d-ftnote.066"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Delaney, 453. </s></p></note><p n="p12.23"><s n="s1.2;p12.23">However, as is proven in <hi rend="underlined">Ireland: A Novel</hi>, storytelling, the greatest Irish talent, is hardly lucrative and often gruelling. </s><s n="s2.2;p12.23">The storyteller here personifies the eternally starving Ireland of the Famine years and Wilde's lifetime, hungry for both food and freedom, yet often subject to 'ignorant people' who have 'no use for stories' and give him 'no food'.<ref target="BAWE_0229d-ftnote.067"/> Wilde echoes this realistic depiction of the storyteller's plight in <hi rend="underlined">The Remarkable Rocket</hi> when the Page describes the Princess. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0229d-ftnote.067"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Delaney, 4. </s></p></note><quote lang="English">She was like a white rose before, said a young page to his neighbour, but she is like a red rose now; and the whole Court was delighted. For the next three days everybody went about saying, White rose, Red rose, Red rose, White rose, and the King gave orders that the Page's salary was to be doubled. As he received no salary at all this was not of much use to him, but it was considered a great honour, and duly published in the Court Gazette.<ref target="BAWE_0229d-ftnote.068"/></quote><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0229d-ftnote.068"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Wilde, 310. </s></p></note><p n="p13.23"><s n="s1.2;p13.23">Clearly, storytelling is a 'profession' which requires talent and yet rewards nothing. </s><s n="s2.2;p13.23">The stereotypical English view of the Irish means that the latter constantly play court jester to the former, and the Irish disgust at having to play a part is exemplified by Lord Arthur Savile's thoughts, who implicitly compares the Irish to unpaid actors, fated to live out future tragedies because of the actions (or lack of action) of England. </s></p><quote lang="English">Actors are so fortunate. They can choose whether they will appear in tragedy or comedy, whether they will suffer or make merry, laugh or shed tears. But in real life it is different. Most men and women are forced to perform parts for which they have no qualifications. Our Guildensterns play Hamlet for us, and our Hamlets have to jest like prince Hal. The world is a stage, but the play is badly cast.<ref target="BAWE_0229d-ftnote.069"/></quote><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0229d-ftnote.069"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Wilde, 174. </s></p></note><p n="p14.23"><s n="s1.5;p14.23">Another story which demonstrates the fact that the English were only interested in the Irish as a submissive colony who performed at their will, changing their religion and language to fit in with English habits, is <hi rend="underlined">The Birthday of the Infanta</hi>. </s><s n="s2.5;p14.23">Witness the eponymous Infanta's incessant commands to the Dwarf to dance with her<ref target="BAWE_0229d-ftnote.070"/>, despite his being prostrate with grief at his ugliness. </s><s n="s3.5;p14.23">Evidently, the Irish are welcome to take the stage, as long as the play is not a tragedy, for, as soon as it is, the stereotype of the spoilt English brat returns, intent on every day being his or her 'Birthday'. </s><s n="s4.5;p14.23">This is shown in the Infanta's response to the Dwarf's dying of a broken heart: 'For the future let those who come to play with me have no hearts'.<ref target="BAWE_0229d-ftnote.071"/> This image of the heartless English people, demanding that the Irish emulate their callousness and 'jump through hoops whenever [they] ask them'<ref target="BAWE_0229d-ftnote.072"/>, is brilliantly condensed in the following ironical sentence from <hi rend="underlined">The Canterville Ghost</hi>: 'Lady Barbara died of a broken heart at Tunbridge Wells'. </s><s n="s5.5;p14.23">Tunbridge Wells is famously the home of the 'Disgusted' middle classes' stiff upper lip, so this phrase, in its brevity, implies that the English are just as brief in their grief, in contrast to the Irish Catholics and their tradition of mourning the dead for a certain length of time in the form of singing and a wake<ref target="BAWE_0229d-ftnote.073"/>. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0229d-ftnote.070"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Wilde, 246. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0229d-ftnote.071"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Wilde, 247. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0229d-ftnote.072"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Wilde, 171. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0229d-ftnote.073"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">'Respect for the dead has always been a prominent feature of Irish culture. [...] A wide range of beliefs and practices were concerned with the issues of death and burial and, in former times, the waking of the dead was an important social occasion.' </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">Ireland Now, <seg type="URL" n="http://www.ireland-now.com/wakes.html"/>, 10th January, 19:31. </s></p></note><p n="p15.23"><s n="s1.5;p15.23">The idea that the English want the Irish to be duplicates of themselves is continued in <hi rend="underlined">The Importance of Being Earnest</hi>. </s><s n="s2.5;p15.23">Although Cecily is a member of the aristocracy, her prescriptive education from a strict governess mimics England's attempts to limit Catholic Education in the Penal Laws of 1695.<ref target="BAWE_0229d-ftnote.074"/> As Miss Prism says, 'The fact is, you have fallen lately, Cecily, into a bad habit of thinking for yourself. </s><s n="s3.5;p15.23">You should give it up. </s><s n="s4.5;p15.23">It is not quite womanly... </s><s n="s5.5;p15.23">Men don't like it'.<ref target="BAWE_0229d-ftnote.075"/> Matthew Arnold's 'essentially feminine'<ref target="BAWE_0229d-ftnote.076"/> Ireland being denied, just as the nineteenth century woman was, the civil right of education, is also depicted by the Colonel in <hi rend="underlined">Vera</hi>, who, in turn, represents the oppressive reign of English imperialism. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0229d-ftnote.074"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Foster, 602. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0229d-ftnote.075"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Wilde, 356. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0229d-ftnote.076"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Matthew Arnold, 'On a Study of Celtic Literature', <hi rend="underlined">Lectures and Essays in Criticism</hi>, ed. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">R. H. Super (Ann Arbor: University of Michigan Press, 1965) 347, quoted in Sloan, 83. </s></p></note><quote lang="English">-Can she read and write? -Ay, that she can, sir. -Then she is a dangerous woman. No peasant should be allowed to do anything of the kind. Till your fields, store your harvests, pay your taxes, and obey your masters - that is your duty. <ref target="BAWE_0229d-ftnote.077"/></quote><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0229d-ftnote.077"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Wilde, 650. </s></p></note><p n="p16.23"><s n="s1.1;p16.23">The Colonel's use of the adjective 'dangerous' echoes the maxim, 'A little knowledge is a dangerous thing'<ref target="BAWE_0229d-ftnote.078"/> and also anticipates 'what one critic has called the 'colonial calibanisation' of the Irish'.<ref target="BAWE_0229d-ftnote.079"/> Clearly, in focusing on Ireland, the English forgot Shakespeare, for, having forced English on the Irish, the latter used their linguistic skills in order to highlight the prejudice of their colonizer, becoming in the process, as McCormack noted, 'both colonizer and colonized'. <ref target="BAWE_0229d-ftnote.080"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0229d-ftnote.078"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Gary Martin, <seg type="URL" n="http://www.phrases.org.uk/meanings/10400.html"/>, 10th January 2006, 19:39. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0229d-ftnote.079"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Richard Kearney, 'Introduction' to <hi rend="underlined">The Irish Mind: Exploring Intellectual Traditions</hi> (Dublin: Wolfhound Press, 1985), quoted in Sloan, 167. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0229d-ftnote.080"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Jerusha McCormack, 'Introduction', <hi rend="underlined">Wilde the Irishman</hi>, ed. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">Jerusha McCormack, (New Haven and London: Yale University Press, 1998), 2. </s></p></note><p n="p17.23"><s n="s1.4;p17.23">One of the ways in which Wilde himself, having been 'condemned to speak the language of Shakespeare'<ref target="BAWE_0229d-ftnote.081"/>, takes revenge on the English through their own language is to satirise their views of the Irish, in order to show just how narrow-minded a race they were during his lifetime (observe 'Tenniel's <hi rend="italic">Punch</hi> cartoons of ape-like Paddies'<ref target="BAWE_0229d-ftnote.082"/>). </s><s n="s2.4;p17.23">The 'image of the stage Irishman'<ref target="BAWE_0229d-ftnote.083"/> is reversed in the presentation of the stereotyping, stereotypical Otis family, whose view of Ireland is limited to an interest in its history, rather than its future. </s><s n="s3.4;p17.23">This view of Ireland as a myth-making nation is satirised in Wilde's humanisation of the paranormal. </s><s n="s4.4;p17.23">Not only are we shown the inner monologue of the ghost, indignant because the Otises offer him 'the Rising Sun Lubricator, and throw pillows at his head'<ref target="BAWE_0229d-ftnote.084"/>, but the sense of routine in his 'life' humorously undercuts his supernatural existence: 'It was his solemn duty to appear in the corridor once a week, and to gibber from the large oriel window on the first and third Wednesday in every month'.<ref target="BAWE_0229d-ftnote.085"/> In addition, the recurrent blood stain both foreshadows the bloody battles of future Irish generations and, on a lighter note, mocks the eternal rationalism of the English in contrast to the romantic myth-making tendency of the Celts. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0229d-ftnote.081"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Kiberd, 35. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0229d-ftnote.082"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Foster, 363. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0229d-ftnote.083"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Kiberd, <hi rend="underlined">Wilde the Irishman</hi>, 11. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0229d-ftnote.084"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Wilde, 198. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0229d-ftnote.085"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Wilde, 202. </s></p></note><quote lang="English">Suddenly Mrs. Otis caught sight of a dull red stain on the floor just by the fireplace and, quite unconscious of what it really signified, said to Mrs. Umney, I am quite afraid something has been spilt there. -Yes, madam, replied the old housekeeper in a low voice, blood has been spilt on that spot..... It is the blood of Lady Eleanor de Canterville, who was murdered on that very spot.... The blood-stain has been much admired by tourists and others, and cannot be removed. -That is all nonsense, cried Washington Otis; Pinkerton's Champion Stain Remover and Paragon Detergent will clean it up in no time...<ref target="BAWE_0229d-ftnote.086"/></quote><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0229d-ftnote.086"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Wilde, 195. </s></p></note><p n="p18.23"><s n="s1.4;p18.23">Despite the comedy within the oxymoronic military language Wilde uses to portray the Otis twins' battle against Sir Simon, the scenes of mock warfare seem to re-enact the violence perpetrated by the English towards the Irish. </s><s n="s2.4;p18.23">On one occasion, he finds 'Washington Otis waiting for him there with the big garden -syringe; and being thus hemmed in by his enemies on all sides...he vanishe[s] into the great iron stove'. </s><s n="s3.4;p18.23">This episode echoes the fairy tale <hi rend="underlined">Hansel and Gretel</hi> and the children's escape from the witch by throwing her into the oven. </s><s n="s4.4;p18.23">In Wilde's version however, our sympathies are reversed, and it is the 'witch', Sir Simon, representing Ireland's persecuted Catholics, for whom we feel sorry. </s></p><p n="p19.23"><s n="s1.5;p19.23">The Otis twins' symbolic murder of Sir Simon reflects Wilde's major motif of the double. </s><s n="s2.5;p19.23">Represented often in Victorian literature, appearing in both <hi rend="underlined">Frankenstein</hi> and <hi rend="underlined">Dr. Jekyll and Mr Hyde</hi>, the <hi rend="italic">Doppelg(nger</hi> is the personification of another character's evil thoughts and intentions, and frequently exists only to be destroyed. </s><s n="s3.5;p19.23">As McCormack suggests, 'the colony is a repository for the 'other', a mirror-image which reverses the colonizer's vision of himself'<ref target="BAWE_0229d-ftnote.087"/>; thus, in the case of Wilde, his doubles are a clear representation of England and Ireland. </s><s n="s4.5;p19.23">This is especially evident in <hi rend="underlined">The Importance of Being Earnest</hi>, in which there is a fabulous mirroring of language and actions. </s><s n="s5.5;p19.23">Ernest and Algy are doubles, as are Gwendolen and Cecily, as well as Miss Prism and Chasuble, reflected in the echoes in their speech. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0229d-ftnote.087"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Jerusha McCormack, 'Introduction', <hi rend="underlined">Wilde the Irishman</hi>, ed. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">Jerusha McCormack, (New Haven and London: Yale University Press, 1998), 4. </s></p></note><quote lang="English">Were I fortunate enough to be Miss Prism's pupil, I would hang upon her lips. (Miss Prism glares.) I spoke metaphorically. My metaphor was drawn from bees. <ref target="BAWE_0229d-ftnote.088"/></quote><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0229d-ftnote.088"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Wilde, 341 </s></p></note><quote lang="English">Ripeness can be trusted. Young women are green. (Dr. Chasuble starts.) I spoke horticulturally. My metaphor was drawn from fruit.<ref target="BAWE_0229d-ftnote.089"/></quote><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0229d-ftnote.089"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Wilde, 345. </s></p></note><p n="p20.23"><s n="s1.3;p20.23">On the other hand, Wilde also implicitly illustrates just how different the 'distinctively and mystically 'Celtic''<ref target="BAWE_0229d-ftnote.090"/> Ireland was from the home of 'Victorian materialism'<ref target="BAWE_0229d-ftnote.091"/>, England. </s><s n="s2.3;p20.23">The character of Mr. Podgers in <hi rend="underlined">Lord Arthur Savile's Crime</hi> not only exhibits what Wilde's fellow writer and Irishman, Yeats, would have called a Celtic quality of mysticism, but also embodies the English pressure on the Irish to look and act in accordance with their wishes (for example, see Ford Madox Brown's <hi rend="underlined">The Irish Girl</hi>). </s><s n="s3.3;p20.23">Thus, Mr. Podgers is expected to display his skills in chiromancy, while at the same time satisfying the English stereotype of how a chiromantist should look. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0229d-ftnote.090"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">National Portrait Gallery, <hi rend="underlined">Conquering England: Ireland in Victorian London</hi> (London: National Portrait Gallery, 2005). </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0229d-ftnote.091"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">National Portrait Gallery, <hi rend="underlined">Conquering England: Ireland in Victorian London</hi> (London: National Portrait Gallery, 2005). </s></p></note><quote lang="English">Well, he is not a bit like a chiromantist. I mean he is not mysterious, or esoteric, or romantic-looking. He is a little, stout man, with a funny, bald head.... People are so annoying. All my pianists look like poets; and all my poets look exactly like pianists... <ref target="BAWE_0229d-ftnote.092"/></quote><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0229d-ftnote.092"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Wilde, 169. </s></p></note><p n="p21.23"><s n="s1.9;p21.23">The state of affairs turns sinister, however, when Lord Arthur Savile, whom Mr. Podgers informs that he will commit a murder, murders Mr Podgers himself. </s><s n="s2.9;p21.23">This is clearly an extreme metaphor for the long slow murder of Ireland by England - the murder of their independence, of their religion, and of their rights. </s><s n="s3.9;p21.23">Clearly, England's happiness lies, in their opinion, in the destruction of anything which attempts to show them the repulsiveness of their imperialism. </s><s n="s4.9;p21.23">Hence, Mr. Podger's murder represents England's suppression of her negative qualities. </s><s n="s5.9;p21.23">This suppression of the 'other' is a theme which also appears in <hi rend="underlined">The Canterville Ghost</hi>. </s><s n="s6.9;p21.23">As one critic has noted, 'The resident ghost is the ultimate commodity, who is released into death in exchange for a box of jewels. </s><s n="s7.9;p21.23">The ghostly is contained and repelled'.<ref target="BAWE_0229d-ftnote.093"/> Thus, Wilde contrasts Irish sacrifice with English profit. </s><s n="s8.9;p21.23">Ultimately, however, rather than viewing this conclusion as a cynical view of English materialism, it is possible to see it as an echo of Patrick Pearse's nationalistic 'aesthetic', which 'frequently celebrated the beauty of boys dying bravely in their prime, rather than growing into the compromises of adulthood'.<ref target="BAWE_0229d-ftnote.094"/> Yet this is an echo with a happy ending, for Virginia, the 'little child'<ref target="BAWE_0229d-ftnote.095"/> representative of Ireland's saviour in allowing the Angel of Death to come for Sir Simon, only goes missing briefly, and is not sacrificed. </s><s n="s9.9;p21.23">So although Wilde, as I have already argued, espoused the idea of a rebellion in Ireland in order to win independence, he evidently also did not believe that that rebellion should involve the sacrifice of youth. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0229d-ftnote.093"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Sloan, 137. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0229d-ftnote.094"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Foster, 477. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0229d-ftnote.095"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Wilde, 208. </s></p></note><p n="p22.23"><s n="s1.8;p22.23">Wilde shows a curiously Irish prizing of youth in his work, particularly in <hi rend="underlined">The Picture of Dorian Gray</hi>. </s><s n="s2.8;p22.23">As Owen Dudley Edwards has observed, 'The preservation of youth in <hi rend="italic">The Picture of Dorian Gray</hi> [is an] echo of <hi rend="italic">Tir na n-Og</hi>'<ref target="BAWE_0229d-ftnote.096"/>, the eponymous place being the Land of Youth. </s><s n="s3.8;p22.23">In this myth, the king asks a Druid how long he will rule, and the latter tells him forever, unless his son-in-law takes the crown from him.<ref target="BAWE_0229d-ftnote.097"/> Yet Wilde not only echoes Irish mythology in his work, but also the writing of his Anglo-Irish contemporaries. </s><s n="s4.8;p22.23">His only novel takes its inspiration from both Yeats's <hi rend="underlined">The Stolen Child</hi>, in which 'the 'real' person spirited away by fairies remains youthful and carefree, while the simulacrum ages and withers away'<ref target="BAWE_0229d-ftnote.098"/>, as well as his highly nationalistic play, <hi rend="underlined">Cathleen ni Houlihan</hi>, in which the 1798 Rebellion is re-imagined. </s><s n="s5.8;p22.23">Yeats personifies Ireland as a 'Poor Old Woman'<ref target="BAWE_0229d-ftnote.099"/>, who needs the young men's blood in order to become a 'young girl'<ref target="BAWE_0229d-ftnote.100"/> again. </s><s n="s6.8;p22.23">This rather vampiric image suggests a major theme of many of Wilde's works, in which 'the erotic animated female threatens to reify or emasculate the hero'<ref target="BAWE_0229d-ftnote.101"/>, and also hints at the major theme of vampirism in another Anglo-Irish author's - Bram Stoker - most famous work, <hi rend="underlined">Dracula</hi>. </s><s n="s7.8;p22.23">Evidently, Wilde's tone in writing about youth demonstrates much more than the purely aesthetic interest with which so many critics are concerned. </s><s n="s8.8;p22.23">Dorian Gray's end, 'with a knife in his heart'<ref target="BAWE_0229d-ftnote.102"/>, 'withered, wrinkled, and loathsome of visage'<ref target="BAWE_0229d-ftnote.103"/>, serves as a warning not to become vainly obsessed with one's youth, as does the 'beautiful boyish insouciance'<ref target="BAWE_0229d-ftnote.104"/> of Lord Arthur Savile, who becomes fixated on murdering anyone after Mr. Podgers warns him of his future as an assassin. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0229d-ftnote.096"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Edwards, Owen Dudley, 'Impressions of an Irish Sphinx', <hi rend="underlined">Wilde the Irishman</hi>, ed. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">Jerusha McCormack (New Haven and London: Yale University Press, 1998), 58. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0229d-ftnote.097"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">D.L. Ashliman, <seg type="URL" n="http://www.pitt.edu/~dash/oisin.html"/>, 10th January 2006, 19:28. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0229d-ftnote.098"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Owen Dudley Edwards, 'Impressions of an Irish Sphinx', <hi rend="underlined">Wilde the Irishman</hi>, ed. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">Jerusha McCormack (New Haven and London: Yale University Press, 1998), 42. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0229d-ftnote.099"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">W.B. Yeats, <hi rend="underlined">Selected Plays</hi>, ed. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">Richard Allen Cave (London: Penguin, 1997), 19. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0229d-ftnote.100"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">W.B. Yeats, <hi rend="underlined">Selected Plays</hi>, ed. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">Richard Allen Cave (London: Penguin, 1997), 28. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0229d-ftnote.101"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Sloan, 136. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0229d-ftnote.102"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Wilde, 167. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0229d-ftnote.103"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Wilde, 167. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0229d-ftnote.104"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Wilde, 173. </s></p></note><p n="p23.23"><s n="s1.3;p23.23">In conclusion, Wilde's writing may barely touch on the subject of Ireland directly, but it is certainly concerned with his native country in an oblique sense. </s><s n="s2.3;p23.23">Defying the narrow-minded English view of the Irish as a people existing only to be conquered, Wilde instead attempts to realise, in his work, George Bernard Shaw's witticism, 'England had conquered Ireland, so there was nothing for it but to come over and conquer England'.<ref target="BAWE_0229d-ftnote.105"/> He does this in challenging English prejudices concerning Ireland, evaluating what he believes to be the true characteristics of the Irish, such as their loquaciousness, their unassailable spirit and their prizing of youth, examining Anglo-Irish relations, particularly in the context of the Great Famine and placing himself firmly in the Anglo-Irish tradition by echoing other Anglo-Irish writers. </s><s n="s3.3;p23.23">Most significantly, however, he demonstrates that to be English and to be Irish is often one and the same thing. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0229d-ftnote.105"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">National Portrait Gallery. </s></p></note></div1></body><back><div1 type="bibliography"><head>Bibliography</head><p>Ashliman, D.L., <hi rend="underlined">Oisin in Tir na n-Og</hi>, <seg type="URL" n="http://www.pitt.edu/~dash/oisin.html"/>, 10<hi rend="sup">th</hi> January 2006, 19:28.</p><p>Delaney, Frank. <hi rend="underlined">Ireland: a Novel</hi>. London: Time Warner Books, 2004.</p><p>Graswurzelrevolution, <hi rend="underlined">Mein Brecht</hi>, <seg type="URL" n="http://www.graswurzel.net/226/brecht.shtml"/>, 10<hi rend="sup">th</hi> January 2006, 19:14.</p><p>Ireland Now, <seg type="URL" n="http://www.ireland-now.com/wakes.html"/>, 10<hi rend="sup">th</hi> January, 19:31.</p><p>Kiberd, Declan. <hi rend="underlined">Inventing Ireland: (check semi-colon in title) The Literature of the Modern Nation</hi>. London: Vintage, 1996.</p><p>McConville, Michael. <hi rend="underlined">Ascendancy to Oblivion: The Story of the Anglo-Irish</hi>. London: Quartet Books, 1986.</p><p>McCormack, Jerusha. Introduction. <hi rend="underlined">Wilde the Irishman</hi>. Ed. Jerusha McCormack. </p><p> New Haven and London: Yale University Press, 1998. </p><p>McCormack, Jerusha ed. <hi rend="underlined">Wilde the Irishman</hi>. New Haven and London: Yale University Press, 1998. </p><p>Toomey, Deirdre. "The Storyteller at Fault: Oscar Wilde and Irish Orality." McCormack.</p><p>Bourke, Angela. "Hunting Out the Fairies: E. F. Benson, Oscar Wilde and the Burning of Bridget Cleary." McCormack</p><p>Edwards, Owen Dudley. "Impressions of an Irish Sphinx." McCormack</p><p>McCormack, Jerusha. "The Wilde Irishman: Oscar as Aesthete and Anarchist."</p><p>O'Donoghue, Bernard. "The Journey to Reading Gaol: Sacrifice and Scapegoats in Irish Literature." </p><p><hi rend="underlined">Literary Corner</hi>, <seg type="URL" n="http://www.ivrit.org/html/literary/alhashehitah.htm"/>, Tuesday 3<hi rend="sup">rd</hi> Jan 2006, 19:13.</p><p>National Portrait Gallery. <hi rend="underlined">Conquering England: Ireland in Victorian London</hi>. London, National Portrait Gallery, 2005.</p><p>O'Connor, Joseph. <hi rend="underlined">The Secret World of the Irish Male</hi>. London: Vintage, 1998.</p><p>Shakespeare, William. <hi rend="underlined">The Illustrated Stratford Shakespeare</hi>. London: Chancellor Press, 1993.</p><p>Sloan, John. <hi rend="underlined">Authors in Context, Oscar Wilde.</hi> Oxford: Oxford University Press, 2003.</p><p>Stoker, Bram. <hi rend="underlined">Dracula</hi>. Oxford: Oxford University Press, 1998.</p><p>Wilde, Oscar. <hi rend="underlined">The Works of Oscar Wilde</hi>. Ed. J. B. Foreman. London and Glasgow: Collins, 1948.</p><p>Yeats, W. B. <hi rend="underlined">Selected Plays</hi>. Ed. Richard Allen Cave. London: Penguin, 1997.</p></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
