<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_0232a" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Green's Potential Theory</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">Language used in quote: <foreign id="English">English</foreign></note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">3</p><p n="date">2005-11</p><p n="module title">History of Mathematics</p><p n="module code">MA3E5</p><p n="genre family">Critique</p><p n="discipline">Mathematics</p><p n="disciplinary group">PS</p><p n="grade">M</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">1138</p><p n="number of s-units">60</p><p n="number of p">35</p><p n="number of tables">0</p><p n="number of figures">0</p><p n="number of block quotes">2</p><p n="number of formulae">14</p><p n="number of lists">1</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">0</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">19.0</p><p n="average s-units per p">1.7</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">m</p><p n="year of birth">1984</p><p n="first language">English</p><p n="education">UKA</p><p n="course">Mathematics</p><p n="student ID">0232</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><docTitle><titlePart rend="bold">Green's Potential Theory</titlePart></docTitle><titlePart rend="italic">A critique of Green's 'Essay on the Application of Mathematical Analysis to the Theories ofElectricity and Magnetism'</titlePart></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="section"><p n="p1.35"><s n="s1.4;p1.35">George Green published his <hi rend="italic">Essay</hi> by subscription in March 1828. </s><s n="s2.4;p1.35">Described by Green's advocate, Edward Bromhead as 'dead born'<hi rend="sup">1</hi>, the publication essentially went unnoticed. </s><s n="s3.4;p1.35">It was only in January 1845, nearly four years after Green's death that William Thomson (later Lord Kelvin) obtained a copy and, amazed by it contents, brought it to the attention of the leading French mathematicians of the time. </s><s n="s4.4;p1.35">Almost two hundred years on, Green's results are still frequently used by mathematicians and physicists alike; not only in electrical engineering, but also in a diverse range of modern applications from the theory of quantum electrodynamics to the study of the Mandelbrot set <hi rend="sup">2</hi>. </s></p><p n="p2.35"><s n="s1.1;p2.35">The <hi rend="italic">Essay</hi> ran to nearly eighty pages - we shall consider just a few of the preliminary results from the first section, analyse the proof given for the first theorem and then go on to discuss why this work was so remarkable. </s></p><p n="p3.35"><s n="s1.2;p3.35">Green began his <hi rend="italic">Essay</hi> by considering a single body through which electricity is arbitrarily distributed and a point <hi rend="italic">p</hi> located outside of the body. </s><s n="s2.2;p3.35">He denoted by <hi rend="italic">x', y', z '</hi> the rectangular co-ordinates of a particle within the body, by ρ ' the density of electricity in the particle, and by <hi rend="italic">r '</hi> the distance between the particle and <hi rend="italic">p.</hi> </s></p><p n="p4.35"><s n="s1.1;p4.35">He then defined a function <hi rend="italic">V</hi> representing the 'sum of all the particles of electricity divided by their respective distances from this point [<hi rend="italic">p</hi>]', </s></p><p n="p5.35"><s n="s1.1;p5.35"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0232a-form.001"/> </s></p><p n="p6.35"><s n="s1.1;p6.35">His opening claim, based on a result from Laplace's <hi rend="italic">Mécanique céleste,</hi> was that <hi rend="italic">V</hi> satisfies the equation </s></p><p n="p7.35"><s n="s1.1;p7.35"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0232a-form.002"/> </s></p><p n="p8.35"><s n="s1.1;p8.35">which he abridged to <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0232a-form.003"/>. </s></p><p n="p9.35"><s n="s1.5;p9.35">Green's next step was to consider the same function for a point <hi rend="italic">p</hi> located within the body. </s><s n="s2.5;p9.35">He showed that in this case <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0232a-form.004"/>. </s><s n="s3.5;p9.35">Green then used this equation to demonstrate that in a perfectly conducting body all of the 'electric fluid' is carried to the surface. </s><s n="s4.5;p9.35">In other words, that  = 0 for all points <hi rend="italic">p</hi> inside such a body. </s><s n="s5.5;p9.35">It was in presenting this result that Green coined the term 'potential function' - a particularly intuitive name for a function that describes the forces impelling and repelling particles (in this case 'of electricity') in a given system - the introduction of which Gray describes as Green's 'deepest insight'<hi rend="sup">3</hi>. </s></p><p n="p10.35"><s n="s1.1;p10.35">This demonstration was immediately followed by a theorem: </s></p><quote lang="English">"Let <hi rend="italic">U</hi> and <hi rend="italic">V</hi> be two continuous functions of the rectangular co-ordinates <hi rend="italic">x, y, z,</hi> whose differential coefficients do not become infinite at any point within a solid body of any form whatever; then will the triple integrals extending over the whole interior of the body, and those relative to <hi rend="italic">d </hi>, over its surface, of which <hi rend="italic">d </hi> represents an element: <hi rend="italic">d </hi> being an infinitely small line perpendicular to the surface, and measured from this surface towards the interior of the body."</quote><p n="p11.35"><s n="s1.2;p11.35">This theorem is now known as Green's theorem and was one of Green's most significant accomplishments (along with what are now called Green's functions; introduced later in the <hi rend="italic">Essay).</hi> </s><s n="s2.2;p11.35">Essentially it relates the properties of the two functions inside the body with those on the surface. </s></p><p n="p12.35"><s n="s1.1;p12.35">Green began his proof by considering the triple integral </s></p><p n="p13.35"><s n="s1.1;p13.35"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0232a-form.005"/> </s></p><p n="p14.35"><s n="s1.1;p14.35">for which integration by parts gave </s></p><p n="p15.35"><s n="s1.1;p15.35"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0232a-form.006"/> </s></p><p n="p16.35"><s n="s1.1;p16.35"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0232a-form.007"/> </s></p><p n="p17.35"><s n="s1.1;p17.35"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0232a-form.008"/> </s></p><p n="p18.35"><s n="s1.1;p18.35">where <hi rend="italic">U', V'</hi> and <hi rend="italic">U'', V''</hi> were used to denote the values of <hi rend="italic">U</hi> and <hi rend="italic">V</hi> at the lower and upper limits of the integral respectively. </s></p><p n="p19.35"><s n="s1.1;p19.35">He then observed that, since <hi rend="italic">d </hi> was defined to be perpendicular to the surface, he could make the following substitutions </s></p><p n="p20.35"><s n="s1.1;p20.35"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0232a-form.009"/> at the upper limit in <hi rend="italic">x</hi> </s></p><p n="p21.35"><s n="s1.1;p21.35"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0232a-form.010"/> ,at the lower limit in <hi rend="italic">x</hi> </s></p><p n="p22.35"><s n="s1.1;p22.35">and analogous substitutions for the other limits, giving rise to the expression </s></p><list type="bulleted"><item><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0232a-form.011"/></item><item>{bawe_formula</item><item><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0232a-form.012"/></item></list><p n="p23.35"><s n="s1.1;p23.35">Green also noted that the integrals with respect to <hi rend="italic">d </hi>' , together with the integrals with respect to <hi rend="italic">d </hi>'' cover the whole surface of the body, and hence reduced the expression to </s></p><p n="p24.35"><s n="s1.1;p24.35"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0232a-form.013"/>. </s></p><p n="p25.35"><s n="s1.1;p25.35">Finally, by noting that inverting the roles of <hi rend="italic">U</hi> and <hi rend="italic">V</hi> would not alter the value of the expression, Green obtained the </s></p><p n="p26.35"><s n="s1.1;p26.35">equation </s></p><p n="p27.35"><s n="s1.1;p27.35"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0232a-form.014"/> </s></p><p n="p28.35"><s n="s1.1;p28.35">completing the proof of his theorem. </s></p><p n="p29.35"><s n="s1.4;p29.35">Green's <hi rend="italic">Essay</hi> is remarkable for a variety of reasons. </s><s n="s2.4;p29.35">One of the most significant is Green's modest education. </s><s n="s3.4;p29.35">Green was born in 1793 the son of a baker. </s><s n="s4.4;p29.35">At the age of eight he was sent to Robert Goodacre's Academy in Nottingham. </s></p><p n="p30.35"><s n="s1.3;p30.35">Challis describes Goodacre as an enthusiastic science teacher <hi rend="sup">4</hi> and this may well have fuelled Green's interest in physics. </s><s n="s2.3;p30.35">However Green only remained at the academy for four terms at which point he returned to work at his father's bakery. </s><s n="s3.3;p30.35">He was to receive no further teaching until his move to Cambridge in 1833, five years after the publication of his <hi rend="italic">Essay.</hi> </s></p><p n="p31.35"><s n="s1.4;p31.35">In 1807, when Green was fourteen, his father built a windmill at Sneinton, then a village about a mile from Nottingham. </s><s n="s2.4;p31.35">He left the bakery to help operate the mill and it is likely that this is where he would have spent calmer days studying mathematics. </s><s n="s3.4;p31.35">However, it is not known how Green came acquainted with the advanced mathematics he appeared to be studying - there were still no public libraries at this point. </s><s n="s4.4;p31.35">One theory is that Green may have known John Toplis, a Cambridge graduate in mathematics living in Nottingham and an avid promoter of French mathematics; </s></p><quote lang="English">"There is no proof that John Toplis was George Green's mentor but circumstantial evidence suggests strongly that he was guiding him in the new mathematics and helped him with the French he undoubtedly acquired in order to read the works of other French mathematicians, such as Lacroix, Poisson and Biot."<hi rend="sup">5</hi></quote><p n="p32.35"><s n="s1.3;p32.35">The opening of Bromley House (later the Nottingham Subscription Library) in 1816 was undoubtedly a tremendous boost to Green's resources. </s><s n="s2.3;p32.35">Green joined the library in 1823 and there he would have had access to a modest collection of textbooks and scientific journals. </s><s n="s3.3;p32.35">These journals would have included abstracts from papers published in foreign journals and hence would have given Green access to some of the new Mathematics being developed abroad. </s></p><p n="p33.35"><s n="s1.4;p33.35">Green's essay was also strikingly original. </s><s n="s2.4;p33.35">British mathematicians were still relying on Newtonian methods. </s><s n="s3.4;p33.35">Their research centred around traditional concepts such as mechanics, optics, astronomy and planetary motion. </s><s n="s4.4;p33.35">Green's calculus, on the other hand, was very analytical - reflecting a sound understanding of methods recently developed in France by the likes of Laplace and Poisson - and his examples were based on the new physics of the time: electricity and magnetism, 'the most interesting of physical sciences'<hi rend="sup">6</hi>. </s></p><p n="p34.35"><s n="s1.4;p34.35">It could perhaps be argued that Green's methods were not always particularly rigorous and the notions of 'electric fluid' and 'particles of electricity' he used seem somewhat vague compared to our modern terminology of charge and electrons. </s><s n="s2.4;p34.35">However his ideas were particularly original and expressed with exceptional clarity. </s><s n="s3.4;p34.35">Most striking of all however, is the longevity if his results. </s><s n="s4.4;p34.35">The fact that mathematicians and physicist are forever finding new applications for Green's techniques is evidence of just how flexible and powerful they really are. </s></p><p n="p35.35"><s n="s1.1;p35.35"><name type="student name"/>, University of <name type="university"/>, 28 <hi rend="sup">th</hi> November 2005 </s></p></div1></body><back><div1 type="bibliography"><head rend="bold">Bibliography</head><p>Cannell, D. M., 1988, <hi rend="italic">George Green: Miller and Mathematician,</hi> Nottingham.</p><p>Challis, L. J., 1987, <hi rend="italic">George Green - Miller, Mathematician and Physicist,</hi> Mathematical Spectrum, volume 20, pages 45-52. Gray, J. J., 1993, <hi rend="italic">There was a Jolly Miller,</hi> New Scientist, issue 1881, pages 24-27.</p><p>Gray, J. J., 1994, <hi rend="italic">Green and Green's Functions,</hi> The Mathematical Intelligencer, volume 16, issue 1, pages 45-47.</p><p>Green, G., 1828, <hi rend="italic">An Essay on the Application of Mathematical Analysis to the Theories of Electricity and Magnetism,</hi> Nottingham. Wallis, P. J., 1978, <hi rend="italic">Green, George,</hi> Dictionary of Scientific Biography, C. C. Gillispie (editor), New York, volume XV, pages 199-201.</p><p>4 See Challis [1987], page 46.</p><p>5 From Cannell [1988].</p><p>6 Quoted in Gray [1993], page 24.</p></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
