<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_0232c" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>It is the early 1830s. Write a letter of advice to a very good student of yours who is about travel abroad to study Mathematics.</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">Language used in quote: <foreign id="French">French</foreign></note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">3</p><p n="date">2005-10</p><p n="module title">History of Mathematics</p><p n="module code">MA3E5</p><p n="genre family">Empathy writing</p><p n="discipline">Mathematics</p><p n="disciplinary group">PS</p><p n="grade">D</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">567</p><p n="number of s-units">23</p><p n="number of p">9</p><p n="number of tables">0</p><p n="number of figures">0</p><p n="number of block quotes">2</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">0</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">0</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">24.7</p><p n="average s-units per p">2.6</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">m</p><p n="year of birth">1984</p><p n="first language">English</p><p n="education">UKA</p><p n="course">Mathematics</p><p n="student ID">0232</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><docTitle><titlePart><hi rend="bold">It is the early 1830s. Write a letter of advice to a very good student of yours who is about travel abroad to study Mathematics.</hi> <hi rend="bold"> Describe recent developments in the theory of functions of a real variable.</hi> </titlePart></docTitle></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="section"><p n="p1.9"><s n="s1.1;p1.9">Dear Student, </s></p><p n="p2.9"><s n="s1.4;p2.9">We live at an exciting time in the development of real analysis. </s><s n="s2.4;p2.9">Over the past ten years Cauchy has done a great deal to formalise the fundamental concepts that our techniques and theories rely upon. </s><s n="s3.4;p2.9">I refer in particular to the lecture notes (<hi rend="italic">Cours d'analyse</hi>) he prepared for the <hi rend="italic">Ecole Polytechnique</hi>, Paris in 1821. </s><s n="s4.4;p2.9">These notes contain definitions for limits, real functions, infinitesimals, and convergence that are more rigorous than ever before. </s></p><p n="p3.9"><s n="s1.3;p3.9">There remains however some uncertainty around the key concept of continuity. </s><s n="s2.3;p3.9">Even Cauchy himself appears to treat continuity with inconsistency. </s><s n="s3.3;p3.9">His definition for continuity is stated on pages 34-35 of <hi rend="italic">Cours d'analyse</hi>, </s></p><quote lang="French">"<hi rend="italic">la fonction f(x) restera continue par rapport à x entre les limites données, si, entre ces limites, un accroissement infiniment petit de la variable produit toujours un accroissement infiniment petit de la fonction elle-même.</hi> "<ref target="BAWE_0232c-ftnote.001"/></quote><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0232c-ftnote.001"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Cauchy, 1821, <hi rend="italic">Cours d'analyse de l'École Royale Polytechnique, 1ère partie</hi>, Bottazzini (ed.), 1992, Clueb, Bologna </s></p></note><p n="p4.9"><s n="s1.2;p4.9">In English, <hi rend="italic">f</hi>(<hi rend="italic">x</hi>) is continuous between the given limits, if, between these limits, an infinitesimal increase in <hi rend="italic">x</hi> always produces an infinitesimal increase in <hi rend="italic">f</hi>(<hi rend="italic">x</hi>). </s><s n="s2.2;p4.9">In particular, the following function satisfies his definition for each <hi rend="italic">n</hi> on any interval: f <hi rend="sub italic">n</hi>(<hi rend="italic">x</hi>) = 0, for <hi rend="italic">x</hi> &lt; 0 ; f <hi rend="sub italic">n</hi>(<hi rend="italic">x</hi>) = <hi rend="italic">nx</hi>, for 0 ≤<hi rend="italic">x </hi>≤ 1/<hi rend="italic">n</hi> ; f <hi rend="sub italic">n</hi>(<hi rend="italic">x</hi>) = 1, for <hi rend="italic">x</hi> > 1/<hi rend="italic">n</hi>. </s></p><p n="p5.9"><s n="s1.1;p5.9">Later, on pages 131-132, he states the following theorem, </s></p><quote lang="French">"<hi rend="italic">Lorsque les differens termes de la série sont des fonctions d'une même variable x, continues par rapport à cette variable dans le voisinage d'une valeur particulière pour laquelle la série est convergente, la somme s de la série est aussi, dans le voisinage de cette valuer particulière, fonction continue de x.</hi> "</quote><p n="p6.9"><s n="s1.3;p6.9">In English, when the terms of a series are functions in the same variable <hi rend="italic">x</hi>, each function being continuous in the neighbourhood of a particular value for which the series converges, then the sum of the series itself will be continuous in that neighbourhood. </s><s n="s2.3;p6.9">But this certainly doesn't hold true for our example f <hi rend="sub italic">n</hi>(<hi rend="italic">x</hi>). </s><s n="s3.3;p6.9">Indeed, for this theorem, Cauchy appears to assume a somewhat stronger definition of continuity, and hence convergence than he himself has has stated. </s></p><p n="p7.9"><s n="s1.2;p7.9">There has also been much progress on making calculus more rigorous. </s><s n="s2.2;p7.9">Again, Cauchy has been at the forefront of this effort, and his <hi rend="italic">Résumé</hi> (1823) is a highly significant work. </s></p><p n="p8.9"><s n="s1.5;p8.9">It has, until recently, been believed that every function can be expanded as a Taylor series. </s><s n="s2.5;p8.9">Indeed Lagrange's attempt to set up a rigorous framework for calculus through his <hi rend="italic">Théorie des fonctions analytique</hi> (1797) was based on the assumption that a function <hi rend="italic">f</hi> could, in general, be expressed as a power series of the form <hi rend="italic">f</hi>(<hi rend="italic">x</hi>+1) = <hi rend="italic">f</hi>(<hi rend="italic">x</hi>) + <hi rend="italic">a</hi><hi rend="sub">1</hi><hi rend="italic">i</hi> + <hi rend="italic">a</hi><hi rend="sub">2</hi><hi rend="italic">i</hi><hi rend="sup">2</hi> + ... where <hi rend="italic">i</hi> was an arbitrary increment. </s><s n="s3.5;p8.9">The derivatives of <hi rend="italic">f</hi> could then be defined from this increment. </s><s n="s4.5;p8.9">In <hi rend="italic">Résum é</hi>Cauchy provides a counter example to this assumption, hence invalidating Lagrange's approach<ref target="BAWE_0232c-ftnote.002"/>. </s><s n="s5.5;p8.9">Cauchy has instead chosen to define the derivative of a function, where it exists, as a limit. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0232c-ftnote.002"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">see Gray J., 2005, <hi rend="italic">Lecture notes for History of Mathematics</hi>, page 33 </s></p></note><p n="p9.9"><s n="s1.2;p9.9">Due to the likes of Ampère and Cauchy, we are entering a new, far more rigorous era in real analysis. </s><s n="s2.2;p9.9">Over the next few years we are likely to find that the rules of differential calculus we have come to take for granted do not lend themselves well to some of the more unusual functions that Abel and others have begun to consider - functions that were either disregarded, or simply slipped the attention of Fourier and Lagrange. </s></p></div1></body><back/></text></TEI.2>
