<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_0234g" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Material Selection Exercise Report</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">The document has a title page which contains:
document title
title part</note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">appendix contains references to webpages, CES DIAGRAMS and DATA</note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">Evaluated as candidate compound assignment. Assigned to S1b: collection of reports: compound.</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">2</p><p n="date">2004-01</p><p n="module title">Materials for Mechanical Engineers</p><p n="module code">ES22A</p><p n="genre family">Methodology recount</p><p n="discipline">Engineering</p><p n="disciplinary group">PS</p><p n="grade">M</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">3397</p><p n="number of s-units">220</p><p n="number of p">125</p><p n="number of tables">4</p><p n="number of figures">1</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">6</p><p n="number of lists">3</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">63</p><p n="abstract present">abstract present</p><p n="average words per s-unit">15.4</p><p n="average s-units per p">1.8</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">compound assignment consisting of 3 parts (see notesStmt for details)</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">f</p><p n="year of birth">1983</p><p n="first language">Chinese unspecified</p><p n="education">UKA</p><p n="course">Mechanical Engineering</p><p n="student ID">0234</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><docTitle><titlePart rend="bold"> Material Selection Exercise Report</titlePart></docTitle><titlePart><hi rend="bold">Module: Material for Mechanical Engineers ES22A Assignment Code: ES22AA1</hi><hi rend="bold"> Student number: <name type="student ID"/> Course: 2nd Year Mechanical Engineering</hi><hi rend="bold"> Date submitted: 26 January 2004</hi></titlePart></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="abstract"><head rend="bold">Abstract</head><p n="p1.125"><s n="s1.3;p1.125">This material selection report consists of two parts and will be focused on materials, shape and process selection with the use of the Cambridge Engineering Selector. </s><s n="s2.3;p1.125">In the first part A, there is a case study on fresh-water heat exchanger tubes material selection and it explains how judgement with the use of CES selector leads to <hi rend="bold italic">high conductivity copper</hi> be selected as material used for fresh-water heat exchanger tubes. </s><s n="s3.3;p1.125">The first part B will be another design study regarding process and material selection this time and will explain how judgement and decision with the help of CES selector affect our final choice on both process and material selection and appreciate the final selection- </s></p><p n="p2.125"><s n="s1.3;p2.125">Second Part concentrates on shape selection and tends to give reader an idea how secondary design factor M affects selection result. </s><s n="s2.3;p2.125">It also contrasts and compares each shape candidates' characteristics in order to obtain a final selection from a range of short listed shape. </s><s n="s3.3;p2.125">This report involves basic knowledge of CES selector and decision to identify the best candidate from a shortlist of candidates, which may have similar properties. </s></p></div1><div1 type="front-back-matter"><head rend="bold">Content:</head><p/></div1><div1 type="text"><head rend="bold">REPORT 1-MATERIAL SELECTION FOR FRESH-WATER HEAT EXCHANGER TUBES</head><div2><head rend="bold">Introduction</head><p n="p3.125"><s n="s1.5;p3.125">Heat exchangers have been used to provide heat for domestic hot water and other commercial and industrial applications for many decades. </s><s n="s2.5;p3.125">In developed, developing and some of the undeveloped countries, the escalating cost of energy has increased due to increasing demand of exhaustible energy fuel. </s><s n="s3.5;p3.125">The use of heat exchangers helps extract and conserve energy that was previously wasted which is very important to both industrial and domestic users. </s><s n="s4.5;p3.125">The theory behind heat exchangers is energy transfer, which will be introduced in detail in Theory. </s><s n="s5.5;p3.125">The purpose of this part of the report is to produce a short list of suitable candidate materials for heat exchangers tubes, which plays a crucial part in energy transfer in heat exchanger, and to identify their weakness and strength. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">Theory</head><p n="p4.125"><s n="s1.1;p4.125">A heat exchanger utilizes the fact that heat transfer occurs when there is a difference in temperature between two mediums. </s></p><p n="p5.125"><s n="s1.6;p5.125">In a heat exchanger, there is a stream of a higher energy and a stream of lower energy. </s><s n="s2.6;p5.125">One of them flows through a set of tubes which are immersed in a chamber through which the other flows. </s><s n="s3.6;p5.125">The two streams are separated by a thin, solid wall of tubes. </s><s n="s4.6;p5.125">The wall must be thin and conductive in order for heat exchange to occur. </s><s n="s5.6;p5.125">The wall must be strong enough to withstand any pressure caused by pressure difference between two fluids and have to be fairly corrosion resistible to fluids used. </s><s n="s6.6;p5.125">Copper seems to be one of a common choice for construction. </s></p><p n="p6.125"><s n="s1.1;p6.125">Here is a simple flow diagram showing how heat transfers in a heat exchanger. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0234g-fig.001"><head rend="bold">Diagram 1 showing how energy transfer takes place</head></figure></div2><div2><head rend="bold">Method</head><p n="p7.125"><s n="s1.2;p7.125">There are a few boundaries in the task given. </s><s n="s2.2;p7.125">The heat exchanger tubes specification is as follows: </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p8.125"><s n="s1.1;p8.125"><hi rend="bold">Working medium</hi>: </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p9.125"><s n="s1.1;p9.125">It is used in a fresh-water heat exchanger so one or both of the mediums is water </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p10.125"><s n="s1.1;p10.125"><hi rend="bold">Bulk non-Mechanical property- Maximum service temperature</hi>: </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p11.125"><s n="s1.1;p11.125">It must have a maximum service temperature of 150 degree Celsius or higher to avoid rapid drop of physical strength </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p12.125"><s n="s1.1;p12.125"><hi rend="bold">Bulk Mechanical requirement</hi>- <hi rend="bold">Ductility:</hi> </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p13.125"><s n="s1.1;p13.125">Elongation must be larger than 20% of its original length as the tubes have to be bent </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p14.125"><s rend="bold" n="s1.1;p14.125">Chemical property- Corrosion resistance: </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p15.125"><s n="s1.1;p15.125">It must have very good corrosion resistance in fresh water as the tubes are in contact with water. </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p16.125"><s n="s1.1;p16.125"><hi rend="bold">Non-Mechanical property- Thermal Conductivity</hi>: </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p17.125"><s n="s1.1;p17.125">Must be as large as possible such that the tubes are efficient enough conducting energy transfer. </s></p><p n="p18.125"><s n="s1.1;p18.125">A short list of suitable candidate materials can be found by inputting different criteria to CES selector program. </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p19.125"><s rend="bold italic" n="s1.1;p19.125">Stage 1 </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p20.125"><s n="s1.1;p20.125">Materials passing this stage must have adequate ductility and have maximum service temperature no less than 423K </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p21.125"><s rend="bold italic" n="s1.1;p21.125">Stage 2 </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p22.125"><s n="s1.1;p22.125">Materials passing this stage must have very good corrosion resistance in fresh water and have very high thermal conductivity </s></p><p n="p23.125"><s n="s1.3;p23.125">After stage 1 and 2, there are only <hi rend="bold">6</hi> materials left on the shortlist as the rest, failed in the previous stages, have been filtered. </s><s n="s2.3;p23.125">They are <hi rend="bold italic">Copper/Alumina Composite</hi>, <hi rend="bold italic">Gold</hi>, <hi rend="bold italic">Commercial Purity, High Conductivity Copper, Silver Magnesium Alloy, Silver Nickel Alloy and Silver, Commercial Purity</hi>. </s><s n="s3.3;p23.125">These materials meet the minimum requirement and it might be essential to identify the most suitable material from the shortlist by inputting additional criteria. </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p24.125"><s rend="bold" n="s1.1;p24.125">Bulk Mechanical property- Compressive strength: </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p25.125"><s n="s1.1;p25.125">It is believed that heat exchanger tubes have to be strong enough to withstand pressure difference between mediums or else they will either crash or change shape, which engineers try to avoid as it may affect the efficiency or may even shorten its life span. </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p26.125"><s rend="bold" n="s1.1;p26.125">Profitability-Price: </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p27.125"><s n="s1.1;p27.125">Cost could be another important factor in this matter as this directly affects retail price and manufacturing cost. </s></p><p n="p28.125"><s n="s1.1;p28.125">Taking these two criteria into account, Stage 3 will shortlist materials that are not too expensive and have high compressive strength. </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p29.125"><s rend="bold italic" n="s1.1;p29.125">Stage 3 </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p30.125"><s n="s1.1;p30.125">Materials passing this stage must have at least 10MPa compressive strength and cost no more than 80GBP/kg (This is to filter those unrealistically expensive materials) </s></p><p n="p31.125"><s n="s1.2;p31.125">After Stage 3, Gold has been filtered out because of its cost. </s><s n="s2.2;p31.125">Only <hi rend="bold italic">Copper/Alumina Composite, Commercial Purity, High Conductivity Copper, Silver Magnesium Alloy, Silver Nickel Alloy and Silver, Commercial Purity </hi>are in the shortlist. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">Analysis/Conclusion:</head><p n="p32.125"><s n="s1.3;p32.125">After 3 stages of selection, materials in the shortlist are suitable to be used in fresh-water heat exchanger tubes manufacturing. </s><s n="s2.3;p32.125">However, more criteria can be used to pick the most suitable material. </s><s n="s3.3;p32.125">Criteria below together with those introduced before affect selection of a suitable material. </s></p><p n="p33.125"><s rend="bold" n="s1.1;p33.125">Bulk mechanical Property- Hardness: </s></p><p n="p34.125"><s n="s1.3;p34.125">In heat exchanger, <hi rend="bold italic">hardness</hi> may be very important because it can resist change of shape in fluid flow. </s><s n="s2.3;p34.125">If its hardness is not adequate, the tubes may collapse. </s><s n="s3.3;p34.125">Hard materials can therefore withstand failure in extensional, impact or flexural stress. </s></p><p n="p35.125"><s rend="bold" n="s1.1;p35.125">Bulk Mechanical Property- Fatigue </s></p><p n="p36.125"><s n="s1.1;p36.125">Also flow of fluid may cause fatigue on tubes so it may be useful to consider <hi rend="bold italic">fracture toughness</hi> in order to obtain a material that can absorb energy of deformation with breaking, which is a show of strength. </s></p><p n="p37.125"><s n="s1.1;p37.125">The best material can be found by comparison on criteria introduced. </s></p><p n="p38.125"><s n="s1.2;p38.125">Properties of <hi rend="bold italic">Copper/Alumina Composite, Commercial Purity, High Conductivity Copper, Silver Magnesium Alloy, Silver Nickel Alloy and Silver, Commercial Purity </hi>can be found in appendix. </s><s n="s2.2;p38.125">With the properties data, a suitable material can simply be spotted by picking the one that performs best on criteria described. </s></p><table id="BAWE_0234g-tab.001"><head rend="bold">Table extracted from datatable showing each candidate property on hardness and fracture toughness</head><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p39.125"><s n="s1.8;p39.125">From the table above, it shows that <hi rend="bold italic">Copper/Alumina Composite, Commercial Purity </hi>has highest hardness strength but poor fracture toughness. </s><s n="s2.8;p39.125">Therefore it should be in consideration list. </s><s n="s3.8;p39.125">The remaining materials have similar properties on these criteria. </s><s n="s4.8;p39.125">Thus, factors like cost have to be considered to find the most suitable material. </s><s n="s5.8;p39.125"><hi rend="bold italic">High Conductivity Copper</hi> is chosen in this report as its cost is far lower than any of the remaining materials. </s><s n="s6.8;p39.125">Even though it has a moderate fracture toughness, its low would definitely favour production. </s><s n="s7.8;p39.125">Therefore, we can conclude that the most suitable material for Fresh-Water heat exchanger tubes is <hi rend="bold italic">High Conductivity Copper </hi>due to its <hi rend="bold italic"> corrosion resistance against water, high maximum service temperature, high ductility, good thermal conductor, high compressive strength, good hardness performance, moderate fracture toughness </hi>and its <hi rend="bold italic"> incredible low cost.</hi> </s><s rend="bold" n="s8.8;p39.125"> </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="text"><head rend="bold">REPORT 2- Selection for Column Spacers under a Varying Compressive Load</head><div2><head rend="bold">Introduction</head><p n="p40.125"><s n="s1.4;p40.125">In manufacturing industry, use of spacers is very common. </s><s n="s2.4;p40.125">They are used to separate two surfaces or plates. </s><s n="s3.4;p40.125">Though spacers are nothing complicated, it is not as easy when it comes to manufacturing as factors such as cost, tolerance, etc have to be considered. </s><s n="s4.4;p40.125">In this part of the report, it is going to have a look on criteria that affect selection of material for spacers. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">Theory</head><p n="p41.125"><s n="s1.11;p41.125">Column spacers are under varying compressive load. </s><s n="s2.11;p41.125">They can fail either by <hi rend="bold italic">buckling</hi> or be being <hi rend="bold italic">crushed</hi> due to the pressure exerted. </s><s n="s3.11;p41.125">It may be important to notice that they do not happen at the same time as only one or the other will cause failure. </s><s n="s4.11;p41.125">If the column is slender, the spacer will buckle long before the material crushes. </s><s n="s5.11;p41.125">This is a failure that is very likely to happen in small to medium columns. </s><s n="s6.11;p41.125">Very short, fat columns, though not likely to buckle, is in danger of crushing. </s><s n="s7.11;p41.125">In industry, <hi rend="bold italic">slender columns</hi> are more often used than fat, short ones as they are believed not to interfere as much as the fat ones do due to water wave behaviour( <seg type="URL" n="www.hazelwood.k12.mo.us/~grichert/sciweb/waves.htm"/> ) - <hi rend="bold italic">diffraction. </hi></s><s n="s8.11;p41.125"><hi rend="bold italic">Diffraction </hi>is the propagation of a wave around an obstacle. </s><s n="s9.11;p41.125">Unlike refraction (which depends on a wave's response to a change of speed), wave diffraction depends on the <hi rend="bold italic">interruption</hi> of the wave by an obstacle. </s><s n="s10.11;p41.125">Therefore, the bigger the obstacle(fat spacer), the more diffraction it causes to water flow. </s><s n="s11.11;p41.125">Thus, big spacers are avoided in some manufacturing industries. </s></p><p n="p42.125"><s n="s1.1;p42.125">Having found that buckling is more likely to happen in slender spacers, which are more often used, it is important to find a solution to its weakness-buckling. </s></p><p n="p43.125"><s n="s1.1;p43.125">Buckling can be predicted by Euler Buckling equation: </s></p><p n="p44.125"><s n="s1.1;p44.125"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0234g-form.001"/>, where </s></p><list type="simple"><item><hi rend="bold">Fe=</hi> Euler Buckling Force </item><item><hi rend="bold">Le2</hi>= Euler equivalent length </item><item><hi rend="bold">I</hi>=πr <hi rend="sup">4</hi>/4</item></list><p n="p45.125"><s n="s1.2;p45.125"><hi rend="bold">Fe</hi> indicates the maximum load a system can take before buckling and the value is dependent on the physical character of the material used. </s><s n="s2.2;p45.125">To link buckling force and materials physical strength, simply rearrange Euler Buckling Load equation: </s></p><p n="p46.125"><s n="s1.1;p46.125"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0234g-form.002"/> </s></p><p n="p47.125"><s n="s1.2;p47.125">It suggests <hi rend="bold italic">radius</hi> of spacers and <hi rend="bold italic">Young Modulus</hi> directly affect the <hi rend="bold italic">maximum buckling force</hi> a spacer can take but as proved earlier, r is tried to be kept small and constant and leaving <hi rend="bold italic">Young Modulus</hi> the only variable in this equation. </s><s n="s2.2;p47.125">Therefore, material used must have very high Young Modulus. </s></p><p n="p48.125"><s n="s1.3;p48.125">Spacers selected must also have adequate ability to resist <hi rend="bold italic">fatigue</hi> as force exerted is <hi rend="bold italic">periodically changing</hi> because of water wave's property. </s><s n="s2.3;p48.125"><hi rend="bold italic">Endurance limit</hi> can be used in this case as it measures the <hi rend="bold italic">maximum stress</hi> operates <hi rend="bold italic">indefinitely</hi> without failure on any given material. </s><s n="s3.3;p48.125">This should be considered as one of the most important factors that would affect the results. </s></p><p n="p49.125"><s n="s1.2;p49.125"><hi rend="bold italic">Thermal distortion</hi> is another criteria that is worth consideration. </s><s n="s2.2;p49.125"><hi rend="bold italic">Thermal distortion</hi> is a measurement of <hi rend="bold italic">mechanical deformations</hi> of the test article due to temperature in combination with vacuum condition and must be minimized to avoid failure of systems. </s></p><p n="p50.125"><s n="s1.10;p50.125"><hi rend="bold italic">Corrosion resistance</hi> strength must be taken into account. </s><s n="s2.10;p50.125">Without adequate corrosion resistance, components often fall short of the expected design life. </s><s n="s3.10;p50.125">Corrosion is due to generally slow chemical reaction between materials and surroundings. </s><s n="s4.10;p50.125">Stable materials are less likely to be damaged by corrosion than instable ones. </s><s n="s5.10;p50.125"><hi rend="bold italic">Acid</hi> is one of the strongest corrosives as it has a free proton flowing around reactive. </s><s n="s6.10;p50.125">These protons combine with electrons and thus corroding the original material. </s><s n="s7.10;p50.125"><hi rend="bold italic">Organic solvents</hi> could be corrosive as they have reactive groups, like hydrocarbons. </s><s n="s8.10;p50.125">Water, comparatively, has less corrosive strength as it contains less reactive flowing group. </s><s n="s9.10;p50.125">Even so, it could cause slow corrosion which has to be aware of. </s><s n="s10.10;p50.125">Therefore, selected material has to be strong enough in terms of corrosion resistance strength. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">Method</head><p n="p51.125"><s n="s1.2;p51.125">There are a few limitations on this selection for spacers. </s><s n="s2.2;p51.125">The basic requirements are as follows: </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p52.125"><s rend="bold" n="s1.1;p52.125">Bulk Mechanical Property- Elastic Moduli: </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p53.125"><s n="s1.1;p53.125">The material must have very high Young Modulus to avoid buckling as proven previously </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p54.125"><s rend="bold" n="s1.1;p54.125">Electrical Property- Electrical Conductivity: </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p55.125"><s n="s1.1;p55.125">The material should be a bad electrical conductor. </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p56.125"><s rend="bold" n="s1.1;p56.125">Bulk Mechanical Property- Thermal distortion: </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p57.125"><s n="s1.1;p57.125">The material thermal expansion should be as low as possible </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p58.125"><s rend="bold" n="s1.1;p58.125">Chemical Property- Corrosion Resistance: </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p59.125"><s n="s1.1;p59.125">The material must have very high corrosion resistance strength to water and organic solvents and high resistance strength to acid </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">Method</head><p rend="ordered" n="p60.125"><s rend="bold italic" n="s1.1;p60.125">Stage 1 </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p61.125"><s n="s1.1;p61.125">Material passing this stage must have very high Young Modulus (It has to be set above 80GPA as this sufficiently removes a lot of useful materials) and must have very high resistivity conducting current ( Its minimum limit must be set to 1e12 as this is the typical resistivity an electrical insulator has. </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p62.125"><s rend="bold italic" n="s1.1;p62.125">Stage 2 </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p63.125"><s n="s1.1;p63.125">Material passing this stage must have small thermal distortion ability( Its minimum is set to be 1e-6/K as this removes a right number of materials ) and at least very good resistance against acid. </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p64.125"><s rend="bold italic" n="s1.1;p64.125">Stage 3 </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p65.125"><s n="s1.1;p65.125">Material passing this stage must have very good resistance to water and organic solvents. </s></p><p n="p66.125"><s n="s1.3;p66.125">After the four stages, only 4 materials remain. </s><s n="s2.3;p66.125">They are Boron <hi rend="bold italic">Nitride(Hot pressing)</hi>, <hi rend="bold italic">Diamond, Glass and Non Machineable Glass Ceramic</hi>. </s><s n="s3.3;p66.125">They all have high <hi rend="bold italic">Young Modulus, high electrical resistivity, low thermal expansion and stable chemical state</hi>. </s></p><p n="p67.125"><s n="s1.3;p67.125">Spacers have to deal with periodically changing pressure. </s><s n="s2.3;p67.125">Material of low endurance limit is very likely to fail. </s><s n="s3.3;p67.125">Cost is also very important in manufacturing as expensive materials are replaced with cheaper ones that have similar properties. </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p68.125"><s rend="bold" n="s1.1;p68.125">Bulk Mechanical Property- Endurance Limit: </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p69.125"><s n="s1.1;p69.125">Materials must have endurance limit must have very high endurance limit to avoid failure. </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p70.125"><s rend="bold" n="s1.1;p70.125">Cost: </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p71.125"><s n="s1.2;p71.125">Materials chosen cannot be too expensive or else it would not be profitable making these spacers. </s><s n="s2.2;p71.125">Setting cost as low as possible (1000GBP/kg chosen in this case as this cost is reasonable) to filter unrealistic materials. </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p72.125"><s rend="bold italic" n="s1.1;p72.125">Stage 4 </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p73.125"><s n="s1.1;p73.125">Material passing this stage must have high endurance limit(50MPa or above) and cost no more than 1000GBP/kg) </s></p><p n="p74.125"><s n="s1.1;p74.125">After the additional stage, </s></p><p n="p75.125"><s n="s1.4;p75.125">Only <hi rend="bold italic">Boron Nitride (Hot pressing) </hi>and <hi rend="bold italic">Non Machineable Glass Ceramic</hi> satisfy all the criteria. </s><s n="s2.4;p75.125">Spacers made by both materials altogether less than 55mm diameter according to Euler's equation. </s><s n="s3.4;p75.125"><hi rend="bold italic">Ductility and elastic limit </hi>also affect design of spacers as they have to be made thin and thus have to be considered. </s><s n="s4.4;p75.125">Hopefully, by comparing their <hi rend="bold italic">ductility and elastic limit </hi>would give the most suitable material. </s></p><table id="BAWE_0234g-tab.002"><head rend="bold">table showing final candidates elastic limit and ductility property</head><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p76.125"><s n="s1.1;p76.125">Since Non Machineable Glass Ceramic has higher ductility, it should be selected as the final materal. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">Method</head><p n="p77.125"><s n="s1.1;p77.125">Below is the limitation: </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p78.125"><s rend="bold" n="s1.1;p78.125">Production rate </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p79.125"><s n="s1.2;p79.125">It is known that 25 sets of spacers (in the other word, 175 spacers are sold) are expected to be sold each year (A spacer is manufactured every 50 hours). </s><s n="s2.2;p79.125">It is necessary to filter out those too-slow processes as they would not be helpful. </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p80.125"><s rend="bold" n="s1.1;p80.125">Tolerance </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p81.125"><s n="s1.3;p81.125">The maximum tolerance is given in specification, i.e. </s><s n="s2.3;p81.125">0.015mm. </s><s n="s3.3;p81.125">Any processes that cannot give accurate finish would not be considered. </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p82.125"><s rend="bold" n="s1.1;p82.125">Cost </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p83.125"><s n="s1.4;p83.125">It is known that the retail price would be £80,000. </s><s n="s2.4;p83.125">In order to make profit, the cost of manufacturing (including assets cost) should never be above the retail price. </s><s n="s3.4;p83.125">Since the retail price is the price for a set of spacers, therefore each spacer retail price would be <hi rend="bold">£11428.5</hi> (It should not be rounded off). </s><s n="s4.4;p83.125">Cost of manufacturing spacers should be below £11428.5 </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p84.125"><s rend="bold italic" n="s1.1;p84.125">Stage 1 </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p85.125"><s n="s1.1;p85.125">Processes passing this stage must have production rate higher than 50hr <hi rend="sup">-1</hi> and has maximum tolerance no bigger than 0.015mm </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p86.125"><s rend="bold italic" n="s1.1;p86.125">Stage 2 </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p87.125"><s n="s1.1;p87.125">Processes passing this stage must have capital cost less than £11428.5 </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">Results/Analysis</head><p n="p88.125"><s n="s1.1;p88.125">There are 5 materials passing the three criteria above and they are <hi rend="bold italic">Centreless Microgrinding, Micromachining (Manual), Micropolishing (Automated), Micropolishing (Manual) and Polishing (Manual)</hi> </s></p><div3><head rend="bold">FINAL SELECTION:</head><p n="p89.125"><s n="s1.3;p89.125">Material: Out of the 3 candidates, <hi rend="bold">Non-Machineable Glass Ceramic</hi> is chosen because of its <hi rend="bold italic">high Young's Modulus </hi>strength and compressive strength, which ensure neither buckling nor crushing is likely to happen. </s><s n="s2.3;p89.125">Moreover, it has high endurance limit, which makes sure spacers are not likely to happen. </s><s n="s3.3;p89.125">It also has high <hi rend="bold">ductility</hi> and <hi rend="bold">elastic limit</hi>, which is very helpful in making slender spacers. </s></p><p n="p90.125"><s n="s1.1;p90.125">Process: Centreless Micro grinding and Micromachining (Manual) cannot be used to manufacture non-machineable Glass Ceramic spacers leaving only 3 possible processes. </s></p><p n="p91.125"><s n="s1.1;p91.125"><hi rend="bold italic">Micropolishing(Manual)</hi> is chosen because of its long designed life span and it is specialised in making conical, cylindrical, flat and spherical surfaces. </s></p></div3></div2></div1><div1 type="text"><head rend="bold">REPORT 2: SHAPE SELECTION FOR A STRUCTURAL ROOF MEMBER</head><div2><head rend="bold">Introduction</head><p n="p92.125"><s n="s1.6;p92.125">A roof can have two functions. </s><s n="s2.6;p92.125">It can be a roof for shelter and also acts as a path for the level above. </s><s n="s3.6;p92.125">This design can be found everywhere, like a shopping mall, a subway and even in houses. </s><s n="s4.6;p92.125">Though it is very useful, it takes extra care when it comes to designing as a mistake could cause loss of lives. </s><s n="s5.6;p92.125">The technical reasons that must be considered will be introduced in Theory. </s><s n="s6.6;p92.125">This part of the report is intended to select a suitable shape for the task given. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">Theory</head><p n="p93.125"><s n="s1.4;p93.125">The most important factor needed to be considered in roof constructing is <hi rend="bold italic">deflection</hi>. </s><s n="s2.4;p93.125">It can be defined as the displacement of a structural member or system under load. </s><s n="s3.4;p93.125">A roof can be treated as a simply supported beam while anything on the roof can be treated as loads. </s><s n="s4.4;p93.125">The maximum deflection of a beam is given by: </s></p><p n="p94.125"><s n="s1.1;p94.125"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0234g-form.003"/><hi rend="bold"> , where q=load in N/m, L=Length of beam and EI=flexural stiffness of beam</hi> </s></p><p n="p95.125"><s n="s1.2;p95.125"><hi rend="bold italic">Lateral Torsional buckling </hi>is twisting buckling about the minor axis which encourages the compression flange to bend further and is another factor that has to be considered in a simply-supported beam with a uniform bending moment. </s><s n="s2.2;p95.125">This can be avoided by high torisional rigidity that resists torsional bending. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">Method</head><p n="p96.125"><s n="s1.1;p96.125">In this task, the followings have to be considered: </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p97.125"><s rend="bold" n="s1.1;p97.125">Bulk Mechanical property- Deflection of roof on load </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p98.125"><s n="s1.1;p98.125">It is known that the maximum deflection cannot be bigger than 25mm so any shapes that cannot limit deflection to 25mm or less are filtered. </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p99.125"><s rend="bold" n="s1.1;p99.125">Bulk Mechanical property- Torsional Rigidity </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p100.125"><s n="s1.1;p100.125">It is known that torsional rigidity can stop lateral torsional buckling and any suitable shape would have high torsional rigidity to avoid failure. </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p101.125"><s rend="bold" n="s1.1;p101.125">Recycle Fraction </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p102.125"><s n="s1.1;p102.125">Given that environmental impact has to be minimised, the ideal shape should have high recycle fraction. </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p103.125"><s rend="bold" n="s1.1;p103.125">Energy Content </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p104.125"><s n="s1.1;p104.125">It has to be minimised to lower environmental impact. </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p105.125"><s rend="bold italic" n="s1.1;p105.125">Stage 1 </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p106.125"><s n="s1.4;p106.125">Setting deflection as X axis while inputting secondary design considerations(M) on Y axis. </s><s n="s2.4;p106.125">M can be defined by (Torsional Stiffness)*(Recycle Fraction)/(Energy Content). </s><s n="s3.4;p106.125">It is essential to obtain M as large as possible as it means that the shortlist comes out at the end will have very high Torsional Stiffness, recycle fraction but very low energy content. </s><s n="s4.4;p106.125">210 unit of M is set as the minimum because having done that would leave us only few suitable materials. </s></p><p n="p107.125"><s n="s1.2;p107.125">Taking gear limitations into account. </s><s n="s2.2;p107.125">It has to be converted into kg and then into kg/m simply by dividing it by the length of the beam, which is 10m </s></p><p n="p108.125"><s n="s1.1;p108.125">Therefore, </s></p><p n="p109.125"><s n="s1.1;p109.125"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0234g-form.004"/> </s></p><p n="p110.125"><s n="s1.1;p110.125">Then </s></p><p n="p111.125"><s n="s1.1;p111.125"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0234g-form.005"/> </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">Result/Analysis</head><p n="p112.125"><s n="s1.1;p112.125">After completing stage one, a shortlist of shapes will be given. </s></p><list type="simple"><item>Glulam Softwood rectangular section</item><item>Hot Fin Steel(Y.S 355MPa) Circular Hollow</item><item>Hot Fin Steel(Y.S 355MPa) Rectangular Hollow</item><item>Hot Rolled Steel(Y.S 355MPa)Univeral Beam-[203×102×23]</item><item>Hot Rolled Steel(Y.S 355MPa)Univeral Beam-[254×102×25]</item></list><p n="p113.125"><s n="s1.2;p113.125">By comparing and contrasting candidates in the shortlist, the best shape would hopefully found out. </s><s n="s2.2;p113.125">It can be done by comparing the values of M. </s></p><table id="BAWE_0234g-tab.003"><head rend="underlined bold">Table showing torsional stiffness, recycle fraction, energy content and M of shortlisted candidates</head><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p114.125"><s n="s1.2;p114.125">Having looked at the table, it is seen that Hot Fin Steel Circular and Hot Fin Steel rectangular are more appropriate to be used as they got high M value. </s><s n="s2.2;p114.125">However, Hot Fini Steel Rectangular has significantly higher torsional stiffness which is believed to be the most important factor in M. Therefore, the chosen shape is Hot Fin Steel Circular. </s></p><div3><head rend="bold">Different forms of M</head><p n="p115.125"><s n="s1.4;p115.125">Different forms of M would directly affect the search results. </s><s n="s2.4;p115.125">M is a value that is made up by factors that influence the designed shape. </s><s n="s3.4;p115.125">It is believed that safety factor, major bending stiffness and price are crucial when it comes to selection. </s><s n="s4.4;p115.125">A new M can be constructed and be explained below. </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p116.125"><s n="s1.1;p116.125">An ideal shape must have very high M <hi rend="sub">new</hi> value </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p117.125"><s n="s1.1;p117.125">It can be obtained by high bending stiffness and safety factor </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p118.125"><s n="s1.1;p118.125">High price is not favoured so it should be kept as low as possible </s></p><p n="p119.125"><s n="s1.1;p119.125">Therefore, to obtain a high M <hi rend="sub">new</hi> </s></p><p n="p120.125"><s n="s1.1;p120.125"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0234g-form.006"/> </s></p><p n="p121.125"><s n="s1.1;p121.125">With new M, a different shortlist will be obtained. </s></p><p n="p122.125"><s n="s1.1;p122.125">With new M, a different shortlist will be obtained. </s></p><list type="simple"><item>The shape shortlist is as follow:</item><item>Hot Rolled Steel Universal Beam-[178×102×19]</item><item>Hot Rolled Steel Universal Beam-[203×102×23]</item><item>Hot Rolled Steel Universal Beam-[203×133×25]</item><item>Hot Rolled Steel Universal Beam-[254×102×22]</item><item>Hot Rolled Steel Universal Beam-[254×102×25]</item><item>Hot Rolled Steel Universal Beam-[305×102×25]</item></list><p n="p123.125"><s n="s1.1;p123.125">Again, by comparing and contrasting the remaining sections a final choice can be made. </s></p><table id="BAWE_0234g-tab.004"><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p124.125"><s rend="bold" n="s1.5;p124.125">Hot Rolled Steel(Y.S. </s><s n="s2.5;p124.125"><hi rend="bold">355MPa) Universal Beam</hi>[254×102×25] would be the most appropriate shape to be used even though its M <hi rend="sub">New</hi> is not the highest. </s><s n="s3.5;p124.125">The main reason behind the choice is because it has <hi rend="bold italic">very high major bending stiffness strength</hi> but at the same time it <hi rend="bold italic">does not cost as much</hi> as <hi rend="bold">Universal Beam-</hi> [305×102×25]. </s><s n="s4.5;p124.125">It is thought that Major bending stiffness strength is as important as cost but in [254×102×25] it has sufficient Major bending stiffness strength. </s><s n="s5.5;p124.125">Therefore, cost is </s></p><p n="p125.125"><s n="s1.1;p125.125">considered as more important in this case. </s></p></div3></div2></div1></body><back><div1 type="appendix"><head rend="bold">Appendix</head><p/></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
