<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_0234b" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Scenario Planning Report. Future of Imaging- Kodak</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">The document has a title page which contains:
document title
title part</note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">deleted: header: student number and module name</note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">Appendices: company data, extracts from text book on scenario planning, scripts for scenarios</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">4</p><p n="date">2005-10</p><p n="module title">Operational Research for Strategic Planning</p><p n="module code">IB3490</p><p n="genre family">Case study</p><p n="discipline">Business</p><p n="disciplinary group">SS</p><p n="grade">M</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">2070</p><p n="number of s-units">109</p><p n="number of p">30</p><p n="number of tables">3</p><p n="number of figures">0</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">5</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">0</p><p n="abstract present">abstract present</p><p n="average words per s-unit">19.0</p><p n="average s-units per p">3.6</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">f</p><p n="year of birth">1983</p><p n="first language">Chinese unspecified</p><p n="education">UKA</p><p n="course">Mechanical Engineering</p><p n="student ID">0234</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><titlePart><hi rend="bold">IB 349 Operational Research for Strategic Planning</hi><hi rend="bold"> Scenario Planning Report </hi></titlePart><docTitle><titlePart><hi rend="bold">Future of Imaging- Kodak</hi> <hi rend="bold"> 12 CAT Submission</hi></titlePart></docTitle><titlePart rend="bold"><name type="student ID"/></titlePart></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="abstract"><head rend="bold">Summary</head><p n="p1.30"><s n="s1.3;p1.30">Group 11 have been commissioned to conduct a strategic planning analysis for Kodak, aiming to develop long term strategies, using WBS scenario planning methods. </s><s n="s2.3;p1.30">12 key factors have been identified as the driving force of Kodak's business environment. </s><s n="s3.3;p1.30">They are: </s></p><list type="bulleted"><item>Balance towards Aesthetics/ Performance</item><item>Holiday Demand</item><item>Changes to Tax Law</item><item>Labour Union Activities</item><item>US Economy</item><item>UK Economy</item><item>Level of Competition</item><item>Level of Merges and Acquisition Activity</item><item>Advances in Manufacturing Efficiency</item><item>Advances in Camera Technology</item><item>Restrictions on File Sharing</item><item>Public Perception of Kodak as a Safe and Environmentally Friendly Company</item></list><p n="p2.30"><s n="s1.1;p2.30">3 scenarios have then been generated using the deductive approach and they are: </s></p><list type="bulleted"><item>UK Economic Depression</item><item>Advances in Integrated Technology</item><item>Collapse of Internet</item></list><p n="p3.30"><s n="s1.3;p3.30">Each factor is given a value in each scenario to ensure the consistency to the scenario and a scenario table has then been generated. </s><s n="s2.3;p3.30">All these information is then presented in a narrative form. </s><s n="s3.3;p3.30">A narrative has been created for each scenario and their titles are: </s></p><list type="bulleted"><item>The Times- Another chairman committed suicide </item><item>IBM Board Meeting</item><item>6 o'clock top stories- The end of Internet Era</item></list><p n="p4.30"><s n="s1.3;p4.30">Based on the scenarios, a SWOT analysis and TOWS Matrix are then generated. </s><s n="s2.3;p4.30">The potential list of strategies is then reduced to two after robustness check. </s><s n="s3.3;p4.30">It is concluded that Kodak should consider develop framework for the two suggested long term strategies: </s></p><list type="bulleted"><item>Possible merging with another company</item><item>Explore opportunities in emerging markets</item></list></div1><div1 type="front-back-matter"><head rend="bold">Contents</head><p/></div1><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="bold">Introduction</hi><ref target="BAWE_0234b-ftnote.001"/><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0234b-ftnote.001"><p n="pn1.1"> Learning from the future- Liam Fahey and Robert Randall, John Wileys and Son, 1998</p></note></head><p n="p5.30"><s n="s1.5;p5.30">Today's organisations, regardless of their sizes and kind of business operated in, are striving to identify clear long term goals in order to stay or grow in the business. </s><s n="s2.5;p5.30">To achieve the set goals, a company must create a clear long term action plan. </s><s n="s3.5;p5.30">This is known as strategic planning. </s><s n="s4.5;p5.30">These long term plans serve as a framework for decision, provide a basis for further detailed planning and used to assist bench marking and monitor performance. </s><s n="s5.5;p5.30">However, all plans contain risk as the future of the business environment is always uncertain. </s></p><p n="p6.30"><s n="s1.4;p6.30">Scenario planning avoids the concern with a single strategy, which could seriously damage the financial health of an organisation through misallocation of limited resources. </s><s n="s2.4;p6.30">Scenarios present alternative images instead of extrapolating current trends from the present. </s><s n="s3.4;p6.30">Scenarios also embrace qualitative perspectives and the potential for sharp discontinuities that econometric models exclude. </s><s n="s4.4;p6.30">This report will look at scenario planning and strategies developed for Kodak. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="bold">Kodak's Profile</hi><ref target="BAWE_0234b-ftnote.002"/><ref target="BAWE_0234b-ftnote.003"/> 5<note place="foot" id="BAWE_0234b-ftnote.002"><p n="pn1.1"> Yahoo Finance</p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0234b-ftnote.003"><p n="pn1.1"> <seg type="URL" n="www.kodak.com"/></p></note></head><p n="p7.30"><s n="s1.8;p7.30">Kodak was found over 125 years ago and is the largest US maker of photographic films and supplement products. </s><s n="s2.8;p7.30">Their business includes the development, manufacture, and marketing of traditional analogue and digital imaging products. </s><s n="s3.8;p7.30">It provides services and solutions for the entertainment and healthcare industry worldwide. </s><s n="s4.8;p7.30">However, as their company's vision suggests, their core attention remains focused in the consumer's products sector. </s><s n="s5.8;p7.30">Kodak, in the last 10 years, suffered from the transition within its operating environment. </s><s n="s6.8;p7.30">They saw a dramatic social shift from chemical- based film photography, the market they had dominated over a century, to modern digital technology. </s><s n="s7.8;p7.30">In their own research, they admitted digital technology would dominate the whole imaging industry in less than 20 years time. </s><s n="s8.8;p7.30">Their main income from analogue camera films, disposable cameras and other supply products are shrinking 3 times faster than predicted. </s></p><p n="p8.30"><s n="s1.11;p8.30">Kodak's response to that was to transform themselves into an imaging and digital business rather than the traditional film market leader. </s><s n="s2.11;p8.30">They have invested millions of dollars in digital technology and last year they sold over 22% of the digital cameras and other supplement products in US. They are also desperate to transform their service business into digital. </s><s n="s3.11;p8.30">Their printing kiosks are everywhere in the US and have started appearing in the UK. In addition, they have gone into the digital printing industry as it is recognised as a huge, continuous income. </s><s n="s4.11;p8.30">They also saw the potential in internet. </s><s n="s5.11;p8.30">They recently developed the world's first Wi-Fi camera, which allows users to send quality digital photos directly to the internet. </s><s n="s6.11;p8.30">Their desperate transformation has been acknowledged and is on the leading edge of the imaging business. </s><s n="s7.11;p8.30">However, it comes with a price as Kodak had a debt of around $ 3 billion. </s><s n="s8.11;p8.30">Layoff and closing down of traditional business assets show no sign of ceasing. </s><s n="s9.11;p8.30">Future remains uncertain as they have to compete with traditional electronic companies such as Sony while people tend to view their photos on the internet rather than buying their camera supplements like printers printing them off. </s><s n="s10.11;p8.30">It is also seen that the digital market will be saturated at some point. </s><s n="s11.11;p8.30">To weather the storm, this report will introduce some long term strategies for Kodak using scenario planning. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Set the Scene</head><p n="p9.30"><s n="s1.4;p9.30">This report will use the WBS approach to scenario planning. </s><s n="s2.4;p9.30">Before starting scenarios, direction of this planning has to be set. </s><s n="s3.4;p9.30">This exercise will focus on the future changes of the imaging business and look at how it would be affected in three different designed scenarios, which are set 10 years ahead (2015). </s><s n="s4.4;p9.30">The scenarios have been developed by group 11 and will be used for individual's strategies development. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="bold">Key External Environment Factors</hi> <ref target="BAWE_0234b-ftnote.004"/><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0234b-ftnote.004"><p n="pn1.1"> Plotting Your Scenarios- Jay Ogilvy and Peter Schwartz</p></note></head><p n="p10.30"><s n="s1.3;p10.30">This stage is to generate a set of factors which characterise the Kodak's external environment. </s><s n="s2.3;p10.30">Factors generated should fall in one of these categories; Social, Political, Economic, Competitive, Technological, Regulatory, Environmental. </s><s n="s3.3;p10.30">The group brainstormed a total of 40 factors and detail can be found in list 1 in Appendices. </s></p><p n="p11.30"><s n="s1.2;p11.30">WBS Approach suggests the list should then be reduced to 12 most uncertain and important factors by using uncertainty/ importance grid. </s><s n="s2.2;p11.30">In figure 1, the top left hand corner of the grid denotes the key 12 factors the group have obtained. </s></p><p n="p12.30"><s n="s1.2;p12.30">A range of values have been assigned to the factors, which the group believe they can plausibly and possibly vary. </s><s n="s2.2;p12.30">Table 2 below lists the Kodak's factor ranges: </s></p><table id="BAWE_0234b-tab.001"><head>Table1. Table showing a possible range of values of the 12 key external factors affecting Kodak</head><row><cell/></row></table></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Scenario Development</head><p n="p13.30"><s n="s1.4;p13.30">There are two different ways to generate scenarios, inductive and deductive approach. </s><s n="s2.4;p13.30">The group use the WBS deductive approach to generate 3 different scenarios in order to project what the future may be like. </s><s n="s3.4;p13.30">It is done by setting a scenario's theme first and then project individual factors to be consistent with them. </s><s n="s4.4;p13.30">The 3 scenarios created for Kodak are presented below: </s></p><list type="bulleted"><item>UK Economic Depression</item><item>Advances of Integrated Technology</item><item>Collapse of Internet</item></list><p n="p14.30"><s n="s1.2;p14.30">For each scenario, a value for each factor is selected from its range of values so they are consistent with the scenario. </s><s n="s2.2;p14.30">The process is then repeated for the rest and the group obtained a scenario table, which is shown as below: </s></p><table id="BAWE_0234b-tab.002"><head>Table 2. Scenario Table showing how the value of each factor varies in different scenarios</head><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p15.30"><s n="s1.5;p15.30">The table shows how the values of each factor under the different scenarios. </s><s n="s2.5;p15.30">The first scenario, UK Economic Depression, came from the idea of replicating the Wall Street Crash and the consequence depression. </s><s n="s3.5;p15.30">The second scenario is based on the advances of integrated technology, such as the present camera phone. </s><s n="s4.5;p15.30">They would be some sort of competition to traditional digital cameras. </s><s n="s5.5;p15.30">The last scenario looks at the collapse of the internet as the current trend shows the threat of spam, viruses causing the downfall of the internet and the consequent impact to digital imaging sharing and sales of products. </s></p><p n="p16.30"><s n="s1.2;p16.30">To ensure all three scenarios produced in table 2 are internally consistent, the group has used the cross-impact matrix to check the internal consistency. </s><s n="s2.2;p16.30">Detail of how to check internal consistency of scenarios can be found in Table 4 in Appendices </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Presenting Scenarios</head><p n="p17.30"><s n="s1.3;p17.30">There are several ways to present scenarios and the WBS approach encourages narrative development. </s><s n="s2.3;p17.30">The group developed a narrative for each scenario, which has a clear time-line and include all the key 12 factors identified in previous stage. </s><s n="s3.3;p17.30">They are attached in the Appendices and below are the summaries: </s></p><p n="p18.30"><s rend="bold" n="s1.1;p18.30">Scenario 1: The Times- Another chairman committed suicide since the crash of Stock market- </s></p><p n="p19.30"><s n="s1.1;p19.30">Sunday Time weekly column looks at the changes in different sectors since the crash of London Stock Market. </s></p><p n="p20.30"><s rend="bold" n="s1.1;p20.30">Scenario 2: IBM Commissioned Meeting </s></p><p n="p21.30"><s n="s1.3;p21.30">IBM monthly meeting looks at the impact of advance in integrated technology. </s><s n="s2.3;p21.30">It is supported by a detail research in social, political, economic, regulation, competitive, technology sectors. </s><s rend="bold" n="s3.3;p21.30">Script is unavailable as some certain group member refuses to share their script. </s></p><p n="p22.30"><s n="s1.3;p22.30"><hi rend="bold">Scenario 3: 6 o'clock top stories- The end of Internet era-</hi> News presenter Fiona reports that the internet has been finally forced to shut down internationally by law. </s><s n="s2.3;p22.30">It is due to the internet being unusable and widespread virus, spams, etc seriously damaging companies and government's database. </s><s n="s3.3;p22.30">The news explores how it would affect the way people have been communicating and electronics companies. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">SWOT Analysis</head><p n="p23.30"><s n="s1.4;p23.30">Scenario planning it does not provide much detail in terms of decision making. </s><s n="s2.4;p23.30">WBS approach uses SWOT Analysis to evaluate the strength, Weaknesses, Opportunities, and Threats involved. </s><s n="s3.4;p23.30">Both Strength and Weaknesses can be seen as internal to an organisation while Threats and Opportunities are external. </s><s n="s4.4;p23.30">Below is an evaluation of both the Strength and Weakness of Kodak: </s></p><div2><head><hi rend="bold">Strengths</hi> 1</head><p n="p24.30"><s n="s1.5;p24.30">Kodak is one of the most established companies in the world, who had a turnover of 13.83 billions US dollars. </s><s n="s2.5;p24.30">Their products are sold worldwide and have top research development facilities. </s><s n="s3.5;p24.30">They have good retailing and marketing networks. </s><s n="s4.5;p24.30">In addition, Kodak's executive board are made up of experienced, young and enthusiastic people. </s><s n="s5.5;p24.30">For example, their CEO, Antonio M. Perez has extensive expertise in digital imaging industry from his 25-year career at Hewlett-Packard Co., where he was a corporate vice-president<ref target="BAWE_0234b-ftnote.005"/>. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0234b-ftnote.005"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1"><seg type="URL" n="http://www.hispanicbusiness.com/influentials/details.asp?id=682&amp;year=2003"/> </s></p></note></div2><div2><head><hi rend="bold">Weaknesses</hi> 7</head><p n="p25.30"><s n="s1.8;p25.30">Even though they had a massive turnover of 13.83 billion USD last year, compared to other traditional electronics producers, such as Sony, and other camera manufacturers, such as Fuji, they seem quite far behind. </s><s n="s2.8;p25.30">Canon's revenue in 2004 was 33 billion US dollars, which was almost 3 times as much as Kodak <ref target="BAWE_0234b-ftnote.006"/>. </s><s n="s3.8;p25.30">Moreover, Kodak are hardly breaking even in their digital camera sales <ref target="BAWE_0234b-ftnote.007"/>. </s><s n="s4.8;p25.30">They are desperate to move into digital imaging and lay off traditional chemical film business, which they have been dominating for a long time. </s><s n="s5.8;p25.30">This does not help especially they are struggling in terms of debt (which they owe 3.97billion USD). </s><s n="s6.8;p25.30">They also have a very poor cash inflow and often forced to sell their properties to stay in the business. </s><s n="s7.8;p25.30">It is worrying that they decided to reduce the number of digital cameras manufactured a year. </s><s n="s8.8;p25.30">It could be a sign of shortage in cash. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0234b-ftnote.006"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1"><seg type="URL" n="http://www.hoovers.com/eastman-kodak/--ID__10500--/free-co-fin-factsheet.xhtml"/> </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0234b-ftnote.007"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1"><seg type="URL" n="http://yahoo.businessweek.com/magazine/content/05_42/b3955106.htm"/> </s></p></note></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">TOWS Matrix</head><table id="BAWE_0234b-tab.003"><head>Table 3. TOWS Matrix of potential strategic options shown above.</head><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p26.30"/></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Strategies Developed</head><p n="p27.30"><s n="s1.3;p27.30">The TOWS matrix generates some potential strategies for Kodak. </s><s n="s2.3;p27.30">They are tested against each of the scenarios for robustness and detail can be found in Appendices. </s><s n="s3.3;p27.30">It can be concluded that both exploring new market and merging with another company would be worthwhile considering. </s></p><p n="p28.30"><s n="s1.5;p28.30">Merging with another would bring temporary growth of the company and thus increase and thus answer the constant pressure from stockholders<ref target="BAWE_0234b-ftnote.008"/>. </s><s n="s2.5;p28.30">It can also introduce new market, increase customer base, acquiring key management personnel, etc. </s><s n="s3.5;p28.30">Exploring new market (such as emerging market) can be an important move to Kodak. </s><s n="s4.5;p28.30">Emerging market has unlimited potential and has yet to be explored. </s><s n="s5.5;p28.30">If Kodak could establish in new unknown markets, it could boost their sales, performance, etc. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0234b-ftnote.008"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1"><seg type="URL" n="http://209.143.248.44/default.aspx?page=article152"/> </s></p></note></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Conclusion</head><p n="p29.30"><s n="s1.4;p29.30">This report has looked at the scenario planning and strategies development for Kodak, using the WBS scenario approach. </s><s n="s2.4;p29.30">It has explored the 12 key factors that affect Kodak's business environment. </s><s n="s3.4;p29.30">3 scenarios, UK Economic Depression, Advances of Integrated Technology and Collapse of Internet, have been developed using a deductive approach. </s><s n="s4.4;p29.30">Based on the 3 scenarios, a few strategies have been recognised using TOWS matrix and two of them, merging with another company and exploring emerging markets, has been identified as the possibility to be successful long term strategy of Kodak. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Evaluation</head><p n="p30.30"><s n="s1.6;p30.30">This report, in my opinion, covers all the essentials of scenario planning and has successfully developed long term strategies for Kodak. </s><s n="s2.6;p30.30">However, a few issues could have led to developing not the best strategies. </s><s n="s3.6;p30.30">The main issue would be considering the imaging market in the UK rather than Kodak as a whole in the key factors development stages. </s><s n="s4.6;p30.30">It could give misleading strategies as in SWOT analysis, Kodak is viewed as a whole rather than just market in the UK, which is not quite consistent. </s><s n="s5.6;p30.30">The other issue would be including some, in my opinion, not so important factors as the key 12. </s><s n="s6.6;p30.30">However, the result of the report is very satisfying and the resulted strategies could be used for serious consideration. </s></p></div1></body><back><div1 type="appendix"><head rend="bold">Appendices</head><p/></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
