<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_0234i" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Assignment 1</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">The document has a title page which contains:
document title
title part</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">2</p><p n="date">2004-01</p><p n="module title">Design of Measurement Systems</p><p n="module code">ES21Q</p><p n="genre family">Methodology recount</p><p n="discipline">Engineering</p><p n="disciplinary group">PS</p><p n="grade">M</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">981</p><p n="number of s-units">68</p><p n="number of p">52</p><p n="number of tables">0</p><p n="number of figures">2</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">17</p><p n="number of lists">1</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">1</p><p n="abstract present">abstract present</p><p n="average words per s-unit">14.4</p><p n="average s-units per p">1.3</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf) </p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">f</p><p n="year of birth">1983</p><p n="first language">Chinese unspecified</p><p n="education">UKA</p><p n="course">Mechanical Engineering</p><p n="student ID">0234</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><docTitle><titlePart rend="bold">ES21QA1 Design of Measurement Systems- Assignment 1</titlePart></docTitle><titlePart><hi rend="bold">Name: <name type="student name"/> Student number: <name type="student ID"/></hi><hi rend="bold"> Course of study: Mechanical Engineering ( 2nd Year )</hi></titlePart></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="abstract"><head rend="bold italic">Abstract</head><p n="p1.52"><s n="s1.1;p1.52">This report focuses on a cantilever system, whereby a low-level of force is applied and its deflection is detected by gauges and the data is processed as a signal in the form of voltage and be displayed on either analogue or digital displaying device. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold italic">Introduction</head><p n="p2.52"><s n="s1.2;p2.52">Low-level force involved in a cantilever beam system can be measured by <hi rend="bold">Beam-Type Load cells</hi> with the use of strain gauges while double ends system can be measured by, <hi rend="bold">Double ended Load Cells</hi>, which are similar to Beam-Type Cells. </s><s n="s2.2;p2.52">This report will focus on a cantilever system, in which a Beam-Type Load cells involved and will be looking at how a system made up of strain gauges and Beam- Type Load Cells amplify signals, transmit data to an analogue device and how to digitise data to a digital signal for further processing, displaying and storage. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold italic">Theory</head><p n="p3.52"><s n="s1.1;p3.52">Before looking at how to make a system work, it is important to understand how this system is expected to work. </s></p><p n="p4.52"><s n="s1.1;p4.52">Force Beam and strain gauges Wheatstone bridge circuit Amplifiers Data Display Force </s></p><p n="p5.52"><s n="s1.1;p5.52">As the design of the cantilever and selection of strain gauges has already been done, only the beam type instrument is left to be designed. </s></p><p n="p6.52"><s n="s1.3;p6.52">The signal must have to be big enough to be detected. </s><s n="s2.3;p6.52">Therefore, amplifier is used in this case. </s><s n="s3.3;p6.52">There are 2 types of amplifier, generally and they are inverting and non-inverting amplifier. </s></p><p n="p7.52"><s n="s1.1;p7.52">Inverting amplifier inverts polarity of the output from the input, which is 190 degree out of phase with the output. </s></p><p n="p8.52"><s n="s1.1;p8.52">The amplification produced by a circuit is described by its gain. </s></p><p n="p9.52"><s n="s1.2;p9.52">Noise is added in all kind of real electronic circuits as signals passing through them. </s><s n="s2.2;p9.52">It has to be one of the factors that have to be considered </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold italic">Methods</head><div2><head>1a.</head><p n="p10.52"><s n="s1.1;p10.52">Measure the geometrical dimensions of the cantilever and the distance between strain gauges and the support. </s></p><p n="p11.52"><s n="s1.1;p11.52">Distance between the far end of the cantilever and the support= 0.135m </s></p><p n="p12.52"><s n="s1.1;p12.52">Distance between the strain gauge and the support= 0.038m </s></p><p n="p13.52"><s n="s1.1;p13.52">Width of the cantilever= 0.013m </s></p><p n="p14.52"><s n="s1.1;p14.52">Thickness= 0.0005m </s></p><p n="p15.52"><s n="s1.1;p15.52">Young Modulus (Given) = 210GPa </s></p><p n="p16.52"><s n="s1.1;p16.52"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0234i-form.001"/> </s></p><p n="p17.52"><s n="s1.1;p17.52">By hook's law, </s></p><p n="p18.52"><s n="s1.1;p18.52">Strain = <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0234i-form.002"/> </s></p><p n="p19.52"><s n="s1.1;p19.52">= <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0234i-form.003"/> </s></p><p n="p20.52"><s n="s1.1;p20.52">= <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0234i-form.004"/> </s></p><p n="p21.52"><s n="s1.1;p21.52">The system must have very high sensitivity as the strain of the system is so small </s></p></div2><div2><head>1b.</head><p n="p22.52"><s n="s1.1;p22.52">Maximum loading force allowed for this system is given by: </s></p><p n="p23.52"><s n="s1.1;p23.52"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0234i-form.005"/> </s></p><list type="simple"><item>where ε is strain</item><item>F is the maximum loading force</item><item>w is the width of the cantilever</item><item>t is the thickness of the cantilever</item><item>E is the Young Modulus</item><item>x is the distance between the strain gauge and the support</item><item>l is the distance between the end of the cantilever and the support</item></list></div2><div2><head>2.</head><p n="p24.52"><s n="s1.1;p24.52">Top and bottom parts of a strain gauge bridge can be treated as individual dividers and would give: </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0234i-pic.001"><head rend="sub">Diagram of a constant-voltage wheatstone bridge circuit</head></figure><p n="p25.52"><s n="s1.1;p25.52"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0234i-form.006"/> </s></p><p n="p26.52"><s n="s1.1;p26.52"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0234i-form.007"/> </s></p><p n="p27.52"><s n="s1.1;p27.52">And would give an output voltage </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p28.52"><s n="s1.1;p28.52"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0234i-form.008"/><hi rend="bold"> .....(1)</hi> </s></p><p n="p29.52"><s n="s1.1;p29.52">Which can be modified as </s></p><p n="p30.52"><s n="s1.1;p30.52"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0234i-form.009"/> </s></p><p n="p31.52"><s n="s1.1;p31.52">If <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0234i-form.010"/>, <hi rend="bold">V0</hi> will become zero. </s></p></div2><div2><head>3.</head><p n="p32.52"><s n="s1.2;p32.52">A choice of amplifier with a gain between 100 and 1000 using op-amp 741has to be made. </s><s n="s2.2;p32.52">A non inverting amplifier is used because it does not invert the output signal </s></p><p n="p33.52"><s n="s1.1;p33.52">Since Gain in an non-inverting amplifier = R1+R2/R2 , providing the gain is between 100 and 1000. </s></p><p n="p34.52"><s n="s1.1;p34.52">Therefore, the resistance of R1 is chosen to be 1MΩ and R2 to be 1kΩ which will give a gain of 1000. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0234i-pic.002"><head rend="sub"> diagram showing the set-up of the circuit</head></figure><p n="p35.52"><s n="s1.4;p35.52">After connection, a considerable amount of noise in the output due to high gain used has to be filtered out as there is no screen protection. </s><s n="s2.4;p35.52">A low pass filter made of a capacitor across a feedback resistor of the amplifier can be used. </s><s n="s3.4;p35.52">In this case, frequency lower than 10Hz will be filtered as it is regarded as noise. </s><s n="s4.4;p35.52">To find out what capacitor should be used, equation below could be used: </s></p><p n="p36.52"><s n="s1.1;p36.52">Time= RC </s></p><p n="p37.52"><s n="s1.1;p37.52">Substitute T=0.1, calculated by equation F=1/T, where F is the frequency and T is the period, which will give </s></p><p n="p38.52"><s n="s1.1;p38.52"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0234i-form.011"/> </s></p><p n="p39.52"><s n="s1.1;p39.52"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0234i-form.012"/> </s></p><p n="p40.52"><s n="s1.1;p40.52"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0234i-form.013"/> </s></p><p n="p41.52"><s n="s1.1;p41.52">By installing a capacitor of 0.1μF, any frequency lower than 10Hz will hopefully be filtered. </s></p></div2><div2><head>4.</head><p n="p42.52"><s n="s1.1;p42.52">Carry out test and calibration of the design made which includes the ready-made cantilever, strain gauges, bridge circuit and amplifier by adding washers to the nylon screw at the end of the cantilever beam progressively after zeroing the system. </s></p></div2><div2><head>5.</head><p n="p43.52"><s n="s1.2;p43.52">To transform analogue signal to digital signal for further processing or other purposes, analogue data is input to a computer system which has integrated or external analogue-to-digital and digital-to-analogue functions. </s><s n="s2.2;p43.52">Labview can be used to process the data. </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold italic">Conclusions/Discussion</head><p n="p44.52"><s n="s1.5;p44.52">System designed is to measure low-level force and transmit data as a signal and be displayed. </s><s n="s2.5;p44.52">The processing is mainly done by the strain gauges in the circuit. </s><s n="s3.5;p44.52">A gauge is put on each side of the cantilever. </s><s n="s4.5;p44.52">So when there is a force applied at the end of the cantilever, gauge 1 on the top of the cantilever would experience a tensile strain while gauge 2 on the bottom will be under a compressive strain. </s><s n="s5.5;p44.52">The theoretical balance condition of the bridge has been derived early on and we can base on equation(1) to derive an overall equation for output voltage, which takes loading force and deflection into account. </s></p><p n="p45.52"><s n="s1.1;p45.52">Equation 1 gives </s></p><p n="p46.52"><s n="s1.1;p46.52"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0234i-form.014"/> </s></p><p n="p47.52"><s n="s1.1;p47.52">As <hi rend="bold">gauge 1</hi> is under a tensile strain, it will change from R <hi rend="sub">1</hi> to <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0234i-form.015"/> </s></p><p n="p48.52"><s n="s1.1;p48.52">While <hi rend="bold">gauge 2</hi> is under a compressive strain, it will change from R <hi rend="sub">2</hi> to <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0234i-form.016"/> </s></p><p n="p49.52"><s n="s1.1;p49.52">Substituting into (1), will give </s></p><p n="p50.52"><s n="s1.1;p50.52"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0234i-form.017"/> </s></p><p n="p51.52"><s n="s1.3;p51.52">As the equation suggests, the deflection becomes one of the factors that have to be considered. </s><s n="s2.3;p51.52">It is believed dimensions of the cantilever would affect the range of deflection. </s><s n="s3.3;p51.52">Therefore, it is assumed that dimensions of the cantilever would influence the sensitivity of the measurement system. </s></p><p n="p52.52"><s n="s1.2;p52.52">To improve the system, 4 active gauges can be introduced as the sensitivity would be increase dramatically and can compensate any other factors that may influence sensitivity like temperature, axial and torsional components. </s><s n="s2.2;p52.52">Also, repeated reading can minimise any human mistakes. </s></p></div1></body><back/></text></TEI.2>
