<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_0234h" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Fluids Mechanics Design Project. Boat and Aeroplane Drag</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">deleted: header: module name and number, student number; footer: page numbers</note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">Evaluated as candidate compound assignment. Assigned to S4: set of tasks/questions/exercises: non-compound
</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">2</p><p n="date">2004-01</p><p n="module title">Fluid Mechanics</p><p n="module code">ES252</p><p n="genre family">Explanation</p><p n="discipline">Engineering</p><p n="disciplinary group">PS</p><p n="grade">M</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">947</p><p n="number of s-units">52</p><p n="number of p">34</p><p n="number of tables">0</p><p n="number of figures">0</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">13</p><p n="number of lists">0</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">0</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">18.2</p><p n="average s-units per p">1.5</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">complex but non-compound assignment (see notesStmt for details)</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">f</p><p n="year of birth">1983</p><p n="first language">Chinese unspecified</p><p n="education">UKA</p><p n="course">Mechanical Engineering</p><p n="student ID">0234</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><docTitle><titlePart rend="bold"> ES252 Fluids Mechanics Design Project Boat and Aeroplane Drag</titlePart></docTitle></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="section"><p n="p1.34"><s n="s1.1;p1.34">This essay investigates drag in the design of airplanes and ships. </s></p><p n="p2.34"><s n="s1.1;p2.34">Using Buckingham Pi method could derive the key parameters relating to drag </s></p><div2><head rend="underlined">a. </head><p n="p3.34"><s n="s1.1;p3.34">Let D be drag force, ρ be the density, U be the velocity and A be the area and π be the drag coefficient </s></p><p n="p4.34"><s n="s1.1;p4.34"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0234h-form.001"/>, <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0234h-form.002"/>, <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0234h-form.003"/>, <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0234h-form.004"/> </s></p><p n="p5.34"><s n="s1.1;p5.34">Since there are four variables (n) and only purely mechanical effects are involved, </s></p><p n="p6.34"><s n="s1.1;p6.34">m (basic dimension) = 3, n = 4 and n-m = 1, therefore </s></p><p n="p7.34"><s n="s1.1;p7.34"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0234h-form.005"/><hi rend="bold"> and since </hi><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0234h-form.006"/> </s></p><p n="p8.34"><s n="s1.1;p8.34"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0234h-form.007"/> </s></p><p n="p9.34"><s n="s1.1;p9.34"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0234h-form.008"/> </s></p><p n="p10.34"><s n="s1.1;p10.34">By comparing coefficients, a=1, b=2, c=1 </s></p><p n="p11.34"><s n="s1.1;p11.34">Therefore, <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0234h-form.009"/> </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">b. </head><p n="p12.34"><s n="s1.1;p12.34">There are three different types of drag that may be experienced by a body in a flow and 3 other types specially found in ships and aircraft. </s></p><p n="p13.34"><s n="s1.5;p13.34"><hi rend="bold">Skin friction drag</hi>- occurs because of viscosity. </s><s n="s2.5;p13.34">The entire skin friction drag occurs within the boundary layer. </s><s n="s3.5;p13.34"><hi rend="bold">Form drag</hi>- also known as wake and pressure drag and is due, indirectly, to viscous forces in that they modify the pressure distribution acting on the body , thus giving rise to a resisting force and is often determined by body shapes. </s><s n="s4.5;p13.34"><hi rend="bold">Profile drag</hi>- is the sum of skin friction and form drags. </s><s n="s5.5;p13.34">The amount of form drag is generally related to general size and shape. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">c. </head><p n="p14.34"><s n="s1.2;p14.34"><hi rend="bold">Induced drag</hi>- is drag due to the production of Lift. </s><s n="s2.2;p14.34">This could come from a wing of finite length which adds downwards momentum, thus changing the pressure distribution or arises at the wingtips, which causes higher pressure below the wing and lower pressure above it will cause the air to "roll around" the wingtip, creating a vortex which is shed behind the aircraft. </s></p><p n="p15.34"><s n="s1.1;p15.34"><hi rend="bold">Pressure drag</hi>- a drag which is a sum-up of profile drag and form drag and can be calculated by integrating the pressure force over the entire body surface (form drag) and resolving the resulting force in the direction of motion (induced drag) </s></p><p n="p16.34"><s n="s1.4;p16.34"><hi rend="bold">Wave</hi> <hi rend="bold">drag</hi> is a sudden and very powerful form of drag caused by shock waves. </s><s n="s2.4;p16.34">It appears, often, on aircraft flying at high-subsonic speeds and boats. </s><s n="s3.4;p16.34">They can also form at much lower speeds at areas on the aircraft where the Bernoulli effect accelerates local airflow to supersonic speeds. </s><s n="s4.4;p16.34">This can be reduced by designing shapes as close to <hi rend="bold">Sears-Haack body</hi> as possible and the most common solution nowadays is to use as wept-wing which is bent back at some angle, instead of sticking straight out from the fuselage. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">d. </head><p n="p17.34"><s n="s1.4;p17.34">For bodies of very high Reynolds numbers, it is common to assume that turbulant boundary layer is throughout the body surface. </s><s n="s2.4;p17.34">A turbulent boundary layer produces a greater skin-friction drag but a reduced wake drag. </s><s n="s3.4;p17.34">It is surprising since the higer flow speeds associated with turbulent boundary layer have been expected to be associated with an increase in drag when compare to the lower-flow-laminar boundary layer. </s><s n="s4.4;p17.34">At high Reynolds number, wake drag can far exceed skin-friction drag. </s></p><p n="p18.34"><s n="s1.1;p18.34">Because of that, the best regime for flow over a wing during normal flight would be best associated with turbulence as this can dramastically reduce wake drag which is far exceed skin-friction drag during normal flight. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">e. </head><p n="p19.34"><s n="s1.1;p19.34">Pressure drag is to do with the turbulence created and is dependant on the reynolds number and waves drag is negligible as bow waves are created at the front of the ship and if they are shorter in length than the ship they have no effect </s></p><p n="p20.34"><s n="s1.1;p20.34">The only drag factor is the pressure drag given by the reynolds number. </s></p><p n="p21.34"><s n="s1.1;p21.34">Assuming that the tank is <hi rend="bold">15m x 10m</hi> and u is the kinematic viscosity </s></p><p n="p22.34"><s n="s1.1;p22.34"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0234h-form.010"/> </s></p><p n="p23.34"><s n="s1.1;p23.34"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0234h-form.011"/> </s></p><p n="p24.34"><s n="s1.1;p24.34"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0234h-form.012"/> </s></p><p n="p25.34"><s n="s1.2;p25.34">Looking up the moody chart, it is found that the <hi rend="bold">drag coefficient is 0.002</hi>. </s><s n="s2.2;p25.34">Substituting this result into <hi rend="bold">drag coefficient = D / (ρ U2 A)/2</hi> </s></p><p n="p26.34"><s n="s1.1;p26.34">The drag force is 4062N ( assuming that the tank is 15m x 10m ) </s></p><p n="p27.34"><s n="s1.1;p27.34">Power required = (4062) (5.14) = <hi rend="bold italic">20879 W</hi> </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">f. </head><p n="p28.34"><s n="s1.1;p28.34">Increase of roughness in hull can never be underestimated as it could result in an increase of skin-friction drag, which would require additional power with increased consumption of feel to maintain the vassel speed and can be given by the equation below: </s></p><p n="p29.34"><s n="s1.1;p29.34"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0234h-form.013"/> </s></p><p n="p30.34"><s n="s1.1;p30.34">where R is the drag, Δ C <hi rend="sub">F</hi> is the drag coefficient increase, C <hi rend="sub">T</hi> is the total drag coefficient, k <hi rend="sub">2</hi> is roughness on a rougher surface and k <hi rend="sub">1</hi> is roughness on a less rough surface. </s></p><p n="p31.34"><s n="s1.1;p31.34">Studies showed that ships generally get tougher due to mechanical damage such as corrosion, cracking, blistering, etc. of the hull surface. </s></p><p n="p32.34"><s n="s1.5;p32.34">Foul released technology products (e.g. paint) can be used to avoid fouling (drag caused by living creatures on the ship) by providing a slippery surface which would inhabit growth of marine organisms and oxidation by avoid contact between water and the hull surface. </s><s n="s2.5;p32.34">Skin friction caused by roughness is also important to aircrafts. </s><s n="s3.5;p32.34">Roughness would cause friction between the skin of the surface and the air flow. </s><s n="s4.5;p32.34">It is obvious that if the surface is dirty, has frost, ice or other obstructions, drag will increase. </s><s n="s5.5;p32.34">Effects of skin drag can be reduced by smooth surfaces and flush riveting in the design, and by keeping the surface clean and waxed. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">g. </head><p n="p33.34"><s n="s1.2;p33.34">Scale models can be used in designs instead of life size ones as it is cheaper in the modelling stage as fluids behave same on small and large scales. </s><s n="s2.2;p33.34">However, the testing environment for scale models is not always the same as life size ones, which might cause errors. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">h. </head><p n="p34.34"><s n="s1.2;p34.34">Nowadays, computer softwares like Matlab can model boat and airplane designs. </s><s n="s2.2;p34.34">They are very easy to access and do not cost as much as real models Moreover, it is very simple to change the input conditions without rewriting the program but at the same time they may not be very accurate as there are lots of assumption to be made </s></p></div2></div1></body><back><div1 type="bibliography"><head rend="bold">Reference: </head><p><seg type="URL" n="http://www.international-marine.com/news/news_items/HRPCtechpaper.pdf"/></p><p><seg type="URL" n="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Aerodynamic"/></p><p><seg type="URL" n="http://fluids.esm.vt.edu/LABS/MANUAL/EXP7.PDF"/></p><p><seg type="URL" n="http://home.swipnet.se/~w-65189/AP_html/aerodynamik.htm"/></p></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
