<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_0237c" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Management report on alternative options of increasing production of Flexi - Connector</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">deleted: header: module name and number, student number; footer: page numbers</note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">appendices: projections and calculations</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">2</p><p n="date">2006-04</p><p n="module title">Management Accounting</p><p n="module code">IB2240</p><p n="genre family">Case study</p><p n="discipline">Business</p><p n="disciplinary group">SS</p><p n="grade">M</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">1988</p><p n="number of s-units">83</p><p n="number of p">57</p><p n="number of tables">0</p><p n="number of figures">0</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">0</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">19</p><p n="abstract present">abstract present</p><p n="average words per s-unit">24.0</p><p n="average s-units per p">1.5</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">f</p><p n="year of birth">1985</p><p n="first language">Czech</p><p n="education">UK2</p><p n="course">Business</p><p n="student ID">0237</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><docTitle><titlePart>Compotech Industries Plc</titlePart></docTitle><titlePart>Management report on alternative options of increasing production of Flexi - Connector</titlePart></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="abstract"><head rend="bold">Executive Summary</head><p rend="ordered" n="p1.57"><s n="s1.1;p1.57">The Flexi Connector component is expected to reach its full capacity of 75 million units in 1994, the expected demand is estimated to rise by 10% per year </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p2.57"><s n="s1.1;p2.57">Three alternative options are presented and analysed. </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p3.57"><s n="s1.1;p3.57"><hi rend="bold">Option 1</hi> - involves expansion of the Santa Clara plant, this would lead to the NPV of -$1,143,242 after 5 years using 20% discount rate, $4,549,094 using 10% discount rate and $40,915,000 after 10 years using 10% rate. </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p4.57"><s n="s1.1;p4.57"><hi rend="bold">Option 2</hi> - involves using an existing plant in Waltham, which yields the MPV of $6,418,086 after 5 years with 20%, $11,297,189 with 10% and $40,189,842 after 10 years with 10% </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p5.57"><s n="s1.1;p5.57"><hi rend="bold">Option 3</hi> - involves building a new plant in Ireland, this gives NPV of -$29,810,367 after 5 years with 20%, -$25,996,435 with 10% and $62,068,509 using 10% discount rate. </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p6.57"><s n="s1.1;p6.57">Based on the analysis, the detailed plan should be established for Waltham and Ireland projects since Waltham produces highest NPV after 5 years and Ireland the highest NPV after 10 years </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p7.57"><s n="s1.1;p7.57">With a detailed plan, there is a need to consider other factors apart from NPV as well, such as labour availability at the area, accessiveness of materials, or other methods such as IRR and Payback </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p8.57"><s n="s1.3;p8.57">This report has been based on assumptions that there is no inventory policy, and thus the production every year corresponds exactly to the demand, up to a point when demand reaches the maximum production capacity, from this point onwards the units of sales are equal to the maximum capacity. </s><s n="s2.3;p8.57">It also assumes that all cash flows occur at the end of the respective year. </s><s n="s3.3;p8.57">Additional assumptions are stated in the appendix. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Introduction</head><p n="p9.57"><s n="s1.3;p9.57">A report has been required to evaluate the alternative options of increasing the production capacity of Flexi - Connector component for Compotech Industries Plc. </s><s n="s2.3;p9.57">The current plant producing this component is projected to reach its full capacity of 75 million units in 1994. </s><s n="s3.3;p9.57">The sale is expected to rise by 10% per year. </s></p><p n="p10.57"><s n="s1.1;p10.57">The possible alternatives to bring additional capacity of Flexi - Connector are as follows: </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p11.57"><s rend="bold" n="s1.1;p11.57">Option 1 - Expansion of the existing Santa Clara plant, headed up by Elisabeth Upton </s></p><p n="p12.57"><s n="s1.2;p12.57">Expand the Santa Clara site in California to produce an additional 30 millions units annually starting from 1995, with a cost involving $23 million. </s><s n="s2.2;p12.57">The selling price and variable costs would remain the same, with fixed cost rising from $2.1 million to $2.4 million in 1997. </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p13.57"><s rend="bold" n="s1.1;p13.57">Option 2 - Using a plant in Waltham with existing equipment, headed up by David Hope </s></p><p n="p14.57"><s n="s1.2;p14.57">The capacity of the plant would be about 25 million units, with a total cost of $14 million spent on renovations of the site and equipment. </s><s n="s2.2;p14.57">Selling price and variable cost remain the same, with higher fixed manufacturing costs - $2.4 million from 1995 to $2.6 million from 1997. </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p15.57"><s rend="bold" n="s1.1;p15.57">Option 3 - Build a new greenfield plant in Ireland, headed up by Jack Dunbar </s></p><p n="p16.57"><s n="s1.4;p16.57">New site can produce up to 70 million units per year. </s><s n="s2.4;p16.57">The cost involves $1 million for acquiring a site, $10 million on building the plant and additional $50 million on equipments. </s><s n="s3.4;p16.57">Selling price remains the same, but variable cost would decrease to $0.195 per unit. </s><s n="s4.4;p16.57">Fixed manufacturing cost would be $2.8 annually beginning in 1995, increasing to $2.9 million from 1999. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Evaluation of the NPV method</head><p n="p17.57"><s n="s1.2;p17.57">NPV method is the method of evaluating project that recognizes that the dollar received immediately is preferable to a dollar received at some future date. </s><s n="s2.2;p17.57">By taking into account the time value of money and discounting cash flows, projects can be appraised before the investment decision is made. </s></p><p n="p18.57"><s n="s1.4;p18.57">This approach finds the present value of expected net cash flows of an investment, discounted at cost of capital and subtract from it the initial cash outlay of the project. </s><s n="s2.4;p18.57">The method has a clear decision rule to apply. </s><s n="s3.4;p18.57">In case the present value is positive, the project should be accepted; if negative, it should be rejected. </s><s n="s4.4;p18.57">If the projects under consideration are mutually exclusive the one with the highest net present value should be chosen. </s></p><p n="p19.57"><s n="s1.1;p19.57">NPV is being most often recommended as the soundest technique for assessing alternative investment opportunities as it: </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p20.57"><s n="s1.1;p20.57">- takes into account the time value of the money (the discount factor is based on the opportunity cost of finance) </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p21.57"><s n="s1.1;p21.57">- includes all of the relevant cash flows irrespective of when they are expected to occur </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p22.57"><s n="s1.1;p22.57">- addresses the objectives of the business: to maximise shareholders´ wealth </s></p><p n="p23.57"><s n="s1.1;p23.57">However, like other investment appraisal methods, it has <hi rend="underlined">limitations</hi> such as: </s></p><p n="p24.57"><s n="s1.1;p24.57">It can be difficult to identify an appropriate discount rate, which is crucial for NPV, i.e. if the discount factor is stated too high, the NPV may come out unnecessarily negative, or if the discount rate is stated too low, all risk factors may not be included and the project maybe over appraised. </s></p><p n="p25.57"><s n="s1.3;p25.57">Moreover, as the solution comes in dollars, the NPV does not show the percentage rate of return. </s><s n="s2.3;p25.57">I.e. </s><s n="s3.3;p25.57">A particular project may seem to give the highest NPV, but the percentage of return, in comparison of the capital initiated, may be lower than other projects. </s></p><p n="p26.57"><s n="s1.2;p26.57">Moreover, in order to calculated NPV, cash flows are usually assumed to occur at the end of a year, which in practice is over simplistic. </s><s n="s2.2;p26.57">NPV also does not show the demand trend, whether it as downward or upward. </s></p><p n="p27.57"><s n="s1.3;p27.57">Despite NPV having disadvantages stated above, it may be the most recommended technique. </s><s n="s2.3;p27.57">IRR is conceivable as realistic as NPV, however, the R value there is much harder to find through the method of trial and error. </s><s n="s3.3;p27.57">Moreover, unlike Payback or ARR takes into account the time factor and discounts cash flows accordingly. </s></p><p n="p28.57"><s n="s1.2;p28.57">Thus the NPV is necessary in assessing the alternative investment opportunities, and is definitely needed in order to asses a project in advance whether it is worth considering. </s><s n="s2.2;p28.57">However it is recommended that other methods, such as Payback, ARR are used at the same time as well, to asses the attractiveness of various options from different perspectives. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Net Present Value Analysis</head><p n="p29.57"><s n="s1.1;p29.57">The NPV calculations using different discount rate and time horizons are included in Appendix 2 and explained below. </s></p><div2><head rend="underlined">NPV using a discount rate of 20% in 5 years horizon</head><p n="p30.57"><s n="s1.1;p30.57">When a discount factor of 20% was used, in five years horizon, Option 1 Santa Clara comes slightly negative, which means that the initial capital would not be recovered after 5 years, thus it would not be recommended at this stage. </s></p><p n="p31.57"><s n="s1.1;p31.57">Option 2 -Waltham project as the only one comes with a positive NPV of $6,418,086, since it involves the lowest initial capital. </s></p><p n="p32.57"><s n="s1.1;p32.57">Option 3 - Ireland project gives a clearly negative NPV value of - $29,810,367, this is due to starting a brand new project, with the highest capital among 3 alternatives required to buy a site and acquire new equipment. </s></p><p n="p33.57"><s n="s1.1;p33.57">From these results, the Waltham project seems clearly most attractive since it shows a relatively high NPV in relation to the size of the project and amount invested as an initial capital. </s></p><p n="p34.57"><s n="s1.1;p34.57">However, 20% discount rate in this set of calculations may mean that the projects have been penalized, since the discount rate might have been set too high and not corresponding to the company's cost of capital. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">NPV using a discount rate of 10% in 5 years horizon</head><p n="p35.57"><s n="s1.1;p35.57">Since the discount rate is reduced to 10%, while the time considered remains at 5 years, NPV in all 3 projects should be expected to improve since the cash flow after discounting in each year should be higher. </s></p><p n="p36.57"><s n="s1.1;p36.57">NPV for Santa Clara project would increase to $4,549,094 , however the NPV seems a bit low in relation to the size of the project. </s></p><p n="p37.57"><s n="s1.1;p37.57">Waltham would further improve to $11,297,189 which remains the highest reward among 3 alternatives. </s></p><p n="p38.57"><s n="s1.2;p38.57">Ireland however still remains significantly negative. </s><s n="s2.2;p38.57">This is due to the plant being too expensive to establish, thus the capital is not recoverable after 5 years. </s></p><p n="p39.57"><s n="s1.1;p39.57">Thus when the NPV is considered at 10% in 5 years horizon, the Waltham project still remains the most attractive one, followed by Santa Clara, while Ireland would still not be recommended. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">NPV using a discount rate of 10% in 10 years horizon</head><p n="p40.57"><s n="s1.4;p40.57">The demand for Flexi - Connect is expected to remain strong for at least 10 years. </s><s n="s2.4;p40.57">This demand has already outweighed the capacity of Santa Clara and Waltham since 1998. </s><s n="s3.4;p40.57">Thus when the time horizon is changed to 10 years, using 10% discount rate, Waltham project with NPV of $40,189,842 , comes out last. </s><s n="s4.4;p40.57">This is because it has the lowest capacity among the other two. </s></p><p n="p41.57"><s n="s1.2;p41.57">The NPV of Santa Clara is approximately $700,000 higher than Waltham. </s><s n="s2.2;p41.57">Despite having a lower NPV value than Ireland, both Santa Clara and Waltham sites with a NPV of over $40 million seems promising. </s></p><p n="p42.57"><s n="s1.2;p42.57">Ireland, which gave a negative value in the first two calculations, comes out best when considered in 10 years horizon. </s><s n="s2.2;p42.57">Since Ireland has twice higher production capacity and lower variable cost than other two plants, the NPV reaches $62,068,509 , which seems most attractive among all 3 projects. </s></p><p n="p43.57"><s n="s1.1;p43.57">Since Waltham and Santa Clara have limited production capacity at 25 million units and 30 million units respectively, they may not be able to cater for the demand later which is expected to rise to twice their maximum capacity. </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Recommendation</head><p n="p44.57"><s n="s1.1;p44.57">According to NPV rules, if the projects under consideration are mutually exclusive the one with the highest net present value should be chosen. </s></p><p n="p45.57"><s n="s1.1;p45.57">From the analysis given above, it would be advisable to focus on Ireland and Waltham and establish a more detailed plan on these two projects, based on expectation that Flexi - Connect is expected to remain strong for at least 10 years. </s></p><p n="p46.57"><s n="s1.2;p46.57">Santa Clara alternative would not be recommended since it involves a higher amount of capital invested in than Waltham, but in 5 years horizon it yields a lower NPV and in 10 years horizon insignificantly higher amount. </s><s n="s2.2;p46.57">However if the Flexi Connect is expected to remain strong for longer than 10 years, Santa Clara may yield a higher NPV than Waltham since then, but this is uncertain. </s></p><p n="p47.57"><s n="s1.1;p47.57">When comparing Waltham with Ireland, Waltham would produce an earlier payback, but after that it would not be able to satisfy a complete demand and other expansion options would need to be considered again or CIS may consider outsourcing as another option. </s></p><p n="p48.57"><s n="s1.1;p48.57">In case of Ireland, in 10 years time it produces the highest NPV but there is a need to consider a risk factor as well since payback will not be achieved before 7 years. </s></p><p n="p49.57"><s n="s1.1;p49.57">Thus based on the arguments and supporting calculations included in the Appendix, there is a need to develop Ireland and Waltham projects more in detail, with the exact calculations on expenditure and other costs. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Conclusion</head><p n="p50.57"><s n="s1.1;p50.57">Based on the exact detailed plans, the decision can then be made on the chosen alternative with higher NPV. </s></p><p n="p51.57"><s n="s1.1;p51.57">However, apart from NPV, other issued should be taken into account as well when making decisions, such as: </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p52.57"><s n="s1.1;p52.57">Firstly it may not be advisable to invest in capacity that will be fully utilised only after 5 yrs and idling afterwards (Waltham, Santa Clara) unless the company considers outsourcing (to ask other businesses to produce the stock) as an additional external source for keeping up the stock </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p53.57"><s n="s1.1;p53.57">There is a need to consider the location of the plant, its proximity to the local market, and cost of transport to transfer components </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p54.57"><s n="s1.1;p54.57">The availability of labour at the specified area, whether enough staff could be recruited to produce the component </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p55.57"><s n="s1.1;p55.57">The availability of materials at that area </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p56.57"><s n="s1.1;p56.57">The availability and skills of managers, and their ability to overlook additional plant </s></p><p n="p57.57"><s n="s1.1;p57.57">With these specific points in mind, the most realistic and appropriate project with highest NPV should be chosen. </s></p></div1></body><back><div1 type="appendix"><head>APPENDICES</head><p/></div1><div1 type="bibliography"><head rend="bold">Bibliography</head><p>Atkinson,A., Kaplan,R.S., Young,M.S. (2003) <hi rend="italic">Management Accounting</hi>. 4<hi rend="sup">th</hi> edition, Prentice Hall</p><p>Drury,C. (2000) Management &amp; Cost Accounting, 5<hi rend="sup">th</hi> edition, Thomson</p><p>McLaney,E., Atrill,P. (2002) <hi rend="italic">Accounting: An Introduction</hi>. 2<hi rend="sup">nd</hi> edition, Prentice Hall</p></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
