<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_0237b" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Management Report on Firm E ´s performance</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">deleted: header: module name and number, student number; footer: page numbers</note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">appendices: SWOT Analysis; Calculations and figures; Product Portfolio Analysis; data tables</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">2</p><p n="date">2006-02</p><p n="module title">Marketing Analysis</p><p n="module code">IB2890</p><p n="genre family">Case study</p><p n="discipline">Business</p><p n="disciplinary group">SS</p><p n="grade">M</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">3036</p><p n="number of s-units">117</p><p n="number of p">61</p><p n="number of tables">0</p><p n="number of figures">0</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">1</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">5</p><p n="abstract present">abstract present</p><p n="average words per s-unit">25.9</p><p n="average s-units per p">1.9</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">f</p><p n="year of birth">1985</p><p n="first language">Czech</p><p n="education">UK2</p><p n="course">Business</p><p n="student ID">0237</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><docTitle><titlePart>Management Report on Firm E ´s performance</titlePart></docTitle></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="abstract"><head rend="bold">Executive Summary</head><p rend="ordered" n="p1.61"><s n="s1.7;p1.61">The company (E) is competing with other 4 firms in the Honduras Industry. </s><s n="s2.7;p1.61">The firms compete in 2 product markets - Sonites and Vodites, where demands for 2 markets are independent of each other. </s><s n="s3.7;p1.61">Both markets may be targeted at different groups of customers. </s><s n="s4.7;p1.61">Sonites are mend for groups of Buffs, Singles, Professionals, High Earners and Others. </s><s n="s5.7;p1.61">Sonites customers, except for High Earners, are quite price - sensitive. </s><s n="s6.7;p1.61">Vodites customers include Innovators, Early Adopters and Followers. </s><s n="s7.7;p1.61">The products are distributed to 3 distinct channels - Specialty stores, Department stores and Mass Merchandisers. </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p2.61"><s n="s1.1;p2.61">During the 7 periods of competing with other companies, the main objective was to maximize the Share Price Index through optimizing the Market share, Sales growth and Net contribution </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p3.61"><s n="s1.2;p3.61">The company' s market share has been growing consistently, this is mostly due to being the only player in the Vodite market. </s><s n="s2.2;p3.61">Currently the company is holding 55.6% of industry, despite losing sales in Sonite market </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p4.61"><s n="s1.1;p4.61">The suggested strategy for next 3 periods is to launch SEN2, modify the marketing mix for SETH and reposition the declining products to extent their life </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p5.61"><s n="s1.1;p5.61">The key lessons learned from the Markstrat experience was to pay attention to Customer Behavior, Market Research Studies and Segmentation </s></p></div1><div1 type="front-back-matter"><head>Contents</head><p/></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Introduction</head><list type="bulleted"><head>The aim of the report is to:</head><item>explain the company´s current market and financial situation, its position in the market and how it was arrived at</item><item>provide a suggested marketing strategy and supporting analysis for the next three periods which the upcoming team could follow</item><item>provide learning evaluation from participation in the marketing team</item></list><p n="p6.61"/></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">2. Company ´s current market and financial situation</head><p n="p7.61"><s n="s1.2;p7.61">When the Marketing team was recruited, Sonite was already a well established market, with several strong brands at different price points covering a wide range of needs. </s><s n="s2.2;p7.61">As other companies, firm E marketed 2 Sonite products - SEMI and SELF, which accounted for 25.6% of market share in terms of value (retail sales) and 19.6% in terms of units sold (the share in terms of unit sold is lower than the share in terms of value due to the firm placing higher prices on SELF than the competitors). </s></p><div2><head rend="underlined"> Analysis of the actions taken in previous periods which led to the current situation: </head><p n="p8.61"><s n="s1.1;p8.61">The company has been growing consistently since Period 1 to Period 7. </s></p><p n="p9.61"><s n="s1.1;p9.61">The main objectives during the 7 periods have been to maximize profit, sustain business growth, maximize market share and shares price and thus keeping the leading market position. </s></p><p n="p10.61"><s n="s1.1;p10.61">This was mainly achieved by Market Research studies as these show how consumers perceive different brands in the market, thus the company could adjust the production levels accordingly. </s></p><p n="p11.61"><s n="s1.1;p11.61">Around 20% of budget was spent on Research and Development studies every week in order to gain a competitive advantage of either Product Development or Diversification. </s></p><p n="p12.61"><s n="s1.1;p12.61">The rest of budget was spent on advertising media, market research and sales force payments. </s></p><p n="p13.61"><s n="s1.2;p13.61">The company has gained the leading market position since Period 3, when the market share rose by 40.9% to 37.2% in the market, with share prices rising by 42% to $1904. </s><s n="s2.2;p13.61">This was due to the introduction of the new product SENG to the existing Sonite market (Product Development). </s></p><p n="p14.61"><s n="s1.1;p14.61">Another key to success of the company was to be the first who entered the new Vodite market, thanks to early R&amp;D projects PVEMI and PVEST. </s></p><p n="p15.61"><s n="s1.1;p15.61">The introduction of VEST in the Period 4 has further increased company's market share to 52.2% and thus to cover half of the market. </s></p><p n="p16.61"><s n="s1.3;p16.61">While there have been increasing demands and net contributions for both Sonites and Vodites products, the sales of SELF had been decreasing gradually. </s><s n="s2.3;p16.61">The retail price of SELF had been increased since Period 2 because of the weak price elasticity of demand <hi rend="italic">(Appendix 2, point 1)</hi> at 1.167, which means that the demand will decrease with an increase in price, however not significantly. </s><s n="s3.3;p16.61">Despite price changes the demand for SELF was still falling, thus the production was stopped since Period 3, with remaining inventories being sold in the following 3 periods. </s></p><p n="p17.61"><s n="s1.1;p17.61">Further products SETH was introduced in Period 5, VERT and VEXY in Period 6. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">Current situation</head><p n="p18.61"><s n="s1.3;p18.61">Company has been enjoying the highest and still increasing Share Price in the market since Period 3, reaching to the amount of $4345, which is an increase of 293% since Period 1 [(4345 -1106) ÷ 1106]. </s><s n="s2.3;p18.61">This is more than twice of the value of the following company U with the share price of $1559. </s><s n="s3.3;p18.61">Return on investment ratio has increased by 133% to 6.9 [(6.9 - 2.96)÷2.96] since the Period 1. </s></p><div3><head rend="underlined">Product portfolio: </head><p n="p19.61"><s n="s1.1;p19.61">At the moment, company is managing 3 Sonite products SEMI, SENG and SETH and 3 Vodites VEST, VERT and VEXY. </s></p><p n="p20.61"><s n="s1.1;p20.61">The highest Retail Sales come from the Vodite market, where the company has been holding 100% of market share since Period 4 when the first Vodite VEST was introduced. </s></p></div3><div3><head rend="underlined">The segmentation and positioning: </head><p n="p21.61"><s n="s1.1;p21.61">Looking at each product specifically, 90% of SEMI was targeted by the company at Professionals and High Earners, SELF was mostly targeted at Buffers and 85% of SENG at Singles and Others. </s></p><p n="p22.61"><s n="s1.2;p22.61">Vodite products were targeted specifically and solely to certain group of customers. </s><s n="s2.2;p22.61">The entire production of VEST was targeted at Innovators, VERT Early Adopters and VEXY is solely for the Followers group. </s></p><p n="p23.61"><s n="s1.2;p23.61">Most of the company E` s sales in the entire market are being sold to Singles - 36.2%, least 8.6% to Buffs. </s><s n="s2.2;p23.61">12.8% of sales shares are sold to Professionals, out of which SEMI is already satisfying half of these needs for Professionals. </s></p></div3><div3><head rend="underlined">Comparison of company's performance over periods</head><p n="p24.61"><s n="s1.1;p24.61">The Net Contribution after Marketing over Revenue has been calculated to compare the performance of Sonites and Vodites over time <hi rend="italic">(Appendix 3)</hi>. </s></p><p n="p25.61"><s n="s1.3;p25.61">These show that the highest contribution over revenue has been earned for both markets during the Period 4, where the company has earned 54 cents for $1 of revenue for a Sonite and 65 cents for one Vodite. </s><s n="s2.3;p25.61">Despite rising Sales for the Vodites, its contribution margin has been decreasing gradually to 53 cents for $1 of revenue for this Period, when its Revenue has been highest ever. </s><s n="s3.3;p25.61">The ratio for the Sonite is also lower than past 4 periods, 45.8%. </s></p></div3><div3><head rend="underlined">Competitors</head><p n="p26.61"><s n="s1.3;p26.61">Despite the consistent rise in the sales of Vodites, reaching $326,894 in Period 7, Sonites sales have been decreasing since Period 4 to the amount of $182,990 now. </s><s n="s2.3;p26.61">The company has lost market share in the Sonite market, falling by 22.6% since last period. </s><s n="s3.3;p26.61">Sonite sales dropped by 21.6% since last period to $182 990 (started falling since Period 5), as its strongest brand SEMI has reached the Maturity stage in Period 4, and now its at the Decline stage. </s></p><p n="p27.61"><s n="s1.1;p27.61">Thus in the past 2 periods, the company has been concentrating on rising the production of Vodites, while reducing the production of SEMI and SENG. </s></p><p n="p28.61"><s n="s1.2;p28.61">Company holds more than half of market share (55.6%), and with companies U and O it forms 95% of the total share in the market. </s><s n="s2.2;p28.61">However, in terms of Sonite market, the company's market share has dropped to 31%, now lying behind company O with 31.6% in the Sonite market. </s></p><p n="p29.61"><s n="s1.2;p29.61">O and U are the strongest competitors as there has been an increase in their Retail Sales and units sold in almost all their products. </s><s n="s2.2;p29.61">While the sales of SEMI and SENG were decreasing by more than 30%, SOOZ from company O has reached the largest share in the Sonite market of 15.5% in terms of value, or SUSI from U rising by 42.5% since last period. </s></p><p n="p30.61"><s n="s1.1;p30.61">However, the company still has the highest Contribution after Marketing over Revenue ratio of 50.6% in Period 7 <hi rend="italic">(Appendix 3)</hi> which means that after marketing costs the company earns 50 cents for $1 of revenue, compared to 36 cents for O and U, and A and I even making losses. </s></p></div3></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">3. Suggested strategy for next 3 periods: </head><p n="p31.61"><s n="s1.2;p31.61">In order to determine the strategy for next 3 periods, the SWOT analysis have been included in the Appendix 1. </s><s n="s2.2;p31.61">Each product has been allocated to the BCG Product portfolio <hi rend="italic"> (Appendix 4),</hi> </s></p><div2><head rend="underlined">PERIOD 8 </head><p n="p32.61"><s n="s1.1;p32.61">The market share for the Sonite market has been decreasing in the past 2 periods, thus there is a need to develop a strategy to increase the share for Sonite and keep the leading position in the Vodite market. </s></p><p n="p33.61"><s n="s1.1;p33.61">The marketing mix is going to be used to determine the strategy. </s></p><div3><head rend="bold">Sonite market</head><p n="p34.61"><s n="s1.4;p34.61">The project PSEN2 has been completed, thus the new product <hi rend="bold">SEN2</hi> should be launched. </s><s n="s2.4;p34.61">This product has similar characteristics to SOOZ with the selling price of $320 and highest product market share <hi rend="italic">(See Appendix 7).</hi> </s><s n="s3.4;p34.61">Although SEN2 has higher power, the retail price should be set at $315 to increase the market share for the company. </s><s n="s4.4;p34.61">At this recommended price and margin of 40%, the company would receive revenue of $189 per unit. </s></p><p n="p35.61"><s n="s1.1;p35.61">SEN2 should be segmented mainly for Buffs (60%) and Singles (25%) who require average to high performance products and are price - sensitive, moreover the Buffs group needs to be penetrated more as now the segment belongs by 70% to company O. </s></p><p n="p36.61"><s n="s1.3;p36.61">Break Even would be reached after 32,877 units of product being sold <hi rend="italic">(Appendix 2,point 3).</hi> </s><s n="s2.3;p36.61">The volume sold for SOOZ was 294,612 units in Period 7, thus 90,000 units of SEN2 could be produced for the Introductory stage. </s><s n="s3.3;p36.61">SEN2 is a new product, thus a budget $4000 needs to be spent on advertising to make consumers aware of the product. </s></p><p n="p37.61"><s n="s1.6;p37.61"><hi rend="bold">SEMI</hi> is currently at the Decline stage, with sales falling by 32.8% since last period. </s><s n="s2.6;p37.61">The BCG Product Analysis <hi rend="italic">(Appendix 4)</hi> shows that SEMI belongs to the "Dog" group. </s><s n="s3.6;p37.61">However it should not be eliminated yet as it is the only product with relatively low volume, high performance and high power, thus the Marketing Mix should be modified instead. </s><s n="s4.6;p37.61">As SEMI is targeted mainly at High Earners and Professionals who require quality and can afford expensive products, the price was raised in previous 2 periods to secure higher sales. </s><s n="s5.6;p37.61">However the price elasticity of demand shows that the demand for SEMI is strongly elastic = 9.3 <hi rend="italic">(Appendix 2,point 2)</hi>, thus it is recommended to decrease the price back to $505 (which is closer to SUSI with the price of $499 and similar characteristics). </s><s n="s6.6;p37.61">The Conjoint analysis shows that the price for both High Earners and Professionals should lie between $434 and $517 <hi rend="italic">(Appendix 5)</hi>, thus the segment target of 75% Professionals and 15% High Earners could be kept the same as last period. </s></p><p n="p38.61"><s n="s1.2;p38.61">The volume sold for SEMI was 172,365 units, with 27,693 units left in inventory. </s><s n="s2.2;p38.61">The aim is to sell 170,000 units in Period 8, thus 145000 units should be produced. </s></p><p n="p39.61"><s n="s1.2;p39.61">Since SEMI is mostly targeted at Professionals and High Earners, the channel distribution should be split accordingly, based on Appendix 9 (Consumers Shopping Habits) i.e. approximately 40% to Specialty stores, 35% to Department stores and 25% to Mass Merchandisers. </s><s n="s2.2;p39.61">As consumers already know about SEMI, advertising should be kept at the same level of $1000. </s></p><p n="p40.61"><s n="s1.2;p40.61"><hi rend="bold">SETH</hi> has been allocated to the "Star" group in BCG <hi rend="italic">(Appendix 4)</hi> as sales have increased by 89.5% since last period. </s><s n="s2.2;p40.61">However the market share could be increased further by using the strategy of Market Penetration (increasing sales in the current market with current products). </s></p><p n="p41.61"><s n="s1.1;p41.61">In the past 2 periods, SETH was targeted entirely at Others group, but it has been forecasted that the penetration of this segment may not be as high as the other segments, thus for the next periods, the product should be targeted at 20% for Singles (as an extremely affordable product) and 20% for Buffs (Appendix 6 shows Buffs purchase intentions for SETH). </s></p><p n="p42.61"><s n="s1.1;p42.61">A threat for the SETH may be the launch of the product SIBU with similar characteristics, however as SIBU is going to be sold for higher price, the price for SETH should be kept the same. </s></p><p n="p43.61"><s n="s1.1;p43.61">During this period 198,000 units of SETH were sold, with no inventories left, thus the production could be increased to 200,000 units. </s></p><p n="p44.61"><s n="s1.4;p44.61"><hi rend="bold">SENG</hi> - in the previous periods, SENG was mostly targeted at Singles, whose recommended price range lies between $224 and $307. </s><s n="s2.4;p44.61">Both price and characteristics of SENG meet the specifications of the Singles group <hi rend="italic">(Appendix 5 and 7)</hi>. </s><s n="s3.4;p44.61">According to the Purchase Intentions table, after Singles, the next 2 interested groups are Buffs and Others, at the proportion of 4.1% and 3.2% respectively. </s><s n="s4.4;p44.61">Thus the market segment for next period should be split as 60% Singles, 15% Buffs and 15% Others. </s></p><p n="p45.61"><s n="s1.2;p45.61">The production of SENG was 298,700 units in Period 7, with 36 units left in inventory, despite the retail prices remaining constant. </s><s n="s2.2;p45.61">Thus an increase advertising expenditure from $1000 to $1500 will be needed to increase the customers` perception about the product. </s></p></div3><div3><head rend="bold">Vodite market</head><p n="p46.61"><s n="s1.5;p46.61">The company continues to keep 100% of the market share in the Vodite market, with Sales increasing consistently since the launch of the first Vodite in Period 4. </s><s n="s2.5;p46.61">Thus the only change could be to decrease the price to make it harder for competitors to enter the market. </s><s n="s3.5;p46.61">The price elasticity of demand for the Vodite products is strongly elastic <hi rend="italic">(Appendix 2, point 4),</hi> thus the price of the VEST should be decreased to $950, VERT to $750, and VEXY $550. </s><s n="s4.5;p46.61">Since there are no inventories left for VERT, the production should be increased to 210,000 units, production of VEST kept at the same level of 192000 since there are few items left in stock and VEXY reduced to 60,000 due to many units in inventory. </s><s n="s5.5;p46.61">Vodite products are already well known in the market, thus an amount of $2,500 respectively for each product should be spent on advertising to remind customers of the product. </s></p><p n="p47.61"><s n="s1.1;p47.61">There are 2 uncompleted projects in the R&amp;D department, thus $1252,000 for PSEM2 and $4940,000 for PVEMI should be spent in order to finish the research and launch the products in Period 9. </s></p><p n="p48.61"><s n="s1.1;p48.61">The amount of budget spend during this period is provided in <hi rend="underlined">Appendix 2, point 5</hi>. </s></p></div3></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">PERIOD 9 and 10</head><p n="p49.61"><s n="s1.1;p49.61">SEN2 was introduced in Period 8 and hopefully as the Product Development it will have gained back the lost Sodite share. </s></p><p n="p50.61"><s n="s1.3;p50.61">The R&amp;D on PSEM2 and PVEMI will probably be completed, thus SEM2 and VEMI would be ready for launch. </s><s n="s2.3;p50.61">SEM2 has the relatively high power and low volume and weight, thus it should be targeted at medium Professionals and High Earners, at a price of $490. </s><s n="s3.3;p50.61">Since the Vodite brands were introduced 5 periods ago, VEMI should be targeted fully at Followers as it is the largest group of Vodite customers at a price of $900 <hi rend="italic">(advised by Conjoint analysis)</hi> </s></p><p n="p51.61"><s n="s1.2;p51.61">During the period 9, new R&amp;D should be started on a new product, targeted at top class of Professionals and High Earners, with higher price than SEMI, low weight and volume and maximum frequency and power. </s><s n="s2.2;p51.61">Either product launch or modification should be done during period 10. </s></p><p n="p52.61"><s n="s1.1;p52.61">Competitors may introduce the Vodite products during next 2 periods, thus the marketing mix will have to be adjusted to keep the leading market position for the company. </s></p><p n="p53.61"><s n="s1.1;p53.61">Further strategies and plans should be adjusted according to the results form Period 8. </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">4. Learning Evaluation</head><p n="p54.61"><s n="s1.1;p54.61">During the time as a manager of the company, I have learned 3 key points, which needs to be followed in order to secure competitive advantages for the company and to keep customers. </s></p><p n="p55.61"><s n="s1.5;p55.61"><hi rend="underlined">Customer behavior</hi> - there is a need to understand and relate to customers, know what they want. </s><s n="s2.5;p55.61">This enables the company to quickly adjust the production levels and product specifications according to current customers' needs. </s><s n="s3.5;p55.61">This can be done by reading through market researches, such as customers' surveys and panels, the stores that they visit, their opinions on the products and how can they be improved. </s><s n="s4.5;p55.61">Reading through reports on performances of the company, or brand results and comparing the figures also helps to understand customers and their behavior. </s><s n="s5.5;p55.61">As the pricing strategy of the company has been the demand - based pricing, the demand of customers needs to be known well to adjust the price levels. </s></p><p n="p56.61"><s n="s1.2;p56.61">There is also a need to conduct frequent <hi rend="underlined">Market research studies</hi>, which help to understand the economy, show the estimated market conditions, customers' behavior and most importantly they show the performances of competitors and their product ranges, thus the firm can decide on how to respond to their actions. </s><s n="s2.2;p56.61">An example would be when the company was launching Vodites, the market had to be thoughtfully researched and studies were used to decide how to brace the entrance for its competitors. </s></p><p n="p57.61"><s n="s1.3;p57.61"><hi rend="underlined">Segmentation</hi> - the market needs to be divided into segments, as customers have different requirements, thus specific groups of customers should be targeted differently. </s><s n="s2.3;p57.61">When a product is launched, it is very important to have the potential customers segmented to know for which group of customers the product would be most suitable for. </s><s n="s3.3;p57.61">The competitive advantage is gained when right customers are offered suitable products at the right time. </s></p><p n="p58.61"><s n="s1.1;p58.61">The segmentation and positioning strategy is also used in deciding which market segments will be </s></p><p n="p59.61"><s n="s1.1;p59.61">targeted and how products will be positioned. </s></p><p n="p60.61"><s n="s1.3;p60.61">Apart from this, there are other points which are necessary for keeping the efficient marketing, such as the marketing mix strategy, the day-to-day operational marketing decisions such as pricing, production, communication and distribution. </s><s n="s2.3;p60.61">The team also needs to establish product position and fortify it by encouraging brand loyalty. </s><s n="s3.3;p60.61">As profits increase, there will be competitors entering the market, thus need to be first in selected market segments and stop the way for competitors. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">5. Conclusion</head><p n="p61.61"><s n="s1.3;p61.61">The company situation was explained in the report, and there has been a suggestion for the marketing strategy for the next 3 periods. </s><s n="s2.3;p61.61">However, the proposed strategy is based on assumptions that there are no external factors affecting the market, as the stability of the economy, or sudden change in taste of customers, could not be anticipated. </s><s n="s3.3;p61.61">Thus the strategy has to be re- examined prior to each period and made suitable for that particular period. </s></p></div1></body><back><div1 type="bibliography"><head rend="bold">BIBLIOGRAPHY</head><p>Dibb,S., Simkin,L., PrideW.M., Ferell,O.C. (2005) <hi rend="italic">Marketing Concepts and Strategies</hi>. 5th edition, Houghton Mifflin</p><p>Larreche, J., Gatignon, H., Triolet, R. (2003) <hi rend="italic">Markstrat Online Student Handbook</hi>. 1st edition. StratX International </p><p>McCArthy, J.,.Perreault W.D. (1990) <hi rend="italic">Basic Marketing: a managerial apporach</hi></p><p>10th edition </p></div1><div1 type="appendix"><head>APPENDICES</head><p/></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
