<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_0237d" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Assignment Number 1</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">deleted: header: module name and number; footer: student number, page numbers</note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">original included floppy disk</note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">Evaluated as candidate compound assignment. Assigned to S4: set of tasks/questions/exercises: non-compound</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">2</p><p n="date">2005-12</p><p n="module title">Computing and Information Systems</p><p n="module code">IB1070</p><p n="genre family">Exercise</p><p n="discipline">Business</p><p n="disciplinary group">SS</p><p n="grade">M</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">1071</p><p n="number of s-units">49</p><p n="number of p">28</p><p n="number of tables">0</p><p n="number of figures">0</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">0</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">0</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">21.9</p><p n="average s-units per p">1.8</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">complex but non-compound assignment (see notesStmt for details)</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">f</p><p n="year of birth">1985</p><p n="first language">Czech</p><p n="education">UK2</p><p n="course">Business</p><p n="student ID">0237</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><titlePart rend="bold">COMPUTING AND INFORMATION SYSTEMS (IB1070)</titlePart><docTitle><titlePart>ASSIGNMENT NUMBER 1 SPREADSHEETS 2005 - 2006</titlePart></docTitle><titlePart>Student I.D.: <name type="student ID"/></titlePart></titlePage><div1 type="toc" n="2"><head>Contents:</head><p/></div1></front><body><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined">Task 3</head><div2><head rend="bold">Performance of CNR INTERNATIONAL (U.K.) INVESTMENTS LIMITED</head><p n="p1.28"><s n="s1.3;p1.28">The turnover of the company has been increasing consistently from £234,885 in 2001 to £584,554 in 2004 by in average £166,000 p.a. </s><s n="s2.3;p1.28">Although the falling turnover between 2000 and 2001, the profit has increased during that time, after that it has decreased in 2002. </s><s n="s3.3;p1.28">Between 2002 to 2004 the profit has been increasing from £67,112 in 2002 to £204,809 in 2004. </s></p><p n="p2.28"><s n="s1.2;p2.28">The company is ranked 7th in turnover and 5 <hi rend="sup">th</hi> in profit among its peers. </s><s rend="sup" n="s2.2;p2.28">1 </s></p><p n="p3.28"><s n="s1.3;p3.28">The ROCE shows the returns that a company is realizing from its capital. </s><s n="s2.3;p3.28">Calculated as profit before interest and tax divided by the Capital Employed. </s><s n="s3.3;p3.28">The ROCE of the company is ranked 1st among its peers at 214% which means that the company has twice more profit than capital employed. </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined">Task 5</head><div2><head rend="bold">Performance of the Peer Group</head><p n="p4.28"><s n="s1.2;p4.28">Out of 21 companies in the Peer group, 12 have been successful with profits over £100,000 in 2004 <hi rend="sup">1</hi> , while GAZ DE FRANCE ESS (UK) LTD was the only company who made a loss. </s><s n="s2.2;p4.28">The highest profit was achieved by BG INTERNATIONAL LIMITED with £629,246, which is approximately 3 times more than our company. </s></p><p n="p5.28"><s n="s1.3;p5.28">In terms of turnover, TALISMAN ENERGY (UK) LIMITED was the only one who achieved over £1 million of sales, which is nearly twice of our company. </s><s n="s2.3;p5.28">Most of companies with the exception of few have gained a turnover of over £200,000. </s><s n="s3.3;p5.28">The lowest turnover was reported by BP EXPLORATION (CASPIAN SEA) LIMITED with £149,944. </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined">Task 6</head><div2><head rend="bold">Worksheet Functions and Their Use</head><p n="p6.28"><s n="s1.1;p6.28">In the worksheet 'Payments' the functions employed are <hi rend="bold">=SUM, =VLOOKUP, =AVERAGE</hi> and <hi rend="bold">IF statements</hi>. </s></p><p n="p7.28"><s n="s1.2;p7.28">VLOOKUP looks in the first column of an array and moves across the row to return the value of a cell. </s><s n="s2.2;p7.28">VLOOKUP was used to calculate the commission for each salesperson. </s></p><p n="p8.28"><s n="s1.1;p8.28">=SUM adds all the numbers in a range of cells. =SUM was used to total the commission and bonus and the number of quarters when salespeople exceeded the quaterly target. </s></p><p n="p9.28"><s n="s1.2;p9.28">=AVERAGE counts the arithmetic mean of all the arguments. </s><s n="s2.2;p9.28">It was used to calculate the Quarterly Average. </s></p><p n="p10.28"><s n="s1.3;p10.28">IF statements return one value if a condition specified is true and a different value if it is false. </s><s n="s2.3;p10.28">IF is used to conduct conditional tests on values and formulas. </s><s n="s3.3;p10.28">IF was used to calculate the bonus for exceeding the target figure and then for total bonus value given to each salesperson. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">Sales and Earnings of Salespeople and Commission and Bonus Schemes</head><p n="p11.28"><s n="s1.1;p11.28">The "Percentage Share By Each Salesperson Of Total Sales chart shows that all workers have received a close percentage of share between 6% - 7%, while the actual figures in Payments show that the highest amount was achieved by Turner. </s></p><p n="p12.28"><s n="s1.3;p12.28">Bonus and commission are calculated quarterly based on percentage of sales by each salesperson. </s><s n="s2.3;p12.28">Although the similar sales amount, the percentage share by each salesperson of the Total Commission and Bonus varies greatly, with the majority of workers receiving around 9% - 10%, and largest amount gained by Bewley (11%). </s><s n="s3.3;p12.28">Only Evans received 1% out of total and Kowolski, Shah and Tsiolkovski 2% each. </s></p><p n="p13.28"><s n="s1.3;p13.28">The total bonus and commission rewarded to each salesperson does not correspond to their annual sales performance. </s><s n="s2.3;p13.28">This is due to rewards being calculated quarterly, not annually. </s><s n="s3.3;p13.28">Thus the scheme does not seem to be equitable. </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined">Task 7</head><div2><head rend="bold">Performance of the three sales groups 2</head><p n="p14.28"><s n="s1.1;p14.28">Group A consists of 3 salespeople <hi rend="sup">2</hi> , Group B of 8 and Group C of 4. </s></p><p n="p15.28"><s n="s1.2;p15.28">In Quarter 1, Group A had the highest average sales for each salesperson and Group B had the lowest. </s><s n="s2.2;p15.28">The total sales of each group corresponds to the number of salespeople there, thus Group B had the highest total, followed by Group C, then Group A. </s></p><p n="p16.28"><s n="s1.2;p16.28">In Quarter 2, Group A dropped to the last place in terms of the average, while Group B´s average has came best. </s><s n="s2.2;p16.28">The order of groups in terms of total sales remains as in the first quarter, with groups B and C doing slightly better. </s></p><p n="p17.28"><s n="s1.1;p17.28">In Quarter 3, Group A has came back to the first place in terms of average, while in Quarter 4 it is again Group B. </s></p><p n="p18.28"><s n="s1.1;p18.28">The Total Sales in Quarter 3 and 4 remain similar to first 2 quarters. </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined">Task 8</head><div2><head><hi rend="bold">The Impact of Scenario Changes on Company´s Personnel Costs</hi> <hi rend="bold">and The Impact of Target Changes on Salespeople Bonuses</hi></head><p n="p19.28"><s n="s1.1;p19.28">The amount the company has to pay to their employees in terms of commission and bonus depends on their predetermined sales target and the bonus and commission rate. </s></p><p n="p20.28"><s n="s1.1;p20.28">Target changes affect the employees as well as the profitability of the company in terms of bonus, while the commission does not change as it does not depend on the sales target. </s></p><p n="p21.28"><s n="s1.1;p21.28">If the target is increased, in this case to 115% of the original target, some salespeople may receive less bonus or none at all, whereas a company may save some personnel cost. </s></p><p n="p22.28"><s n="s1.2;p22.28">In the Scenario when the target is increased from £425,000 to £489,000, only 3 salespeople have kept the same level of bonus as the amount of their sales was already above the new target, while the bonus for Frances and Beechwood decreased to a half, and the rest, having usually a bonus of around £8,000 - £9,000 there was no bonus at all. </s><s n="s2.2;p22.28">Thus in this scenario, the company would save approx. £88,000 on personnel cost. </s></p><p n="p23.28"><s n="s1.1;p23.28">If the target is decreased, workers can make less effort to achieve the goals, or even those who did not reach the original target may receive a bonus, but company may have to spend more on personnel cost. </s></p><p n="p24.28"><s n="s1.3;p24.28">A reduced target set by the company from £425,000 to £361,000 did not affect most of the salespeople. </s><s n="s2.3;p24.28">In one case the bonus doubled and other 4 salespeople who did not reach the original target and thus would not receive a bonus, would also benefit from this target. </s><s n="s3.3;p24.28">Thus in this scenario, the company would have to spend approx. £34,000 more. </s></p><p n="p25.28"><s rend="sup" n="s1.1;p25.28">___________________________________________________________________ </s></p><p n="p26.28"><s n="s1.1;p26.28"><hi rend="sup">1</hi> Comparison possible only in 2004 since the Peer report shows the performances of other </s></p><p n="p27.28"><s n="s1.1;p27.28">companies only for this year. </s></p><p n="p28.28"><s n="s1.1;p28.28"><hi rend="sup">2</hi> Frances belongs to group B in Qtr 1 - 4, but in the Payment Scheme he is under group A, thus in Qtr 1 - 4 it is assumed that he belongs to group B. </s></p></div2></div1></body><back/></text></TEI.2>
