<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_0243b" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Assignment 2: A Stylus Type Instrument</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">deleted: header: module and student number; footer: page numbers</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">2</p><p n="date">2005-03</p><p n="module title">Design and Measurement of Systems</p><p n="module code">ES21Q</p><p n="genre family">Design specification</p><p n="discipline">Engineering</p><p n="disciplinary group">PS</p><p n="grade">M</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">2709</p><p n="number of s-units">170</p><p n="number of p">79</p><p n="number of tables">0</p><p n="number of figures">2</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">24</p><p n="number of lists">1</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">4</p><p n="abstract present">abstract present</p><p n="average words per s-unit">15.9</p><p n="average s-units per p">2.2</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">m</p><p n="year of birth">1984</p><p n="first language">English</p><p n="education">UKA</p><p n="course">Engineering</p><p n="student ID">0243</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><titlePart rend="bold">University of <name type="university"/> School of Engineering</titlePart><docTitle><titlePart><hi rend="bold">Design of Measurement Systems Assignment 2</hi><hi rend="bold"> Option B - A Stylus Type Instrument</hi></titlePart></docTitle><titlePart><hi rend="bold">Student Number: <name type="student ID"/> Report Reference Code: ES21QA2</hi><hi rend="bold"> Affiliation: Year 2 Engineering</hi></titlePart></titlePage><div1 type="toc" n="1"><head rend="bold">Table of Contents</head><p/></div1></front><body><div1 type="abstract"><head rend="bold">Summary</head><p n="p1.79"><s n="s1.4;p1.79">This report outlines the design for a system that measures the surface texture of a given material sample. </s><s n="s2.4;p1.79">A stylus type device is used to run a minute tip across the surface and record the variations in vertical displacement in order to map out a profile of the surface features. </s><s n="s3.4;p1.79">A laser interferometer was chosen to measure the displacement, due to its extreme sensitivity. </s><s n="s4.4;p1.79">Specifications required the device to be able to record variations a small as 0.01μm, and other displacement sensors do not have the sensitivity to be considered suitable. </s></p><p n="p2.79"><s n="s1.3;p2.79">The laser interferometer uses the phenomenon of interference to cause patterns of dark and light fringes. </s><s n="s2.3;p2.79">The number of these fringes determines the displacement of the stylus tip. </s><s n="s3.3;p2.79">An optical reader is used to transfer the data via an analogue to digital converter to a computer which displays a profile of the surface and a calculation for the surface roughness. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Analysis of the Mechanical System</head><p n="p3.79"><s n="s1.6;p3.79">The stylus pick up system is shown in figure 1. </s><s n="s2.6;p3.79">It is made up of a sharp pointed stylus tip situated at the end of a pivoting rod. </s><s n="s3.6;p3.79">The stylus is usually a diamond that has been rounded or flattened at the tip. </s><s n="s4.6;p3.79">The radius of the tip is usually less than 10μm, a typical value being just 2μm. </s><s n="s5.6;p3.79">At the other end there is a sensor that measures the vertical displacement of the stylus. </s><s n="s6.6;p3.79">The stylus is moved over the surface being tested and the varying heights of the surface features are recorded. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0243b-pic.001"><head><hi rend="bold">Figure 1: Schematic Diagram of the Pick-up head of a stylus instrument</hi><ref target="BAWE_0243b-ftnote.001"/><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0243b-ftnote.001"><p n="pn1.1"> X Ping Liu. Lecture Notes "<hi rend="italic">Design of Measurement Systems</hi>" University of Warwick, School of Engineering.</p></note></head></figure><p n="p4.79"><s n="s1.1;p4.79">The ability of the stylus to remain in contact with the surface is the key to accurate measurement and is dependant on: </s></p><list type="bulleted"><item>The inertia of the pivoting system</item><item>The static stylus force on the surface</item><item>The horizontal speed of the stylus over the surface</item><item>The amplitude and wavelength of the features on the surface</item></list><p n="p5.79"><s n="s1.1;p5.79">Figure 2 shows a simple diagram of the pivoting stylus. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0243b-pic.002"><head><hi rend="bold">Figure 2: Schematic of a simple pivoting stylus</hi><ref target="BAWE_0243b-ftnote.002"/><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0243b-ftnote.002"><p n="pn1.1"> E Morrison. "<hi rend="italic">The Development of a Prototype High-speed Stylus Profilometer and its Application to Rapid 3D Surface Measurement</hi>". 1996, IOP Publishing Ltd.</p></note></head></figure><p n="p6.79"><s n="s1.1;p6.79">Considering the inertia: </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p7.79"><s n="s1.1;p7.79"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0243b-form.001"/> (A) </s></p><p n="p8.79"><s n="s1.3;p8.79">Where I is the moment of inertia of the system, z is the vertical position of the tip of the stylus, <hi rend="italic">l</hi> is the length if the stylus form the tip to the pivot, T <hi rend="sub">s</hi> is the net sum of the static torques acting about the stylus due to its own mass and any externally applied forces, and T <hi rend="sub">r</hi> is the torque due to the reaction of the stylus on the surface. </s><s n="s2.3;p8.79">It is obvious to see that when T <hi rend="sub">r</hi> becomes equal to zero, the tip of the stylus will have lost contact with the surface. </s><s n="s3.3;p8.79">If we now consider the stylus moving over a surface that varies in height sinusoidally, we can express the position of the tip by the following equation: </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p9.79"><s n="s1.1;p9.79"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0243b-form.002"/> (B)<ref target="BAWE_0243b-ftnote.003"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0243b-ftnote.003"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.3;pn1.1">Equations for the motion of the system taken from E Morrison. </s><s n="s2.3;pn1.1">"<hi rend="italic">The Development of a Prototype High-speed Stylus Profilometer and its Application to Rapid 3D Surface Measurement</hi>". </s><s n="s3.3;pn1.1">1996, IOP Publishing Ltd. </s></p></note><p n="p10.79"><s n="s1.2;p10.79">Where A is the amplitude of the sinusoidal surface and ω is the frequency of oscillation of the tip as it is moved across the surface. </s><s n="s2.2;p10.79">The frequency is dependant on the spatial wavelength (λ) of the sinusoidal surface and the horizontal speed (ν): </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p11.79"><s n="s1.1;p11.79"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0243b-form.003"/> (C) </s></p><p n="p12.79"><s n="s1.1;p12.79">Combining equations B and C into equation A gives us an expression for the conditions that result in the tip lifting of the ground: </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p13.79"><s n="s1.1;p13.79"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0243b-form.004"/> (D) </s></p><p n="p14.79"><s n="s1.5;p14.79">This equation shows that there is a maximum speed at which the stylus can be traversed across the surface while keeping the tip in contact with the surface. </s><s n="s2.5;p14.79">To combat the problem we do two things. </s><s n="s3.5;p14.79">Firstly we keep the horizontal movement at a sensible speed and secondly we use a spring to provide a static torque to the stylus. </s><s n="s4.5;p14.79">A typical value for the stiffness of the spring is 35 Nm <hi rend="sup">-1</hi>. </s><s n="s5.5;p14.79">We would want to keep the stiffness to a minimum so as to avoid damaging the surface that we are measuring. </s></p><p n="p15.79"><s n="s1.2;p15.79">The rod that holds the stylus tip at one end and the displacement sensor at the other has the pivot at its centre. </s><s n="s2.2;p15.79">This means that the displacement measured at the sensor end will be the same as the vertical displacement of the tip. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Selection Criterion</head><p n="p16.79"><s n="s1.4;p16.79">The selection of the sensing device depends on the minimum change in displacement that it must be able to detect. </s><s n="s2.4;p16.79">We must be careful to find a reasonable resonant frequency for the pick-mechanism. </s><s n="s3.4;p16.79">We are given that the displacement sensor must be able to sense a change in height of 0.01μm or less. </s><s n="s4.4;p16.79">The radius of the stylus tip is 2μm. </s></p><p n="p17.79"><s n="s1.2;p17.79">The smallest measurable sinusoidal surface can be taken as 0.01μm (although this is not actually the smallest measurable change). </s><s n="s2.2;p17.79">In order to work out the wavelength and hence the corresponding frequency let us consider figure 3, which shows the tip on a sinusoidal surface with the same radius of curvature. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0243b-fig.001"><head rend="bold">Figure 3: Stylus tip on a sinusoidal surface</head></figure><p n="p18.79"><s n="s1.1;p18.79">We can use Pythagoras' theorem and the numbers shown in the diagram to calculate one half of the wavelength and therefore one whole wavelength: </s></p><p n="p19.79"><s n="s1.1;p19.79"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0243b-form.005"/> </s></p><p n="p20.79"><s n="s1.1;p20.79"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0243b-form.006"/> </s></p><p n="p21.79"><s n="s1.1;p21.79"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0243b-form.007"/> </s></p><p n="p22.79"><s n="s1.1;p22.79"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0243b-form.008"/> </s></p><p n="p23.79"><s n="s1.1;p23.79"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0243b-form.009"/> </s></p><p n="p24.79"><s n="s1.1;p24.79"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0243b-form.010"/> </s></p><p n="p25.79"><s n="s1.1;p25.79">We can work out the frequency using equation C and taking the horizontal speed as 0.0005ms <hi rend="sup">-1</hi> (which is a typical speed for this kind of instrument): </s></p><p n="p26.79"><s n="s1.1;p26.79"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0243b-form.011"/> </s></p><p n="p27.79"><s n="s1.1;p27.79"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0243b-form.012"/> </s></p><p n="p28.79"><s n="s1.1;p28.79"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0243b-form.013"/> </s></p><p n="p29.79"><s n="s1.1;p29.79">A suitable resonant frequency for the system is therefore about 7900 rads <hi rend="sup">-1</hi>. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Selection of the Sensing Device</head><p n="p30.79"><s n="s1.6;p30.79">The key feature of the sensing device we are looking for is its sensitivity. </s><s n="s2.6;p30.79">The device must be able to measure a change in displacement of 0.01μm. </s><s n="s3.6;p30.79">Inductive and capacitive devices are not suitable because neither if these have the sensitivity required. </s><s n="s4.6;p30.79">A typical range for these displacement sensors is ±0.25mm to ±25cm, which is several orders of magnitude away from what is needed. </s><s n="s5.6;p30.79">Another drawback from the inductive sensors such as LVDT's are their inertia. </s><s n="s6.6;p30.79">The magnetic core has too much momentum to allow quick changes of direction in response to the minute changes in displacement that need to be measured. </s></p><p n="p31.79"><s n="s1.5;p31.79">Optical encoders are binary type devices. </s><s n="s2.5;p31.79">The output is in digital form and expressed as either "on" or "off". </s><s n="s3.5;p31.79">Ideally we are looking for a sensor that will give a continuous reading as the stylus moves horizontally across the surface. </s><s n="s4.5;p31.79">A digital device is not really suitable for this purpose. </s><s n="s5.5;p31.79">We would prefer a device that gives a continuous output that can be transferred to a computer via an analogue to digital converter for data presentation. </s></p><p n="p32.79"><s n="s1.1;p32.79">The obvious choice for the displacement sensor is a laser interferometer because it is the most accurate of the devices available. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Laser Interferometers</head><p n="p33.79"><s n="s1.1;p33.79">These are very precise measuring devices that rely on the phenomenon of interference to provide a measure of displacement. </s></p><p n="p34.79"><s n="s1.1;p34.79">Figure 4 shows the layout of an interferometer whose operation is described below. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0243b-pic.003"><head><hi rend="bold">Figure 4: Layout of a laser interferometer</hi><ref target="BAWE_0243b-ftnote.004"/><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0243b-ftnote.004"><p n="pn1.1"> Diagram taken from <seg type="URL" n="http://hyperphysics.phy-astr.gsu.edu/hbase/phyopt/michel.html"/> accessed 26/04/05.</p></note></head></figure><p n="p35.79"><s n="s1.4;p35.79">A beam of monochromatic light from a laser, of single frequency ω and corresponding wavelength λ, are passed through a beam splitter to give two beams of equal amplitude a. </s><s n="s2.4;p35.79">One beam travels along a path of length x <hi rend="sub">1</hi> to a fixed mirror. </s><s n="s3.4;p35.79">The other travels a distance of x <hi rend="sub">2</hi> to a moveable mirror. </s><s n="s4.4;p35.79">Both beams are reflected back off their respective mirrors to a detector. </s></p><p n="p36.79"><s n="s1.1;p36.79">On reaching the detector the beams can be described by the following wave equations: </s></p><p n="p37.79"><s n="s1.1;p37.79"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0243b-form.014"/> </s></p><p n="p38.79"><s n="s1.1;p38.79"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0243b-form.015"/><ref target="BAWE_0243b-ftnote.005"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0243b-ftnote.005"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Equation taken from X Ping Liu. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">Lecture Notes "<hi rend="italic">Design of Measurement Systems</hi>" University of Warwick, School of Engineering. </s></p></note><p n="p39.79"><s n="s1.1;p39.79">The resultant light beam incident on the detector is given by: </s></p><p n="p40.79"><s n="s1.1;p40.79"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0243b-form.016"/> </s></p><p n="p41.79"><s n="s1.1;p41.79"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0243b-form.017"/> </s></p><p n="p42.79"><s n="s1.1;p42.79"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0243b-form.018"/>. </s></p><p n="p43.79"><s n="s1.1;p43.79">This describes a wave with amplitude a <hi rend="sub">R</hi>: </s></p><p n="p44.79"><s n="s1.1;p44.79"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0243b-form.019"/> </s></p><p n="p45.79"><s n="s1.1;p45.79">where <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0243b-form.020"/> </s></p><p n="p46.79"><s n="s1.1;p46.79">(which is the optical path difference) </s></p><p n="p47.79"><s n="s1.1;p47.79">The intensity I <hi rend="sub">R</hi> is given by: </s></p><p n="p48.79"><s n="s1.1;p48.79"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0243b-form.021"/>. </s></p><p n="p49.79"><s n="s1.2;p49.79">The intensity is therefore a function of the optical path difference. </s><s n="s2.2;p49.79">The distance that the movable mirror moves though is related to the number of fringes that are detected. </s></p><p n="p50.79"><s n="s1.3;p50.79">Maxima occur when x = 0, λ, 2λ, 3λ etc. </s><s n="s2.3;p50.79">In these cases the two beams are interfering constructively because they are in phase. </s><s n="s3.3;p50.79">A bright fringe is therefore observed. </s></p><p n="p51.79"><s n="s1.3;p51.79">Minima occur when x= λ/2, 3λ/2, 5λ/2 etc. </s><s n="s2.3;p51.79">Here they interfere destructively because they are 180° (or π radians) out of phase. </s><s n="s3.3;p51.79">A dark fringe is therefore observed. </s></p><p n="p52.79"><s n="s1.1;p52.79">The number of light-dark fringe cycles on the detector can be used to calculate the distanced moved by the mirror: </s></p><p n="p53.79"><s n="s1.1;p53.79"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0243b-form.022"/><ref target="BAWE_0243b-ftnote.006"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0243b-ftnote.006"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">From <seg type="URL" n="http://hyperphysics.phy-astr.gsu.edu/hbase/phyopt/michel.html"/> accessed 26/04/05. </s></p></note><p n="p54.79"><s n="s1.1;p54.79">Where d is the distance the mirror had travelled, <hi rend="italic">m</hi> is the number of light-dark fringe cycles and λ is the wavelength. </s></p><p n="p55.79"><s n="s1.3;p55.79">Figure 4 shows that there is a second piece of glass between the beam splitter and the fixed mirror. </s><s n="s2.3;p55.79">This is called a compensation plate. </s><s n="s3.3;p55.79">It is made of the same material and thickness as the fixed mirror and is there so that the beams on both arms pass through the same thickness of glass. </s></p><p n="p56.79"><s n="s1.1;p56.79">The beam splitter is a half silvered mirror that allows half of the light though and reflects the other half. </s></p><p n="p57.79"><s n="s1.5;p57.79">The interferometer will be placed into the stylus system in such a way so that the moveable mirror sits at the opposite end to the tip and facing upwards. </s><s n="s2.5;p57.79">The detector will have an optical reader so that the output in the form of light and dark fringes can be processed and transferred to a computer. </s><s n="s3.5;p57.79">The data will be displayed in the form of a graph of vertical displacement from a starting datum against the horizontal distance travelled by the stylus. </s><s n="s4.5;p57.79">The output will be not need to be amplified in the way that it would if an inductance sensor had been used for example, since the optical reader can distinguish the fringes that are produced by the interferometer and transmit them to the computer to be processed. </s><s n="s5.5;p57.79">The signal will be amplified after it has been read by by the optical reader. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Block Diagram of the System</head><p n="p58.79"><s n="s1.1;p58.79">Below is a block diagram of the stylus measuring system. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0243b-fig.002"/><p n="p59.79"><s n="s1.4;p59.79">The stylus is the lever arm that is in contact with the surface. </s><s n="s2.4;p59.79">The tip runs along the surface and moves up and down. </s><s n="s3.4;p59.79">The arm is pivoted, so that the other end also moves up and down. </s><s n="s4.4;p59.79">The displacement is measured at the opposite and to the tip. </s></p><p n="p60.79"><s n="s1.3;p60.79">The laser interferometer is the measuring device that measures the displacement of the stylus. </s><s n="s2.3;p60.79">Its function is described in the section above (Laser Interferometers). </s><s n="s3.3;p60.79">It can measure minute changes in displacement, as small as 0.01μm. </s></p><p n="p61.79"><s n="s1.4;p61.79">The data processing comes in two sections. </s><s n="s2.4;p61.79">The optical reader can record the fringe pattern and allows it to be transferred via and analogue to digital (A/D) converter to the computer for display. </s><s n="s3.4;p61.79">The signal will be amplified at this point. </s><s n="s4.4;p61.79">A dynamic range of 10 <hi rend="sup">5</hi> is required therefore the A/D converter will require 17 bits (the 17 <hi rend="sup">th</hi> power of 2 is the first whole number that satisfies the bit equation 2 <hi rend="sup">N</hi> > 10 <hi rend="sup">5</hi>, where N is the number of bits). </s></p><p n="p62.79"><s n="s1.4;p62.79">The computer provides the data display. </s><s n="s2.4;p62.79">It is represented graphically. </s><s n="s3.4;p62.79">The signal that it receives tells it how many light-dark fringe cycles are detected at any given horizontal displacement. </s><s n="s4.4;p62.79">The computer converts this information into a displacement using the equation: </s></p><p n="p63.79"><s n="s1.1;p63.79"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0243b-form.023"/>. </s></p><p n="p64.79"><s n="s1.4;p64.79">The computer will have a sample rate (several thousand per second). </s><s n="s2.4;p64.79">This allows a graph of vertical displacement against horizontal displacement to be plotted. </s><s n="s3.4;p64.79">As well as displaying a profile of the surface the computer can also calculate the surface roughness. </s><s n="s4.4;p64.79">This is defined as the centre-line average R <hi rend="sub">a</hi> and can be calculated by the following equation: </s></p><p n="p65.79"><s n="s1.1;p65.79"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0243b-form.024"/><ref target="BAWE_0243b-ftnote.007"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0243b-ftnote.007"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Equation taken from X Ping Liu. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">Lecture Notes "<hi rend="italic">Design of Measurement Systems</hi>" University of Warwick, School of Engineering. </s></p></note><p n="p66.79"><s n="s1.1;p66.79">where y(x) is the surface profile relative to the mean value, sampled by a set of N points over the length L. </s></p><p n="p67.79"><s n="s1.4;p67.79">The primary function of the computer is to store and display the data but it could also be used to control the movement of the stylus. </s><s n="s2.4;p67.79">The stylus would be automatically controlled anyway but using the computer would make the system more integrated. </s><s n="s3.4;p67.79">The computer would have control of both the position of the stylus and the sampling rate. </s><s n="s4.4;p67.79">This would be a very accurate way to keep the speed and applied pressure of the stylus on the surface constant. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Measurement Limitations</head><p n="p68.79"><s n="s1.5;p68.79">The stylus system has several limitations. </s><s n="s2.5;p68.79">The tip can only cover depressions where the radius of curvature is greater than that of the tip. </s><s n="s3.5;p68.79">In places where there is a depression in the surface which has a radius of curvature smaller than that of the tip, the tip will not be able to reach the bottom of the depression. </s><s n="s4.5;p68.79">This means that the correct depth will not be measured. </s><s n="s5.5;p68.79">This is a major limitation and for this reason, the tip is made to be as small as possible (just a couple of microns in radius). </s></p><p n="p69.79"><s n="s1.8;p69.79">There are also limitations to the horizontal motion of the stylus. </s><s n="s2.8;p69.79">It must not move above a critical speed. </s><s n="s3.8;p69.79">If it travels across the surface too fast the tip may come of the surface immediately after it as reached a peak. </s><s n="s4.8;p69.79">This will result in an inaccurate recording of the surface features. </s><s n="s5.8;p69.79">As mentioned already, a spring is used to provide a static torque so that the tip is pushed into the surface. </s><s n="s6.8;p69.79">If the tip moves too fast over the surface there is also the possibility of it causing damage to the surface features. </s><s n="s7.8;p69.79">This must be avoided at all costs. </s><s n="s8.8;p69.79">There is little point in using measurements from a sample that has been damaged in the process. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Design Improvements</head><p n="p70.79"><s n="s1.4;p70.79">Using a laser interferometer as the displacement sensor has many advantages in that it is very accurate. </s><s n="s2.4;p70.79">However, this accuracy is subject to the ambient conditions being carefully controlled. </s><s n="s3.4;p70.79">The wavelength of a laser beam in air is affected by the air pressure, temperature and humidity. </s><s n="s4.4;p70.79">These three factors need to be kept constant. </s></p><p n="p71.79"><s n="s1.1;p71.79">The sampling rate that the computer uses to display the data could be increased thus giving a more continuous representation of the data. </s></p><p n="p72.79"><s n="s1.3;p72.79">Similarly the frequency of the beam from the laser could be increased thus causing more interference patterns that can be detected. </s><s n="s2.3;p72.79">This is effectively increasing the resolution of the system. </s><s n="s3.3;p72.79">More light-dark cycles means that there is more raw data that can be processed. </s></p><p n="p73.79"><s n="s1.2;p73.79">A further improvement but much more complicated would be to use more than one interferometer and double pass the beams to compensate for misalignment. </s><s n="s2.2;p73.79">Making the mirror and prism system as small as possible would also help to compensate for misalignment. </s></p><p n="p74.79"><s n="s1.5;p74.79">It was mentioned earlier that the radius of the stylus tip is a limitation on the vertical measurement. </s><s n="s2.5;p74.79">The tip should be made as small as is possible to give it every chance of measuring even the narrowest of depressions. </s><s n="s3.5;p74.79">A more radical step would be to do away with the stylus tip altogether and use a laser beam directed at the surface. </s><s n="s4.5;p74.79">The beam would have to be very narrow to compensate for the roughness that would cause a scattering of the light. </s><s n="s5.5;p74.79">It would be a similar system to that used to measure the ocean floor but obviously on a much smaller scale. </s></p><p n="p75.79"><s n="s1.4;p75.79">The translational speed of the stylus is another area that could be improved upon. </s><s n="s2.4;p75.79">A faster translation across the surface would allow the measurements to be taken more quickly. </s><s n="s3.4;p75.79">However a higher data sampling rate would be required if the spatial resolution is to be maintained. </s><s n="s4.4;p75.79">It is therefore important that the displacement sensor is able to cope with the increased rate of data acquisition. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Conclusion</head><p n="p76.79"><s n="s1.2;p76.79">The stylus system that has been designed uses a laser interferometer as the displacement sensor. </s><s n="s2.2;p76.79">This device is able to measure the smallest of changes in displacement and was therefore deemed to be the most suitable of the available sensors. </s></p><p n="p77.79"><s n="s1.3;p77.79">The system allows for the optical output of the interferometer to be amplified and converted into digital output via an optical reader and an A/D converter. </s><s n="s2.3;p77.79">The data is processed to give an output on a computer in the form of a surface profile. </s><s n="s3.3;p77.79">This profile can be used to provide a calculation for surface roughness. </s></p><p n="p78.79"><s n="s1.3;p78.79">The interferometer is a very precise piece of equipment that requires careful control of the ambient conditions. </s><s n="s2.3;p78.79">There are limitations to both the accuracy of the vertical displacement reading due to the size of stylus tip and the frequency of the laser beam. </s><s n="s3.3;p78.79">The speed of measurement is limited due to the need for care when traversing across the surface so as not to damage the sample or cause the stylus tip to leave the surface. </s></p><p n="p79.79"><s n="s1.1;p79.79">Improvements to the system are based on increasing the resolution to give a greater sampling rate and increasing the accuracy of the interferometer by taking steps to correct misalignment. </s></p></div1></body><back><div1 type="bibliography"><head rend="bold">Bibliography</head><p>"<hi rend="italic">Handbook of Industrial Metrology</hi>". John W Greve Ed. 1967, Prentice Hall.</p><p>E Morrison. "<hi rend="italic">The Development of a Prototype High-speed Stylus Profilometer and its Application to Rapid 3D Surface Measurement</hi>". 1996, IOP Publishing Ltd.</p><p>J Fraden. "<hi rend="italic">AIP Handbook of Modern Sensors. Physics Designs and Applications</hi>". 1993, American Institute of Physics.</p><p>X Ping Liu. Lecture Notes "<hi rend="italic">Design of Measurement Systems</hi>" University of <name type="university"/>, School of Engineering.</p><p>R Nave <seg type="URL" n="http://hyperphysics.phy-astr.gsu.edu/hbase/phyopt/michel.html"/></p></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
