<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_0243a" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Assignment 1: Instrumentation</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">deleted: footer: student and page numbers</note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">appendix: data tables</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">2</p><p n="date">2005-03</p><p n="module title">Design and Measurement of Systems</p><p n="module code">ES21Q</p><p n="genre family">Methodology recount</p><p n="discipline">Engineering</p><p n="disciplinary group">PS</p><p n="grade">D</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">2540</p><p n="number of s-units">169</p><p n="number of p">91</p><p n="number of tables">0</p><p n="number of figures">2</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">41</p><p n="number of lists">1</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">0</p><p n="abstract present">abstract present</p><p n="average words per s-unit">15.0</p><p n="average s-units per p">1.9</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">m</p><p n="year of birth">1984</p><p n="first language">English</p><p n="education">UKA</p><p n="course">Engineering</p><p n="student ID">0243</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><titlePart rend="bold">University of <name type="university"/> School of Engineering</titlePart><docTitle><titlePart rend="bold">Design and Measurement of Systems Assignment 1: Instrumentation</titlePart></docTitle><titlePart rend="bold">By Student Number: <name type="student ID"/></titlePart><titlePart rend="bold">Report Reference Code: ES21QA1 Affiliation: Year 2 Engineering</titlePart></titlePage><div1 type="toc" n="1"><head rend="bold">Table of Contents</head><p/></div1></front><body><div1 type="abstract"><head rend="bold">Summary</head><p n="p1.91"><s n="s1.3;p1.91">The purpose of this assignment was to design and construct a Wheatstone Deflection Bridge and amplifier system in order to measure and analyse the change in output under loading. </s><s n="s2.3;p1.91">The first stage involved applying a force to the end of the cantilever beam by stacking washers onto the end. </s><s n="s3.3;p1.91">This enabled the sensitivity of the system to be calculated. </s></p><p n="p2.91"><s n="s1.2;p2.91">The system was also analysed using a computer software package to record the output. </s><s n="s2.2;p2.91">It was possible to determine the resonant frequency of the system after it was disturbed by analysing a graph of output voltage against time. </s></p><p n="p3.91"><s n="s1.1;p3.91">The system had a low pass filter added in order to reduce the noise that would have reduced the accuracy of all the readings. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">1. Introduction</head><p n="p4.91"><s n="s1.5;p4.91">The investigation involved the use a cantilever beam with strain gauges attached to the top and bottom at the same distance along the beam. </s><s n="s2.5;p4.91">The application of force at the end of the beam causes a variation in the resistance in the strain gauges. </s><s n="s3.5;p4.91">This variation can be measured by analysing the output voltage produced by the system, called a Wheatstone Deflection Bridge. </s><s n="s4.5;p4.91">The Voltage must be amplified to a suitable level since the output of the bridge is in the order of millivolts. </s><s n="s5.5;p4.91">The Wheatstone Deflection Bridge set up is shown in Figure 1. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0243a-pic.001"><head rend="bold">Figure 1: Wheatstone Deflection Bridge</head></figure><p n="p5.91"><s n="s1.4;p5.91">The signal must be amplified because the output is very small. </s><s n="s2.4;p5.91">The amplified signal can be displayed either by an oscilloscope or digital voltmeter. </s><s n="s3.4;p5.91">The process is illustrated as a flow diagram in figure 2. </s><s n="s4.4;p5.91">The method section outlines how the system was used to measure the strain variation in the beam caused by loading the end of the beam with washers. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0243a-pic.002"><head rend="bold">Figure 2: Flow diagram for the investigation</head></figure><p n="p6.91"><s n="s1.6;p6.91">As well as the analysis using the digital voltmeter, a computer package was used to record the change in output voltage with time. </s><s n="s2.6;p6.91">The software package is called Labview. </s><s n="s3.6;p6.91">The bridge and amplifier system used in the first part of the investigation can be plugged into a computer and the system analysed by the program. </s><s n="s4.6;p6.91">The program allows the user to record the output voltage for a given length of time at any chosen sample rate. </s><s n="s5.6;p6.91">For example; 2000 samples to be collected at a sample rate of 1000 samples per second will cause the program to record the system for 2 seconds and collect enough sample to plot a very accurate graph of output voltage against time. </s><s n="s6.6;p6.91">The results can be used to calculate the resonant frequency of the system when disturbed and also the length of time it takes to stabilise. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">2. Theory and Calculation</head><p n="p7.91"><s n="s1.1;p7.91">Figure 3 shows the Wheatstone bridge setup with dimensions for the beam and the distance from the built-in end to the strain gauges. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0243a-pic.003"><head rend="bold">Figure 3: Wheatstone Deflection Bridge Dimensions</head></figure><p n="p8.91"><s n="s1.2;p8.91">The beam is made of steel which has a modulus of elasticity of 210 GPa. </s><s n="s2.2;p8.91">The Strain is given by the following equation: </s></p><p n="p9.91"><s n="s1.1;p9.91"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0243a-form.001"/>, </s></p><p n="p10.91"><s n="s1.3;p10.91">where <hi rend="italic">x</hi> is the distance from the built in end to the strain gauges, w is the width of the beam, <hi rend="italic">t</hi> is the thickness, <hi rend="italic">l</hi> is the length, <hi rend="italic">E</hi> is the modulus of elasticity of the beam material and <hi rend="italic">F</hi> is the force applied at the end of the beam. </s><s n="s2.3;p10.91">The dimensions measure with a standard ruler. </s><s n="s3.3;p10.91">Using the dimensions from Figure 3 the equation becomes: </s></p><p n="p11.91"><s n="s1.1;p11.91"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0243a-form.002"/> </s></p><p n="p12.91"><s n="s1.1;p12.91"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0243a-form.003"/>. </s></p><p n="p13.91"><s n="s1.2;p13.91">This equation of <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0243a-form.004"/> in terms of the force suggests that the system is not very sensitive to changes in force because the coefficient of force is very small. </s><s n="s2.2;p13.91">The thickness of the beam is a more influential factor because the strain varies inversely with the square of this dimension. </s></p><p n="p14.91"><s n="s1.1;p14.91">If we assume that the gauges are located at or near the beam support and have the maximum moment we can estimate the maximum loading force using the given values: E=210 GPa and <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0243a-form.005"/>. </s></p><p n="p15.91"><s n="s1.1;p15.91"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0243a-form.006"/> </s></p><p n="p16.91"><s n="s1.1;p16.91"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0243a-form.007"/> </s></p><p n="p17.91"><s n="s1.1;p17.91"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0243a-form.008"/>. </s></p><p n="p18.91"><s n="s1.1;p18.91">If we now combine this with the expression for strain in terms of force we can calculate the maximum force. </s></p><p n="p19.91"><s n="s1.1;p19.91"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0243a-form.009"/> </s></p><p n="p20.91"><s n="s1.1;p20.91"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0243a-form.010"/> </s></p><p n="p21.91"><s n="s1.1;p21.91"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0243a-form.011"/>. </s></p><p n="p22.91"><s n="s1.1;p22.91">In theory the system should be able to support a load of about 3 N which corresponds to an applied mass of about 0.3 Kg. </s></p><p n="p23.91"><s n="s1.4;p23.91">The bridge has a supply voltage of 9V from a battery. </s><s n="s2.4;p23.91">Balancing the bridge allows us to measure very small changes in output voltage. </s><s n="s3.4;p23.91">Figure 4 shows the circuit diagram for the system. </s><s n="s4.4;p23.91">R <hi rend="sub">1</hi> and R <hi rend="sub">2</hi> are the strain gauges. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0243a-fig.001"><head rend="bold">Figure 4: Circuit diagram for the Strain gauge set up</head></figure><p n="p24.91"><s n="s1.1;p24.91">The output voltage is equal to V <hi rend="sub">BD</hi> which is equal to the sum of the voltages across R <hi rend="sub">1</hi> and R <hi rend="sub">4</hi> (V <hi rend="sub">BA</hi> and V <hi rend="sub">DA</hi>). </s></p><p n="p25.91"><s n="s1.1;p25.91"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0243a-form.012"/> </s></p><p n="p26.91"><s n="s1.1;p26.91"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0243a-form.013"/> </s></p><p n="p27.91"><s n="s1.1;p27.91">Since <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0243a-form.014"/>. </s></p><p n="p28.91"><s n="s1.1;p28.91">The above equation can be rewritten in the form: </s></p><p n="p29.91"><s n="s1.1;p29.91"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0243a-form.015"/>. </s></p><p n="p30.91"><s n="s1.3;p30.91">To balance the bridge we need to set the output voltage to zero. </s><s n="s2.3;p30.91">For this to occur either the input voltage must be zero (which it clearly won't be) or the top section of the resistance fraction must equal zero. </s><s n="s3.3;p30.91">Thus for the bridge to be balanced: </s></p><p n="p31.91"><s n="s1.1;p31.91"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0243a-form.016"/>. </s></p><p n="p32.91"><s n="s1.2;p32.91">Since we are going to be measuring the output voltage of the system we need to relate this to the changing resistance of the strain gauges. </s><s n="s2.2;p32.91">If R <hi rend="sub">1</hi> and R <hi rend="sub">2</hi> represent the resistance of the two stain gauges then we can express the change in resistance when a force is applied to the beam as follows: </s></p><p n="p33.91"><s n="s1.1;p33.91"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0243a-form.017"/> </s></p><p n="p34.91"><s n="s1.1;p34.91"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0243a-form.018"/> </s></p><p n="p35.91"><s n="s1.2;p35.91">For the investigation the value of the resistors R <hi rend="sub">3</hi> and R <hi rend="sub">4</hi> are 1KΩ. </s><s n="s2.2;p35.91">If these two resistors have the same value then the conditions for balancing results in R <hi rend="sub">1</hi> and R <hi rend="sub">2</hi> also having the same value. </s></p><p n="p36.91"><s n="s1.1;p36.91">The change in output voltage can now be expressed as follows: </s></p><p n="p37.91"><s n="s1.1;p37.91"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0243a-form.019"/>. </s></p><p n="p38.91"><s n="s1.1;p38.91">Since as explained above the resistances are all the same; <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0243a-form.020"/>, we can express the change in output voltage as: </s></p><p n="p39.91"><s n="s1.1;p39.91"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0243a-form.021"/>. </s></p><p n="p40.91"><s n="s1.1;p40.91">If we substitute in the values for the resistance and the input voltage to the bridge we get an expression for the change in output voltage as: </s></p><p n="p41.91"><s n="s1.1;p41.91"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0243a-form.022"/> </s></p><p n="p42.91"><s n="s1.1;p42.91"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0243a-form.023"/>. </s></p><p n="p43.91"><s n="s1.3;p43.91">The amplifier that was chosen needed to have again between 100 and 1000, the closer to 1000 being the more favourable. </s><s n="s2.3;p43.91">The amplifier was a non-inverting type (shown in Figure 5 below) and the resistors were chosen using the following calculations. </s><s n="s3.3;p43.91">A non-inverting amplifier was chosen over the inverting type because it has a high output impedance and the integration of a low pass filter in the form of a capacitor is very simple. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0243a-fig.002"><head rend="bold">Figure 5: Circuit diagram for a non-inverting amplifier</head></figure><p n="p44.91"><s n="s1.1;p44.91">The gain of a non-inverting amplifier is given by: </s></p><p n="p45.91"><s n="s1.1;p45.91"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0243a-form.024"/> </s></p><p n="p46.91"><s n="s1.1;p46.91">In order to calculate values for R <hi rend="sub">1</hi> and R <hi rend="sub">2</hi> we set the gain at 1000: </s></p><p n="p47.91"><s n="s1.1;p47.91"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0243a-form.025"/> </s></p><p n="p48.91"><s n="s1.1;p48.91"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0243a-form.026"/> </s></p><p n="p49.91"><s n="s1.1;p49.91"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0243a-form.027"/> </s></p><p n="p50.91"><s n="s1.1;p50.91"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0243a-form.028"/> </s></p><p n="p51.91"><s n="s1.1;p51.91"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0243a-form.029"/> </s></p><p n="p52.91"><s n="s1.1;p52.91">Using this we set R <hi rend="sub">1</hi>= 1 MΩ and R <hi rend="sub">2</hi>=1 KΩ. </s></p><p n="p53.91"><s n="s1.4;p53.91">A problem associated with this set-up is that of noise. </s><s n="s2.4;p53.91">To counter this problem a low pass filter can be added in the form of a capacitor. </s><s n="s3.4;p53.91">For the addition of the capacitor we are given that RC = 0.1 seconds. </s><s n="s4.4;p53.91">The R referred to here is the R <hi rend="sub">1</hi> of the amplifier set up (see Figure 5) not the R <hi rend="sub">1</hi> in the bridge set up: </s></p><p n="p54.91"><s n="s1.1;p54.91"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0243a-form.030"/> </s></p><p n="p55.91"><s n="s1.1;p55.91"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0243a-form.031"/>. </s></p><p n="p56.91"><s n="s1.1;p56.91">We therefore use a capacitor with a capacitance of 0.1 μF. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">3. Method</head><p n="p57.91"><s n="s1.1;p57.91">This section describes the process of the investigation and the implementation of the theory outlined in the above section. </s></p><p n="p58.91"><s n="s1.3;p58.91">The Wheatstone Deflection Bridge was set up as shown in Figure 1. </s><s n="s2.3;p58.91">A 9 V battery was attached as the power supply. </s><s n="s3.3;p58.91">The two resistors each have a resistance of 1000 Ω. </s></p><p n="p59.91"><s n="s1.4;p59.91">The next step involved constructing the non-inverting amplifier using a 'breadboard' with a 741 operational amplifier provided. </s><s n="s2.4;p59.91">The amplifier was set up using the resistors of 1 MΩ and 1 KΩ as calculated in the 'Theory and Calculations' section. </s><s n="s3.4;p59.91">A digital voltmeter was connected to the circuit to display the output voltage of the system. </s><s n="s4.4;p59.91">The system was also zeroed using the potentiometer. </s></p><p n="p60.91"><s n="s1.4;p60.91">To measure the change in output voltage a force was applied to the end of the cantilever beam by placing washers on the peg. </s><s n="s2.4;p60.91">Each washer has a mass of 0.25 g (or 0.00025 Kg). </s><s n="s3.4;p60.91">A table of output voltage against mass was created by adding washers to the beam. </s><s n="s4.4;p60.91">A graph of output voltage against force was then drawn to calculate the sensitivity of the system. </s></p><p n="p61.91"><s n="s1.3;p61.91">Having analysed the system using a digital voltmeter the system was then connected up to a computer. </s><s n="s2.3;p61.91">The computer software is able to record the output voltage over a period of time at any given sampling rate. </s><s n="s3.3;p61.91">Recordings were made of the following scenarios: </s></p><list type="bulleted"><item>Static without the capacitor</item><item>Oscillating with the capacitor present in the system</item><item>Oscillating without the capacitor</item></list><p n="p62.91"><s n="s1.2;p62.91">In order to record the oscillating beam it was held down to its maximum deflection and released. </s><s n="s2.2;p62.91">It was left to oscillate freely until it came to rest. </s></p><p n="p63.91"><s n="s1.1;p63.91">Graphs of output voltage against time were created by transferring the data from the program into Excel. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">4. Results and Discussion</head><p n="p64.91"><s n="s1.4;p64.91">The graph of output voltage against force from the experiment with the washers is shown in the appendix. </s><s n="s2.4;p64.91">The graph is very much linear all the way. </s><s n="s3.4;p64.91">A trend line has been added so that the sensitivity of the systems can be calculated. </s><s n="s4.4;p64.91">The sensitivity is given by the gradient therefore this system has a sensitivity of 10.954 VN <hi rend="sup">-1</hi>. </s></p><p n="p65.91"><s n="s1.4;p65.91">The maximum force that was applied to the system is shown on the graph as just under 0.05 N. This is well below the theoretical maximum force of about 3 N that was calculated earlier in this report. </s><s n="s2.4;p65.91">This explains why the graph is linear up to the maximum value that was applied in the test. </s><s n="s3.4;p65.91">It should be noted that it was not possible to approach the maximum load of 3 N because the peg at the end of the beam was not tall enough to accommodate the required number of washers. </s><s n="s4.4;p65.91">The linear range can however be calculated using the maximum load and the equation shown on the graph that we found the sensitivity from: </s></p><p n="p66.91"><s n="s1.1;p66.91"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0243a-form.032"/> </s></p><p n="p67.91"><s n="s1.1;p67.91"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0243a-form.033"/>. </s></p><p n="p68.91"><s n="s1.1;p68.91">This means that the linear range goes from zero up to 33.04 V if the maximum for of 3.016 N is applied. </s></p><p n="p69.91"><s n="s1.3;p69.91">The output of the system depends on the strain. </s><s n="s2.3;p69.91">The strain in turn depends on the force applied and the dimensions of the beam. </s><s n="s3.3;p69.91">To measure the influence of each parameter let us consider the equation for strain: </s></p><p n="p70.91"><s n="s1.1;p70.91"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0243a-form.034"/>. </s></p><p n="p71.91"><s n="s1.4;p71.91">The parameters that affect the output voltage are therefore <hi rend="italic">l</hi>, <hi rend="italic">x</hi>, <hi rend="italic">w</hi>, <hi rend="italic">t</hi>, <hi rend="italic">E</hi> and <hi rend="italic">F</hi>. </s><s n="s2.4;p71.91">We can see that the strain varies linearly with all of these except the thickness of the beam (<hi rend="italic">t</hi>). </s><s n="s3.4;p71.91">The strain varies inversely with the square of the thickness, thus we can say that this is the most influential parameter. </s><s n="s4.4;p71.91">The system would be significantly more sensitive if we reduced the thickness of the beam. </s></p><p n="p72.91"><s n="s1.3;p72.91">It is possible to work out the maximum possible change in resistance using the maximum strain (ε<hi rend="sub">max</hi>), the gauge factor (G) and the unstrained resistance of the strain gauges (R <hi rend="sub">o</hi>). </s><s n="s2.3;p72.91">The maximum strain is equal to <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0243a-form.035"/>, the gauge factor is 2.1 and the unstrained resistance of the gauges is 1000 Ω. </s><s n="s3.3;p72.91">Using the relationship: </s></p><p n="p73.91"><s n="s1.1;p73.91"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0243a-form.036"/> </s></p><p n="p74.91"><s n="s1.1;p74.91"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0243a-form.037"/> </s></p><p n="p75.91"><s n="s1.1;p75.91"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0243a-form.038"/>. </s></p><p n="p76.91"><s n="s1.1;p76.91">This value of R <hi rend="sub">max</hi> corresponds to the maximum force that the system can support, which is about 3 N. </s></p><p n="p77.91"><s n="s1.5;p77.91">The graph of output voltage against time for the oscillating system with the low pass filter is shown in the appendix. </s><s n="s2.5;p77.91">It is possible to calculate the resonant frequency of the system using this graph. </s><s n="s3.5;p77.91">If we count the number of peaks to the first second we can see that there are about 21. </s><s n="s4.5;p77.91">This gives us an estimate for the resonant frequency of 21 Hz. </s><s n="s5.5;p77.91">A more accurate method would be to use the exact time coordinates of two peaks or troughs and then to apply the expression: </s></p><p n="p78.91"><s n="s1.1;p78.91"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0243a-form.039"/>. </s></p><p n="p79.91"><s n="s1.2;p79.91">Selected troughs have time coordinates of 198 ms and 246 ms. </s><s n="s2.2;p79.91">Putting these values into the above expression will give us a more accurate value for the resonant frequency: </s></p><p n="p80.91"><s n="s1.1;p80.91"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0243a-form.040"/>. </s></p><p n="p81.91"><s n="s1.4;p81.91">We can also use the graph to work out how long it takes for the system to stabilise after being disturbed. </s><s n="s2.4;p81.91">To do this we can use both the graph of the oscillating system with the low pass filter in place and the graph showing the same scenario without the low pass filter (also shown in the appendix). </s><s n="s3.4;p81.91">The graph without the low pass filter shows up the noise more than the one with the filter but they are both useful for determining the length of time it takes for the system to settle. </s><s n="s4.4;p81.91">In both cases the line appears to stabilise just short of 2 seconds. </s></p><p n="p82.91"><s n="s1.1;p82.91">The graph showing output voltage against time when no load is applied and no filter is in place (shown in the appendix) highlights the level of noise the system has if we don't have the low pass filter. </s></p><p n="p83.91"><s n="s1.2;p83.91">We will now consider whether the ambient temperature will affect the measured results. </s><s n="s2.2;p83.91">The error or change in length of a dimension can be expressed using the following equation: </s></p><p n="p84.91"><s n="s1.1;p84.91"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0243a-form.041"/>, </s></p><p n="p85.91"><s n="s1.1;p85.91">where α is the thermal expansion coefficient of the material, L <hi rend="sub">o</hi> is the original length at a temperature of 20°C and ∆<hi rend="italic">T</hi> is the change in temperature. </s></p><p n="p86.91"><s n="s1.2;p86.91">The thermal expansion coefficient for steel is 11×10 <hi rend="sup">-6</hi> / °C and the temperature variations where virtually zero. </s><s n="s2.2;p86.91">This means that temperature would have had little effect on our measured results since α is very small and ∆<hi rend="italic">T</hi> is also very small. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">5. Conclusion</head><p n="p87.91"><s n="s1.8;p87.91">The Wheatstone Deflection Bridge system was tested using two methods. </s><s n="s2.8;p87.91">In both cases a non-inverting amplifier was constructed in order to amplify the output signal front the system. </s><s n="s3.8;p87.91">The amplifier increased the signal form the order of millivolts to volts. </s><s n="s4.8;p87.91">The first test involving the application of force by placing washers on the end of the beam gave us the information we needed to calculate the sensitivity of the system. </s><s n="s5.8;p87.91">The sensitivity was found to be 10.954 VN <hi rend="sup">-1</hi>. </s><s n="s6.8;p87.91">Of the parameters that affect the output of the system, the thickness of the cantilever beam was found to be the most influential. </s><s n="s7.8;p87.91">The maximum load that the bridge could support was calculated to be 3 N. This was not possible to get close to however because the equipment was not capable of accommodating the required number of washers. </s><s n="s8.8;p87.91">The resulting graph of output voltage against force was therefore completely linear. </s></p><p n="p88.91"><s n="s1.4;p88.91">The second test involving the computer software allowed us to calculate the resonant frequency of the system if it is disturbed and left to settle. </s><s n="s2.4;p88.91">It was estimated to be 20.83 Hz. </s><s n="s3.4;p88.91">The system took just under 2 seconds to settle after being disturbed. </s><s n="s4.4;p88.91">It was also found that the output voltage settled nearer to zero much faster if a low pass filter was present in the system. </s></p><p n="p89.91"><s n="s1.3;p89.91">The system could be improved by using a more sensitive beam. </s><s n="s2.3;p89.91">This could be achieved by reducing the thickness of the beam. </s><s n="s3.3;p89.91">The peg at then end should be taller so that enough washers can be added to reach the maximum load of 3 N. </s></p><p n="p90.91"><s n="s1.1;p90.91">Although the temperature was shown not to have a significant effect on the experiment, a material with a lower thermal expansion coefficient for the beam would be an improvement. </s></p><p n="p91.91"><s n="s1.2;p91.91">The measurements of the dimensions were done using a standard ruler. </s><s n="s2.2;p91.91">More accurate measuring equipment would result in a more accurate calculation of the strain. </s></p></div1></body><back><div1 type="bibliography"><head rend="bold">6. References</head><p>All equations relating to the Wheatstone Deflection Bride are taking from the laboratory handout and the lecture notes associated with the ES21Q module.</p><p>Figures 1 and 2 are from the laboratory handout.</p><p>Figure 4 is taken form page 40 of the notes for ES21Q (Fig. 6.5).</p><p>Figure 5 and equations relating to the non-inverting amplifier are taken from the Engineering Data Book, University of <name type="university"/> School of Engineering, Fourth Edition.</p></div1><div1 type="appendix"><head rend="bold">7. Appendix</head><p/></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
