<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_0243d" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Road Vehicle Drag</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">deleted: header: module name and number, student number; footer: page numbers</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">2</p><p n="date">2005-03</p><p n="module title">Fluid Mechanics</p><p n="module code">ES252</p><p n="genre family">Explanation</p><p n="discipline">Engineering</p><p n="disciplinary group">PS</p><p n="grade">M</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">927</p><p n="number of s-units">92</p><p n="number of p">58</p><p n="number of tables">0</p><p n="number of figures">2</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">39</p><p n="number of lists">0</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">0</p><p n="abstract present">abstract present</p><p n="average words per s-unit">10.1</p><p n="average s-units per p">1.6</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">m</p><p n="year of birth">1984</p><p n="first language">English</p><p n="education">UKA</p><p n="course">Engineering</p><p n="student ID">0243</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><docTitle><titlePart><hi rend="bold">Project Title:</hi> <hi rend="bold">Road Vehicle Drag</hi></titlePart></docTitle><titlePart rend="bold">Name: <name type="student name"/> Student ID: <name type="student ID"/></titlePart></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="abstract"><head rend="bold">Summary:</head><p n="p1.58"><s n="s1.4;p1.58">Drag plays an important role in vehicle design. </s><s n="s2.4;p1.58">There a two types of drag mechanism whose significance depends on the type of body that the fluid must flow past. </s><s n="s3.4;p1.58">In all cases we seek to reduce the drag. </s><s n="s4.4;p1.58">For a racing car this is particularly important along with generating downforce. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Introduction:</head><p n="p2.58"><s n="s1.2;p2.58">Drag is a force that is generated as a result of a body blocking the path of a fluid flow. </s><s n="s2.2;p2.58">This force can be expressed by the following equation: </s></p><p n="p3.58"><s n="s1.1;p3.58"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0243d-form.001"/><ref target="BAWE_0243d-ftnote.001"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0243d-ftnote.001"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">"<hi rend="italic">Engineering Data Book</hi>" AJ Cartwright (ed) 4th ed. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">2001 University of Warwick, School of Engineering </s></p></note><p n="p4.58"><s n="s1.2;p4.58">The coefficient of drag (C <hi rend="sub">D</hi>) can be analysed using dimensional analysis. </s><s n="s2.2;p4.58">We assume that drag is a function of fluid density ρ, viscosity μ, free stream velocity U <hi rend="sub">0</hi>, a linear dimension of the body l, weight of the body per unit mass g (acceleration due to gravity), surface tension σ and bulk modulus K. <ref target="BAWE_0243d-ftnote.002"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0243d-ftnote.002"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Analysis from JF Douglas, JM Gasiorek, JA Swaffield "<hi rend="italic">Fluid mechanics</hi>" 3rd ed. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">1995 Longman group Ltd </s></p></note><p n="p5.58"><s n="s1.1;p5.58"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0243d-form.002"/> </s></p><p n="p6.58"><s n="s1.1;p6.58"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0243d-form.003"/>. </s></p><p n="p7.58"><s n="s1.1;p7.58">Substituting in the dimensions: </s></p><p n="p8.58"><s n="s1.1;p8.58"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0243d-form.004"/>. </s></p><p n="p9.58"><s n="s1.1;p9.58">Equating indices: </s></p><p n="p10.58"><s n="s1.1;p10.58"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0243d-form.005"/>, </s></p><p n="p11.58"><s n="s1.1;p11.58">therefore <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0243d-form.006"/>. </s></p><p n="p12.58"><s n="s1.1;p12.58"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0243d-form.007"/>, </s></p><p n="p13.58"><s n="s1.1;p13.58">therefore <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0243d-form.008"/>. </s></p><p n="p14.58"><s n="s1.1;p14.58"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0243d-form.009"/>. </s></p><p n="p15.58"><s n="s1.1;p15.58">From which <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0243d-form.010"/> </s></p><p n="p16.58"><s n="s1.1;p16.58"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0243d-form.011"/> </s></p><p n="p17.58"><s n="s1.1;p17.58"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0243d-form.012"/>. </s></p><p n="p18.58"><s n="s1.1;p18.58">Therefore </s></p><p n="p19.58"><s n="s1.1;p19.58"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0243d-form.013"/> </s></p><p n="p20.58"><s n="s1.1;p20.58"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0243d-form.014"/>. </s></p><p n="p21.58"><s n="s1.1;p21.58"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0243d-form.015"/>, </s></p><p n="p22.58"><s n="s1.1;p22.58"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0243d-form.016"/> </s></p><p n="p23.58"><s n="s1.1;p23.58"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0243d-form.017"/> </s></p><p n="p24.58"><s n="s1.1;p24.58"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0243d-form.018"/> </s></p><p n="p25.58"><s n="s1.1;p25.58">so that: </s></p><p n="p26.58"><s n="s1.1;p26.58"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0243d-form.019"/>. </s></p><p n="p27.58"><s n="s1.1;p27.58">Compare with our original equation for drag: </s></p><p n="p28.58"><s n="s1.1;p28.58"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0243d-form.020"/>. </s></p><p n="p29.58"><s n="s1.1;p29.58">Since for a body of a fixed shape </s></p><p n="p30.58"><s n="s1.1;p30.58"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0243d-form.021"/>, </s></p><p n="p31.58"><s n="s1.1;p31.58">where l is a numerical constant and incorporating the constant ½ as well as l into the function <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0243d-form.022"/> such that <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0243d-form.023"/>, we obtain </s></p><p n="p32.58"><s n="s1.1;p32.58"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0243d-form.024"/> </s></p><p n="p33.58"><s n="s1.1;p33.58"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0243d-form.025"/> </s></p><p n="p34.58"><s n="s1.1;p34.58">The drag coefficient is therefore a dimensionless quantity that is determined by four dimensionless groups. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Design Solutions:</head><p n="p35.58"><s n="s1.8;p35.58">The level and type of drag depends on the shape of the body. </s><s n="s2.8;p35.58">Bluff and streamlined bodies are both subject to drag forces, but of a different nature. </s><s n="s3.8;p35.58">For bluff bodies it is pressure drag that dominates. </s><s n="s4.8;p35.58">This is caused by adverse pressure gradients resulting in a low pressure area at the rear of the body. </s><s n="s5.8;p35.58">The adverse pressure gradient causes the boundary layer to separate (see figure 1) and a wake forms. </s><s n="s6.8;p35.58">The wake exists in the form of eddies that flow in a rotary manner and where the fluid pressure is low. </s><s n="s7.8;p35.58">The size of the wake depends on the point at which the boundary layer separates. </s><s n="s8.8;p35.58">It is desirable to delay the separation so that the wake is as small as possible and hence the pressure drag will be lower because the pressure difference between the front and rear of the body will be smaller. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0243d-fig.001"><head><hi rend="bold">Figure 1: Boundary layer separation</hi><ref target="BAWE_0243d-ftnote.003"/><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0243d-ftnote.003"><p n="pn1.1"> Figures 1 and 2 from BS Massey "<hi rend="italic">Mechanics of Fluids</hi>" 6th ed. 1989 Chapman &amp; Hall</p></note></head></figure><p n="p36.58"><s n="s1.9;p36.58">In the case of streamlined bodies the boundary layer separation takes place very near to the rear of the body. </s><s n="s2.9;p36.58">The pressure drag is not that significant (although still a factor). </s><s n="s3.9;p36.58">In this case it is the skin friction drag that is dominant. </s><s n="s4.9;p36.58">This type of drag is caused by the action of viscosity in the boundary layer setting up shear forces that act on the body. </s><s n="s5.9;p36.58">We can relate the two mechanisms to a coach and a racing car. </s><s n="s6.9;p36.58">The coach is not at all aerodynamic and therefore the pressure drag will be dominant. </s><s n="s7.9;p36.58">A racing car is designed to minimise drag and maximise downforce. </s><s n="s8.9;p36.58">The car is made with stream lining in mind and therefore skin friction is an important factor. </s><s n="s9.9;p36.58">The generation of negative lift does however cause a separation of the boundary layer and so pressure drag is of more significance to a racing car than to a purely streamlined body that does not need to generate downforce. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0243d-fig.002"><head rend="bold">Figure 2: Boundary layer formation</head></figure><p n="p37.58"><s n="s1.5;p37.58">The relationship between drag and turbulence has been touched upon above. </s><s n="s2.5;p37.58">The turbulence in the wake causes the low pressure and hence pressure drag. </s><s n="s3.5;p37.58">The turbulent boundary layer is also important. </s><s n="s4.5;p37.58">The turbulent boundary layer separates less easily than the laminar boundary layer. </s><s n="s5.5;p37.58">The turbulence in the boundary layer causes the streamlines to move closer together at the rear of the body thus increasing the pressure at the rear of the body hence reducing pressure drag. </s></p><p n="p38.58"><s n="s1.3;p38.58">The design of a car is completely under the control of engineers working on different aspects such as chassis, engine, suspension, tyres, aerodynamics etc. </s><s n="s2.3;p38.58">The aesthetics are important because a car needs to look good to sell but also it must be aerodynamically efficient. </s><s n="s3.3;p38.58">There is a compromise that must be reached. </s></p><p n="p39.58"><s n="s1.3;p39.58">We can estimate the drag force exerted on a coach by modelling it as a rectangular cross section. </s><s n="s2.3;p39.58">We will assume that the cross section is 2.5m x 3.5m. </s><s n="s3.3;p39.58">Existing data for drag coefficients gives a value of 1.1 for such a body<ref target="BAWE_0243d-ftnote.004"/>. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0243d-ftnote.004"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Streeter, Wiley, Bedford "<hi rend="italic">Fluid Mechanics</hi>". </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">1998 McGraw Hill </s></p></note><p n="p40.58"><s n="s1.1;p40.58">Calculation of drag force and power required to travel at 50 mph: </s></p><p n="p41.58"><s n="s1.1;p41.58"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0243d-form.026"/> </s></p><p n="p42.58"><s n="s1.1;p42.58">The density of air is <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0243d-form.027"/>. </s></p><p n="p43.58"><s n="s1.1;p43.58"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0243d-form.028"/> </s></p><p n="p44.58"><s n="s1.1;p44.58"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0243d-form.029"/> </s></p><p n="p45.58"><s n="s1.1;p45.58"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0243d-form.030"/> </s></p><p n="p46.58"><s n="s1.1;p46.58"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0243d-form.031"/> </s></p><p n="p47.58"><s n="s1.1;p47.58"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0243d-form.032"/> </s></p><p n="p48.58"><s n="s1.1;p48.58"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0243d-form.033"/>. </s></p><p n="p49.58"><s n="s1.1;p49.58">The most aerodynamically efficient design for a racing car is shown on the right below and a calculation for the drag force and power output required to attain a speed of 150 mph follows. </s></p><p n="p50.58"><s n="s1.1;p50.58">Existing data for the design on the right gives a value for C <hi rend="sub">D</hi> of 0.12.<ref target="BAWE_0243d-ftnote.005"/> The cross section can be modelled as an ellipse with an area of about 3.5 m <hi rend="sup">2</hi>. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0243d-ftnote.005"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">JA Roberson, Clayton T Crowe "<hi rend="italic">Fluid Mechanics</hi>" 6th ed. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">1997 Wiley </s></p></note><p n="p51.58"><s n="s1.1;p51.58"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0243d-form.034"/> </s></p><p n="p52.58"><s n="s1.1;p52.58"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0243d-form.035"/> </s></p><p n="p53.58"><s n="s1.1;p53.58"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0243d-form.036"/> </s></p><p n="p54.58"><s n="s1.1;p54.58"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0243d-form.037"/> </s></p><p n="p55.58"><s n="s1.1;p55.58"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0243d-form.038"/>. </s></p><p n="p56.58"><s n="s1.4;p56.58">Scale models can be used in a wind tunnel to model the air flow over a prototype design. </s><s n="s2.4;p56.58">The conditions for model testing are geometric similarity, kinematic similarity and dynamic similarity <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0243d-form.039"/>. </s><s n="s3.4;p56.58">This is hard to achieve. </s><s n="s4.4;p56.58">A huge wind tunnel is needed which must also be pressurised in order to achieve the same Reynolds number for model and prototype. </s></p><p n="p57.58"><s n="s1.2;p57.58">Other techniques would be by the use of computer programs using computational fluid dynamics. </s><s n="s2.2;p57.58">This reduces amount of wind tunnel testing but is not yet advanced enough to allow for no physical testing at all. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Conclusions:</head><p n="p58.58"><s n="s1.3;p58.58">Drag occurs as a result of the interruption of a flow by a body. </s><s n="s2.3;p58.58">It is a function primarily of the Reynolds number and also of other dimensionless numbers. </s><s n="s3.3;p58.58">In vehicle design it is desirable to reduce drag but there is always a compromise between the best aerodynamic solution and the aesthetics. </s></p></div1></body><back><div1 type="bibliography"><head rend="bold">References:</head><p>JF Douglas, JM Gasiorek, JA Swaffield "<hi rend="italic">Fluid mechanics</hi>" 3<hi rend="sup">rd</hi> ed. 1995 Longman group Ltd</p><p>BS Massey "<hi rend="italic">Mechanics of Fluids</hi>" 6<hi rend="sup">th</hi> ed. 1989 Chapman &amp; Hall</p><p>JA Roberson, Clayton T Crowe "<hi rend="italic">Fluid Mechanics</hi>" 6<hi rend="sup">th</hi> ed. 1997 Wiley</p><p>"<hi rend="italic">Engineering Data Book</hi>" AJ Cartwright (ed) 4<hi rend="sup">th</hi> ed. 2001 University of <name type="university"/>, School of Engineering</p></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
