<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_0243e" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>The Use of Analysis Tools in Design</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">deleted: header: module name, student number</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">3</p><p n="date">2005-11</p><p n="module title">Design Techniques and Management</p><p n="module code">ES380</p><p n="genre family">Critique</p><p n="discipline">Engineering</p><p n="disciplinary group">PS</p><p n="grade">M</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">2943</p><p n="number of s-units">125</p><p n="number of p">37</p><p n="number of tables">0</p><p n="number of figures">9</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">0</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">4</p><p n="abstract present">abstract present</p><p n="average words per s-unit">23.5</p><p n="average s-units per p">3.4</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">m</p><p n="year of birth">1984</p><p n="first language">English</p><p n="education">UKA</p><p n="course">Engineering</p><p n="student ID">0243</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><titlePart rend="bold">The Use of Analysis Tools in Design</titlePart><docTitle><titlePart rend="bold">Design Study: Formula 1 car Front Wing and Nose Section</titlePart></docTitle><figure id="BAWE_0243e-pic.001"/></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="abstract"><head rend="bold">Summary</head><p n="p1.37"><s n="s1.4;p1.37">This report outlines the application of two analysis tools that are utilised in the design of a formula 1 front wing and nose section. </s><s n="s2.4;p1.37">These tools are computational fluid dynamics and finite element analysis. </s><s n="s3.4;p1.37">Both are software programs that require a high level of computing power in order to produce accurate simulations. </s><s n="s4.4;p1.37">The discussion in this report considers the benefits and limitations of these tools and contrasts them manual techniques such as wind tunnel testing and prototyping. </s></p><p n="p2.37"><s n="s1.2;p2.37">An example FEA analysis of the front wing section shown above has been carried out using the COSMOSWorks facility in SolidWorks. </s><s n="s2.2;p2.37">The model has been assigned a material (carbon fibre aluminium composite) and various pressures have been applied to the appropriate surfaces to simulate the loading experienced at top speed. </s></p><p n="p3.37"><s n="s1.3;p3.37">The analysis found that the front wing and nose section was structurally sound with a minimum factor of safety throughout the structure of approximately 17. </s><s n="s2.3;p3.37">The analysis was subject to simplification however which means that the results cannot be treated as absolute. </s><s n="s3.3;p3.37">The analysis must only be used as a guide and engineers should rely on their own experience in designing a suitable component solution. </s></p><p n="p4.37"><s n="s1.1;p4.37">FEA provides formula 1 designers with a powerful tool for getting designs analysed quickly and without the need for costly prototyping and testing various solutions thus reducing the timescale which is all important in formula 1. </s></p><p n="p5.37"><s n="s1.3;p5.37">CFD is less well utilised although it still provides a useful analysis of individual aerodynamic devices. </s><s n="s2.3;p5.37">The computing power required for accurate simulations of an entire car is too high for our current capability. </s><s n="s3.3;p5.37">The experience and imaginative flare of the designer combined with testing in the wind tunnel remains the best solution for the aerodynamics department. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Discussion</head><p n="p6.37"><s n="s1.2;p6.37">Finite element analysis and computational fluid dynamics both play a very significant part in the design of a formula 1 car. </s><s n="s2.2;p6.37">In a sport where hundredths of a second can be the difference between the outright pace of two different cars, the teams spend huge amounts of money embracing technology that will enable them to increase the pace of the car by even the tiniest amount. </s></p><div2><head>Computational Fluid Dymanics as an Analysis Tool</head><p n="p7.37"><s n="s1.7;p7.37">CFD is behind FEA in terms of its use in formula design purely because of the problems associated with computing the necessary calculations to simulate the flow over such a complicated vehicle. </s><s n="s2.7;p7.37">Even with the very latest supercomputers the aerodynamics department still rely mainly on the wind tunnel and track testing for developing the aerodynamics of the car. </s><s n="s3.7;p7.37">This is purely because the direct method provides more accurate results than any computer simulation program will ever be able to (with current levels of computing power). </s><s n="s4.7;p7.37">For this reason it is very likely that the engineers will continue to rely more on manual testing using the near full scale wind tunnels that they have invested millions of pounds in. </s><s n="s5.7;p7.37">This is shown by the recent investment that the Sauber F1 team (now BMW) made in a new full scale wind tunnel with rolling surface which became operational at the end of 2003. </s><s n="s6.7;p7.37">The Head of aerodynamics Dirk de Beer said at the time that "It's probably 15-20% of our personnel that are involved with CFD"<ref target="BAWE_0243e-ftnote.001"/>. </s><s n="s7.7;p7.37">The rest of the department is based around the wind tunnel testing. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0243e-ftnote.001"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">David Tremayne "<hi rend="italic">The science of Formula 1 Cars</hi>", p21, Haynes Publishing 2004 </s></p></note><p n="p8.37"><s n="s1.5;p8.37">The design of a formula 1 cars aerodynamics is very much conception rather than an analytical process. </s><s n="s2.5;p8.37">Many of the best designers in formula 1 are happier to work at a drawing board working out the aerodynamic profile for a car than to play with a CAD model. </s><s n="s3.5;p8.37">CFD will be used for analysis of individual components but even this is restricted by the flow assumptions and boundary conditions that must be used in the simulation. </s><s n="s4.5;p8.37">The more components that are included in the model, the more computing power needed and the greater number of assumptions that have to be incorporated into the simulation. </s><s n="s5.5;p8.37">Therefore it is only by manual analysis in the wind tunnel and ultimately on the track in testing that a true analysis of the aerodynamic efficiency and overall performance can be made. </s></p><p n="p9.37"><s n="s1.3;p9.37">Aerodynamics is still considered to be a "black art" in formula 1 simply because the way in which the air interacts with the car is so complicated that even the best don't claim to fully understand it! </s><s n="s2.3;p9.37">CFD is therefore a valuable tool if a high level of computing power is available but it remains only a guide in the overall strive for increased downforce and reduced drag. </s><s n="s3.3;p9.37">The wind tunnel is the tried and tested analysis method and will remain so for the foreseeable future. </s></p></div2><div2><head>Finite Element Analysis as an Analysis Tool</head><p n="p10.37"><s n="s1.15;p10.37">Since the introduction of mandatory crash tests in formula 1 and also the advent of carbon fibre composite as the main material for the chassis, FEA has become a very useful design analysis tool. </s><s n="s2.15;p10.37">Formula 1 cars are subjected to huge forces but at the same time they must be as light as possible for obvious performance reasons. </s><s n="s3.15;p10.37">This makes the design of the structure a quest for the minimum amount of material that will be strong enough to cope with the loads imposed on it. </s><s n="s4.15;p10.37">The crash tests that each car must go though are very rigorous. </s><s n="s5.15;p10.37">Given that the designers have to work to a very strict time scale they must be able to analyse a design very quickly and get an idea of how it will deform under loading. </s><s n="s6.15;p10.37">FEA is an extremely useful tool for helping an engineer to visualise what will happen to a component or whole section of the car under loading. </s><s n="s7.15;p10.37">The FEA gives a very accurate guide (much more so than CFD does in aerodynamics) as to the stresses, strains and deflections within a structure. </s><s n="s8.15;p10.37">This allows the designers to fine tune the design down to the optimal requirements before anything is manufactured for testing. </s><s n="s9.15;p10.37">Without FEA the design process would have to involve many more prototype models that would have to be tested on crash test rigs and in the wind tunnel. </s><s n="s10.15;p10.37">This is very costly and more importantly to formula teams it is very time consuming. </s><s n="s11.15;p10.37">FEA does of course have its limitations given that assumptions have to be made in the model. </s><s n="s12.15;p10.37">The component may well have to be modified after tests despite what the FEA model says. </s><s n="s13.15;p10.37">This is because, like CFD, it is only a guide. </s><s n="s14.15;p10.37">The results should not be treated as absolute. </s><s n="s15.15;p10.37">What it does enable though is for a better solution to a problem to be achieved much more quickly. </s></p><p n="p11.37"><s n="s1.3;p11.37">FEA can be used to analyse very complicated shapes that are extremely difficult to analyse by hand. </s><s n="s2.3;p11.37">The result is that complicated components can be optimised in that just the right amount of material can be used rather than having to be "over-engineered" to guard against failure. </s><s n="s3.3;p11.37">Such a use of FEA is that illustrated by the example analysis in this report. </s></p><p n="p12.37"><s n="s1.4;p12.37">In the fast moving cutting edge world of formula 1 there really is no alternative to FEA in the design process for the structure of the car. </s><s n="s2.4;p12.37">It provides a very accurate model for the behaviour of structures under loading and can be used for very complicated shapes. </s><s n="s3.4;p12.37">A very good design solution can be achieved that will need very little modification before anything has to be manufactured. </s><s n="s4.4;p12.37">It reduces the need to manufacture many prototype models that may be far away from the optimal solution thus using it as a guide, it allows for a solution to be reached in a much shorter timescale. </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Example FEA on a Front Wing and Nose Section of a Formula 1 Car</head><p n="p13.37"><s n="s1.6;p13.37">The front wing exists to generate downforce which pushes the front of the car into the ground thus resulting in more grip. </s><s n="s2.6;p13.37">It can consist of several elements all attached to endplates at either end. </s><s n="s3.6;p13.37">The wing section is joined to the nose by two uprights at the centre of the wing section. </s><s n="s4.6;p13.37">The nose section in turn joins to the monocoque just in front of the front axel. </s><s n="s5.6;p13.37">From this mounting point the section must be able to cope with the downforce that the wing generates at top speed, with negligible deflection. </s><s n="s6.6;p13.37">This is due to the regulation that prohibits any moveable aerodynamic device<ref target="BAWE_0243e-ftnote.002"/>. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0243e-ftnote.002"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">FIA Formula 1 Technical Regulations </s></p></note><figure id="BAWE_0243e-pic.002"/><p n="p14.37"><s n="s1.2;p14.37">The wing section must be stiff enough to not deflect under high loading and the endplates must be strong enough to resist the twisting force that they will be subjected to as the wing generates more downforce at higher speeds. </s><s n="s2.2;p14.37">However the wings themselves must be quite thin so as not to create too much drag and also the endplates must not be too thick in profile or they too will cause a lot of drag. </s></p><p n="p15.37"><s n="s1.3;p15.37">A front wing can typically generate an equivalent mass of 560Kg in downforce at top speed<ref target="BAWE_0243e-ftnote.003"/>. </s><s n="s2.3;p15.37">In the COSMOSWorks FEA program this can be modelled as a negative pressure on the underside of the wing elements. </s><s n="s3.3;p15.37">The deflectors on the endplates will also experience a small force which is modelled in the same way. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0243e-ftnote.003"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">David Tremayne "<hi rend="italic">The science of Formula 1 Cars</hi>", p22, Haynes Publishing 2004 </s></p></note><p n="p16.37"><s n="s1.1;p16.37">The following pages show the results of the analysis which in turn is followed by a critical analysis of the process and the reliability of the results. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0243e-pic.003"><head>Figure 1: Mesh detail used for the FEA</head></figure><figure id="BAWE_0243e-pic.004"><head>Figure 2: Stress distribution throughout the wing and nose section</head></figure><figure id="BAWE_0243e-pic.005"><head>Figure 3: Strain distribution thought the wing and nose section</head></figure><figure id="BAWE_0243e-pic.006"><head>Figure 4: Displacement of the deformed wing section</head></figure><figure id="BAWE_0243e-pic.007"><head>Figure 5: Deformation of the wing section (grossly exaggerated)</head></figure><figure id="BAWE_0243e-pic.008"><head>Figure 6: Design check showing the range in factor of safety throughout the wing and nose section </head></figure></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Critical Analysis</head><p n="p17.37"><s n="s1.4;p17.37">The downforce has been split evenly between the two wing elements and modelled as a pressure distribution on the lower surfaces of each element. </s><s n="s2.4;p17.37">The much smaller downforce generated by the deflectors on the endplates has been modelled in the same manner. </s><s n="s3.4;p17.37">The material properties were obtained from the CES Selector materials database. </s><s n="s4.4;p17.37">The chosen material being a carbon fibre aluminium composite similar to the material actually used in formula 1. </s></p><p n="p18.37"><s n="s1.1;p18.37">The main points that we can initially take from the analysis are as follows: </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p19.37"><s n="s1.1;p19.37">The stress within the structure does not exceed the yield stress at any point therefore all deformation is elastic </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p20.37"><s n="s1.1;p20.37">The maximum deflection is just over 1mm and occurs at the outer edges of the endplates </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p21.37"><s n="s1.1;p21.37">The overall deformation is well within the rules regarding moveable aerodynamic devices </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p22.37"><s n="s1.1;p22.37">The minimum factor of safety throughout the wing and nose section is approximately 17 </s></p><p n="p23.37"><s n="s1.7;p23.37">Before taking these results at face value we need to examine the validity of the model. </s><s n="s2.7;p23.37">The pressure distribution on the surfaces of each wing element is assumed to be constant. </s><s n="s3.7;p23.37">This is not the case in practice, however it is not possible to apply an exact representation of the pressure distribution in COSMOSWorks and so the model had to be simplified. </s><s n="s4.7;p23.37">This simplification affects all of the results for stress, strain and deflection. </s><s n="s5.7;p23.37">The next step may be to refine the analysis by reducing the simplifications however this would result in a more complicated model that would take longer to simulate. </s><s n="s6.7;p23.37">This analysis was also undertaken using the finest mesh possible within the program. </s><s n="s7.7;p23.37">Therefore in terms of the number of nodes and degrees of freedom, the model cannot be made more accurate. </s></p><p n="p24.37"><s n="s1.6;p24.37">Since the lowest factor of safety is 17, it would be reasonable to assume that the structure is sound despite the simplifications that have been introduced into the analysis. </s><s n="s2.6;p24.37">This means that the designer can modify parts of the design such as the shape of the endplates (these play a critical role in the aerodynamics of the car) without affecting the structural integrity of the wing section. </s><s n="s3.6;p24.37">Once a modified shape has been modelled it is very easy to run the FEA again. </s><s n="s4.6;p24.37">The alternative and indeed logical next step is to choose to manufacture and test the part in the wind tunnel. </s><s n="s5.6;p24.37">It is only by this more direct approach that the component parts can be analysed fully before they are tested at the track. </s><s n="s6.6;p24.37">The FEA helps to produce a near optimal solution before the wind tunnel need even be utilised. </s></p><p n="p25.37"><s n="s1.2;p25.37">The manual approach to the same design problem would be to examine the forces that are exerted throughout the wing and nose section. </s><s n="s2.2;p25.37">Figure 7 shows the wing and nose section model with the significant forces and likely areas of stress highlighted. </s></p><p n="p26.37"><s n="s1.7;p26.37">High areas of stress are likely to occur at sharp edges and along thin sections subject to a twisting force. </s><s n="s2.7;p26.37">The wings will bend downwards under loading and exert a twisting force on the endplates. </s><s n="s3.7;p26.37">With this in mind the designer must consider where the structure needs to be strengthened by adding some thickness to the appropriate places. </s><s n="s4.7;p26.37">The venturi components seated at the bottom of each endplate act both as an aerodynamic device affecting the flow to the underside of the car but also as a strengthening component for the endplate by giving it extra thickness. </s><s n="s5.7;p26.37">This is where the experience of the designer and their own imagination helps to find a solution to the structural problem by use of a component that is there to perform a completely different function. </s><s n="s6.7;p26.37">It is this thought process that is the most important design technique in formula 1. </s><s n="s7.7;p26.37">The FEA is only the tool that is used to analyse the effects of this design philosophy. </s></p><p n="p27.37"><s n="s1.2;p27.37">The nose sections is fixed to the monocoque. </s><s n="s2.2;p27.37">This is the point that acts as the restraint for the entire wing and nose section and must be able to cope with all the associated loads imposed on the whole section. </s></p><p n="p28.37"><s n="s1.1;p28.37">The wing elements will be subject to a bending force causing them to deflect at their extremities. </s></p><p n="p29.37"><s n="s1.1;p29.37">The uprights must support a downforce of about 5500N when the car is going at top speed. </s></p><p n="p30.37"><s n="s1.1;p30.37">The endplates will be twisted by the deflecting ends of the wing elements. </s></p><p n="p31.37"><s n="s1.1;p31.37">The Winglets on the outer edges give some thickness to the endplate to resist this force. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0243e-pic.009"><head>Figure 7: Forces and areas of stress highlighted for manual analysis</head></figure><p n="p32.37"><s n="s1.11;p32.37">In terms of cost, the design and manufacture of a formula 1 car is astronomical. </s><s n="s2.11;p32.37">It is not the same process as for a product that is to be marketed to the public or for a particular use etc. </s><s n="s3.11;p32.37">Those sorts of products have a finite design process from conception through to production. </s><s n="s4.11;p32.37">A formula 1 car is an ever changing design. </s><s n="s5.11;p32.37">The car is never the same from one race to the next and the engineers are constantly working on developments that will improve the car. </s><s n="s6.11;p32.37">In order to do this they spend millions on analysis tools such as FEA and CFD along with the wind tunnel etc. </s><s n="s7.11;p32.37">Using these analysis tools is the only way to get to the front of the grid. </s><s n="s8.11;p32.37">The engineers will always push the team bosses to invest in more powerful computers and more sophisticated and the team bosses in turn will search for sponsorship in order to raise the finance. </s><s n="s9.11;p32.37">No formula 1 team makes a profit. </s><s n="s10.11;p32.37">It is a unique sport where on the face of it, the teams seem to just throw huge amounts of money into research that will gain them maybe a few tenths of a second over their rivals. </s><s n="s11.11;p32.37">Until the governing body take action over the huge costs associated with competing in formula 1, the only management option for the teams is to continue to invest in technology otherwise they will end up at the back of the grid. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Conclusion</head><p n="p33.37"><s n="s1.3;p33.37">It is possible to arrive at different conclusions regarding the use of CFD and FEA as analysis tools in formula 1 design. </s><s n="s2.3;p33.37">Whilst they both have significant uses in formula 1 design they remain a guide to the process and their findings should not be treated as absolute. </s><s n="s3.3;p33.37">All analysis models have to make assumptions that are not entirely consistent with the real world if they are to perform some sort of simulation. </s></p><p n="p34.37"><s n="s1.4;p34.37">FEA is a very important analysis tool in the overall design of the car. </s><s n="s2.4;p34.37">It can be used to analyse practically every part of the car's different components and provides very accurate results if the right program and computing power are available. </s><s n="s3.4;p34.37">For formula 1 the use of FEA does not detract from the skills of the design team. </s><s n="s4.4;p34.37">It is simply a necessity because the pace of development is such that any tool that will help guide the design team to the optimal solution is a must have or the team will fall behind. </s></p><p n="p35.37"><s n="s1.1;p35.37">The process of conceiving a design that combines the aerodynamic devices with their use as stressed elements in the design is very much a skill that the designer brings to the process through experience and not by simply analysing all sorts of solutions using an analysis tool such as FEA. </s></p><p n="p36.37"><s n="s1.3;p36.37">CFD is utilised less as an analysis tool than FEA because the parameters governing airflow over the car are much more wide ranging and more complicated than the stresses and strains within a material. </s><s n="s2.3;p36.37">CFD therefore requires a lot more computing power than FEA. The uses of CFD are therefore restricted mainly to the analysis of flow over individual aerodynamic devices which can lead to problems of boundary condition assumptions that may not be an accurate simulation of what really happens. </s><s n="s3.3;p36.37">CFD is not currently capable of modelling the airflow over a whole car to sufficient accuracy for it to supersede the wind tunnel. </s></p><p n="p37.37"><s n="s1.2;p37.37">The conception of aerodynamics is also very much an imaginative process based on years of experience in the field. </s><s n="s2.2;p37.37">The manual process of testing aerodynamic solutions in the wind tunnel is still the favoured analysis technique. </s></p></div1></body><back/></text></TEI.2>
