<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_0244n" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>What was to Blame for the Failure of the Great Leap Forward?</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">The document has a title page which contains:
document title
title part</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">2</p><p n="date">2004-11</p><p n="module title">Politics of Contemporary China</p><p n="module code">PO222</p><p n="genre family">Essay</p><p n="discipline">Politics</p><p n="disciplinary group">SS</p><p n="grade">M</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">2409</p><p n="number of s-units">68</p><p n="number of p">19</p><p n="number of tables">0</p><p n="number of figures">0</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">0</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">0</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">35.4</p><p n="average s-units per p">3.6</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">f</p><p n="year of birth">1985</p><p n="first language">English</p><p n="education">UKA</p><p n="course">Politics</p><p n="student ID">0244</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><titlePart>Contemporary Politics of China<name type="tutor name"/></titlePart><docTitle><titlePart rend="italic">What was to Blame for the Failure of the Great Leap Forward? </titlePart></docTitle><titlePart><name type="student name"/> (2 <hi rend="sup">nd</hi> year His/Pol)</titlePart><docTitle><titlePart rend="underlined">What was to Blame for the Failure of the Great Leap Forward? </titlePart></docTitle></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="section"><p n="p1.19"><s n="s1.4;p1.19">The Great Leap Forward was an initiative put forward by Mao Zedong which was ratified in May of 1958 at the Second Session of Eight Party Congress and was chiefly an attempt to catch up with the West in economic terms. </s><s n="s2.4;p1.19">Mao focussed on setting grain and steel targets to boost production and moulded the existing cooperatives into a smaller number of communes. </s><s n="s3.4;p1.19">He wanted to achieve this through a process of 'walking on two legs' by combining modern, large-scale capital intensive methods with traditional, small-scale methods of production. </s><s n="s4.4;p1.19">However, despite these seemingly good intentions the Great Leap Forward was a one of the biggest failures in China's recent history and there are a number of reasons for its lack of success. </s></p><p n="p2.19"><s n="s1.3;p2.19">One important reason to consider is how much it was solely Mao's influence and how much he personally was responsible for the Great Leap Forward's (GLF) lack of success. </s><s n="s2.3;p2.19">Obviously as the most powerful man within the Chinese Communist Party the majority of authority lay with him and certainly "Mao himself, as with the Hundred Flowers earlier, again was clearly the critical figure pushing forward an innovative program"<ref target="BAWE_0244n-ftnote.001"/>. </s><s n="s3.3;p2.19">Of course this alone does not necessarily mean he was the reason for its unsuccessful path but there are a number of examples of how Mao did indeed make the situation worsen and reach crisis point. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0244n-ftnote.001"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.3;pn1.1">Teiwes, Frederick C. </s><s n="s2.3;pn1.1">(1979) <hi rend="underlined">Politics and Purges in China.</hi> </s><s n="s3.3;pn1.1">White Plains ; Folkestone : Sharpe : Dawson, p. 335. </s></p></note><p n="p3.19"><s n="s1.4;p3.19">Some historians have concentrated on Mao's utopian views perhaps not allowing to him to see the actual situation and having too much faith in human nature. </s><s n="s2.4;p3.19">His decision to call the process a 'Leap' forward shows he knew how much he wanted to achieve against a very small time scale and he has been criticised for not thoroughly planning how would be the most effective way of doing so. </s><s n="s3.4;p3.19">Mao knew how far China was behind the West in terms of their economy but seemed to believe that having faith in socialism overtaking capitalism would be enough. </s><s n="s4.4;p3.19">It was almost as though he was actually "convinced that he had a formula for boosting agricultural production which would guarantee the success of his utopian plans"<ref target="BAWE_0244n-ftnote.002"/>. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0244n-ftnote.002"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.3;pn1.1">Becker, Jasper. </s><s n="s2.3;pn1.1">(1999) <hi rend="underlined">Hungry Ghosts: China's Secret Famine</hi>. </s><s n="s3.3;pn1.1">London: John Murray. p. 57. </s></p></note><p n="p4.19"><s n="s1.3;p4.19">It could be argued that Mao's desire to beat the West overshadowed everything else and led him to have such a blinkered view that ultimately he would have done anything to achieve his goal. </s><s n="s2.3;p4.19">So even if he did not have an infallible belief in human nature before he came to power, he forced himself into believing that "human will and energy, properly mobilised can overcome any objective impediments to revolutionary change and economic development"<ref target="BAWE_0244n-ftnote.003"/>. </s><s n="s3.3;p4.19">All of this contributed towards the impossibly ambitious aims and methods Mao pushed forward and which were the some of the main causes for the number of people who suffered as a result of the GLF. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0244n-ftnote.003"><p n="pn1.4"><s n="s1.4;pn1.4">Joseph, William A. </s><s n="s2.4;pn1.4">"A Tragedy of Good Intentions: Post Mao Views of the Great Leap Forward" <hi rend="underlined">Modern China</hi>, Vol. 12, No. </s><s n="s3.4;pn1.4">4. </s><s n="s4.4;pn1.4">(Oct., 1986), p. 434. </s></p><p n="pn2.4"><s n="s1.1;pn2.4"><seg type="URL" n="http://links.jstor.org/sici?sici=0097"/>- </s></p><p n="pn3.4"><s n="s1.1;pn3.4">7004%28198610%2912%3A4%3C419%3AATOGIP%3E2.0.CO%3B </s></p><p n="pn4.4"><s n="s1.2;pn4.4">2-2. </s><s n="s2.2;pn4.4">Accessed November 13 2004. </s></p></note><p n="p5.19"><s n="s1.3;p5.19">Even in the official Resolution on Party History ultra left deviations were blamed and Mao's policies of "excessive targets, the issuing of arbitrary directions, boastfulness, and stirring up of a 'communist wind'"<ref target="BAWE_0244n-ftnote.004"/> are all identified as reasons for the failure of the GLF. It could be argued that if Mao had set more realistic targets within a larger time scale the GL may have enjoyed some success but instead he set huge targets mainly in grain and steel production. </s><s n="s2.3;p5.19">It was not only those who already worked in these areas who had to contribute, "Everyone had to meet a quota by handing over their metal possessions." </s><ref target="BAWE_0244n-ftnote.005"/><s n="s3.3;p5.19">Mao's megalomania meant that he refused to accept criticism and would not believe that his strategy was not working until it was too late to rectify the damage. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0244n-ftnote.004"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Joseph, "A Tragedy of Good Intentions." p. 431. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0244n-ftnote.005"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Becker, <hi rend="underlined">Hungry Ghosts</hi>. p. 63. </s></p></note><p n="p6.19"><s n="s1.4;p6.19">However it was not solely Mao who was responsible for these policies and ambitious targets, the entire leadership of the Party can have part of the blame attributed to them at least. </s><s n="s2.4;p6.19">The Party had been extremely successful up until the period of the GLF and maybe they could not envisage one of their policies completely failing in such a way. </s><s n="s3.4;p6.19">The "combination of inexperience and arrogance that it said to have characterized the leadership of the Chinese Communist Party"<ref target="BAWE_0244n-ftnote.006"/> could have led to the devastating impact that the GLF had on the Chinese people. </s><s n="s4.4;p6.19">This may have led the leadership into falling into Mao's train of thought where they let "their own revolutionary aspirations overwhelm their appreciation of the material and ideological constraints on what was possible to do at that point in time"<ref target="BAWE_0244n-ftnote.007"/>. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0244n-ftnote.006"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Joseph, "A Tragedy of Good Intentions." p. 424. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0244n-ftnote.007"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Joseph, "A Tragedy of Good Intentions." p. 433. </s></p></note><p n="p7.19"><s n="s1.4;p7.19">The leadership then, Mao included, were far too slow in realising how much the population were suffering from the GLF, predominantly because of their naïve view on the situation. </s><s n="s2.4;p7.19">In fact late in 1958 "the leaders did acknowledge that the GL had produced some disorganisation and problems; but they remained blind to the magnitude and nature of the difficulties that were developing"<ref target="BAWE_0244n-ftnote.008"/>. </s><s n="s3.4;p7.19">This may not have been true of the entire leadership however, there is evidence that some leaders were just too scared to stand up to Mao. </s><s n="s4.4;p7.19">Many were desperate to keep hold of their positions of power and knew that Mao would not react kindly to any criticism that was put his way. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0244n-ftnote.008"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.3;pn1.1">Lieberthal, K. </s><s n="s2.3;pn1.1">(1995) <hi rend="underlined">Governing China: From Revolution to Reform</hi>. </s><s n="s3.3;pn1.1">New York; London: W.W. Norton. p. 105. </s></p></note><p n="p8.19"><s n="s1.3;p8.19">One glaring example of this is Mao's treatment of the Minister of Defence, Marshall Peng Duhuai, who was one of the few people to report back to the Party that things were not actually as good as they appeared to be when he toured parts of the country in the autumn of 1958.<ref target="BAWE_0244n-ftnote.009"/> The result of this was that in the Lushan plenum in 1959, Peng and other supposed 'rightists' were purged and Mao sent a clear signal that criticism would not be tolerated. </s><s n="s2.3;p8.19">This one incident had a dramatic effect on the success of the GLF as it meant that a new upsurge in radicalism took place in 1959 and 1960 as "everyone was eager to demonstrate that they leaned to the 'left' instead of to the 'right'"<ref target="BAWE_0244n-ftnote.010"/>. </s><s n="s3.3;p8.19">This has led to the argument that if enough senior leaders had dared to stand up to Mao "the famine could easily have been arrested after the first year of the GLF"<ref target="BAWE_0244n-ftnote.011"/> and the number of people who died would have been greatly reduced. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0244n-ftnote.009"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Becker, <hi rend="underlined">Hungry Ghosts</hi>. p. 87. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0244n-ftnote.010"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Lieberthal, <hi rend="underlined">Governing China</hi>. p. 107. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0244n-ftnote.011"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Becker, <hi rend="underlined">Hungry Ghosts</hi>. p. 83. </s></p></note><p n="p9.19"><s n="s1.3;p9.19">This fear of voicing criticism was not just a problem at the senior leadership level but all the way down the ranks of the Party. </s><s n="s2.3;p9.19">There is evidence to suggest that "Most communes and industrial units falsified production figures to show that they were more 'red' than their neighbours.<ref target="BAWE_0244n-ftnote.012"/>" The fact that Mao even warned in the People's Daily that dissent would not be tolerated meant that people would rather face the consequences of food shortages and famine than those that they would face if they dared to speak the truth. </s><s n="s3.3;p9.19">On his travels across China in 1958 Mao "listened to reports designed to flatter him, which hailed the fantastic success in agriculture that he had wisely predicted"<ref target="BAWE_0244n-ftnote.013"/>. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0244n-ftnote.012"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.3;pn1.1">Saich, Tony. </s><s n="s2.3;pn1.1">(2001) <hi rend="underlined">Governance and Politics of China.</hi> </s><s n="s3.3;pn1.1">Basingstoke; London: Palgrave. p. 37. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0244n-ftnote.013"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Becker, <hi rend="underlined">Hungry Ghosts</hi>. p. 84. </s></p></note><p n="p10.19"><s n="s1.4;p10.19">One such report came from Anhui province where the man responsible for its terrible famine and its reforms "was a paunchy, aggressive former peasant called Zeng Xisheng"<ref target="BAWE_0244n-ftnote.014"/>. </s><s n="s2.4;p10.19">Mao hailed him as the perfect role model for other parts of China to look to and to try and produce similarly large amounts of grain and steel. </s><s n="s3.4;p10.19">The problem was that Zeng was using extreme methods to make these quotas and they could not possibly have enjoyed any long term success. </s><s n="s4.4;p10.19">He is thought to have locked local party secretaries locked up in rooms for weeks until they agreed that they would make the targets set in front of them.<ref target="BAWE_0244n-ftnote.015"/> This led to higher and more absurd grain targets being put forward and even greater successes being announced which in turn meant that Mao did not see any reason for halting the GLF and easing the suffering of the population. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0244n-ftnote.014"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Becker, <hi rend="underlined">Hungry Ghosts</hi>. p. 132. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0244n-ftnote.015"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Becker, <hi rend="underlined">Hungry Ghosts</hi>. p. 132-3. </s></p></note><p n="p11.19"><s n="s1.5;p11.19">Zeng also had an impact in another area where the GLF did not provide success; small, backyard furnaces. </s><s n="s2.5;p11.19">When Mao put forward huge targets for making steel, "Zeng showed this could be done not just in big furnaces but in every backyard"<ref target="BAWE_0244n-ftnote.016"/>. </s><s n="s3.5;p11.19">This idea just seemed to encourage the melting down of useful steel items in everyday life into lumps of steel which were rarely used for anything that actually improved China's economy or standard of living. </s><s n="s4.5;p11.19">In addition "Forests and any available rainforests were torn up to fuel the production of steel, most of which was useless"<ref target="BAWE_0244n-ftnote.017"/>, and the result was only to cause environmental damage. </s><s n="s5.5;p11.19">Even Mao himself later accepted responsibility for these small-scale blast furnaces and admitted they were one of the worst mistakes of the GLF. <ref target="BAWE_0244n-ftnote.018"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0244n-ftnote.016"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Becker, <hi rend="underlined">Hungry Ghosts</hi>. p. 132. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0244n-ftnote.017"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Saich, <hi rend="underlined">Governance and Politics.</hi> </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">p. 295. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0244n-ftnote.018"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.3;pn1.1">Gray, Jack. </s><s n="s2.3;pn1.1">(1990) <hi rend="underlined">Rebellions and Revolutions - China From the 1800's to the 1980's</hi>. </s><s n="s3.3;pn1.1">Oxford: Oxford University Press. p. 314. </s></p></note><p n="p12.19"><s n="s1.3;p12.19">A further consequence of officials at all levels exaggerating the number of targets they met was that they were enjoying a new found power and status which many had not experienced to such an extent before. </s><s n="s2.3;p12.19">Even when Mao finally realised that he needed to reverse the measures of the GL he found it very difficult "to convince those levels at provincial, municipal, county and commune levels, whose power and resources had grown enormously"<ref target="BAWE_0244n-ftnote.019"/>. </s><s n="s3.3;p12.19">An example of this is two early stalwarts of the Leap from Henan and Sichuan, Wu Zhipu and Li Jinquan, who "showed little inclination to pull back on their earlier positions<ref target="BAWE_0244n-ftnote.020"/>" as Mao tried to regain control of what he had unleashed. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0244n-ftnote.019"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.3;pn1.1">Lieberthal, K. </s><s n="s2.3;pn1.1">(1993) "The Great Leap Forward and the Split in the Yan'an Leadership", in Macfarquhar, R. (ed.) <hi rend="underlined">The Politics of China</hi>. </s><s n="s3.3;pn1.1">Cambridge: Cambridge University Press. p. 103. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0244n-ftnote.020"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Lieberthal, "The Great Leap Forward." p. 103. </s></p></note><p n="p13.19"><s n="s1.5;p13.19">Another important factor to consider during the GLF is the role of the Soviet Union. </s><s n="s2.5;p13.19">It was Stalin who launched the first five-year plan in 1928 and this was to be the model for many of Mao's policies in the GLF.<ref target="BAWE_0244n-ftnote.021"/> However the plan was not a huge success in Russia and the Russians even advised Mao not to repeat Stalin's mistakes and pointed out that China was much poorer than Russia had been in 1928. </s><s n="s3.5;p13.19">Mao did not take any of this on board though and his reluctance to listen to their advice even went so far as to cause the Sino-Soviet split in 1960 which did nothing to help China's economy. </s><s n="s4.5;p13.19">All Soviet technicians were removed from China and Russia cancelled their aid program which only exacerbated the shortages and poverty across China. </s><s n="s5.5;p13.19">This went some way to contributing to the fact that by the end of the GLF "roughly thirty million people, primarily the very young and the old, starved to death"<ref target="BAWE_0244n-ftnote.022"/>. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0244n-ftnote.021"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Becker, <hi rend="underlined">Hungry Ghosts</hi>. p. 55. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0244n-ftnote.022"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Lieberthal, <hi rend="underlined">Governing China.</hi> </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">p. 108. </s></p></note><p n="p14.19"><s n="s1.4;p14.19">Further influence from the Soviet Union came from Trofim Denisovich Lysenko who was a Soviet agronomist, and was the leader of the Soviet school of genetics that opposed Mendel's laws and maintained that acquired characteristics can be inherited. </s><s n="s2.4;p14.19">His theories received official support; they were taught in biology courses in the USSR and incorporated, with sometimes disastrous results, into Soviet agricultural programmes. </s><s n="s3.4;p14.19">China had their own Lysenkoist in the form of Luo Tianyo and in a purge of Party members in the 1942 rectification movement "Luo enthusiastically persecuted those who believed in genetics"<ref target="BAWE_0244n-ftnote.023"/>. </s><s n="s4.4;p14.19">It has been argued that Mao used this scientific reasoning for the GLF and that in 1958 "Mao personally drew up an eight-point Lysenkoist blueprint for all Chinese agriculture"<ref target="BAWE_0244n-ftnote.024"/>. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0244n-ftnote.023"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Becker, <hi rend="underlined">Hungry Ghosts</hi>. p. 69. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0244n-ftnote.024"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Becker, <hi rend="underlined">Hungry Ghosts</hi>. p. 70. </s></p></note><p n="p15.19"><s n="s1.4;p15.19">It was not simply scientific and economic issues which led to the failure of the GLF but socially the peasants resisted some of Mao's policies. </s><s n="s2.4;p15.19">"Many peasants resisted communal living and the confiscation of private plots"<ref target="BAWE_0244n-ftnote.025"/> and this was actually one of the first things that was rectified in the years following the GL where private plots were given back to the farmers. </s><s n="s3.4;p15.19">In addition there seems to have been a lack of competent personnel to administer the communes and the size of them proved to be a problem. </s><s n="s4.4;p15.19">The existence of communal places to eat, where theoretically one was allowed to eat as much as you liked, meant that none of the excess food was saved and when the leaders demanded sufficient food to feed the cities, neither the people in rural or urban areas had enough to eat. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0244n-ftnote.025"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Saich, <hi rend="underlined">Governance and Politics.</hi> </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">p. 37. </s></p></note><p n="p16.19"><s n="s1.3;p16.19">Furthermore Mao and the Party began to see the peasants as the enemy and not as a group that desperately needed help and freedom from the restrictions of the GLF. Party documents at the beginning of the GLF show that officials believed peasants to be standing in the way of progress and Mao even believed that the peasants were hiding their grain so he refused to open the state granaries to ease the crisis. </s><s n="s2.3;p16.19">To add to the situation "over the three years from 1958 China doubled her grain exports and cut her imports of food"<ref target="BAWE_0244n-ftnote.026"/>. </s><s n="s3.3;p16.19">Overall the rural sector was severely damaged by a host of policies "designed to subordinate agriculture to the drive for rapid industrial growth"<ref target="BAWE_0244n-ftnote.027"/>. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0244n-ftnote.026"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Becker, <hi rend="underlined">Hungry Ghosts.</hi> </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">p. 81. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0244n-ftnote.027"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Joseph, "A Tragedy of Good Intentions." p. 434. </s></p></note><p n="p17.19"><s n="s1.3;p17.19">Even if the Party had acted more quickly as the failure of the GLF policies began to emerge they still would have faced major difficulties due to the state planned structure of the Chinese economy not being able to cope or adapt to the situation. </s><s n="s2.3;p17.19">The GLF put unbearable pressure on the poorly developed transport system, "thus inducing bottlenecks and the overstocking of goods at critical transit points"<ref target="BAWE_0244n-ftnote.028"/>. </s><s n="s3.3;p17.19">This imbalance within the structure of the national economy, combined with inevitable bottlenecks meant that "stoppages in production occurred and many enterprises overextended their productive capacity"<ref target="BAWE_0244n-ftnote.029"/>. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0244n-ftnote.028"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Joseph, "A Tragedy of Good Intentions." p. 436. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0244n-ftnote.029"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Saich, <hi rend="underlined">Governance and Politics.</hi> </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">p. 37. </s></p></note><p n="p18.19"><s n="s1.3;p18.19">In addition, during the years of the GLF, China was further disadvantaged by poor harvests as a result of bad weather. </s><s n="s2.3;p18.19">The "summer harvest of 1959 was poor, and the harvests of 1960 were disastrous" with one third of China's arable stricken with drought and another sixth being flooded.<ref target="BAWE_0244n-ftnote.030"/> These natural difficulties most probably had an effect on the huge urban population growth from 1958<ref target="BAWE_0244n-ftnote.031"/> which in turn made food shortages even more acute. </s><s n="s3.3;p18.19">So aside from Mao's insatiable ambition and the Party's co-operation with such extreme policies it is also necessary to consider that drought, flood and Soviet betrayal may have complicated the situation. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0244n-ftnote.030"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Gray, <hi rend="underlined">Rebellions and Revolutions.</hi> </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">p. 315. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0244n-ftnote.031"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Lieberthal, "The Great Leap Forward." p. 102. </s></p></note><p n="p19.19"><s n="s1.3;p19.19">However Mao was the dominating figure who was determined to go through with the GLF and without his strong desire to beat the West and prove that Socialism could provide a stronger economy than capitalism then the GL would not have been such a tragedy. </s><s n="s2.3;p19.19">If you take the role of the leadership as well (and the record makes clear that Liu Shaoqi, Deng Xiaoping, and most other leaders supported the GLF wholeheartedly throughout<ref target="BAWE_0244n-ftnote.032"/>) then it was inevitable that the GLF was to be a terrible failure. </s><s n="s3.3;p19.19">The poor harvests and natural circumstances only served to deepen the crisis which was already occurring due to the unrealistic targets for grain and steel and unwillingness of the Party to accept criticism even when they realised that it was not going according to plan. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0244n-ftnote.032"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Lieberthal, "The Great Leap Forward." p. 99. </s></p></note></div1></body><back><div1 type="bibliography"><head rend="underlined">Bibliography</head><p>Becker, Jasper. (1999) <hi rend="underlined">Hungry Ghosts: China's Secret Famine</hi>. London: John Murray.</p><p>Gray, Jack. (1990) <hi rend="underlined">Rebellions and Revolutions - China From the 1800's to the 1980's</hi>. Oxford: Oxford University Press.</p><p>Joseph, William A. "A Tragedy of Good Intentions: Post Mao Views of the Great Leap Forward" <hi rend="underlined">Modern China</hi>, Vol. 12, No. 4. (Oct., 1986), </p><p><seg type="URL" n="http://links.jstor.org/sici?sici=0097-7004%28198610%2912%3A4%3C419%3AATOGIP%3E2.0.CO%3B"/></p><p>2-2. Accessed November 13 2004.</p><p>Lieberthal, K. (1995) <hi rend="underlined">Governing China: From Revolution to Reform</hi>. New York; London: W.W. Norton.</p><p>Lieberthal, K. (1993) "The Great Leap Forward and the Split in the Yan'an Leadership", in Macfarquhar, R. (ed.) <hi rend="underlined">The Politics of China</hi>. Cambridge: Cambridge University Press.</p><p>Saich, Tony. (2001) <hi rend="underlined">Governance and Politics of China.</hi> Basingstoke; London: Palgrave.</p><p>Teiwes, Frederick C. (1979) <hi rend="underlined">Politics and Purges in China.</hi> White Plains; Folkestone: Sharpe: Dawson.</p></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
