<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_0245i" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Rash Patient Portfolio</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">proforma</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">4</p><p n="date">2005-09</p><p n="module title">Other Rotations</p><p n="module code">unknown</p><p n="genre family">Case study</p><p n="discipline">Medicine</p><p n="disciplinary group">LS</p><p n="grade">D</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">4074</p><p n="number of s-units">232</p><p n="number of p">118</p><p n="number of tables">3</p><p n="number of figures">0</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">9</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">37</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">17.6</p><p n="average s-units per p">2.0</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">f</p><p n="year of birth">1980</p><p n="first language">English</p><p n="education">UKA</p><p n="course">Medicine</p><p n="student ID">0245</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><docTitle><titlePart><hi rend="bold">PORTFOLIO CASE No:</hi> 15</titlePart></docTitle><titlePart>Patient Initials<name type="other"/> Hospital Number<name type="other"/> Age 68 Gender Female</titlePart><titlePart>Portfolio Case presentation number: Phase 2 course document objectives(s) Has the patient' permission, including for follow up contact by telephone, been sought and recorded in the case notes? Yes</titlePart></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="bold">Referral information</hi> Source of referral and a summary of key information</head><p n="p1.118"><s n="s1.3;p1.118"><name type="other"/> presented at A + E on the <name type="date"/> with symptoms of increasing shortness of breath. </s><s n="s2.3;p1.118">She had been feeling 'unwell' for the few days prior to presentation. </s><s n="s3.3;p1.118">She has a longstanding history of asthma; her current dyspnoea was however unresponsive to the regular inhalers and nebulisers she uses at home. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="bold">History</hi> All <hi rend="bold italic">relevant</hi> information gathered from the patient about the presenting illness, co-existing problems, current treatment, significant past medical history and the social and family background. The patient's view of the nature of the problem and their expectations for treatment. </head><div2><head rend="underlined bold">Presenting Complaint. </head><list type="bulleted"><item>Increasing shortness of breath.</item><item>Generally feeling 'unwell' for the few days prior to presentation</item><item>Cough</item></list><p n="p2.118"/></div2><div2><head rend="underlined bold">History of Presenting Complaint. </head><p n="p3.118"><s n="s1.5;p3.118"><name type="other"/> had progressively worsening shortness of breath and wheezing in the 2-3 days prior to presentation at A+E. Dyspnoea was at its worst last night (<name type="date"/>) so that by presentation at A+E at 4am on the <name type="date"/> she was gasping for breath. </s><s n="s2.5;p3.118">Dyspnoea was described as 'not being able to catch my breath, I was gasping' with associated chest tightness. </s><s n="s3.5;p3.118">This presenting episode of dyspnoea came on suddenly on the <name type="date"/> and has progressed in severity since. </s><s n="s4.5;p3.118">It was variable in nature i.e. 'came and went' limiting her ability to manage the single flight of stairs in her home and to generally move around the house. </s><s n="s5.5;p3.118">Her dyspnoea was unresponsive to either her regular nebulised or inhaled medication but was said to improve following administration of salbutamol 5mg, atrovent 500mg and IV hydrocortisone 200g in A+E. </s></p><p n="p4.118"><s n="s1.10;p4.118">Despite having had asthma for 37 years, her exercise tolerance is usually reasonable. </s><s n="s2.10;p4.118">She regularly uses a nebuliser and is usually able to manage stairs at home without any difficulty. </s><s n="s3.10;p4.118">Over the past few days prior to admission she has experienced progressive difficulty managing this same flight of stairs. </s><s n="s4.10;p4.118">Her breathlessness also has impaired her ability to dress and wash herself. </s><s n="s5.10;p4.118">Her dyspnoea was exacerbated by physical exertion, emotional upset or stress. </s><s n="s6.10;p4.118">She generally has reasonable control of her asthma. </s><s n="s7.10;p4.118">Her last asthma attack requiring hospitalisation was in <name type="date"/>. </s><s n="s8.10;p4.118">Her asthma is worst in the mornings on waking and this has been especially so over the last week. </s><s n="s9.10;p4.118">To 'get going' in the mornings she had to take her 'drugs' on waking and then wait about half an hour until she felt sufficiently less breathless to get up and walk. </s><s n="s10.10;p4.118">This was unachievable on the 2 days prior to admission. </s></p><p n="p5.118"><s n="s1.7;p5.118">Cigarette smoke, aerosol sprays, cats and dogs exacerbate her asthma. </s><s n="s2.7;p5.118">She becomes wheezier when she is ill with a cold or similar and wonders if her current cough is associated with her breathlessness. </s><s n="s3.7;p5.118">She has not yet had a flu vaccination this year. </s><s n="s4.7;p5.118">Her chest has over the 3 days prior to admission woken her at night when she was aware of being 'breathy and gasping for breath'. </s><s n="s5.7;p5.118">This is however, not a regular occurrence. </s><s n="s6.7;p5.118">She sleeps currently with a single pillow and has done for many years. </s><s n="s7.7;p5.118">Breathlessness at night was relieved slightly using her inhaler and reading (relaxing). </s></p><p n="p6.118"><s n="s1.6;p6.118">Associated with her progressive breathlessness was a cough. </s><s n="s2.6;p6.118">She was unable to catch her breath sufficiently to be able to cough up much in the way of secretions. </s><s n="s3.6;p6.118">What was brought up was cloudy in colour. </s><s n="s4.6;p6.118">There was no associated pain, phlegm, haemoptysis, nausea, vomiting or sweating. </s><s n="s5.6;p6.118">She complained of feeling 'unwell' in the 2 days prior to admission describing feelings of fatigue, headache and 'generally not feeling herself'. </s><s n="s6.6;p6.118">She was also currently aware of her hands shaking. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined bold">Systems Review: </head><p n="p7.118"><s n="s1.2;p7.118">No other significant signs or symptoms associated with other major systems. </s><s n="s2.2;p7.118">No recent change in weight or appetite, she has no difficulty swallowing. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined bold">Past Medical and Surgical History. </head><list type="bulleted"><item>Asthma - 37 year history</item><item>Osteoporosis - 10 year history</item><item>Gastro-oesophageal reflux - longstanding history</item><item>Repeated cystitis</item><item>'Operation' to the right hand, details not provided - 2000</item></list><p n="p8.118"><s n="s1.1;p8.118">No history of other respiratory disease such as rheumatic fever, chronic bronchitis, TB or COPD. No hypertension, diabetes, ischaemic heart disease (MI/angina), jaundice, arthritis, cancer, stroke, hypercholesterolaemia. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined bold">Medication. </head><p rend="bulleted" n="p9.118"><s n="s1.2;p9.118">Montelukast 10mg - leukotriene receptor antagonist block the effects of cysteinyl leukotrienes in the airways. </s><s n="s2.2;p9.118">Effective in asthma when used alone or with an inhaled corticosteroid. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p10.118"><s n="s1.1;p10.118">Paracetamol 500mg QDS - non-opioid analgesic. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p11.118"><s n="s1.1;p11.118">Prednisolone 5mg - glucocorticoid, for suppression of inflammatory and allergic disorders. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p12.118"><s n="s1.1;p12.118">Rabeprazole 10mg OD - proton pump inhibitor, inhibits gastric acid by blocking the hydrogen-potassium adenosine triphosphatase enzyme system of the gastric parietal cell. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p13.118"><s n="s1.1;p13.118">Salbutamol (nebuliser) 100mg per puff, 2 puff QDS - selective short-acting B <hi rend="sub">2</hi> agonist. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p14.118"><s n="s1.1;p14.118">Salmetorol xinafoate aerosol 25 BD - longer acting B <hi rend="sub">2</hi> agonist. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p15.118"><s n="s1.2;p15.118">Zolpidem tartrate 5mg - non benzodiazepine hypnotic acting at the benzodiazepine receptor. </s><s n="s2.2;p15.118">Used in the management of insomnia. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p16.118"><s n="s1.1;p16.118">Adcal 1.5g - calcium carbonate. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p17.118"><s n="s1.1;p17.118">Alendronic acid 70mg x1 weekly - bisphosphonate, absorbed onto hydroxyapatite crystals in bone slowing their rate of growth and dissolution therefore reducing rate of bone turnover. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p18.118"><s n="s1.1;p18.118">Fluticasone propionate nasal spray - prophylaxis of asthma. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p19.118"><s n="s1.1;p19.118">Ipratropium bromide nebuliser 500ug/2ml - antimuscarinic bronchodilator, provides short-term relief in chronic asthma. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p20.118"><s n="s1.2;p20.118">Loratidine tab. </s><s n="s2.2;p20.118">10mg - antihistamine, symptomatic relief of allergy e.g. hayfever. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined bold">Allergies: </head><p n="p21.118"><s n="s1.1;p21.118">Aspirin, Ibuprofen and Non-steroidal anti-inflammatories. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined bold">Family History: </head><p n="p22.118"><s n="s1.3;p22.118">No known significant family history. </s><s n="s2.3;p22.118">Both parents died at 'a good age', the mother had Parkinson's disease, the father a stroke. </s><s n="s3.3;p22.118">She has 2 children both of whom are also severely asthmatic. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined bold">Social History: </head><p n="p23.118"><s n="s1.7;p23.118"><name type="other"/> lives with her husband in <name type="other"/>, <name type="other"/>. </s><s n="s2.7;p23.118">She is fully independent and describes her quality of life as "good". </s><s n="s3.7;p23.118">She has 2 adult children and is retired having been a housewife for many years. </s><s n="s4.7;p23.118">She has some paid help with cleaning the house but otherwise is independent around the house when well. </s><s n="s5.7;p23.118">She requires assistance washing and dressing when particularly wheezy or when recovering from an asthma attack and will continue to receive this from her husband on discharge. </s><s n="s6.7;p23.118">She has never owned pets. </s><s n="s7.7;p23.118">She is a non-smoker and drinks no alcohol. </s></p><p n="p24.118"><s n="s1.2;p24.118">She thought herself that this was an exacerbation of the longstanding asthma, which she experiences. </s><s n="s2.2;p24.118">She was anxious to become less breathless so that she may feel more comfortable and was keen to return home as rapidly as possible. </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="bold">Analysis of history</hi> The most likely single cause of the presentation, other possible causes and reasons for these choices. The findings to be looked for on physical examination to help decide the cause.</head><p n="p25.118"><s n="s1.2;p25.118">Given <name type="other"/>'s long-standing history of asthma, the most likely cause of her current presenting symptoms is an acute exacerbation of her asthma. </s><s n="s2.2;p25.118">Dyspnoea was relatively acute in onset and variable in nature ruling out obstructive causes such as malignancy. </s></p><p n="p26.118"><s n="s1.1;p26.118">Asthma is a common inflammatory condition of the airways, characterised by 3 pathological processes: </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p27.118"><s n="s1.1;p27.118">airflow limitation - usually reversible spontaneously or with treatment </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p28.118"><s n="s1.1;p28.118">airway hyperresponsiveness - to a wide range of stimuli e.g. cold air, exercise, emotions. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p29.118"><s n="s1.1;p29.118">bronchial inflammation - involves mast cells, eosinophils, macrophages and lymphocytes. </s></p><p n="p30.118"><s n="s1.3;p30.118">Inflammation results in remodelling of both bronchiolar structure and function. </s><s n="s2.3;p30.118">This remodelling in addition to alteration in smooth muscle contractility causes bronchial hyperresponsivity. </s><s n="s3.3;p30.118">Remodelling is achieved by a number of factors, (i) epithelium of conducting airways is damaged with loss of ciliated columnar cells onto the lumen, (ii) thickened basement membrane, (iii) hyperplasia of the helical bands of airways smooth muscle, (iv) central and peripheral neural reflexes contribute to enhancing airway irritability. </s></p><p n="p31.118"><s n="s1.4;p31.118">Symptoms, which may be found, include cough, wheeze, chest tightness and shortness of breath. <name type="other"/> presents with all these. </s><s n="s2.4;p31.118">Her asthma is on occasions worse at night as can often be the case. </s><s n="s3.4;p31.118">Asthmatic individuals may demonstrate symptoms of airflow limitation almost identical to those of COPD. These are cough, wheeze, breathlessness and tachypnoea. </s><s n="s4.4;p31.118">Dyspnoea in asthma is typically intermittent and variable in nature, which contrasts with the constant dyspnoea seen in COPD. Findings to be looked for on physical examination include tachypnoea, an audible wheeze, hyperinflated chest, hyperresonant percussion, decreased air entry and widespread, polyphonic wheeze. </s></p><p n="p32.118"><s n="s1.1;p32.118">Differential diagnosis for <name type="other"/>'s dyspnoea: </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p33.118"><s n="s1.2;p33.118">Pulmonary oedema - unlikely as although presents with acute dyspnoea and wheezing does not have a cough producing characteristic frothy, blood tinged sputum. </s><s n="s2.2;p33.118">There is no indication of peripheral circulatory shutdown from the history either. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p34.118"><s n="s1.1;p34.118">Large airway obstruction e.g. tumour - unlikely, dyspnoea had relatively acute onset and variable nature. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p35.118"><s n="s1.2;p35.118">Pneumothorax - does present with progressively increasing breathlessness as here but there is no associated unilateral pleuritic pain as would be expected. </s><s n="s2.2;p35.118">Look for tracheal and mediastinal shift. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p36.118"><s n="s1.1;p36.118">Superior vena cava obstruction - unlikely no indication of venous congestion or stridor. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p37.118"><s n="s1.2;p37.118">Bronchiectasis - no production of yellow/green sputum. </s><s n="s2.2;p37.118">Does present with malaise however. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="bold">Physical and mental state examination</hi> Highlight the findings most relevant to your clinical problem solving by underlining them</head><p n="p38.118"><s n="s1.4;p38.118">An elderly lady who appeared comfortable when sitting and non-septic. </s><s n="s2.4;p38.118">She was not obviously jaundiced. </s><s n="s3.4;p38.118">She was cannulated, had a nasal cannula in situ and a nebuliser at her bedside. <name type="other"/> was fully conscious, cooperative and was able to talk expressively and freely at the time of interview. </s><s n="s4.4;p38.118">She had however, been unable to complete sentences whilst in A+E and subsequently MAU. </s></p><div2><head rend="underlined bold">General. </head><div3><head rend="underlined bold">Hands. </head><p n="p39.118"><s n="s1.1;p39.118"><hi rend="underlined">Peripheral cyanosis</hi>. </s></p><p n="p40.118"><s n="s1.2;p40.118">No pale palmar creases, palmer erythema, clubbing, cyanosis, leukonychia, Dupuytren's contracture, kolonychia, liver flap. </s><s n="s2.2;p40.118"><hi rend="bold">Fine observable tremor of hands</hi>. </s></p></div3><div3><head rend="underlined bold">Face. </head><p n="p41.118"><s n="s1.1;p41.118">No pale palpebral conjunctivae or signs of jaundice (icteus) or cyanosis. </s></p></div3><div3><head rend="underlined bold">Neck. </head><p n="p42.118"><s n="s1.1;p42.118">No lymphadenopathy. </s></p><p n="p43.118"><s n="s1.1;p43.118">Temperature - 37.7ºC: presence of current systemic infection. </s></p></div3></div2><div2><head rend="underlined bold">Respiratory system. </head><p n="p44.118"><s n="s1.1;p44.118"><hi rend="bold">Respiratory rate 32/min</hi> - Tachypnoea </s></p><p n="p45.118"><s n="s1.1;p45.118">Oxygen saturation 95% on air </s></p><p n="p46.118"><s n="s1.1;p46.118"><hi rend="bold">Peak flow 100-150ml</hi> (normal 280-300) - approximate 33.3% decrease </s></p><p n="p47.118"><s rend="bold" n="s1.1;p47.118">Decreased depth of breathing but rate is regular </s></p><p n="p48.118"><s n="s1.1;p48.118"><hi rend="bold">Cough</hi> - chesty, no observed sputum production </s></p><p n="p49.118"><s n="s1.1;p49.118">No tracheal deviation - rules out pneumothorax, No crackles, stridor or pleural rub </s></p><p n="p50.118"><s n="s1.1;p50.118">Equal chest expansion but <hi rend="bold">expansion is limited</hi>, chest hardly moves </s></p><p n="p51.118"><s rend="bold" n="s1.1;p51.118">Hyperinflation of chest </s></p><p n="p52.118"><s rend="bold" n="s1.1;p52.118">Prolonged expiration </s></p><p n="p53.118"><s n="s1.1;p53.118">Resonant percussion - absence of consolidation, fibrosis or pleural fluid </s></p><p n="p54.118"><s rend="bold" n="s1.1;p54.118">Decreased vesicular breath sounds </s></p><p n="p55.118"><s n="s1.1;p55.118"><hi rend="bold">No use of accessory muscles -</hi> gauge of severity of respiratory distress </s></p><p n="p56.118"><s n="s1.1;p56.118">Normal vocal fremitus and vocal resonance </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined bold">Cardiovascular system. </head><p n="p57.118"><s n="s1.1;p57.118">No Peripheral or central cyanosis </s></p><p n="p58.118"><s n="s1.1;p58.118">Mild ankle oedema </s></p><p n="p59.118"><s n="s1.1;p59.118"><hi rend="underlined bold">Pulse 128bpm</hi> - tachycardia associated acute exacerbation of asthma, contribution by ?concomitant infection, Blood pressure 160/80 </s></p><p n="p60.118"><s n="s1.1;p60.118">Radial pulse palpable, regular, radial and carotid pulses normal strength </s></p><p n="p61.118"><s n="s1.1;p61.118">All other peripheral pulses palpable </s></p><p n="p62.118"><s n="s1.1;p62.118">JVP normal </s></p><p n="p63.118"><s n="s1.1;p63.118">Heart sounds I and II normal </s></p><p n="p64.118"><s n="s1.1;p64.118">No murmurs or displacement of the apex beat. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined bold">Abdomen. </head><p n="p65.118"><s n="s1.1;p65.118">Symmetrical </s></p><p n="p66.118"><s n="s1.1;p66.118">No spider naevi, caput medusa, obvious abdominal distension, hepatomegaly </s></p><p n="p67.118"><s n="s1.1;p67.118">Spleen, kidneys and bladder impalpable </s></p><p n="p68.118"><s n="s1.1;p68.118">No renal angle tenderness - infection unlikely, No ascites, shifting dullness, palpable masses </s></p><p n="p69.118"><s n="s1.1;p69.118">Abdomen soft and non-tender on palpation, percussion resonant, normal bowel sounds </s></p><p n="p70.118"><s n="s1.1;p70.118">A PR exam was not performed at the time of examination, as supervision was unavailable </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="bold">Analysis of history and examination</hi> Reasons for your choice of the cause of the patient's problem(s) and any other cause that still needs to be considered at this stage</head><p n="p71.118"><s n="s1.2;p71.118"><hi rend="bold">Acute exacerbation of Chronic Asthma</hi>. </s><s n="s2.2;p71.118">Findings on examination that support this diagnosis are: </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p72.118"><s rend="bold" n="s1.1;p72.118">Tachypnoea - respiratory rate > 25 breaths per minute </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p73.118"><s rend="bold" n="s1.1;p73.118">Tachycardia - > 110 bpm </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p74.118"><s rend="bold" n="s1.1;p74.118">PEFR &lt; 50% of predicted normal or best </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p75.118"><s rend="bold" n="s1.1;p75.118">Inability to complete sentences on presentation at A+E </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p76.118"><s n="s1.2;p76.118">An audible wheeze, hyperinflated chest and decreased air entry. </s><s n="s2.2;p76.118">Hyperinflation of the chest is seen in states of chronic airflow limitation such as chronic asthma. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p77.118"><s n="s1.1;p77.118">Absence of cyanosis at presentation at A+E - important as cyanosis is a feature of a life-threatening attack. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p78.118"><s n="s1.1;p78.118">Her dyspnoea was acute in onset and then worsened progressively in severity. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p79.118"><s n="s1.1;p79.118">Dyspnoea was variable in nature. </s></p><p n="p80.118"><s n="s1.5;p80.118">The presenting cough is a frequent symptom associated with asthma. </s><s n="s2.5;p80.118">It can commonly be misdiagnosed as bronchitis, careful investigation is required for clarification. </s><s n="s3.5;p80.118">The tremor observed in the patient's hands and fingers is most likely caused by stimulation of β receptors in skeletal muscle by bronchodilator drugs e.g. </s><s n="s4.5;p80.118">Salbutamol. </s><s n="s5.5;p80.118">It can be distinguished from CO <hi rend="sub">2</hi> retention as found in chronic airflow limitation by absence of warm peripheries, bounding pulses or headache. </s></p><p n="p81.118"><s n="s1.4;p81.118">Asthma can be divided into extrinsic (atopic) or intrinsic types. </s><s n="s2.4;p81.118">Asthma is an atopic disorder, which may run in families as is the case for <name type="other"/>. </s><s n="s3.4;p81.118">Atopic individuals (30-40% of the UK population) have IgE antibodies against common environmental materials. </s><s n="s4.4;p81.118">Association between serum IgE level, prevalence of asthma and airway responsiveness to histamine and methacholine has been shown. </s></p><p n="p82.118"><s n="s1.1;p82.118">Inhalation of an allergen in an atopic individual such as <name type="other"/>, compounded by a possible concomitant respiratory infection will have led to the following reactive process. </s></p><p n="p83.118"><s n="s1.1;p83.118"><hi rend="bold">Immediate asthma</hi> (early reaction) - airflow limitation occurs within minutes of exposure, reaches max. within 15-20 minutes and can subside within an hour. </s></p><p n="p84.118"><s n="s1.1;p84.118">↓ </s></p><p n="p85.118"><s n="s1.1;p85.118"><hi rend="bold">Late phase reaction</hi> - <name type="other"/> developed a more prolonged and sustained airflow limitation which was unresponsive to her regular bronchodilator medication </s></p><p n="p86.118"><s n="s1.1;p86.118">↓ </s></p><p n="p87.118"><s n="s1.1;p87.118">Late phase reaction associated with increase in airway hyperreactivity causing <name type="other"/> to experience episodes of asthma on subsequent days as seen. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="bold">Formulation of the patient's problem(s)</hi> Encapsulate this in physical, psychological and social terms (the triple diagnosis)</head><p n="p88.118"><s n="s1.3;p88.118"><hi rend="underlined">Physical</hi>-: <name type="other"/> suffers with chronic asthma, which presents with acute episodes several times a year. </s><s n="s2.3;p88.118">She is terrified by her attacks as she cannot control when they will happen, their duration and resolution and indeed has no indication at all of when an attack is imminent. <name type="other"/> has had to come to terms with losing some of her physical independence, as she is unable to walk far when particularly wheezy. </s><s n="s3.3;p88.118">She also has osteoporosis and is concerned that she may incur fractures with little or no precipitating trauma. </s></p><p n="p89.118"><s n="s1.1;p89.118"><hi rend="underlined">Psychological</hi>-: She is highly intelligent and expressive and finds it hard to accept her current physical ability and independence do not match her level of mental independence. </s></p><p n="p90.118"><s n="s1.1;p90.118"><hi rend="underlined">Social</hi>-: She has extensive social input from family and maintains contact with some local friends. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="bold">Management</hi> Use the framework of RAPRIOP to structure your proposed management. Refer to the guidelines to the writing of portfolio cases for the details of the issues to be addressed under each heading.</head><div2><head rend="bold">Investigations</head><table id="BAWE_0245i-tab.001"><head rend="underlined bold">FBC - on admission <name type="date"/>. </head><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p91.118"><s n="s1.2;p91.118">The raised D-dimer does warrant further investigation with doppler ultrasound to exclude deep vein thrombosis as a cause for the presenting symptoms. </s><s n="s2.2;p91.118">Various factors including respiratory infection may contribute however, to raise D-dimer level. </s></p><table id="BAWE_0245i-tab.002"><head rend="underlined bold">Biochemistry - results obtained <name type="date"/>. </head><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p92.118"><s n="s1.2;p92.118">Raised CRP indicates presence of systemic infection. </s><s n="s2.2;p92.118">LFT results were all within the normal range. </s></p><table id="BAWE_0245i-tab.003"><head rend="underlined bold">Arterial blood gases. </head><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p93.118"><s n="s1.5;p93.118">A respiratory alkalosis caused by <name type="other"/>'s hyperventilation is indicated. </s><s n="s2.5;p93.118">Removal of CO <hi rend="sub">2</hi> from the body is excessive, decreasing arterial pCO <hi rend="sub">2</hi> below 5.3kPa. </s><s n="s3.5;p93.118">This leads to both a decrease in [H+] and [HCO <hi rend="sub">3</hi>]. </s><s n="s4.5;p93.118">The decreased pCO <hi rend="sub">2</hi> and [H+] in renal tubule cells reduces rate of H+ secretion; so that although plasma [HCO <hi rend="sub">3</hi>] is reduced thus reducing the amount filtered by the kidney; rate of H+ secretion is insufficient to reabsorb all the filtered bicarbonate. </s><s n="s5.5;p93.118">HCO <hi rend="sub">3</hi> is therefore excreted in the urine and plasma [HCO <hi rend="sub">3</hi>] falls further. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p94.118"><s n="s1.4;p94.118"><hi rend="bold">Chest X-ray</hi> (PA view) <name type="date"/> - evidence of old rib fracture. </s><s n="s2.4;p94.118">Thickened pleura. </s><s n="s3.4;p94.118">No consolidation seen ruling out pneumonia. </s><s n="s4.4;p94.118"><hi rend="bold">No evidence of pneumothorax</hi>. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p95.118"><s n="s1.1;p95.118"><hi rend="bold">ECG </hi><name type="date"/> - sinus tachycardia. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p96.118"><s n="s1.1;p96.118"><hi rend="bold">Sputum tests</hi> - look for raised eosinophils. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold italic">Reassurance and explanation</head><p n="p97.118"><s n="s1.7;p97.118">The breathlessness you are currently experiencing is due to an acute exacerbation of your asthma. </s><s n="s2.7;p97.118">Your asthma attack bringing you to hospital this time may well have been triggered by a chest infection, which you have picked up, and we will treat this whilst you are an inpatient. </s><s n="s3.7;p97.118">Whilst in hospital we will look at and perhaps modify your medication in order to optimise control of your asthma for the winter. </s><s n="s4.7;p97.118">The chest physicians will then continue your care on hospital discharge. </s><s n="s5.7;p97.118">By decreasing your breathlessness, we aim to significantly improve your mobility and level of independence. </s><s n="s6.7;p97.118">We will consider discharge when your breathlessness is reduced, your peak flow is back to your normal levels and your cough has gone. </s><s n="s7.7;p97.118">If you should have any questions whilst in hospital please don't hesitate to ask. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">Prescription/medical intervention</head><list type="bulleted"><head rend="underlined bold">In A+E:</head><item>Salbutamol 5mg (oral)</item><item>Atrovent 250ug - Ipratropium bromide (nebulised), antimuscarinic bronchodilator</item><item>Hydrocortisone 200g IV - administer 4-hourly for 24 hours.</item><item>Salbutamol 2.5mg (nebulised)</item><item>Nuelin SA 175mg - theophylline, bronchodilator</item></list><list type="bulleted"><head rend="underlined bold">Plan, commenced on the <name type="date"/>:</head><item>To increase prednisolone to 40 mg from 20mg, given orally daily</item><item>Amoxicillin 500mg PO - penicillin based antibiotic</item><item>Aminophylline 200mg - stable mixture of theophylline and ethylenediamine for management of acute severe asthma. Measurement of plasma theophylline concentration is essential if have been taking theophylline in addition as it has a very <hi rend="bold">narrow therapeutic index</hi>. A plasma concentration of 10-20mg/L is required for satisfactory bronchodilation however, adverse effects can also occur within this range. </item><item>Continue nebulised medications PRN</item><item>Review by respiratory team</item></list><list type="bulleted"><head rend="underlined bold"><name type="date"/>:</head><item>Continued cough, no improvement in peak flow (150L), widespread bilateral rhonchi on auscultation</item><item>Swop from oral to IV Aminophylline 25mg/mL</item><item>Increase prednisolone to 60mg</item></list><list type="bulleted"><head rend="underlined bold"><name type="date"/>:</head><item>Peak flow 150 L</item><item>No sputum produced, noisy breathing, feeling better than when first came in, CRP of 8 indicating resolution of infection</item><item>Saline nebs, to lift phlegm</item><item>Cough, breathless on exertion, wheezes</item><item>Theophylline 200mg PO, plasma [theophylline] 10.9 mg/L</item><item>Continue all other treatment until peak flow increases</item></list><p n="p98.118"/></div2><div2><head rend="bold italic">Observation</head><p n="p99.118"><s n="s1.8;p99.118"><name type="other"/> should be monitored closely in a general medical ward for exacerbation of her condition. </s><s n="s2.8;p99.118">Features of a life-threatening asthma attack are silent chest, cyanosis, exhaustion, confusion or coma, bradycardia or hypotension and a PEFR &lt; 30% of the predicted normal or best approx. </s><s n="s3.8;p99.118">150L in adults. </s><s n="s4.8;p99.118">She is reasonably nourished and hydrated and unlikely to require supplementation during her hospital stay. </s><s n="s5.8;p99.118">She should ideally be kept in hospital for a minimum of 5 days as the majority of deaths occur 2-5 days after admission. </s><s n="s6.8;p99.118">Regular oxygen saturation should be monitored by oximetry. </s><s n="s7.8;p99.118">Reduction in prednisolone should be performed gradually with substitution by an inhaled corticosteroid preparation. </s><s n="s8.8;p99.118">A synthaxin test may be required on steroid withdrawal to assess adrenal function. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">Referral and team working</head><list type="bulleted"><item>Respiratory and general physicians</item><item>Asthma nurse and clinic services</item><item>GP - follow up care and support on hospital discharge</item></list><p n="p100.118"/></div2><div2><head rend="bold">Advice and Prevention</head><p rend="bulleted" n="p101.118"><s n="s1.1;p101.118">Reduce allergens in home - wash bedding and carpets regularly to avoid dust mites </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p102.118"><s n="s1.1;p102.118">Humidifier at home </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p103.118"><s n="s1.1;p103.118">Avoid contact with pets </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p104.118"><s n="s1.1;p104.118">Increase consumption of dairy products, calcium rich foods e.g. spinach </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p105.118"><s n="s1.1;p105.118">Mild weight bearing exercise when asthma permits </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p106.118"><s n="s1.1;p106.118">Hip protectors/Good shoes and slippers to minimise likelihood of falls </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="bold">Outcome</hi> A description of the progress of the patient as far as possible. This should include consideration of further issues to be resolved. Where appropriate you should contact by telephone patients who have been discharged home.</head><p n="p107.118"><s n="s1.6;p107.118">Peak expiratory flow rate (PEFR) on the <name type="date"/> was 150L; still below her normal range of 250-300L. Peak flow rate varies considerably between individuals with sex, age and height. </s><s n="s2.6;p107.118">PEFR measures expiratory flow in the first 2ms of expiration only, overestimating lung function in individuals with moderate airflow limitation. </s><s n="s3.6;p107.118">PEFR is best used therefore to monitor disease progression and its treatment rather than airflow limitation. </s><s n="s4.6;p107.118">Clearly, peak flow needs to be restored towards her normal levels prior to discharge to optimise prognosis. </s><s n="s5.6;p107.118">At the ward round on the same day, she was comfortable and feeling 'better than when she first came in'. </s><s n="s6.6;p107.118">CRP was less than 10mg/L indicating resolution of infection. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="bold">Evidence based care and issues for research</hi> A brief consideration of the evidence base required for the diagnosis and management of the patient's problem(s)</head><p n="p108.118"><s n="s1.4;p108.118">The evidence base for the management of asthma is vast. </s><s n="s2.4;p108.118">As <name type="other"/> is presenting with an acute exacerbation of her asthma, I have chosen to focus as such on this aspect here. </s><s n="s3.4;p108.118">Aims of treatment for <name type="other"/> are to (i) minimise or eliminate symptoms, (ii) maximise lung function, (iii) prevent further exacerbations, (iv) minimise side-effects associated with medication and (v) provide sufficient information to enable her to manage her asthma effectively herself. </s><s n="s4.4;p108.118">Concerning the management of acute asthma: </s></p><p n="p109.118"><s n="s1.2;p109.118"><hi rend="underlined bold">Inhaled corticosteroids</hi>: systematic review evidence has shown that inhaled corticosteroids administered in A+E significantly reduce admission rates when compared to placebo <hi rend="sup">1</hi>. </s><s n="s2.2;p109.118">No significant difference was found between the efficacy of inhaled plus oral corticosteroid versus oral corticosteroid in either the same setting or in preventing relapse within a 24-day period. </s></p><p n="p110.118"><s n="s1.2;p110.118"><hi rend="underlined bold">Short acting β2 agonists</hi>: hospital admission rates have been shown in systematic reviews to be equally affected by both continuous and intermittent short acting β<hi rend="sub">2</hi> agonists when delivered via a nebuliser <hi rend="sup">2</hi>. </s><s n="s2.2;p110.118">Intravenous administration has also been shown to have no significantly different effect on either hospital admission rates or peak expiratory flow readings. </s></p><p n="p111.118"><s n="s1.4;p111.118"><hi rend="underlined bold">Ipratropium bromide</hi>: the addition of Ipratropium bromide to a β<hi rend="sub">2</hi> agonist such as salbutamol significantly improves FEV <hi rend="sub">1</hi> over a period of 90 minutes compared to salbutamol alone and in addition significantly reduces hospital admission rates <hi rend="sup">3</hi>. </s><s n="s2.4;p111.118">This data can only be supported by 2 further randomised controlled trials, as these were the only ones, which reported their data in sufficient detail to be included in analysis of hospital admission rates. </s><s n="s3.4;p111.118">This is certainly an area to be addressed in future clinical research. </s><s n="s4.4;p111.118">Areas for future research also include the use of <hi rend="bold">oxygen supplementation</hi> and <hi rend="bold">mechanical ventilation</hi> in the management of acute asthma as there is no published randomised controlled trial evidence concerning this. </s></p><p n="p112.118"><s n="s1.4;p112.118"><hi rend="underlined bold">Specialist versus generalist care</hi>: limited evidence suggests that outcomes in those individuals with severe asthma may be improved with specialist rather than generalised care. </s><s n="s2.4;p112.118">Parameters measuring improvement include number waking at night, those suffering relapse requiring emergency hospital admission within 6 months and the number suffering multiple relapses. </s><s n="s3.4;p112.118">These same individuals were however more likely to receive inhales corticosteroids and sodium cromoglycate. </s><s n="s4.4;p112.118">Mortality in medical intensive care units is higher than in general care but accounts for less than 3% of hospital admissions <hi rend="sup">4</hi>. </s></p><p n="p113.118"><s n="s1.3;p113.118"><hi rend="underlined bold">Education</hi>: facilitating disease self-management by providing specialist education concerning asthma has been found by a number of randomised controlled trials to reduce further hospital admission rates, doctors appointments (excluding those which are routine) and days off work through illness <hi rend="sup">5</hi>. </s><s n="s2.3;p113.118">This has interesting implications for future delivery of healthcare. </s><s n="s3.3;p113.118">Reduced admission rates and appointments will help alleviate current financial and resource stresses in the NHS. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="bold">Commentary</hi> A commentary on issues of health care delivery, ethical issues or disability relevant to the patient and/or problem</head><p n="p114.118"><s n="s1.3;p114.118">Asthma is extremely common and causes considerable morbidity. </s><s n="s2.3;p114.118">Prevalence is increasing in the UK particularly in the 2 <hi rend="sup">nd</hi> decade of life where between 10-15% of the population are affected <hi rend="sup">6</hi>. </s><s n="s3.3;p114.118">Various stimuli either cause or trigger asthma: </s></p><list type="bulleted"><item>Environmental exposure to an allergen e.g. domestic pollen, domestic pets</item><item>Occupational sensitizers - isocyanates, colophony fumes</item><item>Altmopsheric pollution - sulphur dioxide, ozone, particulate matter</item><item>Drugs - NSAIDs, β-adrenoceptor antagonists</item><item>Viral infections - Rhinovirus, Parainfluenza virus, RSV</item><item>Cold air</item><item>Emotion</item><item>Irritant dusts, vapour and fumes</item></list><p n="p115.118"><s n="s1.6;p115.118">Clearly, in this case the presenting exacerbation of asthma required secondary specialist hospital based care. </s><s n="s2.6;p115.118">Chronic, stable asthma can however be effectively managed in the community/primary care setting incorporating a multidisciplinary led team care approach. <name type="other"/> is greatly concerned and anxious about her asthma and the prospect of having further attacks. </s><s n="s3.6;p115.118">Manipulation of her treatment regime in order to minimise the risk of these attacks occurring must be explained to her in a format she is able to understand and absorb. </s><s n="s4.6;p115.118">As well as optimising disease control by modifying pharmacotherapy, interventions such as controlling extrinsic factors e.g. dust mites and particular drugs and educating affected individuals and their families can help optimise health outcome and prognosis. </s><s n="s5.6;p115.118">Facilitating the self-management of asthma has diffuse future healthcare implications. </s><s n="s6.6;p115.118">For example, patient care and healthcare experience could be optimised, helping a patient 'take ownership' of their disease e.g. taking peak flow readings can help with acceptance of a chronic disease and resource strains on the NHS alleviated. </s></p><p n="p116.118"><s n="s1.4;p116.118">Relapse rate from acute exacerbations of asthma varies between 7-15% depending on how aggressively the patient is treated. </s><s n="s2.4;p116.118">Current therapeutic regimens comprising ipratropium, corticosteroids and β2 selective agonists demonstrate suboptimal efficacy. </s><s n="s3.4;p116.118">Long-term prognosis following severe, life-threatening attacks is poor, mortality may reach 10%. </s><s n="s4.4;p116.118">Clearly, this is an area to address with future research <hi rend="sup">7</hi>. </s></p><p n="p117.118"><s n="s1.6;p117.118">This case demonstrates ethical controversy inherent with the treatment of chronic diseases such as asthma. </s><s n="s2.6;p117.118">Clearly, for <name type="other"/> the use of steroid treatment when required in both her acute management and for longer term purposes to achieve maintenance is life saving. </s><s n="s3.6;p117.118">However, this same treatment has decreased her bone density causing osteoporosis. </s><s n="s4.6;p117.118">She demonstrates radiological evidence of an associated pathological fracture in her ribs largely contributed to by this drug-induced osteoporosis. </s><s n="s5.6;p117.118">This highlights the need for continuing future research into optimising drug treatments for asthma. </s><s n="s6.6;p117.118">Morbidity and mortality associated with asthma increases with socioeconomic deprivation and ethnicity. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="bold">Impact on your learning</hi> Describe what you have learnt from this case</head><list type="bulleted"><item>Exacerbating factors of asthma</item><item>Factors determining prognosis</item><item>The importance of a multi-disciplinary team in patient care</item><item>Management of both chronic and acute episodes of asthma</item><item>Impact of diagnosis of an acute illness</item><item>Biopsychosocial model of health</item></list><p n="p118.118"/></div1></body><back><div1 type="bibliography"><p>Edmonds, M.L., Camargo, C.A. &amp; Saunders, L.D. 2002 Inhaled steroids in acute asthma following emergency department discharge. The Cochrane Library, Issue 3. </p><p>Rodrigo, G.J. &amp;Rodrigo, C. 2002 Continuous versus intermittent β agonists in the treatment of acute asthma. A systematic review with meta-analysis. Chest 122: 160-165.</p><p>Stoodley, R.G., Aaron, S.D. &amp; Dales, R.E. 1999 The role of ipratropium bromide in the emergency management of acute asthma exacerbation: a meta-analysis of randomized controlled trials. Ann. Emerg. Med. 34: 8-18.</p><p>Eastwood, A.J. &amp; Sheldon, T.A. 1996 Organisation of asthma care: what difference does it make? A systematic review of the literature. Quality Health Care 5: 134-143.</p><p>Cote, J., Bowie, D. &amp; Robichaud, P. 2001 Evaluation of two different educational interventions for adult patients consulting with an acute asthma exacerbation. Am. J. Respir. Crit. Care Med. 163: 1415-1419.</p><p>Holgate, S.T. 1999 The epidemic of allergy and asthma. Nature 402: 2-4.</p><p>McFadden, E.R. 2003 Acute severe asthma. Am J. Resp. &amp; Crit. Care Med. 168: 740-759.</p></div1><div1 type="back text"><head rend="bold">ASPECTS OF CASE AS RECORDED IN SUMMARY OF PORTFOLIO CASES •</head><table id="BAWE_0245i-tab.004"><row><cell/></row></table><p/></div1><div1 type="back text"><head rend="bold">PORTFOLIO COMPLETION CERTIFICATE</head><p rend="bold">Portfolio completion certificated</p><p>I confirm that this student has satisfactorily completed 3 word-processed portfolio cases.</p><p>Signed.....................................................................</p><p> Date......................................................................</p></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
