<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_0245h" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Asthma Patient Portfolio</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">proforma</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">4</p><p n="date">2005-09</p><p n="module title">Other Rotations</p><p n="module code">unknown</p><p n="genre family">Case study</p><p n="discipline">Medicine</p><p n="disciplinary group">LS</p><p n="grade">D</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">1822</p><p n="number of s-units">124</p><p n="number of p">83</p><p n="number of tables">0</p><p n="number of figures">0</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">5</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">11</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">14.7</p><p n="average s-units per p">1.5</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">f</p><p n="year of birth">1980</p><p n="first language">English</p><p n="education">UKA</p><p n="course">Medicine</p><p n="student ID">0245</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><docTitle><titlePart><hi rend="bold">PORTFOLIO CASE No:</hi> 15</titlePart></docTitle><titlePart>Patient Initials<name type="other"/> Hospital Number<name type="other"/> Age 39 Gender Male</titlePart><titlePart>Portfolio Case presentation number: Phase 2 course document objectives(s) Has the patient' permission, including for follow up contact by telephone, been sought and recorded in the case notes? Yes</titlePart></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="bold">Referral information</hi> Source of referral and a summary of key information</head><p n="p1.83"><s n="s1.2;p1.83"><name type="other"/> presented as an urgent 2 week referral at an outpatient dermatology clinic at <name type="other"/> hospital on the <name type="date"/>. </s><s n="s2.2;p1.83">He had a 3 year history of a mole on the right shoulder blade which had been progressively increasing in size with intermittent, spontaneous bleeding. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="bold">History</hi> All <hi rend="bold italic">relevant</hi> information gathered from the patient about the presenting illness, co-existing problems, current treatment, <hi rend="italic">significant</hi> past medical history and the social and family background. The patient's view of the nature of the problem and their expectations for treatment. </head><div2><head rend="underlined bold">Presenting Complaint. </head><p rend="bulleted" n="p2.83"><s n="s1.1;p2.83">Mole on right shoulder - increase in size, spontaneous bleeding. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined bold">History of Presenting Complaint. </head><p n="p3.83"><s n="s1.12;p3.83"><name type="other"/> presented with a 3 year history of a mole on his right shoulder blade. </s><s n="s2.12;p3.83">He was unaware of having had a mole in the same position prior to this time but could remember being severely sunburnt over "the back and shoulders as a child". </s><s n="s3.12;p3.83">Over the 3 years prior to presentation on the <name type="date"/> this mole had been progressively increasing in size approxiamtely doubling from 0.5cm x 0.5cm to 1cm x 1cm. </s><s n="s4.12;p3.83">In addition, the mole was spontaneously bleeding with frequency of 4/5 times a week. </s><s n="s5.12;p3.83">This again had worsened in the year prior to presentation. </s><s n="s6.12;p3.83">Bleeding didn't tend to be of significant magnitude but did occur spontaneously and not necessarily in response to contact from clothes for example. </s><s n="s7.12;p3.83">The mole had darkened significantly in colour over the same period. </s><s n="s8.12;p3.83">His partner has told him, "this mole is far far darker than the others". </s><s n="s9.12;p3.83">The shape had also altered from being "perfectly round to more oval". </s><s n="s10.12;p3.83">He had experienced no other forms of discharge or any associated pain or inflammation. </s><s n="s11.12;p3.83">There was no associated itch or altered sensation. </s><s n="s12.12;p3.83">His mole really caused him little concern, it was his wife who urged him to consult his GP for advice. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined bold">Past Medical History. </head><p n="p4.83"><s n="s1.4;p4.83"><name type="other"/> had no significant past medical or surgical history. </s><s n="s2.4;p4.83">Of dermatological relevance, he has no history of eczema, psoriasis, hayfever, urticaria, asthma, dry skin, varicose veins or leg ulcers. </s><s n="s3.4;p4.83">He did appear to have excessive distribution of moles and had never had a skin cancer before. </s><s n="s4.4;p4.83">No history of diabetes, epilepsy, hypertension, jaundice, strokes, heart attacks, rheumatoid or osteoarthritis, cervical arthropathy, obstructive sleep apnoea, acromegaly or thyroid disease. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined bold">Systems Review: </head><p n="p5.83"><s n="s1.1;p5.83">No significant findings to note. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined bold">Medication. </head><p n="p6.83"><s n="s1.2;p6.83">He takes no prescribed or alternative medication. </s><s n="s2.2;p6.83">Uses paracetamol for occasional mild headaches. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined bold">Allergies: </head><p n="p7.83"><s n="s1.1;p7.83">no drug or other allergies known. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined bold">Family History: </head><p n="p8.83"><s n="s1.2;p8.83">No known significant family history. </s><s n="s2.2;p8.83">No history of eczema, psoriasis, asthma or skin cancers. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined bold">Social History: </head><p n="p9.83"><s n="s1.6;p9.83"><name type="other"/> lives with his wife in <name type="other"/>. </s><s n="s2.6;p9.83">He is fully independent and describes his quality of life as "good". </s><s n="s3.6;p9.83">He has no children and works full time in an administration position. </s><s n="s4.6;p9.83">He does not spend excessive amounts of time outdoors or sunbathing in his spare time and does not have any pets currently. </s><s n="s5.6;p9.83">He is smoker with a habit of "up to 10" cigarettes a day. </s><s n="s6.6;p9.83">He drinks alcohol socially with maximum weekly consumption of approximately 16 units. </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="bold">Analysis of history</hi> The most likely single cause of the presentation, other possible causes and reasons for these choices. The findings to be looked for on physical examination to help decide the cause.</head><p n="p10.83"><s n="s1.1;p10.83">Malignant melanoma of either of the following two types. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p11.83"><s n="s1.3;p11.83">Nodular malignant melanoma - most aggressive type. </s><s n="s2.3;p11.83">Presents as a rapidly growing pigmented nodule which bleeds or ulcerates. </s><s n="s3.3;p11.83">Rarely are non-pigmented/amelanotic and can mimic pyogenic granuloma. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p12.83"><s n="s1.2;p12.83">Superficial spreading malignant melanoma - a flat, irregularly pigmented lesion, large in size. </s><s n="s2.2;p12.83">Grows laterally before vertical invasion develops. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p13.83"><s n="s1.1;p13.83">Benign naevus </s></p><p n="p14.83"><s n="s1.1;p14.83">The following clinical criteria are an aid in distinguishing between the above differential diagnoses. </s></p><list type="bulleted"><head>ABCDE criteria (USA)</head><item>Asymmetry of mole</item><item>Border irregularity</item><item>Colour variegation</item><item>Diameter >6mm</item><item>Elevation</item></list><p n="p15.83"><s n="s1.1;p15.83">The Glasgow 7-point checklist </s></p><list type="bulleted"><head>Major criteria:</head><item>Change in size</item><item>Change in shape</item><item>Change in colour</item></list><list type="bulleted"><head>Minor criteria:</head><item>Diameter >6mm</item><item>Inflammation</item><item>Oozing or bleeding</item><item>Mild itch or altered sensation</item></list><p n="p16.83"><s n="s1.2;p16.83">To support the most likely presenting diagnosis of malignant melanoma <name type="other"/> presents with all 3 of the major criteria in the Glasgow 7-point checklist, his mole has changed in size, shape and colour. </s><s n="s2.2;p16.83">Of the minor criteria, his mole measures more than 6mm and it bleeds spontaneously on regular occasions. </s></p><p n="p17.83"><s n="s1.4;p17.83">History of sun exposure in childhood and intermittent exposure in adulthood are particularly important aetiological factors in the development of malignant melanoma. <name type="other"/> had been severely sunburnt in his childhood across his back and shoulder blades. </s><s n="s2.4;p17.83">Other predisposing factors include atypical mole syndrome, giant congenital melanocytic naevi, lentigo maligna and positive family history of malignant melanoma. </s><s n="s3.4;p17.83">Malignant melanoma is commoner in later life but can affect younger individuals. </s><s n="s4.4;p17.83">Incidence is continuing to increase due to excessive exposure to sunlight. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="bold">Physical and mental state examination</hi> Highlight the findings most relevant to your clinical problem solving by underlining them</head><p n="p18.83"><s n="s1.3;p18.83">A middle-aged gentleman who appeared fit and non-septic. </s><s n="s2.3;p18.83">He was not obviously jaundiced. </s><s n="s3.3;p18.83">He was cannulated and had no respiratory or mobility aids around his bedside. <name type="other"/> was fully conscious, cooperative and talked expressively and freely. </s></p><div2><head rend="underlined bold">General. </head><div3><head rend="underlined bold">Hands. </head><p n="p19.83"><s n="s1.1;p19.83"><hi rend="underlined">No pale palmar creases</hi> - suggesting blood loss in urine has been neither of sufficient duration or volume to cause anaemia. </s></p><p n="p20.83"><s n="s1.1;p20.83">No signs of peripheral cyanosis. </s></p><p n="p21.83"><s n="s1.1;p21.83">No palmer erythema, clubbing, cyanosis, leukonychia, Dupuytren's contracture, kolonychia, liver flap. </s></p></div3><div3><head rend="underlined bold">Face. </head><p n="p22.83"><s n="s1.1;p22.83">No pale palpebral conjunctivae. </s></p><p n="p23.83"><s n="s1.1;p23.83">No signs of jaundice (icteus) or cyanosis. </s></p></div3><div3><head rend="underlined bold">Mouth. </head><p n="p24.83"><s n="s1.1;p24.83">No cyanosis </s></p><p n="p25.83"><s n="s1.1;p25.83">No ulcers </s></p><p n="p26.83"><s n="s1.1;p26.83">Not dehydrated </s></p></div3><div3><head rend="underlined bold">Neck. </head><p n="p27.83"><s n="s1.1;p27.83">No lymphadenopathy. </s></p><p n="p28.83"><s n="s1.1;p28.83"><hi rend="underlined">Temperature - 37.1ºC</hi> - <hi rend="underlined">absence</hi> of current <hi rend="underlined">systemic</hi> infection. </s></p></div3><div3><head rend="underlined bold">Examination of left leg. </head><p n="p29.83"><s n="s1.1;p29.83">Erythema and swelling visible from tibial tuberosity to the foot </s></p><p n="p30.83"><s n="s1.1;p30.83">Leg warm to the touch </s></p><p n="p31.83"><s n="s1.1;p31.83">Posterior tibial pulse palpable </s></p><p n="p32.83"><s n="s1.1;p32.83">Serous exudatefrom tibial surface of leg </s></p><p n="p33.83"><s n="s1.1;p33.83">Full range of movement at both the ankle and knee joints </s></p><p n="p34.83"><s n="s1.1;p34.83">Able to weight-bear </s></p></div3><div3><head rend="underlined bold">Abdomen. </head><p n="p35.83"><s n="s1.1;p35.83">Symmetrical </s></p><p n="p36.83"><s n="s1.1;p36.83">No spider naevi, caput medusa or obvious abdominal distension </s></p><p n="p37.83"><s n="s1.1;p37.83">No hepatomegaly </s></p><p n="p38.83"><s n="s1.1;p38.83">Spleen and kidneys impalpable </s></p><p n="p39.83"><s n="s1.1;p39.83">No renal angle tenderness - infection unlikely </s></p><p n="p40.83"><s n="s1.1;p40.83">No ascites, shifting dullness, palpable masses </s></p><p n="p41.83"><s n="s1.1;p41.83">Bladder impalpable </s></p><p n="p42.83"><s n="s1.1;p42.83">Abdomen soft and non-tender on palpation, percussion resonant, normal bowel sounds </s></p><p n="p43.83"><s n="s1.1;p43.83">A PR exam was not performed at the time of examination, as supervision was unavailable. </s></p></div3></div2><div2><head rend="underlined bold">Cardiovascular system. </head><p n="p44.83"><s n="s1.1;p44.83">No signs of peripheral or central cyanosis </s></p><p n="p45.83"><s n="s1.1;p45.83">No peripheral oedema </s></p><p n="p46.83"><s n="s1.1;p46.83"><hi rend="underlined">Pulse 98bpm</hi> - tachycardia associated with current infection, Blood pressure 152/79 </s></p><p n="p47.83"><s n="s1.1;p47.83">Radial pulse palpable, regular, radial and carotid pulses normal strength </s></p><p n="p48.83"><s n="s1.1;p48.83">All other peripheral pulses palpable </s></p><p n="p49.83"><s n="s1.1;p49.83">JVP normal </s></p><p n="p50.83"><s n="s1.1;p50.83">Heart sounds I and II normal </s></p><p n="p51.83"><s n="s1.1;p51.83">No murmurs or displacement of the apex beat. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined bold">Respiratory system. </head><p n="p52.83"><s n="s1.1;p52.83">Respiratory rate 20/min </s></p><p n="p53.83"><s n="s1.1;p53.83">Oxygen saturation 97% on air </s></p><p n="p54.83"><s n="s1.1;p54.83">Breathing appeared to be of normal depth </s></p><p n="p55.83"><s n="s1.1;p55.83">No cough, sputum, tracheal deviation </s></p><p n="p56.83"><s n="s1.1;p56.83">Equal chest expansion, normal vesicular breath sounds </s></p><p n="p57.83"><s n="s1.1;p57.83">No crackles </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="bold">Analysis of history and examination</hi> Reasons for your choice of the cause of the patient's problem(s) and any other cause that still needs to be considered at this stage</head><p n="p58.83"><s n="s1.2;p58.83">Histological analysis determines both the thickness of the tumour (Breslow thickness) and the depth of invasion (Clarke's level). </s><s n="s2.2;p58.83">Both these factors aid in predicting prognosis and 5 year survival rates. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="bold">Formulation of the patient's problem(s)</hi> Encapsulate this in physical, psychological and social terms (the triple diagnosis)</head><p n="p59.83"><s n="s1.1;p59.83">Physical-: </s></p><p n="p60.83"><s n="s1.1;p60.83">Psychological-: </s></p><p n="p61.83"><s n="s1.1;p61.83">Social-: </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="bold">Management</hi> Use the framework of RAPRIOP to structure your proposed management. Refer to the guidelines to the writing of portfolio cases for the details of the issues to be addressed under each heading.</head><div2><head rend="bold">Investigations</head><p n="p62.83"><s n="s1.1;p62.83">Mole excised under local anaesthetic on the <name type="date"/>. </s></p><p n="p63.83"><s n="s1.1;p63.83"><hi rend="underlined">Macroscopic features</hi>: </s></p><p n="p64.83"><s n="s1.4;p64.83">Skin excision of mole on right shoulder. </s><s n="s2.4;p64.83">Ellipse of skin measuring 2 x 1.2 x 1.1cm. </s><s n="s3.4;p64.83">Irregularly pigmented, evenly outlined nodule 0.9 x 0.9 x 0.2cm. </s><s n="s4.4;p64.83">Border regular. </s></p><p n="p65.83"><s n="s1.1;p65.83"><hi rend="underlined">Microscopic features</hi>: </s></p><list type="bulleted"><item>Superficial spreading malignant melanoma. </item><item>Breslow thickness 1.6mm </item><item>Clarkes level III (index of depth of invasion). </item><item>Mitotic index 0.1-6mm <hi rend="sup">2</hi></item><item>Pre-exisiting naevus</item><item>No vascular or peri-neural invasion</item><item>No dysplasia</item><item>Distance to radial margin 1mm clear</item><item>Distance to deep margin 11.5mm clear</item></list><p n="p66.83"><s n="s1.1;p66.83"><hi rend="underlined">Staging</hi>: </s></p><p n="p67.83"><s n="s1.1;p67.83">TMN microstage pT2a </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold italic">Reassurance and explanation</head><p n="p68.83"/></div2><div2><head rend="bold">Prescription/medical intervention</head><p rend="bulleted" n="p69.83"><s n="s1.1;p69.83">Urgent wide excision </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold italic">Observation</head><p n="p70.83"><s n="s1.2;p70.83"><name type="other"/> will be transferred to a general urology ward immediately following his cystoscopic investigation where he should receive regular monitoring of his oxygen saturation and heart rate during his recovery from the local anaesthesia. </s><s n="s2.2;p70.83">Regular observations should be continued and altered as appropriate for a 24-hour period following anaesthesia. <name type="other"/> should be able to be discharged the day after his procedure. </s></p><p n="p71.83"><s n="s1.1;p71.83"><name type="other"/> is well nourished and hydrated and is unlikely to require special supplementation during his hospital stay. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">Referral and team working</head><p rend="bulleted" n="p72.83"><s n="s1.1;p72.83">GP - post-discharge monitoring and support </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p73.83"><s n="s1.1;p73.83">Cardiologist - optimise cardiovascular function and assess exercise tolerance </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">Advice and Prevention</head><p rend="bulleted" n="p74.83"><s n="s1.1;p74.83">A low-fat, high-fibre diet is recommended </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p75.83"><s n="s1.1;p75.83">Increase daily fluid intake </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p76.83"><s n="s1.1;p76.83">For recurrent infections self-administration of antibiotics at onset of symptoms </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p77.83"><s n="s1.1;p77.83">Moderate regular exercise </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="bold">Outcome</hi> A description of the progress of the patient as far as possible. This should include consideration of further issues to be resolved. Where appropriate you should contact by telephone patients who have been discharged home.</head><p n="p78.83"><s n="s1.3;p78.83"><name type="other"/> was discharged the day after his cystoscopic procedure. </s><s n="s2.3;p78.83">He was relieved as to his diagnosis and felt he had been fully informed regarding his condition and the treatment he received. </s><s n="s3.3;p78.83">He does not need to attend a urology outpatient appointment and should receive further cystoscopic examination in the future should his symptoms return. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="bold">Evidence based care and issues for research</hi> A brief consideration of the evidence base required for the diagnosis and management of the patient's problem(s)</head><p n="p79.83"><s n="s1.2;p79.83">Both government and medical personnel have a role to play in the management of malignant melanoma. </s><s n="s2.2;p79.83">Public health education should discourage sunbathing and encourage widespread use of the appropriate factor suncream. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="bold">Commentary</hi> A commentary on issues of health care delivery, ethical issues or disability relevant to the patient and/or problem</head><p n="p80.83"><s n="s1.2;p80.83">Transitional cell tumours account for about 3% of deaths from all causes of malignancy. </s><s n="s2.2;p80.83">Painless, frank haematuria is commonly the presenting symptom of bladder cancer and is an 'alarm' symptom warranting an urgent 2 week referral from a primary care setting (GP) to secondary care (hospital) for further investigation. <name type="other"/> fast-tracked this process by self-presenting straight to secondary care. </s></p><p n="p81.83"><s n="s1.3;p81.83">A diagnosis of bladder cancer is made by cystoscopy and should cancer be found regular cystoscopic screening is advised to monitor future occurrence of neoplastic growth. </s><s n="s2.3;p81.83">Clearly the earlier the diagnosis, the sooner treatment can be started and the better the prognosis for the patient. <name type="other"/> presented with an 'alarm' symptom of cancer and although was found not to have this it was crucial he received treatment investigative of such. </s><s n="s3.3;p81.83">The prognosis of bladder cancer ranges from a 5-year survival of 80-90% for lesions not involving bladder muscle to 5% for those invasive cancers with metastatic spread. </s></p><p n="p82.83"><s n="s1.2;p82.83">Patients from a stable family background and with social support respond best to treatment. </s><s n="s2.2;p82.83">His family could contribute towards care and as such should be involved in his treatment and diagnosis. <name type="other"/>'s health needs to be optimised to enable him to maximise independence and quality of life. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="bold">Impact on your learning</hi> Describe what you have learnt from this case</head><list type="bulleted"><item>Risk factors for transitional cell carcinoma</item><item>Factors determining prognosis</item><item>The importance of a multi-disciplinary team in patient care</item><item>Co-morbidity and impact on patient's lifestyle</item><item>Biopsychosocial model of health</item></list><p n="p83.83"/></div1></body><back><div1 type="bibliography"><p>1. Cohen, R.A. &amp; Brown, R.S. Microscopic Haematuria. N. Engl. J. Med. 2003 349: 2330- 2338.</p><p>2.Harper, M., Arya, M., Hamid, R. &amp; Patel, H.R.H. Haematuria: a stream-lined approach to management. Hosp. Med. 2001; 62: 696-698.</p><p>3. Reynard, J. 2000 BMJ 1598.</p><p>4. The National Service Framework for Older people 2000, DoH, London.</p></div1><div1 type="back text"><head rend="bold">ASPECTS OF CASE AS RECORDED IN SUMMARY OF PORTFOLIO CASES •</head><table id="BAWE_0245h-tab.001"><row><cell/></row></table><p/></div1><div1 type="back text"><head rend="bold">PORTFOLIO COMPLETION CERTIFICATE</head><p rend="bold">Portfolio completion certificated</p><p>I confirm that this student has satisfactorily completed 3 word-processed portfolio cases.</p><p>Signed.....................................................................</p><p> Date......................................................................</p></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
