<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_0246g" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Portfolio 23 - JK</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">proforma</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">4</p><p n="date">2006-05</p><p n="module title">Other Rotations</p><p n="module code">unknown</p><p n="genre family">Case study</p><p n="discipline">Medicine</p><p n="disciplinary group">LS</p><p n="grade">D</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">2616</p><p n="number of s-units">133</p><p n="number of p">56</p><p n="number of tables">2</p><p n="number of figures">0</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">8</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">14</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">19.7</p><p n="average s-units per p">2.4</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">f</p><p n="year of birth">1981</p><p n="first language">English</p><p n="education">UKA</p><p n="course">Medicine</p><p n="student ID">0246</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><docTitle><titlePart><hi rend="bold">PORTFOLIO CASE No:</hi> 24</titlePart></docTitle><titlePart>Patient Initials<name type="other"/> Hospital Number<name type="other"/> Age 81 Gender Male</titlePart><titlePart>Portfolio Case presentation number: 7.2 Phase 2 course document objectives(s): 7.14 Has the patient' permission, including for follow up contact by telephone, been sought and recorded in the case notes?</titlePart></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="bold">Referral information</hi> Source of referral and a summary of key information</head><p n="p1.56"><s n="s1.2;p1.56">Mr <name type="other"/> was referred to <name type="other"/> Hospital, <name type="other"/> on the <name type="date"/> by his general practitioner (GP). </s><s n="s2.2;p1.56">The referral was made on the basis of worsening pain In Mr <name type="other"/>'s right-side chest wall. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="bold">History</hi> All <hi rend="bold italic">relevant</hi> information gathered from the patient about the presenting illness, co-existing problems, current treatment, <hi rend="italic">significant</hi> past medical history and the social and family background. The patient's view of the nature of the problem and their expectations for treatment. </head><div2><head rend="bold">Presenting Complaint</head><p n="p2.56"><s n="s1.1;p2.56">Mr <name type="other"/> had a <hi rend="bold">4-5 week history of pain in the right-hand side of his chest</hi>, which had been getting <hi rend="bold">progressively worse.</hi> </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">History of Presenting Complaint</head><p n="p3.56"><s n="s1.15;p3.56">Mr <name type="other"/> had been experiencing this <hi rend="bold">pain for 4-5 weeks and described it getting worse</hi>. </s><s n="s2.15;p3.56">The pain was <hi rend="bold">localised at the "top" of his chest</hi> and it <hi rend="bold">radiated down to his waist</hi>. </s><s n="s3.15;p3.56">Mr <name type="other"/> described the <hi rend="bold">pain as a dull ache,</hi> which was always present. </s><s n="s4.15;p3.56">Mr <name type="other"/> graded his <hi rend="bold">pain 6-7/10</hi> (10 worst pain ever experienced). </s><s n="s5.15;p3.56">Nothing relieved the pain but he had <hi rend="bold">not taken any analgesics</hi>. </s><s n="s6.15;p3.56">Mr <name type="other"/> became more aware of the pain when he was moving and if he <hi rend="bold">coughed or sneezed the pain became more severe</hi>. </s><s n="s7.15;p3.56">Mr <name type="other"/> had not experienced this type of problem before. </s><s n="s8.15;p3.56">There was <hi rend="bold">no associated nausea or vomiting</hi>. </s><s n="s9.15;p3.56">Mr <name type="other"/> was <hi rend="bold">breathless on exertion</hi> (10 yards on the flat ground and going up the stairs) and <hi rend="bold">did not have a persistent cough</hi>. </s><s n="s10.15;p3.56">There had been <hi rend="bold">no haemoptysis</hi>. </s><s n="s11.15;p3.56">Mr <name type="other"/> did <hi rend="bold">not have a wheeze</hi> and did not use inhalers. </s><s n="s12.15;p3.56">There was <hi rend="bold">no paroxysmal nocturnal dyspnoea or orthopnoea</hi>. </s><s n="s13.15;p3.56">Mr <name type="other"/> felt lethargic over the last month. </s><s n="s14.15;p3.56">There was <hi rend="bold">no dizziness or loss of consciousness.</hi> </s><s rend="bold" n="s15.15;p3.56">Mr <name type="other"/> did not have any palpitations. </s></p><p n="p4.56"><s n="s1.3;p4.56">Mr <name type="other"/> opened his bowels regularly, he had <hi rend="bold">lost 3lbs in the last 2 weeks</hi> and his appetite was good. </s><s n="s2.3;p4.56">There was <hi rend="bold">no constipation, no diarrhoea and no malaena.</hi> </s><s n="s3.3;p4.56">Mr <name type="other"/><hi rend="bold">micturated frequently</hi> but there was <hi rend="bold">no pain on urinating</hi>; he had a history of an enlarged irregular prostate. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">Past Medical History</head><list type="bulleted"><item> Type 2 Diabetes Mellitus - 2003</item><item>Alopecia - 2003 - unknown cause</item><item>TUPR - 2001</item><item>Hypercholesterolaemia</item><item>No history of thyroid problems, rheumatoid arthritis, epilepsy, asthma, myocardial infarction, stroke or TB. </item></list><p n="p5.56"/></div2><div2><head rend="bold">Current Medication</head><list type="simple"><item>Paracetamol - 1g <hi rend="italic">qds </hi></item><item>Gliclazide - 90mg <hi rend="italic">od</hi></item><item>Finasteride - 5mg <hi rend="italic">od</hi></item><item>ISMN - 20mg <hi rend="italic">bd</hi></item><item>Ramipril - 2.5mg <hi rend="italic">od</hi></item><item>Aspirin - 75mg <hi rend="italic">od</hi></item><item>Amylodipine - 10mg <hi rend="italic">od</hi></item><item>Rosiglitazone - 4mg <hi rend="italic">od</hi></item><item>Liquifilm tears</item></list><p n="p6.56"><s rend="bold" n="s1.1;p6.56">No known drug allergies. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">Family History</head><p n="p7.56"><s n="s1.1;p7.56">There was no significant family history. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">Social History</head><p n="p8.56"><s n="s1.6;p8.56">Mr <name type="other"/> lived with his wife in a house and is an independent, mobile man. </s><s n="s2.6;p8.56">Mr <name type="other"/> has 2 children whom he has regular contact with. </s><s n="s3.6;p8.56">Mr <name type="other"/> is a retired electrical engineer. </s><s n="s4.6;p8.56">There was no exposure to asbestos or other occupational hazards. </s><s n="s5.6;p8.56">Mr <name type="other"/> was an ex-smoker of 40 years, when he smoked 10/day for 25 years. </s><s n="s6.6;p8.56">Mr <name type="other"/> drinks on average 6-8 units of alcohol per week. </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="bold">Analysis of history</hi> The most likely single cause of the presentation, other possible causes and reasons for these choices. The findings to be looked for on physical examination to help decide the cause.</head><p n="p9.56"><s n="s1.1;p9.56">Based on the symptoms Mr <name type="other"/> presented with, the differential diagnoses of right-sided chest pain, worsening over 4-5 weeks and on exertion are: </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p10.56"><s n="s1.4;p10.56"><hi rend="bold">Pleural Effusion:</hi> fluid in the pleural space, which can be divided into low protein content (transudate) and high protein content (exudates). </s><s n="s2.4;p10.56">They are often asymptomatic but patients can experience dyspnoea and a pleuritic chest pain. </s><s n="s3.4;p10.56">Transudates are due to an increase in venous pressure (such as from cardiac failure, constrictive pericarditis or fluid overload). </s><s n="s4.4;p10.56">Exudates are most likely due to an increase in the leakiness of pleural capillaries secondary to malignancy, infection or inflammation. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p11.56"><s n="s1.2;p11.56"><hi rend="bold">Neoplasm:</hi> with clinical symptoms of a persistent cough, haemoptysis, dyspnoea, chest pain, anorexia and weight loss. </s><s n="s2.2;p11.56">Recurrent slowly resolving pneumonias are also a common feature. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p12.56"><s n="s1.1;p12.56"><hi rend="bold">Pneumonia:</hi> consider atypical pneumonias, for example mycoplasma. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p13.56"><s rend="bold" n="s1.1;p13.56">Tuberculosis </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p14.56"><s rend="bold" n="s1.1;p14.56">Trauma-related; rib fracture: </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p15.56"><s n="s1.3;p15.56"><hi rend="bold">Pulmonary Embolism:</hi> a clinical picture of acute breathlessness, pleuritic chest pain, haemoptysis, dizziness and syncope. </s><s n="s2.3;p15.56">PEs usually arise from a venous thrombosis in the pelvis or legs. </s><s n="s3.3;p15.56">Clots break off and pass through the venous system and the right side of the heart before lodging in the pulmonary circulation. </s></p><p n="p16.56"><s n="s1.4;p16.56">On physical examination, a full respiratory examination will be carried out; assessment of respiratory rate, oxygen saturations, breath sounds (bronchial breathing is often heard in pleural effusions). </s><s n="s2.4;p16.56">Listening to air entry and the presence of added sounds; crackles indicating infection or wheezes suggestive of airways disease. </s><s n="s3.4;p16.56">It is also important to look for signs of trauma and palpate for tenderness over the chest wall, which would be present if there was a rib fracture. </s><s n="s4.4;p16.56">An overall examination of Mr <name type="other"/> will help build a clinical picture that may indicate a malignancy; palpating for lymphadenopathy should be carried out. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="bold">Physical examination and mental state examination</hi> Highlight the findings most relevant to your clinical problem solving by underlining them</head><p n="p17.56"><s n="s1.5;p17.56">On general examination, Mr <name type="other"/> was alert and orientated. </s><s n="s2.5;p17.56">There were <hi rend="bold">no signs of clubbing, cyanosis, jaundice or lymphadenopathy</hi>. </s><s n="s3.5;p17.56">Mr <name type="other"/> had <hi rend="bold">pale conjunctiva</hi>. </s><s n="s4.5;p17.56">Capillary refill &lt;2 seconds. </s><s n="s5.5;p17.56"><hi rend="bold">Reduced skin turgor and dry mucus membranes</hi>. </s></p><div2><head rend="underlined">Respiratory System</head><list type="bulleted"><item>Respiratory rate 24 breaths per minute; Saturations 87% on air, 98% on 100% oxygen. </item><item>Vesicular breath sounds present</item><item>Equal air entry. </item><item>Stony dull percussion on the right side</item><item>Crackles heard on the right. </item><item>No wheeze present</item><item>Trachea midline</item></list><p n="p18.56"/></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">Cardiovascular System</head><list type="bulleted"><item>Pulse 104 irregular - indicative of atrial fibrillation</item><item>BP 152/63</item><item>Heart sounds I + II + 0</item><item>JVP no raised</item><item>No pedal oedema. </item><item>Temperature 37.4 <hi rend="sup">o</hi>C</item></list><p n="p19.56"/></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">Gastrointestinal System</head><list type="bulleted"><item>Abdomen soft and non-tender</item><item>No masses felt. </item><item>Hepatomegaly present - 3 finger widths</item><item>No splenomegaly. </item><item>PR - sphincter tone normal, impacted stools, no malaena. </item></list><p n="p20.56"/></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="bold">Analysis of history and examination</hi> Reasons for your choice of the cause of the patient's problem(s) and any other cause that still needs to be considered at this stage</head><p n="p21.56"><s n="s1.6;p21.56">Following examination, the most likely diagnosis for Mr <name type="other"/>'s presentation is a right-sided pleural effusion, possibly secondary to a neoplasm in light of the presence of hepatomegaly. </s><s n="s2.6;p21.56">The effusion could also be complicated by a chest infection suggested by the crackles heard on examination. </s><s n="s3.6;p21.56">The pleural effusion will need to be aspirated and sent for histology to determine whether it is an exudate or a transudate fluid. </s><s n="s4.6;p21.56">Exudative effusion (protein >30g/dL) can be caused by infection or malignancy. </s><s n="s5.6;p21.56">Malignant cells can be seen on cytology. </s><s n="s6.6;p21.56">It is important to rule out a malignancy as a cause for the effusion and Mr <name type="other"/> requires a chest X-ray followed by a CT if a lesion is found. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="bold">Formulation of the patient's problem(s)</hi> Encapsulate this in physical, psychological and social terms (the triple diagnosis)</head><p n="p22.56"><s n="s1.3;p22.56"><hi rend="bold">Physical -</hi> Mr <name type="other"/> is physically able and independent. </s><s n="s2.3;p22.56">Since his chest pain started he has been finding it more difficult to carry out his usual tasks of daily living. </s><s n="s3.3;p22.56">His difficulty breathing also makes mobilising more difficult. </s></p><p n="p23.56"><s n="s1.2;p23.56"><hi rend="bold">Psychological -</hi> Mr <name type="other"/> had become worried about his chest pain as it had been continuing for so long. </s><s n="s2.2;p23.56">He went to his GP because he was worried he was having a heart attack. </s></p><p n="p24.56"><s n="s1.1;p24.56"><hi rend="bold">Social</hi> - Mr <name type="other"/> had support from his wife and family and was an independent man. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="bold">Management</hi> Use the framework of RAPRIOP to structure your proposed management. Refer to the guidelines to the writing of portfolio cases for the details of the issues to be addressed under each heading.</head><div2><head rend="bold">Investigations </head><p n="p25.56"><s n="s1.1;p25.56">Mr <name type="other"/>'s blood results following admission on <name type="date"/> were as follows: </s></p><table id="BAWE_0246g-tab.001"><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p26.56"><s n="s1.1;p26.56">Mr <name type="other"/>'s biochemistry results following admission on <name type="date"/> were as follows: </s></p><table id="BAWE_0246g-tab.002"><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p27.56"><s rend="bold" n="s1.1;p27.56">CA19-9 (upper GI cancer marker) - normal, CEA marker - normal. </s></p><p n="p28.56"><s rend="bold" n="s1.1;p28.56">Antibody screen - negative </s></p><p n="p29.56"><s rend="bold" n="s1.1;p29.56">Mr <name type="other"/> was cross-matched for a blood transfusion (normocytic, normochromic anaemia). </s></p><p n="p30.56"><s rend="bold" n="s1.1;p30.56">Mr <name type="other"/>'s urea and creatinine results indicate he is in acute renal failure. </s></p><div3><head rend="underlined">X-Ray Chest</head><p n="p31.56"><s n="s1.1;p31.56">"Large area of shadowing in lower right lung". </s></p></div3><div3><head rend="underlined">Pleural Fluid Analysis</head><p n="p32.56"><s n="s1.2;p32.56">LDH - 845: <hi rend="bold">Total Protein 41g/dL i.e. exudative</hi>. </s><s n="s2.2;p32.56"><hi rend="bold">Aspirate analysis: "Predominantly Neutrophils, scanty mesothelial cells, no malignant cells seen"</hi>. </s></p></div3></div2><div2><head rend="bold">Reassurance and Explanation</head><p n="p33.56"><s n="s1.7;p33.56">To appropriately reassure Mr <name type="other"/>, I would say: "As you know, you have been experiencing some chest pain for a little while now. </s><s n="s2.7;p33.56">There are a number of reasons why you might have this chest pain and we would like to do some investigations whilst you are in hospital. </s><s n="s3.7;p33.56">The type of pain you are describing indicates to us that you may have some fluid collected in your lungs, which can be the result of a number of things. </s><s n="s4.7;p33.56">One of the things that can cause this problem is cancer in your lungs and we would like to investigate you for that possibility whilst you are in hospital. </s><s n="s5.7;p33.56">You do not seem to have any current risk factors for a lung cancer but you were a smoker in the past, which could have a role to play. </s><s n="s6.7;p33.56">We would like to carry out some blood tests, organise a chest X-ray and a CT scan. </s><s n="s7.7;p33.56">At the moment we will give you some oxygen to help with your breathing". </s></p><p n="p34.56"><s n="s1.6;p34.56">To explain the nature of the disease: "Following your blood tests and X-ray, they confirm that you have a collection of fluid in your right lung. </s><s n="s2.6;p34.56">This is the most likely cause of your chest pain and breathing difficulties. </s><s n="s3.6;p34.56">Your blood tests also show us that you are very anaemic and we would like to give you some blood to help improve this. </s><s n="s4.6;p34.56">Having such a low haemoglobin level may also be another cause for your breathlessness. </s><s n="s5.6;p34.56">Your blood results also indicate that you have an infection, which is also most likely to be in your lungs. </s><s n="s6.6;p34.56">The cause of the fluid in your lungs could still be a result of a malignancy and we would like to investigate you further t rule this out". </s></p><p n="p35.56"><s n="s1.5;p35.56">To describe the management plan: "Whilst you are in hospital we are going to carry out some tests to find a reason for the fluid in your lung. </s><s n="s2.5;p35.56">We would like to get an ultrasound of your tummy and a CT scan of your chest. </s><s n="s3.5;p35.56">We are going to aspirate your chest to get the fluid out of your lung, which we hope will reduce your pain and ease your breathlessness. </s><s n="s4.5;p35.56">We feel that your diabetes is not very well controlled so we are going to put you on an insulin drip and ask the diabetic nurse to talk with you about how to help you best control your sugar levels. </s><s n="s5.5;p35.56">Once we have the results of all of the tests we will be in a better position to tell you what has caused the fluid to collect in your lungs". </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">Prescription/Medical Intervention</head><p n="p36.56"><s n="s1.4;p36.56">Whilst in hospital, Mr <name type="other"/> had a chest drain to remove the fluid in his right lung. </s><s n="s2.4;p36.56">He was transfused to improve his haemoglobin levels and he received fluids to treat is acute renal failure. </s><s n="s3.4;p36.56">Mr <name type="other"/> was put on a sliding scale of insulin to better control his diabetes. </s><s n="s4.4;p36.56">Mr <name type="other"/> was prescribed antibiotics to treat a suspected chest infection. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">Observation</head><p n="p37.56"><s n="s1.4;p37.56">Following admission, Mr <name type="other"/> was monitored for any further deterioration in his breathing and general health, for example the onset of a fever. </s><s n="s2.4;p37.56">His blood levels were monitored to check his haemoglobin levels were rising and his blood glucose was closely monitored to achieve a better diabetic control. </s><s n="s3.4;p37.56">Long-term observation will include diabetic follow-up; if his blood glucose has been uncontrolled in the past, it is possible it will decline again when he leave hospital. </s><s n="s4.4;p37.56">Observation in the primary care setting will be needed. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">Referral and Team Working</head><p n="p38.56"><s n="s1.2;p38.56">Mr <name type="other"/> was not referred to any other team during his stay in hospital. </s><s n="s2.2;p38.56">Team-working between the team looking after him in hospital and the diabetic nurses will be necessary to get improvement in his blood glucose control. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">Advice and Prevention</head><p n="p39.56"><s n="s1.4;p39.56">Mr <name type="other"/> should be advised with regard to his blood glucose control once he is at home. </s><s n="s2.4;p39.56">He should be given advice about his diet and when to take his medication. </s><s n="s3.4;p39.56">He should also be given information about the complications of diabetes if blood glucose is not well controlled. </s><s n="s4.4;p39.56">With regards to his chest pain, he should be advised to visit his GP if he experiences any more problems. </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="bold">Outcome</hi> A description of the progress of the patient as far as possible. This should include consideration of further issues to be resolved. Where appropriate you should contact by telephone patients who have been discharged home.</head><p n="p40.56"><s n="s1.3;p40.56">Mr <name type="other"/> remained an inpatient for over 1 week whilst the necessary investigations were carried out. </s><s n="s2.3;p40.56">Mr <name type="other"/> had a confirmed diagnosis of a right-sided pleural effusion, most likely to be a reactive pleural effusion to a right lower lobe pneumonia. </s><s n="s3.3;p40.56">No malignant changes were identified. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="bold">Evidence based care</hi> A brief consideration of the evidence base required for the diagnosis and management of the patient's problem(s)</head><div2><head rend="underlined">Pleural effusions</head><p n="p41.56"><s n="s1.3;p41.56">The pleural cavity is a potential space which normally contains little fluid. </s><s n="s2.3;p41.56">A pleural effusion is an accumulation of fluid within this pleural space. </s><s n="s3.3;p41.56">The fluid may be either transudative or exudative: </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p42.56"><s n="s1.1;p42.56">a transudate results from an alteration in the hydrostatic forces operating across the pleural membrane </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p43.56"><s n="s1.1;p43.56">an exudate results from a change in the permeability of the membrane due to inflammation </s></p><p n="p44.56"><s n="s1.1;p44.56">A pleural effusion will only be detected: </s></p><list type="bulleted"><item>on a chest radiograph when the volume of the effusion exceeds 300 ml </item><item>clinically when the volume exceeds 500 ml</item></list></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">Clinically</head><list type="bulleted"><head>Symptoms:</head><item>may be asymptomatic </item><item>dyspnoea - dependent on size of effusion </item><item>dull chest pain</item></list><p n="p45.56"><s n="s1.1;p45.56">Signs: </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p46.56"><s n="s1.1;p46.56">there may be a displacement of the trachea and the lung apex away from the effusion if it is very large </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p47.56"><s n="s1.1;p47.56">there is reduced movement of the affected side </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p48.56"><s n="s1.1;p48.56">the site of the pleural effusion is dull to percussion; classical stony dullness is not a constant sign </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p49.56"><s n="s1.1;p49.56">there is reduced vocal fremitus over a pleural effusion </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p50.56"><s n="s1.1;p50.56">breath sounds are reduced or absent over a pleural effusion </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p51.56"><s n="s1.1;p51.56">towards the upper part of an effusion there may be signs of consolidation i.e. bronchial breathing and bleating vocal resonance. </s></p><p n="p52.56"><s n="s1.4;p52.56">Malignant pleural effusions indicate a late stage of lung cancer using the TNM staging strategy. </s><s n="s2.4;p52.56">Under the TNM classification, tumour staging at T3 implies a tumour of any size which is invading surrounding structures but not involving the heart, great vessels, oesophagus or vertebral body or a tumour within 2 cm of the carina but not involving the carina. </s><s n="s3.4;p52.56">T4 classification implies a tumour of any size which is invading any of the structures excluded from T3 and the presence of a malignant pleural effusion. </s><s n="s4.4;p52.56">(1) </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">Management</head><p n="p53.56"><s n="s1.4;p53.56">The effusion should be investigated by diagnostic aspiration and the fluid examined for protein content, cell type and bacteria. </s><s n="s2.4;p53.56">If the effusion is an exudate then a pleural biopsy is useful. </s><s n="s3.4;p53.56">If there is a large effusion then symptomatic relief can be achieved via aspiration of the effusion. </s><s n="s4.4;p53.56">A chest drain is an alternative to repeated aspiration - this must be able to drain the base of pleural effusion (1). </s></p><p n="p54.56"><s n="s1.3;p54.56">A systematic review on the effectiveness of management for malignant pleural effusion investigated the best ways in which to carry out pleurodesis for malignant effusions. </s><s n="s2.3;p54.56">It concluded that bleomycin was effective in reducing recurrences and tetracycline (doxycycline) was not superior to bleomycin (2). </s><s n="s3.3;p54.56">The study also looked at strategies such as rolling the patients after instillation of the sclerosing agent, protracted drainage of the effusion and the use of larger chest tubes, which were not found to have any substantial advantages (2). </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="bold">Commentary</hi> A commentary on issues of health care delivery, ethical issues or disability relevant to the patient and/or problem</head><p n="p55.56"><s n="s1.2;p55.56">An important issue raised in this case includes the issue of breaking bad news with regards to a terminal diagnosis. </s><s n="s2.2;p55.56">There was no terminal diagnosis in this case but it was necessary to discuss the possibility that Mr <name type="other"/> had a lung cancer. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="bold">Impact on your learning</hi> Describe what you have learnt from this case</head><list type="bulleted"><item>Differential diagnosis of chest pain. </item><item>Investigations in chest pain. </item><item>Management of pleural effusions. </item></list><p n="p56.56"/></div1></body><back><div1 type="bibliography"><head rend="underlined">References</head><p><seg type="URL" n="www.gpnotebook.com"/>, Visited 15 May 2006. </p><p>Tan C, Sedrakyan A, Browne J, Swift S, Treasure T. The evidence on the effectiveness of management for malignant pleural effusion: a systematic review. Eur J Cardiothorac Surg. 2006 May;29(5):829-838. Epub 2006 Apr 12. </p></div1><div1 type="back text"><head rend="bold">ASPECTS OF CASE AS RECORDED IN SUMMARY OF PORTFOLIO CASES •</head><table id="BAWE_0246g-tab.003"><row><cell/></row></table><p/></div1><div1 type="back text"><head rend="bold">PORTFOLIO COMPLETION CERTIFICATE</head><p rend="bold">Portfolio completion certificated</p><p>I confirm that this student has satisfactorily completed 3 word-processed portfolio cases.</p><p>Signed.....................................................................</p><p> Date......................................................................</p></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
