<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_0246a" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Portfolio 1 - CM</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">proforma</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">4</p><p n="date">2005-10</p><p n="module title">Other Rotations</p><p n="module code">unknown</p><p n="genre family">Case study</p><p n="discipline">Medicine</p><p n="disciplinary group">LS</p><p n="grade">D</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">3024</p><p n="number of s-units">154</p><p n="number of p">77</p><p n="number of tables">3</p><p n="number of figures">0</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">7</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">37</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">19.6</p><p n="average s-units per p">2.0</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">f</p><p n="year of birth">1981</p><p n="first language">English</p><p n="education">UKA</p><p n="course">Medicine</p><p n="student ID">0246</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><docTitle><titlePart><hi rend="bold">PORTFOLIO CASE No:</hi> 12</titlePart></docTitle><titlePart>Patient Initials<name type="other"/> Hospital Number<name type="other"/> Age 70 Gender Male</titlePart><titlePart>Portfolio Case presentation number: 3.4, 3.8 Phase 2 course document objectives(s): 3.1, 3.6, 3.9, 13.9 Has the patient' permission, including for follow up contact by telephone, been sought and recorded in the case notes? <hi rend="bold">The patient's permission has been sought.</hi> </titlePart></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="bold">Referral information</hi> Source of referral and a summary of key information</head><p n="p1.77"><s n="s1.2;p1.77"><name type="other"/> was referred to <name type="other"/> Medical Assessment Unit by his General Practitioner (GP) on <name type="date"/>. </s><s n="s2.2;p1.77">The referral was on the basis of <hi rend="bold">abnormal blood results and obvious jaundice in the skin and sclera.</hi> </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="bold">History</hi> All <hi rend="bold italic">relevant</hi> information gathered from the patient about the presenting illness, co-existing problems, current treatment, <hi rend="italic">significant</hi> past medical history and the social and family background. The patient's view of the nature of the problem and their expectations for treatment. </head><div2><head rend="bold">Presenting Complaint</head><p n="p2.77"><s n="s1.1;p2.77"><name type="other"/> had a <hi rend="bold">2 week history of diarrhoea</hi> which had not resolved, despite improving having taken loperamide. <name type="other"/> had been feeling progressively more tired over the last week. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">History of Presenting Complaint </head><p n="p3.77"><s n="s1.5;p3.77"><name type="other"/> had a <hi rend="bold">2 week history of severe diarrhoea</hi>. </s><s n="s2.5;p3.77">His <hi rend="bold">stool was white in colour, with no blood or mucus</hi> present. </s><s n="s3.5;p3.77"><hi rend="bold">Stool frequency on average was 10 times per day</hi>. </s><s n="s4.5;p3.77">There was <hi rend="bold">no associated abdominal pain</hi>. <name type="other"/> had <hi rend="bold">lost 1 and a half stones</hi> in weight over the <hi rend="bold">past 2 weeks</hi> and he described his appetite as normal, having maintained his normal diet and fluids. </s><s n="s5.5;p3.77">There was no history of nausea or vomiting, no dysphagia, no dyspepsia and no abdominal obvious distension. </s></p><p n="p4.77"><s n="s1.2;p4.77"><name type="other"/> had <hi rend="bold">dark urine</hi> but was passing regularly with <hi rend="bold">no dysuria or haematuria</hi>. <name type="other"/> had <hi rend="bold">yellow sclera and skin for 1 week</hi> prior to his referral to the MAU. There was <hi rend="bold">no history of travel</hi> and <hi rend="bold">no history of recent blood transfusions</hi>. </s><s n="s2.2;p4.77">There had been <hi rend="bold">no contact with other jaundice people</hi> (Hepatitis A and E, Epstein-Barr virus). <name type="other"/> had not eaten any seafood recently. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">Past Medical History </head><list type="bulleted"><item>Hypertension - 2000</item><item>Mild Asthma - 1995</item><item>Appendectomy - 1950s</item><item>No history of diabetes, thyroid problems, rheumatoid arthritis, epilepsy, asthma, myocardial infarction, stroke or TB. </item></list><list type="simple"><head rend="bold">Current Medication</head><item>Ramipril - 5mg <hi rend="italic">od</hi></item><item>Indapamide - 2.5mg <hi rend="italic">od</hi></item><item>Aspirin - 75 mg <hi rend="italic">od</hi></item><item>Ciprofloxacin - 500mg <hi rend="italic">bd</hi></item><item>Loperamide - 2mg <hi rend="italic">prn</hi></item></list><p n="p5.77"><s rend="bold" n="s1.1;p5.77">No known allergies </s></p><p n="p6.77"><s rend="bold" n="s1.1;p6.77">Family History </s></p><p n="p7.77"><s n="s1.1;p7.77">There is no significant family history. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">Social History</head><p n="p8.77"><s n="s1.3;p8.77"><name type="other"/> is an independent married with 1 son and lives with his wife. </s><s n="s2.3;p8.77">He is a retired motor mechanic. </s><s n="s3.3;p8.77">He is a <hi rend="bold">non-smoker</hi> and his <hi rend="bold">alcohol intake has now stopped</hi> (he has <hi rend="bold">reduced his intake to about 2 pints per month</hi> over the <hi rend="bold">past 2-3 years</hi>, <hi rend="bold">previously consuming 5-8pints per week</hi>). <name type="other"/><hi rend="bold">does not use recreational drugs</hi>. </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="bold">Analysis of history</hi> The most likely single cause of the presentation, other possible causes and reasons for these choices. The findings to be looked for on physical examination to help decide the cause.</head><p n="p9.77"><s n="s1.1;p9.77">Based on the acute symptoms <name type="other"/> presented with, the differential diagnoses of pale diarrhoea with weight loss and painless obstructive jaundice include: </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p10.77"><s n="s1.2;p10.77"><hi rend="bold">Malignancy -</hi> Primary: carcinoma of head of pancreas, cholangiocarcinoma. </s><s n="s2.2;p10.77">Secondary: metastases from the colon, stomach, lung or oesophagus. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p11.77"><s n="s1.1;p11.77"><hi rend="bold">Alcoholic liver disease -</hi> e.g. cirrhosis </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p12.77"><s n="s1.1;p12.77"><hi rend="bold">Chronic pancreatitis -</hi> although this most commonly presents with pain. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p13.77"><s rend="bold" n="s1.1;p13.77">Alcoholic hepatitis </s></p><p n="p14.77"><s n="s1.1;p14.77">A number of features along with jaundice help to suggest underlying pathology and include: </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p15.77"><s n="s1.1;p15.77"><hi rend="bold">Presence of abdominal pain</hi> (particularly right upper quadrant) suggestive of bile duct stones. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p16.77"><s n="s1.1;p16.77"><hi rend="bold">Acute onset of abdominal distension with jaundice</hi> suggestive of hepatic vein thrombosis or acute hepatitis. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p17.77"><s n="s1.1;p17.77"><hi rend="bold">Signs of right ventricular failure</hi> (raised JVP, peripheral oedema and a palpable tender liver edge) suggest congestion of the liver with resultant jaundice (+/- liver failure). </s></p><p n="p18.77"><s n="s1.1;p18.77">These features were not present in <name type="other"/>, leading to the most likely cause of his presentation of <hi rend="bold">painless obstructive jaundice with weight loss in the older aged population to be carcinoma of the pancreas, cholangiocarcinoma or enlarged metastatic lymph nodes at the porta hepatis.</hi> </s></p><p n="p19.77"><s n="s1.3;p19.77">The physical examination will look for signs of chronic liver disease (spider naevi, palmar erythema, dupretyon's contracture, caput medusae, gynaecomastia, hepatosplenomegaly and ascites), signs of anaemia and generalised lymphadenopathy. </s><s n="s2.3;p19.77">A PR examination will rule out the possibility of a prostatic or rectal mass. </s><s n="s3.3;p19.77">Palpation of the gall bladder will also indicate a gall bladder obstruction and help determine the presence of gall stones. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="bold">Physical examination</hi> Highlight the findings most relevant to your clinical problem solving by underlining them</head><p n="p20.77"><s n="s1.5;p20.77">On general examination, <name type="other"/> was <hi rend="bold">alert, orientated and comfortable at rest</hi>. </s><s n="s2.5;p20.77"><hi rend="bold">Jaundice was present in the sclera and skin</hi>. </s><s n="s3.5;p20.77">Capillary refill &lt;2secounds. </s><s n="s4.5;p20.77">There were <hi rend="bold">no signs of clubbing, cyanosis or lymphadenopathy.</hi> </s><s n="s5.5;p20.77"><name type="other"/> had <hi rend="bold">pale conjunctiva and pallor, indicative of anaemia.</hi> </s></p><div2><head rend="underlined">Gastrointestinal System</head><p rend="bulleted" n="p21.77"><s n="s1.2;p21.77">The <hi rend="bold">abdomen was soft and non-tender</hi>. </s><s n="s2.2;p21.77">The abdomen was <hi rend="bold">overweight</hi>. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p22.77"><s n="s1.1;p22.77">There was <hi rend="bold">no organomegaly</hi>. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p23.77"><s n="s1.1;p23.77">There were <hi rend="bold">no signs of caput medusae, spider naevi, palmar erythema, Dupuytren's contracture or gynaecomastia.</hi> </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p24.77"><s n="s1.1;p24.77"><hi rend="bold">Yellow pigmentation over the skin</hi>. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p25.77"><s n="s1.1;p25.77">The patient complained of <hi rend="bold">pruritus but no excoriations were visible.</hi> </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p26.77"><s n="s1.1;p26.77"><hi rend="bold">No ascites present</hi>. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p27.77"><s n="s1.1;p27.77">Liver edge was percussed - normal size. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p28.77"><s rend="bold" n="s1.1;p28.77">No masses were palpated. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p29.77"><s n="s1.1;p29.77">Bowel sounds were present. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p30.77"><s rend="bold" n="s1.1;p30.77">PR was normal with no masses, bleeding or mucus. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">Cardiovascular System</head><list type="bulleted"><item rend="bold">Pulse 70 regular</item><item rend="bold">Blood pressure 106/62</item><item rend="bold">Temperature 36.3oC</item><item>Heart Sounds I + II + 0</item><item>JVP - not raised</item></list><p n="p31.77"/></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">Respiratory System</head><list type="bulleted"><item>Respiratory rate <hi rend="bold">18 breaths per minute</hi>. </item><item>Vesicular breath sounds were present. </item><item><hi rend="bold">Chest was clear</hi> - no wheeze/crackles. </item><item>Saturations - 98% on air. </item></list><p n="p32.77"/></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="bold">Analysis of history and examination</hi> Reasons for your choice of the cause of the patient's problem(s) and any other cause that still needs to be considered at this stage</head><p n="p33.77"><s n="s1.6;p33.77">History and examination confirm initial possible causes. </s><s n="s2.6;p33.77">There were <hi rend="bold">no signs of chronic liver disease and no palpable gall bladder.</hi> </s><s n="s3.6;p33.77">According to Courvoisier's Law, if the gall bladder is palpable with painless jaundice, the cause will not be gall stones however, there was too much subcutaneous fat on <name type="other"/>'s abdomen to palpate the gall bladder effectively if it were inflamed. </s><s n="s4.6;p33.77">Therefore a diagnosis involving the gall bladder cannot be ruled out. </s><s n="s5.6;p33.77">The <hi rend="bold">bright yellow hue of <name type="other"/>'s jaundice indicates that his jaundice is acute jaundice.</hi> </s><s n="s6.6;p33.77">Due to the presence of dark urine and pale stools, we know that <name type="other"/> has obstructive jaundice. </s></p><p n="p34.77"><s n="s1.1;p34.77">Post-hepatic (obstructive) causes of jaundice include: </s></p><list type="simple"><head rend="bold">Intra-hepatic - Cholangiocarcinoma</head><item rend="bold"> Primary Biliary Cirrhosis</item></list><list type="simple"><head rend="bold">Extra-hepatic - Carcinoma of the head of pancreas</head><item rend="bold"> Enlarged lymph nodes at the porta hepatis</item></list></div1><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="bold">Formulation of the patient's problem(s)</hi> Encapsulate this in physical, psychological and social terms (the triple diagnosis)</head><p n="p35.77"><s n="s1.3;p35.77"><hi rend="bold">Physical -</hi> Physically, <name type="other"/> does not feel too unwell. </s><s n="s2.3;p35.77">The lethargy he has been experiencing over the last 2-3 weeks has restricted him in that he has felt too tired to try and do lots of things but he does not feel that he has any physical problems. </s><s n="s3.3;p35.77">He stressed that he still feels quite fit and well. </s></p><p n="p36.77"><s n="s1.3;p36.77"><hi rend="bold">Psychological</hi> - <name type="other"/> was initially at presentation to MAU very upbeat and did not appear very worried about his jaundice and believed it to be hepatitis related. </s><s n="s2.3;p36.77">He did not feel too unwell although his sever diarrhoea was worrying him. <name type="other"/> was not aware of the seriousness of his complaint when he was first referred but despite being informed about his diagnosis he remained quite upbeat whilst he was an in-patient. </s><s n="s3.3;p36.77">He has a lot of support from his family and has been on weekend leave in between further investigations and treatment. </s></p><p n="p37.77"><s n="s1.2;p37.77"><hi rend="bold">Social - </hi><name type="other"/> found his severe diarrhoea prior to admission difficult to deal with. </s><s n="s2.2;p37.77">He was restricted to his home because he was having to go to the toilet so often. <name type="other"/> has very supportive family and friends who live nearby and who have been visiting him regularly. <name type="other"/> is able to take weekend leave from the hospital. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="bold">Management</hi> Use the framework of RAPRIOP to structure your proposed management. Refer to the guidelines to the writing of portfolio cases for the details of the issues to be addressed under each heading.</head><div2><head rend="bold">Investigations</head><p n="p38.77"><s rend="bold" n="s1.1;p38.77"><name type="other"/>'s blood biochemistry results on following admission (<name type="date"/>) were as follows: </s></p><table id="BAWE_0246a-tab.001"><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p39.77"><s rend="bold" n="s1.1;p39.77"><name type="other"/>'s blood results following admission (<name type="date"/>) were as follows: </s></p><table id="BAWE_0246a-tab.002"><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p40.77"><s rend="bold" n="s1.1;p40.77"><name type="other"/>'s tumour marker results following admission (<name type="date"/>) were as follows: </s></p><table id="BAWE_0246a-tab.003"><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p41.77"><s n="s1.2;p41.77">Tumour markers are rarely sufficiently specific to be diagnostic but are a good way to monitor the course of an illness and the effectiveness of treatment. </s><s n="s2.2;p41.77">CA 19-9 is typically raised in colorectal carcinoma, pancreatic carcinoma and cholestasis. </s></p><p n="p42.77"><s n="s1.1;p42.77">High alkaline phosphatase and bilirubin is seen in cholangiocarcinoma indicating cholestatic jaundice. </s></p><p n="p43.77"><s n="s1.1;p43.77">Ultrasound investigation following admission detailed: </s></p><div3><head rend="underlined">Abdomen </head><p rend="bulleted" n="p44.77"><s n="s1.1;p44.77">Dilated intrahepatic biliary ducts, dilated gall bladder, no stones, small amount of ascites. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p45.77"><s n="s1.1;p45.77">Liver, spleen and both kidneys appear normal. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p46.77"><s n="s1.1;p46.77">Pancreas not seen due to overlying adipose tissue. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p47.77"><s n="s1.2;p47.77">Appearance either: 1. </s><s n="s2.2;p47.77">Lesion in the ampulla of Vater </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p48.77"><s n="s1.2;p48.77">2. </s><s n="s2.2;p48.77">Stone in distal CBD causing back pressure. </s></p></div3><div3><head rend="underlined">X-ray of the Chest</head><p rend="bulleted" n="p49.77"><s n="s1.1;p49.77">Heart normal size. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p50.77"><s n="s1.1;p50.77">Lungs clear. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p51.77"><s n="s1.1;p51.77">No obvious ribs fractures or pneumothorax. </s></p><p n="p52.77"><s n="s1.6;p52.77">ERCP was performed on the <name type="date"/> and revealed that the preliminary diagnosis is of a malignant neoplasm of the liver, intrahepatic bile ducts. </s><s n="s2.6;p52.77">A 1cm long hepatic hilar biliary stricture due to cholangiocarcinoma was found (A Klatskin tumour). </s><s n="s3.6;p52.77">The right intra-hepatic duct was dilated. </s><s n="s4.6;p52.77">There was no filling of the left intrahepatic duct. </s><s n="s5.6;p52.77">The CBD was normal. </s><s n="s6.6;p52.77">A stent was inserted into the right hepatic duct. </s></p><p n="p53.77"><s n="s1.1;p53.77">CT investigation revealed: </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p54.77"><s n="s1.1;p54.77">Marked dilatation of the intrahepatic bile ducts. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p55.77"><s n="s1.1;p55.77">Poorly seen small soft tissue mass at the top of the CHD. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p56.77"><s n="s1.1;p56.77">Appearance highly suspicious of a Klatskin tumour (Cholangiocarcinoma) </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p57.77"><s n="s1.1;p57.77">A number of small nodes were seen at the porta, ranging up to 1.4cm and 1.2cm celiac nodes. </s></p></div3></div2><div2><head rend="bold">Reassurance and Explanation</head><p n="p58.77"><s n="s1.5;p58.77">To appropriately reassure <name type="other"/> I would say: "As you know, you have been suffering from jaundice and diarrhoea for 2 weeks now and we would like to get to the bottom of what is causing this problem. </s><s n="s2.5;p58.77">There are a number of possibilities that could be causing your symptoms and we would like to investigate them all. </s><s n="s3.5;p58.77">There are a number of causes of jaundice, some of them benign and some of them malignant and looking at your clinical picture and the story you have told us, we cannot rule out the possibility that you may have a cancer that is obstructing your bile system, which is why you are suffering from jaundice. </s><s n="s4.5;p58.77">We are going to carry out a number of different blood tests and investigations to look inside at your liver, gall bladder and pancreas. </s><s n="s5.5;p58.77">For the moment we will make you as comfortable as possible and given you some medication to help reduce your itching". </s></p><p n="p59.77"><s n="s1.5;p59.77">To explain the nature of the disease: "Following all of your investigations, we have confirmed your diagnosis as a cancer, known as cholangiocarcinoma, which is originating from the central bile duct. </s><s n="s2.5;p59.77">Such a cancer causes stasis in the bile fluid, blocking its flow, which is why you have become jaundice. </s><s n="s3.5;p59.77">Unfortunately, this type of cancer often grows without any symptoms, which is why you have been feeling well up until the 2 weeks before you came in to MAU. The causes of this cancer are unknown and they are a relatively uncommon tumour. </s><s n="s4.5;p59.77">It is difficult to say how the cancer will affect you but I am sorry to have to tell you that it will shorten the length of your life. </s><s n="s5.5;p59.77">Tumours such as these are difficult to manage but your quality of life may be improved by palliative measures such as the insertion of biliary stents and antibiotics to prevent infection". </s></p><p n="p60.77"><s n="s1.5;p60.77">To describe the management plan: "The options we have to manage this cancer include the relief of the biliary obstruction so to relieve your jaundice by using a stent, which we can place during a camera test. </s><s n="s2.5;p60.77">It may also be possible to surgically remove of the tumour but this can be very difficult. </s><s n="s3.5;p60.77">Unfortunately for this type of cancer, radiotherapy and chemotherapy are not helpful and are not used. </s><s n="s4.5;p60.77">Our aim is to investigate the extent of the tumour and then place a stent in the duct in order to improve the flow of bile. </s><s n="s5.5;p60.77">We will also refer you to the oncologists at Walsgrave where they can be involved in your care". </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">Prescription/Medical Intervention</head><p n="p61.77"><s n="s1.3;p61.77">On admission to <name type="other"/>, <name type="other"/> was prescribed Ciprofloxacin (500mg) and Loperamide (2mg) and an anti-histamine (chlorpheniramine) for his jaundice-induced pruritus. </s><s n="s2.3;p61.77">During his admission, <name type="other"/> underwent an ERCP, CT and ultrasound of his abdomen and chest. </s><s n="s3.3;p61.77">A stent was placed in his right hepatic duct and he had a sphincterectomy. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">Observation</head><p n="p62.77"><s n="s1.3;p62.77">Following admission from MAU, <name type="other"/> was required to remain as an inpatient until the cause of his jaundice and diarrhoea was found. </s><s n="s2.3;p62.77">Following the results of the investigations (ERCP, CT, Ultrasound) it was important to observe whether <name type="other"/> jaundice lessened, indicating that the stent applied during ERCP was working. </s><s n="s3.3;p62.77">It is also important to monitor <name type="other"/>'s blood results and liver function tests. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">Referral and Team Working</head><p n="p63.77"><s n="s1.2;p63.77"><name type="other"/> was referred to the care of the oncologists at the <name type="other"/> Hospital in order for them to best manage his condition. </s><s n="s2.2;p63.77">Referrals that may have to be made in the future include referrals to the palliative care team and the upper gastrointestinal surgeons. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">Advice and Prevention</head><p n="p64.77"><s n="s1.3;p64.77"><name type="other"/> should be advised and informed about the clinical progression of his condition. </s><s n="s2.3;p64.77">If he wishes to include his family in these discussions it should be made possible for the diagnosis to be discussed with himself and his family members. </s><s n="s3.3;p64.77">Thorough and detailed information should be given regarding is medication (e.g. concordance with his anti-histamine medication to help reduce the itching he experiences with his jaundice) and the pain relief he may require in the later stages of his diagnosis. </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="bold">Outcome</hi> A description of the progress of the patient as far as possible. This should include consideration of further issues to be resolved. Where appropriate you should contact by telephone patients who have been discharged home.</head><p n="p65.77"><s n="s1.2;p65.77"><name type="other"/> had a confirmed diagnosis of cholangiocarcinoma with the use of CT and ERCP. At present he remains jaundice despite the placement of a stent in the right hepatic duct. <name type="other"/> has remained an inpatient since <name type="date"/>. </s><s n="s2.2;p65.77">He has been on weekend leave to spend time with his family. <name type="other"/> was transferred to the <name type="date"/> Hospital on <name type="date"/>. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="bold">Evidence based care</hi> A brief consideration of the evidence base required for the diagnosis and management of the patient's problem(s)</head><p n="p66.77"><s n="s1.10;p66.77">Cholangiocarcinomas are adenomas of the bile ducts associated with dense fibrous tissue. </s><s n="s2.10;p66.77">They can be intra-hepatic (arising from the bile ducts), central (hilar) or extra-hepatic. </s><s n="s3.10;p66.77">Cholangiocarcinomas are uncommon tumours; 8-10% of primary liver tumours. </s><s n="s4.10;p66.77">Such malignancies are representative of approximately 1% of all carcinomas (1). </s><s n="s5.10;p66.77">As in the case of <name type="other"/>, the extra-hepatic tumours present with progressive jaundice with associated clinical features of weight loss, malaise and nausea and vomiting. </s><s n="s6.10;p66.77">The disease spreads by the local lymphatics of by local extension. </s><s n="s7.10;p66.77">The patients with hilar cholangiocarcinoma are frequently elderly in the 6 <hi rend="sup">th</hi> or 7 <hi rend="sup">th</hi> decade and present with jaundice in more than 90% of cases (2). </s><s n="s8.10;p66.77">The jaundice is frequently 'painless' and only around one third of the patients complain of pain in the right upper quadrant. </s><s n="s9.10;p66.77">Itching is reported in 30-70% of patients (3). </s><s n="s10.10;p66.77">The clinical course is progressive and death from liver failure or cholangitis is in 6 months to 1 year if the biliary obstruction is unrelieved. </s></p><p n="p67.77"><s n="s1.7;p67.77">To establish the diagnosis and appropriate management in a patient suspected to have hilar cholangiocarcinoma on clinical presentation and initial imaging it is necessary to identify candidates for curative resection and to plan appropriate palliative care for the remaining individuals. </s><s n="s2.7;p67.77">The parameters that need further investigation include an assessment of the patient's fitness for undergoing major surgery, the extent of bile duct involvement, the involvement of the common hepatic artery or main portal vein at the hepatic hilum and the lymph nodes and distant metastases. </s><s n="s3.7;p67.77">ERCP is required for diagnosis as ultrasound shows features of dilated bile ducts or lesions within the liver parenchyma, which are not specific to cholangiocarcinoma. </s><s n="s4.7;p67.77">The prognosis of cholangiocarcinoma is poor and the survival is rarely more than 6 months. </s><s n="s5.7;p67.77">The treatment options are limited and usually palliative. </s><s n="s6.7;p67.77">Radical resection of the extra-hepatic tumours can offer a cure but this is rare. </s><s n="s7.7;p67.77">Symptomatic relief of the jaundice and an improvement in the quality of life is achieved by the insertion of endoprostheses (stent) during ERCP in order to re-establish the flow of bile. </s></p><p n="p68.77"><s n="s1.6;p68.77">A small proportion of cholangiocarcinoma are surgically resectable but those at the hilar region (as <name type="other"/>'s was) are less likely to be operable than those in the distal bile duct. </s><s n="s2.6;p68.77">The greater proportion of patient treatment is palliative with the response to chemotherapy and radiotherapy being poor. </s><s n="s3.6;p68.77">Relief of the bile duct obstruction has been shown to improve quality of life (1) considerably and along with pain control this is the end-point of palliation. </s><s n="s4.6;p68.77">The World Health Organisation describes the essence of palliative medicine to involve improve the quality of life of a patient faced with a terminal diagnosis and to provide a relief from any pain and symptoms. </s><s n="s5.6;p68.77">Alongside the patient, palliative care should also incorporate the needs of the family and/or the caregiver. </s><s n="s6.6;p68.77">In patients in whom the quality of life is preserved or improved a survival benefit is more likely (4), with this in mind, the aims of palliation in unresectable hilar cholangiocarcinoma is to: </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p69.77"><s n="s1.2;p69.77">1. </s><s n="s2.2;p69.77">Provide relief from </s></p><list type="bulleted"><item> - obstructive jaundice</item><item> - pruritis</item><item> - cholangitis</item><item> - pain</item></list><p rend="ordered" n="p70.77"><s n="s1.2;p70.77">2. </s><s n="s2.2;p70.77">Prolongation of life with the aim of improving the quality of life. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="bold">Commentary</hi> A commentary on issues of health care delivery, ethical issues or disability relevant to the patient and/or problem</head><p n="p71.77"><s n="s1.4;p71.77">Important issues raised by this case include issues of health care delivery in the aspects of waiting times for CT scans for individuals with a terminal diagnosis. </s><s n="s2.4;p71.77">I found it very surprising that, in a patient where staging and investigation into the extent of his cancer was critical not only to his management but also for himself and his family, that he had to wait almost 2 weeks for a CT scan. </s><s n="s3.4;p71.77">It is important to consider how health care is delivered to these individuals and to understand that if at all possible, patients do not, on the whole like to be in hospital any longer than they need to be and in terminal diagnoses this should not be overlooked while individuals have to wait for investigations that they should perhaps get priority for. </s><s n="s4.4;p71.77">Other issues of interest involve the delivery of palliative care and the aspect of "breaking bad news" and how and where is a good place to discuss such subjects with the patients and their families. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="bold">Impact on your learning</hi> Describe what you have learnt from this case</head><p rend="ordered" n="p72.77"><s n="s1.1;p72.77">Importance of acute severe diarrhoea and painless jaundice on presentation. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p73.77"><s n="s1.1;p73.77">The need for thorough investigations and continued blood tests. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p74.77"><s n="s1.1;p74.77">The importance of medication for the relief of symptoms. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p75.77"><s n="s1.1;p75.77">Differential diagnoses of jaundice. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p76.77"><s n="s1.1;p76.77">Details of cholangiocarcinoma. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p77.77"><s n="s1.1;p77.77">Aspects of management for palliative care. </s></p></div1></body><back><div1 type="bibliography"><head rend="underlined">References</head><p>Kumar and Clark, Clincal Medicine. </p><p>Singhal D., Van Gulik TM., Gouma DJ. Palliative management of hilar cholangiocarcinoma. Surgical Oncology, 14 (2005) 59-74. </p><p>Chamberlain JS., Blumgart LH. Hilar cholangiocarcinoma: a review and commentary. Annals of Surgical Oncology 2000; 7 (1): 55-66. </p><p>Khan SA., Davidson BR., Goldin R., et al. Guidelines for the diagnosis and treatment of cholangiocarcinoma: consensus document. Gut 2002;5 (Suppl 6):VI1-9. </p></div1><div1 type="back text"><head rend="bold">ASPECTS OF CASE AS RECORDED IN SUMMARY OF PORTFOLIO CASES •</head><table id="BAWE_0246a-tab.004"><row><cell/></row></table><p/></div1><div1 type="back text"><head rend="bold">PORTFOLIO COMPLETION CERTIFICATE</head><p rend="bold">Portfolio completion certificated</p><p>I confirm that this student has satisfactorily completed 3 word-processed portfolio cases.</p><p>Signed.....................................................................</p><p> Date......................................................................</p></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
