<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_0246f" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Portfolio 22 - RH</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">proforma</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">4</p><p n="date">2006-06</p><p n="module title">Other Rotations</p><p n="module code">unknown</p><p n="genre family">Case study</p><p n="discipline">Medicine</p><p n="disciplinary group">LS</p><p n="grade">D</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">2599</p><p n="number of s-units">141</p><p n="number of p">49</p><p n="number of tables">1</p><p n="number of figures">0</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">4</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">10</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">18.4</p><p n="average s-units per p">2.9</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">f</p><p n="year of birth">1981</p><p n="first language">English</p><p n="education">UKA</p><p n="course">Medicine</p><p n="student ID">0246</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><docTitle><titlePart><hi rend="bold">PORTFOLIO CASE No:</hi> 17</titlePart></docTitle><titlePart>Patient Initials<name type="other"/> Hospital Number<name type="other"/> Age 88 Gender Female</titlePart><titlePart>Portfolio Case presentation number: 9 Phase 2 course document objectives(s): 9.1 Has the patient' permission, including for follow up contact by telephone, been sought and recorded in the case notes? <hi rend="bold">The patient's permission has been sought.</hi> </titlePart></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="bold">Referral information</hi> Source of referral and a summary of key information</head><p n="p1.49"><s n="s1.2;p1.49">Mrs <name type="other"/> was referred to the Dermatologists at <name type="other"/> Hospital from <name type="other"/> Hospital after being in their care for 3 years. </s><s n="s2.2;p1.49">Mrs <name type="other"/><hi rend="bold">first presented with dry skin and erythematous patches in <name type="date"/></hi>. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="bold">History</hi> All <hi rend="bold italic">relevant</hi> information gathered from the patient about the presenting illness, co-existing problems, current treatment, <hi rend="italic">significant</hi> past medical history and the social and family background. The patient's view of the nature of the problem and their expectations for treatment. </head><div2><head rend="bold">Presenting Complaint </head><p n="p2.49"><s n="s1.2;p2.49">Mrs <name type="other"/> presented to <name type="other"/> Hospital dermatology clinic on <name type="date"/> with a <hi rend="bold">history of worsening itching over the past 2-3 weeks</hi> on areas that were <hi rend="bold">previously dry and erythematous.</hi> </s><s rend="bold" n="s2.2;p2.49">There were blisters on her right leg. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">History of Presenting Complaint </head><p n="p3.49"><s n="s1.13;p3.49">Mrs <name type="other"/> had been suffering from <hi rend="bold">this skin complaint since <name type="date"/></hi>, when she first noticed <hi rend="bold">dry, erythematous patches on her arms and legs.</hi> </s><s n="s2.13;p3.49">Mrs <name type="other"/> also had <hi rend="bold">dry, scaly skin on her scalp and diffuse erythema.</hi> </s><s n="s3.13;p3.49">The <hi rend="bold">soles of her feet were extremely dry.</hi> </s><s n="s4.13;p3.49">In the first year of the complaint, Mrs <name type="other"/> had severe dry skin on the backs of her arms, back of the legs, back, chest and upper arms. </s><s n="s5.13;p3.49">There was scaling on her feet and toenail dystrophy was present. </s><s n="s6.13;p3.49">The toenails were white-yellow in colour. </s><s n="s7.13;p3.49"><hi rend="bold">In <name type="date"/> the patches were still there and became itchier and they remained there for approximately 7 months</hi>. </s><s n="s8.13;p3.49">In <hi rend="bold"><name type="date"/>, Mrs <name type="other"/> had areas covered in papules and excoriations on her back, back of legs and the backs of the arms</hi>. </s><s n="s9.13;p3.49">Bullae had also appeared on her right lower leg. </s><s n="s10.13;p3.49">In <hi rend="bold"><name type="date"/>, these areas changed to urticarial, transient papules</hi> and were consequently treated with a course of steroids and anti-histamines. </s><s n="s11.13;p3.49">Mrs <name type="other"/> was <hi rend="bold">now experiencing blistering on her feet, arms, back and knees.</hi> </s><s n="s12.13;p3.49">The <hi rend="bold">areas had become very itchy.</hi> </s><s rend="bold" n="s13.13;p3.49">There was widespread patchy urticated erythema. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">Past Medical History</head><list type="bulleted"><item>History of childhood flexural eczema</item><item>Hypertension</item><item>Left eye cataract</item><item>Right total hip replacement</item><item>No history of diabetes, thyroid problems, rheumatoid arthritis, asthma, myocardial infarction, or stroke. </item></list><p n="p4.49"/></div2><div2><head rend="bold">Current Medication</head><list type="simple"><item>Lisinopril (10mg <hi rend="italic">od</hi>) and hydrochlorthiazide (12.5mg <hi rend="italic">od</hi>)</item><item>Flecainide - 50mg <hi rend="italic">bd</hi></item><item>Dermovate - 30g on feet (topical)</item><item>Bisoprolol - 5mg <hi rend="italic">od</hi></item><item>Prednisolone - 5mg <hi rend="italic">od</hi></item><item>Omeprazole - 20mg <hi rend="italic">od</hi></item><item>Fosamax - 5mg <hi rend="italic">od </hi></item><item>Amoxicillin - <hi rend="italic">50mg </hi></item><item>Doxazosin </item></list><p n="p5.49"><s rend="bold" n="s1.1;p5.49">No known allergies. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">Family History </head><p n="p6.49"><s n="s1.1;p6.49">No significant family history </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">Social History</head><p n="p7.49"><s n="s1.3;p7.49">Mrs <name type="other"/> is widowed and lives alone. </s><s n="s2.3;p7.49">She is supported by her daughter. </s><s n="s3.3;p7.49">Mrs <name type="other"/> does not smoke or drink alcohol. </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="bold">Analysis of history</hi> The most likely single cause of the presentation, other possible causes and reasons for these choices. The findings to be looked for on physical examination to help decide the cause.</head><p n="p8.49"><s n="s1.3;p8.49">Mrs <name type="other"/> had no previous history of any skin condition. </s><s n="s2.3;p8.49">When her skin complaints first started, she was treated with a course of steroids and anti-histamines, which initially worked to treat her problems. </s><s n="s3.3;p8.49">Following that, the erythematous areas become itchier and eventually began to blister. </s></p><p n="p9.49"><s n="s1.2;p9.49">Based on the history, there are a number of possible causes for Mrs <name type="other"/>'s presentation. </s><s n="s2.2;p9.49">These causes include: </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p10.49"><s rend="bold" n="s1.4;p10.49">Bullous Pemphigoid. </s><s rend="bold" n="s2.4;p10.49">Chronic and not uncommon blistering eruption of the elderly. </s><s rend="bold" n="s3.4;p10.49">Tense large blisters arise on red or normal-looking skin, often of the limbs, trunk and flexures. </s><s rend="bold" n="s4.4;p10.49">A urticarial eruption may precede the onset of blistering. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p11.49"><s rend="bold" n="s1.6;p11.49">Dermatitis Herpetiformis (DH). </s><s n="s2.6;p11.49">The uncommon eruption of symmetrical, itchy blisters on the extensor surfaces. </s><s n="s3.6;p11.49">Jejunal villous atrophy is an associated finding in most cases. </s><s n="s4.6;p11.49">DH usually presents in the third to fourth decade and is twice as common in males as it is in females. </s><s n="s5.6;p11.49">The classical onset is with groups of small, intensely itchy vesicles on the elbows, knees, buttocks and scalp. </s><s n="s6.6;p11.49">The blisters are often broken by scratching to leave excoriations. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p12.49"><s rend="bold" n="s1.3;p12.49">Linear IgA Disease. </s><s n="s2.3;p12.49">A rare heterozygous condition of blisters and urticarial lesions on the back or extensor surfaces. </s><s n="s3.3;p12.49">The disorder responds to dapsone (an antileprotic drug effective in DH) and may resemble DH or Pemphigoid. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p13.49"><s rend="bold" n="s1.4;p13.49">Pemphigus. </s><s n="s2.4;p13.49">Tends to affect the middle-aged or younger people so this differential diagnosis is least likely in Mrs <name type="other"/>. </s><s n="s3.4;p13.49">Cutaneous blistering is seen with flaccid superficial blisters on the scalp, face, back, chest and flexures. </s><s n="s4.4;p13.49">The lesions may consist of crusted erosions. </s></p><p n="p14.49"><s n="s1.4;p14.49">On physical examination it is important to look over the whole of the body for the full representation of the skin problems. </s><s n="s2.4;p14.49">You should look for current blisters and feel how tense they are. </s><s n="s3.4;p14.49">You should feel the erythematous areas to distinguish their surfaces and look if the skin is excoriated, flaky/scaly or inflamed. </s><s n="s4.4;p14.49">Looking for signs of infection (pus/weeping areas) is also important. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="bold">Physical examination</hi> Highlight the findings most relevant to your clinical problem solving by underlining them</head><p n="p15.49"><s n="s1.2;p15.49">On general examination, Mrs <name type="other"/> was alert and orientated at rest. </s><s n="s2.2;p15.49">There were no signs of jaundice, clubbing, cyanosis, lymphadenopathy or anaemia. </s></p><div2><head rend="underlined">Dermatological Examination</head><p n="p16.49"><s rend="bold" n="s1.5;p16.49">There were erythematous plaques on the back, feet, legs and arms. </s><s rend="bold" n="s2.5;p16.49">Blisters had been present on the back and feet but there were no visible blisters at the time of examination. </s><s n="s3.5;p16.49">When the blisters were present they were tense on palpation. </s><s n="s4.5;p16.49">There was no scarring on the sites where the blisters had been. </s><s n="s5.5;p16.49">The <hi rend="bold">skin was dry and scaly.</hi> </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">Cardiovascular System</head><list type="bulleted"><item rend="bold">Pulse 74 regular</item><item rend="bold">Blood pressure 130/60</item><item rend="bold">Temperature 36.7oC</item><item>Heart Sounds I + II + 0</item><item>JVP - not raised</item></list><p n="p17.49"/></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">Respiratory System</head><p rend="bulleted" n="p18.49"><s n="s1.1;p18.49">Respiratory rate <hi rend="bold">17 breaths per minute</hi>. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p19.49"><s rend="bold" n="s1.1;p19.49">Chest was clear. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p20.49"><s rend="bold" n="s1.1;p20.49">Vesicular breath sounds were present. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p21.49"><s rend="bold" n="s1.1;p21.49">Air entry equal. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">Gastrointestinal System</head><p rend="bulleted" n="p22.49"><s n="s1.1;p22.49">Abdomen was <hi rend="bold">soft and non-tender.</hi> </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p23.49"><s n="s1.1;p23.49">Bowel sounds present. </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="bold">Analysis of history and examination</hi> Reasons for your choice of the cause of the patient's problem(s) and any other cause that still needs to be considered at this stage</head><p n="p24.49"><s n="s1.5;p24.49">Mrs <name type="other"/>'s skin complaint has now been progressing over a period of 3 year. </s><s n="s2.5;p24.49">On examination at initial presentation, the blisters were indicative of subepidermal blisters because of their tense nature. </s><s n="s3.5;p24.49">The year long history with dry erythematous patches with itching and then blistering later in its course are a typical presentation of bullous pemphigoid. </s><s n="s4.5;p24.49">The urticarial eruption is also typical of bullous pemphigoid. </s><s n="s5.5;p24.49">Mrs <name type="other"/>'s age increases the likelihood of the diagnosis being BP. </s></p><p n="p25.49"><s n="s1.1;p25.49">At this stage, the most likely cause of Mrs <name type="other"/>'s presentation remains as bullous pemphigoid. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="bold">Formulation of the patient's problem(s)</hi> Encapsulate this in physical, psychological and social terms (the triple diagnosis)</head><p n="p26.49"><s n="s1.3;p26.49"><hi rend="bold">Physical</hi> - Mrs <name type="other"/>'s physical health was not affected by her skin complaint. </s><s n="s2.3;p26.49">She felt quite fit and healthy despite the blisters on her skin and the itching she was experiencing. </s><s n="s3.3;p26.49">Mrs <name type="other"/> had been feeling more tired recently. </s></p><p n="p27.49"><s n="s1.3;p27.49"><hi rend="bold">Psychological -</hi> Mrs <name type="other"/> was quite worried about her skin, especially that the blisters may leave scars. </s><s n="s2.3;p27.49">She was anxious about the steroids she had to take and did not want to put any weight or have bad side effects from them. </s><s n="s3.3;p27.49">Following the immunofluorescence studies Mrs <name type="other"/> felt more at ease knowing that a label had been put on her skin complaint and she could be given a diagnosis. </s></p><p n="p28.49"><s n="s1.3;p28.49"><hi rend="bold">Social -</hi> Mrs <name type="other"/> had a lot of support from her family and felt well supported. </s><s n="s2.3;p28.49">She was otherwise a relatively healthy lady. </s><s n="s3.3;p28.49">Mrs <name type="other"/> was pleased that she had not had any blisters on her face and she felt that she was still able to do most of the things she would normally do in her life. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="bold">Management</hi> Use the framework of RAPRIOP to structure your proposed management. Refer to the guidelines to the writing of portfolio cases for the details of the issues to be addressed under each heading.</head><div2><head rend="bold">Investigations</head><table id="BAWE_0246f-tab.001"><head rend="bold">Mrs <name type="other"/>'s blood results on following referral (<name type="date"/>) were as follows:</head><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p29.49"><s rend="italic" n="s1.1;p29.49">'L' represents a 'Low' reading, 'H' represents a 'High' reading. </s></p><p n="p30.49"><s n="s1.1;p30.49">Thiopurine methyl transferase (TPMT) activity (Azathioprine intolerance) - <hi rend="bold">28mmol-MTG/gHb/h (25-55 normal range).</hi> </s></p><p n="p31.49"><s n="s1.5;p31.49">There was no growth on culture. </s><s n="s2.5;p31.49">A skin incision from the right calf exposed to immunofluorescence studies revealed weak positive staining for C3 in keeping with but not the diagnosis of Bullous Pemphigoid. </s><s n="s3.5;p31.49">IgG negative, IgA negative and IgM negative. </s><s n="s4.5;p31.49">Fibrin was negative. </s><s n="s5.5;p31.49">C3 weak positive staining was on the epidermal basement membrane. </s></p><p n="p32.49"><s n="s1.2;p32.49">The microscopy report revealed no established bullae, some significant eosinophilic infiltrate around the junction of reticular papillary dermis with occasional groups of Eosinophils in dermo-epidermal region. </s><s n="s2.2;p32.49">In the absence of the bullae, no definitive diagnosis was made from this biopsy. </s></p><p n="p33.49"><s n="s1.1;p33.49">The TPMT activity test confirmed that there had been no low enzyme activity from the azathioprine treatment Mrs <name type="other"/> had received in September. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">Reassurance and Explanation</head><p n="p34.49"><s n="s1.3;p34.49">To appropriately reassure the patient I would say: "As you know, you have been suffering from this skin complaint for some time now and we have diagnosed a condition known as Bullous Pemphigoid. </s><s n="s2.3;p34.49">This condition is not uncommon in people of your age range and it is manageable, with a time course of approximately 2 years. </s><s n="s3.3;p34.49">We are able to treat the condition in the out-patient department and you will be able to get in touch with the Dermatologists should there be any other problems or further outbreaks of the blisters". </s></p><p n="p35.49"><s n="s1.5;p35.49">To explain the nature of the condition: "Bullous Pemphigoid is a chronic, not uncommon blistering eruption affecting the older population. </s><s n="s2.5;p35.49">It is the result of an immune reaction in your body whereby antibodies in the body attack components of your skin. </s><s n="s3.5;p35.49">These results in the blisters that you have been experiencing on you skin. </s><s n="s4.5;p35.49">These blisters commonly affect the limbs, trunk and flexures as they have in you and they can arise on normal or reddened skin. </s><s n="s5.5;p35.49">The disease is a self-limiting disease in about 50% of people and the medication we prescribe can usually be stopped within 2 years". </s></p><p n="p36.49"><s n="s1.5;p36.49">To describe the management plan: "To manage your Bullous Pemphigoid we would like to put you on some steroid medication that can be taken orally. </s><s n="s2.5;p36.49">Bullous Pemphigoid responds to a relatively low dose of steroids (30-60mg oral prednisolone, reduced to 10mg within weeks). </s><s n="s3.5;p36.49">If the blisters do not respond very well to the steroids, another drug called azathioprine can be prescribed, which suppresses your immune system. </s><s n="s4.5;p36.49">If we prescribe azathioprine we will have to carry out regular blood tests in order to assess you liver functions because the drug can cause some side-effects. </s><s n="s5.5;p36.49">We will continue to see you in the outpatient departments under the care of the dermatologists to make sure that the medication is working and that you aren't having any further outbreaks of blisters". </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">Prescription/Medical Intervention</head><p n="p37.49"><s n="s1.3;p37.49">Mrs <name type="other"/> was first prescribed the steroid prednisolone 30mg daily, which was to be reduced gradually over the following weeks to 5mg daily. </s><s n="s2.3;p37.49">Fosamax 5mg (a bisphosphonate to reduce the rate of bone turnover, used prophylactically with the use of azathioprine) was also prescribed daily. </s><s n="s3.3;p37.49">Following the eruption of more blisters, azathioprine was prescribed. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">Observation</head><p n="p38.49"><s n="s1.3;p38.49">Mrs <name type="other"/> was kept under the care of the dermatologists with follow-up out patient appointments. </s><s n="s2.3;p38.49">The eruptions of new blisters were monitored at the clinic appointments. </s><s n="s3.3;p38.49">Mrs <name type="other"/> will remain under observation until she is in complete remission and off all treatment. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">Referral and Team Working</head><p n="p39.49"><s n="s1.3;p39.49">Mrs <name type="other"/> was referred to the dermatologists and will remain under their care until the blisters have healed. </s><s n="s2.3;p39.49">The disease is self-limiting in the majority of cases and the steroids can usually be stopped after two years. </s><s n="s3.3;p39.49">The medication and treatment plan will be shared with Mrs <name type="other"/>'s GP. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">Advice and Prevention</head><p n="p40.49"><s n="s1.3;p40.49">Mrs <name type="other"/> should be advised to try and not scratch or pop the blisters and to take her prednisolone as instructed. </s><s n="s2.3;p40.49">Steroid-induced side-effects should also be monitored for and the dermatologists contacted if any side-effects present. </s><s n="s3.3;p40.49">Having started azathioprine, Mrs <name type="other"/> should be advised to get regular blood tests, every month due to the possibility of side-effects. </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="bold">Outcome</hi> A description of the progress of the patient as far as possible. This should include consideration of further issues to be resolved. Where appropriate you should contact by telephone patients who have been discharged home.</head><p n="p41.49"><s n="s1.7;p41.49">Mrs <name type="other"/> has remained under the care of the Dermatologists at <name type="other"/>. </s><s n="s2.7;p41.49">Mrs <name type="other"/> attends regular clinic appointment to follow the progress of her treatment and the eruption of new blisters. </s><s n="s3.7;p41.49">Mrs <name type="other"/> was diagnosed with Bullous Pemphigoid. </s><s n="s4.7;p41.49">Mrs <name type="other"/> was started on a course of azathioprine. </s><s n="s5.7;p41.49">Mrs <name type="other"/> will continue to be followed up in out-patient appointments until the affected areas are seen to be resolving and no new areas are erupting. </s><s n="s6.7;p41.49">On the <name type="date"/>, Mrs <name type="other"/> was admitted to <name type="other"/> Ward with a chest infection. </s><s n="s7.7;p41.49">There have been no complications with her bullous pemphigoid treatment; she was discharged home 4 days later. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="bold">Evidence based care and issues for research</hi> A brief consideration of the evidence base required for the diagnosis and management of the patient's problem(s)</head><p n="p42.49"><s n="s1.4;p42.49">Bullous Pemphigoid (BP) is a chronic, acquired autoimmune subepidermal bullous disease in which autoantibodies are directed against components of the basement membrane zone of the skin, causing blistering of the skin. </s><s n="s2.4;p42.49">BP is characterised by the presence of IgG autoantibodies specific to hemidesmosomal BP antigens. </s><s n="s3.4;p42.49">BP is the most common blistering disease in the West, with an estimated incidence of 6-7 cases per million population per year (1). </s><s n="s4.4;p42.49">BP occurs equally in both sexes and it is usually a disease of the elderly (>70 years). </s></p><p n="p43.49"><s n="s1.4;p43.49">BP is a non-scarring blistering disease, with a typical presentation in the flexure regions, however the disease can be generalised. </s><s n="s2.4;p43.49">Mucous membranes are involved in about 50% of patients (2). </s><s n="s3.4;p43.49">Tense blisters occur on either erythematous or normal appearing skin and the blister formation may be preceded by an urticarial or eczematous rash. </s><s n="s4.4;p43.49">The degree of itch in each individual varies from none to intense and it can precede the presentation of blisters by weeks, months and occasionally years. </s></p><p n="p44.49"><s n="s1.4;p44.49">Diagnosis of BP is made clinically, histologically and immunohistochemically (using either direct and/or indirect immunofluorescence). </s><s n="s2.4;p44.49">Biopsies of a fresh blister show a subepidermal cleft with a mixed dermal inflammatory infiltrate containing numerous Eosinophils. </s><s n="s3.4;p44.49">IgG and/or C3 deposits are found at the basement membrane zone. </s><s n="s4.4;p44.49">The class of immunoglobulin bound to the basement membrane zone distinguishes from Linear IgA disease. </s></p><p n="p45.49"><s n="s1.4;p45.49">The treatment aim in BP is to suppress the clinical signs sufficiently to make the disease tolerable to an individual patient, i.e. the reduction of blister formation, urticarial lesions and pruritus. </s><s n="s2.4;p45.49">The disease is self-limiting and usually remits within 5 years, the mortality rates today vary between 6% and 41% (3). </s><s n="s3.4;p45.49">The treatment primarily aims to reduce the inflammatory process, i.e. with the use of corticosteroids and antibiotics. </s><s n="s4.4;p45.49">Immunosuppressive agents aim to suppress the production of the pathogenic antibodies. </s></p><p n="p46.49"><s n="s1.2;p46.49">BP is a long-term disease and ideally all patients should be followed until they are in complete remission and off all treatment. </s><s n="s2.2;p46.49">They should be regularly reviewed to ensure that they are not being continued on higher doses of topical or systemic treatment than are necessary to provide sufficient control of their disease. </s></p><p n="p47.49"><s n="s1.3;p47.49">There is no established optimum treatment for BP and therefore there is no gold standard against which to audit clinical practice. </s><s n="s2.3;p47.49">In an age when our population are living longer, it is inevitable that BP will become increasingly more frequent. </s><s n="s3.3;p47.49">There is a clear need to determine how to assess patients clinically and how to ascertain optimum regimes for the treatment of mild, moderate and severe BP. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="bold">Commentary</hi> A commentary on issues of health care delivery, ethical issues or disability relevant to the patient and/or problem</head><p n="p48.49"><s n="s1.2;p48.49">The important issue of continuing investigations into a long-standing complaint has been raised by this case. </s><s n="s2.2;p48.49">It is important that health care delivery continues until the correct management plan can be implemented and the individual's quality of life is improved or indeed returns back to the level it was prior to illness. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="bold">Impact on your learning</hi> Describe what you have learnt from this case</head><list type="bulleted"><item>Differential diagnoses for blistering presentations in skin conditions. </item><item>The importance of biopsy in determining histology for unknown skin complaints. </item><item>Bullous Pemphigoid and the management required. </item><item>The psychosocial implications that such a skin condition can have on an individual. </item></list><p n="p49.49"/></div1></body><back><div1 type="bibliography"><head rend="underlined">References</head><p>Bernard P., Vaillant L., Labeille B et al. Incidence and distribution of subepidermal autoimmune bullous skin diseases in three French regions. Arch Dermatol 1995: 131: 48-52. </p><p>Wojnarowska F., Kurtschig G, Highet AS., Avenning V., Khumalo NP. Guidelines for the management of bullous pemphigoid. British Association of Dermatologists, Clinical Guidelines. January 2002. </p><p>Korman NU. Bullous Pemphigoid. The latest in diagnosis, prognosis and therapy. Arch Dermatol, 1998: 134; 1137-41/. </p></div1><div1 type="back text"><head rend="bold">ASPECTS OF CASE AS RECORDED IN SUMMARY OF PORTFOLIO CASES •</head><table id="BAWE_0246f-tab.002"><row><cell/></row></table><p/></div1><div1 type="back text"><head rend="bold">PORTFOLIO COMPLETION CERTIFICATE</head><p rend="bold">Portfolio completion certificated</p><p>I confirm that this student has satisfactorily completed 3 word-processed portfolio cases.</p><p>Signed.....................................................................</p><p> Date......................................................................</p></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
