<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_0246h" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Portfolio 24 - GC</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">proforma</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">4</p><p n="date">2006-05</p><p n="module title">Other Rotations</p><p n="module code">unknown</p><p n="genre family">Case study</p><p n="discipline">Medicine</p><p n="disciplinary group">LS</p><p n="grade">D</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">2041</p><p n="number of s-units">103</p><p n="number of p">48</p><p n="number of tables">1</p><p n="number of figures">0</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">6</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">13</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">19.8</p><p n="average s-units per p">2.1</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">f</p><p n="year of birth">1981</p><p n="first language">English</p><p n="education">UKA</p><p n="course">Medicine</p><p n="student ID">0246</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><docTitle><titlePart><hi rend="bold">PORTFOLIO CASE No:</hi> 23</titlePart></docTitle><titlePart>Patient Initials<name type="other"/> Hospital Number<name type="other"/> Age 81 Gender Female</titlePart><titlePart>Portfolio Case presentation number: 13.5 Phase 2 course document objectives(s): 10.4,13.1, 13.7 Has the patient' permission, including for follow up contact by telephone, been sought and recorded in the case notes?<hi rend="bold"> The patient's permission has been sought.</hi> </titlePart></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="bold">Referral information</hi> Source of referral and a summary of key information</head><p n="p1.48"><s n="s1.1;p1.48">Mrs <name type="other"/> was admitted to the Medical Assessment Unit (MAU) at <name type="other"/> Hospital, <name type="other"/> following a <hi rend="bold">collapse at her nursing home</hi> on <name type="date"/>. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="bold">History</hi> All <hi rend="bold italic">relevant</hi> information gathered from the patient about the presenting illness, co-existing problems, current treatment, <hi rend="italic">significant</hi> past medical history and the social and family background. The patient's view of the nature of the problem and their expectations for treatment. </head><div2><head rend="bold">Presenting Complaint</head><p n="p2.48"><s n="s1.1;p2.48">Mrs <name type="other"/> was <hi rend="bold">found unresponsive by the carers</hi> in her nursing home whilst lying in her bed. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">History of Presenting Complaint</head><p n="p3.48"><s n="s1.7;p3.48">Mrs <name type="other"/> had <hi rend="bold">been responsive and talking the day prior</hi> to her collapse and had <hi rend="bold">not been complaining of feeling unwell</hi>. </s><s n="s2.7;p3.48">8 weeks previously on <hi rend="bold"><name type="date"/>,</hi> Mrs <name type="other"/> had been admitted to the <name type="other"/> General Hospital <hi rend="bold">following a fall at the home</hi>. </s><s n="s3.7;p3.48">She was admitted for 2-3 days and was subsequently discharged. </s><s n="s4.7;p3.48">On arrival, Mrs <name type="other"/> was able to maintain her airway. </s><s n="s5.7;p3.48">She was dyspnoeic and tachycardic with an adequate blood pressure (154/72). </s><s n="s6.7;p3.48">Mrs <name type="other"/> was <hi rend="bold">moving all four limbs and localising sources of pain, she was not responding to a commands</hi>. </s><s n="s7.7;p3.48">Mrs <name type="other"/> had <hi rend="bold">not been incontinent</hi> whilst in her bed or on her arrival to the MAU. There were <hi rend="bold">no obvious signs of trauma</hi>. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">Past Medical History</head><list type="bulleted"><item>COPD - on home oxygen</item><item>Hyperparathyroidism</item><item>Atrial fibrillation</item><item>Previous MI</item><item>Congestive Cardiac Failure</item><item>Recurrent UTIs</item><item>Poor mobility</item><item>No history of diabetes, rheumatoid arthritis, epilepsy, asthma,, stroke or TB. </item></list><p n="p4.48"/></div2><div2><head rend="bold">Medication</head><list type="simple"><item>Ramipril - 2.5mg <hi rend="italic">od</hi></item><item>Lactulose - 20ml <hi rend="italic">bd</hi></item><item>Aspirin - 75mg <hi rend="italic">od</hi></item><item>Digoxin - 125µg <hi rend="italic">od</hi></item><item>Furosemide - 40mg <hi rend="italic">od</hi></item><item>Amitryptiline - 10mg <hi rend="italic">od</hi></item><item>Nefopan - 30mg 2 tablets <hi rend="italic">tds</hi></item><item>Combivent inhalers</item></list><p n="p5.48"><s rend="bold" n="s1.1;p5.48">No known drug allergies </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">Family History</head><p n="p6.48"><s n="s1.1;p6.48">There is no significant family history. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">Social History</head><p n="p7.48"><s n="s1.5;p7.48">Mrs <name type="other"/><hi rend="bold">lives in a nursing home</hi>. </s><s n="s2.5;p7.48">Mrs <name type="other"/> is an ex-smoker of 40 years. </s><s n="s3.5;p7.48">Mrs <name type="other"/> has <hi rend="bold">poor mobility</hi>. </s><s n="s4.5;p7.48">Her family live nearby and visit regularly. </s><s n="s5.5;p7.48">Mrs <name type="other"/> is widowed. </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="bold">Analysis of history</hi> The most likely single cause of the presentation, other possible causes and reasons for these choices. The findings to be looked for on physical examination to help decide the cause.</head><p n="p8.48"><s n="s1.1;p8.48">Based on the acute symptoms Mrs <name type="other"/> presented with, the differential diagnoses of collapse, verbally unresponsive in a COPD patient are: </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p9.48"><s n="s1.1;p9.48"><hi rend="bold">Collapse secondary to CO2 retention:</hi> given Mrs <name type="other"/>'s history of COPD, her dyspnoea, drowsiness, tachycardia and confusion fit with this diagnosis. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p10.48"><s n="s1.1;p10.48"><hi rend="bold">Collapse secondary to Stroke/TIA:</hi> the risk factors of her age and previous coronary events coupled with her acute presentation and weakness could be indicative of a stroke. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p11.48"><s rend="bold" n="s1.1;p11.48">Lower respiratory tract infection </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p12.48"><s rend="bold" n="s1.1;p12.48">Left Ventricular Failure/Congestive Cardiac Failure </s></p><p n="p13.48"><s n="s1.3;p13.48">On physical examination, it is important to assess the level of Mrs <name type="other"/>'s responsiveness from the GCS assessment. </s><s n="s2.3;p13.48">Her vital signs should be assessed, particularly her oxygen saturations and blood gases. </s><s n="s3.3;p13.48">An examination should assess her cardiovascular and respiratory status, listening for crackles and air entry. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="bold">Physical examination and mental state examination</hi> Highlight the findings most relevant to your clinical problem solving by underlining them</head><p n="p14.48"><s n="s1.6;p14.48">On general examination, Mrs <name type="other"/><hi rend="bold">was drowsy and non-rousable</hi>. </s><s n="s2.6;p14.48">She did <hi rend="bold">not respond verbally</hi> but would <hi rend="bold">respond to painful stimuli with moans</hi>. </s><s n="s3.6;p14.48">She would <hi rend="bold">open her eyes after persistent commands</hi>. </s><s n="s4.6;p14.48">Mrs <name type="other"/> had <hi rend="bold">cold peripheries and her capillary refill was 3 seconds</hi>. </s><s n="s5.6;p14.48">There were <hi rend="bold">no signs of jaundice, clubbing or lymphadenopathy</hi>. </s><s n="s6.6;p14.48">Mrs <name type="other"/> was <hi rend="bold">very pale and was cyanosed</hi>. </s></p><p n="p15.48"><s rend="bold" n="s1.1;p15.48">GCS - Motor response 5/6 (localising response to pain), Verbal response 2/5 (incomprehensible speech), Eye opening 3/4 (eye opening in response to speech) = 10/15 </s></p><list type="bulleted"><head rend="bold">Cardiovascular Examination</head><item rend="bold">Pulse 110 regular</item><item>BP 154/72</item><item>Heart sounds I + II + 0</item><item>No pedal oedema</item><item>Temperature 35.4</item><item rend="bold">Glucose 7.3</item></list><list type="bulleted"><head rend="bold">Respiratory System</head><item>Respiratory rate 20</item><item>Vesicular breath sounds present.</item><item rend="bold">Bilateral crackles at the lung bases. </item><item><hi rend="bold">Saturations 70% on 2L O2 on admission rising to 90% in MAU</hi>. </item></list><list type="bulleted"><head rend="bold">Gastrointestinal System</head><item>Abdomen generally soft. </item><item rend="bold">Faecal load felt in lower right quadrant. </item><item>Abdomen non-tender</item><item>No organomegaly</item><item>Bowel sounds present. </item></list></div1><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="bold">Analysis of history and examination</hi> Reasons for your choice of the cause of the patient's problem(s) and any other cause that still needs to be considered at this stage</head><p n="p16.48"><s n="s1.5;p16.48">History and examination confirm the initial possible causes of Mrs <name type="other"/>'s presentation. </s><s rend="bold" n="s2.5;p16.48">A collapse secondary to an infective exacerbation of COPD leading to Type II respiratory failure and CO2 retention is the most likely diagnosis. </s><s n="s3.5;p16.48">Her O <hi rend="sub">2</hi> saturations indicate she has poor respiratory function and an ABG will help determine her respiratory state. </s><s n="s4.5;p16.48">Tachycardia, confusion, drowsiness and central cyanosis all support this diagnosis. </s><s n="s5.5;p16.48">The presence of crackles bilaterally would indicate a possible respiratory tract infection which may have precipitated Mrs <name type="other"/>'s collapse. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="bold">Formulation of the patient's problem(s)</hi> Encapsulate this in physical, psychological and social terms (the triple diagnosis)</head><p n="p17.48"><s n="s1.6;p17.48"><hi rend="bold">Physical -</hi> Mrs <name type="other"/> found it difficult to mobilise herself prior to admission. </s><s n="s2.6;p17.48">She has had repeated falls, one of which she was admitted for. </s><s n="s3.6;p17.48">She is becoming progressively more unsteady on her feet. </s><s n="s4.6;p17.48">This is putting her at increase risk of further falls and consequently reducing her physical state further. </s><s n="s5.6;p17.48">As a result of her COPD, Mrs <name type="other"/> is unable to walk without O <hi rend="sub">2</hi>; this further limits her physical ability. </s><s n="s6.6;p17.48">Her immobility increases the risk of retaining respiratory secretions predisposing Mrs <name type="other"/> to chest infections. </s></p><p n="p18.48"><s n="s1.2;p18.48"><hi rend="bold">Psychological -</hi> On admission, Mrs <name type="other"/> was verbally unresponsive but following admission and some degree of recovery she became upset regarding about her poor mobility and loss of independence. </s><s n="s2.2;p18.48">Mrs <name type="other"/> exhibited a fear about her death. </s></p><p n="p19.48"><s n="s1.2;p19.48"><hi rend="bold">Social -</hi> Mrs <name type="other"/>'s social situation is stable and well supported. </s><s n="s2.2;p19.48">She gets full-time care from her nursing home and requires help dressing, washing and some support mobilising. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="bold">Management</hi> Use the framework of RAPRIOP to structure your proposed management. Refer to the guidelines to the writing of portfolio cases for the details of the issues to be addressed under each heading.</head><div2><head rend="bold">Investigations</head><p n="p20.48"><s n="s1.1;p20.48">Mrs <name type="other"/>'s ABG results on <name type="date"/> were as follows: </s></p><table id="BAWE_0246h-tab.001"><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p21.48"><s n="s1.2;p21.48">The pH level of 7.130 indicates an acidosis, a raised pCO <hi rend="sub">2</hi> of 20.57kPa illustrates pCO <hi rend="sub">2</hi> retention and a pO <hi rend="sub">2</hi> of6.70 confirms the presence of hypoxia, indicating Type II respiratory failure caused by alveolar hypoventilation. </s><s n="s2.2;p21.48">These results support Mrs <name type="other"/>'s clinical picture. </s></p><p n="p22.48"><s rend="underlined" n="s1.1;p22.48">Chest X-Ray </s></p><p n="p23.48"><s n="s1.1;p23.48">No indication of infection seen. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">Reassurance and Explanation</head><p n="p24.48"><s n="s1.5;p24.48">To appropriately reassure Mrs <name type="other"/> and her family I would say: "As you know, Mrs <name type="other"/> has been suffering from COPD for many years now making it difficult for her to breathe. </s><s n="s2.5;p24.48">There are a number of reasons why she may have collapsed and we would like to investigate them all. </s><s n="s3.5;p24.48">It is most likely that she has collapsed as a complication to her COPD and we will carry out some tests to find out exactly the best way to treat her. </s><s n="s4.5;p24.48">At the moment we will give her restricted oxygen (2-4L), antibiotics and fluids. </s><s n="s5.5;p24.48">As Mrs <name type="other"/> has been deteriorating recently and has been in hospital a number of times now for a similar admission we are not sure how she will respond to this admission". </s></p><p n="p25.48"><s n="s1.2;p25.48">To explain the nature of the disease:"COPD is a disease of the airways and it becomes increasingly more difficult for you to get oxygen in to your lungs, which limits the amount of oxygen getting to your vital organs and muscles. </s><s n="s2.2;p25.48">As your condition gets worse it is more difficult for you to expel CO <hi rend="sub">2</hi>, which can cause the problems you have experienced when it gets retained in your blood". </s></p><p n="p26.48"><s n="s1.3;p26.48">To describe the management plan: "We will keep Mrs <name type="other"/> in hospital and monitor her blood gases and oxygen saturations closely giving her oxygen and fluids. </s><s n="s2.3;p26.48">We will get a chest X-ray to look for any signs of an infection. </s><s n="s3.3;p26.48">We will have to wait and see how well she responds to her oxygen and fluids". </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">Prescription/Medical Intervention</head><p n="p27.48"><s n="s1.3;p27.48">Mrs <name type="other"/> was prescribed augmentin for a possible chest infection on admission. </s><s n="s2.3;p27.48">She was given oxygen 2L via a face mask. </s><s n="s3.3;p27.48">A urinary catheter was fitted. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">Observation</head><p n="p28.48"><s n="s1.2;p28.48">Following admission from MAU, Mrs <name type="other"/> was transferred to a ward where her saturations were monitored. </s><s n="s2.2;p28.48">Over the following days she became more responsive and was helped to sit in a chair whilst on oxygen. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">Referral and Team Working</head><p n="p29.48"><s n="s1.3;p29.48">Mrs <name type="other"/> was not referred to any further care once she was admitted. </s><s n="s2.3;p29.48">The team based on the ward of nurses, doctors and care assistants need to liaise with each other regarding the progress of Mrs <name type="other"/>. </s><s n="s3.3;p29.48">Each of these teams also needs to relay information back to the family so that they can remain fully informed about Ms <name type="other"/>'s health. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">Advice and Prevention</head><p n="p30.48"><s n="s1.2;p30.48">Advice should be given with regards to looking after the terminally ill family members. </s><s n="s2.2;p30.48">The family may also require advice on bereavement and counselling services. </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="bold">Outcome</hi> A description of the progress of the patient as far as possible. This should include consideration of further issues to be resolved. Where appropriate you should contact by telephone patients who have been discharged home.</head><p n="p31.48"><s n="s1.2;p31.48">Mrs <name type="other"/> was admitted to the ward and began responding verbally but remained unable to mobilise. </s><s n="s2.2;p31.48">Sadly, Mrs <name type="other"/> passed away 2 days after her admission to the ward. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="bold">Evidence based care and issues for research</hi> A brief consideration of the evidence base required for the diagnosis and management of the patient's problem(s)</head><p n="p32.48"><s n="s1.2;p32.48">Respiratory failure occurs when there is an inadequate gas exchange, which results in hypoxia (pO <hi rend="sub">2</hi> &lt;8kPa). </s><s n="s2.2;p32.48">Respiratory failure is subdivided into two types according to the pCO <hi rend="sub">2.</hi> </s></p><p n="p33.48"><s n="s1.2;p33.48"><hi rend="bold">Type I Respiratory Failure</hi> is defined as hypoxia (pO <hi rend="sub">2</hi> &lt;8kPa) with a normal or low pCO <hi rend="sub">2</hi>. </s><s n="s2.2;p33.48">It is primarily caused by a ventilation/perfusion mismatch. </s></p><p n="p34.48"><s n="s1.3;p34.48"><hi rend="bold">Type II Respiratory Failure</hi> is defined as hypoxia with hypercapnia (pCO <hi rend="sub">2</hi> > 6.5kPa). </s><s n="s2.3;p34.48">It is caused by alveolar hypoventilation with or without ventilation/perfusion mismatch. </s><s n="s3.3;p34.48">(1) </s></p><p n="p35.48"><s n="s1.1;p35.48">The management of respiratory failure includes the administration of supplemental oxygen, the control of secretions, the treatment of any underlying pulmonary infection, the control of any bronchospasm and measures to limit pulmonary oedema. </s></p><p n="p36.48"><s n="s1.1;p36.48">The management principles are: </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p37.48"><s n="s1.1;p37.48">treat the underlying disease </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p38.48"><s n="s1.1;p38.48">physiotherapy </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p39.48"><s n="s1.1;p39.48">oxygen therapy - try to maintain pO <hi rend="sub">2</hi> > 8 kPa </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p40.48"><s n="s1.1;p40.48">bronchodilators and steroids if there is airways obstruction </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p41.48"><s n="s1.1;p41.48">in some circumstances, respiratory stimulants such as i.v. doxapram 1-4 mg / min, may be indicated if the pCO <hi rend="sub">2</hi> begins to rise </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p42.48"><s n="s1.1;p42.48">if arterial O <hi rend="sub">2</hi> continues to deteriorate or fails to improve then some form of respiratory support should be considered </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p43.48"><s n="s1.2;p43.48">long-term management should be aimed at the underlying cause of the condition e.g. </s><s n="s2.2;p43.48">COPD </s></p><div2><head rend="bold">Oxygen Therapy in Respiratory Failure:</head><p rend="bulleted" n="p44.48"><s n="s1.2;p44.48"><hi rend="underlined">Type 1 failure</hi> - treat with unrestricted oxygen therapy i.e. </s><s n="s2.2;p44.48">35+ %; blood gases should be repeated after 20 mins to ensure correction of PaO <hi rend="sub">2</hi> and absence of a significant rise in PaCO <hi rend="sub">2</hi>. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p45.48"><s n="s1.2;p45.48"><hi rend="underlined">Type 2 failure and COPD</hi> - give 24% O2. </s><s n="s2.2;p45.48">Monitor PaCO <hi rend="sub">2</hi> closely by blood gas measurement; if it rises by more than 1 kPa, consider ventilation. </s></p><p n="p46.48"><s n="s1.2;p46.48">The concentration of oxygen is important to patients with chronic bronchitis and chronically elevated PaCO <hi rend="sub">2</hi> - as these patients rely on hypoxic drive to maintain respiratory effort, it is dangerous to give supplemental oxygen without careful observation as hypoventilation or apnoea may result. </s><s n="s2.2;p46.48">Blood gases must be monitored regularly. </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="bold">Commentary</hi> A commentary on issues of health care delivery, ethical issues or disability relevant to the patient and/or problem</head><p n="p47.48"><s n="s1.7;p47.48">An important issue raised in this case was the issue of resuscitation in the event of a cardiac arrest. </s><s n="s2.7;p47.48">Mrs <name type="other"/> had been deteriorating steadily over the past few months and her respiratory function is poor. </s><s n="s3.7;p47.48">On previous occasions her family had been notified that it was difficult to predict whether she would recover. </s><s n="s4.7;p47.48">On her admission this time, Mrs <name type="other"/> was in a similar position and at risk of a cardiac arrest and it was a sensitive issue that needed to be discussed with the family. </s><s n="s5.7;p47.48">This case highlighted the issues of health care delivery to patients who may not benefit from further medical intervention and how to approach this issue with the family. </s><s n="s6.7;p47.48">Mrs <name type="other"/> was fully dependent on care, had restricted mobility and struggling with a progressive terminal illness. </s><s n="s7.7;p47.48">The decision was taken not to resuscitate in the event of a cardiac arrest on the basis of a reduced quality of life. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="bold">Impact on your learning</hi> Describe what you have learnt from this case</head><list type="bulleted"><item>Acute presentation of COPD</item><item>Management of an unresponsive patient.</item><item>Breaking bad news</item><item>Ethical issues of resuscitation and further medical intervention in critically ill patients. </item><item>Management of Type II respiratory Failure</item></list><p n="p48.48"/></div1></body><back><div1 type="bibliography"><head rend="underlined">References</head><p>Oxford Handbook of Clinical Medicine: Oxford University Press, 2002, </p><p>gpnotebook.co.uk, visited May 2006. </p></div1><div1 type="back text"><head rend="bold">ASPECTS OF CASE AS RECORDED IN SUMMARY OF PORTFOLIO CASES •</head><p/></div1><div1 type="back text"><head rend="bold">PORTFOLIO COMPLETION CERTIFICATE</head><p rend="bold">Portfolio completion certificated</p><p>I confirm that this student has satisfactorily completed 3 word-processed portfolio cases.</p><p>Signed.....................................................................</p><p> Date......................................................................</p></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
