<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_0249b" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>'The implementation of computational analysis in Bioengineering'</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">The document has a title page which contains:
document title
title part</note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">deleted: footer: student number, page numbers
</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">3</p><p n="date">2006-03</p><p n="module title">Design Techniques and Management</p><p n="module code">ES380</p><p n="genre family">Design specification</p><p n="discipline">Engineering</p><p n="disciplinary group">PS</p><p n="grade">M</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">1991</p><p n="number of s-units">96</p><p n="number of p">50</p><p n="number of tables">1</p><p n="number of figures">28</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">5</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">7</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">20.7</p><p n="average s-units per p">1.9</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">m</p><p n="year of birth">1985</p><p n="first language">English</p><p n="education">UKA</p><p n="course">Engineering</p><p n="student ID">0249</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><titlePart>ES 380 Design Techniques and Management</titlePart><docTitle><titlePart rend="bold">'The implementation of computational analysis in Bioengineering'</titlePart></docTitle><titlePart><name type="student ID"/></titlePart></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Introduction</head><p n="p1.50"><s n="s1.2;p1.50">Since the end of the 19 <hi rend="sup">th</hi> century, scientists have experimented with how to best alleviate discomfort and rehabilitate joints struck with arthritis. </s><s n="s2.2;p1.50">The joint that is hardest struck is usually the hip, and accordingly research has been more focussed in this area. </s></p><p n="p2.50"><s n="s1.3;p2.50">A complete hip replacement is required to reproduce the kind of mobility offered by the original hip. </s><s n="s2.3;p2.50">For this, two primary components are used, the cup to replicate the hip socket, and the femur, including the ball to rotate within the socket. </s><s n="s3.3;p2.50">In practise, the ball is attached separately onto the femur replacement to allow the use of harder wearing materials, and often the cup has a lining to improve longevity and decrease friction within the joint. </s></p><list type="bulleted"><head rend="bold">Design Objectives</head><item>Good mobility within joint</item><item>Alleviate discomfort within joint</item><item>Replacement to last decades</item></list><list type="bulleted"><head rend="bold">Key Parameters</head><item>Strong bone replacements</item><item>Precision joint</item><item>Hard wearing/low friction interactive bearing surfaces</item><item>Biocompatible materials</item><item>Secure bonding</item></list><p n="p3.50"><s n="s1.3;p3.50">The historical solution for this problem involves manual modelling, and a great deal of trial and error. </s><s n="s2.3;p3.50">Due to the demands upon these replacements, the time required for testing results in slowed development. </s><s n="s3.3;p3.50">The advance of computational methods for design and development can be utilised to minimise the extent of the required testing and hence reduce the overall development time frame. </s></p><p n="p4.50"><s n="s1.2;p4.50">A model will be created and a static analysis be performed. </s><s n="s2.2;p4.50">Computational methods shall then be evaluated as a tool within the design process. </s></p><div2><head rend="bold">Discussion</head><p n="p5.50"/></div2><div2><head rend="bold">Historical manual methods</head><p n="p6.50"><s n="s1.1;p6.50">Early treatments for arthritic joints included </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p7.50"><s n="s1.1;p7.50">arthrodesis - fusion of the bones (resulting in loss of mobility) </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p8.50"><s n="s1.1;p8.50">osteotomy - where the bone is cut and angled differently in order to improve the mechanics of the joint (results often in reduced mobility) </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p9.50"><s n="s1.1;p9.50">nerve division (did not improve or reduce mobility as it failed to treat the problem) </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p10.50"><s n="s1.1;p10.50">joint debridements - removal of arthritic lumps and smoothing of interactive bearing surfaces (reducing pain levels but may not produce long term improvements) </s></p><p n="p11.50"><s n="s1.2;p11.50">One development leading on from joint debridgements was the introduction of experiments to find a suitable material to resurface the joints. </s><s n="s2.2;p11.50">Materials tested included: </s></p><list type="bulleted"><item>muscles, </item><item>fat, </item><item>chromatized pig bladder, </item><item>gold, </item><item>magnesium and </item><item>zinc. </item></list><p n="p12.50"><s n="s1.2;p12.50">The requirements for such a material are that it is both biocompatible with the human body, and able to withstand the large forces exerted upon the hip, millions of times per year. </s><s n="s2.2;p12.50">Development continued slowly over many decades: </s></p><p n="p13.50"><s n="s1.3;p13.50"><hi rend="bold">1925</hi> - in Boston a scientist pioneered "mold arthroplasty", initially a piece of glass was successfully molded to fit over the ball of the hip joint providing a smooth surface to replace the worn one. </s><s n="s2.3;p13.50">Glass proved biocompatible, but failed under the forces exerted by movement and walking. </s><s n="s3.3;p13.50">Other materials used included stainless steel and plastics. </s></p><p n="p14.50"><s n="s1.2;p14.50"><hi rend="bold">1936</hi> - A strong and corrosion resistant cobalt-chromium alloy was. </s><s n="s2.2;p14.50">It was applied during mold arthroplasty, and the material is still in use today within orthopaedics. </s></p><p n="p15.50"><s n="s1.2;p15.50"><hi rend="bold">1938</hi> - In Paris, acrylic was used to replace hip surfaces. </s><s n="s2.2;p15.50">This proved successful in terms of wear, but fixation to the bone was difficult but inspired a New York scientist to successfully utilise fast setting dental acrylic to glue the new surface to the bone. </s></p><p n="p16.50"><s n="s1.1;p16.50"><hi rend="bold">1940's</hi> - Mold arthroplasty is considered an technically advanced procedure </s></p><p n="p17.50"><s n="s1.3;p17.50"><hi rend="bold">1950's</hi> - In New York, Hemiarthroplasty (the replacement of the ball of the hip) included a stem that attached at one end to the femur, and the other end to the ball. </s><s n="s2.3;p17.50">This ball then fitted into the hip socket, which became more and more arthritic. </s><s n="s3.3;p17.50">Problems arose within the socket, and with attaching the prosthesis to the bone. </s></p><p n="p18.50"><s n="s1.4;p18.50"><hi rend="bold">1958</hi> - In England, John Charnley worked towards replacing both parts of the joint, the femoral head and the hip socket. </s><s n="s2.4;p18.50">He initially used a Teflon implant to provide a smooth surface to interact with the metal femoral implant, with further further development using a polyethylene surface. </s><s n="s3.4;p18.50">Polymehtylmethacrylate was used (as it is in dentistry) to secure the prosthesis to the bones, the first complete hip replacements. </s><s n="s4.4;p18.50">John Charnley was later knighted for his contributions. </s></p><p n="p19.50"><s n="s1.6;p19.50">To this day the concept of John Charnley's prosthesis remains the same. </s><s n="s2.6;p19.50">Improvements have been made to the design and a great deal of time has been spent developing the cement to fix it to the bone. </s><s n="s3.6;p19.50">In the last decade or so, work has centred on developing a 'living bond' has been desired, whereby the bone grows into a porous, textured surface on the implant. </s><s n="s4.6;p19.50">This is necessary to overcome difficulties with fixation techniques which continue to prove problematic over long periods. </s><s n="s5.6;p19.50">Traditionally design validation has required surgically implanting the prosthesis in a patient and monitoring progress. </s><s n="s6.6;p19.50">This is a lengthy and risky process which could potentially cause much discomfort to the patient and ultimately necessitate further surgery.<ref target="BAWE_0249b-ftnote.001"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0249b-ftnote.001"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1"><seg type="URL" n="http://www.utahhipandknee.com/history.htm"/> </s></p></note><figure id="BAWE_0249b-pic.001"><head><ref target="BAWE_0249b-ftnote.002"/><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0249b-ftnote.002"><p n="pn1.1"> courtesy of Sakamoto et. al.,Kanazawa University, Japan</p></note></head></figure></div2><div2><head rend="bold">Computational methods</head><p n="p20.50"><s n="s1.3;p20.50">Recent improvements upon John Charnley's total hip replacement have in part been achieved by better modelling the original hip joint. </s><s n="s2.3;p20.50">Using CAD and FEA, it is possible to 'scan' a three dimensional model from a human joint, and create a solid within the software package that is a virtual copy of the bone itself. </s><s n="s3.3;p20.50">Loads can be applied to the model and the deformation and stress contours be calculated. </s></p><p n="p21.50"><s n="s1.2;p21.50">Designs can therefore be verified and tested in a virtual world without any need for prototyping at this stage. </s><s n="s2.2;p21.50">It is possible to subject the model to cyclical loading at a far greater rate than a real-world equivalent model, proving longevity or fatigue failures of any design. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">Project Modelling</head><p n="p22.50"><s n="s1.1;p22.50">First a solid model was created in Solidworks for each component: </s></p><list type="bulleted"><item>femoral stem</item><item>ball</item><item>cup</item><item>cup lining</item></list><p n="p23.50"><s n="s1.2;p23.50">These models were then assembled and mating restraints imposed to mimic their interaction. </s><s n="s2.2;p23.50">Materials were individually assigned to each component, the physical properties of which are downloaded from databases (e.g from within the FEA package Cosmosworks) or a dedication material package such as CES Material Selector.. </s></p><p n="p24.50"><s n="s1.2;p24.50">Forces were selected to best model the loading that the hip would be subjected to in real use (i.e. if it were it used to replace someone's hip). </s><s n="s2.2;p24.50">This often requires physical modelling to ascertain, but approximations can easily be made. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0249b-pic.002"><head>a) Standing Load - 800 N </head></figure><figure id="BAWE_0249b-pic.003"><head>b) Torque - 50 Nm</head></figure><p n="p25.50"><s n="s1.1;p25.50">A mesh was created for the solid, descretising it into very small elements than could be readiliy and uniqulely 'loaded' to produce deformations and stresses. </s></p><p n="p26.50"><s n="s1.3;p26.50">Once the simulation was run, plots were viewed showing the stress and shear values throughout the model. </s><s n="s2.3;p26.50">The visual representation was given by a gradient of colours responding to different values. </s><s n="s3.3;p26.50">These values can then be checked against the material properties to ascertain whether the design is sufficient, or where it is most likely to fail. </s></p><p n="p27.50"><s n="s1.5;p27.50">These illustrations provide means to quickly and easily assess the performance of a component. </s><s n="s2.5;p27.50">Little skill is required to operate such software and read the results, however in this comes the danger. </s><s n="s3.5;p27.50">Expertise is necessary to apply the appropriate boundary conditions and forces to the model to extract the relevant data. </s><s n="s4.5;p27.50">Instead of modelling countless prototypes, designs can be altered as soon as the simulation is run to better performance. </s><s n="s5.5;p27.50">This process of virtual development ensures designs are closer to completion by the time prototyping is needed, in a fraction of the time. </s></p><p n="p28.50"><s n="s1.1;p28.50">Following the modelling of Ford's fluidic windscreen wiper system, it was said that such tools reduced the design time by over 50%.<ref target="BAWE_0249b-ftnote.003"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0249b-ftnote.003"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1"><seg type="URL" n="http://www.fluent.com/solutions/articles/ja084.pdf"/> </s></p></note></div2><div2><head rend="bold">CAD/FEA design process</head><p n="p29.50"/></div2><div2><head rend="bold">Pros/cons</head><p n="p30.50"/></div2><div2><head rend="bold">Analysis</head><p n="p31.50"><s n="s1.2;p31.50">A generic design was modelled in Solidworks and subjected to static analysis under typical loading conditions, using an FEA add-in called Cosmosworks. </s><s n="s2.2;p31.50">Two situations were modelled: </s></p><list type="ordered"><item>Standing load of 800N</item><item>Subject to torque of 50Nm</item></list><figure id="BAWE_0249b-pic.004"/><p n="p32.50"><s n="s1.3;p32.50">These were assumed to be representative of loads applied regularly to any hip. </s><s n="s2.3;p32.50">These were modelled for the whole assembly, as well as for the femoral stem in isolation. </s><s n="s3.3;p32.50">This was necessary because the different materials are able to tolerate different stresses, and within the assembly, stress concentrated within the cup lining and could not be seen within the femoral stem using the same scale. </s></p><p n="p33.50"><s n="s1.1;p33.50">The following stress data was determined from the reading the stress contours: </s></p><table id="BAWE_0249b-tab.001"><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p34.50"><s n="s1.2;p34.50">The surface of the cup lining has the lowest factor of safety, and has been deemed by the software as the weakest component of the design. </s><s n="s2.2;p34.50">This is verified by the years of experimentation where the lining has been the main part to fail over time. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">Further discussion</head><p n="p35.50"><s n="s1.5;p35.50">It was necessary to carry out separate analysis of different components to see a sufficient spectrum to ascertain what stress was present and where in each part. </s><s n="s2.5;p35.50">User initiative is required to analyse the results properly, and not take them on face value. </s><s n="s3.5;p35.50">The mesh that was created in Cosmosworks was the finest available, yet still elements appear quite course on smaller components. </s><s n="s4.5;p35.50">This is a limitation of the software, not the technology, as other packages offer greatly reduced element size. </s><s n="s5.5;p35.50">The only true limitation of element size is computer power and time for calculation. </s></p><p n="p36.50"><s n="s1.3;p36.50">Further limitations of FEA include the restraints and loadings. </s><s n="s2.3;p36.50">These are idealised and must be approximated by the user. </s><s n="s3.3;p36.50">Results from such approximates can only be used as a guide within the design process. </s></p><p n="p37.50"><s n="s1.1;p37.50">Improvements in analysis could be produced through a more detailed study of experimental failure data and subsequent validation of the FEA modelling used against this experimental failure data and failure modes. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">Costing</head><p n="p38.50"><s n="s1.1;p38.50">Manual design is:- </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p39.50"><s n="s1.1;p39.50">very hit and miss, </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p40.50"><s n="s1.1;p40.50">prototypes are costly to produce on a one-off basis, </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p41.50"><s n="s1.1;p41.50">design validation requires expensive test rigs to run for long periods of time. </s></p><p n="p42.50"><s n="s1.3;p42.50">In contrast, whilst FEA requires a steep initial investment for both the package and staff training, benefits will quickly be realised as new materials and designs are able to be tested seamlessly with minimal time and effort. </s><s n="s2.3;p42.50">Modern FEA packages such as Solidworks' Cosmosworks require little time to learn, only a matter of hours if one is familiar with Solidworks itself. </s><s n="s3.3;p42.50">Selection of an FEA package familiar to staff would be one way to minimise costs. </s></p><p n="p43.50"><s n="s1.6;p43.50">Only once designs pass initial FEA analysis need they pass through to physical prototyping and testing. </s><s n="s2.6;p43.50">This enables designs to reach a much more developed stage, nearer to completion before the first prototype is required. </s><s n="s3.6;p43.50">This would reduce costs in terms of man-hours spent producing the prototypes and in unnecessary testing. </s><s n="s4.6;p43.50">It is likely that the necessary hardware is already available to the enterprise in this day to complete computer models already. </s><s n="s5.6;p43.50">If necessary, additional expenditure may be necessary to further decrease the computing time required. </s><s n="s6.6;p43.50">The level of expense needed depends heavily upon the number of consoles required, as separate licences may be required from the software vendor, raising costs from hundreds into many thousands of pounds. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">Conclusion</head><figure id="BAWE_0249b-pic.005"/><p n="p44.50"><s n="s1.1;p44.50">Finite element analysis tools enable prototypes to be virtually modelled in a fraction of the time for physical models to be produced and tested. </s></p><p n="p45.50"><s n="s1.2;p45.50">Fewer iterations of designs are required, and alternative materials can be 'virtually' tested and only those with adequate potential tested in the laboratory. </s><s n="s2.2;p45.50">Testing must be performed however to validate any results obtained through computational analysis due to calculation errors and over-simplifications. </s></p><p n="p46.50"><s n="s1.2;p46.50">For an initial expense, the investment into CAD and FEA is of great benefit to enterprises. </s><s n="s2.2;p46.50">Data management is far simpler due to electronic storage, and designs are easily passed between departments and even continents so design can continue around the clock. </s></p><p n="p47.50"><ref target="BAWE_0249b-ftnote.004"/><s n="s1.1;p47.50"> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0249b-ftnote.004"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1"><hi rend="italic">DAG Technologies (M'sia) Sdn Bhd</hi> (<seg type="URL" n="http://www.symbiosisonline.com/aug05_bioengine.htm"/>) </s></p></note></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Assembly under standing load</head><figure id="BAWE_0249b-pic.006"><head>Assembly meshed </head></figure><figure id="BAWE_0249b-pic.007"><head>Strain within assembly</head></figure><figure id="BAWE_0249b-pic.008"><head>Design check - Factor of safety </head></figure><figure id="BAWE_0249b-pic.009"><head>Displacement of Assembly</head></figure><figure id="BAWE_0249b-pic.010"><head>Cup lining meshed </head></figure><figure id="BAWE_0249b-pic.011"><head>Strain within cup lining</head></figure><div2><head rend="bold">Femoral stem under Load</head><figure id="BAWE_0249b-pic.012"><head>Forces and restraints upon femoral stem </head></figure><figure id="BAWE_0249b-pic.013"><head>Strain within femoral stem </head></figure><figure id="BAWE_0249b-pic.014"><head>Stress in femoral stem</head></figure><p n="p48.50"/></div2><div2><head rend="bold">Assembly under torque</head><figure id="BAWE_0249b-pic.015"><head>Assembly meshed </head></figure><figure id="BAWE_0249b-pic.016"><head>Strain within assembly </head></figure><figure id="BAWE_0249b-pic.017"><head>Design Check - Factor of safety inc. ball</head></figure><figure id="BAWE_0249b-pic.018"><head>Strain within cup lining inc. ball</head></figure><figure id="BAWE_0249b-pic.019"><head>Design Check - factor of safety</head></figure><figure id="BAWE_0249b-pic.020"><head>Strain within cup lining</head></figure><figure id="BAWE_0249b-pic.021"><head>Design Check - Factor of safety</head></figure><figure id="BAWE_0249b-pic.022"><head>Strain within cup lining</head></figure><p n="p49.50"/></div2><div2><head rend="bold">Hip under torque</head><figure id="BAWE_0249b-pic.023"><head>Design Check - Factor of safety</head></figure><figure id="BAWE_0249b-pic.024"><head>Femoral stem meshed</head></figure><figure id="BAWE_0249b-pic.025"><head>Femoral stem meshed</head></figure><figure id="BAWE_0249b-pic.026"><head>Strain within femoral stem</head></figure><figure id="BAWE_0249b-pic.027"><head>Stress within femoral stem</head></figure><figure id="BAWE_0249b-pic.028"><head>Design check - factor of safety</head></figure><p n="p50.50"/></div2></div1></body><back/></text></TEI.2>
