<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_0249j" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Case Study 3 - Assignment 2</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">The document has a title page which contains:
document title
title part
abstract</note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">Language used in quote: <foreign id="English">English</foreign></note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">deleted: page numbers</note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">group work; students wrote separate sections; only section written by 0249 was tagged</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">1</p><p n="date">2003-11</p><p n="module title">Professional Studies</p><p n="module code">ES156</p><p n="genre family">Design specification</p><p n="discipline">Engineering</p><p n="disciplinary group">PS</p><p n="grade">M</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">1984</p><p n="number of s-units">88</p><p n="number of p">31</p><p n="number of tables">0</p><p n="number of figures">2</p><p n="number of block quotes">2</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">1</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">6</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">22.5</p><p n="average s-units per p">2.8</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">m</p><p n="year of birth">1985</p><p n="first language">English</p><p n="education">UKA</p><p n="course">Engineering</p><p n="student ID">0249</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><docTitle><titlePart rend="bold">Case Study 3 - Assignment 2</titlePart></docTitle><titlePart>ES 156: Professional Studies</titlePart><titlePart><hi rend="bold">Group 4:</hi><name type="student name"/><name type="student name"/><name type="student name"/><name type="student name"/> 1 <hi rend="sup">st</hi> year undergraduates, School of Engineering, University of <name type="university"/></titlePart><titlePart>Tuesday, 9 <hi rend="sup">th</hi> March 2004 Written report</titlePart></titlePage><div1 type="abstract"><head rend="bold">Summary</head><p>The aim of this project was to investigate the effects of body shell design and other safety features, on car crash safety. This was done by assessing current methods and producing a simple model, and applying this to notional car, the Jaguar 'Y-Type'.</p></div1><div1 type="toc" n="2"><head rend="bold">Table of Contents</head><p/></div1><titlePage><titlePart><name type="student name"/><name type="student ID"/></titlePart></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Computer Modelling</head><p n="p1.31"><s n="s1.1;p1.31">How computer models and experimental work are used in the design process to improve car performance in crashes </s></p><div2><head rend="bold">Introduction</head><p n="p2.31"><s n="s1.6;p2.31">Since the introduction of computers in the design of static and dynamic components in engineering, the Finite Element Method (FEM) has continually developed to become the unparalleled numerical analysis method. </s><s n="s2.6;p2.31">First introduced in the 1940's as an analysis tool for structural components in the aerospace industry, the nuclear industry soon found it useful in many applications. </s><s n="s3.6;p2.31">The critical requirements for structural integrity justified the very consuming process of the lengthy integrations and calculations involved. </s><s n="s4.6;p2.31">Computers began to play a larger and larger role as their computational power increased exponentially. </s><s n="s5.6;p2.31">The time involved to model components, and the manual task force required to complete the calculations subsequently dropped off. </s><s n="s6.6;p2.31">As computers advanced, the advantages of this technology could be reaped by less wealthy industries and by those with fewer requirements for the achievable high degree of accuracy. </s></p><p n="p3.31"><s n="s1.1;p3.31">Finite Element Analysis (FEA) has broken down many of the barriers in the design process, integrating the separate entities and bringing the divisions a lot closer. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0249j-fig.001"/><p n="p4.31"><s n="s1.5;p4.31">The Design can be modified directly, run through complex numerical testing, the results, and resultant modifications be applied to the computer model and retested before any physical models need be created. </s><s n="s2.5;p4.31">At the time of prototyping and testing, the design has now undergone a great deal of analysis, and will be significantly more advanced in its development. </s><s n="s3.5;p4.31">This saves time in the lengthy processes of realisation, performing tests, and analysing the implications of each tests results. </s><s n="s4.5;p4.31">The cost is cut dramatically with each test as the simulation can be carried out in-house, at cost of labour, without any sourcing or contracting, and without the additional expense of materials and manufacture. </s><s n="s5.5;p4.31">Testing by this point of the development process should be more of a formality, as well as a check that the technology of FEA has been correctly applied. </s></p><p n="p5.31"><s n="s1.5;p5.31">As the design will be a model on the computer, the manufacturing process can take advantage of Computer Aided Manufacture (CAM). </s><s n="s2.5;p5.31">This involves Computer Numerical Control (CNC), where geometry incorporated in the computer model is transmitted to machines where it is translated by the machine tools onto the material and the desired product is produced. </s><s n="s3.5;p5.31">This allows for a very high degree of accuracy and clearly cuts down the manual labour required reducing costs from the outset. </s><s n="s4.5;p5.31">Faster production, self-maintaining machines, and 24 hour production are amongst the advantages offered by integrating Computer Aided Design with manufacture (CAD/CAM). </s><s n="s5.5;p5.31">Rapid prototyping can also be employed, allowing designs to be realised even faster and a physical model to be 'printed' off from a computer. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">How the automotive industry makes use of FEA</head><p n="p6.31"><s n="s1.2;p6.31">The properties of FEA make the technology ideally suited to application in the automotive industry. </s><s n="s2.2;p6.31">FEA is utilised in almost every field of the automotive industry: </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p7.31"><s n="s1.2;p7.31">Clashes - where two or more components are positioned such that they both occupy the same point in space. </s><s n="s2.2;p7.31">Such clashes can be highlighted and the space reallocated by rearranging components, either automatically or manually. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p8.31"><s n="s1.1;p8.31">Aerodynamics - supplementing the use of high-cost wind tunnels, the aerodynamics of a car can be analysed to reduce resistance and losses in turbulence. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p9.31"><s n="s1.1;p9.31">Fluid dynamics - the behaviour of the various fluids in the engine and fuel tank can be modelled and simulated with the different uses of FEA. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p10.31"><s n="s1.1;p10.31">Temperature simulation - ensuring a component does not exceed the limiting properties of the material and cause weakness, excessive expansion or failure. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p11.31"><s n="s1.1;p11.31">Electrical field modelling - allowing engineers to design the vehicle so that charge is directed away from the occupants in the event of lightening strike, or merely static build-up as a result of friction with charged particles in the air during the journey. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p12.31"><s n="s1.2;p12.31">Stress/strain - originally applied in static applications such as the stresses in supports. </s><s n="s2.2;p12.31">More complex models allow dynamic simulations, and most importantly, crash simulations. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">Theory</head><p n="p13.31"><s n="s1.4;p13.31">FEA, is the implementation of FEM with regard to a particular situation. </s><s n="s2.4;p13.31">The theory of FEM is to model any two or three-dimensional shape as multiples of simple polynomials. </s><s n="s3.4;p13.31">These polynomials are called 'elements', and the model is meshed into a number of these finite sized elements. </s><s n="s4.4;p13.31">The vertices of these elements are called 'nodes', and the edges are called 'splines'. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0249j-pic.001"><head rend="italic">Examples of 1st order finite elements, followed by their respective 2nd order counterpart. </head></figure><p n="p14.31"><s n="s1.5;p14.31">The displacement of each 'element' is then modelled with simple polynomial shape functions, and the displacements of the elements' nodes. </s><s n="s2.5;p14.31">Very few components utilise wholly straight edges now, and indeed it is rare that this would be the best shape for the components, as this concentrates stresses, and would be a likely point of failure. </s><s n="s3.5;p14.31">As FEM creates an approximation of values, the truer the mesh is to the model, the more accurate the analysis will be. </s><s n="s4.5;p14.31">Rather than modelling a radius as a finite number of linear elements (lower, or 1 <hi rend="sup">st</hi> order elements), akin to a curve, nodes can be placed mid-spline, and parabolic functions be applied to explain the geometry of the curve (higher, or 2 <hi rend="sup">nd</hi> order elements). </s><s n="s5.5;p14.31">The quadratic equations applied yield better modelling than their linear counterparts as they can adjust to the model bending, without over-simplifying the resultant curved structures. </s></p><p n="p15.31"><s n="s1.2;p15.31">Although an increasingly automated process, the meshing of an object is a technical operation, requiring great skill and knowledge to apply a suitable mesh to achieve the required level of accuracy, and with as low a calculation time as possible. </s><s n="s2.2;p15.31">The number of finite elements regulates the time required for the calculations to be made. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0249j-pic.002"/><p n="p16.31"><s n="s1.1;p16.31">The above diagrams illustrate how users can apply the mesh to optimise the compromises made, and how smaller elements are required in areas of greater detail and complexity. {A} is the simple approach, {B} is extremely complicated whilst {C} concentrates the computations in the main area of interest. </s></p><p n="p17.31"><s n="s1.2;p17.31">Without ensuring the relevant areas are suitably meshed, descretisation errors occur, simply meaning that the model is very inaccurate as a result of oversimplification. </s><s n="s2.2;p17.31">As with all differential mathematics, the smaller the element the model is divided into, the more accurate the model will be in representing the actual behaviour of the component. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">Stress and displacement analysis</head><p n="p18.31"><s n="s1.6;p18.31">Stress can be described as a measurement of the intensity of a force. </s><s n="s2.6;p18.31">If this increases beyond the yield point, the material will no longer behave elastically and will permanently deform, and with sufficient intensity, fail. </s><s n="s3.6;p18.31">There are two approaches to FEA, using the 'stiffness matrix' and via the 'force matrix' methods. </s><s n="s4.6;p18.31">The latter equates the stresses for a known displacement, whereas the stiffness matrix would be used if the displacement is unknown. </s><s n="s5.6;p18.31">Simulating the impact of car crashes, the displacement is the unknown, and whilst the force is non-linear, the computer calculates this in incremental steps. </s><s n="s6.6;p18.31">This adds a further degree of approximation, reduced by limiting the size of each increment. </s></p><p n="p19.31"><s n="s1.1;p19.31">The wireframe model can be meshed using suitable software, e.g. </s></p><list type="bulleted"><item>PATRAN </item><item>ABAQUS </item><item>EXPLICIT-ABAQUS </item><item>MARC </item><item>ANSYS </item><item>IDEAS </item><item>PRO-ENGINEER </item><item>FEAMAP </item><item>STRUCAD</item></list><p n="p20.31"><s n="s1.8;p20.31">The model can then be assigned a material. </s><s n="s2.8;p20.31">With this assignment the material's properties, coupled with the model geometry are used to create the stiffness matrix. </s><s n="s3.8;p20.31">With the calculated forces, the displacement of each node can be evaluated using the stiffness matrix. </s><s n="s4.8;p20.31">When the displacements are evaluated, they are differentiated to give six strain distributions. </s><s n="s5.8;p20.31">Three of these mutually perpendicular direct strains &amp; three corresponding shear strains. </s><s n="s6.8;p20.31">Six stress distributions are then calculated using the stress/strain relationships specific to the material applied to the mesh. </s><s n="s7.8;p20.31">The stresses within an element can be calculated once the internal forces are determined, calculated using the displacements and the elements stiffness. </s><s n="s8.8;p20.31">This allows for higher resolution analysis, and thus allowing slightly larger elements to be used on occasion. </s></p><p n="p21.31"><s n="s1.2;p21.31">Constraints are made to respective nodes to simulate immovable properties, for instance the road's surface, a wall, or perhaps a post. </s><s n="s2.2;p21.31">The connection between surfaces for instance the axle with the chassis and the wheels can also be built into the model. </s></p><p n="p22.31"><s n="s1.2;p22.31">Velocity and acceleration Degrees Of Freedom (DOF) are applied to appropriate nodes of the mesh representing the motion of the vehicle, and in addition any other constraint. </s><s n="s2.2;p22.31">Rotational DOF are also applied, modelling the freedom of the wheels and axles to turn within the model. </s></p><p n="p23.31"><s n="s1.3;p23.31">The simulation can now begin, and the computer will compute the forces and displacements in each element. </s><s n="s2.3;p23.31">The complex equations relating the many elements are compiled in a matrix that the computer can solve by integration. </s><s n="s3.3;p23.31">The stresses can then be computed from the forces and displacements. </s></p><p n="p24.31"><s n="s1.2;p24.31">Increasingly common within FEA packages, is the integration of CAD capabilities. </s><s n="s2.2;p24.31">This allows designs to be modified as faults are discovered with the minimal of time before testing can recommence. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">How accurate? </head><p n="p25.31"><s n="s1.4;p25.31">The reliability of FEA has led to a rapid spread throughout industry. </s><s n="s2.4;p25.31">Crash investigation now utilises this method to reconstruct and accurately calculate the forces involved in. </s><s n="s3.4;p25.31">Billions are invested by companies across the world to upgrade to make use of computers as an analytical tool, and the improvements in performance of crash safety is proof to its integrity. </s><s n="s4.4;p25.31">So prolific is the use of FEA the following statement was made by a SkodaAuto Manager: </s></p><quote lang="English">"Increased competition and higher market standard have made it impossible for SkodaAuto to develop a car model without digital simulation", says Milos Safr, CAE Manager, SkodaAuto.</quote><p n="p26.31"><s n="s1.2;p26.31">Recently Skoda has started using PAM-Crash, a particular FEA package. </s><s n="s2.2;p26.31">As a result the Skoda Fabia achieved an excellent four star rating in the Euro-NCAP (European New Car Assessment Programme) crash tests. </s></p><quote lang="English">" ESI Group's simulation solution for crash analysis has taken our company one step closer towards fully virtual prototypes".</quote></div2><div2><head rend="bold">Developement</head><p n="p27.31"><s n="s1.6;p27.31">The Vehicle Technology Research team at Birmingham University's Mechanical Engineering Department are actively involved with furthering the development of FEA and its applications. </s><s n="s2.6;p27.31">Anthropometrically correct models can also be meshed, simulating humans within the vehicle. </s><s n="s3.6;p27.31">Crash test dummies cost £100,000 per model, so great expense is saved by using this digital methodology. </s><s n="s4.6;p27.31">Skoda made early use of this adaptation of crash testing, simulating a total of 700,000 finite elements including the vehicle, passengers and airbag. </s><s n="s5.6;p27.31">Birmingham has been using these models to simulate passenger collisions, and so increase the safety of the car with regards to humans outside of the vehicle. </s><s n="s6.6;p27.31">The importance of this is not yet fully reflected in NCAP tests, but digital simulations can allow manufacturers to design and supply safer vehicles for everyone. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">Alternatives</head><p n="p28.31"><s n="s1.4;p28.31">Computers are also improving results in physical crash testing. </s><s n="s2.4;p28.31">Rapid firing digital cameras have improved in resolution and sensitivity sufficiently to replace previous film cameras. </s><s n="s3.4;p28.31">This provides instant results and cuts out the expense of film processing, although significant capital is required for set-up costs. </s><s n="s4.4;p28.31">Film sequences can be further slowed by the computers ability to interpolate frames between those taken by the camera, allowing more detailed analysis of crashes. </s></p><p n="p29.31"><s n="s1.1;p29.31">Developments in true 3-dimensional displays are set to make a big impact as virtual simulations can then be scrutinised from every angle and designers can better visualise the product under development. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">Business, Marketing, Finance and Cash flow</head><p n="p30.31"><s n="s1.3;p30.31">The use of latest technology such as FEA is an order qualifier, but the resultant class-leading crash test results are order winners in themselves. </s><s n="s2.3;p30.31">Jaguar already incorporates FEA into its design process, so training or expense of setting up is not required. </s><s n="s3.3;p30.31">The NCAP crash test ratings achieved in cases such as the Skoda Fabia highlight the benefits to safety offered by FEA. The increased sales resulting from such publicity cover costs of setting up the facility, with massive savings in prototyping and testing too. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">Environmental</head><p n="p31.31"><s n="s1.2;p31.31">As prototyping is kept to a minimum, raw materials are not used, and much less power is required to power the computers used to model digitally. </s><s n="s2.2;p31.31">As no product is actually made, there is no recycling associated, although recycled paper may be used to make hard copies of some results. </s></p></div2></div1></body><back><div1 type="bibliography"><head rend="bold">References</head><p>Engineeringtalk (2004) website</p><p><seg type="URL" n="http://www.engineeringtalk.com/news/esi/esi110.html"/></p><p>(as visited 02/03/04)</p><p>Cultivate interactive (2004) website</p><p><seg type="URL" n="http://www.cultivate-int.org/issue2/vakhum/"/></p><p>(as visited 02/03/04)</p><p>Ceintl (2004) website</p><p><seg type="URL" n="http://www.ceintl.com/industries/industries.html"/></p><p>(as visited 02/03/04)</p><p>Birmingham University (2004) website</p><p><seg type="URL" n="http://www.vtech.bham.ac.uk/"/></p><p>(as visited 02/03/04)</p><p>Stress Engineering Services (2004) website</p><p><seg type="URL" n="http://www.stress.com/oilgas/fin_elem_analysis.htm"/></p><p>(as visited 02/03/04)</p><p>Dermotmonaghan (2004) website</p><p><seg type="URL" n="http://www.dermotmonaghan.com/"/></p><p><seg type="URL" n="http://www.dermotmonaghan.com/feInformation/introduction/whatIsFea.php"/></p><p><seg type="URL" n="http://www.dermotmonaghan.com/feInformation/introduction/applicationAreas.php"/></p><p><seg type="URL" n="http://www.dermotmonaghan.com/feInformation/introduction/typicalAnalysis.php"/></p><p><seg type="URL" n="http://www.dermotmonaghan.com/feInformation/introduction/femVsFea.php"/></p><p><seg type="URL" n="http://www.dermotmonaghan.com/feInformation/introduction/wordOfCaution.php"/></p><p><seg type="URL" n="http://www.dermotmonaghan.com/feInformation/analysisTypes/displacement.php"/></p><p><seg type="URL" n="http://www.dermotmonaghan.com/feInformation/analysisTypes/dynamic.php"/></p><p><seg type="URL" n="http://www.dermotmonaghan.com/feInformation/analysisTypes/modal.php"/></p><p><seg type="URL" n="http://www.dermotmonaghan.com/feInformation/improvingResults/planningAnalyses.php"/></p><p><seg type="URL" n="http://www.dermotmonaghan.com/feInformation/improvingResults/sourcesOfError.php"/></p><p><seg type="URL" n="http://www.dermotmonaghan.com/feInformation/improvingResults/readingResults.php"/></p><p><seg type="URL" n="http://www.dermotmonaghan.com/feInformation/improvingResults/designPlanning.php"/></p><p><seg type="URL" n="http://www.dermotmonaghan.com/feInformation/meshGeneration/introductionToMeshing.php"/></p><p><seg type="URL" n="http://www.dermotmonaghan.com/feInformation/meshGeneration/elementTypes.php"/></p><p><seg type="URL" n="http://www.dermotmonaghan.com/feInformation//meshGeneration/automaticMeshing.php"/></p><p>(as visited 02/03/04)</p><p>IABG (2004) website</p><p><seg type="URL" n="http://www.iabg.de/automotive/cae_cad/insassensimu_crashanalyse_en.php"/></p><p>(as visited 02/03/04)</p><p>ESI-Group (2004) website</p><p><seg type="URL" n="http://www.esi-group.com/SimulationSoftware/crash.html"/></p><p><seg type="URL" n="http://www.esi-group.com/SimulationSoftware/SimulationSoftware/NumericalSimulation"/></p><p>(as visited 02/03/04)</p><p>Easi (website) 2004</p><p><seg type="URL" n="http://www.easi.de/products/ecd/_img/ecd_pre.gif"/></p><p>(as visited 02/03/04)</p><p>Corus Automotive (2004) website</p><p><seg type="URL" n="http://www.corusautomotive.com/pub/technical/CorusF2C.pdf"/></p><p>(as visited 02/03/04)</p><p>Applied Research Associates (2004) website</p><p><seg type="URL" n="http://www.arasvo.com/crown_victoria/crown_vic.htm"/></p><p>(as visited 02/03/04)</p><p>CEI (2004) website</p><p><seg type="URL" n="http://www.ceintl.com/news/miss-state.html"/></p><p>(as visited 02/03/04)</p><p>SGI (2004) website</p><p><seg type="URL" n="http://www.sgi.com/industries/manufacturing/eoi/vol2/summer/partner.html"/></p><p>(as visited 02/03/04)</p><p>Polxwest (2004) website</p><p><seg type="URL" n="http://www.polxwest.com/crash.htm"/></p><p>(as visited 2004)</p><p>3dcgi (2004) website</p><p><seg type="URL" n="http://www.3dcgi.com/cooltech/displays/displays.htm"/></p><p>(as visited 02/03/04)</p></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
