<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_0249h" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Bending and Torsion</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">appendix: Figures, Tables and Graphs</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">1</p><p n="date">2004-05</p><p n="module title">Engineering Mechanics</p><p n="module code">ES161</p><p n="genre family">Methodology recount</p><p n="discipline">Engineering</p><p n="disciplinary group">PS</p><p n="grade">M</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">932</p><p n="number of s-units">64</p><p n="number of p">34</p><p n="number of tables">1</p><p n="number of figures">1</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">32</p><p n="number of lists">8</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">8</p><p n="abstract present">abstract present</p><p n="average words per s-unit">14.6</p><p n="average s-units per p">1.9</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">m</p><p n="year of birth">1985</p><p n="first language">English</p><p n="education">UKA</p><p n="course">Engineering</p><p n="student ID">0249</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><docTitle><titlePart rend="bold">Bending and Torsion</titlePart></docTitle><titlePart>ES161: Engineering Mechanics <hi rend="bold"><name type="student name"/></hi> 1 <hi rend="sup">st</hi> year undergraduate, School of Engineering, University of <name type="university"/></titlePart></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="abstract"><head rend="bold">Summary</head><p n="p1.34"><s n="s1.3;p1.34">This investigation was to assess the usefulness of mathematical models to calculate deflection due to bending and torsion behaviour. </s><s n="s2.3;p1.34">This used models derived from simple linear elastic theory, including judgements of the approximations involved. </s><s n="s3.3;p1.34">These models were then compared against experimental data obtained in the years of 1995 and 1998. </s></p><p n="p2.34"><s n="s1.2;p2.34">The bending data was collected from a rig consisting of a simply supported beam, and a sliding mass. </s><s n="s2.2;p2.34">The torsion behaviour was collected from a rig comprising a cantilevered hollow shaft. </s></p><p n="p3.34"><s n="s1.1;p3.34">The models proved to be inaccurate and could not supply sufficient modelling of the deformations. </s></p></div1><div1 type="front-back-matter"><head rend="bold">Table of Contents</head><p/></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Introduction</head><p n="p4.34"><s n="s1.3;p4.34">This investigation assesses the usefulness of mathematical models to calculate deflection due to bending and torsion behaviour. </s><s n="s2.3;p4.34">This used models derived from simple linear elastic theory, including judgements of the approximations involved. </s><s n="s3.3;p4.34">These models were then compared against experimental data obtained in the years of 1995 and 1998. </s></p><p n="p5.34"><s n="s1.2;p5.34">The bending data was collected from a rig consisting of a simply supported beam, and a sliding mass. </s><s n="s2.2;p5.34">The torsion behaviour was collected from a rig comprising a cantilevered hollow shaft. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Theory</head><div2><head rend="bold">Simply Supported Beam</head><p n="p6.34"><s n="s1.3;p6.34">This mathematical model calculates the displacement of a simply supported beam caused by a load applied between the supports. </s><s n="s2.3;p6.34">The model is derived used linear elastic theory. </s><s n="s3.3;p6.34">The general beam equation is: </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p7.34"><s n="s1.1;p7.34">1. <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0249h-form.001"/> </s></p><list type="simple"><head>where:</head><item><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0249h-form.002"/></item><item><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0249h-form.003"/></item><item><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0249h-form.004"/></item><item><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0249h-form.005"/></item><item><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0249h-form.006"/></item><item><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0249h-form.007"/></item></list><p n="p8.34"><s n="s1.1;p8.34">The displacement of the beam after a load is applied can be modelled by: </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p9.34"><s n="s1.1;p9.34">2. <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0249h-form.008"/> </s></p><p n="p10.34"><s n="s1.1;p10.34">Using McCauley's method we can create one formula: </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p11.34"><s n="s1.1;p11.34">3. <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0249h-form.009"/> </s></p><list type="simple"><head>Where:</head><item><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0249h-form.010"/></item><item><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0249h-form.011"/></item><item><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0249h-form.012"/></item><item><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0249h-form.013"/></item></list><p n="p12.34"><s n="s1.1;p12.34">For a rectangular cross sectional area: </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p13.34"><s n="s1.1;p13.34">4. <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0249h-form.014"/> </s></p><p n="p14.34"><s n="s1.1;p14.34">Integrating equation 3 twice gives us a working model for vertical deflection of a simply supported beam. </s></p><div3><head rend="bold italic">Maximum displacement</head><p n="p15.34"><s n="s1.4;p15.34">The formula above calculates only the maximum displacement. </s><s n="s2.4;p15.34">This assumes a sinusoidal deformation. </s><s n="s3.4;p15.34">In reality, if the load is applied offset from the centre of the beam, then the maximum displacement occurs close to the centre, but towards the direction of the load. </s><s n="s4.4;p15.34">The following formula calculates where maximum displacement will be: </s></p><p n="p16.34"><s n="s1.1;p16.34">Maximum displacement: </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p17.34"><s n="s1.1;p17.34">5. <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0249h-form.015"/> </s></p><p n="p18.34"><s n="s1.1;p18.34">occurs at a distance of c from 'A': </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p19.34"><s n="s1.1;p19.34">6. <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0249h-form.016"/> </s></p><list type="simple"><head>where</head><item><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0249h-form.017"/></item><item><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0249h-form.018"/></item></list></div3></div2><div2><head rend="bold">Cantilevered Beam</head><p n="p20.34"><s n="s1.1;p20.34">Total deflection of the beam consists of three components: </s></p><list type="bulleted"><item>Bending of the lever arm</item><item>Bending of the tube</item><item>Twisting of the tube</item></list><p n="p21.34"><s n="s1.1;p21.34">Experiments to calculate the bending components can provide results to negate their effect upon the displacement. </s></p><p n="p22.34"><s n="s1.1;p22.34">The formula for a cantilevered beam is: </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p23.34"><s n="s1.1;p23.34">7. <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0249h-form.019"/> </s></p><list type="simple"><head>where:</head><item><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0249h-form.020"/></item><item><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0249h-form.021"/></item><item><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0249h-form.022"/></item><item><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0249h-form.023"/></item><item><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0249h-form.024"/></item></list><p n="p24.34"><s n="s1.1;p24.34">And deflection due to twisting: </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p25.34"><s n="s1.1;p25.34">8. <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0249h-form.025"/> </s></p><list type="simple"><head>]where:</head><item><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0249h-form.026"/></item><item><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0249h-form.027"/></item><item><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0249h-form.028"/></item><item><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0249h-form.029"/></item><item><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0249h-form.030"/></item><item><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0249h-form.031"/></item><item><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0249h-form.032"/></item></list></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Apparatus and Method</head><p n="p26.34"><s n="s1.2;p26.34">Two separate rigs were used for the bending and for the torsion experiments. </s><s n="s2.2;p26.34">A simply supported beam with a knife edge support at either end, a sliding adjustable mass, and sliding displacement gauge were used: </s></p><p n="p27.34"><s n="s1.3;p27.34">The mass slider was placed at specific distances from 'A' along the beam. </s><s n="s2.3;p27.34">The displacement gauge was also placed at specific distances from 'A' for each of the positions of the mass slider. </s><s n="s3.3;p27.34">The masses were used for each of the following combinations: </s></p><table id="BAWE_0249h-tab.001"><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p28.34"><s n="s1.2;p28.34">The masses used were 0.5 and 1.0 Kg. </s><s n="s2.2;p28.34">The displacement was then recorded for each of the above combinations. </s></p><div2><head rend="bold">Cantilevered Shaft</head><p n="p29.34"><s n="s1.3;p29.34">A lever arm was clamped onto the free end of a cantilevered tube, fixed at the other end into a wooden frame. </s><s n="s2.3;p29.34">The lever arm was first distanced from the fixed end of the tube by 200 mm, and later repeated at 100 mm. </s><s n="s3.3;p29.34">An adjustable mass was then hung on the lever arm, firstly 200 mm from the centre of the tube, and then repeated again at 100 mm. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0249h-pic.001"/><p n="p30.34"><s n="s1.9;p30.34">The total displacement was recorded by using a height gauge, and measuring at the free end of the lever arm. </s><s n="s2.9;p30.34">This was recorded before and after load was applied, the change being the total deflection. </s><s n="s3.9;p30.34">As explained in the theory, this is not the deflection due to the torque of the tube. </s><s n="s4.9;p30.34">To isolate this, the mass was also hung from the free end of the tube, and the displacement measured. </s><s n="s5.9;p30.34">The deflection due to the tube bending was then be deducted from the total deflection. </s><s n="s6.9;p30.34">The same principle was applied to negate the deflection due to the lever arm bending. </s><s n="s7.9;p30.34">The mass was hung from the lever arm, whilst the lever arm was fixed to the tube at the fixed end. </s><s n="s8.9;p30.34">This eliminated torsion in the tube as the4 length of tube under load was negligible. </s><s n="s9.9;p30.34">The deflection due to the bending of the lever arm was then deducted too, leaving the deflection due entirely to the torque applied to the tube remaining. </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Observations and Results</head><p n="p31.34"><s n="s1.1;p31.34">The results of the simply supported beam are displayed in Table 1, whilst the cantilevered beam results are displayed in Tables 2 and 3. </s></p><p n="p32.34"><s n="s1.1;p32.34">The models proved to be so inaccurate that estimations could not be made rendering the models useless. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Analysis of Results</head><p n="p33.34"><s n="s1.3;p33.34">The mathematical models proved useless, and estimations could not be made. </s><s n="s2.3;p33.34">The second set of results taken from the cantilevered beam is plotted in Graph 1, and shows a good linear relationship. </s><s n="s3.3;p33.34">Errors in the results are great. </s></p><list type="bulleted"><head rend="bold italic"> Bending</head><item>Placement of the mass and displacement gauge +/- 5 mm</item><item>Reading of displacement +/- 0.01 mm</item></list><list type="bulleted"><head rend="bold italic">Torsion</head><item>Slipping of the lever arm on the tube</item><item>Reading and using the height gauge</item><item>Bending of the lever arm and the tube, though this been reduced by taking further experiments to subtract their deformation from the total displacement.</item><item>Position of load and lever arm +/- 5 mm</item></list></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Conclusions</head><p n="p34.34"><s n="s1.4;p34.34">The deformation of simply supported beams, and of cantilevered hollow shafts depends upon many variables. </s><s n="s2.4;p34.34">This proved difficult when devising mathematical models. </s><s n="s3.4;p34.34">The models proved too difficult, the behaviour of the deformations backed up the theory of linear deformation. </s><s n="s4.4;p34.34">Variables include the geometry of the beam, the material and many more dimensions. </s></p></div1></body><back><div1 type="appendix"><head rend="bold">Figures, Tables and Graphs</head><p/></div1><div1 type="bibliography"><head rend="bold">References and Bibliography</head><p>Lecture slides by D Woods. </p><p>Bedford and Fowler</p><p><hi rend="bold">"Engineering Mechanics: Statics and Dynamics principles"</hi>, Prentice Hall </p><p>The following supplementary notes are available in the lab:</p><p rend="bold">Laboratory briefing sheet, D Chetwynd</p><p>Engineering Data Book 4<hi rend="sup">th</hi> edition (ed. AJ Cartwright) 2001</p><p>Civil.ubc (2004) website </p><p><seg type="URL" n="http://www.civil.ubc.ca/courses/civilcourses/civl436/notes/Civl436NotesOnBeams.pdf"/> (as visited on 18/04/04)</p></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
