<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_0249f" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Measurement of induction motor characteristics</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">The document has a title page which contains:
document title
title part
abstract</note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">deleted: header: assignment title; footer: student name, page numbers</note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">appendices: figure, tables and graphs; equipment, connections; lab briefing sheet; detailed equipment specs</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">1</p><p n="date">2004-03</p><p n="module title">Electrical and Electronic Machines</p><p n="module code">ES163</p><p n="genre family">Methodology recount</p><p n="discipline">Engineering</p><p n="disciplinary group">PS</p><p n="grade">M</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">2014</p><p n="number of s-units">117</p><p n="number of p">68</p><p n="number of tables">1</p><p n="number of figures">0</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">20</p><p n="number of lists">4</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">6</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">17.2</p><p n="average s-units per p">1.7</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">m</p><p n="year of birth">1985</p><p n="first language">English</p><p n="education">UKA</p><p n="course">Engineering</p><p n="student ID">0249</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><docTitle><titlePart rend="bold">Measurement of induction motor characteristics</titlePart></docTitle><titlePart>ES 163: Electrical &amp; Electronic Machines <hi rend="bold"><name type="student name"/></hi> 1 <hi rend="sup">st</hi> year undergraduate, School of Engineering, University of <name type="university"/> Thursday, 20 <hi rend="sup">th</hi> November 2003</titlePart></titlePage><div1 type="abstract"><head rend="bold">Summary</head><p>Investigation into the characteristics of an induction motor. Calculating the efficiency at various loads and confirming the necessity to operate at loads relating to the rated power levels to achieve optimum results.</p></div1><div1 type="toc" n="1"><head rend="bold">Table Of Contents</head><p/></div1></front><body><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Introduction</head><p n="p1.68"><s n="s1.4;p1.68">The report details the investigation and measurement of the characteristics specific to an induction motor. </s><s n="s2.4;p1.68">A three-phase induction motor was connected to a test system comprising a dynamometer (an electronically-controlled brake) and a tachometer (an electrical speed-measuring device) to complete this experiment. </s><s n="s3.4;p1.68">The torque on the brake was measured by a cantilever spring fitted with a strain gauge, and the signals from this, along with the data produced by the tachometer were fed to a control box. </s><s n="s4.4;p1.68">This allowed manual control of the torque on the brake, as well as feeding back the values for torque, speed and a calculated value for mechanical power output, using: </s></p><p n="p2.68"><s n="s1.1;p2.68">Mechanical power = torque x time, or </s></p><p n="p3.68"><s n="s1.1;p3.68"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0249f-form.001"/> </s></p><p n="p4.68"><s n="s1.2;p4.68">Values were tabulated with varied load applied to the motor increasing in increments of 0.5 Nm till the point that the motor stalled. </s><s n="s2.2;p4.68">Graphs were then traced showing the relationship between torque and speed, as well as another illustrating the efficiency of the motor at these varied loads. </s></p><p n="p5.68"><s n="s1.1;p5.68">The conclusion of this laboratory serves to reinforce the need to run inductor motors at their rated power levels to obtain maximum efficiency and reduce the likelihood of damaging the motor by overloading. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Theory</head><p n="p6.68"><s n="s1.1;p6.68">Whilst the entirety of this section is not utilised in the calculations, below are a number of equations relevant to this report. </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p7.68"><s n="s1.2;p7.68">1. </s><s n="s2.2;p7.68">Mechanical power = torque x time, or </s></p><p n="p8.68"><s n="s1.1;p8.68"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0249f-form.002"/> </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p9.68"><s n="s1.2;p9.68">2. </s><s n="s2.2;p9.68">In the absence of a measuring unit that measures power factor (p.f), it is possible to calculate the value using: </s></p><p n="p10.68"><s n="s1.1;p10.68"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0249f-form.003"/> </s></p><p n="p11.68"><s n="s1.1;p11.68">or </s></p><p n="p12.68"><s n="s1.1;p12.68"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0249f-form.004"/> </s></p><p n="p13.68"><s n="s1.1;p13.68">where </s></p><p n="p14.68"><s n="s1.1;p14.68"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0249f-form.005"/> </s></p><p n="p15.68"><s n="s1.1;p15.68"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0249f-form.006"/> </s></p><p n="p16.68"><s n="s1.1;p16.68"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0249f-form.007"/> </s></p><p n="p17.68"><s n="s1.1;p17.68"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0249f-form.008"/> </s></p><p n="p18.68"><s n="s1.1;p18.68">For more theory see appendix 3, as well as websites listed in 'References and Bibliography'. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Apparatus and Method</head><p n="p19.68"><s n="s1.7;p19.68">The apparatus required for this laboratory are detailed in Appendix A1. </s><s n="s2.7;p19.68">The rated values were read and recorded from the motor nameplate (O1). </s><s n="s3.7;p19.68">The equipment was then calibrated to ensure that the measurements were traceable back to a known standard. </s><s n="s4.7;p19.68">The measuring unit was switched on by means of the switch marked (C), and the three-phase energy analyser on the measuring unit lit up as expected. </s><s n="s5.7;p19.68">The display was set up to the first measuring page, showing voltage, current, power and power factor. </s><s n="s6.7;p19.68">This page had the symbol '3Φ' at the bottom. </s><s n="s7.7;p19.68">By pressing 'PAGE' repeatedly, the display was set to page 4, showing 'V L1, L2, L3' corresponding to the voltages on the three lines relative to neutral. </s></p><p n="p20.68"><s n="s1.3;p20.68">The switch marked (D) was switched off, the variable output control knob on the supply panel set to zero, and the output voltage selector set to 1 (three-phase). </s><s n="s2.3;p20.68">The variable three-phase outputs, L1, L2, L3 and N on the supply panel, were connected respectively to the corresponding connections on the left-hand side of the measuring unit. </s><s n="s3.3;p20.68">The switches marked (B) and (D) were then enabled. </s></p><p n="p21.68"><s n="s1.5;p21.68">The variable output control was turned to about 25% and the values for the three line-to-neutral voltages were recorded (O2) to check they were all within 1 or 2% of one another to enable errors to be spotted and corrected, to reduce inconsistencies at a later stage. </s><s n="s2.5;p21.68">The measurement display was then changed back to page 1 and it was noted that the voltage now displayed a larger voltage. </s><s n="s3.5;p21.68">This value was the average of the three line-to-line values, and approximately √3 times the line-to-neutral voltage. </s><s n="s4.5;p21.68">These values were calculated (C1), and the values fell within the acceptable tolerance of 1 to 2%. </s><s n="s5.5;p21.68">The line-to-line voltage was increased from 112 V until the value read on the display of the measuring unit equalled the rated motor voltage (380 V) within a tolerance of 1%, and switch (D) was deactivated. </s></p><p n="p22.68"><s n="s1.3;p22.68">The induction motor was then connected 'in star', meaning that U2, V2 and W2 were all connected together. </s><s n="s2.3;p22.68">The three terminals L1, L2 and L3 on the right of the measuring unit were connected to U1, V1 and W1 respectively on the motor. </s><s n="s3.3;p22.68">Switch (D) was then activated and the motor started. </s></p><p n="p23.68"><s n="s1.2;p23.68">The dynamometer control box was set for manual control of torque (T manu on the selector switch) and the manual control set to zero. </s><s n="s2.2;p23.68">The speed range was also set to 200 /min and the power range to 300 W. The indicated output torque and power were non-zero but were below the accepted tolerance values of 0.1 Nm and 5 W respectively. </s></p><p n="p24.68"><s n="s1.1;p24.68">The values of torque, speed, mechanical power output, current, power factor and electrical power input were recorded from this point, and as the load torque was increased in steps of 0.5 Nm up until the motor was running at its rated power of 300 W (Table 1). </s></p><p n="p25.68"><s n="s1.4;p25.68">The following measurements were taken quickly as the motor was required to run at a level above its rated value, and could not be run in this state for more than two minutes. </s><s n="s2.4;p25.68">Prolonged usage at these levels would have resulted in damage to the insulation. </s><s n="s3.4;p25.68">The load torque was again increased in increments of 0.5 Nm and measurements taken as before, up to the point that the motor stalled (Table 1). </s><s n="s4.4;p25.68">The load torque was then immediately reduced to zero, but the motor was not switched off, so enabling its in-built cooling fans to cool the over-clocked motor. </s></p><p n="p26.68"><s n="s1.3;p26.68">The motor was stopped by switching off at switch (D) after it had been allowed to cool for some time, and the oscilloscope was switched on. </s><s n="s2.3;p26.68">The current probe was clipped around one of the motor supply leads, and connected to Ch 1 of the oscilloscope and switched on. </s><s n="s3.3;p26.68">The oscilloscope was set up as follows: </s></p><list type="bulleted"><item>Channel 1 Volts/div = 200 mV. Timebase sec/div = 50 msec</item><item>Acquire>peak detect</item><item>Trigger>'mode' to single, 'slope' to rising</item><item>Trigger level ≈ 200 mV</item><item>Run/stop>Armed/ready.</item></list><p n="p27.68"><s n="s1.1;p27.68">The oscilloscope was then ready to use. </s></p><p n="p28.68"><s n="s1.4;p28.68">The motor was switched back on, with the oscilloscope now displaying the transient starting current of the motor. </s><s n="s2.4;p28.68">A copy of the oscilloscope screen was printed off (Graph 3). </s><s n="s3.4;p28.68">Full load was then applied to the motor while it was running, and the motor switched off. </s><s n="s4.4;p28.68">The motor was switched back on again to repeat the transient measurement, another readout printed off (Graph 4), and then instantly switched back off again. </s></p><p n="p29.68"><s n="s1.2;p29.68">The steady-state no-load current was measured on the oscilloscope by pressing 'autoset', and then pressing 'measure' to set the on-screen menu to Ch1, rms. </s><s n="s2.2;p29.68">The current probe was switched off once that reading was taken. </s></p><p n="p30.68"><s n="s1.1;p30.68">More detail regarding the connections and how to set up the assortment of equipment, refer to Appendices A2 - A6. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Observations and results</head><list type="bulleted"><head><hi rend="bold">O1:</hi> Electrical data recorded from the motor nameplate:</head><item>Rated power: 0.3 kW</item><item>Voltage: 380 V</item><item>Current: 1.0 A</item><item>Power factor: 0.6 cosΦ</item></list><list type="bulleted"><head><hi rend="bold">O2:</hi> Line voltages as recorded from the measuring unit:</head><item>L1: 66.2 V</item><item>L2: 63.1 V</item><item>L3: 65.3 V</item></list><p n="p31.68"><s n="s1.1;p31.68">Average of the three line-line voltages = 112 V as recorded from the display. </s></p><p n="p32.68"><s n="s1.1;p32.68">This value was then calculated to be within the tolerable range of values (C1). </s></p><p n="p33.68"><s n="s1.1;p33.68">The readings taken for torque, speed, mechanical power output, current, power factor and electrical power input as the load torque was increased incrementally are tabulated in 'Table 1.' </s></p><p n="p34.68"><s n="s1.1;p34.68">From the results in 'Table 1,' the following were observed: </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p35.68"><s n="s1.1;p35.68">The range of variation of speed with load equals 241 min <hi rend="sup">-1</hi> </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p36.68"><s n="s1.1;p36.68">Power factor at no load equals: 0.23 cosΦ </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p37.68"><s n="s1.1;p37.68">Power factor at full load equals: 0.86 cosΦ </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p38.68"><s n="s1.1;p38.68">Power factor at rated load equals: 0.67 cos Φ </s></p><p n="p39.68"><s n="s1.2;p39.68">The efficiency of the motor at the various loads was calculated (C2) and recorded in 'Table 2'. </s><s n="s2.2;p39.68">From this table, the efficiency of the motor was observed at the rated load of 300 W, 80.7 % efficient. </s></p><p n="p40.68"><s n="s1.4;p40.68">The print-outs showing the initial current as the motor was switched on with no load, and secondly with full-load are attached (Figure 1 and 2). </s><s n="s2.4;p40.68">The peak current when starting the motor was read off the printout. </s><s n="s3.4;p40.68">The scale for the horizontal axis is each grid square represents 200mV, however this is because the oscilloscope could only plot voltage, and treated the signal from the current probe as such. </s><s n="s4.4;p40.68">The data from the probe was then multiplied by a scaling factor (100 mV/A), and can now the readings can be read as mA, so the scale would be, each square representing 200 mA. The maximum peak-to-peak current when switching on the motor at no load is therefore: </s></p><p n="p41.68"><s n="s1.1;p41.68"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0249f-form.009"/> </s></p><p n="p42.68"><s n="s1.1;p42.68">The peak current when switching on the motor at full-load was calculated using the same method. </s></p><p n="p43.68"><s n="s1.1;p43.68"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0249f-form.010"/> </s></p><p n="p44.68"><s n="s1.1;p44.68">The time taken to reach operating speed in each case were: </s></p><list type="bulleted"><item>100 ms at no load, and</item><item>150 ms at full-load.</item></list></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Analysis of Results</head><div2><head rend="bold">C1: </head><p n="p45.68"><s n="s1.1;p45.68">The average of the three line-to-neutral voltages, </s></p><p n="p46.68"><s n="s1.1;p46.68"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0249f-form.011"/> </s></p><p n="p47.68"><s n="s1.1;p47.68"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0249f-form.012"/> </s></p><p n="p48.68"><s n="s1.1;p48.68">This value, multiplied by <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0249f-form.013"/> should fall within 1 or 2% deviation from the recorded Line-line voltage recorded, 112 V. </s></p><p n="p49.68"><s n="s1.1;p49.68"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0249f-form.014"/> </s></p><p n="p50.68"><s n="s1.1;p50.68">and </s></p><p n="p51.68"><s n="s1.1;p51.68"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0249f-form.015"/> </s></p><p n="p52.68"><s n="s1.1;p52.68">Therefore the values fall within the accepted tolerance. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">C2:</head><p n="p53.68"><s n="s1.1;p53.68">The efficiency of the motor was calculated for all values of load torque applied in 'Table 1', and recorded in 'Table 2.' </s></p><p n="p54.68"><s n="s1.1;p54.68"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0249f-form.016"/> </s></p><p n="p55.68"><s n="s1.3;p55.68">A graph of Torque against speed was plotted, 'Graph 1.' </s><s n="s2.3;p55.68">A second graph was later plotted illustrating the peak of efficiency as the motor nears its rated load (Graph 2). </s><s n="s3.3;p55.68">On both graphs the point corresponding to the rated power output (300 W) is marked. </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Discussion</head><p n="p56.68"><s n="s1.1;p56.68">The figures quoted on the motor nameplate (O1) and the figures taken from the test results compare as follows: </s></p><table id="BAWE_0249f-tab.001"><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p57.68"><s n="s1.3;p57.68">These are very similar with the possible exception of current. </s><s n="s2.3;p57.68">This could be largely due to the inaccuracy of the current probe, coupled with the acute inaccuracy of evaluating graphs printed out from the oscilloscope. </s><s n="s3.3;p57.68">The power factor is clearly inversely proportional to current so should be expected to deviate in a similar fashion. </s></p><p n="p58.68"><s n="s1.1;p58.68"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0249f-form.017"/> </s></p><p n="p59.68"><s n="s1.1;p59.68">so expected PF should </s></p><p n="p60.68"><s n="s1.1;p60.68"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0249f-form.018"/> </s></p><p n="p61.68"><s n="s1.1;p61.68"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0249f-form.019"/> </s></p><p n="p62.68"><s n="s1.1;p62.68"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0249f-form.020"/> </s></p><p n="p63.68"><s n="s1.1;p63.68">as read by the measuring unit. </s></p><p n="p64.68"><s n="s1.4;p64.68">At very low levels of torque, i.e. should the motor be driving small loads, the usefulness of this motor diminishes. </s><s n="s2.4;p64.68">At these low levels, whilst the speed is high, the efficiency, as illustrated in 'Graph 2' is very low, and remains below 50% efficiency until a load torque of 0.5 Nm is applied. </s><s n="s3.4;p64.68">The efficiency then gently increases at a decreasing rate, and peaks at about 82% efficiency with a load torque of 2.5 Nm, before gradually decreasing once more as the motor is overloaded. </s><s n="s4.4;p64.68">The efficiency then starts to fall a little faster as the motor nears stalling, a little over 5 Nm. </s></p><p n="p65.68"><s n="s1.4;p65.68">Power factor increases almost linearly from no load up till the rated power equating to 0.2 Nm of load torque. </s><s n="s2.4;p65.68">From this point, up till the point of stalling, illustrated in 'Graph 3', the power factor starts to plateau. </s><s n="s3.4;p65.68">With addition of more results, the behaviour of Power Factor as the motor verged on stalling could be better simulated. </s><s n="s4.4;p65.68">Greater insight into the behaviour of the induction motor at both the lower and higher load torque's could be achieved by increasing the load in much smaller increments, and building a greater set of results with which to plot the curve on the graphs. </s></p><p n="p66.68"><s n="s1.2;p66.68">Instrumentation of greater accuracy should eliminate discrepancies, and decrease the tolerance levels from 1 or 2% to a fraction of 1%. </s><s n="s2.2;p66.68">Eliminating the need to read the peak current manually by counting off an oscilloscope, and instead recording a readout from a much more precise machine would produce far more accurate results. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Conclusions</head><p n="p67.68"><s n="s1.3;p67.68">The three-phase induction motor upon which the laboratory was conducted showed that for loads requiring power levels much lower than the rated values, the efficiency of the motor is very low indeed. </s><s n="s2.3;p67.68">This results in wasted energy and therefore increased cost with prolonged usage. </s><s n="s3.3;p67.68">The speed at which the motor rotates is also a lot higher at low torque values, possibly resulting in excessive wear to the motor. </s></p><p n="p68.68"><s n="s1.3;p68.68">The motor performs, as is to be expected, at greatest efficiency when operated at its rated values. </s><s n="s2.3;p68.68">When the motor becomes overloaded, efficiency starts to fall, and power factor plateaus and at that point the motor stalls. </s><s n="s3.3;p68.68">When in operation at loads greater than the rated power levels, the motor can quickly overheat, so should not be used in this state for more than a couple of minutes. </s></p></div1></body><back><div1 type="appendix"><head rend="bold">Figures, Tables and Graphs</head><p/></div1><div1 type="appendix"><head rend="bold">Appendices</head><p/></div1><div1 type="bibliography"><head rend="bold">References and Bibliography</head><p>Edward Hughes (rev. I McKenzie Smith):</p><p><hi rend="bold">"Electrical Technology" 7th Edition</hi>, Longman 1995 (Library TK145, HB), Ch. 32 pp 542-547 &amp; Ch. 41 pp 698-703.</p><p>Note that the 8<hi rend="sup">th</hi> Edition of this book is now available but not yet in the library.</p><p>The following supplementary notes are available in the lab:</p><p rend="bold">Single &amp; three-phase power systems &amp; safety devices.</p><p rend="bold"> Feedback/Elcontrol energy analyser</p><p rend="bold"> Tektronix TDS 210 oscilloscope</p><p>Innovatia Designs (2003) website <seg type="URL" n="http://www.innovatia.com/Design_Center/Maximum_Motor_Power.htm"/></p><p>(as visited on 22/01/04)</p><p>Chuck Yung (June 27, 2002) website <seg type="URL" n="http://www.plantservices.com/Web_First/ps.nsf/ArticleID/HCOK-5BHU6K/"/> (as visited on 21/01/04)</p><p>Metglas (2003) website <seg type="URL" n="http://www.metglas.com/downloads/apps/pfc.pdf"/> (as visited on 21/01/04)</p></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
