<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_0249d" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>'Flueric Control of Elastomeric Cells'</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">The document has a title page which contains:
document title
title part</note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">Language used in quote: <foreign id="English">English</foreign></note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">back matter: glossary</note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">appendix: figures</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">3</p><p n="date">2006-05</p><p n="module title">Project</p><p n="module code">ES327</p><p n="genre family">Research report</p><p n="discipline">Engineering</p><p n="disciplinary group">PS</p><p n="grade">D</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">13099</p><p n="number of s-units">667</p><p n="number of p">262</p><p n="number of tables">8</p><p n="number of figures">39</p><p n="number of block quotes">1</p><p n="number of formulae">11</p><p n="number of lists">17</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">72</p><p n="abstract present">abstract present</p><p n="average words per s-unit">19.6</p><p n="average s-units per p">2.5</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">m</p><p n="year of birth">1985</p><p n="first language">English</p><p n="education">UKA</p><p n="course">Engineering</p><p n="student ID">0249</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><docTitle><titlePart>ES327 'Flueric Control of Elastomeric Cells'</titlePart></docTitle><titlePart>MR <name type="student name"/> 3 <hi rend="sup">rd</hi> Year Undergraduate</titlePart></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="abstract"><head rend="bold">Abstract</head><p n="p1.262"><s n="s1.2;p1.262">In depth literature reviews, of University of <name type="university"/> library, Internet and other resources failed to identify much information on flueric design data. </s><s n="s2.2;p1.262">A limited amount of information on the principles was however obtained. </s></p><p n="p2.262"><s n="s1.3;p2.262">Existing fluidic and flueric devices were evaluated and remodelled, making use of current methods of manufacture and new materials. </s><s n="s2.3;p2.262">For ease and speed of manufacture rapid prototype manufacture was selected. </s><s n="s3.3;p2.262">The main disadvantage of this was that the rig overall size was restricted (200 mm x 200 mm ) by the capacity of the <name type="university"/> University rapid prototyping machine. </s></p><p n="p3.262"><s n="s1.4;p3.262">Two basic systems to fluerically control the bistable switching of hydraulic or pneumatic cells were designed. </s><s n="s2.4;p3.262">The models were designed so that specific parameters could be changed, in order for their effectiveness to be evaluated. </s><s n="s3.4;p3.262">Account was taken of the need to model different fluids (air and water). </s><s n="s4.4;p3.262">The designs were kept simple the aim being to demonstrate each principle by using manual stimulation to control the flow. </s></p><p n="p4.262"><s n="s1.2;p4.262">The rigs were designed with variable jet input geometry, different flow channel geometries and different active flow control. </s><s n="s2.2;p4.262">The test programme, in which both fluids were tested on each rig, demonstrated that for different inlet profiles and flow channels the flow could be switched from one side wall or channel to another under controlled conditions. </s></p><p n="p5.262"><s n="s1.4;p5.262">This showed that switching could be triggered not randomly, but in accordance with loading or volume. </s><s n="s2.4;p5.262">Thus the flow discharge path can be controlled. </s><s n="s3.4;p5.262">This has significant potential in a number of areas, including the medical field. </s><s n="s4.4;p5.262">A number of these potential areas were identified during the literature search. </s></p><p n="p6.262"><s n="s1.3;p6.262">Computational analysis was carried out using commercial code STAR-CD. This was not completely successful. </s><s n="s2.3;p6.262">The computational time to complete a simple profile such as weir was roughly 10 minutes, after which time the programme produced flow patterns downstream of the weir. </s><s n="s3.3;p6.262">Work using the geometry of the rig designed for the project did run to completion (typically after a couple of hours) but failed then to produce any flow data for further analysis. </s></p><p n="p7.262"><s n="s1.1;p7.262">The test programme identified a number of potential areas for further investigation:- </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p8.262"><s n="s1.2;p8.262">The relationship between the dimensions of the inlet chamber to the fluid inlet pipe and the effects these have on successful jet attachment. </s><s n="s2.2;p8.262">This should include an investigation to ascertain the effect of the interaction of the fluid with the top and bottom surfaces of the device. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p9.262"><s n="s1.2;p9.262">The Perspex lid should be redesigned to produce a better seal. </s><s n="s2.2;p9.262">There is no evidence that the existing small leakages adversely affected the test results, but this aspect of the design should be improved in future work. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p10.262"><s n="s1.1;p10.262">Rigs of various sizes and ratios should be considered. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p11.262"><s n="s1.1;p11.262">Impact of fluid properties should be evaluated in order to determine what if any effect they have in maintaining strong jet attachment around a surface that creates an adverse pressure gradient (i.e. to follow a convex profile). </s></p><p n="p12.262"><s n="s1.1;p12.262">The designed rigs demonstrate that flow attachment and flow switching can be achieved with cheap, easy to manufacture devices, with the added advantage that dimensional accuracy is not essential. </s></p></div1><div1 type="front-back-matter"><head rend="bold">Author's Assessment of the Project</head><p>
The engineering data obtained from the literature searches was very limited. 
In this report the author has designed simple experimental rigs. 
These rigs successfully demonstrated the engineering principles of fluerics. 
The rig design allowed the author to illustrate the effects on flow attachment for a range of geometric profiles. 
The work carried out to date should be considered the beginning of a more detailed investigation that considers other aspects such as fluid flow rates and pressures as well as general fluid conditions. 
The author had insufficient time to consider what effect changes of fluid properties would have on the jet attachment. 
</p><p>
This work is important as it showed that the jet attachment principle operated for different fluids (water and air being tested). 
It showed that the principle applied to different geometries and to different fluids. 
Thus the usefulness of the principle is not limited to either gaseous or liquid fluids. 
The tests showed that great accuracy in manufacture is not necessary for successful jet attachment and switching. 
Nor are exotic materials required, making this a principal that should be easy to use, simple and cheap to manufacture. 
</p><p>
The work of this project should be continued to determine:- 
</p><p rend="bulleted">
What effect do different geometric profiles have on the point of attachment 
</p><p rend="bulleted">
What effect do these same geometries have on the strength of jet attachment. 
</p><p>
These are only a couple of examples for further investigation. 
Taking this forward will provide designers with empirical data for designing the profiles to give the most appropriate jet attachment conditions for a range of applications ( i.e. what profiles provide strong attachment, what profile of bleeds or valve shape provide rapid switching, what is the range of angles for the segments over which the unit operates satisfactorily). 
</p><p>
The work was a success in that:- 
</p><p rend="bulleted">
An extensive literature was carried out and some examples of the use of fluerics were identified 
</p><p rend="bulleted">
Simple rigs were designed with variable geometric profile features. 
</p><p rend="bulleted">
Rapid prototyping proved a viable method of manufacture for flueric devices. 
</p><p rend="bulleted">
The rigs demonstrated jet attachment and jet switching for gaseous and liquid fluids. 
</p><p rend="bulleted">
The design of the rigs permits other profiles to be tested. 
</p><p>
The extent of the experimental work completed is not as great as originally expected. 
The author found obtaining information on past experimentation very difficult, with the result that a considerable time was spent searching for data than planned. 
This reduced the time spent on testing. 
</p><p>
The rigs had to be a limited overall size to use the preferred manufacturing technique (rapid prototyping). 
Thus the scale of model used for the testing was predetermined. 
There was no scope in the available time to consider alternative, larger rigs. 
</p><p>
Flow rates and pressures of the fluid flows were not measured. 
Whilst efforts were made to minimise variations in flow and pressure fluctuations these could not be eliminated completely during the project test phase. 
</p></div1><div1 type="front-back-matter" n="3"><head rend="bold">Table of Contents</head><p/></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Chapter 1 Introduction</head><p n="p13.262"><s n="s1.1;p13.262">The term Fluidics can be defined as:- </s></p><p n="p14.262"><s n="s1.1;p14.262">"The technology of using the flows and pressures of fluids in sensing, control, and information-processing systems with no moving parts." </s></p><p n="p15.262"><s n="s1.3;p15.262">Within this field, all methods of flow control are covered, including conventional mechanical valves. </s><s n="s2.3;p15.262">For the purpose of this report, the broad term of fluidics must be narrowed to include only those applications with no moving parts. </s><s n="s3.3;p15.262">Such components, while satisfying the term fluidics, are part of a subcategory, fluerics. </s></p><p n="p16.262"><s n="s1.2;p16.262">The subject of fluerics, where flow-rates, pressures, or volumetric flows allow operators to control discharge flow paths, of any fluid, were investigated in the 1960s.<ref target="BAWE_0249d-ftnote.001"/> This field had been largely overlooked with the rapid rise and advancement in electronics and computers. </s><s n="s2.2;p16.262">There does not appear to have been significant further work in the is area in the intervening decades, though further work was carried out in related fields including aerodynamics and nanotechnology relating to flow control in recent decades.<ref target="BAWE_0249d-ftnote.002"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0249d-ftnote.001"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Bradshaw, B.A., Experimental Fluid Mechanics, 2nd Edition, Pergamon Press, 1964, page 198 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0249d-ftnote.002"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">'Microscale behaviour of fluids', Microfluidics, Wikipedia &lt;<seg type="URL" n="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Microfluidics"/>> 20/03/06, Para. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">3 </s></p></note><p n="p17.262"><s n="s1.1;p17.262">However none of the referenced material seemed to have fully investigated how critical changes in the device dimensions or geometry may be in achieving consistent control, focussing instead upon rigid assemblies honed to provide ever more precise timing systems, or increasingly small laboratory test apparatus. </s></p><p n="p18.262"><s n="s1.1;p18.262">With changes in manufacturing processes, such as rapid prototyping, and new materials (suitable for use in clinical applications) and advances in medical practice, development of a workable fluidic control device could be a major breakthrough. </s></p><p n="p19.262"><s n="s1.1;p19.262">This paper summarises the approach and the results of the research and development carried out:- </s></p><list type="bulleted"><item>Research of local resources, including library and Internet sources</item><item>Early development of fluerics and flueric devices</item><item>Review and selection of appropriate manufacturing processes</item><item>Design criteria/ specification/ constraints</item><item>Physical modelling</item><item>Generation of test data from use of the physical models</item><item>Use of computer modelling to validate the test results.</item></list><p n="p20.262"><s n="s1.2;p20.262">The development phase concentrated on design, construction and testing of simple devices to demonstrate flow attachment and switching, for different fluids. </s><s n="s2.2;p20.262">The rigs were to be adaptable (i.e. geometries could rapidly be changed and tested) and be easy and cheap to manufacture. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Chapter 2 Literature Review</head><div2><head rend="bold italic">Research Methodology</head><p n="p21.262"><s n="s1.5;p21.262">To initiate the necessary research for this investigation, efforts were first concentrated upon the University of <name type="university"/> Central Campus Library. </s><s n="s2.5;p21.262">Extensive research uncovered many references for fluidic devices in general but these were of limited use in terms of flueric motion. </s><s n="s3.5;p21.262">Some information and literature was obtained through private communication which proved to be more helpful. </s><s n="s4.5;p21.262">Since some early work on fluerics was carried out in the 1960s an internet search for old text books was undertaken. </s><s n="s5.5;p21.262">One book, of limited availability, was purchased late on in the project and provided further useful input. <ref target="BAWE_0249d-ftnote.003"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0249d-ftnote.003"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Conway, A., A Guide to Fluidics, 1st edition, Macdonald &amp; Co., 1971. </s></p></note><p n="p22.262"><s n="s1.2;p22.262">Broadening the search to include Internet sources, and electronic resources for journals and articles relating to the subject, identified modern applications of fluerics including Ford's windscreen washer. </s><s n="s2.2;p22.262">Further general reading continued around the following subjects: </s></p><list type="bulleted"><item>Historical developments</item><item>Existing fluidic and flueric devices</item><item>Flow control.</item><item>Aerodynamics.</item><item>Boundary layer theory.</item><item>The Coanda effect and </item><item>Venturi effects.</item></list><p n="p23.262"><s n="s1.1;p23.262">As literature proved hard to come by, development and testing ran in parallel with continued research for the latter half of this investigation. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold italic">History</head><p n="p24.262"><s n="s1.2;p24.262">The subject of fluidics was borne out of the invention of dynamic fluid elements. </s><s n="s2.2;p24.262">Prior to this there were only static devices, where forces within the devices are created by the static pressure of the fluid, and power is only expended intermittently whilst the fluid is in motion. </s></p><p n="p25.262"><s n="s1.3;p25.262">However, within Dynamic devices, the new class of fluid element, the kinetic energy of the fluid as it flows through the element is the essential component. </s><s n="s2.3;p25.262">Power is therefore expended continuously. </s><s n="s3.3;p25.262">These elements do not depend upon moving parts as the static devices do, and a subsequent advantage is the expectation of greater reliability and longer life-span.<ref target="BAWE_0249d-ftnote.004"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0249d-ftnote.004"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Conway, A., A Guide to Fluidics, 1st edition, Macdonald &amp; Co., 1971 </s></p></note><p n="p26.262"><s n="s1.4;p26.262">The invention of these dynamic fluidic elements is generally attributed to work carried out in 1960 at the Harry Diamond Laboratories in Washington. </s><s n="s2.4;p26.262">For the next decade after that, there were three Harry Diamond Conferences, four Cranfield Conferences, as well as other meetings where developments were reported and discussed.<ref target="BAWE_0249d-ftnote.005"/> A survey taken in 1969 estimated total expenditure within the UK researching fluidics up to the end of 1967 to be £2.5m. </s><s n="s3.4;p26.262">Further predictions were made, that this would rise to £3m per annum in 1972, and from £5m to £15m by 1975, such was the expected interest in fluidics. </s><s n="s4.4;p26.262">A tripling of the European market was expected by 1975.2 </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0249d-ftnote.005"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">McCloy, D., An Introduction to Fluidics </s></p></note><p n="p27.262"><s n="s1.3;p27.262">The introduction of elements with no moving parts even served to renew interest in those with moving parts, with a flurry of developments in this area as well. </s><s n="s2.3;p27.262">Particular attention was paid to devices using only diaphragms and ball-operated elements. </s><s n="s3.3;p27.262">Strictly, these would be classed as static devices, but are generally included within fluidics, whilst a new term, fluerics, covers exclusively dynamic elements.3 </s></p><p n="p28.262"><s n="s1.5;p28.262">Fluid diodes are an early example of flueric devices. </s><s n="s2.5;p28.262">They can be considered fluid elements in themselves and predate the Harry Diamond Laboratory work by around 40 years, with the earliest reference published being 1920. </s><s n="s3.5;p28.262">Work on Vortex diodes, probably the most common of these fluid diodes, was not published until 1935 however. </s><s n="s4.5;p28.262">Fluid diodes offer greater resistance to flow in one direction, than the other. </s><s n="s5.5;p28.262">This is usually orchestrated by the onset of turbulence or eddies that prevent pressure collection when flow is in that particular direction. </s></p><p n="p29.262"><s n="s1.2;p29.262">Later fluid amplifiers were investigated, and by arranging several of these in series allowed for very high fluid amplification. </s><s n="s2.2;p29.262">Other methods of amplification became available at this time with the advance of electronics, and subsequently fluid amplifiers fell out of favour for some time.<hi rend="sup">2</hi> </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold italic">So what are these Diodes? </head><p n="p30.262"><s n="s1.3;p30.262">As previously mentioned, these elements are designed to offer greater resistance to flow in one direction as opposed to another. </s><s n="s2.3;p30.262">The performance of these are then measured as a ratio, either of the relative flows, or relative pressure drops passing through each way. </s><s n="s3.3;p30.262">Typically a pressure ratio for a vortex diode would fall between 39:1<ref target="BAWE_0249d-ftnote.006"/> and 50:1<ref target="BAWE_0249d-ftnote.007"/>, calculated using:- </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0249d-ftnote.006"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Grant, J., and Wright, J., 'Potential applications of fluidics in nuclear plant', Paper K2, <hi rend="italic">Proc.</hi> </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1"><hi rend="italic">2nd Cranfield Fluidics conference,</hi> British Hydromechanics Research Association, 1967, pp. K2-9 to K2-19 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0249d-ftnote.007"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Baker, P. J., 'A comparison of fluid diodes', Paper D6, <hi rend="italic">Proc.</hi> </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1"><hi rend="italic">2nd Cranfield Fluidics Conference,</hi> British Hydromechanics Research Association, 1967, pp. D6-88 to D6-115 </s></p></note><p rend="ordered" n="p31.262"><s rend="italic" n="s1.1;p31.262">(Pressure of flow with highest resistance)/(Pressure of flow with lowest resistance):1 </s></p><div3><head rend="bold">Tesla Diode</head><p n="p32.262"><s n="s1.2;p32.262">The Tesla diode (Figure 2.1: Tesla-Diode) is believed to be the first pure fluid device to offer much greater resistance to flow in one direction as opposed to the other, and invented in 1916. </s><s n="s2.2;p32.262">The illustration clearly shows how the difference in resistance is created. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0249d-pic.001"><head>Figure 2.1 Tesla Diode</head></figure></div3><div3><head rend="bold">Nozzle Diode</head><p n="p33.262"><s n="s1.1;p33.262">This is another simple diode (Figure 2.2: Nozzle-Diode) which encourages vortices when flow passes from right to left, with the inevitable increase in resistance of flow in this direction. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0249d-pic.002"><head>Figure 2.3: Nozzle-Diode<ref target="BAWE_0249d-ftnote.008"/><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0249d-ftnote.008"><p n="pn1.1"> McCloy, D., An introduction to Fluidics</p></note></head></figure></div3><div3><head rend="bold">Vortex Diode</head><p n="p34.262"><s n="s1.3;p34.262">The vortex diode (Figure 2.3: Vortex-Diode) offers high resistance when flow enters the diode through the inlet on the left hand side, tangentially to the cylindrical chamber. </s><s n="s2.3;p34.262">This instantly creates a swirling vortex, which in turn forces the water outward and against the diode walls. </s><s n="s3.3;p34.262">The centrifugal effect of the rotating fluid is such that pressure is very great at the diode walls (due to the centripetal forces applied here) but a definite pressure drop is caused at the outlet, in the centre of the cylindrical cavity. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0249d-pic.003"><head>Figure 2.3: Vortex-Diode <hi rend="sup">8</hi></head></figure><p n="p35.262"><s n="s1.2;p35.262">When flow is reversed, the fluid simply enters the diode through the central inlet, filling the cavity, and exiting through the tangential outlet. </s><s n="s2.2;p35.262">Little pressure is lost as minimal rotation is present in this flow situation. </s></p><p n="p36.262"><s n="s1.4;p36.262">As noted, the first report published on this diode quoted a pressure ratio of up to about 40:1. </s><s n="s2.4;p36.262">Since then, more recent works have quoted figures of 39:1 and 50:1. </s><s n="s3.4;p36.262">It is worth mentioning that larger ratios can easily be achieved with disproportionately large vortex chambers. </s><s n="s4.4;p36.262">The downside of this however is a significant lag whilst the vortex is generated for reversed flow. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0249d-pic.004"><head>Figure 2.4: Reversed flow in a Vortex</head></figure><p n="p37.262"><s n="s1.3;p37.262">When the central inlet is used, cavitation can sometimes occur at the tangential outlet, adversely affecting performance. </s><s n="s2.3;p37.262">Resistance is increased here and the pressure ratio reduced. </s><s n="s3.3;p37.262">A further consideration with this diode is that inlet and outlet are set at 90 degrees to one another, when a co-linear arrangement is usually preferable. </s></p></div3><div3><head rend="bold">Turbulence Diode</head><p n="p38.262"><s n="s1.5;p38.262">A turbulence diode (Figure 2.5) is a simple diode, consisting of two co-linear pipes, separated by an open cavity. </s><s n="s2.5;p38.262">One pipe has a fluted end, the other is of constant profile along it's length. </s><s n="s3.5;p38.262">If flow travels from left to right, the jet remains laminar, and a significant proportion of the pressure is captured by the fluted mouth of the right-hand tube. </s><s n="s4.5;p38.262">If the flow passes from the right hand side however, the jet becomes turbulent upon exiting the tube, and very little pressure is captured by the second tube. </s><s n="s5.5;p38.262">The latter scenario is therefore the direction of higher resistance. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0249d-pic.005"><head>Figure 2.5: Turbulence - Diode <hi rend="sup">8</hi></head></figure></div3><div3><head rend="bold">Scroll Diode</head><p n="p39.262"><s n="s1.3;p39.262">Also referred to sometimes as a cup diode, this diode (Figure 2.6) does not offer great performance, with quoted pressure ratios of only 8:1 and 6.6:1. </s><s n="s2.3;p39.262">Greatest resistance is present when flow passes from left to right in the diagram below. </s><s n="s3.3;p39.262">An annular vortex is formed as illustrated, and pressure losses result when flow is in this direction. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0249d-pic.006"><head>Figure 2.6: Scroll-Diode <hi rend="sup">8</hi></head></figure></div3><div3><head rend="bold">Cascade Diode</head><p n="p40.262"><s n="s1.5;p40.262">Also known as the fluid flow rectifier, this is perhaps the most complex of common diodes (Figure 2.7). </s><s n="s2.5;p40.262">There are many stationary blades attached to a rod running the length of a tube. </s><s n="s3.5;p40.262">If fluid enters from one side, the blades encourage the flow to spin and rotate about the tube. </s><s n="s4.5;p40.262">As the flow moved progressively toward the outlet, the velocity of the flow becomes almost perpendicular to the axis of the tube. </s><s n="s5.5;p40.262">A large vortex is created and with similar principals to the vortex diode, large pressure losses are induced. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0249d-pic.007"><head>Figure 2.7: Cascade-Diode <hi rend="sup">7</hi></head></figure><p n="p41.262"><s n="s1.6;p41.262">Flow in the opposite direction meets the blades as bluff obstacles. </s><s n="s2.6;p41.262">There is some resistance to flow but no rotation is caused by the blades. </s><s n="s3.6;p41.262">The flow continues almost along the axis of the tube with only minimal rotation along its entire length. </s><s n="s4.6;p41.262">High pressure ratios can be achieved using this device, some recorded as high as 181:1<ref target="BAWE_0249d-ftnote.009"/>, but it's believed that higher still could be achieved. </s><s n="s5.6;p41.262">Cavitation does not occur in this vortex device, and it's performance is greater than that of any fluidic diode. </s><s n="s6.6;p41.262">The complexity of it however limit it's use to specialist areas where cost is of lesser concern. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0249d-ftnote.009"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.3;pn1.1">Jacobs, B. E. </s><s n="s2.3;pn1.1">A., and Baker, P. J., 'The Cascade Diode', Paper K5, <hi rend="italic">Proc.</hi> </s><s n="s3.3;pn1.1"><hi rend="italic">3rd Cranfield Fluidics Conference,</hi> British Hydromechanics Research Association, 1968, pp. K5-63 to K5-82 </s></p></note></div3></div2><div2><head rend="bold italic">How this can apply to Amplification</head><p n="p42.262"><s n="s1.2;p42.262">By the late 1960s, experimentalists had noted that (for example) in a two-dimensional diffuser, with an included angle of approximately 8 degrees, flow switched from one wall to another. </s><s n="s2.2;p42.262">This was discovered whilst the investigators used a hot wire anemometer to visualise the flow through a rig designed to show patterns caused by turning shear flow around a mitred, sharp-cornered pipe bend. </s></p><p n="p43.262"><s n="s1.1;p43.262">The switching of flow to and from alternating paths is fundamental to many types of fluid amplifier. </s></p><div3><head rend="bold">Proportional Amplifier</head><p n="p44.262"><s n="s1.5;p44.262">As implied in its title, this amplifier (Figure 2.8) can give varied outputs depending upon the inputs given. </s><s n="s2.5;p44.262">Accordingly this gives an analogue signal, and is often referred to as either an Analogue, or Beam Deflection Amplifier. </s><s n="s3.5;p44.262">The main jet is deflected by use of a pair of co-linear control jets. </s><s n="s4.5;p44.262">The resultant exchange of momentum between the jets is the reason for the deflection of the main jet. </s><s n="s5.5;p44.262">This can be varied then to direct full signal to one or other of the outputs, or simply to divide the output unevenly between two outputs. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0249d-pic.008"><head>Figure 2.8: Proportional-amplifier <hi rend="sup">8</hi></head></figure><p n="p45.262"><s n="s1.1;p45.262">The deflection of the jet can be simply calculated by working out the resultant momentum after impact of the two jets </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0249d-pic.009"><head>Figure 2.9: Resultant momentum after jet interaction <hi rend="sup">8</hi></head></figure><p n="p46.262"><s n="s1.2;p46.262">Pressure changes on either side of the main jet can also be harnessed to affect the path of the flow. </s><s n="s2.2;p46.262">This leads on to something called jet reattachment. </s></p></div3><div3><head rend="bold">Jet Reattachment</head><p n="p47.262"><s n="s1.12;p47.262">The early use of switching flows from one channel to another was, as explained above, for fluid amplification. </s><s n="s2.12;p47.262">At this time however, it was necessary for the control signal to be present at all times to direct the main jet. </s><s n="s3.12;p47.262">It wasn't too long before it was discovered that a jet could be made to stay attached once the control had been removed.<ref target="BAWE_0249d-ftnote.010"/> The phenomenon of jet reattachment occurs when a pressure difference is created, and directs the jet toward one side or another, in turn increasing the pressure gradient. </s><s n="s4.12;p47.262">For this example, take the scenario of a jet entering a symmetrical, diverging chamber, with a splitter and two outlets downstream. </s><s n="s5.12;p47.262">Initially if the jet is laminar and with small flow rate, then the jet will follow the central streamline, the flow evenly divided by the splitter, and the flow remaining symmetrical. </s><s n="s6.12;p47.262">As the flow rate is gradually increased, there will be a point where the jet attaches itself to one side in preference to the other. </s><s n="s7.12;p47.262">This occurs when the upper minimum Reynolds number, or Re <hi rend="sub">u</hi>, is reached. </s><s n="s8.12;p47.262">Reducing the flow rate gradually from this point will not immediately separate the flow from the wall. </s><s n="s9.12;p47.262">It will remain attached for a certain range, until the lower minimum Reynolds number, or Re <hi rend="sub">l</hi>, is reached. </s><s n="s10.12;p47.262">Flow then resumes it's course along the centre of the flow chamber. </s><s n="s11.12;p47.262">The normal operating range of an amplifier is set higher than Re <hi rend="sub">u</hi> and the jet remains attached to one wall until an applied control signal, or sufficient pressure change is created as to exceed the attraction toward that wall. </s><s n="s12.12;p47.262">The flow would then rapidly switch toward the opposite wall as the flow is no longer stable and cannot support flow along the centre line any longer. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0249d-ftnote.010"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Streeter, V.L., Fluid Mechanics, Fourth Edition, McGraw-Hill Book Company, 1966, page 447 </s></p></note><figure id="BAWE_0249d-pic.010"><head>Figure 2.10: The Coanda Effect <hi rend="sup">8</hi></head></figure><p n="p48.262"><s n="s1.9;p48.262">As a jet enters a cavity, the surrounding fluid, be it similar to that of the jet or perhaps gas, is entrained as the jet flows through it. </s><s n="s2.9;p48.262">The velocity profile of the jet at instances after leaving the inlet is discussed in section 3.2. </s><s n="s3.9;p48.262">The pressure to either side of the jet is lowered as fluid here is removed (i.e. entrained into the jet). </s><s n="s4.9;p48.262">This produces an unstable situation that cannot be sustained. </s><s n="s5.9;p48.262">If disturbed, e.g. to the right hand side in the illustration, the pressure falls more on that side as the jet passes through a smaller area. </s><s n="s6.9;p48.262">A resultant force is created due to the pressure differences either side of the jet, and pushes the jet further and further toward the right-hand wall, until eventually it attaches there. </s><s n="s7.9;p48.262">A separation bubble is trapped between the jet and the wall in which there is low pressure. </s><s n="s8.9;p48.262">The pressure difference is therefore maintained, unless external factors such as control signals or blockages balance it, and the jet will stay attached to that wall. </s><s n="s9.9;p48.262">This system is said to have a memory. </s></p></div3><div3><head rend="bold">Bistable Amplifier</head><p n="p49.262"><s n="s1.2;p49.262">If once flow is attached to one wall, the separation bubble is expanded sufficiently along the length of the wall, the flow can either detach from that wall, or reattach to the opposite wall. </s><s n="s2.2;p49.262">Methods for doing this are to:- </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p50.262"><s n="s1.1;p50.262">Increase the pressure within the bubble by the use of control jets, whereby the bubble will lengthen and ultimately switch to the opposite wall </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p51.262"><s n="s1.1;p51.262">Increase flow rate, the greater momentum of the jet will lengthen the separation bubble, and further increasing this will eventually break the bubble, as the reattachment point is pushed further and further downstream. </s></p><p n="p52.262"><s n="s1.3;p52.262">If at any point before the flow is detached from the wall, the path of the jet is such that it merely touches the opposite wall, then the jet immediately switches to that wall, and the state of the separation bubble is immaterial. </s><s n="s2.3;p52.262">An engineering example of this is the bistable amplifier which continually cyclically alternates the signal from one channel to the other. </s><s n="s3.3;p52.262">Here, the control flow is feedback from the circulation of fluid escaping through the bleed (Figure 2.11: Recirculation of bleed flow for control). </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0249d-pic.011"><head>Figure 2.11: Recirculation of bleed flow for control</head></figure><p n="p53.262"><s n="s1.2;p53.262">The switching time is typically about 10, where <ref target="BAWE_0249d-ftnote.011"/> is the time taken for a particle travelling at initial supply velocity to travel the length of the reattachment wall. </s><s n="s2.2;p53.262">This can vary though, typically increasing by a factor of four if the pressures involved are only barely sufficient to cause the supply to switch. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0249d-ftnote.011"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Conway, A., A Guide to Fluidics, 1st edition, Macdonald &amp; Co., 1971, p. 16 </s></p></note><div4><head rend="bold">Design</head><p n="p54.262"><s n="s1.4;p54.262">The design of such elements is complex to achieve the desired performance. </s><s n="s2.4;p54.262">Wall length must be chosen in relation to the wall angle and offset. </s><s n="s3.4;p54.262">A short bubble helps produce greater pressure recovery, which in turn require a small wall angle and setback. </s><s n="s4.4;p54.262">Manufacture places limits on how small an angle and setback is possible whilst maintaining symmetrical and repeatable performance. </s></p></div4><div4><head rend="bold">Splitters</head><p n="p55.262"><s n="s1.4;p55.262">A simple sharp-edged splitter merely divides flow, and some flow will stray into the opposite outlet as well as the active one. </s><s n="s2.4;p55.262">Flat ended or profiles splitters are designed to deflect excess flow back into the interaction region. </s><s n="s3.4;p55.262">A reverse vortex can be formed on the outside of the jet, strongly stabilising the jet attachment. </s><s n="s4.4;p55.262">Shaping the vents can help achieve this, and the diagram illustrates a design which gives good pressure recovery as well as being stable under blocked load conditions (as shown in Figure 12 (b): Shaped splitter). </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0249d-pic.012"><head>Figure 2.12: Example of a shaper splitter <hi rend="sup">11</hi></head></figure></div4><div4><head rend="bold">Observations</head><p n="p56.262"><s n="s1.1;p56.262">Warren<ref target="BAWE_0249d-ftnote.012"/> concluded the following from his observations of bistable amplifiers with design such as Figure 2.13: Technical diagram of a bistable amplifier. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0249d-ftnote.012"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Warren, R. W., "Some parameters affecting the design of bistable "amplifiers Fluid jet devices Symposium. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">A.S.M.E. November 1962 </s></p></note><p rend="ordered" n="p57.262"><s n="s1.2;p57.262">1. </s><s n="s2.2;p57.262">Increasing the cross section of the receiver aperture </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p58.262"><s n="s1.1;p58.262">(a) Increased the flow entrained through the non-active output </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p59.262"><s n="s1.1;p59.262">(b) Reduced the pressure recovery (the pressure recovered in the receiver) </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p60.262"><s n="s1.2;p60.262">2. </s><s n="s2.2;p60.262">Increasing the wall angle </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p61.262"><s n="s1.1;p61.262">(a) Decreased the control flow needed to switch the jet </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p62.262"><s n="s1.1;p62.262">(b) Moved the stream reattachment point further downstream </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p63.262"><s n="s1.2;p63.262">3. </s><s n="s2.2;p63.262">Increasing the area of the control nozzle </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p64.262"><s n="s1.1;p64.262">(a) Increased the tendency of the jet to oscillate between the two walls </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p65.262"><s n="s1.1;p65.262">(b) Increased the effect of active control jets </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p66.262"><s n="s1.2;p66.262">4. </s><s n="s2.2;p66.262">Increasing the width of the interaction region </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p67.262"><s n="s1.1;p67.262">(a) increased the control flow needed to switch the jet, up to a setback of 2w and thereafter decreased the control flow </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p68.262"><s n="s1.1;p68.262">(b) Increased the power jet pressure at which the jet attaches to both walls </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p69.262"><s n="s1.2;p69.262">5. </s><s n="s2.2;p69.262">Increasing the aspect ratio (orifice depth/orifice width) </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p70.262"><s n="s1.1;p70.262">(a) Increased the flow through the element </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p71.262"><s n="s1.1;p71.262">(b) Reduced the effect of the top and bottom boundaries in the orifice. </s></p><p n="p72.262"><s n="s1.3;p72.262">The latter point was examined further by Glaettli<ref target="BAWE_0249d-ftnote.013"/> who noted that the jet would not spontaneously reattach when the nozzle flow was laminar. </s><s n="s2.3;p72.262">Parker<ref target="BAWE_0249d-ftnote.014"/> went on further to state that a Reynolds number of 4000 was the lowest practical limit of the operation of bistable amplifiers. </s><s n="s3.3;p72.262">This can be written in relation the amplifiers geometry as:- </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0249d-ftnote.013"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.3;pn1.1">Gaettli, H. H., Muller, H. R. and Zinag, R. H., "Remarks on the limitations of pure fluid "elements Proc. </s><s n="s2.3;pn1.1">Fluid Amplification Symposium. </s><s n="s3.3;pn1.1">Vol. 1, p. 217, Washington 1964. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0249d-ftnote.014"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Parker, G. A., "Some aspects of fluidic sequencing and digital control systems for machine "tools 7th International M.T.D.R. Conference, Birmingham, September 1966. </s></p></note><p n="p73.262"><s n="s1.1;p73.262"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0249d-form.001"/> </s></p><list type="simple"><head>where:-</head><item>Q= measured flow rate</item><item>h= depth of the power nozzle</item><item>D <hi rend="sub">h</hi>= hydraulic diameter</item><item>n= ratio h/w</item><item>µ= kinematic viscosity</item></list><figure id="BAWE_0249d-pic.013"><head>Figure 2.13: Technical diagram of a bistable amplifier <hi rend="sup">8</hi></head></figure></div4></div3><div3><head rend="bold">Turbulence Amplifier</head><p n="p74.262"><s n="s1.6;p74.262">This is a digital device which performs as the nor function when used as a logic element. </s><s n="s2.6;p74.262">Based upon the transition between laminar and turbulent flow, pressure losses are achieved by initiating the change a little earlier. </s><s n="s3.6;p74.262">Co-linear inlet and outlet are arranged so that they open into a larger vented chamber. </s><s n="s4.6;p74.262">A laminar jet enters this chamber, and if undisturbed, remains laminar as it reaches and flows into the outlet. </s><s n="s5.6;p74.262">Minimal interaction occurs with the walls of this element, so the only way to bring on transition to turbulent flow is by the use of control jets. </s><s n="s6.6;p74.262">Control jets directed at 90 degrees to the main jet are sufficient to do this and the resultant turbulence causes large pressure losses due to the viscous shear forces. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0249d-pic.014"><head>Figure 2.14: Turbulence amplifier<ref target="BAWE_0249d-ftnote.015"/><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0249d-ftnote.015"><p n="pn1.1"> Conway, A., A Guide to Fluidics, 1st edition, Macdonald &amp; Co., 1971, p.11</p></note></head></figure><p n="p75.262"><s n="s1.2;p75.262">Laminar flow does not resume immediately after the control signal has stopped. </s><s n="s2.2;p75.262">The delay is approximately four times longer than it takes for a particle to travel the length of the jet. </s></p></div3><div3><head rend="bold">Vortex Amplifier</head><p n="p76.262"><s n="s1.9;p76.262">The vortex amplifier is a flow-modulating element (Figure 2.15: Vortex-amplifier). </s><s n="s2.9;p76.262">It exploits similar principals to those of the vortex diode. </s><s n="s3.9;p76.262">Flow is contained within a cylindrical chamber, supplied radially by any number of inlets, arranged perpendicularly to the chamber walls. </s><s n="s4.9;p76.262">Instead of inlet tubes, some of these amplifiers have permeable perimeter walls allowing flow to enter the chamber from every point. </s><s n="s5.9;p76.262">Without any control signal (Figure 2.15 (a) Vortex-amplifier), flow simply continues toward the centre of the chamber, where there is an outlet. </s><s n="s6.9;p76.262">Control signals can be delivered though, supplied tangentially from any number of control inlets. </s><s n="s7.9;p76.262">Each control would then encourage the main supply to rotate in the same direction, clock-wise for instance (Figure 2.15 (b): Vortex-amplifier). </s><s n="s8.9;p76.262">The rotational flow causes a pressure gradient within the circulating fluid, with great pressures against the perimeter walls due to centripetal forces acting on the fluid through the walls. </s><s n="s9.9;p76.262">Pressure around the central outlet is dropped significantly as fluid is centrifuged away from it, and so flow through the outlet is also reduced. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0249d-pic.015"><head>Figure 2.15: Vortex amplifier<ref target="BAWE_0249d-ftnote.016"/><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0249d-ftnote.016"><p n="pn1.1"> Conway, A., A Guide to Fluidics, 1st edition, Macdonald &amp; Co., 1971, p. 18</p></note></head></figure><figure id="BAWE_0249d-fig.001"><head>Figure 2.16: Typical performance of a vortex amplifier <hi rend="sup">16</hi></head></figure><p n="p77.262"><s n="s1.1;p77.262">The amplifier offers a negative gain, whereby a control increase reduces the output. </s></p></div3><div3><head rend="bold">Impact Modulator</head><p n="p78.262"><s n="s1.1;p78.262">There are two variations upon this design: </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p79.262"><s n="s1.1;p79.262">Direct Impact Modulator (Figure 2.17) </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0249d-pic.016"><head>Figure 2.17: Direct Impact Modulator<ref target="BAWE_0249d-ftnote.017"/><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0249d-ftnote.017"><p n="pn1.1"> Conway, A., A Guide to Fluidics, 1st edition, Macdonald &amp; Co., 1971, p. 29,30</p></note></head></figure><p n="p80.262"><s n="s1.7;p80.262">The two supply jets, the emitter and collector, impact at a point along the dotted line. </s><s n="s2.7;p80.262">The momentum of the jets decides this, and if the momentum of either jet were changed somehow, the balance point would change, and move downstream from the increased supply. </s><s n="s3.7;p80.262">At impact, a radial flow cone is produced, which may be collected at the output. </s><s n="s4.7;p80.262">The emitter and collector pressures are adjusted so that without the presence of any control signal, no flow is captured at the outlet, but is very close to the recapture edge of the annular receiver, escaping into the vented chamber. </s><s n="s5.7;p80.262">When a control is supplied, co-axially with the emitter, the momentum of this jet increases pushing the flow cone further downstream and across the point whereby flow is collected at the recapture edge. </s><s n="s6.7;p80.262">Increases thereafter of the control signal result in proportional increases of the output. </s><s n="s7.7;p80.262">The pressure gains achieved from this device are higher than any other, and have been reported as high as 200. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p81.262"><s n="s1.1;p81.262">Transverse Impact Modulator (t.i.m.) (Figure 2.18) </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0249d-pic.017"><head>Figure 2.18: Transverse Impact TIM Modulator <hi rend="sup">17</hi></head></figure><p n="p82.262"><s n="s1.6;p82.262">Similar in principal to the direct impact modulator, the control for this amplifier fires perpendicular to the supply jet. </s><s n="s2.6;p82.262">The pressures are initially calibrated so that some of the flow is captured at the output when there is no control signal. </s><s n="s3.6;p82.262">This is known as the t.i.m. reference output level. </s><s n="s4.6;p82.262">When a control signal is present, the main supply is deflected away from the shared axis of the emitter and collector. </s><s n="s5.6;p82.262">The impact plane moves upstream toward the controlled jet, and less, or no flow is collected by the recapture edge. </s><s n="s6.6;p82.262">Negative pressure gains of -100 have been reported under no-load for this type of amplifier. </s></p></div3><div3><head rend="bold">Edgestone Amplifier</head><p n="p83.262"><s n="s1.4;p83.262">A jet impinging on an edge oscillates to each side (Figure 2.19: Edgestone amplifier). </s><s n="s2.4;p83.262">The jet sheds a vortex to one side, and switches in turn to the other. </s><s n="s3.4;p83.262">This process then repeats, shedding a vortex to the other side and restoring the jet back to it's original path. </s><s n="s4.4;p83.262">Only a very weak signal is required to switch this inherently unstable jet. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0249d-pic.018"><head>Figure 2.19: Edgestone amplifier <hi rend="sup">8</hi></head></figure></div3><div3><head rend="bold">Induction Amplifier</head><p n="p84.262"><s n="s1.3;p84.262">The control flow follows the profile of the walls (Figure 2.20: Induction amplifier). </s><s n="s2.3;p84.262">These are shaped as aerofoils and so flow does not tend to separate from them. </s><s n="s3.3;p84.262">The main jet is drawn along by the control signal due to the viscous forces, and unusually, it switches to the side that the control signal is present. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0249d-pic.019"><head>Figure 2.20: Induction amplifier <hi rend="sup">8</hi></head></figure></div3></div2><div2><head rend="bold italic">What can come from this? </head><p n="p85.262"><s n="s1.2;p85.262">Fluidics has been referred to as an 'Art', the implication being that only experimentation can reveal quite how a device might operate. </s><s n="s2.2;p85.262">They have however been adapted for use in many disciplines. </s></p><div3><head rend="bold">Medical Applications</head><p n="p86.262"><s n="s1.5;p86.262">Perhaps the most evident use for a bistable amplifier would be to replicate the operation of a human heart. </s><s n="s2.5;p86.262">Investigation began around the late 1950s, early 1960s in America, by Kolff<ref target="BAWE_0249d-ftnote.018"/>, Akutsu<ref target="BAWE_0249d-ftnote.019"/> amongst others<ref target="BAWE_0249d-ftnote.020"/>. </s><s n="s3.5;p86.262">Initial priorities lay with producing a simple pulsating flow, whilst preventing blood coagulation or damage to components within the blood, the blood corpuscles (haemolysis). </s><s n="s4.5;p86.262">Research since then has been specific to better matching the output-pressure waveform of an actual heart. </s><s n="s5.5;p86.262">Four types of assisted circulatory artificial heart-pumps (Figure 2.21: Four types of heart by-pass): </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0249d-ftnote.018"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.9;pn1.1">Kolff, et al.: T. Amer. </s><s n="s2.9;pn1.1">Soc. </s><s n="s3.9;pn1.1">Art. </s><s n="s4.9;pn1.1">Int. </s><s n="s5.9;pn1.1">Org., Vol. 5, p. 298, 1959.Kolff, et al.: T. Amer. </s><s n="s6.9;pn1.1">Soc. </s><s n="s7.9;pn1.1">Art. </s><s n="s8.9;pn1.1">Int. </s><s n="s9.9;pn1.1">Org., Vol. 8, p. 135, 1962. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0249d-ftnote.019"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Akutsu, et al.: Amer. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">Heart J., Vol. 59, p.731, 1960. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0249d-ftnote.020"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.5;pn1.1">Kantrowitz: T. Amer. </s><s n="s2.5;pn1.1">Soc. </s><s n="s3.5;pn1.1">Art. </s><s n="s4.5;pn1.1">Int. </s><s n="s5.5;pn1.1">Org., Vol. 6, p. 292, 1960. </s></p></note><list type="ordered"><item>Right by-pass</item><item>Left by-pass</item><item>Total by-pass and</item><item>Counter pulsation</item></list><p n="p87.262"><s n="s1.2;p87.262">The counter pulsation method places the artificial heart in series with the heart artery, receiving and supplying blood from the natural heart. </s><s n="s2.2;p87.262">This allows the pump to fully synchronise with the heart assisting it and hence reducing cardiac work. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0249d-pic.020"><head>Figure 2.21: Four types of heart by-pass<ref target="BAWE_0249d-ftnote.021"/><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0249d-ftnote.021"><p n="pn1.1"> Tsuchiya, K. <hi rend="italic">et al</hi>., 'Artificial heart controlled by fluid amplification', <hi rend="italic">Proc. I.F.A.C.,</hi> Paper C7, 1968, London.</p></note></head></figure><p n="p88.262"><s n="s1.1;p88.262">At least up till the early 1970s, valves were still commonly in operation within these fluidic devices, but were themselves the primary cause of damage to the blood as mentioned earlier. </s></p><p n="p89.262"><s n="s1.1;p89.262">In 1968, an experiment was performed to assess the performance of the Left Heart By-pass by fitting them to dogs, with limited success (Table 2.1). </s></p><table id="BAWE_0249d-tab.001"><head><hi rend="bold">Table 2.1: Success of Left Heart By-pass fitted in dogs</hi><hi rend="sup">21</hi></head><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p90.262"><s n="s1.2;p90.262">Another common application would be a simple ventilator unit. </s><s n="s2.2;p90.262">This is an illustration of the mechanical equivalent of the pulmonary system (Figure 2.22). </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0249d-pic.021"><head>Figure 2.22: Fluidic representation of a ventilator<ref target="BAWE_0249d-ftnote.022"/><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0249d-ftnote.022"><p n="pn1.1"> Ball, G. J., 'Fluidic control of automatic lung ventilators', M.Phil. thesis, University of London, 1968</p></note></head></figure><p n="p91.262"><s n="s1.5;p91.262">Applying fluidics to this otherwise mechanical application has many benefits, such as reduced cost, but particularly it eases sterilisation of the equipment. </s><s n="s2.5;p91.262">Considerable effort was spent adapting the technology for artificial kidney systems, some of which would be self cleaning. </s><s n="s3.5;p91.262">Indeed the application of fluidic devices to organic systems is diverse. </s><s n="s4.5;p91.262">Interestingly Petrovick<ref target="BAWE_0249d-ftnote.023"/> created a fluidic model of the human oral system. </s><s n="s5.5;p91.262">Experimentation with this model has given better insight into the human oral physiology, and the equivalent relationships are suggested between the two (Table 2.2). </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0249d-ftnote.023"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Petrovick, M. L.: 'On the nature of fluid amplifiers and the oral cavity', Trans. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">I.S.A., Vol. 7, p. 130, 1968. </s></p></note><table id="BAWE_0249d-tab.002"><head rend="bold">Table 2.2: Fluidic equivalents to the human oral system</head><row><cell/></row></table><figure id="BAWE_0249d-pic.022"><head>Figure 2.23: Fluidic model of human oral system <hi rend="sup">23</hi></head></figure><p n="p92.262"><s n="s1.1;p92.262">After the creation of this model, it became apparent that any number of human systems could one day be modelled with fluidics (Figure 2.23). </s></p></div3><div3><head rend="bold">Other applications</head><p n="p93.262"><s n="s1.1;p93.262">Apart from areas of medicine, other applications have included: </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0249d-pic.023"><head>Figure 2.24: Bow thrusters<ref target="BAWE_0249d-ftnote.024"/><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0249d-ftnote.024"><p n="pn1.1"> Conway, A., A Guide to Fluidics, 1st edition, Macdonald &amp; Co., 1971, p. 87</p></note></head></figure><list type="bulleted"><item>bow thrusters for manoeuvring ships in close confine (Figure 2.24).</item><item>Missile thrust control</item><item>Aircraft controls</item><item>Jet engine controls</item><item>Vortex angular rate sensor (Figure 2.25).</item></list><figure id="BAWE_0249d-pic.024"><head>Figure 2.25: Vortex angular rate sensor<ref target="BAWE_0249d-ftnote.025"/><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0249d-ftnote.025"><p n="pn1.1"> Conway, A., A Guide to Fluidics, 1st edition, Macdonald &amp; Co., 1971, p. 115</p></note></head></figure><p n="p94.262"><s n="s1.6;p94.262">Gas passes radially through the porous perimeter wall of the cylindrical chamber. </s><s n="s2.6;p94.262">If the chamber is not rotating, flow continues radially across the chamber and exits down the sink tube. </s><s n="s3.6;p94.262">If the chamber is rotating, then a vortex will be developed within it, and the gas passing down the sink hole will take a helical path. </s><s n="s4.6;p94.262">A tube crosses the sink hole with the purpose of determining pressure differences as described below. </s><s n="s5.6;p94.262">The tube is sealed at the centre, with two holes either side of the divide positioned close, but symmetrically distanced from the central axis of the sink hole. </s><s n="s6.6;p94.262">This tube crosses the sink hole part way down. </s></p><p n="p95.262"><s n="s1.9;p95.262">The position of these holes can be seen in Figure 2.26. </s><s n="s2.9;p95.262">They are angled such that the helical flow path will impact upon one, but be flowing away from the other. </s><s n="s3.9;p95.262">The tangential velocity of the flow near the central axis is high, and these sensing holes measure the different pressures resultant from a rotating flow. </s><s n="s4.9;p95.262">The impacting flow will record the static pressure, plus a fraction of the dynamic pressure (P <hi rend="sub">S</hi>+P). </s><s n="s5.9;p95.262">The other hole will measure the static pressure, minus the same fraction of the dynamic pressure (P <hi rend="sub">S</hi>-P). </s><s n="s6.9;p95.262">The pressure difference (P <hi rend="sub">S</hi>+P)-(P <hi rend="sub">S</hi>-P) = 2P is proportional to the rate of rotation. </s><s n="s7.9;p95.262">This signal is weak but can easily be sent to a high-input-impedance, fluidic, proportional amplifier. </s><s n="s8.9;p95.262">Sensitivity of this device falls as the diameter of the chamber decreases, so smaller applications are less suited. </s><s n="s9.9;p95.262">Typical performance figures for such a sensor, with 150 mm diameter are: </s></p><list type="bulleted"><item>Gain of 40 (N/m <hi rend="sup">2</hi>)/(<hi rend="sup">o</hi>/s)</item><item>Transportation lag of 10 ms</item><item>Output threshold 0.5 <hi rend="sup">o</hi>/s</item></list><figure id="BAWE_0249d-pic.025"><head>Figure 2.26: Detail of the sink hole in a Vortex angular-rate sensor</head></figure><p rend="bulleted" n="p96.262"><s n="s1.1;p96.262">Automotive windscreen washer jets </s></p><p n="p97.262"><s n="s1.5;p97.262">In 1999, the first successful simulations were made of Ford's fluidic windscreen washer nozzle using Computational Fluid Dynamics, or CFD (Figure 2.27). </s><s n="s2.5;p97.262">The software used was supplied by Fluent, an important player even today in the field of CFD. The use of CFD has not been around for very long, and this initial simulation was heralded as a breakthrough, reducing design time by up to 50%. </s><s n="s3.5;p97.262">CFD has come a long way even in the last seven years, but remains a complex and controversial subject. </s><s n="s4.5;p97.262">Few applications can justify it's use due to the cost involved (CFD packages can be very expensive), limiting it mostly to aerodynamics. </s><s n="s5.5;p97.262">For instance Star-CCM, another industry-leading package, is employed by the racing team McLaren. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0249d-pic.026"><head>Figure 2.27: Modelling of Ford's flueric windscreen washer jet<ref target="BAWE_0249d-ftnote.026"/><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0249d-ftnote.026"><p n="pn1.1"> Anju K, First Successful Computer Simulation of Flow in Fluidic Windshield Washer Nozzle Shows Potential to Reduce Design Time 50%, Journal Articles by Fluent Software Users, JA084, 1999 &lt;[<seg type="URL" n="http://www.fluent.com/solutions/articles/ja084.pdf"/>]> [December 2005]</p></note></head></figure><p rend="bulleted" n="p98.262"><s n="s1.1;p98.262">Nuclear reactors </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p99.262"><s n="s1.1;p99.262">Air conditioning </s></p><p n="p100.262"><s n="s1.1;p100.262">Using the Coanda effect (section 3.5) to ensure optimal spread and mixing of the gasses, air conditioning might have seemed an unlikely client, but fluidics is perfect for this application. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p101.262"><s n="s1.1;p101.262">Micro-fluidics </s></p><p n="p102.262"><s n="s1.8;p102.262">Recent research in fluidics has focused enormously on work in the micro and even nano scales. </s><s n="s2.8;p102.262">Lab-on-a-chip is a concept that is becoming more realistic as manufacturing processes allow increasingly smaller flow channels. </s><s n="s3.8;p102.262">The principal behind many of these fluid elements however is largely different to those described up to this point. </s><s n="s4.8;p102.262">Instead of the geometry, or jet properties determining the outputs, the properties of the fluids themselves are the key. </s><s n="s5.8;p102.262">As one fluid passes through another of greater, or lesser viscosity, it's path will be affected. </s><s n="s6.8;p102.262">The output then is determined by the difference in viscosity of the two fluids, of which one will be predetermined. </s><s n="s7.8;p102.262">Multiple outlets can be present in a device of this kind, and it is the type of fluid that is determined to be carrying the signal. </s><s n="s8.8;p102.262">The inlet fluid (or carrying signal) is often marked with a dye for ease of identification and visualisation of the resultant fluid path. </s></p></div3></div2><div2><head><hi rend="bold italic">Advantages and disadvantages of flueric components</hi><ref target="BAWE_0249d-ftnote.027"/><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0249d-ftnote.027"><p n="pn1.1"> McCloy, D., 'An Introduction to Fluidics', page 19</p></note></head><p n="p103.262"><s n="s1.1;p103.262">Flueric components have some special advantages: </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p104.262"><s n="s1.3;p104.262">They have potentially a longer life-span since they have no moving parts. </s><s n="s2.3;p104.262">For example it is reported<ref target="BAWE_0249d-ftnote.028"/> that the fluidic multi-vibrator has shown no deterioration in performance after 3.5*10 <hi rend="sup">9</hi>cycles of operation in standard shop air. </s><s n="s3.3;p104.262">This also results in improved liability and makes the use of fluerics attractive in redundant aircraft control systems where reliability is at a premium. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0249d-ftnote.028"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Shinn, J. N., "No moving parts needed" S.A.E. Journal, August, 1963 </s></p></note><p rend="ordered" n="p105.262"><s n="s1.1;p105.262">They can tolerate extremes of temperature with vortex amplifiers<ref target="BAWE_0249d-ftnote.029"/> operating at 760 degrees Celsius, and in Liquid Nitrogen. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0249d-ftnote.029"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Kompass, E. J., "Perspective on fluid amplifiers" Control Engineering, September 1964 </s></p></note><p rend="ordered" n="p106.262"><s n="s1.2;p106.262">They are insensitive to shock and vibration. </s><s n="s2.2;p106.262">Tests<ref target="BAWE_0249d-ftnote.030"/> run on digital devices indicate satisfactory operation at accelerations up to 50g. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0249d-ftnote.030"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Gray, W. E., and Hans Stern "Fluid amplifiers - capabilities and applications" Control Engineering, September 1964 </s></p></note><p rend="ordered" n="p107.262"><s n="s1.2;p107.262">Their operation is unaffected by radiation and thus can be operated in some extremely harsh environments. </s><s n="s2.2;p107.262">This is very important in space applications where radiation tolerance is highly desirable. </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p108.262"><s n="s1.2;p108.262">They are inexpensive when mass-produced. </s><s n="s2.2;p108.262">Chemical machining, moulding or forming can be used to produce cheap planar devices. </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p109.262"><s n="s1.2;p109.262">They are relatively small and can be joined together to form a compact package. </s><s n="s2.2;p109.262">Power nozzle widths are typically as small as 0.5 to 1.0 mm. </s></p><p n="p110.262"><s n="s1.3;p110.262">Their main disadvantage is that they are slow relative to electronics. </s><s n="s2.3;p110.262">Electronic circuits operate typically in the range 10 <hi rend="sup">-6</hi> to 10 <hi rend="sup">-12</hi> seconds, whereas flueric devices are only 10 <hi rend="sup">-3</hi> to 10 <hi rend="sup">-4</hi> seconds. </s><s n="s3.3;p110.262">This is primarily due to the speed of propagation in a flueric system being governed by the speed of sound in the medium, with electronic devices operating up to the speed of light. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold italic">Development trends since the 1960s</head><p n="p111.262"><s n="s1.4;p111.262">Despite the obvious and enormous potential of fluidics and fluerics, predictions as to the expansion and increase of the market have all been grossly optimistic. </s><s n="s2.4;p111.262">Estimates for the four years following 1971 predicted a potential future market varying in the range of £5m to £300m per annum. </s><s n="s3.4;p111.262">With the competitive and advanced nature of electronics, fluidics has been sidelined somewhat over recent decades. </s><s n="s4.4;p111.262">However there is still much to benefit from the development of fluid technologies as indicated in section 2.6. </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Chapter 3 Theory</head><div2><head rend="bold italic">Flow Regimes</head><p n="p112.262"><s n="s1.1;p112.262">The nature of flow can be categorised in the following ways: </s></p><p n="p113.262"><s n="s1.4;p113.262"><hi rend="bold">Turbulent</hi>: This is the flow regime most commonly encountered within engineering. </s><s n="s2.4;p113.262">The fluid particles move in an erratic manner, following irregular paths and momentum gets transferred from one part of the flow to another. </s><s n="s3.4;p113.262">These fluid particles, or bodies, can range greatly in size. </s><s n="s4.4;p113.262">For instance, the scale varies in size from just a few thousand molecules, right up to the large swirls in rivers, or gusts in the atmosphere, comprising many thousands of cubic metres. </s></p><p n="p114.262"><s n="s1.5;p114.262">For similar flow systems, a turbulent flow will create larger shear stresses through the fluid than would a laminar flow. </s><s n="s2.5;p114.262">The stresses that exist throughout the turbulent fluid flow therefore cause more irreversibility or losses than for laminar flow. </s><s n="s3.5;p114.262">Losses within turbulent flow vary proportionally to the square of velocity, whilst losses in laminar flow, vary proportionally to the first power of velocity. </s><s n="s4.5;p114.262">In flueric applications, losses present themselves most dominantly as pressure losses between inlet and outlets. </s><s n="s5.5;p114.262">Thus designing a flueric device subject to turbulent flow may prove more problematic than if it were possible to maintain laminar flow through the device, and pressure recovery harder to achieve. </s></p><p n="p115.262"><s n="s1.3;p115.262"><hi rend="bold">Laminar</hi>: Still an important flow regime to engineers, the fluid particles move along smooth paths in layers, or laminas. </s><s n="s2.3;p115.262">These layers glide smoothly over one another, and are governed by Newton's law of viscosity, which is a relation of shear stress to rate of angular deformation. </s><s n="s3.3;p115.262">Viscosity of the fluid acts to damp out turbulent tendencies, however, laminar flow is not stable in many situations, it is liable to develop into turbulent flow under conditions of:- </s></p><list type="bulleted"><item>low velocity</item><item>high velocity or </item><item>large flow passages.</item></list><p n="p116.262"><s n="s1.1;p116.262">The equation of motion for turbulent flow, which is similar in form to Newton's law of viscosity, may be written as: </s></p><p n="p117.262"><s n="s1.1;p117.262"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0249d-form.002"/> </s></p><p n="p118.262"><s n="s1.4;p118.262">Here, depends upon the fluid motion and the fluid density. </s><s n="s2.4;p118.262">It () is not a property of the fluid itself, i.e. it changes with situation. </s><s n="s3.4;p118.262">It is referred to as the Eddy viscosity. </s><s n="s4.4;p118.262">Viscosity and turbulence can often both contribute to the shear stress within engineering applications. </s></p><p n="p119.262"><s n="s1.1;p119.262"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0249d-form.003"/> </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold italic"> Mechanics of a jet</head><p n="p120.262"><s n="s1.4;p120.262">At relatively low velocities the mechanics of a jet are governed by the fluid viscosity. </s><s n="s2.4;p120.262">The outer layer of a jet decelerates whilst accelerating the stationary fluid particles in which it has contact, due to the viscous shear affects. </s><s n="s3.4;p120.262">If the velocity profile across the jet decreases smoothly to zero, the flow in the jet is said to be laminar. </s><s n="s4.4;p120.262">Turbulent flow is where the jet motion is random. </s></p><div3><head rend="bold">Transition</head><p n="p121.262"><s n="s1.3;p121.262">Transition refers to the change between laminar and turbulent flow. </s><s n="s2.3;p121.262">The transition is basically governed by the Reynolds number. </s><s n="s3.3;p121.262">In terms of jets, the position at which transition occurs is determined by the size and velocity of the jet and the fluid properties. </s></p></div3><div3><head rend="bold">Flow entrainment</head><p n="p122.262"><s n="s1.1;p122.262">As the jet passes over an adjacent stationary layer some of the fluid particles of the stationary layer become pulled into, or entrained into the jet (Figure 3.1). </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0249d-pic.027"><head>Figure 3.1: Velocity profile of a jet as surrounding fluid is entrained<ref target="BAWE_0249d-ftnote.031"/><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0249d-ftnote.031"><p n="pn1.1"> Conway, A., A Guide to Fluidics, 1st edition, Macdonald &amp; Co., 1971., p.3</p></note></head></figure></div3></div2><div2><head rend="bold italic">Reynolds Number</head><p n="p123.262"><s n="s1.1;p123.262">The Reynolds number is the ratio of inertial forces to viscous forces. </s></p><p n="p124.262"><s n="s1.1;p124.262"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0249d-form.004"/> </s></p><p n="p125.262"><s n="s1.1;p125.262">A critical Reynolds number (Re <hi rend="sub">c</hi>) is the point that defines when flow switches from laminar to turbulent flow in a number of situations: </s></p><list type="bulleted"><item>flow in pipes, </item><item>in the boundary layer, or </item><item>around immersed objects. </item></list><p n="p126.262"><s n="s1.1;p126.262">The value of Re <hi rend="sub">c</hi> however depends upon the situation. </s></p><p n="p127.262"><s n="s1.2;p127.262">It is anticipated that a detailed understanding of the effect of the Reynolds number on flow regimes will be an important factor in the development of and understanding of the operation of fluidic control devices. </s><s n="s2.2;p127.262">The following pages therefore describe the effects of Reynolds number in some detail. </s></p><p n="p128.262"><s n="s1.5;p128.262">Laminar flow has been defined as flow in which fluid moves in layers, one layer gliding smoothly over adjacent layers. </s><s n="s2.5;p128.262">The motion of the fluid particles within Turbulent flow is very different. </s><s n="s3.5;p128.262">Movement is erratic, with abrupt changes of momentum. </s><s n="s4.5;p128.262">Any tendencies within laminar flow, toward instability and turbulent flow, are inhibited by viscous shear forces. </s><s n="s5.5;p128.262">These help to resist relative motion of the fluid layers. </s></p><p n="p129.262"><s n="s1.2;p129.262">The Reynolds number indicates the flow regime, whether laminar or turbulent. </s><s n="s2.2;p129.262">It can also describe the relative importance of laminar flow and turbulence within the flow during the transformation process. </s></p><p n="p130.262"><s n="s1.3;p130.262">Navier-Stokes equations are used to describe the motion of fluid, and take into account the viscous shear forces. </s><s n="s2.3;p130.262">These are complex, nonlinear partial differential equations, and have no general solution to date. </s><s n="s3.3;p130.262">In the last century, Osbourne Reynolds studied these equations as discussed below. </s></p><p n="p131.262"><s n="s1.1;p131.262">Two flow cases are said to be dynamically similar when: </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p132.262"><s n="s1.1;p132.262">they are geometrically similar </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p133.262"><s n="s1.1;p133.262">the corresponding streamlines are geometrically similar, or pressures etc </s></p><p n="p134.262"><s n="s1.2;p134.262">For two geometrically similar flows to be dynamically similar, the general differential equations describing their flow must be identical. </s><s n="s2.2;p134.262">Reynolds found that the dimensionless group </s></p><p n="p135.262"><s n="s1.1;p135.262"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0249d-form.005"/> </s></p><p n="p136.262"><s n="s1.1;p136.262">must be the same for both cases, where:- </s></p><list type="simple"><item>u= characteristic velocity</item><item>l= characteristic length</item><item>ρ= the mass density</item><item>µ= the viscosity</item></list><p n="p137.262"><s n="s1.1;p137.262">This has become known as the Reynolds number, Re </s></p><p n="p138.262"><s n="s1.1;p138.262"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0249d-form.006"/> </s></p><p n="p139.262"><s n="s1.2;p139.262">In practical pipe flow applications, laminar flow changes to turbulent flow in the range of the Reynolds numbers from 2000 to 4000. </s><s n="s2.2;p139.262">Likewise, reducing the velocity of turbulent pipe flow such that R falls below 2000, the flow becomes laminar. </s></p><p n="p140.262"><s n="s1.1;p140.262">Reynolds number may also be viewed as a ratio of shear stress due to turbulence to shear stress due to viscosity. </s></p><p n="p141.262"><s n="s1.1;p141.262">The nature of a given flow of an incompressible fluid, be it turbulent or laminar, is characterised by its Reynolds number. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p142.262"><s n="s1.2;p142.262">For large values of R, at least one of the terms in the numerator is large in comparison with the denominator. </s><s n="s2.2;p142.262">This implies </s></p><list type="bulleted"><item>A large expanse of fluid,</item><item>high velocity,</item><item>great density,</item><item>extremely small viscosity,</item><item>or some combination of these extremes.</item></list><p n="p143.262"><s n="s1.4;p143.262">Terms within the numerator relate to the inertial forces, forces that result from the acceleration or deceleration of the fluid. </s><s n="s2.4;p143.262">The denominator term is the cause of viscous shear forces. </s><s n="s3.4;p143.262">Hence the Reynolds number is an expression describing the inertial forces as a ratio to viscous forces. </s><s n="s4.4;p143.262">A large Reynolds number suggests that the flow be highly turbulent. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p144.262"><s n="s1.1;p144.262">For intermediate values of Reynolds number, neither the viscous nor the inertial effects are dominant, and so changes in viscosity change the velocity distribution and the resistance to flow.<ref target="BAWE_0249d-ftnote.032"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0249d-ftnote.032"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Streeter, V.L., Fluid Mechanics, Fourth Edition, McGraw-Hill Book Company, 1966, page 222 </s></p></note></div2><div2><head rend="bold italic">Boundary Layer</head><p n="p145.262"><s n="s1.2;p145.262">In 1904 Prandtl developed the concept of the boundary layer. </s><s n="s2.2;p145.262">This draws and defines a distinction between ideal-fluid flow and real fluid flow. </s></p><quote lang="English">"For fluids having relatively small viscosity, the effect of internal friction in a fluid is appreciable only in a narrow region surrounding the fluid boundaries."</quote><p n="p146.262"><s n="s1.2;p146.262">Accordingly, the flow outside of this narrow boundary layer can be considered ideal. </s><s n="s2.2;p146.262">Approximate equations can be developed using the momentum equations, for boundary-layer growth and drag, although relations within the boundary-layer may also be computed using the general equations for viscous fluids. </s></p><p n="p147.262"><s n="s1.5;p147.262">The boundary layer is often studied by analysing Two-dimensional flow along a flat plate. </s><s n="s2.5;p147.262">It is studied for both laminar and turbulent boundary layers using the respective momentum equations. </s><s n="s3.5;p147.262">The phenomenon of separation of the boundary layer is described in Prandtl's 1904 work<ref target="BAWE_0249d-ftnote.033"/>. </s><s n="s4.5;p147.262">Boundary layer effects are an important part of aerodynamics today as the subsequent wake is the cause of form drag. </s><s n="s5.5;p147.262">Work has been carried out (for example footnote reference<ref target="BAWE_0249d-ftnote.034"/>) with regards to controlling the boundary layer and helping prevent/delay separation, thus reducing the adverse effects of drag (i.e. loss in performance of the aerofoil). </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0249d-ftnote.033"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.3;pn1.1">Prandtl, Über Flussigkeitsbewegung bei sehr Reibung, <hi rend="italic">Verhandl.</hi> </s><s rend="italic" n="s2.3;pn1.1">III Intern. </s><s n="s3.3;pn1.1"><hi rend="italic">Math.-Kongr.,</hi> Heidelberg, 1904 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0249d-ftnote.034"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Carriere, P., and Eichelbrenner, E. A., 'Theory of flow reattachment by a tangential jet discharging against a strong adverse pressure gradient', Boundary layer and flow control (G. V. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">Lachmann, ed.), <hi rend="italic">I,</hi> 209-231, London, 1961 </s></p></note><p n="p148.262"><s n="s1.7;p148.262">Since the velocity at the boundary is zero relative to the boundaries, there is a steep velocity gradient from the boundary to the flow. </s><s n="s2.7;p148.262">The velocity in the boundary layer approaches that of the main flow asymptotically. </s><s n="s3.7;p148.262">The boundary layer on a streamlined body with uniform flow passing over it starts very thin upstream. </s><s n="s4.7;p148.262">Moving downstream with the boundary layer, the continual action of shear stress slows down additional fluid particles near the boundary layer, which thickens as the progression is made further downstream for the original point. </s><s n="s5.7;p148.262">The fluid in the layer is also subjected to a pressure gradient. </s><s n="s6.7;p148.262">This increases the momentum of the layer when the pressure decreases downstream, but decreases its momentum when the pressure increases downstream, an adverse pressure gradient. </s><s n="s7.7;p148.262">The flow outside of the boundary layer also affects the momentum entering the boundary layer. </s></p><p n="p149.262"><s n="s1.5;p149.262">Assuming a smooth boundary, the boundary layer starts out laminar. </s><s n="s2.5;p149.262">As the thickness of the laminar boundary layer increases further downstream, it becomes unstable and finally transforms into a turbulent boundary layer. </s><s n="s3.5;p149.262">The transformation only occurs once sufficient energy has entered the boundary layer. </s><s n="s4.5;p149.262">When the boundary layer has become turbulent, there is still a very thin layer next to the boundary that behaves as a laminar boundary layer. </s><s n="s5.5;p149.262">This thin layer is called the viscous sub-layer. <ref target="BAWE_0249d-ftnote.035"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0249d-ftnote.035"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Schlichting, Dr. H., Boundary-Layer Theory, Seventh Edition, McGraw-Hill, 1979 </s></p></note><p n="p150.262"><s n="s1.3;p150.262">Various definitions of boundary-layer thickness have been suggested. </s><s n="s2.3;p150.262">The most basic definition refers to the displacement of the main flow due to slowing down of fluid particles in the boundary zone. </s><s n="s3.3;p150.262">This thickness, called the displacement thickness, is expressed by </s></p><p n="p151.262"><s n="s1.1;p151.262"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0249d-form.007"/> </s></p><p n="p152.262"><s n="s1.1;p152.262">In which δ is that value of y at which u=U. Flow at the distance calculated with this equation is not strongly affected by the boundary though, so the boundary layer is frequently taken as distance to the point where u/U = 0.99 (i.e. the distance from the boundary that flow retains 99% of the velocity in free stream flow). </s></p><p n="p153.262"><s n="s1.2;p153.262">When the Reynolds number for the plate reaches a value between 500,000 and 1,000,000, the boundary layer becomes turbulent. </s><s n="s2.2;p153.262">The critical Reynolds number depends upon the initial turbulence of the fluid stream, upon the upstream edge of the plate, and upon the plate roughness. </s></p><p n="p154.262"><s n="s1.4;p154.262">For adverse pressure gradients, the boundary layer thickens rapidly. </s><s n="s2.4;p154.262">The adverse gradient in addition to the boundary shear decrease the momentum in the boundary layer. </s><s n="s3.4;p154.262">If they act for a sufficient length of time or distance, it is possible for the boundary layer to be brought to rest. </s><s n="s4.4;p154.262">If this occurs, then a phenomenon called separation results. </s></p><p n="p155.262"><s n="s1.4;p155.262">At the stagnation point, the boundary streamline must leave the boundary, illustrating the separation. </s><s n="s2.4;p155.262">Back-flow occurs immediately downstream from this point, and this region is known as the wake. </s><s n="s3.4;p155.262">As a result of separation, less work can be done by the fluid, and kinetic energy is lost. </s><s n="s4.4;p155.262">When separation occurs, pressure recovery is incomplete and flow losses (drag) increase. </s></p><p n="p156.262"><s n="s1.2;p156.262">In the laminar boundary layer, an adverse pressure gradient causes separation more readily than in a turbulent boundary layer, because of the small amount of momentum passed into the laminar boundary layer from the main flow. </s><s n="s2.2;p156.262">If separation occurs in the laminar boundary layer, the location of separation is farther upstream than it is when the boundary layer becomes turbulent first and then separation occurs. </s></p><p n="p157.262"><s n="s1.1;p157.262">A turbulent boundary layer therefore enables flow to continue unseparated with adverse pressure gradient, i.e. bending round a wall (see next section). </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold italic">Coanda Effect</head><p n="p158.262"><s n="s1.7;p158.262">As mentioned earlier, when a fluid passes over a surface it experiences friction. </s><s n="s2.7;p158.262">This slows down the fluid near the boundary in the boundary layer. </s><s n="s3.7;p158.262">Within a turbulent boundary layer, particles within the faster moving stream are drawn down into the slower moving boundary layer, adding their momentum to, and maintaining the necessary energy within the boundary layer to prevent separation. </s><s n="s4.7;p158.262">This turbulence allows flow to follow contours that instigate adverse pressure gradients. </s><s n="s5.7;p158.262">The skin tension of a fluid is such that there is attraction between the boundary and fluid. </s><s n="s6.7;p158.262">In this instance it is possible to redirect flow by the use of contoured geometry. </s><s n="s7.7;p158.262">This phenomenon is particularly strong in more viscous fluids, and as such the effect should be more noticeable with water than air. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold italic">Active Flow Control</head><p n="p159.262"><s n="s1.4;p159.262">This can be the use of a control jet, whether continuous or intermittent, to redirect or influence the direction of the main fluid flow. </s><s n="s2.4;p159.262">It is the fundamental premise on which fluerics is based. </s><s n="s3.4;p159.262">Boundary layer control can also be used to direct fluid flow (Figure 3.3). </s><s n="s4.4;p159.262">These can be:- </s></p><list type="ordered"><item>a) discharge of a fluid</item><item>b) venting of pressures to other areas</item><item>c) suction</item></list><figure id="BAWE_0249d-pic.028"><head>Figure 3.3: Examples of flow control <hi rend="sup">35</hi></head></figure></div2><div2><head><hi rend="bold italic">Amplification</hi><ref target="BAWE_0249d-ftnote.036"/><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0249d-ftnote.036"><p n="pn1.1"> Conway, A., A Guide to Fluidics, 1st edition, Macdonald &amp; Co., 1971</p></note></head><p n="p160.262"><s n="s1.1;p160.262">A good deal of the literature originally uncovered relates to this section. </s></p><p n="p161.262"><s n="s1.2;p161.262">The gain of amplifiers can be measured as either pressure gain G <hi rend="sub">p</hi> or flow gain G <hi rend="sub">f</hi>. </s><s n="s2.2;p161.262">These are both in turn calculated after measuring the values at the control (c) and the outputs (o): </s></p><p n="p162.262"><s n="s1.1;p162.262"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0249d-form.008"/> </s></p><p n="p163.262"><s n="s1.4;p163.262">Gains might appear high at times, but it is common for the maximum output pressure to only be about 40% of the supply pressure. </s><s n="s2.4;p163.262">Another important characteristic of amplifiers is the speed of response. </s><s n="s3.4;p163.262">Clearly signals cannot be sent at the same kind of speed that electrical signals can be, and so there is often a lag between the control and the desired output. </s><s n="s4.4;p163.262">This is measured by: </s></p><p n="p164.262"><s n="s1.1;p164.262"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0249d-form.009"/> </s></p><list type="simple"><head>where</head><item>U <hi rend="sub">s</hi> = jet velocity</item><item>L= jet length</item><item>= lag time</item></list><p n="p165.262"><s n="s1.3;p165.262">The presence of turbulence at the outputs causes noise in the signal. </s><s n="s2.3;p165.262">This is a consequence of turbulent flow, and a great deal of effort is being spent developing completely laminar elements. </s><s n="s3.3;p165.262">By reducing the aspect ratio, and including many parallel paths with low aspect ratios, signal-noise ratios can be very good indeed, sometimes as high as 1500. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold italic">Cavitation37</head><p n="p166.262"><s n="s1.3;p166.262">By increasing the speed of a jet when flow is attached to one wall, the pressure in a separation bubble might fall to the vapour pressure of the fluid. </s><s n="s2.3;p166.262">At this point, any increase in speed will elongate the bubble since it's pressure can not fall any lower, and detachment will follow. </s><s n="s3.3;p166.262">This effect is usually measured in relation to the cavitation number, σ, </s></p><p n="p167.262"><s n="s1.1;p167.262"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0249d-form.010"/> </s></p><list type="simple"><head>where</head><item>p <hi rend="sub">a</hi> = pressure outside the bubble</item><item>p <hi rend="sub">v</hi> = vapour pressure of the fluid</item><item>0.5 * ρU <hi rend="sub">s</hi><hi rend="sup">2</hi> = dynamic pressure in the jet</item></list><p n="p168.262"><s n="s1.1;p168.262">For gasses it is the <hi rend="italic">Mach Number</hi>, and liquids it is the <hi rend="italic">cavitation number</hi> that limits the supply pressure necessary for bistable operation of a particular element. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold italic">Power Consumption37</head><p n="p169.262"><s n="s1.1;p169.262">The power consumption of a wall attachment amplifier using incompressible fluid of density ρ supplied at pressure p <hi rend="sub">s</hi> is given approximately by:- </s></p><p n="p170.262"><s n="s1.1;p170.262"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0249d-form.011"/> </s></p><p n="p171.262"><s n="s1.3;p171.262">Therefore the power increases as the square of the size with constant supply pressure, but increases as the size decreases if the Reynolds number is held constant instead. </s><s n="s2.3;p171.262">Elements are preferred to be as small as possible to allow for faster switching times, and so maintain the necessary Reynolds number. </s><s n="s3.3;p171.262">This results in power consumption rising for smaller elements. </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Chapter 4 Methodology</head><div2><head rend="bold italic">Initial attack</head><p n="p172.262"><s n="s1.2;p172.262">The literature review uncovered a number of existing fluidic and flueric devices, and extensive research revealed the mechanisms and theory behind their operation. </s><s n="s2.2;p172.262">Key principals were identified from past and current solutions, and new angles suggested for investigation: </s></p><list type="ordered"><item>changing the profile or geometry of the element, see Figure 4.1.</item><item>changing the angle of incident of the nozzle, see Figure 4.2.</item><item>varying the offset of the nozzle from the walls, see Figure 4.3.</item><item>alternately blocking the outlet channels, see Figure 4.4.</item><item>active flow control/boundary-layer control, see Figure 4.5.</item></list><figure id="BAWE_0249d-pic.029"><head>Figure 4.1: Changing inlet geometry</head></figure><figure id="BAWE_0249d-pic.030"><head>Figure 4.2: Changing inlet nozzle angle</head></figure><figure id="BAWE_0249d-pic.031"><head>Figure 4.3: Varying nozzle offset from walls</head></figure><figure id="BAWE_0249d-pic.032"><head>Figure 4.4: Alternately blocking outlet channels</head></figure><figure id="BAWE_0249d-pic.033"><head>Figure 4.5: Boundary layer control</head></figure><p n="p173.262"><s n="s1.1;p173.262">These were considered at length, and initial concepts drawn on paper as preliminary ideas. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold italic">Development of selected ideas</head><p n="p174.262"><s n="s1.3;p174.262">Tangible designs from this initial brainstorming offered several avenues for development. </s><s n="s2.3;p174.262">The theory behind numbers 2, 3 and 4 above appears undeniable, and research has already been completed to some extent on each of these. </s><s n="s3.3;p174.262">Greater interest was in ideas 1 and 5: </s></p><list type="bulleted"><item>triggering flow to switch path by altering the geometry at the exit of the nozzle</item><item>causing reattachment by method of suction, or energising of the boundary layer</item></list></div2><div2><head rend="bold italic">Material Selection</head><p n="p175.262"><s n="s1.1;p175.262">The materials available for manufacture of the rig included: </s></p><list type="bulleted"><item>aluminium</item><item>steel</item><item>plastic</item></list><p n="p176.262"><s n="s1.2;p176.262">Aluminium could be formed into the desired shape but would have involved a considerable amount of machining. </s><s n="s2.2;p176.262">Whilst this was a possibility the narrowness of some of the channels might have proven difficult to accurately machine with the available university machinery. </s></p><p n="p177.262"><s n="s1.2;p177.262">Steel similarly could have been machined. </s><s n="s2.2;p177.262">Similar difficulties in achieving the bleed channels might have occurred. </s></p><p n="p178.262"><s n="s1.2;p178.262">Plastic sheet was considered. </s><s n="s2.2;p178.262">This was rejected on the grounds of its flexibility and the problems this could create in machining. </s></p><p n="p179.262"><s n="s1.3;p179.262">However plastic can also be simply formed into complex shapes using rapid prototyping. </s><s n="s2.3;p179.262">The University of <name type="university"/> has the necessary facilities for this type of production. </s><s n="s3.3;p179.262">This process was chosen as the most efficient way to produce the required rig geometries. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold italic">Rapid Prototyping</head><p n="p180.262"><s n="s1.5;p180.262">Rapid Prototyping machines were selected for manufacture for it's quick turnaround and integration with CAD software. </s><s n="s2.5;p180.262">Accordingly it would be easy to modify designs and resume testing in a short time. </s><s n="s3.5;p180.262">It has always been intended that rapid prototyping (RP) machines manufacture the flueric components for testing. </s><s n="s4.5;p180.262">Design for manufacture was essential at an early stage as from the offset, a maximum footprint of 200mm by 200mm was set. </s><s n="s5.5;p180.262">Designing then continued, working the 2-dimensional drawings into 3-dimensional CAD (computer aided design) models using a CAD package called Solidworks. </s></p><p n="p181.262"><s n="s1.6;p181.262">Where possible the machine was set to create components with sparse fill, where a low density honeycomb structure is created instead of a high density solid. </s><s n="s2.6;p181.262">This drastically reduces the amount of material used, and is particularly suitable when structural strength is not required. </s><s n="s3.6;p181.262">Once created by the rapid prototyping, the support material was first removed. </s><s n="s4.6;p181.262">The material is the same as the rest of the model, however an additive is mixed with it to inhibit the adhesion of the material, reducing strength and rigidity, allowing for easy removal. </s><s n="s5.6;p181.262">The support material is also low density with a woven appearance to minimise material wastage. </s><s n="s6.6;p181.262">This is material necessary to create the geometry, but unwanted on the finished model. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold italic">Initial Feedback</head><p n="p182.262"><s n="s1.2;p182.262">An early test was run to test that CosmosFlowWorks, the CFD add-on for Solidworks, could simulate flow attachment around a curve with and adverse pressure gradient. </s><s n="s2.2;p182.262">It was therefore possible to confirm theoretical principals before manufacture. </s></p><p n="p183.262"><s n="s1.1;p183.262">Prototypes were finalised for manufacture, to physically demonstrate the effects that had already been seen on the CAD package outputs. </s></p><p n="p184.262"><s n="s1.5;p184.262">Perspex was cut and drilled to fit the geometry of the rapid prototyped base, as designed. </s><s n="s2.5;p184.262">Some smoothing and drilling was required to assemble the model as the rapid prototyping machine produces components with a minute excess of material at all surfaces of the model and fitting was a little too tight. </s><s n="s3.5;p184.262">It is assumed with rapid prototyping that small amounts of material will need removing in order to achieve the desired dimensions. </s><s n="s4.5;p184.262">If components are too tight to fit together problems occur, as highlighted when one component on the profiling model sheared off inside another. </s><s n="s5.5;p184.262">A replacement was made however in time for testing. </s></p><p n="p185.262"><s n="s1.4;p185.262">The model created to test the theory of energising the boundary layer proved disappointing. </s><s n="s2.4;p185.262">The geometry was right on the limitation of the machine, and so accuracy was not good. </s><s n="s3.4;p185.262">The model was completed however and tested. </s><s n="s4.4;p185.262">A second revision was designed to eliminate the faults of the initial design, for example using a better aspect ratio for visualising flow improving attachment of the flow to the vessel wall, and attaching inlet flow. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold italic">Testing</head><p n="p186.262"><s n="s1.1;p186.262">Whilst the physical modelling was of prime concern, it was of interest to attempt to model the flows using computational analysis as well. </s></p><div3><head rend="bold">CFD</head><p n="p187.262"><s n="s1.4;p187.262">The models were simplified within Solidworks to reduce unnecessary geometry that would only serve to increase computing time. </s><s n="s2.4;p187.262">The models were then saved and exported as Parasolids (*.x_t file extension, or *.x_b for binary parasolids) </s><s n="s3.4;p187.262">This is a file format that is compatible largely with the majority of CAD and FEA packages, serving as the ideal medium to transport across to a superior CFD package, Star-Design. </s><s n="s4.4;p187.262">Within this package, a mesh was applied and flow conditions set: </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p188.262"><s n="s1.3;p188.262">First the model was subtracted from a cuboid that encompassed it. </s><s n="s2.3;p188.262">Flow is modelled through 'solids' as we perceive them, and the voids around the solids are seen by the package as the boundaries governing the flow. </s><s n="s3.3;p188.262">This is the reason for subtracting the geometry initially. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p189.262"><s n="s1.1;p189.262">A surface mesh was applied, and subsequently refined to make it finer where complex geometry was present on the model, or where flow was expected to be most complex. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p190.262"><s n="s1.1;p190.262">Once this was completed, a volume mesh was created to simulate the whole chamber through which the flow was to pass. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p191.262"><s n="s1.1;p191.262">The inlet face was selected and assigned as a velocity inlet. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p192.262"><s n="s1.1;p192.262">The walls through which the flow would escape the chamber were selected and assigned as pressure outlets. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p193.262"><s n="s1.1;p193.262">Flow conditions were set experimentally, in accordance to the fluid to be simulated. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p194.262"><s n="s1.1;p194.262">The simulation was then run for up to 200 iterations (Excessive iterations took too much computing time, too few resulted in poor results). </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p195.262"><s n="s1.1;p195.262">The residuals converged and the results were visualised as streamlines and velocity components </s></p></div3><div3><head rend="bold">Physical</head><div4><head rend="bold">Air flow</head><p n="p196.262"><s n="s1.6;p196.262">The model components were smoothed, fitted together and Perspex lids added to enable visualisation of the flow patterns. </s><s n="s2.6;p196.262">Some surfaces of the models were 'sealed' with nail varnish as the material used for manufacture is slightly porous (basically due to the sparse fill of some components). </s><s n="s3.6;p196.262">A tube was attached to each, and the author merely blew through the tube to check for obvious faults with the models. </s><s n="s4.6;p196.262">Condensation of the breathe upon the Perspex lid was so apparent that it was possible to clearly see the flow path taken. </s><s n="s5.6;p196.262">It was deemed so successful that for air at least, it was decided that no other flow visualisation was required. </s><s n="s6.6;p196.262">The other flow visualisation techniques discussed were time consuming and complicated, whilst creating resistance to flow, or slightly changing the property of the fluid. </s></p><p n="p197.262"><s n="s1.4;p197.262">The models were tested with varying geometries and, each time photographs taken of the flow recorded. </s><s n="s2.4;p197.262">This was done 'blind' (without the knowledge of what position controls and profiles were set to) and more than ten times for each configuration. </s><s n="s3.4;p197.262">The purpose of this was to reduce the likelihood of false results. </s><s n="s4.4;p197.262">Potential errors identified include:- </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p198.262"><s n="s1.1;p198.262">One can easily direct the flow merely by altering the method of blowing. </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p199.262"><s n="s1.1;p199.262">One can alter the direction in which the main jet enters the flow chamber. </s></p><p n="p200.262"><s n="s1.3;p200.262">As it was difficult to photograph condensation on a transparent material, in front of a white background, the images required the levels to be adjusted to make it more visible. </s><s n="s2.3;p200.262">The adjustments were made using Adobe Photoshop. </s><s n="s3.3;p200.262">This is no way affects the results taken, merely aids in identifying them. </s></p></div4><div4><head rend="bold">Water flow</head><p n="p201.262"><s n="s1.4;p201.262">Additional apparatus was required to demonstrate liquid flow through the models. </s><s n="s2.4;p201.262">It was quickly realised that only a gentle flow was required else the element would fill completely to accommodate the volume of water and make visualisation of the attachment flow impossible. </s><s n="s3.4;p201.262">A reservoir was required that could be raised or lowered to increase pressure. </s><s n="s4.4;p201.262">It was also necessary to control the flow rate. </s></p><p n="p202.262"><s n="s1.5;p202.262">Both of these objectives were met by cannibalising a milk bottle. </s><s n="s2.5;p202.262">A hole was drilled in the bottle cap (Fig 4.7) such that the tube used previously for air flow, could be fitted tightly inside it. </s><s n="s3.5;p202.262">The bottle could be filled, and inverted with the lid in place (Fig 4.8). </s><s n="s4.5;p202.262">Flow would then be forced to flow through the tube, at a rate dependant upon the height above the exit of the tube. </s><s n="s5.5;p202.262">A variable clamp was fitted over the tube after it was realised that pinching the tube was sufficient to reduce the flow rate, but was open to inconsistencies. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0249d-pic.034"><head>Figure 4.6: Drilled bottle cap</head></figure><p n="p203.262"><s n="s1.3;p203.262">The open end of the tube was then held in place on the model with putty to provide a good seal. </s><s n="s2.3;p203.262">The jet was made to flow ever so slightly down a gradient as this ensured proper drainage of the element downstream. </s><s n="s3.3;p203.262">Deflections of the jet to the side wall were independent of gravitational effects. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0249d-pic.035"><head>Figure 4.7: Bottle and tube</head></figure><p n="p204.262"><s n="s1.2;p204.262">The water was easily visible itself as it was streaming through a gas (air) and so no dyes or particles were necessary. </s><s n="s2.2;p204.262">Photographs were again captured and enhanced in a couple of instances to better highlight the flow (again using the Photoshop software package). </s></p></div4></div3></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Chapter 5 Observations and Results</head><div2><head rend="bold italic">Verification of CFD Models</head><p n="p205.262"><s n="s1.3;p205.262">Reference will be made to, and observations recorded for successive simulations. </s><s n="s2.3;p205.262">Verification is therefore limited to reporting the observed outcome of each of the test runs. </s><s n="s3.3;p205.262">The tables of results presented for each run include a column of comment, stating how well the observed flow pattern indicated wall attachment. </s></p><p n="p206.262"><s n="s1.2;p206.262">Discussion of the results is presented in the next chapter. </s><s n="s2.2;p206.262">Similarly discussion of model developments is included in the next chapter. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold italic">Photographic Evidence of Models</head><p n="p207.262"><s n="s1.1;p207.262">Digital photographs were taken of each test run and are presented below. </s></p><div3><head rend="bold">Model A - Profile changes</head><p n="p208.262"><s n="s1.4;p208.262">Table 5.1 shows the results and observations noted when the first model was tested with air (Figure 5.1). </s><s n="s2.4;p208.262">As the inlet opening was quite wide, the tube available for testing was too small. </s><s n="s3.4;p208.262">This meant that the main stream did not necessary come into contact with either of the profiles on each side. </s><s n="s4.4;p208.262">Blowing straight into the model, and not through the tube gave much more consistent results, whilst also providing a non-directional inlet jet. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0249d-pic.036"><head>Figure 5.1: Testing Model A</head></figure><p n="p209.262"><s n="s1.3;p209.262">Table 5.2 shows that the results when the rig was tested with water were much more decisive. </s><s n="s2.3;p209.262">The flow deflections noted were far more distinct, and whilst flowing through the smaller tube (sealed with putty) the jet instantly attached itself to one profile or the other, depending on geometry. </s><s n="s3.3;p209.262">The tube size was not found to be a problem when using water as the fluid. </s></p></div3><div3><head rend="bold">Model B - 'Blowing' the boundary-layer</head><p n="p210.262"><s n="s1.4;p210.262">Tables 5.3 and 5.4 display the observations from testing the second model (Figure 5.2) with jets of air. </s><s n="s2.4;p210.262">With the shorter segments (i.e. tighter curvature) the jet did detach from the segment before reattaching to the side-walls. </s><s n="s3.4;p210.262">A small separation bubble was noted. </s><s n="s4.4;p210.262">This bubble was not present with the longer segments as the curvature was sufficient to ensure attachment along its length. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0249d-pic.037"><head>Figure 5.2: Testing Model B</head></figure><p n="p211.262"><s n="s1.6;p211.262">When testing with water, the tube was attached directly to the custom nozzle. </s><s n="s2.6;p211.262">The tube made a good seal with the inlet pipe connection. </s><s n="s3.6;p211.262">It was noted early on however that this inlet nozzle was imperfect due to manufacturing inaccuracies, and so flow was not even. </s><s n="s4.6;p211.262">Deflections were far greater with the shorter segments, with a small separation bubble between the segment and the side wall as mentioned in Table 5.5. </s><s n="s5.6;p211.262">When testing with the longer segments, as reported in Table 5.6, attachment was prolonged between both segments, as the jet continued to widen and 'flood' the gap between them. </s><s n="s6.6;p211.262">It was necessary to incline the model about the x axis, thus lowering the downstream section of the model to improve drainage of the element and prevent it from filling completely. </s></p><table id="BAWE_0249d-tab.003"><head rend="bold">Table 5.1: Observations from Model A, tested with air</head><row><cell/></row></table><table id="BAWE_0249d-tab.004"><head rend="bold">Table 5.2: Observations from Model A, tested with water</head><row><cell/></row></table><table id="BAWE_0249d-tab.005"><head rend="bold">Table 5.3: Observations from Model B, tested with air, and shorter tight segments</head><row><cell/></row></table><table id="BAWE_0249d-tab.006"><head rend="bold">Table 5.4: Observations from Model B, tested with air, and tapered segments</head><row><cell/></row></table><table id="BAWE_0249d-tab.007"><head rend="bold">Table 5.5: Observations from Model B, tested with water and shorter segments</head><row><cell/></row></table><table id="BAWE_0249d-tab.008"><head rend="bold">Table 5.6: Observations from Model B, tested with water, and tapered segments</head><row><cell/></row></table></div3></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Chapter 6 Analysis and Discussion of Results</head><div2><head rend="bold italic"> Development of initial concepts</head><p n="p212.262"><s n="s1.9;p212.262">After the initial transfer of designs into CAD packages, it was necessary to scale them correctly to fall within the restriction of the footprint available when using the rapid prototyping machine. </s><s n="s2.9;p212.262">The footprint was smaller than expected. </s><s n="s3.9;p212.262">One result of this was that not as many test rigs were completed as had originally been planned. </s><s n="s4.9;p212.262">The cost of the material was much greater than expected when planning the experiments. </s><s n="s5.9;p212.262">This encouraged the author to design the form of some components to offer strength within the models, whilst minimising the amount of material required to do so. </s><s n="s6.9;p212.262">This can be seen in Figure 6.1. </s><s n="s7.9;p212.262">Despite ingenious design, the material proved much weaker than first expected, with two components failing as a result of a strong friction fit (Figure 6.1). </s><s n="s8.9;p212.262">The components were remade, and the interacting regions enlarged so as to loosen the fit. </s><s n="s9.9;p212.262">This is a direct result of the rapid prototyping machines creating a marginally thicker 'skin' than the CAD design specifies. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0249d-pic.038"><head>Figure 6.1: Minimising material used within model</head></figure><figure id="BAWE_0249d-pic.039"><head>Figure 6.2: Failed components</head></figure><p n="p213.262"><s n="s1.9;p213.262">The part that failed had a textured finish to aid grip when testing with water etc. </s><s n="s2.9;p213.262">The reason for this was that the design fell outside the rapid prototyping machine's resolution. </s><s n="s3.9;p213.262">This was not immediately realised, and an early component for Model B (the boundary blower) was created. </s><s n="s4.9;p213.262">The rapid prototype machine could not reproduce the design geometry exactly. </s><s n="s5.9;p213.262">This meant that flow did not take the paths expected. </s><s n="s6.9;p213.262">Once the resolution restrictions of the rapid prototype machine were realised, better designs were produced. </s><s n="s7.9;p213.262">This was a timely lesson, allowing the renovation and redesign of Model B to create a working model. </s><s n="s8.9;p213.262">Initial testing of Model A also suggested that a better method of introducing flow into the element was necessary. </s><s n="s9.9;p213.262">Some of these changes were also incorporated into the second design of Model B. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold italic">General Discussion </head><p n="p214.262"><s n="s1.1;p214.262">The physical experimentation confirmed the theoretical principals behind them, although perhaps not to the degree that was expected. </s></p><div3><head rend="bold">Model A</head><p n="p215.262"><s n="s1.6;p215.262">Model A turned out to be the most successful with definitive results for every asymmetrical configuration, whilst appearing to show only very slight partiality to one side as opposed to the other when the input geometry was balanced. </s><s n="s2.6;p215.262">This slight partiality for one side over the other was more prevalent with air than with water, despite the deflections of water being far greater when the geometry was unbalanced (one profile being rounded whilst the other was sharp). </s><s n="s3.6;p215.262">The opening for flow was far too big for this model, and ideally should have been narrower. </s><s n="s4.6;p215.262">This meant that in testing, the jet did not always attach as it was expected when using the pipe, as the jet was simply too narrow. </s><s n="s5.6;p215.262">Narrowing the entrance however would completely change the aspect ratio of the element, as the height of inlet and chamber remain quite high. </s><s n="s6.6;p215.262">Creating a shallower model, with a narrower input would be a worthy improvement. </s></p><p n="p216.262"><s n="s1.2;p216.262">The generation of different geometries of the inlet area was sufficient to demonstrate a principal, but the circulation of fluid around the back of the profilers cannot be discounted from the investigation. </s><s n="s2.2;p216.262">Their presence is likely to have had the following effect:- </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p217.262"><s n="s1.1;p217.262">Serving to extend the volume of the separation bubble, increasing the time necessary for attachment forces to develop </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p218.262"><s n="s1.1;p218.262">Encouraging the jet to attach to the profile from the very offset due to the additional opening of the separation bubble </s></p><p n="p219.262"><s n="s1.2;p219.262">These effects could therefore be advantageous if a strong attachment were prioritised above a rapid attachment. </s><s n="s2.2;p219.262">Further investigation would be necessary to isolate this effect and determine it's merit. </s></p></div3><div3><head rend="bold">Model B</head><p n="p220.262"><s n="s1.3;p220.262">Flow did not divert sufficiently significantly into the outside flow channels when testing Model B. This meant that flow was not encouraged sufficiently to attach, and sometimes the attachment was not particularly strong. </s><s n="s2.3;p220.262">Unlike Model A, it appeared that for Model B the air testing was more successful than the water testing. </s><s n="s3.3;p220.262">The exception to this was that when testing with air there was attachment regardless of whether the controls were both open or both closed. </s></p><p n="p221.262"><s n="s1.3;p221.262">It is the author's belief that the attachment was not controlled strictly in line with the principals to which it was designed. </s><s n="s2.3;p221.262">Instead, the deflections were caused in a manner akin to the Induction Amplifier, whereby the control flows follow the boundary wall, and the viscous shear induces the main jet to follow suit, instead of acting upon the boundary layer as such. </s><s n="s3.3;p221.262">This would explain why it was not necessary for the presence of any control flow to deflect the main jet. </s></p><p n="p222.262"><s n="s1.2;p222.262">The manufacture of the segments was also such that a little work had to be done to correctly align their edges with the control inlets. </s><s n="s2.2;p222.262">Small imperfections such as this could have attributed to the bias flow toward one side. </s></p></div3><div3><head rend="bold">General</head><p n="p223.262"><s n="s1.5;p223.262">In both models, it is evident that there was leakage of flow along the joins of the model boundaries with the Perspex lid. </s><s n="s2.5;p223.262">The lid had to be frequently removed to permit cleaning/drying. </s><s n="s3.5;p223.262">The effect of this leakage flow would serve to balance pressure differences and weaken attachment forces. </s><s n="s4.5;p223.262">Their presence cannot enhance the performance, only hinder it, and so are not a criticism of the experimental results. </s><s n="s5.5;p223.262">In future experiments, a more sealed lid arrangement should be considered. </s></p><p n="p224.262"><s n="s1.5;p224.262">Limitations arose regarding time, equipment and resources. </s><s n="s2.5;p224.262">The material used by the rapid prototype machine works out more expensive gram for gram than silver, and so it's use had to be sparing, with as few models as possible, and very few revisions. </s><s n="s3.5;p224.262">The rapid prototype machine was also out of action for a period shortly after the 22 <hi rend="sup">nd</hi> March whilst repairs were carried out. </s><s n="s4.5;p224.262">The problem was that lamina's of the rapid prototyping material were not aligning properly and not adhering correctly. </s><s n="s5.5;p224.262">A couple of the replacement components for Model A were affected, but the imperfection was considered negligible for this application. </s></p><p n="p225.262"><s n="s1.9;p225.262">There were also problems on the <name type="university"/> IT network that resulted in communication breakdowns. </s><s n="s2.9;p225.262">In order to use the rapid prototyping machine it was necessary to provide Mr P. J. </s><s n="s3.9;p225.262">Kimber with electronic files of the design. </s><s n="s4.9;p225.262">The necessary files could not therefore be sent by email when the <name type="university"/> IT network was not fully functional. </s><s n="s5.9;p225.262">This resulted in delays in the programme. </s><s n="s6.9;p225.262">The files therefore had to be brought in on a USB stick to get around this, but this was not the ideal method. </s><s n="s7.9;p225.262">The <name type="university"/> IT network functionality was necessary again to send files down to the rapid prototyping machine. </s><s n="s8.9;p225.262">The whole network crashed down around the 16 <hi rend="sup">th</hi> March, following on from a week-long absence of email, thus preventing the production and subsequent testing of Model B for about 3 weeks. </s><s n="s9.9;p225.262">This significantly delayed the testing programme and adversely impacted on the whole project timetable. </s></p><p n="p226.262"><s n="s1.4;p226.262">The reproducibility of all results achieved in this investigation are very good. </s><s n="s2.4;p226.262">Testing consisted of numerous experiments over several days, including 'blind' tests to ensure that no subconscious bias was afflicted upon the flow affecting results either positively or negatively. </s><s n="s3.4;p226.262">The results remained consistent, and trends were indicated beyond doubt in all instances. </s><s n="s4.4;p226.262">The designs for the models are included within the report allowing exact copies to be created for further investigation by another party. </s></p><p n="p227.262"><s n="s1.2;p227.262">The consistency of results and the frequency with which the theories were backed up by experimentation makes for sound ground on which to draw any conclusions. </s><s n="s2.2;p227.262">Potential faults with both models and experimental methods have been detailed (section 6.4), but it is still with reasonable confidence that the conclusions are drawn from this experimental test programme, based on the results obtained. </s></p></div3></div2><div2><head rend="bold italic">What can be drawn from this</head><p n="p228.262"><s n="s1.1;p228.262">The author believes that the experiments show good reason to believe that changes in the geometry of the element, mimicked within the reported tests by movement of key components, can achieve similar flow control as witnessed here. </s></p><div3><head rend="bold">Model A</head><p n="p229.262"><s n="s1.2;p229.262">As cells are filled, a deformation can be achieved of the region illustrated here. </s><s n="s2.2;p229.262">A change in profile can be achieved, similar to the rotation of the profilers in Model A. This was the assumption that the model was designed upon, however the results suggest benefits from the addition of a 'bleed channel' as pictured here, and discussed here. </s></p></div3><div3><head rend="bold">Model B</head><p n="p230.262"><s n="s1.2;p230.262">When the cells are loaded, the control paths would be squeezed shut, whilst the other would be relaxed and open, encouraging flow to attach to the other channel. </s><s n="s2.2;p230.262">This replaces the sliders in Model B with channels that would simply pinch shut to stem the flow through them as shown here. </s></p></div3></div2><div2><head rend="bold italic">Criticisms</head><list type="bulleted"><item>Discussion of errors or inaccuracies inherent within the methodology</item><item>Failure in research</item><item>Ambiguity of design</item><item>Methods of fitting supply flows</item><item>Methods of testing</item></list><p n="p231.262"><s n="s1.5;p231.262">Research failed to uncover any papers from the period from 1970's where initial interest peaked in fluidics. </s><s n="s2.5;p231.262">This slowed the process, having to delve deeper to uncover outdated research, and lack of any information in a currently competitive commercial market hampered early progress in the investigation. </s><s n="s3.5;p231.262">More time should have been spent trying to trace early research back through the various library re-cataloguing in which it has become entangled. </s><s n="s4.5;p231.262">It is not the author's belief that the elements tested within this report have been investigated publicly anywhere prior to this investigation. </s><s n="s5.5;p231.262">However, if more knowledge could be gathered in related subjects, then designs could have been better refined: </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p232.262"><s n="s1.1;p232.262">maximum curvature of elements/segments that still resulted in attached flow </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p233.262"><s n="s1.1;p233.262">suggestion of channel dimensions (in all dimensions) </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p234.262"><s n="s1.1;p234.262">maximum flow rate for different viscosities </s></p><p n="p235.262"><s n="s1.1;p235.262">These fields have been identified as potential avenues for further investigation and development. </s></p><p n="p236.262"><s n="s1.5;p236.262">The elements produced and the investigation as a whole stuck closely with the project specification for the majority of the time. </s><s n="s2.5;p236.262">Modelling did not occur using elastomeric materials, which is regrettable, although not entirely necessary. </s><s n="s3.5;p236.262">The results obtained give sufficient reason to believe that alternative construction would be every bit as successful as the rigid models produced. </s><s n="s4.5;p236.262">CFD analysis proved too time consuming and complex to continue as a major component of the investigation due to it's steep learning curve and limited access. </s><s n="s5.5;p236.262">The work that was completed in this area indicate it may be of use in future developments provided sufficient time is allocated. </s></p><p n="p237.262"><s n="s1.1;p237.262">Progress was too slow in the beginning, and not enough was achieved in the early half of the investigation, leading to pressures in completion of models when unforeseen complication arose such as the rapid prototyping machine breaking down. </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Chapter 7 Conclusions</head><p n="p238.262"><s n="s1.1;p238.262">The conclusions will be drawn in the following sections </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p239.262"><s n="s1.1;p239.262">Comments will be made in evaluation of the success of CFD within this investigation, and its shortcomings. </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p240.262"><s n="s1.1;p240.262">Success with respective models will be noted and their failures criticised, outlining their impact upon current/future development. </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p241.262"><s n="s1.1;p241.262">Evaluation of the methodology will ensue, including the level to which the projects specification has been met, and suggestions for application. </s></p><div2><head rend="bold italic">General Conclusions</head><p rend="ordered" n="p242.262"><s n="s1.6;p242.262">The success in CFD analysis during this project was mixed. </s><s n="s2.6;p242.262">Simulations of simple flow devices (flow through a pipe with a simple obstruction) were easy to model and run. </s><s n="s3.6;p242.262">However since the curved geometry of the designed rigs was modelled the CFD package used (CosmosFlowWorks) immediately had problems. </s><s n="s4.6;p242.262">The time taken for the program to perform 100-200 iterations ran into many hours. </s><s n="s5.6;p242.262">At the end of the runs it was found that the necessary data for analysis (curves, vortex shapes etc) could not always be extracted. </s><s n="s6.6;p242.262">Alternative CFD packages should be considered in the future or more time allocated to develop simpler CFD modelling. </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p243.262"><s n="s1.2;p243.262">Both models were successfully tested to demonstrate flow attachment. </s><s n="s2.2;p243.262">There were some inconsistencies, such as one model (Model A) providing better results for air than water, whilst the other did not produce consistent results when using water. </s></p><p n="p244.262"><s n="s1.3;p244.262">The Perspex lid should be redesigned to give a lower or zero leak-path. </s><s n="s2.3;p244.262">The geometry of the models in relation to the inlet aperture should be reviewed. </s><s n="s3.3;p244.262">As stated for model A, the inlet pipe diameter was too small in relation to the inlet chamber dimensions, for example, when the fluid being used was air. </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p245.262"><s n="s1.3;p245.262">The investigation stuck closely with the project specification. </s><s n="s2.3;p245.262">Literature was always going to be hard to come by, and it transpires than more time was required to achieve sufficient amounts than initially thought. </s><s n="s3.3;p245.262">Whilst elastomeric models were not created, clear outlines have been stated to transform the models into this format. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold italic">Suggestion for further work</head><p n="p246.262"><s n="s1.2;p246.262">It would be worth completing a shallower model, with a narrower inlet entrance, to ensure attachment to either wall. </s><s n="s2.2;p246.262">Some investigation should be conducted to ascertain the effect of the interaction of the fluid with the top and bottom surfaces. </s></p><p n="p247.262"><s n="s1.2;p247.262">A more sealed lid should be considered for future developments, as small leakages could have adversely balanced many pressure gradients, and inhibited attachment of the fluid jet. </s><s n="s2.2;p247.262">The jet still attached with the poorly fitting lid, however this should still be confirmed. </s></p><p n="p248.262"><s n="s1.3;p248.262">The effect of geometric scale upon the fluid behaviour is little known. </s><s n="s2.3;p248.262">Restrictions were in place for this investigation due to the limitations of manufacturability, however channel dimensions and aspect ratios could alter behaviour of these elements significantly. </s><s n="s3.3;p248.262">Rigs of various sizes and ratios should therefore be considered in future investigation. </s></p><p n="p249.262"><s n="s1.1;p249.262">Design in the future would benefit greatly from better understanding of the fluid's property, as a factor in maintaining attachment around a surface that creates an adverse pressure gradient (i.e. to follow a convex profile). </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold italic">Costing</head><p n="p250.262"><s n="s1.2;p250.262">A book was acquired for £6 from The BookBarns book store. </s><s n="s2.2;p250.262">This item was deemed essential due to the lack of literature available from the internet and other searches including public libraries. </s></p><div3><head rend="bold">Personnel</head><p n="p251.262"><s n="s1.2;p251.262">The costing for this investigation has been drawn up in accordance with guidelines laid down by the University of <name type="university"/>. </s><s n="s2.2;p251.262">These suggest hourly rates in line with those of industry, and according to the following hierarchy: </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p252.262"><s n="s1.3;p252.262">Academic staff time should be costed at a (modest) rate of £50 per hour, inclusive of overheads. </s><s n="s2.3;p252.262">You should include the total time that any academic has spent contributing to the project in meetings, laboratory or visits etc. </s><s n="s3.3;p252.262">Do not cost academic time used in assessment. </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p253.262"><s n="s1.1;p253.262">Technician time should be costed at £20 per hour to include overheads. </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p254.262"><s n="s1.1;p254.262">Student time should be costed at £15 per hour to include overheads. </s></p><p n="p255.262"><s n="s1.1;p255.262">Over the course of this investigation, there have been </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p256.262"><s n="s1.2;p256.262">18 meetings with Mr P. J. </s><s n="s2.2;p256.262">Kimber, averaging about 30 minutes per meeting, discussing every aspect of the project, progress, and the manufacture of components. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p257.262"><s n="s1.2;p257.262">2 meetings of about 15 minutes each, with Mr Y. M. </s><s n="s2.2;p257.262">Chung discussing the use of computational analysis. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p258.262"><s n="s1.1;p258.262">1 meeting of about an hour with a student colleague to get to grips with Star-Design and speed the learning curve for its use. </s></p><p n="p259.262"><s n="s1.1;p259.262">In accordance with the guidelines, time spent in consultation with academic staff reached £475, and student colleagues reached just £15 bringing the total to £490. </s></p></div3><div3><head rend="bold">Consumables</head><p n="p260.262"><s n="s1.6;p260.262">A total of 210 grams or rapid prototyping material is contained in all the components that were made for this investigation. </s><s n="s2.6;p260.262">At an estimate, a further 5% may have been used in the process as support material, which is essentially waste. </s><s n="s3.6;p260.262">The total mass of material used in this investigation then rises to just under 225 grams. </s><s n="s4.6;p260.262">At around 40pence per gram, the cost reaches £90. </s><s n="s5.6;p260.262">The Perspex lids cost a total of £5 as scraps were used when possible. </s><s n="s6.6;p260.262">There were no other consumable costs incurred during the investigation. </s></p><p n="p261.262"><s n="s1.1;p261.262">The total costing of this investigation, including consumables, literature and personnel time, is £591. </s></p></div3><div3><head rend="bold">Total costs</head><p n="p262.262"><s n="s1.1;p262.262">Including the text book, labour and consumables as detailed above, the total project cost (excluding the time of the author) totals £591, excluding VAT where applicable. </s></p></div3></div2></div1></body><back><div1 type="bibliography"><head rend="bold">References</head><p>McCloy, D., An Introduction to Fluidics</p><p>Streeter, V.L., Fluid Mechanics, Fourth Edition, McGraw-Hill Book Company, 1966</p><p>Rosenhead, L., Laminar Boundary Layers, Oxford University Press, 1963. </p><p>Schlichting, Dr. H., Boundary-Layer Theory, Seventh Edition, McGraw-Hill, 1979</p><p>Abramovich, G.N., The Theory of Turbulent Jets, The Massachusetts Institute of Technology, 1963</p><p>Mataoui, A., Schiestel, R., Salem, A., Study of the oscillatory regime of a turbulent plane jet impinging in a rectangular cavity, Applied Mathematical Modelling 27 (2003) p. 89-114</p><p>Eliphas Wagner Simõesa, E.W., Furlanc, R., Leminskia, R.E.B., Gongora-Rubioa, M.R., Pereirab, M.T., Morimotoa, N.I., Avilésd, J.J.S., Microfluidic oscillator for gas flow control and measurement, Sensors and Actuators A 125 (2006) p. 159-169</p><p>Tesa?r, V., Hung, C.H., Zimmerman, W.B., No-moving-part hybrid-synthetic jet actuator, Sensors and Actuators A 125 (2006) p. 159-169</p><p>Mahapatra, T.R., Layek, G.C., Maiti, M.K., Unsteady laminar separated flow through constricted channel, International Journal of Non-Linear Mechanics 37 (2002) p. 171-186</p><p>Geropp, D., Odenthal, H.-J., Drag reduction of motor vehicles by active flow control using the Coanda effect, Experiments in Fluids 28 (2000) p. 74-85</p><p>Fiedler, H.E., Fernholz, H.-H., On management and control of turbulent shear flows, Prog. Aerospace Sci. Vol. 27, p. 305-387, 1990</p><p>Trávnícek, Z., Peszynski, K., Hosek, J., Wawrzyniak, S., Aerodynamic and mass transfer characteristics of an annular bistable impinging jet with a fluidic flipflop control, International Journal of Heat and Mass Transfer 46 (2003) p. 1265-1278</p><p>L. Prandtl, Über Flussigkeitsbewegung bei sehr kleiner Reibung, Verhandl. III Intern. Math.-Kongr., Heidelberg, 1904.</p><p>O. Reynolds, An Experimental Investigation of the Circumstances Which Determine whether the Motion of Water Shall Be Direct or Sinuous, and of the Laws of Resistance in Parallel Channels, Trans. Roy. Soc. London, vol. 174, 1883.</p><p>Houghton Mifflin Company, The American Heritage Dictionary of the English Language, Fourth Edition, Houghton Mifflin Company, 2000 &lt;[<seg type="URL" n="http://www.bartleby.com/61/43/F0204300.html"/>]> [October 2005]</p><p>Anju K, First Successful Computer Simulation of Flow in Fluidic Windshield Washer Nozzle Shows Potential to Reduce Design Time 50%, Journal Articles by Fluent Software Users, JA084, 1999 &lt;[<seg type="URL" n="http://www.fluent.com/solutions/articles/ja084.pdf"/>]> [December 2005]</p><p>Bradshaw, B.A., Experimental Fluid Mechanics, 2nd Edition, Pergamon Press, 1964, page 198</p><p>Microscale behaviour of fluids, Microfluidics, Wikipedia &lt;<seg type="URL" n="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Microfluidics"/>> 20/03/06, Para. 3</p><p>Conway, A., A Guide to Fluidics, 1st edition, Macdonald &amp; Co., 1971</p><p>Grant, J., and Wright, J., Potential applications of fluidics in nuclear plant, Paper K2, Proc. 2nd Cranfield Fluidics conference, British Hydromechanics Research Association, 1967, pp. K2-9 to K2-19</p><p>Baker, P. J., A comparison of fluid diodes, Paper D6, Proc. 2nd Cranfield Fluidics Conference, British Hydromechanics Research Association, 1967, pp. D6-88 to D6-115</p><p>Jacobs, B. E. A., and Baker, P. J., The Cascade Diode, Paper K5, Proc. 3rd Cranfield Fluidics Conference, British Hydromechanics Research Association, 1968, pp. K5-63 to K5-82</p><p>Warren, R. W., "Some parameters affecting the design of bistable "amplifiers Fluid jet devices Symposium. A.S.M.E. November 1962</p><p>Gaettli, H. H., Muller, H. R. and Zinag, R. H., "Remarks on the limitations of pure fluid "elements Proc. Fluid Amplification Symposium. Vol. 1, p. 217, Washington 1964.</p><p>Parker, G. A., "Some aspects of fluidic sequencing and digital control systems for machine "tools 7th International M.T.D.R. Conference, Birmingham, September 1966</p><p>Kolff, et al.: T. Amer. Soc. Art. Int. Org., Vol. 5, p. 298, 1959.Kolff, et al.: T. Amer. Soc. Art. Int. Org., Vol. 8, p. 135, 1962.</p><p>Akutsu, et al.: Amer. Heart J., Vol. 59, p.731, 1960.</p><p>Kantrowitz: T. Amer. Soc. Art. Int. Org., Vol. 6, p. 292, 1960.</p><p>Tsuchiya, K. et al., Artificial heart controlled by fluid amplification, Proc. I.F.A.C., Paper C7, 1968, London.</p><p>Ball, G. J., Fluidic control of automatic lung ventilators, M.Phil. thesis, University of London, 1968</p><p>Petrovick, M. L.: 'On the nature of fluid amplifiers and the oral cavity', Trans. I.S.A., Vol. 7, p. 130, 1968.</p><p>Anju K, First Successful Computer Simulation of Flow in Fluidic Windshield Washer Nozzle Shows Potential to Reduce Design Time 50%, Journal Articles by Fluent Software Users, JA084, 1999 &lt;[<seg type="URL" n="http://www.fluent.com/solutions/articles/ja084.pdf"/>]> [December 2005]</p><p>J. N., No moving parts needed S.A.E. Journal, August, 1963</p><p>Kompass, E. J., Perspective on fluid amplifiers Control Engineering, September 1964</p><p>Gray, W. E., and Hans Stern Fluid amplifiers capabilities and applications Control Engineering, September 1964</p><p>Carriere, P., and Eichelbrenner, E. A., Theory of flow reattachment by a tangential jet discharging against a strong adverse pressure gradient, Boundary layer and flow control (G. V. Lachmann, ed.), I, 209-231, London, 1961</p></div1><div1 type="back text"><head rend="bold">Glossary</head><p><hi rend="bold">Turbulent Flow:</hi> see section 3.1.</p><p><hi rend="bold">Vortices</hi> are rotational flows present within turbulent fluids</p><p><hi rend="bold">Cavitation</hi> is the generation of bubbles which instantaneously release large amounts of energy when the bubble collapses.</p><p><hi rend="bold">Laminar Flow</hi>: see section 3.1.</p><p><hi rend="bold">Real Flow</hi> is the flow that actually exists, for which any calculation is approximate and is often simplified to make calculations less complicated.</p><p><hi rend="bold">Ideal Flow</hi> is frictionless and incompressible. This can be a useful model for analysing large expanses of fluid for instance aeronautical or marine engineering.</p><p><hi rend="bold">Frictionless Fluid</hi> by its very nature is non-viscous and its processes are reversible. There is no such thing as frictionless fluid however, and this is used simply as a model for improved understanding of real flow.</p><p><hi rend="bold">Boundary Layer</hi> is that band of fluid between the vessel wall and the main fluid flow; the main fluid flow is considered independent of the shear or friction effects of the fluid passing over the vessel wall. The boundary layer is affected by these shear or friction effects. The fluid in direct contact with the vessel boundary has zero velocity relative to the boundary; the subsequent velocity gradient throughout the boundary layer is dependant upon the viscous shear. Boundary layers can be laminar or turbulent, and is dependant upon several functions <ref target="BAWE_0249d-ftnote.037"/></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0249d-ftnote.037"><p> Streeter, V.L., Fluid Mechanics, Fourth Edition, McGraw-Hill Book Company, 1966, page</p></note><list type="bulleted"><item>length,</item><item>viscosity,</item><item>velocity of the flow near them</item><item>boundary roughness. </item></list><p>All play a part in deciding whether the boundary layer is laminar, turbulent, or indeed at some stage in transformation between the two.</p><p><hi rend="bold">Adiabatic Flow</hi> is flow where there is no exchange of heat, neither to, nor from the fluid. When modelling frictionless flow, where processes are reversible, if the fluid is also adiabatic, it is said to be isentropic.</p><p><hi rend="bold">Steady Flow</hi> occurs when conditions at any point in the fluid do not change with time i.e. velocities at every point remain constant indefinitely.<hi rend="sup">37</hi></p><p><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0249d-form.012"/></p><p>The definition also implies there is no change in density, pressure or temperature</p><p><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0249d-form.013"/>, <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0249d-form.014"/>, <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0249d-form.015"/></p><p><hi rend="bold">Steady Turbulent Flow</hi> exists when the mean velocity throughout the fluid remains constant. Due to the turbulence there will of course be minor fluctuations, and so the temporal mean velocity is defined as:-</p><p><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0249d-form.016"/></p><p>Similarly, the same must be said of pressure, density, temperature etc, (substituting the v in the equation for the relevant descriptor, be it p, σ or t).</p><p><hi rend="bold">Unsteady Flow</hi> occurs when the conditions above, are not met.</p><p><hi rend="bold">Uniform Flow</hi> is common in pipe flow. It is defined by:-</p><p><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0249d-form.017"/></p><p>i.e. where the velocity vector at every point in the flow is equal and constant. This cannot occur in any real flow due to the boundary layer, but the definition is applied nonetheless, even though the velocity vector at the boundary is always zero. In this case, the more general definition is applied:</p><quote lang="English">"When all parallel cross sections through the conduit are identical and the average velocity at each cross section is the same at any given instant, the flow is said to be uniform."</quote><p>Again, flow that does not meet this condition is said to be non-uniform flow.</p><p><hi rend="bold">2-Dimensional Flow</hi> is a model that assumes within a 3d flow, that all particles must flow in parallel planes along identical paths in each of these planes, with no changes in flow normal to these planes. Analysis of this flow is considerably easier, and in the instance of CFD, minimises computational time. </p><p><hi rend="bold">3-Dimensional Flow</hi> is the flow that occurs most commonly due to turbulence and geometry of flow. Methods of analysis are generally complex mathematically, and only simple geometrical flow boundaries may be handled.</p><p>A <hi rend="bold">Streamline</hi> is a continuous line drawn through the fluid so that it has the direction of the velocity vector at every point. There can be no flow across a streamline.</p><p><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0249d-form.018"/></p><p>Regardless of nature of flows, all flows are subject to the following relationships:</p><p rend="ordered">Newton's laws of motion must hold for every particle at every instant</p><p rend="ordered">The continuity relationship, i.e. the law of conservation of mass</p><p rend="ordered">The first and second laws of thermodynamics</p><p rend="ordered">Boundary conditions, analytical statements that a real fluid has zero velocity relative to a boundary at a boundary or that ideal fluids cannot penetrate a boundary.</p><p><hi rend="bold">Reynolds Number:</hi> see section 3.3</p><p><hi rend="bold">Coanda Effect:</hi> see section 3.5</p><p><hi rend="bold">Venturi Effect:</hi> see section 3.6</p><p><hi rend="bold">Flow Control:</hi> see section 3.7</p></div1><div1 type="appendix"><head rend="bold">Figures</head><p/></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
