<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_0250g" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>~ Motor Vehicle Disc Brakes ~</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">The document has a title page which contains:
document title
title part</note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">Language used in quote: <foreign id="English">English</foreign></note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">deleted: header: module name and number, date; footer: student and page numbers</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">3</p><p n="date">2006-04</p><p n="module title">Design of Machines</p><p n="module code">ES22A</p><p n="genre family">Design specification</p><p n="discipline">Engineering</p><p n="disciplinary group">PS</p><p n="grade">D</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">2798</p><p n="number of s-units">129</p><p n="number of p">61</p><p n="number of tables">2</p><p n="number of figures">2</p><p n="number of block quotes">7</p><p n="number of formulae">19</p><p n="number of lists">3</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">19</p><p n="abstract present">abstract present</p><p n="average words per s-unit">21.7</p><p n="average s-units per p">2.1</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">m</p><p n="year of birth">1985</p><p n="first language">English</p><p n="education">UKA</p><p n="course">Engineering</p><p n="student ID">0250</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><docTitle><titlePart><hi rend="bold">Design of Machines - Option B</hi><hi rend="italic"> ~ Motor Vehicle Disc Brakes ~</hi></titlePart></docTitle><titlePart><name type="student name"/><name type="student ID"/> 3 <hi rend="sup">rd</hi> Yr. Mech. Engineer</titlePart></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="abstract"><head rend="bold">Summary</head><p n="p1.61"><s n="s1.2;p1.61">Adequate disc brake design is an important aspect of motor vehicle safety, contributing to the overall performance of a motor vehicle. </s><s n="s2.2;p1.61">This study investigates some of the theoretical design considerations of disc brakes, and aims to relate the theory to the practical design of motor vehicle disc brakes. </s></p><p n="p2.61"><s n="s1.2;p2.61">The theoretical optimisation of disc brakes is primarily associated with the geometry of the disc and pad assembly, along with the friction coefficient of the pad material. </s><s n="s2.2;p2.61">In terms of practical design, there are many considerations which are made for instance, optimising temperature dissipation during prolonged use, and minimising brake squeal. </s></p><p n="p3.61"><s n="s1.1;p3.61">By designing disc brakes practically, manufacturers are able to address issues which would not arise from theoretical design alone, which makes practical design vital, to ensure the optimal braking performance is achieved. </s></p></div1><div1 type="front-back-matter"><head rend="bold">Contents</head><p/></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">1.0 - Introduction</head><p n="p4.61"><s n="s1.5;p4.61">Motor vehicle braking systems are a critical component of a vehicles safety and as a result, rigorous research and development has aimed to optimise the braking performance of motor vehicles. </s><s n="s2.5;p4.61">The functional requirement of the vehicle braking system is to dissipate the kinetic energy of the vehicle into heat energy, in order to bring the vehicle to a controlled stop. </s><s n="s3.5;p4.61">The performance of the braking system can be expressed as the rate at which the retardation occurs, and it is this factor which braking system design aims to optimise. </s><s n="s4.5;p4.61">This study aims to investigate the design of motor vehicle disc brakes in terms of both the theoretical and practical design considerations. </s><s n="s5.5;p4.61">The principal objective of this study is to investigate the variables associated with the design of a disc brake, for a typical saloon car weighing 1000 kg. </s></p><div2><head rend="underlined">1.1 - Disc Brakes</head><p n="p5.61"><s n="s1.4;p5.61">Disc brakes are a type of friction brake in which the braking forces are generated by the pressure of a high friction brake pad, against the surface of a rotating disc, or brake rotor. </s><s n="s2.4;p5.61">There are two types of disc brake in use, namely fixed caliper and floating calliper disc brakes. </s><s n="s3.4;p5.61">Floating caliper disc brakes utilise a single piston which presses the brake pad against the rotating disc. </s><s n="s4.4;p5.61">The reaction force causes the caliper housing to shift to the right, pressing the remaining brake pad against the opposite face of the disc (see fig.1) </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0250g-pic.001"><head rend="bold italic">Fig.1 - Diagram of a Floating Caliper Disc Brake</head></figure><p n="p6.61"><s n="s1.6;p6.61">Upon release of the brake, piston seals with defined deformation properties retract the piston from the brake. </s><s n="s2.6;p6.61">The fixed caliper system however, uses a separate piston to actuate each brake pad on each face of the disc. </s><s n="s3.6;p6.61">Although the fixed caliper disc brake is the simplest in terms of manufacture, and is the stronger of the two types, the system has been eliminated by the floating caliper design, since many road vehicles are restricted by available space and the floating caliper system provides a compact alternative. </s><s n="s4.6;p6.61">In addition, the fixed caliper disc system is found to be sensitive to high temperatures caused by prolonged use, which can result in brake failure due to overheating brake fluid. </s><s n="s5.6;p6.61">The floating caliper system is found to be far less sensitive to high temperatures, and consequently, this type of brake failure is uncommon. </s><s n="s6.6;p6.61">As a result, the floating caliper system is most commonly applied to motor vehicles due to its compact dimensions, and reliability. </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">2.0 - Theoretical Design of Disc Brakes</head><p n="p7.61"><s n="s1.2;p7.61">The braking effect which is produced by disc brakes occurs as a result of a friction material being compressed against the surfaces of the disc (rotor). </s><s n="s2.2;p7.61">The typical contact area of a brake pad is shown below in figure 2: </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0250g-pic.002"><head rend="bold italic">Fig.2 - Typical Geometry of Disc and Pad Assembly</head></figure><p n="p8.61"><s n="s1.2;p8.61">Since the friction material of the brake pads suffers wear during braking, the extent of this wear can be quantified. the frontal area of the brake pad experiences pressure caused by the actuating piston. </s><s n="s2.2;p8.61">The work done by this force on the brake pad can be expressed as: </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p9.61"><s n="s1.2;p9.61"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0250g-form.001"/><hi rend="bold italic">~Eqn. </hi></s><s rend="bold italic" n="s2.2;p9.61">1 </s></p><list type="simple"><head>Where f <hi rend="sub">s</hi> = Sliding coefficient of friction</head><item> P = Pressure</item><item> A = Area</item><item> S = Displacement</item></list><p n="p10.61"><s n="s1.1;p10.61">The displacement can be substituted by the product of velocity and time to give the following: </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p11.61"><s n="s1.2;p11.61"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0250g-form.002"/><hi rend="bold italic">~Eqn. </hi></s><s rend="bold italic" n="s2.2;p11.61">2 </s></p><p n="p12.61"><s n="s1.2;p12.61">As a result of the work done by the brake pad, a finite volume of material will be eroded. </s><s n="s2.2;p12.61">The volume of material will be proportional to the amount of work done, which gives the following expression: </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p13.61"><s n="s1.2;p13.61"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0250g-form.003"/><hi rend="bold italic">~Eqn. </hi></s><s rend="bold italic" n="s2.2;p13.61">3 </s></p><p n="p14.61"><s n="s1.1;p14.61">or </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p15.61"><s rend="bold italic" n="s1.2;p15.61"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0250g-form.004"/> ~Eqn. </s><s rend="bold italic" n="s2.2;p15.61">4 </s></p><list type="simple"><head>Where w=linear wear</head><item> K=proportionality factor</item></list><p n="p16.61"><s n="s1.2;p16.61">By cancelling the area in the above equation (Eqn. </s><s n="s2.2;p16.61">4), the expression for linear wear can be derived as: </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p17.61"><s n="s1.2;p17.61"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0250g-form.005"/><hi rend="bold italic">~Eqn. </hi></s><s rend="bold italic" n="s2.2;p17.61">5 </s></p><p n="p18.61"><s n="s1.1;p18.61">The linear wear on the brake will depend on certain environmental factors such as temperature and also other motion factors such as the loading, and the speed of the vehicle. equation 5 can be modified to account for these factors to give: </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p19.61"><s n="s1.2;p19.61"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0250g-form.006"/><hi rend="bold italic">~Eqn. </hi></s><s rend="bold italic" n="s2.2;p19.61">6 </s></p><list type="simple"><head>Where f <hi rend="sub">1</hi> = modifying factor for motion type, speed and loading</head><item> f <hi rend="sub">2</hi> = modifying factor to account for the environment</item></list><p n="p20.61"><s n="s1.2;p20.61">Using figure 2, an expression can be derived for the actuating force of the disc along with the friction torque. </s><s n="s2.2;p20.61">If the local contact pressure on the disc is p, the actuating force and friction torque are given by: </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p21.61"><s n="s1.2;p21.61"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0250g-form.007"/><hi rend="bold italic">~Eqn. </hi></s><s rend="bold italic" n="s2.2;p21.61">7 </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p22.61"><s n="s1.2;p22.61"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0250g-form.008"/><hi rend="bold italic">~Eqn. </hi></s><s rend="bold italic" n="s2.2;p22.61">8 </s></p><p n="p23.61"><s n="s1.2;p23.61">From equation 6, the axial wear is the same everywhere only when the product PV remains constant. </s><s n="s2.2;p23.61">By substituting the pressure for the maximum allowable pressure, pa, which occurs at the inner radius, the above equations can be modified to give expressions for the actuating force and friction torque for the uniform wear condition: </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p24.61"><s n="s1.2;p24.61"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0250g-form.009"/><hi rend="bold italic">~Eqn. </hi></s><s rend="bold italic" n="s2.2;p24.61">9 </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p25.61"><s n="s1.2;p25.61"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0250g-form.010"/><hi rend="bold italic">~Eqn. </hi></s><s rend="bold italic" n="s2.2;p25.61">10 </s></p><p n="p26.61"><s n="s1.3;p26.61">From equations 9 and 10, it is evident that the actuating force of a disc brake depends upon the angle with which the pad subtends, along with the radius of the inner and outer pad. </s><s n="s2.3;p26.61">In order to design a disc brake system for a typical saloon car, the properties of the car must be defined. </s><s n="s3.3;p26.61">Below is a typical layout of the variables involved with designing a brake system for a saloon car: </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0250g-pic.003"><head rend="bold italic">Fig.3 - Typical Variables involved in brake design for a typical saloon car</head></figure><p n="p27.61"><s n="s1.1;p27.61">In a typical braking situation, the car would decelerate with an acceleration given by, a ms <hi rend="sup">-1</hi>. using the above dimensions, and by taking moments about the point Q, the reaction force of each front wheel R <hi rend="sub">f</hi> can be derived as follows: </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p28.61"><s n="s1.2;p28.61"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0250g-form.011"/><hi rend="bold italic">~Eqn. </hi></s><s rend="bold italic" n="s2.2;p28.61">11 </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p29.61"><s n="s1.2;p29.61"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0250g-form.012"/><hi rend="bold italic">~Eqn. </hi></s><s rend="bold italic" n="s2.2;p29.61">12 </s></p><p n="p30.61"><s n="s1.2;p30.61">Under braking, the maximum braking force depends on the level of friction between the tyres and the road surface, and also the reaction force of each wheel. </s><s n="s2.2;p30.61">The total braking force can therefore be given as: </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p31.61"><s n="s1.2;p31.61"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0250g-form.013"/><hi rend="bold italic">~Eqn. </hi></s><s rend="bold italic" n="s2.2;p31.61">13 </s></p><p n="p32.61"><s n="s1.1;p32.61">The maximum deceleration of the vehicle can also be expressed in terms of the friction coefficient, since: </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p33.61"><s n="s1.2;p33.61"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0250g-form.014"/><hi rend="bold italic">~Eqn. </hi></s><s rend="bold italic" n="s2.2;p33.61">14 </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p34.61"><s n="s1.2;p34.61"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0250g-form.015"/><hi rend="bold italic">~Eqn. </hi></s><s rend="bold italic" n="s2.2;p34.61">15 </s></p><p n="p35.61"><s n="s1.2;p35.61">By substituting the expression for the reaction force (Eqn. </s><s n="s2.2;p35.61">12) into equation 13, along with the expression for maximum deceleration, the final expression for the maximum braking force at the front wheel can be given by the following: </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p36.61"><s n="s1.2;p36.61"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0250g-form.016"/><hi rend="bold italic">~Eqn. </hi></s><s rend="bold italic" n="s2.2;p36.61">16 </s></p><p n="p37.61"><s n="s1.1;p37.61">In terms of the braking torque, the above expression can also be modified to include the radius of the wheel, to yield the following expression: </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p38.61"><s n="s1.2;p38.61"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0250g-form.017"/><hi rend="bold italic">~Eqn. </hi></s><s rend="bold italic" n="s2.2;p38.61">17 </s></p><p n="p39.61"><s n="s1.2;p39.61">The above expression indicates that the braking torque depends upon the friction between the tyres and the road surface, along with the dimensional characteristics of the vehicle. </s><s n="s2.2;p39.61">In the case of the saloon car shown in figure 3, the torque depends upon the mass, the radius of the wheel, the distance between the front and rear wheels, and the height of the centre of mass. </s></p><p n="p40.61"><s n="s1.2;p40.61">In order to theoretically design a disc brake system for a saloon car, the properties of the vehicle must be quantified. </s><s n="s2.2;p40.61">Table 1 indicates typical parameters for the saloon car in figure 3: </s></p><table id="BAWE_0250g-tab.001"><head rend="bold italic">Table 1 - Typical Parameters for a Saloon Car</head><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p41.61"><s n="s1.1;p41.61">By substituting the vehicle parameters into equation 17, and including a typical coefficient of friction of 0.7, the torque requirement can be approximated as follows: </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p42.61"><s n="s1.2;p42.61"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0250g-form.018"/><hi rend="bold italic">~Eqn. </hi></s><s rend="bold italic" n="s2.2;p42.61">18 </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p43.61"><s n="s1.2;p43.61"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0250g-form.019"/><hi rend="bold italic">~Eqn. </hi></s><s rend="bold italic" n="s2.2;p43.61">19 </s></p><p n="p44.61"><s n="s1.2;p44.61">The above expression indicates that for maximum braking, the torque requirement is approximately 750Nm. </s><s n="s2.2;p44.61">This provides a value of torque which, using equation 8 can be designed by selecting suitable brake pad geometry and friction materials. </s></p><p n="p45.61"><s n="s1.2;p45.61">There are a number of material choices for the pad material, with varying properties. </s><s n="s2.2;p45.61">A selection of pad materials is shown below in table 2: </s></p><table id="BAWE_0250g-tab.002"><head rend="bold italic">Table 2 - A Selection of Properties for Typical Brake Pad Materials</head><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p46.61"><s n="s1.5;p46.61">In order to maximise the torque provided by the disc brake, the material should be selected with the greatest coefficient of friction. </s><s n="s2.5;p46.61">As the above indicates, the rigid moulded asbestos and non-asbestos material types offer the greatest coefficients of friction. </s><s n="s3.5;p46.61">In addition the two materials also withstand a high degree of temperature, which is important in order to prevent the brake from distorting. </s><s n="s4.5;p46.61">However, Asbestos dust is harmful, and despite offering excellent properties, due to safety implications it would not be suitable for the application. </s><s n="s5.5;p46.61">For the purpose of the saloon car shown in figure 3, the ideal material would be a rigid moulded non-asbestos pad. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">3.0 - Practical Design of Disc Brakes</head><p n="p47.61"><s n="s1.1;p47.61">Theoretical disc brake design can vary greatly from practical design, since the braking performance which can be achieved is not only dependant on the brake pad material and geometry, but there are many other considerations which are made in practical design, such as problems associated with manufacture, the type of usage and the durability of the brake pads. </s></p><p n="p48.61"><s n="s1.1;p48.61">In order to maintain the braking performance at a variety of operating conditions, practical brake design is aimed at three basic requirements: </s></p><p n="p49.61"><s n="s1.1;p49.61">Adequate thermal absorption and dissipation </s></p><p n="p50.61"><s n="s1.1;p50.61">Sufficient air flow over the brakes to dissipate the heat generated during braking and, </s></p><p n="p51.61"><s n="s1.1;p51.61">The brake pads must maintain their frictional properties throughout an extended temperature range. </s></p><p n="p52.61"><s n="s1.3;p52.61">The performance of a particular arrangement of disc and pad must remain insensitive to high temperatures which may reach up to 700C during prolonged use. </s><s n="s2.3;p52.61">In practical design, manufacturers favour ventilated discs as opposed to solid brake discs (see fig.4). </s><s n="s3.3;p52.61">Due to the greater mass of the ventilated disc, the amount of heat which can be absorbed is increased, while the internal cooling channels allow for rapid cooling. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0250g-pic.004"><head rend="bold italic">Figure 4 - Photograph of Solid and Vented Disc Rotors </head></figure><p n="p53.61"><s n="s1.7;p53.61">Disc brake rotors are often machined with grooves as shown above in figure 4, to improve cooling across the face of the disc, and also as a solution to glazing. </s><s n="s2.7;p53.61">Due to excessive heat under braking, the contact of the pad with the disc can cause the glazing affect, seriously affecting the performance. </s><s n="s3.7;p53.61">The grooved design scrapes the surface of the brake pad, and removes any glazing as a result of excessive heat. </s><s n="s4.7;p53.61">In addition to optimal cooling and reduced glazing, the surface finish of the disc rotor is an important practical design consideration. </s><s n="s5.7;p53.61">The surface finish of disc rotors varies from each manufacturer, with some choosing a non-directional swirl finish, and others opting for a smooth cut finish. </s><s n="s6.7;p53.61">Lathing at excessive cut and feed rates can cause microscopic furrows of metal on the surface of the disc. </s><s n="s7.7;p53.61">Under braking, these furrows can become embedded in the brake pad, causing metal to metal contact. </s></p><p n="p54.61"><s n="s1.2;p54.61">This manufacturing problem can affect the performance of the brakes, and is partly responsible for brake squeal. </s><s n="s2.2;p54.61">As a result, practical design favours a non-directional cut, which minimises the onset of furrows developing. </s></p><p n="p55.61"><s n="s1.4;p55.61">Another requirement of motor vehicle disc brakes is the ability to minimise brake noise. </s><s n="s2.4;p55.61">This is often caused by the edges of brake pads engaging the rotor, causing chatter, or by corrosion of the steel backing plates of the brake pads. </s><s n="s3.4;p55.61">Manufactures such as BOSCH, fabricate brake pads, to include powder coating of the steel backing plates, which inhibits corrosion. </s><s n="s4.4;p55.61">The pads are often fabricated with chamfered edges and slotted surfaces which aim to allow the pads to engage smoothly, while the slotted surface provides an escape route for hot gases under harsh braking. </s></p><div2><head rend="underlined">3.1 - Manufacturers' Design Considerations</head><p n="p56.61"><s n="s1.3;p56.61">Practical design of disc brakes depends primarily on experience. </s><s n="s2.3;p56.61">There are a number of problems, which must be considered during usage which cannot be understood by theory alone. </s><s n="s3.3;p56.61">The following pages provide further information supplied by two manufacturers (BAER and AKEBONO) which indicate some of their own design optimisations, which contribute to the basic requirements of disc brakes. </s></p><div3><head rend="underlined">3.1.1 - BAER Brake Systems</head><figure id="BAWE_0250g-pic.005"/><p n="p57.61"/></div3><div3><head rend="underlined">3.1.2 - Akebono Caliper Design</head><quote lang="English">Akebono recognizes every caliper must be harmonized with its brake pad materials to optimize performance. Our unique product development approach ensures the caliper design is in tune with each vehicle application. This careful attention to detail guarantees the caliper is integrated with other brake system components to optimize pedal feel and NVH performance, as well as maximize caliper performance over the life of the vehicle.</quote><figure id="BAWE_0250g-pic.006"/><quote lang="English">For example, we carefully match the piston seal rollback and caliper stiffness to the friction material's characteristics. We also design the brake pad shape specifically to reduce noise, and match the pad area and volume with power absorption to meet or exceed lining life requirements. Other Akebono caliper technology innovations include our fully sealed caliper slide mechanism and corrosion-protected pad slides. We design the caliper's sealed two-piece pins for minimal taper wear and reduced drag. This improves lining life and helps reduce judder and noise. The pins are greased and sealed for life. During relining, a pin's pinch bolts can be removed without contaminating the slide mechanism. The clearance pin's large bushing prevents housing rattle and our pin design that overhangs the rotor eliminates the need for outboard housing support.</quote><figure id="BAWE_0250g-pic.007"><head>Cut Away Drawing of Akebono Caliper Guidance Pin</head></figure><quote lang="English">Akebono's caliper slide mechanism uses a close-fit, metal-to-metal guide system that is spring loaded between the pads and anchor bracket to prevent pad rattle. No spring load exists on the caliper body. The brake pad slides in female guide slots which provide consistent contact points for reaction loads. Stainless steel pad springs line the abutment contact area and maintain low pad slide load in a corrosive environment.</quote><figure id="BAWE_0250g-pic.008"><head>Akebono Caliper Pad Slide Loads</head></figure><quote lang="English">Our caliper pad retraction springs are v-springs that separate the pads and keep them in contact with caliper fingers and pistons. This design reduces residual drag and can be applied to sliding or opposed piston calipers.</quote><figure id="BAWE_0250g-pic.009"><head>Akebono Caliper Pad Retraction Springs</head></figure><quote lang="English">During design and development, Akebono tests calipers for leakage, fluid displacement, deflection, noise, strength and endurance. We are the only company in the industry that tests 100 percent of all our calipers in production for residual drag. To the customer, this means minimal brake pulsation and optimized pedal feel.<hi rend="bold"> NVH SOLUTIONS</hi> Akebono's world-class brake R&amp;D and manufacturing capabilities deliver customized brake noise, vibration and harshness (NVH) solutions for our customers. Extensive NVH testing and analysis capabilities produce disc pads and drum brake linings featuring outstanding noise control and longer life.<hi rend="bold"> ROTOR KINDNESS</hi> Akebono's innovative friction materials are less abrasive to rotors than any others in the market. The result? A decrease in disc thickness variation, resulting in minimal roughness. We also increase rotor life by reducing the amount of high-hardness raw materials. In addition, our friction material generates much less wheel dust.</quote><figure id="BAWE_0250g-fig.001"/><quote lang="English"><hi rend="bold">FRICTION (µ) STABILITY</hi> The difference in µ between a normal stop and panic stop with Akebono's technology is typically less than 10 percent compared with our competition, who may lose 30 percent or more. This means predictable, safe performance when it is needed most.</quote><figure id="BAWE_0250g-fig.002"/><quote lang="English"><hi rend="bold">SYSTEM APPROACH</hi> Akebono knows friction materials play an integral role in a vehicle's braking system. We apply a total system approach to designing and manufacturing our friction products, carefully analyzing their interaction with a vehicle's brake calipers and rotors. Optimum performance of brake disc pads and linings involves a complex interaction of raw material components combined with an exact production process to maximize braking consistency.</quote><p n="p58.61"/></div3></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">4.0 - Conclusions</head><p n="p59.61"><s n="s1.3;p59.61">This report provides an indication of the variables associated with the design of disc brakes, using a theoretical approach. </s><s n="s2.3;p59.61">Disc brake performance has shown to be dependant upon the geometry of the disc and pads, and the friction coefficient between the pad material and the rotor. </s><s n="s3.3;p59.61">Using a specification for a typical saloon car, weighing 1000kg, the maximum braking torque was established to be approximately 750Nm for the front wheel. </s></p><p n="p60.61"><s n="s1.1;p60.61">A number of material choices were selected for the brake pads, and based on the relevant material properties; a rigid moulded non-asbestos pad was selected as the optimal material. </s></p><p n="p61.61"><s n="s1.4;p61.61">Theoretical Design was found to vary greatly with the practical design performed by brake manufacturers. </s><s n="s2.4;p61.61">There are many problems associated with braking systems which can only be addressed through experience and experimentation. </s><s n="s3.4;p61.61">Practical design considerations vary greatly from maintaining optimal temperature dissipation and minimising brake squeal, to optimising the manufacturing techniques. </s><s n="s4.4;p61.61">Using manufacturer's information, this report has provided a comparison between the theoretical design and practical design of motor vehicle disc brakes. </s></p></div1></body><back><div1 type="bibliography"><head rend="bold">References and Bibliography</head><p>ES388 - Design of Machines Lecture Notes</p><p>Chapter 8, Brake Design, J. Rakels</p><p>Newton, "The Motor Vehicle", Eleventh Edition, Chapter 31.8 - Disc Brakes, pp.694-698</p><p>Wong, "Theory of Ground Vehicles", Third Edition, Chapter 3.7 - Braking Performance, pp.265-275</p><p>ImportCar Magazine, "Causes and Cures for Disc Brake Problems", October 2005 - <seg type="URL" n="http://www.forparts.com/ICdiscbrakeproblems10.05.htm"/></p><p>Akebono Brake Corporation, North America - "Brake Design Information"</p><p>Farmington Hills MI 48331 USA</p><p>BAER Brake Systems, USA - "Brake Design Information"</p><p>Phoenix AZ 85017 USA</p><p>BOSCH Brake Systems - "Technical Instruction Pamphlet", 1994, pp.1-16</p></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
