<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_0250b" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Assignment 1: Instrumentation</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">deleted: header: student name and number, assignment title, date; footer: module and page numbers
</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">2</p><p n="date">2005-01</p><p n="module title">Design of Measurement Systems</p><p n="module code">ES21Q</p><p n="genre family">Design specification</p><p n="discipline">Engineering</p><p n="disciplinary group">PS</p><p n="grade">M</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">2871</p><p n="number of s-units">170</p><p n="number of p">100</p><p n="number of tables">3</p><p n="number of figures">5</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">18</p><p n="number of lists">2</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">33</p><p n="abstract present">abstract present</p><p n="average words per s-unit">16.9</p><p n="average s-units per p">1.7</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">m</p><p n="year of birth">1985</p><p n="first language">English</p><p n="education">UKA</p><p n="course">Engineering</p><p n="student ID">0250</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><docTitle><titlePart>Assignment 1 - Instrumentation</titlePart></docTitle></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="abstract"><head rend="underlined bold">Summary</head><p n="p1.100"><s n="s1.4;p1.100">The principle objective of this report is to design and build a cantilever beam-type force sensor, to measure an output voltage in terms of a loading force. </s><s n="s2.4;p1.100">A cantilever rig is used, incorporating two active strain gauges. </s><s n="s3.4;p1.100">When the resistance of the gauges changes under load, a Wheatstone bridge circuit is utilised to convert this resistance change into a voltage. </s><s n="s4.4;p1.100">Finally a non-inverting operational amplifier circuit is introduced to the system to amplify the bridge voltage to a degree which can be digitised and analysed. </s></p><p n="p2.100"><s n="s1.1;p2.100">The output voltage is found to follow an approximate linear relationship with the input load, and the designed system offers a sensitivity value of 12.5 V/N. </s></p><p n="p3.100"><s n="s1.2;p3.100">It is believed that the sensitivity of the system could be improved by upgrading the gauge material at an extra cost, or by increasing the number of active gauges in the bridge circuit. </s><s n="s2.2;p3.100">This reduces one of the biggest sources of error caused by resistance changes due to temperature fluctuations in the bridge. </s></p></div1><div1 type="front-back-matter"><head rend="underlined bold">Contents</head><p/></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">Introduction</head><p n="p4.100"><s n="s1.2;p4.100">The purpose of this report is to design and construct a beam-type instrument for force measurement. </s><s n="s2.2;p4.100">The design of the instrument is based upon a ready made cantilever rig, incorporating two strain gauges. </s></p><p n="p5.100"><s n="s1.2;p5.100">The strain variation in the beam under the action of a force alters the resistance of the gauges, which is measured by a wheatstone bridge circuit. </s><s n="s2.2;p5.100">The relatively small output voltage from the bridge circuit requires amplification, in order for that signal to be processed, or displayed. </s></p><p n="p6.100"><s n="s1.1;p6.100">After determining the sensitivity of the rig, along with the maximum allowed loading force, the principle objectives are to design a suitable wheatstone bridge circuit and an appropriate amplifier, to provide a suitable voltage level, with a gain of 100-1000, using a standard 741 operational amplifier. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">Theory</head><p n="p7.100"><s n="s1.1;p7.100">The cantilever rig used for force measurement is as follows: </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0250b-pic.001"><head rend="bold italic">~Fig. 1</head></figure><div2><head rend="underlined">Strain Gauges</head><p n="p8.100"><s n="s1.2;p8.100">A strain gauge is a type of semiconductor whose resistance changes under a strain. </s><s n="s2.2;p8.100">The fractional change in the gauge resistance caused by an induced strain is defined as the Gauge Factor, 'G', which represents the strain sensitivity, where: </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p9.100"><s n="s1.1;p9.100"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0250b-form.001"/> </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p10.100"><s rend="bold italic" n="s1.2;p10.100"> ~Eqn. </s><s rend="bold italic" n="s2.2;p10.100">1 </s></p><p n="p11.100"><s n="s1.1;p11.100">In most strain gauges, the gauge factor ranges between 2 and 4. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">Wheatstone Bridge Circuits</head><p n="p12.100"><s n="s1.4;p12.100">The purpose of the bridge circuit is to convert a change in resistance to a voltage. </s><s n="s2.4;p12.100">A variety of circuits exist, but since the strain gauges are used to measure force measurement, the most common arrangement of bridge circuit, is one using 2 active strain gauges. </s><s n="s3.4;p12.100">When the cantilever beam is subjected to a load, each gauge experiences either a tensile or compressive stress depending on the surface which it is attached to. </s><s n="s4.4;p12.100">This typical arrangement is shown below: </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0250b-fig.001"><head rend="bold italic">~Fig. 2</head></figure><p n="p13.100"><s n="s1.1;p13.100">The bridge circuit shown in figure 2, is used in the test rig, but with the addition of a potentiometer across terminals B and D. This allows the bridge circuit to be zeroed before any readings are taken. </s></p><p n="p14.100"><s n="s1.1;p14.100">In this circuit, for the bridge to be balanced, it is expected that: </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p15.100"><s n="s1.1;p15.100"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0250b-form.002"/> </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p16.100"><s rend="bold italic" n="s1.2;p16.100">~Eqn. </s><s rend="bold italic" n="s2.2;p16.100">2 </s></p><p n="p17.100"><s n="s1.1;p17.100">Where R <hi rend="sub">1</hi> and R <hi rend="sub">2</hi> are active strain gauges. </s></p><p n="p18.100"><s n="s1.1;p18.100">If a force now acts on the strain gauges, the resistances R <hi rend="sub">1</hi> and R <hi rend="sub">2</hi>, will become R <hi rend="sub">1</hi>+ΔR, and R <hi rend="sub">2</hi>- ΔR. In this case, the bridge output voltage can be calculated by: </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p19.100"><s n="s1.1;p19.100"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0250b-form.003"/> </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p20.100"><s rend="bold italic" n="s1.2;p20.100">~Eqn. </s><s rend="bold italic" n="s2.2;p20.100">3 </s></p><p n="p21.100"><s n="s1.1;p21.100">For the purpose of simplicity, the bridge circuit can be designed with R <hi rend="sub">1</hi>=R <hi rend="sub">2</hi>=R <hi rend="sub">3</hi>=R <hi rend="sub">4</hi>=R <hi rend="sub">5</hi> and so eqn.3 is simplified to: </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p22.100"><s n="s1.1;p22.100"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0250b-form.004"/> </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p23.100"><s rend="bold italic" n="s1.2;p23.100">~Eqn. </s><s rend="bold italic" n="s2.2;p23.100">4 </s></p><p n="p24.100"><s n="s1.1;p24.100">This gives the bridge circuit output voltage, in terms of the change in gauge resistance, and supply voltage. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">Cantilever Beam Arrangement</head><p n="p25.100"><s n="s1.1;p25.100">The cantilever beam used in the laboratory is set up in the following way: </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0250b-pic.002"><head rend="bold italic">~Fig. 3</head></figure><p n="p26.100"><s n="s1.3;p26.100">When the cantilever is loaded by a force 'F'. </s><s n="s2.3;p26.100">The gauges experience a strain in accordance with Hooke's Law. </s><s n="s3.3;p26.100">This strain is given by: </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p27.100"><s n="s1.1;p27.100"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0250b-form.005"/> </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p28.100"><s rend="bold italic" n="s1.2;p28.100">~Eqn. </s><s rend="bold italic" n="s2.2;p28.100">5 </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">Operational Amplifiers</head><p n="p29.100"><s n="s1.3;p29.100">Since the output from the bridge circuit is very small, an operational amplifier has to be incorporated into the rig, to amplify this voltage to an appropriate level. </s><s n="s2.3;p29.100">In order to reach the appropriate voltage level, an amplifier must be designed with a gain of 100-1000. </s><s n="s3.3;p29.100">Using a 741 operational amplifier, there are two possible configurations: </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0250b-pic.003"><head rend="bold italic">~Fig. 4</head></figure><p n="p30.100"><s n="s1.1;p30.100">For the purpose of voltage amplification, the non-inverting operational amplifier is the ideal choice, for its very high input impedance (~10 <hi rend="sup">13 </hi>Ω), which lowers the input currents, and causes the circuit to behave more like an ideal operational amplifier. </s></p><p n="p31.100"><s n="s1.2;p31.100">The non-inverting amplifier also has a higher gain in comparison to the inverting amplifier. </s><s n="s2.2;p31.100">This gain is given by: </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p32.100"><s n="s1.1;p32.100"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0250b-form.006"/> </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p33.100"><s rend="bold italic" n="s1.2;p33.100">~Eqn. </s><s rend="bold italic" n="s2.2;p33.100">6 </s></p><p n="p34.100"><s n="s1.2;p34.100">In order to achieve the target gain of 1000, this circuit requires that R1 = 999R2. </s><s n="s2.2;p34.100">Using standard resistors, an ideal choice for each resistor is as follows: </s></p><p n="p35.100"><s n="s1.1;p35.100"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0250b-form.007"/> </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">Static Characteristics of Measuring Equipment</head><p n="p36.100"><s n="s1.2;p36.100">Static characteristics are the relationships between output and input of an instrument, which is either constant or changing slowly. </s><s n="s2.2;p36.100">As well as being characterised by standard terms such as accuracy and range, the force sensor is also characterised by sensitivity and resolution. </s></p><p n="p37.100"><s n="s1.1;p37.100">Sensitivity is a measure of the change in an output which occurs when the input changes by a given amount: </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p38.100"><s n="s1.1;p38.100"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0250b-form.008"/> </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p39.100"><s rend="bold italic" n="s1.2;p39.100">~Eqn. </s><s rend="bold italic" n="s2.2;p39.100">7 </s></p><p n="p40.100"><s n="s1.1;p40.100">Where y = change in output, and x = change in input. </s></p><p n="p41.100"><s n="s1.2;p41.100">The instrument may also be characterised by its <hi rend="italic">Resolution</hi>, which is the smallest change in the input which can be registered by the instrument. </s><s n="s2.2;p41.100">All of the static characteristics of a measurement system contribute to the accuracy and reliability of the system. </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">Apparatus and Methods</head><p n="p42.100"><s n="s1.1;p42.100">The following equipment is required for the chosen method of force measurement: </s></p><list type="bulleted"><item>Cantilever Rig - Analogue Experimental Transducer (see fig.1 page 3)</item><item>Standard Ruler - Millimetre Increments</item><item>A Set of Washers - Each Weighing 0.25g</item><item>9V Battery</item><item>DC Power Supply</item><item>Digital Voltmeter</item><item>Oscilloscope</item><item>Bread Board</item><item>741 Operational Amplifier</item><item>Capacitors</item><item>Resistors</item><item>Microsoft Excel Computer Program - For Graph Construction</item><item>Labview Computer Software - For Data Acquisition</item><item>Data Acquisition Card - 6023E (12-bits A/D)</item></list><p n="p43.100"><s n="s1.1;p43.100">Below is an account of the method taken to construct, test and calibrate the beam-type force sensor. </s></p><div2><head rend="underlined">Cantilever Rig Measurements</head><p rend="ordered" n="p44.100"><s n="s1.3;p44.100">The steel cantilever must be measured, along with the position of the strain gauges. </s><s n="s2.3;p44.100">The measurements taken are those illustrated in <hi rend="italic">figure 3, page 6.</hi> </s><s n="s3.3;p44.100">The accuracy of these values is limited by the choice of measuring instrument. </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p45.100"><s n="s1.3;p45.100">The strain produced at the gauges is calculated in terms of the force applied. </s><s n="s2.3;p45.100">This is given by <hi rend="italic">equation 5 page 6</hi>. </s><s n="s3.3;p45.100">The Young's Modulus of the steel is given to be 210GPa. </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p46.100"><s n="s1.1;p46.100">The range of the force sensor is determined by Hooke's Law, with the given fatigue strength of the steel being 540Mpa. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">Design of Wheatstone Bridge Circuit</head><p rend="ordered" n="p47.100"><s n="s1.2;p47.100">The strain gauges are assumed to be identical, and have a nominal gauge resistance of 1000Ω. </s><s n="s2.2;p47.100">The gauge factor is given as G=2.1 and a standard 9V battery is provided as the Bridge power supply. </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p48.100"><s n="s1.1;p48.100">The theoretical balance condition is derived using <hi rend="italic">equation 2 page 5.</hi> </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p49.100"><s n="s1.2;p49.100">With the balance condition known, the remaining bridge resistances can be selected. </s><s n="s2.2;p49.100">It should be noted that the balance condition is only theoretical due to temperature fluctuations in the system. </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p50.100"><s n="s1.1;p50.100">A potentiometer is incorporated in the bridge, to zero the system. </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p51.100"><s n="s1.1;p51.100">The relationship between the bridge output and the resistance change of the gauges can then be calculated from <hi rend="italic">Equation 4 page 5.</hi> </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">Design of Non-Inverting Amplifier</head><p rend="ordered" n="p52.100"><s n="s1.1;p52.100">Once the type of amplifier is selected, the feedback resistances are chosen to provide the required gain as in <hi rend="italic">Equation 6 page 7.</hi> </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p53.100"><s n="s1.3;p53.100">The amplifier is tested prior to connection of the bridge circuit, by connecting the amplifier to the oscilloscope. </s><s n="s2.3;p53.100">The high gain of the non-inverting amplifier results in a considerable amount of noise present in the signal which is displayed (~50Hz). </s><s n="s3.3;p53.100">It is to be noted that the noise present is a source of error in the measurements. </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p54.100"><s n="s1.2;p54.100">Due to the induced noise, a low pass filter is constructed by connecting a capacitor across R <hi rend="sub">1</hi> in the amplifiers feedback loop. </s><s n="s2.2;p54.100">By assuming that RC=0.1 seconds, a capacitor of 100nF is chosen to reduce the noise produced at low frequencies. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">Test and Calibration of Force Sensor System</head><p rend="ordered" n="p55.100"><s n="s1.1;p55.100">The entire system is constructed and through the use of the potentiometer of the bridge, an initial zero condition is achieved. </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p56.100"><s n="s1.2;p56.100">One washer at a time is added to the end of the cantilever, and the output of the amplifier is recorded. </s><s n="s2.2;p56.100">Note also that the output fluctuates as the cantilever oscillates at the instant the load is applied, before settling. </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p57.100"><s n="s1.2;p57.100">The collected data can then be plotted on a graph using MatLab, and a linear fit of the data can be analysed. </s><s n="s2.2;p57.100">This allows the sensitivity of the system to be calculated. </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p58.100"><s n="s1.2;p58.100">The force sensor can finally be connected to the data acquisition software, which converts the analogue signal to digital. </s><s n="s2.2;p58.100">Tests can be made to determine the dynamic behaviour of the cantilever, such as the stabilising time, and resonant frequency of the system. </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">Observations and Results</head><p n="p59.100"><s n="s1.1;p59.100">The geometrical dimensions of the cantilever, as shown in <hi rend="italic">figure 3 page 6</hi>, are measured as follows: </s></p><table id="BAWE_0250b-tab.001"><head rend="bold italic">~Table. 1</head><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p60.100"><s n="s1.1;p60.100">Using the given value of Young's Modulus (210GPa) and the <hi rend="italic">equation 5, from page 6</hi>, the strain produced is calculated in terms of the force applied as: </s></p><p n="p61.100"><s n="s1.1;p61.100"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0250b-form.009"/> </s></p><p n="p62.100"><s n="s1.1;p62.100">Using the above expression, and the given fatigue strength (540MPa), the maximum loading force is given by: </s></p><p n="p63.100"><s n="s1.1;p63.100"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0250b-form.010"/> </s></p><p n="p64.100"><s n="s1.1;p64.100"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0250b-form.011"/> </s></p><p n="p65.100"><s n="s1.3;p65.100">For the construction of the bridge circuit, the theoretical balance condition has already been discussed in <hi rend="italic">equation 2 page 5</hi>. the resistors chosen for the bridge are both 1000Ω. </s><s n="s2.3;p65.100">This balance condition is only theoretical due to fluctuations in temperature which will occur as the bridge circuit is in operation. </s><s n="s3.3;p65.100">Any increase in temperature will affect the resistance of the bridge. </s></p><p n="p66.100"><s n="s1.4;p66.100">In order to test the designed amplifier circuit, it is connected to the oscilloscope to analyse the output signal. </s><s n="s2.4;p66.100">The signal reveals a large amount of noise at low frequencies, which affects the accuracy of the reading. </s><s n="s3.4;p66.100">To remedy this, a low pass filter is constructed as detailed in the method section. </s><s n="s4.4;p66.100">This has the effect of reducing the noise to a more tolerable level. </s></p><p n="p67.100"><s n="s1.4;p67.100">As each washer is added to the cantilever rig, the resulting output voltage is measured. </s><s n="s2.4;p67.100">The output voltage is observed to fluctuate as each washer is added, due to the beam oscillating. </s><s n="s3.4;p67.100">The cantilever is allowed a few moments to come to rest before the voltage reading is taken. </s><s n="s4.4;p67.100">The following table shows the results: </s></p><table id="BAWE_0250b-tab.002"><head rend="bold italic">~Table. 2</head><row><cell/></row></table></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">Analysis of Results</head><p n="p68.100"><s n="s1.3;p68.100">With the numerical data obtained in the previous section, an analysis can be made to assess the linear range and sensitivity of the system. </s><s n="s2.3;p68.100">In order to do so, the output data is plotted vs. the loading force. </s><s n="s3.3;p68.100">This is shown graphically below: </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0250b-fig.002"><head><hi rend="underlined">System Output vs Loading Force</hi><hi rend="bold italic">~Graph. 1</hi></head></figure><p n="p69.100"><s n="s1.2;p69.100">From the linear fitting of the data in <hi rend="italic">graph.1</hi>, the data is shown to follow an approximate straight line. </s><s n="s2.2;p69.100">From this linear fit, the following deductions can be made: Using <hi rend="italic">equation 7 page 8</hi>, the sensitivity of this system can be determined, as: </s></p><p n="p70.100"><s n="s1.1;p70.100"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0250b-form.012"/> </s></p><p n="p71.100"><s n="s1.1;p71.100">This figure signifies that a change in load of 1N, results in an output fluctuation of 12.5V. </s></p><p n="p72.100"><s n="s1.1;p72.100">The linear trend shown provides an overall equation for output voltage against loading force, and is given by: </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p73.100"><s n="s1.1;p73.100"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0250b-form.013"/> </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p74.100"><s rend="bold italic" n="s1.2;p74.100">~Eqn. </s><s rend="bold italic" n="s2.2;p74.100">8 </s></p><p n="p75.100"><s rend="italic" n="s1.1;p75.100">Where x = the load applied in Newton's </s></p><p n="p76.100"><s n="s1.1;p76.100">The accuracy of this equation is best demonstrated by comparing the obtained values with the actual values: </s></p><table id="BAWE_0250b-tab.003"><head rend="bold italic">~Table. 3</head><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p77.100"><s n="s1.1;p77.100">Table 3 confirms that <hi rend="italic">equation 8</hi> above is a reliable model for the output voltage and by taking into account the sources of error in the method, the overall uncertainty in <hi rend="italic">equation 8</hi> is approximately, +/- 0.03V </s></p><p n="p78.100"><s n="s1.3;p78.100">Since the output from the force measurement system is analogue, by digitising the signal, further analyses can be made. </s><s n="s2.3;p78.100">This is achieved by connecting the output from the amplifier to a 12-bit A/D converter (6023E). </s><s n="s3.3;p78.100">The digital signal is then displayed using the LabView computer program. </s></p><p n="p79.100"><s n="s1.2;p79.100">The program is setup to analyse the signal at a sample rate of 1000/s, with 1000 samples taken. </s><s n="s2.2;p79.100">The following graphs demonstrate the affect of the capacitor in reducing the noise in the signal: </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0250b-fig.003"><head><hi rend="underlined">Demonstration of noise present with no low-pass filter</hi><hi rend="bold italic">~Graph. 2</hi></head></figure><figure id="BAWE_0250b-fig.004"><head><hi rend="underlined">Demonstration of noise present with a low-pass filter</hi><hi rend="bold italic">~Graph. 3</hi></head></figure><p n="p80.100"><s n="s1.3;p80.100">Evidently by comparison of <hi rend="italic">graph 3,</hi> and <hi rend="italic"> graph 2,</hi> the low pass filter has the effect of dramatically reducing the amount of noise, and therefore improves the reliability of the instrument. </s><s n="s2.3;p80.100">An analysis of the dynamic behaviour is analysed using LabView, by tapping the end of the cantilever prior to sampling, and determining the time taken for it to stabilise. </s><s n="s3.3;p80.100">The following figures show this graphically: </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0250b-fig.005"><head rend="bold italic">~Graph. 4</head></figure><p n="p81.100"><s n="s1.2;p81.100">After the initial disturbance, <hi rend="italic">graph 4</hi> shows the number of oscillations occurring before the system stabilises. </s><s n="s2.2;p81.100">From this graph it is evident that approximately 20 oscillations occur every second, signifying that the system has a resonant frequency of 20Hz. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">Discussion</head><p n="p82.100"><s n="s1.1;p82.100">The results obtained illustrate that the force measurement system which has been designed, offers an approximate linear trend in the output voltage, in response to a load. </s></p><p n="p83.100"><s n="s1.1;p83.100">The resulting output voltage has been shown to follow an approximate linear trend, given by <hi rend="italic">equation 8 page 14</hi>. </s></p><p n="p84.100"><s n="s1.3;p84.100">Although the results are satisfactory, there could be improvements made to the method in order to reduce the uncertainty. </s><s n="s2.3;p84.100">The ambient temperature for example has not been considered in this report, but may affect the accuracy of the results. </s><s n="s3.3;p84.100">The thermal expansion of a material follows the equation: </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p85.100"><s n="s1.1;p85.100"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0250b-form.014"/> </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p86.100"><s rend="bold italic" n="s1.2;p86.100">~Eqn. </s><s rend="bold italic" n="s2.2;p86.100">9 </s></p><list type="simple"><head rend="italic">Where </head><item><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0250b-form.015"/></item><item><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0250b-form.016"/></item><item><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0250b-form.017"/></item></list><p n="p87.100"><s n="s1.2;p87.100">Therefore, if it is assumed that Lo = the length calculated in <hi rend="italic">figure 3 page 6</hi>, then for each degree change in temperature, the length of the cantilever is expected to increase by only 1.628x10 <hi rend="sup">-6</hi>m. </s><s n="s2.2;p87.100">Considering this very small increase in length, it is believed that the resultant effect on the strain produced and the maximum loading force will be negligible. </s></p><p n="p88.100"><s n="s1.4;p88.100">In order to design the bridge circuit, a theoretical balance condition is used to determine the resistances in the bridge. </s><s n="s2.4;p88.100">However, these resistances are expected to change as the temperature of the system rises. </s><s n="s3.4;p88.100">An effort could be made to turn the circuit on for only a short period of time to reduce the heating effect, and therefore improve accuracy. </s><s n="s4.4;p88.100">The amount of noise in the signal also has an affect on the accuracy of the data, but the inclusion of a low pass filter, in the amplifier circuit is sufficient to reduce the noise to a tolerable level. </s></p><p n="p89.100"><s n="s1.3;p89.100">A big factor in the errors calculated occurs from the measurements made of the geometrical dimensions of the cantilever. </s><s n="s2.3;p89.100">Since only a standard rule was used, the precision of the method was very poor. </s><s n="s3.3;p89.100">If a set of Vernier Callipers had been used, and perhaps a Micrometer for the thickness measurement, the error in dimension measurement could be reduced, which would have an effect on the overall accuracy of the force sensor. </s></p><p n="p90.100"><s n="s1.3;p90.100">The sensitivity of the system could be improved even further by increasing the number of gauges. </s><s n="s2.3;p90.100">For instance, if 2 gauges had been used for each side of the cantilever, then all four resistances in the bridge would be replaced, and this would have the effect of increasing the sensitivity by a factor of two. </s><s n="s3.3;p90.100">This arrangement also compensates any variation caused by temperature, axial and Torsional components. </s></p><p n="p91.100"><s n="s1.3;p91.100">The sensitivity of the system is dependant primarily on the sensitivity of the actual gauges. </s><s n="s2.3;p91.100">By changing the material of the strain gauges, for example to Platinum-Tungsten, the gauge factor would be increased from 2.1-4.0. </s><s n="s3.3;p91.100">However, despite the improvement in sensitivity, the relative cost of a platinum gauge would be far too excessive for this type of instrument. </s></p><p n="p92.100"><s n="s1.2;p92.100">The resolution is also responsible for reliability in the results. </s><s n="s2.2;p92.100">The bit-rate of the A/D converter limits the resolution of the device, and so by increasing the bit-rate the resolution could be improved, so a smaller change in the input can be registered by the program. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">Conclusions</head><p n="p93.100"><s n="s1.1;p93.100">The results obtained illustrate that the force measurement system which has been designed, offers an approximate linear trend in the output voltage to the input load, and is given by the equation: </s></p><p n="p94.100"><s n="s1.1;p94.100"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0250b-form.018"/> </s></p><p n="p95.100"><s n="s1.1;p95.100">The sensitivity of the system is calculated to be <hi rend="bold">12.5V/N</hi>, signifying that a change in load of 1 Newton will result in an output voltage fluctuation of 12.5 volts. </s></p><p n="p96.100"><s n="s1.1;p96.100">The force measurement system is found to have a resonant frequency of approximately <hi rend="bold">20Hz</hi>. </s></p><p n="p97.100"><s n="s1.1;p97.100">There are many factors which are affecting the uncertainty in the results obtained, such as noise, temperature fluctuation, and gauge sensitivity. </s></p><p n="p98.100"><s n="s1.1;p98.100">The effects of fluctuations in ambient temperature are shown to be negligible in their affect on the force measurement, due to the only small temperature change which is expected. </s></p><p n="p99.100"><s n="s1.2;p99.100">It is believed that the strain gauge material could be upgraded to improve the gauge sensitivity, but the cost of such an improvement would not be economically viable. </s><s n="s2.2;p99.100">The number of active gauges in the bridge circuit could also be increased to four, as this arrangement is believed to compensate for any variation caused by temperature, axial and Torsional components. </s></p><p n="p100.100"><s n="s1.1;p100.100">The choice of method used to measure the geometrical dimensions of the cantilever is an enormous factor in the errors, and could easily be reduced by replacing standard rulers for Vernier scales and micrometers. </s></p></div1></body><back><div1 type="bibliography"><head rend="underlined bold">References and Bibliography</head><p>Design of Measurement Systems Lecture Notes, Part I and II - Dr X. Ping Liu</p><p><seg type="URL" n="http://www.saburchill.com/tech/adobe/002.pdf"/> - </p><p>Operational Amplifier Selection - David Hoult 2001</p><p><seg type="URL" n="http://hibp.ecse.rpi.edu/~connor/education/Exp4.ppt"/> - </p><p>Op-Amp Analysis - Unknown Author</p><p>University of <name type="university"/> Engineering Data Book - Cantilever Beams</p></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
