<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_0250a" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Assignment 2: Design of a Torque Sensor</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">The document has a title page which contains:
document title
title part</note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">deleted: header: student name, module name and number, date; footer: student, module and page numbers</note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">appendices: reproductions of data from source materials</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">2</p><p n="date">2005-03</p><p n="module title">Design of Measurement Systems</p><p n="module code">ES21Q</p><p n="genre family">Design specification</p><p n="discipline">Engineering</p><p n="disciplinary group">PS</p><p n="grade">M</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">3318</p><p n="number of s-units">202</p><p n="number of p">102</p><p n="number of tables">0</p><p n="number of figures">5</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">36</p><p n="number of lists">5</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">14</p><p n="abstract present">abstract present</p><p n="average words per s-unit">16.4</p><p n="average s-units per p">2.0</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">m</p><p n="year of birth">1985</p><p n="first language">English</p><p n="education">UKA</p><p n="course">Engineering</p><p n="student ID">0250</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><titlePart>Design of Measurement Systems Assignment 2 - Design and Evaluation</titlePart><docTitle><titlePart rend="underlined bold">Design of a Torque Sensor</titlePart></docTitle></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="abstract"><head rend="underlined bold">Summary</head><p n="p1.102"><s n="s1.6;p1.102">The purpose of this report is to design a system which is instrumented to give an automatic measurement of the torsion applied to a hollow steel shaft. </s><s n="s2.6;p1.102">The design incorporates four active gauges, in a full Wheatstone bridge arrangement. </s><s n="s3.6;p1.102">The applied torque provides a bridge output voltage which is proportional to the input torque. </s><s n="s4.6;p1.102">For the purpose of data acquisition, and presentation, the relatively small bridge voltage is amplified by an instrumentation amplifier, designed with a gain of 1000. </s><s n="s5.6;p1.102">A low pass filter is also introduced to reduce the high frequency noise present in the output signal. </s><s n="s6.6;p1.102">The bridge output voltage is related to the input torque by the following expression: </s></p><p n="p2.102"><s n="s1.1;p2.102"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0250a-form.001"/> </s></p><p n="p3.102"><s n="s1.1;p3.102">The torque cell is capable of measuring a maximum torsional load of approximately 2634Nm, and is designed to reject the effects of axial and bending forces, as well as the effect of temperature fluctuations on the gauge resistance. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">Design Brief</head><p n="p4.102"><s n="s1.1;p4.102">The purpose of this report is to design a suitable system for measuring the torque which is applied to a hollow steel shaft, as shown in figure 1. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0250a-pic.001"><head rend="bold italic">Fig. 1</head></figure><p n="p5.102"><s n="s1.2;p5.102">The torque can be applied to the shaft by adding weights to the steel bar attached to the free end of the hollow section. </s><s n="s2.2;p5.102">The principal objective is to design a system which allows the rig to be instrumented to give an automatic measurement of the torque, based on a strain gauge arrangement. </s></p><p n="p6.102"><s n="s1.2;p6.102">The system is to be designed to provide an output signal, which is representative of the input torque. </s><s n="s2.2;p6.102">The measurement system should be made insensitive to temperature changes, and other loading effects, such as axial/bending forces, and provide a means for calibration along with some form of data presentation. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">Initial Concepts</head><p n="p7.102"><s n="s1.1;p7.102">The basic concept behind the proposed measurement system is shown diagrammatically below: </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0250a-fig.001"><head rend="bold italic">Fig. 2</head></figure><p n="p8.102"><s n="s1.3;p8.102">As the torque is applied, one or more strain gauges located on the shaft, will deform under stress, and this deformation will cause the gauge resistance to change. </s><s n="s2.3;p8.102">By incorporating the gauges into a bridge circuit, this change in resistance can be converted into a voltage. </s><s n="s3.3;p8.102">Since the bridge output voltage will be relatively minute, a suitable operational amplifier circuit can be included to amplify the output voltage to a level which allows the signal to be presented, or processed further. </s></p><p n="p9.102"><s n="s1.2;p9.102">With the basic concept described above, there are numerous considerations which can be made in order to provide the most effective measurement system. </s><s n="s2.2;p9.102">The design considerations are explained in the following pages. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">Design Considerations</head><p n="p10.102"><s n="s1.2;p10.102">The following is a number of factors which must be considered, with respect to the initial concept described above. </s><s n="s2.2;p10.102">These factors should provide the most effective measurement system, based around the brief principles discussed. </s></p><list type="bulleted"><item>Type of strain gauge used</item><item>Number of gauges</item><item>Bridge Circuit Type / Design</item><item>Arrangement of gauges on shaft to ensure optimal performance</item><item>Optimisation of measurement characteristics - Sensitivity, Range etc...</item><item>Inclusion of system to ensure the sensor is insensitive to other loading affects, and Temperature fluctuations</item><item>Amplification method</item><item>Minimisation of signal noise</item><item>System calibration method</item><item>Data presentation method</item></list><div2><head rend="underlined">Strain Gauge / Bridge Circuit Selection</head><p n="p11.102"><s n="s1.8;p11.102">The type of strain gauge, and the number to be used, depends on the influence that this choice has on the requirements of the system. </s><s n="s2.8;p11.102">The sensitivity of the system for example, will be directly related to the Gauge factor of the gauges used. </s><s n="s3.8;p11.102">The gauge factor determines the amount of change in resistance caused by a change in strain, and in most cases lies between 2 and 4. </s><s n="s4.8;p11.102">The strain gauge(s) must also have a minimal temperature coefficient, to reduce the effects of temperature fluctuations, along with a low linear expansion. </s><s n="s5.8;p11.102">The majority of commercially available strain gauges have a gauge factor of around 2, and considering the required application, a gauge of this factor will be sufficient without incurring excess costs. </s><s n="s6.8;p11.102">In this design, a bonded foil strain gauge will be selected, for its availability, and adequate performance. </s><s n="s7.8;p11.102">The foil strain gauge to be used has a wide operating range, and a considerably low linear expansion. </s><s n="s8.8;p11.102">Further details of the characteristics of this gauge can be found in appendix A. </s></p><p n="p12.102"><s n="s1.4;p12.102">The number of gauges which are chosen for the design is important as it will dictate the type of bridge circuit to be used. </s><s n="s2.4;p12.102">Upon selecting the number of gauges, considerations must also be made to ensure that the gauges can be located on the shaft in a way which ensures that they sense the maximum Torsional stresses. </s><s n="s3.4;p12.102">With respect to the bridge circuit, it is expected that four active gauges will provide the optimal choice. </s><s n="s4.4;p12.102">The four gauge bridge circuit diagram is shown in figure 3 below: </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0250a-pic.002"><head rend="bold italic">Fig. 3</head></figure><p n="p13.102"><s n="s1.1;p13.102">In this situation, if it is expected that two gauges will respond to a positive strain and two will respond to a negative strain, the gauge resistances will change as follows: </s></p><p n="p14.102"><s n="s1.1;p14.102"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0250a-form.002"/> </s></p><p n="p15.102"><s n="s1.1;p15.102"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0250a-form.003"/> </s></p><p n="p16.102"><s n="s1.1;p16.102"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0250a-form.004"/> </s></p><p n="p17.102"><s n="s1.1;p17.102"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0250a-form.005"/> </s></p><p n="p18.102"><s n="s1.1;p18.102">Therefore, the bridge output voltage can be given by: </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p19.102"><s n="s1.2;p19.102"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0250a-form.006"/><hi rend="bold italic">Eqn. </hi></s><s rend="bold italic" n="s2.2;p19.102">1 </s></p><p n="p20.102"><s n="s1.1;p20.102">Since the gauge resistances are identical (120Ω (see appendix A)), equation 1 can be written as follows: </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p21.102"><s n="s1.2;p21.102"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0250a-form.007"/><hi rend="bold italic">Eqn. </hi></s><s rend="bold italic" n="s2.2;p21.102">2 </s></p><p n="p22.102"><s n="s1.7;p22.102">In this arrangement, the total strain experienced will be four times that experienced by a single gauge. </s><s n="s2.7;p22.102">Therefore the output voltage will be four times larger, and the sensitivity of the system will be improved. </s><s n="s3.7;p22.102">The sensitivity of the bridge is also dependant on the supply voltage to the bridge (V <hi rend="sub">s</hi>). </s><s n="s4.7;p22.102">Since all four gauges are mounted on the same material, any changes in temperature will affect all the gauges in the same way. </s><s n="s5.7;p22.102">Because any temperature change will be common, the ratio of the gauge resistances will be unchanged, and so the bridge output will not change. </s><s n="s6.7;p22.102">This full bridge is the best method to achieve temperature compensation. </s><s n="s7.7;p22.102">In the same way, this bridge circuit compensates any variation caused by axial and bending forces. </s></p><p n="p23.102"><s n="s1.2;p23.102">Included in figure 3, is a simple potential divider placed across the outputs of the circuit. </s><s n="s2.2;p23.102">The inclusion of this device allows the output to be adjusted to zero when there is no torque applied to the shaft, thereby contributing to the device accuracy. </s></p><p n="p24.102"><s n="s1.1;p24.102">With the bridge circuit determined, the position of the gauges on the shaft must now be considered to ensure that the maximum strain can be sensed. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">Strain Gauge Arrangement</head><p n="p25.102"><s n="s1.1;p25.102">For a circular shaft, which is subjected to pure torsion, it is found that the directions of principal stresses and strain follow two 45 Helices, as shown in figure 4: </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0250a-pic.003"><head rend="bold italic">Fig. 4</head></figure><p n="p26.102"><s n="s1.3;p26.102">Therefore, in order to achieve optimal sensing capability, the strain gauges should be located on the lines of principal stresses/strains. </s><s n="s2.3;p26.102">This ensures that each gauge will experience 100% of the tensile/compressive strain applied to the shaft. </s><s n="s3.3;p26.102">The optimal arrangement of strain gauges is shown diagrammatically in figure 5: </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0250a-pic.004"><head rend="bold italic">Fig. 5</head></figure><p n="p27.102"><s n="s1.4;p27.102">In this arrangement, strain gauge 1 is located where the tensile strain has the maximum value of +ε. </s><s n="s2.4;p27.102">Similarly, gauge 2 is mounted on the second helix, where the compressive strain has the maximum value of - ε. </s><s n="s3.4;p27.102">Gauges 3 and 4 are mounted on the opposite side of the shaft, and will experience the same magnitude of strain. </s><s n="s4.4;p27.102">Therefore, gauge 1 and 3 will sense a positive strain, and gauges 2 and 4 will sense a negative strain, when a torque is applied. </s></p><p n="p28.102"><s n="s1.2;p28.102">The design brief indicates that the system must provide a means of data presentation. </s><s n="s2.2;p28.102">In order for the output signal to be processed, the minute bridge output must be amplified, to a suitable level. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">Amplification Method</head><p n="p29.102"><s n="s1.4;p29.102">For simplicity in the design, the use of operational amplifiers is ideal, for cost effectiveness, and availability. </s><s n="s2.4;p29.102">Since operational amplifiers have considerably high open loop gain, a very strong negative feedback can be provided. </s><s n="s3.4;p29.102">The addition of negative feedback acts to stabilise the signal, whilst reducing distortion. </s><s n="s4.4;p29.102">Since it is the difference between the two bridge outputs which must be amplified, one suitable option is to incorporate a differential amplifier, shown in figure 6 below: </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0250a-fig.002"><head rend="bold italic">Fig. 6</head></figure><p n="p30.102"><s n="s1.1;p30.102">The typical gain that can be produced by the differential amplifier shown in figure 6 is expressed by the following equation: </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p31.102"><s n="s1.2;p31.102"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0250a-form.008"/><hi rend="bold italic">Eqn. </hi></s><s rend="bold italic" n="s2.2;p31.102">3 </s></p><p n="p32.102"><s n="s1.3;p32.102">Therefore, by selecting standard resistors for R1 and R2, the required gain can easily be achieved. </s><s n="s2.3;p32.102">For the purpose of data processing and presentation, a suitable amplifier gain would be 1000. </s><s n="s3.3;p32.102">On this basis, the following resistors can be chosen: </s></p><p n="p33.102"><s n="s1.1;p33.102"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0250a-form.009"/> </s></p><p n="p34.102"><s n="s1.4;p34.102">However, the differential amplifier in figure 6 is limited, because it has relatively low input impedance, and there is a common mode gain produced by the inputs, which would also produce an output signal. </s><s n="s2.4;p34.102">This amplifier alone would therefore be unsuitable for amplification of the bridge outputs. </s><s n="s3.4;p34.102">In order to remove the limitations of the differential amplifier, it is possible to add two buffer amplifiers to the circuit, shown below in figure 7. </s><s n="s4.4;p34.102">This configuration is commonly known as an instrumentation amplifier: </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0250a-fig.003"><head rend="bold italic">Fig. 7</head></figure><p n="p35.102"><s n="s1.5;p35.102">The two voltage followers, shown above, buffer the input signals, to create near-ideal input conditions, such as high input impedance (10 <hi rend="sup">10</hi>Ω), and low input currents. </s><s n="s2.5;p35.102">In addition to the instrumentation amplifier, the resistor R <hi rend="sub">1</hi> is included, which acts to zero the output, and prevent a zero shift. </s><s n="s3.5;p35.102">The instrumentation amplifier is ideal for rejecting the common mode noise in the input signals, whilst accurately amplifying the bridge outputs. </s><s n="s4.5;p35.102">The gain produced by the circuit depends on the resistor ratios, R <hi rend="sub">4</hi>/R <hi rend="sub">2</hi>, and R <hi rend="sub">5</hi>/R <hi rend="sub">3</hi>. </s><s n="s5.5;p35.102">Therefore, to produce a gain of 1000, the following resistors may be selected: </s></p><list type="simple"><item>R <hi rend="sub">2</hi> = 1KΩ</item><item>R <hi rend="sub">3</hi> = 1KΩ</item><item>R <hi rend="sub">4</hi> = 1MΩ</item><item>R <hi rend="sub">5</hi> = 1MΩ</item></list><p n="p36.102"><s n="s1.1;p36.102">Further information regarding the instrumentation amplifier in figure 7 can be found in appendix B. </s></p><p n="p37.102"><s n="s1.4;p37.102">Due to the nature of the amplification method, it is expected that the output signal will contain some degree of high frequency noise. </s><s n="s2.4;p37.102">The noise present in the signal, will have a detrimental affect on the output signal, and so will reduce accuracy in the data presentation. </s><s n="s3.4;p37.102">To eliminate the noise in the signal, the amplifier output can be passed through an active low pass filter. </s><s n="s4.4;p37.102">A suitable low pass filter circuit diagram is shown below in figure 8: </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0250a-fig.004"><head rend="bold italic">Fig. 8</head></figure><p n="p38.102"><s n="s1.1;p38.102">As shown above, the active filter is designed with a cut off frequency of 100Hz, and a Gain of 1. </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">Analysis of Measurement System</head><p n="p39.102"><s n="s1.1;p39.102">In order for the devised system to be used practically, an understanding of the relationship between the inputs and outputs of the system must be achieved. </s></p><p n="p40.102"><s n="s1.1;p40.102">The St. Venant Torsion expression for a round shaft gives the following: </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p41.102"><s n="s1.2;p41.102"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0250a-form.010"/><hi rend="bold italic">Eqn. </hi></s><s rend="bold italic" n="s2.2;p41.102">4 </s></p><list type="simple"><head rend="italic">Where T=Torque</head><item rend="italic"> J=Polar Second Moment of Area</item><item rend="italic"> G=Shear Modulus</item><item rend="italic"> r=Radius</item><item rend="italic">θ=Angle of Twist</item><item rend="italic">τ=Shear Stress</item></list><p n="p42.102"><s n="s1.1;p42.102">Rearranging equation 4 in terms of the shear stress gives the following: </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p43.102"><s n="s1.2;p43.102"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0250a-form.011"/><hi rend="bold italic">Eqn. </hi></s><s rend="bold italic" n="s2.2;p43.102">5 </s></p><p n="p44.102"><s n="s1.1;p44.102">For a hollow circular section, the polar second moment of area (J) is expressed by: </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p45.102"><s n="s1.2;p45.102"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0250a-form.012"/><hi rend="bold italic">Eqn. </hi></s><s rend="bold italic" n="s2.2;p45.102">6 </s></p><p n="p46.102"><s n="s1.1;p46.102">Therefore, the maximum shear stress applied to the hollow shaft can be given by substituting equation 6 into equation 5, to give the following: </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p47.102"><s n="s1.2;p47.102"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0250a-form.013"/><hi rend="bold italic">Eqn. </hi></s><s rend="bold italic" n="s2.2;p47.102">7 </s></p><p n="p48.102"><s n="s1.2;p48.102">By substituting the dimensional characteristics of the shaft (see page 3), into equation 7, the shear stress can be expressed in terms of the torque alone. </s><s n="s2.2;p48.102">This expression is shown below: </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p49.102"><s n="s1.2;p49.102"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0250a-form.014"/><hi rend="bold italic">Eqn. </hi></s><s rend="bold italic" n="s2.2;p49.102">8 </s></p><p n="p50.102"><s n="s1.1;p50.102">Where <hi rend="bold">C = 1851177</hi> (Constant defined by geometric properties of the shaft). </s></p><p n="p51.102"><s n="s1.3;p51.102">The principal strain, ε<hi rend="sub">1</hi> which is found along the helical lines shown in figure 5 (page 8) is also related to the shear stress. </s><s n="s2.3;p51.102">By substituting equation 8 into this relationship, the principal strain can be expressed in terms of the torque, Poisson ratio and the Young's Modulus of the shaft material. </s><s n="s3.3;p51.102">This expression is shown below: </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p52.102"><s n="s1.2;p52.102"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0250a-form.015"/><hi rend="bold italic">Eqn. </hi></s><s rend="bold italic" n="s2.2;p52.102">9 </s></p><p n="p53.102"><s rend="bold" n="s1.1;p53.102">Where C=1851177 </s></p><p n="p54.102"><s n="s1.2;p54.102">In the above analysis, it is evident that the sensitivity of the torque cell is dependant upon the Poisson ratio, along with the young's modulus of the material. </s><s n="s2.2;p54.102">In the design specification, the shaft used is described as steel, which offers the following properties: </s></p><list type="simple"><item>E <hi rend="sub">Steel</hi> = 210GPa</item><item>v <hi rend="sub">Steel</hi> = 0.292</item></list><p n="p55.102"><s n="s1.4;p55.102">When any of the four strain gauges on the shaft are subjected to a force, the gauge itself undergoes an extension in length, and the cross section is reduced. </s><s n="s2.4;p55.102">The effect of this deformation, acts to alter the gauge resistance. </s><s n="s3.4;p55.102">The sensitivity of the gauges is expressed as the percentage change in resistance which occurs under a given strain. </s><s n="s4.4;p55.102">This is expressed algebraically below: </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p56.102"><s n="s1.2;p56.102"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0250a-form.016"/><hi rend="bold italic">Eqn. </hi></s><s rend="bold italic" n="s2.2;p56.102">10 </s></p><list type="simple"><head rend="italic">Where Ro = initial gauge resistance </head><item rend="italic">ε1 = Strain</item><item rend="italic"> G = Gauge factor (sensitivity)</item></list><p n="p57.102"><s n="s1.1;p57.102">The gauge factor, and initial resistance can be found in appendix A. By substituting these values into equation 10, along with the expression for strain given in equation 9, an overall expression for the relationship between torque and resistance change can be derived: </s></p><p n="p58.102"><s n="s1.1;p58.102">From Appendix A, <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0250a-form.017"/> </s></p><p n="p59.102"><s n="s1.1;p59.102"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0250a-form.018"/> </s></p><p n="p60.102"><s n="s1.1;p60.102"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0250a-form.019"/> </s></p><p n="p61.102"><s n="s1.1;p61.102"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0250a-form.020"/> </s></p><p n="p62.102"><s n="s1.1;p62.102"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0250a-form.021"/> </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p63.102"><s n="s1.2;p63.102"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0250a-form.022"/><hi rend="bold italic">Eqn. </hi></s><s rend="bold italic" n="s2.2;p63.102">11 </s></p><p n="p64.102"><s rend="bold" n="s1.1;p64.102">Where C=1851177 </s></p><p n="p65.102"><s n="s1.2;p65.102">Finally, an expression can be derived, relating the bridge output voltage, to the input torque. </s><s n="s2.2;p65.102">From equation 2 (page 6), the bridge circuit is modelled by: </s></p><p n="p66.102"><s n="s1.1;p66.102"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0250a-form.023"/> </s></p><p n="p67.102"><s n="s1.1;p67.102">From equation 11 (page 11), the change in gauge resistance can be substituted into this equation, along with the parameter R, to give an expression relating the bridge output to the input torque: </s></p><p n="p68.102"><s n="s1.1;p68.102"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0250a-form.024"/>, </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p69.102"><s n="s1.2;p69.102"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0250a-form.025"/><hi rend="bold italic">Eqn. </hi></s><s rend="bold italic" n="s2.2;p69.102">12 </s></p><p n="p70.102"><s rend="bold" n="s1.1;p70.102">Where C=1851177 </s></p><p n="p71.102"><s n="s1.1;p71.102">The design brief indicates that the shaft is made from steel, and so values of the Poisson ratio and young's modulus can be entered into the above equation, which yields the following: </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p72.102"><s n="s1.2;p72.102"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0250a-form.026"/><hi rend="bold italic">Eqn. </hi></s><s rend="bold italic" n="s2.2;p72.102">13 </s></p><p n="p73.102"><s n="s1.1;p73.102">If can also be assumed that the bridge circuit will be supplied by a simple 9V battery, and so the bridge output is related to the input torque by the following expression: </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p74.102"><s n="s1.2;p74.102"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0250a-form.027"/><hi rend="bold italic">Eqn. </hi></s><s rend="bold italic" n="s2.2;p74.102">14 </s></p><p n="p75.102"><s n="s1.2;p75.102">It is now evident from equation 14, that the bridge output voltage will be considerably small with respect to the torque. </s><s n="s2.2;p75.102">However, the amplifier circuit designed on page 9 will amplify this output voltage by a factor of approximately 1000, and thus allowing the signal to be processed further. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">Final System</head><p n="p76.102"><s n="s1.1;p76.102">In summary of all the design considerations made in pages 5 through 10, the complete system diagram can be constructed as follows: </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0250a-fig.005"/></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">Discussion and Evaluation</head><p n="p77.102"><s n="s1.5;p77.102">In order for the system to be used for measuring torque, it must be possible to calibrate the system, and for the output signal to be presented by a suitable media. </s><s n="s2.5;p77.102">For this purpose, digitisation of the output signal is ideal, as it allows the signal to be displayed, and/or processed, by a computer. </s><s n="s3.5;p77.102">This method involves using a data-acquisition system, consisting of an analogue-digital card, connected to a PC. After digitising the signal, a software program such as Labview (By National Instruments®), can be used to display the test data. </s><s n="s4.5;p77.102">The advantage of using a computer for data acquisition, allows further processing to be made more simply. </s><s n="s5.5;p77.102">The output signal can be related to the torque variable using equation 14, and the data can easily be presented by any means from a simple pointer-scale indicator to a LED or LCD display. </s></p><p n="p78.102"><s n="s1.4;p78.102">In order to calibrate the measurement system, a known input torque can be applied to the shaft, to confirm the relationship between the input torque and the output voltage. </s><s n="s2.4;p78.102">The torque can be applied by placing standard weights to the beam attached to the free end of the shaft. </s><s n="s3.4;p78.102">The strain gauge bridge circuit also includes a potential divider, which will allow the systems output to be zeroed, when no load is applied to the shaft. </s><s n="s4.4;p78.102">This eliminates the initial torque which is a result of the steel beam's own mass providing a torsional force on the shaft. </s></p><p n="p79.102"><s n="s1.3;p79.102">The measurement system is limited in its range of operation, primarily by the strain gauges used. </s><s n="s2.3;p79.102">The strain gauge specification provided in appendix A, indicates the maximum measurable strain lies between 3 and 4%. </s><s n="s3.3;p79.102">The principle strain has already been defined by equation 9, and is as follows: </s></p><p n="p80.102"><s n="s1.1;p80.102"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0250a-form.028"/> </s></p><p n="p81.102"><s n="s1.1;p81.102">Therefore, if the strain is limited to 3% (0.03), the maximum allowable torque can be expressed by the following: </s></p><p n="p82.102"><s n="s1.1;p82.102"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0250a-form.029"/> </s></p><p n="p83.102"><s n="s1.1;p83.102"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0250a-form.030"/> </s></p><p n="p84.102"><s n="s1.1;p84.102"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0250a-form.031"/> </s></p><p n="p85.102"><s n="s1.1;p85.102">The maximum strain which can be measured by the gauges corresponds to a maximum torque of 2634 Nm, which can be applied to the shaft. </s></p><p n="p86.102"><s n="s1.2;p86.102">This range of the torque cell's operation is also limited by the shaft geometry, particularly the inner and outer radii. </s><s n="s2.2;p86.102">By increasing the second moment of area of the section, the maximum allowable torque would also increase. </s></p><p n="p87.102"><s n="s1.3;p87.102">The designed system can easily be tested for linearity by measuring the output produced by two individual masses, and comparing this to the output provided by a weight with the combined mass of the two. </s><s n="s2.3;p87.102">The sum of the two readings should be equal to the reading of the combined mass. </s><s n="s3.3;p87.102">This test will confirm the quality of the system in delivering identical sensitivity throughout its measuring range. </s></p><p n="p88.102"><s n="s1.3;p88.102">As for the sensitivity of the system, this is dependant upon the shaft geometry, the shaft material, the gauge factor, and the Wheatstone bridge voltage (Vs). </s><s n="s2.3;p88.102">By simply changing the type of gauge, to platinum tungsten for instance, the gauge factor can easily be increased from 2 to 4, therefore doubling the sensitivity of the system. </s><s n="s3.3;p88.102">However, this modification would be expensive, and realistically, could only be implemented if cost effectiveness was not an issue. </s></p><p n="p89.102"><s n="s1.1;p89.102">The bridge output voltage has already been defined by the following expression: </s></p><p n="p90.102"><s n="s1.1;p90.102"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0250a-form.032"/> </s></p><p n="p91.102"><s n="s1.4;p91.102">Based on this expression, a shaft with a smaller Young's Modulus will create a greater voltage difference, for a given torque. </s><s n="s2.4;p91.102">Similarly, if the supply voltage to the bridge (currently set at 9V) was increased, the sensitivity of the system would also increase. </s><s n="s3.4;p91.102">Conversely, any increase in bridge voltage, may produce more heat, and hence the bridge will become more susceptible to temperature. </s><s n="s4.4;p91.102">Therefore the sensitivity of the system may be increased at the expense of accuracy. </s></p><p n="p92.102"><s n="s1.5;p92.102">The accuracy of the system depends primarily on the sensor's ability to be insensitive to other loading effects, such as axial forces and bending forces. </s><s n="s2.5;p92.102">Due to the method of applying the torque to the shaft, there will be a resultant bending force caused by the hanging weights. </s><s n="s3.5;p92.102">Similarly, temperature fluctuations affecting the gauge resistance will also act as a source of errors in the measurement. </s><s n="s4.5;p92.102">However, in the four gauge bridge, axial and bending forces are rejected because the effect of these loads is cancelled out by the gauges in adjacent arms of the bridge. </s><s n="s5.5;p92.102">Similarly in terms of temperature fluctuation, since all four gauges will experience the same temperature, the bridge remains balanced and the error is eliminated. </s></p><p n="p93.102"><s n="s1.1;p93.102">The overall system provides a linear relationship between the applied torque, and the bridge output voltage, and is expressed by the following equation: </s></p><p n="p94.102"><s n="s1.1;p94.102"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0250a-form.033"/> </s></p><p n="p95.102"><s n="s1.2;p95.102">For every Newton-Metre of torque applied, there is a bridge output voltage of 0.205mV produced. </s><s n="s2.2;p95.102">Therefore, there is an overall sensitivity of 0.205mV/Nm in the designed system. </s></p><p n="p96.102"><s n="s1.4;p96.102">The torque measurement system could be improved by upgrading some of the elements of the system, however upgrading these parts results in a decrease in cost efficiency. </s><s n="s2.4;p96.102">The gain of the amplifier circuit could be increased further to improve the signal to noise ratio, which will produce more reliable results. </s><s n="s3.4;p96.102">The type of strain gauge could be upgraded to a type offering a greater gauge factor, which would increase the sensitivity of the measurement system. </s><s n="s4.4;p96.102">In addition, the measurable strain of the gauges could be increased with different gauges, and hence the range of operation could be improved. </s></p><p n="p97.102"><s n="s1.1;p97.102">The bridge output is related to the input torque by the following equations: </s></p><p n="p98.102"><s n="s1.1;p98.102"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0250a-form.034"/> </s></p><p n="p99.102"><s n="s1.1;p99.102"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0250a-form.035"/> </s></p><p n="p100.102"><s n="s1.3;p100.102">The latter, indicates the system sensitivity, with respect to the design parameters which have been chosen. </s><s n="s2.3;p100.102">Therefore, it is possible to increase the sensitivity by reducing the Young's Modulus of the material, and increasing the Poisson ratio. </s><s n="s3.3;p100.102">However, the principal strain is also related to the torque by the following: </s></p><p n="p101.102"><s n="s1.1;p101.102"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0250a-form.036"/> </s></p><p n="p102.102"><s n="s1.2;p102.102">Therefore, if the Young's Modulus was reduced in order to increase the sensitivity, it would have a negative effect on the range of the torque cell, as the strain produced would be greater for a given torque, and the maximum torque would be limited. </s><s n="s2.2;p102.102">Depending on the requirements of the system, it is possible for the shaft properties to be adjusted to allow for a greater measuring range, or for greater sensitivity. </s></p></div1></body><back><div1 type="appendix"><head rend="underlined bold">Appendices</head><p/></div1><div1 type="bibliography"><head rend="underlined bold">References and Bibliography</head><p>Design of Measurement Systems ES21Q lecture notes, part I and II</p><p>Dr X. Ping Liu</p><p>Part I - Pg. 3,6,15</p><p>Part II - Pg. 36-43</p><p>University of <name type="university"/> Engineering Data Book</p><p>Pg. 85</p><p>Electronics, A Systems Approach</p><p>Dr. N Storey</p><p>Pg. 312</p><p>Resistive Bridge Basics - Part I</p><p><seg type="URL" n="http://www.maxim-ic.com/appnote_number/3426"/></p><p>National Instruments Developer Zone</p><p><seg type="URL" n="http://zone.ni.com"/></p><p>Torque Measurement Using Strain Gauges</p><p><seg type="URL" n="http://haptic.mech.northwestern.edu/library/brownjm/master/section4.2.2/"/></p><p>Active Low Pass Filters</p><p><seg type="URL" n="http://www.biopac.com/bslprolessons/h25/h25.htm#Active%20Filter"/>:%20Low%20Pass</p><p>Introduction to Strain Gages</p><p><seg type="URL" n="http://www.omega.com/prodinfo/StrainGages.html"/></p><p>Stress, Strain and Strain Gages</p><p><seg type="URL" n="http://www.me.psu.edu/me82/Learning/Strain/strain.html"/></p><p>RS Components - Strain Gauges</p><p><seg type="URL" n="http://www.rswww.com"/></p><p>Differential Amplifiers</p><p><seg type="URL" n="http://www.phys.ualberta.ca/~gingrich/phys395/notes/node110.html"/></p><p>Strain Gauge Connections and Bridge Circuits</p><p><seg type="URL" n="http://www.tokyosokki.co.jp/e/product/strain_gauge/bridge_list.html"/></p></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
