<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_0251a" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Experiment P1 - Ultrasound</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">deleted: page numbers</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">2</p><p n="date">2005-12</p><p n="module title">Physics Skills</p><p n="module code">PX271</p><p n="genre family">Methodology recount</p><p n="discipline">Physics</p><p n="disciplinary group">PS</p><p n="grade">D</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">3658</p><p n="number of s-units">156</p><p n="number of p">93</p><p n="number of tables">2</p><p n="number of figures">9</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">20</p><p n="number of lists">1</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">9</p><p n="abstract present">abstract present</p><p n="average words per s-unit">23.4</p><p n="average s-units per p">1.7</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">f</p><p n="year of birth">1987</p><p n="first language">English</p><p n="education">UKA</p><p n="course">Physics</p><p n="student ID">0251</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><titlePart rend="underlined bold">Second Year Lab Report</titlePart><docTitle><titlePart rend="underlined bold">Experiment P1 - Ultrasound</titlePart></docTitle><titlePart rend="underlined bold"><name type="student name"/>, <name type="other"/></titlePart></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="abstract"><head rend="underlined bold">Abstract</head><p n="p1.93"><s n="s1.9;p1.93">Five experiments were carried out to investigate the properties and uses of ultrasound waves in solids. </s><s n="s2.9;p1.93">Longitudinal waves were passed through two metal blocks to determine their longitudinal moduli, M, and Poisson's ratios, . </s><s n="s3.9;p1.93">For the aluminium block, M was (101±1)GPa, and  was 0.33. </s><s n="s4.9;p1.93">For the mild steel block, M was (264.5±3.1)GPa and  was 0.24. </s><s n="s5.9;p1.93">The echoes of longitudinal waves were also used to detect and size defects in an aluminium block, which proved successful as four defects were found. </s><s n="s6.9;p1.93">Shear waves were then produced from reflected longitudinal waves and were measured to have a velocity of (3500±400)ms <hi rend="sup">-1</hi>, just fitting the expected value of 3100ms <hi rend="sup">-1</hi>. </s><s n="s7.9;p1.93">Their angle of reflection and velocity were then tested against a version of Snell's Law, which proved inconclusive. </s><s n="s8.9;p1.93">Longitudinal waves were totally internally reflected to produce surface waves, the velocity of which was measured to be 2860ms <hi rend="sup">-1</hi>, matching the theoretical value within experimental error. </s><s n="s9.9;p1.93">The wavelength of a surface wave is proportional to energy, which is related to the depth of the wave, so by passing the waves through a slot of varying depths, its wavelength was found, with a value of (0.98±.05)mm. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">1 Introduction</head><div2><head rend="underlined">1.1 Ultrasound waves</head><p n="p2.93"><s n="s1.2;p2.93">Sound with a frequency greater than 20kHz<ref target="BAWE_0251a-endnote.001"/> is known as ultrasound. </s><s n="s2.2;p2.93">This experiment investigated the properties and some uses of the three types of ultrasound waves that travel in solids: longitudinal waves, shear waves and Rayleigh waves (see fig.1). </s></p><note place="end" id="BAWE_0251a-endnote.001"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Physics, Alonso and Finn, <hi rend="italic">Addison-Wesley</hi> 1992 </s></p></note><figure id="BAWE_0251a-fig.001"><head><hi rend="bold">Figure 1:</hi> The three types of ultrasound waves: Rayleigh waves which only travel on the surface of solids and shear and longitudinal waves which travel on the surface and through the bulk of solids. In this instance, all the waves have velocities to the right, indicated by v <hi rend="sub">R</hi> , v <hi rend="sub">S</hi> , v <hi rend="sub">L</hi> , but the particle motion is different in each case, indicated by  .</head></figure><p n="p3.93"><s n="s1.4;p3.93">In this experiment, the wave pulses are produced by transducers, whose mechanical vibrations (causing the ultrasound) are made by the Piezoelectric effect. </s><s n="s2.4;p3.93">More about this effect, regarding transducers, can be found in reference 2.<ref target="BAWE_0251a-endnote.002"/> Liquid couplant coupled the ultrasound from the transducers into the solid samples. </s><s n="s3.4;p3.93">Although all three types of waves travel through solids, only longitudinal waves can travel through liquids. </s><s n="s4.4;p3.93">Therefore longitudinal pulses are the only ones that were generated by transducers in this experiment. </s></p><note place="end" id="BAWE_0251a-endnote.002"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ultrasound Physics and Instrumentation, Hedrick, Hykes and Starchman, <hi rend="italic">Mosby</hi> 1995 </s></p></note><div3><head rend="underlined">1.1.1 Longitudinal and shear bulk ultrasound waves</head><p n="p4.93"><s n="s1.1;p4.93">A longitudinal pulse can be converted into shear waves can be produced by means of reflection and refraction, as figure 2 shows. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0251a-fig.002"><head><hi rend="bold">Figure 2:</hi> If the sample were just a uniform metal block, for example, then only the mode converted shear reflected wave S <hi rend="sub">R</hi> and the longitudinal reflected wave L <hi rend="sub">R</hi> would result from the longitudinal incident pulse L <hi rend="sub">I.</hi> However if the sample, medium A, is adjacent to a <hi rend="bold">less</hi> dense sample, medium B, then refraction occurs, resulting in a refracted longitudinal wave L <hi rend="sub">R</hi> ' and a refracted shear wave S <hi rend="sub">R</hi> '</head></figure></div3><div3><head rend="underlined">1.1.2 Rayleigh ultrasound bulk waves</head><p n="p5.93"><s n="s1.2;p5.93">As Rayleigh waves only travel on the surface of a solid, they are also known as Surface Acoustic Waves, or SAWs. </s><s n="s2.2;p5.93">They are produced by setting <hi rend="sub">i</hi> in figure 2 at the critical angle for total internal reflection for either the reflected shear or longitudinal wave, giving an angle of reflection of 90 <hi rend="sup">o</hi>, leading to a surface wave. </s></p><p n="p6.93"><s n="s1.3;p6.93">SAWs travel with a retrograde elliptical motion (fig. </s><s n="s2.3;p6.93">1), and have exponentially decreasing energy as they get further from the surface (fig. </s><s n="s3.3;p6.93">3). </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0251a-fig.003"><head><hi rend="bold">Figure 3</hi> Graph showing the exponential decrease of energy of a SAW at different depths. The energy at a depth of one wavelength, is E/e if maximum energy is E.</head></figure></div3></div2><div2><head rend="underlined bold">1.2 The objectives of the experiment</head><p n="p7.93"><s n="s1.1;p7.93">This investigation comprises five experiments, each with specific aims. </s></p><div3><head rend="underlined">1.2.1 Bulk Wave Generation</head><p n="p8.93"><s n="s1.2;p8.93">Bulk ultrasound waves can be used to determine properties of solids. </s><s n="s2.2;p8.93">Consider this equation for Young's Modulus: </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p9.93"><s n="s1.1;p9.93"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0251a-form.001"/> (1) </s></p><p n="p10.93"><s n="s1.1;p10.93"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0251a-form.002"/> </s></p><p n="p11.93"><s n="s1.1;p11.93"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0251a-form.003"/> </s></p><p n="p12.93"><s n="s1.1;p12.93"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0251a-form.004"/> </s></p><p n="p13.93"><s n="s1.2;p13.93">The density of material is easy to measure, so if a longitudinal wave were passed through a material, its Young's modulus can be calculated. </s><s n="s2.2;p13.93">Notice however that equation 1 is only effective for a 1D object, so for this experiment, where 3D solids were used, the equation gives the longitudinal modulus, M, instead of E. </s></p><p n="p14.93"><s n="s1.3;p14.93">Poisson's ratio, , is another property that can be calculated. </s><s n="s2.3;p14.93">Poisson's ratio is defined to be "the ratio of the contraction strain normal to the applied load divided by the extension strain in the direction of the applied load"<hi rend="sup">iii</hi> and is given by equation 2. </s><s n="s3.3;p14.93">Due to the ± sign in (2) it is important to know that  is positive for all materials that get thinner when stretched<ref target="BAWE_0251a-endnote.003"/>. </s></p><note place="end" id="BAWE_0251a-endnote.003"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Poisson's ratio website </s></p></note><p rend="ordered" n="p15.93"><s n="s1.1;p15.93"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0251a-form.005"/> (2) </s></p><p n="p16.93"><s n="s1.1;p16.93">This can be solved by using M from the previous part of the experiment and the theoretical value of E. </s></p></div3><div3><head rend="underlined">1.3.2 Mode conversion</head><p n="p17.93"><s n="s1.2;p17.93">The second part of the experiment investigated the conversion of longitudinal waves into shear waves (fig. </s><s n="s2.2;p17.93">2) by testing their properties against two given equations. </s></p><p n="p18.93"><s n="s1.1;p18.93">Firstly, an equation was given linking the distance the pulse has travelled as a longitudinal wave, <hi rend="italic">dl</hi>; the distance the pulse has travelled as a shear wave, <hi rend="italic">ds</hi>; the time taken, <hi rend="italic">ts</hi>, for the shear wave to travel it's distance; the velocity of the longitudinal wave, <hi rend="italic">vl</hi>; and the velocity of the shear wave, <hi rend="italic">vs</hi>: </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p19.93"><s n="s1.1;p19.93"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0251a-form.006"/> (3) </s></p><p n="p20.93"><s n="s1.1;p20.93">The second equation is an arrangement of Snell's Law: </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p21.93"><s n="s1.1;p21.93"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0251a-form.007"/> (4) </s></p><p n="p22.93"><s n="s1.1;p22.93">Where <hi rend="sub">2</hi> is the angle of reflection of the shear wave and <hi rend="sub">i</hi> is the angle of incidence of the longitudinal wave. </s></p><p n="p23.93"><s n="s1.1;p23.93">Equation 3 can be used to calculate <hi rend="italic">vs</hi> and if the value is correct and a shear wave has been located, equation 4 should apply. </s></p></div3><div3><head rend="underlined">1.3.3 Detecting and sizing defects</head><p n="p24.93"><s n="s1.2;p24.93">The third aim was to use 'sonar' properties of longitudinal ultrasound to detect, locate and size defects within an aluminium block. </s><s n="s2.2;p24.93">Detection can be achieved quite simply by knowing the velocity of a wave and the time it takes for the wave to reach the defect. </s></p></div3><div3><head rend="underlined">1.3.4 Calculating the velocity of a Rayleigh wave (SAW)</head><p n="p25.93"><s n="s1.1;p25.93">Once a SAW has been generated (see 1.1.2) their velocity, <hi rend="italic">cr,</hi> can be calculated by making time and distance measurements. </s></p><p n="p26.93"><s n="s1.1;p26.93">Theoretical value of <hi rend="italic">cr</hi> is given by: </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p27.93"><s n="s1.1;p27.93"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0251a-form.008"/> (5) </s></p></div3><div3><head rend="underlined">1.3.5 Crack Detection</head><p n="p28.93"><s n="s1.2;p28.93">Finally, by measuring the energy of the wave at different depths in a block, an estimate of the wavelength of the SAW can be found (see 1.1.2). </s><s n="s2.2;p28.93">If this situation is inverted, it can be seen that knowing the wavelength of a Rayleigh wave is therefore very useful in finding surface cracks and their depth. </s></p><p n="p29.93"><s n="s1.1;p29.93">The following section goes into more depth on how the aims of this experiment were achieved. </s></p></div3></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">2. Experimental details</head><p n="p30.93"><s n="s1.3;p30.93">In each part of the experiment, an ultrasound signal generator was connected to a PC oscilloscope (so the signal could be seen) and a transducer. </s><s n="s2.3;p30.93">For many of the experiments an additional 'receiver' transducer was connected to another channel of the oscilloscope, which picked up the pulse once it had travelled through the sample. </s><s n="s3.3;p30.93">The transducers and the samples were assembled as shown in figure 5 </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0251a-fig.004"><head><hi rend="bold">Figure 5</hi> Setup (a) shows one transducer (transducer 1) being used to transmit a pulse and then detect its reflection. This can be used to detect defects, for example, within a sample. Setup (b) shows transducer 3 emitting a pulse at an angle into the sample. This leads to reflections at angles, in which case another transducer (transducer 2) is used to pick up the reflections.</head></figure><p n="p31.93"><s n="s1.5;p31.93">The delay-time facility on the oscilloscope enables the time between wave transmission and reflection to be determined. </s><s n="s2.5;p31.93">The pulse was set at slowest rate so that the subsequent transmitted pulse wasn't shown on the oscilloscope before the first reflection. </s><s n="s3.5;p31.93">All time errors in this investigation are due to the pulse having multiple peaks (fig. </s><s n="s4.5;p31.93">6). </s><s n="s5.5;p31.93">Also, the errors were based on the accuracy to which it was possible to read from the oscilloscope so try to and minimise the error the timebase was set to the smallest readable value. </s></p><p n="p32.93"><s n="s1.3;p32.93">All distances measured in the experiment were generally measured using vernier scale callipers as these are more accurate than a ruler. </s><s n="s2.3;p32.93">All distance errors were based on the callipers' accuracy, unless otherwise stated. </s><s n="s3.3;p32.93">In graphs, the errors for the gradients were all calculated in 'Origin' </s></p><p n="p33.93"><s n="s1.1;p33.93">Throughout the experiments the velocity = displacement/time relationship was used if velocities, lengths or depths needed to be found. </s></p><p n="p34.93"><s n="s1.3;p34.93">Two types of transducers were used (but never together in one experiment): 5MHz longitudinal wave transducers and wedge transducers. </s><s n="s2.3;p34.93">The former were cylindrical, with a circular base juxtaposed with the sample. </s><s n="s3.3;p34.93">The latter were as shown in figure 7. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0251a-pic.001"><head><hi rend="bold">Figure 7</hi> Wedge transducer - ultrasound from the transducer travels through the perspex to a sample below</head></figure></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">3. Experimental detail, results and discussion </head><div2><head rend="underlined">3.1 Bulk wave generation</head><div3><head rend="underlined">3.1.1 Experimental Details</head><figure id="BAWE_0251a-fig.005"><head><hi rend="bold">Figure 8</hi> Setup of apparatus for measuring the velocity of a longitudinal ultrasound wave</head></figure><p n="p35.93"><s n="s1.5;p35.93">The time for ½, 1... </s><s n="s2.5;p35.93">4½ pulses to travel was noted from the oscilloscope readings. </s><s n="s3.5;p35.93">Repeat readings were also taken and then averaged to try and smooth out any anomalies. </s><s n="s4.5;p35.93">The length of these pulses (multiples of the block length) was measured to enable the velocity of the pulse, <hi rend="italic">vl</hi>, to be calculated. </s><s n="s5.5;p35.93">The metal samples were also weighed, using digital scales, and measured so that their density could be calculated and thus the longitudinal moduli and then the Poisson's ratios could be obtained. </s></p></div3><div3><head rend="underlined">3.1.2 Results and discussion</head><figure id="BAWE_0251a-fig.006"><head><hi rend="bold">Figure 9</hi> Graphs to determine, in (a), the velocity of longitudinal waves, <hi rend="italic">vl</hi> , in aluminium and in (b) the velocity of longitudinal waves in mild steel. The distance error was estimated for ½ pulse (one length of the block) so as length of pulse increased, so would the error, by the same factor. Notice that the gradients of the graphs show the inverse of <hi rend="italic">vl</hi> . To convert its error into one for <hi rend="italic">vl</hi> ,, the error was simply converted into a percentage error and then applied to the value of <hi rend="italic">vl</hi> ,. Note that the errors on graph (b) are smaller than those for graph (a) because the length of ½ a wave pulse for mild steel was smaller as it was a smaller block than the aluminium, so time and distance readings could be more accurate. However, the error in the gradient is greater for graph (b) because the points do not lie as well on the best fit line as for (a).</head></figure><p n="p36.93"><s n="s1.1;p36.93">The graphs shows <hi rend="italic">vl</hi>, to be (6173±11)ms <hi rend="sup">-1</hi>through aluminium and (5814±34)ms <hi rend="sup">-1</hi> through mild steel. </s></p><p n="p37.93"><s n="s1.3;p37.93">The actual value of <hi rend="italic">vl</hi><hi rend="sub">(aluminium)</hi> should be 6400ms <hi rend="sup">-1</hi><ref target="BAWE_0251a-endnote.004"/> so the gradient of figure 8(a) should be steeper. </s><s n="s2.3;p37.93">Since the time measurements all seemed quite accurate, increasing by sensibly even amounts, then the problem must lie in the distance measurement. </s><s n="s3.3;p37.93">A possible reason for this is that the thickness of the liquid couplant wasn't taken into account, so the distances should all be slightly greater, which would give a steeper graph. </s></p><note place="end" id="BAWE_0251a-endnote.004"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Fundamentals of Ultrasonics, Blitz </s></p></note><p n="p38.93"><s n="s1.1;p38.93">The actual value of <hi rend="italic">vl(</hi><hi rend="sub">steel)</hi> should be 5500-6000ms <hi rend="sup">-1v</hi>, therefore the value obtained experimentally was within the expected range. </s></p><p n="p39.93"><s n="s1.1;p39.93">The density of the aluminium was calculated to be (2643±10)kgm <hi rend="sup">-3</hi> and the density of the mild steel to be (7824±10)kgm <hi rend="sup">-3</hi> </s></p><p n="p40.93"><s n="s1.1;p40.93">Substituting these values into equation (1) (adapted for M) gives: </s></p><p n="p41.93"><s n="s1.1;p41.93"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0251a-form.009"/> </s></p><p n="p42.93"><s n="s1.1;p42.93">(Errors based on a square root of the sum of the squares of the fractional errors formula) </s></p><p n="p43.93"><s n="s1.3;p43.93">Theoretically, M <hi rend="sub">aluminium</hi>=110.3GPa <hi rend="sup">vi</hi> and M <hi rend="sub">steel</hi>=278.6GPa <hi rend="sup">vi</hi>. </s><s n="s2.3;p43.93">Both values are larger than the experimental ones, which should be expected from the fact that <hi rend="italic">vl</hi> for aluminium is too low and <hi rend="italic">vl</hi> for mild steel could be too low. </s><s n="s3.3;p43.93">Also, it shows that the above errors have been underestimated. </s></p><p n="p44.93"><s n="s1.2;p44.93">The theoretical value for <hi rend="italic">Young's</hi> modulus is 70.3GPa <hi rend="sup">vi</hi> for aluminium and 211.9GPa <hi rend="sup">vi</hi> for mild steel. </s><s n="s2.2;p44.93">Putting this and the experimental value for M into equation 2 gives </s></p><p n="p45.93"><s n="s1.1;p45.93"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0251a-form.010"/> </s></p><p n="p46.93"><s n="s1.1;p46.93">Due to the small errors in M, these both have negligible errors, despite them not quite matching their theoretical values of 0.345 <hi rend="sup">vi</hi> for aluminium and 0.291 <hi rend="sup">vi</hi> for mild steel </s></p></div3></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">3.2 Mode Conversion</head><div3><head rend="underlined">3.2.1 Experimental Details</head><figure id="BAWE_0251a-pic.002"><head><hi rend="bold">Figure 10</hi> Setup of apparatus for producing a shear ultrasound wave</head></figure><p n="p47.93"><s n="s1.3;p47.93">The longitudinal wave hits the metal-air interface at <hi rend="sub">i</hi> = 45 <hi rend="sup">o</hi> then a shear wave is reflected at angle <hi rend="sub">2.</hi> </s><s n="s2.3;p47.93">In this case, a distance was measured by means other than vernier callipers as distance <hi rend="italic">dl</hi> was measured using trigonometry. </s><s n="s3.3;p47.93">Sin<hi rend="sub">2</hi> was also measured using trigonometry by using distance <hi rend="italic">ds</hi> and the height. </s></p><p n="p48.93"><s n="s1.2;p48.93">Both the reflected longitudinal and the reflected shear waves were detected, but were far enough apart to be distinguishable. </s><s n="s2.2;p48.93">All the waves are actually divergent beams, so it was important to ensure that the <hi rend="italic">peak</hi> of the shear wave had been located. </s></p></div3><div3><head rend="underlined">3.2.2 Results and discussion</head><p n="p49.93"><s n="s1.1;p49.93">Referring back to equation 3, on insertion of the measured values of <hi rend="italic">dl</hi> and <hi rend="italic">ds</hi>, the observed value of <hi rend="italic">ts</hi> and the known value of <hi rend="italic">vl</hi> <hi rend="sup">iv</hi> the velocity of the reflected shear wave turned out to be </s></p><p n="p50.93"><s n="s1.1;p50.93"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0251a-form.011"/> </s></p><p n="p51.93"><s n="s1.1;p51.93">Error was calculated using standard error formulae. </s></p><p n="p52.93"><s n="s1.1;p52.93">The actual value for <hi rend="italic">vs</hi> for aluminium is 3100ms <hi rend="sup">-1</hi> so the experimental value was just accurate within error. </s></p><p n="p53.93"><s n="s1.2;p53.93">Testing equation 4, sin<hi rend="sub">2</hi> was found to equal 0.21. </s><s n="s2.2;p53.93">Looking at the right hand side of the equation, substituting in 3500ms <hi rend="sup">-1</hi> for v <hi rend="sub">s</hi> and known values of sin45 and <hi rend="italic">vl</hi> gives 0.39. </s></p><p n="p54.93"><s n="s1.1;p54.93">The fact that the two sides are not equal might well be due to <hi rend="italic">vs</hi> being too big. </s></p><p n="p55.93"><s n="s1.1;p55.93">This experiment could be improved by using the oscilloscope to test if some of the longitudinal wave was picked up as well, and repeating readings at different points to find if the equation does hold at any point. </s></p></div3></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">3.3 Locating and sizing defects</head><div3><head rend="underlined">3.3.1 Experimental Details </head><figure id="BAWE_0251a-pic.003"><head><hi rend="bold">Figure 11</hi> Setup of apparatus. The defects are located at the bottom of the block, just above the plastic sheet.</head></figure><p n="p56.93"><s n="s1.1;p56.93">In this experiment the 6dB drop-technique method<ref target="BAWE_0251a-endnote.005"/> was used: </s></p><note place="end" id="BAWE_0251a-endnote.005"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ultrasonic Methods of NDT, Blitz and Simpson </s></p></note><p n="p57.93"><s n="s1.3;p57.93">The 5MHz transducer is moved around the block until a defect is found (the amplitude of the pulse will increase). </s><s n="s2.3;p57.93">Once found, the transducer can find the centres (where the amplitude is at a maximum) and edges (the point at which the amplitude of the ultrasound pulse has decreased by 6dB, equivalent to one half of the maximum). </s><s n="s3.3;p57.93">By moving the transducer across the whole of the block all of the defects can be found. </s></p><p n="p58.93"><s n="s1.2;p58.93">The plotted points for the defects, as seen in figure 12, were measured from one edge of the block to the middle of the transducer. </s><s n="s2.2;p58.93">Finding the centre of a defect proved tricky as the amplitude at a point would fluctuate from one frame to the next, so an estimation of maximum/ half amplitude had to be made, resulting in a larger than usual distance error. </s></p><p n="p59.93"><s n="s1.1;p59.93">When calculating the depth, the theoretical value for <hi rend="italic">vl</hi> for aluminium <hi rend="sup">iv</hi> was used with the observed times. </s></p></div3><div3><head rend="underlined">3.3.2 Results</head><figure id="BAWE_0251a-fig.007"><head><hi rend="bold">Figure 12</hi> Four defects were found, of various sizes and depths. All were more or less circular and lied on a straight line at a breadth of about 2.3cm</head></figure><p n="p60.93"><s n="s1.1;p60.93">All of the defects were small in relation to the size of the transducer, leading to an important error, shown in the following diagrams: </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0251a-pic.004"><head><hi rend="bold">Figure 13a)</hi> A transducer accurately detecting the edge a large defect - half of the transducer is 'seeing' the defect so amplitude of wave increases by 6dB, leading to the correct conclusion that the middle of the transducer is over a defect edge.</head></figure><figure id="BAWE_0251a-pic.005"><head><hi rend="bold">Figure 13b)</hi> A transducer inaccurately detecting the edge of a defect - half of the transducer is 'seeing' the defect so amplitude of wave increases by 6dB. However, it is clear to see that the middle of the transducer is not over the edge of the transducer as one would assume, instead, due to the size of the defect, it is 'seeing' the whole defect.</head></figure><p n="p61.93"><s n="s1.1;p61.93">A better method would be the 20dB drop technique (reference v gives more information) </s></p></div3></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">3.4 Surface wave generation</head><div3><head rend="underlined">3.4.1 Experimental Detail</head><figure id="BAWE_0251a-pic.006"><head><hi rend="bold">Figure 14</hi> Setup of apparatus to produce Rayleigh waves. The angle of incidence of the longitudinal wave is approximately equal to the critical angle to produce a Rayleigh wave at a Perspex/ steel interface.</head></figure><p n="p62.93"><s n="s1.1;p62.93">To find the critical angle of a Rayleigh wave in mild steel the following arrangements of Snell's Law were used: </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p63.93"><s n="s1.1;p63.93"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0251a-form.012"/> (6) </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p64.93"><s n="s1.1;p64.93"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0251a-form.013"/> (7) </s></p><p n="p65.93"><s n="s1.1;p65.93">Values used:<ref target="BAWE_0251a-endnote.006"/> </s></p><note place="end" id="BAWE_0251a-endnote.006"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">From Tables of Physical and Chemical Constants, Kaye and Laby </s></p></note><list type="simple"><item><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0251a-form.014"/></item><item><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0251a-form.015"/></item><item><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0251a-form.016"/></item></list><p n="p66.93"><s n="s1.1;p66.93">To produce surface waves <hi rend="sub italic">l</hi> and <hi rend="sub italic">s</hi> must = 90 <hi rend="sup">o</hi> </s></p><table id="BAWE_0251a-tab.001"><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p67.93"><s n="s1.1;p67.93"><hi rend="sub">i</hi> is set to 63 <hi rend="sup">o</hi>, which is fairly close to <hi rend="sub">i</hi> for the shear wave so this will be the one to turn into a Rayleigh wave. </s></p></div3><div3><head rend="underlined">3.4.1 Results</head><figure id="BAWE_0251a-fig.008"><head><hi rend="bold">Figure 15</hi> The inverse of this graph's gradient gives the velocity of the Rayleigh wave. Note the systematic error, shown by the graph not going through zero. However, this can be ignored as it is only the gradient that is of interest.</head></figure><p n="p68.93"><s n="s1.1;p68.93">The graph shows that the experimental value of v is (2860±60)ms <hi rend="sup">-1</hi> </s></p><p n="p69.93"><s n="s1.2;p69.93">The theoretical value for a Rayleigh wave (by using equation 5 and the above values for the <hi rend="italic">v2</hi><hi rend="sub">(<hi rend="italic">l</hi>)</hi> and <hi rend="italic">v2</hi><hi rend="sub">(<hi rend="italic">s</hi>)</hi>) works out as 2900ms <hi rend="sup">-1</hi>. </s><s n="s2.2;p69.93">Therefore the experimental result is correct within experimental error. </s></p><p n="p70.93"><s n="s1.1;p70.93">It might be useful to see if using a combination of materials where the critical angles of the samples match exactly would give an even better result. </s></p></div3></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">3.5 Crack Detection</head><div3><head rend="underlined">3.5.1 Experimental Details</head><figure id="BAWE_0251a-pic.007"><head><hi rend="bold">Figure 14</hi> Wedge transducers measured the amplitude of the Rayleigh wave...explain what measurements were made more.</head></figure><p n="p71.93"><s n="s1.2;p71.93">The depth at each point could be measured by knowing the gradient of the slot and the distance the transducers were along the block.Four amplitude measurements were made for each depth. </s><s n="s2.2;p71.93">The average value of the amplitude was then taken, with its corresponding error being the standard deviation of all the amplitude values at that point. </s></p></div3><div3><head rend="underlined">3.5.2 Results</head><figure id="BAWE_0251a-fig.009"><head><hi rend="bold">Figure 13</hi> This graph's straight line isn't as convincing as some of the others; however the gradient error should take this into account. Note that Amplitude <hi rend="sup">2 </hi><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0251a-form.017"/> intensity <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0251a-form.018"/> energy. Therefore this graph is of the form ln(energy) = ln E +mx</head></figure><p n="p72.93"><s n="s1.1;p72.93">When energy = E/e (at the point where the depth, x, will equal ) the equation becomes </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p73.93"><s n="s1.1;p73.93"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0251a-form.019"/> (8) </s></p><p n="p74.93"><s n="s1.1;p74.93">Simplifying and rearranging this gives </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p75.93"><s n="s1.1;p75.93"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0251a-form.020"/> (9) </s></p><p n="p76.93"><s n="s1.1;p76.93">Therefore, mm </s></p></div3></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">4. Summary and conclusion</head><div2><head rend="underlined">4.1 Bulk Wave Generation</head><table id="BAWE_0251a-tab.002"><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p77.93"><s n="s1.2;p77.93">Methods for finding the velocity of longitudinal waves were tested and found to be fundamentally correct; however the value for aluminium was slightly lower than the theoretical value. </s><s n="s2.2;p77.93">This could be due to too small distance measurements, which could have been because the distance of the liquid couplant wasn't taken into account. </s></p><p n="p78.93"><s n="s1.1;p78.93">The longitudinal moduli and Poisson's ratios were all slightly lower than the expected values, which reflects the possible low values of both the velocities. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">4.2 Mode Conversion</head><p n="p79.93"><s n="s1.1;p79.93">Longitudinal and shear reflected waves were detected, with the shear wave having the smaller angle of reflection, as expected. </s></p><p n="p80.93"><s n="s1.1;p80.93">The velocity of the reflected shear wave <hi rend="italic">vs</hi> in aluminium was found to be (3,500±400)ms <hi rend="sup">-1</hi> so was fairly accurate considering it should have been 3110ms </s></p><p n="p81.93"><s n="s1.4;p81.93">Snell's law was tested for the shear waves. </s><s n="s2.4;p81.93">From the experimental results the equation did not seem to hold. </s><s n="s3.4;p81.93">This could have been due to not finding the correct position of the shear wave, which could be why <hi rend="italic">vs</hi> (taking value without error) was slightly too large. </s><s n="s4.4;p81.93">Therefore, testing to see whether the equation was true proved inconclusive. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">4.2 Detecting and sizing defects</head><p n="p82.93"><s n="s1.2;p82.93">The size, shape and depth of defects were found using ultrasound waves and their reflections through an aluminium block. </s><s n="s2.2;p82.93">As all four defects were found, the 6dB drop technique method proved to be useful, however the sizing of the defects was probably incorrect due to the fact that relative to the transducer the defects were small. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">4.3 Surface Wave Generation</head><p n="p83.93"><s n="s1.2;p83.93">Surface waves were generated using total internal reflection of shear waves. </s><s n="s2.2;p83.93">The angle of incidence was set by the wedge transducers used and was close to the angle calculated using Snell's law for Perspex/ mild steel. </s></p><p n="p84.93"><s n="s1.2;p84.93">The velocity of the Rayleigh waves was calculated to be... </s><s n="s2.2;p84.93">Equations were used to find the theoretical value (approx 2900ms) and the results matched within error. </s></p><p n="p85.93"><s rend="bold" n="s1.1;p85.93">Distance between transducers had error due to it being tricky to ensure that they were exactly in position, as they slid easily on the liquid couplant. </s></p><p n="p86.93"><s n="s1.1;p86.93">There is a systematic error, as time for waves to travel through Perspex hadn't been subtracted from final times, however, this will not affect the gradient, which is all that is of interest. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">4.4 Crack Detection</head><p n="p87.93"><s n="s1.3;p87.93">The amplitude of Rayleigh waves were measured as the passed through an aluminium slot of varying depths. </s><s n="s2.3;p87.93">The square of the amplitude is proportional to the wave energy. </s><s n="s3.3;p87.93">It is known that at 1/e times max energy the depth of slot there will equal the wavelength of the Rayleigh wave. </s></p><p n="p88.93"><s n="s1.1;p88.93">From the graph,  was found to be (0.98 0.05)mm The graph was a fairly good straight line ln graph, showing that the energy did decrease exponentially with slot depth. </s></p><p n="p89.93"><s n="s1.1;p89.93">Difficulties here were firstly with the block: anomalous results in a first attempt suggest that the slot was not smooth and the couplant might be filling it. </s></p><p n="p90.93"><s n="s1.1;p90.93">Overall points to note </s></p><p n="p91.93"><s n="s1.3;p91.93">The PC oscilloscope was used throughout the experiment to make time and distance measurements. </s><s n="s2.3;p91.93">Often peaks jumped with amplitudes varying significantly from one frame to the next, so affecting distance measurements. </s><s n="s3.3;p91.93">Also it was hard to measure the time due to multiple peaks (ass figs 13 and 14) </s></p><p n="p92.93"><s n="s1.2;p92.93">Overall the PC oscilloscope seemed as if it would be a better instrument than the traditional oscilloscope as it has cursors, which avoids human measurement error. </s><s n="s2.2;p92.93">Also, values for time, </s></p><p n="p93.93"><s n="s1.2;p93.93">volts/div etc. can be shown on the monitor so reading them off by eye is no longer a problem. </s><s n="s2.2;p93.93">Its one disadvantage is hat the PC and cables introduce noise into the system, which the other one wouldn't. </s></p></div2></div1></body><back/></text></TEI.2>
