<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_0252j" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Private/independent and state schools are completely different (and separate) entities. Critically discuss.</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">deleted: page numbers</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">3</p><p n="date">2006-04</p><p n="module title">Sociology of Education</p><p n="module code">SO306</p><p n="genre family">Essay</p><p n="discipline">Sociology</p><p n="disciplinary group">SS</p><p n="grade">D</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">3640</p><p n="number of s-units">133</p><p n="number of p">33</p><p n="number of tables">0</p><p n="number of figures">0</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">0</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">0</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">27.4</p><p n="average s-units per p">4.0</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">f</p><p n="year of birth">1984</p><p n="first language">English</p><p n="education">UKA</p><p n="course">Sociology</p><p n="student ID">0252</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><titlePart><name type="student ID"/>, Sociology of Education April 2006 Word Count - 3,585 </titlePart><docTitle><titlePart rend="underlined bold">Private/independent and state schools are completely different (and separate) entities. Critically discuss. </titlePart></docTitle></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="section"><p n="p1.33"><s n="s1.3;p1.33">The existence of an independent sector of schooling as a fee-paying alternative to state provision has drawn considerable attention, ever since the 1944 Education Act first established free education as a right. </s><s n="s2.3;p1.33">The sector as a whole is small: the Independent Schools Council (ISC) (n.d.) estimate that there are approximately 2,500 independent schools in the UK, catering for just seven per cent of the school-age population. </s><s n="s3.3;p1.33">It would thus be fair to ask why this educational minority attracts 'a level of public debate which is out of all proportion to their numerical significance' (Fox, 1984, p.45). </s></p><p n="p2.33"><s n="s1.4;p2.33">One finds a likely solution in the extent to which these forms of schooling have been identified as offering a fundamentally <hi rend="italic">different</hi> type of education. </s><s n="s2.4;p2.33">Chubb and Moe (1997, p.364) tell us that 'the organisation of schools is largely endogenous to the system of institutional control in which the schools are embedded.' </s><s n="s3.4;p2.33">This suggests that the different governing mechanisms experienced by the state and independent sectors must produce fundamentally distinct types of school. </s><s n="s4.4;p2.33">The very nature of independent education, as a purchasable market commodity, should thus make it different to state schooling, established on the principle of being 'provided as free at point of use by the government' (Reid <hi rend="italic">et al</hi>, 1991, p.14). </s></p><p n="p3.33"><s n="s1.4;p3.33">This, it would seem, is how we have come to perceive independent and state schools as completely different entities. </s><s n="s2.4;p3.33">However, the idea that institutional control is significant provides a platform from which wide-ranging changes in the relationship of these two forms of schooling can be identified. </s><s n="s3.4;p3.33">Modifications of the state sector over the last 30 years have created a quasi-market and begun to increase government influence over independent education. </s><s n="s4.4;p3.33">Such changes, it can be argued, have gone some way towards creating an educational milieu within which these two forms of schooling are no longer so distinct. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Elitism and social selection</head><p n="p4.33"><s n="s1.2;p4.33">Much has been written on the role of independent schools in helping to sustain a class divided society (Fox, 1984; Reid <hi rend="italic">et al</hi>, 1991). </s><s n="s2.2;p4.33">Such accusations are closely linked to what the independent sector offers, in terms of both educational outcomes and the experience of schooling itself. </s></p><p n="p5.33"><s n="s1.4;p5.33">That independent schools have traditionally had a rather different class composition to the state sector, seems indisputable. </s><s n="s2.4;p5.33">The 1870 Act established the principle of distinct types of school for those of varying social origins, with independent schools explicitly intended for the elites (Reid <hi rend="italic">et al</hi>, 1991). </s><s n="s3.4;p5.33">The foundations of independent and state schooling have thus moulded their development as entirely different entities. </s><s n="s4.4;p5.33">The former were not created to cater for all, instead to offer what Reid <hi rend="italic">et al</hi> (1991, p.17) call a 'particular type' of education; the latter to ensure the population at large had the basic skills necessary for economic productivity (Hempsall, 1986). </s></p><p n="p6.33"><s n="s1.5;p6.33">Access to independent schooling, unlike that provided by the state, is generally restricted by the ability to pay fees. </s><s n="s2.5;p6.33">As Walford (1991, p.2) indicates, this is important in upholding the presumption that independent schools are 'automatically superior' (and therefore the providers of something distinct) to state institutions. </s><s n="s3.5;p6.33">Across the entire sector fees can vary enormously, from the £23,688 requested by Eton College (2001b) to approximately £1,500 in many smaller institutions (Griffiths, 1991, p.87). </s><s n="s4.5;p6.33">The rendering of fees means that the position of a child's parents in the occupational structure (i.e. their class) is probably the single greatest factor in determining whether a child attends an independent or state institution. </s><s n="s5.5;p6.33">As Griffiths (1991) points out, even the lowest charging are still out of the question for most working-class parents, when compared to a state sector offering an educational service free of charge. </s></p><p n="p7.33"><s n="s1.3;p7.33">As a result of this financially selective gateway, independent institutions tend to show a 'remarkable social homogeneity' (Whitty <hi rend="italic">et al</hi>, 1989, p.13), dominated by the children of those with fathers in professional or managerial occupations. </s><s n="s2.3;p7.33">Only 6 per cent of children educated within the independent sector come from working-class families, despite their predominance in the social make-up of British society (Palfreyman, 2003, p.152). </s><s n="s3.3;p7.33">The difference to the state sector is clear: comprehensives draw two thirds of their intake from manual backgrounds (Halsey <hi rend="italic">et al</hi>, 1984, p.22). </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Resources</head><p n="p8.33"><s n="s1.4;p8.33">Charging a fee to each pupil means that independent institutions clearly have greater resources at their disposal and can provide a range of facilities unavailable to those in state education. </s><s n="s2.4;p8.33">These include lower teacher-pupil ratios, of approximately 1:10 compared with 1:18 in the state sector (Tomlinson, 2005, p.173; Griffiths, 1991, p.88). </s><s n="s3.4;p8.33">This must be considered a crucial difference, when one considers that 36 per cent of parents cite smaller class sizes as their reason for choosing for the independent sector (West and Noden, 2003, p.178). </s><s n="s4.4;p8.33">Where state schools seem to operate at one level, the smaller class sizes of the independent school means that pupils are given more specific attention according to their needs and pace of learning (Fox, 1984). </s></p><p n="p9.33"><s n="s1.4;p9.33">Apparent differences in teaching quality, reflected in higher turnover rates within state schools, are important in this respect (Sullivan and Heath, 2003). </s><s n="s2.4;p9.33">The greater professional autonomy available to teachers in the independent sector means that they have more opportunity for creativity in their approach (Griffiths, 1991). </s><s n="s3.4;p9.33">Such opportunities are, by contrast, restricted for those who teach in state schools, particularly after the 1988 Education Reform Act (ERA), which imposed a National Curriculum and increased staff accountability (Tomlinson, 2005). </s><s n="s4.4;p9.33">As a result, state schools seem less able to attract the most talented teaching staff, resulting in more of what Chubb and Moe (1997) describe as heterogeneity among staff goal orientations. </s></p><p n="p10.33"><s n="s1.3;p10.33">Added to this of course one must also consider the additional (and often superior) material facilities that parents can buy for their children within the independent sector. </s><s n="s2.3;p10.33">'Expansive playing fields; well stocked libraries and... new or modernised laboratories' are just some of the examples used by the 1980 Labour Party document, <hi rend="italic">Private Schools</hi>, to illustrate this distinction (cited in Tapper and Salter, 1984, p.186). </s><s n="s3.3;p10.33">It seems relatively straight forward to state that, with respect to the resources available to pupils within schools, the two sectors of education do appear to be clearly different and separate entities, with the independent offering superior access. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Ethos </head><p n="p11.33"><s n="s1.5;p11.33">Independent schools remain outside of the demands of the National Curriculum (Independent Schools Council, n.d.). </s><s n="s2.5;p11.33">As a result, they are often seen to provide a different, broader format of learning than 'nine-to-five' state institutions (Fox, 1984, p.60). </s><s n="s3.5;p11.33">There is a greater emphasis on the development of qualities outside formal education, particularly attitudes and discipline (Hempsall, 1986). </s><s n="s4.5;p11.33">Tapper and Salter (1984, p.181) indicate that such cultural differences are a major reason behind parental choice, with state schools seen as providing 'insufficient teaching of good manners... insufficient emphasis on correct speech'. </s><s n="s5.5;p11.33">This training of <hi rend="italic">character</hi> seems to indicate fundamental differences in the socialisation process provided by independent and state schools (Roker, 1993). </s></p><p n="p12.33"><s n="s1.6;p12.33">The distinct class compositions and value commitments of state and independent institutions have the knock-on effect of encouraging the development of different forms of 'ethos'. </s><s n="s2.6;p12.33">There is a widespread perception among those who choose independent education that a different type of child attends state school, creating 'socially problematic environments' (Sullivan and Heath, 2003, p.82). </s><s n="s3.6;p12.33">In illustration, parents seem to associate fears about bullying, or children failing to understand the value of academic work, with the state sector (Fox, 1984). </s><s n="s4.6;p12.33">By contrast, the atmosphere of the independent school is described as one that inspires self-belief and a 'sense of belonging' (Griffiths, 1991, p.94). </s><s n="s5.6;p12.33">At an independent school 'A boy can walk... carrying a violin without ridicule'; the same child in the state sector would be ridiculed, or so this opinion suggests. </s><s n="s6.6;p12.33">The state school, then, is a different entity because peer groups there are associated with risk (West and Noden, 2003). </s></p><p n="p13.33"><s n="s1.3;p13.33">The distinctive educational experience provided by the independent school also includes the potential to form a network of social contacts, known as the 'old-boy network' (Reid <hi rend="italic">et al</hi>, 1991, p.17). </s><s n="s2.3;p13.33">This provides those who attend independent schools with 'social capital' (Sullivan and Heath, 2003, p.81): their contacts are more likely to prove useful, often in terms of occupational advancement, than those of their state school counterparts. </s><s n="s3.3;p13.33">State schools, it would seem, are not only different entities in terms of their class composition but also in terms of the school experience they provide: basic academic training is only one segment of education in most independent institutions. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Educational outcomes</head><p n="p14.33"><s n="s1.7;p14.33">Sullivan and Heath (2003, p.78) suggest that parents paying for independent education do so in the expectation that their child will have access to 'some benefits that would not be available to them in the rival free state schools'. </s><s n="s2.7;p14.33">This is not simply with respect to facilities. </s><s n="s3.7;p14.33">Many independent institutions have historically differed from those provided by the state by being academically selective (Sullivan and Heath, 2003). </s><s n="s4.7;p14.33">As a result, the consistency of independent schools in producing better academic results is well documented. </s><s n="s5.7;p14.33">Hutton (2004), for example, points out that close to a quarter of private school pupils achieve three A-levels at grade A, whereas only 6 per cent at state institutions achieve this result. </s><s n="s6.7;p14.33">Such levels of attainment indicate a distinct separation between the sectors. </s><s n="s7.7;p14.33">In most state schools (the majority that do not select by aptitude), educational goals reflect the fact that 'educational excellence must compete with much more basic needs' in everyday learning (Chubb and Moe, 1997, p.374). </s></p><p n="p15.33"><s n="s1.3;p15.33">Educational advantages provide a 'ladder of opportunity' (West and Noden, 2003, p.178) for those attending independent schools, resulting in over-representation in various elite groups (Reid <hi rend="italic">et al</hi>, 1991). </s><s n="s2.3;p15.33">A gap in the support networks provided for higher education applications, as illustrated by Pugsley (2003, p.212), means that post-compulsory education is more of a 'natural progression' for pupils in the independent sector. </s><s n="s3.3;p15.33">Puglsey's 'Llanover High' pupils exemplify the difference for those in state schooling, where making an application required particular individual effort. </s></p><p n="p16.33"><s n="s1.3;p16.33">The independent sector also has a stranglehold on access to certain occupational positions. </s><s n="s2.3;p16.33">For example, only one third of the 1963 Conservative cabinet had attended a state school (Halsey <hi rend="italic">et al</hi>, 1984, p.18). </s><s n="s3.3;p16.33">Whitty <hi rend="italic">et al</hi> (1989, p.16) make clear the difference in prospects provided by state schools, in arguing that attendance at an independent school is 'almost a basic requirement for entry to the ruling elite.' </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Charitable status</head><p n="p17.33"><s n="s1.7;p17.33">While discrepancies in educational experience have traditionally separated the two sectors of education, there has always been one factor preventing this from becoming complete: the status of many independent schools as registered charities. </s><s n="s2.7;p17.33">These schools, allegedly free of government control are, in fact, in receipt of considerable financial assistance from that source (Reid <hi rend="italic">et al</hi>, 1991). </s><s n="s3.7;p17.33">Via relief from certain taxes, the most important being exemption from VAT on fees, charitable independent schools impose an annual cost to the Exchequer of something in the region of £200 million (Palfreyman, 2003, pp.146-47). </s><s n="s4.7;p17.33">Crucially, this money is not just an added bonus: many smaller independent institutions rely on this indirect funding to operate (Hempsall, 1986). </s><s n="s5.7;p17.33">That government allows charitable status means that we cannot argue that the education sectors are <hi rend="italic">entirely</hi> separate. </s><s n="s6.7;p17.33">The redirection of taxpayers' money into independent schools is a display of both financial and ideological support from the state (Walford, 1991). </s><s n="s7.7;p17.33">As Palfreyman (2003, p.154) points out, it means that independent schools are equally as absorbed into "the system". </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Choice policies and the market in education</head><p n="p18.33"><s n="s1.4;p18.33">In 1991, Walford (p.2) stated that it was becoming increasingly clear that 'the distinction between State and private schools is now less clear'. </s><s n="s2.4;p18.33">While inequalities still exist, various measures undertaken by both the Conservative governments of the 1980s/early 1990s, and New Labour since 1997, have gone some way to reduce the traditional separation of independent and state schools. </s><s n="s3.4;p18.33">The 1980 Education Act established the principle of parental choice in the state sector, a quality that, up until this point, had singled out the independent sector (Fox, 1984). </s><s n="s4.4;p18.33">The beginnings of an educational marketplace in state education took shape, with policy increasingly reflecting this principle. </s></p><p n="p19.33"><s n="s1.6;p19.33">The Assisted Places Scheme (APS) was one such policy. </s><s n="s2.6;p19.33">Establishing an annual number of places for state-educated children at independent institutions, the scheme widened the concept of choice between different types of schooling (Fox, 1984). </s><s n="s3.6;p19.33">Means testing of places meant that independent education became 'accessible to an even broader cross-section of the population' (Hempsall, 1986, p.8), thus reducing at least some of the social exclusivity that made it so distinct from the state sector. </s><s n="s4.6;p19.33">APS did, however, provide only a minority of places to those in state schooling. </s><s n="s5.6;p19.33">In addition, critics suggest that the academically selective nature of many assisted places meant that they went largely to more middle-class state students rather than the socially disadvantaged (Tapper, 2003, p.20). </s><s n="s6.6;p19.33">Other choice policies seem to have more realistically narrowed the gap between the two sectors. </s></p><p n="p20.33"><s n="s1.5;p20.33">Until the comprehensive movement took hold in the late 1960s there was always some crossover of qualities between education sectors. </s><s n="s2.5;p20.33">Grammar schools under the tripartite system, in particular, shared many of the characteristics of schools in the independent sector, such as academic selection (Whitty <hi rend="italic">et al</hi>, 1989). </s><s n="s3.5;p20.33">Choice policies post-1980 have renewed the idea of this middle ground by bringing the market principle to state education. </s><s n="s4.5;p20.33">Under the Conservatives, moves to promote 'a much greater variety of schools outside LEA control' (Whitty <hi rend="italic">et al</hi>, 1989, p.27) led to the establishment of City Technology Colleges (funded by industry and government) and Grant-Maintained Schools (outside LEA control and funded direct from government) (Walford, 1991). </s><s n="s5.5;p20.33">Free at point of use and nominally state institutions, yet often selective in nature and outside LEA responsibility, these schools shared common principles with both sectors. </s></p><p n="p21.33"><s n="s1.5;p21.33">New Labour has continued this trend in state sector 'privatisation', encouraging the diversification of educational provision (Tapper, 2003). </s><s n="s2.5;p21.33">In working towards their 1997 Manifesto promise, to offer all parents 'real choice through good quality schools, each with its own strengths and individual ethos' (Tapper, 2003, p.18), the government has offered increasingly varied forms of provision. </s><s n="s3.5;p21.33">By 2000, the state supported fourteen major types of school, including voluntary schools (outside LEA control) and specialist schools (concentrating on a particular area, such as sport or arts) (Tomlinson, 2005). </s><s n="s4.5;p21.33">Many of these institutions are also selective due to over-demand, making it clear that these new types of school represent something of a 'mixed territory' (Halsey <hi rend="italic">et al</hi>, 1984, p.11). </s><s n="s5.5;p21.33">They have blurred the boundaries between the principles of state and independent schooling to the extent that it is now difficult to talk of two distinct sectors. </s></p><p n="p22.33"><s n="s1.4;p22.33">In addition, policies of open enrolment initiated by the 1988 ERA mean that those utilising the state sector now also possess what Chubb and Moe (1997, p.365) name the 'exit option'. </s><s n="s2.4;p22.33">If a school is not seen to be meeting expected standards (made explicit by league table publication), then open enrolment allows a child to be withdrawn and placed elsewhere. </s><s n="s3.4;p22.33">Like the independent sector, state schools are now in direct competition and must be more responsive to the demands of those who use them (Tomlinson, 2005). </s><s n="s4.4;p22.33">With government funding following children's feet, state schools experience the same highly competitive situation of maintain standards, or face closure (Walford, 2001: 23). </s></p><p n="p23.33"><s n="s1.4;p23.33">Walford (2001: 27) is correct in suggesting that, despite the effects that 'choice' policies have had in creating a state sector educational marketplace, differences remain because it is 'At best... only a limited market or quasi-market.' </s><s n="s2.4;p23.33">However, it does seem to have made it less plausible to argue that independent and state schools are <hi rend="italic">completely</hi> different (and separate). </s><s n="s3.4;p23.33">Specialist forms of state provision have blurred the boundaries between what it means to be maintained or independent, and policies emphasising parental choice have brought many of the qualities of the independent sector, such as direct competition and selectiveness, into state schooling. </s><s n="s4.4;p23.33">Education in the state sector, like its independent counterpart, seems to have become a commodity (Tomlinson, 2005). </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Government supervision</head><p n="p24.33"><s n="s1.4;p24.33">Increased state supervision of the independent sector is another way in which its separation from the state sector has been narrowed. </s><s n="s2.4;p24.33">This can be exemplified by changes in inspection procedures, which mean standards in the independent sector are now more closely tied into government apparatus. </s><s n="s3.4;p24.33">The work of the Independent Schools Inspectorate is officially approved by government and also monitored by the state agency Ofsted (Ofsted, n.d.]. </s><s n="s4.4;p24.33">This emphasises that the level of association between standards in the independent and state sectors has increased. </s></p><p n="p25.33"><s n="s1.4;p25.33">This trend in state management looks set to continue with the Draft Charities Bill (2004). </s><s n="s2.4;p25.33">In reconsidering the extent to which the advancement of education can be seen as a charitable objective, the Bill creates a requirement for independent schools to provide increased evidence of how they are beneficial to the public (The Charity Commission, 2006). </s><s n="s3.4;p25.33">In order for the many independent schools with registered charity status to retain the financial benefits that it affords, the government will request them to engage more fully with the state sector (BBC, 2004). </s><s n="s4.4;p25.33">Such movements in government policy are important: they suggest that the state support shown to the independent sector (as VAT-free charities) can be manipulated to decrease the level of difference between the two school sectors. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Partnership</head><p n="p26.33"><s n="s1.4;p26.33">This narrowing will be achieved by building partnerships between state and independent schools, with the aim of reducing existing inequalities through collaboration (Blair and Halpin, 2006). </s><s n="s2.4;p26.33">Many such schemes are already in place as the 'Building Bridges' Partnerships Grants Scheme gains momentum, particularly with reference to sharing facilities and widening educational opportunities (DfES, 2005b). </s><s n="s3.4;p26.33">Eton College, for example, provides several summer schools designed to encourage interest in further education among state school pupils and has also funded a rowing lake open to public use (Eton College, 2001a). </s><s n="s4.4;p26.33">An example provided by the DfES (2005a), the 'Cheshire Partnership', similarly illustrates the collaboration of an independent school with state pupils, its 'Bright Sparks' project providing workshops for talented students in particular curriculum subjects, such as ICT. </s></p><p n="p27.33"><s n="s1.4;p27.33">Such schemes do highlight the problem that many partnerships are actually something of a one-way process, often incorporating only particularly able state students. </s><s n="s2.4;p27.33">However, they must certainly be seen as a major step towards overcoming the traditional separation of the two sectors. </s><s n="s3.4;p27.33">The setting up of an advisory group (which became permanent in 2002) to oversee the distribution of government funds towards these projects, suggests that movements to integrate the education sectors are a solid feature of New Labour policy (Passmore, 1999; DfES, 2005d). </s><s n="s4.4;p27.33">Evaluated by Oftsed as successful in 'building bridges between the sectors' (Ofsted, 2005), and with 80,000 pupils involved over the first six years (DfES, 2005c), the partnership movement does seem to have great potential to continue the trend in reducing educational disparity. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Conclusions</head><p n="p28.33"><s n="s1.6;p28.33">It appears that at least some of the most crucial elements identifying state and independent schools as different entities have undertaken something of a transformation. </s><s n="s2.6;p28.33">Central government seems to be taking an increased role in overseeing the independent sector, meaning that it is now more accountable to the same forces as state education. </s><s n="s3.6;p28.33">Equally, the 'privatisation' of the state sector has opened up maintained schools to a similar form of educational marketplace to that experienced by independent institutions. </s><s n="s4.6;p28.33">Government policies emphasising 'choice' mean that state schools, like their independent counterparts, must now increasingly respond to competition and consumer demand. </s><s n="s5.6;p28.33">The trend in diversification of school forms has also created a middle ground of educational provision. </s><s n="s6.6;p28.33">By allowing some schools to opt out of LEA control or be selective in a proportion of their intake, the government has blurred the boundaries between the traditional principles of independent and state schooling. </s></p><p n="p29.33"><s n="s1.5;p29.33">Acknowledging the many ways in which state and independent schooling have become closer is, however, only part of the story. </s><s n="s2.5;p29.33">Many differences between the sectors still exist, such as inequalities in educational outcomes and differential access to educational resources. </s><s n="s3.5;p29.33">As Tapper and Salter (1984, p.195) suggest, the image of state schooling remains one of turmoil and poor educational standards when compared to an independent sector which is 'stable and educationally respectable.' </s><s n="s4.5;p29.33">The unique ethos of independent education also remains in existence, and perhaps will always be so long as the class composition of each sector remains so distinct. </s><s n="s5.5;p29.33">In turn, little can be done to address social class differences without physically drawing independent schools under the state wing and removing fees. </s></p><p n="p30.33"><s n="s1.2;p30.33">Partnership schemes seem to represent one of the best possibilities for creating actual cooperation between independent and state schools, thus reducing their separation. </s><s n="s2.2;p30.33">Although, as Webster and Parsons (cited in Tapper, 2003, p.22) point out, they seem inadequate to fully resolve the 'educational apartheid', they may at least increase movement and discussion between the sectors. </s></p><p n="p31.33"><s n="s1.3;p31.33">In concluding, there do seem to be some things that remain fundamentally different about independent and state schools. </s><s n="s2.3;p31.33">A significant proportion of parents continue to choose the independent sector, a decision that involves the outlay of considerable sums of money, regardless of the structure of state education. </s><s n="s3.3;p31.33">In the exclusivity that the very name 'independent' denotes and in the bestowing of a 'cultural security' (West and Noden, 2003, p.192) cut off to most state school children, independent schools seem to offer an alternative educational experience. </s></p><p n="p32.33"><s n="s1.2;p32.33">However, as a result of the initiating of 'choice' policies and a competitive marketplace to raise standards, state schools increasingly share certain characteristics with their independent counterparts. </s><s n="s2.2;p32.33">By becoming more involved in the management of the independent sector, particularly through inducing the partnership movement, New Labour governments have created a dependency, albeit a limited one, by the independent sector on government backing (Tapper, 2003). </s></p><p n="p33.33"><s n="s1.1;p33.33">Independent and state schools are not therefore <hi rend="italic">completely</hi> different (and separate) entities, but do still possess many distinct qualities, highlighted by inequalities in class composition and educational outcomes. </s></p></div1></body><back><div1 type="bibliography"><head rend="underlined bold">Bibliography</head><p>Chubb, J.E. and Moe, T.M. (1997) 'Politics, Markets, and the Organization of Schools', in A.H. Halsey, H. Lauder, P. Brown and A.S. Wells (Eds.) <hi rend="italic">Education, Culture, Economy, and Society</hi>, Oxford: Oxford University Press, pp.363-381.</p><p>Fox, I. (1984) 'The Demand for a Public School Education: A Crisis of Confidence in Comprehensive Schooling?', in G. Walford (ed.) <hi rend="italic">British Public Schools: Policy and Practice</hi>, London: Falmer Press, pp.45-64.</p><p>Griffiths, J. (1991) 'Small Private Schools in South Wales', in G. Walford (ed.) <hi rend="italic">Private Schooling: Tradition, Change and Diversity</hi>, London: Paul Chapman Publishing, pp.84-97.</p><p>Halsey, A.H., Heath, A.F. and Ridge, J.M. (1984) 'The Political Arithmetic of Public Schools, in G. Walford (ed.) <hi rend="italic">British Public Schools: Policy and Practice</hi>, London: Falmer Press, pp.9-44.</p><p>Hempsall, D.S. (1986) 'The Boarding School and Total Education', in V.A. McClelland (ed.) <hi rend="italic">Private and Independent Education</hi>, Hull: Institute of Education, University of Hull, pp.5-11.</p><p>Hutton, W. (2004) 'Good for Oxford... but for the rest?', <hi rend="italic">Observer</hi>, 10 October, p.30.</p><p>Passmore, B. (1999) 'Divided sectors, equal partners', <hi rend="italic">The Times Educational Supplement</hi>, 22 January.</p><p>Palfreyman, D. (2003) 'Independent Schools and Charitable Status: Legal Meaning, Taxation Advantages and Potential Removal', in G. Walford (ed.) <hi rend="italic">British Private Schools: Research on Policy and Practice</hi>, London: Woburn Press, pp.144-157.</p><p>Pugsley, L. (2003) 'Choice or Chance: The University Challenge - How Schools Reproduce and Produce Social Capital in the Choice Process', in G. Walford (ed.) <hi rend="italic">British Private Schools: Research on Policy and Practice</hi>, London: Woburn Press, pp.208-224.</p><p>Reid, I., Williams, R. and Rayner, M. (1991) 'The Education of the Elite', in G. Walford (ed.) <hi rend="italic">Private Schooling: Tradition, Change and Diversity</hi>, London: Paul Chapman Publishing, pp.14-34.</p><p>Roker, D. (1993) 'Private Education and Political Socialization', in G. Walford (ed.) <hi rend="italic">Private Schooling: Tradition, Change and Diversity</hi>, London: Paul Chapman Publishing, pp.101-126.</p><p>Sullivan, A. and Heath, A.F. (2003) 'Intakes and Examination Results at State and Private Schools', in G. Walford (ed.) <hi rend="italic">British Private Schools: Research on Policy and Practice</hi>, London: Woburn Press, pp.77-106.</p><p>Tapper, T. and Salter, B. (1984) 'Images of Independent Schooling: Exploring the Perceptions of Parents and Politicians', in G. Walford (ed.) <hi rend="italic">British Public Schools: Policy and Practice</hi>, London: Falmer Press, pp.179-208.</p><p>Tapper, T. (2003) 'From Labour to New Labour: Bridging the Divide between State and Private Schooling', in G. Walford (ed.) <hi rend="italic">British Private Schools: Research on Policy and Practice</hi>, London: Woburn Press, pp.11-30.</p><p>Tomlinson, S. (2005) <hi rend="italic">Education in a Post-Welfare Society</hi>, Second Edition, Maidenhead: Open University Press.</p><p>Walford, G. (1991) 'Private Schooling into the 1990s', in G. Walford (ed.) <hi rend="italic">Private Schooling: Tradition, Change and Diversity</hi>, London: Paul Chapman Publishing, pp.1-13.</p><p>Walford, G. (2001) 'Does the Market Ensure Quality?', <hi rend="italic">Westminster Studies in Education</hi>, 24, (1): 23-33.</p><p>West, A. and Noden, P. (2003) 'Parental Choice and Involvement: Private and State Schools, in G. Walford (ed.) <hi rend="italic">British Private Schools: Research on Policy and Practice</hi>, London: Woburn Press, pp.177-193.</p><p>Whitty, G., Edwards, T. and Fitz, J. (1989) 'England and Wales: The Role of the Private Sector', in G. Walford (ed.) <hi rend="italic">Private Schools in Ten Countries: Policy and Practice</hi>, London; New York: Routledge, pp.8-31.</p><p>Wilkinson, R.W. (1986) 'The Assisted Places Scheme', in V.A. McClelland (ed.) <hi rend="italic">Private and Independent Education</hi>, Hull: Institute of Education, University of Hull, pp.49-62.</p><p rend="underlined bold">Electronic Resources</p><p>BBC. [2004] 'Charity status warning to schools', <hi rend="italic">BBC News</hi>. Online. Available: <seg type="URL" n="http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/education/3701161.stm"/> [accessed 10/4/06]</p><p>Blair, A. and Halpin, T. [2006] 'Private heads are not won over to new state of independence', <hi rend="italic">The Times Online</hi>. Online. Available: <seg type="URL" n="http://www.timesonline.co.uk/article/0,,591-2088280,00.html"/> [accessed 11/4/06] </p><p>The Charity Commission. [2006] 'The Charities Bill', <hi rend="italic">Charity Commission</hi>. Online. Available: <seg type="URL" n="http://www.charity-commission.gov.uk/spr/charbill.asp"/> [accessed 11/4/06]</p><p>Department for Education and Skills. [2005a] 'Case Studies: The Cheshire Partnership', <hi rend="italic">Teachernet</hi>. Online. Available: <seg type="URL" n="http://www.teachernet.gov.uk/casestudies/casestudy.cfm?id=338&amp;subcatid=104&amp;catid=103"/> [accessed 12/4/06]</p><p>Department for Education and Skills. [2005b] 'Independent/State School Partnerships: Building Bridges', <hi rend="italic">Teachernet</hi>. Online. Available: <seg type="URL" n="http://www.teachernet.gov.uk/wholeschool/buildingbridges"/> [accessed 12/4/06]</p><p>Department for Education and Skills. [2005c] 'Independent/State School Partnerships: Building Bridges: Frequently asked questions', <hi rend="italic">Teachernet</hi>. Online. Available: <seg type="URL" n="http://www.teachernet.gov.uk/wholeschool/buildingbridges/faq"/> [accessed 12/4/06]</p><p>Department for Education and Skills. [2005d] 'Independent/State School Partnerships: Building Bridges: History', <hi rend="italic">Teachernet</hi>. Online. Available: <seg type="URL" n="http://www.teachernet.gov.uk/wholeschool/buildingbridges/history"/> [accessed 12/4/06]</p><p>Eton College. [2001a] 'Public Benefit', <hi rend="italic">Eton College</hi>, Online: Available: <seg type="URL" n="http://www.etoncollege.com/default.asp"/> [accessed 10/4/06]</p><p>Eton College. [2001b] 'Some Frequently-Asked Questions About Eton', <hi rend="italic">Eton College.</hi> Online. Available: <seg type="URL" n="http://www.etoncollege.com/default.asp"/> [accessed 10/4/06]</p><p>Independent Schools Council. [no date]'Frequently asked questions', <hi rend="italic">Independent Schools Council</hi>. Online. Available: <seg type="URL" n="http://www.isc.co.uk/index.php/357"/> [accessed 13/4/06]</p><p>Ofsted. [2005] 'Barriers between the independent and state school sectors are being broken down', <hi rend="italic">Ofsted</hi>. Online. Available: <seg type="URL" n="http://www.ofsted.gov.uk/whatsnew/index.cfm?fuseaction=newsStory&amp;id=841"/> [accessed 12/4/06]</p><p>Ofsted. [no date] 'How we inspect independent schools', <hi rend="italic">Ofsted</hi>. Online. Available: <seg type="URL" n="http://www.ofsted.gov.uk/howwework/index.cfm?fuseaction=howwework.inspections&amp;id=5"/> [accessed 12/4/06]</p></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
