<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_0252a" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Was Cortés' leadership the key to the Spanish conquest of Mexico?</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">deleted: page numbers</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">2</p><p n="date">2005-04</p><p n="module title">Pre-Colombian and Spanish America</p><p n="module code">AM209</p><p n="genre family">Essay</p><p n="discipline">Comparative American Studies</p><p n="disciplinary group">AH</p><p n="grade">M</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">4710</p><p n="number of s-units">139</p><p n="number of p">33</p><p n="number of tables">0</p><p n="number of figures">0</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">0</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">0</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">33.9</p><p n="average s-units per p">4.2</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">f</p><p n="year of birth">1984</p><p n="first language">English</p><p n="education">UKA</p><p n="course">Comparative American Studies</p><p n="student ID">0252</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><titlePart><name type="student ID"/>, HiSoc May 2005 Word Count - 4,729</titlePart><docTitle><titlePart rend="underlined bold">Was Cortés' leadership the key to the Spanish conquest of Mexico? </titlePart></docTitle></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="section"><p n="p1.33"><s n="s1.5;p1.33">The conquest of Mexico poses a complex problem in history: how is it possible that a small band of Spanish explorers were able to conquer a Mesoamerican warlike and powerful society, on their own territory, in the space of just two years? </s><s n="s2.5;p1.33">As Prescott argues, 'There is probably no instance in history where so vast an enterprise has been achieved by means apparently so inadequate'.<ref target="BAWE_0252a-ftnote.001"/> The sixteenth-century notion that Europeans inevitably endure over native populations because of their inherent 'cultural superiority'<ref target="BAWE_0252a-ftnote.002"/> has, thankfully, come under criticism. </s><s n="s3.5;p1.33">Historians researching this period have put numerous other explanations forward. </s><s n="s4.5;p1.33">However, within the course of theories on military supremacy, victory by 'signs' and the part played by disease transfer, one enduring theme has been that it was Hernán Cortés whose leadership acted as the crucial factor enabling the Spanish conquest to occur. </s><s n="s5.5;p1.33">Yet this is by no means a confirmed notion and is surrounded by years of historical debate. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0252a-ftnote.001"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Prescott, William Hickling, <hi rend="italic">Conquest of Mexico</hi>, Vol. II, (London; New York: Dent; Dutton, 1909), p.363 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0252a-ftnote.002"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Clendinnen, Inga, '"Fierce and Unnatural Cruelty": Cortés and the Conquest of Mexico', in S. Greenblatt (ed.), <hi rend="italic">New World Encounters</hi> (Berkeley; Oxford: University of California Press, 1993), p.12 </s></p></note><p n="p2.33"><s n="s1.4;p2.33">An important factor one must consider within this framework is how we know about and understand these events. </s><s n="s2.4;p2.33">For many years Spanish accounts held a complete monopoly and Cortés' own letters to the King have had a crucial place in the record of the conquest. </s><s n="s3.4;p2.33">More recently emerging accounts taken from the Indian perspective have admittedly gone some way to redress the balance. </s><s n="s4.4;p2.33">However such post-conquest records, laden with omen and prophecy are not enough to explain the Spanish success, and the fact remains that the best records we have (and those which historians have tended to refer to) are Cortés' letters, the account by Cortés' chaplain and secretary Francisco Lopéz de Gómara and Diáz' <hi rend="italic">True History</hi>. </s></p><p n="p3.33"><s n="s1.3;p3.33">This reliance upon select accounts has created the potential for bias in our understanding of the role played by different factors in the conquest. </s><s n="s2.3;p3.33">It is fairly obvious an assumption to say that, in his commentary, Cortés may have coloured what actually happened with his own thoughts and assumptions, as well as perhaps exaggerating the extent to which his presence was pivotal. </s><s n="s3.3;p3.33">This seems particularly illuminating when one considers that Cortés was acting in rebellion against the authority granted to him by Velazquez in Cuba.<ref target="BAWE_0252a-ftnote.003"/> In his desire to construct an image of himself, to the King, as a credible leader, it seems plausible that he may have omitted evidence that works to the contrary. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0252a-ftnote.003"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Greene, Paul E., 'The Conquest of Mexico: The Views of the Chroniclers', in <hi rend="italic">The Americas</hi>, Vol. 31 (1974-75), p.164 </s></p></note><p n="p4.33"><s n="s1.3;p4.33">However Cortés' own account is not the only area of questionable accuracy among the historian's sources for this event. </s><s n="s2.3;p4.33">As his personal secretary and, as many historians have pointed out, somebody who was not actually present during the conquest, Gómara's version of events also has to be treated with caution. </s><s n="s3.3;p4.33">Díaz' insistence that Gómara placed too much power in the lap of Cortés has rubbed off among historians, who have tended to view the former as the more reliable account. </s></p><p n="p5.33"><s n="s1.6;p5.33">However, Iglesia argues that it too suffers similar problems of bias, this time being coloured by the desire to increase awareness of the role played by the ordinary soldiers. </s><s n="s2.6;p5.33">Underlying his narrative is the continual presence of resentment towards the idea that Cortés' skills alone completed the conquest and, in turn, that Gómara completely ignores the role played by the men. </s><s n="s3.6;p5.33">As a result, in his efforts to discredit this work, Díaz destroys confidence in his own, through his constant use of the first person plural, which makes Cortés merely 'a tool in the hands of his captains'<ref target="BAWE_0252a-ftnote.004"/>. </s><s n="s4.6;p5.33">Díaz claims that Cortés' soldiers and captains were fundamental in decision-making, a theme recurring throughout his work.<ref target="BAWE_0252a-ftnote.005"/> We might ask if this type of consultation is likely. </s><s n="s5.6;p5.33">In general one would probably say no, war not being the time for democracy and debate, but it is possible that those who participated in conquest expeditions were treated in different manner to the ordinary soldier.<ref target="BAWE_0252a-ftnote.006"/> However, in this dangerous and dynamic situation, encountered by an army with little formal hierarchy, it seems most plausible that decisions must <hi rend="italic"> ultimately</hi> lay with the leader of the expedition, regardless of whether or not he consulted before making them. </s><s n="s6.6;p5.33">Perhaps because Cortés had so great an ability to inspire his men with devotion to his plans that they, including Díaz, took them on as their own.<ref target="BAWE_0252a-ftnote.007"/> What this tells us, then, is that Díaz' work, if taken as accurate, may <hi rend="italic">disguise</hi> the extent to which Cortés leadership was crucial<ref target="BAWE_0252a-ftnote.008"/>, and this is something we must bare in mind in using his chronicles to understand the events. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0252a-ftnote.004"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Iglesia, Ramón, <hi rend="italic">Columbus, Cortés, and Other Essays</hi> (Berkeley: University of California Press, 1969), p.59 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0252a-ftnote.005"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Greene, 'The Conquest of Mexico', p.168 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0252a-ftnote.006"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Iglesia, <hi rend="italic">Columbus, Cortés and Other Essays,</hi> p.45 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0252a-ftnote.007"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ib id., p.60 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0252a-ftnote.008"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ib id., p.37 </s></p></note><p n="p6.33"><s n="s1.4;p6.33">We are thus reminded that any conclusions drawn as to the role of Cortés in the conquest must tend toward the tentative. </s><s n="s2.4;p6.33">All of the main chroniclers wrote for 'specific objectives'<ref target="BAWE_0252a-ftnote.009"/> and thus cannot be taken as wholly accurate. </s><s n="s3.4;p6.33">As Iglesia points out, the way in which evidence is arranged can alter the way it is perceived, and thus no writer can ever be entirely impartial because it is they who choose this arrangement<ref target="BAWE_0252a-ftnote.010"/>. </s><s n="s4.4;p6.33">However, we cannot afford to neglect these chronicles, despite their subjectivity, not only because of their capacity for description but also because they are all we have by which to comprehend the events. <ref target="BAWE_0252a-ftnote.011"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0252a-ftnote.009"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Greene, 'The Conquest of Mexico', p.164 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0252a-ftnote.010"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Iglesia, <hi rend="italic">Columbus, Cortés, and Other Essays,</hi> p.34 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0252a-ftnote.011"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Todorov, Tzvetan, <hi rend="italic">The Conquest of America: The Question of the Other</hi> (New York: Harper and Row, 1984), p.54 </s></p></note><p n="p7.33"><s n="s1.2;p7.33">In order to clarify the space within which this essay is situated I have chosen to define the 'conquest' as being the period between when Cortés and his followers landed at Vera Cruz and the fall of Tenochitlan, that is, the period of <hi rend="italic">military</hi> conquest of the Aztecs. </s><s n="s2.2;p7.33">Others may view the conquest period as including the aftermath of the defeat, the conquest of Indian religion and way of life perhaps, but here I will concentrate upon this first and most crucial act of Spanish conquest in Mexico. </s></p><p n="p8.33"><s n="s1.8;p8.33">It has been noted that Cortés' skills in the battlefield were perhaps not those we would expect from someone we have come to see as one of the greatest military leaders. </s><s n="s2.8;p8.33">However the importance of his leadership in many other elements of the conquest is undeniable. </s><s n="s3.8;p8.33">Prescott argues that Cortés had 'an air of resolution that meant those who approached him felt they must obey'<ref target="BAWE_0252a-ftnote.012"/>. </s><s n="s4.8;p8.33">It would indeed appear that his pivotal role lies in his ability to inspire his men to fight so determinedly for his cause. </s><s n="s5.8;p8.33">Uneasiness about his plans certainly existed among his followers and thus Cortés demonstrated great skill in maintaining the cohesion and passion that is essential to win a great battle. </s><s n="s6.8;p8.33">Díaz often notes Cortés' ability to appease those who disagreed with, or feared the consequences, of his ideas. </s><s n="s7.8;p8.33">To give an example, unrest spreads among those loyal to Valezquez once Cortés renounces his authority to him. </s><s n="s8.8;p8.33">Yet Cortés, through his mastery of language, was able 'bring them round' and prevent the loss of valuable troops<ref target="BAWE_0252a-ftnote.013"/>. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0252a-ftnote.012"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Prescott, William Hickling, <hi rend="italic">Conquest of Mexico</hi>, Vol. I, (London; New York: Dent; Dutton, 1909), p.162 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0252a-ftnote.013"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Díaz del Castillo, Bernal, <hi rend="italic">The Conquest of New Spain</hi> (Harmondsworth: Penguin, 1963), p.105 </s></p></note><p n="p9.33"><s n="s1.3;p9.33">Cortés seems, on many occasions, to understand the effectiveness of using symbolic language to inspire camaraderie between his men. </s><s n="s2.3;p9.33">Common among the chronicles are battle cries that infer unity behind a common cause, "Saint James and Spain" being an example.<ref target="BAWE_0252a-ftnote.014"/> This cry unifies perfectly the two concepts that Cortés seems to have most frequently used to motivate his men: the Church and the Crown, or more precisely, their loyalty to serve both. </s><s n="s3.3;p9.33">Cortés consistently reminded his men that they were vassals of the King and that it was their duty as such, and as Christians, to oppose their religious enemies.<ref target="BAWE_0252a-ftnote.015"/> His depth of conviction to the cause, and ability to make others share in this by adopting such measures, is what some view as his essential quality as leader.<ref target="BAWE_0252a-ftnote.016"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0252a-ftnote.014"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Elliott, J.H., 'The Spanish Conquest and settlement of America', in L. Bethell (ed.), <hi rend="italic">The Cambridge History of Latin America</hi>, Vol.1, (Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 1984), p.179 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0252a-ftnote.015"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Iglesia, <hi rend="italic">Columbus, Cortés, and Other Essays,</hi> p.160 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0252a-ftnote.016"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Clendinnen, "Fierce and Unnatural Cruelty", p.23 </s></p></note><p n="p10.33"><s n="s1.5;p10.33">Clendinnen calls Cortés 'A specialist in human communication'<ref target="BAWE_0252a-ftnote.017"/> and this ability extended further than simply his oratorical skills. </s><s n="s2.5;p10.33">Cortés excelled in understanding the symbolic, bringing out the theatrical in events in order to frighten the natives and suggest to them the might of the Spanish. </s><s n="s3.5;p10.33">For example, during his first contact with the natives, Cortés fires a cannon to exemplify the power of the new arrivals.<ref target="BAWE_0252a-ftnote.018"/> Such unprecedented behaviour was unintelligible to the Aztecs. </s><s n="s4.5;p10.33">They do attempt this sort of use of signs later, when they sacrifice Spanish captives within eyeshot, but fail because of their poorer grasp of the cultural differences between the groups. </s><s n="s5.5;p10.33">Rather than scare away the Spanish, with their linear way of thinking, such behaviour served only to increase the Spanish desire to complete their ultimate goal in conquering the city. <ref target="BAWE_0252a-ftnote.019"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0252a-ftnote.017"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ib id., p.13 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0252a-ftnote.018"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Todorov, <hi rend="italic">The Conquest of America</hi>, p.115 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0252a-ftnote.019"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ib id., p.88 </s></p></note><p n="p11.33"><s n="s1.4;p11.33">Cortés' determination as a leader is admirable, and is in evidence in particular at certain key moments during the conquest campaign, such as after the Noche Triste. </s><s n="s2.4;p11.33">Although his letters reflect a sombre mood during retreat, on reaching safety as Tlaxcala, Cortés immediately resumes his resolve to return: 'I remembered that Fortune always favours the bold, and furthermore that we were Christians who trusted in the great goodness of God, who would not let us perish utterly'.<ref target="BAWE_0252a-ftnote.020"/> One would assume that this resolute aspect of Cortés' character must have been an important part of overcoming the fears of those who followed, fears that were certainly in existence. </s><s n="s3.4;p11.33">Díaz speaks of this period as the time of greatest unrest among the troops, with demands made to abandon the mission and return to Cuba.<ref target="BAWE_0252a-ftnote.021"/> In the face of this atmosphere, Cortés exemplifies impressive organisational ability in reforming his troops and in particular in the process of brigantine construction. </s><s n="s4.4;p11.33">These ships prove crucial to the final battles because they allow the Spanish to attack the natives in water, where they are at their most vulnerable. <ref target="BAWE_0252a-ftnote.022"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0252a-ftnote.020"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Pagden, Anthony (ed.), <hi rend="italic">Hernán Cortés: Letters from Mexico</hi> (New Haven; London: Yale University Press, 1986), p.145 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0252a-ftnote.021"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Díaz, <hi rend="italic">The Conquest of New Spain,</hi> p.308 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0252a-ftnote.022"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Iglesia, <hi rend="italic">Columbus, Cortés, and Other Essays,</hi> p.177 </s></p></note><p n="p12.33"><s n="s1.6;p12.33">Equally as crucial was Cortés' leadership after the arrival of Narvaez on the coast. </s><s n="s2.6;p12.33">He makes a tactical decision to go out and meet him, despite the risk of leaving the city in the hands of the least reliable soldiers. </s><s n="s3.6;p12.33">Through clever manipulation Cortés is able to win friends in Naravez' camp while simultaneously planning an attack<ref target="BAWE_0252a-ftnote.023"/>. </s><s n="s4.6;p12.33">What could have been disastrous for the conquest thus becomes one of Cortés shining moments: within the space of one short battle Cortés is able to revolutionise the fortune of his mission. </s><s n="s5.6;p12.33">With Narvaez' men on side, Cortés had an army 'strong enough not only to secure his present conquests, but to open a career for still loftier ambitions'.<ref target="BAWE_0252a-ftnote.024"/> Throughout the campaign Cortés' behaviour mirrors this. </s><s n="s6.6;p12.33">In his determination to meet his ultimate goal, he undertakes risky measures in order to maximise his gains, for example by destroying the ships in which they arrived, an act that his supporters view as one of his most remarkable.<ref target="BAWE_0252a-ftnote.025"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0252a-ftnote.023"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Díaz, <hi rend="italic">The Conquest of New Spain,</hi> p.282 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0252a-ftnote.024"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Prescott, <hi rend="italic">Conquest of Mexico,</hi> Vol. 2, p.38 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0252a-ftnote.025"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Gómara, Francisco López de, <hi rend="italic">Cortés: The Life of the Conqueror by His Secretary</hi> (Berkeley; Los Angeles: University of California Press, 1965), p.90 </s></p></note><p n="p13.33"><s n="s1.4;p13.33">Cortés also appears to have been a master of improvisation, a necessary characteristic of leadership in the face of the ritualised Mexican way of life. </s><s n="s2.4;p13.33">Cortés' most important skills, then, lay perhaps not in leading the battles of the conquest, but in exploiting those favourable circumstances already in existence. </s><s n="s3.4;p13.33">As Elliott suggests, he seems to have had an 'extraordinary capacity to size up a situation and turn it to account'.<ref target="BAWE_0252a-ftnote.026"/> To give an example, on arrival, Cortés is quick to recognise that divisions exist between those subordinate to the Aztecs and he moves rapidly to realise the effectiveness of this knowledge to the to the best advantage of the Spanish.<ref target="BAWE_0252a-ftnote.027"/> Cortés seems to exemplify cultural awareness in his rapid attempts to use these grievances as a way of bringing about alliances with local tribes and widening his soldierly base<ref target="BAWE_0252a-ftnote.028"/>. </s><s n="s4.4;p13.33">To lead such a 'motley congregation'<ref target="BAWE_0252a-ftnote.029"/> of men, whose cultural differences could not have been more stark, on a march through the interior of the country and to command them to act on a common principle, it would seem that Iglesia is right in claiming that Cortés who possessed the character of one born to lead. <ref target="BAWE_0252a-ftnote.030"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0252a-ftnote.026"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Elliott, 'The Spanish Conquest and settlement of America', p.181 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0252a-ftnote.027"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Townsend, Camilla, 'Burying the White Gods: New Perspectives on the Conquest of Mexico', in <hi rend="italic">The American Historical Review</hi>, Vol. 108, No. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">3 (Jun 2003), p.667 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0252a-ftnote.028"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Elliott, 'The Spanish Conquest and the settlement of America', p.181 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0252a-ftnote.029"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Prescott, <hi rend="italic">Conquest of Mexico,</hi> Vol. 2, p.364 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0252a-ftnote.030"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Iglesia, <hi rend="italic">Columbus, Cortés, and Other Essays,</hi> p.158 </s></p></note><p n="p14.33"><s n="s1.4;p14.33">However, one might argue that, despite possessing the qualities of a great leader, Cortés was not 'the model of calculation, rationality and control' that we have tended to perceive him as.<ref target="BAWE_0252a-ftnote.031"/> It might be argued that little of what Cortés achieved during his leadership was done so through rational planning and more because fate provided him with opportunities he was able to exploit. </s><s n="s2.4;p14.33">The tendency, after events occur, to credit people with having followed a clear policy to reach such conclusions is also greater than usual with Cortés because he is at pains to project this image of himself in his letters<ref target="BAWE_0252a-ftnote.032"/>. </s><s n="s3.4;p14.33">It is clear that not all of what unfurled was the result of calculation by the Spanish leader from the fact that he was forced to destroy Tenochitlan in order to capture it. </s><s n="s4.4;p14.33">While the conquest is completed under his direction then, it is probably not in a way in which Cortés ever intended or planned for. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0252a-ftnote.031"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Clendinnen, "Fierce and Unnatural Cruelty", p.21 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0252a-ftnote.032"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ib id., p.22 </s></p></note><p n="p15.33"><s n="s1.7;p15.33">The story of the conquest is by no means straightforward. </s><s n="s2.7;p15.33">Many other factors seem to have operated to the Spanish advantage and it might be argued that these are at least equally as important to the conquest as Cortés' leadership. </s><s n="s3.7;p15.33">For example, constrained by his religion's emphasis upon prophecy and cyclical development, the Aztec leader's understanding of the unfolding events was limited to what his society had previously dealt with, in encounters with other Mesoamerican powers. </s><s n="s4.7;p15.33">As a result he found himself incapable of producing effective messages in order to repel the Spanish.<ref target="BAWE_0252a-ftnote.033"/> The constant receipt of gifts that Cortés encounters provides a good example. </s><s n="s5.7;p15.33">From a Mexican standpoint this would be seen to demonstrate the great power of the Aztec empire, a technique used to strike fear into any potential enemies. </s><s n="s6.7;p15.33">Yet in coming up against the Europeans, whose belief system works on an entirely different basis, this message is lost. </s><s n="s7.7;p15.33">Moctezuma's actions perhaps indicated an indecisive ruler, a fatal flaw in competition with Cortés' mastery of improvisation. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0252a-ftnote.033"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ib id., p.13 </s></p></note><p n="p16.33"><s n="s1.5;p16.33">Many historians view Moctezuma's fatal mistake as believing that the Spanish might be returning gods<ref target="BAWE_0252a-ftnote.034"/>. </s><s n="s2.5;p16.33">Díaz asserts that a helmet worn by one of the Spanish soldiers was mistaken for that worn by a former god, who had returned to rule over their land<ref target="BAWE_0252a-ftnote.035"/>. </s><s n="s3.5;p16.33">This perhaps created the sense of inevitability that made Moctezuma's response to the newcomers so meagre. </s><s n="s4.5;p16.33">Although this does not account for the losses in the second phase of conquest, it was possibly what gained the Spanish entry into the city. </s><s n="s5.5;p16.33">This gave Cortés precious breathing time to begin to understand how this society operated and also, of course, for the capture of Moctezuma, something that fundamentally undermined the native leadership. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0252a-ftnote.034"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ib id., p.13 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0252a-ftnote.035"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Díaz, <hi rend="italic">The Conquest of New Spain,</hi> p.92 </s></p></note><p n="p17.33"><s n="s1.2;p17.33">That this belief was key to the conquest focuses upon certain accounts of Aztec society before the Spanish arrival, namely Book Twelve of the Florentine Codex, which create a Moctezuma overcome by the fear that Cortés is the returning god Quetzalcoatl.<ref target="BAWE_0252a-ftnote.036"/> However, this image is one disputed in recent years. </s><s n="s2.2;p17.33">Townsend suggests that the story of the returning god was created <hi rend="italic">after</hi> the conquest in order that ritualised Aztec society could try to understand and excuse it.<ref target="BAWE_0252a-ftnote.037"/> If the Aztecs did call the Spanish 'gods' it might be because they cannot find a name for them among their pattern of human stratification based on tribal origins, rather than because of a genuine belief that they were divine. <ref target="BAWE_0252a-ftnote.038"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0252a-ftnote.036"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Townsend, 'Burying the White Gods', p.663 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0252a-ftnote.037"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ib id., p.665 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0252a-ftnote.038"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ib id., p.666 </s></p></note><p n="p18.33"><s n="s1.7;p18.33">It is difficult to argue exactly what Moctezuma intended through any of his actions towards the Spanish. </s><s n="s2.7;p18.33">For example, was his cooperation in Spanish captivity an attempt to secure his city, based on his knowledge of the Spanish ferocity in battle with other tribes, as Townsend suggests<ref target="BAWE_0252a-ftnote.039"/>, or was he simply unable to manoeuvre his power when held up against Cortés ability to manipulate? </s><s n="s3.7;p18.33">We will probably never know because it appears that he confided in very few, and those he did were most likely killed during the fighting. </s><s n="s4.7;p18.33">As such then we have no reliable source from which to grasp Moctezuma's state of mind, given the problems of bias in the Spanish accounts. </s><s n="s5.7;p18.33">However, that he was constrained in his responses by the nature of his religion seems likely. </s><s n="s6.7;p18.33">Prescott provides evidence for this in arguing that Moctezuma's commitment to 'all the burdensome ceremonial of the Aztec worship'<ref target="BAWE_0252a-ftnote.040"/> was fundamental to his reign. </s><s n="s7.7;p18.33">That Cortés was able to persuade the Aztec leader to give up his residence and become a captive, but not to discard his religion<ref target="BAWE_0252a-ftnote.041"/>, reveals most clearly the extent to which faith was central and guiding to Moctezuma. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0252a-ftnote.039"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ib id., p.672 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0252a-ftnote.040"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Prescott, <hi rend="italic">Conquest of Mexico</hi>, Vol. 1, p.191 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0252a-ftnote.041"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Díaz, <hi rend="italic">The Conquest of New Spain,</hi> p.223 </s></p></note><p n="p19.33"><s n="s1.5;p19.33">Eliott argues that the conquest was 'as much a revolt by a subjugated population against its overlords'<ref target="BAWE_0252a-ftnote.042"/> as something imposed from outside by Cortés, an idea that elevates the importance of the native allies in this campaign. </s><s n="s2.5;p19.33">Cortés' Indian allies, 'cheered with the sweet hope of regaining their ancient liberty'<ref target="BAWE_0252a-ftnote.043"/>, fought determinedly on the side of the Spanish. </s><s n="s3.5;p19.33">Cortés' knowledge of Mesoamerican political organisation would probably not have grasped the intricacies of factional divisions present within the empire and, as a result, it was the Indians themselves who retained most of the control.<ref target="BAWE_0252a-ftnote.044"/> This is perhaps exemplified best in the events following the siege of Tenochitlan, where Cortés himself notes that he is unable to control the ferocity and violence of his allied army.<ref target="BAWE_0252a-ftnote.045"/> Their importance in terms of numbers is also clearly in evidence, for example in Díaz we find mention of 10,000 warriors provided by the Tlaxcalans in Cortés second assault on Tenochitlan. </s><s n="s4.5;p19.33">Equally their lands offer shelter and an invaluable opportunity for the Europeans to regain strength after their expulsion. </s><s n="s5.5;p19.33">It is perhaps true to say, then, that, 'A few hundred Spaniards became an unbeatable force only when combined with thousands of indigenous pouring in behind them'.<ref target="BAWE_0252a-ftnote.046"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0252a-ftnote.042"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Elliott, 'The Spanish Conquest and the settlement of America', p.183 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0252a-ftnote.043"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Prescott, <hi rend="italic">Conquest of Mexico,</hi> Vol. 1, p.217 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0252a-ftnote.044"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Hassig, Ross, <hi rend="italic">Mexico and the Spanish Conquest</hi> (London; New York: Longman, 1994), p.146 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0252a-ftnote.045"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Pagden, <hi rend="italic">Hernán Cortés: Letters from Mexico</hi>, p.264 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0252a-ftnote.046"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Townsend, 'Burying the White Gods', p.669 </s></p></note><p n="p20.33"><s n="s1.4;p20.33">That these allies were one of the most crucial elements in the Spanish success is virtually indisputable. </s><s n="s2.4;p20.33">However, their presence does not necessarily detract from the idea that Cortés' leadership was key. </s><s n="s3.4;p20.33">It was his skills as a communicator that extracted the information necessary to learn of the internal divisions among the native population<ref target="BAWE_0252a-ftnote.047"/>, information that he then exploited to the greatest European advantage. </s><s n="s4.4;p20.33">As Prescott eloquently argues, in gaining the native allies, Cortés 'arrested the arm that was lifted to smite him, and made it do battle in his behalf'. <ref target="BAWE_0252a-ftnote.048"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0252a-ftnote.047"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Prescott, <hi rend="italic">Conquest of Mexico,</hi> Vol. 1, p.215 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0252a-ftnote.048"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Prescott, <hi rend="italic">Conquest of Mexico,</hi> Vol. 2, p.363 </s></p></note><p n="p21.33"><s n="s1.3;p21.33">Perhaps the most obvious advantage that lay before the invaders was their vast military superiority in terms of weaponry and formations. </s><s n="s2.3;p21.33">As Elliott indicates, the horse provided the Spanish with both a greater mobility and, at least initially, the opportunity to surprise and unsettle their enemies.<ref target="BAWE_0252a-ftnote.049"/> Even though Cortés and his men were poorly equipped by the standards of the day (having set out on a mission of exploration not conquest) this was still a war between the 'world of iron and gunpowder in collision with the world of stone'<ref target="BAWE_0252a-ftnote.050"/>. </s><s n="s3.3;p21.33">The 'slings, bows and arrows'<ref target="BAWE_0252a-ftnote.051"/> used by the Indians could not penetrate the Spaniards' metal armour, while their own cotton armour did little to ward off blows received from steel swords.<ref target="BAWE_0252a-ftnote.052"/> That the Indians recognised the military prowess of the newcomers is apparent from the way in which the Tarascans offered Moctezuma assistance in repelling the Europeans until they heard about their horses and firearms. <ref target="BAWE_0252a-ftnote.053"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0252a-ftnote.049"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Elliott, 'The Spanish Conquest and the settlement of America', p.175 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0252a-ftnote.050"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ib id., p.175 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0252a-ftnote.051"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Prescott, <hi rend="italic">Conquest of Mexico,</hi> Vol. 1, pp.272-273 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0252a-ftnote.052"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Townsend, 'Burying the White Gods', p.669 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0252a-ftnote.053"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Warren, J. Benedict, <hi rend="italic">The Conquest of Michoacán: The Spanish Domination of the Tarascan Kingdom in Western Mexico, 1521-1530</hi> (Norman: University of Oklahoma Press, 1985), p.26 </s></p></note><p n="p22.33"><s n="s1.4;p22.33">The different battle techniques used and, more importantly, understood were perhaps even more critical to the Spanish success. </s><s n="s2.4;p22.33">'Just as there are two forms of communication, there are two forms of war'<ref target="BAWE_0252a-ftnote.054"/>, and it is this fact that often leaves the Indians at a disadvantage. </s><s n="s3.4;p22.33">For example, the Europeans were more accustomed at producing the protective formations in battle that limit losses<ref target="BAWE_0252a-ftnote.055"/>, probably a result of the usual native conception of taking captives rather than killing on the battlefield. </s><s n="s4.4;p22.33">The ritualistic style of native warfare and warrior dress, with soldiers 'gaudily painted' and chiefs glittering with helmets made of gold and jewels, meant that they could not be prepared to fight at any given moment, and also that they were more easily spotted on the battlefield.<ref target="BAWE_0252a-ftnote.056"/> Equally problematic in this respect was the war cry given by Indian warriors in an attempt to frighten enemies, which here simply revealed their position. <ref target="BAWE_0252a-ftnote.057"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0252a-ftnote.054"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Todorov, <hi rend="italic">The Conquest of America,</hi> p.93 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0252a-ftnote.055"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Hassig, <hi rend="italic">Mexico and the Spanish Conquest,</hi> p.98 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0252a-ftnote.056"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Prescott, <hi rend="italic">Conquest of Mexico,</hi> Vol. 1, p.270 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0252a-ftnote.057"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Todorov, <hi rend="italic">The Conquest of America,</hi> p.89 </s></p></note><p n="p23.33"><s n="s1.3;p23.33">Never were these different practices of warfare so crucial as during the final siege, when Cortés blockaded the city, cutting off the water supply and allowing its population to starve as the battle continued<ref target="BAWE_0252a-ftnote.058"/>. </s><s n="s2.3;p23.33">The great anguish this caused is measurable from its volume of references in native sources: in illustration, "Nothing can compare with the horrors of that siege and the agonies of the starving." </s><ref target="BAWE_0252a-ftnote.059"/><s n="s3.3;p23.33">To the Aztec peoples, to involve civilians in this way was the very antithesis of warfare, and had no part in their experience of it. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0252a-ftnote.058"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Díaz, <hi rend="italic">The Conquest of New Spain,</hi> pp.359-368. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0252a-ftnote.059"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Leon-Portilla, Miguel (ed.), <hi rend="italic">The Broken Spears: The Aztec Account of the Conquest of Mexico</hi> (Boston: Beacon Press, 1992), p.109 </s></p></note><p n="p24.33"><s n="s1.3;p24.33">The Indians saw 'signs' on the battlefield that the Spanish did not, omens that destroyed their ability to fight. </s><s n="s2.3;p24.33">To give an example, Spanish sources cite the fall of the Indian commander at the battle of Otumba as the reason for their success, but it probably more likely the taking of the banner that signified for the natives that the battle was lost.<ref target="BAWE_0252a-ftnote.060"/> The tactics used by the Europeans were simply not present in the Aztec mind and thus had no way of comprehending them. </s><s n="s3.3;p24.33">Although Aztecs did gradually learn to adapt in the face of European weaponry, for example by beginning to kill on the battlefield, their belief system would only allow this up to a certain point and thus they remained at a disadvantage. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0252a-ftnote.060"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Clendinnen, "Fierce and Unnatural Cruelty", p.32 </s></p></note><p n="p25.33"><s n="s1.4;p25.33">As clearly, then, as we can see its effect on Moctezuma's behaviour, religion plays a central role in other areas of life. </s><s n="s2.4;p25.33">The use of a cyclical calendar meant that the Aztec world was an over-determined one, and they were incapable of understanding anything as a unique event.<ref target="BAWE_0252a-ftnote.061"/> Religion bound them to ritual and prophecy, thus limiting and sometimes paralysing their viable responses. </s><s n="s3.4;p25.33">In short, in both messages and actions, on the battlefield and beyond, the natives were unable to improvise in the face of the unparalleled behaviour enacted by the Spanish, and the mastery of adaptation presented by their leader.<ref target="BAWE_0252a-ftnote.062"/> Again therefore it seems to have been these cultural differences, something beyond Cortés control, which worked to help him gain the advantage. </s><s n="s4.4;p25.33">Such baffling of the Indians, more than any deliberate or intended policy, worked to knock them off balance. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0252a-ftnote.061"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Todorov, <hi rend="italic">The Conquest of America,</hi> p.63 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0252a-ftnote.062"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ib id., p.87 </s></p></note><p n="p26.33"><s n="s1.2;p26.33">Meanwhile, for the Spanish, absolute faith in the superiority of their culture and in particular their religion, gives them a unique edge in many situations. </s><s n="s2.2;p26.33">The sense that their mission was in the name of God created an inner confidence among the Spanish that allowed them to exploit the weaknesses of their enemies without fear or guilt.<ref target="BAWE_0252a-ftnote.063"/> While Cortés did play upon religious ideas to increase the commitment of his men to the cause, they would have had to be deeply imbedded in their consciousness already to have the necessary result. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0252a-ftnote.063"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ib id., p.107 </s></p></note><p n="p27.33"><s n="s1.5;p27.33">Unlike the leaders of the Aztec army, bound by their ritualised conduct of war, Cortés' religion justified the use every route available to ensure the success of his mission. </s><s n="s2.5;p27.33">In short, the religion of the Aztecs, more likely to inspire resignation to death than to glory, was a poor match for Christianity<ref target="BAWE_0252a-ftnote.064"/>. </s><s n="s3.5;p27.33">For the Spanish, religion offered a motivation, justification and giver of confidence with the knowledge that God is on their side. </s><s n="s4.5;p27.33">For the Aztecs, on the other hand, the requirement for ritualised practices, and also its emphasis on omen and inevitability, places them in a position from which it is much harder to defend. </s><s n="s5.5;p27.33">A good illustration of this can be found in <hi rend="italic">Broken Spears</hi>, where we are reminded that the achievement of the Spanish in reaching their city and destroying their idols is, to the Aztecs, a sign of the inevitability of their success.<ref target="BAWE_0252a-ftnote.065"/> Díaz goes as far as to infer that the native Aztecs might still be in power if their religion had not prevented them from granting Cortés' numerous pleas for peace during the final siege, because political domination was not strictly the Spanish aim. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0252a-ftnote.064"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Elliott, 'The Spanish Conquest and the settlement of America', p.182 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0252a-ftnote.065"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Leon-Portilla, <hi rend="italic">The Broken Spears</hi>, p.48 </s></p></note><p n="p28.33"><s n="s1.6;p28.33">In addition one must pause to acknowledge the importance of disease to the fall of Tenochitlan. </s><s n="s2.6;p28.33">During the period in which Cortés and his men regrouped at Tlaxcala, Mexico was ravaged by a smallpox epidemic, spreading rapidly in a population with absolutely no previous exposure. </s><s n="s3.6;p28.33">Of course, this did affect both sides in terms of men available to fight, as many of Cortés' native allies also fell victim. </s><s n="s4.6;p28.33">However the Aztecs, who relied on sheer manpower to overwhelm the technology of the Spanish, felt its effect far more keenly. </s><s n="s5.6;p28.33">The massive effect smallpox had on the Aztecs is clear from the way in which they subsequently counted the years from it.<ref target="BAWE_0252a-ftnote.066"/> It sapped their will to resist and perhaps goes some way to suggest why the final battles were so more effective for the Europeans. </s><s n="s6.6;p28.33">This bacteriological warfare, albeit the responsibility of the Spanish, was another <hi rend="italic">unwitting</hi> tactic that allowed Cortés a distinct advantage. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0252a-ftnote.066"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Gómara, <hi rend="italic">The Life of the Conquerer by his Secretary,</hi> p.204 </s></p></note><p n="p29.33"><s n="s1.2;p29.33">One's conclusions, then, about the role of Cortés, like the sources from which they derive, will always tend toward the subjective because it is hard to establish an objective, scientific kind of history from data so laden with bias and agenda.<ref target="BAWE_0252a-ftnote.067"/> It does however, seem sensible to assume that where Cortés and Gómara may have over-emphasised the importance of the former's leadership, Díaz probably under-estimated it. </s><s n="s2.2;p29.33">Although common soldiers undeniably carried out the conquest, it is perhaps unlikely that they could have done so without the presence of Cortés' leadership, which 'gave them ideals and guided their energies'<ref target="BAWE_0252a-ftnote.068"/>. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0252a-ftnote.067"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Iglesia, <hi rend="italic">Columbus, Cortés, and Other Essays,</hi> p.39 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0252a-ftnote.068"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ib id., p.52 </s></p></note><p n="p30.33"><s n="s1.5;p30.33">Cortés was a master of human communication and it seems to have been his grasp of the symbolic that was crucial to the conquest. </s><s n="s2.5;p30.33">His talent for great speeches, filled with words of honour and religious commitment, not only saved him the loss of potential deserters at many points throughout the campaign, but also roused confidence in his leadership. </s><s n="s3.5;p30.33">Many of the ideas Cortés communicated were beliefs his men already held as part of their inherent notion of European cultural superiority. </s><s n="s4.5;p30.33">Yet it was Cortés ability to exploit such cultural circumstances that created the unity and dedication that gave the Europeans their advantage. </s><s n="s5.5;p30.33">Thus, to give an example, while the Spanish must be viewed as forever indebted to their Indian allies, it was Cortés' genius that obtained command of them and that united this army, of such gaping cultural commitments, to fight devotedly, and as one, for the cause he so deeply felt. </s></p><p n="p31.33"><s n="s1.3;p31.33">As a leader, his determination never waned, even after his troops' expulsion from Mexico, and all negotiations were carried out by him. </s><s n="s2.3;p31.33">Cortés was a master at performing great accomplishments with limited resources available to him, and his astuteness at some of the key moments in this campaign was that of 'great men', rarely seen throughout history<ref target="BAWE_0252a-ftnote.069"/>. </s><s n="s3.3;p31.33">His ability to adapt to whatever circumstances lay before him was perhaps his most commanding talent and saved the conquest from termination and disaster at many points, such as after the Noche Triste or on the arrival of Narvaez. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0252a-ftnote.069"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Gómara, <hi rend="italic">The Life of the Conqueror by his Secretary,</hi> p.91 </s></p></note><p n="p32.33"><s n="s1.4;p32.33">It seems likely that this improvisation, in the face of the Aztec ritualised way of understanding, was what offered the Spanish their chance of success. </s><s n="s2.4;p32.33">Although the Europeans military superiority was vast, and disease weakened their opposition, they perhaps might have been defeated if the Aztecs, and more importantly perhaps, Moctezuma, had been able to modify their behaviour and responses with changed circumstances, in the way that Cortés was able to. </s><s n="s3.4;p32.33">Perhaps paralysed by the belief that Cortés was a returning god, or perhaps simply unable to fit the newcomers into their cyclical way of understanding, Moctezuma first, and warriors on the battlefield later, cannot grasp the conquest as a unique event. </s><s n="s4.4;p32.33">Where Cortés is affected by, and grows into, his environment, the Aztecs are bound by religion and tradition to behaviour that consistently leaves them at a disadvantage, both in battle and diplomacy. </s></p><p n="p33.33"><s n="s1.4;p33.33">What Díaz perhaps offers us is a realistic version of the extent to which Cortés' leadership was key to the conquest. </s><s n="s2.4;p33.33">We must attempt to see a real commander rather than the literary hero figure we hold in our imagination, a man who was indeed assisted by what fate provided him, but who still exemplifies extraordinary tenacity, ability to inspire and sharp-witted improvisation. </s><s n="s3.4;p33.33">Even though other crucial factors tended to fall to the Spanish advantage, without a figure of this ability leading the expedition, it seems likely that, at one of the several occasions where the Spanish are left vulnerable, the conquest would have been aborted. </s><s n="s4.4;p33.33">The story of the conquest is therefore inevitably the story of Cortés because he is 'not merely the soul, but the body, of the enterprise, present everywhere in person'.<ref target="BAWE_0252a-ftnote.070"/> Although the circumstances in existence without doubt worked to the benefit of the Europeans, it required a leader like Cortés to exploit them and to ensure the success of the Spanish conquest of Mexico. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0252a-ftnote.070"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Prescott, <hi rend="italic">Conquest of Mexico,</hi> Vol. 2, p.362 </s></p></note></div1></body><back><div1 type="bibliography"><head rend="underlined bold">Bibliography </head><p>Clendinnen, Inga, <hi rend="italic">Ambivalent Conquests: Maya and Spaniard in Yucatan, 1517-1570</hi> (Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 1987)</p><p>Clendinnen, Inga, '"Fierce and Unnatural Cruelty": Cortés and the Conquest of Mexico', in S. Greenblatt (ed.), <hi rend="italic">New World Encounters</hi> (Berkeley; Oxford: University of California Press, 1993)</p><p>Díaz del Castillo, Bernal, <hi rend="italic">The Conquest of New Spain</hi> (Harmondsworth: Penguin, 1963)</p><p>Elliott, J.H., 'The Spanish Conquest and settlement of America', in L. Bethell (ed.), <hi rend="italic">The Cambridge History of Latin America</hi>, Vol.1, (Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 1984)</p><p>Gómara, Francisco López de, <hi rend="italic">Cortés: The Life of the Conqueror by His Secretary</hi> (Berkeley; Los Angeles: University of California Press, 1965)</p><p>Greene, Paul E., 'The Conquest of Mexico: The Views of the Chroniclers', in <hi rend="italic">The Americas</hi>, Vol. 31 (1974-75), pp.164-172.</p><p>Hassig, Ross, <hi rend="italic">Mexico and the Spanish Conquest</hi> (London; New York: Longman, 1994)</p><p>Iglesia, Ramón, <hi rend="italic">Columbus, Cortés, and Other Essays</hi> (Berkeley: University of California Press, 1969)</p><p>Leon-Portilla, Miguel (ed.), <hi rend="italic">The Broken Spears: The Aztec Account of the Conquest of Mexico</hi> (Boston: Beacon Press, 1992) </p><p>Pagden, Anthony (ed.), <hi rend="italic">Hernán Cortés: Letters from Mexico</hi> (New Haven; London: Yale University Press, 1986)</p><p>Prescott, William Hickling, <hi rend="italic">Conquest of Mexico</hi>, Vol. I, (London; New York: Dent; Dutton, 1909)</p><p>Prescott, William Hickling, <hi rend="italic">Conquest of Mexico</hi>, Vol. II, (London; New York: Dent; Dutton, 1909)</p><p>Todorov, Tzvetan, <hi rend="italic">The Conquest of America: The Question of the Other</hi> (New York: Harper and Row, 1984)</p><p>Townsend, Camilla, 'Burying the White Gods: New Perspectives on the Conquest of Mexico', in <hi rend="italic">The American Historical Review</hi>, Vol. 108, No. 3 (Jun 2003), pp.659-688.</p><p>Warren, J. Benedict, <hi rend="italic">The Conquest of Michoacán: The Spanish Domination of the Tarascan Kingdom in Western Mexico, 1521-1530</hi> (Norman: University of Oklahoma Press, 1985)</p></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
