<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_0254c" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Materials and Production Laboratory Report - Mechanical Testing</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">The document has a title page which contains:
document title
title part</note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">deleted: header: student number, university name; footer: page numbers</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">1</p><p n="date">2003-05</p><p n="module title">Materials and Production</p><p n="module code">ES160</p><p n="genre family">Methodology recount</p><p n="discipline">Engineering</p><p n="disciplinary group">PS</p><p n="grade">M</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">986</p><p n="number of s-units">44</p><p n="number of p">23</p><p n="number of tables">0</p><p n="number of figures">0</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">43</p><p n="number of lists">9</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">2</p><p n="abstract present">abstract present</p><p n="average words per s-unit">22.4</p><p n="average s-units per p">1.9</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">m</p><p n="year of birth">1982</p><p n="first language">Chinese unspecified</p><p n="education">OSA</p><p n="course">Engineering</p><p n="student ID">0254</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><titlePart rend="bold">University of <name type="university"/> School of Engineering</titlePart><docTitle><titlePart rend="bold">Materials and Production Laboratory Report - Mechanical Testing</titlePart></docTitle><titlePart rend="bold">by<name type="student ID"/></titlePart><titlePart>Report Reference Code: ES160A5A Affiliation: Year 1 Engineering Report of laboratory performed on: 20 April 2004</titlePart></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="abstract"><head rend="bold">Summary</head><p n="p1.23"><s n="s1.5;p1.23">In order to develop an understanding of the standard tensile test, study the mechanical properties of some important engineering materials, obtain values for the yield stress (or proof stress), tensile strength and ductility for those materials and to ascertain the variability of these properties for certain nominally identical specimens, the materials and production assignment associated with the mechanical testing laboratory was set up. </s><s n="s2.5;p1.23">In this laboratory, different types of metal specimens were available to test with the Hounsfield Type W Hand Tensometer. </s><s n="s3.5;p1.23">And in this assignment, two carbon steels were tested, one was carbon steel AN with 0.1% C, the other one was carbon steel N with 0.8% C. By the tensometer, two copies of force-extension graphs for each of these specimens were obtained, and values of yield stress, tensile strength, ductility could be worked out from the graphs as well. </s><s n="s4.5;p1.23">Finally, those data derived from the experiment was compared with a reference data which was done in previous years. </s><s n="s5.5;p1.23">Then, the values could be assessed whether it agreed or disagreed with the reference data, and even found out the problems of the experiment. </s></p></div1><div1 type="front-back-matter"><head rend="bold">Contents</head><p/></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Introduction</head><p n="p2.23"><s n="s1.5;p2.23">In this materials and production assignment associated with the mechanical testing laboratory, six types of metal specimens were available to test with the Hounsfield Type W Hand Tensometer. </s><s n="s2.5;p2.23">The aim of the experiments was to develop an understanding of the standard tensile test, to study the mechanical properties of some important engineering materials, to obtain values for the yield stress (or proof stress), tensile strength and ductility for those materials and to ascertain the variability of these properties for certain nominally identical specimens. </s><s n="s3.5;p2.23">During the test, the specimens were extended in the direction of the applied load and reduce in cross-section in the perpendicular direction, they were ended with fracture. </s><s n="s4.5;p2.23">And the tensile curve was obtained, which showing how the important mechanical properties were derived. </s><s n="s5.5;p2.23">In the assignment, the objective was to assess whether the values derived from experiments could identify a real variation in the properties of selected carbon steel specimens. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Theory</head><p n="p3.23"><s n="s1.1;p3.23">The theory of the analysis of results was stated in section 'The tensile test' of the laboratory briefing sheet in Appendix 1. </s></p><p n="p4.23"><s n="s1.1;p4.23">And all the equations that would be used were listed as below. </s></p><list type="simple"><item><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0254c-form.001"/></item><item><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0254c-form.002"/></item><item><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0254c-form.003"/></item><item><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0254c-form.004"/></item><item><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0254c-form.005"/></item><item><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0254c-form.006"/></item><item><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0254c-form.007"/></item><item><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0254c-form.008"/></item></list></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">3. Apparatus and Methods</head><div2><head>(1). Apparatus</head><p n="p5.23"><s n="s1.1;p5.23">Hounsfield Type W Hand Tensometer </s></p><p n="p6.23"><s n="s1.1;p6.23">Six types of metal specimen (Specimens were listed in section 'SPECIMENS' of the laboratory briefing sheet in Appendix 1) </s></p></div2><div2><head>(2). Method</head><p n="p7.23"><s n="s1.5;p7.23">The specimen was fixed between tension head and operating screw, it was linked with a force-measuring system and a means of applying the extension. </s><s n="s2.5;p7.23">And a worm gearbox applied to the extension, it could extend the specimen. </s><s n="s3.5;p7.23">Furthermore, the force applied to the specimen was transmitted to a beam which would deflect, as the force is directly proportional to its deflection, the force could be obtained by measuring the deflection. </s><s n="s4.5;p7.23">And the deflection could be measured by puncturing a graph sheet at frequent intervals, which was directly linked with the gearbox. </s><s n="s5.5;p7.23">Therefore, a tensile curve would be achieved. </s></p><p n="p8.23"><s n="s1.1;p8.23">N.B. Please check method details in section 'The Tensometer Type W Testing Machine' of the laboratory briefing sheet in Appendix 1. </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">4. Observations and Results</head><p n="p9.23"><s n="s1.1;p9.23">By the Tensometer Type W Testing Machine, six force-extension graphs were obtained, while two of them were attached as reference 1 and reference 2, they were carbon steel AN and carbon steel N, and measurements of these two specimens from the graphs were recorded as below. </s></p><p n="p10.23"><s n="s1.1;p10.23">P.S. The scale of the force is 2.5KN; the scale of extension is 16:1. </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p11.23"><s n="s1.2;p11.23">(1). </s><s n="s2.2;p11.23">Carbon steel AN, 0.1% C Normalised, 900° </s></p><list type="simple"><item><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0254c-form.009"/></item><item><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0254c-form.010"/></item><item><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0254c-form.011"/></item><item><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0254c-form.012"/></item><item><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0254c-form.013"/></item><item><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0254c-form.014"/></item><item><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0254c-form.015"/></item></list><p rend="ordered" n="p12.23"><s n="s1.2;p12.23">(2). </s><s n="s2.2;p12.23">Carbon steel N, 0.8% C, Normalised, 830° </s></p><list type="simple"><item><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0254c-form.016"/></item><item><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0254c-form.017"/></item><item><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0254c-form.018"/></item><item><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0254c-form.019"/></item><item><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0254c-form.020"/></item></list></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">5. Analysis and Discussion of Results</head><p n="p13.23"><s n="s1.1;p13.23">Analysis the measurements that showed in the last part, values of the yield stress (<formula notation="" id="BAWE_0254c-form.021"/>), tensile strength (<formula notation="" id="BAWE_0254c-form.022"/>) and ductility (<formula notation="" id="BAWE_0254c-form.023"/>) for each of these two specimens could be worked out. </s></p><p n="p14.23"><s n="s1.1;p14.23">In terms of Carbon steel AN, applying equation 2.5. </s></p><list type="simple"><item><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0254c-form.024"/></item><item><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0254c-form.025"/></item><item><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0254c-form.026"/></item><item><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0254c-form.027"/></item><item><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0254c-form.028"/></item></list><p n="p15.23"><s n="s1.1;p15.23">Applying equation 2.6 </s></p><list type="simple"><item><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0254c-form.029"/></item><item><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0254c-form.030"/></item><item><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0254c-form.031"/></item></list><p n="p16.23"><s n="s1.1;p16.23">Applying equation 2.8 </s></p><list type="simple"><item><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0254c-form.032"/></item><item><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0254c-form.033"/></item><item><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0254c-form.034"/></item></list><p n="p17.23"><s n="s1.3;p17.23">Therefore, the upper yield stress was 381.5MPa, the lower yield stress was 366.5MPa, the tensile strength was 525MPa, and the ductility was 0.339. </s><s n="s2.3;p17.23">Comparing these data with lab exercise data in the Appendix 1, the first three values were not match with them, and only the ductility was a little bit similar as the Appendix 1. </s><s n="s3.3;p17.23">So, the experiment was not quite successful. </s></p><p n="p18.23"><s n="s1.1;p18.23">In terms of Carbon steel N, applying equation 2.5. </s></p><list type="simple"><item><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0254c-form.035"/></item><item><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0254c-form.036"/></item><item><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0254c-form.037"/></item></list><p n="p19.23"><s n="s1.1;p19.23">Applying equation 2.6 </s></p><list type="simple"><item><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0254c-form.038"/></item><item><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0254c-form.039"/></item><item><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0254c-form.040"/></item></list><p n="p20.23"><s n="s1.1;p20.23">Applying equation 2.8 </s></p><list type="simple"><item><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0254c-form.041"/></item><item><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0254c-form.042"/></item><item><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0254c-form.043"/></item></list><p n="p21.23"><s n="s1.2;p21.23">Therefore, the yield stress was 441.5MPa, the tensile strength was 962.5MPa, the ductility was 0.111. </s><s n="s2.2;p21.23">Comparing these data with the lab exercise data in the Appendix 1, these values were agree with them, and it was quite correspondingly, so it was a correct experiment. </s></p><p n="p22.23"><s n="s1.4;p22.23">There were a number of sources of error associated with the experiment. </s><s n="s2.4;p22.23">Firstly, errors associated with recording of data while puncturing a graph sheet at frequent intervals, because it should be really careful to observe the mercury level. </s><s n="s3.4;p22.23">Secondly, errors in identifying significant feature, the material was different even they came from the same factory. </s><s n="s4.4;p22.23">Thirdly, errors associated with measurements from the force-extension curve, the elastic line was extremely important for the whole calculation, incorrect identification of the proper elastic line would lead to wrong values not only for yield stress but also for ductility. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">6. Conclusions</head><p n="p23.23"><s n="s1.2;p23.23">From the experiment, it was known that the mechanical properties of carbon steel AN and carbon steel N. After comparing the values that obtained from this experiment with four tables of data that derived from experiments done in previous years. </s><s n="s2.2;p23.23">It was found out the mechanical properties of carbon steel AN was incorrect in this experiment, while the mechanical properties of carbon steel N was agree with those reference data, and the values of the yield stress, tensile strength, ductility for it was 441.5MPa, 962.5MPa and 0.111 respectively. </s></p></div1></body><back><div1 type="bibliography"><head rend="bold">7. References</head><p/></div1><div1 type="appendix"><head rend="bold">Appendices</head><p/></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
