<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_0254b" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Assignment 2: A stylus type instrument (Profilometer)</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">The document has a title page which contains:
document title
title part</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">2</p><p n="date">2004-05</p><p n="module title">Design of Measurement Systems</p><p n="module code">ES21Q</p><p n="genre family">Design specification</p><p n="discipline">Engineering</p><p n="disciplinary group">PS</p><p n="grade">M</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">2328</p><p n="number of s-units">132</p><p n="number of p">42</p><p n="number of tables">0</p><p n="number of figures">5</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">35</p><p n="number of lists">0</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">2</p><p n="abstract present">abstract present</p><p n="average words per s-unit">17.6</p><p n="average s-units per p">3.1</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">m</p><p n="year of birth">1982</p><p n="first language">Chinese unspecified</p><p n="education">OSA</p><p n="course">Engineering</p><p n="student ID">0254</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><titlePart rend="bold">University of <name type="university"/> School of Engineering</titlePart><docTitle><titlePart><hi rend="bold">ES21QA2 Design of Measurement System - Assignment 2</hi><hi rend="underlined bold"> A stylus type instrument (Profilometer)</hi></titlePart></docTitle><titlePart><hi rend="bold">by<name type="student ID"/></hi><hi rend="bold"><name type="student name"/></hi></titlePart><titlePart><hi rend="bold">Report Reference Code: ES21Q Affiliation: 2nd Year Mechanical Engineering</hi><hi rend="bold"> Report performed on: 28 April 2005</hi></titlePart></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="abstract"><head rend="underlined bold">Summary</head><p n="p1.42"><s n="s1.8;p1.42">The aim of the assignment is to design a stylus instrument to measure the surface profile of work-piece. </s><s n="s2.8;p1.42">The stylus instrument is broken down into three parts, mechanical system, sensing elements and output system. </s><s n="s3.8;p1.42">Mechanical system defines the setup of stylus, stylus beam and spring, also, skidded system is chosen for the reference datum of the instrument. </s><s n="s4.8;p1.42">A LVDT is selected as sensing element, because it has got lots advantages over other displacement sensors. </s><s n="s5.8;p1.42">The vertical movements of the stylus is transformed into an electrical signal through the LVDT, the LVDT output is insufficient to be outputted as it is very small and is therefore amplified. </s><s n="s6.8;p1.42">In order to eliminate unwanted frequency, a filter is added during data processing. </s><s n="s7.8;p1.42">The design is used a gauge mechanism to represent the roughness average of the surface. </s><s n="s8.8;p1.42">If a PC is used, then, an A/D converter is connected between the gauge mechanism and the PC, a digital form of roughness average is displayed. </s></p></div1><div1 type="front-back-matter"><head rend="underlined bold">Table of Contents</head><p/></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">Introduction</head><p n="p2.42"><s n="s1.3;p2.42">The aim of the assignment is to design a stylus instrument to measure the surface profile of work-piece. </s><s n="s2.3;p2.42">Stylus instruments are the best-known and most widely used instrument of the tracer type with electronic amplification of the stylus movement as it is traversed over the test surface. </s><s n="s3.3;p2.42">The sharply pointed stylus is rested lightly on the surface of a tested work-piece, as it traverses slowly in a straight line across the surface, the vertical movements of the stylus relative to a reference datum are measured by a sensor, and it converts the information into an electrical signal, processed to give analog or digital representation of the profile. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">Theory</head><p n="p3.42"><s n="s1.5;p3.42">Surface finish, or texture, consists of the peaks and valleys that make up a surface and their direction on the surface. </s><s n="s2.5;p3.42">On analysis, texture can be broken down into three components: roughness, waviness and form. </s><s n="s3.5;p3.42">Roughness is irregularities inherent in the production left by the machining agent such as cutting, tearing and surface fatigue, and it is a basic parameter to describe surface characteristics. </s><s n="s4.5;p3.42">Currently, centre-line-average, or roughness average, is the parameter most widely specified and measured. </s><s n="s5.5;p3.42">In this design, the roughness average is the only parameter to be measured. </s></p><p n="p4.42"><s n="s1.3;p4.42">The stylus instrument system can be divided into three elements, which are mechanical system, sensing elements and output system. </s><s n="s2.3;p4.42">The mechanical system is the pick-up system. </s><s n="s3.3;p4.42">The surface deviations traced by the stylus are received by mechanical system. </s></p><p n="p5.42"><s n="s1.2;p5.42">The sensing element measures the vertical movements of the stylus from mechanical system. </s><s n="s2.2;p5.42">And the movements are transformed into electrical signal. </s></p><p n="p6.42"><s n="s1.1;p6.42">The output of the sensing element is converted into a form more suitable for further processing, and the output system displays the roughness average visually using the most appropriate format. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">System Design</head><div2><head>Mechanical system</head><p n="p7.42"><s n="s1.3;p7.42">In mechanical system, the stylus is attached to a lever arm; knife edge pivot and a spring are set up with the stylus beam, it is shown schematically in Fig. </s><s n="s2.3;p7.42">1. </s><s n="s3.3;p7.42">Part texture is </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0254b-pic.001"><head rend="italic">Fig. 1 Schematic diagram of a stylus instrument</head></figure><p n="p8.42"><s n="s1.3;p8.42">measured by moving a stylus in a straight line across the surface, and by monitoring the vertical movement of the stylus. </s><s n="s2.3;p8.42">In this design, the surface of the part itself is used as a reference, these are called skidded gages. </s><s n="s3.3;p8.42">The signal from stylus is compared with the reference, then it is transferred to the other end of the stylus beam, which is connected with a sensing element. </s></p><p n="p9.42"><s n="s1.6;p9.42">The initial signal of the surface profile is come from the movements of the stylus; the traverse length <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0254b-form.001"/> includes an initial run-up length to allow the stylus to accelerate to constant speed and a final run-out length to allow it to stop (Fig. </s><s n="s2.6;p9.42">2). </s><s n="s3.6;p9.42">Only the portion in between the measurement length <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0254b-form.002"/>, is used for assessment. </s><s n="s4.6;p9.42">A standard roughness evaluation length <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0254b-form.003"/> is equal to <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0254b-form.004"/> being comprised five-sample length. </s><s n="s5.6;p9.42">Each sample of length <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0254b-form.005"/> is equal to the filter cut-off <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0254b-form.006"/>. </s><s n="s6.6;p9.42">Because there is so much statistical variation in most roughness parameters, some parameter values are </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0254b-fig.001"><head><hi rend="italic">Fig.2 Sample length </hi><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0254b-form.007"/><hi rend="italic">, assessment length </hi><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0254b-form.008"/><hi rend="italic"> and traverse length </hi><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0254b-form.009"/> .</head></figure><p n="p10.42"><s n="s1.2;p10.42">calculated for each sample length individually, and the individual values are then averaged over the whole measuring length. </s><s n="s2.2;p10.42">Other parameter values are referred to the entire evaluation length. </s></p><p n="p11.42"><s n="s1.1;p11.42">The average roughness <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0254b-form.010"/> can be calculated by </s></p><p n="p12.42"><s n="s1.1;p12.42"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0254b-form.011"/> </s></p><p n="p13.42"><s n="s1.2;p13.42">It is the area between the roughness profile and its mean line, or the integral of the absolute value of the roughness profile height over the evaluation length <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0254b-form.012"/> (Fig. </s><s n="s2.2;p13.42">3). </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0254b-fig.002"><head><hi rend="italic">Fig. 3 The average roughness </hi><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0254b-form.013"/></head></figure><p n="p14.42"><s n="s1.1;p14.42">The mean line is defined as the line parallel to the general profile of the surface such that </s></p><p n="p15.42"><s n="s1.1;p15.42"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0254b-form.014"/> </s></p><p n="p16.42"><s n="s1.1;p16.42">So, L indicates the evaluation length <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0254b-form.015"/>, and <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0254b-form.016"/> is the surface profile relative to the mean line. </s></p><p n="p17.42"><s n="s1.1;p17.42">When evaluated from digital data, the integral is normally approximated by a trapezoidal rule: </s></p><p n="p18.42"><s n="s1.1;p18.42"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0254b-form.017"/> </s></p><p n="p19.42"><s n="s1.3;p19.42">The dynamic characteristics of the mechanical system are affected by several factors. </s><s n="s2.3;p19.42">Some of these factors are the size of the stylus, stylus load, stylus speed, and lateral deflection by asperities. </s><s n="s3.3;p19.42">The effect of stylus size is illustrated in Figure 4, which is a </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0254b-fig.003"><head rend="italic">Fig. 4 The actual surface and traced surface</head></figure><p n="p20.42"><s n="s1.8;p20.42">schematic comparison of an actual surface against the traced surface. </s><s n="s2.8;p20.42">Because the stylus' tip is larger than the troughs of the surface, the surface trace is inaccurate with the actual surface. </s><s n="s3.8;p20.42">This effect becomes more significant as the curvature of the peaks and valleys decrease, or the magnitude of the slope increases. </s><s n="s4.8;p20.42">Regarding the effect of stylus load, it is a topic which has been argued. </s><s n="s5.8;p20.42">Whereas, if the magnitude of plastic deformation is the same everywhere along the segment measured, the profile obtained is still representative of the original surface. </s><s n="s6.8;p20.42">Another factor is if the stylus loses contact with the surface as a result of its speed, but, for most surfaces, the effect introduced by the stylus speed is minor. </s><s n="s7.8;p20.42">Lateral deflection of the stylus has also been considered as a factor. </s><s n="s8.8;p20.42">Nevertheless, its effect on profile measurement is also determined to be inconsequential when compared to the dimensions of the stylus. </s></p><p n="p21.42"><s n="s1.1;p21.42">In addition, an extra displacement of the stylus will be caused by stylus beam and pick-up body, as the stylus beam can resonate to give an unwanted output, and the pick-up body can vibrate as a simple beam clamped at one end. </s></p><p n="p22.42"><s n="s1.4;p22.42">The frequency response of the stylus and its supporting system is a question of design. </s><s n="s2.4;p22.42">To ensure that the stylus can accurately trace the surface irregularities within the range of traversing speeds, the stylus, stylus beam, and transducer elements should be of minimum mass. </s><s n="s3.4;p22.42">And the stylus beam must be rigid, the knife edge pivot friction should be minimal. </s><s n="s4.4;p22.42">The frequency response is given by </s></p><p n="p23.42"><s n="s1.1;p23.42"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0254b-form.018"/> </s></p><p n="p24.42"><s n="s1.3;p24.42">where K is the spring stiffness of the mechanical system, M is the effective mass. </s><s n="s2.3;p24.42">With respect to the spring stiffness in the mechanical system, in general, it has to be kept as low as possible because the stylus may damage the surface as it measures. </s><s n="s3.3;p24.42">A typical value for the spring stiffness is <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0254b-form.019"/>. </s></p></div2><div2><head>Sensing elements</head><p n="p25.42"><s n="s1.2;p25.42">Several types of sensing methods are in use for measuring surface profiles. </s><s n="s2.2;p25.42">There are four basic displacement sensors, such as variable inductance sensor, capacitive sensor, laser interferometer and optical encoders. </s></p><p n="p26.42"><s n="s1.5;p26.42">A kind of variable inductance sensor has been chosen as a sensing method in this design, which is LVDT (Linear variable differential transformer). </s><s n="s2.5;p26.42">Since LVDTs are very linear and repeatable, they have a definite zero point and have good response as far as the highest frequency they can resolve. </s><s n="s3.5;p26.42">Another advantage of the LVDT principle over other types of displacement transducer is their high degree of robustness. </s><s n="s4.5;p26.42">Furthermore, there is no physical contact across the sensing element. </s><s n="s5.5;p26.42">This also means that LVDTs can be made waterproof and in a format suitable for the most arduous applications. </s></p><p n="p27.42"><s n="s1.2;p27.42">The LVDT principle of measurement is based on magnetic transfer which also means that the resolution of LVDT transducers in infinite. </s><s n="s2.2;p27.42">The smallest fraction of movement can be detected by suitable signal conditioning electronics. </s></p><p n="p28.42"><s n="s1.8;p28.42">This sensor is a transformer which comprises a single primary winding and two identical secondary windings wound on a tubular ferromagnetic former, it is shown as Fig. </s><s n="s2.8;p28.42">5. </s><s n="s3.8;p28.42">The primary winding is excited by an a.c voltage <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0254b-form.020"/>, which is normally in the region of 400 to 50 KHZ to 10 V rms. </s><s n="s4.8;p28.42">The two secondaries are connected in series opposition so that the output voltage is the difference of the voltages induced between secondary coil 1 and secondary coil 2. </s><s n="s5.8;p28.42">A ferromagnetic core or plunger moves inside the former, while in an actual transducer, the core, primary coil, and secondary coils share a common axis, as shown in Fig. </s><s n="s6.8;p28.42">5. </s><s n="s7.8;p28.42">As the core moves up or down, the mutual inductance between the primary and secondaries is changed. </s><s n="s8.8;p28.42">With </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0254b-pic.002"><head rend="italic">Fig. 5 Circuit diagram representing LVDT</head></figure><p n="p29.42"><s n="s1.1;p29.42">the core removed, the secondary voltages <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0254b-form.021"/> and <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0254b-form.022"/> are ideally equal, so that </s></p><p n="p30.42"><s n="s1.1;p30.42"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0254b-form.023"/> </s></p><p n="p31.42"><s n="s1.6;p31.42">With the core in the former, <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0254b-form.024"/> and <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0254b-form.025"/> change with core position x, causing amplitude <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0254b-form.026"/> and phase <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0254b-form.027"/> to change. </s><s n="s2.6;p31.42">The relationship between <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0254b-form.028"/>, <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0254b-form.029"/> and x are shown in Fig. </s><s n="s3.6;p31.42">6. </s><s n="s4.6;p31.42">It represents that there is a null point C at the centre of the sensor (<formula notation="" id="BAWE_0254b-form.030"/>), since an equal voltage is induced into each coil, and the secondaries are connected in opposition so that in the central position the outputs of the two secondaries cancel each other out, where <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0254b-form.031"/>. </s><s n="s5.6;p31.42">At the points A and B, equally spaced either side of the null point, <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0254b-form.032"/> has the same value <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0254b-form.033"/>. </s><s n="s6.6;p31.42">However, they have got different phases, <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0254b-form.034"/>, <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0254b-form.035"/>. </s></p><p n="p32.42"><s n="s1.2;p32.42">With the stylus instrument, the LVDT is connected with mechanical system. </s><s n="s2.2;p32.42">The tubular ferrous core is fixed in the end of the stylus beam which has got a stylus on </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0254b-fig.004"><head rend="italic">Fig. 6 LVDT characteristics</head></figure><p n="p33.42"><s n="s1.2;p33.42">the other end, the primary and secondary coils are attached with the other part of the mechanical system, which share a common axis with the core (Fig. </s><s n="s2.2;p33.42">1). </s></p><p n="p34.42"><s n="s1.2;p34.42">The up and down movements of the stylus make the ferrous core of LVDT move inside the coils through the stylus beam. </s><s n="s2.2;p34.42">Therefore, the displacement signal is transformed into an electrical signal. </s></p></div2><div2><head>Output system</head><p n="p35.42"><s n="s1.3;p35.42">The electrical signal from the LVDT is very small, it has to be amplified with an appropriate amplifier, in order to achieve a proper level of output voltage. </s><s n="s2.3;p35.42">Furthermore, with processing data, a kind of filter is always needed to separate certain frequency components of a surface profile, this process is called filtering. </s><s n="s3.3;p35.42">It also means that the output need go through filters to eliminate some unwanted signals. </s></p><p n="p36.42"><s n="s1.5;p36.42">After the output data has been processed it will need to be presented in a form, which the user can understand. </s><s n="s2.5;p36.42">The easiest way to show the output would be connecting the system to a gauge mechanism, which represents the output in an analogue form (Fig. </s><s n="s3.5;p36.42">7). </s><s n="s4.5;p36.42">Whereas, analogue gauge is not effective in showing the results of the stylus measurement, so an analogue to digital converter is required to translate the reading into binary form (Fig. </s><s n="s5.5;p36.42">8). </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0254b-pic.003"><head>Fig. 7 Analogue form</head></figure><figure id="BAWE_0254b-pic.004"><head>Fig. 8 Digital form</head></figure></div2><div2><head>Overall system</head><figure id="BAWE_0254b-fig.005"/><p n="p37.42"><s n="s1.8;p37.42">This is a block diagram of the overall system. </s><s n="s2.8;p37.42">Work-piece is the measured surface of materials. </s><s n="s3.8;p37.42">Sensor is the stylus which incorporated in the mechanical system, its function is moving across the surface of work-piece to collect the original data of surface profile. </s><s n="s4.8;p37.42">In this design, a LVDT is chosen as transducer, and the reference is skid reference datum, the vertical movements of the stylus are compared with the reference datum, and the LVDT transform this information into an electrical signal which can be further processing. </s><s n="s5.8;p37.42">The block of processing data comprises lots of procedures, such as amplification, filtering. </s><s n="s6.8;p37.42">Finally, the output will be represented in an analogue form or a digital form, which can be read by user and describe the roughness of the measured surface. </s><s n="s7.8;p37.42">The possible arrangement of the overall system is shown as Fig. </s><s n="s8.8;p37.42">9. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0254b-pic.005"><head>Fig. 9 The arrangement of the overall system</head></figure></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">Analysis and Discussion</head><p n="p38.42"><s n="s1.5;p38.42">If an A/D converter and a PC are to be used as a part of the instrument system, which means the output will be a digital form, it will make the system much better, and people can easily to read from the output, even print out the result to do further research. </s><s n="s2.5;p38.42">The computer could analysis the signal and automatically correct the output signal from the amplifier and filter. </s><s n="s3.5;p38.42">This would allow the user to analysis the surface roughness even more easily. </s><s n="s4.5;p38.42">The computer will automatically change the analogue signal into sampled digital output. </s><s n="s5.5;p38.42">To do this, an A/D converter with 12-bits is suggested. </s></p><p n="p39.42"><s n="s1.3;p39.42">The measurement limitations in both horizontal and vertical direction depend on stylus size and geometry. </s><s n="s2.3;p39.42">Generally, stylus tips are flat or rounded tip, while rounded tip will provide less limitation in horizontal direction than flat one. </s><s n="s3.3;p39.42">In addition, limitation in vertical direction indicates the range of vertical displacement. </s></p><div2><head>IMPROVEMENTS</head><p rend="ordered" n="p40.42"><s n="s1.3;p40.42">Choosing a skidless gage instead of skid reference datum. </s><s n="s2.3;p40.42">Skidless system, by comparison, has a straightness reference located in the driver unit. </s><s n="s3.3;p40.42">This significantly reduces the possibility of false measurements that can occur with skidded systems. </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p41.42"><s n="s1.1;p41.42">If the measuring system has a suitable interface with a computer, and make it both Metric and Imperial mode of the digital outputs, the instrument will be wildly used. </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">Conclusions</head><p n="p42.42"><s n="s1.8;p42.42">To conclude, the general design does fulfill all the specifications set to it. </s><s n="s2.8;p42.42">A stylus instrument has been designed which allows the users to measure the roughness average of surface, which is displayed in analogue or digital form. </s><s n="s3.8;p42.42">The mechanical system has been analysis and clearly defined, several parameters that affecting the dynamic characteristics of the pick-up system is discussed as well. </s><s n="s4.8;p42.42">In this stylus instrument, a LVDT is chosen for a transducer since it has many advantages over other displacement sensors. </s><s n="s5.8;p42.42">In one word, the overall system can be described as four parts: sensor, transducer, process data, and output. </s><s n="s6.8;p42.42">Sensor collects original information from a surface, transducer transforms it into an electrical signal, then an amplifier and a filter are used to improve the data signal during data processing. </s><s n="s7.8;p42.42">After that, output is represented with gauge mechanism or computer. </s><s n="s8.8;p42.42">Finally, surface roughness is achieved. </s></p></div1></body><back><div1 type="bibliography"><head rend="underlined bold">Bibliography</head><p>1. Handbook of surface and nanometrology</p><p> c2003</p><p> Whitehouse, D. J.</p><p> P372-376</p><p> P400-401</p><p> P406-423</p><p>2. Properties and metrology of surfaces</p><p> 1968</p><p> International conference organized by the Institution at Oxford</p><p> P335-337</p><p>Principles of measurement systems</p><p>1995</p><p> Bentley, John P</p><p> P146-150</p><p><seg type="URL" n="http://www.predev.com/smg/instrument.htm"/></p><p>5. <seg type="URL" n="http://www.qualitydigest.com/may98/html/surface.html"/></p><p>6. <seg type="URL" n="http://www.mmsonline.com/articles/039903.html"/></p><p>7. <seg type="URL" n="http://www.predev.com/surf400.htm"/></p><p>8. <seg type="URL" n="http://www.qualitest-inc.com/tr100.htm"/></p><p>9. <seg type="URL" n="http://www.qualitymag.com/CDA/ArticleInformation/features/BNP__Features__Item/0,6425,100324,00.html"/></p><p>10. <seg type="URL" n="http://www.qfm.uni-erlangen.de/gps/content/Chapters/chapter_16.htm#16.1%20%20%20%20%20Introduction"/></p></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
