<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_0254g" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Laboratory Report: Centrifugal Pump Experiment</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">The document has a title page which contains:
document title
title part</note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">Running text contains reference to external or missing appendix.
</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">2</p><p n="date">2005-05</p><p n="module title">Fluid Mechanics</p><p n="module code">ES252</p><p n="genre family">Methodology recount</p><p n="discipline">Engineering</p><p n="disciplinary group">PS</p><p n="grade">M</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">1419</p><p n="number of s-units">77</p><p n="number of p">50</p><p n="number of tables">1</p><p n="number of figures">1</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">34</p><p n="number of lists">2</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">9</p><p n="abstract present">abstract present</p><p n="average words per s-unit">18.4</p><p n="average s-units per p">1.5</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">m</p><p n="year of birth">1982</p><p n="first language">Chinese unspecified</p><p n="education">OSA</p><p n="course">Engineering</p><p n="student ID">0254</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><titlePart rend="bold">University of <name type="university"/> School of Engineering</titlePart><docTitle><titlePart rend="bold">ES252A2 Laboratory Report Centrifugal Pump Experiment</titlePart></docTitle><titlePart><hi rend="bold">by<name type="student ID"/></hi><hi rend="bold"><name type="student name"/></hi></titlePart><titlePart><hi rend="bold">Report Reference Code: ES252 Affiliation: 2nd Year Mechanical Engineering</hi><hi rend="bold"> Report of laboratory performed on: 4 March 2005 Laboratory performed on 11th Feb 2005, with group members:</hi><hi rend="bold"><name type="student name"/>, <name type="student name"/>. <name type="student name"/>.</hi> </titlePart></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="abstract"><head rend="underlined bold">Summary</head><p n="p1.50"><s n="s1.9;p1.50">An experiment was conducted to investigate the performance characteristics of a single stage centrifugal pump at two different speed settings, which were 2000 RPM and 3000 RPM. Nineteen sets of measured suction and delivery pressure, force, pump speed and manometer readings were obtained. </s><s n="s2.9;p1.50">Total head, input power, discharge, output power and efficiency were calculated with the fundamental equations. </s><s n="s3.9;p1.50">Three non-dimensional groups were introduced and compared with each other. </s><s n="s4.9;p1.50">Efficiency, input power and total head were compared with discharge. </s><s n="s5.9;p1.50">The relationship between the total head and the discharge were not affected by pump speed. </s><s n="s6.9;p1.50">As the discharge increased, the input power increased faster with higher pump speed. </s><s n="s7.9;p1.50">And higher pump speed made the centrifugal pump works much more efficient. </s><s n="s8.9;p1.50">The errors associated with the measured values may have been caused by improperly balancing the spring. </s><s n="s9.9;p1.50">And error propagation was interpreted like that the dissipated energy was not considered within the suction and delivery valves when the readings were made from pressure meters. </s></p></div1><div1 type="front-back-matter"><head rend="underlined bold">Table of Contents</head><p/></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">Introduction</head><p n="p2.50"><s n="s1.4;p2.50">The performance characteristics of a single stage centrifugal pump can be investigated by measuring the suction and delivery pressure, the force of the spring balance, and the venturi meter manometer. </s><s n="s2.4;p2.50">The suction and delivery pressure provides a means of measuring total head. </s><s n="s3.4;p2.50">The force and the manometer are used to estimate input power and output power respectively. </s><s n="s4.4;p2.50">This application was explored through achieving one objective which was the efficiency, input power and total head of a single stage centrifugal pump at two different speed settings, which were 2000 and 3000 RPM. </s></p><p n="p3.50"><s n="s1.1;p3.50">The relationship of total head, suction and delivery pressure is </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p4.50"><s n="s1.1;p4.50"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0254g-form.001"/> (1) </s></p><p n="p5.50"><s n="s1.1;p5.50">And the total pressure head in <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0254g-form.002"/> is represented as below </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p6.50"><s n="s1.1;p6.50"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0254g-form.003"/> (2) </s></p><p n="p7.50"><s n="s1.1;p7.50">Here <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0254g-form.004"/> depends on the total head <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0254g-form.005"/>, the mass density of water <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0254g-form.006"/> and the gravitational constant <hi rend="italic">g</hi>. </s></p><p n="p8.50"><s n="s1.1;p8.50">The power input equation </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p9.50"><s n="s1.1;p9.50"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0254g-form.007"/> (3) </s></p><p n="p10.50"><s n="s1.2;p10.50">yields the relationship between torque and angular speed of the pump. </s><s n="s2.2;p10.50">In Eq.3, the torque is determined by the product of force and torque arm length. </s></p><p n="p11.50"><s n="s1.1;p11.50">The calibration of venturi meter discharge is represented as below </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p12.50"><s n="s1.1;p12.50"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0254g-form.008"/> (4) </s></p><p n="p13.50"><s n="s1.1;p13.50">Here the discharge <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0254g-form.009"/> depends on calibration constant <hi rend="italic">c</hi>, which is written on the machine, and manometer reading in <hi rend="italic">mm</hi> mercury <hi rend="italic">h</hi>. </s></p><p n="p14.50"><s n="s1.1;p14.50">The power output equation </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p15.50"><s n="s1.1;p15.50"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0254g-form.010"/> (5) </s></p><p n="p16.50"><s n="s1.1;p16.50">yields the relationship between the total head <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0254g-form.011"/> and discharge <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0254g-form.012"/>. </s></p><p n="p17.50"><s n="s1.1;p17.50">Determining the efficiency of the single centrifugal pump by using the following equation </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p18.50"><s n="s1.1;p18.50"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0254g-form.013"/> (6) </s></p><p n="p19.50"><s n="s1.1;p19.50">Here <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0254g-form.014"/> and <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0254g-form.015"/> represent the power output and power input respectively. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">Apparatus and Methods</head><p n="p20.50"><s n="s1.4;p20.50">The apparatus was manufactured by PLINT Limited, it consisted of a suction valve, a discharge valve, a suction pressure meter and a delivery pressure meter. </s><s n="s2.4;p20.50">A pump speed meter showed the angular velocity of the centrifugal pump in RPM, it was adjustable. </s><s n="s3.4;p20.50">A spring was used to balance the torque arm with a fixed pointer, then, force can be measured. </s><s n="s4.4;p20.50">A venturi meter manometer, which was located on the right of the apparatus, was used to measure the discharge. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0254g-pic.001"><head rend="bold">A picture of a single stage centrifugal pump (manufactured by PLINT Limited)</head></figure><p n="p21.50"><s n="s1.1;p21.50">The following procedure was used to obtain the basic experiment data. </s></p><list type="ordered"><item>Open the suction value and close the discharge value.</item><item>Switch on the pump and run at maximum speed.</item><item>Open the delivery valve fully. Run for a few minutes to clear any air from the system, and record the delivery pressure.</item><item>Record the delivery pressure when the deliver valve is fully closed.</item><item>Decide the various settings of the delivery valve depend on the range of delivery pressure.</item><item>Set the pump speed to 2000 RPM.</item><item>Record the following:</item><item>--suction and delivery pressure</item><item>--the force after adjusting the level of the spring balance so that the point on the arm coincides with the fixed pointer</item><item>--the venturi meter manometer reading</item><item>Collect data for 9 to 10 different settings of the delivery value, adjusting the speed to the appropriate value if necessary for each setting.</item><item>Set the pump speed to 3000 RPM and repeat steps 7 and 8.</item></list></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">Observations and Results</head><p n="p22.50"><s n="s1.1;p22.50">The basic data collected, it was tabulated as Table 1. </s></p><table id="BAWE_0254g-tab.001"><head rend="bold">Table 1. Experimental Recording</head><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p23.50"><s n="s1.3;p23.50">Eq.1 and Eq.2 were used to calculate total head, discharge was achieved by Eq.4, hence, power input and power output can be worked out with Eq.3 and Eq.5 respectively, they leaded to calculate the efficiency of the pump. </s><s n="s2.3;p23.50">The full results appeared in Table 2 in the Appendix 1. </s><s n="s3.3;p23.50">Here, the one with 0.68 <hi rend="italic">bar</hi> delivery pressure and 3000 RPM pump speed was chosen for an example. </s></p><p n="p24.50"><s n="s1.1;p24.50">The measured values were: </s></p><list type="simple"><item><hi rend="italic">Suction pressure</hi> = <hi rend="italic">-0.16 bar </hi></item><item rend="italic">Delivery pressure = 0.68 bar</item><item rend="italic"> Force (F) = 6.0 N</item><item><hi rend="italic"> Pump speed (</hi><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0254g-form.016"/><hi rend="italic">) = 2987 RPM</hi></item><item><hi rend="italic"> Manometer (h) =</hi> <hi rend="italic">277 mm Hg</hi></item></list><p n="p25.50"><s n="s1.1;p25.50">Total head <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0254g-form.017"/> was calculated with Eq.1. </s></p><p n="p26.50"><s n="s1.1;p26.50"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0254g-form.018"/> </s></p><p n="p27.50"><s n="s1.1;p27.50">Therefore, the total pressure head in <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0254g-form.019"/> was calculated with Eq.2. </s></p><p n="p28.50"><s n="s1.1;p28.50"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0254g-form.020"/> </s></p><p n="p29.50"><s n="s1.1;p29.50">And power input was calculated with Eq.3 using the measured values of F and <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0254g-form.021"/>. </s></p><p n="p30.50"><s n="s1.1;p30.50"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0254g-form.022"/> </s></p><p n="p31.50"><s n="s1.1;p31.50">Discharge was calculated with Eq.4. </s></p><p n="p32.50"><s n="s1.1;p32.50"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0254g-form.023"/> </s></p><p n="p33.50"><s n="s1.1;p33.50">And power output was calculated with Eq.5 using the calculated values of <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0254g-form.024"/> and <hi rend="italic">Q</hi>. </s></p><p n="p34.50"><s n="s1.1;p34.50"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0254g-form.025"/> </s></p><p n="p35.50"><s n="s1.1;p35.50">With power input and power output, the efficiency of the pump was calculated by Eq.6. </s></p><p n="p36.50"><s n="s1.1;p36.50"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0254g-form.026"/> </s></p><p n="p37.50"><s n="s1.1;p37.50">In order to estimate non-dimensional results, three non-dimensional groups were introduced. </s></p><p n="p38.50"><s n="s1.1;p38.50">Firstly <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0254g-form.027"/> </s></p><p n="p39.50"><s n="s1.1;p39.50">Secondly <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0254g-form.028"/> </s></p><p n="p40.50"><s n="s1.1;p40.50">Thirdly <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0254g-form.029"/> </s></p><p n="p41.50"><s n="s1.1;p41.50">The relationship between input power and discharge, efficiency and discharge, total head and discharge were shown in Figure 1 in the Appendix 2, which represented the pump performance characteristics. </s></p><p n="p42.50"><s n="s1.1;p42.50">And the non-dimensional groups were shown in Figure 2 in the Appendix 2. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">Analysis and Discussion of Results</head><p n="p43.50"><s n="s1.7;p43.50">Figure 1 in the Appendix 2 showed the performance characteristics of the centrifugal pump. </s><s n="s2.7;p43.50">Firstly, the total head of the pump decreased as the discharge increased, whatever the pump frequency was 2000 RPM or 3000 RPM. The curves of the relationship between total head and discharge were identical between 2000 RPM and 3000 RPM, but the total head of 3000 RPM was much higher than the one with 2000 RPM. Secondly, the efficiency was fluctuant as the discharge increased. </s><s n="s3.7;p43.50">Whereas, the efficiency was direct proportional to the discharge for both speed settings when the discharge was less than <hi rend="italic">0.5 l/s</hi>. </s><s n="s4.7;p43.50">And for the pump speed of 2000 RPM, the efficiency peaked when the discharge was about <hi rend="italic">1 l/s</hi>, for the pump speed of 3000 RPM, the efficiency peaked when the discharge was about <hi rend="italic">0.9 l/s</hi>. </s><s n="s5.7;p43.50">The highest value of efficiency for 3000 RPM was <hi rend="italic">64%</hi>, and the peak efficiency for 2000 RPM was <hi rend="italic">18</hi> percentages less, which was <hi rend="italic">46%</hi>. </s><s n="s6.7;p43.50">Overall, the higher speed pump worked more efficient than lower speed pump. </s><s n="s7.7;p43.50">Thirdly, input power was direct proportional to the discharge for both speed settings, but the gradient of the relationship with 3000 RPM was greater than the one with 2000 RPM, it indicated that the input power increased faster with higher pump speed. </s></p><p n="p44.50"><s n="s1.2;p44.50">Figure 2 in the Appendix 2 showed the relationship among the non-dimensional groups. </s><s n="s2.2;p44.50">Firstly, the non-dimensional group <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0254g-form.030"/> was inverse proportional to the non-dimensional group <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0254g-form.031"/> for both speed settings, and those two linear lines were parallel, but the one with 3000 RPM was 5 units greater than the one with 2000 RPM. Secondly, the non-dimensional group <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0254g-form.032"/> decreased as the non-dimensional group <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0254g-form.033"/> increased, the relationship was a curve, those two curves of 3000 RPM and 2000 RPM were identical, but the non-dimensional group <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0254g-form.034"/> was greater with higher pump speed. </s></p><p n="p45.50"><s n="s1.4;p45.50">From Table 2 in the Appendix 1, two groups of manometer reading were minus, and it caused that some parameters can not be achieved. </s><s n="s2.4;p45.50">Two groups of manometer reading were really small, which was only <hi rend="italic">1 mm</hi> Hg, and it caused that some parameters were inaccurate. </s><s n="s3.4;p45.50">Therefore, two or three points were far away from the graphs that showed in both Figure 1 and Figure 2 in the Appendix 2, but they were ignored during drawing. </s><s n="s4.4;p45.50">A likely explanation was that the level of the spring was not properly balanced during the experiment. </s></p><p n="p46.50"><s n="s1.1;p46.50">Standard error propagation methods showed that measured values of suction and delivery pressure were not accurately the total pressure needed in the fundamental calculation, because there was friction in the suction and delivery valve, and dissipated energy was not considered when the suction and delivery pressure were read from pressure meters. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">Conclusions</head><p n="p47.50"><s n="s1.1;p47.50">The experiment yielded the following conclusions: </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p48.50"><s n="s1.1;p48.50">The efficiency of a single stage centrifugal pump at high pump speed (3000 RPM) is better than it at low pump speed (2000 RPM). </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p49.50"><s n="s1.1;p49.50">The input power with high pump speed increases faster than the one with low pump speed as discharge increases. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p50.50"><s n="s1.1;p50.50">The relationship between total head and discharge is not affected by pump speed, but higher pump speed provides higher total head. </s></p></div1></body><back><div1 type="missing or external appendix"><p/></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
