<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_0254e" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Electrical Machines Laboratory Report</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">The document has a title page which contains:
document title
title part</note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">deleted: header: student name, university name; footer: page numbers</note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">appendices: laboratory briefing sheet, lab notes</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">1</p><p n="date">2003-05</p><p n="module title">Electrical and Electronic Systems</p><p n="module code">ES163</p><p n="genre family">Methodology recount</p><p n="discipline">Engineering</p><p n="disciplinary group">PS</p><p n="grade">M</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">1251</p><p n="number of s-units">47</p><p n="number of p">30</p><p n="number of tables">2</p><p n="number of figures">0</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">3</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">0</p><p n="abstract present">abstract present</p><p n="average words per s-unit">26.6</p><p n="average s-units per p">1.6</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">m</p><p n="year of birth">1982</p><p n="first language">Chinese unspecified</p><p n="education">OSA</p><p n="course">Engineering</p><p n="student ID">0254</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><docTitle><titlePart><hi rend="bold">Electrical and Electronic Systems Electrical Machines Laboratory Report</hi><hi rend="bold"> ES163A9B</hi></titlePart></docTitle><titlePart><hi rend="bold"><name type="student name"/> First Year School of Engineering</hi><hi rend="bold"> University of <name type="university"/> 26 January 2004</hi></titlePart></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="abstract"><head rend="underlined bold">Summary</head><p n="p1.30"><s n="s1.8;p1.30">In order to develop an understanding of current, voltage, power and power factor in a simple electrical power system, and know well on measurement of torque and mechanical power, the performance of a small three-phase induction motor, we did a laboratory about measurement of induction motor characteristics. </s><s n="s2.8;p1.30">In this laboratory, a three-phase induction motor was connected to an electrically-controlled brake and an electrical speed-measuring device, and a control box showed us speed, torque and mechanical power output. </s><s n="s3.8;p1.30">At first, the motor was running at rated voltage on no-load, then, we increased the load torque in steps of 0.5Nm and repeated the above measurements until the motor was running at its rated output power of 300W, during this step, we recorded the value of torque, speed, mechanical power, current, power factor and electrical power input, after that, continue to increase the load torque in the same way and take measurements as before, stop it when the motor stalled. </s><s n="s4.8;p1.30">In this part, we could achieve a table of data, and calculate the percentage efficiency for each value of load. </s><s n="s5.8;p1.30">Therefore, we were able to plot two graphs (Graph 1 and Graph2). </s><s n="s6.8;p1.30">And the highest efficiency was about 78% from graph 2, the efficiency would be declined rapidly when the motor was overloaded. </s><s n="s7.8;p1.30">Meanwhile, if we clipped the current probe round one of the motor supply leads, and connected it to Ch1 of the oscilloscope, we could get two copies of the transient starting current of the motor from the oscilloscope. </s><s n="s8.8;p1.30">From these two copies, we could calculated the peak starting current of the motor, which was 5.8A, and the time taken to reach operating speed on no-load and full load, which was 100ms and 150ms respectively. </s></p></div1><div1 type="front-back-matter"><head rend="underlined">CONTENTS</head><p/></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">1. Introduction</head><p n="p2.30"><s n="s1.7;p2.30">In this electrical machines laboratory, we did measurement of induction motor characteristics. </s><s n="s2.7;p2.30">The aim of the experiment was to develop an understanding of current, voltage, power and power factor in a simple electrical power system, and familiar with measurement of torque and mechanical power and the performance of a small three-phase induction motor. </s><s n="s3.7;p2.30">The three-phase induction motor was the main part of this exercise, it was connected to a test system comprising a dynamometer and a tachometer. </s><s n="s4.7;p2.30">The torque on the brake was measured by a cantilever spring fitted with a strain gauge, and there was a control box that collected signals from the cantilever spring and the tachometer. </s><s n="s5.7;p2.30">It displayed speed, torque and mechanical power output. </s><s n="s6.7;p2.30">In this exercise, by recording these quantities, we could calculate efficiency of this system, and draw graphs of these data. </s><s n="s7.7;p2.30">Finally, we would know more details about electrical machines. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">2. Apparatus and Methods</head><div2><head rend="bold">2.1 Apparatus</head><p n="p3.30"><s n="s1.1;p3.30">Electrical power test panel (Feedback) equipped with: </s></p><list type="simple"><item>Three-phase supply control unit, ref. 60-100 (The control unit)</item><item>Variable three-phase measurement unit, ref. 68-100 (The measuring unit)</item></list><p n="p4.30"><s n="s1.1;p4.30">Electrical machines test bed (Leroy Somer) equipped with </s></p><list type="simple"><item>Induction motor rated at 0.3kW 50Hz 1440rpm</item><item>(Delta-connected: 220V 1.75A, Star-connected 380V 1.00A)</item><item>Tachometer &amp; powder brake dynamometer (Leroy Somer Modmeca), rated at 300W for 15min, 500W for 5min &amp; equipped with overload trip.</item></list><p n="p5.30"><s n="s1.1;p5.30">Dynamometer control box (Modmeca 3) </s></p><list type="simple"><item>Oscilloscope (Tektronix TDS 210)</item><item>Current probe Lem Heme 20Amax, 100mV/A</item></list><p n="p6.30"><s n="s1.1;p6.30">Connecting leads 9, 4 mm to 4 mm with shrouded connectors </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">2.2 Methods</head><div3><head>Switch on C and the power switch (a green push-button) on the measuring unit, press 'PAGE' repeatedly to set the unit to display page 4 which shows 'V, L1, L2, L3' (Appendix 1, page 1).</head><p n="p7.30"/></div3><div3><head>Connect the variable three-phase outputs L1, L2, L3 and N on the supply panel to L1, L2, L3 and N respectively on the left-hand side of the measuring unit. Switch on B and D, press 'PAGE' to change the measurement display back to page 1. Increase the line-to-line voltage until it reads the rated motor voltage(380V) with in a tolerance of 1%.</head><p n="p8.30"/></div3><div3><head>Connect the three terminals L1, L2 and L3 on the right of the measuring unit to U1, V1 and W1 on the motor, then switch on D. The motor starts (Appendix 1, page 1). </head><p n="p9.30"/></div3><div3><head>Increase the load torque in steps of 0.5Nm and repeat the above measurements until the motor is running at its rated output power at 300W, then continue to increase the load torque in steps of 0.5Nm and take measurements as before. Continue until the motor stops.</head><p n="p10.30"/></div3><div3><head>Switch off D to stop the motor. Clip the current probe round one of the motor supply leads, connect it to Ch1 of the oscilloscope and switch it on. Set the oscilloscope correctly (Appendix 1, page 3). Switch on the motor, apply no-load to the motor while it is running, and a copy of the oscilloscope screen display can be printed when you press 'hardcopy' on the oscilloscope control panel. In the same way, you can get a copy of full load to the motor. Then switch it off.</head><p n="p11.30"><s n="s1.1;p11.30">N.B: Please check method details by the Appendix 1. </s></p></div3></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">3. Observations and Results</head><p n="p12.30"><s n="s1.1;p12.30">Measurements of output power, speed, torque and electrical power were recorded as below. </s></p><table id="BAWE_0254e-tab.001"><head rend="bold">Table 1</head><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p13.30"><s n="s1.1;p13.30">When the torque reached 5.0Nm, the motor stalled. </s></p><p n="p14.30"><s n="s1.1;p14.30">The copies of the transient starting current of the motor were gotten from oscilloscope (Graph 1 and Graph 2). </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">4. Analysis and Discussion of Results</head><div2><head>4.1 .</head><p n="p15.30"><s n="s1.2;p15.30">Analysis the measurements that we had got in the last part, we could plot a graph of torque vs. speed (Graph 3). </s><s n="s2.2;p15.30">After that, we need to calculate the percentage efficiency for each value of load. </s></p><p n="p16.30"><s n="s1.1;p16.30">Apply equation </s></p><p n="p17.30"><s n="s1.1;p17.30">Percentage efficiency = 100 x mechanical power out / electrical power in </s></p><p n="p18.30"><s n="s1.1;p18.30">We could achieve another table of data. </s></p><table id="BAWE_0254e-tab.002"><head rend="bold">Table 2</head><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p19.30"><s n="s1.4;p19.30">According to Table 2, we could plot a graph of efficiency vs. mechanical power output (Graph 4). </s><s n="s2.4;p19.30">From graph 3, it was obviously that torque decreased as speed increased. </s><s n="s3.4;p19.30">When speed was less than 1200 1/min, torque was generally stable, but torque declined rapidly since speed was greater than 1200 1/min. </s><s n="s4.4;p19.30">From graph 4, the efficiency was the highest when the mechanical power out was between 300W and 430W, in the remain range of variation of mechanical power out, it was increasing when it was from 0W to 300W, and it was decreasing when it was from 430W to 600W. </s></p></div2><div2><head>4.2 .</head><p n="p20.30"><s n="s1.3;p20.30">We also got two graphs from oscilloscope (Graph 1 and Graph 2). </s><s n="s2.3;p20.30">According to graph 1, the peak voltage was 580mV, and we knew scale factor was 100mV/A (Appendix 1, page 3). </s><s n="s3.3;p20.30">Therefore, the peak starting current of the motor could be calculated. </s></p><p n="p21.30"><s n="s1.1;p21.30">Peak current = 580mV x 1A / 100mV </s></p><p n="p22.30"><s n="s1.1;p22.30">= 5.8A </s></p><p n="p23.30"><s n="s1.2;p23.30">Now, we had to calculate the time taken to reach operating speed on no-load and full load. </s><s n="s2.2;p23.30">Graph 1 was about no-load, it took two scales to reach operating speed, and one scale was 50.0ms, so </s></p><p n="p24.30"><s n="s1.1;p24.30">The time taken for no-load = 50ms x 2 </s></p><p n="p25.30"><s n="s1.1;p25.30">= 100ms </s></p><p n="p26.30"><s n="s1.1;p26.30">Graph 2 was about full load, it took three scales to reach operating speed, and one scale wad the same as graph 1, so </s></p><p n="p27.30"><s n="s1.1;p27.30">The time taken for full load = 50ms x 3 </s></p><p n="p28.30"><s n="s1.1;p28.30">= 150ms </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">5. Conclusions</head><p n="p29.30"><s n="s1.3;p29.30">From this experiment, we know that the efficiency of load was really low when using the motor to drive small loads, and the efficiency was low when the motor was overloaded. </s><s n="s2.3;p29.30">The highest efficiency was about 78% in this exercise. </s><s n="s3.3;p29.30">And the peak starting current of the motor was 5.8A, the time taken to reach operating speed on no-load was 100ms, while it was 150ms for full load. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">6. Figures, Tables and Graphs</head><p n="p30.30"/></div1></body><back><div1 type="bibliography"><head rend="underlined bold">7. References and bibliography</head><p>Edward Haghes (rev. I McKenzie Smith):</p><p>"Electrical Technology" 7<hi rend="sup">th</hi> Edition, Longman 1995</p><p>Ch. 32pp 542-547 &amp; Ch. 41pp 698-703</p></div1><div1 type="appendix"><head rend="underlined bold">8. Appendices</head><p/></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
