<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_0254d" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Engineering Mechanics Laboratory Report - Bending and Torsion</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">The document has a title page which contains:
document title
title part</note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">deleted: header: student number, university name; footer: page numbers</note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">appendix: laboratory briefing sheet</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">1</p><p n="date">2003-05</p><p n="module title">Engineering Mechanics</p><p n="module code">ES161</p><p n="genre family">Methodology recount</p><p n="discipline">Engineering</p><p n="disciplinary group">PS</p><p n="grade">M</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">954</p><p n="number of s-units">35</p><p n="number of p">21</p><p n="number of tables">12</p><p n="number of figures">0</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">0</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">0</p><p n="abstract present">abstract present</p><p n="average words per s-unit">27.3</p><p n="average s-units per p">1.7</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">m</p><p n="year of birth">1982</p><p n="first language">Chinese unspecified</p><p n="education">OSA</p><p n="course">Engineering</p><p n="student ID">0254</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><titlePart rend="bold">University of <name type="university"/> School of Engineering</titlePart><docTitle><titlePart rend="bold">Engineering Mechanics Laboratory Report - Bending and Torsion</titlePart></docTitle><titlePart rend="bold">by<name type="student ID"/></titlePart><titlePart>Report Reference Code: ES161A7 Affiliation: Year 1 Engineering Report of laboratory performed on: 22 April 2004</titlePart></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="abstract"><head rend="bold">Summary</head><p n="p1.21"><s n="s1.6;p1.21">In order to provide a physical insight into the deflection in bending and torsion of statically determinate beams and shafts, a laboratory exercise about measurement of change in deflection and height with two separate test rigs were set up. </s><s n="s2.6;p1.21">In this laboratory, one test rig was a simply-supported beam, the other one was a cantilevered hollow shaft. </s><s n="s3.6;p1.21">In terms of the first one, a load was put at different positions on the beam and change in deflection at different positions was measured. </s><s n="s4.6;p1.21">And with the other one, it was done in two different conditions, one was putting load on a lever arm at 200mm from the shaft centre, and then change in height was measured, the other one just made the load 100mm less from the shaft centre. </s><s n="s5.6;p1.21">And the load was increased in steps of 0.2kg, data was recorded as well. </s><s n="s6.6;p1.21">Finally, from these tables of data, it was found out the change of deflection and height is proportional to the load, the range between the load point and deflection point had relationship with it as well. </s></p></div1><div1 type="front-back-matter"><head rend="bold">Contents</head><p/></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">1. Introduction</head><p n="p2.21"><s n="s1.5;p2.21">In this bending and torsion laboratory exercise, two separate test rigs were used, one with a simply-supported beam, and the other one with a cantilevered hollow shaft. </s><s n="s2.5;p2.21">The aim of the experiment was intended to provide a physical insight into the deflection in bending and torsion of statically determinate beams and shafts. </s><s n="s3.5;p2.21">In terms of the simply-supported beam, the load were changed at different positions on the beam and deflection at different positions on the beam were measured. </s><s n="s4.5;p2.21">In terms of the cantilevered shaft, load was set at different distance from the shaft centre on a lever arm, and it was decided to choose suitable values of load that would give reasonable deflections in those experiments. </s><s n="s5.5;p2.21">So the deflections of those two test rigs could be worked out, furthermore, more details about bending and torsion were achieved. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Observations and Results</head><div2><head>Measurements on the simply-supported beam</head><p n="p3.21"><s n="s1.1;p3.21">The laboratory set-up was on page 2 of the briefing sheet in Appendix 1. </s></p><p n="p4.21"><s n="s1.1;p4.21">Measurements of load and deflection were recorded as below. </s></p><table id="BAWE_0254d-tab.001"><head>① Change in load at 500mm V change in deflection at 500mm. Table 1 </head><row><cell/></row></table><table id="BAWE_0254d-tab.002"><head>② Change in load at 500mm V change in deflection at 1200mm. Table 2</head><row><cell/></row></table><table id="BAWE_0254d-tab.003"><head>③ Change in load at 500mm V change in deflection at 750mm. Table 3 </head><row><cell/></row></table><table id="BAWE_0254d-tab.004"><head>④ Change in load at 750mm V change in deflection at 500mm. Table 4</head><row><cell/></row></table></div2><div2><head>2.2 Measurement on the cantilevered shaft</head><p n="p5.21"><s n="s1.1;p5.21">The laboratory set-up was on page 2 of the briefing sheet in Appendix 1. </s></p><p n="p6.21"><s n="s1.1;p6.21">Measurement of load and height were recorded as below. </s></p><p n="p7.21"><s n="s1.1;p7.21">Initial height of the lever arm was 266.78mm. </s></p><table id="BAWE_0254d-tab.005"><head>① Load was applied 200mm from the shaft centre. Table 5</head><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p8.21"><s n="s1.1;p8.21">After that, on removing the weight, the height of the lever arm was 266.20mm. </s></p><table id="BAWE_0254d-tab.006"><head>② Load was applied 100mm from the shaft centre. Table 6</head><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p9.21"><s n="s1.1;p9.21">After that, on removing the weight, the height of the lever arm was 266.30mm. </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Analysis and Discussion of Results</head><div2><head>Analysis </head><p n="p10.21"><s n="s1.1;p10.21">The measurements that showed in the last part, in measurements on the simply-supported beam, deflections of the beam with variable load had been got in different situations, so change in deflection could be calculated easily. </s></p><p n="p11.21"><s n="s1.1;p11.21">Apply equation: </s></p><p n="p12.21"><s n="s1.1;p12.21">Change in deflection = Deflection with a load - Deflection without any load </s></p><p n="p13.21"><s n="s1.1;p13.21">Then another four tables of data for measurements on the simply-supported beam could be obtained. </s></p><table id="BAWE_0254d-tab.007"><head>① Change in load at 500mm V change in deflection at 500mm. Table 7</head><row><cell/></row></table><table id="BAWE_0254d-tab.008"><head>② Change in load at 500mm V change in deflection at 1200mm. Table 8</head><row><cell/></row></table><table id="BAWE_0254d-tab.009"><head>③ Change in load at 500mm V change in deflection at 750mm. Table 9</head><row><cell/></row></table><table id="BAWE_0254d-tab.010"><head>④ Change in load at 750mm V change in deflection at 500mm. Table 10</head><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p14.21"><s n="s1.3;p14.21">From those tables, it was found out that the change in deflection was increasing as the load was increasing, and the difference between each change in deflection was roughly the same. </s><s n="s2.3;p14.21">Take the first table for example, weight was increased in steps of 0.2kg, and the differences of change in deflection between each other were 0.33, 0.39, 0.37, 0.33, and 0.37 respectively. </s><s n="s3.3;p14.21">So the change in deflection is proportional to the load. </s></p><p n="p15.21"><s n="s1.1;p15.21">According to the equation 1.1 in the reference, deflection <hi rend="italic">y</hi> is proportional to the load <hi rend="italic">W</hi>, while there are still three more variables that affect the deflection, such as Young's Modulus of the PVC tube, second moment of area of cross-section of beam. </s></p></div2><div2><head>.</head><p n="p16.21"><s n="s1.1;p16.21">And in measurements on the cantilevered shaft, heights of the lever arm with variable load had been got in different situations, so, in the same way, change in height could be worked out. </s></p><p n="p17.21"><s n="s1.1;p17.21">Apply equation: </s></p><p n="p18.21"><s n="s1.1;p18.21">Change in height = Height with a load - Height without any load </s></p><p n="p19.21"><s n="s1.1;p19.21">Then another two tables of data for measurements on the cantilevered shaft could be achieved. </s></p><table id="BAWE_0254d-tab.011"><head>① Load was applied 200mm from the shaft centre. Table 11</head><row><cell/></row></table><table id="BAWE_0254d-tab.012"><head>② Load was applied 100mm from the shaft centre. Table 12</head><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p20.21"><s n="s1.1;p20.21">From those tables, the same thing as section 3.1 could be found out, so, the change in height is proportional to the load. </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Conclusions</head><p n="p21.21"><s n="s1.4;p21.21">From the experiment, it was known that the change of deflection and height were proportional to the load. </s><s n="s2.4;p21.21">The change of deflection and height was increasing as the load was increasing, and it increased with nearly the same dimension since the load was added up by the same weight each time. </s><s n="s3.4;p21.21">Also, the range between the load point and deflection point affected it, and some other variables had relationship with it, such as Young's Modulus, second moment of area of cross-section of beam and polar second moment of area. </s><s n="s4.4;p21.21">Therefore, the bending and torsion mainly depend on the load and the position of point that the load acting on them. </s></p></div1></body><back><div1 type="bibliography"><head rend="bold">5. References</head><p/></div1><div1 type="appendix"><head rend="bold">Appendices</head><p/></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
