<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_0254f" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Road Vehicle Drag</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note/></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">2</p><p n="date">2005-05</p><p n="module title">Fluid Mechanics</p><p n="module code">ES252</p><p n="genre family">Explanation</p><p n="discipline">Engineering</p><p n="disciplinary group">PS</p><p n="grade">M</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">1133</p><p n="number of s-units">58</p><p n="number of p">18</p><p n="number of tables">0</p><p n="number of figures">1</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">18</p><p n="number of lists">0</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">0</p><p n="abstract present">abstract present</p><p n="average words per s-unit">19.5</p><p n="average s-units per p">3.2</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">m</p><p n="year of birth">1982</p><p n="first language">Chinese unspecified</p><p n="education">OSA</p><p n="course">Engineering</p><p n="student ID">0254</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><docTitle><titlePart>Project Title: <hi rend="bold">Road Vehicle Drag</hi></titlePart></docTitle><titlePart>Name: <name type="student name"/> Student ID: <hi rend="bold"><name type="student ID"/></hi></titlePart></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="abstract"><head rend="underlined bold">Summary</head><p n="p1.18"><s n="s1.3;p1.18">The aim of this report is to provide an in-depth knowledge about the different types of drag that are present on road vehicles. </s><s n="s2.3;p1.18">The effects of the drag on the body will be investigated. </s><s n="s3.3;p1.18">And the key factors of designing a car will be briefly researched. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">Introduction</head><p n="p2.18"><s n="s1.3;p2.18">The estimation of drag is an essential element in the design of road vehicles. </s><s n="s2.3;p2.18">Drag is a force that some energy is used to overcome to move road vehicle through the air, it is a main topic of aerodynamics. </s><s n="s3.3;p2.18">In addition, drag reduction is key to gaining good fuel efficiency and also speed. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">Design Solution</head><p n="p3.18"><s n="s1.3;p3.18">The resultant aerodynamic force from drag is <hi rend="italic">R</hi>, it is expected to depend on freestream velocity <hi rend="italic">V</hi>, freestream density <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0254f-form.001"/>, viscosity of the fluid <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0254f-form.002"/>, the size of body <hi rend="italic">c</hi> and the compressibility of the fluid <hi rend="italic">a</hi>, which is expressed as <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0254f-form.003"/>. </s><s n="s2.3;p3.18">Using Buckingham Pi theorem, three dimensionless <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0254f-form.004"/> products are achieved, which are <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0254f-form.005"/>, <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0254f-form.006"/>, <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0254f-form.007"/>. </s><s n="s3.3;p3.18">Then a new equation is formed </s></p><p n="p4.18"><s n="s1.2;p4.18"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0254f-form.008"/>, where <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0254f-form.009"/> is drag coefficient, Re is Reynolds Number, and <hi rend="italic">M</hi> is Mach Number. </s><s n="s2.2;p4.18">Therefore, the key parameters relating to drag are <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0254f-form.010"/>, Re and <hi rend="italic">M</hi>, it can also be expressed like this: <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0254f-form.011"/>. </s></p><p n="p5.18"><s n="s1.9;p5.18">A body moving through a fluid experiences a drag force, which can be divided into two parts: frictional drag and pressure drag. </s><s n="s2.9;p5.18">Frictional drag is caused by friction between the fluid and the surface over which it is flowing. </s><s n="s3.9;p5.18">Pressure drag is arisen by the eddying motions that are set up in the fluid by the passage of the body. </s><s n="s4.9;p5.18">Formally, both types of drag are due to viscosity of the fluid, but the distinction is useful because the two types of drag are caused by different flow phenomena. </s><s n="s5.9;p5.18">Frictional drag is important for attached flows, which means there is no separation, and pressure drag is important for separated flows. </s><s n="s6.9;p5.18">When the drag is dominated by frictional drag, the body is called streamlined one, and when it is dominated by pressure drag, the body is called bluff one. </s><s n="s7.9;p5.18">Comparing road vehicles of coach and racing car, a coach is bluff body because it is boxy, so the dominant source of drag on the coach is pressure drag. </s><s n="s8.9;p5.18">However, a racing car is streamlined body because of the shape of the bodywork, and airflow is attached on the surface of the car, so the dominant source of drag on the racing car is frictional drag. </s><s n="s9.9;p5.18">The airflow on the coach and racing car are shown in the Fig 1. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0254f-pic.001"><head rend="italic">Fig.1 Airflow on the streamlined bodies and bluff bodies</head></figure><p n="p6.18"><s n="s1.6;p6.18">Turbulence is created by flow detachment. </s><s n="s2.6;p6.18">When the flow is separated from the body, it creates turbulence which deteriorates drag coefficient and increases drag. </s><s n="s3.6;p6.18">If we look at a protrusion from road vehicle such as a wing mirror, we see a compounding effect. </s><s n="s4.6;p6.18">For instance, the air flow detaches from the flat side of the mirror, which of course faces toward the back of the vehicle. </s><s n="s5.6;p6.18">The turbulence created by this detachment can then affect the air flow to parts of the vehicle which lie behind the mirror. </s><s n="s6.6;p6.18">Then drag coefficient is changed, and drag is increased. </s></p><p n="p7.18"><s n="s1.10;p7.18">Nowadays, most often cars must look good, designers are more important than aerodynamicists. </s><s n="s2.10;p7.18">One important element of a car design is the classification of its shape, which are fastback, notchback and hatchback. </s><s n="s3.10;p7.18">These types have different aerodynamic response to cross winds. </s><s n="s4.10;p7.18">Furthermore, the frontal area of the car is minimized in order to improve top speed and acceleration. </s><s n="s5.10;p7.18">Bodywork is designed to converge slowly, which avoids turbulence. </s><s n="s6.10;p7.18">Spoilers are widely used on sedan type cars, the aerodynamic aids produce downforce by creating a 'dam' at the rear lip of the trunk. </s><s n="s7.10;p7.18">A smooth undertray is used by some cars which covers the car's bottom to reduce the influence of underside airflow. </s><s n="s8.10;p7.18">Again, from a point view of racing car, wings which are the inverted version of what you find on aircraft are used, and front air dams are used as well, the air dams at the front of the car restrict the flow of air reaching the underside of the car. </s><s n="s9.10;p7.18">Both of these two aerodynamic devices have got the same purpose, which effectively providing downforce. </s><s n="s10.10;p7.18">Another method that generates downforce is raking the chasis, which brings ground effect. </s></p><p n="p8.18"><s n="s1.1;p8.18">In order to work out the aerodynamic drag and the engine power required of a typical coach at 50 mph, using the equation: <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0254f-form.012"/>. </s></p><p n="p9.18"><s n="s1.1;p9.18">Assumptions: air remains incompressible, uniform upstream fluid velocity </s></p><p n="p10.18"><s n="s1.2;p10.18">The drag coefficient of a typical coach is approximately 0.7, and the front area is approximately <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0254f-form.013"/>. </s><s n="s2.2;p10.18">The velocity of the coach is 50 mph, which is 22.4m/s. </s></p><p n="p11.18"><s n="s1.1;p11.18">Therefore, drag force D=<formula notation="" id="BAWE_0254f-form.014"/> </s></p><p n="p12.18"><s n="s1.1;p12.18">Engine power required P=<formula notation="" id="BAWE_0254f-form.015"/> </s></p><p n="p13.18"><s n="s1.6;p13.18">Considering on aerodynamics and passenger accommodation of a high speed racing car, to be ideal, the car body would be shaped like tear drop. </s><s n="s2.6;p13.18">The front end of the car should start at a low stagnation line, and curve up in a continuous line, the windshield should be steeply raked, the curvature of the roofline should be increased, which brings the roof line down at the front and rear. </s><s n="s3.6;p13.18">The slope of the back of the car should be reduced to 20 degrees or less, the back is followed by a long tail. </s><s n="s4.6;p13.18">The ground clearance below the grill should be minimized, and the underside of the car should be slightly raked and smooth. </s><s n="s5.6;p13.18">Furthermore, in order to improve passenger comfort, the levels of wind noise must be lowered. </s><s n="s6.6;p13.18">A major source of wind noise is the A-post and door mirror, therefore, the wind noise can be minimized by smoothing the form of the A-post and door mirror, also increasing the curvature of both the A-post and the screen. </s></p><p n="p14.18"><s n="s1.1;p14.18">In order to work out the aerodynamic drag and the engine power required of the best design racing car at 150 mph, using the same equation and assumptions. </s></p><p n="p15.18"><s n="s1.1;p15.18">The drag coefficient of the racing car is approximately 0.3, and the front area is approximately <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0254f-form.016"/>, the velocity of the car is 150 mph, which is 67m/s. </s></p><p n="p16.18"><s n="s1.1;p16.18">Therefore, drag force D= <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0254f-form.017"/> </s></p><p n="p17.18"><s n="s1.1;p17.18">Engine power required P=<formula notation="" id="BAWE_0254f-form.018"/> </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">Conclusions</head><p n="p18.18"><s n="s1.6;p18.18">To prefigure the performance of the designing road vehicle, the scaled models are employed. </s><s n="s2.6;p18.18">It can be used to find out whether the vehicle can cope in model situations that are realistic. </s><s n="s3.6;p18.18">However, an apparent problem would be that the conditions of the models would not represent reality completely accurately. </s><s n="s4.6;p18.18">Consequently, CFD (Computational fluid dynamics) and CAD (Computer aided design) are employed by engineers to design a car, and immediately simulate the airflow around it, incorporating environmental parameters like wind speed and direction. </s><s n="s5.6;p18.18">But many elements of vehicle's form can not be anticipated on computer; hence, wind tunnel is used to assess the advanced aerodynamic performance of a vehicle, such as wind noise. </s><s n="s6.6;p18.18">But the major problem is too expensive to build a wind tunnel. </s></p></div1></body><back><div1 type="bibliography"><head rend="underlined bold">References</head><p>John D. Anderson, Jr, Fundamentals of Aerodynamics, 3<hi rend="sup">rd</hi> edition, 2001, p30-35.</p><p>The official formula 1 website <seg type="URL" n="http://www.formula1.com"/></p><p><seg type="URL" n="http://www.cardesignonline.com"/></p><p><seg type="URL" n="http://www.f1technical.net"/></p><p><seg type="URL" n="http://aerodyn.org"/></p></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
