<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_0254i" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Break Disc Design Exercise</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">The document has a title page which contains:
document title
title part</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">3</p><p n="date">2006-05</p><p n="module title">Design Techniques and Management</p><p n="module code">ES380</p><p n="genre family">Design specification</p><p n="discipline">Engineering</p><p n="disciplinary group">PS</p><p n="grade">M</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">788</p><p n="number of s-units">41</p><p n="number of p">13</p><p n="number of tables">0</p><p n="number of figures">3</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">5</p><p n="number of lists">0</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">0</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">19.2</p><p n="average s-units per p">3.2</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">m</p><p n="year of birth">1982</p><p n="first language">Chinese unspecified</p><p n="education">OSA</p><p n="course">Engineering</p><p n="student ID">0254</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><titlePart rend="bold">University of <name type="university"/> School of Engineering</titlePart><docTitle><titlePart rend="bold">ES380A1 Design Techniques and Management Break Disc Design Exercise</titlePart></docTitle><titlePart><hi rend="bold">by<name type="student ID"/></hi><hi rend="bold"><name type="student name"/></hi></titlePart><titlePart><hi rend="bold">Report Reference Code: ES380 Affiliation: 3rd Year Mechanical Engineering</hi><hi rend="bold"> Report performed on: 23 January 2006</hi></titlePart></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Introduction</head><p n="p1.13"><s n="s1.4;p1.13">In this assignment, a brake disc of motorcar is chosen as a component to design. </s><s n="s2.4;p1.13">Disc brake is a device for slowing or stopping the rotation of a wheel, a brake disc is connected to the wheel or the axle. </s><s n="s3.4;p1.13">To stop the wheel, the braking pads are squeezed mechanically or hydraulically against the disc on both sides. </s><s n="s4.4;p1.13">Friction causes the disc and attached wheel to slow or stop. </s></p><p n="p2.13"><s n="s1.4;p2.13">In order to design an appropriate brake disc, lots of things have to be considered, thermal and mechanical stresses the disc will endure during different operation has to be analysised. </s><s n="s2.4;p2.13">However, the main disc damage modes are warping, cracking and scarring, and warping is the most important thing that engineer has to take into account to determine what kind of material they are going to use, and what is the thickness of the disc. </s><s n="s3.4;p2.13">So the design parameters for the brake disc are disc velocity, brake pedal force and structural loading, such as surface moment from hub and surface pressure from pads. </s><s n="s4.4;p2.13">The design objective is to prevent the brake disc damaged by the three main damage modes, especially warping. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Manual design of Brake Disc</head><p n="p3.13"><s n="s1.5;p3.13">First of all, the dimension of the brake disc is decided. </s><s n="s2.5;p3.13">In this design, the radius of the disc is 150mm, although bigger disc will provide better braking performance, but this dimension is suitable for road cars. </s><s n="s3.5;p3.13">And the thickness of the disc is 22mm. </s><s n="s4.5;p3.13">It is hollowed out with fins joining together its two contact surfaces, this kind of design helps to dissipate the generated heat. </s><s n="s5.5;p3.13">Because the temperature on the disc is very high, when braking pads embed on the brake disc, it can reach to 1200°C. </s></p><p n="p4.13"><s n="s1.4;p4.13">Secondly, plain carbon steel is selected as the material of the disc. </s><s n="s2.4;p4.13">Since carbon steel can either be cast to shape or wrought into various mill forms, and it can be machined easily. </s><s n="s3.4;p4.13">This is very important for brake disc, if scarring on the disc is not excessive, usually, it can be repaired by machining off a layer of the disc's surface. </s><s n="s4.4;p4.13">In addition, the mechanical properties of carbon steel meet the distinct mechanical requirements in the structural applications. </s></p><p n="p5.13"><s n="s1.3;p5.13">Thirdly, Structural loading is considered. </s><s n="s2.3;p5.13">The surface moment on the hub is assumed to be <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0254i-form.001"/> , the brake pedal force is assumed to be 800N, and the disc velocity is assumed to be 2000 rpm. </s><s n="s3.3;p5.13">Assuming the mass of the brake disc is 9kg, according to centrifugal force formula <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0254i-form.002"/>, then centrifugal force of the disc F is </s></p><p n="p6.13"><s n="s1.1;p6.13"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0254i-form.003"/> </s></p><p n="p7.13"><s n="s1.1;p7.13">And the brake pedal force on the disc is 800N, the area of the disc that the force apply to is </s></p><p n="p8.13"><s n="s1.1;p8.13"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0254i-form.004"/> </s></p><p n="p9.13"><s n="s1.1;p9.13">Therefore, the surface pressure on each side of the disc is </s></p><p n="p10.13"><s n="s1.1;p10.13"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0254i-form.005"/> </s></p><p n="p11.13"><s n="s1.3;p11.13">Fourthly, structural supports are considered. </s><s n="s2.3;p11.13">There are two supports, which are cylindrical support and fixed support. </s><s n="s3.3;p11.13">Empirically, the reaction force from the fixed cylinder is about 2500N and the reaction force from fixed surface is about 40000N. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Design with Cosmos tools</head><p n="p12.13"><s n="s1.5;p12.13">In aid of Solidworks and Cosmos tools, the geometry of the disc is shown as Figure 1. </s><s n="s2.5;p12.13">One restraint and four loadings are applied to the brake disc, as shown in the Figure 2. </s><s n="s3.5;p12.13">The central hole in the hub is fixed, the five bolt holes are applied with 30 Newton force respectively, 800 Newton force is applied on each side of disc face, the disc velocity 2000rpm is applied with the central axis, and the temperature condition on the disc is 600°. </s><s n="s4.5;p12.13">After that, the "Mesh" geometry of the disc is obtained (Figure 3). </s><s n="s5.5;p12.13">Finally, run the finite element analysis to get "Equivalent Stress" and "Deformation" contours, which are shown as Figure 4 and Figure 5 respectively. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Conclusion</head><p n="p13.13"><s n="s1.8;p13.13">In comparison with computer based tools and manual design, computer based tools, such as Solidworks and Cosmos tools, provide lots of powerful functions that can reduce the solution time for the problem. </s><s n="s2.8;p13.13">It is easy to make a product or component with Solidworks, then apply different kinds of restraints and loadings in concert with design problems, such as thermo-mechanical problems. </s><s n="s3.8;p13.13">Afterwards, just run the analysis, a finite element analysis result of the product or component can be achieved, even some restraints and loadings are changed slightly, it can be really easy to modify and run again. </s><s n="s4.8;p13.13">So computer based tools is an excellent way to do a design project. </s><s n="s5.8;p13.13">Whereas, manual design is verbosely and inconvenient. </s><s n="s6.8;p13.13">Especially, when design parameters are considered, huge calculations have to be done by hand. </s><s n="s7.8;p13.13">If a force or pressure on the component is changed, then calculation has to be done again originally. </s><s n="s8.8;p13.13">In one word, computer based tools contribute an accurate and convenient way to design products. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0254i-pic.001"><head>Figure 2. <hi rend="italic">"Restraint/Loading"</hi> Geometry</head></figure><figure id="BAWE_0254i-pic.002"><head>Figure 3. <hi rend="italic">"Mesh"</hi> Geometry</head></figure><figure id="BAWE_0254i-pic.003"><head>Figure 4. <hi rend="italic">"Equivalent Stress"</hi> Contour</head></figure></div1></body><back/></text></TEI.2>
