<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_0255b" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Containment or Engagement? A Critical Analysis of Approaches towards the North Korea Nuclear Crisis</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note/></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">4</p><p n="date">2006-05</p><p n="module title">International Relations of Pacific Asia</p><p n="module code">PO920</p><p n="genre family">Essay</p><p n="discipline">Politics</p><p n="disciplinary group">SS</p><p n="grade">M</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">5611</p><p n="number of s-units">125</p><p n="number of p">31</p><p n="number of tables">0</p><p n="number of figures">0</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">0</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">0</p><p n="abstract present">abstract present</p><p n="average words per s-unit">44.9</p><p n="average s-units per p">4.0</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">m</p><p n="year of birth">1984</p><p n="first language">English</p><p n="education">UKA</p><p n="course">International Relations</p><p n="student ID">0255</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><docTitle><titlePart rend="underlined">Containment or Engagement? A Critical Analysis of Approaches towards the North Korea Nuclear Crisis</titlePart></docTitle></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="abstract"><head rend="underlined">Abstract</head><p n="p1.31"><s n="s1.7;p1.31">The approach to the North Korea nuclear crisis requires a more balanced and historically aware perspective in order that North Korea can be constructively engaged. </s><s n="s2.7;p1.31">One only has to listen to the multitudinous and compelling invocations from the top authorities on the subject in academe and the policymakers of the past, armed with the enlightenment of hindsight, to be confident that seeking to wholeheartedly engage North Korea may prove worthwhile. </s><s n="s3.7;p1.31">In an analysis of approaches toward the crisis it is important to look at how crucial events in recent years have unfolded, how policymakers have managed them, and how they have been conceptualised by erudite observers. </s><s n="s4.7;p1.31">Almost without exception in the latter case there is a belief that the essential security fears of the D.P.R.K regime have been neglected and thus the crisis continues. </s><s n="s5.7;p1.31">Even pessimistic assessments assert that some form of engagement is superior to a policy of coercion or neglect which will simply force the Kim regime to take more desperate measures to survive. </s><s n="s6.7;p1.31">North Korea must be made to feel that incentives are more advantageous than coercive bargaining, which will potentially jeopardise its relatively propitious position. </s><s n="s7.7;p1.31">In the final assessment it must be understood that 'without resolving North Korea's security fears' the crisis is never likely to abate. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">I. Introduction</head><p n="p2.31"><s n="s1.3;p2.31">The approach to the North Korea nuclear crisis requires a more balanced and historically aware perspective in order that North Korea can be constructively engaged.<ref target="BAWE_0255b-ftnote.001"/> Currently, this so-called "rogue state" simply has no incentive to reform given the strategic climate. </s><s n="s2.3;p2.31">While it is tempting to succumb to a kind of ivory-tower hubris, a scholarly understanding of the nature of the conflict does not automatically prescribe for the implementation of a radical new policy, even if it appears that one might be needed. </s><s n="s3.3;p2.31">Clearly, there are immense domestic and international constraints that often limit even the best of intentions.<ref target="BAWE_0255b-ftnote.002"/> However, one only has to listen to the multitudinous and compelling invocations from the top authorities on the subject in academe and the policymakers of the past, armed with the enlightenment of hindsight, to be confident that seeking to wholeheartedly engage North Korea may prove worthwhile. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0255b-ftnote.001"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Bruce Cumings, <hi rend="italic">North Korea: Another Country</hi>, New York: The New Press, 2003 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0255b-ftnote.002"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.10;pn1.1">For example, during the first North Korean crisis a plethora of forces conspired against the Clinton administration's best attempts to constructively engage North Korea. </s><s n="s2.10;pn1.1">Robert Litwak, 'North Korea: Limited Engagement by Necessity', in Robert Litwak, <hi rend="italic">Rogue States and U.S. Foreign Policy: Containment after the Cold War</hi>, Baltimore: Johns Hopkins University Press, 2000, pp.199-201. </s><s n="s3.10;pn1.1">As such, 'congressional scepticism toward the Framework translated into a chronic battle by the administration to secure the few tens of millions of dollars needed to support the heavy fuel oil shipments owed by KEDO to the North... </s><s n="s4.10;pn1.1">At the same time, once the 1994 crisis had passed the international mood quickly shifted from galvanised anxiety to lethargic apathy, leaving the administration struggling in vain to raise significant funding for KEDO from countries beyond South Korea and Japan'. </s><s n="s5.10;pn1.1">Joel Wit, Daniel Poneman, and Robert Gallucci, <hi rend="italic">Going Critical: The First North Korean Nuclear Crisis</hi>, Washington D.C.: Brookings Institute Press, 2004, p.373. </s><s n="s6.10;pn1.1">In the international arena, the United States must 'negotiate an R.O.K somewhat in limbo; its faithful Pacific sidekick Japan perhaps willing to toughen up but lacking teeth; and, two former superpower adversaries [Russia and China] that are immersed in the mire of domestic political upheavals'. </s><s n="s7.10;pn1.1">Wit, Poneman, and Gallucci, <hi rend="italic">Going Critical</hi>, p.xvii. </s><s n="s8.10;pn1.1">Hence, 'problems with Congress, Pyongyang and Seoul' as well as the logistical difficulty in carrying out 'a complex multi-billion dollar construction project in a country as lacking in resources and infrastructure as North Korea' forced us negotiators to be vague in agreeing a time scale. </s><s n="s9.10;pn1.1">Thus, there is some weight behind the idea that 'the better explanation for the delays in implementation is mundane rather than Machiavellian'. </s><s n="s10.10;pn1.1">Wit, Poneman, and Gallucci, <hi rend="italic">Going Critical</hi>, pp.373-4 </s></p></note><p n="p3.31"><s n="s1.3;p3.31">Inevitably, the focus of the nuclear crisis centres on U.S.-D.P.R.K relations. </s><s n="s2.3;p3.31">From North Korea's perspective the key to its national security and the door to the international community is held by the United States. </s><s n="s3.3;p3.31">Therefore, normalising relations with the world's primary power is regarded as essential to survival, not just of the regime, but of the North Korean state itself.<ref target="BAWE_0255b-ftnote.003"/> From the perspective of the United States, rogue polities such as the D.P.R.K have potentially stark consequences for the non-proliferation regime and provide an unwelcome challenge to its global predominance, although this is often couched in the rhetoric of universal norms.<ref target="BAWE_0255b-ftnote.004"/> Moreover, although other powers cannot be ignored the United States has been ardently unilateralist wherever possible and especially when necessary.<ref target="BAWE_0255b-ftnote.005"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0255b-ftnote.003"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Leon Sigal, <hi rend="italic">Disarming Strangers: Nuclear Diplomacy with North Korea</hi>, Princeton, New Jersey: Princeton University Press, 1999, p.24, Bruce Cumings, <hi rend="italic">Parallax Visions: Making Sense of American-East Asian Relations at the End of the Century</hi>, London: Duke University Press, 1999, pp.121-4, and Leon Sigal, 'North Korea: Fibs versus Facts', <hi rend="italic">Nautilus Institute Policy Forum Online PFO 03-</hi>38, 2003 <seg type="URL" n="http://www.nautilus.org/fora/security/0338_Sigal.html"/> </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0255b-ftnote.004"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Sigal, <hi rend="italic">Disarming Strangers</hi>, p.22 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0255b-ftnote.005"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid., p.85 and p.193 </s></p></note><p n="p4.31"><s n="s1.3;p4.31">In United States foreign policy towards North Korea there has been much vacillation between limited, co-operative engagement and cautious containment.<ref target="BAWE_0255b-ftnote.006"/> Policy has fluctuated and played into the hands of a shrewd strategy of coercive bargaining by Pyongyang which will continue so long as the United States fails to alleviate North Korea's security anxiety. </s><s n="s2.3;p4.31">In an analysis of approaches toward the crisis it is important to look at how crucial events in recent years have unfolded, how policymakers have managed them, and how they have been conceptualised by erudite observers. </s><s n="s3.3;p4.31">Almost without exception in the latter case there is a belief that the essential security fears of the D.P.R.K regime have been neglected and thus the crisis continues. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0255b-ftnote.006"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Cumings, <hi rend="italic">North Korea: Another Country</hi>, p.43 </s></p></note></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">II. Misinterpreting North Korean Security</head><p n="p5.31"><s n="s1.3;p5.31">North Korea, its foreign policy and its security strategy 'cannot be understood apart from a terrible fratricidal war that has never ended, the guerrilla struggle against Japanese imperialism in the 1930s, its emergence as a state in 1945, its fraught relationship with the South, its brittle and defensive reaction to the end of the Cold War and the collapse of the Soviet Union, and its interminable daily struggle with the United States of America'.<ref target="BAWE_0255b-ftnote.007"/> Washington has gravely misunderstood the situation time and again and 'bureaucratic infighting between hawks and doves' obfuscates the essence of the crisis. </s><s n="s2.3;p5.31">Throughout the 1990s, overzealous intelligence estimates only gave impetus to Pyongyang's strategy. </s><s n="s3.3;p5.31">North Korea was 'a Rorschach inkblot absorbing anticommunist, Orientalist, and rogue state imagery', and during times of crisis 'North Korea was not our daily enemy of forty years' standing, but a new "renegade state"'.<ref target="BAWE_0255b-ftnote.008"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0255b-ftnote.007"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid., p.ix </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0255b-ftnote.008"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid., pp.48-52 </s></p></note><p n="p6.31"><s n="s1.3;p6.31">Hence, 'the first nuclear crisis rested upon the American desire to get Pyongyang to commit to the inspection regime of the NPT [Nuclear Non-Proliferation Treaty]...and Pyongyang's desire to get out from under a nuclear threat that had been palpable since the 1950s'.<ref target="BAWE_0255b-ftnote.009"/> In fact, 'this is still the basic nub of the problem today'.<ref target="BAWE_0255b-ftnote.010"/> The rhetoric of the 'unilateralists' and Republicans in Washington flies in the face of history and ignores regional concerns and the determination of the D.P.R.K to survive. </s><s n="s2.3;p6.31">The stereotypical images of the regime and its leader, Kim Jong Il, likewise fly in the face of facts.<ref target="BAWE_0255b-ftnote.011"/> Bruce Cumings' remarks about the state of the crisis today are not objectionably scathing. </s><s n="s3.3;p6.31">He believes that 'diplomacy with the North is anathema because the Republican right wont allow it and because the same group that brought us an illegal war with Iraq wants to overthrow Kim Jong Il, too'.<ref target="BAWE_0255b-ftnote.012"/> Cumings maintains that 'American foreign policy...often resembles amateur night at a halfway house'.<ref target="BAWE_0255b-ftnote.013"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0255b-ftnote.009"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid., p.52 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0255b-ftnote.010"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid., p.52 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0255b-ftnote.011"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid., p.47 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0255b-ftnote.012"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid., p.94 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0255b-ftnote.013"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid., p.97 </s></p></note><p n="p7.31"><s n="s1.3;p7.31">Contemporary doctrine, atop a lofty foreign policy to "rid the world of evil", has brought back the idealistic crusading of old that had been precluded by Cold War containment pragmatism, 'as if nothing was learned, back to the quiet American - "impregnably armoured by his good intentions and his ignorance"'.<ref target="BAWE_0255b-ftnote.014"/> Critics accuse policymakers of missing the point and ignoring the fact that the North has countless times shown itself to be willing to trade away 'its entire nuclear complex'. </s><s n="s2.3;p7.31">Moreover, Pyongyang actually perceives American regional preponderance as beneficial to national security, preferring that the U.S. 'continues to station troops in the South'.<ref target="BAWE_0255b-ftnote.015"/> Despite this, in the recent history of the crisis, 'threats seemed cheaper and more expedient than promises, at least in the political currency of Washington'. </s><s n="s3.3;p7.31">Consequently, in the half decade between the end of the Cold War and 1994, U.S. policy was guided by a reluctance to engage North Korea, preferring to condemn and sanction the regime for transgressing international norms.<ref target="BAWE_0255b-ftnote.016"/> Throughout this period, 'North Korea was playing tit-for-tat - co-operating when the United States co-operated, retaliating when the United States reneged - in an effort to get the U.S. to negotiate in earnest'.<ref target="BAWE_0255b-ftnote.017"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0255b-ftnote.014"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid., p.99 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0255b-ftnote.015"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid., pp.45-8 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0255b-ftnote.016"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Leon Sigal, 'The United States and North Korea: Co-operative Security on the Agreed Framework and Beyond', in Richard Haass and Meghan O'Sullivan, (eds.) <hi rend="italic">Honey and Vinegar: Incentives, Sanctions and Foreign Policy</hi>, Washington D.C.: Brookings Institute Press, 2000, pp.70-1 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0255b-ftnote.017"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.6;pn1.1">'When the U.S unilaterally withdrew its nuclear arms from Korea and suspended Team Spirit military exercises, Pyongyang reciprocated in December 1991 by signing a denuclearisation accord with Seoul and a safeguards agreement with the IAEA [International Atomic Energy Agency]. </s><s n="s2.6;pn1.1">To demonstrate its interest in co-operating, North Korea halted reprocessing in 1991 and delayed removing spent nuclear fuel from its reactor until 1994'. </s><s n="s3.6;pn1.1">However, 'when Washington refused to engage in high level talks after January 1992, Pyongyang was slow to let the safeguards agreement come into force'. </s><s n="s4.6;pn1.1">In this instance, the situation was made worse when 'Washington ignored Pyongyang's proposal for replacement reactors in June 1992 and instead resumed Team Spirit...after the IAEA demanded special inspections'. </s><s n="s5.6;pn1.1">Typically, in March of the following year, without any negotiations forthcoming, 'Pyongyang announced its intent to renounce the NPT [Nuclear Non-Proliferation Treaty]'. </s><s n="s6.6;pn1.1">Sigal, 'The United States and North Korea', p.72 </s></p></note><p n="p8.31"><s n="s1.5;p8.31">Clearly there is a real threat posed by North Korea, and Pyongyang has never been afraid to heighten crises in order to show its teeth to the world. </s><s n="s2.5;p8.31">Concerns about the potential of the North Korean regime to partake in illicit activity are widely regarded as legitimate and it would seem foolish to disagree.<ref target="BAWE_0255b-ftnote.018"/> However, the situation has been exacerbated by the extent to which foreign powers continue to hound the regime and try to force it to reform or attempt to restrain its power.<ref target="BAWE_0255b-ftnote.019"/> Leon Sigal asserts that 'an appreciation of North Korea's insecurity might have led America to abandon coercive diplomacy altogether'.<ref target="BAWE_0255b-ftnote.020"/> Between 1993 and 1994, the U.S. and the D.P.R.K narrowly escaped being plunged into a state of military hostilities and, potentially, full-blown war. </s><s n="s3.5;p8.31">In the end, this realisation forced both parties to the negotiating table to try and reach a compromise. </s><s n="s4.5;p8.31">Eventually, the 1994 Framework Agreement set the tone for the following years of relative tranquillity. </s><s n="s5.5;p8.31">The deal 'was structured so that the United States would not have to give anything away without getting something in return', hence, 'it could also retract its inducements if North Korea did not comply'.<ref target="BAWE_0255b-ftnote.021"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0255b-ftnote.018"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Siegfried S.Hecker, 'Technical Summary of D.P.R.K Nuclear Program', 2005 Carnegie International Non-Proliferation Conference (2005) <seg type="URL" n="http://www.nautilus.org/napsnet/sr/2005/0597Hecker.ppt"/>, and Michael O'Hanlon and Mike Mochizuki, <hi rend="italic">Crisis on the Korean Peninsula: How to Deal with a Nuclear North Korea</hi>, New York: McGraw-Hill, 2003, p.40, and David Asher, 'The North Korean Criminal State, its Ties to Organised Crime, and the Possibility of WMD Proliferation', <hi rend="italic">Nautilus Institute Policy Forum Online 05-92A</hi>, 2005 <seg type="URL" n="http://www.nautilus.org/fora/security/0592Asher.html"/>, and Sheena E., Chestnut, 'The "Soprano's State"? </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">North Korean Involvement in Criminal Activity and Implications for International Security', Centre for International Security and Co-operation, Stanford University (2005) <seg type="URL" n="http://www.nautilus.org/napsnet/sr/2006/0605Chestnut.pdf"/> </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0255b-ftnote.019"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Chestnut, 'The "Soprano's State"?', p.119 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0255b-ftnote.020"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Sigal, 'The United States and North Korea', p.74 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0255b-ftnote.021"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid., p.84 </s></p></note><p n="p9.31"><s n="s1.8;p9.31">The 1994 accord goes against the assessment of many American policymakers that the D.P.R.K is inherently untrustworthy and desirous of the nuclear capability to protect its abhorrent political system from the forces of democracy. </s><s n="s2.8;p9.31">'There is significant evidence' that North Korea has been attempting to woo the United States and that it is seeking détente rather than a powerful military arsenal. </s><s n="s3.8;p9.31">It has been suggested that in its formative years, the regime's nuclear programme had this latter aim, however it is unlikely that this is now the case. </s><s n="s4.8;p9.31">'If North Korea had been determined to acquire nuclear arms in the early 1990s, as most people in Washington believed at the time, it could have shut down its nuclear reactor any time between 1991 and 1994, removed fuel rods, and quickly reprocessed the spent fuel to extract plutonium'.<ref target="BAWE_0255b-ftnote.022"/> The explanation for this is that the D.P.R.K 'seems to want the United States to help ensure its security against a South Korea it fears, a Japan it hates, and a China it distrusts'. </s><s n="s5.8;p9.31">In the late 1990s, 'in Pyongyang's view... </s><s n="s6.8;p9.31">Washington has been unwilling to extend co-operation beyond the Agreed Framework or even to keep its end of the nuclear bargain'.<ref target="BAWE_0255b-ftnote.023"/> Furthermore, 'Washington was reluctant to move beyond the 1994 accord to greater political and economic engagement'. </s><s n="s7.8;p9.31">In signing the agreement, 'Pyongyang reasoned, if Washington was willing to supply more reactors, improved diplomatic, trade, and other ties would surely follow'. </s><s n="s8.8;p9.31">However, 'Washington did not even take the modest steps to ease U.S. unilateral sanctions that North Korea was promised in February 1995'.<ref target="BAWE_0255b-ftnote.024"/> The Framework Agreement worked to avert an unprecedented nuclear crisis 'once broadened to include energy, economic, security, and diplomatic incentives'.<ref target="BAWE_0255b-ftnote.025"/> It failed when none of those guarantees appeared legitimate.<ref target="BAWE_0255b-ftnote.026"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0255b-ftnote.022"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0255b-ftnote.023"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid., p.85 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0255b-ftnote.024"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid., p.86 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0255b-ftnote.025"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">O'Hanlon and Mochizuki, <hi rend="italic">Crisis on the Korean Peninsula</hi>, p.83 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0255b-ftnote.026"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Sigal, 'North Korea: Fibs versus Facts' </s></p></note><p n="p10.31"><s n="s1.4;p10.31">Consequently, 'the spurt of activity at the suspect underground site at Kumchangi in autumn 1997 should be understood in this context'.<ref target="BAWE_0255b-ftnote.027"/> At this time, 'had North Korea wanted to break the nuclear accord, it could have thrown out the international inspectors, opened the casks, and removed the spent fuel for reprocessing. </s><s n="s2.4;p10.31">Instead, the North resumed excavation...which U.S. intelligence [had] been observing for over a decade'.<ref target="BAWE_0255b-ftnote.028"/> The typical tactic of the North Korean regime is to combine such provocative acts with uncompromising bombast.<ref target="BAWE_0255b-ftnote.029"/> Ignoring such obfuscated pleas for negotiation and co-operation simply ignites frustration and desperation in Pyongyang. </s><s n="s3.4;p10.31">This time, the North Koreans took it as a 'reluctance or disinterest', motivating them to carry out their 'Taepong test on August 31, 1998 - a test that violated Japanese airspace'.<ref target="BAWE_0255b-ftnote.030"/> The test created 'virtual panic in Tokyo - as if the missile had barely cleared the treetops'.<ref target="BAWE_0255b-ftnote.031"/> Obviously, 'there was a deep-seated issue at the crux of this a conflict for which economic bargaining and foreign assistance can only be a means to political dialogue, not an end in itself'.<ref target="BAWE_0255b-ftnote.032"/> It was at this time that many analysts, such as Selig Harrison, believe that the D.P.R.K 'lost patience with American unwillingness to fulfil its commitments under the Framework Agreement'. </s><s n="s4.4;p10.31">Its threats and posturing a part of its peculiar way of begging the U.S to renegotiate the 1994 accord.<ref target="BAWE_0255b-ftnote.033"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0255b-ftnote.027"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Sigal, 'The United States and North Korea', p.86 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0255b-ftnote.028"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid., p.86 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0255b-ftnote.029"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.3;pn1.1">The D.P.R.K made the following announcement on June 16, 1998: "if the United States really wants to prevent our missile export, it should lift the economic embargo as early as possible and make a compensation for the losses to be caused by discontinuing missile export... </s><s n="s2.3;pn1.1">The discontinuing of our missile development is a matter which can be discussed after a peace agreement is signed between the D.P.R.K and the United states and the military threat completely removed'. </s><s n="s3.3;pn1.1">Ibid., pp.87-8 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0255b-ftnote.030"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid., pp.87-8 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0255b-ftnote.031"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Cumings, <hi rend="italic">North Korea: Another Country</hi>, p.78 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0255b-ftnote.032"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Sigal, 'The United States and North Korea', pp.87-8 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0255b-ftnote.033"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Cumings, <hi rend="italic">North Korea: Another Country</hi>, pp.81-4 </s></p></note><p n="p11.31"><s n="s1.6;p11.31">The U.S. never offered a comprehensive security guarantee; it refused to lump nuclear, political and economic concessions together. </s><s n="s2.6;p11.31">"Basically", according to Charles Kartman's assessment of the first crisis, the U.S. "had it wrong". </s><s n="s3.6;p11.31">He said, "we had been going down the wrong road for a long time". </s><s n="s4.6;p11.31">'In Pyongyang's view, it was being asked to give up its bargaining chip first, and only then would the United States talk about quid pro quos'. </s><s n="s5.6;p11.31">However, 'in Washington's view, it was not about to pay for North Korea to do what it had already agreed to do by signing the Non-Proliferation Treaty'. </s><s n="s6.6;p11.31">Sigal maintains that 'Washington had yet to learn that in dealing with Pyongyang, it would not get something for nothing'.<ref target="BAWE_0255b-ftnote.034"/> Rather than a "cheat and retreat" strategy, a better explanation may be one of 'show and tell', whereby North Korea revealed 'enough to demonstrate willingness to make a deal while withholding enough to retain bargaining leverage'.<ref target="BAWE_0255b-ftnote.035"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0255b-ftnote.034"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Sigal, <hi rend="italic">Disarming Strangers</hi>, p.37 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0255b-ftnote.035"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid., pp.38-9, and Leon Sigal, 'Six Myths about Dealing with Pyongyang', <hi rend="italic">Nautilus Institute Policy Forum Online PFO 01-02</hi>, 2001 <seg type="URL" n="http://www.nautilus.org/fora/security/0102C_Sigal.html#sect2"/>, and Cumings, <hi rend="italic">North Korea: Another Country</hi>, pp.58-60 </s></p></note><p n="p12.31"><s n="s1.4;p12.31">North Korea needs 'reassurance to ease...insecurity, a lesson most proliferation experts have been loathe to learn'.<ref target="BAWE_0255b-ftnote.036"/> Coercion is a risky business in this particular conflict: 'short of attacking, defeating, and occupying a nuclear-arming state, the use of armed force - like sanctions - can at best set back a nuclear weapons program or drive it underground; it cannot stop it'. </s><s n="s2.4;p12.31">In the late 1990s, 'if North Korea had nuclear arms or enough plutonium to make bombs, U.S. intelligence had no idea where they were; air strikes could not target what could not be found. </s><s n="s3.4;p12.31">Even striking the reactor at Yongbyon risked spewing radiation over Japan'.<ref target="BAWE_0255b-ftnote.037"/> However, the severity of the situation does help the U.S. justify immense defence budgets and pet-projects such as missile defence.<ref target="BAWE_0255b-ftnote.038"/> Keeping North Korea threatened and thus threatening may suit some in the American military establishment, but it is a very risky and irresponsible strategy that undermines its own non-proliferation regime.<ref target="BAWE_0255b-ftnote.039"/> Particularly 'when the state in question has a history of egregious or seemingly irrational behaviour, when evidence of internal change is difficult to discern or deliberately obscured, and when contact with the country is so limited that potential allies with its political system are not easy to find'.<ref target="BAWE_0255b-ftnote.040"/> North Korea is thus inherently insecure and notoriously determined to get what it wants. </s><s n="s4.4;p12.31">Sigal emphasises that 'so long as the United States persists in criminalising proliferation and demonising so-called rogue states in order to confront them, it will leave itself politically unpalatable options: to live with more nuclear armed states or to go to war to disarm them'.<ref target="BAWE_0255b-ftnote.041"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0255b-ftnote.036"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Sigal, 'The United States and North Korea', p.89 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0255b-ftnote.037"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0255b-ftnote.038"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Kim Myong Chol, 'Sanctions on Pyongyang Will Backfire', <hi rend="italic">Nautilus Institute Policy Forum Online 06-14A</hi>, 2006 <seg type="URL" n="http://www.nautilus.org/fora/security/0614Kim.html"/>, and Sigal, <hi rend="italic">Disarming Strangers</hi>, pp.232-5 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0255b-ftnote.039"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Timothy Savage, 'Letting the Genie out of the Bottle: The Bush Nuclear Doctrine in Asia', in Mel Gurtov and Peter Van Ness, <hi rend="italic">Confronting the Bush Doctrine: Critical Views from the Asia-Pacific</hi>, New York: Routledge, 2005 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0255b-ftnote.040"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Sigal, 'The United States and North Korea', p.90 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0255b-ftnote.041"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid., p.91 </s></p></note><p n="p13.31"><s n="s1.6;p13.31">'No country has been the target of more American nuclear threats than North Korea'. </s><s n="s2.6;p13.31">Since the Korean War, the U.S has 'conducted numerous military exercises with nuclear-capable artillery and aircraft on the Korean peninsula and carrier aircraft just offshore'.<ref target="BAWE_0255b-ftnote.042"/> Moreover, the effects of devastating total war and the possibility of nuclear destruction that bore upon the D.P.R.K have never been forgotten.<ref target="BAWE_0255b-ftnote.043"/> The U.S. military agenda 'puts Pyongyang's activity into perspective: much of it has been responsive to U.S. pressures...consistent with the logic of a Korean civil conflict and the nuclear confrontation since 1958'.<ref target="BAWE_0255b-ftnote.044"/> Such a state of affairs can convincingly be regarded as one of the most crucial determinants of the North Korean nuclear programme of the 1960s which was augmented as a result of 'clear signs of nuclear-arming by South Korea in the 1970s'. </s><s n="s3.6;p13.31">The security climate steadily declined over the next two decades as the R.O.K outstripped the D.P.R.K militarily and the U.S. achieved rapprochement with the Soviet Union and China. </s><s n="s4.6;p13.31">By this time, 'some North Korean officials were seeing the American troop presence in a new light, a restraint on South Korea and a counter-weight against Japan, Russia and China'. </s><ref target="BAWE_0255b-ftnote.045"/><s n="s5.6;p13.31">North Korea still now perceives American preponderance to be the key to its desperate security situation.<ref target="BAWE_0255b-ftnote.046"/> Given this assessment, North Korea's behaviour becomes all the more understandable. </s><s n="s6.6;p13.31">In fact 'forward deployment, instead of showing North Korea's aggressive intent, maybe its way to compensate for qualitative inferiority'.<ref target="BAWE_0255b-ftnote.047"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0255b-ftnote.042"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Sigal, <hi rend="italic">Disarming Strangers</hi>, p.20 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0255b-ftnote.043"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Bruce Cumings, 'Korea: Forgotten Nuclear Threats', <hi rend="italic">Nautilus Institute Policy Forum Online PFO 05-03A</hi>, 2005 <seg type="URL" n="http://www.nautilus.org/fora/security/0503A_Cumings.html"/> </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0255b-ftnote.044"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Cumings, <hi rend="italic">North Korea: Another Country</hi>, pp.52-6 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0255b-ftnote.045"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Sigal, <hi rend="italic">Disarming Strangers</hi>, pp.20-1 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0255b-ftnote.046"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Cumings, <hi rend="italic">North Korea: Another Country</hi>, p.x </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0255b-ftnote.047"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Sigal, <hi rend="italic">Disarming Strangers</hi>, pp.20-1 </s></p></note><p n="p14.31"><s n="s1.4;p14.31">The current situation in North Korea, by no stretch of the imagination, is the result of a 'crash programme' initiated by a maniacal dictatorship to satisfy despotic urges. </s><s n="s2.4;p14.31">No doubt, the regime is unwaveringly autocratic and loathsome, but its governance methods do not bear direct responsibility for its choice of security strategy or foreign policy. </s><s n="s3.4;p14.31">Since the mid-1950s, the D.P.R.K has sought out a solution to its 'precarious' encircled position as well as its economic shortcomings and its energy dearth and concluded that if the U.S wont provide it, then a nuclear programme will certainly help, one way or another.<ref target="BAWE_0255b-ftnote.048"/> Sigal believes that 'economic stagnation' has worsened the security situation in North Korea.<ref target="BAWE_0255b-ftnote.049"/> Moreover, with the demise of the Soviet Union and China, and South Korea's development of 'diplomatic relations with all of North Korea's one time allies', Pyongyang is in a sorry state politically.<ref target="BAWE_0255b-ftnote.050"/> The problem is thus threefold: North Korea assumed it had to develop an arms program that would give it some measure of protection militarily, mitigate for political isolation and allow the regime to extort financial sustenance from the powers a nuclear capability threatened that would not otherwise be forthcoming. </s><s n="s4.4;p14.31">Thus, 'Yongbyon... began in pursuit of energy self-reliance, and ended up as a bargaining chip to trade away for a new relationship with the United States'.<ref target="BAWE_0255b-ftnote.051"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0255b-ftnote.048"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid., pp.21-2 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0255b-ftnote.049"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid., p.22, and David Kang, 'Response: Why Are We Afraid of Engagement?' in Victor Cha and David Kang, <hi rend="italic">Nuclear North Korea: A Debate on Engagement Strategies</hi>, New York: Columbia University Press, 2003, p.104, and Litwak, 'North Korea: Limited Engagement by Necessity', p.223-30 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0255b-ftnote.050"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Sigal, <hi rend="italic">Disarming Strangers</hi>, pp.22-3 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0255b-ftnote.051"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Cumings, <hi rend="italic">North Korea: Another Country</hi>, p.60 </s></p></note><p n="p15.31"><s n="s1.5;p15.31">Pyongyang has not put all its eggs in one basket as it were, and at times allowed its 'autarkic economy' to open up to some limited foreign trade. </s><s n="s2.5;p15.31">This occurred mainly between the two Koreas and peaked at times of détente, 'tapering off' in times of hostility. </s><s n="s3.5;p15.31">The D.P.R.K regime was aware that - without building a new relationship with the U.S. that provided security - unbridled economic resurgence might be an unsettling force and consequently offered the hand of friendship to Washington.<ref target="BAWE_0255b-ftnote.052"/> Pyongyang's behaviour in the early 1990s is testament to this notion. </s><s n="s4.5;p15.31">When 'American security assurances...took nuclear forms: withdrawal of all American nuclear warheads...suspension of Team Spirit... </s><s n="s5.5;p15.31">North Korea reciprocated, putting the breaks on bomb making' and ratifying 'historic accords' to formalise the reconciliation.<ref target="BAWE_0255b-ftnote.053"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0255b-ftnote.052"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Sigal, <hi rend="italic">Disarming Strangers</hi>, p.24 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0255b-ftnote.053"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid., pp.25-32 </s></p></note></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">III. The Engagement Critique</head><p n="p16.31"><s n="s1.3;p16.31">Current hawkish assessments admonish the latest crisis as unsurprising in an inevitable sequence of underhand tactics from Pyongyang.<ref target="BAWE_0255b-ftnote.054"/> These 'unchanged and "evil" intentions" demand that engagement strategies of the past be abandoned in favour of 'isolation and containment' and a rejection of Kim Dae Jung's 'policy of unconditional engagement'.<ref target="BAWE_0255b-ftnote.055"/> The antithetical, 'more doveish' hypothesis is that 'North Korea's need for such a secret program, albeit in violation of standing agreements, derives from basic insecurity fears'. </s><s n="s2.3;p16.31">In this sense North Korean behaviour is a "cry for help", intended to tie the United States into a desperate situation in order that it give the security guarantees it would not otherwise consider. </s><s n="s3.3;p16.31">Thus, 'to the hawks, the doves are weak-kneed appeasers, while doves dismiss hawks as irresponsible ideologues'.<ref target="BAWE_0255b-ftnote.056"/> Clearly, the military teeth of the D.P.R.K are not an elaborate sham and pose a grave potential danger in the East Asian region and the economic crisis there has provoked a range of illicit activities by the Kim Jong Il regime.<ref target="BAWE_0255b-ftnote.057"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0255b-ftnote.054"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Nicholas Eberstadt, 'La Grande Illusion, Korean Style', <hi rend="italic">American Enterprise Institute</hi>, 2004 <seg type="URL" n="http://www.nautilus.org/D.P.R.KBriefingBook/multilateralTalks/Eberstadt-LaGrande.html"/> </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0255b-ftnote.055"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Victor Cha and David Kang, 'Introduction: The Debate Over North Korea', in Victor Cha and David Kang, <hi rend="italic">Nuclear North Korea: A Debate on Engagement Strategies</hi>, New York: Columbia University Press, 2003, pp.1-2 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0255b-ftnote.056"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0255b-ftnote.057"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Chestnut, 'The "Soprano's State"?' </s></p></note><p n="p17.31"><s n="s1.3;p17.31">Truth be told, 'Pyongyang is the world's worst nightmare - an illiberal and irrational regime that is the number one proliferator of ballistic missiles and enabling technology, and is willing to sell them'.<ref target="BAWE_0255b-ftnote.058"/> Consequently, the North Korean crisis 'has become intricately tied to partisan politics: rivalries between the executive branch and Congress; controversies over intelligence assessments; the viability of the non-proliferation regime; the efficacy of homeland defence; and differing assessments of the utility of deterrence versus pre-emption in U.S. security doctrine'.<ref target="BAWE_0255b-ftnote.059"/> That said, 'North Korea is not irrational nor undeterable'. </s><s n="s2.3;p17.31">In fact, 'whether one is optimistic or pessimistic with regard to the regime's intentions...some form of conditional engagement with North Korea - barring extremely deviant behaviour by Pyongyang - remains the best policy for the United States'.<ref target="BAWE_0255b-ftnote.060"/> Hard-liners disagree with those willing to 'compromise American values'.<ref target="BAWE_0255b-ftnote.061"/> A touch ignorant and conceited one might think. </s><s n="s3.3;p17.31">However, the belief remains that 'dealing with dictators in a principled and determined manner...is more likely to see positive results'.<ref target="BAWE_0255b-ftnote.062"/> This is often based on a '<hi rend="italic">papier mâché</hi> version of the D.P.R.K as a "rogue, irrational" state'.<ref target="BAWE_0255b-ftnote.063"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0255b-ftnote.058"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Cha and Kang, 'Introduction: The Debate Over North Korea', pp.2-3 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0255b-ftnote.059"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid., p.2 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0255b-ftnote.060"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid., p.4 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0255b-ftnote.061"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid., pp.4-5 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0255b-ftnote.062"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0255b-ftnote.063"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid., p.8 </s></p></note><p n="p18.31"><s n="s1.5;p18.31">Possibly an equally naïve perception is the direct antithesis of this. </s><s n="s2.5;p18.31">While North Korea certainly remains a pawn in the political chess-game of the major powers it is perhaps a little gullible to assume it has shown 'whole hearted attempts...to reform its system'. </s><s n="s3.5;p18.31">Yet, the solution put forth by advocates of this approach offers a more constructive alternative than coercion. </s><s n="s4.5;p18.31">Encouraging the D.P.R.K to emerge into the international system and helping it to reform 'emphasises the responsibility that the world's most powerful nation has in resolving the crisis through negotiation'.<ref target="BAWE_0255b-ftnote.064"/> A coercive policy could conceivably trigger a war that, in the words of General Gary Luck, would cost "one million and one trillion".<ref target="BAWE_0255b-ftnote.065"/> Unfortunately, '"area specialists" who actually know something about North Korea are spectacularly incapable of communicating with the public and policy makers in a useful manner'. </s><s n="s5.5;p18.31">As a result of this and the deliberate obfuscation of information that emerges from Pyongyang we 'are left with a policy and scholarly chasm'.<ref target="BAWE_0255b-ftnote.066"/> In addition, containment and engagement by the U.S has always been restricted to a very narrow remit of tactical non-proliferation objectives which has caused the crisis to reach an impasse where tit-for-tat diplomacy goes round in circles.<ref target="BAWE_0255b-ftnote.067"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0255b-ftnote.064"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid., p.5 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0255b-ftnote.065"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid., p.6 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0255b-ftnote.066"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid., p.8, and Sigal, <hi rend="italic">Disarming Strangers</hi>, pp.234-5 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0255b-ftnote.067"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Cha and Kang, 'Introduction: The Debate Over North Korea', p.10, and Kang, 'Why Are We Afraid of Engagement?', p.122, and Litwak, 'North Korea: Limited Engagement by Necessity', pp.210-19 and p.231 </s></p></note><p n="p19.31"><s n="s1.4;p19.31">The 1994 Framework Agreement set an important precedent although many hawks do not recognise the fact. </s><s n="s2.4;p19.31">The accord, 'under which North Korea froze its major nuclear weapons programs and promised ultimately to undo whatever nuclear weapons progress it had made', was widely condemned as 'giving in to North Korean blackmail'.<ref target="BAWE_0255b-ftnote.068"/> However, others believe that 'at worst the 1994 accord bought time'. </s><s n="s3.4;p19.31">In fact, 'a few years of difficult relations marked by smaller crises and mutual recriminations followed...but then a process of diplomacy and engagement began...especially after President Kim Dae Jung took office in South Korea in February 1998'.<ref target="BAWE_0255b-ftnote.069"/> Furthermore, in 2000, Clinton proposed a package to effectively buy out the North Korean missile development program. </s><s n="s4.4;p19.31">This was a seriously tempting proposition for the Pyongyang regime given the détente on the peninsula since the Framework Agreement and the inception of the "Sunshine Policy".<ref target="BAWE_0255b-ftnote.070"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0255b-ftnote.068"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">O'Hanlon and Mochizuki, <hi rend="italic">Crisis on the Korean Peninsula</hi>, pp.10-12 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0255b-ftnote.069"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid., p.12 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0255b-ftnote.070"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Cumings, <hi rend="italic">North Korea: Another Country</hi>, p.78 </s></p></note><p n="p20.31"><s n="s1.4;p20.31">Depending on one's normative position, it was perhaps 'right' that Clinton attempted to buy out the North Korean programme. </s><s n="s2.4;p20.31">After all, the D.P.R.K's missiles 'are commodities for sale' and a package that would cost around $1 billion paled into insignificance against the staggering amount that National Missile Defence was costing the U.S. - </s><s n="s3.4;p20.31">by the end of the 1990s the figure was somewhere in the region of $60 billion.<ref target="BAWE_0255b-ftnote.071"/> This newly proposed assistance went even beyond the 1994 agreement and could have possibly injected renewed vigour into what is once again becoming a desperate situation.<ref target="BAWE_0255b-ftnote.072"/> Unfortunately, it still did not get to the heart of the problem and allowed the tit-for-tat diplomatic relationship to maintain. </s><s n="s4.4;p20.31">By not offering a peace treaty or initiating a process of conventional arms reductions, North Korea was to remain inherently insecure and economically fragile.<ref target="BAWE_0255b-ftnote.073"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0255b-ftnote.071"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid., p.85 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0255b-ftnote.072"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid., p.93 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0255b-ftnote.073"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">O'Hanlon and Mochizuki, <hi rend="italic">Crisis on the Korean Peninsula</hi>, pp.6-8, and pp.13-14 </s></p></note><p n="p21.31"><s n="s1.6;p21.31">From another point of view, it 'risked encouraging North Korea to develop dangerous weapons...as its primary means of gaining hard currency and diplomatic respect'. </s><s n="s2.6;p21.31">Consequently, 'President Bush has taken a hard line toward North Korea', and, in fact, 'turned a cold shoulder' even to South Korean doves.<ref target="BAWE_0255b-ftnote.074"/> Many analysts have been critical of President Bush's unsophisticated "axis of evil" condemnation of North Korea, particularly given the highly tenuous claim that North Korea has links to significant terrorist organisations. </s><s n="s3.6;p21.31">Bush's hard-line policy comes in the wake of renewed vigour on the part of the D.P.R.K to provoke and altogether bully its way to secure guarantees from the United States. </s><s n="s4.6;p21.31">By 2002, the North's efforts saw it violate the Nuclear Non-Proliferation Treaty, which it signed in 1985, the accord it signed with Seoul, in 1991, and the 1994 Framework Agreement. </s><s n="s5.6;p21.31">However, the U.S reaction to this age-old D.P.R.K tactic was to yet again toughen its stance. </s><s n="s6.6;p21.31">Inevitably, causing Pyongyang to remove 'monitors and seals from its stock and waste fuel...and [expel] UN monitoring personnel', which 'put it in a position to add to its probable stock of one or two bombs by...perhaps half a dozen'.<ref target="BAWE_0255b-ftnote.075"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0255b-ftnote.074"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid., p.14, and Cumings, <hi rend="italic">North Korea: Another Country</hi>, pp.81-5 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0255b-ftnote.075"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">O'Hanlon and Mochizuki, <hi rend="italic">Crisis on the Korean Peninsula</hi>, pp.14-15 </s></p></note><p n="p22.31"><s n="s1.3;p22.31">True to previous policy, 'the Bush administration eventually relaxed its terms...agreeing to a session in Beijing in April of 2003'. </s><s n="s2.3;p22.31">The Beijing negotiations heralded little, 'except the possibility of more talks', and in fact set the stage for the North Koreans to up the ante, supposedly admitting to possessing the nuclear arsenal that U.S. analysts had 'long suspected'.<ref target="BAWE_0255b-ftnote.076"/> The 'theatrics' that followed further U.S reluctance are evidence of North Korea's perception that only America can provide the security the nation craves. </s><s n="s3.3;p22.31">Without meaningful American input the Six-Party Talks thus yielded little since the 2002 crisis.<ref target="BAWE_0255b-ftnote.077"/> The upshot of this most recent antagonism saw President Bush enthuse about concessions that would be made to Pyongyang if they reduced the conventional military threat and the possibility of comprehensive multilateral dialogue.<ref target="BAWE_0255b-ftnote.078"/> However, Bush never elaborated the 'specifics',<ref target="BAWE_0255b-ftnote.079"/> and the current administration appears reluctant to engage North Korea with intrinsic tact.<ref target="BAWE_0255b-ftnote.080"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0255b-ftnote.076"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid., p.16 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0255b-ftnote.077"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Wit, Poneman, and Gallucci, <hi rend="italic">Going Critical</hi>, p.380, and Marta Bailey, 'Another Engagement Strategy For North Korea', <hi rend="italic">Nautilus Institute Policy Forum Online 04-31A</hi>, 2004 <seg type="URL" n="http://www.nautilus.org/fora/security/0431_Baily.html"/>, and Christopher Hill, 'Dealing With North Korea's Nuclear Programs', <hi rend="italic">Statement to the Senate Foreign Relations Committee</hi>, Washington DC, 2005 <seg type="URL" n="http://www.state.gov/p/eap/rls/rm/2005/47875.htm"/>, and Sean McCormack, 'Joint Statement', <hi rend="italic">Joint Statement of the Fourth Round of the Six-Party Talks Beijing</hi>, 2005 <seg type="URL" n="http://www.state.gov/r/pa/prs/ps/2005/53490.htm"/> </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0255b-ftnote.078"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">James Kelly, 'Ensuring a Korean Peninsula Free of Nuclear Weapons', <hi rend="italic">Remarks to The Research Conference - North Korea: Towards a New International Engagement Framework</hi>, Washington DC, 2004 <seg type="URL" n="http://www.state.gov/p/eap/rls/rm/2004/29396.htm"/> </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0255b-ftnote.079"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">O'Hanlon and Mochizuki, <hi rend="italic">Crisis on the Korean Peninsula</hi>, p.17, and Kang, 'Why Are We Afraid of Engagement?', p.122 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0255b-ftnote.080"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Chung In Moon and Jong Yun Bae essay in Gurtov </s></p></note><p n="p23.31"><s n="s1.4;p23.31">The 1994 Framework Agreement 'showed that North Korea was willing to trade away a substantial nuclear capability for a package of benefits that included alternative sources of energy and the hope of gradual diplomatic engagement and economic recovery'. </s><s n="s2.4;p23.31">These days, the situation in North Korea is even bleaker with economic collapse seemingly just over the horizon. </s><s n="s3.4;p23.31">'Accordingly, Kim Jong Il has demonstrated at least a limited interest in trying economic reform, as attested by his numerous visits to China's special enterprise zones and temperate but frequent efforts to test new economic ideas'. </s><s n="s4.4;p23.31">'North Korean leaders seem to want change; they just cannot figure out how to do it successfully while also holding onto power'.<ref target="BAWE_0255b-ftnote.081"/> Therefore, unless the international community, and its self-appointed leader, offer guidance then North Korea will likely continue to be prepared to go to the brink in order that the regime survive.<ref target="BAWE_0255b-ftnote.082"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0255b-ftnote.081"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">O'Hanlon and Mochizuki, <hi rend="italic">Crisis on the Korean Peninsula</hi>, p.20 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0255b-ftnote.082"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Cumings, <hi rend="italic">North Korea: Another Country</hi>, p.189 </s></p></note><p n="p24.31"><s n="s1.5;p24.31">Containment and engagement strategies are often debated in a heated, circus-like rhetoric that is entirely unhelpful. </s><s n="s2.5;p24.31">Victor Cha and David Kang's eminent study takes the scholarly debate beyond what is often a farcical intellectual abyss and presents an excellent critique of current policy hypotheses. </s><s n="s3.5;p24.31">Containment need not be an empty vessel fuelled by blustering, reactionary discourse. </s><s n="s4.5;p24.31">Sophisticated containment premises assert that the Pyongyang regime is fundamentally averse to reform and any deviations from its conspicuously secretive, introvert and aggressive carapace is merely a 'change in diplomatic tactics' designed to reap maximum rewards from the prevailing political climate. </s><s n="s5.5;p24.31">The regimes '<hi rend="italic">intentions</hi>' remain the same.<ref target="BAWE_0255b-ftnote.083"/> Thus, 'absent changes in the military situation...that go beyond "smile summitry" and political atmospherics...it is difficult to assume that tactical warming by Pyongyang carries deeper meaning'.<ref target="BAWE_0255b-ftnote.084"/> Despite this, it is maintained that the default policy, 'even for "hawks" in Washington, Seoul and Tokyo', should be a form of limited engagement.<ref target="BAWE_0255b-ftnote.085"/> This means that it is possible to 'engage, while gaining a window on the degree of change in D.P.R.K intentions...[and] also laying the groundwork for punishment if necessary'.<ref target="BAWE_0255b-ftnote.086"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0255b-ftnote.083"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Victor Cha, 'Weak but Still Threatening', in Victor Cha and David Kang, <hi rend="italic">Nuclear North Korea: A Debate on Engagement Strategies</hi>, New York: Columbia University Press, 2003, pp.13-15, and Victor Cha, 'Response: Why We Must Pursue "Hawk Engagement"', in Victor Cha and David Kang, <hi rend="italic">Nuclear North Korea: A Debate on Engagement Strategies</hi>, New York Columbia University Press, 2003, pp.71-84 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0255b-ftnote.084"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Cha, 'Weak but Still Threatening', p.15 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0255b-ftnote.085"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid., p.16 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0255b-ftnote.086"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Ibid., p.17, and Gary Samore, 'The North Korean Nuclear Crisis', <hi rend="italic">Survival</hi>, Vol. 45, No. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">1, 2003, pp.7-24, pp.19-23 </s></p></note><p n="p25.31"><s n="s1.2;p25.31">Although the D.P.R.K is desperately weak, it is not lacking the potential to go to extreme measures to survive 'despite the many premature eulogies'.<ref target="BAWE_0255b-ftnote.087"/> Therefore, coercion is more likely to lead to pre-emption or a preventative attack by Pyongyang. </s><s n="s2.2;p25.31">'While fears of an imminent South Korean attack are not a salient pre-emptive/preventative motivation for Pyongyang today, the yawning deficit in capabilities vis-à-vis the South undoubtedly raises the anticipatory fears of extinction-through-absorption in North Korean eyes'.<ref target="BAWE_0255b-ftnote.088"/> North Korea's militarisation is no longer intended to conquer the South; it is now a fearful, defensive equipoise dedicated to the survival of the state - 'precisely the type of fear behind a preventive lashing-out type action'.<ref target="BAWE_0255b-ftnote.089"/> Moreover, the D.P.R.K no longer has a military advantage over the South and has no potential allies.<ref target="BAWE_0255b-ftnote.090"/> Clearly, pushing North Korea to the brink is not advisable and it is certainly not supported by East Asian powers.<ref target="BAWE_0255b-ftnote.091"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0255b-ftnote.087"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Cha, 'Weak but Still Threatening', p.18 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0255b-ftnote.088"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid., pp.19-20 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0255b-ftnote.089"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid., p.21 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0255b-ftnote.090"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid., pp.22-24 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0255b-ftnote.091"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">O'Hanlon and Mochizuki, <hi rend="italic">Crisis on the Korean Peninsula</hi>, pp.1-5 </s></p></note><p n="p26.31"><s n="s1.1;p26.31">North Korea's behaviour is thoroughly informed by intelligent strategy and 'it utilises deliberate, limited acts of violence to create small crises and then negotiates down from the heightened sense of tension to a bargaining outcome more to [its] advantage than the status quo'.<ref target="BAWE_0255b-ftnote.092"/> The more extreme the circumstances, it should be expected that, 'short of all-out war', the D.P.R.K will employ more extreme tactics to cope, thus the regime's behaviour is 'context dependent'.<ref target="BAWE_0255b-ftnote.093"/> The Cold-War status quo gave Pyongyang the 'impression that with time, gaps could be closed...[its] decisional frame was at worst neutral, and more often than not in the domain of wins'.<ref target="BAWE_0255b-ftnote.094"/> This is unarguably not the case now.<ref target="BAWE_0255b-ftnote.095"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0255b-ftnote.092"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Cha, 'Weak but Still Threatening', p.24, Cha, 'Why We Must Pursue "Hawk Engagement"', pp.73-4, and Eberstadt, 'La Grande Illusion, Korean Style' </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0255b-ftnote.093"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Cha, 'Weak but Still Threatening', p.25, and Cha, 'Why We Must Pursue "Hawk Engagement"', p.74 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0255b-ftnote.094"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Cha, 'Weak but Still Threatening', p.29 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0255b-ftnote.095"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid., pp.30-35 </s></p></note><p n="p27.31"><s n="s1.4;p27.31">Cha accepts that critics are adamant that events circa 2000 to 2001 marked a watershed in Pyongyang's political behaviour. </s><s n="s2.4;p27.31">South Korean rapprochement and a U.S. government finally willing to seriously negotiate turned the tide in favour of resolving the crisis of some fifty years standing. </s><s n="s3.4;p27.31">However, Cha argues that this was a consequence of a temporarily favourable status quo that historically does not last. </s><s n="s4.4;p27.31">Hence, 'without meaningful reciprocal responses from Pyongyang' to the R.O.K's "sunshine policy" and President Clinton's initiatives there was no evidence to suggest that this was anything substantial.<ref target="BAWE_0255b-ftnote.096"/> What is necessary is 'a distinction between permanent changes in the status quo and temporary deviations from it'.<ref target="BAWE_0255b-ftnote.097"/> According to Cha, 'understanding the North Korean threat in terms of this logic highlights the misdirected focus of D.P.R.K engagement debates in Washington and Seoul'.<ref target="BAWE_0255b-ftnote.098"/> The international community must seek to induce the Kim regime - rather than to coerce it and push it to more extreme measures - in order to reach a new status quo in which the North has an advantageous stake.<ref target="BAWE_0255b-ftnote.099"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0255b-ftnote.096"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid., pp.35-6 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0255b-ftnote.097"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid., p.36 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0255b-ftnote.098"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0255b-ftnote.099"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid., p.37 </s></p></note><p n="p28.31"><s n="s1.5;p28.31">This is a much more sophisticated assessment of the crisis than many of those emanating from the political policy debates that enter the public arena, however, it is still absent any substantial assessment of the crux of the crisis: North Korean insecurity.<ref target="BAWE_0255b-ftnote.100"/> From this perspective, 'North Korea's threatening rhetoric and large army exist to deter...and convince the U.S. that the costs of war are too high'.<ref target="BAWE_0255b-ftnote.101"/> Kang states that, 'in a nutshell, the problem is this: the United States refuses to give security guarantees to North Korea until it proves it has dismantled its weapons program. </s><s n="s2.5;p28.31">The North refuses to disarm until it has security guarantees'.<ref target="BAWE_0255b-ftnote.102"/> Kang's thesis is utterly convincing in respect to the possibility that the D.P.R.K will use or export nuclear weapons should it develop them. </s><s n="s3.5;p28.31">Under no circumstances whatsoever - other than in the gung-ho, unsophisticated, irrational, rogue state imagery - does Pyongyang believe it will achieve anything other than its own destruction should it do so.<ref target="BAWE_0255b-ftnote.103"/> Nevertheless, a nuclear arsenal does provide the 'status quo ante 1991, before the U.S.S.R collapsed'.<ref target="BAWE_0255b-ftnote.104"/> 'For deterrence to be stable, it requires a level of force that is adequate to make an attack seem senseless, but not so high that it would make pre-emption tempting to the other side'. </s><s n="s4.5;p28.31">More crucially, 'deterrence also means that North Korea will not use its weapons - if it actually develops them - for offensive purposes. </s><s n="s5.5;p28.31">The consequences would be annihilation by the U.S.'<ref target="BAWE_0255b-ftnote.105"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0255b-ftnote.100"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">David Kang, 'Threatening, but Deterrence Works', in Victor Cha and David Kang, <hi rend="italic">Nuclear North Korea: A Debate on Engagement Strategies</hi>, New York: Columbia University Press, 2003, p.42 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0255b-ftnote.101"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid., p.43 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0255b-ftnote.102"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid., p.43 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0255b-ftnote.103"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Cumings, <hi rend="italic">Parallax Visions</hi>, pp.127-33, and Chestnut, 'The "Soprano's State"?', pp.117-20 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0255b-ftnote.104"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Cumings, <hi rend="italic">Parallax Visions</hi>, pp.127-33 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0255b-ftnote.105"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Kang, 'Threatening, but Deterrence Works', pp.43-58 </s></p></note><p n="p29.31"><s n="s1.2;p29.31">Considering contemporary Beltway rhetoric, it follows that 'the North Korean regime would interpret...signals as conveying that the use of force by the United States remains an option'. </s><s n="s2.2;p29.31">It is also the reason 'why North Korea has a nuclear weapons program'.<ref target="BAWE_0255b-ftnote.106"/> Given Cha's hypothesis, the U.S. ought to refrain from such coercive behaviour.<ref target="BAWE_0255b-ftnote.107"/> 'Whether...a bargaining chip or an effective deterrent, the pursuit of nuclear weapons by North Korea should come as no surprise'.<ref target="BAWE_0255b-ftnote.108"/> In the end, 'North Korea has made very clear that they intend to be treated with respect...no matter who is morally right...the United States needs to realise that a policy that expects North Korean capitulation has fairly predictable - and negative - consequences'.<ref target="BAWE_0255b-ftnote.109"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0255b-ftnote.106"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid., p.57 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0255b-ftnote.107"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Cha, 'Weak but Still Threatening', pp.13-37 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0255b-ftnote.108"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Kang, 'Threatening but Deterrence Works', p.60 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0255b-ftnote.109"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid., p.69 </s></p></note></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">IV. Conclusions</head><p n="p30.31"><s n="s1.4;p30.31">The historically sophisticated perspective recognises that North Korea has no fundamental flaw that will prevent it from shrugging off its dire recent past.<ref target="BAWE_0255b-ftnote.110"/> 'North Korea can be brought into the community of nations'. </s><s n="s2.4;p30.31">However, 'even if Pyongyang wants to go in the same direction that the West wishes it to go, that process will be cautious and halting, and North Korea will not quickly let its guard down. </s><s n="s3.4;p30.31">Slow change is not bad - rapid change on the peninsula will be disastrous'.<ref target="BAWE_0255b-ftnote.111"/> While Cha's contention is admirable, it still fails to recognise that the D.P.R.K will continue the same mode of coercive negotiation until it is given the security guarantees it so desperately needs.<ref target="BAWE_0255b-ftnote.112"/> In the economic arena, reforms suggest that the D.P.R.K is in fact changing the nature of its polity as well as extorting the international community in order to survive.<ref target="BAWE_0255b-ftnote.113"/> This does not mean that the Kim regime advocates "open society" or is contemplating 'wholesale economic reforms anytime soon', but it does reflect a general shift in North Korean society which marks a more optimistic opportunity to engage the outside than ever before. </s><s n="s4.4;p30.31">The United States would be foolish to disregard this and push for the unrealistic change its zealous political oratory and ideology demand.<ref target="BAWE_0255b-ftnote.114"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0255b-ftnote.110"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Cumings, <hi rend="italic">Parallax Visions</hi>, pp.124-7 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0255b-ftnote.111"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Kang, 'Threatening but Deterrence Works', p.69 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0255b-ftnote.112"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Kang, 'Why Are We Afraid of Engagement?', p.105, and Kang, 'Threatening but Deterrence Works', p.43 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0255b-ftnote.113"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Kang, 'Why Are We Afraid of Engagement?', pp.102-113, and O'Hanlon and Mochizuki, <hi rend="italic">Crisis on the Korean Peninsula</hi>, p.20 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0255b-ftnote.114"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Kang, 'Why Are We Afraid of Engagement?', p.113 </s></p></note><p n="p31.31"><s n="s1.3;p31.31">In focusing on not just military North Korea, but on the country's 'political and economic behaviour in a broader historical context, there is a story to be told of slow plodding reform'. </s><s n="s2.3;p31.31">Despite the apparent resistance of the <hi rend="italic">Juche</hi> ideology, 'engagement works...it sends the right signals to the insecure regime that the United States, the Republic of Korea, and Japan are interested in trading the North's proliferation threat for a path of economic reform and integration'.<ref target="BAWE_0255b-ftnote.115"/> Even from the contrary, pessimistic view contingent engagement must be seen as superior to a policy of coercion or neglect which will simply force the Kim regime to take more desperate measures to survive. </s><s n="s3.3;p31.31">North Korea must be made to feel that incentives are more advantageous than coercive bargaining, which will potentially jeopardise its relatively propitious position.<ref target="BAWE_0255b-ftnote.116"/> In the final assessment it must be understood that 'without resolving North Korea's security fears' the crisis is never likely to abate.<ref target="BAWE_0255b-ftnote.117"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0255b-ftnote.115"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Victor Cha and David Kang, 'Hyperbole Dominates: The 2003 Nuclear Crisis', in Victor Cha and David Kang, <hi rend="italic">Nuclear North Korea: A Debate on Engagement Strategies</hi>, Columbia University Press: New York, 2003, p.129, and Cha, 'Why We Must Pursue "Hawk Engagement"', pp.86-9 and pp.92-100 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0255b-ftnote.116"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Cha and Kang, 'Hyperbolae Dominates: the 2003 Nuclear Crisis', p.129 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0255b-ftnote.117"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid., pp.146-8 </s></p></note></div1></body><back><div1 type="bibliography"><head rend="underlined bold">Bibliography</head><p>Asher, David, 'The North Korean Criminal State, its Ties to Organised Crime, and the Possibility of WMD Proliferation', <hi rend="italic">Nautilus Institute Policy Forum Online 05-92A</hi>, 2005 <seg type="URL" n="http://www.nautilus.org/fora/security/0592Asher.html"/> </p><p>Bailey, Marta, 'Another Engagement Strategy For North Korea', <hi rend="italic">Nautilus Institute Policy Forum Online 04-31A</hi>, 2004 <seg type="URL" n="http://www.nautilus.org/fora/security/0431_Baily.html"/> </p><p>Cha, Victor, 'Engaging North Korea Credibly', Survival, Vol.42, No.2 (2000) pp.136-55</p><p>Cha, Victor, 'Weak but Still Threatening', in Victor Cha and David Kang, <hi rend="italic">Nuclear North Korea: A Debate on Engagement Strategies</hi>, New York: Columbia University Press, 2003</p><p>Cha, Victor, 'Response: Why We Must Pursue "Hawk Engagement"', in Victor Cha and David Kang, <hi rend="italic">Nuclear North Korea: A Debate on Engagement Strategies</hi>, New York Columbia University Press, 2003</p><p>Cha, Victor, and Kang, David, 'Introduction: The Debate Over North Korea', in Victor Cha and David Kang, <hi rend="italic">Nuclear North Korea: A Debate on Engagement Strategies</hi>, New York: Columbia University Press, 2003</p><p>Cha, Victor, and Kang, David, 'Hyperbole Dominates: The 2003 Nuclear Crisis', in Victor Cha and David Kang, <hi rend="italic">Nuclear North Korea: A Debate on Engagement Strategies</hi>, Columbia University Press: New York, 2003</p><p>Cha, Victor, and Kang, David, 'Beyond Hyperbole, Toward a Strategy', in Victor Cha and David Kang, <hi rend="italic">Nuclear North Korea: A Debate on Engagement Strategies</hi>, New York: Columbia University Press, 2003</p><p>Chestnut, Sheena E., 'The "Soprano's State"? North Korean Involvement in Criminal Activity and Implications for International Security', Centre for International Security and Co-operation, Stanford University (2005) <seg type="URL" n="http://www.nautilus.org/napsnet/sr/2006/0605Chestnut.pdf"/> </p><p>Chol, Kim Myong, 'Sanctions on Pyongyang Will Backfire', <hi rend="italic">Nautilus Institute Policy Forum Online 06-14A</hi>, 2006 <seg type="URL" n="http://www.nautilus.org/fora/security/0614Kim.html"/> </p><p>Cumings, Bruce, <hi rend="italic">Parallax Visions: Making Sense of American-East Asian Relations at the End of the Century</hi>, London: Duke University Press, 1999</p><p>Cumings, Bruce, <hi rend="italic">North Korea: Another Country</hi>, New York: The New Press, 2003</p><p>Cumings, Bruce, 'Korea: Forgotten Nuclear Threats', <hi rend="italic">Nautilus Institute Policy Forum Online PFO 05-03A</hi>, 2005 <seg type="URL" n="http://www.nautilus.org/fora/security/0503A_Cumings.html"/> </p><p>Eberstadt, Nicholas, 'La Grande Illusion, Korean Style', <hi rend="italic">American Enterprise Institute</hi>, 2004 <seg type="URL" n="http://www.nautilus.org/D.P.R.KBriefingBook/multilateralTalks/Eberstadt-LaGrande.html"/> </p><p>Hecker, Siegfried S., 'Technical Summary of D.P.R.K Nuclear Program', 2005 Carnegie International Non-Proliferation Conference (2005) <seg type="URL" n="http://www.nautilus.org/napsnet/sr/2005/0597Hecker.ppt"/></p><p>Hill, Christopher, 'Dealing With North Korea's Nuclear Programs', <hi rend="italic">Statement to the Senate Foreign Relations Committee</hi>, Washington DC, 2005 <seg type="URL" n="http://www.state.gov/p/eap/rls/rm/2005/47875.htm"/> </p><p>Kang, David, 'Threatening, but Deterrence Works', in Victor Cha and David Kang, <hi rend="italic">Nuclear North Korea: A Debate on Engagement Strategies</hi>, New York: Columbia University Press, 2003</p><p>Kang, David, 'Response: Why Are We Afraid of Engagement?' in Victor Cha and David Kang, <hi rend="italic">Nuclear North Korea: A Debate on Engagement Strategies</hi>, New York: Columbia University Press, 2003</p><p>Kelly, James, 'Ensuring a Korean Peninsula Free of Nuclear Weapons', <hi rend="italic">Remarks to The Research Conference - North Korea: Towards a New International Engagement Framework</hi>, Washington DC, 2004 <seg type="URL" n="http://www.state.gov/p/eap/rls/rm/2004/29396.htm"/></p><p>Litwak, Robert, 'North Korea: Limited Engagement by Necessity', in Robert Litwak, <hi rend="italic">Rogue States and U.S. Foreign Policy: Containment after the Cold War</hi>, Baltimore: Johns Hopkins University Press, 2000</p><p>Manyin, Mark E., 'U.S. Assistance to North Korea: Fact Sheet', CRS Report to Congress (2006) <seg type="URL" n="http://www.nautilus.org/fora/security/0612.pdf"/> </p><p>McCormack, Sean, 'Joint Statement', <hi rend="italic">Joint Statement of the Fourth Round of the Six-Party Talks Beijing</hi>, 2005 <seg type="URL" n="http://www.state.gov/r/pa/prs/ps/2005/53490.htm"/> </p><p>Moon, Chung In, and Bae, Jong Yun, 'The Bush Doctrine and the North Korea Nuclear Crisis', in Mel Gurtov and Peter Van Ness, <hi rend="italic">Confronting the Bush Doctrine: Critical Views from the Asia-Pacific</hi>, New York: Routledge, 2005</p><p>O'Hanlon, Michael, and Mochizuki, Mike, <hi rend="italic">Crisis on the Korean Peninsula: How to Deal with a Nuclear North Korea</hi>, New York: McGraw-Hill, 2003</p><p>Samore, Gary, 'The North Korean Nuclear Crisis', <hi rend="italic">Survival</hi>, Vol. 45, No. 1, 2003, pp.7-24</p><p>Savage, Timothy, 'Letting the Genie out of the Bottle: The Bush Nuclear Doctrine in Asia', in Mel Gurtov and Peter Van Ness, <hi rend="italic">Confronting the Bush Doctrine: Critical Views from the Asia-Pacific</hi>, New York: Routledge, 2005</p><p>Shaplen, Jason T., and Laney, James, 'What Should the U.S Do About North Korea?' <hi rend="italic">Nautilus Institute Policy Forum Online 05-36A</hi>, 2005 <seg type="URL" n="http://www.nautilus.org/fora/security/0536AShaplen_Laney.html"/> </p><p>Sigal, Leon, <hi rend="italic">Disarming Strangers: Nuclear Diplomacy with North Korea</hi>, Princeton, New Jersey: Princeton University Press, 1999</p><p>Sigal, Leon, 'The United States and North Korea: Co-operative Security on the Agreed Framework and Beyond', in Haass, Richard, and O'Sullivan, Meghan, (eds.) <hi rend="italic">Honey and Vinegar: Incentives, Sanctions and Foreign Policy</hi>, Washington D.C.: Brookings Institute Press, 2000</p><p>Sigal, Leon, 'Six Myths about Dealing with Pyongyang', <hi rend="italic">Nautilus Institute Policy Forum Online PFO 01-02</hi>, 2001 <seg type="URL" n="http://www.nautilus.org/fora/security/0102C_Sigal.html#sect2"/></p><p>Sigal, Leon, 'N. Korea: Fibs versus Facts', <hi rend="italic">Nautilus Institute Policy Forum Online PFO 03-</hi>38, 2003 <seg type="URL" n="http://www.nautilus.org/fora/security/0338_Sigal.html"/> </p><p>Sigal, Leon, 'The Cabal is Alive and Well', <hi rend="italic">Nautilus Institute Policy Forum Online 05-95A</hi>, 2005 <seg type="URL" n="http://www.nautilus.org/fora/security/0595Sigal.html"/> </p><p>Sigal, Leon, 'Bush Policy Backfiring in Asia',<hi rend="italic"> Nautilus Institute Policy Forum Online 05-64A</hi>, 2005 <seg type="URL" n="http://www.nautilus.org/fora/security/0564Sigal.html"/> </p><p>Sterling, Harry, 'Bush's Hard Line Approach to NK is Producing No Results', <hi rend="italic">Nautilus Institute Policy Forum Online 04/36A</hi>, 2004 <seg type="URL" n="http://www.nautilus.org/fora/security/0437A_Sterling.html"/> </p><p>Vershbow, Alexander, 'President Bush's Foreign Policy and the Future of us-Korean Relations', <hi rend="italic">Korean Human Development Institute's CEO Forum for Human Development</hi>, 2006 <seg type="URL" n="http://www.state.gov/p/eap/rls/rm/59503.htm"/></p><p>Wit, Joel; Poneman, Daniel; and Gallucci, Robert, <hi rend="italic">Going Critical: The First North Korean Nuclear Crisis</hi>, Washington D.C.: Brookings Institute Press, 2004</p></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
