<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_0255d" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Japanese Imperialism in East Asia: Obstacle or Facilitator for Contemporary Regional Cooperation?</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">deleted: header: student and page numbers</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">4</p><p n="date">2006-02</p><p n="module title">International Relations of Pacific Asia</p><p n="module code">PO920</p><p n="genre family">Essay</p><p n="discipline">Politics</p><p n="disciplinary group">SS</p><p n="grade">M</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">5481</p><p n="number of s-units">148</p><p n="number of p">25</p><p n="number of tables">0</p><p n="number of figures">0</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">0</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">0</p><p n="abstract present">abstract present</p><p n="average words per s-unit">37.0</p><p n="average s-units per p">5.9</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">m</p><p n="year of birth">1984</p><p n="first language">English</p><p n="education">UKA</p><p n="course">International Relations</p><p n="student ID">0255</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><docTitle><titlePart rend="underlined bold">Japanese Imperialism in East Asia: Obstacle or Facilitator for Contemporary Regional Cooperation? </titlePart></docTitle></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="abstract"><head rend="underlined bold">Abstract</head><p n="p1.25"><s n="s1.8;p1.25">This essay argues that Japanese imperialism was a crucial factor in the history of regional cooperation. </s><s n="s2.8;p1.25">Wrenching East Asian nations into modernity via economic development and industrialisation, Japanese imperialism left an indelible imprint on the region which remains to this day. </s><s n="s3.8;p1.25">The economic interdependency which emerged prior to the Second World War was subsequently consolidated by the post-bellum foreign policy of the United States in order to promote regional stability. </s><s n="s4.8;p1.25">From this, cooperation has developed around a core of economic and production networks. </s><s n="s5.8;p1.25">This core of functional interdependency still forms the concrete basis from which regionalism in Pacific Asia is occurring today. </s><s n="s6.8;p1.25">Despite a proliferation of potentially divisive issues that have abounded since the turn of the century, economic cooperation provides the impetus for cooperation concerning new and increasingly salient issues which are potentially dangerous conflict ridden. </s><s n="s7.8;p1.25">Beginning with locating Japanese imperialism in its historical context, this essay demonstrates that notwithstanding the political and military nature of expansion, the Japanese colonial project had a lasting economic legacy which pervaded the cold-war period and to some extent remains today. </s><s n="s8.8;p1.25">In the final sections, attempts to institutionalise regional cooperation and the response of regionalism to challenges that are inherent in East Asian relations today are assessed. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">I. Introduction</head><p n="p2.25"><s n="s1.4;p2.25">Japanese imperialism was the precursor for economic regionalism based on modernisation and industrialisation in East Asia. </s><s n="s2.4;p2.25">With an analysis of the economic legacy of the empire and of contemporary regionalism it is possible to assess how useful regional bilateral and multilateral ties have become and whether the economic basis for a united region remains significant. </s><s n="s3.4;p2.25">Regional networks that crystallised during the twentieth century as a result of Japan engaging the region have increasingly become strained by new issues in the era of globalisation. </s><s n="s4.4;p2.25">This assertion does not signify the impotency of functional and pragmatic economic interdependence but emphasises the need to accommodate the new and highly salient issues which pervade the epoch. </s></p><p n="p3.25"><s n="s1.2;p3.25">Beginning with locating Japanese imperialism in its historical context, this essay will aim to demonstrate that despite the political and military nature of expansion, the Japanese colonial project had a lasting economic legacy which pervaded the cold-war period and is still prominent today. </s><s n="s2.2;p3.25">In the final sections, attempts to institutionalise regional cooperation and the response of regionalism to challenges that are inherent in East Asian relations today will be assessed.<ref target="BAWE_0255d-ftnote.001"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0255d-ftnote.001"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.6;pn1.1">The term 'East Asia' will be employed throughout this essay to imply a region including both the nations of northeast and southeast Asia, 'China, Japan, South Korea and the ten members of the Association of Southeast Asian Nations (ASEAN)'. </s><s n="s2.6;pn1.1">Nations to the north, south, west, or in the centre of Asia, or supposedly 'non-Asian' nations with an interest in the region such as Australia and the United States, are not included in this definition of East Asia, Takashi Terada, 'Constructing an "East Asian" Concept and Growing Regional Identity: From EAEC to ASEAN+3', <hi rend="italic">The Pacific Review</hi>, Vol.16, No.2 (2003), p.252. </s><s n="s3.6;pn1.1">When the latter, 'non-Asian' states are included in relation to the region, the term 'Pacific Asia' will be used. </s><s n="s4.6;pn1.1">The implication of this second distinction is that cross-Pacific issues which impact on East Asia and vice-versa are entering into the discussion. </s><s n="s5.6;pn1.1">Finally, when other 'Asian' states are involved - those not regarded as part of 'East Asia' or 'Pacific Asia' in the above distinction - the term 'Asia' will be used to denote the region in question Glen Hook, 'Japan and the Construction of Asia-Pacific', in Andrew Gamble and Anthony Payne (eds.) <hi rend="italic">Regionalism and World Order</hi>, Basingstoke : Macmillan Press, 1996, p.170. </s><s n="s6.6;pn1.1">These distinctions make no claim to authority and are mere analytical tools for the sake of convenience. </s></p></note><p n="p4.25"><s n="s1.2;p4.25">There are rich and profound historical and political discourses concerning imperialism which help to conceive of it as a particular form of political and economic development rather than simply a militaristic, historical aberration.<ref target="BAWE_0255d-ftnote.002"/> Unfortunately, this essay does not have the scope to include such a discussion at any great length. </s><s n="s2.2;p4.25">Moreover, when studying Japanese imperialism in particular - and East Asian relations in general - it is essential to remain aware of the need to ignore the tendency to impose Western-specific theoretical models if they do not apply.<ref target="BAWE_0255d-ftnote.003"/> Again, such a discussion is beyond the scope of this essay, but hopefully it is implicit in the argument that follows. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0255d-ftnote.002"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Germaine A., Hoston, 'Marxism and Japanese Expansionism: Takahashi Kamekichi and the Theory of "Petty Imperialism"', <hi rend="italic">Journal of Japanese Studies</hi>, Vol.10, No.1 (1984), pp.1-30, Hilary Conroy, 'Lessons of Japanese Imperialism', <hi rend="italic">Monumenta Nipponica</hi>, Vol.21, No.3/4 (1966), p.334, Bill Warren, <hi rend="italic">Imperialism: The Pioneer of Capitalism</hi>, London: Verso, 1980, and Ankie Hoogvelt, <hi rend="italic">Globalization and the Postcolonial World: the New Political Economy of Development</hi>, Basingstoke: Palgrave, 2001 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0255d-ftnote.003"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">David C. Kang, 'Getting Asia wrong: the need for new analytical frameworks', <hi rend="italic">International Security</hi>, Vol.27, No.4 (2003), pp.57-60 Having fired out a useful warning shot to international relations scholars interested in explaining 'Asia', Kang proceeds to challenge static realist concepts of international politics that often to do not fit well with the prevailing reality in the region which serves as a timely reminder of the complementary nature of political science theorising and area studies-style particularism. </s></p></note></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">II. Japanese Imperialism in Historical and Political Context</head><p n="p5.25"><s n="s1.5;p5.25">Hilary Conroy sets Japanese imperialism within the context of imperialism as a political phenomenon, referring to the theories of Hobson, Lenin, Schumpeter, Aron, Morgenthau and Waltz, in order to explain how imperialism must be understood as a consequence of the political thought of an era in which the "national interest [was] defined in terms of power". </s><s n="s2.5;p5.25">Japanese expansionism is no exception and it too must be explained vis-à-vis the contemporary political interpretation of the national interest.<ref target="BAWE_0255d-ftnote.004"/> In this sense, the Meiji era in Japanese history can be regarded as the beginning of the modern Japanese concept of national security which defined the political agenda. </s><s n="s3.5;p5.25">It was at this time that the Korean peninsula was referred to as a "dagger pointed at the heart of Japan". </s><s n="s4.5;p5.25">Japanese imperialism was conceptualised in <hi rend="italic">realpolitik</hi> terms of national survival. </s><s n="s5.5;p5.25">In a desperate attempt to modernise, or else succumb to the Great Powers, the attainment of territory and wealth was assumed to be an urgent requirement.<ref target="BAWE_0255d-ftnote.005"/> Japanese expansionist wars were wars 'waged in order to establish Japan as an independent state'.<ref target="BAWE_0255d-ftnote.006"/> As the Japanese scholar Takahashi Kamekichi stated, "Japan's wars with China and Russia and its annexation of Korea were all wars for the sake of Japan's independence and self-support".<ref target="BAWE_0255d-ftnote.007"/> Japanese imperialism is best understood as an extraordinary fusion of the political and economic motivations to expand which permeated the era.<ref target="BAWE_0255d-ftnote.008"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0255d-ftnote.004"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Conroy, 'Lessons of Japanese Imperialism', pp.335-7 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0255d-ftnote.005"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Conroy, 'Lessons of Japanese Imperialism', pp.338-43 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0255d-ftnote.006"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Hoston, 'Marxism and Japanese Expansionism', p.14 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0255d-ftnote.007"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Hoston, 'Marxism and Japanese Expansionism', pp.1921 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0255d-ftnote.008"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Peter Liberman, <hi rend="italic">Does Conquest Pay?</hi> </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1"><hi rend="italic">The Exploitation of Occupied Industrial Societies</hi>, Princeton, New Jersey: Princeton University Press, 1996, p.99 </s></p></note></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">III. Japanese Imperialism and its Economic Legacy</head><p n="p6.25"><s n="s1.5;p6.25">At the height of expansion, immersed in the rhetoric of leading Asia into modernity, Japanese elites recognised that in order to realise their goals they 'would need to have at [their] disposal...the greater part of the region's resources'. </s><s n="s2.5;p6.25">The intensification of militarist expansion paved the way for conflict with Russia, Britain and the United States.<ref target="BAWE_0255d-ftnote.009"/> In 1940, at the height of its hubris, Japan officially announced the concept of the Greater East Asian Co-Prosperity Sphere (GEACPS). </s><s n="s3.5;p6.25">The GEACPS was to have more than just connotations of economic interdependence - it was to be the basis of a political, social and cultural homogeneity extending across East Asia determined by supposedly ethnically superior Japanese elites.<ref target="BAWE_0255d-ftnote.010"/> In order to fully realise these ambitions, the Japanese decided they would have to completely remove the Western powers from the region. </s><s n="s4.5;p6.25">Therefore, at the end of 1941 they launched the infamous attack on the United States Navy at Pearl Harbour and nullified the British naval threat in Singapore. </s><s n="s5.5;p6.25">At this point, the Japanese empire straddled a vast unchallenged territory, 'from Rangoon to the mid-Pacific, from Timor to the Mongolian steppe'.<ref target="BAWE_0255d-ftnote.011"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0255d-ftnote.009"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">William G. Beasley, <hi rend="italic">The Rise of Modern Japan</hi>, London: Weidenfeld &amp; Nicolson, 1995, p.199 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0255d-ftnote.010"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Beasley, <hi rend="italic">The Rise of Modern Japan</hi>, pp.201-2 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0255d-ftnote.011"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Beasley, <hi rend="italic">The Rise of Modern Japan</hi>, pp.203-4 </s></p></note><p n="p7.25"><s n="s1.6;p7.25">Rejecting the official dogma, which heralded notions of cultural, moral, political and economic philanthropy and 'pan-Asian' prosperity, John Dower highlights the racial perspective of Japanese expansionism, which was inspired by modern Western born concepts of social Darwinism combined with apparently Confucian ideals of "proper place".<ref target="BAWE_0255d-ftnote.012"/> What becomes clear through such accounts is that the peculiar fusion of Occidental and Oriental ideas resulted in anything but an altruistic conceptualisation of modernising the region to compete with the West. </s><s n="s2.6;p7.25">Although the Japanese never achieved a homogenous, identity bound empire, since political conflict against communism raged to the north and clashes of religion and culture were widespread to the south, the barbaric subjugation imposed upon the region served one concrete end - industrialisation and modernisation.<ref target="BAWE_0255d-ftnote.013"/> The Japanese national interest hinged on 'the spoils of war'. </s><s n="s3.6;p7.25">If expansion had not been primarily belligerent, war and oppression became regarded as pragmatic measures through which commercial success would breed political might. </s><s n="s4.6;p7.25">Wars were 'to be fought over rice, minerals, markets and farming land'. </s><s n="s5.6;p7.25">Quite rightly, Donald Calman warns against forgetting that military atrocities and officially sanctioned oppression were 'monstrosities'.<ref target="BAWE_0255d-ftnote.014"/> Furthermore, issues such as slavery and the exploitation of "comfort women" still haunt the region's history today.<ref target="BAWE_0255d-ftnote.015"/> However, it is important here to flush out from the dark history of Japanese imperialism the economic aspects which were very much intertwined with the political motivation to expand. </s><s n="s6.6;p7.25">The legacy of Japanese expansion is highly salient in the context of the region's international relations. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0255d-ftnote.012"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">John Dower, <hi rend="italic">War Without Mercy: Race and Power in the Pacific War</hi>, London; Faber and Faber, 1986, pp.265-84 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0255d-ftnote.013"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Beasley, <hi rend="italic">The Rise of Modern Japan</hi>, pp.206-8 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0255d-ftnote.014"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Donald Calman, <hi rend="italic">The Nature and Origins of Japanese Imperialism: A Reinterpretation of The Great Crisis of 1873</hi>, London: Routledge, 1992, p.171 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0255d-ftnote.015"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Liberman, <hi rend="italic">Does Conquest Pay?</hi> </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">pp.107 </s></p></note><p n="p8.25"><s n="s1.7;p8.25">The Meiji regime implemented some longstanding economic reforms - the fusion of public and private initiatives in 'protected industries', and the creation of vast conglomerates, <hi rend="italic">zaibatsu</hi> - which gave Japan a unique perception of political and economic interests and remained influential throughout the twentieth century. </s><s n="s2.7;p8.25">François Godement, without ignoring Calman's warning, highlights the modernising influence of the extension of Japanese economic development across the region - although some fared better than others - 'between 1896 and 1936...[Taiwan's] GNP rose by 260 per cent'.<ref target="BAWE_0255d-ftnote.016"/> Japanese imperialism undoubtedly led to the modernisation and development of its colonial acquisitions. </s><s n="s3.7;p8.25">'Commercial infrastructure was improved by the construction of railways, roads, telegraph networks, harbours, and warehouses, the standardization of currency and measures, and the availability of credit'. </s><s n="s4.7;p8.25">Moreover, Japanese initiatives improved 'agricultural productivity', 'industrial development', and "human resources", in which health, medial and educational provisions were made to raise the economic potential of the colonies. </s><s n="s5.7;p8.25">'Rapid growth was necessary to Japan's quest for economic autarky'.<ref target="BAWE_0255d-ftnote.017"/> In this respect, the GEACPS can be regarded as a regional economic "blueprint".<ref target="BAWE_0255d-ftnote.018"/> Cumings concurs, stating that 'the place to begin in comprehending the region's economic dynamism is with the advent of Japanese imperialism'.<ref target="BAWE_0255d-ftnote.019"/> This expansionism was competitive, planned and mimicked the policy of the West.<ref target="BAWE_0255d-ftnote.020"/> The close knit and oppressive nature of the empire meant that it 'provided a model for state-directed development'. </s><s n="s6.7;p8.25">Japan exported industry and economic development to the region in order to consolidate an inward looking autarkic bloc which would feed the metropolis and assert Japan's status as a Great Power.<ref target="BAWE_0255d-ftnote.021"/> However, by the end of the war Japanese imperialism had been crushed. </s><s n="s7.7;p8.25">Regional economic development, on the other hand, continued. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0255d-ftnote.016"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">François Godement, <hi rend="italic">The New Asian Renaissance: From Colonialism to Post-Cold War</hi>, London: Routledge, 1997, pp.64-8 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0255d-ftnote.017"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Liberman,<hi rend="italic"> Does Conquest Pay?</hi> </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">pp.100-107 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0255d-ftnote.018"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Dower,<hi rend="italic"> War Without Mercy</hi>, p.272 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0255d-ftnote.019"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Bruce Cumings, 'The Origins and Development of the Northeast Asian Political Economy: Industrial Sectors, Product Cycles, and Political Consequences', <hi rend="italic">International Organisation</hi>, Vol.38, No.1, 1984, p.8 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0255d-ftnote.020"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Cumings, 'The Origins and Development of the Northeast Asian Political Economy', pp.9-11 Although Cumings asserts that Japanese imperialism was similar to the expansionist policies of Western states in previous centuries, he asserts that by 1910 territorial expansion was 'anachronistic' as it became viewed in the West as 'outdated or immoral, or both'. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0255d-ftnote.021"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Cumings, 'The Origins and Development of the Northeast Asian Political Economy', pp.8-14 </s></p></note></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">IV. Cold War Era Regional Cooperation</head><p n="p9.25"><s n="s1.10;p9.25">It took Washington until 1948 to devise their strategy for consolidating US regional dominion. </s><s n="s2.10;p9.25">Occupation and a thorough dissemination of the Japanese war machine followed in order to satisfy the international community. </s><s n="s3.10;p9.25">The 'Kennan Restoration' was subsequently designed to restore Japanese 'economic prowess' devoid of a military capability.<ref target="BAWE_0255d-ftnote.022"/> This 'rollback' was part of the US policy of containment, to keep the region free of Communism and to keep South East Asia open to Western economies.<ref target="BAWE_0255d-ftnote.023"/> Hence, Japan's role in regional and international politics after 1945 was a design of American post-bellum foreign policy. </s><s n="s4.10;p9.25">The Security Treaty signed between the United States and Japan in 1952 signalled the end of Japanese international 'ignominy'. </s><s n="s5.10;p9.25">Moreover, alliance with the world's primary power and self-professed protagonist of democracy afforded Japan the 'muscle [that] would inaugurate a new era in which trade issues came to dominate Japan's foreign relations'.<ref target="BAWE_0255d-ftnote.024"/> The nature of the cold war security arrangement in East Asia, and Japan's wartime image, forced Japan into a 'passive and cautious' foreign policy - which meant pursuing the national interest could be a commercial venture only - one which was wholly supported by the US because regional stability was high on the agenda.<ref target="BAWE_0255d-ftnote.025"/> Japan was thus handed an almost <hi rend="italic">carte blanche</hi> to undertake a vigorous national and regional economic reconstruction. </s><s n="s6.10;p9.25">As far as the US was concerned during the Cold War, the more powerful Japan and its regional allies could become the better. </s><s n="s7.10;p9.25">With this, the US underwrote Japanese security in order that all it resources were geared towards rapid reindustrialisation and market exploitation. </s><s n="s8.10;p9.25">'US policy makers recognized that Japan's Asian colonies had provided 33 per cent of pre-war Japan's raw materials and absorbed 40 per cent of its exports. </s><s n="s9.10;p9.25">Restoration of these links...would be critical to a Japanese economic recovery consistent with the US attempt to isolate China'.<ref target="BAWE_0255d-ftnote.026"/> In doing so, the US afforded the region a 'rare breathing space'; under conditions of 'tariffs, overvalued exchange rates and other obstacles for foreign entry' the region thrived and was propelled into an era of 'new export led industrialization in the early 1960s'. </s><s n="s10.10;p9.25">This set the tone of economic relations in the region up to the 1970s.<ref target="BAWE_0255d-ftnote.027"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0255d-ftnote.022"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.4;pn1.1">Cumings, 'The Origins and Development of the Northeast Asian Political Economy', pp.16-18 Cumings employs a remarkable anecdote here which cleverly links the economic aspects of Japanese imperialism and US post-war foreign policy: 'an American officer walked into a Mitsui office in Tokyo and introduced himself. </s><s n="s2.4;pn1.1">A man in the office pointed to a map of the Greater East Asian Co-Prosperity Sphere and said "There it is. </s><s n="s3.4;pn1.1">We tried. </s><s n="s4.4;pn1.1">See what you can do with it!"'. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0255d-ftnote.023"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Cumings, 'The Origins and Development of the Northeast Asian Political Economy', pp.18-20 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0255d-ftnote.024"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Michael A. Barnhart, <hi rend="italic">Japan and The World Since 1868</hi>, London: Edward Arnold, 1995, pp.164-5 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0255d-ftnote.025"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Yung-Hwan Jo, 'Regional Cooperation in Southeast Asia and Japan's Role', Journal of Politics, Vol.30, No.3 (1968) pp.784-5 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0255d-ftnote.026"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Mark Selden, 'China, Japan, and the Regional Political Economy of East Asia, 1945-1995', in Peter J. Katzenstein and Takashi Shiraishi, <hi rend="italic">Network Power: Japan and Asia</hi>, Ithaca, NY: Cornell University Press, 1997, pp.306-10 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0255d-ftnote.027"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Cumings, 'The Origins and Development of the Northeast Asian Political Economy', pp.20-26 </s></p></note><p n="p10.25"><s n="s1.8;p10.25">In terms of the economic integration of East Asia during the twentieth century, 'Japan...provided both the engine...and [the] influential model of economic development for the region as a whole'. </s><s n="s2.8;p10.25">Japanese imperialism forcefully imposed a particular model on the region which resulted in 'consolidating the role of the state in domestic economic development'. </s><s n="s3.8;p10.25">Moreover, the propping up of the regional economy, designed to support the growth of Japanese commerce, was symptomatic of the dispersion of Japanese corporations across East Asia. </s><s n="s4.8;p10.25">Industrialisation spread as these businesses sought newer and cheaper locations for production. </s><s n="s5.8;p10.25">Japan's successful fusion of politics and economics was such that 'aid and infrastructure packages...effectively lock[ed] host governments into symbiotic relationships with Japanese capital'. </s><s n="s6.8;p10.25">The "Asian Way" became synonymous with rapid modernisation and 'accelerated industrial development'. </s><s n="s7.8;p10.25">For Western liberal economies a certain disdain for this economic model invoked initiatives to prize the region open.<ref target="BAWE_0255d-ftnote.028"/> However, regionalism remained a fundamental part of the Japanese national interest and its international relations, 'by the late 1990s, [East] Asia was an extension of Japan's highly relational political economy'. </s><s n="s8.8;p10.25">This model has come under increasing pressure but it still remains a vitally important factor in terms of regionalism.<ref target="BAWE_0255d-ftnote.029"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0255d-ftnote.028"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Mark Beeson, 'The Political Economy of East Asia at a Time of Crisis', in Richard Stubbs and Geoffrey R.D. Underhill,<hi rend="italic"> Political Economy and the Changing Global Order</hi> (2nd Edition), Toronto: Oxford University Press, 2000, pp.352-9 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0255d-ftnote.029"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Walter Hatch, 'Regionalization Trumps Globalization: Japanese Production Networks in Asia', in Richard Stubbs and Geoffrey R.D. Underhill <hi rend="italic">, Political Economy and the Changing Global Order</hi> (2nd Edition), Toronto: Oxford University Press, 2000, pp.382-9 </s></p></note><p n="p11.25"><s n="s1.4;p11.25">Even when the US was forced to reconsider the massive post-war military deployment in the area in the 1970s they remained committed to the stability of the region based on the economic vibrancy Japanese activity had brought. </s><s n="s2.4;p11.25">With the emergence of China - consequential of Sino-Soviet conflict - and the boom experienced in the Newly Industrialised Economies (NIEs) regional economic relationships, particularly with Japan, coaxed the communist giant into the global market and warmed relations with the West.<ref target="BAWE_0255d-ftnote.030"/> Although the region remained a focal point of its foreign policy, the US was satisfied that it could downscale its military presence and use political measures to assert its hegemony.<ref target="BAWE_0255d-ftnote.031"/> Since the 1970s, the region was subjected to 'Washington's geo-political shift', which centred on Sino-American rapprochement. </s><s n="s3.4;p11.25">The so-called "Nixon Shocks" were designed to realign the regional agenda as Cold War tensions subsided and the need for a military presence eased. </s><s n="s4.4;p11.25">The focus of this policy was to reign in Japanese economic development which was occurring at a phenomenal and unchallenged rate.<ref target="BAWE_0255d-ftnote.032"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0255d-ftnote.030"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Since the Second World War, 'real GNP multiplied twelve times in the NIEs, eleven times in Japan and six times in China and the ASEAN countries', Selden, 'China, Japan, and the Regional Political Economy of East Asia', in Katzenstein and Shiraishi, <hi rend="italic">Network Power</hi>, p.320 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0255d-ftnote.031"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Selden, 'China, Japan, and the Regional Political Economy of East Asia', in Katzenstein and Shiraishi, <hi rend="italic">Network Power</hi>, pp.310-21 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0255d-ftnote.032"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Mark T. Berger, The Battle for Asia: From Decolonisation to Globalisation, London: Routledge, 2004, pp.251-62 </s></p></note><p n="p12.25"><s n="s1.3;p12.25">The Japanese reaction to such challenges has always been distinguished by an effective tweaking, rather than a wholesale reappraisal, of the regional economic system. </s><s n="s2.3;p12.25">Consequently, in the mid-1990s, East Asian regionalism was 'buzzing with a competitive energy' that had marked Japan's own economic development throughout the second half of the twentieth century. </s><s n="s3.3;p12.25">Clearly, there have been periods of change and fluctuation - in the Japanese domestic economy, the regional economy and the international economy - but this form of economic interdependence has characterised the region for almost a century.<ref target="BAWE_0255d-ftnote.033"/> The unique public-private linkages of Japanese economic policy extended overseas with the extension of Japanese investment into the region.<ref target="BAWE_0255d-ftnote.034"/> This was facilitated by three main factors: firstly, the concerted effort made by South East Asian economies to boost their faltering development by opening up to foreign investment; secondly, the move by the US and other economies to protect against large scale Japanese export, forcing Japan to look to the Asian market; and, thirdly, the 1985 Plaza Accord, which forced a dramatic appreciation of the Yen and culminated, not in reducing Japanese exports <hi rend="italic">per se</hi> and reducing the massive US trade deficit, but in forcing the Japanese to rethink their economic policy to encourage continued investment.<ref target="BAWE_0255d-ftnote.035"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0255d-ftnote.033"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Walter Hatch and Kozo Yamamura, <hi rend="italic">Asia in Japan's Embrace: Building a Regional Production Alliance</hi>, Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 1996, pp.3-12 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0255d-ftnote.034"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Hatch and Yamamura, <hi rend="italic">Asia in Japan's Embrace</hi>, pp.15-17 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0255d-ftnote.035"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Hatch and Yamamura, <hi rend="italic">Asia in Japan's Embrace</hi>, pp.20-1 </s></p></note><p n="p13.25"><s n="s1.6;p13.25">Rather than simply relying on export oriented production, the Japanese encouraged a great boost in foreign direct investment in order to produce overseas and therefore reduce costs and regain profitability. </s><s n="s2.6;p13.25">Investment in the region was a consequence of a concerted strategy by Japanese manufacturers, 'to achieve economies of scale, scope, and networking by capitalising on the regions deepening division of labour'. </s><s n="s3.6;p13.25">The impetus for this action was to create "a single market from which to pursue a global corporate strategy".<ref target="BAWE_0255d-ftnote.036"/> It is this which can be recognised as the 'peaceful ghost of the Greater East Asian Co-Prosperity Sphere'.<ref target="BAWE_0255d-ftnote.037"/> The significance of this 'alliance' is that it serves the political and economic needs of both Japan and the other countries in the region. </s><s n="s4.6;p13.25">For Japan, not only does it [help] escape the potentially crushing impact of the high yen, but it reduces the size of the trade surplus directly attributable to Japan, and thus reduces some of the international pressure the nation would otherwise face'. </s><s n="s5.6;p13.25">For the rest of the region, it provides an element of stability in the face of a prying international community.<ref target="BAWE_0255d-ftnote.038"/> This was a conscious process which had 'long been identified as critical to Japan's national security' and it enabled Japan to hurdle successive crises, in the 1970s - with the "Nixon shocks" and the Middle Eastern oil embargoes - and in the 1980s - with the affects of the dramatic appreciation of the Yen. </s><s n="s6.6;p13.25">As Japan's Ministry of International Trade and Industry (MITI) stated, "the globalization of economic activity has made it impossible to push ahead with economic development within the limited framework of a country defined by strict national boundaries".<ref target="BAWE_0255d-ftnote.039"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0255d-ftnote.036"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Hatch and Yamamura, <hi rend="italic">Asia in Japan's Embrace</hi>, pp.22-3 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0255d-ftnote.037"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Hatch and Yamamura, <hi rend="italic">Asia in Japan's Embrace</hi>, p.115 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0255d-ftnote.038"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Hatch and Yamamura, <hi rend="italic">Asia in Japan's Embrace</hi>, pp.36-40 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0255d-ftnote.039"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Hatch and Yamamura, <hi rend="italic">Asia in Japan's Embrace</hi>,, pp.117-9 </s></p></note><p n="p14.25"><s n="s1.6;p14.25">However, since the mid-1990s there had been a transition in Pacific Asia regionalism. </s><s n="s2.6;p14.25">Two distinct periods are now apparent: first, 'from about 1985 to 1994...the period of the flying geese model and of "open regionalism", or APEC style consensual cooperation among governments'; and, second, 'a period of instability in economic hierarchies and economic relations' since around 1994 which has been characterised, in simple terms, by a divergent contest between the 'Japan-centred' and 'greater China' centred regional production networks.<ref target="BAWE_0255d-ftnote.040"/> Up to 1994, according to Andrew Macintyre and Barry Naughton, Japan remained as closed as possible to foreign investment yet championed "open regionalism". </s><s n="s3.6;p14.25">This 'served as a convenient framework to coordinate some aspects of economic policy and to lower transaction costs faced by Japanese corporations (as investors) and Japanese financial institutions operating in other Asian economies. </s><s n="s4.6;p14.25">Thus, the fit was perfect with the notion of Japan acting as "lead goose", maintaining its own economic model intact, while gradually incorporating what were (mistakenly) perceived as junior versions of its model into an Asian community'. </s><s n="s5.6;p14.25">Whilst Japan continued to bankroll and provide the technology for regional development and prosperity, East Asian governments realised the benefits of loose political cooperation in order to achieve economic goals. </s><s n="s6.6;p14.25">Thus, 'APECs consensual and nonbinding pattern of policy cooperation suited perfectly'.<ref target="BAWE_0255d-ftnote.041"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0255d-ftnote.040"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Andrew Macintyre and Barry Naughton, 'The Decline of a Japan-Led Model of the East Asian Economy', in T.J Pempel (ed.), <hi rend="italic">Remapping East Asia: The Construction of a Region</hi>, Ithaca: Cornell University Press, 2005, p.77 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0255d-ftnote.041"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Macintyre and Naughton, 'The Decline of a Japan-Led Model', in Pempel (ed.), <hi rend="italic">Remapping East Asia</hi>, pp.83-5, and Mitchell Bernard and John Ravenhill, 'Beyond Product Cyles and Flying Geese: Regionalization, Hierarchy, and the Industrialization of East Asia', <hi rend="italic">World Politics</hi>, Vol.47, No.2, 1995, pp.183-99. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">Bernard and Ravenhill accept that Japanese economic development was perhaps the most significant factor in stimulating the interdependence that characterised the region based on the perceived efficacy of the "flying geese" model, however, they concur that the model is far too static to explain regional economic development. </s></p></note><p n="p15.25"><s n="s1.4;p15.25">After 1994, however, 'the flying goose pattern [had] disintegrated, and the countries in East Asia were left to search for other models and definitions of their self-interest'.<ref target="BAWE_0255d-ftnote.042"/> Moreover, a downturn in the 'economic dynamism' of the region in the mid-1990s mirrored a downturn in the vibrancy of the Japanese economy; particularly its investment capability was waning. </s><s n="s2.4;p15.25">The greater China economic network, including Taiwan and Hong Kong, was gradually beginning to outstrip Japan's 'technological and competitive superiority'. </s><s n="s3.4;p15.25">This period, therefore, experienced what can be seen as the erosion of the principles upon which the previous conception of regionalism, the "flying geese" model, had been founded.<ref target="BAWE_0255d-ftnote.043"/> A whole new economic region, more intricately networked, more specialised and more contested than ever before has emerged. </s><s n="s4.4;p15.25">APEC proved impotent in the face of this increased complexity.<ref target="BAWE_0255d-ftnote.044"/> In economic terms the emergence of China signalled the demise of Japanese dominance, to some extent, and in non-economic terms it is of particular significance 'because of...[its] unresolved territorial disputes, the unresolved reunification issue, the [apparent] zero-sum-game approach of China's leaders to foreign and security policy, the Chinese perception of having to regain their country's dignity and place in the world and the region, the huge perception gap between the Chinese élite's self-perception of a peaceful China and that of its Asian neighbours, and China's past record of using military power to achieve political objectives'.<ref target="BAWE_0255d-ftnote.045"/> Macintyre and Naughton are correct to raise concern about the traditional perception of Japanese led economic development providing the sole impetus for regionalism since the 1990s.<ref target="BAWE_0255d-ftnote.046"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0255d-ftnote.042"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Macintyre and Naughton, 'The Decline of a Japan-Led Model', in Pempel (ed.), <hi rend="italic">Remapping East Asia</hi>, p.85 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0255d-ftnote.043"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Macintyre and Naughton, 'The Decline of a Japan-Led Model', in Pempel (ed.), <hi rend="italic">Remapping East Asia</hi>, pp.86-90 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0255d-ftnote.044"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Macintyre and Naughton, 'The Decline of a Japan-Led Model', in Pempel (ed.), <hi rend="italic">Remapping East Asia</hi>, pp.94-6 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0255d-ftnote.045"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Reinhard Drifte, <hi rend="italic">Japan's Foreign Policy for the Twenty First Century: From Economic Superpower to What Power?</hi> </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">Basingstoke : Macmillan in association with St Antony's College, Oxford, 1998, pp.56-61 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0255d-ftnote.046"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Drifte, <hi rend="italic">Japan's Foreign Policy for the Twenty First Century</hi>, p.88 </s></p></note></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">V. The Institutionalisation of Regional Cooperation</head><p n="p16.25"><s n="s1.6;p16.25">In light of the changing nature of regionalism, Richard Higgot and Richard Stubbs juxtapose the Asia-Pacific Economic Cooperation (APEC) forum with the East Asia Economic Caucus (EAEC) which highlights diverging trends that remain poignant in the twenty first century. </s><s n="s2.6;p16.25">APEC, as an open forum devoted to economic liberalisation, came under challenge from the EAEC, a more narrowly defined bloc based on concepts of the 'Asian Way'. </s><s n="s3.6;p16.25">APEC formed in 1989 amid a proliferation of initiatives designed to institutionalise regional economic cooperation. </s><s n="s4.6;p16.25">Theoretically, it was underpinned by liberal institutionalist notions of relative gain driven international cooperation - APEC was, therefore, seen as a means to pull the region together and assimilate it with the international political economy. </s><s n="s5.6;p16.25">Prior to 1997, APEC was built on the optimism of the remarkable economic achievements experienced in the region - for the international community, and America in particular, it was necessary to break open these economies in order to remain competitive. </s><s n="s6.6;p16.25">Hence, APEC was riddled with a political agenda, namely the 'spread...the neo-liberal economic creed'.<ref target="BAWE_0255d-ftnote.047"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0255d-ftnote.047"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Richard Higgot and Richard Stubbs, 'Competing Conceptions of Economic Regionalism: APEC versus EAEC in the Asia Pacific', <hi rend="italic">Review of International Political Economy</hi>, Vol.2, No.3, 1995, pp.516-22 </s></p></note><p n="p17.25"><s n="s1.4;p17.25">Despite this, within Pacific Asia, APEC was regarded as essential in order to consolidate regionalism.<ref target="BAWE_0255d-ftnote.048"/> However, as John Ravenhill has commented, there are 'considerable weaknesses...evident...that limit its capacity to overcome collective action problems'. </s><s n="s2.4;p17.25">APEC has failed to either achieve the goals it was designed to achieve or to affect the behaviour and identity of the actors involved. </s><s n="s3.4;p17.25">The general consensus among scholars appears to be that APEC has thus far failed to instil any profound adherence to the tenets of economic liberalism - economic, financial and technical cooperation initiatives remain mundane. </s><s n="s4.4;p17.25">However, the process is considered a prerequisite to 'deeper integration' which has as yet failed to materialise.<ref target="BAWE_0255d-ftnote.049"/> As a result, Ravenhill has argued that APEC is a weak institution because it has not affected actor identities.<ref target="BAWE_0255d-ftnote.050"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0255d-ftnote.048"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Yoichi Funabashi, <hi rend="italic">Asia Pacific Fusion: Japan's Role in APEC</hi>, Washington DC: Institute for International Economics, 1995, p.195 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0255d-ftnote.049"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">John Ravenhill, <hi rend="italic">APEC and the Construction of Pacific Rim Regionalism</hi>, Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 2001, pp.186-95 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0255d-ftnote.050"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ravenhill, <hi rend="italic">APEC</hi>, pp.195-210 </s></p></note><p n="p18.25"><s n="s1.11;p18.25">The EAEC emerged in distinct opposition to APEC as the anti-thesis of a perceived capitulation to Western economic dogma and globalisation. </s><s n="s2.11;p18.25">Furthermore, it was intended to reflect the 'political, historical and cultural dimensions' of the region in contrast to American and European regionalism. </s><s n="s3.11;p18.25">It was assumed to be "an independent Asian voice". </s><s n="s4.11;p18.25">Under pinned by the investment capabilities of Japanese corporations, and, increasingly, Chinese ones, the region had experienced a surge in economic interdependence based on tightly knit production networks. </s><s n="s5.11;p18.25">The twentieth century experience in the region, with Japanese imperialism and US Cold War hegemony, marked out an ever more distinguishable politico-economic identity. </s><s n="s6.11;p18.25">For many, the time was ripe for an inward looking consolidation of this regionalism to promote social and cultural Asian-ness. </s><s n="s7.11;p18.25">However, the EAEC never gained any ground. </s><s n="s8.11;p18.25">Governments in the West opposed it and put pressure on its allies in the region, especially Japan, to reject the proposal. </s><s n="s9.11;p18.25">The EAEC would have negated the advantages the regions economies reaped from global trade, alienating the US in particular, and would have relied too heavily on Japanese finance - the latter provoked uneasy sentiments given Japan's history in the region. </s><s n="s10.11;p18.25">The EAEC was eventually swallowed up by APEC. However, East Asia represents a security interest for America, so in that sense, Japan has not written off the potential of closer regional cooperation. </s><s n="s11.11;p18.25">Also, the rest of the region, imbued with a sense of antagonism towards the West since 1997, has not abandoned closer cooperation.<ref target="BAWE_0255d-ftnote.051"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0255d-ftnote.051"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Higgot and Stubbs, 'Competing Conceptions of Economic Regionalism', pp.522-32 </s></p></note></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">VI. Contemporary Regional Initiatives</head><p n="p19.25"><s n="s1.9;p19.25">Economic integration still fuels the regionalism process even though its formal institutionalism has remained a benign phenomenon. </s><s n="s2.9;p19.25">Continuing the process that began with Japanese imperialism - and was actively pursued under US hegemony during the Cold War - cross border networks still form the basis of regional interdependence. </s><s n="s3.9;p19.25">In particular, Japanese corporations provide 'goods and investment' which is warmly received across the region provided that it 'contribute[s] to national prosperity and the Japanese government does not use its economic leverage to impose specific policies'. </s><s n="s4.9;p19.25">In this sense, the ambiguity of APEC, which has led to its "standstill", serves the interests of its largest two members - the US and Japan - by promoting the status quo. </s><s n="s5.9;p19.25">For Japan, the inherent flexibility of APEC means that it can bend the rules and protect vital interests while putting pressure on other countries not to discriminate against its products. </s><s n="s6.9;p19.25">For the US, any symbol of economic liberalism is useful, whilst an ineffective institution allows them to go beyond the APEC forum and apply pressure to individual countries in bilateral negotiations.<ref target="BAWE_0255d-ftnote.052"/> The profound and deep rooted economic networks consolidated by a century of economic interdependence based on the Japanese imperial design and its strategic role after the Second World War still pervade the region and inhibit formal institutionalism. </s><s n="s7.9;p19.25">The lack of formal institutionalism in the region does not imply that the regionalism agenda is in jeopardy. </s><s n="s8.9;p19.25">The proliferation of 'transboundary' economic and security issues as the process of globalisation abounds means that there is an increasing necessity for the countries of the region to cooperate in order to maintain national interests. </s><s n="s9.9;p19.25">To date, 'ad hoc, piecemeal negotiations' have characterised the system of 'open regionalism' and 'unilateral liberalization'.<ref target="BAWE_0255d-ftnote.053"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0255d-ftnote.052"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Keiichi Tsunekawa, 'Why So Many Maps There? </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">Japan and Regional Cooperation', in T.J Pempel (ed.), <hi rend="italic">Remapping East Asia: The Construction of a Region</hi>, Ithaca: Cornell University Press, 2005, pp.124-34 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0255d-ftnote.053"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Tsunekawa, 'Why So Many Maps There?' pp.101-15 </s></p></note><p n="p20.25"><s n="s1.4;p20.25">In light of this, the successful longevity of the Association of South East Asian Nations (ASEAN), as 'one of the most...enduring regional associations of the contemporary period', holds some potential. </s><s n="s2.4;p20.25">Philip Charier believes that ASEAN formed, not just as a result of historical interactions, but as a result of a common socially constructed spatial awareness in relation to "outsiders".<ref target="BAWE_0255d-ftnote.054"/> As an abstract, 'imagined' concept rather than an empirical 'reality' the idea of the region has served the purpose of actors both within and outside the region as it exists, not a closed or limited entity but as one which is open to changing circumstances.<ref target="BAWE_0255d-ftnote.055"/> Up to the mid-1990s ASEAN has also been influential in East Asian regionalism, particularly as a result of its relationship with Japan - based on a common interest in military-security and open intra-regional as well as extra-regional trade as 'global exporters'.<ref target="BAWE_0255d-ftnote.056"/> ASEAN's importance to Japan and vice-versa is determined by Japan's role as an 'investor, trader, aid donor and political actor' which is reliant on the natural resources of the South East Asian nations. </s><s n="s3.4;p20.25">Economic cooperation and interdependence is seen as vital by both parties in order to maintain political stability.<ref target="BAWE_0255d-ftnote.057"/> However, ASEAN has failed to concretely develop formal economic or military-security institutions. </s><s n="s4.4;p20.25">Despite its apparent significance, bilateral trade links with individual countries prevailed as did reliance on external powers to resolve conflicts as a consequence of the adherence to mutual non-intervention norms within ASEAN which had been enshrined in the Bangkok Declaration of 1967.<ref target="BAWE_0255d-ftnote.058"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0255d-ftnote.054"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Philip Charier, 'ASEAN's Inheritance: The Regionalisation of Southeast Asia, 1941-61', <hi rend="italic">The Pacific Review</hi>, Vol.14, No.3, 2001, pp.313-5 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0255d-ftnote.055"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Charier, 'ASEAN's Inheritance', pp.330-1 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0255d-ftnote.056"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Hook, 'Japan and the Construction of Asia-Pacific', in Gamble and Payne (eds.) <hi rend="italic">Regionalism and World Order</hi>, pp.191-2 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0255d-ftnote.057"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Alan Rix, 'Japan and the region: leading from behind', in Richard Higgott, Richard Leaver and John Ravenhill (eds.) <hi rend="italic">Pacific Economic Relations in the 1990s: Cooperation or Conflict?,</hi> Boulder, Colorado: Lynne Rienner, 1993, pp.68-73 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0255d-ftnote.058"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Wolf Mendl, Japan's Asia Policy: Regional Security and Global Interests, London: Routledge, 1995, pp.100-7 </s></p></note><p n="p21.25"><s n="s1.7;p21.25">The 1997 Financial Crisis, which was exacerbated by environmental concerns, such as the "haze", and political conflict in Cambodia occurring almost concomitantly, served to highlight the impotency of ASEAN in practical matters. </s><s n="s2.7;p21.25">Although only the latter fell directly under the aegis of the ASEAN framework, the inability to provide regional solutions to these problems was regarded as a failure on ASEAN's part. </s><s n="s3.7;p21.25">The impact of these crises on the North East Asian economies imbued the entire region with a sense of commonality which made the ASEAN Plus Three (APT) initiative all the more welcomed. </s><s n="s4.7;p21.25">The realisation of the dependency on external actors in particular invoked a sense of vulnerability. </s><s n="s5.7;p21.25">ASEAN, as the longest standing regional association, was seen as a useful body through which solutions could be reached'.<ref target="BAWE_0255d-ftnote.059"/> The emergence of economic, environmental and political crises all at once triggered a reappraisal of ASEAN's role as simply a security community founded on the principle of non-intervention. </s><s n="s6.7;p21.25">Rather than succumb to this inherent impotency, ASEAN proved that it was not a 'static' organisation and could 'grow beyond its limitations'.<ref target="BAWE_0255d-ftnote.060"/> As such, APT was conceived to expand ASEAN and bring East Asian nations together in order to coordinate policy involving economic, political issues and non-traditional security concerns such as anti-drug enforcement. </s><s n="s7.7;p21.25">Moreover, cooperation has moved beyond government issues to embrace a 'broad range of commercial and social bodies'.<ref target="BAWE_0255d-ftnote.061"/> Although economic cooperation still forms the bulk of regional integration, the new recognition of the importance of political credibility should stand APT in good stead to tackle new issues which is of particular significance in the post-9/11 world.<ref target="BAWE_0255d-ftnote.062"/> Environmental issues remain peripheral as do socio-cultural and education initiatives, but there presence on the agenda is indicative of a move toward a more pervasive regionalism.<ref target="BAWE_0255d-ftnote.063"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0255d-ftnote.059"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Nick Thomas, 'From ASEAN to an East Asian Community? </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">The Role of Functional Cooperation', <hi rend="italic">City University of Hong Kong South East Asia Research Centre Working Paper Series</hi>, No.28 (2002) <seg type="URL" n="http://www.cityu.edu.hk/searc/"/>, pp.3-4 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0255d-ftnote.060"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Thomas, 'From ASEAN to an East Asian Community?', pp.4-6 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0255d-ftnote.061"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Thomas, 'From ASEAN to an East Asian Community?', pp.6-10 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0255d-ftnote.062"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.3;pn1.1">As security issues now transcend national borders there is a direct link between the previously distinct realms of the domestic and the international. </s><s n="s2.3;pn1.1">The 'Pandora's Box' which sprung open after 1997 in East Asia has seen a proliferation of 'stateless' security issues which can no longer be neatly divided between political, economic and environmental and strategic categories. </s><s n="s3.3;pn1.1">Christopher W Hughes, 'Conceptualising the Globalisation-Security Nexus in the Asia-Pacific', <hi rend="italic">Security Dialogue</hi>, Vol.32, No.4 (2001), pp.412-21 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0255d-ftnote.063"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Thomas, 'From ASEAN to an East Asian Community?', pp.17-24 </s></p></note><p n="p22.25"><s n="s1.7;p22.25">APT signals a recognition that 'the global norms that upheld the non-intervention principle have changed dramatically in the last few years', and that conflict resolution may necessitate 'preventative' aspects, not just post-crisis management.<ref target="BAWE_0255d-ftnote.064"/> The ambiguity of the contemporary world must be met with a flexible approach to regionalism and a desire to coordinate between governments, rather than static concepts of regional problems - there is a sense that this is occurring with the APT initiative. </s><s n="s2.7;p22.25">That said, 'Asia should not be complacent...[and] should not delude itself into thinking that its identity can develop solely in regional terms'. </s><s n="s3.7;p22.25">Previous attempts have met with crisis throughout the history of the region. </s><s n="s4.7;p22.25">The region - however defined - must not attempt to shut out the rest of the world in a 'reactive' and closed response to issues of globalisation. </s><s n="s5.7;p22.25">Rather, regionalism should pursue an embracing response in order to harness the forces of the contemporary world to the benefit of the region. </s><s n="s6.7;p22.25">To do so, closer cooperation and collective bargaining will be the linchpin of the Asian voice in the international community.<ref target="BAWE_0255d-ftnote.065"/> APT has a great deal of potential and it is the source of much optimism in the region as a forum to overcome crisis.<ref target="BAWE_0255d-ftnote.066"/> Perhaps the regionalism initiative and the current convergence towards a common identity hinges on the open and more transparent coordination of economic and political preferences to avoid the recurrence of recent crises which is supported by Japan and the United States. </s><s n="s7.7;p22.25">If this convergence remains then a common cultural and social identity may well crystallise.<ref target="BAWE_0255d-ftnote.067"/> Yoichi Funabashi believe that, given a lack of common history and culture, the Asian community should look toward regionalism based on a common present and look to coordinate in order to face the contemporary challenges of modernity and globalisation.<ref target="BAWE_0255d-ftnote.068"/> This does not imply ruling out regionalism open to non-East Asian nations. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0255d-ftnote.064"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Thomas, 'From ASEAN to an East Asian Community?', pp.25-7 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0255d-ftnote.065"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Yoichi Funabashi, 'The Asianization of Asia', <hi rend="italic">Foreign Affairs</hi>, Vol.72, No.5 (1993), pp.75-84, and Peter J. Katzenstein, 'Regionalism and Asia', <hi rend="italic">New Political Economy</hi>, Vol.5, No.3, 2000, p.365 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0255d-ftnote.066"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Philip Bowring, 'East Asia: Centripetal or Centrifugal?', <hi rend="italic">City University of Hong Kong South East Asia Research Centre Working Paper Series</hi>, No.20 (2002) <seg type="URL" n="http://www.cityu.edu.hk/searc/"/>, pp.1-8 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0255d-ftnote.067"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Terada, 'Constructing an "East Asian" Concept', pp.270-4 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0255d-ftnote.068"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Paul Evans, 'Between Regionalism and Regionalization: Policy Networks and the Nascent East Asian Institutional Identity', in T.J Pempel (ed.), <hi rend="italic">Remapping East Asia: The Construction of a Region</hi>, Ithaca: Cornell University Press, 2005, pp.205-9 </s></p></note><p n="p23.25"><s n="s1.6;p23.25">Consequently, the APT initiative has become, 'the most ambitious and comprehensive of the governmental efforts to create an institutional framework to support East Asian regionalism'.<ref target="BAWE_0255d-ftnote.069"/> However, APT still faces the two-fold challenge of satisfying conflicting national interests in the practical sense and institutionalising a far from clear cut regional identity. </s><s n="s2.6;p23.25">There is a considerable disparity between North East Asian and South East Asian states, both in the practical sense of economic expertise and in the social and cultural sense. </s><s n="s3.6;p23.25">This lack of commonality is exacerbated by political issues. </s><s n="s4.6;p23.25">For instance, there is no interest from any individual government, or desire among the collective for any single state, to take the lead in advancing regionalism given the nature of previous attempts to do so. </s><s n="s5.6;p23.25">The role of the US is also crucial - it is unlikely to favour any closed form of regionalism which takes the strategic economic and security agenda out of its hands.<ref target="BAWE_0255d-ftnote.070"/> APT must proceed cautiously so as not to antagonise these areas of concern.<ref target="BAWE_0255d-ftnote.071"/> However, despite the traditional perception of regionalism as a government led phenomenon, there is much to suggest that it is moving ahead in a less formal, less state centric basis. </s><s n="s6.6;p23.25">Epistemic communities and policy networks, as detailed by Paul Evans based on influential works by John Gerard Ruggie and Richard Higgott, can evolve through the interaction of previously disparate individuals and groups that consequently forge a common sense of purpose and identity which provides not just optimism for, but a distinct basis from which to advance, regionalism.<ref target="BAWE_0255d-ftnote.072"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0255d-ftnote.069"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Evans, 'Between Regionalism and Regionalization', p.200 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0255d-ftnote.070"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">François Godement's assessment of the post-9/11 shift in US foreign policy and its implications for the region is an authoritative account of this. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">Godement, 'Escaping the Merchant/Missionary Dilemma, pp.176-87 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0255d-ftnote.071"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Evans, 'Between Regionalism and Regionalization', pp.200-1 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0255d-ftnote.072"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Evans, 'Between Regionalism and Regionalization', pp.202-4 </s></p></note><p n="p24.25"><s n="s1.8;p24.25">APT regionalism does not imply closed regionalism based on previous concepts of an East Asian identity which failed in the past. </s><s n="s2.8;p24.25">Contrary to Markus Hund's assessment of APT as unrepresentative of East Asian identity, the argument here is that regional perceptions have changed which are now more conducive to an open form of regionalism as best represented by the APT association. Regional perceptions have changed as a result of globalisation, and in particular, the 1997 Financial Crisis. </s><s n="s3.8;p24.25">Clearly at this stage doubts about the commitment of members, particularly the northern three, are an issue as it remains to be seen whether APT will bring about 'significant...achievements'.<ref target="BAWE_0255d-ftnote.073"/> Hund's pessimistic conclusion that there appears to be a lack of will to achieve concrete goals may be overly pessimistic - the most significant thing about APT to date is the recognition and gradual acknowledgement of a common purpose. </s><s n="s4.8;p24.25">Clearly, only time will tell if it is successful or not. </s><s n="s5.8;p24.25">Hund himself acknowledges that, 'regardless of APT's internal divisions and uncertainties, its dynamic has nevertheless already had an impact on the political and economic landscape of East Asia'. </s><s n="s6.8;p24.25">The point that 'the evolution of an exclusive East Asian identity seems to be a long way off' is a mute one.<ref target="BAWE_0255d-ftnote.074"/> Beeson points us back to David Kang's standpoint whereby he asserts that international relations in the region may not fit well with purely Western interpretations. </s><s n="s7.8;p24.25">In this sense, traditional power relations might well evolve differently in East Asia than they did for example in Europe, if at all. </s><s n="s8.8;p24.25">If this is the case then the rise of a powerful China will be more beneficial than confrontational.<ref target="BAWE_0255d-ftnote.075"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0255d-ftnote.073"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Markus Hund, 'ASEAN Plus Three: Towards a New Age of Pan-East Asian Regionalism? </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">A Critic's Appraisal', <hi rend="italic">The Pacific Review</hi>, Vol.16, No.3 (2003), pp.403-6 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0255d-ftnote.074"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Hund, 'ASEAN Plus Three', p.411 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0255d-ftnote.075"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Mark Beeson, 'Multilateralism, American Power and East Asian Regionalism', <hi rend="italic">City University of Hong Kong South East Asia Research Centre Working Paper Series</hi>, No.64 (2004) <seg type="URL" n="http://www.cityu.edu.hk/searc/"/>, pp.12-13 </s></p></note></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">VII. Conclusion</head><p n="p25.25"><s n="s1.6;p25.25">In summary, Japanese imperialism must be seen as a crucial factor in the history of regional cooperation. </s><s n="s2.6;p25.25">Wrenching East Asian nations into modernity, via economic development and industrialisation, Japanese imperialism left an indelible imprint on the region. </s><s n="s3.6;p25.25">The economic interdependency which emerged prior to the Second World War was subsequently consolidated by the post-bellum foreign policy of the United States in order to promote regional stability. </s><s n="s4.6;p25.25">From this, cooperation has developed around a core of economic and production networks. </s><s n="s5.6;p25.25">This core of functional interdependency still forms the concrete basis from which regionalism in Pacific Asia is occurring today. </s><s n="s6.6;p25.25">This essay has attempted to demonstrate that despite a proliferation of potentially divisive issues that have abounded since the turn of the century, economic cooperation provides the impetus for cooperation concerning new and increasingly salient issues which are potentially conflict ridden. </s></p></div1></body><back><div1 type="bibliography"><head rend="underlined bold">Bibliography</head><p>Acharya, Amitav, 'Regional Military-Security Cooperation in the Third World: a Conceptual Analysis of the Association of Southeast Asian Nations', <hi rend="italic">Journal of Peace Research</hi>, Vol.29, No.1 (1992), pp.7-21</p><p>Acharya, Amitav, <hi rend="italic">Constructing a Security Community in South East Asia: ASEA and the Problem of Regional Order</hi>, London: Routledge, 2001</p><p>Anderson, Benedict, The Spectre of Comparisons: Nationalism, Southeast Asia and the World, London: Verso, 1998</p><p>Barnhart, Michael, A., <hi rend="italic">Japan and The World Since 1868</hi>, London: Edward Arnold, 1995</p><p>Beasley, William G., <hi rend="italic">The Rise of Modern Japan</hi>, London: Weidenfeld &amp; Nicolson, 1995</p><p>Beeson, Mark, 'The Political Economy of East Asia at a Time of Crisis', in Richard Stubbs and Geoffrey R.D. Underhill,<hi rend="italic"> Political Economy and the Changing Global Order</hi> (2<hi rend="sup">nd</hi> Edition), Toronto: Oxford University Press, 2000</p><p>Beeson, Mark, 'Multilateralism, American Power and East Asian Regionalism', <hi rend="italic">City University of Hong Kong South East Asia Research Centre Working Paper Series</hi>, No.64 (2004) <seg type="URL" n="http://www.cityu.edu.hk/searc/"/></p><p>Berger, Mark T., <hi rend="italic">The Battle for Asia: From Decolonisation to Globalisation</hi>, London: Routledge, 2004</p><p>Bernard, Mitchell, and Ravenhill, John, 'Beyond Product Cyles and Flying Geese: Regionalization, Hierarchy, and the Industrialization of East Asia', <hi rend="italic">World Politics</hi>, Vol.47, No.2, 1995</p><p>Bevacqua, Ron, 'Whither the Japanese model? The Asian Economic Crisis and the Continuation of Cold War politics in the Pacific Rim', <hi rend="italic">Review of International Political Economy</hi>, Vol.5, No. 3 (1998), pp.410-23.</p><p>Bowring, Philip, 'East Asia: Centripetal or Centrifugal?', <hi rend="italic">City University of Hong Kong South East Asia Research Centre Working Paper Series</hi>, No.20 (2002) <seg type="URL" n="http://www.cityu.edu.hk/searc/"/> </p><p>Calman, Donald, <hi rend="italic">The Nature and Origins of Japanese Imperialism: A Reinterpretation of The Great Crisis of 1873</hi>, London: Routledge, 1992</p><p>Charier, Philip, 'ASEAN's Inheritance: The Regionalisation of Southeast Asia, 1941-61', <hi rend="italic">The Pacific Review</hi>, Vol.14, No.3, 2001</p><p>Cheow, Eric Teo Chu, 'Challenges to "East Asia": Fears and uncertainties may block wider regionalism', <hi rend="italic">Asiaweek</hi>, Vol.26, No.36 (2000) <seg type="URL" n="http://www.asiaweek.com/asiaweek/magazine/2000/0915/viewpoint.html"/></p><p>Conroy, Hilary, 'Lessons of Japanese Imperialism', <hi rend="italic">Monumenta Nipponica</hi>, Vol.21, No.3/4 (1966), pp.334-45</p><p>Cumings, Bruce, 'The Origins and Development of the Northeast Asian Political Economy: Industrial Sectors, Product Cycles, and Political Consequences', <hi rend="italic">International Organisation</hi>, Vol.38, No.1, 1984</p><p>Drifte, Reinhard, <hi rend="italic">Japan's Foreign Policy for the Twenty First Century: From Economic Superpower to What Power?</hi> Basingstoke : Macmillan in association with St Antony's College, Oxford, 1998</p><p>Dower, John, <hi rend="italic">War Without Mercy: Race and Power in the Pacific War</hi>, London; Faber and Faber, 1986</p><p>Evans, Paul, 'Between Regionalism and Regionalization: Policy Networks and the Nascent East Asian Institutional Identity', in T.J Pempel (ed.), <hi rend="italic">Remapping East Asia: The Construction of a Region</hi>, Ithaca: Cornell University Press, 2005</p><p>Funabashi, Yoichi, 'The Asianization of Asia', <hi rend="italic">Foreign Affairs</hi>, Vol.72, No.5 (1993)</p><p>Funabashi, Yoichi, <hi rend="italic">Asia Pacific Fusion: Japan's Role in APEC</hi>, Washington DC: Institute for International Economics, 1995</p><p>Gamble, Andrew, and Payne, Anthony, (eds.) <hi rend="italic">Regionalism and World Order</hi>, Basingstoke : Macmillan Press, 1996</p><p>Godement, François, <hi rend="italic">The New Asian Renaissance: From Colonialism to Post-Cold War</hi>, London: Routledge, 1997</p><p>Godement, François, 'Escaping the Merchant/Missionary Dilemma: An Imperial Policy for the Asia Pacific', <hi rend="italic">The Pacific Review</hi>, Vol.16, No.2, 2003</p><p>Hatch, Walter, 'Regionalization Trumps Globalization: Japanese Production Networks in Asia', in Richard Stubbs and Geoffrey R.D. Underhill<hi rend="italic">, Political Economy and the Changing Global Order</hi> (2<hi rend="sup">nd</hi> Edition), Toronto: Oxford University Press, 2000</p><p>Hatch, Walter and Yamamura, Kozo, <hi rend="italic">Asia in Japan's Embrace: Building a Regional Production Alliance</hi>, Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 1996</p><p>Higgot, Richard, and Stubbs, Richard, 'Competing Conceptions of Economic Regionalism: APEC versus EAEC in the Asia Pacific', <hi rend="italic">Review of International Political Economy</hi>, Vol.2, No.3, 1995</p><p>Higgott, Richard, 'Regionalism in the Asia-Pacific: Two-Steps Forward, One Step Back?' in Richard Stubbs and Geoffrey R.D. <hi rend="italic">Underhill, Political Economy and the Changing Global Order</hi> (2<hi rend="sup">nd</hi> Edition), Toronto: Oxford University Press, 2000</p><p>Hoogvelt, Ankie, <hi rend="italic">Globalization and the Postcolonial World: the New Political Economy of Development</hi>, Basingstoke: Palgrave, 2001</p><p>Hoston, Germaine A., 'Marxism and Japanese Expansionism: Takahashi Kamekichi and the Theory of "Petty Imperialism"', Journal of Japanese Studies, Vol.10, No.1 (1984), pp.1-30</p><p>Hughes, Christopher W., 'Conceptualising the Globalisation-Security Nexus in the Asia-Pacific', <hi rend="italic">Security Dialogue</hi>, Vol.32, No.4 (2001), pp.407-421</p><p>Hund, Markus, 'ASEAN Plus Three: Towards a New Age of Pan-East Asian Regionalism? A Critic's Appraisal', <hi rend="italic">The Pacific Review</hi>, Vol.16, No.3 (2003), pp.383-418</p><p>Jo, Yung-Hwan, 'Regional Cooperation in Southeast Asia and Japan's Role', Journal of Politics, Vol.30, No.3 (Aug., 1968) pp.780-797</p><p>Johnson, Chalmers, 'Economic Crisis in East Asia: the Clash of Capitalisms'<hi rend="italic">, Cambridge Journal of Economics</hi>, Vol.22, No.6 (1998), pp.652-62.</p><p>Kang, David C., 'Getting Asia wrong: the need for new analytical frameworks', <hi rend="italic">International Security</hi>, Vol.27, No.4 (2003), pp. 57-85.</p><p>Katzenstein, Peter, 'Regionalism and Asia', <hi rend="italic">New Political Economy</hi>, Vol.5, No.3, 2000</p><p>Koschmann, Victor, J., 'Asianism's Ambivalent Legacy', in Peter J. Katzenstein and Takashi Shiraishi, <hi rend="italic">Network Power: Japan and Asia</hi>, Ithaca, NY: Cornell University Press, 1997</p><p>Liberman, Peter, <hi rend="italic">Does Conquest Pay? The Exploitation of Occupied Industrial Societies</hi>, Princeton, New Jersey: Princeton University Press, 1996</p><p>Macintyre, Andrew, and Naughton, Barry, 'The Decline of a Japan-Led Model of the East Asian Economy', in T.J Pempel (ed.), <hi rend="italic">Remapping East Asia: The Construction of a Region</hi>, Ithaca: Cornell University Press, 2005</p><p>Mendl, Wolf, <hi rend="italic">Japan's Asia Policy: Regional Security and Global Interests</hi>, London: Routledge, 1995</p><p>Mitton, Roger, 'Asia Looks to Itself', <hi rend="italic">Asiaweek</hi>, (23 August 2001) <seg type="URL" n="http://www.asiaweek.com/asiaweek/magazine/dateline/0,8782,172286,00.html"/> </p><p>Ravenhill, John, <hi rend="italic">APEC and the Construction of Pacific Rim Regionalism</hi>, Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 2001</p><p>Rix, Alan, 'Japan and the region: leading from behind', in Richard Higgott, Richard Leaver and John Ravenhill (eds.) <hi rend="italic">Pacific Economic Relations in the 1990s: Cooperation or Conflict?,</hi> Boulder, Colorado: Lynne Rienner, 1993, pp. 62-82.</p><p>Selden, Mark, 'China, Japan, and the Regional Political Economy of East Asia, 1945-1995', in Peter J. Katzenstein and Takashi Shiraishi, <hi rend="italic">Network Power: Japan and Asia</hi>, Ithaca, NY: Cornell University Press, 1997</p><p>Terada, Takashi, 'Constructing an "East Asian" Concept and Growing Regional Identity: From EAEC to ASEAN+3', <hi rend="italic">The Pacific Review</hi>, Vol.16, No.2 (2003), pp.251-277</p><p>Thomas, Nick, 'From ASEAN to an East Asian Community? The Role of Functional Cooperation', <hi rend="italic">City University of Hong Kong South East Asia Research Centre Working Paper Series</hi>, No.28 (2002) <seg type="URL" n="http://www.cityu.edu.hk/searc/"/> </p><p>Tsunekawa, Keiichi, 'Why So Many Maps There? Japan and Regional Cooperation', in T.J Pempel (ed.), <hi rend="italic">Remapping East Asia: The Construction of a Region</hi>, Ithaca: Cornell University Press, 2005</p><p>Warren, Bill, <hi rend="italic">Imperialism: The Pioneer of Capitalism</hi>, London: Verso, 1980</p><p>Yahuda, Michael, <hi rend="italic">The International Politics of the Asia-Pacific</hi>, New York: RoutledgeCurzon, 2004</p></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
