<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_0258g" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Holerith Integrated Tabulator</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">Evaluated as candidate compound assignment. Assigned to S4: set of tasks/questions/exercises: non-compound</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">2</p><p n="date">2004-05</p><p n="module title">Human Computer Interaction</p><p n="module code">CS231</p><p n="genre family">Explanation + Explanation + Explanation + Explanation</p><p n="discipline">Computer Science</p><p n="disciplinary group">PS</p><p n="grade">M</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">1285</p><p n="number of s-units">55</p><p n="number of p">20</p><p n="number of tables">0</p><p n="number of figures">4</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">0</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">0</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">23.4</p><p n="average s-units per p">2.8</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">complex but non-compound assignment (see notesStmt for details)</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">m</p><p n="year of birth">1984</p><p n="first language">Hindi</p><p n="education">OSA</p><p n="course">Computer Science</p><p n="student ID">0258</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><figure id="BAWE_0258g-pic.001"><head>#1 </head></figure></front><body><div1 type="section"><head>Course: Computer Science ID: <name type="student ID"/> Holerith Integrated Tabulator.</head><p n="p1.20"><s n="s1.1;p1.20">The device shown in the figure is the Herman Hollerith Integrated tabulator designed between 1888 and mid-1890s, debuting in 1896, it was designed to handle the large aggregate totals demanded by farm statistics and railroad accounting and had a major impact on the performance and way data was processed. </s></p><p n="p2.20"><s n="s1.2;p2.20">Herman Hollerith was born in Buffalo, New York, in 1860, the son of German immigrants. </s><s n="s2.2;p2.20">Hollerith initially invented his <hi rend="bold">Electric Tabulating System</hi> in 1890 to: "Provide a system which will reduce the labor necessary in the compilation of such statistics, which will increase the rapidity of making complicated tallies, and which will insure accuracy". </s></p><p n="p3.20"><s n="s1.3;p3.20">Hollerith's machine tabulated the results of the 1890 census in the United States, making it the fastest and most economical census to date. </s><s n="s2.3;p3.20">In a single day, 56 of these machines could tabulate census information about more than six million people and this marked a major step forward in processing of information. </s><s n="s3.3;p3.20">It was a technical and financial success for the US Government as it reduced the man power which was required and reduced the time it took previously to complete census, where there was always a danger of starting next census simultaneously with process of last. </s></p><p n="p4.20"><s n="s1.2;p4.20">The 1890 tabulator was capable only of counting using dials and it lacked in storing numerical quantities. </s><s n="s2.2;p4.20">So, the next significant contribution by Hollerith was to produce a machine for agriculture census, which required the accumulation of quantities. </s></p><p n="p5.20"><s n="s1.3;p5.20">In the Hollerith method information about person was represented on a card which was punched by punching machines and used for further evaluation and bringing census results. </s><s n="s2.3;p5.20">The card after punching was placed in the tabulating machine in position so that every hole in the card was exactly over a mercury cup. </s><s n="s3.3;p5.20">Each hole allowed a needle-like connecting wire to come down and make an electrical contact with the mercury and counts were made. </s></p><p n="p6.20"><s n="s1.2;p6.20">The new machine added various columns then just counting one by one. </s><s n="s2.2;p6.20">Hollerith produced an Integrated tabulation machine that used a row of columns, which simultaneously added multi-digit numbers in each field on given card, thus it broadened the scope to accounting, warehousing and shipping applications. </s></p></div1><div1 type="front-back-matter"><head>References</head><p>
The Pieces of Science: <seg type="URL" n="http://www.sln.org/pieces/owens/story.html"/> 
</p><p>
From the US Constitution to IBM <seg type="URL" n="http://www4.wittenberg.edu/academics/mathcomp/bjsdir/history0.shtml"/> 
</p><p>
Tabulating Machines: <seg type="URL" n="http://www.earlyofficemuseum.com/data_processing_machines.htm"/> 
</p><p>
Computing before Computer - Chapter 4 
</p><figure id="BAWE_0258g-pic.002"><head>#2 </head></figure></div1><div1 type="section"><head>Course: Computer Science ID: <name type="student ID"/> Amsler Planimeter</head><p n="p7.20"><s n="s1.1;p7.20">The device shown is an Amsler Planimeter, which was invented in about 1854 by Jacob Amsler then a student at Konigsberg, it was easily able to measure the area of any plane shape. </s></p><p n="p8.20"><s n="s1.3;p8.20">Jacob Amsler grew up in Stalden, a town in the Vispa valley. </s><s n="s2.3;p8.20">He studied theology at University of Jena and then moved to the University of Konigsberg to study Mathematics and Physics. </s><s n="s3.3;p8.20">Shortly after his marriage, he began to study the construction of precision mathematical instruments and soon after had the idea to design a new type of planimeter. </s></p><p n="p9.20"><s n="s1.4;p9.20">During the first half of the Nineteenth Century, the need for an instrument that would accurately measure area inspired several ingenious devices. </s><s n="s2.4;p9.20">Planimeters prior to Amsler's invention were either inaccurate, difficult to use, or cumbersome. </s><s n="s3.4;p9.20">The Amsler planimeter was new in the sense that it took a different approach compared to those previously designed, it was based on the polar coordinates concept whereas the earlier instruments where based on Cartesian coordinates. </s><s n="s4.4;p9.20">It differed from the previous planimeters in the movement of the end of the tracer arm opposite the tracer point. </s></p><p n="p10.20"><s n="s1.6;p10.20">The device was a major step forward and became very popular in a short time. </s><s n="s2.6;p10.20">This was due to the ease of use of the instrument. </s><s n="s3.6;p10.20">It could readily measure the area of any plane shape. </s><s n="s4.6;p10.20">The operator had to simply trace the outline of the shape with the pointer attached. </s><s n="s5.6;p10.20">The difference of the readings on the graduate roller taken before and after the trace was the area of shape. </s><s n="s6.6;p10.20">The other reason for its popularity was that the device was cheap to buy which led to manufacture of thousands of the instrument in the nineteenth century. </s></p><p n="p11.20"><s n="s1.1;p11.20">The device was susceptible to faults, as it was not meant for irregular surfaces; this limited its use and leads to further development of new planimeters in last century. </s></p></div1><div1 type="front-back-matter"><head>References:</head><p>
1. 
Computing Science Technical Report No. 
99 Brown and Holbrook - 1982 
</p><p>
2. 
Biography of Jacob Amsler: Dictionary of Scientific Biography. 
</p><p>
3. 
Computing before Computers: William Aspray 1990. 
</p><figure id="BAWE_0258g-pic.003"><head>#3 </head></figure></div1><div1 type="section"><head>Course: Computer Science ID: <name type="student ID"/> Manual for Flow-Matic</head><p n="p12.20"><s n="s1.1;p12.20">The picture shows the manual which was published for the first English language data-processing compiler Flow-Matic by Grace Hopper of Remington Rand Corporation. </s></p><p n="p13.20"><s n="s1.5;p13.20">Grace Murray Hopper spent much of her inventive career proving that it was perfectly possible to devise totally new concepts. </s><s n="s2.5;p13.20">She believed that computer programs could be written in English. </s><s n="s3.5;p13.20">It was this kind of positive thinking that inspired Hopper to invent the first computer "compiler" in 1952. </s><s n="s4.5;p13.20">That was her best known contribution to computing, which was an intermediate program, designed to translate English language instruction into the instruction of the target computer. </s><s n="s5.5;p13.20">This software facilitated the first automatic programming of computer language. </s></p><p n="p14.20"><s n="s1.3;p14.20">Grace Hopper was born Grace Brewster Murray, the oldest of three children. </s><s n="s2.3;p14.20">Her father was an insurance broker while her mother had a love of mathematics, which she passed to her daughter. </s><s n="s3.3;p14.20">Grace Hopper was an intellectual lady and gained several degrees and always had a desire to join the military. </s></p><p n="p15.20"><s n="s1.1;p15.20">In 1949 Hopper joined the Eckert- Mauchly Computer Corporation as a senior mathematician and then worked on the UNIVAC computer and at that time she designed an improved compiler. </s></p><p n="p16.20"><s n="s1.5;p16.20">In 1950 the Remington Rand Corporation acquired the Eckert-Mauchly Computer Corporation where Hopper was a senior mathematician and its name was changed to UNIVAC Division of Remington Rand. </s><s n="s2.5;p16.20">Hopper continued her work on compilers and published her first paper on that topic in 1952. </s><s n="s3.5;p16.20">The compiler was a time and error saving breakthrough for the computer world as previously programmers had to write lengthy instruction in binary code for every new piece of software. </s><s n="s4.5;p16.20">This was difficult for programmers as this type of programming was time consuming and prone to frustrating mistakes. </s><s n="s5.5;p16.20">She was also involved in work for producing specification for the COBOL language. </s></p></div1><div1 type="front-back-matter"><head>References:</head><p>
Wikipedia: <seg type="URL" n="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/FLOW-MATIC"/> 
</p><p>
Hopper Biography: <seg type="URL" n="http://www.thocp.net/biograpies/hopper_grace.html"/> 
</p><p>
The History of Programming Languages. 
</p><figure id="BAWE_0258g-pic.004"><head>#4 </head></figure></div1><div1 type="section"><head>Course: Computer Science ID: <name type="student ID"/> Honeywell DDP - 516</head><p n="p17.20"><s n="s1.1;p17.20">The device shown in the figure is a Honeywell DDP -516 minicomputer with 12kb of Core memory - originally designed by Computer Control Company, but was later bought and introduced by Honeywell in 1966. </s></p><p n="p18.20"><s n="s1.4;p18.20">The series 16 included several 16-bit minicomputers such as models 116,316,416,516,716. </s><s n="s2.4;p18.20">They were 16 bit minicomputers. </s><s n="s3.4;p18.20">By today's standard they were extremely simple; a single accumulator, an index register, one auxiliary register and magnetic core memory. </s><s n="s4.4;p18.20">They were commonly used for data acquisitions and controls, remote message concentration, clinical laboratory system and time-sharing. </s></p><p n="p19.20"><s n="s1.6;p19.20">DDP 516 was introduced in 1966 and formed the core of the series 16. </s><s n="s2.6;p19.20">According to some sources it was the first series 16 minicomputer that was used in wide applications. </s><s n="s3.6;p19.20">Many were used in computer control applications, and many educational establishments used them as general-purpose computers. </s><s n="s4.6;p19.20">The 516 were configured with 12kw of core memory and 16-channel direct multiplex control unit. </s><s n="s5.6;p19.20">The DDP-516 machine had many of the CPU options and optional peripherals; Extended addressing, Memory lockout, High speed arithmetic, Real-time clock, Direct multiplex control, High speed paper tape reader and punch, Line printer, Magnetic tape, and Moving head disc file. </s><s n="s6.6;p19.20">DDP - 516 were clearly the forerunner of all the machines, but seem to have made little impact commercially. </s></p><p n="p20.20"><s n="s1.1;p20.20">DDP - 516 was used in wide applications and the most important of these relates to the origin of Internet where it was used as the basis of "Interface Message Processor" IMPs that were used to connect the very first networked computers to the ARPANET. It was chosen by Frank Heart for designing and programming of IMP because it was one of the most powerful minicomputer available at that time and it was built to military specification which was of significant importance for its choice. </s></p></div1></body><back><div1 type="bibliography"><head>References:</head><p>DDP - 516 <seg type="URL" n="http://www.old-computers.com/museum/computer.asp?st=1&amp;c=551"/></p><p>Micro-coding the DDP 516 computer: <seg type="URL" n="http://www.series16.adrianwise.co.uk/microcode.html"/></p><p>Series 16 History <seg type="URL" n="http://www.series16.adrianwise.co.uk/my_machines.html"/></p></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
