<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_0259c" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>On Husserl's Phenomenological Reduction and Metaphysical Idealism</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">Language used in quote: <foreign id="English">English</foreign></note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">deleted: page numbers</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">4</p><p n="date">2006-02</p><p n="module title">Origins of Phenomenology</p><p n="module code">PH955</p><p n="genre family">Essay</p><p n="discipline">Philosophy</p><p n="disciplinary group">AH</p><p n="grade">D</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">4870</p><p n="number of s-units">160</p><p n="number of p">35</p><p n="number of tables">0</p><p n="number of figures">0</p><p n="number of block quotes">11</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">0</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">0</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">30.4</p><p n="average s-units per p">4.6</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">f</p><p n="year of birth">1982</p><p n="first language">English</p><p n="education">OSA</p><p n="course">Philosophy</p><p n="student ID">0259</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><docTitle><titlePart rend="bold">On Husserl's Phenomenological Reduction and Metaphysical Idealism</titlePart></docTitle><epigraph><p><hi rend="italic">"Only someone who misunderstands either the deepest sense of intentional method, or that of transcendental reduction, or perhaps both, can attempt to separate phenomenology from transcendental idealism."</hi><ref target="BAWE_0259c-ftnote.001"/></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0259c-ftnote.001"><p> Husserl, Edmund. <hi rend="italic">Cartesian Meditations,</hi> Dorion Cairns (tr.), Martinus Nijhoff, The Hague, 1960, p. 86. This work will be referred to as <hi rend="italic">Cart.</hi> </p></note></epigraph></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined">Introduction</head><p n="p1.35"><s n="s1.7;p1.35">It is the method of the phenomenological reduction that distinguished Husserl from all others. </s><s n="s2.7;p1.35">Not only did he spend his entire career carefully writing further and further elaboration of its proper conception, but although many of his students took on the general idea of the reductions and incorporated it into their own work, not one followed him in its complete application. </s><s n="s3.7;p1.35">In fact, by the end of his life, Husserl's students had all to some degree or another turned away from his teachings, being convinced that Husserl had taken phenomenology down an overly idealist path. </s><s n="s4.7;p1.35">Now, it is obvious from the opening quote that the charge of idealism would be readily admitted by Husserl himself. </s><s n="s5.7;p1.35">From as early as Ideas 1, Husserl began to argue that the only possible conclusion to be taken from the phenomenological method was that of transcendental idealism.<ref target="BAWE_0259c-ftnote.002"/> And although he maintained this position with increasing conviction for the remainder of his life, at the same time he maintained that by this he was taking no stance on metaphysics, or at least not an idealist metaphysical stance. </s><s n="s6.7;p1.35">He explicitly fought against his work being interpreted along the lines of idealism typically conceived (i.e. </s><s n="s7.7;p1.35">Berkeylan idealism), seeing his own contribution as staying within the realm of epistemology. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0259c-ftnote.002"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.3;pn1.1">Husserl, Edmund. </s><s n="s2.3;pn1.1"><hi rend="italic">Ideas Pertaining to a Pure Phenomenology and to a Phenomenological Philosophy, First Book</hi>, F. Kersten (tr.), Kluwer, 1998, section 49. </s><s n="s3.3;pn1.1">This work will be referred to as <hi rend="italic">Ideas 1.</hi> </s></p></note><p n="p2.35"><s n="s1.5;p2.35">Despite Husserl's insistence to the contrary, the charge of metaphysical idealism can still be argued for convincingly. </s><s n="s2.5;p2.35">Roman Ingarden, in his work <hi rend="italic">On the Motives which led Husserl to Transcendental Idealism</hi>, takes up precisely this issue.<ref target="BAWE_0259c-ftnote.003"/> In this paper, I will first explain Husserl's reduction in terms of his philosophical project as a whole, its role as key methodological tool becoming apparent. </s><s n="s3.5;p2.35">Second, I will argue, following some of the criticisms laid out by Ingarden in <hi rend="italic">Motives</hi>, that the reduction in the way Husserl conceived of it, can and must be interpreted as taking a particular metaphysical stance: an idealistic one. </s><s n="s4.5;p2.35">It will be crucial, in order to fully understand Ingarden's criticisms, and to do as much justice to Husserl as possible, to come to grips with how this idealism is unique, and therefore not to be confused with a Berkeleyan-style metaphysical idealism. </s><s n="s5.5;p2.35">Despite the fact that Husserl denied vehemently that he was committed to any metaphysical position, idealistic or otherwise, it will become clear that Ingarden's criticisms are justified, and that, acknowledged by Husserl or not, the reduction not only suggests, but insists significant metaphysical implications. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0259c-ftnote.003"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.3;pn1.1">Ingarden, Roman. </s><s n="s2.3;pn1.1"><hi rend="italic">On the Motives which led Husserl to Transcendental Idealism</hi>, Arnor Hannibalsson (tr.), Martinus Nijhoff, The Hague, 1975. </s><s n="s3.3;pn1.1">This work will be referred to as <hi rend="italic">Motives.</hi> </s></p></note><p n="p3.35"><s n="s1.7;p3.35">Although Ingarden is by no means the originator of the interpretation of Husserl as a metaphysical idealist, I have chosen his work for two reasons. </s><s n="s2.7;p3.35">First, Ingarden was for many years a student of Husserl, considered for much of that time to be Husserl's favourite. </s><s n="s3.7;p3.35">From this we can fairly expect that Ingarden had excellent opportunity to gain a sophisticated grasp of Husserl's work. </s><s n="s4.7;p3.35">Second, Ingarden was for his entire career centrally concerned with the idealism/realism debate, his thoughts made fully manifest in his magnum opus <hi rend="italic">Controversy over the Existence of the World</hi>. </s><s n="s5.7;p3.35">The problem of idealism is not Ingarden's side project; it is the driving issue of his philosophical career. </s><s n="s6.7;p3.35">What this adds up to, in my mind, is a potentially more interesting and worthwhile critic. </s><s n="s7.7;p3.35">Indeed, I take Ingarden's critique to be based on a sound and charitable reading of Husserl, and I think he quite rightly elaborates (what he argues to be) inevitable metaphysical conclusions. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined">Husserl's Project</head><p n="p4.35"><s n="s1.1;p4.35">I will first offer only the briefest of sketches of Husserl's over-arching philosophical concerns before getting to the reduction in detail. </s></p><p n="p5.35"><s n="s1.3;p5.35">Influenced heavily by his early career in mathematics, as well as the reigning ideal of scientific objectivity, Husserl's goal was to set up for cognition absolute foundations.<ref target="BAWE_0259c-ftnote.004"/> Philosophy, as the investigation into the meaning of being, and thus the most ultimate human discipline, must, for Husserl, identify itself with the scientific ideal, i.e. it must be <hi rend="italic">objective</hi> and <hi rend="italic">apodictic</hi>. </s><s n="s2.3;p5.35">What this demands is "the demonstration of an absolutely certain, indubitable philosophical cognition and the elaboration of a method of inquiry that may be systematically employed in order to ensure the validity of such cognition".<ref target="BAWE_0259c-ftnote.005"/> Through the method he spent his entire life carefully elaborating, he believed to have established a way to provide clear and incontrovertible evidence for and thereby knowledge of that which is. </s><s n="s3.3;p5.35">Phenomenology, and its method of the reduction, was the only philosophy to achieve this standard. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0259c-ftnote.004"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Kockelmans, Joseph J. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">"What is Phenomenology: Some Fundamental Themes of Husserl's Phenomenology" in <hi rend="italic">Phenomenology: The Philosophy of Edmund Husserl and Its Interpreation</hi>, Kockelmans, Joseph J. (ed.), Anchor, 1967, p. 26. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0259c-ftnote.005"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Mitscherling, Jeff. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1"><hi rend="underlined">Roman Ingarden's Ontology and Aesthetics</hi>, University of Ottawa Press, 1997, p. 62. </s></p></note><p n="p6.35"><s n="s1.4;p6.35">The term 'phenomenology' refers back to Kantian terminology, where the <hi rend="italic">phenomenon</hi> is taken as reality-appearing-to-consciousness, as opposed to the <hi rend="italic">noumenon</hi>, or the realm of being of reality-as-it-is-in-itself. </s><s n="s2.4;p6.35">Generally, then, phenomenology refers to an investigation into the data given in consciousness, to be distinguished from speculative or non-immanent philosophizing. </s><s n="s3.4;p6.35">It purports to be a method of <hi rend="italic">describing</hi>, rather than <hi rend="italic">explaining</hi> or <hi rend="italic">positing,</hi> the contents of consciousness; the contents being given as a result of consciousness' intentionality. </s><s n="s4.4;p6.35">The phenomena themselves are constituted by the directedness-towards that <hi rend="italic">is</hi> the activity of consciousness. </s></p><p n="p7.35"><s n="s1.8;p7.35">Now, this perhaps would not be a significant enterprise if we were to take over the Kantian skeptical attitude. </s><s n="s2.8;p7.35">By this I mean the prejudice that the true being of anything, how it is in itself, is necessarily to be found only outside of consciousness. </s><s n="s3.8;p7.35">Clearly, taking on this belief would exclude phenomenology from succeeding in describing the real essence of any one of its objects of investigation. </s><s n="s4.8;p7.35">However, phenomenology as a whole takes its beginning in the conviction that, contrary to Kant, the essences of things <hi rend="italic">are</hi> to be found in reality as it appears to consciousness. </s><s n="s5.8;p7.35">"He agrees with [Kant] in asserting that only phenomena are <hi rend="italic">given</hi>, but he will claim that <hi rend="italic">in</hi> them is given the very <hi rend="italic">essence</hi> of that which is".<ref target="BAWE_0259c-ftnote.006"/> If, then, the very essence of a thing is contained in the experience of that thing, we need only find a way of exploiting the immanence of experience in order to describe with absolute certainty the <hi rend="italic">way being must be</hi>. </s><s n="s6.8;p7.35">It is for this task that a phenomenological method is required. </s><s n="s7.8;p7.35">And it is to the task of elucidating Husserl's method that we now turn. </s><s n="s8.8;p7.35">As Merleau-Ponty assures us, "[p]henomenology is accessible only through a phenomenological method".<ref target="BAWE_0259c-ftnote.007"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0259c-ftnote.006"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Lauer, Quentin. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1"><hi rend="underlined">Phenomenology: Its Genesis and Prospect,</hi> Harper Torchbooks, 1958. p. 3-4. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0259c-ftnote.007"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.4;pn1.1">Merleau-Ponty, Maurice. </s><s n="s2.4;pn1.1">"What is Phenomenology" in <hi rend="underlined">Phenomenology: The Philosophy of Edmund Husserl and Its Interpretation</hi>. </s><s n="s3.4;pn1.1">Joseph J. Kockelmans (ed.) </s><s n="s4.4;pn1.1">Anchor, 1967, p. 358. </s></p></note></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined">The Phenomenological Reduction</head><p n="p8.35"><s n="s1.2;p8.35">Husserl asks us to begin, as phenomenology should, with the immediate experience that consciousness makes. </s><s n="s2.2;p8.35">In the first: </s></p><quote lang="English">I am aware of a world, spread out in space endlessly, and in time becoming and become, without end. I am aware of it, that means, first of all, I discover it immediately, intuitively, I experience it. Through sight, touch, hearing, etc., in the different ways of sensory perception, corporeal things somehow spatially distributed are <hi rend="italic">for me simply there</hi>, in verbal or figurative sense "present," whether or not I pay them special attention by busying myself with them, considering, thinking, feeling, willing. <ref target="BAWE_0259c-ftnote.008"/></quote><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0259c-ftnote.008"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1"><hi rend="italic">Ideas 1,</hi> p. 51. </s></p></note><p n="p9.35"><s n="s1.5;p9.35">It is this awareness that Husserl terms the <hi rend="italic">natural standpoint or natural attitude</hi>; named as such because it is the stance towards our world that we naturally take. </s><s n="s2.5;p9.35">In it, the world as spatial, temporal, and most of all <hi rend="italic">immediate</hi> entity is always already in front of us, and we accept this experience uncritically. </s><s n="s3.5;p9.35">As long as we are in the natural standpoint, the world is simply and constantly there for me; and we understand ourselves <hi rend="italic">as the ones experiencing it.</hi> </s><s n="s4.5;p9.35">It can be called 'naïve' insofar as the question of the existence of this world, i.e. whether or not it really exists, or really exists in the way that it exists for me, is simply not an issue. </s><s n="s5.5;p9.35">Through all practical matters, whether mundane acts of sensation, or complex physical experiments, the <hi rend="italic">fact</hi> of the world's there-ness is perpetually and tacitly accepted. </s></p><p n="p10.35"><s n="s1.3;p10.35">Now, it is Husserl's claim that the essence of things can be found in the phenomena: in how the world appears to consciousness.<ref target="BAWE_0259c-ftnote.009"/> And since the essence of something is the way that something is, irrespective of any element of contingency, knowledge of the essence of something is knowledge with objective validity. </s><s n="s2.3;p10.35">This is the only kind of knowledge with which Husserl takes an interest. </s><s n="s3.3;p10.35">"In order, then, that there be an "essential" knowledge of things, it becomes necessary both that consciousness be viewed minus the contingent functions which accompany it and that the essences of things be disengaged from all that which is simply accidental to them".<ref target="BAWE_0259c-ftnote.010"/> It is contingency that Husserl sees present in the natural standpoint, and so in order for his phenomenological method to be successful, it is from this natural standpoint that we must become "disengaged". </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0259c-ftnote.009"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1"><hi rend="italic">Ideas 1,</hi> p. 63. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0259c-ftnote.010"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Lauer, Quentin. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1"><hi rend="italic">Phenomenology: Its Genesis and Prospect,</hi> Harper Torchbooks, 1958, p. 48. </s></p></note><p n="p11.35"><s n="s1.5;p11.35">He asks that we begin by altering our attitude in a radical way. </s><s n="s2.5;p11.35">We do not deny what the natural standpoint posits; we do not replace a positive judgment about the world's existing with a negative one. </s><s n="s3.5;p11.35">It is very important, he insists, that we do not seek to alter our convictions in such a way. </s><s n="s4.5;p11.35">Rather, without changing the nature of the standpoint itself, "<hi rend="italic">we, so to speak, "put it out of action" we "exclude it," we "parenthesize it""</hi> .<ref target="BAWE_0259c-ftnote.011"/> This Husserl calls the phenomenological <hi rend="italic">epoche</hi>, a Greek word meaning a reservation of judgment about a particular issue. </s><s n="s5.5;p11.35">Our beliefs about the world are put to one side and must cease to play any influence in our thought. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0259c-ftnote.011"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1"><hi rend="italic">Ideas 1,</hi> p. 59. </s></p></note><p n="p12.35"><s n="s1.4;p12.35">A crucial clarification must be emphasized: the <hi rend="italic">epoche</hi> is not an eliminating of factual existence or any kind of doubt about the world's existence as such. </s><s n="s2.4;p12.35">What is eliminated, however, is any kind of <hi rend="italic">position</hi> regarding factual existence. </s><s n="s3.4;p12.35">Husserl wants us to set to one side the convictions of the natural standpoint because they are simply assumed: which means they are not necessarily warranted. </s><s n="s4.4;p12.35">To replace a positive belief in existence with a negative one would be to change one's belief, indeed, but it would not change the fact that it too is an assumption. </s></p><p n="p13.35"><s n="s1.4;p13.35">Along with the need to stand boldly aloof from our convictions about the existence of the world, we also make no use of any other theoretical presuppositions concerning it. </s><s n="s2.4;p13.35">This means that the theoretical entities of the natural sciences (this term is used as loosely as possible) are excluded from phenomenological description. </s><s n="s3.4;p13.35">All those pursuits driven towards the explaining of the real, or as Husserl often calls it, the transcendent world, are left out. </s><s n="s4.4;p13.35">These 'transcendencies,' such as logic, math, culture and religion, become no longer available to the phenomenologist. <ref target="BAWE_0259c-ftnote.012"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0259c-ftnote.012"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1"><hi rend="italic">Ideas 1,</hi> p. 131. </s></p></note><p n="p14.35"><s n="s1.5;p14.35">The result of this <hi rend="italic">epoche</hi>, once enacted, is that the world becomes present to us as <hi rend="italic">pure phenomenon</hi>. </s><s n="s2.5;p14.35">It appears to us in an entirely different way, as we look on it with 'new eyes'. </s><s n="s3.5;p14.35">Instead of its appearing simply being the background to our practical pursuits, we now attend to <hi rend="italic">the very fact of its appearing.</hi> </s><s n="s4.5;p14.35">It presents itself vividly as something of which we have a re-awakened basic experience; it is something that persists, insists, and claims to be; however, we now refrain from passing judgment on the truth of any claims of this sort. </s><s n="s5.5;p14.35">As Husserl says, we abstract from our presumptions, and </s></p><quote lang="English">instead of living <hi rend="italic">in</hi> them, instead of effecting <hi rend="italic">them</hi>, we effect acts of <hi rend="italic">reflection</hi> directed to them; and we seize upon them themselves as the <hi rend="italic">absolute</hi> being which they are. <ref target="BAWE_0259c-ftnote.013"/></quote><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0259c-ftnote.013"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1"><hi rend="italic">Ideas 1,</hi> p. 114. </s></p></note><p n="p15.35"><s n="s1.5;p15.35">It is from this point that the reductions begin. </s><s n="s2.5;p15.35">The exact number and distinctness of each of the reductions is a point of considerable ambiguity in Husserl's texts. </s><s n="s3.5;p15.35">In no one place is the whole process mapped out in full completeness, and even where sections are explained, clarity remains an issue. </s><s n="s4.5;p15.35">I propose to divide the full reduction into three main steps: the psychological, the eidetic, and the transcendental. </s><s n="s5.5;p15.35">It is hoped that these divisions will serve well enough to relate the important results of the reduction as a whole, and that this aim will redeem the passing over of certain more complicated details. </s></p><quote lang="English">"In no sense of the word is the <hi rend="italic">reduction</hi> to be looked on as a <hi rend="italic">deduction</hi>; rather, in the constant application of the <hi rend="italic">epoche</hi>, it is the gradual penetration into the purified essential residue, gradually revealing the pure subjectivity as the exclusive source of all objectivity". <ref target="BAWE_0259c-ftnote.014"/></quote><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0259c-ftnote.014"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Lauer, Quentin. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1"><hi rend="italic">Phenomenology: Its Genesis and Prospect,</hi> Harper Torchbooks, 1958, p. 50. </s></p></note><p n="p16.35"><s n="s1.7;p16.35">The first step in this gradual movement concerns the purification of the psychological sphere. </s><s n="s2.7;p16.35">As was remarked above, the enactment of the epoche allows the world and its objects to appear to consciousness in their pure phenomenality; we undertake an investigation into <hi rend="italic">what things are</hi> without taking any position <hi rend="italic">that things are</hi>. </s><s n="s3.7;p16.35">The psychological reduction, as each reduction does, leads us back to a realm of more pure being, towards objective truth. </s><s n="s4.7;p16.35">At this particular step, our attention is lead back to the subject in its very attending. </s><s n="s5.7;p16.35">We disengage ourselves from the actual object of our attention and <hi rend="italic">look at the subject's looking at the world</hi>. </s><s n="s6.7;p16.35">This is considered to be a purification because we are led away from the world and towards the activity of consciousness; it is a move away from the multiplicity and <hi rend="italic">contingency</hi> of the transcendent world. </s><s n="s7.7;p16.35">It is Husserl's belief that the truth of things is not to be found in the transcendent world at all, but can only be found in consciousness.<ref target="BAWE_0259c-ftnote.015"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0259c-ftnote.015"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">It could be argued that in <hi rend="italic">Being and Time</hi>, Heidegger's investigations take place at this level. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">Whereas Husserl extracts the subject from its involvement in the transcendent world, Heidegger sees the ultimate field of inquiry as Dasein <hi rend="italic">in its very preoccupation with the world</hi>. </s></p></note><p n="p17.35"><s n="s1.5;p17.35">The next level of reduction is called the eidetic. </s><s n="s2.5;p17.35">The term comes from the Greek word <hi rend="italic">eidos</hi>, often translated as the act of seeing, or the appearance of something. </s><s n="s3.5;p17.35">Here our attention is turned from a subject's looking at the world to the <hi rend="italic">very way of appearing done by the world</hi>. </s><s n="s4.5;p17.35">Again, we are not concerned with <hi rend="italic">what</hi> exists, only with <hi rend="italic">how</hi> it exists to the consciousness whose intending it is: "it looks at consciousness precisely insofar as its essence is to be consciousness-of something".<ref target="BAWE_0259c-ftnote.016"/> It is through this attention to the mode of appearing that an object does that allows us to make use of the phenomenological technique of ideation. </s><s n="s5.5;p17.35">If the essence of something is what it is as unchanging or universal, and the essence of things are available to us through the phenomena, then in order to uncover the essence of a thing, we need to find out what is unchanging in the way it appears to consciousness. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0259c-ftnote.016"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Lauer, Quentin. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1"><hi rend="italic">Phenomenology: Its Genesis and Prospect,</hi> Harper Torchbooks, 1958, p. 52. </s></p></note><p n="p18.35"><s n="s1.11;p18.35">The technique of ideation is a process which employs the imagination in order to subject the appearing of any one thing to a play of free variation.<ref target="BAWE_0259c-ftnote.017"/> We imagine all the ways in which this thing could appear differently <hi rend="italic">while still remaining what it was to begin with</hi>. </s><s n="s2.11;p18.35">For example, a book sits next to me on my desk. </s><s n="s3.11;p18.35">I experience it with particular aspectual characteristics which are unique to this experience: I see it as a book with a cover, as blue, with binding. </s><s n="s4.11;p18.35">The book would not be experienced the same way if its orientation with respect to me and my desk were altered. </s><s n="s5.11;p18.35">I submit the book to ideation, and therefore ask, in what way can this book be changed while still remaining a book? </s><s n="s6.11;p18.35">With both thorough reflection and imagination, we gradually discover what the essence of not this book, but <hi rend="italic">book</hi>, <hi rend="italic">as such</hi>, must be. </s><s n="s7.11;p18.35">Questions such as the following could be asked: Can it have no pages? </s><s n="s8.11;p18.35">Could it simply be papers in a binder? </s><s n="s9.11;p18.35">Must it be of a certain length? </s><s n="s10.11;p18.35">Could it be a pamphlet? </s><s n="s11.11;p18.35">Could it be a manuscript? </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0259c-ftnote.017"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1"><hi rend="italic">Cart.,</hi> p. 57-9. </s></p></note><p n="p19.35"><s n="s1.4;p19.35">What emerges as the invariants in these exercises in ideation is the essence of whatever is under investigation, and it emerges as such through an act of intuition or 'seeing'. </s><s n="s2.4;p19.35">After a number of variations, which will depend entirely on the object in question, the essence is simply grasped immediately as the identical element. </s><s n="s3.4;p19.35">This is not to be understood, as Quentin Lauer puts it, as "an irrational leap beyond the data of experience. </s><s n="s4.4;p19.35">Rather it is intended as a rational penetration <hi rend="italic">into</hi> the data of experience".<ref target="BAWE_0259c-ftnote.018"/> Just where this essence is constituted however, remains to be seen, in the next reduction. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0259c-ftnote.018"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Lauer, Quentin. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1"><hi rend="italic">Phenomenology: Its Genesis and Prospect,</hi> Harper Torchbooks, 1958, p. 62. </s></p></note><p n="p20.35"><s n="s1.6;p20.35">It is by the transcendental reduction that we come to understand the <hi rend="italic">source</hi> of the object's meaning. </s><s n="s2.6;p20.35">Having said this, it is not to be taken as discovering <hi rend="italic">only</hi> the source of the meaning of the object while the object <hi rend="italic">itself</hi> has some other source. </s><s n="s3.6;p20.35">For Husserl, an object <hi rend="italic">is</hi> truly object-as-meaning. </s><s n="s4.6;p20.35">It is not transcendent object, but rather object-for-consciousness, object-as-phenomena, which both amount to the same thing. </s><s n="s5.6;p20.35">It is because Husserl's understanding of object is none other than object-as-meaning that we can come to see, in the transcendental reduction, that the source of all meaning is the constitutive activities of consciousness' <hi rend="italic">intentionality</hi>. </s><s n="s6.6;p20.35">This transcendental ego, in its essential mode of <hi rend="italic">relatedness</hi>, constitutes the very meaning unities that appear in phenomena as intentional objects. <ref target="BAWE_0259c-ftnote.019"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0259c-ftnote.019"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.3;pn1.1">Husserl, Edmund. </s><s n="s2.3;pn1.1"><hi rend="italic">The Crisis of European Sciences and Transcendental Phenomenology,</hi> David Carr (tr.), Northwestern University Press, 1970, p. 151-2. </s><s n="s3.3;pn1.1">This work will be referred to as <hi rend="italic">Crisis.</hi> </s></p></note><p n="p21.35"><s n="s1.5;p21.35">We must take notice of an important distinction: transcendental subjectivity constitutes its objects; it does <hi rend="italic">not create them</hi>. </s><s n="s2.5;p21.35">Husserl does not espouse a kind of total idealism where the reality of transcendent objects springs from the very activity of consciousness. </s><s n="s3.5;p21.35">For him, the transcendent world of objects is there, the world does exist; however, the only world available to consciousness, and thereby for phenomenological, <hi rend="italic">objective</hi> cognition, is the world-as-meaning. </s><s n="s4.5;p21.35">This 'seeing' that the phenomenological reduction facilitates is objective precisely because what is 'seen' is <hi rend="italic">essential</hi>, and therefore necessary. </s><s n="s5.5;p21.35">For Husserl, to be essential and to be objective is the same: being that endures as identical despite plurality, perspective, or contingency. <ref target="BAWE_0259c-ftnote.020"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0259c-ftnote.020"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.3;pn1.1">Thus, through his position, Husserl avoids having to supply a criterion by which one can decide between the conflicting descriptions of different phenomenologists. </s><s n="s2.3;pn1.1">There simply can be no disagreement. </s><s n="s3.3;pn1.1">If one understands and executes the method of the reduction properly, one can be sure that one sees the essence of what is as it is constituted by the transcendental ego, and one can be sure that if anyone disagrees, they are wrong. </s></p></note><p n="p22.35"><s n="s1.2;p22.35">Although Husserl never makes it explicit that the above methodological ideas occur in a chronological sequence proper, we are to take each as a necessary contribution to the phenomenological method as a whole. </s><s n="s2.2;p22.35">It is only when precisely these techniques are combined that the knowledge Husserl seeks can be accessed: </s></p><quote lang="English">"Epoche, reductions, ideation, and essential intuition are[...] four interdependent factors in an over-all process known as 'intentional constitution,' which at one and the same time renders knowledge completely immanent and hence capable of complete verification, and completely necessary for subjectivity as such, which gains it its universal objective validity".<ref target="BAWE_0259c-ftnote.021"/></quote><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0259c-ftnote.021"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Lauer, Quentin. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1"><hi rend="italic">Phenomenology: Its Genesis and Prospect,</hi> Harper Torchbooks, 1958, p. 62. </s></p></note></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined">Ingarden's Charge of Metaphysical Idealism</head><p n="p23.35"><s n="s1.4;p23.35">Having remarked above that Husserl does not support a position that sees objects as springing directly from the activities of consciousness, it may be wondered in what way then it is justified to attribute to him the position of metaphysical idealism. </s><s n="s2.4;p23.35">Yet this is precisely the position taken up by Roman Ingarden in his work <hi rend="italic">On the Motives which led Husserl to Transcendental Idealism</hi>. </s><s n="s3.4;p23.35">Once his criticism has been developed, as it will be in the following, it will become clear that Ingarden is indeed justified in making this claim, and that Husserl is in fact committed to some form of idealism, and that this is inextricably tied to his making a <hi rend="italic">metaphysical</hi> claim. </s><s n="s4.4;p23.35">For our purposes here, we will restrict ourselves to looking at how Husserl's conception of <hi rend="italic">the reduction</hi> itself leads inevitably to an idealist conclusion. </s></p><p n="p24.35"><s n="s1.3;p24.35">Throughout his whole life, Husserl consistently denied that his phenomenology committed him to an idealist metaphysics. </s><s n="s2.3;p24.35">Although Ingarden argues that precisely this implication cannot be avoided, we would do well to note that Husserl did make it clear that he in no way supports idealism as it understood historically. </s><s n="s3.3;p24.35">The following two passages from Ideas 1 are illuminating on this point: </s></p><quote lang="English">Precisely in that the essentially necessary diversity among modes of being, the most cardinal of them all, becomes manifest: the diversity between <hi rend="italic">consciousness and reality</hi>. <ref target="BAWE_0259c-ftnote.022"/></quote><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0259c-ftnote.022"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1"><hi rend="italic">Ideas 1,</hi> p. 90. </s></p></note><quote lang="English">If anyone reading our statements objects that they mean changing all the world into a subjective illusion and committing oneself to a "Berkeleyan idealism," we can only answer that he has not seized upon the <hi rend="italic">sense</hi> of those statements. They take nothing away from the fully valid being of the world as the all of realities, just as nothing is taken away from the fully valid geometrical being of the square by denying that the square is round (a denial admittedly based, in this case, on what is immediately obvious). The real actuality is not "reinterpreted," to say nothing of its being denied; it is rather that a countersensical interpretation of the real actuality, i.e., an interpretation which contradicts the latter's <hi rend="italic">own</hi> sense as clarified by insight, is removed. <ref target="BAWE_0259c-ftnote.023"/></quote><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0259c-ftnote.023"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1"><hi rend="italic">Ideas 1,</hi> p. 129. </s></p></note><p n="p25.35"><s n="s1.3;p25.35">And indeed Ingarden does not propose that Husserl is claiming that the transcendent world of things is purely a construction of consciousness. </s><s n="s2.3;p25.35">As it has been emphasized in the previous, that at the very beginning of the phenomenological reduction Husserl expressly forbids himself from making any judgments about the fact of the existence of the transcendent world, it would certainly amount to no criticism at all if we were to suggest that he is in fact denying the existence of reality in this way. </s><s n="s3.3;p25.35">But there is a further subtlety to this distinction between realism and idealism that Ingarden points out: </s></p><quote lang="English">The controversy between realists and idealists concerning the existence of the real world is not about the question whether the real world, the material world in particular, exists in general (even Berkeley would protest energetically if somebody told him that he affirmed the non-existence of the material world), but about the mode of the world's existence and what its existential relation is to acts of consciousness in which objects belonging to this world are cognized. <ref target="BAWE_0259c-ftnote.024"/></quote><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0259c-ftnote.024"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1"><hi rend="italic">Motives,</hi> p. 31. </s></p></note><p n="p26.35"><s n="s1.1;p26.35">It is just to this point that we must pay close attention: in order to justifiably attribute any sort of idealism to Husserl, the evidence is to be found in the <hi rend="italic"> way</hi> in which the 'material' world, for him, exists. </s></p><p n="p27.35"><s n="s1.4;p27.35">The question of the reduction is precisely the question of the demonstration of indubitable knowledge about the sense of the real world. </s><s n="s2.4;p27.35">Through the initial epoche, our presuppositions about the world are set aside, in order that we can proceed, through the steps of the reduction, to an increasingly pure encounter with and therefore knowledge of the world as it appears to consciousness. </s><s n="s3.4;p27.35">The absolute being discovered in the transcendental ego, responsible for the constitution of all meaning, is to be contrasted with the realm of the transcendent - i.e. the world of things, taken by Husserl to be ultimately relative and contingent. </s><s n="s4.4;p27.35">Along with his understanding of the essential being of objects as being exclusively in the realm of consciousness, Husserl goes so far even to say that anything, insofar as it does not exist for-consciousness, is nothing: </s></p><quote lang="English">On the other hand, the whole <hi rend="italic">spatio-temporal world</hi>, which includes human being and the human Ego as subordinate realities is, <hi rend="italic">according to its sense, a merely intentional being,</hi> thus one has the merely secondary sense of a being <hi rend="italic">for</hi> a consciousness. It is a being posited by consciousness in its experiences which, of essential necessity, can be determined and intuited only as something identical belonging to motivated multiplicities of appearances: <hi rend="italic">beyond that</hi> it is nothing.<ref target="BAWE_0259c-ftnote.025"/> [author's emphasis] </quote><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0259c-ftnote.025"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1"><hi rend="italic">Ideas 1,</hi> p. 112. </s></p></note><p n="p28.35"><s n="s1.5;p28.35">What Husserl here denies is the existence of an 'in-itself' outside of the way phenomena appear to consciousness. </s><s n="s2.5;p28.35">Because Kant recognized this realm as existing, and containing in it the real being of things, he was forced to the skeptical conclusion that a complete knowledge of something as it is 'in itself' will always be impossible. </s><s n="s3.5;p28.35">For Berkeley, the problem of somehow bridging a gap between knowledge-for-consciousness and knowledge-in-itself is simply not an issue: consciousness and world are essentially identical. </s><s n="s4.5;p28.35">In something of a peculiar combination of the two, Husserl holds that the objects <hi rend="italic">are out there</hi>, but they are not <hi rend="italic">in themselves outside of consciousness</hi>. </s><s n="s5.5;p28.35">Object-for-consciousness and object-in-itself are not opposing terms: they are the exact same thing. "[O]ne must not let oneself be deceived by speaking of the physical thing as transcending consciousness or as "existing in itself".<ref target="BAWE_0259c-ftnote.026"/> The objects of the transcendent world are not denied existence; rather, they are denied <hi rend="italic">autonomy</hi>. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0259c-ftnote.026"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1"><hi rend="italic">Ideas 1,</hi> p. 106. </s></p></note><p n="p29.35"><s n="s1.6;p29.35">Indeed, the reduction as conceived by Husserl requires such a position regarding the 'in itself'. </s><s n="s2.6;p29.35">It proceeds successfully on the presumption that the <hi rend="italic">world as knowable</hi> is precisely and exclusively the world of consciousness. </s><s n="s3.6;p29.35">The phenomenologist begins at the transcendent world, and the phenomena that they become as presented to consciousness, but the penetration towards true cognition ends at the realm of the ideal: in absolute constituting subjectivity. </s><s n="s4.6;p29.35">Despite the fact that Husserl insisted that the reduction does <hi rend="italic">not</hi> lead us away from the concrete manifestations of the world in any way, it is to be wondered whether this is not the issue exactly. </s><s n="s5.6;p29.35">Instead of taking up the world of objects, the reduction involves only objects <hi rend="italic">as experienceable</hi>, objectivities-as-meaning. </s><s n="s6.6;p29.35">As Ingarden points out, this means Husserl is </s></p><quote lang="English">treating the sense of the object constituted in the cognitive process exclusively as the creation of the acts coming into consideration. Consequently, he treats the analyzed objects from the beginning exclusively as <hi rend="italic">intentional correlates of these acts</hi> and these objects have <hi rend="italic">only</hi> in these acts the source and basis of their existence and such and no other formation of their contents. <ref target="BAWE_0259c-ftnote.027"/></quote><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0259c-ftnote.027"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1"><hi rend="italic">Motives,</hi> p. 37. </s></p></note><p n="p30.35"><s n="s1.1;p30.35">It is in order to escape the prejudice of dogmatic assumptions that we make no appeal to the transcendent world in our investigations, but as long as the definitive result of the reduction is transcendental subjectivity, the only world relevant for Husserl's objective cognition is <hi rend="italic">the world of consciousness</hi>. </s></p><p n="p31.35"><s n="s1.5;p31.35">Now it could be objected at this point that Ingarden's criticisms are based on an unwarranted conflation of two realms that Husserl keeps distinct: the realm of <hi rend="italic">knowing</hi> and the realm of <hi rend="italic">being</hi>. </s><s n="s2.5;p31.35">Another way of saying this would be that Ingarden is confusing epistemological idealism with metaphysical idealism. </s><s n="s3.5;p31.35">Husserl is not making metaphysical claims, the objection would read, because the reduction only leads to conclusions about <hi rend="italic">the world that we can know</hi>. </s><s n="s4.5;p31.35">There is no denial of the <hi rend="italic">being</hi> of the 'real', external world. </s><s n="s5.5;p31.35">Thus, the reduction's implications are solely epistemological: all he is saying is that the only world of which we can have indubitable knowledge is the one constituted by consciousness. </s></p><p n="p32.35"><s n="s1.12;p32.35">The problem with such an objection is that it makes use of an overly simplistic characterization of idealism. </s><s n="s2.12;p32.35">For such a criticism to stand, making a metaphysically idealistic claim <hi rend="italic">must</hi> amount to a denial of the actual being of the world outside of consciousness. </s><s n="s3.12;p32.35">However, one <hi rend="italic">can</hi> assert the general existence of the world and still be a metaphysical idealist. </s><s n="s4.12;p32.35">In order to avoid a skeptical conclusion of the Kantian variety, Husserl cannot accept that the 'in itself' is outside the bounds of consciousness. </s><s n="s5.12;p32.35">Instead, the 'in itself' is literally divorced from the world. </s><s n="s6.12;p32.35">The physical world is ultimately unknowable, but not in the same way that it is for Kant. </s><s n="s7.12;p32.35">For Husserl, it need not concern us that we cannot go outside consciousness, for what is to be known outside of consciousness is <hi rend="italic">not</hi> the object as it is 'in itself'. </s><s n="s8.12;p32.35">And despite the epistemological aim of such a move, there is no way Husserl can maintain it and metaphysical realism or neutrality at the same time. </s><s n="s9.12;p32.35">To say that there is no <hi rend="italic">autonomous</hi> world 'in itself' outside the realm of consciousness is to deny a moment of existence, and this is more than an epistemological claim - it is a <hi rend="italic">metaphysical</hi> one. </s><s n="s10.12;p32.35">It is a claim regarding not only <hi rend="italic">knowability</hi>, but also the <hi rend="italic">being</hi> of both the transcendent world and the knowable world. </s><s n="s11.12;p32.35">The evidence is in Husserl's own clear statements. </s><s n="s12.12;p32.35">The transcendent world exists, but it exists in such a way that it essentially lacks independence: </s></p><quote lang="English">Reality is not in itself something absolute which becomes tied secondarily to something else; rather, in the absolute sense, it is nothing at all; it has no "absolute essence" whatever; it has the essentiality of something which, of necessity, is <hi rend="italic">only</hi> intentional, <hi rend="italic">only</hi> an object of consciousness, something presented [<hi rend="italic">Vorstelliges</hi>] in the manner peculiar to consciousness, something apparent &lt;as apparent>. <ref target="BAWE_0259c-ftnote.028"/></quote><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0259c-ftnote.028"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1"><hi rend="italic">Ideas 1,</hi> p. 113. </s></p></note><p n="p33.35"><s n="s1.2;p33.35">It is in <hi rend="italic">this</hi> sense, then, and not in the Berkeleyan sense, that Ingarden interprets Husserl as a metaphysical idealist. </s><s n="s2.2;p33.35">And although it is different from idealism typically understood, it <hi rend="italic">is</hi> undeniably an idealist stance: 'being' is made dependent upon 'being experienced'. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined">Conclusion</head><p n="p34.35"><s n="s1.5;p34.35">It should now be clear that Husserl's denial of metaphysical idealism is contradicted by significant evidence in his own works to the extent that we can call seriously into question the justification for such a denial. </s><s n="s2.5;p34.35">By his conviction that rigorous philosophy must take as its objects of investigation only the experiences of consciousness, Husserl established the phenomenological reduction as the way in which we can immanently describe the contents of those experiences, thereby producing knowledge which is absolutely certain. </s><s n="s3.5;p34.35">However, because Husserl's reduction functions to abstract from the objects of the transcendent world to the meaning-contents of intentional acts, and because such meaning is determined to be constituted <hi rend="italic">solely</hi> through transcendental subjectivity, Ingarden is convinced that there is no way Husserl can avoid committing himself to the claim that the 'in itself' is to be found <hi rend="italic">solely</hi> in the realm of consciousness. </s><s n="s4.5;p34.35">By directly restricting the being of the 'in itself' to the being of the ideal realm, and by making the transcendent world a mere intentional correlate of consciousness, that commitment in turn forces undeniably metaphysical implications. </s><s n="s5.5;p34.35">As Mitscherling summarizes: </s></p><quote lang="English">Ingarden clearly regarded the central problem involved in Husserl's concept of constitution as arising from the [...] implicitly metaphysical assumptions lying in the phenomenological reduction's denial of an autonomous 'in-itself' existence to the physical world.<ref target="BAWE_0259c-ftnote.029"/></quote><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0259c-ftnote.029"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Mitscherling, Jeff. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1"><hi rend="italic">Roman Ingarden's Ontology and Aesthetics,</hi> Ottawa University Press, 1997, p. 73-4. </s></p></note><p n="p35.35"><s n="s1.1;p35.35">Despite Husserl's maintaining otherwise, Ingarden persuasively demonstrates that the phenomenological reduction, as Husserl conceived it, "forbids the return to the objects appearing through the analyzed phenomena",<ref target="BAWE_0259c-ftnote.030"/> the objects of the transcendent world being replaced entirely by their meaning-structure, affirmed as real 'in themselves' only insofar as they are experienced by consciousness. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0259c-ftnote.030"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1"><hi rend="italic">Motives,</hi> p. 37. </s></p></note></div1></body><back><div1 type="bibliography"><head rend="underlined bold">Bibliography</head><p>Husserl, Edmund. <hi rend="italic">Ideas Pertaining to a Pure Phenomenology and to a Phenomenological Philosophy, First Book</hi>, F. Kersten (tr.), Kluwer, 1998.</p><p>Husserl, Edmund. <hi rend="italic">Cartesian Meditations,</hi> Dorion Cairns (tr.), Martinus Nijhoff, The Hague, 1960.</p><p>Husserl, Edmund. <hi rend="italic">The Crisis of European Sciences and Transcendental Phenomenology</hi>, David Carr (tr.), Northwestern University Press, 1970.</p><p>Ingarden, Roman. <hi rend="italic">On the Motives which led Husserl to Transcendental Idealism</hi>, Arnor Hannibalsson (tr.), Martinus Nijhoff, The Hague, 1975.</p><p>Kockelmans, Joseph J. "Husserl's Transcendental Idealism" in <hi rend="italic">Phenomenology: The Philosophy of Edmund Husserl and Its Interpretation</hi>, Joseph J. Kockelmans (ed.), Anchor, 1967.</p><p>Kockelmans, Joseph J. "What is Phenomenology: Some Fundamental Themes of Husserl's Phenomenology" in <hi rend="italic">Phenomenology: The Philosophy of Edmund Husserl and Its Interpretation</hi>, Joseph J. Kockelmans (ed.), Anchor, 1967.</p><p>Lauer, Quentin. <hi rend="italic">Phenomenology: Its Genesis and Prospect</hi>, Harper Torchbooks, 1958.</p><p>Merleau-Ponty, Maurice. "What is Phenomenology?" in <hi rend="italic">Phenomenology: The Philosophy of Edmund Husserl and Its Interpretation</hi>, Joseph J. Kockelmans (ed.), Anchor, 1967. </p><p>Mitscherling, Jeff. <hi rend="italic">Roman Ingarden's Ontology and Aesthetics</hi>, Ottawa University Press, 1997. </p><p>Stroker, Elizabeth. <hi rend="italic">Husserl's Transcendental Phenomenology</hi>, Lee Hardy (tr.), Stanford University Press, 1993.</p></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
