<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_0260d" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Hearing and Hearing Tests, an overview</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note/></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">4</p><p n="date">2004-12</p><p n="module title">Special Study Module</p><p n="module code">unknown</p><p n="genre family">Explanation</p><p n="discipline">Medicine</p><p n="disciplinary group">LS</p><p n="grade">D</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">2017</p><p n="number of s-units">106</p><p n="number of p">45</p><p n="number of tables">1</p><p n="number of figures">3</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">0</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">9</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">19.0</p><p n="average s-units per p">2.4</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">f</p><p n="year of birth">1982</p><p n="first language">English</p><p n="education">UKA</p><p n="course">Medicine</p><p n="student ID">0260</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><docTitle><titlePart rend="underlined">Hearing and Hearing Tests, an overview</titlePart></docTitle></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="section"><p n="p1.45"><s n="s1.3;p1.45">The ear is our organ of hearing; throughout the world there are some "250 million people who have a disabling hearing impairment" (<hi rend="italic">World health organisation,</hi> <seg type="URL" n="www.who.int/"/>). </s><s n="s2.3;p1.45">If the impairment is from birth or a young age it can lead to a retardation of development by causing a delay in language acquisition and impede school progress. </s><s n="s3.3;p1.45">Hearing impairment in adults can lead to vocational and economic difficulties resulting in social isolation and stigmatisation. </s></p><p n="p2.45"><s n="s1.2;p2.45">In the UK there is estimated to be about 9 million deaf and hard of hearing people, this number is rising as the number of people over 60 increases. </s><s n="s2.2;p2.45">Of the 9 million 698,000 adults are estimated to be severely or profoundly deaf, 20,000 children between the ages of 0 and 15 are moderately to profoundly deaf, 12,000 of these children were born deaf. (<hi rend="italic">Statistics from RNID</hi>, <seg type="URL" n="www.rnid.org.uk"/>) </s></p><table id="BAWE_0260d-tab.001"><head>Figure 1- estimated percentage of the UK population who are deaf or hard of hearing. (<hi rend="italic">Facts and figures on deafness and tinnitus,</hi> <seg type="URL" n="www.rnid.org.uk"/>)</head><row><cell/></row></table></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined">Basic anatomy of the ear and physiology of hearing. </head><p n="p3.45"><s n="s1.1;p3.45">The ear is made up of three different parts, the outer, middle and inner ear. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0260d-pic.001"><head><hi rend="italic">Figure 2 -</hi> Diagram of the ear (<seg type="URL" n="www.rnid.org.uk"/>)</head></figure><p n="p4.45"><s n="s1.3;p4.45">The outer or external ear consists of the pinna and external auditory canal. </s><s n="s2.3;p4.45">Sound travels along the passage to the eardrum (tympanic membrane) which is situated at the end. </s><s n="s3.3;p4.45">The canal also contains hairs and glands which produce wax (cerumen), together this is thought to keep the ear clean. </s></p><p n="p5.45"><s n="s1.5;p5.45">The middle ear is a cavity approximately 1.3cm across which is filled with air. </s><s n="s2.5;p5.45">A chain of three tiny bones, the ossicles stretch right across the middle ear cavity. </s><s n="s3.5;p5.45">They are the malleus (hammer bone), incus (anvil bone) and the stapes (stirrup). </s><s n="s4.5;p5.45">"Their function is to transmit mechanical energy from the tympanic membrane across the air filled middle ear to the fluid filled inner ear."(<hi rend="italic">Wilson et al</hi>, 2002) </s><s n="s5.5;p5.45">There is a connection between the middle ear and pharynx via the Eustachian tube which helps to equalise air pressure. </s></p><p n="p6.45"><s n="s1.5;p6.45">The inner ear is made up of two parts, the cochlea and semicircular canals. </s><s n="s2.5;p6.45">Along the length of the cochlea are tiny hair cells, each cell has stereocilia which project into the cochlear fluid. </s><s n="s3.5;p6.45">"When sound waves enter the cochlea the stereocilia are moved which causes the hair cells to trigger an electrical pulse in the auditory nerve" (<hi rend="italic">Burton et al, 2000)</hi>. </s><s n="s4.5;p6.45">The nerve passes impulses to the brain which recognise them as different sounds. </s><s n="s5.5;p6.45">The semicircular canals are not used for hearing; they are part of your balance system. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined">Deafness</head><p n="p7.45"><s n="s1.5;p7.45">There are many ways in which you could classify types of deafness, one way of doing this is to categorise deafness into varying severity. </s><s n="s2.5;p7.45">"Threshold is the level at which you can just make out the tone of a particular frequency. </s><s n="s3.5;p7.45">Thresholds are measured in decibels for hearing level (dBHL). </s><s n="s4.5;p7.45">Normal hearing is thresholds between 0-20 dBHL across all frequencies" (<hi rend="italic">RNID,</hi> <seg type="URL" n="www.rnid.org.uk"/>). </s><s n="s5.5;p7.45">The greater the threshold, the worse the hearing loss. </s></p><p n="p8.45"><s n="s1.1;p8.45">Perhaps a more clinical way of classifying types of deafness is to split deafness up into four categories. </s></p><div2><head>1 <hi rend="bold">. <hi rend="italic">Conductive Deafness</hi></hi></head><p n="p9.45"><s n="s1.3;p9.45">This is caused by the failure of the three ossicles in the middle ear to pass the sound waves to the inner ear. </s><s n="s2.3;p9.45">Another common cause of conductive deafness is the failure of the eardrum to vibrate in response to sound waves. </s><s n="s3.3;p9.45">In many cases treatment is available for conductive deafness and normal hearing will return. </s></p></div2><div2><head>2 <hi rend="bold">.<hi rend="italic"> Sensorineural Deafness</hi></hi></head><p n="p10.45"><s n="s1.3;p10.45">This results from disease or trauma to the cochlear nerve, the rest of the ear machinery may be working but the electrical impulses are unable to reach the brain. </s><s n="s2.3;p10.45">Another cause is damage to the brain itself so that the message form the cochlear nerve cannot be translated. </s><s n="s3.3;p10.45">The vast majority of nerve deafness cases do not respond to treatment. </s></p></div2><div2><head>3.<hi rend="italic"> Temporary deafness</hi></head><p n="p11.45"><s n="s1.1;p11.45">There are many causes of temporary deafness, (<hi rend="italic">better health,</hi> <seg type="URL" n="www.betterhealth.vic.gov.au"/>) </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p12.45"><s n="s1.1;p12.45">i)Cerumen (wax) or a foreign object can block the ear canal causing temporary conductive deafness. </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p13.45"><s n="s1.1;p13.45">ii)Excess Mucous - The common cold or hay fever can cause an excessive production of mucous which may block the Eustachian tubes. </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p14.45"><s n="s1.1;p14.45">iii)Ear infections - Otitis media/externa can cause fluid and pus accumulation which damps down the conduction of sound </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p15.45"><s n="s1.1;p15.45">iv)Drugs - Aminoglycosides and chloroquine can cause temporary deafness in susceptible people. </s></p></div2><div2><head>4.<hi rend="italic"> Age related hearing loss</hi></head><p n="p16.45"><s n="s1.2;p16.45">This is termed presbycusis, our hearing gradually becomes less acute as we age, this is normal and rarely leads to complete deafness. </s><s n="s2.2;p16.45">Higher frequencies are typically loss first. </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined">Ear Examination and Hearing Tests</head><p n="p17.45"><s n="s1.1;p17.45">A thorough examination of a persons hearing requires an ear examination and hearing tests. </s></p><div2><head rend="italic">The ear examination</head><p n="p18.45"><s n="s1.1;p18.45">This involves inserting an otoscope into the ear canal which allows you to view the canal and the tympanic membrane. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="italic">Hearing (Audiometric) tests</head><p n="p19.45"><s n="s1.1;p19.45">These may be carried out for the following reasons: </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p20.45"><s n="s1.1;p20.45">i) To screen newborns and young children for hearing problems. </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p21.45"><s n="s1.1;p21.45">ii) As part of a routine physical examination </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p22.45"><s n="s1.1;p22.45">iii) To evaluate possible hearing loss in anyone who has noticed a persistent hearing problem. </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p23.45"><s n="s1.1;p23.45">iv) To screen for hearing loss in people who are repeatedly exposed to loud noises. </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p24.45"><s n="s1.1;p24.45">v) To determine the amount and type of hearing loss experienced by a person. </s></p><p n="p25.45"><s n="s1.1;p25.45">(<hi rend="italic">web MDhealth</hi>, <seg type="URL" n="www.my.webmd.com"/>) </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined">Types of Hearing test</head><div2><head>1. Whispered Speech Test</head><p n="p26.45"><s n="s1.5;p26.45">According to the systematic review carried out by <hi rend="italic">Pirozzo at al,</hi> 2003, "the whispered voice test is a simple and accurate screening test for detecting hearing impairment which can be carried out in children and adults". </s><s n="s2.5;p26.45">The examiner stands at arms length behind the seated patient and whispers a combination of numbers and letter. </s><s n="s3.5;p26.45">They then ask the patient to repeat the sequence. </s><s n="s4.5;p26.45">The patient is deemed to have passed if the answer three out of the six letter or numbers correctly. </s><s n="s5.5;p26.45">Although this is a quick and easy screen which can be carried out in the community, it is difficult to standardise the test by controlling the loudness of the whisper. </s></p></div2><div2><head>2. Pure tone audiometry</head><p n="p27.45"><s n="s1.8;p27.45">The usual primary purpose of pure-tone tests is to determine the type and degree of hearing loss. (<hi rend="italic">Mullin-Derrick &amp; Campbell, 2004)</hi> define pure tone audiometry as "a behavioural test measure used to determine hearing sensitivity. </s><s n="s2.8;p27.45">Pure tone thresholds (PTT's) indicate the softest sound audible to an individual at least 50% of the time. </s><s n="s3.8;p27.45">Hearing sensitivity is plotted on an audiogram, which is a graph displaying intensity as a function of frequency". </s><s n="s4.8;p27.45">The test is carried out by a pure tone audiometer, which produces a range of pure tones at varying intensity in 5 decibel steps. </s><s n="s5.8;p27.45">The sounds are played through a set of headphones which are placed on the patient. </s><s n="s6.8;p27.45">"The health professional will send a tone and reduce its loudness until you can no longer hear it. </s><s n="s7.8;p27.45">Then the tone will get louder until you can hear it again. </s><s n="s8.8;p27.45">The patient signals by raising their hand or pressing a button every time they hear a tone." (<hi rend="italic">My webMD,</hi> <seg type="URL" n="www.mywebmd.com"/>) </s></p><p n="p28.45"><s n="s1.1;p28.45">The test is suitable for children above the age of three and adults; this is on the condition that they can respond to commands. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0260d-fig.001"><head><hi rend="italic">Figure 3</hi> - An example of an audiogram. This Person has normal hearing.</head></figure><p n="p29.45"><s n="s1.2;p29.45">The white area on the diagram indicates the sounds that the person would not hear; they are termed "softer than threshold sounds". </s><s n="s2.2;p29.45">The grey area demonstrates the sounds that the person would be able to hear i.e. the "louder than threshold sounds". </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0260d-fig.002"><head><hi rend="italic">Figure 4</hi> - A sample audiogram, this person has sensori-neural deafness.</head></figure><p n="p30.45"><s n="s1.1;p30.45">This audiogram shows significant hearing loss over the higher frequencies in sounds up to 60 decibels. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0260d-fig.003"><head><hi rend="italic">Figure 5</hi> - A sample audiogram, this person has conductive deafness.</head></figure><p n="p31.45"><s n="s1.1;p31.45">This audiogram shows hearing loss of sounds of all frequencies below 50 decibels. </s></p><p n="p32.45"><s n="s1.1;p32.45">All audiogram figures taken from (<hi rend="italic">Audiology awareness campaign, <seg type="URL" n="www.audiologyawareness.com"/>)</hi> </s></p></div2><div2><head>3.Tuning fork tests</head><p n="p33.45"><s n="s1.1;p33.45">These are crude tests but are routinely used in clinical examination. </s></p><div3><head rend="underlined">Rinne's test</head><p n="p34.45"><s n="s1.3;p34.45">This compares the patients ability to hear a tone conducted via air and bone. </s><s n="s2.3;p34.45">"A vibrating tuning fork is placed on the mastoid process and then help in line with the external auditory meatus. </s><s n="s3.3;p34.45">The patient is asked whether the sound is louder behind or in front referring to bone and air conduction respectively" (<hi rend="italic">GP notebook,</hi> <seg type="URL" n="www.gpnotebook.co.uk"/>). </s></p><p n="p35.45"><s n="s1.2;p35.45">In the normal ear, air conduction is better than bone and so the tone is heard more clearly at the external meatus. </s><s n="s2.2;p35.45">Conductive hearing loss, the sound is heard better over the mastoid process. </s></p></div3><div3><head rend="underlined">Weber's test</head><p n="p36.45"><s n="s1.3;p36.45">This compares bone conduction in both ears. </s><s n="s2.3;p36.45">"A vibrating tuning fork is placed in the centre of the forehead. </s><s n="s3.3;p36.45">The patient is asked if the sound is heard in the midline or to one side" (<hi rend="italic">GP notebook,</hi> <seg type="URL" n="www.gpnotebook.co.uk"/>). </s></p><p n="p37.45"><s n="s1.3;p37.45">If hearing is normal the patient perceives the sound in the midline. </s><s n="s2.3;p37.45">If there is unilateral conductive loss the patient perceives the sound in the ear with conductive loss. </s><s n="s3.3;p37.45">If there is unilateral sensorineural loss the patient perceives the sound in the ear with the better cochlea. </s></p><p n="p38.45"><s n="s1.2;p38.45">A drawback to the rinne's and weber's test according to <hi rend="italic">Mulrow,</hi> 1991, is that "because the tuning fork test evaluates hearing at a single low frequency, it is not appropriate for most elderly patients. </s><s n="s2.2;p38.45">This is because most of them have presbycusis and have lost the ability to hear high frequencies." </s></p></div3></div2><div2><head>4. Otoacoustic emission</head><p n="p39.45"><s n="s1.6;p39.45">As discussed previously, external sound waves move the basilar membrane in the cochlea. </s><s n="s2.6;p39.45">The cochlea itself then produces sounds and these are termed otoacoustic emissions. </s><s n="s3.6;p39.45">Otoacousitc emissions can then be detected and measured by a microphone in the external ear. </s><s n="s4.6;p39.45"><hi rend="italic">Hinton &amp; Moore Gillon,</hi> 1994 have found that "emissions are more easily recordable in younger subjects than in older people. </s><s n="s5.6;p39.45">This makes the technique particularly valuable in those in whom the more conventional tests of hearing function, which require a subjective response and the cooperation of the patient, difficult. </s><s n="s6.6;p39.45">This test which takes around ten minutes has obvious potential as a screening test in neonates. </s></p></div2><div2><head>5 Auditory brainstem evoked potential</head><p n="p40.45"><s n="s1.4;p40.45">For this test electrodes are placed on the scalp and each earlobe. </s><s n="s2.4;p40.45">Clicking noises are then sent through earphones. </s><s n="s3.4;p40.45">The electrodes monitor the brains response to the clicking noises and record the response on a graph. </s><s n="s4.4;p40.45">This test detects sensorineural hearing loss. </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined">Summary</head><p n="p41.45"><s n="s1.3;p41.45">This essay has identified various tests which can be used to assess hearing. </s><s n="s2.3;p41.45">It is clear that screening neonates and children for hearing defects is important. </s><s n="s3.3;p41.45">The earlier the problems can be identified and managed, the better long term prospects for the child and family who will then receive the specialised support they need. </s></p><p n="p42.45"><s n="s1.3;p42.45">Routine clinical examination has a place, but mainly in the detection of ear infections and cerumen via an otoscope. </s><s n="s2.3;p42.45">The tuning fork tests will give an immediate indication as to whether there is a hearing deficit present; however these tests are crude and can only be applied if the patient can understand and follow a command. </s><s n="s3.3;p42.45">It has been highlighted that they are of little use in elderly patients due to the loss of ability, to hear high frequencies as we age. </s></p><p n="p43.45"><s n="s1.5;p43.45">The whispered speech test has advantages in that it is cheap, quick and can be performed on mass in the community by a range of health professionals. </s><s n="s2.5;p43.45">I.e. health visitors. </s><s n="s3.5;p43.45">This makes it a convenient test for screening purposes. </s><s n="s4.5;p43.45">However its major disadvantage is that again the patient needs to be able to understand a command and respond, which is only possible in children above approximately 3 years old. </s><s n="s5.5;p43.45">Another problem is standardising this test due to the loudness of the whisper. </s></p><p n="p44.45"><s n="s1.3;p44.45">The pure tone audiometry is probably the gold standard test; it is the most accurate at determining the type and extent of hearing loss. </s><s n="s2.3;p44.45">Its disadvantage is that it needs to be carried out in a specialised department by a technician. </s><s n="s3.3;p44.45">This renders it ineffective for community screening. </s></p><p n="p45.45"><s n="s1.2;p45.45">Finally the two tests which can be used in neonates and patients which cannot respond to a command are otoacoustic emission and auditory brainstem evoked response. </s><s n="s2.2;p45.45">The drawback to both these tests is that they require specialised equipment and so it is difficult to take them out into the community. </s></p></div1></body><back><div1 type="bibliography"><head rend="underlined">References</head><p>World Health Organisation</p><p>Authors - unknown</p><p>2004</p><p>Prevention of blindness and deafness</p><p>Retrieved 27/11/04 from</p><p><seg type="URL" n="www.who.int/noncommunicable_diseases/about/pbd/en/"/></p><p>RNID</p><p>Authors - unknown</p><p>January 2003</p><p>Facts and figures on deafness and tinnitus</p><p>Retrieved 27/11/04 from</p><p><seg type="URL" n="www.rnid.org.uk/html/factsheets/general_statistics_on_deafness.htm"/></p><p>Better Heath</p><p>Authors - unknown</p><p>2004</p><p>Deafness a range of causes</p><p>Retrieved 08/10/04 from</p><p><seg type="URL" n="www.betterhealth.vic.gov.au/bhcv2/bharticles.nsf/"/></p><p>Wilson.W.R, Nadol.J.B, Randolph.G.W. 2002. <hi rend="italic">The clinical handbook of ear,nose and throat disorders.</hi> Parthenon Publishing. London.</p><p>Burton. M , Leighton. S, Robson.A, Russel. J. 2000, <hi rend="italic">Hall and Colman's diseases of the ear, nose and throat</hi>. Churchill Livingstone. London.</p><p>Web MDhealth</p><p>Author - Kattie Payne</p><p>May 2003</p><p>Ear examination and hearing tests</p><p>Retrieved 27/11/04 from </p><p><seg type="URL" n="www.my.webmd.com/hw/health_guide_atoz"/></p><p>e-medicine</p><p>Author - Mullin-Derrick.G, Campbell, K.C.M</p><p>October 2004</p><p>Audiology, pure tone testing</p><p>Retrieved 29/11/04 from</p><p><seg type="URL" n="www.e-medicine.com/ent/topic311.htm"/></p><p>Audiology Awareness Campaign</p><p>Author - Meier, G.R</p><p>2004</p><p>How do we read an audiogram</p><p>Retrieved 29/11/04 from</p><p><seg type="URL" n="www.audiologyawareness.com"/></p><p>Pirozzo.S, Papinczak.T, Glasalou.P, <hi rend="italic">Whispered voice test for screening for hearing impairment in adults and children a systematic review.</hi> BMJ:2003, vol. 327 pages 967-971.</p><p>GP notebook</p><p>Author - unknown</p><p>2004</p><p>Rinne's test / Weber's test</p><p>Retrieved 27/11/04 from</p><p><seg type="URL" n="www.gpnotebook.org.uk/simplepage.cfm"/></p><p>Hinton, A, Moore-Gillon, V. <hi rend="italic">Recent advances in otorhinolaryngology</hi>. BMJ:1994, vol 309, pages 651-654.</p><p>Mulrow.C, <hi rend="italic">Screening for hearing impairment in the elderly</hi>. Hospital practise:1991, vol 26, pages 83-86.</p></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
