<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_0260g" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Portfolio Case 3</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">proforma</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">4</p><p n="date">2004-03</p><p n="module title">Introductory Clinical Course</p><p n="module code">unknown</p><p n="genre family">Case study</p><p n="discipline">Medicine</p><p n="disciplinary group">LS</p><p n="grade">M</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">1328</p><p n="number of s-units">84</p><p n="number of p">62</p><p n="number of tables">0</p><p n="number of figures">0</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">1</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">0</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">15.8</p><p n="average s-units per p">1.4</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">f</p><p n="year of birth">1982</p><p n="first language">English</p><p n="education">UKA</p><p n="course">Medicine</p><p n="student ID">0260</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><docTitle><titlePart rend="bold">PORTFOLIO CASE No: </titlePart></docTitle><titlePart>Patient Initials Mrs <name type="other"/> Hospital Number Keep separate list Age 75 Gender Female</titlePart><titlePart>Portfolio Case presentation number: 1 Phase 2 course document objectives(s) Has the patient' permission, including for follow up contact by telephone, been sought and recorded in the case notes?</titlePart></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="bold">Referral information</hi> Source of referral and a summary of key information</head><p n="p1.62"><s n="s1.1;p1.62">Elective Surgical Referral following outpatient visit to cardiology. </s></p><p n="p2.62"><s n="s1.1;p2.62">Admitted on the <name type="date"/> to the <name type="other"/> hospital <name type="other"/>. </s></p><p n="p3.62"><s n="s1.1;p3.62">Came into hospital on the bus. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="bold">History</hi> All <hi rend="bold italic">relevant</hi> information gathered from the patient about the presenting illness, co-existing problems, current treatment, <hi rend="italic">significant</hi> past medical history and the social and family background. The patient's view of the nature of the problem and their expectations for treatment. </head><p n="p4.62"><s rend="italic" n="s1.1;p4.62">The patient was seen post operatively, but was able to give me a history of her condition before she had her operation and treatment. </s></p><div2><head rend="underlined">Presenting Complaint </head><p n="p5.62"><s n="s1.1;p5.62">Shortness of breath and a cough. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">History of Presenting Complaint</head><p n="p6.62"><s n="s1.4;p6.62">Presented to cardiology outpatients in December 2003, with a persistent dry cough and shortness of breath. </s><s n="s2.4;p6.62">An ECHO (echocardiogram) was performed. </s><s n="s3.4;p6.62">It was discovered that the patient had aortic regurgitation, with an early diastolic murmur, radiating to the neck. </s><s n="s4.4;p6.62">The left ventricular systolic function was good and an operation to insert a prosthetic valve was planned. </s></p><div3><head><hi rend="underlined italic">Upon presentation to hospital for operation</hi> .</head><p n="p7.62"><s n="s1.1;p7.62">The shortness of breath and wheeze present for most of the time, waking the patient approximately twice every night. </s></p><p n="p8.62"><s n="s1.2;p8.62">To sleep the patient needed four pillows and was unable to lie flat without getting breathless. </s><s n="s2.2;p8.62">Patient also experienced some night sweats. </s></p><p n="p9.62"><s n="s1.1;p9.62">The patient reported that her ankles were never swollen. </s></p><p n="p10.62"><s n="s1.1;p10.62">Cough was persistent, phlegm was white and frothy mainly brought up at night. </s></p><p n="p11.62"><s n="s1.1;p11.62">Exercise tolerance was 50 yards on the flat. </s></p><p n="p12.62"><s n="s1.1;p12.62">No chest Pain, palpitations, intermittent claudication, cold/blue hands or feet and no syncope. </s></p></div3></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">Past Medical History</head><p n="p13.62"><s n="s1.1;p13.62">Hypertension (unknown when this was diagnosed) </s></p><p n="p14.62"><s n="s1.1;p14.62">Hypothyroidism (Diagnosed and treated since 1991) </s></p><p n="p15.62"><s n="s1.1;p15.62">Appendicectomy (1960) </s></p><p n="p16.62"><s n="s1.1;p16.62">Voice Problems (2002), Received speech therapy for 7 months. </s></p><p n="p17.62"><s n="s1.1;p17.62">No previous Myocardial Infarction, Ischaemic Heart Disease, Cerebrovascular accident, Diabetes, Rheumatic Fever, Pneumonia, Asthma or Tuberculosis, </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">Medication</head><list type="simple"><item>Thyroxine 125mg PO Replacement therapy of thyroid hormone</item><item>Ranitidine 150mg PO Histamine H2 receptor antagonist used to inhibit gastric acid secretion</item><item>Celexane 40mg OD Low molecular weight Heparin taken to prevent formation of blood clots.</item><item>Aspirin 75mg PO NSAID which inhibits platelet aggregation</item><item>Paracetamol 1g PO Non narcotic analgesic antipyretic </item><item>Senna TT Laxative</item><item>Lactulose 15ml Laxative</item></list><p n="p18.62"/></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">Allergies</head><p n="p19.62"><s n="s1.1;p19.62">Penicillin </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">Family History</head><p n="p20.62"><s n="s1.1;p20.62">Mother died when patient was 20 months old from ruptured aortic aneurysm, also had rheumatic fever </s></p><p n="p21.62"><s n="s1.1;p21.62">Mothers Sister died from heart problems and had rheumatic fever. </s></p><p n="p22.62"><s n="s1.1;p22.62">Father died aged 73 from a stroke </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">Social History</head><p n="p23.62"><s n="s1.1;p23.62">Lives alone in a flat, no stairs </s></p><p n="p24.62"><s n="s1.1;p24.62">Smoking - 0 pack years Alcohol - 0 units/week </s></p><p n="p25.62"><s n="s1.1;p25.62">Retired aged 72 previously a nurse. </s></p><p n="p26.62"><s n="s1.2;p26.62">The patient has a good social network and normally manages to do everything for herself. </s><s n="s2.2;p26.62">Recently has had some help with cleaning and shopping due to the shortness of breath. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">Systems Review</head><p n="p27.62"><s n="s1.1;p27.62">RS and CVS, see history of presenting complaint </s></p><p n="p28.62"><s n="s1.2;p28.62">GIT No indigestion, abdominal pain, changes in bowel habit, problems with swallowing, heartburn or nausea and vomiting. </s><s n="s2.2;p28.62">Weight loss of approximately 7lbs since being in hospital and the patient's appetite has been reduced since being admitted. </s></p><p n="p29.62"><s n="s1.1;p29.62">GUT Some stress incontinence when coughing but no other urinary symptoms </s></p><p n="p30.62"><s n="s1.1;p30.62">CNS Occasional migraine, Some dizziness since admission, No faints, fits or blackout. </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="bold">Analysis of history</hi> The most likely single cause of the presentation, other possible causes and reasons for these choices. The findings to be looked for on physical examination to help decide the cause.</head><p n="p31.62"><s n="s1.1;p31.62">The cause for the presenting complaint is already known as the patient is an elective admission and was seen post operatively. </s></p><p n="p32.62"><s n="s1.2;p32.62">The incompetent aortic valve allows regurgitation of blood from the aorta to the left ventricle during diastole. </s><s n="s2.2;p32.62">This produced the early diastolic murmur seen at the cardiology clinic. </s></p><p n="p33.62"><s n="s1.3;p33.62">The patient was experiencing shortness of breath, orthopnoea and paroxysmal nocturnal dyspnoea due to oedema. </s><s n="s2.3;p33.62">Oedema arises because the incompetence of the aortic valve leads to an increased workload for the left ventricle. </s><s n="s3.3;p33.62">In response to this the cardiac cells hypertrophy and the hydrostatic pressure increases in the pulmonary circulation resulting in fluid accumulation in the lungs. </s></p><p n="p34.62"><s n="s1.2;p34.62">As the operation was successful and a soft prosthetic aortic valve fitted upon examination I would expect to find that the patients symptoms had been relieved. </s><s n="s2.2;p34.62">I would not expect to find an early diastolic murmur, visible carotid pulsations or a JVP. I would expect the apex beat of the heart to be slightly displaced due to its increased workload in the time leading up to Mrs <name type="other"/>'s operation. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="bold">Physical examination and mental state examination</hi> Highlight the findings most relevant to your clinical problem solving by underlining them</head><div2><head><hi rend="underlined">General Examination</hi> (carried out post operatively)</head><p n="p35.62"><s n="s1.2;p35.62">The patient was an elderly slightly overweight lady, sitting comfortably in bed. </s><s n="s2.2;p35.62">Mrs <name type="other"/> was alert and feeling quite well. </s></p><p n="p36.62"><s n="s1.1;p36.62">Around the bed was a sputum pot (empty), oxygen mask, no walking aids. </s></p><p n="p37.62"><s n="s1.1;p37.62">Inspection of the hands showed them to be normal temperature and not clammy. </s></p><p n="p38.62"><s n="s1.1;p38.62">Skin showed no signs of dehydration. </s></p><p n="p39.62"><s n="s1.1;p39.62">No Clubbing, peripheral cyanosis were noted. </s></p><p n="p40.62"><s n="s1.1;p40.62">Bruising to both wrists from canula put in for operation. </s></p><p n="p41.62"><s n="s1.1;p41.62">Pulse 68 bpm upon admission it was 60 bpm </s></p><p n="p42.62"><s n="s1.1;p42.62">Blood Pressure Lying down 140/70 standing 113/60 and upon admission it was 170/60 </s></p><p n="p43.62"><s n="s1.1;p43.62">No Xanthelasma seen on the face. </s></p><p n="p44.62"><s n="s1.1;p44.62">No Jaundice seen in sclera of the eye. </s></p><p n="p45.62"><s n="s1.1;p45.62">Conjunctiva a little pale. </s></p><p n="p46.62"><s n="s1.1;p46.62">No central cyanosis </s></p><p n="p47.62"><s n="s1.1;p47.62">Appearance of the tongue was normal </s></p><p n="p48.62"><s n="s1.1;p48.62">No Lymphadenopathy or thyroid enlargement </s></p><p n="p49.62"><s n="s1.1;p49.62">No Pedal Oedema </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">CVS Examination</head><div3><head rend="underlined">Inspection</head><p n="p50.62"><s n="s1.4;p50.62">The patient was quite comfortable, she felt a little tenderness and discomfort in her chest due to the stitch's and scar but had no breathlessness or cough. </s><s n="s2.4;p50.62">Median sternotomy scar present, stitches still in. </s><s n="s3.4;p50.62">No varicose veins in the legs. </s><s n="s4.4;p50.62">Patient was wearing post operative support stockings. </s></p></div3><div3><head rend="underlined">Palpation</head><p n="p51.62"><s n="s1.1;p51.62">Apex Beat was felt in the 5 <hi rend="sup">th</hi> intercostal space but slightly displaced to the left. </s></p><p n="p52.62"><s n="s1.1;p52.62">JVP not raised. </s></p><p n="p53.62"><s n="s1.1;p53.62">All peripheral pulses were present. </s></p></div3><div3><head rend="underlined">Auscultation</head><p n="p54.62"><s n="s1.2;p54.62">1 <hi rend="sup">st</hi> and 2 <hi rend="sup">nd</hi> heart sounds heard in mitral, tricuspid, pulmonic and aortic regions. </s><s n="s2.2;p54.62">A sharp closing sound could be heard in S2 due to the closure of the prosthetic valve. </s></p><p n="p55.62"><s n="s1.1;p55.62">ICE - Would like to go home very soon and resume normal activities. </s></p></div3></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="bold">Analysis of history and examination</hi> Reasons for your choice of the cause of the patient's problem(s) and any other cause that still needs to be considered at this stage</head><p n="p56.62"><s n="s1.4;p56.62">The examination supported the fact that the operation was a success. </s><s n="s2.4;p56.62">The patient's symptoms had been relieved and no early diastolic murmur could be heard. </s><s n="s3.4;p56.62">The apex beat was slightly displaced due to the increased demand on the left ventricle pre intervention. </s><s n="s4.4;p56.62">A significant decrease in Mrs <name type="other"/>'s blood pressure has also been achieved. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="bold">Formulation of the patient's problem(s)</hi> Encapsulate this in physical, psychological and social terms (the triple diagnosis)</head><p n="p57.62"><s n="s1.4;p57.62">Having undergone a successful major surgical operation. </s><s n="s2.4;p57.62">Mrs <name type="other"/> is anxious to continue her post operative recovery at home. </s><s n="s3.4;p57.62">This should be possible provided that she has enough support to do so. </s><s n="s4.4;p57.62">Psychologically Mrs <name type="other"/> is concerned as to whether she will recover completely to her pre morbid state and whether she will be able to cope as before, doing everything for herself. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Management</head><div2><head rend="bold italic">Investigations</head><p n="p58.62"><s n="s1.1;p58.62">Monitor vital signs (such as pulse, blood pressure, electrolytes and temperature) to ensure that she doesn't develop any post operative complications such as a blood clot. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold italic">Reassurance and explanation</head><p n="p59.62"><s n="s1.2;p59.62">Keep the patient informed of when it is realistically likely that they will be able to go home. </s><s n="s2.2;p59.62">Ensure that they are aware of how long it may take them to recover and encourage them not to do too much too quickly. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold italic">Prescription/medical intervention</head><p n="p60.62"><s n="s1.1;p60.62">Review medication and aftercare regularly to ensure the patient is recovering as fast as possible. </s></p><p n="p61.62"><s n="s1.2;p61.62">Ensure that Mrs <name type="other"/> has enough support in the community and that any help she may need with daily tasks is arranged. </s><s n="s2.2;p61.62">Ensure that she is followed up by her GP and via outpatients at the hospital. </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="bold">Impact on your learning</hi> Describe what you have learnt from this case</head><p n="p62.62"><s n="s1.1;p62.62">From this case I have seen for the first time, a heart valve lesion and also that major surgery can be performed successfully on an older patient, significantly improving the quality of their life. </s></p></div1></body><back><div1 type="back text"><head rend="bold">ASPECTS OF CASE AS RECORDED IN SUMMARY OF PORTFOLIO CASES •</head><table id="BAWE_0260g-tab.001"><row><cell/></row></table><p/></div1><div1 type="back text"><head rend="bold">PORTFOLIO COMPLETION CERTIFICATE</head><p rend="bold">Portfolio completion certificated</p><p>I confirm that this student has satisfactorily completed 3 word-processed portfolio cases.</p><p>Signed.....................................................................</p><p> Date......................................................................</p></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
