<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_0263b" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Design of Discrete Digital Controllers</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">The document has a title page which contains:
document title
title part</note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">deleted: footer: student and page numbers, assignment title</note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">apendix: simulation outputs</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">3</p><p n="date">2006-01</p><p n="module title">Control I</p><p n="module code">ES330</p><p n="genre family">Critique</p><p n="discipline">Engineering</p><p n="disciplinary group">PS</p><p n="grade">D</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">2990</p><p n="number of s-units">182</p><p n="number of p">112</p><p n="number of tables">1</p><p n="number of figures">3</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">86</p><p n="number of lists">0</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">36</p><p n="abstract present">abstract present</p><p n="average words per s-unit">16.4</p><p n="average s-units per p">1.6</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">f</p><p n="year of birth">1986</p><p n="first language">English</p><p n="education">UKA</p><p n="course">Engineering</p><p n="student ID">0263</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><docTitle><titlePart rend="bold">Design of Discrete Digital Controllers</titlePart></docTitle><titlePart>ES330 Control I <name type="student name"/><name type="student ID"/> Computer Systems Engineering MEng Year 3 23 <hi rend="sup">rd</hi> January 2006</titlePart></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="abstract"><head rend="bold">SummarySummary</head><p n="p1.112"><s n="s1.6;p1.112">This report is concerned with the design of discrete controllers, and the comparison of theoretical to simulated controllers. </s><s n="s2.6;p1.112">A basic First Order Plus Dead Time (FOPDT) system was selected to be controlled and various preliminary calculations were carried out to determine suitable values for system controller coefficients. </s><s n="s3.6;p1.112">Using these values, a proportional-only discrete controller, a PID discrete controller and a Dahlin controller were designed theoretically to control the system. </s><s n="s4.6;p1.112">These controllers were then simulated using the SDS simulator available at <seg type="URL" n="www.eng"/>.<name type="university"/>.ac.uk/cgi-bin/sds and their outputs with various values of controller gain were observed. </s><s n="s5.6;p1.112">It was noted that in general the outputs produced using the simulator matched well with what was expected from the theoretically calculated values. </s><s n="s6.6;p1.112">It was also noted that the Dahlin controller performed better overall than the PID discrete controller or the proportional only discrete controller, as it reached the correct final value very quickly and had no overshoot from this value. </s></p></div1><div1 type="front-back-matter"><head rend="bold">Contents &amp; Figures</head><p/></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Introduction</head><div2><head rend="bold">Introduction</head><p n="p2.112"><s n="s1.7;p2.112">Every system must be controlled in some way or another, but designing suitable controllers is not always an easy task. </s><s n="s2.7;p2.112">There are a variety of ways of designing controllers and this report seeks to investigate and compare some of the possible methods. </s><s n="s3.7;p2.112">The report is mainly concerned with the design of discrete controllers but some preliminary calculations based on analog control were required. </s><s n="s4.7;p2.112">Following these calculations, it was possible to select suitable values for a proportional only discrete controller, a PID discrete controller and a Dahlin controller. </s><s n="s5.7;p2.112">These values were then used with the SDS simulator in order to examine the behaviour of such controllers. </s><s n="s6.7;p2.112">Output graphs were generated with different controller gains to see the effect of varying this parameter on the different types of controller. </s><s n="s7.7;p2.112">The results obtained from the simulation were then compared to the behaviour predicted by the calculations carried out initially, as well as allowing for a comparison between the different types of controller. </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Background Information</head><div2><head rend="bold">Ziegler Nichols Values</head><div3><head rend="italic">Purpose</head><p n="p3.112"><s n="s1.2;p3.112">When designing controllers, various parameters cannot be determined purely from the system equations and must be selected appropriately. </s><s n="s2.2;p3.112">For example, in a typical analog PID controller: </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p4.112"><s n="s1.1;p4.112"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0263b-form.001"/> (1.1) </s></p><p n="p5.112"><s n="s1.1;p5.112">This can be rearranged to show it has a gain of </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p6.112"><s n="s1.1;p6.112"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0263b-form.002"/> (1.2) </s></p><p n="p7.112"><s n="s1.3;p7.112">Note that <hi rend="italic">Kc</hi>, <hi rend="italic">τi</hi> and <hi rend="italic">τD</hi> cannot be determined just from the system equation and therefore values must be selected using some appropriate method. </s><s n="s2.3;p7.112">Ziegler Nichols equations may be used to determine suitable values for these coefficients. </s><s n="s3.3;p7.112">Note that they are not based in theory and have been determined experimentally, but are generally accepted as providing sensible values for the coefficients in proportional, integral and derivative systems. </s></p></div3><div3><head rend="italic">Methods of Calculation</head><p n="p8.112"><s n="s1.2;p8.112">There are two methods of determining Ziegler Nichols settings for a controller: the reaction curve method and the continuous oscillation method, which is the method used here. </s><s n="s2.2;p8.112">In order to determine the values using this method, the following steps are used: </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p9.112"><s n="s1.1;p9.112">Consider the closed loop system with a proportional-only controller, i.e. <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0263b-form.003"/>, and find the value <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0263b-form.004"/> where the system just continuously oscillates, with period <hi rend="italic">Tu</hi>. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p10.112"><s n="s1.1;p10.112">Note that when the system just continuously oscillates, the phase of the forward path is - and the magnitude of the open loop gain is 1. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p11.112"><s n="s1.1;p11.112">Hence set <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0263b-form.005"/> and solve to find <hi rend="italic">(u</hi> (and hence <hi rend="italic">Tu</hi>), then set <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0263b-form.006"/> and solve to find <hi rend="italic">Ku</hi>. </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p12.112"><s n="s1.1;p12.112">Using the values found for <hi rend="italic">Ku</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Tu</hi>, substitute into the appropriate equations below to find suitable coefficient values for the controller type desired. </s></p><p n="p13.112"><s n="s1.1;p13.112">The equations used with the values for <hi rend="italic">Ku</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Tu</hi> depend on the type of controller and are as follows. </s></p><p n="p14.112"><s n="s1.1;p14.112"><hi rend="underlined">Proportional Only Controller</hi>: </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p15.112"><s n="s1.1;p15.112"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0263b-form.007"/> (1.3) </s></p><p n="p16.112"><s n="s1.1;p16.112"><hi rend="underlined">PI Controller</hi>: </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p17.112"><s n="s1.1;p17.112"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0263b-form.008"/> (1.4) </s></p><p n="p18.112"><s n="s1.1;p18.112"><hi rend="underlined">PID Controller</hi>: </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p19.112"><s n="s1.1;p19.112"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0263b-form.009"/> (1.5) </s></p></div3></div2><div2><head rend="bold">Jury's Stability Criteria</head><p n="p20.112"><s n="s1.3;p20.112">Jury's stability criteria are the necessary and sufficient criteria for a discrete controller to be stable. </s><s n="s2.3;p20.112">In order that the system is stable, the characteristic equation, <hi rend="italic">F(z)</hi> must have no roots on or outside the unit circle when plotted on a z-plane. </s><s n="s3.3;p20.112">Jury's stability criteria provide a simple way of checking this without actually plotting <hi rend="italic">F(z)</hi>. </s></p><p n="p21.112"><s n="s1.2;p21.112">Firstly, the characteristic equation of a system is written in the form <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0263b-form.010"/>. </s><s n="s2.2;p21.112">If we consider only the simplest case, when the characteristic equation is of order 2 (i.e. <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0263b-form.011"/>), then the following criteria are necessary and sufficient for system stability. </s></p><p n="p22.112"><s n="s1.1;p22.112">Condition 1: <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0263b-form.012"/>. </s></p><p n="p23.112"><s n="s1.1;p23.112">Condition 2: <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0263b-form.013"/>. </s></p><p n="p24.112"><s n="s1.1;p24.112">Condition 3: <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0263b-form.014"/>. [1] </s></p><p n="p25.112"><s n="s1.1;p25.112">Providing all three of these criteria are met, the system will be stable. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">Simple Backwards Differencing</head><p n="p26.112"><s n="s1.2;p26.112">Simple backwards differencing is a method of converting an analog controller to a discrete controller. </s><s n="s2.2;p26.112">For an analog PID controller, the system may be specified as </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p27.112"><s n="s1.1;p27.112"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0263b-form.015"/> (1.6) </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p28.112"><s n="s1.1;p28.112"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0263b-form.016"/> (1.7) </s></p><p n="p29.112"><s n="s1.1;p29.112">The discrete equivalent may be found by taking first backward differences: </s></p><p n="p30.112"><s n="s1.1;p30.112"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0263b-form.017"/> </s></p><p n="p31.112"><s n="s1.1;p31.112"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0263b-form.018"/> </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p32.112"><s n="s1.1;p32.112"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0263b-form.019"/> (1.8) </s></p><p n="p33.112"><s n="s1.1;p33.112">In z-transform terms, </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p34.112"><s n="s1.1;p34.112"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0263b-form.020"/> (1.9) </s></p><p n="p35.112"><s n="s1.1;p35.112">where <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0263b-form.021"/>, <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0263b-form.022"/> and <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0263b-form.023"/>. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">Dahlin Controller</head><p n="p36.112"><s n="s1.2;p36.112">An alternative method of discrete controller design which is not based on analog systems at all is the Dahlin algorithm. </s><s n="s2.2;p36.112">First, note that they system equation for an FOPDT system with dead time NT and a zero-order hold is </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p37.112"><s n="s1.1;p37.112"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0263b-form.024"/> (1.10) </s></p><p n="p38.112"><s n="s1.1;p38.112">As a function of z, </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p39.112"><s n="s1.1;p39.112"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0263b-form.025"/> (1.11) </s></p><p n="p40.112"><s n="s1.1;p40.112">Equation 1.11 may be written more succinctly as </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p41.112"><s n="s1.1;p41.112"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0263b-form.026"/> (1.12) </s></p><p n="p42.112"><s n="s1.1;p42.112">The objective then is to obtain a closed-loop transfer function of the form </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p43.112"><s n="s1.1;p43.112"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0263b-form.027"/> (1.13) </s></p><p n="p44.112"><s n="s1.2;p44.112">where <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0263b-form.028"/> and <hi rend="italic">TCL</hi> is the closed-loop time constant. </s><s n="s2.2;p44.112">This means that the closed-loop response to a step input at the step point will have an exponential response with gain of unity after the same time delay as the process. </s></p><p n="p45.112"><s n="s1.1;p45.112"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0263b-form.029"/> where <hi rend="italic">Gc</hi> is controller gain, </s></p><p n="p46.112"><s n="s1.1;p46.112"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0263b-form.030"/> </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p47.112"><s n="s1.1;p47.112"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0263b-form.031"/> (1.14) </s></p><p n="p48.112"><s n="s1.1;p48.112">Hence the controller algorithm is given by </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p49.112"><s n="s1.1;p49.112"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0263b-form.032"/> (1.15) </s></p><p n="p50.112"><s n="s1.2;p50.112">A suitable value of <hi rend="italic">TCL</hi> should be selected to give adequate controller performance by setting <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0263b-form.033"/>, i.e. <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0263b-form.034"/>. </s><s n="s2.2;p50.112">Note that the maximum value of <hi rend="italic">Q</hi> (unity) occurs when <hi rend="italic">TCL</hi> is zero; this is known as dead beat control and, while perfect in theory, is not used in practise as problems arise if process dynamics are not perfectly modelled. </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Preliminary Calculations</head><div2><head rend="bold">Process System</head><p n="p51.112"><s n="s1.1;p51.112">The process to be controlled is an FOPDT system and therefore has Laplace transfer function given by </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p52.112"><s n="s1.1;p52.112"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0263b-form.035"/> (2.1) </s></p><p n="p53.112"><s n="s1.2;p53.112">In this particular system <hi rend="italic">Kp</hi>, the steady state gain of the process, is 1 and <hi rend="italic">td</hi>, the dead time, is 1s. </s><s n="s2.2;p53.112">The time constant, <hi rend="italic">Tp</hi>, was calculated as follows: </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p54.112"><s n="s1.1;p54.112">Author's University Card Number is <name type="student ID"/>, giving last 2 digits as 24. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p55.112"><s n="s1.1;p55.112"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0263b-form.036"/>. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">Analog Control</head><div3><head rend="italic">Proportional Only Analog Controller</head><p n="p56.112"><s n="s1.1;p56.112">Suppose that the process is controlled by an analog proportional-only controller, i.e. that <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0263b-form.037"/>, as shown in Figure 8.1. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0263b-fig.001"><head rend="bold">Figure 8.1 Analog Control System</head></figure><p n="p57.112"><s n="s1.1;p57.112">It is possible to write an expression for the open loop gain of the system: </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p58.112"><s n="s1.1;p58.112"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0263b-form.038"/> (2.2) </s></p><p n="p59.112"><s n="s1.1;p59.112">Using the values specified in section 7 above, this can be further expanded to give an expression specific to this system. </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p60.112"><s n="s1.1;p60.112"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0263b-form.039"/> (2.3) </s></p></div3><div3><head rend="italic">Ziegler Nichols Settings</head><p n="p61.112"><s n="s1.1;p61.112">With the open loop gain of the system as given in equation 1.3 above, it is possible to calculate the coefficient <hi rend="italic">Ku</hi> which can be used with the continuous oscillation method and Ziegler Nichols equations to find appropriate settings for the system. </s></p><p n="p62.112"><s n="s1.1;p62.112">First we find the phase part of the open loop gain: </s></p><p n="p63.112"><s n="s1.1;p63.112"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0263b-form.040"/> </s></p><p n="p64.112"><s n="s1.4;p64.112">For continuous oscillation, phase is - radians, i.e. <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0263b-form.041"/>. </s><s n="s2.4;p64.112">This can be solved iteratively for <hi rend="italic">(u</hi>, the frequency at which the control loop just continuously oscillates. </s><s n="s3.4;p64.112">To solve the equation iteratively, a spreadsheet was used varying <hi rend="italic">(u</hi> and tracking the value of <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0263b-form.042"/> to get it as close to zero as possible. </s><s n="s4.4;p64.112">The results are shown in Table 8.1 below, with the best value to two decimal places (<hi rend="italic">(u</hi> of 1.84 rad s <hi rend="sup">-1</hi>) shown in bold. </s></p><p n="p65.112"><s n="s1.2;p65.112">Using the equation <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0263b-form.043"/> and substituting the value for <hi rend="italic">(u</hi> allows <hi rend="italic">Tu</hi>, the period of the system at this frequency, to be found. </s><s n="s2.2;p65.112">In this case, <hi rend="italic">Tu</hi> = 3.41s. </s></p><table id="BAWE_0263b-tab.001"><head rend="bold">Table 8.1 Iteration to Find <hi rend="italic">ωu</hi></head><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p66.112"><s n="s1.1;p66.112">Referring again to equation 1.3, the magnitude part of the open loop gain can be found by <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0263b-form.044"/>. </s></p><p n="p67.112"><s n="s1.3;p67.112">For just continuous oscillation, the magnitude of the gain must be exactly unity, i.e. <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0263b-form.045"/>, which can be solved using the value for <hi rend="italic">ωu</hi> found above to give the controller gain at which the system just continuously oscillates. </s><s n="s2.3;p67.112">Recall that <hi rend="italic">ωu</hi>, was found to be 1.84 rad s <hi rend="sup">-1</hi>, hence the value of <hi rend="italic">Ku</hi> is given by <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0263b-form.046"/>, i.e. </s><s n="s3.3;p67.112"><hi rend="italic">Ku</hi> is approximately 3.74. </s></p><p n="p68.112"><s n="s1.3;p68.112">With these coefficient values, it is possible to calculate the Ziegler-Nichols settings for the system. </s><s n="s2.3;p68.112">As only proportional control is used, the calculation is very simple and requires only one equation, namely equation 1.3. </s><s n="s3.3;p68.112">Substituting the value of <hi rend="italic">Ku</hi> found above gives a value for <hi rend="italic">Kc</hi> of <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0263b-form.047"/>. </s></p></div3><div3><head rend="italic">Final Value of c(t)</head><p n="p69.112"><s n="s1.3;p69.112">The value calculated for <hi rend="italic">Kc</hi> above can be used with the Laplace transform Final Value Theorem to find the final value of <hi rend="italic">c(t)</hi>. </s><s n="s2.3;p69.112">Here we consider the response to a step increase of 0 to 1 in <hi rend="italic">r(t)</hi> applied at time 0 seconds. </s><s n="s3.3;p69.112">The Final Value Theorem states </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p70.112"><s n="s1.1;p70.112"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0263b-form.048"/> (2.4) </s></p><p n="p71.112"><s n="s1.1;p71.112">Hence, <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0263b-form.049"/>. </s></p><p n="p72.112"><s n="s1.1;p72.112">This means that <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0263b-form.050"/> which, with the value of <hi rend="italic">Kc</hi> established above, gives a final value for <hi rend="italic">c(t)</hi> of <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0263b-form.051"/> or approximately 0.65. </s></p></div3></div2><div2><head rend="bold">Discrete Control</head><div3><head rend="italic">Proportional Only Discrete Controller</head><p n="p73.112"><s n="s1.1;p73.112">Suppose now that the process is controlled by a discrete proportional-only controller, i.e. that <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0263b-form.052"/>, as shown in Figure 9.1. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0263b-fig.002"><head rend="bold">Figure 9.1 Discrete Control System</head></figure><p n="p74.112"><s n="s1.1;p74.112">As with the analog system, it is possible to write an expression for the open loop gain of the system. </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p75.112"><s n="s1.1;p75.112"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0263b-form.053"/> (2.5) </s></p><p n="p76.112"><s n="s1.1;p76.112">Using values specified in section 7 above and choosing a sampling interval, T, of 1s, this can be expanded to give an expression for this particular system. </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p77.112"><s n="s1.1;p77.112"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0263b-form.054"/> (2.6) </s></p></div3><div3><head rend="italic">Jury's Stability Criterion</head><p n="p78.112"><s n="s1.1;p78.112">Jury's Stability Criterion can be used to determine the maximum value of <hi rend="italic">Kc</hi> which allows for a stable system, here referred to as <hi rend="italic">KcMAX</hi>. </s></p><p n="p79.112"><s n="s1.1;p79.112">Using equation 1.7 above, the characteristic equation for the system can be written as </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p80.112"><s n="s1.1;p80.112"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0263b-form.055"/> (2.7) </s></p><p n="p81.112"><s n="s1.2;p81.112">This gives coefficients of <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0263b-form.056"/>, <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0263b-form.057"/> and <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0263b-form.058"/>. </s><s n="s2.2;p81.112">Note that the characteristic equation is of order 2 and therefore the conditions laid out in section 4 are the necessary and sufficient criteria for system stability. </s></p><p n="p82.112"><s n="s1.2;p82.112">From condition 1, <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0263b-form.059"/> for system stability. </s><s n="s2.2;p82.112">Solving for <hi rend="italic">Kc</hi> implies that <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0263b-form.060"/>. </s></p><p n="p83.112"><s n="s1.2;p83.112">From condition 2, <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0263b-form.061"/> for system stability. </s><s n="s2.2;p83.112">Solving for <hi rend="italic">Kc</hi> implies that <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0263b-form.062"/>. </s></p><p n="p84.112"><s n="s1.2;p84.112">Finally, from condition 3, <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0263b-form.063"/>. </s><s n="s2.2;p84.112">Solving for <hi rend="italic">Kc</hi> implies that <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0263b-form.064"/>. </s></p><p n="p85.112"><s n="s1.3;p85.112">Combining the solutions for these conditions gives the inequality <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0263b-form.065"/> for a stable system. </s><s n="s2.3;p85.112">Therefore, the largest possible value of <hi rend="italic">Kc</hi> for stability is <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0263b-form.066"/>. </s><s n="s3.3;p85.112">Note that this is considerably smaller than the value for an analog system found in section 8.2 (recall <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0263b-form.067"/>). </s></p></div3><div3><head rend="italic">Final Value of c(t)</head><p n="p86.112"><s n="s1.2;p86.112">Using the same value of <hi rend="italic">Kc</hi> as in section 8.2 above, the Final Value Theorem can be used to find the final value of <hi rend="italic">c(t)</hi>. </s><s n="s2.2;p86.112">Noting that <hi rend="italic">c(nT)</hi> is the sampled value sequence of <hi rend="italic">c(t)</hi>, the z-transform version of the Final Value Theorem may be written </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0263b-fig.003"/><p rend="ordered" n="p87.112"><s n="s1.1;p87.112">(2.8) </s></p><p n="p88.112"><s n="s1.1;p88.112">Hence, <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0263b-form.068"/>. <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0263b-form.069"/>. </s></p><p n="p89.112"><s n="s1.2;p89.112">This means that <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0263b-form.070"/> which, with the value of <hi rend="italic">Kc</hi> established above, gives a final value for <hi rend="italic">c(t)</hi> of <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0263b-form.071"/> or approximately 0.65. </s><s n="s2.2;p89.112">Note that this is exactly the same as in section 8.3 above, meaning that the final value of <hi rend="italic">c(t)</hi> is completely unaffected by sampling. </s></p></div3><div3><head rend="italic">PID Discrete Controller - Ziegler Nichols &amp; Backward Differencing</head><p n="p90.112"><s n="s1.2;p90.112">Using the values for <hi rend="italic">Ku</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Tu</hi> found in section 8.2 above (found using the continuous oscillation method), it is possible to find suitable coefficients for a PID controller. </s><s n="s2.2;p90.112">The relevant Ziegler Nichols equations are given in equations 1.5, which give values of <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0263b-form.072"/>, <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0263b-form.073"/> and <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0263b-form.074"/>. </s></p><p n="p91.112"><s n="s1.2;p91.112">Using the simple backward differencing method as described in section 5, the controller can be described in the form of equation 1.11. </s><s n="s2.2;p91.112">Substituting in values of <hi rend="italic">Kc</hi>, <hi rend="italic">(i</hi> and <hi rend="italic">(D</hi> as found above, and a sampling interval <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0263b-form.075"/>, <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0263b-form.076"/>, <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0263b-form.077"/> and <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0263b-form.078"/>. </s></p><p n="p92.112"><s n="s1.1;p92.112">Hence the discrete version of the controller equation may be written </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p93.112"><s n="s1.1;p93.112"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0263b-form.079"/> (2.9) </s></p></div3><div3><head rend="italic">PID Discrete Controller - Dahlin Algorithm</head><p n="p94.112"><s n="s1.2;p94.112">To create a Dahlin controller, equation 1.15 is used with the closed loop constant equal to the open loop time constant (i.e. <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0263b-form.080"/>), <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0263b-form.081"/>, a sampling interval <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0263b-form.082"/> and a process gain of 1 as described in section 7. </s><s n="s2.2;p94.112">This gives a controller gain of </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p95.112"><s n="s1.1;p95.112"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0263b-form.083"/> (2.10) </s></p><p n="p96.112"><s n="s1.1;p96.112">which can be simplified to </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p97.112"><s n="s1.1;p97.112"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0263b-form.084"/> (2.11) </s></p></div3></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Computer Work</head><div2><head rend="bold">Proportional Only Discrete Controller</head><p n="p98.112"><s n="s1.1;p98.112">Using the SDS tool available at <seg type="URL" n="www.eng"/>.<name type="university"/>.ac.uk/cgi-bin/sds it was possible to simulate the operation of a proportional-only discrete controller using the following steps: </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p99.112"><s n="s1.1;p99.112">The process parameters were set up according to equation 2.1 using the values in section 7. </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p100.112"><s n="s1.1;p100.112">A factor <hi rend="italic">z-1</hi> was factored out of equation 2.6 (to remove the effect of the zero-order hold, which is taken into account by the simulator): </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p101.112"><s n="s1.1;p101.112"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0263b-form.085"/> (3.11) </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p102.112"><s n="s1.1;p102.112">The controller parameters were set up according to equation 3.1. </s></p><p n="p103.112"><s n="s1.1;p103.112">The controller gain, <hi rend="italic">Kc</hi>, was initially set up as the value of <hi rend="italic">KcMAX</hi> calculated in section 9.2 with <hi rend="italic">tL</hi> set to 100 seconds to provide a reasonable time interval over which to observe the response, which can be seen in appendix 1, simulation 1. </s></p><p n="p104.112"><s n="s1.1;p104.112"><hi rend="italic">Kc</hi> was then reduced to its Ziegler Nichols value, 0.5 <hi rend="italic">Ku</hi>, as calculated in section 8.2 and, again, the output was simulated (see appendix 1, simulation 2). </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">PID Discrete Controller</head><p n="p105.112"><s n="s1.4;p105.112">Again, using the SDS tool, it was possible to simulate the operation of a PID discrete controller. </s><s n="s2.4;p105.112">The process parameters were entered in the same way as for the simulations in section 10. </s><s n="s3.4;p105.112">For the controller parameters, equation 2.9 was used with controller gain initially set to its Ziegler Nichols value of 0.6 <hi rend="italic">Ku</hi>, and <hi rend="italic">tL</hi> of 100 seconds again. </s><s n="s4.4;p105.112">The response found can be seen in appendix 1, simulation 3. </s></p><p n="p106.112"><s n="s1.3;p106.112">The value of <hi rend="italic">Kc</hi> was then adjusted to obtain a response which settled within a reasonable time period (here chosen as under around 30 seconds). </s><s n="s2.3;p106.112">Kc was decreased to a value of 2.0, followed by 1.5 then 1.3 and finally 1.2 to obtain a reasonable response. </s><s n="s3.3;p106.112">The response obtained with <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0263b-form.086"/> can be seen in appendix 1, simulation 4. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">Dahlin Controller</head><p n="p107.112"><s n="s1.4;p107.112">Finally, using the SDS tool, it was possible to simulate the operation of a Dahlin discrete controller. </s><s n="s2.4;p107.112">Again, process parameters remained the same as in section 10, and controller parameters were set up according to equation 2.11. </s><s n="s3.4;p107.112"><hi rend="italic">tL</hi> was set to a value of 20 seconds to give a reasonable time period over which to observe the response. </s><s n="s4.4;p107.112">The output was observed and can be seen in appendix 1, simulation 5. </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Conclusions</head><div2><head rend="bold">Discussion of Results</head><div3><head rend="italic">Proportional Only Discrete Controller</head><p n="p108.112"><s n="s1.5;p108.112">The behaviour of the simulated proportional only discrete controller matched very well with the results expected from the preliminary calculations. </s><s n="s2.5;p108.112">With the controller gain set at <hi rend="italic">KcMAX</hi>, the system output just continuously oscillated, as was expected. </s><s n="s3.5;p108.112">When the value of <hi rend="italic">Kc</hi> was reduced to 0.5 <hi rend="italic">Ku</hi>, the system settled to a final value of around 0.65, again as predicted by the preliminary calculations. </s><s n="s4.5;p108.112">The response took around 85 seconds to settle to this value, making it rather less than ideal for a process of this kind. </s><s n="s5.5;p108.112">Also, as the controller has only proportional control, the correct final value was not reached leaving an offset between the required and actual final values. </s></p></div3><div3><head rend="italic">PID Discrete Controller</head><p n="p109.112"><s n="s1.5;p109.112">As with the proportional only discrete controller, the behaviour of the PID discrete controller matched very well with the results expected from the preliminary calculations. </s><s n="s2.5;p109.112">With <hi rend="italic">Kc</hi> at the analog Ziegler Nichols value of 0.6 <hi rend="italic">Ku</hi>, although the graph appears reasonably flat to begin with, examining the scale carefully shows that after 100 seconds the response is varying with orders of magnitude around 10 <hi rend="sup">9</hi>. </s><s n="s3.5;p109.112">This output is far too unstable to be of any use in a control system, so the value of <hi rend="italic">Kc</hi> was reduced until a reasonable response was produced. </s><s n="s4.5;p109.112">It was found that a value of <hi rend="italic">Kc</hi> of 1.2 produced a response which settled to its final value in under 30 seconds, suggesting that this would be a good value for such a system. </s><s n="s5.5;p109.112">Although the controller gain had to be kept lower for stability, the overall performance of the PID discrete controller was clearly better than that of the proportional only discrete controller as the value settled far more quickly to the correct final value. </s></p></div3><div3><head rend="italic">Dahlin Controller</head><p n="p110.112"><s n="s1.3;p110.112">Again, the behaviour of the simulated Dahlin controller matched very well with the results expected from the preliminary calculations. </s><s n="s2.3;p110.112">The closed-loop time constant in the simulated version was found to be <hi rend="italic">Tp</hi>, (i.e. the controller settled to 63% of its final value in around 1.96 seconds) as was expected based on the design. </s><s n="s3.3;p110.112">One of the most obvious features of the Dahlin controller output is that there is no overshoot and the final value is reached very quickly, in this case in around 12 seconds. </s></p></div3><div3><head rend="italic">Overall</head><p n="p111.112"><s n="s1.4;p111.112">The proportional only discrete controller was clearly the worst controller design of the three. </s><s n="s2.4;p111.112">It took a long time to settle to its final value, and even when it did there was an offset between the required and actual final values. </s><s n="s3.4;p111.112">The PID discrete controller was a great improvement; although controller gain had to be kept reasonably low for system stability, the response reached the correct final value and parameters could be adjusted so that the response settled within a reasonable time. </s><s n="s4.4;p111.112">Of the three controllers, however, the overall best was clearly the Dahlin controller, which not only settled far quicker than either of the other two designs, but also did not overshoot its final value at all. </s></p></div3></div2><div2><head rend="bold">Recommendations for Further Work</head><p n="p112.112"><s n="s1.6;p112.112">The investigation could be extended to comparing analog and discrete controller design methods. </s><s n="s2.6;p112.112">The initial preliminary calculations carried out were based on analog controllers, however these were not developed into complete systems, nor were they simulated. </s><s n="s3.6;p112.112">It would be relatively simple to extend the investigation to include the required calculations and simulations to allow a comparison of analog and discrete controllers. </s><s n="s4.6;p112.112">An alternative development could be examining different methods of discrete controller design, which would give a wider range of choices for selecting the "best" controller design method for a system such as this one. </s><s n="s5.6;p112.112">Finally, it could also be beneficial to examine non-linear control systems. </s><s n="s6.6;p112.112">No real system will be totally linear so it could be interesting to look at how non-linearities would affect the performance of these simulated systems. </s></p></div2></div1></body><back><div1 type="bibliography"><head rend="bold">References &amp; Bibliography</head><div2 type="bibliography"><head rend="bold">References &amp; Acknowledgements</head><p>Godfrey, Keith, <hi rend="italic">Control I - Assignment A1</hi>, p1 (see appendix 2).</p><p>Godfrey, Keith, <hi rend="italic">Control Handout 4 - "Jury's Stability Criterion"</hi>, p2.</p><p>Please note that much of the information in the "Background Information" section is based on information from lectures given by Keith Godfrey during the Control I module in the academic year 2005/06.</p></div2><div2 type="bibliography"><head rend="bold">Bibliography</head><p>Bissell, C. C. (1994), <hi rend="italic">"Control Engineering" (second edition)</hi>, CRC Press.</p></div2></div1><div1 type="appendix"><head rend="bold">Appendix - Computer Simulation Output Graphs</head><p/></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
