<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_0263e" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Project Specification: Comparison of Block and Stream Ciphers</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">The document has a title page which contains:
document title
title part</note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">deleted: footer: student and page numbers, assignment title</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">3</p><p n="date">2005-09</p><p n="module title">Computer Systems Engineering Project</p><p n="module code">CG352</p><p n="genre family">Proposal</p><p n="discipline">Computer Science</p><p n="disciplinary group">PS</p><p n="grade">D</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">1024</p><p n="number of s-units">80</p><p n="number of p">73</p><p n="number of tables">0</p><p n="number of figures">0</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">2</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">11</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">12.8</p><p n="average s-units per p">1.1</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">f</p><p n="year of birth">1986</p><p n="first language">English</p><p n="education">UKA</p><p n="course">Computer Science</p><p n="student ID">0263</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><docTitle><titlePart><hi rend="bold">Project Specification</hi> "Comparison of Block and Stream Ciphers" </titlePart></docTitle><titlePart><name type="student name"/><name type="student ID"/><name type="tutor name"/>(School of Engineering) 2005/06</titlePart></titlePage><div1 type="toc" n="2"><head rend="bold">Contents</head><p/></div1></front><body><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Project Specification</head><div2><head rend="bold">Project Title</head><p n="p1.73"><s n="s1.1;p1.73">The title of the project is "Comparison of Block and Stream Ciphers". </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">Problem</head><p n="p2.73"><s n="s1.2;p2.73">Due to the technological developments in telecommunications in recent years, the need for new methods of maintaining security and privacy over insecure communication media has emerged. </s><s n="s2.2;p2.73">This is usually achieved through using some form of data encryption. </s></p><p n="p3.73"><s n="s1.2;p3.73">Data encryption involves taking some type of data (in computer communications, generally in binary form) and in some way altering it so that only the intended recipient - and possibly also the sender - can work out what the original data was. </s><s n="s2.2;p3.73">The alteration generally involves either rearranging the characters in the data, or replacing certain characters with other characters, or may involve a combination of both of these. </s></p><p n="p4.73"><s n="s1.2;p4.73">Encryption algorithms can be split into two general categories: block ciphers (which encrypt multiple characters at a time) and steam ciphers (which encrypt data character by character). </s><s n="s2.2;p4.73">There are many different algorithms within these categories, and often even different ways of implementing the basic algorithms, which leads to a huge array of choices for any given application. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">Objectives</head><list type="ordered"><item>To gain a good understanding of the theory behind block ciphers.</item><item>To gain a good understanding of the theory behind stream ciphers.</item><item>To select two algorithms from each category and examine them in detail.</item><item>To implement versions of these algorithms in software.</item><item>To compare the implementations in terms of speed of use.</item><item>To compare the chosen algorithms in terms of speed of use and resistance to attack.</item></list><p n="p5.73"/></div2><div2><head rend="bold">Achieving Objectives</head><p rend="ordered" n="p6.73"><s n="s1.1;p6.73">Refer to resources listed below to gain a thorough understanding of the principles behind block ciphers. </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p7.73"><s n="s1.1;p7.73">Refer to resources listed below to gain a thorough understanding of the principles behind stream ciphers. </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p8.73"><s n="s1.1;p8.73">Refer to resources listed below to find examples of algorithms in each category. </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p9.73"><s n="s1.1;p9.73">From research, select two algorithms from each category which are worthy of further investigation. </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p10.73"><s n="s1.1;p10.73">Refer to resources listed below to gain a thorough understanding of the principles behind each specific algorithm. </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p11.73"><s n="s1.1;p11.73">Using a suitable programming language (most likely C++) produce an implementation of each selected algorithm. </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p12.73"><s n="s1.1;p12.73">Using a selection of example data, test the implementations of the algorithms to establish their relative speeds of encryption. </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p13.73"><s n="s1.1;p13.73">Refer to resources listed below to gain a thorough understanding of the mathematical principles behind proving theoretical speed of encryption. </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p14.73"><s n="s1.1;p14.73">Refer to resources listed below to gain a thorough understanding of different types of cryptographic attack and mathematical ways of examining algorithms' resistance to such attacks. </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p15.73"><s n="s1.1;p15.73">Use knowledge gained from this research to examine the theoretical speed of encryption and resistance to attack of each of the chosen algorithms. </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p16.73"><s n="s1.1;p16.73">Produce a comparison of the algorithms in terms of these properties. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">Resources</head><p n="p17.73"><s n="s1.2;p17.73">It is likely that the algorithm implementation will be done in C++, therefore access to a computer with a C++ compiler and a suitable text editor will be required. </s><s n="s2.2;p17.73">If appropriate, access to compiler documentation will be required. </s></p><p n="p18.73"><s n="s1.3;p18.73">As a large part of this project involves research, most of the resources required are books, websites or similar reference sources. </s><s n="s2.3;p18.73">Sources which are likely to be useful are listed below. </s><s n="s3.3;p18.73">This list may be expanded later. </s></p><list type="ordered"><item>Stinson, Douglas R. (2002). <hi rend="italic">Cryptography: Theory and Practice (second edition)</hi>. CRC Press.</item><item>Welsh, D. J. A (1988). <hi rend="italic">Codes and Cryptography (first edition)</hi>. Clarendon Press.</item><item>Damgård, Ivan (1999). <hi rend="italic">Lectures on Data Secutiry: Modern Cryptology in Theory and Practice (first edition)</hi>. Heidelbery GmbH &amp; Co.</item><item>Koblitz, Neal (1987). <hi rend="italic">A Course in Number Theory and Cryptography (first edition)</hi>. Spinger.</item><item>Welschenback, Michael (2001). <hi rend="italic">Cryptography in C and C++ (first edition)</hi>. Apress.</item><item>Buchmann, Johannes (2004). <hi rend="italic">Introduction to Cryptography (first edition)</hi>. Springer-Verlag New York Inc.</item><item>Schneier, Bruce (1995). <hi rend="italic">Applied Cryptography: Protocols, Algorithms and Source Code in C (first edition)</hi>. John Wiley &amp; Sons Inc.</item><item><hi rend="italic">Wikipedia</hi>. <seg type="URL" n="http://www.wikipedia.com"/></item><item><hi rend="italic">RSA Security; Crypto FAQ</hi>. <seg type="URL" n="http://www.rsasecurity.com/rsalabs/node.asp?id=2152"/></item><item><hi rend="italic">Bruce Schneier's Publications</hi>; <seg type="URL" n="http://www.schneier.com/papers.html"/></item></list></div2><div2><head rend="bold">Risk Assessment</head><p n="p19.73"><s n="s1.1;p19.73">Hazard </s></p><p n="p20.73"><s n="s1.1;p20.73">Working at a computer </s></p><p n="p21.73"><s n="s1.1;p21.73">Risk </s></p><p n="p22.73"><s n="s1.1;p22.73">Eye strain </s></p><p n="p23.73"><s n="s1.1;p23.73">Minimise By </s></p><p n="p24.73"><s n="s1.1;p24.73">Take regular breaks </s></p><p n="p25.73"><s n="s1.1;p25.73">Risk </s></p><p n="p26.73"><s n="s1.1;p26.73">RSI (Repetitive Strain Injury) </s></p><p n="p27.73"><s n="s1.1;p27.73">Minimise By </s></p><p n="p28.73"><s n="s1.1;p28.73">Use a variety of input peripherals (mouse, keyboard, etc.) </s></p><p n="p29.73"><s n="s1.1;p29.73">Risk </s></p><p n="p30.73"><s n="s1.1;p30.73">Pain due to poor posture </s></p><p n="p31.73"><s n="s1.1;p31.73">Minimise By </s></p><p n="p32.73"><s n="s1.1;p32.73">Ensure posture is good while working </s></p><p n="p33.73"><s n="s1.1;p33.73">Hazard </s></p><p n="p34.73"><s n="s1.1;p34.73">Storing files on computer media </s></p><p n="p35.73"><s n="s1.1;p35.73">Risk </s></p><p n="p36.73"><s n="s1.1;p36.73">Files become corrupted/lost </s></p><p n="p37.73"><s n="s1.1;p37.73">Minimise By </s></p><p n="p38.73"><s n="s1.2;p38.73">Take regular back-ups of work and store on separate media (e.g. </s><s n="s2.2;p38.73">CD) </s></p><p n="p39.73"><s n="s1.1;p39.73">Hazard </s></p><p n="p40.73"><s n="s1.1;p40.73">Copyright held on proprietary algorithms </s></p><p n="p41.73"><s n="s1.1;p41.73">Risk </s></p><p n="p42.73"><s n="s1.1;p42.73">Infringing copyright </s></p><p n="p43.73"><s n="s1.1;p43.73">Minimise By </s></p><p n="p44.73"><s n="s1.1;p44.73">Ensure all selected algorithms do not have copyright preventing them from being implemented in an academic context </s></p><p n="p45.73"><s n="s1.1;p45.73">Hazard </s></p><p n="p46.73"><s n="s1.1;p46.73">Illness/injury/other unforeseen circumstances </s></p><p n="p47.73"><s n="s1.1;p47.73">Risk </s></p><p n="p48.73"><s n="s1.1;p48.73">Project is delayed </s></p><p n="p49.73"><s n="s1.1;p49.73">Minimise By </s></p><p n="p50.73"><s n="s1.1;p50.73">Allowing plenty of time for each activity in the schedule; allowing time towards the end of the schedule for completion of any outstanding tasks </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">Timetable</head><div3><head rend="italic">Term 1</head><p n="p51.73"><s n="s1.2;p51.73">Date Task(s) </s><s n="s2.2;p51.73">To Be Completed </s></p><p n="p52.73"><s n="s1.1;p52.73">07/10/05 <hi rend="bold">Begin to draft specification</hi>; find appropriate resources; research mathematics and basics of cryptography </s></p><p n="p53.73"><s n="s1.1;p53.73">14/10/05 <hi rend="bold">Complete project specification</hi>; research block ciphers </s></p><p n="p54.73"><s n="s1.1;p54.73">21/10/05 Research block ciphers; research specific block cipher algorithms </s></p><p n="p55.73"><s n="s1.1;p55.73">28/10/05 Research stream ciphers </s></p><p n="p56.73"><s n="s1.1;p56.73">04/11/05 Research specific stream cipher algorithms </s></p><p n="p57.73"><s n="s1.1;p57.73">11/11/05 Research cryptographic attacks </s></p><p n="p58.73"><s n="s1.1;p58.73">18/11/05 Research any remaining areas which are unclear </s></p><p n="p59.73"><s n="s1.1;p59.73">25/11/05 <hi rend="bold">Begin to draft progress report</hi>; complete any remaining research </s></p><p n="p60.73"><s n="s1.1;p60.73">02/12/05 <hi rend="bold">Complete progress report</hi>; investigate C++ development environments and compilers </s></p></div3><div3><head rend="italic">Term 2</head><p n="p61.73"><s n="s1.1;p61.73">Date Task(s) To Be Completed </s></p><p n="p62.73"><s n="s1.1;p62.73">06/01/06 Complete familiarisation with C++ development environment </s></p><p n="p63.73"><s n="s1.1;p63.73">13/01/06 Begin implementation of algorithms in C++ </s></p><p n="p64.73"><s n="s1.1;p64.73">20/01/06 Complete implementation of algorithms in C++ </s></p><p n="p65.73"><s n="s1.1;p65.73">27/01/06 Test implementations for speed of use </s></p><p n="p66.73"><s n="s1.1;p66.73">03/02/06 Begin speed of use &amp; ease of attack analysis </s></p><p n="p67.73"><s n="s1.1;p67.73">10/02/06 Complete speed of use &amp; ease of attack analysis </s></p><p n="p68.73"><s n="s1.1;p68.73">17/02/06 <hi rend="bold">Begin producing presentation</hi>; bring research together and begin to <hi rend="bold">draft report</hi> </s></p><p n="p69.73"><s n="s1.1;p69.73">24/02/06 <hi rend="bold">Finish producing presentation</hi>; <hi rend="bold">continue drafting report</hi> </s></p><p n="p70.73"><s n="s1.1;p70.73">03/03/06 <hi rend="bold">Give presentation</hi> (if appropriate); <hi rend="bold">complete draft report</hi> and discuss with supervisor </s></p><p n="p71.73"><s n="s1.1;p71.73">10/03/06 Give presentation (if appropriate); make alterations to report </s></p></div3><div3><head rend="italic">Holiday Periods</head><p n="p72.73"><s n="s1.1;p72.73">Over the Christmas vacation, some refamiliarisation with the C++ programming language should be done, as well as selection of an appropriate development environment and compiler. </s></p><p n="p73.73"><s n="s1.1;p73.73">By week 1 of term 3, final report must be completed therefore any final alterations to the drafted report should be made over the Easter break. </s></p></div3></div2></div1></body><back/></text></TEI.2>
