<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_0265b" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Structure and Function of the Mitochondrial Cytochrome bc1 Complex</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">deleted: footer: student and page numbers</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">2</p><p n="date">2006-01</p><p n="module title">Biochemistry assessments</p><p n="module code">BS242</p><p n="genre family">Explanation</p><p n="discipline">Biological Sciences</p><p n="disciplinary group">LS</p><p n="grade">D</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">3756</p><p n="number of s-units">91</p><p n="number of p">29</p><p n="number of tables">1</p><p n="number of figures">7</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">1</p><p n="number of lists">0</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">1</p><p n="abstract present">abstract present</p><p n="average words per s-unit">41.3</p><p n="average s-units per p">3.1</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">m</p><p n="year of birth">1985</p><p n="first language">English</p><p n="education">UKA</p><p n="course">Biochemistry</p><p n="student ID">0265</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><docTitle><titlePart><hi rend="underlined">Structure and Function of the Mitochondrial Cytochrome <hi rend="italic">bc</hi></hi><hi rend="sub">1</hi><hi rend="underlined"> Complex</hi></titlePart></docTitle></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="abstract"><head rend="underlined">Abstract</head><p n="p1.29"><s n="s1.5;p1.29">Mitochondrial myopathies in particular those that are situated in the cytochrome <hi rend="italic">b</hi> of the <hi rend="italic">bc1</hi> complex, exacerbate free-radical damage by enhancing superoxide production. </s><s n="s2.5;p1.29">Superoxide damage to DNA and protein is a major contributing factor in many diseases of old age. </s><s n="s3.5;p1.29">Thus an understanding of the structure and mechanism of the complex is central to our understanding of the aging process. </s><s n="s4.5;p1.29">The mechanism of the Q-cycle will be discussed first, then that of the structure of the mammalian cytochrome <hi rend="italic">bc1</hi> complex. </s><s n="s5.5;p1.29">Finally the evidence for the movement and function of the iron sulphur protein will be discussed with reference to the Q-cycle </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined">Introduction</head><p n="p2.29"><s n="s1.2;p2.29">Cytochrome <hi rend="italic">bc1</hi> is the second of the three proton pumps located in the respiratory chain. </s><s n="s2.2;p2.29">Located in the inner mitochondria, the complex catalyses electron transfer from ubiquinol to cytochrome <hi rend="italic">c</hi> by a proton motive Q-cycle mechanism, in which electron transfer is linked to proton translocation across the inner mitochondrial membrane.<hi rend="sup">1</hi> Thus the complex contributes to the generation of the electrochemical proton gradient that subsequently drives ATP synthesis as well as ion and metabolite transport.<hi rend="sup">2</hi> </s></p><p n="p3.29"><s n="s1.4;p3.29">Mitochondrial myopathies especially those that are situated in the cytochrome <hi rend="italic">b</hi> of the <hi rend="italic">bc1</hi> complex, exacerbate free-radical damage by enhancing superoxide production at the Qo site.<hi rend="sup">3</hi> The production of the ubisemiquinone anion is an unavoidable intermediate of the Q-cycle. </s><s n="s2.4;p3.29">Molecular oxygen has access to the ubisemiquinone anion located at the Qo site; there is a finite chance that it may donate its electron to O <hi rend="sub">2</hi> rather than <hi rend="italic">b</hi><hi rend="sub">L</hi> therefore forming a superoxide anion. </s><s n="s3.4;p3.29">These superoxides are capable of causing oxidative damage to the surrounding DNA and protein this is a major contributing factor in many diseases of old age. </s><s n="s4.4;p3.29">Thus an understanding of the mechanism of the <hi rend="italic">bc1</hi> complex is central to our understanding of the aging process.<hi rend="sup">3,4</hi> </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined">The Q-cycle Mechanism</head><p n="p4.29"><s n="s1.2;p4.29">Ubiquinone is a quinine derivative with a long isoprenoid tail, the number of isoprenoid units depends on the species e.g. mammals contain 10 isoprene units. </s><s n="s2.2;p4.29">Quinones can exist in three oxidation states (Figure 1); electron transfer reactions are coupled to proton binding and release a feature key to cytochrome <hi rend="italic">bc1</hi>.<hi rend="sup">5</hi> Ubiquinone (Q) and ubiquinol (QH <hi rend="sub">2</hi>) exist in the inner mitochondrial membrane in large molar excess over that of other components of the respiratory chain.<hi rend="sup">4</hi> </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0265b-pic.001"><head><hi rend="bold">Figure 1:</hi> The reduction of ubiquinol to ubiquinone proceeds through a ubisemiquinone anion <hi rend="sup">5</hi></head></figure><p n="p5.29"><s n="s1.4;p5.29">The mode of function of cytochrome <hi rend="italic">bc1</hi> is best described by considering two consecutive single turnovers of the enzyme.<hi rend="sup">2</hi> In the first turnover a molecule of ubiquinol from this bulk pool is oxidised at the Q <hi rend="sub">o</hi> site near the P-side of the inner mitochondrial membrane in a concerted reaction. </s><s n="s2.4;p5.29">One electron is conveyed to the Rieske iron-sulphur cluster yielding a ubisemiquinone anion, which reduces the cytochrome <hi rend="italic">b</hi><hi rend="sub">L</hi>.<hi rend="sup">6</hi> The Rieske iron-sulphur cluster oscillates to within electron transfer distance of cytochrome c <hi rend="sub">1</hi> therefore facilitating the transfer of an electron form iron sulphur cluster to c <hi rend="sub">1</hi> haem which is then transferred to cytochrome <hi rend="italic">c</hi>.<hi rend="sup">1</hi> The reduced cytochrome <hi rend="italic">c</hi> molecule is now free to diffuse away from the enzyme. </s><s n="s3.4;p5.29">The second electron is transferred from the ubisemiquinone anion to cytochrome <hi rend="italic">b</hi><hi rend="sub">L</hi> and then to <hi rend="italic">b</hi><hi rend="sub">H</hi> and finally to a bound ubiquinone bound at the Q <hi rend="sub">i</hi> site reducing it to a ubisemiquinone anion. </s><s n="s4.4;p5.29">As ubiquinol is at the Q <hi rend="sub">o</hi> site is oxidised to ubiquinone 2 protons are released to the cytoplasmic side; the ubiquinone in the Q <hi rend="sub">o</hi> site then diffuses back into the ubiquinone/ubiquinol pool (Figure: 2a).<hi rend="sup">5</hi> </s></p><p n="p6.29"><s n="s1.6;p6.29">In the second turnover a second molecule of ubiquinol binds to the Qo site and the Qo site reactions are repeated.<hi rend="sup">2</hi> The ubiquinol is oxidised, one of the electrons is conveyed through the Rieske iron sulphur cluster to cytochrome <hi rend="italic">c1</hi> which reduces a second molecule of cytochrome <hi rend="italic">c</hi>. </s><s n="s2.6;p6.29">As before a ubisemiquinone anion is formed in at the Qo site. </s><s n="s3.6;p6.29">Two further protons are deposited on the cytoplasmic side through the oxidation of ubiquinol. </s><s n="s4.6;p6.29">The second electron is transferred from the ubisemiquinone anion to cytochrome <hi rend="italic">b</hi><hi rend="sub">L</hi> and then to <hi rend="italic">b</hi><hi rend="sub">H</hi> and finally to the bound ubisemiquinone anion at the Q <hi rend="sub">i</hi> site. </s><s n="s5.6;p6.29">Upon the addition of this second electron, the ubisemiquinone anion takes up two protons from the matrix to form ubiquinol. </s><s n="s6.6;p6.29">The removal of these two protons from the matrix contributes to the formation of the proton gradient (Figure 2b).<hi rend="sup">5</hi> </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0265b-pic.002"><head><hi rend="bold">Figure 2:</hi> (a) This illustrates the electron transfer events that follow the oxidation of a ubiquinol at the P-side of the inner mitochondrial membrane when the Q <hi rend="sub">i</hi> site is occupied by ubiquinone molecule or vacant. (b) This illustrates the electron transfer events that follow the oxidation of a second ubiquinol at the P-side of the inner mitochondrial membrane when Q <hi rend="sub">i</hi> is occupied by a ubisemiquinone anion.<hi rend="sup">4 </hi></head></figure><p n="p7.29"><s n="s1.2;p7.29">After two complete turnovers of cytochrome <hi rend="italic">bc1</hi>, two molecules of QH <hi rend="sub">2</hi> have been oxidised at the Qo site to form two molecules of Q and one molecule of Q is reduced to QH <hi rend="sub">2</hi>. </s><s n="s2.2;p7.29">Two molecules of cytochrome c are reduced, four protons are released in the cytoplasmic side and two protons are removed form the mitochondrial matrix.<hi rend="sup">5</hi> (Equation: 1) </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p8.29"><s n="s1.1;p8.29"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0265b-form.001"/> Equation:1 <hi rend="sup">5</hi> </s></p><div2><head><hi rend="underlined">Evidence for a Bifurcated Mechanism of QH</hi><hi rend="sub">2</hi><hi rend="underlined"> Oxidation</hi></head><p n="p9.29"><s n="s1.2;p9.29">Initial evidence of a bifurcated mechanism of ubiquinol oxidation lies in the observation that oxidation of cytochrome <hi rend="italic">c</hi> and cytochrome <hi rend="italic">c1</hi> led to the reduction of haem <hi rend="italic">b</hi><hi rend="sub">L</hi> and haem <hi rend="italic">b</hi><hi rend="sub">H</hi>. </s><s n="s2.2;p9.29">This observation of an oxidant-induced reduction of haem <hi rend="italic">b</hi> is illogical when considered in a linear mechanism not that of a bifurcated mechanism.<hi rend="sup">7 </hi> </s></p><p n="p10.29"><s n="s1.5;p10.29">The bifurcated mechanism of ubiquinol oxidation was experimentally illustrated by examining the pre-steady state reduction of the cytochromes when the iron sulphur protein was removed from the cytochrome <hi rend="italic">bc</hi><hi rend="sub">1</hi> complex. </s><s n="s2.5;p10.29">Removal of the iron-sulphur protein from the <hi rend="italic">bc1</hi> complex blocked the reduction of cytochrome <hi rend="italic">c1</hi> but not the reduction of cytochrome <hi rend="italic">b</hi>. </s><s n="s3.5;p10.29">However the addition of antimycin an inhibitor that binds to the Q <hi rend="sub">i</hi> site blocks the reduction of both cytochromes <hi rend="italic">b</hi> and <hi rend="italic">c1</hi>. </s><s n="s4.5;p10.29">Thus the iron sulphur protein is required for <hi rend="italic">c1</hi> reduction through the normal mechanism. </s><s n="s5.5;p10.29">The b-cytochromes can be reduced by an iron sulphur protein independent pathway which is a reversal of the normal mechanism through the Qi site which is inhibited by antimycin.<hi rend="sup">6,7</hi> Additional evidence for the Q-cycle was obtained using specific inhibitors for either the Q <hi rend="sub">o</hi> or the Q <hi rend="sub">i</hi> site.<hi rend="sup">7</hi> </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined">Structure of Cytochrome <hi rend="italic">bc1</hi> complex</head><p n="p11.29"><s n="s1.2;p11.29">The cytochrome <hi rend="italic">bc1</hi> complex is a homodimeric, multisubunit membrane complex comprising of 3-11 protein subunits of which only three contain redox active prosthetic groups.<hi rend="sup">2</hi> The complex of the two monomers has a two fold axis of symmetry that runs vertically between the two monomers.<hi rend="sup">8</hi> The overall shape of the <hi rend="italic">bc1</hi> complex dimer from a bovine mitochondrial described below is similar to that of a chicken complex (Figure: 3). </s><s n="s2.2;p11.29">The dimmer extends from the membrane 75Å into the matrix space and 38Å into the intermembrane region on either side of a transmembrane region 42Å thick thus giving a total length of 155Å perpendicular to the membrane.<hi rend="sup">9</hi> </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0265b-pic.003"><head><hi rend="bold">Figure 3:</hi> Panel (a) Partial structure model of the dimeric bovine mitochondrial cytochrome bc1 complex.<hi rend="sup">9</hi> Panel (b) Stereo-view ribbon diagram of the native chicken mitochondrial cytochrome bc1 complex <hi rend="sup">8</hi> The monomers shown can be divided into three regions from top to bottom: the inter membrane space region, membrane spanning region and the matrix region.</head></figure><p n="p12.29"><s n="s1.2;p12.29">The three subunits which form the catalytic core of the enzyme are as follows: the Rieske Fe-S subunit which contains a [2Fe2S] cluster non-covalently liganded to the protein through two cysteines and two histidines; cytochrome <hi rend="italic">b</hi> which contains two haem groups held together through non-covalent interactions between bis histidine residues; cytochrome <hi rend="italic">c1</hi> which contains a haem <hi rend="italic">c</hi> group in contrast to cytochrome <hi rend="italic">b</hi> they are covalently attached to the protein by thiol ether linkages to cysteines. </s><s n="s2.2;p12.29">The cytochrome <hi rend="italic">bc1</hi> complex contains two active sites, one for ubiquinol oxidation (Q <hi rend="sub">o</hi>) and the second one for ubiquinone reduction (Q <hi rend="sub">i</hi>).<hi rend="sup">2,5,6</hi> </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0265b-pic.004"><head><hi rend="bold">Figure 4:</hi> Shows the topographical arrangement of the 3 electron transfer protein subunits and the two active sites of the cytochrome <hi rend="italic">bc1</hi> complex <hi rend="sup">1 </hi></head></figure><p n="p13.29"><s n="s1.3;p13.29">The topographical arrangement of the three electron transfer protein subunits in the cytochrome <hi rend="italic">bc1</hi> complex are as follows. </s><s n="s2.3;p13.29">Cytochrome <hi rend="italic">b</hi> is a transmembrane protein with eight transmembrane helices, with the haem <hi rend="italic">bL</hi> located near the P surface of the membrane and the haem <hi rend="italic">bH</hi> located towards the N side of the membrane. </s><s n="s3.3;p13.29">The redox potential of the haem <hi rend="italic">bH</hi> is approximately 60-120mV more positive than that of haem <hi rend="italic">bL</hi>, this difference facilitates electron transfer from haem <hi rend="italic">bL</hi> to the haem <hi rend="italic">bH</hi> even though there is an opposing membrane potential.<hi rend="sup">6,7</hi> Cytochrome <hi rend="italic">c1</hi> and the Rieske protein are located on the P side of the complex where both are anchored to the core of the complex by single transmembrane helices; their catalytic domains are located in the intermembrane space(Figure: 4).<hi rend="sup">1</hi> </s></p><p n="p14.29"><s n="s1.1;p14.29">Structural analysis of the <hi rend="italic">bc1</hi>-inhibitor complexes reveals two separate inhibitor binding pockets, located at opposite sides of the membrane for Qo and Q <hi rend="sub">i</hi> site inhibitors.<hi rend="sup">9</hi> The Qo site is located on the P-side of the inner mitochondrial membrane while Q <hi rend="sub">i</hi> site is located on that of the N-side of the outer mitochondrial membrane; both sites are located at the border of the hydrophobic core of the complex </s></p><p n="p15.29"><s n="s1.1;p15.29">(Figure: 4).<hi rend="sup">1</hi> </s></p><div2><head><hi rend="underlined">Superoxide production at the Q</hi><hi rend="sub">o</hi><hi rend="underlined"> site</hi></head><p n="p16.29"><s n="s1.4;p16.29">Molecular oxygen has access to the Q <hi rend="sub">o</hi> site and so there is a finite chance that the ubisemiquinone intermediate will donate its electrons to oxygen rather than <hi rend="italic">bL</hi> forming a superoxide. </s><s n="s2.4;p16.29">The superoxide is capable of causing oxidative damage to the mitochondrion and the cell. </s><s n="s3.4;p16.29">The oxidation of the ubisemiquinone intermediate at the Qo site is dependent on the passage of an electron across the membrane via the b cytochromes. </s><s n="s4.4;p16.29">At high ΔΨ this translocation is retarded therefore increasing the occupancy of the Q <hi rend="sub">o</hi> site by the ubisemiquinone anion and enhancing the chance of superoxide production.<hi rend="sup">4</hi> </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">Cytochrome <hi rend="italic">bc1</hi> complex functions as a dimer</head><p n="p17.29"><s n="s1.4;p17.29">From structural analysis of <hi rend="italic">bc1</hi> complexes it not only shows dimeric association but also suggest that the dimmer is in fact functional. </s><s n="s2.4;p17.29">The evidence for this hypothesis lays within its structure, in particular three structural features. </s><s n="s3.4;p17.29">First the distance between the two <hi rend="italic">bL</hi> haems in the two symmetrically related monomers is equal to that of that of the distance between <hi rend="italic">bL</hi> and <hi rend="italic">bH</hi> monomers suggesting that electron transfer between the two <hi rend="italic">bL</hi> haems of the dimmer is energetically feasible. </s><s rend="sup" n="s4.4;p17.29">9 </s></p><p n="p18.29"><s n="s1.5;p18.29">Second the globular domain of the Rieske protein of one monomer interacts with the Qo site and the cytochrome <hi rend="italic">c</hi><hi rend="sub">1</hi> in the other.<hi rend="sup">1,9</hi> Third the dimeric cytochrome <hi rend="italic">bc1</hi> complex forms two symmetrically related cavities in the membrane spanning region. </s><s n="s2.5;p18.29">Each monomer contains both Q <hi rend="sub">i</hi> and Q <hi rend="sub">o</hi> sites however they are unable to interact, however each cavity between the two monomers connects Q <hi rend="sub">o</hi> site of one monomer to the Q <hi rend="sub">i</hi> site of the other. </s><s n="s3.5;p18.29">This would allow the reduced ubiquinone at Q <hi rend="sub">i</hi> site of one monomer to be oxidised at the Q <hi rend="sub">o</hi> site of the other monomer without having to leave the <hi rend="italic">bc1</hi> complex and without having to equilibrate with the quinone pool. </s><s n="s4.5;p18.29">Thus these internal transfers would increase the efficiency of the complex since it would reduce the entries and exits of ubiquinone and ubiquinol from and to the bulk pool. </s><s n="s5.5;p18.29">This is consistent with the fact that 1 mole of ubiquinone per mole of <hi rend="italic">c</hi><hi rend="sub">1</hi> is sufficient for maximal activity of electron transfer in an isolated complex.<hi rend="sup">4,9</hi> </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined">[2Fe2S] domain movement in cytochrome <hi rend="italic">bc1</hi></head><p n="p19.29"><s n="s1.6;p19.29">From X-ray crystallographic studies of cytochrome <hi rend="italic">bc1</hi> it was discovered that the Rieske iron sulphur protein occurs in several different conformations depending on the crystal form and the presence of Qo site inhibitors. </s><s n="s2.6;p19.29">In native bovine crystals only a small intensity anomalous signal for 2Fe-2S was found to haem <hi rend="italic">bL</hi> indicating that the majority of the Rieske iron sulphur protein was to conformationally mobile to be observed in X-ray diffraction.<hi rend="sup">7</hi> Crystallization studies of cytochrome <hi rend="italic">bc1</hi> in the presence of the inhibitor stigmatellin, which is thought to bind to the 2Fe2S cluster and mimic a reaction intermediate the Fe-S subunit is in a fixed conformation proximal to the haem <hi rend="italic">bL</hi> (called the b state). </s><s n="s3.6;p19.29">In the presence of inhibitors such as myxothiazol or methoxy-acrylates which are thought to displace Q or QH <hi rend="sub">2</hi> at the Q <hi rend="sub">o</hi> site without directly interacting with the 2Fe2S cluster. </s><s n="s4.6;p19.29">The Fe-S subunit is released from this fixed conformation.<hi rend="sup">2</hi> In the absence of any inhibitors the Fe-S subunit can be found in a conformation with 2Fe-2S close the cytochrome <hi rend="italic">c1</hi>, called the <hi rend="italic">c1</hi> state (Figure 5).<hi rend="sup">7</hi> A novel shuttle mechanism for the Rieske iron sulphur protein has been proposed. </s><s n="s5.6;p19.29">It is based on these structural studies and the evidence from the Q-cycle and that of the structure of the <hi rend="italic">bc1</hi> complex before the movement of the Rieske iron sulphur protein was detected. </s><s n="s6.6;p19.29">The details of this evidence which pointed towards the movement of the Rieske iron sulphur protein is described below. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0265b-pic.005"><head><hi rend="bold">Figure 5:</hi> Shows the different positions of the Fe-S subunit extrinsic domain. The Fe-S subunit is in blue with the flexible hinge region in orange. Cyt b and cyt c1 subunits in grey and the cofactors heme bL, bH and c1 and the [2Fe2S] cluster are in red with the ef loop of cyt b in green.<hi rend="sup">10</hi></head></figure><p n="p20.29"><s n="s1.3;p20.29">The Q-cycle described previously, explains how the first electron from the QH <hi rend="sub">2</hi> oxidation flows to the Rieske iron-sulphur cluster but fails to suggest why the second electron fails to follow the same route. </s><s n="s2.3;p20.29">The second electron takes the less thermodynamically favourable route [redox midpoint potential E <hi rend="sub">m</hi> (<hi rend="italic">bL</hi>, <hi rend="italic">bH</hi>) &lt;&lt; E <hi rend="sub">m</hi> (FeS,<hi rend="italic">c1</hi>)]. </s><s n="s3.3;p20.29">The path of this second electron through the cytochrome <hi rend="italic">bH</hi> and its translocation across the membrane is critical for the formation of a ΔΨ across it.<hi rend="sup">2</hi> </s></p><p n="p21.29"><s n="s1.2;p21.29">The distance between <hi rend="italic">b</hi><hi rend="sub">L</hi> and <hi rend="italic">b</hi><hi rend="sub">H</hi> is that of 21Å and 27Å between <hi rend="italic">bL</hi> and 2Fe2S cluster, given that ubiquinol is bound between <hi rend="italic">b</hi><hi rend="sub">L</hi> and 2Fe2S cluster then the observed fast electron transport rates can be accounted for. </s><s n="s2.2;p21.29">However the distance between haem <hi rend="italic">bL</hi> and 2Fe2S cluster is 31Å which is too great to account for the large electron transfer rate between the two redox centres.<hi rend="sup">9</hi> </s></p><div2><head rend="underlined">Mobility of the Catalytic Rieske domain through a hinge region </head><p n="p22.29"><s n="s1.4;p22.29">Comparison of various crystallographic data indicates that movement of the 2Fe2S cluster domain indicates the presence of a flexible 'hinge' region that connects the fixed membrane anchor to that of the cluster domain.<hi rend="sup">10</hi> Applying mutations to this hinge region in microbial species such as <hi rend="italic">R.capsulatus</hi> the effects on enzyme function have been investigated (Table 1). </s><s n="s2.4;p22.29">Shortening the hinge region has little effect, however increased flexibility and length is deleterious. </s><s n="s3.4;p22.29">Proline substitutions decreased its flexibility, cysteine residues formed disulphide bonds both of which greatly reduced the activity of the complex. </s><s n="s4.4;p22.29">Thus one can conclude that an optimum in hinge length and flexibility is critical for an efficient and functionally <hi rend="italic">bc1</hi> complex.<hi rend="sup">2</hi> </s></p><table id="BAWE_0265b-tab.001"><head><hi rend="bold">Table 1:</hi> Mutants affecting the hinge region of the Fe-S subunit of cytochrome <hi rend="italic">bc1</hi> <hi rend="sup">2</hi></head><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p23.29"><s n="s1.2;p23.29">If the Q <hi rend="sub">i</hi> site is blocked, electrons in the low potential chain are unable to flow back to the high potential chain suggesting that the motion of the Fe-S subunit is not that of free diffusion but rather a controlled process.<hi rend="sup">2</hi> From crystallographic inhibitor studies with UHDBT and MOAS it has been suggested that there are two transient binding quinone binding sites at the Qo site. </s><s n="s2.2;p23.29">UHDBT reduces the mobility of ISP and binds to a site close to ISP at a sight designated P1 , while the inhibitor MOAS increases the mobility of ISP and binds to a site close to <hi rend="italic">bL</hi> haem designated P2.<hi rend="sup">9</hi> </s></p><p n="p24.29"><s n="s1.2;p24.29">The conformational changes in the Qo site are thought to be conveyed to the ISP by the EF loop, evidence for this lies in X-ray crystallographic studies of famoxadone. </s><s n="s2.2;p24.29">The EF loop is thought to convey these conformational changes to the ISP crater and neck contact domain therefore resulting in the capture or release of the ISP.<hi rend="sup">7</hi> </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined">Function and Movement of the Iron Sulphur protein </head><p n="p25.29"><s n="s1.6;p25.29">Ubiquinol enters the Qo site and binds to the P1 site, the ISP is in the b state conformation. </s><s n="s2.6;p25.29">The oxidised state of the 2Fe2S cluster of the Rieske protein is close to the surface of the protein and is held in position by electrostatic interactions with amino acid residues close to the Qo site. </s><s n="s3.6;p25.29">Ubiquinol becomes oxidised and one proton is released followed by the transfer of one electron to the ISP. Upon accepting this electron the 2Fe2S cluster becomes reduced therefore the strength of these stabilising interactions reduces. </s><s n="s4.6;p25.29">The Rieske protein dissociates and rotates through ~57˚ so that the same conserved docking surface of the Rieske protein that interacted with the cytochrome <hi rend="italic">b</hi> now interacts with cytochrome <hi rend="italic">c1</hi> (b).<hi rend="sup">8</hi> After the second proton is released the ubisemiquinone radical relocates and occupies P2 site, this is also thought to enhance the dissociation of the ISP. The dissociation of the ISP prevents the second electron from being conveyed to the ISP, since the distance (~16.4Å) between the Qo site and the ISP is too great for electron transfer.<hi rend="sup">8</hi> Thus the second electron is transferred to the <hi rend="italic">bL</hi> and then to the <hi rend="italic">bH</hi> haem possibly causing a conformational change in cytochrome <hi rend="italic">b</hi>, which results in the release of the reduced ISP to a second position closer to cytochrome <hi rend="italic">c1</hi> where it can transfer its electron. </s><s n="s5.6;p25.29">X-ray crystallographic studies have shown three positions rather than just two. </s><s n="s6.6;p25.29">Electron transfer to the haem of cytochrome <hi rend="italic">c1</hi> occurs, the 2Fe2S cluster becomes reduced and so does its affinity towards cytochrome <hi rend="italic">c1</hi>, thus the Rieske protein dissociates and moves back towards the Qo site (figure 6).<hi rend="sup">4,9</hi> </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0265b-pic.006"><head><hi rend="bold">Figure 6:</hi> Only cyt <hi rend="italic">b</hi> , cyt <hi rend="italic">c1</hi> and the Rieske iron-sulphur protein (ISP) are shown in this model. In (a) the ISP is in its <hi rend="italic">c1</hi> state, the reduced 2Fe/2S centre is held adjacent to cyt <hi rend="italic">c1</hi> . An electron is transferred from the haem of the ISP to cytochrome <hi rend="italic">c1</hi> , thus leaving the 2Fe/2S centre oxidised which results in its reduced affinity for cytochrome <hi rend="italic">c1</hi> (b). The Rieske protein dissociates and moves ~20Å so that it is repositions in the b state. 1e- is transferred (c) from the bound ubiquinol bound at the Q <hi rend="sub">o</hi> site to the 2Fe/2S centre, which decreases its affinity for this site, a ubisemiquinone anion is formed at the Qo site as two protons are released to the P-phase (d). An electron from ubisemiquinone anion is then transferred to <hi rend="italic">b</hi><hi rend="sub">L</hi> and then <hi rend="italic">b</hi><hi rend="sub">H</hi> and ubiquinone is released and the Fe/S domain of ISP dissociate fully from the Q <hi rend="sub">o</hi> site. In (f) an electron is transferred from the cytochrome <hi rend="italic">c1</hi> to that of cytochrome <hi rend="italic">c</hi> which is then reduced and dissociates away from the <hi rend="italic">bc1</hi> complex. The electron shown on the <hi rend="italic">b</hi><hi rend="sub">H</hi> haem is transferred to a ubiquinone bound at the Q <hi rend="sub">i</hi> site reducing it to a ubisemiquinone anion. This summaries the events of a single turnover of the enzyme, the system is now ready to complete a second turnover (events of (a) to (f) repeated) to complete the total turnover of the enzyme (equation: 1). In the second turnover of the enzyme the cytochrome <hi rend="italic">b</hi> will transmit the electron to the bound ubisemiquinone anion located at the Q <hi rend="sub">i</hi> site therefore oxidising it to ubiquinol.<hi rend="sup">4</hi></head></figure><div2><head rend="underlined">Reaction between cytochrome <hi rend="italic">bc1</hi> and cytochrome c</head><p n="p26.29"><s n="s1.2;p26.29">Cytochrome <hi rend="italic">c</hi> is a small water soluble haem protein that transfers electrons from the <hi rend="italic">bc1</hi> complex to cytochrome <hi rend="italic">c</hi> oxidase by a diffusional shuttle mechanism. </s><s n="s2.2;p26.29">The electron transfer between that of reduced <hi rend="italic">bc1</hi> complex and cytochrome <hi rend="italic">c</hi> is that of a 1:1 reactant complex in which cytochrome <hi rend="italic">c1</hi><hi rend="sup">2+</hi> transfers an electron to cytochrome <hi rend="italic">c</hi><hi rend="sup">3+</hi> resulting in the release of the product: cytochrome <hi rend="italic">c</hi><hi rend="sup">2+</hi> which is free to diffuse to cytochrome <hi rend="italic">c</hi> oxidase.<hi rend="sup">7</hi> </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">The Importance of the Fe-S subunit movement</head><p n="p27.29"><s n="s1.1;p27.29">The movement of the Fe-S subunit is critical for the electron bifurcation of the Q <hi rend="sub">o</hi> site, since it ensures that the second electron from QH <hi rend="sub">2</hi> oxidation does not follow the thermodynamically favourable path i.e. to <hi rend="italic">bL</hi> rather than the Rieske iron sulphur protein.<hi rend="sup">2</hi> </s></p><p n="p28.29"><s n="s1.3;p28.29">The speed of the Fe-S domain motion appears to occur between two functional limits to ensure productive electron bifurcation at the Qo site (Figure: 7). </s><s n="s2.3;p28.29">Through kinetics studies the movement of the Fe-S domain is not the rate limiting step for the cytochrome <hi rend="italic">bc1</hi> complex but is required for catalytic activity. </s><s n="s3.3;p28.29">Slowing the movement of the Fe-S domain to just less than the normal rate of Qo site catalysis k <hi rend="sub">cat</hi>, compromises the enzymes turnover and the rate of physiological growth.<hi rend="sup">10</hi> Excessively rapid movement of the Fe-S subunit has been calculated to result in the short circuiting of the low potential electron transfer chain and thus the decrease in the energetic efficiency of the complex (Figure).<hi rend="sup">2,10</hi> The Fe-S movement also permits the large electron transfer rates observed between <hi rend="italic">bL</hi> and the Fe-S which would not be facilitated by a soluble electron carrier such as cytochrome <hi rend="italic">c</hi>.<hi rend="sup">2</hi> </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0265b-pic.007"><head><hi rend="bold">Figure 7:</hi> Functional range of the [2Fe2S] cluster domain movement. The time scale of the [2Fe2S] cluster domain movement is between two points of failure.<hi rend="sup">10</hi></head></figure></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined">Concluding Remarks</head><p n="p29.29"><s n="s1.5;p29.29">The Cytochrome <hi rend="italic">bc1</hi> complex transfers electrons from ubiquinol to cytochrome <hi rend="italic">c</hi> and links electron transfer to the translocation of protons across the membrane via a mechanism called the Q-cycle. </s><s n="s2.5;p29.29">From X-ray crystallographic studies of cytochrome <hi rend="italic">bc1</hi> it has been proposed that the Rieske iron sulphur protein undergoes a large conformational change, which facilitates the rapid transfer of electrons from ubiquinol bound at the Q <hi rend="sub">o</hi> site to cytochrome <hi rend="italic">c</hi>. </s><s n="s3.5;p29.29">A link between the conformational changes at the ubiquinol binding site and that of the movement of the iron sulphur protein has been discovered, and this is thought to be involved in the bifurcated oxidation of ubiquinol. </s><s n="s4.5;p29.29">The structure of the complex has provided great insight into its mechanistic features such as the bifurcated oxidation of ubiquinol. </s><s n="s5.5;p29.29">A greater understanding of the structure of the <hi rend="italic">bc1</hi> complex is enabling the mechanisms of the Q-cycle and the prevention of superoxide production at the Qo site to be understood in greater detail. </s></p></div1></body><back><div1 type="bibliography"><head rend="underlined">References</head><p>[1] Hunte C. <hi rend="italic">et al</hi>. (2003) Protonmotive pathways and mechanisms in the cytochrome bc<hi rend="sub">1</hi> complex. <hi rend="italic">Federation of European Biochemical Societies</hi> 545:39-46</p><p>[2] Darrouzet, E. <hi rend="italic">et al</hi> (2001) Large scale domain movement in cytochrome <hi rend="italic">bc1</hi>: a new device for electron transfer in proteins. <hi rend="italic">Trends in Biochemical Sciences</hi> 26:445-451</p><p>[3] Crofts, A.R. (2004) The cytochrome <hi rend="italic">bc1</hi> complex: Function in the context of structure. <hi rend="italic">Annual Review of Physiology</hi> 66: 689-733</p><p>[4] Nicholls, D.G. Ferguson, S.J. (2001) <hi rend="italic">Bioenergetics 3.</hi> Third edn. Oxford: Academic Press.</p><p>[5] Berg, J.M. (2003) Biochemistry. Fifth edn. New York: W.H.Freeman</p><p>[6] Trumpower, B.L. (1990) The Protonmotive Q-cycle. <hi rend="italic">The Journal of Biological Chemistry</hi> 265:11409-11412</p><p>[7] Durham, B. Millett, F. (2004) Kinetics of electron transfer within cytochrome bc<hi rend="sub">1</hi> and between cytochrome <hi rend="italic">bc1</hi> and cytochrome <hi rend="italic">c</hi>. <hi rend="italic">Photosynthesis Research</hi> 82: 1-16.</p><p>[8] Zhang, Z <hi rend="italic">et al.</hi> (1998) Electron transfer by domain movement in cytochrome <hi rend="italic">bc</hi><hi rend="sub">1</hi>. Nature 392:677-684.</p><p>[9] Yu, Chang-An <hi rend="italic">et al</hi>. (1998) Structural basis of functions of the mitochondrial cytochrome <hi rend="italic">bc1</hi> complex. Biochimica et Biophysica Acta 1365:151-158.</p><p>[10] Darrouzet, E. <hi rend="italic">et al.</hi> (2000) Uncovering the [2Fe2S] domain movement in cytochrome <hi rend="italic">bc1</hi> and its implications for energy conversion. <hi rend="italic">Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences</hi> 97: 4567-4572.</p></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
