<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_0265c" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Compare and Contrast the Cell Signalling Mechanisms that Allow us to Sense Touch, Heat, Light, Sound and Smell.</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">deleted: footer: student and page numbers</note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">deleted: Word Count:2,981</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">2</p><p n="date">2006-01</p><p n="module title">Biochemistry assessments</p><p n="module code">BS242</p><p n="genre family">Explanation</p><p n="discipline">Biological Sciences</p><p n="disciplinary group">LS</p><p n="grade">D</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">3843</p><p n="number of s-units">115</p><p n="number of p">30</p><p n="number of tables">4</p><p n="number of figures">10</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">0</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">0</p><p n="abstract present">abstract present</p><p n="average words per s-unit">33.4</p><p n="average s-units per p">3.8</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">m</p><p n="year of birth">1985</p><p n="first language">English</p><p n="education">UKA</p><p n="course">Biochemistry</p><p n="student ID">0265</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><docTitle><titlePart rend="underlined">Compare and Contrast the Cell Signalling Mechanisms that Allow us to Sense Touch, Heat, Light, Sound and Smell. </titlePart></docTitle></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="abstract"><head rend="underlined">Abstract</head><p n="p1.30"><s n="s1.3;p1.30">The senses sight, smell, touch and hearing provide us as humans with the means to detect a diverse set of external signals with great sensitivity and specificity giving us a perception of external environment allowing us to alter of perform, informed decisions based upon that. </s><s n="s2.3;p1.30">The cell signalling mechanisms of the senses, with regards to their activation, amplification and termination will be discussed before finally comparing and contrasting the different mechanisms. </s><s n="s3.3;p1.30">The neurobiology of the senses is out of the scope of this essay and so will not be discussed in any great depth. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined">Introduction</head><p n="p2.30"><s n="s1.4;p2.30">The senses touch, heat, light, sound and smell allow us to perceive different aspects of are external environment i.e. shape/texture, temperature, sound and odor respectively. </s><s n="s2.4;p2.30">These signals are then processed and combined with additional information in the central nervous system allowing us to perceive the situation and alter or perform, informed decisions based on that of the external environment. </s><s n="s3.4;p2.30">For example the ability to recognise an attractive pleasant smelling rose (sight, olfaction) and to be capable of picking the rose up without damaging it (pressure sensing). </s><s n="s4.4;p2.30">The study of how the brain perceives these cell signals and responds to them is that of neurobiology. </s></p><p n="p3.30"><s n="s1.4;p3.30">Olfaction, phototransduction are examples of G-protein linked 7TM receptors, while thermo/pressure sensing and hearing are examples of mechanosensory transduction. </s><s n="s2.4;p3.30">The contrasting and similar mechanisms go far to explain many aspects of the senses, such as the sensitivity and the speed of transduction. </s><s n="s3.4;p3.30">For example the ability of humans to locate sound sources, is achieved by the transduction mechanism. . </s><s n="s4.4;p3.30">The importance of the study of cell signalling is clear to see, for it has given new understanding to many diseases and allowed the development of new drug therapies e.g. pain-management for arthritis </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined">Phototransduction</head><p n="p4.30"><s n="s1.4;p4.30">Phototransduction is the process by which a photon of light is captured by a molecule of visual pigment which generates an electrical response in a photoreceptor cell <hi rend="sup">1</hi>. </s><s n="s2.4;p4.30">These photoreceptor molecules are located in the retina of the eye and are sensitive to wavelengths between 300 and 850nm, often referred to as visible light. </s><s n="s3.4;p4.30">Vertebrates contain two types of these photoreceptor cells called rods and cones and are so named due to their distinctive shape. </s><s n="s4.4;p4.30">Cones function in bright light and are responsible for colour vision, while rods function in dim light but do not perceive colour <hi rend="sup">2</hi>. </s></p><p n="p5.30"><s n="s1.3;p5.30">Phototransduction will be discussed with regard to rod photoreceptors as opposed to cone photoreceptors for they have been studied in greater detail; however the mechanism is thought to be similar. </s><s n="s2.3;p5.30">Rods are slender elongated structures (<hi rend="italic">figure 1</hi>); the outer segment where photoreception occurs consists of approximately 1000 discs which are membrane enclosed sacs containing photoreceptor molecules <hi rend="sup">2</hi>. </s><s n="s3.3;p5.30">In rods the photoreceptor molecule is rhodopsin, which is a transmembrane protein linked to 11-cis-retinal, upon photoabsorption it decomposes to opsin and all-trans-retinal. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0265c-pic.001"><head><hi rend="bold">Figure 1</hi><hi rend="sup">2</hi> : The Rod Cell (left) Scanning electron micrograph of retinal cells (Right) Schematic representation of a rod cell <hi rend="sup">2</hi></head></figure><div2><head rend="underlined">Activation of Phototransduction</head><p n="p6.30"><s n="s1.7;p6.30">11-cis-retinal is a preattached ligand to that of the Rhodopsin transmembrane protein, upon exposure to a single photon it is isomerised by this captured photon. </s><s n="s2.7;p6.30">Rhodopsin undergoes a series of intramolecular transitions ending in the formation of an all-trans-retinal form called metarhodopsin II (or R*)<hi rend="sup">1-3</hi>. </s><s n="s3.7;p6.30">R* interacts with the bound heterotrimeric G protein causing the exchange of GDP for GTP by the alpha subunit of transducin <hi rend="sup">2</hi>. </s><s n="s4.7;p6.30">Upon this exchange of GDP for GTP, the alpha subunit dissociates from R* and the βy subunit of transducin dissociate from that of the alpha subunit. </s><s n="s5.7;p6.30">The GαGTP stimulates cyclic GMP phosphodiesterase which hydrolyses cyclic GMP thus reducing the cytoplasmic concentration of cyclic GMP <hi rend="sup">1</hi>. </s><s n="s6.7;p6.30">This drop in concentration causes the closure of cation ion selective ion channels in the plasma membrane. </s><s n="s7.7;p6.30">The reduction in the influx of Na+ and Ca <hi rend="sup">2+</hi> results in the hyperpolarization of the plasma membrane, the decrease in cystolic Ca <hi rend="sup">2+</hi> concentration reduces the rate of release of the neurotransmitter: glutamate from the synaptic region (Figure 3). </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0265c-pic.002"><head><hi rend="bold">Figure 2</hi><hi rend="sup">2</hi> : Visual signal transduction. The receptor bound G-protein is activated by that of a single photon which promotes the activation of cGMP Phosphodiesterase, and thus the decrease in cystolic cGMP concentration and therefore the closure of CNG channels.</head></figure><figure id="BAWE_0265c-pic.003"><head><hi rend="bold">Figure 3</hi><hi rend="sup">3</hi> : The response of a rod photoreceptor cell to light. Exposure of the rhodopsin located in the outer segment discs to that of a single photon, activates a G-protein signalling cascade resulting in the closure of membrane bound ion channels. This causes the cell to hyperpolarise and reduce the rate of neural transmitter release from the synaptic region, thus it is this reduced rate of release which infact excites the postsynaptic retinal neurons. </head></figure><figure id="BAWE_0265c-fig.001"><head><hi rend="bold">Figure 4:</hi> Amplification in the light-induced cascade in vertebrate rods. The divergent arrows indicate the steps where amplification occurs <hi rend="sup">3</hi> .</head></figure></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">Amplification</head><p n="p7.30"><s n="s1.4;p7.30">The ability of rod cell to elicit a reliable response to a single photon of light is due to the amplification of the light induced catalytic cascade that it activates (Figure 4). </s><s n="s2.4;p7.30">The cascade needs to be inactivated rapidly enough to allow the cell to respond to changes in light, colour and repetitive stimulation. </s><s n="s3.4;p7.30">This allows humans to perceive continuous motion at nearly 1000 frames per second <hi rend="sup">2</hi>. </s><s n="s4.4;p7.30">Thus every intermediate generated in this amplification cascade also requires an inactivation mechanism to ensure that the photoreceptor cell is returned back to its dark, basal state, ready for signalling again. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">Inactivation of Phototransduction</head><p n="p8.30"><s n="s1.4;p8.30">An outwardly Ca <hi rend="sup">2+</hi> rectify membrane protein continues to take up 4Na+ and expel one Ca <hi rend="sup">2+</hi> and one K+ since it is voltage independent thus causing a low intracellular calcium ion concentration when the voltage gated channels are closed. </s><s n="s2.4;p8.30">The calcium binding protein, recoverin looses its affinity to that of Rhodopsin Kinase, thus activating it. </s><s n="s3.4;p8.30">Rhodopsin Kinase catalyses the phosphorylation of the cytosolic tail of activated rhodopsin on multiple serines, this acts to partially inhibit the ability of rhodopsin to activate transducin this effect is enhanced further by the binding of the inhibitory protein arrestin (Figure 5). </s><s n="s4.4;p8.30">In the hyperpolarised state the cytosolic concentration of calcium is low (resting state: 500nM, depolarised state: 50nM), this stimulates guanylyl cyclase rapidly restoring the concentration of cGMP which in turn activates the reopening of the cGMP-gated channels.3 </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0265c-pic.004"><head><hi rend="bold">Figure 5:</hi> The roles of G-protein linked receptor kinases (GRKs) and arrestins in receptor desensitization.<hi rend="sup">3</hi></head></figure></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined">Olfaction</head><p n="p9.30"><s n="s1.3;p9.30">The human olfactory system is capable of detecting and discriminating approximately 10,000 odors which are structurally diverse and carry information about the environment <hi rend="sup">4</hi>. </s><s n="s2.3;p9.30">Odors must have the capacity to be volatile e.g. the scent of a rose, for the odor must be inhaled to reach that of the main olfactory epithelium located at the top of the nasal cavity. </s><s n="s3.3;p9.30">Volatile molecules can bind to receptors in the nasal cavity eliciting a electrical signal which is transmitted from the axons of the olfactory sensory neurons to second order neurons in the olfactory bulb which in turn project to the olfactory cortex and then to other areas off the brain <hi rend="sup">2</hi>. </s></p><p n="p10.30"><s n="s1.5;p10.30">Odorant recognition creates a ligand bound receptor which activates a G protein (G <hi rend="sub">olf</hi> olfactory specific). </s><s n="s2.5;p10.30">The GαGTP stimulates adenylyl cyclase (ACIII) which converts intracellular ATP to cyclic AMP which binds to the intracellular face of a cyclic nucleotide gated causing a conformational change favouring the open position <hi rend="sup">5</hi>. </s><s n="s3.5;p10.30">Na+ and Ca <hi rend="sup">2+</hi> flow through this open channel, thus depolarising the cell. </s><s n="s4.5;p10.30">An inactive OSN maintains a resting potential of approximately -65mV, if the membrane potential becomes 20mV less negative then the cell reaches a threshold and generates an action potential. </s><s n="s5.5;p10.30">Ca <hi rend="sup">2+</hi> ions play an important amplification mechanism, since they are capable of activating a Cl- Ca2+ dependent ion channel causing the efflux of Cl- (OSN maintains an unusual high intracellular Cl- concentration) this acts to further depolarise the cell therefore adding to the excitatory response magnitude. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0265c-pic.005"><head><hi rend="bold">Figure 6</hi><hi rend="sup">5</hi> : Olfaction signal response and adaptation. The above pathway has been confirmed by the use of mutant mice containing deleted components of the transduction cascade. AC, adenylyl cyclase; CNG channel, cyclic nucleotide-gated channel; PDE, phosphodiesterase; PKA, protein kinase A; ORK, olfactory receptor Kinase; RGS, regulator of G proteins (but here acts on AC); CaBP, calmodulin-binding protein. Green arrows indicate stimulatory pathways; red indicates inhibitory (feedback)</head></figure><div2><head rend="underlined">Adaptation</head><p n="p11.30"><s n="s1.2;p11.30">In the presence of a sustained odour stimulus, adaptation occurs which explains the transient current response generated by the stimulated neuron. </s><s n="s2.2;p11.30">Two forms of adaptation in olfactory neurons have been identified involving Ca <hi rend="sup">2+</hi> and cAMP. </s></p><p n="p12.30"><s n="s1.5;p12.30">During sustained depolarisation of a neuron there is a transient rise in Ca <hi rend="sup">2+</hi> ions which acts on the open CNG channel (probably with calmodulin) to cause a conformational change which decreases its sensitivity to cAMP <hi rend="sup">5</hi>. </s><s n="s2.5;p12.30">Therefore requiring a greater concentration of cAMP, to be generated to elicit the opening of the CNG channel. </s><s n="s3.5;p12.30">This is important for it allows the cells to be sensitive to small changes in concentration therefore allowing greater sensitivity over a wide range of concentrations. </s><s n="s4.5;p12.30">The high transient Ca <hi rend="sup">2+</hi> concentration activates the kinase PKA. PKA can phosphorlate the receptor sending them into their desensitized state directly or by phospharylating and therefore activating putative olfactory receptor kinase (ORK). </s><s n="s5.5;p12.30">PDE is also activated by this high transient Ca <hi rend="sup">2+</hi> concentration which acts on adenylyl cyclase to down regulate its activity, thus decreasing the intracellular concentration of cAMP and therefore stimulation of the cell. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0265c-fig.002"><head><hi rend="bold">Figure 7:</hi> Amplification in the odor induced cascade in OSN. The divergent arrows indicate the steps where amplification occurs.</head></figure></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">Amplification</head><p n="p13.30"><s n="s1.1;p13.30">Human olfaction is capable of detecting low concentrations of odor molecules, due to </s></p><p n="p14.30"><s n="s1.1;p14.30">the process of amplification, which is made capable due to the second messenger cascade of enzymes (Figure 7). </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined">How the Ear Works</head><figure id="BAWE_0265c-pic.006"><head><hi rend="bold">Figure 8:</hi> An electron micrograph of a hair bundle.<hi rend="sup">2</hi></head></figure><p n="p15.30"><s n="s1.7;p15.30">Sound waves enter the ear and are funnelled into a structure with in the inner called the cochlea. </s><s n="s2.7;p15.30">The cochlea is a fluid-filled membranous sac that is coiled like a snail shell <hi rend="sup">2</hi>. </s><s n="s3.7;p15.30">The cochlea contains approximately 16,000 hair cells; from the flattened apical surface of a hair cell protrudes a structure called a hair bundle consisting of a cluster containing 20-300 stereocilia (Figure 8). </s><s n="s4.7;p15.30">Each stereocilia contain an actin cytoskeleton ensheathed by a plasma membrane. </s><s n="s5.7;p15.30">These actin filaments are extensively cross linked by fimbrin to form parallel rows spaced approximately 10nm apart giving rise to either a liquid like order or alternatively one that displays hexagonal symmetry <hi rend="sup">6</hi>. </s><s n="s6.7;p15.30">The stereocilia vary in height across the length of the hair cell so that the increment between successive ranks is constant and they are hexagonally packed. </s><s n="s7.7;p15.30">At the tallest region of this mirror symmetrical bevelled structure a single axonemal cilium referred to as the kinocilium projects with as of yet an undefined function. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0265c-fig.003"><head><hi rend="bold">Figure 92:</hi> Displacement towards the kinocilium causes depolarisation of the cell, deflection in the other direction results in hyperpolarisation</head></figure><p n="p16.30"><s n="s1.4;p16.30">When a hair bundle is deflected in a positive direction, the elastic gating springs transmit the external force to the transduction channels. </s><s n="s2.4;p16.30">The channels open probability depends on the tension in these springs, thus when tension is high channels spend most of their time open. </s><s n="s3.4;p16.30">The open channel admits dominantly K+ but also Ca <hi rend="sup">2+</hi> leading to the depolarisation of the cell (Figure 9) which opens voltage gated calcium channels. </s><s n="s4.4;p16.30">The resultant Ca <hi rend="sup">2+</hi> influx mediates the release of the excitatory afferent transmitter, glutamate and/or another compound that can excite glutamate receptors on the primary afferent neurons <hi rend="sup">7</hi>. </s></p><div2><head rend="underlined">Adaptation</head><p n="p17.30"><s n="s1.4;p17.30">Hair cells respond to sustained stimuli by adapting restoring its sensitivity to threshold deflections, by setting a resting tension in that of the gating springs. </s><s n="s2.4;p17.30">This returns the transduction channel open probability to that of 5%<hi rend="sup">9</hi>. </s><s n="s3.4;p17.30">It has been found that two distinct Ca <hi rend="sup">2+</hi> dependent forms of adaptation operate simultaneously in hair cells. </s><s n="s4.4;p17.30">One of which occurs on a millisecond to sub-millisecond timescale involving the transduction channels directly while the other requires ten to hundreds of milliseconds for completion and is believed to involve an adaptation motor.<hi rend="sup">9</hi> </s></p><p n="p18.30"><s n="s1.2;p18.30">The transduction channels contains one or more Ca <hi rend="sup">2+</hi> binding sites on its cytoplasmic surface, when occupied by Ca <hi rend="sup">2+</hi> ions it induces a molecular rearrangement which favours reclosure of the channel <hi rend="sup">9</hi>. </s><s n="s2.2;p18.30">The high intracellular concentration of Ca <hi rend="sup">2+</hi> activates calcium dependent K+ channels causing an efflux of potassium ions.<hi rend="sup">10</hi> The efflux of the K+ ions hyperpolarises the cell and so closes the voltage gated Ca2+ and the Ca2+ intracellular concentration dissipates (Figure 10). </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0265c-pic.007"><head><hi rend="bold">Figure 1011:</hi> K+ acts to depolarise and repolarize the hair cell, it is capable of doing this since basal and apical surfaces of the hair cell are separated by tight junctions therefore creating two separate ionic environments. The apical end is exposed to K+ rich, Na+ poor endolymph created by the actions of ion channels located in the stria vascularis. The two ionic environments cause a large electrical gradient across the membrane of the stereocilia which acts to drive the K+ ions into the cell even though the intracellular K+ concentration is high. The basal end of the cell is surrounded by a K+ poor Na+ rich fluid, K+ effluxes through Ca2+ activated K+ channels i.e. down the concentration gradient results in the repolarisation of the cell.</head></figure><p n="p19.30"><s n="s1.3;p19.30">Adaptation to a negative stimulus involves re-establishing the tension in the gating spring. </s><s n="s2.3;p19.30">While for a positive deflection it is thought that sufficient elastic energy would be stored in the gating spring so that upon adaptation it would pull down the insertional plaque returning the gating springs to their resting state i.e. a passive system (Figure 11a). </s><s n="s3.3;p19.30">However to re-establish the tension created by a negative stimulus, work must be done and it is hypothesised that a myosin ATPase climbs along actin filaments in the stereocilium and actively resets the tension in the transduction spring <hi rend="sup">8</hi>. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0265c-pic.008"><head><hi rend="bold">Figure 11</hi><hi rend="sup">8</hi> : Hair cell transduction and adaptation. <hi rend="bold">a</hi> At rest transduction channels spend approximately 5% of the time open allowing limited Ca <hi rend="sup">2+</hi> entry. (Middle) positive deflection causes increased tip link tension and increase in the time that transduction channels remain open allowing a greater Ca <hi rend="sup">2+</hi> influx which in turn promotes the closure of transduction channels. (Right) As the transduction channels close they increase the tension in the gating springs which results in the hair bundle being pulled back to its resting position. <hi rend="bold">b</hi> . The resulting slow adaptation in response to a positive deflection. The small circle representing the myosin motor slides down the stereocilium (lower right) allowing the open transduction channels to close. Once the hair bundle has returned to its rest position, the gating spring tension will be low; the intracellular Ca <hi rend="sup">2+</hi> concentration will also be low therefore the motor will climb and re-establish the tension in the gating springs.</head></figure><p n="p20.30"><s n="s1.3;p20.30">During a depolarised state there is an influx of Ca <hi rend="sup">2+</hi> which causes the motor to spend a greater fraction of its time unbound from the actin, resulting in slippage of the insertional plaque and therefore decrease in tip link tension. </s><s n="s2.3;p20.30">As the tension is increased the intracellular Ca <hi rend="sup">2+</hi> concentration decreases therefore the motor spends a greater proportion of its time attached to the actin core, thus climbing the actin filament and the raising of the attached plaque therefore increasing tip link tension (Figure 12). </s><s n="s3.3;p20.30">The plaque climbs until a balance is reached between the motor molecules propensity to ascend and Ca <hi rend="sup">2+</hi> stimulated slippage (Figure 11b)<hi rend="sup">12</hi>. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0265c-pic.009"><head><hi rend="bold">Figure 12</hi><hi rend="sup">11</hi> : (far left) upon a negative displacement the tension in the gating spring decreases allowing the closure of the transduction channels, resulting in a decrease of internal Ca2+ concentration. (Far right) the motor spends a greater proportion of its time attached to the actin filament, thus climbing the actin filament and the raising of the attached plaque (grey squares) therefore increasing tip link tension resulting in ~5% of the transduction channels being open <hi rend="sup">9</hi> .</head></figure></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined">Sense Touch and Heat. </head><figure id="BAWE_0265c-pic.010"><head><hi rend="bold">Figure 13</hi><hi rend="sup">8</hi> : Hypothetical features of a Mechanosensory transduction channel. The channel is opened due to the total change in displacement between that of the intracellular and extracellular structures.</head></figure><p n="p21.30"><s n="s1.7;p21.30">The molecular mechanism with which sensory neurons detect mechanical change or force, are still very poorly understood <hi rend="sup">13</hi>. </s><s n="s2.7;p21.30">However this does not prevent one from forming a general mechanotransduction model based on known facts and that of other similar mechanisms. </s><s n="s3.7;p21.30">As with other sensory mechanism speed and sensitivity in the mechanosensory cells are vital. </s><s n="s4.7;p21.30">Thus any proposed mechanism is unlikely to involve that of a second messenger cascade but rather the direct effect of mechanical force on that of transduction channels. </s><s n="s5.7;p21.30">These channels are likely to detect a deflection of an external structure i.e. skin relative to an internal structure such as the cytoskeleton These transduction channels are a source of stimuli amplification since they allow the rapid entry of a large number of ions e.g. </s><s n="s6.7;p21.30">Na+ Ca <hi rend="sup">2+</hi> and it is thought likely to generate a Na+ dependent action potential. </s><s n="s7.7;p21.30">TRPV4 has been proposed as a suitable channel involved in mechanosensation for it is known to be located in the keratinocyte and that mice deficient of TRPV4 were found to be insensitive to mechanosensation8. </s></p><div2><head rend="underlined">Thermo-sensors</head><p n="p22.30"><s n="s1.5;p22.30">Humans can sense a wide range of temperatures from that of cold to heat, through the interaction of the external environment with that of the skin. </s><s n="s2.5;p22.30">Temperature sensitive transient receptor potential vanilloid (TRPV) ion channels have been identified as the possible ion channels involved in heat sensing. </s><s n="s3.5;p22.30">TRPV1 not only be activated by that of capsaicin but is also by temperatures greater than 43°C, three other TRPV channels: TRPV2, TRPV3 and TPRV4 have also been identified as heat thermosensors <hi rend="sup">14</hi>. </s><s n="s4.5;p22.30">Two other TRP channels: TRPA1 and TRPM8 have been found to be activated by cold stimuli, since both TRPA1 and TRPV2 sense temperatures at either end of the 'comfortable' temperature scale thus it is that they are involved in nociception <hi rend="sup">14</hi>. </s><s n="s5.5;p22.30">The locations of at least three of the thermosensors: TRPV1, TRPV3 and TRPV4 are expressed in skin keratinocytes, suggesting that they act in conjunction with sensory neurons (which have also been found to contain heat activated TRP channels) to aid us to perceive our thermal environment <hi rend="sup">15</hi>. </s></p><p n="p23.30"><s n="s1.4;p23.30">TRPV1 has been shown via single channel openings recording in excised membrane patches expressing it that heat directly gates the channel <hi rend="sup">14</hi>. </s><s n="s2.4;p23.30">For the other mentioned channels this has not of yet conclusively been determined that heat directly gates the channel however it is thought likely <hi rend="sup">14</hi>. </s><s n="s3.4;p23.30">Upon activation by heat TRPV ion channels open allowing the influx ions (non-selective ion channel), TRPV1-4 have all shown relatively high Ca <hi rend="sup">2+</hi> permeability. </s><s n="s4.4;p23.30">The influx in ions is thought to lead to the depolarisation of the cell and generation of an action potential. </s></p><table id="BAWE_0265c-tab.001"><head><hi rend="bold">Table 1</hi><hi rend="sup">16</hi> : Activation temperatures of TRP channels expressed in Humans</head><row><cell/></row></table></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined">Compare and Contrast. </head><p n="p24.30"><s n="s1.1;p24.30">The senses touch, heat, light, sound and smell all occur in specialised cells which show significant specialisation for the sensing of a given stimulus (Table 2). </s></p><table id="BAWE_0265c-tab.002"><head><hi rend="bold">Table 2</hi> : Location and adaptation of the sense cells</head><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p25.30"><s n="s1.4;p25.30">Olfaction and phototransduction both use analogous of the 7TM receptor family attached to G-proteins. </s><s n="s2.4;p25.30">Upon stimulation by the by the appropriate stimulus i.e. odor and photon respectively, the7TM receptor activates the attached G-protein which in turn which regulates cyclic-nucleotide-gated ion channels. </s><s n="s3.4;p25.30">Both utilise different G proteins: Olfaction G <hi rend="sub">olf</hi>, Phototransduction: G <hi rend="sub">t</hi> however the action of both G proteins is mediated by the alpha subunit. </s><s n="s4.4;p25.30">The target of these alpha units is to activate two different target proteins (Table 3). </s></p><table id="BAWE_0265c-tab.003"><head><hi rend="bold">Table 3:</hi> Key points of the G-protein cascade in olfaction and phototransduction</head><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p26.30"><s n="s1.2;p26.30">Both pressure sensing and hearing are examples of mechanosensory transduction for they take mechanical stimuli and convert it into that of an electrical signal which is transmitted to the brain. </s><s n="s2.2;p26.30">Hearing takes sound waves and converts the deflections that they cause on the stereocilia into electrical signals, while pressure sensing takes the direct pressure on the skin to promote the opening on ion channels resulting in the generation of an action potential. </s></p><p n="p27.30"><s n="s1.8;p27.30">The difference in speed of perception between that of G-protein linked senses (olfaction, phototransduction) and that of direct sensing (thermo/pressure sensing and hearing), for it does not utilise cyclic nucleotides or secondary messengers in transduction. </s><s n="s2.8;p27.30">Advantages which stem from this alternative strategy is that the enzymatic cascades that generate the second messengers or cyclic nucleotides e.g. cGMP in phototransduction provides a source of amplification. </s><s n="s3.8;p27.30">By the use of intermediates, feedback is possible to gain control of adaptation e.g. phototransduction Ca <hi rend="sup">2+</hi> acts as a second messenger to deregulate cyclic GMP phosphodiesterase thus promoting the opening of CNG ion channels. </s><s n="s4.8;p27.30">Obviously direct transduction has its own advantages otherwise the hearing mechanism would not be evolutionary favourable and less organism would utilise this mechanism. </s><s n="s5.8;p27.30">Direct transduction allows for great speed (transduction occurs faster than it does in sensory neurons), this feature is utilised to allow humans to hear different frequencies and to enable us to locate sound based on small temporal delays i.e. less than 20µs. </s><s n="s6.8;p27.30">All the named senses utilise ion channels to generate an action potential, ion channels are themselves a source of amplification for they allow the entry of 10 <hi rend="sup">4</hi> ions per second. </s><s n="s7.8;p27.30">The importance of amplification is that it allows the senses to posses their great sensitivity and the ability to generate a reliable response to that of their agonist e.g. </s><s n="s8.8;p27.30">Phototransduction: a rod cell is able to detect one photon. </s></p><p n="p28.30"><s n="s1.2;p28.30">Adaptation in all the sensory cells requires the cell to be 'reset' to that of the unstimulated state. </s><s n="s2.2;p28.30">The adaptation mechanism involved in heat sensing and pressure is unknown, however in olfaction, phototransduction and hearing it is known to be influenced by the presence or absence of Ca <hi rend="sup">2+</hi> (Table 4) </s></p><table id="BAWE_0265c-tab.004"><head><hi rend="bold">Table 4:</hi> Role of Ca <hi rend="sup">2+</hi> in adaptation</head><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p29.30"><s n="s1.3;p29.30">The photoreceptor cells: rod cells exhibit cell hyperpolarisation when activated by a photon, while negative hair displacement in hearing also causes hyperpolarisation it does not lead to a message being transmitted to the brain. </s><s n="s2.3;p29.30">However the hyperpolarisation in a rod cell reduces the rate of transmitter release, which acts to excite the postsynaptic retinal neurons, since the transmitter acts to inhibit them (Figure 3). </s><s n="s3.3;p29.30">While in olfaction, hearing, touch and pressure upon excitement they undergo depolarisation and the generation of an action potential. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined">Concluding Remarks</head><p n="p30.30"><s n="s1.6;p30.30">Olfaction and Phototransduction involve 7TM receptors bound to G-proteins in specialised cells: olfactory sensory neuron, rod cells which undergo signal transduction cascades analogous to each other. </s><s n="s2.6;p30.30">Hearing and thermo/pressure sensing are examples of direct mechanotransduction. </s><s n="s3.6;p30.30">Hearing is known to take place in the specialised cell called hair cells however the cells which are responsible for thermo/pressure sensing remain elusive along with a detailed understanding of their cell signalling mechanisms. </s><s n="s4.6;p30.30">Direct mechanotransduction mechanisms display greater speed in signal transduction as opposed to that of G-protein linked cascades; however they forfeit the amplification that G-protein cascades bring. </s><s n="s5.6;p30.30">Ca <hi rend="sup">2+</hi> has been identified as an important ion involved in the process of adaptation in all the cell signalling mechanisms discussed. </s><s n="s6.6;p30.30">The importance of adaptation can not be stressed enough for it gives us as humans such great sensitivity in our senses. </s></p></div1></body><back><div1 type="bibliography"><head rend="underlined">References</head><p>1. Arshavsky, V.Y., Lamb, T.D., Pugh E.N., (2002) G Proteins and Phototransduction. Annual Review of Physiology, 64, p153-187.</p><p>2. Berg, J.M, Tymoczko J.L., Stryer, L, (2002) Biochemistry. Fifth Edition. W.H.Freeman and Company, p898-919. </p><p>3. Alberts Johnson, Lewis Raff, Roberts Walter, (2002) Molecular Biology of The Cell. Fourth Edition. Garland Science p861-870.</p><p>4. Menini A, Lagostena L, Boccaccio A, (2004) Olfaction: From Odorant Molecules to the Olfactory Cortex. American Physiological Society, 19, p101-104.</p><p>5. Firestein, Stuart (2001) How the Olfactory System Makes Sense of Scents, Nature volume 413, p211-218</p><p>6. Hudspeth A.J., (1989) How the Ear's Works Work, Nature, volume 341, p397-341</p><p>7. Eatock Ruth Anne (2000) Adaptation in Hair cells, Annual Review of Neuroscience volume 23 p285-314</p><p>8. Gillespie Peter G., Walker, Richard G., (2001) Molecular Basis of Mechanosensory Transduction, Nature, volume 413 p194-201</p><p>9. Choe Yung, Magnasco Marcelo O, Hudspeth A.J. (1998) A model for Amplification of Hair-Bundle Motion by Cyclinical Binding of Ca<hi rend="sup">2+</hi> to Mechanoelectrical-transduction Channels. Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences of the United States of America. Volume 95 p15321-15326.</p><p>10. Fettiplace R., Fuchs P.A., (1999) Mechanisms of Hair Cell Tuning. Annual Review of Physiology. Volume 61 p809-834.</p><p>11. Sinauer Associates, Inc (2001) <seg type="URL" n="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/books/bv.fcgi?rid=neurosci.box.949"/> (Accessed 01/12/05)</p><p>12. Hudspeth A.J., Gillespie Peter G. (1994), Pulling Springs to Tune Transduction:Adaptation by hair cells Neuron volume12 p1-9</p><p>13. Lewin Gary R., Moshourab Rabih, (2004) Mechanosensation and Pain. Neurobiology volume 61 p30-44</p><p>14. Tominaga Makoto, Caterina Michael J., (2004) Thermosensation and Pain. Neurobiology volume 61, p3-12</p><p>15. Lee Hyosang, Caterina Michael J, (2005) TRPV Channels as Thermosensory receptors in Epithelial cells. European Journal of Physiology. Volume 451 p160-167.</p><p>16. Clapham David E, (2003) TRP Channels as cellular Sensors. Nature. Volume 426 p517-523.</p></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
