<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_0267a" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>What caused the Wars of Independence?</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">deleted: header: student name, module name and number; footer: page numbers</note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">deleted: Word Count: 2077</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">1</p><p n="date">2005-11</p><p n="module title">Latin American Themes and Problems</p><p n="module code">AM101</p><p n="genre family">Essay</p><p n="discipline">Comparative American Studies</p><p n="disciplinary group">AH</p><p n="grade">D</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">2069</p><p n="number of s-units">42</p><p n="number of p">8</p><p n="number of tables">0</p><p n="number of figures">0</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">0</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">0</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">49.3</p><p n="average s-units per p">5.3</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">m</p><p n="year of birth">1987</p><p n="first language">English</p><p n="education">UKA</p><p n="course">CAS</p><p n="student ID">0267</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><docTitle><titlePart rend="underlined bold">What caused the Wars of Independence? </titlePart></docTitle></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="section"><p n="p1.8"><s n="s1.8;p1.8">What characterises the aerial view of the Wars of Independence is confusion: a sprawling area of uncertainty and strife undergoing great upheaval in a time of revolution and counter-revolution, grand mountain crossings of polyglot armies<ref target="BAWE_0267a-ftnote.001"/> over the impermanent borders of ill-defined fledgling states. </s><s n="s2.8;p1.8">A landscape of general disarray and division between foreign and local, between races and classes and between different social groups with shifting allegiances, political or otherwise, in a war of huge scale and all-encompassing reach, basically a scene of chaos. </s><s n="s3.8;p1.8">What further adds to this confusion is the continued stubborn refusal of Latin American history to fit neatly into anything near a consistent and simultaneous chronology, the different areas reaching independence in their unique ways with individual consequences and in their own sweet time. </s><s n="s4.8;p1.8">The ebb and flow of forces that can be broadly categorised as separatist or royalist results in a back-and-forth struggle that cannot be used as evidence for the ascendancy of momentum or the inevitability of victory for independence, as the example of Cuba, Puerto Rico and the Philippines, under Spain until the 1898 Spanish-American War, testifies. </s><s n="s5.8;p1.8">To extract from this cross-continent jumble some 'principal processes and patterns'<ref target="BAWE_0267a-ftnote.002"/> of the independence period could be a hazardous task where care must be taken not to succumb wholly to indulgent narratives of an awakened nationalism, or detached explanations of economic and social Creole self-interest, and not to slip into a euro-centric focus and understanding of this genuinely American phenomenon. </s><s n="s6.8;p1.8">While the individual paths taken to independence must be constantly remembered as a demonstration of diversity in the region, the fact remains that root causes and processes are similar among all of them, and the key to discerning the pattern in the chaotic mass of conflicting information and issues is realising that it is possible to do too much analysis. </s><s n="s7.8;p1.8">That is, to treat every contradiction as a nullification, to see every exception as a parallel trend of equal importance, in effect, cluttering the facts with sheer information. </s><s n="s8.8;p1.8">This is especially applicable with the non-uniformity and lack of depth that the Wars of Independence seemed to have in their causes, but it needs to be controlled, because independence could occur without the deep roots easily pointed to as causation, it is possible for small groups of dedicated people to radically change history, and that is what is underestimated in the analysis of the Wars of Independence in the face of the slightly unsatisfactory 'heavyweight' factors of nationalism, colonial society and European influence. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0267a-ftnote.001"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Williamson, E., <hi rend="italic">The Penguin History of Latin America</hi>, (London, 1992) p223 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0267a-ftnote.002"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Hamnett, Brian, 'Process and Pattern: A Re-Examination of the Ibero-American Independence Movements, 1808-1826', JLAS, vol. 29:2 (1997) p.279 </s></p></note><p n="p2.8"><s n="s1.6;p2.8">A very credible, if euro-centric, understanding can be reached of the causes of the Wars of Independence as having all to do with events in Paris, Madrid, Cadiz and the rest of the old world. </s><s n="s2.6;p2.8">This can primarily draw from the unavoidable fact that before the Peninsular War and the crises of legitimacy that it provoked, there was little serious prospect for an independent Spanish America. </s><s n="s3.6;p2.8">While Tupac Amaru's campaign was large-scale and threatening, it lacked a definitive objective and must therefore be classed as simply the most significant of the various rebellions under Spanish rule. </s><s n="s4.6;p2.8">With the colonial authority split between the new crown of Joseph I and the Supreme Junta, the cabildo abiertos of the Americas found virtual independence thrust upon them, but still they took time before realising that Royalist reaction was going to rob them of their new-found influence and mobilise to assert their independence. </s><s n="s5.6;p2.8">This combined with the contrast of the relatively peaceful state of Portuguese Brazil which 'shows how much difference the King's presence could make'<ref target="BAWE_0267a-ftnote.003"/> demonstrates the undeniable contribution of European separation and the resultant power vacuum towards the Wars of Independence. </s><s n="s6.6;p2.8">However, to stress the abrupt release of the Spanish grip over Latin America as the principal cause of their revolt is to overestimate the American desire to be free for freedoms sake; the history of the Spanish provinces shows that foreign rule did not have to be ever present to ensure order, as long as a significant portion of the population was content and they did not have expectations for anything better. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0267a-ftnote.003"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Chasteen, John Charles, <hi rend="italic">Born in Blood and Fire: A Concise History of Latin America</hi> (New York, 2002) p.97 </s></p></note><p n="p3.8"><s n="s1.3;p3.8">In that respect it was not simply the Spanish abdication that primarily caused independence, but the combination of the Bourbon reforms that demanded more collectively of the Indies, and also embittered the career-limited Creole to whom 'how irrational his exclusion must have seemed'<ref target="BAWE_0267a-ftnote.004"/>. </s><s n="s2.3;p3.8">This tightening and thereafter enforced loosening of the Spanish fist resulted, as all things do when pressured and given a release, in a burst of energy and frustration, the Creole sense of rejection by his ethnic and cultural brethren prompting a more local search for validity and identity, and of course to supplant the peninsulars as the top rung in the social hierarchy. </s><s n="s3.3;p3.8">This is why in assessing the doubtless huge importance of Europe as a factor in the Wars of Independence, it must go beyond simply charting the events of the independence period as prime movers, but requires 'a broader periodisation' from the second half of the eighteenth century to note the 'significant readjustment of the Atlantic world'<ref target="BAWE_0267a-ftnote.005"/> in the gulf that is created between the Spanish rulers and administrators and their natural allies in oppressing the other classes and races of Latin America. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0267a-ftnote.004"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Anderson, Benedict, <hi rend="italic">Imagined Communities: Reflections on the Origin and Spread of Nationalism</hi>, Verson (London, 1991) p.58 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0267a-ftnote.005"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Hamnett, Brian, 'Process and Pattern: A Re-Examination of the Ibero-American Independence Movements, 1808-1826', JLAS, vol. 29:2 (1997) p.282 </s></p></note><p n="p4.8"><s n="s1.4;p4.8">Since white attitudes and post-independence developments indicate that the majority of Creoles had no interest in revolution for an egalitarian society, they simply wanted a change of leadership, it is ironic that the downtrodden peoples of Latin America were used as the greatest symbol for the Wars which benefited one group of their superiors over another. </s><s n="s2.4;p4.8">In order to create an image all 'Americanos' could fight for, the liberators invoked the spirit of the 'European fantasy of the 'gentle savage' dependent for her salvation on Creole heroism'<ref target="BAWE_0267a-ftnote.006"/>, conveniently or perhaps hypocritically forgetting the Creole descent from the Conquistadors now suddenly despised, 'to turn elsewhere for an alternative myth'<ref target="BAWE_0267a-ftnote.007"/>. </s><s n="s3.4;p4.8">This was necessary, however, because of the unlikelihood of nationalism in the cause of independence: 'people who shared a common language and common descent with those against whom they fought'<ref target="BAWE_0267a-ftnote.008"/> banding together with the groups they had previously exploited daily and leading them in the name of some intangible common background that could not be ethnic, cultural nor political as long as popular sovereignty was delayed and denied. </s><s n="s4.4;p4.8">All they had was a common birthplace, and this formed a devotion to the land that manifested itself in exalted inhabitants of that geography, as in Peru where 'the creoles regarded themselves as the true heirs of the Araucanians'<ref target="BAWE_0267a-ftnote.009"/> and saw that link as a more valid descent that legitimised their cause. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0267a-ftnote.006"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Platt, Tristan, 'Simon Bolivar, the Sun of Justice and the Amerindian Virgin: Andean Conceptions of the Patria in Nineteenth-Century Potosi', <hi rend="italic">JLAS</hi>, vol. 25:1 (1993) p.170 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0267a-ftnote.007"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Chasteen, John Charles, and Joseph Tulchin, eds., <hi rend="italic">Problems in Modern Latin American History</hi> (Wilmington, 1994) p.10 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0267a-ftnote.008"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Anderson, Benedict, <hi rend="italic">Imagined Communities: Reflections on the Origin and Spread of Nationalism</hi>, Verson (London, 1991) p.47 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0267a-ftnote.009"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Anderson, Benedict, <hi rend="italic">Imagined Communities: Reflections on the Origin and Spread of Nationalism</hi>, Verson (London, 1991) p.48 </s></p></note><p n="p5.8"><s n="s1.4;p5.8">In defence of Creole nationalism, that similarity of birthplace can count for a lot in a society where culture and attitudes cannot quite remain impermeable no matter what the social and ethnic divides, and strictly speaking is the same criteria on which most people would base the 'original' nationalism of European nation-states. </s><s n="s2.4;p5.8">Even despite the fact that it is mostly a negative definition where mere rhetoric and finger-pointing 'constructed a simple dichotomy: Americans versus Europeans'<ref target="BAWE_0267a-ftnote.010"/>, that should not diminish its power, negative integration being a powerful tool and one of the easiest to mobilise: <hi rend="italic">they</hi> are the peninsulars, <hi rend="italic">we</hi> are the Chileans/Argentineans/Mexicans etc, and therefore <hi rend="italic">we</hi> must have our nation. </s><s n="s3.4;p5.8">The differing aims of the independence fighters is also a factor that affects the unity, but not the validity of the movement's nationalism, Creoles in the main wanting autonomy and influence while 'Indian...groups looked to Republican legislation to ensure the curtailment of colonial abuses'<ref target="BAWE_0267a-ftnote.011"/>. </s><s n="s4.4;p5.8">What this signifies is that a unified groundswell of support with kindred motives was not necessary so long as the force was concerted in 'a certain project of nationhood pursued by a small Eurocentric elite in the face of a massive ethnic majority with its own ideas about the significance of independence'<ref target="BAWE_0267a-ftnote.012"/>. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0267a-ftnote.010"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Chasteen, John Charles, <hi rend="italic">Born in Blood and Fire: A Concise History of Latin America</hi> (New York, 2002) p.100 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0267a-ftnote.011"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Platt, Tristan, 'Simon Bolivar, the Sun of Justice and the Amerindian Virgin: Andean Conceptions of the Patria in Nineteenth-Century Potosi', <hi rend="italic">JLAS</hi>, vol. 25:1 (1993) p.167 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0267a-ftnote.012"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Platt, Tristan, 'Simon Bolivar, the Sun of Justice and the Amerindian Virgin: Andean Conceptions of the Patria in Nineteenth-Century Potosi', <hi rend="italic">JLAS</hi>, vol. 25:1 (1993) p.166 </s></p></note><p n="p6.8"><s n="s1.9;p6.8">When those differing ideas turn into opposition is where the argument of a progressively unified nationalism sparked by European detachment cannot totally convince. </s><s n="s2.9;p6.8">The large majority of the population that were Indian, African or mixed were not a dependable ethnic bloc, they had no allegiances except to themselves, especially not to the revolutionaries, who they sometimes resented more since 'the Creoles were the masters and overlords who exploited them directly, in daily life'<ref target="BAWE_0267a-ftnote.013"/>. </s><s n="s3.9;p6.8">In turn the Creole landowners, far from trying to encourage a political motive and thereby enlist the sympathies of the lower classes, were afraid of their mobilisation, a fear of revolution and ethnic uprising beyond their limited demands and beyond their control, 'one key factor initially spurring the drive for independence from Madrid'<ref target="BAWE_0267a-ftnote.014"/>. </s><s n="s4.9;p6.8">There was a mutual dislike, racial, social and political in nature, between the classes that prevented wholesale unity, if that was ever likely, and enabled the use of local forces for the purpose of reaction. </s><s n="s5.9;p6.8">Despite appeals to nationalism and liberty, the forces for independence found it hard to keep all the lower classes in their coalition, 'the fact that Chileans of the lower class could fight on the royalist side (as they did in large numbers) as well as on the patriot side shows that patriotic sentiment had not penetrated very far below a certain level of society'<ref target="BAWE_0267a-ftnote.015"/>. </s><s n="s6.9;p6.8">This is another blow to the narrative of a growing national movement that drove out the 'foreigners' in that the Spanish come-back of 1815 and 1816 was partly because 'she won the support of slaves in the former, and of Indians in the latter, in the struggle against insurgent creoles'<ref target="BAWE_0267a-ftnote.016"/>. </s><s n="s7.9;p6.8">This illustrates the gulf between the rungs on the social ladder, but it is also important to note that the Creoles were not a homogenous group all bent on repudiating colonial rule in the spirit of the Enlightenment and towards Republicanism. </s><s n="s8.9;p6.8">The mundane truth is that they were mostly landowners and the privileged, natural conservatives in fact, so 'the French Revolution and the example of Haiti brought home to the white elites of the colonies the value of the Crown as a guarantor of law and order within their own racially divided societies'<ref target="BAWE_0267a-ftnote.017"/>. </s><s n="s9.9;p6.8">It is important to see the independence as much a reaction to threats on the status quo as an adapting of Enlightenment ideas and that conservatism as much as revolution was on the minds even of those who pushed for separation. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0267a-ftnote.013"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Chasteen, John Charles, <hi rend="italic">Born in Blood and Fire: A Concise History of Latin America</hi> (New York, 2002) p.99 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0267a-ftnote.014"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Anderson, Benedict, <hi rend="italic">Imagined Communities: Reflections on the Origin and Spread of Nationalism</hi>, Verson (London, 1991) p.48 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0267a-ftnote.015"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Chasteen, John Charles, and Joseph Tulchin, eds., <hi rend="italic">Problems in Modern Latin American History</hi> (Wilmington, 1994) p.8 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0267a-ftnote.016"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Anderson, Benedict, <hi rend="italic">Imagined Communities: Reflections on the Origin and Spread of Nationalism</hi>, Verson (London, 1991) p.49 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0267a-ftnote.017"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Williamson, E., <hi rend="italic">The Penguin History of Latin America</hi>, (London, 1992) p210 </s></p></note><p n="p7.8"><s n="s1.4;p7.8">That discongruity however, is the problem when analysing the independence movements, there are so many contradictions among what are surely the root causes that it seems as if there is a 'thinness' to the causation that does not convince of their contribution. </s><s n="s2.4;p7.8">What needs to be recognised is that the history of this era in this region was not inevitable and because it could have happened either way so easily (the example of Cuba, Puerto Rico and the Philippines emerges again) then it is legitimate to attribute success to the tip of the iceberg, namely the vanguard of revolutionary success. </s><s n="s3.4;p7.8">At the very pinnacle, Simon Bolivar and Jose de San Martin do embody the nationalistic spirit and were Enlightened gentlemen of Republican and Liberal credentials, and so it is not necessary to demand of the deeper social and political factors a consistent and pro-active evidence to be overwhelmingly causative. </s><s n="s4.4;p7.8">Those factors can be contradictory and disunited, they just need to have some amount of conduciveness for inspired leaders (there should still be room for that sort of person in history) and a dedicated cadre to work from them and produce results. </s></p><p n="p8.8"><s n="s1.4;p8.8">In analysing the causes of the Wars of Independence, it is too easy to get lost in the myriad of different factors and counter-factors to take into account, that focus can be distracted from how the significant difference was made, just because there are other vital contributions to consider also. </s><s n="s2.4;p8.8">Undoubtedly Nationalism, the effect of Colonial rule on society, and the European influence of ideas and events were root causes, indispensable to the necessity of independence, but they were consistent only with the general landscape of confusion and contradiction in the first half of the nineteenth century in Latin America. </s><s n="s3.4;p8.8">What they contributed, without having to be indisputably convincing in their primacy, was the support they gave to those who drove the revolutions and shaped this fledgling and ill-defined world. </s><s n="s4.4;p8.8">Their conducive facets and manifestations provided the elements for the decisive vanguard to lift support from them and push on to give these half-supportive factors the momentum and human inspiration to start and complete the Wars of Independence. </s></p></div1></body><back/></text></TEI.2>
