<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_0277a" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>The fair delivery of high standard health care has been the objective of the National Health Service (NHS) since its establishment in 1948</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">deleted: header: module name and number, department name; footer: page numbers</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">4</p><p n="date">2005-10</p><p n="module title">Health in the Community</p><p n="module code">MD100</p><p n="genre family">Essay</p><p n="discipline">Medicine</p><p n="disciplinary group">LS</p><p n="grade">M</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">2003</p><p n="number of s-units">83</p><p n="number of p">20</p><p n="number of tables">0</p><p n="number of figures">5</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">0</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">0</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">24.1</p><p n="average s-units per p">4.2</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">f</p><p n="year of birth">1982</p><p n="first language">Portuguese</p><p n="education">OSA</p><p n="course">MCchB</p><p n="student ID">0277</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front/><body><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined">Introduction</head><p n="p1.20"><s n="s1.2;p1.20">The fair delivery of high standard health care has been the objective of the National Health Service (NHS) since its establishment in 1948. </s><s n="s2.2;p1.20">However this has proven to be a difficult task and to require a thorough understanding of the complex and variable health needs of different population groups. </s></p><p n="p2.20"><s n="s1.7;p2.20">Health is defined as "a state of complete physical, mental and social well-being and not merely the absence of disease or infirmity". </s><s n="s2.7;p2.20">(1) Therefore, in order to account for the health of the nation, not only the physical maladies have to be prevented and treated, the social determinants of health must also be accounted for. </s><s n="s3.7;p2.20">This dimension poses the greatest challenge as it involves long-term approaches using profound measures designed to impact not only in lifestyles, but also in social and community networks and general socioeconomic and environmental factors such as income, housing, education, safety, access to fresh food, transport, access to health services. </s><s n="s4.7;p2.20">(2) (Figure 1) It thus implies that an equitable health service will be the one shaped to meet the needs of the populations, dynamically changing according to the changing needs of the populations. </s><s n="s5.7;p2.20">Contrastingly, a health care system which is delivered in a way that favours certain groups of people in detriment of others will systematically generate health inequalities amongst such groups. </s><s n="s6.7;p2.20">The differential exposure to socioeconomic factors influencing health prior to birth and across the lifespan will result in socioeconomic health inequalities, and are particularly important in explaining health differences related to gender and ethnicity. </s><s n="s7.7;p2.20">(2) </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0277a-fig.001"><head><hi rend="bold">Figure 1</hi> : The main determinants of health (2)</head></figure></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined">The assessment of health inequalities</head><p n="p3.20"><s n="s1.2;p3.20">Several factors complicate the assessment of the populations' health status. </s><s n="s2.2;p3.20">The definition and measurement of need, availability and utilisation of health care services can present variations which influence the results obtained. </s></p><p n="p4.20"><s n="s1.3;p4.20">It is generally assumed that the needs of individuals integrated in a certain socio-economic group in a specific place will be similar and therefore can be revealed by a representative individual, a concept derived from statistical studies. </s><s n="s2.3;p4.20">(3) However, individuals from the same background may report their maladies in distinctive ways and require different immediate approaches. </s><s n="s3.3;p4.20">(3) </s></p><p n="p5.20"><s n="s1.5;p5.20">Availability of health care may also be different across population groups. </s><s n="s2.5;p5.20">If, in one hand, certain services may not be available in some places, clinicians may tend to offer different treatments to patients from distinct socio-economic groups. </s><s n="s3.5;p5.20">Additionally, the acknowledgment of specific existing health services may be different between such groups. </s><s n="s4.5;p5.20">Lastly, the heath care budget may be distributed unequally across the populations. </s><s n="s5.5;p5.20">(3) </s></p><p n="p6.20"><s n="s1.3;p6.20">Moreover, the measurement of utilisation of health services normally records broad categories such as GP visits or hospital admissions which can be deceiving as a measurement of quality or quantity of health care received, as some may only require administrative work. </s><s n="s2.3;p6.20">In other circumstances, groups which seem to under-utilise some health services may be choosing alternative or private services, which will fall out of most studies and bias the results. </s><s n="s3.3;p6.20">(3) </s></p><p n="p7.20"><s n="s1.4;p7.20">Despite the difficulty in standardising methodologies and conclusions, health inequalities exist, regardless of whether the variables measured are mortality, life expectancy or health status, and independently of falling into socioeconomic, ethnic or gender categories.(2) </s><s n="s2.4;p7.20">The general trends of health show that although mortality has decreased and life expectancy has increased in the last years, healthy life expectancy has actually decreased, which implies that the added years of life involve chronic illness and disability. </s><s n="s3.4;p7.20">(2,4) It is also important to note that even though mortality as a whole has been decreasing, the gap between mortality rates for subjects at the top and bottom of the social scale has increased. </s><s n="s4.4;p7.20">(2,4) (Figure 2) </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0277a-fig.002"><head><hi rend="bold">Figure 2</hi> : The widening mortality gap between the social classes (4)</head></figure></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined">Some explanations for health inequalities</head><p n="p8.20"><s n="s1.1;p8.20">Several theories have been formulated to explain the existence and persistence of health inequalities, three of which stand out as more encompassing explanations: behavioural and cultural, materialist and psychosocial. </s></p><div2><head rend="bold">Behavioural/ cultural </head><p n="p9.20"><s n="s1.7;p9.20">The behavioural theory defends that patterns of lifestyles and health beliefs are present amongst cultural groups. </s><s n="s2.7;p9.20">Inequalities in health thus derive from unhealthy lifestyles of lower social classes in contrast to healthier behaviours assumed by higher social classes, particularly in respect to nutrition, exercise and smoking. </s><s n="s3.7;p9.20">The consumption of a high amount of refined foods along with the reduced ingestion of vegetables and fruit is more prevalent in lower social classes than in their higher counterparts. </s><s n="s4.7;p9.20">They also seem to practice less exercise and to smoke more. </s><s n="s5.7;p9.20">(2,5,6,7) (Figure 3) Moreover, the underutilisation of preventive health care and contraception by subjects in lower social classes has been detected.(6) </s><s n="s6.7;p9.20">The adoption of some of these health behaviours is shaped by lay beliefs of health, as illustrated in a study by Wardle and Steptoe, which reported that individuals from lower social classes tend to believe that good or bad health is due to chance.(7) </s><s n="s7.7;p9.20">The association of unhealthy lifestyles to a certain cultural or social class may lead to culture blaming. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0277a-fig.003"><head><hi rend="bold">Figure 3</hi> : Health behaviour and self rated health (7)</head></figure></div2><div2><head rend="bold">Materialist </head><p n="p10.20"><s n="s1.7;p10.20">The materialist theory of health inequalities defends that individuals from lower social classes have a more limited access to basics such as food and shelter but also to amenities such as the telephone, internet, car and home ownership. </s><s n="s2.7;p10.20">(5) Poor health thus comes as the result of increasing material disadvantage. </s><s n="s3.7;p10.20">(2) This generates a socioeconomic gradient in health. </s><s n="s4.7;p10.20">(5) Figure 4 illustrates the socioeconomic gradient of health, in what concerns to propensity of developing psychoses and drug dependence according to social class. </s><s n="s5.7;p10.20">(7) The tendency to develop such conditions increases as one goes down the social ladder. </s><s n="s6.7;p10.20">It also shows how unemployment can treble the chance of developing psychoses and drug addiction. </s><s n="s7.7;p10.20">(7) </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0277a-fig.004"><head><hi rend="bold">Figure 4</hi> : Prevalence (%) of psychiatric disorders according to social class, with odds ratio of employment status (6)</head></figure><p n="p11.20"><s n="s1.4;p11.20">The association between poverty and inequalities in health is widely discussed in the literature. </s><s n="s2.4;p11.20">There is no doubt that poverty strongly impacts on one's health, however the idea that it can be perceived rather than at an absolute level has to be considered. </s><s n="s3.4;p11.20">In other words, poverty is not only defined by one's income but also by how it compares to the income of others in society. </s><s n="s4.4;p11.20">(5) </s></p><p n="p12.20"><s n="s1.1;p12.20">A variation of this theory is presented by the <hi rend="bold">neo-materialist view</hi>, which interprets health inequalities as the combination of the negative exposures suffered by individuals who have restricted access to resources, with a systematic underinvestment in human, physical, health and social infrastructures.(8) </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">Psychosocial </head><p n="p13.20"><s n="s1.5;p13.20">This theory suggests that the relative position of an individual to others in society according to their income, and the consequent negative emotions and distress that can affect individuals who believe they occupy a low place in the social hierarchy induce poor health through psycho-neuro-endocrine mechanisms. </s><s n="s2.5;p13.20">This perception would motivate 'escape' behaviours such as smoking. </s><s n="s3.5;p13.20">(7-9) </s><s n="s4.5;p13.20">Furthermore, such negative perceptions are revealed externally through antisocial behaviour, reduced civic participation, less social capital and cohesion within the community. </s><s n="s5.5;p13.20">(8) </s></p><p n="p14.20"><s n="s1.7;p14.20">Other theories have attempted to explain health inequalities. </s><s n="s2.7;p14.20">The <hi rend="bold">artefactual theory</hi> which argues that the concept of health inequalities may be the result of an artefact, as concepts such as class and health are variable. </s><s n="s3.7;p14.20">The assessment of social class at time of death would be inaccurate and thus induce a numerator/denominator bias. </s><s n="s4.7;p14.20">Also, the use of different methodologies in the assessment of the population's health status and delivery of care would induce a false concept of inequality. </s><s n="s5.7;p14.20">However, this idea cannot account for the patterns of mortality and morbidity amongst different ethnic and/or social groups. </s><s n="s6.7;p14.20">The <hi rend="bold">social selection</hi> theory argues that healthy workers will move up the social ladder whilst unhealthy ones move down, creating a pool of healthier individuals in higher social classes and of unhealthy ones in the lower social classes. </s><s n="s7.7;p14.20">Nevertheless, the number of socially mobile individuals is thought to be too small to bias the health status of entire social classes. </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined">Tackling health inequalities</head><p n="p15.20"><s n="s1.3;p15.20">The acknowledgement of the existence of health inequalities carries the responsibility to address them. </s><s n="s2.3;p15.20">Since its election, the Labour government has introduced important measures to improve understanding and reduce health inequalities. </s><s n="s3.3;p15.20">In the <hi rend="italic">Tackling health inequalities: a programme for action</hi> document a series of targets were set to impact upon four main areas (supporting families, mothers and children; engaging communities and individuals; preventing illness and providing effective treatment and care; addressing the underlying determinants of health principles), based on five underlying principles (preventing inequalities worsening; working through the mainstream; targeted interventions; support from the centre; delivering at local level) as shown in figure 5.(4) </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0277a-fig.005"><head><hi rend="bold">Figure 5</hi> : Health Inequalities Programme for Action: Themes and Principles (4)</head></figure><p n="p16.20"><s n="s1.3;p16.20">Specific national interventions were also defined concerning life expectancy and infant mortality, including: the reduction of smoking amongst manual social groups; prevention and management of risk factors (poor diet, obesity, physical inactivity and hypertension); improvement of environmental health (quality of housing and reduction of the risk of accidents); targeting over-50s. </s><s n="s2.3;p16.20">Interventions aiming to reduce infant mortality include the improvement of quality and accessibility of antenatal care and early years support in disadvantaged areas; reducing smoking and improving diet during pregnancy and early years (increase numbers of mothers breastfeeding); preventing teenage pregnancy and providing support; improving housing conditions for children in disadvantaged areas. </s><s n="s3.3;p16.20">(4) </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined">The roles of doctors in reducing health inequalities</head><p n="p17.20"><s n="s1.6;p17.20">Health professionals are expected to play a central role in the reduction of health inequalities and in the promotion of health, by lobbying against policies promoting health exclusion and through the provision of services which combat poverty and support/equip families who live in poverty. </s><s n="s2.6;p17.20">(10) </s><s n="s3.6;p17.20">Doctors are expected to hold a good understanding of the causes of poverty and its impact on health. </s><s n="s4.6;p17.20">They should also overcome any putative negative preconceptions or attitudes towards poor patients. </s><s n="s5.6;p17.20">(10) Based on these concepts, three main areas of action have been pointed out as paramount in a doctor's clinical practice: health profiling and monitoring; preventing and alleviating measures; working for social change. </s><s n="s6.6;p17.20">(10) </s></p><p n="p18.20"><s n="s1.3;p18.20">Doctors are expected to be involved in health profiling activities investigating the relationship between poverty and health exclusion, its nature and causes, so that adequate services can be delivered to such individuals. </s><s n="s2.3;p18.20">In addition, the health status of the population must be monitored so that services can be shaped according to need across time. </s><s n="s3.3;p18.20">(10) </s></p><p n="p19.20"><s n="s1.6;p19.20">Doctors have a role to play in the prevention of health exclusion due to poverty and should encourage and implement alleviating measures to reduce health inequalities at two levels: through their potentially strong lobbying influence over the government, working towards social change; in the community, through the identification of specific needs of local populations and individual patients and the mediation with relevant agencies which may be able to supply them with the resources needed.(10) </s><s n="s2.6;p19.20">In order to improve the delivery and accessibility of health care, the facilitation of transport and the introduction of extended surgery hours along with childcare services could be implemented. </s><s n="s3.6;p19.20">This would enable workers and mothers to attend consultations without compromising their professional/family commitments, and would decrease the amount of non-attended GP consultations. </s><s n="s4.6;p19.20">Additionally, some primary care trusts (PCTs) will face social and cultural challenges such as language, which can be reduced with the distribution of leaflets in different languages and the use of interpreters. </s><s n="s5.6;p19.20">Additionally, doctors could ease the financial burden of low income patients by not charging for services such as sick notes and prescribing gym membership, nicotine replacement therapy and counselling. </s><s n="s6.6;p19.20">They could also refer patients to appropriate agencies which can provide advice on how to claim for benefits and how to manage a budget. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined">Conclusion</head><p n="p20.20"><s n="s1.4;p20.20">The existence and persistence of health inequalities is undeniable in our society. </s><s n="s2.4;p20.20">The government has developed an elaborate plan to further assess, understand and tackle health exclusion and has set specific and ambitious targets. </s><s n="s3.4;p20.20">Doctors and other health care professionals are expected to play a central role in this process. </s><s n="s4.4;p20.20">However it is clear that measures beyond the efficient and adequate delivery of health care and health promotion are needed to reduce health inequalities, especially focusing in income and participation in society. </s></p></div1></body><back><div1 type="bibliography"><head rend="underlined">References</head><p>Preamble to the Constitution of the World Health Organization as adopted by the International Health Conference, New York, 19 June - 22 July 1946; Official Records of the World Health Organization, no. 2, p. 100. </p><p>Sir Donald Acheson: Independent Inquiry into inequalities in health report;1997. <seg type="URL" n="http://www.archive.official-documents.co.uk/document/doh/ih/ih.htm"/></p><p>Goddard, M.; Smith, P. (2001): Equity of access to health care services: theory and evidence from the UK; <hi rend="italic">Social Science &amp; Medicine</hi>, 53: 1149-1162.</p><p><hi rend="italic">Tackling health inequalities: a programme for action</hi>; Department of Health; July 2003. Accessed on 20/11/2005: <seg type="URL" n="www.doh.gov.uk/healthinequalities/programmeforaction"/></p><p>Kawachi, I.; Subramanian, S.V.; Almeida-Filho, N. (2002): A glossary for health inequalities; <hi rend="italic">Journal of Epidemiology and Community Health</hi>, 56:647-652.</p><p>Murali, V.; Oyebode, F. (2004): Poverty, social inequality and mental health; <hi rend="italic">Advances in Psychiatric Treatment</hi> 10:216-224.</p><p>Wardle, J.; Steptoe, A. (2003): Socioeconomic differences in attitudes and beliefs about healthy lifestyles; <hi rend="italic">Journal of Epidemiology and Community Health</hi> 57:440-443.</p><p>Lynch, J.W.; Davey Smith, G.; Kaplan, G.A.; House, J.S. (2000): Income inequality and mortality: importance to health of individual income, psychosocial environment, or material conditions; <hi rend="italic">British Medical Journal</hi> 320: 1200-1204.</p><p>Wilkinson, R.G. (1997): Socioeconomic determinants of health: Health inequalities: relative or absolute material standards?; <hi rend="italic">British Medical Journal</hi> 314: 591-595.</p><p>Blackburn, C. (1999): 'Poor health and poor health care: the experiences of low income households with children' <hi rend="italic">in</hi> Purdy, M. and Banks, D. (eds) Health exclusion: policy and practice in health provision. London: Routledge.</p></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
