<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_0278a" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Companies for comparison: Hyundai and Audi</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">The document has a title page which contains:
document title
title part</note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">deleted: header: student number; footer: page numbers</note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">deleted: Total number of Words: 1,847</note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">deleted: Declaration: The work herein submitted for assessment is solely my own and conforms to the guidelines on plagiarism of the University of <name type="university"/>.
</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">1</p><p n="date">2006-01</p><p n="module title">Business Studies II</p><p n="module code">IB3140</p><p n="genre family">Critique</p><p n="discipline">Business</p><p n="disciplinary group">SS</p><p n="grade">M</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">1683</p><p n="number of s-units">62</p><p n="number of p">20</p><p n="number of tables">6</p><p n="number of figures">0</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">2</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">0</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">27.1</p><p n="average s-units per p">3.1</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">f</p><p n="year of birth">1987</p><p n="first language">Korean</p><p n="education">OSA</p><p n="course">Law and Business</p><p n="student ID">0278</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><titlePart>Module Name: Business Studies 2, IB3140</titlePart><docTitle><titlePart>Subject Title: Accounting Companies for comparison: Hyundai and Audi </titlePart></docTitle><titlePart>By: <name type="student name"/> (<name type="student ID"/>)</titlePart></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="section"><p n="p1.20"><s n="s1.2;p1.20">Using Financial Statements of two companies from 2001 to 2004, their financial performance had been compared. </s><s n="s2.2;p1.20">In order to evaluate profitability of two businesses, the following ratios were used. </s></p><list type="ordered"><item>Return on Capital employed. (ROCE)</item><item>Gross Profit Margin </item><item>Net Profit Margin.</item></list><div2><head>Return on Capital employed. (ROCE)</head><table id="BAWE_0278a-tab.001"><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p2.20"><s n="s1.6;p2.20">As a fundamental measure of business performance, this ratio shows how effective a company uses its assets, where inputs and outputs are compared. </s><s n="s2.6;p2.20">It is calculated by Earnings before interest and tax divided by Capital employed expresses in percentage. </s><s n="s3.6;p2.20">Also, this is the same as Return on Assets (ROA) which is Trading profit divided by Assets employed, expressed as percentage. </s><s n="s4.6;p2.20">In this case, Net profit <hi rend="italic">before</hi> interest and taxation are used because the ratio measures the "return to all suppliers of long-term finance before any deductions for interest payable to lenders payments of dividends to shareholders, are made"<ref target="BAWE_0278a-ftnote.001"/>. </s><s n="s5.6;p2.20">Comparison shows that Audi was more successful in handling its assets, where its percentage was almost three times bigger than Hyundai's. </s><s n="s6.6;p2.20">This shows that Audi is more efficient in "utilizing capital to generate revenue"<ref target="BAWE_0278a-ftnote.002"/>. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0278a-ftnote.001"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.6;pn1.1">Mclaney, E and Atrill, P. </s><s n="s2.6;pn1.1">(2005). </s><s rend="italic" n="s3.6;pn1.1">Accounting, An introduction. </s><s n="s4.6;pn1.1">3rd ed. </s><s n="s5.6;pn1.1">Essex: Pearson Education Limited. </s><s n="s6.6;pn1.1">P 214 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0278a-ftnote.002"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.3;pn1.1">Investorwords.<hi rend="italic"> Retrun on Capital employed.</hi> </s><s n="s2.3;pn1.1">[Online]. </s><s n="s3.3;pn1.1">(URL <seg type="URL" n="http://www.investorwords.com/5770/Return_on_Capital_Employed.html"/>) </s></p></note></div2><div2><head>Gross Profit Margin </head><table id="BAWE_0278a-tab.002"><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p3.20"><s n="s1.4;p3.20">Gross profit margin relates the gross profit (Sales revenue minus cost of sales or the cost of goods sold) of the business to the sales revenue generated during that period. </s><s n="s2.4;p3.20">It is calculated by gross profit divided by the sales revenue, expressed in percentage. </s><s n="s3.4;p3.20">Thus, it is a "measure of profitability in buying (producing) and selling goods before any other expenses are taken into account"<ref target="BAWE_0278a-ftnote.003"/>, used as an indication of financial health of the company. </s><s n="s4.4;p3.20">Gross profit margin should be stable since change in this ratio can have a significant impact on Net profit for the year and without adequate gross margin, a company will not be able to "pay its operation and other expenses and build for the future"<ref target="BAWE_0278a-ftnote.004"/>. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0278a-ftnote.003"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.6;pn1.1">Mclaney, E and Atrill, P. </s><s n="s2.6;pn1.1">(2005). </s><s rend="italic" n="s3.6;pn1.1">Accounting, An introduction. </s><s n="s4.6;pn1.1">3rd ed. </s><s n="s5.6;pn1.1">Essex: Pearson Education Limited. </s><s n="s6.6;pn1.1">P 216 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0278a-ftnote.004"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.3;pn1.1">Investopedia <hi rend="italic">.Gross Profit Margin.</hi> </s><s n="s2.3;pn1.1">[Online]. </s><s n="s3.3;pn1.1">(URL <seg type="URL" n="http://www.investopedia.com/university/ratios/grossprofit"/> margin.asp) </s></p></note><p n="p4.20"><s n="s1.2;p4.20">Both Audi and Hyundai show a relatively stable gross profit margin. </s><s n="s2.2;p4.20">However, Hyundai has higher gross profit margin almost by twice showing that it has been having a better net profit than Audi for three consecutive years. </s></p></div2><div2><head>Net Profit Margin</head><table id="BAWE_0278a-tab.003"><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p5.20"><s n="s1.7;p5.20">Net Profit Margin relates Net profit of a particular period to the sales revenue during the same period. </s><s n="s2.7;p5.20">It is calculated by net profit before interest and taxation divided by sales revenue, expressed in percentage. </s><s n="s3.7;p5.20">In this case, net profit <hi rend="italic">before</hi> taxation and interest and taxation are used since, "it represents the profit from trading operations before the interest are taken into account"<ref target="BAWE_0278a-ftnote.005"/>. </s><s n="s4.7;p5.20">This is an appropriate measure of operational performance, since the different business conditions will not influence the measure. </s><s n="s5.7;p5.20">This is used as an indication of how effective a company is at cost control and in general it is regarded "the higher the net profit margin is, the more effective the company is at converting revenue into actual profit"<ref target="BAWE_0278a-ftnote.006"/>. </s><s n="s6.7;p5.20">Even though net profit margin are effected by various factors such as degree of competition, the type of customer, the economic climate and industry characteristics<ref target="BAWE_0278a-ftnote.007"/>, in this case since two companies are in similar sector and size, these factors will have limited influence on comparing net profit margin. </s><s n="s7.7;p5.20">It can be noticed that Audi has been more efficient in converting revenue into actual profit for three consecutive years, even though Hyundai is slowly catching up. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0278a-ftnote.005"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.6;pn1.1">Mclaney, E and Atrill, P. </s><s n="s2.6;pn1.1">(2005). </s><s rend="italic" n="s3.6;pn1.1">Accounting, An introduction. </s><s n="s4.6;pn1.1">3rd ed. </s><s n="s5.6;pn1.1">Essex: Pearson Education Limited. </s><s n="s6.6;pn1.1">P 215 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0278a-ftnote.006"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.3;pn1.1">Investorwords.<hi rend="italic"> Net Profit Margin.</hi> </s><s n="s2.3;pn1.1">[Online]. </s><s n="s3.3;pn1.1">(URL <seg type="URL" n="http://www.investorwords.com/3260/net_profit_margin.html"/>) </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0278a-ftnote.007"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.6;pn1.1">Mclaney, E and Atrill, P. </s><s n="s2.6;pn1.1">(2005). </s><s rend="italic" n="s3.6;pn1.1">Accounting, An introduction. </s><s n="s4.6;pn1.1">3rd ed. </s><s n="s5.6;pn1.1">Essex: Pearson Education Limited. </s><s n="s6.6;pn1.1">P 215 </s></p></note><p n="p6.20"><s n="s1.1;p6.20">In order to evaluate the ability of the business to meet its short-term financial obligations, the following ratios are used; </s></p><list type="ordered"><item>Current ratios</item><item>Cash generated from operations to measuring obligations. </item></list></div2><div2><head>1. Current ratios.</head><table id="BAWE_0278a-tab.004"><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p7.20"><s n="s1.1;p7.20">Current ratio relates current assets with current liabilities (Current ration divided by current liabilities) and provides an idea as to "efficiency of the company's operating cycle"<ref target="BAWE_0278a-ftnote.008"/>. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0278a-ftnote.008"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.3;pn1.1">Investopedia <hi rend="italic">.Current ratio.</hi> </s><s n="s2.3;pn1.1">[Online]. </s><s n="s3.3;pn1.1">(URL <seg type="URL" n="http://www.investopedia.com/terms/currentratio.asp"/>) </s></p></note><p n="p8.20"><s n="s1.2;p8.20">Different types of business requires different current ratios but in general the ideal current ratio is regarded to be 2:1, where higher the current ratio is, the more capable the company is at paying their obligations. </s><s n="s2.2;p8.20">Even though Hyundai's ratio is increasing throughout the year, they are all under one, meaning it is less capable in paying their short-term obligations. </s></p></div2><div2><head>2. Cash generated from operations to measuring obligations. </head><table id="BAWE_0278a-tab.005"><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p9.20"><s n="s1.3;p9.20">Cash generated from operations to measuring obligations, relates cash generated from operations to current liabilities (cash generated from operations divided by current liabilities), used as "further indication of the ability of the business to meet its maturing obligations"<ref target="BAWE_0278a-ftnote.009"/>. </s><s n="s2.3;p9.20">Same as Current ratio, higher the ration is, the better liquidity of the company is. </s><s n="s3.3;p9.20">However, it is used as more "reliable guide to the liquidity of a business than the current assets held at the balance sheet date"<ref target="BAWE_0278a-ftnote.010"/>. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0278a-ftnote.009"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.5;pn1.1">Mclaney, E and Atrill, P. </s><s n="s2.5;pn1.1">(2005). </s><s rend="italic" n="s3.5;pn1.1">Accounting, An introduction. </s><s n="s4.5;pn1.1">3rd ed. </s><s n="s5.5;pn1.1">Essex: Pearson Education Limited. p 226 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0278a-ftnote.010"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">ibid </s></p></note><p n="p10.20"><s n="s1.5;p10.20">Audi still has higher ratio meaning it is more capable of meeting maturing obligations. </s><s n="s2.5;p10.20">From 2003, Hyundai indicates an alarming decline in the ratio, showing liquidity is a real cause of problem for the business. </s><s n="s3.5;p10.20">Even though it is not really possible to make a valid judgment without knowing planned ratio, the alarming ratio obviously shows that the ability of the company to "generate cash from trading operations has declined, relative to the short-tem debts"<ref target="BAWE_0278a-ftnote.011"/> from 2001 to 2004. </s><s n="s4.5;p10.20">However, this could also be a short-term, linked to the "expansion in non-current assets and staffing"<ref target="BAWE_0278a-ftnote.012"/>, where when the benefits of the expansion become stable, liquidity will improve. </s><s n="s5.5;p10.20">Thus, Hyundai must take necessary steps to improve the liquidity, since it can give a concern for short-term creditors, where they could press for payment. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0278a-ftnote.011"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.5;pn1.1">Mclaney, E and Atrill, P. </s><s n="s2.5;pn1.1">(2005). </s><s rend="italic" n="s3.5;pn1.1">Accounting, An introduction. </s><s n="s4.5;pn1.1">3rd ed. </s><s n="s5.5;pn1.1">Essex: Pearson Education Limited. p 227 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0278a-ftnote.012"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">ibid </s></p></note></div2><div2><head>Gearing ratio</head><table id="BAWE_0278a-tab.006"><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p11.20"><s n="s1.2;p11.20">Gearing is an important factor in assessing the risk, where it measures the extent to "which company is financed from sources that require a fixed return"<ref target="BAWE_0278a-ftnote.013"/>. </s><s n="s2.2;p11.20">It measures "the contribution of long term lenders to the long-term capital structure of a business"<ref target="BAWE_0278a-ftnote.014"/>. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0278a-ftnote.013"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.6;pn1.1">Mclaney, E and Atrill, P. </s><s n="s2.6;pn1.1">(2005). </s><s rend="italic" n="s3.6;pn1.1">Accounting, An introduction. </s><s n="s4.6;pn1.1">3rd ed. </s><s n="s5.6;pn1.1">Essex: Pearson Education Limited. </s><s n="s6.6;pn1.1">P 227 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0278a-ftnote.014"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">ibid. p 230 </s></p></note><p n="p12.20"><s n="s1.4;p12.20">A company with high gearing is considered to be risky and vulnerable to downturns in the business cycle since it takes on a "commitment to pay interest charges and make capital repayments"<ref target="BAWE_0278a-ftnote.015"/>. </s><s n="s2.4;p12.20">In 2001 and 2002, Hyundai had higher gearing ratio, which was opposite in 2003 and 2004. </s><s n="s3.4;p12.20">Audi's gearing ratio shows an increase from 2001 to 2004 in contrast to Hyundai's, meaning it is becoming less financed by the owners (shareholders), which could be due to an increase in the long-term loan. </s><s n="s4.4;p12.20">Also, it must be remembered that larger businesses tend to have higher gearing ratio since it attracts interest of investors. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0278a-ftnote.015"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">ibid. p 227 </s></p></note><p n="p13.20"><s n="s1.4;p13.20">However, this ratio analysis does have some limitations. </s><s n="s2.4;p13.20">For example, since balance sheet is a snapshot of the business at a particular time, some ratios that that are based on balance sheet data (liquidity ratio) may not be an appropriate representative of the financial position of the business for the year as a whole. </s><s n="s3.4;p13.20">Moreover, even though similar companies are compared, no two businesses will be identical, and "the greater the difference between the businesses being compared, the great the limitations of ratio analysis"<ref target="BAWE_0278a-ftnote.016"/>. </s><s n="s4.4;p13.20">Differences can arise from various factors, such as accounting policies, financing methods and financial year-ends<ref target="BAWE_0278a-ftnote.017"/>. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0278a-ftnote.016"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.6;pn1.1">Mclaney, E and Atrill, P. </s><s n="s2.6;pn1.1">(2005). </s><s rend="italic" n="s3.6;pn1.1">Accounting, An introduction. </s><s n="s4.6;pn1.1">3rd ed. </s><s n="s5.6;pn1.1">Essex: Pearson Education Limited. </s><s n="s6.6;pn1.1">P 248 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0278a-ftnote.017"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">ibid </s></p></note><p n="p14.20"><s n="s1.1;p14.20">As mentioned before, it will be almost impossible to make a valid judgment without knowing planned ratio where each ratio depends on the size of the company, economic activity of the company and past history of the company. </s></p><p n="p15.20"><s n="s1.2;p15.20">However, from comparing various rations, it seems that Audi has been more successful from 2001 to 2004. </s><s n="s2.2;p15.20">In general, it is more capable of producing profit, and handling its short-term obligations, where both companies are similarly financed from sources that require a fixed return. </s></p><p n="p16.20"><s n="s1.8;p16.20">One of the main reasons for Audi's success is its ability to maintain its brandship with a high goal, where they invest heavily in developing additional attractive models and also raising their brand as a premium brand that match exclusive image of Mercedes-Benz and BMW. Also, Audi has an effective marketing strategy, which contributes to increase in sales. </s><s n="s2.8;p16.20">For example, the company understands that customers want more exclusive cars with a more extensive equipment specification, which allowed the company to raise its sales<ref target="BAWE_0278a-ftnote.018"/>. </s><s n="s3.8;p16.20">Also, in 2002 Audi showed a big improvement in various financial results as a result of the "reduced expense for the compounding of long-term provisions thanks to lower capital market interest rate"<ref target="BAWE_0278a-ftnote.019"/>. </s><s n="s4.8;p16.20">For example, net profit rose to EUR 774 million, which was the highest-ever level in the company's history<ref target="BAWE_0278a-ftnote.020"/>. </s><s n="s5.8;p16.20">From 2003, Audi implemented a risk management system, as obliged by the German corporate governance legislation in order to ensure that "risks which could pose a threat to the company's survival are identified at an early stage"<ref target="BAWE_0278a-ftnote.021"/>. </s><s n="s6.8;p16.20">It takes into account the risks of all corporate divisions and all major subsidiaries of the group. </s><s n="s7.8;p16.20">Also, a similar process is done for liquidity risks. </s><s n="s8.8;p16.20">Thus, more efficient management system to limit the risk is also shown by the Cash generated from operations to measuring obligations ratio, where Hyundai showed an alarming decline in 2003 and 2004, its ration as low as 0.07 and 0.00631. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0278a-ftnote.018"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.4;pn1.1">Businessweek.<hi rend="italic">Hot Audi, It's finally blasting into the luxuiry-car pack.</hi> </s><s rend="italic" n="s2.4;pn1.1">Can it stay there?. </s><s n="s3.4;pn1.1">[Online]. </s><s n="s4.4;pn1.1">(URL <seg type="URL" n="http://www.businessweek.com/magazine/content/05_11/b3924003.htm"/>) </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0278a-ftnote.019"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.3;pn1.1">Audi:Annual report.<hi rend="italic"> Financial Performance 2002.</hi> </s><s n="s2.3;pn1.1">[Online]. </s><s n="s3.3;pn1.1">(URL <seg type="URL" n="http://www.audi.com/audi/com/en1/company/financial_information.html"/>) </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0278a-ftnote.020"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.3;pn1.1">Audi:Annual report.<hi rend="italic"> Financial Performance 2002.</hi> </s><s n="s2.3;pn1.1">[Online]. </s><s n="s3.3;pn1.1">(URL <seg type="URL" n="http://www.audi.com/audi/com/en1/company/financial_information.html"/>) </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0278a-ftnote.021"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.3;pn1.1">Audi:Annual report.<hi rend="italic"> Financial Performance 2003.</hi> </s><s n="s2.3;pn1.1">[Online]. </s><s n="s3.3;pn1.1">(URL <seg type="URL" n="http://www.audi.com/audi/com/en1/company/financial_information.html"/>) </s></p></note><p n="p17.20"><s n="s1.2;p17.20">Moreover, Audi has better engineering system, setting industry benchmarks in everything from "lightweight aluminum frames, drive systems, and engine performance to the soft skin materials covering plastic parts that give Audi's interiors a richer feel"<ref target="BAWE_0278a-ftnote.022"/>. </s><s n="s2.2;p17.20">This adds to the customer satisfaction, which again contributed again to the raise in sales. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0278a-ftnote.022"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.4;pn1.1">Businessweek.<hi rend="italic">Hot Audi, It's finally blasting into the luxuiry-car pack.</hi> </s><s rend="italic" n="s2.4;pn1.1">Can it stay there?. </s><s n="s3.4;pn1.1">[Online]. </s><s n="s4.4;pn1.1">(URL <seg type="URL" n="http://www.businessweek.com/magazine/content/05_11/b3924003.htm"/>) </s></p></note><p n="p18.20"><s n="s1.1;p18.20">Thus, Audi's growth and profits are major importance to Volkswagen, where "in 2004 the average operating profit per car at Audi was $1374 while Volkswagen brand cars, suffering from high costs, model mistakes, and an aging fleet, lost an average $13 per vehicle, according to estimates by Paris-based brokerage Exane"<ref target="BAWE_0278a-ftnote.023"/>. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0278a-ftnote.023"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.3;pn1.1">Audi:Annual report.<hi rend="italic"> Financial Performance 2004.</hi> </s><s n="s2.3;pn1.1">[Online]. </s><s n="s3.3;pn1.1">(URL <seg type="URL" n="http://www.audi.com/audi/com/en1/company/financial_information.html"/>) </s></p></note><p n="p19.20"><s n="s1.2;p19.20">However, the rate of growth in Western Europe is slightly falling, where "exports will moreover hindered by the continuing strength of the euro"<ref target="BAWE_0278a-ftnote.024"/>. </s><s n="s2.2;p19.20">Also, Audi needs improve "reliability over the long haul, where it is 2 <hi rend="sup">nd</hi> in Power's 2004 ranking of long-term dependability "<ref target="BAWE_0278a-ftnote.025"/>. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0278a-ftnote.024"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.3;pn1.1">Audi:Annual report.<hi rend="italic"> Financial Performance 2004.</hi> </s><s n="s2.3;pn1.1">[Online]. </s><s n="s3.3;pn1.1">(URL <seg type="URL" n="http://www.audi.com/audi/com/en1/company/financial_information.html"/>) </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0278a-ftnote.025"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.4;pn1.1">Businessweek.<hi rend="italic">Hot Audi, It's finally blasting into the luxuiry-car pack.</hi> </s><s rend="italic" n="s2.4;pn1.1">Can it stay there?. </s><s n="s3.4;pn1.1">[Online]. </s><s n="s4.4;pn1.1">(URL <seg type="URL" n="http://www.businessweek.com/magazine/content/05_11/b3924003.htm"/>) </s></p></note><p n="p20.20"><s n="s1.3;p20.20">Even though Audi has been more successful that Hyundai for three years, Hyundai is rapidly catching up the standard of Audi, where with its "compounded annual revenue growth of 20% over the past five years, Hyundai has been the <hi rend="italic">world's</hi> fastest-growing major automaker since 1999"<ref target="BAWE_0278a-ftnote.026"/>. </s><s n="s2.3;p20.20">Hyundai is focusing on the market growth in Asia, especially Japanese motorcars, where they ensure that "Hyundai is competitive with Japanese benchmarks in technology and styling"<ref target="BAWE_0278a-ftnote.027"/>. </s><s n="s3.3;p20.20">However, it seems that they need to improve their risk management system that is more organized as Audi's mainly in order to provide more confidence to their short-term creditors. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0278a-ftnote.026"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.3;pn1.1">Time,Asia. </s><s n="s2.3;pn1.1"><hi rend="italic">Global Business</hi>. [Online]. </s><s n="s3.3;pn1.1">(URL <seg type="URL" n="http://www.time.com/time/asia/magazine/article/0,13673,501050425-1050380-2,00.html"/>) </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0278a-ftnote.027"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.3;pn1.1">Time,Asia. </s><s n="s2.3;pn1.1"><hi rend="italic">Global Business</hi>. [Online]. </s><s n="s3.3;pn1.1">(URL <seg type="URL" n="http://www.time.com/time/asia/magazine/article/0,13673,501050425-1050380-2,00.html"/>) </s></p></note></div2></div1></body><back><div1 type="bibliography"><head rend="bold">Bibliography</head><div2 type="bibliography"><head rend="bold">Book</head><p>Mclaney, E and Atrill, P. (2005). <hi rend="italic">Accounting, An introduction.</hi> 3<hi rend="sup">rd</hi> ed. Essex: Pearson Education Limited.</p></div2><div2 type="bibliography"><head rend="bold">Websites</head><p rend="bold">Audi Financial statements.</p><p><seg type="URL" n="http://www.audi.com/audi/com/en1/company/financial_information.html"/></p><p rend="bold">Hyundai Financial Statements.</p><p><seg type="URL" n="http://ir.hyundai-motor.com/eng/index.html"/></p><p>Businessweek.<hi rend="italic">Hot Audi, It's finally blasting into the luxuiry-car pack. Can it stay there?.</hi> [Online]. (URL <seg type="URL" n="http://www.businessweek.com/magazine/content/05_11/b3924003.htm"/>) (accessed on 18<hi rend="sup">th</hi> of December 2005)</p><p>Investorwords.<hi rend="italic"> Retrun on Capital employed..</hi> [Online]. (URL <seg type="URL" n="http://www.investorwords.com/5770/Return_on_Capital_Employed.html"/>) (accessed on 18<hi rend="sup">th</hi> of December 2005)</p><p>Investopedia<hi rend="italic">.Gross Profit Margin.</hi> [Online]. (URL <seg type="URL" n="http://www.investopedia.com/university/ratios/grossprofit"/> margin.asp) (accessed on 20th of December 2005)</p><p>Investorwords.<hi rend="italic"> Net Profit Margin.</hi> [Online]. (URL <seg type="URL" n="http://www.investorwords.com/3260/net_profit_margin.html"/>) (accessed on 25<hi rend="sup">th</hi> of December 2005)</p><p>Investopedia<hi rend="italic">.Current ratio.</hi> [Online]. (URL <seg type="URL" n="http://www.investopedia.com/terms/currentratio.asp"/>) (accessed on 27<hi rend="sup">th</hi> of December 2005)</p><p>Time,Asia. <hi rend="italic">Global Business</hi>. [Online]. (URL <seg type="URL" n="http://www.time.com/time/asia/magazine/article/0,13673,501050425-1050380-2,00.html"/>) (accessed on 12<hi rend="sup">th</hi> of December 2005)</p></div2></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
