<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_0278c" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Levi Strauss &amp; Co</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">The document has a title page which contains:
document title
title part</note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">deleted: header: student number; footer: page numbers</note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">deleted: Total number of Words: 1437</note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">deleted: Declaration: The work herein submitted for assessment is solely my own and conforms to the guidelines on plagiarism of the University of <name type="university"/>.
</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">1</p><p n="date">2005-12</p><p n="module title">Business Studies II</p><p n="module code">IB3140</p><p n="genre family">Explanation</p><p n="discipline">Business</p><p n="disciplinary group">SS</p><p n="grade">D</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">1420</p><p n="number of s-units">47</p><p n="number of p">11</p><p n="number of tables">0</p><p n="number of figures">0</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">0</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">0</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">30.2</p><p n="average s-units per p">4.3</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">f</p><p n="year of birth">1987</p><p n="first language">Korean</p><p n="education">OSA</p><p n="course">Law and Business</p><p n="student ID">0278</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><docTitle><titlePart>Module Name: Business Studies 2, IB3140 Subject Title: Marketing Organization: Levi Strauss &amp; Co Product: 501 ® Original Jeans (Misses)</titlePart></docTitle><titlePart>By: <name type="student name"/> (<name type="student ID"/>)</titlePart></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="section"><p n="p1.11"><s n="s1.5;p1.11">Levi Strauss &amp; Co, which was "founded in 1853 by Bavarian immigrant Levi Strauss"<ref target="BAWE_0278c-ftnote.001"/> is "one of the world's largest brand-name apparel marketers with sales in more than 100 countries"<ref target="BAWE_0278c-ftnote.002"/>. </s><s n="s2.5;p1.11">Its success is such that there is no other company "with a comparable global presence in the jeans and casual pants markets"<ref target="BAWE_0278c-ftnote.003"/>. </s><s n="s3.5;p1.11">The trademark, Levi's® and their very first product, 501 ® Original Jeans are well recognized around the world and is registered in more than 160 countries with its headquarters in North America, Europe and in Asia. </s><s n="s4.5;p1.11">As stated by Peter Drucker, "The purpose of a business is to create a satisfied customer"; in order to suceed in today's competitive marketplace the company must be customer-orientated, where they must be able to successfully recognize the needs and wants of the customers. </s><s n="s5.5;p1.11">The Levi Strauss &amp; Co managed to establish high standard customer value with long term customer relationship where they were effetive in using various marketing strategies. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0278c-ftnote.001"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.5;pn1.1">Vrontis, D. and Vronti,P. </s><s n="s2.5;pn1.1">(2004). </s><s n="s3.5;pn1.1">Levi Strauss: an international marketing investigation. </s><s rend="italic" n="s4.5;pn1.1">Journal of Fashion Marketing and Management. </s><s n="s5.5;pn1.1">vol 8 (4). p389 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0278c-ftnote.002"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">ibid. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0278c-ftnote.003"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">ibid. </s></p></note><p n="p2.11"><s n="s1.4;p2.11">The most succesful marketing strategy the Levi Strauss &amp; Co have adaopted would be promotion, the main factor which allowed the Levi Strauss &amp; Co to maintain its Brand leadership. </s><s n="s2.4;p2.11">Levi Strauss &amp; Co has a high promotion spending, especially on TV commercials, which are considered to be the main contributor in advertsement strategy. </s><s n="s3.4;p2.11">For example, the company put £5 million on an iconic TV advertisement showing "a group of young people twisting and contorting their limbs into strange positions"<ref target="BAWE_0278c-ftnote.004"/>, which led to a rise in the market share from 10.6% in 1999 to 11.1% in 2000. </s><s n="s4.4;p2.11">The dominant role, which TV played was that it allowed 501 ® Original Jeans to establish and maintain its brand leadership by shaping up the consumer perception. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0278c-ftnote.004"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">ibid. </s></p></note><p n="p3.11"><s n="s1.2;p3.11">Consumer perception is greatly influenced by branding and successful brand must be able to create "feeling of confidence that brand is of higher quality or more desirable than similar products from competitors"<ref target="BAWE_0278c-ftnote.005"/>. </s><s n="s2.2;p3.11">Once this brand leadership is reached, people are willing to pay higher price for it even though the other competitors offer a better deal. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0278c-ftnote.005"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.5;pn1.1">Doyle, P. </s><s n="s2.5;pn1.1">(2002). </s><s rend="italic" n="s3.5;pn1.1">Marketing Management and Strategy. </s><s n="s4.5;pn1.1">2nd ed. </s><s n="s5.5;pn1.1">University of Warwick: FT Prentice Hall. p158 </s></p></note><p n="p4.11"><s n="s1.4;p4.11">Once the Levi's® established its brand, the price of 501 ® Original Jeans became inelastic, where even though the price increased the demand fell only slightly since high price signified high quality. </s><s n="s2.4;p4.11">Also, as a leading brand, Levi's® worked to sustain its brand image successfully. </s><s n="s3.4;p4.11">For example it did not allow Tesco from selling 501 ® Original Jeans since it undermines its brand image. </s><s n="s4.4;p4.11">Instead, Levi Strauss &amp; Co introduced discounts Jeans with a brand called Signature, which is sold in Wal-Mart Store in America. </s></p><p n="p5.11"><s n="s1.2;p5.11">The fact that the Levi Strauss &amp; Co is able to establish and sustain its brand leadership and maintain high profit from selling 501 ® Original Jeans is also due to its successful tactics against the competitors by constantly "comparing its products, prices, channels of distribution and promotional methods"<ref target="BAWE_0278c-ftnote.006"/> to identify areas where it can gain a competitive advantage. </s><s n="s2.2;p5.11">Levi's® is a market challenger and these are the main areas, which allowed the 501 ® Original Jeans to achieve a competitive advantage over the competitors. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0278c-ftnote.006"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.5;pn1.1">Proctor, T. </s><s n="s2.5;pn1.1">(1992). </s><s rend="italic" n="s3.5;pn1.1">Essential Marketing. </s><s n="s4.5;pn1.1">1st ed. </s><s n="s5.5;pn1.1">London: Collins Educational Ltd. p 82 </s></p></note><div2><head>Strengthening value advantage by promotion.</head><p n="p6.11"><s n="s1.4;p6.11">Lees Jeans is one of the main rivals of the Levi's®, where both of them are associated with American west, designed and priced similarly. </s><s n="s2.4;p6.11">However, Levi's® has a higher market share, where perception of Levis being more "powerful and vivid"<ref target="BAWE_0278c-ftnote.007"/> led the consumers to choose Levi's® over Lees Jeans, especially teenagers and young adults, the main targets of the Levi's®. </s><s n="s3.4;p6.11">However, it could be stated that the advertisements are too iconic, where it only targets teenagers and young adults. </s><s n="s4.4;p6.11">Since signature is introduced in Wal-Mart, a common supermarket, advertisement would need to appeal to a broader base including people in their 30s and even 40s. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0278c-ftnote.007"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.6;pn1.1">Financial Times. </s><s n="s2.6;pn1.1">(1999). </s><s n="s3.6;pn1.1"><hi rend="italic">Mastering Marketing</hi>. </s><s rend="italic" n="s4.6;pn1.1">Complete MBA companion in Marketing. </s><s n="s5.6;pn1.1">1st ed. </s><s n="s6.6;pn1.1">London: Prentice Hall. p 8 </s></p></note></div2><div2><head>More focus on customer value. </head><p n="p7.11"><s n="s1.6;p7.11">As Levi Strauss and Co have stated in their mission statement, under empathy (one of the main four core values the Levi's uphold), they focus on analyzing consumer needs and wants; "Understanding and appreciating needs - consumer insight - is central to our commercial success"<ref target="BAWE_0278c-ftnote.008"/>. </s><s n="s2.6;p7.11">An example of Levi's® focusing on the customer value is one to one marketing, where Levi's introduced personal pair system to design 501 ® Original Jeans according to individual customer's measurements. </s><s n="s3.6;p7.11">They use what is called, "the 'Original Spin' program, an in-store computerized kiosk to let the consumer select between specific models, fabric, leg openings, buttons and colors. </s><s n="s4.6;p7.11">Then a sales associate measures length and waist size"<ref target="BAWE_0278c-ftnote.009"/>. </s><s n="s5.6;p7.11">When this personal pair system was introduced, there was 38 percent repurchase rate, where there was an increase of 16 percent. </s><s n="s6.6;p7.11">Also, "they have expanded their made-to-order jeans from 10,000 different sizes for women, to 1.5 million customized styles for both sexes." <ref target="BAWE_0278c-ftnote.010"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0278c-ftnote.008"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.3;pn1.1">Levi Strauss and Co.<hi rend="italic">About LS&amp;CO. / Values and vision.</hi> </s><s n="s2.3;pn1.1">[Online]. </s><s n="s3.3;pn1.1">(URL <seg type="URL" n="http://www.levistrauss.com/about/vision/"/>) </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0278c-ftnote.009"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.4;pn1.1">Zeiger,D. (1999). </s><s n="s2.4;pn1.1">Customization nation. </s><s rend="italic" n="s3.4;pn1.1">Incentive. </s><s n="s4.4;pn1.1"><hi rend="bold">Vol 173</hi> (5). p35 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0278c-ftnote.010"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">ibid </s></p></note></div2><div2><head>Brand Stretchability</head><p n="p8.11"><s n="s1.6;p8.11">Levi's® did attempt to extend its brand by selling men suits under its name but it failed dramatically since Denim was perceived as "informal, denim association "<ref target="BAWE_0278c-ftnote.011"/>. </s><s n="s2.6;p8.11">This is also a failure in perceiving market opportunities where they failed to recognize the benefits consumers look for from the products. </s><s n="s3.6;p8.11">However, Levi's introduced Docker®, a very successful brand where for example, "Dockers® Khakis quickly became the No. </s><s n="s4.6;p8.11">1 khaki pant brand in the United States and still holds that leadership status today"<ref target="BAWE_0278c-ftnote.012"/>. </s><s n="s5.6;p8.11">Also, in march 2005, Levi's® entered into "a licensing relationship with GMI Europe to manufacture and sell men's and women's lifestyle footwear under the Levi's® brand name in the U.S., Canada and Latin America"<ref target="BAWE_0278c-ftnote.013"/>, which was based on the consumer appeal of the Levi's® brand footwear in Asia. </s><s n="s6.6;p8.11">However, there is always a risk of stretching its brand too much, where it might lose its core market and objective, which is producing fashionable and quality denim. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0278c-ftnote.011"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.5;pn1.1">Doyle, P. </s><s n="s2.5;pn1.1">(2002). </s><s rend="italic" n="s3.5;pn1.1">Marketing Management and Strategy. </s><s n="s4.5;pn1.1">2nd ed. </s><s n="s5.5;pn1.1">University of Warwick: FT Prentice Hall.p175 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0278c-ftnote.012"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.3;pn1.1">Levi Strauss and Co. </s><s n="s2.3;pn1.1"><hi rend="italic">Our brands / Dockers® brands</hi>. [Online]. </s><s n="s3.3;pn1.1">(URL<seg type="URL" n="http://www.levistrauss.com/brands/dockers.htm"/>) </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0278c-ftnote.013"><p n="pn1.2"><s n="s1.2;pn1.2">Levi Strauss and Co. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.2"><hi rend="italic">Levi Strauss and Co. signs license with GMI Europe</hi>. </s></p><p n="pn2.2"><s n="s1.2;pn2.2">ands. [Online]. </s><s n="s2.2;pn2.2">(URL<seg type="URL" n="http://www.levistrauss.com/news/pressrelease.asp?r=3&amp;c=0&amp;cat=6&amp;pr=733&amp;area=Europe"/>). </s></p></note><p n="p9.11"><s n="s1.2;p9.11">Well-Segmented market is another factor, which allowed Levi's® to gain a competitive advantage over its competitors. </s><s n="s2.2;p9.11">Segmentation is advantageous in that firstly, it can provide higher satisfaction to customers and secondly, it can enhance profits since customers have different attitudes towards the price and lastly communication targeting can be carried out more efficiently. </s></p><p n="p10.11"><s n="s1.9;p10.11">Levi's®, which adopted mixture of differentiated and concentrated marketing strategy are divided into three segments in demographical terms; Women, men and Kids. </s><s n="s2.9;p10.11">The style of the Jeans is different for each segment; for example, the Jeans for men are loose where as for women it is usually tight on the hip and flare at the bottom. </s><s n="s3.9;p10.11">Levi's® however focuses its market on teenagers and young adults as they have more disposable income and tend to be more in to the fashion. </s><s n="s4.9;p10.11">In order to get closer to the youth market, not only Levi's® produces iconic advertisements but also Levi's® introduced 'Antidote' with digital agency, Lateral. </s><s n="s5.9;p10.11">Antidote is an user-generated content, "a living, growing snapshot of what people are thinking and doing across Europe, which aim to "actively try to link different groups together with similar interests, or common themes"<ref target="BAWE_0278c-ftnote.014"/>. </s><s n="s6.9;p10.11">Even though this might help to promote Levi's® brand to the youth groups, the company should always focus on the effectiveness and quality of the site, where it is possible that it will undermine the brand. </s><s n="s7.9;p10.11">In regards to geographical factor, Levi Strauss &amp; Co has headquarters in North America, Europe and in Asia as "products do not always occupy the same stage in the life cycle between different countries"<ref target="BAWE_0278c-ftnote.015"/> and also the wants of the consumers can be distinctive in each area due to various factors such as climate and culture. </s><s n="s8.9;p10.11">For example, Jeans in America are in mature stage, where as it is in growth stage in eastern countries and Europe. </s><s n="s9.9;p10.11">Moreover, recently as the European market is falling down in the women's market including the profit made from 501 ® Original Jeans, Levi Strauss &amp; Co tries to focus on its premium repositioning. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0278c-ftnote.014"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.3;pn1.1">Levi Strauss and Co. </s><s n="s2.3;pn1.1"><hi rend="italic">Antidote</hi>. [Online]. </s><s n="s3.3;pn1.1">(URL eu.levi.com/antidote). </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0278c-ftnote.015"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.6;pn1.1">Vrontis, D. and Vronti,P. </s><s n="s2.6;pn1.1">(2004). </s><s n="s3.6;pn1.1">Levi Strauss: an international marketing investigation. </s><s rend="italic" n="s4.6;pn1.1">Journal of Fashion Marketing and Management. </s><s n="s5.6;pn1.1"><hi rend="bold">vol 8</hi> (4). </s><s n="s6.6;pn1.1">P389 </s></p></note><p n="p11.11"><s n="s1.3;p11.11">Levi Strauss &amp; Co was able to achieve 'customer intimacy'<ref target="BAWE_0278c-ftnote.016"/>, where they were able to segment and target markets precisely to fulfill the demand of each sector and maintain 'product leadership'<ref target="BAWE_0278c-ftnote.017"/>, where they offered superior services such as one to one marketing and thus was able to create "superior custom value"<ref target="BAWE_0278c-ftnote.018"/>. </s><s n="s2.3;p11.11">"Levi was successful in meeting customer need economically and conveniently and with effective communication"<ref target="BAWE_0278c-ftnote.019"/>, where they were able to maintain customer satisfactions and create long-term customer relationship more effectively than the competitors. </s><s n="s3.3;p11.11">Even though it could be argued that recently the market seems to be driven by fashion rather than brand and thus brands such as Kelvin Klein and Tommy Hilfiger seem to gain more attention from the teenagers and young adults, it continues to benefit from "economies of scale, global uniformity and consistency with the mobile consumer"<ref target="BAWE_0278c-ftnote.020"/> and maximizes its competitive advantage across the world market. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0278c-ftnote.016"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.3;pn1.1">Piercy,N.(2002). </s><s rend="italic" n="s2.3;pn1.1">Market led strategic change. </s><s n="s3.3;pn1.1">Oxford: Butterworth-Heinemann. p77 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0278c-ftnote.017"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">ibid </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0278c-ftnote.018"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">ibid, p76. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0278c-ftnote.019"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.6;pn1.1">Freeman, J, <hi rend="italic">et al</hi>. </s><s n="s2.6;pn1.1">(2005). </s><s rend="italic" n="s3.6;pn1.1">Business and management: selected readings for Non-Business Students. </s><s n="s4.6;pn1.1">Volume 1. </s><s n="s5.6;pn1.1">2nd ed. </s><s n="s6.6;pn1.1">Essex: Pearson Education Ltd. p98 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0278c-ftnote.020"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.5;pn1.1">Vrontis, D. and Vronti,P. </s><s n="s2.5;pn1.1">(2004). </s><s n="s3.5;pn1.1">Levi Strauss: an international marketing investigation. </s><s rend="italic" n="s4.5;pn1.1">Journal of Fashion Marketing and Management. </s><s n="s5.5;pn1.1"><hi rend="bold">vol 8</hi> (4). p389 </s></p></note></div2></div1></body><back><div1 type="bibliography"><head rend="bold">Bibliography</head><div2 type="bibliography"><head rend="underlined">Books </head><p>Doyle, P. (2002). <hi rend="italic">Marketing Management and Strategy.</hi> 2<hi rend="sup">nd</hi> ed. University of <name type="university"/>: FT Prentice Hall.</p><p>Financial Times. (1999). <hi rend="italic">Mastering Marketing</hi>.1<hi rend="sup">st</hi> ed. London: Prentice Hall. </p><p>Freeman, J, <hi rend="italic">et al</hi>. (2005). <hi rend="italic">Business and management: selected readings for Non-Business Students.</hi> Volume 1. 2<hi rend="sup">nd</hi> ed. Essex: Pearson Education Ltd.</p><p>Piercy,N.(2002). <hi rend="italic">Market led strategic change.</hi> Oxford: Butterworth-Heinemann. </p><p>Proctor, T. (1992). <hi rend="italic">Essential Marketing.</hi> 1<hi rend="sup">st</hi> ed. London: Collins Educational Ltd. </p></div2><div2 type="bibliography"><head rend="underlined">Journal article</head><p>Vrontis, D. and Vronti,P. (2004). Levi Strauss: an international marketing investigation. <hi rend="italic">Journal of Fashion Marketing and Management. </hi><hi rend="bold">vol 8</hi> (4). p389</p><p>Zeiger,D. (1999). Customization nation. <hi rend="italic">Incentive. </hi><hi rend="bold">Vol 173</hi> (5). p35</p></div2><div2 type="bibliography"><head rend="underlined">Websites</head><p>Levi Strauss and Co.<hi rend="italic">About LS&amp;CO. / Values and vision.</hi> [Online]. (URL <seg type="URL" n="http://www.levistrauss.com/about/vision/"/>) (Accessed on 15<hi rend="sup">th</hi> of November 2005)</p><p>Levi Strauss and Co. <hi rend="italic">Our brands / Dockers® brands</hi>. [Online]. </p><p>(URL<seg type="URL" n="http://www.levistrauss.com/brands/dockers.htm"/>) (Accessed on 18<hi rend="sup">th</hi> of November 2005)</p><p>Levi Strauss and Co. <hi rend="italic">Levi Strauss and Co. signs license with GMI Europe</hi>. [Online].(URL<seg type="URL" n="http://www.levistrauss.com/news/pressrelease.asp?r=3&amp;c=0&amp;cat=6&amp;pr=733&amp;area=Europe).(Accessed"/> on 20<hi rend="sup">th</hi> of November 2005)</p><p>Levi Strauss and Co. <hi rend="italic">Antidote</hi>. [Online]. (URL eu.levi.com/antidote).(Accessed on 20<hi rend="sup">th</hi> of November 2005)</p></div2></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
