<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_0284c" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Information Systems Assessment</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">The document has a title page which contains:
document title
title part</note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">Language used in quote: <foreign id="English">English</foreign></note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">deleted: page numbers</note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">deleted: [total: approx. 1750 words]</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">3</p><p n="date">2006-01</p><p n="module title">Information Systems</p><p n="module code">IB3460</p><p n="genre family">Critique</p><p n="discipline">Business</p><p n="disciplinary group">SS</p><p n="grade">M</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">1862</p><p n="number of s-units">78</p><p n="number of p">38</p><p n="number of tables">0</p><p n="number of figures">0</p><p n="number of block quotes">3</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">0</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">0</p><p n="abstract present">abstract present</p><p n="average words per s-unit">23.9</p><p n="average s-units per p">2.1</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">m</p><p n="year of birth">1984</p><p n="first language">German</p><p n="education">OSA</p><p n="course">Computer and Management Sciences</p><p n="student ID">0284</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><titlePart><name type="student ID"/> Computer and Management Sciences 2 <hi rend="sup">nd</hi> year</titlePart><docTitle><titlePart>Information Systems Assessment</titlePart></docTitle></titlePage><div1 type="toc" n="2"><p/></div1></front><body><div1 type="abstract"><head rend="bold">Overview</head><p n="p1.38"><s n="s1.1;p1.38">The description of SSM is mostly based on the literature authored or co-authored by Checkland, who appears to be the best source as he is one of the fathers of SSM. In addition, copies of the lecture handouts were used. </s></p><p n="p2.38"><s n="s1.1;p2.38">Since I was not able to participate in the practical part of the assignment, my critical review is based on secondary literature only. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">1. Critical Review of SSM Mode 1</head><div2><head rend="bold">Classification of SSM</head><p n="p3.38"><s n="s1.2;p3.38">Different authors (c.f. [3] and [4]) agree that SSM is an organizational-oriented analysis tool for strategic decision-making, which tends to be used for the social analysis rather than the technical one. </s><s n="s2.2;p3.38">As such, it can be the first step in tackling a project like an IT project. </s></p><p n="p4.38"><s n="s1.1;p4.38">It is not enough, though, and has to be followed by requirements elicitation, specification and analysis phases as well as the actual design phases<ref target="BAWE_0284c-ftnote.001"/>. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0284c-ftnote.001"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">As taught, for instance, in "Introduction to Software Engineering" (CS223) and "Systematic Software Development" (CS230). </s></p></note></div2><div2><head rend="bold">The Development of SSM</head><p n="p5.38"><s n="s1.4;p5.38">In Checkland and Scholes [1], SSM is introduced as an organised way of tackling "messy" situations, the kind of problem situations which arise frequently in organisations and encompass scientific and technical as well as cultural, social and political aspects. </s><s n="s2.4;p5.38">It is based on systems thinking and can be seen as part of management science. </s><s n="s3.4;p5.38">The simplest view of SSM is that of a learning cycle, which emphasizes the iterative nature of SSM. It originates in the idea of human beings in social roles trying to take purposeful action ([1] Checkland and Scholes, 1999, p. 20). </s><s n="s4.4;p5.38">These "human activity systems" can be frequently identified in the organisational context and elsewhere and are ideally studied in interdisciplinary teams. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">SSM in Detail</head><p n="p6.38"><s n="s1.2;p6.38">More precisely, SSM is a seven-stage process starting with a situation considered problematic, which has to be expressed (usually as one or more rich pictures) in order to be able to derive root definitions following the XYZ ("a system to do X by Y to achieve Z") or the extended CATWOE scheme (Customers, Actors, Transformation, Weltanschauung, Owner and Environment). </s><s n="s2.2;p6.38">The central activity is the development of conceptual models, which are subsequently compared to the real world to filter out changes that are systemically desirable and culturally feasible - not the other way round ([1], p. 27). </s></p><p n="p7.38"><s n="s1.1;p7.38">For the first five of these activities, methods are suggested by Checkland, the remaining two (changes and action) are more or less left to the user. </s></p><p n="p8.38"><s n="s1.1;p8.38">The problem situation is supposed to be expressed as a rich picture, an informal diagramming technique which adds emotions and attitudes of the actors, thus emphasizing the human interaction side at the expense of technical detail. </s></p><p n="p9.38"><s n="s1.2;p9.38">The purpose of the whole exercise is, of course, to bring about transformations - going from a "bad" state to a "good" state. </s><s n="s2.2;p9.38">For example, quoting a group's work on the Job Center case, an unemployed client should become an employed client by visiting a counsellor for job matching. </s></p><p n="p10.38"><s n="s1.3;p10.38">A conceptual model, being a simplified part of the world, has a boundary according to the Weltanschauung of the user within which there is a flow of activities. </s><s n="s2.3;p10.38">The model is judged by the 3E criteria (Efficacy - does the means work? / Efficiency - are minimal resources used? / Effectiveness - does it contribute to long-term aims?). </s><s n="s3.3;p10.38">Environmental constraints are included as well as a monitoring system. </s></p><p n="p11.38"><s n="s1.2;p11.38">Note that the stages are not supposed to be iterated through in order. </s><s n="s2.2;p11.38">Overlappings, backtracking and repeated iteration are accepted as part of the model ([4], pp. 471). </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">Why SSM? </head><p n="p12.38"><s n="s1.3;p12.38">SSM originated as a response to failed attempts to apply the more scientific systems engineering to situations susceptible to "the unpredictable nature of human activity systems" ([4], p. 470). </s><s n="s2.3;p12.38">It borrows methods from the social sciences rather than the natural sciences or engineering, where it is easier to formulate a problem (even though it may be just as hard to solve!). </s><s n="s3.3;p12.38">As we will see, its "softness" is its major strength and weakness at the same time, making it inappropriate for technical analysis. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">Practical Issues</head><p n="p13.38"><s n="s1.5;p13.38">Even though the above instructions seem precise, I am sure that when applying them to a problem, questions would arise as to how to flesh them out. </s><s n="s2.5;p13.38">It is necessary to go through the process several times in order to grasp it. </s><s n="s3.5;p13.38">Having not done that, the concepts seem very vague. </s><s n="s4.5;p13.38">The "recipe" approach is misleading at best and is likely to be unsuccessful. </s><s n="s5.5;p13.38">A "feel" for the situation at hand is required, which can only be gained by experience. </s></p><p n="p14.38"><s n="s1.1;p14.38">Checkland himself diverges from the original model when he puts SSM into action ([1]). </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">A Fool with a Tool is Still a Fool</head><p n="p15.38"><s n="s1.3;p15.38">Another point is that the method is not formal enough to be able to measure its contribution to the success of a project. </s><s n="s2.3;p15.38">It is hard to tell whether a good engineer or manager would not have done equally well without having studied SSM. Romm picks up this idea in [6] (p. </s><s n="s3.3;p15.38">4). </s></p><p n="p16.38"><s n="s1.2;p16.38">This leads to the next point, that it is all just common sense. </s><s n="s2.2;p16.38">Every intelligent person would tackle a difficult problem like that, i.e. identify the problem, express it in an appropriate way, whether textual, graphic or in some other appropriate notation, finding hypotheses (here they are called root definitions), modelling, do a reality check and finally take action. </s></p><p n="p17.38"><s n="s1.2;p17.38">The problems organizations have to deal with are naturally "messy" or "wicked". </s><s n="s2.2;p17.38">But someone lacking the talent would not be able to solve them even when he is given the tool that SSM is, and someone suitable for the job would choose a systematic approach anyway. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">The Ideal World of SSM</head><p n="p18.38"><s n="s1.3;p18.38">In the ideal world of SSM, everyone would participate in the enquiry process, would cooperate with the external consultants and would give accurate and unbiased accounts. </s><s n="s2.3;p18.38">In reality, people have their own agendas, will be suspicious and reluctant to change. </s><s n="s3.3;p18.38">Romm writes: </s></p><quote lang="English"><hi rend="italic">Checkland admits (with Habermas) that "debate in stages 5 and 6 of the soft systems methodology [may] be inhibited by society's structure [or patterns]".</hi> <hi rend="italic"> [6], p. 5</hi></quote><p n="p19.38"><s n="s1.3;p19.38">For example, it is unlikely for an employee to openly admit a conflict or a communication problem with their superior, especially if they know it will be made public in the form of a rich picture or the like. </s><s n="s2.3;p19.38">So, instead of revealing problems, I believe the rich picture will cover them up. </s><s n="s3.3;p19.38">SSM thus maintains the status quo ([3], p. 96). </s></p><p n="p20.38"><s n="s1.2;p20.38">Consequently, a modern view of the organization is assumed by SSM, putting collective action and communication above competition and conflict. </s><s n="s2.2;p20.38">It is arguable whether this corporate culture is widespread nowadays, but the internet will continue to contribute to the trend towards more collaboration through integration across company borders, which blurs boundaries. </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">2. Roles, Norms and Values in SSM Analysis 2</head><p n="p21.38"><s n="s1.1;p21.38">In mode 2, there are two streams of enquiry, one logic-driven and a cultural stream, which is the actual novelty. </s></p><p n="p22.38"><s n="s1.4;p22.38">The logic-driven stream ([1], pp. 32) is initiated by selecting relevant systems. </s><s n="s2.4;p22.38">These can be somewhere between primary task systems (systems that map to institutional boundaries) and issue-based systems (map to mental processes, not necessarily real-world entities). </s><s n="s3.4;p22.38">Metaphors can help with understanding difficult situations. </s><s n="s4.4;p22.38">The next steps are identical to SSM mode 1 outlined in the previous section. </s></p><p n="p23.38"><s n="s1.3;p23.38">The cultural stream, which is intertwined with the logic-driven one, tries to take into account the social and cultural environment. </s><s n="s2.3;p23.38">It consists of three analyses: the intervention, the social system and power ([3], p. 95). </s><s n="s3.3;p23.38">This section will focus on analysis 2. </s></p><p n="p24.38"><s n="s1.3;p24.38">The aforementioned social system is seen as an interaction between roles, norms and values ([1], p. 49). </s><s n="s2.3;p24.38">Roles are either institutionally or behaviourally defined. </s><s n="s3.3;p24.38">In an organization, they are often equivalent to task descriptions like planner, liaiser, coordinator ([1], p. 117). </s></p><p n="p25.38"><s n="s1.2;p25.38">Norms are a role's expected behaviours and values are defined as local standards ([1], p. 49). </s><s n="s2.2;p25.38">Norms, values and roles are historically motivated ([2], p. A15) and are hard to change from one day to the next. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">3. Politics, Power and SSM Analysis 3</head><p n="p26.38"><s n="s1.2;p26.38">Checkland ([1], p. 50) refers back to Aristotle when he describes politics as a process to accommodate different interests. </s><s n="s2.2;p26.38">This means there is a political dimension in everything, so, as it is so far-reaching, we must not ignore it. </s></p><p n="p27.38"><s n="s1.1;p27.38">Politics is based on power and analysis 3 asks how power is expressed in a given situation ([1], p. 50). </s></p><p n="p28.38"><s n="s1.1;p28.38">Power is expressed through "commodities of power": </s></p><quote lang="English"><hi rend="italic">In the last five years very many 'commodities' of power have been observed in different situations. Examples include: formal (role-based) authority, intellectual authority, personal charisma, external reputation, commanding access (or lack of access) to important information, membership or non-membership of various committees or less formal groups, the authority to write the minutes of meetings, etc.</hi> <hi rend="italic"> ([1], p. 51)</hi></quote><p n="p29.38"><s n="s1.1;p29.38">So power can be based on something as circumstantial as "authority" (or duty?) to take meeting minutes as well as on the position in the company hierarchy. </s></p><p n="p30.38"><s n="s1.2;p30.38">Naturally, the mechanisms of power are on a more tacit level, so it will be difficult to get direct answers in an interview. </s><s n="s2.2;p30.38">The analyst should also avoid being too direct by asking "difficult" questions and thus jeopardizing his own authority ([1], p. 51). </s></p><p n="p31.38"><s n="s1.1;p31.38">In his study of East Berkshire Health Authority, Checkland ([1], pp. 118) includes "disposition of power" (who disposes of power), "nature of power" (ability to make something happen) and a short analysis about how power is obtained, exercised, preserved and passed on. </s></p><p n="p32.38"><s n="s1.2;p32.38">Romm [6] investigates the issue of power by asking question 3 (pp. </s><s n="s2.2;p32.38">6): </s></p><quote lang="English" rend="italic">Would SSM set out to generate overt conflict (as a grounding for a consequent "accommodation")? </quote><p n="p33.38"><s n="s1.2;p33.38">...thus implying that SSM may cause more trouble than good by fuelling conflicts as well as benefiting those who already have power (p. </s><s n="s2.2;p33.38">7). </s></p><p n="p34.38"><s n="s1.3;p34.38">Checkland claims that sometimes people have to be educated (quoted in [6], p. 8), suggesting that people have to be told what they want. </s><s n="s2.3;p34.38">This attitude towards consulting seems very patronising and it seems like the consultants who apply SSM (according to Checkland) are power-hungry themselves. </s><s n="s3.3;p34.38">(However, it is true that people often do not voice their needs and so it should be left to professionals to assess them ([1], p. 116)) </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">4. Conclusion</head><p n="p35.38"><s n="s1.2;p35.38">There are many approaches to systems and SSM is just one of many. [5] compares and contrast a number of them, ranging from conventional systems engineering to distributed knowledge engineering and what seems to be SSM's fiercest contender, Critical Systems Heuristics (CSH). </s><s n="s2.2;p35.38">It would have been interesting to learn more about another approach in order to avoid the impression that SSM is the only way to reason about systems. </s></p><p n="p36.38"><s n="s1.1;p36.38">In this soft area of engineering, what matters most is probably experience in industry and being able to try out and adapt different approaches to suit the situation. </s></p><p n="p37.38"><s n="s1.2;p37.38">As a computer science student I hasten to add that the process of SSM seems to be quite costly (in theory it's never ending), thus consuming valuable software development time. </s><s n="s2.2;p37.38">However, there are ways of integrating both, as with SSADM (structured systems analysis and design methodology) ([3], p. 96). </s></p><p n="p38.38"><s n="s1.1;p38.38">Ultimately the effort may well be worth it since it adds another level of certainty that the IT solution provided will be useful to the customer in a larger context. </s></p></div1></body><back><div1 type="bibliography"><head rend="bold">Bibliography </head><p>[1] CHECKLAND, P. &amp; SCHOLES, J. (1999) Soft Systems Methodology in Action : A 30-year Retrospective (Wiley, Chichester)</p><p>[2] CHECKLAND, P. (1999) Systems Thinking, Systems Practice (Wiley, Chichester)</p><p>[3] VIDGEN, P.; AVISON, D.; WOOD, B.; WOOD-HARPER, T. (2002) Developing Web Information Systems (Butterworth-Heinemann, Oxford)</p><p>[4] AVISON, D. &amp; FIZTGERALD, D. (2003) Information Systems Development: Methodologies, Techniques and Tools (McGraw Hill, Maidenhead)</p><p>[5] STAKER, R., Towards a Syncretic Method for Complex Systems-of-Systems Problems (<seg type="URL" n="http://www.unisa.edu.au/seec/pubs/01papers/ANZSYS7-paper-rjstaker.pdf"/>)</p><p>[6] ROMM, N. (1994) Continuing Tension between Soft Systems Methodology and Critical Systems Heuristics </p><p><seg type="URL" n="http://www-staff.it.uts.edu.au/~jim/bpt/ssm.html"/></p><p><seg type="URL" n="http://www.accaglobal.com/publications/studentaccountant/1073535"/> </p></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
