<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_0287a" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Monopoly And Resource Allocation</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note/></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">3</p><p n="date">2003-12</p><p n="module title">Economics 2</p><p n="module code">EC204</p><p n="genre family">Essay</p><p n="discipline">Economics</p><p n="disciplinary group">SS</p><p n="grade">M</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">2100</p><p n="number of s-units">104</p><p n="number of p">38</p><p n="number of tables">0</p><p n="number of figures">0</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">2</p><p n="number of lists">0</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">4</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">20.2</p><p n="average s-units per p">2.7</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">f</p><p n="year of birth">1984</p><p n="first language">Chinese unspecified</p><p n="education">UK2</p><p n="course">MORSE</p><p n="student ID">0287</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><docTitle><titlePart rend="bold">Monopoly And Resource Allocation</titlePart></docTitle></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">1.Introduction </head><p n="p1.38"><s n="s1.1;p1.38">There are three fundamental questions about efficient allocation of resources: </s></p><p n="p2.38"><s n="s1.1;p2.38">·What commodities will be produced and in what quantity? </s></p><p n="p3.38"><s n="s1.1;p3.38">·How are goods produced? </s></p><p n="p4.38"><s n="s1.1;p4.38">·For whom are goods produced? </s></p><p n="p5.38"><s n="s1.2;p5.38">Economists have rather consistently argued that monopoly is undesirable and accused it of being straining competition and worsening resource allocation. </s><s n="s2.2;p5.38">In this assay, I am going to make a thorough discussion on the factors that may affect the extent of monopoly economic inefficiency. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">2. Monopoly vs. Inefficient Resource Allocation</head><div2><head rend="bold">2.1 Characteristics of monopoly</head><p n="p6.38"><s n="s1.4;p6.38">A pure monopoly consists of a single seller of a product in a given market. </s><s n="s2.4;p6.38">Another more practical definition of monopoly relates to any firms with greater than 25% of the industries' total sales. </s><s n="s3.4;p6.38">Because of its dominant market power, a monopolist can set various prices by adjusting the output level to achieve profit maximization. </s><s n="s4.4;p6.38">In this sense, the price elasticity of the demand curve acts as a constraint on the pricing behavior of the monopolist. </s></p><p n="p7.38"><s n="s1.1;p7.38">As a key factor, high entry barriers are the source of all monopoly power: </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p8.38"><s n="s1.3;p8.38">(a) High Cost Of Entry. </s><s n="s2.3;p8.38">Take railway transport industry, for example. </s><s n="s3.3;p8.38">The enormous capital cost of designing and building new railways discourages potential entrants enter the market. </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p9.38"><s n="s1.2;p9.38">(b) Economies Of Scale. </s><s n="s2.2;p9.38">If existing firms providing goods a substantial scale, they may be better placed to take advantages of economies of scale─leading to a fall in the average of total cost. </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p10.38"><s n="s1.3;p10.38">(c) Product Differentiation &amp;Brand Loyalty. </s><s n="s2.3;p10.38">By creating unique-selling-point or extensive advertising, a monopolist can makes their rivals very expensive to break into the market. </s><s n="s3.3;p10.38">Every year, Coca-Cola and Pepsi spend together hundreds of millions of dollars promoting their brands. </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p11.38"><s n="s1.4;p11.38">(d) Legal Protections. </s><s n="s2.4;p11.38">Important legal restrictions include patents, foreign-trade tariffs and quotas. </s><s n="s3.4;p11.38">A firm may acquire a monopoly over the production of a good by having patents over a certain period. </s><s n="s4.4;p11.38">For instance, the United States government adopts strong monopoly patent protections for pharmaceutical drug companies. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">2.2 Causes of inefficient resource allocation </head><p n="p12.38"><s n="s1.1;p12.38">First of all, I will use a perfectly competitive industry as a basis of comparison to depict monopoly inefficiency in a partial equilibrium model. </s></p><p n="p13.38"><s n="s1.6;p13.38">Many economists argue that under certain conditions, including perfect competition, the " invisible hand of market force" will deliver allocative efficiency. </s><s n="s2.6;p13.38">In such a system, the economy as a whole is efficient, in the sense that no one can be made better off without making someone else worse off. </s><s n="s3.6;p13.38">This is known as Pareto efficiency (see dig 1). </s><s n="s4.6;p13.38">In the long-run competitive market, firms will produce outputs alone their production possibilities curve in terms of choosing optimal input combination and appropriate technology ( MC=AC). </s><s n="s5.6;p13.38">Besides, profit maximization rule implies firms will prefer output level at Q* where price equals P*, i.e. </s><s n="s6.6;p13.38">MC=MR=Price, thus the competitive equilibrium occurs.( see dig 2) </s></p><p n="p14.38"><s n="s1.2;p14.38">However, under a monopoly market it would be different. </s><s n="s2.2;p14.38">In diagram3, the price a monopoly can charge is a function of output, so total revenue becomes </s></p><p n="p15.38"><s n="s1.1;p15.38"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0287a-form.001"/> </s></p><p n="p16.38"><s n="s1.1;p16.38">Marginal revenue is the change in TR with respect to a change in output, which must lie below the AR curve because AR is falling. </s></p><p n="p17.38"><s n="s1.1;p17.38"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0287a-form.002"/> </s></p><p n="p18.38"><s n="s1.6;p18.38">The rule for profit maximization is also applied to pure monopolist, so it will produce output at level Q*, where MR=MC. The corresponding price would be P* and the shaded area in the diagram illustrates the supernormal profits earned by the monopolist. </s><s n="s2.6;p18.38">In addition to the profit, the diagram indicates the average cost incurred at Q*, denoted by AC*, is grater than the minimum AC (MC=AC). </s><s n="s3.6;p18.38">It does not pay the firm to exploit the remaining economies of scale. </s><s n="s4.6;p18.38">As a result, the average cost of production is higher than they could be by having more competitors, therefore production inefficiency occurs. </s><s n="s5.6;p18.38">Another important point is P* >MR due to the downward-sloping demand curve. </s><s n="s6.6;p18.38">Because P* is above the MC for a profit maximizing monopolist, the monopolist lowers output level that would be found in perfect competitive industry thus creates economic inefficiency. . </s></p><p n="p19.38"><s n="s1.3;p19.38">Now I put two diagrams together referring to diagram 4, compared to the Pareto optimal solution occurs at point C, the consumer surplus would fall by area ABCD contrasts to the rising producer surplus of area ABED under the monopoly competition. </s><s n="s2.3;p19.38">The area of triangle BEC represents consumer surplus decreases by more than producer surplus, which economist measure this economic harm from inefficiency in terms of the "deadweight loss". </s><s n="s3.3;p19.38">One typical case is in 1984, the Common Agricultural policy introducing quotas to restrict the output level by farmers, which was advocated as stabilizing the price of agricultural product and increasing farmers' living standard in EU countries. </s></p><p n="p20.38"><s n="s1.5;p20.38">The second issue arising from monopoly inefficiency is equity. </s><s n="s2.5;p20.38">Consumers are induced to pay more for each good from the monopolist perspective, and the area of BEC is a pure transfer of income from consumers to the monopolist. </s><s n="s3.5;p20.38">Hence some low-income consumers might be exploited by increasing prices, and part of their purchasing power is transferred via dividends to shareholders in the higher income brackets - thus making the overall distribution of income more unequal. </s><s n="s4.5;p20.38">As I mentioned before, one question of resource allocation is "for whom?" </s><s n="s5.5;p20.38">If people are not equally endowed with purchasing power, then individual demand curves may not appear fair, which can results in the misallocation of scarce resources. </s></p><p n="p21.38"><s n="s1.2;p21.38">From another point of view, the monopolist may well argue that some of the supernormal profits are used to invest in R&amp;D programs and having the potential to bring dynamic efficiency gains to consumers in the markets (I will elaborate this point later). </s><s n="s2.2;p21.38">Thus different conclusions could be drawn regarding individual ethical judgment and specific circumstances. </s></p><p n="p22.38"><s n="s1.5;p22.38">The third inefficient problem here refers to operating inefficiency. </s><s n="s2.5;p22.38">A key argument here is whether a monopoly becomes complacent if not faced by competition from rival firms, as a consequence it allows X-inefficiency to build. </s><s n="s3.5;p22.38">Take UK electricity industry as an example. </s><s n="s4.5;p22.38">It was a natural monopoly in public ownership since 1948. </s><s n="s5.5;p22.38">In order to tackle its cost inefficiency problem, the liberalization process has started in 1990 by opening access to transmission and distribution networks. </s></p><p n="p23.38"><s n="s1.4;p23.38">Moreover, although a monopolist has the cost advantage by expanding its production scale in the long term, it may eventually experience a rise in LRAC caused by diseconomies of scale (see diagram 5). </s><s n="s2.4;p23.38">It is profitable for the firm to choose a scale beyond the size of minimum long-run average costs, because the extra revenue gained from producing Q* more than compensates for the diseconomies of scale. </s><s n="s3.4;p23.38">The operating inefficiency results in the firm producing output inside rather than on the production possibility frontier. </s><s n="s4.4;p23.38">(See dig 6) </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">3.Other factors affect the extent of monopoly inefficiency</head><p n="p24.38"><s n="s1.3;p24.38">The first factor is price discrimination. </s><s n="s2.3;p24.38">A monopoly is recognized as inefficient to production as it produced at a relatively low level of output in order to charge a higher price than the marginal cost. </s><s n="s3.3;p24.38">But if the monopolist engages in price discrimination, then it is another situation. </s></p><p n="p25.38"><s n="s1.6;p25.38">First-degree-price discrimination involves prefect segmentation of the market where the individuals is charged by the amount he is willing to pay. </s><s n="s2.6;p25.38">Consequently the monopolist will able to extract all consumers' surplus and all the surplus transfer to the monopolist (diagram 7). </s><s n="s3.6;p25.38">This outcome would be Pareto efficient: the producer already maximized its profit, and the consumers' surplus will not increase without decreasing the benefit of the producer. </s><s n="s4.6;p25.38">There is no deadweight loss, thus efficiency is achieved by resource allocation mechanism other than a competitive market. </s><s n="s5.6;p25.38">One common example of it includes the car sales at most dealership and roadside sellers of fruit. </s><s n="s6.6;p25.38">Nevertheless, whether a price discrimination strategy is feasible depends on the inability of buyer to practice arbitrage and the sellers' ability to identify every customer's willingness. </s></p><p n="p26.38"><s n="s1.4;p26.38">Secondly, in general equilibrium analysis, a monopoly is possible to have close substitutes. </s><s n="s2.4;p26.38">Assuming the UK tea market is a monopoly, but the decisions of price and output in the UK coffee market may have significant impact on demand and supply of tea markets. </s><s n="s3.4;p26.38">It's because they are close substitutions for many consumers. </s><s n="s4.4;p26.38">Consequently, the interaction in different market may put pressure upon the monopolist and force them to improve its competitiveness. . </s></p><p n="p27.38"><s n="s1.4;p27.38">In reality, in attempting to control economic activity, governments will use laws or rules to regulate large corporations as well. </s><s n="s2.4;p27.38">Take Antitrust law for instance. </s><s n="s3.4;p27.38">It is designed for making companies act in a competitive manner by breaking up companies those are monopolies and prohibiting mergers that would increase market power. </s><s n="s4.4;p27.38">In June 2000, soft ware giant Microsoft was ordered to broken up in two for "antitrust violations", because it had forced customers to adopt its own browser by discounting and putting pressure to the detriment of rival software maker Netscape. </s></p><p n="p28.38"><s n="s1.4;p28.38">Price ceiling is an alternative approach if the authorities consider it is too inefficient to break the monopoly into smaller firms due to loss of economies of scale. </s><s n="s2.4;p28.38">In 1979 the US government fixed the price of gasoline at about＄1.0 per gallon. </s><s n="s3.4;p28.38">In diagram 8, the effective demand curve becomes horizontal at the ceiling price P', and the firm will adjust quantity at Q', which increases output by (Q*-Q'). </s><s n="s4.4;p28.38">In this case, the monopolist is forced to behave as a price-taking firm under government regulation, and it has reduced the inefficiency caused by too higher monopoly price.. </s></p><p n="p29.38"><s n="s1.4;p29.38">Thirdly, if the regulatory situation is to allow monopoly to charge a price greater than what would occur in a competitive market, then monopoly power may stimulate innovative activities. </s><s n="s2.4;p29.38">Some large firms and some highly concentrated market (e.g. computers and telecommunications) proved to be among the industries with the highest performance with respect to innovation and productivity growth. </s><s n="s3.4;p29.38">Whereas economics theory held that monopoly keeps price high, history experience indicated that highly concentrated industries often had rapidly declining prices relative to less concentrated industries. </s><s n="s4.4;p29.38">So why? </s></p><p n="p30.38"><s n="s1.3;p30.38">Huge corporations enjoying super profit are well allocating some of it to fund high cost of capital investment and research and development projects. </s><s n="s2.3;p30.38">The Solow growth model and the neoclassical model of capital accumulation predict that, in stationary equilibrium, the rate of economic growth is equal to the exogenous rate of technological progress. </s><s n="s3.3;p30.38">In this sense, monopoly firms may be able to increase the pace of innovation and push the PPF outward through integrated technology in the comparison with perfect competitive firms, who will be incapable with zero profit in the long term. </s></p><p n="p31.38"><s n="s1.2;p31.38">The other argument in support of business with monopoly is economies of scale as I mentioned before. </s><s n="s2.2;p31.38">Falls in long run average cost provide gains in welfare for both customers and producer, thus satisfy Pareto efficiency improvement condition. </s></p><p n="p32.38"><s n="s1.3;p32.38">In my opinion, some of the characteristics described as monopoly are not valid anymore since the economic globalization and free trade becomes an inevitable trend. </s><s n="s2.3;p32.38">Many national monopolists have realized the threat from the whole world. </s><s n="s3.3;p32.38">Even a domestic monopoly has to make great effort to improve its productivity and efficiency in order to keep one step ahead of potential competitors from overseas. </s></p><p n="p33.38"><s n="s1.4;p33.38">Furthermore, externality is present whenever there is spillover effect to groups rather than the decision maker, and it is the forth factor here associating with the extent of monopoly inefficiency. </s><s n="s2.4;p33.38">If the producer of externalities doesn't have the incentives to take into account the effect of their actions on the others, the outcome might cause the deviation from present Pareto efficiency. </s><s n="s3.4;p33.38">In fact, the excess profit implies a monopoly may be able to be benevolent and internalize the negative externality e.g. pay the cost of pollution. </s><s n="s4.4;p33.38">Consequently, the efficiency of resource allocation can be improved since perfectly competitive firm would have no choice but to overproduce according to the private cost. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">4. Contestable Markets (Evaluation)</head><p n="p34.38"><s n="s1.3;p34.38">The theory of contestable market suggests that even there is only one seller; the seller may be force to act as if there were many more and eventually the market will become effectively competitive. </s><s n="s2.3;p34.38">Market contestability measures the ease in which suppliers can enter or invade another competitor's market thus few sunk cost is required. </s><s n="s3.3;p34.38">In the UK, for example, retail commercial banking is undergoing a revolution with dramatic implications for the ways we experience banking and related financial service: </s></p><p n="p35.38"><s n="s1.1;p35.38">·Many former building societies including Halifax plc have de-mutualised and become fully-fledged commercial banks. </s></p><p n="p36.38"><s n="s1.1;p36.38">·National food retailers such as Tesco and Sainsbury have launched hugely successful banking operations with millions of customers. </s></p><p n="p37.38"><s n="s1.1;p37.38">·European and North American mortgage lenders are entering the UK market in increasing numbers. </s></p><p n="p38.38"><s n="s1.1;p38.38">In such a market, competitiveness supplied by the potential threat of entry, as well as by the presence of the actual current rivals, can prevent monopoly inefficiency caused by higher price and restrict output, thus entails resource allocative efficiency. </s></p></div1></body><back><div1 type="bibliography"><head rend="bold">5. Bibliography</head><p> Intermediate Microeconomics by Sloberg</p><p> Microeconomics (5<hi rend="sup">th</hi> edition) by Paul A.Samuelson</p></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
