<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_0289a" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Tesco PLC - The Annual Accounts</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">deleted: cover sheet, with tutor's comments</note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">deleted: tutor's comments in text
</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">4</p><p n="date">2006-08</p><p n="module title">Accounting and Finance</p><p n="module code">IB8010</p><p n="genre family">Exercise</p><p n="discipline">Business</p><p n="disciplinary group">SS</p><p n="grade">D</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">1287</p><p n="number of s-units">54</p><p n="number of p">37</p><p n="number of tables">0</p><p n="number of figures">0</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">3</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">0</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">23.8</p><p n="average s-units per p">1.5</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf) </p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">m</p><p n="year of birth">1978</p><p n="first language">English</p><p n="education">UKA</p><p n="course">MBA</p><p n="student ID">0289</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><docTitle><titlePart><hi rend="underlined bold">Accounting and Finance Assignment A</hi><hi rend="bold"> Tesco PLC - The Annual Accounts</hi></titlePart></docTitle></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Question 1</head><div2><p n="p1.37"><s n="s1.1;p1.37">a) 79.5% of sales came from the UK last year (£29.5bn as compared to global sales of £37.1bn) </s></p></div2><div2><p n="p2.37"><s n="s1.1;p2.37">b) 30.9% of Capital Expenditure was overseas (£746m out of a total of £2,417m) </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Question 2</head><div2><p n="p3.37"><s n="s1.1;p3.37">Tesco.com made a £36m profit from sales of £719m </s></p></div2><div2><p n="p4.37"><s n="s1.1;p4.37">Tesco Personal Finance made £202m, £101m of that is Tesco's share, with the other 50% going to the Joint Venture partner, RBS </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Question 3</head><p n="p5.37"><s n="s1.2;p5.37">Currently, Barclays Bank PLC hold almost 271m shares, 3.48% of the company. </s><s n="s2.2;p5.37">It is also worth noting that employees and directors hold significant shares and share options - although not enough to warrant disclosure as the total amount does not come to more than 3% of the company </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Question 4</head><div2><p n="p6.37"><s n="s1.1;p6.37">The auditors are PriceWaterhouse Coopers </s></p></div2><div2><p n="p7.37"><s n="s1.1;p7.37">The auditors gave an unqualified approval of the accounts, giving the company a clean bill of health </s></p></div2><div2><p n="p8.37"><s n="s1.1;p8.37">The auditors were paid £1.7m for the statutory audit, £0.4m for other audit related services and £2.0m for non-audit services, a total of £4.1m for the year </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Question 5</head><p n="p9.37"><s n="s1.1;p9.37">Total net debt decreased by £248m (6.5%) between the 2004 (restated) accounts and the 2005 accounts </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Question 6</head><p n="p10.37"><s n="s1.3;p10.37">The implication is that the balance sheet is prepared conservatively, in line with accounting conventions. </s><s n="s2.3;p10.37">It also implies that the actual balance sheet is stronger than the reported balance sheet. </s><s n="s3.3;p10.37">Had the company needed to strengthen the balance sheet it could have revalued the properties and included their current market values, however given the financial strength of the company this does not seem to be necessary - and means that should the company need to strengthen the accounts at a later stage this could be a way to do it </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Question 7</head><div2><p n="p11.37"><s n="s1.4;p11.37">First impressions of the company based on the accounts are that it is doing extremely well. </s><s n="s2.4;p11.37">Retail is currently a touch marketplace and to report these kinds of results mean that the company is significantly outperforming the market and improving on last year - in fact it is leading the sector. </s><s n="s3.4;p11.37">Comparing 2004 to 2005 continuing operations, and also comparing to the 53 week year in 2004 which will mean that the figures are conservative - Sales rose from £33.5bn to £37bn and profit increased by £222m and both profit and retained profit showed healthy increases. </s><s n="s4.4;p11.37">EPS and DEPS both increased and dividend cover increased from 2.38 to 2.42 times. </s></p></div2><div2><p n="p12.37"><s n="s1.1;p12.37">Specifically on the figures, again comparing 2004 (53 weeks) to 2005 to ensure all figures can be compared on the same basis: </s></p><list type="ordered"><item>Sales +10.5%</item><item>Gross Profit (PBIT) +22.6% </item><item>Operating profit +12.3%</item><item>Profit for the year +24.1%</item><item>Retained Profit +33.4%</item><item>Dividends +13.8%</item><item>EPS +17.8%</item><item>Underlying EPS +12.6%</item><item>Underlying undiluted EPS +12.2%</item></list></div2><div2><p n="p13.37"><s n="s1.2;p13.37">The share price performance during the year was good - an increase of 17.8% on earnings per share, with underlying undiluted EPS rising by 12.2%. </s><s n="s2.2;p13.37">The share price itself rose from circa 250p at the start of the financial year to circa 320p at the end, with the main increase coming from the August 2004 - February 2005 period. </s></p></div2><div2><p n="p14.37"><s n="s1.3;p14.37">Directors pay in total decreased by 24%; however this was due to 2 retirements of highly paid Executive Directors during the year. </s><s n="s2.3;p14.37">As an example, the CEO's pay increased by 7.2%, and this was broadly reflected in the increase in packages of the other Directors. </s><s n="s3.3;p14.37">This is significantly less than the increase in performance so the Directors cannot be accused of receiving pay for poor performance - quite the opposite in fact </s></p></div2><div2><p n="p15.37"><s n="s1.2;p15.37">Pension values increased significantly, again taking the CEO as an example, the value of his pension fund increased the 21.7%, again broadly reflective of the other Directors. </s><s n="s2.2;p15.37">Again however, this does not seem to be hugely out of kilter with company performance, and is most likely to be due to an improved investment performance in the year </s></p></div2><div2><p n="p16.37"><s n="s1.3;p16.37">The executive incentive scheme seems to be in line with good corporate governance procedure. </s><s n="s2.3;p16.37">Pay is heavily geared to performance, with 60-80% of total remuneration dependent on short and long term performance and specific targets set. </s><s n="s3.3;p16.37">This does mean that the executives have a large number of shares and share options in their packages but given the structure of remuneration and company performance this does not seem excessive and compares well with the employee schemes, SAYE (which the Directors are also part of) and Shares in Success, in which £65m (+14%) was allocated. </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Question 8</head><div2><p n="p17.37"><s n="s1.1;p17.37">Average FTE pay was £12,713 to nearest £, +6.8%, based on total global employees </s></p></div2><div2><p n="p18.37"><s n="s1.1;p18.37">Average FTE cost was £14,544 to nearest £, +9.3% on the same basis, the difference being the cost of social security and pensions.√ </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Question 9</head><div2><p n="p19.37"><s n="s1.1;p19.37">At the UK level, average store size has risen by 14.6% over the past 5 years (31,677 sq ft from 27,636 sq ft), fairly steady increments over the period </s></p></div2><div2><p n="p20.37"><s n="s1.2;p20.37">At the UK level, weekly sales per sq ft have risen 9.8% or £2.14 from £21.75 to £23.89 over the 5 year period. </s><s n="s2.2;p20.37">This rise was less steady, with a dip in 2003 and the lions share of the increase (£1.41) being between 2004 and 2005-09-19 </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Question 10</head><div2><head rend="bold">Strong UK Core Business - Summary:</head><list type="simple"><item>'∙ Sales up 11.9%</item><item>∙ Average Spend up 2%</item><item>∙ 1.5m sq ft increase in sales area</item><item>∙ Introduction of more self service checkouts</item><item>∙ Investing in price cuts</item><item>∙ Expanding Tesco Extra</item><item>∙ Converting acquired brands to "Tesco Express" format</item></list><p n="p21.37"><s n="s1.3;p21.37">Overall a strong performance and in line with the strategy. </s><s n="s2.3;p21.37">Tesco are currently leading the market in UK retail. </s><s n="s3.3;p21.37">Perhaps not as strong a growth performance when compared to Tesco's other divisions; however it is a tough marketplace at the current time </s></p><p n="p22.37"><s rend="underlined bold" n="s1.1;p22.37">8/10 </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">Non Food - Summary:</head><list type="simple"><item>∙ 17% sales growth (total sales)</item><item>∙ Clothing sales up 28%</item><item>∙ Above average sales growth in home entertainment, stationery and seasonal non-food products to name a few</item></list><p n="p23.37"><s n="s1.3;p23.37">Overall, a great performance in a very tough sector, growing sales whilst increasing market share. </s><s n="s2.3;p23.37">Not as strong as food of course but the strategy is to make progress towards this goal, rather than achieving it this year. </s><s n="s3.3;p23.37">Again, leading the market in terms of growth and potential </s></p><p n="p24.37"><s rend="underlined bold" n="s1.1;p24.37">9/10 </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">Retailing Services - Summary:</head><p n="p25.37"><s n="s1.1;p25.37">∙ Telecoms - 1m customers, introduced broadband, made a loss of £4m although the company states that this is due to start up costs </s></p><p n="p26.37"><s n="s1.1;p26.37">∙ Tesco.com - Sales up 24.1%, profit up 51.8% in this key area for future growth </s></p><p n="p27.37"><s n="s1.1;p27.37">∙ Tesco Personal Finance - Profit up 26.5%, now has 5m accounts (0.7m increase in the year) </s></p><p n="p28.37"><s n="s1.1;p28.37">Overall an excellent performance, delivering on their strategy of diversifying into other markets and stretching the Tesco brand - "following the customer" as well as huge success in the fast growing area of online sales </s></p><p n="p29.37"><s rend="underlined bold" n="s1.1;p29.37">9/10 </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">International - Summary:</head><p n="p30.37"><s n="s1.1;p30.37">∙ At constant exchange rates, Sales +18.3%, Profit +26.5% </s></p><p n="p31.37"><s n="s1.1;p31.37">∙ At actual exchange rates, Sales +13.1%, Profit +20.9% </s></p><p n="p32.37"><s n="s1.1;p32.37">∙ Margin up by 0.3% points to 5.4% </s></p><p n="p33.37"><s n="s1.1;p33.37">∙ Sales only £370m so still a relatively small operation </s></p><p n="p34.37"><s n="s1.1;p34.37">∙ Europe seems to have challenging market conditions (slowly improving) although growth does look to be organic, in line with the strategy </s></p><p n="p35.37"><s n="s1.1;p35.37">∙ Trading in Asia and the rest of the world seems better than in Europe, however with the exception of Malaysia and Taiwan which do seem to be growing organically, most of the growth in these regions seems to be through JV's and acquisitions which although a perfectly acceptable way to grow businesses, does not seem to be in line with the strategy for International </s></p><p n="p36.37"><s n="s1.1;p36.37">Overall, a small business which is growing, however not completely in line with the published strategy </s></p><p n="p37.37"><s rend="underlined bold" n="s1.1;p37.37">6/10 </s></p></div2></div1></body><back/></text></TEI.2>
