<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_0292e" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Locke asked 'Why should men who were afraid of polecats and foxes arrange to be devoured by lions?' Would Hobbes have an answer?</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note/></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">1</p><p n="date">2006-03</p><p n="module title">Introduction to Moral and Political Philosophy</p><p n="module code">PH120</p><p n="genre family">Essay</p><p n="discipline">Philosophy</p><p n="disciplinary group">AH</p><p n="grade">M</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">1620</p><p n="number of s-units">50</p><p n="number of p">5</p><p n="number of tables">0</p><p n="number of figures">0</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">0</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">0</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">32.4</p><p n="average s-units per p">10.0</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">m</p><p n="year of birth">1984</p><p n="first language">English</p><p n="education">UKA</p><p n="course">PPE</p><p n="student ID">0292</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><docTitle><titlePart rend="bold">Locke asked 'Why should men who were afraid of polecats and foxes arrange to be devoured by lions?' Would Hobbes have an answer? </titlePart></docTitle><epigraph><p rend="italic">"I believe we're not alone,</p><p rend="italic">I believe in Beatles,</p><p rend="italic">I believe my little soul has grown,</p><p rend="italic">And I'm still so afraid"</p><p rend="bold"> David Bowie - Afraid</p></epigraph><epigraph><p rend="italic">"Be afraid. Be very afraid"</p><p rend="bold">Geena Davies - The Fly</p></epigraph></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="section"><p n="p1.5"><s n="s1.9;p1.5">In his autobiography Hobbes dramatically writes that "Fear and I were born as twins!" </s><ref target="BAWE_0292e-ftnote.001"/><s n="s2.9;p1.5">and fear is the underlying principle of his political philosophy. </s><s n="s3.9;p1.5">It is inherent in his conception of the nature of man and from there a driving force towards the development of a political society. </s><s n="s4.9;p1.5">The political society that Hobbes aims to create, as the logical conclusion of his premises about man, is an absolute sovereignty with no restrictions on the ruler<ref target="BAWE_0292e-ftnote.002"/>, an idea that Locke vehemently attacks in the Two Treatises<ref target="BAWE_0292e-ftnote.003"/>. </s><s n="s5.9;p1.5">This absurdity Locke illustrates using his polecats and lions<ref target="BAWE_0292e-ftnote.004"/>, an attack not necessarily specifically directed at Hobbes, but like much of the Treatises was an attempt to detect and overthrow 'the false principles and foundations of Sir Robert Filmer'<ref target="BAWE_0292e-ftnote.005"/>, who repeatedly contended that 'A King according to law makes no kind of government'<ref target="BAWE_0292e-ftnote.006"/>. </s><s n="s6.9;p1.5">Hobbes, however, is the most famous exponent of the defence of the absolute monarchical tradition, most famously in <hi rend="italic">Leviathan</hi> but also in <hi rend="italic">De Cive</hi> and <hi rend="italic">De Corpore Politico</hi> and for this reason consideration of his hypothetical response to the criticism is of the utmost importance. </s><s n="s7.9;p1.5">In order to analyse the respective arguments for and against an absolute sovereign, it is first necessary to look at the basis for Locke's criticism of a monarch outside the law. </s><s n="s8.9;p1.5">Then it will be possible to work through Hobbes' arguments in support of a sovereign, to assess what his answers would be to Locke's criticism, looking at the crux of their theoretical divergence, the important role of fear and the pressing need, in the historical context, for a stable political system. </s><s n="s9.9;p1.5">Then finally an attempt will be made to evaluate Hobbes' argument to see if it is possible to find any flaws while also looking at some of the possible alternatives. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0292e-ftnote.001"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Hobbes, Thomas <hi rend="italic">Tracts Of Thomas Hobbes</hi> ed. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">W. Crooke </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0292e-ftnote.002"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Or rulers, power could be given to an assembly of men, monarchy was not, unlike Filmer, his only form of government. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0292e-ftnote.003"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Locke <hi rend="italic">Two Treatises Of Government</hi> II, § 93 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0292e-ftnote.004"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">And cattle and sheep elsewhere in the <hi rend="italic">Treatises</hi> </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0292e-ftnote.005"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">ibid. Title page </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0292e-ftnote.006"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Filmer <hi rend="italic">Patriarcha</hi> p. 304. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">At the time when Locke wrote the <hi rend="italic">Treatises</hi> Filmer was, politically, a much more important absolutist writer than Hobbes. </s></p></note><p n="p2.5"><s n="s1.15;p2.5">To understand Locke's criticism a brief explanation of his analogy is required. </s><s n="s2.15;p2.5">Talking of absolute monarchies Locke asks '<hi rend="italic">What Fence</hi> is there in such a State, <hi rend="italic">against the Violence and Oppression of this Absolute Ruler</hi>?" </s><ref target="BAWE_0292e-ftnote.007"/><s n="s3.15;p2.5">These rulers are the lions to which Locke refers. </s><s n="s4.15;p2.5">The polecats and foxes come from the State of Nature, hypotheses about which are common to both thinkers. </s><s n="s5.15;p2.5">Based on similar assumptions, Locke follows a slightly different, some would say more optimistic, logical path to form his State of Nature, they both arrive at similar conclusions, namely that in the absence of a political system humans will often be at war<ref target="BAWE_0292e-ftnote.008"/>. </s><s n="s6.15;p2.5">The difference between them at this stage is that while Hobbes believes that the State of War is almost synonymous with the State of Nature, Locke argues that is only an incident arising from it because of the absence of an established Judge who can administer the God-given Laws of Nature. </s><s n="s7.15;p2.5">Over this Locke attacks 'some Men', specifically Hobbes, who 'have confounded [the two States]'<ref target="BAWE_0292e-ftnote.009"/>. </s><s n="s8.15;p2.5">So the Hobbesian State of War, 'where every man is Enemy to every man'<ref target="BAWE_0292e-ftnote.010"/>, contains Locke's polecats and the foxes, they are all the other men which one might meet, for in the State of War they will almost certainly be aggressive towards you<ref target="BAWE_0292e-ftnote.011"/>. </s><s n="s9.15;p2.5">While not agreeing entirely on the exact nature of the world in the absence of political systems<ref target="BAWE_0292e-ftnote.012"/>, Hobbes and Locke do agree that the situation is abhorrent and that remedy lies in a social state<ref target="BAWE_0292e-ftnote.013"/>. </s><s n="s10.15;p2.5">Here, however is where the two thinkers diverge, for while Locke espouses a ruler who is there under the consent of the people. </s><s n="s11.15;p2.5">Governments are to be given power, that 'can never be suppos'd to extend farther than the common good'<ref target="BAWE_0292e-ftnote.014"/> and that is to be used only towards the achievement of certain end. </s><s n="s12.15;p2.5">Failure by a government to attain this end will result in the withdrawal of consent and the dissolution of the governing body. </s><s n="s13.15;p2.5">The three ends which such a body would be established in order to attain: the protection of property, the appointment of an independent Judge of the Laws of Nature and the creation of the power to sentence and punish those found in breach of the Laws<ref target="BAWE_0292e-ftnote.015"/>. </s><s n="s14.15;p2.5">The key difference here is the limit on political power, the ability the subjects have to remove a ruler or rulers who they feel are not protecting their property or correctly administering the Laws of Nature, something that would not happen to an absolute monarch. </s><s n="s15.15;p2.5">Both writers agree that man must escape the polecats, the question is whether the social state he escapes to should contain a Hobbesian lion or a Lockeian sheep dog. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0292e-ftnote.007"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Locke <hi rend="italic">Two Treatises Of Government</hi> II, § 93 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0292e-ftnote.008"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">ibid. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">II, § 16 - 21, Hobbes <hi rend="italic">Leviathan</hi> p. 88 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0292e-ftnote.009"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Locke <hi rend="italic">Two Treatises Of Government</hi> II, § 19 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0292e-ftnote.010"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Hobbes <hi rend="italic">Leviathan</hi> p. 89 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0292e-ftnote.011"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.4;pn1.1">The problem is illustrated well by the Prisoner's Dilemma (Axelrod <hi rend="italic">Evolution Of Co-Operation</hi>), a puzzle derived from Game Theory, where two prisoners must decide independently whether to betray their fellow prisoner by co-operating with the police thus receiving a shorter sentence or to stay quiet. </s><s n="s2.4;pn1.1">If both stay quiet this will be the best outcome but rather than risk betrayal by the other they are more likely both to talk. </s><s n="s3.4;pn1.1">In the same way, an inhabitant of the State of Nature would be unwise to risk co-operating with someone who would then be aggressive leading to the atmosphere of diffidence and mistrust that characterises the State of War. </s><s n="s4.4;pn1.1">The outcome is predicted by the principle of suboptimisation. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0292e-ftnote.012"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Both Hobbes and Locke use the example of international conflict as a State of War where the actors are often in a state conflict. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0292e-ftnote.013"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Locke <hi rend="italic">Two Treatises Of Government</hi> II, § 21, Hobbes <hi rend="italic">Leviathan</hi> p.117 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0292e-ftnote.014"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Locke <hi rend="italic">Two Treatises Of Government</hi> II, § 131 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0292e-ftnote.015"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">ibid. II, § 124 - 126 </s></p></note><p n="p3.5"><s n="s1.12;p3.5">In order defend the increased powers of his sovereign compared with that of Locke, Hobbes must show that the absence of limitations for the ruler is not just an overall benefit to society, but of enough benefit to individuals that they would sign up to the Social Contract. </s><s n="s2.12;p3.5">A large part of the absurdity for Locke is that man would 'arrange' to be 'devoured'; in other words, he willingly agrees to be ruled by the absolute monarch, meaning the most important part of Hobbes answer must concern the private benefit gained that leads a rational individual submit to absolute rule. </s><s n="s3.12;p3.5">Hobbes outlines three key features of men within the State of Nature, stemming from their relative equality, diffidence, competition and vainglory. </s><s n="s4.12;p3.5">Diffidence is fear and mistrust, of your fellow man, of polecats and foxes, and this fear for their lives is what makes the State of Nature so undesirable for men within it. </s><s n="s5.12;p3.5">Their lives are 'nasty brutish and short'<ref target="BAWE_0292e-ftnote.016"/> and it is in the interests of each one that a change is made to raise the average standard of living. </s><s n="s6.12;p3.5">An overwhelming force is required to impose order, essentially, in order to control the fear inherent in the State of Nature, an all encompassing fear is required. </s><s n="s7.12;p3.5">However, given the men's relative equality, this cannot be done by any single individual, but must be a collective agreement<ref target="BAWE_0292e-ftnote.017"/>. </s><s n="s8.12;p3.5">The contract needs to be agreed by a majority, but not by all men, for when they establish a sovereign whom they shall be subservient to, it is fear of the reprisals of the majority whom the ruler commands that men will now fear<ref target="BAWE_0292e-ftnote.018"/>. </s><s n="s9.12;p3.5">The establishment of an overwhelming power of fear is the only way for Hobbes that order can be upheld, because men's chief fear, the only one that will truly restrict their natural tendencies, is the fear of a violent death. </s><s n="s10.12;p3.5">The ruler's powers are directly connected to this, his lack of limits, leaving him all the licence of the State of Nature, is precisely because the sovereign's lion must be inspire more fear than the collected polecats and foxes of the rest of humankind. </s><s n="s11.12;p3.5">Locke also believes however, that fear is an important element in the running of a society, for it is, to some extent, fear of punishment by the sovereign that acts as a preventative for criminal action, "Punishing the crime for restraint, and preventing the like offence"<ref target="BAWE_0292e-ftnote.019"/>. </s><s n="s12.12;p3.5">Locke places a limit here too, saying that each transgression should be punished proportionately to the extent that it becomes "an ill bargain to the Offender"<ref target="BAWE_0292e-ftnote.020"/> again referring to its preventative nature. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0292e-ftnote.016"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">In the animal kingdom, aside from the examples of ants and bees that Hobbes describes, animals without a political system avoid an early extinction by having aggressive rituals that avoid actual violence. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0292e-ftnote.017"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Man's relative equality does not stop later sovereigns claiming authority by acquisition, as distinct to the institution discussed here. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">This is because they already have a system of control that allows them to amass a physical majority of man. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0292e-ftnote.018"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Hobbes says that any man not within the Social Contract is logically in the State Of Nature and deserves all that he gets. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0292e-ftnote.019"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Locke <hi rend="italic">Two Treatises Of Government</hi> II, § 11 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0292e-ftnote.020"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">ibid. II, § 12 </s></p></note><p n="p4.5"><s n="s1.8;p4.5">The difference between Hobbes and Locke's attitude to punishment is explained in their differing Laws of Nature. </s><s n="s2.8;p4.5">For Hobbes the Laws of Nature are guidelines dictated by reason<ref target="BAWE_0292e-ftnote.021"/>, but often subordinate to the passions, the first and most important of which is to seek peace at all costs. </s><s n="s3.8;p4.5">This is similar to Locke's tenet that one should "preserve the rest of Mankind"<ref target="BAWE_0292e-ftnote.022"/>. </s><s n="s4.8;p4.5">Both of these Laws come with additional clauses and it is because Hobbes' is that much more aggressive than Locke's that their ideas diverge. </s><s n="s5.8;p4.5">In Hobbes' case if peace is unobtainable a man "may seek, and use, all helps, and advantages of Warre" whereas Locke merely releases you of your obligation only when your own preservation comes in competition. </s><s n="s6.8;p4.5">This difference can be further explained by the two thinker's respective origins for the Laws, Hobbes' being derived from reason and not ever calling upon God as a sole ground for a premise even talking of the State of War resulting from the absence of a "visible Power", intimating somewhat blasphemous lack of control for an omnipotent deity. </s><s n="s7.8;p4.5">On the other hand, Locke's Laws are more Divine, saying that God appoints a government to be the adjudicator of all things<ref target="BAWE_0292e-ftnote.023"/> and that as we are all the "Workmanship of one Omnipotent, and infinitely wise Maker" and can have no "Subordination among us"<ref target="BAWE_0292e-ftnote.024"/>. </s><s n="s8.8;p4.5">Locke also quotes "the judicious Hooker" extensively, who uses men's equality as the "Foundation of that Obligation to mutual Love"<ref target="BAWE_0292e-ftnote.025"/>, compare this to Hobbes, who, as already quoted, uses equality to demonstrate how all man may kill each other. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0292e-ftnote.021"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Hobbes <hi rend="italic">Leviathan</hi> p.91 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0292e-ftnote.022"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Locke <hi rend="italic">Two Treatises Of Government</hi> II, § 6 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0292e-ftnote.023"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">ibid. II, § 13 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0292e-ftnote.024"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">ibid. II, § 7 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0292e-ftnote.025"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">ibid. II, § 5 </s></p></note><p n="p5.5"><s n="s1.6;p5.5">These differing views then explain their final positions, one advocating sovereignty with limits and by consent, the other advocating absolute sovereignty, and total control without the possibility of injustice. </s><s n="s2.6;p5.5">Hobbes desires stability above all else and as a result of his more pessimistic view of mankind feels that the less control is in the hands of the masses, the further from the State of War and the safer we will be. </s><s n="s3.6;p5.5">Locke, coming from slightly more settled times, sees unlimited powers as an unacceptable threat and trusts that the community should still maintain some control over their destiny. </s><s n="s4.6;p5.5">For me, Hobbes' view of humankind is more realistic, but because of his practical political agenda, contradictions do appear, to the extent that Bishop Bramhall felt able to brand it a "rebel's catechism" despite Hobbes' intention. </s><s n="s5.6;p5.5">The tenets of Locke's philosophy have been the foundations for much of modern society, the basis, most famously, for the American constitution. </s><s n="s6.6;p5.5">His final draft of society is more practical but is reached by a less plausible trans-historical route, incorporating throughout a Christian agenda with respect to morality. </s></p></div1></body><back><div1 type="bibliography"><head>Bibliography</head><p>Axelrod, Robert <hi rend="italic">The Evolution Of Co-Operation</hi> (1985)</p><p>Filmer, Robert <hi rend="italic">Patriarcha</hi> Ed. Johann P. Sommerville (1991)</p><p>Gauthier, David <hi rend="italic">The Logic Of Leviathan</hi> (1969)</p><p>Hobbes, Thomas <hi rend="italic">Leviathan</hi> Ed. Richard Tuck (1996)</p><p>Hobbes, Thomas <hi rend="italic">Tracts Of Thomas Hobbes</hi> ed. W. Crooke (1682)</p><p>Hooker, Richard The Laws Of Ecclesiastical Polity Ed. A. S. McGrade (1989)</p><p>Levine, Andrew <hi rend="italic">Engaging Political Philosophy</hi> (2002)</p><p>Locke, John <hi rend="italic">Two Treatises Of Government</hi> Ed. Peter Laslett (1960)</p><p>Macpherson, C.B. <hi rend="italic">The Political Theory Of Possessive Individualism</hi> (1962)</p><p>Warrender, Howard <hi rend="italic">Political Philosophy of Hobbes His Theory of Obligation</hi> (2000)</p></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
