<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_0293d" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An old-fashioned debate between free trade and protectionism is recently re-emerging in the form of wrangling between multilateralism and bilateralism.</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note/></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">4</p><p n="date">2006-05</p><p n="module title">Theories and Issues in International Political Economy</p><p n="module code">PO907</p><p n="genre family">Essay</p><p n="discipline">Politics</p><p n="disciplinary group">SS</p><p n="grade">M</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">5177</p><p n="number of s-units">183</p><p n="number of p">73</p><p n="number of tables">0</p><p n="number of figures">0</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">1</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">0</p><p n="abstract present">abstract present</p><p n="average words per s-unit">28.3</p><p n="average s-units per p">2.5</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">m</p><p n="year of birth">1968</p><p n="first language">Korean</p><p n="education">OSA</p><p n="course">IPE</p><p n="student ID">0293</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front/><body><div1 type="abstract"><head rend="bold">ABSTRACT</head><p n="p1.73"><s n="s1.3;p1.73">An old-fashioned debate between free trade and protectionism is recently re-emerging in the form of wrangling between multilateralism and bilateralism. </s><s n="s2.3;p1.73">From the liberal political economy perspective in IPE, bilateral trade treaties are regarded as attempts to incorporate each party into a global market, thus these are completely compatible with the postwar international trade regime based on non-discriminatory multilateralism. </s><s n="s3.3;p1.73">In contrast to this, economic realists condemn the discriminatory nature of the PTAs on the grounds that bilateral or regional trade relationship is contradictory to the postwar arrangement based on the spirit of 'freer and fairer' trade that the GATT earlier committed. </s></p><p n="p2.73"><s n="s1.2;p2.73">This article first analyse the inter-relationship between multilateralism and bilateralism through the examination of historical episodes in international trade realm since the second half of the nineteenth century. </s><s n="s2.2;p2.73">This will be carried out with the categorisation into three chronological phases. </s></p><p n="p3.73"><s n="s1.3;p3.73">The first phase as a prologue shows the bilateralism does not necessarily undermine the trade liberalisation. </s><s n="s2.3;p3.73">On the other hand, the wave of protectionist regionalism among LDCs in the 1960s-1970s and the explosion of bilateral PTAs after the end of Cold War imply that the absence of hegemonic leadership in international trade facilitated the enhancement of bilateral PTAs. </s><s n="s3.3;p3.73">Finally, this article concludes that such increasing number of bilateral PTAs inevitably erodes the multilateral regime, but still, more salient emphasis would be placed on the existence of hegemonic leadership rather than the dichotomy between multilateralism and bilateralism. </s></p><list type="simple"><head>Key words : PTAs, multilateralism, open regionalism, hegemonic leadership </head></list></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Introduction</head><p n="p4.73"><s n="s1.2;p4.73">The postwar international trade regime launched under the auspices of the General Agreement on Tariffs and Trade (GATT) has been challenged by two strands of criticism. </s><s n="s2.2;p4.73">Some observers who centered on the unequal nature of international trade criticised the Most Favoured Nation (MFN) clause (Evans 1968, 92-93) and the principle of reciprocity (Spero 1981, 188) on the grounds that, in practice, these key provisions of the GATT promote unfair free competition between less-developed members and industrialised advanced countries. </s></p><p n="p5.73"><s n="s1.1;p5.73">On the other hand, the liberal purists advocating multilateralism showed great concern for the emergence of a bilateral trade treaty among the GATT contracting parties, which might undermine the global free trade order (Krugman 1993, Bahgwati and Panagariya 1996). </s></p><p n="p6.73"><s n="s1.3;p6.73">The former issue still remained as a significant cause which might endanger the multilateral free trade regime, although a series of measures for internal reform such as the introduction of Generalised System of Preference (GSP). </s><s n="s2.3;p6.73">However, a much more dreadful scenario is likely to caused by the latter. </s><s n="s3.3;p6.73">Given that reckless mercantilist interstate competition during the interwar period triggered World War Ⅱ, multilateralists are likely to argue that the formation of excusive trading blocs is even dangerous as well as undesirable. </s></p><p n="p7.73"><s n="s1.3;p7.73">They point out that Preferential Trade Agreements (PTAs)<ref target="BAWE_0293d-ftnote.001"/> will erode the multilateral trade system that has underpinned economic relations since the end of World WarⅡ. </s><s n="s2.3;p7.73">The PTAs are regarded as contradictory to the non-discriminatory rule on which the GATT is based, because they allow excusive access right for selected partners' markets. </s><s n="s3.3;p7.73">Although the GATT article ⅩⅩⅣ approves the arrangements, the dramatically increasing number of PTAs cast a cloud over the commitment of welfare increase and peace settlement promised by the GATT planners. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0293d-ftnote.001"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">In this article, Preferential Trade Agreements (PTAs) will be used rather than bilateral Free Trade Agreements (FTAs). </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">This term will reveal the nature of discriminatory arrangements of bilateral or regional FTAs contrasting the original stipulation of the GATT. PTAs are defined as a regional institution by both bilateral and more than two countries' arrangement for the elimination of trade barriers. </s></p></note><p n="p8.73"><s n="s1.3;p8.73">On the contrary, the advocates of PTAs state that trade liberalisation at a regional level is complementary to multilateral free trade order and that, ultimately, it can jump-start the stalled multilateral trade negotiation (Bergsten and Noland 1993, Lawrence 1996, Mansfield and Milner 1999). </s><s n="s2.3;p8.73">They stress the non-exclusiveness and openness of contemporary regional PTAs which are willing to accept outsiders if they once want to join. </s><s n="s3.3;p8.73">A seemingly self-contradictory term, 'open regionalism' was coined under such underlying assumption. </s></p><p n="p9.73"><s n="s1.2;p9.73">This article begins with an historical approach examining the trajectory that regional PTAs have created. </s><s n="s2.2;p9.73">The development of regionalism in this article is largely divided into three phases. </s></p><p n="p10.73"><s n="s1.2;p10.73">The first phase starts from the second half of nineteenth century, the heyday of liberal trade order, and this lasts up to the outbreak of World WarⅡ including interwar periods. </s><s n="s2.2;p10.73">Interstate exchange of manufactures to maximise national interest under the circumstance of the political disorder in this phase clearly indicates the tension between bilateralism and multilateralism through the episodes of success and failure occurred by turns. </s></p><p n="p11.73"><s n="s1.3;p11.73">The second phase ranges from the late 1950s to 1970s. </s><s n="s2.3;p11.73">The demise of American hegemonic power with the collapse of Bretton Woods system facilitated the moves of regional PTAs in this period. </s><s n="s3.3;p11.73">However, the main actors in this wave were still less-developed and small-sized economies, thus, these show insufficient evidence in explaining the sharp conflict between bilateralism and multilateralism. </s></p><p n="p12.73"><s n="s1.3;p12.73">Vehement debates were not deployed until the post-Cold War economic giants, including the United States and European Union (EU), struggled with each other towards an initiative within multilateral negotiation with eliminated trade barriers in the 1990s. </s><s n="s2.3;p12.73">In this period, the traditional supporter for non-discriminatory multilateralism, the United States, dramatically changed its underlying tone of trade policy from multilateralism to bilateralism. </s><s n="s3.3;p12.73">Further, the United States has actively led the recent wave of bilateral PTAs. </s></p><p n="p13.73"><s n="s1.4;p13.73">After the chronological survey to trace the meaningful evolution of postwar multilateral trade regime, the relevance of the concept of 'open regionalism' which represents the liberal view over the increasing regionalism will be examined. </s><s n="s2.4;p13.73">One of the most accessible conceptualisations of this multilateralism-bilateralism conflict seems to be the 'building block <hi rend="italic">versus</hi> stumbling block' hypothesis (Bhagwati and Panagariya 1999). </s><s n="s3.4;p13.73">That is, the former views the role of PTAs as a facilitator to achieve worldwide multilateral trade liberalisation, while the latter regards them as impeding the non-discriminating trade liberalisation. </s><s n="s4.4;p13.73">In conclusion, the historical scrutiny and theoretical examination in this article will show the outcome : that current PTAs led by the United States are in a state of considerable tension with the multilateral and liberal trade order that GATT architects envisaged. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">PhaseⅠ: From Nineteenth Century to Interwar Period</head><p n="p14.73"><s n="s1.3;p14.73">Development of regionalism has been undertaken since the second half of nineteenth century. </s><s n="s2.3;p14.73">A vast number of custom unions, which culminated in the formation of the Zollverein in 1834, were emerged and bilateral commercial agreements hastened by Anglo-French commercial treaty in 1860 also contributed to the enhancement of trade. </s><s n="s3.3;p14.73">However, it should be noted these trends were a largely European phenomenon (Irwin 1993, 92, Mansfield and Milner 1999, 596). </s></p><p n="p15.73"><s n="s1.4;p15.73">At this time, the broad network of bilateral commercial agreements in Europe was heavily linked by unconditional Most Favoured Nation (MFN) rules. </s><s n="s2.4;p15.73">Irwin depicted such a trend as 'progressive bilateralism' ; European countries 'effectively pursued multilateralism via bilateral treaties' in the nineteenth century (Irwin 1993, 99, 114). </s><s n="s3.4;p15.73">Unfortunately, however, bilateral trade regime came to an end in 1914 with the outbreak of World WarⅠ. </s><s n="s4.4;p15.73">Nonetheless, such experiences offered substantial inspiration later to construct a postwar international trade regime based on the GATT's provision of non-discriminatory treatment to their trading partners. </s></p><p n="p16.73"><s n="s1.3;p16.73">By contrast, the interstate trade relationship during the interwar period was likely to be characterised as highly 'preferential' and 'discriminatory'. </s><s n="s2.3;p16.73">The central aims of European states that had experienced devastating war were zeroed in on the maximisation of political power. </s><s n="s3.3;p16.73">Also the mercantilist trade policy was an efficient way to coerce past enemies into abandoning any military threat to themselves. </s></p><p n="p17.73"><s n="s1.2;p17.73">Paradoxical episodes were clearly seen in the evolution of the pattern of international trade between the second half of nineteenth century and the 1930s with this phase. </s><s n="s2.2;p17.73">In other words, one can identify the fact that international trade system grounded in bilateral agreements in the nineteenth century did not generate pernicious effects even though it failed to create any form of multilateral institution. </s></p><p n="p18.73"><s n="s1.2;p18.73">On the contrary, multilateral attempts to prevent interstate conflicts driven by mercantilist trade policy in the 1930s failed to dissuade major powers from the beggar-thy-neighbour strategy which led to World WarⅡ(Irwin 1993, 114). </s><s n="s2.2;p18.73">Frequently, the failures of the formation of multilateral agreements in trade and finance are also regarded as one of the factors that triggered disastrous war (Kenwood and Lougheed 1971, 218 Eichengreen and Frankel 1995, 97). </s></p><p n="p19.73"><s n="s1.3;p19.73">In the light of such historical episodes, it is difficult to generalise hastily that multilateral institution is likely to guarantee trade liberalisation without consideration the influence of other variables. </s><s n="s2.3;p19.73">Moreover, the postwar international trade order created by the GATT shows remarkable differentiation from that of prewar era. </s><s n="s3.3;p19.73">The principal factor constituting such difference was the emergence of a new hegemonic leadership in the world trade regime. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Phase Ⅱ : Regional grouping among LDCs</head><p n="p20.73"><s n="s1.2;p20.73">Despite widespread consensus requiring 'freer and fairer' trade flows, the onset of the postwar trading system was accompanied with subtle distinction about the pace and degree of trade barriers elimination between Britain and the United States. </s><s n="s2.2;p20.73">While the United States wanted to achieve completely free movement of goods, as soon as possible, under the conviction of industrial superiority, British negotiators worried about the erosion of domestic economic autonomy to pursue a full employment policy (Gilpin 2001, 217). </s></p><p n="p21.73"><s n="s1.2;p21.73">The final beneficiary in this war of nerves seemed to be the United States. </s><s n="s2.2;p21.73">Although Britain was concerned over its commitment to the creation of a Keynesian welfare state, the founders of the GATT subordinated individual parties' domestic circumstances to the aim to construct an open world economy, with no return to the vicious cycle of retaliation and counter-retaliation that had characterised the 1930s (Gilpin 2001, 220). </s></p><p n="p22.73"><s n="s1.3;p22.73">Being propped up by the request for leadership able to replace the decayed British hegemony of the nineteenth century, the United States consolidated its newly obtained hegemonic role in the postwar period. </s><s n="s2.3;p22.73">As a result, the GATT efficiently implemented its commitment and still remained as a most significant and powerful party who set the trade rules and achieved liberalisation by multilateral arrangements (Panagariya 1999, 480). </s><s n="s3.3;p22.73">Also the repeated multilateral trade negotiations, by and large, were successfully led by the United States. </s></p><p n="p23.73"><s n="s1.3;p23.73">Nonetheless, there is an uneven fluctuation of the formation of PTAs between 1948 and the 1990s. </s><s n="s2.3;p23.73">Most striking point in this trend was the surge in PTAs during two decades from 1960 to 1980 (phaseⅡ) and the explosion of regionalism in the 1990s (phase Ⅲ). </s><s n="s3.3;p23.73">In this period, nearly thirty PTAs during every ten years in phaseⅡ and also similar number of PTAs during ten years of phase Ⅲ were signed respectively (Mansfield and Milner 1999, 600-1). </s></p><p n="p24.73"><s n="s1.4;p24.73">The increase of PTAs between phaseⅡ and phase Ⅲ shows the sharp difference with respect to the causes and impetus to trigger regionalism. </s><s n="s2.4;p24.73">The former wave was mainly initiated by less developed countries (LDCs) which wanted to reduce political dependence on industrialised advanced countries. </s><s n="s3.4;p24.73">Latin American regional groupings such as the Latin American Free Trade Area (LAFTA, 1960) and the Andean Pact (1969) emerged in this phase. </s><s n="s4.4;p24.73">Subsequently, it affected the disillusion of regionalism in Sub-Saharan African countries and promoted PTAs like the Economic Community of Western African States (ECOWAS) and the Customs and Economic Union of Central Africa (UDEAC). </s></p><p n="p25.73"><s n="s1.4;p25.73">The spate of PTAs in this phase, however, had the colour of protectionism caused by the member countries' import-substituting industrialisation strategy. </s><s n="s2.4;p25.73">Regulatory measures like the import licenses and high levels of tariffs were devised and maintained for the creation of the PTAs in this region (Noguès and Quintanilla 1993, 281). </s><s n="s3.4;p25.73">As a result, the attempts of these states were assessed as fundamental failures. </s><s n="s4.4;p25.73">They could neither stimulate regional economic growth nor overcome the structural weakness of their economies (Faezeh 1993, 264). </s></p><p n="p26.73"><s n="s1.2;p26.73">PTAs among LDCs without a hegemonic leader are likely to bring about unavoidable conflict over the distribution of benefits and costs and compensation rate of relative losses stemming from economic integration (Mansfield and Milner 1999, 600). </s><s n="s2.2;p26.73">This failure, thus, can be attributed to the absence of a powerful leader with a great consumer market which is able to absorb the exports from less-developed PTAs partners. </s></p><p n="p27.73"><s n="s1.3;p27.73">Moreover, the members of trading blocs among developing countries tended to try to produce every goods within their own union instead of importing from the rest of the world. </s><s n="s2.3;p27.73">They strove to give preferential access rights to individual members' markets to one another and inevitably this self-sufficient trading system engendered a 'trade diversion effect'<ref target="BAWE_0293d-ftnote.002"/> which poses higher cost to the importing country (Lawrence 1996, 6). </s><s n="s3.3;p27.73">This empirical evidence indicates the fact that such failures can be attributed to the outcome of pursuit the extended import-substitute strategy. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0293d-ftnote.002"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">The most popular method so far, to measure the effect of PTAs is the comparative analysis between 'trade creation' effect and 'trade diversion' effect. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">See Viner (1950) for details. </s></p></note><p n="p28.73"><s n="s1.3;p28.73">The perspective of key institutions constituting postwar world economic order also shows the sceptical view over the PTAs among LDCs. </s><s n="s2.3;p28.73">The International Monetary Fund (IMF) survey report regarded the voluntary regional groupings in two continents in this phase as conscious efforts to reinforce political stability rather than economic development (Torre and Kelly 1992, 25). </s><s n="s3.3;p28.73">At the same time, the participants in the conference jointly organised by the World Bank also criticised the discriminatory and regulatory nature of Latin American regional agreements (Nogués and Quintanilla 281-85). </s></p><p n="p29.73"><s n="s1.2;p29.73">This implies that the increased number of the PTAs in the phaseⅡ were not necessarily consistent with the underlying assumption which the architects of the GATT designed in the late 1940s. </s><s n="s2.2;p29.73">The PTAs could not contribute to the creation of enhanced welfare (Mansfield and Milner 1999, 600), and finally turned out to be a 'stumbling block' rather than a 'building block' to achieve global liberalisation (Panagariya 1999, 493). </s></p><div2><head rend="italic">US hegemony, rise and fall </head><p n="p30.73"><s n="s1.2;p30.73">The second question raised from this phase is something to do with the role of the United States in promoting multilateralism. </s><s n="s2.2;p30.73">Although the successful conclusion of the Kennedy Round (1967) ostensibly signified the golden age of free trade after the War, world trade has intermittently revealed controversial problems due mainly to the decreasing economic power of the United States. </s></p><p n="p31.73"><s n="s1.1;p31.73">Indeed, many scholars have stressed the hegemonic role in shaping multilateral international economic order, since Kindleberger manifested the importance of unchallenged leadership in the name of 'hegemonic stability theory' (Kindleberger 1973). </s></p><p n="p32.73"><s n="s1.3;p32.73">Krasner (1976) elaborated that the hegemonic state in an economically ascending position is likely to engender global openness. </s><s n="s2.3;p32.73">Crone (1993) also principally took into account the power differential between a hegemonic state and a non-hegemonic one in forming the international co-operative regime. </s><s n="s3.3;p32.73">More recently, Gilpin emphasised again that one or more core political entities should play a decisive role to pursue political integration (Gilpin 2001, 356) </s></p><p n="p33.73"><s n="s1.4;p33.73">Historical evidences are likely to enhance the explanatory power of the assumptions that these 'hegemony' theorists have made. </s><s n="s2.4;p33.73">In particular, despite the overall trend of export increase caused by a series of tariff reduction, the export portion of the United States divided by the world total has continuously decreased. </s><s n="s3.4;p33.73">While the export of European Economic Community (EEC) and that of Japan increased from 22% and 2% in 1955 to 39% and 10% in 1988 respectively, the US portion of export within the world trade strikingly decreased from 19% in 1955 to 12% in 1988 (Walters and Blake 1992, 17). </s><s n="s4.4;p33.73">This indicates that world trade can no longer be maintained by the unilateral leadership of the United States and the alternative super power replacing it has not burgeoned yet. </s></p><p n="p34.73"><s n="s1.2;p34.73">In other words, the increasing trend of regional grouping shows the attempts to frame developing countries' own solutions to international economic problems such as gaining greater export markets. </s><s n="s2.2;p34.73">Particularly the endeavours for pursuing regional autarky with no dependence upon an external power were decisively facilitated by the breakdown of the Bretton Woods system (Gilpin 2001, 359). </s></p><p n="p35.73"><s n="s1.1;p35.73">In the different vein, liberal multilateralists later join the criticism against the United States for its lack of vision and programme towards returning to its initial commitment of multilateral trade liberalisation (Bhagwati 1993, 45). <ref target="BAWE_0293d-ftnote.003"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0293d-ftnote.003"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">For example, as his own alternative programme, Baghwati suggests a 'grand finale' scenario envisaging trilateral integration comprising the NAFTA including Latin economic area, the Asian bloc including even South Asia and the EU. </s></p></note><p n="p36.73"><s n="s1.3;p36.73">It was with the arrangement of the NAFTA in 1992 examined below that the United States incurred severe censure from both hegemony theorists and multilateralists. </s><s n="s2.3;p36.73">The establishment of the NAFTA was perceived as a proclamation of the advocate of multilateralism manifesting the re-orientation of the US trade policy. </s><s n="s3.3;p36.73">It was a critical turning point, at the same time, signifying its willingness to pursue bilateral free trade agreements unless the lingering multilateral trade negotiation in Uruguay Round would come to an end. </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Phase Ⅲ : Post-Cold War Period</head><p n="p37.73"><s n="s1.1;p37.73">While the wave of regionalism in the previous phase mirrors the confrontation provoked by the Cold War to the extent that it has sought to pull themselves out of political influence of industrial nations, phaseⅢ which commenced from 1990 reflects changed international power politics after the end of the Cold War. </s></p><p n="p38.73"><s n="s1.3;p38.73">In retrospect, the United States, by and large, successfully led the seven rounds of multilateral trade negotiations. </s><s n="s2.3;p38.73">One piece of evidence that substantiates the sustained evolution of the postwar multilateral international trade regime was the amendment of the GATT provisions. </s><s n="s3.3;p38.73">More active participation of developing countries was encouraged by the introduction of 'Enabling Clause' which allowed the application of Generalised System of Preferences (GSP). </s></p><p n="p39.73"><s n="s1.4;p39.73">However, the United States faced an obstacle to resume the eighth multilateral round due mainly to the influence of external factors. </s><s n="s2.4;p39.73">It seemed to be at the GATT Ministerial Meeting in 1982 that the United States began to take into account the re-orientation of underlying agenda of trade policy towards bilateralism (Schott 1983). </s><s n="s3.4;p39.73">Despite the repeated persuasion of the United States, the EU and the other trading partners still showed reluctance to restore the stalled multilateral negotiating table. </s><s n="s4.4;p39.73">Meanwhile, the outward expansion of the EU was continued and Greece (1981), Portugal and Spain (1986) became new members in turn. </s></p><p n="p40.73"><s n="s1.1;p40.73">At the same time, the United States adopted a 'multi-track' approach as an alternative measure replacing consistent commitment to multilateralism, which means, in practice, the declaration showing willingness to pursue bilateral trade arrangements with individual WTO members despite nominal re-affirmation of multilateralism it has inherently espoused (Wyatt-Walter 1994, 85). </s></p><p n="p41.73"><s n="s1.1;p41.73">On the other hand, the voice of protectionism was burgeoning, caused by the vast amount of the US trade deficit along with the appearance of strategic trade theory in the realm of economics, which emphasised the state's deeper intervention in industrial policy to enhance the competitiveness for export (Brander and Spencer 1985, Reich 1992, Thurow 1993). </s></p><p n="p42.73"><s n="s1.3;p42.73">Bilateral FTAs led by the United States began with the arrangement with Israel in 1985. </s><s n="s2.3;p42.73">This was precipitated by the consolidation of European politico-economic integration and stalled Uruguay Round negotiations, and the United States increasingly expanded the partners of bilateral treaties towards North America and Middle East. </s><s n="s3.3;p42.73">As a result, the Bush administration concluded ten FTAs in his first term since he entered into office in 2001 (Schott 2004, 359-381). </s></p><p n="p43.73"><s n="s1.2;p43.73">The re-orientation of US trade policy reignited the ongoing debate over multilateralism <hi rend="italic">versus</hi> bilateralism. </s><s n="s2.2;p43.73">This wrangling ranges from the censure blaming the breach of hegemonic leadership, to the defense stressing the complementarity between FTAs and multilateral trade liberalisation. </s></p><p n="p44.73"><s n="s1.3;p44.73">The key difference between the regionalism in the phaseⅠ,Ⅱ and the recent wave of bilateral FTAs can be pointed to a high level of economic 'interdependence' (Mansfield and Milner 1999, 601). </s><s n="s2.3;p44.73">Unlike the observation of regional grouping under the Cold War regime, the bilateral FTAs after the Cold War have facilitated the members to join the world economy rather than insulating them from multilateral order (Lawrence 1996, 6). </s><s n="s3.3;p44.73">This indicates that enhanced politico-economic 'interdependence' could be the main feature of post-Cold War bilateralism. </s></p><p n="p45.73"><s n="s1.3;p45.73">Regarding interdependence, as Keohane and Nye stated, 'vulnerability' needs to be emphasised as well as the 'sensitivity' earlier formulated by Cooper (Cooper 1968). </s><s n="s2.3;p45.73">Keohane and Nye elaborated that less dependent actors tended to be empowered to exercise influence in order to set the rules of the game in asymmetrical interdependence relationships (Keohane and Nye 1989, 11-19). </s><s n="s3.3;p45.73">In this sense, it can be generally accepted that the relatively superior country in economic capability which is able to coerce its trading partners into accepting its request has little preference for a formal institution of economic co-operation than more vulnerable partners. </s></p><p n="p46.73"><s n="s1.2;p46.73">In contrast to this, the relatively weaker country is more likely to have preference to institution of economic co-operation. </s><s n="s2.2;p46.73">As political neo-realists named it as 'binding thesis', the creation of formal institutions such as PTAs was believed to give developing countries increased 'voice opportunities' and enhanced bargaining power in the international trade regime (Grieco 1993, 331). </s></p><p n="p47.73"><s n="s1.2;p47.73">Such hypotheses clearly show that the bilateral trade arrangements were traditionally developed as a policy option of the weaker countries that wanted to be guaranteed an opportunity to sell their goods to a larger market, and by doing so, they sought to enhance their security under the influence of stronger countries. </s><s n="s2.2;p47.73">Even if the United States cannot be regarded as a weaker country, at least since the end of Bretton Woods system, the environment of international political economy certainly indicates declining American economic power. </s></p><p n="p48.73"><s n="s1.1;p48.73">The relatively decayed economic power of the United States was the fundamental factor which forced the main architect of postwar multilateral international trade regime to pursue bilateralism in spite of the censure that blamed them for 'self-contradictory' attitude. </s></p><p n="p49.73"><s n="s1.2;p49.73">From time to time, some critics attack the FTA policy of the United States on the grounds that the overwhelming super power pursues the weaker countries' trade policy (Jonquières 2004, 31-32). </s><s n="s2.2;p49.73">However, one can easily know that this criticism is off target if we consider the decreased power of the United States during the period that PTAs were expanding. </s></p><p n="p50.73"><s n="s1.4;p50.73">The arguments deployed so far reflect the so-called 'stumbling block' school who insist on the contradiction between multilateralism and bilateral PTAs. </s><s n="s2.4;p50.73">They assert that increasing regional trade arrangements will undermine the multilateral trade regime, whereas the 'building block' theorists emphasise the complementarity between expanding regionalism and the development of the multilateral trade regime. </s><s n="s3.4;p50.73">The latter has mainly explained the explosive increase of regional trade blocs, including East Asia, the only exception from the worldwide regionalism, as a progress towards ultimately integrated multilateralism. </s><s n="s4.4;p50.73">Open regionalism, which will be examined in the next section, reflects this view. </s></p><div2><head rend="italic">'Open regionalism' debate </head><p n="p51.73"><s n="s1.3;p51.73">The scholars emphasising the role of PTAs as a building block frequently quote an example of the upgrading of Asia Pacific Economic Corporation (APEC) forum by the United States in 1993. </s><s n="s2.3;p51.73">The APEC was originally proposed by Australia in the late 1980s and was strongly backed by Japan. </s><s n="s3.3;p51.73">In particular, Japan expected the restoration of leadership in East Asia through the establishment of APEC. The United States, at least until this stage, was satisfied with the role of friendly supporter and a key member. </s></p><p n="p52.73"><s n="s1.3;p52.73">President Clinton, however, ambitiously began to lead the discussion on regional trade liberalisation by hosting the first APEC summit meeting in Seattle in 1993. </s><s n="s2.3;p52.73">By being done in this way, the APEC annual meeting was remarkably upgraded from ministerial to summit level and subsequently ambitious timetable for regional trade liberalisation which pledged complete elimination of trade barriers by 2010 (by 2020 for developing member countries) was suggested in 1994. </s><s n="s3.3;p52.73">However, this blueprint was later revealed as an nominal political proclamation </s></p><p n="p53.73"><s n="s1.2;p53.73">The intention of the United States to avoid censure against leading 'closed' regional grouping, unlike the commitment for multilateralism, created the unique rule in managing the APEC. The APEC members did not exclusively dependent upon formal rules and stipulated provisions in implementing arrangements in trade liberalisation. </s><s n="s2.2;p53.73">Instead, consensus building and non-coercive recommendations from the peer members were emphasised as the main element of decision making. <ref target="BAWE_0293d-ftnote.004"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0293d-ftnote.004"><p n="pn1.2"><s n="s1.1;pn1.2">See <seg type="URL" n="http://www.apec.org/apec/ministerial_statements/annual_ministerial/1989_1st_apec_ministerial.html"/> </s></p><p n="pn2.2"><s n="s1.1;pn2.2">Accesed on 29/4/2006 </s></p></note><p n="p54.73"><s n="s1.1;p54.73">This voluntary co-operative mechanism was also facilitated the traditional type of social communication named the 'Asian Way' in Confucianism-based Asian countries. </s></p><p n="p55.73"><s n="s1.4;p55.73">Liberalists dubbed this new trend as 'open regionalism'. </s><s n="s2.4;p55.73">However, no concept generated more diverse interpretation than this term within the realm of international political economy since the establishment of the GATT regime. </s><s n="s3.4;p55.73">To begin with, simply speaking, by the definition of dictionary, 'open' structure is far from the nature of 'regionalism' and 'regionalism' can hardly be described by 'open' structure. </s><s n="s4.4;p55.73">Thus, the assessment about 'open regionalism' also varies, ranging from a historically new concept to distinguish the PTAs led by the United States since the 1980s to mere rhetoric dazzling people. </s></p><p n="p56.73"><s n="s1.3;p56.73">Liberalists denied the fear of re-emergence of exclusiveness and protectionism which might be generated from the competition among three regional powers - the United States, EU and Japan -which formed the tripolarity after the end of the Cold War (Gamble and Payne 1996, 251). </s><s n="s2.3;p56.73">Even the radical strategic trade policy of the United States was advocated on the grounds that it was an attempt to stimulate foreign competition rather than avoid it (Gamble and Payne 1996, 252). </s><s n="s3.3;p56.73">Post-Cold War moves towards regionalism were also strongly supported under the name of open regionalism. </s></p><p n="p57.73"><s n="s1.2;p57.73">They stressed the proliferation of the resultant benefit of unilateral trade liberalisation implemented by one member (Drysdale and Garnaut 1993, 187)<ref target="BAWE_0293d-ftnote.005"/> and the lack of obstacles to entry for outsiders (Gamble and Payne 1996, 251). </s><s n="s2.2;p57.73">From the perspective of liberalism, thus, the non-discriminatory nature of open regionalism is consistent with the spirit of the GATT. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0293d-ftnote.005"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Drysdale and Garnaut described the benefit of unilateral trade liberalisation as a 'prisoner's delight' in contrast with the 'prisoner's dilemma' which warned the unfavourable outcome the absence of actors' co-operation can provoke. </s></p></note><p n="p58.73"><s n="s1.2;p58.73">On the other hand, economic realists<ref target="BAWE_0293d-ftnote.006"/> have viewed the intention of the United States to support the emergence of regional trade bloc in Asia Pacific as a mean to threaten to force unwilling Europe to conclude the long-lasting Uruguay Round negotiation. </s><s n="s2.2;p58.73">Likewise, the NAFTA was also perceived as one of the potential alternatives the United States was willing to choose if the multilateral negotiation would fail (Hurrell 1994, 266). </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0293d-ftnote.006"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">'Economic realists' as a theoretical strand on IPE is used as the perspective emphasising the state actor's willingness and aim in determining international economic policy, which is derived from classical realism in international relations theory, for example, Hans Morgenthau and E.H.Carr. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">See Nesadurai (2002) for details. </s></p></note><p n="p59.73"><s n="s1.3;p59.73">This argument is also substantiated by the fact that even American ideologists overtly began to warn reluctant negotiators of the emergence of trans-Pacific deal, and resurrection of aggressive unilateralism by the United States if the Uruguay Round failed (Bergsten and Noland 1993, 8-9). </s><s n="s2.3;p59.73">They argued that the pursuit of open regionalism really performed a function of a lever to jump-start the negotiating procedure in stagnation. </s><s n="s3.3;p59.73">However, their statement, that emphasised the effectiveness of PTAs as a means of menace coping with the crisis of multilateralism, resulted in showing acknowledgement of the incompatibility - i.e. self-contradiction - between bilateral PTAs and multilateralism. </s></p><p n="p60.73"><s n="s1.3;p60.73">Moreover, one needs to distinguish the resultant historical event from the state actors' original intention at which their political behaviour aimed. </s><s n="s2.3;p60.73">Realists formulate that the fundamental goal of a state is to prevent others from achieving advance in their relative capabilities (Grieco 1993, 498). </s><s n="s3.3;p60.73">Also they intensively pay attention to the political frame -work of economic activities, which is exclusively led by the state (Gilpin 1987, 47)<ref target="BAWE_0293d-ftnote.007"/>. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0293d-ftnote.007"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Gilpin explains his perspective as 'state-centric' realism in distinction from 'system-centred' neo-realism by Kenneth Waltz. </s></p></note><p n="p61.73"><s n="s1.1;p61.73">In this sense, the unveiled intention of the United States to occupy the advantageous position in an ongoing negotiation by pursuing bilateral PTAs should not be overlooked from the perspective of economic realism. </s></p><p n="p62.73"><s n="s1.2;p62.73">This also shows the fact that the FTA policy of the United States was derived from its strategic incentive, which grounded in the objective to discover breakthrough by escaping from the stalled multilateral negotiation for trade liberalisation. </s><s n="s2.2;p62.73">This means that even the United States itself regarded the PTAs as contradictory, rather than complementary to multilateralism. </s></p><p n="p63.73"><s n="s1.3;p63.73">Moreover, in the light of the subsequent process, which bilateral PTAs led by the United States was rather accelerated after the conclusion of the Uruguay Round, the ostensible argument that US-led bilateralism was a detour (or shortcut) to reach multilateralism is not logically coherent unless it is hypocrisy. </s><s n="s2.3;p63.73">In reality, the United States pursued FTAs more vigorously since President Bush took office in 2000. </s><s n="s3.3;p63.73">A recent presumption shows that approximately 50% of US trade are supposed to occur with the FTA partners if all the negotiations underway and scheduled were successfully concluded (Schott 2004, 359). </s></p><p n="p64.73"><s n="s1.1;p64.73">A more surprising finding was the strengthening nexus of trade and security after the September 11 (Schott 2004, 364). <ref target="BAWE_0293d-ftnote.008"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0293d-ftnote.008"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">See Schott (2004) on details of current selection criteria for US FTA partners (Schott 2004, 356-71) </s></p></note><p n="p65.73"><s n="s1.1;p65.73">The exclusiveness of military alliance based on bilateral relationship will make it harder to restore multilateral coalition in international trade system. </s></p><p n="p66.73"><s n="s1.4;p66.73">Needless to say, the more issue divergence will take place, the harder the negotiation will conclude. </s><s n="s2.4;p66.73">Even liberal economists have condemned that the bilateral deals led by the United States became a vehicle for introducing extraneous issues such as intellectual property rights (IPR), labour standards and environment into the WTO (Bahgwati and Panagariya 2003). </s><s n="s3.4;p66.73">Further, a ridiculous incident that one witnesses the security issue in the WTO agendas list might be happened if the strong trade-security nexus would be persisted and deepened. </s><s n="s4.4;p66.73">The labour, environment and IPR agendas that are not related to trade were mainly introduced by the pressure of domestic lobbies of interest groups, but security issues, if it were realised, might be added by more coercive power than civil society. </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Conclusion</head><p n="p67.73"><s n="s1.3;p67.73">Increased PTAs should not be solely attributed the United States. </s><s n="s2.3;p67.73">Even the WTO was unable to deter the proliferation of bilateralism at a global level. </s><s n="s3.3;p67.73">Among 250 PTAs notified to the GATT / WTO up to 2002, more than half were created during just ten years after the establishment of the WTO. (<seg type="URL" n="www.wto.org/english/tratop_e/region_e/regfac_e.htm"/> accessed on 20/04/2006). </s></p><p n="p68.73"><s n="s1.2;p68.73">Notwithstanding this global trend, one should take into account the fact that postwar trade regime based on non-discriminatory treatment granted far more relative gain to the United States, rather than European countries that enjoyed trade preferences. </s><s n="s2.2;p68.73">The United States successfully obtained market access to efficiently exploit the devastated Western Europe by forcing the United Kingdom and other European countries to accept a multilateral system (Gilpin 1971, 58-59). </s></p><p n="p69.73"><s n="s1.1;p69.73">Considering this relative gain the United States took just after the end of World War Ⅱ, the reality that the supreme beneficiary of multilateral trade order clamors for bilateralism is certainly self-contradictory. </s></p><p n="p70.73"><s n="s1.4;p70.73">From the historical survey examined above, we can draw several implications about the key factors that affect the formation of PTAs and the evolution of regionalism. </s><s n="s2.4;p70.73">First of all, the role of hegemonic leadership is primarily important to facilitate the development of multilateral trade order. </s><s n="s3.4;p70.73">While the several rounds of multilateral negotiations, which voluntarily altered the GATT rules and agendas up to the 1960s, show the integral role of the United States as a postwar hegemon, the abortive regionalism among the LDCs in the 1960s-1970s can be attributed, at least partly, to the lack of hegemonic power. </s><s n="s4.4;p70.73">Particularly, increasingly important controversial issue, such as the distribution of 'adjustment cost' caused by the PTAs between the developed countries and developing countries, needs the sufficient contribution of hegemonic leader. </s></p><p n="p71.73"><s n="s1.2;p71.73">Secondly, the notion of 'open regionalism', in practice created by the United States, shows the self-contradictory nature of currently expanded bilateral PTAs. </s><s n="s2.2;p71.73">Although such justification offered a cornerstone to artificially change the traditional stance of the United States, as we can see from the fact that even liberalists acknowledged the incompatibility of the two, the priority in the allocation of resources for trade negotiation - e.g. distribution of civil servants or feasibility research - was unilaterally given to bilateralism rather than multilateralism. </s></p><p n="p72.73"><s n="s1.4;p72.73">Thirdly, the environment of multi-polarisation and economic instability after the end of the Cold War was likely to give rise to regionalism. </s><s n="s2.4;p72.73">Although joint efforts by business groups and government to restore multilateralism were partly made, they were subordinated by increasing economic uncertainty. </s><s n="s3.4;p72.73">As a result, states competitively pursued bilateral trade treaties for securing their own interest just in preparation for any eventuality. </s><s n="s4.4;p72.73">The United States also did not have willingness and capability to undertake the hegemonic role in international trade to alleviate increasing instability. </s></p><p n="p73.73"><s n="s1.2;p73.73">Despite the concerns from both multilateral purists and civil society group, the current wave for bilateral PTAs seems to be accelerated for the time being at least, in so far as the United States maintains bilateralist trade policy. </s><s n="s2.2;p73.73">However, in so far as the United States fail to demonstrates the persuasive reasons why the world's only superpower devote itself to pursue self-serving policies, its political and economic - except military - influence in the international trade regime will be eroded. </s></p></div1></body><back><div1 type="bibliography"><head>BIBLIOGRAPHY</head><p>Baghwati J, Panagariya A. Preferential Trading Areas and Multilateralism : Strangers, Friends or Foes. In: Jagdish Baghwati, Arvind Panagariya. <hi rend="italic">The Economics of Preferential Trade Agreements.</hi> Washington D.C.: AEI Press, 1996. </p><p>Bahgwati J. Regionalism and Multilateralism : An Overview. In: J. de Melo and A. Panagariya. <hi rend="italic">New Dimensions in Regional Integration.</hi> Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 1993. </p><p>Bergsten, C.Fred : Noland, Marcus. Introduction and Overview. In: C.Fred Begsten and Marcus Noland. <hi rend="italic">Pacific Dynamism and the International Economic System.</hi> Washington D.C.: Institute for Internationlal Economics, 1993; 3-13. </p><p>Bhagwati J., Panagariya A. Bilateral Trade Treaties are a sham. <hi rend="italic">Financial Times</hi> 14 July 2003. </p><p>Blake D., Walters R. <hi rend="italic">The Politics of Global Economic Relations.</hi> 4th., N.J.: Prentice-Hall, 1992. </p><p>Brander James A., Spencer B.J. Export Subsidies and International Market Share Rivalry. <hi rend="italic">Journal of International Economics</hi> ; 18(1-2): 83-100. </p><p>Crone D. Does Hegemony Matter? The Reorganization of the Pacific Political Economy. <hi rend="italic">World Politics</hi> 1993; 45(4). </p><p>Dresser D. Post-NAFTA Politics in Mexico. In: Carol Wise. <hi rend="italic">The Post-NAFTA Political Economy : Mexico and the Western Hemisphere.</hi> Pennsylvania State University Press: Pennsylvania, 1998; 221-256. </p><p>Drysdale P, Garnaut R. The Pacific : An Application of a General Theory of Economic Integration. In: Bergsten CF, Noland M. <hi rend="italic">Pacific Dynamism and the International Economic System.</hi> Washington D.C.: Institute for International Economics, 1993; 183-223. </p><p>Eichengreen B, Frankel J.A. Economic Regionalism : Evidence from Two Twentieth Century Episodes. <hi rend="italic">North American Journal of Economics and Finance</hi> 1995; 6(2): 89-106. </p><p>Evans J.W. The General Agreement on Tariffs and Trade. In: R.Gardner and M.Milikan. <hi rend="italic">The Global Partnerships.</hi> New York: Praeger, 1968. </p><p>Faezeh, Foroutan. Regional Integration in Sub-Saharan Africa. In: Jaime de Melo and Arvind Panagariya. <hi rend="italic">New Dimensions in Regional Integration.</hi> Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 1993; 234-277. </p><p>Gamble A, Payne A. Conclusion : The New Regionalism. In: Andrew Gamble and Anthony Payne. <hi rend="italic">Regionalism and World Order.</hi> London: Macmillan, 1996; 247-264. </p><p>Gilpin R. <hi rend="italic">Global Political Economy : Understanding the International Economic Order.</hi> Princeton and Oxford: Princeton University Press, 2001. </p><p>Gilpin R. The Politics of Transnational Economic Relations. In: Robert Keohane and Joseph Nye. <hi rend="italic">Transnational Relations and World Politics.</hi> Cambridge: Harvard University Press, 1971 . </p><p>Gilpin R. <hi rend="italic">The Political Economy of International Relations.</hi> Princeton: Princeton University Press, 1987. </p><p>Grieco J.M. Understanding the Problem of International Cooperation : The Limits of Neoliberal Institutionalism and the Future of Realist Theory. In: David A. Baldwin. <hi rend="italic">Neorealism and Neoliberalism.</hi> New York: Columbia University Press, 1993; 301-338. </p><p>Hurrell A. Regionalism in the Americas. In: Louise Fawcett and Andrew Hurrell. <hi rend="italic">Regionalism in World Politics : Regional Organization and International Order.</hi> Oxford: Oxford University Press, 1994; 250-282. </p><p>Irwin D.A. Multilateral and Bilateral Trade Policies in the World Trading System : An Historical Perspective. In: Jaime de Melo and Arvind Panagariya. <hi rend="italic">New Dimensions in Regional Integration.</hi> New York: Cambridge University Press, 1993; 90-119. </p><p>Jonquières G.D. Comment. In: Jeffrey J. Schott. <hi rend="italic">Free Trade Agreements : US Strtegies and Priorities.</hi> Washington D.C.: Institute of International Economics, 2004; 30-33. </p><p>Kenwood A.G, Lougheed A.L. <hi rend="italic">The Growth of the International Economy : 1820-1960 An Introductory Text.</hi> London: Allen and Unwin, 1971. </p><p>Keohane R.O, Nye J.S. <hi rend="italic">Power and Interdependence.</hi> 2nd., New York: Longman, 1989. </p><p>Kindleberger C.P. <hi rend="italic">The world in depression, 1929-1939.</hi> Berkeley: University of California Press, 1986. </p><p>Krasner S.D. State Power and the Structure of International Trade. <hi rend="italic">World Politics</hi></p><p>Krugman P. Regionalism versus multilateralism : Analytical Notes. In: Arvind Panagariya, de Melo J. <hi rend="italic">New Dimensions in Regional Integration.</hi> New York: Cambridge University Press, 1993; . </p><p>Lawrence R.Z. <hi rend="italic">Regionalism, Multilateralism and Deeper Integration.</hi> Washington D.C.: Brooking Institution, 1996. </p><p>Mansfield E,D, Milner H.V. The New Wave of Regionalism. <hi rend="italic">International Organization</hi> 1999; 53(3): 589-627. </p><p>Nesadurai H. Globalisation and Economic Regionalism : A Survey and Critique of the Literature. In: <hi rend="italic">CSGR Working Paper No.108/02.</hi> Coventry: Center for the Study of Globalisation and Regionalisation, 2002. </p><p>Noguès, Quintanilla. Latin America's Integration and the Multilateral System. In: Jaime de Melo and Arvind Panagariya. <hi rend="italic">New Dimensions in Regional Integration.</hi> Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 1993; 278-318. </p><p>Panagariya A. The Regionalism Debate : An Overview. <hi rend="italic">The World Economy</hi> ; 22(4): 477-511. </p><p>Schott J.J. Assessing US FTA Policy. In: Jeffrey J.Schott. <hi rend="italic">Free Trade Agreements : US Startegies and Priorities.</hi> Washington D.C.: Institute for International Economics, 2004; 359-381. </p><p>Schott J.J. The GATT Ministerial : A Postmortem. <hi rend="italic">Challenge</hi> 1983; 26(2): 40-45. </p><p>Spero J.E. <hi rend="italic">The Politics of International Economic Relations.</hi> 2nd., New York: St. Martins, 1981. </p><p>Thurow L.C. <hi rend="italic">Head to Head : The Coming Economic Battle among Japan, Europe, and America.</hi> New York: Warner Books, 1993. </p><p>Torre, Augusto de la., Kelly M.R. <hi rend="italic">Regional Trade Arrangements.</hi> Washington D.C.: International Monetary Fund, 1992. </p><p>Viner J. <hi rend="italic">The Customs Union Issue.</hi> New York: Chicago University Press, 1950. </p><p>Wyatt-Walter A. Regionalism, Globalisation and World Economic Order. In: Louise Fawcett. <hi rend="italic">Regionalism in World Politics : Regional Organization and International Order.</hi> Oxford: Oxford University Press, 1994; 74-121. </p></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
