<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_0296b" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Key learnings on Entrepreneurial Finance.</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">deleted: header: module name, student number; footer: page numbers</note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">deleted: cover sheet</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">4</p><p n="date">2006-05</p><p n="module title">Entrepreneurial Finance</p><p n="module code">WB9545</p><p n="genre family">Explanation</p><p n="discipline">Business</p><p n="disciplinary group">SS</p><p n="grade">M</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">2309</p><p n="number of s-units">140</p><p n="number of p">46</p><p n="number of tables">0</p><p n="number of figures">3</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">3</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">3</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">16.5</p><p n="average s-units per p">3.0</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">m</p><p n="year of birth">1967</p><p n="first language">Pulaar</p><p n="education">OSA</p><p n="course">MBA</p><p n="student ID">0296</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><docTitle><titlePart rend="bold">Key learnings on Entrepreneurial Finance. </titlePart></docTitle></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Finance definition and introduction</head><p n="p1.46"><s n="s1.2;p1.46">Entrepreneurial Finance is about data (collecting information) and cash (raising funds), about asking the right questions among which: what's attractive for investors? </s><s n="s2.2;p1.46">How to improve our business to raise sufficient money for our investment? </s></p><p n="p2.46"><s n="s1.1;p2.46">The manager has to be in control of the balance going from Goals and Products/Services to the 5 year strategy plan, via 2 routes: </s></p><list type="ordered"><item>a/ Revenues and expenses on one side</item><item>b/ Assets and Financing on the other</item></list><figure id="BAWE_0296b-fig.001"><head rend="underlined bold italic">Figure 1: Business Process (slightly adapted from W. Cockrum concept)</head></figure><p n="p3.46"><s n="s1.2;p3.46">However, Finance is NOT about crunching numbers. </s><s n="s2.2;p3.46">To assess a business, any manager should know what to expect from the calculations before doing them. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p4.46"><s n="s1.4;p4.46">Businesses are not stand-alone entities. </s><s n="s2.4;p4.46">They are part of a wide network called market. </s><s n="s3.4;p4.46">Decisions within businesses cannot override the market rules. </s><s n="s4.4;p4.46">The market will remember any manager "cheating" it. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Diagnosing a firm</head><p n="p5.46"><s n="s1.2;p5.46">Before investing or exiting any business, investors need to diagnose a company. </s><s n="s2.2;p5.46">There are very thorough diagnostics tools but also quick ways to assess a business: SWOT<ref target="BAWE_0296b-ftnote.001"/> analysis, Cash Flow analysis and Ratios analysis </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0296b-ftnote.001"><p n="pn1.2"><s rend="italic" n="s1.1;pn1.2">Strengths, weaknesses, Opportunities and Threats </s></p><p n="pn2.2"><s rend="italic" n="s1.1;pn2.2">OM = Operations Management </s></p></note><p n="p6.46"><s n="s1.3;p6.46">SWOT analysis is the first and foremost way to have a good overview of the situations. </s><s n="s2.3;p6.46">The SWOT analysis must be done by looking at various functions: management, marketing, operations, finance For example, the SWOT can show that there is no backup (team) but one manager on which the success of a firm relies. </s><s n="s3.3;p6.46">To diversify risks, a life insurance must then be tied to the single manager. </s></p><p n="p7.46"><s n="s1.6;p7.46">Cash Flow analysis is crucial to decide on the health of a corporate. </s><s n="s2.6;p7.46">A quick way to assess the cash position of a business is to write the cash sources and uses, from which one can assess the most important source and uses. </s><s n="s3.6;p7.46">In CLC case, that pointed us towards Receivables and Inventory issues being financed by Account/Notes payables and Bank short-term loans. </s><s n="s4.6;p7.46">We must always base our analysis on cash flow, NOT accounting. </s><s n="s5.6;p7.46">Cash Flow analysis points directly to what's wrong in the business. </s><s n="s6.6;p7.46">By doing it, we can find another source of funding for long production cycle businesses: e.g. prepayments. </s></p><p n="p8.46"><s n="s1.8;p8.46">Ratios analysis is the third tool applicable. </s><s n="s2.8;p8.46">It allows to measure financial issues. </s><s n="s3.8;p8.46">However, it is important to know the standard ratios of the industry. </s><s n="s4.8;p8.46">In fact, diagnosing ratios (data) should drive our conclusions. </s><s n="s5.8;p8.46">There is no need to do ALL the ratios mechanically but one can focus on important and relevant one to provide evidences. </s><s n="s6.8;p8.46">Again, managers must know what to expect from those ratios even before running them. </s><s n="s7.8;p8.46">For example, a quick way to assess the ROI is to use the rule of thumb called "rule of 72". </s><s n="s8.8;p8.46">Also, one can focus on specific months where the balance sheet shows weakness and seek for precision: break down items like profits by unit (cars, seats etc) to better analyse the margins (yield management). </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Business valuation/forecast</head><p n="p9.46"><s n="s1.6;p9.46">Once the diagnostic done, the next step can be valuing the business. </s><s n="s2.6;p9.46">It is very difficult to value a business. </s><s n="s3.6;p9.46">Again, there is no need to start with complexity. </s><s n="s4.6;p9.46">We can go for the "back of the envelope" calculations to value businesses as a first assessment. </s><s n="s5.6;p9.46">A simple valuation can be comparing with actual sales within similar industry. </s><s n="s6.6;p9.46">Academic concepts are important but in reality, the firm price is negotiated between the buyer and the seller. </s></p><p n="p10.46"><s n="s1.5;p10.46">At the Venture Capital cycle (early stages), we can look at revenues/EBIT multiples, even though this is much risky. </s><s n="s2.5;p10.46">These multiples are given by the market (2.5 to 7.5 in general but there are exceptions). </s><s n="s3.5;p10.46">Indeed, we must bear in mind that multiples are conversely proportional to debt costs and a smart seller will always try to maximise earnings before putting the firm on the market. </s><s n="s4.5;p10.46">From observation, the rule is simple for VCs<ref target="BAWE_0296b-ftnote.002"/>: value = ¼ * (multiple*EBIT<ref target="BAWE_0296b-ftnote.003"/>). </s><s n="s5.5;p10.46">This is because only one out of 4 businesses will be successful. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0296b-ftnote.002"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">VC = Venture Capital </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0296b-ftnote.003"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">EBITDA for "zero-assets" businesses (e.g. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">IT consultancy) </s></p></note><p n="p11.46"><s n="s1.7;p11.46">At the Private Equity cycle (later stages), we can look at Adjusted Net Present Values. </s><s n="s2.7;p11.46">As operations (investments in assets) are different from finance (financing in liabilities), the discount rate is dissimilar: WACC for assets (NPV) and cost of debts for financing (interests rates). </s><s n="s3.7;p11.46">For the Adjusted NPV, we will use WACC. However, there is an issue with taxation: the tax is embedded in the interest rates and WACC. We must discount those taxes from the actual rates. </s><s n="s4.7;p11.46">Consistency is crucial to make meaningful figures in the business valuation: use WACC before tax and EBIT OR use WACC and EBIT minus Tax. </s><s n="s5.7;p11.46">Another issue lies on the residual values (equipments). </s><s n="s6.7;p11.46">These residuals must be considered with different options (price level, inflation impact, probability of occurrence). </s><s n="s7.7;p11.46">The rule of thumb is to double the value and discount with the relevant rate before tax. </s></p><p n="p12.46"><s n="s1.3;p12.46">As these valuations are based on future earnings or cash flows, any financial planning must be "reasonable", with a high-low band including a "most probable" scenario. </s><s n="s2.3;p12.46">We also need to include the funding level, the price changes (inflation). </s><s n="s3.3;p12.46">No matter how wide it is, the gap between budgets versus actual figures is not the best way to measure management qualities </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Business process: Buying, funding, selling</head><p n="p13.46"><s n="s1.4;p13.46">This is the heart of Entrepreneurial Finance. </s><s n="s2.4;p13.46">Businesses should forecast when they will need cash long before running out of it. </s><s n="s3.4;p13.46">For investors, getting out (exiting or harvesting) is as important as getting in (investing). </s><s n="s4.4;p13.46">The exit (harvest) is as important as the entrance in any investment. </s></p><p n="p14.46"><s n="s1.1;p14.46">As fundraising never stops; to be successful, managers must hit their plans. </s></p><p n="p15.46"><s n="s1.3;p15.46">We must separate Short term and Long Term financing which have different objectives. </s><s n="s2.3;p15.46">While we aim to optimize for long term, we also aim to survive for the short term. </s><s n="s3.3;p15.46">There are exceptions but basically, long/short term liabilities respectively finance long/short term assets<ref target="BAWE_0296b-ftnote.004"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0296b-ftnote.004"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">There are exceptions to that rule like when the company is over-capitalized </s></p></note><div2><head rend="bold">1/Buying (acquiring, entering)</head><p n="p16.46"><s n="s1.2;p16.46">Once the diagnostic and valuations done, we can think of the acquisition process. </s><s n="s2.2;p16.46">An acquisition has multiple alternatives: acquire &amp; diversify, expand in existing markets, slow growth and take cash from business or sell. </s></p><p n="p17.46"><s n="s1.1;p17.46">Here, there are two important rules to remember: </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p18.46"><s n="s1.2;p18.46">By acquiring assets, we have to use the "appropriate" period, discount rates; we should never mingle several decisions (assess buildings and assets lease for example). </s><s n="s2.2;p18.46">The basic question to analyse is "what if we don't go for it?" </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p19.46"><s n="s1.1;p19.46">For small business acquisitions, we should never ever acquire the liabilities but only the assets </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">2/Funding</head><p n="p20.46"><s n="s1.1;p20.46">Managers must always go for smart money, not more money. </s></p><div3><head rend="underlined">Short-term</head><p n="p21.46"><s n="s1.5;p21.46">There are different short-term loans, each with its own positive and negative sides. </s><s n="s2.5;p21.46">Stretching the payables is one way to avoid WC strains but might hurt the relationship with suppliers or customers. </s><s n="s3.5;p21.46">Basically, short-term funding is aimed at financing the WC. For seasonal problems in contrast with secular issues, a short term loan like the revolving credit is required. </s><s n="s4.5;p21.46">Bankers always look at the cash conversion cycle before granting a loan. </s><s n="s5.5;p21.46">Generally, they consider 80% of receivables plus 50% of inventory to quickly assess how much to lend. </s></p><p n="p22.46"><s n="s1.1;p22.46">When the WC problem is not cyclical but secular, the solution is long term external financing. </s></p></div3><div3><head rend="underlined">Long Term</head><p n="p23.46"><s n="s1.1;p23.46">Long term financing is driven by EBIT and funding is done by different types of Capital, at different life stages; e.g. personal funds or VCs for early growth of the S curve. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0296b-fig.002"><head rend="underlined bold italic">Figure 2: S curve showing growth versus time</head></figure><p n="p24.46"><s n="s1.7;p24.46">VCs can decide in 1 hour whether they will invest or not in a company. </s><s n="s2.7;p24.46">It is very similar to interviewers who can judge in 5 minutes whether someone will fit to the company. </s><s n="s3.7;p24.46">It is OK to make losses at VC level. </s><s n="s4.7;p24.46">One must insure however to get higher returns once every three (four in the UK) trials. </s><s n="s5.7;p24.46">Faced to dilemmas, we must remember that "deals you do not do are those to worry about". </s><s n="s6.7;p24.46">Eventually, it is a matter of the investor's risk profile (mindset). </s><s n="s7.7;p24.46">The recent trend is showing that VCs are moving towards Private Equities and financing at later stages. </s></p><p n="p25.46"><s n="s1.4;p25.46">Lease is another huge source of financing and is often off book. </s><s n="s2.4;p25.46">It can be either on the assets side or the liabilities side. </s><s n="s3.4;p25.46">It allows to expand without tying up capital. </s><s n="s4.4;p25.46">Unless differences are high, it can be tricky to decide which way to go between leasing and buying through a loan, especially because discount rates are linked to uncertainties. </s></p><p n="p26.46"><s n="s1.1;p26.46">Whatever the choices are, one must keep in mind the pyramid, the PE ratios and the EPS. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0296b-fig.003"><head rend="underlined bold italic">Figure 3: Financial Pyramid (how to capitalize a firm)</head></figure><p n="p27.46"><s n="s1.3;p27.46">Deal structures can be complex and hide smart objectives. </s><s n="s2.3;p27.46">Therefore, managers must always keep flexibility to be attractive to investors. </s><s n="s3.3;p27.46">Example: setting preferred stocks in a capital structure has many advantages among which: </s></p><list type="ordered"><item>a/ controlling the business with a smaller share of capital</item><item>b/ avoiding capital tax gain (getting money out tax-free)</item><item>c/ tying results to management via soft stocks (watchdog)</item></list><p n="p28.46"><s n="s1.2;p28.46">Issuing convertibles is a flexible option although final benefits are linked to market share prices at the time of conversion. </s><s n="s2.2;p28.46">Convertibles are better to operate at lower costs than common BUT for risk strategy, common is better because of the risk of hung convertibles </s></p><p n="p29.46"><s n="s1.1;p29.46">For large deals (UK), mezzanine debt is very helpful to avoid straining the WC (revolving credit). </s></p></div3><div3><head rend="underlined">Leverage</head><p n="p30.46"><s n="s1.2;p30.46">Within an industry, the leverage level is proportional to the scale of the firm. </s><s n="s2.2;p30.46">In general, leverage is great in an upmarket, bad otherwise (value falls more than equity). </s></p><p n="p31.46"><s n="s1.2;p31.46">When market value of assets is higher, one can extract the equity and borrow more money to invest in new products (e.g. </s><s n="s2.2;p31.46">Real Estates business) </s></p><p n="p32.46"><s n="s1.5;p32.46">As the debt decreases and the cash inflows increases, we get a better debt capacity and hence can leverage further. </s><s n="s2.5;p32.46">Yet, we should never go to limit values (optimization). </s><s n="s3.5;p32.46">It is dangerous and inflexible. </s><s n="s4.5;p32.46">In a falling market, equity is worthless. </s><s n="s5.5;p32.46">Moreover, one difference between debt and equity is the tax issues. </s></p><list type="bulleted"><head>Two rules of thumb to memorize about the debt ratio: </head><item>1/ debt is 5 times equity; </item><item>2/ fixed charges of interest must have 2 times of coverage (range of 1.4 to 2.5)</item></list><p n="p33.46"><s n="s1.1;p33.46">In conclusion, we should repay long term debt with operations Cash Flow first, then with assets liquidation. </s></p></div3></div2><div2><head rend="bold">3/Selling (divesting, exiting, harvesting)</head><p n="p34.46"><s n="s1.2;p34.46">Selling to strategic buyers - who expect economies of scale- yields more return than selling to financial buyers. </s><s n="s2.2;p34.46">However, best deals are made when you are in the right place at the right time. </s></p><p n="p35.46"><s n="s1.3;p35.46">Knowing that, managers must answer to a key question: "what is the fatal flaw? </s><s n="s2.3;p35.46">What's NOT going to make the deal work? </s><s n="s3.3;p35.46">(The exit, the covenants etc). </s></p><p n="p36.46"><s n="s1.2;p36.46">Unlike common thinking, going public (IPO) is expensive and is NOT an objective as such. </s><s n="s2.2;p36.46">Thus, it cannot be considered as a way to harvest </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Guarantees</head><p n="p37.46"><s n="s1.3;p37.46">A banker, bearing more risk to accept the loan, would generally add more covenants. </s><s n="s2.3;p37.46">Also, the receivables quality -on which a loan can be based- is linked to the client reputation. </s><s n="s3.3;p37.46">For example, the UK government would be more reliable than a small firm. </s></p><p n="p38.46"><s n="s1.3;p38.46">There are intangible guarantees like relationship. </s><s n="s2.3;p38.46">The track record, the relationship and the market status of the industry are important for Private Equity Firms. </s><s n="s3.3;p38.46">Seeking partnership is better than fostering competition. </s></p><p n="p39.46"><s n="s1.1;p39.46">Stopping the dividends payments is a must to convince the banker about the manager's commitment when the WC is strained for example. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Management and Team dynamics</head><p n="p40.46"><s n="s1.4;p40.46">Even lacking complete information, one can invest on a business by investing on the management. </s><s n="s2.4;p40.46">Management is key to any investment and is what's financed, not assets<ref target="BAWE_0296b-ftnote.005"/>. </s><s n="s3.4;p40.46">Any single case of bankruptcy is caused by one person's control. </s><s n="s4.4;p40.46">Indeed, functions processes (management, marketing etc) are totally depending on companies' life stage and managers who understand that are those who are successful. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0296b-ftnote.005"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Some scholars argue that the industry is as important as the management </s></p></note><p n="p41.46"><s n="s1.1;p41.46">Managing growth, entrepreneurial culture implies knowing the drivers at different growth stages; e.g. a good manager is not always a good founder and vice-versa. </s></p><p n="p42.46"><s n="s1.5;p42.46">Management control of equity is not crucial indeed. </s><s n="s2.5;p42.46">The best example is that any reasonable person would prefer owning 1% of Google than 51% of a corner shop. </s><s n="s3.5;p42.46">If the reason for seeking control is to retain job, it is better to meet plan instead. </s><s n="s4.5;p42.46">Oddly enough, non financial factors can impact a firm; as managers get older (and richer), they tend to be conservative ("less hungry") and that affects their company's profitability. </s><s n="s5.5;p42.46">New management/strategy is critical to increase growth further. </s></p><p n="p43.46"><s n="s1.8;p43.46">Beside management, teamwork is very important. </s><s n="s2.8;p43.46">A great business opportunity involves having a team that have knowledge of industry and who have worked together before. </s><s n="s3.8;p43.46">A biggest mistake of managers: expect others to be like you. </s><s n="s4.8;p43.46">In short, keys factors are: strong team, good balance action/analysis and efficient diagnostic tools. </s><s n="s5.8;p43.46">They should focus on facts, not opinions. </s><s n="s6.8;p43.46">It's all about good people and managers should not economise on them but on other aspects of the firm. </s><s n="s7.8;p43.46">An excellent illustration is in Private Equity Funds businesses. </s><s n="s8.8;p43.46">Team members must be expert in a specific area (marketing, finance etc). </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Timing</head><p n="p44.46"><s n="s1.3;p44.46">Good managers always consider the sequence in financing overtime (capital structure flexibility) and optimize costs overtime. </s><s n="s2.3;p44.46">Timing is one clear advantage than one can use to negotiate deals. </s><s n="s3.3;p44.46">There is no way to know where the market is going; therefore, we have to be cautious in the funding options, not to close future opportunities of financing. </s></p><p n="p45.46"><s n="s1.4;p45.46">The principle of timing in financing is similar, no matter the business type and size (dynamic financing). </s><s n="s2.4;p45.46">The common concept for all cases was about timing issues today: thinking overtime rather than at a specific point of time. </s><s n="s3.4;p45.46">Some scholars argue that issuing equity is negative for the company. </s><s n="s4.4;p45.46">It might be the last resort but is definitely better in some cases to "buy time", to breathe. </s></p><p n="p46.46"><s n="s1.2;p46.46">In conclusion, all concepts presented in this paper are important to grasp, no matter which role one person is fulfilling. </s><s n="s2.2;p46.46">All managerial decisions are linked to financing issues and that criteria cannot be ignored during the decision process. </s></p></div1></body><back/></text></TEI.2>
