<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_0300c" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Forecast Performance for Malibu Garden Furniture Ltd</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">deleted: Cover sheet, including tutor's comments</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">4</p><p n="date">2006-10</p><p n="module title">Accounting and Financial Management</p><p n="module code">IB8010</p><p n="genre family">Problem question</p><p n="discipline">Business</p><p n="disciplinary group">SS</p><p n="grade">D</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">704</p><p n="number of s-units">43</p><p n="number of p">29</p><p n="number of tables">1</p><p n="number of figures">1</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">0</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">0</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">16.4</p><p n="average s-units per p">1.5</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">m</p><p n="year of birth">1975</p><p n="first language">English</p><p n="education">OSA</p><p n="course">DLMBA</p><p n="student ID">0300</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><docTitle><titlePart rend="bold">Forecast Performance for Malibu Garden Furniture Ltd</titlePart></docTitle></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Introduction</head><p n="p1.29"><s n="s1.4;p1.29">Burt Lanchester of Malibu Garden Furniture Ltd has provided forecasts of costs and cash flow information for garden chairs that he intends to begin manufacturing and selling in January 2006. </s><s n="s2.4;p1.29">The data that he has provided will be analysed to produce a profit forecast as well as a cash flow forecast. </s><s n="s3.4;p1.29">The profit forecast will give an estimate of future performance at different levels of sales and at different selling prices, whilst the cash flow forecast will give an indication of the ability of the business to survive with or without additional funding or overdraft facility. </s><s n="s4.4;p1.29">Recommendations will be made on how performance can be improved. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Contribution Per Chair</head><p n="p2.29"><s n="s1.2;p2.29">Each chair, when sold, contributes an amount of money to the fixed costs of the company. </s><s n="s2.2;p2.29">Once the fixed costs have been covered, the remainder is profit for the business. </s></p><p n="p3.29"><s n="s1.1;p3.29">Sales price per unit: £70 </s></p><p n="p4.29"><s n="s1.1;p4.29">Less variable costs per unit: £12.50 + £7.25 + 2(£7.50) + £6.25 + £4.50 </s></p><p n="p5.29"><s n="s1.1;p5.29">Contribution per chair: <hi rend="bold">£24.50</hi> </s></p><p n="p6.29"><s n="s1.1;p6.29">Repeating the calculations for a sales price 10% higher (i.e. £77): </s></p><p n="p7.29"><s n="s1.1;p7.29">Contribution per chair: <hi rend="bold">£31.50</hi> </s></p><p n="p8.29"><s n="s1.1;p8.29">Repeating the calculations for a sales price 10% lower (i.e. £63): </s></p><p n="p9.29"><s n="s1.1;p9.29">Contribution per chair: <hi rend="bold">£17.50</hi> </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Break Even Point</head><p n="p10.29"><s n="s1.1;p10.29">To break even, total contribution must equal the fixed costs: Contribution x (number of units) = 45,000 </s></p><p n="p11.29"><s n="s1.1;p11.29">Therefore the number of units required to break even = <hi rend="bold">1837</hi> </s></p><p n="p12.29"><s n="s1.1;p12.29">At 10% higher sales price and 10% lower demand (=2160 units): </s></p><p n="p13.29"><s n="s1.1;p13.29">The number of units required to break even = <hi rend="bold">1439</hi> </s></p><p n="p14.29"><s n="s1.1;p14.29">At 10% lower sales price and 10% higher demand (=2640 units): </s></p><p n="p15.29"><s n="s1.1;p15.29">The number of units required to break even = <hi rend="bold">2572</hi> </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Operating Profit</head><p n="p16.29"><s n="s1.1;p16.29">When the total contribution exceeds fixed costs, the additional amount is profit: </s></p><p n="p17.29"><s n="s1.1;p17.29">Profit = Total Contribution - Fixed Costs </s></p><p n="p18.29"><s n="s1.1;p18.29">Where Total Contribution = (Contribution per unit) x (number of units) = 24.5 x 2,400 = 58,800 </s></p><p n="p19.29"><s n="s1.1;p19.29">Hence Profit = 58,800 - 45,000 = <hi rend="bold">£13,800</hi> </s></p><p n="p20.29"><s n="s1.1;p20.29">At 10% higher sales price, profit = <hi rend="bold">£23,040</hi> </s></p><p n="p21.29"><s n="s1.1;p21.29">At 10% lower sales price, profit = <hi rend="bold">£1,200</hi> </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Margin of Safety</head><p n="p22.29"><s n="s1.2;p22.29">The margin of safety indicates the volume of sales that can fall short of the forecast sales, before the company falls below the break-even point. </s><s n="s2.2;p22.29">It is hence the forecast volume of sales minus the volume to break even: </s></p><p n="p23.29"><s n="s1.1;p23.29">2400 - 1837 = <hi rend="bold">563 units</hi> </s></p><p n="p24.29"><s n="s1.1;p24.29">At 10% higher sales price, margin of safety = <hi rend="bold">731 units</hi> </s></p><p n="p25.29"><s n="s1.1;p25.29">At 10% lower sales price, margin of safety = <hi rend="bold">68 units</hi> </s></p><p n="p26.29"><s n="s1.1;p26.29">The resulting Profit - Volume graph for the three sales prices is provided here: </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0300c-fig.001"><head rend="bold">Profit-Volume Chart - Malibu Garden Furniture Ltd</head></figure><table id="BAWE_0300c-tab.001"><head rend="bold">Monthly Cash Flow Forecast for 2006 (£)</head><row><cell/></row></table></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Conclusions and Recommendations</head><p n="p27.29"><s n="s1.3;p27.29">At the current forecast levels, the company is going to face bankruptcy unless it receives additional funding in the form of a loan, or a higher overdraft limit is allowed by the bank. </s><s n="s2.3;p27.29">In February the closing cash is -£13,150 yet the current overdraft limit is only £10,000. </s><s n="s3.3;p27.29">The problem becomes more severe in March and April and then slowly improves as sales increase. </s></p><p n="p28.29"><s n="s1.4;p28.29">A further problem is that the company is not going to have enough chairs to meet demand at the forecast levels. </s><s n="s2.4;p28.29">If it manufactures 200 chairs per month, then in May it will already have run out of chairs. </s><s n="s3.4;p28.29">The recommendation here is to alter the production schedule so that slightly more chairs are produced in the spring/summer months, and less in the autumn/winter months. </s><s n="s4.4;p28.29">Obviously this will affect the monthly costs of labour and purchases in the cash flow forecast, </s></p><p n="p29.29"><s n="s1.5;p29.29">At a 10% higher sales price, the profit is greater for any given level of sales (as per the profit-volume graph). </s><s n="s2.5;p29.29">On the whole, larger amounts of cash will come into the company in the same space of time, and so the closing cash will be higher and also less overdraft (or loan) will be required. </s><s n="s3.5;p29.29">The margin of safety is also higher. </s><s n="s4.5;p29.29">The reverse is true if the sales price is 10% lower. </s><s n="s5.5;p29.29">Hence the recommendation is to increase the sales price, and also to obtain funding (or an increased overdraft limit) if the closing cash in any given month still exceeds the current overdraft limit. </s></p></div1></body><back/></text></TEI.2>
