<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_0300a" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Waite First Securities - Assignment B</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">deleted: Cover sheet, including tutor's comments</note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">deleted: tutor's comments throughout text</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">4</p><p n="date">2006-07</p><p n="module title">Modelling and Analysis for Management</p><p n="module code">IB8200</p><p n="genre family">Exercise</p><p n="discipline">Business</p><p n="disciplinary group">SS</p><p n="grade">M</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">2210</p><p n="number of s-units">122</p><p n="number of p">74</p><p n="number of tables">4</p><p n="number of figures">8</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">1</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">0</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">18.1</p><p n="average s-units per p">1.6</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">m</p><p n="year of birth">1975</p><p n="first language">English</p><p n="education">OSA</p><p n="course">DLMBA</p><p n="student ID">0300</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><docTitle><titlePart rend="underlined bold">Waite First Securities - Assignment B</titlePart></docTitle></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined">Question 1</head><p n="p1.74"><s n="s1.7;p1.74">Brenda Hagarty has been asked by Harold Gagnon to investigate three stocks. </s><s n="s2.7;p1.74">Harold would like to buy one of the three stocks to add to his portfolio but he's not sure which one. </s><s n="s3.7;p1.74">He is approaching retirement and already has a number of risky stocks in his portfolio. </s><s n="s4.7;p1.74">He is looking for a stock that performs well in both an up or down S&amp;P 500 market, and has asked Brenda to perform a beta analysis on the stocks to work out which is the best stock to buy. </s><s n="s5.7;p1.74">Harold understands that the beta analysis will indicate the risks attached to each stock, and he's asked Brenda to calculate these beta values. </s><s n="s6.7;p1.74">He's also asked Brenda to prepare an explanation for him on how to interpret the beta values. </s><s n="s7.7;p1.74">He needs this information by tomorrow. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined">Question 2</head><p n="p2.74"><s n="s1.2;p2.74">The relationship being hypothesised is that the change in the company stock price is related to the change in the S&amp;P 500 stock price. </s><s n="s2.2;p2.74">The hypothesis is that the relationship between the two is sufficiently linear to be modelled using a linear relationship: </s></p><p n="p3.74"><s rend="italic" n="s1.1;p3.74">Company Stock Price = a + beta( S&amp;P500 ) </s></p><p n="p4.74"><s n="s1.3;p4.74">where the Company Stock Price is the dependent variable, and the S&amp;P500 Price is the independent variable. </s><s n="s2.3;p4.74">The hypothesis is that the relationship is a positive relationship in that as the S&amp;P 500 price rises, so does the company stock price. </s><s n="s3.3;p4.74">Likewise, as the S&amp;P 500 price falls, so does the company stock price. </s></p><p n="p5.74"><s n="s1.1;p5.74">We hypothesise that a change in one variable (the S&amp;P 500) impacts upon the other (the company stock price) and that the relationship is a simple linear regression. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined">Question 3</head><p n="p6.74"><s n="s1.3;p6.74">Brenda has been asked to perform a beta analysis because this will provide an indication of the risk attached to each of the stocks. </s><s n="s2.3;p6.74">More specifically, the beta coefficient gives an indication of the sensitivity of each stock's return to that of the market (S&amp;P 500) portfolio. </s><s n="s3.3;p6.74">A high beta coefficient value would indicate a high sensitivity and a higher risk. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined">Question 4</head><p n="p7.74"><s n="s1.1;p7.74">If Brenda uses Excel's regression tool, the residuals, standardised residuals, residual plots and line fit plots would also be useful. </s></p><p n="p8.74"><s n="s1.5;p8.74">The <hi rend="bold">line fit plot</hi> is a scatter diagram of all the company stock prices against the S&amp;P 500 prices, with the line of best fit superimposed on top. </s><s n="s2.5;p8.74">The residuals, or errors, are scattered about the line. </s><s n="s3.5;p8.74">The extent to which they lie close to or away from the line is an indication of the strength of the linear relationship. </s><s n="s4.5;p8.74">The standard deviation of the residuals measures this dispersion of the points about the line. </s><s n="s5.5;p8.74">This residual standard deviation is useful as it measures the stock's company-specific risk i.e. the risk that is not associated with the S&amp;P 500. </s></p><p n="p9.74"><s n="s1.2;p9.74">The <hi rend="bold">residual plot</hi> is a plot of the residuals against the x-axis (S&amp;P 500). </s><s n="s2.2;p9.74">This is useful for the same reasons as the line fit plot, but is even more useful in that the trend in the linear pattern is removed and our eye can focus on the residuals without being distracted by the linear pattern. </s></p><p n="p10.74"><s n="s1.3;p10.74">The <hi rend="bold">standardised residuals</hi> are the residual values converted to standardised form. </s><s n="s2.3;p10.74">This is useful in that using the standardised residuals we can perform a quick check to determine whether or not the regression line is a useful summary of the relationship in the data. </s><s n="s3.3;p10.74">If more than 5% of the observations lie outside the range - 2 to +2 then this indicates that the regression line may not be a good summary of the relationship in the data. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined">Question 5</head><div2><head rend="underlined bold">Hilton</head><table id="BAWE_0300a-tab.001"><head>SUMMARY OUTPUT FOR HILTON</head><row><cell/></row></table><figure id="BAWE_0300a-fig.001"><head>Line Fit Plot - Hilton</head></figure><figure id="BAWE_0300a-fig.002"><head>Residual Plot - Hilton</head></figure><p n="p11.74"/></div2><div2><head rend="underlined bold">TI</head><table id="BAWE_0300a-tab.002"><head>SUMMARY OUTPUT FOR TI</head><row><cell/></row></table><figure id="BAWE_0300a-fig.003"><head>Line Fit Plot - TI</head></figure><figure id="BAWE_0300a-fig.004"><head>Residual Plot - TI</head></figure><p n="p12.74"/></div2><div2><head rend="underlined bold">Giant</head><table id="BAWE_0300a-tab.003"><head>SUMMARY OUTPUT</head><row><cell/></row></table><figure id="BAWE_0300a-fig.005"><head>Line Fit Plot - Giant</head></figure><figure id="BAWE_0300a-fig.006"><head>Residual Plot - Giant</head></figure><p n="p13.74"/></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined">Question 6</head><div2><head rend="underlined bold">Hilton</head><p n="p14.74"><s rend="bold" n="s1.1;p14.74">The regression equation </s></p><p n="p15.74"><s n="s1.1;p15.74">The regression equation given in the output is: </s></p><p n="p16.74"><s n="s1.1;p16.74">Hilton Stock Price = -0.59 + 1.80(S&amp;P500) </s></p><p n="p17.74"><s n="s1.3;p17.74">From question 2, we now know that beta coefficient here is 1.80. </s><s n="s2.3;p17.74">This is a positive value indicating a positive relationship between the company stock price and the S&amp;P 500, as we would expect from our hypothesis. </s><s n="s3.3;p17.74">The beta coefficient is greater than 1, which means that the change in the Hilton stock price will rise or fall more on average than the change in the S&amp;P 500 stock price. </s></p><p n="p18.74"><s rend="bold" n="s1.1;p18.74">The correlation coefficient </s></p><p n="p19.74"><s n="s1.3;p19.74">The correlation coefficient R is 0.56. </s><s n="s2.3;p19.74">On a scale of 0 to 1, this value indicates medium strength in a linear relationship between the two prices. </s><s n="s3.3;p19.74">The value is positive which satisfies our hypothesis of a positive relationship. </s></p><p n="p20.74"><s rend="bold" n="s1.1;p20.74">The standard error </s></p><p n="p21.74"><s n="s1.3;p21.74">The standard error is 9.87. </s><s n="s2.3;p21.74">This equates to about 107% of the average (mean) Hilton stock price change, which is a large percentage change. </s><s n="s3.3;p21.74">This indicates that the predictions have a very low level of accuracy. </s></p><p n="p22.74"><s rend="bold" n="s1.1;p22.74">t stat, P-value, and Upper and Lower 95% </s></p><p n="p23.74"><s n="s1.3;p23.74">The t stat, P-value and Upper and Lower 95% statistics all indicate that it is highly unlikely that the slope of the regression line is zero. </s><s n="s2.3;p23.74">This adds credibility to our model, which has a positive slope. </s><s n="s3.3;p23.74">The probability of the y-intercept being 0 is high, which fits with our model, since the y-intercept is close to zero. </s></p><p n="p24.74"><s rend="bold" n="s1.1;p24.74">The line fit plot </s></p><p n="p25.74"><s n="s1.2;p25.74">The line fit plot shows a positive gradient indicating a positive relationship between the stock prices, as one would expect from the hypothesis. </s><s n="s2.2;p25.74">The line of best fit runs through the scatter diagram leaving many points far away from the line, indicating a low level of accuracy in the predictions, as confirmed by the high standard error. </s></p><p n="p26.74"><s rend="bold" n="s1.1;p26.74">The residual plot </s></p><p n="p27.74"><s n="s1.2;p27.74">The residual plot shows the residuals or errors scattered randomly. </s><s n="s2.2;p27.74">This fits with our model since the model does not include any pattern in the residuals. </s></p><p n="p28.74"><s rend="bold" n="s1.1;p28.74">Standard residuals </s></p><p n="p29.74"><s n="s1.2;p29.74">As a rule of thumb, if more than 5% of the standard residual values lie outside of range - 2 to 2, then the regression line may not be a good summary of the relationship in the data. </s><s n="s2.2;p29.74">Since only two of the standard residuals lie outside of this range, the regression line still looks sensible enough. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined bold">TI</head><p n="p30.74"><s rend="bold" n="s1.1;p30.74">The regression equation </s></p><p n="p31.74"><s n="s1.1;p31.74">The regression equation given in the output is: </s></p><p n="p32.74"><s n="s1.1;p32.74">TI Stock Price = -0.07 + 1.62(S&amp;P500) </s></p><p n="p33.74"><s n="s1.2;p33.74">This is a positive value of beta (1.62) indicating a positive relationship between the company stock price and the S&amp;P 500, as we would expect from our hypothesis. </s><s n="s2.2;p33.74">The beta coefficient is greater than 1, which means that the change in the TI stock price will rise or fall more on average than the change in the S&amp;P 500 stock price, but to a slightly lesser degree than Hilton since the beta coefficient is slightly lower. </s></p><p n="p34.74"><s rend="bold" n="s1.1;p34.74">The correlation coefficient </s></p><p n="p35.74"><s n="s1.1;p35.74">Same as for Hilton </s></p><p n="p36.74"><s rend="bold" n="s1.1;p36.74">The standard error </s></p><p n="p37.74"><s n="s1.1;p37.74">Very similar to Hilton, but the difference between the standard error and the average (mean) price change is 162%, which means the predictions have an even lower level of accuracy than for Hilton stocks. </s></p><p n="p38.74"><s rend="bold" n="s1.1;p38.74">t stat, P-value, and Upper and Lower 95% </s></p><p n="p39.74"><s n="s1.1;p39.74">Very similar to Hilton </s></p><p n="p40.74"><s rend="bold" n="s1.1;p40.74">The line fit plot </s></p><p n="p41.74"><s n="s1.1;p41.74">Very similar to Hilton </s></p><p n="p42.74"><s rend="bold" n="s1.1;p42.74">The residual plot </s></p><p n="p43.74"><s n="s1.1;p43.74">Very similar to Hilton </s></p><p n="p44.74"><s rend="bold" n="s1.1;p44.74">Standard residuals </s></p><p n="p45.74"><s n="s1.3;p45.74">Three of the standard residuals lie outside of the range - 2 to 2. </s><s n="s2.3;p45.74">This is only marginally higher than for Hilton, yet exactly 5% of the standard residuals lie outside of this range. </s><s n="s3.3;p45.74">This is the value above which the regression line may not be a good summary of the relationship in the data (as a rule of thumb). </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined bold">Giant</head><p n="p46.74"><s rend="bold" n="s1.1;p46.74">The regression equation </s></p><p n="p47.74"><s n="s1.1;p47.74">Giant Stock Price = -0.22 + 0.90(S&amp;P 500) </s></p><p n="p48.74"><s n="s1.1;p48.74">The beta coefficient is less than 1, which means that the change in the TI stock price will rise or fall less on average than the change in the S&amp;P 500 stock price, and so is considerably less sensitive to changes in the S&amp;P 500 compared to both Hilton and TI. </s></p><p n="p49.74"><s rend="bold" n="s1.1;p49.74">The correlation coefficient </s></p><p n="p50.74"><s n="s1.2;p50.74">The correlation coefficient R is 0.43 . </s><s n="s2.2;p50.74">On a scale of 0 to 1, this value indicates low to medium strength in a linear relationship between the two prices, slightly lower than for Hilton and TI. </s></p><p n="p51.74"><s rend="bold" n="s1.1;p51.74">The standard error </s></p><p n="p52.74"><s n="s1.3;p52.74">The standard error is 7.08 or 84% of the average (mean) stock price change. </s><s n="s2.3;p52.74">This is a high value and indicates a low level of accuracy in the predictions. </s><s n="s3.3;p52.74">However, the level of accuracy is better than for both Hilton and TI. </s></p><p n="p53.74"><s rend="bold" n="s1.1;p53.74">t stat, P-value, and Upper and Lower 95% </s></p><p n="p54.74"><s n="s1.1;p54.74">Very similar to both Hilton and TI </s></p><p n="p55.74"><s rend="bold" n="s1.1;p55.74">The line fit plot </s></p><p n="p56.74"><s n="s1.1;p56.74">Very similar to both Hilton and TI </s></p><p n="p57.74"><s rend="bold" n="s1.1;p57.74">The residual plot </s></p><p n="p58.74"><s n="s1.1;p58.74">Very similar to both Hilton and TI </s></p><p n="p59.74"><s rend="bold" n="s1.1;p59.74">Standard residuals </s></p><p n="p60.74"><s n="s1.2;p60.74">There are 5 standard residuals outside of the range - 2 to 2, which means that more than 5% of the standard residuals lie outside of this range. </s><s n="s2.2;p60.74">According to the rule of thumb, this indicates that the regression may not be a good summary of the relationship in the data. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">Question 7</head><p n="p61.74"><s n="s1.4;p61.74">I would recommend that Harold buy stock in Giant. </s><s n="s2.4;p61.74">Harold is interested in a stock that performs well in both an up and down S&amp;P 500 market. </s><s n="s3.4;p61.74">In other words, the stock should not be highly sensitive to the S&amp;P. Since the beta coefficient of Giant is almost half that of Hilton or TI, it is considerably less sensitive. </s><s n="s4.4;p61.74">The regression analysis shows reasonable confidence in the linear relationship in all three stocks, albeit slightly higher confidence in Hilton and TI. Nevertheless, the beta coefficient is what Harold is most interested in, and this interest should be met with an appropriate response, taking into consideration his desire for a low risk stock. </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined">Question 8</head><p n="p62.74"><s n="s1.1;p62.74">Taking an average (mean) of the stock prices for Hilton, TI, and Giant, for each period, gives the following regression results, referred to as the "portfolio" results. </s></p><table id="BAWE_0300a-tab.004"><head>SUMMARY OUTPUT FOR PORTFOLIO </head><row><cell/></row></table><figure id="BAWE_0300a-fig.007"><head>Line Fit Plot - Portfolio</head></figure><figure id="BAWE_0300a-fig.008"><head>Residual Plot - Portfolio</head></figure><p n="p63.74"><s n="s1.4;p63.74">The main difference between the portfolio regression results and the individual company results is that the correlation coefficient is significantly higher in the portfolio. </s><s n="s2.4;p63.74">This indicates that the linear relationship is stronger and so the accuracy of predictions is greater. </s><s n="s3.4;p63.74">This means lower risk, compared to investment in one single company, in making predictions based on market fluctuations and is why investors develop diversified portfolios. </s><s n="s4.4;p63.74">This makes intuitive sense, because a portfolio including every single stock in the market would be the same as investing in the market as a whole, and so would move linearly with it. </s></p><p n="p64.74"><s n="s1.1;p64.74">However, the beta in this case is not lowered by investing in a mix of all three, indicating that risk due to market sensitivity is not necessarily lowered by developing a diversified portfolio. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined">Question 9</head><p n="p65.74"><s n="s1.1;p65.74">TO: Harold Gagnon </s></p><p n="p66.74"><s n="s1.1;p66.74">FROM: Brenda Hagerty </s></p><p n="p67.74"><s n="s1.1;p67.74">DATE: 12 July 2006 </s></p><p n="p68.74"><s n="s1.1;p68.74">SUBJECT: Appraisal of the use of Beta Coefficients in Risk Evaluation, including suggestions, based on three stock options: Hilton, Texas Instruments, and Giant Foods. </s></p><div2><head rend="underlined bold">Beta analysis</head><p n="p69.74"><s n="s1.2;p69.74">Analysis of Beta coefficients provides a way of evaluating the risk attached to a stock or portfolio of stocks by the strength of their sensitivity to market fluctuations. </s><s n="s2.2;p69.74">The greater the beta coefficient the greater the sensitivity is to market fluctuations. </s></p><p n="p70.74"><s n="s1.3;p70.74">Before we analyse the beta coefficients, however, we need to ensure that the relationship between the company's stock price and the market price is sufficiently linear by performing a regression analysis. </s><s n="s2.3;p70.74">After satisfying ourselves that the relationship is sufficiently linear, we then know that the results of the regression analysis are useful. </s><s n="s3.3;p70.74">One of the most useful results is the beta coefficient, which is an indicator of market sensitivity of the company's stock price. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined bold">Other forms of risk evaluation</head><p n="p71.74"><s n="s1.5;p71.74">There are other risks involved that are not purely related to the beta coefficient. </s><s n="s2.5;p71.74">It is important to also consider the non-market risk, and this is another aspect of the regression analysis. </s><s n="s3.5;p71.74">Analysing the non-market risk, we see that it is greater for Giant Foods than for the other two stocks. </s><s n="s4.5;p71.74">In the appraisal of Beta coefficients in risk evaluation we therefore conclude that it is a useful tool but that other risk factors need to be taken into account. </s><s n="s5.5;p71.74">The remainder of this report analyses the beta coefficients of Hilton, TI, and Giant Foods, and, in conjunction with analysis of other risk factors, a suggestion is made as to the best single investment option. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined bold">Calculations</head><p n="p72.74"><s n="s1.1;p72.74">Taking market fluctuations on a per month basis over the past 60 months for each of the three companies as compared to the S&amp;P 500, the following are the results of the Beta analysis: </s></p><list type="simple"><item>Hilton Beta Coefficient: 1.80</item><item>Texas Instruments Beta Coefficient: 1.62</item><item>Giant Foods Beta Coefficient: 0.90</item></list></div2><div2><head rend="underlined bold">Analysis of Results</head><p n="p73.74"><s n="s1.3;p73.74">Looking at the beta coefficients, it is clear that Giant Foods is least sensitive to changes in the market. </s><s n="s2.3;p73.74">If it is a stock that performs well, then it should perform relatively well in a down as well as an up market, when compared to the other two stocks. </s><s n="s3.3;p73.74">Choosing Giant would lower the beta coefficient of the current portfolio, which is currently at 1.4 and which, 10 years from retirement, is regarded as high. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined bold">Conclusion</head><p n="p74.74"><s n="s1.1;p74.74">If market fluctuation is the most important risk factor then the suggestion would be to choose Giant Foods as the stock to invest in. </s></p></div2></div1></body><back/></text></TEI.2>
