<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_0300e" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Assignment A</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">deleted: Cover sheet, including tutor's comments</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">4</p><p n="date">2006-02</p><p n="module title">Operations Management</p><p n="module code">IB8160</p><p n="genre family">Exercise</p><p n="discipline">Business</p><p n="disciplinary group">SS</p><p n="grade">M</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">1252</p><p n="number of s-units">61</p><p n="number of p">26</p><p n="number of tables">0</p><p n="number of figures">1</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">0</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">6</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">20.5</p><p n="average s-units per p">2.3</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">m</p><p n="year of birth">1975</p><p n="first language">English</p><p n="education">OSA</p><p n="course">DLMBA</p><p n="student ID">0300</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><docTitle><titlePart rend="bold">Assignment A</titlePart></docTitle></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Question 1</head><p n="p1.26"><s n="s1.6;p1.26">Ikea's philosophy is to provide "low price, value for money furnishings with a wide range of choice". </s><s n="s2.6;p1.26">This philosophy, along with Ikea's associated competitive strategy, influences the operations performance objectives of the company. </s><s n="s3.6;p1.26">The company's overall competitive strategy influences the operation's competitive role within the company which in turn influences the performance objectives. </s><s n="s4.6;p1.26">It will be shown that the resulting main performance objectives of Ikea's operations are Cost (influenced by the philosophy and overall strategy of offering "prices so low the majority of people can afford to buy them") and Flexibility (most specifically Mix Flexibility, influenced by the overall strategy of providing a "wide range of home furnishings"). </s><s n="s5.6;p1.26">In contrast it will be demonstrated that Ikea's traditional competitors would probably place more importance on the Quality objective than perhaps Ikea would, whereas the Cost objective would be a less important objective. </s><s n="s6.6;p1.26">In the following paragraphs, the five performance objectives (Slack et al p.44) of Ikea and traditional competitors will be compared and contrasted. </s></p><div2><head rend="bold">Quality</head><p n="p2.26"><s n="s1.3;p2.26">Whilst the quality performance objective is important to Ikea (their philosophy states "We must not compromise on function or technical quality"), it is nevertheless relatively less important than the cost and flexibility objectives. </s><s n="s2.3;p2.26">In contrast, traditional competitors place greater importance on quality, particularly with regards to customer service. </s><s n="s3.3;p2.26">At Ikea, customers must pick the parts off the shelves in the warehouse, whereas traditional competitors will in general allow for delivery directly from the warehouse shelf to the customer's vehicle or final destination. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">Speed</head><p n="p3.26"><s n="s1.3;p3.26">The speed objective for both Ikea and its competitors is less important than other performance objectives. </s><s n="s2.3;p3.26">This is especially so for Ikea when it comes to that specific subdivision of the speed performance objective which is the time taken for the total transaction of going to Ikea, making the purchase and returning. </s><s n="s3.3;p3.26">This process is usually longer than for traditional retailers because the layout of the Ikea store results in customers spending more time that at traditional competitors (typically 2 and up to 4 hours). </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">Dependability</head><p n="p4.26"><s n="s1.5;p4.26">For Ikea, the dependability objective is probably less important than the cost and flexibility objectives. </s><s n="s2.5;p4.26">When it comes to opening hours, dependability is equally important for Ikea as it is for traditional competitors. </s><s n="s3.5;p4.26">With regards to queuing however, dependability is less important for Ikea, where one manager is reported to have stated "We are famous for our queues", illustrating acceptance of this and therefore that increasing dependability when it comes to queuing isn't a main performance objective. </s><s n="s4.5;p4.26">In contrast, traditional competitors generally have shorter queuing times. </s><s n="s5.5;p4.26">With regards to parking, however, Ikea has constant availability and so place importance on dependability in this arena, whereas this isn't always the case with its competitors. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">Flexibility</head><p n="p5.26"><s n="s1.1;p5.26">Flexibility is one of the two most important performance objectives for Ikea (cost being the other). </s></p><div3><head rend="bold">Mix Flexibility</head><p n="p6.26"><s n="s1.3;p6.26">Ikea achieves mix flexibility through mass customisation. </s><s n="s2.3;p6.26">It achieves this through design of modular components and also through each stores stocking about 10 000 of the 14 000+ items of the Ikea range. </s><s n="s3.3;p6.26">In contrast, traditional competitors generally have far less flexibility than Ikea due to much smaller stock ranges. </s></p></div3><div3><head rend="bold">Product/service flexibility</head><p n="p7.26"><s n="s1.3;p7.26">Ikea's philosophy states "By daring to be different, we find new ways". </s><s n="s2.3;p7.26">This strategic objective can influence (or vice versa) the product/service flexibility objective to introduce new of modified products, resulting in the "creative sourcing" from approximately 2100 suppliers in 63 countries. </s><s n="s3.3;p7.26">In contrast, competitors generally have far less product flexibility due to in part to having far less flexibility in sourcing. </s></p></div3></div2><div2><head rend="bold">Cost</head><p n="p8.26"><s n="s1.5;p8.26">Cost is the other of the two most important objectives for Ikea. </s><s n="s2.5;p8.26">Ikea's philosophy is once again to provide "low price, value for money furnishings with a wide range of choice". </s><s n="s3.5;p8.26">Cost is one of its major competitive factors. </s><s n="s4.5;p8.26">Whilst its competitors will see cost as a major factor, it is relatively less of a competitive factor than it is for Ikea. </s><s n="s5.5;p8.26">Ikea achieves low cost by: </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p9.26"><s n="s1.3;p9.26">Reducing staff numbers and therefore the associated cost of hiring and paying them. </s><s n="s2.3;p9.26">It does this by using automated machines in the warehouse (robots) and store (integrated computer systems). </s><s n="s3.3;p9.26">It also manages to keep staff numbers down by being largely a self service store. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p10.26"><s n="s1.1;p10.26">Facilities are out of town where they are cheaper. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p11.26"><s n="s1.1;p11.26">Material costs - by sourcing from 2100 different suppliers, the company manages to achieve economies of scale. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0300e-fig.001"><head>Figure 1. Polar Representations of the relative importance of performance objectives for Ikea and its traditional competitors. </head></figure></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Question 2</head><p n="p12.26"><s n="s1.1;p12.26">Using table 3.3 in Slack et al (p.81) as a framework, the following are the key structural and infrastructural operations decisions that Ikea has made in order to achieve the appropriate levels of performance: </s></p><div2><head rend="bold">Structural Operations Decisions</head><div3><head rend="bold">New product/service development</head><p n="p13.26"><s n="s1.4;p13.26">Ikea continuously looks for new products. </s><s n="s2.4;p13.26">It's philosophy includes the phrase "Most things still remain to be done". </s><s n="s3.4;p13.26">This philosophy results in the operations decision of "creative sourcing" whereby products are sourced from 2100 suppliers in 63 countries resulting in economies of scale. </s><s n="s4.4;p13.26">Some products even start off as by-products of furniture, resulting in low cost furniture. </s></p></div3><div3><head rend="bold">Supply network</head><p n="p14.26"><s n="s1.1;p14.26">Ikea acquires its suppliers through "creative sourcing" from many different suppliers. </s></p></div3><div3><head rend="bold">Facilities</head><p n="p15.26"><s n="s1.2;p15.26">Ikea has limited its UK operations due to shortage of facilities of the right size, location and cost. </s><s n="s2.2;p15.26">It is this operations decision to use such facilities that contributes to the low cost and flexibility of the products. </s></p></div3><div3><head rend="bold">Technology</head><p n="p16.26"><s n="s1.1;p16.26">Ikea makes the following technology operations decisions to achieve levels of performance: </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p17.26"><s n="s1.1;p17.26">Robots are used in the central warehouse, reducing the need for staff, resulting in lower costs. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p18.26"><s n="s1.1;p18.26">Conveyer belts at the checkouts enable large items to be transported past the cashier, improving quality of service for customers </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p19.26"><s n="s1.1;p19.26">Inventory control is achieved through an integrated, automated computer system, resulting in flexibility in a reduction in stock-outs and therefore greater volume flexibility. </s></p></div3></div2><div2><head rend="bold">Infrastructural Operations Decisions</head><div3><head rend="bold">Workforce &amp; organisation strategy</head><p n="p20.26"><s n="s1.4;p20.26">The people who staff Ikea should play a strong role in its management. </s><s n="s2.4;p20.26">"To assume responsibility" is a philosophy of Ikea. </s><s n="s3.4;p20.26">All are expected to work together towards the organisation's objectives. </s><s n="s4.4;p20.26">The operations decision to have management wearing the same clothes as the rest of the staff helps to reach this objective. </s></p><p n="p21.26"><s n="s1.1;p21.26">The division of roles is reached by employees either wearing red or grey sweatshirts, depending on whether they are customer contact or not. </s></p></div3><div3><head rend="bold">Capacity adjustment strategy</head><p n="p22.26"><s n="s1.2;p22.26">Ikea adjusts to fluctuations in demand by having a completely automated system of re-ordering. </s><s n="s2.2;p22.26">Stock-outs do occur, usually resulting in the buffer and re-order quantities being reviewed. </s></p></div3><div3><head rend="bold">Supplier development strategy</head><p n="p23.26"><s n="s1.2;p23.26">"Creative sourcing" means that suppliers are sourced from many different countries and companies. </s><s n="s2.2;p23.26">This enables Ikea to achieve economies of scale and thus contributes to attaining the appropriate levels of performance in terms of cost. </s></p></div3><div3><head rend="bold">Inventory strategy</head><p n="p24.26"><s n="s1.2;p24.26">Ikea stores have automatic inventory management through a completely automated system of re-ordering. </s><s n="s2.2;p24.26">At present there is no warehouse capacity in the UK, and all products come from a central warehouse in Sweden, simplifying inventory. </s></p></div3><div3><head rend="bold">Improvement strategy</head><p n="p25.26"><s n="s1.1;p25.26">By continuously finding new creative sourcing of products and by involving all staff in the improvement process, the operations manages to implement an improvement strategy. </s></p></div3></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Question 3</head><p n="p26.26"><s n="s1.3;p26.26">One possible source of tension between marking and operations is the objective of marketing to have a "Scandinavian Feel" to the designs of the furniture. </s><s n="s2.3;p26.26">The differences in taste between the different countries results in slow-moving items in some countries. </s><s n="s3.3;p26.26">The operations objective to source products from many different sources and countries, is limited to those products having a "Scandinavian feel" and hence there is a tension between marketing and operations. </s></p></div1></body><back/></text></TEI.2>
