<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_0302i" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>What was "traditional" sport?</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">deleted: header: assignment title and page numbers</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">3</p><p n="date">2006-10</p><p n="module title">Sport, Politics and Society</p><p n="module code">PO370</p><p n="genre family">Literature survey</p><p n="discipline">Politics</p><p n="disciplinary group">SS</p><p n="grade">M</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">518</p><p n="number of s-units">39</p><p n="number of p">33</p><p n="number of tables">0</p><p n="number of figures">0</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">1</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">23</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">13.3</p><p n="average s-units per p">1.2</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">f</p><p n="year of birth">1985</p><p n="first language">English</p><p n="education">UKA</p><p n="course">History and Politics</p><p n="student ID">0302</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><docTitle><titlePart><hi rend="underlined bold">What was "traditional" sport?</hi> <hi rend="underlined bold"> Was it in decline from 1800 to 1850 and, if so, why? </hi></titlePart></docTitle></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold italic">What was "traditional" sport? </head><p rend="bulleted" n="p1.33"><s n="s1.1;p1.33">"Traditional" implies longevity= first clue: these sports were pursued over many centuries </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p2.33"><s n="s1.1;p2.33">Key principle= variety </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p3.33"><s n="s1.1;p3.33">Most involved animals </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p4.33"><s n="s1.1;p4.33">Often played as part of festivals/ annual holidays </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p5.33"><s n="s1.2;p5.33">Lot of forms of football and athleticism. </s><s n="s2.2;p5.33">Most developed, however, was cricket. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p6.33"><s n="s1.1;p6.33">All sports were disorderly and riotous and often violent </s></p><list type="simple"><head rend="italic">Some popular sports:</head><item rend="bold">Football</item><item rend="bold">Wrestling</item><item rend="bold">Cudgels</item><item rend="bold">Ninepins</item><item rend="bold">Shovel-board</item><item rend="bold">Cricket</item><item rend="bold">Horse racing</item><item rend="bold">Rowing (esp. Thames and Tyne)</item><item rend="bold">Hunting</item><item rend="bold">Stow-ball</item><item rend="bold">Ringing of bells</item><item rend="bold">Quoits</item><item rend="bold">Pitching the bar</item><item rend="bold">Bull and bear baiting</item><item rend="bold">Throwing at cocks</item><item rend="bold">Hurling to goales</item><item rend="bold">Fighting (most popular individual sport):</item><item rend="bold">Cudgelling matches</item><item rend="bold">Pugilism</item><item rend="bold">Hitting each others' head with a stick</item><item rend="bold">Stone fights</item><item rend="bold">Prize fighting</item></list></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold italic">Was it in decline from 1800 to 1850? </head><p n="p7.33"><s n="s1.1;p7.33">Has been suggested that by the 2 <hi rend="sup">nd</hi> quarter of the 19 <hi rend="sup">th</hi> century a thriving sporting culture persisted only among the landed elites </s></p><p n="p8.33"><s n="s1.1;p8.33"><hi rend="underlined bold">PRESUMPTIONS </hi>(Malcolmson)<hi rend="underlined bold"> vs REALITY </hi>(Tranter) </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p9.33"><s n="s1.1;p9.33"><hi rend="bold italic">Industrialisation( restraints</hi>: people moving into the cities, working day lengthening, urbanisationlack of space, and impoverishment </s></p><p n="p10.33"><s n="s1.1;p10.33"><hi rend="bold">BUT</hi> <hi rend="italic">Overestimating the number of people working long hours</hi> </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p11.33"><s n="s1.1;p11.33">1851, only minority of males in factories whose working hours increased </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p12.33"><s n="s1.3;p12.33">Even factory workers could still play football- e.g. </s><s n="s2.3;p12.33">1835, Blairdrummond estates vs. </s><s n="s3.3;p12.33">Deadston cotton mills </s></p><p n="p13.33"><s n="s1.1;p13.33"><hi rend="bold">ALSO</hi> <hi rend="italic">Cunningham:</hi> population growth as likely to encourage as discourage popular sport. </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p14.33"><s n="s1.1;p14.33"><hi rend="bold italic">Religious revival</hi>- initial hostility between religion and sport </s></p><p n="p15.33"><s rend="bold italic" n="s1.1;p15.33">SOME validity </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p16.33"><s n="s1.1;p16.33">Wider acceptance of Enlightenment, Evangelical and Methodist values repugnant to unnecessary violence and cruelty meant that animal blood sports and other disruptive past times did decline (growing desire for respectability) </s></p><p n="p17.33"><s n="s1.1;p17.33"><hi rend="bold italic">BUT </hi><hi rend="italic">limitations:</hi> most sports were shared with the elite or were no disrespectful </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p18.33"><s n="s1.1;p18.33"><hi rend="bold italic">Political campaigning</hi> against sports and games: middle- class rulers didn't tolerate it, animal rights campaigns, corruption calls for abolition </s></p><p n="p19.33"><s rend="bold italic" n="s1.1;p19.33">BUT Pre-occupation with "brutal" sports </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p20.33"><s n="s1.2;p20.33">More detailed analysis shows that the only working-class sports that definitely declined were blood sports involving animals- even these survived more than was presumed. </s><s n="s2.2;p20.33">E.g. badger- baiting and cock- fighting in London during 1 <hi rend="sup">st</hi> half of 19 <hi rend="sup">th</hi> century </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p21.33"><s n="s1.1;p21.33">Re. other working- class sports: evidence suggests growth or, at least, stability </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p22.33"><s n="s1.1;p22.33">E.g. sculling/ rowing- lots of participants, prize fighting- no decline until the 1840s, Scottish curling clubs increased, athletics soared 1750- 1860, potshare, bowling, wrestling. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p23.33"><s n="s1.1;p23.33">Horseracing, cricket and football survived outside the elite private school more extensively than assumed </s></p><p n="p24.33"><s n="s1.1;p24.33"><hi rend="bold">THEREFORE</hi> many have overlooked the growth/ stability of many sports by concentrating on brutal working- class sports </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p25.33"><s n="s1.1;p25.33">Establishment of <hi rend="bold italic">more effective ways of policing</hi>- growing use by local authorities </s></p><p n="p26.33"><s n="s1.1;p26.33"><hi rend="bold">BUT</hi> <hi rend="italic">ineffective methods of policing</hi> </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p27.33"><s n="s1.1;p27.33">normal methods of policing were ineffective to remove speedily and completely aspects of sport that the working class wanted to retain </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p28.33"><s n="s1.1;p28.33">E.g. no one succeeded in stopping much street football until the 1850s or 1860s </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p29.33"><s n="s1.3;p29.33">E.g. </s><s n="s2.3;p29.33">2. </s><s n="s3.3;p29.33">The street football at Derby and Newark-on-Trent was only stopped in the late 1840s by the army and special constables </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p30.33"><s n="s1.1;p30.33">Widespread <hi rend="bold italic">withdrawal of aristocratic and gentry patronage</hi> </s></p><p n="p31.33"><s n="s1.1;p31.33"><hi rend="bold">BUT</hi> <hi rend="italic">too little evidence about patronage to guess overall trends</hi> </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p32.33"><s n="s1.1;p32.33">DID reduce support of animal blood sports BUT continued to support other sports- boat racing, cricket, curling, etc. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p33.33"><s n="s1.1;p33.33">Even if was a decline, patronage may have been filled by other groups- e.g. publicans </s></p></div1></body><back/></text></TEI.2>
