<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_0303b" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Transcendence and Creation</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">Language used in quote: <foreign id="English">English</foreign></note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">deleted: page numbers</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">2</p><p n="date">2006-04</p><p n="module title">Philosophy of Religion</p><p n="module code">PH307</p><p n="genre family">Essay</p><p n="discipline">Philosophy</p><p n="disciplinary group">AH</p><p n="grade">M</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">2686</p><p n="number of s-units">97</p><p n="number of p">26</p><p n="number of tables">0</p><p n="number of figures">0</p><p n="number of block quotes">4</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">0</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">0</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">27.7</p><p n="average s-units per p">3.7</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">m</p><p n="year of birth">1986</p><p n="first language">English</p><p n="education">UKA</p><p n="course">V500</p><p n="student ID">0303</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><docTitle><titlePart rend="bold">Transcendence and Creation</titlePart></docTitle><epigraph><p>'To say that God is transcendent is to emphasise the non-applicability of any concept whatsoever'</p><p rend="italic">Miles (1966; 150)</p></epigraph></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="section"><p n="p1.26"><s n="s1.4;p1.26">There are many problems associated with God's spatial and temporal transcendence. </s><s n="s2.4;p1.26">Many wish to maintain that a God that is personal and interacts with the world must be located, in some way, within space and time, whilst others claim that the classical qualities of omnipotence and omniscience are compromised when God is bound, and arguably limited, by temporal and spatial constraints. </s><s n="s3.4;p1.26">In particular, arguments for the existence of God that posit an unmoved mover, first cause and omnipotent creator of the universe, arguably, require that God is not limited by spatial and temporal constraints; as this may limit His creative abilities enough to postpone the creation of the universe, and thus His existence<ref target="BAWE_0303b-ftnote.001"/>. </s><s n="s4.4;p1.26">On the other hand it is not clear that is possible to create something if one has no spatial or temporal precedence over said creation<ref target="BAWE_0303b-ftnote.002"/>. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0303b-ftnote.001"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">If the creation of the universe is an argument for the necessary existence of God (cf Aquinas, Descartes), and God arguably did not, and could not, have created the universe then God did not necessarily exist. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0303b-ftnote.002"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">It is not clear that one can create if one is not temporally prior to the creation nor spatially connected to the creation. </s></p></note><p n="p2.26"><s n="s1.3;p2.26">I hope to show that these conflicts can be resolved and that we can be left with a notion of God as metaphysically within time and space, yet transcendent of the traditional four dimensions we occupy. </s><s n="s2.3;p2.26">As such, God is transcendent of <hi rend="italic">our</hi> time and space but not transcendent of time and space <hi rend="italic">qua</hi> time and space. </s><s n="s3.3;p2.26">God is thus epistemologically transcendent, conveniently explaining our difficulties in discussing Him. </s></p><p n="p3.26"><s n="s1.2;p3.26">Firstly, let us sketch some arguments for God's transcendence. </s><s n="s2.2;p3.26">Leftow (1997) argues that a temporally bound God would be less than perfect as he would be limited: </s></p><quote lang="English">'If a life lasts forever in time, always one part of it's past and another is future. So any life in time contains at least one limit.'<hi rend="italic"> Leftow (1997; 258)</hi></quote><p n="p4.26"><s n="s1.3;p4.26">The other limit that Leftow alludes to is a beginning and an end of a life, but we shall assume here that God is eternal and so has no such limit. </s><s n="s2.3;p4.26">Now in the case of an imperfect being, that the past, present and future are segmented can be a bonus; we can forget mistakes we have made in the past and remain oblivious to the dreadful things fated to us in the future. </s><s n="s3.3;p4.26">In the case of a perfect being, however, such a segmentation is a hindrance to perfection; God is totally perfect, by not currently experiencing past and future perfections, the presently perfect God is not as perfect as the God that experiences the whole of His life at once: </s></p><quote lang="English">'In not living part of His life, God would lose some good in living it... Thus, having a past and a future would limit the perfection of God's life'<hi rend="italic"> Leftow (1997; 258)</hi></quote><p n="p5.26"><s n="s1.1;p5.26">From Leftow's argument we can conclude that God either transcends time, or else His present is infinitely long, not the instantaneous now that we typically associate with 'present'. </s></p><p n="p6.26"><s n="s1.1;p6.26">There is an association with time and change; for things change within a time frame and different time frames are signified by changes in objects<ref target="BAWE_0303b-ftnote.003"/>, which leads to an argument for God's timelessness from Bertocci: </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0303b-ftnote.003"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">See Taliaferro (1998; 148-149) for a discussion of time and change. </s></p></note><quote lang="English">'[C]hange...must involve either adding or subtracting, for better or worse. If a being is perfect what can there be to add or subtract?'<hi rend="italic"> Bertocci (1951; 309)</hi></quote><p n="p7.26"><s n="s1.2;p7.26">Bertocci concludes that God does not change and many theists maintain that a changeless God is a timeless God. </s><s n="s2.2;p7.26">It is, however, altogether possible that God is changeless and yet within time; the association with change and time is not a necessary one. </s></p><p n="p8.26"><s n="s1.3;p8.26">To turn our attention specifically to transcendence and creation; God must be temporally transcendent if He is to create the universe, for if He is within time then He must be infinitely extended within it<ref target="BAWE_0303b-ftnote.004"/>. </s><s n="s2.3;p8.26">However, if God is infinitely extended within time then the Augustinian question of 'why did God choose to create the universe when he did?' arises<ref target="BAWE_0303b-ftnote.005"/>, and in answering such a question we must be considering changes within God, which Bertocci (above) forbids. </s><s n="s3.3;p8.26">Alston (1989; 133) concludes that '...if we are to defend the classical doctrine of creation we must come to think of God as nontemporal'. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0303b-ftnote.004"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">If God is not infinitely extended within time then it begs the questions; 'what created God?' or at the very least 'what was before God?' </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0303b-ftnote.005"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Alston (1989) cited in Taliaferro (1998; 147) </s></p></note><p n="p9.26"><s n="s1.2;p9.26">It seems that God must be transcendent of time, or at least He must possess an infinitely long present and be capable of creating the universe without changing in anyway. </s><s n="s2.2;p9.26">There are, however, reasons for believing that God must be within time and space, and to these we now turn our attention. </s></p><p n="p10.26"><s n="s1.3;p10.26">The argument from omniscience (presented in Taliaferro; 1998) is essentially that if God is outside of time and had knowledge of time it would be knowledge of time as a 'B-series'<ref target="BAWE_0303b-ftnote.006"/> and as such He would have no knowledge of what moment is present, even though He would know what all events were and in what relation they stand to other events (before, simultaneous with, and after). </s><s n="s2.3;p10.26">He would know that the event at <hi rend="italic">t1</hi> happened before the events at <hi rend="italic">t2</hi> and <hi rend="italic">t3</hi>, but He would not know that it is presently <hi rend="italic">t1</hi>. </s><s n="s3.3;p10.26">Although God would know everything, He would not know when 'now' is, God must therefore be within time in order to preserve His omniscience. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0303b-ftnote.006"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">See Poidevin (2003; 122-143) for a discussion of A-theory, presentism and B-theory </s></p></note><p n="p11.26"><s n="s1.3;p11.26">However, this can be dismissed by relativising the present, i.e. if I occupy <hi rend="italic">t1</hi> then <hi rend="italic">t1</hi> is the present time, if I occupy <hi rend="italic">t2</hi> then <hi rend="italic">t2</hi> is the present time, and so on. </s><s n="s2.3;p11.26">God can thus know that for individual <hi rend="italic">x</hi> at time <hi rend="italic">t2</hi> that <hi rend="italic">t2</hi> is present, <hi rend="italic">t1</hi> is past and <hi rend="italic">t3</hi> is future. </s><s n="s3.3;p11.26">He can also know that for individual <hi rend="italic">y</hi> at time <hi rend="italic">t3</hi> that <hi rend="italic">t3</hi> is present, <hi rend="italic">t2</hi> is past and <hi rend="italic">t4</hi> is future. </s></p><p n="p12.26"><s n="s1.7;p12.26">'Now' is thus relegated to the same relative status as 'here'. </s><s n="s2.7;p12.26">Some would not allow this move; Gale (1968; 215) argues that although it makes sense to ask 'Where are you now?' and receive an answer of 'here', the same cannot be said of 'When are you now?'. </s><s n="s3.7;p12.26">To ask 'When are you now?' simply makes no sense. </s><s n="s4.7;p12.26">Now it does not seem that 'When are you now?' makes no sense, it just seems that it is entirely pointless to ask the question, just as if we shared our spatial location with Bob and asked 'Where are you now?'; we clearly know the answer; 'here'. </s><s n="s5.7;p12.26">That our temporal location has so far been determined and that we are always in the same present as other objects is why 'When are you now?' appears meaningless. </s><s n="s6.7;p12.26">Suppose we can travel through time, suddenly 'When are you now?' is not so meaningless as time-travelling Bob can reply 'now' meaningfully, if not informatively. </s><s n="s7.7;p12.26">If we allow the possibility of time-travel as we do spatial-travel<ref target="BAWE_0303b-ftnote.007"/> then 'now' has as much significance as 'here' our current, fixed view of 'now' as privileged and granted is subjective and not the objective given that Gale assumes; 'now' is not necessarily now, 'now' could just as easily have been then, it is as subjective and relative as 'here' is<ref target="BAWE_0303b-ftnote.008"/>. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0303b-ftnote.007"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">That time travel is or is not metaphysically possible is not really at issue, that it is conceivable allows 'When are you now?' to make sense. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0303b-ftnote.008"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">If <hi rend="italic">t2</hi> is 'now' it is not necessarily so, as 'now' could have been <hi rend="italic">t1</hi>, just as 'here' is at my desk it is not necessarily so, as 'here' could have been on top of the Eiffel tower. </s></p></note><p n="p13.26"><s n="s1.7;p13.26">Another argument that suggests that God is within time is the argument from simultaneity<ref target="BAWE_0303b-ftnote.009"/>. </s><s n="s2.7;p13.26">Essentially the argument is a reductio ad absurdum; if we grant that God is transcendent then he must exist at all instants in history. </s><s n="s3.7;p13.26">Now if <hi rend="italic">t1</hi> is simultaneous with <hi rend="italic">t2</hi>, and <hi rend="italic">t2</hi> with <hi rend="italic">t3</hi>, then <hi rend="italic">t1</hi> is simultaneous with <hi rend="italic">t3</hi>; simultaneity is a transitive relation between events/times. </s><s n="s4.7;p13.26">If God timelessly exists at all instants then the past event, <hi rend="italic">e1</hi>, is existent simultaneously with God. </s><s n="s5.7;p13.26">A present event, <hi rend="italic">e2</hi>, and a future event <hi rend="italic">, e3</hi>, are similarly simultaneous with God's timeless existence. </s><s n="s6.7;p13.26"><hi rend="italic">E1, e2</hi> and <hi rend="italic">e3</hi> are thus simultaneous with each other and so the past, present and future are all co-occurent. </s><s n="s7.7;p13.26">As the past, present and future are not co-occurent God cannot be transcendent of time and must, therefore, exist within time. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0303b-ftnote.009"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Again, presented in Taliaferro (1998; 159) </s></p></note><p n="p14.26"><s n="s1.4;p14.26">If we are to refute this argument and allow God to be transcendent we must either reject the transitive nature of simultaneity, or else allow God special privileges that mean His simultaneous present with events is a different kind of simultaneity that is not transitive in nature. </s><s n="s2.4;p14.26">This is precisely what Stump and Kretzmann (1981; 443) do when they introduce eternal simultaneity, or ET-simultaneity. </s><s n="s3.4;p14.26">Past, present and future events can all be ET-simultaneous with God, but this simultaneity is not transitive and so the past, present and future remain distinct from one another. </s><s n="s4.4;p14.26">This train of thought will be picked up later in the essay. </s></p><p n="p15.26"><s n="s1.4;p15.26">One last argument as to why God must exist within time is the argument from causality; it is simply not possible to create temporal and spatial objects when one is outside of time and space. </s><s n="s2.4;p15.26">Taylor (1974; 107) claims that creation essentially means dependence and not, as is supposed here, creation in time or space. </s><s n="s3.4;p15.26">The relationship between creator and creation is thus one of dependence and not of cause and effect. </s><s n="s4.4;p15.26">Taylor also says: </s></p><quote lang="English">'If one thing is the creation of another, then it depends for its existence on that other, and this is perfectly consistent with saying that both are eternal, that neither came into being, and hence, that neither was ever created at any point of time'<hi rend="italic"> Taylor (1974; 107)</hi></quote><p n="p16.26"><s n="s1.1;p16.26">It may seem strange that an essay considering transcendence and creation would admit of the possibility of the universe existing eternally and thus not having a point of creation, but this is precisely the direction in which this essay shall turn. </s></p><p n="p17.26"><s n="s1.3;p17.26">It seems that a temporally bound God is limited and less than perfect (Leftow; 1997) and that, even if God were to exist within time, he must be changeless (Bertocci; 1951). </s><s n="s2.3;p17.26">Alston (1989) claims that the creator must be nontemporal in order to avoid the Augustinian 'why create then and not at some other time?' yet if creation involved cause and effect, then surely God must be within time. </s><s n="s3.3;p17.26">There are also problems with the transitivity of simultaneity with a transcendent God. </s></p><p n="p18.26"><s n="s1.4;p18.26">Fortunately, we can present a view of transcendence and creation that meets all of these points. </s><s n="s2.4;p18.26">We have been assuming creation of the universe within the human-observable four dimensions; three of space and one of time. </s><s n="s3.4;p18.26">There is nothing to stop us positing as many dimensions as we like, indeed current string-theorists posit about eleven (Smolin; 2003). </s><s n="s4.4;p18.26">As contrary to Ockham's Razor as it may appear, we only need two more dimensions to explain the creation of the universe. </s></p><p n="p19.26"><s n="s1.4;p19.26">The fifth dimension is a spatial one, God exists in it, yet it is unknowable to humans; it transcends our understanding. </s><s n="s2.4;p19.26">The sixth dimension is a second temporal one and is similarly unknowable. </s><s n="s3.4;p19.26">God also transcends 'our' four dimensions. </s><s n="s4.4;p19.26">To clarify the metaphysical and epistemological status of these dimensions: God exists in the fifth and sixth dimensions and yet we know nothing of these domains, the universe exists in the first four and we only have knowledge of these dimensions<ref target="BAWE_0303b-ftnote.010"/>. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0303b-ftnote.010"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Although bear in mind that the universe could exist in the extra two dimensions and we simply do not know. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">This may be necessary to explain a causal relationship between God and the universe (see below) </s></p></note><p n="p20.26"><s n="s1.7;p20.26">Now, the problem of simultaneity dissolves. </s><s n="s2.7;p20.26">An event at time <hi rend="italic">t1</hi> in the first dimension of time can be simultaneous with God's existence in the second dimension of time, as can event <hi rend="italic">t2</hi>. </s><s n="s3.7;p20.26"><hi rend="italic">t1</hi> and <hi rend="italic">t2</hi> are not simultaneous. </s><s n="s4.7;p20.26">This is really an explication of Stump and Kretzmann's (1981) ET-simultaneity. </s><s n="s5.7;p20.26">The transitive nature of simultaneous relations only holds <hi rend="italic">within</hi> a dimension, not across dimensions. </s><s n="s6.7;p20.26"><hi rend="italic">T1,</hi> in dimension (i), is simultaneous with God in dimension (ii) and <hi rend="italic">t2</hi>, in dimension (i), is similarly simultaneous with God in (ii), yet <hi rend="italic">t1</hi> and <hi rend="italic">t2</hi> are not simultaneous in virtue of them being simultaneous with God in another dimension alone. </s><s n="s7.7;p20.26">The transitivity of simultaneity does not transcend dimensional boundaries. </s></p><p n="p21.26"><s n="s1.7;p21.26">God is also changeless, thus preserving His perfection. </s><s n="s2.7;p21.26">The Augustinian question of 'why create at time <hi rend="italic">x</hi> and not at any other time?' is avoided if we assert that both the universe and God are eternal, as Taylor (1974) suggests. </s><s n="s3.7;p21.26">All six dimensions are eternal and the creative relation between God and the universe is a relation of dependence, not of cause and effect. </s><s n="s4.7;p21.26">That the universe is eternal is compatible with recent scientific thought. </s><s n="s5.7;p21.26">Steinhardt and Turok (2004) present a cyclical life for the universe in which a Big Bang occurs and the universe expands, gravity then pulls the universe back in again ending with a Big Crunch. </s><s n="s6.7;p21.26">Once the universe collapses into a Big Crunch it is followed immediately by another Big Bang and the process repeats ad infinitum. </s><s n="s7.7;p21.26">Here we have an eternal universe and an eternal God<ref target="BAWE_0303b-ftnote.011"/> and so we have no need to ask the question 'how did God <hi rend="italic">cause</hi> the universe to come into being?' as we cannot even ask 'when did God create the universe?'. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0303b-ftnote.011"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Theistic intentions are my own, not Steinhardt and Turok's, their picture of the universe was invoked as an illustration of God and science being compatible in the assertion of extra dimenions. </s></p></note><p n="p22.26"><s n="s1.8;p22.26">God's existence in other dimensions can explain many of the problems associated with a transcendent God and also avoid the difficulties presented to a temporal and spatial God. </s><s n="s2.8;p22.26">Leftow's (1997) concern that a temporally bound God is limited and less than perfect can be addressed if we allow that God exists in an everlasting present in the sixth dimension. </s><s n="s3.8;p22.26">As such, His life would not be divisible, either actually or potentially. </s><s n="s4.8;p22.26">If the structure of the sixth dimension was such that there was only a present moment then God's life would be whole. </s><s n="s5.8;p22.26">He can also enjoy an omniscient view of 'our' temporal dimension; viewing it as a B-series of events. </s><s n="s6.8;p22.26">God would also know what moment was present. </s><s n="s7.8;p22.26">Reality as viewed from the sixth dimension would mean that everything was present, yet the fragmented view of past, present and future viewed from our temporal dimension also exists and God would know, through his omniscience, that a certain time in our dimension is present for a certain person whereas another time is present for another individual. </s><s n="s8.8;p22.26">As such God exists in the sixth dimension yet has knowledge of our temporal fourth dimension, as well as the sixth, whereas we exist in the fourth and have epistemic access only to the fourth. </s></p><p n="p23.26"><s n="s1.6;p23.26">Although God's existence in an extra two dimensions can explain most, if not all of the problems presented in considering transcendence, there is one problem that is decidedly more problematic than the others. </s><s n="s2.6;p23.26">It remains to be seen whether or not God, in residence in two dimensions, can be in a causal relationship with the other four, distinct dimensions. </s><s n="s3.6;p23.26">As alluded to in footnote 10, the universe may have to exist in the extra two dimensions in order for God to have any causal powers over the other four; we just do not have epistemic access to these two extra dimensions. </s><s n="s4.6;p23.26">If we view a cube head on, it appears to us as a square despite it having a third dimension; depth. </s><s n="s5.6;p23.26">Also, if we cannot gain a change in perspective the cube will appear to us as a square and, as such, we will be unable to determine if it is a cube or a square. </s><s n="s6.6;p23.26">There is nothing incoherent with positing extra dimensions that are epistemically inaccessible. </s></p><p n="p24.26"><s n="s1.5;p24.26">A three-dimensional object can cause changes to a two-dimensional object, we can imagine a cube striking a straight line and causing it to bend. </s><s n="s2.5;p24.26">However, the dimension that is influenced is the dimension shared by both objects. </s><s n="s3.5;p24.26">God may thus have to share the same four dimensions that we exist in; in order to exert any causal power over them. </s><s n="s4.5;p24.26">It remains to be seen whether a God transcendent of these four dimensions can have any causal authority over them, although if we see the universe as dependent upon God rather than existing in a causal relationship then this problem does not arise. </s><s n="s5.5;p24.26">It depends on whether we wish to view Biblical stories of an interactive God as literal or metaphorical. </s></p><p n="p25.26"><s n="s1.1;p25.26">It must also be noted that finite objects can only affect other finite objects in the same, shared dimension, an infinite being such as God may well be perfectly capable of asserting Himself upon dimensions in which he transcends. </s></p><p n="p26.26"><s n="s1.2;p26.26">This essay has hopefully shown that we can have a view of a God, in which He transcends our space and time, yet exists in space and time qua space and time. </s><s n="s2.2;p26.26">God's transcendence is likely to be an epistemic transcendence rather than a metaphysical one and although the extra dimensions posited above may create more problems than they solve, it does seem as though progress can be made on the issues bought to light in the essay. </s></p></div1></body><back><div1 type="bibliography"><head rend="bold">Bibliography</head><p>Bertocci, P; 1951; <hi rend="italic">Introduction to the Philosophy of Religion</hi>; New York: Prentice Hall</p><p>Leftow, B [ed. Quine, P; Taliaferro, C]; 1997; <hi rend="italic">Eternity</hi> [<hi rend="italic">A Companion to Philosophy of Religion</hi>]; Oxford: Blackwell Publishing </p><p>Miles, T; 1966; <hi rend="italic">On Excluding the Supernatural</hi>; Religious Studies 1: 2</p><p>Poidevin, R; 2003; <hi rend="italic">Travels in Four Dimensions; The Enigmas of Space and Time</hi>; Oxford: Oxford University Press</p><p>Smolin, L [ed. Brockman, J]; 2003; <hi rend="italic">Loop Quantum Gravity</hi> [<seg type="URL" n="www.edge.org"/>]; URL: <seg type="URL" n="http://www.edge.org/3rd_culture/smolin03/smolin03_print.html"/>; last accessed: 24/04/06</p><p>Steinhardt, P and Turok, N; 2004; <hi rend="italic">The Cyclic Model Simplified</hi>; URL: <seg type="URL" n="http://wwwphy.princeton.edu/~steinh/dm2004.pdf"/>; last accessed: 24/04/06</p><p>Stump, E and Kretzmann, N; 1981; <hi rend="italic">Eternity</hi>; Journal of Philosophy 78</p><p>Taliaferro, C; 1998; <hi rend="italic">Contemporary Philosophy of Religion</hi>; Oxford: Blackwell Publishing</p><p>Taylor, R; 1974; <hi rend="italic">Metaphysics</hi>; Englewood Cliffs: Prentice Hall</p></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
