<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_0306g" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>A Mössbauer Investigation into the Hyperfine Interactions of Magnetite and Barium Hexaferrite</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">deleted: header: three student names; footer: page number</note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">two columns</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">3</p><p n="date">2005-02</p><p n="module title">Physics Laboratory</p><p n="module code">PX428</p><p n="genre family">Research report</p><p n="discipline">Physics</p><p n="disciplinary group">PS</p><p n="grade">M</p><p n="number of authors">3</p><p n="number of words">3275</p><p n="number of s-units">133</p><p n="number of p">46</p><p n="number of tables">2</p><p n="number of figures">8</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">18</p><p n="number of lists">0</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">6</p><p n="abstract present">abstract present</p><p n="average words per s-unit">24.6</p><p n="average s-units per p">2.9</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">f</p><p n="year of birth">1984</p><p n="first language">English</p><p n="education">UKA</p><p n="course">Mphys F303</p><p n="student ID">0306</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><docTitle><titlePart rend="bold italic">A Mössbauer Investigation into the Hyperfine Interactions of Magnetite and Barium Hexaferrite</titlePart></docTitle><titlePart rend="italic"><name type="student name"/>, <name type="student name"/>, <name type="student name"/></titlePart></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="abstract"><p n="p1.46"><s n="s1.4;p1.46">Hyperfine interactions within the nuclei of Magnetite [Fe <hi rend="sub">3</hi>O <hi rend="sub">4</hi>] and Barium Ferrite [BaFe <hi rend="sub">12</hi>O <hi rend="sub">19</hi>] were studied using the Mössbauer effect at s.t.p with a 10mCi <hi rend="sup">57</hi>Co gamma ray source. </s><s n="s2.4;p1.46">Zeeman Splitting and Isomer and Quadrupole shifting was observed in the Magnetite and Barium Ferrite samples. </s><s n="s3.4;p1.46">It was determined that both sources produced two spectra from their respective A and B sites with Hyperfine fields; <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0306g-form.001"/>, <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0306g-form.002"/>, <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0306g-form.003"/>, <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0306g-form.004"/> and relative isomer shifts (A-B); <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0306g-form.005"/>, <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0306g-form.006"/>. </s><s n="s4.4;p1.46">Quadrupolar shifts were observed to be minor contributors to the overall spectra. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">1. Introduction </head><div2><head rend="bold">1.1 The Mössbauer Effect</head><p n="p2.46"><s n="s1.2;p2.46">In order for a gamma ray that has been emitted from an excited nuclear state, to be absorbed into an identical nuclear state it must have exactly the same transition energy. </s><s n="s2.2;p2.46">This process is known as resonant absorption. </s></p><p n="p3.46"><s n="s1.8;p3.46">Under normal circumstances, as a nucleus emits this γ-ray, it recoils as a result of conservation of energy. </s><s n="s2.8;p3.46">The emitted gamma ray therefore has less energy than the transition that produced it, and this energy is less than the natural line width necessary for photon absorption to occur. </s><s n="s3.8;p3.46">The Mössbauer effect describes the particular cases in which the nuclei are effectively 'recoil-less' and the gamma ray can once again be absorbed. </s><s n="s4.8;p3.46">The radiation can be supplied with the exact amount of energy necessary by two common methods. </s><s n="s5.8;p3.46">Firstly, the nuclei can be frozen into a crystal lattice with low states of vibration, and hence the recoil energy will be effectively reduced to zero. </s><s n="s6.8;p3.46">The second method, that will be made use of in this experiment, is to Doppler broaden the gamma ray spectrum so that there is a possibility of resonant absorption in another atom. </s><s n="s7.8;p3.46">This is achieved by varying <hi rend="italic">v</hi>, the velocity of the source relative to the absorber which, in turn, increases the kinetic energy of the gamma ray. </s><s n="s8.8;p3.46">This effectively cancels out the effect of the recoil and the gamma ray now has enough energy to be within the natural line width, and will be absorbed into similar nuclei <hi rend="bold">[1].</hi> </s></p><p n="p4.46"><s n="s1.4;p4.46">If we place a certain material (absorber) in between a gamma ray emitter of a particular energy, and a detector, we will produce a spectrum that shows at which energy some of the gamma rays were absorbed into that material. </s><s n="s2.4;p4.46">If the detector were of infinite resolution efficiency, the line on this spectrum would represent a Dirac delta function, but instead it will appear as a Lorentzian curve where that line would be. </s><s n="s3.4;p4.46">The full width at half maximum height (FWHM) divided by the height of the Lorenztian (ΔΕ/Ε) will compute to give the error in the detector resolution. </s><s n="s4.4;p4.46"><hi rend="italic">Figure 1.1</hi> shows the simplest Lorenztian modelled spectrum that is produced when the emitter and absorber are identical. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0306g-fig.001"><head>Figure 1.1. A Gamma Ray absorption spectrum <hi rend="bold">[2]</hi></head></figure><p n="p5.46"><s n="s1.3;p5.46">This principle of photon absorption is the basis for determining the hyperfine structures of different materials. </s><s n="s2.3;p5.46">There are three main quantum mechanical effects known as hyperfine interactions that distort the picture as shown in <hi rend="italic">figure 1.1</hi>. </s><s n="s3.3;p5.46">These effects will split energy levels within the nuclei and hence will split the lines that appear on the spectrum where the gamma rays have been absorbed. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">1.2 Hyperfine Interactions</head><div3><head rend="bold">1.2.1 Isomer Shift</head><p n="p6.46"><s n="s1.3;p6.46">The isomer shift is caused by the non-infinitesimal volume of the nucleus and the electron charge density due to the s-electrons within it. </s><s n="s2.3;p6.46">S-orbitals have a maximum electron density centred at the nucleus and therefore have a large effect on the overall charge density of the nucleus (see <hi rend="italic">figure 1.2</hi>). </s><s n="s3.3;p6.46">Any differences between the s-electrons in the source and in the sample result in a monopole (Coulomb) interaction changing the nuclear energy levels and hence a shift in the Mössbauer absorption lines. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0306g-pic.001"><head>Figure 1.2a. S-orbitals (<hi rend="italic">l</hi> = 0) are spherically symmetric about the nucleus, since <hi rend="italic">ml</hi> (the magnetic quantum number) can only equal 0. </head></figure><figure id="BAWE_0306g-pic.002"><head>Figure 1.2b. A plot of the probability function for an s-electron (in this case a 1s) showing the electron density maximum at the nucleus. To the right a 3-D plot illustrates this <hi rend="bold">[3]</hi> . </head></figure><p n="p7.46"><s n="s1.2;p7.46">The first factor to be considered is the total number of s-electrons present. </s><s n="s2.2;p7.46">Any change in valency or configuration, resulting in a change in the total number of s-electrons, will result in a significant isomer shift. </s></p><p n="p8.46"><s n="s1.7;p8.46">Another main factor contributing to the isomer shift regards the density of the non s-electrons. </s><s n="s2.7;p8.46">This is because the wave function of an s-electron is not independent of the number and type of other electrons in the same atom. </s><s n="s3.7;p8.46">The electron density of the p, d, f etc. electrons influences the spatial distribution of the s-electrons on the same atom by inter-electronic repulsion, and the amplitudes of s-electron wavefunctions at the nucleus are therefore dependent on electron densities elsewhere in the atom. </s><s n="s4.7;p8.46">The p, d, f etc. electrons are said to "shield" the s-electrons from the nucleus. </s><s n="s5.7;p8.46">Consider, for example, the electron configurations of Fe <hi rend="sup">2+</hi> and Fe <hi rend="sup">3+</hi> which are (3d)<hi rend="sup">6</hi> and (3d)<hi rend="sup">5</hi> respectively. </s><s n="s6.7;p8.46">The ferrous (Fe <hi rend="sup">2+</hi>) have fewer s-electrons at the nucleus due to the greater screening of the d-electrons. </s><s n="s7.7;p8.46">Hence the ferrous ions have a greater positive isomer shifts than the ferric (Fe <hi rend="sup">3+</hi>) ions. </s></p><p n="p9.46"><s n="s1.1;p9.46">The isomer shift δ (mms <hi rend="sup">-1</hi>) can be found from the spectra as the difference of the energy peak(s) from the zero velocity point, as shown in <hi rend="italic">figure 1.3</hi>. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0306g-fig.002"><head>Figure 1.3. Representation of isomer shift on a gamma ray absorption spectrum</head></figure></div3><div3><head rend="bold">1.2.2 Quadrupole Splitting </head><p n="p10.46"><s n="s1.8;p10.46">In the nucleus the charge density ρ is given at any point by ρ = ψ *ψ where ψ is the wavefunction describing charge bearing nuclear particles, and ψ * is its complex conjugate. </s><s n="s2.8;p10.46">Therefore ρ is always an even function. </s><s n="s3.8;p10.46">A nuclear dipole moment is not allowed because it means that there would have to be an inversion through the coordinate centre, a coordinate system which is centro-symmetric (i.e it is not an even function). </s><s n="s4.8;p10.46">However a quadrupole moment is allowed with this system, because it has a charge density which is symmetrical with respect to inversion through the centre (an even function). </s><s n="s5.8;p10.46">This does not mean that there are negative charges on the nucleus, just a non spherical charge distribution. </s><s n="s6.8;p10.46">This asymmetric electric field (produced by an asymmetric electronic charge distribution or ligand arrangement) splits the nuclear energy levels. </s><s n="s7.8;p10.46">The quantity describing this charge distribution is known a as the Electric Field Gradient (EFG). </s><s n="s8.8;p10.46">EFG's are generated at a nucleus whenever the symmetry is less than cubic. </s></p><p n="p11.46"><s n="s1.4;p11.46">The interaction between a nuclear quadrupole and an EFG is quantised, splitting the nuclear energy levels without removing the degeneracy remains in states with the same spin M <hi rend="sub">I</hi>. </s><s n="s2.4;p11.46">In the case of <hi rend="sup">57</hi>Fe the ground state has a spin of ½, whilst the excited state at 14.4 keV has a spin of 3/2. </s><s n="s3.4;p11.46">The EFG does not effect the ground state, however it splits the excited state into sub-states with M <hi rend="sub">I</hi> = ±3/2 and M <hi rend="sub">I</hi> = ±1/2 removing the degeneracy between the sub-states. </s><s n="s4.4;p11.46">This is observed as a "quadrupole split" in the Mössbauer spectrum corresponding to the energy difference between the sub-states (<hi rend="italic">figure 1.4</hi>). </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0306g-fig.003"><head>Figure 1.4. A Diagram showing the quadrupole split of <hi rend="sup">57</hi> Fe nucleus in its excited state. This split corresponds to two observed absorption energies <hi rend="bold">[2]</hi> . </head></figure><p n="p12.46"><s n="s1.3;p12.46">EFG's at nuclear sites can be generated by charges in the lattice of those of the atom itself. </s><s n="s2.3;p12.46">For a closed-shell (i.e full outer shell) atom EFG's are generated in non-cubic structures, in the octahedral site of a cubic lattice the symmetry is such that an EFG is not produced. </s><s n="s3.3;p12.46">EFG's also produced by open-shell atoms, once each orbital has been allocated an electron (spherically symmetric case) the next electron joins one of the orbitals with opposite spin (Pauli Exclusion Principle) creating a non-spherically symmetric charge distribution and hence an electric field gradient. </s></p></div3><div3><head rend="bold">1.2.3 Magnetic Interactions</head><p n="p13.46"><s n="s1.5;p13.46">In the presence of a magnetic field the nuclear energy states are split causing splitting in the observed Mössbauer spectrum. </s><s n="s2.5;p13.46">For <hi rend="sup">57</hi>Fe the upper state with I = 3/2 splits into four, I = ±3/2 and I = ±1/2, and the lower state with I = 1/2 splits into two, I = ±1/2. </s><s n="s3.5;p13.46">This is known as Zeeman splitting. </s><s n="s4.5;p13.46">Here it might be expected that this would lead to 8 different absorption lines. </s><s n="s5.5;p13.46">However, the value of M <hi rend="sub">I</hi> is not allowed to change by more than one during a Mössbauer transition, reducing the number of absorption lines to 6 (see <hi rend="italic">figure 1.5</hi>). </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0306g-fig.004"><head>Figure 1.5. A diagram showing how a magnetic field splits the nuclear energy levels for <hi rend="sup">57</hi> Fe. The excited state splits into four and the ground state splits into two. The energy transitions produce the six absorption lines on the Mö ssbauer spectrum <hi rend="bold">[2]</hi> . </head></figure><p n="p14.46"><s n="s1.1;p14.46">The total effective magnetic field at the nucleus, B <hi rend="sub">eff</hi> is given by </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p15.46"><s n="s1.1;p15.46"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0306g-form.007"/><hi rend="bold">(1)</hi> </s></p><p n="p16.46"><s n="s1.3;p16.46">The B <hi rend="sub">applied</hi> term can be ignored there as there were no external magnetic fields applied in this experiment. </s><s n="s2.3;p16.46">The cases investigated in this experiment are due to the other three terms because of the atom's own unpaired electrons. </s><s n="s3.3;p16.46">B <hi rend="sub">contact</hi> is due to the spin on those electrons polarising the spin density at the nucleus, B <hi rend="sub">orbital</hi> is due to the orbital moment of those electrons, and B <hi rend="sub">dipolar</hi> is the dipolar field due to the spin of those electrons. </s></p><p n="p17.46"><s n="s1.7;p17.46">In the case of <hi rend="sup">57</hi>Fe, B <hi rend="sub">contact</hi> is due to the unpaired electrons in the 3d orbitals. </s><s n="s2.7;p17.46">There is a superior number of electrons one particular spin (m <hi rend="sub">s</hi> = ±1/2) because the unpaired electrons are all of the same spin. </s><s n="s3.7;p17.46">The exchange interaction has the effect of slightly reducing the repulsion between electrons having the same value of m <hi rend="sub">s</hi>. </s><s n="s4.7;p17.46">The 3d unpaired electrons "attract" all the other electrons in the atom with matching spin. </s><s n="s5.7;p17.46">This leaves a superior number of electrons with the opposite m <hi rend="sub">s</hi> at all the other points in the atom. </s><s n="s6.7;p17.46">If the s-electrons, which have electron density centred on the nucleus (see <hi rend="italic">figure 1.2b</hi>), become polarized they interact with the nucleus by a mechanism known as the Fermi contact interaction. </s><s n="s7.7;p17.46">This produces a large magnetic field at the nucleus, H <hi rend="sub">B</hi>, opposing the field generated by the spins in the 3d orbitals. </s></p><p n="p18.46"><s n="s1.2;p18.46">The B <hi rend="sub">orbital</hi> term is due to the orbital motion of the unpaired electrons about the nucleus. </s><s n="s2.2;p18.46">This constitutes to a circular electric current generating a magnetic field H <hi rend="sub">L</hi> at the nucleus. </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p19.46"><s n="s1.1;p19.46"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0306g-form.008"/><hi rend="bold">(2)</hi> </s></p><p n="p20.46"><s n="s1.1;p20.46">Above, μ<hi rend="sub">B</hi> is the Bohr magnetron and L is the orbital angular momentum vector where <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0306g-form.009"/> </s></p><p n="p21.46"><s n="s1.2;p21.46">and <hi rend="italic"> l</hi> is the orbital quantum number. </s><s n="s2.2;p21.46">The triangular brackets indicate integration over the whole atom. </s></p><p n="p22.46"><s n="s1.1;p22.46">Finally, the unpaired electrons behave as small bar magnets, due to their spin, generating a magnetic field, H <hi rend="sub">D</hi>, by dipole interaction with the nucleus. </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p23.46"><s n="s1.1;p23.46"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0306g-form.010"/><hi rend="bold">(3)</hi> </s></p><p n="p24.46"><s n="s1.1;p24.46">In this equation, S is the spin angular momentum vector where <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0306g-form.011"/> </s></p><p n="p25.46"><s n="s1.2;p25.46">and <hi rend="italic">s</hi> is the spin quantum number. </s><s rend="bold" n="s2.2;p25.46">[4] </s></p></div3></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">2. Procedure</head><p n="p26.46"><s n="s1.1;p26.46">This experiment made use of a 10mCi <hi rend="sup">57</hi>Co source that decayed to produce <hi rend="sup">57</hi>Fe in its excited state which, in turn, will produce gamma rays of 14.4keV. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0306g-fig.005"><head>Figure 2.1. The decay of <hi rend="sup">57</hi> Fe to produce gamma radiation</head></figure><p n="p27.46"><s n="s1.1;p27.46">These rays were used to create absorption spectra for Magnetite [Fe <hi rend="sub">3</hi>O <hi rend="sub">4</hi>] and Barium Ferrite [BaFe <hi rend="sub">12</hi>O <hi rend="sub">19</hi>] and hence determine the hyperfine interactions present in these materials. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0306g-pic.003"><head>Figure 2.2. Schematic of apparatus used to collect absorption spectra <hi rend="bold">[4]</hi></head></figure><div2><head rend="bold">2.1 Apparatus </head><p n="p28.46"><s n="s1.5;p28.46">The Cobalt source was secured inside lead shielding, with a collimator to direct the gamma radiation towards the absorber and detector. </s><s n="s2.5;p28.46">It was also mounted upon an oscillating loudspeaker coil, to produce the Doppler broadening. </s><s n="s3.5;p28.46">This vibrating device was connected to a control system with which the velocity <hi rend="italic">v</hi> could be measured and varied. </s><s n="s4.5;p28.46">Linked in with this system was an oscilloscope, so that the pulse characteristics and stability could be monitored and altered in order to ensure that the whole spectrum was detected. </s><s n="s5.5;p28.46">All of this is shown schematically in <hi rend="italic">figure 2.2</hi>. </s></p><p n="p29.46"><s n="s1.2;p29.46">The absorbers Magnetite and Barium Ferrite were prepared specifically by hand, as thin discs of powder held together under high pressure. </s><s n="s2.2;p29.46">In order for an ideal spectrum that let just enough counts through as to be distinguishable we wanted the sample to be of the appropriate thickness so that the recorded intensity, <hi rend="italic">I,</hi> that could pass through the absorber, as a fraction of the initial intensity <hi rend="italic">Io</hi>, would be roughly eight percent. </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p30.46"><s n="s1.1;p30.46"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0306g-form.012"/><hi rend="bold">(4)</hi> </s></p><p n="p31.46"><s n="s1.2;p31.46">By <hi rend="italic">equation 5</hi>, where <hi rend="italic">x</hi> is the thickness of the absorber (m), and μ (m <hi rend="sup">-1</hi>) is the absorption coefficient of that material, this corresponds to a given <hi rend="italic">x</hi> so that <hi rend="italic">μx</hi> = 2.5. </s><s n="s2.2;p31.46">The absorption coefficients for Magnetite and Barium Ferrite were determined using the formula </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p32.46"><s n="s1.1;p32.46"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0306g-form.013"/><hi rend="bold">(5)</hi> </s></p><p n="p33.46"><s n="s1.5;p33.46">This describes the mass absorption coefficient μ/ρ for the compound as a sum of the mass absorption coefficients for the <hi rend="italic">i</hi> elements within that compound multiplied by the mass fraction <hi rend="italic">gi</hi> of that element present in the compound. </s><s n="s2.5;p33.46">Once this was determined by referencing μ/ρ values, the final value was multiplied by the density of the compound ρ (kgm <hi rend="sup">-3</hi>) to find the appropriate μ for both Magnetite and Barium Ferrite. </s><s n="s3.5;p33.46">From this, the necessary thickness of the sample <hi rend="italic">x</hi> was deduced, and this would be used to create a cylindrical disc of 13mm diameter (<hi rend="italic">r</hi> = 6.5mm). </s><s n="s4.5;p33.46">This would correspond to a mass of <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0306g-form.014"/> of that sample that would be accurately measured upon a balance and crushed into a fine powder with a pestle and mortar. </s><s n="s5.5;p33.46">Both the Magnetite and Barium Ferrite samples used a mass of powder of the order of 10 <hi rend="sup">-5</hi>kg. </s></p><p n="p34.46"><s n="s1.2;p34.46">Boron Nitrate was added to the powder so that it would hold together more easily when compacted using a 10 ton hydraulic press. </s><s n="s2.2;p34.46">The Boron Nitrate would not introduce a significant absorbing power into the disc as it possesses a much smaller atomic mass than the heavier iron-based compounds used to experiment. </s></p><p n="p35.46"><s n="s1.5;p35.46">Once prepared, the sample was placed in between the source and the detector, which was of the proportional counter type. </s><s n="s2.5;p35.46">Counts were registered in 1024 channels that covered the entire range of the velocity scale that was chosen. </s><s n="s3.5;p35.46">The counts and velocity were linked via the multi-channel store, and the information was finally displayed on the monitor as a spectrum of counts vs. channel number. </s><s n="s4.5;p35.46">Channel number could later be calibrated to the velocity values and finally energy values by reference to Doppler formulae. </s><s n="s5.5;p35.46">The calibration was performed by obtaining a spectrum for <hi rend="sup">57</hi>Fe, for which the expected velocity peaks were known. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">2.2 Normos</head><p n="p36.46"><s n="s1.5;p36.46">The spectra obtained, and stored in terms of number of counts per channel, were analysed using the Normos Mössbauer fitting program <hi rend="bold">[5]</hi>. </s><s n="s2.5;p36.46">This allows for retrieval of accurate data relating to the sample as follows. </s><s n="s3.5;p36.46">Estimated values of relevant parameters (most importantly source velocity (V), Magnetic Hyperfine Field Strength (BHF) and Isomer and Quadrupolar shifts (ISO and QUA)) are input by the user for a chosen number of subspectra. </s><s n="s4.5;p36.46">A theoretical spectrum is generated based on the input parameters. </s><s n="s5.5;p36.46">This is fitted to the experimental spectrum and more accurate parameter values are calculated, this will only work if the input parameters are similar to the actual values, if they are not then the fit will be poor and the parameter values given will be inaccurate. </s></p><p n="p37.46"><s n="s1.1;p37.46">Normos also calculates <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0306g-form.015"/>, an important result in this kind of statistical analysis, which is a measure of the deviation in experiment from theory and is given by: </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p38.46"><s n="s1.1;p38.46"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0306g-form.016"/><hi rend="bold"> (6)</hi> </s></p><p n="p39.46"><s n="s1.1;p39.46">where <hi rend="italic">O</hi> is the observed spectrum and <hi rend="italic">T</hi> is the theoretical spectrum. </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">3. Results and Analysis</head><div2><head rend="bold">3.1 Calibration using 57Fe enriched sample</head><p n="p40.46"><s n="s1.2;p40.46"><hi rend="sup">57</hi>Fe is a well known Mössbauer sample with a monocrystalline structure and has BHF = 33.3 0.05 Tesla <hi rend="bold">[6]</hi> (and ISO = 0.1mms <hi rend="sup">-1</hi><hi rend="bold">[7]</hi>). </s><s n="s2.2;p40.46">This was used to accurately calibrate V, it was found that V = 11.3mms <hi rend="sup">-1</hi> 0.05mms <hi rend="sup">-1</hi>. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">3.2 Magnetite (Fe3O4)</head><p n="p41.46"><s n="s1.3;p41.46">Magnetite is known to produce two subspectra due to its tetrahedral and octahedral crystal structures, referred to as sites A and B respectively, with a relative isomer shift of 0.4 mms <hi rend="sup">-1</hi><hi rend="bold">[7]</hi>. </s><s n="s2.3;p41.46">Results from the fitting are given in Table 3.1, the final spectrum is shown in Figure 3.1. </s><s n="s3.3;p41.46">The fitted double spectrum (figure 3.1) shows good agreement with experiment, <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0306g-form.017"/> (a value of the order unity is generally acceptable <hi rend="bold">[8]</hi>). </s></p><table id="BAWE_0306g-tab.001"><head>Table 3.1: Results from fitted Magnetite spectrum.</head><row><cell/></row></table><figure id="BAWE_0306g-fig.006"><head>Figure 3.1: The Mö ssbauer spectrum for Magnetite Fe <hi rend="sub">3</hi> O <hi rend="sub">4</hi> . Experimental points are shown in blue, theoretical points are shown in pink. Coloured circles explained in discussion.</head></figure></div2><div2><head rend="bold">3.3 Barium Ferrite BaFe12O19</head><p n="p42.46"><s n="s1.2;p42.46">Barium Ferrite also has tetrahedral and octahedral crystal structures and so was treated in the same way as the Magnetite sample (its relative isomer shift is -01±0.03); results are given in Table 3.2 and Figure 3.2 below. </s><s n="s2.2;p42.46">This double spectrum agrees well with experiment, <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0306g-form.018"/>. </s></p><table id="BAWE_0306g-tab.002"><head>Table 3.2: Results from fitted Barium Ferrite spectrum.</head><row><cell/></row></table><figure id="BAWE_0306g-fig.007"><head>Figure 3.2: The Mö ssbauer spectrum for Barrium Ferrite BaFe <hi rend="sub">12</hi> O <hi rend="sub">19.</hi> Experimental points are shown in blue, theoretical points are shown in pink.</head></figure></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">4. Discussion </head><p n="p43.46"><s n="s1.1;p43.46">Upon entering the octahedral site the iron p-orbitals split from their degeneracy to form an upper pair of orbitals d <hi rend="sub">z</hi>2 and d <hi rend="sub">x</hi>2 <hi rend="sub">y</hi>2 and a lower triplet d <hi rend="sub">yz</hi>, d <hi rend="sub">xy</hi>, d <hi rend="sub">xz</hi> due to the proximity to negative charges in the crystal <hi rend="bold">[9]</hi>. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0306g-fig.008"><head>Fig 4.1. Diagram showing the splitting iron p-orbitals in an octahedral site <hi rend="bold">[10]</hi> .</head></figure><div2><head rend="bold">4.1 Magnetite</head><p n="p44.46"><s n="s1.9;p44.46">Fe <hi rend="sub">3</hi>O <hi rend="sub">4</hi> molecule, which can be thought of as FeO.Fe <hi rend="sub">2</hi>0 <hi rend="sub">3 ,</hi>has a spinel crystal structure with a cubic unit cell containing 32 oxygen ions in an approximately close-packed array; the interstices between the oxygen ions are partially filled by the (smaller) Fe <hi rend="sup">2+</hi> and Fe <hi rend="sup">3+</hi> ions. </s><s n="s2.9;p44.46">The eight Fe <hi rend="sup">2+</hi> ions occupy half the octahedral (B) sites, surrounded by six oxygen atoms, with parallel spin. </s><s n="s3.9;p44.46">Eight of the Fe <hi rend="sup">3+</hi> ions occupy the rest of the B sites also with parallel spin. </s><s n="s4.9;p44.46">The remaining eight Fe <hi rend="sup">3+</hi> ions occupy tetrahedral (A) sites with anti-parallel spins (i.e opposing the spins of the B sites)<hi rend="bold"> [11]</hi>. </s><s n="s5.9;p44.46">Above a threshold temperature of 119K "hopping" of electrons removes the difference between the Fe <hi rend="sup">2+</hi> and Fe <hi rend="sup">3+</hi> and consequently the nuclei in the B sites feel the same field <hi rend="bold">[12][13][14][15]</hi>. </s><s n="s6.9;p44.46">Therefore the two different spectra correspond to the A sites and the B sites. </s><s n="s7.9;p44.46">It is the parallel spin B sites that create the larger positive isomer shift. </s><s n="s8.9;p44.46">The split in degeneracy associated with the octahedral site (illustrated in figure 4.1) creates an asymmetric electric field, which influences the s-electron density, consequently changing the field at the nucleus. </s><s n="s9.9;p44.46">The areas under each of the absorption peaks (assuming Lorentzian line shapes) correspond to the relative abundance of the associated site <hi rend="bold">[16].</hi> </s></p><p n="p45.46"><s n="s1.3;p45.46">The recorded spectrum for magnetite shows, quite clearly, the magnetic sextet associated with the iron nucleus. </s><s n="s2.3;p45.46">The A sites have a higher nuclear magnetic field resulting in a broader energy range of Zeeman splitting. </s><s n="s3.3;p45.46">For clarity the first two peaks have been labelled with a green and red dot for the A and B sites respectively. </s></p><p n="p46.46"><s n="s1.3;p46.46">However, this is not the whole story, because there does not appear to a difference between the 5 <hi rend="sup">th</hi> and 6 <hi rend="sup">th</hi> peak positions for the A and B sites (labelled with a blue dot). </s><s n="s2.3;p46.46">This is due to the positive isomer shift on the B sites caused by the asymmetrical charge distribution described earlier. </s><s n="s3.3;p46.46">For the B sites the spectrum has been shifted by an amount so as to compensate for the difference in magnetic Zeeman splitting for the 5 <hi rend="sup">th</hi> and 6 <hi rend="sup">th</hi> peaks resulting in superposition. </s></p></div2></div1></body><back><div1 type="bibliography"><head rend="bold">References</head><p><hi rend="bold">[1]</hi> <seg type="URL" n="http://people.ucsc.edu/~iwh/plotdata/mossbauer.pdf"/> (1st February 2005)</p><p><hi rend="bold">[2]</hi> <seg type="URL" n="http://www.rsc.org/lap/rsccom/dab/mossbauerspec/intro.htm"/> (1st February 2005)</p><p><hi rend="bold">[3]</hi> <seg type="URL" n="http://www.shef.ac.uk/chemistry/orbitron/AOs/4f/e-density-xzz-dots.html"/> (1st February 2005)</p><p><hi rend="bold">[4]</hi> T.E.Cranshaw, B.W. Dale, G.O. Longworth and C.E. Johnson, Mössbauer Spectroscopy and its applications, Cambridge University Press (1985)</p><p><hi rend="bold">[5]</hi> Normos Mössbauer Fitting Program, Wissenschaftliche Elektronik GMBH, Starnberg (1992)</p><p><hi rend="bold">[6]</hi> Günter Shatz and Alois Wiedinger, Nuclear Condensed Matter Physics, Wiley 1995</p><p><hi rend="bold">[7]</hi> I.J. Gruverman, Mössbauer Effect Methodology V. 4, Plenum Press (1968)</p><p><hi rend="bold">[8]</hi> <seg type="URL" n="http://www.georgetown.edu/faculty/ballc/webtools/web_chi_tut.html"/> (1st February 2005)</p><p><hi rend="bold">[9]</hi> G.W.C. Kaye and T.H. Labe, Table of Physical and Chemical Constants 16th edition, Longman (1995) pp391</p><p><hi rend="bold">[10]</hi> <seg type="URL" n="http://www.wwnorton.com/chemistry/concepts/chapter10/ch10_2.htm"/> (1st February 2005)</p><p><hi rend="bold">[11]</hi> J.R. Hook and H.E. Hall, Solid State Physics 2<hi rend="sup">nd</hi> Edition, Wiley (2003) pp241</p><p><hi rend="bold">[12]</hi> <seg type="URL" n="http://prola.aps.org/pdf/PR/v183/i2/p383_1"/></p><p><hi rend="bold">[13]</hi> W.Ќüding, Bull. Am. Phys. Soc. 13, 667 (1968).</p><p><hi rend="bold">[14]</hi> E.J.W.Verwey and P.W. Haayman, Physica 8, 979 (1941)</p><p><hi rend="bold">[15]</hi> A. Ito and Y. Ishikawa, J.Phys. Soc. Japan 18, 1465 (1963)</p><p><hi rend="bold">[16]</hi> G.A.Sawatzky, J.M.D.Coey, and A.H. Morrish, J. Appl. Phys. 40, 1402 (1969)</p></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
