<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_0306b" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Probing Hydrogen Bonds by High Resolution Solid-State NMR</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">deleted: page numbers</note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">two columns</note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">appendices: data tables</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">4</p><p n="date">2006-04</p><p n="module title">Project</p><p n="module code">PX402</p><p n="genre family">Research report</p><p n="discipline">Physics</p><p n="disciplinary group">PS</p><p n="grade">D</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">6711</p><p n="number of s-units">177</p><p n="number of p">52</p><p n="number of tables">6</p><p n="number of figures">17</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">10</p><p n="number of lists">0</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">0</p><p n="abstract present">abstract present</p><p n="average words per s-unit">37.9</p><p n="average s-units per p">3.4</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">f</p><p n="year of birth">1984</p><p n="first language">English</p><p n="education">UKA</p><p n="course">Mphys F303</p><p n="student ID">0306</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><docTitle><titlePart rend="bold italic">Probing Hydrogen Bonds by High Resolution Solid-State NMR</titlePart></docTitle><titlePart><name type="student name"/></titlePart></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="abstract"><p n="p1.52"><s rend="sup italic" n="s1.4;p1.52">13C CP MAS, 1H DQ MAS and 1H CRAMPS solid-state NMR spectroscopy were used in conjunction with solution-state NMR and crystal structure analyses to investigate weak intermolecular C-H···O bonding between bis(pyridinium)ethane and dibenzo-24-crown-8 structures, and uracil in crystalline form. </s><s rend="sup italic" n="s2.4;p1.52">Changes to 13C and 1H chemical shifts and proton proximity data strengthened the proposal of weak hydrogen bonding between the samples in both cases, as implied by the crystal structure data. </s><s rend="sup italic" n="s3.4;p1.52">The observed results add credence to the argument that weak hydrogen bonding plays as essential role in the self assembly of molecules in supramolecular crystalline structures. </s><s rend="sup" n="s4.4;p1.52"> </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">1. Introduction</head><div2><head rend="bold">1. 1 Hydrogen Bonding in Structural Chemistry</head><p n="p2.52"><s n="s1.2;p2.52">Previous studies clearly demonstrate the role of the intra-molecular hydrogen bond in influencing the self assembly of organic molecules into large crystal structures. </s><s n="s2.2;p2.52">This unique interaction is an essential component in determining the structure and function of biological molecules, the most prominent example of which can be seen in the base pairing structure of nucleic acids as shown in <hi rend="italic">Figure 1.1</hi>* [1].[2] </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0306b-fig.001"><head rend="italic">Figure 1.1. Strong hydrogen bonds between Watson and Crick DNA base pairs</head></figure><p n="p3.52"><s n="s1.5;p3.52">The textbook definition of a hydrogen bond is an electrostatic, donor-acceptor interaction that arises between hydrogen atoms and heteroatoms X and A under specific conditions. </s><s n="s2.5;p3.52">The electron density of a hydrogen atom that is covalently bonded to a strongly electronegative X atom is withdrawn from the hydrogen nucleus leaving it with a partial positive charge. </s><s n="s3.5;p3.52">A bond is formed if this X-H donor then interacts with a lone pair of electrons from another electronegative heteroatom, A, or polarisable pi electrons. </s><s n="s4.5;p3.52">This bond is universally noted as X-H···A, in which the hydrogen acts as a bonding agent between the donor X and acceptor A [2]. </s><s n="s5.5;p3.52">The geometry of this arrangement can be seen in <hi rend="italic">Figure 1.2a</hi>. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0306b-fig.002"><head><hi rend="italic">Figure 1.2</hi> <hi rend="italic">(a) Geometrical representation of a hydrogen bond.</hi> <hi rend="italic">(b) Electro-negativities of some common elements, given by the Pauling Scale </hi></head></figure><p n="p4.52"><s n="s1.5;p4.52">The electronegativities of X and A provide quantitative measures of the strength with which the hydrogen is stripped of electron density and hence interacts with acceptor atoms, playing an essential role in establishing which atoms can take part in hydrogen bonding as well as the strength of the resulting interaction. </s><s n="s2.5;p4.52">As shown in <hi rend="italic">Figure 1.2b</hi> [3], the strongest hydrogen bond will arise from F-H donors; decreasing in strength to the O-H and N-H configurations, and more controversially to C-H. Due to the variety of donor-acceptor pairs and strengths of interactions that were discovered over time, attempts were made to classify the interactions into 'very strong', 'strong' and 'weak' based upon various parameters such as the bond energy and the typical H···A distance <hi rend="italic">d,</hi> although the situation is still difficult to define (see <hi rend="italic">Table 1</hi>) [3]. </s><s n="s3.5;p4.52">Previously, a hydrogen bond was thought to mediate between two molecules only if the H···A distance were shorter than the sum of the van der Waal radii of these two atoms. </s><s n="s4.5;p4.52">This van der Waal criterion implied that the electrostatic force associated with the hydrogen bond would effectively 'switch off' over a large enough range, and at the time that this was hypothesised, was satisfied by all conventional bonds. </s><s n="s5.5;p4.52">It was not until after the weaker C-H···O bond was found to exhibit <hi rend="italic">d</hi> bond lengths in the range of 2.0-3.0Å, and yet a H···O radii sum of 2.5Å, that the view of the conventional bond was challenged [3,3b]. </s></p><table id="BAWE_0306b-tab.001"><head rend="italic">Table 1. Some properties of hydrogen bonds</head><row><cell/></row></table></div2><div2><head rend="bold">1. 2 The Weak Hydrogen Bond</head><p n="p5.52"><s n="s1.4;p5.52">The 'weak' hydrogen bond is formed when either or both of the X and A atoms are slightly more electroneutral relative to the hydrogen atom. </s><s n="s2.4;p5.52">As well as the C-H···O, C-H···N interactions, this classification also includes weak π bonds, where the acceptor has no lone electron pairs but a π electron orbital such as in a multiple bond or aromatic ring [3]. </s><s n="s3.4;p5.52">Multiple bonds and cyclic arrangements occur frequently in organic chemistry due to the high abundance of carbon and its necessity to create four attachments to surrounding atoms. </s><s n="s4.4;p5.52">The bond energies of weak interactions are comparable with van der Waals forces, whereas some very strong hydrogen bonds exhibit energies close to many covalently bonded systems. </s></p><p n="p6.52"><s n="s1.2;p6.52">In early years, the effects of the hydrogen bond were seen long before it was given a name, and there were few methods available in order to study the interaction in detail. </s><s n="s2.2;p6.52">Since then, crystal structure analysis, vibrational and NMR spectroscopy have become powerful tools for examining molecular structures and hydrogen bonding effects. </s></p><p n="p7.52"><s n="s1.3;p7.52">X-Ray and neutron diffraction experiments can provide direct information regarding stereochemistry of crystal structures; with regards to hydrogen bonding, it is crucial to know the position of the hydrogen atom and in turn the bond lengths and angles associated with different atoms can be observed. </s><s n="s2.3;p7.52">Crystallographic data stored in databases such as C.S.D.<ref target="BAWE_0306b-ftnote.001"/>† has made it possible to compare certain trends of strong and weak interactions in large numbers of crystals. </s><s n="s3.3;p7.52">The data implies that strong hydrogen bonds, such as O-H···O, favour short, linear arrangements (<hi rend="italic">θ~180o)</hi>, whereas the geometrical parameters tend to deviate much more for the weaker C-H···O bonds as they are more easily deformed by other interactions and must compromise with other forces present in the crystalline state (<hi rend="italic">Figure 1.3</hi>). [3] </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0306b-ftnote.001"><p n="pn1.2"><s n="s1.1;pn1.2">* It is common to find unlabelled carbon atoms and their connected hydrogens omitted from many structural diagrams due to their abundance </s></p><p n="pn2.2"><s n="s1.1;pn2.2">† Cambridge Structural Database, Cambridge Crystallographic Data Centre, Cambridge, U.K[3] </s></p></note><figure id="BAWE_0306b-fig.003"><head><hi rend="italic">Figure 1.3.</hi> <hi rend="italic">Geometrical characteristics for strong and weak hydrogen bonds, O-H···O shown in blue and C-H···O in red </hi></head></figure><p n="p8.52"><s n="s1.5;p8.52">In conjunction with crystal structure analysis, vibrational spectroscopy methods were used for many years to seek classifications of strength and donor-acceptor groups. </s><s n="s2.5;p8.52">These methods make use of electromagnetic radiation at the vibrational frequency of the atomic groups involved in the hydrogen bonding as a probe. </s><s n="s3.5;p8.52">When a hydrogen bond is formed the vibrational motion of the surrounding atoms is restricted, leading to frequency shifts sensitive to the strength of this bond. </s><s n="s4.5;p8.52">IR is still a major tool in this field, with around 100 papers written every year regarding hydrogen bonding [2]. </s><s n="s5.5;p8.52">However, while the correlations of structural and vibrational parameters prove true for stronger bonds, the effects of weak hydrogen bonds on vibrational spectra are less clear and can often be misinterpreted due to their frailty. </s></p><p n="p9.52"><s n="s1.2;p9.52">There is still much controversy amongst structural chemists as to whether these 'weak', 'non conventional' hydrogen bonds, such as the C-H···O or aromatic X-H-Ph bonds that occur so frequently in molecular biology, can indeed be regarded as stabilising interactions. </s><s n="s2.2;p9.52">While the conventional hydrogen bond has been long established in determining stable and predictable crystal packing arrangements [4], we must now establish whether the close proximities we observe in non conventional systems can similarly be attributed to the presence of a weaker hydrogen bond, or are simply chance arrangements caused by the other existing forces [5]. </s></p><p n="p10.52"><s n="s1.6;p10.52">NMR spectroscopy already enables us to chemically analyse crystals but, by comparison with other methods, truly compliments the investigation into hydrogen bonding. </s><s n="s2.6;p10.52">The <hi rend="sup">1</hi>H chemical shift provides an extremely powerful measure of the proton electronic environment and hence a probe of the hydrogen bond, with a magnitude qualitatively proportional to the bond strength [2]. </s><s n="s3.6;p10.52">The sensitivity of this technique makes it especially useful in identifying weak donors such as C-H or weak acceptors such as multiple bonds or aromatic rings. </s><s n="s4.6;p10.52">NMR and crystallographic data can be further reinforced using semi empirical or quantum chemistry calculations such as ab initio molecular orbital calculations that predict theoretical energy values of intermolecular interactions. </s><s n="s5.6;p10.52">Of particular relevance to the hydrogen bond, first principles calculations of chemical shift values have generally been found to agree within experimental limits [6,7]. </s><s n="s6.6;p10.52">As well as proton chemical shift data, the measurement of dipolar couplings with Double Quantum NMR techniques allow us to determine hydrogen proximities, to add to the direct detection of bonds via hydrogen bond mediated J couplings in liquids, and more recently, in the solid state [7,8,9].The full potential of solid-state NMR has not yet been recognized in this area, and some of the above techniques shall be exploited in this investigation. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">1. 3. Nuclear Magnetic Resonance</head><div3><head rend="bold">1. 3. 1. The NMR Phenomenon</head><p n="p11.52"><s n="s1.6;p11.52">The NMR phenomenon is based upon the inherent magnetic property of atomic nuclei, characterised by their nuclear spin quantum number <hi rend="italic">I</hi>. </s><s n="s2.6;p11.52">In a typical experiment, the sample of interest is immersed in a strong, static magnetic field, often defined as <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0306b-form.001"/>, which gives rise to different spin energy levels. </s><s n="s3.6;p11.52">In the absence of a magnetic field the nuclear spins are randomly orientated in space, but on application, the field acts to create a preferred alignment of the non-zero spins present in the sample, along the <hi rend="italic">Bo</hi> direction. </s><s n="s4.6;p11.52">The bulk magnetisation that arises, <hi rend="underlined italic">Mo</hi> (defined as the total induced magnetic moment per unit volume) can then be perturbed by a second oscillatory electromagnetic pulse. </s><s n="s5.6;p11.52">The response of the nuclei to this perturbation provides specific, localised information about the chemical structure of that sample. </s><s n="s6.6;p11.52">This study will probe the environments of the spin ½ nuclei shown in <hi rend="italic">Table 2</hi> [10] to gain localised information about weakly hydrogen bonded systems based upon the interactions of these nuclei with a strong magnetic field, and with each other [10,11,12]. </s></p><table id="BAWE_0306b-tab.002"><head rend="italic">Table 2. Properties of nuclei commonly found in organic solids </head><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p12.52"><s n="s1.1;p12.52">The static magnetic field, <hi rend="italic">Bo</hi>, causes the nuclear magnetic moments of the ensemble of non-zero spins to precess around </s></p><p n="p13.52"><s n="s1.5;p13.52">the field with constant angle and frequency <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0306b-form.002"/>, where is the gyromagnetic ratio of the nucleus. </s><s n="s2.5;p13.52">This frequency, known as the Larmor frequency is specific to each isotope, allowing us to differentiate between them. </s><s n="s3.5;p13.52">A much weaker, oscillatory magnetic field, <hi rend="underlined italic">B1</hi>, is then applied to the spin system perpendicular to the static field, in the xy plane, in the form of a radio frequency pulse. </s><s n="s4.5;p13.52">In order to perturb the aligned spins, the frequency of this pulsed field, <hi rend="italic">ωrf</hi>, must be close to, or on resonance with the particular nuclei we wish to observe <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0306b-form.003"/>, hence we apply pulses of the order of 10 <hi rend="sup">6</hi> Hz. </s><s n="s5.5;p13.52">In doing so, the bulk magnetisation is forced to rotate about the axis that the oscillatory field was applied [13]. </s></p><p n="p14.52"><s n="s1.5;p14.52">During an NMR experiment, the radiofrequency pulses are applied to manipulate the spin system in a certain manner, and are finally timed in order to 'flip' the magnetisation fully into the transverse plane for the signal to be detected. </s><s n="s2.5;p14.52">In the absence of the pulse, <hi rend="underlined italic">M</hi> then continues to precess about the static field with the same frequency, <hi rend="italic">ωo</hi>, as before the perturbing field was applied. </s><s n="s3.5;p14.52">It is the evolution of this rotating transverse magnetization that provides us with our NMR signal by inducing a voltage in the same coil of wire that was previously used to apply the oscillating pulse in the transverse plane, as demonstrated in <hi rend="italic">Figure 1.4</hi> [14]. </s><s n="s4.5;p14.52">The voltage will be a superposition of decaying oscillations of different <hi rend="italic">ωo</hi> frequencies, containing specific information about the structural environments of the nuclei that we perturbed. </s><s n="s5.5;p14.52">The NMR spectrometer then 'mixes down' this superposition of Larmor frequencies with the input radiofrequency to display resonance offset values of the sample <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0306b-form.004"/>[12]. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0306b-fig.004"><head><hi rend="italic">Figure 1.4.</hi> <hi rend="italic">Induction of an NMR Signal due to the rotation of the bulk magnetisation M, created from non-zero nuclear spins surrounded by a Bo field </hi></head></figure><p n="p15.52"><s n="s1.4;p15.52">Transient molecular fields of the magnetic particles that surround the nuclei force the magnetisation to relax back into its originally aligned state over time, causing an exponential decay of the detected signal. </s><s n="s2.4;p15.52">For this reason, the NMR signal is known as a Free Induction Decay (FID). </s><s n="s3.4;p15.52">Typical NMR signals are far more complex than that shown in <hi rend="italic">Figure 1.4</hi> due to the various ways in which the spins in sample interact with the magnetic field and with one another. </s><s n="s4.4;p15.52">It is these interactions that tell us about the structure of that sample. </s></p></div3><div3><head rend="bold">1. 3. 2. Nuclear Spin Interactions and Fourier Transform NMR</head><p n="p16.52"><s n="s1.6;p16.52">The most important nuclear spin interaction in NMR spectroscopy is undoubtedly the chemical shift, δ, that allows us to distinguish between different chemical sites of a given nucleus in any molecule or compound. </s><s n="s2.6;p16.52">Each nucleus is shielded from the static field by its surrounding electrons, as they interact with <hi rend="italic">Bo</hi> to create their own induced magnetic fields. </s><s n="s3.6;p16.52">The amount of shielding at each site is determined by the shielding tensor σ, and the local field that is experienced by any nucleus is hence dependent upon its electronic environment. </s><s n="s4.6;p16.52">This results in different Larmor frequencies for each chemical site, and the detected NMR signal is then a complex superposition of chemically shifted frequencies, <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0306b-form.005"/>[11]. </s><s n="s5.6;p16.52">In order to display this information more effectively, the FID signal in the time domain can be computationally Fourier transformed into the frequency domain where each peak represents a different chemical environment of the nuclei in the sample, see Figure 1.5 [15]. </s><s n="s6.6;p16.52">As the chemical shielding is dependent upon the B <hi rend="sub">o</hi> field strength, shifts are often quoted with reference to a common reference compound and given on an absolute scale of parts-per-million, defined by <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0306b-form.006"/>[11].[12] </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0306b-fig.005"><head><hi rend="italic">Figure 1.5 Representation of a Fourier Transformation of a time dependent NMR signal to give a frequency domain spectra. The widths of the resulting Lorentzian peaks are governed by the transverse relaxation time constants, T2</hi> , <hi rend="italic">for each chemical site, as well as anisotropic broadening interactions.</hi> </head></figure><p n="p17.52"><s n="s1.2;p17.52">Other interactions, most predominantly the dipolar coupling between spins, <hi rend="italic">D</hi>, are anisotropic (see <hi rend="italic">Figure 1.6a</hi>) [16] and therefore the resonance frequencies of the nuclei also depend upon the orientation of molecules in space. </s><s n="s2.2;p17.52">For solid-state experiments it is most probable that samples will be obtained in powdered form, and as such they consist of crystallites of all possible orientations with respect to the static field so that the resulting linewidths of NMR powder spectra are of considerably poor resolution, as shown in <hi rend="italic">Figure 1.6b</hi> [10,11]. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0306b-fig.006"><head><hi rend="italic">Figure 1.6(a) The Dipolar coupling interaction between two spins j, k, with separation vector rjk at an angle θ to the Bo field.</hi> <hi rend="italic">(b) Anisotropic broadening of spectral linewidth for a solid-state powdered sample</hi></head></figure></div3><div3><head rend="bold">1. 3. 3. High Resolution techniques in Solid State NMR</head><p n="p18.52"><s n="s1.8;p18.52">Samples in a liquid state undergo fast molecular tumbling that averages over all orientations on a timescale which is short compared to the NMR experiment. </s><s n="s2.8;p18.52">Since <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0306b-form.007"/>, anisotropic interactions are reduced to zero to yield well resolved spectral lines. </s><s n="s3.8;p18.52">We therefore improve spectral resolution in the solid state by mimicking this condition and physically rotate the powdered sample with a rotation frequency <hi rend="italic">υR</hi>, at an angle of <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0306b-form.008"/> to the static field [10,11]. </s><s n="s4.8;p18.52">The Magic Angle Spinning (MAS) technique has proven invaluable in distinguishing and assigning separate peaks, and hence interpreting NMR spectra accurately. </s><s n="s5.8;p18.52">For <hi rend="sup">13</hi>C spectra, increasing the rotation speed acts to separate out the 'spinning sidebands' that surround central peaks. </s><s n="s6.8;p18.52">Distances between the sidebands in Hz correspond to <hi rend="italic">υR</hi>, and it can be seen from <hi rend="italic">Figure 1.7b</hi> that for samples at speeds over 8kHz, these <hi rend="sup">13</hi>C sidebands exceed the ppm scale to produce resolutions of similar quality to solution state spectra. </s><s n="s7.8;p18.52">However, for <hi rend="sup">1</hi>H systems containing more than two spins, the anisotropic broadening caused by homonuclear dipolar coupling is not averaged to zero over one rotor period, τ<hi rend="sub">R.</hi> </s><s n="s8.8;p18.52">Instead, the linewidth reduces with the spinning speed <hi rend="italic">υR</hi> (see <hi rend="italic">Figure 1.7a</hi>) making it a critical yet limiting factor in proton NMR resolution and determination of chemical sites. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0306b-fig.007"><head rend="italic">Figure 1.7 Comparison of different MAS rotor speeds υR, upon (a) 1H and (b) 13C spectra for L-alanine. The parameters used for the above 13C CP MAS and 1H MAS experiments can be found in Section 2. </head></figure><p n="p19.52"><s n="s1.7;p19.52">As the overall line integral of many spectral peaks is constant, improved resolution also increases the ratio of signal to noise; an equally critical factor in recovering useful information from experiments [17]. </s><s n="s2.7;p19.52">The size of the NMR signal produced in a typical experiment is proportional to <hi rend="italic">γ3</hi> of a particular isotope as well as the number of nuclear spins, <hi rend="italic">N</hi>, present in the sample; a factor that creates further problems when observing nuclei of low natural abundance. </s><s n="s3.7;p19.52">Isotopes containing equal number of protons and neutrons such as <hi rend="sup">12</hi>C (see <hi rend="italic">Table 2</hi>) possess zero nuclear spin and do not respond to magnetic fields and hence the NMR procedure. </s><s n="s4.7;p19.52">In such cases we must often observe isotopes of much lower natural abundance, in this case <hi rend="sup">13</hi>C, which are much less receptive to the technique. </s><s n="s5.7;p19.52">For these experiments the overall signal produced will be around 6000 times weaker than that of a typical proton experiment due to a combination of these factors [11]. </s><s n="s6.7;p19.52">Dilute spins also tend to have considerably lengthened relaxation periods; taking a longer time for the bulk magnetisation to relax back to its equilibrium state before each experiment can be repeated. </s><s n="s7.7;p19.52">The fewer repeats that can be performed during experimental time limits reduces the signal to noise ratio further [17]. </s></p><p n="p20.52"><s n="s1.6;p20.52">The sensitivity of dilute spins can be considerably improved by transferring strong transverse magnetisation from nearby abundant nuclei to the rarer Y nuclei using a Cross Polarization (CP) technique, as shown in <hi rend="italic">Figure 1.8</hi> [18]. </s><s n="s2.6;p20.52">This transfer is mediated by the heteronuclear dipolar coupling between the two spin types, which also transfers the much shorter proton recycle time to the <hi rend="sup">13</hi>C nuclei; an even greater advantage to the technique. </s><s n="s3.6;p20.52">The CP sequence simultaneously applies on resonance contact pulses, B <hi rend="sub">1</hi>(Y) and B <hi rend="sub">1</hi>(<hi rend="sup">1</hi>H), to spin lock the dilute nuclei and the abundant protons in the same direction, where the magnitudes of the contact pulses satisfy the condition <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0306b-form.009"/>. </s><s n="s4.6;p20.52">However, during acquisition of the FID, anisotropic dipolar couplings between the two spin types cause broadenings of these weak spectra, and so heteronuclear decoupling must be carried out alongside this technique. </s><s n="s5.6;p20.52">High power pulses are therefore applied at proton resonance during the acquisition of the Y nuclei FID in order to repress these nuclear interactions and improve spectral resolution [19]. </s><s n="s6.6;p20.52">Multiple pulse decoupling sequences such as TPPM [20][21] (Two Pulse Phase Modulated) have proven to be much more effective than continuous wave (CW) decoupling methods. </s></p><p n="p21.52"><s n="s1.2;p21.52">A disadvantage of the cross polarisation technique is that results obtained via this process do not retain the quantitative nature of most single pulse NMR spectra. </s><s n="s2.2;p21.52">The integral ratios of the spectral peaks no longer represent the number of nuclei at each site due to the manner in which the magnetization is mediated. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0306b-fig.008"><head rend="italic">Figure 1.8Ramped CP pulse sequence for 13C spins. </head></figure><p n="p22.52"><s n="s1.1;p22.52"><hi rend="italic">A variable amplitude contact pulse is used to ease the matching condition and improve sensitivity, and TPPM decoupling (consisting of 180° pulses with a phase difference between pulses of 10-15°) to enhance resolution</hi> [12,19,22]. </s></p><p n="p23.52"><s n="s1.3;p23.52">The CP MAS technique is the principal method used for studying <hi rend="sup">13</hi>C in the solid state, and the spectra can be compared to those of single molecules in solution state to look for evidence of intermolecular weak hydrogen bonds in the crystal structure, indicated by chemical shifts of higher ppm values. </s><s n="s2.3;p23.52">The importance of the proton in the hydrogen bonding interaction, as well as their high sensitivity and ubiquity and nature, makes <hi rend="sup">1</hi>H spectroscopy essential to this investigation [10]. </s><s n="s3.3;p23.52">However, the lack of resolution of <hi rend="sup">1</hi>H spectra even at very high speeds imposes limits on the technique, and much more information regarding hydrogen bonding can be obtained by studying the separations of pairs of protons in space using two dimensional experiments. </s></p></div3><div3><head rend="bold">1. 3. 4. Two Dimensional Double Quantum Experiments </head><p n="p24.52"><s n="s1.2;p24.52">During a one dimensional sequence, isolated nuclear spins are 'flipped' between two energy levels corresponding to a single quantum coherence (SQC) frequency and, similarly, a strongly coupled pair of spins <hi rend="italic">j</hi> and <hi rend="italic">k</hi> can be flipped together as if a single unit to excite a double quantum coherence (DQC). </s><s n="s2.2;p24.52">A schematic of the energy levels between single and dipolar-coupled pairs that arise during these situations is shown in <hi rend="italic">Figure 1.9</hi> [23]. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0306b-fig.009"><head rend="italic">Figure 1.9. Energy levels and resonance frequencies for (a) a single spin I=½ nucleus and (b) dipolar-coupled pair of spin I=½ nuclei</head></figure><p n="p25.52"><s n="s1.2;p25.52">Double quantum coherences cannot be directly observed in an NMR experiment, and so spectra are inherently two dimensional and can be probed via a sequence such as that in <hi rend="italic">Figure 1.10</hi> [12]. </s><s n="s2.2;p25.52">Two dimensional experiments consist of two blocks of pulses separated by a time t <hi rend="sub">1</hi>, which is incremented, and each FID, acquired during t <hi rend="sub">2</hi> is stored as an array. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0306b-fig.010"><head><hi rend="italic">Figure 1.10. A two dimensional Fourier Transform experiment with two time variables. Double quantum coherences are created and reconverted using the BABA (back to back) pulse sequence, suitable for very fast MAS spinning speeds, υR ~ 40kHz</hi> [19, 24, 25].</head></figure><p n="p26.52"><s n="s1.3;p26.52">The strength of the dipolar coupling between the spin pair, <hi rend="italic">D</hi>, directly determines the excitation efficiency of the DQC and hence the evolution of the two spins as a function of the t <hi rend="sub">1</hi> time of the experiment. </s><s n="s2.3;p26.52">This coupling itself is strongly dependent upon the proximities of the spins, varying with separation as <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0306b-form.010"/> as displayed in <hi rend="italic">Figure 1.6</hi> [16].[26] Therefore, when the t <hi rend="sub">1</hi> and t <hi rend="sub">2</hi> signals are Fourier transformed in two dimensions, the presence of a spectral peak indicates a close separation between the <hi rend="italic">j</hi> and <hi rend="italic">k</hi> nuclei as demonstrated by <hi rend="italic">Figure 1.11</hi> [23]. </s><s n="s3.3;p26.52">For <hi rend="sup">1</hi>H DQ MAS this generally implies separations of less than 0.35nm, hence providing valuable information about inter- and intra-molecular proton-proton proximities and the structure of the sample [10]. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0306b-fig.011"><head rend="italic">Figure 1.11. Representation of a two dimensional Double Quantum Spectrum. The DQ frequency if the sum of the two SQ frequencies of close proximity spins j,k. </head></figure><p n="p27.52"><s n="s1.3;p27.52">As ever, the greater the resolution of spectra, the more accurately we can make assignments and deduce separations. </s><s n="s2.3;p27.52">The recently devised CRAMPS technique (Combined Rotation and Multiple Pulse Spectroscopy) has allowed an improvement of five fold in spectral resolution for such proton DQ experiments at much lower spinning speeds, as can be seen in <hi rend="italic">Figure 1.12</hi> [27]. </s><s n="s3.3;p27.52">The addition of optimized homonuclear decoupling sequences during the t <hi rend="sub">1</hi> and t <hi rend="sub">2</hi> experimental times act to reduce anisotropic broadenings in spin space, in a similar manner that MAS performs this task in real space, to produce enhanced spectral resolution ideal for <hi rend="sup">1</hi>H spectroscopy. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0306b-fig.012"><head><hi rend="italic">Figure 1.12Two dimensional Double Quantum 1H spectra of the dipeptide β-AspAla for</hi><hi rend="italic">(a) 1H DQ MAS with υR = 30kHz and(b) 1H DQ CRAMPS with υR = 12.5kHz</hi><hi rend="italic">The DQ frequency is the sum of the two SQ frequencies of close proximity </hi></head></figure></div3></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">2. Experimental Details </head><div2><head rend="bold">2. 1. Solid-state NMR</head><p n="p28.52"><s n="s1.5;p28.52">Solid-state NMR experiments were performed using finely ground powder samples of natural abundance. </s><s n="s2.5;p28.52">Those discussed in §3.1 were prepared at University of <name type="university"/> Chemistry Department, and others were obtained from Sigma Aldrich [28]. </s><s n="s3.5;p28.52">A Varian Infinity Plus spectrometer operating at a <hi rend="sup">13</hi>C resonance of 75.5MHz was used for <hi rend="sup">13</hi>C CP MAS experiments with a Bruker 4mm double resonance probe, spinning at approximately 8.5kHz. </s><s n="s4.5;p28.52">Ramped cross polarization from <hi rend="sup">1</hi>H to <hi rend="sup">13</hi>C with a contact time of 1ms was employed and TPPM heteronuclear decoupling [20,21] applied during acquisition. </s><s n="s5.5;p28.52">Each experiment incorporated a recycle delay of 3s unless stated otherwise in §3, along with a 2.5μs 90 <hi rend="sup">o</hi> pulse length corresponding to a nutation frequency of 100 kHz. </s></p><p n="p29.52"><s n="s1.5;p29.52"><hi rend="sup">1</hi>H double quantum experiments were performed on a Chemagnetics spectrometer operating at <hi rend="sup">1</hi>H Larmor frequency of 600.1MHz, using a Samoson 1.8mm probe. </s><s n="s2.5;p29.52">The MAS frequency of approximately 40kHz was synchronised with the rotor period τ<hi rend="sub">R</hi> of the BABA pulse sequence. </s><s n="s3.5;p29.52">As for the CP experiments, a 90 <hi rend="sup">o</hi> pulse length of 2.5μs was optimised for all proton experiments and a recycle time of 3s used for each sample, unless stated otherwise. </s><s n="s4.5;p29.52">Both spectrometers were controlled by Varian Spinsight software, also used for data processing and chemical shift scale calibration. </s><s n="s5.5;p29.52">All spectra were indirectly referenced to Tetra Methyl Silane (TMS) using L-alanine of natural abundance as a secondary reference </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">2. 2. Solution State NMR</head><p n="p30.52"><s n="s1.3;p30.52">Spectral peaks were assigned against solution-state NMR spectra from the online SDBS database [29] or from in-house experiments, for which samples were dissolved in acetonitrile (CD <hi rend="sub">3</hi>CN) with known <hi rend="sup">13</hi>C resonances of 117ppm and 1.9ppm. </s><s n="s2.3;p30.52">All experiments were performed on a Bruker DPX400 spectrometer with a Bruker 5mm dual resonance probe operating at a <hi rend="sup">1</hi>H frequency of 400.03MHz and a <hi rend="sup">13</hi>C frequency of 100.6MHz. </s><s n="s3.3;p30.52">This spectrometer operated with XwinNMR Version 3.4 software for data acquisition and processing. </s></p><p n="p31.52"><s n="s1.2;p31.52">Spectral editing methods that distinguished between carbons with even (CH <hi rend="sub">2</hi>, quaternary) and odd (CH <hi rend="sub">3</hi>, CH) numbers of attached protons were used to assign <hi rend="sup">13</hi>C MAS spectra.[3] Data was acquired with a 90 <hi rend="sup">o</hi> pulse length of 13.7us, 128 transients, a pulse delay of 2s and a WALTZ16 decoupling sequence set to 95μs at 17dB. </s><s n="s2.2;p31.52"><hi rend="sup">1</hi>H spectra were obtained using a 90 <hi rend="sup">o</hi> pulse length of 11.25μs, 16 transients and a recycle delay of 1s. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">2. 3. Crystal Structure Analyses</head><p n="p32.52"><s n="s1.1;p32.52">NMR data were compared with crystal structures of samples, viewed using Diamond Crystal and Molecular Structure Visualization software [30] with data from x-ray or neutron diffraction studies taken from the CDS structural database [31]. </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">3. Results </head><div2><head rend="bold">3. 1. Weak C-H···O hydrogen bonds in the self-assembly of pseudorotoxanes</head><p n="p33.52"><s n="s1.5;p33.52">As the NMR chemical shift is directly governed by the electronic structure of molecules, it is an ideal tool for identifying interactions that alter electronic environment, such as the hydrogen bond. </s><s n="s2.5;p33.52">It is commonly accepted that a strong hydrogen bond, such as that involving N···H groups in proteins, will deshield the proton and nitrogen atoms, in turn shifting their resonance frequencies 'downfield' to higher ppm values. </s><s n="s3.5;p33.52">For protons involved in this hydrogen bond, the shift, Δδ, typically ranges between 0.5~3ppm. </s><s n="s4.5;p33.52">It has also been investigated that the magnitude of this shift is quantitatively related to the strength of the bond and hence the H···X distance (<hi rend="italic">d</hi>) [32,33]. </s><s n="s5.5;p33.52">Based on this previous work one can infer that C-H···O bonds will also result in altered <hi rend="sup">1</hi>H and <hi rend="sup">13</hi>C chemical shifts, with many other studies attempting to substantiate this and hence the argument in favour of the weaker C-H···O interaction as a stablizing bond. </s></p><p n="p34.52"><s n="s1.3;p34.52">This study endeavours to confirm intermolecular connectivies between the bis(pyridinium)ethane axle (C <hi rend="sub">18</hi>H <hi rend="sub">22</hi>B <hi rend="sub">2</hi>F <hi rend="sub">8</hi>N <hi rend="sub">2</hi>O <hi rend="sub">4</hi>) and the symmetrical dibenzo-24-crown-8 (C <hi rend="sub">24</hi>H <hi rend="sub">32</hi>O <hi rend="sub">8</hi>) ether ring when combined to form a pseudorotoxane, using solution and solid state <hi rend="sup">13</hi>C and <hi rend="sup">1</hi>H shifts in conjunction with crystal structure analysis. </s><s n="s2.3;p34.52">It has recently been reported that, in solution, the axle <hi rend="bold">1</hi> threads through the crown molecule <hi rend="bold">2,</hi> directed by weak C-H···O hydrogen bonds, N+···O interactions and pi-pi stackings of the aromatic rings [34,35], behaviour that should be apparent from such experiments. </s><s n="s3.3;p34.52">The structures below are labelled with carbon assigned in blue, and hydrogen in red. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0306b-pic.001"/><figure id="BAWE_0306b-pic.002"/><p n="p35.52"><s n="s1.6;p35.52">It is evident from the solution state <hi rend="sup">1</hi>H shifts shown in <hi rend="italic">Table 3</hi>, that non covalent interactions do indeed arise between the two molecules when combined. </s><s n="s2.6;p35.52">Peaks shifted downfield in the mixture to 9.27 ppm and 5.60 ppm, correspond to H1A and H2 axle protons respectively and demonstrate typical C-H···O hydrogen bonding behaviour, as expected from previous studies. </s><s n="s3.6;p35.52">Pi-pi stacking between the molecules is also supported by the upfield shifts of the H1B pyridinium aromatic protons to 8.17 ppm and also of the H5 crown aromatic protons to 6.78 ppm and 6.72 ppm. </s><s n="s4.6;p35.52">Both results are fully supported by the crystal structure data [34] as displayed in <hi rend="italic">Figure 3.1</hi> [15]. </s><s n="s5.6;p35.52">The shift of the crown CH <hi rend="sub">2</hi> protons H6 to 4.39 ppm and 4.02 ppm can not be accounted for by connectivities with the threading axle, and could be due to inter-molecular interactions between neighbouring molecules, although such bonds are not usually present in solution state spectra. </s><s n="s6.6;p35.52">The short timescale of molecular tumbling in the liquid state usually allows us to consider the molecule as if it were isolated, and hence in comparing solution and solid state spectra, inter-molecular bonding of the whole crystal can be deduced as in §3.2 </s></p><table id="BAWE_0306b-tab.003"><head><hi rend="italic">Table 3. Solution-state 1H chemical shifts for molecules</hi> <hi rend="bold">1</hi><hi rend="italic"> and</hi> <hi rend="bold">2</hi><hi rend="italic"> while separate and combined. Site assignments for discrete molecule</hi> <hi rend="bold">2</hi><hi rend="italic"> made using online database</hi> [29]<hi rend="italic"> and previous studies</hi> [34]<hi rend="italic">. Data and experimental information can be found in Appendix A or §2.2</hi></head><row><cell/></row></table><figure id="BAWE_0306b-pic.003"><head><hi rend="italic">Figure 3.1. Ball and stick representation of mixture of</hi> <hi rend="bold">1</hi><hi rend="italic"> and</hi> <hi rend="bold">2</hi> [30,34].<hi rend="italic"> Crown carbons are shaded darker to display threading effect. Weak hydrogen C-H···O bonds indicated by grey dashed lines. H··O (d) distances, Å, and (θ) angles; C(2)-H(1) ··O, 2.39, 154.2; 2.56, 141.3; C(5)-H(2) ··O, 2.54, 164.9; 2.66, 149.9. Aromatic pi-pi interactions shown in red.</hi> </head></figure><p n="p36.52"><s n="s1.2;p36.52">The solid-state proton spectra of the combined molecules displayed in <hi rend="italic">Appendix B</hi> adds little further information regarding the hydrogen bonding as the poor resolution causes much greater uncertainty in assigning chemical sites. </s><s n="s2.2;p36.52">However, the <hi rend="sup">1</hi>H double quantum experiments reveal proton proximities both within and between the structures that agree well with the solution state and crystal structure evidence to support expected interactions. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0306b-fig.013"><head><hi rend="italic">Figure 3.2. 1H DQ MAS of Bis(pyridinium)ethane axle,</hi> <hi rend="bold">1</hi> <hi rend="italic">63mg, 18800 acquisitions. See Table 4 for ppm data. Areas in red show contours of low SQC intensity. Proton-proton distances (Å) from Figure 3.1</hi> [29,31,34]<hi rend="italic"> agree with observed proximities; 4-4 (1.57), 3-3 (1.57),3-4 (2.31), 1A-2B(2.72), 1A-1B (2.30), 2-2 (1.57,2.36). Relative heights of the DQC peaks shown on the vertical axis can be roughly representative of the proximity and abundance of chemical sites.</hi> </head></figure><p n="p37.52"><s n="s1.3;p37.52"><hi rend="italic">Figure 3.2</hi> shows close inter-molecular proximities between protons of the axle as expected from the structure and mixed crystal data [34] but will also contain information about solid state inter-molecular bonding, such as the cross peak that appears between H1B and H4 sites. </s><s n="s2.3;p37.52">This can not be confirmed without crystal structure data for the bis (pyridinium) ethane alone. </s><s n="s3.3;p37.52">One would also expect a diagonal peak between H2-H2 (+NCH <hi rend="sub">2</hi>) protons around 5.2~5.6 ppm single quantum frequency, but this could have changed position due to other interactions and is possibly masked by the H3-H3 diagonal peak. </s></p><p n="p38.52"><s n="s1.1;p38.52">The double quantum data for structure <hi rend="bold">2,</hi> shown in <hi rend="italic">Figure 3.3</hi>, is much less informative than for <hi rend="bold">1</hi> as the hydrogen atoms of this molecule are in very similar environments leading to two broad diagonal peaks that hide many of the cross peaks, which could not be assigned with the greatest of accuracy at such poor resolution. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0306b-fig.014"><head><hi rend="italic">Figure 3.3. 1H DQ MAS of dibenzo-24-crown-8, 2, 50mg, 2400 acquisitions. See Table 4 for ppm data. Proton-proton distances (Å) from Figure 3.1</hi> [31,34].<hi rend="italic"> 6A-6A, etc. (1.57), 6A-6B etc. ( 2.18-2.44), 5-5 (2.24-2.30), 5A-6A (1.57).</hi> </head></figure><p n="p39.52"><s n="s1.3;p39.52">This resolution could be greatly improved by repeating this experiment with a <hi rend="sup">1</hi>H CRAMPS sequence as discussed in §3.2, or alternatively an INADEQUATE homonuclear correlation [36,37] could help to further assign the solid-state chemical shifts of through-bond connected hydrogens H5A-H5B, H6A-H6A etc. to support the proximities suggested by the mixed crystal structure. </s><s n="s2.3;p39.52">Such a correlation, would however, retain the poor proton resolution whereas a heteronuclear <hi rend="sup">13</hi>C-<hi rend="sup">1</hi>H correlation sequence such as MAS-<hi rend="italic">J</hi>-HMQC [38,39] could help to further determine more accurate chemical shifts for certain sites. </s><s n="s3.3;p39.52">Nevertheless, the broad diagonal peaks of <hi rend="italic">Figure 3.3</hi> are consistent with the crown molecular structure and in comparison to the solution state data, crown CH protons (H5) appear to have moved upfield to 6.1 ppm, possible further evidence for pi stacking interactions, although the width of the peak means that this can not be concluded with much certainty. </s></p><p n="p40.52"><s n="s1.1;p40.52">The mixture two dimensional data, <hi rend="italic">Figure 3.4</hi>, displays similar cross peaks and diagonals to <hi rend="italic">Figures 3.2</hi> and <hi rend="italic">3.3</hi> as found on molecules <hi rend="bold">1</hi> and <hi rend="bold">2</hi> alone, but also displays clear downfield chemical shifts of axle +NCH <hi rend="sub">2</hi> (H2) and crown aromatic (H5) protons in the mixture of Δδ=0.4ppm, Δδ=0.6ppm respectively, (see Table 4) again supporting inter-molecular C-H···O interactions. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0306b-fig.015"><head><hi rend="italic">Figure 3.4. 1H DQ MAS of axle-crown mixture, 80mg, 18000 acquisitions</hi> [31,34]. <hi rend="italic">See Table 4 for ppm data.</hi> </head></figure><p n="p41.52"><s n="s1.2;p41.52">To be even more conclusive, the presence of a double quantum peak on <hi rend="italic">Figure 3.4</hi> between H1A-H6C, 2.40Å H1A-H6B, 2.80 Å would support the close H-H proximities as quoted from the crystal structure data, although it is possible that the large H6-H6 proximity is obscuring this peak. </s><s n="s2.2;p41.52">By referring again to <hi rend="italic">Table 4</hi>, the large downfield shift of H5, indicates alterations to their molecular arrangement, most probably between neighbouring similar molecules, but is again ambiguous due to the lack of resolution of <hi rend="italic">Figure 3.3</hi>. </s></p><table id="BAWE_0306b-tab.004"><head rend="italic">Table 4. Solid-state 1H chemical shifts taken from Figures 3.2, 3.2 and 3.4 for separate structures 1,2 and their combined compound respectively. </head><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p42.52"><s n="s1.4;p42.52"><hi rend="sup">13</hi>C experiments were firstly performed in solution-state, with the aid of spectral editing methods to differentiate between atoms with odd or even attached protons in order to assign chemical shift values to each site [10]. </s><s n="s2.4;p42.52">As the <hi rend="sup">1</hi>H solution-state data displayed clear shift arrangements to support C-H···O behaviour, we would expect similar changes to arise for the relevant carbon atoms C2 and C5 in the mixed solution of <hi rend="bold">1</hi> and <hi rend="bold">2</hi>, shown in <hi rend="italic">Table 5</hi>. </s><s n="s3.4;p42.52">However, as peaks C1 and C3 appeared to be missing from some data there was some difficulty in assigning the CH peaks C2, C3, C8, and C2 could have remained at 146.6 ppm or could have been shifted downfield, like C5 by Δδ=0.4ppm. </s><s n="s4.4;p42.52">If the latter is indeed true, this would indicate a large upfield shift of C8 of Δδ=2.1ppm, potentially an indication of aromatic stacking. </s></p><table id="BAWE_0306b-tab.005"><head><hi rend="italic">Table 5. 13C solution-state chemical shifts for molecules</hi> <hi rend="bold">1</hi><hi rend="italic"> and</hi> <hi rend="bold">2</hi><hi rend="italic"> while separate and combined. Site assignments for discrete molecule</hi> <hi rend="bold">2</hi><hi rend="italic"> made using online database</hi> [29]<hi rend="italic"> and previous studies</hi> [34].<hi rend="italic"> Data and experimental information can be found in Appendix C or §2.2</hi></head><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p43.52"><s n="s1.2;p43.52">The solid-state mixture data, displayed in <hi rend="italic">Figure 3.5,</hi> also exhibits a movement of the axle carbons C2 and C5, again implying that a C-H···O molecular arrangement takes place for the thread crown combination in solid form. </s><s n="s2.2;p43.52">It is important to note that the <hi rend="sup">13</hi>C chemical shift will also be susceptible to other interactions between or amongst the molecules. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0306b-fig.016"><head><hi rend="italic">Figure 3.5.</hi> <hi rend="sup italic">13C solid-state data for bis(pyridinium)thread (red) dibenzo-24-crown-8 (blue) and mixture (black). If assignments are correct, C2 peak shifts downfield in mixture by 2.0ppm, and C5 by 2.7ppm. Upfield peak shifts C3; 1.9ppm, C4; 2.1ppm, 1.4 ppm, C9B; 1.3ppm, C10; 1.0ppm, 1.8ppm, 3.1ppm. Data comparison can be found in Appendix D </hi><hi rend="italic">* represent spinning sidebands.</hi> </head></figure></div2><div2><head rend="bold">3. 2. C-H···O and N-H···O interactions in the supramolecular structure of uracil </head><p n="p44.52"><s n="s1.2;p44.52">It is well established in molecular biology that purine and pyrimidine pairs are held together with strong hydrogen bonds to form helical RNA and DNA chains in the solid state <hi rend="italic">(Figure 1.1</hi>). </s><s n="s2.2;p44.52">As the crystalline molecules possess a repeating style structure, it is not surprising to also find inter-molecular hydrogen bonds present in their separate crystal structures. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0306b-pic.004"/><p n="p45.52"><s n="s1.1;p45.52">Early studies of the pyrimidine uracil (C <hi rend="sub">4</hi>H <hi rend="sub">4</hi>N <hi rend="sub">2</hi>O <hi rend="sub">2</hi>) in crystal form, molecule <hi rend="bold">3</hi>, show that both strong and weak hydrogen bonds are formed between molecules incorporating all 4 of the hydrogen atoms (see <hi rend="italic">Figure 3.6</hi>) [3,30,31]. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0306b-pic.005"><head><hi rend="italic">Figure 3.6. Ball and stick representations of the uracil</hi> <hi rend="bold">3</hi><hi rend="italic"> crystal structure to demonstrate hydrogen bonding C-H</hi>···<hi rend="italic">O in grey, N-H</hi>···<hi rend="italic">O in blue and pi-pi stacking arrangements in red. H···O (d) distances, Å, and (θ) angles; N-H(1)···O, 1.99, 171.3 ; N-H(2)···O, 2.03, 171.4; C(3)-H(3)···O, 2.32, 163.0 ; C(4)-H(4)···O, 2.42, 163.0</hi></head></figure><p n="p46.52"><s n="s1.2;p46.52">By evaluating the change in <hi rend="sup">1</hi>H chemical shift between the isolated uracil molecule, represented by solution-state, and the repeating crystalline state, we can quantitatively measure the intermolecular hydrogen bonding observed in its crystal form [6]. </s><s n="s2.2;p46.52">(See <hi rend="italic">Table 6</hi>) </s></p><table id="BAWE_0306b-tab.006"><head><hi rend="italic">Table 6. 1H chemical shift data for uracil 3 in solution and solid-state.</hi> <hi rend="italic">Solution-state values have been rounded to same accuracy as solid-state.</hi> <hi rend="italic">Data can be found in Appendix E.</hi> </head><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p47.52"><s n="s1.5;p47.52">Solution state information was taken directly from a database [29] and was also used to assign the peaks in the solid state spectra, assuming that the peak positions were unaltered. </s><s n="s2.5;p47.52">Once again, the poor resolution of solid-state <hi rend="sup">1</hi>H yielded very approximate chemical shift data. </s><s n="s3.5;p47.52">It would be expected that similar shifts would occur for the stronger bonded N-H1 and N-H2, and weaker similarly for C-H3 and C-H4. </s><s n="s4.5;p47.52">Despite this, there is still evidence of downfield shifting, even if it does not appear to be quantitative of the hydrogen bond strength, or correlated with the H···O distances given by <hi rend="italic">Figure 3.6</hi> [29]. </s><s n="s5.5;p47.52">It is likely that the protons are simultaneously shifted downfield by hydrogen bonding interactions, and upfield due to the aromatic stacking by different degrees, making the over <hi rend="sup">1</hi>H shift unreliable for determining bonding strengths alone. </s></p><p n="p48.52"><s n="s1.4;p48.52">Much more information regarding intermolecular bonding can be found from the double quantum data of proton proximities to confirm the crystal structure evidence. </s><s n="s2.4;p48.52"><hi rend="italic">Figure 3.7</hi> shows the <hi rend="sup">1</hi>H (a) </s><s n="s3.4;p48.52">DQ MAS and (b) CRAMPS spectra to be entirely consistent with <hi rend="italic">Figure 3.6</hi>, particularly as the weakest correlation between H2-H4 is in fact the most distant proximity at 2.81Å. </s><s n="s4.4;p48.52">Unfortunately, the relative heights of the other double quantum peaks differs for the CRAMPS and DQ MAS data, which could be due to various experimental parameters employed during the evolution of the double quantum coherence. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0306b-pic.006"><head><hi rend="italic">Figure 3.7. 1H Double Quantum Coherence data for uracil determined by (a) DQ MAS, 10mg, 288 acquisitions. (b) CRAMPS, 16 acquisitions. From Figure 3.6</hi> [30,31]<hi rend="italic"> proton proximities (Å) H2-H4; 2.81, H3-H4; 2.37, H2-H3; 2.20, H1-H1; 2.53. See Appendix F for peak data.</hi> </head></figure><p n="p49.52"><s n="s1.3;p49.52">Again, <hi rend="sup">13</hi>C peak shifts between solution and solid-state spectra in <hi rend="italic">Figure 3.8</hi> show signs of altered molecular arrangement. </s><s n="s2.3;p49.52">However, as with the <hi rend="sup">1</hi>H chemical shift data, one would suppose that the donor C3 and C4 carbon atoms would display similar shifts, and to be greater than C1 and C2 that are attached to acceptor oxygens. </s><s n="s3.3;p49.52">Again this discrepancy could be due to the combined effect of aromatic stacking and could also explain huge differences in Δδ values as compared in <hi rend="italic">Appendix G</hi>. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0306b-fig.017"><head><hi rend="italic">Figure 3.8. 13C CP spectra for uracil 3 (a) Solution-state taken from database</hi> [29]<hi rend="italic"> SDBS No. 1062, 38.5mg, 0.4 ml DMSO-d6, 100.72MHz (b) Solid-state ~ 80mg, 2960 acquisitions, further experimental information can be found in §2.1 </hi></head></figure></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">4. Discussion</head><p n="p50.52"><s n="s1.4;p50.52">The role of the weak C-H···O bond as a stabilizing interaction in structural chemistry seems evident from this and many studies, and as the recorded number of such interactions increases [5], so does the likelihood that these arrangements do not simply occur by chance. </s><s n="s2.4;p50.52">The distances and angles given in the supramolecular structure of uracil are comparable to the stronger N-H···O hydrogen bonds, present suggesting notable if not equal importance. </s><s n="s3.4;p50.52">Also, the flexibility of the ranges of these geometrical parameters makes the weaker hydrogen bonds even more likely to influence crystal engineering. </s><s n="s4.4;p50.52">Equilibrium crystal structure arrangements are such a precise balance of many molecular interactions that it is extremely unlikely for such an importance influence as the hydrogen bond to cease acting at well defined distances and electronegativities. </s></p><p n="p51.52"><s n="s1.3;p51.52">Some of the NMR data presented in this investigation proved slightly weaker than expected in detecting these hydrogen bonds due to interference from other interactions caused by the sensitivity of the technique. </s><s n="s2.3;p51.52">To add to this, poor resolution of <hi rend="sup">1</hi>H solid-state results made definite conclusions more difficult, highlighting the need for more advanced techniques in proton NMR. <hi rend="sup">13</hi>C data also supported the existence of weak interactions, again somewhat inhibited by other processes, and particularly in S3.2 the lack of predicted peaks suggests possible errors in sample preparation or contamination. </s><s n="s3.3;p51.52">Of course ever present and all important when considering NMR chemical shifts is errors of calibration and reference of spectra, particularly when used as solitary evidence. </s></p><p n="p52.52"><s n="s1.1;p52.52">However, this emphasises another key factor to such an investigation; that the best possible results were obtained when spectroscopic and crystallographic data were combined [40]; and this is evident here as the most conclusive results were obtained from higher resolution proton proximity data when used along side crystal structure information to support weak hydrogen bonding interactions. </s></p></div1></body><back><div1 type="appendix"><head rend="bold">Appendix A</head><p/></div1><div1 type="appendix"><head rend="bold">Appendix B</head><p/></div1><div1 type="appendix"><head rend="bold">Appendix C</head><p/></div1><div1 type="appendix"><head rend="bold">Appendix D</head><p/></div1><div1 type="appendix"><head rend="bold">Appendix E</head><p/></div1><div1 type="appendix"><head rend="bold">Appendix F</head><p/></div1><div1 type="appendix"><head rend="bold">Appendix G</head><p/></div1><div1 type="bibliography"><head rend="bold">References</head><p>[1] Dobson, C. M.; Gerrard, J. A.; Pratt, A. J.; <hi rend="italic">Foundations of Chemical Biology</hi>; Oxford Science Publications, 2004</p><p>[2] Jeffrey, G. A.; <hi rend="italic">An Introduction to Hydrogen Bonding</hi>; Oxford University Press, 1997</p><p>[3] Desiraju, G. R.; Steiner, T.; <hi rend="italic">The Weak Hydrogen Bond - In Structural Chemistry and Biology</hi>; Oxford University Press, 1999</p><p>[3b] Desiraju, G. R.; <hi rend="italic">Acc. Chem. Res.; </hi><hi rend="bold">1991, </hi><hi rend="italic">24,</hi> 290-296</p><p>[4] Desiraju, G. R.; <hi rend="italic">Journal of Molecular Structure; </hi><hi rend="bold">2003</hi>, <hi rend="italic">656</hi>, 5 - 15</p><p>[5] Desiraju, G. R.; <hi rend="italic">Acc. Chem. Res.; </hi><hi rend="bold">2002, </hi><hi rend="italic">35</hi>, 565-573</p><p>[6] Yates, J. R.; Pham, T. N.; Pickard, C. J.; Mauri, F.; Amado, A. M.; Gil, A.M.; Brown, S. P.; <hi rend="italic">J. Am. Chem. Soc.</hi>; <hi rend="bold">2005</hi>, <hi rend="italic">127</hi>, 10216-10220</p><p>[7] Brown, S. P.; <hi rend="italic">Probing Weak CH...O Hydrogen Bonds in Maltose Anomers by a Combined Experimental Solid-State NMR and Computational Approach</hi>; Presentation; Charmonix, 2005</p><p>[8] Brown, S. P.; Peréz-Torralba, M.; Sanz, D.; Claramunt, R. M.; Emsley, L.;<hi rend="italic"> J. Am. Chem. Soc</hi>.; <hi rend="bold">2001</hi>, <hi rend="italic">124</hi>, 1152-1153</p><p>[9] Brown, S. P.; Peréz-Torralba, M.; Sanz, D.; Claramunt, R. M.; Emsley, L.;<hi rend="italic"> Chem. Comm.</hi>; <hi rend="bold">2002</hi>, 1852-1853</p><p>[10] Brown, S. P.; Emsley, L. <hi rend="italic">Solid State NMR, Handbook for Spectroscopy</hi>; Wiley </p><p>[11] Brown, S. P.; <hi rend="italic">Nuclear Magnetic Resonance</hi>; Undergraduate Lecture Course, Department of Physics, University of <name type="university"/>, 2004</p><p>[12] Levitt, M. H.; Spin Dynamics, <hi rend="italic">Basic Principles of NMR Spectroscopy;</hi> J. Wiley and Sons Ltd., Oxford; 2003</p><p>[13] Hore, P. J.; Jones, J. A.; Wimperis, S., <hi rend="italic">NMR: The Toolkit</hi>; Oxford University Press, 2000</p><p>[14] <seg type="URL" n="http://www.mhl.soton.ac.uk/public/publications/"/></p><p>books/SpinDynamics/index.html; Levitt, M. H.; Spin</p><p>[15] Griffin, J.; <hi rend="italic">A Nuclear Magnetic Resonance Investigation of Non - Stoichiometric Vanadium Carbide</hi>; Undergraduate Project Report, Department of Physics, University of <name type="university"/>, 2004</p><p>[16] Brown, S. P.; <hi rend="italic">Applications of High-Resolution Spin I = ½ Solid-State NMR</hi>; Presentation; St. Andrews, 2005</p><p>[17] Jackman, L. M.; Sternhell, S.; <hi rend="italic">Applications of Nuclear Magnetic Resonance Spectroscopy in Organic Chemistry</hi>; Pergamon Press, New York, 1969 <hi rend="bold">2</hi></p><p>[18] Breitmaier, E; Voelter, W.; <hi rend="italic">Carbon-13 NMR Spectroscopy - High Resolution Methods and Applications in Organic Chemistry and Biochemistry</hi>; VHC, 1987, <hi rend="bold">3</hi></p><p>[19] Duer, M. J.; <hi rend="italic">Solid State NMR Spectroscopy - Principles and Applications</hi>; Blackwell Science, 2000</p><p>[20] Ernst. M.; <hi rend="italic">J. Mag. Reson.</hi>; <hi rend="bold">2003</hi>, <hi rend="italic">162</hi>, 1-34</p><p>[21] Khitrin, A. K.; Fujiwara, T.; Akutsu, H.; <hi rend="italic">J. Mag. Reson.</hi>; <hi rend="bold">2003</hi>, <hi rend="italic">162</hi>, 46-53</p><p>[22] Harris, R. K.; <hi rend="italic">Nuclear Magnetic Resonance Spectroscopy - A Physiochemical View</hi>; Pitman Books Ltd. 1983</p><p>[23] Brown, S. P.; <hi rend="italic">Probing the Structure and Dynamics of Hydrogen Bonds and Aromatic Pi-Pi Interactions by Solid-State NMR</hi>; Presentation; Aveiro, 2003</p><p>[24] Schnell, I.; Spiess, H. W.; <hi rend="italic">J. Mag. Reson.</hi>; <hi rend="bold">2001</hi>, <hi rend="italic">151</hi>, 153-227</p><p>[25] Sommer, W.; Gottwald, J.; Demco, D. E.; Spiess, H. W.; <hi rend="italic">J. Mag. Reson</hi>., <hi rend="bold">1995</hi>, <hi rend="italic">113</hi>, 131-134</p><p>[26] Brown, S. P.; Spiess, H. W.; <hi rend="italic">Chem. Rev.</hi>; <hi rend="bold">2001</hi>, <hi rend="italic">101</hi>, 4125</p><p>[27] Brown, S. P.; Lesage, A.; Elena, B.; Emsley, L.; <hi rend="italic">J. Am. Chem. Soc</hi>.; <hi rend="bold">2004</hi>, <hi rend="italic">126</hi>, 13230-13231</p><p>[28] <seg type="URL" n="http://www.sigmaaldrich.com/"/></p><p>[29] <seg type="URL" n="http://www.aist.go.jp/RIODB/SDBS/cgi-bin/cre_index.cgi"/>; <hi rend="italic">Solution State NMR Database, AIST National Institute of Advanced Industrial Science and Technology</hi>; accessed November 2005</p><p>[30] Diamond Version 3, 2004 Crystal Impact Dr. K. Brandenburg &amp; Dr. H. Putz GbR <seg type="URL" n="www.crystalimpact.com"/></p><p>[31] CDS Chemical Database Service. UK National online crystal structure database, Daresbury Laboratory, <seg type="URL" n="http://cds.dl.ac.uk"/>. </p><p>[32] Ash, E. L.; Sudmeier, J. L.; Day, R. M.; Vincent, M.; Torchilin, E. V.; Haddad, K. C.; Bradshaw, E. M.; Sanford, D. G.; Bachovchin W. W.; <hi rend="italic">PNAS</hi>; <hi rend="bold">2000</hi>, <hi rend="italic">97</hi>, 10371-10376</p><p>[32] Wishart, D. S.; Sykes, B. D.; Richards, F. M.; <hi rend="italic">J. Mol. Biol.; </hi><hi rend="bold">1991, </hi><hi rend="italic"> 222</hi>, 311 - 333.</p><p>[34] Loeb, S. J.; Wisner, J. A.; <hi rend="italic">Chem. Commun.</hi>; <hi rend="bold">2000</hi>, 1939-1940</p><p>[35] Loeb, S. J.;Wisner, J. A.; <hi rend="italic">Angew. Chem. Int. Ed</hi>.; <hi rend="bold">1998</hi>, <hi rend="italic">37</hi>, 2838-2840</p><p>[36] Pham, T. N.; Kövér, K. A.; Jin, L.; Uhrín, D.; <hi rend="italic">J. Mag. Reson.</hi>, <hi rend="bold">2005</hi>, <hi rend="italic">176</hi>, 199-206</p><p>[37] Lesage, A.; Bardet, M.; Emsley, L.; <hi rend="italic">J. Am. Chem. Soc.</hi>; <hi rend="bold">1999</hi>, <hi rend="italic">121</hi>, 10987.</p><p>[38] Lesage, A.; Sakellariou, D.; Steuernagel, S.; Emsley, L.; <hi rend="italic">J. Am. Chem. Soc.</hi>; <hi rend="bold">1998</hi>, <hi rend="italic">120</hi>, 13194.</p><p>[39] Lesage, A.; Charmont, P.; Steuernagel, S.; Emsley, L.; <hi rend="italic">J. Am. Chem. Soc.</hi>; <hi rend="bold">2000</hi>, <hi rend="italic">122</hi>, 9739.</p><p>[40] Desiraju, G. R.; Murty, B. N.; <hi rend="italic">Chemical Physics Letters</hi>; <hi rend="bold">1987</hi>, <hi rend="italic">139</hi>, 360-361</p></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
