<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_0306d" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>The beginning of the twentieth century has been termed by many physical scientists as 'the Atomic Age'.</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">two columns</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">2</p><p n="date">2004-02</p><p n="module title">Physics Skills</p><p n="module code">PX271</p><p n="genre family">Narrative recount</p><p n="discipline">Physics</p><p n="disciplinary group">PS</p><p n="grade">M</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">3696</p><p n="number of s-units">145</p><p n="number of p">60</p><p n="number of tables">0</p><p n="number of figures">8</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">7</p><p n="number of lists">0</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">7</p><p n="abstract present">abstract present</p><p n="average words per s-unit">25.5</p><p n="average s-units per p">2.4</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">f</p><p n="year of birth">1984</p><p n="first language">English</p><p n="education">UKA</p><p n="course">Mphys F303</p><p n="student ID">0306</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><docTitle><titlePart rend="bold">The Physics of Particle Accelerators</titlePart></docTitle><titlePart><name type="student name"/></titlePart></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="abstract"><p n="p1.60"><s rend="italic" n="s1.1;p1.60">Since the invention of particle accelerators in the 1930s, scientists have continuously upgraded their design and performance to increase the energy yields achievable. </s></p><p n="p2.60"><s rend="italic" n="s1.1;p2.60">In doing so, we have been able to experiment thoroughly with atoms, and explore the fundamental structure of matter, in the world around us. </s></p><p n="p3.60"><s rend="italic" n="s1.1;p3.60">This field of high-energy physics has been one of the most successful as can be seen by its advanced development, which is still ongoing today. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><div2><head rend="bold"> Introduction</head><p n="p4.60"><s n="s1.5;p4.60">The beginning of the twentieth century has been termed by many physical scientists as 'the Atomic Age'. </s><s n="s2.5;p4.60">It was around this time that physicists began to experiment with materials in order to discover the fundamental structure of matter. </s><s n="s3.5;p4.60">In 1897, J.J. Thompson discovered the negatively charged mass now known as the electron, but it was not for another fourteen years that the nucleus was detected and finally the proton and the neutron in the 1930s. </s><s n="s4.5;p4.60">The reason for such a delay in this field is due to the fact that high energies are needed in experimentation to overcome electrostatic and nuclear forces. </s><s n="s5.5;p4.60">Once we achieve these energies we are able to penetrate into the atom and learn more about its constituents. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold"> Why did we need accelerators? </head><p n="p5.60"><s n="s1.3;p5.60">By 1920 the race was on for scientists to provide a reliable source of high-energy particles to experiment quantitatively on matter, as naturally occurring sources such as radioactive minerals e.g. </s><s n="s2.3;p5.60">Uranium, or cosmic rays, had failed to provide enough energy for this purpose. </s><s n="s3.3;p5.60">Twelve years later the first ever nuclear reaction occurred using artificially accelerated protons, and the particle accelerator was born. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0306d-pic.001"><head rend="bold">Figure 1Cockcroft-Walton Voltage Multiplier</head></figure></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">The first accelerators</head><p n="p6.60"><s n="s1.3;p6.60">The main requirement for any such apparatus to be deemed an accelerator is that it will increase the energy of the charged particles that are inputted into it. </s><s n="s2.3;p6.60">The most simple method of doing this is by accelerating ions of charge <hi rend="italic">q</hi> through a potential difference <hi rend="italic">V</hi>, and in doing this they gain energy from the electric field to the value of the product <hi rend="italic">Vq</hi>. </s><s n="s3.3;p6.60">The particles then emerge from the accelerator with increased kinetic energy ie. with greater velocity, mass or both. </s></p><div2><head rend="bold">2.1 Direct Low Voltage Generators </head><p n="p7.60"><s n="s1.2;p7.60">This key principle used in the early particle accelerator designs was simply a method of increasing the potential difference in that system, which would then be used to accelerate ions from a source nearby. </s><s n="s2.2;p7.60">The most basic form of this potential increase came in the form of transformer coils to 'step up' the voltage, which made use of Faraday's Law of Electromagnetic Inductance. </s></p><p n="p8.60"><s n="s1.3;p8.60">The second most commonly used circuitry invented for amplifying a potential difference was the 'Voltage Multiplier'. </s><s n="s2.3;p8.60">Scientists Cockcroft and Walton made this design famous in 1932 using a fourfold voltage multiplying circuit to accelerate protons to 0.7MeV<ref target="BAWE_0306d-ftnote.001"/>, as shown in <hi rend="italic">Figure 1</hi>. </s><s n="s3.3;p8.60">This created the first nuclear reaction by artificial means and the pair were later awarded the Nobel Prize in 1951 for this breakthrough. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0306d-ftnote.001"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">The electron volt (eV) is a commonly used unit of energy at particle level equivalent to Energy in Joules divided by the charge on an electron, e = 1.6=10-19C </s></p></note><p n="p9.60"><s n="s1.5;p9.60">The multiplier circuit uses a series of <hi rend="italic">N</hi> capacitors that are charged in parallel and then discharged in series using <hi rend="italic">N</hi> rectifiers (or 'diodes') that act as switches to direct the alternating current. </s><s n="s2.5;p9.60">In <hi rend="italic">Figure 1</hi>, <hi rend="italic">N</hi> is shown to equal 4 as in the original layout. </s><s n="s3.5;p9.60">The alternating current and diodes are essential to the amplification, hence it is necessary to explain the voltage increase in terms of 'half cycles' as the current reverses direction. </s><s n="s4.5;p9.60">Each capacitor is gradually charged to <hi rend="italic">Vo</hi> in one half cycle and then shares its charge with the next in the following half cycle, as the switches open and close accordingly to direct the flow of current. </s><s n="s5.5;p9.60">This continues until all capacitors are charged to <hi rend="italic">Vo</hi> and eventually FB will be at +4 <hi rend="italic">Vo</hi> with respect to earth. </s></p><p n="p10.60"><s n="s1.4;p10.60">These terminals are then connected to an evacuated accelerator tube, which is also connected to ground. </s><s n="s2.4;p10.60">This sets up a voltage difference of 4 <hi rend="italic">Vo</hi>, or generally <hi rend="italic">N</hi> x input voltage, between the top of the tube (where the ions are situated) and the bottom, at earth. </s><s n="s3.4;p10.60">The ions then become accelerated down the tube due to this electric field and are usually aimed a target in the experimental room below. </s><s n="s4.4;p10.60">The high-energy particles are then able to split the nuclei of this target and the products of this reaction can be investigated thoroughly. </s></p><p n="p11.60"><s n="s1.2;p11.60">The protons used in this first reaction were of roughly 0.7MeV. At the time the mega electron-volt was highly celebrated but is over a million times smaller than some typical energies achieved today. </s><s n="s2.2;p11.60">At this early period it was only possible for us to experiment with large atoms due to the fact that this energy was so small, it could not overcome nuclear repulsions of smaller atoms, and so we searched for higher energies. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">The Van der Graaff Generator</head><p n="p12.60"><s n="s1.2;p12.60">Also in the 1930s emerged a direct low voltage generator using a completely different idea and giving a greater yield of energy. </s><s n="s2.2;p12.60">The Van der Graaff design uses the principle of transporting charge from a source at earth to a relatively 'high' voltage terminal and set up a potential difference that also will accelerate ions. </s></p><p n="p13.60"><s n="s1.4;p13.60">The charge, from a power pack set at a few tens of kilovolts, is continuously placed onto an insulating belt using 'spray points' which typically consists of a few hundred thin metal wires. </s><s n="s2.4;p13.60">This belt is then run using an electric motor and pulley system, and the charge is removed, using similar spray points, onto the equipotential terminal. </s><s n="s3.4;p13.60">The charge then accumulates on the outside of the terminal creating a field free region inside, but setting up a 'high' potential at the top of the accelerator tube. </s><s n="s4.4;p13.60">This is illustrated in <hi rend="italic">Figure 2</hi>. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0306d-pic.002"><head><hi rend="bold">Figure 2</hi> <hi rend="bold">Van der Graaff Generator</hi></head></figure><p n="p14.60"><s n="s1.1;p14.60">As in the Cockcroft-Walton design, this voltage difference between the top of the tube and ground accelerates the ions to higher energies for use in experiments. </s></p><p n="p15.60"><s n="s1.5;p15.60">The Van der Graaff is capable of energies of roughly 7~8MeV, or 12MeV using a double 'tandem' generator with two columns. </s><s n="s2.5;p15.60">It became a very successful voltage source as the steadiness of the motor gave an equally steady and focussed beam of ions that were ideal for experimentation at the MeV scale. </s><s n="s3.5;p15.60">However the main limitation of the Van der Graaff, and of other low voltage generators is the problem of insulation, as these direct generators rely on one large voltage to raise the energy of given ions. </s><s n="s4.5;p15.60">To add to this, the Van der Graaff is also inhibited by its overall size. </s><s n="s5.5;p15.60">As can be seen in the diagram, the equipment needs to be encased in a large steel vessel, containing low-pressure gas to decrease the risk of fire from any sparks. </s></p><p n="p16.60"><s n="s1.1;p16.60">All these factors must be taken into consideration when designing an accelerator for efficient methods of research, and is one of the main reasons that we moved onto the 'indirect' acceleration approach. </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Indirect/Resonant Accelerators </head><div2><head rend="bold">3.1 The Linear Accelerator </head><p n="p17.60"><s n="s1.2;p17.60">Instead of using a single large potential difference once, the indirect accelerators use a smaller, more accessible alternating voltage a number of times to accelerate the particle in successive stages and get even higher outputs. </s><s n="s2.2;p17.60">The most basic of these indirect designs was the linear accelerator, shown in <hi rend="italic">Figure 3</hi>. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0306d-pic.003"><head rend="bold">Figure 3Basic Design of a Linear Accelerator</head></figure><p n="p18.60"><s n="s1.2;p18.60">In this figure, we assume the particles are protons, which are accelerated through a series of cylindrical electrodes or drift tubes that are alternately connected to a radio frequency supply voltage. </s><s n="s2.2;p18.60">Each time a particle crosses a gap between two electrodes it gains the energy <hi rend="italic">Vq</hi> where <hi rend="italic">V</hi> is the potential difference between these tubes. </s></p><p n="p19.60"><s n="s1.1;p19.60">Non-relativistically we can assume: </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p20.60"><s n="s1.1;p20.60"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0306d-form.001"/><hi rend="bold">(1)</hi> </s></p><p n="p21.60"><s n="s1.1;p21.60">and we can determine the speeds with which the ions will travel. </s></p><p n="p22.60"><s n="s1.5;p22.60">The particles will travel at constant velocity through the electrodes as there is no electric field inside them, but each time they traverse a gap between two electrodes they will receive this same <hi rend="italic">Vq</hi> of energy and their velocity is successively increased. </s><s n="s2.5;p22.60">This works due to the resonance factor involved. </s><s n="s3.5;p22.60">The frequency of the supply voltage is set at an appropriate value to correspond (or resonate) with the time it takes a particle to travel through one electrode. </s><s n="s4.5;p22.60">For example in <hi rend="italic">Figure 1</hi> if we imagine a proton enters the first negative electrode at time t <hi rend="sub">1</hi>, but by a later time t <hi rend="sub">2</hi> when the proton has reached the end of this first tube, the R.F. supply has reversed and now this first electrode is positive and the second negative. </s><s n="s5.5;p22.60">The proton is both repelled from the first and attracted to the second and gains its energy from the electric field set up in between these two electrodes. </s></p><p n="p23.60"><s n="s1.2;p23.60">Also as the supply frequency is fixed, but the velocity of the particles is greater at each electrode, we must, in turn, increase the length of the drift tubes at later times. </s><s n="s2.2;p23.60">This ensures that the transit time through each tube is also fixed and the particle always arrives at the end of the cylinder at the correct instant for the field to reverse and it to be accelerated once more. </s></p><p n="p24.60"><s n="s1.4;p24.60">Linear accelerators were not widely used until after World War II, as before this we did not have large enough frequency generators ~ 200MHz to allow this resonance principle to be effective. </s><s n="s2.4;p24.60">After this we began to get compact, focused beams of particles with protons reaching up to 50MeV and electrons up to 20GeV due to their smaller mass. </s><s n="s3.4;p24.60">However this was only achievable for very long accelerators, for example at Stanford National Laboratory the equipment is over 3km in length. </s><s n="s4.4;p24.60">It was this limitation that caused physicists to bend these beams into circular trajectories that used the same principle but took up much less space! </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">The Cyclotron </head><p n="p25.60"><s n="s1.2;p25.60">The cyclotron uses the resonance principle as in the linear accelerator or 'linac' as they are sometimes known, but also makes use of circular orbits to reduce the need for so much space, and hundreds more tonnes of steel. </s><s n="s2.2;p25.60">As with all accelerators, the ions are kept enclosed in evacuated chambers to ensure no reactions occur with surrounding particles. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0306d-pic.004"><head rend="bold">Figure 4The Cyclotron </head></figure><p n="p26.60"><s n="s1.3;p26.60">So how do we deviate the particles into a circle? </s><s n="s2.3;p26.60">The particles we typically accelerate must all be charged in order to be affected by electric fields, so we simply extend this idea to that of magnetic effects as well. </s><s n="s3.3;p26.60">We know from the Lorentz <hi rend="italic">q</hi>(<hi rend="underlined italic">v</hi> x <hi rend="underlined italic">B</hi>) force, that a magnetic field placed perpendicularly to a moving charge will create a centripetal force on that particle perpendicular both to the particle's motion and the direction of the field. </s></p><p n="p27.60"><s n="s1.1;p27.60">If we equate this Lorentz force above to the centripetal force we can see that: </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p28.60"><s n="s1.1;p28.60"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0306d-form.002"/><hi rend="bold">(2)</hi> </s></p><p n="p29.60"><s n="s1.1;p29.60">We assume charge <hi rend="italic">q</hi>, non-relativistic mass <hi rend="italic">m</hi>, and the magnetic field strength <hi rend="italic">B</hi> are constant, and therefore <hi rend="italic">r</hi> the radius of the particle's orbit will increase with its velocity as shown in <hi rend="italic">Figure 4</hi>. </s></p><p n="p30.60"><s n="s1.2;p30.60">The magnetic field <hi rend="italic">B</hi> is illustrated, in the above figure, as pointing upwards with respect to the path of ions in a horizontal plane. </s><s n="s2.2;p30.60">Therefore we place large north and south poles above and below the 'dees' in such a way as to create this centripetal force on the ions and propel them into circular motion. </s></p><p n="p31.60"><s n="s1.3;p31.60">As in the linac, the electrodes are connected to an alternating voltage supply. </s><s n="s2.3;p31.60">In the cyclotron the electrodes are these hollow shaped dees and the ions are deviated outwards from a central source. </s><s n="s3.3;p31.60">In a very similar way the ions are successively given 'kicks' of <hi rend="italic">Vq</hi> energy as they traverse the two electrodes. </s></p><p n="p32.60"><s n="s1.2;p32.60">As the cyclotron uses this same resonance principle we need to determine the fixed 'cyclotron frequency' based on the physical features of the design. </s><s n="s2.2;p32.60">The frequency must reverse as the particle crosses a 'dee' hence it must change twice as quickly as it takes a particle to complete a whole circle of radius <hi rend="italic">r</hi>. </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p33.60"><s n="s1.1;p33.60"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0306d-form.003"/><hi rend="bold">(3)</hi> </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p34.60"><s n="s1.1;p34.60"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0306d-form.004"/><hi rend="bold"> (4)</hi> </s></p><p n="p35.60"><s n="s1.2;p35.60">At this constant frequency, the particles can make many revolutions in this circular manner without needing the kilometres of space as in a linac, and can also get more energies out for a relatively low input. </s><s n="s2.2;p35.60">A typical value for cyclotron output energy using a proton source is similar to that of a linac ~ 25MeV depending on dimensions. </s></p><p n="p36.60"><s n="s1.1;p36.60">This implies that the particles will reach much higher speeds and eventually will approach the speed of light '<hi rend="italic">c</hi>'. </s></p><p n="p37.60"><s n="s1.2;p37.60">In doing this, a very prominent feature from Einstein's Theory of General Relatively needs to be considered. </s><s n="s2.2;p37.60">One of these laws states that as a particle's velocity <hi rend="italic">v</hi> approaches '<hi rend="italic">c</hi>' (roughly 3 x 10 <hi rend="sup">8</hi> ms <hi rend="sup">-1</hi>) then its 'rest' mass <hi rend="italic">mo</hi> shall increase by the Lorentz factor γ as expressed in Equation 5. </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p38.60"><s n="s1.1;p38.60"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0306d-form.005"/><hi rend="bold"> (5)</hi> </s></p><p n="p39.60"><s n="s1.4;p39.60">Therefore comparing this with Equation 4 we see that if the mass of the particle increases the frequency can no longer be kept constant as the two are inversely proportional. </s><s n="s2.4;p39.60">This is where the main limitations of the resonance accelerators lie; as we approach relativistic speeds we can no longer rely on the resonance principle between fixed frequency voltage supply and time for particles to traverse electrodes. </s><s n="s3.4;p39.60">This is displayed more prominently in Equation 3 that clearly shows the transit time of the particle is directly related to its mass, so as this mass becomes greater with relativity, the particle will take a longer time to reach the accelerating gap and arrive out of resonance with the fixed frequency voltage. </s><s n="s4.4;p39.60">It was because of this relativistic effect that we needed accelerator frequencies to become synchronised with the motion of the particles. </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="bold">The Principle of Phase Stability</hi> <hi rend="bold"> and Synchronous Accelerators </hi></head><p n="p40.60"><s n="s1.3;p40.60">The next improvement to be made to accelerator design was hence to escape the resonance idea and to account for these higher energy and speed situations where relativity had an effect. </s><s n="s2.3;p40.60">This development, that would yield a more concentrated particle beam, came with the Principle of Phase Stability. </s><s n="s3.3;p40.60">This idea depended upon adjusting the frequency of the voltage supply to ensure that each time a particle was accelerated it would arrive at the e.m. wave at the right time, with the right energy, and the right 'synchronous' phase. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0306d-fig.001"><head><hi rend="bold">Figure 5Diagrammatic Representation of</hi> <hi rend="bold">Phase Stability and points where</hi> <hi rend="bold">particles should meet the E.M. Wave</hi></head></figure><p n="p41.60"><s n="s1.6;p41.60"><hi rend="italic">Figure 5</hi> illustrates this idea of phase stable orbits. </s><s n="s2.6;p41.60">Ideally we wish for the frequency to change in such a way that the particle always arrives at the accelerating gap at the right time so that it meets the voltage wave in the first (positive and increasing) quarter of its sine cycle. </s><s n="s3.6;p41.60">The path <hi rend="italic">S</hi> shows the ideal synchronous phase of a particle, which always arrives at this point on the wave, gains the same voltage and stays in phase. </s><s n="s4.6;p41.60">However, if the particle arrives a little early at point <hi rend="italic">A,</hi> it receives less of a voltage 'kick' from the wave. </s><s n="s5.6;p41.60">It then travels slower, and next time arrives at <hi rend="italic">A'</hi>, where it gains a higher kick, will travel faster and arrive at <hi rend="italic">A</hi> again... etc, and vice versa if a particle arrives a little later than this synchronous phase. </s><s n="s6.6;p41.60">We can also see that if a particle arrives on a decelerating voltage, for example at <hi rend="italic">R,</hi> it will continually receive lower impulses, and simply become lost . </s></p><p n="p42.60"><s n="s1.3;p42.60">This method of automatic regulation ensures that the particles, if they arrive in roughly the right voltage region, will oscillate around this synchronous phase as a phase stable group of particles. </s><s n="s2.3;p42.60">Now, only the correctly stable and energetic particles will emerge in the beam in phase, as opposed to earlier designs that often had particles arriving randomly with different energies. </s><s n="s3.3;p42.60">This then allows us to obtain even higher energies of up to hundreds and thousands of MeV. </s></p><div2><head rend="bold"> 4.1 The Synchrocyclotron</head><p n="p43.60"><s n="s1.3;p43.60">The most simple phase stable accelerator is a slight adaptation of the fixed frequency cyclotron. </s><s n="s2.3;p43.60">Since the circular design arose, all other variations have kept this for efficiency and altered various other features. </s><s n="s3.3;p43.60">The synchrocyclotron uses a variable capacitor to decrease the frequency of the supply voltage at an appropriate rate to account for the relativistic mass increases as discussed before using Equations 4 and 5. </s></p><p n="p44.60"><s n="s1.3;p44.60">Another design evolution is to use just one semicircular 'dee' (<hi rend="italic">Figure 6</hi>) and have the particles accelerated across the other half of the evacuated tube. </s><s n="s2.3;p44.60">This cuts down the costs and size of steel and magnets; yet, due to phase stability, still remains more efficient than the fixed frequency cyclotron. </s><s n="s3.3;p44.60">For example, the famous synchrocyclotron at Berkeley, USA can achieve energies of 720MeV. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0306d-pic.005"><head rend="bold">Figure 6A Synchrocyclotron Plan </head></figure></div2><div2><head rend="bold">4.2 The Synchrotrons</head><p n="p45.60"><s n="s1.3;p45.60">The (proton and electron) synchrotrons also make adaptations to the simple cyclic design to increase the output immensely. </s><s n="s2.3;p45.60">The first, most obvious feature is the new torus shape A (See <hi rend="italic">Figure 7</hi>). </s><s n="s3.3;p45.60">This is made possible by increasing the strength of the magnetic field <hi rend="italic">B</hi> and hence keeping the radius of the particle beam constant. </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p46.60"><s n="s1.1;p46.60"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0306d-form.006"/><hi rend="bold">(2)</hi> </s></p><p n="p47.60"><s n="s1.3;p47.60">As the ions are all pre-accelerated using linacs they are already relativistic once they enter the synchrotron. </s><s n="s2.3;p47.60">Relativistically the velocity of the particle will not vary too much, but overall the momentum <hi rend="italic">mv</hi> of the particle will increase as it gains more energy on increasing circuits of the accelerator. </s><s n="s3.3;p47.60">Therefore by increasing <hi rend="italic">B</hi> at the correct rate, it can be proven, via Equation 2, that this radius will remain constant. </s></p><p n="p48.60"><s n="s1.3;p48.60">The main advantage of this torus is that it cuts down the need for all the metal for the dee cavities previously needed with increasing radii, and more importantly the huge electromagnets, as were required previously, can be discarded. </s><s n="s2.3;p48.60">Instead, we place much smaller electromagnets around the orbit (see also <hi rend="italic">Figure 8a</hi>). </s><s n="s3.3;p48.60">The size of these magnets means that power consumption is considerably reduced, and hence the cost of these giant machines, which is always welcomed! </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0306d-pic.006"><head rend="bold">Figure 7A proton Synchrotron (UK Design)</head></figure><p n="p49.60"><s n="s1.2;p49.60">To add to this, we gain much more space to extract the particles, and can now have multiple experimental areas <hi rend="italic">H</hi> that surround the accelerator. </s><s n="s2.2;p49.60">Hence we can experiment more with just one beam reducing energy losses and costs even further. </s></p><p n="p50.60"><s n="s1.2;p50.60">The second principle of the synchrotron is, of course, phase stability. </s><s n="s2.2;p50.60">If we look back to Equation 4: </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p51.60"><s n="s1.1;p51.60"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0306d-form.007"/><hi rend="bold"> (4)</hi> </s></p><p n="p52.60"><s n="s1.1;p52.60">Both <hi rend="italic">B</hi> and <hi rend="italic">m</hi> will be increasing, but at different rates, so we need to increase the synchrotron frequency of the voltage supply in this case to keep the phase constant and synchronise the supply voltage with the particle once more. </s></p><p n="p53.60"><s n="s1.2;p53.60">Now that we can experiment with a single ring beam of protons arriving at the same time and in phase we are reaching energies of around 10GeV. This is roughly 10,000 times more than the MeV produced by the first voltage generators! </s><s n="s2.2;p53.60">The final alteration that aided energy yield and also expenses, was that of beam focusing. </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="bold"> Alternating Gradient</hi> <hi rend="bold"> Accelerators</hi></head><p n="p54.60"><s n="s1.2;p54.60">By the 1950s it was estimated that to increase the energy yield of our synchrotrons tenfold we would need over 100 times more steel, roughly 200,000 tonnes, to focus the beam using conventional electromagnets and cavities. </s><s n="s2.2;p54.60">Instead, we developed the idea of simply alternating the orientation of these 'c' shaped magnets that surround the synchrotron torus (<hi rend="italic">Figure 8a</hi>) </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0306d-pic.007"><head><hi rend="bold">Figure 8Representation of synchrotron</hi> <hi rend="bold"> 'c' shaped magnetsFocusing and defocusing alignments as using in alternating gradient devices</hi></head></figure><p n="p55.60"><s n="s1.2;p55.60">By alternating the gradient of the magnets into successive focusing and defocusing sections we act on the particle trajectory, as lenses would to light. </s><s n="s2.2;p55.60">Before this method, we were only extracting a fraction of our weak phase stable beams as the ion paths deviated horizontally and vertically due to asymmetries in the magnetic field and particle alignments (<hi rend="italic">Figure 9</hi>) </s></p><p n="p56.60"><s n="s1.1;p56.60">This simple reversal of the orientation of the magnets meant we only needed twice as much steel and were now reaching energies between 75GeV and 1TeV (based on size and power input). </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0306d-fig.002"><head rend="bold">Figure 9Weak focusing of a circular ion path </head></figure></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold"> Development of the Accelerator and their discoveries</head><p n="p57.60"><s n="s1.4;p57.60">Since the voltage multipliers in the 1930s there has not been a single instance in which, when a scientist has attempted to gain higher energy particles, he has not succeeded. </s><s n="s2.4;p57.60">This is one of the main reasons that the fascination with these 'atom smashers' has persisted. </s><s n="s3.4;p57.60">The resonance accelerators overcame the problems of insulation as first encountered by direct voltage generators, and the principle of phase stability was later able to account for relativistic effects. </s><s n="s4.4;p57.60">Finally the A.G. synchrotrons abolished all physical limits and now we are technically unstoppable! </s></p><p n="p58.60"><s n="s1.4;p58.60">So what was it all for? </s><s n="s2.4;p58.60">Once the field of particle accelerator physics had begun, we began to explore the nucleus and its constituents thoroughly through experimentation. </s><s n="s3.4;p58.60">We soon found that the smaller particles we had discovered, contained stronger nuclear binding forces and would require even more energies to disintegrate them further. </s><s n="s4.4;p58.60">This thirst for higher energies and to learn more about these particles has caused us to constantly modify our accelerators and develop new principles to achieve this. </s></p><p n="p59.60"><s n="s1.4;p59.60">Before we had the use of these machines, we only knew of the proton, neutron and electron, which were thought to be fundamental at the beginning of the century. </s><s n="s2.4;p59.60">Since then we have discovered all the many particles that make up the well-known and often 'accepted' Standard Model for matter. </s><s n="s3.4;p59.60">Knowledge of these particles, and often more importantly their interactions, allows us to understand many physical phenomena and everyday occurrences. </s><s n="s4.4;p59.60">Current projects include the search for the Higg's Particle that will finally complete and prove the Standard Model, as being undertaken at CERN, Geneva. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="bold"> Accelerator Complexes and</hi> <hi rend="bold"> the future </hi></head><p n="p60.60"><s n="s1.4;p60.60">The only obstacle that we now face, theoretically, is that of funding. </s><s n="s2.4;p60.60">The sheer size and cost of steel, magnets, and power consumption, although greatly reduced by the Alternating Gradient principle, has now become far too much for one country and it's government to fund alone. </s><s n="s3.4;p60.60">This is why the CERN project in Geneva, which is jointly owned by 13 European countries, is so successful and versatile. </s><s n="s4.4;p60.60">CERN is home to all types of accelerator (<hi rend="italic">Figure 10</hi>) and is currently in process of replacing its Large Electron Position Collider (LEP) with a Large Hadron Collider (LHC) that should be capable of producing protons with over 50 TeV. With all these energies at our fingertips who knows how many more particles there may be out there for us to discover? </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0306d-pic.008"><head rend="bold">Figure 10The CERN Complex</head></figure></div1></body><back><div1 type="bibliography"><head rend="bold">References</head><p>[1] J. Yarwood, "Electricity, Magnetism and Atomic Physics" <hi rend="bold">2</hi> University Tutorial Press, 1963, pages 414-441</p><p>[2] T. A. Littlefield and N. Thornley, "Atomic and Nuclear Physics", D. Van Nostrand Company Ltd., 1968, pages 251-270</p><p>[3] R Gouiran and W. F. G. Crozier, "Particles and Accelerators", World University Library, 1967, pages 182-234</p><p>[4] M.S. Livingston and J. P Blewitt, "Particle Accelerators", McGraw-Hill Book Company Ltd., 1962 pages 1-645</p><p>[5] D. H. Perkins, "Introduction to High Energy Physics" <hi rend="bold">4</hi> Cambridge University Press, 2000, pages 1-12, 338-348</p><p>CERN Website : <seg type="URL" n="http://public.web.cern.ch/public/index.html"/></p><p>Early Particle Accelerators : <seg type="URL" n="http://www.aip.org/history/lawrence/epa.htm"/></p><p><seg type="URL" n="http://www.aip.org/history/lawrence/"/></p><p>BBC i Particle Accelerators: <hi rend="underlined">http://</hi><seg type="URL" n="www.bbc.co.uk/dna/h2g2/alabaster/A305407"/></p><p>Teachers notes on Particle </p><p>Accelerators: <seg type="URL" n="http://teachers.web.cern.ch/teachers/archiv/HST2001/"/> accelerators/teachers%20notes/intro.htm</p></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
