<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_0306c" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>A crystalline solid is a closely packed lattice of ions with uniform and symmetrical arrangement</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note/></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">2</p><p n="date">2004-01</p><p n="module title">Physics Skills</p><p n="module code">PX271</p><p n="genre family">Methodology recount</p><p n="discipline">Physics</p><p n="disciplinary group">PS</p><p n="grade">M</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">5729</p><p n="number of s-units">211</p><p n="number of p">63</p><p n="number of tables">5</p><p n="number of figures">12</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">9</p><p n="number of lists">0</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">7</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">27.2</p><p n="average s-units per p">3.3</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">f</p><p n="year of birth">1984</p><p n="first language">English</p><p n="education">UKA</p><p n="course">Mphys F303</p><p n="student ID">0306</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front/><body><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Introduction</head><p n="p1.63"><s n="s1.7;p1.63">A crystalline solid is a closely packed lattice of ions with uniform and symmetrical arrangement. </s><s n="s2.7;p1.63">In the case of cubic crystals this symmetry is 3 dimensional and we are able to characterise any compound by a lattice parameter 'a' that will be the same for any sample of that compound. </s><s n="s3.7;p1.63">The positioning of ions within the crystal will vary for each compound due to the size and bonding nature between atoms. </s><s n="s4.7;p1.63">A very common crystal structure is that of Sodium Chloride, commonly known as table salt, shown in <hi rend="italic">Figure 1</hi>, where we can clearly see the uniform arrangement of Na+ and Cl- ions. </s><s n="s5.7;p1.63">This figure represents a 'unit cell' of NaCl, which, by a simple repeating pattern would describe the complete composition of that substance. </s><s n="s6.7;p1.63">This unit cell can be expressed for any cubic crystal, and a value that closely follows this is the lattice parameter , 'a' which is simply the lengths of the sides of the unit cell. </s><s n="s7.7;p1.63">Unlike the figure, the ions would be touching and therefore 'a' will depend only on the size of radius of ions within the cell and hence any sample of NaCl will have this same 'a' value. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0306c-pic.001"><head><hi rend="bold">Figure 1 - An example of a cubic structure and its unit cell,</hi> <hi rend="bold">in this case Sodium Chloride of type face-centred cubic.</hi> </head></figure><p n="p2.63"><s n="s1.3;p2.63">Also shown in the figure is a further characteristic of crystals 'd' which is the distance between adjacent layers or 'planes' of ions. </s><s n="s2.3;p2.63">This is known as the plane separation, and to be fully understood we must firstly refer to the 'Miller Indices' (h k l) used to describe cubic crystals. </s><s n="s3.3;p2.63">In reference to the unit cell of length 'a': </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0306c-fig.001"><head rend="bold">Figure 2 - Demonstration of the miller indices as intercepts of 3 dimensional axes and examples of how this relates to lattice plane spacing dhkl</head></figure><p n="p3.63"><s n="s1.3;p3.63">The Miller Indices are used to represent a crystal type by the order atoms are arranged to create parallel planes. </s><s n="s2.3;p3.63">In reference to the unit cell as a 3 dimensional image in the x, y and z co-ordinates, the Miller Indices refer to h, k and l that represent the 1/x, 1/y and 1/z positions on the axes of this unit cell respectively. </s><s n="s3.3;p3.63">The d <hi rend="sub">hkl</hi> value can be related to the lattice parameter 'a' using </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p4.63"><s n="s1.1;p4.63"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0306c-form.001"/><hi rend="bold">(1)</hi> </s></p><p n="p5.63"><s n="s1.8;p5.63">Hence, and also shown in <hi rend="italic">Figure 2</hi> we can see that d <hi rend="sub">100</hi> = a. </s><s n="s2.8;p5.63">In the case of cubic structures the three most common types of lattice are the simple (or primitive) cubic of symbol (P), the face centred cubic (F) and the body centred cubic (I). </s><s n="s3.8;p5.63">These are shown in <hi rend="italic">Figure 3</hi> and it should be clear why they are named so, given the position of the atoms in the unit cell. </s><s n="s4.8;p5.63">It is then important to show that only certain (hkl) values are allowed for each type of cubic structure, which plays a large role when determining the crystal type (e.g. </s><s n="s5.8;p5.63">P, F or I) based on the d values detected. </s><s n="s6.8;p5.63">For the simple cell all (hkl) are allowed, for face centred only combinations of all odd or all even (hkl) are possible, e.g. </s><s n="s7.8;p5.63">(111), (200), (311), and for body centred only combinations where the sum h+k+l is even are allowed e.g. </s><s n="s8.8;p5.63">(110), (200), (211). </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0306c-fig.002"><head rend="bold">Figure 3 - Schematic of the three most common types of cubic structure</head></figure><p n="p6.63"><s n="s1.5;p6.63">These certain allowed values mean that for each of the three types of crystal the 'd' values will produce a distinct pattern, for example for a body-centred cubic they are evenly spaced. </s><s n="s2.5;p6.63">From this pattern and furthermore by indexing these values we can determine the type of cubic structure of any given crystal once we know these plane spacing values. </s><s n="s3.5;p6.63">By equation (1) we can calculate the lattice parameter 'a' and we can also later use these pieces of information and certain software to identify the chemical compounds of the substance we wish to study. </s><s n="s4.5;p6.63">These are the three main aims of this experiment, which are all derived from obtaining lattice separation values 'd' for certain crystals. </s><s n="s5.5;p6.63">The method with which we obtain these results is known as the process of X-Ray diffraction. </s></p><p n="p7.63"><s n="s1.5;p7.63">X-Rays are defined as high frequency electromagnetic radiation produced when high-speed electrons strike a solid target. </s><s n="s2.5;p7.63">In this experiment we use the fundamental property of x-rays in that they are very high-energy beams and so they will penetrate all materials to reveal information about the inner structure of most substances. </s><s n="s3.5;p7.63">If we irradiate a crystal with such a beam, it will interact with the atoms in the solid and by simple diffraction laws will produce interference lines when detected on exit of the material. </s><s n="s4.5;p7.63">We then combine our knowledge of interference patterns and the atomic arrangement within crystalline solids in order to determine various dimensions of the solid, and ultimately to identify them. </s><s n="s5.5;p7.63">This is known as the X-ray diffraction method, which is used in conjunction with Bragg's Law to examine these crystals. </s></p><p n="p8.63"><s n="s1.1;p8.63">Bragg's Law is given by: </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p9.63"><s n="s1.1;p9.63"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0306c-form.002"/><hi rend="bold">(2)</hi> </s></p><p n="p10.63"><s n="s1.1;p10.63">where n is any non-zero integer </s></p><p n="p11.63"><s n="s1.1;p11.63">λ is the wavelength of the incident radiation (m) </s></p><p n="p12.63"><s n="s1.1;p12.63">d is the distance between adjacent lattice planes (m) </s></p><p n="p13.63"><s n="s1.1;p13.63">and θ is the angle of incidence the beam makes with the crystal planes (rad) </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0306c-fig.003"><head><hi rend="bold">Figure 4 - 2 dimensional demonstration of how Bragg's Law is derived</hi> <hi rend="bold">as x-ray beams are incident on parallel planes of a cubic lattice</hi></head></figure><p n="p14.63"><s n="s1.4;p14.63"><hi rend="italic">Figure 4</hi> demonstrates the origin of the Bragg Law in relation to interference. </s><s n="s2.4;p14.63">We know that for constructive interference, the pattern we wish to observe, will occur when the path difference between any two beams is in phase by a complete wavelength λ (i.e. nλ). </s><s n="s3.4;p14.63">We then relate this to the path difference from <hi rend="italic">Beam A</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Beam B</hi> as shown below to be <hi rend="italic">2x = 2d sinθ</hi>, and therefore diffraction lines will occur at these θ angles. </s><s n="s4.4;p14.63">Combining equations (1) and (2) we can also show: </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p15.63"><s n="s1.1;p15.63"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0306c-form.003"/><hi rend="bold">(3)</hi> </s></p><p n="p16.63"><s n="s1.3;p16.63">This experiment used photographic film to detect x-ray diffraction patterns produced when x-rays of a known wavelength were incident on different crystals. </s><s n="s2.3;p16.63">The angles of diffraction were measured and indexed suitably according to the miller indices allowed for each cubic type. </s><s n="s3.3;p16.63">For convenience (h <hi rend="sup">2</hi> + k <hi rend="sup">2</hi> + l <hi rend="sup">2</hi>) was set as N. Consequently, using these last two equations it was possible to determine the type of cubic structure, 'd' and 'a' values for certain crystalline solids, and, based on the three strongest 'd' lines, to identify various chemical compounds. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Experimental Details </head><p n="p17.63"><s n="s1.1;p17.63">The fundamental pieces of equipment used in this experiment needed to include a source of </s></p><p n="p18.63"><s n="s1.2;p18.63">high energy x-rays, a method of detecting and measuring diffraction patterns and various crystal samples to investigate. </s><s n="s2.2;p18.63">Therefore, we used a high power X-Ray generator and a Debye-Scherrer camera and photographic film that to the powder diffraction method. </s></p><div2><head rend="bold">1 X-Ray Generator</head><p n="p19.63"><s n="s1.5;p19.63">X-Rays are produced when high-speed electrons collide with a metal target, and so for this to occur we need an electron source, high accelerating voltage and a metal target. </s><s n="s2.5;p19.63">We also require some cooling method (often water-cooling) to prevent the target melting due to all the heat produced as a result of the kinetic energy in the target. </s><s n="s3.5;p19.63">In this investigation we used a Phillips Generator that used excitations in a copper x-ray tube to produce the beam. </s><s n="s4.5;p19.63">Here, a high voltage transformer is connected to a filament, which will emit electrons when heated by the current and these will be attracted to a target by the high voltage across the filament tube. </s><s n="s5.5;p19.63">This x-ray set was operated at a maximum voltage of 40kV and current of 17mA. The reason for such a high voltage can be explained by looking at the x-ray spectra of copper as in <hi rend="italic">Figure 5a</hi>. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0306c-fig.004"><head rend="bold">Figure 5a - X-ray spectra of copper to show how x-rays are emitted at higher voltages</head></figure><figure id="BAWE_0306c-fig.005"><head rend="bold"> Figure 5b - describing x-ray Figure 5b - describing x-ray emissions as transitions of electrons between different electron shells</head></figure><p n="p20.63"><s n="s1.8;p20.63">This Figure shows that once we exceed voltages of roughly 20kV we begin to see sharp maxima at certain wavelengths superimposed onto the original continuous spectrum of the metal used. </s><s n="s2.8;p20.63">These lines are the x-ray emissions that will only occur at high voltages and we will generally see what are known as Kα and Kβ lines that correspond to certain emissions from different electron shells. </s><s n="s3.8;p20.63"><hi rend="italic">Figure 5b</hi> shows how this is related to the copper atom and that the observed K emissions are those that fall into the K shell. </s><s n="s4.8;p20.63">For this experiment we only wished to examine the Kα lines as too many lines would prove confusing to distinguish. </s><s n="s5.8;p20.63">In order to do this we selected a nickel filter on the copper x-ray set that would absorb the Kβ emissions. </s><s n="s6.8;p20.63"><hi rend="italic">Figure 6</hi> shows the x-ray emission lines with and without a nickel filter. </s><s n="s7.8;p20.63">This occurs due to the properties of the mass absorption coefficient of nickel μ that is very large at wavelengths lower than K α, including K β, and hence the K β is dramatically attenuated. </s><s n="s8.8;p20.63">However, at longer wavelengths including K α, μ has dropped rapidly so the K α line will be absorbed a lot less and will be detected more prominently. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0306c-fig.006"><head rend="bold">Figure 6a - closer examination of Kα and Kβ emissions from copper spectrum</head></figure><figure id="BAWE_0306c-fig.007"><head rend="bold">Figure 6b - attenuating effect of a nickel filter on the Kβ emission due to properties of mass absorption coefficient of nickel, μ</head></figure><p n="p21.63"><s n="s1.2;p21.63">If we look more closely at this Kα line, we see it actually resolves into two further lines Kα1 and Kα2 due to various sub-states within the atom. </s><s n="s2.2;p21.63">At low diffraction angles the two Kα lines are often very close together and we see only one unresolved line where the wavelength of this Kα is given by: </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p22.63"><s n="s1.1;p22.63"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0306c-form.004"/><hi rend="bold">(4)</hi> </s></p><p n="p23.63"><s n="s1.2;p23.63">However, if we move to higher diffraction angles, the two lines become resolvable and we observe high angle 'doublets'. </s><s n="s2.2;p23.63">For this example we often obtain more reliable results, as it is not necessary to take an average wavelength. </s></p><div3><head rend="bold">1. 1. Safety Precautions for the X-Ray Generator</head><p n="p24.63"><s n="s1.1;p24.63">The x-ray generator is an extremely powerful piece of equipment and could easily cause death </s></p><p n="p25.63"><s n="s1.6;p25.63">or injury if misused. </s><s n="s2.6;p25.63">Careful attention should be paid to the safe working voltages and currents that should be altered slowly as not to overloads the generator. </s><s n="s3.6;p25.63">All equipment had its own interlocking trip system so that if at any time it was possible for the x-rays to leak into the surroundings the machine would shut down, but still it was necessary to check all locks were closed and equipment in place before the machine was put into operation. </s><s n="s4.6;p25.63">As well as this were linings of lead and stops to prevent much radiation leaking out this way. </s><s n="s5.6;p25.63">Despite the shut off, under no circumstances would it be a good idea to open the doors to the x-ray compartment whilst the x-rays were on, as indicated by the red warning light. </s><s n="s6.6;p25.63">If at any time we were uncertain of radiation leakage, there was a Geiger counter present in the room to check for any harmful doses escaping the equipment. </s></p></div3></div2><div2><head rend="bold">2. 2 Powder Diffraction and the Debye-Scherrer Camera</head><p n="p26.63"><s n="s1.7;p26.63">Of the different X-Ray diffraction methods available, this experiment made use of the powder method of crystallography and hence used the 'Debye-Scherrer camera' shown in <hi rend="italic">Figure 7a</hi>. </s><s n="s2.7;p26.63">X-Rays are allowed to enter the camera through one hole and are then passed through a collimator to become incident on the fine crystal powder sample contained in a very fine glass capillary tube which does not diffract the beam. </s><s n="s3.7;p26.63">The rays diffracted by the beam produce cone shaped beams that intersect the photographic film that lines the circumference of the camera to produce these diffraction lines. </s><s n="s4.7;p26.63">We relate this to our Bragg formula as the angular width of each cone is taken to be 4θ by geometry. </s><s n="s5.7;p26.63">From this, we can determine the θ values of each line, taking the origin as the exit point O of the straight-through beam from the camera. </s><s n="s6.7;p26.63">The 4θ and hence θ values were the only raw data taken from all the samples used in the investigation. </s><s n="s7.7;p26.63">From this we determined our lattice parameter 'a' and plane spacing 'd' values to meet the objectives of the experiment. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0306c-pic.002"><head rend="bold"> Figure 7a - The debye scherrer camera </head></figure><figure id="BAWE_0306c-fig.008"><head rend="bold"> Figure 7b - demonstration of how x-rays incident on the sample produce cones of diffraction and hence lines on photographic film at an angle of 4θ apart </head></figure></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Experimental Method </head><p n="p27.63"><s n="s1.7;p27.63">For each part of the experiment the method of loading the camera and irradiating the samples remained the same. </s><s n="s2.7;p27.63">Each crystal sample was ground into a very fine powder using a pestle and mortar. </s><s n="s3.7;p27.63">The crystals and this equipment were kept inside a warm oven to ensure that no water droplets could contaminate the samples. </s><s n="s4.7;p27.63">This powder was then inserted into a very fine capillary tube and gentled filed so that the sample remained compact at the bottom of the tube. </s><s n="s5.7;p27.63">The top of this tube was snapped off and it was carefully placed in the centre of the camera (as can be seen in <hi rend="italic">Figures 7a and 7b</hi>). </s><s n="s6.7;p27.63">The central positioning of the sample was essential to ensure the beam was striking at constant points, which was carried out by placing the camera x-ray in point on a light source and observing the light beam through the x-ray out point. </s><s n="s7.7;p27.63">It would them be clear if the capillary tube were central and could be positioned more accurately using the adjuster, if necessary. </s></p><p n="p28.63"><s n="s1.6;p28.63">Once this alignment was complete, the following procedure was carried out in the absence of light in the dark room to avoid any exposure of the photographic film. </s><s n="s2.6;p28.63">The cameras used were of circumference 360mm so for convenience each millimetre on the photographic film would correspond to an angle of one degree. </s><s n="s3.6;p28.63">Therefore it was necessary to measure and cut the correct length film to fit well inside the camera and also to punch two holes in the film to allow the insertion of the two collimators for the x-ray in and out beams. </s><s n="s4.6;p28.63">This preparation of the film was all performed using a special cutting board and hole punches. </s><s n="s5.6;p28.63">The collimators were then removed from the camera and the film was loaded carefully without disturbing the sample, the collimators replaced along with the lid of the camera and the film was tightened using the other adjustment switch. </s><s n="s6.6;p28.63">It was good practice to lay out all equipment necessary in the darkroom before the lights were extinguished as to avoid upsetting any apparatus. </s></p><p n="p29.63"><s n="s1.9;p29.63">The loaded camera was then placed in the x-ray generator set, with the x-ray in hole carefully concealed in transport so no light exposed the film. </s><s n="s2.9;p29.63">As all results were to be taken from this film exposure it was of priority that no radiation was able to enter the camera other than the x-rays. </s><s n="s3.9;p29.63">Various locks and screws held the camera in place within the x-ray set and a motor was attached onto the rotating table where the sample was mounted. </s><s n="s4.9;p29.63">This meant that the sample slowly rotated in the x-ray beam to give many collisions between the rays and the powder and hence to produce strong accurate lines on the film. </s><s n="s5.9;p29.63">The set was operated carefully according to safety regulations, and slowly set to a working voltage of 40kV and current of 17mA and left on a timer to irradiate the camera for four hours. </s><s n="s6.9;p29.63">After this time had elapsed the machines was switched off and the camera removed, once again concealing the x-ray in hole against light. </s><s n="s7.9;p29.63">The camera was returned to the dark room, the film removed and developed. </s><s n="s8.9;p29.63">This was done using developer of dilution 1:10 with water for roughly one minute, agitated, and the fixer of dilution 1:3 for roughly 6 minutes. </s><s n="s9.9;p29.63">The strip of film was then washed and hung to dry and we expected to see a pattern on the film similar to that of <hi rend="italic">Figure 6</hi>, but in our case there would be two holes with the diffraction circles centred around them. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0306c-pic.003"><head rend="bold">Figure 8 - Example of a developed x-ray film with low angle and higher angle doublet lines</head></figure><p n="p30.63"><s n="s1.5;p30.63">A light box and vernier scale was then used to record the distances in mm between corresponding lines. </s><s n="s2.5;p30.63">It was more accurate to measure between two matching lines that between one line and the centre of the hole as this always introduced discrepancy. </s><s n="s3.5;p30.63">This gave us our 4θ values in degrees and hence we could determine our θ values from the origin O. </s><s n="s4.5;p30.63"><hi rend="italic">Figure 9</hi> shows a more detailed schematic of the angle we wish to find. </s><s n="s5.5;p30.63">Further care needed to be taken when examining the higher angle lines, remembering the dimensions of θ and the point the angle was being taken about. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0306c-pic.004"><head><hi rend="bold">Figure 9 - Description of how θ is measured in relation to the film</hi> <hi rend="bold">whilst in the camera and laid out flat</hi></head></figure><p n="p31.63"><s n="s1.2;p31.63">For some idea of experimental error, we would measure at the extremities of each line through the most vertical point as many lines were quite thick and hence has a large error in their position. </s><s n="s2.2;p31.63">From this we noted the maximum and minimum 4θ figures for each pair of lines and hence determined an error in this, θ, and later in our 'd' and 'a' values we wished to find. </s></p><div2><head rend="bold">1. Determining the lattice type and parameter of two unknown samples</head><p n="p32.63"><s n="s1.2;p32.63">In this section we carried out the debye-scherrer method for two unknown samples of crystal powder (Sample 1 and Sample 2) that had been prepared as in the above section. </s><s n="s2.2;p32.63">From the developed films, we measured the most prominent lower angle diffraction lines of 4θ and hence θ, with experimental error </s></p><p n="p33.63"><s n="s1.1;p33.63">If we refer back to <hi rend="italic">equation 3</hi>: </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p34.63"><s n="s1.1;p34.63"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0306c-form.005"/><hi rend="bold">(3)</hi> </s></p><p n="p35.63"><s n="s1.7;p35.63">where N = (h <hi rend="sup">2</hi> + k <hi rend="sup">2</hi> + l <hi rend="sup">2</hi>), we index the measured θ values against the most appropriate N values for diffraction lines based on the most obvious pattern for each of the three crystal types. </s><s n="s2.7;p35.63">The first 20 'N' values for primitive, face-centred cubic and body-centred cubic are given in <hi rend="italic">Figure 10</hi>. </s><s n="s3.7;p35.63">For this section of the experiment we plotted the sin <hi rend="sup">2</hi>θ values against the allowed N for P, F and I cubic structures. </s><s n="s4.7;p35.63">The best fitting straight lines of these points would prove the type of cubic structure. </s><s n="s5.7;p35.63">The gradient of this line could then be used to calculate 'a' using our known value of the wavelength of the x-rays λ for the lower angle lines as given by <hi rend="italic">equation 4</hi>. </s><s n="s6.7;p35.63">The uncertainty found in 4θ was carried through into sin <hi rend="sup">2</hi>θ using appropriate error formulas and this was expressed using error bars on the graph. </s><s n="s7.7;p35.63">The Origin 7.0 software was then used to determine the error in the gradient, based on steepest and shallowest slopes given by these error bars, and this gradient error was finally brought forward to give an uncertainty in the lattice parameter 'a'. </s></p><table id="BAWE_0306c-tab.001"><head rend="bold">Figure 10 - The allowed reflections for the first 20 (hkl) spacings of simple, face-centred and body centred cubic, listing the N values were N = (h2 + k2 + l2)</head><row><cell/></row></table></div2><div2><head rend="bold">3. 2. Determining two unknown samples' chemical composition </head><p n="p36.63"><s n="s1.2;p36.63">Using the same photographic films as in Section 3.1, the three darkest lines on the film were chosen and the indexes noted. </s><s n="s2.2;p36.63">For these three θ values the corresponding plane spacing 'd' were calculated and the appropriate error analysis performed for each of the two samples. </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p37.63"><s n="s1.1;p37.63"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0306c-form.006"/><hi rend="bold">(5)</hi> </s></p><p n="p38.63"><s n="s1.2;p38.63">These three strongest 'd' values were then inputted into the ASTM software with their related uncertainties and the software then generated and a list of various compounds whose strongest 'd' lines corresponded with those inputted within this experimental error. </s><s n="s2.2;p38.63">The list was examined for both samples so that compounds could be eliminated on the basis of their mismatching cubic type, colour, 'a' and 'd' values, and so the correct chemical compound could be identified for each sample. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">3. 3. Accurate measurement of lattice parameter using higher angle diffraction lines</head><p n="p39.63"><s n="s1.1;p39.63">The photographic film for Sample 2 was re-examined at the higher angle doublets (see <hi rend="italic">Figure</hi> </s></p><p n="p40.63"><s n="s1.2;p40.63"><hi rend="italic">6</hi>) and these θ values deduced. </s><s n="s2.2;p40.63">The lattice parameter had already been found approximately for Sample 2 and therefore by rearranging <hi rend="italic">equation 3</hi> to give </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p41.63"><s n="s1.1;p41.63"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0306c-form.007"/><hi rend="bold">(3b)</hi> </s></p><p n="p42.63"><s n="s1.3;p42.63">and we can predict the corresponding N values for the higher angles that may be harder to index. </s><s n="s2.3;p42.63">We then determined 'a' much more accurately for each angle using the exact K <hi rend="sub">α1</hi> and K <hi rend="sub">α2</hi> wavelengths and plotted these against an error function <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0306c-form.008"/>. </s><s n="s3.3;p42.63">This should produce a straight-line graph which when extrapolated back to the y-axis should give the most accurate value of the lattice parameter for Sample 2 as the y-axis intercept. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">3. 4. Vegard's Law</head><p n="p43.63"><s n="s1.1;p43.63">This section of the experiment attempted to verify Vegard's Law, in that the lattice parameter of </s></p><p n="p44.63"><s n="s1.8;p44.63">any compound varies linearly with atomic composition. </s><s n="s2.8;p44.63">Here, we were given two halides; Potassium Chloride (KCl) and Potassium Bromide (KBr) both of face-centred cubic structure, and quoted their lattice parameters 6.217 and 6.600 , respectively. </s><s n="s3.8;p44.63">In order to verify this law we were to make a mixture of the two halides, where the ratio of each component was measured explicitly, and calculate 'a' for this new mixture, verifying that 'a' would fit well onto a straight-line graph proportional to the atomic composition of the mixture in relation to each compound. </s><s n="s4.8;p44.63">The only difference in this part of the investigation is in the composition of the mixture. </s><s n="s5.8;p44.63">Known weights of each of KCl and KBr were measured using electronic scales (with error) so that the mixture was 2-3 grams in total. </s><s n="s6.8;p44.63">This was then heated in a small pyrex tube using a blowtorch to fuse the atoms together. </s><s n="s7.8;p44.63">The tube needed to be carefully rotated as it was held in the flame as the melting point of the mixture was very close to that of the pyrex tube. </s><s n="s8.8;p44.63">Once the two compounds had become liquid and then left to cool to form a new crystal, it was then ground down to a powder and inserted into the capillary tube and the debye-scherrer method carried out as before. </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Results </head><div2><head rend="bold">4. 1. Determining the lattice type and parameter of two unknown samples</head><p n="p45.63"><s n="s1.1;p45.63"><hi rend="italic">Figures 11</hi> and <hi rend="italic"> 12</hi> have been plotted using the sin <hi rend="sup">2</hi>θ values obtained from the θs of two </s></p><p n="p46.63"><s n="s1.7;p46.63">photographic films for Samples 1 and 2 against the allowed N values for each of the three cubic types as given in <hi rend="italic">Figure 8</hi>. </s><s n="s2.7;p46.63">As can be seen the best straight line fit for sample one was the face centred cubic with a gradient of 0.0186, and for sample two a simple cubic with a gradient of 0.0147. </s><s n="s3.7;p46.63">From equation 3 we know that this gradient must be equal to λ<hi rend="sup">2</hi>/4a <hi rend="sup">2</hi>. </s><s n="s4.7;p46.63">We also calculated the wavelengths [Ref(3)] to be K <hi rend="sub">α1</hi> = 1.54052 Ǻ and K <hi rend="sub">α2</hi> = 1.54436 Ǻ, and hence by <hi rend="italic">equation 4</hi> the average wavelength for lower angle Kα = 1.5418 Ǻ. </s><s n="s5.7;p46.63">The error analysis was carried out by differentiating sinθ twice to give <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0306c-form.009"/> and plotting these as error bars. </s><s n="s6.7;p46.63">Origin 7.0 was used again to calculate linear regression analysis and determine the error in our gradient value, of which this percentage error was carried forward to our 'a' value found from the gradient. </s><s n="s7.7;p46.63">By rearranging this term for the gradient in terms of 'a' we obtained the values that for sample one a = 5.66 ± 0.06Ǻ and sample two a = 6.57 ± 0.033 Ǻ. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0306c-fig.009"><head rend="bold">Figure 11 - Graph, based on equation (3) used to find best linear fit for a given crystal type and also find the lattice parameter from the gradient for Sample 1</head></figure><figure id="BAWE_0306c-fig.010"><head rend="bold">Figure 12 - Graph, based on equation (3), used to find best linear fit for a given crystal type and also find the lattice parameter from the gradient for Sample 2</head></figure></div2><div2><head rend="bold">4. 2. Determining two unknown samples' chemical composition</head><div3><head rend="bold">4. 2. 1. Sample one </head><p n="p47.63"><s n="s1.8;p47.63">The strongest diffraction lines for sample one were chosen to be at N = 4, 8 and 12. </s><s n="s2.8;p47.63">This gave place spacing values of d <hi rend="sub">4</hi> = 2.83 ± 0.05 Ǻ, d <hi rend="sub">8</hi> = 2.00 ± 0.03 Ǻ d <hi rend="sub">12</hi> = 1.62 ± 0.03 Ǻ. </s><s n="s3.8;p47.63">These values, and their experimental error were intputted into the ASTM software. </s><s n="s4.8;p47.63">The list that was generated began with the results below in <hi rend="italic">Figure 13</hi>. </s><s n="s5.8;p47.63">The original list was much longer but the other compounds were eliminated. </s><s n="s6.8;p47.63">The first criteria was that of cubic type as sown in the right hand column. </s><s n="s7.8;p47.63">Here we were looking for a face-centred cubic as had been determined in the previous section denoted by Fm-3m, and all other crystal types were ignored. </s><s n="s8.8;p47.63">The columns next to these contained the three strongest lines within the error quoted, hence if we trusted the results we could choose a substance with d lines close to our expected value. </s></p><table id="BAWE_0306c-tab.002"><head rend="bold">Figure 13 - Some of the first ASTM list results for Sample One. </head><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p48.63"><s n="s1.2;p48.63">Further eliminations were made by clicking on the compound to bring up its specific 'card', like that in <hi rend="italic">Figure 14</hi>, with extra information; namely the lattice parameter, colour (see <hi rend="italic">Figure 16</hi> also) and intensities in the '<hi rend="italic">Int</hi>' column. </s><s n="s2.2;p48.63">If after all other factors are used and the crystal is still undetermined we can look at the relative intensities of each (h k l) line and see how they match with our film for any obvious pattern. </s></p><p n="p49.63"><s n="s1.2;p49.63">For sample one the most obvious selection was that of NaCl with corresponding cubic type, lattice parameter within in experimental error as found to be a = 5.66 ± 0.06Ǻ in section 4. </s><s n="s2.2;p49.63">1, and all the 'd' values matched within 0.01, well within expected uncertainty. </s></p><table id="BAWE_0306c-tab.003"><head rend="bold">Figure 14 - The Sodium Chloride card in more detail from the ASTM</head><row><cell/></row></table></div3><div3><head rend="bold"> 4. 2. 2. Sample two </head><p n="p50.63"><s n="s1.1;p50.63">For Sample two, the strongest lines were 4, 5 and 14 with corresponding spacings of d <hi rend="sub">4</hi> = 3.30 ± </s></p><p n="p51.63"><s n="s1.3;p51.63">0.06 Ǻ, d <hi rend="sub">5</hi> = 2.94 ± 0.03 Ǻ and d <hi rend="sub">14</hi> = 1.76 ± 0.01 Ǻ. </s><s n="s2.3;p51.63">Only 6 results were generated in this case, as some of the experimental error was much smaller than the previous sample ie for d <hi rend="sub">14.</hi> </s><s n="s3.3;p51.63">Here we were looking for a simple cubic structure (section 4.1) hence a primitive unit cell P as highlighted in <hi rend="italic">Figure 15</hi>. </s></p><table id="BAWE_0306c-tab.004"><head rend="bold">Figure 15 - The list of 6 results generated by the ASTM for Sample Two </head><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p52.63"><s n="s1.2;p52.63">NaCl <hi rend="sub">3</hi> and Na(Cl <hi rend="sub">3</hi>), the remaining choices had very similar 'd' values both close to that found above but with Sodium Chlorate slightly closer. </s><s n="s2.2;p52.63">On examination of the lattice constant in comparison to our found value of a = 6.57 ± 0.033 Ǻ we finally chose NaCl <hi rend="sub">3</hi> due to its colourlessness (see Figure 16) intensity lines, and its value of 6.5756 Ǻ, as opposed to Na(Cl <hi rend="sub">3</hi>) with a value of 6.6302 Ǻ. </s></p><table id="BAWE_0306c-tab.005"><head rend="bold">Figure 16 - The Sodium Chlorate card used to correctly identify Sample Two</head><row><cell/></row></table></div3></div2><div2><head rend="bold">4. 3. Accurate measurement of lattice parameter using higher angle diffraction lines</head><p n="p53.63"><s n="s1.1;p53.63">Here, we looked at the higher angle doublet lines and calculated 'a' values for each line for both </s></p><p n="p54.63"><s n="s1.3;p54.63">K <hi rend="sub">α1</hi> = 1.54052 Ǻ and K <hi rend="sub">α2</hi> = 1.54436 Ǻ wavelengths. </s><s n="s2.3;p54.63">These were then plotted against the error function in theta for that angle and is shown in <hi rend="italic">Figure 17</hi>. </s><s n="s3.3;p54.63">This graph is a very poor linear fit and the actual result for 'a' (when extrapolated back to θ=90 <hi rend="sup">o</hi>) is worse than the one previously determined by the supposedly less accurate method and we obtain 6.46Ǻ as opposed to 6.57Ǻ. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0306c-fig.011"><head><hi rend="bold">Figure 17 - Graph of lattice parameters in relation to error functions for certain</hi> <hi rend="bold">angles used to find a more accurate value for 'a' for Sample Two </hi></head></figure></div2><div2><head rend="bold">4. 4. Vegard's Law </head><p n="p55.63"><s n="s1.4;p55.63">The amounts of KCl and KBr used in this crystal mixture were 1.485 ± 0.010 g and 1.000 ± 0.010g respectively. </s><s n="s2.4;p55.63">The percentage errors in these were carried through to work out greatest and least amounts of KCl and KBr possible in the mixture and this was plotted as x-axis error bars in <hi rend="italic">Figure 18</hi>. </s><s n="s3.4;p55.63">From the periodic table we found the molecular weights of the atoms KCl to be 74.5513g and KBr 119.0023g which would be one mole of that substance of 6.0221367 x 1023 atoms. </s><s n="s4.4;p55.63">From this we deduced the number of molecules of KBr and KCl that would be present and determined a ratio of KBr : KCl to be 29.67% : 70.33%. </s></p><p n="p56.63"><s n="s1.6;p56.63">For this mixture we plotted sin <hi rend="sup">2</hi>θ against N as in the first section to work out our value for the lattice parameter a. </s><s n="s2.6;p56.63">This process was repeated for pure KCl and KBr to check for any systematic error that could be present and skew results, and hence we checked to see how close we would reach to a = 6.217 and 6.600, respectively for these two. </s><s n="s3.6;p56.63">For our roughly 30:70 mixture we obtained a graph in Origin 7.0 with appropriate linear regression analysis for estimated error based on sin <hi rend="sup">2</hi>θ error bars, and found 'a' for this mixture to be 6.458 ± 0.136 Ǻ. </s><s n="s4.6;p56.63">The KBr film was developed badly and this part of the experiment was not completed but for KCl we obtained the result 6.300 ± 0.245 Ǻ to be compared with 6.217. </s><s n="s5.6;p56.63">Hence the theoretical and experimental values for KBr, KCl and the mixture lattice constant values were plotted on a graph relating the percentage compositon of KBr, to prove a proportionality relationship. </s><s n="s6.6;p56.63">See <hi rend="italic">Figure 18</hi>: </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0306c-fig.012"><head rend="bold">Figure 18 - Graph to demonstrate Vegard's Law for KCl, KBr and a mixture of the two</head></figure></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Discussion </head><div2><head rend="bold">5. 1. Determining the lattice type and parameter of two unknown samples and their chemical composition</head><p n="p57.63"><s n="s1.7;p57.63">This section of the experiment was completed most easily. </s><s n="s2.7;p57.63">The lower angle diffraction lines for samples one and two were very easy to index as they had quite clear patterns on appearance and hence the results were not surprising. </s><s n="s3.7;p57.63">The graphs confirmed the face-centred and simple cubic structures, which were later used in identifying the crystals correctly. </s><s n="s4.7;p57.63">The lattice parameter values obtained here, although by a less accurate average of the wavelength proved to be well within experimental error boundaries as determined by error analysis of the thickness of the diffraction lines. </s><s n="s5.7;p57.63">The line thickness introduced most error into any measurements and this occurred usually as a result of not centralising the sample thoroughly. </s><s n="s6.7;p57.63">If the sample is not through the straight-though of the x-ray beam the majority of the time, each time an interaction occurs at a point slightly off centre it will create a diffraction line also slightly off position and hence thicken the original line. </s><s n="s7.7;p57.63">Here, this was not too much of an issue but played a role later. </s></p><p n="p58.63"><s n="s1.3;p58.63">We finally determined sample one to be Sodium Chloride with reasonable certainty, as a colourless face-centred cubic structure with lattice parameter a = 5.66 ± 0.06Ǻ which matched correctly within error that given by the computer to be 5.62 Ǻ. </s><s n="s2.3;p58.63">The errors for this were larger than those for sample two and hence many results were generated. </s><s n="s3.3;p58.63">Lots of these could easily be eliminated using cubic type alone so it was important that the details in the first section were completed accurately. </s></p><p n="p59.63"><s n="s1.5;p59.63">Sample two was later decided as Sodium Chlorate, chosen from a much smaller list but with a very close competitor Sodium Chlorate Bromate. </s><s n="s2.5;p59.63">The former was chosen mainly due to a very good agreement between the measured lattice parameter a = 6.57 ± 0.033 Ǻ and the stated parameter from the ASTM of 6.5756 Ǻ. </s><s n="s3.5;p59.63">The d values for this were much harder to index. </s><s n="s4.5;p59.63">The lines were fainter probably due to some interference of the beam or lack of exposure, and hence the errors in θ were smaller but the lines were harder to examine. </s><s n="s5.5;p59.63">This also became a problem when studying to doublets. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">5. 2. Accurate measurement of lattice parameter using higher angle diffraction lines</head><p n="p60.63"><s n="s1.2;p60.63">The higher angle doublet lines were so much harder to index as they were very faint. </s><s n="s2.2;p60.63">This meant </s></p><p n="p61.63"><s n="s1.3;p61.63">that when the values were being indexed most were guesses as some laid quite easily in between two N values, and it was also difficult to match pairs of lines either side of the exit hole and hence increased error further. </s><s n="s2.3;p61.63">As a result of this the error function plot did not fall into the uncertainty allowance, and was actually less accurate than the lattice parameter found for sample two in the previous section that matched Sodium Chlorate exceptionally, assuming this was the correct compound choice. </s><s n="s3.3;p61.63">If completed again this would have been exposed for slightly longer and the positioning of the crystal checked more thoroughly to reduce the errors that this film introduced for both investigations of sample two. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">5. 3. Vegard's Law </head><p n="p62.63"><s n="s1.5;p62.63"><hi rend="italic">Figure 18</hi> proves that there is a linear proportional relationship between atomic composition and lattice parameter, but to a very optimistic extent as the errors introduced here are very high. </s><s n="s2.5;p62.63">The measurement of the lattice parameter of KCl is quite different (in the context of these values) to that of the value quoted in the lab script and hence without this part being performed we would have been unaware of any systematic error. </s><s n="s3.5;p62.63">The mixture value on this graph does fit in with the theoretical proportionality, as given by the blue line, within its experimental error but this is still quite great. </s><s n="s4.5;p62.63">Assuming the same proportionality gradient for our measured values, shown by the pink line, this value agrees much more complacently. </s><s n="s5.5;p62.63">Either way vegard's law is proven correct, but this section would have been greatly helped if the pure KBr had given us a value that fitted well with the pink line to prove this systematic error beyond a doubt, or simply the wrong lattice constant values for KBr and KCl as quoted. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">5. 4 Further Sources of Error</head><p n="p63.63"><s n="s1.4;p63.63">The only raw data taken in this experiment came from reading diffraction lines on photographic film. </s><s n="s2.4;p63.63">Hence the main sources of error were those in reading these lines for exmaple ensuring the sample was kept central in the camera for reasonably thin but distinguishable lines. </s><s n="s3.4;p63.63">Also, the lower resolution higher angles could be improved with longer exposure time as many were very faint and hard to index. </s><s n="s4.4;p63.63">Also in actual sample preparation the sample needed to be ground finely enough so that it fitted easily and compactly in the capillary tube with no air holes and the x-rays would interact consistently, and ensuring that the film was exposed as little as possible to external light or other radiation to the film was clear with dark lines and easy to read. </s></p></div2></div1></body><back><div1 type="bibliography"><head rend="bold">References </head><p> (1) 2<hi rend="sup">nd</hi> Year Laboratory Script P4 - X-Ray Crystallography </p><p>Department of Physics</p><p>University of <name type="university"/></p><p> (2) The Elements of Physics </p><p>I. S. Grant and W. R. Phillips </p><p> Oxford University Press</p><p> (3) Elements of X-ray Diffraction</p><p>B. D. Cullity</p><p>Addison Wesley </p><p> (4) 1<hi rend="sup">st</hi> Year 'Matter' Lecture Notes</p><p>David Leadley, October 2002</p><p> (5) <seg type="URL" n="http://www.matter.org.uk/diffraction/x-ray/default.htm"/></p><p> (6) <seg type="URL" n="http://bca.cryst.bbk.ac.uk/bca/Cnews/1997/Mar97/Bragg.html"/></p><p> (7) <seg type="URL" n="http://www.bmsc.washington.edu/people/merritt/bc530/bragg"/></p><p> (8) <seg type="URL" n="http://www.scienceall.com/menu/time/p23.html"/></p><p> (9) <seg type="URL" n="http://people.hws.edu/craig/chem120/Liq_Sol/sld022.htm"/></p><p> (10) <seg type="URL" n="http://www.chem.qmw.ac.uk/surfaces/scc/scat1_1b.htm"/></p></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
