<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_0306h" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Laser Interferometry</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">deleted: header: three student names, module name, date; footer: page number</note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">two columns</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">3</p><p n="date">2005-03</p><p n="module title">Physics Laboratory</p><p n="module code">PX428</p><p n="genre family">Research report</p><p n="discipline">Physics</p><p n="disciplinary group">PS</p><p n="grade">M</p><p n="number of authors">3</p><p n="number of words">3143</p><p n="number of s-units">139</p><p n="number of p">51</p><p n="number of tables">2</p><p n="number of figures">6</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">68</p><p n="number of lists">0</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">10</p><p n="abstract present">abstract present</p><p n="average words per s-unit">22.6</p><p n="average s-units per p">2.7</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">f</p><p n="year of birth">1984</p><p n="first language">English</p><p n="education">UKA</p><p n="course">Mphys F303</p><p n="student ID">0306</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><div1 type="front text"><p rend="italic">The coherence of Na, Hg and white light sources and the refractive indices of He, N, Ar, CO2 and Air using the Michelson Interferometer</p></div1><div1 type="front text"><p><name type="student name"/>, <name type="student name"/>, <name type="student name"/></p></div1></front><body><div1 type="abstract"><p n="p1.51"><s n="s1.7;p1.51">A Michelson Interferometer, calibrated using a He-Ne laser, was used to observe the fringe pattern of Na, Hg and white light. </s><s n="s2.7;p1.51">It was shown that Na light is consistent of two wavelengths with a separation: <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0306h-form.001"/>, interfering to give regions of maximum and minimum interference pattern intensity. </s><s n="s3.7;p1.51">This was used to determine the position of zero optical path difference. </s><s n="s4.7;p1.51">Here white light fringes were observed and used to determine the coherence length of white light; <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0306h-form.002"/>. </s><s n="s5.7;p1.51">It was shown using a Fourier Transform method that the characteristic wavelengths, and their relative abundances, of the Mercury emission spectrum could be found. </s><s n="s6.7;p1.51">Unfortunately the data was not accurate enough to directly determine the coherence length of the mercury lamp. </s><s n="s7.7;p1.51">By observation of fringes in the He-Ne laser spectrum as various gases, He, N, Ar, CO <hi rend="sub">2</hi> and Air, were introduced into a chamber in the path of one of the arms of the interferometer, the refractive indices of these gases were found; <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0306h-form.003"/>, <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0306h-form.004"/>, <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0306h-form.005"/>, <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0306h-form.006"/>, <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0306h-form.007"/>. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">1. Introduction </head><p n="p2.51"><s n="s1.2;p2.51">The Michelson Interferometer, shown in Figure 1, is commonly regarded as one of the most significant pieces of scientific apparatus of the last century. </s><s n="s2.2;p2.51">Whilst it has lead to great discoveries in many fields, most famously in relativity, here it has been used to study the spectra of a variety of light sources and the refractive indices of various gases <hi rend="sup">[1]</hi>. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0306h-pic.001"><head>Figure 1: A schematic diagram of the Michelson Interferometer</head></figure><p n="p3.51"><s n="s1.6;p3.51">The Michelson Interferometer, shown schematically in Figure 1, works by splitting light in two (by amplitude <hi rend="sup">[2]</hi>) using a glass block known as the Beam Splitter (B), silvered on the side furthest from the light source, and recombining the light after both arms have reflected normally off mirrors (M1 and M2) to form an interference pattern that can be recorded by the detector. </s><s n="s2.6;p3.51">If necessary light entering B can be focussed to infinity and light reaching the detector can be focussed to as sharp a point as possible using lenses as in Figure 1. </s><s n="s3.6;p3.51">M1 can be moved towards or away from B using a geared micrometer operated by a motor. </s><s n="s4.6;p3.51">The horizontal and vertical tilt of M2 can be controlled using screws. </s><s n="s5.6;p3.51">The beam of light travelling towards M2 passes through a Compensation Plate (C), a block of glass of the same optical thickness as B, such that upon recombination at B both beams have travelled the same optical distance for optimum interference. </s><s n="s6.6;p3.51">The detector is a photo-detector of variable gain, detecting photo intensity, linked via an ADC to a computer. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">2. Background Theory</head><div2><head rend="bold">2.1 Circular Fringes</head><p n="p4.51"><s n="s1.1;p4.51">If we assume that the distances <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0306h-form.008"/>, then we will observe interference maxima (fringes, shown in Figure 2) satisfying ; </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p5.51"><s n="s1.1;p5.51"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0306h-form.009"/>(1)<hi rend="sup">[2,3]</hi>, </s></p><p n="p6.51"><s n="s1.3;p6.51">where <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0306h-form.010"/> is the angle at which the fringe appears, <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0306h-form.011"/> is the wavelength of the light and <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0306h-form.012"/> is the order of the fringe. </s><s n="s2.3;p6.51">The resulting fringes will be circular (as <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0306h-form.013"/> is constant for a given <hi rend="italic">m</hi>, <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0306h-form.014"/> and <hi rend="italic">d</hi>) and centred on <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0306h-form.015"/> where <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0306h-form.016"/>. </s><s n="s3.3;p6.51">The intensity of the rings is given by: </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p7.51"><s n="s1.1;p7.51"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0306h-form.017"/>(2)<hi rend="sup">[2]</hi>, </s></p><p n="p8.51"><s n="s1.1;p8.51">where <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0306h-form.018"/> is the amplitude of the waves being combined, and their phase difference is given by: </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p9.51"><s n="s1.1;p9.51"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0306h-form.019"/> (3)<hi rend="sup">[2]</hi>. </s></p><p n="p10.51"><s n="s1.2;p10.51">The rings will appear to move out from, or in towards, the centre point as the micrometer position is varied. </s><s n="s2.2;p10.51">Thus one can observe the variation of intensity of the centre point as a function of <hi rend="italic">d</hi> (this will be used in the subsequent sections, see Figure 4). </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">2.2 Localized Fringes </head><p n="p11.51"><s n="s1.4;p11.51">Consider a case similar to that discussed in 2.1 but now with M <hi rend="sub">2</hi> tilted slightly. </s><s n="s2.4;p11.51">The geometry can be simplified by superimposing M2' onto M1 (see Figure 2). </s><s n="s3.4;p11.51">Collimated light propagates from point P and the two rays reaching the observer (looking parallel at M1) appear to diverge from point P'. </s><s n="s4.4;p11.51">The position of P' varies with the angle of the incident light (i.e. position of P) however, importantly, it has been proven that the path difference between ray 1 and 2 does not <hi rend="sup">[4]</hi>. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0306h-fig.001"><head>Figure 2: A diagram for formation of localised fringes with angled M2 replaced by its virtual image M2'<hi rend="sup">[2]</hi> .</head></figure><p n="p12.51"><s n="s1.4;p12.51">By considering light incident on M2 it becomes clear that the extra distance travelled is due to an "air film" in the shape of a wedge (see Figure 3). </s><s n="s2.4;p12.51">This extra distance is constant parallel to the edge of the wedge. </s><s n="s3.4;p12.51">Where the distance between M1 and M2 is small the thickness of the wedge can be approximated as the half the path difference (points A, B, B and D correspond to constructive interference). </s><s n="s4.4;p12.51">It is easy to show that the separation, <hi rend="italic">l</hi>, between adjacent maxima </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p13.51"><s n="s1.1;p13.51"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0306h-form.020"/> (4) </s></p><p n="p14.51"><s n="s1.5;p14.51">where φ is the wedge angle (φ is small). </s><s n="s2.5;p14.51">This gives vertical localised fringes in the field of view. </s><s n="s3.5;p14.51">However, because of some variation of path difference with angle, these approximations only hold when the distance between M1 and M2 is small. </s><s n="s4.5;p14.51">Thus in general the fringes are usually curved and are always convex towards the thin end of the wedge. </s><s n="s5.5;p14.51">These localized fringes are known as "Fizeau's wedge fringes" <hi rend="sup">[2][6][5]</hi>. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0306h-pic.002"><head>Figure 3: A diagram illustrating the positions of localised adjacent maxima <hi rend="sup">[5] </hi></head></figure></div2><div2><head rend="bold">2.3 Coherence length</head><p n="p15.51"><s n="s1.2;p15.51">An important parameter of any light source used in this experiment is coherence length because it is a measure of the length of an emitted wave-train before it breaks down. </s><s n="s2.2;p15.51">The Coherence length of a single spectral line or band can be found from <hi rend="italic">bandwidth</hi> </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p16.51"><s n="s1.1;p16.51"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0306h-form.021"/> (5) </s></p><p n="p17.51"><s n="s1.2;p17.51">where Δ<hi rend="italic">tc</hi> is the coherent time. </s><s n="s2.2;p17.51">From equation (5) it is obvious that the <hi rend="italic">coherence length</hi> is given by </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p18.51"><s n="s1.1;p18.51"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0306h-form.022"/> (6)<hi rend="sup">[2 p.650]</hi> </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">3 Results </head><div2><head rend="bold">3.1Calibration Using He-Ne Laser </head><p n="p19.51"><s n="s1.5;p19.51">A He-Ne laser was used to determine the ratio of movement of M1 to a given movement of the micrometer. </s><s n="s2.5;p19.51">The laser was aligned such that fringes were observed and the motor was left running so that the micrometer moved through 2.20mm, as it did so the intensity recorded by the detector varied sinusoidally as one would expect from equation (1). </s><s n="s3.5;p19.51">In that time 1454 fringes were observed by the detector corresponding to a movement of <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0306h-form.023"/> of M1 (given by <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0306h-form.024"/>, where <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0306h-form.025"/>). </s><s n="s4.5;p19.51">From this a ratio of <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0306h-form.026"/> was found (movement of M1: movement of micrometer). </s><s n="s5.5;p19.51">The laser was also used to align the interferometer in subsequent experiments due to its long coherence length. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">3.2 Interference of Sodium light </head><p n="p20.51"><s n="s1.7;p20.51">Sodium light is known to consist of two main wavelengths, rather than one as with a laser. </s><s n="s2.7;p20.51">Because of this the intensity of the bright fringes was observed to vary as a function of <hi rend="italic">d</hi>, as the two wavelengths interfered constructively and destructively with each other. </s><s n="s3.7;p20.51">From equations (2) and (3) we can see that maximum intensity will occur at <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0306h-form.027"/>. </s><s n="s4.7;p20.51">Since this point is very hard to locate the sodium spectrum (<hi rend="italic">I</hi> as a function of micrometer reading) was recorded for a large sweep of the micrometer, shown in Figure 4. </s><s n="s5.7;p20.51">It was noted that wave packets formed at regular intervals, increasing in peak intensity as they approached the largest wave packet, where <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0306h-form.028"/>, clearly visible in Figure 4 and marked by the pink dashed line. </s><s n="s6.7;p20.51">From this graph it was found that <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0306h-form.029"/> at a micrometer reading of <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0306h-form.030"/>. </s><s n="s7.7;p20.51">The interference pattern of Sodium light is shown in Figure 5. </s></p><p n="p21.51"><s n="s1.1;p21.51">Consider the position of M1 when the two wavelengths (λ<hi rend="sub">1</hi> > λ<hi rend="sub">2</hi>) that make up the spectrum of sodium are out of phase. </s></p><p n="p22.51"><s n="s1.1;p22.51"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0306h-form.031"/> </s></p><p n="p23.51"><s n="s1.3;p23.51">where n is an integer. </s><s n="s2.3;p23.51">The extra half wavelength is required for destructive interference. </s><s n="s3.3;p23.51">Next M1 is moved to the next destructive interference of λ<hi rend="sub">1</hi> and λ<hi rend="sub">2</hi> (i.e. the next minima in the wave packet). </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0306h-fig.002"><head>Figure 4: The Sodium Spectrum, intensity as a function of micrometer reading (green). <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0306h-form.032"/> shown in pink.</head></figure><figure id="BAWE_0306h-pic.003"><head>Figure 5: The Na interference pattern clearly showing rings of maximum and minimum intensity coming from a central point. </head></figure><p n="p24.51"><s n="s1.1;p24.51"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0306h-form.033"/> </s></p><p n="p25.51"><s n="s1.1;p25.51">From these equations it can be shown that the difference between the two wavelengths in the sodium doublet can be calculated from the separation, s, between destructive (<hi rend="italic">or constructive</hi>) interferences (equation (7)). </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p26.51"><s n="s1.1;p26.51"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0306h-form.034"/> (7) </s></p><p n="p27.51"><s n="s1.1;p27.51">λ<hi rend="sub">av</hi> is the mean wavelength of sodium light = 589.3nm <hi rend="sup">[7]</hi>.It was found that <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0306h-form.035"/>. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">3.3 White-light interference</head><div3><head rend="bold">3.3.1 Theory of White-light interference</head><p n="p28.51"><s n="s1.4;p28.51">White-light contains a continuous spread of wavelengths from 400 to 750nm and consequently has a very short coherence length (see equation (6)). </s><s n="s2.4;p28.51">Using equation (1) for constructive interference and equation (1) where <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0306h-form.036"/> for destructive interference, consider a white light source with d = 1000nm. </s><s n="s3.4;p28.51">Assuming θ is small, light with wavelength 667nm, 500nm and 400nm will interfere constructively and light with wavelength 571nm, 444nm will interfere destructively and consequently no fringe pattern will be observed. </s><s n="s4.4;p28.51">White-light interference will only be observable where d is very close to 0, the position of zero path difference. </s></p><p n="p29.51"><s n="s1.4;p29.51">In order to achieve zero path difference M2 must be tilted as with localised fringes. </s><s n="s2.4;p29.51">Let us again consider a system where M2 is replaced by its virtual image M2' formed by a reflection along the line of beam splitter B (see Figure 6). </s><s n="s3.4;p29.51">The position of zero path difference can be found at the point where M2' intersects M1. </s><s n="s4.4;p29.51">The white-light fringes were expected to be vertically aligned because the path difference, <hi rend="italic">d</hi>, is very small (see section 2.2) <hi rend="sup">[2]</hi>. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0306h-fig.003"><head>Figure 6: Virtual image of M2' superimposed onto M1. White-light fringes are formed at the position of zero path difference. Anti-parallel rays are spaced for the sake of clarity </head></figure></div3><div3><head rend="bold">3.3.2 Observation of coloured fringes</head><p n="p30.51"><s n="s1.4;p30.51">The equipment was set up as in Figure 1 with a white-light source positioned a distance of the focal length away from the convex lens, focusing it into a parallel beam, with M1 at the position of zero optical path difference (calculated in the sodium section) and M2 slightly angled as with localised fringes. </s><s n="s2.4;p30.51">The focusing lens was removed so the fringes could be observed by eye. </s><s n="s3.4;p30.51">The field of view contained vertically aligned fringes; a central black fringe surrounded by coloured fringes fading with distance from the centre (Figure 7). </s><s n="s4.4;p30.51">The number of fringes in the field of view increased with increase in the angle of M2, (φ). </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0306h-pic.004"><head>Figure 7: photograph of white-light fringes taken with a digital camera</head></figure></div3><div3><head rend="bold">3.3.3 Explanation of spectrum separation</head><p n="p31.51"><s n="s1.9;p31.51">At first it seems a little confusing that the central fringe is black since it appears that, for any wavelength of light, the two beams should be in phase with each other. </s><s n="s2.9;p31.51">This is due to the paths taken by ray 1 and 2 respectively. </s><s n="s3.9;p31.51">Ray 1 undergoes an internal reflection at B with no associated phase change whereas ray 2 undergoes an external reflection and consequently a phase change of π. </s><s n="s4.9;p31.51">Therefore at zero path difference and θ = 0 there is destructive interference. </s><s n="s5.9;p31.51">Either side of the central fringe, fringe separation is increased for longer wavelengths due to "Fizeau's wedge" (equation (4)) and hence the colours appear to separate (illustrated in Figure 8 for wavelengths corresponding to green and red). </s><s n="s6.9;p31.51">This separation produces the various impure spectral colours observed. </s><s n="s7.9;p31.51">Eventually, so many colours are present at a particular point that the resultant colour appears white. </s><s n="s8.9;p31.51">This limits the number of fringes visible <hi rend="sup">[2]</hi>. </s><s n="s9.9;p31.51">As φ increases the separation decreases (from equation (4)) so more fringes become visible in the field of view. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0306h-fig.004"><head>Figure 8: A graph illustrating the formation of white-light fringes centred on a dark fringe. The solid and dashed curves corresponding to green and red light respectively become separated as θ increases <hi rend="sup">[2 p.277].</hi> </head></figure></div3><div3><head rend="bold">3.3.4 Dispersion</head><p n="p32.51"><s n="s1.8;p32.51">The compensation plate C in the Michelson Interferometer plays a vital role in white-light interference. </s><s n="s2.8;p32.51">It is required because light reflects off the back surface of the beam splitter mirror B. This means that light reflected by M1 travels through B three times whereas light reflected by M2 only travels through B once. </s><s n="s3.8;p32.51">B has a higher refractive index than air, consequently the light that travels through it is slowed (<formula notation="" id="BAWE_0306h-form.037"/>). </s><s n="s4.8;p32.51">For a monochromatic light source this is the only consideration and without C the distance to M1 appears longer. </s><s n="s5.8;p32.51">However, for a light source comprising of different constituent wavelengths, or indeed a continuum as in the case of white-light, the effect of dispersion must be considered. </s><s n="s6.8;p32.51">The different wavelengths of white-light experience different refractive indices in B, meaning that light of shorter wavelength is slowed more than light of longer wavelength (as with light in a prism). </s><s n="s7.8;p32.51">Without C, M1 could be moved to give equal path for say green light, but now the paths would no longer be equal for red or blue light. </s><s n="s8.8;p32.51">With the introduction of C rays 1 and 2 travel through the same amount of material B, have equal dispersion, and therefore equal path for all wavelengths <hi rend="sup">[5]</hi>. </s></p></div3><div3><head rend="bold">3.3.5 Coherence Length of White-light </head><p n="p33.51"><s n="s1.3;p33.51">The motor for driving M1 was run whilst the intensity of white-light was measured as a function of distance using the photodiode. </s><s n="s2.3;p33.51">The coherence length was found to be <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0306h-form.038"/> from Figure 9. </s><s n="s3.3;p33.51">It is unsurprising that this is small because of the continuous range of interfering frequencies in the white-light spectrum (see equation (6)). </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0306h-fig.005"><head>Figure 9: A graph of intensity verses micrometer reading for a white-light source.</head></figure></div3></div2><div2><head rend="bold">3.4 Mercury fringes</head><p n="p34.51"><s n="s1.2;p34.51">The equipment was set up as for white-light, using a Mercury lamp, and Mercury fringes were observed (see Figure 10). </s><s n="s2.2;p34.51">By the repetitiveness of the spectrum, it is evident that the emission spectrum of Mercury contains a number of spectral lines rather than the continuous spectrum seen with white-light. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0306h-pic.005"><head>Figure 10: A photograph of Mercury fringes centred on a dark fringe.</head></figure><div3><head rend="bold">3.4.1 Coherence length of Mercury</head><p n="p35.51"><s n="s1.5;p35.51">As in section 3.2, intensity was recorded as a function of micrometer reading using the photodiode. </s><s n="s2.5;p35.51">The beat pattern observed was longer than the total adjustable length of M1 and therefore the coherence length could not be measured directly. </s><s n="s3.5;p35.51">The coherence length of the individual spectral lines was calculated from the emission spectrum (equation (6)). </s><s n="s4.5;p35.51">This was done by a Fourier analysis of the recorded intensity verses extension data. </s><s n="s5.5;p35.51">Consider equation (8) for two waves of equal amplitude, the contribution to intensity for a small increment in wavenumber <hi rend="italic">k</hi> can be written as: </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p36.51"><s n="s1.1;p36.51"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0306h-form.039"/> (8) </s></p><p n="p37.51"><s n="s1.2;p37.51">where the extension <hi rend="italic">x</hi> = 2 <hi rend="italic">d</hi> and consequently <hi rend="italic">kx</hi> = δ and <hi rend="italic">S(k)</hi> is the wavenumber spectrum of the source. </s><s n="s2.2;p37.51">By integration it can be shown that:<hi rend="sup">[6 p.17]</hi> </s></p><p n="p38.51"><s n="s1.1;p38.51"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0306h-form.040"/> </s></p><p n="p39.51"><s n="s1.2;p39.51">where <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0306h-form.041"/>. </s><s n="s2.2;p39.51">Now by taking the real (cosine) part of the Fourier transform of intensity the observed wavenumber spectrum of the sample can be found. </s></p><p n="p40.51"><s n="s1.1;p40.51"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0306h-form.042"/> </s></p><p n="p41.51"><s n="s1.2;p41.51">The computer performed the Fourier transform on this data to produce a graph of k space (Figure 11). </s><s n="s2.2;p41.51">For each λ in the emission spectrum the intensity varies sinusoidally with extension, resulting in a Fourier transform that is symmetrical about is centre. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0306h-fig.006"><head>Figure 11: Experimentally recorded mercury fringes in k-space. The colours correspond to data in Figure 12.</head></figure><p n="p42.51"><s n="s1.4;p42.51">Using data shown in Figure 12, which is colour coded to correspond to Figure 11, the relative abundances of the measured spectral frequencies can be found. </s><s n="s2.4;p42.51">The low signal to noise ratio in Figure 11 means that the information displayed is not of a high enough degree of accuracy for any calculations of coherence length to be made. </s><s n="s3.4;p42.51">However, this does at least offer an insight into how this method can be used, and had the data been recorded over a larger range of micrometer readings the signal to noise ratio could have been improved. </s><s n="s4.4;p42.51">The anomalous peak, which precedes the yellow peak, is in fact in the infrared range and the data quoted is only for the visible spectrum. </s></p><table id="BAWE_0306h-tab.001"><head>Figure 12: Values for wavelengths and corresponding wavenumbers of mercury emission spectrum, <hi rend="italic">s</hi> = strong, <hi rend="italic">m</hi> = medium, <hi rend="italic">w</hi> = weak <hi rend="sup">[2 p452]</hi> .</head><row><cell/></row></table></div3></div2><div2><head rend="bold">3.5 Calculating the Refractive Indices of gases</head><p n="p43.51"><s n="s1.4;p43.51">The refractive index of a material is defined as <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0306h-form.043"/> where <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0306h-form.044"/> is the speed of light in a vacuum, and <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0306h-form.045"/> is the speed of light within that medium. </s><s n="s2.4;p43.51">In order to determine the refractive indices of various gases the Helium-Neon laser was, once again, mounted upon the interferometer apparatus and a gas cell of length <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0306h-form.046"/> was placed in between the beam splitter (B) and the mirror M1. </s><s n="s3.4;p43.51">The cell, as shown in Figure 13, could be filled with the different gases that were stored within a gas bladder and releasing the appropriate valves. </s><s n="s4.4;p43.51">The length of the gas cell disregarding the length of glass either end was taken to be 40.57 mm and a pressure gauge was attached to the cell so the pressure could be determined at any given time. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0306h-pic.006"><head>Figure 13: Schematic of the gas cell and accompanying equipment used to find the refractive indices of different gases <hi rend="sup">[8]</hi></head></figure><p n="p44.51"><s n="s1.3;p44.51">When the gas cell is evacuated the laser light travels through the cell at <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0306h-form.047"/> with frequency <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0306h-form.048"/> and <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0306h-form.049"/> of <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0306h-form.050"/>. </s><s n="s2.3;p44.51">At this time, the cell length <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0306h-form.051"/> will hold <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0306h-form.052"/> wavelengths. </s><s n="s3.3;p44.51">The frequency of the laser light is directly associated with the energy of the photons produced by the laser<formula notation="" id="BAWE_0306h-form.053"/> and will remain constant at all times. </s></p><p n="p45.51"><s n="s1.2;p45.51">As a gas of refractive index <hi rend="italic">n</hi> is introduced into the cell at a steady rate, the speed with which the laser light propagates will vary as the pressure within the chamber changes. </s><s n="s2.2;p45.51">Using <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0306h-form.054"/>, and by equating <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0306h-form.055"/> here to that above we can show that : </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p46.51"><s n="s1.1;p46.51"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0306h-form.056"/> (9) </s></p><p n="p47.51"><s n="s1.3;p47.51">This shows that as the pressure in the chamber is increased to atmospheric pressure <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0306h-form.057"/> the wavelength of light in the gas cell <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0306h-form.058"/>) has been reduced by a factor of <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0306h-form.059"/>. </s><s n="s2.3;p47.51">As the wavelength during this time is effectively shorter, the length of the cell will hold <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0306h-form.060"/> more wavelengths of light, i.e. <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0306h-form.061"/><hi rend="sup">[8]</hi>. </s><s n="s3.3;p47.51">By equating <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0306h-form.062"/> when empty and during the pressure change and also taking into account that the laser passes through the gas cell twice (once towards M1 and again towards the beam splitter (B)) we get : </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p48.51"><s n="s1.1;p48.51"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0306h-form.063"/> (10)<hi rend="sup">[7]</hi> </s></p><p n="p49.51"><s n="s1.2;p49.51">The difference in wavelengths between the beam that reflects from M2 and the beam that passes through the gas cell causes a path difference, and hence we will see <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0306h-form.064"/> fringes as the gas is allowed into the chamber. </s><s n="s2.2;p49.51">Therefore, by counting the fringes that occur whilst the cell is being filled, we will be able to determine <hi rend="italic">n</hi> for various gases (<formula notation="" id="BAWE_0306h-form.065"/> results are displayed to show the values more clearly in standard form). </s></p><table id="BAWE_0306h-tab.002"><head>Figure 14: Results for <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0306h-form.066"/> , determined by counting the number of fringes <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0306h-form.067"/> for different gases, compared to theoretical values <hi rend="sup">[9 p.133]</hi></head><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p50.51"><s n="s1.2;p50.51">As the wavelength of the laser light in a vacuum and the length of the gas cell were quoted on the apparatus to a high degree of accuracy, we assumed negligible error in these measurements, and that the error originated from the counting of the fringes <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0306h-form.068"/>. </s><s n="s2.2;p50.51">We assumed each measurement followed Poisson statistics and the error was averaged over three repeats. </s></p><p n="p51.51"><s n="s1.3;p51.51">Most of the indices calculated were just within the boundary of experimental error with respect to the quoted values. </s><s n="s2.3;p51.51">The values were systematically higher than those expected, suggesting that we recorded a slower laser light speed within the cell. </s><s n="s3.3;p51.51">This could be because the value of <hi rend="italic">L</hi> was quoted as too small, or from simply counting too many fringes. </s></p></div2></div1></body><back><div1 type="bibliography"><head rend="bold">4. References</head><p>[1] MPhys Laboratory Online Guide: <seg type="URL" n="http://physweb.spec"/>.<name type="university"/>.ac.uk/teach/course_home/px369/ (15<hi rend="sup">th</hi> March 2005)</p><p>[2] F.A. Jenkins and H.E. White, "Fundamentals of Optics" <hi rend="bold">3</hi> (McGraw-Hill) 1957 </p><p>[3] R.S. Longhurst, "Geometrical and Physical Optics", 3rd Ed, Longman (London) 1973 </p><p>[4] R.W. Ditchburn, "Light", <hi rend="bold">2</hi> (John Wiley and Sons, Inc.) 1963</p><p>[5] The Michelson Interferometer: <seg type="URL" n="http://polaris.phys.ualberta.ca/info/Phys29x/Manual/6Michelson99.pdf"/> (20th March 2005)</p><p>[6] Interference:</p><p> <seg type="URL" n="http://www.abdn.ac.uk/physics/px2009/int.pdf"/></p><p>[7] Interferometry:</p><p> <seg type="URL" n="http://engphys.mcmaster.ca/~glen/3e3/3e3lab3.pdf"/> </p><p> (16th March 2005)</p><p>[8] Refractive Indices:</p><p> <seg type="URL" n="http://www.sussex.ac.uk/Units/physics/teaching/rcs/"/></p><p> FYlab/Refractive_gases.doc (2nd April 2005)</p><p>[9] G. W. C. Kaye and T. H. Laby, "Tables of Chemical and Physical Constants", <hi rend="bold">16</hi> (Longman) 1995</p></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
