<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_0306a" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>The Gamma ray is a high-energy form of electromagnetic radiation and often occurs as a product of radioactive decay.</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note/></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">2</p><p n="date">2003-12</p><p n="module title">Physics Skills</p><p n="module code">PX271</p><p n="genre family">Methodology recount</p><p n="discipline">Physics</p><p n="disciplinary group">PS</p><p n="grade">M</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">5506</p><p n="number of s-units">226</p><p n="number of p">94</p><p n="number of tables">5</p><p n="number of figures">9</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">99</p><p n="number of lists">3</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">14</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">24.4</p><p n="average s-units per p">2.4</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">f</p><p n="year of birth">1984</p><p n="first language">English</p><p n="education">UKA</p><p n="course">Mphys F303</p><p n="student ID">0306</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front/><body><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Introduction and Background Theory </head><p n="p1.94"><s n="s1.4;p1.94">The Gamma ray is a high-energy form of electromagnetic radiation and often occurs as a product of radioactive decay. </s><s n="s2.4;p1.94">This experiment uses a radioactive source that emits these rays, and other pieces of equipment to study the various properties that gamma rays possess. </s><s n="s3.4;p1.94">To begin with, we obtain a spectrum of the radiation from this particular source to study its features and explain them scientifically. </s><s n="s4.4;p1.94">Secondly, we scatter the gamma rays upon electrons to examine a common property known as the Compton Effect, and then finally observe the effect of absorptive materials upon these rays. </s></p><div2><head rend="bold">1. Gamma-Ray Spectra and Detector Characteristics</head><div3><head rend="bold">1. 1. Detecting and processing Gamma Rays</head><p n="p2.94"><s n="s1.1;p2.94">In order to obtain quantitative data of gamma rays and their energies we must use </s></p><p n="p3.94"><s n="s1.4;p3.94">various pieces of equipment to detect them, and then display the information we require in a suitable manner. </s><s n="s2.4;p3.94">The main piece of apparatus used to for detection will be a sodium iodide (NaI) scintillation counter. </s><s n="s3.4;p3.94">This makes use of one primary feature of gamma rays, known as the photoelectric effect, in order to change the rays into electrical information that we can manipulate with a computer[2]. </s><s n="s4.4;p3.94">A multi-channel analyser subsequently stores and processes this information ready for use. </s></p><p n="p4.94"><s n="s1.5;p4.94">The Scintillation Counter uses a NaI crystal and a photo-multiplier to convert any gamma rays that fall upon the crystal into voltage pulses. </s><s n="s2.5;p4.94">The photoelectric effect states that if a high-energy photon is incident on a certain material, it will eject a photoelectron from the surface of that material with the same energy as the photon that displaced it. </s><s n="s3.5;p4.94">In this case, the gamma ray photon ejects a photoelectron from the NaI crystal, which in turn emits a light photon from the crystal with energy proportional to that of the original gamma ray photon. </s><s n="s4.5;p4.94">These light photons are collected by the photo-multiplier, converted into electrons by the same principle, and are amplified into a voltage pulse. </s><s n="s5.5;p4.94">Therefore, for each gamma ray that strikes the crystal, a charged pulse will appear on the anode of the photo-multiplier, where the voltage of the pulse is proportional to the original energy of the gamma ray[3][6]. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0306a-pic.001"><head><hi rend="bold">Figure 1[4] A Sodium Iodide Scintillation Counter</hi> <hi rend="bold">used to detect and process gamma radiation</hi></head></figure><p n="p5.94"><s n="s1.7;p5.94">The Multi-Channel Pulse Height Analyser takes these voltage pulses and sorts them according to height (voltage) into one of 256 channels. </s><s n="s2.7;p5.94">The pulses are recorded as 'counts' in corresponding channels, and are later calibrated so that each voltage channel represents a given energy. </s><s n="s3.7;p5.94">The information is finally displayed on the computer monitor for extraction. </s><s n="s4.7;p5.94">So if data is recorded for a given time, the number of counts in a certain channel will then denote the number of gamma rays with that specific corresponding energy that have been detected in that time[7]. </s><s n="s5.7;p5.94">One consequence of this type of analyser is that it introduces what is known as a 'dead time' into the calculations. </s><s n="s6.7;p5.94">This is the time that the analyser cannot detect a count, as it is still processessing the previous one. </s><s n="s7.7;p5.94">The monitor therefore displays the real time, the actual time that counts can be detected as the 'live time', and the 'dead time' in which they cannot be, which is simply the live subtracted from the real. </s></p><p n="p6.94"><s n="s1.2;p6.94">This experiment uses a radioactive isotope of (Cs137) Caesium that emits gamma radiation of only one energy, equal to 662keV. Therefore, if we place the detection apparatus near this source we would expect to see a line from just one channel (that corresponds to this energy value) in which counts have been recorded. </s><s n="s2.2;p6.94">This is known as the 'photopeak' for the radioactive source and is shown in <hi rend="italic">Figure 2</hi>. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0306a-pic.002"><head><hi rend="bold"> Figure 2 Idealised photopeak expected from a</hi> <hi rend="bold"> monoenergetic source of gamma rays</hi></head></figure></div3><div3><head rend="bold">1. 2. Gamma-Ray Spectra and The Compton Effect </head><p n="p7.94"><s n="s1.5;p7.94">As described above, the scintillator uses the photoelectric effect to convert the energy of these incoming gamma rays into photoelectrons and processes these to give a signal, so it is important to remember that the actual spectra will really be an energy spectrum of these electrons that have received energy from the gamma rays. </s><s n="s2.5;p7.94">Therefore, unlike the idealisation shown in <hi rend="italic">Figure 2</hi>, the spectra we record may display many more features due to other physical processes that have caused absorption of these rays. </s><s n="s3.5;p7.94">Some of these features are effects of the second property of gamma rays, in that they undergo Compton scattering. </s><s n="s4.5;p7.94">In reference to the spectrum characteristics, the scattering occurs inside the detector crystal, and hence is a result of the equipment used. </s><s n="s5.5;p7.94">Later parts of the experiment will investigate this scattering property further but it is necessary to discuss the Compton Effect in order to understand the spectra we obtain. </s></p><p n="p8.94"><s n="s1.1;p8.94">In 1922 Arthur H. Compton experimented with high frequency rays by scattering them </s></p><p n="p9.94"><s n="s1.2;p9.94">upon electrons in a carbon target, and he observed that the wavelength of these scattered Rays was greater than that of those that were incident on the target [5]. </s><s n="s2.2;p9.94">This change in wavelength of the radiation as a function of the angle (<formula notation="" id="BAWE_0306a-form.001"/>) with which the rays were scattered through with respect to their incident path on the target was found to be: </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p10.94"><s n="s1.1;p10.94"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0306a-form.002"/><hi rend="bold">(1)[8]</hi> </s></p><p n="p11.94"><s n="s1.1;p11.94">where <hi rend="italic">me</hi> = the mass of the electron in the sample = 1.9 x 10 <hi rend="sup">-27</hi> kg </s></p><p n="p12.94"><s n="s1.1;p12.94"><hi rend="italic"> h</hi> = Planck's constant = 6.63 x 10 <hi rend="sup">-34</hi> Js </s></p><p n="p13.94"><s n="s1.1;p13.94"><hi rend="italic">c =</hi> the speed of light = 3 x 10 <hi rend="sup">-8</hi> ms <hi rend="sup">-1</hi> </s></p><p n="p14.94"><s n="s1.1;p14.94">By then referring to the Planck hypothesis, (<hi rend="italic">Equation 2</hi>) it could be shown that the energy of these was decreasing upon collision, and also changed with scattering angle <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0306a-form.003"/><hi rend="italic">(Equation 3).</hi> </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p15.94"><s n="s1.1;p15.94"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0306a-form.004"/><hi rend="bold">(2)</hi> </s></p><p n="p16.94"><s n="s1.1;p16.94">where <hi rend="italic">E</hi> is the energy of the radiation (J) </s></p><p n="p17.94"><s n="s1.1;p17.94">υ is the frequency of the radiation (Hz) </s></p><p n="p18.94"><s n="s1.1;p18.94">λ is the wavelength of the radiation (m) </s></p><p n="p19.94"><s n="s1.2;p19.94">If we consider this situation as demonstrated by Compton, and shown in <hi rend="italic">Figure 3</hi>, it is clear that as the incident ray collides with the electron, some of the initial energy of this ray (<hi rend="italic">E1</hi>) is transferred to the electron (<hi rend="italic">Ee</hi>), which then becomes known as the recoil electron. </s><s n="s2.2;p19.94">The final energy of the ray (<hi rend="italic">E2</hi>) is hence less than before, and in accordance with this, the final wavelength <hi rend="italic">λ2</hi> has increased from the initial <hi rend="italic">λ1</hi>. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0306a-fig.001"><head><hi rend="bold">Figure 3</hi><ref target="BAWE_0306a-endnote.001"/><hi rend="bold"> Demonstration of 'Compton Scattering' in which</hi> <hi rend="bold">radiation is incident on a stationary electron</hi><note place="end" id="BAWE_0306a-endnote.001"><p n="pn1.1"> Adapted from website theory.uwinnipeg.ca/physics/ quant/node4.html</p></note></head></figure><p n="p20.94"><s n="s1.2;p20.94">Combining <hi rend="italic">Equations 1</hi> <hi rend="italic">and 2</hi> we obtain the ratio of the energies of this photon before and after collision with the electron and hence the final energy <hi rend="italic">E2</hi>. </s><s n="s2.2;p20.94">It is this equation below that we that attempted to verify in the Compton Scattering section of the experiment[1] </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p21.94"><s n="s1.1;p21.94"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0306a-form.005"/><hi rend="bold"> (3)</hi> </s></p><p n="p22.94"><s n="s1.1;p22.94">In this equation the term "<hi rend="italic">mec2</hi>" represents the 'rest-mass energy' of the electron, </s></p><p n="p23.94"><s n="s1.1;p23.94">which by simple calculation can be found to be 511keV<ref target="BAWE_0306a-endnote.002"/>. </s></p><note place="end" id="BAWE_0306a-endnote.002"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">This value was taken from [12 <hi rend="bold">p302</hi>] The electron-volt (eV) is a unit of energy commonly used at the atomic scale. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">The eV value is determined by dividing the energy in Joules by the charge on an electron 1.6x10-19C. </s></p></note><p n="p24.94"><s n="s1.4;p24.94">Now we refer back to the case in which, upon detection, the gamma ray collides with a free electron inside then NaI crystal. </s><s n="s2.4;p24.94">The result of this is that some of the gamma ray's energy (<hi rend="italic">E1</hi>) is transferred to the electron by the Compton process, where this <hi rend="italic">Ee</hi> of the electron is equal to <hi rend="italic">E1 - E2.</hi> </s><s n="s3.4;p24.94">Now if the scattered gamma ray escapes the crystal only a fraction of the incident energy is present in the electron which will be detected by the computer. </s><s n="s4.4;p24.94">From <hi rend="italic">Equation 3</hi> it is clear that the amount of energy absorbed by the electron will also depend upon the angle with which it is struck by the gamma ray, and hence we see this wide range of energies that are detected, known as the Compton Plateau as in <hi rend="italic">Figure 4</hi>. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0306a-pic.003"><head><hi rend="bold">Figure 4</hi> [4]<hi rend="bold">Idealised spectrum showingCompton Features</hi></head></figure><p n="p25.94"><s n="s1.4;p25.94">Simple conservation laws tell us that the maximum possible energy (<hi rend="italic">Emax</hi>) that can have been delivered to the electron occurs at an angle of 180 <hi rend="sup">o</hi> and this is described as the Compton Edge[2]. </s><s n="s2.4;p25.94">In practice, the photopeak and Compton Edge appeared much less sharp due to the electrons emitted from the photo cathode with the flash of light. </s><s n="s3.4;p25.94">Each interaction will cause a statistical spread of the number of electrons emitted during this process of analysis, so that the spectrum features appear smeared. </s><s n="s4.4;p25.94">Taking into account all of these other sources that can distort the signal received by the analyser, the spectrum we expected would appear more like that in <hi rend="italic">Figure 5</hi>. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0306a-pic.004"><head><hi rend="bold">Figure 5[7]More realistic spectrum</hi> <hi rend="bold"> showing Compton Effects and 'smearing' introduced</hi> <hi rend="bold"> by the equipment</hi></head></figure><p n="p26.94"><s n="s1.1;p26.94">It was then possible to determine just how 'smeared' these effects were by calculating </s></p><p n="p27.94"><s n="s1.2;p27.94">two properties of the energy photopeak. </s><s n="s2.2;p27.94">These were known as the Energy Resolution '<hi rend="italic">RE</hi>' and the Relative efficiency of the detector 'ε'. </s></p></div3></div2><div2><head rend="bold">2. Compton Scattering </head><p n="p28.94"><s n="s1.2;p28.94">As well as investigating the energy of the scattered rays as described by <hi rend="italic">Equation 3</hi>, we also examined the scattering cross-section as it varied with angle. </s><s n="s2.2;p28.94">The Klein-Nishina Formula corrects for relativistic quantum mechanics to give a more exact angular distribution of Compton scattered gamma-rays[7]: </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p29.94"><s n="s1.1;p29.94"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0306a-form.006"/><hi rend="bold"> (4)[1] </hi> </s></p><p n="p30.94"><s n="s1.1;p30.94"><hi rend="italic">ro</hi> is the classical radius of the electron = 2.82 x 10 <hi rend="sup">-15</hi>m </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p31.94"><s n="s1.1;p31.94">also <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0306a-form.007"/><hi rend="bold">(5)</hi> </s></p><list type="simple"><item><hi rend="italic">N</hi> = number of photons incident on detector per unit time </item><item><hi rend="italic">n</hi> = number of scattering electrons in the scatterer in the path of the beam </item><item><hi rend="italic">I</hi> = incident flux of photons </item><item>ΔΩ = solid angle subtended by the counter at the scattering point</item></list><p n="p32.94"><s n="s1.1;p32.94">Therefore, to obtain the values for the cross section we needed to adapt our values of the count rate '<hi rend="italic">N</hi>' i.e. the number of photons detected per second, by taking measurements based on the geometry of the system. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">3. Absorption Spectroscopy</head><p n="p33.94"><s n="s1.6;p33.94">All types of radiation are absorbed by matter, but this absorption varies depending on the type of radiation and the material used to absorb it. </s><s n="s2.6;p33.94">Gamma radiation is very penetrating and will pass through many materials, but at the same time some photons will be absorbed and the intensity reduced. </s><s n="s3.6;p33.94">This absorption can occur in three ways. </s><s n="s4.6;p33.94">The first of these is photoelectric absorption, by which the photon gives all of its energy to an electron in the material causing it to escape, providing this energy is great enough to overcome the binding energy of the atom that contains it. </s><s n="s5.6;p33.94">Secondly, during Compton scattering, some gamma ray energy is transferred to the scattering electrons, and finally in pair production all the gamma energy is absorbed and produces an electron and a positron. </s><s n="s6.6;p33.94">In all of these processes the incident gamma ray loses energy on passing through the material and hence the intensity of the beam will be reduced. </s></p><p n="p34.94"><s n="s1.1;p34.94">It can be shown experimentally that if a beam of intensity <hi rend="italic">Io</hi> is incident on a slab of thickness <hi rend="italic">t</hi> (m), the intensity of the emerging beam <hi rend="italic">I</hi> will be governed by the following equation <hi rend="bold">[1]</hi>: </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p35.94"><s n="s1.1;p35.94"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0306a-form.008"/><hi rend="bold">(6)</hi> </s></p><p n="p36.94"><s n="s1.1;p36.94">where <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0306a-form.009"/> is the linear absorption coefficient in (m <hi rend="sup">-1</hi>) </s></p><p n="p37.94"><s n="s1.2;p37.94">This experiment used lead filters of varying thickness in order to test this equation. </s><s n="s2.2;p37.94">This was then repeated at different angles ie. photopeak energies, in order to find a relationship between <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0306a-form.010"/> and energy <hi rend="italic">E2</hi>. </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Experimental Details</head><p n="p38.94"><s n="s1.7;p38.94">Before any measurements could be taken it was necessary to calibrate the channels to correspond to energies to give the results meaning. </s><s n="s2.7;p38.94">The high voltage supply that powers the detector, must be set to 800V and switched on before any readings can be taken. </s><s n="s3.7;p38.94">We leave the detector to record a spectrum of the Caesium 137 (<formula notation="" id="BAWE_0306a-form.011"/>) source (that should resemble <hi rend="italic">Figure 5)</hi> and locate the photopeak. </s><s n="s4.7;p38.94">The monitor will display the live, real and dead time counters, and each 'count' will be recorded as a point on screen. </s><s n="s5.7;p38.94">We then place another radioactive source Americium 241 (<formula notation="" id="BAWE_0306a-form.012"/>) in front of the detector and once again leave the detector to record these counts on top of the previous spectrum. </s><s n="s6.7;p38.94">It should be clear that there are now two photopeaks, one corresponding to 662keV of the Caesium, and the other 57.5keV that we are told is the energy of the Americium 241 source. </s><s n="s7.7;p38.94">By setting the software to 'calibrate' and determining, as accurately as possible, the corresponding channel for each photopeak we assign each channel a given energy to take measurements from in later sections. </s></p><div2><head rend="bold">1. Gamma-Ray Spectra and Detector Characteristics</head><div3><head rend="bold">2. 1. 1. Poisson's Statistics </head><p n="p39.94"><s n="s1.2;p39.94">Radioactive decay is a random process, and hence as each count represents a single decay, the number of counts obtained in a set interval of time will display the statistics determined by the random process known as Poisson statistics. </s><s n="s2.2;p39.94">One application of Poisson's statistics is that the square root of the mean value of some readings <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0306a-form.013"/> should be equal to the standard deviation of those same set of readings <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0306a-form.014"/>. </s></p><p n="p40.94"><s n="s1.3;p40.94">In order to demonstrate this we must use the software to set up a region of interest that contains the full energy peak of the Caesium source. </s><s n="s2.3;p40.94">Then each time the detector is left to run the computer will show the total number or counts collected in this region over a given time. </s><s n="s3.3;p40.94">In this example the region of interest was set up and the software left for a real time of 15 seconds, 30 times, and the total number of counts in the photopeak was noted for each recording. </s></p></div3><div3><head rend="bold"> 2. 1. 2. Gamma Ray Spectra </head><p n="p41.94"><s n="s1.2;p41.94">The detector was left to record for roughly 5 minutes until a clear spectrum could be seen for the Caesium sample. </s><s n="s2.2;p41.94">This was saved and printed and the various features were labelled and explained scientifically. </s></p></div3><div3><head rend="bold"> 2. 1. 3. Detector Characteristics</head><p n="p42.94"><s n="s1.6;p42.94">For this same spectrum, three typical properties of the detector were examined. </s><s n="s2.6;p42.94">The first of these was the energy resolution of the photopeak '<hi rend="italic">R</hi>' where <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0306a-form.015"/>, <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0306a-form.016"/> is the full width at half maximum height (FWHM) and E is the peak = 662keV (see <hi rend="italic">Figure 6</hi>). </s><s n="s3.6;p42.94">As shown in <hi rend="italic">Figure 2</hi> we wanted the photopeak to be a single line, but the detector introduces this smearing effect. </s><s n="s4.6;p42.94">This resolution is an indication of that extent. </s><s n="s5.6;p42.94">A further indication of this was the relative efficiency of the detector that showed the fraction of the total flux that contributed to the photopeak, given by <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0306a-form.017"/>[1]. </s><s n="s6.6;p42.94">This was done by recording the total number of counts over this time and then setting up a region of interest, with errors, around the photopeak to see how many counts were contained within that area. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0306a-fig.002"><head><hi rend="bold">Figure 6 Exaggeration of the 'smeared'</hi> <hi rend="bold"> photopeak to show how the</hi> <hi rend="bold"> resolution <hi rend="italic">RE</hi> was found </hi></head></figure><p n="p43.94"><s n="s1.1;p43.94">Finally, the detector was left for roughly six minutes and from this the total number of counts were recorded and the dead time, to find the dead time per count for this given activity. </s></p></div3></div2><div2><head rend="bold"> 2. 2. Compton Scattering</head><div3><head rend="bold">2. 2. 1. Compton Energy as a function of angle</head><p n="p44.94"><s n="s1.6;p44.94">After a typical spectra had been obtained and appeared to show the correct features, we were able to test the Compton formula to verify the relationship between scattered energy and scattering angle. </s><s n="s2.6;p44.94">The iron rod, that acts as the scattering target, is placed in between the gamma ray source and the detector and the position of the detector was varied with the angle via the markings on the apparatus. </s><s n="s3.6;p44.94">This is displayed in <hi rend="italic">Figure 7</hi>. </s><s n="s4.6;p44.94">At each of these angles spectra were recorded and we then determined, with errors, the energy peak of the scattered rays (<hi rend="italic">E2</hi>) for each one. </s><s n="s5.6;p44.94">It was impractical to use angles less than 20 <hi rend="sup">o</hi> as the beam would saturate the detector and the results would be unreliable. </s><s n="s6.6;p44.94">The values of (<formula notation="" id="BAWE_0306a-form.018"/>) used were <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0306a-form.019"/> at 5 <hi rend="sup">o</hi> intervals, and these results were later compared to the theoretical values we would expect for this source at the same angles. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0306a-pic.005"><head><hi rend="bold">Figure 7Diagram of Compton Scattering equipment</hi> <hi rend="bold">in which scattering angle could be varied</hi></head></figure></div3><div3><head rend="bold"> 2. 2. 2. Klein-Nishina Cross-section</head><p n="p45.94"><s n="s1.8;p45.94">Here, the iron rod target was replaced by the large sphere in order that we could find the number of scattering electrons '<hi rend="italic">n</hi>' in this sample for later calculations. </s><s n="s2.8;p45.94">As above we, once again, varied the detector with angle and recorded spectra at a range of angles <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0306a-form.020"/> at 10 <hi rend="sup">o</hi> intervals, each for 5 minutes of real time. </s><s n="s3.8;p45.94">The sphere was then removed and a further set of readings taken at each angle to act as the background count for each <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0306a-form.021"/>. </s><s n="s4.8;p45.94">All the spectra were saved and suitable regions of interest set up around the photopeak to show the integrated number of counts in this region. </s><s n="s5.8;p45.94">The background integrated counts were subtracted from the scattered counts for these 8 angles, and these values were modified to give the cross-section values. </s><s n="s6.8;p45.94">To obtain these values we needed to find (i) the number of scattering electrons '<hi rend="italic">n</hi>', (ii) unit solid angle subtended by the detector '<formula notation="" id="BAWE_0306a-form.022"/>' and (iii) the gamma ray flux at the sample '<hi rend="italic">I</hi>', as shown in <hi rend="italic">Equation 7</hi>. </s><s n="s7.8;p45.94">In order to do this, we recorded the mass '<hi rend="italic">m</hi>' and radius '<hi rend="italic">R</hi>' of the scattering sphere, noted the activity of the sample at the source, the distance '<hi rend="italic">d</hi>' between the source and the scatterer, and the width of the aperture of the detector '<hi rend="italic">2r</hi>'. </s><s n="s8.8;p45.94">These are shown in <hi rend="italic">Figure 8</hi>. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0306a-pic.006"><head><hi rend="bold"> Figure 8 Diagram of Compton</hi> <hi rend="bold"> equipment to show</hi> <hi rend="bold"> measurements that were</hi> <hi rend="bold"> taken for corrections </hi></head></figure></div3></div2><div2><head rend="bold"> 2. 3. Absorption Spectroscopy </head><div3><head rend="bold"> 2. 3. 1. Gamma-Ray Absorption Coefficients </head><p n="p46.94"><s n="s1.8;p46.94">For this section we were given a table of theoretical values for absorption coefficients and we wished to verify those that corresponded to scattered energies in the range <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0306a-form.023"/>. </s><s n="s2.8;p46.94">In order to test this relationship we selected four angles that would show this energy range as related by <hi rend="italic">Equation 3</hi>. </s><s n="s3.8;p46.94">Hence, we chose <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0306a-form.024"/>. </s><s n="s4.8;p46.94">For each of these four angles we recorded spectra for five real minutes, using the large rod as a scatterer and with 0, 1, 2, 3, and 4 sheets of lead in front of the detector. </s><s n="s5.8;p46.94">The values for <hi rend="italic">Io</hi> were those when no leads sheets were blocking the beam. </s><s n="s6.8;p46.94">The thickness of the lead sheets was measured using a micrometer in three different places and an average taken for the value of '<hi rend="italic">t</hi>' to reduce errors as the lead surfaces were quite uneven. </s><s n="s7.8;p46.94">At each <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0306a-form.025"/> a region of interest set up around the photopeak and these channels were noted to ensure the same area was observed for each attenuation, and the total number of counts recorded at each reading. </s><s n="s8.8;p46.94">These were then manipulated to fit <hi rend="italic">Equation 6</hi> and test the attenuation relationship of gamma rays. </s></p></div3><div3><head rend="bold">2. 3. 2. Attenuation Coefficients as a function of Energy </head><p n="p47.94"><s n="s1.2;p47.94">The data obtained above was used to determine values of μ at each angle ie. energy. </s><s n="s2.2;p47.94">These were then separately plotted to show the absorption coefficient as a function of energy and to find a relationship between the two. </s></p></div3></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">3. Experimental Results </head><div2><head rend="bold">1. Gamma-Ray Spectra and Detector Characteristics</head><div3><head rend="bold">3. 1. 1. Poisson's Statistics </head><p n="p48.94"><s n="s1.1;p48.94">The photopeak was taken to be in the region of interest between channels 1219 and </s></p><p n="p49.94"><s n="s1.3;p49.94">1585 that correspond to energy values of <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0306a-form.026"/> around the 662keV peak. </s><s n="s2.3;p49.94">The readings below are the number of counts found in this region after 15 seconds of real time, repeated 30 times. </s><s n="s3.3;p49.94">This was to show a key property of Poission's statistics in that the standard deviation of a set of results <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0306a-form.027"/> where <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0306a-form.028"/> is the mean of the set of readings. </s></p><table id="BAWE_0306a-tab.001"><head rend="bold">Table 1Readings taken to illustrate Poisson's statistics</head><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p50.94"><s n="s1.3;p50.94">For these readings we get <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0306a-form.029"/> and hence <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0306a-form.030"/>. </s><s n="s2.3;p50.94">We then analysed the values using excel to get a value of <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0306a-form.031"/> which is almost a 50% error between this and <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0306a-form.032"/>! </s><s n="s3.3;p50.94">Instead, by taking away the 5 most extreme values we reduced <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0306a-form.033"/> to 2110.4, so <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0306a-form.034"/> and also <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0306a-form.035"/> was now 45.7 giving much better agreement. </s></p></div3><div3><head rend="bold">3. 1. 2. Gamma Ray Spectra</head><p n="p51.94"><s n="s1.3;p51.94">After 5 minutes the spectra shown in <hi rend="italic">Figure 9</hi> was obtained. </s><s n="s2.3;p51.94">The cursor was moved to the positions labelled and values for the various features were shown on screen. </s><s n="s3.3;p51.94">Errors were estimated and these features shown were then compared with their theoretical positions. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0306a-fig.003"><head><hi rend="bold">Figure 9Copy of the Spectrum obtained by</hi> <hi rend="bold">the NaI detector after 5 minutes</hi></head></figure><p n="p52.94"><s n="s1.1;p52.94"><hi rend="italic">A (photopeak) = 662keV</hi> (given). </s></p><p n="p53.94"><s n="s1.1;p53.94">As the Compton Edge was more drastically smeared two ends of it were considered to give <hi rend="italic">B = 439.2 keV,</hi> and <hi rend="italic">B' = 488.0 keV</hi> and so an average value for the Compton edge of <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0306a-form.036"/>. </s></p><p n="p54.94"><s n="s1.1;p54.94"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0306a-form.037"/> </s></p><p n="p55.94"><s n="s1.1;p55.94"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0306a-form.038"/> </s></p></div3><div3><head rend="bold">3. 1. 3. Detector Characteristics</head><p n="p56.94"><s n="s1.4;p56.94">For this same spectrum, the cursor was placed at different regions in the photopeak to determine the features of the equipment '<hi rend="italic">RE</hi>' the energy resolution and the relative efficiency. </s><s n="s2.4;p56.94">Half maximum height was estimated and <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0306a-form.039"/> was taken to be <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0306a-form.040"/>. </s><s n="s3.4;p56.94">Therefore <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0306a-form.041"/>. </s><s n="s4.4;p56.94">If we assume the same percentage error in <hi rend="italic">RE</hi> as in <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0306a-form.042"/> we get an energy resolution percentage of <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0306a-form.043"/>. </s></p><p n="p57.94"><s n="s1.3;p57.94">Then for the relative efficiency we used the number of counts to give <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0306a-form.044"/>, an efficiency of roughly 25%. </s><s n="s2.3;p57.94">We estimated an error of <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0306a-form.045"/> counts in the photopeak and so roughly around 1% of the efficiency. </s><s n="s3.3;p57.94">Consequently, by rounding, we found <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0306a-form.046"/>. </s></p><p n="p58.94"><s n="s1.2;p58.94">For a spectrum of roughly 6 minutes long we recorded 270532 counts in total. </s><s n="s2.2;p58.94">The displays showed: </s></p><list type="simple"><item rend="bold">REAL 5:59.85 s</item><item rend="bold">LIVE 5:55.59 s</item><item><hi rend="bold">DEAD</hi> <hi rend="bold">4.26 s</hi></item></list><p n="p59.94"><s n="s1.2;p59.94">And so for an activity of 170 counts per second (as shown on equipment) we see a dead time of <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0306a-form.047"/>. </s><s n="s2.2;p59.94">Hence for each count there is a delay of this number of seconds before the next count can be processed. </s></p></div3></div2><div2><head rend="bold">3. 2. Compton Scattering </head><div3><head rend="bold">3. 2. 1. Compton Energy as a function of angle </head><p n="p60.94"><s n="s1.2;p60.94">We determined the theoretical values from <hi rend="italic">Equation 3</hi> and compared these with the position of the energy peaks at each angle. </s><s n="s2.2;p60.94">We estimate an error of 5keV each side of the photopeak due to smearing. </s></p><table id="BAWE_0306a-tab.002"><head><hi rend="bold">Table 2Readings and theoretical values to show</hi> <hi rend="bold">scattered energy as a function of angle</hi></head><row><cell/></row></table></div3><div3><head rend="bold">3. 2. 2. Klein-Nishina Cross-section</head><p n="p61.94"><s n="s1.7;p61.94">After recording the integrated and background counts at each angle we were able to correct for background radiation by subtracting the two values. </s><s n="s2.7;p61.94">These background corrected counts are shown in <hi rend="italic">Table 3.</hi> </s><s n="s3.7;p61.94">It was then necessary to take into account the absolute detector photopeak efficiency <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0306a-form.048"/> as it varied with energy. </s><s n="s4.7;p61.94">For example, a value of <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0306a-form.049"/> means that for every 10 counts the detector only registers as 1, so all of the background-corrected counts needed to be divided by the correct <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0306a-form.050"/> value to account for this. </s><s n="s5.7;p61.94">We were given that for NaI detectors <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0306a-form.051"/> and that for <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0306a-form.052"/>, <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0306a-form.053"/> where '<hi rend="italic">a'</hi> is a proportionality constant. </s><s n="s6.7;p61.94">This constant was found by substituting in these values to give <hi rend="italic">a</hi> = 577.0. </s><s n="s7.7;p61.94">By inverting <hi rend="italic">Equation 3</hi> we determined the theoretical energy values for each <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0306a-form.054"/> and hence the corresponding detector photopeak efficiency <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0306a-form.055"/>, and then finally divided the background corrected counts by the corresponding <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0306a-form.056"/> values for the fully corrected counts. </s></p><p n="p62.94"><s n="s1.1;p62.94">Now to convert these counts to Klein Nishina cross-section we refer back to: </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p63.94"><s n="s1.1;p63.94"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0306a-form.057"/><hi rend="bold">(5)</hi> </s></p><list type="simple"><item><hi rend="italic">N</hi> = number of photons incident on detector per unit time </item><item><hi rend="italic">n</hi> = number of scattering electrons in the scatterer in the path of the beam </item><item><hi rend="italic">I</hi> = incident flux of photons </item><item>ΔΩ = solid angle subtended by the counter at the scattering point</item></list><p rend="ordered" n="p64.94"><s n="s1.1;p64.94">'n', the number of electrons by finding the number of moles and atoms in that given </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p65.94"><s n="s1.5;p65.94">mass via some chemistry. </s><s n="s2.5;p65.94">The mass of the iron sample was <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0306a-form.058"/> due to discrepancies in the spherical shape. </s><s n="s3.5;p65.94">Using <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0306a-form.059"/> we know one mole is 56g and hence we have 0.502mol in this sample. </s><s n="s4.5;p65.94">We can find the number of atoms by multiplying by Avagadro's constant 6.023 x 10 <hi rend="sup">23</hi>[12,<hi rend="bold">p.416</hi>], and the number of electrons by then multiplying by 26 from <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0306a-form.060"/>. </s><s n="s5.5;p65.94">By carrying the same percentage error as in the mass measurement we determine: </s></p><p n="p66.94"><s n="s1.1;p66.94"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0306a-form.061"/> electrons (an error of 7.12%) </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p67.94"><s n="s1.3;p67.94">'I', the flux at the centre of the scatterer as <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0306a-form.062"/> where <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0306a-form.063"/> in <hi rend="italic">Figure 8.</hi> </s><s n="s2.3;p67.94">Activity at sample quoted at 3.7 x 10 <hi rend="sup">8</hi> disintegrations per second on apparatus, <hi rend="italic">x</hi> given as 75mm [Labscript], <hi rend="italic">d</hi> measured at <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0306a-form.064"/>, <hi rend="italic">R</hi> measured at <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0306a-form.065"/>. </s><s n="s3.3;p67.94">Hence <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0306a-form.066"/>, an error of 1.44% and so an error of 2.88% in z <hi rend="sup">2</hi> and in I. </s></p><p n="p68.94"><s n="s1.1;p68.94"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0306a-form.067"/>. </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p69.94"><s n="s1.3;p69.94">unit solid angle using <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0306a-form.068"/>. </s><s n="s2.3;p69.94"><hi rend="italic">R</hi> is quoted above and the aperture of the detector <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0306a-form.069"/>. </s><s n="s3.3;p69.94">Adding percentage errors in these two measurements gives </s></p><p n="p70.94"><s n="s1.1;p70.94"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0306a-form.070"/> </s></p><p n="p71.94"><s n="s1.3;p71.94">We then divide the <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0306a-form.071"/> corrected count rate by <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0306a-form.072"/>. </s><s n="s2.3;p71.94">Summing all these percentage errors we get 16.85% error introduced when converting counts in cross section values. </s><s n="s3.3;p71.94">Also, assuming a 5% error in each of the primary and background corrected counts we can add error bars of 26.85% to the cross-section graph. </s></p><table id="BAWE_0306a-tab.003"><head rend="bold">Table 3Corrected readings taken to determine Klein Nishina Cross-Section</head><row><cell/></row></table></div3></div2><div2><head rend="bold">3. 3. Absorption Spectroscopy </head><div3><head rend="bold">3. 3. 1. Gamma-Ray Absorption Coefficients</head><p n="p72.94"><s n="s1.1;p72.94">By manipulating <hi rend="italic">Equation 6</hi> we can see that: </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p73.94"><s n="s1.1;p73.94"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0306a-form.073"/><hi rend="bold">(6b)</hi> </s></p><p n="p74.94"><s n="s1.4;p74.94">and therefore if we plot a graph of <hi rend="italic"> -Ln(I/Io)</hi> against <hi rend="italic">t</hi> the gradient will give us a value for the absorption coefficient. </s><s n="s2.4;p74.94">Once again, discrepancies in finding the photopeak lead us to an error of roughly <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0306a-form.074"/> in the number of counts. </s><s n="s3.4;p74.94">The errors in <hi rend="italic">t</hi> were found by taking the greatest difference between the average of the three values. </s><s n="s4.4;p74.94">The errors in <hi rend="italic">I/Io</hi> were simply the sums of the percentage errors hence <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0306a-form.075"/> and this was carried forward in the logarithm, also. </s></p><table id="BAWE_0306a-tab.004"><head><hi rend="bold">Table 4</hi> <hi rend="bold">Readings taken at first three angles to</hi> <hi rend="bold">demonstrate absorption coefficients</hi></head><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p75.94"><s n="s1.3;p75.94">It was impossible to obtain any reliable results for <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0306a-form.076"/> as the photopeak was so smeared that the peak was inconclusive. </s><s n="s2.3;p75.94">This would have left us with only three values to determine the correlation between the absorption coefficient and energy, hence we took further readings at an angle of 20 <hi rend="sup">o</hi> as angles lower than this caused saturation of the detector. </s><s n="s3.3;p75.94">For the same reason, the readings were only taken for one and a half minutes of live time but we were still able to find a value for μ at this energy. </s></p><p n="p76.94"><s n="s1.2;p76.94">An example graph for <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0306a-form.077"/> to show how <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0306a-form.078"/> was found is shown below. </s><s n="s2.2;p76.94">Using the errors bars we found the greatest possible difference in the gradient and hence the error in the coefficient values. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0306a-fig.004"><head><hi rend="bold">Figure 10Graph to illustrate how absorption coefficients</hi> <hi rend="bold">were found by manipulating <hi rend="italic">Equation 6</hi></hi></head></figure></div3><div3><head rend="bold">3. 3. 2. Attenuation Coefficients as a function of Energy </head><p n="p77.94"><s n="s1.3;p77.94">The theoretical values for the absorption coefficient as a function of energy were plotted, and then the values obtained above were used to compare these values in the energy range <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0306a-form.079"/>. </s><s n="s2.3;p77.94">From these graphs we attempted to find the type of relation between the two properties. </s><s n="s3.3;p77.94">Once again we assume an error of <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0306a-form.080"/> in finding the photopeak and used these values, shown in <hi rend="italic">Table 5.</hi> </s></p><table id="BAWE_0306a-tab.005"><head><hi rend="bold">Table 5Summary of results obtained above and used to determine a relation</hi> <hi rend="bold">between the absorption coefficient μ and the scattered energy <hi rend="italic">E2</hi></hi></head><row><cell/></row></table></div3></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">4. Discussion</head><div2><head rend="bold">4. 1. Gamma-Ray Spectra and Detector Characteristics</head><p n="p78.94"><s n="s1.1;p78.94">In order to test that gamma decay was a random radioactive process that obeyed </s></p><p n="p79.94"><s n="s1.4;p79.94">Poisson's statistics we wished to show that <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0306a-form.081"/>; square root of the average is equal to the standard deviation of a set of readings. </s><s n="s2.4;p79.94">We managed to obtain <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0306a-form.082"/> and b.fo but only if we ignored the most extreme readings. </s><s n="s3.4;p79.94">This proves that Poisson's statistics are obeyed but that there were other errors to be considered such as human timing, computer analysis in recording counts, that would be improved if more readings were made for longer and. </s><s n="s4.4;p79.94">Also, if we refer to <hi rend="italic">Figure 11</hi> we can see that it takes a lot of readings for the average to fully converge to a given value and hence more readings will be more accurate. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0306a-fig.005"><head><hi rend="bold">Figure 11Graph to illustrate the convergence</hi> <hi rend="bold">of the mean of a set of values </hi><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0306a-form.083"/></head></figure><p n="p80.94"><s n="s1.3;p80.94">The experimental spectrum and its features as shown in <hi rend="italic">Figure 9</hi> agreed well with the expectations of Figure 5 with the full energy peak, Compton plateau and Compton Edge all clearly visible. </s><s n="s2.3;p80.94">The theoretical <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0306a-form.084"/> for the Compton Edge was to be 477.7keV using the formula below [2]. </s><s n="s3.3;p80.94">From the spectrum we determined <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0306a-form.085"/> proving to be well within the boundaries introduced by the smearing effect of the detector. </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p81.94"><s n="s1.1;p81.94"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0306a-form.086"/><hi rend="bold"> (7)</hi> </s></p><p n="p82.94"><s n="s1.2;p82.94">We also expected to see a 'backscatter peak' at roughly 200keV, caused by gamma rays that have interacted with the materials that surround the detector by Compton scattering also. </s><s n="s2.2;p82.94">This <hi rend="italic">Ebackscatter</hi> for gamma rays of 662keV, found when <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0306a-form.087"/> can be found more precisely from the formula given below </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p83.94"><s n="s1.1;p83.94"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0306a-form.088"/><hi rend="bold">(8)</hi> </s></p><p n="p84.94"><s n="s1.1;p84.94">which gives <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0306a-form.089"/> of <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0306a-form.090"/>. </s></p><p n="p85.94"><s n="s1.2;p85.94">From the spectrum we found this energy as <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0306a-form.091"/>, showing that the experimental peak lies just outside of the theoretical value according to estimated errors. </s><s n="s2.2;p85.94">The position is very nearly correct but shifted slightly to a higher energy which is probably due to the fact that some photons are scattering from materials between <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0306a-form.092"/> and hence moving the peak. </s></p><p n="p86.94"><s n="s1.1;p86.94">Also found, as shown as feature <hi rend="italic">D</hi> in <hi rend="italic">Figure 10</hi> is a peak at an energy of <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0306a-form.093"/> which is most possibly an X-Ray escape peak that arises from photo-electric absorbtion in the shielding materials and are typically less than 100keV. [2][11] </s></p><p n="p87.94"><s n="s1.5;p87.94">Other features observed from this spectrum include the energy resolution <hi rend="italic">RE</hi> that shows the extent to which the photopeak has deviated from a single valued straight line of 662 keV and was found at <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0306a-form.094"/> so the peak is quite easily resolvable for this spectrum. </s><s n="s2.5;p87.94">However, at larger scattering angles the photopeak became much flatter and wider as the detector adds a much larger error. </s><s n="s3.5;p87.94">Also, the relative detector efficiency analyses the counts so <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0306a-form.095"/> accounts for background radiation and other features showing that only a quarter of all counts appear as the photopeak showing just how prominent the other features of the spectra are. </s><s n="s4.5;p87.94">Finally, the dead time for 6 minutes was of quite small proportion at 1.57 x 10 <hi rend="sup">-5</hi> counts/second but this may play a much bigger role at larger counts. </s><s n="s5.5;p87.94">This could be accounted for as lost time and the results monitored, but if it remains constant then the proportions could still be reliable enough. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">2. Compton Scattering </head><p n="p88.94"><s n="s1.1;p88.94">To verify the Compton Energy formula as given by <hi rend="italic">Equation 3</hi> we plotted our </s></p><p n="p89.94"><s n="s1.4;p89.94">experimental values with the theoretical values as determined by this equation, as shown in <hi rend="italic">Figure 12</hi>. </s><s n="s2.4;p89.94">From this we see an almost perfect agreement in terms of both shape and value, for scattered energy as a function of angle. </s><s n="s3.4;p89.94">All results fit within error bars of <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0306a-form.096"/>, except the first value of 25o. </s><s n="s4.4;p89.94">This may be due to some saturation of the detector at the low angle that will pick up radiation from the straight-through beam. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0306a-fig.006"><head><hi rend="bold">Figure 12Comparison of measured values for Compton Energy (E2)</hi><hi rend="bold">as a function of angle (</hi><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0306a-form.097"/><hi rend="bold">), with those predicted by <hi rend="italic">Equation 3</hi></hi></head></figure><p n="p90.94"><s n="s1.1;p90.94">Similarly, for the Klein-Nishina cross-section graph (<hi rend="italic">Figure 19</hi>) we see the correct shape and order of magnitude of the measured values compared to theoretical values as given by <hi rend="italic">Equation 4</hi>, but some of the values after 70 <hi rend="sup">o</hi> scattering angles seem to settle near 2x10 <hi rend="sup">-30</hi> as the photopeaks become much flatter and undeterminable. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0306a-fig.007"><head><hi rend="bold">Figure 13Comparison of measured Klein-Nishina Cross-section (</hi><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0306a-form.098"/> ) <hi rend="bold">values as a function of angle (</hi><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0306a-form.099"/><hi rend="bold">), with those predicted by <hi rend="italic">Equation 4 </hi></hi></head></figure></div2><div2><head rend="bold">4. 3. Absorption Spectroscopy </head><p n="p91.94"><s n="s1.1;p91.94">Firstly, the theoretical values of absorption coefficients were plotted to determine some kind of relation between this and the energy they were measured at to give <hi rend="italic">Figure 14</hi>, which showed different kinds of correlation at high and low energy values. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0306a-fig.008"><head rend="bold">Figure 14Graph to show theoretical attenuation coefficient values and experimental range </head></figure><p n="p92.94"><s n="s1.3;p92.94">We then looked more closely in the range of the energy values that corresponded to the angles used in the measurements and, expecting an exponential relation from <hi rend="italic">Figure 14</hi>, plotted to natural log of coefficients against energy to give a straight line as in <hi rend="italic">Figure 15</hi>. </s><s n="s2.3;p92.94">All values fit within experimental errors but the main problem with this argument is that there are only 4 points, and the extra point determined early at 20 <hi rend="sup">o</hi> only made a minor improvement on this. </s><s n="s3.3;p92.94">For these values it would be fair to assume that Ln(μ) = -1.71 Ln(E <hi rend="sub">2</hi>) + 15.851 and hence the amount of absorption that occurs in a material will depend exponentially upon the energy of the rays used. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0306a-fig.009"><head><hi rend="bold">Figure 15Graph to determine the exponential relation</hi> <hi rend="bold">between absorption coefficient µ and scattered energy <hi rend="italic">E2</hi></hi></head></figure></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Conclusions </head><p n="p93.94"><s n="s1.2;p93.94">This experiment proved well the statistical nature of radioactive decay, and Poisons statistics demonstrated that the error in a reading could be given by its square root and that results would improve in accuracy if left for longer and more data recorded. </s><s n="s2.2;p93.94">The spectrum obtained by the detector fitted well to theoretical predictions as did its features, and the characteristics of the detector were able to tell us limitations in the method so that we could account for them, e.g. with the absolute detector efficiency η, energy resolution <hi rend="italic">RE</hi> and photopeak efficiency ε. </s></p><p n="p94.94"><s n="s1.5;p94.94">Both the Compton energy and the Cross-section as a function of angle were in good agreement with theory within experimental error, but various aspects of geometry could be improved. </s><s n="s2.5;p94.94">The various measurements and corrections that needed to be made added a great deal of error into some values. </s><s n="s3.5;p94.94">Also, determining the photopeak and also the background radiation was always quite difficult due to the operation of the detector as explained in the primary sections, so a more efficient detector would always be beneficial. </s><s n="s4.5;p94.94">Finally, the attenuation coefficients were found successfully and also agreed well with data but needed many more evenly spread readings in order to confidently predict a relation with scattered energy, as four points could agree with a many theories. </s><s n="s5.5;p94.94">Overall, further and longer readings would help to confirm many of the results found here but this experiment was very useful in statistically verifying the various properties possessed by gamma rays. </s></p></div1></body><back/></text></TEI.2>
