<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_0311i" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Superstructural Units in Lithium Borate Glasses</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">The document has a title page which contains:
document title
title part</note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">deleted: footer: student name, page numbers, assignment title</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">4</p><p n="date">2006-03</p><p n="module title">Project</p><p n="module code">PX402</p><p n="genre family">Research report</p><p n="discipline">Physics</p><p n="disciplinary group">PS</p><p n="grade">D</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">8466</p><p n="number of s-units">358</p><p n="number of p">102</p><p n="number of tables">8</p><p n="number of figures">15</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">16</p><p n="number of lists">0</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">7</p><p n="abstract present">abstract present</p><p n="average words per s-unit">23.6</p><p n="average s-units per p">3.5</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">m</p><p n="year of birth">1984</p><p n="first language">English</p><p n="education">UKA</p><p n="course">MPhys</p><p n="student ID">0311</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><docTitle><titlePart rend="underlined bold">Superstructural Units in Lithium Borate Glasses</titlePart></docTitle><titlePart><name type="student ID"/></titlePart><titlePart rend="italic">Department of Physics, University of <name type="university"/>, <name type="other"/> March 2006</titlePart></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="abstract"><head>Abstract</head><p n="p1.102"><s n="s1.7;p1.102">Ten glasses of nominal composition <hi rend="italic">x</hi>Li <hi rend="sub">2</hi>O·(100-<hi rend="italic">x</hi>)B <hi rend="sub">2</hi>O <hi rend="sub">3</hi> were prepared over the range <hi rend="italic">x</hi> = 0 to 40 mol%. </s><s n="s2.7;p1.102">A boron-11 NMR investigation has provided the fraction of 4-coordinated boron in the samples and this is consistent with previous studies. </s><s n="s3.7;p1.102">Raman spectra showed the intermediate range order associated with this type of binary borate glass. </s><s n="s4.7;p1.102">Superstructural units were assigned to the Raman peaks and this provided the fraction of 4-coordinated boron in the samples. </s><s n="s5.7;p1.102">The fraction of 4-coordinated boron given by Raman spectroscopy was compared to that given by NMR spectroscopy and a correlation of N4 <hi rend="sub">Raman</hi> = 0.87 (±0.18) N4 <hi rend="sub">NMR</hi> + 0.035 (± 0.056) was found. </s><s n="s6.7;p1.102">Six glasses of nominal composition <hi rend="italic">x</hi>CoO·(20-<hi rend="italic">x</hi>)Li <hi rend="sub">2</hi>O·80B <hi rend="sub">2</hi>O <hi rend="sub">3</hi> were prepared over the range <hi rend="italic">x</hi> = 0.1 to 5 mol%. </s><s n="s7.7;p1.102">It is shown that accurate determination of N4 fraction in glasses from boron-11 NMR spectra is unattainable for samples containing 2 mol% cobalt oxide or greater. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="bold">I.</hi> Introduction</head><p n="p2.102"><s n="s1.4;p2.102">Borate glasses have been well studied over the past decade and there has been much research into their structure and spectra. </s><s n="s2.4;p2.102">This interest is partly because of the anomalous behaviour of the glass in that it forms superstructural units: well defined arrangements of the basic BO <hi rend="sub">3</hi> and BO <hi rend="sub">4</hi> structures (Fig. </s><s n="s3.4;p2.102">1) [1]. </s><s n="s4.4;p2.102">BO <hi rend="sub">3</hi> forms a planar triangle whereas BO <hi rend="sub">4</hi> has a tetrahedral arrangement of oxygen around the boron atom. </s></p><p n="p3.102"><s n="s1.3;p3.102">Borates participate in the formation of borosilicate glasses that are used to immobilise high level nuclear waste for long-term storage. </s><s n="s2.3;p3.102">The existence of superstructural units in these glasses could have important consequences on the final structure of the nuclear waste glass, so it is worthwhile investigating the superstructural groups of simpler binary borate glasses. </s><s n="s3.3;p3.102">Evidence for the existence of the intermediate range order in borates, which does not occur in other glasses, are the sharp lines witnessed in Raman spectra corresponding to the breathing mode of the boroxol, and triborate, groups [2,3]. </s></p><p n="p4.102"><s n="s1.5;p4.102">Pure B <hi rend="sub">2</hi>O <hi rend="sub">3</hi> forms a glass by itself and forms binary borates with many oxides. </s><s n="s2.5;p4.102">While pure B <hi rend="sub">2</hi>O <hi rend="sub">3</hi> only consists of 3-coordinated 'B3' boron at standard pressure, the addition of cations makes boron structures containing 'B4' possible. </s><s n="s3.5;p4.102">This is basically because it is more energetically favourable to form BO <hi rend="sub">4</hi> tetrahedra than break B-O-B bridges and leave a non-bridging oxygen. </s><s n="s4.5;p4.102">This is discussed in detail by Wright, Vedishcheva and Shakhmatkin [1]. </s><s n="s5.5;p4.102">This special behaviour gives borate glasses the ability to form superstructural units, some of which are shown in figure 1. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0311i-pic.001"><head><hi rend="bold">]Figure 1.</hi> A selection of superstructural units composing of boron (● ) and bridging oxygens (○ )(a) boroxol ring, B <hi rend="sub">3</hi> O <hi rend="sub">6</hi> ; (b) triborate, B <hi rend="sub">3</hi> O <hi rend="sub">7</hi> ; (c) di-triborate, B <hi rend="sub">3</hi> O <hi rend="sub">8</hi> ; (d) pentaborate, B <hi rend="sub">5</hi> O <hi rend="sub">10</hi> ; (e) diborate, B <hi rend="sub">4</hi> O <hi rend="sub">9</hi></head></figure><p n="p5.102"><s n="s1.1;p5.102">An interesting parameter of borate glasses is the N4 fraction, which is the amount of 4-coordinated boron compared to the total amount of boron: </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p6.102"><s n="s1.1;p6.102"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0311i-form.001"/> (1) </s></p><p n="p7.102"><s n="s1.4;p7.102">Hence, pure B <hi rend="sub">2</hi>O <hi rend="sub">3</hi> has an N4 fraction of zero and a hypothetical borate glass consisting of nothing but diborate units would have an N4 fraction of 50%. </s><s n="s2.4;p7.102">The proportion of 4-coordinated boron is detectable by, amongst other means, Raman spectroscopy and Nuclear Magnetic Resonance (NMR) spectroscopy. </s><s n="s3.4;p7.102">The most extensive study on lithium borates was performed by Jellison, Feller and Bray in 1978 [4]. </s><s n="s4.4;p7.102">They showed the N4 fraction peaking at around 40 mol% Li <hi rend="sub">2</hi>O with a proportion of approximately 0.45 B4 to 0.55 B3. </s></p><p n="p8.102"><s n="s1.4;p8.102">A primary aim of this project is to correlate the N4 fraction given by NMR spectroscopy to that given by Raman spectroscopy. </s><s n="s2.4;p8.102">This is worthwhile as various radioactive elements that would be present in the nuclear waste glass, such as uranium and its oxides, are paramagnetic, which prevents NMR spectroscopy being performed when these species are in high abundance. </s><s n="s3.4;p8.102">However, Raman spectroscopy does not depend on the magnetic susceptibility of the sample. </s><s n="s4.4;p8.102">By correlating the two techniques the N4 fraction can be found from the Raman spectrum of a glass containing too much paramagnetism to be analysed with NMR. Although Raman scattering produces a spectrum unaffected by magnetisation of the sample, the spectrum is significantly harder to interpret in terms of N4 fraction than an NMR spectrum. </s></p><p n="p9.102"><s n="s1.3;p9.102">One of the seminal papers in the field of Raman spectroscopy of borate glasses is by Konijnendijk and Stevels (1975), and offers insight into which peaks correspond to which superstructural units in borate glasses [5]. </s><s n="s2.3;p9.102">Another key study into superstructural unit peak assignment was performed by Kamitsos, Karakassides and Chryssikos (1989), in which they concentrated on caesium, rubidium and potassium binary borates [6]. </s><s n="s3.3;p9.102">Meera and Ramakrishna also contributed to the peak assignment debate in 1991 discussing a wide range of borate glasses [2]. </s></p><p n="p10.102"><s n="s1.3;p10.102">Densities and structural models for various alkali borates, including lithium and caesium, were investigated by Royle et al. [7]. </s><s n="s2.3;p10.102">Neutron diffraction studies of caesium borate glasses performed by Shaw et al. have provided further information about the role of superstructural units in vitreous B <hi rend="sub">2</hi>O <hi rend="sub">3</hi> and borate glasses [8]. </s><s n="s3.3;p10.102">Massot, Souto and Balkanski have tested borate glasses with Raman and light scattering spectroscopy as well as acoustic wave velocity and glass density measurements to help describe the short and medium range order [9]. </s></p><p n="p11.102"><s n="s1.6;p11.102">NMR spectroscopy is very useful in the study of borate glasses as it can clearly distinguish between the two chemically distinct B3 and B4 sites and quantify the proportion of each. </s><s n="s2.6;p11.102">In 1993 Wüllen and Müller-Warmuth showed that magic-angle-spinning (MAS) NMR was a reliable method to do this in both theory and experiment [10]. </s><s n="s3.6;p11.102">However, as boron-11 is a quadrupolar species, this single-quantum method contained second order anisotropies. </s><s n="s4.6;p11.102">Amoureux, Fernandez and Frydman showed how to optimise an earlier multiple quantum experiment on half-integer quadrupoles that would remove these anisotropies [11]. </s><s n="s5.6;p11.102">This led to a study of the short range order in B <hi rend="sub">2</hi>O <hi rend="sub">3</hi> by Hwang et al. [12]. </s><s n="s6.6;p11.102">A helpful communication on the theory of multiple-quantum magic-angle spinning (MQMAS) containing further optimisation methods is provided by Brown and Wimperis [13]. </s></p><p n="p12.102"><s n="s1.5;p12.102">Using 3QMAS-NMR Stebbins, Zhao and Kroeker have directly measured the concentrations of non-bridging oxygens in borate glasses [14]. </s><s n="s2.5;p12.102">Kroeker has also related the B4 sites in caesium borate glasses to superstructural units using MAS-NMR [15]. </s><s n="s3.5;p12.102">The proportion of B4 in the borate glass as alkali modifier content is varied has been explored, again using MAS-NMR, by Clarida et al. [16]. </s><s n="s4.5;p12.102">Du and Stebbins have examined, using 3QMAS-NMR, the connectivities within borate glasses and shown that there are boroxol rings [17]. </s><s n="s5.5;p12.102">Further studies on the NMR response of boroxol rings were performed by Zwanziger in 2004 [18]. </s></p><p n="p13.102"><s n="s1.1;p13.102">Alkali-borate glasses are still actively studied by many groups around the world and while there is now a great amount of knowledge about these glasses, there are still many unanswered questions about them and interesting research to perform on them. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><div2><head><hi rend="bold">II.1</hi> Glass Forming Theory</head><p n="p14.102"><s n="s1.5;p14.102">Glasses have no long range order and are thermodynamically unstable compared to crystals, having a higher enthalpy for a given temperature. </s><s n="s2.5;p14.102">Glasses also exhibit time-dependent behaviour during formation; their final enthalpy will depend on their rate of cooling, which is not the case for crystals. </s><s n="s3.5;p14.102">Generally, on cooling a liquid below its melting point it can suddenly order itself causing a sharp drop in enthalpy, or it can remain disordered and become a supercooled liquid. </s><s n="s4.5;p14.102">In the latter case, as temperature continues to drop the viscosity of the liquid will rise until the rearrangement of atoms ceases, leaving a disordered solid. </s><s n="s5.5;p14.102">This explains the time-dependence, as faster cooling will leave less time for atomic rearrangements to lower enthalpy. </s></p><p n="p15.102"><s n="s1.5;p15.102">Vitreous B <hi rend="sub">2</hi>O <hi rend="sub">3</hi> forms a glass on cooling, contains only B3 and is thought to comprise of locally independent interpenetrating networks made up of boroxol groups and BO <hi rend="sub">3</hi> triangles, as opposed to one large single network. </s><s n="s2.5;p15.102">Introducing cations initially (upto 40 mol%) converts BO <hi rend="sub">3</hi> triangles into BO <hi rend="sub">4</hi> tetrahedra. </s><s n="s3.5;p15.102">This increase in coordination number strengthens the network [1]. </s><s n="s4.5;p15.102">The addition of 4-coordinated boron in the network allows the possibility of having different superstructural units other than the boroxol group. </s><s n="s5.5;p15.102">One determination of the fractions of superstructural units present as a function of composition is shown in figure 2: </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0311i-fig.001"><head><hi rend="bold">Figure 2.</hi> The intensities of Raman signals of boroxol rings, tetraborate and diborate configurations as a function of mol% Li <hi rend="sub">2</hi> O/mol% B <hi rend="sub">2</hi> O <hi rend="sub">3</hi> [19].</head></figure><p n="p16.102"><s n="s1.2;p16.102">Meera and Ramakrishna have a differing view to that of Kerner, for the structural groups present at various compositions of <hi rend="italic">x</hi>Li <hi rend="sub">2</hi>O·(100-<hi rend="italic">x</hi>)B <hi rend="sub">2</hi>O <hi rend="sub">3</hi>, mainly by the inclusion of pentaborate and dipentaborate and the exclusion of tetraborate [2,19]. </s><s n="s2.2;p16.102">Tetraborate can be considered to be pentaborate and triborate joined by a bridging oxygen and so not a true superstructural unit. </s></p></div2><div2><head><hi rend="bold">II.2</hi> Nuclear Magnetic Resonance Spectroscopy Theory</head><p n="p17.102"><s n="s1.6;p17.102">NMR is used as a probe of local structure in materials. </s><s n="s2.6;p17.102">It is a technique particularly suited to glasses as their lack of long-range order prevents their structure from being determined easily by X-ray diffraction. </s><s n="s3.6;p17.102">In a magnetic field every particle has a magnetic moment, μ, which is proportional to the intrinsic spin of the particle by the gyromagnetic ratio, γ. </s><s n="s4.6;p17.102">It is this symmetry between magnetic moments and spins that is exploited by NMR. Compass needles have magnetic moments, so do nuclear spins. </s><s n="s5.6;p17.102">But unlike a compass needle that aligns itself to minimise the magnetic potential energy, a nuclear spin precesses around the magnetic field lines, always keeping at the same angle. </s><s n="s6.6;p17.102">The spin cannot align with the magnetic field to minimise its energy because magnetic spin is quantised, and so to change angles (and thus energy) by amounts that represent an energy less than a single quantum is forbidden by quantum mechanics. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0311i-pic.002"><head><hi rend="bold">Figure 3.</hi> Spin precession of a magnetic moment in a magnetic field, B.</head></figure><p n="p18.102"><s n="s1.1;p18.102">The frequency of this precession, ω<hi rend="sub">0</hi>, is proportional to the strength of the magnetic field, B <hi rend="sub">0</hi>, by the gyromagnetic ratio: </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p19.102"><s n="s1.1;p19.102"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0311i-form.002"/> (2) </s></p><p n="p20.102"><s n="s1.7;p20.102">Different nuclei possess different gyromagnetic ratios and will precess at different frequencies in the same magnetic field. </s><s n="s2.7;p20.102">This allows NMR spectroscopy to be a nucleus-specific technique. </s><s n="s3.7;p20.102">Even if the magnetic field is perfectly homogenous on a macroscopic level, there will be small deviations caused by the presence of atoms and molecules, as electrons are magnetic and distort the field. </s><s n="s4.7;p20.102">This effect is called chemical shift because, as there will be different local-magnetic-field strengths around chemically-distinct nuclei, the precessional frequency (given in equation 2) will be slightly different. </s><s n="s5.7;p20.102">As B3 and B4 boron-11 are in different chemical (and hence magnetic) environments their spins will precess at slightly different frequencies and so the separation of the two sites will be easily determined by using NMR. The chemical shift that is measured is compared to the chemical shift of a reference value, defined as zero. </s><s n="s6.7;p20.102">The chemical shift is dimensionless and measured in parts per million (ppm). </s><s n="s7.7;p20.102">This allows comparison of results from different magnetic fields, as although the absolute precessional frequencies will differ, the chemical shifts will remain the same. </s></p><p n="p21.102"><s n="s1.3;p21.102">Although it has been said that nuclear spins do not change their angle of precession in a magnetic field, there is a small effect caused by thermal vibrations, such that over millions of precessions an ensemble of nuclear spins generate a small net magnetic moment aligned with the applied magnetic field. </s><s n="s2.3;p21.102">This is the microscopic mechanism for nuclear paramagnetism, and is about four orders of magnitude weaker than electron diamagnetism. </s><s n="s3.3;p21.102">As such, the net magnetic moment of the nuclear spins cannot be detected directly because the effect is overwhelmed by the signal from the electrons. </s></p><p n="p22.102"><s n="s1.4;p22.102">The method of detection used in NMR is to irradiate the sample with radio-frequency electromagnetic radiation. </s><s n="s2.4;p22.102">It is the magnetic part of the wave that interacts with the nuclear magnetic moments and, as shown in equation 2, the spins will precess around the magnetic field of the wave. </s><s n="s3.4;p22.102">This oscillating magnetic field is (about 10 <hi rend="sup">4</hi> times) weaker than the static field and the frequency of the pulse must be tuned to 'resonate' the nuclear spin to have an effect. </s><s n="s4.4;p22.102">The frequency in the case of nuclear spins in a magnetic field of several Tesla falls in the radio region. </s></p><p n="p23.102"><s n="s1.6;p23.102">For a fixed power the duration of the radio-frequency pulse governs by what angle the individual spins, and in turn the net magnetic moment, will be rotated. </s><s n="s2.6;p23.102">The pulse can be applied to flip the spins by 90°. </s><s n="s3.6;p23.102">Once the pulse is gone, microscopically, the spins carry on precessing around the static magnetic field, as before. </s><s n="s4.6;p23.102">But macroscopically, instead of being aligned with the magnetic field, the net magnetic moment starts precessing around as well, perpendicular to the magnetic field in this 90° case. </s><s n="s5.6;p23.102">This rotating magnetic moment generates a rotating magnetic field, and a changing magnetic field generates an electric field, according to Maxwell's equations. </s><s n="s6.6;p23.102">This tiny, oscillating, electric field is picked up by a coil of wire, amplified and sent to a computer. </s></p><p n="p24.102"><s n="s1.4;p24.102">Over time, the same action that causes a slight bias in the magnetic alignment of the spins causes the spins to line up with the main magnetic field once again. </s><s n="s2.4;p24.102">This is called spin-lattice relaxation. </s><s n="s3.4;p24.102">Additionally, the individual spins can fall out of synchronisation with each other due to the inhomogeneous magnetic fields present across the sample. </s><s n="s4.4;p24.102">This causes the net magnetic moment to decrease in magnitude and is called transverse relaxation. </s></p><p n="p25.102"><s n="s1.4;p25.102">Archaically, the term 'spin' was used because the mathematics involved with the phenomenon looked similar to classical angular momentum; the term does not reflect the actual physical rotation of a particle. </s><s n="s2.4;p25.102">Many particles have half-integer spin, a value not allowed classically. </s><s n="s3.4;p25.102">The quantum numbers governing the angular momentum energy eigenstates are <hi rend="italic">I</hi> (which can have any positive integer or half-integer value) and <hi rend="italic">m</hi> (which has values from - <hi rend="italic">I</hi> to +<hi rend="italic">I</hi> in integer steps). </s><s n="s4.4;p25.102">For quantum number <hi rend="italic">I</hi> = 3/2, <hi rend="italic">m</hi> can have any of the following values; -3/2, -1/2, +1/2, +3/2, as shown in figure 4: </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0311i-fig.002"><head><hi rend="bold">Figure 4</hi> . An energy level diagram of the four energy states allowed for a particle with spin <hi rend="italic">I</hi> = 3/2.</head></figure><p n="p26.102"><s n="s1.2;p26.102">Boron-11 has a nuclear spin of 3/2 and has both electric dipole and electric quadrupole moments. </s><s n="s2.2;p26.102">The quadrupolar moment of the nucleus, <hi rend="italic">Q</hi>, interacts with the electric field gradient, which can be defined by a second-rank symmetrical tensor, <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0311i-form.003"/>: </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p27.102"><s n="s1.1;p27.102"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0311i-form.004"/> (3) </s></p><p n="p28.102"><s n="s1.2;p28.102">The diagonal components represent the electric field gradient in the <hi rend="italic">x</hi>, <hi rend="italic">y</hi>, and <hi rend="italic">z</hi> directions respectively. </s><s n="s2.2;p28.102">This tensor can be defined by two parameters, the strength of the quadrupolar coupling constant, <hi rend="italic">CQ</hi> (Hz), and the asymmetry parameter, η (0-1): </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p29.102"><s n="s1.1;p29.102"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0311i-form.005"/> (4) </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p30.102"><s n="s1.1;p30.102"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0311i-form.006"/> (5) </s></p><p n="p31.102"><s n="s1.5;p31.102">The dipole moments, which cause first-order broadening of the spectral lines, can be removed by spinning the sample at a so-called 'magic' angle of 54.7° to the magnetic field. </s><s n="s2.5;p31.102">The quadrupole moments cause second-order broadening by interacting with the electric field gradient in the sample. </s><s n="s3.5;p31.102">This broadening can be removed by spinning the sample at 30.6° or 70.1°, but this would cause the first-order broadening to reappear. </s><s n="s4.5;p31.102">Thus second-order 'quadrupolar' broadening can only be partially removed by rotation around a single axis. </s><s n="s5.5;p31.102">The angles given here are the roots of the Wigner rotation matrices for second rank (54.7°) and fourth rank (30.6° or 70.1°) cases and are further discussed by Llor and Virlet [20]. </s></p><p n="p32.102"><s n="s1.4;p32.102">Double rotation experiments (DOR) can remove this second-order quadrupolar broadening, but the technique is complicated and limited to slow rotation speeds. </s><s n="s2.4;p32.102">Triple-quantum magic angle spinning (3QMAS) is an experiment that can separate the overlapping spectral lines by producing a 2D spectrum [11-14]. </s><s n="s3.4;p32.102">Although the second-order broadening is still present in the direct dimension, taking a projection along a certain angle, orthogonal to the ridges in the spectrum, reveals a spectrum containing only isotropic shifts. </s><s n="s4.4;p32.102">This spectrum, unbroadened by second-order quadrupolar effects, will show the different chemical environments of B3 and B4 boron. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0311i-fig.003"><head><hi rend="bold">Figure 5</hi> . A schematic of how MQMAS can remove second-order broadening by taking an isotropic projection.</head></figure><p n="p33.102"><s n="s1.5;p33.102">At high enough magnetic fields, where quadrupolar broadening is reduced naturally, a one-pulse MAS experiment is suitable for distinguishing between B3 and B4 as the different species are in different magnetic environments and will show different chemical shifts. </s><s n="s2.5;p33.102">The fast spinning of the sample at the magic angle simulates isotropic molecular motion, like in a liquid, which causes the broad lines to form narrow peaks with the addition of spinning side-bands. </s><s n="s3.5;p33.102">This experiment will provide two peaks and, by comparing the integral under each of the two curves the proportion of B4 to B3 can be found. </s><s n="s4.5;p33.102">Theory predicts there are actually two separate, overlapping lines under each peak. </s><s n="s5.5;p33.102">For example, the one pulse spectrum of pure B <hi rend="sub">2</hi>O <hi rend="sub">3</hi> shows one broad line that is really two overlapping lines corresponding to the different environments of boron in the structure, that is, symmetric and asymmetric [22]. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0311i-pic.003"><head><hi rend="bold">Figure 6</hi> . A schematic diagram showing how boron (● ) and bridging oxygens (○ ) make up boroxol groups and BO <hi rend="sub">3</hi> triangles. The dashed lines enclose the repeated unit. The central boron is in a symmetric environment, whereas the borons in the boroxol groups are in asymmetric environments.</head></figure><p n="p34.102"><s n="s1.3;p34.102">To deconvolute the two lines under the curve a phase modulated split-t1 triple-quantum MAS experiment can be used (Fig. </s><s n="s2.3;p34.102">7). </s><s n="s3.3;p34.102">This pulse sequence excites the triple-quantum coherence of the boron nucleus <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0311i-form.007"/>[13]. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0311i-fig.004"><head><hi rend="bold">Figure 7.</hi> The pulse sequence and coherence transfer pathway diagram for the phase modulated split-t1 3QMAS experiment.</head></figure><p n="p35.102"><s n="s1.3;p35.102">The first two pulses in figure 7 are 'hard': they excite all the transitions of the spin 3/2 nucleus; the triple quantum <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0311i-form.008"/>, central transition <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0311i-form.009"/>, as well as the satellite transitions. </s><s n="s2.3;p35.102">The first pulse length is optimised to give the largest triple quantum coherence amplitude and the second pulse length is optimised to provide the maximum conversion from the -3 to the +1 coherence. </s><s n="s3.3;p35.102">The third and final pulse is 'soft' and so just excites the central transition <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0311i-form.010"/> to put the coherence in the -1 pathway ready for quadrature detection at during t <hi rend="sub">2</hi>. </s></p><p n="p36.102"><s n="s1.3;p36.102">The experiment is called 'split-t1' as the t <hi rend="sub">1</hi> period is shared between the triple quantum evolution and single quantum evolution, as shown by the coherence transfer pathway diagram in figure 7. </s><s n="s2.3;p36.102">This causes the second order quadrupolar broadening to become refocused at the end of the t <hi rend="sub">1</hi> period, which not only removes the need for double angle rotation but also avoids the need for additional processing (shearing) that similar pulse sequences have to undergo. </s><s n="s3.3;p36.102">This pulse sequence acquires a whole echo and is programmed such that it appears at a fixed position in t <hi rend="sub">2</hi> [13]. </s></p></div2><div2><head><hi rend="bold">II.3</hi> Raman Spectroscopy Theory</head><p n="p37.102"><s n="s1.3;p37.102">When intense, monochromatic, light is incident on a material most of the photons are elastically scattered (Rayleigh scattering) and so have the same energy as the incident photons. </s><s n="s2.3;p37.102">The Raman spectrometer filters these photons out with a holographic filter, leaving only those photons that have scattered inelastically (Raman scattering) to reach the detector. </s><s n="s3.3;p37.102">Raman scattering occurs when there is a change in the energy of the molecule, in this case; vibrational energy. </s></p><p n="p38.102"><s n="s1.4;p38.102">The incident photon interacts with the electric dipole of the molecule, which excites the vibrational energy of the molecule into a virtual energy state. </s><s n="s2.4;p38.102">De-excitation occurs in less than 10 <hi rend="sup">-14</hi> seconds with the emission of a photon. </s><s n="s3.4;p38.102">If the final energy is greater than the initial energy then the process is called 'Stokes' Raman scattering, which leaves the photon with less energy than it started with. </s><s n="s4.4;p38.102">This is what is observed in Raman spectroscopy [21]. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0311i-fig.005"><head><hi rend="bold">Figure 8.</hi> An energy level diagram for Raman scattering. The photon gives up some of its energy in exciting the vibrational ground state of a molecule.</head></figure><p n="p39.102"><s n="s1.1;p39.102">A spectrum is created by plotting the intensity of 'Stokes' Raman scattered photons as a function of wavenumber, <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0311i-form.011"/>. </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p40.102"><s n="s1.1;p40.102"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0311i-form.012"/> (7) </s></p><p n="p41.102"><s n="s1.1;p41.102">Where <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0311i-form.013"/> is the wavelength (in cm) of the incident laser photons and <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0311i-form.014"/> is the wavelength (in cm) of the detected scattered photons. </s></p><p n="p42.102"><s n="s1.5;p42.102">Different structural units (Fig. </s><s n="s2.5;p42.102">1) will have different vibrational modes. </s><s n="s3.5;p42.102">At room temperature the strongest vibrational mode in borate glasses is the lowest energy 'breathing' mode of the boroxol unit. </s><s n="s4.5;p42.102">By acquiring a spectrum of these modes it is possible to match up peaks corresponding to various structural units. </s><s n="s5.5;p42.102">Combining the peak areas and N4 fraction for each structural unit makes it is possible to find the total fraction of N4 as a function of glass composition. </s></p><p n="p43.102"><s n="s1.2;p43.102">Raman is not, however, a quantitative technique, as the intensity of light given off by different scattering centres may vary depending on their configuration. </s><s n="s2.2;p43.102">Thus different peaks areas may not be a true reflection of their relative proportions in the material. </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><div2><head><hi rend="bold">III.1</hi> Glass Creation Details</head><p n="p44.102"><s n="s1.1;p44.102">The balanced stoichiometric equation for creating lithium borate is: </s></p><p n="p45.102"><s n="s1.1;p45.102"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0311i-form.015"/> </s></p><p n="p46.102"><s n="s1.3;p46.102">Whether the product is crystalline or vitreous depends on the cooling rate of the melt. </s><s n="s2.3;p46.102">In this investigation ten glasses were made of various nominal compositions to give a product <hi rend="italic">x</hi>Li <hi rend="sub">2</hi>O•(100-<hi rend="italic">x</hi>)B <hi rend="sub">2</hi>O <hi rend="sub">3</hi> over the range <hi rend="italic">x</hi>=0 to <hi rend="italic">x</hi>=40. </s><s n="s3.3;p46.102">The paramagnetic compound iron oxide (Fe <hi rend="sub">2</hi>O <hi rend="sub">3</hi>) was added at a concentration of 0.1 molar percent to each composition to decrease the spin-lattice relaxation time of the nuclear spins and hence speed up the NMR acquisition process. </s></p><table id="BAWE_0311i-tab.001"><head><hi rend="bold">Table 1</hi> . Mass measurements to make 20 grams of nominal composition of <hi rend="italic">x</hi> Li <hi rend="sub">2</hi> O• (100-<hi rend="italic">x</hi> )B <hi rend="sub">2</hi> O <hi rend="sub">3</hi> .</head><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p47.102"><s n="s1.3;p47.102">All compositions were weighed out on the same calibrated Oertling balance to 3 decimal place accuracy. </s><s n="s2.3;p47.102">The pre-melt powders were put in glass jars and shaken well to roughly homogenise the different reactants before being stored in a desiccator. </s><s n="s3.3;p47.102">Due to the iron oxide, the lower the lithium carbonate content the pinker the mixed powders appeared. </s></p><p n="p48.102"><s n="s1.5;p48.102">Two compositions were fired in an electrically heated furnace at the same time in large platinum-rhodium crucibles (with mass around 250g). </s><s n="s2.5;p48.102">The large crucibles were necessary to prevent the overflow of material due to gas evolution on heating. </s><s n="s3.5;p48.102">The furnace was programmed to ramp at 10°C per minute before dwelling at 1000°C. When the furnace reached this temperature a stopwatch was started and after 20 minutes the melts were poured from their crucibles onto a graphite coated steel plate that was at 200°C. The hotplate was then turned off and left to cool naturally. </s><s n="s4.5;p48.102">This procedure is designated method 1. </s><s n="s5.5;p48.102">See figure 9: </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0311i-pic.004"><head><hi rend="bold">Figure 9</hi> . The heating program for method 1 lithium borate glass creation (not to scale).</head></figure><p n="p49.102"><s n="s1.2;p49.102">The nominal compositions were reweighed as in table 1 and the above process repeated exactly, except instead of the graphite coated steel plate being at room temperature, the melt was plate quenched to rapidly cool it to form a glass. </s><s n="s2.2;p49.102">This new method has the advantage of forming thin sheets of glass that are easier to grind up for analysis and is designated method 2. </s></p><p n="p50.102"><s n="s1.2;p50.102">A third reweighing and firing with a halved ramping rate of 5°C a minute was performed for reweighed nominal compositions of <hi rend="italic">x</hi>=35 and <hi rend="italic">x</hi>=40. </s><s n="s2.2;p50.102">This is method 3. </s></p><p n="p51.102"><s n="s1.4;p51.102">In addition to the binary borate glasses, six samples containing cobalt oxide substituted for di-lithium oxide were also prepared. </s><s n="s2.4;p51.102">All six had the boron oxide proportion fixed at 80 mol%. </s><s n="s3.4;p51.102">As cobalt oxide is paramagnetic there was no need to add iron oxide. </s><s n="s4.4;p51.102">Method 3 was employed for the creation of these samples. </s></p><table id="BAWE_0311i-tab.002"><head><hi rend="bold">Table 2</hi> . Mass measurements to make 20 grams of nominal composition of <hi rend="italic">x</hi> CoO• (20-<hi rend="italic">x</hi> )Li <hi rend="sub">2</hi> O• 80B <hi rend="sub">2</hi> O <hi rend="sub">3</hi> .</head><row><cell/></row></table></div2><div2><head><hi rend="bold">III.2</hi> NMR Experimental Details</head><p n="p52.102"><s n="s1.7;p52.102">Boron has two isotopes, boron-10 and boron-11. </s><s n="s2.7;p52.102">Boron-11 will be probed as it is 80% naturally abundant and has a nuclear spin of 3/2. </s><s n="s3.7;p52.102">Boron-11 has gyromagnetic ratio of 8.585x10 <hi rend="sup">7</hi> rad T <hi rend="sup">-1</hi> s <hi rend="sup">-1</hi>, roughly a third that of the proton. </s><s n="s4.7;p52.102">This is compared to boron-10 which is 20% abundant, has spin 3, a gyromagnetic ratio a tenth that of the proton, and a quadrupolar moment twice that of boron-11. </s><s n="s5.7;p52.102">The spectrometer used was a Varian Chemagnetics CMX 600 (14.1 T) spectrometer operating at 192.5 MHz. </s><s n="s6.7;p52.102">The well ground samples were packed in 4 mm diameter zirconia rotors and spun at 10 kHz in a CMX 4mm probe (serial #6300). </s><s n="s7.7;p52.102">Boron phosphate (BPO <hi rend="sub">4</hi>) was used as a secondary reference, having a single line at -3.3 ppm, with respect to the primary reference Et <hi rend="sub">2</hi>O•BF <hi rend="sub">3</hi> at 0 ppm. </s></p><p n="p53.102"><s n="s1.3;p53.102">A pulse-delay array experiment was run on the (arbitrarily chosen) <hi rend="italic">x</hi>=40 sample to determine the most suitable time delay between running the pulse sequences. </s><s n="s2.3;p53.102">Due to the iron oxide, spin-lattice relaxation was very quick and it was determined that 0.1 seconds between pulses sequences was enough time to allow the bulk nuclear magnetisation to realign with the static magnetic field. </s><s n="s3.3;p53.102">A pulse-length array experiment was also run, giving the π-flip angle to be 21.0 μs, which makes the nutation frequency for this particular probe's power 23.8 kHz. </s></p><p n="p54.102"><s n="s1.5;p54.102">All the samples from <hi rend="italic">x</hi>=0 to <hi rend="italic">x</hi>=40 were then recorded using an identical experimental procedure. </s><s n="s2.5;p54.102">The pulse sequence was just one 0.60 μs pulse at 192.547 MHz, phase cycled over four acquisitions to remove the quadrature ghost that appears at the pulse frequency (192.547 MHz) in the spectra. </s><s n="s3.5;p54.102">After the pulse there was a 2.5 μs receiver delay and then a 2.5 μs acquisition delay to allow the 'ringing' in the coil to dissipate as well as give time for the measurement electronics to recover. </s><s n="s4.5;p54.102">Then followed 4096 measurements of the electric field, 2.5 μs apart, giving a total acquisition length of 10.24 ms. </s><s n="s5.5;p54.102">This experiment recorded and summed 2048 transients to improve the signal-to-noise ratio. </s></p><p n="p55.102"><s n="s1.5;p55.102">The data acquired in the 1D experiment, a free induction decay (FID) signal, was processed in Spinsight. </s><s n="s2.5;p55.102">The FID had one extra initial point back-predicted to make up for the acquisition delay and thus reduce the need for first-order phasing. </s><s n="s3.5;p55.102">The FID then underwent a complex fast Fourier transform to convert the time signal into the frequency domain. </s><s n="s4.5;p55.102">The spectrum was then zero-order phased so that the 'real' part was purely 'absorptive', that is, all positive. </s><s n="s5.5;p55.102">A DC-offset was finally applied to put the lineshape down on the baseline and prevent spurious peak fits. </s></p><p n="p56.102"><s n="s1.2;p56.102">Peak fitting was performed using a program called DMFit [23]. </s><s n="s2.2;p56.102">The B3 peak was fitted with two quadrupole lineshapes and the B4 was fitted with two 50% Gaussian-50% Lorentzian lineshapes. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0311i-fig.006"><head><hi rend="bold">Figure 10</hi> . MAS NMR spectrum of 20Li <hi rend="sub">2</hi> O• 80B <hi rend="sub">2</hi> O <hi rend="sub">3</hi> peak fitted in DMFit.</head></figure><p n="p57.102"><s n="s1.3;p57.102">The peak areas were then given by the fitting program, along with the quadrupole parameters for the peaks. </s><s n="s2.3;p57.102">The B3 area was multiplied by 1.04 to account for area lost to the spinning sidebands. </s><s n="s3.3;p57.102">It has been shown that the B4 area does not suffer from this effect and thus no adjustment was necessary [25]. </s></p><p n="p58.102"><s n="s1.1;p58.102">Boron-11 MAS NMR was also performed on the cobalt oxide doped lithium borate glasses with a very similar 1D experiment to that described above, the main difference was a change of probe to a Varian T3 4 mm. </s></p><p n="p59.102"><s n="s1.7;p59.102">The phase modulated split-t1 triple-quantum MAS experiment, shown in figure 7, was experimentally more complex than the one-pulse experiment. </s><s n="s2.7;p59.102">The <hi rend="italic">x</hi>=0 sample was tested first as it has the least complicated spectrum. </s><s n="s3.7;p59.102">To begin, each of the three pulse lengths were varied separately to discover the optimum pulse length for each one. </s><s n="s4.7;p59.102">The following lengths; excitation pulse - 6 μs, conversion pulse - 2.3 μs, echo pulse - 11.2 μs, were determined to give the best signal-to-noise ratio. </s><s n="s5.7;p59.102">The pulse sequence makes use of phase cycling to select the appropriate coherence transfer pathway, so the signal is summed over multiples of 96 transients. </s><s n="s6.7;p59.102">Adding the signal from 4608 transients produced an acceptable signal-to-noise ratio. </s><s n="s7.7;p59.102">The pulse lengths were later changed to the following; excitation pulse - 8 μs, conversion pulse - 3.25 μs, echo pulse - 12.5 μs, which yielded slightly improved signal-to-noise for the <hi rend="italic">x</hi>=20 sample. </s></p><p n="p60.102"><s n="s1.7;p60.102">The 2D recorded signal was a whole echo centred in the middle of t <hi rend="sub">2</hi> acquisition time. </s><s n="s2.7;p60.102">Gaussian apodization of 250 Hz was applied to the centre of the 1 <hi rend="sup">st</hi> dimension. </s><s n="s3.7;p60.102">The 1 <hi rend="sup">st</hi> dimension was then complex Fourier transformed with a length equal to the number of acquisition points. </s><s n="s4.7;p60.102">It is important that the peak signal is the centre of the Fourier transform to enable accurate phasing. </s><s n="s5.7;p60.102">Next, the imaginary part of the spectrum was phased to zero signal, leaving the real part purely absorptive. </s><s n="s6.7;p60.102">The 2 <hi rend="sup">nd</hi> dimension was then Fourier transformed and reversed. </s><s n="s7.7;p60.102">This processed spectrum had every other point negative, as is expected in whole echo acquisition, and so the final processing was achieved by running a personally written macro to invert alternate points across the whole 2D frequency-domain spectrum, still within Spinsight. </s></p></div2><div2><head><hi rend="bold">III.3</hi> Raman Experimental Details</head><p n="p61.102"><s n="s1.4;p61.102">All Raman spectra, from <hi rend="italic">x</hi>=0 to <hi rend="italic">x</hi>=40, were recorded using a Renishaw inVia Raman microscope running WiRE 2.0 software. </s><s n="s2.4;p61.102">The laser had a 514 nm wavelength and 10 mW power. </s><s n="s3.4;p61.102">The spectral width was 100 cm <hi rend="sup">-1</hi> to 3200 cm <hi rend="sup">-1</hi>. </s><s n="s4.4;p61.102">Each spectrum consisted of 50 acquisitions to improve the signal-to-noise ratio and the sampling region was at 50x magnification. </s></p><p n="p62.102"><s n="s1.3;p62.102">The laser beam was focused on to the surface of each sample, which was unpolished. </s><s n="s2.3;p62.102">Due to the varying thickness and roughness of the samples the absolute intensities of the spectra are not quantitatively comparable. </s><s n="s3.3;p62.102">However, as Raman spectroscopy is not a directly quantitative technique it is only the relative areas of the peaks that are of interest. </s></p><p n="p63.102"><s n="s1.4;p63.102">The raw spectrum for each sample was imported into Origin 7.0 software for baseline subtraction. </s><s n="s2.4;p63.102">By picking several points that were assumed to represent a true zero at around 300 cm <hi rend="sup">-1</hi>, 1180 cm <hi rend="sup">-1</hi>, and then from 1700 cm <hi rend="sup">-1</hi> to 2000 cm <hi rend="sup">-1</hi>, a second order polynomial line could be fitted. </s><s n="s3.4;p63.102">The equation of this line was then entered as a baseline and subtracted from the data. </s><s n="s4.4;p63.102">This method was carried out identically for all samples except <hi rend="italic">x</hi>=33 1/3 to <hi rend="italic">x</hi>=40 which omitted the 1700 cm <hi rend="sup">-1</hi> data points as it no longer represented a true zero. </s></p><p n="p64.102"><s n="s1.2;p64.102">Peak fitting of this baseline-subtracted data was also performed in Origin 7.0, after it was found that DMFit incorrectly renders the abscissa thus distorting relative peak areas. </s><s n="s2.2;p64.102">Each spectrum was assumed to have ten Gaussian peaks. </s></p></div2><div2><head><hi rend="bold">IV.1</hi> Glass Creation Results</head><p n="p65.102"><s n="s1.2;p65.102">Compositions <hi rend="italic">x</hi>=0 to <hi rend="italic">x</hi>=35 were made from method 1. </s><s n="s2.2;p65.102">The pure B <hi rend="sub">2</hi>O <hi rend="sub">3</hi> formed a toffee coloured lump, <hi rend="italic">x</hi>=5 to <hi rend="italic">x</hi>=25 formed lumps of transparent yellow glass and <hi rend="italic">x</hi>=30 to <hi rend="italic">x</hi>=35 crystallised. </s></p><p n="p66.102"><s n="s1.2;p66.102">Method 2 made compositions <hi rend="italic">x</hi>=0 to <hi rend="italic">x</hi>=40. </s><s n="s2.2;p66.102">Compositions <hi rend="italic">x</hi>=0 to <hi rend="italic">x</hi>=25 formed clear glass but there was still some devitrification for <hi rend="italic">x</hi>=30 to <hi rend="italic">x</hi>=40 and the sample yields were very low for the expected 20g product. </s></p><p n="p67.102"><s n="s1.3;p67.102">An observation of the inside of the furnace around 500°C during the ramping phase of method 2 showed the melts to be very frothy, overflowing the crucibles and touching each other as well as the furnace walls and heating elements. </s><s n="s2.3;p67.102">As the crucibles were only a quarter full of powder initially, this overflowing is most likely due to the rapid release of CO <hi rend="sub">2</hi>. </s><s n="s3.3;p67.102">Consequently these samples may be suffering from contamination and due to the mixing, be of altered composition. </s></p><p n="p68.102"><s n="s1.3;p68.102">Method 3 made compositions <hi rend="italic">x</hi>=35 and <hi rend="italic">x</hi>=40. </s><s n="s2.3;p68.102">Although the yields were larger for this run and despite the plate quenching, there was still portions of crystal mixed in with the glass. </s><s n="s3.3;p68.102">Throughout the rest of the report <hi rend="italic">x</hi>=35 and <hi rend="italic">x</hi>=40 will refer to these third method samples and the other compositions will refer to the second method samples. </s></p><p n="p69.102"><s n="s1.3;p69.102">The cobalt oxide glasses were also made with method 3. </s><s n="s2.3;p69.102">Mass measurements of the crucibles before and after the melt indicated mass losses of 3-4% from the expected 20 grams, thus they are expected to be suitably close to their desired nominal compositions. </s><s n="s3.3;p69.102">The cobalt oxide made the glasses appear a transparent pale blue for 0.1% CoO, to an intense blue that strongly absorbed light for 5% CoO. UV-Visible photospectrometry revealed that the 1% CoO glass strongly absorbed (>70% absorption) light between 500 nm and 650 nm. </s></p><p n="p70.102"><s n="s1.3;p70.102">X-ray diffraction (XRD) was performed on a selection of the lithium borate only samples to ensure they were glasses. </s><s n="s2.3;p70.102">A Hilton-Brooks diffractometer was used with a 40kV accelerating voltage and 30mA current striking a copper target tube. </s><s n="s3.3;p70.102">The 2θ angle was varied from 10° to 70° and over this range the spectrum was broad and featureless indicating a lack of long range order, and thus a glass. </s></p><p n="p71.102"><s n="s1.3;p71.102">Simultaneous thermal analysis (STA) was performed on samples <hi rend="italic">x</hi>=30 to <hi rend="italic">x</hi>=40 to determine their glass transition temperature (T <hi rend="sub">g</hi>) which reduces their compositional uncertainty. </s><s n="s2.3;p71.102">Ideally all samples would have been tested. </s><s n="s3.3;p71.102">The 20 mg samples were heated in small platinum crucibles along with quartz, a reference material, using a Perkin Elmer Pyris Diamond Thermogravimetric and Differential Thermal Analyzer under normal atmosphere. </s></p><table id="BAWE_0311i-tab.003"><head><hi rend="bold">Table 3</hi> . Measured glass transition temperatures, taken from the onset of the T <hi rend="sub">g</hi> peak, and T <hi rend="sub">g</hi> value given in the literature [24].</head><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p72.102"><s n="s1.2;p72.102">Magnetic susceptibility measurements were made on the cobalt oxide glasses, cooled down to 50 (±0.5) °K, by measuring the magnetisation, <hi rend="italic">M</hi>, as an applied magnetic field, <hi rend="italic">H</hi>, was varied from 0 to 1 Tesla at a rate of 0.5 Tesla a minute. </s><s n="s2.2;p72.102">The relation: </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p73.102"><s n="s1.1;p73.102"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0311i-form.016"/> (8) </s></p><p n="p74.102"><s n="s1.1;p74.102">was used to find the bulk magnetic susceptibility, χ. </s></p><table id="BAWE_0311i-tab.004"><head><hi rend="bold">Table 4.</hi> Magnetic susceptibility measurement results on cobalt oxide glass.</head><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p75.102"><s n="s1.2;p75.102">This increase in magnetic susceptibility has a clear effect on the NMR spectra of the cobalt glasses. </s><s n="s2.2;p75.102">Comparison with other paramagnetic species could be performed by calculating the magnetic moments of the Co <hi rend="sup">2+</hi> in the glass. </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><div2><head><hi rend="bold">IV.2</hi> NMR Spectroscopy Results</head><figure id="BAWE_0311i-fig.007"><head><hi rend="bold">Figure 11.</hi> Boron-11 MAS NMR spectra showing the effect of increasing cobalt oxide (legend in mol%).Recorded using identical settings for all spectra. There is negligible sample quantity variation.</head></figure><p n="p76.102"><s n="s1.2;p76.102">Figure 11 shows the effect of increasing magnetic susceptibility, caused in this case by the paramagnetic species, Co <hi rend="sup">2+</hi>. </s><s n="s2.2;p76.102">After 2 mol% CoO the B3/B4 peaks cannot be resolved and so finding an accurate N4 fraction is unfeasible using NMR. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0311i-fig.008"><head><hi rend="bold">Figure 12.</hi> Boron-11 MAS NMR spectra, recorded using identical settings for all spectra. The low-frequency B3 peak is on the left, and the sharper, high-frequency, B4 peak is on the right. The legend refers to <hi rend="italic">x</hi> in of <hi rend="italic">x</hi> Li <hi rend="sub">2</hi> O• (100-<hi rend="italic">x</hi> )B <hi rend="sub">2</hi> O <hi rend="sub">3</hi> .</head></figure><p n="p77.102"><s n="s1.4;p77.102">There is clear systematic change in the NMR spectra produced by varying the proportion of Li <hi rend="sub">2</hi>O in the lithium borate glasses. </s><s n="s2.4;p77.102">As more lithium is added, B3 sites convert into B4 sites. </s><s n="s3.4;p77.102">The two quadrupole parameters, defined in equations 4 and 5, for the two peaks fitting the B3 site (see Fig. </s><s n="s4.4;p77.102">10) are given in table 5. </s></p><table id="BAWE_0311i-tab.005"><head><hi rend="bold">Table 5.</hi> Quadrupole parameters for B3 peaks as given by DMFit [23].</head><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p78.102"><s n="s1.1;p78.102">Using the peak fits for the data in figure 11 the N4 fractions were calculated: </s></p><table id="BAWE_0311i-tab.006"><head><hi rend="bold">Table 6.</hi> N4 fractions given by NMR data for <hi rend="italic">x</hi> Li <hi rend="sub">2</hi> O• (100-<hi rend="italic">x</hi> )B <hi rend="sub">2</hi> O <hi rend="sub">3</hi> .</head><row><cell/></row></table><figure id="BAWE_0311i-fig.009"><head><hi rend="bold">Figure 13.</hi> N4 fraction given by NMR data as a function of composition <hi rend="italic">x</hi> Li <hi rend="sub">2</hi> O• (100-<hi rend="italic">x</hi> )B <hi rend="sub">2</hi> O <hi rend="sub">3</hi> .Dotted line is theoretical N4 = <hi rend="italic">x</hi> /(100-<hi rend="italic">x</hi> ) curve.</head></figure><p n="p79.102"><s n="s1.2;p79.102">The measured N4 fraction is in good agreement with previous studies. </s><s n="s2.2;p79.102">The deviation from the theoretical line around <hi rend="italic">x</hi>=30 is also observed in other studies. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0311i-fig.010"><head><hi rend="bold">Figure 14</hi> . 3QMAS processed data for <hi rend="italic">x</hi> =0 (left) and <hi rend="italic">x</hi> =20 (right).</head></figure><p n="p80.102"><s n="s1.6;p80.102">The 3QMAS experimental results are unexpected. </s><s n="s2.6;p80.102">Two reasons are proposed. </s><s n="s3.6;p80.102">Firstly the CMX 4 mm probe used lacked the power to excite the triple-quantum coherence required by the experiment, which is why there is a large amount of noise present in the <hi rend="italic">x</hi>=20 spectrum and both are missing the expected peak that should appear in the bottom-left of the spectra. </s><s n="s4.6;p80.102">Secondly, the pulse sequence used was not the same as that given in figure 6. </s><s n="s5.6;p80.102">Tests on rubidium nitrate (RbNO <hi rend="sub">3</hi>) have revealed a departure from the expected spectrum in terms of shearing. </s><s n="s6.6;p80.102">Because of these reasons no isotropic projection of the data is given. </s></p></div2><div2><head><hi rend="bold">IV.3</hi> Raman Spectroscopy Results</head><figure id="BAWE_0311i-fig.011"><head><hi rend="bold">Figure 15</hi> . Baseline subtracted Raman data, the side values refer to <hi rend="italic">x</hi> in <hi rend="italic">x</hi> Li <hi rend="sub">2</hi> O• (100-<hi rend="italic">x</hi> )B <hi rend="sub">2</hi> O <hi rend="sub">3</hi> . * indicates boric acid contamination.</head></figure><p n="p81.102"><s n="s1.3;p81.102">The most striking feature of figure 15 is the decrease of the peak around 806 cm <hi rend="sup">-1</hi> and the increase of the peak around 770 cm <hi rend="sup">-1</hi>, as composition changes. </s><s n="s2.3;p81.102">Other remarkable features are the increase of broad peaks around 950 cm <hi rend="sup">-1</hi> and 1100 cm <hi rend="sup">-1</hi>, as well as the decrease and broadening of a peak around 1250 cm <hi rend="sup">-1</hi>. </s><s n="s3.3;p81.102">The other features in the plots show no systematic variation with composition. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0311i-fig.012"><head><hi rend="bold">Figure 16</hi> . A typical spectrum, in this case <hi rend="italic">x</hi> =15, showing one determination of fitting ten Gaussian peaks. The intensity below 300 cm <hi rend="sup">-1</hi> is an experimental artefact.</head></figure><p n="p82.102"><s n="s1.2;p82.102">From the peak fit results given by the Origin software, trends in the areas of the peaks could be plotted against composition to help recognise systematic variation. </s><s n="s2.2;p82.102">By using this approach, along with studying the literature, peak assignments were found [2,5,6]. </s></p><table id="BAWE_0311i-tab.007"><head><hi rend="bold">Table 7</hi> . Raman peak assignments. Figure 1 shows diagrams of the groups.</head><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p83.102"><s n="s1.7;p83.102">The boroxol and triborate group assignments are strongly backed up by previous studies [2,5,6]. </s><s n="s2.7;p83.102">However, the broader dipentaborate and diborate group assignments are only partially backed up by the literature and there still exists some debate on the matter. </s><s n="s3.7;p83.102">However, the choice is not unreasonable or unphysical in this instance. </s><s n="s4.7;p83.102">The B-O stretching is a non-localised optical mode. </s><s n="s5.7;p83.102">Due to the presence of the peak in vitreous B <hi rend="sub">2</hi>O <hi rend="sub">3</hi> it must part of the network that consists of boroxol rings and BO <hi rend="sub">3</hi> triangles. </s><s n="s6.7;p83.102">As it appears to have no N4 fraction it is suggested the B-O bonds in question are around the symmetric boron site between the boroxol rings (Fig. </s><s n="s7.7;p83.102">6). </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0311i-fig.013"><head><hi rend="bold">Figure 17</hi> . Superstructural group variation with composition of <hi rend="italic">x</hi> Li <hi rend="sub">2</hi> O• (100-<hi rend="italic">x</hi> )B <hi rend="sub">2</hi> O <hi rend="sub">3</hi> . Compare to theoretical fractions in figure 2. The errors regarding the area of the units could be calculated by refitting the spectra with a different baseline subtraction and/or slightly different Gaussian locations and widths, but are assumed to be roughly ± 5%.</head></figure><p n="p84.102"><s n="s1.3;p84.102">It is the clear trends of peak area shown in figure 17 that help the designation of superstructural groups. </s><s n="s2.3;p84.102">The zero N4 boroxol and B-O stretching groups are at a maximum for low lithium content, whilst the 1/2 N4 diborate group is see to progressively increase along with lithium content. </s><s n="s3.3;p84.102">Only five peaks were found to have trends, the others remained at a constant area or fluctuated randomly. </s></p><p n="p85.102"><s n="s1.3;p85.102">Any peak found outside the range given in table 7 was excluded from calculations for total N4 fraction. </s><s n="s2.3;p85.102">The area of the superstructural groups were multiplied by their respective N4 fraction and then this value was divided by the total area of the peaks involved to give the total N4 fraction, this is effectively equation 1. </s><s n="s3.3;p85.102">Following these strict directions the following total N4 fractions were calculated for each composition: </s></p><table id="BAWE_0311i-tab.008"><head><hi rend="bold">Table 8</hi> . N4 fractions given by Raman data following superstructural unit assignments as given in table 7.</head><row><cell/></row></table><figure id="BAWE_0311i-fig.014"><head><hi rend="bold">Figure 18.</hi> N4 fraction given by Raman data as a function of composition <hi rend="italic">x</hi> Li <hi rend="sub">2</hi> O• (100-<hi rend="italic">x</hi> )B <hi rend="sub">2</hi> O <hi rend="sub">3</hi> .</head></figure></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="bold">V.</hi> NMR - Raman Calibration</head><p n="p86.102"><s n="s1.3;p86.102">Comparision of N4 fraction given by the Raman data (Fig. </s><s n="s2.3;p86.102">17) against that given by NMR spectroscopy (Fig. </s><s n="s3.3;p86.102">13) provides a calibration for one method from the other. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0311i-fig.015"><head><hi rend="bold">Figure 19</hi> . Raman N4 fraction as a function of NMR N4 fraction. Each data point represents a composition.</head></figure><p n="p87.102"><s n="s1.2;p87.102">A linear fit has been used as the same composition must have the same N4 fraction regardless of technique used to probe it and, theoretically, both techniques used here should provide an absolute N4 fraction. </s><s n="s2.2;p87.102">The equation of the fit is given as N4 <hi rend="sub">Raman</hi> = 0.87 (±0.18) N4 <hi rend="sub">NMR</hi> + 0.035 (± 0.056). </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="bold">VI.</hi> Discussion</head><p n="p88.102"><s n="s1.2;p88.102">It has been shown (Fig. </s><s n="s2.2;p88.102">13) that the addition of di-lithium oxide into boron oxide glass increases the boron co-ordination number and strengthens the network, at least up to 40 mol% Li <hi rend="sub">2</hi>O. It is suspected that beyond this level of doping, the N4 fraction will decrease, as is hinted at by the N4 fraction deviating from the <hi rend="italic">x</hi>/(100-<hi rend="italic">x</hi>) curve at the higher concentrations. </s></p><p n="p89.102"><s n="s1.6;p89.102">The N4 fraction given by Raman spectroscopy (Fig. </s><s n="s2.6;p89.102">18) does not appear to be showing the same trend of decreasing N4 fraction at higher concentrations of Li <hi rend="sub">2</hi>O. It is important that the two techniques are in agreement if this method is to be reliable. </s><s n="s3.6;p89.102">In the future, this method of calibrating Raman N4 fractions against NMR N4 fractions will be performed on very structurally-complicated glasses that mimic nuclear waste glass. </s><s n="s4.6;p89.102">The technique must be robust and cover all feasible values of doping, not just from alkali metals. </s><s n="s5.6;p89.102">Currently, the Raman technique employed here is too sensitive to the data processing, such as baseline subtraction and peak fitting, to be considered robust. </s><s n="s6.6;p89.102">There is room for improvement and with further research into more complex glass systems using this calibration technique it will become possible to measure N4 fraction using Raman spectroscopy, even on nuclear waste glass. </s></p><p n="p90.102"><s n="s1.5;p90.102">The peak assignment for the boroxol and diborate groups has a high confidence. </s><s n="s2.5;p90.102">The triborate and dipentaborate groups do not have such a certain peak assignment, as they both contain six-membered rings with an amount of B4 present. </s><s n="s3.5;p90.102">This causes the Raman spectra to show similar peak trends that can not be used to accurately give the superstructural group. </s><s n="s4.5;p90.102">The B-O stretching assignment has been noted before in the literature, but its structural assignment to the symmetric boron between the boroxol units is an original proposition [2]. </s><s n="s5.5;p90.102">Boron-10 isotopic substitution could be employed to see if there is the expected shift up in frequency of the 1250 cm <hi rend="sup">-1</hi> peak, which would indicate the dependence of the boron mass on this stretching mode and consequently whether the structural assignment is valid. </s></p><p n="p91.102"><s n="s1.7;p91.102">Since the calibration method compares Raman N4 fraction to NMR N4 fraction, the precise composition of the glass is trivial. </s><s n="s2.7;p91.102">However, it is important that the glasses made are not contaminated with impurities as these may distort the appearance of the underlying trend. </s><s n="s3.7;p91.102">With the method 2 ramping rate of 600°C per hour it is possible that the glasses made contained impurities dissolved into the melt from the furnace. </s><s n="s4.7;p91.102">Also, method 2 produced reduced yields due to the overflow of material on heating. </s><s n="s5.7;p91.102">Method 3, a halved ramping rate, was found to be a far more reliable method of consistent glass creation. </s><s n="s6.7;p91.102">Impurities, however, might still be dissolved into the melt from unclean crucibles, or from the metal plates when quenching, and steps must be taken to avoid these scenarios. </s><s n="s7.7;p91.102">Reasonable steps were taken to make sure the compositions were accurate; the reactants were generally of a high purity, the least being 99% pure lithium carbonate. </s></p><p n="p92.102"><s n="s1.7;p92.102">The samples were checked using XRD to ensure they were glasses, and STA to check if the glass transition temperature (T <hi rend="sub">g</hi>) matched the literature values. </s><s n="s2.7;p92.102">The XRD confirmed the vitreous nature of the glasses and it is noted that it is hard to <hi rend="italic">not</hi> form a glass for <hi rend="italic">x</hi> &lt; 25. </s><s n="s3.7;p92.102">The STA measurements were of little help ascertaining composition as they were performed inconsistently and with long intervals between measurements. </s><s n="s4.7;p92.102">No trends were seen in the measurement of T <hi rend="sub">g</hi> although the compositional variation is clearly seen to be reliable in the NMR and Raman measurements. </s><s n="s5.7;p92.102">A consistent and calibrated STA measurement on all the glasses is called for. </s><s n="s6.7;p92.102">Further compositional checks could be carried out by measuring the densities of the lithium borate glasses, as their values are well documented [26]. </s><s n="s7.7;p92.102">EDX measurements could also be performed on polished samples of the glasses to find any contamination. </s></p><p n="p93.102"><s n="s1.4;p93.102">Polishing the surface of the samples would also assist the Raman spectroscopy technique. </s><s n="s2.4;p93.102">Performing multiple readings at varying depths for each sample would determine if there were any structural changes due to chemical attack. </s><s n="s3.4;p93.102">Raman spectroscopy could also be performed over a range of temperatures to see which gave the optimal information about the superstructural units present. </s><s n="s4.4;p93.102">It would be interesting to know if the Raman spectra changed significantly at higher temperatures, such as those produced by radiogenic heating during the storage of radioactive waste. </s></p><p n="p94.102"><s n="s1.5;p94.102">Understanding the baseline of the Raman spectra would be helpful in performing an accurate subtraction of it. </s><s n="s2.5;p94.102">It is suspected to have a <hi rend="sup">4</hi> Rayleigh-scattering dependence, but this has not been fully tested. </s><s n="s3.5;p94.102">A second-order polynomial was used as a baseline as it provided the most accurate fit over the range used, but at larger wavenumbers this model deviated considerable. </s><s n="s4.5;p94.102">It is suspected that a main error in the N4 fraction values from the Raman spectroscopy come from the inaccurate baseline subtraction. </s><s n="s5.5;p94.102">As compositions <hi rend="italic">x</hi>=33 1/3 to <hi rend="italic">x</hi>=40 were fitted with a different baseline, not touching at 1700 cm <hi rend="sup">-1</hi>, a systematic error is possible in the results for these higher compositions. </s></p><p n="p95.102"><s n="s1.2;p95.102">For compositions greater than <hi rend="italic">x</hi>=30, when there are no more boroxol rings, other superstructural groups are likely to be present. </s><s n="s2.2;p95.102">Their peaks and impact on the total N4 fraction measured were not accounted for and this could be a reason for the deviation from the expected N4 fractions for the higher compositions. </s></p><p n="p96.102"><s n="s1.6;p96.102">Another potential source of error in the Raman technique is the peak fitting. </s><s n="s2.6;p96.102">The number of peaks is not known and so estimations and approximations must be made. </s><s n="s3.6;p96.102">The peaks that are fitted are broad and often overlap with their neighbours so they cannot be resolved; this hampers clear superstructural group assignments. </s><s n="s4.6;p96.102">It should be possible to have a computer program to look through the Raman spectra of all the compositions and taking, say, 5 cm <hi rend="sup">-1</hi> strips at a time, try to detect if there is any systematic variation with composition. </s><s n="s5.6;p96.102">This would cut out the ambiguous peak fitting and get straight to the important compositional variation, a key indicator of superstructural groups. </s><s n="s6.6;p96.102">This would also rule out errors from incorrect assumptions about the number of peaks in the spectra. </s></p><p n="p97.102"><s n="s1.5;p97.102">If convincing systematic variation was detected, there would still be the issue of which superstructural group was actually causing it. </s><s n="s2.5;p97.102">Debate still goes on about which units are really present in borate glasses and crystals. </s><s n="s3.5;p97.102">Contrary to theory proposed by Kerner the Raman spectra can be interpreted without tetraborate and still produce likely N4 fractions [19]. </s><s n="s4.5;p97.102">A definite list of peak assignments in borate glasses would be ideal, but for now the best practice is to focus on the systematic variation of area and make an informed estimate. </s><s n="s5.5;p97.102">It is important to remain rigorous and systematic, across compositions, for the peak assignments to give reliable N4 fractions. </s></p><p n="p98.102"><s n="s1.6;p98.102">Whilst the N4 fractions given by Raman are uncertain, the error is much less for the N4 fractions given by NMR, as the B3 and B4 sites are so easily distinguishable by the NMR technique. </s><s n="s2.6;p98.102">The ability for the high-field 1D MAS experiment to confidently report the N4 fraction is remarkable. </s><s n="s3.6;p98.102">Figure 13 shows the NMR N4 fraction to be in very good agreement, up to <hi rend="italic">x</hi>=30, with the theoretical model. </s><s n="s4.6;p98.102">It should be noted, however, that each data point from <hi rend="italic">x</hi>=5 to <hi rend="italic">x</hi>=25 is slightly above what is predicted by the theory. </s><s n="s5.6;p98.102">This systematic positive deviation could be due to the 1.04 multiplier for the B3 peak area not being large enough. </s><s n="s6.6;p98.102">Calculations suggest this correction should be nearer to 1.13 times the B3 area to match the data to the model. </s></p><p n="p99.102"><s n="s1.6;p99.102">The 2D MQMAS experiment suffered some failings. </s><s n="s2.6;p99.102">The lack of power to the probe is a significant, but easily remedied, problem. </s><s n="s3.6;p99.102">The difficulties in optimising the length of the pulses experimentally could be avoided by using theory to calculate the optimal lengths instead. </s><s n="s4.6;p99.102">As noise is an issue with the MQMAS experiment a modern receiver on the spectrometer would reduce this and enhance the signal-to-noise ratio. </s><s n="s5.6;p99.102">Although it is interesting to observe how the symmetric and asymmetric quadrupolar lines fit into the broad B3-site peak, this is not necessary for finding the total N4 fraction. </s><s n="s6.6;p99.102">The B3 peak was fitted with two lines for the calculations, but it was shown that a distribution of quadrupolar lines with η=0 can be made to fit the peak just as well. </s></p><p n="p100.102"><s n="s1.4;p100.102">As NMR is sensitive to the local structural environment of the nucleus it is probing it might be possible to see if the cobalt atoms changed the structure significantly when substituted for the di-lithium atoms, if the cobalt oxide was not paramagnetic and caused the spectra to broaden. </s><s n="s2.4;p100.102">The reason paramagnetic species cause the NMR spectrum to broaden is because they provide a larger spread of magnetic fields within the sample and hence cause a large variation in precession frequency. </s><s n="s3.4;p100.102">The task of understanding the properties of borate glasses as they are doped with paramagnetic species is an important one as, ultimately, the nuclear waste glass will contain significant numbers of paramagnetic species of all sizes. </s><s n="s4.4;p100.102">It is important that the Raman to NMR calibration holds for all similar structures if it is to be of practical use. </s></p><p n="p101.102"><s n="s1.6;p101.102">To further improve the calibration more data points should be collected. </s><s n="s2.6;p101.102">The closer together the compositions the finer the systematic variation of superstructural groups will appear in the Raman spectra. </s><s n="s3.6;p101.102">This would further restrict the choice of superstructural groups and hopefully lead to an accurate peak assignment. </s><s n="s4.6;p101.102">Making compositions greater than the <hi rend="italic">x</hi>=40 studied here would further refine the calibration. </s><s n="s5.6;p101.102">Making glasses of high lithium content will require very fast cooling to prevent devitrification, such as roller quenching. </s><s n="s6.6;p101.102">It is important that the calibration can ultimately work for all feasible values of <hi rend="italic">x</hi>. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="bold">VII.</hi> Conclusions</head><p n="p102.102"><s n="s1.8;p102.102">Over the compositional range <hi rend="italic">x</hi>=0 to <hi rend="italic">x</hi>=40 of <hi rend="italic">x</hi>Li <hi rend="sub">2</hi>O·(100-<hi rend="italic">x</hi>)B <hi rend="sub">2</hi>O <hi rend="sub">3</hi> the N4 fraction was determined through the application the boron-11 MAS NMR spectroscopy and Raman spectroscopy. </s><s n="s2.8;p102.102">Calibrating the Raman results to the NMR results gives a linear fit of N4 <hi rend="sub">Raman</hi> = 0.87 (±0.18) N4 <hi rend="sub">NMR</hi> + 0.035 (± 0.056). </s><s n="s3.8;p102.102">This calibration is suitable over the range covered, but is deemed less reliable at the higher compositions due to potential errors in the baseline subtractions and superstructural group peak assignments. </s><s n="s4.8;p102.102">The methods used have been shown to provide accurate and repeatable results. </s><s n="s5.8;p102.102">There should be continued research into the superstructural units present in borate glasses at higher compositions, as well as with different alkali modifiers. </s><s n="s6.8;p102.102">A rigorous and systematic study of the Raman peaks and their superstructural group assignments would be paramount for any future study hoping to provide an accurate N4 fraction measurement. </s><s n="s7.8;p102.102">Studies like this are vital for the endeavour of characterising nuclear waste glass. </s><s n="s8.8;p102.102">It is conceived that, one day, nuclear waste glass will be probed on-site, using portable Raman spectroscopy, and an accurate value for the N4 fraction given with a high degree of certainty. </s></p></div1></body><back><div1 type="back text"><head><hi rend="bold">VIII.</hi> Acknowledgments</head><p>Dr <name type="dedicatee"/>, Professor <name type="dedicatee"/>, Professor <name type="dedicatee"/> for discussions on lithium borate glasses, Mr <name type="dedicatee"/> for Raman and STA measurements, Dr <name type="dedicatee"/> for assistance with the MQMAS NMR technique, Dr <name type="dedicatee"/> for magnetisation measurements, Mr <name type="dedicatee"/> for laboratory assistance, and Miss <name type="dedicatee"/> for invaluable assistance and discussions throughout this project.</p></div1><div1 type="bibliography"><head><hi rend="bold">IX.</hi> References</head><p>[1] A. C. Wright, N. M. Vedishcheva &amp; B. A. Shakhmatkin, <hi rend="italic">Mat. Res. Soc. Symp. Proc.</hi>, 1997, <hi rend="bold">455</hi>, 381-396</p><p>[2] B. N. Meera &amp; J. Ramakrishna, <hi rend="italic">J. Non-Cryst. Solids</hi>, 1993, <hi rend="bold">159</hi>, 1-21</p><p>[3] B. P. Dwivedi, M. H. Rahman, Y. Kumar &amp; B. N. Khanna, <hi rend="italic">J. Phys. Chems. Solids</hi>, 1993, <hi rend="bold">54</hi>, 621-628</p><p>[4] G. E. Jellison, S. A. Feller &amp; P. J. Bray, <hi rend="italic">Phys. Chem. Glasses</hi>, 1978, <hi rend="bold">19</hi>, 52</p><p>[5] W. L. Konijnendijk &amp; J. M. Stevels, <hi rend="italic">J. Non-Cryst. Solids</hi>, 1975, <hi rend="bold">18</hi>, 307-331</p><p>[6] E. I. Kamitsos, M. A. Karakassides &amp; G. D. Chryssikos, <hi rend="italic">Phys. Chem. Glasses</hi>, 1989, <hi rend="bold">30</hi>, 229-234</p><p>[7] M. Royle, M. Sharma, S. Feller, J. MacKenzie &amp; S. Nijhawan, <hi rend="italic">Phys. Chem. Glasses</hi>, 1993, <hi rend="bold">34</hi>, 149-152</p><p>[8] J. L. Shaw, A. C. Wright, R. N. Sinclair, J. R. Frueh, R. B. Williams, N. D. Nelson, M. Affatigato, S. A. Feller &amp; C. R. Scales, <hi rend="italic">Phys. Chem. Glasses</hi>, 2003, <hi rend="bold">44</hi>, 256-259</p><p>[9] M. Massot, S. Souto &amp; M. Balkanski, <hi rend="italic">J. Non-Cryst. Solids</hi>, 1995, <hi rend="bold">182</hi>, 49-58</p><p>[10] L. van Wüllen &amp; W. Müller-Warmuth, <hi rend="italic">S. S. Nuc. Mag. Res.</hi>, 1993, <hi rend="bold">2</hi>, 279-284</p><p>[11] J. P. Amoureux, C. Fernandez &amp; L. Frydman, <hi rend="italic">Chem. Phys. Lett.</hi>, 1996, <hi rend="bold">259</hi>, 347-355</p><p>[12] S-J. Hwang, C. Femandez, J. P. Amoureux, J. Cho, S. W. Martin &amp; M. Pruski, <hi rend="italic">S. S. Nuc. Mag. Res.</hi>, 1997, <hi rend="bold">8</hi>, 109-121</p><p>[13] S. P. Brown &amp; S. Wimperis, <hi rend="italic">J. Mag. Res.</hi>, 1997, <hi rend="bold">124</hi>, 279-286</p><p>[14] J. F. Stebbins, P. Zhao &amp; S. Kroeker, <hi rend="italic">S. S. Nuc. Mag. Res.</hi>, 2000, <hi rend="bold">16</hi>, 9-19</p><p>[15] S. Kroeker, S. A. Feller, M. Affatigato, C. P. O'Brien, W. J. Clarida &amp; M. Kodama, <hi rend="italic">Phys. Chem. Glasses</hi>, 2003, <hi rend="bold">44</hi>, 54-58</p><p>[16] W. J. Clarida, J. R. Berryman, M. Affatigato, S. A. Feller, S. C. Kroeker, J. Ash, J. W. Zwanziger, B. Meyer, F. Borsa &amp; S. W. Martin, <hi rend="italic">Phys. Chem. Glasses</hi>, 2003, <hi rend="bold">44</hi>, 215-217</p><p>[17] L-S. Du &amp; J. F. Stebbins, <hi rend="italic">J. Phys. Chem. B</hi>, 2003, <hi rend="bold">107</hi>, 10063-10076</p><p>[18] J. W. Zwanziger, <hi rend="italic">S. S. Nuc. Mag. Res.</hi>, 2005, <hi rend="bold">27</hi>, 5-9</p><p>[19] R. Kerner, <hi rend="italic">J. Non-Cryst. Solids</hi>, 1991, <hi rend="bold">135</hi>, 155-170</p><p>[20] A. Llor &amp; J. Virlet, <hi rend="italic">Chem. Phys. Lett.</hi>, 1988, <hi rend="bold">152</hi>, 248-253</p><p>[21] <seg type="URL" n="http://www.kosi.com/Raman/resources/tutorial/"/>, Raman Spectroscopy Tutorial by Kaiser Optical Systems, Inc.</p><p>[22] B. G. Parkinson, D. Holland, M. E. Smith, A. P. Howes &amp; C. R. Scales, <hi rend="italic">J. Non-Cryst. Solids</hi>, 2005, <hi rend="bold">351</hi>, 2425-2432</p><p>[23] D. Massiot, F. Fayon, M. Capron, I. King, S. Le Calvé, B. Alonso, J-O. Durand, B. Bujoli, Z. Gan &amp; G. Hoatson, <hi rend="italic">Magn. Res. Chem.</hi>, 2002, <hi rend="bold">40</hi>, 70-76</p><p>[24] M. Affatigato, S. Feller, E. J. Khaw, D. Feil, B. Teoh, &amp; O. Mathew, <hi rend="italic">Phys. Chem. Glasses</hi>, 1990, <hi rend="bold">31</hi>, 19-24</p><p>[25] K. MacKenzie and M. E. Smith, <hi rend="italic">Multinuclear solid-state NMR of inorganic materials</hi>, Pergamon Materials Series, 6, Pergamon-Elsevier, Oxford, 2002</p><p>[26] M. Shibata, C. Sanchez, H. Patel, S. Feller, J. Stark, G. Sumcad &amp; J. Kasper, <hi rend="italic">J. Non-Cryst. Solids</hi>, 1986, <hi rend="bold">85</hi>, 29-41</p></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
