<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_0311d" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>The Two Slit Experiment; Modern Variants with Atoms and Delayed Choice</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">Language used in quote: <foreign id="English">English</foreign></note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">deleted: page numbers</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">2</p><p n="date">2003-11</p><p n="module title">Physics Essay</p><p n="module code">PX221</p><p n="genre family">Explanation</p><p n="discipline">Physics</p><p n="disciplinary group">PS</p><p n="grade">M</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">2503</p><p n="number of s-units">110</p><p n="number of p">43</p><p n="number of tables">0</p><p n="number of figures">3</p><p n="number of block quotes">2</p><p n="number of formulae">3</p><p n="number of lists">0</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">2</p><p n="abstract present">abstract present</p><p n="average words per s-unit">22.8</p><p n="average s-units per p">2.6</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">m</p><p n="year of birth">1984</p><p n="first language">English</p><p n="education">UKA</p><p n="course">MPhys</p><p n="student ID">0311</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><docTitle><titlePart rend="bold">The Two Slit Experiment; Modern Variants with Atoms and Delayed Choice</titlePart></docTitle><titlePart><name type="student name"/> (<name type="student ID"/>) University of <name type="university"/></titlePart></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="abstract"><head rend="bold">Abstract</head><p n="p1.43"><s n="s1.5;p1.43">The classic two-slit experiment is discussed with photons. </s><s n="s2.5;p1.43">Modern variants are revealed and pose questions for quantum theory to answer. </s><s n="s3.5;p1.43">Delayed choice is introduced as a method to answer some of these questions however it raises more. </s><s n="s4.5;p1.43">The non-intuitive behaviour of quantum objects is commented upon before an explanation for the two-slit experiment is given. </s><s n="s5.5;p1.43">This is followed by various interpretations of the explanation. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Introduction</head><div2><head rend="underlined">The Two-Slit Experiment with Photons</head><figure id="BAWE_0311d-pic.001"><head><hi rend="bold">Figure 1</hi> A laser on the left emits a coherent beam of light towards a collimating slit, then through two slits and onto a detector screen at the far right hand side.</head></figure><p n="p2.43"><s n="s1.4;p2.43">Coherence of the wave is important. </s><s n="s2.4;p2.43">If two lasers each lit a different slit, it would be unlikely to cause interference. </s><s n="s3.4;p2.43">Even if the sources had the same wavelength, the two wavefronts could be out of phase. </s><s n="s4.4;p2.43">This would cause a point on the detector screen to measure the sum of the individual squares rather than the average of the square of the resultant amplitude. </s></p><p n="p3.43"><s n="s1.2;p3.43">This is why a single source has to be utilised and split into two. </s><s n="s2.2;p3.43">These Huygens' wavelets emerging from the slits are identical to the original source, and are coherent with each other. </s></p><p n="p4.43"><s n="s1.1;p4.43">Lasers also produce monochromatic light, which is important for the detection of interference, as white light would mask the results by having a different interference pattern for each wavelength of light that would all overlap. </s></p><p n="p5.43"><s n="s1.1;p5.43">By blocking off one hole and measuring the intensity on the screen, you obtain pattern P <hi rend="sub">1</hi>, similarly with the other hole you get the same pattern but slightly displaced, P <hi rend="sub">2</hi>. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0311d-fig.001"><head><hi rend="bold">Figure 2</hi> A graph showing the separately summed intensity patterns from each of the holes. The peak of each graph is directly behind the open slit for each case. There is a broad spread because of the diffraction of the wave.</head></figure><p n="p6.43"><s n="s1.2;p6.43">If the light was not coherent and both slits were open, the measured intensity would be the sum of the two curves in Figure 2. </s><s n="s2.2;p6.43">This would give the area of maximum intensity behind the space halfway between the two slits. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0311d-fig.002"><head><hi rend="bold">Figure 3</hi> A graph showing the interference pattern of two monochromatic and coherent light sources (Huygens' wavelets from single source). The area of maximum intensity is behind the space halfway between the two slits.</head></figure><p n="p7.43"><s n="s1.2;p7.43">This is a typical distribution obtained when both slits are open. </s><s n="s2.2;p7.43">It shows that light is wave and interferes with itself. </s></p><p n="p8.43"><s n="s1.1;p8.43">The average intensity at angle can be proven <hi rend="sup">1</hi> to be: </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p9.43"><s n="s1.1;p9.43"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0311d-form.001"/> (1) </s></p><p n="p10.43"><s n="s1.1;p10.43">Where <hi rend="italic">I0</hi> is the initial intensity, <hi rend="italic">a</hi> is the slit separation, <hi rend="italic">d</hi> is the slit width, is the wavelength and k is the wavenumber of the light. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">The Two-Slit Experiment with Electrons, Atoms, or Molecules</head><p n="p11.43"><s n="s1.2;p11.43">The two-slit experiment can be reproduced with electrons, atoms, or molecules. </s><s n="s2.2;p11.43">Electrons can be fired using a hot cathode then are accelerated through an anode before passing through the two slits (an electron biprism) and being detected on a phosphorus screen, like a television. </s></p><p n="p12.43"><s n="s1.3;p12.43">"The experiment with two holes was first performed using atoms only at the beginning of the 1990s. </s><s n="s2.3;p12.43">A team at the University of Konstantz, in Germany, used atoms of Helium passing through slits 1m wide in gold foil, with a detector on the other side. </s><s n="s3.3;p12.43">The measurement of the number of helium atoms arriving at different parts of the detector 'screen' showed the now familiar [interference] pattern" <hi rend="sup">2</hi> </s></p><p n="p13.43"><s n="s1.1;p13.43">A group at MIT using sodium atoms confirmed these results. </s></p><p n="p14.43"><s n="s1.4;p14.43">Carbon molecules, over two orders of magnitude larger than helium atoms have also been seen to interfere. </s><s n="s2.4;p14.43">Molecules of C <hi rend="sub">60</hi> or C <hi rend="sub">70</hi> are created in an oven containing carbon power. </s><s n="s3.4;p14.43">The molecules escape from a hole and pass through two collimating slits towards a fine grating before being detected by a high resolution laser detector that can be shifted to record the spatial distribution of the molecular beam. </s><s rend="sup" n="s4.4;p14.43">3 </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0311d-pic.002"><head><hi rend="bold">Figure 4</hi> A C <hi rend="sub">60</hi> molecule <hi rend="sup">4</hi> , two collimating slits, a grating of 50nm wide slits separated by 50nm, and finally on the far right a laser detector that can be focused along a line.</head></figure><p n="p15.43"><s n="s1.3;p15.43">Light is not the only phenomenon that interferes; it has been found that particles large enough to be photographed also behave like waves. </s><s n="s2.3;p15.43">A relation between momentum, a property of particles, and wavelength, a property of waves, is: <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0311d-form.002"/>. </s><s n="s3.3;p15.43">Where is the wavelength, h-bar is Planck's constant over 2, and p is the momentum. </s></p><p n="p16.43"><s n="s1.3;p16.43">If you reduce the intensity of the laser, or electron gun, or atom stream, then the number of 'particles' fired per second is reduced. </s><s n="s2.3;p16.43">It is possible to fire only one quantum at a time, and after that quantum has been detected then you can fire another. </s><s n="s3.3;p16.43">After several thousand detections, the pattern on the screen will reveal the same intensity distribution as if all the quanta were fired together. </s></p><p n="p17.43"><s n="s1.5;p17.43">To elucidate, <hi rend="italic">one particle</hi> is fired, passes through two slits, and detected. </s><s n="s2.5;p17.43">If it just passes through one slit or the other, then the pattern on the screen would not show any interference. </s><s n="s3.5;p17.43">Somehow, the particle is able to split up and pass through both slits before interfering and being detected as a localised particle (rather than a wave). </s><s n="s4.5;p17.43">If it remains as a particle and goes through only one slit, how does it sense how many slits are open and change the probability of where it will arrive? </s><s n="s5.5;p17.43">As demonstrated in figures 2 and 3 where the maxima are in different locations depending on the number paths open to the particle. </s></p><p n="p18.43"><s n="s1.1;p18.43">In an attempt to explain this behaviour, physicists decided it would be an astute idea to observe the slits and see if the particle went one way, the other, or somehow they caught two "half-particles" each going through their own slit. </s></p><p n="p19.43"><s n="s1.3;p19.43">As expected, they always saw a whole particle at either one of the slits. </s><s n="s2.3;p19.43">Unexpectedly though, the interference pattern disappeared when they knew which way the particle was going. </s><s n="s3.3;p19.43">Turn the measuring equipment off and the interference pattern returns. </s></p><p n="p20.43"><s n="s1.1;p20.43">What would the particle do if we try to measure its path <hi rend="italic">after</hi> it has passed through the slits? </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">The Delayed Choice Experiment</head><figure id="BAWE_0311d-pic.003"><head><hi rend="bold">Figure 5</hi> A coherent beam of light is emitted onto a beam splitter (usually a half silvered mirror). One path has a phase-shifter the other does not. Both paths are reflected back onto another beam splitter through Pockels cells before being recombined and measured by the detection screen.</head></figure><p n="p21.43"><s n="s1.7;p21.43">In this experiment, performed by the University of Maryland and University of Munich the half silvered mirror acts like two slits, a single photon decides whether to go one way or the other. </s><s n="s2.7;p21.43">The phase shifter acting on one of the paths will say which way the photon went if we decide to measure its phase, which is a wave property. </s><s n="s3.7;p21.43">The Pockels cells are devices that detect photons and can tell us which way the photon went if they are turned on. </s><s n="s4.7;p21.43">When turned off the photon passes through unperturbed. </s><s n="s5.7;p21.43">Pockels cells can be turned on and off within 9ns. </s><s n="s6.7;p21.43">In the actual experiment, the path from the first beam splitter to the detector screen was 4.3m, which takes 14.5ns for light to travel. </s><s n="s7.7;p21.43">Therefore, the Pockels cells could be turned on or off <hi rend="italic">after</hi> the photon has gone through the beam splitter and chosen its path. </s></p><p n="p22.43"><s n="s1.4;p22.43">With the Pockels cells turned off the path information is hidden and the light interferes, when we know which way the photon has gone there is no interference. </s><s n="s2.4;p22.43">These are exactly the same results as when the path information was measured at the slits, except the photon has to decide which way to go before anyone knows whether to measure its path or not. </s><s n="s3.4;p22.43">The astonishing fact is that the photons have this kind of precognition. </s><s n="s4.4;p22.43">This experiment has not been performed with other particles, but there is no reason to doubt the results would be any different. </s></p><p n="p23.43"><s n="s1.3;p23.43">Due to the lensing effect gravity has on light it is possible for a very bright light source (such as quasar) to be behind a massive galaxy and for the light from the star to travel both sides of the galaxy before reaching us. </s><s n="s2.3;p23.43">In a popular thought experiment the light could be recombined and an interference pattern made (realistically the coherence time for the light source is much shorter than the difference in time for the two paths so interference would not be possible) or a telescope pointed at either side of the galaxy thus revealing which way the photon went. </s><s n="s3.3;p23.43">According to the results of the experiments the photons will decide how to behave millions of years before they are detected depending on whether an astronomer decides to turn his Pockels cells on or not. </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Conclusions</head><div2><head rend="underlined">The Non-intuitive Behaviour of Quantum Objects</head><p n="p24.43"><s n="s1.2;p24.43">Opening up a second slit changes where a single particle is likely to be detected. </s><s n="s2.2;p24.43">This solitary quantum knows the entire experimental set-up even though it can only go through just one of the slits, because when if you look you see it goes through one or the other. </s></p><p n="p25.43"><s n="s1.2;p25.43">This single particle also must interfere with itself but every measurement of it reveals it to be localised and have particle properties. </s><s n="s2.2;p25.43">If you measure the particle before it has chosen its path then the wave properties disappear all together and no interference occurs. </s></p><p n="p26.43"><s n="s1.1;p26.43">However, the delayed choice experiment shows you can measure the choice of path after it has been made and that tells the particle back in time how to behave. </s></p><p n="p27.43"><s n="s1.3;p27.43">The two-slit experiment cannot be explained by assuming matter is made of particles, nor by assuming matter is wavelike in nature. </s><s n="s2.3;p27.43">To fully explain the experimental results matter must be both. </s><s n="s3.3;p27.43">This wave-particle duality, or complementarity, is a fundamental part of nature. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">Explanations and Interpretations</head><p n="p28.43"><s n="s1.2;p28.43">The first step to an explanation of the two-slit experiment is knowing that each particle has a wavefunction associated with it. </s><s n="s2.2;p28.43">This is called the Schrödinger wave equation: </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p29.43"><s n="s1.1;p29.43"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0311d-form.003"/> (2) </s></p><p n="p30.43"><s n="s1.1;p30.43">Where <hi rend="italic">m</hi> is the mass of the particle, ψ is the what you need to solve in order to get the probability amplitude (ψψ*) for a certain time and space, <hi rend="italic">V</hi> is the potential that the particle is in, <hi rend="italic">i</hi> is the square root of minus one, which makes the equation imaginary hence you can never really measure the wavefunction directly. </s></p><p n="p31.43"><s n="s1.5;p31.43">The solution to this equation is linear, and consequently you can add many of them together and still have a solution. </s><s n="s2.5;p31.43">You may have a particle go one way, you may have a particle go the other way. </s><s n="s3.5;p31.43">There will be two solutions to the equation added together in this case. </s><s n="s4.5;p31.43">Interpretation of this can suggest that the particle is in two places at the same time, the particle will be in a superposition of states. </s><s n="s5.5;p31.43">This superposition of states are able to interfere with each other, and bring arise to the wave like behaviour of a particle. </s></p><p n="p32.43"><s n="s1.3;p32.43">What is <hi rend="italic">in effect</hi> happening is the particle is fired, and instantly becomes an imaginary wavefunction the moment it is not being observed. </s><s n="s2.3;p32.43">This wavefunction spreads out (and can go through slits and interfere with itself like a wave would) until it is required to give information about the particle it represents. </s><s n="s3.3;p32.43">If we measure momentum then we get localised particle properties, if we measure position then we get wave properties with interference. </s></p><p n="p33.43"><s n="s1.4;p33.43">An explanation for the delayed choice experiment can be sought from solving the wave equation. </s><s n="s2.4;p33.43">If you solve it for position you get the probability distribution showing interference, it has no time parameter in the solution, the probability is the same whenever the measurement is performed. </s><s n="s3.4;p33.43">Solving for the momentum gives no interference and similarly no time parameter. </s><s n="s4.4;p33.43">Mathematically it does not matter when the measurement is made. </s></p><quote lang="English">"The photon passing through the slits does not need to "decide" whether to pass through both slits or one of them. It passes through both, irrespective of whether the observer subsequently measures position or momentum. The decision to manifest particle or wave nature occurs at the detector system according the observable, and hence allowed eigenstates, chosen by the observer. Amplitude information from both paths superpose at all x's." <hi rend="sup">5</hi></quote><p n="p34.43"><s n="s1.4;p34.43">The mathematics behind quantum mechanics is open to interpretation. </s><s n="s2.4;p34.43">The orthodox interpretation is called the "Copenhagen Interpretation <hi rend="sup">6</hi>" and says that we can never describe a quantum system independently of a measuring apparatus. </s><s n="s3.4;p34.43">It also says the role of the observer is central and that the properties of the particle remain suspended in superposition only to be endowed with reality at the moment of measurement. </s><s n="s4.4;p34.43">This interpretation doesn't explain how the wavefunction collapses, or why the wavefunction is accurate and without uncertainty, but the measurements we make are only probabilities. </s></p><p n="p35.43"><s n="s1.2;p35.43">In the de Broglie-Bohm explanation the particle remains as a localised entity throughout and only ever goes through one slit. </s><s n="s2.2;p35.43">However, the quantum potential's influence is spread over both slits and it guides the atom alone a definite yet uncontrollable and unpredictable path etched out by the pattern of its distribution.<hi rend="sup">7</hi> </s></p><p n="p36.43"><s n="s1.4;p36.43">In the Many Worlds explanation, all possible realities co-exist. </s><s n="s2.4;p36.43">The particle goes through a different slit in each universe and the two universes overlap only at the level of the single particle. </s><s n="s3.4;p36.43">In each universe, the particle feels the presence of its parallel self, which has gone through the other slit. </s><s n="s4.4;p36.43">The superposition, and hence interference, is the result of superposition of universes.<hi rend="sup">8</hi> </s></p><p n="p37.43"><s n="s1.2;p37.43">The transactional interpretation is one that completely defies locality. </s><s n="s2.2;p37.43">When a measurement is made, a signal is sent back in time to where the particle was fired that sets all its properties there and then. </s></p><p n="p38.43"><s n="s1.3;p38.43">The sum-over-histories interpretation says that the particles remains as a particle but it explores all possible paths simultaneously, however improbable their route. </s><s n="s2.3;p38.43">Summed together, all paths cancel each other out leaving just the physical path taken by the atom. </s><s n="s3.3;p38.43">The way the paths cancel depends on what options are available, if both slits are open, more paths are available and the cancellation is different.<hi rend="sup">9</hi> </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">Summary</head><p n="p39.43"><s n="s1.1;p39.43">All interpretations are open for debate but there are some aspects of reality that the two-slit experiment reveals that are harder to discount. </s></p><p n="p40.43"><s n="s1.3;p40.43">The universe is non-local. </s><s n="s2.3;p40.43">That is, a wavefunction collapsing happens instantly, over any distance. </s><s n="s3.3;p40.43">While the two-slit experiment described above does not show this obviously, an adapted experiment in the similar quantum environment proves this is true.<hi rend="sup">10</hi> </s></p><p n="p41.43"><s n="s1.2;p41.43">Matter is a complementary duality: a particle and a wave together. </s><s n="s2.2;p41.43">Both aspects are needed to explain the two-slit experiment but neither are seen together in a single measurement. </s></p><p n="p42.43"><s n="s1.4;p42.43">Not all the properties of a particle can be known. </s><s n="s2.4;p42.43">Measuring one characteristic of a quantum entity changes it, losing some other information about it. </s><s n="s3.4;p42.43">This agrees with the Heisenberg Uncertainty Principle. </s><s n="s4.4;p42.43">You cannot know the position and momentum of a particle with absolute accuracy. </s></p><p n="p43.43"><s n="s1.1;p43.43">The two-slit experiment is best summed up with this quote from Richard Feynman - </s></p><quote lang="English">"The experiment with two holes encapsulates the "central mystery" of quantum mechanics, and that nobody understands what is going on in it."</quote></div2></div1></body><back><div1 type="bibliography"><head rend="bold">References and Acknowledgements</head><p>[1] I.S.Grant, W.R.Phillips, "The Elements of Physics", page 226</p><p>[2] J.Gribbin, "Schrödinger's Kittens", page 8</p><p>[3] J.Al-Khalili, "Quantum. A Guide for the Perplexed", page 24</p><p>[4] Picture from <seg type="URL" n="http://www.slb.com/seed/en/watch/fullerenes/"/></p><p>[5] R.Srikanth, "A quantum field theoretic description of the delayed choice experiment", arXiv:quant-ph/0106154</p><p>[6] J.Al-Khalili, "Quantum. A Guide for the Perplexed", page 138</p><p>[7] J.Al-Khalili, "Quantum. A Guide for the Perplexed", page 142</p><p>[8] J.Al-Khalili, "Quantum. A Guide for the Perplexed", page 146</p><p>[9] J.Al-Khalili, "Quantum. A Guide for the Perplexed", page 149</p><p>[10] W.Tittel et al. "Violation of Bell Inequalities More Than 10km Apart," Physical Review Letters 65, no. 15 (October 8, 1990):1838-1840</p></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
