<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_0311g" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An Investigation Into and Evaluation of the Drude Model Regarding the Hall Effect, Magnetoresistance and Cyclotron Frequency</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">deleted: page numbers</note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">two columns</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">3</p><p n="date">2005-02</p><p n="module title">Third Year Laboratory</p><p n="module code">PX368</p><p n="genre family">Research report</p><p n="discipline">Physics</p><p n="disciplinary group">PS</p><p n="grade">M</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">3575</p><p n="number of s-units">170</p><p n="number of p">88</p><p n="number of tables">2</p><p n="number of figures">9</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">30</p><p n="number of lists">0</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">14</p><p n="abstract present">abstract present</p><p n="average words per s-unit">21.0</p><p n="average s-units per p">1.9</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">m</p><p n="year of birth">1984</p><p n="first language">English</p><p n="education">UKA</p><p n="course">MPhys</p><p n="student ID">0311</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><docTitle><titlePart rend="bold">An Investigation Into and Evaluation of the Drude Model Regarding the Hall Effect, Magnetoresistance and Cyclotron Frequency</titlePart></docTitle><titlePart><name type="student name"/><hi rend="italic"> Department of Physics, University of <name type="university"/></hi> (24 <hi rend="sup">th</hi> February, 2005)</titlePart></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="abstract"><head rend="bold">ABSTRACT</head><p n="p1.88"><s n="s1.7;p1.88">Crossed fields are examined leading to the Hall effect and the Hall angle. </s><s n="s2.7;p1.88">The experimental results agree with the theoretical prediction for the Hall angle in the case of negative charge carriers. </s><s n="s3.7;p1.88">However, the Drude model was shown to fail in high valence systems. </s><s n="s4.7;p1.88">Magnetoresistance was derived but not found in the Drude or Sommerfeld models. </s><s n="s5.7;p1.88">Cyclotron frequency was investigated and a resonance relation found dependant on the magnetic field. </s><s n="s6.7;p1.88">A relation for the phase shift between the electric field and velocity between beats was found to be <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0311g-form.001"/>. </s><s n="s7.7;p1.88">It was also found that scattering prevents resonance from building up for sufficiently low . </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">1. Introduction</head><p n="p2.88"><s n="s1.3;p2.88">Today we are aware that the distribution of electron speeds is governed by quantum factors, and our models relating to free electron theory will therefore incorporate them. </s><s n="s2.3;p2.88">There are classical models, however, which predate Fermi-Dirac statistics and still give good accounts of many aspects of the behaviour of electrons in metals. </s><s n="s3.3;p2.88">These non-quantum models are based on the Maxwell-Boltzmann velocity distribution. </s></p><p n="p3.88"><s n="s1.3;p3.88">One such classical model is the Drude model, which is employed in this investigation. </s><s n="s2.3;p3.88">For comparison, the Sommerfeld model will also be considered; the Sommerfeld model was an early free electron model which applied quantum mechanical concepts. </s><s n="s3.3;p3.88">This model uses Fermi-Dirac rather than Maxwell-Boltzmann statistics, though in other respects it shares similarities with the Drude version. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">2. Theory</head><div2><head rend="bold">2.1 The Drude Model</head><p n="p4.88"><s n="s1.3;p4.88">Drude was the first simple classical model for a free electron gas in a metal. </s><s n="s2.3;p4.88">He constructed the model by applying the kinetic theory of gases to a metal. </s><s n="s3.3;p4.88">The model remains useful, despite some fairly serious limitations, since it is the origin of some ideas still included in more complicated modern models. </s></p><p n="p5.88"><s n="s1.2;p5.88">Drude supposed that each of the metal's atoms contributes one or more valence electron to the so-called 'electron gas': these became the <hi rend="italic">conduction electrons</hi>. </s><s n="s2.2;p5.88">In this simplified model, Drude set up each electron with the kinetic energy relating to its three (classical) degrees of translational freedom, 3/2 <hi rend="italic">kBT</hi>, and the electron speeds were governed by the Boltzmann distribution. </s></p><p n="p6.88"><s n="s1.3;p6.88">Drude also supposed that the free electrons are scattered via random collisions with the metallic ion cores. </s><s n="s2.3;p6.88">After a collision, any drift velocity 'built up' in the direction of an applied field is effectively lost. </s><s n="s3.3;p6.88">As a result, the larger the mean free time, or scattering time τ, between collisions, the greater the influence of such a field will be. </s></p><p n="p7.88"><s n="s1.1;p7.88">Importantly, the only interactions between electrons and ions considered in this model are collisions: there are no other electron-ion interactions, and no electron-electron interactions. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">2.2 The Sommerfeld Model</head><p n="p8.88"><s n="s1.2;p8.88">The Sommerfeld model was a later free electron model, and incorporated an element of quantum effects into its theory. </s><s n="s2.2;p8.88">Sommerfeld employed Fermi-Dirac statistics, and recognized that at 'ordinary' temperatures, most electrons in the metallic electron gas are many factors of <hi rend="italic">kBT</hi> below the Fermi energy. </s></p><p n="p9.88"><s n="s1.1;p9.88">These members cannot take part in a scattering collision to a slightly different energy, like those in the Drude model, since all such states are already occupied; further electrons occupying the same state is prohibited by the Pauli exclusion principle. </s></p><p n="p10.88"><s n="s1.2;p10.88">The outcome is that only a certain proportion of the electrons, that is, those near the Fermi energy, is capable of gradually responding to an external electrical field or thermal gradient. </s><s n="s2.2;p10.88">These then, in the Sommerfeld model, are the only electrons contribute to the macro-characteristics of a metal. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0311g-fig.001"><head><hi rend="bold">Fig 1.</hi> Difference in distributions between Drude (Maxwell-Boltzmann) and Sommerfeld (Fermi-Dirac) models.</head></figure></div2><div2><head rend="bold">2.3 Crossed Fields</head><p n="p11.88"><s n="s1.1;p11.88">In reality, a study of free electron behaviour cannot observe actual paths of individual electrons but must take the form of a study of how a material's response to an electric field of some kind varies with the application of a magnetic field. </s></p><p n="p12.88"><s n="s1.1;p12.88">The material's response on a macro scale is governed by the behaviour of its electrons; the average velocity of these electrons, their average response to applied fields, dictates the material's overall behaviour. </s></p><p n="p13.88"><s n="s1.1;p13.88">Between scattering events, the electrons move due to the Lorentz force, <hi rend="bold">F</hi>: </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p14.88"><s n="s1.1;p14.88"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0311g-form.002"/> (1) </s></p><p n="p15.88"><s n="s1.1;p15.88">which dictates an electron's basic response to applied fields. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">2.4 Hall Angles</head><p n="p16.88"><s n="s1.1;p16.88">In a uniform magnetic field, electron drift velocity, and hence current density, is not parallel to the electric field; current density <hi rend="bold italic">j</hi> is at an angle to the electric field <hi rend="bold">E</hi>: is known as the Hall angle. </s></p><p n="p17.88"><s n="s1.1;p17.88">If we assume that <hi rend="bold">B</hi> is in the z-direction and that <hi rend="bold">E</hi> is in the (positive) x-direction, knowing that in terms of drift velocities </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p18.88"><s n="s1.1;p18.88"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0311g-form.003"/> (2) </s></p><p n="p19.88"><s n="s1.1;p19.88">we can apply the steady state condition to the Drude equation to yield: </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p20.88"><s n="s1.1;p20.88"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0311g-form.004"/> (3) </s></p><p n="p21.88"><s n="s1.1;p21.88">and find an expression for the magnitude of this Hall angle. </s></p><p n="p22.88"><s n="s1.1;p22.88">From equation (3), we obtain: </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p23.88"><s n="s1.1;p23.88"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0311g-form.005"/> (4) </s></p><p n="p24.88"><s n="s1.1;p24.88">which, combined with (2) and defining <hi rend="italic">ωc=eB/m</hi>, gives us: </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p25.88"><s n="s1.1;p25.88"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0311g-form.006"/> (5) </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">2.5 The Hall Effect</head><p n="p26.88"><s n="s1.3;p26.88">Hall wanted to know if a magnet attracted the moving charges in a wire (the electrons) or if it was attracted to the wire itself. </s><s n="s2.3;p26.88">He suspected that the former was true, and postulated that this would lead to a build up of electrons on one side of the wire. </s><s n="s3.3;p26.88">He set about testing this theory by investigating the behaviour of these electrons. </s></p><p n="p27.88"><s n="s1.3;p27.88">Figure 2 Shows the Lorentz force deflects the electrons in the negative y direction, moving them up against one side of the wire. </s><s n="s2.3;p27.88">This causes the build up of an electric field opposing this motion and further accumulation of electrons. </s><s n="s3.3;p27.88">When equilibrium is reached, current will flow only in the x direction. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0311g-fig.002"><head><hi rend="bold">Fig. 2</hi> A schematic representation of the Hall effect</head></figure><p n="p28.88"><s n="s1.1;p28.88">Current density <hi rend="bold italic">j</hi> is given by: </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p29.88"><s n="s1.1;p29.88"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0311g-form.007"/> (6) </s></p><p n="p30.88"><s n="s1.1;p30.88">Where n is the number of free electrons and <hi rend="bold">v</hi><hi rend="sub">ave</hi> is the average velocity of the electrons. </s></p><p n="p31.88"><s n="s1.2;p31.88">In equilibrium E <hi rend="sub">y</hi> should act to balance the magnetic field, and thus would be expected to be proportional to both H and j <hi rend="sub">x</hi>. </s><s n="s2.2;p31.88">We thus define the Hall coefficient as: </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p32.88"><s n="s1.1;p32.88"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0311g-form.008"/> (7) </s></p><p n="p33.88"><s n="s1.1;p33.88">According to this model, the Hall coefficient should be negative, since the Hall field is in the negative y direction only. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">2.6 Magnetoresistance</head><p n="p34.88"><s n="s1.5;p34.88">Another effect Hall expected to observe was an increased resistance as a result of E <hi rend="sub">y</hi> due to the build up of the electrons. </s><s n="s2.5;p34.88">Drude tested this, expecting to find a field dependant resistance, but found no such thing. </s><s n="s3.5;p34.88">He did not however believe his findings to be conclusive. </s><s n="s4.5;p34.88">He postulated that if this was not observed, there would be other evidence, in the form of "a state of stress in the conductor, the electricity pressing, as it were, on one side of the wire". </s><s n="s5.5;p34.88">This takes the form of a voltage, which Hall was able to observe. </s></p><p n="p35.88"><s n="s1.1;p35.88">In the case of crossed fields a steady state for drift velocity can arise, and under these conditions conductivity can be found. </s></p><p n="p36.88"><s n="s1.1;p36.88">The alternative form of Ohm's law is </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p37.88"><s n="s1.1;p37.88"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0311g-form.009"/> (8) </s></p><p n="p38.88"><s n="s1.2;p38.88">Where <hi rend="bold italic">j</hi> is current density, <hi rend="bold italic">E</hi> electric field and <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0311g-form.010"/> the second rank conductivity tensor. </s><s n="s2.2;p38.88">We must use this tensorial form of Ohm's law because in the limit of large <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0311g-form.011"/> the case is that <hi rend="bold italic">j</hi> and <hi rend="bold italic">E</hi> are nearly perpendicular to each other, rather than parallel. </s></p><p n="p39.88"><s n="s1.1;p39.88">As <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0311g-form.012"/> and <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0311g-form.013"/>, we can find a set of equations that satisfy equation (3): </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p40.88"><s n="s1.1;p40.88"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0311g-form.014"/> (9) </s></p><p n="p41.88"><s n="s1.2;p41.88">Where <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0311g-form.015"/> is the Drude model DC conductivity in the absence of a magnetic field. </s><s n="s2.2;p41.88">If we say that <hi rend="italic">jy</hi> = 0, that is, no current is flowing out the sides of the wire, then: </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p42.88"><s n="s1.1;p42.88"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0311g-form.016"/> (10) </s></p><p n="p43.88"><s n="s1.3;p43.88">Where <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0311g-form.017"/> is the magnetoresistance, and this equation predicts it to be magnetic field independent. </s><s n="s2.3;p43.88"><hi rend="italic">RH</hi> is known as the Hall coefficient and is defined by this equation. </s><s n="s3.3;p43.88"><hi rend="italic">RH</hi> is also given in the form <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0311g-form.018"/>. </s></p><p n="p44.88"><s n="s1.1;p44.88">The conductivity tensor may be written: </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p45.88"><s n="s1.1;p45.88"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0311g-form.019"/> (11) </s></p><p n="p46.88"><s n="s1.1;p46.88">Which inversing gives the resistivity tensor: </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p47.88"><s n="s1.1;p47.88"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0311g-form.020"/> (12) </s></p><p n="p48.88"><s n="s1.1;p48.88">The <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0311g-form.021"/> component of this tensor is called the Hall Resistivity: </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p49.88"><s n="s1.1;p49.88"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0311g-form.022"/> (13) </s></p><p n="p50.88"><s n="s1.1;p50.88">This approach works the same for Drude and Sommerfeld models. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">2.7 Cyclotron Frequency</head><p n="p51.88"><s n="s1.2;p51.88">As the position of an electron in a magnetic field moves around in a circle, so too does the velocity of the electron. </s><s n="s2.2;p51.88">Whilst the position vector of an electron rotates around an arbitrary position, the velocity vector rotates around the origin in velocity space. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0311g-pic.001"><head><hi rend="bold">Fig 3.</hi> Position space on the left and velocity space on the right, which their relative vectors drawn on.</head></figure><p n="p52.88"><s n="s1.1;p52.88">Increasing the magnetic field causes the orbital radius of the electron to diminish, however the magnitude of the velocity stays the same. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0311g-pic.002"><head><hi rend="bold">Fig 4.</hi> Position space on the left and velocity space on the right, showing the shortening of the position vector and the velocity vector unchanged in a higher magnetic field.</head></figure><p n="p53.88"><s n="s1.3;p53.88">Due the shorter path the electron now takes in its orbit the velocity vector rotates faster accordingly. </s><s n="s2.3;p53.88">The rate at which the velocity of the electron changes in a magnetic field is directly proportional to the strength of that magnetic field. </s><s n="s3.3;p53.88">That relation is given by </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p54.88"><s n="s1.1;p54.88"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0311g-form.023"/> (14) </s></p><p n="p55.88"><s n="s1.1;p55.88">Where <hi rend="italic">B</hi> is the magnetic field, <hi rend="italic">e</hi> the electron charge, <hi rend="italic">m</hi> the electron mass, and <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0311g-form.024"/> the cyclotron frequency. </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">3. Experimental Details: General</head><p n="p56.88"><s n="s1.2;p56.88">These experiments utilised a computer simulation program 'drude' which encodes the concepts of the Drude model. </s><s n="s2.2;p56.88">The program allows for electric field (x and y components of), magnetic field (z component of), scattering time, temperature, and AC field frequency to be varied according to the requirements of the experiment. </s></p><p n="p57.88"><s n="s1.1;p57.88">The program displays the electron activity in real and velocity space, and is capable of plotting this behaviour on position-time and velocity-time graphs. </s></p><p n="p58.88"><s n="s1.2;p58.88">For comparative purposes, another program, 'sommer', was also considered. </s><s n="s2.2;p58.88">This simulation incorporates the concepts of the Sommerfeld model. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">4. Hall Angles</head><p n="p59.88"><s n="s1.2;p59.88">As discussed in 2.4, the Hall angle can be calculated via the x-direction and y-direction drift velocities. </s><s n="s2.2;p59.88">The theory predicts that will vary with the magnetic field and with scattering time (see equation 5). </s></p><p n="p60.88"><s n="s1.3;p60.88">The Drude model simulation was run a number of times with varying values of magnetic field B <hi rend="sub">z</hi> and scattering time τ. </s><s n="s2.3;p60.88">The component drift velocities were obtained from the gradients of the resulting position space graphs (of mean position against time). </s><s n="s3.3;p60.88">In each instance, the simulation was left to run for a sufficient period for the position space graph lines to approximate straight lines, for accurate measurement of gradients. </s></p><div2><head rend="bold">4.1 Hall Angles: Results</head><p n="p61.88"><s n="s1.1;p61.88">A plot of calculated (see equation 2) Hall angles against the product B.τ was obtained and compared to a theoretical plot: see figure 5. </s></p><p n="p62.88"><s n="s1.2;p62.88">Here error bars reflect the slight deviations from the position space graph lines from perfect straight lines (and hence possible error in gradient measurement) and also the uncertainty in determining gradients characteristic of the on-screen measuring method. </s><s n="s2.2;p62.88">The estimated errors in <hi rend="italic">v</hi><hi rend="sub">x</hi> and <hi rend="italic">v</hi><hi rend="sub">y</hi> propagate to an overall estimated error in Hall angle of 8%. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0311g-fig.003"><head><hi rend="bold">Fig. 5 Experimental and Theoretical Hall Angles against B.</hi> τ A plot of Hall angles from the data against the product of the magnitude of <hi rend="bold">B</hi> and scattering time τ , compared to the results predicted by theory (the red line).</head></figure></div2><div2><head rend="bold">4.2 Hall Angles: Discussion</head><p n="p63.88"><s n="s1.1;p63.88">The Drude model simulation gives Hall angles that are in agreement with the theoretical predictions to within estimated error. </s></p><p n="p64.88"><s n="s1.5;p64.88">In these cases, therefore, the Drude model appears to give an accurate account of Hall angles as they vary with magnetic field and scattering time. </s><s n="s2.5;p64.88">At first, there seems to be in this application no fundamental flaw, or omission, in the model giving rise to some systematic failure in the simulation. </s><s n="s3.5;p64.88">In fact, the model <hi rend="italic">does</hi> have a shortcoming in this area: in the simulation, with a positive x-direction electric field, we will always find the electron drift velocity in the third quadrant (the lower left of the window). </s><s n="s4.5;p64.88">Current density always appears to be deflected to the left; this is not representative of <hi rend="italic">all</hi> metals and semiconductors. </s><s n="s5.5;p64.88">There are many instances for which, in reality, the current density would be deflected the other way, resulting in a Hall angle with the opposite sign (see figures 6a and 6b). </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0311g-pic.003"><head><hi rend="bold">Fig. 6a</hi> Negative charge carriers (that is, electrons) are deflected by an x-direction E field.</head></figure><figure id="BAWE_0311g-pic.004"><head><hi rend="bold">Fig. 6b</hi> Positive charge carriers are deflected in the opposite direction, giving a Hall angle with reversed sign. Note that current density remains in the same direction due to the moving <hi rend="italic">positive</hi> charges.</head></figure><p n="p65.88"><s n="s1.2;p65.88">The problem arises from the Drude model making no allowances for non-negative charge carriers; the sign of is reversed if the carriers are positively charged. </s><s n="s2.2;p65.88">This shortcoming also makes problems for the Drude model in predicting Hall coefficients, and will be discussed in greater depths later. </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">5. Hall Effect</head><p n="p66.88"><s n="s1.4;p66.88">E <hi rend="sub">x</hi> was fixed at 2x10 <hi rend="sup">5</hi> Vm <hi rend="sup">-1</hi>, E <hi rend="sub">y</hi> at 0, B <hi rend="sub">z</hi> at 2T and T to 300K. τ was set as to be high enough as to be assumed infinite. </s><s n="s2.4;p66.88">A 1000 picosecond simulation was run, and a graph plotted of mean position against time, from which the gradient can be taken and used to calculate the mean velocity of the electrons in the system. </s><s n="s3.4;p66.88">The simulation was run with one, two and three electrons in the system, to represent valence atoms. </s><s n="s4.4;p66.88">Using equations (6) and (7), <hi rend="bold italic">j</hi> and subsequently R <hi rend="sub">H</hi> were calculated. </s></p><table id="BAWE_0311g-tab.001"><head><hi rend="bold">Table 1.</hi> Showing experimental and calculated values for the Hall coefficient and related results.</head><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p67.88"><s n="s1.5;p67.88">It can be seen from table 1 that the simulated data for elements with a valence of one or two agrees closely with data obtained from experiment. </s><s n="s2.5;p67.88">For elements with a valence of three however, there is a discrepancy: The experimental data shows these elements to have a positive Hall coefficient, whereas the simulation gives a negative coefficient. </s><s n="s3.5;p67.88">One explanation for this would be if the charge carriers were positive, and hence the Hall field in the positive y direction. </s><s n="s4.5;p67.88">It is now known that charge carriers are sometimes 'holes' - absences of electrons. </s><s n="s5.5;p67.88">These are a phenomenon that require quantum theory to explain, and so are not accounted for by the Drude model. </s></p><p n="p68.88"><s n="s1.2;p68.88">The main improvement of the Sommerfeld model on the Drude model is the addition of the exclusion principle. </s><s n="s2.2;p68.88">Although the Sommerfeld model does take some quantum effects into account, it still makes no allowance for positive charge carriers (holes) and therefore does not solve this problem. </s></p><p n="p69.88"><s n="s1.2;p69.88">It has been observed that elements with greater numbers of non-conduction electrons obey this relationship less well, since the Drude model does not take account of what type of scattering is taking place. </s><s n="s2.2;p69.88">Since the model does not take this into account, it is not possible to replicate the effect in the simulation. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">6. Magnetoresistance</head><p n="p70.88"><s n="s1.2;p70.88">In the Drude simulation it is possible to choose a value for the y-component of the electric field to give zero drift velocity in the y-direction. </s><s n="s2.2;p70.88">See figure 7. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0311g-fig.004"><head><hi rend="bold">Fig 7.</hi> A force diagram showing that an electric field in the y-direction can cancel out the Lorentz force and keep the drift velocity in the x-direction only.</head></figure><p n="p71.88"><s n="s1.3;p71.88">Setting the experimental parameters as E <hi rend="sub">x</hi> = 10x10 <hi rend="sup">4</hi> V/m, E <hi rend="sub">y</hi> = -9x10 <hi rend="sup">4</hi> V/m, B = 1 T, τ = 6 ps, gives the relation; Mean Position (10 <hi rend="sup">-6</hi> m) = 0.0922 (m/s) x Time Elapsed (ps). </s><s n="s2.3;p71.88">Turning off the magnetic field and the y-component of the E field gives drift velocity to be 0.0905 m/s. </s><s n="s3.3;p71.88">The similarity of the drift velocities shows that the Drude model does not account for the increased resistance due to a magnetic field. </s></p><p n="p72.88"><s n="s1.1;p72.88">Because the Drude model neglects electron-electron interaction then it is not possible for electrons to form a backlog in the material, slowing the approaching electrons and manifesting as a resistance. </s></p><p n="p73.88"><s n="s1.3;p73.88">As the Sommerfeld model also neglects electron-electron interaction it too falsely predicts zero magnetoresistance. </s><s n="s2.3;p73.88">If such interactions were to be taken into account then it would be found that the resistance of material would depend on the magnetic field as well as the temperature. </s><s n="s3.3;p73.88">The complexity of the electron motion in a magnetic field leads us to expect a certain amount of resistance. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">7. Cyclotron Frequency</head><p n="p74.88"><s n="s1.2;p74.88">In crossed electric and magnetic fields charged particles, such as electrons, follow circular trajectories in real space and also velocity space. </s><s n="s2.2;p74.88">The rate of change in this velocity space has a constant angular frequency, known as the cyclotron frequency. </s></p><div2><head rend="bold">7.1 Cyclotron Resonance</head><p n="p75.88"><s n="s1.2;p75.88">Using equation (14) with a B field of 1 T gives <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0311g-form.025"/> as <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0311g-form.026"/>. </s><s n="s2.2;p75.88">This is a cyclotron resonant frequency. </s></p><p n="p76.88"><s n="s1.3;p76.88">The Drude simulation provides a way of observing the effect of an alternating electric field on a sample of free electrons. </s><s n="s2.3;p76.88">The experimental settings were E <hi rend="sub">y</hi> = 0 V/m, B <hi rend="sub">z</hi> = 1 T, τ = 6 ps, T = 1 K, <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0311g-form.027"/> = 0. </s><s n="s3.3;p76.88">E <hi rend="sub">x</hi> oscillates sinusoidal between ±3x10 <hi rend="sup">4</hi> V/m with a variable frequency of Ω. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0311g-fig.005"><head><hi rend="bold">Fig 8.</hi> Mean velocity plotted against time for an electron in an electric field oscillating at 0.16 THz, the periodic variation in the envelope of the oscillations (beats) is clearly shown.</head></figure><p n="p77.88"><s n="s1.2;p77.88">By changing Ω we can study the effect of resonance by observing the duration of the beats. </s><s n="s2.2;p77.88">Longer duration meaning more resonant. </s></p><table id="BAWE_0311g-tab.002"><head><hi rend="bold">Table 2.</hi> Showing the length of a beat in relation to the frequency of the electric field in the x-direction.</head><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p78.88"><s n="s1.2;p78.88">As predicted from equation (14) there is cyclotron resonance at 1.758x10 <hi rend="sup">11</hi> Hz, where the beats take on the maximum duration. </s><s n="s2.2;p78.88">The electrons also have the highest maximum velocity at this frequency; although this was not recorded it is not quantitatively important to this investigation. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">7.2 Cyclotron Frequency Phase Offset</head><figure id="BAWE_0311g-fig.006"><head><hi rend="bold">Fig 9.</hi> In between beats the velocity does not achieve zero acceleration when the mean velocity is zero. Either the electron is accelerating through 0 m/s or stops accelerating at a certain velocity, so it is still moving. This implies that the energy transfer between the electron and the electric field is incomplete.</head></figure><p n="p79.88"><s n="s1.1;p79.88">Due to the incompleteness of energy transfer between beats, there is a phase offset between the mean velocity and the electric field. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0311g-fig.007"><head><hi rend="bold">Fig 10.</hi> Mean velocity against time. The blue line represents the mean velocity and the red line electric field. Initially in-phase, after the beat there is a shift so that the velocity now lags behind the electric field.</head></figure><p n="p80.88"><s n="s1.3;p80.88">It is possible to find a relation between the phase shift and Ω. </s><s n="s2.3;p80.88">Using the same experimental setup as the last cyclotron experiment, Ω was varied between 0.155 THz and 0.195 THz. </s><s n="s3.3;p80.88">The phase shift was calculated from a close-up section in between the beats, as shown in figure 10. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0311g-fig.008"><head><hi rend="bold">Fig 11.</hi> The linear relation between phase shift and cyclotron frequency.</head></figure><p n="p81.88"><s n="s1.3;p81.88">From figure 11, <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0311g-form.028"/>. </s><s n="s2.3;p81.88">Note this is normalised phase shift, so <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0311g-form.029"/> is <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0311g-form.030"/> out of phase. </s><s n="s3.3;p81.88">Note also that there the resonance around 0.1750 THz has no effect on the phase shift between the mean velocity and the electric field. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">7.3 Cyclotron Resonance as a function of Mean Scattering Time</head><p n="p82.88"><s n="s1.3;p82.88">Cyclotron resonance is also a function of τ, the mean time before scattering. </s><s n="s2.3;p82.88">For this experiment Ω was fixed at 0.18 THz, which gives a beat duration, or resonance width, of 1520 ps when τ is higher than 1.5x10 <hi rend="sup">3</hi> ps. </s><s n="s3.3;p82.88">This is expected and found, as if there is a long scattering time, the electron will be able to complete a full resonance cycle going from minimum velocity, to peak velocity and back down again. </s></p><p n="p83.88"><s n="s1.3;p83.88">For τ &lt; 1.0x10 <hi rend="sup">3</hi> ps the resonance width is cut short. </s><s n="s2.3;p83.88">The electron scatters whilst travelling far faster than the temperature distribution would allow for, as so its velocity is brought back down rapidly. </s><s n="s3.3;p83.88">This is shown in figure 12. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0311g-fig.009"><head><hi rend="bold">Fig 12.</hi> Resonances peaks building up before scattering occurs bringing the velocity of the electron down again.</head></figure></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">8. Conclusion</head><p n="p84.88"><s n="s1.3;p84.88">In conclusion, the classical Drude model suffers from some limitations, but if applied in the appropriate cases can be quite useful for predicting the behaviour of free electrons. </s><s n="s2.3;p84.88">The Sommerfeld model addresses some of the problems of the earlier model by including the Pauli exclusion principle: it gives a better account of thermal and electrical conductivity. </s><s n="s3.3;p84.88">In this investigation, however, the Sommerfeld model does not have a great advantage over the Drude model, since they both encounter problems regarding the Hall effect and magnetoresistance. </s></p><p n="p85.88"><s n="s1.3;p85.88">The Hall angles predicted by theory and those obtained from the Drude model simulation agreed to within estimated error. </s><s n="s2.3;p85.88">The shortcoming here is that since the Drude model is only equipped to deal with negative charge carriers (that is, electrons), it cannot consider the Hall angles obtained with positive charge carriers (that is, holes). </s><s n="s3.3;p85.88">In the case of holes, the sign of the Hall angle would be reversed; there is no allowance for this in the Drude model. </s></p><p n="p86.88"><s n="s1.3;p86.88">For metallic atoms with valences of 1 or 2, the model simulation gave accurate (to within estimated errors) Hall coefficients. </s><s n="s2.3;p86.88">However, for valences of 3, it gave Hall coefficients with the wrong sign. </s><s n="s3.3;p86.88">This is again due to the inability of the Drude model to take into account positive charge carriers. </s></p><p n="p87.88"><s n="s1.4;p87.88">The Drude model gives no account of magnetoresistance, as it neglects electron-electron interactions. </s><s n="s2.4;p87.88">The Sommerfeld model similarly neglects these interactions, and so does not provide a suitable solution. </s><s n="s3.4;p87.88">Cyclotron frequency is shown by the model to be proportional to the applied magnetic field. </s><s n="s4.4;p87.88">If the frequency of the external AC electric field is varied, then cyclotron resonance can be obtained. </s></p><p n="p88.88"><s n="s1.2;p88.88">The Drude model is therefore a simple and convenient one if applied with restrictions; these restrictions are formulated with an awareness of the shortcomings of the model, as discussed above. </s><s n="s2.2;p88.88">The cases where the Drude model (and the Sommerfeld model) cannot be applied, as in investigations into magnetoresistance, for example, must be approached with different, perhaps more elaborate, models: models which take into account the various effects which are neglected in the Drude and Sommerfeld approaches. </s></p></div1></body><back><div1 type="bibliography"><head rend="bold">9. References</head><p>This investigation made use of the Solid State Simulation project's simulation programs 'drude' and 'sommer', available at:</p><p><seg type="URL" n="http://www.ruph.cornell.edu/sss/sss.html"/></p><p>along with its companion book:</p><p>Robert H. Silsbee and Jörg Dräger, <hi rend="italic">Simulations for Solid State Physics</hi>, CUP, 1997</p><div2 type="bibliography"><head rend="bold">Other references:</head><p>J.S. Blakemore, <hi rend="italic">Solid State Physics</hi>, CUP, 1985</p><p>Neil W. Ashcroft and N. David Mermin, <hi rend="italic">Solid State Physics -International Edition</hi>, Saunders College Publishing, 1976</p><p>Charles Kittel, <hi rend="italic">Introduction to Solid State Physics - Seventh Edition</hi>, Wiley, 1996 </p></div2></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
