<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_0311f" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Report on Ultrasound (Experiment P1)</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">The document has a title page which contains:
document title
title part
abstract</note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">deleted: footer: student name, page number, assignment title
</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">2</p><p n="date">2004-01</p><p n="module title">Physics Essay</p><p n="module code">PX271</p><p n="genre family">Methodology recount</p><p n="discipline">Physics</p><p n="disciplinary group">PS</p><p n="grade">M</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">4420</p><p n="number of s-units">199</p><p n="number of p">100</p><p n="number of tables">5</p><p n="number of figures">10</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">12</p><p n="number of lists">0</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">11</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">22.2</p><p n="average s-units per p">2.0</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">m</p><p n="year of birth">1984</p><p n="first language">English</p><p n="education">UKA</p><p n="course">MPhys</p><p n="student ID">0311</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><docTitle><titlePart>Report on Ultrasound (Experiment P1)</titlePart></docTitle><titlePart rend="bold"><name type="student name"/></titlePart></titlePage><div1 type="abstract"><head rend="underlined bold">Abstract</head><p>The velocity of longitudinal, shear, and surface, ultrasound waves in various solids was found to be in good agreement with the expected values and the governing theory. The attenuation of the ultrasound waves was more than expected. The angle at which a mode converted shear wave refracts was unexpected. Defects in an object were found and improved method suggested. The wavelength of a surface wave was unsuccessful.</p></div1></front><body><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">. Introduction</head><p n="p1.100"><s n="s1.3;p1.100">Ultrasound is the range of acoustic frequencies above the range audible to the human ear, or above approximately 20,000 Hertz. </s><s n="s2.3;p1.100">Ultrasound is used commercially as a method of non-destructive testing. </s><s n="s3.3;p1.100">It can be used to determine object thickness, detect cracks, and ascertain various properties of the materials being tested. </s></p><p n="p2.100"><s n="s1.1;p2.100">The range of uses for ultrasound makes ultrasonics an important area for research. </s></p><p n="p3.100"><s n="s1.1;p3.100">Ultrasound is used medically for such activities as prenatal scans and can measure blood flow using the Doppler shift of the ultrasound waves. </s></p><p n="p4.100"><s n="s1.1;p4.100">Today it is possible to place a component for testing in a tank of water (used as an ultrasonic couplant since air attenuates the signal greatly) and computer controlled robotic arms with transducers will scan the object, feeding the data into a computer for evaluation. </s></p><p n="p5.100"><s n="s1.2;p5.100">The University of <name type="university"/> ultrasonics group <hi rend="sup">[1]</hi> has research areas in thickness gauging, weld and bond inspection to name a few. </s><s n="s2.2;p5.100">They use laser ultrasound, plasma ultrasound, EMATs and piezoelectric transducers, which this report will focus on. </s></p><p n="p6.100"><s n="s1.2;p6.100">Since all material is comprised of atoms, and in a solid these atoms are held in equilibrium by internal electrostatic forces, it is possible to produce a mechanical wave in the object. </s><s n="s2.2;p6.100">The atoms will move together and if the material is not forced beyond its elastic limits then the atoms will return to their equilibrium position. </s></p><p n="p7.100"><s n="s1.2;p7.100">The inertia of the atoms and the electrostatic restoring force causes oscillatory motion to be established in the object. </s><s n="s2.2;p7.100">In solids, acoustic waves have three main methods of propagation; longitudinal, shear, and surface. </s></p><p n="p8.100"><s n="s1.2;p8.100">Longitudinal waves have oscillatory motion in the direction of propagation. </s><s n="s2.2;p8.100">They consist of areas of higher density (compression) followed by lower density (rarefaction) and are sometimes called compressional waves. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0311f-pic.001"><head><hi rend="bold">Figure 1:</hi> A longitudinal wave propagating across the page. The thicker lines represent the areas of compression between atoms while the thinner lines are the areas of rarefaction caused by the wave. One wavelength is the distance between two lines of the same thickness.</head></figure><p n="p9.100"><s n="s1.3;p9.100">Shear waves have oscillatory motion perpendicular to the direction of propagation and are also called transverse waves. </s><s n="s2.3;p9.100">They require an acoustically solid material and consequently are greatly attenuated in liquids and gases. </s><s n="s3.3;p9.100">They are usually created from the energy of a longitudinal wave and so are comparatively weak. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0311f-pic.002"><head><hi rend="bold">Figure 2:</hi> A shear wave propagating across the page. The rows of atoms stay the same distance apart from each other but are pulled side-to-side by the electrostatic forces. One wavelength is the distance between two rows of the same displacement.</head></figure><p n="p10.100"><s n="s1.4;p10.100">Surface waves, or Rayleigh waves, propagate along surface of the object and the energy of the wave is exponentially diminished the further down into the material the wave gets. </s><s n="s2.4;p10.100">Most of the energy is contained within a layer with depth equal to the wavelength of the surface wave. </s><s n="s3.4;p10.100">The particle movement is elliptical in fashion. </s><s n="s4.4;p10.100">This type of wave follows the surface closely and so is useful for inspecting areas that other waves could not reach so easily. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0311f-pic.003"><head><hi rend="bold">Figure 3:</hi> A Rayleigh wave propagating from left to right across the page. The particle motion is elliptical with the magnitude of the ellipses decreasing exponentially the deeper into the material.</head></figure><p n="p11.100"><s n="s1.1;p11.100">Other wave modes are possible in solids that go beyond the scope of this introduction and so are not mentioned here. </s></p><p n="p12.100"><s n="s1.5;p12.100">The wavelength of the ultrasound is critical for the detection of flaws in a material. </s><s n="s2.5;p12.100">The "sensitivity" of the apparatus is the capability to detect a small flaw whereas the "resolution" is the capability to discern flaws close together or near the surface of the object. </s><s n="s3.5;p12.100">Both increase when wavelength decreases. </s><s n="s4.5;p12.100">However, as wavelength decreases it becomes more liable to scatter and so the penetration of ultrasound into the object is reduced. </s><s n="s5.5;p12.100">Consequently it is hard to have an ultrasound beam that can resolve fine detail deep into an object. </s></p><p n="p13.100"><s n="s1.1;p13.100">Other variables that can affect flaw detection include the diameter of the transducer, the voltage given to the crystal, and the type of crystal used. </s></p><p n="p14.100"><s n="s1.2;p14.100">Ideally the ultrasonic energy would only be reduced by the spreading of the sound wave but in real solids scattering and absorption also occurs. </s><s n="s2.2;p14.100">Attenuation is the combined effects of these phenomena and is expressed as: </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p15.100"><s n="s1.1;p15.100"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0311f-form.001"/> (1) </s></p><p n="p16.100"><s n="s1.1;p16.100">Where <hi rend="italic">A0</hi> is the amplitude at the initial location, <hi rend="italic">A</hi> is the attenuated amplitude at a distance <hi rend="italic">z</hi> from the initial location α is Nepers per length. </s></p><p n="p17.100"><s n="s1.3;p17.100">Nepers is a dimensionless quantity like decibels. </s><s n="s2.3;p17.100">1 dB is 0.1151 Np. </s><s n="s3.3;p17.100">They are both related to the ratio of intensity (or sound pressure squared) the difference being decibels take the base-10 log and Nepers takes the natural log. </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p18.100"><s n="s1.1;p18.100"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0311f-form.002"/> (2) </s></p><p n="p19.100"><s n="s1.2;p19.100">As ultrasound is a wave it experiences refraction at the interface between two materials of different densities. </s><s n="s2.2;p19.100">Snell's Law governs this behaviour at a planar interface. </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p20.100"><s n="s1.1;p20.100"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0311f-form.003"/> (3a) </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p21.100"><s n="s1.1;p21.100"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0311f-form.004"/> (3b) </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0311f-fig.001"><head><hi rend="bold">Figure 4:</hi> A longitudinal travelling at <hi rend="italic">V</hi><hi rend="sub">1</hi> going from a less dense medium to denser one at angle θ<hi rend="sub">1</hi> . The longitudinal wave travelling at <hi rend="italic">VL</hi> and the shear wave travelling at <hi rend="italic">VS</hi> are refracted according the Snell's Law.</head></figure><p n="p22.100"><s n="s1.3;p22.100">In the case where the longitudinal wave passes into a denser medium it is possible for the refracted angle to equal 90°. </s><s n="s2.3;p22.100">This is the first critical angle and produces a surface acoustic wave (SAW) called a creep wave. </s><s n="s3.3;p22.100">These have a longer wavelength than Rayleigh waves but as they are of an inhomogeneous nature and decay rapidly they are not as useful as Rayleigh waves. </s></p><p n="p23.100"><s n="s1.3;p23.100">When a wave encounters an medium with different acoustic impedance and a non-perpendicular incidence angle something called "mode conversion" occurs. </s><s n="s2.3;p23.100">A longitudinal wave hitting another material will produce a shear wave. </s><s n="s3.3;p23.100">As shear waves move with a velocity less than that of the longitudinal wave then according to Snell's Law the refraction angle will be less than the refraction angle for the longitudinal wave (see Figure 4). </s></p><p n="p24.100"><s n="s1.2;p24.100">The second critical angle is found by increasing the incident angle past the first critical angle to where the refracted shear wave angle becomes 90°. </s><s n="s2.2;p24.100">This produces a shear creep wave that moves along the interface. </s></p><p n="p25.100"><s n="s1.2;p25.100">Adjusting the incidence angle to slightly beyond the second critical angle causes the Rayleigh surface waves to be generated. </s><s n="s2.2;p25.100">These travel slower than shear waves, which in turn travel slower than longitudinal waves. </s></p><p n="p26.100"><s n="s1.5;p26.100">The foundation for ultrasound production is in the piezoelectric transducers and their property of being able to convert electrical signals into mechanic vibration and vice versa. </s><s n="s2.5;p26.100">The crystal is a polarised material, with some parts positive and some negative, and it has electrodes attached to opposite sides. </s><s n="s3.5;p26.100">When an electric field is applied across the electrodes the crystal undergoes electrostriction whereby its dimensions are changed. </s><s n="s4.5;p26.100">In some crystals, such as Quartz, which are permanently polarised, a force changing the dimensions causes an electric field so the effect can work both ways. </s><s n="s5.5;p26.100">This is called the piezoelectric effect. </s></p><p n="p27.100"><s n="s1.2;p27.100">In the 1950's the piezoelectric effect was discovered in ceramics, by 1960 lead zirconate titanate compositions were being widely used. </s><s n="s2.2;p27.100">These ceramic acoustic transducers have the advantages of being produced in a variety of shapes to produce different wave modes, operating at a lower voltage and usable up to 300°C. </s></p><p n="p28.100"><s n="s1.2;p28.100">The vibrating piezoelectric element produces ultrasound with a wavelength of twice its thickness. </s><s n="s2.2;p28.100">The main reason high resolution transducers cannot be produced is because the element required would be very thin and delicate. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0311f-pic.004"><head><hi rend="bold">Figure 5:</hi> A contact transducer showing the following parts; backing material, piezoelectric element, matching layer, wear plate. This is not to scale.</head></figure><p n="p29.100"><s n="s1.2;p29.100">To get maximum energy the matching layer will be of the same acoustic impedance to the piezoelectric element and will have a thickness of a quarter wavelength. </s><s n="s2.2;p29.100">This keeps the reflected waves inside the matching layer in phase since the wave will have to travel twice the quarter wavelength. </s></p><p n="p30.100"><s n="s1.3;p30.100">The wear plate simple protects the matching layer from getting scratched. </s><s n="s2.3;p30.100">The backing material has a large affect on the overall damping properties of the transducer. </s><s n="s3.3;p30.100">Similar impedance to the element will produce maximal damping causing a narrow bandwidth and high sensitivity. </s></p><p n="p31.100"><s n="s1.2;p31.100">There are many forms of contact transducer but the ones that concern us here are the direct-contact sort and the wedge sort. </s><s n="s2.2;p31.100">The wedge transducer is carefully designed to cut out most of the longitudinal wave energy and only transmit the shear wave into the material in order to generate surface waves. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><div2><div3><head rend="bold">2.1.1 Bulk Wave Generation: Details</head><figure id="BAWE_0311f-pic.005"><head><hi rend="bold">Figure 6:</hi> Experimental setup for experiment.</head></figure><p n="p32.100"><s n="s1.4;p32.100">The pulser/receiver outputs a 5 MHz signal to a transducer and the scope. </s><s n="s2.4;p32.100">The initial pulse is the trigger and following ultrasonic echoes are plotted against time. </s><s n="s3.4;p32.100">The vertical axis displayed on the scope represents the energy of the echoes in millivolts. </s><s n="s4.4;p32.100">The signals received over many cycles are averaged to gain a better signal to noise ratio and consequently the results will be more accurate. </s></p><p n="p33.100"><s n="s1.1;p33.100">The length of the object is measured using Vernier callipers. </s></p><p n="p34.100"><s n="s1.5;p34.100">The aim of this experiment is to find the velocity of longitudinal ultrasound waves in a variety of different materials. </s><s n="s2.5;p34.100">The velocity is obtained by knowing the length of the material then measuring the time it takes for the pulse to travel to the bottom of the material, be reflected, and travel back up through the material. </s><s n="s3.5;p34.100">Distance over time gives the velocity of the wave. </s><s n="s4.5;p34.100">For added accuracy it is possible to plot the time the echoes were received against the distance that echo would have travelled (integer multiples of length). </s><s n="s5.5;p34.100">The straight line produced would have a gradient equal to the velocity. </s></p><p n="p35.100"><s n="s1.1;p35.100">By knowing <hi rend="italic">v</hi>, the velocity of the wave and ρ, the density, it will be possible to estimate <hi rend="italic">E</hi>, the Young's modulus. </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p36.100"><s n="s1.1;p36.100"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0311f-form.005"/> (4) </s></p><p n="p37.100"><s n="s1.1;p37.100">An equation for Poisson's ratio υ, is given as: </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p38.100"><s n="s1.1;p38.100"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0311f-form.006"/> (5) </s></p><p n="p39.100"><s n="s1.1;p39.100">Where <hi rend="italic">L</hi> is the longitudinal wave velocity and <hi rend="italic">S</hi> the shear wave velocity. </s></p><p n="p40.100"><s n="s1.1;p40.100">Rearranging equation 1 and using base-10 to get decibels: </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p41.100"><s n="s1.1;p41.100"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0311f-form.007"/> (6) </s></p><p n="p42.100"><s n="s1.2;p42.100">So by taking the log of the ratio of amplitudes for successive ultrasonic echoes and plotting against distance the attenuation of the materials can be found. </s><s n="s2.2;p42.100">For a sample with perfectly flat and parallel sides the decay should be exponential. </s></p></div3><div3><head rend="bold">2.1.2 Bulk Wave Generation: Results</head><p n="p43.100"><s n="s1.3;p43.100">The distance against time graphs are Figures 7 to 12 inclusive. </s><s n="s2.3;p43.100">The error in time is due to the pulse being spread out in space and so the head of the wave arrives at a different time to the tail. </s><s n="s3.3;p43.100">The error in the length of the material is negligible, despite increasing with successive echoes, as the uncertainty in length was 0.000005 m. </s></p><table id="BAWE_0311f-tab.001"><head><hi rend="bold">Table 1:</hi> The velocities calculated from the graphs with the regressional error are shown in column 2. Column 3 contains the expected values. The densities of the materials are listed and the calculated Young's modulus given. The expected Young's modulus is in the final column.</head><row><cell/></row></table><table id="BAWE_0311f-tab.002"><head><hi rend="bold">Table 2:</hi> Using equation 4 with the measured values for longitudinal wave velocity and the book values for shear wave velocity it is possible to work out Poisson's ratio for the various materials.</head><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p44.100"><s n="s1.1;p44.100">The log of amplitude over initial amplitude against distance graphs, showing attenuation, are Figures 13 to 18 inclusive. </s></p><table id="BAWE_0311f-tab.003"><head><hi rend="bold">Table 3:</hi> Summary table of attenuation. For Aluminium the expected value is 0.40 Np/m for a 10MHz signal, and for Glass it is 2.65 Np/m.<hi rend="sup">[6]</hi></head><row><cell/></row></table></div3><div3><head rend="bold">2.1.3 Bulk Wave Generation: Discussion</head><p n="p45.100"><s n="s1.5;p45.100">The measured velocities were in good agreement with the expected values. </s><s n="s2.5;p45.100">However the error for the measurement does not cover the actual value and so the actual error present in the experiment must be far larger than the assumed error. </s><s n="s3.5;p45.100">This is due to a systematic error present in the setup. </s><s n="s4.5;p45.100">There might have been anisotropy in the objects so testing again in different directions could help. </s><s n="s5.5;p45.100">It is more likely however that the densities of the objects tested were of different densities to the objects tested for the textbook values. </s></p><p n="p46.100"><s n="s1.4;p46.100">The Young's modulus results are not in agreement with the expected values. </s><s n="s2.4;p46.100">Especially the Copper and Mild Steel results. </s><s n="s3.4;p46.100">This systematic error is because the equation used is only accurate when the object is 'thin' compared to the wavelength. </s><s n="s4.4;p46.100">Knowing the material's Poisson's ratio υ, and shear modulus <hi rend="italic">G</hi>, it is possible to calculate Young's modulus <hi rend="italic">E</hi>, accurately: </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p47.100"><s n="s1.1;p47.100"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0311f-form.008"/> (7) </s></p><p n="p48.100"><s n="s1.1;p48.100">The Poisson's ratio results are in good agreement with expected values. </s></p><p n="p49.100"><s n="s1.5;p49.100">The attenuation was difficult to measure consistently. </s><s n="s2.5;p49.100">The amount of couplant used and the pressure on the transducer had dramatic effects. </s><s n="s3.5;p49.100">Figure 19 shows the A-scan for mild steel. </s><s n="s4.5;p49.100">Note the erroneous peaks between the echoes of the pulse that seem to increase in amplitude as time goes on. </s><s n="s5.5;p49.100">This repeatable phenomenon might be due to mode converted shear waves added up inside the block. </s></p><p n="p50.100"><s n="s1.4;p50.100">The values were obtained with a 5 MHz signal. </s><s n="s2.4;p50.100">Since acoustic attenuation is proportional to frequency <hi rend="sup">4</hi> the 10 MHz signal used for the expected values should be 16 times greater than the measured values. </s><s n="s3.4;p50.100">In fact, the measured values were just under 3 times less attenuated rather than 16. </s><s n="s4.4;p50.100">This could be for many reasons the most reasonable being the roughness of the object's interfaces caused excess scattering. </s></p><p n="p51.100"><s n="s1.1;p51.100">This would have been a more repeatable experiment if a non-contact transducer were used, such as an EMAT or laser since the couplant was a large variable in the detection of the ultrasound waves. </s></p></div3><div3><head rend="bold">2.2.1 Mode Conversion: Details</head><figure id="BAWE_0311f-pic.006"><head><hi rend="bold">Figure 20:</hi> The transmitter (on the left) is connected to the pulser/receiver as in Figure 6. The receiver transducer (on top of the Aluminium block) is connected to the scope. The transmitted longitudinal wave is reflected at the same angle it was incident to the plane. Couplant was used and the dimensions of the object were measured with a Vernier calliper.</head></figure><p n="p52.100"><s n="s1.3;p52.100">As described in the introduction mode conversion will occur when the longitudinal wave encounters the bottom of the block. </s><s n="s2.3;p52.100">The ultrasound transmitter will produce a divergent beam but θ can be found from the maximum amplitude of shear wave arrival. </s><s n="s3.3;p52.100">The shear was will be refracted more than the longitudinal wave as it travels at a slower velocity. </s></p><p n="p53.100"><s n="s1.1;p53.100">The velocity of the shear wave can also be calculated from the geometry of the object since the total time from transmit to receive will be: </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p54.100"><s n="s1.1;p54.100"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0311f-form.009"/> (8) </s></p><p n="p55.100"><s n="s1.2;p55.100">Where <hi rend="italic">dL</hi> is the distance travelled by the longitudinal wave down to the interface, <hi rend="italic">dS</hi> is the distance travelled up from the interface to the receiver and <hi rend="italic">vL</hi> and <hi rend="italic">vS</hi> are the velocities of the longitudinal and shear waves respectively. </s><s n="s2.2;p55.100">However, this equation does not take into account the time the waves spent travelling through the wear plates of the transducers. </s></p></div3><div3><head rend="bold">2.2.2 Mode Conversion: Results</head><p n="p56.100"><s n="s1.1;p56.100">The receiver was in this position when the shear wave amplitude was greatest: </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0311f-pic.007"><head><hi rend="bold">Figure 21:</hi> The position of the receiver when the shear wave amplitude was greatest.</head></figure><p n="p57.100"><s n="s1.3;p57.100">To find out the angle θ, trigonometry can be employed and since we know the lengths of all three sides of the right-angled triangle, three values can be sought. </s><s n="s2.3;p57.100">These turn out to be 55.1° for the tangent, 55.4° for the sine, and 54.4° for the cosine. </s><s n="s3.3;p57.100">Averaging these values gives 55.0°. </s></p><p n="p58.100"><s n="s1.3;p58.100">Referring to Figure 21: there were two pulses picked up by the receiver in this position. </s><s n="s2.3;p58.100">The foremost pulse is the fast moving longitudinal wave and the later one is the shear wave, arriving at <hi rend="italic">tS</hi> = 36.8 μs. </s><s n="s3.3;p58.100">Rearranging equation 8: </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p59.100"><s n="s1.1;p59.100"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0311f-form.010"/> (9) </s></p><p n="p60.100"><s n="s1.2;p60.100">Plugging in the known values of the right hand side of equation 9 gives us a shear wave velocity of 3264 (±44) ms <hi rend="sup">-1</hi>. </s><s n="s2.2;p60.100">The expected value being 3111 ms <hi rend="sup">-1</hi>.<hi rend="sup">[7]</hi> </s></p><p n="p61.100"><s n="s1.2;p61.100">Using Snell's Law (equation 3) the angle the shear wave is expected to arrive from can be determined by knowing the velocities of the waves and the incidence angle. </s><s n="s2.2;p61.100">Plugging in the values for longitudinal velocity, shear wave velocity, and the incidence angle gives the expected shear wave refraction to be 69°. </s></p></div3><div3><head rend="bold">2.2.3 Mode Conversion: Discussion</head><p n="p62.100"><s n="s1.2;p62.100">The high precision of the Vernier calliper, combined with the three separate calculations of angle showing the setup to be a very close to a right-angled triangle, means there is a good reliability that the receiver was at a 55° offset to the point of refraction. </s><s n="s2.2;p62.100">The transmitter beam was at 45° to the base of the object and it is assumed that the transducers emit ultrasound perpendicular to their bases. </s></p><p n="p63.100"><s n="s1.1;p63.100">Therefore it is surprising that the expected shear wave maxima would occur 14° away from the experimentally measured maxima occurred. </s></p><p n="p64.100"><s n="s1.2;p64.100">The velocity measured using the travelling time of the waves produced a result in good agreement with the expected value. </s><s n="s2.2;p64.100">However, the error in the measurement was too small; the velocities of the waves as they moved through the transducer parts were not taken into account. </s></p></div3><div3><head rend="bold">2.3.1 Detecting and Sizing Defects: Details</head><figure id="BAWE_0311f-pic.008"><head><hi rend="bold">Figure 22:</hi> A block with flat-bottomed holes in. The transducer is connected in the same way as shown in Figure 6.</head></figure><p n="p65.100"><s n="s1.2;p65.100">Ultrasound is used predominantly in non-destructive testing to determine the internal structure of solids. </s><s n="s2.2;p65.100">The detection and sizing of defects is an important industrial procedure, relying on the 6 dB drop technique. </s></p><p n="p66.100"><s n="s1.2;p66.100">A 6 dB drop in amplitude is indicative that the sound pressure has been attenuated to half its initial amplitude. </s><s n="s2.2;p66.100">Using equation 2 and letting the measured pressure be half the initial pressure gives <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0311f-form.011"/>, and this is where the 6 dB drop comes from. </s></p><p n="p67.100"><s n="s1.2;p67.100">On the A-scan it is not necessary to measure the actual decibel drop. </s><s n="s2.2;p67.100">Since the ultrasound beam can be considered collimated, when the centre of the beam is directly over the edge of a flat-bottomed hole, half the amplitude will return from the base of the object and half from the hole. </s></p><p n="p68.100"><s n="s1.2;p68.100">This is shown on the A-scan obtained from one of the holes. </s><s n="s2.2;p68.100">See Figure 23. </s></p><p n="p69.100"><s n="s1.2;p69.100">By sliding the transducer across the top of the object and noting when the 6 dB drops occur it is possible to detect the defects, and size them by noting the position of the centre of the transducer when the drop occurs. </s><s n="s2.2;p69.100">Although not required for this experiment it would be possible to know the depth of the defect by knowing the velocity of sound in the material and by measuring at what time the first echo received. </s></p><p n="p70.100"><s n="s1.1;p70.100">Marks were made on the block by eye according to the transducer position and measured with a Vernier calliper to a precision of ±0.000005 m. </s></p></div3><div3><head rend="bold">2.3.2 Detecting and Sizing Defects: Results</head><p n="p71.100"><s n="s1.1;p71.100">The error in position of the transducer was ±0.001 m as the amplitudes displayed on the scope were fluctuating so the mark made on the object covered a range greater than the precision for the calliper. </s></p><p n="p72.100"><s n="s1.2;p72.100">The object contained four holes. </s><s n="s2.2;p72.100">Here are the recorded 6 dB drops: </s></p><table id="BAWE_0311f-tab.004"><head><hi rend="bold">Table 4:</hi> The recorded 6 dB drops in the object as measured from the edge of the object.</head><row><cell/></row></table></div3><div3><head rend="bold">2.3.3 Detecting and Sizing Defects: Discussion</head><p n="p73.100"><s n="s1.2;p73.100">As the holes were circular the transducer has to be centred along the block so the 6 dB drop technique would be accurate. </s><s n="s2.2;p73.100">Any back-forth offset would result in the 6 dB drop being detected sooner or later than the actual beginning or end of a hole. </s></p><p n="p74.100"><s n="s1.3;p74.100">A better technique for this experiment would be to have used the C-scan method. </s><s n="s2.3;p74.100">This is usually done by a robotic arm and computer, which scans the object in a sweeping pattern until the entire surface is covered. </s><s n="s3.3;p74.100">The computer then displays a plan view of the object with the echo-time or echo-intensity displayed as a shade of grey according to its magnitude. </s></p><p n="p75.100"><s n="s1.1;p75.100">This would reveal any and all defects, and it would be possible to accurately measure their dimensions whatever the shape as long as the defect was greater than the resolution of the transducer. </s></p></div3><div3><head rend="bold">2.4.1 Surface Wave Generation: Details</head><figure id="BAWE_0311f-pic.009"><head><hi rend="bold">Figure 24:</hi> The Perspex wedge transducers are set to an incidence angle of 63° from the vertical. The leftmost transducer is transmitting whilst the other is receiving, in a similar setup to Figure 21. Between the transducers and solid object is couplant.</head></figure><p n="p76.100"><s n="s1.1;p76.100">From equation 3, letting <hi rend="italic">V1</hi> be the speed of a longitudinal wave in Perspex, <hi rend="italic">V2</hi> the speed of a longitudinal wave in Stainless Steel and <hi rend="italic">θ2</hi> to be 90°, we can find the first critical incidence angle, which is 26.8°. </s></p><p n="p77.100"><s n="s1.1;p77.100">Letting <hi rend="italic">V2</hi> be the speed of a shear wave in Stainless Steel yields the second critical angle of 55.0°. </s></p><p n="p78.100"><s n="s1.2;p78.100">By sending longitudinal waves at these two angles the only surface waves produced would be creep waves, which decay rapidly. </s><s n="s2.2;p78.100">As stated in the introduction Rayleigh waves are produced by longitudinal waves striking the interface at slightly more than the second critical angle, so it is reasonable to assume a 63° incidence angle would meet this criteria. </s></p><p n="p79.100"><s n="s1.2;p79.100">To be sure the detected amplitude by the receiver is a surface wave it will be possible to attenuate the signal by placing an object in the path of the wave, such as a finger. </s><s n="s2.2;p79.100">No attenuation would mean the detected wave is travelling by bulk propagation. </s></p><p n="p80.100"><s n="s1.4;p80.100">Measuring the speed of the Rayleigh wave can be achieved by recording the time the signal is detected and comparing it to the distance between the transducers. </s><s n="s2.4;p80.100">There will be a linear correlation directly proportional to the velocity of the Rayleigh wave. </s><s n="s3.4;p80.100">The offset in distance will be equal to the distance the wave travelled inside the transducers. </s><s n="s4.4;p80.100">The time will be measured on the scope and the distance by a Vernier calliper. </s></p><p n="p81.100"><s n="s1.1;p81.100">Theoretically, a good approximation to the speed of a surface wave is: </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p82.100"><s n="s1.1;p82.100"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0311f-form.012"/> (10) </s></p><p n="p83.100"><s n="s1.1;p83.100">Where <hi rend="italic">vR</hi> is the velocity of the Rayleigh wave, <hi rend="italic">vS</hi> the shear wave velocity and υ is the Poisson's ratio for the material the waves are travelling through. </s></p></div3><div3><head rend="bold">2.4.2 Surface Wave Generation: Results</head><p n="p84.100"><s n="s1.3;p84.100">For various materials the time for the Rayleigh wave to travel between the transducers was plotted against the separation of the transducers. </s><s n="s2.3;p84.100">Some materials did not show signs of having a surface wave. </s><s n="s3.3;p84.100">The ones that did are shown below along with their Rayleigh wave speed: </s></p><table id="BAWE_0311f-tab.005"><head><hi rend="bold">Table 5:</hi> The speed of Rayleigh waves in some materials. The second column is the speed experimentally found, the third column are the expected values, and the final column contains the theoretical speeds predicted by equation 10 using the textbook values for shear wave velocity and Poisson's ratio.</head><row><cell/></row></table></div3><div3><head rend="bold">2.4.3 Surface Wave Generation: Discussion</head><p n="p85.100"><s n="s1.2;p85.100">The measured velocities compare well with the expected values and also the predictions of the theory. </s><s n="s2.2;p85.100">The uncertainty in the experiment covers the actual value, which assures of the accuracy of the measurements. </s></p><p n="p86.100"><s n="s1.1;p86.100">The offsets for the linear relation between distance and time were all similar, as expected due to the waves travelling in the same pair of transducers. </s></p><p n="p87.100"><s n="s1.3;p87.100">The materials in which surface waves were not detected had differing densities. </s><s n="s2.3;p87.100">In the case of the Perspex block there was no density change and thus no interface for the mode conversion to make surface waves. </s><s n="s3.3;p87.100">The denser objects like Copper would have made the actual angle less than what is necessary for the second critical angle. </s></p><p n="p88.100"><s n="s1.1;p88.100">A variable angle transducer would have allowed the setting of the incidence angle to maximise the amplitude of the surface wave and also extend the test range over a wider value for densities of materials. </s></p><p n="p89.100"><s n="s1.1;p89.100">The couplant was an issue with this experiment as different thickness yielded different amplitudes, and it was not experimentally simple as to whether the lack of a surface wave was due to the material being of unsuitable density, or the couplant was incorrectly used. </s></p><p n="p90.100"><s n="s1.1;p90.100">A non-contact transducer would supple a more repeatable experimental result or perhaps performing the experiment in a tank of couplant so it was a constant. </s></p></div3><div3><head rend="bold">2.5.1 Crack Detection: Details</head><figure id="BAWE_0311f-pic.010"><head><hi rend="bold">Figure 25:</hi> In an identical setup to Figure 24 the object is replaced with a groove cut between where the transducers are placed. The groove gets deeper from one side of the block to the other. The dimensions were measured with a Vernier calliper.</head></figure><p n="p91.100"><s n="s1.1;p91.100">As the Rayleigh wave generated will only have an effective depth equal to its wavelength it will be possible to slide the transducers along the Aluminium object, either side of the groove, until the amplitude of the Rayleigh wave detected becomes insignificantly small. </s></p><p n="p92.100"><s n="s1.2;p92.100">By measuring the depth of the groove at both ends, the width of the object, and knowing it is linear, a function of groove depth can be found. </s><s n="s2.2;p92.100">Once the Rayleigh wave amplitude becomes unperceivable the distance of the transducers from the start of the groove can be found using Vernier callipers. </s></p><p n="p93.100"><s n="s1.1;p93.100">Then the groove depth is calculated and the wavelength of the Rayleigh wave found. </s></p></div3><div3><head rend="bold">2.5.2 Crack Detection: Results</head><p n="p94.100"><s n="s1.2;p94.100">Although some waves were detected on the Aluminium block they were inconsistent and unrepeatable. </s><s n="s2.2;p94.100">Placing a finger between the transducers resulted in no attenuation, which in not expected in the case of a surface wave. </s></p><p n="p95.100"><s n="s1.1;p95.100">The physical dimensions of the groove are irrelevant as there were no surface waves detected. </s></p></div3><div3><head rend="bold">2.5.3 Crack Detection: Discussion</head><p n="p96.100"><s n="s1.3;p96.100">The reasons for the lack of surface wave detection are unknown. </s><s n="s2.3;p96.100">As the Aluminium block showed surface waves in experiment 2.4 it is reasonable to assume that they are being generated adequately. </s><s n="s3.3;p96.100">The difference in this experiment was the groove and this was somehow damping the Rayleigh wave, even when tested at the smallest depth of groove. </s></p><p n="p97.100"><s n="s1.1;p97.100">Once again couplant played a critical role in the experiment and it was very difficult to get consistent measurements as the depth of couplant varied. </s></p><p n="p98.100"><s n="s1.2;p98.100">Non-contact transducers would be preferred in an experiment like this. </s><s n="s2.2;p98.100">Else variable angle transducers should be applied as the wedge ones used were designed to generate surface waves in Steel and not Aluminium. </s></p></div3></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">3. Conclusion</head><p n="p99.100"><s n="s1.4;p99.100">Ultrasound can be successfully used to determine a variety of different properties of materials. </s><s n="s2.4;p99.100">Velocities of sound, bulk/shear/Young's moduli, Poisson's ratio, densities, and more can all be determined using ultrasonic techniques. </s><s n="s3.4;p99.100">The limitation of using couplant and contact transducers in these experiments is understandable, however a better situation for finding out the properties of materials ascertained in the experiments above would be to use EMATs and have the data collected by a computer. </s><s n="s4.4;p99.100">The flexibility offered by being able to view the data as different scans (mentioned above are the A and C scans) depending on the scenario would be valuable as well. </s></p><p n="p100.100"><s n="s1.3;p100.100">Overall the experiments were accurate and where discrepancy arose it was followed with a suggested reason for the inaccuracy. </s><s n="s2.3;p100.100">The theoretical basis for the experiments was sound along with the experimental procedure carried out. </s><s n="s3.3;p100.100">Thus the results concluded are mostly strong, repeatable and reliable. </s></p></div1></body><back><div1 type="bibliography"><head rend="bold">4. References</head><p>[1] <seg type="URL" n="http://www"/>.<name type="university"/>.ac.uk/staff/S.M.Dixon/rarea.html, January 2004.</p><p>[2] G.W. Kaye and T.H. Laby, Table of Physical and Chemical Constants (sixteenth edition), pg 100-102</p><p>[3] G.W. Kaye and T.H. Laby, Table of Physical and Chemical Constants (sixteenth edition), pg 42</p><p>[4] G.W. Kaye and T.H. Laby, Table of Physical and Chemical Constants (sixteenth edition), pg 44</p><p>[5] G.W. Kaye and T.H. Laby, Table of Physical and Chemical Constants (sixteenth edition), pg 44</p><p>[6] G.W. Kaye and T.H. Laby, Table of Physical and Chemical Constants (sixteenth edition), pg 100-102</p><p>[7] G.W. Kaye and T.H. Laby, Table of Physical and Chemical Constants (sixteenth edition), pg 100-102</p></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
