<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_0311b" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Report on Finding Planck's Constant (Experiment FC3)</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">Language used in quote: <foreign id="English">English</foreign></note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">deleted: footer: student name, page number, assignment title</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">1</p><p n="date">2002-11</p><p n="module title">Physics Laboratory</p><p n="module code">PX110</p><p n="genre family">Methodology recount</p><p n="discipline">Physics</p><p n="disciplinary group">PS</p><p n="grade">M</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">4712</p><p n="number of s-units">235</p><p n="number of p">91</p><p n="number of tables">0</p><p n="number of figures">2</p><p n="number of block quotes">2</p><p n="number of formulae">10</p><p n="number of lists">1</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">3</p><p n="abstract present">abstract present</p><p n="average words per s-unit">20.1</p><p n="average s-units per p">2.6</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">m</p><p n="year of birth">1984</p><p n="first language">English</p><p n="education">UKA</p><p n="course">MPhys</p><p n="student ID">0311</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><docTitle><titlePart>Report on Finding Planck's Constant (Experiment FC3)</titlePart></docTitle><titlePart rend="bold"><name type="student name"/></titlePart></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="abstract"><head rend="underlined bold">Abstract</head><p n="p1.91"><s n="s1.2;p1.91">By measuring the kinetic energy of photoelectrons ejected from potassium over a range of frequencies from 518.5THz to 821.1THz (578nm to 365nm wavelengths), Planck's constant was measured to be 5.22x10 <hi rend="sup">-34</hi> (±0.13x10 <hi rend="sup">-34</hi>) Js. </s><s n="s2.2;p1.91">The accepted value is taken to be 6.626x10 <hi rend="sup">-34</hi> Js as quoted in Grant and Phillips. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">Introduction</head><p n="p2.91"><s n="s1.3;p2.91">Planck's constant is a universal and fundamental constant of the universe. </s><s n="s2.3;p2.91">It is important to realise that we have this constant in the first place. </s><s n="s3.3;p2.91">It shows that the universe is not continuous, but at very small intervals of time and space it is indeed quite coarse. </s></p><p n="p3.91"><s n="s1.1;p3.91">Its units are <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0311b-form.001"/> or Joule-seconds. </s></p><p n="p4.91"><s n="s1.2;p4.91">If Planck's constant, denoted by the symbol <hi rend="italic">h</hi>, were much different to its incredibly small value then the universe would be a completely different place. </s><s n="s2.2;p4.91">If there was no Planck's constant then there would be no randomness in the universe - it would be totally deterministic. </s></p><p n="p5.91"><s n="s1.5;p5.91">However, there is, but because the value is very small compared to our common day experiences we don't notice its uncertainty effects. </s><s n="s2.5;p5.91">If the value were larger (and we still existed), we would find various uncertainties cropping up often. </s><s n="s3.5;p5.91">Solid objects would wobble about and appear in random places. </s><s n="s4.5;p5.91">There would also be an affect in the passage of time; we would encounter various echoes from the immediate past and future. </s><s n="s5.5;p5.91">All in all a very weird situation. </s></p><p n="p6.91"><s n="s1.3;p6.91">For atomic particles however, this indeterministic behaviour is all around them. </s><s n="s2.3;p6.91">This means we can only calculate the probability of various atomic particles being in a certain place at a certain time, as they are always "wobbling" so to speak. </s><s n="s3.3;p6.91">If there was no Planck's constant then we would be able to calculate positions and times absolutely. </s></p><p n="p7.91"><s n="s1.2;p7.91">Planck's constant plays a critical role in this uncertainty, which is governed by Heisenberg's uncertainty principle. </s><s n="s2.2;p7.91">Which states that uncertainty in momentum multiplied by uncertainty in position must be less than Planck's constant over 4π. </s></p><p n="p8.91"><s n="s1.3;p8.91">Despite this knowledge that the universe can never be fully known, in the absolute sense, we have gained more understanding of the physical laws, with interesting and practical upshots. </s><s n="s2.3;p8.91">Electrons around a nucleus cannot exist anywhere, only in discrete energy levels. </s><s n="s3.3;p8.91">This is a main principle of quantum mechanics and shows how important Planck's constant is to this field, as the energy levels are in Planck-size quanta. </s></p><p n="p9.91"><s n="s1.4;p9.91">To oversimplify: Electrons can exist in a high state, with potential energy to spare, or in a ground state, near the nucleus, but not in-between. </s><s n="s2.4;p9.91">If they want to 'jump down' to a lower state, they have to lose some energy. </s><s n="s3.4;p9.91">However, energy cannot be destroyed or created so where does it go? </s><s n="s4.4;p9.91">The electron emits a photon, and this photon carries the energy away, so energy levels balance out and nothing is lost. </s></p><p n="p10.91"><s n="s1.5;p10.91">How do you measure the energy of a photon? </s><s n="s2.5;p10.91">The frequency of this particle is such a measure. </s><s n="s3.5;p10.91">Higher frequencies mean more energy, more ability to do work. </s><s n="s4.5;p10.91">Remember that electrons can only exist in certain, discrete, shells of potential, so there can only be a quantum of energy of energy released - there are no in-betweens. </s><s n="s5.5;p10.91">This energy is proportional to the frequency of the photon as follows: </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p11.91"><s n="s1.1;p11.91"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0311b-form.002"/> (1) </s></p><p n="p12.91"><s n="s1.3;p12.91">Where <hi rend="italic">E</hi> is the energy, <hi rend="italic">h</hi> is Planck's constant and <hi rend="italic">f</hi> is the frequency. </s><s n="s2.3;p12.91">Planck's constant has turned up here, as the smallest length you can get is Planck-length, and so the closest two energy shells can be is this length. </s><s n="s3.3;p12.91">So this is the smallest distance an electron can 'fall' and so the energy of the photon has to be in these sized chunks. </s></p><p n="p13.91"><s n="s1.5;p13.91">You can consider the reverse scenario, as the situation is symmetric. </s><s n="s2.5;p13.91">Consider a photon with a certain quanta of energy hitting an electron in the ground state. </s><s n="s3.5;p13.91">If the energy levels are high enough, i.e. frequency is over a certain threshold, then this electron will absorb this energy and will now have enough energy to leave the grip of the nucleus and be ejected off in a random direction. </s><s n="s4.5;p13.91">This leaves the atom ionised with positive charge. </s><s n="s5.5;p13.91">This is called the photoelectric effect. </s></p><p n="p14.91"><s n="s1.4;p14.91">The ejected photoelectron can be made to accelerate under the influence of an electric field. </s><s n="s2.4;p14.91">You could accelerate this photoelectron to a sufficiently high enough velocity towards a metal surface, with the property that an incoming electron can cause several electrons to leave the surface, so that more electrons will be ejected. </s><s n="s3.4;p14.91">Repeat this several times, and what was once a single electron is now a detectable current. </s><s n="s4.4;p14.91">These devices are called photomultipliers. </s></p><p n="p15.91"><s n="s1.2;p15.91">Due to the random nature of the emission of the electrons you end up with a series of peaks on the detector, and usually have to average them number of pulses over a fixed time interval. </s><s n="s2.2;p15.91">Photomultipliers are widely used in the scientific field for detecting individual photons in interactions such as neutrinos and protons for example, and are based on the photoelectric effect. </s></p><p n="p16.91"><s n="s1.5;p16.91">Another use based on the photoelectric effect is when you shine light on silicon. </s><s n="s2.5;p16.91">"Silicon is a semiconductor, which means that it is a very poor electrical conductor compared to a metal. </s><s n="s3.5;p16.91">Electric current is carried by electrons moving about within the silicon, and normally hardly any of the electrons from the silicon atoms are free to move. </s><s n="s4.5;p16.91">However, when photons with sufficient energy illuminate a silicon surface, some electrons may leave the atoms to which they were bound, without having enough energy to escape completely from the surface. </s><s n="s5.5;p16.91">These electrons can generate electric currents and voltages in a photoelectric cell which converts light energy into electrical energy."<hi rend="sup">[1]</hi> </s></p><p n="p17.91"><s n="s1.3;p17.91">The conclusion of this particular circumstance is that these devices can be used to measure light intensity, so long as the light is of a high enough frequency, and also to generate electrical potentials that can be stored and used to power electrical devices. </s><s n="s2.3;p17.91">Solar panels, as they are called, are used worldwide and on all man-made satellites. </s><s n="s3.3;p17.91">The power they provide depends of the photoelectric effect. </s></p><p n="p18.91"><s n="s1.11;p18.91">Even the existence of a photoelectric effect is an important discovery as it shows that light is made up of particles. </s><s n="s2.11;p18.91">But they also exhibit interference and have a wavelength. </s><s n="s3.11;p18.91">This is what is called wave-particle duality. </s><s n="s4.11;p18.91">It would seem that photons are not strictly a particle and are not strictly a wave either. </s><s n="s5.11;p18.91">This is because of the quantum weirdness at these very short distances. </s><s n="s6.11;p18.91">Planck's constant was a very significant discovery in 1916 when mainstream physics was getting into quantum mechanics. </s><s n="s7.11;p18.91">The discovered wave-particle duality revolutionised thinking about atomic conditions. </s><s n="s8.11;p18.91">Eight years later de Broglie was to publish his famous wave-particle equation, linking the momentum of a particle to the wavelength of a wave. </s><s n="s9.11;p18.91">This featured Planck's constant as the coefficient of proportionality showing how fundamentally important this constant is. </s><s n="s10.11;p18.91">Again, because of Planck's constant having such a small value, objects with very small momentums only exhibit these wave-particle effects. </s><s n="s11.11;p18.91">If Planck's constant was larger then to add to the uncertainty of solid objects, we would find things interfering with themselves and diffracting around objects. </s></p><p n="p19.91"><s n="s1.5;p19.91">As stated before, frequency is the deciding factor in the kinetic energy of the ejected photoelectron. </s><s n="s2.5;p19.91">If you imagine an energy well of electrons, all these are below the Fermi level, in the valence band of the metal. </s><s n="s3.5;p19.91">When a photon lands in the well, an electron will jump out to balance the energy. </s><s n="s4.5;p19.91">Higher frequency photons make the electrons jump out faster, so they go higher. </s><s n="s5.5;p19.91">Some fall back in, some have the energy to jump out but because the angle is acute they fail to attain the height needed to leave, some have enough energy but came from the bottom of the well so a lot has been used up before they even reach the top. </s></p><p n="p20.91"><s n="s1.2;p20.91">The electrons we are interesting in are the ones that start at the top of the valence band, at the Fermi level, and travel straight up out of the well. </s><s n="s2.2;p20.91">If the frequency is the same, they all reach the same height, so they all started with the same kinetic energy. </s></p><quote lang="English">"The exact shape of the curve giving the electron kinetic energy up to KE <hi rend="sub">max</hi> depends not only on the cathode material but also on how clean it is and on how the cathode surface was prepared (e.g. how thick the layer is if it is a thin film deposited onto glass)." <hi rend="sup">[2]</hi></quote><p n="p21.91"><s n="s1.3;p21.91">So how do you go about finding out what the maximum kinetic energy is? </s><s n="s2.3;p21.91">When you shine light on a metallic plate photoelectrons will leave, giving the plate a positive charge. </s><s n="s3.3;p21.91">If this plate was connected to another plate, and the electrons were to hit this plate, a current would flow. </s></p><p n="p22.91"><s n="s1.5;p22.91">If there was a capacitor in the circuit between the two plates, then this would gradually store more and more charge as the current flowed round. </s><s n="s2.5;p22.91">This charge would build up an electric field, not only between the plates of the capacitor, but also between our original metallic plates - a cathode and anode. </s><s n="s3.5;p22.91">Since electrons are charged then an electric field will accelerate them. </s><s n="s4.5;p22.91">As the light is hitting the cathode and the photoelectrons are travelling towards the anode, the electric field is in the directions such that the photoelectrons will be accelerated back towards the cathode. </s><s n="s5.5;p22.91">As more photoelectrons hit the cathode the electric field becomes greater and so less photoelectrons make it to the anode, ipso facto the current decreases. </s></p><p n="p23.91"><s n="s1.3;p23.91">High energy photoelectrons require more voltage between the plates to slow them down. </s><s n="s2.3;p23.91">If they do make it, then they will charge the capacitor up even more until the current reaches zero when a balance is reached. </s><s n="s3.3;p23.91">The voltage across the capacitor at this point will reveal the stopping voltage needed to stop a photoelectron for that particular frequency. </s></p><p n="p24.91"><s n="s1.3;p24.91">From this model you can see that intensity should have no part in the determination of the stopping voltage. </s><s n="s2.3;p24.91">Consider many billions of low-energy photons hitting the metal; they just don't have the energy to knock the electrons out of their shells. </s><s n="s3.3;p24.91">However, a couple of high-energy photons will knock the electrons out will energy to spare. </s></p><p n="p25.91"><s n="s1.4;p25.91">It is important to bear in mind that if you were to turn off the light no photoelectrons would escape the cathode, consequently the capacitor will loose charge if it is earthed. </s><s n="s2.4;p25.91">From this aspect it is easy to see that high intensity light will be able to charge up the capacitor faster than lower intensity light. </s><s n="s3.4;p25.91">Consider filling up a bath with no plug with buckets of water - the faster you pour the buckets in, the higher the level will be, on average. </s><s n="s4.4;p25.91">But the maximum obtainable value for the height of the water/voltage is still a constant, however slowly you fill it. </s></p><p n="p26.91"><s n="s1.3;p26.91">We are at the stage where we know the stopping voltage for electrons for a certain frequency (energy). </s><s n="s2.3;p26.91">Due to the principle of the conservation of energy we know energy in (<hi rend="italic">hf</hi>) must be equal to energy out, which is the stopping voltage, plus in order to extract the photoelectron from the surface of the metal, we must give it enough energy to rise from the Fermi level and into the conduction band. </s><s n="s3.3;p26.91">Thus; </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p27.91"><s n="s1.1;p27.91"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0311b-form.003"/> (2) </s></p><p n="p28.91"><s n="s1.1;p28.91">Where <hi rend="italic">e</hi> is the electronic charge, <hi rend="italic">V0</hi> is the stopping voltage and <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0311b-form.004"/> is the work function of the metal - the energy required to raise the electron into the conduction band. </s></p><p n="p29.91"><s n="s1.5;p29.91">Alkali metals, such as potassium, have 1 electron in their outer shells. </s><s n="s2.5;p29.91">Not only is this electron further away from the nucleus than the other electrons, but it is also being pushed away by the electrons closer to the nucleus than it by the electromagnetic force. </s><s n="s3.5;p29.91">Effectively screening the outer electron from the electromagnetic pull of the positive nucleus. </s><s n="s4.5;p29.91">This is represented in the successive ionisation energies for potassium. </s><s n="s5.5;p29.91">It takes 419 kJmol <hi rend="sup">-1</hi> for the first electron to be removed, compared to 3051 kJmol <hi rend="sup">-1</hi> for the next one.<hi rend="sup"> [3]</hi> </s></p><p n="p30.91"><s n="s1.2;p30.91">Because of this initial ease to ionise potassium the work function of this metal is low. </s><s n="s2.2;p30.91">Work functions for metals are very dependant on the purity of the surface of the metal, and can pose a large uncertainty. </s></p><p n="p31.91"><s n="s1.1;p31.91">Rearranging equation (2) gives; </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p32.91"><s n="s1.1;p32.91"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0311b-form.005"/> (3) </s></p><p n="p33.91"><s n="s1.1;p33.91">Which is in the form y=mx+c. </s></p><p n="p34.91"><s n="s1.2;p34.91">This shows that a plot of stopping voltage against frequency will give a straight line with a gradient of Planck's constant divided by electronic charge. </s><s n="s2.2;p34.91">The intercept will be negative and the absolute value of this number will be the work function of the metal. </s></p><p n="p35.91"><s n="s1.1;p35.91">If you were to have a range of values for frequency, and the corresponding value for stopping voltage then by knowing the electronic charge you could calculate Planck's constant. </s></p><p n="p36.91"><s n="s1.4;p36.91">We now have the task of generating photons of certain frequencies. </s><s n="s2.4;p36.91">We could use a normal light bulb that heats up a metal in a vacuum to such a temperature that it incandesces. </s><s n="s3.4;p36.91">This would create a broad range of photons with no discernible peaks, but the majority of the intensity of the spectrum would be located near the longer, redder, wavelengths. </s><s n="s4.4;p36.91">We could select various frequencies using interference filters. </s></p><quote lang="English">"If a thin transparent spacer is placed between two semireflective coatings, multiple reflections and interference can be used to select a narrow frequency band, producing an interference filter. If the spacer is a half wavelength for the desired wavelength, then other wavelengths will be attenuated by destructive interference." <hi rend="sup">[4]</hi></quote><p n="p37.91"><s n="s1.3;p37.91">These filters need to be perpendicular to the incident light to filter the specified frequency. </s><s n="s2.3;p37.91">Tilting them will shift the filtered frequency towards shorter wavelengths. </s><s n="s3.3;p37.91">Similarly lower temperatures will shift to short wavelengths. </s></p><p n="p38.91"><s n="s1.2;p38.91">However, when you filter out one wavelength from an incandescent source it is usually relatively dark compared to the total output of the bulb. </s><s n="s2.2;p38.91">Although intensity doesn't affect the release of photoelectrons, it could make a difference to the stopping voltage measured due to current leakage. </s></p><p n="p39.91"><s n="s1.2;p39.91">A better method would be to use a source with high intensity peaks, then you could use the interference filters to select the high peaks. </s><s n="s2.2;p39.91">The relativity intensity would be much higher compared to the power output of the bulb in this case, and would reduce errors. </s></p><p n="p40.91"><s n="s1.2;p40.91">A high pressure mercury lamp has a spectrum which consists mainly of a series of lines, the more prominent of which are at wavelengths of 253.7 nm, 365.4 nm, 404.7 nm, 435.8 nm, 546.1 nm, and 578.0 nm. </s><s n="s2.2;p40.91">If you were to single out each of these wavelengths with an interference filter, it would provide an accurate source of frequency measurement. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0311b-fig.001"><head><hi rend="bold italic">Figure 1 The relative intensity of a high pressure mercury lamp over a spectral range.</hi> <hi rend="sup">[5]</hi></head></figure><p n="p41.91"><s n="s1.4;p41.91">These high pressure lamps consist of a "starter gas" with some mercury in a sealed quartz tube under about 5 atmospheres of pressure. </s><s n="s2.4;p41.91">Electrodes are sealed in quartz holders at each end. </s><s n="s3.4;p41.91">A high voltage is passed through the tube which breaks down the starter gas and vapourises the mercury, then a lower voltage is used to produce the illumination. </s><s n="s4.4;p41.91">This is produced by electrically exciting the electrons in the mercury atoms, as they fall back down to a ground state photons are emitted. </s></p><p n="p42.91"><s n="s1.3;p42.91">As stated before, these levels are discrete, so only certain energies (and so frequencies) can be emitted. </s><s n="s2.3;p42.91">This gives rise to the peaks in the spectral distribution. </s><s n="s3.3;p42.91">There are many spikes due to the numerous electrons and shells mercury atoms have access too. </s></p><p n="p43.91"><s n="s1.1;p43.91">The method of using a high pressure mercury lamp is preferred over the common incandescent bulb as the frequencies are more controlled and this will leave to a more accurate experiment which relies heavily on knowing the frequency of photons. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">Experiment Details</head><figure id="BAWE_0311b-pic.001"><head><hi rend="bold italic">Figure 2 </hi><hi rend="italic">Experimental setup on the optical bench with positions (in cm) of the optical riders. [6]</hi></head></figure><p n="p44.91"><s n="s1.1;p44.91"><hi rend="bold italic">Figure 2</hi>'s labels correspond to the following equipment; </s></p><list type="ordered"><item>High pressure mercury lamp</item><item>Iris diaphragm</item><item>Lens, f=100mm</item><item>Rotating holder containing interference filters</item><item>Photocell</item><item>Capacitor coupled to electrometer amplifier and switch</item><item>Galvanometer</item></list><figure id="BAWE_0311b-pic.002"><head rend="bold italic">Figure 3 Showing a schematic representation how the electrical components connect to each other. </head></figure><p n="p45.91"><s n="s1.2;p45.91">The galvanometer had a dial to select the precision of the readings. </s><s n="s2.2;p45.91">For stopping voltages under 1 volt the scale went 0 - 1 V every 0.001 V. Above 1 volt the scale went 0 - 3 V every 0.01 V. Due to the sensitive nature of the galvanometer it was zeroed before every reading, and was left untouched during the readings. </s></p><p n="p46.91"><s n="s1.2;p46.91">During this calibration the capacitor was discharged so the voltage was zero. </s><s n="s2.2;p46.91">The switch was released and the capacitor was ready to store the charge. </s></p><p n="p47.91"><s n="s1.5;p47.91">This charge came from the photocell. </s><s n="s2.5;p47.91">As mentioned in the introduction, light of a high enough frequency can dislodge electrons from the surface of a metal. </s><s n="s3.5;p47.91">These travelled to the capacitor and were stored on its plates. </s><s n="s4.5;p47.91">This caused a potential difference and so a voltage was created between the plates of the capacitor, but also the cathode and anode of the photocell. </s><s n="s5.5;p47.91">As the voltage built up it became harder for the electrons to reach the cathode in the photocell as the electric field was increasing proportionally, since the distance between the surfaces was constant. </s></p><p n="p48.91"><s n="s1.3;p48.91">Eventually the voltage was such that the electric field it generated was strong enough to completely prevent electrons reaches the cathode. </s><s n="s2.3;p48.91">This voltage was measured on the galvanometer and represented the stopping voltage. </s><s n="s3.3;p48.91">It would be plotted against that specific frequency. </s></p><p n="p49.91"><s n="s1.5;p49.91">To select that frequency first of all it is necessary to generate such a frequency of photons. </s><s n="s2.5;p49.91">This was accomplished with the high pressure mercury lamp. </s><s n="s3.5;p49.91">It generates frequencies as shown in <hi rend="bold italic">figure 1</hi>. </s><s n="s4.5;p49.91">There are distinct peaks in this spectrum. </s><s n="s5.5;p49.91">The interference filters were chosen such that they correspond with these high intensity peaks. </s></p><p n="p50.91"><s n="s1.2;p50.91">Thus the filters were of the following wavelengths: 365 nm, 405 nm, 436 nm, 546 nm, 578 nm. </s><s n="s2.2;p50.91">These are accurate to an insignificant fraction of a percent. </s></p><p n="p51.91"><s n="s1.2;p51.91">To avoid errors the filters were kept at a constant temperature throughout the experiment, as low temperature shifts the filtered frequency towards shorter wavelengths. </s><s n="s2.2;p51.91">Similarly, the angle of incidence was kept at right angles, as tilting the filter would have resulted in a shorter wavelength shift. </s></p><p n="p52.91"><s n="s1.3;p52.91">Once the monochromatic light was up to full intensity, which was accomplished by leaving the lamp on for 10 minutes, the light was passed through the iris diaphragm. </s><s n="s2.3;p52.91">This had the effect of collimating the light for the lens. </s><s n="s3.3;p52.91">The lens then focused the light onto the metal centre in the photocell. </s></p><p n="p53.91"><s n="s1.2;p53.91">To avoid errors the light was not allowed to fall on another other part of the photocell as this may cause stray photoelectrons and distort the results. </s><s n="s2.2;p53.91">If the light fell on another metal other than the photocell, and this was made of a similar alkali metal to the photocell, then photoelectrons would be released from this, and these would probably be attracted towards the positive anode. </s></p><p n="p54.91"><s n="s1.4;p54.91">After the galvanometer was calibrated with the first filter in place the switch was released and the voltage started building up. </s><s n="s2.4;p54.91">Once the voltage had stopped increasing the reading was recorded. </s><s n="s3.4;p54.91">The next filter was turned into view and the galvanometer was calibrated again. </s><s n="s4.4;p54.91">All 5 filters were used 3 times each and the stopping voltage for each filter averaged over the 3 readings. </s></p><p n="p55.91"><s n="s1.3;p55.91">Then the iris was closed slightly. </s><s n="s2.3;p55.91">This reduced the intensity of light reaching the photocell. </s><s n="s3.3;p55.91">Three sets of readings for the 5 filters were recorded. </s></p><p n="p56.91"><s n="s1.1;p56.91">The iris was then closed to an even smaller aperture, and the results recorded in the same fashion. </s></p><p n="p57.91"><s n="s1.5;p57.91">The error in the stopping voltages were higher for the less intense light due to the leakage currents. </s><s n="s2.5;p57.91">The capacitor was discharging continuously when there is no light on the photocell (in a very short timeframe), thus lowering the stopping voltage slightly. </s><s n="s3.5;p57.91">With the closed iris the incident light was less intense, so less photoelectrons strike the photocell per second. </s><s n="s4.5;p57.91">This means that the capacitor took longer to charge with the less intense light. </s><s n="s5.5;p57.91">When the capacitor looked like it was charged to the stopping voltage, it was actually just below that value as the reading given was effectively averaged by the galvanometer as the capacitor tried to discharge and the current was tricking in, recharging it. </s></p><p n="p58.91"><s n="s1.1;p58.91">The error in the frequency is insignificantly small due to the nature of the setup. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">Results</head><p n="p59.91"><s n="s1.1;p59.91">See attached <hi rend="bold italic">Figure 4</hi>. </s></p><p n="p60.91"><s n="s1.2;p60.91"><hi rend="bold italic">Figure 4</hi> is a graph plotting the measured stopping voltages against frequency for the various intensities. </s><s n="s2.2;p60.91">Normally error bars would be drawn on but in this case the predicted errors were so small they would not show if drawn on <hi rend="bold italic">figure 4</hi>. </s></p><p n="p61.91"><s n="s1.2;p61.91">The points are evenly distributed around the line of best fit indicating there is a good linear approximation as theory predicts. </s><s n="s2.2;p61.91">The gradient is the constant <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0311b-form.006"/> as shown in equation (3) and is measured to be: </s></p><p n="p62.91"><s n="s1.1;p62.91"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0311b-form.007"/> </s></p><p n="p63.91"><s n="s1.1;p63.91">With the uncertainty in the gradient being the difference between the steepest and the shallowest gradients. </s></p><p n="p64.91"><s n="s1.1;p64.91">Multiplying by <hi rend="italic">e</hi>, which is 1.60x10 <hi rend="sup">-19</hi> C gives the value for Planck's constant: </s></p><p n="p65.91"><s n="s1.1;p65.91"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0311b-form.008"/> </s></p><p n="p66.91"><s n="s1.2;p66.91">Extrapolating the line of best fit back to the x-axis intercept gives the threshold frequency of the potassium. </s><s n="s2.2;p66.91">This is calculated to have a wavelength of: </s></p><p n="p67.91"><s n="s1.1;p67.91"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0311b-form.009"/> </s></p><p n="p68.91"><s n="s1.1;p68.91">Which is in the near-infrared section of the electromagnetic spectrum. </s></p><p n="p69.91"><s n="s1.3;p69.91">The value at which the line of best fit intercepts the y-axis gives the (negative) work function of the metal. </s><s n="s2.3;p69.91">It is the voltage required to remove the electron from the bounds of the atom, analogously speaking, the minimum force needed to push the electron up from the Fermi level into the conduction band. </s><s n="s3.3;p69.91">This was calculated to be: </s></p><p n="p70.91"><s n="s1.1;p70.91"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0311b-form.010"/> </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">Discussion</head><p n="p71.91"><s n="s1.2;p71.91">There were no general limitations of this experimental procedure. </s><s n="s2.2;p71.91">It has stood the test of time and along the way received helpful modifications to improve accuracy and reliability. </s></p><p n="p72.91"><s n="s1.2;p72.91">Some suggestions to further test Planck's constant are to use different alkali metals, perhaps sodium and rubidium. </s><s n="s2.2;p72.91">These both have similar electronic structure to potassium, featuring a low work function and low first ionisation energy. </s></p><p n="p73.91"><s n="s1.1;p73.91">Extending the testing frequencies down to below the threshold frequency to confirm the photoelectric theory that there will be no ejected photoelectrons could be a suitable advancement to the experiment. </s></p><p n="p74.91"><s n="s1.4;p74.91">Looking at <hi rend="bold italic">Figure 4</hi> however shows that the theoretical model for potassium, has a threshold frequency above that of the yellow light. </s><s n="s2.4;p74.91">However the experiment clearly recorded a stopping voltage for yellow light. </s><s n="s3.4;p74.91">The conclusion is that the work function for the material used in the experiment was less than the accepted value for potassium. </s><s n="s4.4;p74.91">This is all the more reason to test the material with frequencies lower than that of yellow light to check experimentally where the threshold frequency is. </s></p><p n="p75.91"><s n="s1.4;p75.91">Using a high pressure mercury lamp is a good choice for this experiment as it provides a range of intense peaks over a spectral region above the threshold frequency and conveniently in the visible range too. </s><s n="s2.4;p75.91">Whilst not a necessity to have the peaks in the visible range it does provide convenience when talking about them as they can be referred to by colour. </s><s n="s3.4;p75.91">The peaks themselves are sharp to enable straightforward filtering with the interference filters. </s><s n="s4.4;p75.91">Also they are suitability spaced out to find the gradient of the slope with a good degree of confidence. </s></p><p n="p76.91"><s n="s1.5;p76.91">The iris diaphragm was mechanically operated, with no real gauge for measuring the intensity it allowed through. </s><s n="s2.5;p76.91">It does its job of collimating the light into the lens well. </s><s n="s3.5;p76.91">An additional property to measure would be the intensity, and with that knowledge the rate of current leakage could be calculated. </s><s n="s4.5;p76.91">Measurement of the intensity could be performed with a light-dependant-resistor. </s><s n="s5.5;p76.91">Then variation of intensity could be achieved with tinted filters that would leave the collimation of the light constant. </s></p><p n="p77.91"><s n="s1.5;p77.91">The lens was used to focus the light onto the cathode. </s><s n="s2.5;p77.91">As it had a focal length of 100mm and the cathode was 100mm away the beam focused satisfactorily on the metal. </s><s n="s3.5;p77.91">The primary reason for this is to prevent the light falling on the anode as this would distort the results be giving incorrect stopping voltages. </s><s n="s4.5;p77.91">However, it also served a secondary purpose of allowing more photons to strike the metal than if there was no lens present. </s><s n="s5.5;p77.91">From this perspective a larger lens would have captured more of the light (assuming the iris did not impinge on this light) and so more photons would be incident on the metal. </s></p><p n="p78.91"><s n="s1.2;p78.91">Interference filters are reliable and precise pieces of equipment. </s><s n="s2.2;p78.91">Although they let through a small amount of light of shorter wavelengths due to the way the light passes through them, on a slight angle due to the lens's focusing effects, this is not a significant uncertainty in the results. </s></p><p n="p79.91"><s n="s1.4;p79.91">The photocell is, by its nature, very susceptible to light. </s><s n="s2.4;p79.91">The importance of not getting any light on the anode and casing was vital to the accuracy of the experiment. </s><s n="s3.4;p79.91">The photocell has a thick black shield around it to absorb any stray photons from the room, as the experiment was not performed in total darkness. </s><s n="s4.4;p79.91">The setup was such that it would have been hard for any light to get into the photocell without passing through the filter, so it is not major concern that there was a little background light. </s></p><p n="p80.91"><s n="s1.2;p80.91">Potassium has a certain work function, 2.24eV <hi rend="sup">[7]</hi>, however this was not the calculated value in the results. </s><s n="s2.2;p80.91">As the work function is highly dependent on the preparation of the material and the condition of the surface, it is reasonable to conclude that the work function of the material measured is not that for a pure sample and be content with a value in the same order of magnitude. </s></p><p n="p81.91"><s n="s1.2;p81.91">However the measured value is nearly half the accepted value and even with the impurities of the experimental material it is a long stretch of the imagination to think that there is not a large error in the method somewhere. </s><s n="s2.2;p81.91">This is all the more reason to test the theory with different materials. </s></p><p n="p82.91"><s n="s1.2;p82.91">The capacitance in the circuit is not critical as it is the relation that charge is proportional to voltage (and hence electrical field) that is paramount. </s><s n="s2.2;p82.91">So long as the capacitor is stable and its dielectric doesn't break down any capacitor should suffice. </s></p><p n="p83.91"><s n="s1.3;p83.91">Galvanometers are very sensitive, but still rely on humans to read and interpret the values given. </s><s n="s2.3;p83.91">A digital multimeter would have greater precision and remove the human element. </s><s n="s3.3;p83.91">The calibration of such a device would be easier also; this has benefits of reliability and repeatability. </s></p><p n="p84.91"><s n="s1.1;p84.91">So it appears that all the experimental equipment has a low tolerance to uncertainty in them, this leaves the large discrepancy in the measured result and the accepted value mysteriously unsolved. </s></p><p n="p85.91"><s n="s1.1;p85.91">Assuming that there are errors at work and the value for Planck's constant hasn't been misquoted for the past 87 years there is one obvious type of error that lends itself to this kind of devious trickery; systematic errors. </s></p><p n="p86.91"><s n="s1.1;p86.91">These errors are most likely at work in this experiment as the equipment is rather precise and this is backed up by the datapoints all being close to the line of best fit. </s></p><p n="p87.91"><s n="s1.2;p87.91">Although the datapoints of the less intense light are further away from the straight line of best fit and so less correlated than the high intensity light, this can be attributed to the leakage currents. </s><s n="s2.2;p87.91">Even though they are less correlated, they still predict an imprecise value for Planck's constant, so the systematic errors are present regardless of the varying intensities. </s></p><p n="p88.91"><s n="s1.1;p88.91">These systematic errors must be proportional to the frequency as each measured point is out by a systematic amount according to the frequency it was measured at. </s></p><p n="p89.91"><s n="s1.1;p89.91">If you were to multiply the frequency by 0.79 (5.22 divided by 6.63) then replot the stopping voltages against this multiple-of-frequency you get a gradient that provides the accepted value for Planck's constant. </s></p><p n="p90.91"><s n="s1.2;p90.91">But what can be causing the frequencies to be "apparently" shifted by 0.79 times their intended values? </s><s n="s2.2;p90.91">If Planck's constant was initially unknown then where could you start looking to find the value for this systematic error? </s></p><p n="p91.91"><s n="s1.2;p91.91">Until this error can be found and eliminated the results for this experiment are inconclusive. </s><s n="s2.2;p91.91">They are not solid enough to base a firm conclusion about the value of Planck's constant and/or the work function of potassium. </s></p></div1></body><back><div1 type="bibliography"><head rend="underlined bold">References</head><p>[1] Grant, I.S. &amp; Phillips, W.R. 2001, The elements of physics, p. 316</p><p>[2] <seg type="URL" n="http://website.lineone.net/~aberdareco/PAGES/phys2TG/Pages/phot.htm"/>, 20/01/03</p><p>[3] <seg type="URL" n="http://www.creative-chemistry.org.uk/alevel/documents/N-as1-05.pdf"/>, 20/01/03</p><p>[4] <seg type="URL" n="http://hyperphysics.phy-astr.gsu.edu/hbase/phyopt/intfilt.html"/>, 21/01/03</p><p>[5] <seg type="URL" n="http://www.exfo.com/en/solutions/EfosTech1.asp"/>, 21/01/03</p><p>[6] Figure and caption from 1<hi rend="sup">st</hi> year physics lab script, experiment FC3, p. 5</p><p>[7] <seg type="URL" n="http://kp.phy.tu-dresden.de/members/schulte-wissermann/html/Boston_2002/examples/photoeffect1.pdf"/>, 22/01/03</p></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
