<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_0311c" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Report on X-Ray Crystallography (Experiment M3)</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">Language used in quote: <foreign id="English">English</foreign></note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">deleted: footer: student name, page number, assignment title</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">1</p><p n="date">2002-11</p><p n="module title">Physics Laboratory</p><p n="module code">PX110</p><p n="genre family">Methodology recount</p><p n="discipline">Physics</p><p n="disciplinary group">PS</p><p n="grade">M</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">2061</p><p n="number of s-units">110</p><p n="number of p">56</p><p n="number of tables">2</p><p n="number of figures">4</p><p n="number of block quotes">1</p><p n="number of formulae">11</p><p n="number of lists">0</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">2</p><p n="abstract present">abstract present</p><p n="average words per s-unit">18.7</p><p n="average s-units per p">2.0</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">m</p><p n="year of birth">1984</p><p n="first language">English</p><p n="education">UKA</p><p n="course">MPhys</p><p n="student ID">0311</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><docTitle><titlePart>Report on X-Ray Crystallography (Experiment M3)</titlePart></docTitle><titlePart rend="bold"><name type="student name"/></titlePart></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="abstract"><head rend="underlined bold">Abstract</head><p n="p1.56"><s n="s1.3;p1.56">By measuring the angles of sharp x-ray diffraction maxima from alkali-halide crystals the lattice constants of five crystals were calculated; LiF 0.398 (±0.013) nm, NaF 0.444 (±0.017) nm, NaCl 0.540 (±0.025) nm, KCl 0.600 (±0.030) nm, CaF <hi rend="sub">2</hi> 0.530 (±0.017) nm. </s><s n="s2.3;p1.56">The atomic radii of the ions was calculated from these lattice constants and knowledge about the crystal structure; F- 0.131 (±0.013) nm, Na+ 0.091 (±0.021) nm, Cl- 0.179 (±0.037) nm, K+ 0.121 (±0.044) nm, Ca2+ 0.098 (±0.021) nm. </s><s n="s3.3;p1.56">By observing the symmetrical exposure of a photographic film sensitive to x-rays it was shown that a LiF crystal has long-range order of its ionic lattice. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">Introduction</head><p n="p2.56"><s n="s1.1;p2.56">Simple ionic crystals are structures that have periodic repetition of a pattern. </s></p><quote lang="English">"In the Face Centred Cubic (FCC) unit cell there is one host atom at each corner and one host atom in each face. The corner and face atoms touch along the face diagonal. The packing efficiency is about 74%. This is the maximum packing efficiency for spheres of equal radius and is call closest packing." <hi rend="sup">[1]</hi></quote><figure id="BAWE_0311c-pic.001"><head rend="bold italic">Figure 1 a stereoscopic model of a FCC unit cell.[1]</head></figure><p n="p3.56"><s n="s1.8;p3.56">From this it can be shown that the unit cell size is a constant value. </s><s n="s2.8;p3.56">This is called the lattice constant, '<hi rend="italic">a</hi>'. </s><s n="s3.8;p3.56">There are three planes to this crystal, the up-down, the left-right and the forward-backward. </s><s n="s4.8;p3.56">There are given numbers, called miller indices, which define which plane one is talking about. </s><s n="s5.8;p3.56">They are based on the reciprocal of the intercept of an axis in the unit cell. </s><s n="s6.8;p3.56">There are given in the form (h,k,l). </s><s n="s7.8;p3.56">Zero denotes that the plane never intercepts that axis (it is parallel). </s><s n="s8.8;p3.56">The higher the miller index the more perpendicular that plane is to that axis. </s></p><p n="p4.56"><s n="s1.1;p4.56">Miller indices are useful as they have important relation between them and the lattice constant. </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p5.56"><s n="s1.1;p5.56"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0311c-form.001"/> (1) </s></p><p n="p6.56"><s n="s1.1;p6.56">Where '<hi rend="italic">d</hi>' is the atomic spacing, '<hi rend="italic">h</hi>', '<hi rend="italic">k</hi>, '<hi rend="italic">l</hi>' are miller indices, and '<hi rend="italic">a</hi>' is the lattice constant. </s></p><p n="p7.56"><s n="s1.3;p7.56">In order to get visual information from an object it is important to take into account the wavelength of light used. </s><s n="s2.3;p7.56">A large wavelength would not have the resolution to discern various parts of the object if they were smaller than the wavelength used. </s><s n="s3.3;p7.56">It would be like trying to find the depths of the notches in a key by touch wearing a bulky glove. </s></p><p n="p8.56"><s n="s1.3;p8.56">Similarly to find the size of atoms (and ions) it is necessary to use a wavelength of light which is smaller than that of what you are trying to find the size of. </s><s n="s2.3;p8.56">However, atoms are incredibly tiny, and the wavelength of light required to resolve that detail is proportionally tiny. </s><s n="s3.3;p8.56">This poses a problem, as wavelength is proportional to the reciprocal of the frequency of the wave, and frequency is proportional to energy, the wave needed will have a very high energy. </s></p><p n="p9.56"><s n="s1.3;p9.56">These are not as easy to produce and measure as lower energy waves. </s><s n="s2.3;p9.56">Equation (1) has the solution. </s><s n="s3.3;p9.56">If we could measure the lattice constant, and with knowledge about which plane the waves were diffracting off, the atomic spacing can be inferred and so can the ionic size. </s></p><p n="p10.56"><s n="s1.5;p10.56">X-rays were discovered over a century ago by certain circumstances involving cathode-rays (streams of electrons) hitting various materials. </s><s n="s2.5;p10.56">Knowledge of how these x-rays were removed from materials came about some decades later when the theory of quantum mechanics was invented. </s><s n="s3.5;p10.56">The quantum aspect of these x-rays shows that the energies produced are in discrete quanta. </s><s n="s4.5;p10.56">Thus the frequencies and wavelengths are also in discrete quanta. </s><s n="s5.5;p10.56">This makes producing specific wavelengths very accurate, as there can exist any other wavelengths if the materials were manipulated correctly. </s></p><p n="p11.56"><s n="s1.2;p11.56">X-rays are suited for finding the atomic spacing because they have a similar wavelength to the gaps between atoms. </s><s n="s2.2;p11.56">This means that they diffract readily through the gaps. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0311c-fig.001"><head rend="bold italic">Figure 2 a schematic diagram of Bragg's model [2]</head></figure><p n="p12.56"><s n="s1.2;p12.56">Bragg proposed that the plane of atoms was like a partially reflecting mirror for x-rays. </s><s n="s2.2;p12.56">Constructive interference was caused when the angle of the incident x-rays was such that the reflection from the second plane was equal to a whole number of wavelengths phase difference. </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p13.56"><s n="s1.1;p13.56"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0311c-form.002"/> (2) </s></p><p n="p14.56"><s n="s1.7;p14.56">This is known as Bragg's Law. </s><s n="s2.7;p14.56">This method requires the wavelength to be of a known value. </s><s n="s3.7;p14.56">However, the Laue method requires holding a crystal stationary with many wavelengths of light being shone on it. </s><s n="s4.7;p14.56">As the x-rays pass through the crystal they diffract. </s><s n="s5.7;p14.56">At certain points some of the x-rays will form destructive interference and some constructive interference. </s><s n="s6.7;p14.56">Placing a film sensitive to x-rays at a known distance from the crystal would record the constructive interferences as dots. </s><s n="s7.7;p14.56">This assumes crystals have long-range order and would give information about the symmetry of the crystal structure. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">Experiment Details</head><p n="p15.56"><s n="s1.5;p15.56">The crystals (LiF, NaF, NaCl, KCl, CaF <hi rend="sub">2</hi>) were encased in a resin and this block was clamped in place on a rotating platform. </s><s n="s2.5;p15.56">As the crystal rotated through θ, the diffractometer arm rotates through 2θ. </s><s n="s3.5;p15.56">The diffractometer arm contains a 2mm collimator slit and a Geiger-Muller tube for detecting the x-rays. </s><s n="s4.5;p15.56">The detector is connected to a time-scaler and frequency meter set to a sensitivity of 450V. The primary x-ray generator was a copper source on 30kV producing x-rays with wavelengths 0.139 nm and 0.154 nm. </s><s n="s5.5;p15.56">These were collimated vertically by a 1mm slit. </s></p><p n="p16.56"><s n="s1.2;p16.56">The detector was moved around the crystal and at various angular intervals the number of counts was recorded over a 10 second period. </s><s n="s2.2;p16.56">At 0° there was a large intensity of x-rays, this was due to the x-rays passing straight through the crystal and no diffracting and so this value was ignored. </s></p><p n="p17.56"><s n="s1.3;p17.56">The range of recordings went from 2θ = 15° to 60° in steps of 5°. </s><s n="s2.3;p17.56">It was noticed that there was more intense x-rays recorded in certain bands. </s><s n="s3.3;p17.56">These bands covered 8° and a measurement was taken every 0.5°. </s></p><p n="p18.56"><s n="s1.1;p18.56">Due to the limited range of angles only the 1 <hi rend="sup">st</hi> order diffractions were discovered. </s></p><p n="p19.56"><s n="s1.3;p19.56">As the angles measured were in 2θ° the resolution of the angles were ±0.25°. </s><s n="s2.3;p19.56">The graphs of intensity against angle revealed two maxima over the particular crystal-dependant 8° range. </s><s n="s3.3;p19.56">The higher angle peak was due to the more intense 0.154 nm x-ray. </s></p><p n="p20.56"><s n="s1.3;p20.56">By using Braggs Law (equation (2)) the distance between the ions in the crystal could be found. </s><s n="s2.3;p20.56">Due to the way the crystals were orientated in the resin the plane that the x-rays were diffracted off was the (200) plane. </s><s n="s3.3;p20.56">Knowing the miller indices and rearranging equation (1) the substitution of '<hi rend="italic">d(200)</hi>' for <hi rend="italic">a/2</hi> can be made and '<hi rend="italic">a</hi>' can be found for the crystal. </s></p><p n="p21.56"><s n="s1.1;p21.56">Knowing the lattice constant for a crystal and its crystalline structure it is possible to calculate the size of the ions by assuming that opposite ions touch. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0311c-pic.002"><head rend="bold italic">Figure 3 showing a plan view of a face centred cubic crystal in the (100) plane. </head></figure><p n="p22.56"><s n="s1.2;p22.56">From <hi rend="bold italic">Figure 3</hi> you can see how the lattice constant '<hi rend="italic">a</hi>' is equal to a diameter of the larger ion and 2 times the radius of the smaller ion. </s><s n="s2.2;p22.56">So '<hi rend="italic">a</hi>' is the sum of the two diameters of the ions. </s></p><p n="p23.56"><s n="s1.2;p23.56">Having worked out '<hi rend="italic">a</hi>' for LiF and knowing that Li+ has radius 0.068 nm, the radius for F- can be worked out easily. </s><s n="s2.2;p23.56">Progressing through all the crystals like this revealed the ionic radii of Li+, F-, Na+, Cl- and K+. </s></p><p n="p24.56"><s n="s1.2;p24.56">By a similar method it is possible to find the ionic radius of Ca <hi rend="sup">2+</hi> because the values for F- and the lattice constant are known. </s><s n="s2.2;p24.56">However, CaF <hi rend="sub">2</hi> has a fluorite crystalline structure rather than a face-centred-cubic. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0311c-pic.003"><head rend="bold italic">Figure 4 showing a truncated plan view of the fluorite structure in the (110) plane. </head></figure><p n="p25.56"><s n="s1.1;p25.56">Knowing the radius of F- and '<hi rend="italic">a</hi>', Ca2+ can be easily calculated. </s></p><p n="p26.56"><s n="s1.2;p26.56">As a test for the above methods for calculating ionic radius a further restriction on the model can be imposed that states that like-ions must not touch. </s><s n="s2.2;p26.56">For the face-centred-cubic structure this means that the diameter of the larger negative ion must be less than <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0311c-form.003"/>, from Pythagoras's rule. </s></p><p n="p27.56"><s n="s1.2;p27.56">As a final check for the ion radii of K+ and F- there is known to be a crystal of KF which has a lattice constant of 0.532 nm. </s><s n="s2.2;p27.56">So the diameter of K+ + the diameter of F- must be less than this constant. </s></p><p n="p28.56"><s n="s1.2;p28.56">For the Laue method the crystal was held stationary and white x-rays shone on it for 55 minutes. </s><s n="s2.2;p28.56">A x-ray sensitive film was placed behind the crystal and developed after the 55 minutes of irradiation. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">Results</head><p n="p29.56"><s n="s1.1;p29.56">From measurements of maxima and equation (2): </s></p><table id="BAWE_0311c-tab.001"><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p30.56"><s n="s1.1;p30.56">From these results equation (1) states that <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0311c-form.004"/> (<formula notation="" id="BAWE_0311c-form.005"/> for CaF <hi rend="sub">2</hi>): </s></p><table id="BAWE_0311c-tab.002"><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p31.56"><s n="s1.1;p31.56">Using <hi rend="bold italic">Figure 3</hi> to see the relation of ions in LiF, and knowing Li+ has a radius of 0.068 nm, the radius of F- is calculated to be: </s></p><p n="p32.56"><s n="s1.1;p32.56"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0311c-form.006"/> </s></p><p n="p33.56"><s n="s1.1;p33.56">Using <hi rend="bold italic">Figure 3</hi> to see the relation of ions in NaF, and assuming F- has a radius of 0.131 nm, the radius of Na+ is calculated to be: </s></p><p n="p34.56"><s n="s1.1;p34.56"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0311c-form.007"/> </s></p><p n="p35.56"><s n="s1.1;p35.56">Using <hi rend="bold italic">Figure 3</hi> to see the relation of ions in NaCl, and assuming Na+ has a radius of 0.091 nm, the radius of Cl- is calculated to be: </s></p><p n="p36.56"><s n="s1.1;p36.56"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0311c-form.008"/> </s></p><p n="p37.56"><s n="s1.1;p37.56">Using <hi rend="bold italic">Figure 3</hi> to see the relation of ions in KCl, and assuming Cl- has a radius of 0.179 nm, the radius of K+ is calculated to be: </s></p><p n="p38.56"><s n="s1.1;p38.56"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0311c-form.009"/> </s></p><p n="p39.56"><s n="s1.2;p39.56">The ionic radius is larger for ions with more electrons. </s><s n="s2.2;p39.56">This is what is expected. </s></p><p n="p40.56"><s n="s1.1;p40.56">Using <hi rend="bold italic">Figure 4</hi> to see the relation of ions in CaF <hi rend="sub">2</hi>, and assuming F- has a radius of 0.131 nm, the radius of Ca2+ is calculated to be: </s></p><p n="p41.56"><s n="s1.1;p41.56"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0311c-form.010"/> </s></p><p n="p42.56"><s n="s1.1;p42.56">For the same-charge ions to be not touching the diameter of the larger negative ion must be less than <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0311c-form.011"/>. </s></p><p n="p43.56"><s n="s1.1;p43.56">In LiF the diameter of F- 0.262 nm is less than 0.281 nm </s></p><p n="p44.56"><s n="s1.1;p44.56">In NaF the diameter of F- 0.262 &lt; 0.314 nm </s></p><p n="p45.56"><s n="s1.1;p45.56">In NaCl the diameter of Cl- 0.358 &lt; 0.382 nm </s></p><p n="p46.56"><s n="s1.1;p46.56">In KCl the diameter of Cl- 0.358 &lt; 0.424 nm </s></p><p n="p47.56"><s n="s1.1;p47.56">So all the ionic radii are consistent with the "hard sphere" model of lattices. </s></p><p n="p48.56"><s n="s1.2;p48.56">Finally the diameter of K+ + the diameter of F- must be less than the lattice constant of KF which is 0.532 nm. </s><s n="s2.2;p48.56">It is as it values 0.504 (±0.046) nm. </s></p><p n="p49.56"><s n="s1.1;p49.56">The Laue method produced this photograph: </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0311c-pic.004"/><p n="p50.56"><s n="s1.6;p50.56">The pattern of symmetry is clearly visible in the placement of the dots. </s><s n="s2.6;p50.56">It has 6 lines of mirror symmetry. </s><s n="s3.6;p50.56">The first and second order diffractions are clearly seen. </s><s n="s4.6;p50.56">The large spot in the centre was where the x-rays travelled straight through the crystal. </s><s n="s5.6;p50.56">If you were to measure the intensities radially then you would find the graph of intensity against radius would be the same as one for a slit and coherent light. </s><s n="s6.6;p50.56">This shows that the LiF crystal had long range order in its lattice structure. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">Discussion</head><p n="p51.56"><s n="s1.2;p51.56">General limitations in the experimental procedure were that the reading of the angle couldn't be more accurate. </s><s n="s2.2;p51.56">However if the diffractometer were made more accurate then the clamp holding the crystal would have to be improved as it was only roughly holding the crystal in the correct alignment. </s></p><p n="p52.56"><s n="s1.2;p52.56">There was no way to test if the x-rays produced were of the wavelengths stated, so from this point of view the data obtained in unreliable. </s><s n="s2.2;p52.56">However there is little reason to think that the wavelengths were not calibrated and since the results are consistent for the two wavelengths it can be assumed they are calibrated. </s></p><p n="p53.56"><s n="s1.2;p53.56">The experimental errors were quite low considering the task of finding the atomic spacing. </s><s n="s2.2;p53.56">Averaging the number of counts over a period of 10 seconds reduced the uncertainty of finding a maxima, which helped with the angular uncertainty. </s></p><p n="p54.56"><s n="s1.1;p54.56">Using the result of one ionic radius to find others propagated errors, however the results for the ionic radii tied in with the distance that like-ions should be apart closely, so this is not a large problem with errors increasing unhelpfully large. </s></p><p n="p55.56"><s n="s1.1;p55.56">The Laue method clearly proves that LiF crystals have long range order and symmetry, this data is reliable as the pattern created related with the theory of the lattice structure and the measured data. </s></p><p n="p56.56"><s n="s1.1;p56.56">Overall the results are accurate and capable of supporting firm conclusions from. </s></p></div1></body><back><div1 type="bibliography"><head rend="underlined bold">References</head><p>[1] <seg type="URL" n="http://www.chem.lsu.edu/htdocs/people/sfwatkins/MERLOT/lattice/04fcc.html"/>, 14/02/03</p><p>[2] Figure and caption from 1<hi rend="sup">st</hi> year physics lab script, experiment M3, p. 2</p></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
