<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_0312c" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>This essay will explore the different concepts pertaining to legal parentage and parental responsibility in family law; focusing on how legal parentage is determined in common law and following the enactment of the Human Fertilisation and Embryology Act 1990 (HFEA 1990).</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">deleted: footer: student, module and page numbers</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">2</p><p n="date">2006-04</p><p n="module title">Law and the Family</p><p n="module code">LA211</p><p n="genre family">Essay</p><p n="discipline">Law</p><p n="disciplinary group">SS</p><p n="grade">M</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">2454</p><p n="number of s-units">103</p><p n="number of p">12</p><p n="number of tables">0</p><p n="number of figures">0</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">0</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">0</p><p n="abstract present">abstract present</p><p n="average words per s-unit">23.8</p><p n="average s-units per p">8.6</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">f</p><p n="year of birth">1985</p><p n="first language">Malay</p><p n="education">UK1.5</p><p n="course">LLB</p><p n="student ID">0312</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front/><body><div1 type="abstract"><p n="p1.12"><s n="s1.4;p1.12">This essay will explore the different concepts pertaining to legal parentage and parental responsibility in family law; focusing on how legal parentage is determined in common law and following the enactment of the Human Fertilisation and Embryology Act 1990 (HFEA 1990). </s><s n="s2.4;p1.12">The emphasis on this essay will then shift to the concept of parental responsibility and the numerous ways in which an individual who does not have parental responsibility can then take steps to acquire it. </s><s n="s3.4;p1.12">As such a discussion of those legal steps e.g. residence and adoption orders will be conducted on the basis of the current problem being analysed. </s><s n="s4.4;p1.12">Lastly the conclusion will be a reassessment of the issues discussed in the main sections and consequently a brief discussion as to whether these concepts are coherent with modern family life. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined">Legal Parentage </head><div2><head>(a) <hi rend="bold">Common Law</hi> : </head><p n="p2.12"><s n="s1.8;p2.12">The genetic mother and father of the resulting child will be the child's legal parents<ref target="BAWE_0312c-ftnote.001"/>. </s><s n="s2.8;p2.12">Therefore in common law Celia's parents will be Annabel; the egg donor and the sperm donor. </s><s n="s3.8;p2.12">However a complication then arises regarding Annabel because she did not give birth to Celia although she provided the genetic material. </s><s n="s4.8;p2.12">It was Beatrice who gave birth to Celia<ref target="BAWE_0312c-ftnote.002"/>. </s><s n="s5.8;p2.12">So the common law rule that a mother of a resulting child is the woman who provides the egg <hi rend="bold">and</hi> subsequently gives birth does not readily apply. </s><s n="s6.8;p2.12">Indeed common law rules are based on 'traditional' ways of conception where the father and mother have intercourse and the latter subsequently conceives naturally<ref target="BAWE_0312c-ftnote.003"/>. </s><s n="s7.8;p2.12">Technological advancements such as Artificial Insemination by a Donor (AID) and Invitro Fertilisation (IVF) were not available during the creation of common law rules and presumptions.<ref target="BAWE_0312c-ftnote.004"/> So situations in which a child is born through such methods had not been envisaged. </s><s n="s8.8;p2.12">Therefore the genetic link between father, mother and child which was the determining factor of legal parentage is no longer accurate in light of new technological methods </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0312c-ftnote.001"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1"><hi rend="italic">Re B (Parentage)</hi> [1996] 2 FLR 15, Fam Div <hi rend="italic">per</hi> Bracewell J, "I find fatherhood concerns [<hi rend="bold">genetics]</hi> and the provision of sperm which results in the birth of a child, unless either there is a presumption of legitimacy which affects the situation or there is statutory intervention such as, for example, the change of status afforded by adoption or freeing for adoption." </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">This highlights the common law rules and presumptions and its residual importance in light of advanced reproductive techniques such as AID and IVF. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0312c-ftnote.002"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Beatrice is termed the gestational mother as she carried the child to term and delivered her. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">The action of giving birth is called 'parturition'- as defined by <hi rend="italic">The Little Oxford English Dictionary</hi>, 2002, (8th ed.), Oxford University Press. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0312c-ftnote.003"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Biological links are important in English law in the context of child maintenance since it is for the natural parents to maintain a child (qualifying child). </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">Refer to Child Support Act 1991-95. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0312c-ftnote.004"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">However the use of blood samples and DNA testing in rebutting common law presumptions were made available in order to more accurately determine legal parentage. </s></p></note></div2><div2><head>(b) <hi rend="bold">Human Embryology Act 1990</hi> :</head><p n="p3.12"><s n="s1.11;p3.12">This Act governs the determination of legal parents in cases of AID and IVF or other modern techniques. </s><s n="s2.11;p3.12">The common law rules and presumptions do not apply unless specifically referred to in the Act. </s><s n="s3.11;p3.12">Therefore there must be consideration of the HFEA 1990 in determining Celia's legal parents. </s><s n="s4.11;p3.12">Consequently Beatrice is Celia's legal parent according to section 27(1) of the HFEA 1990<ref target="BAWE_0312c-ftnote.005"/>. </s><s n="s5.11;p3.12">It does seem slightly unfair that Annabel; the egg donor is not the legal parent considering that she provided the genetic material. </s><s n="s6.11;p3.12">But the Act probably envisaged cases where the egg may be anonymously<ref target="BAWE_0312c-ftnote.006"/> donated and holding such an individual as legal parent would be unnecessarily complicated since the donor usually has no intention to start a relationship with the resulting child. </s><s n="s7.11;p3.12">However surely the intention to donate and carry a child to term is sufficient evidence of an existing; albeit tenuous relationship with the child. </s><s n="s8.11;p3.12">Furthermore a relationship begins to develop between 'mother' and child through a growing 'maternal-foetal bond'. </s><s n="s9.11;p3.12">The purpose of the Act is also to protect donors. </s><s n="s10.11;p3.12">In order to encourage sperm and egg donors such rules had to be enacted especially since a natural parent is liable for child maintenance. </s><s n="s11.11;p3.12">Surely an individual who donates out of 'goodwill' should not be so unduly burdened<ref target="BAWE_0312c-ftnote.007"/>. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0312c-ftnote.005"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Section 27(1) HFEA 1990: The woman who is carrying or has carried a child as a result of the placing in her of an embryo or of sperm and eggs, and no other woman, is to be treated as the mother of the child. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0312c-ftnote.006"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Sperm, egg and embryo donors have lost anonymity since new law has been in force from 1 April 2005. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0312c-ftnote.007"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">However not all sperm donors are wholly voluntary since some fertility clinics such as 'The London Bridge Fertility Gynaecology and Genetics Centre' pay a sum of money e.g. £12 plus £5.50 expenses to sperm donors. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1"><seg type="URL" n="http://www.thebridgecentre.co.uk"/> </s></p></note><p n="p4.12"><s n="s1.17;p4.12">The next question is whether the sperm donor is considered as the legal father. </s><s n="s2.17;p4.12">The common law rules do not apply since the medical procedures were carried out in a regulated private clinic. </s><s n="s3.17;p4.12">The HFEA 1990 only applies in cases where the treatment services are provided in clinics licensed by the Human Fertilisation and Embryology Authority. </s><s n="s4.17;p4.12">It is safe to conclude that the private clinic in this case is licensed by the Authority.<ref target="BAWE_0312c-ftnote.008"/> Thus according to section 28(6)(a) of the HFEA 1990 a sperm donor who has consented to use of his genetic material for the purposes of treatment services will not be treated as the father of the child. </s><s n="s5.17;p4.12">This is reiterated in numerous cases such as <hi rend="italic">Re Q (Parental Order)</hi> (1996)<ref target="BAWE_0312c-ftnote.009"/> where Johnson J stated the law that "[t]he sperm was donated at a clinic under a licensed arrangement so that the donor is not the father, this being one of the exceptions under s 28(6)." </s><s n="s6.17;p4.12">Therefore Celia does not have a legal father and Beatrice is her only legal parent. </s><s n="s7.17;p4.12">This would seem to be an oddity in law since section 13(5)<ref target="BAWE_0312c-ftnote.010"/> HFEA 1990 provides that treatment services are subject to the welfare of a child including the need of a child for a father. </s><s n="s8.17;p4.12">This statement has been held to be prejudicial towards lesbians who wish to beget a child but case law<ref target="BAWE_0312c-ftnote.011"/> shows a growing acceptance that the 'traditional' and 'conventional' family is no longer the only concept of family. </s><s n="s9.17;p4.12">Thus lesbians e.g. in this instance can now have a child of their own although the resulting child has no legal father. </s><s n="s10.17;p4.12">However a sperm donor in an unregulated setting will still be considered the legal father in common law. </s><s n="s11.17;p4.12">This seems consistent with law; striving to deter informal AID but simultaneously providing for the resulting child to have a legal father. </s><s n="s12.17;p4.12">Is this justifiable? </s><s n="s13.17;p4.12">It is if viewed in respect of freedom of the parties. </s><s n="s14.17;p4.12">They are aware of the legal consequences and should be ready to bear them. </s><s n="s15.17;p4.12">Since having a child in these circumstances is a complex issue we would assume that the parties would have done research as to AID and parenting.<ref target="BAWE_0312c-ftnote.012"/> How about the ignorant individual who is unaware of the legal consequences attached to sperm donation? </s><s n="s16.17;p4.12">One view may be that his ignorance should not be held to negate his legal responsibilities since there is opportunity to discover the legal facts. </s><s n="s17.17;p4.12">Contrast this with the recent case of <hi rend="italic">B v A and others</hi> (2006)<ref target="BAWE_0312c-ftnote.013"/> where a sperm donor; the legal parent was quite aware of the legal consequences. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0312c-ftnote.008"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">This conclusion is inferred through the Human Fertilisation and Embryology Authority website: <seg type="URL" n="www.hfea.gov.uk/Home"/> which states that "The Human Fertilisation and Embryology Authority (HFEA) is a non-departmental Government body that regulates and inspects [<hi rend="bold">all]</hi> UK clinics providing IVF, donor insemination, or the storage of eggs, sperms or embryos." </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0312c-ftnote.009"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1"><hi rend="italic">Re Q (Parental Order)</hi> [1996] 1 FLR 369, 370, Fam Div </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0312c-ftnote.010"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Section 13(5) HFEA 1990: A woman shall not be provided with treatment services unless account has been taken of the welfare of any child who may be born as a result of the treatment (including the need of that child for a father), and any other child who may be affect by the birth. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0312c-ftnote.011"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">This is supported by cases such as <hi rend="italic">Re M (Adoption: Joint Residence Order: Same-Sex Couple)</hi> [2004] N.I.241, Fam Div, <hi rend="italic">X v Y (Parental Rights: Insemination)</hi> [2002] Fam L.R. 58, <hi rend="italic">B v B</hi> [1994] C.L.Y. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">3262 where parental responsibility were granted to non-heterosexual individuals; highlighting the importance of family relationships. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0312c-ftnote.012"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Many websites are available for same-sex couples who are planning to have a child through AID; whether formal or informal. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">Examples of websites such as <seg type="URL" n="www.stonewall.org.uk"/> , <seg type="URL" n="www.pinkparents.org.uk"/> and <seg type="URL" n="www.mannotincluded.com"/> </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0312c-ftnote.013"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1"><hi rend="italic">B v A and others</hi> [2006] EWHC 0002 Fam Div </s></p></note></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined">Parental Responsibility</head><div2><head><hi rend="bold">(a)</hi> <hi rend="bold">Who has Parental Responsibility?</hi> </head><p n="p5.12"><s n="s1.4;p5.12">The definition<ref target="BAWE_0312c-ftnote.014"/> of parental responsibility is listed in section 3(1) of the Children Act 1989 (CA 1989) and is a different concept from legal parentage. </s><s n="s2.4;p5.12">We must not assume that only legal parents will have parental responsibility because the latter can be acquired through law by other individuals e.g. local authority in a form of a care order; albeit in a limited sense. </s><s n="s3.4;p5.12">Beatrice who is the legal parent has automatic parental responsibility according to section 2(1) and (2) of CA 1989; specifically section 2(2)(a)<ref target="BAWE_0312c-ftnote.015"/> since she was not married to the sperm donor. </s><s n="s4.4;p5.12">Annabel who is not Celia's legal parent although genetically linked to her does <hi rend="bold">not</hi> have automatic parental responsibility. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0312c-ftnote.014"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Section 3(1) Children Act 1989: In this Act "parental responsibility" means all the rights, duties, powers, responsibilities and authority which by law a parent of a child has in relation to the child and his property. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0312c-ftnote.015"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Section 2(2)(a) CA 1989: Where a child's father and mother were not married to each other at the time of his birth-the mother shall have parental responsibility for the child </s></p></note></div2><div2><head><hi rend="bold">(b)</hi> <hi rend="bold">Acquiring Parental Responsibility</hi> :</head><div3><head rend="bold">Section 4A Acquisition of parental responsibility by step-parent</head><p n="p6.12"><s n="s1.14;p6.12">Annabel could potentially acquire parental responsibility through section 4A CA 1989. </s><s n="s2.14;p6.12">However the latter option is only available to married couples or civil partners and not cohabitants. </s><s n="s3.14;p6.12">Do Annabel and Beatrice have a civil partnership<ref target="BAWE_0312c-ftnote.016"/>? </s><s n="s4.14;p6.12">It seems unlikely since the words 'living together' indicate cohabitation. </s><s n="s5.14;p6.12">But they can subsequently register a civil partnership; allowing Annabel to acquire parental responsibility through section 4A(1)(a): parental responsibility agreement or section 4A(1)(b): court order. </s><s n="s6.14;p6.12">Both subsections require that the person acquiring parental responsibility is <hi rend="bold">not</hi> the child's parent. </s><s n="s7.14;p6.12">Does Annabel qualify? </s><s n="s8.14;p6.12">We have determined that Annabel is not the legal parent although she is the natural parent. </s><s n="s9.14;p6.12">Therefore if 'parent' in those sections imply legal parent; then Annabel can subsequently apply for parental responsibility. </s><s n="s10.14;p6.12">However it seems more likely for the law to mean <hi rend="italic">natural parent</hi> in this context; since it would make sense that a step-parent would not be genetically linked to the child as would normally be perceived. </s><s n="s11.14;p6.12">Furthermore step-parent is defined as "a person who is married [or a civil partner] to the father or mother of a child but is <hi rend="bold">not</hi> the natural parent of the child." </s><ref target="BAWE_0312c-ftnote.017"/><s n="s12.14;p6.12">It would seem absurd for the law to allow a natural parent who does not have parental responsibility to acquire it through a provision entitled "Acquisition of Parental Responsibility by <hi rend="bold italic">Step-Parent</hi>" since in most cases the natural parent; usually the father can acquire parental responsibility through e.g. parental responsibility agreements<ref target="BAWE_0312c-ftnote.018"/> and parental responsibility orders<ref target="BAWE_0312c-ftnote.019"/>. </s><s n="s13.14;p6.12">Therefore Annabel cannot be granted parental responsibility through section 4A since she is Celia's natural parent. </s><s n="s14.14;p6.12">However if donor egg was used Annabel could technically be able to acquire parental responsibility. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0312c-ftnote.016"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">The Civil Partnership Act 2004 came into force on the 5th of December 2005. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0312c-ftnote.017"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Editor: Martin, Elizabeth A., <hi rend="italic">A Dictionary of Law</hi>, (5th ed.), 2002, Oxford University Press. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0312c-ftnote.018"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Section 4(1)(b) CA 1989. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0312c-ftnote.019"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Section 4(1)(c) CA 1989. </s></p></note><p n="p7.12"><s n="s1.2;p7.12">If Annabel and Beatrice had split up shortly after the birth of Celia, it would still not be possible for Annabel to apply for parental responsibility since she would not qualify as 'step-parent'; being Celia's natural parent. </s><s n="s2.2;p7.12">Furthermore even if the law were to read 'parent' as legal parent and <hi rend="bold">not</hi> a natural parent there would still be complications i.e. the relationship has to be subsisting in order to acquire parental responsibility since the term "<hi rend="bold">is</hi> married to, or a civil partner of...." indicates current rather than past relationships. </s></p></div3><div3><head rend="bold">Residence Order</head><p n="p8.12"><s n="s1.7;p8.12">In order to apply automatically for a residence order Annabel has to be in a civil partnership with Beatrice according to section 10(5)(aa) CA 1989<ref target="BAWE_0312c-ftnote.020"/> or either acquire Beatrice's consent. </s><s n="s2.7;p8.12">It is likely that Beatrice will consent to such a resident order since there is no indication of any altercation. </s><s n="s3.7;p8.12">Annabel can still apply for a residence order if granted leave to apply<ref target="BAWE_0312c-ftnote.021"/> even without a civil partnership or consent. </s><s n="s4.7;p8.12">This is subject to the factors listed in section 10(9) CA 1989 that the court has to take into account when deciding the question of leave. </s><s n="s5.7;p8.12">It is likely that the court will grant leave since both Annabel and Beatrice are in an enduring family relationship and Annabel has a genetic link to Celia. </s><s n="s6.7;p8.12">Therefore Annabel will acquire parental responsibility through a residence order<ref target="BAWE_0312c-ftnote.022"/> which will last until Celia reaches the age of 18<ref target="BAWE_0312c-ftnote.023"/> unless varied or ended earlier. </s><s n="s7.7;p8.12">This form of parental responsibility is however limited since an individual with a residence order cannot consent to adoption<ref target="BAWE_0312c-ftnote.024"/> or appointment of a guardian<ref target="BAWE_0312c-ftnote.025"/>. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0312c-ftnote.020"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Section 10(5)(aa) CA 1989: The following persons are entitled to apply for a residence or contact order with respect to a child-any civil partner in a civil partnership (whether or not subsisting) in relation to whom the child is a child of the family. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0312c-ftnote.021"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Section 10(1)(a)(ii) CA 1989: In any family proceedings in which a question arises with respect to the welfare of any child, the court may make a section 8 order with respect to the child if an application for the order has been made by a person who has obtained the leave of the court to make the application. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0312c-ftnote.022"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Section 12(2) CA 1989: Where the court makes a residence order in favour of any person who is not the parent or guardian of the child concerned that person shall have parental responsibility for the child while the residence order remains in force. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0312c-ftnote.023"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Section 114 Adoption and Children Act 2002: Residence orders: extension to age of 18. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0312c-ftnote.024"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Section 12(3)(b) CA 1989 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0312c-ftnote.025"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Section 12(3)(c) CA 1989 </s></p></note><p n="p9.12"><s n="s1.14;p9.12">Annabel is still able to apply for a residence order even if they had split up shortly after the birth. </s><s n="s2.14;p9.12">She needs to apply for leave unless there is an automatic right to apply by acquiring Beatrice's consent. </s><s n="s3.14;p9.12">In this instance it is less likely that Beatrice will consent unless they are still on good terms. </s><s n="s4.14;p9.12">Thus in order to obtain leave Annabel has to show that she is still very involved in Celia's life and continues to be involved in her upbringing. </s><s n="s5.14;p9.12">Indeed in <hi rend="italic">G</hi> v <hi rend="italic"> F (shared residence: parental responsibility)</hi> (1998) <ref target="BAWE_0312c-ftnote.026"/><hi rend="italic">per</hi> Bracewell J, "...the applicant has played such an important role in the life and upbringing of a child and continues to do so, in my judgment, she fulfils the criteria for being granted leave to make an application." </s><s n="s6.14;p9.12">Therefore it highlights the importance of a continuing and genuine involvement in a child's life in order to succeed. </s><s n="s7.14;p9.12">The question of leave does not involve section 1(1)<ref target="BAWE_0312c-ftnote.027"/> but the granting of a residence order will. </s><s n="s8.14;p9.12">This is highlighted in cases such as <hi rend="italic">G</hi> v <hi rend="italic"> F (shared residence: parental responsibility)</hi> (1998) and <hi rend="italic">Re G (Residence: Same-Sex Partner)</hi> (2005)<ref target="BAWE_0312c-ftnote.028"/> where the court granted shared residence orders in both instances. </s><s n="s9.14;p9.12">In those two cases it was found that the individuals applying for a residence order were in fear of being marginalised and they both shared a close relationship with the child in question. </s><s n="s10.14;p9.12">It was in the child's welfare that a joint residence order be granted. </s><s n="s11.14;p9.12">Furthermore in the latter case <hi rend="italic">per</hi> Thorpe LJ, "A significant feature... was that the appellant could only achieve parental responsibility in relation to these two children if she succeeded in her application for a joint residence order." </s><s n="s12.14;p9.12">Thus it seems that the order was granted on the basis that it was the only way in which she could acquire parental responsibility. </s><s n="s13.14;p9.12">So it implies that a joint residence order will be granted if it is the only and last resort. </s><s n="s14.14;p9.12">In cases where the parties have not split up and have recourse to other legal procedures e.g. section 4A CA 1989 that is available to same-sex couples; it is likely that courts will less readily grant shared residence orders. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0312c-ftnote.026"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1"><hi rend="italic">G v F (shared residence: parental responsibility)</hi> [1998] Fam Law 587, Fam Div </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0312c-ftnote.027"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Section 1(1) Children Act 1989 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0312c-ftnote.028"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1"><hi rend="italic">Re G (Residence: Same-Sex Partner)</hi> [2005] 2 FLR 957 </s></p></note></div3><div3><head rend="bold">Adoption Order</head><p n="p10.12"><s n="s1.9;p10.12">Another option in which Annabel can acquire parental responsibility is through an adoption order<ref target="BAWE_0312c-ftnote.029"/>. </s><s n="s2.9;p10.12">The Adoption and Children Act 2002 (ACA 2002) now allows same-sex couples who are civil partners or cohabitants to adopt jointly. </s><s n="s3.9;p10.12">This is possible with the existence of section 50 ACA 2002 particularly section 50(2)<ref target="BAWE_0312c-ftnote.030"/>. </s><s n="s4.9;p10.12">However cohabitants have to prove they are "living as partners in an enduring family relationship." </s><s n="s5.9;p10.12">Annabel should adopt individually as it would seem strange for Beatrice to adopt Celia since Beatrice already has automatic parental responsibility. </s><s n="s6.9;p10.12">Hence Annabel can invoke section 51(2) ACA 2002<ref target="BAWE_0312c-ftnote.031"/> in order to adopt Celia subject to the interpretation of 'partner of a child's parent'<ref target="BAWE_0312c-ftnote.032"/> and with Beatrice's consent<ref target="BAWE_0312c-ftnote.033"/>. </s><s n="s7.9;p10.12">'Parent' is probably interpreted as <hi rend="italic">natural</hi> parent since this would be consistent with the interpretation of parent as according to section 4A CA 1989 and section 14C CA 1989-special guardianship orders. </s><s n="s8.9;p10.12">Therefore Annabel would not fulfil the adoption order requirements since she is Celia's natural parent. </s><s n="s9.9;p10.12">So Annabel and Beatrice have no choice but to adopt jointly as a couple. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0312c-ftnote.029"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Section 46(1) Adoption and Children Act 2002 states that "an adoption order is an order made by the court on an application under section 50 or 51 giving parental responsibility for a child to the adopters or adopter." </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0312c-ftnote.030"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Section 50(2) ACA 2002: An adoption order may be made on the application of a couple where (a) one of the couple is the mother or the father of the person to be adopted and has attained the age of 18 years, and (b) the other has attained the age of 21 years. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0312c-ftnote.031"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Section 51(2) ACA 2002: An adoption order may be made on the application of one person who has attained the age of 21 years if the court is satisfied that the person is the partner of a parent of the person to be adopted. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0312c-ftnote.032"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Section 114(7) ACA 2002: For the purposes of this Act, a person is the partner of a child's parent if the person and the parent are a couple but the person is not the child's parent. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0312c-ftnote.033"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Section 47-Conditions for making adoption orders and Section 52- Parental etc. consent ACA 2002 are applicable. </s></p></note><p n="p11.12"><s n="s1.6;p11.12">If Annabel and Beatrice subsequently split up after Celia's birth it is still possible to apply for an adoption order by invoking section 51(3A)(b) ACA 2002<ref target="BAWE_0312c-ftnote.034"/>; as long as Annabel can satisfy the courts that their separation is likely to be permanent. </s><s n="s2.6;p11.12">However the term 'likely to be permanent' is ambiguous since it has many degrees. </s><s n="s3.6;p11.12">It can be interpreted as being a probability, virtually permanent or a possibility. </s><s n="s4.6;p11.12">How it is interpreted will remain to be seen in future cases. </s><s n="s5.6;p11.12">Furthermore there is an additional hurdle in the form of section 51(4) ACA 2002 which prevents a natural parent from being granted an adoption order unless certain requirements are fulfilled. </s><s n="s6.6;p11.12">So it is unlikely that Annabel will succeed in obtaining an adoption order. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0312c-ftnote.034"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Section 51(3A) ACA 2002: An adoption order may be made on the application of one person who has attained the age of 21 years and is a civil partner if the court is satisfied that the civil partners are separated and are living apart, and the separation is likely to be permanent. </s></p></note><p n="p12.12"><s n="s1.7;p12.12">The problems in determining legal parentage and parental responsibility are clearly highlighted in cases involving AID and IVF; especially in the context of same-sex relationships. </s><s n="s2.7;p12.12">These problems arise because common law rules do not readily apply in such circumstances and are instead governed by the HFEA 1990. </s><s n="s3.7;p12.12">Yet the latter is not a perfect solution since there are still aspects prejudicial to lesbian relationships i.e. section 13(5) HFEA 1990. </s><s n="s4.7;p12.12">The law has been lagging in terms of implementing legislation that reflects social realities. </s><s n="s5.7;p12.12">But at least the law has started to legally acknowledge same-sex relationships by allowing joint adoption by same-sex couples<ref target="BAWE_0312c-ftnote.035"/> and civil partnerships. </s><s n="s6.7;p12.12">This is indeed an encouraging start in solving difficulties pertaining to parental responsibility in the context of non-traditional families. </s><s n="s7.7;p12.12">But the extent to which recent legislation<ref target="BAWE_0312c-ftnote.036"/> is applied and interpreted in such 'unconventional' relationships will have to be examined in light of future cases. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0312c-ftnote.035"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Joint adoption by same-sex couples or non-heterosexual individuals has been allowed ever since the Adoption Act 1976; which has been repealed by the new Adoption and Children Act 2002 that recognises civil partnerships. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0312c-ftnote.036"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Examples of recent legislation are the Adoption and Children Act 2002 and Civil Partnership Act 2004. </s></p></note></div3></div2></div1></body><back><div1 type="bibliography"><div2 type="bibliography"><head rend="underlined bold">Bibliography</head><p>Cretney, Stephen. 2003. <hi rend="italic">Family Law in the Twentieth Century</hi>. Oxford University Press.</p><p>Cretney, Stephen M., Masson, Judith M. &amp; Bailey-Harris, Rebecca. 2003. <hi rend="italic">Principles of</hi></p><p><hi rend="italic">Family Law</hi>. Sweet &amp; Maxwell Ltd. London.</p><p>Dewar, John. 1992. <hi rend="italic">Law and the Family</hi>. Butterworth &amp; Co (Publishers) Ltd. </p><p>Martin, Elizabeth A. (Editor). <hi rend="italic">A Dictionary of Law</hi>. Oxford University Press.</p><p>Probert, Rebecca. 2003. <hi rend="italic">Cretney's Family Law</hi>. Sweet &amp; Maxwell Ltd. London</p><p>Standley, Kate. 2001. <hi rend="italic">Family Law</hi>. Palgrave Publishers Ltd. </p></div2><div2 type="bibliography"><head rend="underlined bold">Cases</head><p>B (Parentage), Re [1996] 2 FLR 15, Fam Div</p><p>B v A and others [2006] EWHC 0002, Fam Div</p><p>B v B [1994] C.L.Y. 3262</p><p>G (Residence: Same-Sex Partner), Re [2005] 2 FLR 957</p><p>G v F (shared residence: parental responsibility) [1998] Fam Law 587, Fam Div</p><p>M (Adoption: Joint Residence Order: Same-Sex Couple), Re [2004] N.I.241, Fam Div</p><p>Q (Parental Order), Re [1996] 1 FLR 369, 370, Fam Div</p><p>X v Y (Parental Rights: Insemination) [2002] Fam L.R. 58</p></div2><div2 type="bibliography"><head rend="underlined bold">Websites</head><p><seg type="URL" n="www.cafcass.gov.uk"/></p><p>(Accessed 8 April 2006)</p><p><seg type="URL" n="www.carelaw.org.uk"/></p><p>(Accessed 8 April 2006)</p><p><seg type="URL" n="www.gro.gov.uk/gro/content/"/></p><p>(Accessed 9 April 2006)</p><p><seg type="URL" n="www.hfea.gov.uk/Home"/></p><p>(Accessed 8 April 2006)</p><p><seg type="URL" n="www.mannotincluded.com"/></p><p>(Accessed 8 April 2006)</p><p><seg type="URL" n="www.pinkparents.org.uk"/></p><p>(Accessed 8 April 2006)</p><p><seg type="URL" n="www.rightsofwomen.org.uk"/></p><p>(Accessed 8 April 2006)</p><p><seg type="URL" n="www.stonewall.org.uk"/></p><p>(Accessed 8 April 2006)</p><p><seg type="URL" n="www.thebridgecentre.co.uk"/></p><p>(Accessed 9 April 2006)</p><p><seg type="URL" n="http://uk.westlaw.com"/></p><p>(Accessed 5 April 2006)</p><p><seg type="URL" n="http://web.lexis-nexis.com/professional/"/></p><p>(Accessed 5 April 2006)</p></div2></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
