<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_0312b" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Discuss: "Custom is now of limited importance as a source of International Law."</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">deleted: footer: student, module and page numbers</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">2</p><p n="date">2006-02</p><p n="module title">International Law</p><p n="module code">LA205</p><p n="genre family">Essay</p><p n="discipline">Law</p><p n="disciplinary group">SS</p><p n="grade">D</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">2509</p><p n="number of s-units">112</p><p n="number of p">6</p><p n="number of tables">0</p><p n="number of figures">0</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">0</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">0</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">22.4</p><p n="average s-units per p">18.7</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">f</p><p n="year of birth">1985</p><p n="first language">Malay</p><p n="education">UK1.5</p><p n="course">LLB</p><p n="student ID">0312</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><docTitle><titlePart rend="underlined"> Discuss: "Custom is now of limited importance as a source of International Law."</titlePart></docTitle></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="section"><p n="p1.6"><s n="s1.10;p1.6">The international legal sphere is a complex framework of symbiotic and interdependent relationships between states. </s><s n="s2.10;p1.6">The fact that there is hardly a coherent legal structure and legislating body to govern these fragile and fluid connections has led to considerable innovation. </s><s n="s3.10;p1.6">In order to give effect and substance to international law, jurists have debated about the role and significance of the various sources of international law. </s><s n="s4.10;p1.6">This essay will primarily explore the notion that the significance of custom is currently waning in international law. </s><s n="s5.10;p1.6">For purposes of limiting and focusing the discussion of this essay; the analysis of other sources of law such as general principles of law, judicial decisions and teachings of highly qualified publicists enumerated in Article 38(1) of the Statute of the International Court of Justice (ICJ) will not be included. </s><s n="s6.10;p1.6">Therefore, there will be an emphasis of custom in relation to international conventions, the use of force, and the role of peremptory norms; <hi rend="italic">jus cogens</hi>, and custom as a proxy for efficiency. </s><s n="s7.10;p1.6">This discussion will also include the inherent problems of the two elements within custom; state practice and opinio juris sive necessitatis (therein referred to as opinio juris). </s><s n="s8.10;p1.6">Appropriate cases from the ICJ will also be referred to as a device in understanding the role of custom in earlier and more recent times. </s><s n="s9.10;p1.6">In addition, this essay will briefly discuss the importance of 'soft law' such as the persuasive force of Security Council and General Assembly Resolutions of the United Nations. </s><s n="s10.10;p1.6">Ergo by taking into consideration all aspects of law discussed in this essay, a conclusion will then be made as to whether custom is now of limited importance as a source of international law. </s></p><p n="p2.6"><s n="s1.25;p2.6">Before starting on a substantive discussion of custom or customary law, it is first essential to define 'source'. </s><s n="s2.25;p2.6">"By 'sources' one means those provisions operating within the legal system on a technical level, and such ultimate sources as reason or morality are excluded..." </s><ref target="BAWE_0312b-ftnote.001"/><s n="s3.25;p2.6">However, the term 'source' is in itself problematic as pointed out by Kelsen that it is "a figurative and highly ambiguous expression." </s><ref target="BAWE_0312b-ftnote.002"/><s n="s4.25;p2.6">International custom is listed in Article 38(1)(b) of the Statute of the ICJ "as evidence of general practice accepted as law." </s><s n="s5.25;p2.6">It is widely accepted that two important elements have to be complied with in order to form custom. </s><s n="s6.25;p2.6">These are (1) state practice and (2) <hi rend="italic">opinio juris</hi>. </s><s n="s7.25;p2.6">It is thus regrettable that these elements pose the most problems in the formation of custom especially since they are the basis of custom formation. </s><s n="s8.25;p2.6">The requirements for constituting state practice are not coherent even though general principles have been expounded in cases brought before the ICJ. In the <hi rend="italic">North Sea Continental Shelf</hi> cases, it was held that "state practice, including that of states whose interests are specially affected, should [be] both extensive and virtually uniform..." </s><ref target="BAWE_0312b-ftnote.003"/><s n="s9.25;p2.6">Questions have arose regarding the usage of 'extensive' and 'virtually uniform'. </s><s n="s10.25;p2.6">Does this mean that consistent practice has to be adopted by all involving states and any irregularities on the part of a state signal a deviance from uniformity? </s><s n="s11.25;p2.6">It has been argued that such a deviance is unlawful if indeed a custom has been formed. </s><s n="s12.25;p2.6">However, this raises the alleged theory of the 'persistent objector'<ref target="BAWE_0312b-ftnote.004"/>. </s><s n="s13.25;p2.6">Thus, it is apparent that custom is plagued with uncertainties that serve to perpetuate mounting criticism on it. </s><s n="s14.25;p2.6">Another inherent complication within custom is that of <hi rend="italic">opinio juris</hi>. </s><s n="s15.25;p2.6">This is termed the 'psychological element' "or belief that a state activity is legally obligatory." </s><ref target="BAWE_0312b-ftnote.005"/><s n="s16.25;p2.6">There is a sense of circularity in this requirement. </s><s n="s17.25;p2.6">In order to create a new custom, there must be a belief by states involved that such a norm is already legally binding. </s><s n="s18.25;p2.6">As encapsulated by Goldsmith and Posner, "The idea of <hi rend="italic">opinio juris</hi> is mysterious because the legal obligation is created by a state's belief in the existence of the legal obligation." </s><ref target="BAWE_0312b-ftnote.006"/><s n="s19.25;p2.6">Therefore it seems rather inefficient to determine a formation of custom on a belief that custom is already in existence. </s><s n="s20.25;p2.6">It is exactly because the existence of <hi rend="italic">opinio juris</hi> cannot be effectively determined that custom is of limited importance in international law. </s><s n="s21.25;p2.6">The uncertainties surrounding the requirements of state practice and <hi rend="italic">opinio juris</hi> make it difficult for states to depend on custom as a source of international law. </s><s n="s22.25;p2.6">For example, in order to establish a concrete argument based on custom, there must also be a concrete basis for an argument; that would be custom itself. </s><s n="s23.25;p2.6">So without certainty it seems that custom is now of limited importance; it will possibly be relegated to the bottom if its problems are not dealt with. </s><s n="s24.25;p2.6">However there is also the argument that custom is rendered flexible without these precise set of requirements. </s><s n="s25.25;p2.6">This is linked with the argument that customary international law as a judicial tool promotes efficiency.<ref target="BAWE_0312b-ftnote.007"/> The facts of this discussion will be expounded in the next section. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0312b-ftnote.001"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Shaw, Malcolm N., <hi rend="italic">International Law</hi>, 5th ed., 2003, Cambridge University Press, p.66. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0312b-ftnote.002"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Kunz, Josef L., 'The Nature of Customary International Law', <hi rend="italic">The American Journal of International Law</hi>, Vol.47, No.4, Oct.,1953, p.663 <seg type="URL" n="http://links.jstor.org/sici?sici=0002-9300%28195310%2947%3A4%3C662%3ATNOCIL%3E2.0.Co%3B2-W"/> 4 February 2006. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0312b-ftnote.003"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1"><hi rend="italic">North Sea Continental Shelf</hi> Cases (1969), ICJ Reports 3 at p.44 (para.74) </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0312b-ftnote.004"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">See Cassese, Antonio, <hi rend="italic">International Law</hi>, 2nd ed., 2005, Oxford University Press, p.163. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">Cassese argues that "the contention is warranted that a State is not entitled to claim that it is not bound by a new customary rule because it consistently opposed it before it ripened into a customary rule." </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0312b-ftnote.005"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Shaw, Malcolm N., <hi rend="italic">International Law</hi>, 5th ed., 2003, Cambridge University Press, p.80. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0312b-ftnote.006"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Goldsmith, Jack L. &amp; Posner, Eric A., <hi rend="italic">The Limits of International Law</hi>, 2005, Oxford University Press, p.24. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0312b-ftnote.007"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">See Benvenisti, Eyal &amp; Hirsch, Moshe, <hi rend="italic">The Impact of International Law on International Cooperation: Theoretical Perspectives</hi>, 1st ed., 2004, Cambridge University Press. </s></p></note><p n="p3.6"><s n="s1.30;p3.6">Custom may at closer inspection still retain its importance in international law especially in relation to states that are not parties to a particular convention. </s><s n="s2.30;p3.6">Therefore allowing some sort of judicial activism to manifest itself and manipulate custom to promote efficiency. </s><s n="s3.30;p3.6">As per Benvenisti, "efficiency is the underlying principle- the <hi rend="italic">grundnorm</hi>- of customary international law." </s><ref target="BAWE_0312b-ftnote.008"/><s n="s4.30;p3.6">Kelsen established the concept of <hi rend="italic">grundnorm</hi> and according to Kelsen, "the <hi rend="italic">grundnorm</hi> is a logical necessity for all normative systems." </s><ref target="BAWE_0312b-ftnote.009"/><s n="s5.30;p3.6">But judicial activism is itself another source of debate as judges are not allowed to make law in a course of proceedings. </s><s n="s6.30;p3.6">Instead judges are to apply the law<ref target="BAWE_0312b-ftnote.010"/>. </s><s n="s7.30;p3.6">But it is evident that custom is used as a judicial tool to create new law as highlighted in the two decisions of the ICJ, <hi rend="italic">Nicaragua v.</hi> </s><s n="s8.30;p3.6"><hi rend="italic">United States</hi>and <hi rend="italic">Gabcikovo-Nagymaros.</hi> </s><s n="s9.30;p3.6">In the former, "it reveals the judges of the [ICJ] deciding the content of customary international law on a tabula rasa." </s><ref target="BAWE_0312b-ftnote.011"/><s n="s10.30;p3.6">So according to D'Amato, the judges circumvented the requirements of state practice and <hi rend="italic">opinio juris</hi> by simply deciding that the latter was furnished by the former and loosely interpreting state practice. </s><s n="s11.30;p3.6">The impetus for such a decision was probably due to strong convictions among the majority judges that there should be a customary international law governing the use of force in that instance. </s><s n="s12.30;p3.6">In <hi rend="italic">Gabcikovo-Nagymaros</hi> "the Court distorted the logic of the [Watercourses Convention] and treated it as an empty vessel into which it injected its own contradictory vision, pouring <hi rend="italic">new law in old bottles</hi>." </s><ref target="BAWE_0312b-ftnote.012"/><s n="s13.30;p3.6">Thus to circumvent the two problematic requirements; state practice and <hi rend="italic">opinio juris</hi> the Court exploited customs' inherent vagueness to promote 'efficiency'. </s><s n="s14.30;p3.6">It can be clearly seen that it is exactly the existence of these problems that eventually lead to efficiency. </s><s n="s15.30;p3.6">But is there really efficiency? </s><s n="s16.30;p3.6">If to promote efficiency means to create uncertainty and vagueness, surely international law is better off with a coherent set of rules and requirements. </s><s n="s17.30;p3.6">Therefore custom may indeed be of limited importance in light of this discussion. </s><s n="s18.30;p3.6"><hi rend="italic">Jus cogens</hi> or peremptory norms are argued by Cassese to be "a special class of <hi rend="italic">general rules</hi> made by custom [that] has been endowed with a <hi rend="italic">special legal force</hi>." </s><ref target="BAWE_0312b-ftnote.013"/><s n="s19.30;p3.6">This means that these norms such as slavery and genocide cannot be derogated from. </s><s n="s20.30;p3.6">So is <hi rend="italic">jus cogens</hi> a 'super-custom' or just another form of international law? </s><s n="s21.30;p3.6">If we take the former approach that it is a higher derivative of custom then the latter is by no means limited in its importance. </s><s n="s22.30;p3.6">Custom's potential role is then to maintain the current peremptory norms and lay the foundation for the formation of others, and thereby promoting issues of humanitarian law. </s><s n="s23.30;p3.6">Another informal source of international law termed 'soft law' has been a source of debate among jurists in the past decade. "['Soft law'] is a body of standards, commitments, joint statements, or declarations of policy or intention." </s><ref target="BAWE_0312b-ftnote.014"/><s n="s24.30;p3.6">The complication is whether 'soft law' has any binding effect. </s><s n="s25.30;p3.6">It is generally held that they do not and therefore General Assembly and Security Council Resolutions are held to be only of persuasive force. </s><s n="s26.30;p3.6">It has been stated by commentators that 'soft law' complements custom in some sense. </s><s n="s27.30;p3.6">This is because they help furnish custom with the necessary state practice and <hi rend="italic">opinio juris</hi> requirements by providing evidence; in the form of basic evidential documents and negotiations within international organizations. </s><s n="s28.30;p3.6">This is supported by Shaw who states that "[a]s well as constituting state practice...such resolutions [are] evidence of the existence of or evolution towards an <hi rend="italic">opinio juris</hi> without which a custom cannot arise." </s><ref target="BAWE_0312b-ftnote.015"/><s n="s29.30;p3.6">It is now easier to satisfy and prove the requirements for the formation of custom with the additional assistance of 'soft law' such as declarations. </s><s n="s30.30;p3.6">This will then prevent the time lag and uncertainty related to custom and subsequently proving that custom is still as important in international law as before. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0312b-ftnote.008"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid. p.88. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0312b-ftnote.009"><p n="pn1.3"><s n="s1.1;pn1.3">Kammerhofer, Jorg, 'Uncertainty in the Formal Sources of International Law: Customary International Law and Some of Its Problems', <hi rend="italic">European Journal of International Law</hi> 2004.15 (523), p. 16. </s></p><p n="pn2.3"><s n="s1.1;pn2.3"><hi rend="underlined"> </hi><seg type="URL" n="http://web.lexis-nexis.com/professional"/> </s></p><p n="pn3.3"><s n="s1.1;pn3.3">5 February 2006. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0312b-ftnote.010"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Benvenisti, Eyal &amp; Hirsch, Moshe, op.cit. note 8, p.86. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">It is argued that the ICJ has the authority to create new customs as long as it is the only insitution capable of making such decisions at the material time. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0312b-ftnote.011"><p n="pn1.3"><s n="s1.1;pn1.3">D'Amato, Anthony, 'Trashing Customary International Law', <hi rend="italic">The American Journal of International Law</hi>, Vol.81, No.1 (Jan., 1987), 101-105, p.101-102. </s></p><p n="pn2.3"><s n="s1.1;pn2.3"><hi rend="underlined"> </hi><seg type="URL" n="http://links.jstor.org/sici?sici=0002-9300%28198701%2981%3A1%3C101%3ATCIL%3E2.0.CO%3B2-1"/> </s></p><p n="pn3.3"><s n="s1.1;pn3.3">5 February 2006. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0312b-ftnote.012"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Benvenisti, Eyal &amp; Hirsch, Moshe, <hi rend="italic">The Impact of International Law on International Cooperation: Theoretical Perspectives</hi>, 1st ed., 2004, Cambridge University Press, p.86. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0312b-ftnote.013"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Cassese, Antonio, <hi rend="italic">International Law</hi>, 2nd ed., 2005, Oxford University Press, p.199. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0312b-ftnote.014"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Cassese, Antonio, <hi rend="italic">International Law</hi>, 2nd ed., 2005, Oxford University Press, p.196. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0312b-ftnote.015"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Shaw, Malcolm N., <hi rend="italic">International Law</hi>, 5th ed., 2003, Cambridge University Press, p.109. </s></p></note><p n="p4.6"><s n="s1.24;p4.6">The relationship between custom and treaty is indeed a complex one. </s><s n="s2.24;p4.6">It is generally accepted by jurists that a hierarchy of sources of international law do not exist. </s><s n="s3.24;p4.6">So both custom and treaty are on equal footing. </s><s n="s4.24;p4.6">But three important maxims have to be taken into account; <hi rend="italic">lex posterior generalis non derogat priori specialis</hi>,<hi rend="italic"> lex posterior generalis derogat priori</hi> and <hi rend="italic">lex specialis derogat legi generalis</hi>. </s><s n="s5.24;p4.6">Custom has been slowly losing its importance as a source of international law ever since the end of the Second World War. </s><s n="s6.24;p4.6">This is evident with the increasing codification of international law in the form of treaties such as the Charter of the United Nations, the 1969 Vienna Convention on the Law of Treaties and the Genocide Convention. </s><s n="s7.24;p4.6">One of the reasons why treaties have surpassed custom in terms of importance is that the formation of the latter is rather time-consuming. </s><s n="s8.24;p4.6">Thus custom may be "outdated and archaic" when it does come into force and "as a result states, recognizing the inadequacy of a customary rule [fall] into the habit of violating it because of that inadequacy." </s><ref target="BAWE_0312b-ftnote.016"/><s n="s9.24;p4.6">But "[t]reaties, on the other hand, are a more direct and formal method of international law creation." </s><ref target="BAWE_0312b-ftnote.017"/><s n="s10.24;p4.6">So formulating a new law by way of treaty produces quicker and arguably better results notwithstanding that some states may simply choose not to be parties to it. </s><s n="s11.24;p4.6">The United States for instance is not a party to the Rome Statue. </s><s n="s12.24;p4.6">Therefore in some cases custom may have a wider ambit than treaties and consequently wider influence. </s><s n="s13.24;p4.6">Treaties are specific in nature and have a degree of certainty because only the states to the treaty can be bound by the law. </s><s n="s14.24;p4.6">Custom is applicable to all states that have fulfilled the requirements of state practice and <hi rend="italic">opinio juris</hi> and even in cases where there is only acquiescence. </s><s n="s15.24;p4.6">Therefore, it is argued by Gerhard von Glahn that custom based on Western homogeneous values are being placed on other diverse legal orders not necessarily sharing such values<ref target="BAWE_0312b-ftnote.018"/>. </s><s n="s16.24;p4.6">But if those values are positive values that for example encourage the protection of human rights then surely custom is doing something right. </s><s n="s17.24;p4.6">Humanitarian intervention is a contentious issue and to argue that customary international law exists or should exist to prevent gross violations of human rights is not a question for this essay. </s><s n="s18.24;p4.6">However if there were custom in that aspect and assuming it were properly utilised without the risk of abuse by powerful states, it would serve nation states well by safeguarding the sanctity of human life. </s><s n="s19.24;p4.6">Every state would then be bound. </s><s n="s20.24;p4.6">This is unlike treaties where "they only bind ... the States that have agreed to be bound by their provisions." </s><ref target="BAWE_0312b-ftnote.019"/><s n="s21.24;p4.6">Treaties themselves are also inherently problematic and may lack certain substance because of being improperly worded and interpreted. </s><s n="s22.24;p4.6">The Rome Statute for example is non-retroactive and so cannot prosecute atrocities committed prior to its coming into force<ref target="BAWE_0312b-ftnote.020"/>. </s><s n="s23.24;p4.6">Custom therefore has an important role to play in instances where treaties do not possess their full weight. </s><s n="s24.24;p4.6">In addition custom still retains its importance in relation to the customary principle of "<hi rend="italic">pacta sunt servanda</hi>"; which is "the bedrock of the customary international law of treaties."<ref target="BAWE_0312b-ftnote.021"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0312b-ftnote.016"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Von Glahn, Gerhard, <hi rend="italic">Law among Nations: An Introduction to Public International Law</hi>, 4th ed., 1981, Collier Macmillan Publishers London, p.23. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0312b-ftnote.017"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Shaw, Malcolm N., <hi rend="italic">International Law</hi>, 5th ed., 2003, Cambridge University Press, p.810. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0312b-ftnote.018"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">See Von Glahn, Gerhard, op.cit. note 20, p.23 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0312b-ftnote.019"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Cassese, Antonio, <hi rend="italic">International Law</hi>, 2nd ed., 2005, Oxford University Press, p.170. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0312b-ftnote.020"><p n="pn1.3"><s n="s1.1;pn1.3">See Article 24: Non-retroactivity ratione personae, Rome Statute of the International Court (entered into force on 1 July 2002) </s></p><p n="pn2.3"><s n="s1.1;pn2.3"><hi rend="underlined"> </hi><seg type="URL" n="http://www.un.org/law/icc/statute/romefra.htm"/> </s></p><p n="pn3.3"><s n="s1.1;pn3.3">6 February 2006. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0312b-ftnote.021"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Editor: A.Martin, Elizabeth, <hi rend="italic">A Dictionary of Law</hi>, 5th ed., 2003, p.350. </s></p></note><p n="p5.6"><s n="s1.14;p5.6">The question is whether "custom is now of limited importance as a source of law." </s><s n="s2.14;p5.6">So is it? </s><s n="s3.14;p5.6">By summarizing all the facts that been discussed above it seems that the inherent problems such as state practice and <hi rend="italic">opinio juris</hi> in custom do contribute to its slow formation in international law. </s><s n="s4.14;p5.6">However, one has to bear in mind that even treaties have its fair share of complications as evident in the Rome Statute of the International Court. </s><s n="s5.14;p5.6">It by no means imply that custom is now limited as a source of international law due to certain weaknesses in its formation. </s><s n="s6.14;p5.6">The significant role that custom plays in relation to humanitarian law is justified by the argument that it is a judicial tool for promoting efficiency. </s><s n="s7.14;p5.6">This is done by allowing judges to manipulate its vagueness and as such circumventing problematic requirements in order to produce efficiency in international law. </s><s n="s8.14;p5.6">Custom is also arguably the basis on which peremptory norms are formed notwithstanding contrary arguments. </s><s n="s9.14;p5.6">This prevents gross violations of human rights such as slavery and genocide and thus is beneficial in maintaining the protection of those rights. </s><s n="s10.14;p5.6">The emergence of 'soft law' has also to a certain extent reinforced the importance of custom. </s><s n="s11.14;p5.6">This is because there is now additional assistance in providing a substantial and more accurate basis for the formation of custom. </s><s n="s12.14;p5.6">Custom is therefore still intact, not limited in its importance and still surviving. </s><s n="s13.14;p5.6">Taking the words of Detlev F. Vagts, "[c]ustom lives." </s><ref target="BAWE_0312b-ftnote.022"/><s n="s14.14;p5.6">This is in contrast to Goldsmith and Posner's theory that lambastes the role of custom and argues that it has no real, significant role in international law with respect to relations between states.<ref target="BAWE_0312b-ftnote.023"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0312b-ftnote.022"><p n="pn1.3"><s n="s1.2;pn1.3">F.Vagts, Detlev, 'International Relations Looks at Customary International Law: A Traditionalist's Defence', <hi rend="italic">European Journal of International Law</hi> November 2004. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.3">15 (1031), p.6. </s></p><p n="pn2.3"><s n="s1.1;pn2.3"><hi rend="underlined"> </hi><seg type="URL" n="http://www.web.lexis-nexis.com/professional"/> </s></p><p n="pn3.3"><s n="s1.1;pn3.3">6 February 2006. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0312b-ftnote.023"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">See Goldsmith, Jack L. &amp; Posner, Eric A., <hi rend="italic">The Limits of International Law</hi>, 2005, Oxford University Press (<hi rend="italic">A Theory of Customary International Law)</hi> </s></p></note><p n="p6.6"><s n="s1.9;p6.6">This essay has argued on both sides of the discussion that "custom is now of limited importance as source of international law." </s><s n="s2.9;p6.6">By analysing the inherent problems within custom, namely state practice and <hi rend="italic">opinio juris</hi> and linking this argument with the notion of efficiency, it is found that it by no means imply that custom is of limited importance just because of certain weaknesses. </s><s n="s3.9;p6.6">The uncertainty and vagueness apparent in custom can arguably be 'cured' by judicial action or rather judges using custom as a judicial tool to promote efficiency. </s><s n="s4.9;p6.6">This was evidenced by the two decisions of the International Court of Justice; <hi rend="italic">Nicaragua v.</hi> </s><s n="s5.9;p6.6"><hi rend="italic">United States</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Gabcikovo-Nagymaros</hi>. </s><s n="s6.9;p6.6">The essay then goes on to briefly discuss <hi rend="italic">jus cogens</hi> as a sort of 'super-custom' and that custom provides a basis for <hi rend="italic">jus cogens</hi> in relation to humanitarian law such as slavery and genocide. </s><s n="s7.9;p6.6">It was also argued that with the emergence of 'soft law' that includes General Assembly and Security Council Resolutions there is now additional assistance to prove the formation of custom in international law. </s><s n="s8.9;p6.6">As this makes it easier to provide a more accurate basis on which custom is formed then the latter still retains its importance. </s><s n="s9.9;p6.6">The essay then concludes by summarizing the different facts discussed and, subsequently arguing that custom is not of limited importance as a source of international law in recent times despite some apparent weaknesses. </s></p></div1></body><back><div1 type="bibliography"><p>A. Martin, Elizabeth. 2003. <hi rend="italic">A Dictionary of Law</hi>. Oxford University Press.</p><p>Benvenisti, Eyal; Hirsch, Moshe. 2004. <hi rend="italic">The Impact of International Law on International Cooperation: Theoretical Perspectives</hi>. Cambridge University Press.</p><p>Cassese, Antonio. 2005. <hi rend="italic">International Law</hi>. Oxford University Press.</p><p>D'Amato, Anthony. Jan 1987. 'Trashing Customary International Law'. <hi rend="italic">The American Journal of International Law</hi>, Vol.81, No.1.</p><p><seg type="URL" n="http://links.jstor.org/sici?sici=0002-9300%28198701%2981%3A1%3C101%3ATCIL%3E2.0.CO%3B2-I"/></p><p>Goldsmith, Jack L.; Posner, Eric A. 2005. <hi rend="italic">The Limits of International Law</hi>. Oxford University Press.</p><p>Guzman, Andrew T. 2005. <hi rend="italic">Saving Customary International Law</hi> Paper 30. American Law &amp; Economics Association Annual Meetings.</p><p><seg type="URL" n="http://law.bepress.com/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1515&amp;context=alea"/></p><p>Harris, D. J. 2004. <hi rend="italic">Cases and Materials on International Law.</hi> London. Sweet &amp; Maxwell Limited.</p><p>Kunz, Josef L. October 1953. 'Nature of Customary International Law'.<hi rend="italic"> The American Journal of International Law</hi>, Vol.47, No.4.</p><p> <seg type="URL" n="http://links.jstor.org/sici?sici=0002-9300%28195310%2947%3A4%3C662%3ATNOCIL%3E2.0.CO%3B2-W"/></p><p>Kammerhofer, Jorg. June 2004. 'Uncertainty in the Formal Sources of International Law: Customary International Law and Some of Its Problems'. <hi rend="italic">European Journal of International Law</hi> 15 (523).</p><p> <seg type="URL" n="http://www.web.lexis-nexis.com/professional"/></p><p>Malanczuk, Peter. 1997. <hi rend="italic">Akehurst's Modern Introduction to International Law</hi>. Routledge London.</p><p>Shaw, Malcolm N. 2003. <hi rend="italic">International Law</hi>. Cambridge University Press.</p><p>Vagts, Detlev F. November 2004. 'International Relations Looks at Customary International Law: A Traditionalist's Defence'. <hi rend="italic">European Journal of International Law</hi> 15 (1031)</p><p> <seg type="URL" n="http://www.web.lexis-nexis.com/professional"/></p><p>Von Glahn, Gerhard. 1981. <hi rend="italic">Law among Nations: An Introduction to Public International Law</hi>. Collier Macmillan Publishers London. </p></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
