<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_0312f" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>'Competition law is a pointless tool in the hands of competition authorities if it is not backed by stringent powers of enforcement.'</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">deleted: footer: student, module and page numbers</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">3</p><p n="date">2007-01</p><p n="module title">Introduction to Competition Law</p><p n="module code">LA227</p><p n="genre family">Essay</p><p n="discipline">Law</p><p n="disciplinary group">SS</p><p n="grade">M</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">2520</p><p n="number of s-units">95</p><p n="number of p">10</p><p n="number of tables">0</p><p n="number of figures">0</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">0</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">0</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">26.5</p><p n="average s-units per p">9.5</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">f</p><p n="year of birth">1985</p><p n="first language">English</p><p n="education">UK1.5</p><p n="course">LLB</p><p n="student ID">0312</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><docTitle><titlePart rend="underlined">'Competition law is a pointless tool in the hands of competition authorities if it is not backed by stringent powers of enforcement.'</titlePart></docTitle></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="section"><p n="p1.10"><s n="s1.8;p1.10">Promoting competition is ultimately the most important responsibility delegated to competition authorities. </s><s n="s2.8;p1.10">But how exactly is this achieved? </s><s n="s3.8;p1.10">Competition authorities are equipped with tools to combat anti-competitive practices and behaviour; one of these tools is the powers of enforcement. </s><s n="s4.8;p1.10">For the purpose of this essay the powers of enforcement are to encompass many different aspects such as the powers of investigation, powers to impose penalties and powers to order the termination of infringements. </s><s n="s5.8;p1.10">However competition authorities cannot apply competition law effectively if the law itself is not bolstered by strict and precise enforcement powers. </s><s n="s6.8;p1.10">Therefore this essay will seek to explore how enforcement powers held by the United Kingdom national competition authority, the Office of Fair Trading (OFT), have developed since the implementation of the Competition Act 1998, Regulation 1/2003/EC and Enterprise Act 2002. </s><s n="s7.8;p1.10">In addition an analysis of the interrelationship between the European Commission's enforcement powers and Regulation 1/2003/EC will be conducted. </s><s n="s8.8;p1.10">Competition law will be an effective mechanism to promote competition if it is backed by stringent powers of enforcement, and provided that competition authorities are confident enough to use them. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="bold">Office of Fair Trading</hi> :</head><p n="p2.10"><s n="s1.3;p2.10">According to the OFT's website its enforcement role is to "uproot and deter all forms of anti-competitive behaviour, including cartels and the abuse of market power." </s><ref target="BAWE_0312f-ftnote.001"/><s n="s2.3;p2.10">This has certainly been made easier with the implementation of Regulation 1/2003/EC as the European competition rules, namely Articles 81 and 82 can now be directly enforced by the OFT. However much of the OFT's current enforcement powers are derived from the Competition Act 1998 which reflect those provisions embodied in the EC competition rules. </s><s n="s3.3;p2.10">This is in addition to newer and more extensive powers of enforcement acquired through the Enterprise Act 2002 and Regulation 1/2003/EC. These provisions have not only served to strengthen the enforcement powers and role of the OFT in the United Kingdom; they have brought it more into line with those powers held by the European Commission. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0312f-ftnote.001"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1"><seg type="URL" n="http://www.oft.gov.uk/About/Aims+and+objectives/default.htm"/> (Accessed January 8th 2007). </s></p></note><div2><head rend="bold">(a) Competition Act 1998 </head><p n="p3.10"><s n="s1.9;p3.10">Indeed one commentator has stated that "the primary purpose of the [1998] Act may not be to fine-tune the substantive rules of competition law but to provide effective means of taking action against those breaches of competition law which have in the past escaped enforcement action because of a lack of evidence and enforcement powers available to the competition authorities." </s><ref target="BAWE_0312f-ftnote.002"/><s n="s2.9;p3.10">Thus it is clear that the quest to equip the OFT with more effective and extensive enforcement powers in the sphere of competition law had begun as far back as a decade ago. </s><s n="s3.9;p3.10">One of the main enforcement powers established through the Competition Act 1998 was the power to enter business premises without or under a warrant.<ref target="BAWE_0312f-ftnote.003"/> This is of course a considerable achievement in the OFT's position of investigating any potential breaches of competition law since it now possesses a more effective enforcement power. </s><s n="s4.9;p3.10">These new powers, as explained by Furse, have also been acknowledged "in the IIB case [where] the CAT noted that the Act has endowed 'the [OFT], in the public interest, with wide ranging and draconian powers..." </s><ref target="BAWE_0312f-ftnote.004"/><s n="s5.9;p3.10">But the enforcement problem still remains, albeit in a different form, if the OFT is reluctant to exercise its new powers no matter how stringent they may be. </s><s n="s6.9;p3.10">Indeed the OFT now holds increased powers of enforcement in its role as the U.K. national competition authority; it has been strengthened by the fact that "the tripartite scheme is effectively extinct [and] [t]he Secretary of State has no real enforcement role under the CA 1998..." </s><ref target="BAWE_0312f-ftnote.005"/><s n="s7.9;p3.10">Thus the eventual depoliticisation of the enforcement framework not only provides the OFT with greater enforcement powers. </s><s n="s8.9;p3.10">But establishes a sense of transparency and certainty in its realisation. </s><s n="s9.9;p3.10">However as aforementioned the question that should be then posed is whether the OFT is capable of enforcing its extensive and valuable enforcement powers? </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0312f-ftnote.002"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Rodger, Barry J. and MacCulloch, Angus, eds., (2000), <hi rend="italic">The UK Competition Act: A New Era for UK Competition Law</hi>, Oxford: Hart Publishing Ltd, p. 76. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0312f-ftnote.003"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ss.27-28, Competition Act 1998 in Middleton, Kirsty, ed., (2005), <hi rend="italic">Blackstone's Statutes: UK &amp; EC Competition Documents,</hi> 4th ed., Oxford; New York: Oxford University Press, pp.10-11. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0312f-ftnote.004"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Furse, Mark, (2006), <hi rend="italic">Competition Law of the EC and UK</hi>, 5th ed., Oxford: Oxford University Press, p.102. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0312f-ftnote.005"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Middleton, Kirsty, Rodger, Barry J. and MacCulloch, Angus, (2003), <hi rend="italic">Cases and Materials on UK &amp; EC Competition Law</hi>, Oxford: Oxford University Press, p.20. </s></p></note></div2><div2><head rend="bold">Enterprise Act 2002</head><p n="p4.10"><s n="s1.14;p4.10">The Enterprise Act 2002 conferred upon the OFT two important enforcement powers. </s><s n="s2.14;p4.10">They are criminal penalties for individual members guilty of cartel offences<ref target="BAWE_0312f-ftnote.006"/> and directors' disqualification.<ref target="BAWE_0312f-ftnote.007"/> These sanctions are by far the harshest penalties that can be imposed upon individuals who engage in anti-competitive behaviour and practices. </s><s n="s3.14;p4.10">This will act as a deterrent in order to prevent the distortion of competition by certain undertakings or rather individuals. </s><s n="s4.14;p4.10">However the U.K. has yet to impose a criminal penalty on individuals involved in a cartel arrangement although there was an opportunity in the Argos and Littlewoods price-fixing arrangement. </s><s n="s5.14;p4.10">Instead in March 2006 Ireland became the first country in the European jurisdiction "to obtain a criminal conviction after a jury trial for a competition offence" involving the home heating oil industry.<ref target="BAWE_0312f-ftnote.008"/> This conviction is a reflection of both the trials and tribulations in competition law enforcement. </s><s n="s6.14;p4.10">A triumph for the Irish Competition Authority in obtaining a criminal conviction under the Competition (Amendment) </s><s n="s7.14;p4.10">Act of 1996 but a disappointment for the OFT who has yet to exercise its new enforcement powers under the Enterprise Act 2002 to impose criminal penalties. </s><s n="s8.14;p4.10">Thus the underlying root problem is not that the OFT possesses a lack of stringent enforcement powers in order to exercise competition law. </s><s n="s9.14;p4.10">But it is a lack of will. </s><s n="s10.14;p4.10">It was even illustrated by an author in The Sunday Telegraph that "the National Audit Office contends that this watchdog is slow, disorganized and poorly trained - more like a wheezing labrador than a whippet." </s><ref target="BAWE_0312f-ftnote.009"/><s n="s11.14;p4.10">However the OFT seems to be playing a more active enforcement role with respect to civil penalties. </s><s n="s12.14;p4.10">The OFT fined Argos and Littlewoods £22.65 million for being a part of a price-fixing arrangement but Hasbro was granted immunity under the leniency programme.<ref target="BAWE_0312f-ftnote.010"/> Therefore the OFT's inactivity in imposing criminal penalties may be tolerated since the deterrent effect may well be achieved through the imposition of a hefty fine. </s><s n="s13.14;p4.10">In addition the OFT can deter prolonged anti-competitive practices (cartels) through their new enforcement weapon, 'no-action letters' that provide immunity from prosecution for those individuals who satisfy certain criteria. </s><s n="s14.14;p4.10">As such competition law is still a valuable tool for competition authorities such as the OFT who enjoys its powers of enforcement through various avenues. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0312f-ftnote.006"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Op.cit. note 3, p.191. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0312f-ftnote.007"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid. pp.196-197. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0312f-ftnote.008"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">U.S Department of Justice, <hi rend="italic">Criminal Enforcement of Antitrust Laws: The U.S. Model</hi>. (online) </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">URL: <seg type="URL" n="http://www.usdoj.gov/atr/public/speeches/218336.htm"/> (Accessed 8th January 2007). </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0312f-ftnote.009"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.3;pn1.1">Watts, Robert, (October 15, 2006), Is the consumer watchdog barking up the wrong tree? </s><s n="s2.3;pn1.1"><hi rend="italic">The Sunday Telegraph</hi>, p.7. </s><s n="s3.3;pn1.1">(Accessed 8th January 2007). </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0312f-ftnote.010"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Agreements between Hasbro U.K. Ltd, Argos Ltd and Littlewoods Ltd. fixing the price of Hasbro toys and games (21 November 2003) Case CP/0480-01 (online) URL: <seg type="URL" n="http://www.oft.gov.uk/NR/rdonlyres/FCDE5CA6-812E-4215-A707-C7803FF57383/0/hasbro3.pdf"/> (Accessed 8th January 2007). </s></p></note></div2><div2><head rend="bold">Regulation 1/2003/EC </head><p n="p5.10"><s n="s1.14;p5.10">One of the key changes in relation to the OFT's enforcement powers is its newly acquired power to decide directly on an Article 81(3)<ref target="BAWE_0312f-ftnote.011"/> exemption without the need to notify the European Commission. </s><s n="s2.14;p5.10">This was a result of decentralisation and the need to create a higher degree of efficiency and clarity; rulings by the Commission usually took a long time and were a hindrance to prompt utilization of enforcement powers. </s><s n="s3.14;p5.10">As a result of this modernization change the OFT can now directly enforce Community rules more effectively, without the need to wait for a Commission ruling and the burden of consuming huge resources. </s><s n="s4.14;p5.10">"The direct applicability of Art 81(3) EC means that many of the barriers to the enforcement of Community competition law by nationally-based authorities have been removed..." </s><ref target="BAWE_0312f-ftnote.012"/><s n="s5.14;p5.10">Hence the enforcement powers of the OFT have greatly increased through this positive change and this is clearly highlighted through recent cases that have been rather expeditious. </s><s n="s6.14;p5.10">However as one commentator has elucidated, "direct enforcement without some form of procedural harmonization may lead to significant divergences in the protection of Community law rights." </s><ref target="BAWE_0312f-ftnote.013"/><s n="s7.14;p5.10">This implies that enforcement powers obtained by competition authorities may not necessarily be advantageous, especially if this results in jurisdictional inconsistencies when applying competition law in the Community. </s><s n="s8.14;p5.10">Furthermore Kon and Iley assert that the various national competition authorities will implement competition rules differently because of their diverse experiences, legal institutions and available resources to name a few. </s><s n="s9.14;p5.10">However these worries may actually be unfounded since States in the European community are issued with guidelines through the form of EC Commission Notices. </s><s n="s10.14;p5.10">Guidelines range from topics such as the calculation of turnover to definition of the relevant market. </s><s n="s11.14;p5.10">Indeed even if "the application of the law in the proposed decentralized system might present a potential source of inconsistency, it is incapable of producing such magnitude to interfere with the effective functioning of the overall system." </s><ref target="BAWE_0312f-ftnote.014"/><s n="s12.14;p5.10">The introduction of Regulation 1/2003 has conferred upon national competition authorities such as the OFT a greater latitude for enforcing community rules through the various enforcement powers. </s><s n="s13.14;p5.10">These include powers to makes decisions requiring the termination of an infringement<ref target="BAWE_0312f-ftnote.015"/>, ordering interim measures<ref target="BAWE_0312f-ftnote.016"/>, accepting commitments<ref target="BAWE_0312f-ftnote.017"/> and imposing penalties<ref target="BAWE_0312f-ftnote.018"/>. </s><s n="s14.14;p5.10">It has certainly strengthened the OFT's pre-existing powers of enforcement derived from the Competition Act 1998 and Enterprise Act 2002. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0312f-ftnote.011"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Op.cit. note 3, p.255. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0312f-ftnote.012"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Rodger, Barry J. and MacCulloch, Angus, (2004), <hi rend="italic">Competition Law and Policy in the EC and UK</hi>, 3rd ed., London: Cavendish Publishing Ltd., p.39. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0312f-ftnote.013"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Kon, Stephen and Iley, Rachel, (2004), EC Modernisation: Aspects of Application by National Courts and NCAs and the Need to Ensure Consistency and Legal Certainty, <hi rend="italic">Competition Law Insight</hi> 14(22), p.2. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0312f-ftnote.014"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Pijetlovic, Katarina, (2004), Reform of EC Antitrust Enforcement: Criticism of the New System is Highly Exaggerated, <hi rend="italic">European Competition Law Review</hi> 25(6):356-369. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0312f-ftnote.015"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Article 7, Council Regulation 1/2003. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">Op.cit. note 3. pp.268-269. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0312f-ftnote.016"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Article 8, Council Regulation 1/2003. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">Ibid. p.269. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0312f-ftnote.017"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Article 9, Council Regulation 1/2003. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">Ibid.p.269. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0312f-ftnote.018"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Chapter VI Penalties, Council Regulation 1/2003. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">Ibid. p.275. </s></p></note></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="bold">Interrelationship between the European Commission and Regulation 1/2003</hi> :</head><p n="p6.10"><s n="s1.7;p6.10">The Commission is tasked with the responsibility of overseeing the activities of all national competition authorities in the European Community, and since Regulation 1/2003 its role has been reduced to that of supervisory level. </s><s n="s2.7;p6.10">As aforementioned national competition authorities can now directly enforce community rules and this applies to individual exemptions under Article 81(3) too. </s><s n="s3.7;p6.10">Thus the Commission no longer holds a monopoly over such an exemption and this can be considered as a reduction in their enforcement armoury. </s><s n="s4.7;p6.10">But essentially "[t]he Commission, alongside the NCAs, has wide powers to carry out investigations into possible infringements of the competition rules and it also has the power to impose fines or, in some cases, a structural remedy." </s><ref target="BAWE_0312f-ftnote.019"/><s n="s5.7;p6.10">Most commentators agree that the Commission's enforcement powers have been increased as a result of Regulation 1/2003. </s><s n="s6.7;p6.10">But the extent to which it has been increased is still debatable. </s><s n="s7.7;p6.10">The main aspects of enhanced enforcement powers are the ability to impose structural remedies and penalties and the powers of investigation. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0312f-ftnote.019"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Rodger, Barry J. and MacCulloch, Angus, (2004), <hi rend="italic">Competition Law and Policy in the EC and UK</hi>, 3rd ed., London: Cavendish Publishing Ltd., p.35. </s></p></note><div2><head rend="bold">Powers of Investigation</head><p n="p7.10"><s n="s1.14;p7.10">These powers are encapsulated within Articles 17 to 22 of Regulation 1/2003<ref target="BAWE_0312f-ftnote.020"/>. </s><s n="s2.14;p7.10">They range from requests for information, to oral statements, to powers of inspection in business premises and other locations. </s><s n="s3.14;p7.10">These enforcement powers are absolutely necessary for the Commission who have to frequently deal with suspected cartel dealings and price-fixing schemes that involve a serious infringement of competition law. </s><s n="s4.14;p7.10">The Commission has the power to impose penalties on undertakings that refuse to supply information or supplies information that is incorrect or misleading. </s><s n="s5.14;p7.10">This is an important power because 'dawn raids' can essentially be carried out with as little interruption and undue interference as possible. </s><s n="s6.14;p7.10">This in turn ensures that competition law is effectively and efficiently utilised to promote competition in the markets. </s><s n="s7.14;p7.10">In addition to the Commission's wide-ranging powers is "[t]he fact that an undertaking [which] considers that the Commission has no grounds for action under Article 81 does not entitle it to resist a request for information." </s><ref target="BAWE_0312f-ftnote.021"/><s n="s8.14;p7.10">Therefore this highlights the disparity between the undertakings and the Commission while an investigation is being carried out. </s><s n="s9.14;p7.10">It is apparent that the Commission is equipped with vast enforcement powers while the undertaking has no real choice but to adhere to their requests. </s><s n="s10.14;p7.10">This is exactly what the Commission needs to promote competition - 'razor sharp teeth' to enforce competition law and thereby to halt anti-competitive practices. </s><s n="s11.14;p7.10">As such this 'teeth' will emerge in the form of stringent powers of enforcement. </s><s n="s12.14;p7.10">The Commission is certainly being endowed with stronger enforcement powers as can be clearly seen from its powers to obtain oral statements under Article 19<ref target="BAWE_0312f-ftnote.022"/>. </s><s n="s13.14;p7.10">This has been described by Whish as being a "novel provision", implying that it is a new, interesting and different kind of provision. </s><s n="s14.14;p7.10">However this still begs the question of its efficacy. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0312f-ftnote.020"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Op.cit. note 3, pp.272-273. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0312f-ftnote.021"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Whish, Richard, (2003), <hi rend="italic">Competition Law</hi>, 5th ed., London: Butterworths, p.261. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0312f-ftnote.022"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Op.cit. note 3, p.273. </s></p></note></div2><div2><head rend="bold">Commission Decisions - Structural Remedies</head><p n="p8.10"><s n="s1.8;p8.10">These can be found at Articles 7 to 10 of Regulation 1/2003<ref target="BAWE_0312f-ftnote.023"/> and are among many of the important enforcement powers held by the Commission. </s><s n="s2.8;p8.10">When the Commission finds an infringement of competition law, namely Article 81 or Article 82, it may require the undertakings to end such infringements. </s><s n="s3.8;p8.10">The commission's powers to request termination of such infringements are further strengthened by their ability to impose behavioural or structural remedies. </s><s n="s4.8;p8.10">Although behavioural remedies such as fines are commonly imposed on undertakings who are obstinate, structural remedies are a more contentious issue and "the inclusion of this possibility in the Modernisation Regulation was controversial." </s><ref target="BAWE_0312f-ftnote.024"/><s n="s5.8;p8.10">It is certainly true that the Commission may use structural remedies in place of behavioural ones but this is subject to a very strict test. </s><s n="s6.8;p8.10">The latter encompasses conditions of effectiveness, necessity and proportionality. </s><s n="s7.8;p8.10">One commentator argues that "the effectiveness, necessity, and proportionality of a structural remedy function as a straitjacket and will rarely allow the adoption of structural remedies." </s><ref target="BAWE_0312f-ftnote.025"/><s n="s8.8;p8.10">Therefore although the Commission is theoretically endowed with this particular remedy it essentially cannot use it in reality because of the many constraints. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0312f-ftnote.023"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid. pp.268-269. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0312f-ftnote.024"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Op.cit. note 21, p.255. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0312f-ftnote.025"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Tajana, Alessandro, (December 2005), <hi rend="italic">Tilec Discussion Paper: Structural Remedies and Abuse of Dominant Position</hi>, (online) URL: <seg type="URL" n="http://www.tilburguniversity.nl/tilec/publications/discussionpapers/2005-033.pdf"/> (Accessed 10th January 2007). </s></p></note></div2><div2><head rend="bold">Penalties</head><p n="p9.10"><s n="s1.13;p9.10">The power to impose penalties are the most useful and usual forms of enforcement powers because of their valuable deterrent effect. </s><s n="s2.13;p9.10">Articles 23 to 24 in Regulation 1/2003 are concerned entirely with penalties; the provisions provide specific percentage values that have to be adhered to when calculating various fines. </s><s n="s3.13;p9.10">This provides the Commission with a wide discretion to calculate and adjust the values; there is no particular maximum amount threshold applicable. </s><s n="s4.13;p9.10">The calculation is essentially a percentage of the undertaking's total turnover subject to the considerations of gravity and duration of infringement. </s><s n="s5.13;p9.10">It can be clearly seen from case law that the Commission wields substantial powers to fine and has been active in using it. </s><s n="s6.13;p9.10">For instance in the <hi rend="italic">Vitamins</hi> cartel case a fine of €462 million was imposed and remains the largest fine imposed on a single undertaking in a cartel case<ref target="BAWE_0312f-ftnote.026"/>. </s><s n="s7.13;p9.10">The Commission also has powers to impose periodic penalties on undertakings that supply inaccurate or misleading information. </s><s n="s8.13;p9.10">This is important to ensure full co-operation and a successful investigation process which in turn leads to competition law being better applied. </s><s n="s9.13;p9.10">However it is regrettable that the Commission has yet to establish a system for criminal penalties in relation to cartel activities considering that some of its Member States have adopted such penalties. </s><s n="s10.13;p9.10">This would greatly enhance the existing wide range of enforcement powers available to the Commission. </s><s n="s11.13;p9.10">But it has been expressed by Rodger and MacCulloch that "...it seems highly unlikely that there would be the political will to bring criminal law within the Community competition system." </s><ref target="BAWE_0312f-ftnote.027"/><s n="s12.13;p9.10">However at least it can be seen that the current enforcement powers held by the Commission functions well in promoting competition. </s><s n="s13.13;p9.10">As long as the Commission continues to exercise its powers fearlessly but legitimately, the potential drawbacks of not possessing criminal penalties may not be as serious as deduced initially. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0312f-ftnote.026"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Commission Press Release, Memo/06/451 (29 November 2006) (online) URL: <seg type="URL" n="http://europa.eu/rapid/pressReleasesAction.do?reference=MEMO/06/451&amp;format=HTML&amp;aged=0&amp;language=EN&amp;guiLanguage=en"/> (Accessed 10th January 2007). </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0312f-ftnote.027"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Op.cit. note 12, p.52. </s></p></note><p n="p10.10"><s n="s1.5;p10.10">In conclusion, competition authorities such as the Office of Fair Trading and European Commission are furnished with strict, precise and wide-ranging enforcement powers in order to better apply competition law. </s><s n="s2.5;p10.10">This is clearly highlighted by the implementation of Regulation 1/2003/EC; it confers upon these authorities enhanced enforcement powers in the areas of investigation and penalties. </s><s n="s3.5;p10.10">This is necessary since competition law cannot be effectively applied without the 'razor sharp teeth' of enforcement powers. </s><s n="s4.5;p10.10">Nevertheless it is inevitable that there will always be deficiencies and inaccuracies. </s><s n="s5.5;p10.10">Ergo it is up to competition authorities to make the most of the existing powers of enforcement they control and to use them boldly in all circumstances. </s></p></div2></div1></body><back><div1 type="bibliography"><head><hi rend="bold">Bibliography</hi> :</head><p>Calvani, Terry. (2003). Devolution and Convergence in Competition Enforcement. <hi rend="italic">European Competition Law Review</hi> 24(9): 415-423. </p><p>Commission Press Release, IP/01/1625 (21 November 2001) (online) URL: <seg type="URL" n="http://europa.eu/rapid/pressReleasesAction.do?reference=IP/01/1625&amp;format=HTML&amp;aged=0&amp;language=EN&amp;guiLanguage=en"/> (Accessed 10th January 2007)</p><p> Commission Press Release, Memo/06/451 (29 November 2006) (online) URL: <seg type="URL" n="http://europa.eu/rapid/pressReleasesAction.do?reference=MEMO/06/451&amp;format=HTML&amp;aged=0&amp;language=EN&amp;guiLanguage=en"/> (Accessed 10<hi rend="sup">th</hi> January 2007).</p><p>Competition Law Monitor. (2003). European Commission's Enforcement Powers: Impact of Council Regulation 1/2003/EC. <hi rend="italic">Competition Law Monitor</hi> 3.2(9).</p><p>Competition Law Monitor. (2001). Direct Enforcement of EC Competition Law. <hi rend="italic">Competition Law Monitor</hi> 1.5(9).</p><p>Ehlermann, Claus-Dieter and Atanasiu, Isabela. (2004). <hi rend="italic">European Competition Law Annual 2002: Constructing the EU Network of Competition Authorities.</hi> Oxford: Hart Publishing Ltd. </p><p>Furse, Mark. (2006). <hi rend="italic">Competition Law of the EC and UK</hi>. 5<hi rend="sup">th</hi> ed. Oxford: Oxford University Press. </p><p>Ginsburg, Douglas H. (2005). Comparing Antitrust Enforcement in the United States and Europe. <hi rend="italic">Journal of Competition Law and Economics</hi> 1(3):427-439. </p><p>Jones, Alison and Sufrin, Brenda. (2004). <hi rend="italic">EC Competition Law: Text, Cases, and Materials.</hi> 2<hi rend="sup">nd</hi> ed. Oxford: Oxford University Press.</p><p>Kon, Stephen and Iley, Rachel. (2004). EC Modernisation: Aspects of Application by National Courts and NCAs and the Need to Ensure Consistency and Legal Certainty. <hi rend="italic">Competiton Law Insight</hi> 14(22).</p><p>Lane, Robert. (2001). <hi rend="italic">EC Competition Law</hi>. Harlow: Longman. </p><p>Middleton, Kirsty. ed. (2005). <hi rend="italic">Blackstone's Statutes: UK &amp; EC Competition Documents</hi>. 4<hi rend="sup">th</hi> ed. Oxford; New York: Oxford University Press. </p><p>Middleton, Kirsty, Rodger, Barry J. and MacCulloch, Angus. (2003). <hi rend="italic">Cases and Materials on UK and EC Competition Law</hi>. Oxford: Oxford University Press. </p><p>Parisi, John J. (1999). Enforcement Co-operation among Antitrust Authorities. <hi rend="italic">European Competition Law Review</hi>, 20(3): 133-142. </p><p>Pijetlovic, Katarina. (2004). Reform of EC Antitrust Enforcement: Criticism of the New System is Highly Exaggerated. <hi rend="italic">European Competition Law Review</hi> 25(6):356-369.</p><p>Rodger, Barry J. and MacCulloch, Angus. (2004). <hi rend="italic">Competition Law and Policy in the EC and UK</hi>. 3<hi rend="sup">rd</hi> ed. London: Cavendish Publishing Ltd. </p><p>Rodger, Barry J. and MacCulloch, Angus. eds. (2000). <hi rend="italic">The UK Competition Act: A New Era for UK Competition Law</hi>. Oxford: Hart Publishing Ltd. </p><p>Rosenberg, David and Sullivan, James P. (2006). Coordinating Private Class Action and Public Agency Enforcement of Antitrust Law. <hi rend="italic">Journal of Competition Law and Economics</hi> 2(2): 159-187. </p><p>Tajana, Alessandro, (December 2005), <hi rend="italic">Tilec Discussion Paper: Structural Remedies and Abuse of Dominant Position</hi>, (online) URL: <seg type="URL" n="http://www.tilburguniversity.nl/tilec/publications/discussionpapers/2005-033.pdf"/> (Accessed 10th January 2007). </p><p>U.S. Department of Justice, <hi rend="italic">Criminal Enforcement of Antitrust Laws: The U.S. Model</hi>. (online) URL: <seg type="URL" n="http://www.usdoj.gov/atr/public/speeches/218336.htm"/> (Accessed 8th January 2007).</p><p>Watts, Robert, (October 15, 2006), Is the consumer watchdog barking up the wrong tree? <hi rend="italic">The Sunday Telegraph</hi>, p.7. (Accessed 8<hi rend="sup">th</hi> January 2007).</p><p>Whish, Richard. (2003). <hi rend="italic">Competition Law</hi>. 5<hi rend="sup">th</hi> ed. London: Butterworths. </p></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
