<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_0315a" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Problem Question</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">deleted: header: assignment title, module name; footer: student and page numbers, date</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">2</p><p n="date">2005-03</p><p n="module title">General Principles of Constitutional &amp; Administrative Law</p><p n="module code">LA201</p><p n="genre family">Problem question</p><p n="discipline">Law</p><p n="disciplinary group">SS</p><p n="grade">D</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">2445</p><p n="number of s-units">109</p><p n="number of p">14</p><p n="number of tables">0</p><p n="number of figures">0</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">0</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">0</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">22.4</p><p n="average s-units per p">7.8</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">f</p><p n="year of birth">1986</p><p n="first language">English</p><p n="education">UKA</p><p n="course">LLB</p><p n="student ID">0315</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><docTitle><titlePart rend="bold">Problem Question</titlePart></docTitle></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="section"><head rend="italic">Introduction</head><p n="p1.14"><s n="s1.6;p1.14">These scenarios raise some contentious issues regarding the availability and utility of judicial review. </s><s n="s2.6;p1.14">The central concepts in all three cases are the <hi rend="italic">Wednesbury</hi> test for reasonableness and natural justice, most notably the issues of bias and procedural fairness. </s><s n="s3.6;p1.14">Broadly speaking, a claim for judicial review can be founded on illegality, irrationality or procedural impropriety, as expounded in the <hi rend="italic">GCHQ</hi> case. </s><s n="s4.6;p1.14">These principles are not mutually exclusive and the reasonableness umbrella further incorporates an assessment of whether all relevant considerations were taken into account and irrelevant factors were excluded. </s><s n="s5.6;p1.14">Judicial review has grown beyond <hi rend="italic">Wednesbury</hi> to incorporate the pursuit of improper purposes, which will prove instrumental to the claim of student Z. Student X's claim that the policy is irrational clearly demonstrates the problems of such rules that "bypass the legislature and foreclose the possibility of parliamentary scrutiny"<ref target="BAWE_0315a-ftnote.001"/>. </s><s n="s6.6;p1.14">It is clear in this case that the panel possess a wide discretionary power, which opens the door to the possibility of them acting <hi rend="italic">ultra vires</hi>. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0315a-ftnote.001"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">P. Craig - "Administrative Law", page 400. </s></p></note><p n="p2.14"><s n="s1.5;p2.14">It will be interesting to consider how the <hi rend="italic">Wednesbury</hi> test and the rules of procedural fairness stand up faced with such challenges. </s><s n="s2.5;p2.14">Many commentators contend that <hi rend="italic">Wednesbury</hi> is becoming obsolete and since "the rules of natural justice are not engraved on tablets of stone"<ref target="BAWE_0315a-ftnote.002"/>, it may be possible for the students to invoke emerging concepts such as fairness or proportionality. </s><s n="s3.5;p2.14">Nonetheless, the reviewing court has only a "supervisory jurisdiction"<ref target="BAWE_0315a-ftnote.003"/> and may not review the merits of each case<ref target="BAWE_0315a-ftnote.004"/>. </s><s n="s4.5;p2.14">It is imperative that the court affords the panel the margin of appreciation it deserves. </s><s n="s5.5;p2.14">If not, the reviewing court risks undermining the legitimacy of the disciplinary process. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0315a-ftnote.002"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Lord Irvine of Lairg - "Judges and Decision-Makers: the Theory and Practice of Wednesbury Review" (1996) PL 59. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0315a-ftnote.003"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">P. Cane - "Administrative Law", page 29. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0315a-ftnote.004"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1"><hi rend="italic">Chief Constable of North Wales v Evans</hi> [1982] 1 WLR 1155, in P. Cane - "Administrative Law", page 149. </s></p></note></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="italic">Standing</head><p n="p3.14"><s n="s1.4;p3.14">The Judicial Review Procedure requires applicants to have standing to bring their case. </s><s n="s2.4;p3.14">The test is one of "sufficient interest"<ref target="BAWE_0315a-ftnote.005"/>, and X, Y and Z should have no problems as they are all individually affected by the panel's decisions. </s><s n="s3.4;p3.14">Under the ECHR<ref target="BAWE_0315a-ftnote.006"/>, they all pass the narrower "victim"<ref target="BAWE_0315a-ftnote.007"/> test, which will be necessary if any of them choose to frame their case in terms of fundamental rights. </s><s n="s4.4;p3.14">A school is clearly a public body exercising a public function, so this procedural hurdle can be easily overcome. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0315a-ftnote.005"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">S 31 (1) Supreme Court Act 1981. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0315a-ftnote.006"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">European Convention on Human Rights. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0315a-ftnote.007"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Article 36.2 ECHR. </s></p></note></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="italic">Student X: Relevant Considerations</head><p n="p4.14"><s n="s1.12;p4.14">X can bring a case on the basis of the panel's failure to consider the medical report, under the broad ground of procedural fairness and error of fact. </s><s n="s2.12;p4.14">As Lord Reid said, "anyone who has to exercise a statutory discretion must not shut his ears to an application"<ref target="BAWE_0315a-ftnote.008"/>. </s><s n="s3.12;p4.14">Natural justice requires that applicants should have the right to a reasoned decision taking account of all relevant considerations<ref target="BAWE_0315a-ftnote.009"/>. </s><s n="s4.12;p4.14">The concept of natural justice can be problematic, but Craig helpfully defines it as "a manifestation of fairness"<ref target="BAWE_0315a-ftnote.010"/>. </s><s n="s5.12;p4.14">Fairness requires the court "to engage in a difficult balancing operation"<ref target="BAWE_0315a-ftnote.011"/> of the individual interest at stake, the benefits from the additional procedural safeguard and the administrative costs of this. </s><s n="s6.12;p4.14">Here, there is visible evidence of failure to consider a very relevant report, which results in a denial of justice via this error of fact. </s><s n="s7.12;p4.14">The medical evidence has the potential to discredit the second positive test. </s><s n="s8.12;p4.14">One can surmise that the cost will be reasonable, especially since X has provided the report himself. </s><s n="s9.12;p4.14">The panel may argue that the court is interfering in their discretion but it is important to remember that the "discretion of a statutory body is never unfettered"<ref target="BAWE_0315a-ftnote.012"/>. </s><s n="s10.12;p4.14">This concept of fairness may include requirements beyond the traditional ambit of natural justice, for example a duty to act on evidence<ref target="BAWE_0315a-ftnote.013"/>, such as a medical report. </s><s n="s11.12;p4.14">The court must allow for a degree of deference regarding the expertise of the decision-maker. </s><s n="s12.12;p4.14">However, in <hi rend="italic">Tesco</hi>, it was held that the court should decide what constitutes a relevant consideration, leaving the decision-maker to attribute to it "such weight as he thinks fit"<ref target="BAWE_0315a-ftnote.014"/>. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0315a-ftnote.008"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Lord Reid in <hi rend="italic">British Oxygen v Board of Trade</hi> [1971] AC 610, quoted in C. Hilson - "Judicial Review, Policies and the Fettering of Discretion" (2002) PL 111, page 116. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0315a-ftnote.009"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">P. Cane - "Administrative Law". </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0315a-ftnote.010"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">P. Craig - "Administrative Law", page 415. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0315a-ftnote.011"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">P. Craig - "Administrative Law", page 416. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0315a-ftnote.012"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Lord Denning in <hi rend="italic">Breen v Amalgamated Engineering Union</hi> [1971] 2 QB 175 at 190, quoted in Wade &amp; Forsyth - "Administrative Law", page 358. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0315a-ftnote.013"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1"><hi rend="italic">R v Deputy Industrial Inquiries Commissioner ex parte Moore</hi> [1965] 1 QB 456, referenced in Allen &amp; Thompson - "Cases and Materials on Constitutional and Administrative Law", page 597. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0315a-ftnote.014"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Quoted in Lord Irvine of Lairg - "Judges and Decision-Makers: the Theory and Practice of Wednesbury Review" (1996) PL 59, page 69. </s></p></note></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="italic">A Wednesbury irrational policy? </head><p n="p5.14"><s n="s1.9;p5.14">The next stage of the court's task is to consider the policy itself. </s><s n="s2.9;p5.14">The test in <hi rend="italic">Wednesbury</hi> is that a decision is "so unreasonable that no other reasonable decision-maker could have reached it"<ref target="BAWE_0315a-ftnote.015"/>. </s><s n="s3.9;p5.14">This is clearly "an onerous standard of review"<ref target="BAWE_0315a-ftnote.016"/>, but Wade suggests that in practice, courts "lower the threshold to fit their more exacting ideas of administrative good behaviour"<ref target="BAWE_0315a-ftnote.017"/>. </s><s n="s4.9;p5.14">Irrationality is linked to abuse of power and captures decisions that are "so unreasonable as to be verging on absurdity". </s><s n="s5.9;p5.14">A commonly cited example is banning red-headed teachers, which unfortunately for X, is a far cry from his complaint relating to his own wrongful act. </s><s n="s6.9;p5.14">The policy at issue here is a general rule together with an automatic punishment on a second offence. </s><s n="s7.9;p5.14">The general rule that drugs are banned cannot viably be challenged and the existence of such a rule actually means that "like cases are more likely to be treated alike"<ref target="BAWE_0315a-ftnote.018"/>. </s><s n="s8.9;p5.14">However, the sanction of automatic expulsion constitutes a blanket policy, against which case law has taken a hard line. </s><s n="s9.9;p5.14">In <hi rend="italic">Osman</hi>, it was held that a blanket policy "constituted an unjustifiable restriction of the applicant's right to a determination on the individual merits of their claim"<ref target="BAWE_0315a-ftnote.019"/>. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0315a-ftnote.015"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Per Lord Greene. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0315a-ftnote.016"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Lord Irvine of Lairg - "Judges and Decision-Makers: the Theory and Practice of Wednesbury Review" (1996) PL 59, page 63. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0315a-ftnote.017"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Wade &amp; Forsyth - "Administrative Law", page 358, page 364. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0315a-ftnote.018"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">C. Hilson - "Judicial Review, Policies and the Fettering of Discretion" (2002) PL 111. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0315a-ftnote.019"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Quoted in C. Hilson - "Judicial Review, Policies and the Fettering of Discretion" (2002) PL 111, page 126. </s></p></note><p n="p6.14"><s n="s1.6;p6.14">However, "the court may not decide either on the validity of the desirability of legislation". </s><s n="s2.6;p6.14">Parliamentary sovereignty must be retained, which for Hart is the "ultimate rule of recognition"<ref target="BAWE_0315a-ftnote.020"/>. </s><s n="s3.6;p6.14">However, the court is entitled the procedure unreasonable, as it "assumes that Parliament cannot have intended to authorise unreasonable action"<ref target="BAWE_0315a-ftnote.021"/>. </s><s n="s4.6;p6.14">It is important to look at Parliament's intention regarding the delegated legislation, as emphasised in <hi rend="italic">Padfield.</hi> </s><s n="s5.6;p6.14">The policy is to prevent drug abuse in schools, a perfectly legitimate aim given that the use of cannabis is illegal. </s><s n="s6.6;p6.14">Nevertheless, the court is likely to uphold the school's policy because it concerns illegal activity and the court would be strained to say that the decision-maker has "taken leave of his senses"<ref target="BAWE_0315a-ftnote.022"/>. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0315a-ftnote.020"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">H. L. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">A. Hart - "The Concept of Law", quoted in Lord Irvine of Lairg - "Judges and Decision-Makers: the Theory and Practice of Wednesbury Review" (1996) PL 59, 62. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0315a-ftnote.021"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Wade &amp; Forsyth - "Administrative Law", page 345. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0315a-ftnote.022"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1"><hi rend="italic">Nottinghamshire County Council v Secretary of State for the Environment</hi> [1986] AC 240 at 247, quoted in J. McEldowney - "Public Law", page 503. </s></p></note></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="italic">Proportionality</head><p n="p7.14"><s n="s1.9;p7.14">It will be difficult for X to prove that the policy is irrational under the <hi rend="italic">Wednesbury</hi> test, which itself has been criticised as "an unfortunately retrogressive decision"<ref target="BAWE_0315a-ftnote.023"/>. </s><s n="s2.9;p7.14">Indeed, as seen above with its inclusion of wider concepts of fairness, "the <hi rend="italic">Wednesbury</hi> test itself is moving closer to proportionality"<ref target="BAWE_0315a-ftnote.024"/>. </s><s n="s3.9;p7.14">The threshold of review is lowered in fundamental rights cases, such as <hi rend="italic">Brind</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Bugdaycay.</hi> </s><s n="s4.9;p7.14">X could centre an argument on the unreasonable deprivation of his right to education, but this cannot be compared to the right to life. </s><s n="s5.9;p7.14">The margin of appreciation does not "cover so many degrees of latitude as that afforded by the traditional <hi rend="italic">Wednesbury</hi> doctrine"<ref target="BAWE_0315a-ftnote.025"/>. </s><s n="s6.9;p7.14">The definition of disproportionate action of "taking a sledgehammer to crack a nut"<ref target="BAWE_0315a-ftnote.026"/> fits in well with X's argument that the policy is disproportionate. </s><s n="s7.9;p7.14">In reality, all he probably needs is drugs counselling and a warning or suspension. </s><s n="s8.9;p7.14">It is arguable that the legitimate aim of stamping out drug abuse cold be achieved with a more lenient policy applied with more regard to the facts of each case. </s><s n="s9.9;p7.14">However, Lord Irvine warns against judges straying into a review of the merits of the case, saying that it "will lead judges into dangerous territory"<ref target="BAWE_0315a-ftnote.027"/>. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0315a-ftnote.023"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1"><hi rend="italic">R v Secretary of State for the Home Department ex parte Daly</hi> [2001] 2 AC 532, quoted in N. Parpworth - "Constitutional and Administrative Law", page 312. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0315a-ftnote.024"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">P. Craig - "Administrative Law", page 630. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0315a-ftnote.025"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Neill LJ in <hi rend="italic">R v Secretary of State for the Environment ex parte NALGO</hi> [1993] Admin LR 785, quoted in Lord Irvine of Lairg - "Judges and Decision-Makers: the Theory and Practice of Wednesbury Review" (1996) PL 59. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0315a-ftnote.026"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">N. Parpworth - "Constitutional and Administrative Law", page 312. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0315a-ftnote.027"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Lord Irvine of Lairg - "Judges and Decision-Makers: the Theory and Practice of Wednesbury Review" (1996) PL 59, page 65. </s></p></note></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="italic">Student Y: bias</head><p n="p8.14"><s n="s1.11;p8.14">Student Y's action centres on the requirements of fairness and natural justice relating to fair procedures. </s><s n="s2.11;p8.14">The rules relating to bias can be expressed by the Latin maxims <hi rend="italic">nemo judex in sua causa</hi> and <hi rend="italic">audi atleram partem</hi>. </s><s n="s3.11;p8.14">Y's argument against the first teacher appears unfounded given that the complaint was dismissed. </s><s n="s4.11;p8.14">However, the second strikes a chord with the <hi rend="italic">Pinnochet</hi> case, where Lord Hoffmann was held not to be impartial due to his involvement with Amnesty International. </s><s n="s5.11;p8.14">The rationale is that justice must not only be done, but must be seen to be done. </s><s n="s6.11;p8.14">Therefore, an open supporter of a cause, as in this case, is inherently biased, even if there is no evidence that they have not acted impartially. </s><s n="s7.11;p8.14">The campaigner's bias fits the <hi rend="italic">Gough</hi> test, namely that a decision-maker is biased "if motivated by a desire to favour one side or the other"<ref target="BAWE_0315a-ftnote.028"/>. </s><s n="s8.11;p8.14">This subjective test has now been replaced by a wider objective test in <hi rend="italic">Porter</hi>, namely "whether those circumstances would lead a fair-minded and informed observer to conclude that there was a real possibility...that the tribunal was biased"<ref target="BAWE_0315a-ftnote.029"/>. </s><s n="s9.11;p8.14">In the present case, it is probable that an observer would conclude that the panel was biased, in the form of the campaigner but not the first teacher. </s><s n="s10.11;p8.14">Rowbottom welcomes the reform as "especially necessary"<ref target="BAWE_0315a-ftnote.030"/> and it is also founded on "the necessity of ensuring public confidence"<ref target="BAWE_0315a-ftnote.031"/>, as stressed in <hi rend="italic">Lawal.</hi> </s><s n="s11.11;p8.14">A similar guarantee exists within article 6 of the ECHR<ref target="BAWE_0315a-ftnote.032"/>, which concerns the right to be heard by an impartial tribunal. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0315a-ftnote.028"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1"><hi rend="italic">R v Gough</hi> [1993] at 659, per Lord Goff, quoted in P. Cane - "Administrative Law", page 149. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0315a-ftnote.029"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1"><hi rend="italic">Porter v Magill</hi> [2002] 2 WLR 37, at 103, per Lord Hope, quoted in P. Cane - "Administrative Law", page 151. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0315a-ftnote.030"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">J. Rowbottom - "Homes for Votes, Bias and Political Purposes" (2002) 118 LQR 364, page 367. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0315a-ftnote.031"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Wade &amp; Forsyth - "Administrative Law", page 453. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0315a-ftnote.032"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1"><hi rend="italic">Taylor v Lawrence</hi> [2002] 3 WLR 640. </s></p></note></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="italic">Legitimate Expectations</head><p n="p9.14"><s n="s1.6;p9.14">The third prong of Y's bias argument could be framed in terms of a procedural legitimate expectation that her case would be listened to. </s><s n="s2.6;p9.14">However, such reasoning, including Lord Denning's<ref target="BAWE_0315a-ftnote.033"/>, is disapproved by Cane, who argues that such an approach "enables the court, in the name of procedural fairness, to judge the merits of the case"<ref target="BAWE_0315a-ftnote.034"/>. </s><s n="s3.6;p9.14">Nevertheless, the courts are generally willing to uphold a procedural legitimate expectation, as in <hi rend="italic">Ng Yuen Shiu.</hi> </s><s n="s4.6;p9.14">Furthermore, Y can use <hi rend="italic">Ridge v Baldwin,</hi> the rules of natural justice and article 6 ECHR to demonstrate her right to a fair hearing. </s><s n="s5.6;p9.14">Evidently, falling asleep negates any possible argument that her case has been heard. </s><s n="s6.6;p9.14">Therefore, the court should rule that Y may have her case reheard, substituting the second member of the panel and ensuring that all members remain awake! </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0315a-ftnote.033"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Lord Denning in <hi rend="italic">Cinnamond v British Airports Authority</hi> [1980] 1 WLR 582. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0315a-ftnote.034"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">P. Cane - Administrative Law", page 158. </s></p></note></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="italic">Student Z: Irrelevant Considerations</head><p n="p10.14"><s n="s1.8;p10.14">The same principles apply as in X's case regarding the factors that should be considered. </s><s n="s2.8;p10.14">Notwithstanding the fact that Z has tested positive for cocaine, the panel are wrong to consider his poor grades. </s><s n="s3.8;p10.14">Z has a strong argument, providing that there is concrete evidence that the grades played a part in the panel's decision. </s><s n="s4.8;p10.14">Thus, irrelevant considerations "provide the court with a weapon of great range and flexibility"<ref target="BAWE_0315a-ftnote.035"/>. </s><s n="s5.8;p10.14">There is a broad range of case law on this issue, from failing to consider the moral arguments against a stag hunting ban<ref target="BAWE_0315a-ftnote.036"/> to considering feminist ambitions when keeping wages inflated<ref target="BAWE_0315a-ftnote.037"/>. </s><s n="s6.8;p10.14">However, it was held in <hi rend="italic">Tesco</hi> that if both relevant and irrelevant considerations influenced the final decision, as is the case here, then it is not unlawful if the decision would have been the same in the absence of the irrelevant considerations. </s><s n="s7.8;p10.14">Cocaine is considerably more serious than cannabis and therefore the expulsion may be lawful in spite of the irrelevant consideration of the grades. </s><s n="s8.8;p10.14">This is a different situation from X's case, where the court was dealing with a failure to incorporate a relevant report. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0315a-ftnote.035"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Wade &amp; Forsyth - "Administrative Law", page 387. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0315a-ftnote.036"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1"><hi rend="italic">R v Somerset County Council ex parte Fewings</hi> [1995] 1 WLR 1037. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0315a-ftnote.037"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1"><hi rend="italic">Roberts v Hopwood</hi> [1925 AC 578. </s></p></note></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="italic">Improper Purposes</head><p n="p11.14"><s n="s1.10;p11.14"><hi rend="italic">Prima facie</hi>, it appears that the panel have expelled Z pursuant to an improper purpose. </s><s n="s2.10;p11.14">"Powers are granted for certain purposes"<ref target="BAWE_0315a-ftnote.038"/>, which here is the control of drug abuse, not saving money. </s><s n="s3.10;p11.14">In <hi rend="italic">Hanson</hi> and <hi rend="italic"> Ferguson,</hi> authorities acted <hi rend="italic">ultra vires</hi> in dismissing teachers to save expenditure. </s><s n="s4.10;p11.14">This was held to be an improper purpose not authorised by the statute. </s><s n="s5.10;p11.14">Z can rely on this precedent to argue that the school had an ulterior motive in expelling him. </s><s n="s6.10;p11.14">However, it could equally be a coincidence if the severity of Z's actions alone justifies his expulsion. </s><s n="s7.10;p11.14">As Wade points out, "the action will be lawful provided that the permitted purpose is the true and dominant purpose behind the act"<ref target="BAWE_0315a-ftnote.039"/>. </s><s n="s8.10;p11.14">Yet, the financial incentive points strongly towards an improper purpose, as did the political purpose in <hi rend="italic">Porter.</hi> </s><s n="s9.10;p11.14">In another education case, <hi rend="italic">Tandy</hi>, lack of resources was held to be an improper purpose, which adds further weight to Z's case. </s><s n="s10.10;p11.14">The court is likely to find in Z's favour, rendering the decision void<ref target="BAWE_0315a-ftnote.040"/>. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0315a-ftnote.038"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">P. Craig - "Administrative Law", page 390. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0315a-ftnote.039"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Wade &amp; Forsyth - "Administrative Law", page 388. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0315a-ftnote.040"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1"><hi rend="italic">Attorney General for Canada v Hallett &amp; Carey Ltd</hi> [1952] AC 427, referenced in P. Craig - "Administrative Law", page 390. </s></p></note></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="italic">Appeal </head><p n="p12.14"><s n="s1.10;p12.14">It is certain that the existence of an appeal to a Local Authority Board would strengthen the legitimacy of the expulsion process. </s><s n="s2.10;p12.14">However, it is not compulsory, as "natural justice does not require that there should be a right of appeal from any decision"<ref target="BAWE_0315a-ftnote.041"/>. </s><s n="s3.10;p12.14">A probable effect of the existence of an appeal would be to preclude judicial review at this stage for X and Z, as Parliament intended that the appeal is the correct channel for airing grievances with the decision-making process<ref target="BAWE_0315a-ftnote.042"/>. </s><s n="s4.10;p12.14">This point was also emphasised in the recent case of <hi rend="italic">Marcic.</hi> </s><s n="s5.10;p12.14">In <hi rend="italic">Calvin</hi>, it was held that an impartial and fair appeal can cure defects in the original procedure. </s><s n="s6.10;p12.14">Here, this goes some way to addressing Y's concerns that the panel is biased, although she is most likely to succeed in getting judicial review notwithstanding the existence of a statutory appeal. </s><s n="s7.10;p12.14">The cases may be able to bypass the appeal if the competence and speed of the alternative statutory remedy are unsatisfactory<ref target="BAWE_0315a-ftnote.043"/>. </s><s n="s8.10;p12.14">For example, it may be difficult for the students to appeal if they have been expelled with no reasons given. </s><s n="s9.10;p12.14">However, <hi rend="italic">Lonrho</hi> shows that there is not yet a general requirement to give reasons. </s><s n="s10.10;p12.14">In any case, if an appeal existed, it would be a better route to justice as it will be possible for the merits of the case to be reviewed and not merely the procedural issues. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0315a-ftnote.041"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1"><hi rend="italic">Ward v Bradford Corporation</hi> [1921] 70 LGR 27, quoted in Wade &amp; Forsyth - "Administrative Law", page 527. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0315a-ftnote.042"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1"><hi rend="italic">R (Dr) v Head teacher of St. George's Catholic School and Others</hi> [2002] EWCA Civ. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">1822. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0315a-ftnote.043"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1"><hi rend="italic">Ex parte Waldron</hi> [1986], referenced in N. Parpworth - "Constitutional and Administrative Law", page 265. </s></p></note></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="italic">Conclusion</head><p n="p13.14"><s n="s1.9;p13.14">To conclude, the three scenarios illustrated pose some interesting problems regarding the scope of judicial review and the adequateness of the <hi rend="italic">Wednesbury</hi> test for rationality of administrative decision-making. </s><s n="s2.9;p13.14">X has a solid case based on procedural unfairness and the panel's error of fact. </s><s n="s3.9;p13.14">The court can demand that the medical report be considered by the panel via a mandatory order. </s><s n="s4.9;p13.14">However, the court does not have the power to dictate the weight that should be given to the report. </s><s n="s5.9;p13.14">However, the line of argument based on the validity of the policy is considerably weaker.<hi rend="italic"> Wednesbury</hi> is a high standard to reach and it is highly unlikely that a court will sympathise with X's argument. </s><s n="s6.9;p13.14">Proportionality would potentially provide a better recourse, although it is not yet the universal test for <hi rend="italic">ultra vires</hi> actions. </s><s n="s7.9;p13.14">Y has a strong case to have her case reheard by a new panel, excluding the anti-drugs campaigner. </s><s n="s8.9;p13.14">Z's case should be successful on the grounds of the panel irrelevantly considering his poor grades. </s><s n="s9.9;p13.14">The line of argument based on an improper purpose is reasonably watertight, but is liable to fail if the court considers that the closure of the department is merely an incidental consequence of Z's serious cocaine offence. </s></p><p n="p14.14"><s n="s1.4;p14.14">Nevertheless, all three cases illustrate the importance of natural justice playing a significant role within the judicial review system. </s><s n="s2.4;p14.14">Cases such as these are important so that the system maintains its integrity and the confidence of the public. </s><s n="s3.4;p14.14">There have been fears of degeneration into a "nightmarish and dehumanising"<ref target="BAWE_0315a-ftnote.044"/> situation where the state becomes omnipotent. </s><s n="s4.4;p14.14">To avoid the occurrence of scenes from one of Kafka's novels, for example, where crucial evidence is ignored or there is blatant bias, it is vital that aggrieved citizens stand up for their rights when they are victims of injustice. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0315a-ftnote.044"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">P. Craig - "The Common Law, Reasons and Administrative Justice" (1994) 53(2) CLJ 282, page 284. </s></p></note></div1></body><back/></text></TEI.2>
