<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_0317b" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>History of Maths Essay 2</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note/></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">3</p><p n="date">2006-12</p><p n="module title">History of Maths</p><p n="module code">MA3E5</p><p n="genre family">Critique</p><p n="discipline">Mathematics</p><p n="disciplinary group">PS</p><p n="grade">D</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">1865</p><p n="number of s-units">67</p><p n="number of p">14</p><p n="number of tables">0</p><p n="number of figures">0</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">0</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">0</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">27.8</p><p n="average s-units per p">4.8</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">m</p><p n="year of birth">1986</p><p n="first language">English</p><p n="education">UKA</p><p n="course">MMathPhys</p><p n="student ID">0317</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><docTitle><titlePart rend="underlined bold">Dirichlet's Paper of 1829</titlePart></docTitle></titlePage><div1 type="front text"><p rend="bulleted">List of equations (1) - (11).</p><p rend="bulleted">Introduction and manipulation of Fourier series, leading to equations (1) and (2). Reduces the problem to showing convergence of Dirichlet integral.</p><p rend="bulleted">Simplest case. Introduce constraints on <hi rend="italic">f(β)</hi> and discuss decomposition of integral (3).</p><p rend="bulleted">Consider arbitrary section of (3). Application of the Mean Value Theorem, leading to (4). Change of variables showing that (4) converges to (5). Use of known fact that (6) = π / 2.</p><p rend="bulleted">Sum all integrals (4) to give (3). Obtain limit for (3) by splitting into two sequences (7) and (8), then using previous results.</p><p rend="bulleted">Generalise to monotonic functions. Condense previous work into Theorem 1.</p><p rend="bulleted">Consider new lower bound of integration. Integrate between this and <hi rend="italic">h</hi> resulting in (9). Obtain Theorem 2.</p><p rend="bulleted">Consider discontinuities in range of integration. Obtain Theorem 3.</p><p rend="bulleted">Start to investigate (2). Split into two parts, (10) and (11).</p><p rend="bulleted">Consider (11) in two cases, <hi rend="italic">x</hi> positive and <hi rend="italic">x</hi> negative. Discover limit of convergence for all values of <hi rend="italic">x</hi> in range.</p><p rend="bulleted">Integral (10) analogous to (11). Limits of convergence.</p><p rend="bulleted">Combine results from (10) and (11) to give limit of (2).</p><p rend="bulleted">Conclusion. Summary of results. Conditions which a function must satisfy to be expandable by a Fourier series.</p><p rend="bulleted">Lifting restrictions on number of discontinuities and extrema in certain cases.</p><p rend="bulleted">Historical context. Aspects of Dirichlet's paper used today.</p><p/></div1><div1 type="front text"><head rend="underlined bold">List of equations used </head><p rend="ordered"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0317b-form.001"/><hi rend="bold">(1) </hi></p><p rend="ordered"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0317b-form.002"/><hi rend="bold">(2) </hi></p><p rend="ordered"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0317b-form.003"/><hi rend="bold">(3) </hi></p><p rend="ordered"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0317b-form.004"/><hi rend="bold">(4) </hi></p><p rend="ordered"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0317b-form.005"/><hi rend="bold">(5) </hi></p><p rend="ordered"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0317b-form.006"/><hi rend="bold">(6) </hi></p><p rend="ordered"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0317b-form.007"/><hi rend="bold">(7) </hi></p><p rend="ordered"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0317b-form.008"/><hi rend="bold">(8)</hi></p><p rend="ordered"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0317b-form.009"/><hi rend="bold"> (9) </hi></p><p rend="ordered"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0317b-form.010"/><hi rend="bold">(10) </hi></p><p rend="ordered"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0317b-form.011"/><hi rend="bold">(11)</hi></p><p/></div1></front><body><div1 type="section"><p n="p1.14"><s n="s1.4;p1.14">Dirichlet's paper of 1829 was mainly concerned with discovering the limit, if any, to which a Fourier series would converge and ascertaining what conditions a function would have to obey for its Fourier series to represent it correctly. </s><s n="s2.4;p1.14">The Fourier series of a function <hi rend="italic">φ(x)</hi> on the interval [-π, π] is well known, and the first 2n+1 terms can be manipulated to give equation (1). </s><s n="s3.4;p1.14">This in turn can be summed, giving equation (2) which is nowadays known as the Dirichlet Integral. </s><s n="s4.4;p1.14">Thus the problem reduces to discovering the conditions which must be placed upon φ(x) for this integral to converge, and finding the limit of this convergence. </s></p><p n="p2.14"><s n="s1.6;p2.14">Dirichlet first considered 'the simplest cases, to which all others can be reduced'<ref target="BAWE_0317b-ftnote.001"/>. </s><s n="s2.6;p2.14">He considered an arbitrary function <hi rend="italic">f(β)</hi> which is positive, monotonic decreasing and continuous on [0, <hi rend="italic">h</hi>], with 0 &lt; <hi rend="italic">h </hi>≤π / 2. </s><s n="s3.6;p2.14">He then considered the integral (3), and worked on discovering its limit as the positive quantity k is increased. </s><s n="s4.6;p2.14">To begin with, he divided the integral into various others, the first from β = to β = π / k, the second from β = π / k to β = 2π / k, and so on, up until the penultimate one, which has limits β = (r-1)π / k to β = rπ / k, where r is the greatest integer multiple of π / k such that rπ / k is less than h. </s><s n="s5.6;p2.14">Therefore, the final integral, which will have a smaller range of integration than the others will be from β = rπ / k to β = h. </s><s n="s6.6;p2.14">Dirichlet noted that these integrals are alternately positive and negative, since the only part of the integrand which changes sign is sin(kβ) and furthermore, that they decrease in size from the first to the last, as f(β) is monotonic decreasing. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0317b-ftnote.001"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Dirichlet [1829] p.2 </s></p></note><p n="p3.14"><s n="s1.8;p3.14">Now, taking ν to be an integer less than r, Dirichlet considered the integral from β = (ν-1)π / k to β = νπ / k. </s><s n="s2.8;p3.14">Since f(β) is continuous and differentiable, he applied the mean value theorem, allowing him to write this integral as (4). </s><s n="s3.8;p3.14">He denoted the absolute value of the integral in this expression by Kν, and then found the limit of these integrals as k tended to infinity. </s><s n="s4.8;p3.14">He did this by setting β = γ / k and found that this converged to the limit (5), the absolute value of which he denoted by kν. </s><s n="s5.8;p3.14">Dirichlet then used the established fact that the integral (6) is finite and in fact equal to π / 2. </s><s n="s6.8;p3.14">This integral can be split up into infinitely many others, the first from γ = 0 to γ = π, the second from γ = π to γ = 2π, the integral of index ν from γ = (ν -1)π to γ = νπ, and so on. </s><s n="s7.8;p3.14">These are alternately positive and negative, decreasing, and the absolute value of the integral of index ν is kν. </s><s n="s8.8;p3.14">Thus the infinite series k1 - k2 + k3.... converges to π / 2. </s></p><p n="p4.14"><s n="s1.9;p4.14">Dirichlet then returned to considering integral (3) as a sum of its decompositions (4). </s><s n="s2.9;p4.14">He took a fixed, arbitrarily even integer <hi rend="italic">m</hi> and noted that <hi rend="italic">r</hi>, defined above, will eventually become larger than <hi rend="italic">m</hi> as <hi rend="italic">k</hi> increases indefinitely. </s><s n="s3.9;p4.14">Thus (3) will be divided into two sequences; the first group, having the same number of terms independent of <hi rend="italic">k</hi>, is given by (7), whilst the second will have a continually increasing number of terms with <hi rend="italic">k</hi> and is given by (8). </s><s n="s4.9;p4.14">In (7) since <hi rend="italic">k</hi> is increasing indefinitely the interval containing ρ tends to [f(0), f(0)], and so all the ρν converge to the value f(0). </s><s n="s5.9;p4.14">We have also seen that the Kν converge to the corresponding kν in these circumstances and hence by setting the sum of the kν equal to Sm, we have that (7) converges to Smf(0). </s><s n="s6.9;p4.14">Using the definition of convergence this means that the difference between (7) and Smf(0) will always be less than an arbitrarily small positive value ω. </s><s n="s7.9;p4.14">The sequence (8) will always be positive and less than its first value, and so will converge to a value less than km+1f(0) + ω', where ω' is an arbitrarily small positive value. </s><s n="s8.9;p4.14">Dirichlet also noticed that the difference between Sm and π / 2 was always less than km+1, and so he could deduce that the difference between (3) and (π / 2)f(0) will always be less than ω + ω' +2km+1. </s><s n="s9.9;p4.14">Since m can be chosen to be arbitrarily large, this limit will be arbitrarily small (since the kν are a decreasing sequence) and so (3) converges to the limit (π / 2)f(0). </s></p><p n="p5.14"><s n="s1.1;p5.14">Dirichlet then adjusted this argument to accommodate functions which were constant, negative, or increasing, and obtained a general statement: The integral (3), where <hi rend="italic">f(β)</hi> is a continuous and monotonic function between 0 and <hi rend="italic">h</hi>, will converge to the limit (π / 2)f(0) as k increases.<ref target="BAWE_0317b-ftnote.002"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0317b-ftnote.002"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">This will now be referred to as Theorem 1 </s></p></note><p n="p6.14"><s n="s1.5;p6.14">Next he considered a function <hi rend="italic">f(β)</hi> defined on [<hi rend="italic">g, h</hi>], where <hi rend="italic">g</hi> &lt; <hi rend="italic">h</hi>. </s><s n="s2.5;p6.14">This function is defined to be continuous between <hi rend="italic">g</hi> and <hi rend="italic">h</hi> and arbitrary between 0 and <hi rend="italic">g</hi> such that if it is increasing from <hi rend="italic">g</hi> to <hi rend="italic">h</hi>, it is increasing from 0 to <hi rend="italic">g</hi> and if it is decreasing from <hi rend="italic">g</hi> to <hi rend="italic">h</hi> it is decreasing from 0 to <hi rend="italic">g</hi>. </s><s n="s3.5;p6.14">Provided <hi rend="italic"> f(β)</hi> is continuous at <hi rend="italic">g</hi>, the integral (3) and the same integral between 0 and <hi rend="italic">g</hi> will both converge to (π / 2)f(0) by Theorem 1. </s><s n="s4.5;p6.14">Hence integral (9), the difference of the previous integrals, will converge to the difference of their limits. </s><s n="s5.5;p6.14">This will be 0 in all cases, except when g is 0, in which case the integral converges to (π / 2)f(0).<ref target="BAWE_0317b-ftnote.003"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0317b-ftnote.003"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">This will now be referred to as Theorem 2 </s></p></note><p n="p7.14"><s n="s1.2;p7.14">The next part of the paper makes an important point - if the function admitted a discontinuity at <hi rend="italic">g</hi> or <hi rend="italic">h</hi>, we would still be able to use the same limit and so we would be able to safely consider the integral on the open interval as well as the closed one. </s><s n="s2.2;p7.14">If <hi rend="italic">f(g) ≠ f(g + ε)</hi> and <hi rend="italic"> f(h) ≠ f(h</hi> - ε) (Dirichlet's definition of discontinuities at g and h), where ε is infinitely small, and the values the functions take at g and h are not infinite, then we simply have to replace f(0) by f(ε) in Theorem 2.<ref target="BAWE_0317b-ftnote.004"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0317b-ftnote.004"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">This will now be referred to as Theorem 3 </s></p></note><p n="p8.14"><s n="s1.3;p8.14">He was now ready to consider the convergence of integral (2) as <hi rend="italic">n</hi> increases. </s><s n="s2.3;p8.14">He first split this up into two other integrals, one from - π to x and the second from x to π. </s><s n="s3.3;p8.14">He did this by setting α = x - 2β in the first case and α = x + 2β in the second, leading to integrals (10) and (11). </s></p><p n="p9.14"><s n="s1.8;p9.14">Let us consider (11) in the case where <hi rend="italic">x</hi> is positive. </s><s n="s2.8;p9.14">The integral is trivially zero when x = π, and in all other cases it will converge. </s><s n="s3.8;p9.14">The function φ(x + 2β) may have a finite number of discontinuities and also a finite number of maxima or minima, so Dirichlet split the integral at each of these points into smaller integrals, so that each integral satisfied the requirements of Theorem 2. </s><s n="s4.8;p9.14">Therefore, they all converged to zero except the first, which converges to (π / 2)φ(x + ε), by Theorem 3. </s><s n="s5.8;p9.14">Considering the same integral, but with values of x less than zero, Dirichlet noticed that he could split the integral again, into two parts, one from β = 0 to β = π / 2, and the other from β = π / 2 to β = (π - x) / 2. </s><s n="s6.8;p9.14">The first of these is simply a case of the integral we have already considered, and so converges to the limit above; the second, upon the change of variables β = π - γ, can be decomposed like the first, and so will converge to 0 in all cases except that where x = - π. </s><s n="s7.8;p9.14">In this case, it will converge to the value (π / 2)φ(π - ε), by Theorem 3. </s><s n="s8.8;p9.14">In summary, integral (11) is zero when x = π, converges to (π / 2)[φ(π - ε ) + φ(-π + ε )] <ref target="BAWE_0317b-ftnote.005"/> when x = - π and converges to (π / 2)φ(x + ε) in all other cases. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0317b-ftnote.005"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">The - π comes from the fact that the integral converges to this point at the value x = - π, and substituting this into the limit attained previously. </s></p></note><p n="p10.14"><s n="s1.1;p10.14">Integral (10) is analogous to (11), and a similar treatment gives us that it is zero when <hi rend="italic"> x = - π</hi>, converges to <hi rend="italic">(π / 2)</hi>[φ(π - ε ) + φ(-π + ε )] at x = π and converges to (π / 2)φ(x - ε) in all other cases. </s></p><p n="p11.14"><s n="s1.3;p11.14">It is easy to see that integral (2) is simply equal to the sum of integrals (10) and (11) divided by π. </s><s n="s2.3;p11.14">Thus on adding the limits of the two integrals we get the result that integral (2), and hence the Fourier Series (1), converge to the limit (1 / 2)[φ(x - ε ) + φ(x + ε )]. </s><s n="s3.3;p11.14">This is also defined at the extreme values of the integral, as being (1 / 2)[φ(π - ε ) + φ(-π + ε )]. </s></p><p n="p12.14"><s n="s1.2;p12.14">In conclusion, Dirichlet had proven that in order for the Fourier series of a function to converge, the function has to admit finite and definite values, have a finite number of discontinuities and also have a finite number of maxima or minima between the extreme values -π and π. </s><s n="s2.2;p12.14">If the function has no discontinuities then the Fourier series will converge to the function itself; if there are discontinuities present, the Fourier series will converge to the mean of the limits that the function attains on either side of these discontinuities. </s></p><p n="p13.14"><s n="s1.4;p13.14">Finally, he remarked that we could relax the conditions on the number of continuities and extrema that the function admitted, so long as any subset of the function's image is not dense in our set theoretical sense of the word. </s><s n="s2.4;p13.14">If this was the case, we would always be able to split the graph into sections to which our previous arguments had applied. </s><s n="s3.4;p13.14">He gave an example of a function whose entire image was dense, which would not be representable by a Fourier series; it mapped rational numbers to an integer <hi rend="italic">a</hi> and irrational numbers to an integer <hi rend="italic">b</hi>. </s><s n="s4.4;p13.14">Attempting to split this into suitable integrals is impossible. </s></p><p n="p14.14"><s n="s1.11;p14.14">The importance of this paper cannot be underestimated. </s><s n="s2.11;p14.14">Before Dirichlet, no one had been able to give a successful proof of the convergence of Fourier series, although eminent mathematicians such as Cauchy had tried. </s><s n="s3.11;p14.14">Dirichlet refuted Cauchy's proof on the grounds that his convergence criterion was flawed; he gave a fairly simple example to support this claim.<ref target="BAWE_0317b-ftnote.006"/> Additionally, he seemed to be of the opinion that Cauchy's method of considering <hi rend="italic">φ(x)</hi> as a function of a complex variable was an unnecessary complication in an already difficult problem. </s><s n="s4.11;p14.14">Poisson and Sturm had both previously criticised Fourier for assuming the convergence of his series, especially the convergence to the correct limit. </s><s n="s5.11;p14.14">Dirichlet appeared to share this criticism, and so gave the first rigorous proof of their convergence. </s><s n="s6.11;p14.14">Not only was this specific result important, but also the general style of Dirichlet's proof. </s><s n="s7.11;p14.14">He clearly sets himself a goal, and defines each condition and step as he goes along. </s><s n="s8.11;p14.14">This constitutes a major shift in mathematical thinking; whereas previously mathematicians considered theorems as being true but admitting exceptions, Dirichlet saw them as being either true in all cases, or not true at all. </s><s n="s9.11;p14.14">This is very much the standard up against which today's theorems are measured. </s><s n="s10.11;p14.14">His results are still used to this day, and even elements of his proof are retained by mathematicians today, namely the Drichlet Kernel<ref target="BAWE_0317b-ftnote.007"/>. </s><s n="s11.11;p14.14">This is used in a more modern interpretation of the Fourier series, which involves convolutions of Fourier coefficients with the Kernel, resulting in the Fourier approximation of the function in question.<ref target="BAWE_0317b-ftnote.008"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0317b-ftnote.006"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Dirichlet [1829], p.2 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0317b-ftnote.007"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">This is twice the integrand of (2) </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0317b-ftnote.008"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">'<seg type="URL" n="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Convergence_of_Fourier_series"/>' </s></p></note></div1></body><back/></text></TEI.2>
