<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_0318f" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>The rise and fall of the Third Reich</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">deleted: header: student name, date; footer: assignment title, page numbers</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">3</p><p n="date">2006-03</p><p n="module title">Eastern Europe in Crisis</p><p n="module code">HI349</p><p n="genre family">Essay</p><p n="discipline">History</p><p n="disciplinary group">AH</p><p n="grade">D</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">3001</p><p n="number of s-units">107</p><p n="number of p">13</p><p n="number of tables">0</p><p n="number of figures">0</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">0</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">0</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">28.0</p><p n="average s-units per p">8.2</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">f</p><p n="year of birth">1985</p><p n="first language">English</p><p n="education">UKA</p><p n="course">History</p><p n="student ID">0318</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><docTitle><titlePart> Eastern Europe in Crisis - Essay Two</titlePart></docTitle></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="section"><p n="p1.13"><s n="s1.14;p1.13">The rise and fall of the Third Reich had the most profound of consequences for the Czechoslovak lands and people.<ref target="BAWE_0318f-ftnote.001"/> Sacrificed by their allies Britain and France in a futile attempt to avoid war by ceding substantial Sudetenland territory in the Munich Settlement of 29 September 1938, full occupation was really only a matter of time. </s><s n="s2.14;p1.13">Beginning on the night of 15 March 1939, official Nazi occupation of Bohemia and Moravia endured until 13 May 1945. </s><s n="s3.14;p1.13">Nazi dominance over the region was one of the darkest periods in Czechoslovak history, and Czechoslovak leaders had only limited scope to protect their nation and its population. </s><s n="s4.14;p1.13">Edvard Beneš (1884 - 1948) and Emil Hàcha (1872-1945) were two of the best-placed figures to fight for the survival of their republic and its people during the occupation. </s><s n="s5.14;p1.13">Beneš was the Czech politician and diplomat who had been a leader of the Czechoslovak independence movement, and became the second President of the republic. </s><s n="s6.14;p1.13">He resigned on 5 October 1938, and became leader of the government-in-exile in London during the Naxi occupation.<ref target="BAWE_0318f-ftnote.002"/> Meanwhile, the celebrated Czech legal mind Hàcha reluctantly accepted the position of was Beneš' successor, who became President of the Protectorate of Bohemia and Moravia. </s><s n="s7.14;p1.13">Beneš was recognised as the figurehead, with his role being to fight for the legal continuity and territorial integrity of the republic after the war, while Hàcha was more concerned with protecting the population during occupation, all the while subordinating his actions to Beneš direction as part of his foreign policy strategy. </s><s n="s8.14;p1.13">The complexity and difficulty of the situation for these two men cannot be overstated. </s><s n="s9.14;p1.13">Geopolitics far greater than the power of a Czechoslovak republic threatened to thwart every effort made by the outstanding political tactician that was Beneš throughout. </s><s n="s10.14;p1.13">The blood of millions of Czechoslovaks was potentially the responsibility of Beneš, and to a more immediate extent, Hacha, with every word written or spoken by him under the auspices of the Nazis inside the Protectorate. </s><s n="s11.14;p1.13">It is certainly not the place of the author to seriously judge either of these men in their unenviable struggles. </s><s n="s12.14;p1.13">Yet, their strategies and actions can be evaluated with respect to whether they interpreted the needs of their people well, and their success can be considered too. </s><s n="s13.14;p1.13">The following enquiry will be primarily concerned with the Protectorate of Bohemia and Moravia, and 'Czech' people will be taken to mean ethnic Czechs, who were by far the majority of the Protectorate's population. </s><s n="s14.14;p1.13">Diaries and memoirs, minutes of official meetings, accounts of conversations, letters and memoranda, and communist reports and despatches, from Czech, German, British, American, and Soviet political figures will be used to determine the strategy and success of Edvard Beneš and Emil Hàcha in protecting the interests of the Czech people under Nazi occupation. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0318f-ftnote.001"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">The First Republic consisted of the territories Bohemia, Moravia-Silesia, Slovakia, and Sub-Carpathian Ruthenia and was in existence between 1927 and 1938. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">In the interwar period, only about fifty per cent of the people were so-called 'Czechs'. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0318f-ftnote.002"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.6;pn1.1">In his radio address on 5 October 1938 Beneš, 'aware that his presence represented at that time an insuperable obstacle to Czechoslovakia's good relations with Germany' took the immediate step of exile. </s><s n="s2.6;pn1.1">(Vojtech Mastny, <hi rend="italic">The Czechs Under Nazi Rule: The Failure of National Resistance, 1939-42</hi> (New York, 1971), 140.) </s><s n="s3.6;pn1.1">When the Protectorate was created Beneš encouraged the Protectorate government to remain in office firstly to ensure the survival of a Czech army, secondly to provide ready administration in the event of a German collapse, and thirdly to prevent the communists filling a power vacuum. </s><s n="s4.6;pn1.1">So Beneš did, therefore, legally resign as president of the Czechoslovak republic. </s><s n="s5.6;pn1.1">As Jaromir Smutný suggested, Beneš achieved an impressive propaganda coup by convincing the Allies that he was rightful leader of a postwar republic. </s><s n="s6.6;pn1.1">(Extract from Smutný's diary, 5 July 1943.) </s></p></note><p n="p2.13"><s n="s1.8;p2.13">Both Beneš and Hàcha began their roles as protectors of the republic and its people on shaky ground. </s><s n="s2.8;p2.13">Beneš at once faced a struggle to acquire recognition as a president-in-exile, because he was the living reminder of the British and French betrayal at Munich. </s><s n="s3.8;p2.13">However, he was energetic and made himself not only visible, but also useful, to the Allies. </s><s n="s4.8;p2.13">The legal anomaly that he was not actually the Czechoslovak president was not so much overcome as overlooked,<ref target="BAWE_0318f-ftnote.003"/> depending on how far Benes was in favour with Britain, the United States and the Soviet Union at any one time. </s><s n="s5.8;p2.13">By late 1939 Beneš had secured British and French recognition of a Czechoslovak national committee, and had also overseen the establishment of a Czechoslovak army in France. </s><s n="s6.8;p2.13">Once Beneš had installed himself as principal diplomat for the Czechoslovak republic, his principle objectives were to acquire official diplomatic recognition of his government-in-exile, to be followed by confirmation by both the Western and Eastern powers of the legal continuity of the Czechoslovak republic after the defeat of the Third Reich, which included the repudiation of the Munich settlement. </s><s n="s7.8;p2.13">In addition, Beneš needed to create a meaningful place for himself in the future world order to ensure the long-term survival of an independent republic, which had had previously proved so short-lived. </s><s n="s8.8;p2.13">He would do so through being a useful source of information for anxious powers, an impressive diplomat and mediator, head of potential Czech armed forces, and head of security apparatus willing to supply the Allies with intelligence. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0318f-ftnote.003"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">It 'was legally difficult to reconcile Beneš' claim to uninterrupted presidential continuity and constitutional permanence with his own resignation in 1938, the selection of a new president, the formation of a new government, and important consitutional changes.' (H. Gordon Skilling, 'The National Liberation in World War II', <hi rend="italic">Slavonic and East European Review</hi>, 39 (Dec., 1960), 180.) </s></p></note><p n="p3.13"><s n="s1.5;p3.13">Although Beneš was tireless in his campaigning, major diplomatic successes were usually decided by decisive events in the war. </s><s n="s2.5;p3.13">It was only in the aftermath of the fall of France, in July 1940, that a provisional Czechoslovak government and parliament were recognised. </s><s n="s3.5;p3.13">The British, at this point, still refused to agree to future territorial arrangements.<ref target="BAWE_0318f-ftnote.004"/> Similarly, when the Soviet Union entered the war in June 1941 a treaty of mutual assistance was signed with the provisional government, which finally afforded the London Czechs with full diplomatic recognition.<ref target="BAWE_0318f-ftnote.005"/> The repudiation of Munich was Beneš' next important objective. </s><s n="s4.5;p3.13">It was Molotov for the Soviet Union who was first to indicate that this would be realised. </s><s n="s5.5;p3.13">In a conversation in June 1942 the commissar assured Beneš that the Soviet Union did not recognise Munich or anything that had happened to the Czechoslovak republic since. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0318f-ftnote.004"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Letter from Halifax to Beneš (18 July 1940). </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0318f-ftnote.005"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Britain granted recognition the same day, but again did not confirm frontiers. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">Two weeks later the United States appointed an ambassador to the London Czechs. </s></p></note><p n="p4.13"><s n="s1.6;p4.13">On the other hand, the main example of these powers responding to the Czech' leader's initiative was the repudiation of Munich, which resulted from Operation Anthropoid. </s><s n="s2.6;p4.13">Beneš was acutely aware that the Protectorate government would be a liability to his diplomatic efforts if it were perceived to be a tool of the Nazis, full of self-serving quislings.<ref target="BAWE_0318f-ftnote.006"/> Once Beneš had decided that Hacha's collaborationism was worrying the Allies, he settled on a dramatic gesture of resistance against the Nazi occupiers was needed to vindicate the Czechs. </s><s n="s3.6;p4.13">On 27 May 1942 two Czech assassins, who had been supported by an underground network in Britain and the Protectorate, attacked the Nazi leader in the Protectorate Reinhard Heydrich, who died a week later. </s><s n="s4.6;p4.13">In addition to ensuring that every participant and underground assistant to the assassins was killed, the Nazis completely destroyed the towns of Lidice and Ležáky. </s><s n="s5.6;p4.13">It was these heavy recriminations against the Czechs in its aftermath, rather than the actual gesture of assassination, which convinced Britain to officially repudiate Munich in August. </s><s n="s6.6;p4.13">The price that Beneš required of his people in order to ensure the territorial continuity of the post-war republic was certainly higher than he had predicted, but he would have been willing to pay it nonetheless. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0318f-ftnote.006"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Callum MacDonald, <hi rend="italic">The Killing of Reinhard Heydrich: The SS "Butcher of Prague"</hi> (New York, 1998), 80. </s></p></note><p n="p5.13"><s n="s1.9;p5.13">Thereafter, Beneš had to continuously prove that the Czechoslovak republic deserved to emerge as a viable entity after the war. </s><s n="s2.9;p5.13">He devoted himself as mediator for Poland, especially after the breakdown in their relations with Moscow in June 1944. </s><s n="s3.9;p5.13">Representing Poland was certainly in the Czechoslovak national interest. </s><s n="s4.9;p5.13">Between November 1940 and mid-1942 Beneš and Sikorski increasingly moved towards a confederation - a powerful Eastern European bloc.<ref target="BAWE_0318f-ftnote.007"/> However, Beneš coldly neglected this alliance once it was clear the Stalin disapproved.<ref target="BAWE_0318f-ftnote.008"/> More ambitiously, Beneš aspired to be the bridge between West and East. </s><s n="s5.9;p5.13">Convinced that the Soviet Union would emerge from the war as a moderate European great power, Beneš shifted his allegiance more towards Stalin. </s><s n="s6.9;p5.13">Beneš effectively was the dictator's champion to the United States, particularly during his visit to Washington between May and June 1943.<ref target="BAWE_0318f-ftnote.009"/> His advising Roosevelt about the Poles and Soviet Union was rewarded by the president agreeing to the transfer of the German population out of the post-war republic. </s><s n="s7.9;p5.13">Beneš was valued in Moscow too in December. </s><s n="s8.9;p5.13">After working hard to persuade Britain, Beneš was able to enter into the Soviet-Czechoslovak Treaty.<ref target="BAWE_0318f-ftnote.010"/> Beneš saw himself as the broker of the Soviet Union's entry into a future stable balance of power in Europe, but the pact was more important to him and the Czech people because it contained the implication that there would be no possible communisation and Sovietisation after the war. </s><s n="s9.9;p5.13">For all of his foresight and efforts, Beneš was too optimistic about there being room for him and an independent Czechoslovak republic in the new world order. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0318f-ftnote.007"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Correspondence includes letter from Beneš to Sikorski (1 November 1940), the Polish-Czechslovak Declaration (11 November 1940), letter from Beneš to Sikorski (25 February 1941), and the Polish-Czechoslovak declaration (19 January 1942). </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0318f-ftnote.008"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Dispatch from Eden to Sir Cecil Dormer (8 January 1942). </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0318f-ftnote.009"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Report from Beneš to Government-in-Exile (13 May - 7 June 1943). </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0318f-ftnote.010"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">The Soviet-Czechoslovak Treaty was signed on 12 December 1943. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">It promised mutual military and other support during and after the war against Germany, prohibited either party from entering into separate negotiations with Hitler, committed to independence and non-interference in internal affairs, and developing economic relations. </s></p></note><p n="p6.13"><s n="s1.14;p6.13">Beneš' diplomatic manoeuvres were undoubtedly impressive, and it is difficult to imagine any man being more successful than he in achieving his objectives. </s><s n="s2.14;p6.13">However, his tireless efforts resulted in serious failures too. </s><s n="s3.14;p6.13">The most grave was, of course, his failure to prevent Czech communists from gaining a following and power during, and especially in the aftermath of, the war. </s><s n="s4.14;p6.13">Once the Soviet Union entered on the side of the Allies on 22 June 1941, the Czech communists in Moscow, the government-in-exile, and the Czech underground did achieve a substantial degree of unity in their resistance to the Nazis, but politically they were antagonistic. </s><s n="s5.14;p6.13">Fierlinger reported to the exile government on 4 January 1942 that 'Some pseudo-liberal regime will not have the support in Moscow that is expected." </s><ref target="BAWE_0318f-ftnote.011"/><s n="s6.14;p6.13">By May, Beneš, was assuring Fierlinger that the first post-war government would be a "popular front", with a radical social and economic programme. </s><s n="s7.14;p6.13">'By the time Beneš visited Moscow at the end of 1943, the communists there were ready to welcome him as the head of the state and the official representative of the Czech movement." </s><ref target="BAWE_0318f-ftnote.012"/><s n="s8.14;p6.13">Yet, his positive feelings towards the Soviet Union were too great an influence on Beneš. </s><s n="s9.14;p6.13">Mastny is particularly critical of his naivety.<ref target="BAWE_0318f-ftnote.013"/> He did not test Soviet sincerity to the Czechoslovak state. </s><s n="s10.14;p6.13">His secretary Taborsky regarded the December 1943 treaty as Beneš' greatest misinterpretation. </s><s n="s11.14;p6.13">'Beneš did misread Stalin's psyche, place too much trust in his assurances, and misinterpret his real intentions." </s><ref target="BAWE_0318f-ftnote.014"/><s n="s12.14;p6.13">Another painful example of Benes' powerlessness was the affair over Sub-Carpathian Ruthenia beginning in October 1944.<ref target="BAWE_0318f-ftnote.015"/> By the end of 1944, despite being treaty-bound to non-interferece, the Soviets began to see the Czech communist leader Klement Gottwald as Beneš replacement. </s><s n="s13.14;p6.13">In a letter to Fierlinger on 30 December 1944, Beneš was essentially resigned to recognising the Lublin Committee as the future government.<ref target="BAWE_0318f-ftnote.016"/> The loss of Sub-Carpathian Ruthenia indicated that policy had swung more to the East than Beneš had envisaged. </s><s n="s14.14;p6.13">The participation of communists in the post-war government was also in excess of his expectations. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0318f-ftnote.011"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Letter from Zdnek Fierlinger to Beneš (4 January 1942). </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0318f-ftnote.012"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Skilling, 'The National Liberation', 183. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0318f-ftnote.013"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Mastny, <hi rend="italic">Czechs Under Nazi Rule</hi>. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0318f-ftnote.014"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Edward Taborsky, <hi rend="italic">President Edvard Beneš: Between East and West, 1938-48</hi> (Stanford, 1981), 5. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0318f-ftnote.015"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.9;pn1.1">In late October, the Red Army began recruiting volunteers in Sub-Carpathian Ruthenia. </s><s n="s2.9;pn1.1">This ran contrary to the treaty of mutual assistance, threatening the Czech right to form their own army. </s><s n="s3.9;pn1.1">At the same time, there were local meetings in areas of recruitment whereby some Ruthenians were demanding incorporation of their territory into the Soviet Union. </s><s n="s4.9;pn1.1">At the end of November a communist party-organised provincial congress demanded that they be allowed to leave the Czechoslovak republic. </s><s n="s5.9;pn1.1">This made a mockery of the pre-Munich borders, and set a dangerous example to the Slovaks. </s><s n="s6.9;pn1.1">'Although deeply disturbed, Beneš was inclined to think that these events were happening without the knowledge of the Soviet government' (Skilling, 'The National Liberation', 183.) </s><s n="s7.9;pn1.1">Czech and Slovak communists claimed no prior knowledge, and moved by Gottwald to reassure the Czechs, Stalin himself acted decisively with a letter to Beneš. (?)The substantial effort to reassure Beneš convinced him of the good intentions of the Soviets. </s><s n="s8.9;pn1.1">Stalin confirmed his support for the Czechs, but suggested that the issue of sovereignty should be addressed at a later date. </s><s n="s9.9;pn1.1">Beneš was adamant that he should not lose the territory during the war to save face, yet he expressed that he was perfectly willing to give them the territory afterwards as a gesture of friendship (he had motioned this willingness in the Moscow talks of 1943). </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0318f-ftnote.016"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Letter from Beneš to Fierlinger (30 December 1944). </s></p></note><p n="p7.13"><s n="s1.10;p7.13">In addition to his work for the future Czechoslovak people, Beneš' strategy and actions affected the Czechs during the occupation directly too. </s><s n="s2.10;p7.13">Beneš was 'inclined, in his broadcasts from London, to discourage active resistance at a time when it would have involved useless sacrifices." </s><ref target="BAWE_0318f-ftnote.017"/><s n="s3.10;p7.13">Beneš advised the Czech army not to irritate the Nazis in case there were reprisals against the Protectorate government or Czech people. </s><s n="s4.10;p7.13">Instead he favoured gathering intelligence as a bargaining tool as well as for protection of the Czech population, an undetectable strategy of sabotaging German communications, and passive resistance of Czechs working for the Nazi war effort. </s><s n="s5.10;p7.13">However, aware that the communists had supported active resistance from the outset, and sensitive to their criticism of him, by February 1944 Beneš himself encouraged Czechs to directly oppose their occupiers. </s><s n="s6.10;p7.13">By August 1944 pressure from Moscow and London, Beneš was seriously advocating resistance in the Protectorate. </s><s n="s7.10;p7.13">Only when it was evident that the Reich would imminently collapse did he envisage the underground taking to the streets, seizing official positions and re-occupying the country. </s><s n="s8.10;p7.13">The final uprising for Prague lasted four days with 2,000 lives lost, in order to demonstrate that the Czechs did not intend to passively await liberation, which was, nonetheless, liberated by the Red Army on 9 May 1945. </s><s n="s9.10;p7.13">More than 50,000 Czechs were tortured or murdered during the occupation - far more than the government-in-exile had expected. </s><s n="s10.10;p7.13">Beneš was disturbingly willing to sacrifice Czech lives for his foreign policy aims. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0318f-ftnote.017"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Skilling, 'The National Liberation', 186. </s></p></note><p n="p8.13"><s n="s1.7;p8.13">On the other hand, Hàcha's main influence was on the experience of the Czech people inside the Protectorate during the occupation, rather than over international diplomatic issues. </s><s n="s2.7;p8.13">Charged by Beneš to keep the Czech people 'in as good condition, as possible',<ref target="BAWE_0318f-ftnote.018"/> Hàcha walked a political tightrope to protect the standard of living, property, and lives of the Czech people with some success. </s><s n="s3.7;p8.13">Hàcha's efforts were often, in fact, with the support of <hi rend="italic">Reichsprotektor</hi> Constantin von Neurath (in office 21 March 1939 - 24 August 1943). </s><s n="s4.7;p8.13">So arguably Neurath was the more successful protector of Czech lives than Hàcha. </s><s n="s5.7;p8.13">Neurath and Hàcha had a mutually respectful relationship, and Neurath where possible responded with compromise to some of the very numerous written and personal appeals to reduce the restriction of civil liberties, terrorism by Nazi organs, and to temper Germanisation policies.<ref target="BAWE_0318f-ftnote.019"/> Of course, there were other influential Nazis who overruled the Protectorate politicians. </s><s n="s6.7;p8.13">Head of the security apparatus K. H. </s><s n="s7.7;p8.13">Frank was the principal threat towards the Czech people for Hàcha during Neurath's time in office.<ref target="BAWE_0318f-ftnote.020"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0318f-ftnote.018"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Letter from Beneš to Hacha (30 November 1938). </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0318f-ftnote.019"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.6;pn1.1">For example, Hàcha met Neurath on 3 July 1940 to ensure that the Czechs would not be subject to military conscription for the Nazis. </s><s n="s2.6;pn1.1">Neurath was in full agreement with the sentiment, recognising the higher importance of Czech wartime production to the Reich. </s><s n="s3.6;pn1.1">(Aide-memoire of the President for a conversation Neurath and Hàcha (3 July 1941).) </s><s n="s4.6;pn1.1">Another example is when Hàcha wrote to Neurath on 13 September 1940 as part of a campaign against the introduction of German language rights in the Protectorate. </s><s n="s5.6;pn1.1">Neurath slightly compromises in his reply to Hàcha by agreeing that Czech language can be used first for administrative announcements in Czechs communes. </s><s n="s6.6;pn1.1">(Letters between Neurath and Hàcha (early September 1940).) </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0318f-ftnote.020"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.4;pn1.1">Almost from the outset, Hàcha and his colleagues in the Protectorate government knew that their lives were at risk with Frank in charge of security apparatus. </s><s n="s2.4;pn1.1">In a letter dated 23 August 1939, Frank made it clear that anti-German activity by Czechs 'will be prosecuted and punished by me with the greatest severity.' </s><s n="s3.4;pn1.1">This punishment was not for the individuals involved alone, but political, economic, and social leaders of the Czechs would be held ultimately responsible too. </s><s n="s4.4;pn1.1">(Letter from Frank to Hàcha (23 August 1939).) </s></p></note><p n="p9.13"><s n="s1.4;p9.13">Part of Hàcha's task involved keeping the favour of leading Nazis, and in this he excelled. </s><s n="s2.4;p9.13">By gaining their confidence, Hàcha was able to pressure them into treating Czechs more considerately. </s><s n="s3.4;p9.13">Hitler believed Hàcha to be a collaborator.<ref target="BAWE_0318f-ftnote.021"/> While appearing the collaborationist host to Goebbels during the propaganda minster's visit to Prague in November 1940, Hàcha at the same time appealed to him on behalf of the Czech people, complaining about the many arrests and the closure of the Prague university. </s><s n="s4.4;p9.13">Encouraged that Hàcha had taken him to his heart, Goebbels resolved to do what he could for the old man. <ref target="BAWE_0318f-ftnote.022"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0318f-ftnote.021"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">If the Czechs are treated with friendly consideration, 'all the Czechs will follow the lead of President Hàcha.' (Extract from Hermann Rauschning, <hi rend="italic">Hitler Speaks: a series of political conversations with Adolf Hitler on his real aims</hi> (London, 1939 [20 May 1942]). </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0318f-ftnote.022"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Extracts from Josef Goebbels, <hi rend="italic">The Goebbels Diaries, 1939-41</hi> (London, 1982 [7 November 1940 and 8 November 1940]). </s></p></note><p n="p10.13"><s n="s1.7;p10.13">Hàcha was a brave, and clever man to have achieved the successes above, and it seems grossly unfair to brand him as ineffectual, or as a collaborator with the Nazis. </s><s n="s2.7;p10.13">However, his efforts came under increasingly severe limitation by various Nazis and from Beneš himself. </s><s n="s3.7;p10.13">Hàcha's displays of loyalty to the Nazi regime do appear damning, but were enacted for fear for the lives of Czechs.<ref target="BAWE_0318f-ftnote.023"/> Each ostensibly pro-Nazi action acutely embarassed Beneš, and he threatened to break with Prague. </s><s n="s4.7;p10.13">Beneš was overly sensitive to the effect Hàcha's actions had on the Allies, and was unrealistically critical of Hàcha. </s><s n="s5.7;p10.13">Hàcha did consider the drastic move of resignation on several occassions during his time as president of the Protectorate. </s><s n="s6.7;p10.13">The first followed the Nazi response to the 28 October and 15 November 1939 student demonstrations. </s><s n="s7.7;p10.13">However, Frank made it clear that he would interpret such a move as provocation, and Neurath convinced him that his resignation would damage the Czech cause. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0318f-ftnote.023"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.3;pn1.1">Mastny cites the example of the Protectorate government's response to the fall of France. </s><s n="s2.3;pn1.1">They appeared in panic, and politicians apparently tried to outdo each other in gestures of loyalty, such as Hàcha's hospital train gift to the German Army, dismissal of the government's central committee and promise to reconstitute it with more "actively loyal" members, his offer to take the loyalty oath, and his 19 June radio speech congratulating German army successes. </s><s n="s3.3;pn1.1">(Mastny, <hi rend="italic">Czechs Under Nazi Rule</hi>, 157.) </s></p></note><p n="p11.13"><s n="s1.4;p11.13">However, the greatest obstacle to Hàcha securing concessions for the treatment of Czechs was Heydrich, who replaced Neurath in September 1941. </s><s n="s2.4;p11.13">Hàcha spent a great deal of energy convincing Heydrich that himself and his government colleagues were not part of the resistance, instead of devoting all his time to campaigning for the Czechs. </s><s n="s3.4;p11.13">Between late September and early October, many of his colleagues and friends were arrested (including the Prime Minister Alois Eliáš) and shot or sent to the concentration camps.<ref target="BAWE_0318f-ftnote.024"/> In the new climate of terror Hàcha not only risked his own life, but the probablity that the Nazis would simply dismiss the Protectorate government and leave nothing in their way to reign terror over the Czechs. </s><s n="s4.4;p11.13">Instead he embarked on a policy of collaboration, designed to spare the Czech people further bloodshed.<ref target="BAWE_0318f-ftnote.025"/> However, it should be noted that in Hàcha's response to Heydrich, he only pledged his and his government's sincere commitment to collaboration, <hi rend="italic">if</hi> Heydrich was supportive of important initiatives suggested by the government. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0318f-ftnote.024"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.15;pn1.1">In a conversation with Feierabend where Hàcha pledged his career if necessary to save his colleague, Hàcha alluded that he considered suicide, but religious belief prevented him. </s><s n="s2.15;pn1.1">Hàcha pledged to Feierabend that 'I shall stand up for you with all the strength I can [including resignation].' </s><s n="s3.15;pn1.1">Feierabend replied by emphasising that it was the President's duty to think of the fate of all Czechs and to forget about unfortunate individuals like. </s><s n="s4.15;pn1.1">Hàcha replied, 'How do I defend the nation if I do not defend its finest representatives'? </s><s n="s5.15;pn1.1">(Extracts from L. K. </s><s n="s6.15;pn1.1">Feierabend, <hi rend="italic">Political Memoirs</hi> (Prague, 1994).) </s><s n="s7.15;pn1.1">In addition, Hàcha was poised to resign after the arrest of Elias (arrested on 27 September 1941, a week after Heydrich's appointment). </s><s n="s8.15;pn1.1">However, on the same day that he would have sent the letter, (Letter from Hàcha to Hitler (unsent) (28 September 1941).) </s><s n="s9.15;pn1.1">Hàcha received word from Heydrich, who imposed martial law and made it clear that he expected the Protectorate government to redeem Elias' betrayl of the Nazis with more enthusiasm. </s><s n="s10.15;pn1.1">As a result of the discovery of Elias' double-game Heydrich wrote to Hàcha on 15 November 1941. </s><s n="s11.15;pn1.1">He confronted the president with precise evidence of his secret communications. </s><s n="s12.15;pn1.1">Hàcha responded in short on 17 November, dismissing his relationship with Borek-Dohalsky as being only vague. </s><s n="s13.15;pn1.1">He pretended ignorance as to whether the Count was going to communicate with London, and flatly denied meeting him at all. </s><s n="s14.15;pn1.1">This was a strong and defiant stance from Hàcha. </s><s n="s15.15;pn1.1">(Letters between Heydrich and Hàcha (from 28 September 1941).) </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0318f-ftnote.025"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">MacDonald, <hi rend="italic">Killing of Reinhard Heydrich</hi>, 115. </s></p></note><p n="p12.13"><s n="s1.7;p12.13">The situation worsened following the assassination of Heydrich. </s><s n="s2.7;p12.13">Hitler called Hàcha to the Reich Chancellory for Heydrich's memorial service and threatened the deportation of every Czech if there were any more anti-German acts. </s><s n="s3.7;p12.13">At this point Hàcha 'collapsed like a pricked balloon'. </s><s n="s4.7;p12.13">At the same meeting Hàcha and his colleagues promised to stamp out pro- Beneš activity. </s><s n="s5.7;p12.13">As a result of the meeting the president oversaw the arrangement of a huge rally where the organisers arranged an appeal for complete co-operation with the Third Reich. </s><s n="s6.7;p12.13">After Hitler surmised this attitude as being '100 per cent pro-German'.<ref target="BAWE_0318f-ftnote.026"/> Of course, this was a massive misjudgment and exaggeration, but it is clear that Hàcha's hands were now more tied than ever with regards to helping the Czech people. </s><s n="s7.7;p12.13">He could only strive to protect his colleagues such as Eliáš and Feierabend in the underground. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0318f-ftnote.026"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Extract from Rauschning, <hi rend="italic">Hitler Speaks</hi> [4 July 1942]. </s></p></note><p n="p13.13"><s n="s1.12;p13.13">In conclusion, Edvard Beneš and Emil Hàcha had the most unenviable of tasks during the Nazi occupation. </s><s n="s2.12;p13.13">Fighting for the survival of the republic and its people fell heavily on their responsibility. </s><s n="s3.12;p13.13">Beneš should be afforded greater admiration for his diplomatic skill and unrivalled contribution to the sheer existence of a post-war republic, but his eventual powerlessness towards the Soviet Union once the communists provided a viable alternative government to his exiled one, severely tempers the significance of his accomplishments. </s><s n="s4.12;p13.13">Meanwhile, Hàcha deserves more thanks from the Czech people for protecting their very lives in the immediacy. </s><s n="s5.12;p13.13">Beneš was, perhaps, too willing to sacrifice Czech people for a greater good, which did not come to pass. </s><s n="s6.12;p13.13">The Czechoslovak republic was relatively the most peaceful of the occupied territories throughout the war, and its population experienced a markedly higher living standard than the Reich itself. </s><s n="s7.12;p13.13">Yet, this had more to do with the population being so instrumental to war production for the Reich, rather that the ability of their president to temper Nazis. </s><s n="s8.12;p13.13">Perhaps Hàcha could have been more use to the Czech people if he had been more confrontational with the Nazis, but this would have been suicide - itself a message to international leaders, but one which they probably would not have reacted strongly too. </s><s n="s9.12;p13.13">His death would have been a symbolic martyrdom, but most probably a futile action, as he would have been replaced by someone even less irritant to the occupying regime, and therefore less of a protector of the Czech people. </s><s n="s10.12;p13.13">The author is ill-qualified to weigh Beneš and Hàcha's achievements against each other, but would argue if pushed that legal existence, even of many, can never carry more weight than the physical existence even of a few. </s><s n="s11.12;p13.13">It is so important to examine cases such the actions of Beneš and Hàcha because they are an interesting case of a sophisticated interaction between exiled and occupied government stuctures. </s><s n="s12.12;p13.13">More generally, inquiry raises fundamental moral questions about the politics of war, nations, and of humanity. </s></p></div1></body><back><div1 type="bibliography"><head rend="underlined bold">Bibliography</head><p>Feierabend, L. K., extracts from <hi rend="italic">Political Memoirs</hi> (Prague, 1994).</p><p>Goebbels, Josef, extracts from <hi rend="italic">The Goebbels Diaries, 1939-41</hi> (London, 1982 [7 November 1940, 8 November 1940, 15 May 1943]).</p><p>MacDonald, Callum, <hi rend="italic">The Killing of Reinhard Heydrich: The SS "Butcher of Prague"</hi> (New York, 1998).</p><p>Mastny, Vojtech, <hi rend="italic">The Czechs Under Nazi Rule: The Failure of National Resistance, 1939-42</hi> (New York, 1971).</p><p>Rauschning, Hermann, extracts from <hi rend="italic">Hitler Speaks: a series of political conversations with Adolf Hitler on his real aims</hi> (London, 1939 [23 January 1942, 20 May 1942, 4 July 1942]).</p><p>Skilling, H. Gordon, 'The National Liberation in World War II', <hi rend="italic">Slavonic and East European Review</hi>, 39 (Dec., 1960), pp. 174-197.</p><p>Smutný, Jaromir, extracts from his Diary [22 March 1940, 5 July 1943].</p><p>Taborsky, Edward, <hi rend="italic">President Edvard Beneš: Between East and West, 1938-48</hi> (Stanford, 1981).</p></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
