<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_0318d" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>The 'passionlessness' debate</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">deleted: header: student name, date; footer: assignment title, page numbers</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">3</p><p n="date">2005-11</p><p n="module title">Histories of Gender in the Americas</p><p n="module code">AM411</p><p n="genre family">Essay</p><p n="discipline">Comparative American Studies</p><p n="disciplinary group">AH</p><p n="grade">D</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">1553</p><p n="number of s-units">66</p><p n="number of p">11</p><p n="number of tables">0</p><p n="number of figures">0</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">0</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">0</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">23.5</p><p n="average s-units per p">6.0</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">f</p><p n="year of birth">1985</p><p n="first language">English</p><p n="education">UKA</p><p n="course">History</p><p n="student ID">0318</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><docTitle><titlePart> Histories of Gender in the Americas - Essay One</titlePart></docTitle></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="section"><p n="p1.11"><s n="s1.8;p1.11">The 'passionlessness' debate was initially a discourse in religious and medical circles about whether female sexual desire was natural or a moral issue. </s><s n="s2.8;p1.11">The debate was central to the gendered life of Americans - to men and women's spheres of work and family, and to the very nature of the male-female relationship. </s><s n="s3.8;p1.11">'Passionlessness' was initially an ideology created by men as a form of controlling women and thus society. </s><s n="s4.8;p1.11">Without economic or political independence, women could only manipulate the ideology to their best advantage rather than overturning it completely. </s><s n="s5.8;p1.11">The ideology meant that, 'middle-class women lost their association with lust and instead were invested with the quality of innate purity." </s><ref target="BAWE_0318d-ftnote.001"/><s n="s6.8;p1.11">In addition, 'passionlessness' did not just apply to pre-marital chastity, but was expected within marriage for the first time. </s><s n="s7.8;p1.11">The condition of 'passionlessness' in a woman, therefore, became the centrepiece to the ideal social unit - the family. </s><s n="s8.8;p1.11">The 'passionlessness' ideology was intrinsically linked with one side of the Cult of True Womanhood (the other side being that womanhood included a satisfying sexual relationship for husband and wife). <ref target="BAWE_0318d-ftnote.002"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0318d-ftnote.001"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">John D'Emilio, in John D'Emilio and Estelle Freedman, <hi rend="italic">Intimate Matters: A History of Sexuality in America</hi> (New York, 1997), 56. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0318d-ftnote.002"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Barbara Welter, 'The Cult of True Womanhood', <hi rend="italic">American Quarterly</hi>, 18 (Summer, 1966), pp. 151-174. </s></p></note><p n="p2.11"><s n="s1.7;p2.11">It was, principally, a self-imposed middle-class ideology, to differentiate themselves from decadent upper classes, and debauched lower classes, in keeping with their self image as the progressive element of American society. </s><s n="s2.7;p2.11">Yet, notions of women's sexuality were never monolithic. </s><s n="s3.7;p2.11">Not all middle class men or women favoured the ideology, and it manifested itself differently across the classes, and with respect to African-Americans. </s><s n="s4.7;p2.11">A critical analysis of the idea of 'passionlessness' will be offered in the following inquiry. </s><s n="s5.7;p2.11">It is vitally important to recognise that discourse until the 1970s has been constructed around public evangelical and medical debates, rather than private accounts of sexuality in nineteenth-century America, due to the lack of evidence on the sensitive subject. </s><s n="s6.7;p2.11">'Passionlessness', therefore, has been given more credence than it had in reality. </s><s n="s7.7;p2.11">There was also discourse, if to a lesser volume and emotive value, of the importance of male continence during the nineteenth century, but it is not possible to do justice to its contribution to the 'passionlessness' ideology here.<ref target="BAWE_0318d-ftnote.003"/> Whether 'passionlessness' was a liberating or repressive ideology for men and women, how it affected other classes and races in American society, and whether or not it actually existed will be addressed with reference to leading figures in past discourse. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0318d-ftnote.003"><p n="pn1.2"><s n="s1.2;pn1.2">John Humphrey Noyes, 'Male Continence: or, Self-control in Sexual Intercourse. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.2">A Letter of Enquiry Answered' (1866), Syracuse University Library Department of Special Collections Oneida Community Collection, 23 September 2003. </s></p><p n="pn2.2"><s n="s1.1;pn2.2">&lt;lib<seg type="URL" n="www.syr.edu/digital/collections/m/MaleContinence-15k/"/>> (16 October 2005) </s></p></note><p n="p3.11"><s n="s1.5;p3.11">The 'passionlessness' debate coincided with the Second Great Awakening, which began in the 1830s. </s><s n="s2.5;p3.11">A feature of the evangelical revival was that ideal Christian virtues and values came to be expected of women, who would in turn uplift the morality of men and therefore society as a whole. </s><s n="s3.5;p3.11">Physicians supported the evangelical condemnation of sexual excess from the point of view that it was detrimental to health - depriving men of their energy and women of their strength and sanity. </s><s n="s4.5;p3.11">Medical opinion was accepted as public opinion. </s><s n="s5.5;p3.11">As physicians wrote on the threat of 'nymphomaniac' women, male society was 'scared spermless' and so attempted to convince themselves that women were naturally 'passionless'.<ref target="BAWE_0318d-ftnote.004"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0318d-ftnote.004"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">For and amusing and informative account of a common male attitude to female sexual aggressiveness, see Ben Barker-Benfield, 'The Spermatic Economy: A Nineteenth Century View of Sexuality', <hi rend="italic">Feminist Studies</hi>, 1 (Summer, 1972), pp. 45-74. </s></p></note><p n="p4.11"><s n="s1.7;p4.11">Nancy Cott is an advocate that 'passionlessness' was a liberating ideology for women. </s><s n="s2.7;p4.11">She convincingly argues that women used their image as 'passionless' to take advantage of new opportunities.<ref target="BAWE_0318d-ftnote.005"/> 'Passionlessness served women's larger interests by downplaying altogether their sexual characterisation, which was the cause of their exclusion from significant "human" pursuits." </s><ref target="BAWE_0318d-ftnote.006"/><s n="s3.7;p4.11">She asserts that women drew great self-confidence from believing themselves to be more Godly, moral, and intellectual than men. </s><s n="s4.7;p4.11">However, Cott does acknowledge that 'passionlessness' protected women from vulnerability and dependence, but did not provide them with full autonomy. </s><s n="s5.7;p4.11">Women might have benefited in the marriage market by emphasising their purity and so improved their social and economic prospects, but they were still constrained to behave towards the will of men, and marry for physical survival. </s><s n="s6.7;p4.11">Yet, figures such as Mary Wollstonecraft emphasised women's moral <hi rend="italic">and</hi> intellectual power. </s><s n="s7.7;p4.11">By invoking 'passionlessness', women would be taken more seriously in the future in the movement for suffrage, which would finally liberate women from dependence on men, and having to resort to 'passionlessness' for protection. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0318d-ftnote.005"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Cott, 'Passionlessness: An Interpretation of Victorian Sexual Ideology, 1790-1850', <hi rend="italic">Signs</hi>, 4 (Winter, 1978), 228. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0318d-ftnote.006"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Cott, 'Passionlessness', 228. </s></p></note><p n="p5.11"><s n="s1.3;p5.11">Furthermore, Daniel Scott Smith's theory of domestic feminism, used to avoid unwanted sexual advances, and most importantly limit family size, was a significant advantage of complying with the ideology. </s><s n="s2.3;p5.11">Sisterly love over matrimonial love may have brought some advantages, but surely none as great as a union of love and respect in marriage. </s><s n="s3.3;p5.11">In any case, sisterly love hardly crossed class or racial divides for middle class women. </s></p><p n="p6.11"><s n="s1.4;p6.11">However, 'passionlessness' essentially denied women the capacity to need or desire pleasurable sex, and so was an overwhelmingly repressive ideology for women. </s><s n="s2.4;p6.11">Moral double standards for the sexes were enshrined in laws which excused man's adultery, and were supported by willing doctors who performed horrendous operations in attempts to reduce women's sexual desires. </s><s n="s3.4;p6.11">Medical attempts to enforce 'passionlessness' were perhaps the most disturbing manifestation of social will to uphold the ideology, and were the ultimate proof that natural 'passionlessness' did not exist.<ref target="BAWE_0318d-ftnote.007"/> For all their defence of happiness and family, crusading surgeons deprived thousands of women of the chance to have children, as well as sexual pleasure. </s><s n="s4.4;p6.11">The 'passionlessness' ideal subordinated a woman's free will to serving God before her marriage, and her husband afterwards, and also could wreak physical damage on her body. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0318d-ftnote.007"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.3;pn1.1">While exclusively male doctors usually treated men with advice, their ignorance of understanding the female condition and support for a 'passionless' social order themselves, meant that they were proud in an era of primitive anaesthetics and lack of knowledge of antiseptics to physically attack female genitalia. </s><s n="s2.3;pn1.1">Clitoridotomy (the removal or splitting of the clitoral hood) reached America from Britain in the late 1850s and was used until as late as 1925 to control female sexual urges. </s><s n="s3.3;pn1.1">Castration (the removal of ovaries) was used from the 1870s. </s></p></note><p n="p7.11"><s n="s1.4;p7.11">'Passionlessness' ideology can be used to analyse the experience of lower class women too. </s><s n="s2.4;p7.11">In poverty these women were forced to live with little dignity, and one way that they could raise themselves above the rest was to conform to the 'passionlessness' ideology. </s><s n="s3.4;p7.11">Middle-class ideologues did not attribute lower class women with much effort in this direction, however. </s><s n="s4.4;p7.11">Yet, the fact they continued to perceive these women as licentious, actually undermined any argument that women were naturally 'passionless'. </s></p><p n="p8.11"><s n="s1.10;p8.11">Similarly, as white society believed African-American men and women to be highly sexual, both in slavery and after, they further undermined the universal 'passionlessness' condition of women. </s><s n="s2.10;p8.11">'Southern gender conventions notoriously treated black women as special inferiors, but they also discriminated among white women of different classes." </s><ref target="BAWE_0318d-ftnote.008"/><s n="s3.10;p8.11">Black women lived with the threat their master believed himself to have a right to sexual relations with any slave of his choosing. </s><s n="s4.10;p8.11">As Harriet Jacobs did, a female slave could behave as 'passionless' to protect herself. </s><s n="s5.10;p8.11">But they faced a dilemma because the master could improve their circumstances if they complied. </s><s n="s6.10;p8.11">To a notable extent, however, both slave masters and slave communities had respected the institution of the slave family since the abolition of the slave trade in 1808. </s><s n="s7.10;p8.11">Without the slave family institution, the entire system of slavery would have expired. </s><s n="s8.10;p8.11">In any case, 'passionlessness' did not have the same relevance to slaves. </s><s n="s9.10;p8.11">African heritage was not critical of pre-marital sex, and valued stable, loving, and sexual unions. </s><s n="s10.10;p8.11">Slave women used (often feigned) pregnancy as resistance to work, and only had use for 'passionlessness' to avoid the wandering eye of their master. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0318d-ftnote.008"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Elizabeth Fox-Genovese, <hi rend="italic">Within the Plantation Household: Black and White Women of the Old South</hi>, (Chapel Hill, 1988), 202. </s></p></note><p n="p9.11"><s n="s1.4;p9.11">Although medical debates initially provided 'evidence' that women were naturally, or should be, 'passionless', medical thought more strongly denied the existence of 'passionlessness' at all. </s><s n="s2.4;p9.11">In addition to the industry of neutering 'excessively' sexual women, 'abundant anti-masturbation literature, aimed at "women of all classes", contradicted the notion of innate purity." </s><ref target="BAWE_0318d-ftnote.009"/><s n="s3.4;p9.11">In fact, any medical discourse discussing 'excessive' female sexual desire, contraception, or abortion, innately undermined notions that women were 'naturally' 'passionlessness'. </s><s n="s4.4;p9.11">The gynaecologist reducing a woman to an extension of her reproductive organs completely defeated the validity of women as 'passionless'. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0318d-ftnote.009"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">D'Emilio, in <hi rend="italic">Intimate Matters</hi>, 71. </s></p></note><p n="p10.11"><s n="s1.8;p10.11">Rather than discussing whether or not women were, or should have been, 'passionless', revisionist discourse since the 1970s has been inspired by evidence along the lines of Clelia Mosher's (1863-1940) work for example. </s><s n="s2.8;p10.11">Writing has focused on criticising the 'passionlessness' industry, and defeating its logic as being in no way representative of real sexual behaviour. </s><s n="s3.8;p10.11">Mosher conducted perhaps the first survey of female sexual habits. </s><s n="s4.8;p10.11">Although the sample group consisted of only 45 women, who were from middle-class, educated backgrounds, she provided convincing evidence that most women had sexual appetites, and that husbands, in fact, complained if their wives were 'passionless'. </s><s n="s5.8;p10.11">Similarly, Karen Lystra, using letters as her evidence, proposed that nineteenth-century women believed that passion in a loving relationship was acceptable. </s><s n="s6.8;p10.11">Sex was even acceptable and usually practiced upon engagement. </s><s n="s7.8;p10.11">'Middle-class American women gave no private indication that they believed in an ideal of female passionlessness." </s><ref target="BAWE_0318d-ftnote.010"/><s n="s8.8;p10.11">She undermines Cott's thesis that women used 'passionlessness' at all. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0318d-ftnote.010"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Karen Lystra, 'Sexuality in Victorian Courtship and Marriage', in Kathy Peiss (ed.), <hi rend="italic">Major Problems in the History of American Sexuality</hi> (Boston, 2002), 229. </s></p></note><p n="p11.11"><s n="s1.6;p11.11">In conclusion, the strong ideology of 'passionlessness' is still present in the historical imagination of nineteenth-century America today. </s><s n="s2.6;p11.11">Yet, 'passionlessness' was only a prescriptive ideology, in evangelical, some medical, and polite middle-class society discourse, largely for middle-class women. </s><s n="s3.6;p11.11">It was not universal, and did not accurately reflect real behaviour. </s><s n="s4.6;p11.11">'Passionlessness' may have been an ideal to some 'scared' men, and socially oppressed but ambitious women, but the evidence proves that men and women simply preferred to have sex throughout the nineteenth century, as they always had done, and were only mindful of creating an image of self-control. </s><s n="s5.6;p11.11">Women were more materially concerned with avoiding pregnancy. </s><s n="s6.6;p11.11">In fact, far from being 'passionless', 'evidence of behavioural change strongly suggests that the procreative function of sex declined over the century'.<ref target="BAWE_0318d-ftnote.011"/> The 'reform' backlash to this phenomenon in the 1880s, which suppressed birth control information, condemned adultery, criminalised abortion, and curbed prostitution, literally proved the inaccuracy of a belief in 'passionless' behaviour to all. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0318d-ftnote.011"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Estelle B. Freedman, 'Sexuality in Nineteenth-Century America: Behaviour, Ideology, and Politics', <hi rend="italic">Reviews in American History</hi>, 10 (Dec., 1982), 201. </s></p></note></div1></body><back><div1 type="bibliography"><head rend="underlined bold">Bibliography</head><p>Barker-Benfield, G.J., 'The Spermatic Economy: A Nineteenth Century View of Sexuality', <hi rend="italic">Feminist Studies</hi>, 1 (Summer, 1972), pp. 45-74.</p><p>Cott, Nancy F., 'Passionlessness: An Interpretation of Victorian Sexual Ideology, 1790-1850', <hi rend="italic">Signs</hi>, 4 (Winter, 1978), pp. 219-236. </p><p>D'Emilio, John and Estelle Freedman, <hi rend="italic">Intimate Matters: A History of Sexuality in America</hi> (New York, 1997). </p><p>Degler, Carl N., 'What Ought to be and What Was: Women's Sexuality in the Nineteenth Century', in <hi rend="italic">The American Historical Review</hi>, 79 (Dec., 1974), pp. 1467-1490.</p><p>Fox-Genovese, Elizabeth, <hi rend="italic">Within the Plantation Household: Black and White Women of the Old South</hi>, (Chapel Hill, 1988).</p><p>Freedman, Estelle B., 'Sexuality in Nineteenth-Century America: Behaviour, Ideology, and Politics', <hi rend="italic">Reviews in American History</hi>, 10 (Dec., 1982), pp. 196-215.</p><p>Logue, Barbara J., 'The Case for Birth Control before 1850: Nantucket Re-examined', <hi rend="italic">Journal of Interdisciplinary History</hi>, 15 (Winter, 1985), pp. 371-391.</p><p>Lystra, Karen, 'Sexuality in Victorian Courtship and Marriage', in Kathy Peiss (ed.), <hi rend="italic">Major Problems in the History of American Sexuality</hi> (Boston, 2002).</p><p>Noyes, John Humphrey, 'Male Continence: or, Self-control in Sexual Intercourse. A Letter of Enquiry Answered' (1866), Syracuse University Library Department of Special Collections Oneida Community Collection, 23 September 2003. </p><p>&lt;lib<seg type="URL" n="www.syr.edu/digital/collections/m/MaleContinence-15k/"/>> (16 October 2005)</p><p>Rosenberg, Charles E., 'Sexuality, Class and Role in 19<hi rend="sup">th</hi>-Century America', <hi rend="italic">American Quarterly</hi>, 25 (May, 1973), pp. 131-153.</p><p>Welter, Barbara, 'The Cult of True Womanhood', <hi rend="italic">American Quarterly</hi>, 18 (Summer, 1966), pp. 151-174.</p></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
