<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_0320h" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>What accounts for the differences in offending between girls and boys?</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">deleted: header: assignment title, student name, date; footer: page numbers</note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">deleted: <name type="student name"/>
November 2005
</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">3</p><p n="date">2005-05</p><p n="module title">Youth and Society</p><p n="module code">SO329</p><p n="genre family">Essay</p><p n="discipline">Sociology</p><p n="disciplinary group">SS</p><p n="grade">M</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">1640</p><p n="number of s-units">60</p><p n="number of p">6</p><p n="number of tables">0</p><p n="number of figures">0</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">0</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">0</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">27.3</p><p n="average s-units per p">10.0</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">f</p><p n="year of birth">1958</p><p n="first language">English</p><p n="education">UKA</p><p n="course">Sociology</p><p n="student ID">0320</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><docTitle><titlePart rend="bold">What accounts for the differences in offending between girls and boys? </titlePart></docTitle></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="section"><p n="p1.6"><s n="s1.4;p1.6">Despite claims that as much as 40% of all crime is committed by under 21 year olds (Muncie 1999 in Worrall and Hoy 2004 :177) the split between crimes committed by boys and girls is far from equal. </s><s n="s2.4;p1.6">The proportion of boys committing and being sentenced for crime far outweighs the number of girls. </s><s n="s3.4;p1.6">In 1999, whilst a quarter of young men had offended, only one in 10 young women had (Flood-Page et al 1998/1999 :55). </s><s n="s4.4;p1.6">In the past this differentiation as been unrecognised, but more recently research has attempted to explain what accounts for the differences in offending between girls and boys. </s></p><p n="p2.6"><s n="s1.5;p2.6">In this essay I argue that there are differences in offending patterns between girls and boys and these result from gender based influences (impact of attitudes) rather than differences in sex (biological aspects) (Heidensohn 1989 :88). </s><s n="s2.5;p2.6">The evidence to support this argument is split into three categories. </s><s n="s3.5;p2.6">Firstly, different attitudes to bringing up boys and girls - boys are allowed to be boys (Worrall and Hoy 2004:190), whist girls must conform to models of femininity (Hudson in Cain 1989 :197). </s><s n="s4.5;p2.6">Secondly, this leads to differences in offending patterns; with more and more serious crime being committed by boys than girls (National Statistics Office website 2005 :1). </s><s n="s5.5;p2.6">Finally, that the justice system enforces double standards on girls, punishing them not only for their crime, but also for breaching morality rules (Campbell 1981 :4) or refusing to take on a subservient woman's role (Hudson in Cain 1989:206/7) and may be more harshly treated (Chesney-Lind and Pasko 2004). </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Apples and pears</head><p n="p3.6"><s n="s1.10;p3.6">Prior to 1960 differences in male and female offending patterns were not considered and therefore girls were both in criminal research as well as the justice system (Hudson 1990 :116, Kersten in Cain 1989 :129, Chesney-Lind and Pasko 2004 :3, Summer 1990). </s><s n="s2.10;p3.6">Surprising findings have emerged in research since that time. </s><s n="s3.10;p3.6">The most dramatic of these is in offending rates between the two groups. </s><s n="s4.10;p3.6">The Home Office reports that in 2002 four out of five crimes were committed by "men and that male offenders outnumbered female offenders by more than four to one" (National Statistics Office website 2005 :1). </s><s n="s5.10;p3.6">It is clear then that young men are more likely to engage in criminal activity than young women. </s><s n="s6.10;p3.6">There is also a difference in the types of crime committed by the two groups. </s><s n="s7.10;p3.6">Boys are more likely to engage in petty theft, vandalism, football hooliganism, mugging and riot behaviour (Muncie 1989 :62) whilst for girls 'crimes' are more likely to include running away from home, breaking curfew rules and unruly behaviour (Chesney-Lind and Pasko 2004 :3). </s><s n="s8.10;p3.6">Theft remains the common crime between the two groups, being the highest offence committed by both groups (National Statistics Office 2005 :2). </s><s n="s9.10;p3.6">This evidence shows a clear difference between the rates and types of crime committed by girls and boys. </s><s n="s10.10;p3.6">Having established this the question of what accounts for these differing offending patterns needs investigation. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Boys will be boys</head><p n="p4.6"><s n="s1.12;p4.6">From an early age children are brought up to hear messages that will define the way they act in later years. </s><s n="s2.12;p4.6">The swashbuckling hero image applied to rebellious young men does not apply to young women (Hudson 1990 in Gelshorpe and Morris :118). </s><s n="s3.12;p4.6">Moreover, young men may actually live up to the widespread image of high youth criminality by being or becoming criminally active (Flood-Page et al 1989/99 :55). </s><s n="s4.12;p4.6">For girls, the opposite is true, the emphasis is on protection (Hudson 89 :197) and the policing of young women's behaviour (Cox 03 :166) to ensure they remain 'respectable and decent' and not become 'promiscuous and dangerous' (Hudson in Cain 1989 :211). </s><s n="s5.12;p4.6">Girls who fight against gender roles, either by running away from family or institutions or attempting suicide to escape the reinforcement of patriarchal influences, are labelled deviant. </s><s n="s6.12;p4.6">(Kersten 1989 in Cain :137). </s><s n="s7.12;p4.6">Ironically, girls are more likely to be offended against than to offend (Petrie 1988), being at risk from violent or sexual attacks upon them by the male population (Cox 2003:10). </s><s n="s8.12;p4.6">The violent behaviour of female street gangs is explained by Worrall and Hoy (2004:189) as resulting from violence they have already received during their lives. </s><s n="s9.12;p4.6">The impact of these attitudes creates a clear difference in the perceived threat from young offenders. </s><s n="s10.12;p4.6">Whilst it is the public who are seen in need of protection from boys' disruptive behaviour, it is the girls themselves who are seen to be in need of protection, especially upon reaching puberty (Petrie 1988). </s><s n="s11.12;p4.6">Different attitudes towards bringing up girls and boys therefore affect societal perceptions overall. </s><s n="s12.12;p4.6">Girls and boys are treated differently throughout their lives including when they have (or are perceived to have) offended and enter the justice system. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Men on top</head><p n="p5.6"><s n="s1.21;p5.6">There is much agreement among feminist researchers that many of society's rules are made by men wanting to retain power over women's behaviour (Campbell 1981 :4, Cox 2003 :10) and when it comes to the justice system, women are therefore judged by men's ideas about how women <hi rend="italic">should</hi> behave (Campbell 1981 :4, Cox 2003 :5, Hudson 1990 :, Kersten in Cain 1989 :129). </s><s n="s2.21;p5.6">With such a male predominance, models of delinquent behaviour are based on male behaviour (Taylor et al 1997 :*), which results in a lack of understanding of girls' behaviour when they enter the justice system. </s><s n="s3.21;p5.6">The application of male models of delinquent behaviour to females impacts upon the resultant treatment in several ways. </s><s n="s4.21;p5.6">When it comes to girls offending, their actions are not divorced from their sexual behaviour. </s><s n="s5.21;p5.6">In expressing their femininity, adolescent girls are in danger of being labelled 'slag or drag' (Worrall and Hoy 2004 :189) - and the line between the two is very fine. </s><s n="s6.21;p5.6">Girls are therefore not only judged for their crime, but for their deviance from moral behaviour (Campbell 1981 :4) and may be treated more harshly as a result of this application of double standards (Chesney-Lind and Pasko 2004 :62, Nacro 2001 :1). </s><s n="s7.21;p5.6">This fixation with female sexuality judges that young women who engage in intercourse are considered immoral, therefore deviant and in need of correction (Chesney-Lind 2004 :60). </s><s n="s8.21;p5.6">The same judgements do not apply to boys, either in the justice or social work systems (Hudson 1990). </s><s n="s9.21;p5.6">As a result the sentences handed out to boys and girls will vary. </s><s n="s10.21;p5.6">Boys who become disruptive are seen in need of punishment and will be sent to residential establishments at an early age, girls are more likely to be sent once they reach puberty, for protection (Petrie 1988) or correction. </s><s n="s11.21;p5.6">However, despite this appearance of more lenient treatment of girls (Worrall and Hoy 2004), the rules applied are likely to be harsher for girls than boys; with boys being allowed more time for physical activities and girls predominantly undertaking domestic chores (Kersten in Cain 1989 :131). </s><s n="s12.21;p5.6">This pattern can be explained by the less serious nature of crimes girls commit and that they are less likely to have previous convictions (Nacro 2001:3). </s><s n="s13.21;p5.6">The application of double standards is more likely to be detrimental to the treatment of girl offenders (Campbell 1981). </s><s n="s14.21;p5.6">More recently, consideration of girls as a separate category within the justice system is even less likely. </s><s n="s15.21;p5.6">Moral panics about increasing female violence and changes in legislation (1998 secure training act) are leading to a move away from measures to protect girls and towards assigning them to the same categories as violent men (Worrall and Hoy 2004 :190). </s><s n="s16.21;p5.6">Interesting figures show how despite falling levels of crime, there is an increase in the number of girls entering the justice system (Worrall and Hoy 2004 :191). </s><s n="s17.21;p5.6">Nacro identify crime levels for girls rose between 1992-1999 by nearly 2,500, plus an increase over boys offending by 2% (2001 :02). </s><s n="s18.21;p5.6">However there is a marked reduction of nearly 9,000 in the level of cautions (Nacro 2001 :02). </s><s n="s19.21;p5.6">So the impact of changing attitudes and legislation stand to disadvantage girl offenders to a greater extent than offending boys. </s><s n="s20.21;p5.6">It must be born in mind that the interpretation of statistics will vary and this can account for reporting differences in offending between girls and boys. </s><s n="s21.21;p5.6">Statistics fail to provide in depth information and can often raise more questions than they answer (Campbell 1981 :3). </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Conclusion</head><p n="p6.6"><s n="s1.8;p6.6">In this essay I have shown a clear difference between patterns of offending between girls and boys (National Statistics Office website 2005 :1), not only in the higher incidence of offences committed by boys than girls, but also in the seriousness of the crimes. </s><s n="s2.8;p6.6">This difference in attitudes follows through into the pattern of offending, whilst for boys criminal activity is seen as a part of growing up and 'maleness' and results in them committing more crime of a more serious nature. </s><s n="s3.8;p6.6">Whilst for girls, lower rates of less serious criminal offences result, reinforcing the attitude that girls should be good and reinforce the idea that girls who fight against these attitudes are deviant. </s><s n="s4.8;p6.6">Differences in attitudes between bringing up girls and boys set the early pattern for acceptable and non-acceptable behaviour (Worrall and Hoy 2004 :189, Campbell 1981 :4, Hudson in Cain 1989: 197) that are based on societal perceptions, rather than any biological difference (Heidenshohn 1989 :88). </s><s n="s5.8;p6.6">When entering the justice system, there are clear differences in the treatment of girls and boys. </s><s n="s6.8;p6.6">Girls will be subjected to double standards - being guilty of their crime and deviance from moral standards (Chesney-Lind and Pasko 2004 :61, Nacro 2001 :1). </s><s n="s7.8;p6.6">The result has been different sentencing for girls to boys, although worryingly, more recent research shows an increase in the number of girls entering the justice system, despite falling levels of crime committed by them (Nacro 2001 :2). </s><s n="s8.8;p6.6">Different attitudes towards how girls and boys should act account for different offending patterns and the treatment young offenders receive; it has nothing to do with biological differences. </s></p></div1></body><back><div1 type="bibliography"><head rend="bold">References</head><p>Campbell, A (1981) <hi rend="italic">Girl Delinquents</hi>, Basil Blackwell, Oxford</p><p>Chesney-Lind, M and Pasko, L (2004) <hi rend="italic">The Female Offender - Girls, Women and Crime,</hi> Sage, London</p><p>Cox, P (2003) <hi rend="italic">Gender, Justice and Welfare: bad girls in Britain 1900-1950,</hi> Palgrave McMillan, New York</p><p>Flood-Page, C, Campbell, S, Harrington V, and Miller J <hi rend="italic">Youth Crime : Findings from 1989/99 Youth Lifestyle Survey,</hi> Home Office, London</p><p>Heidensohn, F (1989) <hi rend="italic">Crime and Society,</hi> MacMillan, Basingstoke</p><p>Hudson, A (1990) 'Elusive Subjects: Researching Young Women in Trouble, in Gelshorpe L and Morris A (eds), <hi rend="italic">Feminist Perspectives in Criminology,</hi> OUP</p><p>Hudson, A (1989) 'Troublesome Girls :Towards alternative definitions of policies' in Cain, M (ed), <hi rend="italic">Growing up Good, policing the behaviour for girls in Europe</hi> Sage, London</p><p>Kersten, J 'The institutional controlof girls and boys, an attempt at a gender-specific approach' in Cain, M (ed), <hi rend="italic">Growing up Good, policing the behaviour for girls in Europe</hi> Sage, London</p><p>NACRO (2001) 'Girls in the Justice System', <hi rend="italic">Youth Crime Briefing</hi>, October 2001</p><p>National Statistics Office website - <seg type="URL" n="www.statistics.gov.uk/CCI"/> </p><p>Muncie, J (1984) <hi rend="italic">The Trouble with Kiths Today, youth crime in post-war Britain,</hi> Hutchinson, London</p><p>Petrie, C (1988) <hi rend="italic">The Nowhere Girls</hi>, Gower, Aldershot</p><p>Summer, C, (1990) 'Foucault, gender and the censure of deviance' in Gelshorpe L and Morris A (eds), <hi rend="italic">Feminist Perspectives in Criminology,</hi> OUP</p><p>Taylor, DL, Biafora Jnr, FA, Warheit, G and Gil (1998) A 'Family Factors, Theft, Vandalism and Major Deviance Among Multiracial/Multiethnic Sample of Adolescent Girls' <hi rend="italic">Journal of Social Distress and Homeless</hi>, vol 6, no 1</p><p>Worrall A, and Hoy, C (2004) <hi rend="italic">Punishment in the community - managing offenders, making choices,</hi> Willan, Cullampton</p></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
