<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_0320j" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Hebdige was a member of the Centre for Contemporary Cultural Studies, University of Birmingham (CCCs) during the 1970s, who challenged the entrenched view of youth as trouble or in trouble</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">deleted: header: assignment title, student number, date; footer: page numbers
</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">3</p><p n="date">2006-05</p><p n="module title">Youth and Society</p><p n="module code">SO329</p><p n="genre family">Essay</p><p n="discipline">Sociology</p><p n="disciplinary group">SS</p><p n="grade">M</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">4430</p><p n="number of s-units">128</p><p n="number of p">17</p><p n="number of tables">0</p><p n="number of figures">0</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">0</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">0</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">34.6</p><p n="average s-units per p">7.5</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">f</p><p n="year of birth">1958</p><p n="first language">English</p><p n="education">UKA</p><p n="course">Sociology</p><p n="student ID">0320</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><docTitle><titlePart>Hebdige's proposition that youth is only present in society when its' presence is a problem </titlePart></docTitle></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="section"><p n="p1.17"><s n="s1.8;p1.17">Hebdige was a member of the Centre for Contemporary Cultural Studies, University of Birmingham (CCCs) during the 1970s, who challenged the entrenched view of youth as trouble or in trouble (Hebdige 1988:27; Muncie 1999:249; Griffin 1993:108; Malbon 1999:13) or a problem to society and themselves (Muncie 1999:9, Griffin 1993:101) and deviancy theory that is, behaviour different from considered 'norms' usually constructed by the middle classes (Griffin 1997A:23). </s><s n="s2.8;p1.17">CCCs research created the subculture theory that went beyond the focus of youthful rebellion purely as a means of resistance (Downes and Rock 2003:143) and argued that youth, using dress, style or music, challenged the parent culture (Hebdige 1988:30) in an effort not only to be heard, but as a way of bringing some control and meaning to their lives 'in a modern industrialised society' (Hebdige 1988 :31). </s><s n="s3.8;p1.17">However, it is important to note that these studies focused on working-class young men (Griffin 1993:100; Muggleton, cited in Bennett and Kahn-Harris 2004:7) with the assumption that it is <hi rend="italic">they</hi> who are the 'problem'. </s><s n="s4.8;p1.17">Labelling theory (Lemert 1967, cited in Griffin 1993:109) influenced studies of criminology during the 1970s and supports the concept that stereotyping increases rather than reduces criminal offending (Becker 1963, cited in Muncie 1999:307; Hebdige 1988). </s><s n="s5.8;p1.17">It is not necessarily the behaviour itself that attracts the label, but the reaction of, or interaction with, other societal groups that therefore determine levels of deviancy (Cohen S 1972:283). </s><s n="s6.8;p1.17">This CCCs argument therefore reinforces labelling theory (Downes and Rock 2003:143) in that behaviour is influenced by judgments applied by powerful bodies over the less powerful (Muncie 1999:118). </s><s n="s7.8;p1.17">Over the last few decades, youth subcultures have become more flexible in their consumption of style, music and experiences, but arguably continue to attract a negative image, particularly from the media. </s><s n="s8.8;p1.17">Hebdige argues young people are predominantly portrayed in a negative light, and this negative stereotypical image is so widely accepted it overlooks any suggestion that this may not be an accurate reflection of young people. </s></p><p n="p2.17"><s n="s1.8;p2.17">In this essay, I will use moral panics and youth subculture and post-subculture theories as a basis for supporting Hebdige's proposition 'that [....] youth is only present when its presence is a problem, or regarded as a problem (1988:17; Hebdige 1983:402). </s><s n="s2.8;p2.17">However, I will firstly explore overwhelming evidence that portrays young people in a negative light; arguing that once negative labels are applied they are difficult to remove and are widely accepted as the truth (Muncie 1999:13). </s><s n="s3.8;p2.17">My arguments will focus on two aspects. </s><s n="s4.8;p2.17">Firstly, that negative labels are used by the media to create moral panics that influence public opinion and result in more restraining action being placed upon young people who are perceived to be a problem (UK Youth Parliament 2005:5). </s><s n="s5.8;p2.17">Secondly, that youth subcultures created by young people challenge class and/or parent domination (Garratt 1997:143) in their search for their own space and recognition of their existence. </s><s n="s6.8;p2.17">Young people's actions and behaviours are misunderstood by the adult world (Muncie 1999:119), as the 'truth' is so embedded in people's minds and society. </s><s n="s7.8;p2.17">Therefore, the only starting point of any contact with young people is from the view of them being a problem. </s><s n="s8.8;p2.17">Within the context of moral panics and subculture theory it is important to understand something about how young people are labelled in negative terms, as this forms the basis from which moral panics escalate and compound the portrayal of young people, and in particular youth subcultures, in a negative light. </s></p><p n="p3.17"><s n="s1.8;p3.17">'Youth' usually refers to young men and carries negative connotations of 'trouble' (Jeffs and Smith 1998/9:46), 'problem' (Jeffs and Smith 1998/9:46, Kelly 2000:301, Hebdige 1983 in Gelder and Thornton 1997:402), 'crime' (BBC News 2004:1, Jeffs and Smith 1998/9:49) or 'deficiency' (Jeffs and Smith 1998/9:45). </s><s n="s2.8;p3.17">The Chicago School's (America), work during the 1920s, formed the basis (Hebdige 1983:400) of discourses during the 1950/60s in which young people were seen as instigators of trouble for example football hooliganism (Hebdige 1979:133; Griffin 1997A:17; Hall 1978:34, cited in Muncie 1999:122) or at risk from trouble for example teenage pregnancy (Griffin 1997A:17). </s><s n="s3.8;p3.17">The problem of youth is debated in terms of attitude or actions that challenge the parent culture for example truancy, dress styles or, in particular, music - which causes the most friction between young people and adults (Thornton 1995:204; Cohen P 1972:95). </s><s n="s4.8;p3.17">In terms of youth crime, reports show a plethora of contradictory evidence for example 'police records show a 1% increase with a 12% jump in violent crime, during the past year. </s><s n="s5.8;p3.17">However, ... the British Crime Survey says crime has fallen 5% on the same period' (BBC News 2006:1). </s><s n="s6.8;p3.17">Statistical information can be misinterpreted or exaggerated and present difficulties in interpretation, as in this case, distinguishing between terms for 'serious' or 'prolific' behaviour, which have been consolidated into one category (Travis 2005:1). </s><s n="s7.8;p3.17">Furthermore, statistics fail to provide explanations for example in the case of higher crime rates and reducing numbers of offenders, persistent offenders <hi rend="italic">might</hi> be responsible for a larger percentage of crime (Farrington 2002:425). </s><s n="s8.8;p3.17">In terms of deficiency, young people are always seen as in need of training or improving (Jeffs and Smith 1998/9:45; Furlong and Carmet 1997:41, cited in Muncie 1999:3; Griffin 1993:115). </s></p><p n="p4.17"><s n="s1.10;p4.17">The period between of development between childhood and adulthood has long been recognised as one of 'storm and stress' (G Hall 1900, cited in Griffin 1997B:19; Jeffs and Smith 1998/9:50). </s><s n="s2.10;p4.17">Foucault suggests that the lack of control experienced during the physiological changes in adolescence can overspill into unpredictable or uncontrollable behaviour (cited in Raby 2005:162). </s><s n="s3.10;p4.17">Intrinsic to young people is their lack of past experience which can mean instability and this 'shaky ground' may threaten to unsettle the more stable environment of adults (Raby 2005:168). </s><s n="s4.10;p4.17">This categorisation of young people's 'deviant' behaviour will be seen as a reason for increased regulation, to bring these groups back in line with what is considered the 'norm' (Jeffs and Smith 1998/9:311). </s><s n="s5.10;p4.17">However, who labels who is disconcerting as it is usually middle class adult views that are considered as the norm - white, male, middle class, heterosexual, able bodied (non-disabled) (Griffin 1997A:23). </s><s n="s6.10;p4.17">Any comparison will be problematic in terms of age as well as ethnicity, gender, class, sexual orientation or disability. </s><s n="s7.10;p4.17">As a result, feminists argue that women have either been ignored by research (Malbon 1999:14) or afforded the same delinquent traits as men (Griffin 1993:110). </s><s n="s8.10;p4.17">Furthermore, certain societal groups can become the stereotypical scapegoat of all that is wrong in society for example the 'black mugger' during the 1970s (Hall et al 1978, cited in Muncie 1999:122; Gilroy 2002:50) when major adverse social changes occurred (Hunt 1997:631) such as mass unemployment in the 1970/80s (Downes and Rock 2003:161). </s><s n="s9.10;p4.17">Evidence therefore supports the perception of youth as trouble or a problem, without any justification. </s><s n="s10.10;p4.17">Finding the way to adulthood is a complex and diverse journey, full of anxieties and unknown experiences, and youthful actions draw attention to these dilemmas which are then emphasised by the principles of 'moral panics'. </s></p><p n="p5.17"><s n="s1.4;p5.17">Moral panics have a long history (McRobbie and Thornton 1995:560), are problematic to define (Cohen 1972, cited in McRobbie 1994:203), oversimplified (McRobbie 1994, cited in Muncie 1999:122), and are considered cyclical, self perpetuating and increasingly more frequent (Thompson 1998:2; Muncie 1999:123). </s><s n="s2.4;p5.17">They have become the 'norm of journalistic practice' and the moralistic voice of society (McRobbie 1994:198). </s><s n="s3.4;p5.17">Critcher (2003:28) believes that moral panics usually have little resemblance to the source of the original occurrence, are an extreme way of defining social problems, and frequently have a direct affect upon influencing legislation and regulations. </s><s n="s4.4;p5.17">It can therefore be seen that moral panics are both powerful and complex. </s></p><p n="p6.17"><s n="s1.15;p6.17">Dominant societal groups have been argued to use moral panics as a means of political control (Kelly 2000:312). </s><s n="s2.15;p6.17">Adults may also use them as a means of control over children (Hendrick, cited in Hughes, Muncie and McLaughlin 2002:20; Willis 1990:54). </s><s n="s3.15;p6.17">The influence of risk in an increasingly risky society (Lupton 1999:9; Beck 1992, cited in Critcher 2003:165) are also important and complex factors pertaining to moral panics <hi rend="sup">(1)</hi>. </s><s n="s4.15;p6.17">Stanley Cohen's empirical study in 1964 (Muncie 1999:120) explored the behaviour of 'Mods' and 'Rockers' within the context of moral panics, the creation of 'folk devils' and the applications of negative labels (Cohen P 1972/80:30, cited in Thompson 1998:33; Cohen S 1972:277, Hunt 1997:630; Critcher 2003:10). </s><s n="s5.15;p6.17">Media hype was responsible for originating the moral panic by reporting incidences that would previously have gone unreported and distorting and/or exaggerating (Thompson 1998:35, Goody 2001:435) what did happen with pictures and 'melodramatic' moralistic vocabulary. </s><s n="s6.15;p6.17">For example one report stated that "all the dance halls near the seafront were smashed", there was only one dance hall in Clacton-on-Sea, Essex at that time and the total cost of damage to <hi rend="italic">all</hi> properties amounted to £513 (Thompson 1998:33). </s><s n="s7.15;p6.17">A snowballing effect is thus created with every subsequent minor disturbance involving any groups of young people reported and soon public opinion is knowledgeable in the 'fact' that young people cause trouble, are a problem. </s><s n="s8.15;p6.17">This is interpreted as an attack upon morality (Hunt 1997:630) and a threat to society (Thompson 1998:3; Garratt 1997:144) - hence the folk devils are born and become something to be feared (Thompson 1998:31, Muncie 1999:119). </s><s n="s9.15;p6.17">The power of the media to generate moral panics must not be underestimated. </s><s n="s10.15;p6.17">Newspaper coverage overwhelmingly shows young people in a negative light. </s><s n="s11.15;p6.17">For example in a review of 603 news articles about young people 203 had a negative focus, with only 46 being positive (Wells 2004:2). </s><s n="s12.15;p6.17">McRobbie and Thornton (1995:571) argue that today "most political strategies <hi rend="italic">are</hi> media strategies" (my emphasis). </s><s n="s13.15;p6.17">However, with the role of the media becoming increasingly embedded in society, and the speed at which news can be disseminated in an increasingly globalised, technology-led society, the future power of the media may increase significantly (McRobbie and Thornton 1995:570). </s><s n="s14.15;p6.17">The increased focus on deviant acts and more stringent surveillance, such as cctv or exclusion policies may result in young people 'acting out' or 'hiding in the light' (Hebdige 1988); believing the labels applied to them and resulting in a self fulfilling and perpetuating prophecy (Muncie 1999:122; Mizen 2004:130; Garratt 1997:147). </s><s n="s15.15;p6.17">Muncie suggests that if less focus was given to less deviant acts, such as those which are primarily young people having fun, the incidence of escalation and seriousness of deviant actions would reduce (Muncie 1999:122). </s></p><p n="p7.17"><s n="s1.5;p7.17">Pressure groups can increase awareness (McRobbie and Thornton 1995:565) of local acts that can have a further reaching impact. </s><s n="s2.5;p7.17">In the study of incidents at Clacton-on-Sea a local resident, Mr Blake', gained support for tighter controls of young people's activities. </s><s n="s3.5;p7.17">He subsequently drew politicians into his group and legislation was enacted to deal with 'malicious damage' (Thompson 1998:38/9). </s><s n="s4.5;p7.17">Increasingly politician may use attacks on morality and the moral structure of society to win political support either for their party or their actions (McRobbie 1994:198). </s><s n="s5.5;p7.17">By making young people the focus of all that is bad in society, governments can elicit support that would otherwise not be so easily won (Thompson 1998:38/9) or divert attention away from real problem areas of deprivation or inequalities in access to work <hi rend="sup">(2)</hi> (Muncie 1999:122; Rutter 1992, cited in Griffin 1993:105; Mizen 2004:134). </s></p><p n="p8.17"><s n="s1.5;p8.17">A more recent example of the power of the media to influence legislation can be seen in the case of the murder of James Bulger by two boys under the age of 10 (Muncie 1999:3-5; McRobbie 1994:198). </s><s n="s2.5;p8.17">The significance of this case was the perpetrators' young age and this may have been seen as by journalists as an excellent opportunity to increase newspaper sales (Young 1974, cited in Muncie 1999:119). </s><s n="s3.5;p8.17">By sensationalising the story all 10 year old boys suddenly became potential demons. </s><s n="s4.5;p8.17">Furthermore, Muncie argues that encouraged by the tabloid newspaper, <hi rend="italic">The</hi> <hi rend="italic">Sun,</hi> numerous readers wrote to the Home Office and could have been instrumental in extending the sentence served by the two offenders. </s><s n="s5.5;p8.17">Certainly the high profile of this incident attracted a raft of legislation aimed at controlling the behaviour of young people in the 1990s, which included truancy, drugs, joyriding - and much tighter legislation followed, for example curfew orders, fast-tracking punishment and zero tolerance (up to 1997) (Muncie 1999:6). </s></p><p n="p9.17"><s n="s1.4;p9.17">The power of the media to reinforce negative labelling by moral panics should not be underestimated. </s><s n="s2.4;p9.17">Social policy and legislation is created in response to what those with the power perceive to be the problem (hegemony), or the threat to social morality or a 'good future' (Muncie 1997:67). </s><s n="s3.4;p9.17">This is illustrated by the creation of the probation service which seeks to control young people considered troublesome (Muncie 1997:67) and bring them back to 'acceptability.' </s><s n="s4.4;p9.17">The major impact of moral panics is that they create or exaggerate negative labels and these are often more influential than the foundation of any truth (Scott 1972:330; Griffin 1997:19; Raby 2005:157) and this is particularly relevant in the case of youth subcultures. </s></p><p n="p10.17"><s n="s1.4;p10.17">The 1950s post war economic boom presented new employment opportunities for many young people (Jeffs and Smith 1998/9:57; Downes and Rock 2003:153), when consumption ceased to be 'a luxury reserved for the wealthier classes' (Bennett and Kahn-Harris 2004:5) and working class young people could create new identities away from the traditional ones (Featherstone 1991 and Chambers 1985, both cited in Bennett and Kahn-Harris 2004:8), allowing some more disposable income than any previous generation and the power to make their position more visible (Hebdige 1983:401). </s><s n="s2.4;p10.17">Increased leisure time pursuits were available and new lifestyles were created as a way of having fun. </s><s n="s3.4;p10.17">However, others argue that this increased financial freedom was seen as a recipe for delinquent behaviour (Downes and Rock 2003:155; Hebdige 1988:35, Raby 2005:159) or the behaviour could just as easily be <hi rend="italic">labelled</hi> 'delinquent' by the elite fearful of losing their hold over the working classes (Cohen P 1972/80:192 in Thompson 1998:41). </s><s n="s4.4;p10.17">Furthermore, previous generations may have been envious of this new freedom that they may have been denied (Cohen P 1972/80:192, cited in Thompson 1998:40; Garratt 1997:143). </s></p><p n="p11.17"><s n="s1.7;p11.17">The original theories of the CCCs argued that subcultures emerged from working class origins as way of rebelling against dominant middle class policies in the form of style, dress and music (Raby 2005:155/6; Willis 1990) or in response to the destruction of working class communities (Cohen P 1972:91). </s><s n="s2.7;p11.17">Subcultures, they argued, were created from a need to define territory (space), find a sense of belonging (Hodkinson 2004:137) as well as defy hegemonic control and as a result of this friction, the perceived problem/trouble/delinquency became synonymous with youth subcultures (Cohen P 1972:97). </s><s n="s3.7;p11.17">However, much early subculture research focussed on gang membership in deprived urban neighbourhoods and concluded that higher levels of crime emanated from gang members than non-gang members. </s><s n="s4.7;p11.17">Downes and Rock argue that this focus on gangs could just have easily influenced the assumption that all young people were delinquent/deviant (2003:145). </s><s n="s5.7;p11.17">Examples of this can be seen in the Mods - working class young people who, by using their increased spending power, dressed up in an attempt to bridge the gap between themselves and the middle classes (Bennett and Kahn-Harris 2004:6), who were notorious for real or perceived clashes with the Rockers (as already discussed). </s><s n="s6.7;p11.17">The focus on working class youth as deviant from middle class norms overlooked any alternative picture and identified a 'problem'. </s><s n="s7.7;p11.17">Thankfully, subculture theory has not been static, and neither have subcultures, but a positive image is still lacking. </s></p><p n="p12.17"><s n="s1.12;p12.17">More recently critiques, including CCCS members themselves and post subcultural theorists, argue that CCCs theory was too simplistic and rigid (Hodkinson 2004:139) and did not look at <hi rend="italic">why</hi> subcultures existed (Raby 2005:161; Clarke 1981:175). </s><s n="s2.12;p12.17">They believe subcultures have increased in fluidity (Thornton 1995:201; Maffesoli 1996, cited in Bennett and Kahn-Harris 2004:12; Hodkinson 2004:135), whilst still retaining collective or communal dimensions (Malbon 2005:185). </s><s n="s3.12;p12.17">Subcultures may be created as a way for young people to possess control over or stability in some part of their lives (Thornton 1995:206) and reflect the modern fragmented world (Kelly 2000:301) by coming together for short periods of time, dissolving and recreating new groups (Maffesoli, cited in Mablon 1999:26), whose object is to find enjoyment in abandonment (usually with the aid of drugs) (Kelly 2000:303; Thompson 1998:45). </s><s n="s4.12;p12.17">Dress and style have become more interchangeable and music also frequently occupies the same space (Bennett and Kahn-Harris 2004:12). </s><s n="s5.12;p12.17">Furthermore, the complex procedure to aspire to high levels of subculture capital or 'hipness' (Thornton 1995:202) or 'coolness' (Malbon 2005:186) is supported by the consumption of music (Hesmondhalgh 2005:37; Malbon 2005:182), style/dress and, most importantly, having the 'right' knowledge (Bennett and Kahn-Harris 2004:2). </s><s n="s6.12;p12.17">Here again the media is powerful as they are the main circulators of 'cultural knowledge' (Thornton 1995:203). </s><s n="s7.12;p12.17">Advertising is frequently couched in terms of 'coolness or hipness' to attract young consumers, especially towards technological gadgets (Ogersby 2004:223; Malbon 1999:24) such as mobile phones. </s><s n="s8.12;p12.17">Furthermore, style and music tastes can cut across 'social class, age and education' to create alternative groupings (Lewis, cited in Bennett and Kahn-Harris 2004:10) to income or occupation classification (Thornton 1995:207). </s><s n="s9.12;p12.17">However, some would argue that consumerism and the emphasis on a material lifestyle creates 'strain' that can lead to increasing crime levels, as those without strive to live the same lifestyle as those that have (Merton 1957, cited in Bennett and Kahn-Harris 2004:4; Griffin 1993:107) resulting in 'anomie' ('normlessness' Merton 1938, cited in Muncie 1999:303). </s><s n="s10.12;p12.17">Furthermore, the majority of funding is directed towards crime and drugs education rather than promotion of youth culture. </s><s n="s11.12;p12.17">As a result policies are informed by young peoples' activities that are most present, or visible (Bennett 2005:258), which it is argued are the minority (Downes 2003:158; Scott 1972:330). </s><s n="s12.12;p12.17">Straw (2004, cited in Bennett and Kahn-Harris 2004:13) argues that subcultures have ceased to be local entities but rather have become global (Pilkington 2004:119) 'scenes', with style and music tastes being the membership card, for example Rave, but that might still have cultural differences at a local level (Pilkington 2004:153). </s></p><p n="p13.17"><s n="s1.12;p13.17">Whereas early subcultures were highly visible in public places, these new scenes have arguably gone 'underground', into clubs or venues outside the mainstream sphere of adults. </s><s n="s2.12;p13.17">In such a way, young people create their own space in which to celebrate individuality (losing oneself) in group solidarity (the crowd) (Brake 1980, cited in Garratt 1997:149), creating a safe, self regulating environment (Malbon 1998:280) where consumption is of the experience itself rather than the type of style. </s><s n="s3.12;p13.17">As a result, the nightclub environment may be seen as a more liberating and safe environment for female clubbers (Malbon 2005:184). </s><s n="s4.12;p13.17">However, as the gap between male and female earnings remains, so music and culture will continue to be less influenced by the lower earning female population (Thornton 1995:207). </s><s n="s5.12;p13.17">Invisibility does not exclude young people from negative labelling, as is seen by the case of Leah Betts whose picture, as she lay dying in hospital as a result of taking drugs, was front page news for most tabloid newspapers. </s><s n="s6.12;p13.17">Leah, from a respectable family and took Ecstasy at her 18 <hi rend="sup">th</hi> birthday party. </s><s n="s7.12;p13.17">Suddenly, the perception, promoted by the media, is that all young people take drugs and are going to die (Saunders 1995). </s><s n="s8.12;p13.17">Media and advertising suggest a 'normalisation' of drug taking amongst clubbers (Taylor 2000:333), but some research shows that young people take them in a conscious and systematic fashion and their consumption is restricted (mainly) to soft, recreational drugs such as cannabis, Ecstasy (Kerrigan 2001, Pilkington 2006:48; Shildrick 2002:46). </s><s n="s9.12;p13.17">Research shows there is little support for 'crossing the Rubicon' into harder drug taking of heroin (MacDonald and March 2002:27-38). </s><s n="s10.12;p13.17">This aspect is little understood by the adult world as is evident from a recent BBC News story claiming the UK as the 'cannabis capital of Europe', but differences reported between hard and recreational drug use is unclear (BBC News 2006:1). </s><s n="s11.12;p13.17">This could be considered yet another moral panic or more realistically recognised as a way young people create lifestyles to cope with the stresses of the modern world (Shildrick 2002:46; Miles 2000:159), just as smoking has been used for past generations. </s><s n="s12.12;p13.17">Instead, again young people are portrayed as a problem, not only by injuring themselves, but threatening the stability of the future of society as a whole. </s></p><p n="p14.17"><s n="s1.23;p14.17">In this essay I have investigated moral panics and youth subcultures and post subcultures with reference to Hebdige's proposition. </s><s n="s2.23;p14.17">The evidence against Hebdige's proposition is scant and sometimes targeted only at those already in a privileged position (gifted and talented) (University of Warwick 2006; UK Youth Parliament 2005; NAGTY 2006), whilst the support for it is substantial (Hebdige 1988:27; Garratt 1997:143; Muncie 1999:249; Jeffs and Smith 1998/9:45/46; Kelly 2000:301; BBC News 2004:1; Griffin 1997A:17; Hall 1978:34, cited in Muncie 1999:122; Griffin 1993:115; Raby 2005:161). </s><s n="s3.23;p14.17">Young people have been labelled as deviant/delinquent or a problem for so long that is has become perceived as the 'truth', so commonplace that the significance of such labelling is not questioned (Hebdige 1988:27; Muncie 1999:2), nor alternative ways of relating to young people sought. </s><s n="s4.23;p14.17">Youth and problem are synonymous, in that there are so many different negative labels applied. </s><s n="s5.23;p14.17">Adolescence is a time of great physical and physiological changes (Hall, cited in Griffin 1997B:19, Jeffs and Smith 1998/9:50) when over spilling exuberant behaviour is looked upon negatively (Foucault, cited in Raby 2005:162); as a problem - the working class young man is always a criminal, the black youth a mugger and any subculture member a drug addict. </s><s n="s6.23;p14.17">Excessive and exaggerated media coverage creates moral panics (Thompson 1999:35), exacerbating the negative labelling of young people. </s><s n="s7.23;p14.17">The media becomes the moral voice of the nation (McRobbie 1994:198) and informs public opinion to a point that legislative changes (McRobbie and Thornton 1995:571) result to curtail the activities of young people (Thompson 1998:38/9). </s><s n="s8.23;p14.17">There is plenty of evidence of this in the newspapers and very little to support positive images of young people (Wells 2004:2). </s><s n="s9.23;p14.17">As more severe restrictions are placed upon them, young people rebel in the only ways they know how - by coming together in groups by consumption of style and music, decorating their bodies and seeking escape from adult spaces (Hebdige 1988:8). </s><s n="s10.23;p14.17">They are not driven by consumerism, but use the commercial market as a way to avoid labelling and away from mainstream that is seen as created and controlled by the parent culture (Clarke et al 1995:19). </s><s n="s11.23;p14.17">Early subculture theorists argue that defiance shown by working class young people against middle class 'norms' created groups who became synonymous with deviant behaviour (whether real or perceived) (Raby 2005:155/6; Cohen P 1972:91; Hodkinson 2004:137), and were especially noticeable at times of major social change (Downes and Rock 2004:161). </s><s n="s12.23;p14.17">More recent subcultures, or neo-tribes 'neo-tribes' (Maffesoli 1988, cited in Malbon 1998:280), are influenced by wider issues than parent culture alone (Malbon 2005:185; Maffesoli, cited in Malbon 1999:26; Kelly 2000:301). </s><s n="s13.23;p14.17">The world has become more global, more risky and faster changing (Lupton 1999:9; Beck 1992, cited in Critcher 2003:165), whilst the restrictions upon young people have become greater (Muncie 1999:6; Muncie 1997:67). </s><s n="s14.23;p14.17">In order to find coping strategies they have become less visible, by creating their own 'clubs', adopted fluid and adaptable cultures and consumption has become one of experience rather than style (Malbon 2005:184). </s><s n="s15.23;p14.17">The 'experience' is enhanced by activities frowned upon by the adult world - loud music, staying out late and the consumption of (usually large amounts of) alcohol and recreational drugs (Kerrigan 2001). </s><s n="s16.23;p14.17">This makes it easy to maintain the negative labelling of young people, easy for negative images of young people to be accepted as the truth and difficult to see the significance negative foundations. </s><s n="s17.23;p14.17">It is unclear how differently young people may be treated if the image of them were positive. </s><s n="s18.23;p14.17">The reasons for subcultures may have developed as theories have changed, but few new understandings have evolved. </s><s n="s19.23;p14.17">Despite adult concern, possibly for themselves and their future than for young people and extensive research, there seems little attempt to understand the desire for young people to find their own identities, rather the focus is on enforcing stricter controls and surveillance in order to bring them back into line. </s><s n="s20.23;p14.17">Furthermore, insufficient consideration of external factors such as boredom (Matza, cited in Downes and Rock 2003:153) 'poverty, addiction, unequal access to education' (Hesmondhalgh, cited in Bennett 2005:256) or employment (MacDonald and Marsh 2002:30; Downes 1972) will do little to support young people who have little accrued knowledge or experience to call on. </s><s n="s21.23;p14.17">Adult misunderstandings and more restriction of young people's behaviour and actions will only lead to more outrageous behaviour on their part (Becker, cited in Bennett and Kahn-Harris 2004:4) and will do little to remove the negative image of young people dealing with the 'storm and stress' of adolescence. </s><s n="s22.23;p14.17">Until young people are allowed to integrate into the adult world and assigned rights as individuals, the negative labelling will remain (Smith 2003:187). </s><s n="s23.23;p14.17">It is heartening to see the UK Youth Parliament manifesto (2005:5) calling for an end to the negative portrayal of young people and the promotion of more positive images by the media, but it is difficult to say how long it will take to effect this momentous change. </s></p><p n="p15.17"><s n="s1.1;p15.17"><hi rend="bold">Notes</hi>: </s></p><p n="p16.17"><s n="s1.1;p16.17"><hi rend="sup">(1)</hi> There is insufficient space within this essay to discuss this important aspect further. </s></p><p n="p17.17"><s n="s1.1;p17.17"><hi rend="sup">(2)</hi> Inequalities in opportunities to enter the job market - 12.3 % of young people were unemployed in 2004, versus only 4.9% of adults (National Statistics Office 2006). </s></p></div1></body><back><div1 type="bibliography"><head rend="bold">References</head><p>BBC News (2004) 'Crime Levels: your experiences', <seg type="URL" n="www.bbcnews.co.uk/haveyoursay"/> (27 July) accessed 4.2.06 </p><p>BBC News (2006) 'UK's cocaine use 'as high as US', <seg type="URL" n="www.bbcnews.co.uk"/> accessed 1.3.06</p><p>Beck, U (1992) <hi rend="italic">Risk Society: towards a new modernity</hi>, Sage London</p><p>Bennett, A (2005) 'In Defence of Neo-tribes: A Response to Blackman and Hesmondhalgh', <hi rend="italic">Journal of Youth Studies</hi>, 2:255-9</p><p>Bennett, A and Kahn-Harris, K (eds) <hi rend="italic">After Subcultures: Critical Studies in Contemporary Youth Culture,</hi> Palgrave, 2004</p><p>Clarke, G (1981) 'Defending Ski-jumpers: a critique of theories of youth subcultures', in K Gelder and S Thornton (eds) (1997) <hi rend="italic">The Subcultures</hi> Reader, London: Routledge (original text in Simon Frith and Andrew Goodwin (eds) (1990) <hi rend="italic">On Record</hi>, London: Routledge)</p><p>Cohen, P (1972) 'Subcultural Conflict and Working-class Community', in K Gelder and S Thornton (eds) (1997) <hi rend="italic">The Subcultures</hi> Reader, London: Routledge (original text<hi rend="italic"> Working Papers in Cultural Studies 2</hi> (University of Birmingham: Centre for Contemporary Cultural Studies))</p><p>Cohen, S (1972) 'Mods, rockers and the rest: community reactions to juvenile delinquency' in JB Mays (ed) <hi rend="italic">Juvenile delinquency, the family and the social group</hi>, London: Longman</p><p>Critcher, C (2003) <hi rend="italic">Moral Panics and the Media</hi>, Buckingham: OUP</p><p>Downes, D (1972) 'The Delinquent Solution' in J B Mays, (ed) <hi rend="italic">Juvenile Delinquency, the family and the social group</hi>, London: Longman</p><p>Downes, D and Rock, P (2003) <hi rend="italic">Understanding Deviance',</hi> Oxford: Oxford University Press</p><p>Farrington, D (2002) 'Understanding and preventing youth crime' in J Muncie, G Hughes and E McLaughlin (eds) <hi rend="italic">Youth Justices - Critical Readings,</hi> London: Sage</p><p>Garratt, D (1997) 'Youth Cultures and Sub-Cultures' in J Roche and S Tucker (eds) <hi rend="italic">Youth in Society,</hi> London: Sage</p><p>Gelder, K (1997) 'Introduction to part two' in K Gelder and S Thornton (1997) <hi rend="italic">The Subcultures Reader</hi>, Routledge, London</p><p>Giddins, A (2001) <hi rend="italic">Sociology,</hi> Cambridge: Polity</p><p>Gilroy, P (2002) 'Lesser breeds without the law' in J Muncie, G Hughes and E McLaughlin (eds) <hi rend="italic">Youth Justices - Critical Readings,</hi> London: Sage</p><p>Griffin, C (1993) <hi rend="italic">Representations of Youth: the study of Youth and Adolescence in Britain and America</hi>, Cambridge: Polity</p><p>Griffin, C (1997A) 'Representations of the Young' in J Roche and S Tucker (eds) <hi rend="italic">Youth in Society,</hi> London: Sage</p><p>Griffin, C (1997B) 'Troubles Teens: managing disorders in transition and consumption', <hi rend="italic">Feminist Review</hi>, 55:4-21</p><p>Goody, J (2001) 'The Criminalization of British Asian Youth: Research from Bradford and Sheffield', <hi rend="italic">Journal of Youth Studies,</hi> 4, 4:429-50</p><p>Hebdige, D (1983) 'Posing .. Threats, Striking ... Poses: Youth, Surveillance and Display' in K Gelder and S Thornton (eds) (1997) <hi rend="italic">The Subcultures</hi> Reader, London: Routledge (original text in<hi rend="italic"> SubStance</hi>, 37: 68-88)</p><p>Hebdige, D (1979) '<hi rend="italic">Subculture: the meaning of style</hi>', in K Gelder and S Thornton (eds) (1997) <hi rend="italic">The Subcultures</hi> Reader, London: Routledge (original text London: Methuen)</p><p>Hebdige, D (1988) <hi rend="italic">Hiding in the Light</hi>, London: Comedia</p><p>Hesmonhalgh, D (2005) 'Subcultures, Scenes or Tribes? None of the Above', <hi rend="italic">Journal of Youth Studies,</hi> 8, 1:21-40</p><p>Hodkinson, P (2004) 'The Goth Scene and (Sub) Culture Substance' in A Bennett and K Kahn-Harris (eds), <hi rend="italic">After Subcultures,</hi> Basingstoke: Palgrave Macmillan</p><p>Kerrigan, J (2001) <hi rend="italic">Human Traffic</hi>, London: Channel 4 (Miramax Films (1999), USA)</p><p>Hunt, A (1997) '"Moral Panic" and Moral language in the Media', <hi rend="italic">The British Journal of Sociology,</hi> 48, 4:629-48</p><p>Jeffs, T and Smith, M (1998/99) 'The Problem of 'Youth' for Youth Work',<hi rend="italic"> Youth and Policy,</hi> 62:45-65</p><p>Kelly, P (2000) 'Youth as an Artefact of Expertise: Problemising the Practice of Youth Studies in an Age of Uncertainty' <hi rend="italic">Journal of Youth Studies,</hi> 2:301-15</p><p>Lupton, D (1999) <hi rend="italic">Risk</hi>, London: Routledge, </p><p>Malbon, B (1998) 'Clubbing: consumption, identify and the special practices of every-night life' in T Skelton and G Valentine (eds) <hi rend="italic">Cool Places</hi>, London: Routledge</p><p>Malbon, B (2005) <hi rend="italic">Clubbing,</hi> London: Routledge</p><p>Malbon, B (1999) <hi rend="italic">Clubbing</hi>, London: Routledge</p><p>MacDonald, R and Marsh, J (2002) 'Crossing the Rubicon: youth transition, poverty, drugs and social exclusion', <hi rend="italic">International Journal of Drug Policy</hi> 13 (2002) :27-38</p><p>McRobbie, A (1994) <hi rend="italic">Postmodernism and popular culture</hi>, London: Routledge</p><p>McRobbie, A and Thornton, S L (1995) 'Rethinking "Moral Panic" for Multi-mediated social worlds' <hi rend="italic">British Journal of Sociology</hi>, 46, 4:559-574</p><p>Miles, S (2000) <hi rend="italic">Youth Lifestyles in a changing World,</hi> Buckingham and Philadelphia: Open University Press</p><p>Mizen, P (2004) <hi rend="italic">The Changing State of Youth</hi>, Basingstoke: Palgrave Macmillan</p><p>Muncie, J (1999) <hi rend="italic">Youth and Crime: a critical introduction</hi>, London: Sage</p><p>Muncie, J, Hughes, G and McLaughlin, E (eds) (2002) <hi rend="italic">Youth Justices - Critical Readings,</hi> London: Sage</p><p>National Statistics Office (2006) 'Unemployment rates: by age, EU comparison 1999', <seg type="URL" n="www.statisstics.gov.uk/statbase/expodata/spreadsheets/d3485.xls"/> accessed 13.2.06</p><p>Ogersby, B (2004) <hi rend="italic">Youth Media</hi>, Routledge, Abingdon</p><p>Pilkington, H (2004) 'Youth Strategies for Glocal Living: Space, Power and Communications in Everyday Cultural Practice' in A Bennett and K Kahn-Harris (eds), Basingstoke: Palgrave Macmillan</p><p>Pilkington, H (2006) <hi rend="italic">'For us it's normal': Exploring the 'Recreational' use of heroin in Russia in youth cultural practice',</hi> Salisbury: Techset Composition</p><p>Raby, R (2005) 'What is Resistance?',<hi rend="italic"> Journal of Youth Studies,</hi> 8, 2:151-171</p><p>Saunders, N (1995) <hi rend="italic">The Leah Betts Story</hi>, <seg type="URL" n="www.ecstacy.org/info/dangers"/> accessed 13.4.06</p><p>Scott, P (1972) 'Delinquency: types and causes' in J B Mays (ed) <hi rend="italic">Juvenile Delinquency, the Family and the Social Group</hi>, London: Longman </p><p>Shildrick, T (2002) 'Young People, Illicit Drug Use and the Question of Normalization' <hi rend="italic">Journal of Youth Studies,</hi> 5,1:35-48</p><p>Taylor, D (2000) 'The Word on the Street: Advertising, Youth Culture and Legitimate Speech in Drug Education', <hi rend="italic">Journal of Youth Studies,</hi> 3,3:333-52</p><p>Thompson, K (1998) <hi rend="italic">Moral Panics</hi>, London: Routledge </p><p>Thornton, S (1995) 'The Social Logic of Subculture Capital', in K Gelder and S Thornton (eds) (1997) <hi rend="italic">The Subcultures</hi> Reader, London: Routledge</p><p>Travis, A (2005) 'The myth of yob Britain', <seg type="URL" n="www.societyguardian.co.uk"/> accessed 4.2.06</p><p>Wells, M (2004) 'Media casts youth in a constant bad light', <seg type="URL" n="www.guardian.co.uk"/> (14 October) accessed 17/1/06</p><p>Willis, P (1990) <hi rend="italic">Common Culture</hi>, Buckingham: OUP</p></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
