<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_0340b" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Post Module Assignment</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">deleted: header: module name; footer: page numbers</note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">deleted: cover sheet</note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">Evaluated as candidate compound assignment. Assigned to S1b: collection of reports: compound.</note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">deleted: Number of words: 3808</note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">deleted: Number of words: 532</note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">deleted: Number of words: 281</note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">deleted: Number of words: 289</note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">appendix: "Winning MarginTM": Year 2 Cash Flow Statement</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">4</p><p n="date">2006-11</p><p n="module title">Financial Analysis and Control Systems</p><p n="module code">ES979</p><p n="genre family">Case study + Narrative recount</p><p n="discipline">Engineering</p><p n="disciplinary group">PS</p><p n="grade">M</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">4686</p><p n="number of s-units">202</p><p n="number of p">100</p><p n="number of tables">2</p><p n="number of figures">0</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">6</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">33</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">23.2</p><p n="average s-units per p">2.0</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">compound assignment consisting of 2 parts (see notesStmt for details)</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">m</p><p n="year of birth">1983</p><p n="first language">Greek</p><p n="education">OSA</p><p n="course">Engineering Business Management</p><p n="student ID">0340</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><div1 type="toc" n="4"><head>List of contents</head><p/></div1></front><body><div1 type="text"><head rend="bold">Question 1</head><div2><head rend="bold">Introduction</head><p n="p1.100"><s n="s1.1;p1.100">The current assignment examines the financial and business performance as well as the future prospects of Bodycote International PLC, a company which is specialized in testing and thermal processing services. </s></p><p n="p2.100"><s n="s1.4;p2.100">The financial and business performance analysis of Bodycote will be initially based on the Consolidated Income Statement, the Consolidated Balance Sheet and the Consolidated Cash Flow Statement of the company. </s><s n="s2.4;p2.100">Moreover, the current analysis makes use of several reports (i.e. </s><s n="s3.4;p2.100">Chairman's Statement, Directors' Report etc), and in order for this analysis to be complete, some ratios must be calculated and interpreted. </s><s n="s4.4;p2.100">Finally, press releases and articles about Bodycote's strategy, performance and potential growth are discussed. </s></p><p n="p3.100"><s n="s1.2;p3.100">The data used for the financial and business performance analysis and the calculation of the ratios can be found at Bodycote's Annual Report for 2005. </s><s n="s2.2;p3.100">Finally, the press releases and the articles can be found at the referenced web-sites. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">1. The Company </head><p n="p4.100"><s n="s1.3;p4.100">According to its official web-site (<seg type="URL" n="www.bodycote.com"/>), the company was founded in 1923 by the Bodycote family and started up as a textile company in Leicester UK. </s><s n="s2.3;p4.100"><hi rend="italic">"By 1972, Bodycote's group turnover was £15.4 million and the company was producing a profit of £1.2 million"</hi>. </s><s n="s3.3;p4.100">Today, Bodycote operates in 26 countries with over 280 facilities. </s></p><p n="p5.100"><s n="s1.1;p5.100">Company's main activities include: </s></p><list type="bulleted"><item>Heat Treatments</item><item>Hot Isostatic Pressing </item><item>Testing</item><item>Metallurgical Coatings</item><item>Measurement Solutions</item></list><p n="p6.100"><s n="s1.1;p6.100">The main markets that Bodycote serves are the following ones: </s></p><list type="bulleted"><item>Aerospace</item><item>Architectural</item><item>Automotive</item><item>Chemicals</item><item>Construction</item><item>Consumer Products</item><item>Defence</item><item>Electrical, Telecomms &amp; IT</item><item>Environmental</item><item>Fire Protection</item><item>Fluid Handling</item><item>General Engineering &amp; Hydraulics</item><item>Litigation Support</item><item>Medical</item><item>Mining</item><item>Novel Materials</item><item>Offshore</item><item>Oil, Gas &amp; Petrochemical</item><item>Pharmaceutical</item><item>Plastics &amp; Polymers</item><item>Power Generation</item><item>Rail</item><item>Tooling</item><item>Water Industry</item></list><p n="p7.100"><s n="s1.3;p7.100">In order to define its business relations with its customers, Bodycote uses Subcontracts, Long Term Agreements and Strategic Partnerships (SP). </s><s n="s2.3;p7.100">Bodycote considers SP as an innovative way of doing business. </s><s n="s3.3;p7.100">SP are characterised as a <hi rend="italic">"win-win approach"</hi>, since Bodycote simply undertakes the construction of a facility near the factory that cooperates with, and the factory binds itself to use the facility. </s></p><p n="p8.100"><s n="s1.2;p8.100">Finally, Bodycote's future objective is to become <hi rend="italic">"the leading provider of metallurgical and testing services"</hi>. </s><s n="s2.2;p8.100">In order to accomplish this, Bodycote tries to successfully fulfil its customers' demands, earning at the same time sustainable profit and 'investing' on its human resources. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">2. Financial &amp; Business Performance Analysis</head><p n="p9.100"><s n="s1.1;p9.100">As abovementioned, the analysis of the financial and business performance of Bodycote will be based on several sources such as financial reports, board members' reports, ratio analysis and analysis of press releases and relative articles. </s></p><div3><head rend="bold">2.1 Financial Reports Analysis </head><p n="p10.100"><s n="s1.1;p10.100">The examined financial reports are the Consolidated Income Statement, the Consolidated Balance Sheet and the Consolidated Cash Flow Statement -all of them for the year ended at 31 December 2005- since according to Bodycote's Accounting Policies<ref target="BAWE_0340b-ftnote.001"/>, <hi rend="italic">"The consolidated financial statements incorporate the financial statements of the Company and entities controlled by the Company (its subsidiaries)".</hi> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0340b-ftnote.001"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Bodycote annual report 2005, p. 30 </s></p></note><p n="p11.100"><s n="s1.1;p11.100"><hi rend="underlined">Note:</hi> The words in <hi rend="bold">Bold</hi> are data taken from the financial statements. </s></p><div4><head><hi rend="bold">2.1.1 Consolidated Income Statement</hi><ref target="BAWE_0340b-ftnote.002"/><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0340b-ftnote.002"><p n="pn1.1"> Bodycote annual report 2005, p. 26</p></note></head><p n="p12.100"><s n="s1.1;p12.100">On examining the Consolidated Income Statement of Bodycote, one can focus on the following main data: </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p13.100"><s n="s1.2;p13.100">The <hi rend="bold"> Revenue-continuing operations</hi> increased by 10% <hi rend="italic">(from £424.6 m in 2004 to £470.9 m in 2005)</hi>. </s><s n="s2.2;p13.100">This increase is mainly based on the increase of <hi rend="bold">Acquisitions</hi> from £1.8 m in 2004 to £17.2 m in 2005. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p14.100"><s n="s1.1;p14.100">The <hi rend="bold">Operating Profit-continuing operations</hi> also increased by 10% <hi rend="italic">(from £55.5 m in 2004 to £61.0 m in 2005)</hi>, and consequently the <hi rend="bold">Profit for the year from continuing operations</hi> has been increased by 9% to £40.9 m <hi rend="italic">(2004: £37.4 m)</hi>. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p15.100"><s n="s1.1;p15.100">In 2005 Bodycote did not make any <hi rend="bold">Loss for the year from discontinued operations</hi> in contrast with 2004 when Bodycote experienced a loss of £9.0 m </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p16.100"><s n="s1.1;p16.100">Finally there was an increase in <hi rend="bold">Profit for the year</hi> by 44% to £40.9 m <hi rend="italic">(2004: £28.4 m).</hi> </s></p></div4><div4><head><hi rend="bold">2.1.2 Consolidated Balance Sheet</hi> <ref target="BAWE_0340b-ftnote.003"/><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0340b-ftnote.003"><p n="pn1.1"> Bodycote annual report 2005, p. 28</p></note></head><p n="p17.100"><s n="s1.1;p17.100">Among the data of the Consolidated Balance Sheet that can be proved particularly useful on analysing the financial and business performance of Bodycote, one can concentrate on the following: </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p18.100"><s n="s1.1;p18.100">The <hi rend="bold">Goodwill</hi> of Bodycote increased by 10% <hi rend="italic">(from £139.7 m in 2004 to £154.2 m in 2005).</hi> </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p19.100"><s n="s1.1;p19.100"><hi rend="bold">Property, plant and equipment</hi> were also increased by 4% to £442.9 m <hi rend="italic">(2004: £425.9 m).</hi> </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p20.100"><s n="s1.1;p20.100">The above two elements were the main reasons for the 7% increase of the <hi rend="bold">Non-current assets</hi> <hi rend="italic">(from £598.2 m in 2004 to £640.7 m in 2005).</hi> </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p21.100"><s n="s1.3;p21.100">On the other hand, the <hi rend="bold">Current assets</hi> of the company decreased by 1% to £251.5 m <hi rend="italic">(2004: £253.3 m)</hi> and, in connection with the increase of <hi rend="bold">Current liabilities</hi> by 11% <hi rend="italic">(from £106.6 m in 2004 to £118.1 m in 2005),</hi> this resulted in a 9% decrease of <hi rend="bold">Net current assets</hi> to £133.4 m <hi rend="italic">(2004: £146.7 m).</hi> </s><s n="s2.3;p21.100">On examining the <hi rend="bold">Current liabilities</hi>, it is important to take into account the 12% increase of <hi rend="bold">Trade and other payables</hi> <hi rend="italic">(from £86.9 m in 2004 to £97.2 m in 2005).</hi> </s><s n="s3.3;p21.100">However, it is obvious that Bodycote could easily meet its Current Liabilities using its Current Assets, for both 2004 and 2005 </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p22.100"><s n="s1.1;p22.100">The <hi rend="bold">Net assets</hi> increased by 3% <hi rend="italic">(from £422.0 m in 2004 to £433.5 m in 2005),</hi> since there was an important increase of <hi rend="bold">Non current assets</hi> as it was stated before. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p23.100"><s n="s1.1;p23.100">Finally, the <hi rend="bold">Total equity</hi> increased by 3% to £433.5 m <hi rend="italic">(2004: £422.0 m)</hi>. </s></p></div4><div4><head><hi rend="bold">2.1.3 Consolidated Cash Flow Statement</hi><ref target="BAWE_0340b-ftnote.004"/><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0340b-ftnote.004"><p n="pn1.1"> Bodycote annual report 2005, p. 29</p></note></head><p n="p24.100"><s n="s1.3;p24.100">The Consolidated Cash Flow Statement is very interesting since it depicts the vigorous investing activities of Bodycote. </s><s n="s2.3;p24.100">However, the financing activities of Bodycote are of great interest too. </s><s n="s3.3;p24.100">Thus, one can focus on: </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p25.100"><s n="s1.1;p25.100">Bodycote's <hi rend="bold">Net cash from operating activities</hi> decreased from £100.5 m in 2004 to £95.7 m in 2004. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p26.100"><s n="s1.1;p26.100">The <hi rend="bold">Purchases of property, plant and equipment</hi> which increased by 38% to £51.8 m <hi rend="italic">(2004: £37.5 m),</hi> as well as the increase of <hi rend="bold">Acquisition of subsidiaries</hi> from £4.7 m in 2004 to £31.8 m in 2005. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p27.100"><s n="s1.1;p27.100">Moreover, the <hi rend="bold">Disposal of subsidiaries</hi> is much smaller in 2005 <hi rend="italic">(£5.8 m)</hi>, compared to 2004 <hi rend="italic">(£20.4 m)</hi>. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p28.100"><s n="s1.1;p28.100">In addition, the <hi rend="bold">Net cash used in investing activities</hi> is increased by 203% to £72.4 m (2004: £23.9 m). </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p29.100"><s n="s1.1;p29.100">In Financing Activities, there was a decrease in <hi rend="bold">New bank loans raised</hi>, from £5.1 m in 2004 to £0.1 m in 2005. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p30.100"><s n="s1.1;p30.100">Moreover, in 2004 <hi rend="bold">Net cash from financing activities</hi> was <hi rend="italic">£31.7 m</hi> where in 2005 Bodycote used £42.0 m in its financing activities. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p31.100"><s n="s1.1;p31.100">In addition, in 2004 the <hi rend="bold">Net cash and cash equivalents</hi> increased by £108.3 where in 2005 decreased by £18.7 m. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p32.100"><s n="s1.1;p32.100">Finally, the <hi rend="bold">Cash and cash equivalents at beginning and end of year</hi> in 2005 were £138.7 m and 120.7 m, whereas in 2004 they were £29.8 m and £138.7 m respectively. </s></p></div4></div3><div3><head rend="bold">2.2 Boards' Members Reports Analysis</head><p n="p33.100"><s n="s1.1;p33.100">The reports that are going to be examined in the current assignment are: </s></p><list type="bulleted"><item>Chairman's Statement</item><item>Chief Executive's Review</item><item>Finance Director's Report</item><item>and Directors' Report</item></list><p n="p34.100"><s n="s1.2;p34.100">These reports include important data which their impact is depicted on the financial reports of part 2.1. </s><s n="s2.2;p34.100">The data presented here explain and justify the differences between the financial reports of 2004 and 2005. </s></p><div4><head><hi rend="bold">2.2.1 Chairman's Statement</hi> <ref target="BAWE_0340b-ftnote.005"/><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0340b-ftnote.005"><p n="pn1.1"> Bodycote annual report 2005, p. 2</p></note></head><p n="p35.100"><s n="s1.3;p35.100">According to Chairman's Statement, Bodycote achieved <hi rend="italic">"a strong organic growth of 5% and a further 5% from a series of bolt-on acquisitions"</hi>. </s><s n="s2.3;p35.100">He also refers that during the year, Bodycote obtained fourteen new acquisitions at a cost of £31.8 m and has invested <hi rend="italic">"in projects that will bring a longer term benefit to the group"</hi>. </s><s n="s3.3;p35.100">Finally, he seems optimistic about Bodycote's future growth, since he believes that markets such as aerospace and health science have great potentials. </s></p><p n="p36.100"><s n="s1.1;p36.100">The 14 new acquisitions justify the increase in <hi rend="bold">Acquisitions,</hi> in <hi rend="bold">Non-current assets (Goodwill</hi> and <hi rend="bold"> Property, plant and equipment),</hi> in <hi rend="bold">Purchases of property, plant and equipment</hi> and in <hi rend="bold"> Net cash used in investing activities.</hi> </s></p></div4><div4><head><hi rend="bold">2.2.2 Chief Executive's Review</hi><ref target="BAWE_0340b-ftnote.006"/><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0340b-ftnote.006"><p n="pn1.1"> Bodycote annual report 2005, pp. 3-7</p></note></head><p n="p37.100"><s n="s1.4;p37.100">The Chief Executive's Review contains several important data, worth mentioning in order to make this analysis more thorough. </s><s n="s2.4;p37.100">Firstly, he states that with the acquisition of the new facilities Bodycote managed to <hi rend="italic">"rebalance its portfolio"</hi>. </s><s n="s3.4;p37.100">In addition, he mentions that the <hi rend="italic">"geographic and market spread"</hi> of Bodycote, reduces the risk of depending too much in a particular country/ market. </s><s n="s4.4;p37.100">He also pinpoints that Bodycote's <hi rend="italic">"top 10 customers accounted for approximately 12% of total revenue"</hi>. </s></p><p n="p38.100"><s n="s1.1;p38.100">In addition he gives a detailed review of the new investments which include: </s></p><list type="bulleted"><item>3 laboratories (Health Science division)</item><item>7 laboratories (Materials testing, Engineering &amp; Technology and Environmental divisions)</item><item>establishment of a European Engineering &amp; Technical Centre in Sweden</item><item>4 acquisitions (Heat Treatment)</item><item>4 plants in Poland</item><item>75% interest of Uttis Industries SA in Romania</item><item>purchase of Nadcap (UK) and ABMT SA (France)</item></list><p n="p39.100"><s n="s1.3;p39.100">Furthermore, he mentions that the Operating Profit for Heat Treatment increased both in America and Europe (<hi rend="italic">38% and 11% respectively</hi>) and Bodycote has started investing in China; a plant of a 10.000 m <hi rend="sup">2</hi> is under construction and Bodycote plans to "<hi rend="italic">complete similar other factories over the next five years"</hi> through China. </s><s n="s2.3;p39.100">He also states that there has been an increase in Revenue for all Bodycote's different activities. </s><s n="s3.3;p39.100">Finally, he points out that energy remains among the most significant costs and Bodycote tries to pass this cost on its customers. </s></p><p n="p40.100"><s n="s1.1;p40.100">Some of the abovementioned data justify the increase in <hi rend="bold">Revenue-continuing operations</hi> as well as the increase in <hi rend="bold">Operating profit-continuing operations.</hi> </s></p></div4><div4><head><hi rend="bold">2.2.3 Finance Director's Report</hi> <ref target="BAWE_0340b-ftnote.007"/><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0340b-ftnote.007"><p n="pn1.1"> Bodycote annual report 2005, pp. 10-12</p></note></head><p n="p41.100"><s n="s1.5;p41.100">Focusing on the Finance Director's Report, one can find several important data concerning Bodycote. </s><s n="s2.5;p41.100">To begin with, he states that demand was improved in most markets, but the automotive sector in North America and Europe faced a <hi rend="italic">"challenging"</hi> period. </s><s n="s3.5;p41.100">He also mentions that Bodycote exited from electroplating business <hi rend="italic">(loss of £3.2 m in 2004),</hi> coming to a break-even point in 2005. </s><s n="s4.5;p41.100">He also mentions that the Basic Earnings/ Share increased to 12.7p <hi rend="italic">(2004: 12.2p)</hi> and the Final Dividend is 4.05p compared to 3.85p in 2004. </s><s n="s5.5;p41.100">Furthermore, he states that various important projects started during the year in different places all over the world. </s></p><p n="p42.100"><s n="s1.7;p42.100">The Finance Director also makes significant comments on Bodycote's cash flow management. </s><s n="s2.7;p42.100">He mentions that company's decrease in <hi rend="bold">Net cash from operating activities</hi> is the result of <hi rend="italic">"increased capital expenditure"</hi>. </s><s n="s3.7;p42.100">He also points out that there has been an increase in <hi rend="italic">"debtor days from 65 to 68",</hi> increasing thus debtors by £4.7 m. </s><s n="s4.7;p42.100">He also states that gearing in 2005 was 25% compared to 21% in 2004. </s><s n="s5.7;p42.100">Moreover, he mentions that Bodycote tries to keep a balance of 25% to 75% between fixed and floating rates and at the end of December 2005 <hi rend="italic">"24% of borrowings were at fixed rates"</hi> for 4 years on average. </s><s n="s6.7;p42.100">He also refers that among Bodycote's main concerns is to reassure <hi rend="italic">"continuity of finance at a reasonable cost".</hi> </s><s n="s7.7;p42.100">Based on this, Bodycote is financed by: </s></p><list type="bulleted"><item>mix of cash flows from operations</item><item>short-term borrowings</item><item>longer-term loans from banks</item><item>capital markets</item><item>finance leases.</item></list><p n="p43.100"><s n="s1.1;p43.100">Finally, he mentions that Bodycote is using <hi rend="italic">"uncommitted and short-term facilities"</hi> in order to successfully manage <hi rend="italic">"day-to-day liquidity and working capital requirements"</hi>. </s></p><p n="p44.100"><s n="s1.1;p44.100">The exit from electroplating business justifies partially both 2004's <hi rend="bold">Loss for the year from discontinued operations</hi> <hi rend="italic">(£9.0 m)</hi> and <hi rend="bold">Disposal of subsidiaries</hi> <hi rend="italic">(£20.4 m).</hi> </s></p></div4><div4><head><hi rend="bold">2.2.4 Directors' Report</hi><ref target="BAWE_0340b-ftnote.008"/><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0340b-ftnote.008"><p n="pn1.1"> Bodycote annual report 2005, pp. 13-16</p></note></head><p n="p45.100"><s n="s1.3;p45.100">The last report examined is that of the Directors. </s><s n="s2.3;p45.100">The particular report does not offer much financial information, however there are some data which can be used for the overall business performance analysis. </s><s n="s3.3;p45.100">Thus: </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p46.100"><s n="s1.1;p46.100">Bodycote carried out a Performance evaluation during 2005, where all the Executive Directors were evaluated, as well as the Chief Executive. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p47.100"><s n="s1.2;p47.100">Among the responsibilities of the Directors is to review the effectiveness of the Bodycote's system of internal control. </s><s n="s2.2;p47.100">It is stressed that this system manages rather eliminates <hi rend="italic">"the risk of failure to achieve business objectives"</hi>. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p48.100"><s n="s1.2;p48.100">It is also stated that Bodycote <hi rend="italic">"is committed to the achievement of the highest practicable standards of safety and health at work for all employees"</hi>, while it also tries to minimize its environmental effects. </s><s n="s2.2;p48.100">Moreover, -where applicable- environmental standards such as ISO 14001 and ISO 17025 are implemented. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p49.100"><s n="s1.1;p49.100">Bodycote tries to keep its employees informed about company's performance and progress, by giving them the opportunity to attend or participate in <hi rend="italic">"production, safety and health meetings at site level"</hi>. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p50.100"><s n="s1.1;p50.100">Bodycote invests on research and development so as to be capable of <hi rend="italic">"deploying the best technology available"</hi>. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p51.100"><s n="s1.1;p51.100">Finally Bodycote's creditor policy is defined by firm agreements and it is worth mentioning that Creditor days for 2004 and 2005 were 45 days. </s></p></div4></div3><div3><head><hi rend="bold">2.3 Ratio Analysis</hi><ref target="BAWE_0340b-ftnote.009"/><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0340b-ftnote.009"><p n="pn1.1"> The Ratios and their analysis used in this section are based on the notes of the WMG module Financial Analysis &amp; Control Systems, unless referenced otherwise.</p></note></head><p n="p52.100"><s n="s1.4;p52.100">Ratio Analysis is the next step in examining Bodycote's performance. </s><s n="s2.4;p52.100">According to Dyson J.R. (1994, p. 185), ratios can be a very useful tool on one's attempt to interpret financial accounts. </s><s n="s3.4;p52.100">Weetman P. </s><s n="s4.4;p52.100">(2003, p. 373) points out that <hi rend="italic">"ratios taken in isolation for a single company or a single period of time are of limited usefulness".</hi> </s></p><p n="p53.100"><s n="s1.2;p53.100">Based on the abovementioned, the ratios' comparison made here is for 2004 and 2005. </s><s n="s2.2;p53.100">The data <hi rend="italic">(in £m)</hi> used for the calculation of the ratios came from Bodycote's 2005 annual report and are presented in the following table. </s></p><table id="BAWE_0340b-tab.001"><head rend="bold">Table 1: Data used for the ratio analysis </head><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p54.100"><s n="s1.1;p54.100">The ratios calculated in the current assignment, are presented on the following table: </s></p><table id="BAWE_0340b-tab.002"><head rend="bold"> Table 2: Analytical table of ratios</head><row><cell/></row></table><div4><head rend="underlined bold">Return on Capital Employed</head><p n="p55.100"><s n="s1.1;p55.100">According to Dyson J.R. (1994, p. 188), the main use of ROCE is to avoid jumping to conclusions about the profit of a company, failing to take into account the capital employed for achieving this profit. </s></p><p n="p56.100"><s n="s1.4;p56.100">Bodycote's ROCE increased by 6.6%, from 7.38% in 2004 to 7.87% in 2005. </s><s n="s2.4;p56.100">This slight boost is due to the equal increase of Operating Profit and Capital Employed. </s><s n="s3.4;p56.100">According to Weetman P. </s><s n="s4.4;p56.100">(2003, p. 378) this increase could be the result of a better utilization of Total Assets. </s></p></div4><div4><head rend="underlined bold">Return on Total Assets</head><p n="p57.100"><s n="s1.2;p57.100">Return on Total Assets increased by 5.6% to 6.83% <hi rend="italic">(2004: 6.47%).</hi> </s><s n="s2.2;p57.100">Undoubtedly, this is an improvement for Bodycote which is mainly justified by the new acquisitions that the company made during the year and its exit from the electroplating business, causing thus a change in the mix of Bodycote's business. </s></p></div4><div4><head rend="underlined bold">Return on Shareholders' Funds</head><p n="p58.100"><s n="s1.1;p58.100">The results of this ratio <hi rend="italic">(2005: 12.16%; 2004: 11.07%)</hi> are an indication of the probable long-term prosperity of the company; Bodycote's stable profits and its reduced business risk -according to Chief Executive's review- attract new investments and shareholders' support, making thus company's future promising. </s></p></div4><div4><head rend="underlined bold">Gross Margin</head><p n="p59.100"><s n="s1.2;p59.100">Gross Margin does not present any significant change from 2004 <hi rend="italic">(33.26%)</hi> to 2005 <hi rend="italic">(33.72%)</hi>. </s><s n="s2.2;p59.100">Although, as abovementioned, the automotive sector in North America and Europe faced a <hi rend="italic">"challenging"</hi> period, the demand in the rest of the markets was increased <hi rend="italic">(see Finance Director's Report)</hi>; thus Bodycote's gross margin remained approximately the same. </s></p></div4><div4><head rend="underlined bold">Net Margin</head><p n="p60.100"><s n="s1.1;p60.100">The slight decrease of this ratio <hi rend="italic">(from 13.02% in 2004 to 12.95% in 2205)</hi> does not seem to be a source of worry, since both of operating profits and total sales increased for the 2 years, but with slightly different analogy. </s></p></div4><div4><head rend="underlined bold">Sales per £1 Capital Employed</head><p n="p61.100"><s n="s1.2;p61.100">From 0.57 in 2004 to 0.61 in 2005, the results of this ratio are probably low. </s><s n="s2.2;p61.100">However, one should take into account that Bodycote has not probably fully utilised the recent acquisitions and the investments it made; higher prices for the particular ratio can be expected for the next years, when the company will be in place to make full use of its utilities. </s></p></div4><div4><head rend="underlined bold">Non-Current Asset Turnover</head><p n="p62.100"><s n="s1.4;p62.100">Again here, although there is a slight increase of the ratio <hi rend="italic">(2004: 0.71; 2005: 0.73)</hi> its results are low. </s><s n="s2.4;p62.100">The same reasons as above possibly affect this ratio. </s><s n="s3.4;p62.100">The capital invested for the new acquisitions has not probably become fully productive, thus the ratio remains in low levels. </s><s n="s4.4;p62.100">As above, better results can be anticipated for the following years. </s></p></div4><div4><head rend="underlined bold">Inventory Turnover</head><p n="p63.100"><s n="s1.2;p63.100">The particular ratio decreased by 17.4% to 39.6 <hi rend="italic">(2004: 47.9)</hi>. </s><s n="s2.2;p63.100">According to Dyson J.R. (1994, p. 203), this means that the company does not <hi rend="italic">"turn over its stocks"</hi> as quickly as it did the previous year. </s></p><p n="p64.100"><s n="s1.3;p64.100">However, one must take into account that Bodycote is a company with various activities and, consequently, with a wide range of products/ services. </s><s n="s2.3;p64.100">This variety probably caused some difficulty in the efficient turnover of the stock to sales, especially after the new acquisitions. </s><s n="s3.3;p64.100">It should be noted that the calculation of the particular ratio is highly affected by the industry trends in inventory management. </s></p></div4><div4><head rend="underlined bold">Debtor days</head><p n="p65.100"><s n="s1.4;p65.100">According to Finance Directors' report <hi rend="italic">(see 2.2.3),</hi> the debtor days were increased from 65 to 68, resulting in an increase on debtors by £4.7 m. </s><s n="s2.4;p65.100">It is obvious that an increase in this ratio is not desirable for the company and it might had a downward impact on the cash statement, which decreased by £18.7 m. </s><s n="s3.4;p65.100">Nevertheless, Dyson J.R. (1994, p. 193) suggests that one must consider the type of the trade and the average debtor collection period for the market. </s><s n="s4.4;p65.100">Thus, it is difficult to draw any more definite conclusions without having any other information about market or competitors' policy. </s></p></div4><div4><head rend="underlined bold">Gearing</head><p n="p66.100"><s n="s1.3;p66.100">Gearing for Bodycote increased from 21% in 2004 to 25% in 2005. </s><s n="s2.3;p66.100">Although significant acquisitions have been made, Gearing has not increased dramatically and remains in relatively low level. </s><s n="s3.3;p66.100">These results prove that Bodycote is not heavily dependent on borrowings, since according to Finance Directors' Report <hi rend="italic">(see 2.2.3),</hi> the company is financed by a mixture of borrowings -short and long term-, cash flows from operations, finance leases etc. </s></p></div4><div4><head rend="underlined bold">Interest Cover</head><p n="p67.100"><s n="s1.2;p67.100">Finally, Interest Cover increased by 22% to 8.4 times <hi rend="italic">(2004: 6.9 times)</hi> since Bodycote's profitability increased, while its borrowings decreased. </s><s n="s2.2;p67.100">The results for this ratio highlight Bodycote's stability and independence in terms of financial resources; however, the figures must be compared with those of its rivals in order to draw a balanced conclusion. </s></p></div4></div3><div3><head rend="bold">2.4 Analysis of Press Releases &amp; Articles</head><p n="p68.100"><s n="s1.1;p68.100">In this part, one press release and four articles about Bodycote's performance are examined. </s></p><p n="p69.100"><s n="s1.2;p69.100">According to the November 3 <hi rend="sup">rd</hi> 2006 Press Release, Bodycote made <hi rend="italic">"further progress in the implementation of its stated corporate strategy",</hi> by acquiring six new businesses, which however will not contribute significantly on 2006 sales and profits. </s><s n="s2.2;p69.100">Furthermore, in 2007 Bodycote plans to <hi rend="italic">"invest approximately £12 m in heat treatment and testing Greenfield start-ups"</hi> in emerging markets" (Brazil, Mexico, Turkey, India, China). </s></p><p n="p70.100"><s n="s1.3;p70.100">On 15/08/2006 the advisory company <hi rend="italic">Merrill Lynch</hi> pointed out that Bodycote's future seems promising, since an ongoing growth in industrial production through 2007 is anticipated. </s><s n="s2.3;p70.100">Moreover, it was stated that Bodycote <hi rend="italic">"has a better medium term end-market profile than many peers",</hi> since it is orientated to the European market. </s><s n="s3.3;p70.100">(TMCnet NEWS, 2006a) </s></p><p n="p71.100"><s n="s1.2;p71.100">Later on the same month however, TMCnet NEWS (2006b) mentioned that Bodycote's performance failed to satisfy analysts' high expectations, since the company did not achieve to take full advantage of what it was thought to be <hi rend="italic">"the peak of the industrial cycle".</hi> </s><s n="s2.2;p71.100">Moreover, it was stated that Bodycote's expansion in China was made just to <hi rend="italic">"catch-up"</hi> with its rivals. </s></p><p n="p72.100"><s n="s1.2;p72.100">On the other hand, an article in the International Journal of Thermal Technology, <hi rend="italic">Industrial Heating</hi> (Aug. </s><s n="s2.2;p72.100">2006) mentioned that Bodycote's revenue from continuing operations increased by 21.8%; it was also stated that Bodycote continues to <hi rend="italic">"attract new businesses from manufacturers in key markets",</hi> and the company tries to <hi rend="italic">"boost its testing business"</hi> by expanding into new services and new markets. </s></p><p n="p73.100"><s n="s1.1;p73.100">Finally, in the same journal in September 2006 it was mentioned that Bodycote formed a strategic alliance with Dynamet Technology, Inc., thus Bodycote can participate more dynamically in the <hi rend="italic">"titanium product area"</hi>, which is thought to have important potentials. </s></p></div3></div2><div2><head rend="bold">3. Conclusion</head><p n="p74.100"><s n="s1.1;p74.100">At this point, it is worth making a brief summary of the key data derived from the previous analysis. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p75.100"><s n="s1.2;p75.100">Operating profit and Profit for the year increased in 2005 by 10% and 9% respectively. </s><s n="s2.2;p75.100">In addition, Bodycote's organic growth reached 5%, possibly indicating company's good managerial performance. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p76.100"><s n="s1.2;p76.100">The company could easily meet its Current Liabilities by making use of its Current Assets. </s><s n="s2.2;p76.100">To what is more, Bodycote has a variety of ways in covering its day-to-day requirements. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p77.100"><s n="s1.1;p77.100">There were some dynamic investing activities throughout 2005, which continued in 2006 and will carry on in 2007. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p78.100"><s n="s1.2;p78.100">Bodycote's geographical and market expansion reduces the associated business risk. </s><s n="s2.2;p78.100">Moreover, demand increased in most markets and future prospects of particular markets seem promising. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p79.100"><s n="s1.1;p79.100">The majority of the Ratios improved, demonstrating Bodycote's strong and consistent performance. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p80.100"><s n="s1.3;p80.100">The decrease of <hi rend="italic">Inventory Turnover</hi> by 17% is probably due to the many activities that Bodycote is involved in and to the new acquisitions and investments which have not been yet fully utilised. </s><s n="s2.3;p80.100">These new investments affected most of the ratios, keeping them in moderate levels; nevertheless, better results can be expected once the company takes full advantage of them. </s><s n="s3.3;p80.100">Moreover, the figures for <hi rend="italic">Interest Cover</hi> probably reveal Group's low financial risk. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p81.100"><s n="s1.1;p81.100">Lastly, according to the examined articles, company's future seems favourable since Bodycote has forcefully entered emerging markets, without however neglecting Europe and USA. </s></p><p n="p82.100"><s n="s1.2;p82.100">Undoubtedly, if parameters such as competitors' performance and industry's averages had been included, the whole analysis would have been more accurate and thorough. </s><s n="s2.2;p82.100">However, taking into account the published data, Bodycote's business and financial performance in 2005 can be characterised as satisfactory and the company's future seems encouraging. </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="text"><head rend="bold">Question 2<hi rend="italic">MANAGEMENT ACCOUNTING</hi></head><div2><head rend="bold">Part A</head><p n="p83.100"><s n="s1.1;p83.100">Before answering the assigned question, it is considered important to make a short review of team's strategy and author's role. </s></p><p n="p84.100"><s n="s1.4;p84.100">Team's goal was to become market leader to selected markets with the product 'Tiger', at the end of year 3. </s><s n="s2.4;p84.100">Thus, it was decided to invest both in new market and new product development. </s><s n="s3.4;p84.100">Author's role was that of the Commercial Manager and his main responsibility was to win orders. </s><s n="s4.4;p84.100">The orders that he was supposed to win had been discussed and agreed with the whole team, paying particular attention to production manager's view about machines' capacity. </s></p><p n="p85.100"><s n="s1.1;p85.100">After mentioning these data, the significance of cash management and the impact of the author's role upon the cash position of the business will be discussed. </s></p><p n="p86.100"><s n="s1.2;p86.100">On examining Year 2 Cash Flow Statement (see Appendix), one can easily realize that the company was in a difficult cash position at the end of year 2. </s><s n="s2.2;p86.100">The decrease in cash by $33 m was disappointing, but the reasons for this decrease had been identified well in advanced. </s></p><p n="p87.100"><s n="s1.6;p87.100">The cash management was poor. </s><s n="s2.6;p87.100">The team aimed to win as many as possible orders in year 1, and the author succeeded in it, after persuading the team to invest $14 m in <hi rend="italic">Engineering &amp; Quality</hi>. </s><s n="s3.6;p87.100">But on trying to complete the won orders, the team came to realise that it was short of cash; the team had failed to take into consideration other costs such as market, product and supplier development and stock expenses. </s><s n="s4.6;p87.100">The easy solution was to make discounts to customers and have bank loans to cover current liabilities. </s><s n="s5.6;p87.100">But both of them deteriorated team's cash position; although the team was achieving high sales, it could not make profit! </s><s n="s6.6;p87.100">That is when the team realised the importance of effective cash management. </s></p><p n="p88.100"><s n="s1.2;p88.100">In year 2, the team decided to invest less money in <hi rend="italic">Engineering &amp; Quality</hi>, but it did not succeed wining significant orders. </s><s n="s2.2;p88.100">Thus there was an increase in stock and debtors ($26 m and $19 m, respectively) and the company consumed $63 m! </s></p><p n="p89.100"><s n="s1.1;p89.100">The impact of the author's role upon the cash position of the business during the simulation can be summarised on the followings: </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p90.100"><s n="s1.2;p90.100">Commercial Manager was responsible for winning the orders. </s><s n="s2.2;p90.100">In order to do so, investments in <hi rend="italic">Engineering &amp; Quality</hi> were necessary, increasing thus the Investing activities of the team. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p91.100"><s n="s1.1;p91.100">Due to the inadequate cash management, in order to satisfy the won orders, team had to borrow money; thus, loans were rising each year (i.e. £30 m in year 2). </s></p><p n="p92.100"><s n="s1.5;p92.100">The impact of Commercial Manager's role in real business's cash management is also very important. </s><s n="s2.5;p92.100">Usually, he is responsible for all company's commercial and sales activities as well as for the relationships with the customers. </s><s n="s3.5;p92.100">The aforementioned activities can provide company with sales and accordingly cash flow. </s><s n="s4.5;p92.100">Just like the game, these orders (hopefully based on a better assessment of different factors, rather than machines' capacity as done above) may demand investments. </s><s n="s5.5;p92.100">These investments, in turn, create cash flows and affect the cash position of the company (i.e. new loans, discounting). </s></p><p n="p93.100"><s n="s1.1;p93.100">Concluding, effective management and close surveillance of cash are two significant elements in order for a company to be successful. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">Part B</head><div3><head rend="bold italic">Activity Based Costing</head><p n="p94.100"><s n="s1.4;p94.100">Firstly, it is considered important to give some data about Activity-Based Costing (ABC). </s><s n="s2.4;p94.100">Weetman P. </s><s n="s3.4;p94.100">(2003, p. 519) mentions that <hi rend="italic">"ABC is a relatively new approach to assigning overhead costs to products"</hi>, while Atkinsonal. (2004, pp. 127-128) state that costs are allocated to activities rather than cost centres, and that <hi rend="italic">"activities should describe what resources, such as people and equipment, are doing"</hi>. </s><s n="s4.4;p94.100">Furthermore, Bhimanial. (2002, p. 336) point out that <hi rend="italic">"by identifying the cost of performing each activity, ABC system seek a greater level of detail in understanding how an organisation uses its resources".</hi> </s></p><p n="p95.100"><s n="s1.4;p95.100">Using ABC method in the "Winning Margin <hi rend="sup">TM</hi>", could have been proved quite useful. </s><s n="s2.4;p95.100">Team's main decision was the development of a new product ('Tiger'), totally based on future sales' forecasts. </s><s n="s3.4;p95.100">Factors such as production cost (i.e. machines' set-up, machines' hours, demand of raw materials) and investments needed (i.e. new machines, suppliers development) in order to develop this new product, were completely ignored, since the team thought that achieving high sales in high prices would bring profit. </s><s n="s4.4;p95.100">But since the results were different from the expected ones, the implementation of ABC may have helped team to make a more circumstantial decision, taking into account the different activities necessary for the new final product, and the cost that these activities were generating in relationship with the product's potential profit. </s></p><p n="p96.100"><s n="s1.2;p96.100">In the complex real world, ABC can deter companies from either undercost <hi rend="italic">("makes sales that result in losses")</hi> or overcost products <hi rend="italic">("risk of losing market share")</hi> (Bhimanial. 2002, p. 332), by taking into account cost elements which traditional cost methods overlook. </s><s n="s2.2;p96.100">Thus, ABC methodology can be a very useful tool for the modern companies. </s></p></div3><div3><head rend="bold italic">Investment Appraisal</head><p n="p97.100"><s n="s1.4;p97.100">According to Moran K. </s><s n="s2.4;p97.100">(1997, p. 3), <hi rend="italic">"Investment Appraisal is about selecting investments where the benefits of the investment outweigh the costs and where the cash generated by the project more than outweighs the lost opportunities for shareholders and banks to invest elsewhere",</hi> while Mott G. </s><s n="s3.4;p97.100">(1997, p. 1) highlights that the main points of Investment Appraisal is <hi rend="italic">"whether, when and how"</hi> to invest capital on projects. </s><s n="s4.4;p97.100">One can focus on the following 5 appraisal methods: </s></p><list type="ordered"><item>Payback Period</item><item>Accounting Rate of Return</item><item>Net Present Value</item><item>Internal Rate of Return</item><item>Discounted Payback Period</item></list><p n="p98.100"><s n="s1.2;p98.100">(Mott G. </s><s n="s2.2;p98.100">1997, p. 52) </s></p><p n="p99.100"><s n="s1.5;p99.100">The first main decision that was made during the business simulation "Winning Margin <hi rend="sup">TM</hi>" was about the development of a new product ('Tiger'). </s><s n="s2.5;p99.100">By using one of the abovementioned techniques, the team could have made a more sound decision, based on other data too, rather than utterly on future sales' forecasts. </s><s n="s3.5;p99.100">By developing the 'Tiger', the team found itself in need of more machines. </s><s n="s4.5;p99.100">The investment in new machines was based on the production rate of the particular type of machines that the team bought. </s><s n="s5.5;p99.100">However, the team could have take into account factors such as the initial investment and the future cashflows on examining the alternative types of machines that were on sale; thus making a different, but more profitable choice. </s></p><p n="p100.100"><s n="s1.4;p100.100">In the real world, Investment Appraisal techniques are indispensable part of any investment decision and can function as a guide for financial managers. </s><s n="s2.4;p100.100">Nevertheless, it is worth mentioning that investments' future performances are to a certain extent based on forecasts, thus <hi rend="italic">"any Investment appraisal technique can only produce advice based on these forecasts"</hi> and not a success-guaranteed decision. </s><s n="s3.4;p100.100">(Lumby S &amp; Jones C. </s><s n="s4.4;p100.100">1999, p. 42) </s></p></div3></div2></div1></body><back><div1 type="bibliography"><head rend="underlined bold">References</head><p>Atkinson, A.A., Kaplan, S.R., Young M. S. (2004). <hi rend="italic">MANAGEMENT ACCOUNTING.</hi> 4<hi rend="sup">th</hi> Edition. THE ROBERT S. KAPLAN SERIES IN MANAGEMENT ACCOUNTING. PEARSON Prentice Hall.</p><p>Bhimani, A., Datar, S.M., Foster, G., Horngren, C.T. (2002). <hi rend="italic">Management and Cost Accounting.</hi> 2<hi rend="sup">nd</hi> Edition. Prentice Hall FINANCIAL TIMES. </p><p>Dyson, J. R. (1994). <hi rend="italic">Accounting for Non-Accounting Students.</hi> 3<hi rend="sup">rd</hi> Edition. Pitman Publishing.</p><p>Lumby, S., Jones, C. (1999). <hi rend="italic">INVSTMENT APPRAISAL &amp; FINANCIAL DECISIONS.</hi> 6<hi rend="sup">th</hi> Edition. INTERNATIONAL THOMSON BUSINESS PRESS. </p><p>Moran, K. (1997). <hi rend="italic">Investment Appraisal for Non-Financial Managers.</hi> PITMAN PUBLISHING.</p><p>Mott, G. (1997). <hi rend="italic">Investment Appraisal.</hi> 3<hi rend="sup">rd</hi> Edition. PITMAN PUBLISHING.</p><p>Weetman, P. (2003). <hi rend="italic">Financial &amp; Management Accounting AN INTRODUCTION.</hi> 3<hi rend="sup">rd</hi> Edition. Prentice Hall Financial Times.</p><p>Industrial Heating, The International Journal of Thermal Technology. <hi rend="italic">Bodycote, Dynamet Technology Form Alliance.</hi> (September 19, 2006). (URL <seg type="URL" n="http://www.industrialheating.com/CDA/Articles/Industry_News/2b21d969d96cd010VgnVCM100000f932a8c0"/> ) [Accessed 25 Nov. 06] </p><p>Industrial Heating, The International Journal of Thermal Technology. <hi rend="italic">Rise in Profits Fuels Bodycote's Expansion.</hi> (August 24, 2006). (URL <seg type="URL" n="http://www.industrialheating.com/CDA/Articles/Industry_News/9d0d6d419904d010VgnVCM100000f932a8c0"/> ) [Accessed 25 Nov. 06]</p><p>PRESS RELEASE. <hi rend="italic">Bodycote Intnl. PLC- Corporate Developments</hi>. (03 November 2006). RNS Number: 5041L. </p><p>(URL <seg type="URL" n="http://www.hemscott.com/news/rna/item.do?newsId=37142877389557"/> )</p><p>[Accessed 25 Nov. 06]</p><p>TMCnet NEWS<hi rend="italic">. Body-Built</hi>. (August 15, 2006a).</p><p>(URL <seg type="URL" n="http://www.tmcnet.com/usubmit/2006/08/15/1794305.htm"/> )</p><p>[Accessed 25 Nov. 06] </p><p>TMCnet NEWS. <hi rend="italic">Bodycote's leap disappoints.</hi> (August 23, 2006b). (URL <seg type="URL" n="http://www.tmcnet.com/usubmit/-bodycotes-leap-disappoints-/2006/08/23/1824314.htm"/> ) [Accessed 25 Nov. 06] </p><p rend="underlined">Also:</p><p><hi rend="italic">About us.</hi> (URL <seg type="URL" n="http://www.bodycote.com/?OB=2"/> ) [Accessed 21 Nov. 06]</p><p><hi rend="italic">Bodycote plc Website</hi> (URL <seg type="URL" n="http://www.bodycote.com/"/> ) </p><p>[Accessed 21 Nov. 06] </p><p><hi rend="italic">Customer Relations.</hi> (URL <seg type="URL" n="http://www.bodycote.com/?OB=19&amp;POB=2"/> ) [Accessed 21 Nov. 06]</p><p><hi rend="italic">History.</hi> (URL <seg type="URL" n="http://www.bodycote.com/?OB=18&amp;POB=2"/> ) </p><p>[Accessed 21 Nov. 06]</p><p><hi rend="italic">Markets We Serve.</hi> (URL <seg type="URL" n="http://www.bodycote.com/?OB=25&amp;POB=3"/> ) [Accessed 21 Nov. 06]</p><p><hi rend="italic">Report &amp; Accounts.</hi> (URL <seg type="URL" n="http://www.bodycote.com/?OB=33&amp;POB=6"/>) [Accessed 21 Nov. 06]</p><p><hi rend="italic">Strategy.</hi> (URL <seg type="URL" n="http://www.bodycote.com/?OB=17&amp;POB=2"/>) </p><p>[Accessed 21 Nov. 06]</p><p><hi rend="italic">What We Do.</hi> (URL <seg type="URL" n="http://www.bodycote.com/?OB=3"/> ) [Accessed 21 Nov. 06]</p><p rend="underlined">As well as:</p><p>Notes of the <name type="university"/> Manufacturing Group module: <hi rend="italic">Financial Analysis &amp; Control Systems</hi>. 2006 FOCUS Business Development &amp; Training Consultancy</p></div1><div1 type="appendix"><head rend="bold italic">Appendix "Winning MarginTM": Year 2 Cash Flow Statement </head><p/></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
