<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_0341c" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Water Pipe Flow</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">The document has a title page which contains:
document title
title part</note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">deleted: page numbers, date</note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">appendix: laboratory handout, results</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">2</p><p n="date">2007-03</p><p n="module title">Fluid Mechanics</p><p n="module code">ES252</p><p n="genre family">Methodology recount</p><p n="discipline">Engineering</p><p n="disciplinary group">PS</p><p n="grade">unknown</p><p n="number of authors">unknown</p><p n="number of words">1334</p><p n="number of s-units">74</p><p n="number of p">41</p><p n="number of tables">0</p><p n="number of figures">2</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">2</p><p n="number of lists">2</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">15</p><p n="abstract present">abstract present</p><p n="average words per s-unit">18.0</p><p n="average s-units per p">1.8</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">m</p><p n="year of birth">1985</p><p n="first language">English</p><p n="education">UKA</p><p n="course">Mechanical Engineering MEng</p><p n="student ID">0341</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><titlePart rend="bold">University of <name type="university"/> School of Engineering</titlePart><docTitle><titlePart rend="bold">Water Pipe Flow Group - W17 (<name type="student name"/>, <name type="student name"/>, <name type="student name"/>, <name type="student name"/>) </titlePart></docTitle><titlePart><hi rend="bold">By<name type="student name"/></hi><hi rend="bold"><name type="student ID"/></hi></titlePart><titlePart>Report Reference Code: ES252A2 Affiliation: Year 2 mechanical engineering</titlePart></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="abstract"><head rend="bold">Summary</head><p n="p1.41"><s n="s1.3;p1.41">The main objective of this assignment is to analyze the transition between turbulent and laminar flow in water. </s><s n="s2.3;p1.41">This was achieved by measuring the pressure drop, flow rate and temperature of water flowing through various cylindrical pipes. </s><s n="s3.3;p1.41">The pipes used had the following diameters; 4mm smooth, 15mm rough and 17mm smooth. </s></p><p n="p2.41"><s n="s1.1;p2.41">The values obtained were computated using the amfield fluid friction software, which derived the Reynolds number and friction factor. </s></p><p n="p3.41"><s n="s1.1;p3.41">The Reynolds number and friction factor increased with the velocity of flow, more energy was lost at higher velocities. </s></p><p n="p4.41"><s n="s1.1;p4.41">Conclusions were: </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p5.41"><s n="s1.1;p5.41">A rough pipe will have a high friction factor (around 0.5); </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p6.41"><s n="s1.1;p6.41">A smooth pipe will give a basic skin friction (friction factor of around 0.2); </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p7.41"><s n="s1.1;p7.41">A pipe with a 4mm diameter will show the turbulent to laminar transition at low velocities (at velocities of below 1m/s the Reynolds number is less than 4000); </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p8.41"><s n="s1.1;p8.41">Fluid viscosity is significantly effected by the temperature; </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p9.41"><s n="s1.1;p9.41">Head loss decreases with velocity. </s></p></div1><div1 type="front-back-matter"><head rend="bold">Table of Contents</head><p/></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">1.0 Introduction</head><list type="bulleted"><head>Aims of the laboratory:</head><item>To view the turbulent-laminar transition in water, as it is pumped through a pipe;</item><item>To view the difference in skin friction between rough and smooth surfaces;</item><item>Draw comparisons between experimentally obtained values and the moody chart.</item></list><p n="p10.41"><s n="s1.1;p10.41">From the experiment it was concluded: </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p11.41"><s n="s1.1;p11.41">A rough pipe will have a high friction factor; </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p12.41"><s n="s1.1;p12.41">A smooth pipe will give a basic skin friction; </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p13.41"><s n="s1.1;p13.41">A pipe with a 4mm diameter will show the turbulent to laminar transition at low velocities; </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p14.41"><s n="s1.1;p14.41">Fluid viscosity is significantly effected by the temperature; </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p15.41"><s n="s1.1;p15.41">Head loss decreases with velocity. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">2.0 Theory</head><div2><head rend="bold">Types of Flow; Reynolds Number </head><p n="p16.41"><s n="s1.3;p16.41">Fluid flow can be either laminar or turbulent. </s><s n="s2.3;p16.41">The factor that determines which type of flow is present is the ratio of inertia forces to viscous forces within the fluid, expressed by the non-dimensional Reynolds Number, <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0341c-form.001"/>, where <hi rend="italic">V</hi> and <hi rend="italic">D</hi> are a fluid characteristic velocity and distance. </s><s n="s3.3;p16.41">For example, for fluid flowing in a pipe, <hi rend="italic">V</hi> could be the average fluid velocity, and <hi rend="italic">D</hi> would be the pipe diameter. </s></p><p n="p17.41"><s n="s1.1;p17.41">Typically, viscous stresses within a fluid tend to stabilize and organize the flow, whereas excessive fluid inertia tends to disrupt organized flow leading to chaotic turbulent behaviour. </s></p><p n="p18.41"><s n="s1.3;p18.41">Fluid flows are laminar for Reynolds Numbers up to 2000. </s><s n="s2.3;p18.41">Beyond a Reynolds Number of 4000, the flow is completely turbulent. </s><s n="s3.3;p18.41">Between 2000 and 4000, the flow is in transition between laminar and turbulent, and it is possible to find sub-regions of both flow types within a given flow field. </s></p><p n="p19.41"><s n="s1.1;p19.41">For detailed theory on the calculation process see appendix </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">3.0 Apparatus and Methods</head><list type="bulleted"><head>Apparatus used,</head><item>Thermometer</item><item>Manometer</item><item>4mm, 15mm and 17mm pipe rig</item></list><p n="p20.41"><s n="s1.2;p20.41">Here are some pictures of the pipe rig used. </s><s n="s2.2;p20.41">On the left is the rig itself and on the right is the valve used to determine the velocity at which the water entered the pipe. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0341c-pic.001"/><figure id="BAWE_0341c-pic.002"/><p n="p21.41"><s n="s1.1;p21.41">Computation software used - Armfield Fluid Friction </s></p><p n="p22.41"><s n="s1.1;p22.41">For method see appendix - lab handout </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">4.0 Observations and Results</head><p n="p23.41"><s n="s1.1;p23.41">For result tables and graphs see appendices </s></p><div2><head>Errors in the experiment</head><div3><head>Volume</head><p n="p24.41"><s n="s1.3;p24.41">The scale for the recording of the volume has definite inaccuracies; the scale itself had large increments giving an error of about +/-0.5L. The computation of the data also led to a loss of accuracy. </s><s n="s2.3;p24.41">The volume in the table has been converted to <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0341c-form.002"/> and rounded to 3 decimal places. </s><s n="s3.3;p24.41">In the case of the 4mm pipe this has lead to some major inaccuracies, with the last 3 recordings registering as volume = 0. </s></p></div3><div3><head>Time</head><p n="p25.41"><s n="s1.2;p25.41">This is linked to the volume, in that the clock is stopped when the volume reaches a predetermined level. </s><s n="s2.2;p25.41">Due to the rate at which the water rises, this is quite inaccurate, and more so the greater the velocity of the water. </s></p></div3><div3><head>Pressure</head><p n="p26.41"><s n="s1.2;p26.41">There were large fluxuations in the digital reading for the pressure change. </s><s n="s2.2;p26.41">This meant that the readings taken had inaccuracies of up to +/-0.1 mH2O. </s></p></div3><div3><head>Temperature</head><p n="p27.41"><s n="s1.1;p27.41">This was recorded using a standard thermometer, which unfortunately is fairly bad at recording small temperature changes. </s></p></div3></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">5.0 Analysis and Discussion of Results</head><div2><head>17mm Smooth Pipe</head><p n="p28.41"><s n="s1.6;p28.41">These results show a basic skin friction. </s><s n="s2.6;p28.41">From the results table it is clear that for this particular pipe all the Reynolds numbers fall between 10000 and 70000. </s><s n="s3.6;p28.41">Now this is clearly turbulent flow with little linearity. </s><s n="s4.6;p28.41">The Reynolds number drops throughout the sample due to the decreased flow rate and velocity of the sample, at higher velocities the water has a higher kinetic energy hence a higher turbulence and Reynolds number. </s><s n="s5.6;p28.41">There are a few anomalies in the friction factor; the value seems to increase significantly for the last few values. </s><s n="s6.6;p28.41">In these cases the volume collected was relatively small and so this rise is likely to be due to errors in the process. </s></p><p n="p29.41"><s n="s1.3;p29.41">From the graph in the appendix it can be seen that the pressure loss, or head loss, decreases as the velocity decreases. </s><s n="s2.3;p29.41">This is due to the fact that as the velocity increases the skin friction will have a greater effect on the liquid. </s><s n="s3.3;p29.41">From the table it can be seen that at velocities of 0.59 m/s the head loss is as low as 0.025 mH2O, in comparison to 0.819 mH2O at a velocity of 3.974 m/s. </s></p></div2><div2><head>15mm Rough Pipe</head><p n="p30.41"><s n="s1.4;p30.41">From the tables you can see that in this case the friction factor averages out at more than double that of the 17mm smooth pipe. </s><s n="s2.4;p30.41">The rough inner surface of this pipe gives it this large friction factor. </s><s n="s3.4;p30.41">The Reynolds number is slightly lower than that of the smooth pipe for similar velocities; compare 57535 at a velocity of 3.751 for the 15mm pipe to 64745 at a velocity of 3.725 for the smooth 17mm pipe. </s><s n="s4.4;p30.41">This shows that the flow is not quite as turbulent as in the smooth pipe due to the restrictive factor of the rough surface. </s></p><p n="p31.41"><s n="s1.2;p31.41">Again it can be seen, from the graph of head loss against velocity, that the head loss decreases as the velocity is decreased. </s><s n="s2.2;p31.41">This graph shows a linear fitting suggesting that the head loss is proportional to the velocity of the water. </s></p></div2><div2><head>4mm Smooth Pipe</head><p n="p32.41"><s n="s1.8;p32.41">For this pipe the transition between turbulent and laminar flow is visible. </s><s n="s2.8;p32.41">The transitional period occurs with Reynolds numbers greater than 2000 and less than 4000. </s><s n="s3.8;p32.41">Anything below 2000 is theoretically laminar flow. </s><s n="s4.8;p32.41">On page 2 of the 4mm table Reynolds numbers ranging from around 12000 to 1873 are shown. </s><s n="s5.8;p32.41">The final recording shows laminar flow, and recordings 8 and 9 show the transition. </s><s n="s6.8;p32.41">These three are at very low velocities. </s><s n="s7.8;p32.41">For the final recording, when the flow is laminar, the table shows a very low head loss of 0.076 mH2O. When the flow is laminar the energy of the water is conserved to a higher degree. </s><s n="s8.8;p32.41">Turbulence causes inefficiencies. </s></p><p n="p33.41"><s n="s1.1;p33.41">Again the graph of head loss against velocity shows a relatively linear relationship, further reinforcing the assumed relationship between the two. </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">6.0 Recommendations</head><p n="p34.41"><s n="s1.5;p34.41">The results collected were limited by many factors. </s><s n="s2.5;p34.41">Further work is needed to study the turbulent-laminar transition. </s><s n="s3.5;p34.41">Pipes with diameters of less than 4mm should be studied to get a detailed view of this transition. </s><s n="s4.5;p34.41">Another limitation was the velocity at which the water entered the system; the valve gave a limit on the maximum speed. </s><s n="s5.5;p34.41">The pipes should be tested again at higher velocities to see how the head loss responds. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">7.0 Conclusions</head><p n="p35.41"><s n="s1.1;p35.41">From these results it can be concluded: </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p36.41"><s n="s1.1;p36.41">A rough pipe will have a high friction factor (around 0.5); </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p37.41"><s n="s1.1;p37.41">A smooth pipe will give a basic skin friction (friction factor of around 0.2); </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p38.41"><s n="s1.1;p38.41">A pipe with a 4mm diameter will show the turbulent to laminar transition at low velocities (at velocities of below 1m/s the Reynolds number is less than 4000); </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p39.41"><s n="s1.1;p39.41">Fluid viscosity is significantly effected by the temperature; </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p40.41"><s n="s1.1;p40.41">Head loss decreases with velocity. </s></p><p n="p41.41"><s n="s1.1;p41.41">Although it seems that head loss and velocity are directly proportional it would be impossible to draw this as a conclusion without further research. </s></p></div1></body><back><div1 type="bibliography"><div2 type="bibliography"><head rend="bold">8.0 References</head><p>Lab briefing sheet used for theory, apparatus and method (Youngmann)</p></div2><div2 type="bibliography"><head rend="bold">9.0 Bibliography</head><p>Fluid Mechanics Volume 1 (Douglass)</p><p>Fluid Mechanics Volume 2 (Douglass)</p><p>Fluid Mechanics 5<hi rend="sup">th</hi> Edition (McGraw-Hill)</p></div2></div1><div1 type="appendix"><head rend="bold">Appendices</head><p/></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
