<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_0341f" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Heat Exchanger Design Exercise</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">The document has a title page which contains:
document title
title part</note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">deleted: date, page numbers</note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">Running text contains reference to external or missing appendix.
</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">3</p><p n="date">2007-03</p><p n="module title">Heat Transfer Theory and Design</p><p n="module code">ES353</p><p n="genre family">Design specification</p><p n="discipline">Engineering</p><p n="disciplinary group">PS</p><p n="grade">unknown</p><p n="number of authors">unknown</p><p n="number of words">2540</p><p n="number of s-units">177</p><p n="number of p">108</p><p n="number of tables">2</p><p n="number of figures">2</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">22</p><p n="number of lists">5</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">42</p><p n="abstract present">abstract present</p><p n="average words per s-unit">14.4</p><p n="average s-units per p">1.6</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">m</p><p n="year of birth">1985</p><p n="first language">English</p><p n="education">UKA</p><p n="course">Mechanical Engineering MEng</p><p n="student ID">0341</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><titlePart rend="bold">University of <name type="university"/> School of Engineering</titlePart><docTitle><titlePart><hi rend="bold">ES353A1 Heat Transfer Theory and Design</hi> <hi rend="bold"> Heat Exchanger Design Exercise</hi></titlePart></docTitle><titlePart rend="bold">By<name type="student ID"/></titlePart><titlePart>Report Reference Code: ES353A1 Affiliation: Year 3 Mechanical Engineering</titlePart></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="abstract"><head rend="bold">Summary</head><p n="p1.108"><s n="s1.3;p1.108">The objective of this report is to design a cross-flow heat exchanger which gives optimum payback time. </s><s n="s2.3;p1.108">The design variables are height, depth, fan model, and fin type. </s><s n="s3.3;p1.108">The optimum design was found by analysis of fins and fans, followed by an iterative procedure. </s></p><p n="p2.108"><s n="s1.1;p2.108">From the results the following conclusions can be drawn; </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p3.108"><s n="s1.2;p3.108">The lower power fans are more appropriate for this type of heat exchanger. </s><s n="s2.2;p3.108">The capital costs have a negative impact on the payback time, hence only the lower power fans are economically viable. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p4.108"><s n="s1.1;p4.108">The louvered fin design is much more efficient and effective that the plain fin design due to larger surface area and increased turbulence. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p5.108"><s n="s1.1;p5.108">The effectiveness increases with size of the heat exchanger. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p6.108"><s n="s1.2;p6.108">The best design was found be a heat exchanger of width 0.22809m, height 0.22809m and depth 0.65872m utilizing the louvered 10.39 fins, with the 83GW 6pole fan. </s><s n="s2.2;p6.108">This design gave the optimum payback time of 2.21 years. </s></p></div1><div1 type="front-back-matter"><head rend="bold">Table of Contents</head><p/></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Introduction</head><p n="p7.108"><s n="s1.4;p7.108">Heat exchangers are commonly used to transfer heat from steam, water, or gases, to gases, or liquids. </s><s n="s2.4;p7.108">The purpose of this report is to optimise the design of a cross-flow heat exchanger in order to obtain the most desirable payback time. </s><s n="s3.4;p7.108">Heat exchangers play a dominant role in the performance of most energy systems; however, optimization of these components is a complex task due to the coupled nature of the design parameters involved. </s><s n="s4.4;p7.108">Anytime the heat transfer coefficient is increased in these components, there is a corresponding increase in frictional pressure drop; therefore, a delicate balance is required between these two effects in heat exchanger optimization. </s></p><p n="p8.108"><s n="s1.2;p8.108">The report shows that the best design was found be a heat exchanger of width 0.22809m, height 0.22809m and depth 0.65872m utilizing the louvered 10.39 fins, with the 83GW 6pole fan. </s><s n="s2.2;p8.108">This design gave the optimum payback time of 2.21 years. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Theory</head><p n="p9.108"><s n="s1.1;p9.108">Formulae used in calculations and spreadsheet, taken from appendices 2-6. </s></p><p n="p10.108"><s n="s1.1;p10.108"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0341f-form.001"/> </s></p><p n="p11.108"><s n="s1.1;p11.108"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0341f-form.002"/> </s></p><p n="p12.108"><s n="s1.1;p12.108"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0341f-form.003"/> </s></p><p n="p13.108"><s n="s1.1;p13.108"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0341f-form.004"/> </s></p><p n="p14.108"><s n="s1.1;p14.108"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0341f-form.005"/> </s></p><p n="p15.108"><s n="s1.1;p15.108"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0341f-form.006"/> </s></p><p n="p16.108"><s n="s1.1;p16.108"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0341f-form.007"/> </s></p><p n="p17.108"><s n="s1.1;p17.108"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0341f-form.008"/> </s></p><p n="p18.108"><s n="s1.1;p18.108"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0341f-form.009"/> </s></p><p n="p19.108"><s n="s1.1;p19.108"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0341f-form.010"/> </s></p><p n="p20.108"><s n="s1.1;p20.108"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0341f-form.011"/> </s></p><p n="p21.108"><s n="s1.1;p21.108"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0341f-form.012"/> </s></p><p n="p22.108"><s n="s1.1;p22.108"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0341f-form.013"/> </s></p><p n="p23.108"><s n="s1.1;p23.108"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0341f-form.014"/> </s></p><p n="p24.108"><s n="s1.1;p24.108"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0341f-form.015"/> </s></p><p n="p25.108"><s n="s1.1;p25.108"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0341f-form.016"/> </s></p><p n="p26.108"><s n="s1.1;p26.108"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0341f-form.017"/> </s></p><p n="p27.108"><s n="s1.1;p27.108"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0341f-form.018"/> </s></p><p n="p28.108"><s n="s1.1;p28.108"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0341f-form.019"/> </s></p><p n="p29.108"><s n="s1.1;p29.108"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0341f-form.020"/> </s></p><p n="p30.108"><s n="s1.1;p30.108"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0341f-form.021"/> </s></p><p n="p31.108"><s n="s1.1;p31.108"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0341f-form.022"/> </s></p><div2><head rend="bold">Cross-flow Heat Exchanger</head><figure id="BAWE_0341f-fig.001"/><p n="p32.108"/></div2><div2><head rend="bold">Design Procedure Chart</head><figure id="BAWE_0341f-fig.002"/><p n="p33.108"/></div2><div2><head rend="bold">Fin Designs</head><p n="p34.108"><s n="s1.3;p34.108">The two fin designs focused on are the plain plate-fin and the louvered fin. </s><s n="s2.3;p34.108">Five plain plate-fin and three louvered fin designs will be analysed. </s><s n="s3.3;p34.108">The dominant thermal resistance in compact heat exchangers occurs on the airside, and fins are used to reduce this thermal resistance and improve the heat exchanger overall performance. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0341f-pic.001"/><p n="p35.108"><s n="s1.1;p35.108">Plain fins are sheet metal with corrugated fins at right angles to the sheet </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0341f-pic.002"/><p n="p36.108"><s n="s1.1;p36.108">Louvered fins are composed of several interrupted surfaces that interact with the boundary layer and generate complex air-flow patterns. </s></p><p n="p37.108"><s n="s1.1;p37.108">The eight designs being analysed are illustrated in appendices 11-12. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">Fouling</head><p n="p38.108"><s n="s1.3;p38.108">During the lifetime of a heat exchanger its performance will be influenced by what happens on the surface where the heat is exchanged. </s><s n="s2.3;p38.108">On the surface deposits of materials can accumulate that reduce the heat transfer and increase the pressure drop. </s><s n="s3.3;p38.108">This is referred to as fouling. </s></p><p n="p39.108"><s n="s1.1;p39.108">A number of questions arise when one designs a heat exchanger: </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p40.108"><s n="s1.1;p40.108">How much additional surface is needed to cater for fouling? </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p41.108"><s n="s1.1;p41.108">How much additional pressure drop can be expected due to fouling? </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p42.108"><s n="s1.1;p42.108">Are provisions needed for cleaning (chemical or mechanical)? </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p43.108"><s n="s1.1;p43.108">Is regular cleaning / inspection required </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p44.108"><s n="s1.1;p44.108">Is it possible to reduce the buildup? </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p45.108"><s n="s1.1;p45.108">Which materials of construction are preferred? </s></p><p n="p46.108"><s n="s1.2;p46.108">Fouling can be caused by several mechanisms which in fact can happen at the same time (combined). </s><s n="s2.2;p46.108">The most important basic mechanisms are: </s></p><list type="bulleted"><item>Crystallization (e.g. Mg- and Ca- bicarbonates) </item><item>Decomposition of organic products resulting in tar or cokes </item><item>Polymerization and or oxidation </item><item>Settlement of sludge, rust or dust particles </item><item>Biological deposits </item><item>Corrosion</item></list><p n="p47.108"><s n="s1.3;p47.108">The tendency for fouling depends on many variables that influence each other and can be difficult to address with a theoretical model. </s><s n="s2.3;p47.108">Allowing for fouling is therefore a matter of experience. </s><s n="s3.3;p47.108">Due to a lack of experience in the field of heat exchanger design and time constraints, fouling will not be considered in the design process. </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">The Problem</head><p n="p48.108"><s n="s1.1;p48.108">The heat exchanger analysis will be based around the following problem; </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p49.108"><s n="s1.1;p49.108">The allowable pressure drop in the extract side of the heat exchanger is 300Pa and the flow rate is 700m^3/hr </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p50.108"><s n="s1.1;p50.108">The heating season is October to April inclusive with a mean outside temperature of 7.5C whilst the plant is in operation (8 hours/day, 5 days/week) </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p51.108"><s n="s1.4;p51.108">The factory is heated by oil costing 22p/litre with S.G. </s><s n="s2.4;p51.108">0.8 and a calorific value of 45 MJ/Kg. </s><s n="s3.4;p51.108">The heating system efficiency is 70%. </s><s n="s4.4;p51.108">Electricity costs 5p/kWh. </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p52.108"><s n="s1.1;p52.108">Assume the pressure drop is the fresh air duct is 3x the dynamic head. </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p53.108"><s n="s1.1;p53.108">Assume equal flow rates and properties on both sides of the heat exchanger. </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p54.108"><s n="s1.1;p54.108">Construction material is aluminium, conductivity 173 W/mK, cost £1.65/Kg. </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p55.108"><s n="s1.1;p55.108">Overheads of 400% apply to the aluminium used in the heat exchanger, fresh air duct and casing. </s></p><p n="p56.108"><s n="s1.1;p56.108">A diagram of the problem can be seen in appendix 1. </s></p><div2><head rend="bold">Assumptions</head><p n="p57.108"><s n="s1.1;p57.108">In heat exchanger analysis three important assumptions are made; </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p58.108"><s n="s1.2;p58.108">U is constant through the heat exchanger. </s><s n="s2.2;p58.108">A reasonable assumption for the cross-flow design. </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p59.108"><s n="s1.2;p59.108">U may be predicted from forced convection correlations. </s><s n="s2.2;p59.108">Prediction from theory and dimensional analysis can result in large uncertainties. </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p60.108"><s n="s1.1;p60.108">Design is a collection of compromises; </s></p><list type="ordered"><item>Effectiveness</item><item>Pressure drop</item><item>Total size and volume</item><item>Cost</item><item>Reliability</item></list><p n="p61.108"><s n="s1.1;p61.108">Ease of maintenance </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p62.108"><s n="s1.1;p62.108">All physical properties for incoming fluid flows are known. </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p63.108"><s n="s1.1;p63.108">The heat exchanger is insulated from its surroundings, the only heat exchange is between hot and cold fluids </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p64.108"><s n="s1.1;p64.108">Conduction along the walls is negligible </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p65.108"><s n="s1.1;p65.108">Potential and kinetic energy changes are negligible </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p66.108"><s n="s1.1;p66.108">Fluid is flowing in one direction inside each tube </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p67.108"><s n="s1.1;p67.108">All fluids enter the heat exchanger with uniform velocity </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">Analytical 'Forced' Errors</head><p rend="bulleted" n="p68.108"><s n="s1.3;p68.108">When calculating the pressure loss coefficients in the analysis of the fin designs only two graphs were available to extract data, these are shown in appendices 9-10. </s><s n="s2.3;p68.108">These graphs applied to triangular and square tube entrances, and several graphs did not fall perfectly under these categories. </s><s n="s3.3;p68.108">The most realistic approximation was made in each case, for example the louvered fin 10.38 was taken as a triangular tube entrance. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p69.108"><s n="s1.1;p69.108">The tolerance levels for the fans are not specific and so an assumed error had to be used. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p70.108"><s n="s1.2;p70.108">Change in duct pressure was a realistic 'guess' giving an unknown error on the total pressure drop. </s><s n="s2.2;p70.108">This error would influence fan choice, hence payback time. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p71.108"><s n="s1.2;p71.108">The louvered fins cannot be analysed properly. </s><s n="s2.2;p71.108">Data for louver gap and spacing cannot be utilised, and so the louvered fins were analysed in an identical way to the plain-plate fins. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">Apparatus</head><p n="p72.108"><s n="s1.1;p72.108">Software used for spreadsheet and calculation - Excel </s></p><p n="p73.108"><s n="s1.1;p73.108">Macro 'Solver' used for iterative optimization procedure. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">Optimisation Technique</head><p n="p74.108"><s n="s1.4;p74.108">The objective of this design exercise is to find the most cost-effective waste heat recovery system by minimising the payback time. </s><s n="s2.4;p74.108">Due to the many variables this will be an iterative process. </s><s n="s3.4;p74.108">The most important inputs are choice of fin and fan. </s><s n="s4.4;p74.108">The payback time for each fan will be analysed for each fin design. </s></p><p n="p75.108"><s n="s1.1;p75.108">Optimisation Steps </s></p><list type="ordered"><item>Analyse fan data and remove inappropriate fans</item><item>Design spreadsheet implementing formulae from theory section to calculate payback time.</item><item>Find optimum payback times when each fan is combined with the different fins</item></list></div2><div2><head rend="bold">Fan Analysis</head><p n="p76.108"><s n="s1.2;p76.108">The fans shown in appendices 7-8 can cope with varied levels of static pressure. </s><s n="s2.2;p76.108">In general, fan price will increase with level of static pressure, therefore a trade-off must be drawn between size of heat exchanger (related to pressure drop) and price of fan (including running costs). </s></p><p n="p77.108"><s n="s1.1;p77.108">In order to select an appropriate fan efficiently, and to draw comparisons between fans that can cope with a comparable amount of pressure, a table can be made to highlight the most important characteristics. </s></p><table id="BAWE_0341f-tab.001"><head>Fig 1</head><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p78.108"><s n="s1.1;p78.108">Some fans from the data table in appendices 7-8 are not shown here as they are not applicable to the volume flow (~410 Ft/Min). </s></p><p n="p79.108"><s n="s1.2;p79.108">Due to likely inaccuracies in the graphs and data tables provided in appendices 7-8, and to leave some room for design inaccuracies and manufacturers tolerances, the static pressures are in increments of 50. </s><s n="s2.2;p79.108">Fans that can cope with these pressures comfortably are shown. </s></p><p n="p80.108"><s n="s1.2;p80.108">It can be seen from fig 1 that some of the fans can be removed for analysis purposes. </s><s n="s2.2;p80.108">The 4 pole 76FW has a higher price and running current than its comparable model, and the 6 pole 114HW is nearly twice the price of the 4 pole 83GW. These models are highlighted. </s></p><p n="p81.108"><s n="s1.1;p81.108">Therefore the possible fans to be used in the heat exchanger are; </s></p><table id="BAWE_0341f-tab.002"><head>Fig. 2</head><row><cell/></row></table></div2><div2><head rend="bold">Excel Formulation</head><p n="p82.108"><s n="s1.8;p82.108">The equations shown in the theory section were used in the optimisation of the heat exchanger design. </s><s n="s2.8;p82.108">They were entered into a spreadsheet, using excels formula function. </s><s n="s3.8;p82.108">The spreadsheet automatically calculates various functions when a number of user inputs are applied. </s><s n="s4.8;p82.108">This enables a quick iterative procedure, and efficient constructive analysis. </s><s n="s5.8;p82.108">The formulation can be seen in appendices 24-25, which shows a trial run. </s><s n="s6.8;p82.108">The functions are grey and the user inputs are left black. </s><s n="s7.8;p82.108">The final output is the payback time of the heat exchanger. </s><s n="s8.8;p82.108">This is changed dramatically by changes to the inputs. </s></p><p n="p83.108"><s n="s1.4;p83.108">In order to analyse every possible heat exchanger this spreadsheet is applied to the different fin types by inputting given values found in appendices 11-12. </s><s n="s2.4;p83.108">The fins are then analysed using each fan type shown in fig 2. </s><s n="s3.4;p83.108">The values for heat-transfer coefficient and friction factor are found by using the graphs in appendices 11-12. </s><s n="s4.4;p83.108">This means that every time the Reynolds number changes so do these values. </s></p><p n="p84.108"><s n="s1.5;p84.108">Excels 'solver' function is the most efficient and accurate iterative procedure, however due to the number of variables, some user input is required as well. </s><s n="s2.5;p84.108">Using fin 10.23 (see appendix 12) as an example, the procedure for using solver is shown in the plastic wallet at back of appendix. </s><s n="s3.5;p84.108">The macro 'solver' allows the user to apply various restraints and also optimises given variables around a target. </s><s n="s4.5;p84.108">Some restraints were dependant on the fan and so had to be altered for each optimisation. </s><s n="s5.5;p84.108">For example when using the 83GW 6Pole model the total pressure drop had to be restrained to &lt;100 (from fig 2). </s></p><p n="p85.108"><s n="s1.1;p85.108">Restrained values were as follows... </s></p><list type="bulleted"><item>0.01m&lt;width&lt;2m</item><item>0.01m&lt;depth&lt;2m</item><item>Reynolds number, dependant on fin</item><item>Total Pressure Loss, dependant on fan</item><item>Payback time>0 (negative payback suggests the exchanger will never pay for itself)</item></list><p n="p86.108"><s n="s1.1;p86.108">Variables are as follows... </s></p><list type="bulleted"><item>depth</item><item>width</item></list><p n="p87.108"><s n="s1.1;p87.108">Therefore solver will optimise the depth and height within the boundaries of the constraints to find the best payback time. </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Observations and Results</head><p n="p88.108"><s n="s1.1;p88.108">See CD on inside cover </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Analysis and Discussion of Results</head><p n="p89.108"><s n="s1.1;p89.108">Charts - Appendices 13-21 </s></p><p n="p90.108"><s n="s1.3;p90.108">The charts in Appendices 13-21 show the optimised payback times for the different fins. </s><s n="s2.3;p90.108">Where there is no value of payback time for a specific fan, the design never pays for itself, hence cannot be optimised. </s><s n="s3.3;p90.108">There are no results when using plate fin 10.37; this fin cannot produce a reasonable design. </s></p><p n="p91.108"><s n="s1.6;p91.108">At a glance it can be seen that when using the lower power fans a lower payback time is achieved. </s><s n="s2.6;p91.108">This is obvious from the 'best designs' chart in appendix 20 , where all but one of the designs utilise the 6 pole 83GW fan, which of all the fans analysed requires the lowest power. </s><s n="s3.6;p91.108">Also note that all the fans shown in appendix 20 are 6pole fans. </s><s n="s4.6;p91.108">The capital and running costs of the lesser pole fans proved too high for this particular heat exchanger design. </s><s n="s5.6;p91.108">The power requirements and initial price of the larger fans are not realistic for the type of heat exchanger in question, however may be more reliable and so provide more long-term benefits. </s><s n="s6.6;p91.108">Due to the lack of information on this aspect, further analysis and discussion is impossible. </s></p><p n="p92.108"><s n="s1.4;p92.108">The larger fans allow for a larger, more effective heat exchanger. </s><s n="s2.4;p92.108">This is visible in the data tables and illustrated in appendix 21. </s><s n="s3.4;p92.108">However this increase in effectiveness does not compensate for the capital, and annual costs of the larger fans. </s><s n="s4.4;p92.108">The larger heat exchangers also save more energy and oil, again clearly visible from the data tables; however the difference is not comparable to the extra energy required to power the larger fan. </s></p><p n="p93.108"><s n="s1.7;p93.108">When the best results from each fin design are compared, this is illustrated in appendix 20, it can be seen that the louvered fins provide the best payback times. </s><s n="s2.7;p93.108">The difference between the louvered and plain-fin designs is quite remarkable, although not unexpected. </s><s n="s3.7;p93.108">The louvered designs provided a larger surface area and also increase the turbulence of the passing air, giving greatly improved heat transfer. </s><s n="s4.7;p93.108">Detailed analysis of why louvered fins improve performance is given in appendix 22. </s><s n="s5.7;p93.108">Comparisons between louvered fins and various other fins are shown in appendix 26. </s><s n="s6.7;p93.108">The table shown clearly demonstrates that the louvered fin, although most expensive, is the most effective design. </s><s n="s7.7;p93.108">The graph reiterates this showing the louvered fin to have the best heat transfer per unit weight. </s></p><p n="p94.108"><s n="s1.2;p94.108">The optimum design calculated from this analysis was a heat exchanger of width 0.22809m, height 0.22809m and depth 0.65872m utilizing the louvered 10.39 fins, with the 83GW 6pole fan. </s><s n="s2.2;p94.108">It can be seen from the chart in appendix 20 that this design gives a payback time of 2.21 years. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Recommendations</head><p n="p95.108"><s n="s1.2;p95.108">There are several areas in which the heat exchanger analysis could be improved and developed. </s><s n="s2.2;p95.108">Recommendations for further investigation are as follows; </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p96.108"><s n="s1.2;p96.108">More data on the fans is required. </s><s n="s2.2;p96.108">More accurate tolerances are required in order to obtain optimum analytical results. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p97.108"><s n="s1.3;p97.108">Multiple passes for the exchanger should be analysed. </s><s n="s2.3;p97.108">In perform this analysis further information is required on how much money an extra pass will cost etc. </s><s n="s3.3;p97.108">It is known that multiple passes increase the efficiency and payback time. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p98.108"><s n="s1.1;p98.108">Other fin designs should be researched and analysed, for example pin and wavy. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p99.108"><s n="s1.1;p99.108">Different heat exchanger designs should be analysed in order to gain a comparative view of how efficient the cross-flow design is in comparison with other standard designs such as the counter-flow exchanger. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p100.108"><s n="s1.3;p100.108">Several improvements can be made to the optimization technique. </s><s n="s2.3;p100.108">The relationship between heat transfer and Reynolds number needs to be more accurate, also there could be more variables for example material used in construction. </s><s n="s3.3;p100.108">Finally if more information was provided on the fans, as stated above, the pressure tolerances could be more exact. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p101.108"><s n="s1.2;p101.108">The software used for analysis could be improved. </s><s n="s2.2;p101.108">A more powerful programming tool could be used for the optimization. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p102.108"><s n="s1.1;p102.108">The selected 'best designs' should be manufactured and tests should be carried out to gain knowledge of how accurate the model is. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p103.108"><s n="s1.2;p103.108">Fouling factors should be taken into consideration upon advancement of the project. </s><s n="s2.2;p103.108">Catering for fouling would be done with the use of appropriate tabulations. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Conclusions</head><p n="p104.108"><s n="s1.1;p104.108">From the results the following conclusions can be drawn; </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p105.108"><s n="s1.2;p105.108">The lower power fans are more appropriate for this type of heat exchanger. </s><s n="s2.2;p105.108">The capital costs have a negative impact on the payback time, hence only the lower power fans are economically viable. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p106.108"><s n="s1.1;p106.108">The louvered fin design is much more efficient and effective that the plain fin design due to larger surface area and increased turbulence. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p107.108"><s n="s1.1;p107.108">The effectiveness increases with size of the heat exchanger. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p108.108"><s n="s1.2;p108.108">The best design was found be a heat exchanger of width 0.22809m, height 0.22809m and depth 0.65872m utilizing the louvered 10.39 fins, with the 83GW 6pole fan. </s><s n="s2.2;p108.108">This design gave the optimum payback time of 2.21 years. </s></p></div1></body><back><div1 type="bibliography"><head rend="bold">References</head><p><seg type="URL" n="http://www.engineersedge.com/heat_exchanger/cross_flow.htm"/></p><p>Shah, R.K., and Sekulic, D.P., Fundamentals of Heat Exchanger Design, Wiley, Hoboken, NY, 2003</p></div1><div1 type="bibliography"><head rend="bold">Bibliography</head><p>Handbook of Heat Transfer, McGraw Hill, 3<hi rend="sup">rd</hi> edition</p><p>Heat exchanger design / Arthur P. Fraas. Publication info. Chichester: Wiley, 1989.</p><p>Developments in heat exchanger technology / edited by Duncan Chisholm. 1. Publication info. Barking: Applied Science Publishers, 1980.</p></div1><div1 type="missing or external appendix"><p/></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
