<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_0341d" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Data Analysis and Visualisation</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">The document has a title page which contains:
document title
title part</note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">deleted: page numbers</note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">Running text contains reference to external or missing appendix.
</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">1</p><p n="date">2003-11</p><p n="module title">Modelling and System Dynamics Laboratory</p><p n="module code">ES162</p><p n="genre family">Methodology recount</p><p n="discipline">Engineering</p><p n="disciplinary group">PS</p><p n="grade">unknown</p><p n="number of authors">unknown</p><p n="number of words">1310</p><p n="number of s-units">75</p><p n="number of p">29</p><p n="number of tables">0</p><p n="number of figures">3</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">3</p><p n="number of lists">1</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">0</p><p n="abstract present">abstract present</p><p n="average words per s-unit">17.5</p><p n="average s-units per p">2.6</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">m</p><p n="year of birth">1985</p><p n="first language">English</p><p n="education">UKA</p><p n="course">Mechanical Engineering MEng</p><p n="student ID">0341</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><titlePart rend="bold">University of <name type="university"/> School of Engineering</titlePart><docTitle><titlePart rend="bold">ES162A3 Modeling and System Dynamics Laboratory Report - Data Analysis and Visualisation. </titlePart></docTitle><titlePart rend="bold">By <name type="student name"/> Student ID: <name type="student ID"/></titlePart><titlePart rend="bold">Report of laboratory performed on: 4th November '03</titlePart></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="abstract"><head rend="bold">Summary</head><p n="p1.29"><s n="s1.2;p1.29">The main objective of this lab is to model and analyse data obtained from physical tests conducted on a car tyre. </s><s n="s2.2;p1.29">At the same time as doing this I will be constantly increasing my proficiency in MATLAB. </s></p><p n="p2.29"><s n="s1.3;p2.29">The lateral and longitudinal force was measured for varying values of slip angle and ratio respectively. </s><s n="s2.3;p2.29">We analysed these on a series of plots and used models to fit the trends. </s><s n="s3.3;p2.29">In doing this we explored MATLAB's capabilities and used many different functions. </s></p><p n="p3.29"><s n="s1.3;p3.29">To conclude our results a linear model works only for values of slip angle &lt;2.5degs and for slip ratios of &lt;0.03. </s><s n="s2.3;p3.29">For values higher than this a non-linear model has to be used to get the exponential characteristics of the changes in lateral and longitudinal force. </s><s n="s3.3;p3.29">It is also possible to conclude that MATLAB is a very efficient program for problems involving data modelling and visualisation, providing an excellent basis for analysis. </s></p></div1><div1 type="front-back-matter"><head rend="bold">Table of Contents</head><p/></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Introduction</head><p n="p4.29"><s n="s1.2;p4.29">The aim of this laboratory is to use MATLAB to model the longitudinal and lateral force characteristics of a road tyre. </s><s n="s2.2;p4.29">The objectives of the laboratory are to: - </s></p><list type="bulleted"><item>import longitudinal and lateral tyre force test data into the MATLAB workspace;</item><item>visualise the tyre test data using MATLAB 1-D graphics tool;</item><item>model the tyre test data in MATLAB using simple 1-D functions.</item><item>A more general aim of the laboratory was to explore MATLAB and familiarise ourselves with the software and its functions. *1*</item></list><p n="p5.29"><s n="s1.2;p5.29">In a previous session we were introduced to MATLAB and shown some basic functions and the language used. </s><s n="s2.2;p5.29">This laboratory will extend this grounding and increase knowledge and familiarity. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Theory</head><figure id="BAWE_0341d-pic.001"><head>Side View</head></figure><figure id="BAWE_0341d-pic.002"><head>Plan View</head></figure><p n="p6.29"><s n="s1.3;p6.29">These diagrams describe the longitudinal (traction/breaking) force F <hi rend="sub">x</hi> and the lateral (cornering) force F <hi rend="sub">y</hi> acting on a road tyre of radius r. </s><s n="s2.3;p6.29">The tyre has translational velocity v with longitudinal component v <hi rend="sub">x</hi> and lateral component v <hi rend="sub">y</hi>, and rotational speed . </s><s n="s3.3;p6.29">The slip angle , which determines the cornering force is given by </s></p><p n="p7.29"><s n="s1.1;p7.29"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0341d-form.001"/> </s></p><p n="p8.29"><s n="s1.1;p8.29">and the slip ratio s, which determines the traction/braking force is given by </s></p><p n="p9.29"><s n="s1.1;p9.29"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0341d-form.002"/> </s></p><p n="p10.29"><s n="s1.1;p10.29">where <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0341d-form.003"/> </s></p><p n="p11.29"><s n="s1.1;p11.29">F <hi rend="sub">z</hi> is the vertical load on the tyre. *1* </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0341d-pic.003"/><p n="p12.29"><s n="s1.2;p12.29">As this diagram shows it is the deformation of the tyre as it turns a corner that causes it to take a slightly different path to the wheel. </s><s n="s2.2;p12.29">It is this difference in paths that generates the slip angle. </s></p><p n="p13.29"><s n="s1.1;p13.29">This slip angle is dependant on many factors, including the inflation of the tyre. *2* </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Apparatus and Methods</head><p n="p14.29"><s n="s1.5;p14.29">The tyre data was obtained from physical tests carried out on a standard car tyre using an industrial tyre test rig. </s><s n="s2.5;p14.29">The vertical force loaded was equivocal to a mass of 500kg. </s><s n="s3.5;p14.29">Lateral force measurements were made at zero slip ratio and with varying slip angles. </s><s n="s4.5;p14.29">Longitudinal force measurements were made at zero slip angle with varying slip ratios. </s><s n="s5.5;p14.29">It is these measurements which we will be visualising and analysing. *1* </s></p><p n="p15.29"><s n="s1.2;p15.29">Names were given to each of the 4 sets of data for ease of use and accessibility. </s><s n="s2.2;p15.29">Using the software to visualise the data, plots of variation in lateral and longitudinal force with slip angle and slip ratio respectively. </s></p><p n="p16.29"><s n="s1.4;p16.29">The data was then modelled with basic formulae. </s><s n="s2.4;p16.29">These models were then compared to actual results, to enable us to determine the best model. </s><s n="s3.4;p16.29">Linear and non-linear models were tested for both longitudinal and lateral force data. </s><s n="s4.4;p16.29">All plots were printed out for analysis and comparison. </s></p><p n="p17.29"><s n="s1.1;p17.29">For a exact description of the method performed see appendix 7-11. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Results</head><p n="p18.29"><s n="s1.1;p18.29">For the results collected see graphs in appendix 1-6 </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Analysis and Discussion of Results</head><p n="p19.29"><s n="s1.1;p19.29">See appendix 1-6 to refer to graphs. </s></p><p n="p20.29"><s n="s1.2;p20.29">G1 is a graph of lateral force vs. slip angle. </s><s n="s2.2;p20.29">It is linear for values of slip angle between 0 and 2 degrees, however it then curves off in the shape of an exponential graph with an asymptote at about 4500N. </s></p><p n="p21.29"><s n="s1.3;p21.29">G2 is a graph of longitudinal force vs. slip ratio. </s><s n="s2.3;p21.29">When the slip ratio is &lt;0.03 then the results are linear. </s><s n="s3.3;p21.29">At values >0.03 then the results are again linear but with a reduced gradient. </s></p><p n="p22.29"><s n="s1.4;p22.29">G3 shows a linear model with three different values of cornering stiffness. </s><s n="s2.4;p22.29">The model is represented by the equation F <hi rend="sub">y</hi> = C + C <hi rend="sub">p</hi> where is the slip angle and C is the cornering stiffness. 'a' represents the line when C = 1005Ndeg <hi rend="sup"> - 1</hi> and is the linear model which applies to the particular data used. </s><s n="s3.4;p22.29">The value of 1005Ndeg <hi rend="sup">-1</hi> is the gradient of the graph up to 2.5 deg. </s><s n="s4.4;p22.29">Different values for cornering stiffness were then modelled. 'b' represents 1200Ndeg <hi rend="sup"> - 1</hi> and 'c' represents 800Ndeg <hi rend="sup"> - 1</hi>. </s></p><p n="p23.29"><s n="s1.2;p23.29">The model itself is certainly accurate up to the 2deg point, however between 2 and 2.5deg it is hard to tell, as there are no results in this boundary. </s><s n="s2.2;p23.29">For values of slip angle >2.5 then this model is obviously inaccurate. </s></p><p n="p24.29"><s n="s1.5;p24.29">G4 represents lateral force vs. slip angle using a non-linear model. </s><s n="s2.5;p24.29">It is effective for large slip angle values and is also reasonably good at estimating small angle values. </s><s n="s3.5;p24.29">However it has zero force at zero slip angle which is inaccurate as proved by the results. </s><s n="s4.5;p24.29">At small angles this model will give about 20% error. </s><s n="s5.5;p24.29">It curves off exponentially. </s></p><p n="p25.29"><s n="s1.5;p25.29">G5 represents longitudinal force vs. slip ratio. </s><s n="s2.5;p25.29">It is another linear model, which applies only to small slip ratios &lt;0.03. </s><s n="s3.5;p25.29">It is modelled by the equation F <hi rend="sub">x</hi> = C <hi rend="sub">s</hi>s + C <hi rend="sub">q</hi> where C <hi rend="sub">s</hi> = 121950N is the longitudinal stiffness and the best fit gradient &lt;0.03 slip ratio. </s><s n="s4.5;p25.29">This is represented by line 'd'. </s><s n="s5.5;p25.29">Line 'e' represents Cs = 150000N and line 'f' represents Cs = 90000N. This model is very inaccurate for estimating longitudinal force for values of slip ratio above 0.03. </s></p><p n="p26.29"><s n="s1.5;p26.29">G6 represents longitudinal force vs. slip ratio in a non-linear model. </s><s n="s2.5;p26.29">This is very useful for larger values of slip ratio but is also quite accurate for smaller values. </s><s n="s3.5;p26.29">Again it has zero force for zero slip ratio which is now a valid assumption if the results are correct. </s><s n="s4.5;p26.29">This model is quite inaccurate between 0.02 and 0.04 slip ratio. </s><s n="s5.5;p26.29">The results take a sharp corner here, which is hard to model. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Recommendations </head><p n="p27.29"><s n="s1.5;p27.29">When estimating the lateral and longitudinal forces in a practical situation like 'car safety when cornering' then it would be very important to use a model that gives an accurate estimate, one that can be used and built into the specifications of a car or tyre. </s><s n="s2.5;p27.29">I think that the non-linear models are really the only models that could be used in a practical sense. </s><s n="s3.5;p27.29">This is because slip angle or ratio has values that deviate and it would be hard to get these to stay under a particular value, as is necessary in the linear models. </s><s n="s4.5;p27.29">Also the non-linear models are accurate at the lower values as well, so they are the all-round performer. </s><s n="s5.5;p27.29">However more research is needed and more results need to be analysed before implementing one of these models in a practical situation. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Conclusions</head><p n="p28.29"><s n="s1.3;p28.29">From the results I can conclude that modeling is an effective way to estimate data. </s><s n="s2.3;p28.29">Although the data was small in quantity, models were still found that reproduced this data as a continuous function. </s><s n="s3.3;p28.29">It was found that when 0&lt;slipangle&lt;2.5 the linear model is most appropriate to find the lateral force. </s></p><p n="p29.29"><s n="s1.4;p29.29">It was also found that if 0&lt;slip ratio&lt;0.3 then again a linear model is most appropriate to find the longitudinal force. </s><s n="s2.4;p29.29">It was also found that these linear models did not work beyond these values even to a reasonable degree. </s><s n="s3.4;p29.29">Non-linear models were then tested and it was found that these worked far better outside these boundaries and produced a comparable performance within them. </s><s n="s4.4;p29.29">Therefore for general use it can be concluded that the non-linear model is most accurate and efficient. </s></p></div1></body><back><div1 type="bibliography"><head rend="bold">References</head><p>*1* R.P Jones, Lab 2 handout sheet, Oct03</p><p>*2* <seg type="URL" n="http://www.motor-tech.co.uk/tyres.htm"/></p></div1><div1 type="missing or external appendix"><p/></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
