<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_0341a" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>"Is Paul Mobbs one joule short of a kWh?"</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">The document has a title page which contains:
document title
title part</note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">Language used in quote: <foreign id="English">English</foreign></note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">deleted: page numbers</note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">deleted: Word count - 2,218 </note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">4</p><p n="date">unknown</p><p n="module title">Energy Studies</p><p n="module code">ES3B4</p><p n="genre family">Critique</p><p n="discipline">Engineering</p><p n="disciplinary group">PS</p><p n="grade">unknown</p><p n="number of authors">unknown</p><p n="number of words">2684</p><p n="number of s-units">140</p><p n="number of p">54</p><p n="number of tables">1</p><p n="number of figures">4</p><p n="number of block quotes">5</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">1</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">14</p><p n="abstract present">abstract present</p><p n="average words per s-unit">19.2</p><p n="average s-units per p">2.6</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">m</p><p n="year of birth">1985</p><p n="first language">English</p><p n="education">UKA</p><p n="course">Mechanical Engineering MEng</p><p n="student ID">0341</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><titlePart>ES3B40 Energy Studies Assignment</titlePart><docTitle><titlePart rend="bold">"Is Paul Mobbs one joule short of a kWh?"</titlePart></docTitle><titlePart>By<name type="student name"/></titlePart><titlePart><name type="student ID"/> MEng Mechanical Engineering - 4 <hi rend="sup">th</hi> year</titlePart></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="abstract"><head rend="bold">Summary</head><p n="p1.54"><s n="s1.2;p1.54">'Peak Oil' and climate change are the two most important issues facing today's society. </s><s n="s2.2;p1.54">Action must be taken now in order to successfully mitigate the forecast consequences. </s></p><p n="p2.54"><s n="s1.1;p2.54">In relation to 'energy future' two possible strategies provide solutions; </s></p><list type="bulleted"><item>Continued rates of growth but with an absolute switch to clean energy sources;</item><item>Reduced rates of growth as a result of a significant reduction in energy consumption.</item></list><p n="p3.54"><s n="s1.2;p3.54">A continued growth rate with no adverse environmental effects is obviously favourable. </s><s n="s2.2;p3.54">But is this possible? </s></p><p n="p4.54"><s n="s1.3;p4.54">Paul Mobbs is an independent environmental consultant who has explored the data, trends, projections and outcomes surrounding 'Peak Oil' and climate change. </s><s n="s2.3;p4.54">His views are largely objective and well researched. </s><s n="s3.3;p4.54">He is without doubt, however, an environmentalist; hence the presented facts are on occasion reflecting his own agenda. </s></p><p n="p5.54"><s n="s1.4;p5.54">Mobbs concludes that the only viable future contingency is a reduction in energy consumption by 75%. </s><s n="s2.4;p5.54">In the process evaluation he dismisses nuclear power as viable primarily due to waste management issues. </s><s n="s3.4;p5.54">He also suggests that nuclear power could only be maintained, at current levels, for 100 years. </s><s n="s4.4;p5.54">This report focuses on proving these assertions wrong by analysing viable energy resources and waste management strategies. </s></p><p n="p6.54"><s n="s1.1;p6.54">From the critical analysis the following conclusion can be drawn; </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p7.54"><s n="s1.2;p7.54">Supplies of uranium suitable for fission are far higher than Mobbs estimate. </s><s n="s2.2;p7.54">Fast breeder reactors can utilise other Uranium isotopes, expanding 0.7% uranium usage to a potential 100%. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p8.54"><s n="s1.2;p8.54">Thorium is of great abundance in the earths crust (roughly 3x that of uranium) and is a proven nuclear fuel. </s><s n="s2.2;p8.54">Operational thorium reactors are well documented; further research and development of this technology would expand possible nuclear fuel resources by a factor of 2. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p9.54"><s n="s1.1;p9.54">Maintaining current levels, the total nuclear energy supply will last ~30000 years. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p10.54"><s n="s1.1;p10.54">Upon replacing all other energy sources, nuclear power has the potential to power the world for ~1000 years. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p11.54"><s n="s1.2;p11.54">Waste management is progressing rapidly, with several methods providing safe long-term solutions. </s><s n="s2.2;p11.54">Subduction zone disposal would provide waste disposal in the absolute sense. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p12.54"><s n="s1.1;p12.54">Nuclear fission has the potential to act as a 'stop-gap' between 'Peak Oil' and fusion. </s></p></div1><div1 type="front-back-matter"><head rend="bold">Contents</head><p/></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">1. Introduction</head><p n="p13.54"><s n="s1.5;p13.54">Energy is the impetus behind every aspect of modern life. </s><s n="s2.5;p13.54">It powers everything from transport to manufacture, providing us with the means to live a life which has been deemed normal by society and fuelled by consumerism and development. </s><s n="s3.5;p13.54">The devastating effects of this lifestyle are becoming more apparent each year; events such as Katrina increase public awareness of climate change. </s><s n="s4.5;p13.54">However few people acknowledge the significant role they play in the world's future and furthermore even on realisation of the evidence fail to adapt their lifestyles accordingly. </s><s n="s5.5;p13.54">Whilst the world's population continues to rise and capitalists continue to promote growth and development, disaster looms. </s></p><p n="p14.54"><s n="s1.2;p14.54">'Peak Oil' and global warming are the two most important issues facing today's society. </s><s n="s2.2;p14.54">Action must be taken now in order to successfully mitigate the forecast consequences. </s></p><div2><head rend="bold">1.1 Global Warming</head><p n="p15.54"><s n="s1.4;p15.54">Recent climate change has been attributed to global warming. </s><s n="s2.4;p15.54">'Global Warming' is the increase in global temperature because of natural processes and/or the "greenhouse effect". </s><s n="s3.4;p15.54">It is the recent increase in the greenhouse effect for which humans are responsible as a result of increased greenhouse gas emission (mainly water vapour and CO2). </s><s n="s4.4;p15.54">If these emissions are not controlled global warming will continue, leading to inevitable global devastation. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0341a-fig.001"><head>Figure 1: Carbon dioxide increase recorder in the Mauna Loa Observatory (NOAA)</head></figure></div2><div2><head rend="bold">1.2 Peak Oil</head><p n="p16.54"><s n="s1.1;p16.54">Peak Oil is defined as; </s></p><quote lang="English">"...the maximum rate of the production of oil in any area under consideration, recognising that it is a finite natural resource, subject to depletion." <ref target="BAWE_0341a-ftnote.001"/> 1</quote><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0341a-ftnote.001"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1"><hi rend="sup">1</hi> C. Campbell, ASPO, accessed 7/3/07, source: <seg type="URL" n="http://www.peakoil.net/"/> </s></p></note><figure id="BAWE_0341a-fig.002"><head>Figure 2: The growing gap between oil discovery and production (ASPO)</head></figure><p n="p17.54"><s n="s1.5;p17.54">Once this maximum is reached the rate of oil production globally will enter a terminal decline. </s><s n="s2.5;p17.54">The exact date of peak oil is an unknown; sources suggest peaks between 1996 and 2035, the range owing to variations in values for 'total oil reserves'<ref target="BAWE_0341a-ftnote.002"/> 2. </s><s n="s3.5;p17.54">Irrelevant of when peak oil occurs, new energy sources must be sought to cope with energy consumption. </s><s n="s4.5;p17.54">It must also be realised that in light of current climate change issues, peak oil is extraneous because cleaner energy sources must be used to lower CO2 production. </s><s n="s5.5;p17.54">Cleaner energy sources include, wind, tidal, solar and nuclear. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0341a-ftnote.002"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1"><hi rend="sup">2</hi> P. Mobbs, Energy Beyond Oil (2005), Matador Publishing, p42 </s></p></note><p n="p18.54"><s n="s1.3;p18.54">Paul Mobbs has researched this dilemma extensively. </s><s n="s2.3;p18.54">He began working as an independent environmental consultant in 1992 and more recently his work has engaged in future energy research with particular reference to 'Peak Oil' and sustainable development. </s><s n="s3.3;p18.54">His findings are highlighted in his 2005 publication 'Energy Beyond Oil' in which he explores data, trends, projections and outcomes. </s></p><p n="p19.54"><s n="s1.2;p19.54">One fact is clear; we cannot continue current energy consumption patterns. </s><s n="s2.2;p19.54">There are two permissible future strategies; </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p20.54"><s n="s1.2;p20.54">Continue growth rates but convert to cleaner energy sources. </s><s n="s2.2;p20.54">Low CO2 energy sources presently include renewable energy sources and nuclear fission. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p21.54"><s n="s1.1;p21.54">Reduce energy usage significantly (Mobbs concludes a 75% reduction is necessary)<ref target="BAWE_0341a-ftnote.003"/> 3. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0341a-ftnote.003"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1"><hi rend="sup">3</hi> P. Mobbs, Energy Beyond Oil, An Introduction (2005) p. 4 </s></p></note><p n="p22.54"><s n="s1.2;p22.54">Unfortunately renewable energy sources do not have the capabilities to support the current population and infrastructure. </s><s n="s2.2;p22.54">Nuclear fission does but for how long? </s></p><p n="p23.54"><s n="s1.1;p23.54">This report will evaluate the conclusions drawn by Mobbs with reference to accuracy and objectivity. </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">2. Critical Evaluation</head><p n="p24.54"><s n="s1.2;p24.54">This critical evaluation will be largely centred on the information given in 'Energy Beyond Oil' in relation to the future of nuclear power. </s><s n="s2.2;p24.54">This is an integral element to the conclusions drawn by Mobbs; if nuclear power is in fact feasible in the long-term, much of his evaluation will prove redundant. </s></p><p n="p25.54"><s n="s1.5;p25.54">Nuclear power generation is certainly not without problems. </s><s n="s2.5;p25.54">Owing to a history marred by failures, the general public considers it unsafe and adopt a 'not in my back yard' attitude to every aspect of the industry. </s><s n="s3.5;p25.54">Opinions can be changed with time and proven good practice. </s><s n="s4.5;p25.54">Opinions aside, as Mobbs correctly points out the two potential drawbacks of nuclear power are the waste products and the amount of uranium available. </s><s n="s5.5;p25.54">These two issues will shape the future of nuclear power. </s></p><div2><head rend="bold">2.1 Nuclear Energy Supply</head><p n="p26.54"><s n="s1.6;p26.54">As stated by Mobbs, it is certainly true that any non-renewable energy source has a "finite lifetime based on the availability of the mineral resources they are reliant on"<ref target="BAWE_0341a-ftnote.004"/> 4. </s><s n="s2.6;p26.54">At current consumption rates he believes there are "100 years of nuclear fuel left to use"<hi rend="sup">4</hi>, with this figure decreasing in proportion to nuclear expansion. </s><s n="s3.6;p26.54">The background data for this figure originates from "0.7% of total uranium resource"<hi rend="sup">4</hi> (which is all that is available given current technology). </s><s n="s4.6;p26.54">This is a very pessimistic view. </s><s n="s5.6;p26.54">With progressive technological improvements and more importantly higher uranium prices, more resources will become available. </s><s n="s6.6;p26.54">This is highlighted by the UIC; </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0341a-ftnote.004"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1"><hi rend="sup">4</hi> Energy Beyond Oil, p. 172 </s></p></note><quote lang="English">"Changes in costs or prices, or further exploration, may alter measured resource figures markedly. At ten times the current price, seawater might become a potential source of vast amounts of uranium." <ref target="BAWE_0341a-ftnote.005"/>5 </quote><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0341a-ftnote.005"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1"><hi rend="sup">5</hi> Uranium Information Centre, Supply of Uranium, UIC Nuclear Issues Briefing Paper # 75 (2006), accessed 12/03/07, source: <seg type="URL" n="http://www.uic.com.au/nip75.htm"/> </s></p></note><p n="p27.54"><s n="s1.3;p27.54">Furthermore there was very little uranium exploration between 1985 and 2005. </s><s n="s2.3;p27.54">Increased exploration would easily double useable uranium resources. </s><s rend="sup" n="s3.3;p27.54">5 </s></p><p n="p28.54"><s n="s1.4;p28.54">Fast breeder reactors present massive increases in potential fuel; they give the ability to utilise uranium-238 which comprises the vast majority of natural uranium. </s><s n="s2.4;p28.54">Mobbs dismisses the fast breeder technology because of "design limitations"<ref target="BAWE_0341a-ftnote.006"/> 6. </s><s n="s3.4;p28.54">This is a flawed opinion for many reasons; primarily development of fast breeder reactor designs continues, and the technology has already proved successful. </s><s n="s4.4;p28.54">Phénix, located in the Marcoule nuclear site in France, is a small scale fast breeder reactor which has been connected to the grid since 1973 and continues to generate power<ref target="BAWE_0341a-ftnote.007"/> 7. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0341a-ftnote.006"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1"><hi rend="sup">6</hi> Energy Beyond Oil, p. 99 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0341a-ftnote.007"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1"><hi rend="sup">7</hi> IAEA, Phénix 30 years of history: the heart of a reactor (2004), source: <seg type="URL" n="http://www.iaea.or.at/inis/aws/fnss/phenix/book/ch9.pdf"/> </s></p></note><figure id="BAWE_0341a-pic.001"><head>Figure 3: Phé nix; One of three commercial fast breeder reactors (CEA)</head></figure><p n="p29.54"><s n="s1.5;p29.54">Furthermore fast breeder reactors have achieved criticality in locations throughout the world including Dounreay in the UK<ref target="BAWE_0341a-ftnote.008"/> 8. </s><s n="s2.5;p29.54">Future proposals in China and India continue to gain momentum. </s><s n="s3.5;p29.54">Of particular interest is the FBR of India which includes to concept of using fertile Thorium <hi rend="sup">8</hi>. </s><s n="s4.5;p29.54">The use of thorium in fission reactors is well documented, and interest is increasing worldwide. </s><s n="s5.5;p29.54">Thorium is much more abundant than uranium (roughly by a factor of 3) <ref target="BAWE_0341a-ftnote.009"/>9 and furthermore is a proven energy source; </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0341a-ftnote.008"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1"><hi rend="sup">8</hi> Wikipedia, the free encyclopaedia, accessed 12/03/07, source: <seg type="URL" n="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fast_breeder_reactor"/> </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0341a-ftnote.009"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1"><hi rend="sup">9</hi> Uranium Information Centre, Thorium, UIC Briefing Paper # 67 (2006), accessed 12/03/07, source: <seg type="URL" n="http://www.uic.com.au/nip67.htm"/> </s></p></note><quote lang="English">"Between 1967 and 1988, the AVR experimental pebble bed reactor at Julich, Germany, operated for over 750 weeks at 15 MWe, about 95% of the time with thorium-based fuel." <hi rend="sup">9</hi></quote><p n="p30.54"><s n="s1.2;p30.54">It is estimated that the use of thorium will provide roughly 18,000 years of power at current energy consumption. </s><s rend="sup" n="s2.2;p30.54">9 </s></p><p n="p31.54"><s n="s1.1;p31.54">With increases in uranium availability, predicted technological improvements, the use of U-238 and the use of thorium, the potential nuclear fuel supply can be calculated; </s></p><table id="BAWE_0341a-tab.001"><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p32.54"><s n="s1.6;p32.54">This is far greater than Mobbs' calculated figure owing to belief in fast breeder reactor designs, and thorium. </s><s n="s2.6;p32.54">30000 years may be considered to be very optimistic; however technological advance is an important factor in any calculation. </s><s n="s3.6;p32.54">It is not optimistic to suggest that fast breeder reactors will am economic reality within the next 50 years. </s><s n="s4.6;p32.54">It must be noted that this figure is for current nuclear energy usage. </s><s n="s5.6;p32.54">In order to maintain current electricity demands and replace fossil fuels this value would be reduce by 30 times. </s><s n="s6.6;p32.54">This implies that nuclear power has the capacity to power the world for 1000 years. </s></p><p n="p33.54"><s n="s1.2;p33.54">Irrelative of these figures, the future of nuclear waste management will determine the future of the nuclear industry. </s><s n="s2.2;p33.54">Mobbs considers nuclear power a "non-starter... irrespective of reactor technology" <ref target="BAWE_0341a-ftnote.010"/>10 since the radioactive waste, as of yet, has proved impossible to manage effectively. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0341a-ftnote.010"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1"><hi rend="sup">10</hi> Energy Beyond Oil, p. 101 </s></p></note></div2><div2><head rend="bold">2.2 Radioactive Waste Management</head><p n="p34.54"><s n="s1.2;p34.54">It is true that waste management is the biggest concern of the nuclear industry and the future of nuclear power. </s><s n="s2.2;p34.54">However it must be seen that this power source is relatively new hence waste management is a problem that we are only recently beginning to understand. </s></p><p n="p35.54"><s n="s1.7;p35.54">With respect to the UK, many regulatory bodies are now in place with the goal of successful waste management. </s><s n="s2.7;p35.54">Nirex are currently designing an underground repository for storage of all ILW (Intermediate-Level Waste) and HLW (High-Level Waste) generated in the UK<ref target="BAWE_0341a-ftnote.011"/> 11. </s><s n="s3.7;p35.54">The concept is illustrated in figure 4. </s><s n="s4.7;p35.54">This type of facility will rely on proven technology and multiple barriers to protect the environment and the general public. </s><s n="s5.7;p35.54">Suitable sites with current, and foreseen, geological stability have been short listed. </s><s n="s6.7;p35.54">This concept will provide the UK with a waste management strategy for the future and will also provide guidance for future waste management concepts. </s><s n="s7.7;p35.54">This same strategy is being adopted in many other countries including the USA and Finland. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0341a-ftnote.011"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1"><hi rend="sup">11</hi> UK Nirex, The Nirex Phased Disposal Concept, Nirex Report No. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">N/074 (2003) </s></p></note><figure id="BAWE_0341a-pic.002"><head>Figure 4: Multi-barrier radioactive waste disposal <hi rend="sup">11</hi></head></figure><p n="p36.54"><s n="s1.5;p36.54">Mobbs states management of HLW as the key issue <hi rend="sup">10</hi>. </s><s n="s2.5;p36.54">HLW accounts for a small volume of total radioactive waste, however it accounts for more than 95% of the total radioactivity<ref target="BAWE_0341a-ftnote.012"/> 12. </s><s n="s3.5;p36.54">This presents handling and storage issues which in the past have proved difficult to manage. </s><s n="s4.5;p36.54">Progressive research and technological development have produced innovative storage methods which will maintain reliability in the long term. </s><s n="s5.5;p36.54">One such method is vitrification, as is employed at Sellafield in the UK. In this process the HLW is bonded into a glass matrix which is pored into steel flasks where it solidifies<ref target="BAWE_0341a-ftnote.013"/> 13. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0341a-ftnote.012"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1"><hi rend="sup">12</hi> World Nuclear Association, Radioactive Wastes (2001), accessed 12/03/07, source: <seg type="URL" n="http://www.world-nuclear.org/info/inf60.html"/> </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0341a-ftnote.013"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1"><hi rend="sup">13</hi> Energy Solutions, What is Vitrification (2007), accessed 12/03/07, source: <seg type="URL" n="http://www.energysolutions.com/Process/vitrification.php?gclid=CLSwg4bt74oCFRnHEAod9zlkkg"/> </s></p></note><figure id="BAWE_0341a-pic.003"><head>Figure 5: Vitrified HLW in a steel flask (BNFL)</head></figure><p n="p37.54"><s n="s1.5;p37.54">Vitrification secures the waste for several thousands of years and would be used in conjunction with a deep repository disposal. </s><s n="s2.5;p37.54">Other final disposal techniques under consideration include disposal within a subduction zone. </s><s n="s3.5;p37.54">This is where the denser of two plates at a destructive plate boundary subducts beneath the earth's crust. </s><s n="s4.5;p37.54">This method has enormous future potential by ensuring absolute waste disposal; locating the waste containers within this zone would ensure "non-return of the material to the biosphere"<ref target="BAWE_0341a-ftnote.014"/> 14. </s><s n="s5.5;p37.54">This would be an international solution and the legality of the method would require worldwide cooperation with reference to "The Law of the Sea"<ref target="BAWE_0341a-ftnote.015"/> 15. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0341a-ftnote.014"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1"><hi rend="sup">14</hi> CORWM, Disposal in Subduction Zones (2004), p. 7, accessed 12/03/07, source: <seg type="URL" n="http://www.corwm.org.uk/PDF/627%20-%20Subduction%20zones.pdf"/> </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0341a-ftnote.015"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1"><hi rend="sup">15</hi> Globe Law, UN Law of the Sea Convention (1996), accessed 12/03/07, source: <seg type="URL" n="http://www.globelaw.com/LawSea/lsconts.htm"/> </s></p></note><figure id="BAWE_0341a-pic.004"><head>Figure 6: Expected path and behaviour of radioactive waste placed in a subduction zone (CORWM)</head></figure><p n="p38.54"><s n="s1.2;p38.54">These techniques and many others in operation or under development are viable solutions to the problem of waste disposal. </s><s n="s2.2;p38.54">Furthermore, technological advance will bring evolved solutions with time, particularly in light of recent heightened interest in nuclear energy. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">2.3 Nuclear Future? </head><p n="p39.54"><s n="s1.4;p39.54">If nuclear power is a long-term energy source, and waste management issues continue to be resolved, then many of the conclusions drawn in 'Energy Beyond Oil' are negated. </s><s n="s2.4;p39.54">'Peak Oil' however, is very much a reality. </s><s n="s3.4;p39.54">The real issue will be the movement from reliance on primary energy sources, like oil and gas, to electricity from nuclear fission. </s><s n="s4.4;p39.54">This will require world-wide change, but a viable change none the less. </s></p><p n="p40.54"><s n="s1.4;p40.54">Furthermore fission will allow technological advance to continue at current rates. </s><s n="s2.4;p40.54">A reduction in energy usage by 75% will not. </s><s n="s3.4;p40.54">Fission could in effect act as an excellent 'stop-gap' to more advanced, cleaner energy sources such as fusion. </s><s n="s4.4;p40.54">As Mobbs states "a viable fusion power plant may be fifty to one hundred years away"<ref target="BAWE_0341a-ftnote.016"/> 16; paired with fission this presents an almost certain energy future. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0341a-ftnote.016"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1"><hi rend="sup">16</hi> Energy Beyond Oil, p. 101 </s></p></note><figure id="BAWE_0341a-fig.003"><head>Figure 7: Fusion progress since the 1960's. (ITER)</head></figure></div2><div2><head rend="bold">2.4 Objectivity</head><p n="p41.54"><s n="s1.3;p41.54">'Energy Beyond Oil' provides an excellent insight into 'Peak Oil' and the problems faced as we reach peak production. </s><s n="s2.3;p41.54">The information presented is informed and accurate; 'Peak Oil' is a factual natural occurrence. </s><s n="s3.3;p41.54">Mobbs is correct in basing subsequent evaluation on a future without oil. </s></p><p n="p42.54"><s n="s1.4;p42.54">Discussions earlier in this report pose the question of why Mobbs is so pessimistic about the role of nuclear energy in the future. </s><s n="s2.4;p42.54">Perhaps his views are not as objective as they should be? </s><s n="s3.4;p42.54">Mobbs is very critical of the feasibility of radioactive waste management. </s><s n="s4.4;p42.54">He bases this largely on lack of proven safeguards, and summarises quoting the RCEP; </s></p><quote lang="English">"It would be morally wrong to commit future generations to the consequences of fission power on a large scale unless it had been demonstrated beyond reasonable doubt that at least one method exists for the safe isolation of these wastes for the indefinite future."<hi rend="sup">16</hi></quote><p n="p43.54"><s n="s1.1;p43.54">Holding this opinion is contradictory of a point he raises in relation to the development of alternative energy sources; </s></p><quote lang="English">"The problem is, if you can't act upon knowledge based precaution, and you must wait for certainty, how can you act until it is too late." <ref target="BAWE_0341a-ftnote.017"/> 17</quote><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0341a-ftnote.017"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1"><hi rend="sup">17</hi> Energy Beyond Oil, p. 166 </s></p></note><p n="p44.54"><s n="s1.2;p44.54">This highlights a certain bias towards environmentalist opinions and politics which negates the supposed scientific impact of Mobbs' work. </s><s n="s2.2;p44.54">He, in fact, is following a work and research ethic which he concedes is flawed; "The primary difference between the approach of wise use and environment groups is the data that they quote in support of their cause, or to refute their opponents."<hi rend="sup">17</hi> </s></p><p n="p45.54"><s n="s1.2;p45.54">After evaluation it can be concluded that Mobbs' opinions on radioactive waste disposal and nuclear power are largely subjective and in many cases the data produced is derived from a worst case scenario. </s><s n="s2.2;p45.54">It is suggested that the information is presented in such a way, serving as to back-up his personal agenda, where in fact common sense would suggest otherwise. </s></p><p n="p46.54"><s n="s1.2;p46.54">Mobbs' overall conclusions suggest voluntary energy deprivation; this unfortunately does not take into account greed, and based on previous human behavioural patterns (with the exception of the environmentalist movement) this concept is an impossibility. </s><s n="s2.2;p46.54">Unfortunately 'Energy Beyond Oil' is largely a promotion of environmentalism, and possibly permaculture, under the façade of a realistic energy solution. </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">3. Conclusions</head><p n="p47.54"><s n="s1.1;p47.54">From the critical analysis the following conclusions can be drawn; </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p48.54"><s n="s1.2;p48.54">Supplies of uranium suitable for fission are far higher than Mobbs estimate. </s><s n="s2.2;p48.54">Fast breeder reactors can utilise other Uranium isotopes, expanding 0.7% uranium usage to a potential 100%. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p49.54"><s n="s1.2;p49.54">Thorium is of great abundance in the earths crust (roughly 3x that of uranium) and is a proven nuclear fuel. </s><s n="s2.2;p49.54">Operational thorium reactors are well documented; further research and development of this technology would expand possible nuclear fuel resources by a factor of 2. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p50.54"><s n="s1.1;p50.54">Maintaining current levels, the total nuclear energy supply will last ~30000 years. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p51.54"><s n="s1.1;p51.54">Upon replacing all other energy sources, nuclear power has the potential to power the world for ~1000 years. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p52.54"><s n="s1.2;p52.54">Waste management is progressing rapidly, with several methods providing safe long-term solutions. </s><s n="s2.2;p52.54">Subduction zone disposal would provide waste disposal in the absolute sense. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p53.54"><s n="s1.1;p53.54">Nuclear fission has the potential to act as a 'stop-gap' between 'Peak Oil' and fusion. </s></p><p n="p54.54"><s n="s1.1;p54.54">A possible timeline for the next 100 years is illustrated below; </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0341a-fig.004"/></div1></body><back><div1 type="back text"><head rend="bold">4. Acronyms</head><list type="simple"><item>ASPO The Association for the Study of Peak Oil and Gas</item><item>AVR Arbeitsgemeinschaft Versuchsreaktor (working group test reactor)</item><item>BNFL British Nuclear Fuels</item><item>CEA France's Atomic Energy Commission</item><item>CORWM Committee on Radioactive Waste Management</item><item>CO2 Carbon Dioxide</item><item>HLW High-Level Waste</item><item>ILW Intermediate-Level Waste</item><item>ITER International Thermonuclear Experimental Reactor;</item><item>MWe MegaWatt Electrical</item><item>NOAA National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration</item><item>UIC Uranium Information Centre</item></list><p/></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
