<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_0341b" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>The deflection of beams depends on the loading, the dimensions and material of the beam and the method of support.</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note/></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">1</p><p n="date">unknown</p><p n="module title">Materials and Production</p><p n="module code">ES160</p><p n="genre family">Critique</p><p n="discipline">Engineering</p><p n="disciplinary group">PS</p><p n="grade">unknown</p><p n="number of authors">unknown</p><p n="number of words">1679</p><p n="number of s-units">141</p><p n="number of p">101</p><p n="number of tables">3</p><p n="number of figures">4</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">57</p><p n="number of lists">7</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">14</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">11.9</p><p n="average s-units per p">1.4</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">m</p><p n="year of birth">1985</p><p n="first language">English</p><p n="education">UKA</p><p n="course">Mechanical Engineering MEng</p><p n="student ID">0341</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><div1 type="toc" n="1"><head rend="bold">Contents Page</head><p/></div1></front><body><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Introduction</head><p n="p1.101"><s n="s1.4;p1.101">The deflection of beams depends on the loading, the dimensions and material of the beam and the method of support. </s><s n="s2.4;p1.101">The principal types of beam to be considered are cantilevered beams where the ends are rigidly built into walls which restrain the ends to be horizontal but free from longitudinal tension, and simply-support beams in which rotation of the ends is unrestrained. </s><s n="s3.4;p1.101">As previously stated the cantilevered beams, for theoretical purposes, are deemed encastre, where in reality they are in fact cantilevered to a hollow circular shaft which will have certain torsion, hence angle of twist. </s><s n="s4.4;p1.101">This will be incorporated to calculate the total displacement of the beam when a load is applied. </s></p><p n="p2.101"><s n="s1.4;p2.101">In this report I will construct mathematical models to predict the displacement of the different beam set-ups, and compare predictions to experimental data obtained through laboratory work. </s><s n="s2.4;p2.101">The goal of mathematical modeling is to represent natural processes by mathematical equations, to analyse the mathematical equations, and then to use the mathematical model to better understand and predict the natural process. </s><s n="s3.4;p2.101">This comparison will enable me to conclude on how accurate the mathematical models are at predicting practical results. </s><s n="s4.4;p2.101">I will also take into account and analyze errors in experimental work. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Summary of Objectives</head><list type="bulleted"><item>Describe the experiment</item><item>Derive mathematical models for the various mechanical problems</item><item>Incorporate errors into this model</item><item>Compare the model to experimental data</item><item>Analyze</item></list><p n="p3.101"/></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">For method see Appendix 5</head><p n="p4.101"/></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Measurements</head><figure id="BAWE_0341b-pic.001"/><list type="simple"><head>Supports at 0 and 1000mm +/-2mm</head><item>W = 25.6mm</item><item>D = 6.6mm</item></list><p n="p5.101"/></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Simply-Support Theory</head><figure id="BAWE_0341b-pic.002"/><p n="p6.101"><s n="s1.1;p6.101">To calculate the displacement of the simply support beam, the formula required is... </s></p><p n="p7.101"><s n="s1.1;p7.101"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0341b-form.001"/> </s></p><list type="simple"><head>Where</head><item><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0341b-form.002"/></item><item><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0341b-form.003"/></item><item><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0341b-form.004"/></item><item><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0341b-form.005"/></item><item><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0341b-form.006"/></item></list><p n="p8.101"><s n="s1.1;p8.101">The Young's modulus and second moment of cross sectional area need to be calculated. </s></p><p n="p9.101"><s n="s1.1;p9.101">For the Young's modulus for carbon steel, a general figure can be used for theoretical purposes obtained from the data book... </s></p><p n="p10.101"><s n="s1.1;p10.101"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0341b-form.007"/> </s></p><p n="p11.101"><s n="s1.1;p11.101">The second moment of cross-sectional area can be calculated using the formula... </s></p><p n="p12.101"><s n="s1.1;p12.101"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0341b-form.008"/> Where <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0341b-form.009"/>, <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0341b-form.010"/> </s></p><p n="p13.101"><s n="s1.1;p13.101"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0341b-form.011"/>. </s></p><p n="p14.101"><s n="s1.1;p14.101">Now the initial equation can be updated to allow for an output when the required variables are input. </s></p><p n="p15.101"><s n="s1.1;p15.101"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0341b-form.012"/> </s></p><p n="p16.101"><s n="s1.2;p16.101">Now data can be input to predict the displacement at position x of the beam. </s><s n="s2.2;p16.101">This can be compared to experimental data to analyze the mathematical model. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Simply-support beamGenerating results from mathematical model and comparison</head><p n="p17.101"><s n="s1.1;p17.101">Using <hi rend="italic">excel</hi> data is automatically input into the acquired formula giving data which can be compared to the experimental data. </s></p><table id="BAWE_0341b-tab.001"><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p18.101"><s n="s1.3;p18.101">The results have only been predicted to 2 decimal places. </s><s n="s2.3;p18.101">It would be inappropriate for any higher levels of accuracy; the original results were recorded to the same accuracy because this was the highest level possible, with the given restrictions inclusive of human error. </s><s n="s3.3;p18.101">The error bounds estimated for x and b (+/- 2mm) has no effect on the end result and so can be ignored. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Comparison of Results</head><p n="p19.101"><s n="s1.5;p19.101">The predicted results actually do show quite an accurate representation of the experiment. </s><s n="s2.5;p19.101">The majority of the results lay within 0.1mm of each other. </s><s n="s3.5;p19.101">It also seems that the error becomes greater as the load increases. </s><s n="s4.5;p19.101">When the load is at 20N the results are mostly just under 0.2mm error. </s><s n="s5.5;p19.101">In general we can say that the results all lay within 10% of each other. </s></p><p n="p20.101"><s n="s1.4;p20.101">The graphs in appendix1 demonstrate this data in more detail, and make detailed analysis easier to achieve. </s><s n="s2.4;p20.101">From these graphs it is very clear how close the model really is to the experimental data. </s><s n="s3.4;p20.101">It is clear from the graphs that the actual results are always fractionally greater than the predicted results. </s><s n="s4.4;p20.101">The graphs also demonstrate that the displacement is proportional to the force applied in all cases. </s></p><p n="p21.101"><s n="s1.1;p21.101">The discrepancies could be due to any or all of the following... </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p22.101"><s n="s1.2;p22.101">Non uniform beam. </s><s n="s2.2;p22.101">This is quite likely, the beam had visible dents. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p23.101"><s n="s1.2;p23.101">Load errors. </s><s n="s2.2;p23.101">The weight were old, hence may not have been exactly as stated </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p24.101"><s n="s1.2;p24.101">Lay of beam. </s><s n="s2.2;p24.101">The beam may not have been totally perpendicular to the supports. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p25.101"><s n="s1.2;p25.101">Young's modulus. </s><s n="s2.2;p25.101">The Young's modulus estimate was taken from the data book, and is unlikely to be the actual modulus of the carbon steel used. </s></p><p n="p26.101"><s n="s1.1;p26.101">These errors are impossible to estimate, hence are variables in the experiment. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Measurements</head><figure id="BAWE_0341b-pic.003"/><p rend="ordered" n="p27.101"><s n="s1.1;p27.101">200mm +/- 0.5mm </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p28.101"><s n="s1.1;p28.101">233mm +/- 1.0mm </s></p><p n="p29.101"><s n="s1.2;p29.101">These were measured with a rule. </s><s n="s2.2;p29.101">The error bounds are due to human error </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p30.101"><s n="s1.1;p30.101">16.105mm +/- 0.001 </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p31.101"><s n="s1.1;p31.101">20.000mm +/- 0.001 </s></p><p n="p32.101"><s n="s1.2;p32.101">These were measured with digital calipers. </s><s n="s2.2;p32.101">The error bounds account for instrumental inaccuracies </s></p><p n="p33.101"><s n="s1.1;p33.101">Equating these measurements to the theory formulae... </s></p><p n="p34.101"><s n="s1.1;p34.101"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0341b-form.013"/> </s></p><p n="p35.101"><s n="s1.1;p35.101"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0341b-form.014"/> </s></p><p n="p36.101"><s n="s1.1;p36.101"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0341b-form.015"/> </s></p><p n="p37.101"><s n="s1.1;p37.101"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0341b-form.016"/> </s></p><p n="p38.101"><s n="s1.2;p38.101">Certain assumptions have been made do reduce the complexity of the mathematical model. </s><s n="s2.2;p38.101">It is assumed that... </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p39.101"><s n="s1.1;p39.101">The materials are all linear with constant properties throughout. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p40.101"><s n="s1.1;p40.101">The materials do not deform plastically at any stage, hence obey Hooke's law. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p41.101"><s n="s1.1;p41.101">The cantilevered shaft will deflect an equal amount to if it was encastre. </s></p><p n="p42.101"><s n="s1.1;p42.101">These assumptions will limit the models accuracy. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Bending Theory</head><figure id="BAWE_0341b-pic.004"/><p n="p43.101"><s n="s1.1;p43.101">This is the theory for a cantilever with a load W, distance b from a, as shown in the diagram. </s></p><p n="p44.101"><s n="s1.1;p44.101">The required formula for calculating the displacement is </s></p><p n="p45.101"><s n="s1.1;p45.101"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0341b-form.017"/> </s></p><list type="simple"><head>Where</head><item><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0341b-form.018"/></item><item><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0341b-form.019"/></item><item><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0341b-form.020"/></item><item><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0341b-form.021"/></item></list><p n="p46.101"><s n="s1.1;p46.101">The Young's modulus for the rod is the same as the simply-support beam. </s></p><p n="p47.101"><s n="s1.1;p47.101">I can be calculated the same way also... </s></p><p n="p48.101"><s n="s1.1;p48.101"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0341b-form.022"/> </s></p><p n="p49.101"><s n="s1.1;p49.101"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0341b-form.023"/> </s></p><p n="p50.101"><s n="s1.1;p50.101">Therefore the mathematical model is... </s></p><p n="p51.101"><s n="s1.1;p51.101"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0341b-form.024"/> </s></p><p n="p52.101"><s n="s1.2;p52.101">The same method can be used to calculate the displacement of the pipe. </s><s n="s2.2;p52.101">This time the formula for I is shown in the torsion of pipe section under the letter K... </s></p><p n="p53.101"><s n="s1.1;p53.101"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0341b-form.025"/> </s></p><p n="p54.101"><s n="s1.2;p54.101">The Young's modulus for materials that deform plastically is called the tensile modulus, and from the data book it is stated that for vinyl polymers this will lay between 2.4 and 4.1. </s><s n="s2.2;p54.101">This is a very rough estimate and due to the fact that the actual material the pipe is made from is an unknown, we can say that E = 3 +/- 1, or 3 +/- 30%. </s></p><p n="p55.101"><s n="s1.1;p55.101"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0341b-form.026"/> </s></p><p n="p56.101"><s n="s1.1;p56.101">Therefore the equation for the vertical deflection of the pipe is </s></p><p n="p57.101"><s n="s1.1;p57.101"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0341b-form.027"/> </s></p><p n="p58.101"><s n="s1.1;p58.101">This can now be used for prediction and comparison. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Torsion of Pipe</head><p n="p59.101"><s n="s1.1;p59.101"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0341b-form.028"/> </s></p><p n="p60.101"><s n="s1.1;p60.101"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0341b-form.029"/> </s></p><p n="p61.101"><s n="s1.1;p61.101"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0341b-form.030"/> </s></p><p n="p62.101"><s n="s1.1;p62.101"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0341b-form.031"/> </s></p><p n="p63.101"><s n="s1.1;p63.101"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0341b-form.032"/> </s></p><p n="p64.101"><s n="s1.1;p64.101"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0341b-form.033"/> </s></p><p n="p65.101"><s n="s1.1;p65.101"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0341b-form.034"/> </s></p><p n="p66.101"><s n="s1.1;p66.101"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0341b-form.035"/> </s></p><p n="p67.101"><s n="s1.1;p67.101"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0341b-form.036"/> </s></p><p n="p68.101"><s n="s1.1;p68.101"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0341b-form.037"/> </s></p><p n="p69.101"><s n="s1.1;p69.101"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0341b-form.038"/> </s></p><p n="p70.101"><s n="s1.3;p70.101">These are the formulae for the torsion of the pipe supporting the cantilever. </s><s n="s2.3;p70.101">Note that both these formulae and the bending formulae only apply while the materials still follow Hooke's Law. </s><s n="s3.3;p70.101">As soon as the material goes beyond the limit of proportionality, these equations no longer apply. </s></p><p n="p71.101"><s n="s1.1;p71.101">Hooke's Law states that: </s></p><p n="p72.101"><s n="s1.1;p72.101">The extension of a sample material is proportional to the stretching force </s></p><p n="p73.101"><s n="s1.1;p73.101">F = ke </s></p><p n="p74.101"><s n="s1.1;p74.101">Where k represents the stiffness of the sample in N/m </s></p><p n="p75.101"><s n="s1.3;p75.101">G is the modulus of rigidity. </s><s n="s2.3;p75.101">It can be calculated using tensile modulus and an estimate for poisson's ratio. </s><s n="s3.3;p75.101">I will use 0.3 as an estimate of this ratio, this is about an average value for a plastic, with error bounds +/- 0.05, therefore 0.3 +/- 20% </s></p><p n="p76.101"><s n="s1.1;p76.101"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0341b-form.039"/> </s></p><p n="p77.101"><s n="s1.1;p77.101">K can be calculated using the radii of the pipe... </s></p><p n="p78.101"><s n="s1.1;p78.101"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0341b-form.040"/> </s></p><p n="p79.101"><s n="s1.1;p79.101">Now the equation reads... </s></p><p n="p80.101"><s n="s1.1;p80.101"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0341b-form.041"/> </s></p><p n="p81.101"><s n="s1.1;p81.101">The torsion can be calculated from the formula </s></p><p n="p82.101"><s n="s1.1;p82.101"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0341b-form.042"/> </s></p><p n="p83.101"><s n="s1.1;p83.101"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0341b-form.043"/> </s></p><p n="p84.101"><s n="s1.1;p84.101">Where F is the load applied to the cantilevered shaft and a1 is the distance from the centre of the pipe. </s></p><p n="p85.101"><s n="s1.1;p85.101"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0341b-form.044"/> </s></p><p n="p86.101"><s n="s1.2;p86.101">To find the actual cantilever displacement this causes, trigonometry must be implemented. </s><s n="s2.2;p86.101">As it is only small angles of deflection, a simplified formula is used </s></p><p n="p87.101"><s n="s1.1;p87.101"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0341b-form.045"/> </s></p><p n="p88.101"><s n="s1.1;p88.101">This can now be put with the bending equations to predict the total displacement of the cantilevered shaft. </s></p><p n="p89.101"><s n="s1.1;p89.101"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0341b-form.046"/> </s></p><list type="simple"><head>where</head><item><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0341b-form.047"/></item><item><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0341b-form.048"/></item><item><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0341b-form.049"/></item><item><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0341b-form.050"/></item><item><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0341b-form.051"/></item></list><p n="p90.101"><s n="s1.1;p90.101"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0341b-form.052"/> </s></p><list type="simple"><head>where</head><item><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0341b-form.053"/></item><item><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0341b-form.054"/></item><item><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0341b-form.055"/></item><item><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0341b-form.056"/></item><item><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0341b-form.057"/></item></list><p n="p91.101"><s n="s1.1;p91.101">Note that... </s></p><list type="simple"><item>L=233mm</item><item>L1=200mm</item></list></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Cantilevered ShaftGenerating results from mathematical model and comparison</head><p n="p92.101"><s n="s1.1;p92.101">Again excel was used to generate the predicted data </s></p><table id="BAWE_0341b-tab.002"><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p93.101"><s n="s1.1;p93.101">Predicted result given to 2 decimal places again for an appropriate level of accuracy. </s></p><p n="p94.101"><s n="s1.4;p94.101">As stated in the calculation of the mathematical models, both the poisson ratio and the tensile modulus are subject to large inaccuracies. </s><s n="s2.4;p94.101">By cross referencing the values of error, clearly an error range needs to be identified for the predicted deflections. </s><s n="s3.4;p94.101">An error of about 30% should be acceptable. </s><s n="s4.4;p94.101">Adopting this to the results... </s></p><table id="BAWE_0341b-tab.003"><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p95.101"><s n="s1.8;p95.101">As you can see about 50% of the results lay within the tolerances. </s><s n="s2.8;p95.101">Most discrepancies occur when the load is applied to a short length of pipe or rod (100mm as apposed to 200mm). </s><s n="s3.8;p95.101">It also can be seen, in particularly from the graphs, the actual results are a lot closer to the lower bounds than to the higher. </s><s n="s4.8;p95.101">In fact looking at graphs B2 and B3 the experimental results are actually very close to the lower bound indeed. </s><s n="s5.8;p95.101">What this suggests is an error in estimate for young's modulus or poisons ration, the properties of the material, which would lead to these systematic errors. </s><s n="s6.8;p95.101">From graph B4 it is clear that the whole range of results for this set is less than the lower bound, hence not within the error bound estimated. </s><s n="s7.8;p95.101">This is again probably due to incorrect estimates. </s><s n="s8.8;p95.101">It could also be partially account for by human error, as the displacements become smaller, readings will be harder to take, hence a greater error. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Comparing mathematical models</head><p n="p96.101"><s n="s1.4;p96.101">Both models predicted experimental data to a reasonable level of accuracy. </s><s n="s2.4;p96.101">However the model constructed for the simply support beam was of a much higher level of accuracy, also it did not require the range of errors the cantilevered shaft model did, this was due to an estimate of Young's modulus that was of a reasonable accuracy. </s><s n="s3.4;p96.101">Looking at the two different materials used, it can be said that the behavior of steel is much easier to predict; it obeys Hooke's Law to a greater degree than a plastic (hence the name <hi rend="italic">plastic</hi>). </s><s n="s4.4;p96.101">The only problem with the carbon steel was the crude method used to measure the deflection, a large source of error, but nothing in comparison to the 30% error of Young's modulus for vinyl polymers. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Conclusion</head><p n="p97.101"><s n="s1.1;p97.101">From this report these conclusions can be drawn... </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p98.101"><s n="s1.1;p98.101">The mathematical model for the simply support provides data to a good level of accuracy (about 10%) </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p99.101"><s n="s1.1;p99.101">The model for the cantilevered shaft, although provided a reasonable estimate for long shafts, was on the whole inaccurate. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p100.101"><s n="s1.1;p100.101">The errors in predicting the behavior or a plastic are far greater than errors in predicting metal behavior. </s></p><p n="p101.101"><s n="s1.1;p101.101">It can now be said that for structures made from plastics, sufficient bounds should be incorporated to allow for the large unpredictability, whereas for carbon steel bounds need not be so great. </s></p></div1></body><back><div1 type="bibliography"><head rend="bold">References</head><div2 type="bibliography"><head>The theory found throughout my report taken from these books...</head><p>Engineering Data Book (2004)</p><p>Mechanical science for technicians: Volume 2 (1984) Ian McDonagh</p><p>Mechanical science for higher technicians (1981) Bacon/Stephens</p></div2><div2 type="bibliography"><head rend="bold">Bibliography</head><p>Material sciences fourth edition (1990) Anderson</p><p>Mechanical science for technicians: Volume 2 (1984) Ian McDonagh</p><p>Mechanical science for higher technicians (1981) Bacon/Stephens</p><p>Perry's Chemical Engineers Handbook fourth edition (1963) Kirkpatrick</p></div2></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
