<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_0342d" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>The Development of Car Interiors</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note/></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">1</p><p n="date">unknown</p><p n="module title">unknown</p><p n="module code">ES178</p><p n="genre family">Explanation</p><p n="discipline">Engineering</p><p n="disciplinary group">PS</p><p n="grade">unknown</p><p n="number of authors">unknown</p><p n="number of words">3607</p><p n="number of s-units">161</p><p n="number of p">40</p><p n="number of tables">0</p><p n="number of figures">4</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">1</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">0</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">22.4</p><p n="average s-units per p">4.0</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">m</p><p n="year of birth">1986</p><p n="first language">English</p><p n="education">UKA</p><p n="course">Meng</p><p n="student ID">0342</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><docTitle><titlePart rend="underlined bold">The Development of Car Interiors</titlePart></docTitle><titlePart><name type="student name"/><name type="student name"/><name type="student name"/><name type="student name"/><name type="student name"/></titlePart></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="section"><p n="p1.40"><s n="s1.5;p1.40">The exterior aesthetics of a vehicle is what initially grabs attention. </s><s n="s2.5;p1.40">For the driver, however, the interior environment is just as important. </s><s n="s3.5;p1.40">The interior is where more time is spent. </s><s n="s4.5;p1.40">Car interiors have developed significantly over the century offering better comfort, safety and entertainment. </s><s n="s5.5;p1.40">These issues shall be explored as well as two iconic British brands; Rolls-Royce and Jaguar, and their advances. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Comfort Features</head><p n="p2.40"><s n="s1.2;p2.40">The appeal of a car depends largely on the comfort it can offer its driver and passengers. </s><s n="s2.2;p2.40">Features like electric and heated seats are becoming more common in the marketplace and seemingly small touches like these can make the difference between one car and another model. </s></p><p n="p3.40"><s n="s1.3;p3.40">Electric seats - or power seats - are front seats that can be controlled by a switch or a joystick. </s><s n="s2.3;p3.40">They are designed to make the adjusting of the position or angle of the seat far easier and less distracting for the driver. </s><s n="s3.3;p3.40">Some luxury cars are also beginning to introduce memories which will remember a certain number of settings so a person needn't adjust the position of the driver's seat every time they get in the car. </s></p><p n="p4.40"><s n="s1.2;p4.40">Whilst electric seats have been around since the 1950s, it is only fairly recently that they have grown in popularity. </s><s n="s2.2;p4.40">Power seats are not strictly a necessity, but in an age where every extra gadget introduced will sell more cars, they are a feature that an increasing number of manufacturers are offering as standard. </s></p><p n="p5.40"><s n="s1.5;p5.40">Another comfort feature is heated seats, which are considered by many to be something of a luxury. </s><s n="s2.5;p5.40">These work by having a heating element made out of an alloy called nichrome in the lower seat. </s><s n="s3.5;p5.40">Unfortunately, they can be quite unreliable as one break anywhere in the system will cause the heater to stop working. </s><s n="s4.5;p5.40">This can happen regularly given the flexing of the seat. </s><s n="s5.5;p5.40">In addition to merely keeping the driver warm, manufacturers of heated seats also claim that they improve the circulation of the driver on long drives. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Future Case Study: Volvo Your Concept Car</head><p n="p6.40"><s n="s1.5;p6.40">In June 2002, Volvo decided to investigate creating a concept car that was designed for and by members of their fastest growing target consumer group - women. </s><s n="s2.5;p6.40">Approximately 54% of all Volvo buyers are women and this is increasing, especially in Europe. </s><s n="s3.5;p6.40">In December of the same year the project was given the go ahead. </s><s n="s4.5;p6.40">Volvo have had a female reference group to advise the company on what consumers want since the early 1980s, but this was the next step up. </s><s n="s5.5;p6.40">Unveiled at the 2004 Geneva Auto Show, everything about the vehicle was designed by women, most noticeably in the case of the interior, which is described as more like a living room than a cockpit. </s></p><p n="p7.40"><s n="s1.3;p7.40">The interior adaptations vary from the obvious - for instance increased storage - to the slightly more unusual - pony tail notches in the headrest. </s><s n="s2.3;p7.40">The use of materials gives the interior a more familiar feel than the bare metal used to and interchangeable seat covers add a bit of variety. </s><s n="s3.3;p7.40">The gear lever and hand-brake have been moved in order to make room for mobile phone and keys storage units. </s></p><p n="p8.40"><s n="s1.2;p8.40">Whilst the car is currently firmly in the concept stage, this sort of design could be the shape of things to come in terms of luxury cars. </s><s n="s2.2;p8.40">As technology develops it becomes easier to tailor car interiors specifically to the needs of particular people. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Protecting the interior</head><p n="p9.40"><s n="s1.4;p9.40">Protecting the occupants of a car should be the main concern in design. </s><s n="s2.4;p9.40">Modern British cars have an amazing array of safety features, some of which you probably don't even know exist. </s><s n="s3.4;p9.40">Here, I aim to give you an insight into the history of the safety features to protect the interior of cars. </s><s n="s4.4;p9.40">Considering the vast number of these features, and our nation's reputation as innovative engineers, it is astonishing that the British car industry has never really been at the forefront of car safety. </s></p><p n="p10.40"><s n="s1.6;p10.40">As cars increased in speed, windshield glass started to shatter during collisions, causing large, sharp shards to fly towards the occupants of the vehicle. </s><s n="s2.6;p10.40">Laminate glass, also called safety glass, was patented by Englishman, John Crew Wood in 1909. </s><s n="s3.6;p10.40">He found that a thin sheet of plastic in-between glass stopped it shattering. </s><s n="s4.6;p10.40">However, even though the technology was developed in Britain, its first use in vehicles was in 1919 by Ford, an American company. </s><s n="s5.6;p10.40">One possible explanation for this is that the maximum speed limit in Britain was 20mph before the Road Traffic Act of 1930 abolished this (afterwards the limit was completely unrestricted for vehicles carrying less than seven people until 1935!) and therefore road accidents in Britain were simply too slow to need the technology. </s><s n="s6.6;p10.40">The first cars with laminate glass included were unfortunately very expensive compared to models without and they were not very popular. </s></p><p n="p11.40"><s n="s1.3;p11.40">Seat belts were conceived in the 1800s by Sir George Cayley, renowned politician and inventor of many things that are common today, including self-righting life-boats, caterpillar tracks and early designs for helicopters. </s><s n="s2.3;p11.40">However, it was not until the 1950s that the automotive seat belt, named the AutoCrat safety belt and patented by Kenneth and Bob Ligon, was first introduced to the USA. In 1956, both Chrysler and Ford offered lap belts on front seats on some of their models, with the latter firm starting a two-year advertising campaign focusing on safety and in particular the use of seat belts. </s><s n="s3.3;p11.40">Three years later, Volvo became the first car manufacturer to offer 3-point belts as standard, in Sweden, and followed this up in the US in 1963. </s></p><p n="p12.40"><s n="s1.2;p12.40">Over the next 25 years, countries including the United States, Japan, New Zealand, Australia and Sweden passed regulations concerning seat belt use, either forcing manufacturers to offer them in all vehicles and/or making the use of them by the general public compulsory. </s><s n="s2.2;p12.40">It was only in 1991 that the European Union adopted Directive 91/671/EC, enforcing the mandatory use of safety belts, where fitted, starting in January 1993. </s></p><p n="p13.40"><s n="s1.6;p13.40">Volvo, from their start in 1927, have been pioneers in vehicle safety. </s><s n="s2.6;p13.40">In 1944 they released the PV model which was the first to include laminate glass inexpensively and the first to have a unibody. </s><s n="s3.6;p13.40">A unibody frame incorporates every bit of the chassis, welded together with the body parts of the car bolted on. </s><s n="s4.6;p13.40">The unibody surrounds the whole interior of a car and transfers the energy of a collision to the bonnet or boot of the car, away from the interior area. </s><s n="s5.6;p13.40">It reduced the cost of the car and also reduced the amount of vibration. </s><s n="s6.6;p13.40">This frame is the most widely used in the design of modern vehicles. </s></p><p n="p14.40"><s n="s1.5;p14.40">In 1956, the first car with a padded dashboard, the Amazon, was introduced by Volvo. </s><s n="s2.5;p14.40">This was before three point seat belts had been invented and was therefore what passengers in the front of the car definitely came into contact with during a collision. </s><s n="s3.5;p14.40">By cushioning the dashboard, the impulse time increased, decreasing the maximum force exerted on the passenger. </s><s n="s4.5;p14.40">Padded dashboards have been estimated to have saved over 2100 lives since their introduction. </s><s n="s5.5;p14.40">A collapsible steering wheel column was invented by the Swedes in 1973 for the same purpose. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0342d-pic.001"/><p n="p15.40"><s n="s1.7;p15.40">In the early 1970s, manufacturers including Chevrolet, General Motors and Ford began experimenting with a new internal safety feature, the airbag. </s><s n="s2.7;p15.40">It is made up of three main sections. </s><s n="s3.7;p15.40">The bag itself is made up of a thin nylon fabric. </s><s n="s4.7;p15.40">The inflation system produces blasts of nitrogen gas from a reaction between sodium azide and potassium nitrate. </s><s n="s5.7;p15.40">The sensor that tells the bag when to inflate does so if a collision occurs that is comparable to driving head first into a brick wall at between 10 and 15 miles per hour. </s><s n="s6.7;p15.40">The bag bursts out of its storage unit at 200 miles per hour, taking a tenth of a second to fully inflate. </s><s n="s7.7;p15.40">After less than a second, the bag deflates as the gas escapes from the bag through tiny holes so as not to cause further danger, like the risk of suffocation, to the driver. </s></p><p n="p16.40"><s n="s1.2;p16.40">In the beginning, concerns over whether early airbags would kill more people than they would save delayed their introduction into the mainstream market on more than one occasion, however many of these fears were somewhat unfounded as there are very few reported incidents where an airbag has caused harm to a driver. </s><s n="s2.2;p16.40">The first report of an airbag related fatality was in fact in 1990 when a 64 year old woman suffered critical injuries from her airbag. </s></p><p n="p17.40"><s n="s1.3;p17.40">Rear-facing child seats were invented by Volvo, in 1964. </s><s n="s2.3;p17.40">They keep the head and spine of a child's body in line during a collision. </s><s n="s3.3;p17.40">They also introduced the first child booster seat in 1978, raising children to a level that seat belts can work effectively. </s></p><p n="p18.40"><s n="s1.2;p18.40">During the 1990's the British car industry finally caught up. </s><s n="s2.2;p18.40">It did so however, by using Volvo technology and could only achieve the same safety standard as Volvo, not exceed it. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0342d-pic.002"><head>WHIPS - Whiplash Protection System</head></figure><p n="p19.40"><s n="s1.5;p19.40">Introduced in 1998, Volvo's whiplash protection system (WHIPS) completely revolutionized safety in the interior of all cars, thrusting the company far ahead of any British one. </s><s n="s2.5;p19.40">The headrest of the seat is positioned and locked in place so that the passenger's head is not able to "whip" backwards. </s><s n="s3.5;p19.40">The seat is designed to support the spine and also recline during an accident to increase impact time. </s><s n="s4.5;p19.40">Recessed dashboard controls and door handles developed over the years have been introduced into modern cars to stop passengers being impaled on them. </s><s n="s5.5;p19.40">Volvo's dominance in safety innovation is not only restricted to car interiors, they have invented nearly every safety system you can find in modern cars. </s></p><p n="p20.40"><s n="s1.4;p20.40">The British car industry has recently caught up in the race. </s><s n="s2.4;p20.40">Since 1999, Volvo has been part of Ford's Premier automotive group. </s><s n="s3.4;p20.40">Since then, safety innovations from Volvo have made their first appearance in "British" companies. </s><s n="s4.4;p20.40">The 2002 Jaguar X-type was the first car to include a collapsible brake pedal that protects the lower leg of the driver and a petrol tank that crumples instead of exploding in an accident. </s></p><p n="p21.40"><s n="s1.3;p21.40">Maybe if firms in the British car industry had put more effort into researching new car safety technology, even in just the interior, it would have a better reputation, higher sales, and might not be in as serious a recline as it is today. </s><s n="s2.3;p21.40">Perhaps if the 1896 motor car act, limiting the maximum speed of a motor car to 20mph had been rectified before 1930, the nation would have needed faster advances in car safety in the early years. </s><s n="s3.3;p21.40">Perhaps this would have given us a head start. </s></p><p n="p22.40"><s n="s1.1;p22.40">Innovations in interior car safety in the British car industry have been completely dominated, without doubt, by another nation. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">The car radio</head><p n="p23.40"><s n="s1.5;p23.40">In 1928, two brothers, Paul and Joseph Galvin purchased a battery eliminator business which allowed battery powered radios to be run from mains electricity. </s><s n="s2.5;p23.40">Using this acquired knowledge, they developed a radio that could run from a car battery which became the first ever car radio - the Motorola 5T71. </s><s n="s3.5;p23.40">The radio itself sold for around $120 and so it was only the preserve of the rich, but in the late 1920's it was generally only the rich who could afford cars. </s><s n="s4.5;p23.40">The sound quality was very poor due to the poor quality of the speakers, which continued until 1936 when Pioneer introduced the A-8 dynamic speaker. </s><s n="s5.5;p23.40">This, combined with the poor radio reception outside of major cities and the noise generated by cars of this period meant that the radio could only really be used when the car was stationary. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0342d-pic.003"/><figure id="BAWE_0342d-pic.004"/><p n="p24.40"><s n="s1.5;p24.40">For a brief period in the mid fifties, Chrysler offered an in-car record player as an option to its customers (records being the only commercially available audio hardware). </s><s n="s2.5;p24.40">They were mounted on the transmission tunnel underneath the dashboard - the only place large enough to accommodate the players and close enough to be played into the radio. </s><s n="s3.5;p24.40">Even though it was a good idea in principle, it was fatally flawed. </s><s n="s4.5;p24.40">To keep the needle in place a spring had to be used which dramatically reduced the record's lifespan. </s><s n="s5.5;p24.40">Also, the fact that each record would only last three to five minutes meant that records had to be changed regularly, which was much more difficult than modern day CDs. </s></p><p n="p25.40"><s n="s1.3;p25.40">One of the most pioneering forms of audio was the 8 track tape. </s><s n="s2.3;p25.40">Although it has always been associated with the car industry, it was originally developed by Bill Lear (later founder of the Lear aeroplanes business) to form a new height of luxury for the 'jet set'. </s><s n="s3.3;p25.40">However, back in 1945 the equipment and technology required was not yet available so the project was soon scrapped. </s></p><p n="p26.40"><s n="s1.5;p26.40">This was until 1963 when Lear became a distributor for Muntz Electronics, which now gave him the ability to develop and install 8 track units for his aircraft. </s><s n="s2.5;p26.40">An 8 track cassette consists of an endless loop of magnetic tape housed in a plastic cartridge. </s><s n="s3.5;p26.40">A great feature of this was that the cartridge never needed 'turning over' as it would just keep on playing, but unfortunately it was not possible to rewind them. </s><s n="s4.5;p26.40">Ford had partially invested in Lear's development of the 8 track, and so in 1966 they offered the players (built by Motorola) as an optional extra on their cars. </s><s n="s5.5;p26.40">The demand for them was huge, and other manufacturers soon began to follow suit. </s></p><p n="p27.40"><s n="s1.4;p27.40">Almost immediately after the 8 track's introduction, Philips introduced the compact audio cassette. </s><s n="s2.4;p27.40">This cassette was considerably smaller than the 8 track's cartridge and its reel to reel format allowed listeners to fast forward and rewind. </s><s n="s3.4;p27.40">The smaller size of the audio cassette meant that the players inside the car could be a lot smaller too, and most manufacturers began to integrate them into the dashboards of new cars. </s><s n="s4.4;p27.40">Audio cassettes eventually became totally dominant, mainly because they were more user friendly and also because it was possible to record onto then (this was the age of the mix tape, after all!), even though the 8 track offered better sound quality. </s></p><p n="p28.40"><s n="s1.3;p28.40">It took until the mid 1980s for car manufacturers to adopt a DIN standard fir mounting for UK car stereos, but when it did eventually happen it allowed numerous electronics manufacturers to offer upgraded versions. </s><s n="s2.3;p28.40">This, in turn, opened the doors for the In Car Entertainment (ICE) scene which had originated in America a decade previously to make its way to Britain. </s><s n="s3.3;p28.40">Since then, this industry has flourished, become more sophisticated and importantly - cheap and accessible even to those with only a basic knowledge of car electronics. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Use of Materials in British Car Interiors since the 1900's</head><p n="p29.40"><s n="s1.2;p29.40">5 classic Jaguars were selected from the Coventry Transport Museum and with the help of a museum attendant the materials used for different parts of the car were identified. </s><s n="s2.2;p29.40">All the cars are from the same manufacturer to ensure consistency of quality. </s></p><p n="p30.40"><s n="s1.1;p30.40">The 5 cars were: </s></p><list type="bulleted"><item>1933 SS1 Coupe (This was before the Jaguar brand was made but the car was designed by William Lyons)</item><item>1953 XK 120</item><item>1957 XK 150</item><item>1962 Mark X</item><item>1975 E type Coupe</item></list><p n="p31.40"><s n="s1.2;p31.40">The interior of all these cars were manufactured by hand thus allowing for high levels of customization. </s><s n="s2.2;p31.40">However, over the years as manufacturing techniques became more and more advanced and efficient the levels of custom ability declined. </s></p><p n="p32.40"><s n="s1.3;p32.40">In today's cars the steering wheels are made of molded pigmented vinyl resins or pigmented urethane and have layers of acetyl to seal off magnetic areas of the steering wheel. </s><s n="s2.3;p32.40">The cars in the museum featured steering wheels made of Bakelite, a plastic developed in 1907. </s><s n="s3.3;p32.40">Although the material was hard and durable it is no longer used due to its brittle nature. </s></p><p n="p33.40"><s n="s1.10;p33.40">The panels of the cars consisted of lots of leather and wood veneer. </s><s n="s2.10;p33.40">Starting with the SS1, the entire front console is thick high quality wood veneer, with the dials in the centre framed by stainless steel. </s><s n="s3.10;p33.40">The XK 120 also features a full wood veneer console, however, it is of lower quality. </s><s n="s4.10;p33.40">The XK 150's console is constructed completely from leather, even the dials in the centre are housed using leather. </s><s n="s5.10;p33.40">The Mark X returns to a full wood front console and the wood used is of high quality and isn't simply flat like in the earlier models. </s><s n="s6.10;p33.40">The E type is where the radical change of materials used is witnessed. </s><s n="s7.10;p33.40">There is no use of wood panels whatsoever in the cars interior, instead the console is wrapped in synthetic leather with use of some plastic. </s><s n="s8.10;p33.40">Synthetic leather was invented in the early 1900's but wasn't used in cars until the late 20's. </s><s n="s9.10;p33.40">It seems that Jaguar chose not to use it as it could hinder the quality of the cars. </s><s n="s10.10;p33.40">However by the 70's the cost difference between real and synthetic leather became significant enough that it was wiser to use the synthetic alternatives for consoles, doors and other parts of the interior cabin. </s></p><p n="p34.40"><s n="s1.11;p34.40">There is an extensive use of cloth in the cars as well, mainly for carpeting purposes. </s><s n="s2.11;p34.40">In the SS1 the thin carpeting had torn off which revealed a wooden floor. </s><s n="s3.11;p34.40">It is only the earlier cars that featured wooden floor as the wood would rot away causing problems. </s><s n="s4.11;p34.40">On today's cars there is a rubber lining that weatherproofs the gaps between the door and the fame. </s><s n="s5.11;p34.40">On the SS1 there is no such lining which meant that water could seep into the car. </s><s n="s6.11;p34.40">On the XK and Mark 10 models there is use of a rubber lining but the rubber is quite hard and was not as good as the soft rubber we use now. </s><s n="s7.11;p34.40">The E type features softer leather and also some synthetic leather to weather proof the cabin. </s><s n="s8.11;p34.40">Something noticeable about the E types interior is that the headrest has deflated. </s><s n="s9.11;p34.40">The reason for this is the manufacturing process. </s><s n="s10.11;p34.40">The foam used in the headrest is heated before being wrapped in leather, therefore, over the years as the effects of the initial heat treatment wear off the foam shrinks. </s><s n="s11.11;p34.40">This problem has now been fixed in modern cars by using different techniques. </s></p><p n="p35.40"><s n="s1.6;p35.40">The materials that are used in cars are chosen for both aesthetics and also functionability. </s><s n="s2.6;p35.40">The key material in the interior of a car is leather, it is aesthetically pleasing and also functions great for seats, doors and consoles. </s><s n="s3.6;p35.40">Synthetic leather is being used more and more in today's cars to save on costs, however, leather seats are still the desired choice. </s><s n="s4.6;p35.40">Wood is mainly used to enhance the interior design of the car, apart from where it is used for the floor of the car. </s><s n="s5.6;p35.40">The most widely used material in present cars however are plastics. </s><s n="s6.6;p35.40">The steering wheel, instrument panel, carpeting, air ducts, switches and the list continues. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Rolls-Royce</head><p n="p36.40"><s n="s1.5;p36.40">The interiors of Rolls-Royce have always been of a very high standard, like the whole car. </s><s n="s2.5;p36.40">It has been said that no two Rolls-Royce vehicles are the same. </s><s n="s3.5;p36.40">There have been a number of different colours for the upholstery, which could have been chosen in a variety of contrasting combinations by the purchaser. </s><s n="s4.5;p36.40">Also as all the woodwork in Rolls-Royce are made of real wood then there is going to be different grain patterns in each car. </s><s n="s5.5;p36.40">Rolls-Royce also offers a bespoke program giving customers the opportunity to stipulate individual requests, such as unique exterior colour or a particular interior feature. </s></p><p n="p37.40"><s n="s1.5;p37.40">Rolls-Royce interior is a haven of natural materials; the upholstery is all leather, Winton carpets with soft lamb's wool rugs and masses of real wood finishes. </s><s n="s2.5;p37.40">The wood was and still is chosen from special forestry's. </s><s n="s3.5;p37.40">The wooden components are all produced by extremely skilled craftsmen who cut out and shape each of the components. </s><s n="s4.5;p37.40">So much craftsmanship went into making these wooden components that in some of the cars it took 30days just to produce them. </s><s n="s5.5;p37.40">In the new Phantom and maybe some of the earlier cars the wood which goes into them is handpicked before it is actually crafted into shape. </s></p><p n="p38.40"><s n="s1.5;p38.40">The leathers used in Rolls-Royce cars have been from handpicked hides from specialist tanneries which have put the hides through a special pigmentation process that gets the chosen colour, rather than painting the leather which other car manufacturers have done and still do. </s><s n="s2.5;p38.40">This has made the leather smoother and more hard wearing, which can be seen in older models in which the leather is still in exceptional condition. </s><s n="s3.5;p38.40">Some Rolls-Royce have two different types of leather used in them, natural grain leather is used on the seats and door panels while tipped leather is used where it has been stitched together. </s><s n="s4.5;p38.40">Like the wood in the cars the leather has also been sewn in to the highest of standard by highly skilled craftsmen. </s><s n="s5.5;p38.40">Standards are so high that in the new Phantom each centre console takes half a day to cover. </s></p><p n="p39.40"><s n="s1.3;p39.40">To test their Winton carpets Rolls-Royce use two imitation wooden heels to test the durability of them. </s><s n="s2.3;p39.40">The heels rub back and forth 100000times over 4inches of the carpets. </s><s n="s3.3;p39.40">This is in line with all their other vigorous quality checks that they have gone through before they were sent out onto the road. </s></p><p n="p40.40"><s n="s1.3;p40.40">All of this superb craftsmanship and engineering is evident when you just look at or sit in a Rolls-Royce. </s><s n="s2.3;p40.40">Even in some of the early models it is clear that the condition of the interior excellent and has worn well over the years due to the effort of the craftsmen. </s><s n="s3.3;p40.40">In any Rolls-Royce you travel in you are guaranteed a comfortable, relaxing ride. </s></p></div1></body><back/></text></TEI.2>
