<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_0342b" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Design Project Circuits</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">The document has a title page which contains:
document title
title part</note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">deleted: header: module and student numbers; footer: page numbers</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">2</p><p n="date">2007-02</p><p n="module title">Electronic Design</p><p n="module code">ES2A4</p><p n="genre family">Methodology recount</p><p n="discipline">Engineering</p><p n="disciplinary group">PS</p><p n="grade">unknown</p><p n="number of authors">unknown</p><p n="number of words">747</p><p n="number of s-units">35</p><p n="number of p">16</p><p n="number of tables">4</p><p n="number of figures">5</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">0</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">0</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">21.3</p><p n="average s-units per p">2.2</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">m</p><p n="year of birth">1986</p><p n="first language">English</p><p n="education">UKA</p><p n="course">Meng</p><p n="student ID">0342</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><docTitle><titlePart rend="bold">ES2A4A8 Electronic Design - Design Project Circuits</titlePart></docTitle><titlePart rend="bold">Submission date: 7th February 2007 Student ID: <name type="student ID"/></titlePart></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">Notes of Load Lines:</head><p n="p1.16"><s n="s1.1;p1.16">The true current flowing in the circuit shown below was found by creating the circuit shown in diagram 1 and plotting the characteristics of the 1N4002 diode. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0342b-pic.001"/><p n="p2.16"><s n="s1.2;p2.16">Load lines were drawn on the characteristic using the supply voltage (6V) and appropriate values of current. </s><s n="s2.2;p2.16">When drawing the load line to find the actual current flowing in the circuit of figure 1 on the handout, the load line intersects the y-axis at 25mA, the current that is assumed to be flowing, calculated using ohms law (R = 240Ω, V = 6). </s></p><p n="p3.16"><s n="s1.2;p3.16">The current required to cause 15mA to flow was found by drawing another load line on the simulated characteristics of the diode. </s><s n="s2.2;p3.16">The load line intersects the characteristic plot (which gives the actual current flowing in the circuit) at 15mA, then the point at which the load line </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">Diode analysis</head><p n="p4.16"><s n="s1.2;p4.16">Using an IV analyser (arranged as in Diagram 1) a simulated characteristic graph can be plotted (Figure 1). </s><s n="s2.2;p4.16">Here the characteristics of the 1N4002GP diode are explored. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0342b-pic.002"><head>(Diagram 1)</head></figure><p n="p5.16"><s n="s1.1;p5.16">I calculated the current to be 22.3mA from the simulated circuit characteristic (Figure 1 - Appendix) with a 240Ω resistor was in series with the diode and the supply voltage was 6V. </s></p><p n="p6.16"><s n="s1.1;p6.16">From the paper design (see page 2 of appendix) I found the current to be 22mA. </s></p><p n="p7.16"><s n="s1.1;p7.16">I tested the circuit using a multimeter (Diagram 2) and found the true value to be 22.29mA. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0342b-pic.003"><head>(Diagram 2)</head></figure><table id="BAWE_0342b-tab.001"><head>(Table 1)</head><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p8.16"><s n="s1.2;p8.16">From table one it can be seen that there is a marked increase in accuracy of the simulated characteristic method over the paper based method. </s><s n="s2.2;p8.16">The %error has been reduced by a factor of more than 3. </s></p><p n="p9.16"><s n="s1.2;p9.16">The required value of R if a current of 15mA was to be achieved was then calculated using a load line from the simulated characteristic plot. </s><s n="s2.2;p9.16">I found the current required to be 16.8mA. Using ohms law a resistor of 357Ω, (1% tolerance) please refer to figure 1 in appendix. </s></p><p n="p10.16"><s n="s1.1;p10.16">From the paper design (see page 2 of appendix) I found the resistor required to be 352Ω. </s></p><p n="p11.16"><s n="s1.2;p11.16">A simulation was then run to determine the actual current in the circuit with the chosen resistors. </s><s n="s2.2;p11.16">I unfortunately chose a resistor from a different series (not E24) in my paper design and therefore had to use 2 different resistors to achieve the value stated, as shown in diagram 3 below. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0342b-pic.004"><head>(Diagram 3 - testing the resistor chosen in paper design)</head></figure><figure id="BAWE_0342b-pic.005"><head>(Diagram 4 - testing the resistor chosen using simulated characteristic)</head></figure><table id="BAWE_0342b-tab.002"><head>(Table 2)</head><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p12.16"><s n="s1.3;p12.16">The paper design does give a good estimate of the operating current of the circuit, however it is less accurate than the simulated characteristic value by a large amount. </s><s n="s2.3;p12.16">It is worth taking into account that the simulated values throughout the analysis of this diode will be inaccurate also as the components used will have tolerances. </s><s n="s3.3;p12.16">In the real world the component values will vary due to this and the operating current would most likely be a different value. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">Transistor amplifier analysis</head><p n="p13.16"><s n="s1.2;p13.16">The table below shows the characteristics of my circuit submitted as the paper design. </s><s n="s2.2;p13.16">Please refer to the appendix for calculations and circuit diagram. </s></p><table id="BAWE_0342b-tab.003"><head>(Table 2)</head><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p14.16"><s n="s1.5;p14.16">There are a number of problems with the original circuit I designed. </s><s n="s2.5;p14.16">The gain and the upper cut-off frequency do not match the specification. </s><s n="s3.5;p14.16">This is because the equations used to calculate the gain was incorrect. </s><s n="s4.5;p14.16">To rectify the gain I performed new calculations. </s><s n="s5.5;p14.16">These can be viewed in the appendix under the title of "Calculating gain". </s></p><p n="p15.16"><s n="s1.6;p15.16">To rectify the upper cut-off value another capacitor is needed. </s><s n="s2.6;p15.16">This should be placed across R <hi rend="sub">C</hi>. </s><s n="s3.6;p15.16">This creates an upper cut-off due to the fact that when the frequencies are above the calculated cut-off frequency (see appendix entitled "Calculating upper cut-off capacitor value") the capacitor's reactance becomes very low. </s><s n="s4.6;p15.16">This causes the current to flow through the capacitor and not the resistor R <hi rend="sub">C</hi>. </s><s n="s5.6;p15.16">This in turn reduces the output as the gain of the circuit is determined by the ratio of the resistance values of R <hi rend="sub">C</hi> and R <hi rend="sub">E</hi>. </s><s n="s6.6;p15.16">When the capacitor's reactance is low, R <hi rend="sub">C</hi> is effectively low, causing the gain to decrease. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Revised circuit:</head><figure id="BAWE_0342b-pic.006"><head>(Diagram 5 - Revised circuit)</head></figure><table id="BAWE_0342b-tab.004"><row><cell/></row></table><figure id="BAWE_0342b-fig.001"/><figure id="BAWE_0342b-fig.002"/><figure id="BAWE_0342b-fig.003"/><figure id="BAWE_0342b-fig.004"/><figure id="BAWE_0342b-fig.005"/><p n="p16.16"><s n="s1.2;p16.16">The circuit now meets all of the specifications bar one, the DC supply current. </s><s n="s2.2;p16.16">I have learnt a great deal about transistor amplifiers and using Multisim software throughout this project, however calculating values that meet the DC supply current gain is beyond my current capabilities. </s></p></div1></body><back/></text></TEI.2>
