<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_0342a" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Enlighten - Bright Ideas for Green Future</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">The document has a title page which contains:
document title
title part</note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">Evaluated as candidate compound assignment. Assigned to A5: Mixed (other than A5a): compound.</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">2</p><p n="date">unknown</p><p n="module title">Starting and Running a Business</p><p n="module code">ES2A6</p><p n="genre family">Empathy writing + Proposal</p><p n="discipline">Engineering</p><p n="disciplinary group">PS</p><p n="grade">unknown</p><p n="number of authors">unknown</p><p n="number of words">1436</p><p n="number of s-units">40</p><p n="number of p">29</p><p n="number of tables">2</p><p n="number of figures">2</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">21</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">10</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">35.9</p><p n="average s-units per p">1.4</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">compound assignment consisting of 2 parts (see notesStmt for details)</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">m</p><p n="year of birth">1986</p><p n="first language">English</p><p n="education">UKA</p><p n="course">Meng</p><p n="student ID">0342</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><titlePart/><docTitle><titlePart rend="bold">bright ideas for a green future</titlePart></docTitle><titlePart><name type="other"/><name type="other"/><name type="other"/></titlePart><titlePart>HSBC Bank PLC Canada Place Canary Wharf Docklands London E14 5AH</titlePart></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="text"><head>To Whom It May Concern</head><p n="p1.29"><s n="s1.3;p1.29">Enclosed is the proposed business plan for the e-commerce company providing energy-efficient light bulbs, "Enlighten". </s><s n="s2.3;p1.29">Climate change is of the utmost importance in today's market place, providing an ideal opportunity for any company offering energy-efficient solutions. </s><s n="s3.3;p1.29">Government legislation may soon see all wasteful incandescent lighting banned for general lighting purposes showing long term advantages and security for the company. </s></p><p n="p2.29"><s n="s1.3;p2.29">Enlighten will offer a high level of service to customers including rapid email response and telephone advice &amp; assistance to build a customer base, differentiating itself from its competitors in the e-commerce market. </s><s n="s2.3;p2.29">Employee relationships with research teams developing the latest technologies in the lighting sector will offer exclusive products. </s><s n="s3.3;p2.29">The managing director of the firm has had previous experience starting a profitable online business providing similar products. </s></p><p n="p3.29"><s n="s1.4;p3.29">To start up this business we require a Flexible Business Loan up to the value of £70,000 for initial funding. </s><s n="s2.4;p3.29">Alongside this we have £20,000 collected of personal finance to invest in this company. </s><s n="s3.4;p3.29">We have qualified for a Small Firms Loan Guarantee with the DTI to make this funding possible. </s><s n="s4.4;p3.29">To reduce start-up costs the firm shall locate in a home office in Royal Leamington Spa (200sq feet). </s></p><p n="p4.29"><s n="s1.1;p4.29">Enlighten will be a limited liability company, privately owned by <name type="student name"/> and <name type="student name"/>. </s></p><div2><head rend="bold">Projected sales</head><table id="BAWE_0342a-tab.001"><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p5.29"/></div2><div2><head rend="bold">Objectives</head><p rend="ordered" n="p6.29"><s n="s1.1;p6.29">To provide a quality service, building a customer base of 3,000 customers at the end of the first year. </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p7.29"><s n="s1.1;p7.29">Achieve a turnover of £150,000 in the first year, £220,000 in the second year and £300,000 in the third year with profits of £30,000, £44,000 and £60,000 respectively. </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p8.29"><s n="s1.1;p8.29">Sell 0.7% of all CFL's<ref target="BAWE_0342a-ftnote.001"/> sold in the UK by the end of the third year, providing the turnover shown. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0342a-ftnote.001"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Compact fluorescent lamp </s></p></note><p n="p9.29"><s n="s1.1;p9.29"><name type="student name"/> </s></p><p n="p10.29"><s n="s1.1;p10.29">MD </s></p><p n="p11.29"><s n="s1.1;p11.29">Enlighten </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="text"><div2><head rend="bold">Marketing</head><p n="p12.29"><s n="s1.1;p12.29">Key elements of marketing strategy: </s></p><div3><head rend="underlined bold">Marketing segmentation</head><p rend="bulleted" n="p13.29"><s n="s1.1;p13.29">Market large enough to justify committing resources - huge market </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p14.29"><s n="s1.1;p14.29">Market has potential for future growth - always growing, development in energy saving. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p15.29"><s n="s1.1;p15.29">Market has potential for increased value - providing energy saving and new technology light bulbs before the competitors will give us the market lead </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p16.29"><s n="s1.1;p16.29">Not too much competition - not for online, small business sellers </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p17.29"><s n="s1.1;p17.29">Need for our company's products - increasing energy prices, keeping companies' spending lower, everyone needs light-bulbs </s></p></div3><div3><head rend="underlined bold">Market entry</head><list type="bulleted"><item>Demand patterns - always in demand; particular demand in the winter</item><item>Education of the end user</item><item>Development of new products - not so much development, as promotion; focus on new technology, not usual old bulbs</item><item>Competitor activity - RESEARCH</item></list><p n="p18.29"/></div3><div3><head rend="underlined bold">Launch</head><list type="bulleted"><item>Lead time - build up stock and create website</item><item>Setting up distribution and stocks - Al covering distribution and packaging; CHECK AOBUT STOCKS</item><item>Training staff - not necessary as internet based company, no sales assistants; internet nature of company reduces need for people which keeps wages low; using automatic phone system (AL)</item></list><p n="p19.29"/></div3><div3><head rend="underlined bold">Marketing Mix</head><figure id="BAWE_0342a-fig.001"><head>Positioning Map:</head></figure><p n="p20.29"><s n="s1.3;p20.29">We aim to sell a wide range of energy saving and CFL (Compact Fluorescent Lamp) bulbs. </s><s n="s2.3;p20.29">Within the next few years, legislation will come in which may force businesses to use such bulbs, so we intend to establish ourselves now as leaders in this market. </s><s n="s3.3;p20.29">We shall supply low price bulbs of a range of qualities, as positioned in the map above. </s></p><p n="p21.29"><s n="s1.3;p21.29">For a successful marketing campaign, we must look at the "Four P's". </s><s n="s2.3;p21.29">These are Product, Promotion, Price and Place. </s><s n="s3.3;p21.29">I will now investigate how these different sections can further our business. </s></p></div3><div3><head>1.5 <hi rend="underlined bold">Product, Place, Price &amp; Promotion</hi></head><div4><head rend="underlined bold">Product</head><list type="bulleted"><head>Features:</head><item>energy saving</item><item>CFLs</item><item>Soon to become the only legal bulbs for businesses.</item></list><list type="bulleted"><head>Quality:</head><item>Varying qualities with correspondingly low prices, to cater for as wide a market as possible.</item></list><list type="bulleted"><head>Brand/image:</head><item>Exclusive production from Ms Zi's company in China</item><item>Supply other bigger brands as the bulbs are too rare to make worthwhile producing ourselves</item></list><list type="bulleted"><head>Packaging:</head><item>Packaging kept to a minimum to help reduce carbon emissions and unnecessary waste</item><item>Packing substantial enough not to break bulbs</item><item>Delivered by post for individual orders, or in bulk by van for larger (office) orders</item></list><list type="bulleted"><head>Guarantees:</head><item>Standard one year guarantee with all products as a minimum</item><item>Bulbs can last up to 8000 hours, so we would expect the average bulb to last for a minimum of two years</item></list><list type="bulleted"><head>Service positioning:</head><item>As an additional service for businesses we can fit out an entire new office and install light fittings</item><item>This is done through an associated chain of electricians whom we can call up at short notice if necessary anywhere across the UK.</item></list><p n="p22.29"/></div4><div4><head rend="underlined bold">Place</head><list type="bulleted"><head>Customers:</head><item>Primarily, advertising is based at small businesses and offices</item><item>Targeting new businesses who will make for long term customers</item><item>Available to anyone browsing the internet</item><item>Domestic customers still benefit from the convenience and speed of delivery, though are unlikely to benefit from bulk buying discounts</item></list><p rend="bulleted" n="p23.29"><s n="s1.1;p23.29">Distribution: see "Selling" in promotion. </s></p><list type="bulleted"><head>Location:</head><item>As a footloose web-based company, our location doesn't affect our customers.</item><item>Can locate anywhere, allowing cheap premises.</item></list><list type="bulleted"><head>Stock levels:</head><item>Lightbulbs don't go out of date or perish at a fast rate, so we would rather have more stock than necessary and always be relied upon to be able to supply any bulb at any time</item><item>Specialising in energy saving and CFL bulbs.</item></list></div4><div4><head rend="underlined bold">Price</head><list type="bulleted"><head>Level:</head><item>Varying prices depending on quality of the product</item><item>Ultimate aim is to undercut other distribution companies</item></list><list type="bulleted"><head>Sensitivity:</head><item>By establishing ourselves early on, we will become noted as the pioneers in this market for when government legislation commands that only our types of bulbs may be used in businesses</item><item>The market inevitably drops over the summer months as there is less need for artificial lighting</item></list><p rend="bulleted" n="p24.29"><s n="s1.1;p24.29">Discounts and Payment: see "Sales Promotion" and "Selling" in promotion. </s></p></div4><div4><head rend="underlined bold">Promotion</head><list type="bulleted"><head>Communication plan:</head><item>Essential in reaching the public</item><item>Several strategies which together should give us good promotion</item></list><list type="bulleted"><head>Advertising:</head><item>Links from web-based DIY companies</item><item><seg type="URL" n="www.batteries-online.co.uk"/></item><item><seg type="URL" n="www.diytradeprices.com"/></item><item><seg type="URL" n="www.screwfix.com"/></item><item><seg type="URL" n="www.foxdiy.co.uk"/></item><item>Ideal for a web-based company such as ourselves</item><item>Makes it easy for shoppers to buy all their DIY products in one go online</item></list><list type="bulleted"><head>Viral Advertising</head><item>Pop up adverts online</item><item>Particularly related to DIY/home living websites</item><item>Ideal for a web based company</item></list><list type="bulleted"><head>Leaflets</head><item>Leaflets advertising current promotions and new products to be sent out with each delivery</item><item>Partnerships with associated companies so every time they send out an order they enclose our leaflets, and vice versa</item><item>Displayed in non-chain DIY stores</item></list><list type="bulleted"><head>Magazines</head><item>Large number of DIY and home improvement magazines available for advertisements</item><item>Advertising in entrepreneurial magazines and newspapers too, to target new companies and businesses</item><item>Advertising in the Economist</item></list><list type="bulleted"><head>Sales promotion:</head><item>Monthly promotions, according to customer sales and current interest</item><item>Discounts for bulk orders</item><item>Free P&amp;P on orders over £25, encouraging bulk buying</item><item>Discounts for new businesses using us for the first time, on condition they use us for a minimum of two more orders</item></list><list type="bulleted"><head>Public relations:</head><item>User friendly website</item><item>Easy search tools within website, enabling you to find the exact bulb you want even for the non-engineering minded</item><item>Extensive "Help" and "FAQ" pages</item><item>12hour guaranteed reply to email queries</item><item>Phone line for any further queries</item></list><list type="bulleted"><head>Selling</head><item>First class post as standard delivery</item><item>Next day delivery available on all orders for minimal extra</item><item>"Within six hours" delivery service available for a premium price</item><item>All transactions by Direct Debit over secure internet sites ensures fast turnaround and payment</item><item>Convenience and flexibility in not having to go to a shop, and always open</item></list><p n="p25.29"/></div4></div3><div3><head rend="underlined bold">Market Segment</head><p n="p26.29"><s n="s1.2;p26.29">The energy-saving light bulb segment is fast growing, and there is a rapidly growing demand for these products by consumers. </s><s n="s2.2;p26.29">As referenced in the introductory letter, there is an opportunity to take advantage of possible future legislation changes in the type of light bulbs that will be available, energy-savers being the focus. </s></p><p n="p27.29"><s n="s1.2;p27.29">As seen by the table on the following page, CFL (Compact Fluorescent Lamp) sales increased by 110% over the 4-year period, indicating a clear direction for the market as a whole. </s><s n="s2.2;p27.29">Enlighten will concentrate on maximising their sales by focusing on selling CFLs. </s></p><table id="BAWE_0342a-tab.002"><head><hi rend="bold">UK retail sales of lamps (bulbs/tubes), by type, 2001-05</hi><hi rend="italic">Source: Mintel</hi></head><row><cell/></row></table></div3><div3><head> 1.7 <hi rend="underlined bold">Market Size</hi></head><p n="p28.29"><s n="s1.2;p28.29">From figure 1 we can see that the size in terms of total units sold does not change significantly over the four year period. </s><s n="s2.2;p28.29">However if we look at the market size in terms of retail sales, we can see an overall upward trend in the amount of money in this market. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0342a-fig.002"><head>Figure 2</head></figure><p n="p29.29"><s n="s1.3;p29.29">Figure 2 shows a clear increase in market value, despite no rise in units sold. </s><s n="s2.3;p29.29">According to Mintel, however this is due to rising sales of specialist lighting, but this is linked directly to trends in luminaries/fittings sales. </s><s n="s3.3;p29.29">For CFLs, retail prices are falling, and therefore Enlighten must concentrate on sourcing cheap manufacturers in order to secure a decent profit margin. </s></p></div3></div2></div1></body><back/></text></TEI.2>
