<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_0342e" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Jaguar Marketing/Industry Exercise</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note/></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">1</p><p n="date">unknown</p><p n="module title">Design for Function</p><p n="module code">ES174</p><p n="genre family">Case study</p><p n="discipline">Engineering</p><p n="disciplinary group">PS</p><p n="grade">unknown</p><p n="number of authors">unknown</p><p n="number of words">1004</p><p n="number of s-units">60</p><p n="number of p">19</p><p n="number of tables">2</p><p n="number of figures">2</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">0</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">0</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">16.7</p><p n="average s-units per p">3.2</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">m</p><p n="year of birth">1986</p><p n="first language">English</p><p n="education">UKA</p><p n="course">Meng</p><p n="student ID">0342</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><titlePart rend="underlined bold"><name type="student name"/></titlePart><docTitle><titlePart rend="underlined bold">ES175 Jaguar Marketing/Industry Exercise</titlePart></docTitle></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined">Structure of the market/industry</head><p n="p1.19"><s n="s1.6;p1.19">Jaguar belongs to the luxury automotive market. </s><s n="s2.6;p1.19">This is an oligopoly containing companies such as BMW, Mercedes-Benz, Austin Martin, Land Rover, Lexus, Porsche, Rolls-Royce, Bentley, etc. </s><s n="s3.6;p1.19">Jaguar's SIC code is 3410 (manufacture of motor vehicles). </s><s n="s4.6;p1.19">BMW is the market leader (Honda is not a luxury car manufacturer) with a profit of almost £80million (2004). </s><s n="s5.6;p1.19">Toyota (Lexus) is second with a profit of £50 million (2004). </s><s n="s6.6;p1.19">Jaguar however made a loss of £601million (2003). </s></p><table id="BAWE_0342e-tab.001"><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p2.19"><s n="s1.3;p2.19">The industry is highly differentiated with products of high quality, cost, and speciality. </s><s n="s2.3;p2.19">With respect to the market adoption graph: the automotive industry is a cash cow. </s><s n="s3.3;p2.19">However, Jaguar is at the dog stage at the moment as the firm has a low market share and growth rate. </s></p><p n="p3.19"><s n="s1.5;p3.19">A new firm would face many barriers trying to enter this market. </s><s n="s2.5;p3.19">It would have to build a reputation of quality. </s><s n="s3.5;p3.19">The specialist machinery needed to enter the industry would be extremely expensive, resulting in sunk costs, resale of which would be difficult. </s><s n="s4.5;p3.19">Leaving the market would also be difficult due to these sunk costs which could not be recovered. </s><s n="s5.5;p3.19">However, an existing firm could be acquired reasonably easily. </s></p><p n="p4.19"><s n="s1.3;p4.19">Firms in this market compete on non price, for example. </s><s n="s2.3;p4.19">Consumers in the market are looking for a luxury vehicle and therefore have money to spare, enough to buy into a brand name purely because of its reputation. </s><s n="s3.3;p4.19">The control over price in the market is therefore limited mainly by the firm's reputation. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0342e-fig.001"/><p n="p5.19"><s n="s1.4;p5.19">The main order winners and qualifiers for Jaguar are its heritage. </s><s n="s2.4;p5.19">They have an outstanding reputation for quality and racing. </s><s n="s3.4;p5.19">However its heritage does limit its market by only appealing to the older generation. </s><s n="s4.4;p5.19">Demand in this market is price elastic as the products are luxury items; demand is responsive to a change in price. </s></p><p n="p6.19"><s n="s1.2;p6.19">The concentration pie chart opposite shows that the market is indeed an oligopoly. </s><s n="s2.2;p6.19">Jaguar holds 11.02% of the market concentration, 3 <hi rend="sup">rd</hi> in the market. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined">Typical conduct of firms competing within the market/industry</head><figure id="BAWE_0342e-pic.001"/><p n="p7.19"><s n="s1.4;p7.19">Within this market there are adversarial relationships between firms and therefore there is no collusion. </s><s n="s2.4;p7.19">This creates a zero sum game. </s><s n="s3.4;p7.19">BMW, the most powerful member of the market receives the largest share of the profit, whist poor performers, such as Jaguar lose business. </s><s n="s4.4;p7.19">There is a finite profit available to the supply chain. </s></p><p n="p8.19"><s n="s1.2;p8.19">Ford's premier automotive group is a small exception to this, as within the group, collusion occurs. </s><s n="s2.2;p8.19">The firms within the group are as follows; Aston Martin, Volvo, Jaguar, and Land Rover. </s></p><p n="p9.19"><s n="s1.3;p9.19">As the market competes on non price, promotional activity is rife. </s><s n="s2.3;p9.19">Promotions such as free optional extras (satellite navigation, leather seats, etc) help to boost sales. </s><s n="s3.3;p9.19">Advertisements in automotive magazines, by the roadside and on television are also common. </s></p><p n="p10.19"><s n="s1.4;p10.19">Research and development is practiced by all companies to be at the forefront of technology. </s><s n="s2.4;p10.19">New designs also have to be researched to keep up with the changing trends in design. </s><s n="s3.4;p10.19">The industry is high tech, requiring the most accurate and fast machines available. </s><s n="s4.4;p10.19">This inadvertently excludes new entrants due to the high cost of research and build of these machines. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined">Performance of this market/industry</head><figure id="BAWE_0342e-fig.002"/><p n="p11.19"><s n="s1.4;p11.19">Jaguar has not performed well. </s><s n="s2.4;p11.19">From the table in page 1, a loss of £601million can be seen. </s><s n="s3.4;p11.19">The net profit (profit/turnover) for Jaguar in 2003 was -24.7%. </s><s n="s4.4;p11.19">From the graph opposite showing net profit, Jaguar can be seen to be falling far behind other firms in the market. </s></p><p n="p12.19"><s n="s1.3;p12.19">The main reason for Jaguar's poor performance is the fact that they export a lot of product to the US. At the start of the year, the exchange rate was $1.6 to the £. </s><s n="s2.3;p12.19">This meant that if Jaguar sold a car for £40,000 in the UK it would cost $64,000 in the US. As the price of the car in $ could not increase (this would result in a decrease in sales), the car would have to be sold for $64,000 at the end of the year when the £ was worth $1.8. </s><s n="s3.3;p12.19">Therefore, at the end of the year, Jaguar would be selling the car for £4,500 less relatively in the US than at the start of the year. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0342e-fig.003"/><table id="BAWE_0342e-tab.002"><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p13.19"><s n="s1.2;p13.19">Jaguar's current ratio is very low, suggesting that the firm is not in good financial health, if their obligations came due they probably could not repay them. </s><s n="s2.2;p13.19">However other firms in the market have much higher current ratios. </s></p><p n="p14.19"><s n="s1.2;p14.19">All is not lost however as Ford invested $2.1billion in jaguar in 2004. </s><s n="s2.2;p14.19">This infusion of capital will allow Jaguar to produce new models, advertise more and possibly make a profit by 2007. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined">Most viable strategy for a new entrant</head><p n="p15.19"><s n="s1.2;p15.19">A new entrant to the luxury car market would need to compete via differentiation and focus differentiation. </s><s n="s2.2;p15.19">To compete with firms such as jaguar, who produce high cost, luxury, quality products a new entrant would need to produce products of the same or better quality, but with a unique quality to the product they produce to differentiate themselves from the rest of the market. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0342e-pic.002"/><p n="p16.19"><s n="s1.1;p16.19">The luxury automotive market spans from companies such as BMW, to companies like Ferrari and Lamborghini, producing top of the range vehicles. </s></p><p n="p17.19"><s n="s1.2;p17.19">To compete with these companies a new entrant would have to compete via focus differentiation. </s><s n="s2.2;p17.19">A small number of high quality products would need to be produced and an amazing reputation built. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined">Recommendation to entrepreneur</head><p n="p18.19"><s n="s1.4;p18.19">Acquiring Jaguar and making a profit is possible. </s><s n="s2.4;p18.19">Out-sourcing factories to America to avoid the dependence on the exchange rate would be beneficial. </s><s n="s3.4;p18.19">However, as Jaguar's heritage lies in Britain this could damage the company's image. </s><s n="s4.4;p18.19">Reducing the number of employees and focusing on new technology could also increase profits. </s></p><p n="p19.19"><s n="s1.4;p19.19">Jaguar's reputation is bought with the company. </s><s n="s2.4;p19.19">A reputation such as Jaguar's takes decades to build. </s><s n="s3.4;p19.19">This is the main reason why I would advise upon the acquisition of Jaguar. </s><s n="s4.4;p19.19">Major changes to the company would need to be made, but large profits are possible after they have been implemented. </s></p></div1></body><back/></text></TEI.2>
