<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_0347a" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Material Characterisation Laboratory Report</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">The document has a title page which contains:
document title
title part</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">2</p><p n="date">2007-03</p><p n="module title">Biomedical Materials</p><p n="module code">ES2A1</p><p n="genre family">Methodology recount</p><p n="discipline">Engineering</p><p n="disciplinary group">PS</p><p n="grade">D</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">3569</p><p n="number of s-units">184</p><p n="number of p">80</p><p n="number of tables">0</p><p n="number of figures">10</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">4</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">0</p><p n="abstract present">abstract present</p><p n="average words per s-unit">19.4</p><p n="average s-units per p">2.3</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">f</p><p n="year of birth">1987</p><p n="first language">English</p><p n="education">UKA</p><p n="course">Meng</p><p n="student ID">0347</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><titlePart rend="bold">University of <name type="university"/> School of Engineering</titlePart><docTitle><titlePart rend="bold">Material Characterisation Laboratory Report</titlePart></docTitle><titlePart rend="bold">by Miss <name type="student name"/><name type="student ID"/></titlePart><titlePart>Report Reference Code: ES2A1A2 Biomedical Materials - Material Characterisation Lab Affiliation: Year 2 Engineering Report of laboratory taken place on: February 13 <hi rend="sup">th</hi> 2007</titlePart></titlePage><div1 type="toc" n="3"><head rend="bold">Table of Contents</head><p/></div1></front><body><div1 type="abstract"><head rend="bold">1.0 Abstract</head><p n="p1.80"><s n="s1.1;p1.80">From visualising different composite materials, it it possible to identify their characteristics and manufacturing techniques. </s></p><p n="p2.80"><s n="s1.3;p2.80">Through the use of XRD, it is seen that two substances within a biocomposite do not "fuse" together, but maintain their individual crystalline structures. </s><s n="s2.3;p2.80">The qualities from both products combine to make the biocomposite. </s><s n="s3.3;p2.80">Therefore, desirable properties can be achieved by mixing products together like this. </s></p><p n="p3.80"><s n="s1.1;p3.80">The OM use has shown that methods used during manufacture can be identified by grain analysis. </s></p><p n="p4.80"><s n="s1.1;p4.80">It was identified that the Brass sample had been strengthened from heat treatment and fast cooling, whereas the steel was identified as malleable, having been heat treated and slowly cooled. </s></p><p n="p5.80"><s n="s1.2;p5.80">From the SEM images, it could be seen that HAP on it's own was brittle, and the PE was flexible. </s><s n="s2.2;p5.80">Combined they supported each other to form a strong, stiff biocomposite. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">2.0 Introduction</head><p n="p6.80"><s n="s1.2;p6.80">The purpose of this laboratory session is to gain an understanding of both materials preparation, and instrumentation for analysis of various degrees of accuracy. </s><s n="s2.2;p6.80">In the duration of which, a knowledge of certain microstructures will be gained. </s></p><div2><head rend="bold italic">2.1 Objectives</head><p n="p7.80"><s n="s1.2;p7.80">From the Briefing Sheet supplied, we can identify the tasks to be undertaken. </s><s n="s2.2;p7.80">These are: </s></p><list type="bulleted"><item>Weighing and mixing of powders for composite processing;</item><item>Hot pressing of a polymer/ceramic biocomposite;</item><item>Analysis of the microstructure using Optical Microscopy (OM);</item><item>Analysis of the microstructure using the Scanning Electron Microscope (SEM);</item><item>Compositional analysis of the materials using X-Ray Diffraction (XRD).</item></list><p n="p8.80"><s n="s1.1;p8.80">Each of these will be preformed in turn and reported upon. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold italic">2.2 The Principle of Microstructure Analysis</head><p n="p9.80"><s n="s1.2;p9.80">Microstructure Analysis is used for examining materials on a granular and crystalline level. </s><s n="s2.2;p9.80">This can help in determining failure patterns, so particular characteristics can be investigated before a material is selected for a specific purpose, such as the components of a hip replacement. </s></p><div3><head rend="bold">2.2.a Optical Microscope</head><p n="p10.80"><s n="s1.5;p10.80">The Optical Microscope is one of the more basic instruments used in material analysis. </s><s n="s2.5;p10.80">It works using a complex set-up of lenses, and a light source, all accurately manufactured, so that a flat sample can be magnified to a degree that cannot be seen with the unaided eye. </s><s n="s3.5;p10.80">This means that we are talking about magnifications of up to 100 or 200. </s><s n="s4.5;p10.80">In the case of this laboratory, the microscope is in stereo, which provides a three-dimensional image of the surface of the sample. </s><s n="s5.5;p10.80">This is important because with higher magnifications, the image has greater boundaries for distortion, and so to achieve worthwhile results, we must use a high powered microscope. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0347a-fig.001"><head><seg type="URL" n="http://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/1/11/Olympus_SZIII_stereo_microscope.jpg"/></head></figure></div3><div3><head rend="bold">2.2.b Scanning Electron Microscope</head><p n="p11.80"><s n="s1.2;p11.80">This instrument was developed around 1935, but not perfected until the late 50s. </s><s n="s2.2;p11.80">It works on a similar principle to the Optical Microscope, except that instead of using light as a medium, thermionically emitted electrons are fired at the surface of the sample, and the image is formed when these are reflected, and detected by a scintillator-photomultiplier device, and converted into a digital image. </s></p><p n="p12.80"><s n="s1.2;p12.80">Resolutions of between 1nm and 20nm can be obtained by this scanning process, so magnifications of over 1000 are entirely possible, and can create very accurate images. </s><s n="s2.2;p12.80">It is a time consuming process, however, as the sample must be treated before it is scanned, and can prove to be very expensive. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0347a-pic.001"><head><seg type="URL" n="http://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/8/82/SEM_blood_cells.jpg"/> Images such as this can be obtained - a SEM image of human blood cells.</head></figure></div3><div3><head rend="bold">2.2.c X-Ray Diffraction</head><p n="p13.80"><s n="s1.4;p13.80">This process is used to examine the crystal structure of a piece of material, and can be used to identify it's components. </s><s n="s2.4;p13.80">The results are given as a graph, of Intensity (counts) and values for 2-theta. </s><s n="s3.4;p13.80">It works by emitting x-rays at measured angles, and the peaks on the graphs are where most of the x-rays are deflected. </s><s n="s4.4;p13.80">Thus the crystal size, purity and texture can be determined by the output of the peaks.(<seg type="URL" n="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/X-ray_crystallography"/>) </s></p><p n="p14.80"><s n="s1.1;p14.80">The formula : n = 2d sinBraggs Law, Shackleford) is used within the program on the PC directly connected to the machine, to produce the graphical presentations of the results. </s></p><p n="p15.80"><s n="s1.2;p15.80">X-Rays of a particular wavelength are emitted (and this is accurately produced because a voltage is applied to Copper elements, which are forced to release photons of energy from their inner energy shells), and fired at the sample, which is then reflected the most when the wavelength is in phase with the crystals. </s><s n="s2.2;p15.80">A simple diagram of which can be found below. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0347a-fig.002"><head><seg type="URL" n="http://www.eserc.stonybrook.edu/ProjectJava/Bragg/"/></head></figure></div3></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">3.0 Composite Processing</head><p n="p16.80"><s n="s1.1;p16.80">Initially, we must produce a specimen using a hot press machine, so that we can use X-Ray Diffraction analysis on it. </s></p><div2><head rend="bold italic">Description of Set Up</head><p n="p17.80"><s n="s1.1;p17.80">The entire walkthrough of the experiment can be found in the Briefing Sheet Appendix. </s></p><p n="p18.80"><s n="s1.1;p18.80">Hydroxyapetite (HAP) powder (a ceramic) and Ultra High Molecular Weight Polyethylene (UHMWPE) powder (a polymer) are to be mixed as accurately as possible in the composition of 20% HAP; 80% PE. This will create a 3g sample known as PEHAP20. </s></p><p n="p19.80"><s n="s1.3;p19.80">The most accurate set of scales available is used. </s><s n="s2.3;p19.80">It has an accuracy of ±0.0001g. </s><s n="s3.3;p19.80">The weights that we managed to achieve are: 0.6013g HAP; 2.4010g PE. </s></p><p n="p20.80"><s n="s1.2;p20.80">These are then mixed using an Agate Mortar and Pestle - which is selected for it's hardness and cleanliness, and so will have minimal effect on the ingredients. </s><s n="s2.2;p20.80">This mixture is then poured into the compression heating chamber of the hot press machine. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold italic">3.2 Process of Hot Pressing</head><figure id="BAWE_0347a-pic.002"/><p n="p21.80"><s n="s1.1;p21.80">The handle on the right hand side increases the pressure within the chamber when pumped (this must be kept around 4bar). </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0347a-pic.003"/><p n="p22.80"><s n="s1.1;p22.80">Above is a photo of the pressure gauge. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0347a-pic.004"/><p n="p23.80"><s n="s1.1;p23.80">This is the heating element that is slipped over the sheath of the compression chamber. </s></p><p n="p24.80"><s n="s1.3;p24.80">The cooling jacket looks like so. </s><s n="s2.3;p24.80">It is stored in cold water and then slipped over until it absorbs the heat from the chamber. </s><s n="s3.3;p24.80">It is then cooled and replaced again. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0347a-pic.005"/><p n="p25.80"><s n="s1.1;p25.80">And the final product that was produced that can be analysed with the XRD Machine looks like: It is a 32mm diameter disk, of width 8mm. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0347a-pic.006"/><p n="p26.80"><s n="s1.1;p26.80">More detailed process descriptions can be found in the Briefing Sheet Appendix. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold italic">3.3 X-Ray Diffractional Analysis (XRD)</head><div3><head rend="bold">3.3.a Results</head><figure id="BAWE_0347a-pic.007"/><p n="p27.80"><s n="s1.1;p27.80">This is a photo of the graph given to us in the Briefing Sheet. </s></p><p n="p28.80"><s n="s1.1;p28.80">The two peaks can be estimated as: </s></p><list type="simple"><item>PE peak 21x2theta @ 240 counts intensity</item><item>HAP peak 32x2theta @ 175 counts intensity</item></list><p n="p29.80"><s n="s1.1;p29.80">Two groups also performed this operation, so we have 2 sets of data: </s></p><list type="simple"><item>1.PE peak 21.423x2theta @ 60091 counts intensity</item><item>1.HAP peak 31.602x2theta @ 8887 counts intensity</item><item>2.PE peak 21.285x2theta @ 75007 counts intensity</item><item>2.HAP peak 31.468x2theta @ 8861 counts intensity</item></list></div3></div2><div2><head rend="bold italic">3.4 Discussion</head><p n="p30.80"><s n="s1.3;p30.80">These results show reasonable consistency in the two samples. </s><s n="s2.3;p30.80">The peaks occur roughly where we expected them to: 21x2theta compared to 21.423x2theta and 21.285x2theta, and 32x2theta compared with 31.602x2theta and 31.468x2theta. </s><s n="s3.3;p30.80">The counts of intensity are not relevant to each other, but they indicate what peak of each substance has occurred(another peak was present for in both cases, but this was disregarded). </s></p><p n="p31.80"><s n="s1.2;p31.80">All of this can tell us that not only do the two substances within the final material (PEHAp) not "fuse" together, and maintain their individual crystalline structures, but it also tells us that the qualities from both products combine to make the biocomposite. </s><s n="s2.2;p31.80">This means that desirable properties can be achieved by mixing products together like this. </s></p><div3><head rend="bold">3.4.a Inaccuracies</head><p n="p32.80"><s n="s1.3;p32.80">The results from the two group's experiments are more accurately estimated, as they were read direct from the machine. </s><s n="s2.3;p32.80">These images were digitally formed, and so are limited by the resolution of the cursor, and also of the screen. </s><s n="s3.3;p32.80">The counts are therefore within an accuracy of ±5 counts of intensity; and ± 0.2x2theta degrees. </s></p><p n="p33.80"><s n="s1.2;p33.80">The differences between the two results also highlight the inaccuracy of the measurement of the components of the polymer/ceramic composite. </s><s n="s2.2;p33.80">As recorded previously, the weightings were made out by hand, and to a degree of accuracy of ± 0.0001g. </s></p></div3></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">4.0 Optical Microscopy (OM)</head><div2><head rend="bold italic">Description of Set Up and Process</head><p n="p34.80"><s n="s1.3;p34.80">Two samples are to be compared - Steel and Brass. </s><s n="s2.3;p34.80">These are pre-prepared, mounted, ground, polished and etched. </s><s n="s3.3;p34.80">The Microscope is set up with lenses of 10x; 20x; 50x; 80x; and 100x magnifications, however, only the highest magnifications are of interest, as the visible grains will be able to be measured more accurately and with greater resolution. </s></p><p n="p35.80"><s n="s1.5;p35.80">The specimen is placed under the microscope and the light power turned on to a dim brightness, which will enable the details to be seen. </s><s n="s2.5;p35.80">The image is viewed using the 100x magnification lens, and focused finely. </s><s n="s3.5;p35.80">The horizontal switch is slid to the left position, which triggers the camera to bring the image up on the PC screen. </s><s n="s4.5;p35.80">The "take photo" function is applied, and the image is recorded. </s><s n="s5.5;p35.80">The results of which can be seen below. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold italic">4.2 Results</head><figure id="BAWE_0347a-pic.008"><head>Brass (B1, 60Cu-40Zn) sample magnified 100 times:</head></figure><p n="p36.80"><s n="s1.4;p36.80">The grains size ranges between diameters of 0.005mm and 0.02mm. </s><s n="s2.4;p36.80">The grains are not well defined, and close together. </s><s n="s3.4;p36.80">Darker grains are visible amongst the brighter grains. </s><s n="s4.4;p36.80">Dark spots appear irregularly. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0347a-pic.009"><head>Steel (X19, 0.35%C) sample magnified 100 times:</head></figure><p n="p37.80"><s n="s1.4;p37.80">Grain size ranges between diameters of 0.01mm and 0.03mm. </s><s n="s2.4;p37.80">They are well spaced and defined. </s><s n="s3.4;p37.80">Some clear crystal boundaries are visible within the grains. </s><s n="s4.4;p37.80">The background matrix is darker in colour than the grains themselves. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold italic">4.3 Discussion</head><p n="p38.80"><s n="s1.3;p38.80">Brass contains both Copper, Zinc, and Traces of Tin, which explains the three different components of the image: the light grains; dark grains; and dark spots. </s><s n="s2.3;p38.80">The matrix is more closely packed, which implies strength, but does not prove that the specimen is malleable. </s><s n="s3.3;p38.80">It also suggests that the metal was cooled quickly, because the grains are small (0.005-0.02mm in diameter), and the range is small(0.0015), which suggests that it was cooled uniformly.(the Brass was in fact hot extruded and then annealed, which supports my discussion) </s></p><p n="p39.80"><s n="s1.6;p39.80">The Steel sample is quite different to the Brass specimen. </s><s n="s2.6;p39.80">Steel contains Iron and Carbon. </s><s n="s3.6;p39.80">It is normally high in strength, which can be seen as the large grains are closely packed. </s><s n="s4.6;p39.80">However, there are big matrix gaps, suggesting malleability. </s><s n="s5.6;p39.80">We can tell that this has been heat treated, as the grains are large(0.01-0.03mm) so it was cooled slowly to allow these to form. </s><s n="s6.6;p39.80">The range of these values is larger than the brass(0.02), which could suggest that it was cooled irregularly, although whether this was in air or some other medium, is unclear. (the carbon steel was in fact furnace cooled from 870°C, which supports my discussion of the structure) </s></p><div3><head rend="bold">4.3.a Inaccuracies</head><p n="p40.80"><s n="s1.3;p40.80">The two images' apparent resolution is not only limited to the capabilities of the camera used to capture them, but also to the microscope. </s><s n="s2.3;p40.80">Through the microscope, a lot finer image could be seen by eye, of which many small details are undefined by the results. </s><s n="s3.3;p40.80">This means that their analysis can only say so much about the microstructure. </s></p><p n="p41.80"><s n="s1.2;p41.80">Also, the maximum magnification that could be achieved by this machine was 100x, which gave a scale(as shown in the jpegs) of 0.01mm. </s><s n="s2.2;p41.80">It only shows the macro-structure of the grains, so the crystalline formations within this have no representation here, so it cannot be seen how each part interacts with another. </s></p><p n="p42.80"><s n="s1.1;p42.80">The surfaces of the two samples were visibly dirtied with finger grease as well, so this would have hindered the accuracy of the images produced. </s></p></div3></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">5.0 Scanning Electron Microscopy (SEM)</head><p n="p43.80"><s n="s1.1;p43.80">The first image is one supplied in Introduction to Materials Science for Engineers, sixth edition, James F. Shackleford. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0347a-pic.010"/><figure id="BAWE_0347a-pic.011"/><p n="p44.80"><s n="s1.1;p44.80">The second image is a modern SEM machine found at <seg type="URL" n="http://www.phy.cuhk.edu.hk/centrallaboratory/CM120/CM120.jpg"/> </s></p><div2><head rend="bold italic">5.1 Device and Sample Set Up and Process</head><p n="p45.80"><s n="s1.2;p45.80">8 Materials, pre-sampled, were made available on the PC that links directly to the SEM machine. </s><s n="s2.2;p45.80">Measurements were taken at our discretion, of the grain sizes and pores within the structure of each sample. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold italic">5.2 Results</head><figure id="BAWE_0347a-fig.003"><head>1mm Scale. Magnification 37.2x. Well distributed, regular pores.</head></figure><figure id="BAWE_0347a-fig.004"><head>2mm Scale. Magnification 21.5x. Strip Width 75.47mm; Total Width 3037.74mm.</head></figure><figure id="BAWE_0347a-fig.005"><head>5μ m Scale. Magnification 8020x. Small lumps with "gappy" pores.</head></figure><figure id="BAWE_0347a-fig.006"><head>200μ m Scale. Magnification 133x.</head></figure><figure id="BAWE_0347a-fig.007"><head>100μ m Scale. Magnification 264x.</head></figure><figure id="BAWE_0347a-fig.008"><head>200μ m Scale. Magnification 126x.</head></figure><figure id="BAWE_0347a-fig.009"><head>20μ m Scale. Magnification 1040x.</head></figure><figure id="BAWE_0347a-fig.010"><head>10μ m Scale. Magnification 3970x.</head></figure><p n="p46.80"/></div2><div2><head rend="bold italic">5.3 Discussion</head><p n="p47.80"><s n="s1.3;p47.80">Porous HAP Biocomposite - this has well distributed, regular pores. </s><s n="s2.3;p47.80">The range between the diameters is roughly 160μm, however, most of the pores are between 40μm and 70μm in diameter. </s><s n="s3.3;p47.80">The magnification is 37.2x, which isn't very high, so none of the granular structure can be identified. </s></p><p n="p48.80"><s n="s1.2;p48.80">Cortical Bone - this seems to be formed by layers of composite, and so the diameters between the layers are not dissimilar from each other (37.74μm, 28.30μm). </s><s n="s2.2;p48.80">This also means that tiny pores can just be seen between the layers, however, the magnification is only 18.7x, therefore these pores cannot be analysed, because the resolution is not high enough. </s></p><p n="p49.80"><s n="s1.4;p49.80">Cancellous Bone - this is a strange material, which is found within the central cavity of a bone. </s><s n="s2.4;p49.80">It is porous and "lumpy", so that movement of particles can take place. </s><s n="s3.4;p49.80">It also provides the internal structure and cushioning strength of the bone, so the pores are very small, with a range of 0.1μm-0.2μm, and this is fairly consistent. </s><s n="s4.4;p49.80">The magnification for this image is 8020x, so the resolution is very good, and we can tell that the structure is regular throughout. </s></p><p n="p50.80"><s n="s1.4;p50.80">PE Particles - the particles of the PE are clearly defined as separate bodies to the medium they are presented on. </s><s n="s2.4;p50.80">Of varying sizes (height and width, ranging from ~50μm to ~250μm and ~35μm to ~115μm) </s><s n="s3.4;p50.80">This suggests no real strength or interaction between the particles. </s><s n="s4.4;p50.80">It can account for the elasticity of the polymeric sample, however. </s></p><p n="p51.80"><s n="s1.4;p51.80">HAP Particles - these "sharp" particles are definitely a ceramic, as you can see the definite edges. </s><s n="s2.4;p51.80">This implies that the material will be brittle. </s><s n="s3.4;p51.80">There are many particles overlaying each other, so strength is a feature of the sample, but easy to fracture. </s><s n="s4.4;p51.80">The particles come in three sizes really - those ranging from 5-10μm; 11-30μm and 40μm+. </s></p><p n="p52.80"><s n="s1.2;p52.80">PE Surface - this looks like quite a flat sample, where all of the grains are "glued" together in a matrix. </s><s n="s2.2;p52.80">The grains are similar sized, with a range of less than 100μm for their diameters. </s></p><p n="p53.80"><s n="s1.5;p53.80">Apatite Formation on PE Surface - this image is highly magnified - 1040x. </s><s n="s2.5;p53.80">It shows apatite on the surface of the PE grains shown on the previous image of PE Surface. </s><s n="s3.5;p53.80">They are irregular formations, of various cluster diameters. </s><s n="s4.5;p53.80">The smallest being as little as 2μm in diameter. </s><s n="s5.5;p53.80">The PE grain boundaries are also irregularly sized. </s></p><p n="p54.80"><s n="s1.3;p54.80">PE Particle Separation - this image is an even higher magnification of the PE surface. </s><s n="s2.3;p54.80">3790x. </s><s n="s3.3;p54.80">The "clump" diameters are regular, and have a range of less than 0.5μm. </s></p><div3><head rend="bold">5.3.a Inaccuracies</head><p n="p55.80"><s n="s1.2;p55.80">For these measurements, there are definite inaccuracies inherent within the testing equipment. </s><s n="s2.2;p55.80">Although the magnification may be very high, and the resolution is very good, the figures provided by the PC program are limited by: the resolution of the cursor; the human error created when selecting the measurements; the resolution of the computer screen; amongst others. </s></p><p n="p56.80"><s n="s1.2;p56.80">Where the same result has occurred more than once, this is an indication that there are limitations in the equipment. </s><s n="s2.2;p56.80">This has happened, for example, in the cortical bone specimen. </s></p><p n="p57.80"><s rend="bold" n="s1.1;p57.80">In occasions such as this, I would suggest that another sample be taken at higher magnification, which could improve the resolution of the image. </s></p></div3></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">6.0 Conclusions</head><div2><head rend="bold">6.0.a X-Ray Diffraction</head><p n="p58.80"><s n="s1.1;p58.80">The results that we gained from this section of the experiment were: </s></p><list type="simple"><item>1.PE peak 21.423x2theta @ 60091 counts intensity</item><item>1.HAP peak 31.602x2theta @ 8887 counts intensity</item><item>2.PE peak 21.285x2theta @ 75007 counts intensity</item><item>2.HAP peak 31.468x2theta @ 8861 counts intensity</item></list><p n="p59.80"><s n="s1.2;p59.80">These results show reasonable consistency in the two samples. </s><s n="s2.2;p59.80">The peaks occur where we expected them to: 21x2theta compared to 21.423x2theta and 21.285x2theta, and 32x2theta compared with 31.602x2theta and 31.468x2theta. </s></p><p n="p60.80"><s n="s1.2;p60.80">All of this can tell us that not only do the two substances within the final material (PEHAp) not "fuse" together, and maintain their individual crystalline structures, but it also tells us that the qualities from both products combine to make the biocomposite. </s><s n="s2.2;p60.80">This means that desirable properties can be achieved by mixing products together like this. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">6.0.b Optical Microscopy</head><p n="p61.80"><s n="s1.1;p61.80">The results that we gained from the Optical Microscopy were: </s></p><p n="p62.80"><s n="s1.1;p62.80">Brass (B1, 60Cu-40Zn) sample magnified 100 times: </s></p><p n="p63.80"><s n="s1.4;p63.80">The grains size ranges between diameters of 0.005mm and 0.02mm. </s><s n="s2.4;p63.80">The grains are not well defined, and close together. </s><s n="s3.4;p63.80">Darker grains are visible amongst the brighter grains. </s><s n="s4.4;p63.80">Dark spots appear irregularly. </s></p><p n="p64.80"><s n="s1.3;p64.80">Brass contains both Copper, Zinc, and Traces of Tin, which explains the three different components of the image: the light grains; dark grains; and dark spots. </s><s n="s2.3;p64.80">The matrix is more closely packed, which implies strength, but does not prove that the specimen is malleable. </s><s n="s3.3;p64.80">It also suggests that the metal was cooled quickly, because the grains are small (0.005-0.02mm in diameter), and the range is small(0.0015), which suggests that it was cooled uniformly. </s></p><p n="p65.80"><s n="s1.1;p65.80">Steel (X19, 0.35%C) sample magnified 100 times: </s></p><p n="p66.80"><s n="s1.6;p66.80">The Steel sample is quite different to the Brass specimen. </s><s n="s2.6;p66.80">Steel contains Iron and Carbon. </s><s n="s3.6;p66.80">It is normally high in strength, which can be seen as the large grains are closely packed. </s><s n="s4.6;p66.80">However, there are big matrix gaps, suggesting malleability. </s><s n="s5.6;p66.80">We can tell that this has been heat treated, as the grains are large(0.01-0.03mm) so it was cooled slowly to allow these to form. </s><s n="s6.6;p66.80">The range of these values is larger than the brass(0.02). </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">6.0.c Scanning Electron Microscopy</head><p n="p67.80"><s n="s1.3;p67.80">Porous HAP Biocomposite - this has well distributed, regular pores. </s><s n="s2.3;p67.80">The range between the diameters is roughly 160μm, however, most of the pores are between 40μm and 70μm in diameter. </s><s n="s3.3;p67.80">The magnification is 37.2x, which isn't very high, so none of the granular structure can be identified. </s></p><p n="p68.80"><s n="s1.2;p68.80">Cortical Bone - this is formed by layers of composite, and so the diameters between the layers are not dissimilar from each other (37.74μm, 28.30μm). </s><s n="s2.2;p68.80">This also means that tiny pores can just be seen between the layers, however, the magnification is only 18.7x, therefore these pores cannot be defined accurately. </s></p><p n="p69.80"><s n="s1.4;p69.80">Cancellous Bone - this is found within the central cavity of a bone. </s><s n="s2.4;p69.80">It is porous and "lumpy", so that movement of particles can take place. </s><s n="s3.4;p69.80">It also provides the internal structure and cushioning strength of the bone, so the pores are very small, with a range of 0.1μm-0.2μm, and this is fairly consistent. </s><s n="s4.4;p69.80">The magnification for this image is 8020x, so the resolution is very good, and we can tell that the structure is regular throughout. </s></p><p n="p70.80"><s n="s1.3;p70.80">PE Particles - the particles of the PE are clearly defined as separate bodies to the medium they are presented on. </s><s n="s2.3;p70.80">Of varying sizes (height and width, ranging from ~50μm to ~250μm and ~35μm to ~115μm) This suggests no real strength or interaction between the particles. </s><s n="s3.3;p70.80">It can account for the elasticity of the polymeric sample, however. </s></p><p n="p71.80"><s n="s1.4;p71.80">HAP Particles - these "sharp" particles are definitely a ceramic, as you can see the definite edges. </s><s n="s2.4;p71.80">This implies that the material will be brittle. </s><s n="s3.4;p71.80">There are many particles overlaying each other, so the sample is easy to fracture. </s><s n="s4.4;p71.80">The particles come in different sizes ranging from 5-10μm; 11-30μm and 40μm+. </s></p><p n="p72.80"><s n="s1.2;p72.80">PE Surface - all of the grains are "glued" together in a matrix. </s><s n="s2.2;p72.80">The grains are similar sized, with a range of less than 100μm for their diameters. </s></p><p n="p73.80"><s n="s1.5;p73.80">Apatite Formation on PE Surface - this image is highly magnified - 1040x. </s><s n="s2.5;p73.80">It shows apatite on the surface of the PE grains shown on the previous image of PE Surface. </s><s n="s3.5;p73.80">They are irregular formations, of various cluster diameters. </s><s n="s4.5;p73.80">The smallest being as little as 2μm in diameter. </s><s n="s5.5;p73.80">The PE grain boundaries are also irregularly sized. </s></p><p n="p74.80"><s n="s1.3;p74.80">PE Particle Separation - this image is an even higher magnification of the PE surface. </s><s n="s2.3;p74.80">3790x. </s><s n="s3.3;p74.80">The "clump" diameters are regular, and have a range of less than 0.5μm. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold italic">6.1 How is this technology useful? </head><p n="p75.80"><s n="s1.2;p75.80">All of these SEM images show combinations of PE and HAP. We can see that when they are combined, the PE acts as a matrix, whereas HAP provides the strength. </s><s n="s2.2;p75.80">The PE reduces the brittleness of the HAP particles, whereas, the HAP stiffens the PE. Therefore creating a strong, stiff biocomposite, which is a highly sought-after characteristic within biomedical materials development. </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">7.0 Summary</head><p n="p76.80"><s n="s1.1;p76.80">From visualising different composite materials, it it possible to identify their characteristics and manufacturing techniques. </s></p><p n="p77.80"><s n="s1.3;p77.80">Through the use of XRD, it is seen that two substances within a biocomposite do not "fuse" together, but maintain their individual crystalline structures. </s><s n="s2.3;p77.80">The qualities from both products combine to make the biocomposite. </s><s n="s3.3;p77.80">Therefore, desirable properties can be achieved by mixing products together like this. </s></p><p n="p78.80"><s n="s1.1;p78.80">The OM use has shown that methods used during manufacture can be identified by grain analysis. </s></p><p n="p79.80"><s n="s1.1;p79.80">It was identified that the Brass sample had been strengthened from heat treatment and fast cooling, whereas the steel was identified as malleable, having been heat treated and slowly cooled. </s></p><p n="p80.80"><s n="s1.2;p80.80">From the SEM images, it could be seen that HAP on it's own was brittle, and the PE was flexible. </s><s n="s2.2;p80.80">Combined they supported each other to form a strong, stiff biocomposite. </s></p></div1></body><back><div1 type="bibliography"><head>Bibliography &amp; References</head><p><seg type="URL" n="http://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/1/11/Olympus_SZIII_stereo_microscope.jpg"/></p><p><seg type="URL" n="http://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/8/82/SEM_blood_cells.jpg"/></p><p><seg type="URL" n="http://www.eserc.stonybrook.edu/ProjectJava/Bragg/"/></p><p><seg type="URL" n="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/X-ray_crystallography"/></p><p><seg type="URL" n="http://www.phy.cuhk.edu.hk/centrallaboratory/CM120/CM120.jpg"/></p><p><seg type="URL" n="www.wikipedia.org"/></p><p>Introduction to Materials Science for Engineers, Sixth Edition, James F. Shackleford, 0-13-127619-0</p><p>Manufacture and Characteristics of Biocomposites Laboratory Briefing Sheet, Dr Kajal Mallick, 21 April 2006</p><p><seg type="URL" n="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Scanning_electron_microscope"/></p><p><seg type="URL" n="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/X-ray_diffraction"/></p><p><seg type="URL" n="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Light_microscope"/></p><p><seg type="URL" n="http://australianmuseum.net.au/evolutionary_biology/sem/prep.htm"/></p></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
