<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_0347h" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Mechanical Testing of Materials Laboratory Report</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">The document has a title page which contains:
document title
title part</note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">deleted: page numbers, date</note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">appendices: briefing sheets, data, calculations</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">2</p><p n="date">2006-11</p><p n="module title">Biomedical Materials</p><p n="module code">ES2A1</p><p n="genre family">Methodology recount</p><p n="discipline">Engineering</p><p n="disciplinary group">PS</p><p n="grade">D</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">2018</p><p n="number of s-units">91</p><p n="number of p">43</p><p n="number of tables">3</p><p n="number of figures">1</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">3</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">0</p><p n="abstract present">abstract present</p><p n="average words per s-unit">22.2</p><p n="average s-units per p">2.1</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">f</p><p n="year of birth">1987</p><p n="first language">English</p><p n="education">UKA</p><p n="course">Meng</p><p n="student ID">0347</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><titlePart rend="bold">University of <name type="university"/> School of Engineering</titlePart><docTitle><titlePart rend="bold">Mechanical Testing of Materials Laboratory Report</titlePart></docTitle><titlePart rend="bold">by Miss <name type="student name"/><name type="student ID"/></titlePart><titlePart>Report Reference Code: ES2A1A1 Biomedical Materials - Report on Lab Exercises Affiliation: Year 2 Engineering Report of laboratory taken place on: November 28 <hi rend="sup">th</hi> 2006</titlePart></titlePage><div1 type="toc" n="2"><head rend="bold">Table of Contents</head><p/></div1></front><body><div1 type="abstract"><head rend="bold">1.0 Abstract</head><p n="p1.43"><s n="s1.2;p1.43">The Materials Testing Laboratory is aimed at allowing the student to develop an understanding of the process of tensile testing. </s><s n="s2.2;p1.43">The Testometric Testing Machine is an extremely accurate and valuable piece of equipment, without the likes of which, we would have no perception of materials qualities and technological options for advancement. </s></p><p n="p2.43"><s n="s1.2;p2.43">This report investigates into 4 materials that are commonly used in biomedical materials science. </s><s n="s2.2;p2.43">Low Carbon Steel, Medium Carbon Steel, Aluminium Alloy, and Alloyed Steel, are all used for very different functions, but can these be predisposed by their qualities as proven by this basic exercise? </s></p><p n="p3.43"><s n="s1.1;p3.43">We use fundamental formulae and results, to rediscover that steel treatments have a great impact on a material's resistance to stresses and load, in the following investigation. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">2.0 Introduction</head><p n="p4.43"><s n="s1.3;p4.43">Within medicine, it is important that when materials are considered for use within the body, their properties are fully understood, so that no unexpected behaviour occurs. </s><s n="s2.3;p4.43">Mechanical failure could be potentially fatal, if the receiver of this technology is frail or affected by a debilitating disease. </s><s n="s3.3;p4.43">For example, an arthritis sufferer's newly fitted replacement hip, could fail at the top of a set of stairs, causing them to fall and severely injure other parts of their body. </s></p><p n="p5.43"><s n="s1.2;p5.43">In order to understand these properties, thorough materials testing must be initiated. </s><s n="s2.2;p5.43">The aim of this set of experiments, is to analyse in some extent, the qualities of some biomedically utilised materials, and to assess how reliable they are for use within the body. </s></p><div2><head><hi rend="bold italic">2.1 Objectives</hi><ref target="BAWE_0347h-endnote.001"/><note place="end" id="BAWE_0347h-endnote.001"><p n="pn1.1"> From briefing sheet provided by Dr. K Mallick (November 7th 2005)</p></note></head><list type="bulleted"><item>To become familiar with the standard tensile test.</item><item>To study the mechanical properties of some important biomedical materials.</item><item>To determine values for σ<hi rend="sub">y</hi> (or σ<hi rend="sub">0.2%</hi>), σ<hi rend="sub">TS</hi> and ε for those materials.</item><item>To investigate the variability of these properties for a number of nominally identical specimens.</item></list><p n="p6.43"/></div2><div2><head rend="bold italic">2.2 The Principle of Materials Testing</head><p n="p7.43"><s n="s1.3;p7.43">There are certain characteristics that are usually examined in the process of materials testing. </s><s n="s2.3;p7.43">In this investigation, we will use <hi rend="italic">yield stress</hi>, <hi rend="italic">proof stress, tensile strength</hi> and <hi rend="italic"> ductility,</hi> to base our analysis upon. </s><s n="s3.3;p7.43">This will give us an idea of how the materials fail, and this can lead us to suggest applications for which they could be used within the body. </s></p><div3><head rend="bold">2.2.a Yield Stress</head><p n="p8.43"><s n="s1.1;p8.43">This is defined as: The stress at which a material begins to plastically deform.<ref target="BAWE_0347h-endnote.002"/> </s></p><note place="end" id="BAWE_0347h-endnote.002"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1"><hi rend="underlined"> </hi><seg type="URL" n="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Yield_(engineering"/>) </s></p></note><p n="p9.43"><s n="s1.3;p9.43">Up until the Yield Stress is reached when testing a material, any deformation is <hi rend="italic">elastic deformation</hi>, whereby, the sample will return to it's initial specifications. </s><s n="s2.3;p9.43">After this point is reached, further deformation is permanent <hi rend="italic">plastic deformation.</hi> </s><s n="s3.3;p9.43">It is important to have knowledge of this figure for Biomedical use, because it represents the maximum load that the material can withstand before failing. </s></p></div3><div3><head rend="bold">2.2.b Proof Stress</head><p n="p10.43"><s n="s1.2;p10.43">In many materials, there is no clear definition between the elastic and plastic regions, therefore the yield point is determined by an offset line from the linear region<ref target="BAWE_0347h-endnote.003"/>. </s><s n="s2.2;p10.43">In this case, we will be using σ<hi rend="sub">0.2%</hi> to standardise the measurement of stress for each specimen that proves to be unspecific. </s></p><note place="end" id="BAWE_0347h-endnote.003"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1"><hi rend="underlined"> </hi><seg type="URL" n="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Yield_(engineering"/>) </s></p></note></div3><div3><head rend="bold">2.2.c Tensile Strength</head><p n="p11.43"><s n="s1.3;p11.43">This is the force required to pull a material to the point at which it breaks.<ref target="BAWE_0347h-endnote.004"/> Therefore, it is a point beyond the plastic region, at the maximum stress point. </s><s n="s2.3;p11.43">We will be able to identify this in our results, because it will be the highest point that the graph reaches. </s><s n="s3.3;p11.43">It will most likely occur before actual fracture of the specimen, although, may occur at the same time. </s></p><note place="end" id="BAWE_0347h-endnote.004"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1"><hi rend="underlined"> </hi><seg type="URL" n="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tensile_strength"/> </s></p></note></div3><div3><head rend="bold">2.2.d Ductility</head><p n="p12.43"><s n="s1.2;p12.43">Generally, this is the ability for a material to be drawn into a wire<ref target="BAWE_0347h-endnote.005"/>. </s><s n="s2.2;p12.43">However, if this extremity is not reached, it is a measurement of the extension of the material between the yield stress and fracture point </s></p><note place="end" id="BAWE_0347h-endnote.005"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1"><hi rend="underlined"> </hi><seg type="URL" n="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ductility"/> </s></p></note></div3></div2><div2><head rend="bold italic">2.3 Calculations</head><p n="p13.43"><s n="s1.3;p13.43">The formulae and calculations to be used for working out and analysing the data have been added on a separate sheet as an appendix. </s><s n="s2.3;p13.43">The figures I aim to determine are values for Tensile Strength, Yield Stress, Young's Modulus, Strain and Ductility. </s><s n="s3.3;p13.43">This way, I will be able to compare the experimental data with standardised figures that can be found in the Engineering Data Book<ref target="BAWE_0347h-endnote.006"/>. </s></p><note place="end" id="BAWE_0347h-endnote.006"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.3;pn1.1">Engineering Data Book, School of Engineering, University of Warwick. </s><s n="s2.3;pn1.1">Fourthe Edition, 2001. </s><s n="s3.3;pn1.1">ISBN 9786000000196, pages 31-32. </s></p></note></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">3.0 Description of the Experiment</head><p n="p14.43"><s n="s1.3;p14.43">We are going to test the specimens with a tensile testing machine, and make records of their responses. </s><s n="s2.3;p14.43">The points we are looking for are the yield point, maximum load stress, and eventual fracture. </s><s n="s3.3;p14.43">The data will then be compared to our expectations, and discussed in context. </s></p><div2><head rend="bold italic">Instrumentation</head><p n="p15.43"><s n="s1.4;p15.43">The instrument we are using to examine the specimens is known as an <hi rend="italic">Automated Testometric 100kN Materials Testing Machine</hi>. </s><s n="s2.4;p15.43">It's specifications can be found as an appendix, found from the manufacturer's website<ref target="BAWE_0347h-endnote.007"/>. </s><s n="s3.4;p15.43">It should be noted, however, that the machine used was an older version, so some updates are included in this leaflet. </s><s n="s4.4;p15.43">The main difference, being that the results are unable for digital transfer between computers, so the only visualisation that can be used, are from the printouts. </s></p><note place="end" id="BAWE_0347h-endnote.007"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1"><hi rend="underlined"> </hi><seg type="URL" n="http://www.testometric.co.uk/pdf/M500-100AT.pdf"/> </s></p></note></div2><div2><head rend="bold italic">3.2 Device Set Up</head><p n="p16.43"><s n="s1.4;p16.43">'There were two formats for the set up, because the materials came in different forms to be tested. </s><s n="s2.4;p16.43">The first was a pair of clamps, a sketch of which can be found as an appendix. </s><s n="s3.4;p16.43">These were used to hold the cylindrical metallic samples. </s><s n="s4.4;p16.43">The second was a jig used to hold the cuboidal form of the plastics, not too dissimilar to the one pictured below. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0347h-pic.001"/></div2><div2><head rend="bold italic">3.3 Measurements</head><p n="p17.43"><s n="s1.2;p17.43">The measurements were taken, such that there was a load cell attached to the specific jig, and this is connected to a PC, that displays and records the results. </s><s n="s2.2;p17.43">This was then printed off, and the result of which is the collection of graphs and measurements included as an appendix. </s></p><p n="p18.43"><s n="s1.3;p18.43">During experimentation, the slack is taken up from between the jig and the material in question. </s><s n="s2.3;p18.43">A constant load is then applied, this was usually 5mm/min, however, in the results this is recorded more accurately for each experiment. </s><s n="s3.3;p18.43">The experiment is completed once the material has fractured. </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">4.0 Results and Discussion</head><p n="p19.43"><s n="s1.1;p19.43">All of the annotated graphically represented results can be found as appendices. </s></p><p n="p20.43"><s n="s1.1;p20.43">The Specimens that we will be using are as follows: </s></p><list type="ordered"><item>Carbon Steel: specimen AN, 0.1%C, Normalised 900°C</item><item>Carbon Steel: specimen DN, 0.4%C, Normalised 860°C</item><item>Alloy Steel: specimen 2, 0.4%C, 1.5%Ni, 1.2%Cr, 0.2%Mo, Oil Quenched from 840°C, Tempered at 400°C</item><item>Aluminium Alloys: specimen E, 0.8%Mg, 1.0%Si, 0.7%Mn, Artificially aged</item></list><div2><head rend="bold italic">Graphs</head><p n="p21.43"><s n="s1.2;p21.43">The graphical representations of the data have been annotated as appendices. </s><s n="s2.2;p21.43">However, the concept of them can be easily described. </s></p><p n="p22.43"><s n="s1.5;p22.43">The print-outs from the Testometric Testing Machine were in the form of sets of data and a series of graphs. </s><s n="s2.5;p22.43">The data sets described the behaviour of each material, by providing data for the following: Diameter; Load at Peak; Elongation at Peak; Stress at Peak; Load at Yield; Elongation at Yield; Stress at Yield; Test Speed. </s><s n="s3.5;p22.43">The series of graphs were labelled with the Load (kN) on the x axis, and the Extension (mm) on the y axis. </s><s n="s4.5;p22.43">During the calculation stage, all of these figures were turned in SI units, so Newtons and Metres. </s><s n="s5.5;p22.43">This ensured that all of the final results were to the correct power. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold italic">4.2 Data</head><p n="p23.43"><s n="s1.2;p23.43">This is a table with all of the calculated results from the graphical data. </s><s n="s2.2;p23.43">As you can see, I have worked out the Yield Stress, Tensile Strength and Young's Modulus for each material. </s></p><table id="BAWE_0347h-tab.001"><head>Table showing mechanical properties of specimens</head><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p24.43"><s n="s1.2;p24.43">Specimen 2 can withstand the largest amount of load before failure, and has the largest Yield Stress and Tensile Strength. </s><s n="s2.2;p24.43">However, it has the lowest Strain, and is not very ductile, which means that it deforms plastically very quickly. </s></p><p n="p25.43"><s n="s1.2;p25.43">Specimen AN has the lowest Yield Stress value, but high ductility, so it's Tensile Strength is more than expected. </s><s n="s2.2;p25.43">It would be easier to machine into different shapes. </s></p><p n="p26.43"><s n="s1.4;p26.43">Specimen DN can take a high load before it yields. </s><s n="s2.4;p26.43">This can also be seen in the graphs. </s><s n="s3.4;p26.43">It has a high strain, and fairly high ductility. </s><s n="s4.4;p26.43">It would be good for use in skeletal structures, as can withstand wear, and is reasonably strong. </s></p><p n="p27.43"><s n="s1.1;p27.43">Specimen E Yields after very little extension, and has a low young's modulus. </s></p><p n="p28.43"><s n="s1.1;p28.43">These figures, compared with the closest-related ones with data available in the Engineering Data Book, look like this: </s></p><table id="BAWE_0347h-tab.002"><head>Data Book mechanical properties for specimens; Experimental Data</head><row><cell/></row></table></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">5.0 Analysis of Data </head><p n="p29.43"><s n="s1.2;p29.43">It is very difficult to compare my own data, unless I combine it with additional results that have been gathered by a different person. </s><s n="s2.2;p29.43">I have chosen the most similar results from a booklet supplied, so that I get a fairer representation of the true results. </s></p><div2><head rend="bold italic">5.1 Comparisons</head><p n="p30.43"><s n="s1.1;p30.43">Set C are my results from above, and sets A and B are completely separate results, but that used the same machine to do the experiments. </s></p><table id="BAWE_0347h-tab.003"><head>Table showing my results plus two additional sets</head><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p31.43"><s n="s1.1;p31.43">As you can see, all sets of data complement eachother, which implies that there is some correlation between the results and the true values. </s></p><p n="p32.43"><s n="s1.2;p32.43">Specimens AN and E however, have irregular Yield Points and Stresses. </s><s n="s2.2;p32.43">This suggests that they are less reliable to be trusted with large loads within the body. </s></p><p n="p33.43"><s n="s1.4;p33.43">It must be noted that there is a definite variability with these sets though. </s><s n="s2.4;p33.43">But not as great between the two additional sets. </s><s n="s3.4;p33.43">This is likely due to the fact that the rate of load applied in my experiments was 5mm/min, whereas in the others it was 2mm/min. </s><s n="s4.4;p33.43">There is proof that this affects the results, which is supported by this website.<ref target="BAWE_0347h-endnote.008"/> </s></p><note place="end" id="BAWE_0347h-endnote.008"><p n="pn1.2"><s n="s1.1;pn1.2"><hi rend="underlined"> </hi><seg type="URL" n="http://www.admet.com/assets/Tensile_Testing_Basics_Quality_Magazine.pdf"/> </s></p><p n="pn2.2"><s n="s1.1;pn2.2"><seg type="URL" n="http://www.admet.com/assets/Tensile_Testing_Basics_Quality_Magazine.pdf"/> </s></p></note><div3><head rend="bold">5.1.a Inaccuracies</head><p n="p34.43"><s n="s1.3;p34.43">The sets of data for the experimental and Data Book results are remarkably similar, which indicates not only that the tensile testing machine is fairly accurate, but also, that there are no apparent human calculation errors. </s><s n="s2.3;p34.43">There are however, inherent errors in the machinery, that I would suggest occurs with age and overuse. </s><s n="s3.3;p34.43">The jigs are produced and always used in pairs, so that they have the same history, which reduces irregularities and sporadic results. </s></p><p n="p35.43"><s n="s1.1;p35.43">The comparative specimens are also not exactly the same specifications as the experimental specimens, they are only the closest ones that could be found, given the situation. </s></p><p n="p36.43"><s n="s1.2;p36.43">The additional sets of data that I used for comparison were taken last year, which would also have an effect on accuracy of the results. </s><s n="s2.2;p36.43">I believe that all tests were carried out by the same technician though, which would reduce inaccuracies, as the students involved were not technically involved in the working of the machinery. </s></p></div3></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">6.0 Conclusions</head><p n="p37.43"><s n="s1.1;p37.43">The aims of this report were to discuss the laboratory that took place. </s></p><p n="p38.43"><s n="s1.1;p38.43">At the beginning, I referred to the Objectives as: </s></p><list type="bulleted"><item>To become familiar with the standard tensile test.</item><item>To study the mechanical properties of some important biomedical materials.</item><item>To determine values for σ<hi rend="sub">y</hi> (or σ<hi rend="sub">0.2%</hi>), σ<hi rend="sub">TS</hi> and ε for those materials.</item><item>To investigate the variability of these properties for a number of nominally identical specimens.</item></list><p n="p39.43"><s n="s1.2;p39.43">The standard tensile test takes place by measuring the reactions of a specimen when placed under load using a Materials Testing Machine. </s><s n="s2.2;p39.43">The specifications of which are attached. </s></p><p n="p40.43"><s n="s1.2;p40.43">The mechanical properties of some important metals used within Biomedical Materials engineering were investigated, and it was found that most of them follow the general rules for their specifications. </s><s n="s2.2;p40.43">However, both the Low Carbon Steel and Aluminium Alloys have more unpredictable Yield Stresses, which may mean that they are less suitable for use within the body. </s></p><p n="p41.43"><s n="s1.1;p41.43">The values for Yield Stress, Tensile Stress and Strain were found, and most frequently were as expected from previous acknowledgments (within the Data Book), but these vary slightly, as the samples have had different heat treatments and processes to prepare them. </s></p><p n="p42.43"><s n="s1.1;p42.43">The variability between sample was also investigated, as just discussed. </s></p><p n="p43.43"><s n="s1.3;p43.43">To conclude, it is very important to analyse materials like this, in order that they can be fully understood, before they can be used practically for Biomedical reasons. </s><s n="s2.3;p43.43">The differences in how they react, is simulated by the testing machine, and can provide vital insight for researchers to determine their optimum application within the body. </s><s n="s3.3;p43.43">Repetitions are important to assess reliability. </s></p></div1></body><back><div1 type="appendix"><head rend="bold">7.0 Appendices</head><p/></div1><div1 type="bibliography"><head rend="bold">8.0 References</head><p/></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
