<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_0347d" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Visualisation: an overview of the eye as a sensory organ</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">The document has a title page which contains:
document title
title part</note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">deleted: page numbers (in lower case roman for title, contents and introduction pages!)</note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">deleted: date</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">1</p><p n="date">2006-06</p><p n="module title">Biomedical Engineering</p><p n="module code">ES173</p><p n="genre family">Explanation</p><p n="discipline">Engineering</p><p n="disciplinary group">PS</p><p n="grade">D</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">2652</p><p n="number of s-units">130</p><p n="number of p">64</p><p n="number of tables">0</p><p n="number of figures">11</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">2</p><p n="number of lists">2</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">0</p><p n="abstract present">abstract present</p><p n="average words per s-unit">20.4</p><p n="average s-units per p">2.0</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">f</p><p n="year of birth">1987</p><p n="first language">English</p><p n="education">UKA</p><p n="course">Meng</p><p n="student ID">0347</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><titlePart rend="bold">University of <name type="university"/> School of Engineering</titlePart><docTitle><titlePart rend="bold">Visualisation: an overview of the eye as a sensory organ</titlePart></docTitle><titlePart><hi rend="bold">by</hi> <hi rend="bold"><name type="student name"/><name type="student ID"/></hi></titlePart><titlePart>Report Reference Code: ES173 Biomedical Engineering Essay Affiliation: Year 1 Engineering</titlePart></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="abstract"><head rend="bold">Abstract</head><p n="p1.64"><s n="s1.4;p1.64">The eye is a multi-functional complex tool, that has taken years to understand. </s><s n="s2.4;p1.64">Many subsystems such as the lacrimal apparatus have been developed to ensure smooth, efficient use of this body part. </s><s n="s3.4;p1.64">Suffice to say, each part had been studied by researchers into extent, which helps us to diagnose, and now treat, many debilitating disorders. </s><s n="s4.4;p1.64">On a reasonably small scale, myopia and hyperopia can be corrected easily with glasses, but this has taken a step further with the introduction of laser eye surgery. </s></p><p n="p2.64"><s n="s1.1;p2.64">Corneal implants can restore sight in patients whose cornea have clouded, likewise, lens replacements can provide a cure for cataracts, a symptom of old age, alcoholism and diabetes. </s></p><p n="p3.64"><s n="s1.2;p3.64">The most interesting development will be artificial impulse creation, that could enable completely blind and partially sighted individuals to have some sight stimulation. </s><s n="s2.2;p3.64">This implant will improve the qualities of lives of countless individuals, and so it is important to further understanding of the optic nerve system, and conversion of these signals to produce an image, within the occipital lobe of the brain. </s></p></div1><div1 type="front-back-matter"><head rend="bold">Table of Contents</head><p/></div1><div1 type="front-back-matter"><head rend="bold">1.0 Keywords </head><list type="simple"><item>Lacrimal Apparatus</item><item>Parasympathetic Nervous System</item><item>Extrinsic Eye Muscles</item><item>Corneal Penetrating keratoplasty </item><item>Myopia</item><item>Hyperopia </item><item>Cataracts</item><item>Photopigments</item><item>Colourblindness</item><item>Implants</item></list><p/></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">2.0 Introduction</head><p n="p4.64"><s n="s1.6;p4.64">Vision is a sense that is regarded to be highly valuable. </s><s n="s2.6;p4.64">From an early age, children are taught that the human experiences five senses: Touch; Taste; Smell; Sound and Sight. </s><s n="s3.6;p4.64">So it is no wonder that it is a subject that attracts much research for development. </s><s n="s4.6;p4.64">It is largely appreciated that the human eye is a complex organ, however, with any structure such as this, irregularities and imperfections can occur. </s><s n="s5.6;p4.64">The most frequently seen of these are myopia and hyperopia: short-sightedness and long-sightedness. </s><s n="s6.6;p4.64">This overview will look at the systems involved with the eye, the issues involved with vision correction, and how it can be hoped for research to develop in the future, so that more people can be given the gift of sight. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">3.0 The Eye </head><p n="p5.64"><s n="s1.3;p5.64">I will begin my discussion with a basic anatomy of the eye. </s><s n="s2.3;p5.64">Fig. </s><s n="s3.3;p5.64">1. indicates the main areas that are of importance when regarding the eye systems<ref target="BAWE_0347d-endnote.001"/>. </s></p><note place="end" id="BAWE_0347d-endnote.001"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1"><seg type="URL" n="http://www.mvrf.org/images/eye_anatomy.gif"/> </s></p></note><figure id="BAWE_0347d-fig.001"><head>Fig. 1. The Anatomy of the Eye. </head></figure><p n="p6.64"><s n="s1.2;p6.64">Each has specific function that helps to maintain the eye. </s><s n="s2.2;p6.64">A brief indication of these would be:<ref target="BAWE_0347d-endnote.002"/> </s></p><note place="end" id="BAWE_0347d-endnote.002"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1"><seg type="URL" n="http://www.college-optometrists.org/index.aspx/pcms/site.Public_Related_Links.Parts_of_the_Eye.Parts_of_the_Eye_home/"/> </s></p></note><p n="p7.64"><s n="s1.2;p7.64">The Lens bends the light entering the eye so that it forms an image on the retina at the back of the eye. </s><s n="s2.2;p7.64">The lens can change shape because it is held in position by the ciliary body. </s></p><p n="p8.64"><s n="s1.2;p8.64">The Cornea is a transparent membrane that covers the iris and pupil. </s><s n="s2.2;p8.64">It helps to focus the light. </s></p><p n="p9.64"><s n="s1.1;p9.64">The pupil is the dark hole in the centre of the iris. </s></p><p n="p10.64"><s n="s1.2;p10.64">The iris is the coloured circular part of the eye. </s><s n="s2.2;p10.64">It changes the size of the pupil to allow varying amounts of light to enter the eye. </s></p><p n="p11.64"><s n="s1.2;p11.64">The retina is at the back of the eye, and contains many receptor cells to sense the light. </s><s n="s2.2;p11.64">This sends a signal along the optic nerve to the brain. </s></p><p n="p12.64"><s n="s1.2;p12.64">The macula is the area that controls our main line of sight. </s><s n="s2.2;p12.64">At the centre of it is the fovea, which is where the highest concentration of cells are, in order that we can see in detail. </s></p><p n="p13.64"><s n="s1.1;p13.64">The sclera is the white part of the eye, which is made up of collagen fibres, and supports the structure. </s></p><p n="p14.64"><s n="s1.1;p14.64">The vitreous humour maintains the pressure within the eye, so that the structure is supported. </s></p><p n="p15.64"><s n="s1.1;p15.64">The choroid is a highly capillarised layer, which supplies blood to the retina and the sensory cells. </s></p><p n="p16.64"><s n="s1.1;p16.64">The optic nerve carries the impulses to the brain to analyse the image. </s></p><p n="p17.64"><s n="s1.1;p17.64">To follow on from this brief summary, each area of the eye will be discussed individually, in order that the system may be understood. </s></p><div2><head rend="bold italic">3.1 The Eyelids and Lacrimal Apparatus </head><p n="p18.64"><s n="s1.4;p18.64">The eyelids, or palpebrae, shade the eye during sleep, and prevents foreign objects entering the eye, that could interfere or damage the surface. </s><s n="s2.4;p18.64">They also spread lubricating secretions across the surface of the eyeball, that are produced in the lacrimal apparatus, found below the eyebrow. </s><s n="s3.4;p18.64">Fig. </s><s n="s4.4;p18.64">2. represents where this occurs<ref target="BAWE_0347d-endnote.003"/>. </s></p><note place="end" id="BAWE_0347d-endnote.003"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1"><seg type="URL" n="http://academia.hixie.ch/bath/eye/AnteriorViewOfLacrimalApparatus.gif"/> </s></p></note><figure id="BAWE_0347d-fig.002"><head>Fig.2. The Lacrimal Apparatus</head></figure><p n="p19.64"><s n="s1.2;p19.64">This is the system that produces and clears tears, which contain salts, mucus and lysozyme, a bactericidal enzyme. </s><s n="s2.2;p19.64">This lacrimal fluid cleans and lubricates the eyeball. </s></p><p n="p20.64"><s n="s1.1;p20.64">To the eyelids are attached eyelashes, tiny hairs that help to prevent dirt getting into the eye, and shade the eyes, to some extent, from bright light that could damage the internal structures. </s></p><p n="p21.64"><s n="s1.1;p21.64">So as can been seen, the eye is a heavily protected organ, even superficially, which makes it very difficult to analyse any maladies that can occur, because there are so many items to consider. </s></p><p n="p22.64"><s n="s1.1;p22.64">It may be noted that strong emotions of happiness or sadness can be expressed by the production of tears, and this is because the glands are parasympathetically stimulated to overproduce fluid, that cannot flow away quickly enough, this is what "crying" is, and is unique to humans, although it is unsure as to why this has evolved to be such. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold italic">3.2 The Iris and Genetics of Eye Colour </head><p n="p23.64"><s n="s1.2;p23.64">The iris is the coloured section of the eye, that controls the amount of light allowed into the eye through the pupil. </s><s n="s2.2;p23.64">It is made from circular and radial muscles, that are, in normal light, relaxed. </s></p><p n="p24.64"><s n="s1.1;p24.64">However, in bright light, the pupil narrows due to the circular muscles contracting, as part of the parasympathetic nerve system response. </s></p><p n="p25.64"><s n="s1.1;p25.64">The opposite happens in dim light, whereby the radial muscles contract, due to stimulation of the sympathetic nervous system. </s></p><p n="p26.64"><s n="s1.3;p26.64">This reaction can be useful to medics, to assess levels of consciousness in casualties. </s><s n="s2.3;p26.64">For example, a person with a head injury may have concussion if their pupils do not respond to light, and they are said to be "fixed and dilated". </s><s n="s3.3;p26.64">It can also be an indicator of brain stem injury in coma patients, because this response is one of the last levels of consciousness to disappear. </s></p><p n="p27.64"><s n="s1.3;p27.64">The colour of the iris is determined by pigments predetermined by genetics. </s><s n="s2.3;p27.64">The brown gene is dominant, which means that the probabilities of offspring's eye colour can be calculated as in Fig. </s><s n="s3.3;p27.64">3<ref target="BAWE_0347d-endnote.004"/>. </s></p><note place="end" id="BAWE_0347d-endnote.004"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1"><seg type="URL" n="http://www.dushkin.com/connectext/psy/ch02/eyes.mhtml"/> </s></p></note><figure id="BAWE_0347d-fig.003"><head>Fig. 3. Eye colour heredity probabilities</head></figure><p n="p28.64"><s n="s1.1;p28.64">Of course, alternative colours to blue and brown do occur, but the brown/blue comparison is more competitive than the other colours, so it provides a better example of dominance. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold italic">3.3 Extrinsic Eye Muscles</head><p n="p29.64"><s n="s1.2;p29.64">The movements of the eye are controlled by the extrinsic eye muscles. </s><s n="s2.2;p29.64">They can also be known as the extraocular muscles, and determine the "gaze direction" of the eye. </s></p><p n="p30.64"><s n="s1.1;p30.64">This is a simple system of muscles attached to the sclera of the eyeball, that pull the sides of the eye when reacting to brain signals. </s></p><p n="p31.64"><s n="s1.2;p31.64">There are six types of muscle that move the eye in each direction<ref target="BAWE_0347d-endnote.005"/>, as can be seen in Fig. </s><s n="s2.2;p31.64">4<ref target="BAWE_0347d-endnote.006"/>.: </s></p><note place="end" id="BAWE_0347d-endnote.005"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1"><seg type="URL" n="http://www.tedmontgomery.com/the_eye/eom.html"/> </s></p></note><note place="end" id="BAWE_0347d-endnote.006"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1"><seg type="URL" n="http://images.encarta.msn.com/xrefmedia/aencmed/targets/illus/ilt/T627350A.gif"/> </s></p></note><list type="simple"><item>medial rectus (MR) - moves the eye toward the nose</item><item>lateral rectus (LR) - moves the eye away from the nose</item><item>superior rectus (SR) - primarily moves the eye upward and secondarily rotates the top of the eye toward the nose</item><item>inferior rectus (IR) - primarily moves the eye downward and secondarily rotates the top of the eye away from the nose</item><item>superior oblique (SO) - primarily rotates the top of the eye toward the nose and secondarily moves the eye downward</item><item>inferior oblique (IO) - primarily rotates the top of the eye away from the nose and secondarily moves the eye upward </item></list><p n="p32.64"><s n="s1.2;p32.64">Which means that various "gazes" can be produced, as seen in Fig. </s><s n="s2.2;p32.64">5<ref target="BAWE_0347d-endnote.007"/>. </s></p><note place="end" id="BAWE_0347d-endnote.007"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1"><seg type="URL" n="http://www.tedmontgomery.com/the_eye/eom.html"/> </s></p></note><figure id="BAWE_0347d-fig.004"><head>Fig. 4. The extrinsic eye muscles</head></figure><figure id="BAWE_0347d-fig.005"><head>Fig. 5. Gazes MR = Medial Rectus LR = Lateral RectusSR = Superior Rectus IR = Inferior RectusSO = Superior Oblique IO = Inferior Oblique</head></figure><p n="p33.64"><s n="s1.2;p33.64">In patients where the eyes do not look in the same direction as eachother, there is a fault in the length of the muscles that control the eye movement. </s><s n="s2.2;p33.64">This can be fairly easily corrected by surgery, either at birth, or even later on in life, depending on the individual's personal wishes. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold italic">3.4 The Cornea (Penetrating keratoplasty)</head><p n="p34.64"><s n="s1.4;p34.64">The cornea (thin cover layer on iris and pupil) is the most frequently transplanted organ. </s><s n="s2.4;p34.64">It covers the surface of the eye, and helps to focus the light before entering the lens. </s><s n="s3.4;p34.64">Antibodies in the blood cannot reject it, so it usually produces a very successful transplant. </s><s n="s4.4;p34.64">A cornea must sometimes be replaced if it has been damaged by cataract operations, or due to chemical burns, but can also degenerate if the sufferer catches viral infections such as herpes simplex<ref target="BAWE_0347d-endnote.008"/>. </s></p><note place="end" id="BAWE_0347d-endnote.008"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1"><seg type="URL" n="http://www.eyemdlink.com/EyeProcedure.asp?EyeProcedureID=65"/> </s></p></note><figure id="BAWE_0347d-fig.006"/><p n="p35.64"><s n="s1.1;p35.64">Due to lack of donors for cornea transplants, sythetic corneas have recently been developed, which work equally as well as a biological replacement, which is excellent news because corneal disturbances can sometimes cause complete blindness, </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold italic">3.5 The Lens</head><p n="p36.64"><s n="s1.3;p36.64">The lens is one of the key structures that make it possible to see. </s><s n="s2.3;p36.64">It is held in position behind the cornea by suspensory ligaments, that are attached to the ciliary muscles. </s><s n="s3.3;p36.64">These muscles relax and contract to shorten or elongate the lens, so that the image can be focussed most appropriately. </s></p><p n="p37.64"><s n="s1.1;p37.64">The principle idea is that light enters the eye from a distant object, and then is curved by the lens and projected onto the retina at the back of the eye. </s></p><p n="p38.64"><s n="s1.2;p38.64">It can be demonstrated by use of a glass lens in Fig. </s><s n="s2.2;p38.64">6<ref target="BAWE_0347d-endnote.009"/>. </s></p><note place="end" id="BAWE_0347d-endnote.009"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1"><seg type="URL" n="http://sciencekit-onlineservices.com/images/SK_glasses2.gif"/> </s></p></note><figure id="BAWE_0347d-fig.007"><head>Fig. 6. Light comes in and is bent to a focal point</head></figure><p n="p39.64"><s n="s1.7;p39.64">However, within the eye, this is more complicated because the focal point occurs in the middle of the eye, which means that the image forms on the retina upside-down. </s><s n="s2.7;p39.64">The brain has become adapted to analysing this image and correcting it. </s><s n="s3.7;p39.64">Experiments have taken place where candidates agreed to wear glasses that flipped the image, so that they saw everything upside-down, but after about a week, the brain would cotton onto this, and correct the image, so that if they took off the glasses, their normal sight would return to the upside-down state. </s><s n="s4.7;p39.64">This shows an interesting ability for the brain to make adaptations. </s><s n="s5.7;p39.64">However, some things cannot be resolved, such as myopia (short sightedness) and hyperopia (long sightedness), which are when the flipped image focusses too close or too far from the retina. </s><s n="s6.7;p39.64">Due to our knowledge of lenses, this can be corrected by using glasses that are either convex, which bend the light in, or concave that bend the light out, Fig. </s><s n="s7.7;p39.64">7<ref target="BAWE_0347d-endnote.010"/>. </s></p><note place="end" id="BAWE_0347d-endnote.010"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1"><seg type="URL" n="http://hyperphysics.phy-astr.gsu.edu/hbase/geoopt/foclen.html"/> </s></p></note><figure id="BAWE_0347d-fig.008"><head>Fig. 7. convex and concave lenses</head></figure><p n="p40.64"><s n="s1.1;p40.64">An optometrist can assess the levels of myopia/hyperopia by examination, and prescribe a power of correctional lens to use. </s></p><p n="p41.64"><s n="s1.1;p41.64"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0347d-form.001"/> </s></p><p n="p42.64"><ref target="BAWE_0347d-endnote.011"/><s n="s1.2;p42.64">The units of focal length are metres (m), therefore the units of refractive power are per meters (m <hi rend="sup">-1</hi>). </s><s n="s2.2;p42.64">There is another name for the units of refractive power though, they are called <hi rend="italic">dioptres</hi> (D). </s></p><note place="end" id="BAWE_0347d-endnote.011"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1"><seg type="URL" n="http://academia.hixie.ch/bath/eye/home.html"/> </s></p></note><p n="p43.64"><s n="s1.1;p43.64">The relationship between <hi rend="italic">u</hi>, the distance between the object and the lens, <hi rend="italic">v</hi>, the distance between the virtual image and the lens, and <hi rend="italic">f</hi>, the focal length of the lens, is </s></p><p n="p44.64"><s n="s1.1;p44.64"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0347d-form.002"/> </s></p><p n="p45.64"><s n="s1.1;p45.64">These calculations are frequently used in optical physics, which goes to show that the process of the eye is another thing that physics can explain. </s></p><p n="p46.64"><s n="s1.3;p46.64">Lenses, similarly to the cornea, can become cloudy caused by the degeration of the cells within the lens. </s><s n="s2.3;p46.64">This is commonly known as cataracts, and is seen often in the elderly, however, eye injuries, or diseases such as diabetes and alcoholism can trigger this. </s><s n="s3.3;p46.64">Cataracts can quite easily be diagnosed, because they are so evident from the surface of the eye <ref target="BAWE_0347d-endnote.012"/> </s></p><note place="end" id="BAWE_0347d-endnote.012"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1"><seg type="URL" n="http://www.stlukeseye.com/Conditions/Cataracts.asp"/> </s></p></note><figure id="BAWE_0347d-pic.001"><head>Fig. 8. A visible cataract in the eye.</head></figure><p n="p47.64"><s n="s1.1;p47.64">Vision becomes highly impaired, and is the leading cause of visual loss in over 55's. </s></p><p n="p48.64"><s n="s1.1;p48.64">. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold italic">3.6 The Retina </head><p n="p49.64"><s n="s1.5;p49.64">This is the sensitive area at the back of the eye, that supports the photoreceptor cells, containing photopigments for light recognition. </s><s n="s2.5;p49.64">There are two types of these cells: rods and cones. </s><s n="s3.5;p49.64">The rods recognise black and white, whereas the cone cells are colour receptors. </s><s n="s4.5;p49.64">The cells are arranged within the retina, so that there are many cone cells at the fovea, but mostly rod cells elsewhere within the eye. </s><s n="s5.5;p49.64">This means that the highest detail definition is at the fovea<ref target="BAWE_0347d-endnote.013"/>, which is the focal point of vision. </s></p><note place="end" id="BAWE_0347d-endnote.013"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1"><seg type="URL" n="http://www.anisn.it/scuola/strumenti/visione/images/fovea.jpg"/> </s></p></note><figure id="BAWE_0347d-fig.009"/><p n="p50.64"><s n="s1.1;p50.64">Of the cones, there are three specifications: </s></p><p n="p51.64"><s n="s1.1;p51.64">cones that absorb long-wavelength light (red) </s></p><p n="p52.64"><s n="s1.1;p52.64">cones that absorb middle-wavelength light (green) </s></p><p n="p53.64"><s n="s1.1;p53.64">cones that absorb short-wavelength light (blue) </s></p><p n="p54.64"><s n="s1.1;p54.64">This gives rise to the occurrence of colour blindness. </s></p><p n="p55.64"><s n="s1.4;p55.64">Colour blindness is a condition that affects a small percentage of the population, and is associated with which versions of the cone cells are present in the fovea. </s><s n="s2.4;p55.64">Some individuals do not have all 3 types, and therefore it is difficult for them to determine differences between certain colours. </s><s n="s3.4;p55.64">Tests such as those in Fig. </s><s n="s4.4;p55.64">9., can be performed to determine this defect<ref target="BAWE_0347d-endnote.014"/> </s></p><note place="end" id="BAWE_0347d-endnote.014"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1"><seg type="URL" n="http://colorvisiontesting.com/ishihara.htm"/> </s></p></note><figure id="BAWE_0347d-fig.010"><head>Fig. 9. Colour-blindness tests</head></figure></div2><div2><head rend="bold italic">3.7 The Sensory Connections</head><p n="p56.64"><s n="s1.2;p56.64">The signal to send via the optic nerve is produced when, within the rod or cone cell, the chemical 11-cis-retinal is stimulated to break down to all-trans-retinal, which happens when the light causes a threshold within the plasma membrane to be breached. </s><s n="s2.2;p56.64">This causes a release of ATP from the mitcochondria, where packages are sent through the synaptic terminal. </s></p><p n="p57.64"><s n="s1.1;p57.64">This terminal is connected to a bipolar cell, which connects to ganglion cells and sends the signal to the optic nerve, which takes the signal to the brain to be translated at the visual association area, within the occipital lobe. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0347d-fig.011"><head>Fig. 10. The internal organelles of the Rod cell</head></figure><p n="p58.64"><s n="s1.3;p58.64">Fig. </s><s n="s2.3;p58.64">11. </s><s n="s3.3;p58.64">The Fovea and Nerve connection structure </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">4.0 The Future for Eye Surgery</head><p n="p59.64"><s n="s1.4;p59.64">A recent boom has taken place in popularity of laser eye surgery. </s><s n="s2.4;p59.64">Its aim is to reduce dependence upon use of contact lenses and glasses. </s><s n="s3.4;p59.64">In the surgery, the actual procedure is to remove some corneal tissue, which alters the shape of the light entering the eye, so that it becomes easier to focus the light on the retina. </s><s n="s4.4;p59.64">Unfortunately, this process still has long healing times, but most often is very successful in creating a vast improvement in sight, of sufferers with myopia and hyperopia. </s></p><p n="p60.64"><s n="s1.3;p60.64">The use of prosthetic lens replacement is being developed by researchers, which would aim to completely remove a distorted lens, and insert a polymer-based material instead. </s><s n="s2.3;p60.64">This is due to the repetition of failures in lens transplants. </s><s n="s3.3;p60.64">A biological lens does not last for long after the donor has deceased, which means that it is not a viable option. </s></p><p n="p61.64"><s n="s1.3;p61.64">An interesting field has opened up, into the possibility of artificial impulse creation in subjects that have complete loss of sight. </s><s n="s2.3;p61.64">This would involve an implant being attached to the visual association area in the brain, which would have the input of a camera, and its output into the brain would be impulses mimicking those that would have been sent, if the eye was functioning correctly. </s><s n="s3.3;p61.64">Some prototypes have been made, but it will be a fair few years until this technology is in circulation. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">5.0 Discussion and Conclusion </head><p n="p62.64"><s n="s1.4;p62.64">The eye is a multi-functional complex tool, that has taken years to understand. </s><s n="s2.4;p62.64">Many subsystems such as the lacrimal apparatus have been developed to ensure smooth, efficient use of this body part. </s><s n="s3.4;p62.64">Suffice to say, each part had been studied by researchers into extent, which helps us to diagnose, and now treat, many debilitating disorders. </s><s n="s4.4;p62.64">On a reasonably small scale, myopia and hyperopia can be corrected easily with glasses, but this has taken a step further with the introduction of laser eye surgery. </s></p><p n="p63.64"><s n="s1.1;p63.64">Corneal implants can restore sight in patients whose cornea have clouded, likewise, lens replacements can provide a cure for cataracts, a symptom of old age, alcoholism and diabetes. </s></p><p n="p64.64"><s n="s1.2;p64.64">The most interesting development will be artificial impulse creation, that could enable completely blind and partially sighted individuals to have some sight stimulation. </s><s n="s2.2;p64.64">This implant will improve the qualities of lives of countless individuals, and so it is important to further understanding of the optic nerve system, and conversion of these signals to produce an image, within the occipital lobe of the brain. </s></p></div1></body><back><div1 type="bibliography"><head rend="bold">6.0 References </head><p>Saladin, K S. (2004) Anatomy and physiology : the unity of form and function 3rd edition, McGraw-Hill</p><p>Silverthorn, D U. (2001) Human Physiology, an integrated approach, Prentice Hall, New Jersey</p><p>Tortura, G J, and Reynolds Grabowski, S. (2003) Principles of Anatomy and Physiology, Tenth Edition, Biological Sciences Textbooks, USA</p><p><seg type="URL" n="http://www.icat.ncsu.edu/projects/retina/"/></p><p><seg type="URL" n="http://www2.warwick.ac.uk/fac/sci/eng/euo/modules/year1/es173/es173new/senses/bioeng04_senses.pdf"/></p><p><seg type="URL" n="http://highered.mcgraw-hill.com/sites/0072919264/student_view0/"/></p><p><seg type="URL" n="http://bcs.whfreeman.com/thelifewire/default.asp?s=&amp;n=&amp;i=&amp;v=&amp;o=&amp;ns=0&amp;uid=0&amp;rau=0"/></p></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
