<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_0347b" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Inertia Laboratory</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">The document has a title page which contains:
document title
title part</note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">Language used in quote: <foreign id="English">English</foreign></note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">deleted: date, page numbers</note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">appendices: briefing sheet, results, calculations</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">1</p><p n="date">2006-06</p><p n="module title">Laboratory</p><p n="module code">ES180</p><p n="genre family">Methodology recount</p><p n="discipline">Engineering</p><p n="disciplinary group">PS</p><p n="grade">M</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">1236</p><p n="number of s-units">57</p><p n="number of p">37</p><p n="number of tables">2</p><p n="number of figures">1</p><p n="number of block quotes">1</p><p n="number of formulae">3</p><p n="number of lists">3</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">0</p><p n="abstract present">abstract present</p><p n="average words per s-unit">21.7</p><p n="average s-units per p">1.5</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">f</p><p n="year of birth">1987</p><p n="first language">English</p><p n="education">UKA</p><p n="course">Meng</p><p n="student ID">0347</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><titlePart rend="bold">University of <name type="university"/> School of Engineering</titlePart><docTitle><titlePart rend="bold">Inertia Laboratory</titlePart></docTitle><titlePart><hi rend="bold">by</hi> <hi rend="bold"><name type="student name"/><name type="student ID"/></hi></titlePart><titlePart>Report Reference Code: ES180L8 Mechanics Affiliation: Year 1 Engineering Report of laboratory performed on: 30 <hi rend="sup">th</hi> January 2006</titlePart></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="abstract"><head rend="bold">Summary</head><p n="p1.37"><s n="s1.2;p1.37">The aim of this laboratory is to devise an experiment to investigate the moment of Inertia of metal disks, whilst assessing the validity of the methods, discussing the ways in which accuracy could be improved. </s><s n="s2.2;p1.37">This is to introduce the basic concept of the moment of Inertia. </s></p><p n="p2.37"><s n="s1.2;p2.37">The method to be used is that the metal disks will be attached to a spindle, with a line of string around it, on which will be attached defined masses. </s><s n="s2.2;p2.37">The time it takes for the mass to reach a certain distance will be recorded, and these figures will be compared and analysed with the aim of discovering the moment of Inertia for each disk. </s></p><p n="p3.37"><s n="s1.2;p3.37">The significant conclusion found by this experiment is that the moment of Inertia increases as the radius and mass of the disk increase. </s><s n="s2.2;p3.37">The experiment results were indicative of a similar value for Inertia that were mathematically predicted, which suggest that the errors inherent in the experiment were not intrusive in analysis. </s></p></div1><div1 type="front-back-matter"><head rend="bold">Table of Contents</head><p/></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">1.0 Introduction</head><p n="p4.37"><s n="s1.3;p4.37">The aim that was provided in the briefing sheet [Appendix I], summarises the idea of the experiment. </s><s n="s2.3;p4.37">However, an ulterior motive of the laboratory was to explain the concept of Inertia, in a way that could be understood. </s><s n="s3.3;p4.37">The objective of the experiment set out by the briefing, was to investigate the moment Inertia of three different sized metal disks, including an assessment of accuracy. </s></p><p n="p5.37"><s n="s1.1;p5.37">The principal conclusion that can be drawn is that the larger the disk, the larger the moment of Inertia, because it takes a greater force to alter the direction and rotational velocities of the disk. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">2.0 Theory</head><p n="p6.37"><s n="s1.1;p6.37">The Theory is mostly explained in the briefing sheet [Appendix I], however, it is important to understand some basic principles: </s></p><p n="p7.37"><s n="s1.1;p7.37">What is Inertia? </s></p><quote lang="English"><hi rend="bold">in·er·tia</hi> (<formula notation="" id="BAWE_0347b-form.001"/>-nûrsh)<hi rend="italic">n.</hi> The tendency of a body to resist acceleration; the tendency of a body at rest to remain at rest or of a body in motion to stay in motion in a straight line unless acted on by an outside force. Resistance or disinclination to motion, action, or change. <ref target="BAWE_0347b-ftnote.001"/></quote><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0347b-ftnote.001"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1"><seg type="URL" n="http://dictionary.reference.com/search?q=inertia"/>, accessed 14th February 2006. </s></p></note><p n="p8.37"><s n="s1.1;p8.37">From this explanation, we can assume that we will need to know some basic formulae in order to analyse any results. </s></p><p n="p9.37"><s n="s1.1;p9.37">The main ones that will be combined will be: </s></p><list type="ordered"><item>(a) F = ma</item><item>(b) T = Iα</item><item>(c) T = Fr</item><item>(d) s = ut + 1/2at <hi rend="sup">2</hi></item></list><p n="p10.37"><s n="s1.1;p10.37">whereby: </s></p><p n="p11.37"><s n="s1.1;p11.37">F = the force required for the given acceleration [N]; m = the mass of the object [kg]; a = acceleration of the object [ms <hi rend="sup">-2</hi>]; </s></p><p n="p12.37"><s n="s1.1;p12.37">T = the torque required for the given angular acceleration [Nm]; I = the moment of Inertia of the object [kgm <hi rend="sup">2</hi>]; α = the angular acceleration of the object [rad/s <hi rend="sup">-2</hi>] </s></p><p n="p13.37"><s n="s1.1;p13.37">s = vertical displacement of the object [m]; u = initial velocity of the object [ms <hi rend="sup">-1</hi>]; t = time that it takes for the action to take place [s] </s></p><p n="p14.37"><s n="s1.1;p14.37">These formulae can be easily transformed to give the following equation that will be of use after the results have been taken [workings can be found as Appendix II]: </s></p><list type="ordered"><item>m ≈ (I <hi rend="sub">disk</hi> 2s)/(gr <hi rend="sup">2</hi>t <hi rend="sup">2</hi>)</item></list><p n="p15.37"><s n="s1.1;p15.37">Therefore, the values of: s; g; and r must be discovered in order that the values for m can be put into the equation, so that the final moment of Inertia can be calculated for each disk, which will be the basis of analysis for the results. </s></p><p n="p16.37"><s n="s1.2;p16.37">These formulae will also come of importance when plotting the results graphically. </s><s n="s2.2;p16.37">It is aimed that the y-axis value shall be a measure of the applied mass, and to obtain a graphical solution of the Inertia, we must have the x-axis representing the value </s></p><p n="p17.37"><s n="s1.1;p17.37"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0347b-form.002"/> </s></p><p n="p18.37"><s n="s1.1;p18.37">so that the gradient of the graph will be </s></p><p n="p19.37"><s n="s1.1;p19.37"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0347b-form.003"/> </s></p><p n="p20.37"><s n="s1.1;p20.37">which then can be rearranged easily to find the Inertia. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">3.0 Apparatus and Methods</head><figure id="BAWE_0347b-pic.001"><head>Fig 1</head></figure><p n="p21.37"><s n="s1.2;p21.37">The set up for the experiment is as shown roughly in Fig. </s><s n="s2.2;p21.37">1. </s></p><p n="p22.37"><s n="s1.1;p22.37">Where the yellow disk is indicative of the metal disks to be tested, and the yellow weights at the bottom are the variable masses. </s></p><p n="p23.37"><s n="s1.2;p23.37">The experiment will take place, such that the string with mass shall be wound on a spindle attached to the disk, and the stopclock will be started as the weight is released, setting the disk spinning, and will stop as the string reaches the set distance. </s><s n="s2.2;p23.37">This is in order to record the time as the independent variable, where the mass is the dependent variable. </s></p><p n="p24.37"><s n="s1.1;p24.37">A more detailed method can be read in Appendix III. </s></p><p n="p25.37"><s n="s1.1;p25.37">Therefore, the apparatus required is: </s></p><list type="simple"><item>Stopclock;</item><item>Variable masses;</item><item>String;</item><item>Spindle;</item><item>Mount;</item><item>Rule.</item></list><p n="p26.37"><s n="s1.1;p26.37">This reasonably simple set up will produce a good set of results for basic analysis. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">4.0 Observations and Results</head><p n="p27.37"><s n="s1.2;p27.37">Observations that were made during the experiment were notably of the differences in the length of the string, as different masses were added. </s><s n="s2.2;p27.37">This meant that the timing of the drop-period was inaccurate because the extension of the string meant that the vertical displacement was different for each experiment. </s></p><p n="p28.37"><s n="s1.2;p28.37">The time will also be inaccurate because the stopclock was not recorded mechanically, so human error will vary the results greatly. </s><s n="s2.2;p28.37">Ensuring that the same person is used for each set of results can reduce this. </s></p><p n="p29.37"><s n="s1.2;p29.37">Fig. </s><s n="s2.2;p29.37">2 is the table of results that were taken directly from the experiments, without analysis. </s></p><p n="p30.37"><s n="s1.1;p30.37">The error for the times will be 0.5[s], and the error for the masses will be 0.002[kg]. </s></p><table id="BAWE_0347b-tab.001"><head rend="italic">Fig 2</head><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p31.37"><s n="s1.1;p31.37">These results have been analysed to find averages [Appendix IV], and also the values to be plotted on the x-axis of the graphs, which are 1/t <hi rend="sup">2</hi> values. </s></p><p n="p32.37"><s n="s1.2;p32.37">Fig. </s><s n="s2.2;p32.37">3 shows the results that will be plotted on the graph [Appendix V] </s></p><table id="BAWE_0347b-tab.002"><head>Fig 3</head><row><cell/></row></table></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">5.0 Analysis and Discussion of Results</head><p n="p33.37"><s n="s1.1;p33.37">The values for the moment of Inertia can not only be calculated from the results, but also mathematically by the means outlined in Appendix I. This means that the two sets of results can be compared, as in Appendix VI and VII. </s></p><p n="p34.37"><s n="s1.5;p34.37">From the graph Appendix V, we can see that the prediction for larger moment of Inertia for larger disks was very evident. </s><s n="s2.5;p34.37">The three lines of best for, one for each disk, show also that the results were by no means perfect, taking into account the errors, however, these errors were minimal. </s><s n="s3.5;p34.37">Comparing the two sets of results from Appendices VI and VII, we can see that the differences between the calculated figures and the mathematical figures are not too large. </s><s n="s4.5;p34.37">This suggests that the experiment's inaccuracies were low. </s><s n="s5.5;p34.37">Therefore, there is reasonable confidence that the experiment was quite effective. </s></p><p n="p35.37"><s n="s1.2;p35.37">To improve the method, and reduce errors, firstly a more accurate method of recording time should be installed. </s><s n="s2.2;p35.37">The use of light gates attached to a computer could log results in with a much smaller error. </s></p><p n="p36.37"><s n="s1.2;p36.37">If the string were inelastic the times would also be more accurate. </s><s n="s2.2;p36.37">The heat increase should also be taken into account, as the more repetitions of experiments, the higher the heat of the system will be, as energy is lost. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">6.0 Conclusions</head><p n="p37.37"><s n="s1.3;p37.37">The moment of Inertia can be calculated quite accurately from even simple experiments. </s><s n="s2.3;p37.37">It has been found that the moment of Inertia is dependant on the radius and mass of the object, both of which increase the final figure. </s><s n="s3.3;p37.37">This is because the measurement of Inertia is resistance to motion, which concurs with the fact that larger objects have greater resistance. </s></p></div1></body><back><div1 type="appendix"><head rend="bold">Appendices</head><p/></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
