<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_0347c" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Numerical Simulation of Car Wind-Tunnel Tests</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note/></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">1</p><p n="date">2006-06</p><p n="module title">Design for Function</p><p n="module code">ES174</p><p n="genre family">Methodology recount</p><p n="discipline">Engineering</p><p n="disciplinary group">PS</p><p n="grade">D</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">953</p><p n="number of s-units">37</p><p n="number of p">24</p><p n="number of tables">1</p><p n="number of figures">1</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">5</p><p n="number of lists">1</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">5</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">25.8</p><p n="average s-units per p">1.5</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">f</p><p n="year of birth">1987</p><p n="first language">English</p><p n="education">UKA</p><p n="course">Meng</p><p n="student ID">0347</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><titlePart><hi rend="bold">UNIVERSITY OF <name type="university"/> School of Engineering</hi><hi rend="bold"> ES174-Stage II</hi></titlePart><docTitle><titlePart rend="bold">Fluid PC Project: Car Aerodynamics - Numerical Simulation of Car Wind-Tunnel Tests - </titlePart></docTitle><titlePart><name type="student name"/><name type="student ID"/>, January 2006</titlePart></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Introduction</head><p n="p1.24"><s n="s1.3;p1.24">This project has been based around the simple principle of learning about basic Car Aerodynamics, and how car bodies can be designed and tested to reach optimal performance, without the extensive use of full prototyping i.e. by use of computer simulation software. </s><s n="s2.3;p1.24">An introduction to <hi rend="italic">Solidworks</hi> has already been performed, so this knowledge can be improved by introducing another Program: <hi rend="italic">CosmosFloWorks</hi>, which will enable the designs in <hi rend="italic">Solidworks</hi> to run and solve calculations for velocity and pressure amongst others. </s><s n="s3.3;p1.24">However, the investigations of this project shall be based around discovering the Drag Force and hence the Drag Coefficient at different wind speeds, and attempting to use this data to develop the initial car design. </s></p><p n="p2.24"><s n="s1.1;p2.24">Therefore, the objectives for this Project are to: </s></p><list type="bulleted"><item>Learn the basic concepts of fluid dynamics and car aerodynamics;</item><item>Learn about design philosophy and approach with use of computer software;</item><item>Perform basic analysis and optimisation techniques, with use of computer software.</item></list></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Theory</head><p n="p3.24"><s n="s1.1;p3.24">After having been given the initial Briefing sheet<ref target="BAWE_0347c-ftnote.001"/>, a varied selection of equations can be recognised, that will be needed in order to reach a sensible analysis. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0347c-ftnote.001"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Given in the accompanying CD </s></p></note><p rend="bulleted" n="p4.24"><s n="s1.1;p4.24">Density (of air at sea level, <hi rend="italic">T</hi> = 288.16 <hi rend="italic">K</hi>): <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0347c-form.001"/> </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p5.24"><s n="s1.1;p5.24">Drag force: <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0347c-form.002"/>, which comes out of the tests as "<hi rend="bold italic">X Component of Force</hi>" </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p6.24"><s n="s1.1;p6.24"><hi rend="italic">Afront:</hi> Frontal (silhouette) area of the car (a constant) </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p7.24"><s n="s1.1;p7.24">Dynamic Pressure: <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0347c-form.003"/>, which can be calculated for each individual wind velocity tested. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p8.24"><s n="s1.1;p8.24">Drag Coefficient: <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0347c-form.004"/>, which will be plotted against Velocity during analysis, to compare whether the design alterations have been effective. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Running the Software</head><p n="p9.24"><s n="s1.1;p9.24">Through use of the instruction sheet<ref target="BAWE_0347c-ftnote.002"/>, a tutorial of the set up of <hi rend="italic">CosmosFloWorks</hi> can be obtained, in order to initialise the basic project, for example, by specifying that the tests should be carried out using SI units, ensuring that it is using air values for fluid, where the surface of the car is regarded as smooth and therefore negligible, and the geometry resolution is small so that a fairly accurate picture of the airflow patterns can be obtained. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0347c-ftnote.002"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Tutorial On CFD Analysis of Air Flow Around Car Using Solidworks </s></p></note><p n="p10.24"><s n="s1.4;p10.24">After this, the Inlet Velocity face and speed can be determined. </s><s n="s2.4;p10.24">This is where the variation in velocity for each run is inputted. </s><s n="s3.4;p10.24">The wind must be coming from the front of the car, so the correct wind tunnel face must be selected. </s><s n="s4.4;p10.24">This is repeated with the Static Pressure opening, which will be at the rear face of the vehicle. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0347c-pic.001"><head>Figure 1</head></figure><p n="p11.24"><s n="s1.1;p11.24">In Figure 1, it can be seen that the red arrows at the front plane are the Inlet Velocity face, and the blue arrows are the Static Pressure Opening face. </s></p><p n="p12.24"><s n="s1.1;p12.24">After this, the surface goals must be selected, whereby each face of the car, apart from those directly joint to the wind tunnel face should be selected, so that when the software runs, it knows which surfaces represent the car. </s></p><p n="p13.24"><s n="s1.2;p13.24">The calculation can then be solved, during which iteration graphs can be obtained, and various surface plots of the velocity and pressure within the wind tunnel, as affected by the structure of the car. </s><s n="s2.2;p13.24">Once completed, the solver calculations are converted into <hi rend="italic">Excel</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Word</hi> documents that represent all of the results<ref target="BAWE_0347c-ftnote.003"/>. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0347c-ftnote.003"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">These results are available in full in the accompanying CD </s></p></note><p n="p14.24"><s n="s1.2;p14.24">The two versions of the car to be tested are available for view in the Accompanying CD. The idea of testing one car first was to design the second car so that it was an aerodynamically improved version of the first. </s><s n="s2.2;p14.24">The data analysis will aim to prove this. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Analysis and Discussion</head><p n="p15.24"><s n="s1.2;p15.24">To analyse the results that were obtained, the drag coefficient will need to be found. </s><s n="s2.2;p15.24">Given that the density of air is a constant 1.23 <hi rend="italic">kg/m3</hi>, likewise the frontal area is constant: measured at 2.732m <hi rend="sup">2</hi>, and the Velocity is decided by the inputted <hi rend="italic">Inlet Velocity</hi>, this means that the Drag Force must be the value that will be measured to find the Drag Coefficient. </s></p><p n="p16.24"><s n="s1.1;p16.24">By using the iterated <hi rend="bold italic">X Component of Force</hi> the Drag Force for each set of results can therefore be found<ref target="BAWE_0347c-ftnote.004"/>, by using the previously discussed formula <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0347c-form.005"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0347c-ftnote.004"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Full results are available in the accompanying CD </s></p></note><p n="p17.24"><s n="s1.1;p17.24">Figure 2 shows a summary of the results that were used to obtain graphical analysis of the car design. </s></p><table id="BAWE_0347c-tab.001"><head>Figure 2</head><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p18.24"><s n="s1.2;p18.24">Hence, Figure 3 shows the graphical representation of these results. </s><s n="s2.2;p18.24">As seen, these results at least show some difference between the two designs. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0347c-fig.001"><head>Figure 3</head></figure><p n="p19.24"><s n="s1.2;p19.24">The lower the Drag Coefficient, the higher the efficiency of the car's movement will be. </s><s n="s2.2;p19.24">This means that around the 30ms <hi rend="sup">-1</hi> velocity region for both sets of data, the movement of the car is more efficient, and reduces drag. </s></p><p n="p20.24"><s n="s1.1;p20.24">The second design's line of best fit is also lower than the line for the first design, which can also be seen in the results table Figure 2. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Conclusions</head><p n="p21.24"><s n="s1.2;p21.24">The analysis is fairly conclusive, in that an improvement in car design has been achieved. </s><s n="s2.2;p21.24">However, there is much space for improvement and increase in experimental accuracy. </s></p><p n="p22.24"><s n="s1.2;p22.24">Some faults in the experiment were that the computational software did not have enough time to solve each run for as many iterations as it needed to get the most accurate final answer, as there were limits applied. </s><s n="s2.2;p22.24">Also, the frontal area of each car was estimated given the dimensions - there was no simple way of working this out. </s></p><p n="p23.24"><s n="s1.1;p23.24">If more repetitions were carried out, then a more definite graphical representation would be attained; as it stands, any 'peak' is entirely averaged. </s></p><p n="p24.24"><s n="s1.2;p24.24">Ideally, this routine would be continued until a design was reached whereby it would be difficult to find any further improvements in aerodynamic efficiency. </s><s n="s2.2;p24.24">The final tests for ultimate streamline would have to take into account the Bernoulli equation, which suggests that at the greatest possible aerodynamic peak, the Dynamic Pressure is equal to the Static Pressure, therefore there being no energy losses due to air resistance. </s></p></div1></body><back/></text></TEI.2>
