<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_0348b" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Simple Life Business Plan</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">The document has a title page which contains:
document title
title part</note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">deleted: page numbers</note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">watermarked paper</note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">appendices: other propducts onm market, CVs of participants, projected accounts</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">2</p><p n="date">2007-01</p><p n="module title">Starting and Running a Business</p><p n="module code">ES2A6</p><p n="genre family">Proposal</p><p n="discipline">Engineering</p><p n="disciplinary group">PS</p><p n="grade">M</p><p n="number of authors">4</p><p n="number of words">2974</p><p n="number of s-units">151</p><p n="number of p">46</p><p n="number of tables">1</p><p n="number of figures">2</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">0</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">7</p><p n="abstract present">abstract present</p><p n="average words per s-unit">19.7</p><p n="average s-units per p">3.3</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">f</p><p n="year of birth">1986</p><p n="first language">English</p><p n="education">UKA</p><p n="course">Civil Engineering</p><p n="student ID">0348</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><docTitle><titlePart rend="bold">Business Plan </titlePart></docTitle><titlePart rend="bold">2007-2009</titlePart><titlePart>This Business Plan has been prepared by Simple Life's CEO, <name type="other"/> and Technical Director, <name type="other"/>.</titlePart></titlePage><div1 type="toc" n="1"><head rend="bold">CONTENTS</head><p/></div1></front><body><div1 type="abstract"><head rend="bold">EXECUTIVE SUMMARY</head><p rend="bulleted" n="p1.46"><s n="s1.2;p1.46">Simple Life Ltd, founded in 2005 By <name type="other"/> requires £75,000 for the development and initial manufacturing of a tool to aid in the turning of everyday object in the household for sufferers of arthritis, carpel tunnel syndrome and claw hand. </s><s n="s2.2;p1.46">This initial investment will be in return for a 20% stake in the company. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p2.46"><s n="s1.2;p2.46">The Arthritis Research Campaign state that 4.4 million people in the UK have X-ray evidence of moderate to severe arthritis in their hands [1]. </s><s n="s2.2;p2.46">This can be seen as Simple Life's potential market. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p3.46"><s n="s1.2;p3.46">A niche product has been designed that is better quality and more aesthetically pleasing than its rivals. </s><s n="s2.2;p3.46">Furthermore, unlike the products currently available, the Simple Life tool is universal. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p4.46"><s n="s1.1;p4.46">By retailing not only through the internet, but through mail order and high street outlets we aim to quickly gain a firm place in the market. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p5.46"><s n="s1.1;p5.46">Current assets stand at £57,000 gathered from family and personal savings. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p6.46"><s n="s1.1;p6.46">In three years we aim to be manufacturing 26000 products a year, and have a closing profit of over £89,000. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p7.46"><s n="s1.1;p7.46">In ten years, if the current trends continue and Simple life gains just 10% of the market from its main competitor Homecraft Roylan, you will have a five-fold return on your investment . </s></p></div1><div1 type="front-back-matter"><head rend="bold">MISSION STATEMENT</head><p>
"Aiding the community through technology" 
</p><p><name type="other"/> 
</p><p>
CEO Simple Life 
</p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">THE PRODUCT</head><div2><head rend="bold">Features</head><p n="p8.46"><s n="s1.4;p8.46">A device to aid in three different household operations that prove particularly difficult for sufferers of common hand ailments such as arthritis, carpel tunnel syndrome and claw hand. </s><s n="s2.4;p8.46">The three different operations are covered by three separate tools. </s><s n="s3.4;p8.46">These are interchangeable about a central handle that is ergonomically designed for comfort and ease of use. </s><s n="s4.4;p8.46">This handle can be seen below. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0348b-pic.002"><head>Fig 1. The Universal Handle</head></figure><p n="p9.46"><s n="s1.1;p9.46">The three tools are as follows: </s></p><p n="p10.46"><s n="s1.1;p10.46">Jar opener - This allows varying sizes of lids to be removed with ease. </s></p><p n="p11.46"><s n="s1.1;p11.46">Key turner - Provides more leverage for a standard door/window key. </s></p><p n="p12.46"><s n="s1.1;p12.46">Contour turner - this tool aids in turning of knobs and dials of various sizes. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0348b-pic.003"><head> Fig 2. The Jar Opening Tool </head></figure><figure id="BAWE_0348b-pic.004"><head> Fig.3. The Key Turner </head></figure><figure id="BAWE_0348b-pic.005"><head> Fig. 4. The Contour Turner</head></figure></div2><div2><head rend="bold">Quality</head><p n="p13.46"><s n="s1.4;p13.46">This is the most important aspect in our business. </s><s n="s2.4;p13.46">We view quality as an order winning feature in this market, as current manufacturers have failed to implement this level of high quality. </s><s n="s3.4;p13.46">As a commitment to our customers and a demonstration of confidence in our product, we want to assure long term functionality and hence will offer a 3 year guarantee on all of our products. </s><s n="s4.4;p13.46">This will make our brand image that of a producer of high quality goods. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">Packaging</head><p n="p14.46"><s n="s1.3;p14.46">Again we feel that this is where our competitors fall down, allowing an exploitable gap in the market. </s><s n="s2.3;p14.46">Competitor's products are sold in a clear plastic wrapper with a named sticky label attached. </s><s n="s3.3;p14.46">We are packaging with professionalism in mind; with visually attractive covering and clear description of the product. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">Place</head><p n="p15.46"><s n="s1.9;p15.46">Currently the majority of sales are through third party companies online. </s><s n="s2.9;p15.46">We do not believe that this is the optimum retail method for the Simple Life product. </s><s n="s3.9;p15.46">The majority of our target market is the age group 65+. </s><s n="s4.9;p15.46">Considering this fact, and the reviewing the chart below for 'Access to internet'. </s><s n="s5.9;p15.46">You can see that retailing through the internet may not be the best method, as only 4% of the UK internet usage is attributed to our majority target age group. </s><s n="s6.9;p15.46">This data is reflected in a report titled ' Home Shopping - UK- March 2005' from the Mintel economic database. </s><s n="s7.9;p15.46">It can be seen that 7% of over 65's have purchased goods from the internet in the past 12 months [3]. </s><s n="s8.9;p15.46">From the same report it is shown that 28% of the same age group have purchased from a mail order catalogue. </s><s n="s9.9;p15.46">Based on this data we believe that mail order catalogues will be a more suitable method of retail than the internet, which is used by our competitors, Homecraft Roylan. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0348b-pic.006"><head>Access to internet</head></figure><figure id="BAWE_0348b-pic.007"><head>Profile of people with arthritic problems</head></figure><p n="p16.46"><s n="s1.4;p16.46">Suffering from arthritis does not impede the ability to stroll down the high street. </s><s n="s2.4;p16.46">We believe that despite the high possible sales through mail order catalogues, Customers always prefer purchasing a physical product. </s><s n="s3.4;p16.46">With our superior quality and eye catching design, it would be unwise to turn a blind eye to the possible sales that could be achieved through this method of retail. </s><s n="s4.4;p16.46">Therefore we are planning to sell through mail order and direct retailing channels. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">Price</head><p n="p17.46"><s n="s1.10;p17.46">Our product has spurred from the rival products (See Appendices a). </s><s n="s2.10;p17.46">These have a combined average cost of £20.27. </s><s n="s3.10;p17.46">As we are selling a focus differentiated product we believe that we can sell at a premium price. </s><s n="s4.10;p17.46">People will pay more for a universal device as it prevents clutter in the household. </s><s n="s5.10;p17.46">Also due to the product's aesthetics it will stand out in the marketplace. </s><s n="s6.10;p17.46">Hence a recommended retail price of £25.00 is suitable. </s><s n="s7.10;p17.46">As our competition has a strong hold on the market, we will offer a high profit of margin for the retailers. </s><s n="s8.10;p17.46">By setting the wholesale price to £12 we offer a profit to the retailer of £13. </s><s n="s9.10;p17.46">At a cost of £2.80 to manufacture each product we achieve a gross profit of £9.20 per product and gross profit margin of over 76%. </s><s n="s10.10;p17.46">By doing this we can ensure that retailers will find it attractive to sell the Simple Life product over the more established competitor who is offering less return on sales. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">Promotion</head><p n="p18.46"><s n="s1.3;p18.46">For high street sales, we believe that a demonstration video would dramatically increase sales and set our product apart from our competitors. </s><s n="s2.3;p18.46">From this, potential customers will clearly see the benefits of having this multipurpose tool and so the product will sell itself. </s><s n="s3.3;p18.46">Expanding to trade shows such as the "Nursing &amp; Elderly Care" whilst providing samples and additional information, can prove very successful in finding distributors for our products; this method can also reduce our overall costs if distributors agree upon sharing marketing and promotional costs. </s></p><table id="BAWE_0348b-tab.001"><head rend="bold">SWOT Analysis</head><row><cell/></row></table></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">THE MARKET</head><p n="p19.46"><s n="s1.2;p19.46">4.4 million people in the UK have X-ray evidence of moderate to severe arthritis in their hands [1]. </s><s n="s2.2;p19.46">Coupled together with the growing number of sufferers of carpel tunnel syndrome and claw hand, this large customer base is expanding year on year. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0348b-fig.001"><head><hi rend="bold">UK population age trends</hi> Sourced from Nation Statistics Online, Focus: Age over 65. (02/01/2007) [4]</head></figure><p n="p20.46"><s n="s1.4;p20.46">As can be seen from the diagram on page 6, the majority of the people with arthritic conditions are above the age of 55 (78%), with nearly half the market lying over the age of 65 [1]. </s><s n="s2.4;p20.46">The UK population is ageing every year, and it is forecast that the over 65s will account for 23.9% of the UK population by 2031. </s><s n="s3.4;p20.46">Hand in hand with this age increase, will be the rise of age related complaints such as arthritis. </s><s n="s4.4;p20.46">Hence our market will grow as the company moves towards the future. </s></p><div2><head rend="bold">Competitors</head><p n="p21.46"><s n="s1.2;p21.46">The industry consists of only one major manufacturer; Homecraft Roylan. </s><s n="s2.2;p21.46">Therefore the market place is monopolistic; however the barriers to entry are easy to overcome with our unique selling points stated in the product section. </s></p><p n="p22.46"><s n="s1.4;p22.46">Over the past three years, Homecraft Roylan have enjoyed high annual turnover. </s><s n="s2.4;p22.46">The latest figures show a global turnover of £25.6 million and a UK turnover of £18.6 million, with a profit margin of 18.4% [5]. </s><s n="s3.4;p22.46">This shows a healthy market in this industry which we could exploit through our new and exciting product. </s><s n="s4.4;p22.46">This healthy market opportunity is echoed through the number of potential customers. </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">THE TEAM</head><div2><head rend="bold"><name type="other"/></head><p n="p23.46"><s n="s1.4;p23.46">Mr <name type="other"/> is married with two children. </s><s n="s2.4;p23.46">He obtained a First in MEng in Civil Engineering with Business Management (Hons) at the University of <name type="university"/> from 1982-1986. </s><s n="s3.4;p23.46">In the last 3 years of University he set up a company to tutor local GCSE students in Maths. </s><s n="s4.4;p23.46">This was a lucrative decision and the business, 'It All Adds Up!' flourished: when he left there were over 50 tutors and 300 tutees. </s></p><p n="p24.46"><s n="s1.2;p24.46">After graduation he joined the Young Talents Development Scheme at Balfour Beatty. </s><s n="s2.2;p24.46">He worked as a graduate engineer on projects of increasing value and achieved Chartership with the Institution of Mechanical Engineers in 1987. </s></p><p n="p25.46"><s n="s1.2;p25.46">In 1989 he left Balfour Beatty to get some International experience in Nigeria, where he worked on the Federal Ministries Complex (valued at ₦ 18,000 million) with Julius Berger, Nigeria. <name type="other"/> then went on to work as a Design Manager for Carillion Caribbean in Jamaica and Trinidad. </s><s n="s2.2;p25.46">He was in charge of design for the J$700 million renovation of the UWI Jamaica Campus. </s></p><p n="p26.46"><s n="s1.2;p26.46">On his return to the UK in 1995 he progressed to the role of Design Manager for the London region within Skanksa Civils UK. Here, he managed a team of 8 and increased productivity by 15%. </s><s n="s2.2;p26.46">It was during this time that he commenced his Global Executive MBA at TRIUM (a consortium consisting of London School of Economics, New York University Stern School of Business and Hautes Etudes Commerciales School of Management, Paris) for which he received a Distinction. </s></p><p n="p27.46"><s n="s1.1;p27.46">In 2000 he was appointed Technical Director of Skanska Civils UK where he secured a deal with Skanska AB (the Global parent company of Skanska, which operates in Sweden) whereby the Procurement department of Global Skanska companies act as one entity to secure economies of scale and deliver greater purchasing power. </s></p><p n="p28.46"><s n="s1.2;p28.46">In 2005 Mr <name type="other"/> envisaged a product that could greatly simplify the life of a member of his family suffering from arthritis. </s><s n="s2.2;p28.46">He identified a flaw in existing products and saw a niche sector which could be exploited. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold"><name type="other"/></head><p n="p29.46"><s n="s1.3;p29.46">Dr <name type="other"/> achieved a First in MEng in Manufacturing and Mechanical Engineering (Hons) at the University of <name type="university"/> from 1991-1995. </s><s n="s2.3;p29.46">He then went on to work as a Graduate Engineer at Western Thomson Plastics. </s><s n="s3.3;p29.46">He gained experience in Finite Element Analysis, plastic moulding and the design process. </s></p><p n="p30.46"><s n="s1.3;p30.46">In 1998 he became a Research Engineer at Flextronics Medical division where he worked on the collaborative project with Acorn developing a revolutionary Superglide Stairlift. </s><s n="s2.3;p30.46">He was then sponsored to undertake a Research Doctorate (EngD) in 'Re-Engineering the New Product Introduction Process' with the <name type="university"/> Manufacturing Group at the University of <name type="university"/>. </s><s n="s3.3;p30.46">During this time was promoted to become Research Manager of the Acorn-Flextronics Medical collaboration. </s></p><p n="p31.46"><s n="s1.1;p31.46">In 2005 he was approached by Mr <name type="other"/> and became the Technical Director of Simple Life </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">Simple Life</head><p n="p32.46"><s n="s1.5;p32.46"><name type="other"/> met <name type="other"/> at the University of <name type="university"/> whilst Dr <name type="other"/> was undertaking his MEng in Manufacturing and Mechanical Engineering. <name type="other"/> was his professional mentor from 1993 until he left in 1995. </s><s n="s2.5;p32.46">The two formed a close bond: <name type="other"/> found <name type="other"/> to be an extremely intelligent student that thought outside of the box, with a penchant for self improvement. <name type="other"/> found <name type="other"/> to be an excellent mentor that encouraged him to achieve in an effective manner. </s><s n="s3.5;p32.46">They stayed in contact, when <name type="other"/> graduated, <name type="other"/> sent 6 students to do placements in <name type="other"/>'s team from 2001-2005. </s><s n="s4.5;p32.46">Their friendship grew whilst <name type="other"/> was studying for his Research Doctorate. <name type="other"/> was the natural choice for Technical Director of Simple Life. </s><s n="s5.5;p32.46">They anticipate hiring a Marketing Executive in Year 4. </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">PHYSICAL RESOURCES</head><div2><head rend="bold">Storage</head><p n="p33.46"><s n="s1.6;p33.46">The cost of physical spaces depends very much upon the location. </s><s n="s2.6;p33.46">A warehouse situated in Newport with security and 1000 sq. ft of floor space can cost as much as £12,000 to rent per annum, and much more if rented from a more expensive location such as the midlands. </s><s n="s3.6;p33.46">In the first two years there will be no need for external storage, as the products are relatively small. </s><s n="s4.6;p33.46">This low volume of products can easily be stored in the converted garage from which Simple Life operates. </s><s n="s5.6;p33.46">However from year three, with an estimated output of 24,700 units sold more space will be required. </s><s n="s6.6;p33.46">It will then be a necessity to rent a 100 sq meter warehouse, which will cost from £2,400 per year. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">Location</head><p n="p34.46"><s n="s1.2;p34.46">One of the other main factors affecting location is the ease of distribution, for example; by renting space next to main transport routes, delivery to the retailers is a lot easier. </s><s n="s2.2;p34.46">By situating our storage close to a postal depot, the time to send off items to Simple Life customers can be dramatically reduced. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">Manufacturing</head><p n="p35.46"><s n="s1.2;p35.46">Assets such as machinery and factory space will be initially leased but molds will be bought, this is included in the tooling costs. </s><s n="s2.2;p35.46">The chosen manufacturing process will be injection molding; this method promises speed and good finishing with little waste of material. </s></p><p n="p36.46"><s n="s1.5;p36.46">Production units will be around 450 units in the first year, rising to 24700 units in the third year. </s><s n="s2.5;p36.46">Depending on success, more capital may be invested in fixed assets and skilled labour. </s><s n="s3.5;p36.46">With increased production, quality control becomes an important factor. </s><s n="s4.5;p36.46">As production will be a continuous process, random units will be taken out at set intervals to check for faults. </s><s n="s5.5;p36.46">This high level of quality control will ensure that the brand image of Simple Life is upheld. </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">LEGAL STRUCTURE </head><div2><head rend="bold">Sole Trader</head><p n="p37.46"><s n="s1.3;p37.46"><name type="other"/> deemed being a sole trader an unsuitable option for Simple Life. </s><s n="s2.3;p37.46">As a Father and Husband, he regarded the level of risk encompassed with unlimited liability, unsuitable due to the potential of personal bankruptcy through the business. </s><s n="s3.3;p37.46">He also felt that <name type="other"/> had played too great a role in the development of the product to be denied shares and Directorship within the company. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">Partnership</head><p n="p38.46"><s n="s1.2;p38.46">As with sole trading, <name type="other"/> did wish to risk being in a partnership due to the risks of personal bankruptcy to both himself and <name type="other"/>. </s><s n="s2.2;p38.46">Since the assets of one partner may be seized to cover the debt of the business, instead he preferred an option where the company is a separate legal entity from the owners. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">Private Limited Company (Ltd)</head><p n="p39.46"><s n="s1.5;p39.46">Private Limited Companies (Ltds) are a separate legal entity from it's owners; the shareholders. </s><s n="s2.5;p39.46">Financial investment in the company leads to share ownership. </s><s n="s3.5;p39.46">Ltds have limited liability with regards to financial problems. </s><s n="s4.5;p39.46">This means shareholders only stand to lose what they have invested in the company. <name type="other"/> chose this option because it offered the optimum balance between limited liability and significant control. </s><s n="s5.5;p39.46">It also gave a high level of responsibility to <name type="other"/>. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">Public Limited Company (Plc)</head><p n="p40.46"><s n="s1.3;p40.46">Public Limited Companies (Plcs) are the same as Ltds but the shares are available for public purchase on the Stock Exchange. </s><s n="s2.3;p40.46">As Simple Life is a small company, this would be impractical. <name type="other"/> also did not want the possibility of losing control of his personal project to shareholders. </s><s n="s3.3;p40.46">Furthermore publicly declaring the finances of Simple Life was not desirable. </s></p><p n="p41.46"><s n="s1.4;p41.46"><name type="other"/> established Simple Life as a Private Limited Company in 2005. </s><s n="s2.4;p41.46">Currently, he owns 60% of the shares and <name type="other"/> owns 40%. </s><s n="s3.4;p41.46">They are offering the Venture Capitalist 20% for £75,000. </s><s n="s4.4;p41.46">Of the remaining shares 50% will belong to <name type="other"/> and <name type="other"/> will have 30%) </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">EXIT STRATEGY</head><p n="p42.46"><s n="s1.3;p42.46"><name type="other"/> plans to sell the business on in 10 years time; even with a 10% share of the total current market, this would relate to a turnover of £2 million per annum, since the market for disability aids at this present date is worth £18.6 million. </s><s n="s2.3;p42.46">The revenue will be returned to each shareholder in the ratio 20:30:50 to the Venture Capitalist, <name type="other"/> and <name type="other"/> respectively. </s><s n="s3.3;p42.46">This performance would relate to over five fold return on your initial investment. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">FINANCIAL REPORT</head><p n="p43.46"><s n="s1.10;p43.46">At present, Simple Life has £57,000 in savings and family donations. </s><s n="s2.10;p43.46">This is used to cover day to day expenditure. </s><s n="s3.10;p43.46">It is estimated that a further £75,000 investment is required to develop the product. </s><s n="s4.10;p43.46">This will bring assets in the bank to a total of £132,000. </s><s n="s5.10;p43.46">Simple Life anticipates producing 450 units in the first year, with sales reaching 400 units. </s><s n="s6.10;p43.46">Simple life can manufacture these units at £2.80 each. </s><s n="s7.10;p43.46">By selling them at a wholesale price of £12, revenue of £4800 will be generated. </s><s n="s8.10;p43.46">Overhead costs (incorporating factors such as salary, training, research and development, marketing and insurance) will be approximately £56,200. </s><s n="s9.10;p43.46">Therefore the predicted net loss/deficit in the first year would be £52,520. </s><s n="s10.10;p43.46">In a worst case scenario, where only 200 units are sold the net loss would be £58160. </s></p><p n="p44.46"><s n="s1.8;p44.46">In the second year Simple Life forecasts sales of 7,000 units. </s><s n="s2.8;p44.46">This would give £84,000 revenue and a gross profit of £4,520. </s><s n="s3.8;p44.46">It is anticipated that sales will peak in winter when the cold exacerbates mobility disabilities. </s><s n="s4.8;p44.46">The second fiscal year will prove extremely challenging as Simple Life has set a target of achieving profit by this year. </s><s n="s5.8;p44.46">Prudence must be exercised to achieve this, as it is anticipated that Simple Life will have £2,200 debt: £500 of which is in receivable accounts. </s><s n="s6.8;p44.46">It is not guaranteed that customers will pay the debt owed to Simple Life. </s><s n="s7.8;p44.46">The receivable accounts figure will increase to £1,500 at the end of the third year. </s><s n="s8.8;p44.46">Stringent credit checks will be used to counter this and use of a collection agency will minimize the risk from bad debtors. </s></p><p n="p45.46"><s n="s1.4;p45.46">At the end of the second year Simple Life will have approximately 1,050 units in storage. </s><s n="s2.4;p45.46">Sales are expected to rise to 24,700 units in year three: this will increase variable costs and overheads as the rate of manufacture will increase to 26,000 units a year. </s><s n="s3.4;p45.46">With increased investment in research and development, this will bring overheads up to £138,082. </s><s n="s4.4;p45.46">However, with forecast sales Simple Life will generate a profit of £89,157. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0348b-fig.002"><head>Three year profit forecast</head></figure></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">SUMMARY</head><p n="p46.46"><s n="s1.6;p46.46">Simple life prides itself on quality innovation, with the hope of "aiding people through technology." </s><s n="s2.6;p46.46">Our mentality and focussed ingenuity will make this business a success. </s><s n="s3.6;p46.46">A modest outlook has been adopted for the creation of our three year projections. </s><s n="s4.6;p46.46">From the great selling points that our product has above the leading competitors, sales could easily surpass our initial predictions. </s><s n="s5.6;p46.46">We see a world in which arthritis, claw hand, carpel tunnel syndrome and other hand affecting ailments will no longer inhibit the day to day living of its sufferers. </s><s n="s6.6;p46.46">The Simple Life tool will provide this solution. </s></p></div1></body><back><div1 type="appendix"><head rend="bold">APPENDICES</head><p/></div1><div1 type="bibliography"><head rend="bold">REFERENCES</head><p>[1] Arthritis Research Campaign, data sourced from: </p><p><seg type="URL" n="http://www.arc.org.uk/about_arth/astats.htm"/></p><p>[2] Mintel, Leisure on the Internet - UK - June 2004 <seg type="URL" n="http://academic.mintel.com/sinatra/academic/search_results/show&amp;&amp;type=RCItem&amp;page=0&amp;noaccess_page=0/display/id=68202/display/id=106402&amp;section#hit1"/></p><p>[3] Mintel, Home Shopping - UK - March 2005</p><p><seg type="URL" n="http://academic.mintel.com/sinatra/academic/search_results/show&amp;&amp;type=RCItem&amp;page=0&amp;noaccess_page=0/display/id=114744"/></p><p>[4] National Statistics, Age structure for 2031: population projections, Government Actuary's Department</p><p><seg type="URL" n="http://www.statistics.gov.uk/cci/nugget.asp?id=1308"/></p><p>[5] Fame Database</p></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
