<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_0348d" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Midlands Metro Report</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">deleted: header: student name, module number, assignment title; footer: page numbers</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">1</p><p n="date">2006-01</p><p n="module title">Economics and Structure of Industry</p><p n="module code">ES175</p><p n="genre family">Case study</p><p n="discipline">Engineering</p><p n="disciplinary group">PS</p><p n="grade">D</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">1207</p><p n="number of s-units">46</p><p n="number of p">11</p><p n="number of tables">1</p><p n="number of figures">1</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">0</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">0</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">26.2</p><p n="average s-units per p">4.2</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">f</p><p n="year of birth">1986</p><p n="first language">English</p><p n="education">UKA</p><p n="course">Civil Engineering</p><p n="student ID">0348</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><docTitle><titlePart rend="underlined">Midlands Metro Report</titlePart></docTitle></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined">Introduction </head><p n="p1.11"><s n="s1.4;p1.11">Midlands Metro is a public transportation business that was created by Centro; the West Midlands Passenger Transport Authority (a Government organisation) to ease congestion and transport issues within the UK's biggest conurbation outside of London, the West Midlands. </s><s n="s2.4;p1.11">Altram have a 23 year contract to maintain Midlands Metro. </s><s n="s3.4;p1.11">Midlands Metro provides a light rail tram (hereafter referred to as LRT) service from Wolverhampton City Centre to Birmingham City Centre (stopping at 21 other locations along the way). </s><s n="s4.4;p1.11">In this report the transport industry in the UK specifically refers to buses, trains and LRTs; modes of transport which can be deemed to be comparable to the service Midlands Metro provides on either a local or national level. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined">Structure of the transport industry in the UK </head><p n="p2.11"><s n="s1.2;p2.11">119 businesses are large companies with the SIC code (Standard Industry Classification code) 6010, transport via railways. </s><s n="s2.2;p2.11">(FAME, 2006a) </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0348d-fig.001"><head>Graph 1 (FAME, 2006j) Companies in the peer group 1. Rail Europe Limited 2. Rail Express Systems LMI 3. Northern Belle Limited 4. Metronet TMU Limited 5.Altram LRT Limited 6. Freight Europe (UK) Limited 7. GE Capital Rail Services 8.Island Line Limited 9. Inter-Capital and Regional Rail Limited 10. North York Moors Historic Limited 11. Travelex UK Limited</head></figure><p n="p3.11"><s n="s1.1;p3.11">Graph 1 shows figures indicating that the rail industry can have a broad array of profitability. </s></p><p n="p4.11"><s n="s1.3;p4.11">When considered against 11 of its peers (that share the same SIC code), Altram LRT possess 9.73% market share (by turnover) of a market valued at £57,000,000 (FAME, 2006b). </s><s n="s2.3;p4.11">In the locality Midlands Metro is competing with medium sized bus companies such as Arriva Midland North and the Birmingham Coach Company (which have averaged profit before tax levels of £100,000 and £55,000,000 respectively over the past 3 years) (FAME 2006c). </s><s n="s3.3;p4.11">LRTs do not generally make this level of profit. </s></p><table id="BAWE_0348d-tab.001"><head>Table 1 (Centro, 2000a)</head><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p5.11"><s n="s1.1;p5.11">Table 1 documents a PEST analysis undertaken by Centro in evaluating the trends of the local market and outlining their 20 year strategy. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined">Typical conduct of the firms in the transport industry in the UK</head><p n="p6.11"><s n="s1.8;p6.11">The transport industry within the UK bears many of the hallmarks of an oligopoly. </s><s n="s2.8;p6.11">The barriers to entry within the transport industry are high due to the large initial out lay required. </s><s n="s3.8;p6.11">For example, in the construction of South Yorkshire Supertram, a comparable light rail tram system, the initial costs were £8.3million/km. </s><s n="s4.8;p6.11">(United Kingdom Parliament, 2000). </s><s n="s5.8;p6.11">Even this is an order of magnitude less than the cost of railway lines for trains. </s><s n="s6.8;p6.11">There are also a large number of well established firms on a more local level (in the Shires and London this would include Arriva, Greenline and Stagecoach buses). </s><s n="s7.8;p6.11">Government legislation is also a deterrent to new entrants as acquiring planning approval is often a lengthy and difficult process. </s><s n="s8.8;p6.11">(In fact, Midlands Metro's plans for the new lines, Line 2 and Line 3 could not be carried out because land acquisition powers ceased when the government could not fund the Lines.) </s></p><p n="p7.11"><s n="s1.4;p7.11">The only factor in which the transport industry may not be considered an oligopoly is the fact that a large number of companies operate within it (776 companies also have SIC code 6010) (FAME, 2006d). </s><s n="s2.4;p7.11">However, considered locally this may generally be scaled down to an oligopoly. </s><s n="s3.4;p7.11">In the West Midlands public transport is dominated by buses: they represent over 95% of all journeys made in the conurbation. </s><s n="s4.4;p7.11">Travel West Midlands has 80% of the market share for buses (Centro, 2000b). </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined">Performance of the transport industry in the UK</head><p n="p8.11"><s n="s1.6;p8.11">The transport industry as a whole experiences some price elasticity of demand, however income elasticity of demand is low (given that the costs of public transport is affordable for most consumers). </s><s n="s2.6;p8.11">Half of the top 10 companies (by turnover) with SIC code 6010 (Transport via railways) each reported losses in excess of £93,000 in the past year (FAME, 2006e). </s><s n="s3.6;p8.11">LRTs specifically are in the question mark stage of the BCG (Boston Consultancy Group) matrix. </s><s n="s4.6;p8.11">However, this looks set to improve (and possibly become a rising star) in the future. </s><s n="s5.6;p8.11">This can in part be attributed to it's high efficiency. </s><s n="s6.6;p8.11">LRTs combine high capacity and speed with comparatively low damage to the environment and local inhabitants. </s></p><p n="p9.11"><s n="s1.5;p9.11">The core competencies of Midland Metro are its lack of disturbance to the locality (compared with trains), high efficiency and favourable perception amongst customers. </s><s n="s2.5;p9.11">Concentration measures are of little relevance to Midlands Metro because the company is not in competition with similar companies in differing regions. </s><s n="s3.5;p9.11">The transport industry is comparable with the construction industry in that it is a large industry, it (generally) requires considerable initial outlay and the government plays an important role in its development. </s><s n="s4.5;p9.11">They are also similarly populous as FAME (2006f) reports that 64,700 companies are in the construction industry (as SIC code 4521, general construction of buildings and Civil Engineering works) and 55,204 companies are in the transport industry. </s><s n="s5.5;p9.11">However the transport industry is more labour intensive, with £12,700,000 as the average total assets for the top 10 firms which is nearly 200% of the equivalent figure for the construction industry (FAME, 2006g). </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined">The most viable strategy for a new entrant in the UK </head><p n="p10.11"><s n="s1.4;p10.11">Public transport, (and notably buses- the most frequently employed mode of transport in the conurbation) are considered to be of poor quality in this region, so focusing on good customer service, frequent and punctual tram services and brand recognition will give an LRT company operating in this locality a competitive advantage. </s><s n="s2.4;p10.11">It is suggested that the best method of entry into this market is to use a focus differentiation approach. </s><s n="s3.4;p10.11">Considering the fact that there is a gap in the market for higher quality transport in the conurbation it is likely that if an LRT company in the locality was to provide a high quality mode of transport then high profit levels could be attained. </s><s n="s4.4;p10.11">This method was employed by Virgin Trains, a company which over the past 4 years has achieved an average of £28,500 profit before tax and unusually high return on capital employed (for the transport industry) of 24% (FAME, 2006h). </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined">Recommendation</head><p n="p11.11"><s n="s1.8;p11.11">The barriers to entry within this industry and locality are great. </s><s n="s2.8;p11.11">In order to overcome the considerable barriers to entry purchasing Midlands Metro is commended as the most feasible method for success. </s><s n="s3.8;p11.11">Profit before taxation figures have been negative and ranging from (£987) to (£11,440) over the years 1999 to 2004 (FAME, 2006i). </s><s n="s4.8;p11.11">Exit barriers are significant which maybe a factor in deciding to continue to run Midlands Metro, despite the fact that it is operating at a loss. </s><s n="s5.8;p11.11">As the current strategy of Midlands Metro is not proving financially beneficial Travel West Midlands may be willing to sell the business at a low cost. </s><s n="s6.8;p11.11">Adopting Michael Porter's generic strategy of focus differentiation will help to recoup the initial outlay more quickly, and help to ensure that profit maximisation occurs as soon as feasibly possible. </s><s n="s7.8;p11.11">Midlands Metro, under the guidance of new leadership can also take advantage of any brand loyalty felt towards the company. </s><s n="s8.8;p11.11">The ensuing renovations and improvements will help attract new customers whilst retaining the old name will help to ensure existing customers do not feel resistance to change. </s></p></div1></body><back><div1 type="bibliography"><head rend="underlined">Bibliography</head><p>CENTRO (2003) 20 Year Public Transport Strategy [Online]. Available from <seg type="URL" n="http://www.centro.org.uk/source/CorpInfo/Corporate/20%20Year%20Stategy%20Main.pdf"/> </p><p>a [Accessed 04/01/06]</p><p>b [Accessed 04/01/06]</p><p>FAME (2006) e-database [Online]. Available from <seg type="URL" n="https://fame.bvdep.com"/> </p><p>a [Accessed 07/01/06]</p><p>b [Accessed 07/01/06]</p><p>c [Accessed 07/01/06]</p><p>d [Accessed 09/01/06]</p><p>e [Accessed 08/01/06]</p><p>f [Accessed 06/01/06]</p><p>g [Accessed 04/01/06]</p><p>h [Accessed 06/01/06]</p><p>i [Accessed 08/01/06]</p><p>j [Accessed 10/01/06]</p><p>UNITED KINGDOM PARLIAMENT (1999) Memorandum [Online]. Available from <seg type="URL" n="http://www.parliament.the-stationery-office.co.uk/pa/cm199900/cmselect/cmenvtra/153/153ap27.htm"/></p><p> [Accessed 10<hi rend="sup">th</hi> January 2006]</p><p>This bibliography has been compiled using the Harvard Referencing System based on British Standards 1629:1989 and 5605:1990.</p></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
