<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_0348a" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>"Trade Magazine Article: Case Study: British Midlands 737 Airplane Crash, Kegworth, East Midlands 1989 Kegworth Air Disaster"</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">Language used in quote: <foreign id="English">English</foreign></note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">deleted: header: university and department; footer: page numbers</note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">two columns</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">2</p><p n="date">2006-11</p><p n="module title">Forensic Engineeing</p><p n="module code">ES2A5</p><p n="genre family">Case study</p><p n="discipline">Engineering</p><p n="disciplinary group">PS</p><p n="grade">D</p><p n="number of authors">4</p><p n="number of words">1847</p><p n="number of s-units">82</p><p n="number of p">20</p><p n="number of tables">1</p><p n="number of figures">1</p><p n="number of block quotes">1</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">0</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">8</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">22.5</p><p n="average s-units per p">4.1</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">f</p><p n="year of birth">1986</p><p n="first language">English</p><p n="education">UKA</p><p n="course">Civil Engineering</p><p n="student ID">0348</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><titlePart><hi rend="bold">ES2A5 Forensic Engineering: Learning from Failure First Part to the Assessment Portfolio - Trade Magazine Article</hi> Team BE: <name type="student name"/>; <name type="student name"/>; <name type="student name"/>; <name type="student name"/></titlePart><docTitle><titlePart rend="bold">Case Study: British Midlands 737 Airplane Crash, Kegworth, East Midlands 1989 Kegworth Air Disaster</titlePart></docTitle></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="section"><p n="p1.20"><s n="s1.5;p1.20">On the evening of January 8 <hi rend="sup">th</hi> 1989 the British Midland Airlines Flight 92, a Boeing 737-400 plane took off from Heathrow on its scheduled flight to Belfast. </s><s n="s2.5;p1.20">It had already made the round trip to Belfast once that day but, on this flight, when reaching 28,300 feet one of the fan blade panels was ripped off, having suffered a fatigue failure. </s><s n="s3.5;p1.20">This was the starting point of the Kegworth disaster which went on to claim the lives of 47 passengers. </s><s n="s4.5;p1.20">The aeroplane crashed into the M1 motorway just short of East Midlands airport to which it has been redirected. </s><s n="s5.5;p1.20">However the accident could have been avoided and it was partly due to the actions of the flight crew that the crash occurred. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Engine deficiencies</head><p n="p2.20"><s n="s1.5;p2.20">The engines which powered the Boeing 737-400 aeroplane were designed especially for it, and were a variant of the type CFM56 engines which powered the majority of the commercial airliners at that time (and still do now). </s><s n="s2.5;p2.20">The engines were all fully certified and tested using the current techniques of the day. </s><s n="s3.5;p2.20">However these techniques did not accurately depict the conditions the engine fans would undergo; certain non-synchronous and low amplitude vibrations were not picked up on as cause for concern, but it was these vibrations which lead to the fatigue failure of the engines. </s><s n="s4.5;p2.20">Flight 92 was not the only aeroplane to suffer a fatigue failure to one of its CFM56 engines. </s><s n="s5.5;p2.20">There were two other incidents that occurred in June of that year which lead to the grounding of the 737-400 fleet while inspections took place. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0348a-fig.001"><head>Figure. 1 (ref. <seg type="URL" n="http://experts.about.com/e/k/ke/kegworth_air_disaster.htm"/>)</head></figure></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Problem wrongly diagnosed</head><p n="p3.20"><s n="s1.7;p3.20">The critical factor for the crash was that while the failure occurred to the plane's left (No. </s><s n="s2.7;p3.20">1) engine it was the No. </s><s n="s3.7;p3.20">2 engine which the flight crew diagnosed as being the faulty engine. </s><s n="s4.7;p3.20">The fatigue failure to the No.1 engine caused heavy vibrations. </s><s n="s5.7;p3.20">It also caused flames to emerge from the rear of the No. </s><s n="s6.7;p3.20">1 engine which a number of passengers and also flight attendants noticed, <hi rend="italic">yet the flight crew were not told</hi>. </s><s n="s7.7;p3.20">There have been a number of reasons suggested as to why the wrong engine was diagnosed as having failed which all combine to give the true picture. </s></p><p n="p4.20"><s n="s1.14;p4.20">Figure 1 depicts the discourse between the pilots at different stages of the incident. </s><s n="s2.14;p4.20">It was the First Officer (co-pilot) who, on being asked by the pilot which engine was responsible, replied 'It's the le... it's the right one'. </s><s n="s3.14;p4.20">From subsequent examination it appears that part of the reason may have been due to the smell of smoke that arose in the cockpit. </s><s n="s4.14;p4.20">On the previous 737-300 aircraft, it was solely the No.2 engine that delivered air through the ventilation system, whereas in the adapted 737-400 aircraft the air was channelled from both engines. </s><s n="s5.14;p4.20">It could be argued that the flight crew had too little experience to be aware of differences like these since they only had one days training on the differences of the 400 series compared with the previous 300 model. </s><s n="s6.14;p4.20">Also the layout of the dials was such that the critical vibration sensors for both engines appeared over the right lever for the No. </s><s n="s7.14;p4.20">2 engine (see Figure 2). </s><s n="s8.14;p4.20">Under such stressed circumstances the First Officer may have mistakenly assumed that it was the No. </s><s n="s9.14;p4.20">2 engine where the problem lay rather than with the No. </s><s n="s10.14;p4.20">1 engine. </s><s n="s11.14;p4.20">These original assumptions were then seemingly confirmed when cutting power to the No. </s><s n="s12.14;p4.20">2 engine seemed to solve the heavy vibrations within the plane though this was merely by chance. </s><s n="s13.14;p4.20">However the vibration indicator for the No. </s><s n="s14.14;p4.20">1 engine was at the maximum level some time after the initial incident but this went unnoticed by the pilots who it was later found did not trust these instruments because they were used to previous model of aeroplane which had less reliable instrumentation. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0348a-pic.001"><head>Figure 2 (ref. "The Blame Machine - Why Human Error Causes Accidents", R. B. Whittingham</head></figure></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">=Lack of communication</head><p n="p5.20"><s n="s1.6;p5.20">Flight 92 was then diverted to East Midlands airport by air traffic control staff who were alerted to the flight's status. </s><s n="s2.6;p5.20">Whilst concentrating on carrying out these instructions the flight crew were distracted from checking the initial assumption that they had made. </s><s n="s3.6;p5.20">Interestingly, no information was passed from the rest of the cabin crew or passengers about the flames from No. </s><s n="s4.6;p5.20">1 engine. </s><s n="s5.6;p5.20">They all just assumed that the pilots had everything under control and were aware of all the information. </s><s n="s6.6;p5.20">This could be seen as a failure resulting from 'aviation hierarchy' where the elevated authority position of the pilot or co-pilot discourages others from sharing information with them. </s></p><p n="p6.20"><s rend="bold" n="s1.1;p6.20">Crash landing </s></p><p n="p7.20"><s n="s1.7;p7.20">Unaware of this extra information, the pilot and First Officer prepared to land. </s><s n="s2.7;p7.20">However, this required more power from the No. </s><s n="s3.7;p7.20">2 engine than was available, and as more fuel was pumped into the damaged engine a catastrophic failure was suffered and the engine burst into flames. </s><s n="s4.7;p7.20">The pilot tried to restart the No. </s><s n="s5.7;p7.20">1 engine but the there was insufficient time for this and the aeroplane was flying too slowly. </s><s n="s6.7;p7.20">By tilting the nose of the plane upwards the pilot was able to miss the village of Kegworth, but the tail impacted with the ground just short of the motorway. </s><s n="s7.7;p7.20">This made the plane bounce back up into the air, before it landed on the opposite embankment of the motorway and broke into pieces. </s></p><p n="p8.20"><s n="s1.3;p8.20">Historically this failure in communication has caused a number of disasters, including the aeroplane related incident with the most loss of life. </s><s n="s2.3;p8.20">This occurred at Las Palmas airport in 1977, where the First Officer was reluctant to question the pilot due to his senior position and so did not prevent him from initiating take-off without the proper clearance. </s><s n="s3.3;p8.20">Under thick fog conditions this caused the plane to crash straight into the back of another aeroplane on the runway. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Media reaction</head><quote lang="English">A man called Graham Pearson was the first civilian on the scene. He was driving down the M1 when the disaster occurred. Mr Pearson rose to the challenge and heroically spent over 3 hours amidst the remains of the plane, helping to rescue people. He dedicated particular efforts to helping a wounded mother and her child. Mr Pearson had previously spent 9 years in the Marines and was working as a kitchen salesperson. After this incident he claimed to have suffered with "feelings of guilt, loss of interest in life and lack of concentration". There were lasting problems as, consequently, he lost his job, suffered marital problems and spent time in hospital. He was diagnosed with post traumatic stress disorder. After spending 9 years in a legal battle, Mr Pearson won £57,000 in damages in 1998. He commented: "I feel very relieved. The legal process has taken nine years and every solicitor's letter, every contact with the defendants reminded me of the plane crash." (ref. BBC News website <seg type="URL" n="http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/uk/54915.stm"/>) Monday, February 9, 1998</quote><p n="p9.20"><s n="s1.6;p9.20">The media of the time somewhat sensationalised the incident. </s><s n="s2.6;p9.20">For example, 'The Observer' (a reputable newspaper renowned for it's realistic reporting style) reported on the 15 <hi rend="sup">th</hi> January following the event that Boeing employees 'blamed excessive overtime, untrained workers and low morale for poor work'. </s><s n="s3.6;p9.20">This contrasts with the official Air Accident Investigation Branch (AAIB) report that states (Section 3. </s><s n="s4.6;p9.20">Conclusion a] Findings 2.) 'The flight deck crew were properly licensed and rested to undertake the flight.' </s><s n="s5.6;p9.20">Such a stance is, however, not surprising in light of the fact that 47 fatalities occurred. </s><s n="s6.6;p9.20">Furthermore newspapers are kept in business by exaggerating stories in order to attract readers by means of eye-catching headlines. </s></p><p n="p10.20"><s n="s1.5;p10.20">The media initially hailed the pilot and co-pilot as heroes. </s><s n="s2.5;p10.20">The 12 <hi rend="sup">th</hi> January 1989 edition of 'The Independent' had a headline that read 'Captain and Co-Pilot are Popular and Respected' and contained a quote (from the Chief Executive of Operations and Chief Pilot of Loganair) saying that Captain McClelland was '"very likeable... (and) very mature. </s><s n="s3.5;p10.20">There was no question at all about his great skill as a pilot."' The media later adopted a stance whereby the pilots were blamed for the accident, although the reasons were more complicated. </s><s n="s4.5;p10.20">The 19 <hi rend="sup">th</hi> October 1990 edition of The Guardian says '"The blame for the accident was yesterday put squarely on the shoulders of the two pilots as the <hi rend="italic">enormity</hi> of their <hi rend="italic">fatal mistakes</hi> became clear."' (The emphasis is ours.) </s><s n="s5.5;p10.20">The need for the public and the media to find a scapegoat The pilots were dismissed after the official AAIB report was published. </s></p><p n="p11.20"><s n="s1.1;p11.20">The emergency services were faced with a number of major problems as a result of the air-crash </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p12.20"><s n="s1.1;p12.20">As the plane came down on a major motor way- The M1, They had to deal with the congestion that ensued </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p13.20"><s n="s1.1;p13.20">There was a large number of survivors who were badly injured and required urgent medical attention </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p14.20"><s n="s1.1;p14.20">There was the risk of fire, because the plane was refuelled for its flight to Belfast, but aborted on route, So it came down with about 4,210 kg of fuel in its tank, which though not breached, still represented a substantial risk to the rescuers and survivors. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Report recommendations</head><p n="p15.20"><s n="s1.3;p15.20">The AAIB report made 31 recommendations based on its findings to improve safety and prevent this type of incident from occurring again. </s><s n="s2.3;p15.20">Many of these were implemented soon after the report was published and in general it had a large effect on the aviation industry as a whole. </s><s n="s3.3;p15.20">A large number of the recommendations proposed enhanced training for flight crews and more frequent safety checks of the planes but other examples of recommendations included: </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p16.20"><s n="s1.3;p16.20">Using Closed Circuit Television (CCTV) systems so flight crew members can monitor internal and external parts of the plane. </s><s rend="bold italic" n="s2.3;p16.20">Currently the FLIGHTVU system is used in over 160 different aircrafts and enables them to gain instant visual information from installed cameras. </s><s rend="bold" n="s3.3;p16.20"> </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p17.20"><s n="s1.3;p17.20">For the engine instrumentation system (EIS) to include a way of getting a pilot's attention when a vibration indicator indicates maximum vibration. </s><s rend="bold italic" n="s2.3;p17.20">Now the case by alterations to the dial layout and LCDs included to give clearer read-outs to pilots. </s><s rend="bold" n="s3.3;p17.20"> </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p18.20"><s n="s1.3;p18.20">That engine-testing should be done more rigorously with more accurate models closer to true flying conditions. </s><s rend="bold italic" n="s2.3;p18.20">Now also in effect. </s><s rend="bold" n="s3.3;p18.20"> </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p19.20"><s n="s1.4;p19.20">To implement as quickly as possible research into passenger seat design particularly into effective upper torso restraint and aft-facing passenger seats. </s><s rend="bold italic" n="s2.4;p19.20">This has contributed to a global thirst for passenger seat development and there have been major technological improvements since then in seat design. </s><s rend="bold italic" n="s3.4;p19.20">Seating is now also positioned strategically to minimise risk. </s><s rend="bold" n="s4.4;p19.20"> </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p20.20"><s n="s1.3;p20.20">To require all infants and young children who are not safely restrained by lap belts to be placed in child seats for take-off, landing and in-flight turbulence. </s><s rend="bold italic" n="s2.3;p20.20">Now a common aspect of most aircraft for a child restraint system (CRS) to be used to protect children of certain weights during the most dangerous times of flight. </s><s rend="bold" n="s3.3;p20.20"> </s></p><table id="BAWE_0348a-tab.001"><head>Figure. 4 The 7Cs of Crisis Management and the Kegworth Accident (ref. "The Kegworth Air Crash: A Crisis in Three Phases?", Smith, D. (1992), <hi rend="italic">Disaster Management</hi> , Vol. 4 No.2, pp.63-72.)</head><row><cell/></row></table></div1></body><back/></text></TEI.2>
