<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_0348e" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Dimnsional Analysis Report</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">The document has a title page which contains:
document title
title part</note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">deleted: date, page numbers</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">1</p><p n="date">2006-02</p><p n="module title">Technological Science I</p><p n="module code">ES180</p><p n="genre family">Methodology recount</p><p n="discipline">Engineering</p><p n="disciplinary group">PS</p><p n="grade">M</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">794</p><p n="number of s-units">52</p><p n="number of p">20</p><p n="number of tables">1</p><p n="number of figures">2</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">4</p><p n="number of lists">0</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">3</p><p n="abstract present">abstract present</p><p n="average words per s-unit">15.3</p><p n="average s-units per p">2.6</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">f</p><p n="year of birth">1986</p><p n="first language">English</p><p n="education">UKA</p><p n="course">Civil Engineering</p><p n="student ID">0348</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><titlePart rend="bold">University of <name type="university"/> School of Engineering</titlePart><docTitle><titlePart rend="bold">Dimensional Analysis Report</titlePart></docTitle><titlePart rend="bold">by<name type="student ID"/></titlePart><titlePart>Report Reference Code: ES180A7 Affiliation: Year 1 Civil Engineering Report of laboratory performed on: 27/01/2006</titlePart></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="abstract"><head rend="bold">Summary</head><p n="p1.20"><s n="s1.6;p1.20">For the ES180 Technological Science module it is a requirement that the Dimensional Analysis laboratory is carried out. </s><s n="s2.6;p1.20">This laboratory is concerned with fluid mechanics, and more specifically analysis of fluid flow in a V-notch weir. </s><s n="s3.6;p1.20">Dimensional analysis is a necessary requisite because of the complex nature of fluid flow. </s><s n="s4.6;p1.20">The objective of this report is to show that <hi rend="bold">Eq.</hi> </s><s n="s5.6;p1.20"><hi rend="bold">1 </hi><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0348e-form.001"/> where Q= volumetric flow rate in m <hi rend="sup">3</hi>s <hi rend="sup">-1</hi>, and h=the depth of fluid over the V-notch. </s><s n="s6.6;p1.20">This being done by using a V-notch weir layout (outlined in the report). </s></p></div1><div1 type="front-back-matter"><head rend="bold">Table of Contents</head><p/></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Introduction</head><p n="p2.20"><s n="s1.2;p2.20">This laboratory was designed to test derived formula for flow rate empirically: its objective is to assess the accuracy of the formula, Eq. </s><s n="s2.2;p2.20">1 via empirical means. </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p3.20"><s rend="bold" n="s1.2;p3.20">Eq. </s><s n="s2.2;p3.20"><hi rend="bold">1 </hi><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0348e-form.002"/> </s></p><p n="p4.20"><s n="s1.3;p4.20">(where Q= volumetric flow rate in m <hi rend="sup">3</hi>s <hi rend="sup">-1</hi>, and h=the depth of fluid over the V-notch.) </s><s n="s2.3;p4.20">Substituting k=<hi rend="sup">5</hi>/<hi rend="sub">2</hi> gives Eq. </s><s n="s3.3;p4.20">2. </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p5.20"><s rend="bold" n="s1.2;p5.20">Eq. </s><s n="s2.2;p5.20"><hi rend="bold">2 </hi><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0348e-form.003"/> </s></p><p n="p6.20"><s n="s1.1;p6.20">Taking logarithms will lead to Eq.3 </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p7.20"><s n="s1.1;p7.20"><hi rend="bold">Eq.3 </hi><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0348e-form.004"/> </s></p><p n="p8.20"><s n="s1.4;p8.20">Therefore, if Eq. </s><s n="s2.4;p8.20">1 is correct then the gradient of a graph depicting Eq. </s><s n="s3.4;p8.20">3 will have a gradient, <hi rend="italic">k</hi>, of <hi rend="sup">5</hi>/<hi rend="sub">2</hi>. </s><s n="s4.4;p8.20">This report will determine a value of <hi rend="italic">k</hi>. </s></p><p n="p9.20"><s n="s1.2;p9.20">The theoretical implications impact upon the design of dams and weirs. </s><s n="s2.2;p9.20">The V-notch method of determining flow rate was used because it is accurate and simple, leaving little room for human error in carrying it out. </s></p><p n="p10.20"><s n="s1.1;p10.20">After completion of the practical laboratory it was concluded that the value of <hi rend="italic">k</hi> calculated in this laboratory, 1.14, was incorrect due to inaccuracies in taking down the results. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Theory</head><p n="p11.20"><s n="s1.5;p11.20">Eq. </s><s n="s2.5;p11.20">1 was derived from application of dimensional analysis and the Buckingham Π theorem, following the process set out in pages 8 to the end of Appendix 1. </s><s n="s3.5;p11.20">The Buckingham Π theorem is key in dimensional analysis. </s><s n="s4.5;p11.20">It states that if there is 'a physically meaningful equation involving a certain number, <hi rend="italic">n</hi>, of physical variables, and these variables are expressible in terms of <hi rend="italic">k</hi> independent fundamental physical quantities, then the original expression is equivalent to an equation involving a set of <hi rend="italic">p</hi> = <hi rend="italic">n </hi>−<hi rend="italic">k</hi> dimensionless variables constructed from the original variables. </s><s n="s5.5;p11.20">For the purposes of the experimenter, different systems which share the same description in terms of these dimensionless numbers are equivalent.'<hi rend="sup">1</hi> </s></p><p n="p12.20"><s n="s1.1;p12.20">In this experiment the relevant dimensions were length, time and mass. </s></p><p n="p13.20"><s n="s1.1;p13.20"><hi rend="sup">1</hi><seg type="URL" n="www.en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Buckingham_Pi_theorem"/> 13/02/06 </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">3.0 Apparatus and Methods</head><figure id="BAWE_0348e-pic.001"><head><hi rend="bold">Fig. 1</hi> Layout of the apparatus </head></figure><figure id="BAWE_0348e-pic.002"><head><hi rend="bold">Fig. 2</hi> Schematic of the apparatus</head></figure><p n="p14.20"><s n="s1.5;p14.20">Fig. </s><s n="s2.5;p14.20">1 is a picture of the equipment used and Fig.2 is a schematic of the apparatus. </s><s n="s3.5;p14.20">Initially the pump was turned off so that new fluid flowed and there was a state of equilibrium whereby the water in the tank was still and at a level just below the V-notch. </s><s n="s4.5;p14.20">At this point the scale (on the side of the blue tank) was set to zero by moving the submerged hook to the same height as the water. </s><s n="s5.5;p14.20">This set a reference point for height difference, <hi rend="italic">h</hi>: it was then measured relative to this zero point. </s></p><p n="p15.20"><s n="s1.3;p15.20">The pump was then switched on and water flowed at a rate determined by the how far the valve was opened. </s><s n="s2.3;p15.20">This discharge rate, <hi rend="italic">Q</hi>, was calculated by equating the height difference in the 2 manometers to the corresponding value for <hi rend="italic">Q</hi> on a graph. </s><s n="s3.3;p15.20">5 readings were taken. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">4.0 Observations and Results</head><table id="BAWE_0348e-tab.001"><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p16.20"><s n="s1.1;p16.20">The manometer reading and <hi rend="italic">h</hi> were calculated by a manometer and gauge (respectively) which had a minimum 0.001m division so the above figures have an accuracy of ±0.0005m. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">5.0 Analysis and Discussion of Results</head><p n="p17.20"><s n="s1.4;p17.20">The graph produced by the results has a gradient of 1.14, which is not close to the expected value of 2.5. </s><s n="s2.4;p17.20">From the graph it is evident that the gradient is closer to 2.5 at the beginning of the experiment. </s><s n="s3.4;p17.20">This enforces my belief that the inaccuracies arise because the readings taken were averaged over a period of time and not instantaneous as the readings diverge more from the expected gradient as the flow rate increases. </s><s n="s4.4;p17.20">These inaccuracies render the results as a whole not especially useful, but the earlier results are more indicative of what one would expect. </s></p><p n="p18.20"><s n="s1.2;p18.20">In the class results were varied, however some came closer to the expected results. </s><s n="s2.2;p18.20">This could be because other groups used a slower flow rate. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">6.0 Recommendations</head><p n="p19.20"><s n="s1.1;p19.20">In order to improve the reliability of these results a high resolution, low shutter speed camera could be used to ensure that results are instantaneous, rather than averaged over a period of time. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">7.0 Conclusions</head><p n="p20.20"><s n="s1.5;p20.20">The results are not sufficiently good to lend weight to Eq. </s><s n="s2.5;p20.20">1. </s><s n="s3.5;p20.20">However the analysis supporting Eq. </s><s n="s4.5;p20.20">1 is rigorous and it seems that errors in the results can be attributed to human fault rather than flaws with Eq. </s><s n="s5.5;p20.20">1. </s></p></div1></body><back><div1 type="bibliography"><head rend="bold">8.0 References</head><p><hi rend="sup">1</hi><seg type="URL" n="www.en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Buckingham_Pi_theorem"/> accessed 13/02/06</p></div1><div1 type="appendix"><head rend="bold">Appendix 1</head><p/></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
