<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_0353d" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Post Module Assignment</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">deleted: header: page numbers</note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">deleted: cover sheet including lengthy rubric</note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">Evaluated as candidate compound assignment. Assigned to Assigned to S1a: collection of essays/discussions: compound.</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">4</p><p n="date">2007-01</p><p n="module title">Information and Communication Technologies</p><p n="module code">ES915</p><p n="genre family">Design specification</p><p n="discipline">Engineering</p><p n="disciplinary group">PS</p><p n="grade">M</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">4151</p><p n="number of s-units">198</p><p n="number of p">94</p><p n="number of tables">1</p><p n="number of figures">6</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">4</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">38</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">21.0</p><p n="average s-units per p">2.1</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">compound assignment consisting of 2 parts (see notesStmt for details)</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">f</p><p n="year of birth">1978</p><p n="first language">Chinese Cantonese</p><p n="education">OSA</p><p n="course">Electronic Business Management</p><p n="student ID">0353</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><docTitle><titlePart rend="bold">ICT Post Module Assignment</titlePart></docTitle></titlePage><div1 type="toc" n="3"><head rend="underlined bold italic">Table of contents</head><p/></div1></front><body><div1 type="text"><head rend="bold">1. Part A</head><div2><head rend="bold italic">1.1 Introduction:</head><p n="p1.94"><s n="s1.3;p1.94">The following report deals with the group work on the hotel database creation case study. </s><s n="s2.3;p1.94">It indicates the methods employed while doing the case study and also the reasons behind doing it. </s><s n="s3.3;p1.94">It also includes the problems and conditions of the final decisions made and how it would affect the performance of the hotel. </s></p><p n="p2.94"><s n="s1.2;p2.94">The following report is based on the group being a part of the reception desk which is Group B in the syndicate group briefing table. </s><s n="s2.2;p2.94">To reiterate the groups' responsibilities, they are listed as follows (Buxton, 2007): </s></p><list type="bulleted"><item>Availability of rooms for their guests as well as the cleaning status of the rooms.</item><item>Customer allocation for their designated rooms.</item><item>Payment of rooms and other services and facilities used by each customer.</item><item>Issues pertaining to a particular guest.</item></list><p n="p3.94"><s n="s1.2;p3.94">The following sub topics will answer the questions regarding the working process and the efficiency of the hotel. </s><s n="s2.2;p3.94">It will also give insights in terms of recommendations regarding changes that could be made for higher standard of service as well as higher profits for the hotel. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold italic">1.2 General recommendations:</head><p n="p4.94"><s n="s1.4;p4.94">To start off the task, the group first looked at all the changes that could be made in general to improve the overall profits of the hotel. </s><s n="s2.4;p4.94">The reason behind doing this general review would give the group an in-depth view of how the hotel could make profits. </s><s n="s3.4;p4.94">The following sub-topic discusses recommendations on increasing revenues and reducing expenditure, which in turn would increase profits for the hotel. </s><s n="s4.4;p4.94">The following paragraphs are sub divided into the factors that could increase the revenue and reduce expenditure and the associated strategies that the hotel could implement. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p5.94"><s n="s1.1;p5.94"><hi rend="bold">Increasing revenue:</hi> The first obvious choice of increasing revenue is to sell more products of the company. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p6.94"><s n="s1.2;p6.94">The company being in the service industry, it needs to bring in more customers. </s><s n="s2.2;p6.94">The strategy that the hotel could use to bring in more customers are as follows. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p7.94"><s n="s1.1;p7.94">Collaboration - with travel agents and tour operators. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p8.94"><s n="s1.1;p8.94">Systematic booking system - to have a more easy and convenient form of booking system so as to capture the market. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p9.94"><s n="s1.1;p9.94">Aggressive advertising - initiate both forms of advertising i.e. offline and online to capture a greater share of the market. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p10.94"><s n="s1.2;p10.94">Apart from getting in more customers, another source of revenue for the hotel industry should be the catering service industry, which the hotel should be quick to tap on. </s><s n="s2.2;p10.94">The strategies that could be used are as follows. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p11.94"><s n="s1.1;p11.94">Establishing contacts - with other event managers and organisers, in order to tap the catering business. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p12.94"><s n="s1.1;p12.94">Training staff - to handle outdoor catering </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p13.94"><s n="s1.1;p13.94">Increase profit margin, to gain revenues and the strategies to be used are as follows. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p14.94"><s n="s1.1;p14.94">Competitive pricing and offers </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p15.94"><s n="s1.1;p15.94">Introduction of more customer centric services like perhaps a collection of his/her favourite music collection available in the room for easy listening. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p16.94"><s n="s1.2;p16.94"><hi rend="bold">Reducing expenditure</hi> is another way of in turn increasing the profits. </s><s n="s2.2;p16.94">The methods suggested are as follows. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p17.94"><s n="s1.1;p17.94">Reduction of staff members/employees. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p18.94"><s n="s1.2;p18.94">In other words the company could perhaps outsource the required man power if it reduces expenditure for the company. </s><s n="s2.2;p18.94">It would work better for the hotel if it could outsource its lesser used work force, for instance, the vehicles and drivers used during the catering service, to reduce expenditure. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p19.94"><s n="s1.1;p19.94">The company could even reduce its staff by improving the quality of technology used. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p20.94"><s n="s1.1;p20.94">In positions of the company where employee retention is not important it could hire people on a part time basis so as to reduce the salaries of otherwise working employees who may not have work to do. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p21.94"><s n="s1.1;p21.94">Another source of reducing expenditure is by reducing the purchasing cost and few of the strategies that could be implemented are as follows. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p22.94"><s n="s1.1;p22.94">By implementing a more efficient supply chain management as well as improved logistics in terms of buying and procuring of items. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p23.94"><s n="s1.1;p23.94">Reverse auction of items and get the most cost effective and reliable source as the supplier. </s></p><p n="p24.94"><s n="s1.2;p24.94">The above stated points are few of the examples of improving the profit margin for the hotel. </s><s n="s2.2;p24.94">The hotel should wisely use all or maybe a combination of the above stated recommendations. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold italic">1.3 Flow chart of the Reception Desk. </head><p n="p25.94"><s n="s1.1;p25.94">After having an over view of the methods of making profit for the hotel as a whole, the report shall now dwell into specifically how certain improvements in the reception desk area of the hotel could make a distinctive difference to the whole functioning of the hotel. </s></p><p n="p26.94"><s n="s1.4;p26.94">The report looks at improving the working methods of the reception desk firstly by breaking it up into flow chart that would help the staff members to visualize all the steps in a sequential manner (Buxton, 2007). </s><s n="s2.4;p26.94">In the following sub-topic, the flow diagrams that show the working of the reception area in the hotel are shown - figure 1, figure 2 and figure 3. </s><s n="s3.4;p26.94">The flow chart is broken up into two distinctive features namely for customer check in and customer check out. </s><s n="s4.4;p26.94">Both the flow charts are connected with the help of connectors, due to the size constraint of the document. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0353d-fig.001"><head rend="sub">FIGURE 1</head></figure><figure id="BAWE_0353d-fig.002"><head rend="sub">FIGURE 2</head></figure><figure id="BAWE_0353d-fig.003"><head rend="sub">FIGURE 3</head></figure></div2><div2><head rend="bold italic">1.4 Business questions to be answered:</head><p n="p27.94"><s n="s1.2;p27.94">After getting the basic structure done, in the form of flow charts, it was now time for the group to discuss more in depth questions that may need answers while improving the reception desk functionalities. </s><s n="s2.2;p27.94">The following reports looks at that aspect of the group work. </s></p><p n="p28.94"><s n="s1.3;p28.94">Users or customers are the major driving force of any business. </s><s n="s2.3;p28.94">It is for the company to see that their efforts are at best always to please their most valuable asset - their users / customers. </s><s n="s3.3;p28.94">For this to be satisfied, companies tend to resort to technologies to help them satisfy their customers more efficiently and more conveniently. </s></p><p n="p29.94"><s n="s1.3;p29.94">As Chaudhuri (1999) mentions, it is very important to find out what exactly the customers are looking for before any company implements any new technology. </s><s n="s2.3;p29.94">Chaudhuri (1999) was being more specific to the database management of the company, which, if well designed against the right questions asked, would in turn help in Customer Relationship Management (CRM). </s><s n="s3.3;p29.94">The following sub topic looks at the various questions that the staff in the hotel would most likely ask in order for a better CRM program. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p30.94"><s n="s1.1;p30.94">The previous times or the number of times the particular customer has checked in the last 12 months, to provide better customised service. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p31.94"><s n="s1.1;p31.94">How many members are accompanying with the person who booked the room - single or family. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p32.94"><s n="s1.1;p32.94">What is the purpose of visit - business or vacation. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p33.94"><s n="s1.1;p33.94">How long is the stay probable to be. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p34.94"><s n="s1.1;p34.94">General information of the customer - name, company, food habits. etc. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p35.94"><s n="s1.1;p35.94">The corresponding room number allocated to the customer. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p36.94"><s n="s1.1;p36.94">Any other specific requirements of the customer. </s></p><p n="p37.94"><s n="s1.2;p37.94">The group now decided to move onto how each of the different entities pertaining to the reception desk would relate to each other. </s><s n="s2.2;p37.94">The following topic moves onto the Entity Relationship (ER) Diagram which is going to be discussed </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold italic">1.5 Entity Relationship (ER) Diagram:</head><p n="p38.94"><s n="s1.4;p38.94">Entity Relationship Diagram (ERD) is a diagram that pictorially represents entities, the relationships between them and the attributes used to describe them (Teorey et al, 1986). </s><s n="s2.4;p38.94">In other words it could be defined as a diagram that is visually used to represent the various data objects of a given business model. </s><s n="s3.4;p38.94">The ERD is considered as a conceptual model where in it views the real world as entities and relations (Buxton, 2007). </s><s n="s4.4;p38.94">It is considered as a flow chart while making and designing a database, only which is more helpful and logical towards database design. </s></p><p n="p39.94"><s n="s1.5;p39.94">From the above statements, entity could be defined as an object which contains some form of descriptive information regarding the data. </s><s n="s2.5;p39.94">On the other hand the attributes of an entity are something that either defines an entity or describes an entity. </s><s n="s3.5;p39.94">Apart from these, relationships are established between entities (Buxton, 2007). </s><s n="s4.5;p39.94">The ERD model of the hotel reception desk is shown below in figure 4. </s><s n="s5.5;p39.94">The crow's foot method was chosen over the Chen model of representation (Rob, 2002) as the group found it easier to express it graphically rather than in the form of numbers and letters (e.g. of Chen's model is - 1: M, M: M, M: M etc.). </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0353d-fig.004"><head rend="sub">FIGURE 4</head></figure></div2><div2><head rend="bold italic">1.6 The entity relations:</head><p n="p40.94"><s n="s1.1;p40.94">The above shown entity-relationship diagram shows the user the relationships between the 5 main entities of the hotel's reception desk, namely </s></p><list type="bulleted"><item>Customer</item><item>Booking</item><item>Bill</item><item>Room and </item><item>Room type.</item></list><p n="p41.94"><s n="s1.1;p41.94">The relationships are as follows: </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p42.94"><s n="s1.3;p42.94">Customer - booking: from the above diagram it is most certain that the relation between customer and booking is a one-to-many relation. </s><s n="s2.3;p42.94">It indicates that at any given instant there may be many bookings from different customers. </s><s n="s3.3;p42.94">But when read the other way, it indicates that there could only be one booking from one customer. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p43.94"><s n="s1.2;p43.94">Booking - bill: the booking - bill relation is strictly a one-to-one relation. </s><s n="s2.2;p43.94">It indicates that there could be only one bill generated for a single booking and when read the other way it states that every booking, if confirmed and occupied by the customer, will have only one final bill. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p44.94"><s n="s1.4;p44.94">Bill - room: this is a one-to-many relation. </s><s n="s2.4;p44.94">This relation indicates that there could be many bills from different attributes of the hotel (e.g. mini bar, internet, restaurant etc.). </s><s n="s3.4;p44.94">But all the bills combined will only be for a particular room. </s><s n="s4.4;p44.94">Read other way, it indicates that a single room could have lots of bills from different areas of the hotel. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p45.94"><s n="s1.2;p45.94">Room - room type: this is also a one-to-many relation. </s><s n="s2.2;p45.94">This relationship diagram indicates that there could be many room for a single room type but a single room can be of only one room type. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p46.94"><s n="s1.2;p46.94">Booking - room type: this relation is a one-to-many relation. </s><s n="s2.2;p46.94">There could be many booking for a single room type, but there could be only one room type for each booking. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold italic">1.7 Screen shot - MS Access relationship diagram:</head><p n="p47.94"><s n="s1.2;p47.94">Shown below in figure 5 is the screen shot of the MS access relationship diagram for the reception desk. </s><s n="s2.2;p47.94">The relationships are the same as discussed in the above sub-topic. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0353d-pic.001"><head rend="sub">FIGURE 5</head></figure></div2><div2><head rend="bold italic">1.8 Entity - attribute matrix:</head><p n="p48.94"><s n="s1.1;p48.94">The diagrams (Figure 6) below represent the entity - attribute matrix for the hotel's reception desk, indicating the entire primary key attributes, foreign key attributes and the owner and migrated keys. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p49.94"><s n="s1.2;p49.94"><hi rend="underlined italic">Primary keys:</hi> As Buxton (2007) points out, primary keys could be defined as one of the most basic components on which relational theory is based. </s><s n="s2.2;p49.94">It allows the user to uniquely define each entity and differentiates each entity from the other. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p50.94"><s n="s1.3;p50.94"><hi rend="underlined italic">Foreign keys: </hi>It forms the other part of the most basic components of relational theory. </s><s n="s2.3;p50.94">It helps to join the relation between the entities and helps the user identify how each entity is dependent on the other entity, where the foreign key belongs. </s><s n="s3.3;p50.94">Each relationship on the model must be supported by a foreign key (Buxton, 2007). </s></p><table id="BAWE_0353d-tab.001"><head rend="sub">FIGURE 6</head><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p51.94"><s n="s1.2;p51.94">From defining and identifying the primary and foreign keys of each entity, it was now time for the group to discuss in-depth, each entity as such. </s><s n="s2.2;p51.94">The following sub-topic discusses each of the entity in detail with the help of a MS Access screen shot of each entity. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold italic">1.9 Explanation of Screen shots of the database table:</head><div3><head rend="bold">1.9.1 Table 1: Bill Entity - </head><p n="p52.94"><s n="s1.4;p52.94">The below screen shot (Figure 7) shows the design view of the bill entity table. </s><s n="s2.4;p52.94">As shown its attributes contain the Bill Id which is the sequence number of the bill, for easy data storing and recovery in the future. </s><s n="s3.4;p52.94">The bill entity also contains the room number which is a foreign key attribute from the room entity. </s><s n="s4.4;p52.94">The remaining attributes are various bills from the different areas of the hotel like the mini bar, restaurant, etc. </s></p><p n="p53.94"><s n="s1.2;p53.94">The reason for adding the room number as one of the attributes helps the employees to link each bill from different parts to a specific room number. </s><s n="s2.2;p53.94">This would ease the process of the final billing when the customer checks out as the employee at the reception would get to see all the bills concerned with the specific room, the customer was staying in. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0353d-pic.002"><head rend="sub">FIGURE 8</head></figure></div3><div3><head rend="bold">1.9.2 Table 2: booking entity - </head><p n="p54.94"><s n="s1.2;p54.94">The figure below (figure 9) shows the design view of the booking entity. </s><s n="s2.2;p54.94">As seen, it contains the attributes - booking ID, date (When occupied), duration (of stay), number of people and customer ID. The booking ID is just a sequential number for easy access and storage. </s></p><p n="p55.94"><s n="s1.4;p55.94">The date arrived is considered as the primary key as it defines and justifies the booking entity. </s><s n="s2.4;p55.94">There are few foreign keys in the form of the customer ID whose parent entity is the customer entity. </s><s n="s3.4;p55.94">The customer ID is used as a foreign key from the customer entity as this would enable us to change bookings as and when required without changing the other details of the customer. </s><s n="s4.4;p55.94">Apart from that the booking entity owns the duration (of stay) and the number of people attribute. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0353d-pic.003"><head rend="sub">FIGURE 9</head></figure></div3><div3><head rend="bold">1.9.3 Table 3: customer entity - </head><p n="p56.94"><s n="s1.2;p56.94">The figure below, figure 10, shows the design view of the customer entity table. </s><s n="s2.2;p56.94">The attributes contained in this entity are as followed - the customer ID, the room number of the customer, the name of the customer along with the contact details in the form of telephone number and the email address. </s></p><p n="p57.94"><s n="s1.4;p57.94">The customer ID is the primary key of the customer entity as it defines who the customer is and indicates other details of the customer. </s><s n="s2.4;p57.94">The room number is a foreign key which is derived from the room entity, which is its parent entity. </s><s n="s3.4;p57.94">The reason for doing it this way is that we, the employees or staff, could change the room number of the customer at any time without having to change his or her entire contact details and other information. </s><s n="s4.4;p57.94">Apart from this the entity also contains the contact details of the customer and this entity is considered to be the owner of those attributes. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0353d-pic.004"><head rend="sub">FIGURE 10</head></figure></div3><div3><head rend="bold">1.9.4 Table 4: Room entity - </head><p n="p58.94"><s n="s1.2;p58.94">Figure 11 is the design view of the room entity. </s><s n="s2.2;p58.94">The attributes that are contained within the room entity are as follows - the room number, the room type and the cleaning status. </s></p><p n="p59.94"><s n="s1.6;p59.94">The room number is considered to be the primary key of the room entity. </s><s n="s2.6;p59.94">It defines and indicates the entity as a whole. </s><s n="s3.6;p59.94">This way the status of the room and the type of room could be changed at will without much hassle as it is contained in a separate entity as such. </s><s n="s4.6;p59.94">The other attributes of this entity are the room type, a foreign key from the room type entity, indicating what type of a room it is. </s><s n="s5.6;p59.94">The room entity also owns the cleaning status indicating the cleaning status for each room. </s><s n="s6.6;p59.94">Apart from this the entity also owns the various bills from different departments of the hotel as it is all associated with the particular room. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0353d-pic.005"><head rend="sub">FIGURE 11</head></figure></div3><div3><head rend="bold">1.9.5 Table 5: room type entity - </head><p n="p60.94"><s n="s1.2;p60.94">Figure 12, shown below, is the design view of the room type entity table. </s><s n="s2.2;p60.94">The entity contains the attribute - room type and price. </s></p><p n="p61.94"><s n="s1.2;p61.94">The room type attribute is considered to be the primary key attribute for the entity. </s><s n="s2.2;p61.94">And the price attribute is a foreign key from the bill entity being the parent entity. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0353d-pic.006"><head rend="sub">FIGURE 12</head></figure><p n="p62.94"><s rend="bold" n="s1.1;p62.94">] </s></p></div3></div2><div2><head rend="bold italic">1.10 Reception desk Database system test and multiple table queries example:</head><p n="p63.94"><s n="s1.2;p63.94">After the implementation of the new system, it was now time for the group to put the new system to test. </s><s n="s2.2;p63.94">The report now aims to demonstrate the effectiveness of the new database system for the reception desk area of the hotel with the help of few screen shots of the new look menu. </s></p><p n="p64.94"><s n="s1.3;p64.94">For testing the system to it full capabilities, the group decided to enter data that would in a form that would have child or dependent entities. </s><s n="s2.3;p64.94">The form chosen was for the customer information entity. </s><s n="s3.3;p64.94">The screen shot of the customer information screen is as shown below in figure 13, which is followed by a multiple table queries. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0353d-pic.007"><head rend="sub">FIGURE 13</head></figure><p n="p65.94"><s n="s1.2;p65.94">In the above figure of a screen shot for the customer information entity, the data corresponding to the attributes are filled in. </s><s n="s2.2;p65.94">The customer information entity was chosen as an example as it had the most number of child entities that were dependent on its parent entities. </s></p><p n="p66.94"><s n="s1.2;p66.94">Both the room type and room number entities were child entities dependent on the room type and room entities respectively. </s><s n="s2.2;p66.94">As shown in the figure, the room type attribute had a drop-down combo box to ease the method of input for the employees. </s></p><p n="p67.94"><s n="s1.1;p67.94">Figure 14 shows a multiple table query where in the group decided to view all the first floor customers along with their details in the form of name, room number and their bills incurred. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0353d-pic.008"><head rend="sub">FIGURE 14</head></figure><p n="p68.94"><s n="s1.1;p68.94">As shown in the figure above, with the help of the newly implemented system, the employees could easily view all the details of the customers residing in the first floor of the hotel. </s></p><p n="p69.94"><s n="s1.1;p69.94">The newly introduced system, hence, makes it easier for the staff members and other employees to gain any form of information with ease and without much changes to the system. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold italic">1.11 Conclusion:</head><p n="p70.94"><s n="s1.1;p70.94">The group, group 2, successfully completed the required task of designing, creating, implementing and testing out the new database management system for the reception desk of a hotel. </s></p><p n="p71.94"><s n="s1.3;p71.94">As part of the future plans, there could be minor changes made in order to adapt to the rest of the database systems around the hotel. </s><s n="s2.3;p71.94">This would help in wholly integrating all the hotel services as a single seamless entity. </s><s n="s3.3;p71.94">This definitely would not suffice those requirements, but is certainly the first step towards achieving those targets. </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="front-back-matter"><head rend="bold italic">1.12 References:</head><p>
Buxton, H. ICT Module Notes. 
2007. 
</p><p>
Chaudhuri, S. and Shim, K. Optimization of Queries with User-Defined Predicates. 
<hi rend="italic">ACM Transactions on Database Systems</hi>, 24(2), 1999, pp. 177 - 228. 
</p><p>
Rob, P. and Coronel, C. 
Database Systems: Design, implementation and management. 
Boston: Thomson learning, 2002. 
</p><p>
Teorey, T.J., Yang, D. and Fry, J.P. A Logical Design Methodology for Relational Databases Using the Extended Entity-Relationship Model. 
<hi rend="italic">Computing Surveys,</hi> 18(2), 1986, pp. 197 - 222. 
</p></div1><div1 type="text"><head rend="bold">2. PART B</head><div2><head rend="bold italic">2.1 Entity-relationship model - university:</head><p n="p72.94"><s n="s1.3;p72.94">A university is a fine example where in data base management could be very cumbersome, if not dealt with in the right manner. </s><s n="s2.3;p72.94">There could be a wide range of interdependencies within various entities of the university. </s><s n="s3.3;p72.94">This report tries to draw conclusions to an entity-relationship model for a university. </s></p><p n="p73.94"><s n="s1.2;p73.94">The first step in defining and designing the entity-relationship model would be to define the various entities of the whole model. </s><s n="s2.2;p73.94">As per the question, the various entities for the university are, </s></p><list type="bulleted"><item>Faculties</item><item>Departments</item><item>Courses</item><item>Modules</item><item>Teaching staff</item></list><p n="p74.94"><s n="s1.3;p74.94">The next step is to try and obtain the relations, as per the question, among the various entities of the university. </s><s n="s2.3;p74.94">The points shown below are just a reiteration of the question. </s><s n="s3.3;p74.94">The various relations are as follows: </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p75.94"><s n="s1.1;p75.94">The university contains various faculties. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p76.94"><s n="s1.2;p76.94">Each faculty ha various departments. </s><s n="s2.2;p76.94">Each specific department could be a part of a single faculty </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p77.94"><s n="s1.2;p77.94">Each department of the faculty has various courses running. </s><s n="s2.2;p77.94">And on the other hand, each course of the university would be associated with only a single department and faculty </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p78.94"><s n="s1.2;p78.94">Each of these courses would have a set number of modules under them. </s><s n="s2.2;p78.94">Each module could be a part of just one or even more courses. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p79.94"><s n="s1.1;p79.94">Each module would have a number of staff and each staff may or may not be a part of the module or could be a part of many modules, teaching various courses. </s></p><div3><head rend="bold">2.1.1 The entity- relationship diagram - University</head><figure id="BAWE_0353d-fig.005"><head rend="sub">FIGURE 1</head></figure><p n="p80.94"><s n="s1.2;p80.94">The figure shown above (Figure 1) represents the Entity relation diagram for the given question along with their probable attributes. </s><s n="s2.2;p80.94">The cardinalities are shown according to the crow's foot method of representation. </s></p><p n="p81.94"><s n="s1.3;p81.94">As per the question, the diagram represents the various relationships between the entities of the university. </s><s n="s2.3;p81.94">As shown above, the university consists of various faculties, and each faculty will have various departments. </s><s n="s3.3;p81.94">But when read from right to left, each department would be a part of only a single faculty, as shown in the cardinality of the diagram. </s></p><p n="p82.94"><s n="s1.2;p82.94">Moving to the next set of relation between the departments, courses and the teaching staff, each department could have various courses running in them, but reading it from the bottom, each course will be a part of only one department. </s><s n="s2.2;p82.94">Additionally, each department would have a set of teaching staff to take care of the courses, but each member of staff would be associated with only one of the departments of the university. </s></p><p n="p83.94"><s n="s1.4;p83.94">The next set of relationship is a many-to-many relation and may need to be resolved for further analyses. </s><s n="s2.4;p83.94">The relation between the courses and the modules indicates that, each course would have various modules running. </s><s n="s3.4;p83.94">And on the other hand, each module could be a part of at least one or more than one course. </s><s n="s4.4;p83.94">This could be resolved by perhaps adding another entity between them for ease of analyses. </s></p><p n="p84.94"><s n="s1.6;p84.94">The next set of relationship also is a many-to-many type of relation and would have to be resolved too. </s><s n="s2.6;p84.94">The relation between the teaching staff and the modules suggests that each module needs to have one or more staff for it to be taught. </s><s n="s3.6;p84.94">While reading the relation the other way, there is a case of optionality in the relation. </s><s n="s4.6;p84.94">Each staff may be a part of one or more module and they could be a part of no module as well. </s><s n="s5.6;p84.94">They could be staff who are on a break or do not have any modules assigned to them. </s><s n="s6.6;p84.94">Nevertheless, they are still a part of the university as they belong to certain departments, as shown in the figure. </s></p></div3></div2><div2><head rend="bold italic">2.2 Refining the ERD:</head><p n="p85.94"><s rend="bold" n="s1.1;p85.94">] </s></p><p n="p86.94"><s n="s1.2;p86.94">According to Buxton (2007), there are broadly 4 basic rules to refining the entity relationship diagram. </s><s n="s2.2;p86.94">It could be done by, </s></p><list type="bulleted"><item>Making all the entities participate in relationships,</item><item>Resolving the many-to-many relationships if they exist.</item><item>Transforming the complex relations into binary relations and </item><item>To eliminate redundant relations.</item></list><p n="p87.94"><s n="s1.3;p87.94">As per the instructions, the ERD in figure 1 could be resolved by making few changes to it. </s><s n="s2.3;p87.94">According the rules laid by Buxton (2007), the diagram does have all the entities participating in relationships. </s><s n="s3.3;p87.94">The remaining 3 rules could come to use while refining the ERD. The new and refined ERD is as shown below in figure 2. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0353d-fig.006"><head rend="sub">FIGURE 2</head></figure><p n="p88.94"><s n="s1.1;p88.94">As shown in the figure above, the ERD shown in figure 1 could be refined in terms of reducing the redundant relation (Teaching staff and department relation, eliminating the many-to-many relationship (the relation between the course and the modules and the teaching staff and the modules) and it could also do away with reducing complex relations. </s></p><p n="p89.94"><s n="s1.4;p89.94">The refinement was done by adding an entity and by removing few redundant relations. </s><s n="s2.4;p89.94">Firstly the relation between the teaching staff and the department could be done away with. </s><s n="s3.4;p89.94">This is done because, it is understood and can be realised that the teaching staff is related to certain modules which in turn are related to the departments. </s><s n="s4.4;p89.94">This helped in reducing the redundant and complex relations. </s></p><p n="p90.94"><s n="s1.2;p90.94">Apart from this a new entity was added to reduce the number of many-to-many relations that were present in the older ERD. The new entity added was the term time entity. </s><s n="s2.2;p90.94">This helped in reducing the previous many-to-many relations that was existing between the teaching staff and the module and the module and the course entity. </s></p><p n="p91.94"><s n="s1.4;p91.94">The new ERD now defines the various relations as follows. </s><s n="s2.4;p91.94">As shown in figure 2, the previous relation between the course and module was a many-to-many relation. </s><s n="s3.4;p91.94">As seen now, with the introduction of the term time entity, it now reads it as there could be various courses held during the term time. </s><s n="s4.4;p91.94">But when read the other way, it indicates that each course will be run only during a specific term time available. </s></p><p n="p92.94"><s n="s1.5;p92.94">Similarly, the module and the teaching staff are now interlinked together through the term time entity. </s><s n="s2.5;p92.94">The new ERD now reads the relations as follows. </s><s n="s3.5;p92.94">It indicates that there would be many modules running during each term time, but when read the other way, it indicates that each module would run only during a specific term time. </s><s n="s4.5;p92.94">Between the teaching staff and the term time, the relation now reads that for each time there would be a number of teaching staff available. </s><s n="s5.5;p92.94">But when the read the other way, it indicates that each teaching staff would be a part of the course for one term time at any given instance of time. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold italic">2.3 A final note</head><p n="p93.94"><s n="s1.2;p93.94">As a final note, the ERD and the refined version of the entity relationship Diagram are, as shown above. </s><s n="s2.2;p93.94">There could be certain refinements done to the diagram in case of integrating it with other facilities of the university, the finance division for instance. </s></p><p n="p94.94"><s n="s1.2;p94.94">There is definitely scope for improvement in the future considerations of the diagram. </s><s n="s2.2;p94.94">This is just the first step towards realising that goal. </s></p></div2></div1></body><back><div1 type="bibliography"><head rend="bold italic">2.4 References:</head><p>Buxton, H. ICT Module Notes. 2007.</p></div1><div1 type="bibliography"><head rend="bold italic">Bibliography:</head><p>Connolly, T.M. (2002). <hi rend="italic">Database systems: a practical approach to design, implementation and management.</hi> 3<hi rend="sup">rd</hi> ed. Harlow: Addison-Wesley.</p><p>Hernandez, M.J. (2003). <hi rend="italic">Database design for mere mortals: a hands-on guide to relational database design.</hi> 2<hi rend="sup">nd</hi> ed. London: Addison-Wesley.</p><p><hi rend="italic">Microsoft office access 2003 step by step.</hi> (2004). <hi rend="italic">Redmond, Wash.:Microsoft Press.</hi></p><p>Rob, P. (2002). <hi rend="italic">Database system: design, implementation, and management.</hi> 5<hi rend="sup">th</hi> ed. Boston, Mass: Course Technology.</p></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
