<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_0354e" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Assignment - Lecture Six: The Petronas Towers</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note/></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">1</p><p n="date">2007-03</p><p n="module title">Aesthetics of Design</p><p n="module code">ES177</p><p n="genre family">Explanation</p><p n="discipline">Engineering</p><p n="disciplinary group">PS</p><p n="grade">M</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">864</p><p n="number of s-units">34</p><p n="number of p">10</p><p n="number of tables">0</p><p n="number of figures">6</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">0</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">0</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">25.4</p><p n="average s-units per p">3.4</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">f</p><p n="year of birth">1987</p><p n="first language">English</p><p n="education">UKA</p><p n="course">Engineering</p><p n="student ID">0354</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><titlePart><hi rend="bold">Aesthetics of Design<name type="student name"/></hi><hi rend="bold"><name type="student ID"/> Assignment - Lecture Six</hi></titlePart><docTitle><titlePart rend="italic">The Petronas Towers are currently the World's tallest buildings. This particular honour has been held by many structures in the last 100 years. Choose one, then explore and explain the story of its design and construction. </titlePart></docTitle></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="section"><p n="p1.10"><s n="s1.3;p1.10">In 1928, construction of the Chrysler Building in New York began. </s><s n="s2.3;p1.10">Two years later, the building was completed where it dominated the New York landscape as the world's tallest building before the Empire State Building was completed the following year. </s><s n="s3.3;p1.10">It is a masterpiece of Art Deco design built at a time when there was great competition in New York to build the tallest building. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0354e-pic.001"/><p n="p2.10"><s n="s1.4;p2.10">The designer of the Chrysler Building was William Van Alen (1883 - 1954). </s><s n="s2.4;p2.10">He subsequently sold his idea to Walter Chrysler (1875 - 1940) as a headquarters for his car company and the project was contracted by William H Reynolds. </s><s n="s3.4;p2.10">It was to stand as a monument to Chrysler's success, and a statement of the modern era and capitalism. </s><s n="s4.4;p2.10">It was also the first building to pass the 1000 foot threshold. </s></p><p n="p3.10"><s n="s1.4;p3.10">The Chrysler Building was built just as the Art Deco movement was reaching America. </s><s n="s2.4;p3.10">Art Deco had been conceived in Paris in 1925 with the first major exhibition of the arts since the First World War, "Exposition Internationale des Arts Decoratifs et Industriels Modernes". </s><s n="s3.4;p3.10">It encompassed many geometric and stylised forms and shapes, and carries an air of primitive arts from Africa and Mexico, as well as Neoclassism and the Jazz Age. </s><s n="s4.4;p3.10">It is considered to be one of the most beautiful eras of American architecture, and is still considered very fashionable today. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0354e-pic.002"/><p n="p4.10"><s n="s1.5;p4.10">The Art Deco movement in America started later than in Europe, and so quickly moved into an age of modernism or streamline moderne. </s><s n="s2.5;p4.10">During the Modernist Period shapes were often very stark and bare, and unnecessary ornamentation was frowned upon. </s><s n="s3.5;p4.10">The streamline moderne uses many curved forms and long horizontal lines, and sometimes nautical elements such as railings (San Fransisco Maritime Museum, above). </s><s n="s4.5;p4.10">By the time the Chrysler Building was completed, some architects of the time criticised it for not being Modernist enough, and thought that its decoration at the top of the building was unnecessary. </s><s n="s5.5;p4.10">This may also have been a reaction to the post-war shortage of materials, and a need to strive forward and look to new sights and production methods and leave the previous century behind. </s></p><p n="p5.10"><s n="s1.4;p5.10">Van Alen originally had planned a 56-story tower to beat out the proposed 55 stories of the Lincoln Building at 60 West 42nd Street. </s><s n="s2.4;p5.10">When J. E. </s><s n="s3.4;p5.10">R. Carpenter, the architect of the Lincoln Building project, upped his project to 63 stories, Van Alen went back to the drawing board and proposed a 65-story tower that soon became a 67-story, 808-foot-high tower with an observatory with a rather squat glass dome that was to be illuminated from within at night. </s><s n="s4.4;p5.10">The Lincoln Building project ultimately decided to only build 54 floors. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0354e-pic.003"/><p n="p6.10"><s n="s1.2;p6.10">When Chrysler bought the plans for this building, he did not instruct Van Alen to radically change the building's form, but to increase its height to 925 feet and add some decorative touches to herald his cars. </s><s n="s2.2;p6.10">When word got out that the Bank of Manhattan tower was being redesigned with the addition of a flagpole atop its lantern-bedecked pyramidal roof that would be two feet tower than his project, Chrysler gave the go ahead to Van Allen to not only prevail against his former partner's project, but to surpass even the 1024-foot-high Eiffel Tower, the world's tallest structure at the time. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0354e-pic.004"/><p n="p7.10"><s n="s1.3;p7.10">In what was certainly one of the greatest secrets and publicity coups in Manhattan real estate history, the stainless steel top was installed to the public's, and the Bank of Manhattan's, utter surprise in about 90 minutes in November, 1929. </s><s n="s2.3;p7.10">The tip of spire was 1046 feet high. </s><s n="s3.3;p7.10">The stainless steel cladding had been hidden in five pieces within the building's shell and was hoisted out of the top of the building and riveted into place. </s></p><p n="p8.10"><s n="s1.3;p8.10">What is remarkable about the stainless steel cladding is how much of the top it covered and, more importantly, how original, striking and exotic it was and what an intricate design it had. </s><s n="s2.3;p8.10">The stainless steel cladding is ribbed in a radiating pattern and has many triangular windows that followed curves of the seven steps of each of the roof's four facades. </s><s n="s3.3;p8.10">The general massing of the building's base and shaft is rather unremarkable, but the building's point is breathtaking. </s></p><p n="p9.10"><s n="s1.3;p9.10">Chrysler had Van Alen incorporate some decorative designs associated with automobiles on the facades, namely simulated hubcaps near the top of one rung of setbacks and great stainless steel eagle gargoyles, two at each of the shaft's four major corners (right). </s><s n="s2.3;p9.10">At a lower setback, stainless steel Chrysler-like hood ornaments serve as ceremonial winged urns (below) which reflect the Chrysler car logo. </s><s n="s3.3;p9.10">The building was opened on 27 <hi rend="sup">th</hi> May 1930. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0354e-pic.005"/><figure id="BAWE_0354e-pic.006"/><p n="p10.10"><s n="s1.3;p10.10">In total, the building is 318.9 metres high to the top of its spire, 282 metres to the top of the roof, and 274 metres to the top floor. </s><s n="s2.3;p10.10">Had there not been such competition for the tallest building, this remarkable structure would never have had these extra details that have made it so famous as so well loved today. </s><s n="s3.3;p10.10">It is a masterpiece of design and one which has been fuelled by competition, and is a testimony to the American age of Art Deco. </s></p></div1></body><back/></text></TEI.2>
