<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_0354b" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Marketing Exercise: Midland Metro</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note/></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">1</p><p n="date">2006-01</p><p n="module title">Economics and the Structure of Industry</p><p n="module code">ES175</p><p n="genre family">Case study</p><p n="discipline">Engineering</p><p n="disciplinary group">PS</p><p n="grade">D</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">977</p><p n="number of s-units">34</p><p n="number of p">11</p><p n="number of tables">0</p><p n="number of figures">1</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">0</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">0</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">28.7</p><p n="average s-units per p">3.1</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">f</p><p n="year of birth">1987</p><p n="first language">English</p><p n="education">UKA</p><p n="course">Engineering</p><p n="student ID">0354</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><titlePart>ES175: Economics and the Structure of Industry Marketing Exercise</titlePart><titlePart><name type="student name"/><name type="student ID"/> January 2006</titlePart><docTitle><titlePart>Midland Metro A Report on Its Structure, Conduct and Performance with Views to Acquiring Midland Metro or Setting Up a Competing Firm.</titlePart></docTitle></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">Introduction</head><p n="p1.11"><s n="s1.3;p1.11">Midland Metro is one of the main transport systems in Birmingham, with 20.13 kilometres of tracks running in and around the city. </s><s n="s2.3;p1.11">Set up in 1999 with funding from a range of sources including £40 million from a government grant, £31 million from a European grant, £4 million from local councils and a £40 million approved loan<ref target="BAWE_0354b-ftnote.001"/>, it has a planned dept lasting 30 years. </s><s n="s3.3;p1.11">This huge capital investment makes its financial analysis especially important for The Entrepreneur choosing to buy the firm or to set up a rival company. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0354b-ftnote.001"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1"><seg type="URL" n="http://www.travelmetro.co.uk/metro/background.asp"/> 17.01.2006 </s></p></note></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">Structure of the Industry</head><p n="p2.11"><s n="s1.2;p2.11">As this company is many years from making any profit and is still fairly early in its development, it could be considered in the Question Mark stage of the market adoption graph. </s><s n="s2.2;p2.11">In 23 years time<ref target="BAWE_0354b-ftnote.002"/>, when the various loans are repaid and the company begins making profit, there will still be large expenses on the tram system, such as repairs and maintenance, extensions to the service and keeping up with any new technology in the transport industry over the next 23 years. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0354b-ftnote.002"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1"><seg type="URL" n="http://www.travelmetro.co.uk/metro/background.asp"/> 17.01.2006 </s></p></note></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">Competition</head><p n="p3.11"><s n="s1.3;p3.11">Midland Metro's competition comes from other modes of transport: at the moment, cars are the biggest threat to any short-distance transport system. </s><s n="s2.3;p3.11">However, buses, local trains and taxis all pose competition to a tram system, and the tram company must keep up service and reliability if it is to remain successful. </s><s n="s3.3;p3.11">A tram system usually draws around half or two thirds of its passengers from buses and a further quarter from car users, thereby also reducing traffic congestion<ref target="BAWE_0354b-ftnote.003"/>. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0354b-ftnote.003"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1"><seg type="URL" n="http://www.parliament.the-stationery-office.co.uk/pa/cm199900/cmselect/cmenvtra/153/153ap27.htm"/> 17.01.2006 </s></p></note><figure id="BAWE_0354b-fig.001"><head>Former Modes if Transport of Tram Users</head></figure><div2><head rend="underlined">Ease of Entry for New Firms</head><p n="p4.11"><s n="s1.4;p4.11">Any transport industry is hard for a new firm to enter, but it is particularly hard for a new tram firm as they require such huge capital investment - £145 million in the case of Midland Metro<ref target="BAWE_0354b-ftnote.004"/>. </s><s n="s2.4;p4.11">Unlike a new car or bus company, trams require a great deal of planning into routes, track laying and flow of passengers which all require heavy research and permission from many authorities. </s><s n="s3.4;p4.11">There is also rarely demand for more than one tram company per city unless the city is very large, particularly with ever-present competition from other forms of transport. </s><s n="s4.4;p4.11">The Entrepreneur might consider looking into other modes of public transport other than trams if s/he is very keen to invest in such a project. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0354b-ftnote.004"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1"><seg type="URL" n="http://www.travelmetro.co.uk/metro/projectfacts.asp"/> 17.01.2006 </s></p></note></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">Price or Non-price Competition</head><p n="p5.11"><s n="s1.4;p5.11">As Midland Metro is a service and not a commodity, most of its competition is non-price competition. </s><s n="s2.4;p5.11">It competes on reliability, comfort, location and routes in comparison to other modes of transport. </s><s n="s3.4;p5.11">However, it still competes on price in the sense that if it is cheaper - and significantly more convenient - for a passenger to pay for petrol and a parking ticket and travel by car than to use the tram then they will do so. </s><s n="s4.4;p5.11">The trams are also competing with buses, although this largely depends on the service and the route and which is more convenient for the passenger. </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">Performance of this Industry</head><div2><head rend="underlined">Qualifiers and Order Winners</head><p n="p6.11"><s n="s1.4;p6.11">Midland Metro's main qualifiers are its reliability and capacity for transporting people around the city. </s><s n="s2.4;p6.11">Its order winners would be its reliability and frequency of service, up to every six<ref target="BAWE_0354b-ftnote.005"/> or seven minutes<ref target="BAWE_0354b-ftnote.006"/>, its speed and apparent lack of pollution and smooth ride<ref target="BAWE_0354b-ftnote.007"/>. </s><s n="s3.4;p6.11">It is highly compatible with pedestrians and can carry 208 people at a time<ref target="BAWE_0354b-ftnote.008"/>. </s><s n="s4.4;p6.11">These all contribute to making Midland Metro a better form of public transport than the competition in Birmingham. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0354b-ftnote.005"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1"><seg type="URL" n="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm199900/cmselect/cmenvtra/153/153ap49.htm"/> 17.01.2006 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0354b-ftnote.006"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1"><seg type="URL" n="http://www.travelmetro.co.uk/metro/projectfacts.asp"/> 17.01.2006 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0354b-ftnote.007"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1"><seg type="URL" n="http://www.parliament.the-stationery-office.co.uk/pa/cm199900/cmselect/cmenvtra/153/153ap27.htm"/> 17.01.2006 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0354b-ftnote.008"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1"><seg type="URL" n="http://www.travelmetro.co.uk/metro/tramfacts.asp"/> 17.01.2006 </s></p></note></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">Demand</head><p n="p7.11"><s n="s1.4;p7.11">Demand is to a large extent inelastic: for many people, those without cars or on direct tram routes, or too young or old to justify driving, the trams will be their only feasible method of transport around the city. </s><s n="s2.4;p7.11">However, if prices to get too high, then people will use other forms of transport such as buses or private cars. </s><s n="s3.4;p7.11">For many people, the tram service will be the only way they can get to where they are going, as other forms of public transport may not serve that area. </s><s n="s4.4;p7.11">It is also clear that demand is high for certain areas of the tram line as there is a proposed extension for the line<ref target="BAWE_0354b-ftnote.009"/> with government funding <ref target="BAWE_0354b-ftnote.010"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0354b-ftnote.009"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1"><seg type="URL" n="http://www.centro.org.uk/metrofuture/index.asp"/> 17.01.2006 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0354b-ftnote.010"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1"><seg type="URL" n="http://www.centro.org.uk/wwwroot/CorpInfo/usrCorpDocList.asp"/> 17.01.2006 </s></p></note></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">Viable Strategies for a New Entrant</head><div2><head rend="underlined">Type of Competition</head><p n="p8.11"><s n="s1.3;p8.11">The competition present within the transport companies in Birmingham is an oligopoly. </s><s n="s2.3;p8.11">This is as there are many different forms of transport all competing in effectively the same market. </s><s n="s3.3;p8.11">Although cars have by far the biggest sector of market share, buses, trams, taxis, cycles and pedestrians also compete for market share. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">Performance</head><p n="p9.11"><s n="s1.2;p9.11">The performance of Midland Metro can be hard to judge: as the company is still generating the money to repay the investments, profits as such are not being made. </s><s n="s2.2;p9.11">In this respect the industry is not so attractive, although Altram's figures show that the company is doing increasingly well each year. </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">Advice for The Entrepreneur</head><div2><head rend="underlined">Prospects</head><p n="p10.11"><s n="s1.2;p10.11">This industry looks like it will, over the next 23 years, manage to pay back the investment that went into its set up. </s><s n="s2.2;p10.11">However, it looks highly unlikely that it will ever be making supernormal profits and it must keep its standards high if it is to compete with other modes of transport. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">Acquire or Compete? </head><p n="p11.11"><s n="s1.3;p11.11">Due to its high capital investment and lack of demand, I would recommend The Entrepreneur to acquire Midland Metro as opposed to setting up a rival company. </s><s n="s2.3;p11.11">This way s/he will be taking on the debt the company is already in but not incurring any further costs or the vast amounts of planning that would go into laying new lines for a new company, and the time until profits are made will be shorter. </s><s n="s3.3;p11.11">However, The Entrepreneur might be wise to consider other forms of transport other than trams if s/he is keen to be active in the public transport market. </s></p></div2></div1></body><back/></text></TEI.2>
