<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_0354d" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Assignment - Lecture Six: The Coca-Cola bottle</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note/></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">1</p><p n="date">2007-03</p><p n="module title">Aesthetics of Design</p><p n="module code">ES177</p><p n="genre family">Explanation</p><p n="discipline">Engineering</p><p n="disciplinary group">PS</p><p n="grade">M</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">630</p><p n="number of s-units">25</p><p n="number of p">10</p><p n="number of tables">0</p><p n="number of figures">6</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">0</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">0</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">25.2</p><p n="average s-units per p">2.5</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">f</p><p n="year of birth">1987</p><p n="first language">English</p><p n="education">UKA</p><p n="course">Engineering</p><p n="student ID">0354</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><titlePart><hi rend="bold">Aesthetics of Design<name type="student name"/></hi><hi rend="bold"><name type="student ID"/> Assignment - Lecture Six</hi></titlePart><docTitle><titlePart rend="italic">The Coca-Cola bottle is widely recognised as a 20th Century design icon. Describe its origins and discuss the reasons for its success as a design. (Essay 500 - 1000 words)</titlePart></docTitle></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="section"><p n="p1.10"><s n="s1.3;p1.10">The sign of any outstanding and lasting design is its recognition. </s><s n="s2.3;p1.10">One of the most easily recognised designs of the 20 <hi rend="sup">th</hi> Century is the Coca-Cola bottle, which almost anyone would recognise regardless of age, nationality or gender. </s><s n="s3.3;p1.10">I will now look at the origins of this design and consider why it is so successful. </s></p><p n="p2.10"><s n="s1.4;p2.10">When Coca-Cola first started bottling their drinks they used a simple rounded bottle of equal radius throughout, known as the Hutchison Bottle, as was common with beverages of the time (left). </s><s n="s2.4;p2.10">Its stopper worked either by using a marble or a stiff wire look and a rubber disk, whereby the pressure inside the bottle forced the disk or marble right to the top of the bottle where it acted as a seal and its own pressure prevented it form leaking (right). </s><s n="s3.4;p2.10">It could be released by pushing the marble down or twisting the wire and letting the pressure out. </s><s n="s4.4;p2.10">However, they found that this bottle and its sealing mechanism were inefficient, costly and liable to leak and break. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0354d-pic.001"/><figure id="BAWE_0354d-pic.002"/><p n="p3.10"><s n="s1.2;p3.10">Coca-Cola then realized the importance of shape in their bottle designs: they realized that a consumer, on reaching into a bucket of ice, would not be able to tell the Coca-Cola bottle from any other bottle just by touch, and so would grab whichever bottle came to hand first. </s><s n="s2.2;p3.10">It was clear that Coca-Cola had to make their bottle a distinctive shape if it was to be recognized and selected out over other bottles. </s></p><p n="p4.10"><s n="s1.3;p4.10">It is then that the initial idea for the Coca-Cola bottle as we know it today first appeared. </s><s n="s2.3;p4.10">The original design was based on the cocoa pod (left) from which Coca-Cola is made which was both distinctive and easy to hold. </s><s n="s3.3;p4.10">The resulted in what was called the Root Bottle (right). </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0354d-pic.003"/><p n="p5.10"><s n="s1.1;p5.10">b/p </s></p><p n="p6.10"><s n="s1.2;p6.10">This design of bottle was the true beginning of Coca-Cola's success: it was distinctive, unusual, modern and it spread throughout the world very fast. </s><s n="s2.2;p6.10">The increased use of the crown cap (as is commonly seen on almost all bottled beers and soft drinks still today) made transportation of Coca-Cola's bottles easier too. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0354d-pic.004"/><p n="p7.10"><s n="s1.2;p7.10">However, the bulky shape of Coca-Cola's bottles still hampered transportation a little; the Hutchison bottle was well equipped for traveling as many bottles could be fitted in a box without much wasted space. </s><s n="s2.2;p7.10">Coca-Cola therefore decided to slim down their bottles to the shape we see them today: </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0354d-pic.005"/><p n="p8.10"><s n="s1.2;p8.10">This shape of bottle is thinner and so many of them can be packed together in a smaller space, but it still maintains the unique shape derived from the cocoa pod that was its inspiration. </s><s n="s2.2;p8.10">There are possibly other points that make this improved bottle shape more appealing. </s></p><p n="p9.10"><s n="s1.2;p9.10">One positive aspect of a thinner bottle is possibly its similarities to the female form: it is curvaceous and yet slim, which epitomises the 20 <hi rend="sup">th</hi> Century desirable shape of women. </s><s n="s2.2;p9.10">The bottle has both a "neck" and a "waist", and although this may seem to be a somewhat specious comparison, it does represent a great deal about Coca-Cola and their image of up-to-the-minute fashion and desirability. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0354d-pic.006"/><p n="p10.10"><s n="s1.4;p10.10">Due to the distinctive design of the Coca-Cola bottle, it has been available for advertising itself merely as distinctive. </s><s n="s2.4;p10.10">It has resulted in a whole troop of collectors worldwide, and itself has become a collector's item. </s><s n="s3.4;p10.10">It is possible to buy Gold Plated, solid silver, chocolate, giant and miniature Coca-Cola bottles, and the bottle itself has largely spawned the overall popularity of the drink and the recognition of the Coca-Cola logo which can be seen throughout the world. </s><s n="s4.4;p10.10">It is a fine example of what clever aesthetic designing can do for a product, and interesting to see how the design of possibly the most famous item and logo throughout the world has come into being. </s></p></div1></body><back/></text></TEI.2>
