<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_0356c" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>The Liquisaver</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">The document has a title page which contains:
document title
title part</note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">deleted: page numbers</note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">appendix: break even analysis</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">2</p><p n="date">2007-01</p><p n="module title">Starting and Running a Business</p><p n="module code">ES2A6</p><p n="genre family">Proposal</p><p n="discipline">Engineering</p><p n="disciplinary group">PS</p><p n="grade">M</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">4220</p><p n="number of s-units">161</p><p n="number of p">82</p><p n="number of tables">2</p><p n="number of figures">8</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">1</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">12</p><p n="abstract present">abstract present</p><p n="average words per s-unit">26.2</p><p n="average s-units per p">2.0</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">m</p><p n="year of birth">1986</p><p n="first language">Sinhala</p><p n="education">OSA</p><p n="course">Engineering Business Management</p><p n="student ID">0356</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><docTitle><titlePart><hi rend="bold">SCS Ltd presents...</hi> <hi rend="bold"> The LiquiSaver</hi></titlePart></docTitle><titlePart rend="bold">A system to stringently measure stock control for kegged, Free Flow Products, with an aim to reduce lost profits through bar staff pilfering</titlePart><titlePart rend="bold">By Group W1</titlePart></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="abstract"><head rend="underlined italic">Section 1 - Executive Summary</head><p n="p1.82"><s n="s1.1;p1.82">A 20% stake in the business, SCS Ltd, if being offered in return for a £70,000 investment to allow us to enter the market with our developed system called LiquiSaver. </s></p><p n="p2.82"><s n="s1.1;p2.82">LiquiSaver is designed to be installed into drinking establishments, and has the ability to stringently measure the volume of free-flow products (lager, cider etc) that have been dispensed by each member of staff. </s></p><p n="p3.82"><s n="s1.1;p3.82">In many establishments, beer is the biggest selling product but does not provide a high level of profit, thus it is important for a manager to be able to account for all the beer that have been dispensed - this requires stringent methods of measuring stock. </s></p><p n="p4.82"><s n="s1.1;p4.82">The LiquiSaver provides this method &amp; also records who has dispensed each beverage, allowing for easy detection of bar staff pilfering. </s></p><p n="p5.82"><s n="s1.2;p5.82">SCS Ltd has a very strong team of four directors from engineering backgrouds, each of whom currently own a 25% stake in the business. </s><s n="s2.2;p5.82">They bring experience from a wide range of areas - <name type="student name"/> manages the company, and brings experience from pub trade management, <name type="student name"/> is the chief engineer of the project, <name type="student name"/> &amp; <name type="student name"/> deal with the financial sector of the business, having worked within several accounting companies. <name type="student name"/> has strong international business relations because of his experiences and interactions with overseas companies. </s></p><p n="p6.82"><s n="s1.2;p6.82">We have identified a niche in the UK dispense monitoring market for a system that not only measures that drinks dispensed, but moreover, recognises each member of staff. </s><s n="s2.2;p6.82">We have recognised that a system would be of great benefit to establishments with many members of staff &amp; are thus focusing our marketing towards students' union bars. </s></p><p n="p7.82"><s n="s1.2;p7.82">As present, we are operating the business from home &amp; carry out all of the field work ourselves (consultations, installations &amp; aftersale service) as we do not require the facilities of dedicated premises nor extra members of staff. </s><s n="s2.2;p7.82">Once the buiness begins to grow &amp; demand for the product increases, we shall relocate the business &amp; employ members of staff to help with the everyday operations </s></p><p n="p8.82"><s n="s1.2;p8.82">Because of the highly differentitated nature of the system that we have developed, we predict excellent returns on your investment, with an expectance to break even after the sale of 17 units - which roughly equates to 3 complete student unions installations. </s><s n="s2.2;p8.82">We furthermore predict that a profit of £100,000 will be reached after the sale of 90 units. </s></p></div1><div1 type="front-back-matter"><head rend="underlined italic">Contents</head><p/></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined italic">Section 2 - History of the Team</head><p n="p9.82"><s n="s1.3;p9.82">SCS Limited is a small company that was set up in June 2006. </s><s n="s2.3;p9.82">The four directors; <name type="student name"/>, <name type="student name"/>, <name type="student name"/> &amp; <name type="student name"/>, currently own 100% of the company (25% each), however, we are offering 20% of the firm's shares in return for a £70,000 investment in the company. </s><s n="s3.3;p9.82">The remaining 80% of the firm's equity would be divided equally between the four current directors. </s></p><p n="p10.82"><s n="s1.3;p10.82">The 'LiquiSaver' system, the current project that SCS Ltd has been developing since it began, is a stock control system for free-flow products. </s><s n="s2.3;p10.82">We have come up with a feasible design for our product and have applied for the patent for the current design. </s><s n="s3.3;p10.82">We have contacted foreign contractors for the production of our device and they have agreed to proceed with our design after the feasibility study. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined italic">Section 3 - Products/Services</head><p n="p11.82"><s n="s1.3;p11.82">The "LiquiSaver" system has been developed with the needs of the customer in mind. </s><s n="s2.3;p11.82">We noticed a gap in the UK dispense monitoring market for product that not only measures the volume of beverages dispensed, but furthermore recognises by whom they have been dispensed. </s><s n="s3.3;p11.82">The system consists of three main parts: flow meters, the processing hardware that provides the manager with a printout of the day's activity and an I.D. checking systems. </s></p><p n="p12.82"><s n="s1.3;p12.82">The flow meters are a cruicial component of the sytem &amp; are designed to be connected in line of the keg and font in order to measure the volume of beverage that has been dispensed. </s><s n="s2.3;p12.82">The I.D. checking system restricts flow through the fonts unless the bartender signifys, by means of either a swipe card or an electromatic plastic ring that is worn on a finger, that he requires use of the font - this derestricts the beer's flow allowing the drink to be dispensed. </s><s n="s3.3;p12.82">The CPU registers how much and by whom the beverage was sold. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0356c-pic.001"><head>Fig 3.1 - Schematic of the System</head></figure><p n="p13.82"><s n="s1.2;p13.82">LiquiSaver was developed for establishments that have a great number of staff, making it difficult to track pilfering without registering by whom the beer was sold. </s><s n="s2.2;p13.82">The main niche that we developed the product for is campus based students' unions. </s></p><p n="p14.82"><s n="s1.2;p14.82">Before we develop a new product and see the need for better services we first need the existing product to mature positively in this market where unexpected problems could arise quickly. </s><s n="s2.2;p14.82">Once the product has reached stable sales, profit targets and generated additional cash for a new investment opportunity then additional parts and new parts will be produced and tested. </s></p><p n="p15.82"><s n="s1.1;p15.82">The new product range we have in mind is an optic dispensed spirit control, line cleaning &amp; temperature checks for the system. </s></p><div2><head rend="bold">Unique selling proposition:</head><p n="p16.82"><s n="s1.3;p16.82">The product is highly differentiated in that it has been developed specifically as a way to prevent pilfering &amp; thus is worth an establishment paying a high fee for because of its ability to prevent the loss of income. </s><s n="s2.3;p16.82">We shall, in future, train staff for maintaining the system, as &amp; when problems arise. </s><s n="s3.3;p16.82">Very special to the maintaining staff is that we train them to train our customers at the first day of installation of how everything works. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">Life span of our products:</head><figure id="BAWE_0356c-fig.001"><head>Fig 3.2 - The Product Life Cycle Curve</head></figure><p n="p17.82"><s n="s1.3;p17.82">Fig 3.1 shows the life cycle curve for the product. </s><s n="s2.3;p17.82">We are aiming for our product not to decline after it has reached its mature point. </s><s n="s3.3;p17.82">Therefore as mentioned before we update our existing products and add new ones depending on the consumers' need. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">Current technology:</head><p n="p18.82"><s n="s1.2;p18.82">The current technology of measuring the beer flow to avoid pilferage already exists from competing companys, Brulines Ltd. and Nucleus Data Ltd. </s><s n="s2.2;p18.82">These products are developed for pub chains, as opposed to the type of venue that we are marketing to, &amp; we will furthermore compete on quality, technology and more user friendly service. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">Future development:</head><p n="p19.82"><s n="s1.1;p19.82">As we think further we understand that we do not see such a large competitor as a disadvantage and more likely as an advantage since it can be learnt from the products they produce. </s></p><p n="p20.82"><s n="s1.3;p20.82">This means that we analyse their and similar products in the markets in order to reverse engineer. </s><s n="s2.3;p20.82">Thus this gives us a broader idea of products in order to create a more updated, technologically advanced product and simple to understand design so that the consumer can cope with it easily. </s><s n="s3.3;p20.82">More importantly we reuse the older equipment from our customers as part of our deal which would reduce the final price of the new updated products and quality will still remain the same. </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined italic">Section 4 - Markets &amp; Marketing</head><div2><head rend="bold">4 i) The Market</head><div3><head>Brief Description &amp; Outlook</head><p n="p21.82"><s n="s1.1;p21.82">Desk research through Mintel databases suggests such free flow beverages account for some 46% of all beverages sold by both on &amp; off trade establishments (as shown in fig 4.1.1), and as fig 4.1.2 shows, the demand for these drinks in increasing. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0356c-fig.002"><head rend="bold">Fig 4.1.1 - Drinks Market - On &amp; off trade by type of beverage in 2003 (values in £m)</head></figure><figure id="BAWE_0356c-fig.003"><head rend="bold">Fig 4.1.2 - Percentage Change of revenue through sales of free flow drinks</head></figure></div3><div3><head>Outline of Current size &amp; projected growth of Market</head><p n="p22.82"><s n="s1.2;p22.82">According to a Mintel report <hi rend="sup">1</hi>, in 2005 the UK Drinks market from on-licensed premises was worth £24.16 billion. </s><s n="s2.2;p22.82">SCS Ltd is positioned in a supply chain by supplying a solution directly to drinking establishments. </s></p><p n="p23.82"><s n="s1.2;p23.82">As we are marketing our product direct to another business, we must orientate ourselves to the business buying system, and more specifically, the system of new task purchase, as opposed to re-buys. </s><s n="s2.2;p23.82">Once the idea has been pitched to the establishments, the business buyer will consider alternatives, which is why it is important for our product to be pitched as higher quality than the competition, so the buyer justifies spending the extra money. </s></p></div3><div3><head>Description of Major Business Application &amp; description of major customers/users</head><p n="p24.82"><s n="s1.2;p24.82">As described in section 3, LiquiSaver has been developed to detect not only what drinks have been sold but who they were sold by. </s><s n="s2.2;p24.82">We are thus pitching the system to privately owned establishments that have many members of staff. </s></p><p n="p25.82"><s n="s1.1;p25.82">Existing &amp; Anticipated Market Share </s></p><p n="p26.82"><s n="s1.3;p26.82">At the current time, we have not entered the market, being still in the prototyping stage. </s><s n="s2.3;p26.82">Once the research &amp; development process is complete, after the first year, we plan to have a 1% market share &amp; shall work towards a 6% market share by 2009, as depicted in Fig 1.1.3. </s><s n="s3.3;p26.82">Although the niche in which we are planning to promote our product is a very small one, we hope that the differentiated nature of our product to suit this niche will allow us to benefit from high profit margins. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0356c-fig.004"><head rend="bold">Fig 4.1.3 - Graphs to show target market share</head></figure><p n="p27.82"><s n="s1.2;p27.82">The system shall be sold directly to on-trade establishments. </s><s n="s2.2;p27.82">By dividing the market up by types of on-licensed establishments, a niche of the drinks market may be chosen in which to promote our product. </s></p><p n="p28.82"><s n="s1.2;p28.82">As fig 4.1.1 shows, we have chosen students' union bars as a niche to promote our product. </s><s n="s2.2;p28.82">The characteristics of students' union bars are as follows: </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0356c-fig.005"><head rend="bold">Fig, 4.1.4 - UK Drinks Trade Market Share, chosen niche labelled</head></figure><p rend="bulleted" n="p29.82"><s n="s1.2;p29.82">High staff turnover as students tend to work as and when they need money. </s><s n="s2.2;p29.82">It is less likely for managers to develop bonds with their staff, from which trust develops. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p30.82"><s n="s1.1;p30.82">Friends of staff drink at unions regularly, which is the main cause for staff dispensing drinks without charging for them. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p31.82"><s n="s1.2;p31.82">Drinks tend to be much cheaper in student union bars than in regular clubs. </s><s n="s2.2;p31.82">This leads to lower profit margins, and a greater need to maximise income from drinks sold. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p32.82"><s n="s1.1;p32.82">The large quantity of drinks sold in a student union bar leads to bar staff pilfering being very difficult to detect. </s></p><p n="p33.82"><s n="s1.2;p33.82">These factors increase the susceptibility of losing income through pilfering, which is the ultimate reason for choosing this niche. </s><s n="s2.2;p33.82">The SCS system is specifically to be aimed at unions of campus based universities, as the social life is much more heavily focused around the student union - students attending city based universities have a much greater choice of pubs/bars/clubs. </s></p><p n="p34.82"><s n="s1.2;p34.82">We currently have a prototype of the SCS System installed into the University of <name type="university"/>'s student union. </s><s n="s2.2;p34.82">Union managers &amp; indeed staff are becoming accustomed to the system &amp; negotiations are currently underway to carry out a full installation. </s></p><p n="p35.82"><s n="s1.3;p35.82">Involving ourselves with <name type="university"/>'s student union will allow us to negotiate deals with the Aldwych group. </s><s n="s2.3;p35.82">This is a group of unions that includes unions such as Birmingham, Cambridge, Glasgow, Leeds, Liverpool, Manchester, Newcastle, Oxford &amp; <name type="university"/>. </s><s n="s3.3;p35.82">The president of <name type="university"/>'s student union, Brian Duggan is also the chair of the Aldwych group, so as SCS Ltd becomes more involved &amp; develops a reputation within <name type="university"/>'s union, the ability to promote ourselves through the Aldwych group may arise. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0356c-fig.006"><head rend="bold">Fig 4.1.5 - Pattern of sales of SCS System</head></figure><p n="p36.82"><s n="s1.2;p36.82">Customer buying patterns are predicted to be as fig 4.1.1 shows. </s><s n="s2.2;p36.82">The buying patterns will be the inverse of union activity as the majority of the installations will take place during student vacations when union activity is much lower than during term time. </s></p></div3></div2><div2><head rend="bold">4 ii) The Competition</head><p n="p37.82"><s n="s1.2;p37.82">There are only two UK companies who produce a similar product to ours. </s><s n="s2.2;p37.82">These companies are Brulines Ltd and Nucleus Data Ltd, who both offer a system that provides pub chains with information for volumes of each beverage dispensed at their tenant run establishments. </s></p><p n="p38.82"><s n="s1.3;p38.82">According to the FAME database, Brulines Ltd is a Very Large company; in 2006 they turned over £2.71 million, at a profit margin of 22.53% and a return on capital employed of 68.75%. </s><s n="s2.3;p38.82">This suggests that the company has the monopoly of this industry &amp; are operating in a very efficient fashion. </s><s n="s3.3;p38.82">Nucleus Data Ltd is a much smaller company and the financial data available is thus very limited. </s></p><p n="p39.82"><s n="s1.1;p39.82">According to their website <hi rend="sup">3</hi>, in May 2006 Brulines Ltd attempted to float on the stock market twice, however, after recommendations from shareholders due to volatile market conditions, decided to withdraw this intention in June 2006. </s></p><p n="p40.82"><s n="s1.1;p40.82">Brulines Ltd supply their system to many of the large UK pub chains - Punch Taverns, Greene Kings, Enterprise Inns etc, who install "the EDISbox" into their establishments. </s></p><p n="p41.82"><s n="s1.2;p41.82">Brulines' system, however, is intended to be used in tenant run establishments as a way to prevent tenants from taking a greater share of the pub's profit than they are entitled to. </s><s n="s2.2;p41.82">Our product is intended to be installed into much larger, privately owned establishments that have many members of bar staff, with a greater emphasis on preventing bar staff pilfering. </s></p><p n="p42.82"><s n="s1.2;p42.82">Brulines Ltd market their product to small public houses, having installed the system into 14,000 premises owned by only 20 pub chains. </s><s n="s2.2;p42.82">They have thus developed a strong hold on this market, which excludes our niche and thus operations shall not be affected by our position in the market, meaning that their response to our entry may be none. </s></p><p n="p43.82"><s n="s1.2;p43.82">Because we have chosen to market our product in such a small niche, Brulines Ltd will not act in a sense that we are in direct competition with them. </s><s n="s2.2;p43.82">Penetration of the chosen niche will allow us entry to the market, allowing us in future to branch out to market our product to other segments of the market, such as privately ran nightclubs. </s></p><p n="p44.82"><s n="s1.1;p44.82">The highly differentiated nature of our product which is aimed at a specific niche of the market means that once we have penetrated the market, and continue to grow as a company whilst reducing production costs, we will set in place a barrier to entry for any potential competitors. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">4 iii) Market &amp; Sales</head><p n="p45.82"><s n="s1.2;p45.82">As fig 4.3.2 shows, customers will be reached via direct contact, and leaflets that highlight the benefits that our product has to offer the companies. </s><s n="s2.2;p45.82">Personal letters to the managers of each establishment would furthermore create an awareness of our system. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0356c-fig.007"><head rend="bold">Fig 4.3.1 - Market positioning of SCS System</head></figure><p n="p46.82"><s n="s1.1;p46.82">Each system that is installed will have a certain degree of uniqueness - consultations will take place with the manager of each student union bar to decide upon a specification to meet the requirements of the location. </s></p><p n="p47.82"><s n="s1.2;p47.82">A basic unit will consist of 4 flow meters, of which a venue of similar size to <name type="university"/>'s will require approximately 8 to provide full accommodation for all of their beer lines. </s><s n="s2.2;p47.82">A complete installation of this size will cost £16,000, working out at £2000 per unit, although this will vary depending on the size of the installation. </s></p><p n="p48.82"><s n="s1.2;p48.82">To minimise costs in the starting up of the company, all of the field services will be carried out by the directors. </s><s n="s2.2;p48.82">The field services that will be required are as follows: </s></p><list type="bulleted"><item>Initial consultation to determine requirements,</item><item>Complete installation of the system into the establishment,</item><item>Tutorial to demonstrate to staff supervisors the functionalities of the product.</item></list><table id="BAWE_0356c-tab.001"><head rend="bold">Fig 4.3.2 - Matrix of Promotion Strategy</head><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p49.82"><s n="s1.2;p49.82">A prototype of the system is currently installed into the University of <name type="university"/>'s students' union. </s><s n="s2.2;p49.82">Negotiations are underway to carry out a complete install of the system - a project that could be worth £16,000. </s></p><p n="p50.82"><s n="s1.1;p50.82">Further consultations are in progress with Loughborough students' union who are, like <name type="university"/>, a campus based University &amp; could considerably benefit from the system. </s></p><p n="p51.82"><s n="s1.1;p51.82">As Fig 4.3.1 shows, do not trade through an agent, wholesaler or retailer &amp; instead, have chosen to distribute the system directly to the customer, with the aim of maximising the proportion of the sales of the systems that we, as the original producer, receive. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0356c-fig.008"><head><hi rend="bold">Fig 4.3.3 - Diagram of Planned</hi> <hi rend="bold">Distribution Channels</hi></head></figure></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined italic">Section 5 - Manufacturing &amp; Operations</head><p n="p52.82"><s n="s1.1;p52.82">Our operations and decision making process will be carried in the main premises based in the UK. </s></p><p n="p53.82"><s n="s1.1;p53.82">At the first stage we think that we are going to be based in one of our residential premises in order to avoid the high cost of renting or leasing a large office. </s></p><p n="p54.82"><s n="s1.2;p54.82">Therefore our current operations capacity in the UK will be 4 people. </s><s n="s2.2;p54.82">The production process and the allocation of its capacity will be done by our sub contractors. </s></p><p n="p55.82"><s n="s1.2;p55.82">Later on once the company is stable and profitable we think to lease a business office which is located in a large business site. </s><s n="s2.2;p55.82">Additionally once there is a higher demand of our products then we will consider working with larger sub contractors. </s></p><p n="p56.82"><s n="s1.2;p56.82">In terms of personal as I mentioned before there will be 4 people in total. </s><s n="s2.2;p56.82">Once we move to bigger premises we would be able to employ more staff depending on the workload and in the areas of need. </s></p><p n="p57.82"><s n="s1.3;p57.82">Our communication to our customers and suppliers will be carried through the internet and telephone. </s><s n="s2.3;p57.82">All our calculations and plans are done using special programs on our notebooks. </s><s n="s3.3;p57.82">Later on once we have the opportunity to move to an office we will invest in IT facilities. </s></p><div2><head rend="bold">Manufacturing capability:</head><p n="p58.82"><s n="s1.6;p58.82">From sub contractors we will buy in products such as the flow meter, the CPU for the self automated hardware and a simple id checking system. </s><s n="s2.6;p58.82">At the beginning stages we will put together the self automated hardware ourselves. </s><s n="s3.6;p58.82">The reason is because we already used a prototype and tested it at a student union at the University of <name type="university"/> where minor problems occurred. </s><s n="s4.6;p58.82">Also it has to be said that we will cut cost since we can avoid salaries for the technical staff at the initial stages. </s><s n="s5.6;p58.82">Later on at the stages of profitability and growth we are going to invest in sub contractors outsourcing our production. </s><s n="s6.6;p58.82">In order to avoid problems such as product defects or a large scale product failure we will have strict quality control processes provided to our suppliers/sub contractors. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">Sources of supply:</head><p n="p59.82"><s n="s1.1;p59.82">In order to have the right supply we need to identify the most important facts that we expect from our suppliers such as reliability, quality, and value for money as well as strong service and clear communication and most importantly a financial security. </s></p><p n="p60.82"><s n="s1.1;p60.82">The sources we are going to use to identify the right supplier down to our needs are recommendations, directories, trade associations, business advisers and exhibitions. </s></p><p n="p61.82"><s n="s1.3;p61.82">Once we have found suppliers down to our needs we will contact them and ask them for a written quotation for half a year or even longer. </s><s n="s2.3;p61.82">Then we will compare terms and conditions of suppliers. </s><s n="s3.3;p61.82">If we find various suppliers that are suitable to us we will go ahead to draw up contracts by negotiating terms and conditions that as such our payment method are shares and loans and maximum delivery time is varying. </s></p><p n="p62.82"><s n="s1.3;p62.82">It has to be said that more than one supplier is needed. </s><s n="s2.3;p62.82">The reason is because we think that only one supplier is too risky to play with even if we have ordered a single piece of a specific raw material. </s><s n="s3.3;p62.82">The reason is because our supplier might be in financial debt or another problem might have occurred during production or transportation and also we might not have the opportunity to pay in cheque beforehand. </s></p><p n="p63.82"><s n="s1.1;p63.82">Since we think that we are going to outsource our supply and production to another country in near future where suppliers can supply and produce much cheaper then we will also have the need of skilled labour in International Relations and Business Studies. </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined italic">Section 6 - Management</head><p n="p64.82"><s n="s1.5;p64.82">SCS Ltd is current operated from <name type="student name"/>'s home address in Lemington Spa, <name type="university"/>shire. <name type="student name"/> mainly manages the company as the company director and the other members of the board of directors provide the best possible support to smoothly drive the company to its goals satisfying our supplier and customer needs. </s><s n="s2.5;p64.82">The management team consists of members with the necessary skills required for the smooth flow of the company. </s><s n="s3.5;p64.82">Since all members are engineers the project's technical division would be a surplus. </s><s n="s4.5;p64.82">The financial sector and the marketing sector would be covered since <name type="student name"/> and <name type="student name"/> have had past work experience and have specialised in these sectors. </s><s n="s5.5;p64.82">The international business would be covered by <name type="student name"/> because of his international experiences and interactions. </s></p><p n="p65.82"><s n="s1.1;p65.82"><name type="student name"/> (Company president), is mainly responsible for the overall management of the firm and the other members of the board of directors look up to him as a good leadership. </s></p><p n="p66.82"><s n="s1.1;p66.82"><name type="student name"/> (Chief engineer), is dedicated mainly to manufacturing our product, design and assembly. </s></p><p n="p67.82"><s n="s1.2;p67.82"><name type="student name"/> (Research analyst), is responsible for developing our current product with new technology and additions. </s><s n="s2.2;p67.82">He is responsible for marketing sector of the product to a certain degree. </s></p><p n="p68.82"><s n="s1.1;p68.82"><name type="student name"/> (Human resource and finance manager), is mainly responsible for the well being of the co-workers and the financial sector of the firm. </s></p><table id="BAWE_0356c-tab.002"><row><cell/></row></table></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined italic">Section 7 Financial Advice</head><p n="p69.82"/></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined italic">Section 8 - Risks &amp; Rewards</head><p n="p70.82"><s n="s1.1;p70.82">Typical risks that may be faced by the company upon start-up are as follows: </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p71.82"><s n="s1.2;p71.82">An insufficient amount of time may have been predicted for start-up processes. </s><s n="s2.2;p71.82">This risk may be reduced by utilising the seasonality of the company's activity - the quiet periods during university term time can be employed to orientate &amp; prepare the business for periods of high level of activity. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p72.82"><s n="s1.2;p72.82">Inaccuracies in financial forecasts, which could lead to cash flow problems. </s><s n="s2.2;p72.82">By pitching our sales price high, underestimations in financial forecasts will be absorbed by this high margin. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p73.82"><s n="s1.2;p73.82">Offering discounts because of the temptation of revenue. </s><s n="s2.2;p73.82">This risk must be minimised by staying focused as a business, to maintain a high level of maturity - strong profit margins &amp; a healthy cash flow are more beneficial to the company than volume of sales. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p74.82"><s n="s1.2;p74.82">Pressure on the management to have to cope with every aspect of the business, which could lead to a loss of focus on the original plan. </s><s n="s2.2;p74.82">The diverse range of experience (including production processes, leadership ability &amp; experience in running drinking establishments) that the management bring to the company mean that we know &amp; can familiarise ourselves with the business market that we are entering, which will allow us to remain focused &amp; manage ourselves through the situations that we are likely to encounter. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p75.82"><s n="s1.1;p75.82">Promotional strategy may not be as effective as originally hoped, although the risk is reduced as we shall be mostly pitching the product directly to the businesses &amp; the promotional strategy is not crucial. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p76.82"><s n="s1.2;p76.82">Time to establish relationships with suppliers may be greater than initially anticipated &amp; may furthermore cause an issue where credit for the business is concerned. </s><s n="s2.2;p76.82">The reliability &amp; quality of suppliers may cause concern; however, by building up relationships over long periods of time, we hope to benefit from loyalty. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p77.82"><s n="s1.2;p77.82">Receiving money from customers. </s><s n="s2.2;p77.82">Being a new business, our bargaining position is not yet strong, however, this risk is reduced by the fact that we are targeting a niche of students' unions who have established themselves over a length of time as professional organisations, as opposed to pitching our product to rough &amp; disreputable venues. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p78.82"><s n="s1.4;p78.82">Time, cost &amp; availability may cause problems when it comes to finding premises. </s><s n="s2.4;p78.82">Upon start-up the business will not be in any great need for premises - for the first few projects, the ability to operate from home will alleviate this requirement. </s><s n="s3.4;p78.82">Once the business establishes itself, the need to obtain premises to operate from will be such that we shall transfer operations. </s><s n="s4.4;p78.82">Such a time will not be for some time, allowing us time, as &amp; when necessary to find a suitable location. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined italic">Section 9 - Objectives &amp; Milestones</head><p n="p79.82"><s n="s1.4;p79.82">The current design of the LiquiSaver is a feasible design which allows the company to proceed with the project. </s><s n="s2.4;p79.82">We have submitted the necessary documentation for the patent which is pending. </s><s n="s3.4;p79.82">The design of the flow meters, the CPU with the wireless connections and the design for the sensors are finalised. </s><s n="s4.4;p79.82">The main objective would be to develop the current design and bring in state of the art technology to our product. </s></p><p n="p80.82"><s n="s1.2;p80.82">The main objective of the finance department and the company as a whole is to succeed in bringing business angels to invest £70,000 in our firm for 20% of the company as equity. </s><s n="s2.2;p80.82">The company plans to achieve a net profit of about £100,000 by the end of our first business year. </s></p><p n="p81.82"><s n="s1.2;p81.82">The Company is fully managed by our board of directors and each member of the board of directors currently has an equal share (25%) in the company. </s><s n="s2.2;p81.82">We plan to employ more staff after we expand which would require a new business property when the work load increases with time. </s></p><p n="p82.82"><s n="s1.3;p82.82">We currently have contacted our foreign suppliers for the purpose of production of our device. </s><s n="s2.3;p82.82">We previewed our design to the foreign suppliers after applying for the patent and they have agreed with the design and proved that it is feasible to proceed with the plan. </s><s n="s3.3;p82.82">Our main objective would be to have a healthy relationship with our international suppliers which would emphasize on reliability, Quality, value for money and financial security. </s></p></div1></body><back><div1 type="appendix"><head rend="underlined italic">Appendicies</head><p/></div1><div1 type="bibliography"><head rend="underlined italic">References</head><p>Mintel Report "Pub Visiting - UK - October 2006" Subsection, 'The Consumer Economy' Accessed 05/01/07</p><p>Lecture Program "Starting a Business" by Nigel Sykes, Francis Green &amp; Karen Bradbury. Lecture 24 - Feedback from "Victor Takes Off"</p><p>Brulines Announces Intention to Float on AIM - <seg type="URL" n="http://www.brulines.com/news_may2006.htm"/></p><p>x </p></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
