<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_0356g" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Lecture Portfolio</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">The document has a title page which contains:
document title
title part</note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">deleted: header: student name; footer: page numbers</note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">Evaluated as candidate compound assignment. Assigned to S4: set of tasks/questions/exercises: non-compound</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">1</p><p n="date">2006-02</p><p n="module title">The Aesthetics of Design</p><p n="module code">ES177</p><p n="genre family">Exercise</p><p n="discipline">Engineering</p><p n="disciplinary group">PS</p><p n="grade">M</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">3666</p><p n="number of s-units">156</p><p n="number of p">65</p><p n="number of tables">0</p><p n="number of figures">47</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">0</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">0</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">23.5</p><p n="average s-units per p">2.4</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">complex but non-compound assignment (see notesStmt for details)</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">m</p><p n="year of birth">1986</p><p n="first language">Sinhala</p><p n="education">OSA</p><p n="course">Engineering Business Management</p><p n="student ID">0356</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><titlePart><hi rend="underlined bold">University of <name type="university"/></hi><hi rend="bold"> School of Engineering</hi></titlePart><docTitle><titlePart>The Aesthetics of Design (ES177) Lecture Portfolio</titlePart></docTitle><titlePart>By <name type="student name"/><name type="student ID"/></titlePart><titlePart>Module name: [The Aesthetics of design] Module code: [ES 177]</titlePart></titlePage><div1 type="toc" n="1"><head>Table of Contents</head><p/></div1></front><body><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Lecture 2 - Assignment</head><figure id="BAWE_0356g-fig.001"><head>1. <hi rend="bold">Point</hi></head></figure><figure id="BAWE_0356g-pic.001"><head>2. <hi rend="bold">Line - horizontal</hi></head></figure><figure id="BAWE_0356g-pic.002"><head>3. <hi rend="bold">Line - Vertical</hi></head></figure><figure id="BAWE_0356g-pic.003"><head>4. <hi rend="bold">Line - Horizontal and Vertical</hi></head></figure><figure id="BAWE_0356g-pic.004"><head>5. <hi rend="bold">Rounded (organic) 3D form from the natural world</hi></head></figure><figure id="BAWE_0356g-pic.005"><head>6. <hi rend="bold">Geometric 3D form from the natural world</hi></head></figure><figure id="BAWE_0356g-pic.006"><head>7. <hi rend="bold">Rounded (organic) man made 3D form</hi></head></figure><figure id="BAWE_0356g-pic.007"><head>8. <hi rend="bold">Geometric man-made 3D form</hi></head></figure><figure id="BAWE_0356g-pic.008"><head>9. <hi rend="bold">Man made product where a feature has been made of tactile texture</hi></head></figure><figure id="BAWE_0356g-pic.009"><head>10. <hi rend="bold">Products which illustrates the idiom "form follows function"</hi></head></figure><figure id="BAWE_0356g-pic.010"><head>11. <hi rend="bold">A product that does not shows "form follows function"</hi></head></figure><p n="p1.65"/></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Lecture 3 - Assignment</head><figure id="BAWE_0356g-pic.011"><head>1. <hi rend="bold">A painting with many hues</hi></head></figure><figure id="BAWE_0356g-pic.012"><head>2. <hi rend="bold">A painting with one hue</hi></head></figure><figure id="BAWE_0356g-pic.013"><head>3. <hi rend="bold">Piet Mondrian</hi> Spatial effect </head></figure><figure id="BAWE_0356g-pic.014"><head>4. <hi rend="bold">Optical colour mixture</hi> Artist - Paul Signac</head></figure><p n="p2.65"><s n="s1.2;p2.65">5. </s><s rend="bold" n="s2.2;p2.65">Positive meanings of green and yellow </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0356g-pic.015"><head> a.)</head></figure><p n="p3.65"><s n="s1.1;p3.65">The colour green in its positive context suggests nature, naturalness and calmness. </s></p><p n="p4.65"><s n="s1.1;p4.65">The picture above shows a very calm and peaceful location with a lot of greenery. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0356g-pic.016"><head>b.)</head></figure><p n="p5.65"><s n="s1.1;p5.65">Yellow suggests victory, joy and happiness. </s></p><p n="p6.65"><s n="s1.1;p6.65">The picture above shows a person with the feeling of victory in a yellow dress and a yellow background. </s></p><p n="p7.65"><s n="s1.2;p7.65">6. </s><s rend="bold" n="s2.2;p7.65">Negative meanings of violet and blue </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0356g-pic.017"><head>a.)</head></figure><p n="p8.65"><s n="s1.1;p8.65">Violet in its negative context means nightmares, madness and negative thoughts. </s></p><p n="p9.65"><s n="s1.1;p9.65">The image above shows an imaginary picture that one would have when he/she is in a bad state of mind. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0356g-pic.018"><head>b.)</head></figure><p n="p10.65"><s n="s1.1;p10.65">Blue in its negative context means depression. </s></p><p n="p11.65"><s n="s1.1;p11.65">The picture above shows a depressing blue image of a thing behind bars and with its background also being blue. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0356g-pic.019"><head>7. <hi rend="bold">Colour illusion</hi></head></figure></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Lecture 4 - assignment</head><div2><head rend="bold">Principles of design</head><figure id="BAWE_0356g-pic.020"><head>1. <hi rend="bold">Symmetrical balance</hi></head></figure><p n="p12.65"><s n="s1.1;p12.65">I chose this picture above because it shows a photograph of perfect symmetry. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0356g-pic.021"><head>2. <hi rend="bold">Asymmetrical balance</hi></head></figure><p n="p13.65"><s n="s1.1;p13.65">Reason for choosing this picture is because it is perfectly balanced and actual line of symmetry is partially visible. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0356g-pic.022"><head>3. <hi rend="bold">Alternating rhythm</hi></head></figure><p n="p14.65"><s n="s1.1;p14.65">I chose this image because it shows alternating rhythm not only on the keyboard but also on the records. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0356g-pic.023"><head>4 <hi rend="bold">. Emphasis by contrast of colour</hi></head></figure><p n="p15.65"><s n="s1.1;p15.65">The reason for picking this picture is because it is a contrast of colour in nature. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0356g-pic.024"><head>5. <hi rend="bold">Emphasis by contrast of size</hi></head></figure><p n="p16.65"><s n="s1.1;p16.65">This picture had my attention because it is a real situation and it shows perfect contrast of size and colour. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0356g-pic.025"><head>6. <hi rend="bold">Unity</hi></head></figure><p n="p17.65"><s n="s1.2;p17.65">The picture above shows unity because the pen is nicely designed with the silver top part and the golden stem. </s><s n="s2.2;p17.65">Therefore I chose this picture. </s></p><p n="p18.65"><s n="s1.1;p18.65">The picture above was chosen by me because the chair's green and silver sections are designed in unity and the brown set of chairs at the back is in unity with the main green chair. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">Golden section</head><figure id="BAWE_0356g-pic.026"><head>The <hi rend="bold">Golden Section in painting</hi></head></figure><p n="p19.65"><s n="s1.1;p19.65">I chose the picture above because it clearly showed the golden section using deferent colours and in different directions. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0356g-pic.027"><head>8. <hi rend="bold">The Golden Section in architecture</hi></head></figure><p n="p20.65"><s n="s1.2;p20.65">This image was chosen by me because it is ancient architecture showing golden section. </s><s n="s2.2;p20.65">The golden section used in the buildings is clearly visible. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0356g-pic.028"><head rend="bold">The golden Section in nature</head></figure><p n="p21.65"><s n="s1.1;p21.65">The image above was chosen because the picture uses golden section and the stem shown in the picture uses golden section. </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Lecture 5 - Assignment</head><div2><head>1. <hi rend="bold">Atmospheric perspective</hi></head><figure id="BAWE_0356g-pic.029"/><p n="p22.65"><s n="s1.1;p22.65">The painting above shows atmospheric perspective and I picked this image because it shows the fading colour of the different planes well. </s></p></div2><div2><head>2. <hi rend="bold">Single Point Perspective</hi></head><figure id="BAWE_0356g-pic.030"/><p n="p23.65"><s n="s1.1;p23.65">The above photograph was picked by me because it shows the single point perspective very well and the colours used on the surfaces make it look even better. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0356g-pic.031"/><p n="p24.65"><s n="s1.1;p24.65">I picked the image above because it shows single point perspective and it shows how the method is used for designing buildings. </s></p></div2><div2><head>3. <hi rend="bold">Two Point Perspective</hi></head><figure id="BAWE_0356g-pic.032"/><p n="p25.65"><s n="s1.1;p25.65">The painting above had my attention because of the way the artist have used the two point perspective to give the painting a 3D view. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0356g-pic.033"/><p n="p26.65"><s n="s1.1;p26.65">The above sketch shows two point perspective very well and this image is a perfect picture to define two point perspective, therefore I picked this sketch. </s></p></div2><div2><head>4. <hi rend="bold">Three point Perspective</hi></head><figure id="BAWE_0356g-pic.034"/><p n="p27.65"><s n="s1.1;p27.65">The photograph above is a good picture to define three point perspective in real life and it shows how the method works in architecture, therefore I picked this image. </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="bold">Lecture 6 - Assignment</hi> <hi rend="underlined">The Coca-Cola bottle</hi></head><figure id="BAWE_0356g-pic.035"/><p n="p28.65"><s n="s1.3;p28.65">The C0ca - Cola bottle is probably the most easily recognisable bottle in the world. </s><s n="s2.3;p28.65">The bottle was first created by Root Glass Company in Indiana and the bottle's unique fluted sides and bulging middle was inspired by the shape of an African kola nut. </s><s n="s3.3;p28.65">The bottle was described by the pop artist Andy Warhol as 'the design icon of the decade'. </s></p><p n="p29.65"><s n="s1.3;p29.65">The smooth, organically shaped bottle was first produced in 1900's and this was a time when the actual Coca - Cola drink and the containers were being imitated. </s><s n="s2.3;p29.65">At this time the company came out with a brief which sounded something like: 'A Coca - Cola bottle which a person will recognise as a Coca - Cola bottle even if he feels it in the dark. </s><s n="s3.3;p29.65">The Coca - Cola bottle should be shaped that, even if broken, one could tell at a glance what it was.' </s></p><p n="p30.65"><s n="s1.5;p30.65">This bottle was called Hobble skirt Coke because of its shape and the bottle was produced in variety of colours such as aqua, clear, ice blue, and green at that time. </s><s n="s2.5;p30.65">The bottles produced after that till today all have a slight green tint except for the bottles made during 1942-45. </s><s n="s3.5;p30.65">These bottles were blue due to the copper shortage during World War II. The copper is the material which gives the green colour to the glass. </s><s n="s4.5;p30.65">This bottle symbolized the American spirit during the World War II and the company pledged that the U.S forces could count on Coca - Cola wherever they go. </s><s n="s5.5;p30.65">The company then opened 64 bottling plants through out the world. </s></p><p n="p31.65"><s n="s1.4;p31.65">The bottle design was re-launched in Britain in 1997 and the company then conducted a study which confirmed that the consumers still prefer to have the Coca - Cola drink in a glass bottle. </s><s n="s2.4;p31.65">This design of the bottle has been a great success because of its appeal to the consumers. </s><s n="s3.4;p31.65">The bottle is shaped as a feminine body (hobble skirt) and it has an easy grip because of its fluted shape and bulging middle. </s><s n="s4.4;p31.65">Even a child can hold on to the bottle because of the bottle's narrow body, regardless of its weight and the size of his hand. </s></p><p n="p32.65"><s n="s1.5;p32.65">The company has given the bottle a slight tint of green which also appeals to the crowd. </s><s n="s2.5;p32.65">This tint of colour is more interesting than a plane bottle and when the drink is in the bottle it looks very tempting. </s><s n="s3.5;p32.65">The colour of the drink with the slight tint of green of the glass bottle shows vivid colours at different angles when light hits on it and this effect attracts especially small children towards the drink. </s><s n="s4.5;p32.65">The company had produced bottles with aqua, clear, ice blue, and green tints and in some cases bottles even had two tones of colour such as green and blue but we are only able to seen bottles with a green tone in it. </s><s n="s5.5;p32.65">Another tactic the company has used is to emboss the drink's name Coca - Cola on the glass bottle. </s></p><p n="p33.65"><s n="s1.1;p33.65">Because of all the design tactics they have used the Coca - Cola bottle has been a great success and it is still sold in more than 200 countries around the world. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="bold">Lecture 7 - Assignment</hi> <hi rend="underlined">The Original Volkswagen Beetle</hi></head><figure id="BAWE_0356g-pic.036"/><p n="p34.65"><s n="s1.3;p34.65">In 1930's the leader of the Nazi Germany Adolf Hitler ordered Ferdinand Porsche to create a vehicle for the people. </s><s n="s2.3;p34.65">That was the start of Volkswagen. </s><s n="s3.3;p34.65">Porsche started to create prototype designs but he was given a certain criteria that he had to stick to such as a maximum speed of 100 km/h, maximum weight of 650 kg, air - cooled engine with 26 hp, a fuel consumption of 7 l per 100 km and should also be cheap. </s></p><p n="p35.65"><s n="s1.6;p35.65">Porsche designed several models and finally the first Volkswagen car was presented in 1938 with all the above specifications required by Hitler. </s><s n="s2.6;p35.65">The car's engine was located at the rear of the car and the car was of a rather weird shape, it was very round. </s><s n="s3.6;p35.65">An American reporter thought that it looked like an insect and called it the Beetle. </s><s n="s4.6;p35.65">This was the reason for the car to get its popular name 'Beetle'. </s><s n="s5.6;p35.65">Volkswagen GmbH was founded in 1939 and in the first stages of the company they produced military vehicles for World War II. Soon after the war the company started producing cars and the car became popular in Europe. </s><s n="s6.6;p35.65">The company had its great success after starting to export Beetles to Holland in 1947 and after this the company's production increased and the specifications of the vehicle increased in order to keep the firm ahead in the business. </s></p><p n="p36.65"><s n="s1.6;p36.65">The first Beetle had split wind screens but then these were replaced by a single curved wind screen but this was again substituted by a wide flat wind screen. </s><s n="s2.6;p36.65">All these models were accepted by the customers because of their preference towards the car. </s><s n="s3.6;p36.65">The car always had round head lamps and rear lamps to keep its unique design and to continue the meaning of 'Beetle'. </s><s n="s4.6;p36.65">The car continued to have its round shaped body and round rear mirrors, again to represent a beetle. </s><s n="s5.6;p36.65">Since the customers kept on asking for this popular design and the sales continued to increase the firm painted the car in colours like red, white and yellow to make the look actually like a Beetle. </s><s n="s6.6;p36.65">The customers liked the feeling of driving in such a car and the company's sales kept on increasing. </s></p><p n="p37.65"><s n="s1.3;p37.65">The company had some unique rim designs for the Beetle and the bulky silver rim cup was a unique part of it. </s><s n="s2.3;p37.65">Most rims were light coloured with a darker body colour. </s><s n="s3.3;p37.65">These rims too gave a very unique look to the car and made it look more like a Beetle. </s></p><p n="p38.65"><s n="s1.1;p38.65">All the Beetles had a light toned interior with a dashboard which could occupy a radio set and these options appealed to the crowd. </s></p><p n="p39.65"><s n="s1.3;p39.65">The old Volkswagen Beetle had a great success in the past and because of this the firm decided to come up with the new Beetle, the one we see on the roads today. </s><s n="s2.3;p39.65">The new Beetle has a similar round shape and it is more of a lady's car today. </s><s n="s3.3;p39.65">Both cars have similar properties such as round head and rear lamps and popular colours such as red, white, yellow and black. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="bold">Lecture 8 - Assignment</hi> <hi rend="underlined">Pop Art</hi></head><figure id="BAWE_0356g-pic.037"/><p n="p40.65"><s n="s1.4;p40.65">Pop art first appeared in Great Britain and United States in late 1950's and referred to the interest of many artists who were involved in mass media, comics, advertising and consumer products. </s><s n="s2.4;p40.65">In 1950 customer demand boomed since that was after the World War and it was a time of optimism. </s><s n="s3.4;p40.65">Pop art is interpreted as a reaction to the dominant ideas of abstract expressionism and pop art used to have a popular image of an art that emphasises banal part of a culture which opposed the elitist culture in art. </s><s n="s4.4;p40.65">Pop art usually aims at a very broad audience and is regarded as academic since pop art is widely used in different teaching methods. </s></p><p n="p41.65"><s n="s1.4;p41.65">Pop art was highly influenced by the work of Eduardo Paolozzi in 1953, Jasper Johns, Robert Rauschenberg and British artists such as Richard Hamilton. </s><s n="s2.4;p41.65">Due to this pop art merged with the youth and pop music in 1950's and 60's. </s><s n="s3.4;p41.65">Artists like Peter Blake designed album covers for great musicians such as Elvis Presley and great bands like Beatles. </s><s n="s4.4;p41.65">He used to have images of film stars such as Brigitte Bardot in his pictures just like the artist Andy Warhol used to do in the United States using images of Marilyn Monroe. </s></p><p n="p42.65"><s n="s1.5;p42.65">Andy Warhol started as a commercial illustrator and did shoe advertisements in the beginning. </s><s n="s2.5;p42.65">He first exhibited his work first in 1962 and his "32 Campbell's soup cans" was then showed. </s><s n="s3.5;p42.65">His best work was done within a time span of six years and he was then shot in 1968. </s><s n="s4.5;p42.65">At this time the culture was glutted with information where most people experienced things second or third hand and then there was the role for affectless art. </s><s n="s5.5;p42.65">Andy never worked it out but just embodied it due to that American state of mind where celebrity and a famous name of a brand replaced the sacredness and solidity. </s></p><p n="p43.65"><s n="s1.4;p43.65">In the other hand the artist Roy Lichtenstein used to be the master of the stereotype and the most sophisticated among the major pop artists. </s><s n="s2.4;p43.65">He did not have a very eventful childhood and art which was his main interest was never taught in his primary or high schools. </s><s n="s3.4;p43.65">His first subjects were jazz musicians and after serving in the army during the war he gained his bachelor of fine art and eventually gained his master of fine art. </s><s n="s4.4;p43.65">His proto-pop art work was first painted in 1956 but it was not that successful. </s></p><p n="p44.65"><s n="s1.4;p44.65">Pop art has been used in different ways to approach different types of audience through out the world. </s><s n="s2.4;p44.65">Pop art appeals to the young crowd when it comes to comics and when it comes to advertising different products it appeals to the more mature audience. </s><s n="s3.4;p44.65">This method of conveying ideas is again mainly used in the academic sector since it attracts the attention of the student. </s><s n="s4.4;p44.65">Considering all these factors we could say that pop art plays a great roll in communication in general through out the world regardless of the language, culture or nationality. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="bold">Lecture 9 - Assignment</hi> <hi rend="underlined">Taipei 101</hi></head><figure id="BAWE_0356g-pic.038"/><p n="p45.65"><s n="s1.7;p45.65">Located in Taipei, Taiwan "Taipei 101" now holds the title of the world's tallest building. </s><s n="s2.7;p45.65">Even though Petronas tower one and Petronas tower two still told the title of the world's tallest twin towers Taipei 101 is the tallest individual building in the world. </s><s n="s3.7;p45.65">The tower exceeded the height of the two Petronas towers in late August of 2003. </s><s n="s4.7;p45.65">The tower is the first tallest building in the 21 <hi rend="sup">st</hi> century and Taipei 101 was the first building in the world to exceed the half - kilometre mark in height. </s><s n="s5.7;p45.65">The building is 509 m tall and has hundred and one floors. </s><s n="s6.7;p45.65">This explains the reason why the building is called "Taipei 101". </s><s n="s7.7;p45.65">This giant is one of the few skyscrapers in the world to be inspired by the Chinese architectural designs and this tower's specifications are all based on "8", this number "8" is regarded as a lucky number in ancient Chinese culture. </s></p><p n="p46.65"><s n="s1.7;p46.65">Construction of the tower finished in 2004 but the shopping mall of the tower, 'Taipei 101 mall' officially opened in 13 <hi rend="sup">th</hi> November, 2003, this mall consist of gothic style architecture and modern architecture. </s><s n="s2.7;p46.65">The tower uses an 80 ton tuned mass damping system to stabilise the building and this system is located near the top of the building and is held in an exposed spherical structure between the restaurant level and the observation level. </s><s n="s3.7;p46.65">The elevators fitted in the tower use state of the art technology and safety. </s><s n="s4.7;p46.65">Each elevator is fixed with pressurization and emergency braking systems. </s><s n="s5.7;p46.65">These elevators are designed aerodynamically, and they are the world's first 'Triple Stage Anti - Overshooting System' and each of these elevators costs about $US two million. </s><s n="s6.7;p46.65">These elevators are the world's fastest elevators and they travel upwards at a speed of 60.48 km/h and downwards at a speed of 36.6 km/h, and this building consists of double deck elevators. </s><s n="s7.7;p46.65">Taipei 101 is the most technologically advanced super tall tower in the world and it features very high speed satellite and fibre - optic internet connections throughout the building. </s></p><p n="p47.65"><s n="s1.3;p47.65">The observation deck is the 91 <hi rend="sup">st</hi> floor of the building and this deck is the second highest observation deck in the world. </s><s n="s2.3;p47.65">The tallest observation deck is located in Shanghai World Financial Centre. </s><s n="s3.3;p47.65">The main designs and consultation of the building plans were done by a Feng Shui Master and this building is the only super tall tower made in a highly active earthquake zone in the world. </s></p><p n="p48.65"><s n="s1.3;p48.65">The tower is panelled with a special type of glass which consists of a slight tone of green. </s><s n="s2.3;p48.65">The building's exterior is lit up using powerful spot lights on the edges of each conical sector and each floor is separated by a stream of lights right around the building. </s><s n="s3.3;p48.65">The buildings interior is fitted with stunning arrangements of lights of deferent sorts and the floors of the mall are tiled in vivid patterns to match the walls and the other components. </s></p><p n="p49.65"><s n="s1.1;p49.65">This building has reached one of the highest pinnacles in the history of mankind with its technology and architectural designs, and it will surely remain as a legend for many more years to come. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="bold">Lecture 10 - Assignment</hi> <hi rend="underlined">Mary Quant</hi></head><figure id="BAWE_0356g-pic.039"/><p n="p50.65"><s n="s1.2;p50.65">Mary Quant was born in Kent on the 11 <hi rend="sup">th</hi> February 1934, and she became one of the leading women in UK's fashion industry. </s><s n="s2.2;p50.65">She created the famous 'mini skirts' and 'hot pants' which turned the 1960's fashion world upside down and which is still is high fashion. </s></p><p n="p51.65"><s n="s1.5;p51.65">She created the famous Mini Skirt to liberate the 1960's woman. </s><s n="s2.5;p51.65">After a lot of experimenting, the Mini Skirt was introduced to the fashion world in the late 1950's which turned out to be one of the defining fashions of the decade, and this made Mary Quant an idol in the fashion industry. </s><s n="s3.5;p51.65">The Mini Skirt is a skirt with a hemline which is usually 20cm or more above the knee. </s><s n="s4.5;p51.65">Since 1958, her design skirts kept getting shorter. </s><s n="s5.5;p51.65">This was an improvement she made which is considered to be practical because it enables the women to run for a bus. </s></p><p n="p52.65"><s n="s1.7;p52.65">She attended Goldsmith's Collage where she studied 'Illustration', which is a kind of art where the subject is defined more than its form. </s><s n="s2.7;p52.65">She was offered a job tight after finishing her studies at a firm called 'Couture Milliner'. </s><s n="s3.7;p52.65">She teamed up with her husband Alexander Plunkett Greene, and an accountant named Archie McNair in 1955, to open a clothes boutique in London called 'Bazaar'. </s><s n="s4.7;p52.65">'Mad House Pyjamas' were put up on the launch of Bazaar and was considered a good attempt due to its never before seen looks. </s><s n="s5.7;p52.65">But the Bazaar lacked in variety of clothes, which concerned Mary Quant. </s><s n="s6.7;p52.65">As a result, Mary Quant started working on her own line of clothes. </s><s n="s7.7;p52.65">Her idea was to put out a different type of clothes which she considered to be fun and exciting and she expanded her business by employing few machinists. </s></p><p n="p53.65"><s n="s1.1;p53.65">In addition to her historical Mini Skirt, she is also credited for creating coloured, patterned tights, which is a leg covering garment which extends from the waist all the way to the feet and was supposed to be tight to the skin. </s></p><p n="p54.65"><s n="s1.2;p54.65">In Mid 1960's, Mary Quant reached the pinnacle in her career in fashion design. </s><s n="s2.2;p54.65">This was the time when she put out the 'Dangerously Short Micro-Mini Skirt', plastic raincoats and also she introduced beauty care products such as 'Paint-box' make up. </s></p><p n="p55.65"><s n="s1.2;p55.65">Mary Quant's success with her unique designs brought Bazaar tot the top. </s><s n="s2.2;p55.65">These achievements convinced Quant to expand her Clothing line by opening her second Bazaar showroom in 1961 in Knightsbridge. </s></p><p n="p56.65"><s n="s1.5;p56.65">She was described to be the leading fashion force outside Paris at that era. </s><s n="s2.5;p56.65">All this fame resulted in very high demand in her clothing and to keep supplying these demands Quant started mass production of her garments setting up the Ginger Group. </s><s n="s3.5;p56.65">In the mid 1960's she started exporting her clothing line to USA. Mary Quant was appointed an OBE in 1966 for immense effort she made to improve the fashion in 'Swinging London'. </s><s n="s4.5;p56.65">In the late 1960's, Quant came up with her last big fashion development, "Hot pants". </s><s n="s5.5;p56.65">These pants are also known as 'Short shorts' since they were extremely short. </s></p><p n="p57.65"><s n="s1.1;p57.65">Mary Quant was a woman who revitalised the fashion industry in the 1960's, and her work is definitely one of the main reasons for the present standard of fashion. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Lecture 11 - AssignmentMaxims</head><div2><head>1 <hi rend="bold">. Affordance</hi></head><figure id="BAWE_0356g-pic.040"/><p n="p58.65"><s n="s1.1;p58.65">Affordance is a property where the physical components of the product help the function of it. </s></p><p n="p59.65"><s n="s1.1;p59.65">The picture above is a good example because the handle of the boor gives a good grip and it gives the idea of pulling the door rather than pushing it. </s></p></div2><div2><head>2. <hi rend="bold">Attractiveness Bias</hi></head><figure id="BAWE_0356g-pic.041"><head>Aston Martin DB9 </head></figure><p n="p60.65"><s n="s1.3;p60.65">People prefer to by the car shown above (Aston Martin DB9) in general rather than buy the car shown below (Pegani Zonda). </s><s n="s2.3;p60.65">This is because the design of the car looks very good and it appeals to the crowd. </s><s n="s3.3;p60.65">Performance wise Pegani Zonda is generally better than the Aston Martin and is referred to as a super car but people still prefer to buy the Aston martin for its looks. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0356g-pic.042"><head>Pegani Zonda</head></figure></div2><div2><head>3. <hi rend="bold">Flexibility Usability Trade-off</hi></head><figure id="BAWE_0356g-pic.043"><head>Nokia 3210</head></figure><p n="p61.65"><s n="s1.3;p61.65">The mobile phone used above is one of the most user friendly phones ever made. </s><s n="s2.3;p61.65">This phone has only a little number of keys and the keys are comparatively big. </s><s n="s3.3;p61.65">Therefore it is easy to use. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0356g-pic.044"><head>Nokia N series</head></figure><p n="p62.65"><s n="s1.1;p62.65">The Nokia phone shown above is a phone from the N series and has a great number of options, but this phone is very hard to use since it has a lot of keys and they are small. </s></p></div2><div2><head>4. <hi rend="bold">Proximity</hi></head><figure id="BAWE_0356g-pic.045"/><p n="p63.65"><s n="s1.2;p63.65">This lamp show above is a nice design but the switch for the bulb is no to be seen. </s><s n="s2.2;p63.65">This makes it hard for the user to figure out the way of switching it on. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0356g-pic.046"/><p n="p64.65"><s n="s1.2;p64.65">The lamp shown above in the other had is a very simple design but it has its only switch right on top of the base of the lamp. </s><s n="s2.2;p64.65">Therefore it makes it very easy for the user to figure out the way of switch it on. </s></p></div2><div2><head>5. <hi rend="bold">Ockham's Razor</hi></head><figure id="BAWE_0356g-pic.047"/><p n="p65.65"><s n="s1.3;p65.65">The glass shown above is a very simple design but it full fills all its requirements. </s><s n="s2.3;p65.65">The glass does not have additional parts attached to it. </s><s n="s3.3;p65.65">It has a good heavy base for the stability. </s></p></div2></div1></body><back/></text></TEI.2>
