<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_0356e" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Peugeot Motor Company Ltd</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">The document has a title page which contains:
document title
title part</note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">deleted: header: student number; footer: page numbers</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">1</p><p n="date">2006-01</p><p n="module title">Economics and Structure of Industry</p><p n="module code">ES175</p><p n="genre family">Case study</p><p n="discipline">Engineering</p><p n="disciplinary group">PS</p><p n="grade">D</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">1032</p><p n="number of s-units">38</p><p n="number of p">24</p><p n="number of tables">1</p><p n="number of figures">4</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">1</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">0</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">27.2</p><p n="average s-units per p">1.6</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">m</p><p n="year of birth">1986</p><p n="first language">Sinhala</p><p n="education">OSA</p><p n="course">Engineering Business Management</p><p n="student ID">0356</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><docTitle><titlePart rend="underlined bold">Peugeot Motor Company Ltd UK</titlePart></docTitle><titlePart>Marketing/Industry Exercise Report ES 175<name type="student ID"/><name type="student name"/></titlePart><docTitle><titlePart><hi rend="underlined bold">Marketing Exercise Report</hi><hi rend="bold"> Peugeot Motor Company Ltd, UK</hi></titlePart></docTitle></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined">General Structure of the Automobile Manufacturing Industry</head><p n="p1.24"><s n="s1.3;p1.24">The automobile manufacturing industry is one of the largest industries and this market is concentrated with few large firms which hold large percentages of the market share. </s><s n="s2.3;p1.24">The firms involved in this industry could be described as 'cash cows' (Boston consultant group matrix) because they hold a great percentage of the market share and the growth rate of the market is very low. </s><s n="s3.3;p1.24">Peugeot Motor Company Ltd, UK is a firm in this industry and could be described as a cash cow. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined">Overview of the similar Firms Competing with Peugeot Motor Company Ltd, UK</head><p n="p2.24"><s n="s1.2;p2.24">The similar firms are Toyota Motor Manufacturing, France with an annual turnover of 2, 172, 065 th USD, General Motors, Belgium with an annual turnover of 1, 802, 406 th USD and Iveco France SA with an annual turnover of 1,887, 627 th USD, etc. </s><s n="s2.2;p2.24">All these firms have a decent percentage of the market share and could be again described as cash cows. </s></p><p n="p3.24"><s n="s1.1;p3.24">(Sourceof the numerical data given above:-<seg type="URL" n="http://amadeus.bvdep.com/cgi/template.dll"/>) </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0356e-fig.001"/><p n="p4.24"><s n="s1.1;p4.24">Above is a pie-chart of the peer firms competing with Peugeot Ltd, UK with respect to the turnover of the firms. </s></p><p n="p5.24"><s n="s1.1;p5.24">(Source of the pie-chart:-<seg type="URL" n="http://amadeus.bvdep.com/cgi/template.dl"/>) </s></p><p n="p6.24"><s n="s1.1;p6.24">The firms competing with Peugeot Motor Company Ltd, UK are all large firms with a good market share and their annual turnovers has been between 1,500,000 th USD and 2,500,000 th USD. Their turnovers are very similar to one another indicating that there is equal competition among the firms. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined">Structure and Performance of Peugeot Motor Company Ltd, UK</head><div2><head rend="bold">General information and Structure of Peugeot Motor Company Ltd, UK</head><p n="p7.24"><s n="s1.1;p7.24">UK SIC Code- 3410 </s></p><p n="p8.24"><s n="s1.5;p8.24">The firm is one of the UK's largest and the stock plant is situated in Humber Road, Coventry, west midlands with a staff of 4, 108. </s><s n="s2.5;p8.24">The firm is a limited liability company with 2 holdings and was incorporated on 25 <hi rend="sup">th</hi> January 2002. </s><s n="s3.5;p8.24">The firm belongs to the peer group of 4310-manufacture of motor vehicles (VL: very large company). </s><s n="s4.5;p8.24">The company's industrial sites hold the ISO 14001 certificate and the company maintains a high-tech production plant with efficient robots and a computerised part delivery system(computer on each folk lift) which works four days a week. </s><s n="s5.5;p8.24">Lot of employees are French and the employees are paid to learn French with the two French teachers provided by the company. </s></p><p n="p9.24"><s n="s1.2;p9.24">60% of the metal required is imported from France and 90% of the companies which manufacture all kinds of materials for the cars are owned by Peugeot. </s><s n="s2.2;p9.24">The plant uses high-tech robots which clean the welding chips them selves and a flat machine to clean the dust off the paint which uses ostrich feathers. </s></p><p n="p10.24"><s n="s1.2;p10.24">All waists are burnt to heat up the paint plant. </s><s n="s2.2;p10.24">Each car consists of a Siemens computer and each vehicle has been given a barcode. </s></p><list type="simple"><head>The current directors of the company are: - Mr. J.P Jombart</head><item> Mr. F.P Favre</item><item> Mr. M.J Lynch</item><item> Mr. R. Vardanega</item><item> Mr. R.A Lewis. </item></list><p n="p11.24"><s n="s1.2;p11.24">The plant site Peugeot motor company Ltd, UK used to be a arms manufacturing centre for the second world war and the site was then bought over by Chrysler group (another automobile manufacturer). </s><s n="s2.2;p11.24">The site was then bought over by Peugeot Ltd, which are its current owners. </s></p><p n="p12.24"><s n="s1.1;p12.24">(sources:- <seg type="URL" n="http://www2"/>.<name type="university"/>.ac.uk/fac/sci/eng/euo/modules/year1/es175/es175-exercise1/peugeot/ and PSA Peugeot citroen The Group in 2005(brochure)) </s></p></div2><div2><head><hi rend="bold">Performance of Peugeot</hi> <hi rend="bold">Motor Company Ltd, UK</hi></head><p n="p13.24"><s n="s1.1;p13.24">Peugeot Motor Company Ltd, UK had a turnover of 534, 300 th GBP in 2002, 1, 117, 300 th GBP in 2003 and 1, 031, 100 th GBP in 2004 and therefore resulting in an average turnover of 894, 233 th GBP. </s></p><p n="p14.24"><s n="s1.1;p14.24">The firm has had a great improvement in year 2003 and they have been able to keep the same standard in 2004. their average profit margin has been 1.13% for years 2002, 2003 and 2004. </s></p><p n="p15.24"><s n="s1.1;p15.24">When comparing the turnovers of 2002 and 2003 there has been a great improvement in 2003 but since the profit margin in 2003 is low the profit before taxation in 2003 does not give such a great value. </s></p><p n="p16.24"><s n="s1.1;p16.24">Below is a table consisting information about comparison of turnovers,etc in 2002 and 2003, </s></p><table id="BAWE_0356e-tab.001"><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p17.24"><s n="s1.1;p17.24">(sources:<seg type="URL" n="http://www2"/>.<name type="university"/>.ac.uk/fac/sci/eng/euo/modules/year1/es175/es175-exercise1/peugeot/) </s></p><p n="p18.24"><s n="s1.1;p18.24">Below are bar-charts of the annual turnover and percentage profit margin of Peugeot Motor Company Ltd, UK for years 2002, 2003, and 2004, </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0356e-fig.002"><head rend="underlined">Turnover bar-chart</head></figure><figure id="BAWE_0356e-fig.003"><head rend="underlined">Profit margin bar-chart</head></figure><p n="p19.24"><s n="s1.1;p19.24">Below is a graphical presentation of the evolution of the key variables during years 2002, 2003 and 2004, </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0356e-fig.004"/><p n="p20.24"><s n="s1.1;p20.24">The above graph shows that operating revenue, cash flow, profit and shareholders funds have been increased over the three year and overall it shows a good positive growth. </s></p><p n="p21.24"><s n="s1.1;p21.24">(sources:- <seg type="URL" n="http://amadeus.bvdep.com/cgi/template.dll"/>) </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined">The most viable strategy and recommended choice for an entrepreneur</head><div2><head rend="bold">Most viable strategy</head><p n="p22.24"><s n="s1.3;p22.24">The most viable strategy for a new entrant would be to <hi rend="bold">differentiate</hi> his/her product. </s><s n="s2.3;p22.24">This is because the market the entrant looking at is a complex monopoly and gaining market share is difficult since the market is very established. </s><s n="s3.3;p22.24">The new entrant would have difficulties gaining market share through low price since the very big companies that already exist which acts as a oligopoly have a low profit margin and a good market share; therefore they could easily start a price war where the new entrant can not exist. </s></p><p n="p23.24"><s n="s1.1;p23.24">By differentiating the product the new entrant could concentrate on a more specific small market and since there is no oligopoly the new entrant can enter the market and gain market share easily. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">Recommended choice for an entrepreneur </head><p n="p24.24"><s n="s1.3;p24.24">The entrepreneur should acquire the company since it already has a good market share and advertising for a new brand name would not be necessary. </s><s n="s2.3;p24.24">The firm has improved during the last few years and will show a positive growth in the future. </s><s n="s3.3;p24.24">Since the market the firm acts in is an oligopoly, it would be difficult to enter the market as a new company to compete with the current firm and starting a price war with the current firm is not possible because the current firm has a good market share and low profit margin. </s></p></div2></div1></body><back/></text></TEI.2>
