<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_0357b" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>The scale plan of what you intended the robot to draw</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">Language used in quote: <foreign id="English">English</foreign></note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">appendices: images drawn by hand and robot</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">3</p><p n="date">unknown</p><p n="module title">unknown</p><p n="module code">ES372</p><p n="genre family">Exercise</p><p n="discipline">Engineering</p><p n="disciplinary group">PS</p><p n="grade">unknown</p><p n="number of authors">unknown</p><p n="number of words">964</p><p n="number of s-units">33</p><p n="number of p">13</p><p n="number of tables">0</p><p n="number of figures">1</p><p n="number of block quotes">1</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">0</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">4</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">29.2</p><p n="average s-units per p">2.5</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">f</p><p n="year of birth">1985</p><p n="first language">Chinese Cantonese</p><p n="education">unknown</p><p n="course">Electrical Engineering</p><p n="student ID">0357</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front/><body><div1 type="section"><head>1. The scale plan of what you intended the robot to draw.</head><p n="p1.13"><s n="s1.1;p1.13">Please see Appendix A. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head>2. The list of moves identifying the motions that the robot had to perform in order to produce the drawing you wanted (in English).</head><p n="p2.13"><s n="s1.7;p2.13">Set the original point, P0.Then move to P1 and put down the pen onto the paper. </s><s n="s2.7;p2.13">Draw the frame by moving the pen from P1 to P2 to P3 to P4 and back to P1. </s><s n="s3.7;p2.13">Lift up the pen and move it to the top right corner of the letter "Y" on the right hand side. </s><s n="s4.7;p2.13">Put down the pen to draw the letter "Y" that the finish point is the same as the starting point of drawing. </s><s n="s5.7;p2.13">Lift the pen up and move it to the top right corner of the letter "Y" on the left hand side. </s><s n="s6.7;p2.13">Put down the pen and again, draw another "Y" on the left. </s><s n="s7.7;p2.13">Finally, lift the pen up. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head>3. The listing of the program that you actually took to the lab (in VAL).</head><quote lang="English">.PROGRAM JULIE() SET original = P0 ;Define the fixed point for P0 SET P1 = SHIFT (P0 BY 0,30,0) ;Define Point 1 SET P2 = SHIFT (P1 BY 0,200,0) ;Define Point 2 SET P3 = SHIFT (P2 BY -160,0,0) ;Define Point 3 SET P4 = SHIFT (P3 BY 0,-200,0) ;Define Point 4 Y=0 SET P0 = original ; Make the Frame APPROS P1, 100 ;MOVE TO 100mm ABOVE POINT1 MOVES P1 ;GO DOWN TO POINT 1 MOVES P2 ;MOVE TO POINT 2 MOVE P3 ;MOVE TO POINT 3 MOVES P4 ;MOVE TO POINT 4 MOVE P1 ;MOVE TO POINT 1 DEPARTS 100 ;LIFT UP 100mm ABOVE POINT 1 ;Draw Y on the right side of the frame 10 APPROS P0:TRANS(-30,45,100) ;MOVE TO 100mm ABOVE Y MOVES P0:TRANS(-30,45,0) ;go down to the top right corner of "Y" MOVES P0:TRANS(30,60,0) ;start drawing MOVES P0:TRANS(66,80,0) MOVES P0:TRANS(30,100,0) MOVES P0:TRANS(30,115,0) MOVES P0:TRANS(81,88,0) MOVES P0:TRANS(130,88,0) MOVES P0:TRANS(130,73,0) MOVES P0:TRANS(81,73,0) MOVES P0:TRANS(30,45,0) ;Done DEPARTS 100 ;LIFT UP 100mm ABOVE ; Draw Y on the left side of the frame SET P0 = SHIFT (P0 BY 0,96,0) Y=Y+1 IF Y&lt;2 THEN GOTO 10 END SET P0 = original .END</quote><p n="p3.13"/></div1><div1 type="section"><head>4. The drawing(s) that the robot produced in the lab (several if it needed correction).</head><p n="p4.13"><s n="s1.1;p4.13">Please see Appendix B. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head>5. A brief description of anything that went wrong during the execution of your program</head><p n="p5.13"><s n="s1.5;p5.13">During the execution of the program, everything went ok. </s><s n="s2.5;p5.13">But before the execution, some correction of the program is needed. </s><s n="s3.5;p5.13">On the line of "10 APPROS P0:TRANS(-30,45,100)", it should be "10 APPROS P0:TRANS(-30,45,), 100". </s><s n="s4.5;p5.13">Also, I declare "Y=0" which the technician said the program is not allowed as it is one of the programming language/ character in the program; it has its own meaning. </s><s n="s5.5;p5.13">Therefore, I changed it from Y to YG. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head>6. A statement of what would happen if you were to run your program for a second time simply by typing EXECUTE &lt;yourname> after the robot's last move, and why.</head><p n="p6.13"><s n="s1.5;p6.13">The program would use the end point of the last program as P0 for the second time. </s><s n="s2.5;p6.13">It is because P0 in the program is not defined. </s><s n="s3.5;p6.13">Therefore, we need to declare where the starting point, P0, is by using the teach pendant. </s><s n="s4.5;p6.13">If we didn't do so before the second execution, it will use the end point of the last execution as the starting point of the next execution. </s><s n="s5.5;p6.13">Hence, the robot will draw out of the paper. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head>7. An explanation of the information that you would have needed to predict the precise shape of the frame drawn by the robot around the two letters.</head><p n="p7.13"><s n="s1.4;p7.13">Linear interpolation and joint interpolation are used to draw the frame. </s><s n="s2.4;p7.13">For join interpolation, a precise straight line can be drawn depends on the type of joints that the robot has. </s><s n="s3.4;p7.13">It also depends on the positions of the point the robot move from and move to. </s><s n="s4.4;p7.13">If only one joint move, the robot will produce a simple arc, centered on the axis of rotation of the joint with a radius equal to the distance from the axis to the point. </s></p><p n="p8.13"><s n="s1.1;p8.13">To predict the precise shape of the frame, we need to know where P1, P2, P3 and P4 are related to the robot and the distance between. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head>8. A reasoned explanation of, and a sketch showing the approximate path followed by the tip of the pen if points P1 and P2, and P3 and P4 were joined by joint interpolated moves, and P1 and P4, and P2 and P3 were joined by linearly interpolated moves.</head><p n="p9.13"><s n="s1.1;p9.13">The path for POINT1 to POINT2 and POINT 3 to POINT4 will be a curved lines while the path for POINT 1 to POINT4 and POINT2 to POINT3 are straight line. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0357b-pic.001"/></div1><div1 type="section"><head>9. An explanation of the commands that you would use to instruct the robot to cut out the frame P1, P2, P3, P4 so that:</head><p rend="ordered" n="p10.13"><s n="s1.2;p10.13">i. </s><s n="s2.2;p10.13">The sides were straight and all the corners were perfectly square. </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p11.13"><s n="s1.2;p11.13">The robot need to stop at the exact points of the frame that the speed can not be too fact when cutting the frame. </s><s n="s2.2;p11.13">Therefore, I will use "CPOFF" command as this set the robot to point-to- point mode </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p12.13"><s n="s1.2;p12.13">ii. </s><s n="s2.2;p12.13">The sides were straight and all the corners were "radiused". </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p13.13"><s n="s1.2;p13.13">The speed must be fast in order to draw "radiused" corner. </s><s n="s2.2;p13.13">An extra command is not needed as the robot will move smoothly and not stopping at any corners without setting it to point- to- point mode </s></p></div1></body><back><div1 type="appendix"><head>Appendix A</head><p/></div1><div1 type="appendix"><head>Appendix B</head><p/></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
