<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_0358g" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>MECHANICAL TESTING OF MATERIALS</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">The document has a title page which contains:
document title
title part</note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">deleted: header: laboratory name, page numbers; footer: assignment title, module name and number, student number</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">2</p><p n="date">2006-04</p><p n="module title">Biomedical Materials</p><p n="module code">ES2A1</p><p n="genre family">Methodology recount</p><p n="discipline">Engineering</p><p n="disciplinary group">PS</p><p n="grade">D</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">2537</p><p n="number of s-units">133</p><p n="number of p">48</p><p n="number of tables">6</p><p n="number of figures">14</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">3</p><p n="number of lists">2</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">6</p><p n="abstract present">abstract present</p><p n="average words per s-unit">19.1</p><p n="average s-units per p">2.8</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">m</p><p n="year of birth">1987</p><p n="first language">Tamil</p><p n="education">OSA</p><p n="course">MEng Mechanical Engineering</p><p n="student ID">0358</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><titlePart><hi rend="bold">THE UNIVERSITY OF</hi> <hi rend="bold"><name type="university"/> School Of Engineering</hi></titlePart><docTitle><titlePart rend="underlined bold"> MECHANICAL TESTING OF MATERIALS</titlePart></docTitle><titlePart><hi rend="bold">BY STUDENT ID: <name type="student ID"/></hi><hi rend="bold"> REPORT REFERENCE CODE: [ES2 A1] AFFLIATION: [YEAR 2 ENGINEERING]</hi></titlePart></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="abstract"><head rend="underlined bold">SUMMARY</head><p n="p1.48"><s n="s1.3;p1.48">The Objective of this Laboratory session was to test the given samples of biomaterials using a materials testing machine. </s><s n="s2.3;p1.48">The materials underwent tensile testing in the process of which a Load-Elongation Plot was obtained for each of these materials. </s><s n="s3.3;p1.48">This plot is characteristic and unique for every material. </s></p><p n="p2.48"><s n="s1.5;p2.48">The Specimens are gripped on to the machine using chucks. </s><s n="s2.5;p2.48">The machine uses a motor to drive two lead screws on either side. </s><s n="s3.5;p2.48">These push the chuck upwards thereby stretching the specimen. </s><s n="s4.5;p2.48">The Force applied is measured using a load cell or a strain gauge and the extension is measured using an extensometer or a transformer in which the distance between the coils can be adjusted. </s><s n="s5.5;p2.48">A computer measures these values at regular small intervals and plots them as a graph. </s></p><p n="p3.48"><s n="s1.2;p3.48">This graph is then used to obtain an engineering Stress- Strain curve of the material. </s><s n="s2.2;p3.48">This plot can then be used to determine the yield points, Ultimate Tensile Strength, Fracture Stress and Ductility of these materials. </s></p><p n="p4.48"><s n="s1.1;p4.48">These values are then compared against tests done previously in the university and other statistical data provided to understand the fluctuations in the values and errors. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">INTRODUCTION</head><p n="p5.48"><s n="s1.5;p5.48">The principle of the testing is the load and elongation plots obtained from the stress and elongation test. </s><s n="s2.5;p5.48">The objective of the experiment was to obtain the characteristic Load Elongation plots of given materials using physical tests on a material testing machine. </s><s n="s3.5;p5.48">These characteristic plots were used to obtain the stress-strain curve of materials. </s><s n="s4.5;p5.48">This in turn will enable us to determine the yield point, the ultimate tensile strength and the ductility of the materials. </s><s n="s5.5;p5.48">These values were then compared with previous tests done in the university on the same materials and other statistical information provided to asses the fluctuations and analyse the causes for these fluctuations. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">THEORY</head><p n="p6.48"><s n="s1.6;p6.48">Every Material experiences deformation when a load is applied on it. </s><s n="s2.6;p6.48">The deformation can either be elastic or plastic. </s><s n="s3.6;p6.48">The material also fractures or fails at a certain point. </s><s n="s4.6;p6.48">The Load applied can be in the form of tension, compression, shear, etc.It this case we only study the response of the given samples of biomaterials when they are subjected to tension. </s><s n="s5.6;p6.48">Every material has a characteristic load and elongation plot that can be obtained from a tensile stress test. </s><s n="s6.6;p6.48">Fig 1 shows the general structure of the plot obtained during tensile testing. </s></p><p n="p7.48"><s n="s1.1;p7.48">Where Stress measured is the engineering stress or in other words, the reduction in the cross sectional area during strain is not taken into account </s></p><p n="p8.48"><s n="s1.1;p8.48"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0358g-form.001"/> </s></p><p n="p9.48"><s n="s1.1;p9.48"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0358g-form.002"/> </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0358g-fig.001"><head><hi rend="underlined bold">Figure 1 </hi><ref target="BAWE_0358g-ftnote.001"/><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0358g-ftnote.001"><p n="pn1.1"> <seg type="URL" n="http://www.uwsp.edu/geo/faculty/hefferan/Geol320/strainrate.html"/></p></note></head></figure><p n="p10.48"><s n="s1.5;p10.48">As we can see from Fig 1 above, the plot takes the form of a straight line in the beginning, this zone is known as the elastic limit where the material undergoes temporary or <hi rend="bold"> Elastic Deformation</hi>. </s><s n="s2.5;p10.48">This essentially means that the material will return back to its original length is the load is removed anywhere in this Zone. </s><s n="s3.5;p10.48">This is a result of the stretching of the atomic bonds in the specimen. </s><s n="s4.5;p10.48">The point at which the material ceases to deform elastically is called yield point. </s><s n="s5.5;p10.48">The line on the graph is not linear beyond this point. </s></p><p n="p11.48"><s n="s1.4;p11.48">The value of stress at the upper limit of this Straight line is called the yield point beyond which the material undergoes permanent or <hi rend="bold">Plastic Deformation</hi>. </s><s n="s2.4;p11.48">This is a result of the sliding of atomic layers with relative to one another. </s><s n="s3.4;p11.48">Once Plastic Strain is achieved, the elongation is irreversible. </s><s n="s4.4;p11.48">The total strain would hence be the sum of the elastic and plastic strain. </s></p><p n="p12.48"><s n="s1.5;p12.48">In some metals like steel, the <hi rend="bold">yield point</hi> is not quite obvious as the region of the graph after elastic deformation is wavy and non-uniform. </s><s n="s2.5;p12.48">Figure 2 is a stress strain plot of soft steel. </s><s n="s3.5;p12.48">This is because the yield strength of these materials is quite sensitive to how axially the load is applied. </s><s n="s4.5;p12.48">Hence the uppermost point of the wavy region is called the <hi rend="bold">upper yield strength (UYS)</hi> which occurs in the beginning of plastic deformation and the lowermost point is called the <hi rend="bold">lower yield stress (LYS)</hi> which occurs further on. </s><s n="s5.5;p12.48">Metals also have some weird effects after this as a result of work hardening. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0358g-fig.002"><head><hi rend="underlined bold"> Figure 2 </hi><ref target="BAWE_0358g-ftnote.002"/><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0358g-ftnote.002"><p n="pn1.1"> <seg type="URL" n="http://cms.mse.berkeley.edu/classes/e45/labs/e45lab7.pdf"/></p></note></head></figure><p n="p13.48"><s n="s1.6;p13.48">After the material starts undergoing plastic deformation, the cross sectional area of the specimen starts narrowing down rapidly at a point. </s><s n="s2.6;p13.48">This point is known as a neck and this effect is called necking. </s><s n="s3.6;p13.48">As more load is applied on the specimen, the atomic bonds break around this neck and the specimen fractures into two different pieces eventually. </s><s n="s4.6;p13.48">This phenomenon is called a <hi rend="bold">Fracture.</hi> </s><s n="s5.6;p13.48">. </s><s n="s6.6;p13.48">Figure 3 is a graphical representation of elastic and plastic deformation, necking and stress concentration changes that occur during the process. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0358g-fig.003"><head><hi rend="underlined bold">Figure 3</hi><ref target="BAWE_0358g-ftnote.003"/><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0358g-ftnote.003"><p n="pn1.1"> <seg type="URL" n="http://msm.guc.edu.eg/tensile_neck.jpeg"/></p></note></head></figure><p n="p14.48"><s n="s1.1;p14.48">The point of fracture in the material is determined by the location of the defect in the material which in turn is governed by the extraction, manufacturing and heat treatment processes that the specimen undergoes and it's almost impossible to make the specimen perfect such that the fracture occurs exactly in between the two ends of the vertical section </s></p><p n="p15.48"><s n="s1.2;p15.48">The Nature of the Stress Strain curve for materials depends not only on the nature of the material but also on heat treatment, prior history of plastic deformation, and the strain rate, temperature, etc. </s><s n="s2.2;p15.48">Hence while trying to obtain a standard value of Ultimate Tensile Strength, Yield Point, fracture point , etc of materials, it is essential for us to use the optimum value for these factors. </s></p><p n="p16.48"><s n="s1.3;p16.48">The Graphs obtained from this testing can also be used to measure the ductility of materials. </s><s n="s2.3;p16.48">Ductility is the permissibility of materials to be drawn into wires. </s><s n="s3.3;p16.48">In other words, it's the ratio of the total plastic extension of the specimen and its original length. </s></p><p n="p17.48"><s n="s1.1;p17.48"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0358g-form.003"/> </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">APPARATUS</head><div2><head rend="bold">General Apparatus Description</head><p n="p18.48"><s n="s1.6;p18.48">We used a Materials Testing Machine made by a company called Testometric. </s><s n="s2.6;p18.48">It had an electromechanical system and is also known as a screw driven machine. </s><s n="s3.6;p18.48">The tensile force is applied on a specimen held axially in between two gripping mechanisms. </s><s n="s4.6;p18.48">The force is applied by a high torque motor normally a dc motor. </s><s n="s5.6;p18.48">This motor pushes a crosshead with the upper chuck upwards using two vertical lead screws on either end. </s><s n="s6.6;p18.48">Figure 4 is a picture of a similair material testing machine with its parts labelled. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0358g-pic.001"><head><hi rend="underlined bold">Figure 4</hi><ref target="BAWE_0358g-ftnote.004"/><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0358g-ftnote.004"><p n="pn1.1"> <seg type="URL" n="http://www.testometric.co.uk/products.asp"/></p></note></head></figure></div2><div2><head rend="bold">Load Measurement</head><p n="p19.48"><s n="s1.4;p19.48">The Tensile Load is measured using Load Cells. </s><s n="s2.4;p19.48">Load cells work on the principle of Piezoresistance or the change in resisitivity of conductors and semi conductors with strain. </s><s n="s3.4;p19.48">The signals produced by these load cells are normally quite low and are hence amplified by differential amplifiers. </s><s n="s4.4;p19.48">These signals are proportional to the applied. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">Strain Rate Measurement</head><p n="p20.48"><s n="s1.5;p20.48">The Strain Rate is measured using Extensometers. </s><s n="s2.5;p20.48">Extensometers work on the principle of induction. </s><s n="s3.5;p20.48">They use linearly variable Differential Transformers (LDVT). </s><s n="s4.5;p20.48">These transformers produce voltage and current signals proportional to the displacement between the two coils used. </s><s n="s5.5;p20.48">While LDVTs are ideal for strain measurement Optical Extensometers that use LASER are more suited for rubbers and plastics </s></p><p n="p21.48"><s n="s1.4;p21.48">The signals in these machines go through different electrical and electronic circuits which causes varying amounts of losses and gains in the signals. </s><s n="s2.4;p21.48">These losses and gains may be different for different machines due to material or manufacturing defects and variability's. </s><s n="s3.4;p21.48">Hence most of these machines are calibrated using another machine which in turn is calibrated by yet another. </s><s n="s4.4;p21.48">This chain of calibration is colossal due to the number of machines in existence and hence should reduce the errors if the machines are calibrated frequently. </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">METHOD</head><p n="p22.48"><s n="s1.2;p22.48">The Process of measuring the Tensile Strength of materials is quite simple. </s><s n="s2.2;p22.48">The instrument has to be setup in order to </s></p><list type="ordered"><item>Produce the Maximum Force required to break the specimen</item><item>Maintain a constant Specified Strain Rate</item><item>Hold the Specimen Rigid and directionally accurate</item></list><p n="p23.48"><s n="s1.4;p23.48">The Machine is then started which makes the upper chuck move upwards as it elongates the specimen. </s><s n="s2.4;p23.48">The Load and elongation signals are sent to a computer that plots the values on a screen. </s><s n="s3.4;p23.48">The machine stops automatically when the specimen gets fractured. </s><s n="s4.4;p23.48">The load-elongation plot of the material can then be printed out from the computer. </s></p><div2><head rend="underlined bold">Specimen</head><p n="p24.48"><s n="s1.2;p24.48">The Specimens of the metals are shaped like a dumb bell with 2 large cylindrical ends and a smaller cylindrical body. </s><s n="s2.2;p24.48">Figure 4 illustrates the upper half of the specimen. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0358g-pic.002"><head><hi rend="underlined bold">Figure 5</hi><ref target="BAWE_0358g-ftnote.005"/><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0358g-ftnote.005"><p n="pn1.1"> <seg type="URL" n="http://www.asminternational.org/pdf/spotlights/5106_01.pdf"/></p></note></head></figure><p n="p25.48"><s n="s1.2;p25.48">The specimens of Plastics and Composites are shaped like dog bones but have a rectangular cross section instead of a circular one. </s><s n="s2.2;p25.48">Figure 5 illustrates the upper half of the specimen. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0358g-pic.003"><head><hi rend="underlined bold">Figure 6</hi><ref target="BAWE_0358g-ftnote.006"/><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0358g-ftnote.006"><p n="pn1.1"> <seg type="URL" n="http://www.asminternational.org/pdf/spotlights/5106_01.pdf"/></p></note></head></figure><p n="p26.48"><s n="s1.2;p26.48">These Specimens are held to the chuck using wedges that use friction to prevent axial displacement of the specimen. </s><s n="s2.2;p26.48">Figure 6 and Figure 7 are illustrations of the wedges used to hold the metallic and Ceramic/Plastic specimens respectively. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0358g-pic.004"><head><hi rend="underlined bold">Figure 7</hi><ref target="BAWE_0358g-ftnote.007"/><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0358g-ftnote.007"><p n="pn1.1"> <seg type="URL" n="http://www.asminternational.org/pdf/spotlights/5106_01.pdf"/></p></note></head></figure><figure id="BAWE_0358g-pic.005"><head><hi rend="underlined bold">Figure 8</hi><ref target="BAWE_0358g-ftnote.008"/><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0358g-ftnote.008"><p n="pn1.1"> <seg type="URL" n="http://www.asminternational.org/pdf/spotlights/5106_01.pdf"/></p></note></head></figure></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">POTENTIAL SOURCES OF ERROR</head><p rend="bulleted" n="p27.48"><s n="s1.2;p27.48"><hi rend="bold">Slips at Chucks</hi> - While the samples were held and elongated at the chucks, there could've been some amount of slip that the samples experience. </s><s n="s2.2;p27.48">This could affect the value of the measured strain. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p28.48"><s n="s1.1;p28.48"><hi rend="bold">Deformation of Testing equipment</hi> - During testing, not only does the material specimen have load acting on it, the chucks and other gripping mechanisms used experience a stress that causes a deformation in them. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p29.48"><s n="s1.1;p29.48"><hi rend="bold">Axial Alignment</hi> - The specimen has to be held axially and straight in between the chucks and any misalignment could lead to errors. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p30.48"><s n="s1.4;p30.48"><hi rend="bold">Temperature</hi> - The specimen gets heated up rapidly at the end of the test which means that a fraction of the energy used to deform the specimen is converted into heat. </s><s n="s2.4;p30.48">This heat could affect the elasticity and plasticity of the materials. </s><s n="s3.4;p30.48">The energy lost to the environment is also not taken into account. </s><s n="s4.4;p30.48">The ambient temperature could also cause a change in the shape of the plot. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p31.48"><s n="s1.4;p31.48"><hi rend="bold">Strain Rate</hi> - The strain rate of the test can potentially affect the shape of the stress strain curve. </s><s n="s2.4;p31.48">Although this is neglected in most cases, there's is some amount of error caused by it. </s><s n="s3.4;p31.48">In my observation of graphs, the slope of the curve seems to reduce with increase in strain rate. </s><s n="s4.4;p31.48">This could happen because, when the material is deformed slowly, the molecules have more time to interact within themselves and increase their cohesive forces but rapid deformation reduces their interaction time and hence speeds up the process. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p32.48"><s n="s1.1;p32.48"><hi rend="bold">Friction and Backlashes</hi> - The Bearings, Gears and screws used in the machine will have experience friction, wear, backlash, etc which could cause errors in readings. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">OBSERVATION AND RESULTS</head><p n="p33.48"><s n="s1.2;p33.48">Table 1, given below is a brief description of the specimens tested including their composition, manufacturing process, Codes, etc. </s><s n="s2.2;p33.48">This Data was obtained from the Lab briefing Sheet. </s></p><table id="BAWE_0358g-tab.001"><head rend="underlined bold">Table 1</head><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p34.48"><s n="s1.4;p34.48">These Specimens were made in batches to make different samples match the same values. </s><s n="s2.4;p34.48">This also reduces the distortion caused by heat treatment, manufacturing processes, impurities, defects, etc. </s><s n="s3.4;p34.48">These specimens were also made to standard sizes. </s><s n="s4.4;p34.48">The cross sectional area and gauge lengths of the different samples are specified in Table 2 on the next page. </s></p><table id="BAWE_0358g-tab.002"><head rend="bold">Table 2: TESTS PERFORMED ON 2-12-05</head><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p35.48"><s n="s1.3;p35.48">These values obtained from the load elongation plots can be used to obtain the engineering stress strain plot values. </s><s n="s2.3;p35.48">The load divided by the cross sectional Area gives the value of stress and the elongation value divided by the gauge length gives us the strain value. </s><s n="s3.3;p35.48">This is done in Table 3 below. </s></p><p n="p36.48"><s n="s1.2;p36.48">During the determination of these values from the graph, a proof stress line was drawn from an elongation value of 0.2% of the gauge length to be as parallel as possible to the elastic line. </s><s n="s2.2;p36.48">The point at which this line intersected the curve was taken to be the yield point. </s></p><table id="BAWE_0358g-tab.003"><head rend="underlined bold">TABLE 3: RESULT INTERPRETATION INTO STRESS AND STRAIN VALUES</head><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p37.48"><s n="s1.1;p37.48">These Stress and Strain values can now be used to plot the characteristic Stress and Strain plot of materials as done in the successive pages. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0358g-fig.004"/><figure id="BAWE_0358g-fig.005"/><figure id="BAWE_0358g-fig.006"/><figure id="BAWE_0358g-fig.007"/><figure id="BAWE_0358g-fig.008"/><table id="BAWE_0358g-tab.004"><head rend="bold">Table 4: GRAPH SET A</head><row><cell/></row></table><table id="BAWE_0358g-tab.005"><head rend="bold">Table 5: GRAPH SET B</head><row><cell/></row></table><table id="BAWE_0358g-tab.006"><head rend="bold">Table 6: STATISTICAL INFORMATION</head><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p38.48"><s n="s1.2;p38.48">The Values in the statistical information table above are the data corresponding to the maximum and minimum yield stress of the various tests done during a particular year. </s><s n="s2.2;p38.48">The Average of this value has been used to plot a statistical graph below to show the variations in the values of some key parameters like Yield Strength and Tensile Strength over time. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">CODE DN : Statistical analysis</head><figure id="BAWE_0358g-fig.009"/><figure id="BAWE_0358g-fig.010"/><p n="p39.48"/></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">CODE 2 : Statistical analysis</head><figure id="BAWE_0358g-fig.011"/><figure id="BAWE_0358g-fig.012"/><p n="p40.48"/></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">CODE E : Statistical analysis</head><figure id="BAWE_0358g-fig.013"/><figure id="BAWE_0358g-fig.014"/><p n="p41.48"/></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">ANALYSIS OF RESULTS</head><p n="p42.48"><s n="s1.3;p42.48">With the testing of metallic materials, we found aluminium alloys (E) to be more elastic than iron alloys like steel (DN). </s><s n="s2.3;p42.48">Aluminium alloys had a high elastic strain or in other words a lower stiffness when compared with steel. </s><s n="s3.3;p42.48">This explains why aluminium is considered to be a soft metal. </s></p><p n="p43.48"><s n="s1.3;p43.48">We found steels to be quite sensitive to the axial alignment of the deforming force. </s><s n="s2.3;p43.48">The Load-Elongation plots of steels hence tend to be quite wavy with too many spikes as the plot approaches the yield point. </s><s n="s3.3;p43.48">Steels also tend to have an upper and lower yield point. </s></p><p n="p44.48"><s n="s1.4;p44.48">The tensile stress readings of polymeric material, Nylon 6, 6 were observed to be quite sensitive to changes in strain rate. </s><s n="s2.4;p44.48">On one hand, while lower strain rates take an awfully long time to fracture the specimen, higher strain rates fracture it too fast. </s><s n="s3.4;p44.48">This is due to the viscoelastic property of the polymers.<ref target="BAWE_0358g-ftnote.009"/> We used a low strain rate in the beginning and increased it progressively as we couldn't wait for a long time. </s><s n="s4.4;p44.48">This resulted in a way load-elongation plot for this material. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0358g-ftnote.009"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Han Patricia; Tensile Testing, ASSM; pg 107 </s></p></note><p n="p45.48"><s n="s1.2;p45.48">As with composites like the GFRC we used, they tend to have a very low elastic limit or in other words their elastic strain is quite low. </s><s n="s2.2;p45.48">Their plastic limit is a lot higher. </s></p><p n="p46.48"><s n="s1.3;p46.48">When the results that we obtained were compared with the Graph Set A, Graph set B (Tests done in the university on the same materials previously) and statistical data provided to us in the lab. </s><s n="s2.3;p46.48">I found a general dip in most values recorded as compared to the previous years. </s><s n="s3.3;p46.48">There are 2 factors that I can account this phenomenon to </s></p><list type="ordered"><item>Calibration errors in the machine </item><item>Evolution and refinement in manufacturing processes to minimise Defects in materials</item></list></div1><div1 type="section"><p n="p47.48"><s n="s1.6;p47.48">The Tensile Testing of materials is very essential and critical in order to understand the behaviour of materials under tension. </s><s n="s2.6;p47.48">A lot of engineering applications use materials under tension like bridges, springs, etc.This test seem to be extremely sensitive with respect to factors concerning the machine and factors concerning the material. </s><s n="s3.6;p47.48">Defects, Impurities and crystal structure variations introduced in the material as a result of heat treatment play an important role in determining the shape of the characteristic plots. </s><s n="s4.6;p47.48">On the other hand slips at the chucks, calibration errors, axial alignment, etc are factors concerning the machine that play an important role in determining the shape of the plot. </s><s n="s5.6;p47.48">This has led to great variations in the statistical records of these characteristic curves. </s><s n="s6.6;p47.48">This test can also be used to determine the Young's Modulus and the creep of different materials. </s></p><p n="p48.48"><s n="s1.2;p48.48">Real Engineering applications however use a safety factor which quite often doubles or triples the strength of the materials used than what is actually required for the particular application. </s><s n="s2.2;p48.48">However, these tests help us in understanding the big picture of the material properties which is what it is used for. </s></p></div1></body><back><div1 type="bibliography"><head rend="underlined bold">REFERENCES &amp; BIBLIOGRAPHY</head><p>Lab Briefing Sheet</p><p>Han Patricia; Tensile Testing, ASSM</p><p><seg type="URL" n="http://www.uwsp.edu/geo/faculty/hefferan/Geol320/strainrate.html"/></p><p><seg type="URL" n="http://cms.mse.berkeley.edu/classes/e45/labs/e45lab7.pdf"/></p><p><seg type="URL" n="http://www.asminternational.org/pdf/spotlights/5106_01.pdf"/></p><p><seg type="URL" n="http://msm.guc.edu.eg/tensile_neck.jpeg"/></p><p><seg type="URL" n="http://www.testometric.co.uk/products.asp"/></p></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
