<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_0358f" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>LAB REPORT ON THE MATERIAL CHARACTERISATION LABORATORY</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">The document has a title page which contains:
document title
title part</note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">deleted: header: laboratory name, page numbers; footer: assignment title, module name and number, student number</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">2</p><p n="date">2006-02</p><p n="module title">Biomedical Materials</p><p n="module code">ES2A1</p><p n="genre family">Methodology recount</p><p n="discipline">Engineering</p><p n="disciplinary group">PS</p><p n="grade">D</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">2580</p><p n="number of s-units">135</p><p n="number of p">50</p><p n="number of tables">1</p><p n="number of figures">15</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">3</p><p n="number of lists">1</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">3</p><p n="abstract present">abstract present</p><p n="average words per s-unit">19.1</p><p n="average s-units per p">2.7</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">m</p><p n="year of birth">1987</p><p n="first language">Tamil</p><p n="education">OSA</p><p n="course">MEng Mechanical Engineering</p><p n="student ID">0358</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><titlePart><hi rend="bold">THE UNIVERSITY OF</hi> <hi rend="bold"><name type="university"/> School Of Engineering</hi></titlePart><docTitle><titlePart rend="underlined bold">LAB REPORT ON THE MATERIAL CHARACTERISATION LABORATORY</titlePart></docTitle><titlePart rend="bold">BY STUDENT ID: <name type="student ID"/></titlePart><titlePart rend="bold">REPORT REFERENCE CODE: [ES2 A1] AFFLIATION: [YEAR 2 ENGINEERING]</titlePart></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="abstract"><head rend="underlined bold">SUMMARY</head><p n="p1.50"><s n="s1.2;p1.50">The objective of this lab session was to get familiarised with the various methods that are used to study the microstructure of materials. </s><s n="s2.2;p1.50">We </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">INTRODUCTION</head><p n="p2.50"><s n="s1.3;p2.50">We used different instruments to analyse the microstructure of materials. </s><s n="s2.3;p2.50">We used The Scanning Electron Microscope (SEM), The Optical Microscope and The X-Ray Diffraction Machine. </s><s n="s3.3;p2.50">We also familiarised ourselves with a high precision weighing machine and a hot polymer/ceramic pressing machine while making samples to X-Ray Diffraction. </s></p><p n="p3.50"><s n="s1.2;p3.50">We looked at the various crystal structures of materials using these instruments. </s><s n="s2.2;p3.50">We compared and analysed various crystal properties like Size, Shape, Distribution, frequency of constituent elements in alloys, Properties like Twinning in the case of Brass, etc. </s></p><p n="p4.50"><s n="s1.2;p4.50">The estimations made using the microscopes were pretty approximate and vague as the imaging software couldn't detect the crystals on its own and we had to make rough measurements of the sizes. </s><s n="s2.2;p4.50">The measurement of crystal sizes on the microscope we a very approximate estimation as well. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">THEORY AND APPARATUS</head><p n="p5.50"><s n="s1.1;p5.50">We analysed the Microstructure of the given materials using three different instruments </s></p><div2><head rend="bold">Scanning Electron Microscope</head><p n="p6.50"><s n="s1.1;p6.50">The principle of electron microscopy is the differential absorption and radiation of electrons due to differences in the topology of surfaces. </s></p><p n="p7.50"><s n="s1.3;p7.50">The wavelength of the particles (light or matter like electrons) used to magnify images is inversely proportional to the wavelength in the case of visible light or the De Broglies wavelength in the case of matter<ref target="BAWE_0358f-ftnote.001"/>. </s><s n="s2.3;p7.50">The wavelength of Visible Light is about 380 - 750 nm <ref target="BAWE_0358f-ftnote.002"/>. </s><s n="s3.3;p7.50">The De Broglies Wavelength of an electron accelerated through 100 V is 0.12 nm <hi rend="sup">2</hi>.Hence the resolution of a microscope that uses electron beams can increase their resolving power by several manifolds as compared with conventional optical Microscopes. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0358f-ftnote.001"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1"><seg type="URL" n="http://hyperphysics.phy-astr.gsu.edu/Hbase/debrog.html"/> </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0358f-ftnote.002"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1"><seg type="URL" n="http://hypertextbook.com/facts/2002/PavelBorodulin.shtml"/> </s></p></note><p n="p8.50"><s n="s1.1;p8.50">Figure 1 is a pictorial representation of a type of Scanning Electron Microscope similair to the one that we used. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0358f-pic.001"><head><hi rend="underlined bold">Figure 1</hi><ref target="BAWE_0358f-ftnote.003"/><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0358f-ftnote.003"><p n="pn1.1"> <seg type="URL" n="http://www.mos.org/sln/sem/intro.html"/></p></note></head></figure><p n="p9.50"><s n="s1.5;p9.50">In this Microscope, a beam of electrons is produces in a vacuum tube with an anode on one end and a cathode in another. </s><s n="s2.5;p9.50">These electrons are focussed on the specimen. </s><s n="s3.5;p9.50">The specimen in turn interacts with these electrons and reflects the beam back. </s><s n="s4.5;p9.50">A detector detects these beams, counts the number of electrons reflected, amplifies the signals and uses its calibrations to produce gray-scale images on a computer. </s><s n="s5.5;p9.50">The beam is focussed on a larger number of points consecutively to produce a larger image. </s></p><p n="p10.50"><s n="s1.1;p10.50">Samples that can conduct electricity like metals can be viewed directly on an electron microscope but specimens that don't conduct electricity are normally painted or sprayed with a thin layer of gold to enable conduction on the surface. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0358f-pic.002"><head rend="underlined bold">Figure 2</head></figure><p n="p11.50"><s n="s1.2;p11.50">The Electron beams of a high velocity and low wavelength can only be produced in a vacumised environment and hence, The Scanning Electron Microscope requires the user to place specimens in a vacumised chamber in which the electron beam gets focussed on the sample. </s><s n="s2.2;p11.50">This makes it impossible for us to view live samples under an electron microscope as the vacuum and electron beams would kill the cells. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">X-Ray Diffraction</head><p n="p12.50"><s n="s1.5;p12.50">X - Ray Diffraction is one of the most important material characterisation methods. </s><s n="s2.5;p12.50">It produces a unique fingerprint for each phase of every material by identifying the crystal structure of the atomic arrangement of the specimen crystal. </s><s n="s3.5;p12.50">The fingerprint is made using a plot of the variation in the intensity of the diffracted X-Rays with variation in the value of <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0358f-form.001"/>. </s><s n="s4.5;p12.50">Since the value of the incident X-Ray differs with different machines and depends on the potential difference of the vacuum tube that produces the X-Rays, etc. </s><s n="s5.5;p12.50">It is better to plot against the relative intensity of the X-ray i.e. the ratio of the intensities of the incident beam and the diffracted beam. </s></p><p n="p13.50"><s n="s1.2;p13.50">When an X-Ray beam is incident on a plane of atoms, various fractions of the beam are reflected, refracted, scattered, absorbed and diffracted. </s><s n="s2.2;p13.50">Diffraction is the bending of light waves round opaque obstacles in its path. </s></p><p n="p14.50"><s n="s1.2;p14.50">The principle of X-Ray Diffraction is Bragg's Law. </s><s n="s2.2;p14.50">The equation of Bragg's law is given by </s></p><p n="p15.50"><s n="s1.1;p15.50"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0358f-form.002"/> </s></p><list type="simple"><head>Where</head><item>n = order of the diffracted beam</item><item>λ = Wavelength of the X-Ray Beam</item><item>d = Space between atomic planes</item><item>θ = angle of incidence = angle of diffraction </item></list><p n="p16.50"><s n="s1.1;p16.50">Figure 3 shown below shows the atomic planes as the thick horizontal lines with the X-Ray being incident on it at an angle of θ.The distance between the atomic planes is d. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0358f-pic.003"><head><hi rend="underlined bold">Figure 3</hi><ref target="BAWE_0358f-ftnote.004"/><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0358f-ftnote.004"><p n="pn1.1"> <seg type="URL" n="http://materials.binghamton.edu/labs/xray/xray.html"/></p></note></head></figure><p n="p17.50"><s n="s1.8;p17.50">In the diffractometer used to obtain the 2θ-intensity graph, the X-Rays are produced using a cathode ray tube or a vacuum tube. </s><s n="s2.8;p17.50">A cylindrical glass tube has a cathode and another on either side of it and is vacumised to a very low pressure. </s><s n="s3.8;p17.50">When a potential difference is applied across the electrodes, cathode rays are produced in the tube. </s><s n="s4.8;p17.50">These Cathode rays are then diverted to hit a metal target, conventionally a copper target. </s><s n="s5.8;p17.50">This produces X-Rays. </s><s n="s6.8;p17.50">The intensity of the X-Rays is measured using a Geiger-Muller counter where the air is ionised and an avalanche of ions is produced at high radiation intensities. </s><s n="s7.8;p17.50">The X-rays then hit a sample of the material under observation. </s><s n="s8.8;p17.50">The X-Rays that get diffracted are counted using a Geiger-Muller Counter again to measure its intensity. </s></p><p n="p18.50"><s n="s1.5;p18.50">This process is carried on while altering the angle of incidence continuously. </s><s n="s2.5;p18.50">A graph is then plotted between twice the angle of incidence and the measured intensity of the diffracted X-Rays. </s><s n="s3.5;p18.50">This plot is characteristic of every material and can be used to identify it. </s><s n="s4.5;p18.50">The wavelength of X-Rays has a standard value of 1.54 Angstorm or 1.54*10^-10 m in machines using a copper target. </s><s n="s5.5;p18.50">Substituting the known values into the equation of Bragg's law can help us in determining the values of the unknown factors. </s></p><p n="p19.50"><s n="s1.4;p19.50">It's hard to perform a quantitative analysis of mixtures using X-Ray Diffraction. </s><s n="s2.4;p19.50">It needs a significant amount of computing power and highly precise, error free measurements. </s><s n="s3.4;p19.50">There are a number of methods of calculating the composition of materials in a mixture like The Absorption-Diffraction method, Method of Standard Additions, Internal Standard method, etc. </s><s n="s4.4;p19.50">It involves using the starting and ending 2θ values of the prominent peaks of the pure sample and comparing it against the area of the peak, etc.<ref target="BAWE_0358f-ftnote.005"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0358f-ftnote.005"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1"><seg type="URL" n="http://epswww.unm.edu/xrd/xrdclass/09-Quant-intro.pdf"/> </s></p></note><figure id="BAWE_0358f-pic.004"><head><hi rend="underlined bold">Figure 4</hi><ref target="BAWE_0358f-ftnote.006"/><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0358f-ftnote.006"><p n="pn1.1"> <seg type="URL" n="http://www.chem.biomedchem.uwa.edu.au/chemistry_home/resources_and_services/pxd"/></p></note></head></figure><p n="p20.50"><s n="s1.1;p20.50">Figure 4 above shows a picture of a Siemens X-Ray Diffractometer. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0358f-fig.001"><head><hi rend="underlined bold">Figure 5</hi><ref target="BAWE_0358f-ftnote.007"/><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0358f-ftnote.007"><p n="pn1.1"> <seg type="URL" n="http://materials.binghamton.edu/labs/xray/xray.html"/></p></note></head></figure><p n="p21.50"><s n="s1.1;p21.50">Figure 5 above shows a <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0358f-form.003"/>-intensity plot of vermiculite clay. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">Optical Microscope</head><figure id="BAWE_0358f-pic.005"><head><hi rend="underlined bold">Figure 6</hi><ref target="BAWE_0358f-ftnote.008"/><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0358f-ftnote.008"><p n="pn1.1"> <seg type="URL" n="http://science.howstuffworks.com/light-microscope.htm/printable"/></p></note></head></figure><p n="p22.50"><s n="s1.4;p22.50">An optical compound microscope like the one we used during the lab session comprises of 2 lenses. </s><s n="s2.4;p22.50">The specimen is placed below these lenses and is illuminated by a light bulb. </s><s n="s3.4;p22.50">The light rays from the specimen are converged and brought to focus by a highly spherical and high focal length convex lens. </s><s n="s4.4;p22.50">These converged rays are then magnified by an ocular lens at the eye piece. </s></p><p n="p23.50"><s n="s1.1;p23.50">The Coarse Focus knob is used to move the objective lens up and down to bring the specimen into focus and the Fine Focus knob is used to fine tune the movement. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">HOT PRESS</head><p n="p24.50"><s n="s1.1;p24.50">We also used a hot press to understand how polymeric specimens get recrystallised into a solid before undergoing X-Ray Diffraction </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0358f-pic.006"/><p n="p25.50"><s n="s1.4;p25.50">The picture above shows a hot press. </s><s n="s2.4;p25.50">The powdered specimen is placed in a chamber and exposed to high temperature and pressure. </s><s n="s3.4;p25.50">The heat is provided by resistance or induction of electricity. </s><s n="s4.4;p25.50">The specimen is then cooled by circulating cold water around the mould. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">SCIENTIFIC BALANCE</head><figure id="BAWE_0358f-pic.007"/><p n="p26.50"><s n="s1.2;p26.50">The picture above shows a scientific balance. </s><s n="s2.2;p26.50">We used a similar balance to weigh the samples of PE and HAP before subjecting them to X-Ray Diffraction tests. </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">METHOD</head><div2><head rend="bold">X-Ray </head><p n="p27.50"><s n="s1.3;p27.50">The samples were ground into a fine powder and placed on a Petri dish before placing the Petri dish into the diffractometer. </s><s n="s2.3;p27.50">Mixtures of definite proportions of samples were weighed carefully on a sensitive electronic weighing machine before testing. </s><s n="s3.3;p27.50">The diffractometer produced a graph of 2θ against intensity </s></p><p n="p28.50"><s n="s1.2;p28.50">The measurements for the pure samples of PE and HAP were done previously along with a 50-50 composition mixture of PE and HAP. The results of these testings were provided to us. </s><s n="s2.2;p28.50">We prepared a 20-80 composition mixture of HAP and PE. We used a scientific balance to measure 0.6g of HAP and 2.4g of PE before placing it in the diffractometer. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">SEM </head><p n="p29.50"><s n="s1.2;p29.50">Since electron microscopy uses electrons to resolve the specimens, the specimens need to be conductors of electricity. </s><s n="s2.2;p29.50">Metals don't need any preparation and can directly be placed in the sample holder but ceramics and plastics and materials with living tissues need to be coated with gold before viewing them. </s></p><p n="p30.50"><s n="s1.1;p30.50">When the sample is placed inside the specimen holder inside the vacumised chamber, the microscope is ready to start and it projects the image on a monitor in a few seconds. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">OPTICAL MICROSCOPE</head><p n="p31.50"><s n="s1.9;p31.50">The sample has to be placed on the sample holder and secured safely with leaf spring like securing device. </s><s n="s2.9;p31.50">The light source or the bulb is then turned on. </s><s n="s3.9;p31.50">The brightness is kept low for low resolutions and is increased for higher resolutions. </s><s n="s4.9;p31.50">Making the bulb work on a high brightness for a long time could cause it to fail. </s><s n="s5.9;p31.50">The eye piece was of a standard magnification value of 10X. There were different objective lenses to choose from. </s><s n="s6.9;p31.50">They have different powers of magnification. </s><s n="s7.9;p31.50">When the right one is chosen, the coarse focus knob is used to move the objective lens up and down until a clear image can be resolved. </s><s n="s8.9;p31.50">The fine focus knob can then be used to fine tune the resolution. </s><s n="s9.9;p31.50">The microscope will now produce a clear and magnified image of the sample. </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">POTENTIAL SOURCES OF ERROR</head><p rend="ordered" n="p32.50"><s n="s1.1;p32.50"><hi rend="bold">Vibrations and thermal expansion:</hi> Since electron microscopes resolve samples to a nanometre resolution, the effects of the vibrations in the environment and the expansion sue to the heat produced by the electron beams; etc could cause errors in the images. </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p33.50"><s n="s1.1;p33.50"><hi rend="bold">Impurities in X-Ray Diffraction Samples:</hi> The samples observed using the X-Ray Diffractometer could be contaminated by impurities while handling it and by the atmosphere. </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p34.50"><s n="s1.2;p34.50">Since we use the optical microscope to get an optical perspective of the crystals and don't make any measurements, errors don't make a significant impact. </s><s n="s2.2;p34.50">Besides there shouldn't be any errors associated with optical microscopy anyway. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">OBSERVATION, RESULTS AND ANALYSIS</head><div2><head rend="bold">X-RAY DIFFRACTION</head><table id="BAWE_0358f-tab.001"><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p35.50"><s n="s1.1;p35.50">The pure samples of hydroxy apatite have significant characteristic peaks at 2 θ values of 24 and 32 degrees while the pure Poly ethylene samples have significant characteristic peaks at 21 and 23 degrees. </s></p><p n="p36.50"><s n="s1.2;p36.50">Although the prominent peaks of the constituent elements can be seen in the graph of the mixture with roughly the same shape. </s><s n="s2.2;p36.50">As mentioned before, determination of composition of materials from the graph is tedious and inaccurate when done using manual methods. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">OPTICAL MICROSCOPE</head><div3><head rend="bold">Brass</head><p n="p37.50"><s n="s1.6;p37.50">Brass displayed its characteristic property of twinning under the optical microscope. </s><s n="s2.6;p37.50">The image looked pretty similar to Figure 7. </s><s n="s3.6;p37.50">We could see alternating white and yellow phases. </s><s n="s4.6;p37.50">The specimen composed of 60% copper and 40% Zinc. </s><s n="s5.6;p37.50">Twinning is the phenomenon by which two portions of a crystal have the same relationship. </s><s n="s6.6;p37.50">It can be formed due to the shear force during machining or by recrystalisation during annealing.<ref target="BAWE_0358f-ftnote.009"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0358f-ftnote.009"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1"><seg type="URL" n="http://www.diracdelta.co.uk/science/source/m/e/mechanical%20engineering/source.html"/> </s></p></note><figure id="BAWE_0358f-pic.008"><head><hi rend="underlined bold">Figure 7</hi><ref target="BAWE_0358f-ftnote.010"/><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0358f-ftnote.010"><p n="pn1.1"> <seg type="URL" n="http://www.copper.org/resources/properties/microstructure/images/D1_073m.JPG"/></p></note></head></figure></div3><div3><head rend="bold">Steel</head><p n="p38.50"><s n="s1.5;p38.50">We looked at a specimen of the X19 steel during the lab session. </s><s n="s2.5;p38.50">It had 0.35% Carbon and it was furnace cooled from 870 C. It however wasn't annealed. </s><s n="s3.5;p38.50">It has dendrite shaped pearlite crystals which is a mixture of cementite and ferrite in a ferritic phase. </s><s n="s4.5;p38.50">The pearlite was formed because of a slightly rapid cooling rate. </s><s n="s5.5;p38.50">It's known to be quite hard and brittle. </s></p></div3></div2><div2><head rend="bold">SEM</head><div3><head rend="bold">Porous HAP Bio composite 2</head><figure id="BAWE_0358f-pic.009"/><p n="p39.50"><s n="s1.6;p39.50">Hydroxyapatite or HAP is supposedly an excellent medium for growing bone tissues in. </s><s n="s2.6;p39.50">Artificial joints use polymethylmethacrylate cement (PMMA) to secure the implant in the bones. </s><s n="s3.6;p39.50">They then coat it with HAP for the bone cells to grow around the implant. </s><s n="s4.6;p39.50">One of the properties that make this material suitable for growing bone tissues in it is its large pore size. </s><s n="s5.6;p39.50">The average size of the pores seems to be about 50-70 microns in diameter. </s><s n="s6.6;p39.50">There also seem to be an average of 140 pores per square mm. </s></p></div3><div3><head rend="bold">Apatite Crystals</head><figure id="BAWE_0358f-pic.010"/><p n="p40.50"><s n="s1.4;p40.50">Figure above, shows the formation of bone tissues in the grain boundary of an apatite crystal. </s><s n="s2.4;p40.50">It's probably a good example of biocompatibility and bio-integration. </s><s n="s3.4;p40.50">The size of the grain boundary is less than 1 micron. </s><s n="s4.4;p40.50">The bone tissues however are growing inside it and integrating with the material. </s></p></div3><div3><head rend="bold">Cancellous Bone</head><p n="p41.50"><s n="s1.4;p41.50">Cancellous bones are found in the interior or a bone structure. </s><s n="s2.4;p41.50">It's a low density spongy bone and is normally surrounded by high density bone on the exterior. </s><s n="s3.4;p41.50">It thus enables the flow of blood and nutrients to the entire depth of the bone to facilitate bone tissue formation. </s><s n="s4.4;p41.50">It forms in layers and is spongy in texture.<ref target="BAWE_0358f-ftnote.011"/> Since the structure is made of layers of tissues attached together, there are vacant zones in between that act as pores and the size of these pores seem to be about 1 micron in diameter. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0358f-ftnote.011"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1"><seg type="URL" n="http://www.wheelessonline.com/ortho/cancellous_bone"/> </s></p></note></div3><div3><head rend="bold">Cortical Bone 1</head><figure id="BAWE_0358f-pic.011"/><p n="p42.50"/></div3><div3><head rend="bold">Cortical Bone 2</head><figure id="BAWE_0358f-pic.012"/><p n="p43.50"><s n="s1.4;p43.50">Cortical bone is present at the outer shell of the bones. </s><s n="s2.4;p43.50">It comprises of cylindrical osteon cells that are stacked vertically. </s><s n="s3.4;p43.50">It has many tiny pores of about 5micron diameter and has some larger holes in some places of diameters between 120 and 200 microns. </s><s n="s4.4;p43.50">The shortage of pores, the vertical dense stacking, etc make it hard and resistant to bending and torsion.<ref target="BAWE_0358f-ftnote.012"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0358f-ftnote.012"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1"><seg type="URL" n="http://www.medes.fr/Eristo/Osteoporosis/BonePhysiology.html"/> </s></p></note></div3><div3><head rend="bold">HAP Particles</head><figure id="BAWE_0358f-pic.013"/><p n="p44.50"><s n="s1.3;p44.50">The HAP Particles are naturally found in bones and are also coated or sprayed on bone implants to allow the implant to integrate with the bones. </s><s n="s2.3;p44.50">The size of the crystals however don't seem to be uniform. </s><s n="s3.3;p44.50">The size of the particles roughly ranges between 10 and 30 microns in length and different breadths. </s></p></div3><div3><head rend="bold">PE Particles</head><figure id="BAWE_0358f-pic.014"/><p n="p45.50"/></div3><div3><head rend="bold">PE Surface</head><figure id="BAWE_0358f-pic.015"/><p n="p46.50"><s n="s1.6;p46.50">PE or Polyethylene is a very important biomedical material that is used in bone implants in surfaces that bear friction especially in between the femoral and tibial component of the knee implant as a plate. </s><s n="s2.6;p46.50">A unique grade of polyethylene called Ultra High molecular weight polyethylene or UHMWPE is used in the knee implant. </s><s n="s3.6;p46.50">The topology of the specimen seems to be quite smooth from the image. </s><s n="s4.6;p46.50">The crystal sizes are not uniform again as it depends on the polymerisation, cooling and environmental factors. </s><s n="s5.6;p46.50">Plastics are quite sensitive to temperature. </s><s n="s6.6;p46.50">The crystal sizes however seem to vary between 72 and 278 microns in length. </s></p></div3></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">CONCLUSIONS</head><p n="p47.50"><s n="s1.1;p47.50">All the instruments used to analyse and study the microstructure of materials were unique and served their own purposes. </s></p><p n="p48.50"><s n="s1.3;p48.50">The Simple optical microscope was extremely useful in getting a basic perspective of the shape, distribution and phases of materials in a specimen. </s><s n="s2.3;p48.50">This information can easily be related to its physical and chemical properties. </s><s n="s3.3;p48.50">It can also help us understand the extraction and manufacturing processes involved with the materials and can aide us in optimising them. </s></p><p n="p49.50"><s n="s1.2;p49.50">The Scanning electron microscope was extremely useful in looking at structure in details and understanding the grain sizes and looking at the grain boundaries in detail. </s><s n="s2.2;p49.50">The actual mechanisms involved with strengthening materials like interstitional or substitutional filling of atomic planes can be studies in greater detail under an SEM. The understanding of pore sizes and pore distribution in HAP and the understanding of the crystal sizes of the bone tissues has helped in designing better biomaterials for orthopaedic implants. </s></p><p n="p50.50"><s n="s1.2;p50.50">X-Ray diffraction is an excellent method to understand the crystal structure and the atomic spacing in crystals. </s><s n="s2.2;p50.50">However a lot of calculations and computational power is required to put the data obtained from this test to proper use. </s></p></div1></body><back><div1 type="bibliography"><head rend="underlined bold">REFERENCES &amp; BIBLIOGRAPHY</head><p><seg type="URL" n="http://epswww.unm.edu/xrd/xrdclass/09-Quant-intro.pdf"/></p><p rend="bold">Lab Briefing Sheet</p></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
