<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_0359a" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Coursework2</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">deleted: header: module number, student name; footer: page numbers
</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">2</p><p n="date">unknown</p><p n="module title">unknown</p><p n="module code">223MTH</p><p n="genre family">Exercise</p><p n="discipline">Mathematics</p><p n="disciplinary group">PS</p><p n="grade">unknown</p><p n="number of authors">unknown</p><p n="number of words">593</p><p n="number of s-units">52</p><p n="number of p">46</p><p n="number of tables">0</p><p n="number of figures">1</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">21</p><p n="number of lists">1</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">0</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">11.4</p><p n="average s-units per p">1.1</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">m</p><p n="year of birth">1987</p><p n="first language">Urdu</p><p n="education">unknown</p><p n="course">Bsc Hounour in Mathematical Sciences and Accounting</p><p n="student ID">0359</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front/><body><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="bold">a)</hi> <hi rend="bold italic">What are the advantages of having the lookout in the crows nest as opposed to on the deck of the ship? </hi></head><p n="p1.46"><s n="s1.3;p1.46">The distance to the horizon is an upper limit to how far away it is physically possible to see. </s><s n="s2.3;p1.46">An observer cannot look much far from the deck of the ship as he/she could from the crows nest. </s><s n="s3.3;p1.46">You can have the best view of the approaching hazards, other ships or land from the crows nest. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="bold">b)</hi> <hi rend="bold italic">Construct a mathematical model to show how far a lookout can see. Clearly indicate any assumptions you make and define any parameters you use in your formula and in the construction of your model. </hi></head><figure id="BAWE_0359a-pic.001"/><list type="simple"><item><hi rend="bold italic">C</hi> is the centre of the earth.</item><item><hi rend="bold italic">S</hi> is the surface of the earth.</item><item><hi rend="bold italic">r</hi> is the radius of the earth</item><item><hi rend="bold italic">h</hi> is the height of the observer's eyes above the surface of the earth.</item><item><hi rend="bold italic">d </hi>is the distance from the observer's eyes to the horizon.</item><item><hi rend="bold italic">l</hi> is the distance from the observe to the horizon along the curve of the earth.</item><item><hi rend="bold italic">a </hi>is the angle between the observer and the horizon, measured from the centre of the earth.</item></list><div2><head rend="bold">Assumptions:</head><p n="p2.46"><s n="s1.3;p2.46">We assume no refraction, without refraction we can see farther away. </s><s n="s2.3;p2.46">Horizon is the point on the world's surface at which the line of sight of the viewer, whatever their height, becomes parallel to the surface of the world and then meets the surface of the world. </s><s n="s3.3;p2.46">We also assume a perfectly spherical world and the horizon you are looking at is at sea level. </s></p><p n="p3.46"><s n="s1.1;p3.46">I am going to use the Pythagoras's theorem on the right angled-triangle to calculate the distance from the observer to the horizon. </s></p><p n="p4.46"><s n="s1.1;p4.46">The triangle is a right-angled one, whose sides are the radius of the planet, the radius of the planet plus the height of the observer, and the distance to the horizon. </s></p><p n="p5.46"><s n="s1.1;p5.46">For a right-angled triangle: </s></p><p n="p6.46"><s n="s1.1;p6.46"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0359a-form.001"/> </s></p><p n="p7.46"><s n="s1.1;p7.46">c is the longest side (h+r) </s></p><p n="p8.46"><s n="s1.1;p8.46">a and b are the other sides (d and r) </s></p><p n="p9.46"><s n="s1.1;p9.46"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0359a-form.002"/> </s></p><p n="p10.46"><s n="s1.1;p10.46">Re-arranged the equation gives </s></p><p n="p11.46"><s n="s1.1;p11.46"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0359a-form.003"/> </s></p><p n="p12.46"><s n="s1.1;p12.46"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0359a-form.004"/> </s></p><p n="p13.46"><s n="s1.1;p13.46"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0359a-form.005"/> </s></p><p n="p14.46"><s n="s1.1;p14.46"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0359a-form.006"/> </s></p><p n="p15.46"><s n="s1.1;p15.46">The total distance to the horizon is given by: </s></p><p n="p16.46"><s n="s1.1;p16.46"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0359a-form.007"/> </s></p><p n="p17.46"><s n="s1.1;p17.46">If the approximation, d, is not sufficient then a more accurate distance can be calculated (l). </s></p><p n="p18.46"><s n="s1.1;p18.46"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0359a-form.008"/> </s></p><p n="p19.46"><s n="s1.1;p19.46"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0359a-form.009"/> </s></p><p n="p20.46"><s rend="bold" n="s1.1;p20.46">So, </s></p><p n="p21.46"><s n="s1.1;p21.46"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0359a-form.010"/> </s></p><p n="p22.46"><s n="s1.1;p22.46">The arc of the circle <hi rend="italic">l</hi> has a length l = r x  </s></p><p n="p23.46"><s n="s1.1;p23.46">So the substitute the above equation into this we get: </s></p><p n="p24.46"><s n="s1.1;p24.46"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0359a-form.011"/> </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">C) <hi rend="italic">you</hi> <hi rend="italic">are given that the eye-level of a typical on deck lookout is 1.75m above deck level, the floor of the crow's nest is 25m above deck level and the deck itself is 5m above (flat) sea level. The radius of the earth can be taken as 6300 kilometers.</hi> </head><div2><head rend="bold">For deck of ship</head><p n="p25.46"><s n="s1.1;p25.46">Radius of earth: 6300 km </s></p><p n="p26.46"><s n="s1.1;p26.46">height= (typical eye level)1.75+ (deck above the sea level) 5 </s></p><p n="p27.46"><s n="s1.1;p27.46">=6.75 m </s></p><p n="p28.46"><s n="s1.1;p28.46">Converting meters into kilometers </s></p><p n="p29.46"><s n="s1.1;p29.46"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0359a-form.012"/> </s></p><p n="p30.46"><s n="s1.1;p30.46"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0359a-form.013"/> </s></p><p n="p31.46"><s n="s1.1;p31.46"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0359a-form.014"/> </s></p><p n="p32.46"><s n="s1.1;p32.46"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0359a-form.015"/> </s></p><p n="p33.46"><s n="s1.1;p33.46"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0359a-form.016"/> </s></p><p n="p34.46"><s rend="bold" n="s1.1;p34.46">d = 9.2 km </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">For crows nest:</head><p n="p35.46"><s n="s1.1;p35.46">Floor of the deck is 25m above the sea level </s></p><p n="p36.46"><s n="s1.1;p36.46">The deck itself is 5 m above the sea level </s></p><p n="p37.46"><s n="s1.1;p37.46">So </s></p><p n="p38.46"><s n="s1.1;p38.46">height= 25+5=30m </s></p><p n="p39.46"><s n="s1.1;p39.46">Converting meter into kilometers we get: </s></p><p n="p40.46"><s n="s1.1;p40.46"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0359a-form.017"/> </s></p><p n="p41.46"><s n="s1.1;p41.46"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0359a-form.018"/> </s></p><p n="p42.46"><s n="s1.1;p42.46"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0359a-form.019"/> </s></p><p n="p43.46"><s n="s1.1;p43.46"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0359a-form.020"/> </s></p><p n="p44.46"><s n="s1.1;p44.46"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0359a-form.021"/> </s></p><p n="p45.46"><s rend="bold" n="s1.1;p45.46">d = 19.4 km </s></p><p n="p46.46"><s n="s1.3;p46.46">From the calculation, we can conclude that we can see much far from the crows nest compare to the deck of the ship. </s><s n="s2.3;p46.46">For the deck of the ship the height is 6.75m and an observer can see up to 9.2 km far whereas the height for the crows nest is 30m and an observer can see 19.4 km far. </s><s n="s3.3;p46.46">It means you can see (19.4-9.2=10.2) up to the double distance from the crows nest compare to the deck of the ship. </s></p></div2></div1></body><back/></text></TEI.2>
