<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_0360e" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Female Genital Mutilation and the Efficacy of International Human Rights Law</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">The document has a title page which contains:
document title</note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">Language used in quote: <foreign id="English">English</foreign></note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">4</p><p n="date">2006-12</p><p n="module title">Women's Human Rights</p><p n="module code">LA967</p><p n="genre family">Essay</p><p n="discipline">Law</p><p n="disciplinary group">SS</p><p n="grade">D</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">2739</p><p n="number of s-units">62</p><p n="number of p">25</p><p n="number of tables">0</p><p n="number of figures">0</p><p n="number of block quotes">2</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">0</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">5</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">44.2</p><p n="average s-units per p">2.5</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">f</p><p n="year of birth">1981</p><p n="first language">Arabic</p><p n="education">OSA</p><p n="course">LLM in International Development Law and Human Rights</p><p n="student ID">0360</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><docTitle><titlePart><hi rend="bold">Female Genital Mutilation and the</hi> <hi rend="bold"> Efficacy of International Human Rights Law</hi></titlePart></docTitle></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Introduction</head><p n="p1.25"><s n="s1.4;p1.25">The efficacy of human rights law as a tool for women's empowerment has been vigorously debated over the past several decades. </s><s n="s2.4;p1.25">This article explores this debate focusing on the practice of female genital mutilation (FGM). </s><s n="s3.4;p1.25">The extensive literature that has been devoted to this practice and grown throughout the 1990s and the wide-ranging impact that this practice has on wide range of planes from the legal, to the political and the cultural, makes it an ideal case study for an examination of both the advantages and drawbacks of using international human rights law in the struggle for women's human rights. </s><s n="s4.4;p1.25">The cultural and religious significance of FGM, its strong links to sexual and reproductive health and rights, and the critiques raised by postcolonial feminists in particular on the dangers of gender essentialism and exclusive focus on violence against women has made FGM a contentious and vigorously debated topic. </s></p><p n="p2.25"><s n="s1.4;p2.25">In the first part of this article, I briefly examine how the practice of FGM gained prominence in the international women's human rights movement. </s><s n="s2.4;p2.25">I summarize some of the contentious issues that FGM has raised, particularly the criticism that the FGM campaign essentializes both gender and culture. </s><s n="s3.4;p2.25">In the second part of the article, I discuss the role of UN treaty bodies and their articulation of FGM as a human right violation through concluding observations on state reports, and explore whether such exchanges between state officials and committee members provide meaningful dialogue that has an impact on the ground. </s><s n="s4.4;p2.25">Finally, I argue that a current gap in the literature on FGM, particularly that written from the international human rights law perspective, is a failure to take sufficient account of the wider social constraints that restrict women's ability to enjoy their rights pronounced under human rights instruments. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">FGM's Rise to Prominence: Violence against Women</head><p n="p3.25"><s n="s1.2;p3.25">When at the 1993 Human Rights Conference in Vienna, the slogan 'women's rights are human rights' became a reality, gender-based violence as a major human rights issue also took off and was the culmination of many decades of activism and lobbying.<ref target="BAWE_0360e-ftnote.001"/> Another watershed was the 1994 International Conference on Population and Development (ICPD) in Cairo, and the 1995 Fourth World Conference in Beijing which brought to the forefront issues regarding women's reproductive health and choices.<ref target="BAWE_0360e-ftnote.002"/> It is particularly important to examine the struggle against FGM within the context of gender-based violence and women's sexual and reproductive health campaigns, which these conferences brought to the forefront. </s><s n="s2.2;p3.25">Although activists and women's rights advocates had written about the practice much earlier<ref target="BAWE_0360e-ftnote.003"/>, it was only in the 1990s that a concerted, vigorous and international campaign against FGM truly gained momentum capturing the attention of human rights activists and academics, UN bodies and the media. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0360e-ftnote.001"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Parisi (2002), 581. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0360e-ftnote.002"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Hellum and Knudsen (2006), 339. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0360e-ftnote.003"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">See, among others, Assaad (1980). </s></p></note><p n="p4.25"><s n="s1.2;p4.25">The World Health Organization (WHO) defines FGM as comprising "all procedures involving partial or total removal of the external female genitalia or other injury to the female genital organs whether for cultural, religious or other non-therapeutic reasons." </s><ref target="BAWE_0360e-ftnote.004"/><s n="s2.2;p4.25">According to the WHO, FGM has both immediate and long-term health consequences in addition to physical, psychosexual and psychological effects.<ref target="BAWE_0360e-ftnote.005"/> For this reason, FGM fits well into both the gender-based violence and sexual and reproductive rights and health; not only is it physically injurious and hence a violent act against women but it has the potential to affect women's sexual and reproductive lives and choices. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0360e-ftnote.004"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">"What is Female Genital Mutilation?" &lt;<seg type="URL" n="http://www.who.int/mediacentre/factsheets/fs241/en/"/>> </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0360e-ftnote.005"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid. </s></p></note><div2><head rend="italic">FGM and the Culture Debate</head><p n="p5.25"><s n="s1.3;p5.25">Questions such as does FGM constitute torture, can and should a cultural and religious practice be vehemently condemned as a human rights violation, is the focus on FGM a Western fetish and what measures, if any, can be taken to deconstruct a deeply embedded practice are just a few examples of the contentious issues raised in the struggle against FGM.<ref target="BAWE_0360e-ftnote.006"/> At the heart of the debate is the construction of cultural and traditional practices and its impact on women. </s><s n="s2.3;p5.25">The Convention on the Elimination of Discrimination against Women (CEDAW) makes clear that culture, tradition and religion cannot be used as an excuse to deprive women of their rights, the implication being that it is largely these three elements that keep women in subordinate positions.<ref target="BAWE_0360e-ftnote.007"/> Sally Engle Merry examines the use of 'culture' and 'tradition' within the discourse of human rights arguing that feminist and human rights scholars and activists "identify culture and tradition as the source of the problem." </s><ref target="BAWE_0360e-ftnote.008"/><s n="s3.3;p5.25">Merry describes FGM (or female genital cutting as she names it) as "the poster child for this understanding of culture"<ref target="BAWE_0360e-ftnote.009"/> where culture plays a harmful and oppressive role through its subordination of women, and further elaborates how FGM "became the prototype of a practice justified by custom and culture and redefined as an act of violence."<ref target="BAWE_0360e-ftnote.010"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0360e-ftnote.006"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">See Han (2002), and Nussbaum (2002), 120-121. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0360e-ftnote.007"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Art. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">2, CEDAW. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0360e-ftnote.008"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Merry (2006), 13. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0360e-ftnote.009"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0360e-ftnote.010"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid, 27-28. </s></p></note><p n="p6.25"><s n="s1.3;p6.25">Postcolonial feminism adds an additional dimension to the controversy surrounding FGM by raising questions about the process of legalization of human rights, the assumptions made about gender and culture and the tendency to universalize women's experiences and universalize solutions.<ref target="BAWE_0360e-ftnote.011"/> FGM is particularly sensitive to this kind of critique and activists have noted the tendency to sensationalize and oversimplify FGM in Western circles. </s><s n="s2.3;p6.25">Toubia has stated how FGM is portrayed "as irrefutable evidence of the barbarism and vulgarity of underdeveloped countries"<ref target="BAWE_0360e-ftnote.012"/>, and Seif El Dawla has similarly noted how activists like her are "constantly trying to make others understand that women who circumcise their daughters are not barbarians or vampires (134). </s><s n="s3.3;p6.25">Moreover, Mugo argues that FGM has been uprooted from its context with the effect of reducing African women's struggle to effectively one issue.<ref target="BAWE_0360e-ftnote.013"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0360e-ftnote.011"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Kapur (2006), 103. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0360e-ftnote.012"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Toubia, as qtd in Abusharaf (2001), 101. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0360e-ftnote.013"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Mugo (1996-1997), 479. </s></p></note><p n="p7.25"><s n="s1.4;p7.25">The debate about FGM's harmfulness is further complicated when reading narratives from women who support the practice. </s><s n="s2.4;p7.25">Obiora points out that FGM can be considered a "form of self-assertion, or even the ultimate expression of their personhood." </s><ref target="BAWE_0360e-ftnote.014"/><s n="s3.4;p7.25">Some women also argue that by decreasing a women's sexual needs she will actually become more powerful and less at the mercy of her husband.<ref target="BAWE_0360e-ftnote.015"/> Others prefer the appearance of circumcised genitals and claim that they still experience sexual pleasure and orgasm.<ref target="BAWE_0360e-ftnote.016"/> These narratives are often very hard for feminists to swallow. </s><s n="s4.4;p7.25">Indeed, researchers on the IRRRAG project admitted the presence of an "avoidable tension" when doing research on the cross-cultural meanings of reproductive rights asking themselves, "what if women's voices tell us things we would rather not hear, or simply cannot hear - because they express values and priorities that are different from those we espouse?<ref target="BAWE_0360e-ftnote.017"/> Philosopher Diana Meyers has also argued that "the feminist literature on the [practice] provides ample evidence that many exercise effective agency" and "autonomy is to be found among accommodaters as well as resisters.<ref target="BAWE_0360e-ftnote.018"/> Invariably however when such voices do emerge, it is often argued that patriarchal assumptions underlie such acceptance and that the 'choice' women exercise in performing FGM "is not truly meaningful, but...shaped by a male dominated culture." <ref target="BAWE_0360e-ftnote.019"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0360e-ftnote.014"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Obiora (1996-1997), 329. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0360e-ftnote.015"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Seif El Dawla (1999), 85 and Abusharaf (2001), 130. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0360e-ftnote.016"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Abusharaf (2001), 122-123; 128. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0360e-ftnote.017"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Petchesky (1998), 20-21. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0360e-ftnote.018"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Meyers, as qtd in Abusharaf (2001), 1. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0360e-ftnote.019"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Trueblood (1999-2000), 453. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">See also Tahzib-Lie (2000) who points out that this 'informed choice' endangers not only the participant's health but others too and hence constitutes a public health threat that should be curtailed by the state, 976-977. </s></p></note><p n="p8.25"><s n="s1.3;p8.25">The above debates are unlikely to subside but will continue to provoke discussion among human rights scholars and activists. </s><s n="s2.3;p8.25">What is significant for this essay is to contemplate how these debates feed into the discussions that take place in UN bodies when states present their reports and experts question state representatives, provide feedback and comment, and ask for further elaboration. </s><s n="s3.3;p8.25">How much leniency, if any, do they give for arguments of 'culture'? </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">UN Treaty Bodies and FGM</head><p n="p9.25"><s n="s1.3;p9.25">There are several UN conventions<ref target="BAWE_0360e-ftnote.020"/> applicable to FGM, but one of the greatest challenges in using international law is the lack of enforceability of human rights instruments is the weak enforcement mechanisms.<ref target="BAWE_0360e-ftnote.021"/> There are few mechanisms that 'force' states to comply with their responsibilities, and it is largely tools such as international pressure and 'naming and shaming' that prompt states into action. </s><s n="s2.3;p9.25">State reporting mechanisms are one of the means used to monitor state compliance with treaty obligations, which also allows experts sitting on the various treaty body committees to engage in a dialogue with states to determine what progress has or has not been made, what measures have been taken to implement the treaties, and what obstacles exist and their possible remedies, in addition to the adoption of concluding observations and comments on state reports. </s><s n="s3.3;p9.25">This section will look at lists of issues, replies to issues and concluding observations of the Committee on Civil and Political Rights (CCPR), the Committee on Economic, Social and Cultural Rights (CESCR), the Committee on the Elimination of Discrimination against Women (CEDAW), and the Committee on the Rights of the Child (CRC) regarding FGM in African countries, and an analysis and critique of these observations. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0360e-ftnote.020"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Although only the Declaration on the Elimination of Violence Against Women specifically identifies FGM as physical, sexual and psychological violence (Art. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">2), other relevant conventions include the Universal Declaration of Human Rights, the Convention against Torture. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0360e-ftnote.021"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">See Wood (2001) and Han (2002). </s></p></note><div2><head rend="italic">The CESCR: Egypt and Sudan</head><p n="p10.25"><s n="s1.1;p10.25">Egypt, Sudan and Senegal were asked by the CESR in May 1999<ref target="BAWE_0360e-ftnote.022"/>, December 1999<ref target="BAWE_0360e-ftnote.023"/> and December 2000<ref target="BAWE_0360e-ftnote.024"/> respectively to respond to a list of issues in their state reports that included questions on FGM. Egypt was requested to provide information on the effectiveness of measures taken to eradicate FGM in Egypt,<ref target="BAWE_0360e-ftnote.025"/> and responded with the following: </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0360e-ftnote.022"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">E/C.12/Q/EGY/1. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">(List of Issues: 21/05/99). </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0360e-ftnote.023"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">E/C.12/Q/Sud/1. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">(List of Issues: 13/12/99). </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0360e-ftnote.024"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">E/C.12/Q/Sen/1. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">(List of Issues: 13/12/2000). </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0360e-ftnote.025"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">E/C.12/Q/EGY/1. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">(List of Issues: 21/05/99), paragraph 34. </s></p></note><quote lang="English">...female education has directly helped to eliminate [FGM] in urban areas and among educated women. This custom is now practised, to a decreasing extent, in remote rural areas.<ref target="BAWE_0360e-ftnote.026"/></quote><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0360e-ftnote.026"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">E/C.12/Q/EGY/1. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">(Reply to List of Issues: 28/03/2000), paragraph 34. </s></p></note><p n="p11.25"><s n="s1.2;p11.25">The reply also noted that the government promotes educational efforts and disseminates health information through the media and with the help of religious ministers to highlight the dangers of excision, and stated that the Egyptian Penal Code "prescribes penalties for anyone who performs such operations." </s><ref target="BAWE_0360e-ftnote.027"/><s n="s2.2;p11.25">However it also added that since it is prohibited in health centres and hospitals, unqualified persons continue to secretly perform it. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0360e-ftnote.027"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid. </s></p></note><p n="p12.25"><s n="s1.2;p12.25">Sudan was requested to provide statistics disaggregated by age group, geographic location and socio-economic standards on reports that urban educated families are abandoning FGM.<ref target="BAWE_0360e-ftnote.028"/> The Sudanese government did not provide a detailed response to the requested information, and instead stated that FGM had considerably dropped in a number of towns, villages and rural areas and that statistic will be provided as soon they are available. </s><s n="s2.2;p12.25">The reply also explained how the government was pursuing education and awareness-raising to highlight the harms of FGM and help eradicate it through lectures, midwife and nurse training and through women's unions.<ref target="BAWE_0360e-ftnote.029"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0360e-ftnote.028"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">E/C.12/Q/Sud/1. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">(List of Issues: 13/12/99), paragraph 37. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0360e-ftnote.029"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">E/C.12/Q/Sud/1. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">(Reply to List of Issues: 24/06/2000), paragraph 37. </s></p></note><p n="p13.25"><s n="s1.3;p13.25">In both cases, the CESCR is concerned with the success of various measures but the responses highlight the difficult in providing immediate and quantifiable 'results'. </s><s n="s2.3;p13.25">Egypt's reply is rather debatable because it is difficult, if not impossible, to make a statement claiming FGM's eradication (even in urban areas), for the main reason that FGM is an irreversible process, and to claim that it has been eradicated requires waiting until the next generation to see if girls who are circumcised now end up circumcising their own daughters. </s><s n="s3.3;p13.25">Sudan's response is slightly more restrained as the reply indicates that such detailed statistics (which would require quite intensive research) are unavailable at present. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="italic">UN Treaty Bodies and Concluding Observations</head><p n="p14.25"><s n="s1.1;p14.25">An examination of concluding observations regarding FGM by the CESCR, CCPR, CRC, CEDAW and CAT of just over twenty African states yields responses that repeated frequently and can be categorized into the following groups: </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p15.25"><s n="s1.1;p15.25">Statements of concern regarding FGM that outline how it is a harmful and discriminatory traditional practice<ref target="BAWE_0360e-ftnote.030"/>, that it constitutes cruel, inhuman and degrading treatment<ref target="BAWE_0360e-ftnote.031"/>, and has physical, psychological and social impact on women's health.<ref target="BAWE_0360e-ftnote.032"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0360e-ftnote.030"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">See, Zimbabwe, CEDAW, A/53/38/Rev.1 part I (1998) 13, paragraph 141. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0360e-ftnote.031"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">See Lesotho, CCPR, A/54/40 vol. I (1999) 52, paragraph 255. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0360e-ftnote.032"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">See Guinea, CESCR, E/1997/22 (1996) 39, paragraph 207. </s></p></note><p rend="ordered" n="p16.25"><s n="s1.1;p16.25">Calls to conduct studies on the practice and plans to eradicate it.<ref target="BAWE_0360e-ftnote.033"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0360e-ftnote.033"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">See, Yemen, CCPR, A/50/40 vol. I (1995) 49 paragraph 261. </s></p></note><p rend="ordered" n="p17.25"><s n="s1.1;p17.25">Calls to take steps to eradicate the practice through education and sensitization programmes<ref target="BAWE_0360e-ftnote.034"/>, and the adoption of legislation prohibiting FGM.<ref target="BAWE_0360e-ftnote.035"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0360e-ftnote.034"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">See, United Republic of Tanzania, CRC, CRC/C/108 (2001) 71, paragraph 403. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0360e-ftnote.035"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">See, Democratic Republic of the Congo, CEDAW, A/55/38 part I (2000) 21, paragraph 216. </s></p></note><p rend="ordered" n="p18.25"><s n="s1.1;p18.25">Positive praise regarding the adoption of laws against FGM or awareness campaigns.<ref target="BAWE_0360e-ftnote.036"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0360e-ftnote.036"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">See Togo, CCPR, A/58/40 vol. I (2002) 36, paragraph 78(5). </s></p></note><p rend="ordered" n="p19.25"><s n="s1.1;p19.25">Statements of concern that despite the existence of legislation banning FGM, its practice is still widespread and therefore requires more effective implementation of education campaigns.<ref target="BAWE_0360e-ftnote.037"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0360e-ftnote.037"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">See, Egypt, CRC, CRC/C/103 (2001) 36, paragraphs 240 and 241. </s></p></note><p n="p20.25"><s n="s1.5;p20.25">It is clear that legislation and education/awareness campaigns are the two main prongs that UN committees advocate in eradicating FGM, and indeed, the former cannot work on its own. </s><s n="s2.5;p20.25">The main criticism however is that recommendations tend to stop at legislation and education. </s><s n="s3.5;p20.25">There are occasionally more detailed suggestions on means to eradicate the practice such as enlisting the support of religious and community leaders<ref target="BAWE_0360e-ftnote.038"/>, or using the support of civil society and NGOs and securing alternate sources of income for those who perform FGM for a living.<ref target="BAWE_0360e-ftnote.039"/> However, the wider context of women's lives, which does influence their attitudes towards a practice such as FGM is left unexamined and untouched. </s><s n="s4.5;p20.25">As can be seen in the list of issues given by the CESCR to Egypt and Sudan, states are asked to explain what measures have been taken, and an evaluation of the success or failure of such measures, but they are not asked about broader health policies or the right of access to a minimum level of health care. </s><s n="s5.5;p20.25">This isolates FGM "from the gamut of auxiliary conditions that anchor and motivate it" and implies a top-down approach that is unlikely to succeed.<ref target="BAWE_0360e-ftnote.040"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0360e-ftnote.038"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">See, Sudan, CRC, CRC/C/20 (1993) 22, paragraph 116. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0360e-ftnote.039"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Kenya, CEDAW, A/58/38 part I (2003) 35, paragraph 214. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0360e-ftnote.040"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Obiora (1996-1997), 364. </s></p></note></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Gaps in the FGM Debate</head><p n="p21.25"><s n="s1.4;p21.25">The above debates illustrate the immense difficulties in bringing about change in people's actions and behaviours through human rights instruments and bodies. </s><s n="s2.4;p21.25">Following on from the critique that the wider context of women's lives is almost absent from FGM debates by UN treaty bodies is the notion that the choices women make in their daily lives are often being 'traded' in for others. </s><s n="s3.4;p21.25">This means that while women seize upon one right, they are often compelled to give up something for that right in a trade-off. </s><s n="s4.4;p21.25">Seif El Dawla <hi rend="italic">et al</hi> explore the strategic accommodations made by Egyptian women in their reproductive lives and illustrate how these trade-offs are made; resorting to the traditional practice of <hi rend="italic">baladi dokhla</hi> (breaking the hymen) on the wedding night is painful and embarrassing but on the other hand it helps ensure greater freedom of mobility and the ability to go out and work because it 'proves' a woman's chastity. <ref target="BAWE_0360e-ftnote.041"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0360e-ftnote.041"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Seif El Dawlaal. (1998), 87. </s></p></note><p n="p22.25"><s n="s1.3;p22.25">The different voices that Seif El Dawla <hi rend="italic">et al</hi> heard from women during their research with regard to decisions made about reproduction and their bodies made it difficult to pin down one prototypical example of strategic accommodation, and instead they used four categories to reflect the comments that women expressed; the first is 'it is just the nature of things'; the second is 'painful, but necessary'; the third is 'resistance and resistance in disguise'; and the fourth is 'no is no!' </s><s n="s2.3;p22.25">The advantages of using these strategic postures as an analytical tool is that rather than presenting a static picture of unchanging gender relations and hierarchies, it highlights how relations and hierarchies change, and how constraints both emerge and dissolve rather than remaining constant. </s><s n="s3.3;p22.25">This is particularly important when looking at FGM that "has a social function that many young girls and women find compelling - beyond choice."<ref target="BAWE_0360e-ftnote.042"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0360e-ftnote.042"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid, 101. </s></p></note><p n="p23.25"><s n="s1.1;p23.25">This provides a much more nuanced, complex and complete picture of the decisions women make when performing such practices as FGM. UN treaty bodies consistently note their concern about traditional harmful practices and the need to combat them through education, however, women are not necessarily ignorant of the harm but </s></p><quote lang="English">...often choose to go along with traditional expectations they dislike, even ones that blatantly violate their own sense of bodily integrity or wellbeing, in order to gain other advantages under existing domestic and community power relations in which their manoeuvrability is constrained. <ref target="BAWE_0360e-ftnote.043"/></quote><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0360e-ftnote.043"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Petchesky (1998), 19. </s></p></note><p n="p24.25"><s n="s1.3;p24.25">Legislation, education, the support of civil society, and religious and community leaders are important 'multidisciplinary' strategies, but at the same time they are not always in harmony which has led Egyptian women for example, "to negotiate the conflicting pressures of religious authorities, medical authorities, class divisions, and above all traditional gender norms when it comes to FGM." </s><ref target="BAWE_0360e-ftnote.044"/><s n="s2.3;p24.25">Ultimately women continuously adopt strategies that sometimes accommodate and at other times resist. </s><s n="s3.3;p24.25">At the international level, such nuanced categories and concepts are often simplified,<ref target="BAWE_0360e-ftnote.045"/> and with limited time and resources it is debatable whether they can delve into the complex underlying reasons that perpetuate 'harmful traditional practices' against women. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0360e-ftnote.044"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Seif El Dawla <hi rend="italic">et al</hi> (1998), 85. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">See Seif El Dawla (1999, 130-133) for a comprehensive discussion of the complex politics surrounding the banning of FGM in Egypt. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0360e-ftnote.045"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Merry (2006), 28. </s></p></note></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Conclusion</head><p n="p25.25"><s n="s1.4;p25.25">International human rights law is only one of several tools that should be used to combat the practice of FGM. The challenged faced is "not only one of opposing harmful practices or mobilizing around rights but of publicly deconstructing the ideological and social system...that makes those practices acceptable and sometimes even desired." </s><ref target="BAWE_0360e-ftnote.046"/><s n="s2.4;p25.25">Ultimately the task of public deconstruction will not take place at international conferences or in UN forums but at the grassroots level. </s><s n="s3.4;p25.25">An-Na'im argues persuasively that, "unless international human rights have sufficient legitimacy within particular cultures and traditions, their implementation will be thwarted." </s><ref target="BAWE_0360e-ftnote.047"/><s n="s4.4;p25.25">Not only is legitimacy of human rights law needed, but also a recognition that this law's efficacy is contingent on adopting a broader socioeconomic scheme. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0360e-ftnote.046"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid, 101. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0360e-ftnote.047"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">An'Naim (1994), 172-173. </s></p></note></div1></body><back><div1 type="bibliography"><head rend="bold">Bibliography</head><p>Abusharaf, R.M. (2001). "Female Virtuous Cuts: Female Genital Circumcision in an African Ontology" <hi rend="bold">12 </hi><hi rend="italic">Differences: A Journal of Feminist Cultural Studies,</hi> pp. 112-140. </p><p>An'Naim, A. (1994). State Responsibility under International Human Rights Law to Change Religious and Customary Laws. <hi rend="italic">In</hi>: Cook, R., ed. <hi rend="italic">Human rights of women: National and international perspectives.</hi> Philadelphia: University of Pennsylvannia Press, pp. 167-188.</p><p>Assaad, M. (1980). "Female Circumcision in Egypt: Social Implications, Current Research, and Prospects for Change" <hi rend="bold">11 </hi><hi rend="italic">Studies in Family Planning</hi>, pp. 3-16. </p><p>Bahin, T. (2000). "Applying a Gender Perspective in the area of the Right to Freedom of Religion or Belief" <hi rend="bold">3 </hi><hi rend="italic">Brigham Young University Law Review</hi>, pp. 967-987.</p><p>Han, E. (2002). "Legal and Non-Legal Responses to Concerns for Women's Rights in Countries Practicing Female Circumcision: Debating Women's Equality" 22 <hi rend="italic">Boston College Third World Law Journal</hi> [online] <hi rend="italic">LexisNexis.</hi> (Accessed 25 Nov. 2006), pp. 201-223. </p><p>Hellum, A. and Knudsen, A.L.S. (2006). "From human development to human rights: A southern African perspective on women and teenage girls' right to reproductive choice," <hi rend="italic">Forum for Development Studies</hi> No. 1, pp.334-363. </p><p>Kapur, R. (2006). Revisioning the role of law in women's human rights struggles. <hi rend="italic">In</hi>: Meckled-Garcia, S. and Cali, B., eds. <hi rend="italic">The Legalization of Human Rights Multidisciplinary perspectives on human rights and human rights law</hi>. London: Routledge, pp. 101-116.</p><p>Merry, S. (2006). <hi rend="italic">Human Rights and Gender Violence: Translating International Law into Local Justice</hi>. Chicago: The University of Chicago Press. </p><p>Mugo, M.G. (1996-1997). "Elitist Anti-Circumcision Discourse as Mutilating and Anti-Feminist" 47 <hi rend="italic">Case Western Reserve Law Journal</hi> [online] <hi rend="italic">HeinOnline</hi>. (Accessed 2 Dec. 2006) pp. 461-479.</p><p>Obiora, L.A. (1996-1997). "Bridges and Barricades: Rethinking Polemics and Instransigence in the Campaign against Female Circumcision" 47 <hi rend="italic">Case Western Reserve Law Journal</hi> [online] <hi rend="italic">HeinOnline</hi>. (Accessed 2 Dec. 2006) pp. 275-378.</p><p>Rahman, A. and Toubia, N. (2000). <hi rend="italic">Female Genital Mutilation: A Guide to Laws and Policies Worldwide</hi>. London: Zed Books. </p><p>Nussbaum, M. (1999). <hi rend="italic">Sex and Social Justice</hi>. Oxford: Oxford University Press.</p><p>Parisi, L. (2002). "Feminist praxis and women's human rights" <hi rend="bold">4 </hi><hi rend="italic">Journal of Human Rights</hi>, pp. 571-585.</p><p>Petchesky, R. (1998). Introduction. <hi rend="italic">In</hi>: Petchesky, R. and Judd, K., eds. <hi rend="italic">Negotiating Reproductive Rights: Women's Perspectives across Countries and Cultures.</hi> London: Zed Books, pp. 1-30.</p><p>Seif El Dawla, A. (1999). "The Political and Legal Struggle over Female Genital Mutilation in Egypt: Five Years since the ICPD" 17 <hi rend="italic">Reproductive Health Matters</hi>, pp. 128-136.</p><p>Seif El Dawla, A., Abdel Hadi, A., and Abdel Wahab, N. (1998). Women's Wit over Men's: Trade-offs and Strategic Accommodations in Egyptian Women's Reproductive Lives. <hi rend="italic">In</hi>: Petchesky, R. and Judd, K., eds. <hi rend="italic">Negotiating Reproductive Rights: Women's Perspectives across Countries and Cultures.</hi> London: Zed Books, pp. 69-107.</p><p>Trueblood, L. (1999-2000). "Female Genital Mutilation: A Discussion of International Human Rights Instruments, Cultural Sovereighnty and Dominance Theory" 28 <hi rend="italic">Denver Journal of International Law and Policy</hi> [online] <hi rend="italic">HeinOnline.</hi> (Accessed 2 Dec. 2006), pp. 437-467.</p><p>"What is Female Genital Mutilation?" <hi rend="italic">World Health Organization</hi> Fact Sheet, &lt;<seg type="URL" n="http://www.who.int/mediacentre/factsheets/fs241/en/"/>></p><p>Wood, A. (2001). "A Cultural Rite of Passage or a form of Torture: Female Genital Mutilation from an International Law Perspective" 12 <hi rend="italic">Hastings Women's Law Journal</hi> [online] <hi rend="italic">LexisNexis</hi>. (Accessed 25 Nov. 2006) pp.347-386.</p><p>United Nations Committee on CEDAW (1990) <hi rend="italic">General Recommendation No. 14, Female circumcision.</hi></p><p>United Nations Committee on CEDAW (1999) <hi rend="italic">General Recommendation No. 24, Article 12, Women and health.</hi></p></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
