<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_0360c" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Refugees and the principle of Burden-Sharing</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">The document has a title page which contains:
document title</note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">Language used in quote: <foreign id="English">English</foreign></note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">deleted: page numbers</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">4</p><p n="date">2006-12</p><p n="module title">Approaches to Global Justice</p><p n="module code">LA958</p><p n="genre family">Essay</p><p n="discipline">Law</p><p n="disciplinary group">SS</p><p n="grade">D</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">2949</p><p n="number of s-units">70</p><p n="number of p">20</p><p n="number of tables">0</p><p n="number of figures">0</p><p n="number of block quotes">1</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">0</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">0</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">42.1</p><p n="average s-units per p">3.5</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">f</p><p n="year of birth">1981</p><p n="first language">Arabic</p><p n="education">OSA</p><p n="course">LLM in International Development Law and Human Rights</p><p n="student ID">0360</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><docTitle><titlePart rend="bold">Refugees and the principle of Burden-Sharing</titlePart></docTitle></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Introduction</head><p n="p1.20"><s n="s1.6;p1.20">The concept of burden-sharing in the context of forced migration raises a host of questions that ultimately spring from the question of what to do and how to deal with 'strangers' in our midst.<ref target="BAWE_0360c-ftnote.001"/> In forced migration these 'strangers' arrive seeking safe haven, and particularly in cases of sudden mass influxes, place burdens<ref target="BAWE_0360c-ftnote.002"/> and strains on the receiving host state. </s><s n="s2.6;p1.20">The Preamble of the 1951 Convention Relating to the Status of Refugees (hereafter the '1951 Convention') acknowledges that "the grant of asylum may place unduly heavy burdens on certain countries," and hence "a satisfactory solution of a problem of which the United Nations has recognized the international scope and nature cannot therefore achieved without international co-operation." </s><s n="s3.6;p1.20">This short statement raises a myriad number of questions such as what does it mean to have an 'unduly heavy burden'? </s><s n="s4.6;p1.20">What is the threshold of such a burden? </s><s n="s5.6;p1.20">What kind of 'solution' is envisaged and does it entail monetary compensation, or other forms of compensation? </s><s n="s6.6;p1.20">Is international co-operation a binding legal obligation, or simply an ethical one? </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0360c-ftnote.001"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">This question was raised during Week 3 of the Approaches to Global Justice module. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0360c-ftnote.002"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">The controversy regarding the use of the term 'burden' to describe refugees has been raised by various authors such as Noll (2003), Taylor (2005: 39), and therefore will not be discussed here. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">Noll points out that burdens can "mutate into resources" and therefore "the language of burden-sharing tends to amplify the short-term bias" (2003: 237). </s></p></note><p n="p2.20"><s n="s1.3;p2.20">This paper focuses in the first part of this essay on the status of claims about justice that were voiced during the drafting of the Convention in the discussion of the notion of 'unduly heavy burden.' </s><s n="s2.3;p2.20">In the second part of this essay I analyze recent literature on burden-sharing examine the Tampa boat crisis as a case study where a large of refugees brought to the forefront questions relating to burden-sharing. </s><s n="s3.3;p2.20">Finally, I comment on Santos' proposition of a transnational conception of burden-sharing<ref target="BAWE_0360c-ftnote.003"/>, and whether such a proposition is likely to succeed in light of growing restrictions on state borders. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0360c-ftnote.003"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Santos (2002), 226. </s></p></note></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">The Drafting of the 1951 Convention: origins of burden-sharing</head><p n="p3.20"><s n="s1.7;p3.20">The term 'burden-sharing' was not used in the Convention, or in the drafting process. </s><s n="s2.7;p3.20">Instead, the notion of 'unduly heavy burden' was inserted in the Preamble by the French delegation with the desire to express "the great human importance of the refugee problem," the need to tackle the refugee problem "in a generous spirit", and to emphasize that the problem "could only be solved <hi rend="italic"> on the basis of justice, and not on purely legal considerations.</hi> </s><s n="s3.7;p3.20">"<ref target="BAWE_0360c-ftnote.004"/> Here the French delegation is appealing to justice as part of the resolution to solving the problem and not just legal considerations. </s><s n="s4.7;p3.20">The question that emerges is why are solely legal considerations insufficient to solve the problem? </s><s n="s5.7;p3.20">Could a purely legal resolution to the problem possibly result in an <hi rend="italic">unjust</hi> situation? </s><s n="s6.7;p3.20">Does justice here refer to justice on behalf of the plight of refugees, or justice on behalf of host countries taking in refugees? </s><s n="s7.7;p3.20">How may an ethical policy, if ethics should enter into the framework at all, be constructed in terms of refugee law? </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0360c-ftnote.004"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Weir (1995) 24 (emphasis added). </s></p></note><p n="p4.20"><s n="s1.3;p4.20">The issue of justice with regards to the refugee situation is interesting for a number of reasons, one of them being the fact that one must think of justice not as a bounded concept within a particular community or nation, but of justice on a global or international scale simply because refugee flows inevitably traverse territorial boundaries, particularly in the case of massive displacement where refugees often spill across the borders of several countries.<ref target="BAWE_0360c-ftnote.005"/> Refugee movements are by their very nature forced rather than voluntary, and failure to allow exit or entry may result in severe human rights violations. </s><s n="s2.3;p4.20">Debra Satz's remark that "humanity's claims are international" and that "neither nationality nor state boundaries, as such, have moral standing with respect to questions of justice"<ref target="BAWE_0360c-ftnote.006"/> is particularly salient here because refugees by their very nature contest territorial boundaries, and this comes up directly against the states' jealously guarded sovereignty. </s><s n="s3.3;p4.20">She adds that one of the main challenges facing contemporary cosmopolitanism is the tension between global justice and "territorially based forms of democratic government" and that unless the latter is restrained in certain instances, such as closed border exclusion, people will be left vulnerable to human rights violations.<ref target="BAWE_0360c-ftnote.007"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0360c-ftnote.005"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Sudanese refugees in Egypt, Chad, Uganda, and Ethiopia are but one example in Africa, and others can be found across all continents. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">The resettling of Sudanese refugees from Egypt to Canada, the US, Australia and Finland spreads them out even further from the regional base. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0360c-ftnote.006"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Satz (1999), 67. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0360c-ftnote.007"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid, 82. </s></p></note><p n="p5.20"><s n="s1.3;p5.20">However, as Gregor Noll points out, "migration control is traditionally regarded as...the personal sovereignty of a state" and it is "doubtful whether international law obliges states to share the burdens of reception." </s><ref target="BAWE_0360c-ftnote.008"/><s n="s2.3;p5.20">While massive displacements of people should invite us to think about our responsibilities towards them, what exactly our obligations are is not clear. </s><s n="s3.3;p5.20">As will be shown below, recognition of responsibility was not matched by an explicit commitment detailing what actions needed to be taken to uphold this responsibility. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0360c-ftnote.008"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Noll (2003), 240. </s></p></note><div2><head rend="italic">The debate surrounding 'unduly heavy burdens'</head><p n="p6.20"><s n="s1.3;p6.20">As noted above, the French delegation inserted the paragraph making reference to unduly heavy burdens and was persistent in its effort to retain the paragraph and its reference to burdens.<ref target="BAWE_0360c-ftnote.009"/> The strong concern taken by the French for this issue is explained when they point out that they have already given asylum to half a million refugees during the Spanish civil war<ref target="BAWE_0360c-ftnote.010"/> and therefore they were "obliged to look to the future" since "there was no guarantee that France would not once more be faced with problems of the same magnitude." </s><ref target="BAWE_0360c-ftnote.011"/><s n="s2.3;p6.20">Clearly, France was trying to assess the risk posed by refugees and to counter any possible future risk. </s><s n="s3.3;p6.20">By assuming the responsibility of taking a large number of Spanish refugees, they were naturally concerned that they may be placed in a similar position in the future and sought to "forestall such a danger."<ref target="BAWE_0360c-ftnote.012"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0360c-ftnote.009"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Some delegations such as the US wanted the French suggestion removed, arguing that while cooperation was needed to alleviate the burdens on certain countries, the French text was not appropriate in what was to be a binding resolution, Weir (1995), 26. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0360c-ftnote.010"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.3;pn1.1">It is particularly interesting to note the reference made to refugees fleeing <hi rend="italic">civil war</hi> by a Western nation. </s><s n="s2.3;pn1.1">Chimni (1998, 355-259) explains how a 'myth of difference' has been formulated to distinguish between refugees from the Third World and refugees from Europe immediate post-war period. </s><s n="s3.3;pn1.1">The latter supposedly conformed to the individualist criteria of the 1951 Convention while the former largely do not, justifying non-entrée regimes. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0360c-ftnote.011"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Weir, 9. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0360c-ftnote.012"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid. </s></p></note><p n="p7.20"><s n="s1.3;p7.20">On further probing by the Chilean representative on the legal drafting of the paragraph, the French replied that "the reference in the fourth paragraph of the Preamble to the undue burden placed on certain countries was merely a statement of fact, and was in no way designed to create a legal obligation." </s><ref target="BAWE_0360c-ftnote.013"/><s n="s2.3;p7.20">However the debate regarding the reference to the distribution of refugees around the world continued to raise a certain degree apprehension among various delegations. </s><s n="s3.3;p7.20">The Chinese delegation declared that the Chinese government would not be in a position to fulfill this by accepting refugees from other countries although it had done so in the past<ref target="BAWE_0360c-ftnote.014"/>; the Canadian delegate pointed out that the draft Convention did not contain an article concerning the distribution of refugees whereas this paragraph of the Preamble "amounted to an acceptance of a decision on high policy"<ref target="BAWE_0360c-ftnote.015"/>; and the Belgian delegate concurred with the Canadian. <ref target="BAWE_0360c-ftnote.016"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0360c-ftnote.013"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid, 10. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0360c-ftnote.014"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid, 12. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0360c-ftnote.015"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid, 13. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0360c-ftnote.016"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid. </s></p></note><p n="p8.20"><s n="s1.4;p8.20">Following this exchange, the French delegation noted that it sensed among some delegations an uneasiness at even the "suggestion of involvement" and once again reminded others of the "undue burden" taken by France adding that "all European countries which ran the same risks should be conscious of the need for including such a safety clause in the Convention." </s><ref target="BAWE_0360c-ftnote.017"/><s n="s2.4;p8.20">As the debate ensued, the French delegation persisted further on the matter of dealing with a large influx of refugees particularly with reference to continental countries. </s><s n="s3.4;p8.20">The argument made was that continental countries had no choice when faced with a large number at their borders to grant the right of asylum, or even refugee status. </s><s n="s4.4;p8.20">As a result, applying provisions of the Convention regarding rights to housing and to work would become nearly impossible without international collaboration.<ref target="BAWE_0360c-ftnote.018"/> The Italian delegation proceeded to support the views of the French adding that they "had always felt that the refugee problem was an international, and not a national responsibility."<ref target="BAWE_0360c-ftnote.019"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0360c-ftnote.017"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid, 14. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0360c-ftnote.018"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid, 30. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0360c-ftnote.019"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid, 31. </s></p></note><p n="p9.20"><s n="s1.5;p9.20">The above debate clearly indicates that, as politicians and state representatives, the purpose was not to engage in the suffering of refugees but to formulate the policy that would be the most palatable. </s><s n="s2.5;p9.20">The French delegation may have sought to define the refugee problem in a manner "equitable both to the refugees themselves and to the countries which grant them hospitality,"<ref target="BAWE_0360c-ftnote.020"/> but the hesitation held by states on the burden-sharing paragraph illustrates the boundaries of such hospitality. </s><s n="s3.5;p9.20">Indeed, there was no discussion on how to specifically alleviate an unduly heavy burden, except for the reference to international collaboration, which was not expanded on further. </s><s n="s4.5;p9.20">During the early stages of drafting, an additional statement was included in the paragraph that explained how cooperation was needed "to help to distribute refugees throughout the world,"<ref target="BAWE_0360c-ftnote.021"/> however, this was dropped in later stages. </s><s n="s5.5;p9.20">In addition, a number of conceptual problems were not addressed such as how to quantify burdens and their cost<ref target="BAWE_0360c-ftnote.022"/>, and more importantly, what are the precise responsibilities that burden-sharing entails. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0360c-ftnote.020"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Weir, (1995) 9. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0360c-ftnote.021"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Weir, 7. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0360c-ftnote.022"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Costs can be of a direct nature, such as those related to refugee status determination, subsistence, housing, schooling and health, while indirect costs such as social integration are more difficult to quantify. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">See Thieleman (2003), 227. </s></p></note><p n="p10.20"><s n="s1.3;p10.20">There are no specific legal obligations to either regulate asylum or admit refugees under the 1951 Convention. </s><s n="s2.3;p10.20">Indeed the main principle agreed upon by states is that of <hi rend="italic">non-refoulement</hi>; states cannot send refugees back to a country where they fear persecution, but it does not create specific legal obligations to allow entry into one's territory. </s><s n="s3.3;p10.20">States are still given precedence to decide who can enter, and boundaries are as strong as ever today, particularly in 'Fortress Europe.' </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Burden-sharing: theory and concepts</head><p n="p11.20"><s n="s1.1;p11.20">The commentary on the <hi rend="italic">travaux preparatoires</hi> claims that the principle of burden-sharing proclaimed in the Preamble "has acquired enormous importance in dealing with refugee problems" and that the debate illustrates that international cooperation was intended both in the field of protection and also assistance.<ref target="BAWE_0360c-ftnote.023"/> Indeed, much recent literature has been devoted to the concept of burden-sharing both on the international and regional level, the latter focusing on policies enacted within the European Union, and this section will briefly outline some of the ideas presented and their critiques. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0360c-ftnote.023"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Weir (1995), 34. </s></p></note><p n="p12.20"><s n="s1.5;p12.20">On the international level, the writings of Hathaway/Neve<ref target="BAWE_0360c-ftnote.024"/> and Schuck<ref target="BAWE_0360c-ftnote.025"/> in particular stimulated heated debate. </s><s n="s2.5;p12.20">Hathaway and Neve propose allocating the physical and financial burdens of protecting refugees through 'sub-global associations' of states composed of inner and outer core groups in a kind of insurance scheme. </s><s n="s3.5;p12.20">Inner core states are those specifically, and outer core states are generally not immediately affected by refugee flows and so contribution will largely take the form of fiscal support and the provision of permanent resettlement for a small number of cases who cannot return home. </s><s n="s4.5;p12.20">Refugees will reside largely in their region of origin with respect of their fundamental human rights, and the goal is eventual repatriation once conditions are safe.<ref target="BAWE_0360c-ftnote.026"/> Schuck puts forward a similar scheme of allocating protection and financial burdens through the creation of a market in refugee quotas by a group of states, with each assigned a protection quota. </s><s n="s5.5;p12.20">States could then trade their quotas by paying other participating states to fulfill their obligations. <ref target="BAWE_0360c-ftnote.027"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0360c-ftnote.024"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Hathaway and Neve (1997). </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0360c-ftnote.025"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Schuck (1997). </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0360c-ftnote.026"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Hathaway and Neve (1997). </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0360c-ftnote.027"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Schuck (1997). </s></p></note><p n="p13.20"><s n="s1.3;p13.20">On the regional level on the European Union, Noll<ref target="BAWE_0360c-ftnote.028"/> has developed analytical frameworks based on risk distribution and public goods theory respectively. </s><s n="s2.3;p13.20">Noll approaches the problem by analyzing risk distribution along a game-theoretical approach, focusing initially on two host states that are negotiating the sharing of burden, and then expanding to involve other actors, highlighting how risks are shifted among players in "criss-crossing alliances." </s><ref target="BAWE_0360c-ftnote.029"/><s n="s3.3;p13.20">Noll argues that states adopt four main strategies to externalize costs and risks: shifting costs onto other states through a burden-sharing scheme that presumes agreement on cooperation based on expectation of reciprocity; pushing refugees to other countries, for example, through safe-third country agreements; preventing migration altogether; and significantly reducing asylum seeker's rights on one's territory.<ref target="BAWE_0360c-ftnote.030"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0360c-ftnote.028"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Noll (2003). </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">See also Betts (2003) and Thieleman (2003b). </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0360c-ftnote.029"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Noll (2003), 252. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">Actors other than host states include sub-state entities such as federal states (in the German case), municipalities, political parties, the media, asylum seekers, people smugglers (248; 251). </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0360c-ftnote.030"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid, 240-241. </s></p></note><p n="p14.20"><s n="s1.3;p14.20">One of the main criticisms leveled against Hathaway/Neve and Schuck on the practicality of their schemes is that the transfer payments from North to South are unlikely to materialize once refugees are contained in the South.<ref target="BAWE_0360c-ftnote.031"/> On an ethical level, their proposals have also been criticized for the commodification of refugees, particularly by using the analogy of an insurance scheme thus associated refugee flows "with other forms of insurable risk, such as natural disaster." </s><ref target="BAWE_0360c-ftnote.032"/><s n="s2.3;p14.20">Smith has also argued that out-sourcing obligations to other states would have the added effect of "muffling...these voices that educate us to the persecution in their homelands." </s><ref target="BAWE_0360c-ftnote.033"/><s n="s3.3;p14.20">The criticisms raise some consensus over the moral and ethical issues of such burden-sharing proposals, pointing out how they fail to recognize the humanitarian element that underpins, or at least should underpin, the provision of asylum. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0360c-ftnote.031"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Anker et al (1998), 301. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0360c-ftnote.032"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Anker et al (1998), 306. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">See also Cook (2004), 349. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0360c-ftnote.033"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Smith (2004), 151. </s></p></note></div1><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="bold">Burden-sharing (in)Action: the <hi rend="italic">Tampa</hi> boat crisis</hi><ref target="BAWE_0360c-ftnote.034"/><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0360c-ftnote.034"><p n="pn1.1"> This section will look at the immediate response to the crisis and not its aftermath which is beyond the scope of this essay. The Tampa boat crisis is just one of several high-profile boat crises involving refugees and others include the Vietnamese boat people and the Indo-China exodus of the 1970s and 1980s and the 1994 Haiti.</p></note></head><p n="p15.20"><s n="s1.4;p15.20">The <hi rend="italic">Tampa</hi> boat crisis is a cogent example of an utter failure to shoulder the responsibility of providing asylum and access to one's territory, thereby inducing great suffering. </s><s n="s2.4;p15.20">In August 2001, over 400 mostly Afghan asylum seekers were stranded on the Norwegian freighter <hi rend="italic">Tampa</hi> for over a week after being rescued from a sinking boat; although the <hi rend="italic">Tampa</hi> was headed for Australia's Christmas Island, it was informed by Australian authorities that it would not be allowed to dock there and instructed to disembark in Indonesia instead. </s><s n="s3.4;p15.20">There were reports of illness among refugees, and conditions on the ship were cramped as it was only designed to hold 30 crew.<ref target="BAWE_0360c-ftnote.035"/> Despite coming under great criticism by the UN Secretary-General and the UN High Commissioner for Human Rights, the Australian Prime Minister declared that, "...it is the right thing to do...and it was in Australia's national interest." </s><ref target="BAWE_0360c-ftnote.036"/><s n="s4.4;p15.20">In the end, an agreement was reached for 150 asylum-seekers to have their claims assessed in New Zealand, and the rest in the Pacific Island State of Nauru.<ref target="BAWE_0360c-ftnote.037"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0360c-ftnote.035"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">"Australia defiant in refugee standoff" Fri 31 Aug, 2001, <seg type="URL" n="http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/asia-pacific/1517868.stm"/> </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0360c-ftnote.036"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.3;pn1.1">John Howard, as qtd in "Australia defiant in refugee standoff." </s><s n="s2.3;pn1.1">There were of course political considerations to his decision. </s><s n="s3.3;pn1.1">An election was looming, and the public was largely supportive of the tough stance taken against the <hi rend="italic">Tampa</hi>, particularly coming so soon after September 11th. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0360c-ftnote.037"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">"Breakthrough over Afghan refugees" Sat 1 Sept, 2001, <seg type="URL" n="http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/asia-pacific/1520097.stm"/> </s></p></note><p n="p16.20"><s n="s1.5;p16.20">What went wrong with burden-sharing in the <hi rend="italic">Tampa</hi> case? </s><s n="s2.5;p16.20">Was there a case to be made for Australia's "national interest" to trump humanitarian concerns? </s><s n="s3.5;p16.20">Or did the Australian government fail to even extend the right to hospitality as outlined by Kant's <hi rend="italic">jus cosmopolticum</hi>? </s><s n="s4.5;p16.20">It appears that the Australian government preferred to pursue the strategy of pushing refugees onto others as outlined by Noll. </s><s n="s5.5;p16.20">The Australian government signed Memorandums of Understanding with Papua New Guinea and Nauru in October 2001 and December 2001 respectively to host more asylum seekers intercepted by the Australian Navy.<ref target="BAWE_0360c-ftnote.038"/> Savitri Taylor points out that the unequal relationship between Australia and these two Pacific islands which depend a great deal on financial assistance, played an important part in accepting the role of offshore processing centres for asylum seekers and that both countries were in a weak bargaining position when they accepted Australia's terms.<ref target="BAWE_0360c-ftnote.039"/> The result was the shifting rather than sharing of burdens in a unilateral and unfair manner onto vulnerable neighbours by the Australian government, which exploited "its asymmetric power relationship...to achieve an outcome that was more in its own interests than theirs."<ref target="BAWE_0360c-ftnote.040"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0360c-ftnote.038"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Taylor (2005), 7. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0360c-ftnote.039"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid, 19-31. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0360c-ftnote.040"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid, 32. </s></p></note></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Transnational Conception of Burden-Sharing</head><p n="p17.20"><s n="s1.2;p17.20"><hi rend="italic">Tampa</hi> is just one of many cases where states have failed to honour the spirit of the 1951 Convention and failed to take justice and not simply legal considerations into account when formulating decisions. </s><s n="s2.2;p17.20">Taylor points out that because there was "no clear legal obligation" on states to take the responsibility for these rescuees at sea, Australia "took advantage of this lack of clarity" by insisting that responsibility for them lay elsewhere.<ref target="BAWE_0360c-ftnote.041"/> Without an outright legal obligation to provide asylum it appears almost inevitable, particularly in today's political climate, that states will be concerned with limiting the number of people entering their borders than with the dictates of humanity. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0360c-ftnote.041"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Australia insisted it was either Norway's (Tampa's flag state), or Indonesia's (allegedly the nearest feasible port of disembarkation) decision to make, Taylor (2005), 5. </s></p></note><p n="p18.20"><s n="s1.3;p18.20">In light of the inequity of the current international system that has placed enormous burdens on already vulnerable countries, Santos asks whether burden-sharing should "be conceived on a global scale? </s><s n="s2.3;p18.20">And will this be possible in an interstate system based on state self-centredness?" </s><ref target="BAWE_0360c-ftnote.042"/><s n="s3.3;p18.20">He suggests that "a new and more solidary transnational conception of burden sharing" ought to be implemented, arguing that in the future, environmental catastrophes will be a major cause of displacement, thus exposing "the dark side of capitalist world development and global lifestyles," and making environmental refugees the ideal candidates for this new transnational conception of burden-sharing.<ref target="BAWE_0360c-ftnote.043"/> The obstacles faced in actually implementing such an idea is recognized by Santos who points out that they are unlikely to fall within the competence of the United Nations High Commissioner for Refugees.<ref target="BAWE_0360c-ftnote.044"/> In addition, Noll has noted that most Northern actors prefer regional burden-sharing to a global one because "risks in a regional scheme are <hi rend="italic">a priori</hi> more circumscribed than those in a global one, which increases predictability and facilitates consensus among would-be participants." <ref target="BAWE_0360c-ftnote.045"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0360c-ftnote.042"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Santos, 226. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0360c-ftnote.043"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0360c-ftnote.044"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid. They are also unlikely to fall within the 1951 Convention definition of a refugee. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0360c-ftnote.045"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Noll (2003), 241. </s></p></note><p n="p19.20"><s n="s1.2;p19.20">However, regional schemes also fail to acknowledge that "many of the conflicts leading to mass refugee flows in recent years can themselves be traced either to the legacy of imperialist politics or to its pursuit in the contemporary era," and hence the large number of states in Africa hosting refugees would benefit from a global rather than regional burden-sharing scheme.<ref target="BAWE_0360c-ftnote.046"/> When taking this externalist view of the reasons for displacement, refugees become more than just "necessitous strangers,"<ref target="BAWE_0360c-ftnote.047"/> and it becomes clear that justice obligations are owed to them. </s><s n="s2.2;p19.20">Such a discussion is not entirely different from those raised about global justice and poverty<ref target="BAWE_0360c-ftnote.048"/> or global justice and the sweatshop industry.<ref target="BAWE_0360c-ftnote.049"/> The important point, as Pogge points out, is not just an exposition of the goals and values of global justice but the "question of obligation" and responsibilities owed in the global context where harms are caused by a variety of agents.<ref target="BAWE_0360c-ftnote.050"/> The debate concerning obligation and responsibilities was absent from the travaux preparatoires of the 1951 Convention as shown above, and in the Tampa case, the Australian government neither any obligations nor responsibilities to the stranded asylum seekers. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0360c-ftnote.046"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Chimni (1998, 359-361) gives the example of the refugee outflow following the Rwandan genocide which was portrayed as solely the result of ethnic conflict rather than looking at the disintegration of the economic environment there following the collapse of the international coffee market and the macro-economic reforms imposed by international financial institutions that exacerbated ethnic tensions. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0360c-ftnote.047"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Walzer, as qtd. in Seglow (2005), 320. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0360c-ftnote.048"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Pogge (2001). </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0360c-ftnote.049"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Young (2004). </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0360c-ftnote.050"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Pogge (2001), 2. </s></p></note></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Conclusion</head><p n="p20.20"><s n="s1.2;p20.20">Suhrke has stated that, "in refugee matters, the logic of burden-sharing starts from the premise that helping refugees is a jointly held moral duty and obligation under international law." </s><ref target="BAWE_0360c-ftnote.051"/><s n="s2.2;p20.20">However, the practical realities of burden-sharing have shown that most states, particularly those of the North, would prefer to shift their obligations and responsibilities onto others whenever possible rather than recognize the words of Grahl-Madsen who said that, </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0360c-ftnote.051"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Suhrke (1998), 398. </s></p></note><quote lang="English">The burden of providing for refugees is a burden on the entire human community of which each nation has to take its reasonable share. The principle of non-refoulement is part of a sacred trust, but the principle does not stand alone; it is, indeed, closely connected with the principle of burden sharing between nations.<ref target="BAWE_0360c-ftnote.052"/></quote><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0360c-ftnote.052"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Grahl-Madsen, as qtd in Cook (2004), 346. </s></p></note></div1></body><back><div1 type="bibliography"><head rend="bold">Bibliography</head><p>Anker, D., Fitzpatrick, J. and Shacknove, A. (1998). Crisis and Cure: A Reply to Hathaway/Neve and Schuck. <hi rend="italic">Harvard Human Rights Journal</hi> [online] <hi rend="bold">11</hi>, pp. 295-310. <hi rend="italic">LexisNexis</hi>. (Accessed 25 Nov. 2006).</p><p>"Australia defiant in refugee standoff" <hi rend="italic">BBC Online</hi>, 31 Friday, Aug. 2001, &lt;<seg type="URL" n="http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/asia-pacific/1517868.stm"/>> </p><p>Bailliet, C. (2003). The Tampa Case and its Impact on Burden Sharing at Sea. <hi rend="italic">Human Rights Quarterly</hi> [online] <hi rend="bold">25</hi>(3) pp. 741-774. <hi rend="italic">ProjectMuse.</hi> (Accessed 25 Nov. 2006).</p><p>Baxi, U. (2006). <hi rend="italic">The Future of Human Rights</hi>. Oxford: Oxford University Press. </p><p>Betts, A. (2003). Public Goods Theory and the Provision of Refugee Protection: The Role of the Joint-Product Model in Burden-Sharing Theory. <hi rend="italic">Journal of Refugee Studies</hi>, <hi rend="bold">16</hi>(3), pp. 274-295.</p><p>"Breakthrough over Afghan refugees" BBC Online, 1 Saturday, Sept. 2001, <seg type="URL" n="http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/asia-pacific/1520097.stm"/></p><p>Brilmayer, L. (1999). Realism Revisited: The Moral Priority of Means and Ends in Anarchy. <hi rend="italic">In</hi>: Shapiro, I. and Brilmayer, L., eds. <hi rend="italic">Global Justice</hi>. New York: New York University Press, pp. 192-215.</p><p>Chimni, B. (1998). The Geopolitics of Refugee Studies: a View from the South. <hi rend="italic">Journal of Refugee Studies</hi>, <hi rend="bold">11</hi>(4), pp. 350-374.</p><p>Cook, B. (2004). "Method in its Madness: the Endowment Effect in an Analysis of Refugee Burden-Sharing and a Proposed Refugee Market" 19 <hi rend="italic">Georgetown Immigration Law Journal</hi> [online] pp. 334-360. <hi rend="italic">LexisNexis</hi>. (Accessed 25 Nov. 2006).</p><p>Hathaway, J. and Neve, A. (1997). Making International Refugee Law Relevant Again: A Proposal for Collectivized and Solution-Oriented Protection. <hi rend="italic">Harvard Human Rights Journal</hi> [online] <hi rend="bold">10</hi>, pp. 115-211. <hi rend="italic">LexisNexis</hi>. (Accessed 25 Nov. 2006).</p><p>Noll, G. (2003). Risky Games? A Theoretical Approach to Burden-Sharing in the Asylum Field. <hi rend="italic">Journal of Refugee Studies</hi>, <hi rend="bold">16</hi>(3), pp. 236-252.</p><p>Pogge, T. (2001). Introduction: Global Justice. In: Pogge, T., ed. <hi rend="italic">Global Justice.</hi> Oxford: Blackwell Publishing, pp. 1-5.</p><p>Robinson, V., Andersson, R., and Musterd, S. (2003). <hi rend="italic">Spreading the 'Burden?': A review of policies to disperse asylum seekers and refugees.</hi> Bristol: Policy Press.</p><p>Santos, B. (2002). <hi rend="italic">Toward a New Legal Common Sense: Law, Globalization, and Emancipation</hi>. London: Butterworths LexisNexis.</p><p>Satz, D. (1999). Equality of What among Whom? Thoughts on Cosmopolitanism, Statism, and Nationalism. <hi rend="italic">In</hi>: Shapiro, I. and Brilmayer, L., eds. <hi rend="italic">Global Justice</hi>. New York: New York University Press, pp. 67-85.</p><p>Schuck, P. (1997). "Refugee Burden-Sharing: a Modest Proposal" 22 <hi rend="italic">Yale Journal of International Law</hi> [online] pp. 244-297. <hi rend="italic">LexisNexis</hi>. (Accessed 8 Dec. 2006).</p><p>Smith, R. (2004). Outsourcing Refugee Protection Responsibilities: the Second Life of an Unconscionable Idea. <hi rend="italic">Journal of Transnational Law &amp; Policy</hi> [online] <hi rend="bold">14</hi>(137), pp. 137-154. <hi rend="italic">LexisNexis</hi>. (Accessed 25 Nov. 2006).</p><p>Suhrke, A. (1998). Burden-sharing during Refugee Emergencies: The Logic of Collective versus National Action. <hi rend="italic">Journal of Refugee Studies</hi>, <hi rend="bold">11</hi>(4), pp. 396-415.</p><p>Taylor, S. (2005). The Pacific Solution or a Pacific Nightmare?: the Difference between Burden Shifting and Responsibility Sharing. <hi rend="italic">Asian-Pacific Law &amp; Policy Journal</hi> [online] <hi rend="bold">6</hi>(1). <hi rend="italic">LexisNexis</hi>. (Accessed 25 Nov. 2006).</p><p>Thielemann, E. (2003). Editorial Introduction. <hi rend="italic">Journal of Refugee Studies</hi>, <hi rend="bold">16</hi>(3), pp. 225-235.</p><p>---. Between Interests and Norms: Explaining Burden-Sharing in the European Union. <hi rend="italic">Journal of Refugee Studies</hi>, <hi rend="bold">16</hi>(3), pp. 253-271.</p><p><hi rend="italic">World Refugee Survey</hi> 2005 <seg type="URL" n="http://www.refugees.org/uploadedFiles/Investigate/Publications_&amp;_Archives/WRS_Archives/2005/refugees_and_asylum_seekers_worldwide.pdf"/> </p></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
