<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_0362d" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>This laboratory session was regarding the construction, working and use of pneumatic circuits and its limitations</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">The document has a title page which contains:
document title
title part</note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">comment@0361e
deleted: footer: module name and number, student and page numbers
comment@0361e
Appendix: LABORATORY BRIEFING SHEET </note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">3</p><p n="date">2006-04</p><p n="module title">Technological Science II</p><p n="module code">ES2A7</p><p n="genre family">Essay</p><p n="discipline">Engineering</p><p n="disciplinary group">PS</p><p n="grade">M</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">4290</p><p n="number of s-units">223</p><p n="number of p">79</p><p n="number of tables">4</p><p n="number of figures">18</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">20</p><p n="number of lists">1</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">14</p><p n="abstract present">abstract present</p><p n="average words per s-unit">19.2</p><p n="average s-units per p">2.8</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">f</p><p n="year of birth">1985</p><p n="first language">Gujarati</p><p n="education">OSA</p><p n="course">Meng Electronics</p><p n="student ID">0362</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><titlePart><hi rend="bold">THE UNIVERSITY OF</hi> <hi rend="bold"><name type="university"/> School Of Engineering</hi></titlePart><docTitle><titlePart rend="underlined bold"> PNEUMATICS LABORATORY</titlePart></docTitle><titlePart><hi rend="bold">BY STUDENT ID: <name type="student ID"/></hi><hi rend="bold"> REPORT REFERENCE CODE: [ES2A7A2] AFFLIATION: [YEAR 2 ENGINEERING]</hi><hi rend="bold"> REPORT PERFORMED ON: 27TH April 2006</hi></titlePart></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="abstract"><head rend="bold">Summary</head><p n="p1.79"><s n="s1.3;p1.79">This laboratory session was regarding the construction, working and use of pneumatic circuits and its limitations. </s><s n="s2.3;p1.79">The features of these circuits were studied using "Pneumate" Basic Pneumatic Trainer assembly panel supplied by SMC Pneumatics (UK) Ltd. </s><s n="s3.3;p1.79">The trainer uses air to actuate the pneumatic values as its ease of use and safe. </s></p><p n="p2.79"><s n="s1.3;p2.79">In the exercises performed the behaviour of pneumatic actuators and the working of directional control values, check valves were learned. </s><s n="s2.3;p2.79">By using the theory learned in the course calculations to predict the speed and force of pneumatic actuators were carried out to be 11.31N and the accuracy of the results was discussed considering that in real life nothing is 100% efficient. </s><s n="s3.3;p2.79">The results obtained were almost as required, but some varied due to time delay. </s></p><p n="p3.79"><s n="s1.3;p3.79">Care had to be taken of the type of air used in the circuits. </s><s n="s2.3;p3.79">Compressed air with less moisture and filtered so that no impurities like oil, dust, dirt, etc should be used. </s><s n="s3.3;p3.79">Pneumatic actuators can perform linear and rotary motion very easily and hence have many applications than electrical actuators. </s></p><p n="p4.79"><s n="s1.2;p4.79">Applications of compressed air are limitless, from optician's gentle use of low pressure to measure fluid pressure in the human eyeball, the multiplicity of linear and rotary motions in robotic mechanisms, to high force required for concrete breaking pneumatic drills. </s><s n="s2.2;p4.79">For the exercises carried out, they can also be used for the operation of automatic doors, to press parts into a die, stamper with a parts feeder and ejection mechanism. </s></p></div1><div1 type="front-back-matter"><head rend="underlined bold">Table of Contents</head><p/></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Introduction</head><p n="p5.79"><s n="s1.1;p5.79"><hi rend="sup">(6)'</hi>The main aim of the laboratory and the learning outcome were the following: </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p6.79"><s n="s1.1;p6.79">Understand the basic principles pneumatics, it limitations and potential for practical applications </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p7.79"><s n="s1.1;p7.79">Create, test and understand the pneumatic circuits and its working </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p8.79"><s n="s1.1;p8.79">Compare pneumatic actuation advantages and disadvantages and control to similar mechanical and electrical systems </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p9.79"><s n="s1.1;p9.79">Apply theory studied in course to carry out fluid calculations to predict speed and force of pneumatic actuators. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p10.79"><s n="s1.1;p10.79">Use engineering drafting packages (such as Microsoft Visio) to create pneumatic circuit diagrams' </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Theory</head><p n="p11.79"><s n="s1.8;p11.79">In order to know the experiment better, we need to know the basics of pneumatics. </s><s n="s2.8;p11.79"><hi rend="sup">(1)'</hi>A fluid power system is one that transmits and controls energy through the use of pressurized liquid or gas. </s><s n="s3.8;p11.79">In Pneumatics, this media is air. </s><s n="s4.8;p11.79">This of course comes from the atmosphere and is reduced in volume by compression, thus increasing its pressure.' <hi rend="sup">(2)'</hi>Pneumatic systems operate on the basis of gas being compressed under extremely high pressure and then contained within a special storage tank. </s><s n="s5.8;p11.79">This gas is then made to rapidly expand by being released into a separate chamber. </s><s n="s6.8;p11.79">The chamber is connected to a rod or cylinder that pushes outward when the gas expands, thereby bringing about the energy required to perform specified task'. </s><s n="s7.8;p11.79">The correct use of pneumatic control requires an adequate knowledge of pneumatic components and their function to ensure their integration into an effective working system. </s><s n="s8.8;p11.79">For this experiment we need to know the working of pneumatic actuators (single acting and double acting), directional control and check valves, some basic notations of pneumatic components and their interpretations. </s></p><div2><head rend="bold">Pneumatic Actuators (Single Acting and double acting): </head><p n="p12.79"><s n="s1.5;p12.79">The pneumatic cylinder converts the potential energy stored in the compressed air into linear displacement. </s><s n="s2.5;p12.79">They are typically cylinders hermetically sealed which house a piston that divides the interior into two sections. </s><s n="s3.5;p12.79">By applying compressed air into one or both sections the piston moves. </s><s n="s4.5;p12.79">You can see this happen as the cylinders rod extends out or contracts into the cylinder. </s><s n="s5.5;p12.79">Cylinders are typically round and their internal radius can be deciphered from their part number. </s></p><div3><p n="p13.79"><s n="s1.6;p13.79"><hi rend="bold">Single Acting cylinder:</hi> Single acting cylinders have one input air inlet, producing power stroke in one direction only. </s><s n="s2.6;p13.79">The pressurized air forces the piston rod out and when the air supply is removed, the air inside the cylinder is allowed to escape. </s><s n="s3.6;p13.79">Hence, the piston rod moves back by the force of the spring. </s><s n="s4.6;p13.79">By restricting the exhaust, the speed of the return of the piston rod can be controlled. </s><s n="s5.6;p13.79">Single acting cylinders are used for compressing, marking, ejecting, etc. </s><s n="s6.6;p13.79">Figure 1 shows the main parts of the single acting cylinder. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0362d-pic.001"><head rend="bold italic">Figure 1: Single acting cylinder working </head></figure><p n="p14.79"><s n="s1.1;p14.79">The ISO symbol for single acting cylinder is </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0362d-pic.002"/><p n="p15.79"><s n="s1.1;p15.79">. </s></p></div3><div3><p n="p16.79"><s n="s1.6;p16.79"><hi rend="bold">Double acting cylinder:</hi> Double acting cylinders have two input air inlet, producing extending and retarding power strokes. </s><s n="s2.6;p16.79">The piston rod extends when pressured air is supplied from one inlet and air from the other inlet is allowed to exhaust freely. </s><s n="s3.6;p16.79">When air is supplied to second inlet, the first is allowed to exhaust freely, resulting the retarding of the piston rod. </s><s n="s4.6;p16.79">This type of cylinder gives greater power on the return stroke than the single acting cylinder, and also ensures that the piston is effectively locked in position at both ends of its stroke. </s><s n="s5.6;p16.79">The thrust available during the retardation is reduced because of the less effective piston area. </s><s n="s6.6;p16.79">Figure 2 shows the working of double acting cylinder. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0362d-pic.003"><head rend="bold italic">Figure2: Double acting cylinder working </head></figure><p n="p17.79"><s n="s1.1;p17.79">The ISO symbol for double acting cylinder is </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0362d-pic.004"/><p n="p18.79"><s n="s1.1;p18.79">. </s></p></div3><div3><p n="p19.79"><s n="s1.3;p19.79"><hi rend="bold">Directional Control Valves:</hi> Valves control the switching and routing of the air in a pneumatic system. </s><s n="s2.3;p19.79">And they not only have to control the flow of compressed air, they also have to control the flow of exhaust air to the atmosphere. </s><s n="s3.3;p19.79">There are two main types of valves used in this experiment, the 3/2way directional valve and the 5/2way directional valve. </s></p><p n="p20.79"><s n="s1.1;p20.79">Check valves: One-Way valve that allows pressurized air to enter the pneumatic system but prevents backflow (and low of pressure) into the compressor when it is stopped. </s></p><p n="p21.79"><s n="s1.4;p21.79">3/2 way directional control valves: Here, the number 3 signifies that the valve has three ports, whilst the number 2 signifies that the valve has 2 directions or states. </s><s n="s2.4;p21.79">The output is connected to port 2, the air supply to port 1 and port 3 is allowed to exhaust to atmosphere. </s><s n="s3.4;p21.79">They are used in as a switch in pneumatic circuits, to control cylinders. </s><s n="s4.4;p21.79">Figure 3 shows the diagram for 3/2 directional valve. </s></p><p n="p22.79"><s n="s1.4;p22.79">5/2 way directional control valves: Here, the number 5 signifies that the valve has five ports, whilst the number 2 signifies that the valve has 2 directions or states. </s><s n="s2.4;p22.79">The outputs are connected to 2 and 4, the air supply to port 1, and port 3 and 5 are for exhaust air. </s><s n="s3.4;p22.79">The port 12 is on, pilot line opens flow 1 to 2 and when port 14 is on, pilot line opens flow from 1 to 4. </s><s n="s4.4;p22.79">This valve is normally used to control. </s></p><p n="p23.79"><s n="s1.1;p23.79">More information about the basic of directional valves is provided in the laboratory briefing sheet in Appendix1. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0362d-pic.005"/></div3></div2><div2><head rend="bold">Basic symbols and their interpretation: </head><figure id="BAWE_0362d-pic.006"><head rend="bold italic">Figure5: Pneumatic Symbols and their interpretations </head></figure><p n="p24.79"><s n="s1.1;p24.79">More Symbol and interpretations are in the laboratory-briefing sheet in appendix 1 </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Apparatus and Methods</head><div2><head rend="bold">Apparatus: </head><p n="p25.79"><s n="s1.3;p25.79"><hi rend="sup">(6)'</hi>A compressed air supply for the pneumatic circuit to work. </s><s n="s2.3;p25.79">"Pneumate" basic pneumatic trainer- assembly panel, which was supplied by the SMC pneumatics (UK) Ltd. </s><s n="s3.3;p25.79">This contained the following components: </s></p><list type="bulleted"><item>Filter Regulator with Gauge</item><item>Piping Module with Check valves</item><item>3/2 single air pilot </item><item>2 <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0362d-form.001"/> 5/2 Double air pilot </item><item>2 3/2 Manual Push Button Valves </item><item>3/2 Twist Selector valve</item><item>Pneumatic AND function </item><item>Pneumatic OR function </item><item>3 3/2 Pneumatic cylinder Limit Switches </item><item>2 Block Mounted Pressure Gauges with Check Valves </item><item>2 Double acting cylinders with port mounted flow controls </item><item>1 Single acting cylinders </item></list><p n="p26.79"><s n="s1.1;p26.79">The following Figure6 is of the "Pneumate" showing the main parts used in the experiment. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0362d-pic.007"><head rend="bold italic">Figure6: Showing the Main components used in the experiment </head></figure></div2><div2><head rend="bold">Method: </head><p n="p27.79"><s n="s1.3;p27.79">Before carrying out the exercise, it should be ensured that the compressed air supply was connected to the Filter Regulator (with gauge) OZ1 on the "Pneumatic 200" basic pneumatic board. </s><s n="s2.3;p27.79">The air supply should be adjusted so that the pressure gauge was reading about 1 to 2 bar or 0.1 to 0.2MPa as per the requirement of the exercise. </s><s n="s3.3;p27.79">"Pneumatic 200" was operated on very low air pressure, to ensure health and safety. </s></p><p n="p28.79"><s n="s1.6;p28.79">The output of the Filter regular was connected to the switch OV1 with a short length pipe of approximately 4mm in diameter. </s><s n="s2.6;p28.79">The main use of the OV1 switch was to turn on/off the air supply to the main circuit. </s><s n="s3.6;p28.79">The OV1 was connected to piping module with check valves OZ2. </s><s n="s4.6;p28.79">This connection of compressed air supply, filter regulator, switch OV1 and piping module with check valves OZ2 formed the main supply of all the circuits generated in the lab and all air supply originated from the manifold OZ2. </s><s n="s5.6;p28.79">The pneumatic diagram of main supply is show in figure 7 below. </s><s n="s6.6;p28.79">After the air supply was adjusted properly we started of with the exercise 1. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0362d-pic.008"><head rend="bold italic">Figure7: Main compressed air supply </head></figure><p n="p29.79"><s n="s1.8;p29.79">All the connections in these exercises were made using pipes of diameter 4mm. </s><s n="s2.8;p29.79">All exercises were carried out in order as each exercise facilitated the next. </s><s n="s3.8;p29.79">Before connecting the circuit, switch OV1 was closed and only after all the connections were made and double-checked for any leakage, switch OV1 was on for air supply. </s><s n="s4.8;p29.79">After the air supply was on, the operation of the circuit was checked, and compared to the requirement of that exercise. </s><s n="s5.8;p29.79">If the circuit did not operate according to the requirement, faultfinding was carried out and hence alteration was done, and again the circuit was checked. </s><s n="s6.8;p29.79">Notes of all the changes were made and recorded. </s><s n="s7.8;p29.79">The pneumatic circuit diagram was made after the working of the circuit was as required. </s><s n="s8.8;p29.79">A phase diagram of result was drawn and compared to the phase diagram given for the exercise and the supplied air pressure was also noted. </s></p><div3><head rend="bold">Exercise1: Directional control of a single acting cylinder</head><p n="p30.79"><s n="s1.5;p30.79">This exercise was to control the direction of a single acting cylinder, using 3/2 way valve. </s><s n="s2.5;p30.79">This can be done by using a 3/2 way valve (switch (S1)) connected to a single acting cylinder (2A) as shown in the figure8 below. </s><s n="s3.5;p30.79">As mentioned earlier in theory about the working of 3/2 directional control valve (manual push button valve), here the port 1 was connected to the OZ2 of the main supply, the port 2 was connected to the single acting cylinder A2, and port 3 operated as exhaust. </s><s n="s4.5;p30.79">Here, all the connections were made using pipe of diameter 4mm. </s><s n="s5.5;p30.79">Hence, when switch S1 was pressed the single acting cylinder rod extended and when the button was released the rod retracted. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0362d-pic.009"><head rend="bold italic">Figure8: Pneumatic sketch of Exercise 1</head></figure></div3><div3><head rend="bold">Exercise2: Pneumatic actuation of a door using a double acting cylinder</head><p n="p31.79"><s n="s1.4;p31.79">This exercise was to create a system that represents using a double acting cylinder to open and close a sliding door. </s><s n="s2.4;p31.79">The direction control of a double acting cylinder can be done by using two 3/2 directional control valve. </s><s n="s3.4;p31.79">As shown in figure 9 the double acting cylinder was connected to two 3/2 manual push directional control valves. </s><s n="s4.4;p31.79">Hence, when S1 was pressed the cylinder rod extended and when S2 was pressed the cylinder rod retracted. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0362d-pic.010"><head rend="bold italic">Figure9: Pneumatic sketch of Exercise 2</head></figure></div3><div3><head rend="bold">Exercise 3: Control of a double acting cylinder from two independent locations</head><p n="p32.79"><s n="s1.4;p32.79">Here, when either of the push buttons was pressed or when both pressed at the same time, a double acting cylinder (A1) extended. </s><s n="s2.4;p32.79">But, when both buttons are released the cylinder retracted. </s><s n="s3.4;p32.79">This was done by connecting the two switches S1 and S2 to double acting cylinder A1 as shown in figure10. </s><s n="s4.4;p32.79">Here as shown in the figure10 the output port 2 of both the switches were connected to pneumatic OR gate input and the output of the OR gate was put into port 14 of the 5/2 directional control valve V2. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0362d-pic.011"><head rend="bold italic">Figure10: Pneumatic sketch of Exercise 3</head></figure></div3><div3><head rend="bold">Exercise4: Pneumatic press with safety actuation (with two push buttons)</head><p n="p33.79"><s n="s1.4;p33.79">For this exercise the circuit had to be designed in such a way that, when two push buttons were pressed only than the double acting cylinder extended and when a third push button was pressed only than the double acting cylinder retracted. </s><s n="s2.4;p33.79">Here as shown in the figure11 the output port 2 of both the switches were connected to pneumatic AND gate input and the output of the AND gate was put into port 14 of the 5/2 directional control valve V2. </s><s n="s3.4;p33.79">The output of the switch S3 was connected to port 12 of V2. </s><s n="s4.4;p33.79">When switch S3 was on, it retracted the double acting cylinder A1. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0362d-pic.012"><head rend="bold italic">Figure11: Pneumatic sketch of Exercise 4</head></figure></div3><div3><head rend="bold">Exercise5: Stamper with a parts feeder and ejection mechanism </head><p n="p34.79"><s n="s1.3;p34.79">The circuit was connected as shown in figure. </s><s n="s2.3;p34.79">Here, switch S1 was used to extend cylinder A, and it was fully extended it triggered the switch 1S2 which is connected to cylinder B and thus causing the extending of cylinder B. Switch S2 is connected to cylinder A and B and is used to retract both the cylinders. </s><s n="s3.3;p34.79">Switch S3 is connected to single acting cylinder C, and controls the extending and retracting of it. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0362d-pic.013"><head rend="bold italic">Figure12: Pneumatic sketch of Exercise 5</head></figure></div3></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Observations and Results</head><div2><p n="p35.79"><s n="s1.3;p35.79"><hi rend="bold">Exercise1:</hi> A phase diagram is shown in figure13 below. </s><s n="s2.3;p35.79">Here, the phase diagram shows that when button S1 was pressed the cylinder extended and when the button was released the cylinder retracted to its starting position. </s><s n="s3.3;p35.79">Here when the air supply was 0.1MPa the transfer of output was slow and when the air supply was 0.2MPa the transfer of output was faster. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0362d-pic.014"><head rend="bold italic">Figure13: Phase diagram obtained of Exercise 1</head></figure></div2><div2><p n="p36.79"><s n="s1.4;p36.79"><hi rend="bold">Exercise2:</hi> A phase diagram is shown in figure14 below. </s><s n="s2.4;p36.79">Here, the phase diagram shows that when S1 was pressed the cylinder extended and when S2 was pressed the cylinder retracted and when both pressed together nothing happened. </s><s n="s3.4;p36.79">The air supply pressure was 0.1MPa. </s><s n="s4.4;p36.79">Sometimes even though both switches were pressed together the output still changes, as it is hard to press both together. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0362d-fig.001"><head rend="bold italic">Figure14: Phase diagram obtained of Exercise 2</head></figure></div2><div2><p n="p37.79"><s n="s1.4;p37.79"><hi rend="bold">Exercise3:</hi> The phase diagram obtained is shown in figure 15. </s><s n="s2.4;p37.79">Here the phase diagram shows that when either of the two push buttons were pressed or were simultaneously the cylinder extended and when both buttons were released the cylinder retracted. </s><s n="s3.4;p37.79">The cylinder retracted a bit quicker than when the cylinder extended, this is because the pressure input to retract the cylinder is may be higher(as there can be loses through switches). </s><s n="s4.4;p37.79">The air supply pressure was 0.1MPa. </s></p><p n="p38.79"><s n="s1.3;p38.79">The table 1 represents the truth table for A+ (when the cylinder extends) and table 2 represents the truth table for A-(when the cylinder retracts). </s><s n="s2.3;p38.79">The logic 1 in table 1 represents the cylinder extends and logic 1 in table2 represents the cylinder retracts. </s><s n="s3.3;p38.79">The Boolean logic equations are <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0362d-form.002"/><hi rend="bold"> and </hi><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0362d-form.003"/>. </s></p><p n="p39.79"><s n="s1.1;p39.79">Hence, A+ is an OR function and A- is a NOR function of S1 and S2 </s></p><table id="BAWE_0362d-tab.001"><row><cell/></row></table><table id="BAWE_0362d-tab.002"><row><cell/></row></table><figure id="BAWE_0362d-pic.015"/><figure id="BAWE_0362d-fig.002"><head rend="bold italic">Figure15: Phase diagram obtained of Exercise 3</head></figure></div2><div2><p n="p40.79"><s n="s1.3;p40.79"><hi rend="bold">Exercise4:</hi> The phase diagram obtained is shown in figure 16. </s><s n="s2.3;p40.79">Here, the phase diagram shows that only when both push buttons S1 and S2 are pressed the cylinder extends and when S3 is pressed the cylinder retracts. </s><s n="s3.3;p40.79">The air supply pressure measured was 0.1MPa. </s></p><p n="p41.79"><s n="s1.3;p41.79">The table 2 represents the truth table for A+ (when the cylinder extends) and table 2 represents the truth table for A-(when the cylinder retracts). </s><s n="s2.3;p41.79">The logic 1 in table 1 represents the cylinder extends and logic 1 in table 2 represents the cylinder retracts. </s><s n="s3.3;p41.79">The Boolean logic equations are <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0362d-form.004"/><hi rend="bold"> and </hi><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0362d-form.005"/>. </s></p><p n="p42.79"><s n="s1.1;p42.79">Hence, A+ is an AND function of S1 and S2 and A- is actually represented by S3. </s></p><table id="BAWE_0362d-tab.003"><row><cell/></row></table><table id="BAWE_0362d-tab.004"><row><cell/></row></table><figure id="BAWE_0362d-pic.016"/><figure id="BAWE_0362d-fig.003"><head rend="bold italic">Figure 16: Phase diagram obtained of Exercise 4</head></figure></div2><div2><p n="p43.79"><s n="s1.5;p43.79"><hi rend="bold">Exercise5:</hi> The air supply pressured measured was 0.1MPa. </s><s n="s2.5;p43.79">The phase diagram obtained is shown in figure 16. </s><s n="s3.5;p43.79">Here, it can be shown that when S1 is pressed cylinder A is extended and when it extends fully, a switch 1S2 is triggered which signals for cylinder B to extend causing the stamping action. </s><s n="s4.5;p43.79">Switch S2 caused the retraction of the cylinders. </s><s n="s5.5;p43.79">A third button S3 extended the single acting cylinder C when on and retract when off. </s></p><p n="p44.79"><s n="s1.3;p44.79">Here, the phase diagram obtained was not same as the expected one. </s><s n="s2.3;p44.79">Here, when cylinder A is fully extended it causes cylinder B to extend when cylinder A retracts, cylinder B takes a little time to retract. </s><s n="s3.3;p44.79">This is because switch S3 needs to set off first affecting the retraction of cylinder B. In the phase diagram the dotted line shows, the time delay. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0362d-fig.004"><head rend="bold italic">Figure17: Phase diagram obtained of exercise 5</head></figure></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Analysis and Discussion of Results</head><p n="p45.79"><s n="s1.10;p45.79">All the exercises performed give almost the same result as required. </s><s n="s2.10;p45.79">In exercise 1 it was noticed that when 0.1MPa was used as air supply the transfer of output was slow and when 0.2MPa was used it was fast. </s><s n="s3.10;p45.79">This was because of high pressured air was supplied which have more energy. </s><s n="s4.10;p45.79">In exercise 2 even though sometimes both switches were pressed together the output changed, as it was hard to press them both together at once. </s><s n="s5.10;p45.79">In exercise 3 the Boolean logic equations obtained for A+ and A- were <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0362d-form.006"/><hi rend="bold"> and </hi><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0362d-form.007"/>. </s><s n="s6.10;p45.79">Hence it proved that the OR gate function was performed. </s><s n="s7.10;p45.79">In exercise 4 the Boolean logic equations obtained are <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0362d-form.008"/><hi rend="bold"> and </hi><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0362d-form.009"/>. </s><s n="s8.10;p45.79">In exercise 5, the phase diagram obtained was not same as the expected one. </s><s n="s9.10;p45.79">Here, when cylinder A is fully extended it causes cylinder B to extend when cylinder A retracts, cylinder B takes a little time to retract. </s><s n="s10.10;p45.79">This is because switch S3 needs to set off first affecting the retraction of cylinder B. Overall the exercises performed had very less error. </s></p><p n="p46.79"><s n="s1.2;p46.79">The dimensions of the cylinders used in the experiment were 12mm diameter, 80mm stroke for double acting cylinder, 50mm stroke for single acting cylinder. </s><s n="s2.2;p46.79">Now, the pneumatic cylinder force can be calculated. </s></p><p n="p47.79"><s n="s1.1;p47.79"><hi rend="italic">Here </hi><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0362d-form.010"/> </s></p><p n="p48.79"><s n="s1.1;p48.79"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0362d-form.011"/> </s></p><p n="p49.79"><s n="s1.1;p49.79"><hi rend="italic">As </hi><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0362d-form.012"/> </s></p><p n="p50.79"><s n="s1.1;p50.79"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0362d-form.013"/> </s></p><p n="p51.79"><s rend="italic" n="s1.2;p51.79">Here diameter of both single acting and double acting cylinder are same. </s><s rend="italic" n="s2.2;p51.79">Hence, </s></p><p n="p52.79"><s n="s1.1;p52.79"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0362d-form.014"/> </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0362d-pic.017"><head rend="bold italic">Figure18: Cylinder with reverse stroke</head></figure><p n="p53.79"><s n="s1.2;p53.79"><hi rend="sup">(8)</hi>'But for the reverse stroke of the piston, the available surface area is decreased by the area of the piston rod. </s><s n="s2.2;p53.79">In that case: </s></p><p n="p54.79"><s n="s1.1;p54.79"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0362d-form.015"/> </s></p><p n="p55.79"><s n="s1.2;p55.79">Note this does not account for inefficiencies in the actuator due to friction between the piston and the cylinder wall, the piston rod and the packing gland, etc. </s><s n="s2.2;p55.79">For our purposes, these factors contribute to an approximate 5% loss in efficiency (i.e. the practical force available from the piston is about 95% of the calculated force). </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0362d-pic.018"><head rend="bold italic">Figure 19: Required force </head></figure><p n="p56.79"><s n="s1.3;p56.79">Next, to know how much force is required to move the required object, required force needs to be calculated. </s><s n="s2.3;p56.79">To determine the <hi rend="bold">Required Force</hi>, the mass of the object to be moved, the direction of motion relative to gravity, and the effects of any friction between the object to be moved and whatever is supporting it should be known. </s><s n="s3.3;p56.79">To calculate the required force: </s></p><p n="p57.79"><s n="s1.1;p57.79"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0362d-form.016"/> </s></p><p n="p58.79"><s n="s1.1;p58.79">where G is the mass of the object to be moved, a is the angle of inclination that the mass will move (between - 90 and 90 degrees), and μ is the coefficient of friction between the moving object and any supporting structure or surface (μ may vary between 0.1 and 0.4 for sliding metal-on metal parts, or about 0.005 for iron rolling on iron as in a ball bearing, etc.). </s></p><p n="p59.79"><s n="s1.2;p59.79">The <hi rend="bold">Load Ratio</hi> is the relationship between the force required to move the load and the available force from the actuator. </s><s n="s2.2;p59.79">The load ratio is determined by: </s></p><p n="p60.79"><s n="s1.1;p60.79"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0362d-form.017"/> </s></p><p n="p61.79"><s n="s1.4;p61.79">In theory, the load ratio must be 100% or lower to be able to perform the task. </s><s n="s2.4;p61.79">In practical applications, the load ratio should be 85% or lower. </s><s n="s3.4;p61.79">Also note that if the actuator is able to deliver more force than the minimum needed to move the load, then the excess force delivered by the actuator is used to accelerate the load. </s><s n="s4.4;p61.79">In other words: </s></p><p n="p62.79"><s n="s1.1;p62.79"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0362d-form.018"/> </s></p><p n="p63.79"><s n="s1.1;p63.79"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0362d-form.019"/> </s></p><p n="p64.79"><s n="s1.1;p64.79"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0362d-form.020"/> </s></p><p n="p65.79"><s n="s1.3;p65.79">Speed is difficult to realistically calculate as it is not linear and dependant on the air pressure at the cylinders' ports which all have restrictors. </s><s n="s2.3;p65.79">But the time was known and as we know the distance, average speed could have been calculated. </s><s n="s3.3;p65.79">Also, if the application and other basic data were known, the required force, load ratio can also be calculated. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Recommendations</head><p n="p66.79"><s n="s1.1;p66.79">In order to make significant improvement in future, the following points should be considered to get more accurate result: </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p67.79"><s n="s1.1;p67.79">Students did not have any background knowledge of pneumatics as this was yet to be covered in course; hence time was taken to understand basic pneumatics. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p68.79"><s n="s1.1;p68.79">More proper and modern instruments should have been used which has less fluctuation. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p69.79"><s n="s1.1;p69.79">Students were also not used to the instruments like "Pneumate". </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p70.79"><s n="s1.1;p70.79">Not sufficient data was provided for as to how this exercises help supported in real life. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p71.79"><s n="s1.1;p71.79">More forces acting on the actuator could have been found if some more information about the use of the exercise was mentioned and some more basic data was provided. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p72.79"><s n="s1.1;p72.79">Time for the cylinders to operate was not noted in the laboratory, which could have helped in measuring average speed of the cylinder. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p73.79"><s n="s1.1;p73.79">There could have been air loss in the circuit due to many factors, like improper connection, affecting the result. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p74.79"><s n="s1.1;p74.79">Students make errors and therefore take time in fault finding pneumatic circuits, giving them less time for analysis of results. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p75.79"><s n="s1.1;p75.79">More filtered air, with less moisture should be used. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Conclusions</head><p n="p76.79"><s n="s1.7;p76.79">The experiment in general was knowledgeable. </s><s n="s2.7;p76.79">Pneumatic exercises carried out can be used in real life in many areas. </s><s n="s3.7;p76.79">For example <hi rend="sup">(6)'</hi>exercise 2 can be used to operate an automatic door which can open when switch S1 is pressed and close when switch S2 is pressed. </s><s n="s4.7;p76.79">Exercise 4 where the double acting cylinder extends only when both buttons are pressed can be used to operate machine to press parts into a die (example: sheet metal into car body panels). </s><s n="s5.7;p76.79">Exercise 5 can be used for stamping action, where when cylinder A extends causes the feeding of the stamper and when cylinder A is fully extended cylinder B extends causing the stamping action, and for ejection of the stamper switch S3 is used which causes the cylinder C to extend. </s><s n="s6.7;p76.79">Here, the stamping action can also be stopped by using S2 which causes the retraction of cylinder'. </s><s n="s7.7;p76.79">A and B. Applications of compressed air are limitless, from opticians gentle use of low pressure to measure fluid pressure in the human eye ball, the multiplicity of linear and rotary motions in robotic mechanisms, to high force required for concrete breaking pneumatic drills. </s></p><p n="p77.79"><s n="s1.16;p77.79">Although pneumatic actuators have many applications, there are advantages and disadvantages of using pneumatics instead of electrical actuators. </s><s n="s2.16;p77.79">Pneumatic actuators are relatively inexpensive as there is low installation cost. </s><s n="s3.16;p77.79">They are safer to use than electrical actuators. </s><s n="s4.16;p77.79">As electrical components get heated easily causing further damage. </s><s n="s5.16;p77.79">Pneumatic actuators can perform linear as well as rotary motion easily, hence are suitable for complex robotic designs while electric actuators are all basically rotary motion and complicated mechanisms are needed to convert rotation into other forms of motion. </s><s n="s6.16;p77.79">Pneumatic actuators also have high speed, while electric actuators have poor torque-speed characteristics at low speed. </s><s n="s7.16;p77.79">Pneumatic actuators are also suitable for lab work. </s><s n="s8.16;p77.79">Pneumatic circuits are also very easy for fault finding and can easily be operated unlike electric. </s><s n="s9.16;p77.79">On the contrary, electricity is easily routed to the actuators, as cables are simpler than pipes. </s><s n="s10.16;p77.79">Leakage of pipelines with high air pressure can be of a concern for health and safety. </s><s n="s11.16;p77.79">Electric actuators are fast and give accurate results, while pneumatic actuators have low accuracy and control. </s><s n="s12.16;p77.79">Pneumatic actuators cause noise pollution. </s><s n="s13.16;p77.79">It is difficult to control the speed of the pneumatic actuators compared to electric. </s><s n="s14.16;p77.79">Also electricity is available very easily compared to compressed air in some industries. </s><s n="s15.16;p77.79">For some applications electric actuators are preferred to pneumatic for instance, where there is large distances between actuated valves, in this case electric cabling is often less expensive than installing a compressed air system. </s><s n="s16.16;p77.79">Thus pneumatic actuators and electric actuators have their own advantages and if used together can help in making robotic mechanisms. </s></p><p n="p78.79"><s n="s1.4;p78.79"><hi rend="sup">(6)'</hi>Normally pneumatic valves are actuated by solenoids triggered by electrical signals sent from a microprocessor controller (example programmable logic controller). </s><s n="s2.4;p78.79">The trainer "Pneumate" uses air instead due to ease of use and safety.' </s><s n="s3.4;p78.79">Another application where air can be more desired instead of electrical solenoids is where there is exploitation of flammable items. </s><s n="s4.4;p78.79">As solenoids and other electronic components can heat up or produce spark and can lead to fire. </s></p><p n="p79.79"><s n="s1.13;p79.79">While using pneumatic systems care must be taken of they type of air that is used. </s><s n="s2.13;p79.79"><hi rend="sup">(9)</hi> 'Moisture in compressed air can adversely affect all elements of the air distribution system. </s><s n="s3.13;p79.79">It can cause rusting and scaling in pipelines, producing particles that are deposited in downstream components. </s><s n="s4.13;p79.79">This dirt alone or in combination with water, oil and other contaminants can cause valves to stick, instruments to clog and air-driven tools to malfunction. </s><s n="s5.13;p79.79">Aside from these obvious problems, moisture also reduces the power and efficiency of air motors and tools. </s><s n="s6.13;p79.79">Oil, dust, dirt and water alone or in combination, are the enemies that attack any compressed air system, plugging orifices of sensitive pneumatic instruments, wearing out seals, eroding system components, reducing the efficiency of air-operated tools, damaging finished products and otherwise contributing to product rejects, lost production hours and rising maintenance costs. </s><s n="s7.13;p79.79">Although the best defence against oil and dirt is effective filtration, this fact is often overlooked until problems arise. </s><s n="s8.13;p79.79">The degree of drying required will be determined by an analysis of the applications and environmental conditions. </s><s n="s9.13;p79.79">Various applications require different levels of air purity. </s><s n="s10.13;p79.79">Pneumatic Products work on a -40oC pressure dew point as standard on most of their products this minimizes any water formation in the system. </s><s n="s11.13;p79.79">However some applications require 'super-dry' air at a -70oC pressure dew point or better. </s><s n="s12.13;p79.79">Typically, these are applications were the purity of the air is critical such as in laboratory and pharmaceutical systems, electronics industries, cryogenic applications and chlorine padding. </s><s n="s13.13;p79.79">Pneumatic Products can engineer equipment for even the most demanding of compressed air duties.' </s></p></div1></body><back><div1 type="bibliography"><div2 type="bibliography"><head rend="bold">References</head><p><seg type="URL" n="http://www.poweraire.com/pdfs/smc/basic_pneumatics.pdf"/> Assessed on 21st April 2006 between 9am -10pm </p><p><seg type="URL" n="http://www.iscid.org/encyclopedia/Pneumatics"/> Assessed on 21st April 2006 between 9am- 10pm </p><p>Figure1 from <seg type="URL" n="http://www.transglobal-aerospace.co.uk/Hydraulics/chap4.htm#1001137"/> assessed on 24<hi rend="sup">th</hi> April 2006 between 9am-10pm</p><p>Figure2 from <seg type="URL" n="http://cast.csufresno.edu/agedweb/agmech/graphics/Hydraulics25.gif"/> assessed on 24th April 2006 between 9am -10pm</p><p>Figure5 from <seg type="URL" n="http://www.rosscontrols.com/symbols2.htm"/> assessed on 24th april 2006 between 9am to 10pm </p><p>Taken from briefing sheet of the laboratory provided </p><p>Figure 18 and 19 taken from <seg type="URL" n="http://ranier.hq.nasa.gov/team116/2003/lessons/Lesson7-Pneumatics.pdf"/> assessed on 25th april 2006 between 9am-10pm</p><p><seg type="URL" n="http://ranier.hq.nasa.gov/team116/2003/lessons/Lesson7-Pneumatics.pdf"/> assessed on 25th april 2006 between 9 am -10pm </p><p><seg type="URL" n="http://www.pneumatic-products.co.uk/faq.htm"/> assessed on 24th April 2006 between 9am -10 pm </p></div2><div2 type="bibliography"><head rend="bold">9.0 Bibliography</head><p><seg type="URL" n="http://www.dtonline.org/areas/5/1/6/p.gif"/> </p><p><seg type="URL" n="http://www.freestudy.co.uk/control/t2.pdf"/></p><p><seg type="URL" n="http://www.festo.com/INetDomino/coorp_sites/en/48a62afe5196f1eac1256c5b004ca5da.htm"/></p><p><seg type="URL" n="http://www.plantservices.com/articles/2006/056.html"/></p></div2></div1><div1 type="appendix"><head rend="bold">Appendices</head><p/></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
