<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_0363a" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>The Importance of Spatial Awareness in the Assessment of the JRC</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">The document has a title page which contains:
document title</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">3</p><p n="date">2006-04</p><p n="module title">Project</p><p n="module code">ES327</p><p n="genre family">Case study</p><p n="discipline">Engineering</p><p n="disciplinary group">PS</p><p n="grade">unknown</p><p n="number of authors">unknown</p><p n="number of words">1250</p><p n="number of s-units">57</p><p n="number of p">22</p><p n="number of tables">4</p><p n="number of figures">6</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">0</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">0</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">21.9</p><p n="average s-units per p">2.6</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">m</p><p n="year of birth">1985</p><p n="first language">English</p><p n="education">UKA</p><p n="course">Civil Engineering</p><p n="student ID">0363</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><docTitle><titlePart><name type="student name"/><name type="student ID"/> Design and Project Engineering ES21PA2 Geotechnical Interpretative Report 25/04/05</titlePart></docTitle></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="section"><head>1.0 Introduction</head><p n="p1.22"><s n="s1.3;p1.22">The field work was carried out in March 2005 at Friog Quarry, nearby to Fairbourne in Wales by JE Engineering Ltd. </s><s n="s2.3;p1.22">The investigation was carried out on the understanding that the site is desired to be converted into an area of public access that can be used for leisure activities such as walking, climbing and diving. </s><s n="s3.3;p1.22">The aim of the investigation was to determine whether the area is suitable for such activities in terms of the stability of the quarry faces. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0363a-pic.001"><head> Fig 1 - Surrounding area of the quarry site</head></figure><figure id="BAWE_0363a-pic.002"><head> Fig 2 - Exact location of the quarry, marked on the map as 'Blue Lake.' (Scale 1:25000)</head></figure><div2><head>1.1 Scope of the Report</head><p n="p2.22"><s n="s1.4;p2.22">This report presents the results of fieldwork comprising the dip direction of each of the quarry faces and a discontinuity survey including the dip readings of the cracks and bedding planes found on each face. </s><s n="s2.4;p2.22">The measurements were taken by means of a compass - clinometer. </s><s n="s3.4;p2.22">These readings can be used to determine the stability of the quarry faces and hence whether the site can be used for its suggested purposes. </s><s n="s4.4;p2.22">The results also allow for a risk assessment to be carried out which helps in deciding what safety measures, if any, need to be put into place. </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head>2.0 The Site</head><div2><head>2.1 Location</head><p n="p3.22"><s n="s1.7;p3.22">Friog Quarry is around 1km South-East of Fairbourne. </s><s n="s2.7;p3.22">Access by road is from the A493 towards Fairbourne and then taking a right next a small amount of cottages, where limited car parking can be found. </s><s n="s3.7;p3.22">From this minor road the only way to the site is by means of path that is around 400m along the track. </s><s n="s4.7;p3.22">The path is steep and unstable and is unsuitable for almost all vehicles as it is very rough and the terrain is uneven. </s><s n="s5.7;p3.22">The National Grid Reference is SH620121. </s><s n="s6.7;p3.22">The site is situated approximately 120m above sea level. </s><s n="s7.7;p3.22">The location of the site can be found on figs 1 and 2. </s></p></div2><div2><head>2.2 Description</head><p n="p4.22"><s n="s1.2;p4.22">The road up to the site is very unstable, has many large cracks and has clearly receded over the years. </s><s n="s2.2;p4.22">Due to the abundance of precipitation in the area, the ground conditions are also very unsafe with uneven rocks providing the majority, particularly on entering the quarry through the tunnel. </s></p><p n="p5.22"><s n="s1.2;p5.22">The quarry can be modelled as a rectangle for simplicity, with the four sides, A,B,C and D, bounding a small lake in the centre which is 16 metres deep. </s><s n="s2.2;p5.22">The lake holds hazardous implications as it is very cold all year round and there is only point of exit should someone be in the lake. </s></p><p n="p6.22"><s n="s1.1;p6.22">There are several disused buildings from when the quarry was operational. </s></p><p n="p7.22"><s n="s1.2;p7.22">There are small amounts of vegetation comprising trees and bushes at the top of faces A and C but the majority of the site is covered with scrap slate. </s><s n="s2.2;p7.22">The path is very hazardous at the top of face A as sections at the top have crumbled away due to army training activities and a diversion path has been made away from the edge but this is quite unclear. </s></p><p n="p8.22"><s n="s1.2;p8.22">Face A has a dip direction of 220° from north and a dip of 89° towards the lake. </s><s n="s2.2;p8.22">The face initially appears to be fairly safe with evidence of a limited amount of creep and toppling at the top, also there appears to be some wedge failure in the corner joining faces A and B. </s></p><p n="p9.22"><s n="s1.7;p9.22">Face B seems quite unstable due to the large amounts of scree that are present at the bottom of the face. </s><s n="s2.7;p9.22">From observation it seems as though there are toppling, plane and wedge failures throughout the face. </s><s n="s3.7;p9.22">The face has a dip direction of 310° and a dip of 75°. </s><s n="s4.7;p9.22">Face C shows a little evidence to suggest toppling failure but aside from that seems fairly stable. </s><s n="s5.7;p9.22">There is a dip direction of 20° and a dip of 76°. </s><s n="s6.7;p9.22">Face D shows a very limited amount of evidence that some minor failures are beginning to occur but seems very stable. </s><s n="s7.7;p9.22">The face has a dip direction of 115° and a dip of 78°. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0363a-fig.001"><head>Fig 3 - Simplified diagram of the quarry summarising dip direction and dip</head></figure><figure id="BAWE_0363a-pic.003"><head>Fig 5 - View from below face D</head></figure><figure id="BAWE_0363a-pic.004"><head>Fig 6 - View from on top of face A</head></figure></div2><div2><head>2.3 Ground Water and Geology</head><figure id="BAWE_0363a-pic.005"><head>Fig 6 - Bedrock geology 1:62500</head></figure><table id="BAWE_0363a-tab.001"><head>Legend</head><row><cell/></row></table><figure id="BAWE_0363a-pic.006"><head>Fig 7 - Superficial Deposits 1:62500</head></figure><table id="BAWE_0363a-tab.002"><head>Legend</head><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p10.22"><s n="s1.1;p10.22">From fig 6 and 7 above, obtained from the British Geological survey, it can be seen that the bedrock geology is Upper Cambrian at a depth of 100-300m. </s></p><p n="p11.22"><s n="s1.2;p11.22">The bedrock is covered by deposits consisting of a shallow layer of alluvium to a depth of 1-10m. </s><s n="s2.2;p11.22">The superficial deposits are mudstone. </s></p></div2><div2><head>2.4 Site History</head><p n="p12.22"><s n="s1.1;p12.22">From maps dating back to 1888 it can be seen that the site was used as a slate quarry. </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head>3.0 Ground Investigation</head><p n="p13.22"><s n="s1.2;p13.22">The field work was carried out by JE Engineering Ltd on 15 <hi rend="sup">th</hi> March 2005. </s><s n="s2.2;p13.22">The tests </s></p><p n="p14.22"><s n="s1.1;p14.22">done comprised a discontinuity survey to determine the stability of the rock faces. </s></p><div2><head>3.1 Discontinuity Survey</head><p n="p15.22"><s n="s1.3;p15.22">Discontinuity surveys were carried out on different locations on every face of the quarry. </s><s n="s2.3;p15.22">It was assumed that through these differing locations an overall representation of the discontinuities in the quarry would be obtained. </s><s n="s3.3;p15.22">The booking sheet is included in the appendix. </s></p><table id="BAWE_0363a-tab.003"><head>Table 1 - Possible failures obtained from observation</head><row><cell/></row></table><table id="BAWE_0363a-tab.004"><head>Table 2 - Possible failures obtained stereonets (included in the appendix) </head><row><cell/></row></table></div2><div2><head>3.2 Sampling</head><p n="p16.22"><s n="s1.2;p16.22">Three chalk scan lines, each of 2 metres in length, were drawn in an orthogonal arrangement. </s><s n="s2.2;p16.22">Any discontinuities that crossed these lines were measured. </s></p></div2><div2><head>3.3 Instrumentation</head><p n="p17.22"><s n="s1.1;p17.22">The instrumentation that was used for recording the discontinuities was a compass-clinometer. </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head>4.0 Engineering recommendations </head><p n="p18.22"><s n="s1.4;p18.22">There are several measures that would need to be taken if the site was to be used for its desired purpose. </s><s n="s2.4;p18.22">People must be made aware of the danger that the lake could potentially hold, this could be done by sign posting. </s><s n="s3.4;p18.22">As it would be impractical to install fences around the waters edge it may be a viable option to position life jackets there. </s><s n="s4.4;p18.22">Proper paths need to be installed around the area because the abundance of slate and loose rocks makes the negotiation of the existing walkways very hazardous. </s></p><p n="p19.22"><s n="s1.3;p19.22">This is particularly the case on the route down to the underground mine and it may be necessary to install steps with proper handrails. </s><s n="s2.3;p19.22">At present there is no overflow system in place on the lake and as a consequence water flows through the access tunnel, this would have to be modified. </s><s n="s3.3;p19.22">The access road, as already mentioned, is unsuitable for vehicles at present and work must be carried out to make it safer. </s></p><p n="p20.22"><s n="s1.4;p20.22">It is also imperative that the unstable slopes be made more stable, there are several measures that could be implemented to achieve this. </s><s n="s2.4;p20.22">Mesh could be placed over the rock face as to catch any falling debris. </s><s n="s3.4;p20.22">Retaining structures could be put in place to counter act the forces that are causing the instability, such structures are piles and anchors. </s><s n="s4.4;p20.22">A drainage system could be implemented to reduce the water that is allowed to build up in the cracks which decreases strength. </s></p><p n="p21.22"><s n="s1.1;p21.22">Fences should be erected around the edges of the quarry to stop anyone from falling over the edge. </s></p><p n="p22.22"><s n="s1.2;p22.22">The underground tunnels house many open mine shafts. </s><s n="s2.2;p22.22">These must be fenced off and a lighting system could be used to aid visibility underground. </s></p></div1></body><back/></text></TEI.2>
