<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_0364a" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Materials Selection Report (Part 1)</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">The document has a title page which contains:
document title
title part</note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">deleted: page numbers</note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">Evaluated as candidate compound assignment. Assigned to S1b: collection of reports: compound.</note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">appendices: selection materials</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">2</p><p n="date">2004-11</p><p n="module title">Materials for Mechanical Engineers</p><p n="module code">ES22A</p><p n="genre family">Problem question</p><p n="discipline">Engineering</p><p n="disciplinary group">PS</p><p n="grade">D</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">2174</p><p n="number of s-units">93</p><p n="number of p">49</p><p n="number of tables">0</p><p n="number of figures">0</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">6</p><p n="number of lists">7</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">2</p><p n="abstract present">abstract present</p><p n="average words per s-unit">23.4</p><p n="average s-units per p">1.9</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">compound assignment consisting of 2 parts (see notesStmt for details)</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">f</p><p n="year of birth">1985</p><p n="first language">English</p><p n="education">UKA</p><p n="course">Mechanical Engineering</p><p n="student ID">0364</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><titlePart rend="bold">University of <name type="university"/> School of Engineering</titlePart><docTitle><titlePart><hi rend="bold">Materials for Mechanical Engineers -</hi> <hi rend="bold"> Materials Selection Report (Part 1)</hi></titlePart></docTitle><titlePart rend="bold">by<name type="student ID"/></titlePart><titlePart>Report Reference Code: ES22AA1 Affiliation: Year 2 Engineering Report of laboratories performed on: 8 <hi rend="sup">th</hi> November 2004 15 <hi rend="sup">th</hi> November 2004 22 <hi rend="sup">nd</hi> November 2004</titlePart></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="abstract"><head rend="bold">Summary</head><p n="p1.49"><s rend="bold" n="s1.1;p1.49">Part A - Material selection for fresh-water heat exchanger tubes </s></p><p n="p2.49"><s n="s1.6;p2.49">Within the heat exchanger fluid is pumped through a series of tubes which are immersed in a chamber that has another fluid flowing through it, during which heat passes from one fluid to the other. </s><s n="s2.6;p2.49">Certain material properties, for example, Maximum service temperature and Thermal conductivity will need to be considered in order to select suitable candidate materials for the heat exchanger tubes to be manufactured from. </s><s n="s3.6;p2.49">The Cambridge Engineering selector (CES) provides a short-list of suitable materials that meet the specification and in this instance six materials are selected. </s><s n="s4.6;p2.49">These can be further reduced by the addition of further selection criteria such as price and recycle fraction. </s><s n="s5.6;p2.49">After all the parameters are set, it is found that high conductivity copper provides the most appropriate solution to the problem. </s><s n="s6.6;p2.49">High conductivity copper has a high thermal conductivity, high recycle fraction and is also the cheapest material on the short-list. </s></p><p n="p3.49"><s rend="bold" n="s1.1;p3.49">Part B - Material Selection and processing for a computer case </s></p><p n="p4.49"><s n="s1.6;p4.49">A computer manufacturing firm requires a new portable computer based on a notebook size so that it has an A4 footprint. </s><s n="s2.6;p4.49">The design specification for the product is given and a suitable material and process of manufacture are required to be selected. </s><s n="s3.6;p4.49">The material must have appropriate properties such that it is able to be used for a computer case, it must be durable i.e. have high fracture toughness and high hardness and be light i.e. have low density. </s><s n="s4.6;p4.49">It is found that polymers provide the most appropriate choice of material and this is demonstrated by the fact that all nine of the materials selected are polymer composites. </s><s n="s5.6;p4.49">Processes of manufacture are also required to be selected and a short-list of these is generated. </s><s n="s6.6;p4.49">BMC moulding is found to be ideal as it is a composite forming technique so is suitable to be used with composite polymers, which are the most appropriate material group for this application. </s></p></div1><div1 type="front-back-matter"><head rend="underlined bold">Index</head><p/></div1><div1 type="text"><head rend="bold">Part A - Material selection for fresh-water heat exchanger tubes</head><div2><head rend="bold">Introduction</head><p n="p5.49"><s n="s1.2;p5.49">The Cambridge Engineering Selector (CES) is a windows based computer program that is used to evaluate information for engineering applications. </s><s n="s2.2;p5.49">The program in this instance can be used to select a suitable material for the tubes within a heat exchanger to be manufactured from. </s></p><p n="p6.49"><s n="s1.2;p6.49">Within the heat exchanger fluid is pumped through a series of tubes which are immersed in a chamber that has another fluid flowing through it, during which heat passes from one fluid to the other. </s><s n="s2.2;p6.49">The following material properties will need to be considered in order to select candidate materials for the heat exchanger tubes to be manufactured from. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">Material Properties of Candidate Materials</head><div3><head rend="bold">Thermal conductivity</head><p n="p7.49"><s n="s1.1;p7.49">Thermal conductivity (<hi rend="italic">k</hi>) is measure of the rate at which heat is transferred through a material and is related by equation 1. </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p8.49"><s n="s1.1;p8.49"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0364a-form.001"/> EQUATION 1 <hi rend="sup">1</hi> </s></p><p n="p9.49"><s n="s1.2;p9.49">Where <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0364a-form.002"/> is the heat flux per unit time per unit area, and <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0364a-form.003"/> is the temperature gradient through the material. </s><s n="s2.2;p9.49">There are two mechanisms that thermal energy is transported within solid materials; it is transferred either via free electrons or by lattice vibrations (phonons). </s></p><p n="p10.49"><s n="s1.2;p10.49">In a heat exchanger it is ideal to manufacture the pipes out of a material that has a high thermal conductivity. </s><s n="s2.2;p10.49">This will ensure that the maximum thermal energy is transferred between the two fluids therefore the efficiency of the heat exchanger will be high. </s></p></div3><div3><head rend="bold">Ductility</head><p n="p11.49"><s n="s1.2;p11.49">Ductility is a measure of the amount of plastic deformation that occurs before a material fractures. </s><s n="s2.2;p11.49">The percentage elongation (Equation 2) is an expression of the ductility where <hi rend="italic">lf</hi> is the distance between gauges marks when a tensile stress-strain test has been carried out on a material, and <hi rend="italic">l0</hi> is the original gauge length. </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p12.49"><s n="s1.1;p12.49"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0364a-form.004"/> EQUATION 2 <hi rend="sup">2</hi> </s></p><p n="p13.49"><s n="s1.2;p13.49">Ductility is an important property of the tubes for the heat exchanger. </s><s n="s2.2;p13.49">The material will need to be bent during the manufacturing process and for this reason the material that they are to be made from will need to be ductile enough to deform before it fractures when a stress is applied during manufacture. </s></p></div3><div3><head rend="bold">Maximum service temperature</head><p n="p14.49"><s n="s1.2;p14.49">The heat exchanger will operate at a certain temperature; the material of the tubes will have to be able to withstand at least this temperature. </s><s n="s2.2;p14.49">The material will have to be able to operate at temperatures above the operating temperature of the heat exchange, if the material is unable to operate at these temperatures, then it is unsuitable for this application. </s></p></div3><div3><head rend="bold">Corrosion resistance</head><p n="p15.49"><s n="s1.3;p15.49">Corrosion is the destruction and unintentional attack on a material. </s><s n="s2.3;p15.49">Corrosion causes a weakening in the structure of a material and can eventually lead to the failure of the component. </s><s n="s3.3;p15.49">As the heat exchanger tube will be submersed in fresh water, the material that it is manufactured from cannot corrode in fresh water, for this reason the material will have to have a very good corrosion resistance. </s></p><p n="p16.49"><s n="s1.1;p16.49">From the required properties of the material for the heat exchanger the following specification of the material is generated: </s></p></div3></div2><div2><head rend="bold">Specification of material:</head><list type="bulleted"><item>Maximum service temperature 150°C</item><item>Elongation >20%</item><item>Corrosion resistance to water very good</item><item>Thermal Conductivity as large as possible</item></list><p n="p17.49"/></div2><div2><head rend="bold">Selection of Candidate Materials</head><p n="p18.49"><s n="s1.1;p18.49">Using the CES selector for materials selection, the filters set as shown below: </s></p><list type="simple"><item>Primary selection table: Materials</item><item>Materials filter: Generic</item><item>Process filter: &lt;All Records></item><item>Shape filter: Shape class</item></list><p n="p19.49"><s n="s1.1;p19.49">Firstly the limit states of the materials are set as shown in Appendix 1 (Stage 1). </s></p><p n="p20.49"><s n="s1.1;p20.49">The required elongation of the material is that it should be greater than 20%. </s></p><p n="p21.49"><s n="s1.1;p21.49"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0364a-form.005"/> </s></p><p n="p22.49"><s n="s1.1;p22.49">Therefore the ductility can be calculated, and the material for the tubes should have a ductility of greater than 0.2. </s></p><p n="p23.49"><s n="s1.1;p23.49"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0364a-form.006"/> </s></p><p n="p24.49"><s n="s1.4;p24.49">To identify a shortlist of candidate materials two Ashby diagrams are created. </s><s n="s2.4;p24.49">Firstly ductility is plotted against Maximum service temperature and a selection box is used to limit the suitable materials. </s><s n="s3.4;p24.49">Secondly thermal conductivity is plotted against resistance to fresh water corrosion. </s><s n="s4.4;p24.49">Appendix 1 (Stage 2 and 3) shows the Ashby charts that were generated. </s></p><p n="p25.49"><s n="s1.1;p25.49">The six results that were generated with the highest thermal conductivity that met the other selection criteria are: </s></p><list type="bulleted"><item>Copper/Alumina Composite</item><item>Gold Commercial Purity</item><item>High Conductivity Copper </item><item>Silver Magnesium Alloy</item><item>Silver Nickel Alloy</item><item>Silver Commercial Purity</item></list><p n="p26.49"><s n="s1.2;p26.49">All six of the materials above meet the original specification for the material that the tubes will be manufactured from. </s><s n="s2.2;p26.49">There are though further material characteristics that can be taken into consideration to ensure that the most suitable material is chosen; </s></p><div3><head rend="bold">Price</head><p n="p27.49"><s n="s1.3;p27.49">The price of the material is an important factor to consider. </s><s n="s2.3;p27.49">If the material is too expensive for the particular application then it will be an unsuitable choice, the price (GBP/Kg) should be as low as possible. </s><s n="s3.3;p27.49">The manufacturer will need to be able to sell the heat-exchanger at a competitive price and still make a profit. </s></p></div3><div3><head rend="bold">Recycle Fraction</head><p n="p28.49"><s n="s1.1;p28.49">A high recycle fraction (a value as close to one as possible) means that most of the material can be recycled. </s></p></div3><div3><head rend="bold">Fracture Toughness</head><p n="p29.49"><s n="s1.1;p29.49">For safety reasons it would be beneficial for the tubes to have a high fracture toughness to ensure that the do not fracture while being used in the heat exchanger. </s></p><p n="p30.49"><s n="s1.5;p30.49">Comparing the six original materials that were selected it is apparent that any gold or silver based materials will be far too expensive for this application (Appendix 1 (Stage 5)). </s><s n="s2.5;p30.49">This leaves the two copper based materials to be considered. </s><s n="s3.5;p30.49">The material properties of these High Conductivity Copper and Copper/Alumina Composite are shown in Appendix 2. </s><s n="s4.5;p30.49">An Ashby diagram with Fracture toughness against recycle fraction is constructed to see which of the two materials is most appropriate (Appendix 1 (Stage 4)). </s><s n="s5.5;p30.49">The high conductivity copper has higher recycle fraction and fracture toughness than the Copper/Alumina Composite. </s></p></div3></div2><div2><head rend="bold">Recommendation</head><p n="p31.49"><s n="s1.1;p31.49">From the six materials that meet all the primary specifications the <hi rend="bold">high conductivity copper</hi> would be the most recommended as it has other beneficial properties including high recycle fraction and fracture stiffness and is also the cheapest of the six materials that were selected. </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="text"><head rend="bold">Part B - Material Selection and processing for a computer case</head><div2><head rend="bold">Introduction </head><p n="p32.49"><s n="s1.2;p32.49">A computer manufacturing firm requires a new portable computer based on a notebook size so that it has an A4 footprint. </s><s n="s2.2;p32.49">The design specification for computer case is shown below: </s></p><list type="bulleted"><item>A two piece construction</item><item>(base and lid, both about the same size)</item><item>Outer dimensions 280 x 220 x 20 mm</item><item>Wall thickness not exceeding 2 mm</item><item>Tolerance on larger dimensions ± 0.5 mm</item><item>RMS roughness not to exceed 0.1 µm</item></list></div2><div2><head rend="bold">Selection of Candidate Materials</head><p n="p33.49"><s n="s1.1;p33.49">The computer case will need to be manufactured from a material for which the following properties are the most important: </s></p><div3><head rend="bold">Resistivity</head><p n="p34.49"><s n="s1.3;p34.49">This is a measure of the electrical conductivity of the material. </s><s n="s2.3;p34.49">For the purpose of the computer case it is beneficial to have as high as possible Resistivity. </s><s n="s3.3;p34.49">This means that if a malfunction occurs within the computers' electrical components, the user of the laptop is unlikely to suffer from an electric shock; so for safety reasons Resistivity should be high. </s></p></div3><div3><head rend="bold">Price</head><p n="p35.49"><s n="s1.1;p35.49">As with the manufacture of any product the cost should be kept to a minimum to optimise profits, the price per kilogram for the material should therefore be kept low. </s></p></div3><div3><head rend="bold">Fracture Toughness</head><p n="p36.49"><s n="s1.1;p36.49">Laptops are inevitably going to suffer from being dropped so the material needs to have a high fracture toughness to ensure that the product does not fracture under small forces. </s></p></div3><div3><head rend="bold">Thermal Conductivity</head><p n="p37.49"><s n="s1.3;p37.49">The internal components of the computer will get hot during use, it is therefore necessary to ensure that this heat is not transferred to the surface of the laptop i.e. the keyboard through the case material. </s><s n="s2.3;p37.49">If excessive heat is transferred through the material it could cause injury to the user. </s><s n="s3.3;p37.49">The thermal conductivity of the material needs to be minimal for safety reasons. </s></p></div3><div3><head rend="bold">Hardness</head><p n="p38.49"><s n="s1.1;p38.49">The material that the case is manufactured from will need to be hard, so that damage is not inflicted on the internal components and to the aesthetic appearance of the computer. </s></p></div3><div3><head rend="bold">Density </head><p n="p39.49"><s n="s1.2;p39.49">Within the growing market of laptop sales, weight is an important sales feature. </s><s n="s2.2;p39.49">The material will therefore need to have a low density so that a light-weight portable computer can be designed. </s></p><p n="p40.49"><s n="s1.2;p40.49">Appendix 3 shows the Ashby diagrams that were created to select a suitable material for the computer case. </s><s n="s2.2;p40.49">The following shortlist of materials was generated: </s></p><list type="bulleted"><item>Acrylobutadienestyrene (ABS)- Medium impact</item><item>Polypropylene</item><item>Polypropylene (PP) - 20% CaCO3</item><item>Polypropylene (PP) - 20% Talc</item><item>Polystyrene</item><item>Structural Polymer Foam (SAN)</item><item>Styrene Acrylonitrile (SAN)</item><item>Styrene Acrylonitrile (SAN) - High impact (a)</item><item>Styrene Acrylonitrile (SAN) - High impact (b)</item></list><p n="p41.49"><s n="s1.2;p41.49">Using the CES selector it shows that plastic materials are a common choice for the base and lid to be manufactured from. </s><s n="s2.2;p41.49">The shortlist of materials generated comprises of all polymer composites. </s></p></div3></div2><div2><head rend="bold">Selection of Suitable Method of Manufacture</head><p n="p42.49"><s n="s1.1;p42.49">A suitable method of manufacture of the computer case is identified by setting the process selection within the CES program to the following parameters: </s></p><list type="simple"><item>Primary selection table: Process</item><item>Materials filter: Material Class</item><item>Process filter: Generic</item><item>Shape filter: Shape Class</item></list><p n="p43.49"><s n="s1.1;p43.49">The limit states (Appendix 4) were set to the specification and the following processes were selected: </s></p><list type="bulleted"><item>BMC Moulding </item><item>Cold Press Moulding</item><item>Pultrusion</item><item>RTM</item><item>SMC Moulding</item></list></div2><div2><head rend="bold">Additional Selection Factors</head><div3><head rend="bold">Price</head><p n="p44.49"><s n="s1.2;p44.49">As with the manufacture of any product the cost is also a factor that has to be considered. </s><s n="s2.2;p44.49">The capital and running costs are important as if a process is too expensive then the product will not be economically viable for manufacture. </s></p></div3><div3><head rend="bold">Energy Content</head><p n="p45.49"><s n="s1.3;p45.49">The energy content is the amount of energy that is used in the production of the component. </s><s n="s2.3;p45.49">This value should be minimised as fuel costs are expensive and will reduce the amount of profit associated with the finished product. </s><s n="s3.3;p45.49">For environmental reasons the energy content should also be low, smaller energy content means that less pollution is created in the generation of the energy so less damage is created to the environment. </s></p></div3><div3><head rend="bold">Hole diameter</head><p n="p46.49"><s n="s1.3;p46.49">The computer case is required to have holes in it for example for headphones/microphones to be attached. </s><s n="s2.3;p46.49">A limit stage can be added to take this into account, for example the minimum hole diameter can be set to 10mm. </s><s n="s3.3;p46.49">This then produces one possible manufacturing process which is BMC moulding. </s></p><p n="p47.49"><s n="s1.3;p47.49">BMC moulding is one of the most economical processes for producing high volume, small to medium sized components. </s><s n="s2.3;p47.49">(Appendix 5 highlights the beneficial properties of the process). </s><s n="s3.3;p47.49">BMC moulding meets all the process specification and as it is a composite forming technique it is suitable to be used with composite polymers, which are the most appropriate material group for this application. </s></p><p n="p48.49"><s n="s1.2;p48.49">All of the processes are composite forming so it is possible to cross-reference with the materials to find which material is suitable to be used to manufacture the computer case. </s><s n="s2.2;p48.49">Only Polypropylene (PP) 20% calcium carbonate and Polypropylene (PP) 20% Talc are able to be formed using a composite forming method, so the computer case has to be made from one of these materials. </s></p></div3></div2><div2><head rend="bold">Recommendation</head><p n="p49.49"><s n="s1.1;p49.49">From the options selected through the CES Iit is suggested that the computer case be made from Polypropylene (PP) 20% calcium carbonate manufactured by BMC moulding. </s></p></div2></div1></body><back><div1 type="bibliography"><head rend="bold">References:</head><p>1 - Donald R. Askeland, <hi rend="italic">'The Science and Engineering of Materials'</hi>, 3<hi rend="sup">rd</hi> Edition, Stanley Thrones Ltd, 1996, p 736</p><p>2 - Donald R. Askeland, <hi rend="italic">'The Science and Engineering of Materials'</hi>, 3<hi rend="sup">rd</hi> Edition, StanleyThrones Ltd, 1996, p 148</p></div1><div1 type="appendix"><head rend="bold">Appendices</head><p/></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
