<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_0364h" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Fundamental Finite Element Methods</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">deleted: page numbers</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">3</p><p n="date">2005-05</p><p n="module title">Finite Element Methods</p><p n="module code">ES385</p><p n="genre family">Explanation</p><p n="discipline">Engineering</p><p n="disciplinary group">PS</p><p n="grade">D</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">1276</p><p n="number of s-units">47</p><p n="number of p">16</p><p n="number of tables">1</p><p n="number of figures">2</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">10</p><p n="number of lists">0</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">0</p><p n="abstract present">abstract present</p><p n="average words per s-unit">27.1</p><p n="average s-units per p">2.9</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">f</p><p n="year of birth">1985</p><p n="first language">English</p><p n="education">UKA</p><p n="course">Mechanical Engineering</p><p n="student ID">0364</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><docTitle><titlePart>Project Title: <hi rend="bold">Road Vehicle Drag</hi></titlePart></docTitle><titlePart>Name <hi rend="bold">: <name type="student name"/></hi> Student ID: <name type="student ID"/></titlePart></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="abstract"><head rend="bold">Summary:</head><p n="p1.16"><s n="s1.3;p1.16">An important consideration in the design of road vehicles in the amount of drag that the vehicle experiences. </s><s n="s2.3;p1.16">Reduction in drag is advantageous to achieve good fuel efficiency and speed; streamlined bodies are therefore favourable over buff bodies as they produced less drag. </s><s n="s3.3;p1.16">The Buckingham Pi method can be used to derive the key parameters associated with drag and although estimations of the drag (using known coefficients of drag) for a designed race car can be calculated, prototype scaled modelling or computational fluid dynamics software can also provide useful information on the aerodynamics of the racing car. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Introduction:</head><p n="p2.16"><s n="s1.3;p2.16">The Buckingham Pi method can be used to derive the key parameters associated with drag. </s><s n="s2.3;p2.16">The force <hi rend="italic">F</hi>, on a body immersed in a stream of fluid depends on the characteristic length <hi rend="italic">L</hi>, fluid velocity <hi rend="italic">U</hi>, fluid density ρ and fluid viscosity μ, and are related by the function <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0364h-form.001"/>, where there are five dimensional variables, <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0364h-form.002"/>. </s><s n="s3.3;p2.16">The dimensions for each variable are shown in Table 1. </s></p><table id="BAWE_0364h-tab.001"><head>Table 1: Dimensions of variables according to {MLTΘ }</head><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p3.16"><s n="s1.2;p3.16">The reduction <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0364h-form.003"/> equals the maximum number of variables which do not form a pi group where <hi rend="italic">n</hi> is the number of dimensional groups and <hi rend="italic">k</hi> is the number of pi groups. </s><s n="s2.2;p3.16">In this case; j = 3 as <hi rend="italic">L</hi>, U and ρ do not form pi groups, so <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0364h-form.004"/>. </s></p><p n="p4.16"><s n="s1.1;p4.16">Combining <hi rend="italic">L</hi>, U and ρ with one additional variable, in sequence, the two pi groups </s></p><p n="p5.16"><s n="s1.1;p5.16">can be found: <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0364h-form.005"/><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0364h-form.006"/>. </s></p><p n="p6.16"><s n="s1.1;p6.16">Equating the exponents for length, mass and time the pi groups shown below are found where the dimensionless group Π<hi rend="sub">1</hi> is called the force coefficient, C <hi rend="sub">F</hi> and Π<hi rend="sub">2</hi> forms the dimensionless group the Reynolds number, <hi rend="italic">Re</hi>. </s></p><p n="p7.16"><s n="s1.1;p7.16"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0364h-form.007"/><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0364h-form.008"/> </s></p><p n="p8.16"><s n="s1.1;p8.16">The functional relationship for drag force <hi rend="italic">F</hi>, is therefore given as, <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0364h-form.009"/>. </s></p><p n="p9.16"><s n="s1.5;p9.16">When the boundary layer thickens rapidly the adverse pressure gradient and boundary shear cause a decrease in the momentum of the boundary layer and over a sufficient distance can cause the boundary layer to come to rest, this phenomenon is known as separation [1]. </s><s n="s2.5;p9.16">Downstream the adverse pressure gradient causes backflow near the wall and this produces a wake. </s><s n="s3.5;p9.16">When a body moves through a fluid it will experience a drag force, which is defined by two components; frictional drag and pressure drag. </s><s n="s4.5;p9.16">Frictional drag occurs due to the friction between the fluid and the surface of the body and is responsible for the formation of boundary layers. </s><s n="s5.5;p9.16">Pressure drag is caused by the difference in the high pressure region in front of the stagnation point and the low pressure in the separation region or wake. </s></p><p n="p10.16"><s n="s1.6;p10.16">When the separation in flow over a body can be minimised, the boundary layer remains thin and the reduction in pressure in the wake is low therefore the pressure drag in minimised. </s><s n="s2.6;p10.16">In such circumstances the drag is dominated by frictional drag and the body is streamlined. </s><s n="s3.6;p10.16">The streamlined smooth rounded shapes on the body of a racing car produces low drag, which is beneficial as it will allow for better fuel efficiency and speed. </s><s n="s4.6;p10.16">When the drag is dominated by pressure drag the body is known as a bluff body. </s><s n="s5.6;p10.16">For a given frontal area and velocity, a streamlined body will always have a lower resistance than a buff body [2]. </s><s n="s6.6;p10.16">Buff bodies have higher drag due to the widespread separation due to any sharp corners present on the body. </s></p><p n="p11.16"><s n="s1.3;p11.16">A coach can be considered as a buff body with a rectangular side section. </s><s n="s2.3;p11.16">The aerodynamic drag <hi rend="italic">D</hi>, for a typical coach with dimensions of 15m length, 3.5m height and 3m width travelling at 50mph can be calculated using the following formula, <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0364h-form.010"/>, where <hi rend="italic">CD</hi>, the drag coefficient is defined by the density of air ρ=1.2255kg/m <hi rend="sup">3</hi> [3], velocity of the coach <hi rend="italic">V</hi> and the frontal area of the coach <hi rend="italic">A</hi>. </s><s n="s3.3;p11.16">The coefficient of drag can be estimated based on the frontal area and an estimated value of C <hi rend="sub">D</hi>=1.14 [4] is used so that the drag on the coach can be estimated as 3664N. The power to drive this coach would be 82kW, but assuming that the coach has a rolling resistance of approximately 80kW [5] the power then needed to drive the coach would be 162kW. </s></p><p n="p12.16"><s n="s1.5;p12.16">There is a complex relationship between drag and turbulence. </s><s n="s2.5;p12.16">In a laminar flow separation is caused more readily due to the small amount of momentum brought into the laminar layer. </s><s n="s3.5;p12.16">In a turbulent boundary layer there is a greater momentum transfer so the separation point is further upstream of the stagnation point than in laminar flow. </s><s n="s4.5;p12.16">The wake formed by a laminar boundary flow is greater than that of a turbulent boundary flow, thus the pressure drag is greater. </s><s n="s5.5;p12.16">The drag on a body subjected to a turbulent flow is therefore less than the same body subjected to a laminar flow. </s></p><p n="p13.16"><s n="s1.3;p13.16">There are limited elements that the engineer has control over within car design. </s><s n="s2.3;p13.16">The engineer has control over the aerodynamic shape of the car although the overall size of the car is generally predetermined by the brief, for example, the number of passengers the car is capable of carrying. </s><s n="s3.3;p13.16">The complex economic relationship between aesthetics and aerodynamic drag performance means that an aesthetically pleasing car maybe designed to ensure high sales figures, but this could be at a detrimental effect on the aerodynamic drag performance of the car. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head>Design Solution:</head><p n="p14.16"><s n="s1.1;p14.16">With aerodynamics and passenger accommodation being the most important factors in designing this race car the following design was achieved where the passenger is completely enclosed within the car. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0364h-pic.001"/><p n="p15.16"><s n="s1.3;p15.16">The drag of the racing car in figure 1 can be estimated by considering the car to be made from two ellipsoid shapes with external wheels. </s><s n="s2.3;p15.16">Each ellipsoid shape is estimated to have a coefficient of drag C <hi rend="sub">D</hi>=0.095 [6]. </s><s n="s3.3;p15.16">The total drag of the lower ellipsoid is 131.5N, and an estimation of the upper ellipsoid, taking into account that only 0.4 of the ellipsoid is actually present within the design, has a drag of 29.6N. It is also necessary to consider the drag from the two front wheels, with a C <hi rend="sub">D</hi>=0.3 [4] the drag due to the tyres is 142.2N therefore giving the total drag on the car to be 303.3N. The power required to drive the car at 150mph is a total of the power required to overcome the drag which is estimated to be 20.3kW and the power to overcome rolling resistance (assuming the car weighs 700kg) is 18.7kW, giving the total power required to be approximately 39.0kW. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Conclusions:</head><p n="p16.16"><s n="s1.8;p16.16">Calculations of the drag acting on the racing car designed are only estimates. </s><s n="s2.8;p16.16">Scaled models can be used in prototype road vehicle design and could be used to investigate the drag acting on the race car designed. </s><s n="s3.8;p16.16">Scale models allow visual observations of the flow over the vehicle while water and wind tunnels examine the streamlines and forces that are induced as fluid flows over the model. </s><s n="s4.8;p16.16">Scale models must have geometric, kinematic and dynamic similarity between model and prototype for accurate quantitative data to be obtained. </s><s n="s5.8;p16.16">In practice this is extremely difficult to attain unless at 1:1 scale ratio is used, which is impractical in most modelling situations. </s><s n="s6.8;p16.16">It is necessary to manufacture the model to be tested which can make scaled model testing very expensive. </s><s n="s7.8;p16.16">Computational fluid dynamics (CFD) software could also be used to analysis the aerodynamics of a race car (figure 2) without the need to produce a scaled model; this process can provide more information than from a wind tunnel. </s><s n="s8.8;p16.16">CFD does though require extensive computer processing power and sophisticated software which can both be expensive. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0364h-pic.002"><head>FIGURE 2: Aerodynamics on a F1 Mclaren using CFD Software</head></figure></div1></body><back><div1 type="bibliography"><head rend="bold">References:</head><p>[1] Streeter, Wylie &amp; Bedford, 'Fluid Mechanics', 9<hi rend="sup">th</hi> Edition, McGraw-Hill, 1998, p329</p><p>[2] Princeton University - <seg type="URL" n="http://www.princeton.edu/~asmits/Bicycle_web/blunt.html"/></p><p>[3] White, F. M., 'Fluid Mechanics', 3<hi rend="sup">rd</hi> Edition, McGraw-Hill, 1994, p703</p><p>[4] Interpolated from White, F.M., Fluid Mechanics 3<hi rend="sup">rd</hi> Edition, McGraw-Hill, 1994, P417, Table 7.2</p><p>[5] Estimated from White, F.M., Fluid Mechanics 3<hi rend="sup">rd</hi> Edition, McGraw-Hill, 1994, P421, Table 7.18</p><p>[6] Interpolated from White, F.M., Fluid Mechanics 3<hi rend="sup">rd</hi> Edition, McGraw-Hill, 1994, P419, Table 7.3</p><p>[7] Mclaren Website: <seg type="URL" n="http://www.mclaren.com/features/2004/something-in-the-air.htm"/></p></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
