<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_0364f" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Reynold Plc</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">The document has a title page which contains:
document title
title part</note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">deleted: student and page numbers</note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">appendix: pictures of car</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">3</p><p n="date">2005-05</p><p n="module title">Finance and Accounting</p><p n="module code">ES379</p><p n="genre family">Critique</p><p n="discipline">Engineering</p><p n="disciplinary group">PS</p><p n="grade">D</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">2169</p><p n="number of s-units">95</p><p n="number of p">37</p><p n="number of tables">0</p><p n="number of figures">6</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">1</p><p n="number of lists">0</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">8</p><p n="abstract present">abstract present</p><p n="average words per s-unit">22.8</p><p n="average s-units per p">2.6</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">f</p><p n="year of birth">1985</p><p n="first language">English</p><p n="education">UKA</p><p n="course">Mechanical Engineering</p><p n="student ID">0364</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><titlePart rend="bold">University of <name type="university"/> School of Engineering</titlePart><docTitle><titlePart rend="bold">DESIGN TECHNIQUES AND MANAGEMENT</titlePart></docTitle><titlePart rend="bold">by<name type="student ID"/></titlePart><titlePart>Report Reference Code: ES380A1 Affiliation: Year 3 Engineering</titlePart></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="abstract"><head rend="underlined bold">Summary</head><p n="p1.37"><s n="s1.6;p1.37">Analysis using Computer Aided Design (CAD) is becoming more widely available and utilised within the design process. </s><s n="s2.6;p1.37">Using CAD in the design process can raise several questions regarding the application and benefits of using these tools. </s><s n="s3.6;p1.37">Within Formula One CAD and Computational Fluid Dynamics are used extensively to model various parts of the car, one such part is the rear wing. </s><s n="s4.6;p1.37">The rear wing is a crucial component on a Formula One car and its' design can greatly affect the performance of the car. </s><s n="s5.6;p1.37">The rear wing can be responsible for generating up to one-third of the cars total down force. </s><s n="s6.6;p1.37">CAD can be used to create an optimal rear wing design that complies to the regulations that govern the Championship. </s></p><p n="p2.37"><s n="s1.3;p2.37">Using CAD can provide benefits to the design process but there are also disadvantages. </s><s n="s2.3;p2.37">CAD must be used appropriately by an experienced engineer to be of value within the overall design process. </s><s n="s3.3;p2.37">Training and experience is invaluable for an operator to ensure that the software is optimised and produces relevant information. </s></p></div1><div1 type="front-back-matter"><head rend="underlined bold">Contents</head><p/></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">Introduction</head><p n="p3.37"><s n="s1.3;p3.37">Analysis using Computer Aided Design (CAD) is becoming more widely available and utilised within the design process. </s><s n="s2.3;p3.37">Various analytical methods including finite element analysis, mechanism dynamic simulation and computational fluid dynamics are being integrated into the design process to enable the most appropriate design to be chosen to solve the original design problem. </s><s n="s3.3;p3.37">Using CAD in the design process can raise several questions regarding the application and benefits of using these tools, such as: </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p4.37"><s n="s1.1;p4.37">Are tools such as these really as beneficial as their promoters suggest or will they create an over dependence on the computer in design? </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p5.37"><s n="s1.1;p5.37">Will they enable designers to produce better products or do they inhibit growth and trust in our engineering insight? </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p6.37"><s n="s1.1;p6.37">Do such tools require and facilitate more sophisticated design techniques? </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p7.37"><s n="s1.1;p7.37">How should an enterprise manage a design process awash with high precision analytical data? </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p8.37"><s n="s1.1;p8.37">How much effort should be spent validating results and how is this best performed? </s></p><p n="p9.37"><s n="s1.2;p9.37">To enable the role of CAD in the design process to be considered and assess the advantages and possible pitfalls that could be encountered when using CAD; a design problem will be identified and investigated. </s><s n="s2.2;p9.37">SolidWorks® Education Edition 2005 SP3.1 can be used to model the design problem and COSMOS® 2005 suit used to analyse the problem. </s></p><p n="p10.37"><s n="s1.1;p10.37">COSMOSWorks® is used for stress, strain and displacement analysis by finite element analysis in both parts and assemblies that are created in SolidWorks. </s></p><p n="p11.37"><s n="s1.1;p11.37">COSMOSMotion™ is a virtual prototyping tool that can simulate mechanical operations and any physical forces they generate. </s></p><p n="p12.37"><s n="s1.1;p12.37">COSMOSFloWorks™ is a fluid flow simulator and thermal analysis program that can be used to model liquid and gas flow both external and internal. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">Design Problem</head><p n="p13.37"><s n="s1.2;p13.37">The Fédération Internationale de l'Automobile (FIA) is the governing body of international motor sport and implements regulations in numerous different motor sports series across the world. </s><s n="s2.2;p13.37">The FIA provides both sporting and technical regulations that all competitors within a particular championship must comply to. </s></p><p n="p14.37"><s n="s1.5;p14.37">The Formula One World Championship is one such series that is governed by the FIA. The FIA has sporting and technical regulations that each team, car and driver must comply with in order to compete in each race of the championship. </s><s n="s2.5;p14.37">Failure to comply with these regulations can lead to a variety of penalties from race bans to expulsion from the Championship. </s><s n="s3.5;p14.37">If a team incurs such a penalty it can inflict financial damage due to loss of revenue associated with competing in races and also damage to the reputation of the team which could lead to reduced sponsorship. </s><s n="s4.5;p14.37">It is therefore necessary to make sure that all components on the racing car conform to the technical regulations as set out by the FIA. Appendix 1 shows two of the technical drawings that illustrate technical regulations which are supplied to Formula One teams showing the FIA rules regarding rear wing design, for example, Regulation 3.10.1 states: No part of the car behind the rear wheel centre line may be more than 800mm above the reference plane <hi rend="sup">1</hi>. </s><s n="s5.5;p14.37">The aerodynamic designers therefore need to design a rear wing that complies with these various regulations. </s></p><p n="p15.37"><s n="s1.1;p15.37">Aerodynamic designers are therefore concerned with two main points when designing components for a car: </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p16.37"><s n="s1.1;p16.37">Creating down force - helps 'push' the car onto the road and improves cornering </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p17.37"><s n="s1.1;p17.37">Minimising drag - caused by turbulence and causes the car to slow down </s></p><p n="p18.37"><s n="s1.6;p18.37">The rear wing is a crucial component on a Formula One car and its' design can greatly affect the performance of the car. </s><s n="s2.6;p18.37">The rear wing can be responsible for generating up to one-third of the cars total down force. </s><s n="s3.6;p18.37">Appendix 2, part one, shows illustrations of different designs of rear wings that were used during the 2004-2005 Formula One season. </s><s n="s4.6;p18.37">These illustrate clearly the various measures adopted in rear wing design to optimise the performance of the car. </s><s n="s5.6;p18.37">Gurney flaps can be added to the back of the top wing, and the angle of tilt varied from race to race depending on the amount of down force required for that particular circuit. </s><s n="s6.6;p18.37">Appendix 2, part two, shows close up the latest designs for the rear wing on the McLaren and Renault cars. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">Design Methodology</head><p n="p19.37"><s n="s1.3;p19.37">The rear wing that an F1 team designs for its' car must comply with the FIA regulations but also produce optimal performance when used. </s><s n="s2.3;p19.37">The FIA regulations are therefore the basis on which any design for the rear wing is constructed from. </s><s n="s3.3;p19.37">There are two methods that can be used when designing the rear wing; Computer aided design and manual design techniques. </s></p><div2><head rend="underlined">Manual Design Techniques</head><p n="p20.37"><s n="s1.3;p20.37">Without the aid of computers the design process would consist of drawing the various design options by hand. </s><s n="s2.3;p20.37">Manual calculations would then be performed using fluid dynamics to predict the flow of air over the rear wing. </s><s n="s3.3;p20.37">The lift per unit span each section of the wing can be calculated using the Kutta-Joukowski Theorem: </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p21.37"><s n="s1.1;p21.37"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0364f-form.001"/> Equation 1 <hi rend="sup">2</hi> </s></p><p n="p22.37"><s n="s1.2;p22.37">When the designers believe an appropriate design has been found scale models of the wing can be made and tested. </s><s n="s2.2;p22.37">To analyse the flow of air over the rear wing a scale model can be built and tested in a wind tunnel with a rolling road (figure 1 and 2). </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0364f-pic.001"><head>Figure 1: Renault F1 Team Wind Tunnel <hi rend="sup">3</hi></head></figure><figure id="BAWE_0364f-pic.002"><head>Figure 2: Illustration of a closed circuit Wind Tunnel <hi rend="sup">4</hi></head></figure></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">Computer Aided Design</head><p n="p23.37"><s n="s1.4;p23.37">Nowadays with modern computers it is possible to use them to aid the design process. </s><s n="s2.4;p23.37">A 2D sketch can be created within modelling software, for example, SolidWorks; which can then be used to generate a 3D model of the rear wing. </s><s n="s3.4;p23.37">This 3D model can be used by an analysis suit, for example, COSMOS to analyse the flow of air over the wing. </s><s n="s4.4;p23.37">Once the computational calculations have been completed the program can be used to visualise the results by producing flow trajectories and surface plots. </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">Solving Design Problem</head><p n="p24.37"><s n="s1.3;p24.37">SolidWorks® Education Edition 2005 SP3.1 is used to model the design problem and COSMOS® 2005 suit used to analyse the problem. </s><s n="s2.3;p24.37">A 2D sketch is drawn of each of the components of the rear wing, for example the large and small components of the wing and the end plates. </s><s n="s3.3;p24.37">Two of the sketches are shown in figures 3 and 4. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0364f-pic.003"><head>Figure 3: 2D small wing section sketch</head></figure><figure id="BAWE_0364f-pic.004"><head>Figure 4: 2D end plate sketch</head></figure><p n="p25.37"><s n="s1.2;p25.37">A 3D assembly of the wing is created as shown in figure 5. </s><s n="s2.2;p25.37">Appendix 3, part 1 and 2, contains the 2D engineering drawings showing the dimensions of the rear wing, all dimensions are in millimetres and comply with the FIA regulations. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0364f-pic.005"><head>Figure 5: 3D assembly of rear wing design</head></figure><p n="p26.37"><s n="s1.2;p26.37">The external fluid flow over the individual components and entire rear wing can then be analysed using COSMOSFloWorks. </s><s n="s2.2;p26.37">The only parameter that will vary within this report is the speed of the air flow; all other parameters are set as follows: </s></p><p n="p27.37"><s n="s1.1;p27.37">Fluid: Air, Analysis type: External, Default wall conditions: Adiabatic wall. </s></p><p n="p28.37"><s n="s1.3;p28.37">The two upper wing components were analysed separately with two different air flow speeds. </s><s n="s2.3;p28.37">During a race the speed of the car changes so it is necessary to analyse the fluid flow at different air flow speeds. </s><s n="s3.3;p28.37">The two speeds were 90ms <hi rend="sup">-1</hi>, which corresponds to the maximum speed of the car at 200mph, and 22ms <hi rend="sup">-1</hi> that corresponds to a speed of 50mph. </s></p><p n="p29.37"><s n="s1.4;p29.37">Appendix 3, part 3 and 4, shows the analysis of the two upper wing components. </s><s n="s2.4;p29.37">For both of the components the goals plot shows the convergence towards a solution and the flow trajectory plot visualises the air flow over the component. </s><s n="s3.4;p29.37">These flow trajectories along with the other analysis tools available within COSMOS can be used to create a rear wing that produces the amount of down force required for each circuit. </s><s n="s4.4;p29.37">Using CAD enables a selection of different rear wing configurations to be created with different small and large components that will be specifically designed for use on a particular circuit. </s></p><p n="p30.37"><s n="s1.3;p30.37">To further investigate the air flow over the rear wing the complete rear wing assembly can be analysed, although it is necessary to evaluate each individual component of the rear wing first. </s><s n="s2.3;p30.37">Once an overall design is created that the engineers believe to be optimal, the rear wing design can be added to the model of the entire car and this can analysed. </s><s n="s3.3;p30.37">Figure 6 demonstrates the path lines over an entire F1 car created through computational fluid dynamics. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0364f-pic.006"><head>Figure 6: CFD Path lines around F1 car <hi rend="sup">5</hi></head></figure></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">Management Report</head><p n="p31.37"><s n="s1.2;p31.37">Using CAD in the design process can raise several questions for both the designer and management regarding the application and benefits of using these tools. </s><s n="s2.2;p31.37">Both CAD and manual methods have their respective benefits and disadvantages. </s></p><p n="p32.37"><s n="s1.6;p32.37">CAD allows rapid and cost effective evaluation of a design. </s><s n="s2.6;p32.37">It is possible to test a large number of designs with relatively low cost compared to evaluating a large number of designs by manual techniques. </s><s n="s3.6;p32.37">Using manual techniques can be expensive, for example, using scale models and wind tunnels. </s><s n="s4.6;p32.37">If a small modification is made to the design it may be necessary to construct a new scale model at cost. </s><s n="s5.6;p32.37">Manual techniques are also expensive due to the cost of construction and running costs associated with wind tunnels. </s><s n="s6.6;p32.37">CAD allows small modifications to be made to the design and reduces the cost as no new prototype is needed as with manual techniques. </s></p><p n="p33.37"><s n="s1.3;p33.37">CAD has a relatively low investment compared with manual techniques as the computers and software are the only initial costs compared to manual prototyping techniques and wind tunnels. </s><s n="s2.3;p33.37">There is also hazard reduction when using CAD compared to prototype testing and many CAD promoters suggest that using computer aided design is more durable. </s><s n="s3.3;p33.37">One of the largest benefits of using CAD is the ability to use the software to visualise the results of the analysis easily. </s></p><p n="p34.37"><s n="s1.4;p34.37">Not only is prototyping expensive but it raises scaling problems associated with using models that are smaller than the actual design. </s><s n="s2.4;p34.37">CAD overcomes these problems as it is possible to draw the sketch to the actual size of the component. </s><s n="s3.4;p34.37">Scaling problems arise in prototyping as using models of different sizes affects the Reynold Numbers achieved. </s><s n="s4.4;p34.37">With a different Reynold Number for the prototype this can lead to results of the prototype being different than those that will be achieved when the final component is tested, this can potentially be dangerous as the component could fail and cause injury as the correct prototype results were not obtained. </s></p><p n="p35.37"><s n="s1.4;p35.37">CAD generates more information than other methods of analysis. </s><s n="s2.4;p35.37">This can be both an advantage and disadvantage to the design process as a large amount of data can be harder to analyse, as the operator needs to be able to extract the correct information that will be useful for evaluating the design. </s><s n="s3.4;p35.37">It is necessary that the engineer using the software is skilled enough to evaluate the results but also configure the parameters. </s><s n="s4.4;p35.37">An over dependence of the engineer on the software/computer in configuring the parameters can lead to results having no value within the design problem </s></p><p n="p36.37"><s n="s1.4;p36.37">Once CAD and analysis has been performed on a design it may be necessary to validate the results obtained, this is when manual techniques can provide useful. </s><s n="s2.4;p36.37">Within F1, teams still use wind tunnels to analyse the final design before going into production, to validate the results obtained from their computational fluid dynamic analysis. </s><s n="s3.4;p36.37">F1 teams overcome the scaling problems by using a full size model of the car within the wind tunnel. </s><s n="s4.4;p36.37">This however is expensive, so for other products it might not be feasible to test at full scale. </s></p><p n="p37.37"><s n="s1.3;p37.37">CAD must be used appropriately by an experienced engineer to be of value within the overall design process. </s><s n="s2.3;p37.37">Training and experience is invaluable for an operator to ensure that the software is optimised and produces relevant information. </s><s n="s3.3;p37.37">I believe that CAD can be used to produce better products but designers and engineers must still use their knowledge and insight and not become over dependent on the software. </s></p></div1></body><back><div1 type="bibliography"><head rend="underlined bold">References</head><p>1 - Fédération Internationale de l'Automobile website</p><p> <seg type="URL" n="http://www.fia.com"/> (as accessed 17/01/2006)</p><p> Formula One 2006 Technical Regulations</p><p>2 - ES252 Fluid Mechanics: Lecture 13</p><p> Lecture notes available from P.J. Thomas website (as accessed 23/01/2006)</p><p> <seg type="URL" n="http://www.eng"/>.<name type="university"/>.ac.uk/staff/pjt/teachdocs.html </p><p>3 - Renault F1 Team Wind Tunnel </p><p> Available at 3D Systems website (as accessed 23/01/2006)</p><p><seg type="URL" n="http://www.3dsystems.com/newsevents/newsreleases/pr-Feb_24_2003.asp"/> </p><p>4- Illustration of Wind Tunnel</p><p> Available at F1 Technical website (as accessed 23/02/2006)</p><p> <seg type="URL" n="http://www.f1technical.net/articles/47"/> </p><p>5- Diagram of Path lines around F1 car</p><p> Available at Fluent website (as accessed 17/01/2006)</p><p><seg type="URL" n="http://www.fluent.com/solutions/automotive/ex166_formula_1_external_aerodynamics.pdf"/> </p></div1><div1 type="appendix"><head rend="underlined bold">APPENDIX </head><p/></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
