<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_0377c" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Evaluate the EC treatment of the anti-competitive effects of conglomerate mergers. You should include in your discussion the ECJ decision in EC v Tetra Laval Case C-12/03 P (2005).</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">deleted: page numbers</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">3</p><p n="date">2007-04</p><p n="module title">Advanced Themes in Competition Law &amp; Policy</p><p n="module code">LA238</p><p n="genre family">Essay</p><p n="discipline">Law</p><p n="disciplinary group">SS</p><p n="grade">M</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">2488</p><p n="number of s-units">78</p><p n="number of p">21</p><p n="number of tables">0</p><p n="number of figures">0</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">0</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">0</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">31.9</p><p n="average s-units per p">3.7</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">f</p><p n="year of birth">1983</p><p n="first language">Polish</p><p n="education">OSA</p><p n="course">Law</p><p n="student ID">0377</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><docTitle><titlePart><hi rend="bold italic">Topic: Evaluate the EC treatment of the anti-competitive effects of conglomerate mergers. You should include in your discussion the ECJ decision in</hi><hi rend="underlined"> EC v Tetra Laval <hi rend="italic"> Case C-12/03 P (2005).</hi> </hi></titlePart></docTitle></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold italic">Introduction</head><p n="p1.21"><s n="s1.4;p1.21">The beginning and the phenomenon of conglomerate mergers had occurred in United States in late 1960'. </s><s n="s2.4;p1.21">A company made of few unrelated businesses running independently - but with one supervisory board- seems to be great idea to spread the financial risk.<ref target="BAWE_0377c-ftnote.001"/> It is an additional question what convince companies to merge in general. </s><s n="s3.4;p1.21">Above reducing risk exposure, some of them want to synergy or to increase market share, cross selling or diversify their risk. </s><s n="s4.4;p1.21">However, as the phrase of late 1960s has shown, in too large conglomerates financial problems and serious difficulties with their management occur quite often. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0377c-ftnote.001"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">In other words when a company was involved in jewellery market and milk cartons production; in case of recession, the company would not potentially suffer from financial problems- foreseeable- when the amount of sold jewellery possibly decreases - the sale of milk would not change. </s></p></note><p n="p2.21"><s n="s1.4;p2.21">How does it work in European Community? </s><s n="s2.4;p2.21">To evaluate the EC treatment of the anti- competitive effect of conglomerate mergers, it is reasonable to define the merger under EC law and to go trough the main regulation on this subject, to understand more complex issues. </s><s n="s3.4;p2.21">The second step will be to characterize the conglomerate merger treatment under EC law- how does it work in general, in what circumstances such a concentration can be profitable or abusive, and moreover what possible effects it may cause. </s><s n="s4.4;p2.21">The main discussion in this essay will regard the anti- competitive effect of conglomerate mergers in reasoning and explanations of the European authorities: The European Commission, Court of First Instance and especially European Court of Justice<ref target="BAWE_0377c-ftnote.002"/> while considering cases, to show how the treatment of conglomerate merger was evolving; also in academic debate. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0377c-ftnote.002"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">I will use in my essay the popular abbreviation- "ECJ" </s></p></note><p n="p3.21"><s n="s1.6;p3.21">The European Council Merger Regulation<ref target="BAWE_0377c-ftnote.003"/> defines what constitute a merger and (art. </s><s n="s2.6;p3.21">3 of ECMR) describe the substantive criteria of a concentration (art. </s><s n="s3.6;p3.21">2)<ref target="BAWE_0377c-ftnote.004"/>. </s><s n="s4.6;p3.21">Conglomerate merger may be characterized as a fusion between two entities having no current or potential competitive relationship. </s><s n="s5.6;p3.21">It is possible to distinguish conglomerate mergers between producers of complimentary, neighbouring and unrelated products. </s><ref target="BAWE_0377c-ftnote.005"/><s n="s6.6;p3.21">Because of the fact, that the Commission is considering conglomerate mergers quite rarely, usually its reasoning refer to so called "pure" conglomerate, involving entirely independent products.<ref target="BAWE_0377c-ftnote.006"/> Even though conglomerate mergers do not produce anti- competitive effect in a form such as an increase of market share (like horizontal merger effect does) or the possibility to foreclose rivals on up stream or down stream market (vertical merger effect) they can possibly give rise to competitive harm. <ref target="BAWE_0377c-ftnote.007"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0377c-ftnote.003"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">EC Merger Regulation No.139/2004 of 20 January 2004 on the control of concentration between undertakings (so called EC Merger Regulation). </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0377c-ftnote.004"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">However, it might be defined differently, for example in UK, the Enterprise Act 2002 applies to "relevant merger situations"; Jones &amp; Sufrin, page 847 and M. Furse, "<hi rend="italic">Competition Law of the EC and UK</hi>", 4-th edition 2004; Oxford Univ. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">Press </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0377c-ftnote.005"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">It is well observed in a conduct of European authorities that, usually, when controlled merger can not by classify as a horizontal or vertical, because such an overlaps are minimal the conglomerate theories of harm tend to be pursued.; based on : Jeffrey Church, "The Impact of Vertical and Conglomerate Mergers on Competition"; Final Report; page 233 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0377c-ftnote.006"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">F. Dethmers, N. Dodoo and A. Morfey; "Conglomerate mergers under EC merger control: an overview"; European Competition Journal; October 2005, vol.1; page 266 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0377c-ftnote.007"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">In fact, there is a need to possess plausible prediction of the behaviour of merged company, rivals and consumers reaction. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">All that assumptions are based in long term effect of a merger, thus there will never be 100% sureness that firstly- it would occur and secondly - that it will cause harm to competitive structure of the market. </s></p></note><p n="p4.21"><s n="s1.3;p4.21">From the economic perspective conglomerate mergers are considered as resulting bundling or tying usually in the context of art. </s><s n="s2.3;p4.21">82 EC Treaty.<ref target="BAWE_0377c-ftnote.008"/> From this point of view there are two conglomerate theories of harm, those arising as a result of strategic behaviour such as leveraging and the latter -resulted by non- strategic behaviour. </s><s n="s3.3;p4.21">Whether it is possible to distinguish them in theory, in practice it is much more difficult, if not impossible to detect, because it is based only on future predictions of potential competitive harm. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0377c-ftnote.008"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Therefore, illegality can be use as a defense against leverage expressed in a form of bundling, tying or predatory pricing- practices infringing the art. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">82 of the EC Treaty. </s></p></note><p n="p5.21"><s n="s1.5;p5.21">CFI while considering the Tetra Laval case showed that conglomerate mergers can also create so called "structural" effect ,when arises directly from the established economic structure or latter- "behavioural" which occurs only if a new entity would engage in particular commercial practices i.e. price discrimination or predatory pricing. </s><s n="s2.5;p5.21">The current or potential advantage from conglomerate merger may be use to eliminate competitors from the market.<ref target="BAWE_0377c-ftnote.009"/> As it will be shown it is very complex and difficult task for EC authorities to collect sufficient evidences proving the anti- competitive intention of mergering entities. </s><s n="s3.5;p5.21">In other words, it is not enough to foresee likelihood of leveraging but "cogent" evidence is needed.<ref target="BAWE_0377c-ftnote.010"/> Therefore it is reasonable to familiarize with the criticism of the Commission analyzes while prohibiting conglomerate mergers in Tetra Laval/ Sidel or GE/ Honeywell cases. </s><s n="s4.5;p5.21">What anti- competitive effect can the conglomerate potentially cause? </s><s n="s5.5;p5.21">The Commission is concerned with mainly two- the portfolio effect, discussed in complex way in the case Guinness/ Grand Metropolitan<ref target="BAWE_0377c-ftnote.011"/> and leveraging- using power from one market to neighbouring one- trough price discrimination, product bundling and predatory pricing- discussed broadly in Tetra Laval/Sidel case.<ref target="BAWE_0377c-ftnote.012"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0377c-ftnote.009"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.3;pn1.1">There can be made a conceptual distinction between the foreclosure of existing and future products in conglomerate strategy. </s><s n="s2.3;pn1.1">The former is determined by the impact on rivals' current sales, latter trough marginalization and reduction of rival's sales. </s><s n="s3.3;pn1.1">Based on: supra note 3, page 277. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0377c-ftnote.010"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1"><hi rend="italic">"Conglomerate mergers under EC merger control: an overview",</hi> supra note 5, page 267 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0377c-ftnote.011"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Guinness Grand Metropolitan [1998] OJ L228/24 par. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">40-41 ; </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0377c-ftnote.012"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Tetra Laval case was the first conglomerate merger issue decided by CFI; Tetra Laval v. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">Commission case T- 5/02, [2002] ECR II- 4381 [2002] 5 CMRL 1182, para 153 </s></p></note><p n="p6.21"><s n="s1.1;p6.21">The main approach of the anti- competitive effect of conglomerate merger may be divided into two periods- after the prohibition in GE/Honeywell but before the Tetra Laval/Sidel case- and after it. </s></p><p n="p7.21"><s n="s1.4;p7.21">The pre- Tetra Laval/Sidel approach was presuming that, if it is possible to find pre- merger dominance and existence of conglomerate links, which as a consequence gives the ability to "pursue" strategic behaviour. </s><s n="s2.4;p7.21">Thus, it was enough to state, that a company is involved in anti competitive behaviour. </s><s n="s3.4;p7.21">Owning to this, as discussed in F. Dethmers, N. Dodoo and A. Morfey<ref target="BAWE_0377c-ftnote.013"/> publication, above concerns are only reasonable if commercial either technical link exists, otherwise there would be no place for a conglomerate theory of harm. </s><s n="s4.4;p7.21">This approach was broadly criticised, because have established the threshold intervention on very low level<ref target="BAWE_0377c-ftnote.014"/>, moreover have left a limited number of protective remedies for entities proving inability to act anti- competitively i.e. to technically tie two products together and as a consequence, can not sell them "only" as a bundle.<ref target="BAWE_0377c-ftnote.015"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0377c-ftnote.013"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Supra note 5, para 197 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0377c-ftnote.014"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Supra note 17, para 196 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0377c-ftnote.015"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Found in : GE/Amersham case M.3304, Commission's decision of 21 January, 2004 </s></p></note><p n="p8.21"><s n="s1.1;p8.21">In fact, as ECJ stated<ref target="BAWE_0377c-ftnote.016"/> in Tetra Laval/Sidel case "merger control must be carried out with great care, since it does not entail the examination of past events - for which often many items of evidence are available which make it possible to understand the causes - or of current events, but rather a prediction of events which are more or less likely to occur in future".<ref target="BAWE_0377c-ftnote.017"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0377c-ftnote.016"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">It was extremely difficult for the court to find a reasonable solution, with no former precedence, moreover because no guideline on conglomerates is still available. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">From years the debate concerning the conglomerate merger guideline is not ended, more on this subject and whole discussion which suppose to be closed at the end of may 2007 may be found on : <seg type="URL" n="http://europa.eu/rapid/pressReleasesAction.do?reference=IP/07/178&amp;format=HTML&amp;aged=0&amp;language=EN&amp;guiLanguage=en"/> </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0377c-ftnote.017"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.4;pn1.1">Commission v. </s><s n="s2.4;pn1.1">Tetra Laval Case C-12/03 P [2003] 4 CMLR 768 (ECJ, 15-th Feb. </s><s n="s3.4;pn1.1">2005) para. </s><s n="s4.4;pn1.1">43 </s></p></note></div1><div1 type="section"><head>"<hi rend="underlined bold italic">The anti-competitive effects and the EC treatment ". </hi></head><p n="p9.21"><s n="s1.3;p9.21">So called "Portfolio effect" may be created if a company possesses a wide range of "similar" products, not exactly on this same market and because of this fact more willingly, with greater financial flexibility can set promotions and discounts. </s><s n="s2.3;p9.21">Consequently tying or threat of a refusal to supply is more likely to occur. </s><s n="s3.3;p9.21">However, it would usually depend on different factors, i.e. how many brand leaders the holder of a portfolio possesses etc.<ref target="BAWE_0377c-ftnote.018"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0377c-ftnote.018"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">supra note 11, para 41, Westlaw; additionally it should be mention, that the Commission's decision in Guinness case was criticised not because of the adoption of portfolio effect, but because it did not stated without any doubts, what was illegal in entities acquisition of a "wider portfolio of products". </s></p></note><p n="p10.21"><s n="s1.2;p10.21">Leveraging in the context of conglomerate mergers control occurs when a company with a strong pre- existing position at one market, acquires an entity performing on related or neighbouring market.<ref target="BAWE_0377c-ftnote.019"/> Additionally this practice may be described as "by which a company extends its market power existing in one market to another market where it did not have this power previously<ref target="BAWE_0377c-ftnote.020"/>".Thus, it is crucial to proof, that there is some chain of cause in examined entity's conduct. </s><s n="s2.2;p10.21">However it is highly complex and complicated to show this dependence (because) the chains of cause and effect are dimly discernible, uncertain, and difficult to establish."<ref target="BAWE_0377c-ftnote.021"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0377c-ftnote.019"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.4;pn1.1">Leveraging is connected to an increase of market power but not in the way of combining existing pre-merger market powers, but trough shifting the market power "by means of a number of conceivable leveraging practices"; based on: Sven B Volcker; "Leveraging as a theory of competitive harm in EU merger control", Common Market Law Review. </s><s n="s2.4;pn1.1">New York: June 2003.Vol.40, Iss. </s><s n="s3.4;pn1.1">3; pg. </s><s n="s4.4;pn1.1">581, </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0377c-ftnote.020"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">ibid ,para 2.1 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0377c-ftnote.021"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.3;pn1.1">Commission v. </s><s n="s2.3;pn1.1">Tetra Laval, supra note 17, para. </s><s n="s3.3;pn1.1">44 </s></p></note><p n="p11.21"><s n="s1.2;p11.21">The desired standard of proof of leveraging was broadly debated in Tetra Laval/Sidel case<ref target="BAWE_0377c-ftnote.022"/>. </s><s n="s2.2;p11.21">The Commission's conduct was based on the problem if particular entity will be likely to create dominant position, when the CFI reasoning in para 153 of its judgment required the proof of dominance in "all likelihood... in relatively near future.<ref target="BAWE_0377c-ftnote.023"/>" While proceeding in the Court of First Instance, the Commission was arguing that inconsistent with "double symmetrical obligation"<ref target="BAWE_0377c-ftnote.024"/>- standard of proof amounts to presumption of legality.<ref target="BAWE_0377c-ftnote.025"/> While debating about the required standard of proof the ECJ stated that, because this type of merger has a prospective effect the quality of the evidence is very important<ref target="BAWE_0377c-ftnote.026"/>, thus the Commission needs to show that " if particular decision would not have been taken, the economic development envisaged by it would be plausible". <ref target="BAWE_0377c-ftnote.027"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0377c-ftnote.022"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Additionally it was highly unclear if the Commission possesses competence to decide or include in its reasoning theories like leveraging, when EMCR do not contain any specific provisions. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">What is more, there was no clear answer if such theories can and should be used under the ECMR in general, for instance as a law and policy matter? </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0377c-ftnote.023"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Tetra Laval v. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">Commission case T- 5/02, [2002] ECR II- 4381 [2002] 5 CMRL 1182, para 153 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0377c-ftnote.024"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Sven B Völcker and Pablo Charro;"Tetra Laval - a landmark judgment on EC merger control" published in the 8 March 2004 issue of Competition Law Insight </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0377c-ftnote.025"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.4;pn1.1">Tetra Laval v. </s><s n="s2.4;pn1.1">Commission, supra note 17 in Sven B Volcker; "Leveraging as a theory of competitive harm in EU merger control", This reasoning was not supported by Attorney General's opinion, who stated that there is no need of "double symmetrical obligation" but the transaction must very probably "lead to dominance". </s><s n="s3.4;pn1.1">2003.Vol.40, Iss. </s><s n="s4.4;pn1.1">3 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0377c-ftnote.026"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">ECJ also find it reasonable and correct conduct of CFI to rely upon a test applied in Kali&amp; Salz case, and consequently set similar requirements to those with regard to creation of collective dominance. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0377c-ftnote.027"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Commission v. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">Tetra Laval case, supra note 17, para 44 </s></p></note><p n="p12.21"><s n="s1.3;p12.21">The Court was also debating about the standards of an economic assessment. </s><s n="s2.3;p12.21">The Court of First Instance in Tetra Laval/ Sidel case claimed that conglomerate merger examination calls for "particularly close" and "precise" analyzes supported by convincing evidence<ref target="BAWE_0377c-ftnote.028"/>, while The Commission stated that it is a shift from Kali Salz<ref target="BAWE_0377c-ftnote.029"/> requirement of "cogent and consistent evidence". </s><s n="s3.3;p12.21">Finally, the ECJ set decision in general supporting the CFI judgment stating that CFI possesses the right to require "close examination" of relevant circumstances because of the fact, that the quality of evidence is particularly important in leveraging cases<ref target="BAWE_0377c-ftnote.030"/>. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0377c-ftnote.028"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Tetra Laval v. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">Commission , supra note 12, para 155 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0377c-ftnote.029"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Case Kali und Salz AG. v. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">Commission 19/74, 20/74 [1975] ECR 499, [1975] 2 CMLR 154 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0377c-ftnote.030"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Thus, a mere "possibility" was clearly not enough, because here the standard of proof remains an elusive issue; Commission v. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">Tetra Laval case , supra note 8, para 40-44 </s></p></note><p n="p13.21"><s n="s1.3;p13.21">The CFI judgment was ruled in favor of Tetra Laval/Sidel, showing that the Commission needs to be still aware of the power of courts, that they can at any time examine its conduct and decision<ref target="BAWE_0377c-ftnote.031"/>. </s><s n="s2.3;p13.21">The highest Court explanations show, how difficult it is to foresee all consequences of decision, for example that the demand of "close examination" of pre merger situation by the Commission will cause the "paralyze" of this authority and much work overload. </s><s n="s3.3;p13.21">Additionally, how complex case the Tetra Laval was and that no without any purpose is so called a "landmark case". </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0377c-ftnote.031"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">However, as it was shown in the ECJ judgment, the CFI made mistakes in its decision </s></p></note><p n="p14.21"><s n="s1.2;p14.21">Unlikely to the opinion of Attorney General who stated that it is unpersuasive reasoning, The Commission was criticizing the CFI settlement, claiming incompatibility with structural nature of Merger Regulation, difficulties with implementation and contradiction with one of the main legal principle- the presumption of innocence. </s><s n="s2.2;p14.21">As a result, appealed to ECJ from the CFI decision, <ref target="BAWE_0377c-ftnote.032"/> hoping, that ECJ rejects the reasoning presented in the CFI decision. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0377c-ftnote.032"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">The Commission was also claiming that the CFI was in a breach of the art. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">230 EC Treaty which gives the Commission the wide discretion which "it enjoys in assessing economic matters" (ECJ judgment; para 37) and do not need to provide the quality of evidence to prove their line of reasoning. </s></p></note><p n="p15.21"><s n="s1.8;p15.21">ECJ was considering two grounds of appeal, pointed by the Commission. </s><s n="s2.8;p15.21">Therefore, decided that however the Commission has a margin of discretion due to economic matters it does not mean that the CFI and other courts in course of judicial review are not able to examine the Commission's interpretation.<ref target="BAWE_0377c-ftnote.033"/> Concluding, it does not mean that the Courts were infringing the art. </s><s n="s3.8;p15.21">230 of EC Treaty as the Commission were claiming. </s><s n="s4.8;p15.21">Furthermore, that debated issue is so complex and extremely difficult also because of its prospective effects, that such a review is necessary. </s><s n="s5.8;p15.21">Conversely to the first ground of appeal which was found irrelevant, the second one was accepted partially. </s><s n="s6.8;p15.21">The debated issue was related to requirement of convincing, cogent and sufficient evidence established by CFI while assessing a proposed merger. </s><s n="s7.8;p15.21">ECJ stated that however the likelihood of leveraging must be examined comprehensively<ref target="BAWE_0377c-ftnote.034"/>, it "would run counter to the main purpose of ECMR- prevention to require the Commission "<ref target="BAWE_0377c-ftnote.035"/> to assess in each proposed merger a number of factors<ref target="BAWE_0377c-ftnote.036"/>. </s><s n="s8.8;p15.21">As a consequence of the CFI statement the required high probability of the facts occurrence would force The Commission to unnecessarily too detailed examination, and shift from relying on relevant fact to more speculative reasoning. <ref target="BAWE_0377c-ftnote.037"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0377c-ftnote.033"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Additionally, important task for the Court as CFI was stating, is not to examine evidence but more to analyze whether the Commission have taken all the substantial information into account. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0377c-ftnote.034"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">What the CFI in its judgment recognized correctly </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0377c-ftnote.035"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Commission v. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">Tetra Laval Case C-12/03 P [2003] 4 CMLR 768 (ECJ, 15-th February 2005) para 75 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0377c-ftnote.036"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Incentives, factors reducing its possibility, prospective unlawfulness of conduct etc. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0377c-ftnote.037"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">ECJ decided also that CFI have erred in law, while rejecting the Commission's statement as to the adoption by the merged company a conduct possibly resulting in leverage. </s></p></note><p n="p16.21"><s n="s1.4;p16.21">The CFI comparison to the Gencor case<ref target="BAWE_0377c-ftnote.038"/> was hardly criticized by the ECJ, mainly because it was completely different from "Tetra case". </s><s n="s2.4;p16.21">The main reason was that in Gencor the concentration would cause the creation of a dominant duopoly and consequently impede the structure of the market and because of this the possibility of an abuse would be foreseeable. </s><s n="s3.4;p16.21">In my opinion this reasoning is highly reasonable. </s><s n="s4.4;p16.21">Unlikely to the Tetra Laval/ Sidel case were the carton market construction may be "slightly changed", but as a matter of fact, did not cause the effective competition on this market, but on the market of PET equipment. <ref target="BAWE_0377c-ftnote.039"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0377c-ftnote.038"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Case T-102/96, Gencor v. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">Commission, judgment 25 March 1999 [1999] ECR II-753 in : P. Craig, G. de Burca <hi rend="italic">"EU law- text, cases and materials</hi>"; 3-rd edition; Oxford 2003 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0377c-ftnote.039"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Thus, the Commission should be aware of leveraging that may occur on this market, not impeding the competition directly but in a longer period of time i.e. by the abusive conduct performed on the carton market; Commission v. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">Tetra Laval case, supra note 17, para 82 </s></p></note><p n="p17.21"><s n="s1.3;p17.21">It has to be highlighted, that the ECJ judgment<ref target="BAWE_0377c-ftnote.040"/> does not exclude prohibition of conglomerate mergers under the ECMR but put a rigid legal and practical constraints on the Commission in case of considering its prospective effect, basing on the theory of competitive harm. </s><s n="s2.3;p17.21">Owning to this, there is a need to show chain of cause and effect of such a conduct, what is more as the ECJ stated, supported by high quality of evidence, what is extremely important while considering potential, future effect. </s><s n="s3.3;p17.21">Secondly the deep analyzes of the effectiveness of behavioural commitments have to be performed.<ref target="BAWE_0377c-ftnote.041"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0377c-ftnote.040"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Because of the fact that ECJ found the grounds of appeal relevant in a part, therefore it was unreasonable to annul the whole contested decision made by CFI. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0377c-ftnote.041"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">The Commission is not allowed to simply "miss that step" and not to consider its possible relevance, what is more push the Commission to reassess its methods of evaluating commitments in general. </s></p></note><p n="p18.21"><s n="s1.2;p18.21">The Commission did not take into account the proposals made by the Tetra Laval company, deciding that they are behavioral in nature, rejecting them without testing the market. </s><s n="s2.2;p18.21">This step taken by The Commission was criticized in course of judicial review- by CFI, Attorney General and ECJ. All stated, that "commitments would have substantially reduced scope for leveraging"<ref target="BAWE_0377c-ftnote.042"/>, what is more, the Commission did not even try to check whether they would have been effective or not, deciding that they are "pure promises"<ref target="BAWE_0377c-ftnote.043"/>, in general "mere" stating to refrain from acting in contravention of Community law<ref target="BAWE_0377c-ftnote.044"/> and " as such, they are not suitable to restore conditions of effective competition on a permanent basis ..., since they do not address the permanent change in the market structure created by the notified operation that causes these concerns' and, that "such behavioural promises are in contrast with the Commission's stated policy on remedies" , moreover conversely to the main principle of ECMR. According to this, it would be very difficult to control it effectively<ref target="BAWE_0377c-ftnote.045"/>. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0377c-ftnote.042"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Sven B. Völcker ; "Conglomerate Merger Control after Tetra Laval", Wilmer Cutler Pickering Hale &amp; Dorr, Brussels and Anthony Whelan, Legal Service, European Commission -College d'Europe 2005; </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0377c-ftnote.043"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">i.e. not to bundle, hold-separate of Sidel for 10 years, having no joint offers of Tetra Pak carton products and Sidel SBM machines </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0377c-ftnote.044"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Commission v. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">Tetra Laval case, supra note 17, para 55 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0377c-ftnote.045"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid , 83 </s></p></note><p n="p19.21"><s n="s1.4;p19.21">The alternative remedy for leveraging concerns is the ex- post merger control under the art. </s><s n="s2.4;p19.21">82 EC Treaty. </s><s n="s3.4;p19.21">However it raises the question, whether the post application would be sufficient examination. </s><s n="s4.4;p19.21">The explanation of the post- merger control is much clear- waiting allows the competition authorities to observe if the leveraging practices will occur and consequently what result they will cause.<ref target="BAWE_0377c-ftnote.046"/> The availability of the ex- post remedies was accepted by the CFI in its judgment in Tetra Laval/Sidel case. <ref target="BAWE_0377c-ftnote.047"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0377c-ftnote.046"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.4;pn1.1"><hi rend="italic">Sven B Volcker</hi>; "Leveraging as a theory of competitive harm in EU merger control", Common Market Law Review. </s><s n="s2.4;pn1.1">New York: June 2003.Vol.40, Iss. </s><s n="s3.4;pn1.1">3; pg. </s><s n="s4.4;pn1.1">581, para 3.3 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0377c-ftnote.047"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.7;pn1.1">Sometimes it may be very difficult to detect and prove some infringements because they are not substantial enough to reach the "unfair" point covered by art.82 EC Treaty, even though, the price increase can cause harm to consumers. </s><s n="s2.7;pn1.1">The difference with leveraging is that if it has an exclusionary effect, will certainly fall under the prohibition. </s><s n="s3.7;pn1.1">Additionally, leveraging is much more likely brought to the attention of rivals or competition authorities noticing changes on the market rapidly. </s><s n="s4.7;pn1.1">Based on: Sven B Volcker; "Leveraging as a theory of competitive harm in EU merger control", Common Market Law Review. </s><s n="s5.7;pn1.1">New York: June 2003.Vol.40, Iss. </s><s n="s6.7;pn1.1">3; pg. </s><s n="s7.7;pn1.1">581, </s></p></note><p n="p20.21"><s n="s1.4;p20.21">Leveraging practice usually tends to lower rivals' profits by affecting its business<ref target="BAWE_0377c-ftnote.048"/> but not in a way of directly increasing their costs. </s><s n="s2.4;p20.21">In the case of Guinness Grand Metropolitan<ref target="BAWE_0377c-ftnote.049"/> the Commission was considering if a new merged entity by widening its "flexibility and capacity" will not try to engage in "tying, to structure its prices, promotions and discounts"<ref target="BAWE_0377c-ftnote.050"/>. </s><s n="s3.4;p20.21">Similar concerns were discussed in a case GE/Honeywell<ref target="BAWE_0377c-ftnote.051"/> were the Commission was relying on "the combined financial ability of the merged entity to cross- subsidize discounts across the products composing the packaged deal"<ref target="BAWE_0377c-ftnote.052"/> Moreover, as it was predicted by the Commission in Tetra Laval/ Sidel case the simple tying as a part of leveraging can even cause the decrease of prices. </s><s n="s4.4;p20.21">Thus, it may be difficult to observe how it convince a sufficient number of customers to purchase the tied good and as a result to achieve expected foreclosure, unless the merged entity reduces the price of the tying and possibly tied product.<ref target="BAWE_0377c-ftnote.053"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0377c-ftnote.048"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.4;pn1.1">For example trough diverting demand to the combined entity- Sven B Volcker; "Leveraging as a theory of competitive harm in EU merger control", Common Market Law Review. </s><s n="s2.4;pn1.1">New York: June 2003.Vol.40, Iss. </s><s n="s3.4;pn1.1">3; pg. </s><s n="s4.4;pn1.1">581,para 2.2 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0377c-ftnote.049"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Guinness Metropolitan IV/M.938, [1998] OJ L228/24 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0377c-ftnote.050"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">So called portfolio effect; ibid ,para 40 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0377c-ftnote.051"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">GE/ Honeywell case T- 209 and 210/01, </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0377c-ftnote.052"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">ibid, para 353 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0377c-ftnote.053"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.4;pn1.1">Sven B Volcker; "Leveraging as a theory of competitive harm in EU merger control", Common Market Law Review. </s><s n="s2.4;pn1.1">New York: June 2003.Vol.40, Iss. </s><s n="s3.4;pn1.1">3; pg. </s><s n="s4.4;pn1.1">581, </s></p></note></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold italic">Conclusion</head><p n="p21.21"><s n="s1.10;p21.21">It is very interesting issue, why practices such as leveraging occur more often on the EC than i.e. </s><s n="s2.10;p21.21">US market? </s><s n="s3.10;p21.21">American competition authorities are less worried about the effect of conglomerate mergers. </s><s n="s4.10;p21.21">Secondly it is observed that companies operating on common market are afraid of legal constraints imposed by art. </s><s n="s5.10;p21.21">82 EC Treaty. </s><s n="s6.10;p21.21">Thus it is a questionable issue for the European Competition Authorities if the present approach is reasonable and creates the desired effect on the market? </s><s n="s7.10;p21.21">Maybe the Commission needs to provide a "time- frame" within which the effect of conglomerate merger should be considered, like it have indicated it in horizontal cases were "countervailing factors" arising more than two years after entities have merged, may be recognize as too speculative<ref target="BAWE_0377c-ftnote.054"/>? </s><s n="s8.10;p21.21">Therefore, the Commission "predictive" powers would be limited by the available evidence, thus all "harming" speculations possibly will not be taken into account? </s><s n="s9.10;p21.21">It is hoped that the situation will be clarified in the nearest future and that the Commission's approach will follow the US one<ref target="BAWE_0377c-ftnote.055"/>. </s><s n="s10.10;p21.21">There is a need for setting up a threshold against which mergering companies would be able to examine their conduct in advance in order to be aware of problematic issues, raising competition concerns in conglomerate cases. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0377c-ftnote.054"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">In Siemens/Dragewerk, the Commission's decision of 30 April 2003. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0377c-ftnote.055"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Which emphasizes the need to prove that the potential harm, basing on the fact of the case, be likely to result from the merger; supra note 4, page 281 </s></p></note></div1></body><back><div1 type="bibliography"><head rend="underlined bold">Bibliography:</head><p><hi rend="bold">Jeffrey Church,</hi> "<hi rend="italic">The Impact of Vertical and Conglomerate Mergers on Competition"</hi> Church Economic Consultants Ltd. and Department of Economics University of Calgary<hi rend="italic"> for</hi> Directorate General for Competition Directorate B Merger Task Force European Commission, September 2004; Final Report; <seg type="URL" n="http://ec.europa.eu/comm/competition/mergers/others/merger_impact.pdf"/></p><p rend="bold">S. Baxter, F. Dethmers and N. Dodoo; <hi rend="italic">"The GE/Honeywell judgment and the assessment of conglomerate effects: what's new in EC practice?"</hi> <seg type="URL" n="http://0-www.hartjournals.co.uk.pugwash.lib"/>.<name type="university"/>.ac.uk/pdf/ECJ-02-01-0893.pdf</p><p><hi rend="bold">F. Dethmers, N. Dodoo and A. Morfey; </hi><hi rend="italic">"Conglomerate mergers under EC merger control: an overview"</hi><hi rend="bold">. <seg type="URL" n="http://0-www.hartjournals.co.uk.pugwash.lib"/>.<name type="university"/>.ac.uk/pdf/ECJ-01-02-0770.pdf</hi></p><p><hi rend="bold">Bo Vesterdorf,</hi> "<hi rend="italic">Standard of proof in merger cases: reflections in the light of recent case law of the community courts".</hi><hi rend="bold"> <seg type="URL" n="http://0-www.hartjournals.co.uk.pugwash.lib"/>.<name type="university"/>.ac.uk/pdf/ECJ-01-01-0657.pdf</hi></p><p><hi rend="bold">J. Cooper, L. Froeb, D. O'Brien, and M. Vita; </hi><hi rend="italic">"A critique of professor church's report on the impact of vertical and conglomerate mergers on competition"</hi> ; Journal of Competition Law and Economics, December 2005; 1: 785 - 792.<hi rend="bold"> <seg type="URL" n="http://0-jcle.oxfordjournals.org.pugwash.lib"/>.<name type="university"/>.ac.uk/cgi/content/full/1/4/785?maxtoshow=&amp;HITS=10&amp;hits=10&amp;RESULTFORMAT=1&amp;andorexacttitle=and&amp;andorexacttitleabs=and&amp;fulltext=conglomerate+merger&amp;andorexactfulltext=and&amp;searchid=1&amp;FIRSTINDEX=0&amp;sortspec=relevance&amp;resourcetype=HWCIT</hi></p><p><hi rend="bold">J. Grant and D.J. Neven; <hi rend="italic">"The attempted merger between General Electric and Honeywell: a case study of transatlantic conflict";</hi></hi> Journal of Competition Law and Economics, September 2005; 1: 595 - 633. <hi rend="bold"><seg type="URL" n="http://0-jcle.oxfordjournals.org.pugwash.lib"/>.<name type="university"/>.ac.uk/cgi/reprint/1/3/595?maxtoshow=&amp;HITS=10&amp;hits=10&amp;RESULTFORMAT=1&amp;andorexacttitle=and&amp;andorexacttitleabs=and&amp;fulltext=conglomerate+merger&amp;andorexactfulltext=and&amp;searchid=1&amp;FIRSTINDEX=0&amp;sortspec=relevance&amp;resourcetype=HWCIT</hi></p><p><hi rend="bold">Yves Botteman; "</hi><hi rend="italic">Mergers, standard of proof and expert economic evidence".</hi>Journal of Competition Law and Economics, March 2006; 2: 71 - 100<hi rend="bold">. <seg type="URL" n="http://0-jcle.oxfordjournals.org.pugwash.lib"/>.<name type="university"/>.ac.uk/cgi/reprint/2/1/71?maxtoshow=&amp;HITS=10&amp;hits=10&amp;RESULTFORMAT=1&amp;andorexacttitle=and&amp;andorexacttitleabs=and&amp;fulltext=conglomerate+merger&amp;andorexactfulltext=and&amp;searchid=1&amp;FIRSTINDEX=0&amp;sortspec=relevance&amp;resourcetype=HWCIT</hi></p><p><hi rend="bold">G. Dari-Mattiacci and F. Parisi, </hi><hi rend="italic">"Substituting complements"</hi>Journal of Competition Law and Economics, September 2006; 2: 333 - 347<hi rend="bold">. <seg type="URL" n="http://0-jcle.oxfordjournals.org.pugwash.lib"/>.<name type="university"/>.ac.uk/cgi/reprint/2/3/333?maxtoshow=&amp;HITS=10&amp;hits=10&amp;RESULTFORMAT=1&amp;andorexacttitle=and&amp;andorexacttitleabs=and&amp;fulltext=conglomerate+merger&amp;andorexactfulltext=and&amp;searchid=1&amp;FIRSTINDEX=0&amp;sortspec=relevance&amp;resourcetype=HWCIT</hi></p><p><hi rend="bold">Sven B. Völcker ; </hi><hi rend="italic">"Conglomerate Merger Control after Tetra Laval", Wilmer Cutler Pickering Hale &amp; Dorr, Brussels and Anthony Whelan, Legal Service, European Commission -</hi>College d'Europe 2005</p><p><seg type="URL" n="http://www.coleurop.be/template.asp?pagename=lunchtalkarchive&amp;sub=20050429"/></p><p><hi rend="bold">Sven B Volcker; <hi rend="italic">"Leveraging as a theory of competitive harm in EU merger control",</hi> Common Market Law Review</hi>. New York: June 2003.Vol.40, Iss. 3; pg. 581, <seg type="URL" n="http://pugwash.lib"/>.<name type="university"/>.ac.uk/validate/http%3A%2F%2F0-proquest.umi.com.pugwash.lib.<name type="university"/>.ac.uk%3A80%2Fpqdweb%3FRQT%3D318%26pmid%3D57934%26TS%3D1174085238%26clientId%3D9678%26VType%3DPQD%26VName%3DPQD%26VInst%3DPROD</p><p><hi rend="bold">Sven B Völcker and Pablo Charro; </hi><hi rend="italic">"Tetra Laval - a landmark judgment</hi></p><p><hi rend="italic">on EC merger control"</hi> published in the 8 March 2004 issue of <hi rend="italic">Competition Law Insight; web page: </hi><seg type="URL" n="http://www.wilmerhale.com/files/Publication/98490b9e-96b2-409f-880e-47a00bbefdee/Presentation/PublicationAttachment/12d65816-2a4b-4ace-b6d0-4d7cfae17792/CLI_Tetra_article.pdf"/></p><p><hi rend="bold">Jose Rivas, Jonathan Branton,</hi> "Developments in EC Competition law in 2002: An overview". Common Market Law Review. New York: Oct 2003.Vol.40, Iss. 5; pg. 1187, <seg type="URL" n="http://pugwash.lib"/>.<name type="university"/>.ac.uk/validate/http%3A%2F%2F0-proquest.umi.com.pugwash.lib.<name type="university"/>.ac.uk%3A80%2Fpqdweb%3FRQT%3D318%26pmid%3D57934%26TS%3D1174084887%26clientId%3D9678%26VType%3DPQD%26VName%3DPQD%26VInst%3DPROD</p><p><hi rend="bold">F.O.W. Vogelaar</hi>, <hi rend="italic">"The European Competition Rules</hi>", Europa Law Publishing, Groningen 2004</p><p><hi rend="bold">J.Maitland- Walker, </hi><hi rend="italic">"Competition laws of Europe</hi>", 2-nd edition 2003 Lexis Nexis Butterworths, 2003</p><p><hi rend="bold">M.Furse,</hi> "<hi rend="italic">Competition Law of the EC and UK</hi>", 4-th edition 2004; Oxford Univ. Press</p><p><hi rend="bold">B.Suffrin, A.Jones</hi> "EC competition law: text, cases, and materials"; Oxford University Press, 2004.</p><p><hi rend="bold">D.G.Goyder</hi> "<hi rend="italic">EC Competition Law",</hi> 4-th edition 2003; Oxford Univ. Press</p><p><hi rend="bold">K.Middleton, B.J.Rodger, A.Mac Culloch</hi> "Cases and materials on UK&amp; EC Competition Law"; Oxford Univ. Press 2003</p><p><hi rend="bold">R.Whish</hi> " Competition Law"; 5-th edition, Lexis Nexis 2003</p><p><hi rend="bold">P. Craig, G. de Burca </hi><hi rend="italic">"EU law- text, cases and materials</hi>"; 3-rd edition; Oxford 2003</p><p><hi rend="bold">EC Merger Regulation</hi> No.139/2004 of 20 January 2004 on the control of concentration between undertakings (so called EC Merger Regulation); Official Journal of the European Union, 29 January 2004 ; L 24/1</p><p>Guinness Grand Metropolitan [1998] OJ L228/24 par. 40-41 </p><p>Commission v. Tetra Laval Case C-12/03 P [2003] 4 CMLR 768 (ECJ, 15-th Feb. 2005) para. 43</p><p>GE/Amersham case M.3304, Commission's decision of 21 January, 2004</p><p>GE/ Honeywell case T- 209 and 210/01</p></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
