<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_0378a" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Extraction and Characterization of Natural Products</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">deleted: header: student name; footer: page numbers</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">3</p><p n="date">2007-06</p><p n="module title">Extended Laboratory Work</p><p n="module code">CH3C6</p><p n="genre family">Methodology recount</p><p n="discipline">Chemistry</p><p n="disciplinary group">PS</p><p n="grade">D</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">2798</p><p n="number of s-units">156</p><p n="number of p">53</p><p n="number of tables">7</p><p n="number of figures">2</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">9</p><p n="number of lists">4</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">19</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">17.9</p><p n="average s-units per p">2.9</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">f</p><p n="year of birth">1986</p><p n="first language">Chinese Cantonese</p><p n="education">UKA</p><p n="course">BSc Biomedical Chemistry</p><p n="student ID">0378</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><titlePart rend="underlined">15/ 05/ 07</titlePart><docTitle><titlePart rend="underlined">Year 3 Chemical Biology Laboratory Extraction and Characterization of Natural Products </titlePart></docTitle></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined">Aim</head><p n="p1.53"><s n="s1.2;p1.53">Extract the pennyroyal oil from pennyroyal leaves using a crude steam distillation method and purify the oil by Thin Layer Chromatography (TLC) and column chromatography. </s><s n="s2.2;p1.53">Use gas Chromatography (GC), FT- IR and H NMR to characterize the oil extracted. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined">Isolation Scheme</head><figure id="BAWE_0378a-fig.001"/><p n="p2.53"><s n="s1.2;p2.53">R- (+) Pulegone is the common oil found in Pennyroyal leaves. </s><s n="s2.2;p2.53">Others include isomethone and piperitenone.<hi rend="sup">1</hi> </s></p><table id="BAWE_0378a-tab.001"><head rend="underlined">List of reagents and safety information</head><row><cell/></row></table></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined">Experimental Procedure </head><div2><head rend="underlined">Extraction of pennyroyal oil</head><p rend="ordered" n="p3.53"><s n="s1.1;p3.53">The steam distillation apparatus was set up as shown in the laboratory manual. </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p4.53"><s n="s1.1;p4.53">25.01 g of Pennyroyal leaves was measured out in a 500 ml round bottom flask and distilled water was added to the flask until it was half full. </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p5.53"><s n="s1.2;p5.53">The flask was connected to the steam distillation apparatus and put in an oil bath. </s><s n="s2.2;p5.53">The leaves were heated and stirred until condensate begins to form in the condenser. </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p6.53"><s n="s1.2;p6.53">The oil temperature was at 130°c when the condensate was formed. </s><s n="s2.2;p6.53">The system was insulated by applying some foil around the neck of the apparatus. </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p7.53"><s n="s1.1;p7.53">The boiling point of the oil and water mixture was about 97- 98°c. </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p8.53"><s n="s1.1;p8.53">The water level was kept at a constant level by allowing water to add from the dropping funnel. </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p9.53"><s n="s1.4;p9.53">The apparatus was checked by the demonstrator to ensure it was safe. </s><s n="s2.4;p9.53">The distillation was left to run for about 1 and a half hour. </s><s n="s3.4;p9.53">About 80 cm <hi rend="sup">3</hi> of distillate was collected. </s><s n="s4.4;p9.53">The apparatus was left to run to collect more distillate. </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p10.53"><s n="s1.1;p10.53">80 cm <hi rend="sup">3</hi> was transferred to a separating funnel where it was washed with 3 x 10 cm <hi rend="sup">3</hi> of dichloromethane DCM. </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p11.53"><s n="s1.3;p11.53">The DCM extracts were collected and was added to 25 cm <hi rend="sup">3</hi> of saturated sodium chloride. </s><s n="s2.3;p11.53">This was mixed and pressure was released at regular intervals. </s><s n="s3.3;p11.53">The DCM layer was collected. </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p12.53"><s n="s1.1;p12.53">2 x 5 cm <hi rend="sup">3</hi> of DCM was used to repeat the extraction and the total DCM extracts were gathered. </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p13.53"><s n="s1.1;p13.53">This was dried with magnesium sulphate until there was a snow storm effect. </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p14.53"><s n="s1.4;p14.53">The solvent was evaporated using a rotary evaporator. </s><s n="s2.4;p14.53">A very pale yellow oily liquid was resulted. </s><s n="s3.4;p14.53">This has the smell of peppermint tea. </s><s n="s4.4;p14.53">The yield of the crude extract can be calculated. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">Optimization of thin layer chromatography (TLC)</head><p n="p15.53"><s n="s1.4;p15.53">A suitable solvent system that gives Rf value of about 0.3- 0.5 from the major component of the oil; R- (+) Pulegone was determined. </s><s n="s2.4;p15.53">A mixture of 60/ 80 petroleum ether and ethyl acetate was used as the solvent. </s><s n="s3.4;p15.53">0.5 % solutions of commercial R- (+) Pulegone in DCM solution were used as the reference solution for the optimization. </s><s n="s4.4;p15.53">By decreasing the more polar ethyl acetate would decrease the Rf value. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">Reference solution</head><p n="p16.53"><s n="s1.2;p16.53">The reference solution was analyzed in different ratios of solvent system. </s><s n="s2.2;p16.53">One spot was observed. </s></p><table id="BAWE_0378a-tab.002"><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p17.53"><s n="s1.1;p17.53">The 15: 1 60/ 80 petroleum ether and ethyl acetate gives an Rf value between 0.3- 0.5 so therefore this could be used. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0378a-fig.002"/></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">Sample solution</head><p n="p18.53"><s n="s1.4;p18.53">Once, a potential solvent system was determined, it was used to analyze the sample. </s><s n="s2.4;p18.53">A small amount of DCM was added to part of a sample. </s><s n="s3.4;p18.53">The reference solution, sample solution and a co-spot of the two were analyzed. </s><s n="s4.4;p18.53">The co- spotting of the two solutions would indicate the existence of R- (+) Pulegone in the sample. </s></p><table id="BAWE_0378a-tab.003"><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p19.53"><s n="s1.9;p19.53">From the Rf values, it clearly showed that the crude extract contains R- (+) Pulegone and two other compounds. </s><s n="s2.9;p19.53">The extract was purified by column chromatography so the solvent system used was essential as the effectiveness of the purification is dependent on this. </s><s n="s3.9;p19.53">The solvent system used must allow the separation of each of the compounds in the sample. </s><s n="s4.9;p19.53">As there are two unwanted compounds in the sample, the solvent was made less polar in order to slow down the flow of compounds to give a better separation. </s><s n="s5.9;p19.53">The 20:1 60/ 80 petroleum ether and ethyl acetate solvent mixture was used. </s><s n="s6.9;p19.53">This gave a bigger separation between the first compound and R- (+) Pulegone so this was the chosen solvent system. </s><s n="s7.9;p19.53">In the co- spotting experiment, it only showed three spots, just like the sample which confirms that the spot for R- (+) Pulegone in the sample is the same as the reference i.e.: same compound. </s><s n="s8.9;p19.53">If they are two different compounds, there would be a total of four spots. </s><s n="s9.9;p19.53">The other two compounds found in the sample could be the other types of oil in the pennyroyal leaves as the leaves contain many essential oils. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0378a-fig.003"/></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">Purification by column chromatography</head><p rend="ordered" n="p20.53"><s n="s1.1;p20.53">A slurry of approximately 5 g of silica and the 20:1 60/ 80 petroleum ether and ethyl acetate was used to pack the column. </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p21.53"><s n="s1.1;p21.53">The column was drained so that the solvent just covered the top of the silica and a small amount of sand was added to stop the column from being disturbed. </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p22.53"><s n="s1.1;p22.53">The column was loaded carefully with 25 % solution of the crude oil in 20:1 solvent mixture. </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p23.53"><s n="s1.1;p23.53">The column was run so that the sample solution was just below the surface of the silica. </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p24.53"><s n="s1.1;p24.53">The column was topped up with about 100 cm <hi rend="sup">3</hi> solvent mixture and was run so that 6 sequential fractions were collected in test tubes. </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p25.53"><s n="s1.1;p25.53">The first 6 tubes were analyzed for R- (+) Pulegone by spotting the fractions against the sample solution. </s></p><table id="BAWE_0378a-tab.004"><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p26.53"><s n="s1.3;p26.53">By spotting the sample solution against the different fractions on the same TLC plate, the fractions containing R- (+) Pulegone can be identified. </s><s n="s2.3;p26.53">Fractions 1, 2, 4 contain the R- (+) Pulegone and another compound. </s><s n="s3.3;p26.53">Fractions 5 and 6 contain the other compound so that the only clean and pure fraction that contains the essential oil R- (+) Pulegone is fraction 3. </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p27.53"><s n="s1.4;p27.53">After determining the fractions that contain R- (+) Pulegone, the solvent was evaporated on the rotary evaporator. </s><s n="s2.4;p27.53">A colourless oily liquid was resulted. </s><s n="s3.4;p27.53">The liquid has a smell of peppermint tea. </s><s n="s4.4;p27.53">The yield of the purified extract can be calculated. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0378a-fig.004"/></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined">Yield of extracts</head><div2><head rend="underlined">Crude extract </head><list type="simple"><item>Mass of flask: 95.67g</item><item>Mass of flask and oil: 95.91g</item><item>Mass of crude extract: 0.24g</item><item>Yield <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0378a-form.001"/> = <hi rend="underlined">0.96%</hi></item></list><p n="p28.53"/></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">Purified extract</head><list type="simple"><item>Mass of flask: 95.84g</item><item>Mass of flask and purified oil: 95.9488g</item><item>Mass of purified extract: 0.1088g</item><item>Yield = <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0378a-form.002"/> = <hi rend="underlined">0.435%</hi></item></list><p n="p29.53"><s n="s1.4;p29.53">There are many reasons why the yield was very low. </s><s n="s2.4;p29.53">Only 80 ml of distillate was carried out to the extraction step when about 170 ml was collected. </s><s n="s3.4;p29.53">Another reason is that the yield was calculated using the mass of the pennyroyal leaves which is inaccurate as this is not the mass of the oil in the leaves. </s><s n="s4.4;p29.53">Inaccuracies were also induced during the purification step because the essential oil R- (+) Pulegone was found in multiple fractions but only the purest fraction was taken to evaporate. </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined">Characterization and Discussion</head><p n="p30.53"><s rend="underlined" n="s1.1;p30.53">NMR </s></p><p n="p31.53"><s rend="underlined" n="s1.1;p31.53">R- (+) Pulegone </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0378a-pic.001"/><p n="p32.53"><s n="s1.11;p32.53">The reference proton NMR and the sample proton NMR were compared so that the purity of the sample can be assessed. </s><s n="s2.11;p32.53">In the reference NMR, all the signals were located below 3.0ppm which is the aliphatic carbon chain region. </s><s n="s3.11;p32.53">There are many signals less than 3.0ppm in the sample NMR which means that there are traces of the essential oil R- (+) Pulegone. </s><s n="s4.11;p32.53">Unfortunately, there are too many signals so making it very hard to interpret therefore, this was used to compare to the reference. </s><s n="s5.11;p32.53">It was found that from 1.8 - 2.75ppm, the splitting pattern is exactly identical which strongly indicates the existence of the essential oil. </s><s n="s6.11;p32.53">However, the multiplet at 1.35ppm and the doublet at 1.02ppm were masked by large signals so cannot be observed. </s><s n="s7.11;p32.53">The extra signals presented could be due to a number of reasons. </s><s n="s8.11;p32.53">One of which was that there are many other compounds and oils in pennyroyal leaves that could have been extracted out during the crude extraction process and then later on, failed to separation from R- (+) Pulegone. </s><s n="s9.11;p32.53">The sample is of pennyroyal oil and not R- (+) Pulegone so therefore it is not unusual that there are other NMR signals as well as the essential oil's signals. </s><s n="s10.11;p32.53">From the TLC analysis, it showed that the sample only contained R- (+) Pulegone in the purified fraction but however, NMR showed different results, This is because TLC is not a very accurate analytical method in identifying the purity of samples as many compounds have similar polarity therefore would travel similar distance and have similar Rf values. </s><s n="s11.11;p32.53">From the NMR spectra, one can conclude that there are definitely traces of R- (+) Pulegone in the sample but however, it is not very pure as there are other compounds presented. </s></p><p n="p33.53"><s n="s1.1;p33.53">In order to interpret and assign the hydrogens correctly, calculations were used to give a rough guide on the chemical shifts. </s></p><div2><head rend="underlined">Calculation2</head><list type="simple"><item><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0378a-form.003"/></item><item><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0378a-form.004"/></item><item><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0378a-form.005"/></item><item><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0378a-form.006"/></item><item><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0378a-form.007"/></item><item><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0378a-form.008"/></item><item><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0378a-form.009"/></item></list><p n="p34.53"><s n="s1.3;p34.53">The splittings of the NMR signals and the integrals were used to help with the assignment but there were many difficulties since a number of hydrogens have the same splittings and integrals. </s><s n="s2.3;p34.53">The calculations give a rough indication of the location of each signal but the calculations are not very accurate since the some numbers used do not exactly describe the environment in which hydrogens are located. </s><s n="s3.3;p34.53">From this only <hi rend="bold">H1</hi> can be assigned confidently as this was the only hydrogen which gives a doublet, an integral of 3 and occur at around 1.0ppm. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0378a-pic.002"/><p n="p35.53"><s n="s1.4;p35.53">The R- (+) Pulegone has a 6-membered cyclic ring which means it could exist as a chair conformation therefore there are axial and equatorial hydrogens. </s><s n="s2.4;p35.53">Even though both the axial and equatorial hydrogens are located on the same carbon but they both have different environment so therefore not equivalent. </s><s n="s3.4;p35.53">This gives a carbon chiral centre as shown in the diagram. </s><s n="s4.4;p35.53">As all the hydrogens are not identical, this makes the spectrum more complex and harder to interpret. </s></p><p n="p36.53"><s n="s1.2;p36.53">As the initial assignment was not successful, extra methods were used to help with the assignment. </s><s n="s2.2;p36.53">This includes COSY, PENDENT, HMBC and HMQC. </s></p><p n="p37.53"><s n="s1.2;p37.53">The HMQC spectrum gives direct C-H correlations. </s><s n="s2.2;p37.53">The HMQC spectrum vs H NMR can indicate the hydrogens that are attached to the same carbon. </s></p><table id="BAWE_0378a-tab.005"><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p38.53"><s n="s1.4;p38.53">There are 3 CH <hi rend="sub">2</hi> in the compound and each pair of hydrogens has been identified. </s><s n="s2.4;p38.53">From this H7 can be assigned as this is the only hydrogen left on its own that has an integral of 1. </s><s n="s3.4;p38.53">This means H7 must be of 2.0ppm. </s><s n="s4.4;p38.53">The multiplet is slightly masked by the singlet around this chemical shift. </s></p><p n="p39.53"><s n="s1.7;p39.53">The PENDANT carbon NMR sort the signals out into how many hydrogens are attached. </s><s n="s2.7;p39.53">This PENDANT show that the signals pointing up are of zero or two hydrogens and the signals pointing down are of one or three hydrogens. </s><s n="s3.7;p39.53">This was known because the signal at 203ppm is due to the carbonyl because this is the most downfield carbon in the compound. </s><s n="s4.7;p39.53">It contains no hydrogen attached to it so the allocation could be done. </s><s n="s5.7;p39.53">The signals at 142 and 132ppm are the carbon double bond. </s><s n="s6.7;p39.53">The signals upfield to the residue solvent peak are the aliphatic carbon signals. </s><s n="s7.7;p39.53">PENDANT confirmed that the hydrogens A, B and C are CH <hi rend="sub">2.</hi> </s></p><p n="p40.53"><s n="s1.6;p40.53">The COSY spectrum shows hydrogen couplings. </s><s n="s2.6;p40.53">The signal intensity show how intense the coupling is. </s><s n="s3.6;p40.53">The <hi rend="bold">H1</hi> signal at 1.0ppm correlates well with hydrogens A and C which means that hydrogens B are <hi rend="bold">H5</hi> as these are the only two hydrogens that are not directly next to <hi rend="bold">H1.</hi> </s><s n="s4.6;p40.53">Hydrogens C show strong correlations with <hi rend="bold">H5</hi> at 2.28 and 2.74ppm. </s><s n="s5.6;p40.53">This clearly indicates that hydrogens C must be <hi rend="bold">H6</hi> as these are the only hydrogens that are directly next to <hi rend="bold">H5</hi>. </s><s n="s6.6;p40.53">As <hi rend="bold">H5</hi> and <hi rend="bold">H6</hi> have been assigned, this means that hydrogens A must be <hi rend="bold">H2</hi>. </s></p><p n="p41.53"><s n="s1.2;p41.53">The HMBC spectrum shows long range C-H correlations only. </s><s n="s2.2;p41.53">From this it confirmed the assignments from HMQC, PENDANT and COSY. </s></p><p n="p42.53"><s n="s1.7;p42.53"><hi rend="bold">H3</hi> and <hi rend="bold">H4</hi> can be assigned even though they both have the same integral and are both singlets. </s><s n="s2.7;p42.53">This is because the carbon double bond is fixed so both of the CH <hi rend="sub">3</hi> are in different environment. </s><s n="s3.7;p42.53"><hi rend="bold">H3</hi> are closer to the carbonyl which would shift the signals more downfield than <hi rend="bold">H4</hi>. </s><s n="s4.7;p42.53">However, this is only a prediction. </s><s n="s5.7;p42.53">In order to prove this is the case, a nOe experiment must be carried out. </s><s n="s6.7;p42.53">By irradiating <hi rend="bold">H5</hi>, this should enhance the signal of <hi rend="bold">H4</hi> and not <hi rend="bold">H3</hi>. </s><s n="s7.7;p42.53">The enhanced signal would be <hi rend="bold">H4</hi> and the one that is reminding would be <hi rend="bold">H3</hi>. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">Assignment</head><table id="BAWE_0378a-tab.006"><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p43.53"><s n="s1.1;p43.53">The calculations were compared to the observed chemical shifts; the order is very similar to the assignment. </s></p><p n="p44.53"><s n="s1.4;p44.53">For <hi rend="bold">H2</hi>, <hi rend="bold">H5</hi> and <hi rend="bold">H6</hi>, there are two hydrogens, both axial and equatorial. </s><s n="s2.4;p44.53">It is very hard to distinguish between the two. </s><s n="s3.4;p44.53">Extra experiments are needed in order to fully assign them. </s><s n="s4.4;p44.53">Axial hydrogens usually come into resonance at higher field than equatorial hydrogens as they are of higher energy.<hi rend="sup">2</hi> This means that one can predict the higher field hydrogens are axial and the lower field hydrogens are equatorial. </s></p><p n="p45.53"><s n="s1.2;p45.53">There are some common impurities that were found in the spectra. </s><s n="s2.2;p45.53">The signal at 1.6 ppm was water and the peak at 2.15 ppm was acetone.<hi rend="sup">3</hi> The water is most likely from the steam distillation and the acetone is probably from the glass tube. </s></p><p n="p46.53"><s n="s1.2;p46.53">As the major functional group; α, β unsaturated ketone cannot be determined using H NMR, it was important to carry out a FT-IR which should indicate all the key functional groups. </s><s n="s2.2;p46.53">With the NMR spectrum, it was very difficult to calculate the ratio between R- (+) Pulegone and other compounds so a GC was carried out. </s></p><p n="p47.53"><s rend="underlined" n="s1.1;p47.53">FT- IR </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">Assignment2</head><table id="BAWE_0378a-tab.007"><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p48.53"><s n="s1.3;p48.53">There are many unassigned peaks. </s><s n="s2.3;p48.53">This is because the peaks could be from other oils in the pennyroyal leaves. </s><s n="s3.3;p48.53">The FT-IR identified the distinct α,β- unsaturated ketone and alkene which showed that the sample could contain R- (+) Pulegone. </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined">GC analysis</head><p n="p49.53"><s n="s1.8;p49.53">The GC analysis can be used to assess the purity of the sample. </s><s n="s2.8;p49.53">The retention time of the peak indicates the identity of R- (+) Pulegone in the sample. </s><s n="s3.8;p49.53">In the reference GC analysis, the commercial R- (+) Pulegone's retention time was 4.04 minutes. </s><s n="s4.8;p49.53">This can be used to compare with the sample. </s><s n="s5.8;p49.53">Yinan Hao's sample was used to compare. </s><s n="s6.8;p49.53">The retention time for R- (+) Pulegone was 4.011 minutes. </s><s n="s7.8;p49.53">The GC showed that as well as containing this essential oil, it also contains other compounds which could be other oils or impurities. </s><s n="s8.8;p49.53">A ratio of R- (+) Pulegone and other compounds can be determined from the areas of the peak. </s></p><div2><head rend="underlined">Purity:</head><list type="simple"><item>Total area of signals = 1361475</item><item>Area of R- (+) Pulegone signal = 761785</item><item>Ratio of R- (+) Pulegone: Other compounds and impurities = 56: 44</item></list><p n="p50.53"><s n="s1.1;p50.53">This shows that the major component in pennyroyal oil is R- (+) Pulegone. </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined">Improvements and other analytical techniques</head><p n="p51.53"><s n="s1.5;p51.53">The experiment can be improved in many ways. </s><s n="s2.5;p51.53">One of which is to undergo the steam distillation for longer which enables the full complete extraction of R- (+) Pulegone to happen. </s><s n="s3.5;p51.53">The purification by column chromatography can be repeated with the multiple fractions that contain the R- (+) Pulegone and another compound. </s><s n="s4.5;p51.53">A less polar solvent e.g.: 50:1 60/ 80 petroleum ether and ethyl acetate can be used to slow down the rate of elution of compounds. </s><s n="s5.5;p51.53">This would improve the quality and the yield. </s></p><p n="p52.53"><s n="s1.13;p52.53">There are many other analytical techniques that could help the characterization of the oil. </s><s n="s2.13;p52.53">One of which was nOe experiment which can help to distinguish <hi rend="bold">H3</hi> and <hi rend="bold">H4</hi>. </s><s n="s3.13;p52.53">Since the major oil is R- (+) Pulegone, it is important to ensure that the right enantiomer was extracted. </s><s n="s4.13;p52.53">Mass spectroscopy (MS) can also be used to analyze the oil as the fragmentation and the molecular weights would give structural information. </s><s n="s5.13;p52.53">GC- MS can identify different compounds and enables a specific compound in a test sample to be analyzed. </s><s n="s6.13;p52.53">This is particularly good as in the sample there are a mixture of substances. </s><s n="s7.13;p52.53">The FT- IR, H NMR and GC used for analysis cannot be used to distinguish different enantiomers. </s><s n="s8.13;p52.53">A polarimeter can be used distinguish between different optical isomers as they would rotate the polarized light at different directions. </s><s n="s9.13;p52.53">R- (+) Pulegone would rotate the polarized light to the right.<hi rend="sup">4</hi> Chiral column chromatography can also be used to distinguish the different enantiomers. </s><s n="s10.13;p52.53">The stationary phase of the column would be chiral instead of achiral so therefore the different enantiomers would elute at different times as their affinities to the stationary phase differ. </s><s n="s11.13;p52.53">Chiral GC would also allow this separation. </s><s n="s12.13;p52.53">Again, a chiral stationary phase would be used which enables the different enantiomers to travel at different rates. </s><s n="s13.13;p52.53">This method would give quantitative results i.e.: the ratio of one enantiomer relative to the other. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined">Conclusions</head><p n="p53.53"><s n="s1.2;p53.53">R- (+) Pulegone has been successfully extracted and isolated from pennyroyal leaves. </s><s n="s2.2;p53.53">However, other compounds were found in the sample so more purification steps such as another column chromatography is needed. </s></p></div1></body><back><div1 type="bibliography"><head rend="underlined">References</head><p><hi rend="sup">1</hi> A, Stoyanova, E. Geodiev, J. Kula, T. Majda, J. Essent. Oil. Res., 2005, 17, 475-476</p><p><hi rend="sup">2</hi> D. H. Williams, I. Fleming, <hi rend="italic">Spectroscopic Methods in Organic Chemistry</hi>, 1995, 5<hi rend="sup">th</hi> ed. McGraw-Hill International (UK) Limited</p><p><hi rend="sup">3</hi> H.E. Gottlieb, Vadim Kotlyar and Abraham Nudelman, <hi rend="italic">J. Org. Chem.</hi> 1997, <hi rend="bold">62</hi>, 7512-7515</p><p>4 Clayden, Greeves, Warren and Wothers, <hi rend="italic">Organic Chemistry</hi>, 2001, Oxford University Press</p></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
