<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_0380b" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Analyse the relationship between prices and theft prosecutions in Elizabethan and Jacobean England.</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">deleted: page numbers</note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">deleted: Word Count - 2, 015</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">3</p><p n="date">2007-03</p><p n="module title">English Communities in Crisis</p><p n="module code">HI375</p><p n="genre family">Essay</p><p n="discipline">History</p><p n="disciplinary group">AH</p><p n="grade">M</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">2027</p><p n="number of s-units">75</p><p n="number of p">11</p><p n="number of tables">0</p><p n="number of figures">0</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">0</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">0</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">27.0</p><p n="average s-units per p">6.8</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">f</p><p n="year of birth">1986</p><p n="first language">English</p><p n="education">UKA</p><p n="course">History</p><p n="student ID">0380</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><titlePart rend="underlined"><name type="student name"/> English Communities in Crisis - short essay 2</titlePart><docTitle><titlePart rend="underlined">Analyse the relationship between prices and theft prosecutions in Elizabethan and Jacobean England. </titlePart></docTitle></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="section"><p n="p1.11"><s n="s1.4;p1.11">There is no doubt that by the end of the sixteenth century, England's criminal courts were busier than ever before.<ref target="BAWE_0380b-ftnote.001"/> Can this be attributed to the fact that the 1590s are seen as the crisis years of the period and therefore rising prices meant more theft for necessity? </s><s n="s2.4;p1.11">Or is the relationship between prices and theft prosecutions in fact not showing more incidence of crime, but simply more prosecutions? </s><s n="s3.4;p1.11">The relationship between prices and theft prosecutions is complex and certainly not direct. </s><s n="s4.4;p1.11">However, it is undeniable that a relationship was present. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0380b-ftnote.001"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Lawson, P.G. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">'Property Crime and Hard Times in England, 1559-1624'<hi rend="italic">, Law &amp; History Review,</hi> 4 (1986) p. 95 </s></p></note><p n="p2.11"><s n="s1.7;p2.11">The prosecution process was very complex and it would be too simple to assume it merely reflected the incidence of crime and there was a simple correlation between prices and theft prosecutions.<ref target="BAWE_0380b-ftnote.002"/> Criminal justice could have been administered differently during periods of dearth. </s><s n="s2.7;p2.11">Lawson argues 'harvest failure invariably promoted fears of social disorder, and it may be that as prices rose constables were more diligent in pursuing suspected thieves and JPs were more inclined to commit theses suspects to trial." </s><ref target="BAWE_0380b-ftnote.003"/><s n="s3.7;p2.11">For example, Wrightson shows that in Essex and Lancashire harvest failure did occasionally provoke bursts of prosecutorial activity.<ref target="BAWE_0380b-ftnote.004"/> In periods of moral panic, deviant behaviour, which is often ignored in normal periods, was prosecuted at a higher rate than usual.<ref target="BAWE_0380b-ftnote.005"/> The peak of prosecutions for major crimes was between 1580 and 1620. </s><s n="s4.7;p2.11">By 1700 there was a massive decline in prosecution levels and a decline in execution rates. </s><s n="s5.7;p2.11">It seems unlikely that there would be such a drop in the incidence of crime. </s><s n="s6.7;p2.11">Therefore, the decline in prosecutions could indicate that the ruling class, who were the magistrates, were less paranoid and saw the poor as less threatening by 1700 perhaps because the new poor law relief system was running across the whole of England and the population had levelled off. </s><s n="s7.7;p2.11">Similarly, the gallows were public exhibitions and were used as a deterrent to others;<ref target="BAWE_0380b-ftnote.006"/> therefore a decline in executions by 1700 would indicate a decline in fear of the incidence of crime. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0380b-ftnote.002"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Lawson, Peter 'Property crime and hard times in England, 1559-1624' p. 97 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0380b-ftnote.003"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid p. 117 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0380b-ftnote.004"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid p. 118 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0380b-ftnote.005"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Sharpe, J.A <hi rend="italic">Crime in Early Modern England 1550-1750</hi> (London, 1999) p.61 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0380b-ftnote.006"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Hindle, Steve <hi rend="italic">The State and Social Change in Early Modern England, c.1550-1640</hi> (London, 2000) p. 132 </s></p></note><p n="p3.11"><s n="s1.8;p3.11">Therefore, increase in theft prosecutions could reflect the change in the formal character of the criminal justice system which occurred in the sixteenth century. </s><s n="s2.8;p3.11">For example, bureaucratization of the courts and changing character of those who administered justice. </s><s n="s3.8;p3.11">The later sixteenth century witnessed a change in the county bench: JPs were more numerous, better educated and better informed. </s><s n="s4.8;p3.11">Sharpe argues that the later sixteenth and early seventeenth centuries were a period of law and order consciousness. </s><s n="s5.8;p3.11">There was a growing determination of the local elites to impose a degree of discipline and order on the labouring poor. </s><s n="s6.8;p3.11">This is mirrored in the workings of the poor laws and poor relief which are increasing in this period. </s><s n="s7.8;p3.11">However, although there was a hardening of attitudes in the legal system, this was probably not great enough to account for the whole increase in the level of theft prosecutions. </s><s n="s8.8;p3.11">Lawson says 'if the attitudes toward crime were changing, this may have been precisely because the level of crime was itself on the rise.' <ref target="BAWE_0380b-ftnote.007"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0380b-ftnote.007"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Lawson, Peter 'Property crime and hard times in England, 1559-1624' p. 126 </s></p></note><p n="p4.11"><s n="s1.5;p4.11">In addition, the English judicial system was a participatory system. </s><s n="s2.5;p4.11">The victims had to make an initial complaint for a prosecution to begin. </s><s n="s3.5;p4.11">During times of crisis, victims may have been less likely to prosecute because of expense. </s><s n="s4.5;p4.11">For example, an initial complaint may have required a journey of several miles and then a trial an even longer journey.<ref target="BAWE_0380b-ftnote.008"/> Victims would have been happier to settle out of court if it meant they got their belongings back and had little expense. </s><s n="s5.5;p4.11">Similarly, in times of dearth victims would not want to see their neighbours hung, thus as punishments were often harsher in times of crisis, as shown with the rise of executions, this could have been another motivate not to prosecute.<ref target="BAWE_0380b-ftnote.009"/> Therefore, if victims were less likely to prosecute, but there were more prosecutions there may have been more incidence of crime. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0380b-ftnote.008"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Sharpe <hi rend="italic">Crime in Early Modern England 1550-1750</hi> p.64 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0380b-ftnote.009"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid p.68 </s></p></note><p n="p5.11"><s n="s1.7;p5.11">Lawson certainly believes that the change in criminal prosecutions could reflect an actual change in criminal behaviour, therefore more stealing was actually taking place. </s><s n="s2.7;p5.11">The state of the Elizabethan economy would support this view: by the 1580s war, plague, industrial stagnation and harvest failure all combined to create rising levels of poverty.<ref target="BAWE_0380b-ftnote.010"/> Lawson uses the word 'necessity' to describe the nature of theft during economic hardship. </s><s n="s3.7;p5.11">Rising food prices would have created hardship because ninety percent of a labourer's income was spent on food and drink. </s><s n="s4.7;p5.11">Therefore, Hoskins suggests the use of wheat prices as an economic indicator. </s><s n="s5.7;p5.11">Despite Appleby's claim that by the end of the sixteenth century the poor ate cheaper grains like oats, it seems likely that Hoskin's suggestion of using wheat prices would probably be an accurate guide to fluctuations in other grain prices.<ref target="BAWE_0380b-ftnote.011"/> For example, Underdown shows that as the price of wheat rose in Dorchester between 1630 and 1631, there was a sharp rise in the number of cases of theft reported. </s><s n="s6.7;p5.11">Underdown suggests this indicates the desperation of the poor.<ref target="BAWE_0380b-ftnote.012"/> Cockburn claims that 'price trends bear a fairly close relationship to the pattern of property crime." </s><ref target="BAWE_0380b-ftnote.013"/><s n="s7.7;p5.11">All three sudden upsurges of indicted theft during Elizabeth's reign were periods of scarcity. <ref target="BAWE_0380b-ftnote.014"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0380b-ftnote.010"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Lawson 'Property crime and hard times in England, 1559-1624' p. 96 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0380b-ftnote.011"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid p. 98 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0380b-ftnote.012"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Underdown, David <hi rend="italic">Fire From Heaven: Life in an English Town in the Seventeenth Century</hi> (London, 1992) p. 87 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0380b-ftnote.013"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Cockburn, J.S. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">'The Nature and Incidence of Crime in England, 1559-1625: A Preliminary Survey', in J.S. Cockburn (ed.), <hi rend="italic">Crime in England, 1550-1800</hi> (London, 1977) p. 69 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0380b-ftnote.014"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Cockburn 'The Nature and Incidence of Crime in England, 1559-1625: A Preliminary Survey' p. 67 </s></p></note><p n="p6.11"><s n="s1.10;p6.11">Generally in the two periods crime was opportunistic and relating to people's current economic status. </s><s n="s2.10;p6.11">Sharpe comments that 'for every Jonathan Wild or Jack Sheppard<ref target="BAWE_0380b-ftnote.015"/> there might well have been a thousand opportunistic pickpockets or shoplifters, concerned with immediate survival rather than running a criminal enterprise." </s><ref target="BAWE_0380b-ftnote.016"/><s n="s3.10;p6.11">There was little professional crime, with few traces of a 'criminal subculture'. </s><s n="s4.10;p6.11">Two thieves caught in Warwick in 1580 confessed to stealing ducks, geese and pigs on their travels. </s><s n="s5.10;p6.11">They either ate them themselves or bartered them for lodgings.<ref target="BAWE_0380b-ftnote.017"/> Therefore, in times of high prices the opportunity for theft rose because of necessity. </s><s n="s6.10;p6.11">However, generally stealing would be a last resort. </s><s n="s7.10;p6.11">The poorer sort may change their diet to cheaper foods such as beans and peas. </s><s n="s8.10;p6.11">Similarly, they may have turned to private charity or statutory relief.<ref target="BAWE_0380b-ftnote.018"/> However, these alternatives could not provide complete support for all those affected by rising prices and declining wages which so often accompanied it. </s><s n="s9.10;p6.11">Lawson argues that 'theft was simply one of several alternative means of survival, and given the possible penalties it was probably the least satisfactory. </s><s n="s10.10;p6.11">But as other alternatives disappeared, theft must have become...a real possibility.' <ref target="BAWE_0380b-ftnote.019"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0380b-ftnote.015"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Criminal entrepreneurs with legendary status </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0380b-ftnote.016"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Sharpe <hi rend="italic">Crime in Early Modern England 1550-1750</hi> p. 169 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0380b-ftnote.017"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid p. 144 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0380b-ftnote.018"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Lawson 'Property crime and hard times in England, 1559-1624' p. 106 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0380b-ftnote.019"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid p. 107 </s></p></note><p n="p7.11"><s n="s1.7;p7.11">The example of Hertfordshire illustrates that the relationship between prices and theft prosecution was positive. </s><s n="s2.7;p7.11">Prosecution levels were higher in years of high prices than they were in years of low prices. </s><s n="s3.7;p7.11">This would suggest that rising food prices were potentially 'criminogenic'.<ref target="BAWE_0380b-ftnote.020"/> Cockburn agrees that theft was a socio-economic phenomenon.<ref target="BAWE_0380b-ftnote.021"/> An example of this relationship between prices and theft is illustrated in 1612 when grain prices began to rise and remained high for four years. </s><s n="s4.7;p7.11">This continued persistence of high prices led to hardship, which in turn led to theft as shown by the peak of prosecutions in Herfordshire being in 1612-1617.<ref target="BAWE_0380b-ftnote.022"/> However, chronology was not always exact. </s><s n="s5.7;p7.11">Lawson argues that 'not only did prosecution levels often begin to climb only after prices, but in some cases they reached their peak slightly later." </s><ref target="BAWE_0380b-ftnote.023"/><s n="s6.7;p7.11">For example, in the 1620s in Hertfordshire and Sussex, prices and prosecution levels were moving in opposite directions creating negative coefficients.<ref target="BAWE_0380b-ftnote.024"/> This perhaps indicates that the relationship between theft prosecutions and prices was nonlinear and that it was not equally strong throughout the period as a whole. </s><s n="s7.7;p7.11">Therefore, where high prices might mean more prosecutions, low prices did not necessarily mean low rates of prosecution. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0380b-ftnote.020"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Lawson 'Property crime and hard times in England, 1559-1624' p. 104 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0380b-ftnote.021"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Cockburn 'The Nature and Incidence of Crime in England, 1559-1625: A Preliminary Survey'p. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">60 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0380b-ftnote.022"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Lawson 'Property crime and hard times in England, 1559-1624' p. 110 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0380b-ftnote.023"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid p. 109 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0380b-ftnote.024"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid p. 112 </s></p></note><p n="p8.11"><s n="s1.5;p8.11">There is a lag between prices and prosecutions most notable during the final crisis years in James' era. </s><s n="s2.5;p8.11">This lag could be a by-product of migration, which generally rose in years of economic crisis. </s><s n="s3.5;p8.11">Migrants may have turned to thieving to help them move around. </s><s n="s4.5;p8.11">Thus, even after prices fell, counties with high migration levels may have still experienced high theft from impoverished migrants who finally crossed their borders.<ref target="BAWE_0380b-ftnote.025"/> This is supported by an increase in the level of prosecutions for squatting and vagrancy in the last decade of the sixteenth century in Hertfordshire.<ref target="BAWE_0380b-ftnote.026"/> For example, William Westfeedle was apprehended in 1598 in Walkern for stealing bread, butter and a pie. </s><s n="s5.5;p8.11">He claimed to have been working in Essex but lost his job and had been unable to find replacement work and had been ''driven by necessitie to search for foode.''<ref target="BAWE_0380b-ftnote.027"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0380b-ftnote.025"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid p. 113 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0380b-ftnote.026"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid p. 121 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0380b-ftnote.027"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">H. R. O in Lawson 'Property crime and hard times in England, 1559-1624' p. 122 </s></p></note><p n="p9.11"><s n="s1.10;p9.11">However, Lawson claims that court records showing these prosecution rates are ambiguous and do not measure absolute crime levels.<ref target="BAWE_0380b-ftnote.028"/> For example, for occupation of the criminal vagrant is rarely stated: instead labourer is written. </s><s n="s2.10;p9.11">This does not mean most of the criminals were labourers; it simply means vagrancy was a crime in itself, so the term could not be used in formal legal records. </s><s n="s3.10;p9.11">Another problem is the incomplete records. </s><s n="s4.10;p9.11">It would be impossible to find all the records from all the courts in all the counties to contemplate the complete relationship between prices and theft prosecution across the whole of England.<ref target="BAWE_0380b-ftnote.029"/> Cockburn continues that fluctuations in grain prices did not produce identical changes in the indictment of theft in adjacent counties of Essex and Hertfordshire.<ref target="BAWE_0380b-ftnote.030"/> In addition, bad harvest might affect proto-industrial areas in Essex more than on upland pastoral farming areas.<ref target="BAWE_0380b-ftnote.031"/> Similarly, theft levels depended on the effectiveness of early-Stuart social policy: the Poor Laws and Book of Orders.<ref target="BAWE_0380b-ftnote.032"/> If these worked effectively the incidence of theft may have been lowered in times of high prices. </s><s n="s5.10;p9.11">However, a positive characteristic of these court records is their 'accidental' nature. </s><s n="s6.10;p9.11">Their usefulness lies in the fact nobody wrote them for historians. </s><s n="s7.10;p9.11">However, the records should not be relied on as gospel. </s><s n="s8.10;p9.11">It would be unwise to assume they include every record of cases that were tried. </s><s n="s9.10;p9.11">However, they are useful if all this is taken into account. </s><s n="s10.10;p9.11">Hindle argues that 'overall fluctuations in the trend of indictment must bear a close, if complex relationship to actual criminal behaviour.' <ref target="BAWE_0380b-ftnote.033"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0380b-ftnote.028"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Lawson, Peter 'Property crime and hard times in England, 1559-1624' p. 97 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0380b-ftnote.029"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Lawson 'Property crime and hard times in England, 1559-1624' p. 100, Sharpe p. 170 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0380b-ftnote.030"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Cockburn 'The Nature and Incidence of Crime in England, 1559-1625: A Preliminary Survey' p. 88 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0380b-ftnote.031"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid p. 89 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0380b-ftnote.032"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Hindle <hi rend="italic">The State and Social Change in Early Modern England, c.1550-1640</hi> p. 128 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0380b-ftnote.033"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid p. 126 </s></p></note><p n="p10.11"><s n="s1.8;p10.11">The relationship between prices and theft prosecutions differed in the Elizabethan and Jacobean periods, with the relationship being stronger in the Elizabethan period. </s><s n="s2.8;p10.11">During the two periods there are anomalies between the correlations between the two variables. </s><s n="s3.8;p10.11">One reason for this could be that by the Jacobean period, population growth was slowing, wages were rising, there were improvements in agriculture, and thus perhaps as the century progressed short-term crises were less severe because the population were less vulnerable. </s><s n="s4.8;p10.11">Therefore, harvest crises and rising food prices would have a less dramatic effect on theft, meaning a weaker relationship between the two variables. </s><s n="s5.8;p10.11">In addition, Beattie and Hay argue that the Elizabethan period was affected by demobilisation bringing a large number of soldiers back to a labour market that failed to re-absorb them. </s><s n="s6.8;p10.11">The influx of discharged servicemen resulted in economic hardship and an increase in theft. </s><s n="s7.8;p10.11">England was involved in foreign wars during the latter part of the Elizabethan period 1585 to 1604.<ref target="BAWE_0380b-ftnote.034"/> Lambard argues that when a soldier returns from war he will be 'either an impudent beggar or an errant thief." </s><ref target="BAWE_0380b-ftnote.035"/><s n="s8.8;p10.11">Lawson and Cockburn use tables of Hertfordshire, Surrey, Kent and Sussex to clearly illustrate that the relationship between prices and theft prosecutions were uniformly strengthened when war was added to the crisis of high prices. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0380b-ftnote.034"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Lawson, Peter 'Property crime and hard times in England, 1559-1624' p. 114 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0380b-ftnote.035"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Lambard in Lawson, Peter 'Property crime and hard times in England, 1559-1624' p. 115 </s></p></note><p n="p11.11"><s n="s1.4;p11.11">Overall, it is questionable whether the short term peak of prosecutions in the 1590s and 1620s 'reflects the driving force of hunger...the fear of the poor encouraged prosecutions cases which were normally ignored or whether loss of goods hurt more when supplies were short?" </s><ref target="BAWE_0380b-ftnote.036"/><s n="s2.4;p11.11">There was definitely some interaction between the three variables; however it is probable that the wave of prosecutions do reflect peaks of theft in times of high prices. </s><s n="s3.4;p11.11">In addition, it was not only short-term crisis that effected this relationship, a longer, more deep-seated crisis of deteriorating living standards of the labouring classes lead to an increase in poverty and an increase in theft.<ref target="BAWE_0380b-ftnote.037"/> The relationship between prices and theft prosecutions in Elizabethan and Jacobean England was not direct, because many aspects need to be considered for example, the attitude of the victim and priorities of local charities. </s><s n="s4.4;p11.11">However, it is undeniable that a positive relationship exists between high prices and theft prosecutions. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0380b-ftnote.036"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Hindle <hi rend="italic"> The State and Social Change in Early Modern England, c.1550-1640</hi> p. 127 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0380b-ftnote.037"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Lawson, Peter 'Property crime and hard times in England, 1559-1624' p. 127 </s></p></note></div1></body><back><div1 type="bibliography"><head rend="underlined">Bibliography</head><p>Cockburn, J.S. 'The Nature and Incidence of Crime in England, 1559-1625: A Preliminary Survey', in J.S. Cockburn (ed.), <hi rend="italic">Crime in England, 1550-1800</hi> (London, 1977).</p><p>Gaskill, Malcolm <hi rend="italic">Crime and Mentalities in Early Modern England</hi> (Cambridge, 2000).</p><p>Hindle, Steve <hi rend="italic">The State and Social Change in Early Modern England, c.1550-1640</hi> (London, 2000).</p><p>Lawson, P.G. 'Property Crime and Hard Times in England, 1559-1624'<hi rend="italic">, Law &amp; History Review,</hi> 4 (1986) pp. 95-127.</p><p>Sharpe, J.A <hi rend="italic">Crime in Early Modern England 1550-1750</hi> (London, 1999).</p><p>Underdown, David <hi rend="italic"> Fire From Heaven: Life in an English Town in the Seventeenth Century</hi> (London, 1992).</p></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
