<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_0381a" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Experiment P6: The reaction between hydrogen iodide and hydrogen peroxide: The Harcourt-Essen reaction</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">deleted: footer: student name, course and year, page numbers</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">1</p><p n="date">2007-02</p><p n="module title">Physical Lab</p><p n="module code">CH155</p><p n="genre family">Methodology recount</p><p n="discipline">Chemistry</p><p n="disciplinary group">PS</p><p n="grade">D</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">1181</p><p n="number of s-units">72</p><p n="number of p">47</p><p n="number of tables">7</p><p n="number of figures">6</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">19</p><p n="number of lists">3</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">2</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">16.4</p><p n="average s-units per p">1.5</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">f</p><p n="year of birth">1981</p><p n="first language">English</p><p n="education">UKA</p><p n="course">Mchem</p><p n="student ID">0381</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><docTitle><titlePart rend="underlined">Experiment P6: The reaction between hydrogen iodide and hydrogen peroxide: The Harcourt-Essen reaction</titlePart></docTitle><titlePart><hi rend="bold">Date:</hi> 23 February 2007 <hi rend="bold"> Partner: </hi><name type="student name"/></titlePart></titlePage><div1 type="front text"><p><hi rend="bold">Aim:</hi> To investigate the effect of temperature and iodide concentration on the rate of the Harcourt-Essen reaction and so determine the order, rate constant and Arrhenius parameters.</p></div1></front><body><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Introduction</head><p n="p1.47"><s n="s1.1;p1.47">The overall Harcourt - Essen reaction is: <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0381a-form.001"/> </s></p><p n="p2.47"><s n="s1.1;p2.47">with a proposed mechanism of bimolecular steps: </s></p><list type="ordered"><item><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0381a-form.002"/> fast (i)</item><item><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0381a-form.003"/> slow (ii)</item><item><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0381a-form.004"/> fast (iii)</item><item><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0381a-form.005"/> fast (iv)</item></list><p n="p3.47"><s n="s1.1;p3.47">The differential rate equation is then: </s></p><p n="p4.47"><s n="s1.1;p4.47"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0381a-form.006"/> </s></p><p n="p5.47"><s n="s1.2;p5.47">The slow, rate determining step was investigated by measuring the rate of loss of hydrogen peroxide, this being proportional to d[H <hi rend="sub">3</hi>O <hi rend="sub">2</hi>+] / dt. </s><s n="s2.2;p5.47">Any iodine formed was reconverted to iodide by addition of thiosulphate (see method): </s></p><p n="p6.47"><s n="s1.1;p6.47"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0381a-form.007"/> </s></p><p n="p7.47"><s n="s1.1;p7.47">Therefore [I-] was kept approximately constant and pseudo-first order kinetics could be assumed: </s></p><p n="p8.47"><s n="s1.1;p8.47"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0381a-form.008"/> </s></p><p n="p9.47"><s n="s1.1;p9.47">The integrated rate equation for such a first order reaction is: </s></p><p n="p10.47"><s n="s1.1;p10.47"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0381a-form.009"/> </s></p><p n="p11.47"><s n="s1.2;p11.47">Plotting the natural logarithm of the initial [H2O2] divided by [H2O2] at each time interval, against time would yield a straight line of gradient k'. </s><s n="s2.2;p11.47">Knowing the amount of I- used, k can be found. </s></p><p n="p12.47"><s n="s1.1;p12.47">By repeating the experiment at various temperatures, the Arrhenius parameters of the Harcourt-Essen reaction can be determined: </s></p><p n="p13.47"><s n="s1.2;p13.47">k = A exp(-E/RT) where E is the activation energy, A the pre-exponential constant, R the gas constant and T the temperature in Kelvin. </s><s n="s2.2;p13.47">Linearising: </s></p><p n="p14.47"><s n="s1.1;p14.47"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0381a-form.010"/> </s></p><p n="p15.47"><s n="s1.1;p15.47">Therefore a plot of lnk (for each temperature) against 1/T enables calculation of A and E. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Experimental - Method</head><p n="p16.47"><s n="s1.1;p16.47">4 different runs of the experiment were carried out sequentially using: </s></p><list type="simple"><item><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0381a-form.011"/></item><item><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0381a-form.012"/></item><item>Approx 4vol H <hi rend="sub">2</hi>O <hi rend="sub">2 </hi></item><item>Sulphuric acid (1 part acid: 5 parts water) </item></list><table id="BAWE_0381a-tab.001"><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p17.47"><s n="s1.2;p17.47">Solutions were kept in thermostatted water baths for 15 mins for temperature equilibration and mixed vigorously and continuously. </s><s n="s2.2;p17.47">10 drops starch indicator were added to each mixture. </s></p><p n="p18.47"><s n="s1.5;p18.47">H <hi rend="sub">2</hi>O <hi rend="sub">2</hi> (25cm <hi rend="sup">3</hi>, 4vol.) was kept in a separate flask at the required temperature, prior to addition. </s><s n="s2.5;p18.47">Sodium thiosulphate (1.5cm <hi rend="sup">3</hi>, 0.094M) was added to the iodide/acid mixture, then the H <hi rend="sub">2</hi>O <hi rend="sub">2</hi> and a stopclock started. </s><s n="s3.5;p18.47">When the starch indicator turned green/blue, the time was noted and 0.5cm <hi rend="sup">3</hi> thiosulphate added. </s><s n="s4.5;p18.47">This was repeated until 9cm <hi rend="sup">3</hi> of thiosulphate had been added. </s><s n="s5.5;p18.47">The reaction flask was kept to one side for later use. </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p19.47"><s n="s1.3;p19.47"><hi rend="bold">Note 1</hi>: the blue colour was due to iodine complexing with starch; the iodine being formed by H <hi rend="sub">2</hi>O <hi rend="sub">2</hi> oxidising I- and so being consumed. </s><s n="s2.3;p19.47">The immediate addition of thiosulphate reduced the iodine back to I- rendering the solution colourless again until more H <hi rend="sub">2</hi>O <hi rend="sub">2</hi> oxidised I- to reform iodine. </s><s n="s3.3;p19.47">Thus the cumulative volume of thiosulphate was inversely proportional to the concentration of H <hi rend="sub">2</hi>O <hi rend="sub">2</hi> remaining in the reaction flask. </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p20.47"><s n="s1.1;p20.47"><hi rend="bold">Note 2:</hi> Towards the end of run 2, the appearance of the blue/green colour was not so sharp, so the individual error in time recorded will be greatest here. </s></p><p n="p21.47"><s n="s1.1;p21.47">By the time all 4 runs had been completed (~2hrs) reaction flask 1 was assumed to have gone to completion and reaction flask 3 (left standing for 1.25 hours) was heated in a 45 <hi rend="sup">o</hi>C water bath for 20mins to achieve completion, i.e all H <hi rend="sub">2</hi>O <hi rend="sub">2</hi> used up. </s></p><p n="p22.47"><s n="s1.2;p22.47">Reaction flasks 1 &amp; 2 were simultaneously titrated with sodium thiosulphate in 0.5cm <hi rend="sup">3</hi> portions as before until no blue/green colour appeared for 20minutes. </s><s n="s2.2;p22.47">The final thiosulphate titre volume was proportional to the initial concentration of peroxide: [H <hi rend="sub">2</hi>O <hi rend="sub">2</hi>]<hi rend="sub">t=0</hi> </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Experimental - Result</head><table id="BAWE_0381a-tab.002"><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p23.47"><s n="s1.1;p23.47"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0381a-form.013"/> and <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0381a-form.014"/> </s></p><p n="p24.47"><s n="s1.2;p24.47">Therefore, H <hi rend="sub">2</hi>O <hi rend="sub">2:</hi> S <hi rend="sub">2</hi>O <hi rend="sub">3</hi><hi rend="sup">2-</hi> ratio is 1:2mol. </s><s n="s2.2;p24.47">S <hi rend="sub">2</hi>O <hi rend="sub">3</hi><hi rend="sup">2-</hi> used=15.6/1000*0.99 =1.55*10 <hi rend="sup">-2</hi> </s></p><p n="p25.47"><s n="s1.2;p25.47">Therefore mol. </s><s n="s2.2;p25.47">H <hi rend="sub">2</hi>O <hi rend="sub">2</hi> in 25cm <hi rend="sup">3</hi>= 7.753*10 <hi rend="sup">-3</hi><hi rend="bold">[H2O2]</hi> =(7.753*10 <hi rend="sup">-3</hi>)/25*1000 = <hi rend="bold">0.3101M</hi> </s></p><p n="p26.47"><s n="s1.1;p26.47">In the table below: A is equivalent to [H <hi rend="sub">2</hi>O <hi rend="sub">2</hi>]<hi rend="sub">t=0</hi> , x is the vol. of S <hi rend="sub">2</hi>O <hi rend="sub">3</hi> added </s></p><p n="p27.47"><s n="s1.1;p27.47">c is equivalent to [H <hi rend="sub">2</hi>O <hi rend="sub">2</hi>]<hi rend="sub">t</hi> which is A-x </s></p><p n="p28.47"><s n="s1.1;p28.47">For a plot of c <hi rend="sup">-1</hi> against time, a straight line would indicate a second order reaction w.r.t to peroxide since for: </s></p><p n="p29.47"><s n="s1.1;p29.47"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0381a-form.015"/> </s></p><p n="p30.47"><s n="s1.1;p30.47"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0381a-form.016"/> when integrated. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0381a-fig.001"/><p n="p31.47"><s n="s1.1;p31.47">Looking closely at the above graph, the relationship between c <hi rend="sup">-1</hi> and time is not linear but an upward curve and so the Harcourt-Essen reaction is not 2 <hi rend="sup">nd</hi> w.r.t to peroxide. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0381a-fig.002"/><p n="p32.47"><s n="s1.1;p32.47">Plotting ln(A/c) against 1/time: </s></p><p n="p33.47"><s n="s1.2;p33.47">There is a clear linear correlation corresponding to first order kinetics w.r.t peroxide. </s><s n="s2.2;p33.47">Similarly for the runs 2,3 and 4: </s></p><table id="BAWE_0381a-tab.003"><row><cell/></row></table><figure id="BAWE_0381a-fig.003"/><table id="BAWE_0381a-tab.004"><row><cell/></row></table><figure id="BAWE_0381a-fig.004"/><table id="BAWE_0381a-tab.005"><row><cell/></row></table><figure id="BAWE_0381a-fig.005"/><p n="p34.47"><s n="s1.1;p34.47">The gradient of each graph gives k', the pseudo-first order rate constant where k'=k[I-] </s></p><p n="p35.47"><s n="s1.2;p35.47">k is calculated in the table below. </s><s n="s2.2;p35.47"><hi rend="bold">Note:</hi> values for k' calculated in MS Excel to more significant figures than shown in the above graphs. </s></p><table id="BAWE_0381a-tab.006"><row><cell/></row></table><list type="simple"><head>Where: total vol. in each reaction flask = 250cm <hi rend="sup">3</hi> (ignoring 10 starch drops)</head><item> Mol. I- in 250cm <hi rend="sup">3</hi> = Vol KI/ 1000 * 0.04819</item><item> [I-] = 4* mol. I- in 250cm3</item><item> k' is regression coefficient calculate in MS Excel</item></list><p n="p36.47"><s n="s1.2;p36.47">Run 2 has half the concentration of iodide as Run 1;both at the same temperature, and k' is almost half, within limits of experimental error. </s><s n="s2.2;p36.47">This is consistent with a directly proportional relationship between rate and iodide concentration and so the reaction is also 1 <hi rend="sup">st</hi> order w.r.t to iodide. </s></p><p n="p37.47"><s n="s1.2;p37.47">Runs 3 and 4, at higher temperatures, show faster rates. </s><s n="s2.2;p37.47">The empirical rule of an approximate doubling of rate for every 10 <hi rend="sup">o</hi>c increase in temperature seems borne out by the values of k for runs 1 and 4:8.68/4.31 = 2.014 </s></p><p n="p38.47"><s n="s1.1;p38.47">The following table sets out the data needed to calculate Arrhenius parameters: </s></p><table id="BAWE_0381a-tab.007"><row><cell/></row></table><figure id="BAWE_0381a-fig.006"/><p n="p39.47"><s n="s1.1;p39.47"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0381a-form.017"/> </s></p><p n="p40.47"><s n="s1.1;p40.47">Gradient of regression line = -E/R where R=8.31451 JK <hi rend="sup">-1</hi>mol <hi rend="sup">-1</hi> </s></p><p n="p41.47"><s n="s1.1;p41.47"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0381a-form.018"/> </s></p><p n="p42.47"><s n="s1.1;p42.47">Intercept of regression line = lnA </s></p><p n="p43.47"><s n="s1.1;p43.47"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0381a-form.019"/> </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Conclusions and Discussion</head><p n="p44.47"><s n="s1.2;p44.47">During all 4 runs, the concentration of iodide can be assumed to be constant due to the regular addition of thiosulphate, so reducing the iodine formed back to iodide. </s><s n="s2.2;p44.47">Therefore, assuming the rate determining step involves no other species than H <hi rend="sub">3</hi>O <hi rend="sub">2</hi>+ and I-, the straight line graph of ln(A/c) against time for all 4 runs, shows 1st order w.r.t H <hi rend="sub">3</hi>O <hi rend="sub">2</hi>+ (=H <hi rend="sub">2</hi>O <hi rend="sub">2</hi>). </s></p><p n="p45.47"><s n="s1.2;p45.47">Runs 1 and 2 (half the iodide concentration, half the pseudo-first order rate constant) showed the reaction to be 1 <hi rend="sup">st</hi> order w.r.t to I- and thus, 2nd order overall. </s><s n="s2.2;p45.47">The mechanism discussed in the introduction is a valid proposal. </s></p><p n="p46.47"><s n="s1.5;p46.47">The difficulty in determining the initial concentration of peroxide will have been a significant source of error for the actual [H <hi rend="sub">2</hi>O <hi rend="sub">2</hi>] calculation. </s><s n="s2.5;p46.47">Reaction flask 1 had been left to stand for 2 hours, and flask 3 for 1.25 hours as well as being heated for 20mins. </s><s n="s3.5;p46.47">It was assumed all the peroxide had been used up by then. </s><s n="s4.5;p46.47">However, during this 'infinite time' titration, even after periods as long as 20mins, the blue colour would reappear; due to time limits in the laboratory, there had to be a cut-off point. </s><s n="s5.5;p46.47">This would not affect the values of the calculated rate constant since the gradient of ln(A/c) against time will have been the same. </s></p><p n="p47.47"><s n="s1.3;p47.47">The linear regression equation used for calculating the Arrhenius parameters was based on 3 measurements. </s><s n="s2.3;p47.47">For a more precise and accurate determination of the collision frequency factor A, and activation energy E, the experiment would need to be repeated at many more temperatures. </s><s n="s3.3;p47.47">This would allow for statistically meaningful confidence intervals to be measured for each parameter. </s></p></div1></body><back/></text></TEI.2>
