<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_0382a" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Living Radical Polymerization</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">deleted: page numbers</note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">laid out as journal article</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">3</p><p n="date">2005-03</p><p n="module title">Macro Lab</p><p n="module code">CH3C6</p><p n="genre family">Methodology recount</p><p n="discipline">Chemistry</p><p n="disciplinary group">PS</p><p n="grade">D</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">1528</p><p n="number of s-units">53</p><p n="number of p">27</p><p n="number of tables">9</p><p n="number of figures">8</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">4</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">0</p><p n="abstract present">abstract present</p><p n="average words per s-unit">28.8</p><p n="average s-units per p">2.0</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">m</p><p n="year of birth">1983</p><p n="first language">English</p><p n="education">UKA</p><p n="course">Mchem</p><p n="student ID">0382</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><docTitle><titlePart rend="bold">Living Radical Polymerization</titlePart></docTitle><titlePart><hi rend="bold"><name type="student name"/></hi><hi rend="italic"> University Of <name type="university"/>, <name type="other"/>, UK<name type="other"/></hi><hi rend="bold"> Received Date May 2005</hi></titlePart></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="abstract"><head rend="bold">ABSTRACT</head><p n="p1.27"><s rend="bold" n="s1.3;p1.27">This experiment involves the preparation of two different ligands and an initiator for transition metal mediated radical polymerization/atom transfer radical polymerization (ATRP). </s><s rend="bold" n="s2.3;p1.27">These products will then be used in polymerization reactions to prepare 5 polymers with a range of different methods. </s><s rend="bold" n="s3.3;p1.27">Comparison of these 5 polymers will be made to determine the effects of changing the metal binding ligand and changing the addition time of the monomers to the rate of the reaction. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">1. Experimental</head><figure id="BAWE_0382a-fig.001"><head rend="italic">i) Octyl Ligand Synthesis (5C):</head></figure><p n="p2.27"><s n="s1.2;p2.27">To a stirred solution of pyridine-2-carboxaldehyde (0.15mol, 14.270mL) in diethylether (15mL) cooled in an ice bath was added excess octylamine (0.19mol, 20mL) drop wise. </s><s n="s2.2;p2.27">After complete addition of amine, anhydrous magnesium sulphate was added, and slurry stirred for two </s></p><p n="p3.27"><s n="s1.3;p3.27">hours at 25 <hi rend="sup">o</hi>C. The solution was filtered, solvent removed and product purified by distillation under reduced pressure, with lagging. </s><s n="s2.3;p3.27">First few mL collected at 80 <hi rend="sup">o</hi>C was discarded. </s><s n="s3.3;p3.27">Yellow oil collected at 125 <hi rend="sup">o</hi>C. </s></p><list type="simple"><item>Yield: 14.42g, 66mmol, 44%</item><item><hi rend="sup">1</hi>H NMR (CDCl <hi rend="sub">3</hi>): 8.55 (s, 1H) 8.30 (s, 1H) 7.90 (m, 1H) 7.65 (m, 1H) 7.20 (m, 1H) 3.60 (m, 2H) 1.75 (s, 2H) 1.25 (m, 10H) 0.85 (m, 3H).</item><item><hi rend="sup">13</hi>C NMR (CDCl <hi rend="sub">3</hi>): 161.5, 154.7 149.3 136.3 124.4, 121.1, {71.5, 77.2, 76.8 - impurities) 61.5, 31.8, 30.6, 29.3, 29.2, 27.3, 22.6, 14.0.</item><item>IR: 2925-2854 (Vsaturated CH stretchs) 1649 cm-1 (VC=N) </item></list><figure id="BAWE_0382a-fig.002"><head rend="italic">ii) Propyl Ligand Synthesis (5A and 5B):</head></figure><p n="p4.27"><s n="s1.1;p4.27">The method is the same as for the Octyl ligand, however with the following changes: </s></p><list type="simple"><item>(0.2mol, 21.42g) Pyridine-2-carboxaldehyde</item><item>(0.24mol, 20mL) excess n-propylamine </item></list><list type="simple"><item>Yield: 81.5%</item><item><hi rend="sup">1</hi>H NMR (CDCl <hi rend="sub">3</hi>): 8.5 (d, 1H), 8.25 (s, 1H), 7.85 (d, 1H), 7.55 (t, 1H), 7.1 (q, 1H), 3.5 (t, 2H), 1.6 (m, 2H), 0.85 (t, 3H)</item><item><hi rend="sup">13</hi>C NMR (CDCl <hi rend="sub">3</hi>): 161.567, 154.583, 149.251, 136.302, 124.407, 124.407, 121, 022, 63.144, 23.744, and 11.2</item><item>IR: 2961-2874 (V <hi rend="sub">saturated CH stretchs</hi>) 1649 cm <hi rend="sup">-1</hi> (<hi rend="italic">VC=N) </hi></item></list><figure id="BAWE_0382a-fig.003"><head rend="italic"> iii) 2-Methyl Phenol Initiator Synthesis (5D and 5E):</head></figure><p n="p5.27"><s n="s1.5;p5.27">2-methyl phenol (5.07g), triethylamine (6.2mL), DCM (200mL) and acid bromide (15.98g) were stirred for 1 hour. </s><s n="s2.5;p5.27">The solution was then washed twice with water (200mL) and then twice with saturated sodium carbonate (200mL). </s><s n="s3.5;p5.27">Then finally washed with dilute HCl, which was made up by using HCl (2M) and diluting with water in a ratio of 1:2000 resulting in a HCl concentration of 0.001 mol dm <hi rend="sup">-3</hi>. </s><s n="s4.5;p5.27">A flash column was then used to remove any impurities using toluene as the solvent. </s><s n="s5.5;p5.27">The resulting solution was rotary evaporated to remove the solvent. </s></p><p n="p6.27"><s n="s1.1;p6.27">Yield: 10.9g, 42mmol, 90.5% </s></p><p n="p7.27"><s n="s1.1;p7.27">IR: </s></p><table id="BAWE_0382a-tab.001"><head><hi rend="bold">Table 1</hi> . A table of the IR absorption peaks for the initiator.</head><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p8.27"><s n="s1.1;p8.27"><hi rend="sup">1</hi>H NMR: </s></p><table id="BAWE_0382a-tab.002"><head><hi rend="bold">Table 2</hi> . A table of the <hi rend="sup">1</hi> H NMR chemical shifts for the initiator.</head><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p9.27"><s n="s1.1;p9.27"><hi rend="sup">13</hi>C NMR: </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0382a-fig.004"/><table id="BAWE_0382a-tab.003"><head><hi rend="bold">Table 3</hi> . A table of the <hi rend="sup">13</hi> C NMR absorption peaks for the initiator.</head><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p10.27"><s n="s1.1;p10.27">Toluene carbon shifts present at: 21.52, 125.36, 128.29, 129.09. </s></p><p n="p11.27"><s n="s1.1;p11.27">Acid anhydride carbon shifts present at: 30.05, 165.80. </s></p><p n="p12.27"><s n="s1.1;p12.27">Acid bromide carbon shifts present at: 31.09, 170.50. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">2. Polymer Synthesis:</head><p n="p13.27"><s n="s1.1;p13.27">The 5 polymers were made with a mixture of the reactants previously mentioned and a mixture of either methyl methacrylate (MMA), butyl methyacrylate (BMA) and benzyl methacrylate (BzMA) to produce a block copolymer or a single component polymer: </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0382a-fig.005"><head rend="italic">Step I - </head></figure><figure id="BAWE_0382a-fig.006"><head rend="italic">Step II -</head></figure><list type="ordered"><item>5A - 10mL of MMA and was left overnight with propyl ligand.</item><item>5B - 10mL of MMA and was left overnight with octyl ligand.</item><item>5C - 10mL of MMA and was left for 2 hours prior to adding 10mL BzMA with propyl ligand.</item><item>5D - 10mL of MMA and was left for 4 hours prior to adding 10mL BzMA with propyl ligand.</item><item>5E - 10mL of BMA and was left overnight with propyl ligand.</item></list><div2><head rend="italic">i) Block Polymer (5D) synthesis:</head><div3><head rend="italic">Step I:</head><p n="p14.27"><s n="s1.4;p14.27">To a solution of MMA (deoxygenated) (10mL) and toluene (deoxygenated) (20mL) was added Cu(I)Br (0.136g), 2-methyl phenol initiator (0.242g) and the propyl ligand (0.277g) respectively. </s><s n="s2.4;p14.27">This solution was mixed at 90 <hi rend="sup">o</hi>C in an inert atmosphere. </s><s n="s3.4;p14.27">After 2 hours of the reaction had passed, a sample was removed from the mixture and a <hi rend="sup">1</hi>H NMR and GPC were recorded. </s><s n="s4.4;p14.27">This was repeated again after 4 hours. </s></p></div3><div3><head rend="italic">Step II:</head><p n="p15.27"><s n="s1.4;p15.27">After the solution in part I had been reacting for 4 hours and the sample had been removed BzMA (10mL) was added and the solution was left to stir overnight. </s><s n="s2.4;p15.27">The solution resulted in a viscous solution, which was dissolved with DCM (20mL). </s><s n="s3.4;p15.27">The resulting solution was added drop wise to a solution of sulphuric acid (40mL) and methanol (400ml) which was stirred vigorously. </s><s n="s4.4;p15.27">The solid product formed was obtained from the solution via vacuum filtration and was then dried for 1 hour in a desicator. </s></p><p n="p16.27"><s n="s1.1;p16.27">Yield: 25.3g </s></p><p n="p17.27"><s n="s1.1;p17.27">IR: 2948 (V <hi rend="sub">saturated CH stretchs</hi>) 1723 cm <hi rend="sup">-1</hi> (<hi rend="italic">VC=O)</hi> </s></p><p n="p18.27"><s n="s1.1;p18.27">All the 5 polymers were made in the same way however with variations in the reagents and compositions as stated earlier. </s></p></div3></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">3. Results and Discussions:</head><table id="BAWE_0382a-tab.004"><head><hi rend="bold">Table 4.</hi> A table of data for 5A polymer.</head><row><cell/></row></table><table id="BAWE_0382a-tab.005"><head><hi rend="bold">Table 5.</hi> A table of data for 5B polymer.</head><row><cell/></row></table><table id="BAWE_0382a-tab.006"><head><hi rend="bold">Table 6.</hi> A table of data for 5C polymer.</head><row><cell/></row></table><table id="BAWE_0382a-tab.007"><head><hi rend="bold">Table 7.</hi> A table of data for 5D polymer.</head><row><cell/></row></table><table id="BAWE_0382a-tab.008"><head><hi rend="bold">Table 8.</hi> A table of data for 5E polymer.</head><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p19.27"><s n="s1.1;p19.27">For each of the polymers a graph was plotted of Mn versus percentage conversion, this is shown in figure 1 below: </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0382a-fig.007"><head><hi rend="bold">Figure</hi> <hi rend="bold">1</hi> . A plot of Mn versus percentage conversion for each of the 5 polymers.</head></figure><p n="p20.27"><s n="s1.1;p20.27">As you can see from figure 1 each polymer results in a straight line graph when its respective Mn is plotted versus percentage conversion, this is characteristic of a living radical polymerisation and so confirms the type of polymerisation involved in all these polymer reactions. </s></p><p n="p21.27"><s n="s1.1;p21.27">A first-order kinetic plot of ln[Mn]<hi rend="sub">o</hi>/[Mn] versus time (mins) for each of the polymers as shown in figure 2 below enables the rate of the reaction to be calculated from the gradient of the line of best fit of the data. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0382a-fig.008"><head><hi rend="bold">Figure</hi> <hi rend="bold">2</hi> . A first-order kinetic plot of ln[Mn]<hi rend="sub">o</hi> /[Mn] vs time for each of the polymers.</head></figure><p n="p22.27"><s n="s1.1;p22.27">The rate constants calculated for each polymer are shown in table 9 shown below: </s></p><table id="BAWE_0382a-tab.009"><head><hi rend="bold">Table 9.</hi> A table of the rates of reactions for each polymer.</head><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p23.27"><s n="s1.1;p23.27">These rate constants for each of the different polymers enable comparisons to be made and so determine the effects of different ligands and time of addition on the rate of the reaction of these polymerizations. </s></p><div2><p n="p24.27"><s n="s1.5;p24.27"><hi rend="bold">Effect of Changing Ligand:</hi> This can be determined from comparison of Polymer 5A and 5B as these reactions involved using the exact same procedure however the only difference was that of the metal binding ligand involved. </s><s n="s2.5;p24.27">Polymer 5A involved using the propyl ligand whereas Polymer 5B uses the octyl ligand. </s><s n="s3.5;p24.27">Polymer 5B had the smaller rate constant of 0.000412 compared to Polymer 5A which had a rate constant of 0.000536. </s><s n="s4.5;p24.27">This difference in the rate of reaction must be due to the respective sizes of the two ligands. </s><s n="s5.5;p24.27">The propyl ligand is small and has less steric hindrance, whereas the octyl ligand is large and bulky, therefore has a large steric hindrance and as a result reduces the rate of the reaction. </s></p></div2><div2><p n="p25.27"><s n="s1.5;p25.27"><hi rend="bold">Effect of Changing the Monomer:</hi> This can be seen by comparison of the rate of the reaction for Polymer 5A and 5E as both have the same experimental procedure however use different monomers. </s><s n="s2.5;p25.27">Polymer 5A involves the polymerisation of methyl methacrylate (MMA) whereas Polymer 5E polymerises the monomer butyl methacrylate (BMA). </s><s n="s3.5;p25.27">Polymer 5E has the smaller rate constant of 0.000280 compared to Polymer 5A which has a rate constant of 0.000536. </s><s n="s4.5;p25.27">The difference in rate constants is due to the size of each of the monomers. </s><s n="s5.5;p25.27">Polymer 5A uses the smaller MMA monomer which has the smaller methoxy group and so a smaller steric hindrance whereas Polymer 5E uses the larger BMA monomer that has the large and bulky butyloxy group attached which carries a larger steric hindrance and so reduces the rate of the reaction. </s></p></div2><div2><p n="p26.27"><s rend="bold" n="s1.1;p26.27">Effect of time of addition: </s></p><p n="p27.27"><s n="s1.4;p27.27">The effect of this can be seen from comparing the rate of reactions of Polymer 5C and 5D. The reaction for Polymer 5C involved addition of benzyl methacrylate (BzMA) to an already forming MMA polymer after 2 hours to form the block co-polymer. </s><s n="s2.4;p27.27">Whereas Polymer 5D involved addition of BzMA to an already forming MMA polymer after 4 hours. </s><s n="s3.4;p27.27">Changing the addition time should have a slight effect on the rate of the reaction. </s><s n="s4.4;p27.27">Polymer 5C involves adding the BzMA 2 hours earlier than that of Polymer 5D. As BzMA is larger than MMA it has a larger steric hinderance and so the longer BzMA is in the reaction mixture the more effect it has on reducing the rate of the reaction, therefore Polymer 5C should have a slower rate of reaction as it had the BzMA in the reaction solution 2 hours earlier than Polymer 5D. </s></p></div2></div1></body><back><div1 type="bibliography"><head rend="bold">4. References:</head><p>[1] Haddleton, D. M.; Crossman, M. C.; Dana, B. H.; Duncalf, D. J.; Heming, A. M.; Kukulj, D.; Shooter, A. J., Atom transfer polymerization of methyl methacrylate mediated by alkylpyridylmethanimine type ligands, copper (I) bromide, and alkyl halides in hydrocarbon solution. <hi rend="italic">Macromolecules </hi><hi rend="bold">1999</hi>, 32, (7), 2110</p><p>[2] Haddleton D. M.; Waterson, C., Phenolic Ester based Initiators for Transition Metal Mediated Living Polymerisation. <hi rend="italic">Macromolecules </hi><hi rend="bold">1999</hi>, 8732-8739</p><p>[3] Kamigaito, M.; Ando, T.; Sawamoto, M., Metal-catalyzed living radical polymerisation. <hi rend="italic">Chem. Rev</hi>. <hi rend="bold">2001</hi>, 101, (12), 3689-3745</p><p>[4] Matyjaszewski, K.; Xia, J., <hi rend="italic">Chem. Rev</hi>. <hi rend="bold">2001</hi>, 101, 2921.</p><p>This is confirmed from the rates of the reactions calculated. The rate of reaction for Polymer 5C is 0.001265 whereas polymer 5D has a greater rate of reaction of 0.001397.</p><p>The PDi's of the polymers increased as Mn did. This trend was the same throughout the 5 polymers. However, there seems to be a link with a very large PDi and the addition of BzMA to form the block copolymer. The introduction of a second monomer to the reaction obviously has a dramatic effect on the PDi of a polymer.</p></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
