<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_0382b" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Organic Laboratory Write Up</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">deleted: header: student name</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">3</p><p n="date">2005-03</p><p n="module title">Organic Lab</p><p n="module code">CH3C6</p><p n="genre family">Methodology recount</p><p n="discipline">Chemistry</p><p n="disciplinary group">PS</p><p n="grade">D</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">737</p><p n="number of s-units">33</p><p n="number of p">16</p><p n="number of tables">9</p><p n="number of figures">9</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">0</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">0</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">22.3</p><p n="average s-units per p">2.1</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">m</p><p n="year of birth">1983</p><p n="first language">English</p><p n="education">UKA</p><p n="course">Mchem</p><p n="student ID">0382</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><docTitle><titlePart rend="underlined">Organic Laboratory Write Up</titlePart></docTitle></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">STEP 1:</head><p n="p1.16"><s n="s1.1;p1.16">The method was carried out as stated in the lab manual with the following alteration: After extraction with diethylether the extracts were washed twice with 20mL water. </s></p><p n="p2.16"><s n="s1.1;p2.16">RJP1 was purified via recrystallisation with methanol and a few drops of water. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0382b-fig.001"><head><hi rend="underlined bold">TLC plate:</hi> Solvent = 10:1 40/60 petroleum ether:ethyl acetate: </head></figure><p n="p3.16"><s n="s1.1;p3.16">The TLC plate clearly shows that the reaction went to completion, as there is no presence of the ortho - hydroxyacetonphenone starting product present in the final spot of RJP1. </s></p><p n="p4.16"><s n="s1.1;p4.16"><hi rend="underlined bold">Yield of RJP1:</hi> (7.33g, 28.63 mmol, 77.1%) </s></p><table id="BAWE_0382b-tab.001"><head rend="underlined bold">Melting Point: </head><row><cell/></row></table></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">STEP 2:</head><p n="p5.16"><s n="s1.2;p5.16">The method was carried out as stated in the lab manual with no alterations. </s><s n="s2.2;p5.16">RJP2 was purified via recrystallisation with 40/60 petroleum ether and a few drops of ethyl acetate. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0382b-fig.002"><head><hi rend="underlined bold">TLC plate:</hi> Solvent = 10:1 40/60 petroleum ether:ethyl acetate: </head></figure><p n="p6.16"><s n="s1.1;p6.16">The TLC plate clearly shows that the reaction went to completion, as there is no presence of the RJP1 starting product present in the final spot of RJP2. </s></p><p n="p7.16"><s n="s1.1;p7.16"><hi rend="underlined bold">Yield of RJP2: </hi>(3.96g, 15.35 mmol, 78.3%) </s></p><table id="BAWE_0382b-tab.002"><head rend="underlined bold">Melting Point: </head><row><cell/></row></table></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">STEP 3:</head><figure id="BAWE_0382b-fig.003"/><p n="p8.16"><s n="s1.3;p8.16">Method adapted from Bebernitz GR, Dain JG, Deems RO, Otero DA, Simpson WR, Strohschein RJ, <hi rend="italic">A Prodrug Approach for Targeting the Liver</hi>, J. Med. </s><s n="s2.3;p8.16">Chem. </s><s n="s3.3;p8.16"><hi rend="bold">2001</hi>, 44, 512 - 523 </s></p><p n="p9.16"><s n="s1.5;p9.16">RJP2 (2.51g) and THF (15mL) was stirred for 30 minutes under an inert nitrogen atmosphere. </s><s n="s2.5;p9.16">NaH (0.45g) was then added to the mixture and stirred for 50 hours. </s><s n="s3.5;p9.16">The solution was then concentrated by the addition of HCl and diluted with ether (30mL). </s><s n="s4.5;p9.16">The solution was then dried over magnesium sulphate and rotary evaporated. </s><s n="s5.5;p9.16">1.02g of the crude product was purified via column chromatography. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0382b-pic.001"><head><hi rend="underlined bold">TLC plate: (after 50 hours stirring)</hi> Solvent = 20:1 40/60 petroleum ether:ethyl acetate </head></figure><p n="p10.16"><s n="s1.3;p10.16">The TLC plate clearly shows that the reaction still contains the starting materials. </s><s n="s2.3;p10.16">However, 50 hours stirring should have been easily enough to ensure that the reaction had gone to completion, especially as the reference literature method only suggested around 4 hours of stirring. </s><s n="s3.3;p10.16">This suggests that the reaction procedure from the literature may not be suitable for this specific reagents used in this experiment; this will be confirmed or disproved with further analysis of the spectroscopic data. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0382b-pic.002"><head><hi rend="underlined bold">TLC plate: (fractions from the flash column)</hi> Solvent = 20:1 40/60 petroleum ether:ethyl acetate.</head></figure><p n="p11.16"><s n="s1.3;p11.16">The TLC's clearly show that fractions 15 - 17 contain the product RJP3. </s><s n="s2.3;p11.16">These fractions were collected together and left to crystallise. </s><s n="s3.3;p11.16">The product was then desiccated. </s></p><p n="p12.16"><s n="s1.1;p12.16"><hi rend="underlined bold">Yield of RJP3: </hi>(0.34g, 0.98 mmol, 24.9%) </s></p><table id="BAWE_0382b-tab.003"><head rend="underlined bold">Melting Point: </head><row><cell/></row></table></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">Spectra Analysis: (for spectra see in appendix)</head><figure id="BAWE_0382b-fig.004"><head><hi rend="bold">Product 1:</hi> (RJP1)</head></figure><table id="BAWE_0382b-tab.004"><head rend="bold">IR:</head><row><cell/></row></table><table id="BAWE_0382b-tab.005"><head rend="bold">NMR:</head><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p13.16"><s n="s1.1;p13.16">The IR and NMR spectra fit the proposed structure of RJP1 and therefore confirms the structure of the product from step 1 to be RJP1. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0382b-fig.005"><head><hi rend="bold">Product 2:</hi> (RJP2)</head></figure><table id="BAWE_0382b-tab.006"><head rend="bold">IR:</head><row><cell/></row></table><table id="BAWE_0382b-tab.007"><head rend="bold">NMR:</head><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p14.16"><s n="s1.2;p14.16">The IR and NMR spectra fit the proposed structure of RJP2 and therefore confirms the structure of the product from step 2 to be RJP2. </s><s n="s2.2;p14.16">Also clearly shown from comparison of the IR spectrum of RJP1 and RJP2, is the disappearance of the strong carbonyl peak (1663.3 cm <hi rend="sup">-1</hi>) and the presence of the strong/broad alcohol peak (3314 cm <hi rend="sup">-1</hi>), which suggests that the product from step 2 is RJP2. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0382b-fig.006"><head><hi rend="bold">Product 3:</hi> (RJP3)</head></figure><table id="BAWE_0382b-tab.008"><head rend="bold">IR:</head><row><cell/></row></table><table id="BAWE_0382b-tab.009"><head rend="bold">NMR:</head><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p15.16"><s n="s1.7;p15.16">From the IR and NMR spectra of RJP3 it clearly shows that the reaction hasn't resulted in RJP3 as the product. </s><s n="s2.7;p15.16">The IR spectrum has a broad/strong alcohol peak (3306 cm <hi rend="sup">-1</hi>) which should not be present as this should have reacted and become the second ether group in this molecule. </s><s n="s3.7;p15.16">This suggests that the reaction has not occurred or is still impure. </s><s n="s4.7;p15.16">The NMR of RJP3 suggests a failed reaction further as it contains nearly an exact match of proton shifts and integrals to that of the NMR of RJP2 and does not show any chemical shifts for the presence of the protons k, l, m and n. </s><s n="s5.7;p15.16">If the reaction had succeeded then there should at least be an extra chemical shift around ~2.3 ppm which would correspond to proton n. </s><s n="s6.7;p15.16">Therefore, my deduction is that the reaction in step 3 failed. </s><s n="s7.7;p15.16">This may be due to the fact that the literature method it was based on may not be effective for the specific set of reagents that were used in step 3 of this chemical synthesis. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">Mechanisms:</head><figure id="BAWE_0382b-fig.007"><head rend="underlined bold">Step 1:</head></figure><figure id="BAWE_0382b-fig.008"><head rend="underlined bold">Step 2: </head></figure><figure id="BAWE_0382b-fig.009"><head rend="underlined bold">Step 3:</head></figure><p n="p16.16"/></div1></body><back/></text></TEI.2>
