<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_0388b" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Process Chemistry in the Pharmaceutical Industry</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">deleted: header: student name and number, module code; footer: page numbers</note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">deleted: Word Count: 2661</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">4</p><p n="date">2006-12</p><p n="module title">Molecular Pharmacology</p><p n="module code">CH3B5</p><p n="genre family">Explanation</p><p n="discipline">Chemistry</p><p n="disciplinary group">PS</p><p n="grade">D</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">2759</p><p n="number of s-units">123</p><p n="number of p">33</p><p n="number of tables">1</p><p n="number of figures">16</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">0</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">0</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">22.4</p><p n="average s-units per p">3.7</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">f</p><p n="year of birth">1984</p><p n="first language">English</p><p n="education">UKA</p><p n="course">Chemistry with Medicinal Chemistry with Industrial Training</p><p n="student ID">0388</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><docTitle><titlePart rend="underlined bold">Process Chemistry in the Pharmaceutical Industry</titlePart></docTitle></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="section"><p n="p1.33"><s n="s1.6;p1.33">Process research and development (PR&amp;D) is an important aspect to any chemical industry that requires the production of large quantities of chemical material. </s><s n="s2.6;p1.33">In the pharmaceutical industry, however, this department is key to the effective production of profitable drugs. </s><s n="s3.6;p1.33">Process chemistry was really established in the 1950s with the development of the modern pharmaceutical industry<ref target="BAWE_0388b-endnote.001"/> and more complicated drug molecules. </s><s n="s4.6;p1.33">Recognition of its importance steadily grew over the years with the release of the journal <hi rend="italic">Organic Process Research and Development</hi> in 1997. </s><s n="s5.6;p1.33">To date this journal has published almost 1,300 papers and had an impact rating of 1.749 in 2005<ref target="BAWE_0388b-endnote.002"/>. </s><s n="s6.6;p1.33">As Figure 1 shows although the number of citations of articles from the journal greatly outweighs the increase in items published each year, showing an increased interest in the journal, which reflects the growing importance of process chemistry in the scientific community. </s></p><note place="end" id="BAWE_0388b-endnote.001"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">T. Zhang, <hi rend="italic">Chem.</hi> </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1"><hi rend="italic">Review</hi>, 2006, <hi rend="bold">106</hi>, 2583-2595 </s></p></note><note place="end" id="BAWE_0388b-endnote.002"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">2005 ISI® Journal Citation Reports® Analyses </s></p></note><figure id="BAWE_0388b-fig.001"><head><hi rend="bold">Figure 1: The number of items published by and citations of <hi rend="italic">Organic Process Research and Development</hi> each year</hi><ref target="BAWE_0388b-endnote.003"/><note place="end" id="BAWE_0388b-endnote.003"><p n="pn1.1"> Data from ISI® Web of Science</p></note></head></figure><p n="p2.33"><s n="s1.5;p2.33">To fully understand the importance of PR&amp;D, it is useful to know where in the drug development timeline it comes into play. </s><s n="s2.5;p2.33">Drug discovery (DD) may spend several years finding hits for a certain biological target, from which lead molecules are developed. </s><s n="s3.5;p2.33">The best of the leads is nominated as a candidate drug (CD) and is taken forward into PR&amp;D. However, as Figure 2 shows a developing drug will spend a very large amount of time in PR&amp;D. This is because even the most promising of drugs cannot be marketed without a viable manufacturing process. </s><s n="s4.5;p2.33">This can take a significant amount of time, depending on the complexity of the molecule. </s><s n="s5.5;p2.33">PR&amp;D can be seen as the interface between organic chemistry and business. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0388b-fig.002"><head rend="bold">Figure 2: The development process for modern pharmaceuticals</head></figure><p n="p3.33"><s n="s1.6;p3.33">The main role of PR&amp;D is to discover and develop robust, as well as economic, manufacturing processes for new chemical entities (NCEs). </s><s n="s2.6;p3.33">The route used to synthesise the CD in drug discovery will have been designed to enable a high degree of functional group variability at certain sites. </s><s n="s3.6;p3.33">This can mean that the route is complex, inefficient and may work well on a small scale, but is impractical for larger scales. </s><s n="s4.6;p3.33">In developing the route the department is capable of producing large variable quantities of active pharmaceutical ingredient (API), from 200g to 2000kg, for use in formulation research, toxicology studies and clinical trials. </s><s n="s5.6;p3.33">From the production of this material important knowledge is then acquired. </s><s n="s6.6;p3.33">However, it would be an oversimplification to describe process chemistry as bucket chemistry, or to assume that it just involves scaling existing processes into larger vessels. </s></p><p n="p4.33"><s n="s1.11;p4.33">At AstraZeneca PR&amp;D is divided into five sections: process chemistry (PC), process analysis (PA), development manufacture (DM), process engineering (PE), and process management (PM). </s><s n="s2.11;p4.33">Each section has an important role in the development of a NCE. PC focuses on the development of the chemical synthetic route to produce a final route for manufacture. </s><s n="s3.11;p4.33">The route must be robust, safe and predictable for manufacture, but ideally it should also be simple, inexpensive and environmentally benign, as well as high yielding with high quality<ref target="BAWE_0388b-endnote.004"/>. </s><s n="s4.11;p4.33">PA is responsible for developing analytical methods to assess the quality of the API and its intermediates. </s><s n="s5.11;p4.33">These methods can also be used to monitor the reactions to gain more information about the processes. </s><s n="s6.11;p4.33">PA and PC can use this information to set specifications for the API. DM is concerned with the running of the pilot plant to produce large quantities of API. It works closely with PC to ensure the route is compatible with the intended site of use. </s><s n="s7.11;p4.33">PE concentrates on plant compatibility and the resolution of scale issues. </s><s n="s8.11;p4.33">Issues can arise with agitation, heat or mass transfer and isolation when scaled larger, which are all key to manufacture. </s><s n="s9.11;p4.33">PM is the link between PR&amp;D and the global projects team. </s><s n="s10.11;p4.33">It manages PR&amp;D at a high level and also oversees interdepartmental interaction. </s><s n="s11.11;p4.33">Successful development of an NCE depends on all the sections working together, as well as with other departments. </s></p><note place="end" id="BAWE_0388b-endnote.004"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">M. Lipton, T. Barrett, <hi rend="italic">Chem.</hi> </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1"><hi rend="italic">Review</hi>, 2006, <hi rend="bold">106</hi>, 2581-2582 </s></p></note><p n="p5.33"><s n="s1.8;p5.33">In order to develop a route for manufacture optimisation of the route by PC must also take place. </s><s n="s2.8;p5.33">Optimisation involves generating large quantities of data, from which knowledge and understanding of the process is deduced. </s><s n="s3.8;p5.33">Thermodynamic and kinetic parameters, along with the heat of reaction are important<ref target="BAWE_0388b-endnote.005"/> as well as the quantity ranges for the reagents. </s><s n="s4.8;p5.33">The establishment of these parameters and ranges is increasingly becoming similar to combinatorial chemistry used in discovery chemistry. </s><s n="s5.8;p5.33">A computer program is used to create a set of experiments that change several variables simultaneously. </s><s n="s6.8;p5.33">These experiments are then carried out used automated equipment. </s><s n="s7.8;p5.33">The design of changing several variables at once creates a more detailed picture of what occurs in the reaction and which parameters are important to the performance of the reaction. </s><s n="s8.8;p5.33">This method is far more effective than changing one variable at a time, with much more data being produced from the former method in the same number of experiments.<ref target="BAWE_0388b-endnote.006"/> </s></p><note place="end" id="BAWE_0388b-endnote.005"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.3;pn1.1">Prof. Dr. G. H. </s><s n="s2.3;pn1.1">Vogel, <hi rend="italic">Process Development: From the Initial Idea to the Chemical Plant</hi>, Wiley, Weinheim, 2005, ch. </s><s n="s3.3;pn1.1">3 </s></p></note><note place="end" id="BAWE_0388b-endnote.006"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">C. M. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">Henry, <hi rend="italic">C&amp;EN</hi>, 2002, <hi rend="bold">80</hi>, 22, 53-66 </s></p></note><p n="p6.33"><s n="s1.7;p6.33">The time constraints on PR&amp;D are increasing due to the market pressures of patents on profitable drugs that will soon expire and no potentially profitable replacements in the pipeline <hi rend="sup">6</hi>. </s><s n="s2.7;p6.33">To decrease development time PR&amp;D have started getting involved in drug discovery earlier in the process that CD nomination. </s><s n="s3.7;p6.33">This increases PR&amp;D's capability of choosing the best route for manufacture, as it has more time to familiarise itself with the potential CDs and their chemistry. </s><s n="s4.7;p6.33">Also earlier involvement enables PR&amp;D to influence the drug discovery process. </s><s n="s5.7;p6.33">This can involve showing medicinal chemists better synthetic routes, so less work is required in drug development. </s><s n="s6.7;p6.33">Also with manufacturing concerns considered at CD nomination, fewer CDs will be taken through to the drug development stage that could fail due to production issues. </s><s n="s7.7;p6.33">Therefore, effort is focussed on more promising CDs, which will increase the pipeline output. </s></p><p n="p7.33"><s n="s1.2;p7.33">One example of PR&amp;D is the development of the synthesis of benzothiophene <hi rend="bold">3</hi>. </s><s n="s2.2;p7.33">The proposed route from drug discovery used lithiated 2-bromothiophenol <hi rend="bold">1</hi> as a starting material. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0388b-fig.003"><head rend="bold">Scheme 1: Synthesis of benzothiophene 3</head></figure><p n="p8.33"><s n="s1.6;p8.33">However, 2-bromothiophenol is very expensive, at £12.70 per gram<ref target="BAWE_0388b-endnote.007"/>, and is only available in relatively small amounts. </s><s n="s2.6;p8.33">This makes it an unsuitable starting material, which should ideally be cheap and readily available in large quantities for manufacture. </s><s n="s3.6;p8.33">PR&amp;D could have solved this problem by synthesising 2-bromothiophenol in-house, however this involved adding extra steps to the synthesis. </s><s n="s4.6;p8.33">Therefore, a complete route change was required to devise a synthetic route suitable for manufacture. </s><s n="s5.6;p8.33">The solution was found in lithiating thiophenol, which is much cheaper than 2-bromothiophenol, to form the dianion <hi rend="bold">4</hi>, which then underwent the same chemistry as <hi rend="bold">1</hi>. </s><s n="s6.6;p8.33">This simple change proved to be very efficient, providing a suitable manufacturing route from the drug discovery route. </s></p><note place="end" id="BAWE_0388b-endnote.007"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1"><seg type="URL" n="http://www.sigmaaldrich.com"/>, last accessed 20/12/06 </s></p></note><figure id="BAWE_0388b-fig.004"><head rend="bold">Scheme 2: PR&amp;D synthesis of benzothiophene</head></figure><p n="p9.33"><s n="s1.5;p9.33">Although the previous problem had a simple solution, often PR&amp;D work extensively on all the stages of a synthetic route of a project. </s><s n="s2.5;p9.33">An example of this is the project AR-C123196 from AstraZeneca. </s><s n="s3.5;p9.33">AR-C123196 was a CD with anti-inflammatory and antihistamine properties, but unfortunately was not launched due to failed clinical trials. </s><s n="s4.5;p9.33">The key structural features of the molecule are the chiral hydroxyl pyridine and the functionalized biaryl ether, with only the (<hi rend="italic">R</hi>) enantiomer required. </s><s n="s5.5;p9.33">The total synthesis of <hi rend="bold">7</hi> also had a target of delivering >1000kg per annum at &lt;£2000 per kg. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0388b-pic.001"/><p n="p10.33"><s n="s1.1;p10.33">Before the project was stopped, however, a great deal of development work was carried out on the synthetic route. </s></p><p n="p11.33"><s n="s1.4;p11.33">The synthesis of <hi rend="bold">7</hi> could be approached in two ways, the linear or convergent approach. </s><s n="s2.4;p11.33">The linear approach involved five steps to link three fragments of the molecule together (Scheme 3). </s><s n="s3.4;p11.33">However, the most expensive compound in the whole synthesis is the chiral hydroxyl pyridine derivative starting material <hi rend="bold">13</hi>. </s><s n="s4.4;p11.33">This is not cost effective as any loss of yield will involve losing expensive starting material, making the whole synthesis expensive. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0388b-fig.005"><head rend="bold">Scheme 3: Linear synthesis of AR-C123196</head></figure><p n="p12.33"><s n="s1.1;p12.33">The convergent approach involves synthesising two fragments of the molecule separately and then coupling them together to form the final compound. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0388b-fig.006"><head rend="bold">Scheme 4: Convergent synthesis of AR-C123196</head></figure><p n="p13.33"><s n="s1.5;p13.33">This approach has many advantages over the linear synthesis. </s><s n="s2.5;p13.33">For one the expensive intermediate <hi rend="bold">13</hi> is used late in the synthesis, so any cost due to loss of yield is kept to a minimum. </s><s n="s3.5;p13.33">Parallel processing of the two fragments also means shorter processing times if both are synthesised at the same time in different reactors, compared to the linear process which would require performing each step in sequence. </s><s n="s4.5;p13.33">Also with two parallel syntheses outsourcing of one was an option, giving the in-house PR&amp;D more time to concentrate on the other synthesis. </s><s n="s5.5;p13.33">With the linear synthesis this would not be possible unless the whole route was outsourced. </s></p><p n="p14.33"><s n="s1.4;p14.33">However, the convergent approach had some issues. </s><s n="s2.4;p14.33">The coupling reaction between the two fragments needed to be selective to attack of the carbonate by the oxygen on <hi rend="bold">15</hi> over attack by the nitrogen, which has some nucleophilic character. </s><s n="s3.4;p14.33">This can be overcome by protecting the amide. </s><s n="s4.4;p14.33">Synthetic methods to form the fragments also needed to be assessed. </s></p><p n="p15.33"><s n="s1.1;p15.33">The biaryl fragment <hi rend="bold">15</hi> was straightforward to synthesise using Suzuki chemistry to link the phenyl and thiophene fragments. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0388b-fig.007"><head rend="bold">Scheme 5: Synthesis of the biaryl fragment</head></figure><p n="p16.33"><s n="s1.6;p16.33">The formation of the boronic acid worked well, with a reasonable yield of 69%. </s><s n="s2.6;p16.33">The Suzuki reaction gave a high yield of 85% with respect to the thiophene sulphonamide <hi rend="bold">18</hi>, with purity >99% by HPLC. The amide in <hi rend="bold">15</hi> is protected in <hi rend="bold">20</hi> with a bulky tertiary butyl group, which sterically hinders any nucleophilic attack by the amide. </s><s n="s3.6;p16.33">A palladium scavenger was needed to remove any remaining palladium in the reaction mixture. </s><s n="s4.6;p16.33">The deloxan resin was an effective scavenger reducing the palladium content from 240ppm after the Suzuki coupling, to &lt;2ppm after treatment. </s><s n="s5.6;p16.33">This prevented palladium carrying through to the API and affecting the patient. </s><s n="s6.6;p16.33">Therefore, the reasonable yields and high quality of the simple biaryl synthesis meant that it was suitable for manufacturing scale. </s></p><p n="p17.33"><s n="s1.3;p17.33">The chiral pyridine intermediate <hi rend="bold">13</hi> was originally synthesised using the drug discovery route (Scheme 6)<ref target="BAWE_0388b-ftnote.001"/>. </s><s n="s2.3;p17.33">This had been scaled to produce multi kilogram batches of <hi rend="bold">13</hi> as the oxalate salt, and time pressures for producing material for clinical trials meant that the route was suitable to use for the first campaign. </s><s n="s3.3;p17.33">This route involves six steps, with the final steps producing the product at >99% purity by HPLC and >99% enantiomeric excess (ee). </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0388b-ftnote.001"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Developed in partnership with Evotec OAI </s></p></note><figure id="BAWE_0388b-fig.008"><head rend="bold">Scheme 6: Synthesis of chiral pyridine intermediate 13</head></figure><p n="p18.33"><s n="s1.6;p18.33">The fragments <hi rend="bold">13</hi> and <hi rend="bold">15</hi> were then linked together using nucleophilic attack of the carbonate by <hi rend="bold">15</hi>. </s><s n="s2.6;p18.33">The intermediate <hi rend="bold">13</hi> is insoluble as the oxalate salt, so the salt was removed to form the free base, which was then used in the reaction. </s><s n="s3.6;p18.33">Also a diol impurity from hydrolysis of the carbonate was formed. </s><s n="s4.6;p18.33">However, it was soluble in the reaction media and so was easily removed. </s><s n="s5.6;p18.33">The amide was then deprotected to give <hi rend="bold">7</hi> as the hydrochloride salt, in a 54% yield (Scheme 7). </s><s n="s6.6;p18.33">The hydorchloride salt is unstable so the compound was transformed to the free base in a 62% recovery and 97.5% purity by HPLC. However, in the laboratory this recovery achieved yields of >90%, so it was clear that there were some problems with scaling up that particular methodology. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0388b-fig.009"><head rend="bold">Scheme 7: Linking of fragments 13 and 15 and deprotection of the amide</head></figure><p n="p19.33"><s n="s1.7;p19.33">A total of 3.4kg of <hi rend="bold">7</hi> were successfully produced in the campaign, although many problems were highlighted. </s><s n="s2.7;p19.33">Although a robust and economic supply of biaryl <hi rend="bold">15</hi> had been developed as well as a simple and scaleable convergent synthesis of <hi rend="bold">7</hi>, synthesis of the chiral pyridine <hi rend="bold">13</hi> was complicated and expensive. </s><s n="s3.7;p19.33">The synthesis of <hi rend="bold">13</hi> uses gulonolactone <hi rend="bold">21</hi> as its starting material. </s><s n="s4.7;p19.33">This compound is very expensive at £350 per kg, and only three carbons from the molecule are used in <hi rend="bold">13</hi>, also making the synthesis very atom inefficient. </s><s n="s5.7;p19.33">The formation of the aldehyde <hi rend="bold">23</hi> also raised issues as it is base sensitive and was synthesised under basic reaction conditions. </s><s n="s6.7;p19.33">This caused enolate formation, which can then polymerise, so the product <hi rend="bold">23</hi> needed cracking before it could be used. </s><s n="s7.7;p19.33">These problems meant that the total synthesis of <hi rend="bold">13</hi> cost £16,000 per kg, eight times the target cost of the total synthesis of <hi rend="bold">7</hi> of &lt;£2000 per kg. </s></p><p n="p20.33"><s n="s1.1;p20.33">Although the recovery of the free base of <hi rend="bold">7</hi> was not performing well on a large scale, it was clear that the redevelopment of the synthesis of <hi rend="bold">13</hi> was a priority for the project to meet its targets. </s></p><p n="p21.33"><s n="s1.5;p21.33">Initially a route that used enzyme resolution of the enantiomers was developed (Scheme 8)<ref target="BAWE_0388b-ftnote.002"/>. </s><s n="s2.5;p21.33">This involved forming the hydroxy ester pryridine <hi rend="bold">32</hi> and then hydrolysing the ester to give the acid. </s><s n="s3.5;p21.33">The hydrolysis formed both enantiomers, but the enzyme selectively reduced the (<hi rend="italic">S</hi>) enantiomer back to the ester so it could again by hydrolysed. </s><s n="s4.5;p21.33">This enzymatic cycle caused an excess of the desired (<hi rend="italic">R</hi>) enantiomer. </s><s n="s5.5;p21.33">This route was used to produce 19kg of <hi rend="bold">13</hi> as the oxalate salt, but was not considered as a viable alternative as it still did not meet the financial requirements of the project. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0388b-ftnote.002"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Developed in partnership with ChiroTech Ltd. </s></p></note><figure id="BAWE_0388b-fig.010"><head rend="bold">Scheme 8: Enzyme resolution synthesis of 13</head></figure><p n="p22.33"><s n="s1.1;p22.33">Many other methods of forming chiral diols were considered, which could than be transformed to the carbonate, but the Heck arylation of the carbonate and asymmetric reduction of the hydroxy ketone were considered to be the most viable options. </s></p><p n="p23.33"><s n="s1.2;p23.33">The asymmetric hydrogenation was a simple and effective route to form the chiral diol <hi rend="bold">27</hi>, using a chiral ruthenium catalyst (Scheme 9)<ref target="BAWE_0388b-ftnote.003"/>. </s><s n="s2.2;p23.33">This reaction gave a yield of 90% and an ee of >98% after the oxalate salt was formed. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0388b-ftnote.003"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Develeoped in partnership with PPG SIPSY </s></p></note><figure id="BAWE_0388b-fig.011"><head rend="bold">Scheme 9: Asymmetric hydrogenation</head></figure><p n="p24.33"><s n="s1.1;p24.33">The Heck reaction between the carbonate fragment and pyridyl bromide initially seemed to be a good option for the synthesis of <hi rend="bold">27</hi>. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0388b-fig.012"><head rend="bold">Scheme 10: Heck synthesis of 27</head></figure><p n="p25.33"><s n="s1.1;p25.33">However, many impurities were formed in the coupling reaction, with migrated alkene impurities <hi rend="bold">40</hi> and <hi rend="bold">41</hi> being the major products. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0388b-fig.013"><head rend="bold">Figure 3: Impurities from the Heck coupling</head></figure><p n="p26.33"><s n="s1.2;p26.33">However, the impurity <hi rend="bold">40</hi> is the enol form of the hydroxy ketone <hi rend="bold">35</hi> needed for the asymmetric hydrogenation. </s><s n="s2.2;p26.33">Therefore the Heck reaction could be used to provide a robust synthesis of <hi rend="bold">35</hi> using the diol analgue of the carbonate fragment <hi rend="bold">36</hi>. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0388b-fig.014"><head rend="bold">Scheme 11: Heck synthesis of the hydroxy ketone 35</head></figure><p n="p27.33"><s n="s1.2;p27.33">Literature precedent demonstrated that the coupling was possible with a palladium catalyst, phosphine ligand and base.<ref target="BAWE_0388b-endnote.008"/> However, the reaction produced the alkenyl diol impurity in significant amounts, although this compound is water soluble and easily removed. </s><s n="s2.2;p27.33">Two sets of conditions were tried for the Heck coupling using different catalysts, ligands and bases to obtain the best ratio of product to impurity. </s></p><note place="end" id="BAWE_0388b-endnote.008"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.3;pn1.1">M. C. </s><s n="s2.3;pn1.1">Viaud, P. Jamoneau, L. Savelon, G. Guillaumet, <hi rend="italic">Tet.</hi> </s><s n="s3.3;pn1.1"><hi rend="italic">Lett</hi>., 1996, <hi rend="bold">37</hi>, 2409-2412 </s></p></note><table id="BAWE_0388b-tab.001"><head rend="bold">Table 1: Reaction conditions for the Heck coupling</head><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p28.33"><s n="s1.5;p28.33">The first set of conditions gave the best product to impurity ratio, but the reaction was not robust on larger scales. </s><s n="s2.5;p28.33">The catalyst and base were also expensive, making the reaction conditions undesirable. </s><s n="s3.5;p28.33">The second set of conditions was better for large scales, with relatively cheap reagents and so was more desirable, even with the smaller product to impurity ratio. </s><s n="s4.5;p28.33">However, using an aqueous work-up dissolved the diol impurity and removed it to give a higher ratio of 18:1. </s><s n="s5.5;p28.33">Using these conditions a multi kg scale reaction was carried out to give a 60-65% yield and 94% purity. </s></p><p n="p29.33"><s n="s1.1;p29.33">Combining the Heck coupling and the asymmetric hydrogenation the chiral intermediate <hi rend="bold">13</hi> was produced in only three steps with 98% ee, from relatively cheap achiral starting materials.<ref target="BAWE_0388b-endnote.009"/> </s></p><note place="end" id="BAWE_0388b-endnote.009"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">D. Angie, L. M. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">Vaz, <hi rend="italic">Organic Process Research &amp; Development</hi>, 2002, <hi rend="bold">6</hi>, 811 </s></p></note><figure id="BAWE_0388b-fig.015"><head rend="bold">Scheme 12: Final synthetic route for the synthesis of intermediate 13</head></figure><p n="p30.33"><s n="s1.1;p30.33">Although the overall yield was 35%, this could have been improved with optimisation. </s></p><p n="p31.33"><s n="s1.4;p31.33">With the developed synthetic route for the chiral pyridine intermediate <hi rend="bold">13</hi> the PR&amp;D team had a viable manufacturing route for the synthesis of AR-C123196 <hi rend="bold">7</hi>. </s><s n="s2.4;p31.33">A convergent synthesis of <hi rend="bold">7</hi> had been developed, with the longest linear sequence consisting of only six steps. </s><s n="s3.4;p31.33">This is mainly down to the full redevelopment of the synthesis of <hi rend="bold">13</hi>, which was reduced from six steps to only three. </s><s n="s4.4;p31.33">The replacement of the expensive reagents in the synthesis of <hi rend="bold">13</hi> also meant that the project's target of a manufacturing cost of &lt;£2000 per kg was realised. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0388b-fig.016"><head rend="bold">Scheme 13: Total synthesis of AR-C123196</head></figure><p n="p32.33"><s n="s1.1;p32.33">Unfortunately, as previously mentioned, the project was terminated at this point after the failure of Phase I clinical trials. </s></p><p n="p33.33"><s n="s1.2;p33.33">In summary the role of PR&amp;D is to take complex, costly and undesirable route and use their knowledge of organic chemistry to transform the route into something simple, cheap and viable for manufacture. </s><s n="s2.2;p33.33">This is a vital role that the pharmaceutical industry could not run without, and its importance is being increasingly recognised over time. </s></p></div1></body><back/></text></TEI.2>
