<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_0388d" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>The Use of HPLC in Industry</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">deleted: Word Count: 1098</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">3</p><p n="date">2006-07</p><p n="module title">Practical Skills for the Industrial Chemist</p><p n="module code">CH3C7</p><p n="genre family">Essay</p><p n="discipline">Chemistry</p><p n="disciplinary group">PS</p><p n="grade">D</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">1101</p><p n="number of s-units">45</p><p n="number of p">11</p><p n="number of tables">0</p><p n="number of figures">2</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">0</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">0</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">24.5</p><p n="average s-units per p">4.1</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">f</p><p n="year of birth">1984</p><p n="first language">English</p><p n="education">UKA</p><p n="course">Chemistry with Medicinal Chemistry with Industrial Training</p><p n="student ID">0388</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><docTitle><titlePart rend="underlined bold">The Use of HPLC in Industry</titlePart></docTitle></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="section"><p n="p1.11"><s n="s1.2;p1.11">High-Performance Liquid Chromatography (HPLC) is one of the leading separation techniques in the chemical industry. </s><s n="s2.2;p1.11">HPLC began in the 1960s and 70s and now represents 60% of the market.<ref target="BAWE_0388d-endnote.001"/> Its success stems from the versatility and ease of use associated with its applications. </s></p><note place="end" id="BAWE_0388d-endnote.001"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.4;pn1.1"><hi rend="italic">High Performance Liquid Chromatography Fundamental Principles and Pratice</hi>, ed. </s><s n="s2.4;pn1.1">W. J. </s><s n="s3.4;pn1.1">Lough, I. W Wainer, Blackie Academic &amp; Professional, Glasgow, 1995, ch. </s><s n="s4.4;pn1.1">1, pp. 12-13 </s></p></note><p n="p2.11"><s n="s1.3;p2.11">HPLC involves the use of a mechanical instrument, which pumps solvent through a tightly packed column of stationary phase. </s><s n="s2.3;p2.11">The sample is injected into this system and the time taken for different compounds to reach the detector at the end of the column is recorded. </s><s n="s3.3;p2.11">This data can then be transferred to a computer program where it can be further manipulated. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0388d-pic.001"><head><hi rend="bold">Figure 1: Schematic diagram of an HPLC unit</hi><ref target="BAWE_0388d-endnote.002"/><note place="end" id="BAWE_0388d-endnote.002"><p n="pn1.1"> V. Meyer, <hi rend="italic">Practical High-Performance Liquid Chromatography</hi>, Wiley, Weinheim, 4th edn., 2004, ch. 1, pp. 7-10</p></note></head></figure><p n="p3.11"><s n="s1.7;p3.11">The chromatography can be modified to suit the system being analysed. </s><s n="s2.7;p3.11">Simply changing the column of stationary phase can access different methods of HPLC. Each column is also compatible with several solvent systems allowing the method to be refined to achieve the best possible separation and resolution. </s><s n="s3.7;p3.11">One of the most common methods is adsorption chromatography. </s><s n="s4.7;p3.11">In principle it is very similar to thin-layer chromatography (TLC), a polar material with a high specific surface area, such as silica, is used as a stationary phase with a non-polar mobile phase (eluent), such as hexane.<hi rend="sup">2</hi> Another popular method of HPLC is reversed-phase chromatography. </s><s n="s5.7;p3.11">This is essentially the reverse of adsorption chromatography, with a non-polar stationary phase and polar mobile phase. </s><s n="s6.7;p3.11">This method is useful for analysis of aqueous solutions, such as pharmaceutical formulations of drug for the body. </s><s n="s7.7;p3.11">Other methods of HPLC include ion-exchange, ion-pair, ion, size-exclusion and affinity chromatography.<hi rend="sup">2</hi> </s></p><p n="p4.11"><s n="s1.3;p4.11">The interactions of the analyte molecules between the different phases cause some to travel slower than others through the stationary phase. </s><s n="s2.3;p4.11">These interactions include van der Waals forces, dipole-dipole, Coulombic forces and hydrogen bonding.<ref target="BAWE_0388d-endnote.003"/> The stronger the interactions between the stationary phase and analyte molecules the slower the molecules will travel. </s><s n="s3.3;p4.11">This provides retention times specific to a particular compound in those particular system conditions. </s></p><note place="end" id="BAWE_0388d-endnote.003"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">T. Hanai, HPLC A Practical Guide, The Royal Society of Chemistry, Cambridge, 1999, ch. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">1, pp. 7 </s></p></note><p n="p5.11"><s n="s1.6;p5.11">There are two models of retention that define its mechanism: the solvent-interaction model by Scott and Kucera in 1979 and the solvent-competition model by Snyder in 1968 and 1983.<ref target="BAWE_0388d-endnote.004"/> Both assume that a layer of solvent molecules, which interact strongly with the stationary phase, is adsorbed onto the surface of the stationary phase. </s><s n="s2.6;p5.11">This restricts the interactions between the stationary phase and the analyte molecules, causing them to rapidly elute from the system.<ref target="BAWE_0388d-endnote.005"/> In the solvent-interaction model the analyte molecule is partitioned between the mobile phase and the layer of adsorbed solvent molecules. </s><s n="s3.6;p5.11">The solvent-competition model has the analyte molecules competing with the strong solvent molecules for active sites in the stationary phase. </s><s n="s4.6;p5.11">However, both models assume that the interactions between a certain analyte and the stationary phase remain constant. </s><s n="s5.6;p5.11">Therefore, it must be concluded that retention is determined by the composition of the mobile phase for any particular stationary phase. </s><s n="s6.6;p5.11">If both models have the same outcome it must be presumed that they are equivalent to another. </s></p><note place="end" id="BAWE_0388d-endnote.004"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.4;pn1.1"><hi rend="italic">High Performance Liquid Chromatography Fundamental Principles and Pratice</hi>, ed. </s><s n="s2.4;pn1.1">W. J. </s><s n="s3.4;pn1.1">Lough, I. W Wainer, Blackie Academic &amp; Professional, Glasgow, 1995, ch. </s><s n="s4.4;pn1.1">3, pp. 39-40 </s></p></note><note place="end" id="BAWE_0388d-endnote.005"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">V. Meyer, <hi rend="italic">Practical High-Performance Liquid Chromatography</hi>, Wiley, Weinheim, 4th edn., 2004, ch. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">10, pp. 159-161 </s></p></note><figure id="BAWE_0388d-fig.001"><head rend="bold">Figure 2: Retention model diagrams4</head></figure><p n="p6.11"><s n="s1.6;p6.11">At AstraZeneca reversed-phase HPLC is one of the most frequently used analytical methods. </s><s n="s2.6;p6.11">The ability of HPLC to separate a significant number of compounds within a mixture makes it ideal to detect the end of a reaction. </s><s n="s3.6;p6.11">All that is required is a representative sample of the reaction, which is dissolved in a similar solvent system to that used in the HPLC method. </s><s n="s4.6;p6.11">Dilution enables the scaling of the response of compounds so they do not exceed the limit of the detector. </s><s n="s5.6;p6.11">Complete dissolution is also important as a partially dissolved sample is not representative of the reaction, but also solid can be injected into the system, which can cause blockages. </s><s n="s6.6;p6.11">By comparing the chromatogram of the reaction to known compound retention times the progress of the reaction can be determined by checking for the absence of the starting material and the presence of the product. </s></p><p n="p7.11"><s n="s1.2;p7.11">My work has relied heavily on HPLC to detect the presence of certain impurities in a solid that had been isolated from a reaction spiked<ref target="BAWE_0388d-ftnote.001"/> with those impurities. </s><s n="s2.2;p7.11">HPLC can be used qualitatively to determine the presence of the impurities, but also quantitatively to calculate the mass of the impurity present in the sample. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0388d-ftnote.001"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">A spike is when a relatively very small amount of a compound under analysis is added to a much larger quantity of a different compound </s></p></note><figure id="BAWE_0388d-fig.002"><head rend="bold">Figure 3: Typical HPLC chromatogram</head></figure><p n="p8.11"><s n="s1.7;p8.11">Most HPLC apparatus uses UV detectors, which measure the UV absorbance of analyte compounds as they elute from the column. </s><s n="s2.7;p8.11">UV absorbance is a constant for a molecule of a compound, over a concentration range, and so is directly proportional to the concentration of the compound. </s><s n="s3.7;p8.11">The relative response of a compound can be calculated by measuring the response of a known quantity of known strength. </s><s n="s4.7;p8.11">From this calculation a scalar can be applied so the response in the chromatogram represents the physical proportion. </s><s n="s5.7;p8.11">The proportional relationship between response and concentration also means the strength<ref target="BAWE_0388d-ftnote.002"/> of a solid compound can be calculated by comparison to a measured standard. </s><s n="s6.7;p8.11">Providing the concentrations of the standard and sample are known then a direct comparison of the response can be made to determine the concentration of the compound in the sample solution and therefore the actual amount of the compound in the solid. </s><s n="s7.7;p8.11">The comparison can only be made over a given range of concentrations in which the response is linear. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0388d-ftnote.002"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Strength is defined as the mass of a compound in 100g of solid. </s></p></note><p n="p9.11"><s n="s1.4;p9.11">The advantages to HPLC are many and varied. </s><s n="s2.4;p9.11">As well as being fast, simple and accurate HPLC is also greatly versatile, due to both phases having a large number of variants.<ref target="BAWE_0388d-endnote.006"/> Sample preparation is also quite simple, as dissolution only requires the correct solvent, unlike gas chromatography (GC), another high-performance analytical method. </s><s n="s3.4;p9.11">GC can only approximately 20% of organic compounds, as it requires samples to be either volatile or able to evaporate without degradation. </s><s n="s4.4;p9.11">Simple dissolution is all that is needed for HPLC and allows the analysis of the majority of compounds.<hi rend="sup">2</hi> </s></p><note place="end" id="BAWE_0388d-endnote.006"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.3;pn1.1">J. M. </s><s n="s2.3;pn1.1">Miller, <hi rend="italic">Chromatography Concepts and Contrasts</hi>, Wiley, New Jersey, 2nd edn., 2005, ch. </s><s n="s3.3;pn1.1">8, pp. 184 </s></p></note><p n="p10.11"><s n="s1.4;p10.11">However, highly insoluble molecules may not dissolve to a high enough concentration to give a response. </s><s n="s2.4;p10.11">Also because the response of each compound vaires with how well it absorbs UV light a compound may not be detected due to its poor absorbance, or it may not absorb the light at all. </s><s n="s3.4;p10.11">However, compounds without a UV chromaphore can be analysed using a different detector, or by GC. Another disadvantage is the time needed to develop the best method, which is dependent on the number of compounds that need to be resolved. </s><s n="s4.4;p10.11">Without that method some compounds may have the same RT as others and this can lead to false negatives and positives. </s></p><p n="p11.11"><s n="s1.1;p11.11">The overall conclusion can be made that HPLC is an incredibly useful method and an important tool in qualitative and quantitative chemical analysis. </s></p></div1></body><back><div1 type="back text"><p><name type="student name"/></p><p>University Number: <name type="student ID"/></p><p>Course: Chemistry with Medicinal Chemistry with Industrial Training</p></div1><div1 type="bibliography"><head rend="underlined">References</head><p/></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
