<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_0397b" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Compare the nature and scope of the cases reported in the Chancery Division Reports for any year between 1950 and 1970 inclusive with those reported for any year between 2000 and 2005 inclusive, reflecting, for example, on changes in judicial attitudes over the intervening period.</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">Language used in quote: <foreign id="English">English</foreign></note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">deleted: header: module and student numbers; footer: page numbers</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">3</p><p n="date">unknown</p><p n="module title">Law of Trusts</p><p n="module code">LA307</p><p n="genre family">Essay</p><p n="discipline">Law</p><p n="disciplinary group">SS</p><p n="grade">unknown</p><p n="number of authors">unknown</p><p n="number of words">4915</p><p n="number of s-units">155</p><p n="number of p">37</p><p n="number of tables">0</p><p n="number of figures">0</p><p n="number of block quotes">6</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">0</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">0</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">31.7</p><p n="average s-units per p">4.2</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">f</p><p n="year of birth">1984</p><p n="first language">English</p><p n="education">UKA</p><p n="course">European Law</p><p n="student ID">0397</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><docTitle><titlePart rend="underlined bold">Compare the nature and scope of the cases reported in the Chancery Division Reports for any year between 1950 and 1970 inclusive with those reported for any year between 2000 and 2005 inclusive, reflecting, for example, on changes in judicial attitudes over the intervening period. </titlePart></docTitle></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="section"><p n="p1.37"><s n="s1.4;p1.37">The Chancery Division Reports are a comprehensive record of decisions of the Chancery Division Courts, and the judgements reported therein provide a chronology of legal developments. </s><s n="s2.4;p1.37">In this essay, the judgments will stimulate discussion of the courts in the regulation and creation of trusts law. </s><s n="s3.4;p1.37">With equity as a guiding concept, the Courts of Chancery have historically intervened in order to remedy defects in and compensate for the rigidity of the common law<ref target="BAWE_0397b-ftnote.001"/>. </s><s n="s4.4;p1.37">The subject of disputes before the court fluctuates as binding precedents are established and new legislation introduced. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0397b-ftnote.001"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">p 5 Pearce R and Stevens J <hi rend="italic">The Law of Trusts and Equitable Obligations</hi> 4th Edition, Oxford University Press 2006 </s></p></note><p n="p2.37"><s n="s1.5;p2.37">This essay will focus on the wealth of decisions from 1953 and contrast them with those of exactly 50 years later, decisions which in relation to trusts law are considerably fewer in number, but no less in value. </s><s n="s2.5;p2.37">Broadly speaking, there has been a shift in the emphasis of the matters brought before the court. </s><s n="s3.5;p2.37">Firstly, there are fewer decisions in 2003 which relate directly to trusts law, with a marked decrease in issues arising from the construction of trusts instruments when compared to the numerous requests for clarification of the scope of terms in 1953<ref target="BAWE_0397b-ftnote.002"/>. </s><s n="s4.5;p2.37">The correlative to this is that there have been additional areas of law for the courts to consider. </s><s n="s5.5;p2.37">The breach of EU Council Regulations<ref target="BAWE_0397b-ftnote.003"/> and potential violation of the Human Rights Act 1998<ref target="BAWE_0397b-ftnote.004"/> are beyond the scope of this essay, but demonstrate the evolutionary nature of the English legal system. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0397b-ftnote.002"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">For example 'if continuing in service' in <hi rend="italic">Re Kendrew</hi> [1953] Ch 291, 'movables' in <hi rend="italic">Re Walsh</hi> [1953] Ch 473 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0397b-ftnote.003"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1"><hi rend="italic">Antonio Muñoz y Cia SA v Frumar Ltd</hi> [2003] Ch 328 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0397b-ftnote.004"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1"><hi rend="italic">Gascoyne v Custom and Excise Commissioners</hi> [2003] Ch 292 </s></p></note><p n="p3.37"><s n="s1.5;p3.37">A theme which is echoed between the years is the way in which intervention of the Chancery Division is required to resolve issues arising from uncertainty or error in the execution of trusts instruments. </s><s n="s2.5;p3.37">It is possible to attribute an element of this uncertainty to attempts at the creative use of the trust, with legal concepts being "manipulated" to achieve beneficial fiscal outcomes<ref target="BAWE_0397b-ftnote.005"/>. </s><s n="s3.5;p3.37"><hi rend="italic">Re Downshire Settled Estates; Re Blackwell's Settlement Trusts; Re Chapman's Settlement Trust</hi><ref target="BAWE_0397b-ftnote.006"/> is one such situation, where the beneficiaries sought to extend the rules of variation of trusts in order to avoid taxation. </s><s n="s4.5;p3.37">With regard to error, the case law in 2003 offers an illustration of errors attributable to trustees and their decisions<ref target="BAWE_0397b-ftnote.007"/>. </s><s n="s5.5;p3.37">The theme of tax avoidance reoccurs indirectly, on this occasion framed in terms of the extent to which the court can intervene to enable the avoidance of detrimental fiscal consequences of trustees' decisions. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0397b-ftnote.005"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">p 108 Moffat G <hi rend="italic">Trusts Law: Texts and materials</hi> 4th Edition, Cambridge University Press, 2005 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0397b-ftnote.006"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">[1953] Ch 218, henceforth <hi rend="italic">Re Chapman</hi> </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0397b-ftnote.007"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">See for example <hi rend="italic">Abacus Trust Co (Isle of Man) and Another v Barr and Others</hi> [2003] Ch 409, henceforth <hi rend="italic">Re Barr</hi> </s></p></note><p n="p4.37"><s n="s1.4;p4.37">It would trivialise the relationship between law and society to enter into speculation as to the extralegal causes and extent of change at this point, but it is important to note that the use of the trust is closely associated with social, political and economic change so as to maximise benefit for the beneficiaries of the trust. </s><s n="s2.4;p4.37">The analysis will focus on overarching themes within the context of trusts, such as judicial intervention, discretion and the awareness of the extralegal consequences of decisions. </s><s n="s3.4;p4.37">With these ideas as the framework, comment will be directed towards the consideration of tax avoidance. </s><s n="s4.4;p4.37">The structure will be based around the decisions of <hi rend="italic">Re Chapman</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Re Gestetner Settlement</hi><ref target="BAWE_0397b-ftnote.008"/>, and <hi rend="italic">Re Barr</hi>, adopting a comparative perspective between 1953 and 2003. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0397b-ftnote.008"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">[1953] Ch 673 </s></p></note></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">1953: the establishment of principle</head><div2><head rend="underlined">Re Chapman: curtailing the beneficiaries' cunning plan</head><p n="p5.37"><s n="s1.4;p5.37">When considering the cases from 1953, <hi rend="italic">Re Chapman</hi> clearly stands out due to its overt and direct acknowledgement that both settlors and beneficiaries may seek to minimise their tax liability, and may obtain the court's approval to do so. </s><s n="s2.4;p5.37">Prior to the decision, it was believed by settlors and their advisers that there was a "safety valve" in the Chancery Division, which left scope for variation of trusts in order to meet the interests of beneficiaries through the accommodation of fiscal developments<ref target="BAWE_0397b-ftnote.009"/>. </s><s n="s3.4;p5.37">This is why the case was so important. </s><s n="s4.4;p5.37">It had the potential to permit gross departures from the trust instrument in order to defeat "the villain whose evil designs must be thwarted"<ref target="BAWE_0397b-ftnote.010"/>, an issue which would have considerable impact on future cases<ref target="BAWE_0397b-ftnote.011"/>. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0397b-ftnote.009"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">p 381 Mitchell J <hi rend="italic">The Court of Chancery and Trust</hi> (1953) 16 MLR (July) pp 381 - 382 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0397b-ftnote.010"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Cozens-Hardy Horne referring to a possible perception of the Inland Revenue at p 256 Cozens-Hardy Horne R <hi rend="italic">Modern Methods of minimising Taxation - VI - Discretionary Settlements</hi> British Tax Review 1957 pp 256-260 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0397b-ftnote.011"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">per Evershed MR [1953] Ch 218 at p 232 </s></p></note><p n="p6.37"><s n="s1.2;p6.37">Putting to one side the statutory regime of the Trustee Act 1925 and the Settled Land Act 1925 for reasons of space and clarity, there are two key elements to the decision: the tax considerations and discussions of the court's inherent jurisdiction. </s><s n="s2.2;p6.37">The judges' position on tax avoidance was undivided: </s></p><quote lang="English">"it is not an objection to the sanction by the court of any proposed scheme in regard to trust property that its object or effect is or may be to reduce liability for tax"<ref target="BAWE_0397b-ftnote.012"/>. </quote><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0397b-ftnote.012"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">ibid at p 233 </s></p></note><p n="p7.37"><s n="s1.2;p7.37">A linguistic analysis of the breadth of this test initially suggests that the court is proposing a wide jurisdiction, with the use of "or" and "may be" intended to be inclusive terms. </s><s n="s2.2;p7.37">However, Evershed MR also demonstrates concern that an extension of the role of the courts would open the floodgates to future litigation and clarifies that </s></p><quote lang="English">"it is no part of the functions of Her Majesty's courts to recast settlements from time to time, merely with a view to tax avoidance even if they had the power to do so which, in our opinion, they have not"<ref target="BAWE_0397b-ftnote.013"/>. </quote><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0397b-ftnote.013"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">ibid at p 266 </s></p></note><p n="p8.37"><s n="s1.2;p8.37">While tax avoidance schemes may be authorised under the umbrella of compromise, they are not strong enough justification to stand alone and unprotected. </s><s n="s2.2;p8.37">Lord Denning provides an insight into the reasoning for allowing tax avoidance, and focuses on the role of the court as protector of infant beneficiaries, not the revenue<ref target="BAWE_0397b-ftnote.014"/>. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0397b-ftnote.014"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">per Denning LJ [1953] Ch 218 at p 276 </s></p></note><p n="p9.37"><s n="s1.5;p9.37">The approach taken to the inherent jurisdiction of the courts differs between the judges. </s><s n="s2.5;p9.37">Lord Denning offers a dissenting judgement, and reaches a different conclusion in the matter of the Chapman settlement. </s><s n="s3.5;p9.37">Evershed MR and Romer LJ were keen to ensure that the regime for variation remained within the existing framework of approval of a compromise. </s><s n="s4.5;p9.37">By stating that a general inherent jurisdiction would be inconsistent with the cases of <hi rend="italic">In re New</hi><ref target="BAWE_0397b-ftnote.015"/> and <hi rend="italic">In re Tollemache</hi><ref target="BAWE_0397b-ftnote.016"/>, yet allowing the definition of compromise to be broadly construed so a not "to be confined to compromises of dispute rights<ref target="BAWE_0397b-ftnote.017"/>, the majority appear to maintain a delicate balance between flexibility and fidelity to the settlors intentions at the time of settlement. </s><s n="s5.5;p9.37">Commentators have noted the "anxiety of the court to avoid any rigid definition of the jurisdiction"<ref target="BAWE_0397b-ftnote.018"/>, and this is evidenced by a general reliance on the principle <hi rend="italic">In re Trenchard</hi><ref target="BAWE_0397b-ftnote.019"/>. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0397b-ftnote.015"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">[1901] 2 Ch 534 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0397b-ftnote.016"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">[1903] 1 Ch 457 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0397b-ftnote.017"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">per Evershed MR [1953] Ch 218 at pp 233 and 239 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0397b-ftnote.018"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">p 382 Mitchell J <hi rend="italic">The Court of Chancery and Trusts</hi> [1953] MLR vol 16 (July) pp 381 - 382 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0397b-ftnote.019"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">[1902] 1 Ch. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">378. </s></p></note><p n="p10.37"><s n="s1.5;p10.37">Denning LJ concludes that the jurisdiction of the court is not limited to cases of compromise<ref target="BAWE_0397b-ftnote.020"/>. </s><s n="s2.5;p10.37">In explaining his decision, Denning LJ has regard for "the gap between non-legal social fact and the limits of formal precedent-based doctrine"<ref target="BAWE_0397b-ftnote.021"/>. </s><s n="s3.5;p10.37">Ever mindful of the protective role of the court towards the infant beneficiaries, Denning LJ also finds justification in the fact that the settlors "are ready and anxious to correct the mistake"<ref target="BAWE_0397b-ftnote.022"/>. </s><s n="s4.5;p10.37">Reading Denning LJ's judgement, it appears that the starting point for his decision was a pre-existing conviction that variation should be allowed in these cases. </s><s n="s5.5;p10.37">Authorities are introduced to support his conclusion, but throughout the judgement it is clear his reasoning is shaped by the core principles of the Chancery Division, particularly that of equity<ref target="BAWE_0397b-ftnote.023"/>. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0397b-ftnote.020"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">per Denning LJ [1953] Ch 218 at p 269 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0397b-ftnote.021"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">p 317 Moffat G <hi rend="italic">Trusts Law: Texts and materials</hi> 4th Edition, Cambridge University Press, 2005 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0397b-ftnote.022"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">p 278 note 21 supra </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0397b-ftnote.023"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">For example see comments at pp 269 and 278, note 21 supra </s></p></note><p n="p11.37"><s n="s1.5;p11.37">While this essay is primarily concerned with decisions reported in the Chancery Division reports, the contrast between the decision of the Court of Appeal and that of the House of Lords in the case of Chapman v Chapman<ref target="BAWE_0397b-ftnote.024"/> provides a basis for contextualising the Court of Appeal decision. </s><s n="s2.5;p11.37">Although the House of Lords (Cohen LJ dissenting) affirmed the decision of the majority, their reasoning was founded on a much narrower interpretation of the concept of compromise. </s><s n="s3.5;p11.37">Simonds LC, in a judgement which exemplifies his "restrictive attitude to precedent"<ref target="BAWE_0397b-ftnote.025"/>, refused to extend the court's jurisdiction to "cases in which there is no real dispute as to rights"<ref target="BAWE_0397b-ftnote.026"/>, ensuring that the court was not required to intervene on the whim of a beneficiary. </s><s n="s4.5;p11.37">He justifies his conclusion with an analysis of the role of the Chancery Division, finding that it is to regulate and administer the execution of the trust, not to sanction unnecessary, although potentially beneficial, alterations<ref target="BAWE_0397b-ftnote.027"/>. </s><s n="s5.5;p11.37">This analysis echoes that of Evershed MR in the Court of Appeal, while contradicting Denning LJ, and serves as an example of the difficulties inherent in discerning the guiding principles of the court as a whole. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0397b-ftnote.024"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">[1954] AC 429 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0397b-ftnote.025"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">p 133 Paterson A <hi rend="italic">The Law Lords</hi> MacMillan Press Ltd, London 1982 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0397b-ftnote.026"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">[1954] AC 429 at p 445 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0397b-ftnote.027"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid at p 446 </s></p></note><p n="p12.37"><s n="s1.6;p12.37">Consideration is also given to the settlor's intentions: "<hi rend="italic">Chapman v Chapman</hi> powerfully reaffirmed the principle of respect for the intention of the settlor as expressed in the terms of the trust instrument"<ref target="BAWE_0397b-ftnote.028"/>. </s><s n="s2.6;p12.37">Combined with the unwillingness to approve variation outside of a compromise situation, the court's attitude appears to be primarily one of fidelity to the trust instrument; they will not be swayed in their decisions by considerations beyond its scope. </s><s n="s3.6;p12.37">The judgements of Simonds and Morton LJJ also show deference to the legislature, with Simonds LJ noting that "[i]t is for the legislature...to determine whether there should be a change in the law and what that change should be"<ref target="BAWE_0397b-ftnote.029"/>. </s><s n="s4.6;p12.37">This is an exemplar of substantive formalism as identified by Stevens<ref target="BAWE_0397b-ftnote.030"/>, something which Denning LJ's argument lacks. </s><s n="s5.6;p12.37">The distinction creates the impression that the Court of Appeal decision is comparably more permissive, which in turn leads to ambiguity. </s><s n="s6.6;p12.37">While the House of Lords did not concur with the decisions reached with regard to the Downshire and Blackwell settlements<ref target="BAWE_0397b-ftnote.031"/>, the cases were not appealed, and remain law. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0397b-ftnote.028"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">p 317 Moffat G <hi rend="italic">Trusts Law: Texts and materials</hi> 4th Edition, Cambridge University Press, 2005 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0397b-ftnote.029"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">[1954] Ch 429 at p 444 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0397b-ftnote.030"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">p 350 Stevens R <hi rend="italic">Law and Politics, The House of Lords as a Judicial Body 1800 - 1976</hi> Carolina Press, Chapel Hill 1978. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0397b-ftnote.031"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">per Lord Morton of Henryton [1954] Ch 429 at p 462: "It follows that, in my view, the majority of the Court of Appeal were right in dismissing this appeal, but their decisions in In re Downshire Settled Estates and In re Blackwell's Settlement Trusts went too far." </s></p></note><quote lang="English" rend="underlined">Re Gestetner: Tax avoidance as a stimulus for original development </quote><p n="p13.37"><s n="s1.3;p13.37">While the judges in <hi rend="italic">Re Chapman</hi> were limiting a previously presumed jurisdiction with regard to variation, <hi rend="italic">Re Gestetner Settlement</hi><ref target="BAWE_0397b-ftnote.032"/> was responding to a new and emerging problem: that of uncertainty in discretionary trusts. </s><s n="s2.3;p13.37">Grbich argues that "practitioners were forced by revenue stimuli and the practical necessity of business reality into the flexible realms of discretionary trusts"<ref target="BAWE_0397b-ftnote.033"/>. </s><s n="s3.3;p13.37">The nature of the case in <hi rend="italic">Re Gestetner</hi> is synoptic of the legal issues surrounding certainty that emerged post World War Two, and were not satisfactorily resolved until McPhail v Doulton<ref target="BAWE_0397b-ftnote.034"/> in May 1970. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0397b-ftnote.032"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">[1953] Ch 672 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0397b-ftnote.033"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">p 656 Grbich Y <hi rend="italic">Baden: Awakening the Conceptually Moribund Trust</hi> (1974) 37 MLR 6 (Nov) pp 643 - 656 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0397b-ftnote.034"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">[1971] AC 424 </s></p></note><p n="p14.37"><s n="s1.7;p14.37">The case, a summons taken out by the trustees, arose out the payment of monies to one of the charities named in the settlement, and the subsequent refusal of the Chief Inspector of Taxes (Claims) to repay the income tax deducted at source<ref target="BAWE_0397b-ftnote.035"/>. </s><s n="s2.7;p14.37">These facts give rise to three fiscal elements to the decision. </s><s n="s3.7;p14.37">Firstly, it highlights the problems of uncertainty when the beneficial class is set this wide in order to avoid the payment of estate duty upon the death of a beneficiary<ref target="BAWE_0397b-ftnote.036"/>; provided the beneficiary's precise share of the settlement remains unknown, it is not liable for tax. </s><s n="s4.7;p14.37">Thus, particularly where there is a duty to distribute, the beneficial class is broad so as to ensure that at no point one beneficiary is solely entitled to the settlement. </s><s n="s5.7;p14.37">Secondly, the case highlights the possibility for the Inland Revenue to be a party to proceedings, ensuring that policy arguments concerning the fiscal consequences of the case are heard. </s><s n="s6.7;p14.37">Finally, there is the effect of the decision for the recipient charity. </s><s n="s7.7;p14.37">If the settlement was found to be void, the donation to charity would be a personal one, which "did not give any right to the charity to recover the tax paid"<ref target="BAWE_0397b-ftnote.037"/>, thus depriving it of additional funds. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0397b-ftnote.035"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">p 675 [1953] Ch 672 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0397b-ftnote.036"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">p 310 Megarry R <hi rend="italic">Notes</hi> (1953) 69 LQR (July) pp 309 - 311 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0397b-ftnote.037"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">p 682 [1953] Ch 672 </s></p></note><p n="p15.37"><s n="s1.3;p15.37">To the financial benefit of the charity in question, Harman J came to the conclusion that the settlement was valid. </s><s n="s2.3;p15.37">The test held to be applicable in cases where there is no duty to distribute, but only a duty to consider is what has become known as the given postulant test<ref target="BAWE_0397b-ftnote.038"/>: for a power to be certain, it must be possible to ascertain whether any given person is or is not an object of the power. </s><s n="s3.3;p15.37">As with the judgement of Denning LJ in <hi rend="italic">Re Chapman</hi>, it is possible to make the inference that the judge reached a conclusion, sought evidence to support it, and did not search for anything contradictory, "There being no uncertainty in that sense, I am reluctant to introduce a notion of uncertainty in the other sense"<ref target="BAWE_0397b-ftnote.039"/>. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0397b-ftnote.038"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">p 60 Oakley A <hi rend="italic">Parker &amp; Mellows: The Modern Law of Trusts</hi> 8th Edition, Sweet &amp; Maxwell, London 2003 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0397b-ftnote.039"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">p 688 [1953] Ch 672 </s></p></note><p n="p16.37"><s n="s1.5;p16.37">In a judgement which does not acknowledge the implications of the decision on tax avoidance, Harman J is motivated in his decision by consideration of two interrelated factors: the settlor's intentions and the practicalities of effecting the settlement. </s><s n="s2.5;p16.37">With regard to the settlor's intentions, Harman J finds justification for not requiring the 'trustee' to survey the whole field in the fact that it "is a task which was and which must have been known to the settlor to be impossible..."<ref target="BAWE_0397b-ftnote.040"/>. </s><s n="s3.5;p16.37">This is a rational inference to be made: if the settlor himself did not feel inclined to include beneficiaries with enough clarity so that they could be considered, it is unlikely that financial provision for them was his paramount concern. </s><s n="s4.5;p16.37">As for the practicalities of distribution, Harman J proffers the conclusion that it is not necessary for the 'trustees' to "worry their heads to survey the world from China to Peru, when there are perfectly good objects of the class in England"<ref target="BAWE_0397b-ftnote.041"/>. </s><s n="s5.5;p16.37">From this it is possible to conclude that the judge is of the opinion that the settlement was intended to be put into practice, and not to be an abstract conundrum for the trustees. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0397b-ftnote.040"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">ibid </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0397b-ftnote.041"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">ibid </s></p></note><p n="p17.37"><s n="s1.6;p17.37">Harman J's concern for the practicalities and clarity of judgement suggests that he intends to facilitate the use of powers. </s><s n="s2.6;p17.37">It had been argued that the use of powers was too precarious as any uncertainty would render the whole settlement void, but Megarry suggests that the "<hi rend="italic">Gestetner Case</hi> may go far towards meeting these objections"<ref target="BAWE_0397b-ftnote.042"/>. </s><s n="s3.6;p17.37">However, it would be naïve to consider the case in isolation, and the inherent dangers difficulties arise when the decision is considered alongside that in <hi rend="italic">IRC v Broadway Cottages Trust</hi><ref target="BAWE_0397b-ftnote.043"/>. </s><s n="s4.6;p17.37">Although <hi rend="italic">Re Gestetner</hi> demonstrates a support of a clear overarching framework as a method of enabling the use of powers, the effect when combined with <hi rend="italic">Broadway Cottages</hi> was that each case still required close analysis with regard to its certainty. </s><s n="s5.6;p17.37">A crucial difference between a discretionary trust and a mere power was established, such that it was the subtle nuances of the facts of each case that led to the overwhelmingly important determination of the applicable test for certainty<ref target="BAWE_0397b-ftnote.044"/>. </s><s n="s6.6;p17.37">In this respect fidelity to historical precedent<ref target="BAWE_0397b-ftnote.045"/> from Harman J and Jenkins LJ et al resulted in a perilous situation for those trying to avoid or limit tax in the 1950s: "if the certainty of objects requirement was not satisfied, a resulting trust might arise with potentially onerous income tax or estate duty consequences for the settlor"<ref target="BAWE_0397b-ftnote.046"/>. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0397b-ftnote.042"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">p 311 Megarry R Notes (1953) 69 LQR (July) pp 309 - 311 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0397b-ftnote.043"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">[1955] Ch 20, p 61 Oakley A Parker &amp; Mellows: The Modern Law of Trusts 8th Edition, Sweet &amp; Maxwell, London 2003 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0397b-ftnote.044"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">p 61 Oakley A Parker &amp; Mellows: The Modern Law of Trusts 8th Edition, Sweet &amp; Maxwell, London 2003 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0397b-ftnote.045"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.4;pn1.1">For example <hi rend="italic">Blight v.</hi> </s><s n="s2.4;pn1.1"><hi rend="italic">Hartnoll</hi> (1881) 19 Ch.D. 294, and <hi rend="italic">Morice v.</hi> </s><s n="s3.4;pn1.1"><hi rend="italic">Bishop of Durham</hi> (1805) 10 Ves. </s><s n="s4.4;pn1.1">522 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0397b-ftnote.046"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">p 208 Moffat G <hi rend="italic">Trusts Law: Texts and materials</hi> 4th Edition, Cambridge University Press, 2005 </s></p></note><quote lang="English" rend="underlined">Summary of the approach in 1953</quote><p n="p18.37"><s n="s1.6;p18.37">In the aftermath of <hi rend="italic">Re Chapman</hi>,<hi rend="italic"> Re Gestetner</hi> and their associated cases, the court's approach appears on the surface to be difficult to reconcile. </s><s n="s2.6;p18.37">On one hand the court had limited the possibilities for tax avoidance, by restricting its jurisdiction to sanction variation of the trust instrument, while on the other ensuring that settlements created for tax avoidance purposes were allowed to stand on the basis of a lower threshold for certainty. </s><s n="s3.6;p18.37">Unity in the decisions comes from an analysis of their attitude to the intervention of the courts. </s><s n="s4.6;p18.37">In <hi rend="italic">Re Chapman</hi> it is explicitly stated that the court should not be requested to sanction non-essential amendments to the trust instrument<ref target="BAWE_0397b-ftnote.047"/>. </s><s n="s5.6;p18.37">Intervention is not an express factor in <hi rend="italic">Re Gestetner</hi>, but it has been observed that it is the court's inability to intervene so as to effect distribution under a mere power which may have resulted in a more flexible threshold for certainty<ref target="BAWE_0397b-ftnote.048"/>. </s><s n="s6.6;p18.37">In turn, the court's reluctance to intervene reflects and promotes the fidelity to the settlor's intentions expressed in the case. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0397b-ftnote.047"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">per Evershed MR, [1953] Ch 218 at p 266 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0397b-ftnote.048"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">p 113 Watt G <hi rend="italic">Trusts and Equity</hi> 2nd Edition, Oxford University Press, 2005 </s></p></note></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">Evolution and Expansion</head><p n="p19.37"><s n="s1.2;p19.37">Having raised some of the key issues before the court in 1953, it is now possible to look at the extent of change when compared to 2003. </s><s n="s2.2;p19.37">In order to contextualise the case law in 2003, I first propose to briefly consider the intermediate developments which offer insight into judicial attitudes in this area of trusts law. </s></p><div2><head rend="underlined">Threads of development </head><div3><head rend="italic">The conclusion to Re Chapman: the Variation of Trusts Act</head><p n="p20.37"><s n="s1.5;p20.37">Following the decisions relating to the Chapman, Downshire and Blackwell settlements discussed above, the law was in a state of flux. </s><s n="s2.5;p20.37">The tension between the Court of Appeal and House of Lords decisions with regard to variation of trusts left the law in unclear, "and accordingly the question of the extent of the Court's jurisdiction in these cases was ... referred to the Law Reform Committee"<ref target="BAWE_0397b-ftnote.049"/>. </s><s n="s3.5;p20.37">In an essay concerned with case law it might appear superfluous to digress into discussions of legislative reform, but as will be explored below, the VTA<ref target="BAWE_0397b-ftnote.050"/> shaped the nature and scope of discussions in subsequent case law. </s><s n="s4.5;p20.37">Much of the commentary surround the VTA has highlighted the shift from the approach in <hi rend="italic">Chapman v Chapman</hi><ref target="BAWE_0397b-ftnote.051"/> and fidelity to the settlor's intentions to that of the Law Reform Committee which was "moved by the spirit of equitable property"<ref target="BAWE_0397b-ftnote.052"/>. </s><s n="s5.5;p20.37">The composition of the Law Reform Committee included five judges, and thus there is evidence to suggest that judicial attitudes had begun to change, with greater favour being given to the beneficiaries. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0397b-ftnote.049"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">p 59 Keeton G <hi rend="italic">Social Change in the Law of Trusts</hi> Sir Isaac Pitman &amp; Sons ltd, London, 1958 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0397b-ftnote.050"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Variation of Trusts Act 1958 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0397b-ftnote.051"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">see note 29 supra </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0397b-ftnote.052"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">p 14 Harris J <hi rend="italic">Variation of Trusts</hi> Sweet &amp; Maxwell, London, 1975 </s></p></note><p n="p21.37"><s n="s1.6;p21.37">The debates in the House of Lords provide an insight into evolving judicial values. </s><s n="s2.6;p21.37">Viscount Simonds recognised the potential use of the new regime and found the avoidance of tax to be "an object from which I, for one, do not dissent in any way"<ref target="BAWE_0397b-ftnote.053"/>. </s><s n="s3.6;p21.37">This suggests that his limitative decision in <hi rend="italic">Chapman v Chapman</hi> was firmly based on the extent of the jurisdiction of the court, not on the propriety of tax avoidance. </s><s n="s4.6;p21.37">He also proposed the inclusion of a clause making express provision that the VTA could be used where its main purpose was "to avoid the exigibility of tax"<ref target="BAWE_0397b-ftnote.054"/>. </s><s n="s5.6;p21.37">His fear was that judges might "take different views on the rightness of the scheme whose sole object was to avoid tax"<ref target="BAWE_0397b-ftnote.055"/>. </s><s n="s6.6;p21.37">On the basis that the jurisdiction needed to be flexible and capable of limitation where the variation is of "questionable character", the clause was not included<ref target="BAWE_0397b-ftnote.056"/>. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0397b-ftnote.053"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1"><hi rend="italic">Variation of Trusts Bill</hi> 210 HL Official Report (5th series) col 377, 30 June 1958 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0397b-ftnote.054"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1"><hi rend="italic">Variation of Trusts Bill</hi> 210 HL Official Report (5th series) col 377, 30 June 1958 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0397b-ftnote.055"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">p 86 Harris J <hi rend="italic">Variation of Trusts</hi> Sweet &amp; Maxwell, London, 1975, referring to Hansard (H.L. deb), Vol 209, cols. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">841-842. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0397b-ftnote.056"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1"><hi rend="italic">Variation of Trusts Bill</hi> 210 HL Official Report (5th series) col 381-2, 30 June 1958 </s></p></note></div3><div3><head rend="italic">The VTA as a building block for the consideration of tax</head><p n="p22.37"><s n="s1.4;p22.37">Perhaps refreshed by the introduction of the VTA, tax avoidance remained a direct concern for the courts. </s><s n="s2.4;p22.37">With the courts ability to sanction tax avoidance agreements confirmed, new questions arose as to the ways in which this should be exercised. </s><s n="s3.4;p22.37">In this respect, it is clear that to some extent Viscount Simonds' fears concerning judicial attitudes towards tax avoidance were realised in the case of <hi rend="italic">Re Weston's Settlement</hi><ref target="BAWE_0397b-ftnote.057"/>. </s><s n="s4.4;p22.37">The applicant in the case sought to export a settlement from England to Jersey in order to avoid tax, but was denied his request at first instance and on appeal, instead receiving a sermon from Denning LJ on the correct way to raise children<ref target="BAWE_0397b-ftnote.058"/>. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0397b-ftnote.057"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">[1969] 1 Ch 223 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0397b-ftnote.058"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">pp 245 - 6 [1969] 1 Ch 223: "Many a child has been ruined by being given too much", "Children are like trees: they grow stronger with firm roots", "There are many things in life more worth while than money. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">One of these things is to be brought up in this our England, which is still 'the envy of less happier lands'". </s></p></note><p n="p23.37"><s n="s1.5;p23.37">Questions have been raised as to whether <hi rend="italic">Re Weston</hi> is "an undesirable example of judicial paternalism"<ref target="BAWE_0397b-ftnote.059"/>, and in a sense this is the crux of the case: is it a careful reflection on all the possible benefits of variation, into which Denning introduces extra-legal considerations, or is there the emergence of moral consideration, such that the court feels it cannot approve an arrangement which is "tainted with 'illegitimate tax avoidance'"?<ref target="BAWE_0397b-ftnote.060"/>. </s><s n="s2.5;p23.37">Commentators have struggled to reach a firm conclusion on the matter. </s><s n="s3.5;p23.37">However, evidence adduced to suggest that the court is motivated in its decision by a distaste for tax avoidance helps to bolster claims that the nature of debates surrounding the tax avoidance has mutated since <hi rend="italic">Re Chapman</hi>. </s><s n="s4.5;p23.37">Stamp J recognises that the court's loyalty does not necessarily lie with the Inland Revenue<ref target="BAWE_0397b-ftnote.061"/> but suggests that "there must ... be some limit to the devices which this court ought to countenance in order to defeat the fiscal intentions of the legislature"<ref target="BAWE_0397b-ftnote.062"/>, an argument which was not raised when tax avoidance was condoned by the court in <hi rend="italic">Re Chapman</hi>. </s><s n="s5.5;p23.37">This is echoed by Denning LJ: "avoidance of tax may be lawful, but it is not yet a virtue"<ref target="BAWE_0397b-ftnote.063"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0397b-ftnote.059"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">p 333 Moffat G <hi rend="italic">Trusts Law: Texts and materials</hi> 4th Edition, Cambridge University Press, 2005 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0397b-ftnote.060"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">p 321 Harris J <hi rend="italic">Variation of Trusts and Tax Avoidance</hi> [1969] 32 MLR (May) pp 320 - 323 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0397b-ftnote.061"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">A principle also noted in <hi rend="italic">Re Slocock's Will Trusts</hi> [1979] 1 All ER 358 "If a mistake is made in a document legitimately designed to avoid the payment of tax, there is no reason why it should not be corrected. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">The Crown is in no privileged position qua such a document". </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0397b-ftnote.062"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">p 232 [1969] 1 Ch 223 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0397b-ftnote.063"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">p 245 [1969] 1 Ch 223 </s></p></note></div3><div3><head rend="italic">McPhail v Doulton: certainty resolved</head><p n="p24.37"><s n="s1.2;p24.37">As with the legislation pursuant to <hi rend="italic">Re Chapman,</hi> subsequent developments following <hi rend="italic">Re Gestetner</hi> and <hi rend="italic"> Broadway Cottages</hi> remedied any resultant fiscal difficulties for beneficiaries. </s><s n="s2.2;p24.37">It was noted at the time that <hi rend="italic">Re Gestetner</hi> </s></p><quote lang="English"> "breaks entirely new ground on the relationship of powers ... and trusts, and ... it is probably the forerunner of much new authority of considerable importance"<ref target="BAWE_0397b-ftnote.064"/>. </quote><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0397b-ftnote.064"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">p 241 (1953) 17 Conv 240 - 241 </s></p></note><p n="p25.37"><s n="s1.5;p25.37">As suggested above<ref target="BAWE_0397b-ftnote.065"/>, that new authority came in 1970 with the case of <hi rend="italic">McPhail v Doulton</hi><ref target="BAWE_0397b-ftnote.066"/>. </s><s n="s2.5;p25.37">Aligning the tests for certainty of powers and discretionary trusts, the case represents a "triumph of pragmatism over theory"<ref target="BAWE_0397b-ftnote.067"/>. </s><s n="s3.5;p25.37">Overruling <hi rend="italic">Broadway Cottages</hi>, Wilberforce LJ examines the role of the court and the way in which it can be called upon to execute the trust. </s><s n="s4.5;p25.37">Whereas the decision in <hi rend="italic">Broadway Cottages</hi> assumed that the application of the maxim 'equity is equality' would result in equal distribution throughout the beneficial class, Wilberforce LJ turned to the settlor's intentions for guidance: "[e]qual division is surely the last thing the settlor ever intended: equal division among all may, probably would, produce a result beneficial to none"<ref target="BAWE_0397b-ftnote.068"/>. </s><s n="s5.5;p25.37">While the consequences of the decision represent a "fundamental change in judicial attitudes"<ref target="BAWE_0397b-ftnote.069"/>, examining the nature and structure of Wilberforce's judgement, it is clear that his reasoning based on the settlor's intentions is not dissimilar to that of Harman J in <hi rend="italic">Re Gestetner</hi><ref target="BAWE_0397b-ftnote.070"/>. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0397b-ftnote.065"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">note 36 supra </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0397b-ftnote.066"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">[1971] AC 424 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0397b-ftnote.067"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">p 114 Watt G <hi rend="italic">Trusts and Equity</hi> 2nd Edition, Oxford University Press, 2005 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0397b-ftnote.068"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">p 451 [1971] AC 424 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0397b-ftnote.069"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">p 63 Oakley A <hi rend="italic">Parker &amp; Mellows: The Modern Law of Trusts</hi> 8th Edition, Sweet &amp; Maxwell, London, 2003 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0397b-ftnote.070"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">See for example p 688 [1953] Ch 672 </s></p></note></div3><div3><head rend="italic">Re Hastings-Bass: the court as administrator and enforcer of trustee discretion</head><p n="p26.37"><s n="s1.4;p26.37">In summarising <hi rend="italic">Re Chapman</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Re Gestetner</hi> reference was made to the way in which the decisions were partly explained by the judges' opinion that the courts should abstain from intervention. </s><s n="s2.4;p26.37">The case of <hi rend="italic">Re Hastings-Bass (dec'd)</hi><ref target="BAWE_0397b-ftnote.071"/> recognises that intervention is more necessary in cases where a mistake has been made by a trustee in the execution or administration of a settlement. </s><s n="s3.4;p26.37">Green notes that at the heart of the principle drawn from the case is "the existence of the trustee's duty to consider ... </s><s n="s4.4;p26.37">A breach of the duty to consider is a breach of fiduciary duty, and a platform from which the court may intervene"<ref target="BAWE_0397b-ftnote.072"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0397b-ftnote.071"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">[1970] Ch 25 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0397b-ftnote.072"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">p 116 Green B <hi rend="italic">The law relating to trustees' mistakes - where are we now?</hi> </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">(2003) 17(3) TLI pp 114 - 128 </s></p></note><p n="p27.37"><s n="s1.2;p27.37">However, this intervention is limited to situations where the trustee has exceeded his powers or erred in making relevant and excluding irrelevant considerations<ref target="BAWE_0397b-ftnote.073"/>. </s><s n="s2.2;p27.37">The outcome of the application of this rule was that estate duty was not payable on the settlor's death, and it was recognised in the case that "[w]e can feel no doubt that in such circumstances the duty-saving aspect of the scheme was a primary consideration in the minds of the trustees"<ref target="BAWE_0397b-ftnote.074"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0397b-ftnote.073"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">p 41 [1970] Ch 25 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0397b-ftnote.074"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">p 39 [1970] Ch 25 </s></p></note><p n="p28.37"><s n="s1.6;p28.37">The appraisal of the effect of the decision will vary according to whose perspective it is considered from. </s><s n="s2.6;p28.37">A trustee's perception of the case is likely to be favourable: the rule can be seen to promote practical certainty. </s><s n="s3.6;p28.37">It allows trustees to make decisions without fear of constant challenge<ref target="BAWE_0397b-ftnote.075"/>. </s><s n="s4.6;p28.37">It can also generally be considered "a useful and convenient escape route where trustees make a mistake"<ref target="BAWE_0397b-ftnote.076"/>. </s><s n="s5.6;p28.37">While many would argue that this is to be encouraged, the counterpoint is that the beneficiaries, settlors and trustees will be unable to challenge the decision where it is the consequences of their decision have been misunderstood<ref target="BAWE_0397b-ftnote.077"/>. </s><s n="s6.6;p28.37">In this respect the extent to which the court is prepared to intervene to set aside misguided decisions impacts significantly on decisions which are directed at, or in some cases made in ignorance of, tax avoidance<ref target="BAWE_0397b-ftnote.078"/>. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0397b-ftnote.075"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">p 376 Watt G <hi rend="italic">Trusts and Equity</hi> 2nd Edition, Oxford University Press, 2005, citing Sir Robert Walker <hi rend="italic">Trust Principles in the Pension Context</hi>, in Oakley A ed. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1"><hi rend="italic">Trends in Contemporary Trust Law</hi> Clarendon Press, Oxford 1996 at 129 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0397b-ftnote.076"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">p 117 Green B <hi rend="italic">The law relating to trustees' mistakes - where are we now?</hi> </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">(2003) 17(3) TLI pp 114 - 128 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0397b-ftnote.077"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">p 530 Moffat G <hi rend="italic">Trusts Law: Texts and materials</hi> 4th Edition, Cambridge University Press, 2005 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0397b-ftnote.078"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">See also p 117 Green B <hi rend="italic">The law relating to trustees' mistakes - where are we now?</hi> </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">(2003) 17(3) TLI pp 114 - 128 where it is noted that "the real issue is how its application may be restricted to cases on the acceptable side of a presently undrawn line." </s></p></note></div3></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">2003 and the case of <hi rend="italic">Re Barr</hi>: you can teach an old dog new tricks</head><p n="p29.37"><s n="s1.3;p29.37">The changes outlined above demonstrate the cyclical nature of the common law, such that resolution of disparity and confusion in one area is met by the emergence of new problems, each requiring due consideration. </s><s n="s2.3;p29.37">In this respect the rule in <hi rend="italic">Hastings-Bass</hi> is the springboard into a new area of concern which came to the fore at the turn of the 21 <hi rend="sup">st</hi> Century. </s><s n="s3.3;p29.37">While the case clearly determines the relationship between the exercise of trustee's discretion and the court's power to intervene, it raises concerns as to the extent to which the principle can be used "to rescue trustees from the consequences of their tax planning misjudgements"<ref target="BAWE_0397b-ftnote.079"/>. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0397b-ftnote.079"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Park J in <hi rend="italic">Breadner v Granville-Grossman</hi> [2001] Ch 523 </s></p></note><p n="p30.37"><s n="s1.4;p30.37">From this background, it was hoped that the case of <hi rend="italic">Re Barr</hi> would enable the policy considerations of invalidating trustees' decisions to be examined by the courts. </s><s n="s2.4;p30.37">The case arose from a request by the trustees to determine the validity of an appointment, which in their opinion they would not have executed had they made proper considerations according to the principle in <hi rend="italic">Hastings-Bass</hi><ref target="BAWE_0397b-ftnote.080"/>. </s><s n="s3.4;p30.37">Deciding that the appointment was voidable and adjourning the hearing in order that argument could be heard on the matter, Lightman J expressly declined to direct his judgement to the consideration of the consequences of invalidating the trustee's decision for fiscal reasons<ref target="BAWE_0397b-ftnote.081"/>. </s><s n="s4.4;p30.37"><hi rend="italic">Re Barr</hi> thus falls short of realising the clarity sought by commentators; it does not enounce the circumstances in which the court might overstep its jurisdiction by declaring an appointment void solely on the basis of its unfavourable fiscal consequences<ref target="BAWE_0397b-ftnote.082"/>. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0397b-ftnote.080"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">p 410 [2003] Ch 409 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0397b-ftnote.081"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">para 20, p 416 [2003] Ch 409 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0397b-ftnote.082"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">p 117 - 118 Green B <hi rend="italic">The law relating to trustees' mistakes - where are we now?</hi> </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">(2003) 17(3) TLI pp 114 - 128 </s></p></note><p n="p31.37"><s n="s1.3;p31.37">However, an in depth analysis of the case does provide insight into the nature and scope of decision making in 2003. </s><s n="s2.3;p31.37">What follows is a discussion of the key governing principles, and an evaluation of the extent to which they reflect those expressed in and since 1953. </s><s n="s3.3;p31.37">Of particular note is the way in which the case juxtaposes old approaches and new circumstances. </s></p><p n="p32.37"><s n="s1.7;p32.37">The suggestions that Lightman J "set off on his own path"<ref target="BAWE_0397b-ftnote.083"/> is highly evocative of the essence of Denning LJ's decisions. </s><s n="s2.7;p32.37">The new principle on which Lightman J embarks relies on the extension of the <hi rend="italic">Hastings-Bass</hi> principle as stated in <hi rend="italic">Mettoy Pension Trustees Ltd v Evans</hi><ref target="BAWE_0397b-ftnote.084"/>. </s><s n="s3.7;p32.37">Lightman J focuses on the whether the trustee has "failed to consider what he was under a duty to consider"<ref target="BAWE_0397b-ftnote.085"/>, and in doing so shifts the focus of the test. </s><s n="s4.7;p32.37">Green suggests that the requirement of breach of a fiduciary duty to consider creates an "additional hurdle" and a "wholly undesirable result", on the basis that relief is available only in respect of the acts of negligent trustees<ref target="BAWE_0397b-ftnote.086"/>. </s><s n="s5.7;p32.37">However, it is possible to argue that this is only detrimental to those seeking to avoid decisions which, although having been carefully considered, have misunderstood the consequences<ref target="BAWE_0397b-ftnote.087"/>. </s><s n="s6.7;p32.37">As such, Lightman J may be asserting a new rule, but clearly founds it on an existing principle: the court's intervention in the exercise of trustee discretion should be limited to what could be seen as worthy cases. </s><s n="s7.7;p32.37">In this respect one is reminded of the test established in <hi rend="italic">Chapman v Chapman</hi>, where a capricious wish to vary the trust was not sufficient; it was necessary to establish a real and genuine dispute. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0397b-ftnote.083"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">p 119 Green B <hi rend="italic">The law relating to trustees' mistakes - where are we now?</hi> </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">(2003) 17(3) TLI pp 114 - 128 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0397b-ftnote.084"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">p 1625 [1990] 1 WLR 1587 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0397b-ftnote.085"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">para 23, p 417 [2003] Ch 409 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0397b-ftnote.086"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">pp 120 - 121 Green B <hi rend="italic">The law relating to trustees' mistakes - where are we now?</hi> </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">(2003) 17(3) TLI pp 114 - 128 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0397b-ftnote.087"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">para 24, p 418 [2003] Ch 409, "the rule does not afford the right to the trustee or any beneficiary to have a decision declared invalid because the trustee's decision was in some way mistaken or has unforeseen and unpalatable consequences" </s></p></note><p n="p33.37"><s n="s1.3;p33.37">Lightman J also shares Denning LJ's reliance on the protection of beneficiaries as a reason for his decision. </s><s n="s2.3;p33.37">He draws on this idea in consideration of the purpose of the <hi rend="italic">Hastings-Bass</hi> principle<ref target="BAWE_0397b-ftnote.088"/>, stating that "this duty [to consider] lies at the heart of the rule, which is directed at ensuring for the protection of the beneficiaries under the trusts that they are not prejudiced by any breach of such duty"<ref target="BAWE_0397b-ftnote.089"/>. </s><s n="s3.3;p33.37">In addition to being reminiscent of the dicta of Denning LJ in <hi rend="italic">Re Chapman</hi>, it also reflects the concern for equitable property as expressed in the VTA, ensuring that beneficiaries receive that to which they are entitled. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0397b-ftnote.088"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">part 1(c) Hilliard J <hi rend="italic">Limiting Re Hastings-Bass?</hi> </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">(2004) Conv., May/Jun, pp 208 - 22 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0397b-ftnote.089"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">para 16, p 415 [2003] Ch 409 </s></p></note><p n="p34.37"><s n="s1.2;p34.37">Much attention has been focused on Lightman J's statement that decisions are voidable. </s><s n="s2.2;p34.37">He notes the </s></p><quote lang="English">"need in justice for some regard to the lapse of time in cases such as the present ... [which] can only be satisfied if the decision successfully challenged under the rule is voidable and not void"<ref target="BAWE_0397b-ftnote.090"/>. </quote><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0397b-ftnote.090"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">para 30, p 420 [2003] Ch 409 </s></p></note><p n="p35.37"><s n="s1.4;p35.37">The benefit of this is that, as Lightman J suggests, it allows the court flexibility in dealing with decisions on which the parties may have relied, arranging their affairs on the assumption that the trustees' action was valid<ref target="BAWE_0397b-ftnote.091"/>. </s><s n="s2.4;p35.37">This leaves the potential for the judges to consider the detrimental effect that voiding a decision may have on those beneficiaries who relied on the decision, and the discretion not to overrule it should the circumstances require. </s><s n="s3.4;p35.37">However, this flexibility may operate to the detriment of trustees as "the countervailing consideration in all cases of flexibility is a consequential increase in practical uncertainty as to the validity of such decisions"<ref target="BAWE_0397b-ftnote.092"/>. </s><s n="s4.4;p35.37">The caveat to perpetual uncertainty is that where a decision is merely voidable, "all the restrictions appropriate to the equitable remedy of rescission would come into play, including delay and the acquisition of third-party rights"<ref target="BAWE_0397b-ftnote.093"/>. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0397b-ftnote.091"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">From The Courts <hi rend="italic">Second thoughts by trustees and the Hastings-Bass principle</hi> Tr. &amp; Est. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">2003, 17(3), 3-4 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0397b-ftnote.092"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">p 285 Conaglen M <hi rend="italic">Judicial Review of Trustees' Discretionary Decisions</hi> [2004] CLJ pp 283 -286 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0397b-ftnote.093"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">p 230 Walker R The Limits of the Principle in Re Hastings-Bass (2002) PCB pp 226 - 240 </s></p></note></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">Summary of 2003 </head><p n="p36.37"><s n="s1.4;p36.37">The regime as a whole was thus guided by an overarching need to do that which is equitable, an approach which merits comparison with 1953. </s><s n="s2.4;p36.37">To Denning LJ, this would be highly appropriate, although it is unlikely his own judgement would have declined the opportunity to comment on the morality of reversing decisions for tax avoidance consequences. </s><s n="s3.4;p36.37">In contrast, if Simonds LJ continued to exhibit the strict interpretation of precedent as highlighted above<ref target="BAWE_0397b-ftnote.094"/>, it is unlikely that the concept of fiduciary duty would have entered into the judgement. </s><s n="s4.4;p36.37">Consequently, the trustee mistakenly understanding the settlor's wishes being insufficient to invoke the principle in <hi rend="italic">Re Hastings-Bass</hi><ref target="BAWE_0397b-ftnote.095"/>, Simonds LJ is unlikely to have held the decision voidable. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0397b-ftnote.094"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">See note 26 supra </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0397b-ftnote.095"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">para 25, p 418 [2003] Ch 409 </s></p></note></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">Conclusion </head><p n="p37.37"><s n="s1.5;p37.37">A comparison over fifty years in reference to a few select cases is an insufficient arena in which to examine the subtle nuances of change. </s><s n="s2.5;p37.37">What has become evident during discussions is that trusts law continues to embody key principles of judicial intervention, equity and to some extent, morality. </s><s n="s3.5;p37.37">Individual judges often take different approaches to these issues, but this is as likely to occur during one decision as it is over a 50 year period. </s><s n="s4.5;p37.37">Where attitudes do vary, it is frequently in response to a demand for change from dissatisfied subjects of trusts law. </s><s n="s5.5;p37.37">Taken as a whole, the judgements create a rich tapestry of judicial reasoning, where strict adherence to the rules runs alongside fanciful comment and brave expeditions into the unknown. </s></p></div1></body><back><div1 type="bibliography"><head rend="underlined">Bibliography</head><div2 type="bibliography"><head rend="underlined">Articles</head><p>Conaglen M, <hi rend="italic">Judicial review of trustees' discretionary decisions</hi> C.L.J. 2004, 63(2), 283-286</p><p>Cozens-Hardy Horne R <hi rend="italic">Modern Methods of minimising Taxation - VI - Discretionary Settlements</hi> British Tax Review 1957 pp 256 - 260</p><p>Crane F (Cree D and George E eds) <hi rend="italic">Trusts: Chapman v Chapman</hi> (1954) 18 Conv 316 - 317 </p><p>From The Courts <hi rend="italic">Second thoughts by trustees and the Hastings-Bass principle</hi> Tr. &amp; Est. 2003, 17(3), 3-4</p><p>Grbich Y <hi rend="italic">Baden: Awakening the Conceptually Moribund Trust</hi> (1974) 37(6) MLR (Nov) pp 643 - 656 </p><p>Green B <hi rend="italic">The law relating to trustees' mistakes - where are we now?</hi> (2003) 17(3) TLI pp 114 - 128</p><p>Harris J <hi rend="italic">Variation of Trusts and Tax Avoidance</hi> (1969) 32 MLR (May) pp 320 - 323 </p><p>Hilliard J <hi rend="italic">Re Hastings-Bass: too good to be true?</hi> (2002) 16(4) TLI pp 202 - 213 </p><p>Hilliard J <hi rend="italic">Limiting Re Hastings-Bass?</hi> (2004) Conv., May/Jun, pp 208-223</p><p>Marshall O <hi rend="italic">Deviations from the terms of a trust</hi> (1954) 17 MLR (Sept) 420 - 433 </p><p>Megarry R <hi rend="italic">Notes</hi> (1953) 69 LQR (July) pp 309 - 311</p><p>Mitchell J <hi rend="italic">The Court of Chancery and Trust</hi> (1953) 16 MLR (July) pp 381 - 382 </p><p>Mitchell J <hi rend="italic">The Finality of Settlements</hi> (1954) 17 MLR (Sept) pp 473 - 476 </p><p>Notes <hi rend="italic">Notes</hi> (1953) 69 LQR (April) pp 150 - 152 </p><p>Notes of Recent Cases <hi rend="italic">Trusts: Re Downshire Settled Estates, Re Chapman's Settled Estates, Re Blackwell's Settlement Trusts</hi> (1953) 17 Conv 81 - 85 </p><p>Notes of Recent Cases <hi rend="italic">Trusts: Re Gestetner's Settlement</hi> (1953) 17 Conv 240 - 241</p><p>Nugee E <hi rend="italic">Re Hastings-Bass Again - Void or Voidable? And Further Reflections</hi> (2003) PCB 173 - 187 </p><p>Palmer G <hi rend="italic">Private Trusts for Indefinite Beneficiaries</hi> (1972) 71(2) Michigan Law Review (Dec) pp 359 - 370 </p><p>Price L <hi rend="italic">Variation of Trusts Act, 1958</hi> (1959) 22 MLR (Jan) pp 56 - 59 </p><p>Walker R <hi rend="italic">The Limits of the Principle in Re Hastings-Bass</hi> (2002) PCB pp 226 - 240 </p><p>Wheatcroft G <hi rend="italic">The Attitude of the Legislature and the Courts to Tax Avoidance</hi> (1955) 18(3) MLR pp 209 - 230 </p></div2><div2 type="bibliography"><head rend="underlined">Books</head><p>Campbell E (Furness M ed) <hi rend="italic">Changing the Terms of Trusts</hi> Butterworths LexisNexis, UK, 2002</p><p>Grbich Y, Munn G, &amp; Reicher H (Baxt R ed) <hi rend="italic">Modern Trusts and Taxation</hi> Butterworths, Australia, 1978</p><p>Harris J <hi rend="italic">Variation of Trusts</hi> Sweet &amp; Maxwell, London, 1975</p><p>Keeton G <hi rend="italic">Modern Developments in the Law of Trusts</hi> Northern Ireland Legal Quarterly, Belfast, 1971</p><p>Keeton G <hi rend="italic">Social Change in the Law of Trusts</hi> Sir Isaac Pitman &amp; Sons ltd, London, 1958</p><p>Moffat G <hi rend="italic">Trusts Law: Texts and materials</hi> 4<hi rend="sup">th</hi> Edition, Cambridge University Press, 2005 </p><p>Mowbray J, Tucker L, Le Poidevin N, Simpson E <hi rend="italic">Lewin on Trusts</hi> 17<hi rend="sup">th</hi> Edition, Sweet &amp; Maxwell, London, 2000</p><p>Oakley A <hi rend="italic">Parker &amp; Mellows: The Modern Law of Trusts</hi> 8<hi rend="sup">th</hi> Edition, Sweet &amp; Maxwell, London, 2003</p><p>Paterson A <hi rend="italic">The Law Lords</hi> MacMillan Press Ltd, London, 1982</p><p>Pearce R and Stevens J <hi rend="italic">The Law of Trusts and Equitable Obligations</hi> 4<hi rend="sup">th</hi> Edition, Oxford University Press, 2006</p><p>Pettit P <hi rend="italic">Equity and the Law of Trusts</hi> 9<hi rend="sup">th</hi> Edition Butterworths, UK 2001</p><p>Stevens R <hi rend="italic">Law &amp; Politics: The House of Lords as a Judicial Body 1800 - 1976</hi> University of North Carolina Press, Chapel Hill, 1978</p><p>Underhill &amp; Hayton 16<hi rend="sup">th</hi> Edition</p><p>Watt G <hi rend="italic">Trusts and Equity</hi> 2<hi rend="sup">nd</hi> Edition, Oxford University Press, 2005</p><p>Wilson S <hi rend="italic">Todd &amp; Wilson's Textbook on Trusts</hi> 7<hi rend="sup">th</hi> Edition, Oxford University Press, 2005</p><p>Wilson W, Duncan A, Elliott W <hi rend="italic">Trusts, Trustees and Executors</hi> W Green &amp; Son Ltd, Edinburgh, 1975</p></div2><div2 type="bibliography"><head rend="underlined">Cases</head><p><hi rend="italic">In Re Downshire Settled Estates, Marquess of Downshire v Royal Bank of Scotland; In Re Chapman's Settlement Trusts, Chapman v Chapman; In Re Blackwell's Settlement Trusts, Blackwell v Blackwell</hi> [1953] Ch 218</p><p><hi rend="italic">In Re Gestetner Settlement, Barnett and Others, Blumka and Others</hi> [1953] Ch 672</p><p rend="italic">Re Kendrew [1953] Ch 291</p><p rend="italic">Re Walsh [1953] Ch 473</p><p><hi rend="italic">Chapman and Others Appellants v Chapman and Others Respondents</hi> [1954] AC 429</p><p><hi rend="italic">In Re Weston's Settlements, Weston v Weston and Others</hi> [1969] 1 Ch 223</p><p><hi rend="italic">Re Slocock's Will Trusts</hi> [1979] 1 All ER 358 </p><p><hi rend="italic">Mettoy Pension Trustees Ltd v Evans</hi> [1990] 1 WLR 1587</p><p><hi rend="italic">Breadner v Granville-Grossman</hi> [2001] Ch 523</p><p><hi rend="italic">Abacus Trust Co (Isle of Man) and Another v Barr and Others</hi> [2003] Ch 409 </p><p><hi rend="italic">Antonio Muñoz y Cia SA v Frumar Ltd</hi> [2003] Ch 328</p><p><hi rend="italic">Gascoyne v Custom and Excise Commissioners</hi> [2003] Ch 292</p></div2><div2 type="bibliography"><head rend="underlined">Parliamentary Debates</head><p><hi rend="italic">Variation of Trusts Bill</hi> 210 HL Official Report (5<hi rend="sup">th</hi> series) col 381-2, 30 June 1958</p></div2><div2 type="bibliography"><head rend="underlined">Government Papers</head><p>Law Reform Committee 6<hi rend="sup">th</hi> Report <hi rend="italic">Court's Power to Sanction Variation of Trusts</hi> Cmnd 310, November 1957</p></div2><div2 type="bibliography"><head rend="underlined">Internet Articles</head><p>Smart J <hi rend="italic">Challenges to trustee's exercise of discretion</hi> (2002) 18(Jan) The TACT review <seg type="URL" n="http://www.trustees.org.uk/review-index/Trustees-Challenges-to-trustee---exercise-of-discretion.php"/></p></div2></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
