<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_0398a" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Problem question - David v Photoprint - advise David</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">deleted: header: module name and student number; footer: page numbers</note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">Words: 2,002</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">2</p><p n="date">unknown</p><p n="module title">unknown</p><p n="module code">LA226</p><p n="genre family">Problem question</p><p n="discipline">Law</p><p n="disciplinary group">SS</p><p n="grade">unknown</p><p n="number of authors">unknown</p><p n="number of words">2050</p><p n="number of s-units">70</p><p n="number of p">29</p><p n="number of tables">0</p><p n="number of figures">0</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">0</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">0</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">29.3</p><p n="average s-units per p">2.4</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">m</p><p n="year of birth">1985</p><p n="first language">English</p><p n="education">UKA</p><p n="course">European Law</p><p n="student ID">0398</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><docTitle><titlePart rend="underlined bold">Problem question - David v Photoprint - advise David</titlePart></docTitle></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="section"><p n="p1.29"><s n="s1.2;p1.29">In order for David to gain a remedy for the loss of the photos, there are several arguments he can advance. </s><s n="s2.2;p1.29">This essay will examine these arguments and comment on the validity of each argument and the likely. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">1) The limitation clause is not incorporated into the contract:</head><p n="p2.29"><s n="s1.2;p2.29">If David is able to prove that the limitation clause was not part of the contract Photoprint will be liable for his loss and he will be able to seek a remedy. </s><s n="s2.2;p2.29">To do this David will need to prove that neither the limitation clause displayed on the sign, nor his irregular signing of the receipt, nor the ticket he received, result in the incorporation of the clause in the contract. </s></p><div2><head rend="underlined">The sign:</head><p n="p3.29"><s n="s1.2;p3.29">In <hi rend="italic">Olley</hi><ref target="BAWE_0398a-ftnote.001"/> Denning LJ stated that "persons who rely on a contract to exempt themselves from their common law liability must prove that contract strictly ... a prominent public notice which was plain for [the other party] to see when he made the contract"<ref target="BAWE_0398a-ftnote.002"/> would be a way of proving such a contract. </s><s n="s2.2;p3.29"><hi rend="italic">Olley</hi><ref target="BAWE_0398a-ftnote.003"/> stressed, that the notice must be visible before the contract is made.<ref target="BAWE_0398a-ftnote.004"/> It can be assumed from the fact that the assistant was able to point to the sign on David's return to Photoprint, that the liability clause was on prominent display, this seems clear to incorporate the clause in David's contract with Photoprint. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0398a-ftnote.001"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.3;pn1.1">Olley v. </s><s n="s2.3;pn1.1">Marlborough Court [1949] 1 K. B. </s><s n="s3.3;pn1.1">532 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0398a-ftnote.002"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">ibid, at 532, per: Denning LJ </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0398a-ftnote.003"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">ibid </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0398a-ftnote.004"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Applebey, G., Contract Law, 2001, Sweet &amp; Maxwell, London, pp.271 </s></p></note><p n="p4.29"><s n="s1.2;p4.29">David could possibly argue that <hi rend="italic">Vine</hi><ref target="BAWE_0398a-ftnote.005"/> applies and that even the prominently displayed notice was insufficient as he had neither read it nor agreed to its terms. </s><s n="s2.2;p4.29">However, <hi rend="italic">Vine</hi> can almost certainly be distinguished, as in that case the action was in tort, for wrongful interference with goods, rather than contract.<ref target="BAWE_0398a-ftnote.006"/> In this case there is no valid argument that David did not intend to form a contract, therefore, this exception is unlikely to apply. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0398a-ftnote.005"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Vine v Waltham Forest LBC [2000] 4 All E.R. 169 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0398a-ftnote.006"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">see: Applebey (op.cit.), pp.272 </s></p></note><p n="p5.29"><s n="s1.1;p5.29">In the highly unlikely event that the sign was not found sufficient to incorporate the clause in the contract, Photoprint could still argue that the receipt and the consistent course of dealing were constitutive of incorporation. </s></p></div2><div2><head><hi rend="underlined">The receipt</hi> :</head><p n="p6.29"><s n="s1.1;p6.29">David could argue successfully that he neither knew, nor was it reasonable to expect him to believe, that the receipt was a document containing contractual conditions.<ref target="BAWE_0398a-ftnote.007"/> A mere receipt will not pass this test<ref target="BAWE_0398a-ftnote.008"/> and Photoprint would need to prove that they had taken reasonable steps to bring the conditions to David's attention.<ref target="BAWE_0398a-ftnote.009"/> One such reasonable and normally definitive step is the act of signing a document, this did not occur on this occasion.<ref target="BAWE_0398a-ftnote.010"/> In this case the ticket he was given, "might reasonably be understood to be [no more than] a voucher ... to produce when collecting the [photos]".<ref target="BAWE_0398a-ftnote.011"/> If, on the other hand, the ticket David was handed had a notice on the front referring him to the back for terms this would be sufficient to limit liability applying <hi rend="italic">Parker</hi><ref target="BAWE_0398a-ftnote.012"/>. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0398a-ftnote.007"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Grogan v Robin Meredith Plant Hire [1996] C.L.C. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">1127, at 1130, per Auld LJ; see also: Bahamas Oil Refining Co v Kristiansands Tankrederie (The Polyduke) [1978] 1 Lloyd's Rep 211, at 215-216, per Kerr J </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0398a-ftnote.008"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">see: Grogan v Robin Meredith Plant Hire [1996] C.L.C. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">1127 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0398a-ftnote.009"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Applebey (op.cit.), pp.268 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0398a-ftnote.010"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">See: L'Estrange v F Graucob Ltd [1934] 2 K.B. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">394 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0398a-ftnote.011"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.3;pn1.1">Curtis v. </s><s n="s2.3;pn1.1">Chemical Cleaning and Dyeing Co. [1951] 1 K.B. </s><s n="s3.3;pn1.1">805, at 809, per: Denning LJ </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0398a-ftnote.012"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Parker v South Eastern Railway Company [1877] 2 C.P.D. 416 </s></p></note><p n="p7.29"><s n="s1.3;p7.29">David was not presented with a receipt to sign, and assuming that the ticket not contain any terms, this would not result in incorporation. </s><s n="s2.3;p7.29">Should David have effectively argued to this point that the ticket was not incorporated, Photoprint would argue that consistent course of dealing result in incorporation. </s><s n="s3.3;p7.29">This argument too is likely to fail. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">Consistent course of dealing:</head><p n="p8.29"><s n="s1.3;p8.29">Where there is insufficient notice, a limitation clause may nonetheless be incorporated "by the course of business and conduct of the parties"<ref target="BAWE_0398a-ftnote.013"/>. </s><s n="s2.3;p8.29">In this case David sometimes contracted orally and other times, where he signed the receipt, he had a written contract. </s><s n="s3.3;p8.29">Differing kinds of contract were held to be indicative of an inconsistent course of dealing in <hi rend="italic">McCutcheon</hi><ref target="BAWE_0398a-ftnote.014"/>. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0398a-ftnote.013"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.3;pn1.1">J. Spurling Ltd. v. </s><s n="s2.3;pn1.1">Bradshaw [1956] 1 W.L.R. 461, at 467, per: Denning LJ; British Crane Hire Corporation Ltd v Ipswich Plant Hire Ltd [1975] Q.B. </s><s n="s3.3;pn1.1">303 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0398a-ftnote.014"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">McCutcheon v David MacBrayne Ltd [1964] 1 W.L.R. 125 </s></p></note><p n="p9.29"><s n="s1.3;p9.29">Furthermore, the courts are more reluctant to incorporate terms on the basis of consistent course of dealing in consumer contracts. </s><s n="s2.3;p9.29">In <hi rend="italic">Hollier</hi><ref target="BAWE_0398a-ftnote.015"/> the court held that there was no consistent course of dealing where there were "at most three or four transactions over a period of five years". </s><s n="s3.3;p9.29">David could argue that bringing photos to be developed less than once a month was not consistent dealing. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0398a-ftnote.015"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Hollier v Ramble Motors (AMC) Ltd [1972] 1 All E.R. 399 </s></p></note><p n="p10.29"><s n="s1.2;p10.29">David may also be able to argue that consistent dealing is irrelevant, as each time he only received the receipt after the conclusion of the contract, and, therefore, on no past occasion was the clause ever incorporated. </s><s n="s2.2;p10.29">In <hi rend="italic">Kendall</hi><ref target="BAWE_0398a-ftnote.016"/> it was held that notice must be reasonably contemporaneous with the formation of the contract and that consistent notification of the standard terms after the conclusion of the contract was unsatisfactory.<ref target="BAWE_0398a-ftnote.017"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0398a-ftnote.016"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Kendall v Lillico [1969] 2 AC 31 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0398a-ftnote.017"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.3;pn1.1">see also: Thornton v Shoe Lane Parking Ltd [1971] 2 QB 163; Olley v. </s><s n="s2.3;pn1.1">Marlborough Court [1949] 1 K. B. </s><s n="s3.3;pn1.1">532 </s></p></note><p n="p11.29"><s n="s1.3;p11.29">It is difficult to establish whether in David's case the courts would find that the receipt was introduced at the appropriate stage of the transaction.<ref target="BAWE_0398a-ftnote.018"/> On one hand, there is not the same temporal separation as there was in <hi rend="italic">Olley</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Kendall</hi>. </s><s n="s2.3;p11.29">On the other hand, in <hi rend="italic">Thornton</hi><ref target="BAWE_0398a-ftnote.019"/>, it was held that the words on a ticket issued at the gate of a car park could not alter the contract, which had been made seconds before. </s><s n="s3.3;p11.29">David will probably succeed in convincing the courts that the consistent course of dealing fails to justify incorporation. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0398a-ftnote.018"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Elizabeth Macdonald, Incorporation of contract terms by a 'consistent course of dealing', 1988, Legal Studies, Volume 8, Issue 1, 48, pp.51 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0398a-ftnote.019"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Thornton v Shoe Lane Parking [1971] 2 Q.B. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">163 </s></p></note></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">Conclusion on incorporation:</head><p n="p12.29"><s n="s1.1;p12.29">The prominently displayed sign renders it extremely probable that the limitation clause was incorporated. </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">2) The limitation clause does not cover the acts which occurred and the clause is not permitted to limit liability for these acts:</head><p n="p13.29"><s n="s1.2;p13.29"><hi rend="italic">Prima facie</hi>, the clause covers the act concerned; the limitation clause covers "any claim loss or damage" and the act in question was clearly negligent damage to the film. </s><s n="s2.2;p13.29">However, David may successfully argue that the clause is not permitted to limit liability for negligence. </s></p><p n="p14.29"><s n="s1.2;p14.29">Exclusion clauses, unless clearly stated, as held in <hi rend="italic">White</hi><ref target="BAWE_0398a-ftnote.020"/>, cannot limit liability for negligence. </s><s n="s2.2;p14.29">However, this strict rule was relaxed in <hi rend="italic">Canada Steamship</hi><ref target="BAWE_0398a-ftnote.021"/>, which held that if the ordinary meaning of the words covered negligence then it could be excluded. <ref target="BAWE_0398a-ftnote.022"/><hi rend="italic">Ailsa Craig Fishing</hi><ref target="BAWE_0398a-ftnote.023"/> further relaxed the rules of construction with regard to limitation clauses.<ref target="BAWE_0398a-ftnote.024"/> Nonetheless, this is a restrained relaxation of the rules and the "words [of the clause] must be given, if possible, their natural, plain meaning"<ref target="BAWE_0398a-ftnote.025"/>. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0398a-ftnote.020"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">White v John Warwick and Co [1953] 2 All E.R. 1021 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0398a-ftnote.021"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Canada Steamship Lines Ltd v The King [1952] A.C. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">192 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0398a-ftnote.022"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">ibid, at 208, per Lord Morton of Henryton </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0398a-ftnote.023"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.5;pn1.1">Ailsa Craig Fishing Co. </s><s n="s2.5;pn1.1">Ltd. v. </s><s n="s3.5;pn1.1">Malvern Fishing Co. </s><s n="s4.5;pn1.1">Ltd. [1983] 1 Lloyd's Rep. </s><s n="s5.5;pn1.1">183 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0398a-ftnote.024"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">see <hi rend="italic">obiter dicta</hi> in :EE Caledonia v Orbit Valve plc [1995] 1 All E.R. 174, at 179, per Steyn LJ </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0398a-ftnote.025"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Ailsa Craig Fishing Co. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">Ltd. (op.cit.), at 184, per Lord Wilberforce </s></p></note><p n="p15.29"><s n="s1.2;p15.29"><hi rend="italic">Shell Chemicals</hi><ref target="BAWE_0398a-ftnote.026"/> demonstrated that ordinary meaning is interpreted strictly, and the court held that a clause excluding "all claims and demands whatever" was not adequately clear. </s><s n="s2.2;p15.29">In the case of any doubt the <hi rend="italic">contra proferentum</hi><ref target="BAWE_0398a-ftnote.027"/> rule, that the courts should construe each term narrowly against the party seeking to rely on it, should be applied. <ref target="BAWE_0398a-ftnote.028"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0398a-ftnote.026"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Shell Chemicals UK Ltd v P&amp;O Roadtanks [1995] 1 Lloyd's Rep. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">297 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0398a-ftnote.027"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">see: Applebey (op.cit.) pp.275; Houghton v Trafalgar Insurance Co [1953] 2 All ER 1409 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0398a-ftnote.028"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.3;pn1.1">see: Andrew Bros (Bournemouth) </s><s n="s2.3;pn1.1">Ltd v Singer &amp; Co. </s><s n="s3.3;pn1.1">Ltd [1933] All E.R. 479 </s></p></note><p n="p16.29"><s n="s1.3;p16.29">Nevertheless, it is uncertain whether the courts would find Photoprint clause to be sufficiently precise to limit liability for negligence. </s><s n="s2.3;p16.29">The phrase in <hi rend="italic">Shell Chemicals</hi> is very similar to the caveat, "howsoever caused", used in the current case. </s><s n="s3.3;p16.29">This would suggest that Photoprint would be unable to limit their liability for negligence. </s></p><p n="p17.29"><s n="s1.2;p17.29">Unfortunately for David, the relaxation of the rules with regard to limitation clauses, as well as the introduction of UCTA, has resulted in a less rigorous attitude displayed by the courts towards the substance of limitation clauses. </s><s n="s2.2;p17.29">It is likely that the courts will determine that the clause does satisfy the construction rules. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">3) The limitation clause does not satisfy the statutory tests and is inapplicable: </head><p n="p18.29"><s rend="underlined" n="s1.1;p18.29">Invalidating the clause under the Supply of Goods and Services Act 1982: </s></p><p n="p19.29"><s n="s1.3;p19.29">This is a contract of service and, therefore, the Supply of Goods and Services Act (SGSA) 1982 is applicable. </s><s n="s2.3;p19.29">David has a contract for supply of service with Photoprint and "there is an implied term that the supplier will carry out the service with reasonable care and skill"<ref target="BAWE_0398a-ftnote.029"/>. </s><s n="s3.3;p19.29">Where the incorrect solution was used there is arguably a breach of this implied term. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0398a-ftnote.029"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Supply of Goods and Services Act 1982, section 13 </s></p></note><p n="p20.29"><s n="s1.3;p20.29">Once the implied term has been established under SGSA David can seek to apply UCTA, to have the limitation clause effectively invalidated. </s><s n="s2.3;p20.29">UCTA clearly applies, as Photoprint is a business<ref target="BAWE_0398a-ftnote.030"/> which satisfies section 1(3)(a) of UCTA, and, assuming that his business is not photography, David falls within the definition of consumer.<ref target="BAWE_0398a-ftnote.031"/> David could rely on either section 2(2), for negligence, or section 3, for breach, to have the limitation clause nullified. </s><s n="s3.3;p20.29">In this case it is immaterial which section David seeks to rely on, as both impose the reasonableness test<ref target="BAWE_0398a-ftnote.032"/> and would result in the same outcome. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0398a-ftnote.030"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">definition in Unfair Contract Terms Act 1977, section 14: "business" includes a profession ... </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0398a-ftnote.031"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Unfair Contract Terms Act 1977, section 12(1)(a); see: Kristina Sheffield v Pickfords Removals Ltd [1997] T.L.R. 337, Lord Woolf M.R. says that as a matter of practice a defendant should include in his defence a statement that his conditions were reasonable </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0398a-ftnote.032"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Unfair Contract Terms Act 1977, section 11 and Schedule 2 </s></p></note><div2><head rend="underlined">The reasonableness test:</head><p n="p21.29"><s n="s1.1;p21.29">Photoprint, as the party who inserted the clause, and thus seek to rely on it, has the burden to prove that it is reasonable in the circumstances.<ref target="BAWE_0398a-ftnote.033"/> Reasonableness is left to the discretion of the courts to decide with the help of the guidelines.<ref target="BAWE_0398a-ftnote.034"/> In this case it would be difficult for Photoprint to prove reasonableness. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0398a-ftnote.033"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Unfair Contract Terms Act 1977, section 11(5); see: Turner, C., Unlocking Contract Law, 2004, Hodder &amp; Stoughton Educational, London, pp.190; </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0398a-ftnote.034"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">ibid, Schedule 2 </s></p></note><p n="p22.29"><s n="s1.4;p22.29">Under section 11(1) there is a general requirement that the term is "fair and reasonable ... having regard to the circumstances ... in the contemplation of the parties when the contract was made". </s><s n="s2.4;p22.29">David could apply the very similar facts of <hi rend="italic">Warren</hi><ref target="BAWE_0398a-ftnote.035"/> to argue that the limitation clause falls down on this test. </s><s n="s3.4;p22.29">In <hi rend="italic">Warren</hi> silver wedding photographs were lost by the defendants. </s><s n="s4.4;p22.29">The court held that a clause limiting the replacement to the value of a new film was not reasonable and that the defendants "ought to have foreseen that some of the films sent to them would be of a particular significance to their customers"<ref target="BAWE_0398a-ftnote.036"/>. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0398a-ftnote.035"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Warren v Truprint [1986] BTLC 344 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0398a-ftnote.036"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">ibid, at 344; see also: Smith v Eric S Bush [1990] 1 AC 831 </s></p></note><p n="p23.29"><s n="s1.5;p23.29">Specific reference to limitation clauses is made in section 11(4), which holds that the opportunity to use insurance, as well as the resources available to the defendant, should be taken into consideration when considering reasonableness. </s><s n="s2.5;p23.29">David could rely on <hi rend="italic">George Mitchell</hi><ref target="BAWE_0398a-ftnote.037"/> to argue that Photoprint's clause was unreasonable due the possibility of easily obtaining insurance to cover a claim such as his. </s><s n="s3.5;p23.29">Clarke J also argues in <hi rend="italic">Woodman</hi><ref target="BAWE_0398a-ftnote.038"/> that "it would be ... reasonable to satisfy claims out of their resources by increased charges to customers". </s><s n="s4.5;p23.29"><hi rend="italic">Salvage Association</hi><ref target="BAWE_0398a-ftnote.039"/> held that where the company had resources which were easily sufficient to cover liabilities in excess of the limit imposed that could be unreasonable. </s><s n="s5.5;p23.29">David could successfully argue that Photoprint has resources in excess of the cost of the replacement film, which renders the clause unreasonable. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0398a-ftnote.037"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">George Mitchell Ltd v Finney Lock Seeds Ltd [1983] 2 AC 803 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0398a-ftnote.038"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Woodman v Photo Trade Processing Ltd [1981] Exeter County Court (unreported), see: Ramsay, I., Consumer Protection: Texts and Materials, 1989, Weidenfeld and Nicolson, London, pp.107 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0398a-ftnote.039"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Salvage Association v CAP Financial Services [1995] F.S.R. 654 </s></p></note></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">The 'lack of alternatives' argument:</head><p n="p24.29"><s n="s1.2;p24.29">Where there is inequality of bargaining power this can be indicative of unreasonableness.<ref target="BAWE_0398a-ftnote.040"/> Bargaining power can be determined by the ability of each of the parties to negotiate the contract and the alternatives open to the party who does not like the conditions of the other. </s><s n="s2.2;p24.29">The alternatives, or lack thereof, available to the customer will also reflect the reasonableness of the clause. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0398a-ftnote.040"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Applebey (op.cit.), pp.301 </s></p></note><p n="p25.29"><s n="s1.3;p25.29">In <hi rend="italic">Peek</hi><ref target="BAWE_0398a-ftnote.041"/> a monopoly which realistically forced the customer to agree to their terms of business rendered a term unreasonable. </s><s n="s2.3;p25.29">Warren and Woodman, both state that by adopting the same terms as the rest of the trade, the company offered the claimant no choice but to accept. </s><s n="s3.3;p25.29">Through applying these two cases and Peek, David could successfully argue that a lack of alternative forced him to entrust the film to Photoprint. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0398a-ftnote.041"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Peek v North Staffordshire Railway [1863] 10 HLC 493 </s></p></note></div2><div2><head><hi rend="underlined">Setting the clause aside under the Unfair Terms in Consumer Contracts Regulations (UTCCR) 1999</hi><ref target="BAWE_0398a-ftnote.042"/> :<note place="foot" id="BAWE_0398a-ftnote.042"><p n="pn1.1"> the UTCCR implements the EC Directive on Unfair Terms in Consumer Contracts (93/13/EC)</p></note></head><p n="p26.29"><s n="s1.1;p26.29">Amongst other things, the UTCCR offers consumers protection from terms which inappropriately limit liability for total, partial or inadequate performance.<ref target="BAWE_0398a-ftnote.043"/> In this case David would have a strong argument that the limitation clause is inappropriate and he could seek to have the clause set aside<ref target="BAWE_0398a-ftnote.044"/>. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0398a-ftnote.043"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Unfair Terms in Consumer Contracts Regulations 1999, Schedule 2(1)(b) </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0398a-ftnote.044"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">ibid, section 8 </s></p></note></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">Conclusion on limiting liability:</head><p n="p27.29"><s n="s1.3;p27.29">David will almost certainly obtain a remedy. </s><s n="s2.3;p27.29">Arguably the clause was never even incorporated in the contract. </s><s n="s3.3;p27.29">However, if it was held to be incorporated, under the reasonableness test in UCTA, the inappropriate limitation test in UTCCR and the case law in <hi rend="italic">Warren</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Woodman</hi>, it is likely that the limitation clause will be set aside. </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">What remedies are available to David? </head><p n="p28.29"><s n="s1.3;p28.29">The only remedy available to David is damages. </s><s n="s2.3;p28.29">In <hi rend="italic">Woodman</hi> 23 of 36 photos were ruined and damages of £75 for distress and disappointment were awarded against the photographic processors. </s><s n="s3.3;p28.29">In <hi rend="italic">Warren </hi>£50 was awarded for the loss of a photographic film, on appeal Judge Kingham<ref target="BAWE_0398a-ftnote.045"/> did not alter the award, but expressed, <hi rend="italic">obiter</hi>, that he held £150 to be a more appropriate sum. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0398a-ftnote.045"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Warren v Truprint [1986] BTLC 344, at 349 </s></p></note><p n="p29.29"><s n="s1.5;p29.29">It is difficult to advise David of the amount he would receive in damages. </s><s n="s2.5;p29.29">In this case David has not suffered any direct distress or disappointment other than failing to fulfil his promise to Sue. </s><s n="s3.5;p29.29">This will be a factor limiting the amount awarded. </s><s n="s4.5;p29.29">However, an aggravating factor is the loss of two complete films, double the loss in Warren. </s><s n="s5.5;p29.29">It is certain that he will be awarded more than the cost of two replacement films and a fair estimate based on the case law and the facts of David's case would be £300 to £400<ref target="BAWE_0398a-ftnote.046"/>. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0398a-ftnote.046"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">this figure accounts for inflation </s></p></note></div1></body><back><div1 type="bibliography"><head rend="underlined bold">Bibliography</head><div2 type="bibliography"><head rend="underlined bold">Books </head><p><hi rend="underlined">Applebey, G.</hi>, <hi rend="bold">Contract Law</hi>, 2001, Sweet &amp; Maxwell, London</p><p><hi rend="underlined">Hooley, R.</hi>, <hi rend="bold">Commercial &amp; Consumer Contract Law</hi>, 2<hi rend="sup">nd</hi> Edition, 1999/2000, Butterworths, London, Edinburgh, Dublin</p><p><hi rend="underlined">McKendrick, E.</hi>, <hi rend="bold">Contract Law: Texts, Cases and Materials</hi>, Second Edition, 2005, Oxford University Press</p><p><hi rend="underlined">Pitch, H.D.</hi>, <hi rend="bold">Damages for Breach of Contract</hi>, 1985, The Carswell Company Ltd, Toronto</p><p><hi rend="underlined">Ramsay, I.</hi>, <hi rend="bold">Consumer Protection: Texts and Materials</hi>, 1989, Weidenfeld and Nicolson, London</p><p><hi rend="underlined">Turner, C.</hi>, <hi rend="bold">Unlocking Contract Law</hi>, 2004, Hodder &amp; Stoughton Educational, London</p></div2><div2 type="bibliography"><head rend="underlined bold">Journals</head><p><hi rend="underlined">Elizabeth Macdonald</hi>, <hi rend="bold">Incorporation of contract terms by a 'consistent course of dealing'</hi>, 1988, Legal Studies, Volume 8, Issue 1, 48</p><p><hi rend="underlined">Mustafa, Z.</hi>, <hi rend="bold">The Treatment of Exemption Clauses by the Sudan Courts: I</hi>, 1967, Journal of African Law, Vol. 11, No. 2. 119 </p></div2><div2 type="bibliography"><head rend="underlined bold">Case Law</head><p>Ailsa Craig Fishing Co. Ltd. v. Malvern Fishing Co. Ltd. [1983] 1 Lloyd's Rep. 183</p><p>Andrew Bros (Bournemouth) Ltd v Singer &amp; Co. Ltd [1933] All E.R. 479</p><p>Bahamas Oil Refining Co v Kristiansands Tankrederie (The Polyduke) [1978] 1 Lloyd's Rep 211</p><p>British Crane Hire Corporation Ltd v Ipswich Plant Hire Ltd [1975] Q.B. 303</p><p>Canada Steamship Lines Ltd v The King [1952] A.C. 192</p><p>Curtis v. Chemical Cleaning and Dyeing Co. [1951] 1 K.B. 805</p><p>EE Caledonia v Orbit Valve plc [1995] 1 All E.R. 174</p><p>George Mitchell Ltd v Finney Lock Seeds Ltd [1983] 2 AC 803</p><p>Grogan v Robin Meredith Plant Hire [1996] C.L.C. 1127</p><p>Hollier v Ramble Motors (AMC) Ltd [1972] 1 All E.R. 399</p><p>Houghton v Trafalgar Insurance Co [1953] 2 All ER 1409</p><p>J. Spurling Ltd. v. Bradshaw [1956] 1 W.L.R. 461</p><p>Kendall v Lillico [1969] 2 AC 31</p><p>Kristina Sheffield v Pickfords Removals Ltd [1997] T.L.R. 337</p><p>L'Estrange v F Graucob Ltd [1934] 2 K.B. 394</p><p>McCutcheon v David MacBrayne Ltd [1964] 1 W.L.R. 125</p><p>Olley v. Marlborough Court [1949] 1 K. B. 532</p><p>Parker v South Eastern Railway Company [1877] 2 C.P.D. 416</p><p>Peek v North Staffordshire Railway [1863] 10 HLC 493</p><p>Salvage Association v CAP Financial Services [1995] F.S.R. 654</p><p>Shell Chemicals UK Ltd v P&amp;O Roadtanks [1995] 1 Lloyd's Rep. 297 </p><p>Smith v Eric S Bush [1990] 1 AC 831</p><p>Thornton v Shoe Lane Parking Ltd [1971] 2 QB 163</p><p>Vine v Waltham Forest LBC [2000] 4 All E.R. 169 </p><p>Warren v Truprint [1986] BTLC 344</p><p>White v John Warwick and Co [1953] 2 All E.R. 1021</p><p>Woodman v Photo Trade Processing Ltd [1981] Exeter County Court (unreported)</p></div2><div2 type="bibliography"><head rend="underlined bold">Legislation</head><p>Supply of Goods and Services Act 1982</p><p>Unfair Contract Terms Act 1977</p><p>Unfair Term in Consumer Contracts Regulation 1999</p></div2></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
