<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_0398d" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>"To date, corporate governance reforms (in the UK) have relied heavily on institutional investors and non-executive directors as enforcers of good corporate practice. Such mechanisms are inadequate to ensure effective corporate governance and other, especially statutory, forms of intervention are required." Discuss.</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">deleted: header: module name and student number; footer: page numbers</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">3</p><p n="date">unknown</p><p n="module title">unknown</p><p n="module code">LA310</p><p n="genre family">Essay</p><p n="discipline">Law</p><p n="disciplinary group">SS</p><p n="grade">unknown</p><p n="number of authors">unknown</p><p n="number of words">2614</p><p n="number of s-units">83</p><p n="number of p">35</p><p n="number of tables">0</p><p n="number of figures">0</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">0</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">0</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">31.5</p><p n="average s-units per p">2.4</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">m</p><p n="year of birth">1985</p><p n="first language">English</p><p n="education">UKA</p><p n="course">European Law</p><p n="student ID">0398</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><docTitle><titlePart rend="bold">"To date, corporate governance reforms (in the UK) have relied heavily on institutional investors and non-executive directors as enforcers of good corporate practice. Such mechanisms are inadequate to ensure effective corporate governance and other, especially statutory, forms of intervention are required." Discuss. </titlePart></docTitle></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined">Introduction</head><p n="p1.35"><s n="s1.2;p1.35">Good corporate practices are vital for the confidence of investors and employees and indispensable to "help ensure the longevity of the organisation"<ref target="BAWE_0398d-ftnote.001"/>. </s><s n="s2.2;p1.35">The centrality of corporations and corporate power in the modern world also profoundly influences the economy and society as a whole.<ref target="BAWE_0398d-ftnote.002"/> In order to ensure that good corporate practices are implemented and maintained, it is vital to apply a steadfast system of corporate governance. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0398d-ftnote.001"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Mallin, C.A., Corporate Governance, Second Edition, 2007, Oxford University Press, Oxford, pp.267; see also: Shleifer, A. &amp; Vishny, R., A survey of Corporate Governance, 1997, Journal of Finance, Vol.52, No.2 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0398d-ftnote.002"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">O'Brien, J., Governing the Corporation: Regulation and Corporate Governance in an Age of Scandal and Global Markets, in: O'Brien, J., Governing the Corporation, 2005, John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd, Chichester </s></p></note><p n="p2.35"><s n="s1.1;p2.35">Definitions of corporate governance are not always consistent.<ref target="BAWE_0398d-ftnote.003"/> Corporate governance is primarily understood to be the relationship within a company between the shareholders (owners) and the directors (managers).<ref target="BAWE_0398d-ftnote.004"/> More specifically it involves the means of the financiers of businesses gaining assurance of a return on their investment.<ref target="BAWE_0398d-ftnote.005"/> Problems can arise where there is a significant separation between owners and managers, as shareholders are not in a position to prevent managerial excess, whether such excess results from incompetence, self-dealing or fraud.<ref target="BAWE_0398d-ftnote.006"/> Corporate governance problems affect small family companies and large public companies alike, although public companies with dispersed shareholding suffer the most serious difficulties and are the focal point of much of the debate. <ref target="BAWE_0398d-ftnote.007"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0398d-ftnote.003"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Keasey, K., Thompson, S., Wright, M., Corporate Governance: Economic, Management and Financial Issues, 1997, Oxford University Press, Oxford, pp.2 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0398d-ftnote.004"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.3;pn1.1">see: Parkinson, J. &amp; Kelly, G., The Combined Code on Corporate Governance, 70(1) The Political Quarterly 101, pp.101; Cioffi, J.W., Governing Globalization? </s><s n="s2.3;pn1.1">The State, Law, and Structural Change in Corporate Governance, 2000, Journal of Law and Society, Vol. 27, No. </s><s n="s3.3;pn1.1">4, 572, pp.574 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0398d-ftnote.005"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Shleifer, A. &amp; Vishny, R., A survey of Corporate Governance, 1997, Journal of Finance, Vol.52, No.2 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0398d-ftnote.006"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Hannigan B., Company Law, 2003, Oxford University Press, Oxford, pp.144 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0398d-ftnote.007"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">ibid, pp.144 </s></p></note><p n="p3.35"><s n="s1.2;p3.35">There is continued discussion as to how good corporate governance should be achieved and enforced. </s><s n="s2.2;p3.35">It is generally agreed that no single mechanism can provide the solution to the issues presented by a separation in ownership and control.<ref target="BAWE_0398d-ftnote.008"/> In the UK corporate governance reforms have focused on the board of directors<ref target="BAWE_0398d-ftnote.009"/>, in particular, the non-executive director<ref target="BAWE_0398d-ftnote.010"/> and also on institutional investors. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0398d-ftnote.008"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">ibid, pp.145 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0398d-ftnote.009"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">see: Elson, C.M., Director Compensation And The Management-Captured Board: The History Of the Symptom And A Cure, 1996, 50 Southern Methodist University Law Review 127, 127: management-dominated, passive boards of directors are cited as the most significant problem facing public companies today </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0398d-ftnote.010"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Hannigan B. (op.cit.), pp.145 </s></p></note><p n="p4.35"><s n="s1.5;p4.35">Shareholders are able to appoint all of the members of the board of directors. </s><s n="s2.5;p4.35">However, the system still relies on non-executives as a controlling element.<ref target="BAWE_0398d-ftnote.011"/> The articles of a company normally allocate extensive managerial powers to executive members of the board. </s><s n="s3.5;p4.35">Non-executives do not have these management capabilities and their responsibilities lie with general policy and strategy as well as the monitoring of executive directors. </s><s n="s4.5;p4.35">Monitoring is not intended to be a mere passive observation of the executives. </s><s n="s5.5;p4.35">Non-executives are entitled, and encouraged, to "give executive directors a rigorous drilling"<ref target="BAWE_0398d-ftnote.012"/> where appropriate. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0398d-ftnote.011"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Esen, R., Managing and monitoring: the dual role of non-executive directors on UK and US boards, 2000, International Company and Commercial Law Review, 11(6), 202, pp.203 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0398d-ftnote.012"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Re Continental Assurance Company of London plc. [2001] WL 720239, per Park J., at para.29 </s></p></note><p n="p5.35"><s n="s1.2;p5.35">The requirement to monitor executive management is reinforced by the Combined Code<ref target="BAWE_0398d-ftnote.013"/> which requires non-executive directors to "scrutinise the performance of management in meeting agreed goals and objectives and monitor the reporting of performance"<ref target="BAWE_0398d-ftnote.014"/>. </s><s n="s2.2;p5.35">The Combined Code specifies that "at least half the board, excluding the chairman, should comprise of non-executive directors"<ref target="BAWE_0398d-ftnote.015"/>. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0398d-ftnote.013"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">The Combined Code on Corporate Governance, June 2006 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0398d-ftnote.014"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">ibid, pp.3 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0398d-ftnote.015"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">ibid, section 1, A.3.2.; this does not apply to smaller companies (ie companies below the FTSE 350 throughout the year prior to the reporting year) who should have at least two independent non-executive members </s></p></note><p n="p6.35"><s n="s1.3;p6.35">There is no legislation in the area of corporate governance. </s><s n="s2.3;p6.35">The objectives of three influential committees<ref target="BAWE_0398d-ftnote.016"/> and resulting codes were to establish proposals which improve the relationship between owners and managers "without recourse to heavy handed government intervention"<ref target="BAWE_0398d-ftnote.017"/>. </s><s n="s3.3;p6.35">The Combined Code is, therefore, not legally binding and there are no sanctions resulting from non-compliance. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0398d-ftnote.016"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">The three committees are: The Committee on the Financial Aspects of Corporate Governance, chaired by Sir Adrian Cadbury, set up in 1991 by the Financial Reporting Council, the London Stock Exchange and the accountancy profession; The Study Group on Director's Remuneration, chaired by Sir Richard Greenbury, set up on January 2005 on the initiative of the CBI; The Committee on Corporate Governance, chaired by Sir Ronald Hampel, set up in November 1995 on the initiative of the Chairman of the Financial Reporting Council </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0398d-ftnote.017"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Parkinson, J. &amp; Kelly, G. (op.cit.), pp.101 </s></p></note><p n="p7.35"><s n="s1.3;p7.35">The Financial Service Authority Listing Rules<ref target="BAWE_0398d-ftnote.018"/> require a public listed company to include details in its annual report and accounts statement of how it has applied the general principles of the Combined Code and state whether or not it has complied with the Code of Best Practice<ref target="BAWE_0398d-ftnote.019"/>. </s><s n="s2.3;p7.35">In the case of non-compliance, an explanation must be provided.<ref target="BAWE_0398d-ftnote.020"/> Listed companies are legally required to comply with the Listing Rules<ref target="BAWE_0398d-ftnote.021"/>. </s><s n="s3.3;p7.35">However, the only sanction for non-compliance with the Combined Code itself is the reaction of the market.<ref target="BAWE_0398d-ftnote.022"/> This reaction can range from indifference to a dramatic drop in share price.<ref target="BAWE_0398d-ftnote.023"/> A significant influence on the market reaction is institutional investors, who play a key role in corporate governance<ref target="BAWE_0398d-ftnote.024"/>. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0398d-ftnote.018"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">see: United Kingdom Listing Authority, Listing Rules, <seg type="URL" n="http://fsahandbook.info/FSA/html/handbook/LR"/> </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0398d-ftnote.019"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">the Code of Best Practice forms one part of the Combined Code </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0398d-ftnote.020"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">see: United Kingdom Listing Authority, Listing Rules, Rule 12.43A </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0398d-ftnote.021"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Financial Services and Markets Act 2000, section 91(1): "contravene[tion of] any provision of listing rules, it may [result in] a penalty of such amount as [the FSA] considers appropriate" </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0398d-ftnote.022"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Hannigan B. (op.cit.), pp.150 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0398d-ftnote.023"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">ibid, pp.150 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0398d-ftnote.024"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Mallin, C.A., (op.cit.), pp.80 </s></p></note><p n="p8.35"><s n="s1.3;p8.35">Institutional investors are shareholders, mainly comprising of pension funds and insurance companies.<ref target="BAWE_0398d-ftnote.025"/> These investors have significantly increased in numbers over the last half century. </s><s n="s2.3;p8.35">The combined share ownership of pension funds and insurance companies in the UK has more than doubled from 16% in 1963 to 33% in 2004<ref target="BAWE_0398d-ftnote.026"/>. </s><s n="s3.3;p8.35">Institutional investors have a strong interest in closely observing the corporate governance of companies, especially in light of the "internationalisation of cross-boarder portfolios"<ref target="BAWE_0398d-ftnote.027"/> and in the wake of several financial crises<ref target="BAWE_0398d-ftnote.028"/> in many parts of the globe. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0398d-ftnote.025"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">ibid, pp.81 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0398d-ftnote.026"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Office of National Statistics, Share Ownership: A report on ownership of shares as at 31 December 2004, 2005, HMSO, Norwich, <seg type="URL" n="http://www.statistics.gov.uk/cci/nugget.asp?id=107"/> </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0398d-ftnote.027"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Mallin, C.A., (op.cit), pp.80 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0398d-ftnote.028"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">see: infra (Barings Bank, Enron, Royal Ahold and Parmalat) </s></p></note><p n="p9.35"><s n="s1.1;p9.35">This paper will examine the current form of corporate governance in the United Kingdom as well as the efficacy of the current regulatory regime. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined">Development and reforms </head><p n="p10.35"><s n="s1.1;p10.35">In spite of the importance of corporate governance, it has only relatively recently achieved prominence in the commercial sector.<ref target="BAWE_0398d-ftnote.029"/> Various corporate collapses and financial scandals have provided the catalyst for this rise to prominence.<ref target="BAWE_0398d-ftnote.030"/> Barings Bank<ref target="BAWE_0398d-ftnote.031"/> illustrated the need for sufficient and effective internal controls; Enron<ref target="BAWE_0398d-ftnote.032"/> underlined the importance of honest directors with integrity and the significance of retaining independent auditors; Royal Ahold<ref target="BAWE_0398d-ftnote.033"/> demonstrated the dangers associated with limiting the involvement of shareholders in the running of a company; and Parmalat<ref target="BAWE_0398d-ftnote.034"/> showed that a lack of independence of board members could have potentially disastrous effects on the company. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0398d-ftnote.029"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Keasey, K., Thompson, S., Wright, M., (op.cit), pp.2 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0398d-ftnote.030"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Mallin, C.A., (op.cit.), pp.266 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0398d-ftnote.031"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">In 1995 Barings Bank became bankrupt because of the insufficient internal controls on trading, one trader, Nick Leeson, amassed losses of over £850 million </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0398d-ftnote.032"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Enron used special purpose entities to conceal large losses, in 2001 Enron declared a recurring loss of $1 billion and a $1.2 billion right-off of shareholders funds </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0398d-ftnote.033"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">In 2003 Royal Ahold announced that it had overstated its earnings of its US subsidiary by $500 million </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0398d-ftnote.034"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">In 2003 Parmalat went into administration with debts estimated at £10 billion after it transpired that supposed cash reserves were non-existent </s></p></note><p n="p11.35"><s n="s1.1;p11.35">Following such high profile and catastrophic failings from company directors and internal systems, much of the recent development of corporate governance has been driven by the need to restore investor confidence in capital markets.<ref target="BAWE_0398d-ftnote.035"/> In the current system in the UK non-executive directors play a critical role in assuring good corporate governance. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0398d-ftnote.035"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Mallin, C.A., (op.cit.), pp.42 </s></p></note></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined">The role of non-executive directors</head><p n="p12.35"><s n="s1.2;p12.35">As well as monitoring the management, non-executives are required to be satisfied "on the integrity of financial information and that financial controls and systems of risk management are robust and defensible"<ref target="BAWE_0398d-ftnote.036"/>. </s><s n="s2.2;p12.35">Appropriate levels of remuneration for executive directors are determined by their non-executive counterparts and non-executives also have an important role in appointing and removing executive directors.<ref target="BAWE_0398d-ftnote.037"/> The non-executive directors are intended to consider the position of shareholders, and not to be sympathetic to the desires of executive colleagues. <ref target="BAWE_0398d-ftnote.038"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0398d-ftnote.036"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">The Combined Code on Corporate Governance, June 2006, pp.3 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0398d-ftnote.037"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">ibid </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0398d-ftnote.038"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Esen, R., (op.cit.), pp.203 </s></p></note><p n="p13.35"><s n="s1.2;p13.35">Many directors, both executive and non-executive, see the role of non-executives as strategic rather than investigatory.<ref target="BAWE_0398d-ftnote.039"/> In the past the non-executives have been accused of doing little more than rubber stamping managerial decisions. </s><s n="s2.2;p13.35">The existence of non-executive members on the board of directors provides no guarantee of effective monitoring and control of the management. <ref target="BAWE_0398d-ftnote.040"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0398d-ftnote.039"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Hannigan B., (op.cit.), pp.145; Company Law Review, Modern Company Law for a Better Economy: Developing the Framework, 2000, URN 00/656, para 3.134 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0398d-ftnote.040"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Esen, R., (op.cit.), pp.204 </s></p></note></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined">The limitations on the enforcement of good corporate practice by non-executives</head><p n="p14.35"><s n="s1.3;p14.35">The system of appointment requires that "a majority of the nomination committee should be independent non-executive directors"<ref target="BAWE_0398d-ftnote.041"/>. </s><s n="s2.3;p14.35">However, there is no concrete guarantee that familiar associates of executive directors, who are unable exercise the impartiality required to properly uphold shareholders' interests, will not be appointed.<ref target="BAWE_0398d-ftnote.042"/> Management often favour chief executives who occupy a similar role in another company. </s><s n="s3.3;p14.35">As a result, these non-executives "will not monitor any more diligently than they feel they should be monitored in running their own companies and will rarely risk loosing their jobs by questioning management's decisions"<ref target="BAWE_0398d-ftnote.043"/>. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0398d-ftnote.041"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">The Combined Code on Corporate Governance, June 2006, para A.4 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0398d-ftnote.042"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Esen, R., (op.cit.), pp.204 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0398d-ftnote.043"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Benfield, R.E., Curing American Managerial Myopia: Can the German System of Corporate Governance Help, 1995, 17 Loyola of Los Angeles International and Comparative Law Review, 615, pp.623 </s></p></note><p n="p15.35"><s n="s1.2;p15.35">The degree of independence to be expected of a non-executive is a key issue.<ref target="BAWE_0398d-ftnote.044"/> Appointments still mainly arise as a result of friendship or a previous business relationship with executive officers. </s><s n="s2.2;p15.35">Reservations have been expressed over the partiality of non-executive directors with existing personal ties.<ref target="BAWE_0398d-ftnote.045"/> Non-executives can also hold several posts and it has been argued that, no matter how talented a director is, "[he] can't be a good watchdog if [he is] only on patrol three times a year"<ref target="BAWE_0398d-ftnote.046"/>. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0398d-ftnote.044"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Hannigan B., (op.cit.), pp.151 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0398d-ftnote.045"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">ibid </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0398d-ftnote.046"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">NACD, Corporate Governance Survey (1995) </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">4, cited in: Esen, R., (op.cit.), pp.205 </s></p></note><p n="p16.35"><s n="s1.1;p16.35">Non-executives who are sympathetic to the views of management and are unlikely to challenge decisions are more prone to being selected and retained.<ref target="BAWE_0398d-ftnote.047"/> The danger is that those selected will feel indebted to the executives for having chosen them and will be more inclined to accommodate management by unquestioningly accepting their actions. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0398d-ftnote.047"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Esen, R., (op.cit.), pp.204 </s></p></note><p n="p17.35"><s n="s1.2;p17.35">Non-executives may find they lack the necessary information in order to correctly monitor the actions of managers. </s><s n="s2.2;p17.35">Often managers control the quality, timing and volume of information released to non-executives.<ref target="BAWE_0398d-ftnote.048"/> As a result information reaching non-executives can be distorted, inaccurate or insufficient.<ref target="BAWE_0398d-ftnote.049"/> The Combined Code attempts thwart this practice by providing that information should be released in a timely manner and be of such quality that non-executives are able to discharge their duties. <ref target="BAWE_0398d-ftnote.050"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0398d-ftnote.048"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">ibid </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0398d-ftnote.049"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">see: Dent, G.W., Jr., The Revolution in Corporate Governance, the Monitoring Board, and the Director's Duty of Care, 1981, 61 Boston University Law Review 623Revolution in Corporate Governance, the Monitoring Board, and the Director's Duty of Care, The; </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0398d-ftnote.050"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">The Combined Code on Corporate Governance, June 2006, para A.5 </s></p></note><p n="p18.35"><s n="s1.2;p18.35">Resignation is a course of action often favoured by non-executives who oppose managerial decisions.<ref target="BAWE_0398d-ftnote.051"/> The majority of non-executives have full time positions in other companies<ref target="BAWE_0398d-ftnote.052"/> and therefore, would not be able to allocate the time necessary to oppose managerial decisions. </s><s n="s2.2;p18.35">Resignation seems to be a particularly inadequate method of exerting pressure on the management and is not a desirable means of ensuring good corporate governance. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0398d-ftnote.051"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Esen, R., (op.cit.), pp. 204 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0398d-ftnote.052"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Hannigan B., (op.cit.), pp.151 </s></p></note><p n="p19.35"><s n="s1.2;p19.35">Monitoring is expected to run throughout a non-executive's term of office and not just in times of crisis.<ref target="BAWE_0398d-ftnote.053"/> Nonetheless, the courts have expressed a reticence to impose too stringent a requirement on non-executives<ref target="BAWE_0398d-ftnote.054"/>. </s><s n="s2.2;p19.35">It is felt, <hi rend="italic">inter alia</hi>, that too high an expectation would result in no well-advised individual possibly agreeing to become a non-executive director. <ref target="BAWE_0398d-ftnote.055"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0398d-ftnote.053"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Business Week, Lessons From Boardroom Dramas, 3rd February 1993, p. 134, cited in: Esen, R., (op.cit.), pp.203 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0398d-ftnote.054"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Re Continental Assurance Company of London plc. [2001] WL 720239, per Park J., at para.110 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0398d-ftnote.055"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">ibid </s></p></note><p n="p20.35"><s n="s1.2;p20.35">In theory impartial members of the board who examine the workings of the company from an insider's perspective are good enforcers of corporate governance. </s><s n="s2.2;p20.35">In reality non-executives are not always independent, have significant pressures on their time, are unlikely to be overly critical of the approach taken by management and lack the necessary influence to resist poor managerial decisions. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined">The role of institutional investors</head><p n="p21.35"><s n="s1.2;p21.35">Due to the size of institutional investors they have the ability to influence the actions of companies and these investors are seen as crucial to realizing good corporate governance.<ref target="BAWE_0398d-ftnote.056"/> Institutional investors are expected to scrutinise company management on behalf of themselves and smaller shareholders.<ref target="BAWE_0398d-ftnote.057"/> The Institutional Shareholders' Committee (ISC) recommends that institutions monitor performance<ref target="BAWE_0398d-ftnote.058"/> and satisfy themselves that the investee company's board is effective<ref target="BAWE_0398d-ftnote.059"/>. </s><s n="s2.2;p21.35">Institutional investors will normally consult reports published by the industry as well as undertake their own research to be sure that companies are complying with good governance recommendations.<ref target="BAWE_0398d-ftnote.060"/> The ISC's aim is to identify problems at an early stage to limit impact on shareholder value. <ref target="BAWE_0398d-ftnote.061"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0398d-ftnote.056"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Keasey, K., Thompson, S., Wright, M., (op.cit.), pp22 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0398d-ftnote.057"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">see: Combined Code 2006, para D.1; the Cadbury Committee (<hi rend="italic">op.cit</hi>.), the Greenbury Report (<hi rend="italic">op.cit</hi>.) and the Hampel Report (<hi rend="italic">op.cit</hi>.) all clearly emphasised the roles of institutional investors </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0398d-ftnote.058"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Institutional Shareholders Committee, The responsibilities of institutional shareholders and agents - statement of principles, 1992, pp.2 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0398d-ftnote.059"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">ibid, pp.3 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0398d-ftnote.060"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Mallin, C.A., (op.cit.), pp84 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0398d-ftnote.061"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Institutional Shareholders Committee, (op.cit.), pp.3 </s></p></note><p n="p22.35"><s n="s1.4;p22.35">Institutional shareholders can show their dissatisfaction with management through an 'exit' or 'voice' framework<ref target="BAWE_0398d-ftnote.062"/>. </s><s n="s2.4;p22.35">Normally institutional investors will seek to resolve any contentious issues with management through discussions. </s><s n="s3.4;p22.35">Abstention from voting on, or voting against, a particular issue is a further extension of the exercise of an institutional investor's 'voice'. </s><s n="s4.4;p22.35">The ISC recommends the use of dialogue, but does not preclude the sale of shares where this would be the most effective response to concerns.<ref target="BAWE_0398d-ftnote.063"/> Institutional investors are also in a position to intervene where they feel that it is necessary to do so.<ref target="BAWE_0398d-ftnote.064"/> Intervention can take several forms, including, public statements or calling extraordinary general meetings.<ref target="BAWE_0398d-ftnote.065"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0398d-ftnote.062"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">see: Hirschman, A.O., Exit, voice, and loyalty: responses to decline in firms, organizations, and states, 1970, Harvard University Press, London, pp.4 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0398d-ftnote.063"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Mallin, C.A., (op.cit.), pp85 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0398d-ftnote.064"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Institutional Shareholders Committee, (op.cit.), pp.3 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0398d-ftnote.065"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Mallin, C.A., (op.cit.), pp85 </s></p></note></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined">The limitations on the enforcement of good corporate practice by institutional investors</head><p n="p23.35"><s n="s1.3;p23.35">Asking institutional investors to monitor and control management on behalf of all shareholders in the firm can present fundamental problems. </s><s n="s2.3;p23.35">There are questions as to how willing or capable institutions are to actively govern corporations.<ref target="BAWE_0398d-ftnote.066"/> It has been argued that "institutions, at least on an individual basis, [do not have the incentive] to devote resources to active monitoring"<ref target="BAWE_0398d-ftnote.067"/>. </s><s n="s3.3;p23.35">This could be as a result of the fact that institutional shareholders are offered protection by the liquidity of the markets and can largely afford to be "uninterested in all but the most substantial abuses"<ref target="BAWE_0398d-ftnote.068"/>. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0398d-ftnote.066"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Keasey, K., Thompson, S., Wright, M., (op.cit.), pp.18 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0398d-ftnote.067"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">ibid </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0398d-ftnote.068"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">ibid, pp.8 </s></p></note><p n="p24.35"><s n="s1.2;p24.35">Institutional shareholders invest money on behalf of their own clients.<ref target="BAWE_0398d-ftnote.069"/> The interests of these clients do not necessarily run parallel to those of other shareholders or stakeholders in the business.<ref target="BAWE_0398d-ftnote.070"/> Large institutional investors may actively seek preferential treatment over other shareholders. </s><s n="s2.2;p24.35">Where these investors own equity with superior voting rights they may seek to avoid paying out cash flows on a pro-rata basis and instead pay themselves special dividends. <ref target="BAWE_0398d-ftnote.071"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0398d-ftnote.069"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">ibid </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0398d-ftnote.070"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Clarke, T. (ed), Corporate Governance: Critical Perspectives on Business and Management, Volume II, 2005, Routledge, London, pp25 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0398d-ftnote.071"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">ibid, pp26 </s></p></note><p n="p25.35"><s n="s1.3;p25.35">Problems of expropriation of smaller shareholders could be compounded where the institution is a different type of investor. </s><s n="s2.3;p25.35">For example, if the institutional investor is an equity holder it could use its position to compel the firm to take on risk, "since [the institutional investor] shares in the upside while the other investors, who might be creditors, bear all the costs of failure"<ref target="BAWE_0398d-ftnote.072"/>. </s><s n="s3.3;p25.35">It can be argued that, "while this governance structure may control managers, it leaves potential minority investors unprotected and hence unwilling to invest"<ref target="BAWE_0398d-ftnote.073"/>. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0398d-ftnote.072"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">ibid, pp27 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0398d-ftnote.073"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">ibid, pp28 </s></p></note></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined">Takeovers as a mechanism for corporate governance</head><p n="p26.35"><s n="s1.3;p26.35">Theory, as well as evidence, suggests that hostile takeovers are an effective means of ensuring a company is well managed.<ref target="BAWE_0398d-ftnote.074"/> Firms which are taken over are normally undervalued, which often reflects poor performance. </s><s n="s2.3;p26.35">Following acquisition, the new owner will typically remove the poorly functioning management. </s><s n="s3.3;p26.35">Takeovers have, therefore, been argued to be a crucial corporate governance mechanism.<ref target="BAWE_0398d-ftnote.075"/> However, the significant cost of a takeover means that only companies with major performance failures are likely to be involved.<ref target="BAWE_0398d-ftnote.076"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0398d-ftnote.074"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">see: Scharfstein, D., The Disciplinary Role of Takeovers, 1988, Review of Economic Studies, Vol. 55, No. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">182, 85; Jensen, M.C., Takeovers: Their Causes and Consequences, 1988, The Journal of Economic Perspectives, Vol. 2, No.1, 21 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0398d-ftnote.075"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">see: Jensen, M.C., 1993, (op.cit.) </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0398d-ftnote.076"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Clarke, T. (ed), (op.cit), pp.23 </s></p></note></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined">Problems with the regulation of corporate governance </head><p n="p27.35"><s n="s1.4;p27.35">Many commentators believe that "the current institutional restraints on managerial behaviour ... are simply inadequate to prevent corporate assets from being used in ways dictated by the managerial interest"<ref target="BAWE_0398d-ftnote.077"/>. </s><s n="s2.4;p27.35">One suggested reason for this is the lack of sanctions behind the provisions of the Combined Code. </s><s n="s3.4;p27.35">At present, the only result of non-compliance will be the response of institutional shareholders and the market itself. </s><s n="s4.4;p27.35">Only in the most serious cases of managerial ineptitude or self-interest is there likely to be a reaction. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0398d-ftnote.077"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Keasey, K., Thompson, S., Wright, M., (op.cit.), pp.7 </s></p></note><p n="p28.35"><s n="s1.3;p28.35">Arguably any meaningful market test is only likely to apply to small firms. </s><s n="s2.3;p28.35">The cost to a 'free' market capitalist society of a large corporation going into administration is too great for the government to endure.<ref target="BAWE_0398d-ftnote.078"/> The government loan which bailed out British Energy in 2002 provides a good example of certain companies being "too large to fail"<ref target="BAWE_0398d-ftnote.079"/>. </s><s n="s3.3;p28.35">Therefore, the only realistic restraint on the management in large firms is the threat of hostile takeover. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0398d-ftnote.078"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Monks, A.G. &amp; Minow, N., Corporate Governance, Third Edition, 2004, Blackwell Publishing, Oxford, pp.39 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0398d-ftnote.079"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">ibid </s></p></note><p n="p29.35"><s n="s1.1;p29.35">Takeovers, institutional investors and non-executive directors all appear to be mechanisms which will detect and react to cases of gross mismanagement but which do not look closely enough or are indifferent to less serious managerial excesses. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined">Why are there no legal sanctions? </head><p n="p30.35"><s n="s1.3;p30.35">The scandals of the end of the twentieth century and the beginning of the twenty-first, provoked immediate demands for legal change. </s><s n="s2.3;p30.35">However, using the law to regulate the financial industry "is not always the panacea hoped for"<ref target="BAWE_0398d-ftnote.080"/>. </s><s n="s3.3;p30.35">Compromises built into the law, inadequate solutions or inadequate resources for policing may be factors preventing the law from exercising effective control.<ref target="BAWE_0398d-ftnote.081"/> The fear is also that companies would be able to easily adapt to the law and use techniques such as creative accounting to circumvent new rules. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0398d-ftnote.080"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">McBarnet, D., After Enron: corporate governance, creative compliance and the uses of corporate social responsibility, in: O'Brien, J., Governing the Corporation, 2005, John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd, Chichester, pp.213 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0398d-ftnote.081"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">ibid </s></p></note><p n="p31.35"><s n="s1.1;p31.35">For this reason, principles, rather than specific rules, have been adopted as the most desirable means of regulating the ever adapting corporate sector.<ref target="BAWE_0398d-ftnote.082"/> This will better serve to see the spirit of the law respected, rather than the use of techniques to thwart the actual letter of the law. <ref target="BAWE_0398d-ftnote.083"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0398d-ftnote.082"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">ibid </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0398d-ftnote.083"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">ibid, pp.220 </s></p></note></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined">Conclusion </head><p n="p32.35"><s n="s1.2;p32.35">Corporate governance regulation is still in its infancy; however, there is no doubt that it "is an economic necessity, a political requirement and a moral imperative"<ref target="BAWE_0398d-ftnote.084"/>. </s><s n="s2.2;p32.35">The foundations of a reliable system have been laid and continued development of the roles of non-executives and institutional investors are the most desirable direction in which to proceed. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0398d-ftnote.084"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Charkham, J., Keeping Good Company: A study of corporate governance in five countries, 1994, Oxford University Press, Oxford, as cited by: Mallin, C.A., (op.cit.), pp269 </s></p></note><p n="p33.35"><s n="s1.4;p33.35">Internal regulation of the board through non-executives is a valuable objective. </s><s n="s2.4;p33.35">It is vital that non-executives exercise sufficient scrutiny and have sufficient independence to exert control over management. </s><s n="s3.4;p33.35">However, arguably, the most important restraint is that of institutional investors. </s><s n="s4.4;p33.35">There is an increased realisation and acceptance from institutional investors that the enforcement of good corporate practice is their role.<ref target="BAWE_0398d-ftnote.085"/> Successful regulation in this area relies on institutional investors continuing to embrace this role and to supplement the work of non-executives through carefully monitoring, and, where necessary, applying pressure on management on behalf of all other shareholders. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0398d-ftnote.085"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">see: Hermes Corporate Governance Principles, 2006 </s></p></note><p n="p34.35"><s n="s1.3;p34.35">Companies are increasingly acceptant of the Combined Code and the Code of Best Practice. </s><s n="s2.3;p34.35">This acceptance, coupled with the willingness of institutional investors to control management, means that there is no need for prescriptive and inflexible laws. </s><s n="s3.3;p34.35">As institutional investors continue to increasingly adapt to their role, monitoring and pressure on the board will increase, and better corporate governance practices will result. </s></p><p n="p35.35"><s n="s1.3;p35.35">It is vital to avoid the repetition of past damaging financial scandals. </s><s n="s2.3;p35.35">Should the current system fail to sufficiently regulate excessive managements, legal regulation should be considered. </s><s n="s3.3;p35.35">Meanwhile, the system should be subjected to continued review and institutional shareholders and the market itself should be encouraged to participate as much as possible. </s></p></div1></body><back><div1 type="bibliography"><head rend="underlined bold">Bibliography</head><div2 type="bibliography"><head rend="underlined bold">Books</head><p><hi rend="underlined">Benn, S. &amp; Dunphy, D. (eds)</hi>,<hi rend="bold"> Corporate governance and sustainability: challenges for theory and practice</hi>, 2007, Routledge, London</p><p><hi rend="underlined">Clarke, T. (ed)</hi>, <hi rend="bold">Corporate Governance: Critical Perspectives on Business and Management</hi>, Volumes I and II, 2005, Routledge, London </p><p><hi rend="underlined">Charkham, J.</hi>, <hi rend="bold">Keeping Good Company: A study of corporate governance in five countries</hi>, 1994, Oxford University Press, Oxford</p><p><hi rend="underlined">Hannigan B.</hi>, <hi rend="bold">Company Law</hi>, 2003, Oxford University Press, Oxford</p><p><hi rend="underlined">Hirschman, A.O.</hi>, <hi rend="bold">Exit, voice, and loyalty: responses to decline in firms, organizations, and states</hi>, 1970, Harvard University Press, London</p><p><hi rend="underlined">Keasey, K., Thompson, S., Wright, M.</hi>, <hi rend="bold">Corporate Governance: Economic, Management and Financial Issues</hi>, 1997, Oxford University Press, Oxford</p><p><hi rend="underlined">Malik, F.</hi>, <hi rend="bold">Effective Top Management: Beyond the Failure of Corporate Governance and Shareholder Value</hi>, 2006, Wiley-VCH, Weinheim</p><p><hi rend="underlined">Mallin, C.A.</hi>, <hi rend="bold">Corporate Governance</hi>, Second Edition, 2007, Oxford University Press, Oxford</p><p><hi rend="underlined">Monks, A.G. &amp; Minow, N.</hi>, <hi rend="bold">Corporate Governance</hi>, Third Edition, 2004, Blackwell Publishing, Oxford</p><p><hi rend="underlined">O'Brien, J.</hi>, <hi rend="bold">Governing the Corporation</hi>, 2005, John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd, Chichester</p><p><hi rend="underlined">Tricker, R.I.</hi>, <hi rend="bold">Corporate Governance</hi>, 2000, Dartmouth Publishing Company, Aldershot</p></div2><div2 type="bibliography"><head rend="underlined bold">Journals </head><p><hi rend="underlined">Benfield, R.E.</hi>, <hi rend="bold">Curing American Managerial Myopia: Can the German System of Corporate Governance Help</hi>, 1995, 17 Loyola of Los Angeles International and Comparative Law Review, 615</p><p><hi rend="underlined">Cioffi, J.W.</hi>, <hi rend="bold">Governing Globalization? The State, Law, and Structural Change in Corporate Governance</hi>, 2000, Journal of Law and Society, Vol. 27, No. 4, pp. 572</p><p><hi rend="underlined">Cosh, A. &amp; Hughes, A.</hi>, <hi rend="bold">The Changing Anatomy of Corporate Control and the Market for Executives in the United Kingdom</hi>, 1997, Journal of Law and Society, Vol. 24, No. 1, 104</p><p><hi rend="underlined">Dent, G.W., Jr.</hi>, <hi rend="bold">The Revolution in Corporate Governance, the Monitoring Board, and the Director's Duty of Care</hi>, 1981, 61 Boston University Law Review 623</p><p><hi rend="underlined">Elson, C.M.</hi>, <hi rend="bold">Director Compensation and the Management-Captured Board: The History of the Symptom and a Cure</hi>, 1996, 50 Southern Methodist University Law Review 127</p><p><hi rend="underlined">Esen, R.</hi>, <hi rend="bold">Managing and monitoring: the dual role of non-executive directors on UK and US boards</hi>, 2000, International Company and Commercial Law Review, 11(6), 202</p><p><hi rend="underlined">Gilson, R.J. &amp; Kraakman, R.</hi>, <hi rend="bold">Reinventing the Outside Director: An Agenda for Institutional Investors</hi>, 1991, Stanford Law Review, Vol. 43, No. 4, 863</p><p><hi rend="underlined">Jensen, M.C.</hi>, <hi rend="bold">Takeovers: Their Causes and Consequences</hi>, 1988, The Journal of Economic Perspectives, Vol. 2, No.1, 21</p><p><hi rend="underlined">Jensen, M.C.</hi>, <hi rend="bold">The Modern Industrial Revolution, Exit, and the Failure of Internal Control Systems</hi>, 1993, Journal of Finance, Vol. 48, No.3, 831</p><p><hi rend="underlined">Parkinson, J. &amp; Kelly, G.</hi>, <hi rend="bold">The Combined Code on Corporate Governance</hi>, 70(1) The Political Quarterly 101</p><p><hi rend="underlined">Scharfstein, D.</hi>, <hi rend="bold">The Disciplinary Role of Takeovers</hi>, 1988, Review of Economic Studies, Vol. 55, No. 182, 85</p><p><hi rend="underlined">Shleifer, A. &amp; Vishny, R.</hi>, <hi rend="bold">A survey of Corporate Governance</hi>, 1997, Journal of Finance, Vol.52, No.2</p></div2><div2 type="bibliography"><head rend="underlined bold">Legislation/Codes</head><p>Financial Services and Markets Act 2000</p><p>The Combined Code on Corporate Governance, June 2006 </p></div2><div2 type="bibliography"><head rend="underlined bold">Case Law</head><p>Re Continental Assurance Company of London plc. [2001] WL 720239</p></div2><div2 type="bibliography"><head rend="underlined bold">Other/electronic resources</head><p><hi rend="underlined">Institutional Shareholders Committee</hi>, <hi rend="bold">The responsibilities of institutional shareholders and agents - statement of principles</hi>, 1992, <seg type="URL" n="http://www.investmentuk.org/press/2002/20021021.asp"/></p><p><hi rend="underlined">United Kingdom Listing Authority</hi>, <hi rend="bold">Listing Rules</hi>, <seg type="URL" n="http://fsahandbook.info/FSA/html/handbook/LR"/></p><p><hi rend="underlined">Office of National Statistics</hi>, <hi rend="bold">Share Ownership: A report on ownership of shares as at 31 December 2004</hi>, 2005, HMSO, Norwich, <seg type="URL" n="http://www.statistics.gov.uk/cci/nugget.asp?id=107"/> </p><p><hi rend="underlined">Institutional Shareholders Committee</hi>, <hi rend="bold">The responsibilities of institutional shareholders and agents - statement of principles</hi>, 1992</p><p><hi rend="underlined">Hermes</hi>, <hi rend="bold">Hermes Corporate Governance Principles</hi>, 2006</p><p><hi rend="underlined">Company Law Review</hi>, <hi rend="bold">Modern Company Law for a Better Economy: Developing the Framework</hi>, 2000, URN 00/656, para 3.134</p></div2></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
