<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_0398e" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Has section 34 CJPOA had the desired effect and to what extent, if at all, has it disadvantaged defendants?</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">Evaluated as candidate compound assignment. Assigned to A4: text + major reflection rask: compound.</note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">deleted: header: module name and student number; footer: page numbers</note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">deleted: Words: 3,765</note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">appendices: Interview with Judge <name type="other"/>; account of two court cases</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">3</p><p n="date">unknown</p><p n="module title">unknown</p><p n="module code">LA313</p><p n="genre family">Critique</p><p n="discipline">Law</p><p n="disciplinary group">SS</p><p n="grade">unknown</p><p n="number of authors">unknown</p><p n="number of words">4281</p><p n="number of s-units">151</p><p n="number of p">48</p><p n="number of tables">0</p><p n="number of figures">0</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">0</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">0</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">28.4</p><p n="average s-units per p">3.1</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">compound assignment consisting of 2 parts (see notesStmt for details)</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">m</p><p n="year of birth">1985</p><p n="first language">English</p><p n="education">UKA</p><p n="course">European Law</p><p n="student ID">0398</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><docTitle><titlePart rend="bold">Has section 34 CJPOA had the desired effect and to what extent, if at all, has it disadvantaged defendants? </titlePart></docTitle></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="text"><p n="p1.48"><s n="s1.2;p1.48">The right to silence is a prominent feature of adversarial justice systems and is often erroneously viewed as a single entitlement<ref target="BAWE_0398e-ftnote.001"/>. </s><s n="s2.2;p1.48">The right to silence is in reality a collection of privileges; with the most important being the right of a suspect to remain silent under accusation or interrogation and the right of a suspect not to have to testify at his own trial. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0398e-ftnote.001"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">R v Director of Serious Fraud Office ex parte Smith [1992] 3 All E.R. 456, at 463-64 six different meanings are identified by Lord Mustill </s></p></note><p n="p2.48"><s n="s1.3;p2.48">The right to silence derives from the privilege against self-incrimination<ref target="BAWE_0398e-ftnote.002"/>. </s><s n="s2.3;p2.48">The judiciary have recognised the privilege as being "<hi rend="italic">deep</hi> <hi rend="italic">rooted in English law</hi>"<ref target="BAWE_0398e-ftnote.003"/> and as one of the rationales behind many other judicial safeguards, such as the rejection of improperly obtained confessions<ref target="BAWE_0398e-ftnote.004"/>. </s><s n="s3.3;p2.48">However, as Lord Mustill indicated, "<hi rend="italic">statutory interference with the right is almost as old as the right itself</hi>".<ref target="BAWE_0398e-ftnote.005"/> Furthermore, the judiciary itself has not always been a staunch advocate of this right and, in the past, courts have expressed regret that restrictive rules have prevented them from commenting on the failure of defendants to answer questions during interrogation. <ref target="BAWE_0398e-ftnote.006"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0398e-ftnote.002"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">described in the Latin maxim: "nemo debet prodere se ipsum" - "no one should be obliged to give himself away" </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0398e-ftnote.003"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.3;pn1.1">Lam Chi-ming and Others v Reginam (Privy Council) [1991] 93 Cr. </s><s n="s2.3;pn1.1">App. </s><s n="s3.3;pn1.1">R. 358, per Lord Griffiths, at 364 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0398e-ftnote.004"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.3;pn1.1">see: R v Sang [1979] 2 All ER 1222, at 1230; Lam Chi-ming and Others v Reginam (Privy Council) [1991] 93 Cr. </s><s n="s2.3;pn1.1">App. </s><s n="s3.3;pn1.1">R. 358, at 360 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0398e-ftnote.005"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">R v Director of Serious Fraud Office ex parte Smith [1992] 95 C.R. App. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">R. 191, per Lord Mustill at 206 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0398e-ftnote.006"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.5;pn1.1">see: Jackson, J., The Right of Silence: Judicial Responses to Parliamentary Encroachment, Vol.57, No.2, 1994, Modern Law Review, 270, pp.270; R v Gilbert [1977] 66 Cr. </s><s n="s2.5;pn1.1">App. </s><s n="s3.5;pn1.1">R. 237; R v Alladice [1988] 87 Cr. </s><s n="s4.5;pn1.1">App. </s><s n="s5.5;pn1.1">R. 380 </s></p></note><p n="p3.48"><s n="s1.3;p3.48">There is a clear tension between trying to strike a balance between protecting the defendant's established privilege against self-incrimination and the need for the courts to obtain the necessary information in order to convict criminals. </s><s n="s2.3;p3.48">Prior to 1994 the judiciary became increasingly reluctant to allow the defendant to thwart the prosecution case through silence, especially in civil matters<ref target="BAWE_0398e-ftnote.007"/>. </s><s n="s3.3;p3.48">The legislature reacted to this and other stimuli, especially the prevalent use of silence by suspected terrorists in Northern Ireland<ref target="BAWE_0398e-ftnote.008"/>, by passing the Criminal Justice and Public Order Act (CJPOA) 1994. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0398e-ftnote.007"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.3;pn1.1">see: Re London United Investments plc. [1991] B.C.C. </s><s n="s2.3;pn1.1">760; AT &amp; Y Istel Ltd v Tully [1993] A.C. </s><s n="s3.3;pn1.1">45 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0398e-ftnote.008"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">see: Jackson, J., Recent Developments in Criminal Evidence, 1989, 40, Northern Ireland Law Quarterly, 105 </s></p></note><p n="p4.48"><s n="s1.4;p4.48">The CJPOA disposed of the absolute right to silence and allowed, for the first time, courts to draw adverse inferences from a defendant's silence. </s><s n="s2.4;p4.48">The most important limitation of the right to silence, and the focus of this essay, is section 34 CJPOA which allows an inference to be drawn if the defendant, "<hi rend="italic">[upon] being questioned, ... failed to mention any fact [later] relied on in his defence</hi>"<ref target="BAWE_0398e-ftnote.009"/>. </s><s n="s3.4;p4.48">The rationale behind section 34 is that it is expected that an innocent individual would wish to provide his exculpatory explanation at the first opportunity. </s><s n="s4.4;p4.48">If he fails to do this the jury should be allowed to draw adverse inferences from his later fabrication, which is little more than an attempt to ambush the prosecution and ensure an unmerited acquittal. <ref target="BAWE_0398e-ftnote.010"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0398e-ftnote.009"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Criminal Justice and Public Order Act 1994 section 34(1)(a) </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0398e-ftnote.010"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Cooper, S., Legal Advice and Pre-trial Silence - Unreasonable Developments, 2006, 10 International Journal of Evidence and Proof, 60, pp.61 </s></p></note><p n="p5.48"><s n="s1.5;p5.48">However, even prior to the CJPOA the "<hi rend="italic">common law right [to remain silent had] been diluted in certain areas</hi>"<ref target="BAWE_0398e-ftnote.011"/>. </s><s n="s2.5;p5.48">For example, in cases where a person is accused of a crime by another speaking to him on even terms, then he ought to reply to that accusation, and "<hi rend="italic">if he does not it is some evidence to show that he admits the [accusation] to be true</hi>"<ref target="BAWE_0398e-ftnote.012"/>. </s><s n="s3.5;p5.48">The judge was also able to comment, although <hi rend="italic">not adversely</hi>, on a defendant's failure to make a statement.<ref target="BAWE_0398e-ftnote.013"/> This allowed the jury to be reminded that, where a defence was raised for the first time in court, the police had not had the opportunity to test its veracity. </s><s n="s4.5;p5.48">The judge could further draw the attention of the jury to the fact that the defendant's silence in court has "<hi rend="italic">deprived [them] of the opportunity of hearing his story tested in cross-examination</hi>"<ref target="BAWE_0398e-ftnote.014"/>. </s><s n="s5.5;p5.48">It is evident, that in reality, prior to the CJPOA, the right to silence did not exist in absolute form and both common law and statutes<ref target="BAWE_0398e-ftnote.015"/> had weakened and limited its application. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0398e-ftnote.011"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Yates, C., Actions Speak Louder than Words, Vol. 40, No. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">3, 1977, The Modern Law Review, 361, pp.361 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0398e-ftnote.012"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.5;pn1.1">R v Mitchell [1892] 17 Cox C.C. </s><s n="s2.5;pn1.1">503, per Cave J. at 508; see also: R v Christie [1914] A.C. </s><s n="s3.5;pn1.1">545; Parkes v The Queen (Privy Council) [1976] 1 W.L.R. 1251; R v Black [1992] 16 Cr. </s><s n="s4.5;pn1.1">App. </s><s n="s5.5;pn1.1">R. 118 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0398e-ftnote.013"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.3;pn1.1">R v Gilbert [1977] 66 Cr. </s><s n="s2.3;pn1.1">App. </s><s n="s3.3;pn1.1">R. 237 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0398e-ftnote.014"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">R v Bathurst [1968] 1 All ER 1175 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0398e-ftnote.015"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">see: Police and Criminal Evidence Act 1984 sections 24-32 - giving police power to arrest for questioning </s></p></note><p n="p6.48"><s n="s1.3;p6.48">Many commentators were heavily opposed to the introduction of adverse inferences, especially as the right to silence had already been significantly undermined. </s><s n="s2.3;p6.48">O'Reilly argued that, "<hi rend="italic">the use of adverse inferences will erode or eliminate the right to silence and, in doing so, shift the burden of proof to the accused, in some cases reduce the prosecution's burden of proof, and will weaken or remove the presumption of innocence</hi>"<ref target="BAWE_0398e-ftnote.016"/>. </s><s n="s3.3;p6.48">This essay shall examine whether, following the introduction of the CJPOA, and the resulting jurisprudence, the legislation has successfully achieved its goal and whether a defendant is in a substantially more disadvantaged position. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0398e-ftnote.016"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">O'Reilly, G.W., England Limits the Right to Silence and Moves Towards an Inquisitorial System of Justice, Vol. 85, No. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">2, 1994, The Journal of Criminal Law and Criminology, pp 444 </s></p></note><div2><head rend="underlined">The affect of section 34 on suspects in police stations</head><p n="p7.48"><s n="s1.4;p7.48">Section 34 has had a marked impact on the practice adopted by suspects in police stations. </s><s n="s2.4;p7.48">Home Office research shows that the percentage of suspects remaining silent during interview, or only selectively answering questions, has dropped by 4% and 3%<ref target="BAWE_0398e-ftnote.017"/> respectively. </s><s n="s3.4;p7.48">The legislation was also successful in persuading criminals charged with serious offences to talk; they were amongst the groups with the "<hi rend="italic">largest drop in the use of silence</hi>"<ref target="BAWE_0398e-ftnote.018"/>. </s><s n="s4.4;p7.48">On the other hand, one of the principal reasons the legislation was introduced was to prevent terrorists and professional criminals from subverting the investigation of offences, and Home Office research<ref target="BAWE_0398e-ftnote.019"/> found that "<hi rend="italic">there had been little change in the willingness of those suspects to answer police questions</hi>"<ref target="BAWE_0398e-ftnote.020"/>. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0398e-ftnote.017"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Bucke, T., Street, R., &amp; Brown, D., The right of silence: the impact of the Criminal Justice and Public Order Act 1994, 2000, Home Office Research Study 199, pp.31 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0398e-ftnote.018"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">ibid, pp.32 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0398e-ftnote.019"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">see: ibid, pp.36-37; Phillips, C. &amp; Brown, D., Entry into the criminal justice system: a survey of police arrests and their outcomes, 1998, Home Office Research Study 185 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0398e-ftnote.020"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Jackson, J., Silence and Proof: Extending the Boundaries of Criminal Proceedings in the United Kingdom, 2001, 5 International Journal of Evidence and Proof, 145, pp. 158 </s></p></note><p n="p8.48"><s n="s1.4;p8.48">Prior to the enactment of CJPOA, 20% of those who received legal advice would remain silent compared with 3% who declined their right to a solicitor<ref target="BAWE_0398e-ftnote.021"/>. </s><s n="s2.4;p8.48">Reducing the number of suspects being advised to remain silent by solicitors was a principal aim of section 34. </s><s n="s3.4;p8.48">Judge Kennedy<ref target="BAWE_0398e-ftnote.022"/> maintains that the legislation has been successful in achieving this aim and he stated that since the introduction of the CJPOA "<hi rend="italic">suspects who have received legal advice ... are a lot more likely to participate</hi>" in police interview. </s><s n="s4.4;p8.48">Research supports Judge Kennedy's view; "<hi rend="italic">among suspects receiving legal advice, the proportion refusing all questions fell from 20 to 13 percent and among those refusing some questions from 19 to nine per cent</hi>"<ref target="BAWE_0398e-ftnote.023"/>. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0398e-ftnote.021"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Home Office Research Study 199, pp.32, see: supra, no.17 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0398e-ftnote.022"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Judge William Kennedy, Snaresbrook Crown Court Judge, see: Appendix A, Interview with Judge William Kennedy </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0398e-ftnote.023"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">ibid, pp.32 </s></p></note><p n="p9.48"><s n="s1.4;p9.48">Whilst it is manifestly obvious that the restriction the CJPOA places on the right to silence has prompted a change in defence practices, it is unclear whether the primary objective, of making it easier for the police and the prosecution to prove their case, has been achieved. </s><s n="s2.4;p9.48">The legislation has been found to be relatively ineffectual where the defendant has refused to speak, "<hi rend="italic">as any adverse inferences ... were unable to fill large deficits in the prosecution case</hi>"<ref target="BAWE_0398e-ftnote.024"/>. </s><s n="s3.4;p9.48">Consequently, and unsurprisingly, the defendant's silence has played only a marginal role in decisions to prosecute. </s><s n="s4.4;p9.48">Many prosecutors see silence as something which only aids the prosecution indirectly by serving to undermine the defence, rather than to bolster the prosecution case. <ref target="BAWE_0398e-ftnote.025"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0398e-ftnote.024"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Jackson, J., Silence and Proof, pp. 162, see: supra, no.20 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0398e-ftnote.025"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">ibid </s></p></note><p n="p10.48"><s n="s1.3;p10.48">Section 34 has, however, rendered the defendant significantly more likely to participate in police interrogation. </s><s n="s2.3;p10.48">As a result, many police officers believe that, instead of receiving silence from a defendant, they now get "<hi rend="italic">a pack of lies</hi>"<ref target="BAWE_0398e-ftnote.026"/>; although, the police see the opportunity to have something to investigate as valuable. </s><s n="s3.3;p10.48">The prosecution case will be reinforced where the police manage to disprove the defendant's claims and, in certain cases, counsel will be forced to advance a different defence at trial, thereby inviting inferences. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0398e-ftnote.026"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Home Office Research Study 199, pp.35, see: supra, no.17 </s></p></note><p n="p11.48"><s n="s1.4;p11.48">Police claims that the provisions are beneficial to the prosecution, are not reflected by the statistics<ref target="BAWE_0398e-ftnote.027"/>. </s><s n="s2.4;p11.48">The charge rate for suspects who answered all questions remained constant and where suspects refused to answer some or all questions the charge rate actually dropped by 6%. </s><s n="s3.4;p11.48">This may be indicative of the fact that "<hi rend="italic">those who now exercise the right of silence mainly do so where the evidence against them is weak</hi>"<ref target="BAWE_0398e-ftnote.028"/>. </s><s n="s4.4;p11.48">The study<ref target="BAWE_0398e-ftnote.029"/> also points out that, as only a minority of suspects exercise their right to silence at the police station, it would be unrealistic to expect the legislation to have a considerable impact on aggregate crime statistics. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0398e-ftnote.027"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">ibid, pp.40-41 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0398e-ftnote.028"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">ibid, introduction, pp. x </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0398e-ftnote.029"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">ibid </s></p></note></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">European and domestic case law following the introduction of the CJPOA 1994</head><p n="p12.48"><s n="s1.1;p12.48">The statutory reforms introduced by the CPJOA were shrouded in controversy and widely expected to result in many appeals in the higher courts.<ref target="BAWE_0398e-ftnote.030"/> These reservations have not proved unfounded<ref target="BAWE_0398e-ftnote.031"/> and the European Court of Human Rights (ECtHR) has frequently been consulted with cases concerning section 34. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0398e-ftnote.030"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Dennis, I., The Criminal Justice and Public Order Act 1994: The Evidence Provisions, 1995, Criminal Law Review, 4 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0398e-ftnote.031"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Cooper, pp.62, see: supra, no.10 </s></p></note><p n="p13.48"><s n="s1.2;p13.48">In Murray v UK<ref target="BAWE_0398e-ftnote.032"/> the ECtHR ruled that, "<hi rend="italic">the question whether the right [to silence] is absolute must be answered in the negative</hi>"<ref target="BAWE_0398e-ftnote.033"/>. </s><s n="s2.2;p13.48">However, much of the subsequent litigation concerning section 34 has restricted the scope of the silence provision of the CJPOA. In R v Bowden<ref target="BAWE_0398e-ftnote.034"/> the Court of Appeal ruled that, "<hi rend="italic">since [sections 34-37 CJPOA] restrict rights recognised at common law as appropriate to protect defendants against the risk of injustice, they should not be construed more widely than the statutory language requires</hi>"<ref target="BAWE_0398e-ftnote.035"/>. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0398e-ftnote.032"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">[1996] 22 E.H.R.R. 29 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0398e-ftnote.033"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">ibid, at 61 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0398e-ftnote.034"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.3;pn1.1">[1999] 2 Cr. </s><s n="s2.3;pn1.1">App. </s><s n="s3.3;pn1.1">R. 176 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0398e-ftnote.035"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">ibid, per Lord Bingham CJ, at 181 </s></p></note><p n="p14.48"><s n="s1.2;p14.48">The European jurisprudence has also conferred specific rights on defendants and, to avoid infringing article 6, the use of adverse inferences must be strictly controlled. </s><s n="s2.2;p14.48">In Murray v UK<ref target="BAWE_0398e-ftnote.036"/> the ECtHR ruled that no inference from silence may be drawn against a defendant who has been denied access to legal advice. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0398e-ftnote.036"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">[1996] 22 E.H.R.R. 29 </s></p></note><p n="p15.48"><s n="s1.3;p15.48">In Condron v UK<ref target="BAWE_0398e-ftnote.037"/> the ECtHR emphasised that the trial judge must direct the jury with particular care with regard to drawing adverse inferences from silence. </s><s n="s2.3;p15.48">The ECtHR stated that, inferences could only be drawn if, "<hi rend="italic">[the jury were] satisfied that silence at police interview could only sensibly be attributed to [the defendant] having no answer or none that would stand up to cross examination</hi>"<ref target="BAWE_0398e-ftnote.038"/>. </s><s n="s3.3;p15.48">This extra protection for the defendant is reflected in the judge's summing up to the jury.<ref target="BAWE_0398e-ftnote.039"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0398e-ftnote.037"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">[2001] 31 E.H.R.R. 1 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0398e-ftnote.038"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">ibid at 61 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0398e-ftnote.039"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">see: Specimen Directions, Judicial Studies Board, No. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">40.(3), Defendant's Failure to Mention Facts when Questioned or Charged - Section 34, CJPOA 1994 </s></p></note><p n="p16.48"><s n="s1.3;p16.48">The ECtHR further reduced the impact of section 34 by affirming that it is "<hi rend="italic">incompatible with the right to silence to base a conviction solely or mainly on the accused's silence</hi>"<ref target="BAWE_0398e-ftnote.040"/>. </s><s n="s2.3;p16.48">This limit is also reflected in the specimen direction, which states that the "<hi rend="italic">prosecution's case against [the suspect must be] so strong that it clearly calls for an answer</hi>"<ref target="BAWE_0398e-ftnote.041"/>. </s><s n="s3.3;p16.48">This requirement for more than simply a <hi rend="italic">prima facie</hi> case prior to drawing adverse inferences clearly further limits the application of section 34. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0398e-ftnote.040"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Averill v United Kingdom [2001] 31 E.H.R.R. 36, at 839 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0398e-ftnote.041"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Specimen Directions, No.40(3), see: supra, no.39 </s></p></note><p n="p17.48"><s n="s1.2;p17.48">European jurisprudence has also prompted important decisions in the English courts. </s><s n="s2.2;p17.48">The recent case of R v Bresa<ref target="BAWE_0398e-ftnote.042"/> held that the judge must specifically warn the jury of the "<hi rend="italic">need to be sure that the defendant's silence is attributable to the fact that he has no explanation to give, or none that would stand up to scrutiny</hi>"<ref target="BAWE_0398e-ftnote.043"/>, otherwise adverse inferences could not be drawn. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0398e-ftnote.042"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">[2005] EWCA Crim 1414 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0398e-ftnote.043"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Cooper, pp.66, see: supra, no.10 </s></p></note><p n="p18.48"><s n="s1.2;p18.48">The courts have rejected the notion that by merely relying on the advice of a lawyer to remain silent, the defendant could avoid adverse inferences being drawn as this would render section 34 "<hi rend="italic">wholly nugatory</hi>"<ref target="BAWE_0398e-ftnote.044"/>. </s><s n="s2.2;p18.48">However, in R v Hoare<ref target="BAWE_0398e-ftnote.045"/> the Court of Appeal confirmed that where a defendant genuinely and reasonably relied on the legal advice to remain silent, then the jury should be directed that an adverse inference could not be drawn.<ref target="BAWE_0398e-ftnote.046"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0398e-ftnote.044"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.3;pn1.1">R v Condron [1997] 1 Cr. </s><s n="s2.3;pn1.1">App. </s><s n="s3.3;pn1.1">R. 185, per Stuart-Smith LJ, at 191 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0398e-ftnote.045"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.3;pn1.1">[2005] 1 Cr. </s><s n="s2.3;pn1.1">App. </s><s n="s3.3;pn1.1">R. 22; see also: R v Beckles [2005] 1 W.L.R. 2829 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0398e-ftnote.046"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.3;pn1.1">Specimen Directions, No. </s><s n="s2.3;pn1.1">40.(5), see: supra, no. </s><s n="s3.3;pn1.1">39 </s></p></note></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">Post-CJPOA disadvantages to the accused</head><p n="p19.48"><s n="s1.2;p19.48">The case law developed from the CJPOA shows clear friction between, on one hand, giving effect to the Parliamentary intention behind the CJPOA and, on the other, guaranteeing the fair trial rights of the defendant. </s><s n="s2.2;p19.48">One of the areas which have come under scrutiny as a result of this tension is the defendant's relationship with his lawyer, and, more specifically, the advice which the defendant chooses to accept. </s></p><p n="p20.48"><s n="s1.3;p20.48">As the law currently stands, "<hi rend="italic">genuine reliance by a defendant on his solicitor's advice to remain silent is not in itself enough to preclude adverse comment</hi>"<ref target="BAWE_0398e-ftnote.047"/>. </s><s n="s2.3;p20.48">Defendants are, therefore, in a very complicated position. </s><s n="s3.3;p20.48">They can no longer be sure if it is <hi rend="italic">reasonable</hi> to rely on their solicitor's advice, consequently, they cannot be sure whether following the advice will be detrimental to their case. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0398e-ftnote.047"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.3;pn1.1">R v Hoare [2005] 1 Cr. </s><s n="s2.3;pn1.1">App. </s><s n="s3.3;pn1.1">R. 22, per Auld L.J., at 372 </s></p></note><p n="p21.48"><s n="s1.3;p21.48">A further difficulty when relying on advice to remain silent relates to legal professional privilege. </s><s n="s2.3;p21.48">The general rule protects any communication between solicitors and their clients, thereby supplying the solicitor with all the information he needs in order to provide accurate and helpful legal advice.<ref target="BAWE_0398e-ftnote.048"/> Section 34 creates a problem where a defendant seeks to disclose the content of a privileged conversation to demonstrate the reasonableness of his decision to follow advice to remain silent. </s><s n="s3.3;p21.48">The defendant is entitled to do this, but this can "<hi rend="italic">amount to a waiver of privilege so that the accused, or if his solicitor is so called, the solicitor, can be asked whether there were any other reasons for the advice</hi>"<ref target="BAWE_0398e-ftnote.049"/>. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0398e-ftnote.048"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">see: R v Derby Magistrates' Court, Ex parte B [1996] 1 AC 487, per Lord Taylor of Gosforth C.J. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0398e-ftnote.049"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.4;pn1.1">Cape, E., Sidelining Defence Lawyers: Police Station Advice after Condron, 1996-1997, 1 International Journal of Evidence &amp; Proof, 386, at 399, citing R v Condron [1997] 1 Cr. </s><s n="s2.4;pn1.1">App. </s><s n="s3.4;pn1.1">R. 185 and R v Roble [1997] Crim. </s><s n="s4.4;pn1.1">L. R. 449 </s></p></note><p n="p22.48"><s n="s1.4;p22.48">Defendants who wish to avoid adverse inferences by demonstrating the reasonableness of their reliance on the advice to remain silent are left with two options. </s><s n="s2.4;p22.48">On one hand, the defendant may decide that the adverse inferences from silence would be more detrimental to his case than revealing the content of his solicitor-client discussions and, therefore, he will waive his solicitor-client privilege. </s><s n="s3.4;p22.48">On the other hand, he may have to suffer the consequences of adverse inferences in order to avoid the content of his potentially incriminating privileged conversations being subject to the scrutiny of the court.<ref target="BAWE_0398e-ftnote.050"/> The defendant is in an unenviable situation and he simply has to choose the course of action which he believes will weaken his defence the least. </s><s n="s4.4;p22.48">There is a clear conflict with the principle against self-incrimination<ref target="BAWE_0398e-ftnote.051"/>. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0398e-ftnote.050"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">see: R v F, Snaresbrook Crown Court, 26 March 2007, unreported (see: Appendix B) </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0398e-ftnote.051"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">see: supra, no.2 </s></p></note><p n="p23.48"><s n="s1.3;p23.48">Proponents of section 34 would argue that an innocent defendant will have nothing to hide and would suffer no ill effects from having his conversations with his legal advisor examined. </s><s n="s2.3;p23.48">This does not account for the multitude of reasons an innocent defendant might have for not wanting the contents of a confidential dialogue scoured in open court. </s><s n="s3.3;p23.48">These reasons include wishing to protect the identity of a third party, or keeping information, such as details of an extra-marital affair<ref target="BAWE_0398e-ftnote.052"/>, secret. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0398e-ftnote.052"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">see: R v H, Snaresbrook Crown Court, 1 April 2007, unreported, (see: Appendix B) </s></p></note><p n="p24.48"><s n="s1.3;p24.48">Vulnerable defendants also come under increased pressure and are those in most danger of suffering a miscarriage at the hands of section 34. </s><s n="s2.3;p24.48">Cooper argues that it is not unrealistic to imagine a vulnerable suspect receiving "<hi rend="italic">honestly given (but nonetheless possibly poor) legal advice to remain silent ... only to discover later that by taking and acting upon that advice, the case against him has been strengthened</hi>"<ref target="BAWE_0398e-ftnote.053"/>. </s><s n="s3.3;p24.48">Whilst it could possibly be naïve and foolish for the defendant to rely on the advice, gullibility does not affect the genuineness of his decision to rely on the advice and is no way indicative of guilt. <ref target="BAWE_0398e-ftnote.054"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0398e-ftnote.053"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Cooper, pp.68-69, see: supra, no.10 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0398e-ftnote.054"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">ibid, pp.68-69 </s></p></note><p n="p25.48"><s n="s1.2;p25.48">Whilst it is possible in theory for such a scenario to occur, many proponents of section 34 argue that increased safeguards at the police station, such as the appropriate adult<ref target="BAWE_0398e-ftnote.055"/> and the custody officer<ref target="BAWE_0398e-ftnote.056"/>, provide ample protection for defendants. </s><s n="s2.2;p25.48">Judge Kennedy<ref target="BAWE_0398e-ftnote.057"/> believes that, "<hi rend="italic">only an incompetent solicitor, an idiotic defendant and an uncaring custody officer would place a [vulnerable] defendant in the position of suffering a miscarriage due to their silence</hi>" he goes on to say that "<hi rend="italic">miscarriages [do not occur] very often ... and certainly not as a result of silence</hi>". </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0398e-ftnote.055"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Judge Kennedy, see: Appendix A, argues that "in the case of a vulnerable or disturbed individual the solicitor should be seeking to have an appropriate adult present" </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0398e-ftnote.056"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Judge Kennedy, see: Appendix A, argues that "the custody officer is the true professional in the police station. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">He is the one who signs everything off and will be held to account for irregularities so he would be sure to make sure that the appropriate provisions are made for vulnerable defendants" </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0398e-ftnote.057"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Judge William Kennedy, see: supra, no.21 </s></p></note><p n="p26.48"><s n="s1.3;p26.48">Regardless of whether the defendant is actually sufficiently protected or not, it is clear that the weakening of the privileged solicitor-client relationship will damage his ability to formulate a defence. </s><s n="s2.3;p26.48">"<hi rend="italic">Instead of [the solicitor] being able to tell his client that anything which the client might say would never in any circumstances be revealed without his consent, he would have to qualify his assurance</hi>"<ref target="BAWE_0398e-ftnote.058"/>. </s><s n="s3.3;p26.48">This undermines the very purpose of the privileged relationship and "<hi rend="italic">raises the fundamental question of the utility of legal advice at the police station; [its value] is in danger of being seriously eroded</hi>"<ref target="BAWE_0398e-ftnote.059"/>. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0398e-ftnote.058"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">R v Derby Magistrates' Court, Ex parte B [1996] 1 AC 487, at 508 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0398e-ftnote.059"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Cape, pp.402, see: supra, no.49 </s></p></note></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">Predicted disadvantages which have failed to materialise</head><p n="p27.48"><s n="s1.4;p27.48">Section 34 has undoubtedly prejudiced the defendant in certain areas, however, numerous concerns raised prior to the CJPOA have failed to materialise or do not appear to have had undesirable consequences for defendants. </s><s n="s2.4;p27.48">Commentators initially predicted that section 34 would provoke more confessions by suspects<ref target="BAWE_0398e-ftnote.060"/> as well as "<hi rend="italic">false confessions from weak suspects</hi>"<ref target="BAWE_0398e-ftnote.061"/>. </s><s n="s3.4;p27.48">Home Office research proved these concerns unfounded. </s><s n="s4.4;p27.48">Since the legislation has been passed police interviews have resulted in exactly the same percentage of confessions as prior to 1994. <ref target="BAWE_0398e-ftnote.062"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0398e-ftnote.060"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">see: Zander, M., Abolition of the Right of Silence 1972-1994, in Morgan &amp; Stephenson (eds), Suspicion and Silence: The Right to Silence in Criminal Investigations, 1994, Blackstone, London </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0398e-ftnote.061"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">O'Reilly, pp. 405, see: supra, no.16 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0398e-ftnote.062"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Home Office Research Study 185, see: supra, no.19 </s></p></note><p n="p28.48"><s n="s1.4;p28.48">It was also thought that the silence provisions would result in the erroneous convictions of innocent defendants who would normally have refused to comment. </s><s n="s2.4;p28.48">This would be in danger of occurring if an innocent defendant failed "<hi rend="italic">to offer cogent explanations for [his] behaviour or became confused</hi>"<ref target="BAWE_0398e-ftnote.063"/>. </s><s n="s3.4;p28.48">It is difficult to assimilate empirical evidence to either prove or disprove this theory. </s><s n="s4.4;p28.48">However, it is obvious that with fewer defendants remaining silent in police interrogation the risk of this occurring has increased. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0398e-ftnote.063"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">O'Reilly, pp. 405, see: supra, no.16 </s></p></note><p n="p29.48"><s n="s1.2;p29.48">Theoretical arguments which oppose to the right to silence have also been expounded, the most noteworthy of which is the game-theoretic analysis proposed by Seidmann and Stein<ref target="BAWE_0398e-ftnote.064"/>. </s><s n="s2.2;p29.48">The concept purports to "<hi rend="italic">distinguish the innocent from the guilty by inducing an anti-pooling effect that enhances the credibility of innocent suspects</hi>"<ref target="BAWE_0398e-ftnote.065"/>. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0398e-ftnote.064"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Seidmann, D.J. &amp; Stein, A., The Right to Silence Helps the Innocent: A Game-Theoretic Analysis of the Fifth Amendment Privilege, Vol.114, No.2, Harvard Law Review, 2000, 430 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0398e-ftnote.065"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">ibid, at 433 </s></p></note><p n="p30.48"><s n="s1.4;p30.48">The game-theoretic analysis speculates that guilty suspects will chose to remain silent rather than risk telling lies because they "<hi rend="italic">fear that the police or the prosecution will discover the truth and use their lies against them as evidence of guilt</hi>"<ref target="BAWE_0398e-ftnote.066"/>. </s><s n="s2.4;p30.48">This sets them apart from innocent suspects, who are expected to offer exculpatory explanations at the earliest opportunity. </s><s n="s3.4;p30.48">Seidmann and Stein argue that, where there is no right to silence, guilty suspects have a greater incentive to lie and these lies would "<hi rend="italic">obscure the differences between the guilty and the innocent and, consequently, reduce the trustworthiness of accounts given by innocent suspects</hi>"<ref target="BAWE_0398e-ftnote.067"/>. </s><s n="s4.4;p30.48">The jury would find it more difficult to give evidential weight to exculpatory statements and miscarriages of justice would be more likely to occur. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0398e-ftnote.066"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">ibid </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0398e-ftnote.067"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">ibid </s></p></note><p n="p31.48"><s n="s1.5;p31.48">If the assumptions made by Seidmann and Stein are correct then the theory puts forward a strong case for maintaining the right to silence. </s><s n="s2.5;p31.48">Unfortunately, however, they present a "<hi rend="italic">logical model rather than an empirically demonstrated thesis</hi>"<ref target="BAWE_0398e-ftnote.068"/>. </s><s n="s3.5;p31.48">Many aspects of the game-theoretic analysis cannot be quantified and the theory is readily undermined. </s><s n="s4.5;p31.48">For example, it does not properly take into account those criminals who believe that they can formulate a convincing lie and therefore would not remain silent anyway. </s><s n="s5.5;p31.48">Prior to 1994 these guilty individuals were already 'pooling' themselves with innocent suspects in considerable numbers. <ref target="BAWE_0398e-ftnote.069"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0398e-ftnote.068"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Roberts, P., &amp; Zuckerman, A., Criminal Evidence, 2004, Oxford University Press, Oxford, pp.423 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0398e-ftnote.069"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">ibid </s></p></note></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">Is the accused necessarily disadvantaged by section 34? </head><p n="p32.48"><s n="s1.2;p32.48">Whilst many commentators maintain that section 34 has significantly diminished the privilege against self-incrimination, there is an argument that defendants are now no more disadvantaged. </s><s n="s2.2;p32.48">In terms of the impact of the legislation on the jury, questions have been raised about the impact of section 34. </s></p><p n="p33.48"><s n="s1.2;p33.48">Prior to the 1994 Act, juries were already taking a dim view of silence<ref target="BAWE_0398e-ftnote.070"/> and although the judge would direct that nothing should be inferred from the defendant's silence, "<hi rend="italic">the jury would still wonder why the defendant gave a 'no comment' interview</hi>"<ref target="BAWE_0398e-ftnote.071"/>. </s><s n="s2.2;p33.48">Due to the secrecy of jury deliberations it is impossible to know the true extent of the affect of silence on the jury either before or after the CJPOA. Many legal professionals and commentators believe, however, that juries have always drawn adverse inferences from what they believed to be an unjustified silence and they continue to do so today.<ref target="BAWE_0398e-ftnote.072"/> This suggests that section 34 has had a negligible impact on the jury. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0398e-ftnote.070"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Home Office Research Study 199, pp.63, see: supra, no.17 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0398e-ftnote.071"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Judge William Kennedy, see: supra, no.21 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0398e-ftnote.072"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">see: Jackson, J., Silence and Proof, pp.157, see: supra, no.20 </s></p></note><p n="p34.48"><s n="s1.4;p34.48">Taking the argument to the next logical stage; it can be claimed that defendants are actually in a more advantageous position. </s><s n="s2.4;p34.48">The current direction to the jury<ref target="BAWE_0398e-ftnote.073"/> is considerably more comprehensive than the pre-CJPOA direction. </s><s n="s3.4;p34.48">The direction explicitly asserts that the jury may draw adverse inferences from the defendant's silence if they believe that "<hi rend="italic">the only sensible explanation for [the defendant's] failure to [mention the facts] is that he had no answer at the time or none that would stand up to scrutiny</hi>"<ref target="BAWE_0398e-ftnote.074"/>. </s><s n="s4.4;p34.48">Judge Kennedy believes that the word 'only' provides significant protection for the defendant, as "<hi rend="italic">it invites the jury to consider the multitude of other reasons why [the defendant] may have remained silent</hi>"<ref target="BAWE_0398e-ftnote.075"/>. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0398e-ftnote.073"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Specimen Directions, No. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">40.(3), see: supra, no.39 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0398e-ftnote.074"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">ibid (emphasis added) </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0398e-ftnote.075"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Judge William Kennedy, see: supra, no.21 </s></p></note><p n="p35.48"><s n="s1.3;p35.48">The word 'only' and the remaining elements of the three test direction leave the jury unlikely to "<hi rend="italic">read anything into silence unless it strikes them as totally unreasonable and without other possible explanation</hi>"<ref target="BAWE_0398e-ftnote.076"/>. </s><s n="s2.3;p35.48">In contrast, before the CJPOA the judge merely gave a statement that the defendant is not obliged to give evidence and that failure to do so must not be taken as an admission of guilt.<ref target="BAWE_0398e-ftnote.077"/> Assuming that juries have always drawn adverse inferences, then prior to 1994 these inferences would have been drawn without direction as to how to apply them. </s><s n="s3.3;p35.48">Judge Kennedy believes that this left scope for "<hi rend="italic">indecision and possible mistake</hi>"<ref target="BAWE_0398e-ftnote.078"/>. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0398e-ftnote.076"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">ibid </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0398e-ftnote.077"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">see: Appendix D, Specimen directions relevant prior to 10 April 1995 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0398e-ftnote.078"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Judge William Kennedy, see: supra, no.21 </s></p></note><p n="p36.48"><s n="s1.2;p36.48">The Court of Appeal expressed anxiety at the comprehensiveness of silence directions, saying that "<hi rend="italic">even in the simplest and most straightforward of cases [section 34 requires a direction] of such length and detail that it seems to promote the adverse inference question to a height it does not merit</hi>"<ref target="BAWE_0398e-ftnote.079"/>. </s><s n="s2.2;p36.48">It is clearly arguable that, this highly detailed direction induces careful consideration of the issue of silence by the jury and accordingly defendants benefit from greater protection. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0398e-ftnote.079"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">R v Bresa [2005] EWCA Crim 1414, per Waller LJ </s></p></note></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">Conclusion</head><p n="p37.48"><s n="s1.5;p37.48">The removal of the right to silence has had mixed success. </s><s n="s2.5;p37.48">The CJPOA has essentially made the problem of ambush defences disappear. </s><s n="s3.5;p37.48">However, it has been unsuccessful in preventing terrorists and criminals involved in serious organised crime from relying on silence.<ref target="BAWE_0398e-ftnote.080"/> The legislation has also been successful in encouraging more suspects to answer questions during interrogation, although the increased information given to the police has not resulted in a rise in the percentage of suspects charged. </s><s n="s4.5;p37.48">Furthermore, "<hi rend="italic">packs of lies</hi>"<ref target="BAWE_0398e-ftnote.081"/> often increase workload by forcing police to investigate spurious claims. </s><s n="s5.5;p37.48">Extra resources are not only required by police and prosecutors; there has been extensive case law surrounding the CJPOA and it has been argued that the act should be repealed on the basis of costs alone<ref target="BAWE_0398e-ftnote.082"/>. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0398e-ftnote.080"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">see: supra, no. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">20 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0398e-ftnote.081"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">see: supra, no. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">26 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0398e-ftnote.082"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Birch, D.J., Suffering in silence: a cost-benefit analysis of section 34 of the Criminal Justice and Public Order Act 1994, 1999, Criminal Law Review, 769 </s></p></note><p n="p38.48"><s n="s1.2;p38.48">It is also evident that ECtHR judgments have significantly reduced the impact of section 34. </s><s n="s2.2;p38.48">Further rulings in the ECtHR will require "<hi rend="italic">Parliament to take further action, [and] tinker with section 34 so as to [further] reduce its impact</hi>"<ref target="BAWE_0398e-ftnote.083"/>. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0398e-ftnote.083"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">ibid pp.788 </s></p></note><p n="p39.48"><s n="s1.3;p39.48">Ensuring fair trial guarantees for vulnerable witnesses relies on the "<hi rend="italic">solicitor giving advice at the police station</hi>"<ref target="BAWE_0398e-ftnote.084"/>. </s><s n="s2.3;p39.48">Suspects cannot, however, confidently rely on advice without fear of reprisals, as the court may find that his reliance was not reasonable or genuine. </s><s n="s3.3;p39.48">It is not a desirable state of affairs where a solicitor is unable to give accurate advice on how the defendant should proceed to ensure the best possible chance of an acquittal. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0398e-ftnote.084"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Judge William Kennedy, see: supra, no.21 </s></p></note><p n="p40.48"><s n="s1.5;p40.48">Authority is given to section 34 by the jury. </s><s n="s2.5;p40.48">The jury's understanding of the law is the most important consideration when deciding whether law has achieved its desired effect and if the defendant is actually disadvantaged. </s><s n="s3.5;p40.48">It is notoriously difficult to gauge the weight given to evidence by the jury. </s><s n="s4.5;p40.48">Assuming the commentators and legal professionals who believe that juries have always drawn inferences from silence are correct, it is clear that defendants are not in a substantially worse position. </s><s n="s5.5;p40.48">Defendants may even benefit from the more instructive section 34 direction to juries. </s></p><p n="p41.48"><s n="s1.5;p41.48">Section 34 of the CJPOA is overcomplicated. </s><s n="s2.5;p41.48">The law puts added pressure on police resources and creates further expenses for the courts. </s><s n="s3.5;p41.48">Section 34 places the critical solicitor-client relationship under unnecessary strain and over complicates the advice given to confused and vulnerable defendants. </s><s n="s4.5;p41.48">Furthermore, the lack of change in charge rates, as well as the view that juries remain largely unaffected, calls into question the impact of section 34. </s><s n="s5.5;p41.48">Parliament should "<hi rend="italic">[give] up the ghost and revert to the common law rule</hi>"<ref target="BAWE_0398e-ftnote.085"/>. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0398e-ftnote.085"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Birch, pp.788, see: supra, no.82 </s></p></note></div2></div1><div1 type="front-back-matter"><head rend="underlined bold">Bibliography</head><div2 type="bibliography"><head rend="underlined bold">Books</head><p><hi rend="underlined">Morgan &amp; Stephenson (eds)</hi>, <hi rend="bold">Suspicion and Silence: The Right to Silence in Criminal Investigations</hi>, 1994, Blackstone, London 
</p><p>
Roberts, P., &amp; Zuckerman, A. 
, <hi rend="bold">Criminal Evidence,</hi> 2004, Oxford University Press, Oxford 
</p></div2><div2 type="bibliography"><head rend="underlined bold">Journals/Articles</head><p>
Baldwin, J. 
, <hi rend="bold">Legal Advice at the Police Station</hi>, 1993, Criminal Law Review, 371 
</p><p>
Berger, M. 
, <hi rend="bold">Reforming Confession Law British Style: A Decade of Experience with Adverse Inferences</hi>, 2000, 31 Columbia Human Rights Law Review, 243 
</p><p>
Birch, D.J. 
, <hi rend="bold">Suffering in silence: a cost-benefit analysis of section 34 of the Criminal Justice and Public Order Act 1994</hi>, 1999, Criminal Law Review, 769 
</p><p>
Cape, E. 
, <hi rend="bold">Defending Suspects at the Police Station: The Practitioner's Guide to Advice and Representation</hi>, 1994, Criminal Law Review, 392 
</p><p>
Cape, E. 
, <hi rend="bold">Sidelining Defence Lawyers: Police Station Advice after Condron</hi>, 1996-1997, 1 International Journal of Evidence &amp; Proof, 386 
</p><p>
Cooper, S. 
, <hi rend="bold">Legal Advice and Pre-trial Silence - Unreasonable Developments</hi>, 2006, 10 International Journal of Evidence and Proof, 60 
</p><p>
Dennis, I. 
,<hi rend="bold"> The Criminal Justice and Public Order Act 1994: The Evidence Provisions,</hi> 1995, Criminal Law Review, 4 
</p><p>
Greer, S. 
, <hi rend="bold">The Right to Silence, Defence Disclosure and Confession Evidence</hi>, Vol.21, No.1, 1994, Journal of Law and Society, 102 
</p><p>
Ingraham, B.L. 
, <hi rend="bold">The Right of Silence, the Presumption of Innocence, the Burden of Proof, and a Modest Proposal: A Reply to O'Reilly,</hi> Vol.86, No.2, 1996, The Journal of Criminal Law and Criminology, 559 
</p><p>
Jackson, J. 
, <hi rend="bold">Recent Developments in Criminal Evidence</hi>, 1989, 40, Northern Ireland Law Quarterly, 105 
</p><p>
Jackson, J. 
, <hi rend="bold">Silence and Proof: Extending the Boundaries of Criminal Proceedings in the United Kingdom</hi>, 2001, 5 International Journal of Evidence and Proof, 145 
</p><p>
Jackson, J. 
, <hi rend="bold">The Right of Silence: Judicial Responses to Parliamentary Encroachment</hi>, Vol.57, No.2, 1994, Modern Law Review, 270 
</p><p>
Jennings, A.F. 
, <hi rend="bold">Silence and safety: the impact of human rights law</hi>, 2000, Criminal Law Review, 879 
</p><p>
McNicol, S.B. 
, <hi rend="bold">Strategies for Reform of the Law Relating to Police Interrogations,</hi> Vol. 33, No. 
2., 1984, The International and Comparative Law Quarterly, 265 
</p><p>
Notz, J.E. 
, <hi rend="bold">Prearrest Silence as Evidence of Guilt: What You Don't Say Shouldn't Be Used against You</hi>, Vol. 64, No. 
3, 1997, The University of Chicago Law Review, 1009 
</p><p>
O'Reilly, G.W. 
, <hi rend="bold">Comment on Ingraham's "Moral Duty" to Talk and the Right to Silence,</hi> Vol. 87, No. 
2, 1997, The Journal of Criminal Law and Criminology, 521 
</p><p>
O'Reilly, G.W. 
, <hi rend="bold">England Limits the Right to Silence and Moves Towards an Inquisitorial System of Justice</hi>, Vol. 85, No. 
2, 1994, The Journal of Criminal Law and Criminology, 402 
</p><p>
Seidmann, D.J. &amp; Stein, A. 
, <hi rend="bold">The Right to Silence Helps the Innocent: A Game-Theoretic Analysis of the Fifth Amendment Privilege</hi>, Vol.114, No.2, Harvard Law Review, 2000, 430 
</p><p>
Yates, C. 
,<hi rend="bold"> Actions Speak Louder than Words,</hi> Vol. 40, No. 
3, 1977, The Modern Law Review, 361 
</p><p>
Zander, M. 
, <hi rend="bold">Abolition of the Right of Silence 1972-1994</hi>, in Morgan &amp; Stephenson (eds), Suspicion and Silence: The Right to Silence in Criminal Investigations, 1994, Blackstone, London 
</p></div2><div2 type="bibliography"><head rend="underlined bold">Research Studies</head><p>
Bucke, T., Street, R., &amp; Brown, D. 
, <hi rend="bold">The right of silence: the impact of the Criminal Justice and Public Order Act 1994,</hi> 2000, Home Office Research Study 199, see: <seg type="URL" n="http://www.homeoffice.gov.uk/rds/pdfs/hors199.pdf"/> 
</p><p>
Phillips, C. &amp; Brown, D. 
, <hi rend="bold">Entry into the criminal justice system: a survey of police arrests and their outcomes,</hi> 1998, Home Office Research Study 185, see: <seg type="URL" n="http://www.homeoffice.gov.uk/rds/pdfs/hors185.pdf"/> 
</p></div2><div2 type="bibliography"><head rend="underlined bold">Cases</head><p>
AT &amp; Y Istel Ltd v Tully [1993] A.C. 
45 
</p><p>
Averill v United Kingdom [2001] 31 E.H.R.R. 36, at 839 
</p><p>
Condron v United Kingdom [2001] 31 E.H.R.R. 1 
</p><p>
Lam Chi-ming and Others v Reginam (Privy Council) [1991] 93 Cr. 
App. 
R. 358 
</p><p>
Murray v United Kingdom [1996] 22 E.H.R.R. 29 
</p><p>
Parkes v The Queen (Privy Council) [1976] 1 W.L.R. 1251 
</p><p>
Re London United Investments plc. [1991] B.C.C. 
760 
</p><p>
R v Alladice [1988] 87 Cr. 
App. 
R. 380 
</p><p>
R v Bathurst [1968] 1 All ER 1175 
</p><p>
R v Beckles [2005] 1 W.L.R. 2829 
</p><p>
R v Black [1992] 16 Cr. 
App. 
R. 118 
</p><p>
R v Bowden [1999] 2 Cr. 
App. 
R. 176 
</p><p>
R v Bresa [2005] EWCA Crim 1414 
</p><p>
R v Christie [1914] A.C. 
545 
</p><p>
R v Condron [1997] 1 Cr. 
App. 
R. 185 
</p><p>
R v Derby Magistrates' Court, Ex parte B [1996] 1 AC 487 
</p><p>
R v Director of Serious Fraud Office ex parte Smith [1992] 3 All E.R. 456 
</p><p>
R v F, Snaresbrook Crown Court, 26 March 2007, unreported (see appendix B) 
</p><p>
R v Gilbert [1977] 66 Cr. 
App. 
R. 237 
</p><p>
R v H, Snaresbrook Crown Court, 1 April 2007, unreported, (see appendix B) 
</p><p>
R v Hoare [2005] 1 Cr. 
App. 
R. 22 
</p><p>
R v Mitchell [1892] 17 Cox C.C. 
503 
</p><p>
R v Roble [1997] Crim. 
L. R. 449 
</p><p>
R v Sang [1979] 2 All ER 1222 
</p></div2><div2 type="bibliography"><head rend="underlined bold">Legislation</head><p>
Criminal Justice and Public Order Act 1994 
</p><p>
Police and Criminal Evidence Act 1984 
</p></div2><div2 type="bibliography"><head rend="underlined bold">Independent Research</head><p>
Interview with Judge <name type="other"/>, Snaresbrook Crown Court Judge (see: Appendix A) 
</p><p>
R v H, Snaresbrook Crown Court, 1 April 2007, unreported, (see: Appendix B) 
</p><p>
R v F, Snaresbrook Crown Court, 26 March 2007, unreported (see: Appendix B) 
</p><p>
Specimen Directions, Judicial Studies Board, No. 
40.(3), Defendant's Failure to Mention Facts when Questioned or Charged - Section 34, CJPOA 1994 (see: Appendix C) 
</p><p>
Specimen directions relevant prior to 10 April 1995 (see: Appendix D) 
</p></div2></div1><div1 type="text"><head rend="underlined bold">Research Memorandum</head><p n="p42.48"><s n="s1.4;p42.48">In February, I wrote to Snaresbrook Crown Court to ask if I could be a Marshal with a Crown Court judge for three days at the end of March. </s><s n="s2.4;p42.48">I was told that this would be possible and I was assigned to Judge <name type="other"/>, on the 26 <hi rend="sup">th</hi>, 27 <hi rend="sup">th</hi> and 28 <hi rend="sup">th</hi> March 2007. </s><s n="s3.4;p42.48">I sat with Judge <name type="other"/> during two cases, the first, <hi rend="underlined">R v F</hi>, involved intercourse with a girl under the age of 13 and the second, <hi rend="underlined">R v H</hi>, involved a street robbery of an elderly woman. </s><s n="s4.4;p42.48">I saw the summing up of <hi rend="underlined">R v F</hi> and the swearing in of the jury and the start of <hi rend="underlined">R v H</hi>. </s></p><p n="p43.48"><s n="s1.2;p43.48">I had decided, prior to sitting with Judge <name type="other"/> that I would see what evidence issues arose in the case or cases I witnessed and I would base my essay on this. </s><s n="s2.2;p43.48">The summing up of <hi rend="underlined">R v F</hi> provoked some interesting issues about the removal of the right to silence, I therefore decided to base my essay on section 34 CJPOA. </s></p><p n="p44.48"><s n="s1.5;p44.48">At this point I consulted <hi rend="bold">Roberts and Zuckerman</hi>, <hi rend="underlined">Criminal Evidence</hi>, our module core textbook for a preliminary discussion on my chosen topic. </s><s n="s2.5;p44.48">It was very helpful in providing an outline of the way in which the right to silence had changed and its impact on defendants. </s><s n="s3.5;p44.48">I also consulted journals referred to at the bottom of the lecture handout and in the footnotes of <hi rend="bold">Roberts and Zuckerman</hi>, <hi rend="underlined">Criminal Evidence</hi>. </s><s n="s4.5;p44.48">These included <hi rend="bold">Birch</hi> <hi rend="underlined">Suffering in silence: a cost-benefit analysis of section 34 of the Criminal Justice and Public Order Act 1994</hi>, <hi rend="bold">Jackson, J.,</hi> <hi rend="underlined">Silence and Proof: Extending the Boundaries of Criminal Proceedings in the United Kingdom</hi>, <hi rend="bold">Cape, E.,</hi> <hi rend="underlined">Sidelining Defence Lawyers: Police Station Advice after Condron</hi>. </s><s n="s5.5;p44.48">These provided me with an interesting discussion on the policy issues surrounding the abolition of the absolute right to silence. </s></p><p n="p45.48"><s n="s1.2;p45.48">Through research, I realised that since the Criminal and Public Order Act 1994 the right to silence has been divided into pre-trial silence, and silence during the trial. </s><s n="s2.2;p45.48">I wished to focus on the relationship between the state as prosecutor and the citizen as defendant, so I decided to focus solely on the issue of pre-trial silence. </s></p><p n="p46.48"><s n="s1.2;p46.48">I then interviewed Judge <name type="other"/>, asking for his opinions on the abolition of the absolute right to silence. </s><s n="s2.2;p46.48">The interview with Judge <name type="other"/>, as well as the two cases I witnessed, formed the basis of my independent research (see appendix for notes). </s></p><p n="p47.48"><s n="s1.6;p47.48">I used the University of <name type="university"/> library catalogue to access journals which dealt with the abolition of the right to silence. </s><s n="s2.6;p47.48">I found the following journals of particular use <hi rend="underlined">Cooper, S.</hi> </s><s n="s3.6;p47.48">, <hi rend="bold">Legal Advice and Pre-trial Silence - Unreasonable Developments</hi>, <hi rend="underlined">O'Reilly, G.W.</hi> </s><s n="s4.6;p47.48">, <hi rend="bold">England Limits the Right to Silence and Moves Towards an Inquisitorial System of Justice</hi> and <hi rend="underlined">Dennis, I.</hi> </s><s n="s5.6;p47.48">,<hi rend="bold"> The Criminal Justice and Public Order Act 1994: The Evidence Provisions</hi>. </s><s n="s6.6;p47.48">These further elucidated the general principles and scope of s34 and provided me with some useful analysis of cases. </s></p><p n="p48.48"><s n="s1.1;p48.48">I then completed the essay. </s></p></div1></body><back><div1 type="appendix"><head rend="underlined bold">Appendix A</head><p/></div1><div1 type="appendix"><head rend="underlined bold">Appendix B</head><p/></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
