<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_0405c" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Participant Observation</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">Evaluated as candidate compound assignment. Assigned to A4: text + major reflection rask: compound.</note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">deleted: page numbers</note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">deleted: Word Count: 588</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">4</p><p n="date">2006-03</p><p n="module title">Qualitative Methods in Social Research</p><p n="module code">SO915</p><p n="genre family">Narrative recount</p><p n="discipline">Sociology</p><p n="disciplinary group">SS</p><p n="grade">D</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">613</p><p n="number of s-units">17</p><p n="number of p">4</p><p n="number of tables">0</p><p n="number of figures">0</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">0</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">0</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">36.1</p><p n="average s-units per p">4.3</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">compound assignment consisting of 0 parts (see notesStmt for details)</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">f</p><p n="year of birth">1983</p><p n="first language">English</p><p n="education">UKA</p><p n="course">Masters in Social Research</p><p n="student ID">0405</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><titlePart><hi rend="underlined bold">Student Number: <name type="student ID"/> Seminar Tutor: <name type="tutor name"/></hi><hi rend="underlined bold"> Qualitative Methods in Social Research February 15th 2006</hi></titlePart><docTitle><titlePart rend="underlined bold">Participant Observation</titlePart></docTitle></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="section"><p n="p1.4"><s n="s1.8;p1.4">Brewer (2000) has described the aim of participant observation as two fold; firstly, as a means to 'understand the world as it is seen by those acting within it' and secondly, to reveal the taken-for-granted nature of that world (Brewer, 2000: 60). </s><s n="s2.8;p1.4">With these aims in mind, I decided to undertake a participant observation which would help me to gain a greater understanding of what has come to be termed 'deaf culture'. </s><s n="s3.8;p1.4">'Deaf culture' is a term used to describe shared sets of meanings, values and experiences inextricably tied to the experience of being deaf in a world predicated on verbal communication (Padden and Humphries, 2005) . </s><s n="s4.8;p1.4">One important expression of this culture has been the emergence of 'deaf clubs', usually organised as informal gatherings of (predominantly) deaf people, in which British Sign Language (BSL) becomes the principal means of communication. </s><s n="s5.8;p1.4">'Deaf clubs' have become an important form of social support for people with various forms of hearing impairment, and offer an opportunity for the sharing of experiences and socialising. </s><s n="s6.8;p1.4">I intended to go into the field as an overt observer and to conduct informal interviews with the participants regarding their experiences of deaf club and the role it played in their lives. </s><s n="s7.8;p1.4">As I have basic training in BSL, I hoped that this would enable me to act not only as an 'observant-as- participant' (Bryman, 2004), in other words, an observer whose role as researcher is first and foremost, but also give me some ability to participate more fully in the club setting. </s><s n="s8.8;p1.4">The training I had received also provided me with the initial contacts through which to organise my entry into the field, which totalled a three hour session one evening at a deaf club in a local town. </s></p><p n="p2.4"><s n="s1.5;p2.4">During my three hours in the field, my role as a participant/observer fluctuated, with one or the other role taking precedence at any given time, and with each impeding my ability to entirely commit to the other. </s><s n="s2.5;p2.4">It is widely recognised that the external socio-demographic characteristics of the researcher, together with their personal autobiography effects not only the acceptance of the researcher within the group (Brewer,2000), but also the way in which the research is recorded by the researcher. </s><s n="s3.5;p2.4">Indeed, I had a strong sense that my identity as a 'hearing person' created somewhat of a distance between myself and the group, exacerbated by my basic understanding of the language. </s><s n="s4.5;p2.4">This inevitably impacted on the form of data I was able to collect, as my inability to keep up with the flow of fast BSL meant that potentially useful data was lost. </s><s n="s5.5;p2.4">However, despite this, I was able to conduct several informal interviews with participants during which I jotted down notes. </s></p><p n="p3.4"><s n="s1.2;p3.4">At points my status as a disabled person, and my ability to use BSL (even in a limited capacity) united me with certain members of the group. </s><s n="s2.2;p3.4">Indeed, my experiences of my disability together with my motivations for taking up sign language were frequently brought up by members of the group as 'conversation-starters', and this common ground enabled me to conduct reasonably in-depth interviews and build a sense of rapport with certain members. </s></p><p n="p4.4"><s n="s1.2;p4.4">Paradoxically, my inability to integrate entirely within the deaf community in this setting could have provided me with a greater understanding, in some respects, of the lives of deaf people, and therefore the importance of such outlets as deaf clubs. </s><s n="s2.2;p4.4">The problems I experienced during my participant observation, for example, the language barrier, is exactly the sort of reality people with hearing impairments face on a daily basis in the 'hearing world', and in this way I gained a form of insight which I had not anticipated. </s></p></div1></body><back><div1 type="bibliography"><head rend="underlined bold">Bibliography</head><p>Brewer, J. D. 2000. 'The Research Process in Ethnography' in <hi rend="underlined">Ethnography</hi> Buckingham: Open University Press</p><p>Bryman, 2004. 'Participant Observation' in <hi rend="underlined">Social Research Methods</hi> Oxford: Oxford University Press</p><p>Padden, A. And T. Humphries. 2005. <hi rend="underlined">Inside Deaf Culture</hi> New York: Havard University Press</p><p rend="underlined bold">Appendix</p><p rend="underlined bold">Research Diary</p><p rend="underlined">Observational Notes</p><p>Despite the initial awkwardness following my entry into the field, after a short amount of time, I began to circulate around the various friendship groups into which people clustered within the group and approach people for interviews. As deaf clubs are social gatherings, people were keen to catch up on each other's news and I was aware that my presence could be viewed as an intrusion. On the whole, however, people responded to me positively and appeared willing to talk to me. I was able to conduct an informal interview with one young woman who described to me how often she attended the club, how she had started going and her experience of having deaf club as a resource in her overall 'coping strategy' in the hearing world.</p><p rend="underlined">Methodological Notes</p><p>My role within the interviews I conducted was informal, and it seemed that the longer I communicated with the club members, the more information they volunteered. Whilst this informal style of interviewing was useful and seemed to be congruent with the overall relaxed environment of the club, I was aware of the ethical implications. Indeed, it was possible in such a situation for respondents to forget that I was doing research and divulge information that they may not have said in a more formal context. I also tried to make the interview more of a two way process by volunteering information about my own experiences of disability, which I felt helped to build rapport.</p><p rend="underlined">Theoretical notes</p><p>My initial expectations about the observation was that the deaf club would be an important outlet for deaf people in the community, and this was largely reflected in the responses I got to interview questions. The participants saw it as a chance to share experiences, to make friendships with people and to be able to communicate freely in BSL which is not possible for the majority of their lives. Whilst this observation is useful in understanding the way in which deaf club can function as a means of social participation for deaf people, perhaps further participant observations would be needed to reach an understanding of how social participation is affected whilst outside of the club. Indeed, the club served in many ways as a 'vent' for negative experiences in the 'hearing world', therefore future observations may provide useful insights into these experiences as opposed to the ones within the club.</p><p rend="underlined">Analytic Memo</p><p>I feel that my research, in line with the literature on deaf culture, revealed the importance of deaf club, set within the broader context of the deaf community, as a vital component in the formation, and confirmation of, deaf identities. By providing a context for the expression of collective experiences, deaf club could be seen as validating the lives of deaf people within the hearing community, and providing them with a place to celebrate and reaffirm deaf culture. </p></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
