<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_0409f" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>THE BRAIN DRAIN AS THE REPRODUCTION OF A COLONIAL PATTERN OF EXPLOITATION</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">Language used in quote: <foreign id="English">English</foreign></note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">deleted: page numbers</note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">deleted: World count (excluding citations): 2998 words</note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">deleted: ,arkers comments in text</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">4</p><p n="date">2007-01</p><p n="module title">Global Law and Politics</p><p n="module code">LA999</p><p n="genre family">Essay</p><p n="discipline">Law</p><p n="disciplinary group">SS</p><p n="grade">D</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">3407</p><p n="number of s-units">117</p><p n="number of p">38</p><p n="number of tables">0</p><p n="number of figures">0</p><p n="number of block quotes">9</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">0</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">0</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">29.1</p><p n="average s-units per p">3.1</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">f</p><p n="year of birth">1982</p><p n="first language">French</p><p n="education">OSA</p><p n="course">International Development Law and Human Rights</p><p n="student ID">0409</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><titlePart><hi rend="bold"><name type="student name"/><name type="student ID"/></hi><hi rend="bold"> University of <name type="university"/>, Law School IDLHR</hi><hi rend="bold"> Module: Global Law and Politics</hi></titlePart><docTitle><titlePart rend="bold">THE BRAIN DRAIN AS THE REPRODUCTION OF A COLONIAL PATTERN OF EXPLOITATION</titlePart></docTitle></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="section"><p n="p1.38"><s n="s1.5;p1.38">This paper addresses the colonial shape of the skilled-workers migration from the South to the North. </s><s n="s2.5;p1.38">The thesis of this study is that the brain drain constitutes a loss for developing countries and benefits the developed countries and that this type of movement of resources (human capital) from the South (sending countries) to the North (receiving countries) is the 'reproduction' (Bourdieu) of a colonial pattern of exploitation, that will be analysed from a Marxian perspective. </s><s n="s3.5;p1.38">What is at stake is the way capitalism, as an ideology, that has the capacity to renew itself (Boltanski, Chiapello), can use new means of exploitation. </s><s n="s4.5;p1.38">It is important to acknowledge that this type of migration is completely voluntary and legal. </s><s n="s5.5;p1.38">This is precisely the nature of this new form of exploitation: it works, through incentives, on the will of high skilled workers from the South, where their home country cannot afford to offer them the wages they expect, to improve their standards of living abroad. </s></p><p n="p2.38"><s n="s1.2;p2.38">After discussing the reality of the brain drain and its effects, the myth of the brain gain and the existence of a brain waste, using empirical findings and theoretical studies (I), the reasons why the brain drain is the reproduction of a colonial pattern of exploitation will be assessed (II). </s><s n="s2.2;p2.38">The possible responses that international law and a global labour movement can eventually give to this type of exploitation will be analysed (III). </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head>I) <hi rend="underlined">The brain drain, the brain gain and the brain waste: myths and reality </hi></head><p n="p3.38"><s n="s1.1;p3.38">In this section I envisage the complexity of the phenomenon of the brain drain, the debates concerning the losses and gains due to the brain drain and conclude by the assertion that the brain drain is the transfer of the human capital from the South to the North. </s></p><div2><head>1.1) <hi rend="underlined">The scope of the brain drain</hi></head><p n="p4.38"><s n="s1.4;p4.38">The brain drain is a complex phenomenon that cannot be apprehended through one variable. </s><s n="s2.4;p4.38">The causes, conditions, extent, and effects of the brain drain vary according to the host and home countries concerned, and the professions. </s><s n="s3.4;p4.38">One cannot assert a univocal definition of such a complex phenomenon and simplify its reality into a generalising theory. </s><s n="s4.4;p4.38">That is why, in order not to deform a complex reality, this study does not envisage the flow of skilled labour as one general phenomenon, but focuses on the situation in the most struck countries (small and low-income countries of Africa, the Caribbean area and the islands Pacific and Oceania). </s></p><p n="p5.38"><s n="s1.3;p5.38">The brain drain is a transfer of skilled and high-skilled workers (13 years and above of tertiary education) which constitutes a loss in terms of externalities that the skilled migrants do not create when they leave the sending country and a benefit in terms of wealth and growth in the receiving country. </s><s n="s2.3;p5.38">Indeed, the migrant' education is most of the times funded by the government on the bases of taxes on the population. </s><s n="s3.3;p5.38">The brain drain is 'a proportion of the total educated labour force' which chose to emigrate and represents 'a pressure imposed on the local labour market'. </s></p><quote lang="English">'The pressure exerted by 1,037,000 Indian skilled emigrants (4.3 percent of the educated total labour force) is less important than the pressure exerted by 16,000 skilled emigrants from Grenada (85 percent of educated labour force)'<ref target="BAWE_0409f-ftnote.001"/>. </quote><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0409f-ftnote.001"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ozden, Schiff (2006: 166) </s></p></note><p n="p6.38"><s n="s1.1;p6.38">The part of total migrants represented by high-skilled migrants is increasing. </s></p><quote lang="English">'Skilled workers are much more concerned with international migration'. Indeed, 'the world average emigration rate increased from 5.0 to 5.4 percent among the highly skilled and from 1.4 to 1.8 percent for the medium skilled. A slight decrease (from 1.2 to 1.1 percent) was observed for low-skilled workers'<ref target="BAWE_0409f-ftnote.002"/>.</quote><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0409f-ftnote.002"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid. p. 167 </s></p></note><p n="p7.38"><s n="s1.5;p7.38">This study takes into consideration the relative effect of the emigration of skilled workers on a society more than the absolutenumbers. </s><s n="s2.5;p7.38">With the same or less( number of skilled emigrants, the effects are crucial in proportion for a small and low-income country than for a large and high-income country. </s><s n="s3.5;p7.38">Most of the detractors of the bad effects of the brain drain on poor countries assert that the flow is relatively important because of the low level of education. </s><s n="s4.5;p7.38">But this low level of education is precisely the consequence of the departure of the most educated part of the population. </s><s n="s5.5;p7.38">It is a vicious circle. </s></p></div2><div2><head>1.2) <hi rend="underlined">The myth of the brain gain as an attempt at legitimising the brain drain</hi></head><p n="p8.38"><s n="s1.5;p8.38">The new brain drain literature strongly argues that, instead of being a loss for the developing country (as the traditional literature affirms), the brain drain constitutes a gain. </s><s n="s2.5;p8.38">The classical arguments are that migrant workers send remittances to the home country which is used in investments in housing, more education, construction... </s><s n="s3.5;p8.38">Besides the remittances, other effects of the brain drain would result in growth and welfare. </s><s n="s4.5;p8.38">The expectation of return from a higher education is induced by the higher wages earned by workers abroad. </s><s n="s5.5;p8.38">The result is a greater investment in education and the will to acquire a higher education. </s></p><quote lang="English">'Because skilled wages are typically higher in destination countries, the brain drain raises the expected benefit from education and induces additional investment in education'<ref target="BAWE_0409f-ftnote.003"/>. </quote><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0409f-ftnote.003"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid. p. 11 </s></p></note><p n="p9.38"><s n="s1.3;p9.38">The assertion of a brain gain is exaggerated because not all the migrants return. </s><s n="s2.3;p9.38">Most of them prefer to enjoy higher wages and better environment in the host country<ref target="BAWE_0409f-ftnote.004"/>. </s><s n="s3.3;p9.38">More arguments are listed in the World Bank report: the uncertainty of the benefit of education and its repercussion on its costs; the investment in education results in the reduction of the expenditures on other sectors such as health and public infrastructures; the brain waste.( </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0409f-ftnote.004"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">W. Glaser (1978: 204) </s></p></note></div2><div2><head>1.3) <hi rend="underlined">Not only the brain drain a transfer of skilled labour but this human capital is sometimes wasted in the destination country</hi></head><p n="p10.38"><s n="s1.9;p10.38">The brain waste is the extreme side of the brain drain. </s><s n="s2.9;p10.38">For equal qualifications, the employer in the destination country will prefer to hire a native than a foreign worker. </s><s n="s3.9;p10.38">The brain drain concerns the welfare of the home country, whereas the brain waste relates to the welfare of both the migrant and after all the home country since the investment in the worker's education is not balanced by the remittances, added skills and knowledge that he would have gained thanks to a job corresponding to his education level. </s><s n="s4.9;p10.38">This phenomenon is due to various causes. </s><s n="s5.9;p10.38">First, the employer may not be aware of the value and the level of qualifications of the migrant because of bad information from the ending country. </s><s n="s6.9;p10.38">Second, the migrant himself does not have the right information about the job opportunities. </s><s n="s7.9;p10.38">Then, the barriers of the language, the difficulty to obtain a legal status, the delay of adaptation are other reasons<ref target="BAWE_0409f-ftnote.005"/>. </s><s n="s8.9;p10.38">A study by Stalker (1994), cited in the World Bank report, states that 'Jamaica has had to train five doctors to retain one, a brain drain of 80 percent'<ref target="BAWE_0409f-ftnote.006"/>. </s><s n="s9.9;p10.38">The case of the Philippino doctors, who go back to college to become nurse because the demand f nurse is more important than the demand f doctors in the U.S.A, is unfortunately well known. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0409f-ftnote.005"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Dina Ionescu ( 2005) </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0409f-ftnote.006"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ozden, Schiff, op. cit., p. 202 </s></p></note><p n="p11.38"><s n="s1.1;p11.38">This section aimed at drawing an overview of the realities and debates about the brain drain. </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head>II/ <hi rend="underlined">The reasons why the brain drain is the reproduction of a colonial pattern of exploitation </hi></head><p n="p12.38"><s n="s1.1;p12.38">I will try to demonstrate the link between the aftermaths of the( colonization, which I believe is not over(, but occurs differently than in the past, in the present postcolonial context; a Marxian approach of the brain drain (as the exploitation of the skills rather than the physical force) an the 'reproduction' of this model of international relations with the Bourdieusian concept of 'symbolic violence'. </s></p><div2><head>2.1) <hi rend="underlined">The colonial shape of the international relations</hi></head><p n="p13.38"><s n="s1.2;p13.38">The terms 'colonial' and 'colonization' are used both in a precise and broad way. </s><s n="s2.2;p13.38">To colonise is the imposition (by the use of force<ref target="BAWE_0409f-ftnote.007"/>, international law<ref target="BAWE_0409f-ftnote.008"/>, discourses, and diplomatic, economic and political means) of a relationship of domination (economical, political, symbolic, cultural<ref target="BAWE_0409f-ftnote.009"/>...) by the countries who possess (and created these means to the others; and to maintain this relation (through the theories of development<ref target="BAWE_0409f-ftnote.010"/>). </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0409f-ftnote.007"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">P. Guillaume (1999) </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0409f-ftnote.008"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">A. Anghie </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0409f-ftnote.009"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">L. Sklair </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0409f-ftnote.010"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">A. Escobar </s></p></note><p n="p14.38"><s n="s1.5;p14.38">The first stage in the history of colonization is the armed conquest and the economic exploitation of the physical resources (human force, natural resources) of the colonised countries which led to their underdevelopment. </s><s n="s2.5;p14.38">Then, the decolonization and the importation/creation of the State gave the sovereignty to the new State and a supposed formal equality with the Western states. </s><s n="s3.5;p14.38">But it was in reality a way to keep control over the new State which had de facto to accept the rules of International law made by and for the European nations. </s><s n="s4.5;p14.38">The aid to development was the new name for dependency and neo-colonization. </s><s n="s5.5;p14.38">Despite the numerous resistances (post-developmental studies and activism<ref target="BAWE_0409f-ftnote.011"/>, subaltern cosmopolitanism, International Law and globalization from below<ref target="BAWE_0409f-ftnote.012"/>) the colonial pattern (the most efficient way for capitalistic countries to take advantage of less powerful countries, for capitalism as an ideology to renew itself, for the 'new spirit of capitalism'<ref target="BAWE_0409f-ftnote.013"/> to realise) is based today on the transfer of human capital form the South to the North. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0409f-ftnote.011"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">M. Rahnema, V. Bawtree </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0409f-ftnote.012"><p n="pn1.2"><s n="s1.1;pn1.2">B. De Sousa Santos </s></p><p n="pn2.2"><s n="s1.1;pn2.2">B. Rajagopal </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0409f-ftnote.013"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">L. Boltanski, E. Chiapello </s></p></note></div2><div2><head>2.2) <hi rend="underlined">A Marxian approach of the brain drain</hi></head><quote lang="English">'From its earliest beginnings 600 years ago down to the present, the capitalist world economy has always expanded through two alternative phases: a phase of material expansion - in the course of which a growing mass of money capital was channelled into trade and production - and a phase of financial expansion, in the course of which a growing mass of capital reverted to its money form and went into lending, borrowing and speculation'<ref target="BAWE_0409f-ftnote.014"/>.</quote><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0409f-ftnote.014"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Silver, Arrighi (2001: 9) </s></p></note><p n="p15.38"><s n="s1.4;p15.38">In the same way, the structure of production has also changed. </s><s n="s2.4;p15.38">Capitalism was first based on material and standardized mass production of consumption goods. </s><s n="s3.4;p15.38">It is today concentrating on the R&amp;D, the conception of high added value goods and technologies, immaterial tertiary services that no longer necessitate a massive labour force but a skilled and educated one. </s><s n="s4.4;p15.38">This relocation of capitalistic production on high added value goods and technologies is also the result of the over accumulation of the normal goods. </s></p><p n="p16.38"><s n="s1.6;p16.38">In a Marxian perspective, the skilled-labour power is a commodity and exploitation. </s><s n="s2.6;p16.38">The proletariat (as a unified and easily identifiable category who sells its physical force) is replaced by an intern subdivision within the workers between manual and mental, low-skilled and high-skilled. </s><s n="s3.6;p16.38">The class is not the object of exploitation but rather the level of education. </s><s n="s4.6;p16.38">The new spirit of capitalism uses the international elite to foster its pattern of exploitation, through a perpetual reinvention of colonialism (as exploitation of human resources). </s><s n="s5.6;p16.38">In this process, the migrant is reduced to his economical utility and ceased to be seen as a person. </s><s n="s6.6;p16.38">This is the depersonalisation of humans by capitalism<ref target="BAWE_0409f-ftnote.015"/>. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0409f-ftnote.015"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">M. Samers (:213) </s></p></note><p n="p17.38"><s n="s1.6;p17.38">The exploitation is subtle in the sense that the worker is not forced to emigrate. </s><s n="s2.6;p17.38">It is his choice. </s><s n="s3.6;p17.38">He is not directly exploited <hi rend="italic">stricto sensu</hi> because he is offered highly qualified jobs for high wages. </s><s n="s4.6;p17.38">It is his country of origin which is damaged. </s><s n="s5.6;p17.38">If we consider the skills and education of a person as part of the potential of a society to develop<ref target="BAWE_0409f-ftnote.016"/>, a society that invested on the education system, then the brain drain is precisely the seize( of an essential resource. </s><s n="s6.6;p17.38">There is exploitation when the receiving country does not compensate the loss caused by the brain drain in the sending country, and benefit the creation of growth (through scientific innovation for instance). </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0409f-ftnote.016"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Development understood as sustainable economic growth, poverty reduction, social advancement, human empowerment and socio-economic equity. </s></p></note></div2><div2><head>2.3) <hi rend="underlined">The interpretation of the concept of 'reproduction' of the colonial pattern of exploitation from the Bourdieusian perspective of the 'symbolic violence'</hi></head><p n="p18.38"><s n="s1.3;p18.38">I wantto analyse the mechanisms of power at stake in the 'reproduction' of a colonial pattern of exploitation through the brain drain. </s><s n="s2.3;p18.38">Therefore, I use the Bourdieusian concepts of 'reproduction' and 'symbolic violence' ('as the imposition of a cultural arbitrary by an arbitrary power'<ref target="BAWE_0409f-ftnote.017"/>) with which he analysed the relation of domination in the French society between a dominant class (the bourgeoisie) and the dominated. </s><s n="s3.3;p18.38">This symbolic and cultural domination consists in the imposition of an arbitrary culture </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0409f-ftnote.017"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">P. Bourdieu, JC Passeron (1989 : 5) </s></p></note><quote lang="English">'as the structure and functions of that culture cannot be deduced from any universal principle, whether physical, biological or spiritual, not being linked with any sort of internal relation to the 'nature of things' or any 'human nature''<ref target="BAWE_0409f-ftnote.018"/>.</quote><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0409f-ftnote.018"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid. p. 8 </s></p></note><p n="p19.38"><s n="s1.1;p19.38">The arbitrary becomes then legitimate because it is imposed by arbitrary means (the 'pedagogic action' through the 'pedagogic authority'). </s></p><p n="p20.38"><s n="s1.3;p20.38">The reproduction of the elite occurs through the acquisition of this culture. </s><s n="s2.3;p20.38">Only the members of the dominant class know and possess the means to acquire this culture ('<hi rend="italic">habitus'</hi>). </s><s n="s3.3;p20.38">As a consequence, the dominant class reproduces the pattern of domination. </s></p><p n="p21.38"><s n="s1.6;p21.38">Let us now transpose these concepts to the international scale. </s><s n="s2.6;p21.38">The dominant culture and economy (the Western or First World) arbitrarily imposed the way to development through technological innovation and an industrialized market economy. </s><s n="s3.6;p21.38">The means to impose these views are arbitrary as well. </s><s n="s4.6;p21.38">These two arbitraries constitute therefore a 'symbolic violence'. </s><s n="s5.6;p21.38">The legitimate state of 'developed' is supposed to be reached by following the same paths as the dominant. </s><s n="s6.6;p21.38">But it is in reality out of reach since the dominant constantly renew the definition of development (mass production and consumption in the 50-70s; tertiary and immaterial services and high-added value technologies today). </s></p><p n="p22.38"><s n="s1.4;p22.38">The brain drain expresses the reproduction of the 'catch-up' pattern from the South to the North. </s><s n="s2.4;p22.38">Indeed, the 'causes of brain drain are closely connected with educational planning and its adjustment to policy objectives in the area of technology'<ref target="BAWE_0409f-ftnote.019"/> in developing countries. </s><s n="s3.4;p22.38">The use of the highly educated population (what we can call the elite) from the South to the prejudice of the South and the benefit of the North, and the means of selection through education can be qualified as a symbolic violence. </s><s n="s4.4;p22.38">The South adapts its educational system and bears its costs, in order to respond to the demand from the North, but without being sure to benefit the investments made. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0409f-ftnote.019"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">W. Glaser, op. cit. p. xxix. </s></p></note></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head>III/ <hi rend="underlined">The responses of International Law </hi></head><p n="p23.38"><s n="s1.1;p23.38">This section focuses on the questions that can be asked to a 'reflexive' labour law and a global labour movement, for a less exploitive relationship between high-skilled workers from the South and the capitalist economies of the North, that would benefit in the first place the home countries of the South and their population, but also to the migrants themselves, and to the host countries (a win-win situation). </s></p><div2><head>3.1) <hi rend="underlined">Towards a 'reflexive' labour law?</hi> </head><p n="p24.38"><s n="s1.5;p24.38">These answers could lie in the elaboration of a new project of convention focusing on how to reduce the brain waste in the receiving country, how to reduce the brain drain in the sending country and how to balance the gains and losses through a brain circulation. </s><s n="s2.5;p24.38">On one hand, the convention could be bilateral, under the auspices of the ILO or the IMO. The advantage of this solution is that the specific problem of the brain drain between two countries (The U.S.A and India; Mali and France for instance) can be addressed through precise provisions that would apply only to the two countries involved. </s><s n="s3.5;p24.38">The provisions could for instance bind the receiving country to give a percentage of the benefits engendered by foreign high-skilled workers (H-1B visa- holders) to the home country. </s><s n="s4.5;p24.38">The disadvantage is that these legal innovations would not encompass global issues. </s><s n="s5.5;p24.38">On the other hand, a multilateral convention applying to all members of the ILO would not be specific enough to address the problems in an efficient way. </s></p><p n="p25.38"><s n="s1.1;p25.38">But isn't the debate biased from the beginning when we know that International Law is the product of Western countries to serve their interests in a context of conflict of interests translated in a legal 'regime-collisions'<ref target="BAWE_0409f-ftnote.020"/> (<hi rend="italic">lex mercatoria</hi> vs. a global labour law regime and human rights regime)? </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0409f-ftnote.020"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">F. Lescano, Teubner (2004) </s></p></note><p n="p26.38"><s n="s1.1;p26.38">Can we realistically expect law to play the role of "gentle civilizer of social systems"<ref target="BAWE_0409f-ftnote.021"/> in a context of fragmented global laws? </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0409f-ftnote.021"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">M. Koskenniemi (2002) cited in Lescano and Teubner (2004: 1045) </s></p></note><p n="p27.38"><s n="s1.1;p27.38">Contrary to Lescano and Teubner who see </s></p><quote lang="English">'a transformation from normative (politics, morality, law) to cognitive expectations (economy, science, technology); a transformation that would be effected during the transition from nationally organized societies to a global society'<ref target="BAWE_0409f-ftnote.022"/>,</quote><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0409f-ftnote.022"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid. p. 1000 </s></p></note><p n="p28.38"><s n="s1.2;p28.38">I see a need for the return of moral expectations in law for the implementation of a notion of fairness in the regulation of a 'global society'. </s><s n="s2.2;p28.38">Indeed, </s></p><quote lang="English">'if brain drain is seen as a result of integration into an international market in professional skills then the only way of achieving a substantial impact on the drain (and on the more serious internal distortions that it reflects) is disengagement from that market'<ref target="BAWE_0409f-ftnote.023"/></quote><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0409f-ftnote.023"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">W. Glaser, op. cit. p. xxii </s></p></note><p n="p29.38"><s n="s1.1;p29.38">Political power-driven interests are pursued by the states and MNCs or governmental firms (NASA), without reference to the common interest (would take into consideration the well-being of the sending country after the departure of its best elements) and can result on a policy conflict (incentives from the destination country for high-skilled workers to immigrate vs. incentives from the home country for them to stay or come back)<ref target="BAWE_0409f-ftnote.024"/>. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0409f-ftnote.024"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">This paragraph is inspired by Lescano &amp; Teubner, p. 1003 </s></p></note><p n="p30.38"><s n="s1.3;p30.38">According to Trubek and Compa, 'there is a way to construct a transnational labour regime to maintain labour standards and protect labour rights in a global economy'<ref target="BAWE_0409f-ftnote.025"/>. </s><s n="s2.3;p30.38">But their proposal does not take our problem into consideration. </s><s n="s3.3;p30.38">It includes: </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0409f-ftnote.025"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Trubek, Compa ( :2) </s></p></note><quote lang="English">'- Trade rules permitting individual countries to use trade sanctions to deter production under substandard working conditions as measured by international standard - Trade rules granting positive incentives to countries that excel at meeting international fair labour standards - Regional or global labour standards setting forth obligations and mechanisms to assess compliance - Programs to augment social protection schemes for people adversely affected by trade - New tools that could encourage a race to the top - Programs to strengthen domestic labour codes in countries with weak systems - Public-private codes of conduct providing for voluntary restraint'<ref target="BAWE_0409f-ftnote.026"/></quote><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0409f-ftnote.026"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid. p. 7 </s></p></note><p n="p31.38"><s n="s1.4;p31.38">Can international law regimes, independently from the state, provide an answer? </s><s n="s2.4;p31.38">Or do we have to expect it from the state? </s><s n="s3.4;p31.38">Should we combine or oppose the two? </s><s n="s4.4;p31.38">Globalized movements of people need regulating norms adapted to each category (low-, middle-, and high-skilled migrants) in function of the level of education, the loss their emigration represents, and the benefits they can provide to the country where they work. </s></p><p n="p32.38"><s n="s1.4;p32.38">But the law of ILO and IMO are only secondary norms of international law. </s><s n="s2.4;p32.38">It means that these norms depend on the primary legal act of creation of these organizations by the states. </s><s n="s3.4;p32.38">Can the ILO/IMO norms become 'self-contained', an 'auto-constitutional' regime which would produce its 'own procedural norms on law-making, law-recognition and legal sanctions', a 'reflexive norm-building' mechanism coupled with those of 'politics'<ref target="BAWE_0409f-ftnote.027"/>? </s><s n="s4.4;p32.38">If yes, would it be a mean to regulate the loss being endured by the South? </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0409f-ftnote.027"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Lescano, Teubner, op. cit. p. 1015 </s></p></note><p n="p33.38"><s n="s1.1;p33.38">The question is: which abuses/exploitations can be judged under which jurisdictional rules in which systems and under which treatment of the redistribution? </s></p><p n="p34.38"><s n="s1.1;p34.38">The brain drain 'should be considered in the elaboration of an international code of conduct for the transfer of technology'<ref target="BAWE_0409f-ftnote.028"/> and this procedure cannot implicate states in order to be fair. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0409f-ftnote.028"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">W. Glaser, op. cit. </s></p></note></div2><div2><head>3.2) <hi rend="underlined">Is a global labour movement possible?</hi> </head><p n="p35.38"><s n="s1.1;p35.38">As pointed out by Silver and Arrighi, there is a </s></p><quote lang="English">'decline of working-class consciousness and organization at a time of great numerical expansion of the world proletariat'<ref target="BAWE_0409f-ftnote.029"/></quote><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0409f-ftnote.029"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Silver, Arrighi (2001 : 1) </s></p></note><p n="p36.38"><s n="s1.3;p36.38">The labour force is no longer united as one entity. </s><s n="s2.3;p36.38">Even if the transnational labour force population (the migrants for work) is increasing, there is not one global labour force united around one principle of struggle, but a fragmented global labour force, divided along the education and skills level (low-, middle-, and high-skilled workers). </s><s n="s3.3;p36.38">How can law encompass this fragmented reality? </s></p><p n="p37.38"><s n="s1.5;p37.38">Is this movement possible among the high-skilled workers, who do not have the feeling to be exploited (except for the ones who are employed in jobs that do not correspond to their qualifications in a phenomenon of brain waste: they can ask for more information about the opportunities, a better enhancement of their formation abroad, less discrimination) because they receive high wages? </s><s n="s2.5;p37.38">The exploitation in this case is outside the worker himself and concerns the society that he left. </s><s n="s3.5;p37.38">Does he feel a duty towards his home country? </s><s n="s4.5;p37.38">Is a labour movement efficient if not massive? </s><s n="s5.5;p37.38">Is a conscious possible? </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined">Conclusion </head><p n="p38.38"><s n="s1.3;p38.38">This paper showed the ambiguity and the difficulty of the debates raised by the issue of the brain drain. </s><s n="s2.3;p38.38">The emigration of high-skilled workers is not a bad thing in itself. </s><s n="s3.3;p38.38">But, as other phenomena of the globalization (movements of goods, services and capital) it has to be regulated in a fair way. </s></p></div1></body><back/></text></TEI.2>
