<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_0410c" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>5. 'Corporate social responsibility sounds fine in theory, but is unworkable in practice.' Discuss.</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">The document has a title page which contains:
document title
title part</note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">deleted: page numbers</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">3</p><p n="date">unknown</p><p n="module title">Law of Business Organisations</p><p n="module code">LA310</p><p n="genre family">Essay</p><p n="discipline">Law</p><p n="disciplinary group">SS</p><p n="grade">unknown</p><p n="number of authors">unknown</p><p n="number of words">2012</p><p n="number of s-units">72</p><p n="number of p">25</p><p n="number of tables">0</p><p n="number of figures">0</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">0</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">0</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">27.9</p><p n="average s-units per p">2.9</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">m</p><p n="year of birth">1984</p><p n="first language">Chinese unspecified</p><p n="education">OSA</p><p n="course">Law</p><p n="student ID">0410</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><titlePart><hi rend="bold">UNIVERSITYOF</hi> <hi rend="bold"><name type="university"/> Law of Business Organisations</hi> <hi rend="bold"> LA 310 </hi></titlePart><docTitle><titlePart rend="bold">5. 'Corporate social responsibility sounds fine in theory, but is unworkable in practice.' Discuss. </titlePart></docTitle></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Introduction</head><p n="p1.25"><s n="s1.3;p1.25">Corporate social responsibility has become a widely held buzzword in the business community for good corporate practices. </s><s n="s2.3;p1.25">However, it has also been the focus of debate on its very nature and theoretical justification. </s><s n="s3.3;p1.25">One of these criticisms is that corporate social responsibility sounds fine in theory but is unworkable in practice. </s></p><p n="p2.25"><s n="s1.3;p2.25">This article investigates the validity of this claim first by briefly looking at the nature of corporate social responsibility. </s><s n="s2.3;p2.25">Then, we undergo an in-depth analysis of the issues related to its implementation from a practical perspective, thereby identifying the limits of the concept and the obstacles to its realization. </s><s n="s3.3;p2.25">We conclude with an assessment of the workability of corporate social responsibility and argue that the current situation is rather disappointing. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">The nature of corporate social responsibility</head><p n="p3.25"><s n="s1.2;p3.25">It is important to have a clear picture of corporate social responsibility in mind at the outset. </s><s n="s2.2;p3.25">Unfortunately, the first and most notable feature of corporate social responsibility is the variety of its definitions<ref target="BAWE_0410c-ftnote.001"/>. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0410c-ftnote.001"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">It has been described as "a tortured concept within the academic literature", see P. Godfrey &amp; N. Hatch, "Researching Corporate social responsibility: An Agenda for the 21st Century", Journal of Business Ethics (2007) 70:87-98, at 87. </s></p></note><p n="p4.25"><s n="s1.3;p4.25">There are at least 25 different conceptual definitions of corporate social responsibility within academic literature.<ref target="BAWE_0410c-ftnote.002"/> The European Commission defines corporate social responsibility as a concept whereby companies "decide voluntarily to contribute to a better society and a cleaner environment"<ref target="BAWE_0410c-ftnote.003"/>. </s><s n="s2.3;p4.25">An alternate description is that corporate social responsibility is concerned with "the relationship between companies and society and in particular, with constraining the adverse impact of corporate activity on individuals and communities as a whole"<ref target="BAWE_0410c-ftnote.004"/>. </s><s n="s3.3;p4.25">In other words, while corporate social responsibility is generally about charity and stewardship from companies, there is no real consensus regarding its definition. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0410c-ftnote.002"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">A. B. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">Carroll, "Corporate social responsibility: Evolution of a Definitional Construct", Business &amp; Ethics 38(3), 268-295. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0410c-ftnote.003"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Green Paper Promoting a European framework for Corporate social responsibility (18/07/2001), COM(2001) 366, available at <hi rend="underlined"><seg type="URL" n="http://ec.europa.eu/employment_social/soc-dial/corporate"/> social responsibility/greenpaper_en.pdf</hi> (last visited, April 21, 2007) </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0410c-ftnote.004"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">L. Whitehouse, "Corporate social responsibility, Corporate Citizenship and the Global Compact", [2003] 3 Global Social Policy, 299, at 300. </s></p></note><p n="p5.25"><s n="s1.3;p5.25">It is also important to bear in mind that the notion of corporate social responsibility is an evolving concept. </s><s n="s2.3;p5.25">The notion of corporate social responsibility evolved over the 20 <hi rend="sup">th</hi> century.<ref target="BAWE_0410c-ftnote.005"/> The original corporate social responsibility debates took place in the 1930s and were primarily concerned with the responsibilities owed by corporate managers and directors to their shareholders and other groups directly influenced by the corporation. </s><s n="s3.3;p5.25">Milton Friedman's famous critique emerged in the 1970s arguing that, on grounds based on economics and morality, there was no place for corporate social responsibility in businesses.<ref target="BAWE_0410c-ftnote.006"/> It was not until the 1990s did corporate social responsibility become the buzzword of many businesses and become a service providing industry of its own.<ref target="BAWE_0410c-ftnote.007"/> Hence, it is likely that this trend of evolution of corporate social responsibility as a concept will continue in the 21 <hi rend="sup">st</hi> century. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0410c-ftnote.005"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">For a history of corporate social responsibility, see A. B. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">Carroll, "Corporate social responsibility: Evolution of a Definitional Construct", Business &amp; Ethics 38(3), 268-295; see also J. Shestack, "Corporate social responsibility in a Changing Corporate World", in Mullerat (ed.), Corporate social responsibility: The Corporate Governance of the 21st Century, 2005 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0410c-ftnote.006"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">M. Friedman, "The Social Responsibility of Business is to Increase Its Profits", The New York Times Magazine, September 13, 1970, at 32. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0410c-ftnote.007"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">See "What's Wrong with corporate social responsibility?", Corporate Watch Report 2006, available at <seg type="URL" n="http://www.corporatewatch.org.uk/?lid=2670"/> (last visited, April 21, 2007). </s></p></note><p n="p6.25"><s n="s1.3;p6.25">Nevertheless, one has to conceptualize corporate social responsibility as a philosophy for purposes of discussion. </s><s n="s2.3;p6.25">Corporate social responsibility is a collective name for many different activities that span a variety of disciplines and professional fields.<ref target="BAWE_0410c-ftnote.008"/> It is an aggregation of socially responsible behaviours of companies that address social and environmental concerns. </s><s n="s3.3;p6.25">The one agreed characteristic about corporate social responsibility is that it is voluntary.<ref target="BAWE_0410c-ftnote.009"/> As will be seen in the analysis below, this has important ramifications in the implementation of corporate social responsibility. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0410c-ftnote.008"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">See P. Godfrey &amp; N. Hatch, "Researching Corporate social responsibility: An Agenda for the 21st Century", Journal of Business Ethics (2007) 70:87-98. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0410c-ftnote.009"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">J. Shestack, "Corporate social responsibility in a Changing Corporate World", in Mullerat (ed.), Corporate social responsibility: The Corporate Governance of the 21st Century, 2005 </s></p></note><p n="p7.25"><s n="s1.2;p7.25">Corporate social responsibility is also associated with ideas such as corporate philanthropy, corporate citizenship, sustainable development and stakeholder accountability.<ref target="BAWE_0410c-ftnote.010"/> Interests concerned with corporate social responsibility may range from shareholder's interests to employee's interests to local communities to environmental concerns.<ref target="BAWE_0410c-ftnote.011"/> In sum, corporate social responsibility is a "fuzzy" concept generally related to "socially good" behaviour of businesses. </s><s n="s2.2;p7.25">As will be seen in the following section, these facets of corporate social responsibility is directly related to the assessment of how practical is corporate social responsibility. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0410c-ftnote.010"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">See for example, A. Rasche &amp; D. Esser, "From Stakeholder Management to Stakeholder Accountability", Journal of Business Ethics (2006) 65:251-267; L. Whitehouse, "Corporate social responsibility, Corporate Citizenship and the Global Compact: A New Approach to Regulating Corporate Social Power?", Global Social Policy, Vol3(3):299-318. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0410c-ftnote.011"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">See J. Shestack, "Corporate social responsibility in a Changing Corporate World", in Mullerat (ed.), Corporate social responsibility: The Corporate Governance of the 21st Century, 2005; N. Barry, "The Stakeholder Concept of Corporate Control is Illogical and Impractical", Independent Review, Spring 2002, Vol.6(4), 541; J. Fitchett, "Consumers as stakeholders: prospects for democracy in marketing theory", Business Ethics: A European Review, Vol.14(1), January 2005, 14. </s></p></note></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Criticisms of corporate social responsibility</head><p n="p8.25"><s n="s1.2;p8.25">As mentioned above, corporate social responsibility is not without its detractors. </s><s n="s2.2;p8.25">Many arguments have already been put forwarded by critics, including Friedman's influential essay on economics and morality.<ref target="BAWE_0410c-ftnote.012"/> In response to these critiques, corporate social responsibility has gradually evolved into various theories such as stakeholder theory and corporate citizenship.<ref target="BAWE_0410c-ftnote.013"/> In general, the competing themes central to the corporate social responsibility debate are economics (which focuses on corporations) and moral philosophy (which focuses on social responsibilities).<ref target="BAWE_0410c-ftnote.014"/> Nonetheless, corporate social responsibility has continued to gain importance in managerial practice.<ref target="BAWE_0410c-ftnote.015"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0410c-ftnote.012"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">See also, R. Wilcke, "An Appropriate Ethical Model for Business and a Critique of Milton Friedman's Thesis", The Independent Review, v.IX, n.2, Fall 2004, 187-209. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0410c-ftnote.013"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">A. B. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">Carroll, "Corporate social responsibility: Evolution of a Definitional Construct", Business &amp; Ethics 38(3), 268-295 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0410c-ftnote.014"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">For an illustrative array of corporate social responsibility theories and models, see P. Godfrey &amp; N. Hatch, "Researching Corporate social responsibility: An Agenda for the 21st Century", Journal of Business Ethics (2007) 70:87-98. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0410c-ftnote.015"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">P. Godfrey &amp; N. Hatch, "Researching Corporate social responsibility: An Agenda for the 21st Century", Journal of Business Ethics (2007) 70:87-98, at 87. </s></p></note><p n="p9.25"><s n="s1.5;p9.25">However, the greater, and perhaps more pragmatic, challenge of corporate social responsibility is concerned with its implementation. </s><s n="s2.5;p9.25">Corporate social responsibility sounds nice and dandy, but is it workable in practice? </s><s n="s3.5;p9.25">This boils down to the focus of this essay and the section that follows provides an in-depth analysis of the issues concerned with its implementation. </s><s n="s4.5;p9.25">The issues analyzed below relates to reasons for businesses to adopt corporate social responsibility, the issues related to the mechanics of implementation, the standards of corporate social responsibility, its assessment and its enforcement. </s><s n="s5.5;p9.25">As will be seen, there are significant obstacles towards the implementation of corporate social responsibility. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined">Incentives for corporate social responsibility</head><p n="p10.25"><s n="s1.3;p10.25">The first question is related to the fact that corporate social responsibility is voluntary. </s><s n="s2.3;p10.25">If corporate social responsibility is to be purely voluntary, the obvious concern is why would businesses adopt it? </s><s n="s3.3;p10.25">On the face of it, corporate social responsibility seems to run contrary to the fundamental premise on which businesses operate: profit generation.<ref target="BAWE_0410c-ftnote.016"/> After all, directors are legally bound to act solely for the best interest for the company's shareholders. <ref target="BAWE_0410c-ftnote.017"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0410c-ftnote.016"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">This is better articulated in Milton Friedman, "The Social Responsibility of Business is to Increase Its Profits", The New York Times Magazine, September 13, 1970, at 32. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0410c-ftnote.017"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">"What's Wrong with corporate social responsibility?", Corporate Watch Report 2006, available at <seg type="URL" n="http://www.corporatewatch.org.uk/?lid=2670"/> (last visited, April 21, 2007) </s></p></note><p n="p11.25"><s n="s1.1;p11.25">A number of reasons have been put forward to establish the "business case" for corporate social responsibility.<ref target="BAWE_0410c-ftnote.018"/> A primary argument relied on is that "morality pays".<ref target="BAWE_0410c-ftnote.019"/> This asserts that businesses adopting corporate social responsibility will increase their profit margins by receiving intangible benefits, such as stakeholder commitment, which leads to stakeholder commitment, ultimately leading to corporate success. <ref target="BAWE_0410c-ftnote.020"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0410c-ftnote.018"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">This includes the concept of corporate citizenship, see L. Whitehouse, "Corporate social responsibility, Corporate Citizenship and the Global Compact", [2003] 3 Global Social Policy, 299. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0410c-ftnote.019"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">See J. Corvino, "Reframing "Morality Pays": Toward a Better Answer to "Why be Moral?" in Business", Journal of Business Ethics (2006) 67:1-14. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0410c-ftnote.020"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.3;pn1.1">For a discussion on the reasons for businesses to adopt corporate social responsibility, see J. Corvino, "Reframing "Morality Pays": Toward a Better Answer to "Why be Moral?" in Business", Journal of Business Ethics (2006) 67:1-14; see also L. T. </s><s n="s2.3;pn1.1">Hosmer, "Why be Moral? </s><s n="s3.3;pn1.1">A Different Rationale for Managers", Business Ethics Quarterly vol.4 (1994), 191-204. </s></p></note><p n="p12.25"><s n="s1.1;p12.25">However, moral behaviour is neither sufficient nor necessary for corporate success.<ref target="BAWE_0410c-ftnote.021"/> Moreover, it has been pointed out that most discussion concerning social and financial performance has been misleading to assume that an unequivocal link between these two ends exists.<ref target="BAWE_0410c-ftnote.022"/> Without a firm understanding between corporate social responsibility and its economic consequences, there is no firm case for businesses to run corporate social responsibility programmes and the businesses that are already running corporate social responsibility programmes are relying on mere speculation.<ref target="BAWE_0410c-ftnote.023"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0410c-ftnote.021"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">J. Corvino, "Reframing "Morality Pays": Toward a Better Answer to "Why be Moral?" in Business", Journal of Business Ethics (2006) 67:1-14, at 2. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0410c-ftnote.022"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">P. Godfrey &amp; N. Hatch, "Researching Corporate social responsibility: An Agenda for the 21st Century", Journal of Business Ethics (2007) 70:87-98, at 93. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0410c-ftnote.023"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Most literature only suggests a reputation for social responsibility correlates to the success of businesses, see, K. Schnietz &amp; M. Epstein, "Exploring the Financial Value of a Reputation for Corporate social responsibility During a Crisis", Corporate Reputation Review, Vol.7, No.4, 2005, 327-345. </s></p></note><p n="p13.25"><s n="s1.2;p13.25">In other words, there is no firm incentive for businesses to adopt corporate social responsibility at all. </s><s n="s2.2;p13.25">Hence, it is doubtful whether corporate social responsibility programmes would be taken seriously. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined">Implementing corporate social responsibility</head><p n="p14.25"><s n="s1.5;p14.25">The second issue concerns engagement of corporate social responsibility. </s><s n="s2.5;p14.25">How are businesses going to adopt it? </s><s n="s3.5;p14.25">Which corporate social responsibility activities should businesses engage in? </s><s n="s4.5;p14.25">How should managers and executives balance the strategic logic of social involvement with other, more tangible strategic investment projects? </s><s n="s5.5;p14.25">These are practical considerations that deserve further scrutiny. </s></p><p n="p15.25"><s n="s1.2;p15.25">We can start by looking at the mechanics of implementing corporate social responsibility. </s><s n="s2.2;p15.25">Basic instruments of corporate social responsibility may include values statements, codes of conducts or ethics, social reporting, auditing and certification.<ref target="BAWE_0410c-ftnote.024"/> While there is no real consensus as to how corporate social responsibility is to be achieved, there has been a proliferation of corporate social responsibility agencies that promises to help businesses incorporate corporate social responsibility policies into their company.<ref target="BAWE_0410c-ftnote.025"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0410c-ftnote.024"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">G. Piskalski, "Can corporate social responsibility work out in Poland and other EU new Member States?" </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">German RKW, available at <hi rend="underlined"><seg type="URL" n="http://www.rkw.de/en/01_forschung/AktuellesThema/0MAG107_Originale/Polen_corporate"/> social responsibility/index.html</hi> (last visited, April 21, 2007). </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0410c-ftnote.025"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">See corporate social responsibility consultancy agencies such as SustainAbility. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1"><seg type="URL" n="http://www.sustainability.com/"/> </s></p></note><p n="p16.25"><s n="s1.1;p16.25">One methodology available is Grayson &amp; Hodges' seven-step model, which includes: identifying triggers, scoping what matters, making the business case, committing to action, integrating and gathering resources, engaging stakeholders, and measuring and reporting.<ref target="BAWE_0410c-ftnote.026"/> These are described as "diagnostic planning tools... [to] provide a practical guide to help business leaders and understand how to assess the impact of corporate social responsibility on their core business strategy and operations and help them identify and prioritise between subsequent options and resulting business opportunities".<ref target="BAWE_0410c-ftnote.027"/> Hence, as a methodology, it does seem that corporate social responsibility is as workable as any quality management programme. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0410c-ftnote.026"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">D. Grayson &amp; A. Hodges, <hi rend="italic">Corporate Social Opportunity!:</hi> <hi rend="italic">Seven Steps to Make Corporate social responsibility Work for your Business</hi>, Greenleaf Publishing (July 2004). </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0410c-ftnote.027"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1"><seg type="URL" n="http://www.greenleaf-publishing.com/productdetail.kmod?productid=63"/> (last visited, April 21, 2007) </s></p></note><p n="p17.25"><s n="s1.1;p17.25">However, a widely held observation of the extent of corporate social responsibility adopted by businesses today is superficial rather than substantial.<ref target="BAWE_0410c-ftnote.028"/> Their corporate social responsibility programmes focus more on elaborate PR schemes rather than substantive issues of corporate social responsibility.<ref target="BAWE_0410c-ftnote.029"/> Moreover, the ideational neutrality of adopted standards and effectiveness of businesses adopting codes of conduct are questionable.<ref target="BAWE_0410c-ftnote.030"/> This hypocrisy has lead to accusations of "corporate sidelining reality" that corporations are exploiting the confusion of corporate social responsibility to their advantage and delaying calls for regulation.<ref target="BAWE_0410c-ftnote.031"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0410c-ftnote.028"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">J. Shestack, "Corporate social responsibility in a Changing Corporate World", in Mullerat (ed.), Corporate social responsibility: The Corporate Governance of the 21st Century, 2005, at 108. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0410c-ftnote.029"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">J. Shestack, "Corporate social responsibility in a Changing Corporate World", in Mullerat (ed.), Corporate social responsibility: The Corporate Governance of the 21st Century, 2005 at 108. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0410c-ftnote.030"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">M. Blowfield, "Corporate social responsibility - The Failing Discipline and Why it Matters for International Relations", International Relations, Vol.19(2):173-191, at 178; see also J. Yimprasert, "More than ten years on, more pressure is needed" in Asia Monitor Resource Centre, <hi rend="italic">A Critical Guide to Corporate Codes of Conduct: Voices from the South</hi>, AMRC, 2004, P93, as cited in "What's Wrong with corporate social responsibility?", Corporate Watch Report 2006, available at <seg type="URL" n="http://www.corporatewatch.org.uk/?lid=2670"/> (last visited, April 21, 2007). </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0410c-ftnote.031"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">This has become a slogan for Corporate Watch's report on corporate social responsibility, see "What's Wrong with corporate social responsibility?", Corporate Watch Report 2006, available at <seg type="URL" n="http://www.corporatewatch.org.uk/?lid=2670"/> (last visited, April 21, 2007). </s></p></note><p n="p18.25"><s n="s1.4;p18.25">Another issue related to practical implementation of corporate social responsibility is the lack of corporate social responsibility related management tools. </s><s n="s2.4;p18.25">Businesses utilize financial management tools to make decisions in allocating their resources, such as cash, time and personnel.<ref target="BAWE_0410c-ftnote.032"/> However, the same tools are rendered obsolete in assessing intangible concepts such as stakeholder interests. </s><s n="s3.4;p18.25">Without better analytic tools to formulate corporate social responsibility decisions, managers could only resort to their personal common sense in making decisions. </s><s n="s4.4;p18.25">The lack of general principles will be highlighted when managers are faced with competing stakeholder interests.<ref target="BAWE_0410c-ftnote.033"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0410c-ftnote.032"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">P. Godfrey &amp; N. Hatch, "Researching Corporate social responsibility: An Agenda for the 21st Century", Journal of Business Ethics (2007) 70:87-98, at 94. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0410c-ftnote.033"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1"><hi rend="italic">Ibid</hi>, at 94. </s></p></note><p n="p19.25"><s n="s1.3;p19.25">The voluntariness of corporate social responsibility entails a further issue concerning the extent of corporate social responsibility to be adopted by businesses. </s><s n="s2.3;p19.25">Given the confusion and lack of consensus regarding corporate social responsibility, one must doubt whether there is an accepted standard of responsibilities.<ref target="BAWE_0410c-ftnote.034"/> A number of conceptual issues may be posited. </s><s n="s3.3;p19.25">A general example may concern whether managers can substitute involvement in some corporate social responsibilities for lack of involvement in others.<ref target="BAWE_0410c-ftnote.035"/> Another question may relate to universality and cultural defences: what does corporate social responsibility mean in a non-Western, non-democratic capitalist institutional framework?<ref target="BAWE_0410c-ftnote.036"/> Although a number of "global" corporate social responsibility instruments have been drafted, these codes are not without objection and their effectiveness are yet to be seen.<ref target="BAWE_0410c-ftnote.037"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0410c-ftnote.034"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">See J. Moon, "Corporate social responsibility: An Overview", in <hi rend="italic">International Directory of Corporate Philanthropy</hi> (London: Europa Publications, 2002), p.1, as cited in M. Blowfield, "Corporate social responsibility - The Failing Discipline and Why it Matters for International Relations", International Relations, Vol.19(2):173-191. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0410c-ftnote.035"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">P. Godfrey &amp; N. Hatch, "Researching Corporate social responsibility: An Agenda for the 21st Century", Journal of Business Ethics (2007) 70:87-98, at 95. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0410c-ftnote.036"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1"><hi rend="italic">Ibid</hi>, at 95. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0410c-ftnote.037"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Examples include the OECD Guidelines for Multinational Enterprises (MNEs), the Global Compact (GC), the International Organization for Standardization (ISO) ISO 26000 Social Responsibility Guidance Standard, and the GRI Sustainability Reporting Guidelines. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">For an account of the Canadian experience in adopting these instruments, see P. Hohnen, "Social Responsibility Instruments: Building the Global Architecture for the 21st Century - Issues and Opportunities for the Emerging Social Responsibility Instruments Landscape", Industry Canada, available at <hi rend="underlined"><seg type="URL" n="http://strategis.ic.gc.ca/epic/site/corporate"/> social responsibility-rse.nsf/en/rs00147e.html</hi> (last visited, April 21, 2007); see also J. Shestack, "Corporate social responsibility in a Changing Corporate World", in Mullerat (ed.), Corporate social responsibility: The Corporate Governance of the 21st Century, 2005, at 107. </s></p></note></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined">Accountability of corporate social responsibility</head><p n="p20.25"><s n="s1.4;p20.25">The logical continuum is the assessment of corporate social responsibility. </s><s n="s2.4;p20.25">If corporate social responsibility is voluntary, businesses are to set up standards for themselves. </s><s n="s3.4;p20.25">Thus corporate social responsibility is effectively a self-regulating regime. </s><s n="s4.4;p20.25">The accountability of such arrangement is undoubtedly put into question. </s></p><p n="p21.25"><s n="s1.2;p21.25">While there is debate about the criteria against which corporate social and environmental performance should be assessed, there is little discussion about the underlying ideational and epistemological premise that acceptable behaviour can be itemised, measured and accounted for.<ref target="BAWE_0410c-ftnote.038"/> Although there are a number of groups supply corporate social responsibility ratings to investors and consumers, the validity and reliability of these ratings may be questionable. </s><ref target="BAWE_0410c-ftnote.039"/><s n="s2.2;p21.25">Thus, there is real difficulty in quantifying business corporate social responsibility performance and public expectations. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0410c-ftnote.038"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">M. Blowfield, "Corporate social responsibility - The Failing Discipline and Why it Matters for International Relations", International Relations, Vol.19(2):173-191, at 175. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0410c-ftnote.039"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">A. Marquez &amp; C. Fombrun, "Measuring Corporate social responsibility", Corporate Reputation Review, Vol7, No.4, 304. </s></p></note><p n="p22.25"><s n="s1.4;p22.25">The last issue that entails voluntariness is the lack of enforcement. </s><s n="s2.4;p22.25">Enforcement is not within the concept of corporate social responsibility. </s><s n="s3.4;p22.25">Since corporate social responsibility is a self-regulating regime, the only enforcement mechanism available is from the market itself. </s><s n="s4.4;p22.25">However, the only apparent enforcement against large corporations seems to be the harassment from NGOs and ratings agencies.<ref target="BAWE_0410c-ftnote.040"/> This adds considerable weight to the criticism of accountability of corporate social responsibility. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0410c-ftnote.040"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1"><hi rend="italic">Ibid</hi>. </s></p></note></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Conclusion</head><p n="p23.25"><s n="s1.6;p23.25">As can be seen, there are a number of obstacles that are in the way to implementing corporate social responsibility. </s><s n="s2.6;p23.25">To sum up our analysis, businesses have little reason to adopt corporate social responsibility programmes at all. </s><s n="s3.6;p23.25">The effectiveness of current implementation methods are yet to be seen. </s><s n="s4.6;p23.25">The know-how of implementing corporate social responsibility is arguably insufficient to effectuate corporate social responsibility in businesses. </s><s n="s5.6;p23.25">Without a consensus in the standards of corporate social responsibility and effective enforcement mechanism, the accountability of corporate social responsibility as a self-regulatory regime falls into question. </s><s n="s6.6;p23.25">Hence, the very features that define corporate social responsibility are also the same that undermines it. </s></p><p n="p24.25"><s n="s1.3;p24.25">Although corporate social responsibility undoubtedly has a normative appeal, the voluntariness of corporate social responsibility has led to serious accountability issues and the hypocrisy in its current implementation. </s><s n="s2.3;p24.25">In light of the above analysis, accusations that corporate social responsibility is unworkable are understandable from a practical perspective. </s><s n="s3.3;p24.25">When compounded with other criticisms of corporate social responsibility<ref target="BAWE_0410c-ftnote.041"/>, the future of corporate social responsibility seems to be cast in a shadow of doubt. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0410c-ftnote.041"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">See, for example, B. Banerjee, "The Problem with Corporate social responsibility", Working Paper Series of the International Graduate School of Business, University of South Australia, available at <seg type="URL" n="http://www.unisa.edu.au/igsb/docs/WP-Banerjee.pdf"/> (last visited April 21, 2007); M. Hopkins, "Criticism of the Corporate social responsibility Movement" in Mullerat (ed.), Corporate social responsibility: The Corporate Governance of the 21st Century, 2005, at 473. </s></p></note><p n="p25.25"><s n="s1.4;p25.25">Looking on the bright side, there may be a future for corporate social responsibility. </s><s n="s2.4;p25.25">The European Commission has aspirations for corporate social responsibility to contribute to making Europe "the most competitive and dynamic knowledge-based economy in the world, capable of sustainable economic growth with more and better jobs and greater social cohesion"<ref target="BAWE_0410c-ftnote.042"/>. </s><s n="s3.4;p25.25">The UK government now has an "ambitious vision" to see corporate social responsibility take root in British businesses and has set out its own approach to corporate social responsibility values.<ref target="BAWE_0410c-ftnote.043"/> These may be seen as pragmatic attempts to implementing corporate social responsibility. </s><s n="s4.4;p25.25">Perhaps in the future, corporate social responsibility may be more workable in practice. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0410c-ftnote.042"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">See the European Commission's "Communication on Corporate social responsibility - A business contribution to Sustainable Development", available at <hi rend="underlined"><seg type="URL" n="http://europa.eu.int/comm/employment_social/soc-dial/corporate"/> social responsibility/corporate social responsibility2002_en.pdf</hi> (last visited, April 21, 2007) </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0410c-ftnote.043"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">See <hi rend="underlined"><seg type="URL" n="http://www.corporate"/> social responsibility.gov.uk/</hi> (last visited, April 21, 2007) </s></p></note></div1></body><back><div1 type="bibliography"><head rend="bold">Bibliography</head><p>P. Godfrey &amp; N. Hatch, "Researching Corporate social responsibility: An Agenda for the 21<hi rend="sup">st</hi> Century", Journal of Business Ethics (2007) 70:87-98</p><p>A. B. Carroll, "Corporate social responsibility: Evolution of a Definitional Construct", Business &amp; Ethics 38(3), 268-295</p><p>L. Whitehouse, "Corporate social responsibility, Corporate Citizenship and the Global Compact", [2003] 3 Global Social Policy, 299</p><p>J. Shestack, "Corporate social responsibility in a Changing Corporate World", in Mullerat (ed.), Corporate social responsibility: The Corporate Governance of the 21<hi rend="sup">st</hi> Century, 2005</p><p>M. Friedman, "The Social Responsibility of Business is to Increase Its Profits", The New York Times Magazine, September 13, 1970, at 32</p><p>A. Rasche &amp; D. Esser, "From Stakeholder Management to Stakeholder Accountability", Journal of Business Ethics (2006) 65:251-267</p><p>N. Barry, "The Stakeholder Concept of Corporate Control is Illogical and Impractical", Independent Review, Spring 2002, Vol.6(4), 541</p><p>J. Fitchett, "Consumers as stakeholders: prospects for democracy in marketing theory", Business Ethics: A European Review, Vol.14(1), January 2005, 14</p><p>R. Wilcke, "An Appropriate Ethical Model for Business and a Critique of Milton Friedman's Thesis", The Independent Review, v.IX, n.2, Fall 2004, 187-209</p><p>J. Corvino, "Reframing "Morality Pays": Toward a Better Answer to "Why be Moral?" in Business", Journal of Business Ethics (2006) 67:1-14</p><p>L. T. Hosmer, "Why be Moral? A Different Rationale for Managers", Business Ethics Quarterly vol.4 (1994), 191-204</p><p>K. Schnietz &amp; M. Epstein, "Exploring the Financial Value of a Reputation for Corporate social responsibility During a Crisis", Corporate Reputation Review, Vol.7, No.4, 2005, 327-345</p><p>D. Grayson &amp; A. Hodges, <hi rend="italic">Corporate Social Opportunity!: Seven Steps to Make Corporate social responsibility Work for your Business</hi>, Greenleaf Publishing (July 2004)</p><p>M. Blowfield, "Corporate social responsibility - The Failing Discipline and Why it Matters for International Relations", International Relations, Vol.19(2):173-191, at 178</p><p>J. Yimprasert, "More than ten years on, more pressure is needed" in Asia Monitor Resource Centre, <hi rend="italic">A Critical Guide to Corporate Codes of Conduct: Voices from the South</hi>, AMRC, 2004, P93</p><p>J. Moon, "Corporate social responsibility: An Overview", in <hi rend="italic">International Directory of Corporate Philanthropy</hi> (London: Europa Publications, 2002)</p><p>A. Marquez &amp; C. Fombrun, "Measuring Corporate social responsibility", Corporate Reputation Review, Vol7, No.4, 304</p><p>M. Hopkins, "Criticism of the Corporate social responsibility Movement" in Mullerat (ed.), Corporate social responsibility: The Corporate Governance of the 21<hi rend="sup">st</hi> Century, 2005, at 473</p><p>Green Paper Promoting a European framework for Corporate social responsibility (18/07/2001), COM(2001) 366, available at <seg type="URL" n="http://ec.europa.eu/employment_social/soc-dial/corporate"/> social responsibility/greenpaper_en.pdf (last visited, April 21, 2007)</p><p>"What's Wrong with corporate social responsibility?", Corporate Watch Report 2006, available at <seg type="URL" n="http://www.corporatewatch.org.uk/?lid=2670"/> (last visited, April 21, 2007)</p><p>G. Piskalski, "Can corporate social responsibility work out in Poland and other EU new Member States?" German RKW, available at <seg type="URL" n="http://www.rkw.de/en/01_forschung/AktuellesThema/0MAG107_Originale/Polen_corporate"/> social responsibility/index.html (last visited, April 21, 2007)</p><p><seg type="URL" n="http://www.greenleaf-publishing.com/productdetail.kmod?productid=63"/> (last visited, April 21, 2007)</p><p>P. Hohnen, "Social Responsibility Instruments: Building the Global Architecture for the 21st Century - Issues and Opportunities for the Emerging Social Responsibility Instruments Landscape", Industry Canada, available at <seg type="URL" n="http://strategis.ic.gc.ca/epic/site/corporate"/> social responsibility-rse.nsf/en/rs00147e.html (last visited, April 21, 2007)</p><p>B. Banerjee, "The Problem with Corporate social responsibility", Working Paper Series of the International Graduate School of Business, University of South Australia, available at <seg type="URL" n="http://www.unisa.edu.au/igsb/docs/WP-Banerjee.pdf"/> (last visited April 21, 2007)</p><p>European Commission's "Communication on Corporate social responsibility - A business contribution to Sustainable Development", available at <seg type="URL" n="http://europa.eu.int/comm/employment_social/soc-dial/corporate"/> social responsibility/corporate social responsibility2002_en.pdf (last visited, April 21, 2007)</p></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
