<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_0410d" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>4. Whereas the English abortion debate has been dominated by the question of whether or not abortion should ever be justified in law, the more difficult moral questions arise in distinguishing circumstances in which abortion should not be permitted from those in which it should. Discuss.</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">The document has a title page which contains:
document title
title part</note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">deleted: page numbers</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">3</p><p n="date">unknown</p><p n="module title">Medicine and the Law</p><p n="module code">LA333</p><p n="genre family">Essay</p><p n="discipline">Law</p><p n="disciplinary group">SS</p><p n="grade">unknown</p><p n="number of authors">unknown</p><p n="number of words">2495</p><p n="number of s-units">86</p><p n="number of p">44</p><p n="number of tables">0</p><p n="number of figures">0</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">0</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">0</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">29.0</p><p n="average s-units per p">2.0</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">m</p><p n="year of birth">1984</p><p n="first language">Chinese unspecified</p><p n="education">OSA</p><p n="course">Law</p><p n="student ID">0410</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><titlePart><hi rend="bold">UNIVERSITYOF <name type="university"/> Medicine and the Law</hi> <hi rend="bold"> LA333 Assessed Essay</hi></titlePart><docTitle><titlePart> 4. Whereas the English abortion debate has been dominated by the question of whether or not abortion should ever be justified in law, the more difficult moral questions arise in distinguishing circumstances in which abortion should not be permitted from those in which it should. Discuss.</titlePart></docTitle></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Introduction</head><p n="p1.44"><s n="s1.3;p1.44">Contemporary English abortion debate has been a tug-of-war between the pro-life camp and the pro-choice camp. </s><s n="s2.3;p1.44">For decades neither side of the debate has been able to declare a conclusive victory. </s><s n="s3.3;p1.44">Central to the debate are two questions: whether or not abortion should ever be justified in law ('the First Question'); and if answered in the positive, in what circumstances should abortion be permitted ('the Second Question'). </s></p><p n="p2.44"><s n="s1.3;p2.44">Despite the on-going controversy, the English legal position has moved forward by the enactment of the Abortion Act 1967 and the Human Fertilisation and Embryology Act 1990. </s><s n="s2.3;p2.44">In general, the law allows abortion in specific circumstances, thus answering the First Question in the positive, while pragmatically addressing the Second Question by setting out certain statutory grounds. </s><s n="s3.3;p2.44">However, a closer examination of the English abortion law in the context of foetal disability reveals that the current law is fails to distinguish those circumstances satisfactorily. </s></p><p n="p3.44"><s n="s1.1;p3.44">By drawing the American legal position as a complementary approach, it is contended that a rights-based approach would give a better result in the balancing exercise than the current approach adopted in the UK. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">The English abortion debate</head><p n="p4.44"><s n="s1.3;p4.44">Abortion, in general, raises complex moral, ethical and legal issues. </s><s n="s2.3;p4.44">The English debate has been dominated by the question of whether or not abortion should ever be justified in law. </s><s n="s3.3;p4.44">Traditionally, the issue is split amongst the pro-life camp and the pro-choice camp. </s></p><p n="p5.44"><s n="s1.3;p5.44">The pro-life camp tends to emphasize a right to life of the foetus and would claim that abortion should never be justified in law. </s><s n="s2.3;p5.44">The pro-lifer argument is that the foetus is a person and terminating pregnancy before its birth is equivalent to murder. </s><s n="s3.3;p5.44">Thus, abortion is morally wrong and should not be justified in law. </s></p><p n="p6.44"><s n="s1.3;p6.44">The pro-choice camp tends to stress a woman's right to choose and would claim that abortion should never be justified in law. </s><s n="s2.3;p6.44">Arguments drawn from a woman's right to autonomy, right to privacy and right to equality has been raised as support, such as the influential 'violinist argument' by Judith Jarvis Thomson<ref target="BAWE_0410d-ftnote.001"/>, which is an argument based on the right to autonomy. </s><s n="s3.3;p6.44">In general, pro-choice advocates contend that the rights of the foetus are trumped by the woman's rights, thus allowing abortion. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0410d-ftnote.001"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">J. Thomson, 'A Defense of Abortion', (1971) <hi rend="italic">Philosophy and Public Affairs</hi>, 1, 47-66. </s></p></note><p n="p7.44"><s n="s1.3;p7.44">However, neither side has come up with a conclusive set of arguments to convince the other. </s><s n="s2.3;p7.44">On one hand, the pro-life camp has been plagued by questions such as when life begins and English law is clear that the foetus has no legal status until it is born.<ref target="BAWE_0410d-ftnote.002"/> On the other, the pro-choice camp has disputed over which right is best to emphasize<ref target="BAWE_0410d-ftnote.003"/> and shows a lack of theoretical consensus. </s><s n="s3.3;p7.44">While it would be futile to pursue the extent of the debate to the whole here, it is safe to conclude that the debate has never really ended. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0410d-ftnote.002"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">See Lord Mustill's judgment in <hi rend="italic">A-G's Reference (No 3 of 1994)</hi> [1997] 3 All ER 936 at 948. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0410d-ftnote.003"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">J. Herring, <hi rend="italic">Medical Law and Ethics</hi> (OUP 2006) at 264. </s></p></note></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">The English legal position</head><p n="p8.44"><s n="s1.2;p8.44">The on-going debate has not impeded the development of English law on abortion. </s><s n="s2.2;p8.44">While abortion remains a criminal offence<ref target="BAWE_0410d-ftnote.004"/>, the law was liberalized through the enactment of the Abortion Act 1967, which was subsequently amended by the Human Fertilisation and Embryology Act 1990<ref target="BAWE_0410d-ftnote.005"/>. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0410d-ftnote.004"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Offences Against the Person Act 1861 ss.58 &amp; 59 and Infant Life (Preservation) Act 1929 s.1; There was also the common law defence of necessity for a doctor facing a criminal charge of procuring a miscarriage, see <hi rend="italic">R v Bourne</hi> [1939] 1 KB 687. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0410d-ftnote.005"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Human Fertilisation and Embryology Act 1990 s.37 amends time limits of viability from 28 weeks to 24 to reflect improving medical technology. </s></p></note><p n="p9.44"><s n="s1.2;p9.44">In general, the Abortion Act 1967 allows a woman to have an abortion if it is performed by a registered medical practitioner and two doctors are satisfied that one of the stipulated statutory grounds is met<ref target="BAWE_0410d-ftnote.006"/>. </s><s n="s2.2;p9.44">The statutory grounds are: (a) to avoid 'injury to the physical or mental health of the pregnant woman or any existing children of her family<ref target="BAWE_0410d-ftnote.007"/>; (b) to 'prevent grave permanent injury to the physical or mental health of the pregnant woman'<ref target="BAWE_0410d-ftnote.008"/>; (c) to save the life of the pregnant woman<ref target="BAWE_0410d-ftnote.009"/>; and (d) where there is a substantial risk that if the child were born it would be 'seriously handicapped'<ref target="BAWE_0410d-ftnote.010"/>. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0410d-ftnote.006"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Abortion Act 1967 s.1. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0410d-ftnote.007"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Abortion Act 1967 s.1(a). </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0410d-ftnote.008"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Abortion Act 1967 s.1(b). </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0410d-ftnote.009"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Abortion Act 1967 s.1(c). </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0410d-ftnote.010"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Abortion Act 1967 s.1(d). </s></p></note><p n="p10.44"><s n="s1.2;p10.44">The law recognizes some interests of the foetus<ref target="BAWE_0410d-ftnote.011"/>, as advocated by the pro-life groups, partly by retaining the crime of abortion; by allowing abortion in certain circumstances, Parliament accepts the position advocated by the pro-choice groups. </s><s n="s2.2;p10.44">Abortion is allowed in specific circumstances, thus answering the First Question in the positive, while the Second Question is pragmatically addressed by setting out each statutory ground for abortion. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0410d-ftnote.011"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">See Judge LJ in <hi rend="italic">St George's NHS Trust v S</hi> (1998) 44 BMLR 160. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">See also <hi rend="italic">R v Gibson</hi> [1990] 2 QB 619. </s></p></note><p n="p11.44"><s n="s1.1;p11.44">Hence, the English legal position has moved forward despite the on-going controversy and appears to have achieved a middle ground between outlawing abortions completely and allowing abortion on demand. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Difficulty in distinguishing circumstances</head><p n="p12.44"><s n="s1.1;p12.44">However, the English debate is far from conclusion. </s></p><p n="p13.44"><s n="s1.1;p13.44">The English legal position has been criticized for its lack of a 'single, coherent, philosophy' that properly considers 'issues of individual rights, the balance between individual rights and public policy, and issues of conflicting rights'.<ref target="BAWE_0410d-ftnote.012"/> By allowing doctors to consider whether the statutory grounds for abortion are met, the decision is shifted onto the medical profession. <ref target="BAWE_0410d-ftnote.013"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0410d-ftnote.012"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.3;pn1.1">M. Brazier, 'Regulating the Reproduction Business' (1999) 7 <hi rend="italic">Med.</hi> </s><s rend="italic" n="s2.3;pn1.1">L. Rev. </s><s n="s3.3;pn1.1">166 at 167. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0410d-ftnote.013"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">S. Sheldon,<hi rend="italic"> Beyond Control: Medical Power and Abortion Law</hi> (Pluto 1997), as cited in J. Herring (2006), n.3, at 240. </s></p></note><p n="p14.44"><s n="s1.3;p14.44">More importantly, the Act fails to distinguish the circumstances where abortion is allowed in a satisfactory manner. </s><s n="s2.3;p14.44">While this is illustrated in the section following, Parliament's failure to address the Second Question highlights how difficult it is to distinguish circumstances in which abortion should not be permitted from those in which it should. </s><s n="s3.3;p14.44">In other words, the more difficult moral questions have not been satisfactorily addressed. </s></p><p n="p15.44"><s n="s1.4;p15.44">The circumstances to be considered may range from the circumstances of conception, to the characteristics of the foetus, to the physical or mental conditions of the woman, which then turns on how fine-grain each circumstance is defined. </s><s n="s2.4;p15.44">The difficulty is in determining whether abortion should not be permitted from those in which it should. </s><s n="s3.4;p15.44">The answer might depend on one's moral values. </s><s n="s4.4;p15.44">This allows diverse opinions on each circumstance yet the law could only entertain one answer. </s></p><p n="p16.44"><s n="s1.2;p16.44">Apart from the notion that abortion should be allowed where a mother's life is in danger<ref target="BAWE_0410d-ftnote.014"/>, there is little consensus on the circumstances that allow abortion. </s><s n="s2.2;p16.44">For example, whether abortion should be allowed after rape is already contentious by some<ref target="BAWE_0410d-ftnote.015"/>. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0410d-ftnote.014"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">BPAS, Public Opinions 2004, as cited in J. Herring (2006), n.3, at 266. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">The level of support where a woman's life was at risk from the pregnancy was at 93 percent. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0410d-ftnote.015"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">The Roman Catholic Church holds a firm line against abortion which includes rape cases. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">See for example, <hi rend="italic">The Guardian</hi>, August 31, 2006 'Church condemns abortion performed on raped girl, 11' <seg type="URL" n="http://www.guardian.co.uk/colombia/story/0,,1861532,00.html"/> </s></p></note><p n="p17.44"><s n="s1.2;p17.44">The question to be answered, framed in the context of English law, is whether it would be unjust to deny legal protection (from the crime of abortion) in such circumstances. </s><s n="s2.2;p17.44">The difficulty in answering this question is best illustrated in the context of disability. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Abortion on grounds of foetal disability</head><p n="p18.44"><s n="s1.1;p18.44">Section 1(1)(d) of the English Act allows abortion on grounds of 'serious disability' if two doctors consider that 'there is a substantial risk that if the child were born it would suffer from such physical or mental abnormalities as to be seriously handicapped'. </s></p><p n="p19.44"><s n="s1.1;p19.44">The difficult questions posed is threefold: (a) whether abortion on grounds of foetal disability should be allowed; (b) which conditions of disability merit termination; and (c) what are the factors to be taken into account when considering 'seriousness'. </s></p><div2><head rend="underlined">(a) Whether abortion on grounds of foetal disability should be allowed</head><p n="p20.44"><s n="s1.3;p20.44">First off, this is contentious on its own. </s><s n="s2.3;p20.44">Some would argue that aborting a severely disabled foetus should be acceptable, at the very least understandable. </s><s n="s3.3;p20.44">The 'Parental Interests Argument' contends that abortion on grounds of foetal disability is justified because 'the strain of caring for a disabled child may be substantially greater than that of caring for a non-disabled one'<ref target="BAWE_0410d-ftnote.016"/>. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0410d-ftnote.016"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.5;pn1.1">S. Sheldon and S. Wilkinson, 'Termination of Pregnancy for Reason of Foetal Disability: Are There Grounds for a Special Exception in Law?' (2001) </s><s n="s2.5;pn1.1">9 <hi rend="italic">Med.</hi> </s><s n="s3.5;pn1.1"><hi rend="italic">L. Rev</hi>. </s><s n="s4.5;pn1.1">85. </s><s n="s5.5;pn1.1">The authors explored two other arguments to defend abortion on grounds of foetal disability (the 'Foetal Interests Argument' and the 'Replacement Argument') but found them to fail. </s></p></note><p n="p21.44"><s n="s1.2;p21.44">Others would argue that disability should not be perceived as a ground for abortion in the first place. </s><s n="s2.2;p21.44">The 'Disability Discrimination Objection' relies on the idea 'that disability is relevantly similar to other categories, such as race, gender and sexuality and that, therefore, selectively terminating disabled foetuses is like selectively terminating black or female foetuses (which would, in the context of a general ban on 'late' abortions, be unacceptably discriminatory)'<ref target="BAWE_0410d-ftnote.017"/>. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0410d-ftnote.017"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">S. Sheldon and S. Wilkinson (2001),ibid. The authors argued against this objection by distinguishing that in addition to harms caused by social discrimination, disability involves harm caused directly by impairment. </s></p></note><p n="p22.44"><s n="s1.1;p22.44">Thus the rationale for allowing abortion on grounds of foetal disability is still open to question. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">(b) Which conditions of disability merit termination</head><p n="p23.44"><s n="s1.1;p23.44">Secondly, and perhaps more importantly, the difficulty is in distinguishing which conditions of disability merit termination. </s></p><p n="p24.44"><s n="s1.1;p24.44">The statute does little to further the meaning of 'seriousness', and the Royal College of Obstetrician's and Gynaecologists' guidelines regarding this point do little to help.<ref target="BAWE_0410d-ftnote.018"/> The lack of consensus, even amongst genetic professionals, as to the 'seriousness' of the various disabilities that may occur, renders it 'one of the most difficult issues in this context'<ref target="BAWE_0410d-ftnote.019"/>. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0410d-ftnote.018"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">See R. Scott, 'Interpreting the Disability Ground of the Abortion Act' (2005a) <hi rend="italic">Cambridge Law Journal</hi> 64: 388. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0410d-ftnote.019"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.3;pn1.1">E. Parens and A. Asch, 'The Disability Rights Critique of Prenatal Genetic Testing: Reflections and Recommendations' in E. Parens and A. Asch (eds), <hi rend="italic">Prenatal Testing and Disability Rights</hi> (Georgetown University Press 2000) 3, as cited in R. Scott, 'Prenatal Screening, Autonomy and Reasons: The Relationship between the Law of Abortion and Wrongful Birth' (2003) <hi rend="italic">Med.</hi> </s><s rend="italic" n="s2.3;pn1.1">L. Rev. </s><s n="s3.3;pn1.1">265. </s></p></note><p n="p25.44"><s n="s1.1;p25.44">While it is relatively clear at the extremes (for example Turner's syndrome versus a susceptibility to moderate obesity), it is the huge range of mid-spectrum disabilities in between that is most contentious.<ref target="BAWE_0410d-ftnote.020"/> The test for each condition should be whether 'such a disability is <hi rend="italic">sufficiently serious</hi> for the parents' interests to merit legal protection'. <ref target="BAWE_0410d-ftnote.021"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0410d-ftnote.020"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">D. Wertz, 'Drawing Lines: Notes for Policy-Makers' in E. Parens and A. Asch (eds), at 261, as cited in R. Scott (2003), ibid.. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0410d-ftnote.021"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">R. Scott (2003), <hi rend="italic">supra</hi>, n.19. </s></p></note><p n="p26.44"><s n="s1.1;p26.44">Apart from the controversy that this test relies on the judgment of doctors<ref target="BAWE_0410d-ftnote.022"/>, given the degree of disagreement, which conditions of disability merit termination remains an open question. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0410d-ftnote.022"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">S. Sheldon (Pluto 1997), <hi rend="italic">supra</hi>, n.13. </s></p></note></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">(c) What are the factors to be taken into account when considering 'seriousness'</head><p n="p27.44"><s n="s1.2;p27.44">Thirdly, in deciding whether it would be unjust to deny a woman's access to abortion, whether other circumstances, such as the family's ability to raise a disabled child, or the parents' perceptions, should be taken into consideration as well is still open to question. </s><s n="s2.2;p27.44">In other words, should parents' interests be taken into account? </s></p><p n="p28.44"><s n="s1.2;p28.44">On one hand, there would be circumstances where it would be unjust to deny legal protection; on the other, taking socioeconomic reasons into consideration may blur the moral status of foetus. </s><s n="s2.2;p28.44">The vague guidance provided by the Royal College of Obstetrician's and Gynaecologists on this point<ref target="BAWE_0410d-ftnote.023"/> leads one to seriously doubt whether the current regulation is practical or not. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0410d-ftnote.023"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.4;pn1.1">As indicated in the letter to the police from the Vice President of the Royal College of Obstetrician's and Gynaecologists in the case of <hi rend="italic">Jepson v The Chief Constable of West Mercia Police Constabulary</hi> [2003] EWHC 3318, which reads: "The decision to abort under Clause E would always ultimately be with the mother having taken into consideration the perception of the parents to the serious nature of the handicap following counselling and information from experts with special knowledge of the condition.". </s><s n="s2.4;pn1.1">See also R. Scott, 'The Uncertain Scope of Reproductive Autonomy in Preimplantation Genetic Diagnosis and Selective Abortion' (2005b) 13 <hi rend="italic">Med.</hi> </s><s n="s3.4;pn1.1"><hi rend="italic">L. Rev</hi>. </s><s n="s4.4;pn1.1">291. </s></p></note></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">The <hi rend="italic">Jepson</hi> case</head><p n="p29.44"><s n="s1.1;p29.44">The uncertainties highlighted in the previous section were raised in the case of <hi rend="italic">Jepson v The Chief Constable of West Mercia Police Constabulary</hi><ref target="BAWE_0410d-ftnote.024"/>. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0410d-ftnote.024"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">[2003] EWHC 3318. </s></p></note><p n="p30.44"><s n="s1.2;p30.44">The case was a successful application for permission to proceed with judicial review for the police's decision not to investigate doctors who authorized an abortion for bilateral cleft lip and palate at 28 weeks under the disability ground of the Act. </s><s n="s2.2;p30.44">Although the issue was left unresolved, the case raises various issues on the legality of an abortion for foetal disability. </s></p><p n="p31.44"><s n="s1.2;p31.44">The Claimant raised a challenge to abortion on grounds of foetal disability first by claiming 'that the foetus at 24 weeks gestation and greater has a right to life pursuant to Article 2 of the European Convention on Human Rights, which is only subject to the competing Article 2 right of the mother' and 'that section 1(1)(d) of the Abortion Act 1967 is incompatible with Articles 2, 3, 8 and 14 of the European Convention on Human Rights'<ref target="BAWE_0410d-ftnote.025"/>. </s><s n="s2.2;p31.44">There is no case law directly on this point but it has been suggested that it is unlikely for this claim to succeed. <ref target="BAWE_0410d-ftnote.026"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0410d-ftnote.025"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1"><hi rend="italic">Ibid</hi>., at [8]. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0410d-ftnote.026"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">R. Scott (2005a), <hi rend="italic">supra</hi>, n.18, at 408. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">See also the judgment from the European Court of Human Rights, <hi rend="italic">Vo v France</hi> [2004] 2 FCR 577. </s></p></note><p n="p32.44"><s n="s1.1;p32.44">The main thrust of the claim was whether cleft lip and palate constitutes 'serious handicap' within the meaning of section 1(1)(d) of the Abortion Act 1967.<ref target="BAWE_0410d-ftnote.027"/> Notions of remediability were invoked to support of this claim. <ref target="BAWE_0410d-ftnote.028"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0410d-ftnote.027"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1"><hi rend="italic">Supra</hi>, n.24, at [8]. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0410d-ftnote.028"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Scott is sceptical of this idea, although 'certain solidity' is acknowledged. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">See R. Scott (2005a), <hi rend="italic">supra</hi>, n.18, at 393. </s></p></note><p n="p33.44"><s n="s1.1;p33.44">Thirdly, although this was not explicitly contended in the case, an issue raised was whether taking the parents' views into account in considering the definition of 'serious handicap' is consistent with the disability ground of the Abortion Act.<ref target="BAWE_0410d-ftnote.029"/> While the claim has not been pursued further<ref target="BAWE_0410d-ftnote.030"/>, the issues raised in the previous section were recognized as issues that will receive judicial attention. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0410d-ftnote.029"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">See also R. Scott (2005b), <hi rend="italic">supra</hi>, n.23. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0410d-ftnote.030"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.5;pn1.1">The Claimant, Rev. </s><s n="s2.5;pn1.1">Jepson issued a press statement (available at <seg type="URL" n="www.jjepson.org"/>) which read: 'I have consulted my solicitor over the last few weeks and am advised that the decision of the CPS does not in any way protect disabled unborn babies in later stages of pregnancy. </s><s n="s3.5;pn1.1">Prime responsibility for these abortions rests with the Secretary of State. </s><s n="s4.5;pn1.1">I will therefore pursue this against the Secretary of State but will not be seeking the prosecution of the doctors concerned. </s><s n="s5.5;pn1.1">Tragic as it is that this baby's life was ended, I hope this case will prevent further late term abortions.', as cited in R. Scott (2005b), <hi rend="italic">supra</hi>, n.23. </s></p></note><p n="p34.44"><s n="s1.3;p34.44">In summary, it has been seen that abortion on grounds of foetal disability is a problematic area which raises difficult moral questions. </s><s n="s2.3;p34.44">Aborting a severely disabled foetus as a circumstance on its own is already arguable. </s><s n="s3.3;p34.44">What is more difficult is in distinguishing which conditions of disability merit termination. </s></p><p n="p35.44"><s n="s1.3;p35.44">Determining the factors that should be taken into consideration in allowing an abortion regarding foetal disability further complicates the matter. </s><s n="s2.3;p35.44">The <hi rend="italic">Jepson</hi> case shows that the court recognizes these difficulties as issues that will receive judicial attention. </s><s n="s3.3;p35.44">In other words, a closer examination of English abortion law in the context of foetal disability has revealed that the current law fails to address the more difficult moral issues that arise in the Second Question. </s></p><p n="p36.44"><s n="s1.1;p36.44">Given the unsatisfactory state of the law and the stalemate in the English abortion debate, is there a way out? </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">The American approach - a plausible alternative? </head><p n="p37.44"><s n="s1.1;p37.44">It may be useful to look at the position across the Atlantic. </s></p><p n="p38.44"><s n="s1.1;p38.44">While the English Act does not provide a 'right to abortion' in any sense, abortion law in the United States is concerned with a pregnant woman's autonomy and is rights-based.<ref target="BAWE_0410d-ftnote.031"/> Instead of treating abortion as a wrong, the right of abortion is derived from the Due Process Clause of the Fourteenth Amendment.<ref target="BAWE_0410d-ftnote.032"/> A woman can exercise her right to abort her foetus (pre-viability) for any reason, unlike the English position where justification is required for abortion. <ref target="BAWE_0410d-ftnote.033"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0410d-ftnote.031"><p n="pn1.1"><s rend="italic" n="s1.4;pn1.1">Roe v. </s><s n="s2.4;pn1.1"><hi rend="italic">Wade</hi>, 35 L.Ed.2d 147 (1973); <hi rend="italic">Planned Parenthood of South-eastern Pennsylvania v.</hi> </s><s n="s3.4;pn1.1"><hi rend="italic">Casey</hi>, 505 U.S. </s><s n="s4.4;pn1.1">833 (1992). </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0410d-ftnote.032"><p n="pn1.1"><s rend="italic" n="s1.3;pn1.1">Planned Parenthood of South-eastern Pennsylvania v. </s><s n="s2.3;pn1.1"><hi rend="italic">Casey</hi>, 505 U.S. </s><s n="s3.3;pn1.1">833 (1992). </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0410d-ftnote.033"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">For a discussion on the English and American legal position on abortion, see R. Scott (2003), <hi rend="italic">supra</hi>, n.19. </s></p></note><p n="p39.44"><s n="s1.3;p39.44">Since no reasons are required, there is no dispute as to the circumstances where abortion is allowed, such as foetal disability.<ref target="BAWE_0410d-ftnote.034"/> Rather, regulation is achieved through the recognition of 'important State interests' which are capable of limiting the right of abortion. </s><s n="s2.3;p39.44">Hence American cases usually turn on whether a woman's right to abort was subject to illegitimate state interference<ref target="BAWE_0410d-ftnote.035"/>. </s><s n="s3.3;p39.44">Only in states allowing termination after viability on the basis of foetal disability does questions of definition, analogous to the English difficulty in interpreting 'seriousness' in the Abortion Act 1967, arise.<ref target="BAWE_0410d-ftnote.036"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0410d-ftnote.034"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">R. Scott (2003), <hi rend="italic">supra</hi>, n.19. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0410d-ftnote.035"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">See <hi rend="italic">Akron v Akron Centre for Reproductive Health</hi> 76 L.Ed.2d 687 (1983); and <hi rend="italic">Thornburgh v American College of Obstetricians and Gynecologists</hi> 90 L.Ed.2d 779 (1986). </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0410d-ftnote.036"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">See D. Stoller, 'Prenatal Genetic Screening: the Enigma of Selective Abortion' (1997/1998) 12 <hi rend="italic">J.L. &amp; Health</hi> 121 at 136-137. </s></p></note><p n="p40.44"><s n="s1.3;p40.44">In other words, the American approach treats abortion as a positive right of autonomy. </s><s n="s2.3;p40.44">State regulations are valid only if it does not impose a 'substantial obstacle in the path of a woman seeking an abortion before the foetus attains viability'<ref target="BAWE_0410d-ftnote.037"/>. </s><s n="s3.3;p40.44">On the contrary, the English approach treats abortion as a negative liberty.<ref target="BAWE_0410d-ftnote.038"/> Access to abortion is allowed only if statutory circumstances are met. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0410d-ftnote.037"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1"><hi rend="italic">Supra</hi>, n.31 at 878. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0410d-ftnote.038"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">See R. Scott (2003), <hi rend="italic">supra</hi>, n.19. </s></p></note><p n="p41.44"><s n="s1.3;p41.44">It is not contended that the American position<ref target="BAWE_0410d-ftnote.039"/> should be adopted, but the rights-based approach may be taken as a plausible complementary alternative. </s><s n="s2.3;p41.44">Instead of defining circumstances that <hi rend="italic">allow</hi> abortion, regulation could alternatively be achieved by stipulating situations where abortion is <hi rend="italic">prohibited</hi>. </s><s n="s3.3;p41.44">Although this alternative merely phrases the same question the other way round, it would have significant changes on the law. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0410d-ftnote.039"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Such as differences in the restrictive period. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">The American position is that abortion is not allowed after viability (subject to exceptions); whereas the English position is that abortion is not allowed throughout the pregnancy (subject to exceptions). </s></p></note><p n="p42.44"><s n="s1.2;p42.44">On one hand, this would give women greater freedom in abortion by removing circumstances where legislation is silent on; on the other, interests of the foetus, in the context of abortion, would be better protected by explicit stipulation. </s><s n="s2.2;p42.44">In other words, by adopting this alternative approach Parliament would recognize circumstances where the foetus is better treated as a person than a non-person.<ref target="BAWE_0410d-ftnote.040"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0410d-ftnote.040"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">This line of reasoning is extended from the 'Playing it safe' argument in J. Herring (2006), n.3, 251. </s></p></note></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Conclusion</head><p n="p43.44"><s n="s1.2;p43.44">Putting abortion in terms of the rights/interests of the woman and those of the foetus, the issue of distinguishing circumstances in which abortion should not be permitted from those in which it should is essentially a balancing exercise. </s><s n="s2.2;p43.44">Between the extremes of banning abortion and allowing it on demand, the extent to which a woman could have access to abortion legally is a matter of degree laid down by Parliament. </s></p><p n="p44.44"><s n="s1.2;p44.44">The current regime in England, Wales and Scotland fails to give a clear distinction between the circumstances where abortion should be allowed and is in an unsatisfactory state. </s><s n="s2.2;p44.44">Although it is unlikely for the UK to adopt the US position, perhaps a move towards a rights based approach would result in a more objective approach to answering the difficult moral questions that arise in distinguishing circumstances in which abortion should not be permitted from those in which it should in the future. </s></p></div1></body><back><div1 type="bibliography"><head rend="bold">Bibliography</head><div2 type="bibliography"><head rend="underlined">Articles</head><p>J. Thomson, 'A Defense of Abortion', (1971) <hi rend="italic">Philosophy and Public Affairs</hi>, 1, 47-66.</p><p>J. Herring, <hi rend="italic">Medical Law and Ethics</hi> (OUP 2006).</p><p>M. Brazier, 'Regulating the Reproduction Business' (1999) 7 <hi rend="italic">Med. L. Rev.</hi> 166 at 167.</p><p>S. Sheldon,<hi rend="italic"> Beyond Control: Medical Power and Abortion Law</hi> (Pluto 1997), as cited in J. Herring (2006).</p><p>BPAS, Public Opinions 2004, as cited in J. Herring (2006).</p><p>S. Sheldon and S. Wilkinson, 'Termination of Pregnancy for Reason of Foetal Disability: Are There Grounds for a Special Exception in Law?' (2001) 9 <hi rend="italic">Med. L. Rev</hi>. 85. </p><p>R. Scott, 'Prenatal Screening, Autonomy and Reasons: The Relationship between the Law of Abortion and Wrongful Birth' (2003) <hi rend="italic">Med. L. Rev.</hi> 265</p><p>R. Scott, 'Interpreting the Disability Ground of the Abortion Act' (2005a) <hi rend="italic">Cambridge Law Journal</hi> 64: 388.</p><p>E. Parens and A. Asch, 'The Disability Rights Critique of Prenatal Genetic Testing: Reflections and Recommendations' in E. Parens and A. Asch (eds), <hi rend="italic">Prenatal Testing and Disability Rights</hi> (Georgetown University Press 2000) 3, as cited in R. Scott (2003).</p><p>D. Wertz, 'Drawing Lines: Notes for Policy-Makers' in E. Parens and A. Asch (eds), at 261, as cited in R. Scott (2003)</p><p>R. Scott, 'The Uncertain Scope of Reproductive Autonomy in Preimplantation Genetic Diagnosis and Selective Abortion' (2005b) 13 <hi rend="italic">Med. L. Rev</hi>. 291.</p><p>D. Stoller, 'Prenatal Genetic Screening: the Enigma of Selective Abortion' (1997/1998) 12 <hi rend="italic">J.L. &amp; Health</hi> 121</p></div2><div2 type="bibliography"><head rend="underlined">Internet</head><p><hi rend="italic">The Guardian</hi>, August 31, 2006 'Church condemns abortion performed on raped girl, 11' <seg type="URL" n="http://www.guardian.co.uk/colombia/story/0,,1861532,00.html"/> </p></div2><div2 type="bibliography"><head rend="underlined">Cases</head><p><hi rend="italic">A-G's Reference (No 3 of 1994)</hi> [1997] 3 All ER 936.</p><p><hi rend="italic">R v Bourne</hi> [1939] 1 KB 687.</p><p><hi rend="italic">St George's NHS Trust v S</hi> (1998) 44 BMLR 160. </p><p><hi rend="italic">R v Gibson</hi> [1990] 2 QB 619.</p><p><hi rend="italic">Jepson v The Chief Constable of West Mercia Police Constabulary</hi> [2003] EWHC 3318</p><p><hi rend="italic">Vo v France</hi> [2004] 2 FCR 577.</p><p rend="bold"><hi rend="italic">Roe v. Wade</hi>, 35 L.Ed.2d 147 (1973)</p><p rend="bold"><hi rend="italic">Planned Parenthood of South-eastern Pennsylvania v. Casey</hi>, 505 U.S. 833 (1992).</p><p><hi rend="italic">Akron v Akron Centre for Reproductive Health</hi> 76 L.Ed.2d 687 (1983)</p><p><hi rend="italic">Thornburgh v American College of Obstetricians and Gynecologists</hi> 90 L.Ed.2d 779 (1986).</p></div2></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
