<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_0410b" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>1. In what circumstances is the judiciary prepared to relax the doctrine of the separate legal personality of a company? Is the current legal situation satisfactory from a policy point of view, particularly in the light of the group structure of many modern businesses?</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">The document has a title page which contains:
document title
title part</note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">deleted: page numbers</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">3</p><p n="date">unknown</p><p n="module title">Law of Business Organisations</p><p n="module code">LA310</p><p n="genre family">Essay</p><p n="discipline">Law</p><p n="disciplinary group">SS</p><p n="grade">unknown</p><p n="number of authors">unknown</p><p n="number of words">2598</p><p n="number of s-units">80</p><p n="number of p">24</p><p n="number of tables">0</p><p n="number of figures">0</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">0</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">0</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">32.5</p><p n="average s-units per p">3.3</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">m</p><p n="year of birth">1984</p><p n="first language">Chinese unspecified</p><p n="education">OSA</p><p n="course">Law</p><p n="student ID">0410</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><titlePart><hi rend="bold">UNIVERSITYOF </hi><name type="university"/><hi rend="bold"> Law of Business Organisations</hi> <hi rend="bold"> LA 310 </hi></titlePart><docTitle><titlePart rend="bold">1. In what circumstances is the judiciary prepared to relax the doctrine of the separate legal personality of a company? Is the current legal situation satisfactory from a policy point of view, particularly in the light of the group structure of many modern businesses? </titlePart></docTitle></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Introduction</head><p n="p1.24"><s n="s1.4;p1.24">The limited liability company has become the flagship of most capitalist economies since its inauguration in the 19 <hi rend="sup">th</hi> century. </s><s n="s2.4;p1.24">Yet there are times where the limited liability of companies may cause undue hardship on creditors. </s><s n="s3.4;p1.24">Consequently, the judiciary may be prepared to relax the doctrine of the separate legal personality of a company in certain circumstances and render shareholders personally liable. </s><s n="s4.4;p1.24">This relaxation is more commonly known as "lifting" or "piercing" the "corporate veil".<ref target="BAWE_0410b-ftnote.001"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0410b-ftnote.001"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">These terms will be used interchangeably throughout the rest of this article. </s></p></note><p n="p2.24"><s n="s1.3;p2.24">However, business practices have changed dramatically over the past century. </s><s n="s2.3;p2.24">A number of factors, such as globalization and intensified competition, have triggered the emergence of corporate groups. </s><s n="s3.3;p2.24">This raises the central issue of this article: whether courts have been able to cope with this commercial development satisfactorily. </s></p><p n="p3.24"><s n="s1.3;p3.24">We start by briefly introducing fundamental concepts of corporate personality, limited liability and the doctrine of piercing the corporate veil. </s><s n="s2.3;p3.24">We then take a look at contemporary problems of corporate group structures before moving on to examine the courts' stance on lifting the corporate veil. </s><s n="s3.3;p3.24">By analyzing the underlying policies for the current legal situation, we argue that the current legal situation does not address the perceived problems of corporate groups satisfactorily. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Separate Personality, Limited Liability and <hi rend="italic"> Salomon v Salomon</hi></head><p n="p4.24"><s n="s1.3;p4.24">The doctrine of separate personality of a company is fundamental to modern company law. </s><s n="s2.3;p4.24">In essence, the corporation is a separate person and its members are not personally liable for its debts.<ref target="BAWE_0410b-ftnote.002"/> Coupled with the principle of limited liability, the corporate personality effectively renders the limited liability company the best vehicle available for making profits with limited risks. </s><s n="s3.3;p4.24">As a result, shareholders "benefit, through limited liability, from a cap of their down-side risk, whereas the chance of up-side gain is unlimited", thus encouraging investment from the public. <ref target="BAWE_0410b-ftnote.003"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0410b-ftnote.002"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Except the case for unlimited company, where s.74 of the Insolvency Act 1986 does impose an obligation onto members to contribute to the assets of the company. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0410b-ftnote.003"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">P.L. Davies, Gower and Davies' <hi rend="italic">Principles of Modern Company Law</hi>, (7th ed., Sweet and Maxwell, London, 2003), at 176. </s></p></note><p n="p5.24"><s n="s1.4;p5.24">However, this doctrine is not without limits. </s><s n="s2.4;p5.24">The basic rationale for the combination of corporate personality and limited liability was to generate economic growth in the wake of the industrial revolution.<ref target="BAWE_0410b-ftnote.004"/> However, this combination has obvious potential for abuse. </s><s n="s3.4;p5.24">Consequently, the doctrine of separate personality has been limited by Parliament<ref target="BAWE_0410b-ftnote.005"/> and the judiciary in certain circumstances. </s><s n="s4.4;p5.24">The doctrine of lifting the corporate veil was cemented into modern company law by the celebrated case of <hi rend="italic">Salomon v Salomon</hi><ref target="BAWE_0410b-ftnote.006"/>, where the House of Lords in <hi rend="italic">Salomon</hi> held that upon incorporation a new and separate artificial entity comes into existence, even in a small private company established and run by an individual human trader.<ref target="BAWE_0410b-ftnote.007"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0410b-ftnote.004"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">S. Griffin, "Limited liability: a necessary revolution?", (2004) </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">Company Lawyer Vol.25(4), 99. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0410b-ftnote.005"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">The corporate veil will be lifted in various situations, such as in cases of fraudulent trading and wrongful trading under sections 213 and 214 of the Insolvency Act 1986. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0410b-ftnote.006"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">[1897] A.C. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">22 (HL). </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0410b-ftnote.007"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">There are many discussions on the decision in <hi rend="italic">Salomon</hi>, see for example G. V. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">Puig, "A Two-Edged Sword: Salomon and the Separate Legal Entity Doctrine", Murdoch University Electronic Journal of Law, Volume 7, Number 3 (September 2000), available at <seg type="URL" n="http://www.murdoch.edu.au/elaw/issues/v7n3/puig73a_text.html"/> (last visited April 21, 2007) </s></p></note></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">The Problem with <hi rend="italic">Salomon v Salomon</hi> and Corporate Groups</head><p n="p6.24"><s n="s1.3;p6.24">The world is now quite different since <hi rend="italic">Salomon</hi>. </s><s n="s2.3;p6.24">An evolution of business structures have occurred through the course of economic development in the twentieth century. </s><s n="s3.3;p6.24">Much of the businesses today are now carried out through a group of holding and subsidiary companies rather than a single company.<ref target="BAWE_0410b-ftnote.008"/> Yet, the principle in <hi rend="italic">Salomon</hi> is still significant because it has been extended to cover the more complex scenario of a multinational inter-corporate group enterprise where a controlling "parent" company operates its business through a number of smaller "subsidiaries", even in cases where each individual entity is indistinguishable. <ref target="BAWE_0410b-ftnote.009"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0410b-ftnote.008"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">P.L. Davies, Gower and Davies' <hi rend="italic">Principles of Modern Company Law</hi>, (7th ed., Sweet and Maxwell, London, 2003), at 178. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0410b-ftnote.009"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Adams v Cape Industries Plc [1991] 1 All E.R. 929 (CA (Civ Div)); for a discussion concerning group enterprises from an Australian perspective, see O. Shub "Separate Corporate Personality: Piercing the Corporate Veil", FDCC Quarterly, Winter 2006; for a comprehensive empirical study of the doctrine of piercing the corporate veil in Australia, see I. Ramsay &amp; D. Noakes, "Piercing the Corporate Veil in Australia", (2001) 19 Company and Securities Law Journal 250-271. </s></p></note><p n="p7.24"><s n="s1.4;p7.24">This extension of <hi rend="italic">Salomon</hi>, however, is not without controversy. </s><s n="s2.4;p7.24">First, the legitimacy of corporate groups operating as a single-economic unit while enjoying separate corporate personality has been questioned. </s><s n="s3.4;p7.24">It has been suggested that the courts have confirmed application of Corporate Personality within corporate groups without deep consideration of its consequences.<ref target="BAWE_0410b-ftnote.010"/> The doctrine of separate corporate personality has clearly been thought to protect shareholders of natural persons<ref target="BAWE_0410b-ftnote.011"/>, and courts have traditionally dealt with cases concerning shareholders of natural persons<ref target="BAWE_0410b-ftnote.012"/>. </s><s n="s4.4;p7.24">Emergence of new problems created by corporate groups raises new challenges to the traditional orthodoxy. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0410b-ftnote.010"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">P.L. Davies, Gower and Davies' <hi rend="italic">Principles of Modern Company Law</hi>, (7th ed., Sweet and Maxwell, London, 2003), at 178. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0410b-ftnote.011"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1"><hi rend="italic">Ibid</hi>, at 178 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0410b-ftnote.012"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">See, for example, Gilford Motor Co Ltd v Horne [1933] Ch 935; Jones v Lipman [1962] 1 WLR 832; Woolfson v Strathclyde Regional Council [1978] STL 159. </s></p></note><p n="p8.24"><s n="s1.2;p8.24">The second line of debate assumes that protection offered to shareholders of natural persons should also be offered to holding companies and corporate groups, but questions <hi rend="italic">when</hi> this protection should be lifted.<ref target="BAWE_0410b-ftnote.013"/> It has also been alleged that the law has failed to keep pace with the developments in the commercial world.<ref target="BAWE_0410b-ftnote.014"/> These accusations merit a thorough assessment of the current legal situation regarding lifting the corporate veil of corporate groups. </s><s n="s2.2;p8.24">We will focus on this line of the debate in the rest of this article. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0410b-ftnote.013"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">The validity of the doctrine of piercing the veil has been challenged, see M. Moore, "A temple built on fault foundations: Piercing the corporate veil and the legacy of Salomon v Salomon", Journal of Business Law, 2006, Mar, 180-203 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0410b-ftnote.014"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">A. Magaisa, "Corporate Groups and Victims of Corporate Torts - Towards a new Architecture of Corporate law in a Dynamic Marketplace" Corporate Law in a Dynamic Marketplace', Law, Social Justice &amp; Global Development Journal (LGD) 2002 (1), available at <seg type="URL" n="http://www2.warwick.ac.uk/fac/soc/law/elj/lgd/2002_1/magaisa/"/> (last visited, April 21, 2007) </s></p></note><p n="p9.24"><s n="s1.4;p9.24">A starting point may be examining the issue related to corporate groups. </s><s n="s2.4;p9.24">While corporate groups vary in structure<ref target="BAWE_0410b-ftnote.015"/>, the exploitation of the company law by corporate groups is also open to variation.<ref target="BAWE_0410b-ftnote.016"/> The classic example is best illustrated in the facts of <hi rend="italic">Adams v Cape Industries Plc</hi><ref target="BAWE_0410b-ftnote.017"/>. </s><s n="s3.4;p9.24">The case concerned the alleged negligence of Cape Industries plc, a multinational company based in England involved in mining asbestos in South Africa and marketing it worldwide, causing asbestos infection to claimants that either worked or lived in the vicinity of the asbestos mines and mills. </s><s n="s4.4;p9.24">Judgment was obtained in the United States but since Cape was not "present" in the United States, the English Court of Appeal declined to recognize and enforce the judgment. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0410b-ftnote.015"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.4;pn1.1">The scenario is even more complex when Transnational business organisations are involved. </s><s n="s2.4;pn1.1">See P. Muchlinski, "Holding Multinationals to Account", Comp. </s><s n="s3.4;pn1.1">Law. </s><s n="s4.4;pn1.1">2002, 23(6), 168. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0410b-ftnote.016"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">For an illustration of how these traditional principles of corporate law are exploited by transnational business organizations in building corporate groups, see A. Magaisa, "Corporate Groups and Victims of Corporate Torts - Towards a new Architecture of Corporate law in a Dynamic Marketplace" Corporate Law in a Dynamic Marketplace', Law, Social Justice &amp; Global Development Journal (LGD) 2002 (1), available at <seg type="URL" n="http://www2.warwick.ac.uk/fac/soc/law/elj/lgd/2002_1/magaisa/"/> (last visited, April 21, 2007) </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0410b-ftnote.017"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">[1991] 1 All E.R. 929 (CA (Civ Div)) </s></p></note><p n="p10.24"><s n="s1.4;p10.24">Hence, part of the commercial reality today is that corporate groups are using the principle established in <hi rend="italic">Salomon</hi> to their advantage by limiting liability to subsidiary companies.<ref target="BAWE_0410b-ftnote.018"/> By establishing subsidiary companies in foreign countries to undergo profitable but risky operations, the parent reaps the rewards if the subsidiary turns out to be successful. </s><s n="s2.4;p10.24">However, if the subsidiary fails and incurs a hefty liability, then a strict application <hi rend="italic">Salomon</hi> would limit liability to the subsidiary and the rest of the corporate group remain unaffected. </s><s n="s3.4;p10.24">This results in serious injustice if the subsidiary is severely undercapitalized while undertaking ultra-hazardous operations in developing countries. </s><s n="s4.4;p10.24">Clearly, this is a serious issue that deserves further scrutiny. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0410b-ftnote.018"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">M. Moore, "A temple built on fault foundations: Piercing the corporate veil and the legacy of Salomon v Salomon", Journal of Business Law, 2006, Mar, 180-203, at 181. </s></p></note></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">The current legal situation</head><p n="p11.24"><s n="s1.3;p11.24">In general, the law limits liability at trading company level. </s><s n="s2.3;p11.24">Although this has been severely criticized<ref target="BAWE_0410b-ftnote.019"/>, <hi rend="italic">Salomon</hi> has been reaffirmed once and again by courts. </s><s n="s3.3;p11.24">Narrow grounds for lifting the corporate veil do exist, but judicial reaction has been seen as inconsistent and lacks uniformity.<ref target="BAWE_0410b-ftnote.020"/> A general observation is that courts are reluctant to lift the corporate veil.<ref target="BAWE_0410b-ftnote.021"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0410b-ftnote.019"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.3;pn1.1">See P. Muchlinski, "Holding Multinationals to Account", Comp. </s><s n="s2.3;pn1.1">Law. </s><s n="s3.3;pn1.1">2002, 23(6), 168. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0410b-ftnote.020"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">A. Magaisa, "Corporate Groups and Victims of Corporate Torts - Towards a new Architecture of Corporate law in a Dynamic Marketplace" Corporate Law in a Dynamic Marketplace', Law, Social Justice &amp; Global Development Journal (LGD) 2002 (1), available at <seg type="URL" n="http://www2.warwick.ac.uk/fac/soc/law/elj/lgd/2002_1/magaisa/"/> (last visited, April 21, 2007) </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0410b-ftnote.021"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.4;pn1.1">P.L. Davies, Gower and Davies' <hi rend="italic">Principles of Modern Company Law</hi>, (7th ed., Sweet and Maxwell, London, 2003), at 189; see also P. Muchlinski, "Holding Multinationals to Account", Comp. </s><s n="s2.4;pn1.1">Law. </s><s n="s3.4;pn1.1">2002, 23(6), 168; S. Griffin, "Limited liability: a necessary revolution?" </s><s n="s4.4;pn1.1">(2004) Co Lawyer vol. 25(4), 99. </s></p></note><p n="p12.24"><s n="s1.4;p12.24">The leading authority for lifting the corporate veil is the leading judgment of Slade L.J. in <hi rend="italic">Adams</hi>. </s><s n="s2.4;p12.24">Slade L.J. stressed that "the court is not free to disregard the principle of <hi rend="italic">Salomon v A Salomon &amp; Co Ltd</hi> merely because it considers that justice so requires"<ref target="BAWE_0410b-ftnote.022"/>. </s><s n="s3.4;p12.24">This is so even cases where the subsidiary is heavily undercapitalized, the risks are huge and the tremendous liabilities are incurred. </s><s n="s4.4;p12.24">A corporate group is perfectly entitled to structure itself "as to ensure that the legal liability (if any) in respect of particular future activities of the group... will fall on another member of the group rather than the defendant company"<ref target="BAWE_0410b-ftnote.023"/>. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0410b-ftnote.022"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">[1991] 1 All E.R. 929, per Slade L.J., at 1020. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0410b-ftnote.023"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">[1991] 1 All E.R. 929, per Slade L.J., at 1026. </s></p></note><p n="p13.24"><s n="s1.4;p13.24">The only grounds where a court may lift the corporate veil were the "exceptional agency" ground and the "façade or sham" ground. </s><s n="s2.4;p13.24">While the circumstances for the former to occur are extremely narrow<ref target="BAWE_0410b-ftnote.024"/>, the latter has generally been recognized as the only possible route for courts to pierce the corporate veil.<ref target="BAWE_0410b-ftnote.025"/> The difficulty is to know <hi rend="italic">when</hi> a company is a "mere façade".<ref target="BAWE_0410b-ftnote.026"/> The authorities concerning "sham" or "façade" prior to <hi rend="italic">Adams</hi> were straightforward 20 <hi rend="sup">th</hi> century cases of clearly fraudulent schemes and Slade L.J. expressly declined to give elaborate guidelines on this matter.<ref target="BAWE_0410b-ftnote.027"/> In <hi rend="italic">Gilford Motor Co v Horne</hi><ref target="BAWE_0410b-ftnote.028"/>, the Court of Appeal lifted the corporate veil by allowing an injunction against both the defendant and his newly established company, because the only purpose of the company was to enable the defendant to defeat the terms of his restrictive covenant from his former employers. </s><s n="s3.4;p13.24">This was followed in <hi rend="italic">Jones v Lipman</hi><ref target="BAWE_0410b-ftnote.029"/>, where the defendant set up a company that received land which the defendant was obliged to transfer in a previously agreed contract. </s><s n="s4.4;p13.24">Hence, the corporate veil would only be lifted in circumstances where the corporate structure had been abused, and abuse includes evading a known and existing, or confidently predicted liability. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0410b-ftnote.024"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">M. Moore, "A temple built on fault foundations: Piercing the corporate veil and the legacy of Salomon v Salomon", Journal of Business Law, 2006, Mar, 180-203, at 184. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0410b-ftnote.025"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">"outside of particular contracts or statutes, the only ground for lifting the veil is that the subsidiary was a mere façade or sham" Adams v Cape [1990] Ch 433, per Slade L.J. at 539 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0410b-ftnote.026"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">P.L. Davies, Gower and Davies' <hi rend="italic">Principles of Modern Company Law</hi>, (7th ed., Sweet and Maxwell, London, 2003), at 185. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0410b-ftnote.027"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">[1991] 1 All ER 929, per Slade L.J., at 1026. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0410b-ftnote.028"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">[1933] Ch 935 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0410b-ftnote.029"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">[1962] 1 WLR 832 </s></p></note><p n="p14.24"><s n="s1.4;p14.24">However, there is little guidance regarding the features that distinguish a company avoiding future liabilities from evading existing liabilities. </s><s n="s2.4;p14.24">It has been suggested that some form of impropriety linked to the use of the corporate structure that goes beyond a subjective assessment of what is "just" on any particular set of facts.<ref target="BAWE_0410b-ftnote.030"/> In <hi rend="italic">Trustor AB v Smallbone and Others</hi><ref target="BAWE_0410b-ftnote.031"/>, a managing director of a company transferred funds from the claimant company to a company owned and controlled by the managing director. </s><s n="s3.4;p14.24">In his judgment, Sir Andrew Morritt VC held that the court was entitled to pierce the corporate veil and recognise the receipt of the company as that of the individual if the company was used as a device or façade to conceal the true facts thereby avoiding or concealing any liability of those individuals.<ref target="BAWE_0410b-ftnote.032"/> Evidence of the intentions and motives of the controller of the company is also evidence that the use of the company structure is also evidence that the use of the company structure is a façade or sham. </s><s n="s4.4;p14.24">While channelling funds through a company will not be sufficient to prevent the controller of the company from incurring personal liability in equity for knowing receipted of those funds, where the company is deemed to be a façade, dishonestly constructed corporate arrangements designed to conceal both the true nature of assets and the true beneficiary of the exploitation of those assets, and furthermore to minimise the liability of that individual, provides a link between the impropriety and the façade to lift the corporate veil.<ref target="BAWE_0410b-ftnote.033"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0410b-ftnote.030"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.3;pn1.1">L. Linklater, "Piercing the Corporate Veil - The Never Ending Story", Comp. </s><s n="s2.3;pn1.1">Law. </s><s n="s3.3;pn1.1">2006, 27(3), 65-66 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0410b-ftnote.031"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">[2001] 1 W.L.R. 1177; <hi rend="italic">Trustor</hi> was recently applied in <hi rend="italic">Raja v Van Hoogstraten (Amendment to Particulars of Claim)</hi> [2006] EWHC 2564 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0410b-ftnote.032"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">See <hi rend="italic">Trustor</hi>, at [23]. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0410b-ftnote.033"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">For a further discussion on the intention and motives of the defendant in cases involving the lifting of the corporate veil and the differing attitudes of the courts to cases involving the use of the company structure to avoid existing and future liabilities, see G. Andrews, "The Veil of Incorporation - Fiction or Façade?", 4 Business Law Review, January 2004 </s></p></note><p n="p15.24"><s n="s1.4;p15.24">As can be seen, it is difficult to derive any specific guidelines from the decisions after <hi rend="italic">Adams</hi>. </s><s n="s2.4;p15.24">The only safe conclusion is that the boundaries of the façade ground are not certain.<ref target="BAWE_0410b-ftnote.034"/> However, one should note that the façade ground does not directly address the problems associated with corporate groups apart from recognizing its legitimate use. </s><s n="s3.4;p15.24">It merely distinguishes abuse by differentiating evasion of past liabilities or avoiding future obligations. </s><s n="s4.4;p15.24">Since most of the cases were settled out of court, there is no legal precedent that settles the issue concerning parental responsibility for the wrongs of subsidiaries apart from <hi rend="italic">Adams</hi>.<ref target="BAWE_0410b-ftnote.035"/> This provides little guidance on the problem of corporate groups. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0410b-ftnote.034"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.3;pn1.1">It has been suggested that "there is still room for claimants to test the boundaries in this area of law", see L. Linklater, "Piercing the Corporate Veil - The Never Ending Story", Comp. </s><s n="s2.3;pn1.1">Law. </s><s n="s3.3;pn1.1">2006, 27(3), 65-66 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0410b-ftnote.035"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.4;pn1.1">The Company Law Review Steering Group was unaware of cases where parent companies have engaged in abuse of limited liability. </s><s n="s2.4;pn1.1">However, Muchlinski counters this claim by explaining that most of the cases are settled out of court, see P. Muchlinski, "Holding Multinationals to Account", Comp. </s><s n="s3.4;pn1.1">Law. </s><s n="s4.4;pn1.1">2002, 23(6), 168, at 175.; see also A. Magaisa, "Corporate Groups and Victims of Corporate Torts - Towards a new Architecture of Corporate law in a Dynamic Marketplace" Corporate Law in a Dynamic Marketplace', Law, Social Justice &amp; Global Development Journal (LGD) 2002 (1), available at <seg type="URL" n="http://www2.warwick.ac.uk/fac/soc/law/elj/lgd/2002_1/magaisa/"/> (last visited, April 21, 2007) </s></p></note></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Is the current legal situation satisfactory? </head><p n="p16.24"><s n="s1.2;p16.24">It is appropriate to keep the entire legal situation in mind. </s><s n="s2.2;p16.24">Legislation deals with specific problems that have arisen by a variety of patchwork statutes, leaving ample scope for exploitation from corporate groups.<ref target="BAWE_0410b-ftnote.036"/> Courts have delivered ad hoc justice through mixed decisions and arguably by "peeping through the corporate veil".<ref target="BAWE_0410b-ftnote.037"/> Although the problems arising from corporate group structures have not been directly dealt upon, one must ask is this legal situation <hi rend="italic">really</hi> dissatisfactory? </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0410b-ftnote.036"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">See, M. Moore, "A temple built on fault foundations: Piercing the corporate veil and the legacy of Salomon v Salomon", Journal of Business Law, 2006, Mar, 180-203; A. Magaisa, "Corporate Groups and Victims of Corporate Torts - Towards a new Architecture of Corporate law in a Dynamic Marketplace" Corporate Law in a Dynamic Marketplace', Law, Social Justice &amp; Global Development Journal (LGD) 2002 (1), available at <seg type="URL" n="http://www2.warwick.ac.uk/fac/soc/law/elj/lgd/2002_1/magaisa/"/> (last visited, April 21, 2007) </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0410b-ftnote.037"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">R. Fletcher, "Lifting the veil of incorporation", Journal of the Institute of Legal Executives, 2 November 2001, available at <seg type="URL" n="http://www.ilexjournal.co.uk/legal_briefings/article.asp?theid=353&amp;themode=2"/> (last visited, April 21, 2007) </s></p></note><p n="p17.24"><s n="s1.2;p17.24">The court in <hi rend="italic">Adams</hi> answered in the negative, that the allocation of risks and quarantining potential liability within the corporate group is a legitimate use of group structure. </s><s n="s2.2;p17.24">Although it has also been suggested that the insistence by Slade L.J. upon the exclusivity of "sham" as the only general basis for piercing the corporate veil is understandable from a practical perspective,<ref target="BAWE_0410b-ftnote.038"/> it has been suggested that the court in <hi rend="italic">Adams</hi> was primarily motivated with the notion of avoiding a "tainted" US award.<ref target="BAWE_0410b-ftnote.039"/> Furthermore, others may have reservations regarding certain "sharp practices" of corporate groups.<ref target="BAWE_0410b-ftnote.040"/> This urges one to consider whether <hi rend="italic">Adams</hi> is valid from a policy point of view. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0410b-ftnote.038"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">M. Moore, "A temple built on fault foundations: Piercing the corporate veil and the legacy of Salomon v Salomon", Journal of Business Law, 2006, Mar, 180-203, at 184 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0410b-ftnote.039"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.3;pn1.1">For a discussion of jurisdictional issues in <hi rend="italic">Adams</hi>, see S. Nahal, "Business and Human Rights - UK Report", 2002, International Council on Human Rights Policy; see also P. Muchlinski, "Holding Multinationals to Account", Comp. </s><s n="s2.3;pn1.1">Law. </s><s n="s3.3;pn1.1">2002, 23(6), 168, at 173. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0410b-ftnote.040"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">M. Moore, "A temple built on fault foundations: Piercing the corporate veil and the legacy of Salomon v Salomon", Journal of Business Law, 2006, Mar, 180-203 </s></p></note><p n="p18.24"><s n="s1.2;p18.24">The question hinges upon one's view on the extent of protection offered to current "norms" of commercial reality concerning corporate groups. </s><s n="s2.2;p18.24">On one hand is the integrity and autonomy of the corporate form established in <hi rend="italic">Salomon</hi>; on the other is the public policy to curb the most economically harmful or morally reprehensible abuses of the corporate form by corporate groups.<ref target="BAWE_0410b-ftnote.041"/> In light of the entire legal situation, the law must strike the right balance between respecting the artificial entity of the company and achieving justice sought for by the claimants. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0410b-ftnote.041"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1"><hi rend="italic">Ibid</hi>, at 184 </s></p></note><p n="p19.24"><s n="s1.4;p19.24">One argument for upholding the doctrine of corporate personality is that creditors should "look after their own skin".<ref target="BAWE_0410b-ftnote.042"/> The doctrine is not mandatory and parties to a contract may opt out of it. </s><s n="s2.4;p19.24">Potential creditors should obtain guarantee from the parent company before dealing with the subsidiary. </s><s n="s3.4;p19.24">However, it is doubtful whether this demand is available to small creditors or involuntary creditors such as victims of tortuous conduct by the subsidiary. </s><s n="s4.4;p19.24">Little legislative protection is provided to these claimants.<ref target="BAWE_0410b-ftnote.043"/> By refusing to pierce the veil in such circumstances, the court in effect bars tort victims just compensation from the parent of an undercapitalized, tortuous subsidiary.<ref target="BAWE_0410b-ftnote.044"/> This is extrapolated in mass tort cases concerning extreme risks and tremendous harm done.<ref target="BAWE_0410b-ftnote.045"/> At least in these circumstances court intervention should be justified to lift the corporate veil by reason of public policy to protect the public from extreme hazards.<ref target="BAWE_0410b-ftnote.046"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0410b-ftnote.042"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">P.L. Davies, Gower and Davies' <hi rend="italic">Principles of Modern Company Law</hi>, (7th ed., Sweet and Maxwell, London, 2003), at 179 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0410b-ftnote.043"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.4;pn1.1">As mentioned above, the main provisions are the fraudulent trading provision (s.213 Insolvency Act 1986) and the wrongful trading provision (s.214 Insolvency Act 1986). </s><s n="s2.4;pn1.1">However, these provisions are difficult to establish in practice. </s><s n="s3.4;pn1.1">See S. Griffin, "Limited liability: a necessary revolution?", (2004) </s><s n="s4.4;pn1.1">Company Lawyer Vol.25(4), 99; see also P.L. Davies, Gower and Davies' <hi rend="italic">Principles of Modern Company Law</hi>, (7th ed., Sweet and Maxwell, London, 2003), Chapters 9 &amp; 10. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0410b-ftnote.044"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.3;pn1.1">For a discussion of the problem with the principle of limited liability in relation to involuntary creditors, see A. Ashwin, "Tortious liability of company in winding up: an analysis", Comp. </s><s n="s2.3;pn1.1">Law. </s><s n="s3.3;pn1.1">2005, 26(6), 163 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0410b-ftnote.045"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">See, for example, the Bhopal Gas Tragedy in India, where thousands of people died from the poisonous methyl isocyanate gas leaked from the Union Carbide pesticide factory in the city, S. Chakrabarti "20th anniversary of world's worst industrial disaster", The World Today - Friday, 3 December , 2004, <seg type="URL" n="http://www.abc.net.au/worldtoday/content/2004/s1257352.htm"/> (last visited April 21, 2007) </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0410b-ftnote.046"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.3;pn1.1">P. Muchlinski, "Holding Multinationals to Account", Comp. </s><s n="s2.3;pn1.1">Law. </s><s n="s3.3;pn1.1">2002, 23(6), 168, at 174. </s></p></note><p n="p20.24"><s n="s1.4;p20.24">Another argument for upholding the separate corporate personality is the "asset partitioning" rationale.<ref target="BAWE_0410b-ftnote.047"/> Although the separation of assets and liabilities is normally considered working against creditors of the subsidiary companies, the same creditors also obtain protection from the creditors of the shareholders of those subsidiary companies. </s><s n="s2.4;p20.24">In other words, separate corporate personality is a two-edged sword that also works to the benefit of creditors. </s><s n="s3.4;p20.24">While the asset partitioning rationale is certainly valid and worth considering, it is also arguably true that limited liability did not anticipate shareholders to be legal persons in the first place.<ref target="BAWE_0410b-ftnote.048"/> As mentioned on the outset, the primary rationale was to encourage investment from the public, not encourage investment from companies. </s><s n="s4.4;p20.24">It is arguable that a parent company should not be entitled to the same disparity in the risks and rewards as shareholders who are natural persons. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0410b-ftnote.047"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">P.L. Davies, Gower and Davies' <hi rend="italic">Principles of Modern Company Law</hi>, (7th ed., Sweet and Maxwell, London, 2003), at 178 - 179 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0410b-ftnote.048"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.3;pn1.1">P. Muchlinski, "Holding Multinationals to Account", Comp. </s><s n="s2.3;pn1.1">Law. </s><s n="s3.3;pn1.1">2002, 23(6), 168, at 174. </s></p></note><p n="p21.24"><s n="s1.3;p21.24">The corporate veil test is clearly not fair. </s><s n="s2.3;p21.24">While the legal position treats both types of shareholders, that is parent companies and natural persons, equally by providing the same legal protection, the different nature of the two works to favour corporate groups. </s><s n="s3.3;p21.24">The "agency" argument fails because the holding company-subsidiary relationship usually falls short of a full agency relationship.<ref target="BAWE_0410b-ftnote.049"/> The "single economic unit" argument<ref target="BAWE_0410b-ftnote.050"/> addresses this commercial reality, but the decision in <hi rend="italic">Adams</hi> seems to turn a blind eye to the different nature of shareholders and allows corporate groups to operate as single economic entities while enjoying partitioned liability as separate legal entities, including the practice of "quarantining risks". </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0410b-ftnote.049"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.4;pn1.1">In contrast, Canadian jurisprudence built upon the "agency" ruling in <hi rend="italic">Smith, Stone and Knight Ltd v Birmingham Corp</hi> [1939] 4 All E.R. 116, borrowing "quasi-agency" principles from American courts, to develop a new line of precedent in lifting the veil in corporate groups, see A. Hargovan &amp; J. Harris, "Piercing the corporate veil in Canada: A comparative analysis", Comp. </s><s n="s2.4;pn1.1">Law. </s><s n="s3.4;pn1.1">2007, 28(2), 58-62; see also J. Neyers, "Canadian Corporate Law, Veil-Piercing, and the Private Law Model Corporate", University of Toronto Law Journal, Volume L, Number 2, Spring 2000; S. Griffin, "Limited liability: a necessary revolution?" </s><s n="s4.4;pn1.1">(2004) Co Lawyer vol. 25(4), 99. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0410b-ftnote.050"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1"><hi rend="italic">DHN Food Distributors Ltd v Tower Hamlets LBC</hi> [1976] 1 W.L.R. 852, CA </s></p></note><p n="p22.24"><s n="s1.3;p22.24">Without clear guidance as to <hi rend="italic">when</hi> corporate group structures constitute a "mere façade", corporate groups are practically free to operate however they please. </s><s n="s2.3;p22.24">The effect of the current position is to allow corporate groups to shift risks to overpowered or involuntary creditors, thereby running serious risk of corporate groups "externalizing" liability in negligence. </s><s n="s3.3;p22.24">This runs contrary to recent calls for greater corporate social responsibility and is clearly not desirable.<ref target="BAWE_0410b-ftnote.051"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0410b-ftnote.051"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.3;pn1.1">P. Muchlinski, "Holding Multinationals to Account", Comp. </s><s n="s2.3;pn1.1">Law. </s><s n="s3.3;pn1.1">2002, 23(6), 168, at 178. </s></p></note></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Conclusion</head><p n="p23.24"><s n="s1.4;p23.24">In sum, the injustice arising from the problem of corporate groups outlined above is not just perceived, but in fact very real. </s><s n="s2.4;p23.24">Current legislative is inadequate to cover these foreseeable problems.<ref target="BAWE_0410b-ftnote.052"/> Courts have been unwilling to curb the apparent exploitation of the principles in <hi rend="italic">Salomon</hi> by corporate groups. </s><s n="s3.4;p23.24">These problems are more severe when one considers recent trends in commercial reality, namely the increasing variety of corporate structures, the growth of multinational conglomerates and an alleged high level of abuse of corporate structure. </s><s n="s4.4;p23.24">Hence, the legal situation is unsatisfactory form a policy point of view, particularly in light of the group structure of many modern businesses. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0410b-ftnote.052"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">S. Griffin, "Limited liability: a necessary revolution?" </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">(2004) Co Lawyer vol. 25(4), 99. </s></p></note><p n="p24.24"><s n="s1.3;p24.24">We have looked at the doctrine and the problems that have arisen with the emergence of corporate groups. </s><s n="s2.3;p24.24">Since the current legal situation essentially allows multinationals to shift risk to involuntary creditors, it is doubtful whether the law is valid from a policy point of view. </s><s n="s3.3;p24.24">In light of the current legal situation and its inadequacies, the case towards formulating a Law of Corporate Groups strong indeed.<ref target="BAWE_0410b-ftnote.053"/> Although the new Companies Act 2006 does not deal with this issue, there can only be room for improvement in the future. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0410b-ftnote.053"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.3;pn1.1">See A. Magaisa, "Corporate Groups and Victims of Corporate Torts - Towards a new Architecture of Corporate law in a Dynamic Marketplace" Corporate Law in a Dynamic Marketplace', Law, Social Justice &amp; Global Development Journal (LGD) 2002 (1), available at <seg type="URL" n="http://www2.warwick.ac.uk/fac/soc/law/elj/lgd/2002_1/magaisa/"/> (last visited, April 21, 2007); see also, P. Muchlinski, "Holding Multinationals to Account", Comp. </s><s n="s2.3;pn1.1">Law. </s><s n="s3.3;pn1.1">2002, 23(6), 168. </s></p></note></div1></body><back><div1 type="bibliography"><head rend="bold">Bibliography </head><p>P.L. Davies, Gower and Davies' <hi rend="italic">Principles of Modern Company Law</hi>, (7<hi rend="sup">th</hi> ed., Sweet and Maxwell, London, 2003)</p><p>S. Griffin, "Limited liability: a necessary revolution?", (2004) Company Lawyer Vol.25(4), 99</p><p>O. Shub "Separate Corporate Personality: Piercing the Corporate Veil", FDCC Quarterly, Winter 2006</p><p>I. Ramsay &amp; D. Noakes, "Piercing the Corporate Veil in Australia", (2001) 19 Company and Securities Law Journal 250-271.</p><p>M. Moore, "A temple built on fault foundations: Piercing the corporate veil and the legacy of Salomon v Salomon", Journal of Business Law, 2006, Mar, 180-203</p><p>P. Muchlinski, "Holding Multinationals to Account", Comp. Law. 2002, 23(6), 168.</p><p>L. Linklater, "Piercing the Corporate Veil - The Never Ending Story", Comp. Law. 2006, 27(3), 65-66</p><p>G. Andrews, "The Veil of Incorporation - Fiction or Façade?", 4 Business Law Review, January 2004</p><p>S. Nahal, "Business and Human Rights - UK Report", 2002, International Council on Human Rights Policy</p><p>A. Ashwin, "Tortious liability of company in winding up: an analysis", Comp. Law. 2005, 26(6), 163</p><p>A. Hargovan &amp; J. Harris, "Piercing the corporate veil in Canada: A comparative analysis", Comp. Law. 2007, 28(2), 58-62</p><p>J. Neyers, "Canadian Corporate Law, Veil-Piercing, and the Private Law Model Corporate", University of Toronto Law Journal, Volume L, Number 2, Spring 2000</p><p>A. Magaisa, "Corporate Groups and Victims of Corporate Torts - Towards a new Architecture of Corporate law in a Dynamic Marketplace" Corporate Law in a Dynamic Marketplace', Law, Social Justice &amp; Global Development Journal (LGD) 2002 (1), available at <seg type="URL" n="http://www2"/>.<name type="university"/>.ac.uk/fac/soc/law/elj/lgd/2002_1/magaisa/ (last visited, April 21, 2007)</p><p>G. V. Puig, "A Two-Edged Sword: Salomon and the Separate Legal Entity Doctrine", Murdoch University Electronic Journal of Law, Volume 7, Number 3 (September 2000), available at <seg type="URL" n="http://www.murdoch.edu.au/elaw/issues/v7n3/puig73a_text.html"/> (last visited April 21, 2007)</p><p>S. Chakrabarti "20th anniversary of world's worst industrial disaster", The World Today - Friday, 3 December , 2004, <seg type="URL" n="http://www.abc.net.au/worldtoday/content/2004/s1257352.htm"/> (last visited April 21, 2007)</p><p>R. Fletcher, "Lifting the veil of incorporation", Journal of the Institute of Legal Executives, 2 November 2001, available at <seg type="URL" n="http://www.ilexjournal.co.uk/legal_briefings/article.asp?theid=353&amp;themode=2"/> (last visited, April 21, 2007)</p></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
