<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_0415e" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Experiment 1: Touton's Rule and Cryogens</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">deleted: header: student name, date</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">1</p><p n="date">2002-01</p><p n="module title">Physical Lab</p><p n="module code">CH155</p><p n="genre family">Methodology recount</p><p n="discipline">Chemistry</p><p n="disciplinary group">PS</p><p n="grade">D</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">516</p><p n="number of s-units">25</p><p n="number of p">14</p><p n="number of tables">2</p><p n="number of figures">4</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">2</p><p n="number of lists">1</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">5</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">20.6</p><p n="average s-units per p">1.8</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">m</p><p n="year of birth">1983</p><p n="first language">English</p><p n="education">UKA</p><p n="course">Msc Chemistry</p><p n="student ID">0415</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><docTitle><titlePart rend="underlined bold">Experiment 1: Touton's Rule and Cryogens</titlePart></docTitle><titlePart>Date performed: 28 <hi rend="sup">th</hi> February 2003 Lab Partner: <name type="student name"/></titlePart></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">Aims:</head><p n="p1.14"><s n="s1.1;p1.14">To measure experimentally the enthalpy of vapourisation of liquid nitrogen (N <hi rend="sub">2</hi>), and that of solid carbon dioxide (CO <hi rend="sub">2</hi>) in order to test the validity of Trouton's Rule. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">Method:</head><p n="p2.14"><s n="s1.4;p2.14">The temperature of 1 dm <hi rend="sup">3</hi> of water in a Styrofoam igloo was measured until constant. </s><s n="s2.4;p2.14">A known amount of the cryogen was added directly and the temperature of the water measured every minute until there was no further temperature change due to the presence of the cryogen. </s><s n="s3.4;p2.14">The temperature of the nitrogen and carbon dioxide vapour evolved was measured using a thermocouple. </s><s n="s4.4;p2.14">The data obtained, along with the boiling points of nitrogen and carbon dioxide was used to calculate the entropy of vapourisation of both these substances. </s></p><p n="p3.14"><s n="s1.1;p3.14">A weighed mass CO <hi rend="sub">2</hi> of was used as follows: </s></p><list type="simple"><item><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0415e-form.001"/></item><item><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0415e-form.002"/></item></list><p n="p4.14"><s n="s1.2;p4.14">The liquid nitrogen could not be weighed accurately directly, so a cup filled to a mark was used to measure a volume of nitrogen. </s><s n="s2.2;p4.14">This volume was equivalent to a mass of water of 110.7 ±1.0g (This large uncertainty is due to the width of the mark). </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">Results</head><table id="BAWE_0415e-tab.001"><row><cell/></row></table><table id="BAWE_0415e-tab.002"><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p5.14"><s n="s1.1;p5.14">N.B. </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p6.14"><s n="s1.1;p6.14">1. * denotes negligible error (2.272 x10 <hi rend="sup">-5</hi> mol) </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p7.14"><s n="s1.2;p7.14">2. </s><s n="s2.2;p7.14">Heat capacities of each substance are found in the lab manual and are taken to have zero uncertainty. </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p8.14"><s n="s1.2;p8.14">3. </s><s n="s2.2;p8.14">The thermocouple reading of gaseous temperature is taken to have an uncertainty of ± 0.5K. </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p9.14"><s n="s1.2;p9.14">4. </s><s n="s2.2;p9.14">The boiling points of N <hi rend="sub">2</hi> and CO <hi rend="sub">2</hi> were taken as 77.0 ± 0.5 K and 194.5 ± 0.5K respectively. </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p10.14"><s n="s1.2;p10.14">5. </s><s n="s2.2;p10.14">The value of enthalpy of fusion of CO <hi rend="sub">2</hi> which needs to be taken into account to work out the enthalpy of vapourisation was taken as 7.94 kJ mol <hi rend="sup">-1</hi>, with zero uncertainty. </s></p><div2><head rend="underlined bold">Graphs used to calculate ∆T</head><figure id="BAWE_0415e-fig.001"><head rend="underlined bold">Graph plotting temperature against time for expt. 1 (Nitrogen)</head></figure><figure id="BAWE_0415e-fig.002"><head rend="underlined bold">Graph plotting temperature against time for expt. 2 (Nitrogen)</head></figure><figure id="BAWE_0415e-fig.003"><head rend="underlined bold">Graph plotting temperature against time for expt. 3 (Carbon Dioxode)</head></figure><figure id="BAWE_0415e-fig.004"><head rend="underlined bold">Graph plotting temperature against time for expt. 3 (Carbon Dioxode)</head></figure><p n="p11.14"/></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">Conclusions</head><p n="p12.14"><s n="s1.2;p12.14">The entropy of vapourisation of carbon dioxide was found to be, on average, 77.87 ± 7.11 JK <hi rend="sup">-1</hi>mol <hi rend="sup">-1</hi>, and that of nitrogen to be 77.66 ± 6.04 JK <hi rend="sup">-1</hi>mol <hi rend="sup">-1</hi>. </s><s n="s2.2;p12.14">These values are in agreement with Trouton's rule that states the entropy of vapourisation of most substances is approximately equal to 85 JK <hi rend="sup">-1</hi>mol <hi rend="sup">-1</hi> . </s></p><p n="p13.14"><s n="s1.4;p13.14">The apparatus used in the experiment is simpler than that which would be desirable to obtain fully accurate data. </s><s n="s2.4;p13.14">However, the uncertainties calculated show that the results were sufficiently accurate to agree with Trouton's rule. </s><s n="s3.4;p13.14">The major sources of uncertainty were the measurement of the volume of water used and the estimation of the temperature change, which at best could only be made to the nearest half-degree. </s><s n="s4.4;p13.14">An accurate thermocouple measurement of the liquid would have been more desirable. </s></p><p n="p14.14"><s n="s1.1;p14.14">The temperature of the gaseous cryogen should have been measured for each experiment, as the amount of cryogen used in each was significantly different (especially for CO <hi rend="sub">2</hi>) to give a large difference in the amount of energy taken out of the water, and hence seriously affect the overall result. </s></p></div1></body><back/></text></TEI.2>
