<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_0415j" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Single atoms are the miniature building blocks that might just be the next big thing in nanotechnology.</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">PowerPoint document (two slides)</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">4</p><p n="date">2006-05</p><p n="module title">Electro and Nanotechnology</p><p n="module code">CH406</p><p n="genre family">Critique</p><p n="discipline">Chemistry</p><p n="disciplinary group">PS</p><p n="grade">D</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">1088</p><p n="number of s-units">47</p><p n="number of p">16</p><p n="number of tables">0</p><p n="number of figures">3</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">0</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">0</p><p n="abstract present">abstract present</p><p n="average words per s-unit">23.1</p><p n="average s-units per p">2.9</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">m</p><p n="year of birth">1983</p><p n="first language">English</p><p n="education">UKA</p><p n="course">Msc Chemistry</p><p n="student ID">0415</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><docTitle><titlePart rend="bold">Single atoms are the miniature building blocks that might just be the next big thing in nanotechnology</titlePart></docTitle><titlePart rend="bold"><name type="student name"/></titlePart></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="abstract"><p n="p1.16"><s rend="bold" n="s1.3;p1.16">Using an STM (Scanning Tunneling Microscope) tip as an engineering tool has made it possible to manufacture structures on an atomic-scale. </s><s rend="bold" n="s2.3;p1.16">These STM manipulations are at the cutting edge of nanotechnology today, representing one of the greatest scientific achievements in the last twenty years. </s><s rend="bold" n="s3.3;p1.16">We take a look into the future of science fact. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><p n="p2.16"><s n="s1.3;p2.16">Using STM manipulation techniques it is possible to construct quantum structures on an atom by atom basis. </s><s n="s2.3;p2.16">Single molecules can be synthesized on a one molecule at a time basis, and detailed physical or chemical properties of atoms and molecules, which are impossible to achieve with other experimental measurements, can be detected at an atomic level. </s><s n="s3.3;p2.16">So how do these manipulations work? </s></p><p n="p3.16"><s n="s1.5;p3.16">A Scanning Tunnelling Microscope is based entirely around a tip that is sharp enough for interactions to occur at just a single atom on a surface. </s><s n="s2.5;p3.16">The tip is brought close to the target atom then moved laterally across the surface before being removed and leaving the atom in its new location. </s><s n="s3.5;p3.16">A voltage-induced electrostatic attractive or repulsive force is used to pull or push the atom around the surface. </s><s n="s4.5;p3.16">STM is used for this because it allows for more accurate placement of the tip than any other technique that is available. </s><s n="s5.5;p3.16">This accuracy is based on the very precise tunnelling current between the tip and the surface. </s></p><p n="p4.16"><s n="s1.1;p4.16">So what is this tunnelling current? </s></p><p n="p5.16"><s n="s1.2;p5.16">Tunnelling occurs when electrons travel past the edges of a material and through an insulator due to their wave behaviour. </s><s n="s2.2;p5.16">Similar to light travelling through paper held up to the sun, these electrons can bridge the gap between the atom and the tip provided the separation distance is small enough (or the paper is very thin to continue the analogy). </s></p><p n="p6.16"><s n="s1.3;p6.16">This STM tunnelling current is really useful because it provides a narrow source of electrons. </s><s n="s2.3;p6.16">A conventional electron beam used in TEM (Transmission Electron Microscopy) cannot be focused with such precision. </s><s n="s3.3;p6.16">This means we can tunnel electrons into or out of just a single molecule, allowing us to analyse them individually and, at least in principle, control their chemical reactions. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Chemistry we can see (with the aid of STM)</head><p n="p7.16"><s n="s1.5;p7.16">Sexiphenyl is a molecule composed of six benzene type rings connected together to form a linear chain. </s><s n="s2.5;p7.16">A single molecule of sexiphenyl can be deposited on an atomically flat silver (Ag) surface. </s><s n="s3.5;p7.16">At temperatures just above absolute zero (-273.15°C), the sexiphenyl is weakly bound to the surface. </s><s n="s4.5;p7.16">This comparatively large molecule can be dragged along the surface by using the STM tip in a pulling mode, and when the tip was retracted and stopped interacting with the sexiphenyl, the molecule carries on moving along the surface for nearly 30nm. </s><s n="s5.5;p7.16">A way to physically 'shoot' molecules across a surface has been discovered! </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0415j-pic.001"/><p n="p8.16"><s n="s1.1;p8.16">On such a small scale, problems can occur when defects in the silver surface produce random electron patterns which interact with the sexiphenyl molecule causing its path to deviate randomly from a straight line. </s></p><p n="p9.16"><s n="s1.5;p9.16">To overcome this effect, two parallel 'walls' of silver atoms can be positioned on the surface. </s><s n="s2.5;p9.16">Breaking up the surface with the STM tip at a remote site is used to provide the silver atoms for these walls. </s><s n="s3.5;p9.16">The walls create a uniform electronic environment in the area between them. </s><s n="s4.5;p9.16">Sexiphenyl could now be shot in a guaranteed straight line on this 'runway' between the walls. </s><s n="s5.5;p9.16">Two Ag atoms placed at the end of the runway can act as targets and the shooting of sexiphenyl molecules can be tested. </s></p><p n="p10.16"><s n="s1.1;p10.16">The molecules of sexiphenyl move by tortional twisting of the rings in an action similar to a caterpillar, and when they reach the silver atom a chemical reaction takes place combining the two. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0415j-pic.002"/><p n="p11.16"><s n="s1.4;p11.16">Studies later showed that sexiphenyl had wrapped itself around the silver atom which now sat in the middle of one of the phenyl rings. </s><s n="s2.4;p11.16">This was ground-breaking research because it showed the versatility of STM. A controlled chemical reaction had been conducted on the single molecule scale over a very small surface area. </s><s n="s3.4;p11.16">In the future it is possible that several computer controlled STM tips could work on the same assembly line, bringing in chemicals, reacting them, and collecting the products. </s><s n="s4.4;p11.16">Controlled engineering on this scale is the dream of every scientist working in nanotechnology. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Chemistry we can see (albeit in a few year's time)</head><p n="p12.16"><s n="s1.4;p12.16">Computers currently work with silicon transistor technology and are fast approaching a scale that they cannot go under. </s><s n="s2.4;p12.16">This has lead to the search for an alternative technique to allow for the ever increasing demand for miniature electronics. </s><s n="s3.4;p12.16">For computation to be achieved a set of two possibilities has to exist, in binary for example this is 0 and 1, but it can be other things. </s><s n="s4.4;p12.16">Recently it can be shown that mechanical computation, where a physical change in position represents the two possible states, can be performed on a truly nanometre scale. </s></p><p n="p13.16"><s n="s1.3;p13.16">It is possible to produce a cascade of hops, or position changes by arranging carbon monoxide (CO) molecules in staggered chains on a copper surface. </s><s n="s2.3;p13.16">This cascade can be initiated by moving a "trigger" CO molecule toward another CO molecule creating a repulsive force. </s><s n="s3.3;p13.16">This next CO molecule then spontaneously moves away, dissipating the repulsive force but creating it in another position, and so on for a cascade of any length. </s></p><p n="p14.16"><s n="s1.3;p14.16">This molecular cascade propagates forward in a very consistent fashion because the energy of the system as a whole is lowered each time a molecule moves to a new site on the surface. </s><s n="s2.3;p14.16">If this was not the case and the energy of the system increased or stayed the same then the movements would be in a random direction and the propagation of the movement would be slow and haphazard as a result. </s><s n="s3.3;p14.16">It is possible to race the cascade with the STM tip to the position F (see below) and then watch the last CO molecule moving to its final resting position to show this is definitely occurring. </s></p><p n="p15.16"><s n="s1.3;p15.16">This technology has been used to make a one time logic gate. </s><s n="s2.3;p15.16">It included several AND gates and OR gates which were connected by a branching system of cascades. </s><s n="s3.3;p15.16">So this technique is on the way to a computer near you, but you would only be able to use it once, and only at -270°C! </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0415j-pic.003"/><p n="p16.16"><s n="s1.1;p16.16">We have seen a few of the exciting things that can be done with STM. From single molecule engineering to applications for computer circuitry, STM will ensure that atomic manipulations really are the next big thing in nanotechnology. </s></p></div1></body><back><div1 type="bibliography"><head rend="bold">Further reading</head><p>An excellent review : Hla, S.-W., <hi rend="italic">J. Vac. Sci. Technol. B, </hi><hi rend="bold">2005</hi>, <hi rend="italic">23(4),</hi> 1351.</p><p>Molecular cascades: Eigler, D. M.; Heinrich, A.J., <hi rend="italic">Science</hi>, <hi rend="bold">2002</hi>, <hi rend="italic">298</hi>, 1381.</p><p>Single molecule manipulation: Hla, S.-W.; Braun, K.-F., <hi rend="italic">Phys. Rev. Lett</hi>., <hi rend="bold">2004</hi>, <hi rend="italic">93</hi>, 208302.</p><p>Identification and manipulation of molecules with STM: Komeda, T., <hi rend="italic">Prog. Surf. Sci., </hi><hi rend="bold">2005</hi>, <hi rend="italic">78</hi>, 41.</p></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
