<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_0415d" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Display Technology: From fast electrons to fast oils.</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">laid out as journal article</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">3</p><p n="date">2005-01</p><p n="module title">Materials Science</p><p n="module code">CH3D1</p><p n="genre family">Case study</p><p n="discipline">Chemistry</p><p n="disciplinary group">PS</p><p n="grade">D</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">4301</p><p n="number of s-units">173</p><p n="number of p">34</p><p n="number of tables">0</p><p n="number of figures">9</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">0</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">0</p><p n="abstract present">abstract present</p><p n="average words per s-unit">24.9</p><p n="average s-units per p">5.1</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">m</p><p n="year of birth">1983</p><p n="first language">English</p><p n="education">UKA</p><p n="course">Msc Chemistry</p><p n="student ID">0415</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><docTitle><titlePart rend="bold">Display Technology: From fast electrons to fast oils. </titlePart></docTitle><titlePart><hi rend="bold"><name type="student name"/></hi><hi rend="italic"><name type="student name"/>, Department Of Chemistry,</hi> <hi rend="italic"> University Of <name type="university"/>,</hi> <hi rend="italic"><name type="other"/><name type="other"/></hi><hi rend="bold"> Received Date (will be automatically inserted after manuscript is accepted)</hi></titlePart></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="abstract"><head rend="bold">ABSTRACT</head><figure id="BAWE_0415d-pic.001"/><p n="p1.34"><s rend="bold" n="s1.2;p1.34">This report provides a review of current display technologies, highlights recent research of the established technologies, and identifies new methods of display that will be used in the near future for the display of static and video information. </s><s rend="bold" n="s2.2;p1.34">Traditional Cathode Ray Tube and Liquid Crystal Displays are likely to be replaced in the future by displays based on electrowetting. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><p n="p2.34"><s n="s1.11;p2.34">It was J. J. </s><s n="s2.11;p2.34">Thomson who in 1897 refined Crooke's vacuum tube from twenty years earlier into the Cathode Ray Tube (CRT). </s><s n="s3.11;p2.34">The phenomenon of phosphorescence had been used solely as a method of detection of electron beams; but in 1931 the first CRT television sets were commercially available. </s><s n="s4.11;p2.34">These represented the first modern method of displaying moving images. </s><s n="s5.11;p2.34">Television sets produced today are based on the same principle. </s><s n="s6.11;p2.34">Electrons produced from a heated cathode filament by thermionic emission are accelerated through a vacuum tube towards the viewing end (anode). </s><s n="s7.11;p2.34">Electromagnets are used to deflect the beam to scan the surface at the viewing end which is coated with a phosphorescent material. </s><s n="s8.11;p2.34">Modern television sets use different materials which specifically emit red, green, and blue light, closely packed together in strips, and three electron guns which fire specifically at each type of phosphor. </s><s n="s9.11;p2.34">A shadow mask consisting of tiny holes in a metal plate prevent each gun hitting the wrong phosphor. </s><s n="s10.11;p2.34">Thus a raster scan of the entire front end of the set allows a full colour picture to be produced by modulating the intensity of the electron beam according to the video signal. </s><s n="s11.11;p2.34">Television sets made using this technology have been highly successful and only recently have other technologies been competing in the display market. </s></p><p n="p3.34"><s n="s1.4;p3.34">CRT displays have several disadvantages that are overcome in part by newer technologies. </s><s n="s2.4;p3.34">They are essentially bulky, heavy and large in size to accommodate the vacuum tube and electron gun and they operate traditionally on an analogue input signal. </s><s n="s3.4;p3.34">Any still image projected onto the screen for an extended period can be 'burnt' into the screen as certain clusters of phosphor are used more than others. </s><s n="s4.4;p3.34">Liquid Crystal Displays (LCDs) were the first to offer a solution to these problems providing a thin and lightweight alternative. </s></p><p n="p4.34"><s n="s1.11;p4.34">LCD technology took its greatest step forward in 1969 when J. Fergason presented an improved LCD which became the basis of modern displays of this type. </s><s n="s2.11;p4.34">Essentially it consisted of a light-polarising liquid crystal material trapped in cells between two transparent polarising sheets arranged perpendicularly to each other. </s><s n="s3.11;p4.34">In the relaxed state before an electric field is applied, incoming light is polarised by the first sheet which encourages the liquid crystal medium to polarise parallel to the light polarisation direction of the sheets. </s><s n="s4.11;p4.34">Between the sheets, the molecules twist naturally between the two perpendicular extremes. </s><s n="s5.11;p4.34">Light is polarised by one sheet, rotated through the smooth twisting of the crystal molecules, then passes through the second sheet. </s><s n="s6.11;p4.34">The assembly looks nearly transparent but some light is lost by the first polarisation sheet. </s><s n="s7.11;p4.34">On application of an electric field across a region of the cell, the molecules align themselves with the electric field thus inhibiting rotation of the polarised light. </s><s n="s8.11;p4.34">All light is absorbed and the cell appears black. </s><s n="s9.11;p4.34">A pair of thin layers of glass impregnated with Indium Tin Oxide (ITO) electrodes allow only certain segments of the cell to be affected by the electric field, producing the desired pattern on the display. </s><s n="s10.11;p4.34">A colour display can be made using an LCD pixel divided into three sections each with a different colour filter. </s><s n="s11.11;p4.34">Any colour can be produced by varying the relative brightness of the three coloured sections. </s></p><p n="p5.34"><s n="s1.10;p5.34">However there are limitations to this type of device. </s><s n="s2.10;p5.34">Small LCDs known as passive displays have one electrical contact per segment. </s><s n="s3.10;p5.34">As the size of the display increases, this becomes unwieldy and a passive matrix structure is adopted which uses one set of contacts per column or row of pixels. </s><s n="s4.10;p5.34">Only one pixel can be addressed at any one time, so the pixel must remember its state until it can be addressed again by the circuit. </s><s n="s5.10;p5.34">This makes the display of video material problematic as the display will respond badly to fast moving images. </s><s n="s6.10;p5.34">To solve this problem a matrix of Thin-Film Transistors (TFTs) are incorporated into the display which remember the electrical state of each pixel and maintain this until the pixel is re-addressed. </s><s n="s7.10;p5.34">This active matrix system allows video to be displayed with only little distortion. </s><s n="s8.10;p5.34">Now more commonly referred to as TFT displays, this technology is present in modern computer monitors and handheld television devices. </s><s n="s9.10;p5.34">The limitations of TFT displays are that of their narrow viewing angle, poor contrast and slow pixel response times. </s><s n="s10.10;p5.34">Research is underway into overcoming these problems - new liquid crystals and composites of liquid crystal elastomers and conductive polymers are being modelled and synthesised at the Liquid Crystal Institute<ref target="BAWE_0415d-endnote.001"/> in Ohio. </s></p><note place="end" id="BAWE_0415d-endnote.001"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Liquid Crystal Institute, Kent State University, <seg type="URL" n="http://www.lci.kent.edu/research.html"/> </s></p></note><p n="p6.34"><s n="s1.7;p6.34">Another limitation of LCD displays is that they require a backlight to allow the user to see the display. </s><s n="s2.7;p6.34">For small appliances this light, generally a cold cathode fluorescent lamp, tends to take up more than 60% of the battery power. </s><s n="s3.7;p6.34">This light is found along the side of the display and a light guide is used to spread the intensity uniformly over the display. </s><s n="s4.7;p6.34">A typical light guide is made from acrylic, with diffusing white dots on the bottom surface to help evenly distribute the light over the top of the display; a reflective sheet to avoid optical loss at the back of the display, and a diffusing sheet to eliminate the images of the diffusing dots. </s><s n="s5.7;p6.34">In short, a lot of light intensity is lost. </s><s n="s6.7;p6.34">A group at Keio University in Japan have been working on a highly efficient back-light guide that uses none of the above optical films but a series of microprisms at the bottom surface which reflect incident light to the top of the display with a high optical efficiency. </s><s n="s7.7;p6.34">They have demonstrated that spherical micron sized particles of (CH3SiO1.5)n in a poly(methylmethacrylate) matrix diffuse light effectively; and have optimised the microprism geometry by computer simulation to produce a guide that is more efficient than any other produced using standard technology<ref target="BAWE_0415d-endnote.002"/>. </s></p><note place="end" id="BAWE_0415d-endnote.002"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.6;pn1.1">T. Okumura; A. Tagaya. </s><s rend="italic" n="s2.6;pn1.1">Mol. </s><s rend="italic" n="s3.6;pn1.1">Cryst. </s><s rend="italic" n="s4.6;pn1.1">Liq. </s><s n="s5.6;pn1.1"><hi rend="italic">Cryst</hi>. </s><s n="s6.6;pn1.1"><hi rend="bold">2004</hi>, 418, 299-313. </s></p></note><p n="p7.34"><s n="s1.8;p7.34">Plasma Display Panels (PDPs) solve some of the problems associated with LCDs and maintain some advantages over CRT technology. </s><s n="s2.8;p7.34">The display essentially consists of millions of small 'gas-discharge tubes' several millimetres in depth. </s><s n="s3.8;p7.34">Electrons are accelerated between electrodes in the discharge cell. </s><s n="s4.8;p7.34">Electrons of appropriate energy collide and excite inert gas molecules which decay back to their ground state releasing UV radiation. </s><s n="s5.8;p7.34">The UV photons stimulate phosphors at the front of the cell to emit visible light. </s><s n="s6.8;p7.34">For colour reproduction, a triad of plasma cells containing red, blue and green phosphors is used. </s><s n="s7.8;p7.34">In order to vary the light intensity of each colour cell and thus produce an arbitrary colour, the voltage across the colour cell is not changed but the length of time that the cell is on during one frame is altered. </s><s n="s8.8;p7.34">Since the eye response time is less than that of the television display frequency, it perceives different colours depending on how long each cell of the triad is on. </s></p><p n="p8.34"><s n="s1.5;p8.34">To allow fast moving video and high definition colour to be displayed UV radiation must be prevented from passing between cells and interacting with the wrong phosphor. </s><s n="s2.5;p8.34">A honeycomb structure of cells separated by barrier ribs is used minimise this problem. </s><s n="s3.5;p8.34">The switching of cells on and off efficiently and cheaply has only recently been possible due to the miniaturisation of electronics. </s><s n="s4.5;p8.34">The cells respond to the applied voltage within a millionth of a second which allows a passive matrix system to be used. </s><s n="s5.5;p8.34">Displays can thus be made up to 80 inches in diameter without any picture quality loss. </s></p><p n="p9.34"><s n="s1.5;p9.34">PDPs present the display market with a large, thin, high definition display which has a wide viewing angle thus overcomes one of the main drawbacks of TFT screens. </s><s n="s2.5;p9.34">However the drawbacks of PDPs must be addressed if they are to compete with new display technologies. </s><s n="s3.5;p9.34">They are relatively expensive to produce, hugely power consuming and have a limited lifetime. </s><s n="s4.5;p9.34">Research is underway at Fujitsu, Samsung and other manufacturers into increasing the energy efficiency of the displays and designing plasma cells which maintain emission intensity for longer<ref target="BAWE_0415d-endnote.003"/>.One example of the research carried out this year is the development of new methods for processing photosensitive films which are used to produce the electrodes and barrier ribs between the cells. </s><s n="s5.5;p9.34">The cells are produced by photolithography (figure 1) - a photosensitive paste is deposited on the backing substrate, a mask with the required pattern is held over the paste and on UV irradiation the masked areas polymerise setting solid and producing the barrier ribs. </s></p><note place="end" id="BAWE_0415d-endnote.003"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Fujitsu laboratories, Plasma display panel research, <seg type="URL" n="http://www.labs.fujitsu.com/en/theme/display/PDP/PDP.html"/> </s></p></note><figure id="BAWE_0415d-pic.002"><head><hi rend="bold">Figure 1</hi> . Ultraviolet radiation is allowed to reach the photosensitive paste only in defined areas which causes in situ polymerisation of the photosensitive paste forming barrier ribs for PDPs.</head></figure><p n="p10.34"><s n="s1.1;p10.34">Y. Igucghi <hi rend="italic">et al</hi>. have been working on ways of increasing the amount of light transmitted through the photomask that travels in a 'straight' line thus producing more defined cells and making the process quicker and more efficient (Figure 2) <ref target="BAWE_0415d-endnote.004"/>. </s></p><note place="end" id="BAWE_0415d-endnote.004"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.5;pn1.1">Y. Iguchi; T. Masaki <hi rend="italic">.</hi> </s><s rend="italic" n="s2.5;pn1.1">Bull. </s><s rend="italic" n="s3.5;pn1.1">Chem. </s><s rend="italic" n="s4.5;pn1.1">Soc. </s><s n="s5.5;pn1.1"><hi rend="italic">Jpn</hi>., <hi rend="bold">2004</hi>, 77, 1613 - 1625. </s></p></note><figure id="BAWE_0415d-pic.003"><head><hi rend="bold">Figure 2.</hi> Cross sectional SEM images of barrier ribs <hi rend="bold">. (a)</hi> shows the shape of barrier ribs formed by photolithography using a simple metal photomask and <hi rend="bold">(b)</hi> shows the results of improving the ratio of straight light transmission using the same photomask. </head></figure><p n="p11.34"><s n="s1.6;p11.34">Another technology in which manufacturers are heavily investing research resources is that of Light Emitting Diode (LED) displays. </s><s n="s2.6;p11.34">An LED consists of a thin film of semiconductor sandwiched between two electrodes. </s><s n="s3.6;p11.34">On application of a voltage, electrons from the cathode and 'holes' from the anode travel into the semiconductor and recombine producing a photon of light. </s><s n="s4.6;p11.34">Modern LEDs essentially consist of six layers: a glass substrate, a transparent anode (made from ITO), a hole transporting layer, an emissive layer (semiconductor), an electron transport layer and a cathode. </s><s n="s5.6;p11.34">Conventional LEDs are made from inorganic materials such as aluminium gallium arsenide (AlGaAs), which emits in the red and far infrared region. </s><s n="s6.6;p11.34">The material used for the pn junction dictates the wavelength of light that is emitted. </s></p><p n="p12.34"><s n="s1.3;p12.34">Organic compounds are likely to replace semiconductors in LED devices in the near future. </s><s n="s2.3;p12.34">These promise to be cheaper to produce and large arrays of them can be deposited using simple printing methods. </s><s n="s3.3;p12.34">They have the added advantage of such displays being lightweight, being able to offer a high degree of resolution, and, if semiconducting polymers are used, being flexible. </s></p><p n="p13.34"><s n="s1.7;p13.34">Small molecule Organic Light Emitting Diodes (OLEDs) are efficient at generating light but harder to produce than Polymer LEDs (PLEDs), however PLEDs have traditionally been much less efficient in generating light. </s><s n="s2.7;p13.34">For inorganic LEDs, there is strong spin-orbit coupling and so intersystem crossing is very efficient and the emissive state has a high 'triplet state' content. </s><s n="s3.7;p13.34">For small molecule OLEDs and PLEDs, intersystem crossing is not so common, leading to the triplet:singlet ratio of excited states being held at 3:1 (This is due to there being three triplet states for each singlet state). </s><s n="s4.7;p13.34">As only the singlet states can decay radiatively, the maximum efficiency of such a device is 25%. </s><s n="s5.7;p13.34">The introduction of triplet emitters into the polymer layer increases the maximum theoretical efficiency of the LED to 100%. </s><s n="s6.7;p13.34">Improving the efficiency of PLEDs in this way is an active area of research. </s><s n="s7.7;p13.34">An international collaboration of researchers have developed a carbaxole-oxadiazole copolymer based on 9,9- dialkyl-[3,3]-bicarbazolyl (see figure 3) which when doped with an iridium triplet emitter allows triplet emissions at 2.6eV - levels similar to that for hosts in small molecule OLEDs<ref target="BAWE_0415d-endnote.005"/>. </s></p><note place="end" id="BAWE_0415d-endnote.005"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.4;pn1.1">A van Dijken, J. Bastiaansen. </s><s rend="italic" n="s2.4;pn1.1">J. Am. </s><s rend="italic" n="s3.4;pn1.1">Chem. </s><s n="s4.4;pn1.1"><hi rend="italic">Soc</hi>., <hi rend="bold">2004</hi>, 126, 7718. </s></p></note><figure id="BAWE_0415d-pic.004"><head><hi rend="bold">Figure 3. (a)</hi> The structure of the carbazole homopolymer. <hi rend="bold">(b)</hi> A schematic energy level diagram showing the singlet ground state (S <hi rend="sub">0</hi> ), singlet and triplet excited states (S <hi rend="sub">1</hi> ) and (T <hi rend="sub">1</hi> ) of the polymer, and the relative energy transition of the iridium triplet emitter. </head></figure><p n="p14.34"><s n="s1.4;p14.34">Research is also underway into finding the most efficient method for producing PLEDs. </s><s n="s2.4;p14.34">Inkjet printing is a common way of transferring electronic data to paper, but in recent years its versatility has led to the method being investigated to print polymer layers for PLEDs. </s><s n="s3.4;p14.34">Inkjet printing allows minute amounts of materials to be accurately deposited on a substrate. </s><s n="s4.4;p14.34">In 1999, a multi-colour active matrix PLED display was produced using an Epson Stylus II printer depositing a poly(phenylene vinylene) precursor between barrier ribs created by photolithography (see section on PDPs)<ref target="BAWE_0415d-endnote.006"/>. </s></p><note place="end" id="BAWE_0415d-endnote.006"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.3;pn1.1">T. Shimoda, S. Kanbe, <hi rend="italic">Soc.</hi> </s><s rend="italic" n="s2.3;pn1.1">Info. </s><s n="s3.3;pn1.1"><hi rend="italic">Disp</hi>., <hi rend="bold">1999</hi>, 376. </s></p></note><p n="p15.34"><s n="s1.2;p15.34">Successful inkjet printing of poly(vinyl carbazole) with a molecular weight of 1.110 <hi rend="sup">-6</hi>Da has been performed; and the technique has been used to fabricate thin film transistors and the circuits based thereon<ref target="BAWE_0415d-endnote.007"/>. </s><s n="s2.2;p15.34">In short, inkjet printing offers manufacturers an efficient way of producing PLEDs and looks to be the best method of depositing polymer for full colour displays. </s></p><note place="end" id="BAWE_0415d-endnote.007"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.3;pn1.1">B. de Gans; P. Duineveld <hi rend="italic">, U. S.</hi> </s><s rend="italic" n="s2.3;pn1.1">Schubert Adv. </s><s n="s3.3;pn1.1"><hi rend="italic">Mat,</hi> <hi rend="bold">2003</hi>, vol. 6 issue 3, 203-213. </s></p></note><p n="p16.34"><s n="s1.1;p16.34">Now we come to two technologies that if developed appropriately may well supplant all other in the display market: they are innovative and hold much potential for widespread use. </s></p><p n="p17.34"><s n="s1.8;p17.34">Electrophoresis is traditionally used as a method of separating mixtures. </s><s n="s2.8;p17.34">The application of an electric field across a solution will cause each type of molecule to travel toward a particular electrode with a speed dependant on the molecules' electronic charge and size. </s><s n="s3.8;p17.34">Thus, if a collection of stable charged microparticles in a clear liquid medium inside a cell are exposed to an external electric field, the particles will migrate toward the appropriate electrode. </s><s n="s4.8;p17.34">A bistable collection of back and white oppositely charged particles will be separated on introduction of an electric field. </s><s n="s5.8;p17.34">Thus a monochrome reflective display can be created. </s><s n="s6.8;p17.34">Among the many applications this technology would suit, 'electronic paper' appears the most feasible. </s><s n="s7.8;p17.34">This is a thin, lightweight and flexible display that has the same optical characteristics as paper and allows material to be displayed that can be updated electronically. </s><s n="s8.8;p17.34">The first active matrix working display was produced by the company E-Ink, in April 2001<ref target="BAWE_0415d-endnote.008"/>. </s></p><note place="end" id="BAWE_0415d-endnote.008"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">E-Ink Corporation, 733 Concord Avenue Cambridge; MA 02138. <seg type="URL" n="http://www.eink.com/news/releases/pr52.html"/> </s></p></note><figure id="BAWE_0415d-pic.005"><head><hi rend="bold">Figure 4. (a)</hi> The principle of the electrophoretic display showing one capsule containing the microparticles. When a potential difference is applied, here the white particles move toward the anode making the capsule appear white.<hi rend="bold"> (b)</hi> Photographs of one capsule with the applied electric field in opposing directions.</head></figure><p n="p18.34"><s n="s1.7;p18.34">B. Comiskey and J. D. Albert worked on improving the resolution of this type of display. </s><s n="s2.7;p18.34">In their system, white microcapsules were created by atomisation of a suspension of titanium dioxide in polyethylene. </s><s n="s3.7;p18.34">Black particles were created the same way using an inorganic black dye. </s><s n="s4.7;p18.34">The particles where then dispersed in an organic solvent mixture, and prevented from coagulating by providing a polymeric adsorbed layer on the surface of each particle which provided the necessary inter-particle repulsive force. </s><s n="s5.7;p18.34">This suspension was emulsified into an aqueous phase and encapsulated by condensation of formaldehyde and urea to form a polymer <hi rend="italic">in situ</hi> to form optically transparent microcapsules which were filtered to obtain particles of 40 micrometer diameter. </s><s n="s6.7;p18.34">A capsule size of 4010 micrometer allowed a resolution of approximately 600 dots per inch (figure 5). </s><s n="s7.7;p18.34">A higher resolution of about 1,200 dots per inch was realised by using a set of thinner upper electrodes using the same capsule diameter<ref target="BAWE_0415d-endnote.009"/>. </s></p><note place="end" id="BAWE_0415d-endnote.009"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">B. Comisky; J. Albert, <hi rend="italic">Nature</hi>,<hi rend="bold"> 1998</hi>, 394, 253 - 255. </s></p></note><figure id="BAWE_0415d-pic.006"><head><hi rend="bold">Figure 5.</hi> Photographs of the letter 'K' addressed by an electrophoretic display. Capsules used here were 4010 micrometer in diameter.</head></figure><p n="p19.34"><s n="s1.7;p19.34">One of the biggest problems faced in producing a large display using this method is that in order to effectively address a large number of pixels, a passive or active matrix system must be used. </s><s n="s2.7;p19.34">The problem is that unlike an LED that has a threshold voltage needed to address the electronic state of the pixel, electrophoretic displays will respond to any current. </s><s n="s3.7;p19.34">This prevents lower voltages being used by the control circuit to switch to which pixel it needs to address. </s><s n="s4.7;p19.34">Active matrix systems are also traditionally expensive to produce and reduce considerably the flexibility of the display. </s><s n="s5.7;p19.34">In 2002 an international team managed to circumvent this problem. </s><s n="s6.7;p19.34">They exploited the fact that the switching characteristics of an electrophoretic cell are not a linear function of the applied voltage. </s><s n="s7.7;p19.34">By appropriate application of AC and DC fields at particular times they produced a working passive matrix display (figure 6)<ref target="BAWE_0415d-endnote.010"/>. </s></p><note place="end" id="BAWE_0415d-endnote.010"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">T. Bert; G. van Steenberg, presented at Eurodisplay conference, Nice <hi rend="bold">2002</hi>. </s></p></note><figure id="BAWE_0415d-pic.007"><head><hi rend="bold">Figure 6.</hi> Photograph of a 57 matrix display, demonstrating the passive matrix driving of an electrophoretic display.</head></figure><p n="p20.34"><s n="s1.1;p20.34">Displays have been made using this technology that have a high resolution, a high pixel density, are less than 0.3mm thick and can be bent to a radius of curvature of 1.5cm without any degradation in the display properties<ref target="BAWE_0415d-endnote.011"/>. </s></p><note place="end" id="BAWE_0415d-endnote.011"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Y. Chen; J. Au, <hi rend="italic">Nature</hi>, <hi rend="bold">2003</hi>, 423, 136 </s></p></note><p n="p21.34"><s n="s1.5;p21.34">A desirable property of such a display is that one might retain a displayed image when the power to the cell is turned off. </s><s n="s2.5;p21.34">A charged toner is electrostatically adsorbed onto the electrode when the voltage is applied exposing the majority of the white backing layer. </s><s n="s3.5;p21.34">The cell appears white. </s><s n="s4.5;p21.34">An opposing electrical field pulls the toner to the other electrode causing a more uniform distribution of toner over the cell and thus the cell appears black. </s><s n="s5.5;p21.34">Research into cells that effectively remember there colour state is being conducted at Canon<ref target="BAWE_0415d-endnote.012"/>. </s></p><note place="end" id="BAWE_0415d-endnote.012"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Cannon research laboratories - <seg type="URL" n="http://www.canon.com/technology/detail/device/pl_display/index.html"/> </s></p></note><p n="p22.34"><s n="s1.4;p22.34">A variation on this type of display is the Reverse Emulsion Electrophoretic Display (REED) developed by the US company Zirkon<ref target="BAWE_0415d-endnote.013"/>. </s><s n="s2.4;p22.34">A reverse emulsion, as the name suggests, is a typical emulsion but the orientation of the surfactant is opposite to that in water (figure 7(a)). </s><s n="s3.4;p22.34">A microemulsion (droplets in the order of several nanometer) is used for the display as a standard emulsion is not thermodynamically stable and prone to degradation. </s><s n="s4.4;p22.34">The structures of the components used in the emulsion are shown in figure 7 (b). </s></p><note place="end" id="BAWE_0415d-endnote.013"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">The REED display: Zikon Corp, 3859 Rincon Ave, Campbell, CA. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">95008 </s></p></note><figure id="BAWE_0415d-fig.001"><head><hi rend="bold">Figure 7. (a)</hi> The Reverse emulsion used in the REED display. The surfactant molecules are orientated in the opposite direction to that commonly found in oil/water emulsions. <hi rend="bold">(b)</hi> The components of the reverse emulsion</head></figure><p n="p23.34"><s n="s1.2;p23.34">A hydrophilic coloured dye can be introduced into the droplet. </s><s n="s2.2;p23.34">An appropriate applied electric field will cause the polar phase to spread out through the volume of the pixel, resulting in a coloured display, or contracted into microscopic droplets which give the pixel a transparent appearance. </s></p><p n="p24.34"><s n="s1.5;p24.34">Several methods of addressing the display have been developed. </s><s n="s2.5;p24.34">The emulsion responds differently to electric fields alternating different frequencies. </s><s n="s3.5;p24.34">It is speculated that when an electric field is applied, the micelles self-assemble into 'supermicellar' structures imposing a periodic distribution of micelles throughout the emulsion. </s><s n="s4.5;p24.34">Figure 8 shows the effect of different frequencies on the micelle structure within the cell. </s><s n="s5.5;p24.34">Those driven at 10Hz and 10000Hz appear transparent to the naked eye. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0415d-pic.008"><head><hi rend="bold">Figure 8.</hi> Optical photographs of reverse emulsion. The field of view is 600x400 micron. From top left clockwise, an emulsion driven at 10Hz; 100Hz; 1000Hz and 10000Hz. </head></figure><p n="p25.34"><s n="s1.2;p25.34">A full colour display can be made by stacking three monochrome displays with different filters in the subtractive CYMK colour scheme on top of each other. </s><s n="s2.2;p25.34">A REED display as such has all of the advantages of an electrophoretic display but is more highly transmissive and it has potential for use as a multicolour display. </s></p><p n="p26.34"><s n="s1.3;p26.34">Recent developments in the area of voltage induced wetting, or electrowetting have brought this technology to the forefront of display technology research. </s><s n="s2.3;p26.34">Electrophoretic systems are suitable for applications such as electronic-paper, but due to trade off between response time and contrast, the display of high definition video material is not possible. </s><s n="s3.3;p26.34">Electrowetting has been shown not only to be a suitable technology to use in this area<ref target="BAWE_0415d-endnote.014"/>, but with it comes many advantages such as reflectivity and contrast that will promote its use in the near future as a leading display technology. </s></p><note place="end" id="BAWE_0415d-endnote.014"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">R.A. Hayes; B. J. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">Feenstra, <hi rend="italic">Nature</hi>,<hi rend="bold"> 2003</hi>, 425, 383-385 </s></p></note><p n="p27.34"><s n="s1.2;p27.34">Electrowetting is the phenomenon whereby an electric field can modify the wetting behaviour of a droplet in contact with an insulated electrode. </s><s n="s2.2;p27.34">If the electric field is applied non-uniformly then a surface free energy gradient is created which can be used to manipulate a droplet sandwiched between two plates. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0415d-fig.002"><head><hi rend="bold">Figure 9. (a)</hi> A schematic of an electrowetting cell <hi rend="bold">. (b)</hi> An applied voltage causes the oil droplet to decrease its contact area with the hydrophobic insulator.<hi rend="bold"> (c)</hi> When no potential is applied, the cell appears red.<hi rend="bold"> (d)</hi> The cell appears transparent after the potential has been applied</head></figure><p n="p28.34"><s n="s1.8;p28.34">Figure 9(a) shows the basic construction of a single display pixel. </s><s n="s2.8;p28.34">The display is of the reflective type - light entering the front of the cell is reflected to the viewer by the backing white substrate. </s><s n="s3.8;p28.34">At equilibrium, the coloured oil spreads itself evenly over the hydrophobic surface (usually a fluoropolymer) to minimise interfacial tension. </s><s n="s4.8;p28.34">Due to the small size of the system, these interfacial forces dominate over gravitational forces and so the oil droplet is stable in all orientations. </s><s n="s5.8;p28.34">When an electric field is applied across the hydrophobic layer, the balanced interfacial forces are overcome by an electrostatic term. </s><s n="s6.8;p28.34">The system lowers its free energy by increasing the contact area between insulator and water, displacing the oil droplet (figure 9(b)). </s><s n="s7.8;p28.34">The hydrophobic effect prevents the oil droplet from bursting. </s><s n="s8.8;p28.34">If a pixel is made as such with a small enough size, the eye will interpret the relaxed state as a red pixel and the electrified state as a white pixel. </s></p><p n="p29.34"><s n="s1.6;p29.34">Roques-Carmes <hi rend="italic">et al</hi>. investigated the switching dynamics of an electrowetting cell<ref target="BAWE_0415d-endnote.015"/>. </s><s n="s2.6;p29.34">A cell was constructed of a white PET backing layer with implanted ITO electrodes to form the base; black PET for the cell walls and a non-polar dye dissolved in C <hi rend="sub">10</hi> - C <hi rend="sub">16</hi> alkanes for the oil. </s><s n="s3.6;p29.34">The area of white PET visible after the electric field had been applied was measured as a function of applied voltage; and the on and off response times (time for the area of white PET to become constant after the field is applied) were measured as a function of cell size using different depths of oil film (figure 10). </s><s n="s4.6;p29.34">The change in white area percentage as a function of time was shown to be potential dependent. </s><s n="s5.6;p29.34">Above 22.5V, the response time was shown to be less than 40ms which due to experimental limitations was the limit to the speed which could be observed. </s><s n="s6.6;p29.34">This demonstrates the speed of on-switching is adequate for video display. </s></p><note place="end" id="BAWE_0415d-endnote.015"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">T. Roques-Carmes; R A. Hayes, <hi rend="italic">J. App.</hi> </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1"><hi rend="italic">Phys</hi>., <hi rend="bold">2004</hi>, 95, number 8 </s></p></note><p n="p30.34"><s n="s1.5;p30.34">It was shown that off-switching or relaxation times were governed by capillary forces alone. </s><s n="s2.5;p30.34">A major factor that determines the speed of electrowetting is the curvature of the oil/water interface. </s><s n="s3.5;p30.34">When increasing the oil film thickness or decreasing the pixel size, the oil film curvature needed to cover a certain percentage of white substrate increases. </s><s n="s4.5;p30.34">Thus, the capillary forces become stronger and a greater voltage is needed to achieve oil contraction. </s><s n="s5.5;p30.34">Therefore careful consideration of pixel size, oil film thickness and oil type needs to be done to obtain an optimal off-switching speed necessary for a video display. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0415d-fig.003"><head><hi rend="bold">Figure 10.</hi> Electrowetting cell on-switching response times measured as a function of applied potential; cell size; and oil type. In the legend C10H22 refers to decane, C12H26 to dodecane, C14H30 to tetradecane, and C16H34 to hexadecane. 1mm refers to a cell of area 1mm <hi rend="sup">2.</hi> Lines are drawn to guide the eye</head></figure><p n="p31.34"><s n="s1.9;p31.34">The electrowetting principle can be used to make full colour displays. </s><s n="s2.9;p31.34">If a second oil is introduced into the top of the cell each oil layer can be switched independently. </s><s n="s3.9;p31.34">By using a colour filter on top of each cell and subtractive colour dyes, an arbitrary colour can be displayed. </s><s n="s4.9;p31.34">Figure 11(a) shows a schematic of the cell design. </s><s n="s5.9;p31.34">Figure 11 shows the working display. </s><s n="s6.9;p31.34">Here electrodes only occupy half the top and bottom of a 2mm cell with a magenta dye in the first oil layer and a cyan dye in the second. </s><s n="s7.9;p31.34">In the relaxed state the pixel appears in one state (figure 11(b)); when both films are contracted the pixel appears as in the electrified state (also figure 11(b)). </s><s n="s8.9;p31.34">With a yellow filter above this pixel, the relaxed state shown would appear black, and the electrified state yellow. </s><s n="s9.9;p31.34">Independent contraction of the oil layers in this way will produce the desired colour. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0415d-pic.009"><head><hi rend="bold">Figure 11. (a)</hi> The construction of a multicolour electrowetting display. <hi rend="bold">(b)</hi> A 2mm wide working display with magenta and cyan dye in the same cell. The first image shows the relaxed state with no applied potential; the second shows both oil layers contracted to produce a white pixel.</head></figure><p n="p32.34"><s n="s1.3;p32.34">The use of electrowetting for colour video displays is an attractive option. </s><s n="s2.3;p32.34">Its reflectivity is four times higher than that of a colour LCD and twice as high as other emerging reflective technologies. </s><s n="s3.3;p32.34">Video response speed has now been decreased to &lt;10ms; the display boasts high colour brightness, good contrast, the possibility of high resolution and low power consumption. </s></p><p n="p33.34"><s n="s1.6;p33.34">There are some problems that have not been highlighted by J. Feenstra or T. Roques-Carmes. </s><s n="s2.6;p33.34">Although interfacial forces are sufficient to overcome gravitational forces in keeping the oil droplets in place inside the cell, any other forced movement of the display could lead to the oils mixing with each other which would render the display useless. </s><s n="s3.6;p33.34">The author asks can the oils be separated irreversibly within the same cell? </s><s n="s4.6;p33.34">Is Ostwald ripening sufficient to keep the oil droplet together after the pixel has been switched a million times? </s><s n="s5.6;p33.34">How significant are impurities inside the pixel for the lifetime of the display? </s><s n="s6.6;p33.34">Before this type of display is mass produced these problems will need to be addressed. </s></p><p n="p34.34"><s n="s1.3;p34.34">The aim of this report was to provide the reader with a review of current display technologies, highlight active areas of research, and identify the methods of display that will be used in the near future. </s><s n="s2.3;p34.34">The positions of CRT, Liquid Crystal, Organic LED and Plasma panel displays have been described in relevance to desirable properties of modern display. </s><s n="s3.3;p34.34">Electrophoretic displays have been shown to be an area of interest for applications such as electronic paper, and electrowetting has been shown to be a very attractive technology that will undoubtedly have an input to the display market in the near future. </s></p></div1></body><back><div1 type="back text"><head><hi rend="bold">Acknowledgments</hi> . </head><p>The author thanks <name type="other"/><hi rend="italic">et al</hi>. at Philips research laboratories for their input into this report; Canon research laboratories for the use of graphics; the companies E-ink and Zirkon for making their research publicly available; the University of <name type="university"/> for use of computer facilities and finally <name type="other"/> for his encouragement and support.</p><p><hi rend="bold">Supporting information</hi> accompanies this report on CD-ROM. Contact the author for multiple copies.</p></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
