<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_0417d" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>The Reality of Buying Dreams: The Global Sex Chain of Filipino Mail Order Brides</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">Language used in quote: <foreign id="English">English</foreign></note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">deleted: header: student name and number, assignment title; footer: page numbers</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">4</p><p n="date">unknown</p><p n="module title">unknown</p><p n="module code">LA964</p><p n="genre family">Critique</p><p n="discipline">Law</p><p n="disciplinary group">SS</p><p n="grade">unknown</p><p n="number of authors">unknown</p><p n="number of words">3079</p><p n="number of s-units">113</p><p n="number of p">23</p><p n="number of tables">0</p><p n="number of figures">0</p><p n="number of block quotes">2</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">0</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">0</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">27.2</p><p n="average s-units per p">4.9</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">f</p><p n="year of birth">1980</p><p n="first language">English</p><p n="education">OSA</p><p n="course">International development law and human rights</p><p n="student ID">0417</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><docTitle><titlePart>The Reality of Buying Dreams: The Global Sex Chain of Filipino Mail Order Brides</titlePart></docTitle></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="section"><p n="p1.23"><s n="s1.7;p1.23">The mail order bride industry is a global commodity chain, and the product is the mail order bride, marketed through a variety of media, but principally now through the internet. </s><s n="s2.7;p1.23">The consumer is (generally) Western men who are seeking an international marriage for a variety of reasons. </s><s n="s3.7;p1.23">The marketer/distributor is International Marriage Agencies. </s><s n="s4.7;p1.23">It can also be argued that a secondary actor in the distribution of mail order brides is States themselves, through their domestic policies. </s><s n="s5.7;p1.23">This paper will focus one specific mail order bride commodity chain: Filipina women as the product, with Japanese, American and Canadian men as buyers. </s><s n="s6.7;p1.23">The first section of this paper will examine all elements of the commodity chain. </s><s n="s7.7;p1.23">The second section will discuss some of the gendered social and economic effects of the mail order bride industry. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">SECTION I: THE COMMODITY CHAIN</head><quote lang="English"><hi rend="italic">"She's a player in an international meat market ... She knows what she's doing ... except now and then when something really bad happens."</hi><ref target="BAWE_0417d-ftnote.001"/></quote><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0417d-ftnote.001"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Lana Mobydeen, <hi rend="italic">Something Old, Something New, Something Borrrowed, Something Mail-Ordered?</hi> </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1"><hi rend="italic">The Mail-Order Bride Industry and Immigration Law</hi> (2004) 49 Wayne Law Review 939 at 942. </s></p></note><div2><head rend="underlined bold">The Product: Mail Order Brides</head><p n="p2.23"><s n="s1.5;p2.23">Women who become Mail Order Brides (MOB) may do so for a multitude of reasons. </s><s n="s2.5;p2.23">The prominent reason for emigration is that the women are seeking a more prosperous life elsewhere. </s><s n="s3.5;p2.23">Tied into this traditional reason for emigrating are socio-cultural reasons unique to women. </s><s n="s4.5;p2.23">Women may also have a romanticized view of the men in the country of destination, due in part largely to stereotypes that are fostered by the mail order industry. </s><s n="s5.5;p2.23">"The purpose behind the perpetuation of these stereotypes is to convince clients that they are getting a higher quality of mate than they could find in their home country." <ref target="BAWE_0417d-ftnote.002"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0417d-ftnote.002"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid. </s></p></note><p n="p3.23"><s n="s1.6;p3.23">The way potential MOB are portrayed by the mail order industry is fairly universal. </s><s n="s2.6;p3.23">The industry caters to what is perceived as the antithesis to Western women. </s><s n="s3.6;p3.23">MOB are characterized as docile, subservient and eager to assume the role of the traditional "housewife". </s><s n="s4.6;p3.23">Men have claimed that the feminist movement is one of the main reasons for seeking an international bride. </s><s n="s5.6;p3.23">Using the U.S. as an example, "there is displeasure among American men that American women are not content as wives and mothers, but rather seek personal fulfillment through their own careers and interests. </s><s n="s6.6;p3.23">Foreign women are thought to be happy as homemakers and mothers serving the interests of their husbands." <ref target="BAWE_0417d-ftnote.003"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0417d-ftnote.003"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid. at 943. </s></p></note></div2><div2><head rend="underlined bold">The Consumer: Western Men</head><p n="p4.23"><s n="s1.8;p4.23">A pre-Internet survey "by David Jedlicka found that the men participating in these relationships were generally white, highly educated, politically and ideologically conservative, and generally economically and professionally successful." </s><ref target="BAWE_0417d-ftnote.004"/><s n="s2.8;p4.23">There is a tendency for consumers to be significantly older then the MOB and for them to have had previous marriages. </s><s n="s3.8;p4.23">The concern for many human rights groups is that with the presumption that consumers will be obtaining a woman that is subordinate and docile, there is an equated presumption that they are seeking a woman to dominate. </s><s n="s4.8;p4.23">Many of the consumers "feel empowered by the number of women they have to choose from when using mail-order bride agencies... </s><s n="s5.8;p4.23">The man usually has his pick of extremely young and beautiful women that he might not were he trying to court women in his native country." </s><ref target="BAWE_0417d-ftnote.005"/><s n="s6.8;p4.23">Given the proven psychological link between male domestic violence abusers and insecurity and low self-esteem, there is obvious reason for the concern that consumers attracted to the MOB industry are those that fall into the category of potential abusers. </s><s n="s7.8;p4.23">"While no national [American] figures exist on abuse of alien wives, there is every reason to believe that the incidence is higher in this population than for the nation as a whole. </s><s n="s8.8;p4.23">Authorities agree that abuse in these marriages can be expected based on the men's desire for a submissive wife..." <ref target="BAWE_0417d-ftnote.006"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0417d-ftnote.004"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid. at 942. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0417d-ftnote.005"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid. at 943. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0417d-ftnote.006"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Robert J. Scholes <hi rend="italic">, Appendix A [to International Matchmaking Organizations: A Report to Congress (February 1999)]: The "Mail-Order Bride" Industry and its Impact on U.S. Immigration</hi>, Immigration and Naturalization Service (1999), online: U.S. Citizenship and Immigration Services &lt;<seg type="URL" n="http://www.uscis.gov/files/article/MobRept_AppendixA.pdf"/>> Accessed on April 25, 2007 </s></p></note></div2><div2><head rend="underlined bold">The Distributor/Marketer: The International Marriage Agencies</head><p n="p5.23"><s n="s1.1;p5.23">There is limited information about International Marriage Agencies (IMA), and with the advent and explosion of the internet, a limited number of marriage agencies have become a booming industry. </s></p><p n="p6.23"><s n="s1.4;p6.23">Historically, IMA were designed to match up individuals of similar cultures, generally when the male spouse had emigrated to a country where there were few women of his culture. </s><s n="s2.4;p6.23">The process was often called the "picture bride" system (from the catalogues of women advertised). </s><s n="s3.4;p6.23">However, in the new millennium, the focus of the industry has dramatically shifted, creating an industry that "is based on a 'different structure, a different focus, and different consequences than the traditional picture bride system.' </s><s n="s4.4;p6.23">Many social and legal implications of the mail-order bride industry were absent from its picture bride counterpart."<ref target="BAWE_0417d-ftnote.007"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0417d-ftnote.007"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Supra note 5 at 940. </s></p></note><p n="p7.23"><s n="s1.3;p7.23">The mail order bride industry of today is powerful and, absent a few exceptions, completely unregulated. </s><s n="s2.3;p7.23">Years after the advent of the Internet, there are still no known statistics for how many IMA exist, either on the Internet or otherwise. </s><s n="s3.3;p7.23">Very few countries are even able to track how many MOB arrive in Western destination countries via international marriage agencies. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined bold">The Secondary Actors: the State Legal Structures that Regulate the Chain</head><p n="p8.23"><s n="s1.3;p8.23">The legal structures surrounding the MOB industry are principally in the area of immigration law. </s><s n="s2.3;p8.23">There has been little success in regulating the MOB industry as an economic entity. </s><s n="s3.3;p8.23">The two exceptions to this are the Anti Mail Order Bride legislation and the International Marriage Broker Regulation Act. </s></p><div3><head rend="underlined">Philippines Anti Mail Order Bride Legislation</head><p n="p9.23"><s n="s1.2;p9.23">In 1990, the Philippine government passed legislation to prohibit Philippine women from participating or being coerced into mail order marriages. </s><s n="s2.2;p9.23">The law was enacted as a result of public pressure and declares all actions affiliated with the mail order bride transaction to be unlawful, including banning any person or company from matching Filipinas with foreign nationals.<ref target="BAWE_0417d-ftnote.008"/> The law also includes a ban on the soliciting of Filipina women by marriage agencies and states punishments for both Filipino and foreign nationals. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0417d-ftnote.008"><p n="pn1.2"><s n="s1.2;pn1.2">The LawPhil Project, <hi rend="italic">An Act to Declare Unlawful the Practice of Matching Filipino Women for Marriage to Foreign Nationals on a Mail Order Basis and Other Similar Practices, including the Advertisement, Publication, Printing or Distribution of Brochures, Fliers and Other Propaganda Materials in Furtherance thereof and Providing Penalty Therefore</hi>, Republic Act No. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.2">6955, online: &lt;<seg type="URL" n="http://www.lawphil.net/"/>> </s></p><p n="pn2.2"><s n="s1.1;pn2.2">Accessed on April 25, 2007 </s></p></note><p n="p10.23"><s n="s1.2;p10.23">Since its adoption, the Anti-Mail Order Bride legislation has had little effect in stemming the flood of agencies recruiting Filipino women. </s><s n="s2.2;p10.23">Even if the legislation could be updated in a manner that could target the elusive online nature of the IMA, there is little likelihood of the government having the resources to enforce the legislation, or the will where such enforcement would negatively affect the significant remittances resulting from MOB transactions. </s></p></div3><div3><head rend="underlined">American Legislation - International Marriage Broker Regulation Act</head><p n="p11.23"><s n="s1.7;p11.23">The International Marriage Broker Regulation Act of 2005 (IMBRA) was enacted under Violence Against Women and Department of Justice Reauthorization act of 2005. </s><s n="s2.7;p11.23">It was drafted as one of the only attempts made so far to regulate International Marriage Agencies. </s><s n="s3.7;p11.23">The main focus of IMBRA is controlling the information that is disseminated by the IMA. IMBRA seeks to control underage marriages by prohibiting the transfer of personal information of females under the age of 18 to a potential consumer by an IMA. The IMA is obligated to collect a consumer's personal information, disseminate it to the MOB, provide the MOB with information about her legal rights as a US immigrant, and obtain the consent of a MOB to release of her personal information to the consumer. </s><s n="s4.7;p11.23">One interesting aspect of IMBRA is that it compels the US Office of Homeland Security to develop a database that tracks multiple applications for a K-visa (visa for fiancé(e))<ref target="BAWE_0417d-ftnote.009"/>. </s><s n="s5.7;p11.23">This is particularly important since a number of the MOB who have experienced domestic violence were not the first MOB that the abuser had married. </s><s n="s6.7;p11.23">This database is likely one of the most effective aspects of the legislation as it can be monitored and enforced domestically, and is not therefore subject to the myriad of difficulties in policing internationally held web-based companies. </s><s n="s7.7;p11.23">IMBRA also modifies the manner in which K-visas are processed and establishes penalties for marriage brokers that violate the Act.<ref target="BAWE_0417d-ftnote.010"/> IMBRA obligates the Office of Homeland Security to conduct a study of international marriages in the US and their correlation with domestic violence to be produced by April of 2009. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0417d-ftnote.009"><p n="pn1.2"><s n="s1.1;pn1.2"><hi rend="italic">Immigration and Nationality Act</hi>, 214, I.N.A.C. §214 (1952), online: U.S. Citizenship and Immigration Services &lt;<seg type="URL" n="http://www.uscis.gov/propub/ProPubVAP.jsp?dockey=baeb6daf5705c4f8629f8b6ea9f7c64d"/>> </s></p><p n="pn2.2"><s n="s1.1;pn2.2">Accessed on April 25, 2007 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0417d-ftnote.010"><p n="pn1.2"><s n="s1.1;pn1.2">U.S. Bill, H.R. 3657, <hi rend="italic">International Marriage Broker Regulation Act of 2005</hi>, 109th Cong., 2005, (enacted), online: Library of Congress &lt;<hi rend="underlined"><seg type="URL" n="http://thomas.loc.gov/cgi-bin/bdquery/z?d109"/>:HR03657:@@@T</hi>> </s></p><p n="pn2.2"><s n="s1.1;pn2.2">Accessed April 25, 2007 </s></p></note></div3><div3><head rend="underlined">Japanese Legislation</head><p n="p12.23"><s n="s1.8;p12.23">The situation for MOB in Japan is very precarious. </s><s n="s2.8;p12.23">Japanese immigration has effectively managed to limit the ability of international spouses to obtain citizenship, and the <hi rend="italic">Claim for the Revocation of a Decision Not to Permit the Change of the Status for a Sojourn in Japan - 1999</hi><ref target="BAWE_0417d-ftnote.011"/> has cemented this limitation. </s><s n="s3.8;p12.23">In Japan, whether an international spouse can retain their residency after divorce turns on the type of visa they hold. </s><s n="s4.8;p12.23">If they hold a spouse visa, which is the likely visa for a MOB, "divorce means that this status will be revoked and this particular type of visa cannot be renewed. </s><s n="s5.8;p12.23">A Spouse Visa is valid for either a one or three year period and can be used after divorce until it expires ... </s><s n="s6.8;p12.23">For those holding a Spouse Visa, the presence or absence of children is a key element in deterring the new residency status." </s><ref target="BAWE_0417d-ftnote.012"/><s n="s7.8;p12.23">The structure of the Spouse Visa limits the options of women in situations of domestic violence, for if they initiate divorce proceedings, there is a strong likelihood of the result being eventual deportation. </s><s n="s8.8;p12.23">"Even if the wife has adjusted well to life in Japan and invested a lot of her life's energy in building up friends and relationships, she faces possible ejection from Japan due to her husband's misdeeds and no wrong doing on her part." <ref target="BAWE_0417d-ftnote.013"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0417d-ftnote.011"><p n="pn1.2"><s n="s1.1;pn1.2"><hi rend="italic">Claim for the Revocation of a Decision Not to Permit the Change of the Status for a Sojourn in Japan - 1999</hi> (Gyo-Hi) No.46 [2002] JPSC 46 (17 October 2002), online: Asianlii.org, &lt;<seg type="URL" n="http://www.asianlii.org/jp/cases/JPSC/2002/46.html"/>> </s></p><p n="pn2.2"><s n="s1.1;pn2.2">Accessed on April 25, 2007 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0417d-ftnote.012"><p n="pn1.2"><s n="s1.1;pn1.2">J. Sean Curtin, <hi rend="italic">International Marriages in Japan: Part One - Visa status of non-Japanese spouses in 2002</hi>, online: Glocom Platform: Japanese Institute of Global Communications &lt;<seg type="URL" n="http://www.glocom.org/special_topics/social_trends/20021028_trends_s13/index.html"/>> </s></p><p n="pn2.2"><s n="s1.1;pn2.2">Accessed on April 25, 2007 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0417d-ftnote.013"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid. </s></p></note></div3><div3><head rend="underlined">Canadian Legislation </head><p n="p13.23"><s n="s1.9;p13.23">Canadian immigration law was completely revamped in 2002 with the creation of the Immigration and Refugee Protection Act (IRPA). </s><s n="s2.9;p13.23">While the immigration of MOB to Canada is slightly more advantageous than other developed countries, there are still problems with the legislation. </s><s n="s3.9;p13.23">"Immigration law provides that the fiancé(e) must prove to the visa officer that he or she is free to marry, that he or she is over the minimum age to be married in Canada and that marriage is not solely for the purpose of immigration. </s><s n="s4.9;p13.23">He or she is then given the permanent resident status on the understanding that the marriage will take place within 90 days of arrival." </s><ref target="BAWE_0417d-ftnote.014"/><s n="s5.9;p13.23">Once the couple is married, the foreign spouse's permanent residency is independent of her relationship with the Canadian spouse. </s><s n="s6.9;p13.23">While this is obviously better than the pre-IRPA legislation, which tied a foreign spouse to their sponsoring partner for 10 years, it still presents difficulties for women. </s><s n="s7.9;p13.23">For example, if women are abused within the 90-day period before the marriage, they will be deported if they leave their future spouse. </s><s n="s8.9;p13.23">This can pose incredible difficulties for women who are culturally limited in terms of their reputation if they end the engagement and return to their home country. </s><s n="s9.9;p13.23">Additionally, there have been grave difficulties for immigrant spouses who have been socially isolated by their Canadian spouse and are not aware that their immigration status is no longer tied to their Canadian spouse's after the marriage. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0417d-ftnote.014"><p n="pn1.3"><s n="s1.1;pn1.3">Centre de recherche interuniversitaire de Montréal sur </s></p><p n="pn2.3"><s n="s1.1;pn2.3">l'immigration, l'intégration et la dynamique urbaine, <hi rend="italic">Precarious Immigration Status, Dependency and Women's Vulnerability to Violence: Impacts on their Health</hi>, online: Centre for Applied Family Studies &lt;<seg type="URL" n="http://im.metropolis.net/research-policy/research_content/doc/Version_ang_PDF.pdf"/>> </s></p><p n="pn3.3"><s n="s1.1;pn3.3">Accessed on April 25, 2007 </s></p></note></div3></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">SECTION 2: THE GENDER IMPLICATIONS OF THE COMMDITY CHAIN</head><quote lang="English"><hi rend="italic">"Heaven is an American salary, an English country home, a Japanese chef, and a Chinese wife. Hell is a Chinese salary, an English chef, a Japanese home and an American wife."</hi><ref target="BAWE_0417d-ftnote.015"/></quote><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0417d-ftnote.015"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Nicole Constable, <hi rend="italic">Romance on a Global Stage: Pen Pals, Virtual Ethnography, and "Mail Order" Marriages</hi>, (London: University of California Press, Ltd., 2003) at 145. </s></p></note><div2><head rend="underlined bold">Feminist Discourse on Mail Order Brides</head><p n="p14.23"><s n="s1.7;p14.23">Within feminist discourse on the issue, there are diametrically opposing views on why women become mail order brides and how mail order brides should be "classified". </s><s n="s2.7;p14.23">There are those who take the view that "sex tourism, mail-order-brides and prostitution are variations on the theme of sexual exploitation." </s><ref target="BAWE_0417d-ftnote.016"/><s n="s3.7;p14.23">A report by the Coalition Against Trafficking Against Women states that "the trade in mail-order-brides is a form of trafficking in women. </s><s n="s4.7;p14.23">Bride trafficking enables men from wealthier countries to seek and acquire women from impoverished countries or those in economic crisis." </s><ref target="BAWE_0417d-ftnote.017"/><s n="s5.7;p14.23">However, there are many feminists who take the opposing view. </s><s n="s6.7;p14.23">They believe that while it cannot be denied that women who become MOB originate from developing countries with weakened and gendered economic and social structures, it is an economic decision made of (relatively) free choice on the part of the women who participate in the MOB industry. </s><s n="s7.7;p14.23">This view recognizes that many MOB face risks of personal violence as a result of gendered power structures, but believes that to class MOB as "victims" or worse, "prostitutes" disempowers them. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0417d-ftnote.016"><p n="pn1.2"><s n="s1.1;pn1.2">Donna M. Hughes <hi rend="italic">, Pimps and Predators on the Internet-Globalizing the Sexual Exploitation of Women and Children [Part 16 of 16]</hi>, University of Rhode Island, online: &lt;<seg type="URL" n="http://www.uri.edu/artsci/wms/hughes/ppcpt1.htm"/>> </s></p><p n="pn2.2"><s n="s1.1;pn2.2">Accessed on April 25, 2007 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0417d-ftnote.017"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid. </s></p></note><p n="p15.23"><s n="s1.8;p15.23">The concern with the "exploitation" view is that it undermines the power of the women as individuals to make choices and have their choices respected. </s><s n="s2.8;p15.23">As stated by Nicole Constable in her critique of the exploitation view, "assuming that Asian women are objects who are bought and sold, that their culture is traditional and unchanging ... [robs] women of their ability to express intelligence, resistance, creativity, independence, dignity and strength." </s><ref target="BAWE_0417d-ftnote.018"/><s n="s3.8;p15.23">However, the assumption that all women participating in the mail order bride industry make their choice freely and unhampered by gendered constructs is naïve. </s><s n="s4.8;p15.23">The fact remains that some women are trafficked into prostitution after agreeing to a mail order bride transaction. </s><s n="s5.8;p15.23">Likewise, a number of mail order brides experience personal violence as a result of their marital transaction. </s><s n="s6.8;p15.23">These facts cannot be denied. </s><s n="s7.8;p15.23">There is a need for a new understanding of mail order brides: one that respects the mail order bride's personal decisions, but also recognizes the need for support for mail order brides and an awareness of the personal dangers they face. </s><s n="s8.8;p15.23">The solution lies in policing the risks women face, rather than the women's decisions. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0417d-ftnote.018"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Supra note 15 at 90. </s></p></note></div2><div2><head rend="underlined bold">The Economic and Social Context for the Filipino Mail Order Bride Industry</head><p n="p16.23"><s n="s1.4;p16.23">One of the most commonly accepted reasons that women become MOB that is because of the economic and social situations in their country of origin. </s><s n="s2.4;p16.23">"Economic considerations and obtaining permanent residency in the United States are often important factors in influencing a woman to become involved in the mail-order industry." </s><ref target="BAWE_0417d-ftnote.019"/><s n="s3.4;p16.23">This is particularly the case with the Philippines, where there is a long-history with the United States. </s><s n="s4.4;p16.23">However, it cannot be denied that Filipinas MOB are also destined for Japan, and for Canada which is a growing destination for MOB and is likely to increase in the near future. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0417d-ftnote.019"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Supra note 1 at 942. </s></p></note><p n="p17.23"><s n="s1.4;p17.23">The Philippines has limited industries and has not been successful in marketing itself to foreign investment and development in the same way many other Asian countries have been. </s><s n="s2.4;p17.23">"As a developing country, the gap between the rich and the poor in the Philippines continues to worsen ... </s><s n="s3.4;p17.23">Seventy percent of the population lives below the poverty line, mostly peasants and workers." </s><ref target="BAWE_0417d-ftnote.020"/><s n="s4.4;p17.23">As in much of the developing world, Filipina women comprise the majority of those living in poverty in the Philippines. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0417d-ftnote.020"><p n="pn1.2"><s n="s1.1;pn1.2">Philippine Women Centre of B.C., <hi rend="italic">Canada: The New Frontier for Filipino Mail-Order Brides</hi>, online: Status of Women Canada &lt;<seg type="URL" n="http://www.swc-sfc.gc.ca/pubs/pubspr/0662653343/200011_0662653343_e.pdf"/>> at 11. </s></p><p n="pn2.2"><s n="s1.1;pn2.2">Access on April 25, 2007 </s></p></note><p n="p18.23"><s n="s1.4;p18.23">One of the main economic sectors for the Philippines is tourism. </s><s n="s2.4;p18.23">"Under the policy of tourism development, Filipinas are also used as prime selling points to attract foreigners to the Philippines... </s><s n="s3.4;p18.23">Filipinas are thus pushed into the informal sectors of the Philippine economy, most tragically into prostitution. </s><s n="s4.4;p18.23">Despite the fact that 'sex for hire (is) not a component of the indigenous culture of the Philippines', the Philippines now has the highest number of prostitutes in Southeast Asia - 600,000 - according to the International Labour Organization." <ref target="BAWE_0417d-ftnote.021"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0417d-ftnote.021"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid. at 12. </s></p></note><p n="p19.23"><s n="s1.5;p19.23">However, the primary economic resource of the Philippines lies in exporting its citizens. </s><s n="s2.5;p19.23">The government actually encourages emigration through its Labour Export Policy (LEP). </s><s n="s3.5;p19.23">This policy of systemically exporting its best and brightest "is part of the Structural Adjustment Programs (SAPs) imposed by the International Monetary Fund (IMF) and the World Bank as conditions for borrowing." </s><ref target="BAWE_0417d-ftnote.022"/><s n="s4.5;p19.23">However, despite pushing its nationals towards emigrating, the government has done little to make Filipinos aware of the risks involved, including the potential for violence, discrimination and exploitation. </s><s n="s5.5;p19.23">The fact that their country of origin happens to be "the top labour exporter in the entire world, described as the world's largest migrant nation"<ref target="BAWE_0417d-ftnote.023"/>, certainly influences the MOB decision to emigrate. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0417d-ftnote.022"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid. at 11. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0417d-ftnote.023"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid. at 10. </s></p></note><p n="p20.23"><s n="s1.3;p20.23">The economic migration sector that has experienced the greatest growth in the last decade is the export of workers for informal employment - domestic work, entertainment, and prostitution. </s><s n="s2.3;p20.23">Now the category of mail order bride must also be added to this category of informal employment. "... </s><s n="s3.3;p20.23">On the one hand, women who are considered as poor, low-earning and in that regard low value-adding individuals, often represented as a burden rather than a resource, and on the other hand, what are emerging as significant sources for profit making, especially in the shadow economy, and for government revenue enhancement." <ref target="BAWE_0417d-ftnote.024"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0417d-ftnote.024"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Ed. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">Krielmild Saunders, <hi rend="italic">Feminist Post-Development Thought</hi>, (London: Zed Books Ltd., 2002) at 91. </s></p></note></div2><div2><head rend="underlined bold">The Impact of the Chain on Gendered Structures </head><p n="p21.23"><s n="s1.5;p21.23">It is clear from the discussion of the description of the characteristics and reasoning of the male suitors, that the social structure of society plays a critical role. </s><s n="s2.5;p21.23">As men search for a woman to fulfill the traditional role of wife - unpaid domestic labour and childcare included with love and devotion - they are inevitably participating in the global economic order, as they are paying into the system to find their bride. </s><s n="s3.5;p21.23">The MOB industry is flourishing in the new millennium - a time of globalization and unadulterated capitalism. </s><s n="s4.5;p21.23">Author Yu Kojima states in her article on cultural reproduction and MOB, that "capitalism cannot function without patriarchy..." </s><ref target="BAWE_0417d-ftnote.025"/><s n="s5.5;p21.23">She clarifies this by stating that "the key characteristics of capitalism is the social and sexual division of labor ... [and] involves two main dimensions - within paid work and between paid and unpaid work - and operates to value men's work more highly than women's work." <ref target="BAWE_0417d-ftnote.026"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0417d-ftnote.025"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Yu Kojima, <hi rend="italic">In the Business of Cultural Reproduction: Theoretical Implications of the Mail-Order Bride Phenomenon</hi> (2001) 24 Women's Studies International Forum 199 at 200. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0417d-ftnote.026"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid. at 201. </s></p></note><p n="p22.23"><s n="s1.5;p22.23">One interesting aspect of the mail order bride phenomenon is the correlation between the stereotyping of women and the cause-and-effect dynamic it has had on Western women and Filipina women. </s><s n="s2.5;p22.23">As stated above, many men have claimed that Western women no longer make adequate wives. </s><s n="s3.5;p22.23">As women become more powerful, both economically and socially, their value has decreased in the view of a signification portion of the Western male population. </s><s n="s4.5;p22.23">The correlation between the commencement of the feminist movement in the 1970s, and the upsurge in the mail order bride industry cannot be denied. </s><s n="s5.5;p22.23">However, one of the results of the shift in social structure in the West has been an alteration in social structure in the Philippines (and other countries of origin for mail order brides); women are shifting in the social structures as they become a valued economic resource, if only for exportation. </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">CONCLUSION</head><p n="p23.23"><s n="s1.3;p23.23">At every level of the chain, from the Mail Order Brides as the product, to Western men as consumers, to the direction of State policies regarding MOB, gendered relations and effects are present. </s><s n="s2.3;p23.23">Whether the actors in the chain act under duress or choice, the ramifications remain the same: gendered structures are affected the world over. </s><s n="s3.3;p23.23">The global sex chain of Filipina mail order brides and Western consumers is much like any other commodity chain - it creates both bridges of opportunity and vises of exploitation. </s></p></div1></body><back><div1 type="bibliography"><head rend="bold">Bibliography</head><div2 type="bibliography"><head rend="underlined bold">Print Sources</head><p>Nicole Constable, <hi rend="italic">Romance on a Global Stage: Pen Pals, Virtual Ethnography, and "Mail Order" Marriages</hi>, (London: University of California Press, Ltd., 2003).</p><p>Virginia O. Del Rosario, <hi rend="italic">Lifting the Smoke Screen: Dynamics of Mail-Order Migration from the Philippines</hi>, (The Hague: Institute of Social Studies, 1994).</p><p>Eds. Gregory A. Kelson and Debra L. DeLaet, <hi rend="italic">Gender and Immigration</hi>, (London: Macmillan Press Ltd., 1999).</p><p>Ed. Krielmild Saunders, <hi rend="italic">Feminist Post-Development Thought</hi>, (London: Zed Books Ltd., 2002).</p></div2><div2 type="bibliography"><head rend="underlined bold">Electronic Journals</head><p>Yu Kojima, <hi rend="italic">In the Business of Cultural Reproduction: Theoretical Implications of the Mail-Order Bride Phenomenon</hi> (2001) 24 Women's Studies International Forum 199</p><p>Lana Mobydeen, <hi rend="italic">Something Old, Something New, Something Borrrowed, Something Mail-Ordered? The Mail-Order Bride Industry and Immigration Law</hi> (2004) 49 Wayne Law Review 939</p><p>Roland B. Tolentino, "Bodies, Letters, Catalogs: Filipinas in Transnational Space." (1996) 48 Social Text Autumn 49</p></div2><div2 type="bibliography"><head rend="underlined bold">Web-based Sources</head><p>Centre de recherche interuniversitaire de Montréal sur l'immigration, l'intégration et la dynamique urbaine, <hi rend="italic">Precarious Immigration Status, Dependency and Women's Vulnerability to Violence: Impacts on their Health</hi>, online: Centre for Applied Family Studies &lt;<seg type="URL" n="http://im.metropolis.net/research-policy/research_content/doc/Version_ang_PDF.pdf"/>> </p><p>Accessed on April 25, 2007</p><p><hi rend="italic">Claim for the Revocation of a Decision Not to Permit the Change of the Status for a Sojourn in Japan - 1999</hi> (Gyo-Hi) No.46 [2002] JPSC 46 (17 October 2002), online: Asianlii.org, &lt;<seg type="URL" n="http://www.asianlii.org/jp/cases/JPSC/2002/46.html"/>> </p><p>Accessed on April 25, 2007</p><p>J. Sean Curtin, <hi rend="italic">International Marriages in Japan: Part One - Visa status of non-Japanese spouses in 2002</hi>, online: Glocom Platform: Japanese Institute of Global Communications &lt;<seg type="URL" n="http://www.glocom.org/special_topics/social_trends/20021028_trends_s13/index.html"/>></p><p>Accessed on April 25, 2007</p><p>Donna M. Hughes<hi rend="italic">, Pimps and Predators on the Internet-Globalizing the Sexual Exploitation of Women and Children</hi> [Part 16 of 16], University of Rhode Island, online: &lt;<seg type="URL" n="http://www.uri.edu/artsci/wms/hughes/ppcpt1.htm"/>></p><p>Accessed on April 25, 2007</p><p><hi rend="italic">Immigration and Nationality Act</hi>, 214, I.N.A.C. §214 (1952), online: U.S. Citizenship and Immigration Services &lt;<seg type="URL" n="http://www.uscis.gov/propub/ProPubVAP.jsp?dockey=baeb6daf5705c4f8629f8b6ea9f7c64d"/>> </p><p>Accessed on April 25, 2007</p><p>The LawPhil Project, <hi rend="italic">An Act to Declare Unlawful the Practice of Matching Filipino Women for Marriage to Foreign Nationals on a Mail Order Basis and Other Similar Practices, including the Advertisement, Publication, Printing or Distribution of Brochures, Fliers and Other Propaganda Materials in Furtherance thereof and Providing Penalty Therefore</hi>, Republic Act No. 6955, online: <seg type="URL" n="http://www.lawphil.net/"/></p><p>Accessed on April 25, 2007</p><p>Philippine Women Centre of B.C., <hi rend="italic">Canada: The New Frontier for Filipino Mail-Order Brides</hi>, online: Status of Women Canada &lt;<seg type="URL" n="http://www.swc-cfc.gc.ca/pubs/pubspr/0662653343/200011_0662653343_e.pdf"/>></p><p>Access on April 25, 2007 </p><p>Robert J. Scholes, <hi rend="italic">Appendix A [to International Matchmaking Organizations: A Report to Congress (February 1999)]: The "Mail-Order Bride" Industry and its Impact on U.S. Immigration</hi>, Immigration and Naturalization Service (1999), online: U.S. Citizenship and Immigration Services &lt;<seg type="URL" n="http://www.uscis.gov/files/article/MobRept_AppendixA.pdf"/>> </p><p>Accessed on April 25, 2007</p><p>U.S. Bill, H.R. 3657, <hi rend="italic">International Marriage Broker Regulation Act of 2005</hi>, 109<hi rend="sup">th</hi> Cong., 2005, (enacted), online: Library of Congress &lt;<seg type="URL" n="http://thomas.loc.gov/cgi-bin/bdquery/z?d109"/>:HR03657:@@@T> </p><p>Accessed April 25, 2007</p></div2></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
