<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_0423d" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>The Application of the International Right to Housing in Domestic Settings</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">Language used in quote: <foreign id="English">English</foreign></note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">deleted: footer: student number, page numbers</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">4</p><p n="date">unknown</p><p n="module title">International and Regional Human Rights Regimes</p><p n="module code">unknown</p><p n="genre family">Critique</p><p n="discipline">Law</p><p n="disciplinary group">SS</p><p n="grade">unknown</p><p n="number of authors">unknown</p><p n="number of words">3028</p><p n="number of s-units">54</p><p n="number of p">37</p><p n="number of tables">0</p><p n="number of figures">0</p><p n="number of block quotes">2</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">0</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">0</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">56.1</p><p n="average s-units per p">1.5</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">f</p><p n="year of birth">1977</p><p n="first language">English</p><p n="education">OSA</p><p n="course">LLM International development law</p><p n="student ID">0423</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><docTitle><titlePart rend="bold">INTERNATIONAL AND REGIONAL HUMAN RIGHTS REGIMES The Application of the International Right to Housing in Domestic Settings</titlePart></docTitle></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Introduction</head><p n="p1.37"><s n="s1.1;p1.37">Current research in relation to housing around the world estimates that 1.1 billion people live in inadequate housing conditions in urban areas alone and that 100 million people are homeless.<ref target="BAWE_0423d-ftnote.001"/> Further, the United Nations Special Rapporteur on the Right to Adequate Housing has reported that the housing and living conditions around the world are deteriorating. <ref target="BAWE_0423d-ftnote.002"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0423d-ftnote.001"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">UN HABITAT, <hi rend="italic">Why Housing Rights?</hi> </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">&lt;<seg type="URL" n="http://www.unhabitat.org/content.asp?typeid=19&amp;catid=282&amp;cid=789"/>> at 17 December 2006. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0423d-ftnote.002"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Miloon Kothari, 'Actions to Promote the Realization of the Right to Adequate Housing' in Berma Goldewijk, Adalid Baspineiro and Paulo Carbonari (eds), <hi rend="italic">Dignity and Human Rights: the Implementation of Economic, Social and Cultural Rights</hi> (2002) 285, 291. </s></p></note><p n="p2.37"><s n="s1.2;p2.37">Over recent decades, numerous human rights legal instruments in relation, either directly or indirectly, to housing and living conditions have been negotiated at the international level, demonstrating the willingness of the international community to focus attention on the various manifestations of the housing crisis. </s><s n="s2.2;p2.37">In addition, the United Nations and other international organisations have increased their focus on the international right to housing and the UN Committee on Economic, Social and Cultural Rights<ref target="BAWE_0423d-ftnote.003"/> (<hi rend="bold">ESCR Committee</hi>) has arguably devoted more attention to this right than to any other within its ambit.<ref target="BAWE_0423d-ftnote.004"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0423d-ftnote.003"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Established under ECOSOC Resolution 1985/17 of 28 May 1985. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0423d-ftnote.004"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Matthew C.R. Craven, <hi rend="italic">The International Covenant on Economic, Social, and Cultural Rights: A Perspective on its Development</hi> (1995) 329. </s></p></note><p n="p3.37"><s n="s1.3;p3.37">However, despite the existence of this established international legal standard, it is clear that a significant gap persists between the theoretical human rights norms and the realities of many local communities. </s><s n="s2.3;p3.37">As is often the case in relation to many human rights, "[t]here can be no doubting that the oft-cited gap between law and practice...is sadly alive and well when it comes to housing rights." </s><ref target="BAWE_0423d-ftnote.005"/><s n="s3.3;p3.37">In an attempt to narrow this gap, housing rights advocates around the world have pursued a variety of human rights strategies in domestic settings, such as community mobilisation, political campaigning for domestic legislative reform, advocacy before regional and international bodies, and legal challenges before courts of all jurisdictions. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0423d-ftnote.005"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Scott Leckie, <hi rend="italic">Sources No.</hi> </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1"><hi rend="italic">4: Legal Resources for Housing Rights: International and National Standards</hi> (2000) Centre on Housing Rights and Evictions 5 &lt;<seg type="URL" n="http://www.cohre.org/view_page.php?page_id=118"/>> at 28 December 2006. </s></p></note><p n="p4.37"><s n="s1.1;p4.37">This essay focuses on one aspect of the legal approach, namely the use of the international right to housing in domestic courts, and examines the potential for this strategy to effect practical benefit for housing conditions at the local level. </s></p><p n="p5.37"><s n="s1.3;p5.37">To this end, the scope of the international human right to housing will be outlined in the first section of this essay. </s><s n="s2.3;p5.37">Secondly, the extent to which the international right to housing is regarded as justiciable, and the basis for judicial reluctance in this regard, will be considered. </s><s n="s3.3;p5.37">Finally, the benefits of, and challenges to, the adoption of this legal approach as a strategy for the amelioration of inadequate housing and living conditions will be evaluated. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">The Human Right to Housing</head><p n="p6.37"><s n="s1.1;p6.37">The human "right to housing" refers to the body of international, regional and national law which elucidates the general and specific regulation of the dimensions of the right to adequate housing and living conditions for all people around the world. </s></p><p n="p7.37"><s n="s1.1;p7.37">At the international level, numerous treaties and related documents recognise the right to housing, outline its relevant components and describe its obligations.<ref target="BAWE_0423d-ftnote.006"/> In this regard, the Universal Declaration of Human Rights, the first human rights standard to recognise housing rights,<ref target="BAWE_0423d-ftnote.007"/> states: </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0423d-ftnote.006"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Maria Foscarinis, 'Realizing Domestic Social Justice through International Human Rights: Part II: Advocating for the Human Right to Housing: Notes from the United States' (2006) 30 <hi rend="italic">New York University Review of Law &amp; Social Change</hi> 447, 448. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0423d-ftnote.007"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">COHRE, <hi rend="italic">Legal resources on housing rights</hi>, &lt;<seg type="URL" n="http://www.cohre.org/view_page.php?page_id=4"/>> at 17 December 2006. </s></p></note><quote lang="English">"Everyone has the right to a standard living adequate for the health and well-being of himself and of his family, including food, clothing, housing and medical care and necessary social services, and the right to security in the event of unemployment, sickness, disability, widowhood, old age or other lack of livelihood in circumstances beyond his control." <ref target="BAWE_0423d-ftnote.008"/></quote><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0423d-ftnote.008"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1"><hi rend="italic">Universal Declaration of Human Rights</hi>, GA Res 217 A (III), [25], UN Doc A/217 (1948). </s></p></note><p n="p8.37"><s n="s1.1;p8.37">The most significant articulation of the right to housing at an international level<ref target="BAWE_0423d-ftnote.009"/>, Article 11(1) of the International Covenant on Economic, Social and Cultural Rights (<hi rend="bold">ICESCR</hi>) states: </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0423d-ftnote.009"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Committee on Economic, Social and Cultural Rights, <hi rend="italic">General Comment 4: The Right to Adequate Housing</hi>, 6th sess, [3], UN Doc E/1992/23 (1991) &lt;<seg type="URL" n="http://www.ohchr.org/english/bodies/cescr/comments.htm"/>> at 2 January 2007. </s></p></note><quote lang="English">"The State parties to the present Covenant recognize the right of everyone to an adequate standard of living for himself and for his family, including adequate food, clothing and housing, and to the continuous improvement of living conditions. The States Parties will take appropriate steps to ensure the realization of this right, recognizing to this effect the essential importance of international co-operation based on free consent."<ref target="BAWE_0423d-ftnote.010"/></quote><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0423d-ftnote.010"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">International Covenant on Economic, Social and Cultural Rights, opened for signature 16 December 1966, art 11 (entered into force 3 January 1976). </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">The ICESCR recognises the right to housing as part of the larger right to an adequate standard of living; however, under international human rights law the right to adequate housing is generally now understood as an independent, free-standing right. </s></p></note><p n="p9.37"><s n="s1.2;p9.37">Responsibility for monitoring State party compliance with the Covenant rests with the ESCR Committee. </s><s n="s2.2;p9.37">Its General Comment 4, intended to interpret and define Article 11(1) of the ICESCR, is widely deemed to be the most authoritative interpretation of the right to housing. <ref target="BAWE_0423d-ftnote.011"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0423d-ftnote.011"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">COHRE, above no 7. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">For a useful overview of the approach of the ESCR Committee to the scope of the right to housing, see Craven, above no 4, 329-349. </s></p></note><p n="p10.37"><s n="s1.2;p10.37">Notably, the ECSR Committee states that "the right to housing should not be interpreted in a narrow or restrictive sense which equates it with, for example, the shelter provided by merely having a roof over one's head or views shelter exclusively as a commodity."<ref target="BAWE_0423d-ftnote.012"/>. </s><s n="s2.2;p10.37">In this regard, the ESCR Committee notes that article 11(1) must be understood as referring not just to housing but to "adequate housing", a concept which includes each of the following factors: legal security of tenure, availability of services, materials, facilities and infrastructure, affordability, habitability, accessibility, location and cultural adequacy.<ref target="BAWE_0423d-ftnote.013"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0423d-ftnote.012"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Committee on Economic, Social and Cultural Rights, above no 9, [7]. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0423d-ftnote.013"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid [8]. </s></p></note><p n="p11.37"><s n="s1.1;p11.37">The right to housing has been reaffirmed either explicitly or implicitly in a number of additional international human rights instruments, including the International Covenant on Civil and Political Rights (<hi rend="bold">ICCPR</hi>),<ref target="BAWE_0423d-ftnote.014"/> the Convention on the Elimination of All Forms of Racial Discrimination,<ref target="BAWE_0423d-ftnote.015"/> the Convention on the Elimination of All Forms of Discrimination against Women,<ref target="BAWE_0423d-ftnote.016"/> and the Convention on the Rights of the Child.<ref target="BAWE_0423d-ftnote.017"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0423d-ftnote.014"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">International Covenant on Civil and Political Rights, opened for signature 16 December 1966, art 17(1) (entered into force 23 March 1976). </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0423d-ftnote.015"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Convention on the Elimination of All Forms of Racial Discrimination, opened for signature 21 December 1965, art 5(e)(iii) (entered into force 4 January 1969). </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0423d-ftnote.016"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Convention on the Elimination of All Forms of Discrimination against Women, opened for signature 18 December 1979, art 14(2)(h) (entered into force 3 September 1981). </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0423d-ftnote.017"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Convention on the Rights of the Child, opened for signature 20 November 1989, art 27(3) (entered into force 2 September 1990). </s></p></note></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">The Justiciability of the International Right to Housing </head><div2><head rend="italic">The Justiciability of Economic, Social and Cultural Rights Generally</head><p n="p12.37"><s n="s1.2;p12.37">Historically, the ICCPR and the ICESCR have been perceived as representing two "generations" of human rights, with the economic, social and cultural rights of the latter attracting categorisation as progressive, purely aspirational and consequently non-justiciable. </s><s n="s2.2;p12.37">However, the notion that all rights are indivisible and interdependent has been stated and reaffirmed many times.<ref target="BAWE_0423d-ftnote.018"/> Further, human rights activists, scholars and lawyers have convincingly established that many aspects of economic, social and cultural rights are justiciable through the evolution of innovative methods of creating paths for making such rights justiciable through public interest litigation. <ref target="BAWE_0423d-ftnote.019"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0423d-ftnote.018"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Asbjørn Eide and Allan Rosas, 'Economic, Social and Cultural Rights: A Universal Challenge' in Asbjørn Eide, Catarina Krause and Allan Rosas (eds), <hi rend="italic">Economic, Social and Cultural Rights</hi> (2nd ed, 2001) 3. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0423d-ftnote.019"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">See generally: Henry J Steiner and Philip Alston (eds), <hi rend="italic">International Human Rights in Context: Law, Politics and Morals</hi> (2nd ed, 2000) 275-286 </s></p></note><p n="p13.37"><s n="s1.1;p13.37">Following the conclusion of the Second World War and the accompanying expansion of the international human rights regimes, domestic courts around the world have made increasing use of international standards, whether official treaties or related documents, to assist in local decision-making.<ref target="BAWE_0423d-ftnote.020"/> This trend has been encouraged by, among other things, an increased willingness of jurists to consider relevant international legal findings or sources,<ref target="BAWE_0423d-ftnote.021"/> a broader awareness of international legal standards by local advocates, and the widespread dissemination of material on international norms by non-governmental organisations.<ref target="BAWE_0423d-ftnote.022"/> The globalisation of the world (in its various guises, whether economic, social or technological) has intensified this development through an increased ease and rate of transnational communication. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0423d-ftnote.020"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Robyn Emerton, Kirstine Adams, Andrew Byrnes and Jane Connors (eds), <hi rend="italic">Women's Human Rights: Leading International and National Cases</hi> (2005) xiii. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0423d-ftnote.021"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Anne-Marie Slaughter, <hi rend="italic">A New World Order</hi> (2004) ch 2. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0423d-ftnote.022"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Emerton, Adams, Byrnes and Connors, above no 20. </s></p></note></div2><div2><head rend="italic">Litigating the International Right to Housing</head><p n="p14.37"><s n="s1.1;p14.37">In relation to the international right to housing specifically, the UN Special Rapporteur for the Right to Adequate Housing has emphasised the need for justiciability of this right "in courts at all levels...in order for states effectively to respect, protect, promote and fulfil"<ref target="BAWE_0423d-ftnote.023"/> this right. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0423d-ftnote.023"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Miloon Kothari, 'Priority Issues and Impediments to Realizing the Right to Adequate Housing' in Berma Goldewijk, Adalid Baspineiro and Paulo Carbonari (eds), <hi rend="italic">Dignity and Human Rights: the Implementation of Economic, Social and Cultural Rights</hi> (2002) 63, 70. </s></p></note><p n="p15.37"><s n="s1.1;p15.37">The ESCR Committee has explicitly confirmed that the legal principle of justiciability and the provision of domestic legal remedies are applicable to the right to adequate housing.<ref target="BAWE_0423d-ftnote.024"/> According to the ESCR Committee, the provisions might apply to: "(a) legal appeals aimed at preventing planned evictions or demolitions through the issuance of court-ordered injunctions (b) legal procedures seeking compensation following an illegal eviction (c) complaints against illegal actions carried out or supported by landlords (whether public or private) in relation to rent levels, dwelling maintenance and racial or other forms of discrimination, (d) allegations of any form of discrimination in the allocation and availability of access to housing (e) complaints against landlords concerning unhealthy or inadequate housing conditions"<ref target="BAWE_0423d-ftnote.025"/> and, in some legal systems, "class action suits in situations involving significantly increased levels of homelessness".<ref target="BAWE_0423d-ftnote.026"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0423d-ftnote.024"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Committee on Economic, Social and Cultural Rights, above no 9, [17]. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">This affirmation by the ESCR Committee was made in the wider context of confirming that many aspects of economic, social and cultural rights generally are justiciable. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0423d-ftnote.025"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0423d-ftnote.026"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid. This is not an exhaustive list. </s></p></note></div2><div2><head rend="italic">Framing a Legal Claim Using the International Right to Housing </head><p n="p16.37"><s n="s1.1;p16.37">The international right to housing may be used in the context of founding a right of action and/or to assist in the interpretation and application of domestic or regional law.<ref target="BAWE_0423d-ftnote.027"/> The manner of use will depend primarily on whether the treaties to be relied upon have been incorporated into the domestic laws of the relevant nation-state.<ref target="BAWE_0423d-ftnote.028"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0423d-ftnote.027"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Anne F. Bayefsky, 'General Approaches to the Domestic Application of Women's International Human Rights Law' in Rebecca Cook (ed), <hi rend="italic">Human Rights of Women: National and International Perspectives</hi> (1994) 362, 363. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0423d-ftnote.028"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid 356-368. </s></p></note><p n="p17.37"><s n="s1.2;p17.37">Although it is generally the case that courts will construe national law in conformity with their countries' national obligations (even where the relevant treaties have not been expressly incorporated), in the absence of formal incorporation of the international right to housing, the justiciability of housing rights may be hampered by the tension resulting from the balance between a country's international obligations and the protection of its national sovereignty.<ref target="BAWE_0423d-ftnote.029"/> In particular, courts may be reluctant to award remedies in cases that require government implementation of specific policies necessitating significant budgetary consequences.<ref target="BAWE_0423d-ftnote.030"/> Appropriate remedies in housing rights cases may necessitate national or local government bodies to expend considerable resources, for example, to conduct large-scale community resettlement or improvements to housing to meet minimum standards. </s><s n="s2.2;p17.37">In such situations, the risk exists that courts will defer to the separation of powers doctrine and argue that such cases involve issues that are appropriately dealt with by governments, with deference to their finite resources, rather than by courts. <ref target="BAWE_0423d-ftnote.031"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0423d-ftnote.029"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">This is an issue in relation to the justiciability of many economic, cultural and social rights. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0423d-ftnote.030"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">See for example: Bayefsky, above no 27, 356, 359. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0423d-ftnote.031"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Malcolm Langford, <hi rend="italic">Litigating Economic, Social and Cultural Rights: Achievements, Challenges and Strategies</hi> (2003) Centre for Housing Rights and Evictions 11 &lt;<seg type="URL" n="http://www.cohre.org/view_page.php?page_id=121"/>> at 20 December 2006. </s></p></note><p n="p18.37"><s n="s1.2;p18.37">The challenge for strategic litigation involving housing rights is to encourage the harmonisation or reconciliation of these conflicting considerations in favour of the human rights beneficiaries. </s><s n="s2.2;p18.37">The principal strategy in such circumstances has often been to ask courts to acknowledge the socio-economic dimensions of civil and political rights since these are more likely to be actionable,<ref target="BAWE_0423d-ftnote.032"/> thereby promoting the bridging of generations of rights and strengthening the basis for an active judicial response. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0423d-ftnote.032"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid [10]. </s></p></note></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">The International Housing Rights Law in Domestic Courts</head><div2><head rend="italic">Outcomes of Relevant Cases </head><p n="p19.37"><s n="s1.1;p19.37">The benefits of, and challenges to, the adoption of this legal approach, with its goal of a reduction of inadequate housing and living conditions, is evaluated below, through a consideration of the major patterns emerging from relevant cases and the experiences of housing advocates. </s></p><p n="p20.37"><s n="s1.1;p20.37">Over the past two decades, there have been numerous strategic litigation and judicial test cases on housing rights issues, with both positive and negative results.<ref target="BAWE_0423d-ftnote.033"/> As one example of a successful outcome, the Constitutional Court of South Africa quoted directly from the ESCR Committee's General Comment No 4 and held that a housing rights plan involving the eviction of 900 people from private property, who were subsequently forced to live on the edge of sports field in horrendous conditions, was flawed due to its failure to uphold the right to housing by progressively addressing emergency relief.<ref target="BAWE_0423d-ftnote.034"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0423d-ftnote.033"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">See for example: COHRE, <hi rend="italic">National Jurisprudence</hi>, &lt;<seg type="URL" n="http://www.cohre.org/view_page.php?page_id=213"/>> at 20 December 2006 for descriptions of cases in Bangladesh, Canada, India, The Philippines, South Africa, and the United States of America. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0423d-ftnote.034"><p n="pn1.1"><s rend="italic" n="s1.4;pn1.1">Grootboom v. </s><s rend="italic" n="s2.4;pn1.1">Oostenberg Municipality Cape Metropolitan Council, et al. </s><s n="s3.4;pn1.1">Case No. </s><s n="s4.4;pn1.1">6826/99 (11 December 1999) Constitutional Court of South Africa. </s></p></note><p n="p21.37"><s n="s1.1;p21.37">A further example of success was documented in Bangladesh in relation to the continued forced eviction of persons without prior notice, where the judgment led to the negotiation of comprehensive plans for resettlement, developed by communities, architects and international agencies.<ref target="BAWE_0423d-ftnote.035"/> As the right to housing was not directly justiciable through the Constitution of Bangladesh, the claim successfully linked the international right to housing to the rights to life and livelihood. <ref target="BAWE_0423d-ftnote.036"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0423d-ftnote.035"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1"><hi rend="italic">Ask v Government of Bangladesh</hi> (1999) Supreme Court of Bangladesh. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0423d-ftnote.036"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Abul Hasnat Monjurul Kabir, 'Development and Human Rights: Litigating the Right to Adequate Housing' (2002) 3 <hi rend="italic">Asia-Pacific Journal on Human Rights and the Law</hi> 97, 112-117. </s></p></note><p n="p22.37"><s n="s1.1;p22.37">On the other hand, possibly an equal number of cases had no direct impact, failed to achieve their objectives or led to contradictory results in relation to other similar jurisdictions, or even the same jurisdiction.<ref target="BAWE_0423d-ftnote.037"/> In India, housing rights suffered a setback when its Supreme Court disregarded human rights and India's obligations under the ICESCR in relation to the displacement of hundreds of thousands of tribal people in connection with the construction of the Narmada Dam.<ref target="BAWE_0423d-ftnote.038"/> Again in India, the Bombay Court gave preference to environmental protection over housing rights in relation to approximately 500,000 people living in poverty in informal settlements.<ref target="BAWE_0423d-ftnote.039"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0423d-ftnote.037"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Langford, above no 30, 18 and ch 18. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0423d-ftnote.038"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Kothari, above no 23, 71, discussing <hi rend="italic">Narmada Bachao Andolan v Union of India and Others</hi> (18 October 2000) Supreme Court of India. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0423d-ftnote.039"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid, 72. </s></p></note><p n="p23.37"><s n="s1.1;p23.37">While it is beyond the scope of this essay to provide a comprehensive analysis and outcome summaries of the myriad cases which have applied the international right to housing at a domestic level, the lessons learned from the outcomes, both positive and negative, contribute to an understanding of the advantages of this type of strategic litigation. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="italic">The Significance of the International Human Rights Framework</head><p n="p24.37"><s n="s1.2;p24.37">The impact of claims that are founded using the international human rights framework is significant. </s><s n="s2.2;p24.37">This framework is a highly recognised and authoritative discourse which adds weight to housing rights issues by affirming the legal nature of these rights.<ref target="BAWE_0423d-ftnote.040"/> It provides a conceptual framework for courts to integrate the norm, standards and principles of the international human rights system into domestic policies, in circumstances in which governments are subject to both positive and negative obligations and the realisation of the right to housing, in all its forms, is necessarily a progressive one given the expenditure of often limited resources.<ref target="BAWE_0423d-ftnote.041"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0423d-ftnote.040"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Langford, above no 31, 26. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0423d-ftnote.041"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">See generally: Craven, above no 4, 330-332 in for a discussion in relation to the progressive realisation characteristic of the right to housing and the implications for governments. </s></p></note><p n="p25.37"><s n="s1.2;p25.37">Official recognition of the international right to housing, and with it the corresponding pressure on governments to respect, protect and fulfil its relevant components, provides individual and group claimants with a legitimate avenue of redress in relation to housing rights violations. </s><s n="s2.2;p25.37">The right to a legal hearing based on a claim framed by international human rights may be as significant as the remedy itself, particularly in circumstances where many suffering such infringements come from poor communities and minorities, where such groups exert minimal social or political power and courts are sometimes the only official institution that will listen.<ref target="BAWE_0423d-ftnote.042"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0423d-ftnote.042"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Langford, above no 31, 18. </s></p></note><p n="p26.37"><s n="s1.1;p26.37">Such recognition provides a solid foundation upon which local communities, non-governmental organisations, housing rights advocates and others can more forcefully assert the demand for adequate housing for everyone on the basis that housing rights are human and legal rights, not merely equivocal policy objectives.<ref target="BAWE_0423d-ftnote.043"/> In this way, merely the use of international human rights law in a domestic setting can become an instrument for empowerment and a long-term strategy to compel policy-makers to take housing rights more seriously. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0423d-ftnote.043"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Leckie, above no 5, 6. </s></p></note><p n="p27.37"><s n="s1.2;p27.37">In addition, an approach which emphasises the indivisibility and interdependence of all human rights is likely to improve the likelihood of a successful outcome, as it both strengthens and expands the understanding of the right to housing and demonstrates how a judicial response to housing rights issues can have a wide impact. </s><s n="s2.2;p27.37">The United Nations has confirmed that "having access to adequate, safe and secure housing substantially strengthens the likelihood of people being able to enjoy certain additional rights."<ref target="BAWE_0423d-ftnote.044"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0423d-ftnote.044"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Office of the High Commissioner for Human Rights,<hi rend="italic"> Fact Sheet No.</hi> </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1"><hi rend="italic">21: The Human Right to Adequate Housing</hi> &lt; <seg type="URL" n="http://www.ohchr.org/english/about/publications/sheets.htm"/>> at 20 December 2006. </s></p></note><p n="p28.37"><s n="s1.1;p28.37">The ESCR Committee has confirmed that the right to housing is "integrally linked to other human rights",<ref target="BAWE_0423d-ftnote.045"/> which most noticeably include the rights to: safe drinking water and sanitation; health, education, freedom of expression; freedom of association; environmental hygiene; attainment of the highest level of physical and mental health; access to resources; access to basic services, schools, transportation and employment options.<ref target="BAWE_0423d-ftnote.046"/> The UN Special Rapporteur on the Right to Adequate Housing, among others, has made reference to the identifiable nexus between poverty and human rights.<ref target="BAWE_0423d-ftnote.047"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0423d-ftnote.045"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Committee on Economic, Social and Cultural Rights, above no 9, [7]. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0423d-ftnote.046"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Kabir, above no 36, 98, 104-106. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0423d-ftnote.047"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Kothari ,above no 23, 65. </s></p></note></div2><div2><head rend="italic">Key Issues Identified by Housing Rights Advocates</head><p n="p29.37"><s n="s1.1;p29.37">Following a succession of housing rights cases around the world, several key concerns have been recognised by advocates as important considerations when pursuing a legal approach based on the international right to housing. </s></p><p n="p30.37"><s n="s1.2;p30.37">At the outset, careful case selection is imperative,<ref target="BAWE_0423d-ftnote.048"/> and ought to be founded on an informed understanding of the extent to which housing rights are considered justiciable in the relevant jurisdiction. </s><s n="s2.2;p30.37">Whether the litigation utilising the international right to housing has succeeded has often been dependent upon the extent to which courts exercised judicial restraint, such restraint generally increasing as the selected claims extended along the continuum of the duties to respect, to protect, or to fulfil, with their progressive impact on the respective state resources.<ref target="BAWE_0423d-ftnote.049"/> In addition to establishing connections between a number of human rights, as noted above, some advocates have employed a strategy of including within their claims detailed examples of alternatives to the treatment of people suffering housing rights violations (with considered input from relevant community members, architects or examples from other jurisdictions), for the court's consideration, therefore making it easier for courts to comprehend the parameters and viability of the remedy sought, rather than expecting the court to design new policy itself.<ref target="BAWE_0423d-ftnote.050"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0423d-ftnote.048"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Langford, above no 31, 18. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0423d-ftnote.049"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Scott Leckie, 'The Right to Housing' in Asbjørn Eide, Catarina Krause and Allan Rosas (eds), <hi rend="italic">Economic, Social and Cultural Rights</hi> (2nd ed, 2001) 153-158. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0423d-ftnote.050"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Langford, above no 31, ch 3. </s></p></note><p n="p31.37"><s n="s1.1;p31.37">Further, housing rights advocates have identified the implementation of court orders as the most essential, but most problematic, task in ensuring that litigation is ultimately effective in ensuring practical impact for local communities and therefore a successful translation of the international standard to daily realities.<ref target="BAWE_0423d-ftnote.051"/> This was demonstrated in the <hi rend="italic">Grootboom</hi> case, where, following its successful outcome, the difficulty lay in the task of ensuring the realisation of the court's orders through appropriate and vigilant monitoring. <ref target="BAWE_0423d-ftnote.052"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0423d-ftnote.051"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid, 17. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0423d-ftnote.052"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid, 9. </s></p></note></div2><div2><head rend="italic">Relevance of Complementary Strategies</head><p n="p32.37"><s n="s1.1;p32.37">In addition to seeking the appropriate framing of judicial remedies, namely supervisory rather than declaratory orders, housing rights advocates have emphasised the importance of implementing the court's orders in conjunction with complementary non-litigious strategies, in particular, a "public or political campaign or the intense involvement of the affected communities".<ref target="BAWE_0423d-ftnote.053"/> As litigation alone has been shown not to have the capacity to address all housing rights issues, placing the application of international norms in domestic courts within a wider political strategy has proven to provide a more holistic approach to, and ultimately greater success in, the correction of violations of housing rights. <ref target="BAWE_0423d-ftnote.054"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0423d-ftnote.053"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid 18. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0423d-ftnote.054"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.3;pn1.1">Ibid 17. </s><s n="s2.3;pn1.1">In this regard, it is important to look to domestic institutions which are able to effectively adjudicate and enforce economic, social and cultural rights as well as coordinating complementary strategies. </s><s n="s3.3;pn1.1">See generally: Philip Lynch, 'Harmonising International Human Rights Law and Domestic Law and Policy: the Establishment and Role of the Human Rights Law Resource Centre' (2006) 7 <hi rend="italic">Melbourne Journal of International Law</hi> 225. </s></p></note><p n="p33.37"><s n="s1.3;p33.37">Where cases fail, housing issues or broader social movements surrounding them may suffer a setback from obstructive legal precedents. </s><s n="s2.3;p33.37">Further, opportunities for direct action may be forfeited and communities may suffer the consequences of false hope. </s><s n="s3.3;p33.37">However, a successful judgment with failed implementation may result in less long-term practical benefit for local communities than an approach involving complementary strategies, even where the litigious aspect disappoints. </s></p><p n="p34.37"><s n="s1.1;p34.37">Housing rights advocates contend that combining litigation with a complementary social mobilisation strategy, including media campaigns and political lobbying, will generally act to lessen the detrimental consequences of unsuccessful cases as the litigious effort and negative judgment, if publicised appropriately, may act as a catalyst for more nuanced future cases which enjoy greater support from communities and advocates, as well as political change even without the originally desired legal outcome. <ref target="BAWE_0423d-ftnote.055"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0423d-ftnote.055"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Langford, above no 31, 25. </s></p></note></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">CONCLUSION</head><p n="p35.37"><s n="s1.1;p35.37">The purpose of this essay was to examine one of the human rights strategies applied by housing rights advocates in a domestic setting, namely the use of the international right to housing in domestic courts, in order to consider the potential for this strategy to effect practical benefit for housing conditions at the local level. </s></p><p n="p36.37"><s n="s1.2;p36.37">The discussion above reveals that this approach has yielded some very successful outcomes and, even in circumstances where the actual legal outcome was not favourable, the strength and authoritative nature of the international human rights regime lends weight to the legitimacy of housing rights in local settings generally. </s><s n="s2.2;p36.37">This is particularly enhanced when combined with a complementary social mobilisation movement in relation to the particular issues. </s></p><p n="p37.37"><s n="s1.1;p37.37">Accordingly, housing rights advocates would be wise to consider this as a central strategy, where appropriate in the circumstances, but at the very least, a significant component of their wider housing rights campaigns. </s></p></div1></body><back><div1 type="bibliography"><head rend="bold">BIBLIOGRAPHY</head><div2 type="bibliography"><head rend="bold">Articles/Books/Reports</head><p>Bayefsky, Anne F., 'General Approaches to the Domestic Application of Women's International Human Rights Law' in Rebecca Cook (ed), <hi rend="italic">Human Rights of Women: National and International Perspectives</hi> (1994) 362.</p><p>Craven, Matthew C.R., <hi rend="italic">The International Covenant on Economic, Social, and Cultural Rights: A Perspective on its Development</hi> (1995) 329.</p><p>Emerton, Robyn, Kirstine Adams, Andrew Byrnes and Jane Connors (eds), <hi rend="italic">Women's Human Rights: Leading International and National Cases</hi> (2005).</p><p>Evatt, Elizabeth, 'The Impact of International Human Rights on Domestic Law' in Grant Huscroft and Paul Rishworth (eds), <hi rend="italic">Litigating Rights: Perspectives from Domestic and International Law</hi> (2002).</p><p>Foscarinis, Maria, 'Realizing Domestic Social Justice through International Human Rights: Part II: Advocating for the Human Right to Housing: Notes from the United States' (2006) 30 <hi rend="italic">New York University Review of Law &amp; Social Change</hi> 447.</p><p>Fox, Hazel, 'Approaches of Domestic Courts to the Assertion of International Jurisdiction' in Patrick Capps, Malcolm Evans and Stratos Konstadinidis (eds), <hi rend="italic">Asserting Jurisdiction: International and European Legal Perspectives</hi> (2003).</p><p>Kabir, Abul Hasnat Monjurul, 'Development and Human Rights: Litigating the Right to Adequate Housing' (2002) 3 <hi rend="italic">Asia-Pacific Journal on Human Rights and the Law</hi> 97.</p><p>Kothari, Miloon, 'Priority Issues and Impediments to Realizing the Right to Adequate Housing' in Berma Goldewijk, Adalid Baspineiro and Paulo Carbonari (eds), <hi rend="italic">Dignity and Human Rights: the Implementation of Economic, Social and Cultural Rights</hi> (2002) 63.</p><p>Kothari, Miloon, 'Actions to Promote the Realization of the Right to Adequate Housing' in Berma Goldewijk, Adalid Baspineiro and Paulo Carbonari (eds), <hi rend="italic">Dignity and Human Rights: the Implementation of Economic, Social and Cultural Rights</hi> (2002) 285.</p><p>Langford, Malcolm, <hi rend="italic">Litigating Economic, Social and Cultural Rights: Achievements, Challenges and Strategies</hi> (2003) Centre for Housing Rights and Evictions 11 &lt;<seg type="URL" n="http://www.cohre.org/view_page.php?page_id=121"/>> at 20 December 2006.</p><p>Leckie, Scott, 'The Right to Adequate Housing' in Asbjørn Eide, Catarina Krause and Allan Rosas (eds), <hi rend="italic">Economic, Social and Cultural Rights</hi> (2<hi rend="sup">nd</hi> ed, 2001) ch 9.</p><p>Leckie, Scott, <hi rend="italic">Sources No. 4: Legal Resources for Housing Rights: International and National Standards</hi> (2000) Centre on Housing Rights and Evictions 5 &lt;<seg type="URL" n="http://www.cohre.org/view_page.php?page_id=118"/>> at 28 December 2006.</p><p>Lynch, Philip, 'Harmonising International Human Rights Law and Domestic Law and Policy: the Establishment and Role of the Human Rights Law Resource Centre' (2006) 7 <hi rend="italic">Melbourne Journal of International Law</hi> 225.</p><p>Anne-Marie Slaughter, <hi rend="italic">A New World Order</hi> (2004) ch 2.</p><p>Steiner, Henry J. and Philip Alston, <hi rend="italic">International Human Rights in Context: Law, Politics, Morals</hi> (2<hi rend="sup">nd</hi> ed, 2000) ch 4.</p><p>Steinhardt, Ralph, 'The Role of Domestic Courts in Enforcing International Human Rights Law' in Hurst Hannum (ed), <hi rend="italic">Guide to International Human Rights Practice</hi> (4<hi rend="sup">th</hi> ed, 2004).</p><p>Thiele, Bret, <hi rend="italic">Litigating Against Forced Evictions Under the American Convention on Human Rights</hi> Centre on Housing Rights and Evictions &lt;<seg type="URL" n="http://www.cohre.org/view_page.php?page_id=212"/>> at 13 December 2006.</p></div2><div2 type="bibliography"><head rend="bold">Case Law</head><p><hi rend="italic">Grootboom v. Oostenberg Municipality Cape Metropolitan Council, et al.</hi> Case No. 6826/99 (11 December 1999) Constitutional Court of South Africa.</p><p><hi rend="italic">Ask v Government of Bangladesh</hi> (1999) Supreme Court of Bangladesh.</p><p><hi rend="italic">Narmada Bachao Andolan v Union of India and Others</hi> (18 October 2000) Supreme Court of India.</p></div2><div2 type="bibliography"><head rend="bold">Treaties</head><p>International Covenant on Economic, Social and Cultural Rights, opened for signature 16 December 1966, (entered into force 3 January 1976).</p><p>International Covenant on Civil and Political Rights, opened for signature 16 December 1966, (entered into force 23 March 1976).</p><p>Convention on the Elimination of All Forms of Racial Discrimination, opened for signature 21 December 1965, (entered into force 4 January 1969).</p><p>Convention on the Elimination of All Forms of Discrimination against Women, opened for signature 18 December 1979, (entered into force 3 December 1981). </p><p>Convention on the Rights of the Child, opened for signature 20 November 1989, (entered into force 2 September 1990).</p></div2><div2 type="bibliography"><head rend="bold">Other Sources</head><p>Committee on Economic, Social and Cultural Rights, <hi rend="italic">General Comment 4: The Right to Adequate Housing</hi>, Office of the High Commission for Human Rights (1991) [3] &lt;<seg type="URL" n="http://www.ohchr.org/english/bodies/cescr/comments.htm"/>> at 2 January 2007.</p><p>Office of the High Commissioner for Human Rights,<hi rend="italic"> Fact Sheet No. 21: The Human Right to Adequate Housing</hi> &lt;<seg type="URL" n="http://www.ohchr.org/english/about/publications/sheets.htm"/>> at 20 December 2006.</p><p><seg type="URL" n="http://www.unhabitat.org"/> (United Nations Human Settlements Programme)</p><p><seg type="URL" n="http://www.cohre.org"/> (Centre for Housing Rights and Evictions)</p><p><seg type="URL" n="http://www.nlchp.org"/> (The National Law Center on Homelessness and Poverty)</p><p rend="bold">Citation Style</p><p>Please note that the citation style used in this essay is that detailed in the Australian Guide to Legal Citation (see <seg type="URL" n="http://mulr.law.unimelb.edu.au/PDFs/aglc_dl.pdf"/>).</p></div2></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
