<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_0423b" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Framework for a Peoples' Tribunal on health violations and the united nations</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">deleted: footer: student name and number, page numbers</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">4</p><p n="date">unknown</p><p n="module title">Global Law in the Making</p><p n="module code">unknown</p><p n="genre family">Proposal</p><p n="discipline">Law</p><p n="disciplinary group">SS</p><p n="grade">unknown</p><p n="number of authors">unknown</p><p n="number of words">3286</p><p n="number of s-units">99</p><p n="number of p">69</p><p n="number of tables">0</p><p n="number of figures">0</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">0</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">23</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">33.2</p><p n="average s-units per p">1.4</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">f</p><p n="year of birth">1977</p><p n="first language">English</p><p n="education">OSA</p><p n="course">LLM International development law</p><p n="student ID">0423</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><docTitle><titlePart><hi rend="bold">LLM IN INTERNATIONAL DEVELOPMENT LAW AND HUMAN RIGHTS GLOBAL LAW IN THE MAKING</hi><hi rend="bold"> FRAMEWORK FOR A PEOPLES' TRIBUNAL</hi> <hi rend="bold"> ON HEALTH VIOLATIONS AND THE UNITED NATIONS</hi></titlePart></docTitle></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">INTRODUCTION</head><p n="p1.69"><s n="s1.1;p1.69">This essay sets out a framework for a peoples' law tribunal (Tribunal) on the health violations suffered by the Roma community at the camps for internally displaced persons (IDP camps) administered by the United Nations Mission in Kosovo (UNMIK). </s></p><p n="p2.69"><s n="s1.3;p2.69">Part I provides the context for the Tribunal and explains the purpose of an application of a peoples' law perspective to the violations. </s><s n="s2.3;p2.69">Part II details the proposed structure of the Tribunal, including the issues for judgment, the participants and the expected nature of the testimony. </s><s n="s3.3;p2.69">Finally, Part III explains the political vision and strategies of the Tribunal, both as an event and as a process. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">PART I: BACKGROUND</head><div2><head rend="bold">The United Nations Mission In Kosovo (UNMIK)</head><p n="p3.69"><s n="s1.1;p3.69">UNMIK was established in June 1999 when the UN Security Council issued a resolution authorising the UN Secretary-General to establish an interim civil administration led by the UN in the war-ravaged province of Kosovo, following the eviction of Yugoslav troops by NATO forces. <ref target="BAWE_0423b-ftnote.001"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0423b-ftnote.001"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1"><hi rend="italic">Resolution on the Establishment of UNMIK</hi>, SC Res 1244, UN Doc S/RES/1244 (1999). </s></p></note><p n="p4.69"><s n="s1.3;p4.69">In Kosovo, UNMIK acts not only as an international organisation, but also as a "surrogate state authority"<ref target="BAWE_0423b-ftnote.002"/>, unprecedented for a UN mission in both its scope and structural complexity. </s><s n="s2.3;p4.69">The mission "performs the whole spectrum of essential administrative functions and services covering such areas as health and education, banking and finance, post and telecommunications, and law and order." </s><ref target="BAWE_0423b-ftnote.003"/><s n="s3.3;p4.69">UNMIK's mandate combines elements of peace-keeping, democracy-promotion, reconstruction and economic development, institution-building and rule of law.<ref target="BAWE_0423b-ftnote.004"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0423b-ftnote.002"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">European Roma Rights Centre, <hi rend="italic">European Court of Human Rights Has No Jurisdiction in Kosovo Lead Poisoning Case</hi> (2006) &lt;<seg type="URL" n="www.errc.org/cikk.php?cikk=2568&amp;archiv=1"/>> accessed on 26 March 2007. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0423b-ftnote.003"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">UNMIK, <hi rend="italic">UNMIK At a Glance</hi> &lt;<seg type="URL" n="http://www.unmikonline.org/intro.htm"/>> accessed on 26 March 2007. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0423b-ftnote.004"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid. </s></p></note></div2><div2><head rend="bold">Violations </head><p n="p5.69"><s n="s1.1;p5.69">In June 1999, approximately 600 displaced persons, predominantly from the Roma<ref target="BAWE_0423b-ftnote.005"/> community in Kosovo, were relocated by the UN High Commissioner for Refugees to three IDP camps situated near the Trepca lead mine in Mitrovica, Kosovo. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0423b-ftnote.005"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">In this essay, the term 'Roma' is used to denote the particular Roma community of Kosovo. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">For a discussion of the Roma range of groupings and identities worldwide, see: Minority Rights Group International website &lt;<seg type="URL" n="www.minorityrights.org"/>> accessed on 4 April 2007. </s></p></note><p n="p6.69"><s n="s1.1;p6.69">In November 2000, the World Health Organisation (WHO), the UN specialised agency for health, issued the first in a series of reports that revealed high blood lead concentrations in all children and most adults at the IDP camps.<ref target="BAWE_0423b-ftnote.006"/> In July 2004, WHO conducted lead exposure testing in the children of the IDP camps and concluded that 88% of the IDP camps' areas were considered unsafe for human habitation.<ref target="BAWE_0423b-ftnote.007"/> In November 2004, WHO issued a further memo recommending that the camp population be moved away on an emergency basis. <ref target="BAWE_0423b-ftnote.008"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0423b-ftnote.006"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Sandra Molano and Andrej Andejew, 'First Phase of Public Health Project on Lead Pollution in Mitrovica Region' (2000) World Health Organization. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0423b-ftnote.007"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">World Health Organization, <hi rend="italic">Preliminary Report on Blood Levels in North Mitrovica and Zvecan</hi> (2004). </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0423b-ftnote.008"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">World Health Organization, <hi rend="italic">Capillary Blood Lead Confirmation and Critical Lead-Related Health Situation of the Roma Camps Children</hi> (2004) 3. </s></p></note><p n="p7.69"><s n="s1.1;p7.69">UNMIK began temporary relocation, and proper medical treatment, of the Roma community in 2006.<ref target="BAWE_0423b-ftnote.009"/> Permanent relocation to new housing did not commence until March 2007, almost seven years after the WHO's initial report.<ref target="BAWE_0423b-ftnote.010"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0423b-ftnote.009"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">'Kosovo's Displaced People Treated for Lead Poisoning', <hi rend="italic">Environment News Service</hi> (New York), 1 September 2006, &lt;<seg type="URL" n="www.ens-newswire.com/ens/sep2006-09-01-01.asp"/>> accessed on 7 April 2007. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0423b-ftnote.010"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Although the camps were intended only as temporary housing for RAE victims of the 1999 looting and burning of the Romani Mahala settlement in Mitrovica, it was not until 2006 that the IDPS were relocated from the lead-contaminated camps to other temporary camps, and on 7 March 2007 UNMIK reported that "after nearly eight years in makeshift camps, a number of Roma families have begun to return to south Mitrovica" to permanent housing. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">See: UNMIK, <hi rend="italic">Kosovo: Roma return to new homes in Mitrovica with help from UN and partners</hi> (2007) &lt;<seg type="URL" n="www.unmikonline.org/news.htm"/>> accessed on 7 April 2007. </s></p></note><p n="p8.69"><s n="s1.2;p8.69">At least 25 deaths have been linked to the prolonged lead exposure. </s><s n="s2.2;p8.69">Further, many Roma of the IDP camps suffered, and continue to suffer, severe health consequences.<ref target="BAWE_0423b-ftnote.011"/> In relation to children in particular, lead poisoning has been linked with permanent loss of cognitive function,<ref target="BAWE_0423b-ftnote.012"/> thereby also affecting education and livelihood prospects. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0423b-ftnote.011"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Lead poisoning symptoms include loss of appetite, lethargy, high blood pressure, fertility problems, stunted growth, hearing damage, neurological damage, seizures, pain in the legs and bones, stomach cramps and vomiting. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">See: Shannon Meehan and Nicole Mailman, <hi rend="italic">Refugee Voices: Lead Poisoning among Displaced Roma in Kosovo</hi> (2005) Refugees International &lt;<seg type="URL" n="www.refugeesinternational.org/section/stories/romavoices3"/>> accessed on 7 April 2007; </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0423b-ftnote.012"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Shilu Tong, Peter Baghurst, Anthony McMichael, Michael Sawyer and Jane Mudge, 'Lifetime exposure to environmental lead and children's intelligence at 11-13 years: the Port Pirie cohort study' (1996) 312 <hi rend="italic">British Medical Journal</hi> 1569. </s></p></note><p n="p9.69"><s n="s1.1;p9.69">From the time that UNMIK first became aware of the lead contamination in November 2000, investigations into the situation (primarily by NGOs) have indicated, among other things, inadequate provision of relevant health education, provision of false information regarding the contamination, and discrimination in the provision of the minimal interim medical treatment. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">Lack of Redress</head><p n="p10.69"><s n="s1.2;p10.69">During the extensive period in which the IDPs remained at the lead-contaminated camps, numerous attempts were made (within the avenues available in the mainstream legality) to bring the health violations to the attention of various institutions or other bodies. </s><s n="s2.2;p10.69">In this regard, the European Roma Rights Centre (ERRC): filed a criminal complaint;<ref target="BAWE_0423b-ftnote.013"/> notified the UN Human Rights Committee;<ref target="BAWE_0423b-ftnote.014"/> attempted to commence an action at the European Court of Human Rights;<ref target="BAWE_0423b-ftnote.015"/> requested the UN Secretary-General, UNHCHR and four Special Rapporteurs (on Housing, Toxic Wastes, Refugees, and Health respectively) to take immediate action for the preservation of the lives and health of children in the affected IDP camps, and to commence an internal investigation to ascertain how a situation (that a WHO expert had described "as one of the most serious lead-related environmental health disasters in the world and in history"<ref target="BAWE_0423b-ftnote.016"/>) was allowed to continue for more than six years;<ref target="BAWE_0423b-ftnote.017"/> filed a third party complaint at the UN;<ref target="BAWE_0423b-ftnote.018"/> and filed a complaint with the UN Oversight Body requesting an investigation into the mismanagement of the IDP camps in Kosovo.<ref target="BAWE_0423b-ftnote.019"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0423b-ftnote.013"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">European Roma Rights Centre, <hi rend="italic">Criminal Complaint Against Unknown Persons</hi> (2005) filed at the Office of Public Prosecutor in Kosovo (2005) &lt;<seg type="URL" n="www.errc.org"/>> accessed on 12 March 2007. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0423b-ftnote.014"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">European Roma Rights Centre, <hi rend="italic">Written Comments of the ERRC Concerning Kosovo for Consideration by the United Nations Human Rights Committee on the Occasion of Review of the Country Report of Task Forces on UNMIK</hi> (2006) &lt;<seg type="URL" n="www.errc.org"/>> accessed on 12 March 2007. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0423b-ftnote.015"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.3;pn1.1">On 20 February 2006, the European Roma Rights Centre filed an application on behalf of 184 IDPs at the European Court of Human Rights. </s><s n="s2.3;pn1.1">On 21 February 2006, the Court notified the ERRC that it did not have the jurisdiction to review the case, since UNMIK is not party to the relevant convention. </s><s n="s3.3;pn1.1">See: European Roma Rights Centre, <hi rend="italic">European Court of Human Rights Has No Jurisdiction in Kosovo Lead Poisoning Case</hi> (2006) &lt;<seg type="URL" n="www.errc.org/cikk.php?cikk=2568&amp;archiv=1"/>> accessed on 26 March 2007. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0423b-ftnote.016"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Laurie Wiseberg, 'The Way Forward Regarding the Roma, Ashkaeli and Egyptians (RAE) and the Lead Contamination', cited in: European Roma Rights Centre, above no 14, 9. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0423b-ftnote.017"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">European Roma Rights Centre, above no 15. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0423b-ftnote.018"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid. The third party complaint was filed pursuant to UN GA Res A/RES/52/247which relates to compensation payable by the UN in relation to injuries sustained at UN missions. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0423b-ftnote.019"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid. The complaint was filed pursuant to ST/SGB/1997/5 and ST/SGB/2002/7. </s></p></note><p n="p11.69"><s n="s1.1;p11.69">Such action was unsuccessful in significantly and expeditiously altering the situation due to the privileges and immunities of UNMIK,<ref target="BAWE_0423b-ftnote.020"/> and the jurisdictional<ref target="BAWE_0423b-ftnote.021"/> and conceptual<ref target="BAWE_0423b-ftnote.022"/> difficulties produced through an understanding of the UN as a 'non-state' in a world order premised on the state framework. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0423b-ftnote.020"><p n="pn1.1"><s rend="italic" n="s1.2;pn1.1">Regulation No. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1"><hi rend="italic">2000/47 on the Status, Privileges and Immunities of KFOR and UNMIK and Their Personnel in Kosovo</hi>, UNMIK/REG/2000/47 (2000) &lt;<seg type="URL" n="http://www.unmikonline.org/regulations/2000/reg47-00.htm"/>> accessed on 10 March 2007. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0423b-ftnote.021"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Marek Antoni Nowicki, <hi rend="italic">Special Report No.1 on the compatibility with recognized international standards of UNMIK Regulation No.</hi> </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1"><hi rend="italic">2000/47</hi> <hi rend="italic">on the Status, Privileges and Immunities of KFOR and UNMIK and Their Personnel in Kosovo (18 August 2000) and on the implementation of the above regulation</hi> (2001) Ombudsperson Institution in Kosovo 18-19. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0423b-ftnote.022"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">For a discussion regarding the perceived theoretical difficulties in conceiving the UN as a violator of human rights given that, as an intergovernmental organisation, it is a non-state actor, see: Frédéric Mégret and Florian Hoffmann, 'The UN as a Human Rights Violator? </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">Some Reflections on the United Nations Changing Human Rights Responsibilities' (2003) 25 <hi rend="italic">Human Rights Quarterly</hi> 314. </s></p></note></div2><div2><head rend="bold">Tribunal Aims </head><p n="p12.69"><s n="s1.1;p12.69">The Tribunal follows in the traditions of the Bertrand Russell War Crimes Tribunal of the late 1960s, the anti-imperialist movement which produced the Algiers Declaration on the Rights of the Peoples in 1976, and various subsequent peoples' tribunals.<ref target="BAWE_0423b-ftnote.023"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0423b-ftnote.023"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">For an overview of the historical foundations, see: Jayan Nayar, 'A People's Tribunal Against the Crime of Silence? </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">The Politics of Judgement and an Agenda for People's Law' (2001) 2 <hi rend="italic">Law, Social Justice &amp; Global Development</hi> [Part 3] &lt;<seg type="URL" n="http://elj.warwick.ac.uk/global/issue/2001-2/nayar.html"/>> accessed on 22 March 2007. </s></p></note><p n="p13.69"><s n="s1.4;p13.69">These initiatives are founded on the re-thinking of the concept of 'law', which is generally presented as apolitical, benign and relatively static. </s><s n="s2.4;p13.69">However, research in relation to historical legal and political processes demonstrates the restriction of such an interpretation and re-conceives law as a political concept not limited solely to the national/international dichotomy.<ref target="BAWE_0423b-ftnote.024"/> Whilst at the present time the law predominantly manifests in accordance with the interests of dominant neoliberal-led globalisation(s),<ref target="BAWE_0423b-ftnote.025"/> its emanicipatory potential is also apparent in relation to communities of suffering around the world. </s><s n="s3.4;p13.69">In addition to resistance and activism <hi rend="italic">within</hi> law,<ref target="BAWE_0423b-ftnote.026"/> it becomes possible to imagine resistance to the current conception <hi rend="italic">of</hi> law. </s><s n="s4.4;p13.69">If 'law' itself is a malleable concept and can be viewed as a "discursive terrain",<ref target="BAWE_0423b-ftnote.027"/> it can be re-thought as a powerful tool for those with less power in today's world order. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0423b-ftnote.024"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">See, for example: Antony Anghie, 'Time Present and Time Past: Globalization, International Financial Institutions, and the Third World' (1999-2000) 32 <hi rend="italic">New York University Journal of International Law and Politics</hi> 243; Balakrishnan Rajagopal, <hi rend="italic">International Law from Below</hi> (2003) ch 4; China Miéville, <hi rend="italic">Between Equal Rights: A Marxist Theory of International Law</hi> (2005) ch 6; and B.S. Chimni, 'International Institutions Today: An Imperial Global State in the Making' (2004) 15 <hi rend="italic">European Journal of International Law</hi> 1. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0423b-ftnote.025"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Jayan Nayar, 'Taking Empire Seriously: Empire's Law, Peoples' Law and the World Tribunal on Iraq' in Amy Bartholomew (ed), <hi rend="italic">Empire's Law: The American Imperial Project and the 'War to Remake the World'</hi> (2006) 320. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0423b-ftnote.026"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">For a comprehensive discussion and examples of this approach, namely the subaltern cosmopolitan legality school of thought, see: Boaventura de Sousa Santos and César A. Rodríguez-Garavito (eds), <hi rend="italic">Law and Globalization from Below: Towards a Cosmopolitan Legality</hi> (2005) chap 1. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0423b-ftnote.027"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ratna Kapur, 'Revisioning the Role of Law in Women's Human Rights Struggles' in Saladin Meckled-Garcia and Basack Cali (eds), <hi rend="italic">The Legalization of Human Rights: Multidisciplinary Perspectives on Human Rights and Human Rights Law</hi> (2006) 101. </s></p></note><p n="p14.69"><s n="s1.1;p14.69">Of particular relevance, the Hardt and Negri "multitude" conception imagines an alternative global order, to be manifested in part through a project of re-thinking the mainstream political form of democracy in a global world.<ref target="BAWE_0423b-ftnote.028"/> In this regard, a peoples' law perspective offers an approach to resisting and confronting the law, and effect a re-appropriation of the common (including free access to and control over knowledge, information, communication and affects<ref target="BAWE_0423b-ftnote.029"/>). </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0423b-ftnote.028"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Caleb Smith and Enrico Minardi, Interview with Michael Hardt (North Carolina, 5 March 2004) question 2 &lt;<seg type="URL" n="http://www.theminnesotareview.org/journal/ns61/hardt.htm"/>> accessed on 10 March 2007. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0423b-ftnote.029"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Chamsy el-Ojeili and Patrick Hayden, <hi rend="italic">Critical Theories of Globalization</hi> (2006), 203. </s></p></note><p n="p15.69"><s n="s1.1;p15.69">A peoples' law perspective facilitates the re-appropriation of 'law' primarily through the recognition of the 'crime of silence' and a re-claiming (by subaltern, less powerful singularities) of judgment, authorship, control and action in relation to specific violations as well as in relation to the wider complex global interactions, processes and institutions of the present hegemonic world order. <ref target="BAWE_0423b-ftnote.030"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0423b-ftnote.030"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Nayar, above no 25, 321-322. </s></p></note></div2><div2><head rend="bold">Application of the Foundational Principles</head><div3><head rend="bold italic">(i) Judgment </head><p n="p16.69"><s n="s1.1;p16.69">The primary issue for judgment is the accountability of the UN for health violations of the Roma community in the IDP camps administered by UNMIK. </s></p><p n="p17.69"><s n="s1.1;p17.69">The Tribunal process commences with a repudiation of the normalcy of 'expected' and 'inevitable' delays, inconveniences and lack of funds in a post-conflict situation administered by the UN, and provides a platform from which the Roma can reclaim their histories, future and 'truth' by re-framing their treatment by UNMIK from a discourse of 'mere misfortune' to one of judgment of violations. </s></p><p n="p18.69"><s n="s1.1;p18.69">Thus, the Tribunal aims challenge the 'crime of silence' in relation to the health violations of the Roma in the IDP camps and, as a wider concern, seeks to situate the violations within a broader global movement that examines the systematic, structural violation against minority communities resulting from a privileging of other interests (for example, 'development', 'nation-building', 'democracy', 'security' and the interests of transnational corporations) over human rights relating to health and life. </s></p></div3><div3><head rend="bold italic">(ii) Authorship</head><p n="p19.69"><s n="s1.1;p19.69">The Tribunal is a forum for the Roma to resist the dominant ideology by reclaiming the power or right to author their version of the 'law' and to define the structures and nature of social relationships conducive to a life of security and welfare. </s></p><p n="p20.69"><s n="s1.2;p20.69">The dominant legality promises, through myriad human rights treaties, international and national legislation, a world order of equality and compassion. </s><s n="s2.2;p20.69">In relation to the specific situation, multiple human rights standards exist that are applicable to the Roma in this context<ref target="BAWE_0423b-ftnote.031"/> that have ostensibly been breached by the (in)actions of UNMIK. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0423b-ftnote.031"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">For example, the International Covenant on Civil and Political Rights, the International Covenant on the Rights of the Child, the International Covenant on Economic, Social and Cultural Rights, guidelines in relation to IDPs, Declaration on the Rights of Persons Belonging to National or Ethnic, Religious and Linguistic Minorities, among others. </s></p></note><p n="p21.69"><s n="s1.2;p21.69">In light of this and as steps taken within the current legal framework were unable to assist the Roma effectively, the Tribunal is an attempt to re-think the 'law' and to generate imaginations for new political action. </s><s n="s2.2;p21.69">The adopted discourse does not derive its validity from any formal source of law, nor from any validation by institutions of power but instead derives from the assertion of the power of peoples' voice and judgment. <ref target="BAWE_0423b-ftnote.032"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0423b-ftnote.032"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Nayar, above no 25, 325-326. </s></p></note></div3><div3><head rend="bold italic">(iii) Control</head><p n="p22.69"><s n="s1.1;p22.69">The Tribunal is a space for the Roma to control (and not merely participate in) the processes of decision-making and judgment in relation to the matters which affect the daily life-conditions of their communities. </s></p><p n="p23.69"><s n="s1.3;p23.69">In relation to the specific situation, it is apparent that the Roma have suffered as 'victims' of the health violations. </s><s n="s2.3;p23.69">As to the wider background conditions leading to such violations, it is important to recognise a shared responsibility, as complex interrelated global practices, inaction and relations each contribute to long-term circumstances of structural injustice. </s><s n="s3.3;p23.69">Accordingly, given this outlook, it would be beneficial ultimately to remove the focus on a 'victims' perspective' as without accepting shared responsibility, it is difficult to re-claim the responsibility, power and direct space for re-claiming truth, of each individual, which can be focused towards shared goals (representing 'a multitude of singularities').<ref target="BAWE_0423b-ftnote.033"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0423b-ftnote.033"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">For an interesting discussion of the concept of 'political responsibility' (which expands on the notions of 'fault/strict liability' and emphasises the shared responsibility of all, through action and non-action in complex global processes, for violations throughout the world, see: Iris Marion Young, 'Responsibility and Global Labor Justice' (2004) 12(4) <hi rend="italic">The Journal of Political Philosophy</hi> 365. </s></p></note></div3><div3><head rend="bold italic">(iv) Action</head><p n="p24.69"><s n="s1.1;p24.69">The Tribunal recognises the right of the Roma to effect the implementation of their alternative visions of social relationships in ways which reinforce and celebrate the diversity of humanity, for humanity. </s></p></div3></div2><div2><head rend="bold">Tribunal Initiation and Timing</head><p n="p25.69"><s n="s1.1;p25.69">It is envisaged that the Roma community and the ERRC will be the joint initiators of the Tribunal, the former for its personal experience and the latter primarily for the following reasons: knowledge of the history and discrimination against the Roma communities of Europe generally;<ref target="BAWE_0423b-ftnote.034"/> knowledge of the specific situation that is the subject of the Tribunal; continuity given ERRC's series of attempts to facilitate justice; resources and ability to organise the Tribunal and subsequently mobilise the public and other NGOs and CSOs. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0423b-ftnote.034"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">European Roma Rights Centre, 'Justice for Kosovo' (2005) 3, 4 <hi rend="italic">Roma Rights Quarterly</hi> &lt;<seg type="URL" n="http://www.errc.org/cikk.php?cikk=2511"/>> accessed on 16 March 2007. </s></p></note><p n="p26.69"><s n="s1.1;p26.69">The Tribunal will be held during the period of UN discussion regarding the future status of Kosovo,<ref target="BAWE_0423b-ftnote.035"/> in order to attract maximum attention from the public/media, and to place pressure on the UN and other relevant bodies to give due consideration to the violations and incorporate justice into any plans for Kosovo. <ref target="BAWE_0423b-ftnote.036"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0423b-ftnote.035"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">UNMIK, <hi rend="italic">Ban Ki-moon receives proposals for future status of UN-administered Kosovo</hi> (2007) &lt;<seg type="URL" n="www.unmikonline.org/news.htm"/>> accessed on 7 April 2007. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0423b-ftnote.036"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">This could be defined as a 'strategy of democratisation', whereby "facts and figures are given a voice, a face and a story, and [the story] told in public by people whose lives have been damaged", see Ulrich Beck, <hi rend="italic">Power in the Global Age</hi> (2005) 245. </s></p></note></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">PART II: TRIBUNAL FRAMEWORK</head><div2><head rend="bold">Originating declaration (judgment)</head><p n="p27.69"><s n="s1.1;p27.69">Through its (in)actions, the UN/UNMIK has violated the health, lives and livelihood prospects of the Roma community housed at the IDP camps in Kosovo. </s></p><p n="p28.69"><s n="s1.1;p28.69">As a starting point, the Tribunal will consider the following violations: </s></p><p n="p29.69"><s n="s1.1;p29.69">Against the Roma community: </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p30.69"><s n="s1.1;p30.69">a wrong of inaction: neglect in the duty to take positive action to rectify health violations expeditiously </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p31.69"><s n="s1.1;p31.69">a wrong of silence: neglect of the duty to give privilege and duty to voices of suffering </s></p><p n="p32.69"><s n="s1.1;p32.69">Against humanity (in addition to the above): </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p33.69"><s n="s1.1;p33.69">a wrong of exclusion: complicity in the exclusion of the voices and visions of communities of less power in the current hegemonic world order, as a result of the privileging of economic and political interests over peoples' aspirations of security, well-being and justice </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">Participants, Testimony and Roles</head><p n="p34.69"><s n="s1.2;p34.69">The Tribunal will undertake to gather evidence and documentation systematically in order to meet the most rigorous requirements of international legal norms with a view to exposing the violations of, and gaps in relation to, existing promises of human rights. </s><s n="s2.2;p34.69">Further, participants will be requested to provide sex- and age-disaggregated data where available, to reflect the different impact of the health violations on women, men and children, in order to expose details of any systematic violations. </s></p><p n="p35.69"><s n="s1.1;p35.69">The following people will be invited to participate in the Tribunal process, to provide testimony/take action as indicated: </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p36.69"><s n="s1.1;p36.69">(1) Roma representatives and their supporters (predominately from ERRC) </s></p><p n="p37.69"><s n="s1.1;p37.69">Mix of first person and advocacy testimony in relation to: </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p38.69"><s n="s1.2;p38.69">(a) The IDP camp environment, health violations suffered, (in)action taken by UNMIK, steps taken by the Roma in response to the health violations. </s><s n="s2.2;p38.69">Due consideration to the safety of the Roma and repercussions resulting from their involvement in the tribunal will be required.<ref target="BAWE_0423b-ftnote.037"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0423b-ftnote.037"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">European Roma Rights Centre, above no 13, 2. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">It is noted in the Complaint that "Their names are not public because of serious concerns of [sic] their safety and fears of any violence or other repercussion following this complaint." </s></p></note><p rend="ordered" n="p39.69"><s n="s1.1;p39.69">(b) The wider context of discrimination against the Roma community in Europe and Kosovo, the health violations at the IDP camps, steps taken by ERRC to attempt to achieve justice. </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p40.69"><s n="s1.1;p40.69">(2) UNMIK and UN representatives </s></p><p n="p41.69"><s n="s1.1;p41.69">First person testimony in relation to: the wider context of UNMIK's role in Kosovo, the IDP camp environment, steps taken to relocate and medically treat the Roma, the role of and any accountability attributable to Kosovo municipalities/Ministry of Health as far as they existed during the relevant time period. </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p42.69"><s n="s1.1;p42.69">(3) Medical experts (WHO/independent) </s></p><p n="p43.69"><s n="s1.1;p43.69">First person testimony in relation to the causes, severity and consequences of the health violations suffered. </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p44.69"><s n="s1.1;p44.69">(4) The jury </s></p><p n="p45.69"><s n="s1.1;p45.69">A jury panel consisting of representatives from the Roma community and experts in the fields of human rights, minority rights, Kosovo, health and international law will be asked to deliberate on the evidence presented and reach a formal Tribunal decision. </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p46.69"><s n="s1.1;p46.69">(5) The audience </s></p><p n="p47.69"><s n="s1.2;p47.69">The Tribunal will be open to the members of the Roma community and their supporters, members of the UN/UN missions (as representatives of the key institution of focus), and the public generally. </s><s n="s2.2;p47.69">The audience will be requested to deliberate on the evidence presented, galvanise world public opinion and reach as many people as possible who can take action in response to the truths revealed. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">Issues for Consideration</head><p n="p48.69"><s n="s1.1;p48.69">The Tribunal process follows a twofold conceptual framework, namely an investigation of the wrongs committed against the Roma people in the IDP camps, as well as an investigation into the unjust background and structural conditions that ought to be addressed in order to re-claim the 'law' from a more compassionate perspective. </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p49.69"><s n="s1.1;p49.69">(1) Investigation into the severe legal, political, social, ethical, cultural wrongs against the Roma people including specific crimes and violations. </s></p><p n="p50.69"><s n="s1.1;p50.69">In order to reach a decision, evidence and testimonies will be considered by the Tribunal, and decisions reached, in relation to the following issues: </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p51.69"><s n="s1.1;p51.69">Whether the treatment of the Roma in the camps violated existing international, regional and national laws specifically, as well as humanity's values of peace, justice and non-violence generally. </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p52.69"><s n="s1.1;p52.69">The accountability and liability of the UN/UNMIK (and other relevant UN departments or agencies, or other institutions or groups generally) in relation to the health violations. </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p53.69"><s n="s1.1;p53.69">Whether international and regional institutions forming the current world legal order, such as the European Court of Human Rights, are guilty of complicity in their failure to respond positively to requests for assistance. </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p54.69"><s n="s1.1;p54.69">(2) Investigation into the background and structural conditions that made possible the crimes and violations. </s></p><p n="p55.69"><s n="s1.1;p55.69">Beyond determining the specific crimes committed, and re-claiming voices, regarding the accepted normalisation of the post-conflict treatment of the Roma community, the situation raises wider issues of concern that are critical for the collective decisions of the Tribunal and world public opinion. </s></p><p n="p56.69"><s n="s1.1;p56.69">In order to consider the broader implications, the following issues will be considered: </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p57.69"><s n="s1.4;p57.69">The role of the UN in post-conflict situations (particularly the unprecedented roles undertaken by evolving peacebuilding missions). </s><s n="s2.4;p57.69">Why is the UN unable or unwilling to uphold its own human rights agenda in relation to individuals under its express care? </s><s n="s3.4;p57.69">What interests and agendas does the UN privilege in such circumstances? </s><s n="s4.4;p57.69">What ideology is revealed through the UN's democratisation project, and what implications does this have for the incorporation of post-conflict states into the 'modern' (economic) world order, as a continuing colonisation project?<ref target="BAWE_0423b-ftnote.038"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0423b-ftnote.038"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Balakrishan Rajagopal, 'From Modernization to Democratization' in Richard Falk, Lester Edwin J. Ruiz and R.B.J.Walker (eds) <hi rend="italic">Reframing the International: Law, Culture, Politics</hi> (2002) chap 7. </s></p></note><p rend="ordered" n="p58.69"><s n="s1.2;p58.69">The impact of the specific situation on the credibility of the UN (and other international political-legal institutions and courts) generally. </s><s n="s2.2;p58.69">What are the future implications for the role of the UN system and the international human rights framework to provide a credible means by which the aspirations and the will of the global population may be effected? </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p59.69"><s n="s1.3;p59.69">The impact of the camp situation on the global health environment and human rights. </s><s n="s2.3;p59.69">Whilst the UN selected the locations of the IDP camps, what action, if any, should be taken against the owners of the Trepca mine? </s><s n="s3.3;p59.69">What implications arise in relation to the ability of corporations to pollute the environment with impunity? </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p60.69"><s n="s1.2;p60.69">The impact of the situation on the Roma diaspora generally throughout Europe. </s><s n="s2.2;p60.69">What implications does the (in)action by the UN, as the purported highest advocate of human rights, have for the world order in relation to communities with less power? </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p61.69"><s n="s1.1;p61.69">The impact of the Kosovo circumstances and war that lead to the displacement of the Roma community and the need for UNMIK to administer the IDP camps.<ref target="BAWE_0423b-ftnote.039"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0423b-ftnote.039"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">It is noted that this issue is very complex and, for the most part, beyond the scope of the present Tribunal. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">For an interesting and instructive application of a peoples' law perspective to the issue of war, see: World Tribunal of Iraq website at &lt;<seg type="URL" n="http://www.worldtribunal.org"/>> accessed on 10 April 2007. </s></p></note></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">PART III: STRATEGIES AND VISION OF TRIBUNAL</head><div2><head rend="bold">The Tribunal as an Event</head><p n="p62.69"><s n="s1.1;p62.69">Through the use of the peoples' law principles outlined above, the Tribunal (including its announcement and organisation) will effect declarative, deliberative and mandating functions in relation to the specific violations as follows: </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p63.69"><s n="s1.3;p63.69">(1) The Tribunal represents a supportive public space in which to articulate and create a historical record of the violations, and to highlight the failure of existing mechanisms to address human rights abuses. </s><s n="s2.3;p63.69">This re-claims 'law' for the violated community, affirms solidarity with minority communities, and educates the public. </s><s n="s3.3;p63.69">Instead of continually reliving 'yesterday's' world legal order, all stages of the Tribunal will assume conscious responsibility (both individual and shared) for the construction of an alternative reality. </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p64.69"><s n="s1.2;p64.69">(2) The Tribunal will provide a process of listening, reflection and evaluation. </s><s n="s2.2;p64.69">A considered and informed decision shall be rendered on the issues presented to the Tribunal, with such decision to be widely distributed throughout the world for the benefit of individuals and groups struggling for peace and justice. </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p65.69"><s n="s1.2;p65.69">(3) To this end, the Tribunal will highlight existing action, consider and decide upon strategic action to be taken at all appropriate levels, with the aim of reclaiming the power of enforcement in terms of acting upon the judgments reached to mobilise world public opinion to invigorate social and political pressure. </s><s n="s2.2;p65.69">The purpose of such pressure will be to contribute to efforts to bring the UN/UNMIK to account as part of the overall campaign to put an end to both the impunity enjoyed by international institutions in relation to violations against minority communities, and the privileging of economic or political interests over basic human rights concerns. </s></p><p n="p66.69"><s n="s1.1;p66.69">Any such strategic action is likely to include: the removal of all Roma from contaminated areas; the provision of appropriate and comprehensive medical treatment to all affected persons desiring such treatment; ongoing medical, financial and other relevant support for long-term health consequences and any other consequences arising from the delay in rectifying the violations (such as loss of employment opportunities and learning difficulties in children due to permanent cognitive dysfunction). </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">The Tribunal as a Process</head><p n="p67.69"><s n="s1.1;p67.69">In addition to any mandated action in relation to the specific subject violations, the Tribunal is a contribution to a peoples' law movement generally (through a recording of alternative 'truths' to preserve against the dominant writing of history) and a practical application of a new political project that rejects the current unjust world order and imagines alternatives. </s></p><p n="p68.69"><s n="s1.3;p68.69">It is likely that issues will arise during the Tribunal process that will require further investigation, deliberation and action that may not be finalised within the scope of the Tribunal. </s><s n="s2.3;p68.69">The Tribunal process ought to indicate at least such need and call on further initiatives to follow these up. </s><s n="s3.3;p68.69">The power of enforcement lies in the ability of the Tribunal, as a component part of a creative global movement for peace and justice, to appeal to public conscience and to mobilise around the emerging truths to create political pressure throughout the world. </s></p><p n="p69.69"><s n="s1.2;p69.69">The actual steps to be taken, and the relevant actors to call upon, will depend on the Tribunal process. </s><s n="s2.2;p69.69">However, at this stage, it is envisaged that recommended options may include: the agreement by relevant NGOs or other civil society organisations to monitor the situation in Kosovo; the establishment of further tribunals in relation to human rights in UN missions; a series of workshops within UN bodies, and between UN representatives and relevant groups to learn from the violations and discuss alternative future approaches or priorities in peacekeeping.<ref target="BAWE_0423b-ftnote.040"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0423b-ftnote.040"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">For a discussion of the difficulties related to the attempted mainstreaming of human rights into all political, development, and other initiatives by the UN, see: Hurst Hannum, 'Human Rights in Conflict Resolution: The Role of the Officer of the High Commissioner for Human Rights in UN Peacemaking and Peacebuilding' (2006) 28(1) <hi rend="italic">Human Rights Quarterly</hi> 1. </s></p></note></div2></div1></body><back><div1 type="bibliography"><head rend="bold">BIBLIOGRAPHY</head><p>(Australian Citation System: <seg type="URL" n="http://mulr.law.unimelb.edu.au/PDFs/aglc_dl.pdf"/>)</p><div2 type="bibliography"><head rend="bold">Books/Chapters/Reports</head><p>Ulrich Beck, <hi rend="italic">Power in the Global Age</hi> (2005) 245.</p><p>China Miéville, <hi rend="italic">Between Equal Rights: A Marxist Theory of International Law</hi> (2005) ch 6.</p><p>Jayan Nayar, 'Taking Empire Seriously: Empire's Law, Peoples' Law and the World Tribunal on Iraq' in Amy Bartholomew (ed), <hi rend="italic">Empire's Law: The American Imperial Project and the 'War to Remake the World'</hi> (2006) 320. </p><p>Chamsy el-Ojeili and Patrick Hayden, <hi rend="italic">Critical Theories of Globalization</hi> (2006).</p><p>Balakrishan Rajagopal, 'From Modernization to Democratization' in Richard Falk, Lester Edwin J. Ruiz and R.B.J.Walker (eds) <hi rend="italic">Reframing the International: Law, Culture, Politics</hi> (2002) chap 7.</p><p>Balakrishnan Rajagopal, <hi rend="italic">International Law from Below</hi> (2003) ch 4.</p><p>Boaventura de Sousa Santos and César A. Rodríguez-Garavito (eds), <hi rend="italic">Law and Globalization from Below: Towards a Cosmopolitan Legality</hi> (2005) chap 1.</p></div2><div2 type="bibliography"><head rend="bold">Journal Articles</head><p>Antony Anghie, 'Time Present and Time Past: Globalization, International Financial Institutions, and the Third World' (1999-2000) 32 <hi rend="italic">New York University Journal of International Law and Politics</hi> 243.</p><p>B.S. Chimni, 'International Institutions Today: An Imperial Global State in the Making' (2004) 15 <hi rend="italic">European Journal of International Law</hi> 1.</p><p>European Roma Rights Centre, 'Justice for Kosovo' (2005) 3, 4 <hi rend="italic">Roma Rights Quarterly</hi> &lt;<seg type="URL" n="http://www.errc.org/cikk.php?cikk=2511"/>> accessed on 16 March 2007.</p><p>Hurst Hannum, 'Human Rights in Conflict Resolution: The Role of the Officer of the High Commissioner for Human Rights in UN Peacemaking and Peacebuilding' (2006) 28(1) <hi rend="italic">Human Rights Quarterly</hi> 1.</p><p>Ratna Kapur, 'Revisioning the Role of Law in Women's Human Rights Struggles' in Saladin Meckled-Garcia and Basack Cali (eds), <hi rend="italic">The Legalization of Human Rights: Multidisciplinary Perspectives on Human Rights and Human Rights Law</hi> (2006) 101.</p><p>Frédéric Mégret and Florian Hoffmann, 'The UN as a Human Rights Violator? Some Reflections on the United Nations Changing Human Rights Responsibilities' (2003) 25 <hi rend="italic">Human Rights Quarterly</hi> 314.</p><p>Jayan Nayar, 'A People's Tribunal Against the Crime of Silence? The Politics of Judgement and an Agenda for People's Law' (2001) 2 <hi rend="italic">Law, Social Justice &amp; Global Development</hi> [Part 3] &lt;<seg type="URL" n="http://elj"/>.<name type="university"/>.ac.uk/global/issue/2001-2/nayar.html> accessed on 22 March 2007.</p><p>Shilu Tong, Peter Baghurst, Anthony McMichael, Michael Sawyer and Jane Mudge, 'Lifetime exposure to environmental lead and children's intelligence at 11-13 years: the Port Pirie cohort study' (1996) 312 <hi rend="italic">British Medical Journal</hi> 1569.</p><p>Iris Marion Young, 'Responsibility and Global Labor Justice' (2004) 12(4) <hi rend="italic">The Journal of Political Philosophy</hi> 365.</p></div2><div2 type="bibliography"><head rend="bold">Reports, Submissions and Legal Documents</head><p>European Roma Rights Centre, <hi rend="italic">Criminal Complaint Against Unknown Persons</hi> (2005) filed at the Office of Public Prosecutor in Kosovo (2005) &lt;<seg type="URL" n="www.errc.org"/>> accessed on 12 March 2007.</p><p>European Roma Rights Centre, <hi rend="italic">Written Comments of the ERRC Concerning Kosovo for Consideration by the United Nations Human Rights Committee on the Occasion of Review of the Country Report of Task Forces on UNMIK</hi> (2006) &lt;<seg type="URL" n="www.errc.org"/>> accessed on 12 March 2007.</p><p>Sandra Molano and Andrej Andejew, 'First Phase of Public Health Project on Lead Pollution in Mitrovica Region' (2000) World Health Organization.</p><p>Marek Antoni Nowicki, <hi rend="italic">Special Report No.1 on the compatibility with recognized international standards of UNMIK Regulation No. 2000/47 on the Status, Privileges and Immunities of KFOR and UNMIK and Their Personnel in Kosovo (18 August 2000) and on the implementation of the above regulation</hi> (2001) Ombudsperson Institution in Kosovo 18-19. </p><p>Niamh Reilly and Linda Posluszny, 'Women Testify: A Planning Guide for Popular Tribunals &amp; Hearings' (2005) <hi rend="italic">Center for Women's Global Leadership</hi>.</p><p>World Health Organization, <hi rend="italic">Preliminary Report on Blood Levels in North Mitrovica and Zvecan</hi> (2004). </p><p>World Health Organization, <hi rend="italic">Capillary Blood Lead Confirmation and Critical Lead-Related Health Situation of the Roma Camps Children</hi> (2004) 3.</p></div2><div2 type="bibliography"><head rend="bold">Other Sources</head><p>European Roma Rights Centre, <hi rend="italic">European Court of Human Rights Has No Jurisdiction in Kosovo Lead Poisoning Case</hi> (2006) &lt;<seg type="URL" n="www.errc.org/cikk.php?cikk=2568&amp;archiv=1"/>> accessed on 26 March 2007.</p><p>'Kosovo's Displaced People Treated for Lead Poisoning', <hi rend="italic">Environment News Service</hi> (New York), 1 September 2006, &lt;<seg type="URL" n="www.ens-newswire.com/ens/sep2006-09-01-01.asp"/>> accessed on 7 April 2007.</p><p>Shannon Meehan and Nicole Mailman, <hi rend="italic">Refugee Voices: Lead Poisoning among Displaced Roma in Kosovo</hi> (2005) Refugees International &lt;<seg type="URL" n="www.refugeesinternational.org/section/stories/romavoices3"/>> accessed on 7 April 2007;</p><p>Minority Rights Group International website &lt;<seg type="URL" n="www.minorityrights.org"/>> accessed on 4 April 2007.</p><p><hi rend="italic">Regulation No. 2000/47 on the Status, Privileges and Immunities of KFOR and UNMIK and Their Personnel in Kosovo</hi>, UNMIK/REG/2000/47 (2000) &lt;<seg type="URL" n="http://www.unmikonline.org/regulations/2000/reg47-00.htm"/>> accessed on 10 March 2007.</p><p><hi rend="italic">Resolution on the Establishment of UNMIK</hi>, SC Res 1244, UN Doc S/RES/1244 (1999).</p><p>Caleb Smith and Enrico Minardi, Interview with Michael Hardt (North Carolina, 5 March 2004) &lt;<seg type="URL" n="http://www.theminnesotareview.org/journal/ns61/hardt.htm"/>> accessed on 10 March 2007.</p><p>UNMIK, <hi rend="italic">UNMIK At a Glance</hi> &lt;<seg type="URL" n="http://www.unmikonline.org/intro.htm"/>> accessed on 26 March 2007.</p><p>UNMIK, <hi rend="italic">Ban Ki-moon receives proposals for future status of UN-administered Kosovo</hi> (2007) &lt;<seg type="URL" n="www.unmikonline.org/news.htm"/>> accessed on 7 April 2007.</p><p>UNMIK, <hi rend="italic">Kosovo: Roma return to new homes in Mitrovica with help from UN and partners</hi> (2007) &lt;<seg type="URL" n="www.unmikonline.org/news.htm"/>> accessed on 7 April 2007.</p><p>World Tribunal of Iraq website at &lt;<seg type="URL" n="http://www.worldtribunal.org"/>> accessed on 10 April 2007.</p></div2></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
