<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_0424d" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Vortex Laboratory Report</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">The document has a title page which contains:
document title
title part</note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">deleted: page numbers, date</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">2</p><p n="date">2007-07</p><p n="module title">Technological Science II</p><p n="module code">ES2A7</p><p n="genre family">Methodology recount</p><p n="discipline">Engineering</p><p n="disciplinary group">PS</p><p n="grade">D</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">4411</p><p n="number of s-units">241</p><p n="number of p">112</p><p n="number of tables">1</p><p n="number of figures">8</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">50</p><p n="number of lists">3</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">14</p><p n="abstract present">abstract present</p><p n="average words per s-unit">18.3</p><p n="average s-units per p">2.2</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">f</p><p n="year of birth">1987</p><p n="first language">English</p><p n="education">UK2</p><p n="course">Engineering</p><p n="student ID">0424</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><titlePart rend="bold">University of <name type="university"/> School of Engineering</titlePart><docTitle><titlePart rend="bold">Vortex Laboratory Report</titlePart></docTitle><titlePart rend="bold">By<name type="student ID"/></titlePart><titlePart>Report Reference Code: ES2A7L5 Affiliation: Year 2 Engineering Report of laboratory performed on: Monday 19 <hi rend="sup">th</hi> February 2007</titlePart></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="abstract"><head rend="bold">Summary</head><p n="p1.112"><s n="s1.1;p1.112">This report investigates the drag force on a cylinder using the method of pressure distribution around a cylinder. </s></p><p n="p2.112"><s n="s1.3;p2.112">A circular cylinder was immersed in the fluid air, using a large low speed wind-tunnel, in the School Of Engineering's laboratory. </s><s n="s2.3;p2.112">Three different scenarios simulating turbulent as well as laminar flow, were investigated, and the factors which affected the drag on the cylinder were investigated. </s><s n="s3.3;p2.112">The importance of the Reynolds Number of the fluid flow was also determined. </s></p><p n="p3.112"><s n="s1.1;p3.112">The report also investigates how to reduce the effect of drag on a body, and how the process of streamlining occurs and its dependence on the magnitude of the Reynolds Number of the fluid flow. </s></p><p n="p4.112"><s n="s1.1;p4.112">It is shown that the drag force was found to be dependent on the flow pattern of the fluid and hence the velocity and density of the fluid the body was immersed in, and the dimensions and shape of the body itself. </s></p><p n="p5.112"><s n="s1.4;p5.112">It was concluded that the drag forces depend on the flow structure in the wake formed at the rear of the cylinder. </s><s n="s2.4;p5.112">The wider the wake is, the higher the drag forces are. </s><s n="s3.4;p5.112">The wake is formed when the flow around the cylinder separates, and the point at which this separates is determined by the Reynolds's number of the flow, which is due to a combination of the size of the body and the speed of flow. </s><s n="s4.4;p5.112">It was also deduced, that in order to reduce drag forces on a body, its shape should be designed to be as streamlined as possible, because streamlining reduces the size of the wake, hence reducing the drag force. </s></p></div1><div1 type="front-back-matter"><head rend="underlined bold">Table of Contents</head><p/></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Introduction</head><p n="p6.112"><s n="s1.5;p6.112">The total drag on any body consists of skin friction drag and form drag. </s><s n="s2.5;p6.112">The skin friction drag is a result of the viscous forces acting on the body while the form drag is due to the unbalanced pressure forces on the body. </s><s n="s3.5;p6.112">The sum of the two is called total or profile drag. </s><s n="s4.5;p6.112">There are several methods that can be used to determine the drag forces, including prediction of drag from wake measurements and from the pressure distribution around a cylinder. </s><s n="s5.5;p6.112">The procedure used during this investigation was to measure the pressure distribution around a cylinder. </s></p><p n="p7.112"><s n="s1.4;p7.112">Flow over a cylinder is a primary fluid mechanics problem of practical importance. </s><s n="s2.4;p7.112">The flow field over the cylinder is symmetric at low values of Reynolds number. </s><s n="s3.4;p7.112">As the Reynolds number increases, flow begins to separate behind the cylinder causing vortex shedding which is an unsteady phenomenon. </s><s n="s4.4;p7.112">The basic theory of fluid flow around a smooth cylinder dates back to nineteenth century hydrodynamics. </s></p><p n="p8.112"><s n="s1.2;p8.112">The theory presented here predicts the velocity and pressure distribution about the circumference of a circular cylinder immersed in a fluid stream. </s><s n="s2.2;p8.112">The same theory predicts the lift and drag forces on the cylinder and can be applied to airfoils in modern aircraft and turbo-machinery applications. </s></p><p n="p9.112"><s n="s1.5;p9.112">In the basic hydrodynamic theory for this experiment, the fluid is assumed to be inviscid and incompressible. </s><s n="s2.5;p9.112">The flow which is at a large distance from the immersed body is assumed to be uniform. </s><s n="s3.5;p9.112">The flow is also assumed to be irrotational. </s><s n="s4.5;p9.112">When the fluid encounters a smooth surface it is assumed to slip tangentially, owing without friction or separation; the fluid neither penetrates the surface nor leaves a gap. </s><s n="s5.5;p9.112">This condition is sufficient to yield a unique solution to the governing flow equations. </s></p><p n="p10.112"><s n="s1.1;p10.112">This boundary condition differs from the more realistic "no slip" condition applied to viscous flows. </s></p><p n="p11.112"><s n="s1.1;p11.112">In this experiment, the total pressure at various locations along the surface of a cylinder placed in a wind tunnel stream is measured </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">2.0 Theory</head><div2><head rend="underlined bold">Pressure Distribution In a Cylinder</head><p n="p12.112"><s n="s1.2;p12.112">Figure 1 shows a cross section of a circular cylinder of radius a in a uniform stream flowing from left to right. </s><s n="s2.2;p12.112">The fluid speed at a large distance from the centre is U∞ and the corresponding pressure is P∞ </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0424d-pic.001"><head rend="underlined bold">Figure 1: Cross-Sectional View of Circular Cylinder in a Cross Flow</head></figure><p n="p13.112"><s n="s1.1;p13.112">The angle <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0424d-form.001"/> takes the values from 0 to <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0424d-form.002"/> radians </s></p><p n="p14.112"><s n="s1.1;p14.112">The purpose of this experiment is served if one accepts the analytical result for the tangential component of the velocity vector on the cylinder surface is </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p15.112"><s n="s1.1;p15.112"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0424d-form.003"/><hi rend="bold"> Equation 1</hi> <ref target="BAWE_0424d-ftnote.001"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0424d-ftnote.001"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1"><hi rend="underlined"><seg type="URL" n="http://www2"/>. <name type="university"/> .ac.uk/fac/sci/eng/staff/pjt/es3c9/lecture_16_Final06.pdf</hi> Accessed on 15th March </s></p></note><p n="p16.112"><s n="s1.1;p16.112">That is at the surface of the cylinder the fluid flows according the above equation. </s></p><p n="p17.112"><s n="s1.1;p17.112">While the radial component <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0424d-form.004"/> </s></p><p n="p18.112"><s n="s1.3;p18.112">The x-axis in the approaching flow, the top surface of the cylinder, and the x-axis in the retreating flow merge to form one valid streamline. </s><s n="s2.3;p18.112">Similarly, the x-axis in the approaching flow, the bottom surface of the cylinder, and the x-axis of the retreating flow is another valid streamline. </s><s n="s3.3;p18.112">These two streamlines are referred to as the stagnation streamlines and wrap tightly around the cylinder as suggested in figure 1. </s></p><p n="p19.112"><s n="s1.1;p19.112">The Bernoulli equation is valid, for steady, inviscid, incompressible flow along a streamline, and will be used to evaluate the pressure distribution along the streamline that originates far upstream where flow is undisturbed. </s></p><p n="p20.112"><s n="s1.1;p20.112">Ignoring gravitational forces: </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p21.112"><s n="s1.1;p21.112"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0424d-form.005"/><hi rend="bold"> Equation 2</hi> <ref target="BAWE_0424d-ftnote.002"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0424d-ftnote.002"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1"><hi rend="underlined"><seg type="URL" n="http://www2"/>. <name type="university"/> .ac.uk/fac/sci/eng/staff/pjt/es3c9/lecture_16_Final06.pdf</hi> Accessed on 15th March </s></p></note><p n="p22.112"><s n="s1.1;p22.112">Where <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0424d-form.006"/> is the fluid speed at a large distance from the centre and the corresponding pressure is <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0424d-form.007"/>, while <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0424d-form.008"/> is the tangential fluid speed along the cylinder surface and <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0424d-form.009"/> is the corresponding static pressure. </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p23.112"><s rend="bold" n="s1.2;p23.112">Rearranging (II)........... </s><s n="s2.2;p23.112"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0424d-form.010"/><hi rend="bold"> Equation 3</hi> </s></p><p n="p24.112"><s n="s1.1;p24.112">Substituting for flow speed <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0424d-form.011"/>, <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0424d-form.012"/> gives </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p25.112"><s n="s1.1;p25.112"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0424d-form.013"/><hi rend="bold"> Equation 4</hi> </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p26.112"><s n="s1.1;p26.112"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0424d-form.014"/><hi rend="bold"> Equation 5</hi> </s></p><p n="p27.112"><s n="s1.1;p27.112">The difference in the pressures between the surface and undisturbed free stream is </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p28.112"><s n="s1.1;p28.112"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0424d-form.015"/> Equation 6 </s></p><p n="p29.112"><s n="s1.1;p29.112">In particular, for a non-rotating cylinder which was used in the procedure </s></p><p n="p30.112"><s n="s1.1;p30.112">K=0 </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p31.112"><s n="s1.1;p31.112"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0424d-form.016"/><hi rend="bold"> Equation 7</hi> </s></p><p n="p32.112"><s n="s1.2;p32.112">The Pressure coefficient which is a dimensionless value which acts as a means of indicating the local pressure at some point of interest around a body, and is independent of velocity . </s><s n="s2.2;p32.112">It is defined as </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p33.112"><s n="s1.1;p33.112"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0424d-form.017"/><hi rend="bold"> Equation 8</hi> </s></p><p n="p34.112"><s n="s1.3;p34.112">where <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0424d-form.018"/> and <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0424d-form.019"/> denote the fluid density and the surface pressure at. </s><s n="s2.3;p34.112"><hi rend="italic">Cp</hi> is called the pressure coefficient. </s><s n="s3.3;p34.112">It is dimensionless quantity. </s></p><p n="p35.112"><s n="s1.1;p35.112">The graph of the equation is shown in figure 2 on the next page. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0424d-fig.001"><head><hi rend="bold">Figure 2- Graph of pressure coefficient</hi> <ref target="BAWE_0424d-ftnote.003"/><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0424d-ftnote.003"><p n="pn1.1"> F.M .White <hi rend="italic">Fluid Mechanics</hi> 5th Edition ( McGraw Hill, 2003)</p></note></head></figure><p n="p36.112"><s n="s1.1;p36.112">It takes the value of 1 at both the forward and rearward stagnation points and descending to the minimum -3 at <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0424d-form.020"/> before recovering back to the stagnation value at <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0424d-form.021"/>.The pressure coefficient is symmetric </s></p><p n="p37.112"><s n="s1.1;p37.112">about both the x and y axes. </s></p><p n="p38.112"><s n="s1.1;p38.112">The surface pressure <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0424d-form.022"/> at <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0424d-form.023"/> denoted by the symbol <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0424d-form.024"/>, is called the stagnation pressure, or total pressure of the flow; obviously, <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0424d-form.025"/>. </s></p><p n="p39.112"><s n="s1.3;p39.112">The quantity <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0424d-form.026"/> is often called the dynamic pressure. </s><s n="s2.3;p39.112">It is the kinetic energy per unit volume of the distant stream, and is one of the terms in the Bernoulli's equation. </s><s n="s3.3;p39.112">While <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0424d-form.027"/> is the static pressure of the distant stream. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined bold">Drag and Lift Forces</head><p n="p40.112"><s n="s1.2;p40.112">When any body moves through a fluid, an interaction between the body and fluid occurs; this effect can be described in terms of the forces at the fluid- body interface. </s><s n="s2.2;p40.112">This can be described in terms of the stresses-wall shear stress <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0424d-form.028"/> due to the viscous effects and normal stresses due to pressure </s></p><p n="p41.112"><s n="s1.3;p41.112">However there are no viscous shear stresses in the analytical model, so the total force that the fluid exerts on the cylinder is obtained by integrating the pressure force over the surface area A of the cylinder. </s><s n="s2.3;p41.112">Generally, the total force can be resolved into components parallel and perpendicular to the flow direction; they are called drag, F <hi rend="sub">D</hi>, and lift, F <hi rend="sub">L</hi>, respectively. </s><s n="s3.3;p41.112">In the present case they are horizontal and vertical components: </s></p><p n="p42.112"><s n="s1.3;p42.112">When the Reynolds number is sufficiently large, i.e. </s><s n="s2.3;p42.112">Re > 10 <hi rend="sup">3</hi>, the skin friction drag of a bluff body is relatively negligible compared to its form drag. </s><s n="s3.3;p42.112">Then the measurement of the drag forces due to normal pressures acting the body will be a good approximation to the total drag. </s></p><p n="p43.112"><s n="s1.1;p43.112">For a cylinder, the body lift and drag per unit length due to normal pressure only are given by: </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p44.112"><s n="s1.1;p44.112"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0424d-form.029"/><hi rend="bold"> Equation 9</hi> </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p45.112"><s n="s1.1;p45.112"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0424d-form.030"/><hi rend="bold"> Equation 10</hi> </s></p><p n="p46.112"><s n="s1.2;p46.112">where the integrations are taken around the contour of the cylinder. </s><s n="s2.2;p46.112">A cylindrical coordinate will be used instead, equation 10 could be re-written as: </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p47.112"><s n="s1.1;p47.112"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0424d-form.031"/><hi rend="bold"> Equation 11</hi> </s></p><p n="p48.112"><s n="s1.1;p48.112">where r is the radius of the cylinder, p is the pressure, is the angular position, and the integration is taken around the cylinder, beginning at the stagnation point. </s></p><p n="p49.112"><s n="s1.1;p49.112">In the same manner, the lift force can be estimated as: </s></p><p n="p50.112"><s n="s1.1;p50.112"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0424d-form.032"/> </s></p><p n="p51.112"><s n="s1.3;p51.112">Substitutions of <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0424d-form.033"/> from equation (8) into the drag and lift force equations, and then integrating, shows that F <hi rend="sub">D</hi>, and F <hi rend="sub">L</hi> are equal to zero(0). </s><s n="s2.3;p51.112">These results indicate that both the lift and drag force as predicted by potential theory for a fixed cylinder in a uniform stream are zero. </s><s rend="italic" n="s3.3;p51.112">This does not happen in real flows as will be seen from the measurements made in the laboratory </s></p><p n="p52.112"><s n="s1.2;p52.112">That outcome is referred to as D'Alembert's paradox. </s><s n="s2.2;p52.112">It was a major point of contention in nineteenth century hydrodynamics until Ludwig Prandtl proposed his boundary layer hypothesis in 1904. </s></p><p n="p53.112"><s n="s1.1;p53.112">This paradox is due to the omission of the influence of viscosity in the flow. </s></p><p n="p54.112"><s n="s1.1;p54.112">In a practical sense the approach necessary to calculate the drag on the cylinder - or the drag coefficient is to measure the pressure along the entire cylinder surface and perform the integration of equation 10 using differential surface elements. </s></p><p n="p55.112"><s n="s1.1;p55.112">The cos <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0424d-form.034"/> term in the above equation (5) generates the horizontal projection of the pressure force. <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0424d-form.035"/> is the actual differential pressure measured by the instrumentation in the lab and the <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0424d-form.036"/> term will simply cancel out of any calculation of the drag force. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined bold">Drag Coefficient (CD)</head><p n="p56.112"><s n="s1.3;p56.112">Another important parameter is the drag coefficient. </s><s n="s2.3;p56.112">It is a non - dimensionless parameter, and is the result of the drag force divided by the pressure and cross-sectional area exposed to drag. </s><s n="s3.3;p56.112">It illustrates that a characteristic amount of aerodynamic drag caused by fluid flow. </s></p><p n="p57.112"><s n="s1.1;p57.112">The equation for the drag coefficient(C <hi rend="sub">D</hi>) is as follows </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p58.112"><s n="s1.1;p58.112"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0424d-form.037"/><hi rend="bold"> Equation 12</hi><ref target="BAWE_0424d-ftnote.004"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0424d-ftnote.004"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Crowe, Roberson and Elger <hi rend="italic">Engineering Fluid Mechanics</hi> 7th Edition John Wiley and Sons pg 486 </s></p></note><p n="p59.112"><s n="s1.1;p59.112">The graph below shows how the drag coefficient for various two-dimensional bodies. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0424d-fig.002"><head><hi rend="bold">Figure 2</hi><ref target="BAWE_0424d-ftnote.005"/><hi rend="bold">: Drag Coefficient for Two-dimensional Bodies</hi><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0424d-ftnote.005"><p n="pn1.1"> B.S. Massey, <hi rend="italic">Mechanics of Fluids</hi> 7th Edition revised by J.W.Smith (Taylor And Francis, 1998)</p></note></head></figure></div2><div2><head rend="underlined bold">Boundary Layer and Boundary Layer Separation</head><p n="p60.112"><s n="s1.8;p60.112">When a body is immersed in a fluid, near the boundary of the body, the velocity of the fluid changes rapidly from zero near the boundary ( no slip condition mentioned previously) to a relatively large value at some distance from the boundary of the body. </s><s n="s2.8;p60.112">This rapid change in velocity gives rise to a velocity gradient perpendicular to the boundary. </s><s n="s3.8;p60.112">Theoretically with invicid fluids, the fluid would just slide past the boundary and flow would be irrotational everywhere. </s><s n="s4.8;p60.112">This is however not the case with real fluids. </s><s n="s5.8;p60.112">There is typically a layer near a fixed surface in the fluid stream in which shearing stresses occur. </s><s n="s6.8;p60.112">This layer is called the <hi rend="italic">boundary layer.</hi> </s><s n="s7.8;p60.112">A possible consequence of the boundary layer is that the main stream may <hi rend="italic">'separate'</hi> from the surface and form a wake downstream from the body. </s><s n="s8.8;p60.112">(See figure 8) </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">3.0 Apparatus and Method</head><div2><head rend="underlined">Apparatus</head><div3><head rend="underlined">Wind-Tunnel</head><p n="p61.112"><s n="s1.3;p61.112">The experiment was carried out in the large low-speed wind tunnel in the department of Engineering. </s><s n="s2.3;p61.112">The cross-sectional area of the working area of the wind-tunnel is approximately 1.04m x 1.37m. </s><s n="s3.3;p61.112">Pictures can be seen in appendix D </s></p></div3><div3><head rend="underlined">Cylinder</head><p n="p62.112"><s n="s1.7;p62.112">A circular cylinder with a diameter d=113mm is mounted horizontally in the working section of the wind-tunnel. </s><s n="s2.7;p62.112">It extends from one side-wall of the working section to another. </s><s n="s3.7;p62.112">At about the central cross-section of the cylinder there are 13 static pressure tappings in its surface. </s><s n="s4.7;p62.112">The front of the tappings <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0424d-form.038"/> is aligned to the free stream direction. </s><s n="s5.7;p62.112">The rest are distributed at <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0424d-form.039"/> intervals. </s><s n="s6.7;p62.112">The thirteenth tapping <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0424d-form.040"/> is located at the rear. </s><s n="s7.7;p62.112">It is assumed that the pressure readings are the same for the bottom surface of the cylinder as the top pressure readings </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0424d-pic.002"><head rend="bold">Figure 3 Cross-Section of the Wind-tunnel</head></figure></div3><div3><head rend="underlined">Multi-water manometer. </head><p n="p63.112"><s n="s1.1;p63.112">The static tappings are connected to 13 adjacent tubes of a multi - water manometer which is used to measure the pressure at different points on the surface of the cylinder </s></p></div3><div3><head rend="underlined">Pitot-Static Probe </head><p n="p64.112"><s n="s1.6;p64.112">A pitot probe can be used in the wind tunnel to measure the velocity of the tunnel. </s><s n="s2.6;p64.112">The assumption made is that the static pressure is constant everywhere in a uniform free-stream inside the wind tunnel. </s><s n="s3.6;p64.112">This is a reasonable assumption considering that there is no pressure loss, therefore, no pressure gradient, in the system. </s><s n="s4.6;p64.112">However, the situation will be very different for measurements taken inside a wake behind a bluff body where a significant amount of pressure variation exists across the wake profile. </s><s n="s5.6;p64.112">In order to accurately determine the velocity profile in the wake, a pitot-static tube is used. </s><s n="s6.6;p64.112">The pitot-static tube, a sketch of which is shown in Figure 4 a combination of the static tube and the pitot tube, it works in the following manner </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p65.112"><s n="s1.1;p65.112"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0424d-form.041"/><hi rend="bold"> Equation 13</hi> </s></p><p n="p66.112"><s n="s1.1;p66.112">where V is flow velocity, is the density of the fluid, p <hi rend="sub">stag</hi> is the stagnation pressure of the free-stream and p <hi rend="sub">stat</hi> is the static pressure </s></p><p n="p67.112"><s rend="bold" n="s1.2;p67.112">The probe is located in the undisturbed flow upstream of the cylinder and is connected to the manometer to measure the free-stream static pressure. </s><s rend="bold" n="s2.2;p67.112">It is also connected to a micro-manometer to measure the tunnel air speed. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0424d-pic.003"><head><hi rend="bold"> Figure 4 The Pitot-Static Probe</hi><ref target="BAWE_0424d-ftnote.006"/><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0424d-ftnote.006"><p n="pn1.1"> <seg type="URL" n="http://www.eng.fsu.edu/~alvi/EML4304L/webpage/exp7description.doc"/>. Accesed on the 23rd March 2007</p></note></head></figure></div3><div3><head rend="underlined">Wire Mesh</head><p n="p68.112"><s n="s1.3;p68.112">This is mounted on the test section about 3 diameters upstream of the cylinder. </s><s n="s2.3;p68.112">It is used to introduce disturbances into the flow and thus simulate the effect of a fluid with a higher Reynolds number, by increasing the free-stream turbulence. </s><s n="s3.3;p68.112">This results in triggering an earlier laminar-turbulent transition of the boundary layer on the surface of the cylinder. </s></p></div3></div2><div2><head rend="underlined bold">Procedure</head><p n="p69.112"><s n="s1.1;p69.112">The first run of the experiment is conducted with the wire mesh securely inserted in the tunnel upstream of the cylinder, to insure conditions of turbulent separation, and with the tunnel at maximum speed. </s></p><p n="p70.112"><s n="s1.2;p70.112">The pressure at the different angles is measured by reading off the levels of the water in each tube of the manometer. </s><s n="s2.2;p70.112">The results are recorded in a table. </s></p><p n="p71.112"><s n="s1.1;p71.112">The tunnel speed is also read and recorded. </s></p><p n="p72.112"><s n="s1.2;p72.112">The experiment is repeated two more times with the wire mesh removed from the tunnel. </s><s n="s2.2;p72.112">The second run is at full speed while the third run is at half speed. </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">4.0 Table of Results</head><table id="BAWE_0424d-tab.001"><head rend="bold italic">MANOMETER READINGS</head><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p73.112"/></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">5.0 Analysis and Discussion of Results</head><p n="p74.112"><s n="s1.2;p74.112">Using values obtained during the experiment, the Reynolds number of the flows is calculated. </s><s n="s2.2;p74.112">By calculating the Reynolds Number of the flows, the boundary layer conditions of the flow can be determined. i.e.( whether the flow is turbulent or laminar) </s></p><div2><head rend="underlined">A. Reynolds Number</head><p rend="ordered" n="p75.112"><s n="s1.1;p75.112"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0424d-form.042"/><hi rend="bold"> Equation 14</hi><ref target="BAWE_0424d-ftnote.007"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0424d-ftnote.007"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.4;pn1.1">Munson, Young and Okiishi. </s><s n="s2.4;pn1.1">'Fundamentals of Fluid Mechanics' Fourth Edition. </s><s n="s3.4;pn1.1">John Wiley and Sons. </s><s n="s4.4;pn1.1">Pg 20. </s></p></note><list type="bulleted"><head>Where </head><item><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0424d-form.043"/> - mean fluid velocity, </item><item>L - characteristic length of the cylinder</item><item>μ - (absolute) dynamic fluid viscosity</item><item>ν - kinematic fluid viscosity: ν = μ / ρ, </item><item>ρ - fluid (air) density</item></list><list type="bulleted"><head>Taking </head><item>air density (ρ) as 1.23 kg m <hi rend="sup">-3</hi></item><item>coefficient of absolute viscosity as 1.79 x 10 <hi rend="sup">-5</hi> kg m <hi rend="sup">-1</hi> s <hi rend="sup">-1</hi></item><item>characteristic length (L) as 113mm</item></list><p n="p76.112"><s n="s1.1;p76.112">Therefore the Reynolds Number for </s></p><div3><head rend="underlined">A. Full Speed With Mesh</head><p n="p77.112"><s n="s1.1;p77.112"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0424d-form.044"/> </s></p><p n="p78.112"><s n="s1.2;p78.112">The flow here is turbulent. </s><s n="s2.2;p78.112">The wire mesh used simulates a condition of turbulent flow. </s></p></div3><div3><head rend="underlined">B. Full Speed Without Mesh</head><p n="p79.112"><s n="s1.1;p79.112"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0424d-form.045"/> </s></p><p n="p80.112"><s n="s1.2;p80.112">The flow is smooth due to the absence of the wire mesh. </s><s n="s2.2;p80.112">However due to the high Reynolds number, the flow can be considered turbulent. </s></p></div3><div3><head rend="underlined">C. Half Speed Without Mesh</head><p n="p81.112"><s n="s1.1;p81.112"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0424d-form.046"/> </s></p><p n="p82.112"><s n="s1.1;p82.112">The flow here is laminar. </s></p></div3></div2><div2><head rend="underlined bold">B.Graphs</head><p n="p83.112"><s n="s1.1;p83.112">All the C <hi rend="sub">p</hi> calculations, plotting of graphs and the integration to find C <hi rend="sub">D</hi> were performed by a computer program that can be accessed online at </s></p><p n="p84.112"><s rend="bold" n="s1.1;p84.112"><seg type="URL" n="http://www.eng"/>.<name type="university"/>.ac.uk/cgi-bin/cyl15 </s></p><p n="p85.112"><s n="s1.3;p85.112">The graphs are shown below for each of the experimental conditions. </s><s n="s2.3;p85.112">On each graph is the theoretical ideal flow distribution (the blue line) based on the equation. </s><s n="s3.3;p85.112">A clearer version of the graphs can be seen in Appendix A-C </s></p><p n="p86.112"><s n="s1.1;p86.112"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0424d-form.047"/> </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0424d-fig.003"><head rend="underlined">Full Speed with Mesh</head></figure><figure id="BAWE_0424d-fig.004"><head rend="underlined">Full Speed without Mesh</head></figure><figure id="BAWE_0424d-fig.005"><head rend="underlined">Half Speed Without Mesh</head></figure><p n="p87.112"><s n="s1.1;p87.112">The computer program CYL15 computes the 13 manometer readings with the aid of Matlab based on the equation to evaluate the pressure coefficient- </s></p><p n="p88.112"><s n="s1.1;p88.112"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0424d-form.048"/> </s></p><p n="p89.112"><s n="s1.4;p89.112">With the aid of the graph, one is able to determine the value of theta at which the flow separates in each case. </s><s n="s2.4;p89.112">This is possible because when separation occurs, the flow pattern is no longer that of irrotational flow. </s><s n="s3.4;p89.112">In accordance, there are changes in the pressure distribution. </s><s n="s4.4;p89.112">That is, the experimental pressure distribution begins to deviate from the theoretical pressure distribution. </s></p><p n="p90.112"><s n="s1.1;p90.112">Therefore the flow begins to separate at approximately Theta equals </s></p><list type="ordered"><item>Full Speed with mesh -125 degrees</item><item>Full Speed without mesh- 67 degrees</item><item>Half Speed without mesh- 60 degrees </item></list><p n="p91.112"><s n="s1.1;p91.112">Separation usually occurs where the physical boundary turns away from the main stream of flow. </s></p><p n="p92.112"><s n="s1.1;p92.112">Considering the flow of a viscous fluid past a circular cylinder, shown the diagram below </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0424d-pic.004"><head><hi rend="bold">Figure 8</hi><ref target="BAWE_0424d-ftnote.008"/><hi rend="bold"> : viscous fluid past a circular cylinder</hi><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0424d-ftnote.008"><p n="pn1.1">ttp://<seg type="URL" n="www.dtu.dk/upload/_fys/billeder/fluid_flows/cylinder%20flow.jpg"/> Accessed 14/03/07</p></note></head></figure><p n="p93.112"><s n="s1.7;p93.112">The flow upstream of the midsection of the cylinder is similar to that of irrotational flow about a cylinder, except very close to the boundary surface. </s><s n="s2.7;p93.112">At this point because of a viscous resistance, a thin layer of fluid has its velocity reduced from that predicted by the irrotational theory. </s><s n="s3.7;p93.112">The fluid particles directly adjacent to the surface actually have zero velocity. </s><s n="s4.7;p93.112">(This is called the no-slip condition.) </s><s n="s5.7;p93.112">The normal tendency is for the layer of reduced velocity (called the Boundary Layer) to grow in thickness in the direction of flow. </s><s n="s6.7;p93.112">However, because the main stream of fluid outside the boundary layer is accelerating in the same direction the boundary layer remains quite thin up to approximately the mid section. </s><s n="s7.7;p93.112">The boundary thick ness is usually defined as that thickness where the flow velocity reaches 99% of the free stream value U <hi rend="sub">0</hi> </s></p><p n="p94.112"><s n="s1.5;p94.112">Upstream of the midsection the irrotational flow pattern shows a significant deceleration of the fluid next to the boundary, with a corresponding increaser in pressure. </s><s n="s2.5;p94.112">For real flow however, the deceleration of the fluid next to the boundary is limited because its velocity is already small ( much smaller than the theoretical flow ) because of viscous resistance. </s><s n="s3.5;p94.112">Therefore the fluid near the boundary can proceed only a very short distance against the adverse pressure gradient. </s><s n="s4.5;p94.112">The adverse pressure gradient is the increase in pressure in the direction of flow along the rear half of the cylinder. </s><s n="s5.5;p94.112">Once the motion of the fluid next to the boundary ceases, this causes the main stream of flow to be directed away or 'separated' from the boundary.Thus the process of separation is produced. </s></p><p n="p95.112"><s n="s1.4;p95.112">The location of the point of separation for a cylinder depends on the character of the flow in the boundary layer. </s><s n="s2.4;p95.112">It may also depend on the shape and roughness if the body. </s><s n="s3.4;p95.112">The Reynolds number is also an indication of the onset of separation. </s><s n="s4.4;p95.112">For Reynolds number greater than 50, the entire flow field is dominated by relatively large viscous stresses that inhibit the development of eddy motion in the flow </s></p><p n="p96.112"><s n="s1.4;p96.112">When separation occurs the flow pattern is changed from that of the theoretical flow. </s><s n="s2.4;p96.112">The corresponding changes in the pressure distribution occur. </s><s n="s3.4;p96.112">For flow past a cylinder, the slight change of the flow pattern next to the forward part of the body only changes the pressure distribution slightly. </s><s n="s4.4;p96.112">However in the zone of separation, marked changes occur. </s></p><p n="p97.112"><s n="s1.5;p97.112">From the previous graphs (figs 4-6) it can be seen that the experimental distribution that is nearest to that of the ideal distribution is that of the turbulent flow at full speed. </s><s n="s2.5;p97.112">It also indicates that the average pressure on the rear half of the cylinder is considerably less than that on the front half. </s><s n="s3.5;p97.112">Thus a large pressure drag is developed, even though the viscous shear drag maybe quite small. </s><s n="s4.5;p97.112">This explained D'Alembert's paradox. </s><s n="s5.5;p97.112">No matter how small the viscosity, provided it is not zero, there will be a boundary layer that separates the surface giving a drag force. </s></p><p n="p98.112"><s n="s1.7;p98.112">Compared to a laminar boundary layer, a turbulent one has more kinetic energy and momentum. </s><s n="s2.7;p98.112">Therefore the turbulent boundary layer can flow farther around the cylinder before it separates than the laminar boundary layer. </s><s n="s3.7;p98.112">Over the front surface of the cylinder the presence of the boundary layer affects the pressure distribution through two major ways. </s><s n="s4.7;p98.112">Firstly through viscous losses and secondly through a slight displacement caused by the retardation of flow within the boundary layer. </s><s n="s5.7;p98.112">Near the shoulder where <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0424d-form.049"/> the pressure gradient changes from being negative to being positive. </s><s n="s6.7;p98.112">The force due to pressure differences changes sign from being an accelerating force to being a retarding force. </s><s n="s7.7;p98.112">In response the flow slows down. </s></p><p n="p99.112"><s n="s1.1;p99.112">Mathematically we could say that inviscid flow cannot satisfy the boundary conditions to real flow, specifically inviscid flows allow slip at the surface while viscous flows do not. </s></p><div3><head rend="underlined bold">Drag Coefficients</head><p n="p100.112"><s n="s1.2;p100.112">The drag coefficients for all the flows are shown on top of the graphs (figures 4-6). </s><s n="s2.2;p100.112">It is Computed from the graphs shown below (which is the graphs of Cp against sin <formula notation="" id="BAWE_0424d-form.050"/>using equations in Appendix(E) for the appropriate experimental condition. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0424d-fig.006"><head>Full speed with Mesh: CD=0.369 <hi rend="bold">Figure 9</hi></head></figure><figure id="BAWE_0424d-fig.007"><head>Full Speed without Mesh: CD=1.2 <hi rend="bold">Figure 10</hi></head></figure><figure id="BAWE_0424d-fig.008"><head>Half Speed Without Mesh: C <hi rend="sub">D</hi> =1.56 <hi rend="bold">Figure 11</hi></head></figure><p n="p101.112"><s n="s1.3;p101.112">The drag coefficient goes from 0.369 for turbulent flow to 1.56 for laminar flow. </s><s n="s2.3;p101.112">This is similar to the graph in figure 2. </s><s n="s3.3;p101.112">The drag coefficient suddenly drops from about 1.2 to 0.3 at a critical Reynolds number of approximately between 10 <hi rend="sup">5</hi> and 10 <hi rend="sup">6</hi> </s></p><p n="p102.112"><s n="s1.6;p102.112">This reduction in C <hi rend="sub">D</hi> at a Reynolds number of approximately 10 <hi rend="sup">5</hi> is due to a change in the flow pattern triggered by a change in the character at the boundary layer. </s><s n="s2.6;p102.112">For Reynolds numbers less than 10 <hi rend="sup">5</hi> flow is laminar, and separation occurs about halfway between the upstream side and the downstream side of the cylinder. </s><s n="s3.6;p102.112">Therefore, the entire downstream side of the cylinder is exposed to relatively low pressure, which in turns produces a relatively high value for C <hi rend="sub">D</hi>. </s><s n="s4.6;p102.112">When the Reynolds number is increased to about 10 <hi rend="sup">5</hi>, the boundary layer becomes turbulent in nature. </s><s n="s5.6;p102.112">This causes higher velocity fluid to be mixed in the region close to the wall of the cylinder. </s><s n="s6.6;p102.112">As an effect of the presence of this high-velocity, high-momentum fluid in the boundary layer, the flow proceeds farther downstream along the surface of the cylinder against adverse pressure before separation occurs. ( Figure 8) </s></p><p n="p103.112"><s n="s1.4;p103.112">Hence the flow pattern, i.e. delayed separation causes the drag to be reduced for the following reasons; with the turbulent boundary layer, the streamlines downstream of the cylinder midsection diverge somewhat before separation, and hence a decrease in velocity occurs before separation. </s><s n="s2.4;p103.112">According to Bernoulli's equation, the decrease in velocity produces a pressure at the point of separation that is greater than the pressure at the midsection. </s><s n="s3.4;p103.112">Therefore at the point of separation, and also in the zone of separation, the pressure is significantly greater under these conditions than when separation occurs farther upstream. </s><s n="s4.4;p103.112">Thus the pressure difference between the upstream and downstream surfaces of the cylinder is less at high values of the Reynolds Number, yielding a lower drag coefficient. </s></p><p n="p104.112"><s n="s1.1;p104.112">Apart from being dependent on the Reynolds number, the drag coefficient is also dependent on shape as well as surface roughness. </s></p><p n="p105.112"><s n="s1.6;p105.112">It must be noted however that the drag coefficient produced during this experiment is not the total one. </s><s n="s2.6;p105.112">This is because the drag force used to compute C <hi rend="sub">D</hi>, is not the total drag force, produced. </s><s n="s3.6;p105.112">It is only one component of the total drag called the pressure drag also known as <hi rend="italic">form drag.</hi> </s><s n="s4.6;p105.112">Usually the total drag force is made up of both the form drag and the viscous drag also known as <hi rend="italic">frictional drag</hi>. </s><s n="s5.6;p105.112">However, because as discussed earlier in the theory sections , the viscous drag is associated with the viscous shear forces. </s><s n="s6.6;p105.112">But there are assumed to be no viscous shear stresses in the analytical model, so the total force that the fluid exerts on the cylinder is obtained by integrating the pressure force over the surface area A of the cylinder </s></p></div3></div2><div2><head rend="underlined bold">Streamlining- A method to reduce Drag</head><p n="p106.112"><s n="s1.4;p106.112">Streamlining is a method used to reduce drag. </s><s n="s2.4;p106.112">It reduces the extreme curvature on the downstream of a body, reducing or eliminating separation in the process. </s><s n="s3.4;p106.112">Therefore, the coefficient of drag is greatly reduced. </s><s n="s4.4;p106.112">It also removes the periodic formation of vortices. </s></p><p n="p107.112"><s n="s1.7;p107.112">When a body is streamlined by elongating it and reducing its curvature, the pressure drag is reduced. </s><s n="s2.7;p107.112">However the viscous drag is increased because there is a greater amount of the surface of the streamlined body, than on the un-streamlined body. </s><s n="s3.7;p107.112">Consequently, when a body is streamlined to produce minimal drag, there is an optimum condition to be required. </s><s n="s4.7;p107.112">This condition occurs when the sum of the surface drag and pressure drag is minimum. </s><s n="s5.7;p107.112">It should be noted that streamlining to produce minimum drag at high Reynolds numbers will probably not produce minimum drag at low Reynolds numbers. </s><s n="s6.7;p107.112">For Reynolds number less than one , the majority of the drag of a body is due to the viscous shear stress on the wall of the body. </s><s n="s7.7;p107.112">Hence if the body is streamlined, the viscous shear stress is simply magnified and the C <hi rend="sub">D</hi> may actually increase for this range of Reynolds numbers where the viscous resistance is predominant. </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">6.0 Conclusions</head><p n="p108.112"><s n="s1.1;p108.112">From the experimental data gathered, it can be concluded that when a blunt object like a cylinder is immersed in a fluid, the magnitude of the drag forces due to the flow, depends on a number of factors. </s></p><p n="p109.112"><s n="s1.7;p109.112">Firstly, the drag force depends on the Reynolds number of the fluid. </s><s n="s2.7;p109.112">The larger the Reynolds number of the flow, the more turbulent the flow is. </s><s n="s3.7;p109.112">However, contrary to expectations, the higher the Reynolds number, the lower the coefficient of drag. </s><s n="s4.7;p109.112">At low Reynolds number flow, (Re&lt; 1), the drag is a function of upstream velocity. </s><s n="s5.7;p109.112">At moderate Reynolds number (10 <hi rend="sup">3</hi>&lt;Re&lt;10 <hi rend="sup">5</hi>) flows the drag coefficient tends to decrease slightly with Reynolds number. </s><s n="s6.7;p109.112">However at high Reynolds numbers (10 <hi rend="sup">5</hi>&lt;Re&lt;10 <hi rend="sup">6</hi>) there is a sudden decrease in the drag force. </s><s n="s7.7;p109.112">This is due to the fact that a turbulent boundary layer, can travel farther along the surface into the adverse pressure gradient on the rear portion of the cylinder before separation occurs .This results in a smaller wake and hence a smaller pressure drag. </s></p><p n="p110.112"><s n="s1.1;p110.112">Due to the fact that the drag force is dependent on the Reynolds number of the flow, it could be deduced that it is therefore dependent on a combination of the size of the object and the speed and density of the fluid flow. </s></p><p n="p111.112"><s n="s1.4;p111.112">To reduce drag forces on an object, the flow must be made to separate as late as possible. </s><s n="s2.4;p111.112">This can be done by redesigning the object into a shape that is more streamlined. </s><s n="s3.4;p111.112">It should be noted however that there are limitations to streamlining. </s><s n="s4.4;p111.112">At low Reynolds number flows, streamlining can actually increase in the areas on which shear forces act. </s></p><p n="p112.112"><s n="s1.1;p112.112">. </s></p></div1></body><back><div1 type="bibliography"><head rend="bold">7.0 References</head><div2 type="bibliography"><head rend="underlined">Internet References</head><p>Dr P.J. Thomas. ES3C9 - Fundamental Fluid Mechanics for Mechanical Engineers lecture 16 , Monday 6<hi rend="sup">th</hi> November 2006. <seg type="URL" n="http://www2"/>.<name type="university"/>.ac.uk/fac/sci/eng/staff/pjt/es3c9/lecture_16_Final06.pdf Accessed on 15th March 2007</p><p><seg type="URL" n="http://www.dtu.dk/upload/_fys/billeder/fluid_flows/cylinder%20flow.jpg"/> Accessed on 10<hi rend="sup">th</hi> March 2007</p><p><seg type="URL" n="http://www.eng.fsu.edu/~alvi/EML4304L/webpage/exp7description.doc"/>. Accessed on the 23rd March 2007</p></div2><div2 type="bibliography"><head rend="underlined">Books</head><p>F.M .White <hi rend="italic">Fluid Mechanics</hi> 5<hi rend="sup">th</hi> Edition ( McGraw Hill, 2003) pg</p><p>Crowe, Roberson and Elger <hi rend="italic">Engineering Fluid Mechanics</hi> 7<hi rend="sup">th</hi> Edition John Wiley and Sons pgs 179, 486, 488</p><p>Munson, Young and Okiishi. '<hi rend="italic">Fundamentals of Fluid Mechanics</hi>' Fourth Edition. John Wiley and Sons. Pg 20.</p><p>Kundu Pijush K. '<hi rend="italic">Fluid Mechanics'</hi> Academic Press Incorporated 1990 pg 326</p><p>B.S. Massey, <hi rend="italic">Mechanics of Fluids</hi> 7<hi rend="sup">th</hi> Edition revised by J.W.Smith (Taylor And Francis, 1998)</p></div2></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
