<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_0424a" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Midlands Metro</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note/></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">1</p><p n="date">2006-03</p><p n="module title">MARKETING AND INDUSTRY EXCERSISE</p><p n="module code">ES175</p><p n="genre family">Case study</p><p n="discipline">Engineering</p><p n="disciplinary group">PS</p><p n="grade">D</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">1005</p><p n="number of s-units">50</p><p n="number of p">23</p><p n="number of tables">1</p><p n="number of figures">1</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">5</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">7</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">20.1</p><p n="average s-units per p">2.2</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">f</p><p n="year of birth">1987</p><p n="first language">English</p><p n="education">UK2</p><p n="course">Engineering</p><p n="student ID">0424</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><docTitle><titlePart rend="underlined">ES175 MARKETING AND INDUSTRY EXCERSISE<hi rend="bold"> Midlands Metro</hi></titlePart></docTitle></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="section"><p n="p1.23"><s n="s1.2;p1.23">Midland Metro is a modern tram system that can run both separated from other traffic and safely on streets with other traffic and pedestrians. </s><s n="s2.2;p1.23">Developed as a higher quality mode of public transport than the bus, it is fast, reliable, convenient and easy to use.<ref target="BAWE_0424a-ftnote.001"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0424a-ftnote.001"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1"><seg type="URL" n="http://www.travelmetro.co.uk/"/># (accessed 2nd January 2006) </s></p></note><p n="p2.23"><s n="s1.2;p2.23">Midlands Metro is in the public transport industry. </s><s n="s2.2;p2.23">It s owned by The West Midlands Transport Authority (Centro) and is under a 23 year concession to Altram L.R.T. Ltd., who have a Design, Build, Operate, Maintain contract </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">Structure of the Industry</head><p n="p3.23"><s n="s1.2;p3.23">Altram has a SIC code of 6010( Transport via railway). </s><s n="s2.2;p3.23">There are 119 companies with this SIC code. </s></p><p n="p4.23"><s n="s1.1;p4.23">The table below shows the performance of Altram amongst its peers </s></p><table id="BAWE_0424a-tab.001"><head> Table 1<ref target="BAWE_0424a-ftnote.002"/><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0424a-ftnote.002"><p n="pn1.1"> Sourced from the FAME database (accessed 23rd December 2005)</p></note></head><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p5.23"><s n="s1.4;p5.23">The other companies with the same SIC code as Altram, do not operate within the same area as Midlands Metro, and therefore are not in direct competition with them. </s><s n="s2.4;p5.23">Consequently, a concentration ratio or Hirschman-Herfindal Index, would not give an accurate scenario. </s><s n="s3.4;p5.23">The main source of competition are motorists .In terms of public transport in the West Midlands, buses account for 95% of all public transport usage; Travel West Midlands having a monopoly of about 80% of the market share.<ref target="BAWE_0424a-ftnote.003"/> There are other medium sized bus operators such as Pete's Travel, Birmingham Coach Company. </s><s n="s4.4;p5.23">Furthermore there is heavy rail; with Central Trains taking 80% of the market. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0424a-ftnote.003"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1"><seg type="URL" n="http://www.centro.org.uk/source/CorpInfo/Corporate/20%20Year%20Stategy%20Main.pdf"/> (accessed 3rd January 2006) </s></p></note></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">Conduct Of The Firms</head><p n="p6.23"><s n="s1.5;p6.23">This is a difficult one to measure. </s><s n="s2.5;p6.23">Midlands Metro is owned by Centro, who also have stakes in the bus and rail companies. </s><s n="s3.5;p6.23">But according to the figures, Travel West Midlands has a monopoly of 80%<ref target="BAWE_0424a-ftnote.004"/>. </s><s n="s4.5;p6.23">There are other medium sizes companies in the market; therefore the type of competition in this market is oligopoly. </s><s n="s5.5;p6.23">As mentioned above, Centro, own bus, rail and the metro. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0424a-ftnote.004"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1"><seg type="URL" n="http://www.centro.org.uk/source/CorpInfo/Corporate/20%20Year%20Stategy%20Main.pdf"/> (accessed 3rd January 2006) </s></p></note><p n="p7.23"><s n="s1.3;p7.23">Therefore there is a degree of collusion, as the ultimate aim is to get more people using public transport. </s><s n="s2.3;p7.23">Centro's reports always include the three forms of transport. </s><s n="s3.3;p7.23">In addition their future plans are for all the forms of transport. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0424a-fig.001"><head><hi rend="underlined bold">Chart 1 </hi><ref target="BAWE_0424a-ftnote.005"/><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0424a-ftnote.005"><p n="pn1.1"><seg type="URL" n="http://www.centro.org.uk/wwwroot/CorpInfo/BEST%20VALUE%2005.pdf"/> (accessed 3rd January 2006)</p></note></head></figure></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">Performance Of The Industry</head><p n="p8.23"><s n="s1.4;p8.23">LRT is in the question mark stage of the BCG matrix. </s><s n="s2.4;p8.23">There are some people like MP Alistair Darling who do not support it<ref target="BAWE_0424a-ftnote.006"/>. </s><s n="s3.4;p8.23">However LRT has been proven to get people out of their cars in a way buses have never done.<ref target="BAWE_0424a-ftnote.007"/> It is the belief of many that it is the way forward to beat traffic congestion. </s><s n="s4.4;p8.23">And it is on its way to becoming a rising star. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0424a-ftnote.006"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Derrick Taylor (Midlands Metro Employee) - Personal communication. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0424a-ftnote.007"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1"><seg type="URL" n="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm199900/cmselect/cmenvtra/153/153ap49.htm"/> (accessed 4th January 2006) </s></p></note><p n="p9.23"><s n="s1.2;p9.23">Demand for the service is fairly elastic. </s><s n="s2.2;p9.23">It is generally accepted that the cost of public transport goes up every year; but if the cost of the metro costs much more than all other forms of transport, customers would look for viable alternatives, and the demand for the service would fall </s></p><p n="p10.23"><s n="s1.3;p10.23">Altram is operating at loss every year. </s><s n="s2.3;p10.23">Profit margin for 2003 was -19.34%<ref target="BAWE_0424a-ftnote.008"/>.Profit is generally low among tram companies across the country, although the bus companies seem to be making profits. </s><s n="s3.3;p10.23">Travel West Midlands, the market leader, made profits of £32, 611, with a profit margin of 16.09%, raking first among companies of similar turnover to it, in 2003. <ref target="BAWE_0424a-ftnote.009"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0424a-ftnote.008"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1"><seg type="URL" n="http://www2.warwick.ac.uk/fac/sci/eng/euo/modules/year1/es175/student_resources/es175-2-firm-2-web.ppt"/> (accessed 3rd December 2005) </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0424a-ftnote.009"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Accessed at the FAME database on 10th January 2005. </s></p></note><p n="p11.23"><s n="s1.3;p11.23">Efficiency wise, LRT operates dynamically. </s><s n="s2.3;p11.23">There is a lot of funds put in to devise better vehicles and tracks, and a better quality of service. </s><s n="s3.3;p11.23">Midland Metro has the following core competencies:- </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p12.23"><s n="s1.2;p12.23">Is faster :- The "rapid" nature of the mode is attributable to the high-performance acceleration and braking characteristics of modern trams and is very attractive to road users. </s><s n="s2.2;p12.23">The existing bus route that parallels Midland Metro Line 1 is takes 79 minutes. <ref target="BAWE_0424a-ftnote.010"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0424a-ftnote.010"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1"><seg type="URL" n="http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm199900/cmselect/cmenvtra/153/153ap49.htm"/> (accessed 4th January 2006) </s></p></note><p rend="bulleted" n="p13.23"><s n="s1.1;p13.23">It offers a higher capacity; </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p14.23"><s n="s1.1;p14.23">It offers a smoother ride; </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p15.23"><s n="s1.1;p15.23">Its precise path makes it more acceptable in pedestrian areas; </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p16.23"><s n="s1.1;p16.23">It appears to have a better image among customers; </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p17.23"><s n="s1.1;p17.23">It attracts more passengers who might otherwise travel by car; </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p18.23"><s n="s1.1;p18.23">Being electrically powered, it reduces pollution in the city <ref target="BAWE_0424a-ftnote.011"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0424a-ftnote.011"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1"><seg type="URL" n="http://www.parliament.the-stationery-office.co.uk/pa/cm199900/cmselect/cmenvtra/153/153ap27.htm"/> Accessed 4th January 2006 </s></p></note></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">Most viable strategy for a new entrant to the UK</head><p n="p19.23"><s n="s1.2;p19.23">There are numerous barriers to entry. </s><s n="s2.2;p19.23">These are </s></p><list type="bulleted"><item>High capital outlay- costs £3-£10 million per km of track <ref target="BAWE_0424a-ftnote.012"/></item><item>Government authorization required to begin the project: - this is often a time consuming process..</item><item> Long gestation period:- 8 -10 years</item><item>Has a life span of 30 years.</item></list><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0424a-ftnote.012"><p n="pn1.2"><s n="s1.1;pn1.2"><seg type="URL" n="http://www.parliament.the-stationery-office.co.uk/pa/cm199900/cmselect/cmenvtra/153/153ap27.htm"/> </s></p><p n="pn2.2"><s n="s1.1;pn2.2">Accessed 4th January 2006 </s></p></note><p n="p20.23"><s n="s1.3;p20.23">I would propose a strategy of <hi rend="bold">differentiation focus</hi> strategy. </s><s n="s2.3;p20.23">This strategy creates a competitive advantage within the niche-which in this case is providing LRT. With this strategy, they have a chance to increase revenue as well as develop customer loyalty. </s><s n="s3.3;p20.23">As there are high capital costs, revenue has to be maximised to increase profitability. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">Recommendation to entrepreneur</head><p n="p21.23"><s n="s1.1;p21.23">Below is a SWOT analysis for Midlands Metro </s></p><list type="bulleted"><head rend="underlined bold">Strength</head><item>High reliability with public perceptions to match (98.9%)</item><item>Safer per kilometre</item><item>Shorter time to reach destination than by bus</item><item>Has a higher capacity</item><item>Very convenient for those within walking distance.</item></list><list type="bulleted"><head rend="underlined bold">Weaknesses</head><item>Not profitable.</item><item>Delays in meeting deadlines.</item></list><list type="bulleted"><head rend="underlined bold">Opportunities</head><item>Number of public transport users has shown an upward trend.</item><item>A large number of people (over a million) have a dependence on public transport in the West Midlands.</item><item>Locations of new development.</item><item>The need to diversify the traditional industrial base and develop the service sector.</item></list><list type="bulleted"><head rend="underlined bold">Threats</head><item>Number of cars per hundred people in the West Midlands is larger than any other metropolitan area in Britain</item><item>Government has L.R.T. not a priority. </item></list><p n="p22.23"><s n="s1.3;p22.23">Midlands Metro has good prospects for the future. </s><s n="s2.3;p22.23">It has proved so popular with users that they want to expand the system in order to bring the benefits of a Metro system to even more people in the West Midlands. </s><s n="s3.3;p22.23">They want to achieve this by adding three more lines, creating a network of trams in the West Midlands. </s></p><p n="p23.23"><s n="s1.2;p23.23">I would recommend that the entrepreneur should acquire the company because, starting a new rival company would require a huge capital outlay, financial capacity to lobby for government approval, because it is a time consuming exercise. </s><s n="s2.2;p23.23">Whereas with acquiring the company, all the groundwork has been done, and it would just be the case of restructuring the company to suit the entrepreneur's company ethos. </s></p></div1></body><back/></text></TEI.2>
