<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_0428b" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>The UK is increasingly becoming a global centre for hedge funds. Is the current system of financial regulation adequate to protect as to financial crisis? Discuss.</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">Language used in quote: <foreign id="English">English</foreign></note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">deleted: page numbers</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">4</p><p n="date">2007-05</p><p n="module title">INTERNATIONAL BANKING LAW</p><p n="module code">LA905</p><p n="genre family">Essay</p><p n="discipline">Law</p><p n="disciplinary group">SS</p><p n="grade">D</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">3687</p><p n="number of s-units">110</p><p n="number of p">53</p><p n="number of tables">0</p><p n="number of figures">0</p><p n="number of block quotes">1</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">0</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">4</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">33.5</p><p n="average s-units per p">2.1</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">m</p><p n="year of birth">1965</p><p n="first language">Portuguese</p><p n="education">OSA</p><p n="course">International Economic Law</p><p n="student ID">0428</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><titlePart><hi rend="underlined bold">INTERNATIONAL BANKING LAW - 2006/2007 SPRING TERM - PROFESSOR <name type="tutor name"/></hi><hi rend="underlined bold"> STUDENT NO. <name type="student ID"/></hi></titlePart><docTitle><titlePart>"The UK is increasingly becoming a global centre for hedge funds. Is the current system of financial regulation adequate to protect as to financial crisis? Discuss."</titlePart></docTitle></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">Introduction</head><p n="p1.53"><s n="s1.3;p1.53">Since the late 1970s, with the adoption of neo-liberal economic policies by US and UK, the world economy entirely shifted its direction. </s><s n="s2.3;p1.53">Practices such as free trade and deregulation policies became so widespread that they came to be known as "The Washington Consensus". </s><s n="s3.3;p1.53">Even the end of History, with the final triumph of Capitalism, was heralded. </s></p><p n="p2.53"><s n="s1.2;p2.53">Hedge Funds, as will see below, are not in any way the product of neo-liberalism. </s><s n="s2.2;p2.53">They were, at least in their most recent form, much fostered by some of its facets, such as deregulation and liberalisation of capital flows, which were much aided by the coming of the Internet. </s></p><p n="p3.53"><s n="s1.3;p3.53">But globalisation is not without its drawbacks. </s><s n="s2.3;p3.53">At this point, a parallel with taxation may be helpful, for at least some of the challenges Hedge Funds present are similar to those faced by regulators as to tax shopping before the enactment of transfer pricing rules - in that the dilemmas our issue presents can never be efficiently tackled solely from the perspective of a single country, even though regulation is intrinsically a sovereign governmental activity, not easily made compatible with a global strategy. </s><s n="s3.3;p3.53">In addition, the weighing of interest by government authorities in regulating hedge funds is far more convoluted than in taxation - where, at least theoretically, most problems could be solved by delegating all powers to a global authority who had powers apportion public revenue amongst states in much the same way a central government does with sub-national entities, so as to attain to the objective of fiscal neutrality as to investment allocation decisions. </s></p><p n="p4.53"><s n="s1.1;p4.53">Conversely, not only do financial regulators of different countries compete against one another for the scarce liquidity that few economic agents apart from hedge funds can provide, they can do so only if the regulations they enact are neither so loose that they fail to protect against crisis, nor so draconian as to prevent maximisation of returns and discourage funds from doing business within their jurisdiction. </s></p><p n="p5.53"><s n="s1.3;p5.53">Moreover, unlike taxation, those Highly Leveraged Financial Institutions (HLIs)<ref target="BAWE_0428b-ftnote.001"/> can only deliver nearly-stratospheric yields if they are allowed to exploit to the fullest, <hi rend="italic">inter alia</hi>, discrepancies in time and is space that are entailed by the pursuit of diverse national economic policies, in a practice known as arbitrage<ref target="BAWE_0428b-ftnote.002"/> in the jargon of the financial markets. </s><s n="s2.3;p5.53">To our imaginary Earth Revenue, tax havens would simply be banned. </s><s n="s3.3;p5.53">Conversely, hedge funds cannot do without them - as most their most common corporate structures rely on a tax-haven based parent company so as to benefit from lower disclosure requirements and tax rates. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0428b-ftnote.001"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">See FINANCIAL STABILITY FORUM - Report of the Working Group on Highly Leveraged Institutions, 5 April 2000, at <seg type="URL" n="http://www.fsforum.org/home/home.html"/> , accessed April 2007. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0428b-ftnote.002"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Or, according to <seg type="URL" n="http://www.investorwords.com/"/> , an online financial glossary, in the corresponding entry, "Attempting to profit by exploiting price differences of identical or similar <hi rend="underlined">financial instruments</hi>, on different markets or in different forms. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">The ideal version is <hi rend="underlined">riskless arbitrage</hi>." at <seg type="URL" n="http://www.investorwords.com/245/arbitrage.html"/> , accessed April 2007. </s></p></note><p n="p6.53"><s n="s1.1;p6.53">If taxation is the antithesis of globalisation - in that it depends on what divides countries - national sovereign powers _, instead of what unites them, hedge funds can only blossom in a globalised world such as ours. </s></p><p n="p7.53"><s n="s1.1;p7.53">Moreover, financial authorities, unlike their tax counterparts, have little incentive to act in coordination while profit is being made, but have all incentive to join one another in action as systemic crises arise. </s></p><p n="p8.53"><s n="s1.6;p8.53">Tax have as a condition rationality, for public revenue is for tax authorities what profits are to an entrepreneur, but the former are entirely contingent upon the latter. </s><s n="s2.6;p8.53">If each tax authority elected to tax all resources available, they would drain off all incentive of private players to make money. </s><s n="s3.6;p8.53">Besides, as the opportunities of making profit are limited in the national level, firms and individuals often go abroad. </s><s n="s4.6;p8.53">If countries cannot strike a bargain as between themselves, double taxation would remove all incentive from overseas activities. </s><s n="s5.6;p8.53">Therefore, countries have much incentive to negotiate alongside lines previously known to all in the form of the Model Conventions. </s><s n="s6.6;p8.53">Conversely, Hedge Funds need diversity to flourish by exploiting differences in currency and interest policies. </s></p><p n="p9.53"><s n="s1.2;p9.53">As to Hedge Funds, is the reverse: in the event all countries adopted the same economic policies in all respects, there would be short of opportunities. </s><s n="s2.2;p9.53">HFs would never flourish under a Fiscal Leviathan, but would be in serious jeopardy under Hobbesian anarchy. </s></p><p n="p10.53"><s n="s1.2;p10.53">National authorities the world wide must, therefore, strike a very delicate balance between their wealth acquisition and their conduct regulation practices, their need to combine occasional collaboration with their overseas counterparts without dismissing the competitive aspects of the interaction between inside and outside the limits of their territory, within and beyond the limits of their sovereignty. </s><s n="s2.2;p10.53">In this respect, as we will be analysing, US and UK authorities seem to have taken different stances in their approaches to hedge funds, with the latter being much laxer then former, with seemingly better results - at least up to now<ref target="BAWE_0428b-ftnote.003"/>. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0428b-ftnote.003"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">"<hi rend="italic">Short selling - No defence,</hi> available in International Financial Law Review, March 2007, <hi rend="underlined"><seg type="URL" n="http://www.iflr.com"/>:80/includes/magazine/PRINT.asp?SID=677714&amp;ISS=23496&amp;PUBID=33</hi> , accessed April 2007. </s></p></note><p n="p11.53"><s n="s1.1;p11.53">In fact, devising an ideal strategy, either municipal or global, for regulating hedge funds is no easy task, but it does give us much food for thought on new challenges of law and regulation of securities and financial markets and possible strategies that may be developed to tackle them, as this is time when long-established distinctions, such as private and public, hard law v. soft law, all blur, and the view of the state as a harmonious whole is no longer tenable, but a new supra-state is not yet born. </s></p><p n="p12.53"><s n="s1.1;p12.53">We shall now examine how hedge funds were created. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">Hedge Funds :Definition, History, Operation, Techniques, Strategies</head><p n="p13.53"><s n="s1.2;p13.53">The primary meaning of "hedge" seems in straight opposition to the high degree of risk commonly associated with hedge funds - at least after the disastrous crises triggered by hedge funds Long Term Capital Management (LGCM)<ref target="BAWE_0428b-ftnote.004"/> and Amaranth<ref target="BAWE_0428b-ftnote.005"/> - when the former was bailed out by the market, but not the latter. </s><s n="s2.2;p13.53">In many dictionaries, the first definitions of this world commonly have the sense of "protection". </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0428b-ftnote.004"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.5;pn1.1">As told in <hi rend="italic">LTCM Speaks - In a series of secretive roadshows, LTCM partners now admit they badly misjudged market dynamics and volatility, making common risk management mistakes on a grand scale.</hi> </s><s n="s2.5;pn1.1">, in <seg type="URL" n="http://www.derivativesstrategy.com/magazine/archive/1999/0499fea1.asp"/> ,and by Daniel A. Stratchman, <hi rend="italic">Getting Started in Hedge Funds</hi>, John Wiley &amp; Sons, Inc., New York • Chichester • Weinheim • Brisbane • Singapore • Toronto, 2000, pages 12-24. </s><s n="s3.5;pn1.1">For the viewpoint of a regulator, see <hi rend="italic">Was There Front Running During the LTCM Crisis?</hi> </s><s n="s4.5;pn1.1">Fang Cai, available at <seg type="URL" n="http://www.federalreserve.gov/pubs/ifdp/2003/758/ifdp758.pdf"/> , Board of Governors of the Federal Reserve System - International Finance Discussion Papers - Number 758 - February 2003. </s><s n="s5.5;pn1.1">All websites accessed April 2007. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0428b-ftnote.005"><p n="pn1.1"><s rend="italic" n="s1.2;pn1.1">Hedge fund's $6bn gas price hit - Amaranth Advisors, the US-based hedge fund whose investments were hit by a misplaced bet on gas prices, has seen its losses reach about $6bn (£3.2bn). </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">, available in <seg type="URL" n="http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/business/5366236.stm"/> , accessed April 2007. </s></p></note><p n="p14.53"><s n="s1.1;p14.53">A purely technical meaning is given by Black's Law Dictionary: </s></p><quote lang="English" rend="italic">"A specialized investment group usually organized as a limited partnership or off-shore investment company - that offers the possibility of high returns through risky techniques such as selling short or buying derivatives. Most Hedge Funds are not registered with SEC and are therefore restricted in marketing their services to the public."</quote><p n="p15.53"><s n="s1.3;p15.53">In fact, the original rationale underlying hedge funds, as devised as early as in 1949 by the first manager of a fund of this sort, Alfred Winslow Jones<ref target="BAWE_0428b-ftnote.006"/>, was precisely to protect against the volatility of the market. </s><s n="s2.3;p15.53">He achieved this by borrowing money at low fixed interest rates in order to borrow various types of securities<ref target="BAWE_0428b-ftnote.007"/> from brokers in different transactions, betting (with grounds on sophisticated market analysis techniques such as stochastics<ref target="BAWE_0428b-ftnote.008"/>) on the future plummeting of their value. </s><s n="s3.3;p15.53">As this plunge in price materialised, the fund would repay loan and return the devalued shares, amassing in the process the variation in price - relying, throughout, on performance fees for its managers. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0428b-ftnote.006"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">According to Daniel A. Stratchman, op. cit., pages 31-41. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0428b-ftnote.007"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.3;pn1.1">Which normally provide better Returns on Investment (ROI) than fixed income, such as a commercial bank loan as a premium for higher risk. </s><s n="s2.3;pn1.1">ROI is "A measure of a corporation's profitability, equal to a fiscal year's income divided by common stock and <hi rend="underlined">preferred stock</hi> <hi rend="underlined">equity</hi> plus <hi rend="underlined">long-term</hi> debt. </s><s n="s3.3;pn1.1">ROI measures how effectively the <hi rend="underlined">firm</hi> uses its capital to generate <hi rend="underlined">profit</hi>; the higher the ROI, the better.", See also <seg type="URL" n="http://www.investorwords.com/4316/ROI.html"/> , and <seg type="URL" n="http://www.wisegeek.com/what-is-roi.htm"/> , both accessed April 2007. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0428b-ftnote.008"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.3;pn1.1">"A model based on the belief that as prices increase (or decrease), <hi rend="underlined">closing prices</hi> tend to accumulate ever more closely to the highs (or lows) for a given period." or "More generally, pertaining to a series of random processes" (from <seg type="URL" n="http://www.investorwords.com/4723/stochastic.html"/> ). - </s><s n="s2.3;pn1.1">the latter by use of the <hi rend="italic">Stochastic oscillator</hi>, (namely "A technical indicator which compares a stock's closing price to its price range over a given period of time. </s><s n="s3.3;pn1.1">The belief is that in rising market stocks will close near their highs, while in a falling market they will close near their lows " - see also <seg type="URL" n="http://www.investorwords.com/4724/Stochastic_oscillator.html"/> , and <seg type="URL" n="http://www.wisegeek.com/what-is-stochastics.htm"/> (All websites accessed April 2007.) </s></p></note><p n="p16.53"><s n="s1.1;p16.53">Borrowing moneys to purchase stock of a company while expecting to repay with profit arising from future trade of same stock is known as "leverage"<ref target="BAWE_0428b-ftnote.009"/> in the parlance of the financial market, while borrowing stock from brokers in order to derive gain from betting on expected fluctuations of its value called a "short selling<ref target="BAWE_0428b-ftnote.010"/>". </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0428b-ftnote.009"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Daniel A. Stratchman, op. cit., page 193. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0428b-ftnote.010"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Daniel A. Stratchman, op. cit., page 191. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">See also entry "short sale" in <seg type="URL" n="http://www.investorwords.com/4556/short_sale.html"/> , accessed April 2007. </s></p></note><p n="p17.53"><s n="s1.2;p17.53">Nevertheless, short sales are not in any way the only transaction hedge funds engage in. </s><s n="s2.2;p17.53">In their pursuit of extremely high returns, they engage in various types of transactions in several different markets, amongst which we might list: </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p18.53"><s n="s1.1;p18.53">Credit Derivatives<ref target="BAWE_0428b-ftnote.011"/>, such as collateralised debt obligations (CDO)<ref target="BAWE_0428b-ftnote.012"/> and Credit Default Swaps (CDS), and diverse variations and repackages<ref target="BAWE_0428b-ftnote.013"/> thereof; </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0428b-ftnote.011"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">"A financial instrument whose value depends on or is derived from performance of a secondary source such as an underlying bond, currency, or commodity. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">Also termed derivative instrument." (<hi rend="italic">Black's Law Dictionary</hi>, 5 ed) </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0428b-ftnote.012"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">See <hi rend="italic">Credit Guide: future of CDOs / The next generation</hi>, available at <seg type="URL" n="http://www.creditmag.com/public/showPage.html?page=168585"/> , and <hi rend="italic">The developing global market for CRE CDOs</hi>, By Stuart Goldstein and Angus Duncan, Cadwalader, Wickersham &amp; Taft LLP, SPONSORED EDITORIAL CADWALADER, WICKERSHAM &amp; TAFT, CDO supplement, March 2007, available in <seg type="URL" n="http://www.cadwalader.com/assets/article/030107DuncanGoldsteinISR.pdf"/> , all websites accessed April 2007. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0428b-ftnote.013"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Whereby original conditions of these instruments such as maturity and seniority are altered as a risk management strategy - see .<seg type="URL" n="http://www.creditmag.com/public/showPage.html?page=168585"/> , accessed April 22, 2007. </s></p></note><p rend="bulleted" n="p19.53"><s n="s1.1;p19.53">Energy<ref target="BAWE_0428b-ftnote.014"/> and Commodity<ref target="BAWE_0428b-ftnote.015"/> Derivatives (crucial because higher returns are usually associated with higher risks, and few things can be more volatile than nature<ref target="BAWE_0428b-ftnote.016"/>); </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0428b-ftnote.014"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">See <hi rend="italic">Hedge funds stake out energy - Hedge funds are the new risk-takers in the energy trading markets, but will their preference for volatility bring more or less stability?</hi> </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1"><hi rend="italic">By Catherine Lacoursière</hi> , available at <seg type="URL" n="http://www.energyrisk.com/public/showPage.html?page=9954"/> ", accessed April 21, 2007. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0428b-ftnote.015"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">See <seg type="URL" n="http://www.investorwords.com/975/commodity.html"/>. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0428b-ftnote.016"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.6;pn1.1">Obviously, wrong bets may trigger huge losses. </s><s n="s2.6;pn1.1">For an account of a typical conflict between investment funds and regulators, see <hi rend="italic">De Vitry warns of energy market regulatory pressures - Benoit de Vitry, global head of commodities and emerging markets rates at Barclays Capital in London, today said that regulatory rules could adversely impact the development of a mature energy trading market</hi>., at <seg type="URL" n="http://www.energyrisk.com/public/showPage.html?page=135273"/> . </s><s n="s3.6;pn1.1">See also <seg type="URL" n="http://money.cnn.com/magazines/fortune/fortune_archive/2006/05/29/8378002/index.htm"/>, accessed April 21, 2007. </s><s n="s4.6;pn1.1">For a report on the material effect hedge funds have on oil and gas prices, see <hi rend="italic">Slick operators - How hedge funds, traders, and Big Oil are really driving gas prices.</hi> </s><s n="s5.6;pn1.1">, by <hi rend="underlined bold">Nelson D. Schwartz</hi> and <hi rend="underlined bold">Jon Birger</hi>, FORTUNE, May 18, 2006: 3:36 PM EDT, at <seg type="URL" n="http://money.cnn.com/magazines/fortune/fortune_archive/2006/05/29/8378002/index.htm"/> . </s><s n="s6.6;pn1.1">(All websites accessed April 21, 2007.) </s></p></note><p rend="bulleted" n="p20.53"><s n="s1.1;p20.53">Credit default swaps<ref target="BAWE_0428b-ftnote.017"/>; </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0428b-ftnote.017"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.3;pn1.1">See <hi rend="italic">The evolution of credit default swaps: singlename to indices.</hi> </s><s n="s2.3;pn1.1">By Richard Schetman and Michael Southwick, Cadwalader, Wickersham &amp; Taft LLP. July 2006- ISR Legal Guide 13 <seg type="URL" n="www.isr-e.com"/>., at <seg type="URL" n="http://www.cadwalader.com/assets/article/070106SchetmanISR.pdf"/> ; <hi rend="italic">Bond Basics June 2006 What Are Credit Default Swaps and How Do They Work?</hi> </s><s n="s3.3;pn1.1">, at <seg type="URL" n="http://www.pimco.com/LeftNav/Bond+Basics/2006/Credit+Default+Swaps+06-01-2006.htm"/>. </s></p></note><p rend="bulleted" n="p21.53"><s n="s1.1;p21.53">Carry trade transactions<ref target="BAWE_0428b-ftnote.018"/>, which uses leverage to post high returns by exploiting correlated risks in different markets, such as American treasure bond and e yen exchange rate as to the US dollar (while expecting that interest rates in both countries remain the same). </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0428b-ftnote.018"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.5;pn1.1">See <hi rend="bold">Investment Outlook</hi> Bill Gross | March 2007 <hi rend="bold">Ten Little Assets -</hi> War! </s><s n="s2.5;pn1.1">What is it good for? </s><s n="s3.5;pn1.1">Absolutely nothing! </s><s n="s4.5;pn1.1">Say it again y'all War! </s><s n="s5.5;pn1.1"><hi rend="italic">"War" Edwin Starr, at <seg type="URL" n="http://singapore.pimco.com/LeftNav/Featured+Market+Commentary/IO/2007/IO+March+2007.htm"/> , all</hi> accessed April 2007. </s></p></note><p n="p22.53"><s n="s1.1;p22.53">New species of hedge funds emerged, such as Funds of Funds<ref target="BAWE_0428b-ftnote.019"/> - who try to lure more risk-averse or retail investors into the industry<ref target="BAWE_0428b-ftnote.020"/> - and Vulture Funds (who trade, with huge discounts, bonds<ref target="BAWE_0428b-ftnote.021"/> of heavily indebted poor countries<ref target="BAWE_0428b-ftnote.022"/>, and tend to specialize in similar papers much below investment grade, such as distressed debt<ref target="BAWE_0428b-ftnote.023"/> and junk bonds); </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0428b-ftnote.019"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.3;pn1.1">Which allocate resources amongst various funds, thereby diluting the risk of investing in a single one. </s><s n="s2.3;pn1.1">See <seg type="URL" n="http://www.investorwords.com/2129/fund_of_funds.html"/> , accessed April 2007. </s><s n="s3.3;pn1.1">See also review of <hi rend="italic">A Guide to Private Equity Fund of Fund Managers</hi>, available in <seg type="URL" n="http://www.privateequityinternational.com/books/home.asp?id=22"/> , accessed April 22, 2007. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0428b-ftnote.020"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">OICV - IOSCO - CONSULTATION REPORT - CALL FOR VIEWS ON ISSUES THAT COULD BE ADDRESSED BY IOSCO ON FUNDS OF HEDGE FUNDS - TECHNICAL COMMITTEE OF THE INTERNATIONAL ORGANIZATION OF SECURITIES COMMISSIONS. APRIL 2007, Available at <seg type="URL" n="http://www.iosco.org/library/pubdocs/pdf/IOSCOPD244.pdf"/> , accessed April 2007. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0428b-ftnote.021"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">See <seg type="URL" n="http://www.investorwords.com/521/bond.html"/> , accessed April, 2007. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0428b-ftnote.022"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">See <hi rend="italic">A Factsheet - April 2007 - Debt Relief Under the Heavily Indebted Poor Countries (HIPC)</hi> </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1"><hi rend="italic">Initiative, a</hi>vailable at <seg type="URL" n="http://www.imf.org/external/np/exr/facts/hipc.htm"/> , accessed April 22, 2007. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0428b-ftnote.023"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">See <hi rend="italic">DISTRESSED DEBT - Here to stay - The trends of 2006 show how the market will adapt and grow over the coming years</hi>, accessed April 2007. </s></p></note></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">Regulatory Framework in the UK</head><p n="p23.53"><s n="s1.3;p23.53">It seems to us that the expression "regulation" in the title of this essay should be given a broad meaning if it is to be given a proper answer. </s><s n="s2.3;p23.53">Therefore, while analyzing whether a particular country is in position of curbing threats of financial crises, an overall view of the applicable law thereto will be required, instead of a quick look at current measures of the specialized regulatory agency, for ultimately a country will need the full force of its whole legal system if it is to sort out this crises, and even that may not suffice - for systemic crises triggered by HFs may assume gargantuan proportions requesting a global response by gathering regulators all over the world<ref target="BAWE_0428b-ftnote.024"/>, all to act in a ad hoc basis in a very much impromptu way, responding to circumstances as they present themselves. </s><s n="s3.3;p23.53">Anyway, before we give a definitive answer, we should have an overall view the tools that the UK legal system possesses to carve out a solution. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0428b-ftnote.024"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Including Bretton Woods institutions such as International Monetary Fund (IMF), who may be require to act as a lender of last resort (LOLR) to bail out countries in distress. </s></p></note><p n="p24.53"><s n="s1.4;p24.53">In the UK, the chief regulatory agency as to securities is the Financial Services Authority (FSA), as is the Securities Exchange Commission (SEC) in the US, the Bank of England performing pretty much the same role of the Federal Reserve as the local central bank. </s><s n="s2.4;p24.53">Prone to a British tradition of self-regulation of the markets, the FSA is perhaps less rigid than the SEC, which is constantly involved in litigation with investors in judicial proceedings. </s><s n="s3.4;p24.53">The FSA refrains from regulating hedge funds directly, as most of these have their central management and control offshore, therefore outside the reach of its powers - whose exercise abroad cannot be required for other countries as it would amount to a denial of sovereignty thereto. </s><s n="s4.4;p24.53">Nevertheless, Hedge Funds normally keep permanent establishments in the cities where most of their prospective clients are located, mainly New York and London, therefore within full reach of local laws and regulations. </s></p><p n="p25.53"><s n="s1.2;p25.53">US stance is in stark contrast with UK's in that, thanks to doctrines such as the effects theory, as well as blatantly extraterritorial statutes such as the FCPA, ATCA, RICO, and worldwide tax liability, an expression whose construction is entirely in the discretion of the Magistrate applying the law, who will ponder interests while considering the circumstances. </s><s n="s2.2;p25.53">Moreover, the crude wording of statutes such as the Patriot Act provides them with various opportunities to assert its jurisdiction to traditional hedge fund locations. </s></p><p n="p26.53"><s n="s1.1;p26.53">In contrast, UK, even before being bound by EU laws, had always fare more modest long-arm statutes, and not much more than one big exception to extraterritorial rules _ worldwide asset freezing orders, once known as Mareva injunctions. </s></p><p n="p27.53"><s n="s1.2;p27.53">It should be borne in mind, however, that much of what amounts to national regulations in finance are not in fact the monopoly of a single country. </s><s n="s2.2;p27.53">Countries have to comply with a great deal of soft law, such as Basel Rules, which most of them enact internally. </s></p><p n="p28.53"><s n="s1.1;p28.53">As it admitted in official papers of the FSA<ref target="BAWE_0428b-ftnote.025"/>, notwithstanding the fact that there are now roughly US$500bn assets under HF management globally (ibid, page 7, item 2.1.), there is no regulation specifically targeted on their marketing and selling within the United Kingdom - whose main city, London, is one of the two largest markets for hedge fund in the world. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0428b-ftnote.025"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">(See Discussion Paper 16, Hedge funds and the FSA, item 1.3., page 4, at <seg type="URL" n="http://www.fsa.gov.uk/pubs/discussion/dp16.pdf"/> , August 2002, accessed April 2007.) </s></p></note><p n="p29.53"><s n="s1.1;p29.53">Chiefly statutes imposing on HF are the Financial Services and Markets Act 2000 (FSMA)<ref target="BAWE_0428b-ftnote.026"/> and various FSA regulations implementing legal rules, the Companies Act 1985<ref target="BAWE_0428b-ftnote.027"/>, the Open-Ended Investment Companies Regulations 2001<ref target="BAWE_0428b-ftnote.028"/>. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0428b-ftnote.026"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">See <seg type="URL" n="http://www.opsi.gov.uk/acts/acts2000/20000008.htm#aofs"/>, accessed April 2007. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0428b-ftnote.027"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Available in <seg type="URL" n="http://www.opsi.gov.uk/si/si2005/20051011.htm"/> , accessed April 2007. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0428b-ftnote.028"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Available in <seg type="URL" n="http://www.opsi.gov.uk/SI/si2001/20011228.htm#n2"/> , accessed April 2007. </s></p></note><p n="p30.53"><s n="s1.4;p30.53">In UK, offshore-based HFs typically hires local manager who establishes a limited company or a limited partnership to cater for clients. </s><s n="s2.4;p30.53">As in most jurisdictions, he needs authorisation of the local regulator, the Financial Services Authority (FSA), prior to start operating through a unregulated collective investment scheme pursuant to article 51(1)(a) of the FSMA)<ref target="BAWE_0428b-ftnote.029"/> - and, more specifically, by way of species of this genus named an "open-ended investment company", provided for in Section 236<ref target="BAWE_0428b-ftnote.030"/> of FSMA and regulated in detail by Statutory Instrument 2001 No. </s><s n="s3.4;p30.53">1228 - The Open-Ended Investment Companies Regulations 2001<ref target="BAWE_0428b-ftnote.031"/>. </s><s n="s4.4;p30.53">These investment companies manage property on behalf of a corporation having as its purpose the investment of its funds with the aim of spreading investment risk; and extend to its members the proceeds of such management of funds by or on behalf of that body. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0428b-ftnote.029"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">See <seg type="URL" n="http://fsahandbook.info/FSA/glossary-html/handbook/Glossary/R?definition=G974"/>. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0428b-ftnote.030"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">See (<seg type="URL" n="http://www.opsi.gov.uk/acts/acts2000/00008--t.htm#236"/>, accessed April 2007. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0428b-ftnote.031"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Available in <seg type="URL" n="http://www.opsi.gov.uk/SI/si2001/20011228.htm#n2"/>. </s></p></note><p n="p31.53"><s n="s1.1;p31.53">Besides a manager established in the UK a hedge fund controlled by a parent based offshore will not be able to carry its activities here without qualifying in the UK as an authorised person pursuant to a specific authorisation following fulfillment of certain conditions, or else he or she will fall in the general prohibition rule of Section 19 of the aforementioned statute<ref target="BAWE_0428b-ftnote.032"/>. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0428b-ftnote.032"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">See <seg type="URL" n="http://www.opsi.gov.uk/acts/acts2000/00008--c.htm#19"/> , accessed April 2007. </s></p></note><p n="p32.53"><s n="s1.1;p32.53">Discussion Paper 16, Hedge funds and the FSA (op. cit.), pages 14-19 propounds various ways whereby UK investors may invest with hedge funds<ref target="BAWE_0428b-ftnote.033"/>. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0428b-ftnote.033"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">(At <seg type="URL" n="http://www.fsa.gov.uk/pubs/discussion/dp16.pdf"/>, August 2002, accessed April 2007. </s></p></note><p n="p33.53"><s n="s1.2;p33.53">Advertisement may be made to Individuals or firms classified as market counterparties or intermediate customers under 5 COB 3.11.2 R, Annex 5, a "Category 7 person" who can purchase unregulated collective investment schemes. </s><s n="s2.2;p33.53">These are the target of hedge fund, amounting to sophisticated or qualified investors. </s></p><p n="p34.53"><s n="s1.2;p34.53">Another exception is private customers upgraded by regulated firms to the status of intermediate customers under rule COB 4.1.9 R. - </s><s n="s2.2;p34.53">in any way a much common alternative, perhaps because this would preclude investors from joining the compensation arrangements. </s></p><p n="p35.53"><s n="s1.2;p35.53">In addition, if the intermediary is approached by customer, he will be enabled to provide counsel by means of a one-off communication under article 15 of the Unregulated CIS Order. </s><s n="s2.2;p35.53">Moreover, under COB 3.11.2 R, Annex 5, explanatory notes 2 and 3., an authorised firm may entered into a Customer Agreement under Rule COB.8 and give counsel pending due diligence. </s></p><p n="p36.53"><s n="s1.3;p36.53">They can also invest under rule 5.5.1 R of the Compensation Sourcebook in a listed company, namely a Fund of Funds. </s><s n="s2.3;p36.53">This option has the advantage of diluting further the risk. </s><s n="s3.3;p36.53">As a drawback, it pushes complex HF's techniques further into retail. </s></p><p n="p37.53"><s n="s1.2;p37.53">The local Hedge Fund manager will then enter into an Approval for particular arrangement under section 59 of the FSMA<ref target="BAWE_0428b-ftnote.034"/> with an approved person<ref target="BAWE_0428b-ftnote.035"/>. </s><s n="s2.2;p37.53">Controlled functions are certain key positions within authorised firms, such as occupied by persons in (a) governing positions, (b) with significant managerial positions or (c) exercising activities required for by the Act or in customer functions<ref target="BAWE_0428b-ftnote.036"/>. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0428b-ftnote.034"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">See <seg type="URL" n="http://www.opsi.gov.uk/acts/acts2000/00008--f.htm#59"/> and specified in Rule SUP 10.1. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">Application of the FSA Handbook (<seg type="URL" n="http://fsahandbook.info/FSA/html/handbook/SUP/10/1"/> ). </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0428b-ftnote.035"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">I.e. a person in relation to whom the FSA has given its approval for the performance of a controlled function. - </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">see <hi rend="underlined"> </hi><seg type="URL" n="http://fsahandbook.info/FSA/html/handbook/Glossary/A"/> , accessed April, 2007. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0428b-ftnote.036"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">See <seg type="URL" n="http://fsahandbook.info/FSA/html/handbook/SUP/10/4#D76"/>, accessed April, 2007. </s></p></note><p n="p38.53"><s n="s1.1;p38.53">Clearly, nothing prevents a resident in the UK or British citizens living in any other country from investing online on an overseas hedge fund; in that event, however, they could not benefit from FSA protection. </s></p><p n="p39.53"><s n="s1.1;p39.53">However, they may instead elect to be labeled an intermediate customer by an authorised firm under rule in which case this firm in question has to produce evidence of their the required expertise - not a very likely event. </s></p><div2><head><hi rend="underlined">Unregulated Collective Investment Scheme (CIS) Order</hi><ref target="BAWE_0428b-ftnote.037"/><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0428b-ftnote.037"><p n="pn1.1"> PART XVII of the Financial Services and Markets Act 2000 (Collective Investment Schemes) Order 2001 (SI2001/1062), available in <seg type="URL" n="http://www.opsi.gov.uk/acts/acts2000/00008--t.htm#235"/> , accessed April 2007.</p></note></head><p n="p40.53"><s n="s1.3;p40.53">A Hedge fund is usually structured as a limited partnership, qualifying under the unregulated collective investment scheme rule and being subject to the restrictions on trading promotion spelled out in Section 238<ref target="BAWE_0428b-ftnote.038"/> of Financial Services and Markets Act 2000 (Collective Investment Schemes) Order 2001. </s><s n="s2.3;p40.53">This precludes them from trading directly with the public, requiring them instead to do so only through intermediate customers, market counterparties or to private customers, unless they qualify under some exceptions contained in Rule COB 3.11 of the Conduct of Business Handbook<ref target="BAWE_0428b-ftnote.039"/> which would apply to hedge funds<ref target="BAWE_0428b-ftnote.040"/> This reduces the likelihood that hedge funds degenerate into retail investment options and preserve them for sophisticated or accredited investors. </s><s n="s3.3;p40.53">It should be noted, however, that the section 238(5) of the FSMA gives the FSA power to make rules exempting from the scheme promotion restriction certain promotions relating to unregulated collective investment schemes such as Hedge Funds, provided, however, that they are not made to the general public, for the purposes set forth in rule COB 3.11.2 R is to make appropriate use of the power which the FSA has under section 238(5) of the FSMA. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0428b-ftnote.038"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Available in <seg type="URL" n="http://www.opsi.gov.uk/acts/acts2000/00008--u.htm"/> , accessed April 2007. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0428b-ftnote.039"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Available in <seg type="URL" n="http://fsahandbook.info/FSA/html/handbook/COB/3/11"/> - in force until 31/10/07, to be substituted the following day by a new COB - see <hi rend="italic">FSA publishes radical proposals for move to principles-based regulation</hi> at <seg type="URL" n="http://www.fsa.gov.uk/pages/Library/Communication/PR/2006/109.shtml"/> . </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0428b-ftnote.040"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">See <seg type="URL" n="http://www.fsa.gov.uk/pubs/discussion/dp16.pdf"/> , accessed April 2007. </s></p></note></div2><div2><head><hi rend="underlined">Financial Services Compensation Scheme (FSCS)</hi><ref target="BAWE_0428b-ftnote.041"/><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0428b-ftnote.041"><p n="pn1.1"> Provided for in PART XV, sections 212 to 224, of the Financial Services and Markets Act 2000 (Collective Investment Schemes) Order 2001 (SI2001/1062), available in <seg type="URL" n="http://www.opsi.gov.uk/acts/acts2000/00008--r.htm#212"/> , accessed April 2007, and regulated in detail in <seg type="URL" n="http://fsahandbook.info/FSA/html/handbook/FEES/6/1"/> in the FSA Handbook.)</p></note></head><p n="p41.53"><s n="s1.3;p41.53">The Financial Services Compensation Scheme (FSCS<ref target="BAWE_0428b-ftnote.042"/>) is the UK official fund of last resort for customers of authorised persons. </s><s n="s2.3;p41.53">In principle, it applies only to UK-based retail institutions: therefore, overseas-controlled funds aimed at sophisticated investors, such as hedge funds, fall outside its scope. </s><s n="s3.3;p41.53">In any event, the threshold for compensation (£48,000<ref target="BAWE_0428b-ftnote.043"/>) would not be of much help. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0428b-ftnote.042"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">See <seg type="URL" n="http://www.fscs.org.uk/"/>, accessed April 2007. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0428b-ftnote.043"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">See op. cit., at <seg type="URL" n="http://www.fsa.gov.uk/pubs/discussion/dp16.pdf"/> , accessed April 2007. </s></p></note><p n="p42.53"><s n="s1.1;p42.53">In keeping with current international standards, FSCS requires authorised firms to submit periodically their financial statements so as to assess their financial situation, as it is the current practice of financial regulators in the world. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">Dealing and Managing Conduct of Business' Rules:</head><p n="p43.53"><s n="s1.2;p43.53">The rules in the FSA's Conduct of Business sourcebook<ref target="BAWE_0428b-ftnote.044"/> cover, <hi rend="italic">inter alia</hi>, business promotion, disclosure policy, advise standards, dealings. </s><s n="s2.2;p43.53">It is applicable to persons authorised by the FSA to carry out designated investment business. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0428b-ftnote.044"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Available in <seg type="URL" n="http://fsahandbook.info/FSA/html/handbook/COB"/> , accessed April 2007. </s></p></note><p n="p44.53"><s n="s1.1;p44.53">The Code of Market Conduct/Market Abuse regime<ref target="BAWE_0428b-ftnote.045"/> encompasses conducts relating to qualifying investments which are traded on a prescribed market in, or accessible in, the UK, even if the perpetrator is not authorised and/or located overseas. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0428b-ftnote.045"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">FSA's analysis (<hi rend="italic">Financial Services Authority - Market Abuse: A Draft Code of Market Conduct - Consultation Paper 59), July 200</hi>) available in <seg type="URL" n="http://www.fsa.gov.uk/pubs/cp/cp59.pdf"/> , accessed April 2007. </s></p></note></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">Market Abuse Directive 2003/6/EC (MAD):</head><p n="p45.53"><s n="s1.2;p45.53">The Market Abuse Directive establishes common grounds within EU to curb rules on disclosure and modalities of market abuse - namely insider dealing and market manipulation, encompassing all traded instruments. </s><s n="s2.2;p45.53">It provide for the maintenance of insider traders' lists and determines the reporting by players of suspicious transactions to authorities and the maintenance of insiders lists as well. <ref target="BAWE_0428b-ftnote.046"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0428b-ftnote.046"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">See <hi rend="italic">FSAP - Market Abuse Directive (MAD)</hi>, at <seg type="URL" n="http://www.fsa.gov.uk/Pages/About/What/International/EU/fsap/mad/index.shtml"/>, accessed April 2007. </s></p></note></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">Markets in Financial Instruments Directive (MFID)</head><p n="p46.53"><s n="s1.3;p46.53">This Directive<ref target="BAWE_0428b-ftnote.047"/> is to be implemented in November 1 <hi rend="sup">st</hi>, 2007, in replacement of Investment Services Directive, which is still in force. </s><s n="s2.3;p46.53">It provides general principles of authorisation and supervision by regulators so as to favour supplying of financial services within the EU as a whole. </s><s n="s3.3;p46.53">Amongst others, it sets up new standards for asset management. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0428b-ftnote.047"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">See <seg type="URL" n="http://www.fsa.gov.uk/Pages/About/What/International/EU/fsap/mifid/index.shtml"/> , accessed April 2007. </s></p></note></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">Capital Requirements Directive (CRD):</head><p n="p47.53"><s n="s1.1;p47.53">The introduction of the Capital Requirements Directive will mark a huge step forward in developing a modern capital framework that will improve the risk sensitivity of capital standards for firms across the EU. Considerable uncertainties remain, however, not least in the timing of its introduction </s></p><p n="p48.53"><s n="s1.1;p48.53">It should be noted that, despite apparent (arguably, intended) loopholes, the 2000 Act provides for a own-initiative power, which provides the FSA with considerable discretion in activity. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">FSA's own-initiative power</head><p n="p49.53"><s n="s1.12;p49.53">Under Section 45. </s><s n="s2.12;p49.53">(1) of the FSMA, FSA may exercise its power under an authorised person not only where he judges that is he is failing, or is likely to fail, to satisfy certain threshold conditions, but also, in a very broadly written clause, where "(c) it is desirable to exercise that power in order to protect the interests of consumers or potential consumers." </s><s n="s3.12;p49.53">It may go as far as varying permissions already granted to UK authorised firms following acquisition of their control by foreign firms as well as, under Section 47. </s><s n="s4.12;p49.53">Most significantly, it may assist overseas regulators in respect of an authorised person. </s><s n="s5.12;p49.53">In that event, it must, while deciding whether or not to exercise that power in response to the request, consider whether it is necessary to do so in order to comply with a Community obligation. </s><s n="s6.12;p49.53">For that purpose, it may take into account in particular criteria of reciprocity. </s><s n="s7.12;p49.53">Besides, it nearly resuscitates the practice of the double actionability rule, as it excuses itself from cooperating if the practice does not constitutes a breach of law in the UK . </s><s n="s8.12;p49.53">It also cites non-recognition of the jurisdiction is not recognized by the United Kingdom, as if systemic crises would spare a market of the importance of the UK in view of diplomatic considerations. </s><s n="s9.12;p49.53">More understandably, the relevance of the case is a factor taking into consideration. </s><s n="s10.12;p49.53">Phrasing that it will "consider the importance to persons in the United Kingdom" may appear reasonable, but shows little sensitivity to the current interconnectedness of financial markets. </s><s n="s11.12;p49.53">Public interest is by far the most acceptable criteria - as in some cases this may not coincide with the interest of the overseas regulators, being the interest of the British public whist abiding by widely acknowledge standards. </s><s n="s12.12;p49.53">Lastly, the requirement for previous commitment of undertaking contributions for the FSA to meet the costs of carrying on its action, without any exception, seems a bit unreasonable in the example of a request of an authority of a poor country whose market has a background of money laundering, as is the case of Burma. </s></p><p n="p50.53"><s n="s1.1;p50.53">This seems to us an unacceptable parochial view in many respects. </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">Conclusion</head><p n="p51.53"><s n="s1.2;p51.53">From the very beginning it might have been tempting to state that not only UK's, but all national financial regulations inadequate to protect as to financial crisis, for the very simple reason that regulators are limited in their action to the limits of their territory and slow in their bureaucratic habits, whilst hedge funds are hectic and global. </s><s n="s2.2;p51.53">Besides, it might be contended that much of British "unregulation" is a conscious policy, as the FSA is in fact striking a bargain with funds by allowing them a larger margin of freedom than the US so that it can reap the benefits of their profit maximization techniques. </s></p><p n="p52.53"><s n="s1.2;p52.53">On the other hand, it is clear that, although the FSA does abide by certain virtually universal standards financial market regulation, an absolute uniformity of rules is in any way desirable, as might be the case as to taxation, for it would dry off various sources of liquidity for the global economy. </s><s n="s2.2;p52.53">In the present state, though, there is not much the UK can do on its own - except, perhaps, lobby for the development of a new global financial architecture whilst acknowledging for the differences between countries, and assigning them different functions by allowing them to enact alternative standards. </s></p><p n="p53.53"><s n="s1.3;p53.53">In Westphalia, the Great Powers gathered an decided the Switzerland, which had not sent any representatives, should remain neutral. </s><s n="s2.3;p53.53">Surprisingly enough, not only it still is and is likely to remain as such, as it also has never had its neutrality violated. </s><s n="s3.3;p53.53">Perhaps the time for a new Westphalia has come. </s></p></div1></body><back><div1 type="bibliography"><head rend="underlined bold">BIBLIOGRAPHY (APART FROM MATERIAL REFERRED TO IN FOOTNOTES)</head><p>1. Speech by SIR JOHN GIEVE - DEPUTY GOVERNOR, BANK OF ENGLAND</p><p>Hedge Funds and Financial Stability - at the HEDGE 2006 Conference, Tuesday 17 October 2006.</p><p>2. Financial Services Authority - Hedge funds: A discussion of risk and regulatory engagement, Discussion Paper 05/4, FSA, June 2005.</p><p>3. "What Constitutes Good Practice?"</p><p>4. Basel Committee on Banking Supervision - Core Principles for Effective Banking Supervision - Bank for International Settlements, October 2006.</p><p>5. Basel Committee on Banking Supervision - BIS Papers No 32 - Financial globalisation - Fifth BIS Annual Research Conference, 19-20 June 2006, Monetary and Economic Development, December 2006.</p><p>6. Core Principles for Effective Banking Supervision - Bank for International Settlements, October 2006.</p><p>7. The Regulation and Supervision of Banks Around the World - A New Database. James R. Barth Gerard Caprio, Jr. and Joss Levine, February 2001.</p><p>8. PCP 2005/01 Issued on 7 January 2005 - The Panel on Takeovers and Mergers - Consultation Paper Issued by The Code Committee of the Panel - Dealings in Derivatives and Options - Outline Proposals Relating to Amendments Proposed to be Made to the Takeover Code and the SARS.</p><p>9. A Survey of Securities Laws and Enforcement - Preliminary Draft By Florencio Lopez-de-Silanes - YALE University and NBER - October 2003.</p><p>10. Guide to Emerging Market Regulators Regarding Capital Adequacy Requirements for Financial Intermediaries - OICV - IOSCO - Report of the Emerging Markets Committee of the International Organization of the Securities Commissions - December 2006.</p><p>11. Investor Protection and Corporate Governance - Rafael La Porta, Florencio Lopez-de-Silanes, Andrei Shleifer and Robert Vishny - Department of Econmics, Harvard University, Cambridge, MA 01238, Kennedy School of Government, Harvard University, Cambridge, MA 01238, Graduate School of Business, University of Chicago, IL 60637.</p><p>12. The Required Threshold to Restructure Sovereign Debt - Jose Garcia-Hamilton Jr., Rodrigo Olivares-Caminal &amp; Octavio M. Zenarruza.</p><p>13. Preventing and Containing International Financial Crises: The Case of Brazil. Jorge M. Guira.</p><p>14. Tannenbaum Helpern Syracuse &amp; Hirschtritt LLP - New York - London - <seg type="URL" n="www.thslaw.com"/> - Global Note - PROPOSED RULE TO PROHIBIT FRAUD BY INVESTMENT ADVISERS AND PROPOSED REVISIONS TO THE DEFINITION OF ACCREDITED INVESTOR - To clients and friends of Tannenbaum Helpern Syracuse &amp; Hirschtritt LLP , Date January 17, 2007 (2007 Tannenbaum Helpern Syracuse &amp; Hirschtritt LLP).</p><p>15. Tannenbaum Helpern Syracuse &amp; Hirschtritt LLP - New York - London - <seg type="URL" n="www.thslaw.com"/> - Global Note - SEC ISSUES NO-ACTION LETTER RESPONSE TO ABA LETTER REQUESTING CLARIFICATION OF <hi rend="italic">GOLDSTEIN</hi> DECISION - To clients and friends of Tannenbaum Helpern Syracuse &amp; Hirschtritt LLP, Date August 2006.</p><p>16. Convergence of Hedge Funds and Private Equity Funds - by Michael G. Tannembaum, President Hedge Fund Association. (This article appears in the International Investment &amp; Securities Review 2006, published by Euromoney Yearbooks. For further information, please visit <seg type="URL" n="www.euromoney-yearbooks.com"/>).</p><p>17. Final SEC Interpretative Guidance on Soft Dollar Arrangement. Bingham McCutchen, Hedge Fund Newsletter, <seg type="URL" n="www.bingham.com"/>.</p><p>18. Senate Committee Hearing on Insider Trading Includes Focus on Hedge Funds. Bingham McCutchen, Hedge Fund Newsletter, <seg type="URL" n="www.bingham.com"/>.</p><p>19. SEC proposes Changes to Short Sale Regulations. Bingham McCutchen, Hedge Fund Newsletter, <seg type="URL" n="www.bingham.com"/>.</p><p>20. How to set up your own Hedge Fund. By: GreenTrader Law on Wed 17 of May, 2006 [14:55 UTC], <seg type="URL" n="http://www.moneyscience.org/tiki/tiki-read-article.php?articleId=108"/>.</p><p>21. Private equity funds bristle as hedge funds muscle in - 13 February 2006, <seg type="URL" n="http://www.thelawyer.com/cgi.bin/item.cgi?id=118792&amp;d=122&amp;h=248&amp;f=46"/>.</p><p>22. Hedge Funds strengthen risk management. Financial Times, Thursday January 28.</p></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
