<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_0431a" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Determinants of Health: A cross national empirical analysis</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">The document has a title page which contains:
document title
title part</note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">deleted: page numbers</note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">appendices: statistics and graphs</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">4</p><p n="date">2007-03</p><p n="module title">ECONOMETRICS</p><p n="module code">EC902</p><p n="genre family">Research report</p><p n="discipline">Economics</p><p n="disciplinary group">SS</p><p n="grade">M</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">5378</p><p n="number of s-units">202</p><p n="number of p">52</p><p n="number of tables">5</p><p n="number of figures">0</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">7</p><p n="number of lists">1</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">0</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">26.6</p><p n="average s-units per p">3.9</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">f</p><p n="year of birth">1984</p><p n="first language">Bengali</p><p n="education">OSA</p><p n="course">MSc Economics</p><p n="student ID">0431</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><docTitle><titlePart>Determinants of Health: A cross national empirical analysis </titlePart></docTitle><titlePart/><titlePart><name type="student name"/> Programme: MSc. Economics Course: (EC 902) Econometrics A University Number: <name type="student ID"/></titlePart></titlePage><div1 type="toc" n="1"><head rend="bold">Table of Contents</head><p/></div1></front><body><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">1. Introduction</head><p n="p1.52"><s n="s1.3;p1.52">What a person is or can be, and does or can do is essentially a function of human well being, within which the factor of indisputable importance would be health. </s><s n="s2.3;p1.52">As Nobel Laureate Amartya Sen argues that the "capability to function" is what really matters for a poor or non poor person, drawing on whom the United Nations 1994 Human Development Report asserts the purpose of development as being able to create an environment in which all people can expand their capabilities, and opportunities can be enlarged for both current and future generations. </s><s n="s3.3;p1.52">This explains why countries with high levels of income but poor standards of health and education have been referred to as cases of "growth without development". </s></p><p n="p2.52"><s n="s1.4;p2.52">Unprecedented advances in human capital have taken place in the last half-century, in both developed and developing countries. </s><s n="s2.4;p2.52">The purpose of this paper is to study the relationship between health and economic development through a cross-national empirical analysis by estimating the determinants of health and emphasising on the impact of income and education on the state of health. </s><s n="s3.4;p2.52">However the paper is not successful in finding a reverse causality for both these relationships, though studies do show that healthier people earn higher wages due to productivity differences thereby increasing utility by increasing income and raising the return to the economy. </s><s n="s4.4;p2.52">Ambiguity with regard to its causal relation with education still holds in reality. </s></p><p n="p3.52"><s n="s1.4;p3.52">In section 2 the paper reviews and discusses plausible findings of prominent economists in this area. </s><s n="s2.4;p3.52">Section 3 presents the methodology undertaken for the study, the econometric techniques used for estimating the model and also describes the data. </s><s n="s3.4;p3.52">Section 4 provides the empirical results, its analysis and implications. </s><s n="s4.4;p3.52">In section 5 the paper concludes with summary of the results, extensions to further study along with suggestions for government policy making. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">2. Literature Review</head><p n="p4.52"><s n="s1.5;p4.52">The study of health has been of immense economic, political and social importance. </s><s n="s2.5;p4.52">The World Health Organisation defines health as "a state of complete physical, mental and social well being and not merely the absence of disease and infirmity". </s><s n="s3.5;p4.52">Health has both intrinsic (as a source of well being) and instrumental value (affects economic growth). </s><s n="s4.5;p4.52">It increases worker productivity through improved nutrition. </s><s n="s5.5;p4.52">Several empirical studies account for this relationship. </s></p><p n="p5.52"><s n="s1.5;p5.52">Three of the eight millennium development goals of the United Nations stress on health, namely a reduction in child mortality by two thirds, improving maternal health by three quarters and halting HIV/AIDS, malaria and other diseases, all by the year 2015. </s><s n="s2.5;p5.52">Several indicators have been used to determine health in prior studies. </s><s n="s3.5;p5.52">The World Health Organisation (2003) drew attention to the social indicators of health like unemployment, stress, social exclusion, work atmosphere, addiction, early life conditions and so on. </s><s n="s4.5;p5.52">Rogers and Wofford (1989) examine factors influencing life expectancy in 95 less developed countries and find it has a strong correlation with the percentage of population in agriculture followed by literacy and safe water. </s><s n="s5.5;p5.52">Urbanisation however was found to be less influential. </s></p><p n="p6.52"><s n="s1.2;p6.52">R. Scott Frey and Caroline Field (2004) used macro social change theories to explain variations in infant mortality rates across countries and found female education, debt dependence and economic disarticulation to play a significant role, whereas factors like industrialisation and state strength did not have very sharp effects. </s><s n="s2.2;p6.52">Strauss, Gertler, Rehman and Fox (1993) investigate the socioeconomic determinants of adult ill health across Bangladesh, Jamaica, Malaysia and the United States and find strong effects of education and to and extent per capita household expenditure, they also find considerable life cycle effects causing gender differentials in reporting health problems, with women reporting problems at an earlier age. </s></p><p n="p7.52"><s n="s1.3;p7.52">Tulijapurkar and Boe (1998) have examined the impact of several factors like education, gender, marital status, race and ethnicity on health; they have also studied the development of mortality and found mortality rates to be declining over time and since life expectancy is negatively correlated with mortality, it would be found to be increasing. </s><s n="s2.3;p7.52">Parsons (1982) showed through a probit model that factors like mortality rate, age, prior unemployment experience, and social security benefit and local welfare are negatively related with labour force participation which is positively related with hourly wage rate. </s><s n="s3.3;p7.52">Few other studies which could be mentioned are those on life expectancy by Carnes,al. (1996); Finch and Kirkwood (2000); Manton, Stallard, and Tolley (1991), Olshanskyal. (2001). </s></p><p n="p8.52"><s n="s1.1;p8.52">J. Strauss and D. Thomas (1998) followed Grossman (1972) and defined the health production function as: </s></p><p n="p9.52"><s n="s1.1;p9.52"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0431a-form.001"/> </s></p><p n="p10.52"><s n="s1.6;p10.52">Where health H depends on a vector of health inputs N; labour supply L; socio economic characteristics like gender A; family background B' including parental health and local health infrastructure; the disease environment D; and unobservables μ which is the inherent healthiness of an individual and e <hi rend="sub">h</hi> the measurement error. </s><s n="s2.6;p10.52">Of all these health is decreasing only in labour supply as greater work would require greater energy. </s><s n="s3.6;p10.52">In another study they found that taller men earn more money in Brazil even after controlling for important determinants like education and experience. </s><s n="s4.6;p10.52">They conclude that "the balance of evidence points to a positive effect of elevated nutrient intakes on wages, at least among those who are malnourished". </s><s n="s5.6;p10.52">Strauss (1986) found a strong positive impact of better nutrition on farm productivity in Sierra Leone using the agricultural production function and average caloric intake per adult in rural households. </s><s n="s6.6;p10.52">There are several studies suggesting the indirect effect of health in increasing productivity of the labour force for instance Harvey Leibenstein (1957), Mushkin (1962) and Sahn and Alderman (1988). </s></p><p n="p11.52"><s n="s1.5;p11.52">Several empirical studies have been undertaken to determine the close relationship between health and education in economic development. </s><s n="s2.5;p11.52">A longer life raises the return to investments in education in several ways while greater education capital raises returns to investment in health. </s><s n="s3.5;p11.52">However this is more common sense knowledge than is proven by some literature. </s><s n="s4.5;p11.52">Behrman (1996) argues that associations do not necessarily indicate causality, he emphasises on the role of unobservables depending on the choices made by individuals and their families such as parental care and guidance. </s><s n="s5.5;p11.52">He incorporates variables like health, gender, pupil teacher ratios, parental education among others and concludes that the effects may be understated or overstated implying an downward or upward bias owing to correlation with the dominant unobserved factor. </s></p><p n="p12.52"><s n="s1.6;p12.52">Pollitt et.al. </s><s n="s2.6;p12.52">(1989) found contradictory results for the impact of iron deficiency on children's school performance in India and Indonesia where there were significant positive effects and in Thailand where the results were contradictory. </s><s n="s3.6;p12.52">Jamison (1986) found a positive correlation between height for age and school performance in China. </s><s n="s4.6;p12.52">Similarly, Moock and Leslie (1986) have found height for age to be a robust indicator of school enrolment. </s><s n="s5.6;p12.52">Analyses by Colclough (1982), Psacharopoulos (1994), World Bank (1993), and the United Nations Development Programme (1990) are based on studies with a wide range of results, some of which indicate little or no effects. </s><s n="s6.6;p12.52">Not only do developing countries have lower levels of health the nature and incidence of diseases are different and cause greater damage as has been found by the World Bank (1993); Dean Jamisonal. (1993); Pinstrup Andersonal. (1993). </s></p><p n="p13.52"><s n="s1.3;p13.52">The plethora of work undertaken in the area of health and economic development speaks for its critical importance in the world today. </s><s n="s2.3;p13.52">However, the advancement has only been recent, until the last quarter of the century (it was the returns to education on which much greater amount of work was done under human capital). </s><s n="s3.3;p13.52">Nonetheless, the fact remains that a healthy population is a prerequisite for successful economic development, and the interrelationships therein are increasingly gaining special interest. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">3. Methodology and Data</head><p n="p14.52"><s n="s1.3;p14.52">Following the examination of prior empirical work in the previous section, both institutional and fundamental variables are incorporated in the model to test first the determinants of health, including income, education and other factors, and then briefly discuss its causal relation with education and economic growth by using it as an explanatory variable. </s><s n="s2.3;p14.52">Cross-country regression models for the world are constructed and the estimation method applied is Ordinary Least Squares (OLS). </s><s n="s3.3;p14.52">As there are several equations estimated with different sets of independent variables, the basic multiple regression model used could be represented by the form: </s></p><p n="p15.52"><s n="s1.1;p15.52"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0431a-form.002"/> </s></p><p n="p16.52"><s n="s1.3;p16.52">where y is the dependent variable, β<hi rend="sub">0</hi> is the constant, β<hi rend="sub">1</hi>,β<hi rend="sub">2,....</hi> </s><s n="s2.3;p16.52">β<hi rend="sub">k</hi> are coefficients of the independent variables x <hi rend="sub">1</hi>,x <hi rend="sub">2</hi>,....x <hi rend="sub">k</hi> which are assumed to be exogenous. </s><s n="s3.3;p16.52">The definitions of variables used in the analysis are provided in table 1. </s></p><list type="simple"><head rend="bold">Table 1: Definition of Variables</head><item><hi rend="bold">edup</hi> = average gross primary school enrolment rate from 1995 to 2004</item><item><hi rend="bold">edus</hi> = average gross secondary school enrolment rate from 1995 to 2004</item><item><hi rend="bold">gdp95</hi> = GDP per capita, PPP (constant 2000 international $) in 1995</item><item><hi rend="bold">gdpg</hi> = average GDP per capita growth (annual %) from 1995 to 2004</item><item><hi rend="bold">gini</hi> = average gini index from 1995 to 2004 </item><item><hi rend="bold">hiv</hi> = average HIV prevalence rate (% of population ages 15-49) from 1995 to 2004</item><item><hi rend="bold">hlthexp</hi> = average total health expenditure (% of GDP) from 1995 to 2004</item><item><hi rend="bold">imdpt</hi> = average immunization against DPT (% of children ages 12-23 months) from 1995 to 2004</item><item><hi rend="bold">immea</hi> = average immunization against measles (% of children ages 12-23 months) from 1995 to 2004</item><item><hi rend="bold">inv</hi> = average gross domestic investment (% of GDP) from 1995 to 2004</item><item><hi rend="bold">le</hi> = average life expectancy at birth (total years) from 1995 to 2004</item><item><hi rend="bold">le95</hi> = life expectancy at birth (total years) in 1995</item><item><hi rend="bold">lf</hi> = average growth rate of total labor force from 1995 to 2004</item><item><hi rend="bold">lite</hi> = 100 - ilite, where ilite = average illiteracy rate from 1995 to 2004</item><item><hi rend="bold">lite95</hi> = 100 - ilite95, where ilite95 = illiteracy rate in 1995</item><item><hi rend="bold">phys</hi> = average number of physicians per 1,000 people from 1995 to 2004</item><item><hi rend="bold">pop</hi> = average annual population growth rate from 1995 to 2004</item><item><hi rend="bold">pute</hi> = average pupil-teacher ratio in primary education from 1995 to 2004</item><item><hi rend="bold">safew</hi> = average improved water source (% of population with access) from 1995 to 2004 </item><item><hi rend="bold">sanit</hi> = average improved sanitation facilities (% of population with access) from 1995 to 2004</item><item><hi rend="bold">smkng</hi> = average smoking prevalence rates (% of adults) from 1995 to 2004</item><item><hi rend="bold">trade</hi> = average share of trade in GDP from 1995 to 2004</item><item><hi rend="bold">urbpop</hi> = average urban population from 1995 to 2004</item></list><p n="p17.52"><s n="s1.4;p17.52">The popular indices used for measuring health under nutrition based efficiency wage theory are per capita caloric intake, body mass index and so on. </s><s n="s2.4;p17.52">However for cross country analysis, there are two kinds of data which are frequently used, life expectancy and mortality rate. </s><s n="s3.4;p17.52">Life expectancy has wider coverage (adult mortality rates give the probability of dying between ages of 15 and 60) and thus is more appropriate and shall be used in this analysis (as a dependent variable for the first set of regressions and then as a dependent variable for the second and third regressions). </s><s n="s4.4;p17.52">To study the causal relation, average GDP per capita growth rate (in case of economic growth) and the average literacy rate (in case of education) are used as dependent variables. </s></p><p n="p18.52"><s n="s1.4;p18.52">The data has primarily been obtained from World Development Indicators, the World Bank database. </s><s n="s2.4;p18.52">Few of the variables for which data was missing (HIV prevalence rates, immunisation rates, rates for access to improved water and sanitation, and literacy rates) were obtained from the United Nations Statistics Division (UNSD); World Health Organisation (WHO); and the United Nations Children's Fund (UNICEF) databases. </s><s n="s3.4;p18.52">All data was accessible through the Economic and Social Data Service International website. </s><s n="s4.4;p18.52">Although the databases contained data for over 200 countries (including both developing and developed countries) after adjustments for missing observations, the sample size reduced considerably. </s></p><p n="p19.52"><s n="s1.4;p19.52">The regressions are based on data averaging over 10 years from 1995 to 2004. </s><s n="s2.4;p19.52">It is extremely costly and time consuming to obtain social indicators, which explains their scarcity. </s><s n="s3.4;p19.52">Some of the indicators are collected only once in every couple of years, also due to the fact that these do not change much within a year. </s><s n="s4.4;p19.52">Thus taking averages reduces measurement error at the same time enables one to get maximum data. </s></p><p n="p20.52"><s n="s1.4;p20.52">The presence of heteroskedasticity is tested using the pure form White Test for Heteroskedasticity with cross terms, wherever possible. </s><s n="s2.4;p20.52">If the null for no heteroskedasticity (homoskedasticity) is rejected at the 10% level of significance, heteroskedasticity is a problem (which would give unbiased and consistent, but inefficient estimators i.e. </s><s n="s3.4;p20.52">OLS is no longer the Best Linear Unbiased Estimator as variance is biased, and does not remain valid for constructing confidence intervals and t-statistics) and the White's Heteroskedasticity consistent standard errors and covariances (which are robust) are used as a remedial measure (WLS i.e. </s><s n="s4.4;p20.52">GLS estimators for correcting heteroskedasticity may also be used when the variance is correctly specified). </s></p><p n="p21.52"><s n="s1.5;p21.52">Specification errors may arise due to inclusion of irrelevant variables (leading to inefficiency), omission of important ones (leading to bias and inconsistency), using proxies leading to errors of measurement bias, or using the wrong functional form. </s><s n="s2.5;p21.52">To test for specification error or more specifically the correct functional form, the Ramsey's RESET test is used. </s><s n="s3.5;p21.52">If the computed F-Statistic is significant at the 5% level, the model has the incorrect functional form and has been mis-specified. </s><s n="s4.5;p21.52">However its drawback is that it provides no real direction to proceed if the model is rejected. </s><s n="s5.5;p21.52">Other data problems like missing data (information missing on key variables for several units in the sample leading to reduction in sample size) and the presence of outliers of influential observations (observation making a large difference on the estimation, are also encountered. </s></p><p n="p22.52"><s n="s1.3;p22.52">To test for adequacy, the normality assumption for the disturbance term u is tested using the Jarque-Bera (JB) test for normality which tests the joint hypothesis of the skewness and kurtosis coefficients (for the skewness and kurtosis of the OLS residuals) being equal to 0 and 3 respectively. </s><s n="s2.3;p22.52">If the p value of the JB statistic is sufficiently high and the hypothesis is not rejected, the residuals are normally distributed. </s><s n="s3.3;p22.52">Ideally the JB statistic should be used for large sample sizes. </s></p><p n="p23.52"><s n="s1.3;p23.52">To test how good the fitted model is, besides using the above mentioned tests, certain basic criteria are used. </s><s n="s2.3;p23.52">Whether the signs of the estimated coefficients are in accordance with prior expectations; whether the relationship is statistically significant (using t and F test statistics, also the Wald test when required) and the explanatory power of the model (using R <hi rend="sup">2</hi> and adjusted R <hi rend="sup">2</hi>) are discussed. </s><s n="s3.3;p23.52">Before the interpretation of these results the statistical tests that need to be performed, on the estimated OLS and its residuals, their reasons and implications are summarized in the table 2 below. </s></p><table id="BAWE_0431a-tab.001"><head rend="bold">Table 2: Summary of tests</head><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p24.52"><s n="s1.3;p24.52">The E-views5 econometrics software has been used to perform the appropriate tests. </s><s n="s2.3;p24.52">All detailed test results are provided in the appendix. </s><s n="s3.3;p24.52">The summarised results and empirical implications are given in the following section. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">4. Results and Empirical Implications</head><div2><head rend="bold">Determinants of Health</head><p n="p25.52"><s n="s1.3;p25.52">Health conditions are determined by factors such as the level of income, education and other health inputs. </s><s n="s2.3;p25.52">Table 3 summarizes these findings using life expectancy as the indicator of health status. </s><s n="s3.3;p25.52">Both economic growth and education are found to play an extremely significant role in explaining the state of health. </s></p><table id="BAWE_0431a-tab.002"><head rend="bold">Table 3: Regressions for Life ExpectancyDependent Variable: le</head><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p26.52"><s n="s1.3;p26.52"><hi rend="bold">Note:</hi> The OLS estimation method with the White Heteroskedasticity-Consistent Standard Errors &amp; Covariance is used for equations (1), (5) and (7) and the OLS estimator is applied to equations (2), (3), (4) and (6). </s><s n="s2.3;p26.52">For notations see previous section. </s><s n="s3.3;p26.52">Standard errors are given in parentheses. </s></p><p n="p27.52"><s n="s1.1;p27.52">* significant at the 10% level, ** significant at the 5% level, *** significant at the 1% level </s></p><p n="p28.52"><s n="s1.8;p28.52">All equations illustrate the strong positive relation between life expectancy and GDP per capita, which is found to be significant even at the 1% level. </s><s n="s2.8;p28.52">Equation (1) shows that a percentage change in GDP per capita increases life expectancy at birth by about 0.07 years. </s><s n="s3.8;p28.52">Education measured by the literacy rate shows a positive impact on the state of health, especially in equations (5) and (7) where it is significant at the 1% level, increasing life expectancy by 0.07 and 0.10 years respectively for a unit increase in the literacy rate. </s><s n="s4.8;p28.52">In equation (1) however it is only significant at the 10% level. </s><s n="s5.8;p28.52">The number of physicians per thousand also play a positive and highly significant role, increasing life expectancy by about 2 years for an additional physician per thousand. </s><s n="s6.8;p28.52">These three indicators together account for almost 67% of the variation in life expectancy as a measure of health as shown by the R <hi rend="sup">2</hi> of 0.67 in equation (1). </s><s n="s7.8;p28.52">The adjusted R <hi rend="sup">2</hi> which has also been reported, imposes a penalty for adding additional independent variables to a model but unfortunately is not known to be a better estimator. </s><s n="s8.8;p28.52">The White's test for heteroskedasticity for equation (1) shows a p value of 0.045 which means that the null hypothesis for homoskedasticity is rejected and the usual OLS t-statistics can no longer be used, thus the OLS standard errors and variances are replaced by heteroskedasticity robust ones. </s></p><p n="p29.52"><s n="s1.6;p29.52">Equation (2) includes access to safe drinking water as an explanatory variable along with GDP per capita and the literacy rate and is found to be statistically significant at the 1% level contributing to 0.19 additional years of life expectancy for a unit increase in percentage of population with access to safe water resources. </s><s n="s2.6;p29.52">It is also highly significant for equations estimated in equations (5), (6) and (7). </s><s n="s3.6;p29.52">The White test in equation (2) cannot be rejected with a p value of 0.51 therefore heteroskedaticity is not a problem and the usual OLS standard errors are used. </s><s n="s4.6;p29.52">With similar reasoning the null for homoskedasticity is not rejected for equations (3), (4) and (6) and rejected for equations (5) and (7) for which heteroskedasticity robust errors are used. </s><s n="s5.6;p29.52">For equation (6) the White's test was used with no cross terms as the variable gini had insufficient observations for it to be calculated. </s><s n="s6.6;p29.52">In the subsequent equation the variable was dropped and heteroskedasticity was indeed found to be a problem using the pure form of the test with cross terms, which has been used for all remaining equations as well. </s></p><p n="p30.52"><s n="s1.6;p30.52">Equations (3) and (4) test for the significance of immunisation against DPT and measles respectively (besides income and education) both turn out to be significant even at the 1% level increasing life expectancy by 0.23 years with a unit increase in the percentage of vaccinations against DPT and 0.25 years in case of measles. </s><s n="s2.6;p30.52">However literacy remains insignificant even at the 10% level in both regressions. </s><s n="s3.6;p30.52">The R <hi rend="sup">2</hi> increases to about 0.73 in each case. </s><s n="s4.6;p30.52">The intercept is highly significant for equation (4) at the 1% level, showing the average life expectancy would to be as low as 11 years in the absence of these three variables. </s><s n="s5.6;p30.52">Equation (5) includes an extremely important determinant of health other than GDP per capita, literacy, and access to safe water all three of which are significant at the 1% level, namely the HIV prevalence rate which is responsible for reducing life expectancy (indicated by the negative sign) by about 1.1 years for a unit increase in the rate of HIV prevalence. </s><s n="s6.6;p30.52">The explanatory power of the model immediately increases to about 88%. </s></p><p n="p31.52"><s n="s1.6;p31.52">In equations (6) and (7) a number of explanatory variables are newly included to indicate health status. </s><s n="s2.6;p31.52">They are the urban population of a country, access to sanitation facilities, smoking prevalence rates, the gini index as a measure of inequality, and the expenditures on health by the government, both equations find GDP per capita, literacy, safe water, HIV, as highly significant either at the 1% or 5% levels. </s><s n="s3.6;p31.52">The intercept in equation (6) is found to be significant at the 5% level indicating life expectancy to be around 16 years in the absence of all other variables. </s><s n="s4.6;p31.52">After dropping the gini index variable in equation (6), in equation (7) health expenditure becomes significant at the 10% level. </s><s n="s5.6;p31.52">The explanatory power of the model is extremely good with an R <hi rend="sup">2</hi> of about 0.91 in both cases. </s><s n="s6.6;p31.52">However quite a few of the new explanatory variables like urban population, sanitation, smoking (which does show a negative effect) and the gini index which have insignificant t-statistics and do not turn out to be as significant as anticipated. </s></p><p n="p32.52"><s n="s1.12;p32.52">Thus with such a high R <hi rend="sup">2</hi> and insignificant t-statistics the problem of multicollinearity is suspected. </s><s n="s2.12;p32.52">However multicollinearity is essentially a data deficiency problem. </s><s n="s3.12;p32.52">Dropping a variable may lead to a specification bias. </s><s n="s4.12;p32.52">Other remedial measures could be centring (subtracting the mean from each offending independent variable) or ridge regression. </s><s n="s5.12;p32.52">The basic solution would be to increase the sample size, as in this particular case data infact was deficient in terms of its scarcity for some particular variables like smoking prevalence, the gini index and few others. </s><s n="s6.12;p32.52">Also the problem of outliers and random samples are not ruled out. </s><s n="s7.12;p32.52">In the data which was missing there could have been some variables which would particularly be influential. </s><s n="s8.12;p32.52">Also the data for developing countries for which the analysis should hold even more strongly by intuition, is even harder to get and is absent for a lot of countries. </s><s n="s9.12;p32.52">However, the each of the regressions is jointly significant, indicated by a p value of zero for the F- statistic for all seven equations. </s><s n="s10.12;p32.52">Few further statistical tests are conducted on equation (6) and its residuals. </s><s n="s11.12;p32.52">The test results are summarised in table 4. </s><s n="s12.12;p32.52">Detailed test statistics for each test are given in the appendix. </s></p><p n="p33.52"><s n="s1.1;p33.52"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0431a-form.003"/> </s></p><table id="BAWE_0431a-tab.003"><head rend="bold">Table 4: Summary of test results </head><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p34.52"><s n="s1.2;p34.52">Thus, even though the variables urbnpop, sanit, smkng, gini and hlthexp are insignificant individually, indicated by their t-statistics, jointly they are extremely significant as shown by the Wald test. </s><s n="s2.2;p34.52">Both the Ramsey Reset test for the correct functional form as well as the test for normality show that the correct functional form has been used (at least at the 10% level) and the residuals are normally distributed which makes the model a valid one. </s></p><p n="p35.52"><s n="s1.4;p35.52">The analysis shows that economic growth plays a highly crucial role in the state of health for a nation. </s><s n="s2.4;p35.52">Income provides food for survival, access to medical services and a basic standard of living. </s><s n="s3.4;p35.52">Education provides the knowledge and understanding of basic nutrition, sanitation and hygiene along with creating awareness regarding certain health programmes and preventive measures of diseases. </s><s n="s4.4;p35.52">In addition to these factors well developed health infrastructure like accessibility to safe water, number of hospitals/physicians, immunisations so on are indispensable. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">Economic Growth and Health</head><p n="p36.52"><s n="s1.3;p36.52">Next the causal relation between health and economic growth is tested. </s><s n="s2.3;p36.52">The growth rate of GDP per capita is used as the dependant variable to indicate economic development and the explanatory variables (based on Barro's neoclassical model of economic growth 1997) include GDP per capita in 1995 viewed as initial income to indicate conditional convergence (i.e. further an economy is below its steady state, the faster the economy grows and the gap between developing and developed countries is narrowed), investment which augments capital accumulation, trade liberalisation which increases access to new technologies and competition by opening the economy, the population showing the demographic condition, and the quantity and quality of labour depicted by the labour force, literacy rates and life expectancy as variables. </s><s n="s3.3;p36.52">The results are summarised below: </s></p><p n="p37.52"><s n="s1.1;p37.52"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0431a-form.004"/> </s></p><p n="p38.52"><s n="s1.1;p38.52"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0431a-form.005"/> </s></p><p n="p39.52"><s n="s1.1;p39.52"><hi rend="bold">Note:</hi> White's heteroskedasticity consistent standard errors and covariance is used and standard errors appear in parentheses.*, ** and *** indicate significance at the 10%, 5% and 1% levels respectively </s></p><table id="BAWE_0431a-tab.004"><head rend="bold">Table 5: Summary of test results </head><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p40.52"><s n="s1.6;p40.52">Equation (8) shows the initial level of GDP to be negatively associated with growth rate which complies with the conditional convergence theory. </s><s n="s2.6;p40.52">Investment however is only significant at the 13% level. </s><s n="s3.6;p40.52">Population too enters with a negative sign as an increase in population leads to a decline in shared income by 0.56 per unit. </s><s n="s4.6;p40.52">The labour force too is significant at the 10% level and has a positive impact on the growth rate, this also captures the indirect effect of health which is responsible for the productivity of the labour force. </s><s n="s5.6;p40.52">However it is unfortunate to find that the model does not predict the positive effect of education and health significantly. </s><s n="s6.6;p40.52">The summary of further statistical tests conducted for equation (8) is given in table 5 which indicates that there are several problems with the model. </s></p><p n="p41.52"><s n="s1.7;p41.52">The White's Test indicates that heteroskedasticity is a problem, the null for homoskedasticity being rejected at the 5% level of significance and the robust standard errors have been used to correct for heteroskedasticity. </s><s n="s2.7;p41.52">However, the Ramsey Reset test rejects the null which means that there is a misspecification of the model in its functional form. </s><s n="s3.7;p41.52">As a remedial measure the log of gdpg i.e. the dependent variable is taken after which the p value for the Reset test increases to 0.789 and therefore the null is no longer rejected, however the test statistics for health and education still remain insignificant and therefore have not been reported here (see appendix for detailed results). </s><s n="s4.7;p41.52">There also could be the problem of an omitted variable especially since the R <hi rend="sup">2</hi> value is quite low around 0.19 which would make the model biased as well as inconsistent. </s><s n="s5.7;p41.52">The final test for the normality assumption also rejects the null and indicates that the errors are not normally distributed. </s><s n="s6.7;p41.52">The F and t statistics require the error term to follow the normal distribution else making the testing procedure invalid in small samples. </s><s n="s7.7;p41.52">Probably adding further variables and increasing the sample size could improve the model there is also scope for improvement in data quality. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">Education and Health</head><p n="p42.52"><s n="s1.2;p42.52">The final relationship tested is the indirect impact of health on economic growth through education. </s><s n="s2.2;p42.52">Life expectancy is included as an explanatory variable in the regression for literacy and the results are as follows: </s></p><p n="p43.52"><s n="s1.1;p43.52"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0431a-form.006"/> </s></p><p n="p44.52"><s n="s1.1;p44.52"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0431a-form.007"/> </s></p><p n="p45.52"><s n="s1.1;p45.52"><hi rend="bold">Note:</hi> The OLS estimation method is used, standard errors appear in parentheses. </s></p><p n="p46.52"><s n="s1.1;p46.52">** and *** indicate significance at the 5% and 1% levels respectively </s></p><table id="BAWE_0431a-tab.005"><head rend="bold">Table 6: Summary of test results </head><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p47.52"><s n="s1.9;p47.52">The literacy rate has a strong positive correlation with the primary and secondary school enrolment rates both of which are significant at the 1% level. </s><s n="s2.9;p47.52">The intercept term suggests the literacy rate to be about 45% in the absence of all included variables. </s><s n="s3.9;p47.52">The pupil teacher ratio also plays a significant role and affects literacy negatively as the ratio increases and there are fewer teachers per student. </s><s n="s4.9;p47.52">However there is considerable ambiguity regarding its causal relation with health as discussed in section 2. </s><s n="s5.9;p47.52">Of course better health means enrolment at younger ages, less grade repetition, less absenteeism, more grades completed, and better performance on test scores, but estimates are generally biased towards one direction or another. </s><s n="s6.9;p47.52">In this case, equations (1) to (7) found a strong positive relation between the two variables in most cases, therefore the possibility of an insignificant relation in equation (9) is not inevitable. </s><s n="s7.9;p47.52">Also the impact is highly sensitive to the underlying behavioural assumptions and the nature of unobserved variables. </s><s n="s8.9;p47.52">Effect of certain unobservables like innate ability, motivation, genetic endowment, capacity to concentrate, household intellectual atmosphere, parental time devoted to cognitive development of child, effectiveness of school management and so on have to be kept in mind. </s><s n="s9.9;p47.52">The model does have an explanatory power of about 70%. </s></p><p n="p48.52"><s n="s1.3;p48.52">Further statistical tests carried out for equation (9) are summarised in table 6.The model is homoskedastic, has the correct functional form and though the normality assumption holds at the 5% level of significance, it no longer holds at the 10% level. </s><s n="s2.3;p48.52">However the model does not really have a large sample for which the normality test is more crucial. </s><s n="s3.3;p48.52">All detail test statistics are provided in the appendix. </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">5. Conclusion</head><p n="p49.52"><s n="s1.8;p49.52">The empirical analysis in this paper suggests that health conditions for a sample of both developed and developing countries, are explained primarily by the level of income of a country, its educational attainment, health inputs such as safe drinking water, the number of physicians, immunisation rates, health expenditure and the deadly human immunodeficiency virus(HIV). </s><s n="s2.8;p49.52">The model showing the causal relation of health with economic growth is quite erroneous and only goes to provide limiting reliance on the cross-sectional work, at the same time it emphasises the need for improving the quality of data and reduce the missing observations, which would solve a lot of problems. </s><s n="s3.8;p49.52">In a nutshell data constraints do cripple the analysis severely. </s><s n="s4.8;p49.52">The final model does resemble earlier findings where the relation between health and education holds one way or has shown conflicting results for different countries. </s><s n="s5.8;p49.52">Another drawback is the inability to control for unobserved variables which bias the estimates. </s><s n="s6.8;p49.52">Instruments for these need to be chosen very carefully so as not to create a bias. </s><s n="s7.8;p49.52">Extensions to this study could firstly include the use of better data in correcting the drawbacks of the model. </s><s n="s8.8;p49.52">Also a country or region specific analysis especially for developing nations would be worthwhile. </s></p><p n="p50.52"><s n="s1.9;p50.52">A point of mention is that all these variables are even more important for developing countries where the basic levels of health and education are yet to be attained and thus even necessary provisions for a minimal level of subsistence like daily food consumption is directly influenced by the level of income. </s><s n="s2.9;p50.52">Also the income distribution in these countries show highly skewed patterns with the top 20% of the population receiving 5 to 10 times the income of the bottom 40%. </s><s n="s3.9;p50.52">Literacy rates remain strikingly low at 45% among the least developed countries and infant mortality rates run as high as 10 times those in developed nations. </s><s n="s4.9;p50.52">Life expectancy in 1998 still averaged only 48 years in the least developed nations compared to 63 years for other developing countries and 75 years for developed countries. </s><s n="s5.9;p50.52">In Asia and Africa over 60% of the population barely met minimum caloric requirements necessary to maintain adequate health. </s><s n="s6.9;p50.52">For the year 2001 certain human deprivation indices show that almost a billion people in poor countries were without access to safe drinking water, 766 million did not have access to health services and 2.4 billion lived without sanitation facilities. </s><s n="s7.9;p50.52">In 1995, the number of physicians per 100,000 people averaged only 4.4 in least developed countries compared to 217 in developed countries. </s><s n="s8.9;p50.52">90% of the people inflicted with HIV in the world, live in LDCs. </s><s n="s9.9;p50.52">By the year 2010 life expectancy in Namibia for instance, is expected to fall from 70.1 years without AIDS to 38.9 years with AIDS. This is only a brief insight to the myriad of problems which need to be tackled in the world today. </s></p><p n="p51.52"><s n="s1.8;p51.52">It is true that cross sectional data may over or underestimate true causal effects. </s><s n="s2.8;p51.52">Moreover prior studies based on past data may show different effects due to different incentives, shocks that might have hit the economy at the time and new market developments and reforms that must have come about making it slightly less comparable. </s><s n="s3.8;p51.52">However, there are better studies to suggest to the policy makers the grave importance of improving health standards for economic development. </s><s n="s4.8;p51.52">The relation between health and economic development can create either a vicious or a virtuous cycle. </s><s n="s5.8;p51.52">There is a debate over whether or not the government should subsidise health and education, however everyone should get an equal go at life at least at the subsistence level in their initial years so that they can translate it into long term productivity gains. </s><s n="s6.8;p51.52">The provision of credit for microenterprises is an important poverty alleviation strategy where the credit can contribute to improvement in the nutrition of the poor. </s><s n="s7.8;p51.52">Other policy options are providing cash transfers to poor families, family clinic visits, other nutritional and health benefit in kind and so on. </s><s n="s8.8;p51.52">Another very important aspect is the dissemination of information and creating awareness among the population especially in rural areas of developing countries which are plagued with myriad social problems. </s></p><p n="p52.52"><s n="s1.3;p52.52">However the picture is not all bleak, greater proportion of the government budgets are being devoted towards human capital, there is a trend towards international convergence in measures of health and education, with unprecedented advances having taken place in the last half of the century. </s><s n="s2.3;p52.52">Gross school enrolment rates, teacher pupil ratios, life expectancy have all shown increases which are statistically significant. </s><s n="s3.3;p52.52">Improvements have been faster in developing countries, though the gap with developed countries still remains large. </s></p></div1></body><back><div1 type="bibliography"><head rend="bold">References</head><p>Behrman, Jere R., 1996 "The impact of health and nutrition on education", The World Bank Research Observer</p><p>Frey R. &amp; Field C. (2004) "The determinants of Infant Mortality in the Less Developed Countries: A Cross-National Test of Five Theories" Social Indicators Research 52 </p><p>Graves, Philip E. &amp; Baer, Audrey, 2002 "Predicting Life Expectancy: a cross country empirical analysis" University of Colorado</p><p>Gujarati, Damodar, 2004 "Basic Econometrics," Boston; London: McGraw-Hill</p><p>Hatasa, Nobuhide, 2001 "Health and Economic Development: a cross national empirical approach" J. National Institute of Public Health</p><p>Karatzas George 2000 "On the determination of the US aggregate health care expenditure" Applied Economics 32</p><p>Lee Jong-Wha Lee "Economic Growth and Human Development in the Republic of Korea 1945-1992", UNDP occasional paper 24</p><p>Strauss, Gertler, Rehman and Fox (1993) "Gender and life cycle differentials in the patterns and determinants of Adult Health" Journal of Human Resources 28</p><p>Strauss John and Thomas Duncan 1998 "Health, Nutrition and Economic Development" Journal of Economic Literature 36</p><p>Todaro Michael P. &amp; Smith Stephen C. "Economic Development", Pearson Education, 2003 </p><p>United Nations Statistics Division "Report on the Global Aids Epidemic" UNAIDS, 2004</p><p>and the WHO-UNICEF "Joint Monitoring Programme"</p><p>Wooldridge, M. Jeffrey, 2006 "Introductory Econometrics: A Modern Approach," Thomson South Western</p><p>World Bank "World Development Indicators" 2006</p></div1><div1 type="appendix"><head rend="bold">Appendix 1a: Statistics and graphs</head><p/></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
