<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_0432a" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title></title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">deleted: page numbers</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">4</p><p n="date">unknown</p><p n="module title">ECONOMETRICS</p><p n="module code">EC902</p><p n="genre family">Methodology recount</p><p n="discipline">Economics</p><p n="disciplinary group">SS</p><p n="grade">unknown</p><p n="number of authors">unknown</p><p n="number of words">3361</p><p n="number of s-units">158</p><p n="number of p">55</p><p n="number of tables">4</p><p n="number of figures">13</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">2</p><p n="number of lists">1</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">0</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">21.3</p><p n="average s-units per p">2.9</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">m</p><p n="year of birth">unknown</p><p n="first language">Hindi</p><p n="education">OSA</p><p n="course">MSc Economics</p><p n="student ID">0432</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front/><body><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined">1. INTRODUCTION</head><p n="p1.55"><s n="s1.1;p1.55">As the demographic transition<ref target="BAWE_0432a-ftnote.001"/> takes place around the globe, its effect is also felt on infant and child mortality rates which have dropped significantly in the past few decades (see table 1). </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0432a-ftnote.001"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">The demographic transition involves the transition of countries from high birthrate, high death rate to low birth rate, low death rate countries as they moved on the path of economic development. </s></p></note><table id="BAWE_0432a-tab.001"><head rend="bold">Table 1. </head><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p2.55"><s n="s1.2;p2.55">As we can see from the table, India has managed to reduce its Child Mortality Rate at quite a rapid pace<ref target="BAWE_0432a-ftnote.002"/>. </s><s n="s2.2;p2.55">However, it is still much higher than the average Child Mortality Rate for high-income countries and significantly higher than the average for middle-income countries. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0432a-ftnote.002"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">The pace of decline has, however, reduced in recent years. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">Claeson, Bos, Mawji &amp; Padmanathan (2000) study the trends in child mortality in India and identify factors leading to this reduction in pace. </s></p></note><p n="p3.55"><s n="s1.1;p3.55">The need to work towards reducing the infant and child mortality rate was felt by the government of India and it announced a new approach towards Reproductive and Child Health in 1996. </s></p><p n="p4.55"><s n="s1.4;p4.55">The paper follows the approach of Murthy, Dreze and Guio (1995) in which the authors attempt to disentangle the effects of different health care practices, socio economic and demographic factors on three indicators of development: total fertility rate, child mortality rate and the relative survival chances of male and female children. </s><s n="s2.4;p4.55">This was done through a cross sectional analysis of data from 296 districts in India. </s><s n="s3.4;p4.55">The data was obtained for 14 of India's 15 most populous states (excluding Assam where the 1981 census was not conducted) for all variables except poverty. </s><s n="s4.4;p4.55">For measures of poverty the authors used the Sen index of rural poverty as estimated by Jain, Sundaram and Tendulkar (1988), based on the 27 <hi rend="sup">th</hi> round of the NSS (1972-73). </s></p><p n="p5.55"><s n="s1.5;p5.55">Apart from this there have been a number of papers that attempt to find determinants of childhood mortality. </s><s n="s2.5;p5.55">However, most of them faced the problem of limited availability of quality data especially at the district level. </s><s n="s3.5;p5.55">Hence they were based mostly on NFHS (National Family Health Survey) state level data. </s><s n="s4.5;p5.55">An NFHS report by Pandey at al (1998) "Infant and Child Mortality in India" and Claeson et al (1999), are examples of such studies. </s><s n="s5.5;p5.55">They use hazard regression models to estimate the effect of variables while controlling for the effects of other variables. </s></p><p n="p6.55"><s n="s1.4;p6.55">Section 2 of the paper presents the data and methodology used in our study. </s><s n="s2.4;p6.55">Section 3 is where we build the model for cross sectional estimation by Ordinary Least Squares. </s><s n="s3.4;p6.55">The section consists of variable selection and testing and correcting for deviations from the Classical Linear Model assumptions. </s><s n="s4.4;p6.55">We shall then analyse the results of our estimation in section 4 and finally conclude in section 5. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined">2. DATA AND METHODOLOGY</head><p n="p7.55"><s n="s1.6;p7.55">Following the adoption of the new RCH approach by the Government of India there has been a particular effort to collect data on health related factors at the district level. </s><s n="s2.6;p7.55">Thus data is available on many more variables for 520 out of the 596 districts in India and we can expect an econometric analysis to give us more accurate results. </s><s n="s3.6;p7.55">As previously stated, we shall follow the approach of Murthy, Dreze and Guio and use cross sectional analysis to identify factors that seem to be the most significant in influencing infant and child mortality. </s><s n="s4.6;p7.55">The data has been combined from two major sources: the Census of India, 2001 and the District<ref target="BAWE_0432a-ftnote.003"/> Level Household Survey conducted by various Regional Agencies and coordinated by the Indian Institute for Population Sciences (IIPS- Mumbai, 1998-2002). </s><s n="s5.6;p7.55">Using data from these two surveys, Ram, Shekhar and Mohanty of the IIPS produced revised estimates of some RCH variables. </s><s n="s6.6;p7.55">Table 2 gives the original list of variables used in our analysis and describes the source of each variable </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0432a-ftnote.003"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.3;pn1.1">A district is a small geopolitical unit of administration within India. </s><s n="s2.3;pn1.1">India has 28 states, each of which contains a number of districts. </s><s n="s3.3;pn1.1">Each district has one major town and may contain a number of villages. </s></p></note><p n="p8.55"><s n="s1.1;p8.55">We shall compare our results with those of previous studies as we go along. </s></p><table id="BAWE_0432a-tab.002"><head><hi rend="bold">Table 2.</hi> <hi rend="underlined">Initial List of Variables which were considered significant by the author for preliminary analysis</hi></head><row><cell/></row></table></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined">3. BUILDING THE MODEL</head><div2><head>3a. <hi rend="underlined">Variable Selection</hi></head><p n="p9.55"><s n="s1.2;p9.55">District level data on 40 variables has been collected which the author feels, may in any way help explain the incidence of child mortality in India. </s><s n="s2.2;p9.55">These are shown in table 2 above. </s></p><p n="p10.55"><s n="s1.4;p10.55">However, in order to decide which of them is relevant for our analysis and must be kept in the models, we find the pair wise correlation between all the independent variables. </s><s n="s2.4;p10.55">Pairs of variables with very high correlation coefficients are selected and amongst those, the insignificant variables that do not help much in explaining the Infant mortality or Under 5 mortality are dropped. </s><s n="s3.4;p10.55">This helps us tackle the problem of multicollinearity in the model and limits the number of explanatory variables to more significant ones. </s><s n="s4.4;p10.55">Finally we are left with 26 variables, which represent 5 different characteristics of a district. </s></p><list type="bulleted"><item>Economic Development </item><item>Demographic Features</item><item>Social Characteristics</item><item>Health Care Utilisation</item><item>Malnutrition (Measured by deviations from norms set by WHO and characterized as severe if &lt; 3S.D below WHO norm, moderate if &lt; 2 S.D and > 3 S.D below WHO norm and 'MILD' if &lt; WHO norm and > 2 S.D below norm). </item></list><p n="p11.55"><s n="s1.1;p11.55">Details of each variable are given in table 3 below. </s></p><p n="p12.55"><s n="s1.1;p12.55">The table below contains a list of variable names, description, and impact of the variables on infant and child mortality as suggested by previous literature<ref target="BAWE_0432a-ftnote.004"/>, and the estimated impact of the variables on infant and child mortality according to this study. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0432a-ftnote.004"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">These results are obtained by combining those in Jain and Visaria (1988), Sandellal. (1985), Pandeyal. (1988), Bhardwaj and Hassan (1983), World Bank (1996) (for effects of Maternal indicators), Claeson, Bos and Padmanathan (Nov, 1999), Phillip (1985), Puffer (1985) </s></p></note><table id="BAWE_0432a-tab.003"><head rend="bold">Table 3</head><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p13.55"><s n="s1.3;p13.55">*Although there are no precise estimates available from previous research about the effect of these malnutrition variables on infant and child mortality, most studies (eg. </s><s n="s2.3;p13.55">Claesonal. 1999, Pelletier et al, 1993), tend to indicate that these variables are positively related with higher infant and child mortality. </s><s n="s3.3;p13.55">In this respect the negative coefficient for wa2 seems odd but it could point towards the explanation that underweight children are more likely to receive better health care and increase their probability of survival. </s></p><p n="p14.55"><s n="s1.1;p14.55">** Insignificant results in our analysis were not included </s></p><p n="p15.55"><s n="s1.1;p15.55">*** No previous estimates found in literature </s></p><p n="p16.55"><s n="s1.1;p16.55">**** b2= (bo3)+(bo3)^2 </s></p><p n="p17.55"><s n="s1.1;p17.55">We study the effect of these variables on both infant as well as under-5-mortality since it has been said that different factors affect the health and survival probabilities of children in different age groups (Pandeyal. 1998). </s></p></div2><div2><head>3b. <hi rend="underlined"> TESTING AND CORRECTING FOR DEVIATIONS FROM THE ASSUMPTIONS OF THE CLASSICAL LINEAR MODEL.</hi> </head><div3><head rend="underlined">Testing for Endogeneity</head><p n="p18.55"><s n="s1.5;p18.55">Multivariate economic analysis assumes that the explanatory variables are exogenously determined. </s><s n="s2.5;p18.55">However, this assumption has to be verified before we go ahead with the analysis. </s><s n="s3.5;p18.55">On inspection, most of the variables included seem to be exogenously determined. </s><s n="s4.5;p18.55">However, the exogeneity of percentage of births of order 3 and above (bo3) can be eyed with suspicion. </s><s n="s5.5;p18.55">High child mortality rates might induce people to have higher planned number of births than the desired family size. </s></p><p n="p19.55"><s n="s1.10;p19.55">We thus test for endogeneity by regressing bo3 on all other exogenous variables and one other variable. </s><s n="s2.10;p19.55">As percentage population in the district below the age of 6(pop06) is highly correlated with bo3 (coefficient .91) but not with the error (coefficient -.03), we take it as the instrumental variable. </s><s n="s3.10;p19.55">The residual from this regression is estimated. </s><s n="s4.10;p19.55">We now regress the Infant Mortality Rate (IMR) on all original variables including the residual from the previous regression. </s><s n="s5.10;p19.55">If the coefficient on the residual is significant we can conclude that the variable (bo3) would be correlated with the error in the original regression. </s><s n="s6.10;p19.55">This would make the OLS estimates inconsistent and we cannot use bo3 as an explanatory variable for infant or child mortality. </s><s n="s7.10;p19.55">However, the above test does not give us significant results (the t statistic for the residual is .93 and p-value is .35) We further use Hausman`s test to see whether the difference between the predicted values of the instrumental variable regression and our OLS regression are large enough to suggest that the OLS estimates are not consistent. </s><s n="s8.10;p19.55">The result shows that the difference between the two is insignificant. </s><s n="s9.10;p19.55">We thus conclude that there is no endogeneity. </s><s n="s10.10;p19.55">We repeat the exercise using U5MR in place of IMR and get the same results. </s></p></div3><div3><head rend="underlined">Testing for Heteroskedasticity</head><p n="p20.55"><s n="s1.5;p20.55">Recall that OLS estimators are BLUE only in the case when there is no heteroskedasticity i.e. when the residuals have a constant variance. </s><s n="s2.5;p20.55">However, if the variances are not constant they could cause the standard errors to be biased and invalidate the test statistics and confidence intervals. </s><s n="s3.5;p20.55">We thus test for homoskedasticity of our estimates using the Breusch-Pagan / Cook-Weisberg test for heteroskedasticity. </s><s n="s4.5;p20.55">This tests the hypothesis of a constant error variance against an alternative hypothesis that the error variance is a multiplicative function of some variable. </s><s n="s5.5;p20.55">On performing the test we find that the null hypothesis is rejected and we can conclude that error variances are not constant. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0432a-fig.001"><head rend="bold">Results of the Test For Heteroskedasticity of errors in the regression of Infant and Child Mortality</head></figure><p n="p21.55"><s n="s1.2;p21.55">This is also shown by a scatter plot of the residuals against the fitted values of IMR (p1) and U5MR (p2).R1 and R2 are the residuals for IMR and U5MR regressions respectively. </s><s n="s2.2;p21.55">The divergence in the error terms depicts heteroskedasticity. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0432a-fig.002"/><figure id="BAWE_0432a-fig.003"/><p n="p22.55"><s n="s1.1;p22.55">To correct for heteroskedasticity we shall conduct a robust regression which gives us White`s(1980) Heteroskedasticity Consistent Standard Errors. </s></p></div3><div3><head rend="underlined">Testing For Normality</head><p n="p23.55"><s n="s1.4;p23.55">OLS regression requires the error terms to be normally distributed. </s><s n="s2.4;p23.55">The graphs below show the distribution of error terms from a regression of IMR and U5MR respectively on the explanatory variables. </s><s n="s3.4;p23.55">The first graph tells us that the residuals obtained by a regression of IMR on the explanatory variables are normally distributed. </s><s n="s4.4;p23.55">However, the residuals obtained from a regression of U5MR do not follow a normal distribution. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0432a-fig.004"><head rend="bold">Residual distribution on regressing IMR</head></figure><figure id="BAWE_0432a-fig.005"><head rend="bold">Residual distribution on regressing U5MR</head></figure><p n="p24.55"><s n="s1.1;p24.55">This can be shown using the Jarque-Bera test or the Kolmogorov-Smirnov test as well which measures the skewness and kurtosis of the residual distribution and compares it with that of a normal distribution to see if the difference is significant. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0432a-fig.006"><head rend="bold">Results of the Test For Normality of Errors in IMR regression (Using STATA)</head></figure><figure id="BAWE_0432a-fig.007"><head rend="bold">Results of the Test for Normality of Errors in U5MR regression (Using STATA)</head></figure><p n="p25.55"><s n="s1.2;p25.55">Two possible causes of non-normality in the u5mr errors could be outliers in the distribution or a misspecified model. </s><s n="s2.2;p25.55">We thus conduct tests for these. </s></p></div3><div3><head rend="underlined">Testing For Misspecification of the Model</head><p n="p26.55"><s n="s1.6;p26.55">In order to check whether misspecification is the actual cause we use the Ramsey Reset test. </s><s n="s2.6;p26.55">The null of no omitted variables is rejected which shows that significant improvements to the model are possible. </s><s n="s3.6;p26.55">We thus try various combinations of functional forms using logs, squares, cubes and square roots. </s><s n="s4.6;p26.55">The most appropriate functional form appears to be when the dependant variable (U5MR) was in logarithmic terms. </s><s n="s5.6;p26.55">A log of the dependant variable implies the estimates would give us the percentage change in U5MR due to a unit change in the dependant variable. </s><s n="s6.6;p26.55">Also after making these changes in the model for U5MR the regression errors become homoskedastic. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0432a-fig.008"><head rend="bold">Results of the Test for homoskedasticity of Errors in U5MR regression after correcting for misspecification. </head></figure><p n="p27.55"><s n="s1.2;p27.55">We can also see this by comparing the two plots of standardised residuals against predicted values below. </s><s n="s2.2;p27.55">The first one for the infant mortality rate depicts heteroskedastic errors (which we had not corrected but had chosen to use robust standard errors in our regressions), and the second one is for U5MR which shows constant error variance. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0432a-fig.009"><head rend="bold">Graph of Standardised Residuals against Predicted Values of IMR </head></figure><figure id="BAWE_0432a-fig.010"><head rend="underlined italic">Graph of Standardised Residuals against fitted values of log(U5MR)</head></figure></div3><div3><head rend="underlined">Testing for the Presence of Outliers in the Distribution</head><p n="p28.55"><s n="s1.4;p28.55">However, we are still unable to generate normally distributed residuals. </s><s n="s2.4;p28.55">We thus check if it could be caused due to the presence of outliers in the distribution. </s><s n="s3.4;p28.55">The presence of outliers can be detected by tabulating the standardised residuals of the equation. </s><s n="s4.4;p28.55">This shows the presence of one outlier and that too with a standardised residual value of just -4.1. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0432a-fig.011"/><p n="p29.55"><s n="s1.2;p29.55">The problem of outliers is corrected by using robust regression estimates. </s><s n="s2.2;p29.55">This attaches a weighting scheme such that outliers would not have as much impact on our estimates. </s></p><p n="p30.55"><s n="s1.1;p30.55">Thus, having discussed the variables to be included and the removal of heteroskedasticity, multicollinearity, non-normallity and misspecification, we shall move on to the actual model and its analysis. </s></p></div3></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined">4. ANALYSIS OF THE RESULTS</head><p n="p31.55"><s n="s1.2;p31.55">Equations 1 and 2 present the model we are estimating. </s><s n="s2.2;p31.55">The results of both regressions are then presented in table 4. </s></p><p n="p32.55"><s n="s1.1;p32.55">EQUATION 1:- </s></p><p n="p33.55"><s n="s1.1;p33.55"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0432a-form.001"/> </s></p><p n="p34.55"><s n="s1.1;p34.55">EQUATION 2:- </s></p><p n="p35.55"><s n="s1.1;p35.55"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_0432a-form.002"/> </s></p><table id="BAWE_0432a-tab.004"><head rend="bold">Table 4: Results of the regression of selected variables on Infant and Under-5-Mortality Rates. </head><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p36.55"><s n="s1.1;p36.55">Note: * coefficient significant at the 10% level of significance </s></p><p n="p37.55"><s n="s1.1;p37.55">** depicts coefficients significant at the 5% level of significance </s></p><p n="p38.55"><s n="s1.1;p38.55">*** depicts coefficients significant at the 1% level of significance. </s></p><p n="p39.55"><s n="s1.1;p39.55">The rest of the variables are insignificant. </s></p><p n="p40.55"><s n="s1.1;p40.55">On the whole the same variables are seen to have a significant affect on both, infant mortality as well as under-5-mortality and in the same direction. </s></p><div2><head rend="bold">Economic Development Variables: - </head><p n="p41.55"><s n="s1.3;p41.55">Urbanisation and percentage households having toilet facility are the two significant Economic Development Variables. </s><s n="s2.3;p41.55">Percentage households with access to toilet facility can in some way be taken as an indicator of district income levels as well. </s><s n="s3.3;p41.55">As one might expect, it has a significant positive impact on child mortality. </s></p><p n="p42.55"><s n="s1.4;p42.55">Surprisingly, the level of urbanisation has a negative impact on child mortality at the ten percent level of significance. </s><s n="s2.4;p42.55">This result seems strange considering unadjusted child mortality in rural India is twice as high as rural india<ref target="BAWE_0432a-ftnote.005"/>. </s><s n="s3.4;p42.55">This result may be a reflection of the deplorable condition of slum dwellers in urban areas. </s><s n="s4.4;p42.55">Low levels of sanitation and lack of information about treatment facilities have been identified as major causes of high child mortality rates among them.<ref target="BAWE_0432a-ftnote.006"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0432a-ftnote.005"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">However, when adjusted for other factors, the difference disappears. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">See Pandeyal. (1998) </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0432a-ftnote.006"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">See ICDS reports on slum dwellers conditions. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">Also see Singhalal. (1986) and de Soyzaal. (1998) </s></p></note></div2><div2><head><hi rend="bold">Social Variables</hi> : - </head><p n="p43.55"><s n="s1.4;p43.55">The percentage proportion of backward castes (scheduled castes and scheduled tribes) and the proportion of girls getting married below the legal age of marriage, all tend to increase child mortality rates in India. </s><s n="s2.4;p43.55">Contraceptive prevalence rate surprisingly also has a significant positive impact on under-5-mortality and infant mortality. </s><s n="s3.4;p43.55">This seems unreasonable since a district with a high contraceptive usage is in a better position to stop unwanted pregnancies and births. </s><s n="s4.4;p43.55">Mean age of marriage of girls does not tend to impact infant mortality levels significantly but increases Under-5-Mortality at the ten percent level of significance. </s></p><p n="p44.55"><s n="s1.2;p44.55">The most surprising finding in our regressions however is that rural female literacy does not have any significant impact on either infant mortality rates or Under-5-Mortality rates. </s><s n="s2.2;p44.55">This goes against most findings and studies which have attempted to show the benefits of female literacy on child health (Murthy, Dreze and Guio, 1995) On the other hand our analysis shows that rural female literacy has, if any, an insignificant negative effect on infant and under-5-mortality. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">Demographic Variables: -</head><p n="p45.55"><s n="s1.3;p45.55">The only significant variable is the Percentage of children of birth order 3 or above in the district. </s><s n="s2.3;p45.55">As expected this tends to increase the infant and under 5 mortality rate. </s><s n="s3.3;p45.55">This can be seen from the graphs below which plot observations of the two variables. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_0432a-fig.012"/><figure id="BAWE_0432a-fig.013"/><p n="p46.55"><s n="s1.5;p46.55">As expected, Percentage children born of women aged 20 or less is significantly negatively related to child mortality. </s><s n="s2.5;p46.55">Its effect on Infant mortality appears to be quite high indeed. </s><s n="s3.5;p46.55">The regression estimate suggests that a one percent rise in such children would lead to a one-point decline in infant mortality rate. </s><s n="s4.5;p46.55">This again is quite surprising and difficult to explain. </s><s n="s5.5;p46.55">Earlier studies tend to support the view that a higher proportion of children born of women under 20 years of age would lead to higher levels of child mortality. </s></p><p n="p47.55"><s n="s1.8;p47.55">The rural sex ratio also does not seem to depict any significant relationship with the infant mortality rate<ref target="BAWE_0432a-ftnote.007"/>. </s><s n="s2.8;p47.55">However at the ten percent level of significance it does seem to be negatively related to the Under-5-Mortality rate. </s><s n="s3.8;p47.55">This is an important finding. </s><s n="s4.8;p47.55">It says that districts with lower rural female-male ratio have higher under-5-mortality rates when other factors are controlled for. </s><s n="s5.8;p47.55">These results can be combined to infer that mortality among girl children in the age group from one to five is much higher than boys. </s><s n="s6.8;p47.55">However, the difference is insignificant in the case of infants. </s><s n="s7.8;p47.55">It is said that infant mortality (primarily neo natal mortality) depends on background characteristics while child mortality depends on the preventive health care behaviour<ref target="BAWE_0432a-ftnote.008"/>. </s><s n="s8.8;p47.55">The fact that girl children have a higher mortality rate in the 1-5 age groups could reveal a bias against the girl child, in measures taken to prevent fatal childhood diseases like tetanus. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0432a-ftnote.007"><p n="pn1.2"><s n="s1.2;pn1.2">We have till now combined neo natal (upto one month of being born) and post neo natal (between one month and twelve months of being born) mortality to study infant mortality. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.2">However, if we break up the two we will be able to explain why sex ratio does not have an effect on infant mortality. </s></p><p n="pn2.2"><s n="s1.4;pn2.2">Neo Natal mortality is supposed to be higher for boys than for girls because of congenital and other causes (Claeson et al, 1999). </s><s n="s2.4;pn2.2">In the post neo natal stage however, diseases become the major cause of child mortality. </s><s n="s3.4;pn2.2">In this period because boys receive better treatment than girl children (Filmer et al (1998), Das Gupta (1987), Chatterjee (1990), their mortality declines relative. </s><s n="s4.4;pn2.2">The net effect is an infant mortality rate, which does not significantly vary with the sex ratio. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_0432a-ftnote.008"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Infant and Child Mortality in India (December, 1998)- Pandey, Choe, Luther, Sahu, Chand </s></p></note></div2><div2><head><hi rend="bold">Reproductive and Child Health Variables: -</hi> . </head><p n="p48.55"><s n="s1.3;p48.55">Among nine such variables only three seem to have a significant negative effect on infant mortality and only one effects under-5-mortality. </s><s n="s2.3;p48.55">These include percentage deliveries carried out at private and public institutions and percentage of pregnant women who had had at least three antenatal checkups. </s><s n="s3.3;p48.55">As expected, private institutional deliveries and antenatal checkups both decrease the probably of infant mortality. </s></p><p n="p49.55"><s n="s1.2;p49.55">Contrary to expectations however, the proportion of deliveries at government institutions is actually significantly positively related to infant mortality. </s><s n="s2.2;p49.55">The result probably has something to say about the quality of government health care institutions in India.. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold"> Malnutrition Indicators: -</head><p n="p50.55"><s n="s1.4;p50.55">A study of the malnutrition indicators yields interesting findings. </s><s n="s2.4;p50.55">Out of five indicators selected in the model, three are significant in explaining both infant and under-5 mortality. </s><s n="s3.4;p50.55">Severe under nourishment among children (indicated by weight for age- 3SD) and severe anemia among pregnant women are positive indicators. </s><s n="s4.4;p50.55">Oddly enough there was a significant negative relationship between the proportion of underweight children (weight for age -2SD) and child mortality. </s></p><p n="p51.55"><s n="s1.2;p51.55">On the whole our analysis brings out some highly unexpected findings. </s><s n="s2.2;p51.55">It creates the ground for further research aimed at explaining the effects of these and other variables on health indicators in India. </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined">5. CONCLUSIONS</head><p n="p52.55"><s n="s1.2;p52.55">We have tried to disentangle the individual effects of social, demographic, nutritional, economic and health care behavioral factors on Childhood mortality in India through a cross sectional analysis of data from 520 districts in India. </s><s n="s2.2;p52.55">Results from this analysis may be questioned on several grounds. </s></p><p n="p53.55"><s n="s1.3;p53.55">Firstly we have not been able to include some variables on which data was not available but which have been proved to be relevant in earlier studies. </s><s n="s2.3;p53.55">This might have caused some omitted variable bias in our results since they are likely to be correlated with other independent variables. </s><s n="s3.3;p53.55">These include female labour force participation, separate male and female mortality rates and literacy among mothers. </s></p><p n="p54.55"><s n="s1.5;p54.55">Secondly, the error terms in our model may be spatially correlated, i.e. their value at any point in space might be correlated with the values of surrounding points. </s><s n="s2.5;p54.55">I have tried to correct for this by including more variables to take care of the correlation between error terms. </s><s n="s3.5;p54.55">I have also tried to include state and region dummies into the equation to take care of spatial correlation. </s><s n="s4.5;p54.55">The results were similar to ones above. </s><s n="s5.5;p54.55">However, if spatial correlation is still present it would give us unrealistic standard errors and show some insignificant variables to be significant. </s></p><p n="p55.55"><s n="s1.13;p55.55">If we overlook these problems with our model, our analysis can yield some interesting policy prescriptions. </s><s n="s2.13;p55.55">Previous research has already laid stress on direct government interventions in Reproductive and Child Health and we shall not repeat that point, although two things are worth mentioning. </s><s n="s3.13;p55.55">One is the importance of antenatal care and the other is the quality of health care facilities provided by the government. </s><s n="s4.13;p55.55">The increased likelihood of child mortality among severely undernourished children implies that the state should identify them and allocate resources to save them. </s><s n="s5.13;p55.55">Such a focused strategy would be much more efficient in reducing the incidence of infant and child mortality and helping India achieve the targets set in the Millenium Development Goals, which seem far fetched going the current rate. </s><s n="s6.13;p55.55">Despite the fact that child marriage is illegal in our country, it is still highly prevalent in rural settings. </s><s n="s7.13;p55.55">Our analysis shows that increased proportion of girls married at the less than 18 years increases the infant mortality rates. </s><s n="s8.13;p55.55">Strict law enforcement and spread of awareness about the ill effects of child marriage are required. </s><s n="s9.13;p55.55">Secondly the study shows that social deprivation can be a very important factor influencing childhood mortality. </s><s n="s10.13;p55.55">Hence, measures need to be taken to improve the social standing of females, Scheduled Castes and Scheduled Tribes. </s><s n="s11.13;p55.55">There is also a need to address the living conditions of slum dwellers in urban areas. </s><s n="s12.13;p55.55">Measures such as reservations that have been taken over the years to uplift the backward classes have clearly not had their impact on the lowest quartiles. </s><s n="s13.13;p55.55">The government then probably needs to review its strategy tackle deprivation among backward classes. </s></p></div1></body><back><div1 type="bibliography"><head rend="underlined">REFERENCES</head><p>Claeson, M., Bos, E. and Padmanathan, I., 1999 "<hi rend="italic">Reducing Child Mortality in India- Keeping up the Pace</hi>", Health and Nutrition Report, World Bank, November, 1999</p><p>Claeson, M., Bos, E., Padmanathan, I., Mawji, T., 2000, <hi rend="italic">"Reducing Child Mortality in India in the New Millenium"</hi>, Bulletin of the World Health Organisation, Vol. 78, No.10, Genebra, 2000</p><p>Jain, A.C., Visaria, P.M., 1988, "Infant and Child Mortality in India: Differentials and Determinants", New Delhi; Newbery Park, Calif.: Sage Publications.</p><p>Murthy, M., Guio, Ann-Catherine, and Dreze, Jean, 1995, "<hi rend="italic">Mortality, Fertility and Gender Bias in India: A District-Level Analysis</hi>", pp. 745-782, Vol. 21, No. 4, December, Population and Development Review </p><p>Pandey, Aravind., Choe, Minja Kim., Luther, Norman Y., Sahu, D., and Chand, J.,1998, "Infant <hi rend="italic">and Child Mortality in India</hi>", National Family Health Survey Reports, No. 11, December,1998</p><p>Ram,F., and Shekhar, C.,2006, "<hi rend="italic">Ranking and Mapping of Districts: Based on Socio Economic and Demographic Indicators</hi>", Indian Institute of Population Studies (IIPS), Research Report</p><p>Ram, F., Shekhar, C., and Mohanty, S.K., 2005, <hi rend="italic">"Preparing database for human development: strengthening vital statistics at the district level</hi>", IIPS Report, 2005</p><p>Ram,F., Mohanty, S.K.,2005 <hi rend="italic">"State of Human Development in States and Districts of India"</hi> IIPS Reports, 2005</p><p>Sandell J.,Upadhya A.K., Mehrotra S.C., "A study of infant mortality rate in selected groups of population in district Gorakhpur", Indian Journal of Public Health, 1985, Jan- March;29(1):37-42</p></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
