<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_3001h" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>What is meant by the term "human - wildlife conflict?" Is this a phenomenon that only occurs within the tropical regions of the world? Give examples to illustrate your answer.</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">Language used in quote: <foreign id="English">English</foreign></note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">
Student name, student number and tutor name in doc header.
</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">3</p><p n="date">2004-10</p><p n="module title">Human Resource Ecology</p><p n="module code">M07335</p><p n="genre family">Essay</p><p n="discipline">Anthropology</p><p n="disciplinary group">SS</p><p n="grade">M</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">1930</p><p n="number of s-units">73</p><p n="number of p">14</p><p n="number of tables">0</p><p n="number of figures">0</p><p n="number of block quotes">4</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">0</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">0</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">26.4</p><p n="average s-units per p">5.2</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">f</p><p n="year of birth">1982</p><p n="first language">English</p><p n="education">UKa</p><p n="course">BA English Studies / Anthropology</p><p n="student ID">3001</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><docTitle><titlePart rend="bold">What is meant by the term "human - wildlife conflict?" Is this a phenomenon that only occurs within the tropical regions of the world? Give examples to illustrate your answer. </titlePart></docTitle></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="section"><p n="p1.14"><s n="s1.1;p1.14">In his book <hi rend="italic">Natural Enemies People-Wildlife Conflicts in an Anthropological Perspective</hi> John Knight defines the phenomenon of human - wildlife conflict as: </s></p><quote lang="English">relations of rivalry or antagonism between human beings and wild animals which typically arise from territorial proximity and involve reliance on the same resources or a threat to human well-being or safety.<ref target="BAWE_3001h-ftnote.001"/></quote><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3001h-ftnote.001"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Knight, John, (2000): <hi rend="italic">Natural Enemies: People-Wildlife Conflicts in an Anthropological Perspective.</hi> </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">Routledge: London &amp; New York. p.3. </s></p></note><p n="p2.14"><s n="s1.9;p2.14">Whilst, this quotation concisely highlights the elemental features of human - wildlife conflicts, it fails to incorporate the numerous complex issues this umbrella idiom covers. </s><s n="s2.9;p2.14">In fact, human-wildlife conflicts are multifaceted and assume a variety of forms. </s><s n="s3.9;p2.14">Therefore, whilst this essay will address the elements of competition and predation that create the primary issues of conflict, including; overlapping of land resources and water resources, animals foraging, mobility and economic development pressures like tourism and road development. </s><s n="s4.9;p2.14">I will mainly target and discuss the symbolic representations that may be attached to human - wildlife conflicts and conclude by addressing the future of human - wildlife conflicts. </s><s n="s5.9;p2.14">There does appear to be a considerably higher number of reports on people- wildlife conflicts within the tropical regions of the world. </s><s n="s6.9;p2.14">However, it is not a phenomenon restricted to the tropics. </s><s n="s7.9;p2.14">Conflicts between humans and wildlife are universal. </s><s n="s8.9;p2.14">Conflicts occurring in the tropics are topical because the developments are recent, in comparison to those countries in the northern hemisphere, where wild predators and livestock were hunted to extinction during the fourteenth and fifteenth centuries. </s><s n="s9.9;p2.14">Therefore, although I do provide several anthropological studies conducted in tropical regions, I have also included examples of studies recorded in Europe. </s></p><p n="p3.14"><s n="s1.4;p3.14">Conflicts arise from competition, this can take the form of 'horizontal'<ref target="BAWE_3001h-ftnote.002"/> competition i.e. between two species that share the same trophic level, or 'vertical'<ref target="BAWE_3001h-ftnote.003"/> predation, which occurs between species at different trophic levels. </s><s n="s2.4;p3.14">When these relations overlap 'garden hunting' occurs, this usually entails wildlife being killed when they come to feed on crops etc and this feeding pattern is used as a kind of hunting bait. </s><s n="s3.4;p3.14">This occurrence is evident within the elitist sport of fox hunting practiced in Britain. </s><s n="s4.4;p3.14">The foxes prey on the 'game birds and domesticated livestock'<ref target="BAWE_3001h-ftnote.004"/> that live on farmer's land and 'the hunt' is given permission to chase and kill the pest. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3001h-ftnote.002"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid., p. 3. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3001h-ftnote.003"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid., p.3. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3001h-ftnote.004"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.3;pn1.1">Marvin.G. </s><s n="s2.3;pn1.1">'The problem of foxes' in Knight, John, (2000): <hi rend="italic">Natural Enemies: People-Wildlife Conflicts in an Anthropological Perspective.</hi> </s><s n="s3.3;pn1.1">Routledge: London &amp; New York. p.189. </s></p></note><p n="p4.14"><s n="s1.4;p4.14">Fox hunting also provides an excellent example of people - wildlife conflicts actually arising from people-people conflicts. </s><s n="s2.4;p4.14">Garry Marvin reports on the 'growing calls for fox hunting to be banned'<ref target="BAWE_3001h-ftnote.005"/> by conservation groups who view it as unnecessary slaughter, in conflict with rural populations who view it as a vital method of pest control. </s><s n="s3.4;p4.14">It seems human-wildlife conflicts are heavily influenced by social determinations, with many disputes occurring from a conflict of opinions between humans towards wildlife. </s><s n="s4.4;p4.14">Conover highlights that: </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3001h-ftnote.005"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid., p.189. </s></p></note><quote lang="English">tolerance of human - wildlife conflicts depends upon what is at risk. That is, people are least tolerant of threats to human health and safety, more tolerant of threats to their personal or community economic well-being and most tolerant of nuisance problems.<ref target="BAWE_3001h-ftnote.006"/></quote><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3001h-ftnote.006"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.3;pn1.1">Conover, Michael. </s><s n="s2.3;pn1.1">(2002): Resolving Human-Wildlife conflicts: The Science of Wildlife Damage Management. </s><s n="s3.3;pn1.1">Lewis Publishers: London &amp; New York.p.358. </s></p></note><p n="p5.14"><s n="s1.2;p5.14">Those who suffer directly from wildlife damage are called 'stakeholders'<ref target="BAWE_3001h-ftnote.007"/> and it is these groups that often influence the government's decisions on wildlife disputes. </s><s n="s2.2;p5.14">Indeed the notion of establishing a ' cultural carrying capacity'<ref target="BAWE_3001h-ftnote.008"/> (i.e. the maximum wildlife population which society will accept within an area) has been suggested but was determined too difficult because it involved a large diversity of opinions. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3001h-ftnote.007"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid., p. 350. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3001h-ftnote.008"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid., p.358. </s></p></note><p n="p6.14"><s n="s1.10;p6.14">Indeed, these differing opinions on wildlife damage give rise to many forms of human - human conflicts. </s><s n="s2.10;p6.14">Firstly, wildlife can cause conflict by enforcing human social divisions, as is present in a rural population living on the outskirts of the Budongo Forest in Uganda. </s><s n="s3.10;p6.14">The population is a conglomeration of different immigrant tribes, each with a different language, however the Bantu are the original inhabitants. </s><s n="s4.10;p6.14">In an attempt to reduce percentage of crop raiding caused by baboons living in the forest, the non-native 'Zairois,' from neighbouring Zaire, are given land closest to the forest. </s><s n="s5.10;p6.14">Their crops get raided first and therefore act as a buffer for the rest of the population. </s><s n="s6.10;p6.14">Secondly, human divisions can occur in conflicts over wildlife. </s><s n="s7.10;p6.14">The wolf may be viewed as a resource for the hunter, but a pest for the farmer or shepherd upon whose livestock the wolf preys. </s><s n="s8.10;p6.14">Thirdly, an element of these conflicts which is often ignored, is the probability that human - wildlife conflicts are used as an outlet to provide a focus point for blame, when human social divisions occur. </s><s n="s9.10;p6.14">For example, logging in the Brazilian rainforest and its subsequent destruction of fragile ecosystems has become the locus for frictions between the Brazilian government and conservationist groups. </s><s n="s10.10;p6.14">However, the issues of the immediate monetary gain from logging and potential presence of unknown medicinal herbs and plants in the forest, are the true issues of dispute. </s></p><p n="p7.14"><s n="s1.15;p7.14">Ironically, conservationism also creates human-wildlife conflicts instead of dissipating them. </s><s n="s2.15;p7.14">Conservationism operates on the assumption that nature should be protected from human resource appropriation. </s><s n="s3.15;p7.14">Therefore, the standard response to human colonisation of animal territories is to remove them and establish a protected area for the wildlife. </s><s n="s4.15;p7.14">However, whilst the competition for land resources is reduced, the threat of poaching and hunting by the populations removed, remains and even increases because these populations do not benefit from the establishment of the protected area, with revenues gained from tourism often going straight back to the government. </s><s n="s5.15;p7.14">This occurred in Uganda when the Virunga Mountains were opened up to tourist groups for gorilla viewing. </s><s n="s6.15;p7.14">The gorillas became habituated to the tourist groups and no longer harbouring a fear for humans they came down the mountain, during the night to raid the crops of the local farmers and often became aggressive and violent when approached. </s><s n="s7.15;p7.14">The local communities did receive a small percentage of the revenue gained from tourists, however the amount was not enough to compensate for the damage caused by the crop raiding. </s><s n="s8.15;p7.14">Similarly, C. Mishra et al conducted a case study in India and Mongolia exploring various incentive programs for conserving the native snow leopard. </s><s n="s9.15;p7.14">They soon discovered that the local populations would 'derive virtually no benefits from wildlife conservation'<ref target="BAWE_3001h-ftnote.009"/> and therefore had to adopt new methods, like the manufacture of handicrafts. </s><s n="s10.15;p7.14">In another study, anthropologist M.N. Tchamba reported on the present status of the human - elephant conflict in the Waza-Logone Region in Cameroon, West Africa. </s><s n="s11.15;p7.14">He highlights that although the convergence between humans and elephants has always existed, the conflict has recently deteriorated further due to the rapid growth of elephant and human populations and the expansion of agricultural land. </s><s n="s12.15;p7.14">These factors have reduced the elephant's habitat and occupied some of their migration routes. </s><s n="s13.15;p7.14">However, legislation requires migratory routes to be built into and out of the National Parks and according to Tchamba's research in 1980 30 elephants came to Waza during the rainy season, this number increased to 50 in 1991 and to 320 elephants in 1992, he concludes it was because the 'Kaele region ha(d) become a wet season refuge for elephants." </s><ref target="BAWE_3001h-ftnote.010"/><s n="s14.15;p7.14">During their migration crop raiding occurred at a time 'when crops were maturing or ready for harvest'<ref target="BAWE_3001h-ftnote.011"/> meaning farmers were unable to plant another batch, causing nearly '27% of [farmers] to lose their entire annual harvest." </s><ref target="BAWE_3001h-ftnote.012"/><s n="s15.15;p7.14">It has been suggested a team of technicians and local informants could be employed to defend the farms located on the vicinity of the Waza National Park to avert the elephants during their migration. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3001h-ftnote.009"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Mishra, C., Allen, P., McCarthy, P Allen, T.,Madhusudan, M.D., Bayarjargal, A., &amp; H.H.T.Prins, (2003): The role of incentive programs in conserving the snow leopard. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">In <hi rend="italic">Conservation Biology,</hi> 17(6): 1512-1520. p. 1514. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3001h-ftnote.010"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.3;pn1.1">Tchamba, M.N., (1996): History and present status of the human/elephant conflict in the Waza-Logone region, Cameroon, West Africa. </s><s n="s2.3;pn1.1">In <hi rend="italic">Biological Conservation,</hi> 75:35-41.p. </s><s n="s3.3;pn1.1">37. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3001h-ftnote.011"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid., p.37. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3001h-ftnote.012"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid., p.38. </s></p></note><p n="p8.14"><s n="s1.9;p8.14">Often human-wildlife conflicts arise from humans invading wildlife habitats. </s><s n="s2.9;p8.14">However, John Knight reports on a new occurrence called 'commensalism,'<ref target="BAWE_3001h-ftnote.013"/> where people-wildlife conflicts have adapted to perform as interfaces, where it seems some wildlife have been able to adapt successfully to humanised environments. </s><s n="s3.9;p8.14">Biologists Merrigi and Lovari have found that the wolf in Southern Europe demonstrates this acclimatisation. </s><s n="s4.9;p8.14">The canid usually feeds on wild herbivore species, however, after analysing their scat and stomach contents, it was discovered that wolves in Southern Europe have adapted to feed mainly on other food resources like, fruit, rubbish and domestic ungulates. </s><s n="s5.9;p8.14">According to the optimal foraging theory, wildlife 'tend to feed in a manner that maximises their nutrient intake in the minimum possible time.' (as cited in Sukumar 1994) </s><s n="s6.9;p8.14">This theory explains the wolves' adaptive behaviour. </s><s n="s7.9;p8.14">It seems livestock is 'left unguarded in the countryside'<ref target="BAWE_3001h-ftnote.014"/> and proves an easy, collected target, whilst rubbish and fruit needed not be chased or hunted and therefore no energy is expended. </s><s n="s8.9;p8.14">Merrigi and Lovari state that shepherds originally tolerated the wolf, however its long absence has made its reacceptance difficult and by preying on domestic ungulates, wolves have acquired the status of pest. </s><s n="s9.9;p8.14">On other hand, it seems this conflict has been culturally institutionalised, through children's stories and games etc where the wolf is portrayed as cunning and evil, which exacerbates the problem. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3001h-ftnote.013"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Knight. op.cit., p. 6. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3001h-ftnote.014"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.3;pn1.1">Meriggi, A., &amp; S. Lovaris, (1996): A review of wolf predation in southern Europe: Does the wolf prefer wild prey to livestock? </s><s n="s2.3;pn1.1">In <hi rend="italic">Journal of Applied Ecology, 33(6): 1561-1571.</hi> </s><s n="s3.3;pn1.1">p.1562. </s></p></note><p n="p9.14"><s n="s1.3;p9.14">The symbolism associated to certain species often creates human-wildlife conflicts. </s><s n="s2.3;p9.14">Mary Douglas's notions of pollution that suggest 'dirt' is just 'matter out of place' (Douglas 1966) can be applied to human - wildlife conflicts, where pests are simply wildlife out of place, they somehow transgress the subscribed boundaries established by humans. </s><s n="s3.3;p9.14">Putman concurs that: </s></p><quote lang="English">much as we may define a weed as a plant in the wrong place, or a pollutant as a perfectly respectable chemical in the wrong place or in inappropriate concentration, so some animal pests too are only pests when in inappropriate numbers or in the wrong context. <ref target="BAWE_3001h-ftnote.015"/></quote><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3001h-ftnote.015"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Knight. op.cit., p.14. </s></p></note><p n="p10.14"><s n="s1.8;p10.14">I earlier referred to the wolves' status as a pest perhaps resulting from its sinister portrayal in children's stories and games. </s><s n="s2.8;p10.14">The same culturally institutionalised epithet is applied to the fox. </s><s n="s3.8;p10.14">In classic tales like Aesop's Fables and Beatrix Potter the fox is portrayed as a 'sly, amoral, wily, cowardly and self seeking creature." </s><ref target="BAWE_3001h-ftnote.016"/><s n="s4.8;p10.14">These negative connotations cannot fail to influence human perception of the creature. </s><s n="s5.8;p10.14">Interestingly, structuralist models of animal symbolism classify the world into groups, but phenomena that resist classification are deemed anomalous. </s><s n="s6.8;p10.14">According to Knight 'foxes have a special anomalous or ambiguous status because they straddle the boundary between field animals and remote wild animals." </s><ref target="BAWE_3001h-ftnote.017"/><s n="s7.8;p10.14">They inhabit a liminal, negative symbolic sphere. </s><s n="s8.8;p10.14">Knight suggests another possibility that 'underlying many people-wildlife conflicts are ideas of balance and reciprocity, with respect to which the behaviour of this or that animal may be deemed to be problematical.' <ref target="BAWE_3001h-ftnote.018"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3001h-ftnote.016"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Marvin.op.cit., p.190. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3001h-ftnote.017"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Knight.op.cit., p.15. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3001h-ftnote.018"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid., p.16. </s></p></note><p n="p11.14"><s n="s1.1;p11.14">In this respect, foxes apparent tendencies for feeding frenzies in hencoops, upset this balance and incur the anger of the farmer and establish a conflict. </s></p><p n="p12.14"><s n="s1.2;p12.14">In conclusion, anthropology as a discipline has huge potential for helping to resolve human - wildlife conflict issues. </s><s n="s2.2;p12.14">Knight reports that 'anthropology provides a cultural contextualization of wildlife that could help achieve a more locally sensitive wildlife management policy'<ref target="BAWE_3001h-ftnote.019"/> and he suggests the implementation of a: </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3001h-ftnote.019"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid.,p.5. </s></p></note><quote lang="English">wildlife damage manager [as] a professional 'buffer' between wildlife and humans, protecting humans form animals, while at the same time protecting wildlife from humans. The wildlife damage management professional needs to be able to understand humans as well as he or she understands wildlife.<ref target="BAWE_3001h-ftnote.020"/></quote><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3001h-ftnote.020"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid., p.5. </s></p></note><p n="p13.14"><s n="s1.1;p13.14">Indeed whilst there is no panacea for the conflict issues, I concur that it is vital to consider the human element of the conflict issues, as discussed in C.M. Hill's article </s></p><p n="p14.14"><s n="s1.4;p14.14">' people should not suffer impoverishment from wildlife preservation." </s><ref target="BAWE_3001h-ftnote.021"/><s n="s2.4;p14.14">The solution is to adopt community-based management schemes that involve the local population in conservation projects. </s><s n="s3.4;p14.14">Finally, it becomes clear that the term 'people' of the people- wildlife conflicts is not a static term, but rather one that carries many connotations. </s><s n="s4.4;p14.14">As I highlighted earlier, it appears that human-wildlife conflicts are a consequence of wider, far ranging conflicts between human populations whether local, national or international and certainly not restricted to the tropics. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3001h-ftnote.021"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Hill, C.M., (2002): Primate Conservation and Local Communities- Ethical Issues and Debates. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">In <hi rend="italic">American Anthropologist,</hi> 104 (4): 1184-1194. p. 1184. </s></p></note></div1></body><back><div1 type="bibliography"><head rend="underlined bold">Bibliography:</head><p>Conover, Michael. (2002): <hi rend="italic">Resolving Human-Wildlife conflicts: The Science of Wildlife Damage Management.</hi> Lewis Publishers: London &amp; New York.</p><p>Gibson, C.C. &amp; S.A Marks (1995): Transforming rural hunters into conservationists: an assessment of community-based wildlife management programs in Africa. In <hi rend="italic">World Development,</hi> 23 (6):941-951.</p><p>Gould &amp; Kolb, (1964): 'conflict' and 'competition.' In <hi rend="italic">A Dictionary of the Social Sciences</hi>. Tavistock Publications: London.</p><p>Hill, C.M., (2002): Primate Conservation and Local Communities- Ethical Issues and Debates. In <hi rend="italic">American Anthropologist,</hi> 104 (4): 1184-1194.</p><p>Knight, John, (2000): <hi rend="italic">Natural Enemies: People-Wildlife Conflicts in an Anthropological Perspective.</hi> Routledge: London &amp; New York.</p><p>Meriggi, A., &amp; S. Lovaris, (1996): A review of wolf predation in southern Europe: Does the wolf prefer wild prey to livestock? In <hi rend="italic">Journal of Applied Ecology, 33(6): 1561-1571.</hi></p><p>Mishra, C., Allen, P., McCarthy, P Allen, T.,Madhusudan, M.D., Bayarjargal, A., &amp; H.H.T.Prins, (2003): The role of incentive programs in conserving the snow leopard. In <hi rend="italic">Conservation Biology,</hi> 17(6): 1512-1520.</p><p>Sills, David.L, (1968): Conflict. In <hi rend="italic">International Encyclopaedia of the Social Sciences Vol 3.</hi> The Macmillian Company &amp; The Free Press: London.</p><p>Tchamba, M.N., (1996): History and present status of the human/elephant conflict in the Waza-Logone region, Cameroon, West Africa. In <hi rend="italic">Biological Conservation,</hi> 75:35-41.</p></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
