<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_3003b" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Using any critical/theoretical ideas that you have encountered so far on this module explore the continuities or discontinuities between any two texts you have read on your degree</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">Language used in quote: <foreign id="English">English</foreign></note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">
Student name and student number in doc header. Word count at the end of running text (before bibliography).
</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">3</p><p n="date">2005-05</p><p n="module title">Contemporary Lit.</p><p n="module code">U67083</p><p n="genre family">Essay</p><p n="discipline">English</p><p n="disciplinary group">AH</p><p n="grade">M</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">3034</p><p n="number of s-units">119</p><p n="number of p">16</p><p n="number of tables">0</p><p n="number of figures">0</p><p n="number of block quotes">2</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">0</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">0</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">25.5</p><p n="average s-units per p">7.4</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">m</p><p n="year of birth">1983</p><p n="first language">English</p><p n="education">UKa</p><p n="course">BA English Studies</p><p n="student ID">3003</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><docTitle><titlePart rend="underlined">Using any critical/theoretical ideas that you have encountered so far on this module explore the continuities or discontinuities between any two texts you have read on your degree</titlePart></docTitle></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="section"><p n="p1.16"><s n="s1.11;p1.16">Michel Foucault's<ref target="BAWE_3003b-ftnote.001"/> essay 'What is an Author?' has had a massive impact upon how people view the idea of authorship and authority. </s><s n="s2.11;p1.16">Foucault claimed that the traditional view of the author was simply a modern construction seeking to exalt the author to an omniscient position. </s><s n="s3.11;p1.16">However, he felt that in reality the author has no authority over their text, as the reader cannot know the author and therefore cannot interpret the author's intentions. </s><s n="s4.11;p1.16">Moreover, he felt it was unnecessary to know the author's intention; what was more important was for the reader to be able to bring their own meaning and interpretation from the text for their own use. </s><s n="s5.11;p1.16">Other Postmodern thinkers have taken this idea further, treating the world as a text and the individuals habiting the world as the readers. </s><s n="s6.11;p1.16">The individual has no clear authority or standards by which to interpret the world and is consequently left to discover 'truth' for themselves, and to live in a way which best serves themselves and their needs. </s><s n="s7.11;p1.16">Sigmund Freud<ref target="BAWE_3003b-ftnote.002"/> thought that in view of death, the central motivation for the individual in life was the feeling of desire and pleasure. </s><s n="s8.11;p1.16">In addition, Jacques Lacan<ref target="BAWE_3003b-ftnote.003"/> said that at the core of human identity is a sense of lack, knowledge that we will never be fulfilled, therefore desire is not the product of the search but the point of it; the individual desires desire. </s><s n="s9.11;p1.16">The Modern subject, in light of the death of God and religion, searched for reason and truth, believing they could be found in science, philosophy and in the benevolence of mankind. </s><s n="s10.11;p1.16">The Postmodern individual, unconvinced by the reality of altruistic humanism, became fluid, hybrid and fragmented. </s><s n="s11.11;p1.16">At the heart of Postmodern subjectivity is the need to define oneself against the 'other'; the need to find self fulfilment and realisation. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3003b-ftnote.001"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">French philosopher (1926-84) </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3003b-ftnote.002"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Born in Moravia (now Czech Republic) to Jewish parents, founder of psychoanalysis (1856-1939) </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3003b-ftnote.003"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">psychoanalyst and intellectual , born in Paris, France (1901-81) </s></p></note><p n="p2.16"><s n="s1.7;p2.16">Modern and Postmodern thought derives from the idea that religion is dead, and in view of human death being the end of life (if religion is dead, so is the afterlife) come the philosophies for the present age. </s><s n="s2.7;p2.16">It is interesting that much of this thought is also taught in the Bible, the book which Postmodern thinkers see as ancient and transient. </s><s n="s3.7;p2.16">The writer of Ecclesiastes<ref target="BAWE_3003b-ftnote.004"/> claims that life under the sun (without God) is in fact meaningless<ref target="BAWE_3003b-ftnote.005"/> and impossible to understand. </s><s n="s4.7;p2.16">The pursuit of pleasure brings no satisfaction<ref target="BAWE_3003b-ftnote.006"/>, we do not know what will happen when we die<ref target="BAWE_3003b-ftnote.007"/> and yet we feel and desire to live.<ref target="BAWE_3003b-ftnote.008"/> The apostle Paul writes to the church in Corinth that if death is the end and there is no resurrection then <hi rend="italic"> "Let us eat and drink for tomorrow we die"</hi><ref target="BAWE_3003b-ftnote.009"/>. </s><s n="s5.7;p2.16">Although both the Biblical writers are arguing that in fact death is not the end, they can see that if it is, then they are in agreement with Freud, Lacan and Foucault that all that is left is instant gratification, desire and self-fulfilment. </s><s n="s6.7;p2.16">The subject must find their identity in a fragmented world. </s><s n="s7.7;p2.16">The exploration of identity through storytelling and the effects of truth upon identity are the themes of continuity that I will look at in Joseph Conrad's<ref target="BAWE_3003b-ftnote.010"/> modern novella <hi rend="underlined">Heart of Darkness</hi> (1899) and Alan Warner's<ref target="BAWE_3003b-ftnote.011"/> contemporary novel <hi rend="underlined">Morvern Callar</hi> (1996). </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3003b-ftnote.004"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">the 'Teacher' could refer to King Solomon, or the writings are at least royal teachings in Solomonic tradition, written no later then 5th century BC, see p.609 in <hi rend="underlined">New Bible Commentary</hi> (IVP, 2004) </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3003b-ftnote.005"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">see Ecclesiastes 1:14 from the <hi rend="underlined">Holy Bible</hi> (NIV, 1973) </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3003b-ftnote.006"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">see Ecclesiastes 2:10-11 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3003b-ftnote.007"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">see Ecclesiastes 3:19b-21 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3003b-ftnote.008"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">see Ecclesiastes 3:11 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3003b-ftnote.009"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">see 1 Corinthians 15:32 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3003b-ftnote.010"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Polish sailor and novelist. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">(1857-1924) </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3003b-ftnote.011"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Warner was born in Argyll in 1964 </s></p></note><p n="p3.16"><s n="s1.11;p3.16"><hi rend="underlined">Heart of Darkness</hi> is Conrad's novella about the journey of a western seaman, Marlow, and his search into Africa for the explorer Kurtz. </s><s n="s2.11;p3.16">Marlow's physical journey is reflective of his psychological journey for truth and meaning that he hopes Kurtz might bring him. </s><s n="s3.11;p3.16">The novella is written from the narrator who is listening to Marlow telling his story to a group of men. </s><s n="s4.11;p3.16">Marlow is portrayed as a thoughtful, insightful, meditative idol (p.16). </s><s n="s5.11;p3.16">He is compared to a Buddhist preacher (p.20), one who is enlightened and has a voice, able to explain the world to his followers. </s><s n="s6.11;p3.16">However, the narrator fears he will only be expounding one of his <hi rend="italic">"inconclusive experiences"</hi> (p.21) which would be the result of attempting to understand an <hi rend="italic">"incomprehensible world"</hi> (p.20). </s><s n="s7.11;p3.16">The white man was viewed as a god-like figure,<ref target="BAWE_3003b-ftnote.012"/> a civilized being. </s><s n="s8.11;p3.16">Yet when Marlow arrives in Belgium, the western city reminds him of a sepulchre (or tomb)<ref target="BAWE_3003b-ftnote.013"/>, an image that suggests an outward adornment of beauty and civility, but an inward shallowness and depravity. </s><s n="s9.11;p3.16">Marlow himself is losing confidence in his own understanding and interpretations as he tells how the injustice of exploitative colonialism that he encountered would slowly have an effect on his view of humanity. </s><s rend="italic" n="s10.11;p3.16">"For a time I would feel that I belonged still to a world of straightforward facts; but the feeling would not last long." </s><s n="s11.11;p3.16">(p.30) </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3003b-ftnote.012"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">as Kurtz is in Africa </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3003b-ftnote.013"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">a reference to Matthew 23:27-8 </s></p></note><p n="p4.16"><s n="s1.4;p4.16">He has given up hope of finding any meaning in the west, cautious of the noble idea of the civilizing mission and sceptical of his aunt's view of him as an apostolic <hi rend="italic">"emissary of light"</hi> (p.28). </s><s n="s2.4;p4.16">Conrad describes Marlow's journey as one into hell, as the women in the waiting room to see the doctor guard <hi rend="italic">"the door of darkness"</hi> (p.26). </s><s n="s3.4;p4.16">He is aware of the dangers of the psychological impact of his journey, he feels he is becoming <hi rend="italic">"scientifically interesting"</hi> (p.40) and he had been warned before by the doctor that <hi rend="italic">"the changes take place inside"</hi> (p.27). </s><s n="s4.4;p4.16">Marlow struggles to narrate his story, despairing at his <hi rend="italic">"impossible"</hi> (p.50) task, unable to become more than a silent voice in the pitch dark. </s></p><p n="p5.16"><s n="s1.5;p5.16">Marlow realises his need to find understanding and although he recognises his own limitations of expression, he believes that he can find this wisdom in Kurtz. </s><s n="s2.5;p5.16">Kurtz is portrayed as an enigmatic god-like figure, the man who has become an idol for the local peoples and an inspiration for all those who hear of him. </s><s n="s3.5;p5.16">Marlow's greatest fear is that he will <hi rend="italic">"Never hear him"</hi> (p.79). </s><s n="s4.5;p5.16">He has not been thinking about meeting or seeing him, but hearing him. </s><s n="s5.5;p5.16">For Kurtz has, </s></p><quote lang="English"><hi rend="italic">"The gift of expression, the bewildering, the illuminating, the most exalted and the most contemptible, the pulsating stream of light, or the deceitful flow from the heart of an impenetrable darkness."</hi> (p.79)</quote><p n="p6.16"><s n="s1.3;p6.16">The image of Kurtz here is of a deity; he has a voice, which the Bible describes is the method (the voice of God) by which God effects his power in creation,<ref target="BAWE_3003b-ftnote.014"/> revelation<ref target="BAWE_3003b-ftnote.015"/> and bringing life<ref target="BAWE_3003b-ftnote.016"/>. </s><s n="s2.3;p6.16">Kurtz is being specifically compared here to Jesus; he has a voice that Marlow believes is able to enlighten the darkness of the world. </s><s n="s3.3;p6.16">As Marlow does not have the expression that brings understanding, it becomes his destiny, or pilgrimage, to hear Kurtz. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3003b-ftnote.014"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">see Psalm 33:6 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3003b-ftnote.015"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Jesus the word incarnate, bringing light into darkness, see John 1:1-5, 14, 8:12, 12:46 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3003b-ftnote.016"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">see 1 John 1:1 </s></p></note><p n="p7.16"><s n="s1.10;p7.16">The Russian, who Marlow meets before he encounters Kurtz, tells him that <hi rend="italic">"You don't talk with that man - you listen to him"</hi> (p.88). </s><s n="s2.10;p7.16">Although he claims that Kurtz has indeed <hi rend="italic">"enlarged my mind"</hi> (p.90) there is a hint that the result of hearing him has indeed left him still without hope or understanding. </s><s n="s3.10;p7.16"><hi rend="italic">'He waved his arm, and in the twinkling of an eye was in the uttermost depths of despondency'</hi> (p.88). </s><s n="s4.10;p7.16">This phrase is a biblical reference to the final triumph of the resurrection,<ref target="BAWE_3003b-ftnote.017"/> the moment when all hope and joy in life is fulfilled but Conrad associates it with an epiphany of despair, a fall to utter hopelessness. </s><s n="s5.10;p7.16">Marlow continues to have faith in his meeting with Kurtz, but as his journey evolves and he finds out more about his methods he becomes increasingly distressed and antipathetic towards him. </s><s n="s6.10;p7.16">The anti-climax that the Russian's despondency predicts comes true in Kurtz's final revelation before he dies. </s><s n="s7.10;p7.16">As he lies in the despair of darkness, he experiences a <hi rend="italic">"supreme moment of complete knowledge"</hi> (p.112), his last words, the hope that Marlow has, are <hi rend="italic">"The Horror!</hi> </s><s rend="italic" n="s8.10;p7.16">The Horror!" </s><s n="s9.10;p7.16">(p.112) The god-figure is dead, the voice is gone and his revelation is ambiguous and at best a bleak summary of the world that he has left behind. </s><s n="s10.10;p7.16">The discovery that their shared fate is simply oblivion is the <hi rend="italic">"appalling face of glimpsed truth"</hi> (p.113) that Marlow discovers which maligns his belief in humanity and mankind. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3003b-ftnote.017"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">see 1 Corinthians 15:52 </s></p></note><p n="p8.16"><s n="s1.9;p8.16">The loss of the voice, the narrator and the author at the end of <hi rend="underlined">Heart of Darkness</hi> destabilises the framework of Marlow's mind and his outlook on society. </s><s n="s2.9;p8.16">When he returns to Europe he views people's lives as meaningless, filled with <hi rend="italic">"insignificant and silly dreams"</hi> (p.114). </s><s n="s3.9;p8.16">Foucault predicts this effect when he sees the death of the author. </s><s n="s4.9;p8.16">The loss of the central and authoritative figure creates disharmony and instability leaving the reader with no answers and no centre. </s><s n="s5.9;p8.16">The centre or the 'heart' is no longer knowable, but in fact filled with darkness. </s><s n="s6.9;p8.16">When there is no longer the god-like figure, the self becomes fragmented and unsure of anything, death is the only common fate and life must be understood subjectively. </s><s n="s7.9;p8.16">At the end of the novella we see that in effect, Marlow has been searching for something that was not actually there. </s><s n="s8.9;p8.16">Lacan's theory is relevant here because although the point of his search is intangible, he would say that he has been searching for desire. </s><s n="s9.9;p8.16">He is fulfilled in the sense that although from the beginning an answer was never there, in his journey he has desired it, and filled his sense of lack. </s></p><p n="p9.16"><s n="s1.11;p9.16">Alan Warner's existential novel <hi rend="underlined"> Morvern Callar</hi> begins when the main protagonist Morvern finds her boyfriend having committed suicide and examines the issues of the morality of her reaction in a seemingly valueless and hedonistic society. </s><s n="s2.11;p9.16">The novel begins where <hi rend="underlined">Heart of Darkness</hi> finishes; with the death of the author, the creator and God. </s><s n="s3.11;p9.16">Morvern's boyfriend remains nameless but is referred to with the divine capital <hi rend="italic">"Him"</hi> (p.7). </s><s n="s4.11;p9.16">He is the author who has written a novel which he leaves with Morvern and he is the creator of the model village of their town which is in the loft of their apartment, where his divine body lies.<ref target="BAWE_3003b-ftnote.018"/> The reader never hears his voice; his life and death are left in Morvern's hands, and he becomes her story. </s><s n="s5.11;p9.16">Morvern is an orphan, unaware of her biological parents and born into a vacuum, with no grounding, stability or history. </s><s n="s6.11;p9.16">She keeps her boyfriend's death a secret and then claims authorship of his work. </s><s n="s7.11;p9.16">Throughout the novel, there is a clear emphasis on the narrative voice; in the Mantrap, Lanna and Tequila Shiela recall their ex-boyfriend stories, at the Kale Onion Hotel the main event is Panatine's 'finger' story and Couris Jean is keen to reminisce with Morvern about her arrival at the port. </s><s n="s8.11;p9.16">All the characters exist and find their identity in storytelling, a discourse which gives them order, meaning and coherence in the midst of an unstable confused world.<ref target="BAWE_3003b-ftnote.019"/> The god-like figure is dead and consequently people have a sense of lack and desire for it to be filled. </s><s n="s9.11;p9.16">The story with its notion of order replaces God and the peace and stability found in the godhead. </s><s n="s10.11;p9.16">The narrative voice is what the characters strive for, which is why Morvern is so keen to hear what Couris Jean had said before she died, and why it is so tragic that she dies speaking an incomprehensible language. </s><s n="s11.11;p9.16">Towards the end of the novel as Morvern becomes increasingly isolated, the storytelling diminishes and all Morvern can hear is the <hi rend="italic">"silentness"</hi> (p.221). </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3003b-ftnote.018"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">a comparison with Jesus, see Luke 23:55 (although His body lies preparatory to dismemberment, like the identities of the individual in wake of his death, whereas Jesus' body lies preparatory to resurrection, with the consequence of meaning and order ) </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3003b-ftnote.019"><p n="pn1.4"><s n="s1.1;pn1.4">this idea is expounded by Jacques Derrida (1930-2004) the French philosopher-linguist. </s></p><p n="pn2.4"><s n="s1.6;pn2.4">Wim Wenders commenting on his film <hi rend="underlined">Wings of Desire</hi> (1987) "People's primary requirement is that some kind of coherence be provided. </s><s n="s2.6;pn2.4">Stories give people the feeling that there is meaning, that there is ultimately an order lurking behind the incredible confusion of appearances and phenomena that surrounds them. </s><s n="s3.6;pn2.4">This order is what people require more than anything else; yes, I would almost say that the notion of order or story is connected with the godhead. </s><s n="s4.6;pn2.4">Stories are substitutes for God. </s><s n="s5.6;pn2.4">Or maybe the other way around. </s><s n="s6.6;pn2.4">(The remarks are from a talk Wenders gave at a "colloquium on narrative technique" in </s></p><p n="pn3.4"><s n="s1.1;pn3.4">1982, published as "Impossible Stories," in Wenders' <hi rend="italic">The Logic of Images: Essays and Conversations</hi>, Frankfurt: Verlag der Autoren, 1988 (English translation by Michael Hoffman, London: Faber and Faber Limited, 1991, pp53-4).) </s></p><p n="pn4.4"><s n="s1.1;pn4.4"><seg type="URL" n="http://www.nathanwolfson.com/scholarship/wings/Wings-PoMo-Wolfson.pdf"/> </s></p></note><p n="p10.16"><s n="s1.10;p10.16">Foucault argues that because the author is dead then the individual must interpret the world subjectively. </s><s n="s2.10;p10.16">The individual becomes inward and self-interested. </s><s n="s3.10;p10.16">This is demonstrated clearly through the narrative by Morvern's meticulous description and fascination of her physicality. </s><s n="s4.10;p10.16">The sensuous narrative continually describes Morvern washing, doing her nails, going to the toilet, applying her lipstick and shaving her legs. </s><s n="s5.10;p10.16">Her inward-looking fascination with herself and her body reaches the extent that she feels separate from it; when she has sex she says <hi rend="italic">"I let them do anything to me and tried to make each as satisfied as I could"</hi> (p.26). </s><s n="s6.10;p10.16">The emphasis here during such a physically binding passionate act, is the disconnection of her body from her mind and the base instinct of self and not mutual gratification. </s><s n="s7.10;p10.16">Morvern's world is the youth culture of sex, drugs and alcohol. </s><s n="s8.10;p10.16">Her music is central to her identity; guiding<ref target="BAWE_3003b-ftnote.020"/> and encapsulating her. </s><s n="s9.10;p10.16">The <hi rend="italic">'Utopian Experience'</hi> (p.73) of the club scene is another escape from reality, a <hi rend="italic">"huge journey in that darkness"</hi> (p.203) where the music takes over and <hi rend="italic">"You didn't really have your body as your own"</hi> (p.203). </s><s n="s10.10;p10.16">She searches for experience by using up her boyfriend's money <ref target="BAWE_3003b-ftnote.021"/> and enjoys all the pleasures of the hot island sunbathing, drinking and clubbing youth-culture, not even wishing to sleep in order that she can <hi rend="italic">"know every minute of that happiness"</hi> (p.210). </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3003b-ftnote.020"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">see p.5 for the reason that she does not tell the police about her boyfriend's death </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3003b-ftnote.021"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">the story is not so dissimilar from the parable of the lost son, see Luke 15:11-31, albeit with a different conclusion </s></p></note><p n="p11.16"><s n="s1.9;p11.16">The fragmented, blurred and illusory identities of the characters in the novel are signified by the use of nicknames. </s><s n="s2.9;p11.16">The individuals create and re-create their subjective identity through a process of deferral from reality. </s><s n="s3.9;p11.16">The alienated self must find definition through different 'others'. </s><s n="s4.9;p11.16">Another example is the individual as consumer; Morvern is closely connected with her favourite drink Southern Comfort, her Silk Cut brand of cigarettes and her gold lighter. </s><s n="s5.9;p11.16">Her constant cycle of re-identification is portrayed by her evolution from Silk Cut onto Regals, then Sobranie and then by the end she has given up smoking. </s><s n="s6.9;p11.16">The most explicit image of the fragmented self is Morvern's boyfriend's body being cut up and spread all across the land. </s><s n="s7.9;p11.16">The cycle of the characters' lives revolve around their meaningless jobs and their nights out, with set venues and structures to their entertainment. </s><s n="s8.9;p11.16">The definition that Trevor gives to describe his group of friends is simply <hi rend="italic">"We drink"</hi> (p.128). </s><s n="s9.9;p11.16">Red Hannah laments the <hi rend="italic">"the world we've made"</hi> suggesting that despite the seemingly endless opportunities of self-fulfilment <hi rend="italic">"There is no freedom, no liberty; there's just money"</hi> as he bemoans his <hi rend="italic">"wasted life"</hi> (p.45). </s></p><p n="p12.16"><s n="s1.4;p12.16">I would like to suggest that Morvern Callar demonstrates the implications of Foucault's theory and the world that is created in the wake of it. </s><s n="s2.4;p12.16">When there is no author or God, there is no objectivity, moral standards, and truth. </s><s n="s3.4;p12.16">One of Morvern's most questionable actions is when, after keeping her boyfriend's suicide a secret, she cuts up his body and distributes it over the countryside. </s><s n="s4.4;p12.16">The narrative during her exercise portrays her as a naïve, innocent and playful youth. </s></p><quote lang="English"><hi rend="italic">"To the happy sound of Salif Keita doing Nyanafin I rounded the great bank of Beinn Mheadhonach, pushing down on my tanned legs. The sun was hot on my hair as His chopped-off head bumped away against my back."</hi> (p.88)</quote><p n="p13.16"><s n="s1.4;p13.16">The narrator gives no moral judgement; she is a child performing what many might see to be a transgressive act, but as though she were playing a game or carrying out a banal task. </s><s n="s2.4;p13.16">Without responsibility to an objective moral standard the individual is left to judge moral actions on conscience alone and the more standards are suppressed the fewer there are and the less immanent one's conscience is. </s><s n="s3.4;p13.16">In a society where there are no rules, her actions are justifiable. </s><s n="s4.4;p13.16">Even her claimed ownership of the novel is an attempt to find an identity, an attempt of self fulfilment which the Postmodern thinker presumably must applaud. </s></p><p n="p14.16"><s n="s1.8;p14.16">Warner's lack of moral criticism opens up the question of whether or not Morvern has any choice in the way she acts. </s><s n="s2.8;p14.16">What happens to morality and ethics when there is no centre? </s><s n="s3.8;p14.16">How does one identify oneself when there is no one to be accountable to? </s><s n="s4.8;p14.16">It could be argued that the society created, and therefore Morvern, is simply amoral, rendering her innocent, blameless and unaware of any harmful consequences of her actions. </s><s n="s5.8;p14.16">However, I would argue that our individual consciences would point us to the distinction between right and wrong.<ref target="BAWE_3003b-ftnote.022"/> If someone were to sadistically rape, beat and cut up a young child, then it would take great courage (or lack of courage) for an individual to claim no objective wrongdoing. </s><s n="s6.8;p14.16">Our objective ability to see a clear wrong action indicates an objective moral standard that is not controlled by the individual or the state.<ref target="BAWE_3003b-ftnote.023"/> I grant that perception and recognition of wrong actions may become increasingly unknowable, as in Morvern's case, but I think that is a self inflicted state to begin with, as one persistently disregards one's conscience. </s><s n="s7.8;p14.16">Morvern may well be a product of her society, but that does not render her or her society innocent. </s><s n="s8.8;p14.16">It is no great intellectual or practical attribute of any individual or society to confuse morality with immorality, or to confuse right with wrong. <ref target="BAWE_3003b-ftnote.024"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3003b-ftnote.022"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">see Romans 2:15 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3003b-ftnote.023"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">ultimately the state cannot control morality as it is constantly in a process of modification, re-interpretation and disintegration with no firm foundation </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3003b-ftnote.024"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">see Isaiah 5:20 </s></p></note><p n="p15.16"><s n="s1.9;p15.16">Foucault is correct that one cannot know dogmatically the intentions, the circumstances and the thoughts of an author. </s><s n="s2.9;p15.16">However, there is a difference between exhaustive and correct knowledge. </s><s n="s3.9;p15.16">The reader's inaptitude to know the whole context does not mean they cannot know some of it. </s><s n="s4.9;p15.16">Enough evidence can lead to a correct conclusion, without having perfect proof. </s><s n="s5.9;p15.16">As human beings, we may not share all circumstances together, but it is not a fair conclusion to say that we have nothing in common, as we are equally human. </s><s n="s6.9;p15.16">Foucault makes an illogical assumption that because meaning and interpretation will be open to some question, it is impossible to communicate any meaning faithfully. </s><s n="s7.9;p15.16">In effect, if Foucault's theory were true, then we would not be able to read his own essay and understand it so coherently. </s><s n="s8.9;p15.16">Foucault leaves the individual as a helpless, alienated and incommunicative being. </s><s n="s9.9;p15.16">However, one does not need to look too far to see communication everywhere, whether by translation, signs or systems; not perfectly, but successfully.<ref target="BAWE_3003b-ftnote.025"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3003b-ftnote.025"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">some of the ideas in this paragraph have been taken from Marcus Honeysett's <hi rend="underlined">Meltdown</hi> (IVP, 2002) esp. pp.21-34 </s></p></note><p n="p16.16"><s n="s1.4;p16.16">In conclusion, I have argued that <hi rend="underlined">Heart of Darkness</hi> represents the modern journey to Foucault's argument that the objective authorial figure is dead, and <hi rend="underlined">Morvern Callar</hi> illustrates the outworking of the theory. </s><s n="s2.4;p16.16">The Modern subject fails in their search to find order and stability in the world and is left darkly disillusioned and empty. </s><s n="s3.4;p16.16">The Postmodern subject seeks to fulfil the 'self' in a desperate conquest to find meaning and identity, a search that has become helplessly subjective. </s><s n="s4.4;p16.16">The individual, if Foucault is right, is left to act alone in a bleak world that has become incommunicative, de-stabilised and seemingly meaningless, despite their inner need for communication, order and morality. </s></p></div1></body><back><div1 type="bibliography"><head rend="bold">Bibliography</head><p>Barry, P <hi rend="underlined">Beginning Theory</hi> (Manchester and New York: Manchester University Press, 2002)</p><p>Carson, D.A, France, R.T, Motyer, J.A, Wenham, G.J (eds.) <hi rend="underlined">New Bible Commentary</hi> (Leicester: Inter Varsity Press, 2004)</p><p>Conrad, J <hi rend="underlined">Heart of Darkness</hi> (London: Penguin Classics, 2000)</p><p>Dale, S <hi rend="underlined">Alan Warner's "Morvern Callar": Continuum Contemporaries</hi> (London; New York: Continuum International Publishing Group, 2002)</p><p>Harari, J.V <hi rend="underlined">Textual strategies: perspectives in post-structuralist criticism</hi> (New York: Cornel University Press, 1979)</p><p>Hodder &amp; Stoughton <hi rend="underlined">Holy Bible, New International Version</hi> (London: International Bible Society, 1973)</p><p>Honeysett, M <hi rend="underlined">Meltdown</hi> (Leicester: Inter Varsity Press, 2002)</p><p>Levenson, M (ed) <hi rend="underlined">The Cambridge Companion to Modernism</hi> (Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 1999)</p><p>Rivkin, J and Ryan, M (eds.) <hi rend="underlined">Literary theory: an anthology</hi> (Oxford; Malden, Mass: Blackwell, 1998)</p><p>Stape, J.H <hi rend="underlined">The Cambridge Companion to Joseph Conrad</hi> (Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 1996)</p><p>Warner, A <hi rend="underlined">Morvern Callar</hi> (London: Vintage, 1996)</p><p><seg type="URL" n="http://www.nathanwolfson.com/scholarship/wings/Wings-PoMo-Wolfson.pdf"/></p></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
