<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_3004a" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Contrastive analysis of two short texts</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">The document has a title page which contains:
document title
title part</note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">
Word count at end of running text (before bibliography).
</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">3</p><p n="date">2005-03</p><p n="module title">Language through Literature</p><p n="module code">U70025</p><p n="genre family">Exercise</p><p n="discipline">English</p><p n="disciplinary group">AH</p><p n="grade">M</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">1228</p><p n="number of s-units">44</p><p n="number of p">9</p><p n="number of tables">0</p><p n="number of figures">0</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">0</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">0</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">27.9</p><p n="average s-units per p">4.9</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">f</p><p n="year of birth">1982</p><p n="first language">German</p><p n="education">OSa</p><p n="course">BA English Studies</p><p n="student ID">3004</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><titlePart rend="bold"> Assignment1</titlePart><docTitle><titlePart><hi rend="bold"> Contrastive analysis of two short texts</hi> Gerard Manley Hopkins : from <hi rend="italic">Binsey Poplars</hi> T. S. Eliot : from <hi rend="italic">The Love Songs of Alfred J. Prufrock</hi></titlePart></docTitle><titlePart>Name: <name type="student name"/> Student number: <name type="student ID"/> Module number: U70025 Module title: Language through Literature Module leaders: <hi rend="underlined"><name type="tutor name"/></hi>, <name type="tutor name"/> Date submitted: 4 <hi rend="sup">th</hi> March 2005 </titlePart><docTitle><titlePart rend="bold">Contrastive analysis of two short texts - poem extracts from <hi rend="italic">Binsey Poplars</hi> by Gerard Manley Hopkins and from <hi rend="italic">The Love Songs of Alfred J. Prufrock</hi> by T. S. Eliot </titlePart></docTitle></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="section"><p n="p1.9"><s n="s1.6;p1.9">The extracts from the poems <hi rend="italic">Binsey Poplars</hi> by Gerard Manley Hopkins, and <hi rend="italic">The Love Song of Alfred J. Prufrock</hi> by T. S. </s><s n="s2.6;p1.9">Eliot share a common theme which is that of cities. </s><s n="s3.6;p1.9">In the case of the poem <hi rend="italic">Binsey Poplars</hi>, the city of Oxford. </s><s n="s4.6;p1.9">Whilst Hopkins 'laments the felling of poplars in the village of Binsey outside Oxford' (Spiro, handout), T. S. </s><s n="s5.6;p1.9">Eliot visualises a situation in an unknown city where fog dashes around the houses like a cat. </s><s n="s6.6;p1.9">In addition to the common elements of a rather negative description of a city and its happenings, both extracts from the much longer poems have some stylistic features in common, but at the same time are different in some instances of their use of sounds, words, figurative language, sentence structure and shapes and patterns. </s></p><p n="p2.9"><s n="s1.2;p2.9">The extract from <hi rend="italic">Binsey Poplars</hi> consists of one stanza, written in the indicative and simple past as well as present perfect, which is comprised of eight lines following an irregular rhyme scheme - a b a c d a c c - with several internal rhymes between the words <hi rend="italic">quelled</hi> and <hi rend="italic">felled</hi>, <hi rend="italic">dandled</hi> and <hi rend="italic">sandaled</hi>, and the half rhyme between <hi rend="italic">shadow</hi> and <hi rend="italic">meadow</hi>. </s><s n="s2.2;p2.9">Furthermore, the poem consists of iambic and trochaic feet, but there is no clear stress pattern which structures the whole poem. </s></p><p n="p3.9"><s n="s1.2;p3.9">The alliteration of the initial sounds such as [kw] in <hi rend="italic">quelled</hi> and <hi rend="italic">quenched</hi>, the lateral [l] in <hi rend="italic">leaves</hi> and <hi rend="italic">leaping</hi>, the fricatives [f] in <hi rend="italic">felled</hi>, <hi rend="italic">following</hi> and <hi rend="italic">folded</hi> and [s] in <hi rend="italic">sandalled</hi>, <hi rend="italic">swam</hi> and <hi rend="italic">sank</hi> and the approximant [w] in <hi rend="italic">wind-wandering weed-winding</hi> as well as the assonance in <hi rend="italic">leaves</hi> and <hi rend="italic">leaping</hi> and in <hi rend="italic">followed</hi> and <hi rend="italic">folded</hi> show that the poem is characterised by its outstanding use of alliteration and assonance. </s><s n="s2.2;p3.9">The choice of these sounds has an effect on the poem, since the fricatives are linked with 'friction, hissing [and] scratching' (Carter, 2001, p54), which supports the ire of the poet as he sees the felled trees as well as the approximant [w] which can be regarded as a 'continuous [flowing] sound' (Carter, 2001, p54), representing the wind and the water mentioned at the end of the poem. </s></p><p n="p4.9"><s n="s1.10;p4.9">Hopkins's choice of words is based upon frequent alliteration and also upon his repetition of words such as <hi rend="italic">quelled</hi>, <hi rend="italic">felled</hi> and <hi rend="italic">all</hi>. </s><s n="s2.10;p4.9">He even uses a repetition of a whole sentence pattern in line three and line five, giving the reader the feeling of an outcry and exclamatory emphasis. </s><s n="s3.10;p4.9">The change of semantics of the word <hi rend="italic">wind</hi> in line eight is remarkable. </s><s n="s4.10;p4.9">Hopkins alters the word by adding <hi rend="italic"> - ing</hi> to it when it occurs for a second time. </s><s n="s5.10;p4.9">Therefore the meaning, although the word <hi rend="italic">winding</hi> reminds one strongly of the word <hi rend="italic">wind</hi>, becomes different. </s><s n="s6.10;p4.9">An unusual word collocation can be found among line six and seven where Hopkins used an enjambment between the words <hi rend="italic">sandalled</hi> and <hi rend="italic">shadow</hi>. </s><s n="s7.10;p4.9">Whereas <hi rend="italic">sandalled</hi> is normally linked with shoes and therefore with a person, it is now connected with <hi rend="italic">shadow</hi>. </s><s n="s8.10;p4.9">In this, together with the use of <hi rend="italic">dear</hi> in relation to <hi rend="italic">my aspens</hi>, the poem shows an personification of nature and a metaphorical language. </s><s n="s9.10;p4.9">Hopkins's metaphorical language is complemented by antonyms such as <hi rend="italic">swam</hi> and <hi rend="italic">sank</hi> or <hi rend="italic">fresh</hi> and <hi rend="italic">felled</hi> - pairs which interestingly consist of the same fricative sounds. </s><s n="s10.10;p4.9">This reveals how well structured and how elaborate the poem <hi rend="italic">Binsey Poplars</hi> is, although it only consists of two complex sentences. </s></p><p n="p5.9"><s n="s1.3;p5.9">The fragment of <hi rend="italic">The Love Song of Alfred J. Prufrock</hi> is composed of one stanza, written in the imperative, simple present, present continuous and simple past, offering a rather mystical view of an unknown city. </s><s n="s2.3;p5.9">The extract from the poem consists of eight lines in which only line six and line eight rhyme with each other. </s><s n="s3.3;p5.9">Metrically, only line one and two, due to their parallel structure, are equal, whereas the following lines have no continuous stress pattern. </s></p><p n="p6.9"><s n="s1.3;p6.9">Alliteration can be found for the fricative sounds [f] in <hi rend="italic">falls from</hi>, [s] in <hi rend="italic">soot</hi>, <hi rend="italic">slipped</hi>, <hi rend="italic">sudden</hi>, <hi rend="italic">seeing</hi> and <hi rend="italic">soft</hi> as well as [รฐ] in <hi rend="italic">the</hi> and <hi rend="italic">that</hi> and in the lateral [l] at the beginning of line three, four and five. </s><s n="s2.3;p6.9">As mentioned before, fricatives are regarded to cause 'friction' (Carter, 2001, p54), which the fog and smoke actually do in line one and two by rubbing their backs or muzzles against the window-panes. </s><s n="s3.3;p6.9">In addition to alliteration Eliot uses assonance in words such as <hi rend="italic">leap</hi> and <hi rend="italic"> asleep</hi>. </s></p><p n="p7.9"><s n="s1.4;p7.9">Eliot's choice of words is characterised by the repetition of words such as <hi rend="italic">back</hi>, <hi rend="italic">upon</hi> and the different forms of the verb to <hi rend="italic">fall</hi>. </s><s n="s2.4;p7.9">This repetition of individual words is complemented by the method of parallelism used in line one and two. </s><s n="s3.4;p7.9">According to Short (1996, p14), the 'interesting [thing] about parallel structures, in addition to their perceptual prominence, is that they invite the reader to search for meaning connections between the parallel structures, in particular in terms of parts which are varied.' </s><s n="s4.4;p7.9">By analysing the first two lines of this poem with regard to this statement, one recognises that they are the only ones written in the simple present with a simple sentence structure and that within these lines only the nouns <hi rend="italic">fog</hi> and <hi rend="italic">back</hi> differ from <hi rend="italic">smoke</hi> and <hi rend="italic">muzzle</hi>. </s></p><p n="p8.9"><s n="s1.8;p8.9">The very same words, together with several other words in this poem such as the combination of the words <hi rend="italic">fog</hi> or <hi rend="italic">smoke</hi> with <hi rend="italic">rubs</hi> and <hi rend="italic">tongue</hi> or the phrase <hi rend="italic">corner of the evening</hi>, offer unusual collocations. </s><s n="s2.8;p8.9"><hi rend="italic">Fog</hi> has no <hi rend="italic">back</hi>, and <hi rend="italic">smoke</hi> has no <hi rend="italic">muzzle</hi> or <hi rend="italic">tongue</hi> and neither of them can rub against window-panes. </s><s n="s3.8;p8.9">Eliot's choice of such central nouns in the poem offers, along with his remarkable selection of verbs such as <hi rend="italic">curled</hi>, <hi rend="italic">licked</hi> or <hi rend="italic">seeing</hi>, a second dimension to the poem. </s><s n="s4.8;p8.9">Throughout the poem the reader has the feeling that the fog and smoke are behaving in the manner of a cat. </s><s n="s5.8;p8.9">This is extremely metaphorical language, where one cannot be sure if 'the fog has turned into a cat, or [if] the cat has turned into the fog' (Spiro, 2004, p63), which makes use of the method of personification, or perhaps "animalisation" in this case. </s><s n="s6.8;p8.9">The word <hi rend="italic">corner</hi> is normally used in conjunction with a building, shape, room or road and not, as the poem uses it, in the unusual collocation <hi rend="italic">the corner of the evening</hi>, with a specific part of the day. </s><s n="s7.8;p8.9">Even the colour <hi rend="italic">yellow</hi> which is normally seen as positive and can be connected with flowers or the sun, is attached to negative words such as <hi rend="italic">fog</hi> and <hi rend="italic">smoke</hi>. </s><s n="s8.8;p8.9">With this change to the usual semantics and Eliot's playfulness with words in general, he emphasises the extraordinary events in this unknown city, where the cat seems to symbolise something positive in contrast to the rather negative fog and smoke. </s></p><p n="p9.9"><s n="s1.6;p9.9">By comparing both poems to each other, one has to recognise that, although they are from different authors and were written at a different time, they are quite similar. </s><s n="s2.6;p9.9">Both poets make an extensive use of alliteration, assonance, metaphors and repetition, and share an extraordinary point of view of a city. </s><s n="s3.6;p9.9">Whereas Hopkins laments the deforestation of trees near Oxford, T. S. </s><s n="s4.6;p9.9">Eliot let us experience a city through the eyes of smoke, fog and a cat. </s><s n="s5.6;p9.9">Beside these similarities, each poem has its special features. </s><s n="s6.6;p9.9"><hi rend="italic">Binsey Poplars</hi> has enjambments, internal rhymes and antonyms while <hi rend="italic">The Love Song of Alfred J. Prufrock</hi> offers a parallelism and an extraordinary use of verbs. </s></p></div1></body><back><div1 type="bibliography"><head rend="bold">Bibliography </head><p>Carter, R. et al. (2001). <hi rend="italic">Working with Texts : A Core Introduction to Language</hi></p><p><hi rend="italic">Analysis</hi>. 2<hi rend="sup">nd</hi> ed. London: Routledge. </p><p>Short, M. (1996). <hi rend="italic">Exploring the Language of Poems, Plays and Prose</hi>. Harlow: </p><p>Longman.</p><p>Spiro, J. (2004). <hi rend="italic">Creative Poetry Writing</hi>. Oxford: Oxford University Press.</p><p>Spiro, J. Handout Poetry Collection.</p></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
