<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_3006m" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>(Character Outline)</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note/></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">1</p><p n="date">2004-06</p><p n="module title">Creative Writing for Publishing</p><p n="module code">M05204</p><p n="genre family">Narrative recount</p><p n="discipline">Publishing</p><p n="disciplinary group">SS</p><p n="grade">D</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">374</p><p n="number of s-units">19</p><p n="number of p">7</p><p n="number of tables">0</p><p n="number of figures">0</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">0</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">0</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">19.7</p><p n="average s-units per p">2.7</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">f</p><p n="year of birth">1985</p><p n="first language">English</p><p n="education">UKa</p><p n="course">BA English Studies</p><p n="student ID">3006</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><titlePart><name type="student name"/> (<name type="student ID"/>) Creative Writing for Publishing</titlePart><docTitle><titlePart>Character Outline</titlePart></docTitle><titlePart>27 <hi rend="sup">th</hi> April 2004</titlePart></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="section"><p n="p1.7"><s n="s1.4;p1.7">Jessica is 14 and lives with her mum and sister, Emma who is 16. </s><s n="s2.4;p1.7">Jessica and Emma have always been close, and even more so when their parents separated two years ago. </s><s n="s3.4;p1.7">They always looked very similar, so much so that when they were younger people often mistook them for twins. </s><s n="s4.4;p1.7">But, these sisters were actually very different. </s></p><p n="p2.7"><s n="s1.3;p2.7">But, Jessica feels that she is living in her sister's shadow and she no where near as good in any way. </s><s n="s2.3;p2.7">At school all of her male friends say how much they fancy Emma and other girls are jealous, secretly wanted to be her. </s><s n="s3.3;p2.7">Jessica wishes that she was as popular as her sister and secretly wanted to be her too. </s></p><p n="p3.7"><s n="s1.2;p3.7">Jessica is much shorter than Emma was at that age and doesn't share the same sporty figure. </s><s n="s2.2;p3.7">Her skin is very pale and her hair has always been frizzy. </s></p><p n="p4.7"><s n="s1.3;p4.7">Emma had always been good at every subject and is one of the best at sports in the school. </s><s n="s2.3;p4.7">Jessica is bright but has never excelled greatly in any subject area, and on the sports field is awkward and clumsy. </s><s n="s3.3;p4.7">Jessica often feels that her parents prefer Emma and feels jealous when they tell other people how well Emma is doing. </s></p><p n="p5.7"><s n="s1.2;p5.7">Jessica has always tried to be like her sister, but wants to find some way of showing people that she is just as special. </s><s n="s2.2;p5.7">Emma is so confident and although Jessica is not shy, the confidence she shows is always part of an act that she puts on to hide her real feelings. </s></p><p n="p6.7"><s n="s1.4;p6.7">One thing that Jessica does well in is drama. </s><s n="s2.4;p6.7">She hasn't auditioned before for any of the school productions because she had been too shy. </s><s n="s3.4;p6.7">However, in drama classes she finds that she is more confident and, in fact, very good. </s><s n="s4.4;p6.7">She been to see lots of shows before and had always dreamed secretly that she up on stage too. </s></p><p n="p7.7"><s n="s1.1;p7.7">Jessica's parents do not consider drama to be a very good route to follow and insisted that she did not pursue the subject at GCSE. Jessica is desperate to find a way to prove how talented she is and show that there is something that she, and not Emma, is good at. </s></p></div1></body><back/></text></TEI.2>
