<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_3008d" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>What strategies have any two writers from different historical periods employed to represent the contemporary moment?</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">Language used in quote: <foreign id="English">English</foreign></note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">3</p><p n="date">2005-03</p><p n="module title">Contemporary Literature</p><p n="module code">U67083</p><p n="genre family">Essay</p><p n="discipline">English</p><p n="disciplinary group">AH</p><p n="grade">D</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">3353</p><p n="number of s-units">124</p><p n="number of p">20</p><p n="number of tables">0</p><p n="number of figures">0</p><p n="number of block quotes">5</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">0</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">0</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">27.0</p><p n="average s-units per p">6.2</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">f</p><p n="year of birth">1983</p><p n="first language">English</p><p n="education">UKa</p><p n="course">BA English Studies</p><p n="student ID">3008</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><titlePart rend="bold"><name type="student name"/><name type="student ID"/></titlePart><titlePart rend="underlined bold">U67083: Contemporary Literature. (Synoptic Module.)</titlePart><docTitle><titlePart rend="underlined bold">What strategies have any two writers from different historical periods employed to represent the contemporary moment? </titlePart></docTitle></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="section"><p n="p1.20"><s n="s1.4;p1.20">Both <hi rend="italic">The Waste Land</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Movern Callar</hi> succeed in representing a contemporary moment; each efficaciously captures the zeitgeist of their age but in highly divergent ways. </s><s n="s2.4;p1.20">Ostensibly worlds apart, many thematic similarities emerge between the texts, leading us to question how and what we define contemporary. </s><s n="s3.4;p1.20">Religion, gender and identity have remained prominent concerns across the ages and each author is unique in their depiction of how these issues impact on their contemporary society. </s><s n="s4.4;p1.20">But, the limitations of language often force the writers to resort to increasingly innovative strategies of rendering these concerns. </s></p><p n="p2.20"><s n="s1.9;p2.20">Religious ambivalence permeates both texts. </s><s n="s2.9;p2.20">In <hi rend="italic">Movern Callar</hi>, capitalizing 'He'<ref target="BAWE_3008d-ftnote.001"/> has religious associations if 'He' is seen to represent God. </s><s n="s3.9;p2.20">Stealing 'His'<ref target="BAWE_3008d-ftnote.002"/> identity allows Movern to become her own God; free to lead an existential life as one self-governed and judged by herself alone. </s><s n="s4.9;p2.20">McEwan supports this believing; 'The modern novelist sees man making his own world." </s><ref target="BAWE_3008d-ftnote.003"/><s n="s5.9;p2.20">Existentialism seems to engender spiritual and physical liberty; 'Salif Keita sounded so good in the sunshine I stuck out my arms and started spinning round slowly." </s><ref target="BAWE_3008d-ftnote.004"/><s n="s6.9;p2.20">Movern appears most positive when communally external and submerged in nature, angered and distressed only when others impose on her world<ref target="BAWE_3008d-ftnote.005"/>. </s><s n="s7.9;p2.20">Nature imparts the freedom and exhilaration she seeks, literarily making her feel high; 'The land was flattening out I was getting so high up and a hot haze had appeared in the clear bright light,'<ref target="BAWE_3008d-ftnote.006"/> where as alcohol and substance abuse often leaves her feeling; 'queerish." </s><ref target="BAWE_3008d-ftnote.007"/><s n="s8.9;p2.20">March's belief that Warner's; '..youth culture is not the downtrodden city youth..but the ebullient resistance to such as a position,'<ref target="BAWE_3008d-ftnote.008"/> can supported by Movern's almost Romantic return to childhood happiness and innocence through nature.<ref target="BAWE_3008d-ftnote.009"/> Incongruously, Movern is drawn toward religion when in the midst of uncertainty and disappointment<ref target="BAWE_3008d-ftnote.010"/> as in London she; 'screwed my eyes shut tight and had a little prayer. </s><s n="s9.9;p2.20">Outside it was daylightish.' <ref target="BAWE_3008d-ftnote.011"/><ref target="BAWE_3008d-ftnote.012"/> Movern's explicit dependence on routine and fascination with the Spanish religious precession suggests she craves the security and structure offered by faith, but by walking; 'towards strobe of the nightclub,'<ref target="BAWE_3008d-ftnote.013"/> she unequivocally turns toward a different leading light for direction. <ref target="BAWE_3008d-ftnote.014"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3008d-ftnote.001"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Warner, A. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1"><hi rend="underlined">Movern Callar</hi> (London: Vintage, 1996.)p1 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3008d-ftnote.002"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid.,p.2 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3008d-ftnote.003"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">McEwan, N. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1"><hi rend="underlined">The Survival of the Novel: British Fiction in the Later Twentieth Century</hi> (London: Macmillan Press, 1981) p.7 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3008d-ftnote.004"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Warner. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">Op.cit.,p.89 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3008d-ftnote.005"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">See p105-107 where Lanna confesses her betrayal leaving Movern irate and sobbing. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">Here capital letters to convey her anger and make it appear that she is shouting. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3008d-ftnote.006"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid.,p.89 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3008d-ftnote.007"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid.,p.35 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3008d-ftnote.008"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid.,p.78 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3008d-ftnote.009"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">See p. 101-2 where Warner infantilises Movern and Lanna as they play like children in the water, laughing and contented i.e; 'Cowardy ben, Cowardy ben bawled Lanna to egg me on. '(p.102) </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3008d-ftnote.010"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.4;pn1.1">Without constraint or imposed direction she quickly becomes; 'dizzy'(p.89) which may imply free-choice is dangerous, as the absence of guidance leads to confusion and apathy. </s><s n="s2.4;pn1.1">Movern's actions rarely engender consequences, making her life a moral wasteland bereft of legal and moral obligation. </s><s n="s3.4;pn1.1">The peril of believing nothing is wrong foregrounds the novel's preoccupation with both the extreme and the liminal. </s><s n="s4.4;pn1.1">The reader must therefore question the necessity, definition and stability of certain boundaries. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3008d-ftnote.011"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid.,p.165. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3008d-ftnote.012"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Becoming light suggests religion offers escape from her bleak nihilistic existence where; 'The dark sky above the port was empty of any little star.'( p.26) </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3008d-ftnote.013"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid.,p.154 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3008d-ftnote.014"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">The ridged order followed by the worshipers may be used to demonstrate the stifling restriction and entrapment of religious routine making the club's unpredictability and excitement appear preferable. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">Warner, like Eliot refuses to provide a straightforward depiction of religion. </s></p></note><p n="p3.20"><s n="s1.10;p3.20">Like language in the contemporary world, nothing in the novel has one stable meaning, a principal faucet of much post-structuralist and post-modern thought. </s><s n="s2.10;p3.20">One strategy used by Warner to reflect this is making all images and acts explicitly subject to manifold interpretation, a motif encapsulated by the dismembered corpse. </s><s n="s3.10;p3.20">On one level, 'His' interment implies there is no God, but severing the unified body may also be demonstrative of contemporary religious multiplicity, as many reject the notion of one God and draw spiritual guidance from various religions. </s><s n="s4.10;p3.20">Religion, like the symbolic purpose of the body, is multiple. </s><s n="s5.10;p3.20">Ripping 'Him' apart may also illustrate the destruction of patriarchal dominance. </s><s n="s6.10;p3.20">Repeatedly referring to her dead boyfriend as 'He,' appears to mock the anachronistic insistence on obeying a man like a God. </s><s n="s7.10;p3.20">'He,' is denied an identity and consequently an existence, which suggests that masculine and religious hierarchy have become obsolete in the contemporary world. </s><s n="s8.10;p3.20">If so, society may be in need of establishing new ideological frameworks. </s><s n="s9.10;p3.20">Movern's buoyant optimism when burying 'His' dissected remains, could be read as a celebratory rejection of imposed hierarchical masculine inflexibility<ref target="BAWE_3008d-ftnote.015"/> and as an indication to embrace multiplicity, a quality often connoted to the female.<ref target="BAWE_3008d-ftnote.016"/> Warner may be implying that future frameworks should be based on more feminine characteristics such as being open and adaptable, values necessary for social advancement. </s><s n="s10.10;p3.20">If so, libratory free-choice in both life and religion seems to be the key to freedom and contentment. <ref target="BAWE_3008d-ftnote.017"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3008d-ftnote.015"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">If female is multiplicity then man is unity according to much feminist criticism. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">Cixous's essay 'Sorties' in <hi rend="underlined">Literary Theory: An Anthology</hi>, edited by J. Rivkin and M. Ryan (Oxford: Blackwell, 2002.) further explores the nature of this binary divide between the male and female. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3008d-ftnote.016"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.4;pn1.1">Irigaray's essay 'The Power of Discourse and the Subordination of the Feminine' in <hi rend="underlined">Literary Theory: An Anthology</hi> , edited by J. Rivkin and M. Ryan (Oxford: Blackwell, 2002.) further explains the fundamental morphological difference between men and women and why the female is characterized by fluidity and multiplicity. </s><s n="s2.4;pn1.1">She claims the female style of writing is 'always fluid.. </s><s n="s3.4;pn1.1">Its "style" resists and explodes every firmly established form, figure idea or concept.' </s><s n="s4.4;pn1.1">P.572 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3008d-ftnote.017"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Movern is often happiest when immersed in water, a fluid and heterogeneous force often connected to the female as previously explained in Irigaray's essay. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">Regularly seen swimming Movern; 'let out a wee laugh, turned and swam on further out.' p208 </s></p></note><p n="p4.20"><s n="s1.5;p4.20">It could be argued that Warner utilizes the variability of <hi rend="italic">ecriture feminine</hi> as a method of reflecting the volatile, insecure nature of language and life in the modern world. </s><s n="s2.5;p4.20"><hi rend="italic">Ecriture feminine</hi> is often deemed unpredictable and flexible,<ref target="BAWE_3008d-ftnote.018"/> which is essentially what contemporary language has become if fixed meaning is redundant. </s><s n="s3.5;p4.20">The fluidity of an <hi rend="italic">ecriture feminine</hi> may therefore offer a more realistic way for Warner to reflect his contemporary world. </s><s n="s4.5;p4.20">Mengham's description of the novel as a; 'stylistically delirious and telepathic account of contemporary social derangements,'<ref target="BAWE_3008d-ftnote.019"/> supports this suggestion, as emblematic divisions and boundaries often overlap, generating the impression of a more female writing style. </s><s n="s5.5;p4.20">Repeated images, places and phrases create a cyclic structure that opposes stereotypical male linearity<ref target="BAWE_3008d-ftnote.020"/>, while the surreal compendium of hallucinogenic images produces an anarchic teleology that makes the text unstable and erratic, prominent characteristics of the <hi rend="italic">ecriture feminine</hi>. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3008d-ftnote.018"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">For further definition regarding the nature and purpose of the ecriture feminine see Cixous's essay 'Sorties' in <hi rend="underlined">Literary Theory: An Anthology</hi>, edited by J. Rivkin and M. Ryan (Oxford: Blackwell, 2002.) where she examines the importance of ensuring that the female voice no longer adheres to circumscribed boundaries; 'She lets the other tongue of a thousand tongues speak-the tongue without barrier or death.. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">Her tongue doesn't hold back..doesn't keep in.' p584 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3008d-ftnote.019"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Mengham, R. <hi rend="underlined">An Introduction to Contemporary fiction.</hi> </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1"><hi rend="underlined">International Writing in English Since 1970 (</hi>Cambridge: Polity Press, 1999)p.9 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3008d-ftnote.020"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Pope describes the archetypical characteristics of 'manly writing' as; 'tightly controlled..orderly and linear progression of topic and a man-centred focus on external actions and public relationships.' (Pope, R. <hi rend="underlined">The English Studies Book.</hi> </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">(London: Routledge, 2001.)p.121) </s></p></note><p n="p5.20"><s n="s1.3;p5.20">Movern's inconsistent femininity leads me to agree with Anderson that; 'writing about women does not necessarily make a writer 'feminist.''<ref target="BAWE_3008d-ftnote.021"/> Warner's feminine style is used to reflect the nature of language as opposed to make a statement about the position of women, something seemingly resistant to definition in contemporary society. </s><s n="s2.3;p5.20">Although the novel is laced with anti-patriarchal nuances, Movern remains reliant on a man, as it is her boyfriend's money that liberates her. </s><s n="s3.3;p5.20">Repeated descriptions of Movern's underwear sexualise and somewhat reduce her to the position of a fetishized object; 'I licked my fingers to roll the stockings up.' <ref target="BAWE_3008d-ftnote.022"/><ref target="BAWE_3008d-ftnote.023"/> Kirk supports this interpretation; </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3008d-ftnote.021"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.3;pn1.1">Anderson, C, 'Listening to the Women Talk' in <hi rend="underlined">The Scottish Novel Since the Seventies.</hi> </s><s n="s2.3;pn1.1"><hi rend="underlined">New Visions, Old Dreams</hi> ed. </s><s n="s3.3;pn1.1">G. Wallace and R. Stevenson, (Edinburgh: Edinburgh University Press, 1994)p.170 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3008d-ftnote.022"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Warner. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">Op.cit., p.14 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3008d-ftnote.023"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.3;pn1.1">The body as a site of gender expression has engendered much contradictory literary criticism, making it highly difficult to ascertain a definite sense of what Warner is trying to imply by reducing Movern to a visual object. </s><s n="s2.3;pn1.1">See Mulvey 'Visual Pleasure and Narrative Cinema' in <hi rend="underlined">Literary Theory: An Anthology</hi> , edited by J. Rivkin and M. Ryan (Oxford: Blackwell, 2002.)for further discussion regarding the female as object especially in relation to the male gaze; 'Woman stands in patriarchal culture as signifier for the male other.. in which man... through linguistic command imposes on them the silent image of woman still tied to her place as bearer of meaning not maker of meaning.' </s><s n="s3.3;pn1.1">The connection between women and silence is further explored later. </s></p></note><quote lang="English">In working class writing by men, despite often sympathetic portrayal of women...female identity is subjected to male desire and fantasy, or their agency subordinated to the protective male embrace. <ref target="BAWE_3008d-ftnote.024"/></quote><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3008d-ftnote.024"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Kirk, J. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1"><hi rend="underlined">Twentieth-century writing and the British Working Class</hi> (Cardiff: University of Wales Press, 2003)p.135 </s></p></note><p n="p6.20"><s n="s1.3;p6.20">This last point is contestable as Movern is seldom a passive female; she elects her sexual partners and controls the action; 'I reached down between my legs to move his fingers correctly.' <ref target="BAWE_3008d-ftnote.025"/><ref target="BAWE_3008d-ftnote.026"/> Contradiction pervades each act of gender significance. </s><s n="s2.3;p6.20">Returning home pregnant with the; 'child of the raves,'<ref target="BAWE_3008d-ftnote.027"/> fortifies the novel's cyclic structure, suggesting Movern will be trapped in a domestic maternal role. </s><s n="s3.3;p6.20">But, as the father's identity remains undisclosed the male again appears insignificant, thus reinforcing the permeable implication that men may be unimportant in the future. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3008d-ftnote.025"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Warner. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">Op.cit., p.135 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3008d-ftnote.026"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Even more complex is her insistence; I'm not a man,' (p.172) while resorting to stereotypically masculine violence with Creeping Jesus as it suggests that only by adopting male behaviour can a woman be heard and empowered. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3008d-ftnote.027"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid., p.229 </s></p></note><p n="p7.20"><s n="s1.5;p7.20">Gender in contemporary society is hugely nebulous; how it is represented often proves as problematic as how it is defined. </s><s n="s2.5;p7.20">Butler argues that now; 'There is no proper gender,'<ref target="BAWE_3008d-ftnote.028"/> believing all gender to be performance. </s><s n="s3.5;p7.20">Discourse is a highly formative part of this performance; while Movern's routines are explicitly those of a female,<ref target="BAWE_3008d-ftnote.029"/> the extent to which a man can genuinely appropriate a woman's voice is questionable. </s><s n="s4.5;p7.20">Accepting Humm's belief that; 'gender is constructed through language and is visible in writing style;' <ref target="BAWE_3008d-ftnote.030"/> using direct, pithy end-stopped sentences rarely coloured by emotion<ref target="BAWE_3008d-ftnote.031"/> make Movern appear more masculine, as conventional male language is seen as ordered and rational.<ref target="BAWE_3008d-ftnote.032"/> If male and female speech are at opposite ends of a gendered linguistic divide, their voices cannot be unified without antithetical fracture; the credibility of Movern's female voice is therefore always contestable, as its core is essentially male. </s><s n="s5.5;p7.20">A similar conflict emerges in the <hi rend="italic">Scarlet Letter</hi>.<ref target="BAWE_3008d-ftnote.033"/> As men, Hawthorne and Warner are socially and linguistically dominant; if Warner has never been externalised by his gender, he cannot empathise with Movern's peripheral position, therefore cannot authentically render her voice. <ref target="BAWE_3008d-ftnote.034"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3008d-ftnote.028"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Butler, J. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">'Imitation and Gender Insubordination' 1991 in <hi rend="underlined">Literary Theory: An Anthology</hi> , edited by J. Rivkin and M. Ryan (Oxford: Blackwell, 2002.)p.723 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3008d-ftnote.029"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">see p.188 for an example; 'I would start waxing legs and bikini line..but you only wax to save time shaving them each morning.' </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3008d-ftnote.030"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Humm, M. A Reader's guide to <hi rend="underlined">Contemporary Feminist Literary Criticism</hi> (London: Harvester Wheatsheaf, 1994)p.4 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3008d-ftnote.031"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Pope believes; 'The general characteristics of such 'womanly writing/speech' are reckoned to be long and loosely co-ordinated sentences, fluid changes of topic, a resistance to 'linear' logic and, implicitly, a woman-centred focus on inner feelings.'(Pope op.cit., p.121) thus supporting the notion that Movern is more masculine in her speech and narration. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3008d-ftnote.032"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Many of these notions are examined in Lakoff's <hi rend="underlined">A Woman's Place</hi> 1975 where he provides a model of what he considers to be the nature of female speech in conversation and how it differs from that used by the male as he sees female speech as hesitant, illogical and disordered. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3008d-ftnote.033"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.3;pn1.1">Here Hawthorne vehemently emphasises the parallels between himself and Hester in an attempt to make her story of 'human frailty and sorrow' (Hawthorne, N. </s><s n="s2.3;pn1.1"><hi rend="underlined">The Scarlet Letter</hi>, (London: Penguin, 1986)p.76) his own to narrate. </s><s n="s3.3;pn1.1">Hawthorne continually attempts to distance him the hypocritical men he depicts by emphasizing his comparative understanding and compassion, stereotypically female characteristics he accentuates in what often seems like an attempt to validate his ability to assume and manifest the female voice and persona; 'I experienced a sensation not altogether physical..of burning heat; as if the letter were not of red cloth, but red-hot iron.'(Ibid., p.62) </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3008d-ftnote.034"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Anderson can be used to support this; 'If male Scottish authors have had to contend with difficulties generated in part by a problematic relationship to national identity, language and literary tradition, for women this experience is compounded by gender.' (Anderson, op.cit., p.171) </s></p></note><p n="p8.20"><s n="s1.12;p8.20">If language is an essentially masculine medium from which woman is excluded,<ref target="BAWE_3008d-ftnote.035"/> the female remains outside of language and is therefore silent, as was Coris Jean; 'I never spoke for four year." </s><ref target="BAWE_3008d-ftnote.036"/><s n="s2.12;p8.20">Such comments confirm Mills' belief that; 'We are still trapped within the notion of woman's language being deviant, powerless and submissive." </s><ref target="BAWE_3008d-ftnote.037"/><s n="s3.12;p8.20">If so, women must find and create their own language. </s><s n="s4.12;p8.20">Interpreting stealing 'His' voice as an empowering reversion of female subordination challenges Mills, yet, it conversely supports hegemonic notions of language as masculine, as only through a male voice, that of Warner and her boyfriend, is Movern ever heard; 'His name on the first page of that novel: By Movern Callar." </s><ref target="BAWE_3008d-ftnote.038"/><s n="s5.12;p8.20">Without graphological speech marks to accompany her words Movern is essentially silent,<ref target="BAWE_3008d-ftnote.039"/> admitting herself; 'I'm a right queer-case for not talking. </s><s n="s6.12;p8.20">I'm taciturn." </s><ref target="BAWE_3008d-ftnote.040"/><s n="s7.12;p8.20">But, this is complicated by also expressing male speech without quotation marks. </s><s n="s8.12;p8.20">The reader is therefore led to question whether an author can or should appropriate the voice of another person. </s><s n="s9.12;p8.20">If a male writer can employ aspects of the <hi rend="italic">ecriture feminine</hi> and the female has access to 'masculine' dominant discourse, then the notion of gendered language seems defunct and outdated, as in the contemporary world gender boundaries, like gendered language, overlap. </s><s n="s10.12;p8.20">Supposed 'male' and 'female' language are no longer straightforward binaries, as both Warner and Movern are published in spite of 'stealing' the voice of another sex. </s><s n="s11.12;p8.20">The relevance of authorship therefore becomes debatable,<ref target="BAWE_3008d-ftnote.041"/> as ownership over discourse seems impossible. </s><s n="s12.12;p8.20">The literal death of the author prefigures symbolic death of authorial control; the originating conscience of the creator no longer exists making Movern's plagiarism questionable, as technically no one owns the text.<ref target="BAWE_3008d-ftnote.042"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3008d-ftnote.035"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Showalter confirms the existence of such opinions by stating in 'The rise of gender' in <hi rend="underlined">Speaking of Gender</hi> Ed Showalter, E (London: Routledge, 1989) 'all speech is necessarily talk about gender..and the masculine is the linguistic norm.' p1 This helps illustrate how accepted and ingrained such estimations have become. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3008d-ftnote.036"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Warner. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">Op.cit., p.39 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3008d-ftnote.037"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Mills, S <hi rend="underlined">Feminist Stylistics</hi> (London: Routledge, 1995)p.48 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3008d-ftnote.038"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Warner. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">Op.cit., p.84 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3008d-ftnote.039"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">This is not only because a man cannot assume a female voice but because a woman's voice cannot be authentically rendered through a discourse that privileges the male. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3008d-ftnote.040"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Warner. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">Op.cit., p.36 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3008d-ftnote.041"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">The author of the text is an ambivalent concept in the novel. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">Foucalt argues; 'It would be just as wrong to equate the author with the real writer as to equate him with the fictitious speaker;' p112 which suggests that the contemporary author, like gender is now a problematic, multiple concept that resists definition. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3008d-ftnote.042"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Barthes can be used to support this; 'To give a text an Author is to impose a limit on that text, to furnish it with a final signified, to close the writing.' p1469 </s></p></note><p n="p9.20"><s n="s1.5;p9.20">Movern concurrently rejects both moral and linguistic codes. </s><s n="s2.5;p9.20">Ignoring established grammatical rules allows her to narrate in her own sociolect, one comprised of compound neologisms, syntactic inversion and unique phonetic spellings that foreground the thematic centrality of manifesting one's identity, see; 'her mouth seeming right deep and darkish cause of the whiteishness of faces.' <ref target="BAWE_3008d-ftnote.043"/><ref target="BAWE_3008d-ftnote.044"/> The Guyanese poet Agard also manipulates language but in making it his own, is seen to violate English; 'mugging de Queen's English/ is the story of my life." </s><ref target="BAWE_3008d-ftnote.045"/><s n="s3.5;p9.20">Dismantling and restructuring language enables those like Movern who are outside of the dominant discourse, to articulate their 'story' with realism and authenticity.<ref target="BAWE_3008d-ftnote.046"/> Substituting 'No' with 'Nut,'<ref target="BAWE_3008d-ftnote.047"/> and Scottish colloquialisms such as; 'wee',<ref target="BAWE_3008d-ftnote.048"/> autographically inscribe Movern's accent and culture in the novel. </s><s n="s4.5;p9.20">This demonstrates both the mutability of language and importance of marking Scotland out as devolved from England, a prominent concern for contemporary Scots.<ref target="BAWE_3008d-ftnote.049"/> Warner unsettles notions of Scotland as substandard by revealing what is often considered the contrastive, inferior other to be disturbingly similar to the dominant. </s><s n="s5.5;p9.20">Exposing the supposed cosmopolitan antithetical Londoners as inarticulate and inept, demonstrates the equal value of Scottish discourse as they; 'talked so constant you found their blethers made less sense than locals back in the resort.' <ref target="BAWE_3008d-ftnote.050"/><ref target="BAWE_3008d-ftnote.051"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3008d-ftnote.043"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Warner. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">Op.cit., p74 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3008d-ftnote.044"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.3;pn1.1">This generates an authentic voice that accurately captures her way of speaking and thinking. </s><s n="s2.3;pn1.1">Making language comply to her own specific rules allows Movern to express precisely what she wants to say how she wants to say it, thus creating a confident, unapologetic and defiant tone to her voice. </s><s n="s3.3;pn1.1">The notion of other as subordinate is contested throughout the novel; assuming the role of centralised 'I,' allows Movern a control over narrative direction that enables her to reverse the conventional marginality engendered by her sex and nationality. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3008d-ftnote.045"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.3;pn1.1">Agard, J. </s><s n="s2.3;pn1.1">'Me not no Oxford Don' (lecture handout) l. </s><s n="s3.3;pn1.1">12-13 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3008d-ftnote.046"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.4;pn1.1">Agard attempts to prove this is something positive to embrace and not be threatened by; 'I only armed wit mih human breath.' (l.30) </s><s n="s2.4;pn1.1">He needs no weapons, as language itself is more influential than violence. </s><s n="s3.4;pn1.1">The multiplicity of English language varieties have made it an increasingly fluid and unstable medium, it is both evolutionary and vulnerable to change. </s><s n="s4.4;pn1.1">Linguistic variation and assimilation allows language to be used as a method of rebellion against enforced colonial discourse, a prominent theme in the work of post-colonial poets such as L.K. Johnson and Grace Nichols who integrate Afro-Caribbean dialect in their verse in order to realistically impart their voices. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3008d-ftnote.047"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Warner. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">Op.cit., p31 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3008d-ftnote.048"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid., p.19 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3008d-ftnote.049"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">The often uneasy amalgamation of Scottish idiolect and Standard English may reflect the conflict inherent in establishing Scottish parliamentary autonomy. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">Division is a key theme, emphasised by the recurrent image of Movern's toe divider, which helps to visually demonstrate how separate entities can remain connected. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3008d-ftnote.050"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Warner. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">Op.cit.,p160 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3008d-ftnote.051"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.4;pn1.1">Very little disparity emerges between the behaviour and club scene in London; without explicitly marking place names and use of Scottish dialect, Warner could be depicting the underclass of any society. </s><s n="s2.4;pn1.1">Here they generate a firm insistence on place and identity that relays a desire to be heard, confirming Wallace's belief that Scottish fiction is no longer 'immured in ignorance and neglect-unpublished, unread, untaught.' (Wallace,G. </s><s rend="underlined" n="s3.4;pn1.1">The Scottish Novel Since the Seventies. </s><s n="s4.4;pn1.1"><hi rend="underlined">New Visions, Old Dreams</hi> (Edinburgh: Edinburgh University Press, 1994)p.1) </s></p></note><p n="p10.20"><s n="s1.11;p10.20">Eliot's contemporary moment was also dominated by conflict. </s><s n="s2.11;p10.20">Lanbaum asserts; 'No poem seemed to express more of its time than <hi rend="italic">The Waste Land</hi>." </s><ref target="BAWE_3008d-ftnote.052"/><s n="s3.11;p10.20">Adopting a cultural materialist reading of the poem seems unavoidable as much of its structure and imagery is utilised specifically to capture social disjunction. </s><s n="s4.11;p10.20">Amalgamating assorted metrical and rhythmical patterns generates an intentional chaos that reflects the uncertainty and insecurity following the First World War. </s><s n="s5.11;p10.20">Abrupt syntactic shifts convey the turbulence of an era characterized by sudden change and decaying social constancy. </s><s n="s6.11;p10.20">Fusing varied poetic forms may be representative of the difficulty inherent in establishing the desired European unity craved by many. </s><s n="s7.11;p10.20">Modernist writers began to pioneer new strategies that enabled them to express the unique concerns of the post war world, a new era unlike any other where previous literary forms began to seem inadequate. </s><s n="s8.11;p10.20">The poem's ostensibly random assimilation of images rejects order and boundaries, reflecting the zeitgeist of writers and painters engaged in a similar process.<ref target="BAWE_3008d-ftnote.053"/> Eliot's radical deployment of literary and mythical allusions, severs the once coherent and admired words of others in order to demonstrate the destruction of stability and tradition engendered by war. </s><s n="s9.11;p10.20">A; 'heap of broken images,'<ref target="BAWE_3008d-ftnote.054"/> without obvious connective associations dislocate history and geography, leaving the reader like those in the wasteland, disorientated and bewildered. </s><s n="s10.11;p10.20">The difficulty of deciphering complex allusive networks enables the reader to undergo a crisis of understanding that engenders a sense of humiliation. </s><s n="s11.11;p10.20">The overwhelming impossibility of understanding the allusive context of each image allows the reader to share the futility and failure plaguing the characters and age; 'We who were living are now dying/ with a little patience.' <ref target="BAWE_3008d-ftnote.055"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3008d-ftnote.052"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Lanbaum, R. 'New Modes of Characterization in The Waste Land' in <hi rend="underlined">Eliot in his Time</hi> ed A.Litz (Princeton: University Press Princeton, 1973) p.95 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3008d-ftnote.053"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1"><hi rend="italic">The Waste Land</hi> seems on occasion an expression of discomfort with what art called itself, as proceeding structural limitations were challenged and transcended by artists and writers engaged in attempting to render coherent forms to an incoherent world. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3008d-ftnote.054"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.3;pn1.1">Eliot, T.S.. </s><s rend="underlined" n="s2.3;pn1.1">The Waste Land and Other Poems. </s><s n="s3.3;pn1.1">(London: Faber and Faber, 1999.) p23 l.22 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3008d-ftnote.055"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid., p.36, l.229-330 </s></p></note><p n="p11.20"><s n="s1.4;p11.20">Cyclic images convey the repetitive ennui plaguing; 'crowds of people, walking round in a ring." </s><ref target="BAWE_3008d-ftnote.056"/><s n="s2.4;p11.20">The poem's lack of structural progression suggests there is no escape from this perpetual psychological wasteland. </s><s n="s3.4;p11.20">Entrapped in the eternal present, past and future become indecipherable. </s><s n="s4.4;p11.20">April is the; 'cruelest month,'<ref target="BAWE_3008d-ftnote.057"/> as the confusion between; 'memory and desire,'<ref target="BAWE_3008d-ftnote.058"/> leaves the inhabitants of post-war Europe wishing for the merciful oblivion of a; 'forgetful snow'.<ref target="BAWE_3008d-ftnote.059"/> Man seems incapable of progression; superficially successful city workers are imprisoned by their pursuit of monetary gain, as capitalist advancement leads to reversion and decay in the; </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3008d-ftnote.056"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid., p.24, l.56 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3008d-ftnote.057"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid., p23 l1 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3008d-ftnote.058"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid., p.23, l.3 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3008d-ftnote.059"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid., p.23, l.6 </s></p></note><quote lang="English">Unreal City Under the brown fog of a winter dawn A crowd flowed.. I had not thought death had undone so many. <ref target="BAWE_3008d-ftnote.060"/></quote><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3008d-ftnote.060"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid.,p.25, l.60-4 </s></p></note><p n="p12.20"><s n="s1.2;p12.20">Pathetic fallacy animates the murky gloom shrouding a capital dominated by pessimism. </s><s n="s2.2;p12.20">Mass urbanization appears to have deprived workers of their identity and humanity, leaving them apathetic and isolated; 'Sighs, short and infrequent, were exhaled,/ And each man fixed his eyes before his feet.' <ref target="BAWE_3008d-ftnote.061"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3008d-ftnote.061"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid.,p.25 l.64-5 </s></p></note><p n="p13.20"><s n="s1.15;p13.20">Man's emotional paralysis is exposed through Eliot's perturbing portrayal of relationships. </s><s n="s2.15;p13.20">Even when seemingly united, characters remain alienated. </s><s n="s3.15;p13.20">Alternate rhyming couplets provide a surface impression of harmony between the typist and clerk, but as the rhyme's mechanical predictability becomes apparent, an impression of monotonous indifference is created. </s><s n="s4.15;p13.20">'Hardly aware of her departed lover',<ref target="BAWE_3008d-ftnote.062"/> reinforces the distance between them; they are physically one but emotionally disconnected. </s><s n="s5.15;p13.20">Characters often appear imprisoned in their minds, doomed to continual misunderstanding in being unable to use language effectively. </s><s n="s6.15;p13.20">Ornate, decorative language in the 'Game of Chess,' generates an artificiality that exposes the essential emptiness of modern life. </s><s n="s7.15;p13.20">The woman is; 'troubled, confused and drowned the sense in orders,' <ref target="BAWE_3008d-ftnote.063"/> as too is the reader, lost in the convoluted syntax, enjambment and sparse punctuation used to illustrate her claustrophobic hysteria. </s><s n="s8.15;p13.20">The omission of inverted commas in the man's responses and absent question mark in; 'Speak to me. </s><s n="s9.15;p13.20">Why do you never speak,'<ref target="BAWE_3008d-ftnote.064"/> suggests that we overhear only his thoughts. </s><s n="s10.15;p13.20">The position of women here lacks the ambivalence of <hi rend="italic">Movern Callar</hi>, as they are explicitly passive. </s><s n="s11.15;p13.20">Disturbing allusions to Philomel imply male dominance, as refusing to speak gives the man power to prolong the woman's anxiety.<ref target="BAWE_3008d-ftnote.065"/> Women also remain controlled sexually by men. </s><s n="s12.15;p13.20">Philomel is; 'so rudely forced,'<ref target="BAWE_3008d-ftnote.066"/> as too is the typist describing the clerk's caresses as; 'assaults,'<ref target="BAWE_3008d-ftnote.067"/> that are 'unreproved, if undesired." </s><ref target="BAWE_3008d-ftnote.068"/><s n="s13.15;p13.20">Movern can be deemed as equally subservient if her voice and actions are seen to be subject to masculine regulation. </s><s n="s14.15;p13.20">To an extent, like Lil she is trapped by pregnancy, although Movern's life is not devoted to fulfilling the sexual needs of a husband who; 'wants a good time." </s><ref target="BAWE_3008d-ftnote.069"/><s n="s15.15;p13.20">Ascertaining how much the position of women has changed is highly problematic; although they appear stronger in <hi rend="italic">Movern Callar</hi>, women remain far from free, condemned to remain governed by their biological function to a degree. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3008d-ftnote.062"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid., p.32 l.250 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3008d-ftnote.063"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid.,p.26, l.88-9 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3008d-ftnote.064"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid.,p.27, l.112 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3008d-ftnote.065"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.3;pn1.1">Ironically, her speech discloses a fear of the death and decay that already traps her. </s><s n="s2.3;pn1.1">The gruesome image of; 'pressing lidless eyes and waiting for a knock upon the door,' (p.28, l.136)demonstrates the impossibility of escaping or ignoring the omnipresent inevitability of death. </s><s n="s3.3;pn1.1">The barman's impatient call reminds us that time dictates and controls all people and classes, making the 'Game of Chess' a metaphor for life. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3008d-ftnote.066"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid.,p26.l.100 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3008d-ftnote.067"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid.,p32, l.239 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3008d-ftnote.068"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid.,p.32, l.238 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3008d-ftnote.069"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid.,p.28 l.148 </s></p></note><p n="p14.20"><s n="s1.7;p14.20">Nameless and faceless characters pervade <hi rend="italic">The Waste Land</hi>, as unsure of themselves as we are of them. </s><s n="s2.7;p14.20">No central voice dominates narration; continual changes in pronoun and tense leave the reader doubting each character's gender, nationality and perspective. </s><s n="s3.7;p14.20">Warner also depicts fragmentary characters whose personalities are often encapsulated by their nicknames.<ref target="BAWE_3008d-ftnote.070"/> Differing concepts of identity were emerging during the Modernist period, forcing writers to resort to new modes of characterization.<ref target="BAWE_3008d-ftnote.071"/> Like gender and language, identity has become polymorphous and heterogeneous. </s><s n="s4.7;p14.20">Chameleonic identities and the limitation of subjectivity are often seen as more post-modern concerns. </s><s n="s5.7;p14.20">Bertens claims; 'the..stable subject of modernity has been replaced by a postmodern agent whose identity is largely other-determined and always in process,'<ref target="BAWE_3008d-ftnote.072"/> but here Eliot demonstrates that attaining a definitive sense of identity was also concern in the Modernist era. </s><s n="s6.7;p14.20">What we define contemporary again becomes contestable, as certain dilemmas are not new or exclusive to one era. </s><s n="s7.7;p14.20">Jain contests this to a degree, interpreting the poem's hetroglossic pollyvocality and dislocated vocalization as demonstrating that; </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3008d-ftnote.070"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">see p.14 Warner.op.cit., for examples such as 'Overdose'. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3008d-ftnote.071"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Lanbaum views this as a; 'reaction against the Nineteenth century belief in the individual as the one reality you could be sure of,' which may be why no stable identity exists in <hi rend="italic">The Waste Land</hi>. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3008d-ftnote.072"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Bertens, H. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1"><hi rend="underlined">The Idea of the Postmodern</hi> (London: Routledge, 1995.) p.19 </s></p></note><quote lang="English">Eliot perceived the divisions and tortured convolutions of consciousness.. as symptomatic of, and resulting from the historical and cultural circumstances of his time. <ref target="BAWE_3008d-ftnote.073"/></quote><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3008d-ftnote.073"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Jain, M. A. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1"><hi rend="underlined">Critical Reading of the Selected Poems of T.S. Eliot</hi> (Oxford: Oxford University Press, 1991) </s></p></note><p n="p15.20"><s n="s1.1;p15.20">The infiltration of foreign languages supports this by creating a sense of displacement that reflects the absence of European geographical stability. </s></p><p n="p16.20"><s n="s1.3;p16.20">Ironically, the more languages and voices used in the poem, the less understanding seems to exist. </s><s n="s2.3;p16.20">Discontinuous, depersonalised voices often merge, as dialogue, monologue and fragmented streams of consciousness coexist confusingly. </s><s n="s3.3;p16.20">Language almost becomes a barrier that prevents communication; </s></p><quote lang="English">I could not Speak, and my eyes failed, I was neither Living nor dead, and I knew nothing. <ref target="BAWE_3008d-ftnote.074"/></quote><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3008d-ftnote.074"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Eliot, op.cit., p.24 l.39-40 </s></p></note><p n="p17.20"><s n="s1.11;p17.20">Structuralist theory supports the notion that language cannot convey meaning;<ref target="BAWE_3008d-ftnote.075"/> if the perceptual image engendered by each signifier is different to each individual reader, then we can never truly communicate with accuracy. </s><s n="s2.11;p17.20">As in many of the relationships depicted, verbal interaction appears pointless, as ascertaining a definitive sense of what someone else means through their language alone seems impossible. </s><s n="s3.11;p17.20">Experimental strategies such as objective correlative and sensory manipulation therefore become paramount in evoking elusive states of mind that language alone cannot convey. </s><s n="s4.11;p17.20">Auditory descriptions such as; 'drip drop drop drop drop,'<ref target="BAWE_3008d-ftnote.076"/> employ repeated harsh plosive phonemes in order to emulate the abrasive and hostile nature of the dystopian future presented. </s><s n="s5.11;p17.20">Drawing our focus to only the aural properties of water make it a physical sound alone, like the deluded traveler we can only hear it as; 'there is no water." </s><ref target="BAWE_3008d-ftnote.077"/><s n="s6.11;p17.20">Certain inexpressible emotions are fundamentally vague and can only be realistically depicted through obscure methods such as imagery. </s><s n="s7.11;p17.20">Nature becomes a metaphor for contemporary humanity, 'sunken' and 'limp,'<ref target="BAWE_3008d-ftnote.078"/> desperate for both literal and spiritual regeneration.<ref target="BAWE_3008d-ftnote.079"/> Scientific progression and industrial growth led to an increased focus on the material which disturbed established notions of morality and engendered religious doubt. </s><s n="s8.11;p17.20">Infinite death appears to replace the promise of eternal life. </s><s n="s9.11;p17.20">The response to the unanswerable question; 'Who is the third who walks always beside you?" </s><ref target="BAWE_3008d-ftnote.080"/><s n="s10.11;p17.20">is formed by a figurative image of the grim reaper; 'There is always another one walking beside you/ Gliding wrapt in a brown mantle, hooded." </s><ref target="BAWE_3008d-ftnote.081"/><s n="s11.11;p17.20">Powerful visual images become a substitute for a language that is unable to articulate the horror of a modern world where hope is nonexistent. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3008d-ftnote.075"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Saussure asserts; 'A linguistic system is a series of differences of sounds combined with a series of differences of ideas,' (Sassure, F. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">'Course in General Linguistics' in <hi rend="underlined">Literary Theory: An Anthology</hi> , edited by J. Rivkin and M. Ryan (Oxford: Blackwell, 2002.)p.88) thus supporting the suggestion that the perceptual concept signified by each signifier differs among each individual, making attempting to explain the complex processes of our minds impossible and therefore futile to an extent. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3008d-ftnote.076"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid.,p37 l.356 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3008d-ftnote.077"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid.,p37 l.358 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3008d-ftnote.078"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid., p.38 l.397 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3008d-ftnote.079"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.5;pn1.1">Personification illustrates the unbearable thirst suffered by both through images of topographical aridity; 'Dead mountain mouth of carious teeth that cannot spit.' (p.36 l.339) </s><s n="s2.5;pn1.1">De-familiarization is also employed; making the conventional appear alien efficaciously demonstrates the absence normality and reliability in Eliot's chaotic society. </s><s n="s3.5;pn1.1">Water becomes a paradox, connected to both sterility and fertility, as repeated depictions of polluted, dirty water manipulate its symbolic properties; 'The river sweats/ oil and tar.' (p.33 l.266-267) </s><s n="s4.5;pn1.1">Explicitly perverting water's regenerative properties reflects the seemingly absent promise of salvation through eternal life. </s><s n="s5.5;pn1.1">This fortifies the despondency engendered by images of false prophets and spiritual impotence that trap; 'hooded hordes swarming over endless plains, stumbling in cracked earth.' (p.37 l.368-70) </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3008d-ftnote.080"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid., p.37 l.359 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3008d-ftnote.081"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid., p.37 l.362-3 </s></p></note><p n="p18.20"><s n="s1.9;p18.20">Tobain supports this argument; 'For Eliot, these visions of contemporary society are inseparable from the loss of faith. </s><s n="s2.9;p18.20">Man no longer believes." </s><ref target="BAWE_3008d-ftnote.082"/><s n="s3.9;p18.20">But this is contestable if we believe the thunder offers a way forward, as the poem's focus on religious futility may be an attempt to capture a moment of extreme potential. </s><s n="s4.9;p18.20">Change is desperately needed; in unifying Buda and St Augustine<ref target="BAWE_3008d-ftnote.083"/>, Eliot may suggest an amalgamation of Western and Eastern wisdom is the answer. </s><s n="s5.9;p18.20">As is possibly implied in the novel, nature may hold 'the key'<ref target="BAWE_3008d-ftnote.084"/> to spiritual advancement as the elements replace God, as in the; 'empty chapel, only the wind's home." </s><ref target="BAWE_3008d-ftnote.085"/><s n="s6.9;p18.20">By leaving the decision to follow or reject the thunder's advice in the reader's hands, Eliot refuses to provide a conclusive resolution, a common feature of Modernist writing. </s><s n="s7.9;p18.20">The sinister repetition of; 'London Bridge is falling down falling down,'<ref target="BAWE_3008d-ftnote.086"/> infers that man is destined to deteriorate further if he ignores this advice. </s><s n="s8.9;p18.20">The poem purposefully lacks closure; ending without a full stop implies that there is no one solution to the problems presented. </s><s n="s9.9;p18.20">I believe Murphy encapsulates Eliot's intention effectively; </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3008d-ftnote.082"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.3;pn1.1">Tobain,D.N. </s><s n="s2.3;pn1.1"><hi rend="underlined">The Presence of the Past</hi>. </s><s n="s3.3;pn1.1"><hi rend="underlined">T.S. Eliot's Victorian Inheritance</hi> (Michigan: UMI Research Press) p.23 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3008d-ftnote.083"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">See the conclusion of part III where Buddha and St Augustine seem to come to an understanding, if not a solution. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3008d-ftnote.084"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Eliot, op.cit., p.48.l.411 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3008d-ftnote.085"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid., p.38 l.388 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3008d-ftnote.086"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Ibid., p.39 l. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">426 </s></p></note><quote lang="English">the absence of a bona fide meaning..might be what Eliot was aiming to achieve: a proof that the absence of meaning is not meaningless but an authentic and verifiable state of psychological being, certainly for the modern instant, but perhaps for most of human experience. <ref target="BAWE_3008d-ftnote.087"/></quote><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3008d-ftnote.087"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.3;pn1.1">Murphy, R.E. ''It is impossible to say just what I mean': The Waste Land as Transcendent Meaning' in T <hi rend="underlined">.S. Eliot.</hi> </s><s n="s2.3;pn1.1"><hi rend="underlined">A Voice Descanting</hi> Ed S. Bagchee. </s><s n="s3.3;pn1.1">(London: Macmillan, 1990)p.53 </s></p></note><p n="p19.20"><s n="s1.1;p19.20">As in <hi rend="italic">Movern Callar</hi>, people are constantly seeking new ways of understanding the self; dissociation from others is central in both texts, but how or whether we can reconcile this remains open to contention. </s></p><p n="p20.20"><s n="s1.4;p20.20">Particular dilemmas continually affect humanity making it appear as though nothing is new, a key component of post-modernist thought. </s><s n="s2.4;p20.20">Both texts to an extent support Monteith's belief that; 'contemporary fiction is a barometer of the nation's intellectual health,'<ref target="BAWE_3008d-ftnote.088"/> but what is unique to our era is made complex by the impression that similar preoccupations will always dominate the contemporary moment. </s><s n="s3.4;p20.20">Certain questions remain irresolvable as no author or age appears to have the solution, an unsettling implication that forces the reader to address the inadequacies of both man and language. </s><s n="s4.4;p20.20">The one thing seemingly set to change are the strategies used to manifest these concerns, as both Warner and Eliot show language to be as unstable and mutable as our concepts of identity, gender and religion. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3008d-ftnote.088"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Monteith, S. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1"><hi rend="underlined">Contemporary British and Irish Fiction</hi> (London: Hodder Headline, 2004) p.2 </s></p></note></div1></body><back><div1 type="bibliography"><head><hi rend="underlined bold">Bibliography</hi><ref target="BAWE_3008d-ftnote.089"/><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3008d-ftnote.089"><p> The word count for this essay is 3,296 words</p></note></head><div2 type="bibliography"><head rend="underlined bold">Primary Texts</head><p>Eliot, T.S. <hi rend="underlined">The Waste Land and Other Poems.</hi> (London: Faber and Faber, 1999.)</p><p>Warner, A. <hi rend="underlined">Movern Callar</hi> (London: Vintage, 1996.)</p></div2><div2 type="bibliography"><head rend="underlined bold">Secondary Texts</head><p>Agard, J. 'Me not no Oxford Don' (lecture handout)</p><p>Anderson, C, 'Listening to the Women Talk' in <hi rend="underlined">The Scottish Novel Since the Seventies. New Visions, Old Dreams</hi> ed. G. Wallace and R. Stevenson, (Edinburgh: Edinburgh University Press, 1994)</p><p>Barthes R. 'The Death of the Author' (1968) in <hi rend="underlined">The Norton Anthology of Theory and Criticism</hi> (London: Norton, 2001.) </p><p>Bertens, H. <hi rend="underlined">The Idea of the Postmodern</hi> (London: Routledge, 1995.)</p><p>Butler, J. 'Imitation and Gender Insubordination' 1991 in <hi rend="underlined">Literary Theory: An Anthology</hi> , edited </p><p>by J. Rivkin and M. Ryan (Oxford: Blackwell, 2002.)</p><p>Cixous 'Sorties' in <hi rend="underlined">Literary Theory: An Anthology</hi> , edited by J. Rivkin and M. Ryan (Oxford: Blackwell, 2002.)</p><p>Coote, S. <hi rend="underlined">The Waste Land</hi> (London: Penguin Books, 1985) </p><p>Foucalt, M "What is an Author?" trans Josue V.Haran in <hi rend="underlined">Textual Strategies: Perspectives in Post-Structuralist Criticism</hi> ed. J.Hancain 1979 (lecture handout)</p><p>Hawthorne, N. <hi rend="underlined">The Scarlet Letter</hi>, (London: Penguin, 1986)</p><p>Humm, M. <hi rend="underlined">A Reader's guide to Contemporary Feminist Literary Criticism</hi> (London: Harvester Wheatsheaf, 1994)</p><p>Irigaray, L. 'The power of Discourse and the Subordination of the Feminine' (1977) in <hi rend="underlined">Literary Theory: An Anthology</hi> , edited by J. Rivkin and M. Ryan (Oxford: Blackwell, 2002.)</p><p>Jain, M. A. <hi rend="underlined">Critical Reading of the Selected Poems of T.S. Eliot</hi> (Oxford: Oxford University Press, 1991)</p><p>Kirk, J. <hi rend="underlined">Twentieth-century writing and the British Working Class</hi> (Cardiff: University of Wales Press, 2003)</p><p>Lanbaum, R. 'New Modes of Characterization in The Waste Land' in <hi rend="underlined">Eliot in his Time</hi> ed A.Litz (Princeton: University Press Princeton, 1973) </p><p>March, C.L. <hi rend="underlined">Rewriting Scotland</hi> (Manchester: Manchester University Press, 2002)</p><p>McEwan, N. <hi rend="underlined">The Survival of the Novel: British Fiction in the Later Twentieth Century</hi> (London: Macmillan Press, 1981) </p><p>Mengham, R. <hi rend="underlined">An Introduction to Contemporary fiction. International Writing in English Since 1970 (</hi>Cambridge: Polity Press, 1999)</p><p>Mills, S. <hi rend="underlined">Feminist Stylistics</hi> (London: Routledge, 1995)</p><p>Monteith, S. <hi rend="underlined">Contemporary British and Irish Fiction</hi> (London: Hodder Headline, 2004)</p><p>Mulvey, L. 'Visual Pleasure and Narrative Cinema' in <hi rend="underlined">Literary Theory: An Anthology</hi> , edited by J. Rivkin and M. Ryan (Oxford: Blackwell, 2002.)</p><p>Murphy, R.E. ''It is impossible to say just what I mean': The Waste Land as Transcendent </p><p>Meaning' in T<hi rend="underlined">.S. Eliot. A Voice Descanting</hi> Ed S. Bagchee. (London: Macmillan, 1990)</p><p>Pope, R. <hi rend="underlined">The English Studies Book.</hi> (London: Routledge, 2001.)</p><p>Showalter, E. in 'The rise of gender' in <hi rend="underlined">Speaking of Gender</hi> Ed E. Showalter, (London: Routledge, 1989)</p><p>Sassure, F. 'Course in General Linguistics' in <hi rend="underlined">Literary Theory: An Anthology</hi> , edited by J. </p><p>Rivkin and M. Ryan (Oxford: Blackwell, 2002.)</p><p>Tobain,D.N <hi rend="underlined">The Presence of the Past</hi>. <hi rend="underlined">T.S. Eliot's Victorian Inheritance</hi> (Michigan: UMI Research Press, 1987) </p><p>Wallace,G. <hi rend="underlined">The Scottish Novel Since the Seventies. New Visions, Old Dreams</hi> (Edinburgh: Edinburgh University Press, 1994)</p></div2></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
