<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_3008i" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>'Writers that were part of that period of experimentation that is often termed "Modernism" seem to have lost faith in narrative. Instead of telling interesting stories, they</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">Language used in quote: <foreign id="English">English</foreign></note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">3</p><p n="date">2005-03</p><p n="module title">Modern Lit. core 1900-1955</p><p n="module code">U67024</p><p n="genre family">Essay</p><p n="discipline">English</p><p n="disciplinary group">AH</p><p n="grade">D</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">3244</p><p n="number of s-units">128</p><p n="number of p">20</p><p n="number of tables">0</p><p n="number of figures">0</p><p n="number of block quotes">6</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">0</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">0</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">25.3</p><p n="average s-units per p">6.4</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">f</p><p n="year of birth">1983</p><p n="first language">English</p><p n="education">UKa</p><p n="course">BA English Studies</p><p n="student ID">3008</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><titlePart rend="bold"><name type="student name"/><name type="student ID"/></titlePart><titlePart rend="underlined bold">U67024 Modern Literature Core. </titlePart><docTitle><titlePart rend="underlined bold">4. 'Writers that were part of that period of experimentation that is often termed "Modernism" seem to have lost faith in narrative. Instead of telling interesting stories, they preferred to capture a mood or create a complex character.' Do you agree? Discuss with reference to at least two texts on the course. </titlePart></docTitle></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="section"><p n="p1.20"><s n="s1.5;p1.20">Murphy describes <hi rend="italic">The Waste Land</hi> as a; 'masterful stroke, the deconstruction of literature for the sake of reconstructing it in the image of the Modern Age." </s><ref target="BAWE_3008i-ftnote.001"/><s n="s2.5;p1.20">Although radical and experimental in his approach to narration, the degree to which Eliot has lost faith in its necessity is debatable. </s><s n="s3.5;p1.20">Character and mood are central in the poem as are they in Conrad's <hi rend="italic">Heart of Darkness</hi>, but the extent to which they replace narrative is contestable, as both Eliot and Conrad often rely on structure to create mood and character. </s><s n="s4.5;p1.20">Establishing a definitive notion of what constitutes narrative is also problematic, as it can often be seen as a component of form, which makes it imperative to examine the structure employed in each work. </s><s n="s5.5;p1.20">The construction and definition of narrative differed in each writer's period, making it like mood and character, a concept that is characterised by indeterminacy. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3008i-ftnote.001"><p n="pn1.2"><s n="s1.1;pn1.2">Murphy, R.E. ''It is impossible to say just what I mean': The Waste Land as Transcendent </s></p><p n="pn2.2"><s n="s1.3;pn2.2">Meaning' in T <hi rend="underlined">.S. Eliot.</hi> </s><s n="s2.3;pn2.2"><hi rend="underlined">A Voice Descanting</hi> Ed S. Bagchee. </s><s n="s3.3;pn2.2">(London: Macmillan, 1990)P57 </s></p></note><p n="p2.20"><s n="s1.7;p2.20">Ostensibly, repeated metaphoric and literal emphasis on journeying suggests the <hi rend="italic">Heart of Darkness</hi> will employ a traditionally sequential narrative; 'Watching the coast as it slips by the ship is like thinking about an enigma. </s><s n="s2.7;p2.20">There it is before you-smiling, frowning, inviting." </s><ref target="BAWE_3008i-ftnote.002"/><s n="s3.7;p2.20">Progressive, present tense dynamic verbs create an immediacy and insistence that move both the reader and boat forward, providing a superficial impression of linearity. </s><s n="s4.7;p2.20">Temporal elasticity complicates this as Marlow continually moves between the past and present tense.<ref target="BAWE_3008i-ftnote.003"/> By superimposing present day awareness on reminiscence, the narrative is able to realistically mirror the flow of cerebral consciousness, as it too is subject to disruption and works by associative rather than linear logic. </s><s n="s5.7;p2.20">Recurrent digressions, pauses and reflections punctuate Marlow's meditative introspection, creating both vocal credibility and a discontinuous narrative. </s><s n="s6.7;p2.20">Preventing the interior monologue from advancing in a strictly chronological manner raises questions about the nature of progression; one of the novel's key tropes. </s><s n="s7.7;p2.20">Narrative is far from defunct in the novel as it often used to fortify thematic preoccupations, leading me to agree with Brooks that Conrad; </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3008i-ftnote.002"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.3;pn1.1">Conrad, J. </s><s n="s2.3;pn1.1"><hi rend="underlined">Heart Of Darkness</hi>. </s><s n="s3.3;pn1.1">(London: Penguin Books, 1994)p.19 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3008i-ftnote.003"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">For an example see; 'You know I am not particularly tender; I've had to strike and fend off.' (Ibid.,p.23) </s></p></note><quote lang="English">Poses in an exemplary way central questions about the shape and epistemology of narrative. It displays an acute self-consciousness about the organising features of traditional narrative, working with them still, but suspiciously. <ref target="BAWE_3008i-ftnote.004"/></quote><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3008i-ftnote.004"><p n="pn1.2"><s n="s1.2;pn1.2">Brooks, P. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.2">'An unreadable report: Conrad's Heart of Darkness' in <hi rend="underlined">Joseph Conrad:</hi> </s></p><p n="pn2.2"><s n="s1.1;pn2.2"><hi rend="underlined">Contemporary Critical Essays</hi> ed E.Jordan, (London: Macmillan, 1996)p.67 </s></p></note><p n="p3.20"><s n="s1.8;p3.20">Conrad's innovative use of narrative is far from traditional as the novel is comprised of a series of framed narratives that lack exclusive confines. </s><s n="s2.8;p3.20">Juxtaposing multiple vantage points engenders an aura of confusion. </s><s n="s3.8;p3.20">The river image, like the narrative, parallels motifs such as disorientation; 'you lose your way on that river as you would in a desert, and butted all day long against shoals, trying to find the channel." </s><ref target="BAWE_3008i-ftnote.005"/><s n="s4.8;p3.20">Narrative therefore operates on both a symbolic and structural level, as the emblematic layers generated by using structure to mirror content, enriches certain moods. </s><s n="s5.8;p3.20">Lothe's belief that there is a; 'remarkably productive interplay of narrative method and thematics,'<ref target="BAWE_3008i-ftnote.006"/> can be supported by Conrad's confusion of time and tense, as it creates the impression of a cyclic narrative. </s><s n="s6.8;p3.20">Culminating where it originates in both location and speaker makes the reader question how far the narrative actually progresses, thus highlighting the illusory nature of what Conrad's society deemed progression. </s><s n="s7.8;p3.20">Resisting linearity utilizes structure to depict the intrinsic paralysis and stagnation inherent in an interminable journey, whilst demonstrating the interdependence of form and content.<ref target="BAWE_3008i-ftnote.007"/> Recurrent fog imagery employs pathetic fallacy to fortify this impression of impenetrability and immobilization, as it makes the crew feel as; 'if we had been buried miles deep in a heap of cotton-wool. </s><s n="s8.8;p3.20">It felt like it too-choking, warm, stifling.' <ref target="BAWE_3008i-ftnote.008"/><ref target="BAWE_3008i-ftnote.009"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3008i-ftnote.005"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Conrad, Op.Cit., p.48 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3008i-ftnote.006"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Lothe, J. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1"><hi rend="underlined">Conrad's Narrative Method</hi> (Oxford: Oxford University Press, 1991) p.296 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3008i-ftnote.007"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.4;pn1.1">Like the anonymous narrator, the reader is only taken into another world and time figuratively, in reality we do not move, it is an aural and sensory journey alone. </s><s n="s2.4;pn1.1">This implies that there is no need to travel to find the heart of darkness; it is present from the outset; 'The air was dark above Gravesend.. condensed into a mournful gloom, brooding motionless over the biggest, and the greatest town on earth.' (Conrad, Op.Cit.,p.5) </s><s n="s3.4;pn1.1">This tangible ironic cynicism and the perceived lack of narrative progression, implies that the; 'dark places on earth'(Ibid.,p.7) not are not confined to Africa but are present in contemporary London society. </s><s n="s4.4;pn1.1">The enveloping narrative therefore draws Africa around Europe unsettling and complicating accepted binaries of such as primitive and civilized as discussed later. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3008i-ftnote.008"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid., p.62 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3008i-ftnote.009"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Such images of reversion and decay create a pessimistic mood that support Watt's claim that; 'Marlow has illuminated the haze which hangs like a pall over the society.' (Watt, I 'Impressionism and Symbolism in Heart of Darkness' in <hi rend="underlined">Joseph Conrad: A Commemoration</hi> ed N. Sherry (London: Macmillan Press, 1979)p.48) </s></p></note><p n="p4.20"><s n="s1.15;p4.20">By refusing to deploy a conclusive culmination, Conrad, like Eliot to an extent, uses structural unpredictability to capture the unrest of an age suffused by uncertainty. </s><s n="s2.15;p4.20">Scientific progression and the growth of industry led to an increased focus on the material, disturbing established notions of morality while engendering religious doubt. </s><s n="s3.15;p4.20">Omitting a categorical ending could be seen as a rejection of the traditional story form. </s><s n="s4.15;p4.20">Although structural experimentation allows Conrad to create a new type of narrative, it does not dismantle its importance and purpose; conversely it seems to foreground the necessity of narrative, almost restoring our faith in the need for form. </s><s n="s5.15;p4.20">The light we expect brought to darkness is denied and contradictions remain unresolved in order to focus our attention on what is absent; 'The inner truth is hidden-luckily, luckily.'<ref target="BAWE_3008i-ftnote.010"/>, <ref target="BAWE_3008i-ftnote.011"/> Like Marlow we yearn to hear Kurtz speak but he never assumes the position of narrator. </s><s n="s6.15;p4.20">His voice is relayed through disjointed and vague fragments of reported speech that offer none of the explanations we desire; 'Live rightly, die, die...." </s><ref target="BAWE_3008i-ftnote.012"/><s n="s7.15;p4.20">Exposing one considered a; 'prodigy..an emissary of pity, and science, and progress,'<ref target="BAWE_3008i-ftnote.013"/> as a; 'pitiful dupiter,'<ref target="BAWE_3008i-ftnote.014"/> enables the reader to truly share Marlow's frustration thus making dissatisfaction a palpable force; Marlow's tangible disillusionment is that of the age. </s><s n="s8.15;p4.20">Mood, narrative structure and character can therefore be seen as interdependent and interweaving, as they are often made more efficacious by intersecting. </s><s n="s9.15;p4.20">Kurtz is a highly complex character who simultaneously functions as an intriguing example of humanity and structural core. </s><s n="s10.15;p4.20">Like his legend, Kurtz is an empty façade, the epitomic hollow that is the missing formal closure craved by the reader and Marlow. </s><s n="s11.15;p4.20">Both are enigmatic, elusive and magnetic; they draw us forward but do not exist; 'He was just a word to me.. </s><s n="s12.15;p4.20">Do you see him? </s><s n="s13.15;p4.20">Do you see the story? </s><s n="s14.15;p4.20">Do you see anything?" </s><ref target="BAWE_3008i-ftnote.015"/><s n="s15.15;p4.20">Narrative and structure therefore remain key components of the novel. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3008i-ftnote.010"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Conrad, Op.Cit., p.49 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3008i-ftnote.011"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Kurtz's relationship with Marlow parallels that of Conrad and the reader; both deny us meaning in order to force us to create our own. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3008i-ftnote.012"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid., p.99 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3008i-ftnote.013"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid., p.36 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3008i-ftnote.014"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid., p.110 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3008i-ftnote.015"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid.,p.39 </s></p></note><p n="p5.20"><s n="s1.5;p5.20">Modernist texts provide intellectual engagement by resisting passive reading; challenging the reader to decipher abstruse imagery and concealed inferences allows them to become a co-creator of meaning. </s><s n="s2.5;p5.20">The narrative continually forces the reader to re-asses their opinions, allowing them to undergo a journey into the self. </s><s n="s3.5;p5.20">Conrad's preoccupation with penetrating the psyche is revealed through repeated allusions to densely layered vegetation; 'The river side bushes were certainly very thick; but the undergrowth was evidently penetrable." </s><ref target="BAWE_3008i-ftnote.016"/><s n="s4.5;p5.20">Whether we should enter the metonymic 'undergrowth' that is the mind, is made questionable by a narrative structure that purposefully penetrates then withdraws. </s><s n="s5.5;p5.20">Marlow symbolically penetrates the self by literally infiltrating the jungle, but providentially retreats; </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3008i-ftnote.016"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid.,p.61 </s></p></note><quote lang="English">I avoided a vast artificial hole somebody had been digging on the slope.. I nearly fell into a very narrow ravine.. My purpose was to stroll into the shade for a moment. <ref target="BAWE_3008i-ftnote.017"/></quote><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3008i-ftnote.017"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid.,p.23 </s></p></note><p n="p6.20"><s n="s1.2;p6.20">Having been; 'permitted to draw back my hesitating foot,' <ref target="BAWE_3008i-ftnote.018"/><ref target="BAWE_3008i-ftnote.019"/> Marlow is salvaged from a similar fate to Kurtz by his augmented knowledge of humanity. </s><s n="s2.2;p6.20">Najder's opinion jars with the suggestion that Conrad focuses on exploring mind and character, as he believes; </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3008i-ftnote.018"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid.,p.101 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3008i-ftnote.019"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.3;pn1.1">Ironically narration in the novel could be seen as purposefully reversing as;'Going up that river was like travelling back to the earliest beginnings of the world.' (Ibid., p.48) </s><s n="s2.3;pn1.1">In both the novel and Conrad's society progression seems to lead to regression, which could be read as suggestive of a possible nostalgia for past security and optimism. </s><s n="s3.3;pn1.1">Having Marlow look to the past for insight and guidance may imply that society needs to re-vive past morals in order to prevent social degeneration. </s></p></note><quote lang="English">his heroes are not studies in character.., but types- he conceives them not as psychologically unique personalities, but as symptomatic cases. <ref target="BAWE_3008i-ftnote.020"/><ref target="BAWE_3008i-ftnote.021"/></quote><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3008i-ftnote.020"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Najder, Z, <hi rend="underlined">Conrad in Perspective: Essays on art and fidelity</hi>. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">(Cambridge University Press: Cambridge, 1997)P.191 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3008i-ftnote.021"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Guerard disagrees believing 'The personal narrative is unmistakeably authentic, which means it explores something truer, more fundamental, and distinctly less material: the night journey into the unconscious and confrontation of an entity within the self.' (Guerard, A.J, 'The Journey Within' 1958 in <hi rend="underlined">Conrad: 'Heart if Darkness', 'Nostromo' and 'Under Western Eyes'</hi> Ed. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">C.B. Cox (London: Macmillan Press, 1981)p.53) </s></p></note><p n="p7.20"><s n="s1.2;p7.20">Reading Kurtz as a Faustian warning regarding the corruptive power of ambition supports this evaluation as he is both literally and figuratively consumed by hubris, reduced to a; 'cage of ribs all astir." </s><ref target="BAWE_3008i-ftnote.022"/><s n="s2.2;p7.20">Kurtz's physical starvation emulates that of his soul, as his fanatical materialism has eroded his sense of humanity and morality leaving him; 'like a vapour exhaled by the earth.' <ref target="BAWE_3008i-ftnote.023"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3008i-ftnote.022"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Conrad, Op.Cit., p.85 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3008i-ftnote.023"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid.,p.93 </s></p></note><p n="p8.20"><s n="s1.4;p8.20">Conversely, Curle believes Conrad's figures are; 'rounded out with extraordinary fullness,'<ref target="BAWE_3008i-ftnote.024"/> but much evidence contradicts this; they are often purposefully ambiguous and incomplete, emblematic of moods and ideas. </s><s n="s2.4;p8.20">I am therefore increasingly inclined to support Najder's argument that Conrad uses characters to; 'focus our attention on problems rather than personalities." </s><ref target="BAWE_3008i-ftnote.025"/><s n="s3.4;p8.20">Crawling, bald and enervated, Kurtz becomes pitifully dependant, explicitly infantilised as a demonstration of how capitalist progression can lead to human degeneration.<ref target="BAWE_3008i-ftnote.026"/> Conrad complicates the binary between culture and civilization through Kurtz, as his desire for wealth and imperialist advancement results in a return to what is base and savage in man; Kurtz becomes the; 'soul.. of sham distinction, of all the appearances of success and power." </s><ref target="BAWE_3008i-ftnote.027"/><s n="s4.4;p8.20">Contrastive opposites create paradoxical images of evolution and success that force the reader to confront the contradictions of imperialism; </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3008i-ftnote.024"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Curle, R. <hi rend="underlined">Joseph Conrad and His Characters</hi>. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">(London: Heinemann, 1957) p.13 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3008i-ftnote.025"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Najder, op.cit., p.191 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3008i-ftnote.026"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Yet, his destructive greed continues to resist satiety and cessation; 'I saw him open his mouth wide..as though he had wanted to swallow all the air.'(Conrad, Op.Cit., p.105) </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3008i-ftnote.027"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid., p.98 </s></p></note><quote lang="English">They were conquerors, and for that you want only brute force..your strength is just an accident arising from the weakness of others.. The conquest of the earth mostly means the taking it away from those who have a different complexion. <ref target="BAWE_3008i-ftnote.028"/><ref target="BAWE_3008i-ftnote.029"/></quote><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3008i-ftnote.028"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid., p.10 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3008i-ftnote.029"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.5;pn1.1">Conrad blurs cultural distinctions by bestowing the natives with recognisable qualities such as despondency and despair that allow the reader to identify with them; 'They were dying slowly.. </s><s n="s2.5;pn1.1">They were not enemies, they were not criminals, they were nothing earthly now,-nothing but black shadows of disease and starvation.' (Ibid.,p.24) </s><s n="s3.5;pn1.1">The contrastive other against which we define ourselves is revealed to be disturbingly similar. </s><s n="s4.5;pn1.1">This can lead to both a personal and national identity crisis, as the savage is no longer a divergent being who embodies all that we are not. </s><s n="s5.5;pn1.1">Eliot too effectively depicts the problems engendered by an unstable concept of identity as discussed later. </s></p></note><p n="p9.20"><s n="s1.1;p9.20">The cyclic narrative structure and evocations of regression fortify the suggestion that progress actually leads to demise if it incites economical, cultural and geographical violation. </s></p><p n="p10.20"><s n="s1.10;p10.20">Confusing dichotomies permeate the text. </s><s n="s2.10;p10.20">New and experimental symbolic binaries unsettle the reader's expectations, making them question the degree to which they accept certain hegemonic ideologies. </s><s n="s3.10;p10.20">Black is traditionally connoted to evil, but here explicitly white characters use violent, primitive methods to tame the dark natives and jungle. </s><s n="s4.10;p10.20">The symbolic association of white, like the white people, is corrupted.<ref target="BAWE_3008i-ftnote.030"/> The chief accountant is sheathed in white,<ref target="BAWE_3008i-ftnote.031"/> blinding the vision of those around in order to conceal the metaphoric darkness of his monetary greed. </s><s n="s5.10;p10.20">Conventionally connoted to purity, ivory ironically corrupts men by enticing them to build wealth instead of civilization. </s><s n="s6.10;p10.20">Kurtz, like ivory becomes polluted; ''ivory' rang in the air...you would think they were praying to it. </s><s n="s7.10;p10.20">A taint.. blew through it all, like a whiff from some corpse." </s><ref target="BAWE_3008i-ftnote.032"/><s n="s8.10;p10.20">Whiteness is further manipulated by being associated with death, as Kurtz in his skeletal state is an; 'animated image of death carved out of ivory.' </s><s n="s9.10;p10.20">The image of white bones evokes notions of fossils, thus implying that humanity faces moral extinction if ethical frameworks continue to be scarified to avarice. </s><s n="s10.10;p10.20">Conrad again reveals an admirable ability to capture mood and character, yet remains dependent on narrative to do so. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3008i-ftnote.030"><p n="pn1.2"><s n="s1.2;pn1.2">Brooks' argument that the narrative operates with; 'constant references to the inadequacy of the inherited orders of meaning,' (Brooks, P. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.2">'An unreadable report: Conrad's Heart of Darkness' in <hi rend="underlined">Joseph Conrad:</hi> </s></p><p n="pn2.2"><s n="s1.1;pn2.2"><hi rend="underlined">Contemporary Critical Essays</hi> ed E.Jordan, (London: Macmillan, 1996.) p.67) is strengthened by this. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3008i-ftnote.031"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">See 'I met a white man.. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">I saw..white cuffs, a light alpaca jacket, snowy trousers, a clear necktie, and varnished boots.' (Conrad, Op.Cit., p. 25) </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3008i-ftnote.032"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid., p.92 </s></p></note><p n="p11.20"><s n="s1.14;p11.20">In 'The Game of Chess,' Eliot too successfully demonstrates that the creation of mood and complex character need not be at the expense of telling an interesting story. </s><s n="s2.14;p11.20">The reader becomes drawn into the fascinating world created through the characters presented. </s><s n="s3.14;p11.20">Ornate, decorative language generates an artificiality that exposes the essential emptiness of modern life. </s><s n="s4.14;p11.20">The woman is; 'troubled, confused and drowned the sense in orders,' <ref target="BAWE_3008i-ftnote.033"/> as too is the reader, lost in the convoluted syntax, enjambment and sparse punctuation used to illustrate her claustrophobic hysteria. </s><s n="s5.14;p11.20">Characters in the poem often appear imprisoned in their minds, doomed to continual misunderstanding in being unable to use language effectively. </s><s n="s6.14;p11.20">The omission of inverted commas in the assumed man's responses and absent question mark in; 'Speak to me. </s><s n="s7.14;p11.20">Why do you never speak,'<ref target="BAWE_3008i-ftnote.034"/> suggests that we overhear only his thoughts. </s><s n="s8.14;p11.20">Accustomed to the woman's habitual questioning, he sees no point in replying. </s><s n="s9.14;p11.20">His flippant indifference reveals an unsettling lack of communication between the sexes. </s><s n="s10.14;p11.20">Much is deliberately and literally unsaid, making suggestibility as powerful here as it is in the novel. </s><s n="s11.14;p11.20">Character seems to not only replace the need for narrative but also mood on occasion. </s><s n="s12.14;p11.20">Even when seemingly united, characters remain alienated. </s><s n="s13.14;p11.20">Alternate rhyming couplets provide a surface impression of harmony between the typist and clerk, but as the rhyme's mechanical predictability becomes apparent, an impression of monotonous apathy is created. </s><s n="s14.14;p11.20">'Hardly aware of her departed lover',<ref target="BAWE_3008i-ftnote.035"/> reinforces the distance between them; they are physically one but emotionally disconnected and isolated. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3008i-ftnote.033"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.3;pn1.1">Eliot, T.S.. </s><s rend="underlined" n="s2.3;pn1.1">The Waste Land and Other Poems. </s><s n="s3.3;pn1.1">(London: Faber and Faber, 1999.) p.26, l.88-9 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3008i-ftnote.034"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid.,p.27, l.112 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3008i-ftnote.035"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid., p.32 l.250 </s></p></note><p n="p12.20"><s n="s1.6;p12.20">Unlike Conrad, Eliot severs the conventional unity between plot and character by depicting fragmentary snatches of individuals that demonstrate how narrative is no longer a necessary component of character creation.<ref target="BAWE_3008i-ftnote.036"/> Lanbaum views this as a; 'reaction against the Nineteenth century belief in the individual as the one reality you could be sure of,'<ref target="BAWE_3008i-ftnote.037"/> which may be why no stable identity exists in <hi rend="italic">The Waste Land</hi>. </s><s n="s2.6;p12.20">Characters are mainly nameless and faceless, as unsure of themselves as we are of them. </s><s n="s3.6;p12.20">Differing concepts of identity were emerging during the period, which may be why writers resorted to new and innovative modes of characterization. </s><s n="s4.6;p12.20">No central voice dominates narration; continual changes in pronoun and tense leave the reader doubting each character's gender, nationality and perspective. </s><s n="s5.6;p12.20">Hetroglossic pollyvocality and dislocated vocalization ensures that mood, like character is subject to abrupt and instantaneous change. </s><s n="s6.6;p12.20">Jain believes; </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3008i-ftnote.036"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.5;pn1.1">Character, like mood, is essentially transitory, which leads us to question whether they need narrative and structure to exist. </s><s n="s2.5;pn1.1">The very existence of character here is open to contention as many are merely fragmented voices, which could be read as Eliot having lost faith in not only narrative but character, as much of the poem centers on an implied loss of faith in humanity. </s><s n="s3.5;pn1.1">Conrad is comparatively traditional in his use of narrative, employing a more realistic depiction of character by presenting figures whose behaviour is subject to economic and political pressure. </s><s n="s4.5;pn1.1">While less textually subversive Conrad is not intellectually so; although less reliant on metaphor and ambiguity, he does not avoid challenging the reader to question his figures. </s><s n="s5.5;pn1.1">To an extent we can see why Conrad is often deemed as being on the cusp of Modernism. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3008i-ftnote.037"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Lanbaum, R. 'New Modes of Characterization in The Waste Land' <hi rend="underlined">Eliot in his Time</hi> Ed A.Litz (Princeton: University Press Princeton, 1973) p.110 </s></p></note><quote lang="English">Eliot perceived the divisions... of consciousness... not merely as aberrations of the individual psyche but as...resulting from the historical and cultural circumstances of his time. <ref target="BAWE_3008i-ftnote.038"/></quote><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3008i-ftnote.038"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Jain, M. A. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1"><hi rend="underlined">Critical Reading of the Selected Poems of T.S. Eliot</hi> (Oxford: Oxford University Press, 1991)Pvi </s></p></note><p n="p13.20"><s n="s1.1;p13.20">The infiltration of foreign languages supports this by creating a sense of disorientating displacement that reflects the absence of European geographical stability. </s></p><p n="p14.20"><s n="s1.3;p14.20">Ironically, the more languages and voices used in the poem, the less understanding seems to exist. </s><s n="s2.3;p14.20">Discontinuous, depersonalised voices often merge, as dialogue, monologue and fragmented streams of consciousness coexist confusingly. </s><s n="s3.3;p14.20">Language appears to have become a barrier that prevents communication<ref target="BAWE_3008i-ftnote.039"/>; </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3008i-ftnote.039"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.6;pn1.1">Structuralist theory supports the notion that language cannot convey meaning. </s><s n="s2.6;pn1.1">Saussure asserts; 'A linguistic system is a series of differences of sound combined with a series of differences of ideas,'(Sassure, F. </s><s n="s3.6;pn1.1">'Course in General Linguistics' in <hi rend="underlined">Literary Theory: An Anthology</hi> , edited by J. Rivkin and M. Ryan (Oxford: Blackwell, 2002.) p.88) </s><s n="s4.6;pn1.1">If the perceptual image engendered by each signifier is different to each individual reader, then we can never truly communicate with accuracy. </s><s n="s5.6;pn1.1">As in many of the relationships depicted, verbal interaction appears pointless, as ascertaining a definitive sense of what someone else means through their language alone seems impossible. </s><s n="s6.6;pn1.1">Language can therefore be deemed incompetent to an extent. </s></p></note><quote lang="English">I could not Speak, and my eyes failed, I was neither Living nor dead, and I knew nothing. <ref target="BAWE_3008i-ftnote.040"/></quote><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3008i-ftnote.040"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Eliot., op.cit., p.24 l.39-40 </s></p></note><p n="p15.20"><s n="s1.4;p15.20">Language, like narrative seems inadequate and defunct, as neither has the power convey the complex workings of the human mind. </s><s n="s2.4;p15.20">The omission of explanatory connections between images may be a method of representing the processes of imagination,<ref target="BAWE_3008i-ftnote.041"/> making the poem, like the novel, a journey into the self. </s><s n="s3.4;p15.20">It could be argued that because certain inexpressible emotions are fundamentally vague, they can only be realistically depicted through obscure methods such as imagery. </s><s n="s4.4;p15.20">Eliot can therefore be seen as generating a new way to communicate, using mood and image in place of narrative. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3008i-ftnote.041"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.3;pn1.1">In accepting such an interpretation, Williams' claim that Eliot's; 'logic of the imagination,' exposed a; 'controlling art behind apparent fragmentation,'(Williams, H. </s><s n="s2.3;pn1.1"><hi rend="underlined">T.S. Eliot The Waste Land</hi> (London: Edward Arnold, 1973) p.17) gains credibility, as in order to realistically depict the random workings of the imagination, a purposefully fragmented structure must be used. </s><s n="s3.3;pn1.1">This technique is not dissimilar to that employed by Conrad in his creation of Marlow's disjointed narrative meditation. </s></p></note><p n="p16.20"><s n="s1.8;p16.20">Powerful visual images become a substitute for a language that is unable to articulate the horror of a future where hope is nonexistent; 'He wept. </s><s n="s2.8;p16.20">He promised "a new start."'<ref target="BAWE_3008i-ftnote.042"/> The response to the unanswerable question; 'Who is the third who walks always beside you?" </s><ref target="BAWE_3008i-ftnote.043"/><s n="s3.8;p16.20">is formed by a figurative image of the grim reaper; 'There is always another one walking beside you/ Gliding wrapt in a brown mantle, hooded." </s><ref target="BAWE_3008i-ftnote.044"/><s n="s4.8;p16.20">Infinite death appears to replace the promise of eternal life. </s><s n="s5.8;p16.20">The desert therefore becomes a metaphoric representation of a Godless world if we agree with Coote that; 'The landscapes are the landscapes of the mind." </s><ref target="BAWE_3008i-ftnote.045"/><s n="s6.8;p16.20">He goes on to argue the poem; 'ends with the narrator sitting amid the wreck of urban culture, threatened by madness and longing for the peace of God,'<ref target="BAWE_3008i-ftnote.046"/> but this becomes contestable if we believe the thunder offers a way forward. </s><s n="s7.8;p16.20">By leaving the decision to follow or reject its advice in the reader's hands, Eliot like Conrad refuses to provide a conclusive resolution. </s><s n="s8.8;p16.20">The sinister repetition of; 'London Bridge is falling down falling down,'<ref target="BAWE_3008i-ftnote.047"/> infers that man is destined to sink and fall continuously if he ignores this advice.<ref target="BAWE_3008i-ftnote.048"/> Like the novel, the poem lacks closure; ending without a full stop implies that there is no one solution to the problems presented. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3008i-ftnote.042"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Eliot, op.cit., p.34 l.298 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3008i-ftnote.043"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid., p.37 l.359 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3008i-ftnote.044"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid., p37 l.362-3 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3008i-ftnote.045"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Coote, S. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1"><hi rend="underlined">The Waste Land</hi> (London: Penguin books, 1985)p.53 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3008i-ftnote.046"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid.,p.79 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3008i-ftnote.047"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Eliot., op.cit., p.39 l. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">426 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3008i-ftnote.048"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.3;pn1.1">The repetitive ennui plaguing; 'crowds of people, walking round in a ring,' (Ibid., p.24, l.56) suggests there is no escape; without spiritual and structural advancement, there is no release from this torturous and perpetual psychological wasteland. </s><s n="s2.3;pn1.1">Entrapped in the eternal present, past and future become indecipherable. </s><s n="s3.3;pn1.1">April is the; 'cruelest month,' (Ibid., p.23 l.1) as the confusion between; 'memory and desire,' (Ibid., p.23, l.3) leaves the inhabitants of post-war Europe wishing for the merciful oblivion of a; 'forgetful snow.' (Ibid., p.23, l.6) </s></p></note><p n="p17.20"><s n="s1.10;p17.20">Seemingly having lost faith in narrative and language, Eliot is forced to experiment with other methods of creating meaning, hence an increased reliance on divergent literary techniques. </s><s n="s2.10;p17.20">Objective correlative and sensory manipulation become paramount in evoking elusive moods and states of mind. </s><s n="s3.10;p17.20">Auditory descriptions such as; 'drip drop drop drop drop,'<ref target="BAWE_3008i-ftnote.049"/> employ repeated harsh plosive phonemes in order to emulate the abrasive and hostile nature of the dystopian future presented. </s><s n="s4.10;p17.20">Drawing our focus to only the aural properties of water make it a physical sound alone, like the deluded traveler we can only hear it as; 'there is no water.' </s><s n="s5.10;p17.20">Tactile and olfactory images also employ sensory deception in order to blur the distinction between reality and illusion.<ref target="BAWE_3008i-ftnote.050"/> Nature is often made a metaphor for humanity; 'sunken' and 'limp,'<ref target="BAWE_3008i-ftnote.051"/> both are desperate for literal and spiritual regeneration. </s><s n="s6.10;p17.20">Topographical aridity and personification illustrates the unbearable thirst suffered by both man and nature in images such as the; 'Dead mountain mouth of carious teeth that cannot spit." </s><ref target="BAWE_3008i-ftnote.052"/><s n="s7.10;p17.20">De-familiarization also becomes an imperative replacement for narrative. </s><s n="s8.10;p17.20">Water, like whiteness in the <hi rend="italic">Heart of Darkness,</hi> becomes a paradox, connected to both sterility and fertility, as repeated depictions of polluted, dirty water manipulate its symbolic properties; 'The river sweats/ oil and tar." </s><ref target="BAWE_3008i-ftnote.053"/><s n="s9.10;p17.20">Explicitly perverting water's regenerative elements reflects the absent promise of salvation through eternal life. </s><s n="s10.10;p17.20">This fortifies the despondent mood engendered by images of false prophets and spiritual impotence that trap; 'hooded hordes swarming over endless plains, stumbling in cracked earth.' <ref target="BAWE_3008i-ftnote.054"/><ref target="BAWE_3008i-ftnote.055"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3008i-ftnote.049"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid.,p37 l.356 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3008i-ftnote.050"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Accumulated hallucinations such as; 'bats with baby faces,' (Ibid., p.37 l.379) enable the reader to become lost in the unnatural confusion between humanity and nature that taunts the traveler. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3008i-ftnote.051"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid., p.38 l.397 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3008i-ftnote.052"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid., p.36 l.339 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3008i-ftnote.053"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid., p.33 l.266-267 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3008i-ftnote.054"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid., p.37 l.368-70 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3008i-ftnote.055"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.3;pn1.1">Tobain can be used to support this argument; 'For Eliot, these visions of contemporary society are inseparable from the loss of faith. </s><s n="s2.3;pn1.1">Man no longer believes consequently his feelings and will are no longer ordered as they once were; they wither away.' (Tobain, D.N <hi rend="underlined">The Presence of the Past: T.S. Eliot's Victorian Inheritance</hi> (Michigan: UMI Research Press, 1987) (p.23)) </s><s n="s3.3;pn1.1">Resolutely refusing to adhere to a consistent form may be a deliberate rejection of the past, a method of demonstrating the inability of old forms to express unique concerns that are exclusive to a godless modern world. </s></p></note><p n="p18.20"><s n="s1.11;p18.20">Allusion becomes a dominant force in the poem as a metaphorical and literal; 'heap of broken images,'<ref target="BAWE_3008i-ftnote.056"/> takes the place of a traditional narrative. </s><s n="s2.11;p18.20">Cryptic cross-connections create a relational rather than sequential structure, as the significance of certain images only becomes apparent through their interaction with other allusions. </s><s n="s3.11;p18.20">The difficulty of deciphering complex allusive networks enables the reader to undergo a crisis of understanding that engenders a sense of humiliation. </s><s n="s4.11;p18.20">The overwhelming impossibility of understanding the allusive context of each image allows the reader to share the futility and failure plaguing the characters and age; 'We who were living are now dying/ with a little patience." </s><ref target="BAWE_3008i-ftnote.057"/><s n="s5.11;p18.20">Understanding the poem's mood is frequently more important than understanding its story. </s><s n="s6.11;p18.20">The absence of a conventional narrative structure often goes unnoticed, as mood proves a far more powerful method of conveying meaning. </s><s n="s7.11;p18.20">Stead's argument that; ''texture' was all-important and 'structure' only a shadow,' <ref target="BAWE_3008i-ftnote.058"/>can be used to support this. </s><s n="s8.11;p18.20">Superficially, the amalgamation of assorted metrical and rhythmical patterns eliminates an external impression of structural order. </s><s n="s9.11;p18.20">Form itself is paradoxical in the poem, as it appears simultaneously cyclical and disjointed. </s><s n="s10.11;p18.20">If the narrative cannot be concurrently processual and cyclic, then fusing these forms may be the ultimate rejection of structure; by arguing that they cancel each other out, narrative and structure cease to exist to an extent. </s><s n="s11.11;p18.20">But, the resultant assimilation of images without coherent, connective associations, generates an intentional chaos that becomes the poem's structure.<ref target="BAWE_3008i-ftnote.059"/> Although Eliot appears to have lost faith in the concept of narrative, the degree to which he truly rejects structure, is questionable. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3008i-ftnote.056"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Eliot, op.cit.,p23 l.22 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3008i-ftnote.057"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid., p.36, l.229-330 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3008i-ftnote.058"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Stead, C.K. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1"><hi rend="underlined">The New Poetic: Yeats to Eliot</hi> (London: Penguin books, 1969) p.156 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3008i-ftnote.059"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">The energy generated by this chaos jars with the poem's pervading sense of ennui, making it possible to argue that Eliot is striving to capture a moment of extreme potential and religious progression, as its focus on futility illustrates a desperate need for change. </s></p></note><p n="p19.20"><s n="s1.5;p19.20">Adopting a Cultural Materialist reading of the poem challenges Stead's opinion, as structure becomes vital if we believe it serves a representative purpose. </s><s n="s2.5;p19.20">The surface impression of structural absence can be seen as deliberate if Eliot, like Conrad uses form to mirror society.<ref target="BAWE_3008i-ftnote.060"/> The seemingly random compendium of literary and mythical allusions, may sever the once coherent, admired words of others in order to replicate the destruction of stability and tradition engendered by war. </s><s n="s3.5;p19.20">Abrupt syntactic shifts appear to convey the turbulence of an era characterized by sudden change and decaying social constancy. </s><s n="s4.5;p19.20">Fusing varied poetic forms may be demonstrative of the difficulty inherent in establishing the European unity craved by many. </s><s n="s5.5;p19.20">If so, Bradbury's argument gains credibility as he believes the poem's; 'ultimate strength' to be its; ''lack of 'purism', and its capacity to maintain a pragmatic and multi-directional momentum.'<ref target="BAWE_3008i-ftnote.061"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3008i-ftnote.060"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">The poem's rejection of order and boundary can be seen as reflecting the zeitgeist of a society engaged in a similar process. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1"><hi rend="italic">The Waste Land</hi> seems on occasion an expression of discomfort with what art called itself, as proceeding structural limitations were challenged and transcended by artists and writers who were attempting to render coherent forms to an incoherent world. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3008i-ftnote.061"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.3;pn1.1">Bradbury, M. </s><s n="s2.3;pn1.1"><hi rend="underlined">The Social Context of Modern English Literature</hi>. </s><s n="s3.3;pn1.1">(Oxford: Basil Blackwell, 1972)p.33 </s></p></note><p n="p20.20"><s n="s1.7;p20.20">How narrative is deployed and its significance inevitably differs between the texts, as each is the product of a divergent time and society, thus making it difficult to generalize regarding narrative function. </s><s n="s2.7;p20.20">Both writers pioneer variants on the traditional narrative form that enable them to articulate their own unique concerns. </s><s n="s3.7;p20.20">The extent to which this eliminates the necessity of narrative becomes questionable, as structure is what often allows them to do so with such success. </s><s n="s4.7;p20.20">Narrative is not eradicated but altered; it may no longer appear in a familiar and recognizable from but it still exists. </s><s n="s5.7;p20.20">Mood and complex character have not become an outright substitute for narrative but have become as structurally important. </s><s n="s6.7;p20.20">Ironically, they do not replace interesting stories; rather they enable the writer to tell them. </s><s n="s7.7;p20.20">Experimentation and progress is key in both literature and the Modern period; narrative seems to have become an evolutionary technique not a redundant one, leaving me inclined to agree with Guetti that; 'as the narrative develops it is redefined so as to deny the basic assumptions upon which it appears to be constructed.'<ref target="BAWE_3008i-ftnote.062"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3008i-ftnote.062"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Guetti, J 'The Failure of Imagination' 1965 in <hi rend="underlined">Conrad: 'Heart if Darkness', 'Nostromo' and 'Under Western Eyes'</hi> ed C.B. Cox (London: Macmillan Press, 1981)p.65 </s></p></note></div1></body><back><div1 type="bibliography"><head><hi rend="underlined bold">Bibliography</hi><ref target="BAWE_3008i-ftnote.063"/><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3008i-ftnote.063"><p> The word count for this essay is; 3,198words.</p></note></head><div2 type="bibliography"><head rend="underlined bold">Primary Texts</head><p>Conrad, J. <hi rend="underlined">Heart Of Darkness</hi>. (London: Penguin Books, 1994.)</p><p>Eliot, T.S.. <hi rend="underlined">The Waste Land and Other Poems.</hi> (London: Faber and Faber, 1999.)</p></div2><div2 type="bibliography"><head rend="underlined bold">Secondary texts</head><p>Bradbury, M. <hi rend="underlined">The Social Context of Modern English Literature</hi>. (Oxford: Basil Blackwell, 1972.)</p><p>Brooks, P. 'An unreadable report: Conrad's Heart of Darkness' in <hi rend="underlined">Joseph Conrad:</hi></p><p><hi rend="underlined">Contemporary Critical Essays</hi> ed E.Jordan, (London: Macmillan, 1996.)</p><p>Coote, S. <hi rend="underlined">The Waste Land</hi> (London: Penguin Books, 1985.) </p><p>Curle, R. <hi rend="underlined">Joseph Conrad and His Characters</hi>. (London: Heinemann, 1957.)</p><p>Guerard, A.J, 'The Journey Within' 1958 in <hi rend="underlined">Conrad: 'Heart if Darkness', 'Nostromo' and 'Under Western Eyes'</hi> Ed. C.B. Cox (London: Macmillan Press, 1981.)</p><p>Guetti, J 'The Failure of Imagination' 1965 in <hi rend="underlined">Conrad: 'Heart if Darkness', 'Nostromo' and 'Under Western Eyes'</hi> ed C.B. Cox (London: Macmillan Press, 1981.)</p><p>Jain, M. A. <hi rend="underlined">Critical Reading of the Selected Poems of T.S. Eliot</hi> (Oxford: Oxford University Press, 1991.)</p><p>Lanbaum, R. 'New Modes of Characterization in The Waste Land' in <hi rend="underlined">Eliot in his Time</hi> Ed. A.Litz (Princeton: University Press Princeton, 1973.) </p><p>Lothe, J. <hi rend="underlined">Conrad's Narrative Method</hi> (Oxford: Oxford University Press, 1991.)</p><p>Murphy, R.E. ''It is impossible to say just what I mean': The Waste Land as Transcendent </p><p>Meaning' in T<hi rend="underlined">.S. Eliot. A Voice Descanting</hi> Ed. S. Bagchee. (London: Macmillan, 1990.) </p><p>Najder, Z, <hi rend="underlined">Conrad in Perspective: Essays on art and fidelity</hi>. (Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 1997)</p><p>Sassure, F. 'Course in General Linguistics' in <hi rend="underlined">Literary Theory: An Anthology</hi> , Edited by J. </p><p>Rivkin and M. Ryan (Oxford: Blackwell, 2002.)</p><p>Stead, C.K. <hi rend="underlined">The New Poetic: Yeats to Eliot</hi> (London: Penguin Books, 1969) </p><p>Tobain, D.N <hi rend="underlined">The Presence of the Past: T.S. Eliot's Victorian Inheritance</hi> (Michigan: UMI Research Press, 1987) </p><p>Watt, I 'Impressionism and Symbolism in Heart of Darkness' in <hi rend="underlined">Joseph Conrad: A Commemoration</hi> Ed. N. Sherry (London: Macmillan Press, 1979)</p><p>Williams, H. <hi rend="underlined">T.S. Eliot The Waste Land</hi> (London: Edward Arnold, 1973) </p></div2></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
