<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_3008j" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Explore Shakespeare's handling of the conventions of tragedy in Othello, and their relationship to matters of politics and gender in the play</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">Language used in quote: <foreign id="English">English</foreign></note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">
Deleted manual line breaks for each line in the running text.
</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">1</p><p n="date">2003-NA</p><p n="module title">Texts, Problems and Approaches</p><p n="module code">M02306</p><p n="genre family">Essay</p><p n="discipline">English</p><p n="disciplinary group">AH</p><p n="grade">M</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">2237</p><p n="number of s-units">114</p><p n="number of p">23</p><p n="number of tables">0</p><p n="number of figures">0</p><p n="number of block quotes">8</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">0</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">0</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">19.6</p><p n="average s-units per p">5.0</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">f</p><p n="year of birth">1983</p><p n="first language">English</p><p n="education">UKa</p><p n="course">BA English Studies</p><p n="student ID">3008</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><titlePart rend="underlined bold">Module 2306 Texts, Problems and Approaches. </titlePart><titlePart><hi rend="underlined bold"><name type="student name"/>.</hi> <hi rend="underlined bold"><name type="student ID"/>. </hi></titlePart><docTitle><titlePart rend="underlined bold">Explore Shakespeare's handling of the conventions of tragedy in Othello, and their relationship to matters of politics and gender in the play. </titlePart></docTitle></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="section"><p n="p1.23"><s n="s1.7;p1.23"><hi rend="italic"> Othello</hi> is a prominent example of Renaissance tragedy as it simultaneously embodies and departs from the traditions of conventional tragedy. </s><s n="s2.7;p1.23">Cultural upheaval and political instability inevitably changed the climate and definition of tragedy. </s><s n="s3.7;p1.23">Theological speculation and the revival of epicureanism led to people being suspended between faith and reason. </s><s n="s4.7;p1.23">Such issues permeate <hi rend="italic">Othello</hi>. </s><s n="s5.7;p1.23">Dollimore argues that it portrays a 'social order which exploits people on grounds of race, gender and class." </s><ref target="BAWE_3008j-ftnote.001"/><s n="s6.7;p1.23">Sinfeild therefore implies that Iago is interpolated into his misogyny and racism as character's 'outlook is supported by their social context." </s><ref target="BAWE_3008j-ftnote.002"/><s n="s7.7;p1.23">Tension between tumultuous emotion and strict political formality is inherent within <hi rend="italic">Othello</hi>'s framework. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3008j-ftnote.001"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.3;pn1.1">Dollimore. </s><s n="s2.3;pn1.1">J, Ed. </s><s n="s3.3;pn1.1"><hi rend="underlined">Political Shakespeare- New essays in cultuaral materialism</hi>, (Manchester: Manchester University press, 1988)p.viii </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3008j-ftnote.002"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Sinfield, A. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">'Cultural Materialism, Othello, and the politics of plausibility' in <hi rend="underlined">Literary Theory: An Anthology</hi> , edited by J. Rivkin and M. Ryan (Oxford: Blackwell, 2002)p807 </s></p></note><p n="p2.23"><s n="s1.5;p2.23">New Historicism allows us examine the text within its genre. </s><s n="s2.5;p2.23">Unlike other Renaissance tragedies, such as Marlowe's Dr Faustus, <hi rend="italic">Othello</hi> betrays the influence of classical Greek tragedy rather than that of the medieval morality play. </s><s n="s3.5;p2.23">Ribner disagrees, viewing Othello as 'the conventional morality play hero." </s><ref target="BAWE_3008j-ftnote.003"/><s n="s4.5;p2.23">Shakespeare transcends the conventions of classical tragedy by discarding certain traditions such as the chorus and infiltrating new devices. </s><s n="s5.5;p2.23">Ribner believes; </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3008j-ftnote.003"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Ribner, I. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1"><hi rend="underlined">Patterns in Shakespearean Tragedy</hi> (London: Methuen, 1979)p.95 </s></p></note><quote lang="English"><hi rend="italic"> Othello</hi>, in its neatness and precision of construction, parallels more closely... what may be called the prototype of tragedy..., that of Adam in the garden of Eden.<ref target="BAWE_3008j-ftnote.004"/></quote><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3008j-ftnote.004"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid,.p.115 </s></p></note><p n="p3.23"><s n="s1.4;p3.23">Some view <hi rend="italic">Othello</hi> a poetic drama, but this seems unlikely as it exhibits the characteristics of Aristotelian tragedy. </s><s n="s2.4;p3.23">It has catharsis, anagorisis and evokes fear amongst the audience. </s><s n="s3.4;p3.23">Othello believes himself to be a tragic hero, having to face moral choice, fall from grace due to harmatia and redeem himself. </s><s n="s4.4;p3.23">Othello's melodramatic proclamations compare his suffering to that of Job and Tantalus; </s></p><quote lang="English"> ..they rained All kinds of..shames on my bare head Steeped me in poverty to the very lips. <ref target="BAWE_3008j-ftnote.005"/></quote><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3008j-ftnote.005"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Shakespeare, op.cit.,V.2. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">47-49 p.145 </s></p></note><p n="p4.23"><s n="s1.4;p4.23">Ribner believes that; 'Othello reflects the... pattern of the Christian soul ensnared by sin, but who through suffering and self-knowledge learns to overcome it." </s><ref target="BAWE_3008j-ftnote.006"/><s n="s2.4;p4.23">But, for Aristotle, the downfall of an evil protagonist is cathartic, not tragic. </s><s n="s3.4;p4.23">Shakespeare challenges this, oscillating the audience between hating and pitying Othello as he is an 'honourable murderer." </s><ref target="BAWE_3008j-ftnote.007"/><s n="s4.4;p4.23">Wine supports this, stating; </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3008j-ftnote.006"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid,.p.96 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3008j-ftnote.007"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Shakespeare, W. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1"><hi rend="underlined">Othello</hi>, Ed.Kenneth Muir (London: Penguin, 1996)V.2. .292, p177 </s></p></note><quote lang="English"> The character of Othello is a paradox ... this paradox divides critical opinion and calls in to question the play as a tragedy. <ref target="BAWE_3008j-ftnote.008"/></quote><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3008j-ftnote.008"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Wine, M.C. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1"><hi rend="underlined">Othello text and performance</hi> (London: Macmillan, 1988) p9 </s></p></note><p n="p5.23"><s n="s1.4;p5.23">As <hi rend="italic">Othello</hi> is primarily concerned with psychological and emotional complexity, I believe it to be a pioneering example of domestic tragedy and agree that it is; 'closer to the immediate world of his audience than that of any other of his tragedies." </s><ref target="BAWE_3008j-ftnote.009"/><s n="s2.4;p5.23">Because Othello is not a monarch, the range of tragedy is significantly diminished and only effects a few individuals. </s><s n="s3.4;p5.23"><hi rend="italic">Othello</hi> is a personal and private tragedy as Othello's nobility is destroyed, not the political state. </s><s n="s4.4;p5.23">As Shakespeare's shortest play, action is concentrated and Dubrow believes this to be; 'more effective since its compactness makes it more...vivid,'<ref target="BAWE_3008j-ftnote.010"/> as its fluid structure aids the play's performance dynamics. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3008j-ftnote.009"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ribner, op.cit p.p91 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3008j-ftnote.010"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Dubrow, H. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1"><hi rend="underlined">Genre</hi> (London: Methuen, 1982)p.49 </s></p></note><p n="p6.23"><s n="s1.6;p6.23">Subsidiary characters and events mirror the central dissension, heightening the emotional intensity, whilst the lack of effective subplot adds to the claustrophobic atmosphere. </s><s n="s2.6;p6.23">The opening senate scenes are deceptive as we are led to expect a political drama, but when the expedition is aborted the action turns in on itself. </s><s n="s3.6;p6.23">The storm is both a rhetorical and narrative device, acting as a literal symbol of imminent conflict and as a metaphor for violent and destructive jealousy. </s><s n="s4.6;p6.23">Audiences may have seen sexual jealousy an insufficient motive for tragedy as it traditionally dealt with what was divine, not animalistic in man. </s><s n="s5.6;p6.23">Yet, sexual passion is central to the tragedy of <hi rend="italic"> Antony and Cleopatra</hi> and Othello, like Mark-Antony is torn between his social and political responsibilities. </s><s n="s6.6;p6.23">Moral conflict between rationality and passion is central to the play's structure. </s></p><p n="p7.23"><s n="s1.6;p7.23">Political instability permeates the play, heightening the suspense and uncertainty thus creating an unsettled feeling. </s><s n="s2.6;p7.23">The omnipresent danger of war adds to the audience's accumulated anxieties. </s><s n="s3.6;p7.23">The binary forces of politics and love are juxtaposed in direct contention and the struggle for dominance between them establishes the central tension around which all else revolves. </s><s n="s4.6;p7.23">Othello promises to balance both, but love takes precedence over his military role despite his ironic promise to never allow 'light-winged toys of feathered cupids,'<ref target="BAWE_3008j-ftnote.011"/> 'corrupt and taint my business." </s><ref target="BAWE_3008j-ftnote.012"/><s n="s5.6;p7.23">Matheson draws attention to the blurred distinction between politics and love stating that; 'Othello prefers to conduct his political relationships in the older language of loyalty and loving service." </s><ref target="BAWE_3008j-ftnote.013"/><s n="s6.6;p7.23">This in turn makes his speech 'an interesting mix of political and sexual discourse' that reveal 'the politicised nature of 'love,''<ref target="BAWE_3008j-ftnote.014"/> as his political register helps elevate speeches concerning love; </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3008j-ftnote.011"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Shakespeare, op.cit.,i.3, 265-6, p71 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3008j-ftnote.012"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid.,i.3, 269, p71 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3008j-ftnote.013"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Matheson. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">M, 'Venetian culture and politics of Othello', in <hi rend="underlined">Shakespeare survey 48-Shakespeare and cultural exchange</hi> (Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 1995)p129 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3008j-ftnote.014"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid.,p130 </s></p></note><quote lang="English"> I have but an hour Of love, of worldly matters and direction To spend with thee.<ref target="BAWE_3008j-ftnote.015"/></quote><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3008j-ftnote.015"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Shakespeare, op.cit.,i.3, 296-9, p73 </s></p></note><p n="p8.23"><s n="s1.11;p8.23">State conflicts mirror those between characters. </s><s n="s2.11;p8.23">Conflicting reports of the Turkish army act as a metaphor for deception and betrayal on different levels; 'tis a pageant/ to keep us in false gaze." </s><ref target="BAWE_3008j-ftnote.016"/><s n="s3.11;p8.23">The political conflict between two cultures is internalised within Othello as he is torn between Christianity and his Islamic origins. </s><s n="s4.11;p8.23">There are opposing geographical and symbolic differences between Venice and Cyprus. </s><s n="s5.11;p8.23">Venice characterises civilised order and authority, whereas Cyprus represents dangerous passionate impulse, making Othello an outsider in Venice, but a powerful hero in Cyprus. </s><s n="s6.11;p8.23">Shakespeare questions the assumptions and politics upon which Elizabethan society was founded through his portrayal of the Venetian state. </s><s n="s7.11;p8.23">Both were supposedly colour blind, which makes the audience question whether is race a political issue. </s><s n="s8.11;p8.23">Dollimore supports this asserting that; 'no cultural practise is ever without political significance." </s><ref target="BAWE_3008j-ftnote.017"/><s n="s9.11;p8.23">In embodying earlier insults, Othello tragically loses his battle against his interpolated role as a black barbarian, describing himself as a 'base Indian." </s><ref target="BAWE_3008j-ftnote.018"/><s n="s10.11;p8.23">Sinfeild believes that 'the civilised and the barbaric are not very different.. maintaining the distinction is a constant ideological task.'<ref target="BAWE_3008j-ftnote.019"/><hi rend="italic">Othello</hi> marks a departure from traditional tragedies, openly exploring xenophobia and racial stereotypes by having a heroic, black central protagonist. </s><s n="s11.11;p8.23">Contradictory racial tensions overshadow political and domestic action. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3008j-ftnote.016"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Shakespeare, op.cit.,i.3, 18-19, p63 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3008j-ftnote.017"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Dollimore, op.cit., p.viii </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3008j-ftnote.018"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Shakespeare, op.cit., V.2, 343, p.179 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3008j-ftnote.019"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Sinfield, op.cit.,p.808 </s></p></note><p n="p9.23"><s n="s1.1;p9.23">Tennenhouse believes politics and gender are inter-linked; </s></p><quote lang="English"> Shakespeare's tragedies invariably show us how a separation of politics and sexuality into different systems... produces political disorder and the breakdown of relationships..if such a separation were actually possible. <ref target="BAWE_3008j-ftnote.020"/></quote><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3008j-ftnote.020"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Tennenhouse, L. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1"><hi rend="underlined">Power on display-The politics of Shakespeare's Genres</hi> (London: Methuen, 1986) p.124 </s></p></note><p n="p10.23"><s n="s1.5;p10.23">Shakespeare's ambivalence towards women leads me to agree with Eagleton's that; 'The woman is a constantly travestied text, perpetually open to misreading." </s><ref target="BAWE_3008j-ftnote.021"/><s n="s2.5;p10.23">Desdemona's duality makes her a problematic figure as she is both 'half the wooer'<ref target="BAWE_3008j-ftnote.022"/> and a passive victim. </s><s n="s3.5;p10.23">Tennenhouse interprets her bold rebellion against Brabantio as a 'Jacobean assault on monarchy as she assumes authority over her body...against the will of the patriarch." </s><ref target="BAWE_3008j-ftnote.023"/><s n="s4.5;p10.23">But to what degree is she rebelling against men when Brabatio's ownership is simply transferred to Othello? </s><s n="s5.5;p10.23">The cost of choosing her own partner, is her identity and the independence that allowed her to do so. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3008j-ftnote.021"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.3;pn1.1">Eagleton, T. </s><s n="s2.3;pn1.1"><hi rend="underlined">William Shakespeare</hi> (Oxford: Basil Blackwell. </s><s n="s3.3;pn1.1">1987) p.68 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3008j-ftnote.022"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Shakespeare, op.cit., i.3 175 p. 68 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3008j-ftnote.023"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Tennenhouse, op.cit., p.127 </s></p></note><p n="p11.23"><s n="s1.8;p11.23">Tragedy is inherent in their relationship. </s><s n="s2.8;p11.23">Othello's discourse reveals that he sees her as a possession; 'use Desdemona well." </s><ref target="BAWE_3008j-ftnote.024"/><s n="s3.8;p11.23">Yet, describing her as 'fair warrior'<ref target="BAWE_3008j-ftnote.025"/> is the ultimate accolade as he recognises her equality and strength. </s><s n="s4.8;p11.23">'Our general's wife is/ now the general'<ref target="BAWE_3008j-ftnote.026"/> alludes to Desdemona's power over Othello and provides an insight into the play's sexual politics. </s><s n="s5.8;p11.23">Matheson believes that; 'the domestic sphere is charged.. with displaced energies of state politics which politicises the language of this sphere." </s><ref target="BAWE_3008j-ftnote.027"/><s n="s6.8;p11.23">Desdemona's 'grace and power'<ref target="BAWE_3008j-ftnote.028"/> to move Othello infers that she is the dominant partner and uses the depth of his infatuation to manipulate him. </s><s n="s7.8;p11.23">Othello's race and 'alien status'<ref target="BAWE_3008j-ftnote.029"/> make him a deeply vulnerable outsider who is abused throughout. </s><s n="s8.8;p11.23">It could therefore be argued that Othello is as much of a victim as Desdemona. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3008j-ftnote.024"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Shakespeare, op.cit., i.3, 288, p72 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3008j-ftnote.025"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid ii.1, 175 p.83 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3008j-ftnote.026"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid ii.3, 305-6, p98 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3008j-ftnote.027"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Matheson, op.cit., p131 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3008j-ftnote.028"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Shakespeare, op.cit.,iii.3 46 p.105. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3008j-ftnote.029"><p n="pn1.2"><s n="s1.3;pn1.2">Pecher, E. </s><s n="s2.3;pn1.2">'Have you not read of some such thing? </s><s n="s3.3;pn1.2">Sex and sexual stories in Othello', in </s></p><p n="pn2.2"><s n="s1.1;pn2.2"><hi rend="underlined">Shakespeare survey 49- Romeo and Juliet in its Afterlife</hi> (Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 1996) </s></p></note><p n="p12.23"><s n="s1.3;p12.23">Often misinterpreted as a dramatic mechanism and symbolic counterbalance to 'hellish villain'<ref target="BAWE_3008j-ftnote.030"/> Iago, Desdemona is more than a component of the tragedy's framework. </s><s n="s2.3;p12.23">She is a flawed character and not simply the victim of her own slavish obedience. </s><s n="s3.3;p12.23">Her sense of justice is exploited by Iago as; </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3008j-ftnote.030"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Shakespeare, op.cit.,v.2, 365 p.180 </s></p></note><quote lang="English"> She's of so free, so kind .. a disposition that she holds it a vice in her Goodness not to do more than she's requested.<ref target="BAWE_3008j-ftnote.031"/></quote><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3008j-ftnote.031"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid., ii.3, 310-312, p98 </s></p></note><p n="p13.23"><s n="s1.3;p13.23">Desdemona's naiveté may represent women's lack of reasoning as she has; 'No judgement in an honest face." </s><ref target="BAWE_3008j-ftnote.032"/><s n="s2.3;p13.23">Her disturbing resignation towards Othello's derogatory abuse is both frustrating and poignant. </s><s n="s3.3;p13.23">Eagleton believes; </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3008j-ftnote.032"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid., iii.3, 50, p105 </s></p></note><quote lang="English"> To suspect that she is adulterous is to credit her with an identity autonomous of his own.. and begins to undermine his own identity. Much of his jealousy is a... fear that his own magnificently replete selfhood is collapsing.'<ref target="BAWE_3008j-ftnote.033"/></quote><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3008j-ftnote.033"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Eagleton, op.cit., p.68 </s></p></note><p n="p14.23"><s n="s1.5;p14.23">The murder allows him to re-establish his rightful masculine dominance as he sees himself as a moral avenger of justice;'she must die, else she'll betray more men." </s><ref target="BAWE_3008j-ftnote.034"/><s n="s2.5;p14.23">Desdemona's tragic surrender destroys her dignity; 'commend me to my kind lord." </s><ref target="BAWE_3008j-ftnote.035"/><s n="s3.5;p14.23">Her self sacrifice symbolises female oppression. </s><s n="s4.5;p14.23">Tennenhouse believes; 'this punishment also points right to the source of the assault upon patriarchy, the woman's political voice." </s><ref target="BAWE_3008j-ftnote.036"/><s n="s5.5;p14.23">He argues that her murder is politically motivated because Elizabethans believed; 'mutilating the female could somehow correct political corruption.'<ref target="BAWE_3008j-ftnote.037"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3008j-ftnote.034"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Shakespeare, op.cit.,V.2, 6, p164. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3008j-ftnote.035"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid., V.2, 126,p170 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3008j-ftnote.036"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Tennenhouse op.cit., p.127 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3008j-ftnote.037"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid., p.116 </s></p></note><p n="p15.23"><s n="s1.5;p15.23">In silencing Emilia's proto-feminist wisdom, Shakespeare implies that her controversial opinions are socially unacceptable, yet he implicitly elevates her views by portraying her as sensible and observant. </s><s n="s2.5;p15.23">New Historicism argues that Emillia's subversive dissenting voice is contained because the text represents society's dominant ideology, whereas formalist critics view the text within a vacuum. </s><s n="s3.5;p15.23">Dusinberrre believes 'Shakespeare saw men and women as equal in a world that declared them unequal." </s><ref target="BAWE_3008j-ftnote.038"/><s n="s4.5;p15.23">Emilia rejects sexual superiority; 'Have we not affections/ desires for sport?" </s><ref target="BAWE_3008j-ftnote.039"/><s n="s5.5;p15.23">Her perceptive comic cynicism stems from her relationship with </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3008j-ftnote.038"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.5;pn1.1">Dusinberrre, J. </s><s rend="underlined" n="s2.5;pn1.1">Shakespeare and the nature of women. </s><s n="s3.5;pn1.1">Second Edition (London: Macmillan Press. </s><s n="s4.5;pn1.1">1996)p. </s><s n="s5.5;pn1.1">308 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3008j-ftnote.039"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Shakespeare, op.cit., iv.3, 99-100, p.156 </s></p></note><p n="p16.23"><s n="s1.7;p16.23">Iago; 'They are all stomachs.. they eat us hungrily.. </s><s n="s2.7;p16.23">They belch us." </s><ref target="BAWE_3008j-ftnote.040"/><s n="s3.7;p16.23">Emila's view of men is as derogatory and playful as Iago's;'It is their husbands' faults/ If wives do fall." </s><ref target="BAWE_3008j-ftnote.041"/><s n="s4.7;p16.23">Her unwavering belief in Desdemona empowers her to confront Othello, confirming Matheson's view that she is 'an agent for..political ideals of justice and liberty." </s><ref target="BAWE_3008j-ftnote.042"/><s n="s5.7;p16.23">Both are murdered because they threaten their husband's masculine identity. </s><s n="s6.7;p16.23">Matheson believes that Iago 'exerts a despotic control over his wife's actions and speech... </s><s n="s7.7;p16.23">Her plight reflects Iago's virulent misogyny.'<ref target="BAWE_3008j-ftnote.043"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3008j-ftnote.040"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid., iii.4, 100-3, p.127 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3008j-ftnote.041"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid., iv.3 185-6 p.156 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3008j-ftnote.042"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Matheson, op.cit., p. 133 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3008j-ftnote.043"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid., p131 </s></p></note><p n="p17.23"><s n="s1.5;p17.23">Bianca's dubious reputation, social ranking and commitment to Cassio enervates her, as she is rejected, neglected and belittled. </s><s n="s2.5;p17.23">Even the judicious Emillia disparages her, confirming Dusinberrre's claim that 'importance.. turns women against each other rather than against men who injure them." </s><ref target="BAWE_3008j-ftnote.044"/><s n="s3.5;p17.23">Bianca and Cassio's relationship parallels that of Desdemona and Othello as it too is based on sexual attraction, but Adamson argues that; 'To suppose that Bianca is a foil for Desdemona is to distort and simplify what the play shows." </s><ref target="BAWE_3008j-ftnote.045"/><s n="s4.5;p17.23">Tennenhouse believes that 'Jacobean drama proves one thing..sexual relationships are always political." </s><ref target="BAWE_3008j-ftnote.046"/><s n="s5.5;p17.23">Iago's fixation with Desdemona's sexual appetite leads him to; </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3008j-ftnote.044"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Dusinberrre, op.cit., p.280 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3008j-ftnote.045"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Adamson, J. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1"><hi rend="underlined">Othello as a tragedy some problems of judgement and feeling</hi> (Cambridge: Cambridge university press, 1980)p.242 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3008j-ftnote.046"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Tennenhouse, op.cit., p.124 </s></p></note><quote lang="English"> turn the features of her political rebellion into the signs of unchaste desire..he translates her exercise of political patronage into an illicit use of her body. <ref target="BAWE_3008j-ftnote.047"/></quote><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3008j-ftnote.047"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid., p.125 </s></p></note><p n="p18.23"><s n="s1.1;p18.23">Desdemona's bold assertion of her sexual rights, leads me to agree with Tennenhouse that; 'In </s></p><p n="p19.23"><s n="s1.2;p19.23">desiring a male, she embodies male desire. </s><s n="s2.2;p19.23">Thus the female becomes monstrous by virtue of containing male parts.' <ref target="BAWE_3008j-ftnote.048"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3008j-ftnote.048"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid., p.119 </s></p></note><p n="p20.23"><s n="s1.6;p20.23">Iago, like Othello is afflicted by a paranoid obsessive sexual jealousy desiring to be 'evened with him wife for wife." </s><ref target="BAWE_3008j-ftnote.049"/><s n="s2.6;p20.23">Masculine tensions permeate the play and Matheson believes; 'The play offers an analysis of male identity within the army as profoundly dependant on place." </s><ref target="BAWE_3008j-ftnote.050"/><s n="s3.6;p20.23">Iago's feeling of emasculation having not being promoted, leads him to embellish the threat of Cassio's potent sexual power. </s><s n="s4.6;p20.23">Dusinberrre believes that; 'Imagining himself wronged, Othello feels his identity as a man of action dissolve." </s><ref target="BAWE_3008j-ftnote.051"/><s n="s5.6;p20.23">Men dominate the play, but aren't portrayed as well as women, as they are murderous, week and vengeful. </s><s n="s6.6;p20.23">The most powerful male character is the embodiment of evil. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3008j-ftnote.049"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Shakespeare., II.1 289-290 p.87 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3008j-ftnote.050"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Matheson, op.cit., p.129 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3008j-ftnote.051"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Dusinberrre, op.cit., p.302 </s></p></note><p n="p21.23"><s n="s1.9;p21.23">Iago manipulates characters and language through his verbal artistry and suggestive punning. </s><s n="s2.9;p21.23">Othello's disturbing admiration for Iago becomes apparent when he claims; 'Iago..thou teachest me." </s><ref target="BAWE_3008j-ftnote.052"/><s n="s3.9;p21.23">Frightening similarities emerge between them as they share a linguistic register, alluding to animals and sexual instincts. </s><s n="s4.9;p21.23">Othello's simultaneous linguistic and physical collapse accompanies his decent into frenzied incoherent prose, whilst paradoxically, Iago becomes increasingly poetic, stealing both his style and dignity. </s><s n="s5.9;p21.23">Othello's name disintegrates into a series of 'O''s; 'O ill-starred wench!" </s><ref target="BAWE_3008j-ftnote.053"/><s n="s6.9;p21.23">This formalist examination of structure and language represents a more scientific approach to literature. </s><s n="s7.9;p21.23">Here, skilful form makes good literature. </s><s n="s8.9;p21.23">American New Critics valued works that promoted unity of form and content, and therefore regard the way the text disrupts and questions itself as a negative feature. </s><s n="s9.9;p21.23">Iago's calm eloquence allows him to communicate more effectively with Othello than </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3008j-ftnote.052"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Shakespeare, op.cit., iii.3 p.114 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3008j-ftnote.053"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid., v.2 270, p.176 </s></p></note><p n="p22.23"><s n="s1.3;p22.23">Desdemona does. </s><s n="s2.3;p22.23">Iago and Othello kneel in a parody of a marriage ceremony that provides an ironic contrast to when Desdemona kneels to proclaim her fidelity. </s><s n="s3.3;p22.23">Collocations relating to marriage such as 'witness,'<ref target="BAWE_3008j-ftnote.054"/> infer that Iago replaces Desdemona in Othello's emotions, whilst hinting at possible repressed homosexual feeling between them. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3008j-ftnote.054"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid., iii.3 460 p.122 </s></p></note><p n="p23.23"><s n="s1.4;p23.23">Shakespeare adheres to the conventions of tragedy, but manipulates and widens its limitations which inevitably effects his portrayal of politics and gender. </s><s n="s2.4;p23.23">The play therefore encompasses the values of the Renaissance, allowing Shakespeare to explore topical issues in a less restricted manner. </s><s n="s3.4;p23.23">Conventional and modernistic tragedy overlap thus reflecting the indivisible nature of gender and politics in the play. </s><s n="s4.4;p23.23">Shakespeare changed the definition of tragedy and what is tragic, thus allowing us to 'participate fully in the horror which falls upon Othello, while we are.. seconded in our faith in divine order,' which is 'essence of tragedy.' <ref target="BAWE_3008j-ftnote.055"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3008j-ftnote.055"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ribner, op.cit., p.115 </s></p></note></div1></body><back><div1 type="bibliography"><head><hi rend="bold">Bibliography</hi><ref target="BAWE_3008j-ftnote.056"/><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3008j-ftnote.056"><p>The word count for this essay excluding footnotes and bibliography is 2174 words. </p></note></head><p>Adamson, J. <hi rend="underlined">Othello as a tragedy some problems of judgement and feeling</hi> (Cambridge: </p><p>Cambridge university press, 1980)</p><p>Dollimore. J, Ed. <hi rend="underlined">Political Shakespeare- New essays in cultural materialism</hi>, (Manchester: </p><p>Manchester University press, 1988)</p><p>Dubrow, H. <hi rend="underlined">Genre</hi> (London: Methuen, 1982)</p><p>Dusinberrre, J. <hi rend="underlined">Shakespeare and the nature of women.</hi> Second Edition (London: Macmillan </p><p>Press. 1996)</p><p>Eagleton, T. <hi rend="underlined">William Shakespeare</hi>( Oxford: Basil Blackwell. 1987)</p><p>Matheson. M, 'Venetian culture and politics of Othello', in <hi rend="underlined">Shakespeare survey</hi></p><p><hi rend="underlined">48-Shakespeare and cultural exchange</hi> (Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 1995)</p><p>Pecher, E. 'Have you not read of some such thing? Sex and sexual stories in Othello', in </p><p><hi rend="underlined">Shakespeare survey 49- Romeo and Juliet in its Afterlife</hi> (Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 1996)</p><p>Ribner, I. <hi rend="underlined">Patterns in Shakespearean Tragedy</hi> (London: Methuen, 1979)</p><p>Shakespeare, W. <hi rend="underlined">Othello</hi>, Ed.Kenneth Muir (London: Penguin, 1996)</p><p>Sinfield, A. 'Cultural Materialism, Othello, and the politics of plausibility' in <hi rend="underlined">Literary Theory: An Anthology</hi> , edited by J. Rivkin and M. Ryan (Oxford: Blackwell, 2002.)</p><p>Tennenhouse, L. <hi rend="underlined">Power on display-The politics of Shakespeare's Genres</hi> (London: Methuen , 1986)</p><p>Wine, M.C. <hi rend="underlined">Othello text and performance</hi> (London: Macmillan, 1988)</p></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
