<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_3016a" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Case Study of the white-throated capuchin monkey</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">The document has a title page which contains:
document title
figure</note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">Student name and number in doc footer.
 
</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">2</p><p n="date">2004-NA</p><p n="module title">Human and other primates</p><p n="module code">M07342</p><p n="genre family">Explanation</p><p n="discipline">Anthropology</p><p n="disciplinary group">SS</p><p n="grade">D</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">2956</p><p n="number of s-units">98</p><p n="number of p">18</p><p n="number of tables">3</p><p n="number of figures">9</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">0</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">0</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">30.2</p><p n="average s-units per p">5.4</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">m</p><p n="year of birth">1980</p><p n="first language">English</p><p n="education">UKa</p><p n="course">BA Anthropology</p><p n="student ID">3016</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><docTitle><titlePart>Case Study of the white-throated capuchin monkey (<hi rend="italic">Cebus capucinus</hi>)</titlePart></docTitle><figure id="BAWE_3016a-pic.001"/><docTitle><titlePart>M07342 - Humans and Other Primates<name type="student name"/><name type="student ID"/></titlePart></docTitle></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="section"><head>Introduction</head><p n="p1.18"><s n="s1.4;p1.18">The white-throated capuchin monkey, <hi rend="italic">Cebus capucinus</hi>, is one of four species of new world monkeys belonging to the genus <hi rend="italic">Cebus</hi> (fig1). </s><s n="s2.4;p1.18">The word capuchin is a French word taken from Italian 'cappucino,' meaning hooded one, a reference to the markings on the monkeys' head which resemble the cloaks worn by the order of capuchin monks (Flannery/2004). </s><s n="s3.4;p1.18">The species is perhaps one of the most well known of South American primates due to its unfortunate status until recently as the preferred choice of monkey for organ grinders and street entertainers (Moynihan/1978). </s><s n="s4.4;p1.18">They are the most typically monkey-like of all the ceboids and according to Moynihan (1978), 'certainly are a climax of ceboids evolution'. </s></p><p n="p2.18"><s n="s1.4;p2.18">Their high level of cognitive ability has earned them the title the 'the chimpanzees of the new world.' </s><s n="s2.4;p2.18">As Garber and Paciulli (1996) state, enlargement of the neocortex in <hi rend="italic">Cebus</hi> is so extreme that when allometrically corrected for body size, they have a neocortex that is comparable to that of a chimpanzee. </s><s n="s3.4;p2.18">Only the great apes, dolphins, and humans have a greater degree of encephalization and complex patterning of cerebral fissures than capuchins (Marino et al/1994) Studies of both wild and captives indicate that capuchins show the highest degree of manual prehension among new world primates and exhibit advanced tool use more often then any other species of monkey (Garber/1996). </s><s n="s4.4;p2.18">Indeed, only white fronted capuchins, chimpanzees and orang-utans have been observed to use tools in their natural habitats. </s></p><p n="p3.18"><s n="s1.3;p3.18">Additionally, capuchins have frequently been observed using rocks to break open palm nuts and oyster shells and at least one study site at La Suerte Biological field Station, Costa Rica, white-throated capuchins have been observed to use twigs to probe holes in trees whilst foraging (Garber/1996; own observations). </s><s n="s2.3;p3.18">There is also substantial evidence indicating that capuchins use several species of plants in behaviour indicative of self-medication (Weldon et al/2003; Baker/1996). </s><s n="s3.3;p3.18">The superficial similarities between capuchin and great ape behaviours are considered significantly important that the International Journal of Primatology has devoted the entire contents of one supplement to a comparison of the Genus and chimpanzees, both common, <hi rend="italic">Pan troglodytes</hi> and bonobo, <hi rend="italic">Pan paniscus</hi> (IJP/vol. 18 (5) 1997). </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head>Phylogeny &amp; Evolution</head><p n="p4.18"><s n="s1.7;p4.18">All new world primates including capuchins are grouped together under the infraorder Platyrrhini and the super family Ceboidea although the two are essentially synonymous since Ceboidea is the only living Platyrrhine super family (fig1). </s><s n="s2.7;p4.18">Recent Genetic studies have shown platyrrhines to be monophyletic group and to share a common basal ancestor with both humans and African primates. </s><s n="s3.7;p4.18">The two groups are estimated to have last shared a common ancestor at approximately 38 million years ago at the end of the Eocene (Horovitz et al/1998; Strier/2003). </s><s n="s4.7;p4.18">Their presence in the new world is interpreted as the result of a single dispersal event, and since by this time South America and Africa had already drifted about half as far apart from each other as they are today it is proposed that they reached South America by rafting or island hopping in some way (Fleagle/1999; Strier/2003). </s><s n="s5.7;p4.18">Upon arrival the ancestor of all extant platyrrhines underwent a process of adaptive radiation that has resulted in the present primate diversity. </s><s n="s6.7;p4.18">The similarities in morphology between Old and New World primates occurred via a process of parallel evolution as a result of exposure to similar environmental and ecological conditions. </s><s n="s7.7;p4.18">However, in contrast to Old World monkeys, capuchins, like most New World primates evolved prehensile tails due to the exclusively arboreal nature of their lifestyle and have well developed olfactory senses which they use for communication (Strier/2003). </s></p><figure id="BAWE_3016a-fig.001"><head>Fig 1: Selected Taxonomic model for Cebus capucinus phylogeny - Adapted from (Strier/2003)</head></figure></div1><div1 type="section"><head>Habitat and Distribution</head><p n="p5.18"><s n="s1.6;p5.18">White-throated capuchins are distributed throughout Central America from Belize and Honduras in the north, to western Columbia and Ecuador in the south. </s><s n="s2.6;p5.18">They are found in Primary and Secondary evergreen rainforest, mangroves and deciduous dry forests from sea level to 2100m (Rowe/1996) (Fig 2). </s><s n="s3.6;p5.18">Their distribution over a large range of different habitats has led them to be behaviourally adapted to a variety of environments and food resources. </s><s n="s4.6;p5.18">As will be discussed below, they are generalist feeders and represent the closest approximation to an omnivore amongst the New World primates (Perry et al/2003). </s><s n="s5.6;p5.18">It has been suggested that their distribution over such a large and varied habitat area has played a major in the development of high levels of cognitive ability (Perry et al/2003). </s><s n="s6.6;p5.18">They generally prefer to move in middle to upper canopy level where most of their food resources are to be found. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_3016a-pic.002"><head rend="underlined">Figure 2</head></figure><div2><head>Morphology &amp; Species Characteristics </head><p n="p6.18"><s n="s1.9;p6.18">As with all primates, the morphology of capuchins is inseparably intertwined with the environment and behaviour of its phylogenetic ancestor (Fleagle/1999). </s><s n="s2.9;p6.18">Consequently, the species are of medium size, lightly built, slender and long limbed (Fig 3), all of which means they are perfectly adapted to moving quickly in their present ecological niche. </s><s n="s3.9;p6.18">For example, in the rainforest canopy most of the resources upon which they feed; insects, flower buds and fruits, are often to be found on thin terminal branches of trees. </s><s n="s4.9;p6.18">Thus they have evolved to be small and light enough to exploit these resources (Moynihan/1978). </s><s n="s5.9;p6.18">Conversely, mantled howler monkeys, <hi rend="italic">Alouatta palliata</hi>, with whom they often share the same forest environment, are large and weighty animals. </s><s n="s6.9;p6.18">They feed primarily upon leaves away from terminal branches and thus this adaptation is represented in their morphology. </s><s n="s7.9;p6.18">Sexual dimorphism is characteristic and as table 1 illustrates, males are generally larger and heavier than females. </s><s n="s8.9;p6.18">This is due to a number of factors, for instance it is adult males over eight years of age who protect the multi-male multi-female society from predators and defend the territory (Robinson et al/1987). </s><s n="s9.9;p6.18">Another characteristic of this sexual dimorphism is the size as canines as indicated by figures 4 and 5, which are larger in males (Strier/2003). </s></p><figure id="BAWE_3016a-pic.003"><head rend="underlined">Fig3: Capuchin Skeleton (3)</head></figure><table id="BAWE_3016a-tab.001"><head rend="underlined">Table 1: Body size and weight (Rowe/1996)</head><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p7.18"><s n="s1.6;p7.18">Capuchins, like all Platyrrhines, have rounded nostrils which are oriented towards their ears, while the noses of members of Catyrrhini, or Old World primates, have narrow nostrils that face downwards. </s><s n="s2.6;p7.18">This characteristic is the result of phylogenetic ancestry and is clearly visible in figure 5 (Chimpanzoo/2004) (fig 2). </s><s n="s3.6;p7.18">White-throated capuchins have a white to yellowish throat, head and shoulders. </s><s n="s4.6;p7.18">The back and prehensile tail are black and the hair on the crown forms a v-shape. </s><s n="s5.6;p7.18">Infants are born with a grey face and ears but by the age of 3 months they have developed adult markings (Rowe/1996). </s><s n="s6.6;p7.18">There is no distinction in terms of markings between males and females and the only other visible characteristics which enable a distinction to be made is the presence of testicles for adult males and an elongated clitoris for females (Fleagle/1999). </s></p><figure id="BAWE_3016a-pic.004"><head rend="underlined">Fig4: Adult Male (3) </head></figure><figure id="BAWE_3016a-pic.005"><head rend="underlined">Fig5: Adult Female (3) </head></figure><p n="p8.18"><s n="s1.8;p8.18">Other notable characteristics include a semi-prehensile tail which is frequently used to lower the body down from one branch to another (although they do not hang of it for long periods of time) and for balance in locomotion. </s><s n="s2.8;p8.18">It is very large and muscular, comprising almost 50% of the adult's body weight. </s><s n="s3.8;p8.18">In addition, capuchins have five digits on each hand with an opposable thumb (polex) and toe (hallux) which allow for superb manual prehension. </s><s n="s4.8;p8.18">The finger tips are capped with nails unlike the claws of prosimians, and have soft pads or dermatoglyphs (fingerprints), combined with meissners corpuscles allowing for increased tactile sensitivity. </s><s n="s5.8;p8.18">As with all primates the eyes are close together and face forward in the skull (fig6) to provide stereoscopic vision, and the magnum foramen is underneath the skull allowing for quadrupedal locomotion (Kinzey/1997; Strier/2003). </s><s n="s6.8;p8.18">The diet of white-throated capuchins has also influenced their morphology. </s><s n="s7.8;p8.18">For example their dentition is typically representative of frugivourous primates with broad incisors and low rounded molar cusps combined with long small intestines to process the fruit. </s><s n="s8.8;p8.18">In addition, the enamel layer is particularly thick allowing them to feed on nuts with hard shells However, the dental formula of 2:1:3:3; two incisors, one canine, three pre-molars and three molars in each quarter of the jaw is phylogenetically characteristic of all Platyrrhines (Strier/2003). </s></p><figure id="BAWE_3016a-pic.006"><head rend="underlined">Fig6:Visible facial characteristics</head></figure></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head>Locomotion &amp; Behaviour</head><p n="p9.18"><s n="s1.3;p9.18">White-throated capuchins are arboreal quadrupeds that spend 60-70% of their time either foraging or moving between foraging sites, often jumping gaps between trees of 3-4 meters (Robinson/1987; Rowe/1996). </s><s n="s2.3;p9.18">As phylogeny affects body size, limb length and construction it also directly affects the type of locomotion used. </s><s n="s3.3;p9.18">For instance, the locomotion of capucinus has </s></p><p n="p10.18"><s n="s1.5;p10.18">undergone extensive selective pressures during the animal's evolutionary history. </s><s n="s2.5;p10.18">Thus quadrupedal running and jumping is the form of locomotion best suited to the ecological niche they inhabit (Strier/2003). </s><s n="s3.5;p10.18">Although they are habitually arboreal they do come to the ground occasionally to search for insects and to drink (Kinzey/1997). </s><s n="s4.5;p10.18">In addition, there is evidence to suggest that some capuchins living in fragmented forest, where the risk of predation is lower, spend a good percentage (37%) of their time in terrestrially foraging (own notes). </s><s n="s5.5;p10.18">It is suggested that such behaviour indicates the animals has learned that the risk of predation is reduced (Perry et al/2003). </s></p><figure id="BAWE_3016a-pic.007"><head rend="underlined">Fig 7: Capuchin enjoying a brief respite </head></figure></div1><div1 type="section"><head>Diet and Behaviour</head><p n="p11.18"><s n="s1.8;p11.18">Capuchin feeding behaviour and diet is influenced by two factors; those of the past, including genetically defined species characteristics, such as ancestral morphology, combined with local traditions in resource exploitation and those of the present. </s><s n="s2.8;p11.18">Present influences are external environmental variables which encompass the relative abundance, quality, distribution of and competition for particular resources at sites and the seasonal fluctuation in their availability (Crook, Ellis &amp; Goss-Custard/lecture notes). </s><s n="s3.8;p11.18">In terms of species characteristics capuchins have evolved to be largely frugivourous-insectivores, for example they have excellent trichromatic colour vision and olfactory abilities which aid them in foraging for both fruits and insects (Robinson/1987; Kinzey/1997). </s><s n="s4.8;p11.18">The typical ratios of foods eaten are as follows: 65% ripe fruits (over 95 types); 15% leaves, berries, nuts, seeds, shoots, buds and flowers; 20% animal matter, largely insect prey (Rowe/1996). </s><s n="s5.8;p11.18">The nature of their diet means that capuchins are often beneficial to the health of the forest as pollinators of some plants and seed dispersers of others (Rowe/1996). </s><s n="s6.8;p11.18">Indeed Robert Sussman argues that the morphological traits, feeding strategies and behaviour of arboreal frugivourous primates, such as capuchins, are the result of a long history of co-evolution with angiosperms (Strier/2003). </s><s n="s7.8;p11.18">However, not all capucinus groups share the same diet, for example white-throated capuchins living only a few hundred kilometres apart have been shown to have completely different diets despite having access to the same resources. </s><s n="s8.8;p11.18">Thus the importance of local traditions in diets within groups of primates should not be underestimated as they have direct consequences for the species behavioural ecology (Strier/2003). </s></p><figure id="BAWE_3016a-pic.008"><head rend="underlined">Fig 8: Capuchin with infant coatimundi</head></figure><p n="p12.18"><s n="s1.6;p12.18">Furthermore, as their range includes such diverse habitats, white-throated capuchins have evolved to be a highly adaptable, opportunistic and generalist feeder which enables them to shape their behaviour in relation to environmental variables (Perry et al/2003). </s><s n="s2.6;p12.18">For instance, should the need arise they may become 100% frugivourous or insectivorous for short periods of time (Kinzey/1997), and at certain coastal sites in Panama and Columbia they are known to eat crabs and to crack open oyster shells with rocks to feed on the contents (Moynihan/1978). </s><s n="s3.6;p12.18">In addition, they also incorporate within their diet small quantities of invertebrates including birds, squirrels, baby coatimundis, and eggs (Rowe/1996; Robinson/1987) (Fig 8). </s><s n="s4.6;p12.18">The majority of observations have been recorded at Santa Rosa National Park, Costa Rica and it is interesting to note that unlike chimpanzees, such deliberate active predation of coati pups and squirrels by capucinus occurs mostly during the dry season when fruit and insects are less abundant (Rose/1997). </s><s n="s5.6;p12.18">Thus predation by primates, such as white-throated capuchins, seems to be a part of the behavioural repertories of intelligent, opportunistic foragers and does not infer the complex social role it plays for chimpanzees (Strier/2003; Rose/1997). </s><s n="s6.6;p12.18">The species is known to crack open palm nut shells using stone hammers, however, even though at many sites the same nuts, and in the case of coastal areas oysters, are available to all groups of monkeys only certain populations engage in such behaviour and it seems likely that at least in this respect their diet is influenced by local traditions of resource exploitation (Moynihan/1978; Perry et al/2003). </s></p><p n="p13.18"><s n="s1.9;p13.18">White-throated capuchins are described as a 'manipulative' or 'extractive forager' due to the nature of its feeding behaviour, which involves physically investigating hollows in trees and destructive foraging in vegetation (Garber/1996). </s><s n="s2.9;p13.18">As stated, the two food sources eaten most frequently are ripe fruits and insects and it appears that their behaviour whilst exploiting such resources is the one which provides each individual with the optimum amount of food combined with the lowest levels of intra-group competition. </s><s n="s3.9;p13.18">In contrast to brown capuchins (<hi rend="italic">Cebus apella</hi>), capucinus habitually feeds mainly on large fruiting trees such as fig with canopies up to 165 feet in diameter. </s><s n="s4.9;p13.18">Here an individual does not need to fight for its share and subsequently group sizes can be larger in capucinus with less intra-group aggression during feeding (Janson/1986). </s><s n="s5.9;p13.18">Whilst feeding on insects, a scramble competition/non-defendable resource, the troop spreads out and animals forage individually, often at large distances from others, whilst constantly moving forwards through the canopy. </s><s n="s6.9;p13.18">Each animal emits a regular high pitched call in order to maintain its distance from other animals and avoid competition. </s><s n="s7.9;p13.18">Foraging for insects constitutes a far greater portion of the capuchins budget than does foraging for fruits as insects scattered throughout the canopy (Robinson/1987). </s><s n="s8.9;p13.18">This illustrates the importance of insects as a protein source within their diets and helps to explain both the need for individual foraging and the huge distances travelled each day in search of food (Table 2). </s><s n="s9.9;p13.18">Therefore, it is clearly evident that the number of large fruit bearing trees and density and abundance of insects directly influences both the population size and range of the species. </s></p><table id="BAWE_3016a-tab.002"><head rend="underlined">Table 2: Daily range and group size (Rowe/1996)</head><row><cell/></row></table></div1><div1 type="section"><head>Social Structure and Reproductive Behaviour</head><figure id="BAWE_3016a-pic.009"><head rend="underlined">Fig 9: Adult male sharing food with two juveniles</head></figure><p n="p14.18"><s n="s1.5;p14.18">White-throated capuchins live in multi-male multi female polygynandrous groups whereby there is little hierarchy evident determining access to females. </s><s n="s2.5;p14.18">Consequently as all the males are likely to be fathers of some of the group's infants, the social structure and cooperation seen in group defence is high (Janson/1986; Fragazy/1997). </s><s n="s3.5;p14.18">For example, when attacked by a predator, in this instance a tayra, all adult males were observed to immediately responded to the alarm calls of the group by collectively mobbing the potential threat (own notes). </s><s n="s4.5;p14.18">Furthermore, the high levels of co-operation amongst individual males also results in them being able to defend more efficiently clumped food resources and drive away considerably larger monkeys (Janson/1986). </s><s n="s5.5;p14.18">Another consequence of such polygynandrous sexual behaviour is that adult males will frequently tolerate the presence of juveniles often sharing forming affiliative bonds and sharing food, on one occasion an adult male was observed to allow a juvenile animal to physically remove food from his mouth (Robinson/1986; own notes) (Fig 9). </s></p><p n="p15.18"><s n="s1.5;p15.18">Groups of monkeys are matrilineally philopatric in that during adolescence it is males who must disperse from their natal groups. </s><s n="s2.5;p15.18">Consequently troops consist of mostly related females and their offspring and unrelated males (Robinson/1986). </s><s n="s3.5;p15.18">The species is territorial and marks its territory by urinating upon its hands and then rubbing their feet and fur, however it is only males who defend the territory (Perry et al/2003; Rowe/1996). </s><s n="s4.5;p15.18">White-throated capuchins are highly social and the vast majority of rest periods are spent in allogrooming. </s><s n="s5.5;p15.18">Mothers frequently groom their infants and it has been observed that as well as reinforcing social bonds grooming also serves to </s></p><table id="BAWE_3016a-tab.003"><head rend="underlined">Table 3: Life history and reproductive cycle for mother and infants (Fragazy/1997; Rowe/1996)</head><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p16.18"><s n="s1.7;p16.18">recapitulate dominance hierarchies. </s><s n="s2.7;p16.18">Indeed, as Robinson states dominant individuals are usually involved in a disproportionately high percentage of grooming bouts and often receive far more grooming than they give (1986). </s><s n="s3.7;p16.18">The species has also been observed to engage in and generate 'original' games which they play amongst themselves, it has been suggested that such games are site dependent and represent evidence of social traditions within capuchin society (Perry et al/2003). </s><s n="s4.7;p16.18">As table 3 illustrates females usually give birth to a single infant during the dry season. </s><s n="s5.7;p16.18">The alpha male relies upon coalitionary support from the females to protect his status within the group (Strier/2003). </s><s n="s6.7;p16.18">White-throated capuchins are precocial and secondarily altricial animals in that although infants are relatively well developed at birth they are not very mobile and must cling to there mothers and rely heavily on extended postnatal development and maternal investment to grow their relatively large adult brain sizes (Strier/2003). </s><s n="s7.7;p16.18">The feeding behaviour and reproductive strategy employed by white-throated capuchins provides numerous benefits for the survival of the group as a whole in that tensions are reduced and greater security is achieved from potential predators. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head>Conservation Status</head><p n="p17.18"><s n="s1.1;p17.18">Although they are hunted in Columbia and Ecuador for meat, white-throated capuchins are in no immediate danger and are categorized under Cites Appendix 2, low risk category (Chimpanzoo/2004). </s></p><p n="p18.18"><s n="s1.2;p18.18">However, it is not direct persecution that represents a problem for <hi rend="italic">capucinus</hi>; the fragmentation of their natural forest habitat represents a far more significant threat. </s><s n="s2.2;p18.18">Males must leave their natal group in late adolescence and join a neighbouring group of monkeys; if they are prevented to do so the future survival of genetically diverse groups may be put placed in jeopardy. </s></p></div1></body><back><div1 type="bibliography"><head rend="underlined">References</head><p>Baker, Mary. (1996). Fur<hi rend="italic"> Rubbing: Use of Medicinal Plants by capuchin monkeys (Cebus capucinus). American Journal of Primatology</hi>. Vol.38, pp263-270. </p><p>Crook, J. H., Ellis, J. E., and Goss-Custard, J. D. (1976). Mammalian social systems: structure and function. <hi rend="italic">Anim. Behav</hi>. 24: 261-274.</p><p>Fleagle, J.(1999). <hi rend="italic">Primate adaptation &amp; evolution.</hi> London : Academic Press, 1988</p><p>Fragazy, D. Bard, K. (1997). <hi rend="italic">Comparison of development and Life History in Pan and Cebus. International Journal of Primatology</hi>. 18 (5), pp683-701</p><p>Garber, P.A. Paciulli, L.M. (1996). Experimental Field Study of Spatial Memory and Learning in Wild Capuchin Monkeys (Cebus capucinus). <hi rend="italic">American Journal of Psychical Anthropology.</hi> 22, pp181-203</p><p>Horovitz, I. Zardoya, R. Meyer, A. (1998). Platyrrhine Systemics: A Simultaneous Analysis of Molecular and Morphological Data. <hi rend="italic">American Journal of Physical Anthropology. 10</hi>6, pp261-281</p><p>Janson, C. (1986). Capuchin Counterpoint. in Ciochon, R.L. Nisbett, R (Eds) (1998) <hi rend="italic">'The Primate Anthology'.</hi> USA: Prentice Hall Inc. </p><p>Kinzey, W.G. (1997<hi rend="italic">). New World primates: ecology, evolution, and behaviour.</hi> New York: Aldine de Gruyter, 1997</p><p>Marino, L. Reiss, D. Gallup, G.G. (1994). Mirror self-recognition in bottlenose dolphins: Implications for comparative investigations of highly dissimilar species. in Parker, S.T. Mitchell, R.W. Boccia, M.L (Eds) <hi rend="italic">'Self-awareness in Animals and Humans: Developmental Perspectives.'</hi> New York: Cambridge University Press</p><p>Moynihan, M. (1978). <hi rend="italic">The New World primates: adaptive radiation and the evolution of social behaviour.</hi> Guildford: Princeton University Press</p><p>Perry Susan, Baker M, Fedigan L, Gros-Louis J, Jack K, MacKinnon KC, Manson JH, Panger M, Pyle K, Rose L (2003). Traditions in Wild-faced Capuchin monkeys. <hi rend="italic">Current Anthropology</hi>. 44 (2), pp241-268 </p><p>Robinson, J. G. &amp; Janson, C. H. (1987). Capuchins, squirrel monkeys, and Atelines: Socio-ecological convergence with old world monkeys. in Smuts. Cheney. Seyfarth. Wrangham. Struhsaker (Eds) <hi rend="italic">'Primate Societies'.</hi> Chicago and London: The University of Chicago Press, pp. 69-82.</p><p>Rose, L. (1997). Vertebrate Predation and Food-sharing in Cebus and Pan. <hi rend="italic">International Journal of Primatology.</hi> 18 (5), pp727-759</p><p>Rowe, N. (1996). <hi rend="italic">The pictorial guide to the living primates.</hi> East Hampton, N.Y. : Pogonias Press.</p><p>Strier, Karen. (2003). <hi rend="italic">Primate Behavioural Ecology.</hi> Boston: Allyn &amp; Bacon.</p><p>Visalberghi, E., McGrew, C. (1997). <hi rend="italic">Cebus Meets Pan. International Journal of Primatology</hi>. 18 (5), pp677-679.</p><p>Weldon, P.J., Aldrich, J.R., Klun, J.A., Oliver, J.E., Debboun, M. (2003). <hi rend="italic">Benzoquinones from millipedes deter mosquitoes and elicit self-anointing in capuchin monkeys (Cebus spp.).</hi> Naturwissenschaften, .90 (7), pp301-304.</p><div2 type="bibliography"><head>Internet Sources</head><p>Chimpanzoo - the Jane Goodall Institute <seg type="URL" n="http://www.chimpanzoo.org/ceboidea.html"/> - accessed 20/05/04 </p><p>Flannery, S - 'The Primates. <seg type="URL" n="http://members.tripod.com/uakari/cebus_capucinus.htmlaccessed"/> - accessed20/05/04</p><p>Mammalian Crania Picture Archive (MCPA) <seg type="URL" n="http://1kai.dokkyomed.ac.jp/mammal/en/species_all/cebus_apella.html"/> - accessed 21/05/04</p><p>Distrubution map <hi rend="bold"><seg type="URL" n="www.elderhostel.org/Programs/"/> map_intl_americas.as -</hi> accessed 20/05/04 </p></div2></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
