<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_3018b" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title></title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">
Starts with section (f).
</note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">Running text contains reference to external or missing appendix.
</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">2</p><p n="date">2003-05</p><p n="module title">Management Accounting for the H &amp; T Industries</p><p n="module code">U54030 (M03179)</p><p n="genre family">Proposal</p><p n="discipline">Hospitality, Leisure &amp; Tourism Management</p><p n="disciplinary group">SS</p><p n="grade">D</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">2643</p><p n="number of s-units">139</p><p n="number of p">125</p><p n="number of tables">0</p><p n="number of figures">0</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">19</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">32</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">19.0</p><p n="average s-units per p">1.1</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">f</p><p n="year of birth">1983</p><p n="first language">Chinese unspecified</p><p n="education">OSa</p><p n="course">BA Business and Hospitality</p><p n="student ID">3018</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><div1 type="toc" n="1"><head rend="bold">CONTENTS</head><p/></div1></front><body><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">f) Alternative Proposals</head><p n="p1.125"><s n="s1.1;p1.125">8 alternative proposals are suggested, all are with reference to the Contribution statement, Appendix (2-5) </s></p><p n="p2.125"><s n="s1.1;p2.125">They are: </s></p><list type="ordered"><item> 1) Raise the selling price by 5%</item><item>2) Raise only food prices by 5%</item><item>3) Raise only beverage prices by 10%</item><item>4) Increase in overall gross profit percentage from 47% to 50%</item><item>5) Increase all sales volume in the present sales mix by 5%</item><item>6) Reduction in permanent labour of £200.</item><item>7) Decrease the expenditure in other expenses by 20%</item><item>8) Launch an advertising campaign</item></list><div2><head rend="underlined">Business decision 1</head><p n="p3.125"><s n="s1.2;p3.125">Raise the selling price per cover. </s><s n="s2.2;p3.125">Assume that there is no change in sales volume, the whole of the price increase are regarded as an additional profit for the business </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p4.125"><s rend="italic" n="s1.1;p4.125">( Raise the selling price by 5% </s></p><p n="p5.125"><s n="s1.1;p5.125">With reference to Appendix 2, the proposed Average Spending Power is £8.40 </s></p><p n="p6.125"><s n="s1.1;p6.125">The effect of a 5% price increase is to decrease the variable cost percentage from 52.8% to 50.3%. </s></p><p n="p7.125"><s n="s1.1;p7.125">This results a higher contribution per unit (£4.18) , and requires 58 fewer covers to reach the break-even point </s></p><p n="p8.125"><s n="s1.1;p8.125">The new level of net profit,£625, is 81.16% higher than the original figure of £345. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">Business decision 2</head><p n="p9.125"><s n="s1.1;p9.125">Since the cost of food is high, with the assumption of no change in sales volume, raising the food price helps to cover the cost and obtain a higher contribution. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p10.125"><s rend="italic" n="s1.1;p10.125">(Raise only food prices by 5% </s></p><p n="p11.125"><s n="s1.1;p11.125">With reference to Appendix 2, the proposed ASP is £8.26 </s></p><p n="p12.125"><s n="s1.1;p12.125">The effect of a 5% increase in food changes the sales mix to 66% food, 33% beverage. </s></p><p n="p13.125"><s n="s1.1;p13.125">This results a higher contribution per unit (£4.04), and requires 39 fewer covers to reach the break-even point. </s></p><p n="p14.125"><s n="s1.1;p14.125">The new level of net profit,£527, is 52.75% higher than the original figure of £345. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">Business decision 3</head><p n="p15.125"><s n="s1.2;p15.125">Since the average spend on beverage is low (£2.8 per cover), raise the beverage price can improve the current profit. </s><s n="s2.2;p15.125">It is believed that customers are willing to pay as the change only costs a slight increase. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p16.125"><s rend="italic" n="s1.1;p16.125">( Raise only beverage prices by 10% (assume no change in sales volume) </s></p><p n="p17.125"><s n="s1.1;p17.125">With reference to Appendix 3, the proposed ASP is £8.28 </s></p><p n="p18.125"><s n="s1.1;p18.125">The effect of a 10% increase in food changes the sales mix to 62.8% food, 37.2% beverage. </s></p><p n="p19.125"><s n="s1.1;p19.125">This results a higher contribution per unit (£4.06), and requires 42 fewer covers to reach the break-even point. </s></p><p n="p20.125"><s n="s1.1;p20.125">The new level of net profit,£541, is 56.81% higher than the original figure of £345. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">Business decision 4</head><p n="p21.125"><s n="s1.1;p21.125">By increasing the gross profit margin, the cost of sales will decrease and the whole of the saving is thus regarded as an additional profit. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p22.125"><s rend="italic" n="s1.1;p22.125">( Increase in overall gross profit percentage from 47% to 50% </s></p><p n="p23.125"><s n="s1.1;p23.125">With reference to Appendix 3, </s></p><p n="p24.125"><s n="s1.1;p24.125">The cost of sales is decreased from 53% to 50%, thus there is an additional profit.£168 (3%) </s></p><p n="p25.125"><s n="s1.1;p25.125">This results a higher contribution per unit (£4.02), and requires 36 fewer covers to reach the break-even point. </s></p><p n="p26.125"><s n="s1.1;p26.125">The new level of net profit,£513, is 48.70% higher than the original figure of £345. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">Business decision 5</head><p n="p27.125"><s n="s1.1;p27.125">It is clearly that the higher level of sales, the more profit will be generated </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p28.125"><s rend="italic" n="s1.1;p28.125">( Increase all sales volume in the present sales mix by 5% </s></p><p n="p29.125"><s n="s1.1;p29.125">With reference to Appendix 4, the ASP is the same (i.e.£8.00) </s></p><p n="p30.125"><s n="s1.1;p30.125">The effect of a 5% increase in sales volume increases the net profit from 6.2% to 8.1%. </s></p><p n="p31.125"><s n="s1.1;p31.125">The new level of net profit is£477, which is 38.33% higher than the original figure of £345. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">Business decision 6</head><p n="p32.125"><s n="s1.2;p32.125">There is a large spend on paying full- time staff. </s><s n="s2.2;p32.125">The manager may decide to reduce the permanent labour so to lower the total fixed costs. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p33.125"><s rend="italic" n="s1.1;p33.125">( Reduction in permanent labour of £200. </s></p><p n="p34.125"><s n="s1.1;p34.125">With reference to Appendix 4, </s></p><p n="p35.125"><s n="s1.1;p35.125">The reduction in labour costs lowers the fixed cost to £2100, </s></p><p n="p36.125"><s n="s1.1;p36.125">This lowers the volume of contribution needed to break even requires 53 fewer covers. </s></p><p n="p37.125"><s n="s1.1;p37.125">Total cost is £200 less which means a corresponding increase in net profit. </s></p><p n="p38.125"><s n="s1.1;p38.125">The new level of net profit,£545, is 57.97% higher than the original figure of £345. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">Business decision 7</head><p n="p39.125"><s n="s1.2;p39.125">The other expenses accounts for a high proportion of the total expenditure (39%). </s><s n="s2.2;p39.125">It should reduce it so to obtain a lower figure. </s></p><p n="p40.125"><s n="s1.1;p40.125">With reference to Appendix 4, </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p41.125"><s rend="italic" n="s1.1;p41.125">( Decrease the expenditure in other expenses by 20% </s></p><p n="p42.125"><s n="s1.1;p42.125">The saving lowers the fixed cost to £2036 </s></p><p n="p43.125"><s n="s1.1;p43.125">This lowers the volume of contribution needed to break even requires 70 fewer covers. </s></p><p n="p44.125"><s n="s1.1;p44.125">Total cost is £264 less which means a corresponding increase in net profit. </s></p><p n="p45.125"><s n="s1.1;p45.125">The new level of net profit,£609, is 76.52% higher than the original figure of £345. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined">Business decision 8 </head><p n="p46.125"><s n="s1.1;p46.125">Promotion may raise customer's awareness; the number of customers is increased and so does the sales volume. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p47.125"><s rend="italic" n="s1.1;p47.125">( Launch an advertising campaign </s></p><p n="p48.125"><s n="s1.1;p48.125">Assumption- An advertising campaign costing £50 would increase the total sales by 10%. </s></p><p n="p49.125"><s n="s1.1;p49.125">With reference to Appendix 5, </s></p><p n="p50.125"><s n="s1.1;p50.125">It should be noted that as the total fixed costs is increased, the number of covers needed to reach the break-even point is higher, which requires 13 more covers. </s></p><p n="p51.125"><s n="s1.1;p51.125">However, the new level of net profit,£559.5, is 62.17% higher than the original figure of £345, which is a significant growth. </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">g) Comments</head><p n="p52.125"><s n="s1.1;p52.125">Besides cost control and financial management, there are several areas that the manager should take into account to improve the wealth of an operation: </s></p><list type="ordered"><item>Human resources</item><item>Food &amp; beverage</item><item>Service</item><item>Capacity management</item><item>Marketing</item></list></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold italic">Human Resources</head><p n="p53.125"><s n="s1.1;p53.125">This includes the management of relationship with customers and employees. </s></p><div2><head rend="underlined bold">Customer relations</head><p n="p54.125"><s n="s1.1;p54.125">Customer loyalty is an important determinant of profit. </s></p><p n="p55.125"><s n="s1.1;p55.125">Benefits of having loyal customers: </s></p><list type="bulleted"><head>• Repeat purchases generate long- term revenue streams </head><item>• Tend to increase spending over time </item><item>• More willing to pay premium prices </item><item>• Cost savings: - the cost to retain customers is much cheaper than attracting new ones.</item><item>- positive word-of month advertising attract more new customers</item></list><p n="p56.125"><s n="s1.1;p56.125">To ensure customer loyalty: The service outcome and experience should of a high standard and matches their </s></p><p n="p57.125"><s n="s1.1;p57.125">own needs that satisfies even delights customers. </s></p><p n="p58.125"><s n="s1.2;p58.125">Satisfaction is the outcome of the consumer's evaluation of a service. </s><s n="s2.2;p58.125">There are four attributes of satisfaction </s></p><p n="p59.125"><s n="s1.1;p59.125">and Dissatisfaction, stated by Cadotte and Turgeon (1988): </s></p><p n="p60.125"><s n="s1.1;p60.125">I) Hygiene factors: Have a low potential to delight customers, however they need to be in place otherwise it will be a source of dissatisfactions. </s></p><p n="p61.125"><s n="s1.1;p61.125">Areas include: </s></p><list type="bulleted"><head>• Availability of parking</head><item>• Traffic congestion at establishment</item><item>• Noise levels</item><item>• Spaciousness of establishment</item><item>• Hours of operation</item></list><p n="p62.125"><s n="s1.1;p62.125">II) Enhancing factors: Have a potential to delight if they are present, but are unlikely to dissatisfy customers if they are not in place. </s></p><list type="bulleted"><head>Areas include: </head><item>• Cleanliness of establishment </item><item>• Neatness of establishment </item><item>• Size of portions </item><item>• Employee appearance </item><item>• Responsiveness to complaints</item></list><p n="p63.125"><s n="s1.1;p63.125">III) Critical factors: Have a high potential that lead to customers delight and dissatisfaction. </s></p><p n="p64.125"><s n="s1.1;p64.125">Areas include: </s></p><list type="bulleted"><head>• Quality of service </head><item>• Food quality </item><item>• Helpful attitude of employees </item><item>• Prices of food &amp; beverage and service</item></list><p n="p65.125"><s n="s1.1;p65.125">IV) Neutral factors: Have little effect on satisfaction. </s></p><p n="p66.125"><s n="s1.1;p66.125">Areas include: </s></p><list type="bulleted"><head>• Management knowledge of service </head><item>• Availability of food on the menu </item><item>• Beverage quality </item><item>• Variety of service </item><item>• Uniformity of establishment's appearance </item><item>• Quality of advertising </item><item>• Convenience of the location </item><item>• Quietness of surroundings </item><item>• Accuracy of the bill </item><item>• Litter outside the restaurant </item><item>• Reservations system</item></list><p n="p67.125"><s n="s1.2;p67.125">The operations manager should realize which factors will delight and which will dissatisfy the customers in order to create external service value. </s><s n="s2.2;p67.125">Thus customers are retained and provide significant benefits for the restaurant. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined bold">Employee relations</head><p n="p68.125"><s n="s1.1;p68.125">In service-operations industry, activities are human-oriented therefore the staff is an important resource in </s></p><p n="p69.125"><s n="s1.2;p69.125">determining organizational effectiveness. </s><s n="s2.2;p69.125">The personal nature of restaurant service places emphasis on the </s></p><p n="p70.125"><s n="s1.1;p70.125">importance of direct interaction between employees and customers. </s></p><list type="bulleted"><head>In view of this, the manager should ensure the staff: </head><item>• Serve effectively</item><item>• Satisfy customers' needs</item><item>• Maintain a good relationship with customers</item><item>• Deliver high quality service</item><item>• Create guest-satisfying values</item><item>• Response and handling complaints appropriately</item></list><p n="p71.125"><s n="s1.1;p71.125">To maintain an effective workforce, this can be done by: </s></p><div3><head>I) <hi rend="underlined">Training </hi></head><p n="p72.125"><s n="s1.1;p72.125">This helps enhancing employees' knowledge and skills to perform their tasks </s></p><list type="bulleted"><head> It should be carried out when: </head><item>• New staff are employed </item><item>• Changes occurs due to new technology, legislation or redeveloped menus or concept.</item><item>• When staff do not perform to the required standard</item></list></div3><div3><head>II) <hi rend="underlined">Staff/ workforce scheduling</hi></head><list type="bulleted"><head>A staff/ workforce scheduling should be well-prepared to: </head><item>• Accommodate the shift pattern</item><item>• Ensure appropriate skill level cover</item><item>• Ensure appropriate levels of supervision</item><item>• Ensure days off and holiday requests</item><item>• Ensure fairness and maintains motivation and efficiency</item></list><p n="p73.125"><s n="s1.2;p73.125">With the use of staff/workforce scheduling, it helps to ensure staffing levels are sufficient to meet demand but not exceed it. </s><s n="s2.2;p73.125">At the same time, it achieves maximum productivity from each and every member of staff taking into account the need for appropriate staff welfare. </s></p><p n="p74.125"><s n="s1.3;p74.125">Tasks should be allocated according to employees' capabilities. </s><s n="s2.3;p74.125">Besides, it needs to ensure the staff understand their tasks clearly. </s><s n="s3.3;p74.125">Development of standards of performance or operating manuals with job description and specifications may play an important role. </s></p></div3><div3><head>III) <hi rend="underlined">Motivation</hi></head><p n="p75.125"><s n="s1.1;p75.125">Levels of performance are determined not only by the ability of staff but also by the strength of their motivation, which is derived from the fulfilment of an individual's needs and expectations. </s></p><p n="p76.125"><s n="s1.2;p76.125">With reference to the Herzberg's two actor theory, the manager should fulfil the hygiene factors to prevent employee dissatisfaction, alongside with the motivators to create an effective workforce. </s><s n="s2.2;p76.125">These include </s></p><p n="p77.125"><s n="s1.1;p77.125">praising employees when they do good work, providing a sense of achievement, increasing the level of responsibility of employees, and taking a proactive view of the organizational climate. </s></p></div3><div3><head>IV)<hi rend="underlined"> Empowerment </hi></head><p n="p78.125"><s n="s1.1;p78.125">As front- line staff communicate directly with customers, it's an opportunity for them to take control of those moments of truth that help building customer loyalty. </s></p><list type="bulleted"><head> Benefits of empowerment: </head><item>• Lead to happy, motivated employees</item><item> Deliver high quality of service</item><item> Low employee turnover (employee retention) </item><item>• Service issues are addressed faster and resolved more effectively </item><item>• Fewer interruptions of manager's time </item><item>• High productivity</item></list><p n="p79.125"><s n="s1.1;p79.125">Therefore, Jones (1994) states that operation manager should empower the workforce by providing specific guidelines with regards to the limits on their decision making; or flexible empowerment, which enables employees to make on-the-spot decisions in order to achieve customer satisfaction. </s></p></div3><div3><head>V) <hi rend="underlined">Teamwork </hi></head><p n="p80.125"><s n="s1.1;p80.125">As roles of staff (i.e. the front-lines employees in the restaurant) are interrelated, the performance of the organization may gain advantages when the employees work as a team: </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p81.125"><s n="s1.1;p81.125">• Complementary skills and experience exceed those of any one individual </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p82.125"><s n="s1.1;p82.125">obtains a more effective response to customer service and high level of customer satisfaction. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p83.125"><s n="s1.1;p83.125">• The employees work towards a common goal and there is effective communication among them. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p84.125"><s n="s1.1;p84.125">allows them to respond more flexibly to changing customer needs </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p85.125"><s n="s1.1;p85.125">• Through working in teams, staff build trust in others and in other's capabilities. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p86.125"><s n="s1.1;p86.125">maintains en effective service delivery system </s></p></div3></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold italic">Food and Beverage</head><p n="p87.125"><s n="s1.1;p87.125">There are several alternatives on the Food &amp; Beverage to gain competitive advantages: </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p88.125"><s n="s1.1;p88.125">• Promote new food items with special offer to attract customers </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p89.125"><s n="s1.3;p89.125">• Create a separate menu for kids. </s><s n="s2.3;p89.125">Provide children's favourite menu with child-size portion at lower prices. </s><s n="s3.3;p89.125">This attracts families with children. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p90.125"><s n="s1.1;p90.125">• As customers become more knowledgeable about nutrition and concern healthy eating, managers might provide the nutritional content of ingredients and menu items. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p91.125"><s n="s1.1;p91.125">• Furthermore, the restaurant can promote low calories menu items so to attract customers who are on diet and prefer light meals </s></p><div2><head rend="underlined">Product quality </head><p n="p92.125"><s n="s1.1;p92.125">To maintain profit growth and to differentiate itself from other competitors, the restaurant should maintain </s></p><p n="p93.125"><s n="s1.2;p93.125">high quality standards. </s><s n="s2.2;p93.125">Since quality is consistent performance to customers' expectations, (Slack et al, 1995), an understanding of customer expectations and their perceptions of quality are therefore a very important part of the management. </s></p><p n="p94.125"><s n="s1.1;p94.125">Benefits of improving and maintaining quality: </s></p><list type="bulleted"><head>• Builds customers loyalty </head><item>• Retains customers </item><item>• Focuses employees on providing a quality service </item><item>• Retention of good employees </item><item>• Reduction on costs </item><item>• Sustaining growth</item></list><p n="p95.125"><s n="s1.1;p95.125">To maintain high quality of products, this can be done by: </s></p><p n="p96.125"><s n="s1.1;p96.125">Quality assurance: Develop processes and procedures which prevent quality mistakes from occurring in the </s></p><p n="p97.125"><s n="s1.1;p97.125">first place. </s></p><list type="bulleted"><head>Several ways of assuring quality: </head><item>• Quality control</item><item>• Purchase specifications </item><item>• Inventory control to cut down costs</item><item>• Set standard recipes to ensure product consistency</item><item>• Set standards of performance, production</item><item>• Human resources practices</item><item>• Run quality audits </item><item>• Planned preventative maintenance</item></list></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold italic">Service</head><p n="p98.125"><s n="s1.1;p98.125">Since a meal experience involves both tangible (the food and beverage) and intangible products (the whole </s></p><p n="p99.125"><s n="s1.1;p99.125">service delivered to customers from the time they enter the restaurant to their departure), customer will expect </s></p><p n="p100.125"><s n="s1.1;p100.125">to pay for products and services and receive value from both tangibles and intangibles, therefore the </s></p><p n="p101.125"><s n="s1.1;p101.125">operations should maintain delivering a high quality service. </s></p><list type="bulleted"><head>To maintain a high quality of service: </head><item>• Provide training to staff: job training and customer care</item><item>• Supervision</item><item>• Spend more time talking to customers to get feedback </item><item>• Giving feedback results to employees </item><item>• Empowerment</item><item>• Measure performance and establish incentives</item><item>•Focus less on technology and more on behaviour</item><item>•Output oriented rather than input driven</item><item>• All staff become central to the pursuit of quality</item><item>• Create a quality culture that includes HR practices</item><item>• View quality from customer's perspective</item><item>• Total quality management: A holistic approach which involves the </item><item>entire organisation in meeting customer requirements habitually and competitively by doing the right things right first time.</item></list></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold italic">Capacity management</head><p n="p102.125"><s n="s1.1;p102.125">The management of capacity has a great impact on long term success. </s></p><list type="bulleted"><head>If resources are underutilised: </head><item>• Not enough revenue to cover the expenditure on expensive resources</item><item> poor financial results </item><item>• If the restaurant is empty, this gives a feeling to customers that the restaurant is unpopular and switch to other restaurants.</item><item>• Employees are demotivated</item><item> poor service attitudes</item><item> customer dissatisfaction</item><item> lower profitability</item></list><p n="p103.125"><s n="s1.1;p103.125">If resources are overstretched: </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p104.125"><s n="s1.1;p104.125">• If there is a sudden surge of customers, this increases the waiting time and staff pay less attention on customers' needs </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p105.125"><s n="s1.1;p105.125">strategy: poor service delivery </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p106.125"><s n="s1.1;p106.125">• As the employees are continually overloaded, they will probably make more mistakes </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p107.125"><s n="s1.1;p107.125">poor performance and lower customer satisfaction </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p108.125"><s n="s1.1;p108.125">• High staff turnover as they are demotivated </s></p><p n="p109.125"><s n="s1.1;p109.125">Therefore, the manager needs to put focus on capacity management to ensure the service process has sufficient </s></p><p n="p110.125"><s n="s1.1;p110.125">resources to deal with the anticipated levels of customer demand in the most cost-effective manner. </s></p><p n="p111.125"><s n="s1.1;p111.125">For a restaurant operation, a combination of the three capacity strategies can be employed: </s></p><list type="bulleted"><head>Level capacity strategy: </head><item>• Manufacture basic food materials as close to level as possible </item><item>• High utilization of process plant </item><item>• Use reservation and seating system as well as proper POS technology</item></list><list type="bulleted"><head>Chase strategy: </head><item>• Increase guest participation e.g. buffets, brunches, self-service stations</item><item>• Adjust employee capacity- scheduling (staggered schedules against shift blocks) </item><item>• Use of causal staff or part-timers to manage peaks </item><item>• Call in staff for demand surges </item><item>• Use cross-training employees to add capacity in "bottle-neck areas" </item><item>• Adjust kitchen capacity (menu variety and velocity, production methods) </item><item>• Adjust operating policies (having flexible operating hours)</item></list><list type="bulleted"><head>Demand management strategy</head><item>: • Use advertising and promotion to stimulate demand in quiet periods </item><item>• Special offers allow for bulk-purchasing discounts</item></list><p n="p112.125"><s n="s1.1;p112.125">Furthermore, emphasis should put on the management on the "coping" zone as well. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold italic">Marketing</head><p rend="bulleted" n="p113.125"><s n="s1.1;p113.125">Benefits of marketing: • Understand customer needs and satisfying local tastes </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p114.125"><s n="s1.1;p114.125">Offer guidelines when designing the mix of products and services that will satisfy them </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p115.125"><s n="s1.1;p115.125">• Understand the trends in the target market </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p116.125"><s n="s1.1;p116.125">Keep improvements on the current business so to prevent lagging behind. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p117.125"><s n="s1.1;p117.125">• By keeping customer records, helps realizing customers attitudes and purchasing habits, </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p118.125"><s n="s1.1;p118.125">and gaining repeat visits information. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p119.125"><s n="s1.1;p119.125">Operators can use these information to improve customer relations and create loyalty </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p120.125"><s n="s1.1;p120.125">• Understand competitors in the market </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p121.125"><s n="s1.1;p121.125">By learning from them such as their strengths and weaknesses, pricing policy and quality; manager can make improvements on the current business and create unique selling point to gain competitive advantage. </s></p><p n="p122.125"><s n="s1.1;p122.125">Therefore, manager should develop a marketing plan and do market research, alongside teaching employees </s></p><p n="p123.125"><s n="s1.1;p123.125">sell suggestively to improve sales. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold italic">Conclusion</head><p n="p124.125"><s n="s1.1;p124.125">With the use of the Service-Profit Chain (Heskett et al, 1994), we can conclude the way for the restaurant gains profit growth: </s></p><p n="p125.125"><s n="s1.1;p125.125">Internal service quality should firstly fulfilled, which includes employee relations, capacity management, control of finance and food &amp; beverage, marketing; this leads to </s></p><list type="bulleted"><item> Employee satisfaction</item><item> Employee retention and productivity</item><item> External service value</item><item> Customer satisfaction (since service designed and delivered to meet customers' needs)</item><item> Customer Loyalty (creates retention, repeat business and referral)</item><item> Revenue growth and Profitability</item></list></div1></body><back><div1 type="bibliography"><head rend="underlined bold italic">Bibliography</head><p>Cadotte, E.R, Turgeon, N. (1998) <hi rend="italic">"Key Factors in Guest Satisfaction" Cornell Hotel and Restaurant Administration Quarterly.</hi> Vol 28, No. 4, pp. 44-51</p><p>Harris, P. (1999). <hi rend="italic">Profit Planning.</hi> 2<hi rend="sup">nd</hi> ed. Hospitality Manager's pocket books, Oxford: Butterworth Heinemann</p><p>Jack, E, David, K Hayes &amp; Lea, R Dopson. (2002) <hi rend="italic">Food and Beverage Cost Control</hi>; 2<hi rend="sup">nd</hi> ed. John Wiley &amp; Sons, New York</p><p>Johnston, R &amp; Clark, G. (2001) <hi rend="italic">Service Operations Management;</hi> Financial Times, Prentice Hall, London</p><p>Kotas, R. (1999) <hi rend="italic">Management Accounting for hospitality and Tourism</hi>, 3<hi rend="sup">rd</hi> ed. International Thomson Business Press.</p><p>Kotas, R &amp; Michael, C (1997). 5<hi rend="sup">th</hi> ed. <hi rend="italic">Hospitality Accounting</hi> , ITP: Oxford </p><p>Laurie, M. (1998) 3<hi rend="sup">rd</hi>.ed. Managing People in the Hospitality Industry, Addison Wesley Longman Limited, pp.313-315</p><p>Robert Christie, M. (2001) <hi rend="italic">Restaurant Management, Customers, Operations, and Employee;</hi> 2<hi rend="sup">nd</hi> ed.Upper Saddle River, Prentice Hall, USA</p></div1><div1 type="missing or external appendix"><p/></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
