<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_3025a" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Marketing Communications Plan for Finance Latin America.com</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">The document has a title page which contains:
document title
title part</note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">
Student name and number in doc footer. Word count at the end of running text.
</note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">Running text contains reference to external or missing appendix.
</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">4</p><p n="date">2004-11</p><p n="module title">Marketing Management for Publishing</p><p n="module code">P65023</p><p n="genre family">Proposal</p><p n="discipline">Publishing</p><p n="disciplinary group">SS</p><p n="grade">D</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">2692</p><p n="number of s-units">120</p><p n="number of p">68</p><p n="number of tables">0</p><p n="number of figures">0</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">8</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">0</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">22.4</p><p n="average s-units per p">1.8</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">f</p><p n="year of birth">1958</p><p n="first language">English</p><p n="education">UKa</p><p n="course">MA Publishing</p><p n="student ID">3025</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><titlePart><hi rend="bold">P65023 Marketing Management for Publishing</hi><hi rend="bold"> Marketing Case Assignment</hi></titlePart><docTitle><titlePart rend="bold">Marketing Communications Planfor Finance Latin America.com</titlePart></docTitle><titlePart rend="bold">By <name type="student name"/> (<name type="student ID"/>)</titlePart><titlePart><hi rend="bold">Scenario 3 - Electronic Product</hi> Publisher: Haymarket Publishing Title: Finance Latin America</titlePart></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">Introduction</head><p n="p1.68"><s n="s1.2;p1.68">Haymarket Publishing is launching a new electronic information package in May 2005. </s><s n="s2.2;p1.68">Called Finance Latin America (see appendix i), it will draw on the success of our Finance Asia product, which has achieved over 1 million page views per month and, in 2002, was named Best Interactive Publication in Asia by the Society of Publishers in Asia. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">Situation Analysis</head><div2><head rend="bold italic">Why Latin America? </head><p n="p2.68"><s n="s1.1;p2.68">The Latin American and Caribbean regions are seen as slowly emerging markets that have much potential in the eyes of the financial world (see appendix ii). </s></p><div3><head rend="italic">Opportunities</head><p n="p3.68"><s n="s1.4;p3.68">Rodrigo de Rato, Managing Director of the International Monetary Fund, is optimistic about the economic future of Latin America. </s><s n="s2.4;p3.68">He says, "If economic growth can be maintained at its present level of between 4 and 5 percent over the next ten years, real per capita income in 2015 will be 40 percent higher than it is today ... a significant change from the relative stagnation of the last 25 years. </s><s n="s3.4;p3.68">This growth will play a major role in alleviating existing social tensions, improving the political environment, and shoring up democracy in the region." </s><s n="s4.4;p3.68">(See appendix iii). </s></p></div3><div3><head rend="italic">Other points to consider</head><p n="p4.68"><s n="s1.2;p4.68">Latin America must also show economic flexibility in responding to the rise of China as a world player. </s><s n="s2.2;p4.68">China competes with Latin America in terms of textiles and labour-intensive manufactured products, but China's constant struggle to feed itself means it is also a large importer of commodities from Latin America. </s></p><p n="p5.68"><s n="s1.1;p5.68">As Latin America's largest and closest neighbour, the United States keeps a close eye on economic developments and investment in the region. </s></p><p n="p6.68"><s n="s1.1;p6.68">Despite the relatively slow take up of information technology, Latin America is an open door for many new markets, but particularly for bankers, commodity brokers, consultants and investors. </s></p></div3></div2><div2><head rend="bold italic">Main Competitors to Finance Latin America</head><div3><head rend="italic">Direct competition</head><p n="p7.68"><s n="s1.1;p7.68"><hi rend="bold">Latin Finance (<seg type="URL" n="www.latinfinance.com"/>)</hi> holds much of the market in terms of the business, finance and investment community. </s></p><p n="p8.68"><s n="s1.3;p8.68">This magazine covers cross-border finance, business and investment in Latin America and the Caribbean. </s><s n="s2.3;p8.68">Its monthly circulation is more than 31,000. </s><s n="s3.3;p8.68">The magazine publishes in English. </s></p><p n="p9.68"><s n="s1.3;p9.68"><hi rend="bold">Latin Trade (<seg type="URL" n="www.latintrade.com"/>)</hi> is Latin America's largest pan-regional business magazine. </s><s n="s2.3;p9.68">It has been established for 12 years and it has a monthly readership of more than 86,000. </s><s n="s3.3;p9.68">It focuses more on general business and publishes in English, Spanish and Portuguese. </s></p></div3><div3><head rend="italic">Indirect competition</head><p n="p10.68"><s n="s1.2;p10.68"><hi rend="bold">Thomson Financial (<seg type="URL" n="www.thomsonfinancial.com"/>)</hi> provides financial IT solutions worldwide. </s><s n="s2.2;p10.68">It has a focus on Latin America. </s></p><p n="p11.68"><s n="s1.1;p11.68"><hi rend="bold">Reuters (</hi><seg type="URL" n="www.reuters.com"/>) is a large, international multimedia news agency, reporting extensively on topics ranging from financial markets to general and political news. </s></p><p n="p12.68"><s n="s1.2;p12.68"><hi rend="bold">Dow Jones &amp; Company (</hi><seg type="URL" n="www.dowjones.com"/>) publishes business and financial news and information. </s><s n="s2.2;p12.68">It provides data, analysis, and networking opportunities via a series of databases, publications, and events that focus on specialised sectors and markets (see appendix iv). </s></p><p n="p13.68"><s n="s1.2;p13.68"><hi rend="bold">World Trade Executives</hi> <hi rend="bold">(<seg type="URL" n="www.wtexec.com"/>)</hi> offers information to business, legal, and financial managers in international markets. </s><s n="s2.2;p13.68">With contributions from top executives in major corporations worldwide, WTE publications are practical, "how-to" guides for worldwide business operations. </s></p><p n="p14.68"><s n="s1.1;p14.68">These and similar sites will be targeted as affiliates or partners to Finance Latin America. </s></p></div3></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">Marketing Objectives</head><p n="p15.68"><s n="s1.1;p15.68">The aim of Finance Latin America is to become the definitive homepage for all financial professionals with an interest in Latin America. </s></p><div2><head rend="italic">How will we achieve this? </head><p n="p16.68"><s n="s1.1;p16.68">Through short-term objectives, which will be to build awareness. </s></p><list type="bulleted"><item>Achieve up to <hi rend="bold">13,000</hi> unique page hits per month, and <hi rend="bold">25,000</hi> views per month within the first six months of launch</item><item>Create a substantial base of link-exchange sites</item></list><p n="p17.68"><s n="s1.1;p17.68">Through longer-term aims, which will be to raise revenue. </s></p><list type="bulleted"><item>Increase unique page hits to <hi rend="bold">20,000</hi> and views per month to <hi rend="bold">100,000</hi> by the end of the first year</item><item>Build subscriptions to its newsletters to reach <hi rend="bold">6,000</hi> within 18 months of launch</item><item>Win partners and affiliates</item><item>Gain advertisers and sponsors</item></list></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">Target Audience</head><div2><head rend="italic">Who are we targeting? </head><list type="bulleted"><item>Commercial and investment bankers; professional CFO and CEOs; institutional investors; analysts and intermediaries</item><item>Organisations looking to invest in Latin American countries, according to financial sector (insurance, investment and banking), country of origin, size (turnover and employees) and demographic profiles</item></list><p n="p18.68"/></div2><div2><head rend="italic">What's in it for them? </head><list type="bulleted"><item>Keener insight into deals, markets, issuers and investors, enabling decision makers to stay ahead of the competition</item><item>Exclusive access to the plans of the institutions and the thoughts of those that drive Latin American financial markets</item><item>The chance to join a Web community of company executives, investors and bankers in the Latin American region</item><item>Low-cost and often free access to a host of financial information</item><item>Useful links to affiliated financial, travel and news sites relating to Latin America</item><item>Daily updated Web site</item><item>Real-time pricing</item><item>A link to investors worldwide, especially from Asia</item><item>Access to the best people through our contacts with business and law schools, and job agencies</item><item>Free subscriptions for partners and affiliates</item><item>Preferential rates for advocates of the site</item></list><p n="p19.68"/></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">Marketing Strategies</head><list type="bulleted"><item>Attract traffic to the site through newsletters and other e-mail campaigns, related links and discussion groups</item><item>Initially target financial executives in Europe and Asia to gain a foothold in the market presently dominated by Latin Finance (see appendix v) </item><item>Gain revenue through sponsorships and advertising from banks, brokers and consultants, and through subscription-only access to newsletters</item></list><p n="p20.68"/></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">Communications Objectives</head><list type="bulleted"><item>Increase awareness of the site through links, partnerships, affiliates, directory listings and advertising</item><item>Selecting the right keywords</item><item>Stimulate prospects to take up free trial of newsletter</item><item>Distribute promotional material at financial conferences</item></list><p n="p21.68"/></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">Communications Strategies </head><div2><head rend="bold italic">Choosing the Right Design</head><p n="p22.68"><s n="s1.2;p22.68">The first step in successful site promotion is to design our pages to be "search-engine friendly". </s><s n="s2.2;p22.68">This means not only using keywords appropriately, but also avoiding design techniques that can confuse search engines, such as frames and certain types of dynamic page delivery. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold italic">Selecting the Right Key Words</head><p n="p23.68"><s n="s1.3;p23.68">It's important to include all the words that someone might type into a search engine if they were looking for a site like ours (including misspellings). </s><s n="s2.3;p23.68">Most or all of these keywords should be found in the text of our home page. </s><s n="s3.3;p23.68">For example: </s></p><list type="simple"><item>Finance</item><item>Financial</item><item>Latin</item><item>Latin America</item><item>Latin American</item><item>South America</item><item>Americas</item><item>News</item><item>Investor</item><item>Publication</item><item>Markets</item><item>Bank</item><item>Magazine</item></list><p n="p24.68"><s n="s1.1;p24.68">We need to craft a brief site description that uses some of the keywords, and which sums up what our site has to offer - many search engines have a limit of 25 words. </s></p><p n="p25.68"><s n="s1.1;p25.68">A description might be: </s></p><p n="p26.68"><s n="s1.1;p26.68">"<hi rend="bold">Finance Latin America magazine</hi> provides <hi rend="bold">bank</hi>ers, CFOs and CEOs, institutional <hi rend="bold">investor</hi>s, analysts and intermediaries with selected free content and up-to-date <hi rend="bold">news</hi> on <hi rend="bold">Latin American financial markets</hi>." </s></p><p n="p27.68"><s n="s1.1;p27.68">We should try to mention a couple of site features that might entice people to visit. </s></p><p n="p28.68"><s n="s1.2;p28.68">This description should also be used in the title tag that appears in the head section of our html page. </s><s n="s2.2;p28.68">Some search engines assign greater weight to keywords that appear in the title tag. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold italic">Submitting the Site to Search Engines</head><p n="p29.68"><s n="s1.3;p29.68">We should submit our home page to all the major search engines. </s><s n="s2.3;p29.68">Using an autosubmitter will save time, see <seg type="URL" n="http://bagheera.sumix.com/"/>, for example. </s><s n="s3.3;p29.68">Almost all search engine traffic goes to the top twenty or thirty search engines (see appendices vi and vii). </s></p><p n="p30.68"><s n="s1.4;p30.68">The most important "search engines", including Yahoo and Google are more accurately described as "directories". </s><s n="s2.4;p30.68">Google is currently driving around 75 percent of the search engine traffic on the Web (see appendix viii). </s><s n="s3.4;p30.68">A directory does not use a "spider" to find sites to index. </s><s n="s4.4;p30.68">Instead, real people evaluate the sites submitted and choose those most suitable for listing. </s></p><p n="p31.68"><s n="s1.2;p31.68">This means that a directory includes far fewer general sites than search engines do. </s><s n="s2.2;p31.68">If we do get listed, we'll see our traffic climb immediately. </s></p><p n="p32.68"><s n="s1.2;p32.68">Getting listed can take anywhere from a few days to a few months so we need to check with search engines a month after submitting to them (see appendix ix). </s><s n="s2.2;p32.68">This gives us a chance to submit again if we're not in there. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold italic">Links</head><p n="p33.68"><s n="s1.4;p33.68">Advertising on link-exchange sites is one of the best and safest ways for new sites to achieve top rankings. </s><s n="s2.4;p33.68">Some sites let you submit a banner ad to them in return for placing their ad on your site. </s><s n="s3.4;p33.68">Every time someone sees the banner on your site, you earn credit towards displays of your banner on other member sites. </s><s n="s4.4;p33.68">For example <seg type="URL" n="http://fisher.osu.edu/fin/journal/jofsites.htm#lnk"/> has a possible link available to the J.P. Morgan Chase site. </s></p><p n="p34.68"><s n="s1.2;p34.68">All these links can appear on a special "links page" on our site. </s><s n="s2.2;p34.68">The links page could become a valuable resource in its own right, building more traffic for our site. </s></p><div3><head rend="italic">Examples of potential link exchanges</head><list type="bulleted"><item>Financial Institutions - International Monetary Fund, the Association of Latino Professionals in Finance and Accounting and the International Finance Corporation (IFC)</item><item>Banks - the World Bank, Inter-American Development Bank</item><item>Headhunters/Recruitment Agencies - <seg type="URL" n="www.efinancialcareers.com"/>, LatPro.com</item><item>Conference/Seminar/Training Organisers - <seg type="URL" n="www.financial-conferences.com"/></item><item>Law Firms - Hieros Gamos</item><item>Financial Technology - SAP, PeopleSoft, Thomson Financial</item><item>Rating Agencies - Standard &amp; Poors</item><item>Product/Information Providers - SSRN-Latin American Network, Center for Latin American Capital Markets and Fundación Gobierno y Sociedad</item><item>Business Schools - Harvard Business School, ENPC School of International Management and Instituto Centroamericano de Admistración de Empresas</item><item>Airlines and Hotels - Aerolineas Argentinas, Lanchille, Tam Brazilian, United Airlines, Hyatt Hotels</item><item>News and Media - Reuters, Dow Jones and The Economist</item></list><p n="p35.68"/></div3></div2><div2><head rend="bold italic">Trade Shows</head><p n="p36.68"><s n="s1.1;p36.68">Before and after May 2005, press releases announcing the launch of the site should be sent to the press offices at various financial seminars and conferences that focus on Latin America. </s></p><p n="p37.68"><s n="s1.2;p37.68">Delegate lists should also be e-mailed and offered information about the launch and a chance to obtain free trials of our newsletter. </s><s n="s2.2;p37.68">There are many conferences to which this could apply (see appendix x). </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold italic">Newsgroups and Discussion Forums</head><p n="p38.68"><s n="s1.1;p38.68">There are very few quality sources focusing solely on Latin America (see appendix xi). </s></p><p n="p39.68"><s n="s1.5;p39.68">Yahoo Groups is one option. </s><s n="s2.5;p39.68">There are two ways to generate traffic through Yahoo Groups (see appendix xii). </s><s n="s3.5;p39.68">The first is by submitting our ad to groups that are specifically looking for ads. </s><s n="s4.5;p39.68">The second is by providing a free service, such as a business advice article or a free e-book and then adding our resource box at the bottom, giving a link to the Web site. </s><s n="s5.5;p39.68">I would suggest doing both if we want to get the best results. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold italic">Sponsors/Partners</head><p n="p40.68"><s n="s1.4;p40.68"><hi rend="bold">EmergingPortfolio.com Fund Research</hi> <hi rend="bold">(<seg type="URL" n="www.emergingportfolio.com"/>)</hi> tracks equity and bond fund flows, country flows, country and sector allocations, and company holdings data. </s><s n="s2.4;p40.68">International analysts, strategists and portfolio managers use this data. </s><s n="s3.4;p40.68">The firm also provides qualitative analysis on international markets. </s><s n="s4.4;p40.68">It produces monthly regional Navigator reports, one of which focuses on Latin America. </s></p><p n="p41.68"><s n="s1.1;p41.68">This site could be considered as a link exchange, but it would also be a suitable sponsor. </s></p><p n="p42.68"><s n="s1.2;p42.68"><hi rend="bold">Organisation for Economic Co-operation and Development (<seg type="URL" n="www.oecd.org"/>)</hi> The Latin America Programme was established in 2001 as a response to the growing importance of the region for the OECD. Activities developed under the programme are complementary to other international institutions active in the region (IMF and World Bank). </s><s n="s2.2;p42.68">Some of these activities are developed in partnership with other international organisations. </s></p><p n="p43.68"><s n="s1.1;p43.68">This non-profit making organisation could be a possible affiliate. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold italic">Advertising</head><p n="p44.68"><s n="s1.2;p44.68"><hi rend="bold">Haymarket Business Interactive (<seg type="URL" n="www.haymarketbusinessinteractive.com"/>)</hi> can design, develop and execute advertising campaigns for us using its industry-standard ad-serving platform. </s><s n="s2.2;p44.68">It has its own network of targeted B2B sites. </s></p><div3><head rend="italic">Paid advertising on other sites</head><p n="p45.68"><s n="s1.1;p45.68">To get results from banner ads, we need to spend a great deal of money, and we need to be prepared to refine both the banners and their placement on an ongoing basis. </s></p><p n="p46.68"><s n="s1.1;p46.68">Mailing list ads, however, are generally far cheaper, and often reach much more finely targeted audiences than banner ads. </s></p></div3><div3><head rend="italic">Press advertising</head><p n="p47.68"><s n="s1.1;p47.68">Advertising in the trade press prior to and just after the launch would encourage journalists to use our editorial, but again, it is very expensive. </s></p></div3><div3><head rend="italic">Google AdWords</head><p n="p48.68"><s n="s1.3;p48.68">Google AdWords can help us reach people that are actively looking for financial products and services. </s><s n="s2.3;p48.68">That means we are more likely to receive targeted customers. </s><s n="s3.3;p48.68">Pricing is on a cost-per-click basis so we only pay when visitors click on our ad, and it's easy to control costs. </s></p></div3><div3><head rend="italic">Advertising through affiliate programmes</head><p n="p49.68"><s n="s1.3;p49.68">E-mail lists can be promoted through an affiliate programme. </s><s n="s2.3;p49.68">One can be easily set-up at zero cost (see <seg type="URL" n="http://listpartners.com"/>). </s><s n="s3.3;p49.68">We then pay our affiliates a small commission per subscriber, or credit them with advertising impressions in our newsletter (see appendix xiii). </s></p></div3></div2><div2><head rend="bold italic">E-Mail Programmes</head><p n="p50.68"><s n="s1.2;p50.68">Research shows that most traffic-driving initiatives generate less than a 5 percent conversion rate (see appendix xiv). </s><s n="s2.2;p50.68">The key to a profitable return-on-investment rests on the ability to gather accurate information about site visitors and get permission to contact them. </s></p><div3><head rend="italic">How can we create successful traffic driving initiatives? </head><p n="p51.68"><s rend="bold" n="s1.3;p51.68">By contacting our existing database. </s><s n="s2.3;p51.68">Our e-mailing campaigns will start with our Finance Asia and Finance China databases. </s><s n="s3.3;p51.68">We will also contact the more general advertisers on our site like HSBC. We would encourage contacts to forward our e-mail to a friend who might be interested in the new content. </s></p><p n="p52.68"><s n="s1.3;p52.68">The most popular house lists generally receive open rates of less than 40 percent. </s><s n="s2.3;p52.68">The average clicked through rate hovers between 6 percent and 10 percent (see appendix xv). </s><s n="s3.3;p52.68">Regardless of verification, a certain percentage of prospects will still bounce, and we should anticipate an average 10 percent bounce rate. </s></p><p n="p53.68"><s rend="bold" n="s1.2;p53.68">By using premium content to obtain reader e-mail addresses. </s><s n="s2.2;p53.68">Premium content is limited-distribution, high-value information sent to prospects in exchange for their e-mail addresses and permission to contact them again in the future. </s></p><p n="p54.68"><s n="s1.2;p54.68">Premium content includes articles that focus on particular issues or in-depth treatment of specialised topics. </s><s n="s2.2;p54.68">It can also consist of comment on current economic and social trends. </s></p><p n="p55.68"><s rend="bold" n="s1.3;p55.68">By encouraging sign-up from visitors to the site. </s><s n="s2.3;p55.68">We need to give our e-mail recipients a reason to visit our site, and to eventually link or advertise with us. </s><s n="s3.3;p55.68">We should arouse their curiosity by offering them a valuable information premium they can download when they visit. </s></p><p n="p56.68"><s n="s1.3;p56.68">To build up our lists, visitors will be invited to fill out a form with their name, e-mail address and other details. </s><s n="s2.3;p56.68">A good way to bring this form to the attention of visitors is to use a "pop-in" box. </s><s n="s3.3;p56.68">For an example pop-in box see (<seg type="URL" n="http://optinlightning.com"/>). </s></p><p n="p57.68"><s n="s1.2;p57.68">Any offer should include an opt-in check box for permission to contact the prospect. </s><s n="s2.2;p57.68">For those that choose to receive messages, any e-mails sent from our site would be permission-based and legally protected. </s></p><p n="p58.68"><s n="s1.1;p58.68">When soliciting prospects' e-mail addresses, we must never forget to always include our privacy statement, which should state that we would never rent, sell or share their addresses. </s></p><p n="p59.68"><s rend="bold" n="s1.3;p59.68">By taking advantage of free list-building services. </s><s n="s2.3;p59.68">Most work on a simple multilevel referral system. </s><s n="s3.3;p59.68">Not only do these generate more subscribers, but they also help to save money (see appendix xvi). </s></p></div3></div2><div2><head rend="bold italic">E-Mail Newsletters</head><p n="p60.68"><s n="s1.3;p60.68">Our e-mail newsletters should be as genuinely helpful as possible. </s><s n="s2.3;p60.68">Short nuggets of information should be offered on a regular basis and our URL should always be promoted in the e-mail signature. </s><s n="s3.3;p60.68">Readers are busy and will respond favourably to concise, easily digested information. </s></p><p n="p61.68"><s n="s1.2;p61.68">Incentives for advertising in our newsletters will include free or reduced subscriptions. </s><s n="s2.2;p61.68">To encourage subscribers, we could have special offers on affiliated sites like those of The Economist or the FT. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold italic">Editorial</head><p n="p62.68"><s n="s1.1;p62.68">We should submit editorial content to financial publications before the launch, but we have no guarantee that this would be accepted unless we accompany it with some advertising. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold italic">Testimonials</head><p n="p63.68"><s n="s1.1;p63.68">Adding a few testimonials to our Web page or ad copy is one of the cheapest, most effective ways to immediately boost response rates. </s></p><p n="p64.68"><s n="s1.1;p64.68">Most people like seeing their words and their names in print, so whenever a reader writes a particularly favourable comment, we need to immediately ask them for permission to use it. </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="underlined bold">Additional Strategies for Future Consideration </hi> (see appendix xvii)</head><p n="p65.68"/></div1><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="underlined bold">Campaign Schedule </hi> (see appendix xviii)</head><p n="p66.68"/></div1><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="underlined bold">Budget </hi> (see appendix xix)</head><p n="p67.68"/></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">Conclusion</head><p n="p68.68"><s n="s1.3;p68.68">We should build on the reputation of the Finance Asia site to reach prospects for the new site. </s><s n="s2.3;p68.68">The best ways of reaching our desired target market are through carefully targeted links and by sending informative, permission-based e-mails that include free, premium content. </s><s n="s3.3;p68.68">An advertising campaign in the trade press is too expensive for all but the biggest financial companies, but there are many established sites that would be useful affiliates and where advertising exchanges would bring in prospects and potential revenue. </s></p></div1></body><back><div1 type="missing or external appendix"><p/></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
