<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_3028b" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Geladas: Cognitive implications for the evolution of human language.</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">The document has a title page which contains:
figure</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">2</p><p n="date">2004-06</p><p n="module title">Human and other primates</p><p n="module code">M07342</p><p n="genre family">Essay</p><p n="discipline">Anthropology</p><p n="disciplinary group">SS</p><p n="grade">D</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">4341</p><p n="number of s-units">143</p><p n="number of p">37</p><p n="number of tables">0</p><p n="number of figures">4</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">1</p><p n="number of lists">2</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">5</p><p n="abstract present">abstract present</p><p n="average words per s-unit">30.4</p><p n="average s-units per p">3.9</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">m</p><p n="year of birth">1976</p><p n="first language">English</p><p n="education">UKa</p><p n="course">BSc hons. Anthropology/Philosophy</p><p n="student ID">3028</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><figure id="BAWE_3028b-pic.001"/><titlePage><docTitle><titlePart>Geladas: Cognitive implications for the evolution of human language. </titlePart></docTitle><titlePart><name type="student name"/><name type="student ID"/></titlePart></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="abstract"><p n="p1.37"><s n="s1.3;p1.37">Studies of geladas could provide beneficial insight into the determining selective pressures of the evolutionary origin of the human cognitive capacity of spoken language. </s><s n="s2.3;p1.37">In light of studies centred around Robin Dunbar, it appears geladas are balanced on an evolutionary threshold, the point where primate grooming is longer sufficiently efficient as the principle cognitive mechanism for social bonding due to their unusually large 'cognitive' group sizes in gelada societies. </s><s n="s3.3;p1.37">Indeed it appears there has been sufficient selective pressure for the adaptation of 'vocal grooming' to arise, which could provide a clue to the evolutionary origins of human language. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_3028b-pic.002"/></div1><div1 type="section"><head>Introduction</head><p n="p2.37"><s n="s1.4;p2.37">Many theories of the origin of language tend to focus on the way language is designed to subserve its primary purpose, that is the communication of information (Pinker 1994), much in the way of; <hi rend="italic">"there are mammoths beyond that hill right now",</hi> or <hi rend="italic">"this is how you made a hand axe"</hi>. </s><s n="s2.4;p2.37">There are several problems with placing the evolutionary determinant basis on this cognitive function alone: Studies of what people actually talk about in both modern societies (Dunbaral. 1997) and in more traditional ones (Haviland 1991) suggest most conversations revolve around social topics. </s><s n="s3.4;p2.37">We use instructional forms of language only occasionally, and then in rather specialised contexts. </s><s n="s4.4;p2.37">Teaching someone how to make simple articles such as a pot or a hand axe for example are best done by visual demonstration of the non-verbal nature, rather than by verbal instruction which would appear limited to utterances in the way of <hi rend="italic">"do you see what I am doing...?"</hi>. </s></p><p n="p3.37"><s n="s1.9;p3.37">There is much debate between factions over timing of the origins of language. </s><s n="s2.9;p3.37">Those who favour a late date for language emergence favour language to have evolved in its fully developed modern symbolic form, in much the way of Pinker (1994) 'the big band', presumably by way of the evolution of gestural communication, the 'spoken word' adopting it in a 'big bang' all of a sudden in a cognitive revolution for an innate syntactic cognitive architecture that was already in place being utilised for gestural communication. </s><s n="s3.9;p3.37">Indeed there has been much recent work on the discovery of mirror neurons in neuroscience, first discovered in macaques, but now have also been observed in humans in the superior temporal sulcus and Broca's area, both associated with cognitive language capacity (Rizzolatti and Arbib 1998). </s><s n="s4.9;p3.37">Although, if we look at modern human anatomy there is no tangible evidence of such a revolution, evidence shows substantial morphological adaptations that must have co-evolved with the development of spoken syntactic language. </s><s n="s5.9;p3.37">Those who favour an earlier, more gradual emergence of language favour a more primitive functional basis's, such as that of 'vocal grooming' as possibly evident in geladas. </s><s n="s6.9;p3.37">Aiello and Dunbar (1993) suggested that we should view language evolution as involving at least three definable stages: an early contentless form of vocal grooming, a purely social content phase, and a fully modern phase of a symbolic representational semantic system. </s><s n="s7.9;p3.37">It is this form of the evolution of language this essay is based in. </s><s n="s8.9;p3.37">The physical constraints of this essay limit further discussion of the 'big bang' thesis, both of which have their plausibility. </s><s n="s9.9;p3.37">The essay will develop with reference to the semantic referential systems observed in the smaller scale societies of vervet monkeys (Cheney and Seyfarth 1996). </s></p><figure id="BAWE_3028b-pic.003"><head>Gelada reproductive group comprised of lead male and his harem of related females, 3-20 individuals</head></figure><p n="p4.37"><s n="s1.1;p4.37"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_3028b-form.001"/> </s></p><p n="p5.37"><s n="s1.3;p5.37">Taxonomy <hi rend="italic">Theropithecus gelada</hi> was believed to be part of the <hi rend="italic">Papio</hi> genus until 1979. </s><s n="s2.3;p5.37">It is now considered the sole surviving member of a widespread historical radiation of <hi rend="italic">Theropithecus</hi> during the Pleistocene and Pliocene epochs which once contained a species the size of a gorilla. </s><s n="s3.3;p5.37">Archaeological remains show <hi rend="italic">Theropithecus</hi> were hunted by early Hominids (Fleagle 1999). </s></p><p n="p6.37"><s n="s1.5;p6.37">Distinguishing Characteristics Male geladas have large shaggy manes of hair. </s><s n="s2.5;p6.37">Both sexes have a naked bright pink hourglass shape on their chest, a sexual displays such as estrus in females is signalled by bumps in the skin residing on the female's chest as opposed to the general position in primates on the rear of the female. </s><s n="s3.5;p6.37">This has been determined by the feeding habits of geladas, long periods of time spend sitting on an individuals rear feeding have moved the necessity of sexual display to the chest of the individual. </s><s n="s4.5;p6.37">The thumb of the Gelada is relatively long and more opposable than any other Old World Primate (Fleagle 1999). </s><s n="s5.5;p6.37">Geladas also have one of the largest sexual dimorphisms in all primates. </s></p><p n="p7.37"><s n="s1.5;p7.37">Physical Characteristics <hi rend="bold"> Head and body length:</hi> female 500-650mm, male 690-740mm. </s><s n="s2.5;p7.37"><hi rend="bold">Tail length:</hi> female 325-400mm, male 460-500mm. </s><s n="s3.5;p7.37"><hi rend="bold">Weight:</hi> female 11.7kg, male 20.0kg. </s><s n="s4.5;p7.37"><hi rend="bold">Intermembral index:</hi> 100. </s><s n="s5.5;p7.37">(Rowe 1996). </s></p><p n="p8.37"><s n="s1.2;p8.37">Habitat Simian mountains, Ethiopia. </s><s n="s2.2;p8.37">Montane grassland with no tall trees, only at altitudes 1400-4400m. </s></p><p n="p9.37"><s n="s1.2;p9.37">Diet Mostly composed of grass and grass seed (Gramineae) (Strummbach 1987), but includes leaves and bulbs. </s><s n="s2.2;p9.37">Animal pray such as insects and small mammals are occasioned (Dunbar 1977). </s></p><p n="p10.37"><s n="s1.8;p10.37">Life History <hi rend="bold"> Weaning:</hi> 15 months. </s><s n="s2.8;p10.37"><hi rend="bold">Sexual maturity:</hi> female 49.5 months. </s><s n="s3.8;p10.37"><hi rend="bold">Estrus Cycle:</hi> 35.7 days. </s><s n="s4.8;p10.37"><hi rend="bold">Gestation:</hi> 150-180 days <hi rend="bold">.</hi> </s><s n="s5.8;p10.37"><hi rend="bold">Life Span:</hi> 19.2 years. </s><s n="s6.8;p10.37">Births are possible year round, but peak between June and July, November and December. </s><s n="s7.8;p10.37">The female's sexual display on chest changes from pink to scarlet 4 to 8 weeks during pregnancy. </s><s n="s8.8;p10.37">(Rowe 1996). </s></p><p n="p11.37"><s n="s1.1;p11.37">Locomotion Quadrupedal </s></p><p n="p12.37"><s n="s1.6;p12.37">Social Structure Multi-male multi-female. </s><s n="s2.6;p12.37">The basic reproductive unit consists of 1 male and his harem of related females (3-20) (Fleagle 1999). </s><s n="s3.6;p12.37">The composition of large bands consists of as well as the male and his harem large units of all males, the 'bachelor pack' always on the look out for week harem leader of whom to dispose and take over the females (Attenborough 2000). </s><s n="s4.6;p12.37">These two types of units can form into bands, and several bands may temporarily form herds of up to 600 individuals. </s><s n="s5.6;p12.37"><hi rend="bold">Emigration:</hi> Males emigrate; females stay in their natal group (Wolfheim 1983). </s><s n="s6.6;p12.37"><hi rend="bold">Group Size:</hi> Reproductive unit, 3-20, band, 30-600 (Fleagle </s></p><p n="p13.37"><s n="s1.4;p13.37">1999). </s><s n="s2.4;p13.37"><hi rend="bold">Home range:</hi> 344ha. </s><s n="s3.4;p13.37"><hi rend="bold">Day Range:</hi> 1500m. </s><s n="s4.4;p13.37">Geladas have relatively small range for a baboon related primate of only 1 to 2 kilometres reflecting both the small foraging units and sedentary feeding habits of geladas (Fleagle 1999). </s></p><p n="p14.37"><s n="s1.8;p14.37">Behaviour Diurnal and terrestrial. </s><s n="s2.8;p14.37">Geladas spend the majority of their days sitting on tough ischial callosities an adaptation for their feeding habits to pluck grass with their hands. </s><s n="s3.8;p14.37">They spend their mornings for 2 hours in social activity, such as grooming (Dunbar 1977). </s><s n="s4.8;p14.37">50-60% of their activity budget is taken up by periodical feeding during the day. </s><s n="s5.8;p14.37">Infanticide has been observed in gelada populations when a harem leader was usurped by the leader of the 'bachelor pack' (Mori et al., 1997), but it is also known for the usurped male to form a coalition with the new lead male of the harem for addition protection against other bachelor packs, in exchange for the protection of the usurped males offspring (Attenborough 2000). </s><s n="s6.8;p14.37">The "lip flip" is a fear grimace in which the upper lip in inverted to show the teeth and gums completely covering the nostrils. </s><s n="s7.8;p14.37">Dominance or threat is expressed by the flashing of pale eyelids by the retraction of the scalp. </s><s n="s8.8;p14.37"><hi rend="bold">Sleeping site:</hi> Rock cliff faces (Wolfheim 1983). </s></p><figure id="BAWE_3028b-pic.004"><head>Adult males are substantially larger than females in geladas. </head></figure><figure id="BAWE_3028b-pic.005"/></div1><div1 type="section"><head>Behavioural and Ecological Determinants of Gelada Group Size</head><p n="p15.37"><s n="s1.9;p15.37">As also studied by, and concurred as above Strummbach (1987) geladas living on the Ethiopian highland steppe have a rich resource of food and plentiful access to water holes. </s><s n="s2.9;p15.37">This is reflected in their daily ranges being only in the region of 1 to 2 kilometres. </s><s n="s3.9;p15.37">The time Geladas spent feeding and moving represents up to 50 to 70 per cent of daily activity, the explanation of which being the abundant but lower energy food source of grass and grass seed (Graminae) but is supplemented by nutritionally rich roots, bulbs and occasional small mammals. </s><s n="s4.9;p15.37">Food is sufficiently abundant and nutritionally sufficient to support very high density populations in the habitat range (63 per km sq.). </s><s n="s5.9;p15.37">Geladas live in multi-level societies dominated by OMUs (one male units) consisting of matrilineal related harems of females, reproductive units each containing up to 30 individuals, OMUs cluster together to form close associations with other OMUs, and can join together to form bands (Dunbar 1975). </s><s n="s6.9;p15.37">Membership of OMUs to these bands is not constant, since OMUs may join other bands, or spend daytime hours alone. </s><s n="s7.9;p15.37">In addition to OMUs are all male groups (AMG) formed by young bachelors who do not have a harem of their own as a reproductive strategy. </s><s n="s8.9;p15.37">AMGs sometimes travel separately to bands, and are feared by OMUs due to attacks, placing great selective pressures on the social organization of OMU bands. </s><s n="s9.9;p15.37">Another level of social organization in geladas is the herd, which maybe should not be considered a social group in the strict sense, but rather temporary congregations of multiple bands at sites where feeding conditions are most favourable. </s></p><p n="p16.37"><s n="s1.3;p16.37">Sub-adult males may become harem leaders by either one of two reproductive strategies: Firstly, they can adopt the 'follower strategy' by which they closely follow an OMU building up close relationships with young females and weak grooming relationships with the lead male, and will attempt to form a new OMU when the time permits (Strummbach 1987). </s><s n="s2.3;p16.37">Or, secondly a young male can join an AMG. As clearly illustrated by Attenborough (2000), AMGs will attack OMU males with the intent of dominating the females within, AMGs lead by an alpha male specifically locate what they perceive to be weak OMU leaders. </s><s n="s3.3;p16.37">OMU males live in constant threat of AMGs, including the females within the OMU on most occasions, as infanticide has been observed upon the usurpation of an OMU by an AMG. Upon victory of an AMG over a OMU male, females have alternative choices; if they disapprove of the AMG they can either abandon the AMG group immediately to join another OMU, or alternatively in acceptance of the takeover all members of the AMG will mate with all the females, functionally as reward for services in the AMG, followed by the domination of the alpha male of the AMG of the females to form a new OMU. It is know for one or more OMU group to band together to form a coalition against AMG attack, OMU males fighting side by side (Attenborough 2000). </s></p><p n="p17.37"><s n="s1.2;p17.37">This basic description of gelada society emphasises the importance of social alliance and strategies, and the internal pressure and defence mechanisms that determine benefits of large group sizes enabled by a resource rich ecological environment. </s><s n="s2.2;p17.37">We are now in a position to outline some of the ecological and behavioural determinants of the large social group sizes of geladas: </s></p><list type="bulleted"><item>Abundant food resources enable large high density populations.</item><item>Socially complex high density societies.</item><item>Nutritional adequacy provides potential for cognitive basis of social networks.</item><item>Internal conflict pressures with AMGs and OMUs over sexual resources have determined reciprocal alliance bonds between reproductive groups.</item><item>Protection from predators (Iwamoto 1996).</item></list></div1><div1 type="section"><head>'Cognitive Groups'</head><p n="p18.37"><s n="s1.4;p18.37">The term 'cognitive group' refers to the amount of individuals a single individual is socially intimately acquainted with. </s><s n="s2.4;p18.37">There is direct correlation in primates with the size of the neocortex (associated with higher cognitive functions) in ratio to the remaining volume of the brain, and also to the size of the cognitive group the individual of the particular species is capable of having (figure 1). </s><s n="s3.4;p18.37">In Humans this figure is around 150, as Dunbar (1993, 1996) puts it: the value of 150 can probably be equated with the number of individuals that you know well enough to ask a favour of, or perhaps would feel comfortable about joining uninvited if you just happened to meet in an exotic location. </s><s n="s4.4;p18.37">Geladas have an unusually large neocortex ratio, as is reflected in their large 'cognitive group' size. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_3028b-fig.001"><head>Figure 1 Mean social group size increases with relative neocortex volume (indexed as the ratio of neocortex volume of the rest of the brain) for new world monkeys and old world monkeys (filled symbols) and apes (open symbols). Each data-point represents a different genus, though in most cases based on a single species. The ape genera are (from left to right) gibbons, gorillas and chimpanzees (Dunbar 1992). </head></figure></div1><div1 type="section"><head>The Evolution of 'Vocal Grooming' </head><p n="p19.37"><s n="s1.2;p19.37">Dunbar (1993, 1996) argues that the principal function of language is the exchange of social interactive information ('gossip' in a broad sense) and that language evolved to support cohesion within large social groups. </s><s n="s2.2;p19.37">The issue preliminarily revolves around two key assumptions: </s></p><figure id="BAWE_3028b-fig.002"><head>figure 2 Mean group size plotted against neocortex ratio, neocortex volume divided by volume of the rest of the brain. For new world and old world monkey (solid symbols) and ape (open symbols) genera. The open square marks the observed mean size of clanlike groupings in contemporary and recent hunter-gatherers (Dunbar 1993).</head></figure><p rend="ordered" n="p20.37"><s n="s1.1;p20.37">Social group size correlates closely with relative neocortex size in primates as a whole (figure 1), humans seeming to fit neatly into this pattern with 'cognitive' group sizes in the order of 150 individuals (figure 2). </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p21.37"><s n="s1.1;p21.37">The other is the suggestion that social grooming is the principal mechanism for bonding their groups. </s></p><p n="p22.37"><s n="s1.2;p22.37">We do not exactly understand how grooming achieves this, or the genetic adaptational basis of grooming itself, though it seems likely that it has something to do with the fact that grooming is particularly good at releasing endogenous opiates (Kerverneal. 1989). </s><s n="s2.2;p22.37">The feelings of pleasure and contentment in the partner, and this in turn may facilitate alliance formation and the reciprocation of many other social and reproductive benefits. </s></p><p n="p23.37"><s n="s1.4;p23.37">Robert Trivers (1971) theory in 'The Evolution of Reciprocal Altruism' offers an evolutionary mathematical explanation for the evolution of reciprocally altruistic acts such as grooming in primates. </s><s n="s2.4;p23.37">The theory follows that altruistic behaviour can evolve in a balanced relationship of interacting individuals that is beneficial for both. </s><s n="s3.4;p23.37">In these reciprocal relationships individuals can turn being the actor and recipient, in this respect reciprocal altruism is favoured by selection because over time the fitness gained by the reciprocal acts outweighs the cost incurred. </s><s n="s4.4;p23.37">Boyd and Silk (2003: 222) suggest there are three conditions occurring together that favour the development of reciprocal altruism, individuals must: </s></p><list type="ordered"><item>have opportunity to interact often,</item><item>have the ability to keep track of support given and received, and</item><item>provide support only to those who help them,</item></list><p n="p24.37"><s n="s1.6;p24.37">It is important to note that exchange does not have to be in kind. </s><s n="s2.6;p24.37">As shown with vervet monkeys (Cheney &amp; Seyfarth 1996) and other primates such as chimpanzees, for example, the act of grooming an individual can be reciprocated by the recipient by way of political coalitionary support, and other such examples. </s><s n="s3.6;p24.37">The big problem with reciprocal altruism is that it is costly to interact with individuals who do not reciprocate. </s><s n="s4.6;p24.37">Thus human cognition (and the cognition of other relevant mammals) should be attune to look for cheaters in social exchanges. </s><s n="s5.6;p24.37">Game theory, such as the 'Prisoner's Dilemma' explored by Axelrod (1984) (also in collaboration with W.D. Hamilton, 1981) demonstrates the logical problems of a behaviour for exchange, and can also shed light on the selective process of evolutionary altruistic behaviour. </s><s n="s6.6;p24.37">If there is only to ever be one exchange between individuals it is always most self-serving to not to co-operate, but with iterated exchanges so called 'nice' strategies are most beneficial to the individual, the most successful by way of 'Tit-for-Tat'. </s></p><p n="p25.37"><s n="s1.3;p25.37">We can now attempt some evolutionary determinant factor for the endogenous opiates (Kerverneal. 1989) released in the brains of primates when groomed. </s><s n="s2.3;p25.37">If we draw a comparison with the feeling of pain we suffer when we do some physical damage to ourselves, this is in effect our genetic constitution's method of behavioural reinforcement, prevention of the competing agents that make up the higher order cognitive faculties of the mind damaging the physical vessel. </s><s n="s3.3;p25.37">This could be analogous with the good feelings released when being groomed being intrinsic to the cognitive faculty of reciprocation, a mechanism for behavioural reinforcement of beneficial behaviours such reciprocally altruistic social bonding and the benefits of group existence. </s></p><p n="p26.37"><s n="s1.7;p26.37">The problem however is that time devoted to social grooming by old world monkeys and apes is more or less linear function of social group size (figure 3). </s><s n="s2.7;p26.37">As our hominid ancestors group sizes began to creep up above that found in that of the most social primates, so the demands on time budgets for social grooming must have become intense. </s><s n="s3.7;p26.37">No species of living nonhuman primate devotes more than 20 per cent of its total daily time budget to social interaction, this in itself is a substantial amount of time as the primate has the biological demands of feeding, travel and resting and ultimately means there is inevitably an upper limit to the amount of time that can be spent on social bonding. </s><s n="s4.7;p26.37">Without a more efficient bonding mechanism than grooming it will also effectually put an upper limit on the size of the group that a given population can maintain as a coherent unit. </s><s n="s5.7;p26.37">According to collated data, this limit would be around 70 individuals in even the most resourcefully rich habitat. </s><s n="s6.7;p26.37">Given that modern human have managed to evolve a stable cognitive group size of around 150 individuals, how have they managed to do this? </s><s n="s7.7;p26.37">This time allowance limitation, it is proposed could have created enough selective pressure for an adaptation of a more efficient bonding cognitive tool in addition to grooming itself, it would have been co-evolving in unison with the other cognitive domains that were enabling the growth of group size. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_3028b-fig.003"><head>figure 3 Grooming time in old world monkeys and apes (filled symbols) increases with group size (the plotted data are for individual species). However, the distribution of the data-points suggests that grooming time may be constrained by time budgeting considerations, with an absolute upper limit of around 20 per cent (broken line). A linear relationship between grooming time and group size (solid line) would predict that modern humans (with social groups of 150) would need to spend 43 percent of their total day time engaged in social grooming if humans (open square) were to bond with members of their groups using the same mechanism as old world monkeys and apes. According to this account a sample of seven contemporary societies (open circles) spend a mean of time of very close to 20 per cent of total time engaged in social interaction (conversation). The human populations include African pastoralists and horticulturalists, Nepalese hill farmers, new Quinean horticulturalists and contemporary Europeans (Dunbar 1993, 1999). </head></figure><p n="p27.37"><s n="s1.3;p27.37">If we examine the information from figure 3 it would suggest that, if humans bonded their groups in exactly the same way that old world monkeys and apes do, that is predominantly by social grooming, this act would require around 40-45 percent of the daytime hours grooming with each other (Dunbar 1993). </s><s n="s2.3;p27.37">This is more than double the time any ecologically hard-pressed old world monkey or ape seems to able to devote to social interaction. </s><s n="s3.3;p27.37">It therefore follows that some alternative more efficient mechanism must have been necessary to enable our human ancestor at the point of this group size/social bonding time (70 individuals/20 per cent of day) threshold to enable bonding in larger groups in the same amount of time, otherwise we simply would not be able maintain cohesive social groups the way we do in modern societies. </s></p><p n="p28.37"><s n="s1.14;p28.37">This is where geladas could provide us with a clue to the answer, as mentioned previously geladas live in the largest societies second to humans. </s><s n="s2.14;p28.37">These large cognitive groups approach and exceed the efficiency threshold described by Dunbar (1993). </s><s n="s3.14;p28.37">It appears that geladas have due to the selective pressures determined by the benefits of large group size could have evolved an additional, more efficient social bonding mechanism that allows them to have groups of these sizes. </s><s n="s4.14;p28.37">Although geladas do spend a small amount of time grooming each other, especially within their reproductive groups firstly in the morning, geladas have an unusual behavioural characteristic; they repeatedly vocalise to each other in a combinatorial fashion with a wide array of sounds while feeding and at other times of the day. </s><s n="s5.14;p28.37">Due to the strain on time budget costs of the demands of the gelada diet (50-70 percent of daytime activity) geladas spent most of their day sitting on their bottoms feeding from the ground, while making these 'language like' wide ranges of vocalisations. </s><s n="s6.14;p28.37">Aichal. (1990) has recorded total of 22 distinguishable calls, half of which are contact calls, the other half relating to aggression and defence. </s><s n="s7.14;p28.37">One call is given only by the highest ranking female within an OMU. No one has yet deciphered any of the gelada vocalisation to represent any kind of intentional semantic representation system as is clearly demonstrated in vervet monkeys (Cheney &amp; Seyfarth 1996). </s><s n="s8.14;p28.37">At this point, two options exist. </s><s n="s9.14;p28.37">One is to suggest that these calls have acquired semantic meaning, the most obvious starting point is probably naming as in vervet monkeys (Cheney &amp; Seyfarth 1996). </s><s n="s10.14;p28.37">The other is the suggestion that the process involved an initial phase that had more in common with singing, as suggested by Dunbar (1996). </s><s n="s11.14;p28.37">In humans, communal singing appears to be capable of tapping into our emotional processes that facilitate the synchronising of participating individuals' emotional states. </s><s n="s12.14;p28.37">It is most probable we share the majority, if not all of our emotional array, in the sense of qualia, with our closest mammalian relatives in the functional sense of basic behavioural reinforcement, for behaviours common in all of us. </s><s n="s13.14;p28.37">Dunbar (1996) refers to these vocalisations in geladas as 'contact-calling choruses'. </s><s n="s14.14;p28.37">As such they may serve an important role in the emotional bonding of social groups, and during human evolution also. </s></p><p n="p29.37"><s n="s1.1;p29.37">As Dunbar (1993, 1999) illustrated in figure 3, the mean amount of time actually spent in social interaction (principally conversation) in the range of modern human societies is, including Europeans and more traditional agriculturalists and horticulturalists is around 20 per cent of waking time - very similar to that of the upper limit on social interactive time in primates. </s></p><p n="p30.37"><s n="s1.1;p30.37">Human language as a cognitive bonding mechanism allows use of social interactive time to be more efficient, and could be considered to enable the bonding of larger groups in three ways; </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p31.37"><s n="s1.1;p31.37">It allows the individuals to socially interact with more people at the same time, that is it increases the size of the area the bonding mechanism can project to and enable multiples of other individuals to be 'groomed' at the same time. </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p32.37"><s n="s1.1;p32.37">At a fundamental level, to a lesser extent, other properties of this cognitive mechanism such as the semantic referential system enables the attainment and exchange of information relating to the cognitive group, without which would not be transferred. </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p33.37"><s n="s1.1;p33.37">It potentially provides an additional cognitive tool in the police of cheats and free riders that are detrimental to time budget efficiency (Axelrod 1984, Trivers 1971). </s></p><p n="p34.37"><s n="s1.6;p34.37">Dunbar (1993) argued that the core problem for language was to raise the size of the bonded group up from the maximum seen in nonhuman primates (such as that of geladas) to the determined 150 individuals for modern humans. </s><s n="s2.6;p34.37">To put from a different angle, the cognitive capacity of language was the adaptation corresponding to the particular selective pressure. </s><s n="s3.6;p34.37">If we use a hypothetical maximum size of 50 for a cognitive group of nonhuman primates using social grooming as the cognitive tool for group bonding for eases sake, this means in effect that human language has to be 150/50 = 3 times more efficient than social grooming in terms of its ability to reach members of the social network. </s><s n="s4.6;p34.37">Social grooming is essentially a one-on-one activity: primates only normally groom one individual at a time. </s><s n="s5.6;p34.37">Indeed this is still characteristic in modern humans when we give someone physical attention (of the non-sexual nature) by way of cuddling, petting, fondling, stroking whatever you want to call it that it does not happen with more than one individual. </s><s n="s6.6;p34.37">Grooming among primates is a very focused activity in which the groomer avidly concentrates on the task, for if the giver shows anything less than their undivided attention it could be interpreted by the recipient as lack of interest in the giver and they may terminate the session by walking off to find a more willing giver, with loss of social benefits for the giver. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_3028b-fig.004"><head>figure 4 As the size of an interacting group increases, it fragments into more independent conversations. The mean number of individuals engaged in conversation, speaker and listener, rises to a upper limit of just below four, irrespective of the size of the group with which multiple conversations occur (Dunbar 1995).</head></figure><p n="p35.37"><s n="s1.4;p35.37">In effect, then, spoken language allows modern humans to engage in social grooming at a distance, thus making it impossible for the 'groomer' to interact simultaneously with several individuals at the same time. </s><s n="s2.4;p35.37">Data on the size of conversational groups in modern humans suggests there is an upper limit on the size of these groups at four (Dunbar, 1995)(figure 4). </s><s n="s3.4;p35.37">Conversational groups typically have only one speaker, to which turn taking is characteristic (Beattie, 1983). </s><s n="s4.4;p35.37">This implies that the maximum number of listeners being 'groomed' at once, according to the data provided here is 3 individuals, which correlates exactly to the efficiency level required of a cognitive bonding mechanism to increase the solely social grooming nonhuman cognitive group sizes up to human cognitive group sizes (150/50 = 3). </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head>Concluding Remarks</head><p n="p36.37"><s n="s1.4;p36.37">There are undoubtedly many distinct differences between humans and geladas at any point during our evolutionary histories. </s><s n="s2.4;p36.37">It is just that the evolution of language is a seeming insurmountable theoretical challenge and any hint of relevant determining selective pressures shared with related cousins during our evolutionary past could be of great importance. </s><s n="s3.4;p36.37">I believe this theory of 'vocal grooming' has shown as substantial amount of plausibility, especially in the facilitation of the emotional content of vocalisation and language. </s><s n="s4.4;p36.37">Yet, it is almost surely to be, if useful, only one factor in many co-evolving in unison with many more, more human cognitive capacities. </s></p><p n="p37.37"><s n="s1.2;p37.37">Human language could not plausibly have evolved solely on its own in isolation; it co-evolved due to selective pressure created by and along with a whole bundle of our modern cognitive domains and anatomical designs. </s><s n="s2.2;p37.37">What the ecological determinants were we can only but speculate. </s></p></div1></body><back><div1 type="bibliography"><head>References</head><p>Aich, H., Moos-Heilen, R., Zimmerman, E. (1990), 'Vocalisations of adult gelada baboons (<hi rend="italic">Theropithecus gelada)</hi>: acoustic structure and behavioural context', <hi rend="italic">Folia Primatol,</hi> 55, 109-132. </p><p>Attenborough, D. (2000)</p><p>Axelrod, R. (1984), <hi rend="italic">The Evolution of Cooperation,</hi> New York: Basic Books.</p><p>Beattie, G. (1983), <hi rend="italic">Talk: an Analysis of Speech and Non-verbal Behaviour in Conversation,</hi> Milton Keynes: Open University Press.</p><p>Boyd, R &amp; Silk, J. (2003), <hi rend="italic">How Humans Evolved</hi>, London: Norton.</p><p>Dunbar, R. I. M. (1977), 'Feeding ecology of the gelada baboons: a preliminary report' in Clutten-Brock, T. H. (ed.), <hi rend="italic">Primate Ecology: Studies of Feeding and Ranging Behaviour in Lemurs, Monkeys, and Apes,</hi> 251-275, London: Academic Press. </p><p>Dunbar, R. I. M. (1992), <hi rend="italic">Neocortical Size as a constraint on Group Size in Primates,</hi> in Journal of Human Evolution 20: 469-493</p><p>Dunbar, R. I. M. (1993), <hi rend="italic">The Co-evolution of Neocortical Size, Group Size and Language in Humans,</hi> in Behaviour and Brain Sciences 16: 681-735</p><p>Dunbar, R. I. M. (1996), <hi rend="italic">Grooming, Gossip and the Evolution of Language,</hi> London: Faber and Faber.</p><p>Dunbar, R. I. M. (1999), 'Culture honesty and the freerider problem', in Dunbar, R. I. M., Knight, C., &amp; Power, C. (eds.) <hi rend="italic">Evolution of Human Cognition,</hi> pp. 205-221, Cambridge, MA: MIT Press. </p><p>Dunbar, R. I. M., Duncan, N. D. C., &amp; Nettle, D. (1995), <hi rend="italic">Size and Structure of Freely Forming Conversational Groups,</hi> in Human Nature 6: 67-78. </p><p>Dunbar, R. I. M., Duncan, N., &amp; Marriot, A. (1997), 'Human Conversational Behaviour', in <hi rend="italic">Human Nature,</hi> 8, 67-78.</p><p>Fleagle, J. G. (1999), <hi rend="italic">Primate Adaptation and Evolution,</hi> San Diego: Academic Press.</p><p>Haviland, J. B. (1991), <hi rend="italic">Gossip, Reputation and Knowledge in Zinacantan,</hi> Chicago: University of Chicago Press.</p><p>Iwamoto, T., Moto, A., Kawai, &amp; Bekeke, A. (1996), 'Anti-Predator Behaviours in Gelada Baboons', in <hi rend="italic">Primates</hi>, 37, 389-397.</p><p>Jablonski, N. G. (1993), <hi rend="italic">Theropithecus: The Rise and Fall of a Primate Genus</hi>, Cambridge: Cambridge University Press.</p><p>Kerverne, E. B., Martensz, N., &amp; Tuite, B. (1989), <hi rend="italic">Beta-endorphin Concentrations in Cerebrospinal Fluid in Monkeys are Influenced by Grooming Relationships,</hi> in Psychodocrinology 14: 155-161.</p><p>Mori, A., Iwamoto, T., &amp; Bekele, A. (1997), 'A Case of Infanticide in a Recently Found Gelada Population in Arsi, Ethiopia', in <hi rend="italic">Primates</hi>, 38, 79-88. </p><p>Pinker, S. (1994), <hi rend="italic">The Language Instinct,</hi> London: Penguin.</p><p>Rizzolatti, G., &amp; Arbib, M. (1998), 'Language Within Our Grasp', in <hi rend="italic">Trends in Neuroscience</hi>, 21, 188.</p><p>Cheney, D. L., Seyfarth, R. M. (1996), 'Function and intention of calls of nonhuman primates', in Runciman, W. G., Maynard Smith, J., &amp; Dunbar R. I. M. (eds.), <hi rend="italic">Evolution of Social Behaviour Patterns in Primates and Man,</hi> Oxford: OUP.</p><p>Rowe, N. (1996), <hi rend="italic">The Pictorial Guide To The Living Primates,</hi> Rhode Island: Pogonias Press.</p><p>Strummbach, E. (1987), 'Desert, forest, and montane baboons: multilevel societies', in Smuts, B., Seyfarth, R. M., Wrangham, R. W., Struhsaker, T. (eds.) <hi rend="italic">Primate Societies</hi>, London: University of Chicago Press. </p><p>Trivers, R. (1971), <hi rend="italic">The Evolution of Reciprocal Altruism,</hi> in Quarterly Review of Biology 46, 35-57. </p><p>Wolfheim, J. H. (ed.) (1983), <hi rend="italic">Primates of the World: Distribution, Abundance, and Conservation,</hi> Seattle: University of Washington Press.</p></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
