<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_3032d" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>(A) Describe the... / (B) Discuss the biological basis of Alzheimer's disease</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">deleted: footer: student number, page numbers</note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">Evaluated as candidate compound assignment. Assigned to S1f: collection of long tasks/questions: compound.</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">2</p><p n="date">2004-11</p><p n="module title">Biological Basis of Human behaviour</p><p n="module code">U43750</p><p n="genre family">Explanation + Explanation + Explanation + Explanation</p><p n="discipline">Health</p><p n="disciplinary group">LS</p><p n="grade">D</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">5628</p><p n="number of s-units">257</p><p n="number of p">51</p><p n="number of tables">0</p><p n="number of figures">3</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">1</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">0</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">21.9</p><p n="average s-units per p">5.0</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">compound assignment consisting of 4 parts (see notesStmt for details)</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">f</p><p n="year of birth">1974</p><p n="first language">English</p><p n="education">UKa</p><p n="course">BA (Hons) Mental Health Nursing</p><p n="student ID">3032</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><docTitle><titlePart>Biological basis for human behavior - module 43750</titlePart></docTitle></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="text"><head rend="bold">1)Describe the functions of the lobes of the human cortex </head><p n="p1.51"><s n="s1.3;p1.51">The Cortex is the thin covering of convoluted grey tissue which covers the human brain. </s><s n="s2.3;p1.51">Although only 4-5mm thick, it accounts for about 50% of the brain's weight due to its density and can be broken down into 4 functional units which are known as lobes. </s><s n="s3.3;p1.51">The following diagram shows where each of the lobes is situated and their various functions are described below. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_3032d-pic.001"/><div2><head rend="bold">The frontal lobe</head><p n="p2.51"><s n="s1.11;p2.51">Known as the memory centre of the brain, this area is responsible for our autobiographical memory, language, logical thinking and abstract thought - all qualities which we associate with consciousness. </s><s n="s2.11;p2.51">This area controls a variety of "higher cognitive functions" including behavior and emotions and the judgments we make about what occurs in our daily activities. </s><s n="s3.11;p2.51">It controls our expressive language and assigns meaning to the words we choose, it is also involved in word associations. </s><s n="s4.11;p2.51">Broca's Aphasia is an illustration of what can happen when the frontal lobe is damaged resulting in an inability to express language. </s><s n="s5.11;p2.51">Another very important job of the frontal lobe is that it inhibits the limbic system (the emotional part of the brain), helping to keep our behavior reasoned and appropriate. </s><s n="s6.11;p2.51">Frontal lobe damage is often found in Dementias where we see loss of memory and uncharacteristic aggressive or tearful behavior due to the lack of limbic system inhibition. </s><s n="s7.11;p2.51">In people with Down Syndrome it is not well developed meaning that they are also unable to control emotions in a way that most people would deem "appropriate". </s><s n="s8.11;p2.51">Damage to this area can result in confusion, disorientation and difficulty understanding instructions and is often observed with amnesiac patients. </s><s n="s9.11;p2.51">Other effects of damage to this area are :Loss of simple movement of various body parts (Paralysis), inability to plan a sequence of complex movements needed to complete multi-stepped tasks, such as making coffee (Sequencing), loss of spontaneity in interacting with others, loss of flexibility in thinking. </s><s n="s10.11;p2.51">Also, persistence of a single thought (Perseveration), inability to focus on task (Attending), mood changes (Emotionally Labile), changes in social behavior, specifically lack of inhibition. </s><s n="s11.11;p2.51">Changes in personality can also occur, as can difficulty with problem solving. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">The Parietal lobe</head><p n="p3.51"><s n="s1.13;p3.51">This is the part of our brain responsible for motor and sensory functions for the whole of the body. </s><s n="s2.13;p3.51">It contains the largest blood vessels in the brain and consequently it is an area very often affected by strokes and bleeds. </s><s n="s3.13;p3.51">Most strokes occur here because of the number of blockages that can occur due to large blood vessels feeding into smaller ones. </s><s n="s4.13;p3.51">Each part of the parietal lobe is responsible for a certain part of the body and the more complex the motor functions of that part of the body, the larger the area of parietal lobe dedicated to it. </s><s n="s5.13;p3.51">There are two parts to the Parietal Lobe, both thought to have slightly different functions. </s><s n="s6.13;p3.51">The right side is to do with visio-spacial awareness and someone with damage to this side may have difficulty finding their way around new, or even familiar, places. </s><s n="s7.13;p3.51">Damage to the left side may disrupt a patient's ability to understand spoken and/or written language. </s><s n="s8.13;p3.51">The parietal lobes contain the primary sensory cortex which controls sensation such as touch, pressure and pain. </s><s n="s9.13;p3.51">Behind the primary sensory cortex is a large association area that controls fine sensation such as judgment of texture, weight, size, shape. </s><s n="s10.13;p3.51">Functions: Location for visual attention, goal directed voluntary movements, manipulation of objects and integration of different senses that allows for understanding a single concept. </s><s n="s11.13;p3.51">Observed problems with people who have suffered damage to the area include: inability to attend to more than one object at a time, inability to name an object (Anomia), inability to locate the words for writing (Agraphia). </s><s n="s12.13;p3.51">There can also be problems with reading (Alexia), difficulty with drawing objects, difficulty in distinguishing left from right, difficulty with doing mathematics (Dyscalculia), inability to focus visual attention and difficulties with eye and hand coordination. </s><s n="s13.13;p3.51">It can also cause lack of awareness of certain body parts and/or surrounding space (Apraxia) that leads to difficulties in self-care. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">The Occipital lobe</head><p n="p4.51"><s n="s1.7;p4.51">This part of the cortex controls our ability to understand vision. </s><s n="s2.7;p4.51">It is situated at the back of the brain because the eyes also need to share information with other parts of the brain in order that an immediate physical response can occur if necessary, prior to the processing of information. </s><s n="s3.7;p4.51">Damage to this area may cause a person not to be able to filter out enough visual stimuli to enable them to concentrate on one task. </s><s n="s4.7;p4.51">Information from the occipital lobe is what we are consciously aware of - the phenomena of deja-vu happens when another part of the brain absorbs some visual information before it reaches the occipital lobe. </s><s n="s5.7;p4.51">Not only is the occipital lobe mainly responsible for visual reception, it also contains association areas that help in the visual recognition of shapes and colors. </s><s n="s6.7;p4.51">Damage to this lobe can cause visual deficits. </s><s n="s7.7;p4.51">Observed Problems in individuals with damage to this area include defects in vision (Visual Field Cuts), difficulty with locating objects, difficulty with identifying colors (Color Agnosia), hallucinations, word blindness, difficulty in recognizing drawn objects, difficulties with reading and writing and the inability to recognize the movement of an object (Movement Agnosia).. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">The Temporal lobe</head><p n="p5.51"><s n="s1.13;p5.51">This lobe is concerned with complex visual phenomena and hearing. </s><s n="s2.13;p5.51">It is the centre for unconscious visual process and perception of angles. </s><s n="s3.13;p5.51">Essentially it dictates how we see the world and make sense of it by helping us to categorize objects. </s><s n="s4.13;p5.51">It also controls our ability to make sense of what we are hearing. </s><s n="s5.13;p5.51">Sometimes in Schizophrenia, low visual stimulation can lead to a drop in audio hallucinations. </s><s n="s6.13;p5.51">The visual field should be kept as constant as possible when dealing with patients experiencing hallucinations. </s><s n="s7.13;p5.51">There are two temporal lobes, one on each side of the brain located at about the level of the ears. </s><s n="s8.13;p5.51">These lobes allow a person to tell one smell from another and one sound from another. </s><s n="s9.13;p5.51">They also help in sorting new information and are believed to be responsible for short-term memory. </s><s n="s10.13;p5.51">The right lobe is mainly involved in visual memory (i.e pictures and faces).The left lobe is mainly involved in verbal memory (i.e.words and names). </s><s n="s11.13;p5.51">Observed problems in people with damage to this area include disjointed behavior and confusion, psychosis and hallucinations. </s><s n="s12.13;p5.51">They may also have difficulty in recognizing faces (Prosopagnosia), difficulty in understanding spoken words (Wernicke's Aphasia), disturbance with selective attention to what we see and hear, difficulty with identification of, and verbalization about objects, interference with long-term memory; there may also be increased or decreased interest in sexual behavior. </s><s n="s13.13;p5.51">This is one of the first areas to become damaged in Dementias and explains why sufferers have trouble remembering recent events and new people </s></p><p n="p6.51"><s n="s1.5;p6.51">Because these lobes are on the cortex of the brain, they are often areas which get damaged due to trauma, the brain will swell and the lobes will push on the skull causing bruising and damaging the tissue. </s><s n="s2.5;p6.51">If the pressure is not relieved, the damage can be irreparable. </s><s n="s3.5;p6.51">This is why a person may recover well from a head trauma where something has penetrated the skull because this will relieve the pressure and allow the area room to swell whilst someone who may have hit their head and have no evidence of damage could die from internal bleeding. </s><s n="s4.5;p6.51">The cortex of the brain is also an area where we see the brain's amazing ability to continue to function despite huge amounts of damage. </s><s n="s5.5;p6.51">This is thought to be due to the huge numbers of neural pathways which allow the function of the damaged part to be taken on by a healthy part and is technically known as"plasticity". </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="text"><head rend="bold">4) Outline how a neurotransmitter is released from the pre-synaptic terminal and describe its post-synaptic actions. </head><p n="p7.51"><s n="s1.9;p7.51">A neurotransmitter is a chemical messenger used by brain cells (neurons) in order to communicate with each other and the rest of the body. </s><s n="s2.9;p7.51">There are 64 different known neurotransmitters and these can be broken into 4 groups or principal classes since they share some enzyme or metabolic pathway. </s><s n="s3.9;p7.51">Each neurotransmitter has a particular biosynthetic pathway. </s><s n="s4.9;p7.51">The first class is made up of acetylcholine alone, the second class are the biogenic amines, that are molecules formed by an amino acid losing a hydroxyl or carboxyl group. </s><s n="s5.9;p7.51">The third class is made up of excitory amino acids per se which are the fastest acting neurotransmitters. </s><s n="s6.9;p7.51">The most damaging amino acid is Glutemate, it is a much stronger messenger than all of the others and can overpower them, this is why parents of hyperactive children are advised to avoid giving them foods containing monosodium glutamate. </s><s n="s7.9;p7.51">Other amino acids are :Aspartate (excitatory), GABA (inhibitory) and Glycine (inhibitory). </s><s n="s8.9;p7.51">The forth group are peptides. </s><s n="s9.9;p7.51">Except for the neuropeptides, which are made in the nerve cell body and transported in vesicles along the axon to the axon terminals, all other neurotransmitters are synthesized at the axon terminals and stored in synaptic vesicles </s></p><p n="p8.51"><s n="s1.12;p8.51">Communication of information between neurons is accomplished by movement of these neurotransmitters across a small gap called the synapse. </s><s n="s2.12;p8.51">The synapse is found mainly at the end of axons and dendrites but can also be a junction with a cell body. </s><s n="s3.12;p8.51">It consists of: a presynaptic ending that contains readymade neurotransmitters in vesicles, a postsynaptic ending that contains receptor sites for neurotransmitters and a synaptic gap between the presynaptic and postsynaptic endings. </s><s n="s4.12;p8.51">For communication between neurons to occur, an electrical impulse must travel down an axon to the synaptic terminal. </s><s n="s5.12;p8.51">As the charge moves down the synapse, calcium will flood in which makes the vesicles move to the bottom of the synapse and fuse with the cell membrane. </s><s n="s6.12;p8.51">On fusion, the membrane breaks and the neurotransmitter is released. </s><s n="s7.12;p8.51">The neurotransmitter molecules then diffuse across the synaptic gap where they can bind with receptor sites on the postsynaptic ending using a lock and key mechanism, to influence the electrical response in the postsynaptic neuron. </s><s n="s8.12;p8.51">The reason that the cells communicate via a chemical messenger rather than an electrical charge is because electricity would be unsafe - 3000 cells fire in the body every second, if these were electrical charges we would explode! </s><s n="s9.12;p8.51">When a neurotransmitter binds to a receptor on the postsynaptic side of the synapse, it changes the postsynaptic cell's excitability and makes the postsynaptic cell either more or less likely to fire an action potential. </s><s n="s10.12;p8.51">Therefore, the neurotransmitter is the first messenger which binds with the receptor site to produce a second messenger, also a chemical substance, the most common in the mental health field is cyclic AMP or CAMP as it is also known. </s><s n="s11.12;p8.51">If the number of excitatory postsynaptic events (second messengers) is large enough and reaches that cell's threshold, they will cause an action potential in the postsynaptic cell and a continuation of the "message." </s><s n="s12.12;p8.51">The diagram at the end of this question illustrates how an impulse moves down a neuron and neurotransmitters cross the synaptic gap. </s></p><p n="p9.51"><s n="s1.5;p9.51">There is sometimes an excess of neurotransmitter in the synapse due to the fact that there are not enough receptor sites to bind to, in this case the excess will be removed, either by an enzyme released from the post synaptic neurone, or it may be reabsorbed by the presynaptic neurone in a process called reuptake. </s><s n="s2.5;p9.51">There is also a specific chain of enzymatic reactions that decompose the transmitter, either for destruction or for recycling. </s><s n="s3.5;p9.51">This is important since a synaptic signal does not subdue until the transmitter is removed from the synaptic gap. </s><s n="s4.5;p9.51">The transmitter can be degraded in the gap, or absorbed by the postsynaptic neuron or a glial cell and decomposed. </s><s n="s5.5;p9.51">Mental health problems are often the result of a breakdown in the way these chemical messages are active in the brain and as such, many drugs used in psychiatry change the properties of neurotransmitter release, neurotransmitter reuptake and the availability of receptor binding sites </s></p><figure id="BAWE_3032d-pic.002"/></div1><div1 type="text"><head rend="bold">Describe the different routes of systemic delivery of drugs, relating your answer to how drugs access the blood stream. </head><p n="p10.51"><s n="s1.2;p10.51">There are a number of different routes for the systematic delivery of drugs into the body, each with their own positive and negative points. </s><s n="s2.2;p10.51">They are discussed below. </s></p><div2><head>1. ALIMENTARY TRACT ROUTES</head><div3><p n="p11.51"><s n="s1.3;p11.51"><hi rend="bold">Oral:</hi> This is a convenient, safe and economical way of delivering a drug into the system providing the patient is compliant. </s><s n="s2.3;p11.51">Most drugs are absorbed in the small intestine (which is about10.5ft long), some in the stomach and some in the colon. </s><s n="s3.3;p11.51">Because the drug must pass through the gastro-intestinal tract, the onset of the drug is slower than some other methods and it is not active until it is in the bloodstream. </s></p><p n="p12.51"><s n="s1.3;p12.51">Water soluble drugs such as paracetamol are also absorbed in the stomach. </s><s n="s2.3;p12.51">Persistent alcohol abuse can cause damage to the stomach lining and painkillers on top of this can cause bleeding. </s><s n="s3.3;p12.51">The practitioner needs to take care when giving advice on non-prescription medication. </s></p><p n="p13.51"><s n="s1.4;p13.51">There are different drug uptake sites in the GI tract, some quicker than others eg.the stomach is quicker than the colon. </s><s n="s2.4;p13.51">The drug is inert until it reached the uptake site therefore there can be delays. </s><s n="s3.4;p13.51">The onset of oral meds is always slower because they take longer to get into the blood stream. </s><s n="s4.4;p13.51">Advantage : drugs active for longer </s></p><p n="p14.51"><s n="s1.2;p14.51">Some drugs would irritate the digestive tract therefore not given orally, also, lots would not survive in GI tract due to acids and alkalines. </s><s n="s2.2;p14.51">Aim is to get in contact with blood. </s></p></div3><div3><p n="p15.51"><s n="s1.3;p15.51"><hi rend="bold">Rectal:</hi> Can have either local or systemic effects. </s><s n="s2.3;p15.51">Systemic drug absorption from this route can be incomplete and unpredictable, especially if the patient is unable to retain the drug long enough eg. </s><s n="s3.3;p15.51">If they have diahorrea. </s></p><p n="p16.51"><s n="s1.1;p16.51">Advantage : quickly results in a high concentration of the drug in circulation because there is </s></p><list type="bulleted"><item>a rich network of capilliaries</item><item>venous blood from the lower part of the rectum does not pass through the liver (liver filters blood for toxins and therefore gets rid of drugs)</item><item>"first pass" effect - won't destroy much of the drug</item></list><p n="p17.51"><s n="s1.2;p17.51">Problems : if you suffer adverse effects eg. </s><s n="s2.2;p17.51">Rectal bleeds which can be very serious due to the amount of venal blood in the area. </s></p></div3></div2><div2><head>2. PARENTERAL ROUTES</head><p n="p18.51"><s n="s1.1;p18.51">(Any route of access to blood other than the gut) </s></p><div3><p n="p19.51"><s n="s1.1;p19.51"><hi rend="bold">Sublingual :</hi> drug placed under the tongue (it is designed for this and not the GI tract) </s></p><p n="p20.51"><s n="s1.2;p20.51">Area is rich in capillaries which permits rapid absorption which in turn quickens the drug action. </s><s n="s2.2;p20.51">Avoids liver and destruction of drugs by gastro-intestinal enzymes. </s></p><p n="p21.51"><s n="s1.4;p21.51">Yields a higher dose in circulation compared to oral administration. </s><s n="s2.4;p21.51">In general, a very safe route. </s><s n="s3.4;p21.51">The practitioner must check that the drug is allowed to be given via this route since some are too powerful and can cause swelling of the tongue causing difficulty breathing. </s><s n="s4.4;p21.51">Some patients will hide drugs under their tongue to spit out later - not all are suitable. </s></p></div3><div3><p n="p22.51"><s n="s1.1;p22.51"><hi rend="bold">Intralingual</hi> : Injection under surface of patient's tongue. </s></p><p n="p23.51"><s n="s1.1;p23.51">Advantages : very rapid absorption - under 10 seconds because of a rich blood supply. </s></p><p n="p24.51"><s n="s1.3;p24.51">Disadvantages : the tongue may swell causing airway obstruction (can happen very fast). </s><s n="s2.3;p24.51">This is sometimes used with people whose vascular access is severely compromised (e.g chronic IV drug users). </s><s n="s3.3;p24.51">This route is sometimes used by users themselves and can be VERY dangerous. </s></p></div3><div3><p n="p25.51"><s n="s1.3;p25.51"><hi rend="bold">Intradermal (ID)</hi> : Injection of drugs into upper layers of skin (make sure that needle is almost parallel to the surface of the skin).used to provide a local drug effect eg. </s><s n="s2.3;p25.51">Treatment of allergies. </s><s n="s3.3;p25.51">Only small amounts can be injected. </s></p><p n="p26.51"><s n="s1.3;p26.51">Insert the bevel and use a 45 degree twist as you go in. </s><s n="s2.3;p26.51">Rate of absorbtion is slow, limited to capillaries of dermis. </s><s n="s3.3;p26.51">E.g Lignocaine anaesthesia- has to be left to take effect before procedure can be commenced. </s></p><p n="p27.51"><s n="s1.2;p27.51">It is better to use a larger vd syringe to give a smaller injection because you don't have to draw up so far, therefore more control over needle as you plunge. </s><s n="s2.2;p27.51">Still need to be able to measure accurately though. </s></p></div3><div3><p n="p28.51"><s n="s1.2;p28.51"><hi rend="bold">Subcutaneaus (sq/sc)</hi> :injection performed by inserting a small needle (1/2 - 5/8 inch, 25g or less) into the fatty tissue ABOVE the muscle. </s><s n="s2.2;p28.51">Usually largest does is 2ml. </s></p><p n="p29.51"><s n="s1.1;p29.51">Advantages : minimal tissue trauma and avoids potential damage to large vessels and nerves. </s></p><p n="p30.51"><s n="s1.2;p30.51">Undesirable for patients who experience compromised artillory perfusions (vascular damage)eg. </s><s n="s2.2;p30.51">Shock or peripheral vascular disease. </s></p><p n="p31.51"><s n="s1.7;p31.51">Inserted at a shallow angle, 45 degrees. </s><s n="s2.7;p31.51">The needle will penetrate skin, go down into fatty layer. </s><s n="s3.7;p31.51">The fatty layer is easy to feel, it is much less resistant than skin. </s><s n="s4.7;p31.51">It is sometimes difficult to do this in older people or those suffering self neglect because neither have much subcutaneous fat. </s><s n="s5.7;p31.51">Good sites are the back, upper arms, abdomen, upper surface of legs, below shoulder blades (best), also just above the backside. </s><s n="s6.7;p31.51">It is essential to make sure there is a good fat pad underneath the skin. </s><s n="s7.7;p31.51">Problems can occur if the needle gets too deep into the muscle. </s></p></div3><div3><p n="p32.51"><s rend="bold" n="s1.1;p32.51">Intramuscular (IM) </s></p><p n="p33.51"><s n="s1.10;p33.51">This is the most common method of injection. </s><s n="s2.10;p33.51">The drug is injected deep into muscle tissue where it is absorbed into the capillaries and enters blood stream. </s><s n="s3.10;p33.51">You must always pull back the plunger to check that it is not in the blood vessel, if any blood is evident, another site must be found. </s><s n="s4.10;p33.51">The drug seeps out across muscles into capillary walls. </s><s n="s5.10;p33.51">Doses are up to 3ml commonly given via 21-25g needle, 1-1.5 inch in length. </s><s n="s6.10;p33.51">Larger doses (more than 3ml) can be given using multiple sites, it is best to spread them out. </s><s n="s7.10;p33.51">Rate of absorption depends on the physical condition of the patient. </s><s n="s8.10;p33.51">Muscular damage (age and malnutrition) leads to poor absorption rate, otherwise the rate is fairly predictable. </s><s n="s9.10;p33.51">Not used where there is inadequate muscle mass or decreased peripheral perfusion. </s><s n="s10.10;p33.51">The practitioner should have a good look and feel of the site, feel the muscle to check that it is adequate. </s></p><p n="p34.51"><s n="s1.1;p34.51">Sites : deltoid (top of arm), dorso gluteal (upper outer buttock), ventrogluteal (below hip) - need to be careful of pelvis with this one, vastus lateralis site (upper outer front leg). </s></p><p n="p35.51"><s n="s1.1;p35.51">The needle should be withdrawn at the same angle and at the same rate as it went in. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_3032d-pic.003"><head rend="bold">Diagram to compare injection angles</head></figure></div3><div3><head rend="bold">Intravenous (IV)</head><p n="p36.51"><s n="s1.5;p36.51">When a situation calls for a rapid therapeutic effect this is used. </s><s n="s2.5;p36.51">It is direct administration of the drug directly into the blood stream. </s><s n="s3.5;p36.51">IVs can be either Bolus or infusion. </s><s n="s4.5;p36.51"><hi rend="bold italic">Bolus</hi> means that one dose of a drug injected into the vein all at once- any reactions to this will be much more severe and side effects are more likely. </s><s n="s5.5;p36.51"><hi rend="bold italic">Infusion</hi> is the continuous introduction at a specified rate over a period of time - these can be stopped and saline solution flushed through if side effects begin to develop. </s></p><p n="p37.51"><s n="s1.4;p37.51">Continuous infusion IV is a way of keeping the amount of drug available to body tissues at a constant level. </s><s n="s2.4;p37.51">Bolus IV : a rapid intervention, no barriers to cross prior to blood access. </s><s n="s3.4;p37.51">Some drugs can be given as Bolus to establish rapid therapeutic effect and this effect can be maintained by infusion eg. </s><s n="s4.4;p37.51">Lignocaine to treat ventricular fibrillation. </s></p><p n="p38.51"><s n="s1.3;p38.51">Once in the vein/vessel the angle of the needle should be flattened to make sure it does not go straight through the other side.With infusion, needles can become dislodged and damage the vein. </s><s n="s2.3;p38.51">Also they can move inside the vein. </s><s n="s3.3;p38.51">Some cannulas have 2 parts, one for infusion and one for bolus at the same time. </s></p><p n="p39.51"><s n="s1.3;p39.51">If IVs can not be continued, some drugs can be given via an <hi rend="bold">endotracheal tube</hi> (ET). </s><s n="s2.3;p39.51">Drugs are absorbed rapidly via capillaries of the lung. </s><s n="s3.3;p39.51">When this is done correctly, the rate of drug absorption can be the same as that of IV. It is rarely used in our setting, only as a last effort to save someone's life. </s></p></div3></div2></div1><div1 type="text"><head rend="bold">Discuss the biological basis of Alzheimer's disease</head><div2><head>Introduction</head><p n="p40.51"><s n="s1.6;p40.51">In this essay I will explore the way Alzheimer's disease damages the human brain, how this manifests itself in the sufferer's behaviour and how this can inform practice for the mental health nurse. </s><s n="s2.6;p40.51">Alzheimer's disease is the most common form of Dementia, accounting for up to 60% of all cases (Alzheimer's disease International). </s><s n="s3.6;p40.51">Dementia is a degenerative disorder of the brain which can be defined as "global impairment of memory and other cognitive functions in the absence of clouding of consciousness" (Lishman 1987). </s><s n="s4.6;p40.51">Characteristic features are confusion and loss of memory in the early stages followed by personality disintegration in the later stages (Rinomhota &amp; Marshall 2000). </s><s n="s5.6;p40.51">Statistics show that the incidence of Alzheimer's disease is increasing; currently, one person in 100 will develop it between 40 and 65, increasing to 1 in 50 at 65-70 and 1 in 5 at 80 and above (Hunt 1996). </s><s n="s6.6;p40.51">The majority of useful research into Alzheimer's disease has only been conducted during the last ten years partly due to new technology that has become available; this has led to the development of new drugs and a better understanding of the disease pathology. </s></p><p n="p41.51"><s n="s1.4;p41.51">To obtain a diagnosis of Alzheimer's disease, there must be the presence of Dementia, clarified by a clinical measurement tool such as the Mini Mental State Examination (Folstein et al 1975) and a slow (sometimes even unrecognised) onset with a uniformly and progressively deteriorating course. </s><s n="s2.4;p41.51">Other causes of dementia such as a tumour, also need to be ruled out and this should be done by a thorough physical examination, laboratory tests, psychometric tests and a complete family history from the client and their family or carers (Cutler N &amp; Sramek 1996). </s><s n="s3.4;p41.51">Illnesses such as severe depression may manifest themselves in the same way as Dementia and can affect cognitive functioning, these also need to be ruled out. </s><s n="s4.4;p41.51">Even though today's computerised brain imaging techniques give us a better idea of what is happening to the brain during the disease process which has helped greatly in its diagnosis, there is still only one way to categorically prove that someone has Alzheimer's disease and this is through a post mortem examination. </s></p><p n="p42.51"><s n="s1.13;p42.51">In a brain which has been affected by Alzheimer's, there will be bodies called "neuritic plaques" which are found chiefly in the cerebral cortex but have also been found in other parts of the brain. </s><s n="s2.13;p42.51">The number of plaques found correlates with the magnitude of the cognitive deterioration. </s><s n="s3.13;p42.51">The plaques consist of a central abnormal protein amyloid which sits half in and half out of a cell; the waste products of the cells collect around the amyloid protein so that the cell becomes surrounded by degenerative cellular fragments which eventually cause it to die. </s><s n="s4.13;p42.51">This is something that happens in normal ageing but at a faster rate. </s><s n="s5.13;p42.51">Another feature of Alzheimer's disease is the presence of paired helical filaments (PHFs), also known as neurofibrillary tangles (Lovestone S 1997). </s><s n="s6.13;p42.51">These are found in both the Cortex and the Hippocampus which is why memory problems are often an early sign of Alzheimer's. </s><s n="s7.13;p42.51">The posterior part of the hippocampus is most badly damaged and this is why sufferers will sometimes have excellent recall of events in their early life that are stored in their long term memory. </s><s n="s8.13;p42.51">These tangles are easily identified by light microscopy during a post mortem. </s><s n="s9.13;p42.51">As well as the plaques and tangles, Mountjoy (1993) notes two other pathogenic irregularities found in the brains of sufferers: neuronal loss and deposition of amyloid. </s><s n="s10.13;p42.51">Granular vascular bodies are also found in brains during post mortem, these are an outer membrane with a small dense granule in the centre - they are found in most aged brains but more common in brains with Alzheimer's disease. </s><s n="s11.13;p42.51">The granular vascular bodies cause the brain to appear darker than a younger brain. </s><s n="s12.13;p42.51">Other things that are noticed during a post mortem is that the cortex becomes atrophied (shrunken), it can lose as much as 1/3 of its volume as the disease progresses. </s><s n="s13.13;p42.51">This atrophy is never uniform but it has been found that most damage occurs in the temporal lobe structures e.g hippocampus and entorhinal cortex, the damage can then spread into the parietal and frontal lobes. </s></p><p n="p43.51"><s n="s1.11;p43.51">As the temporal-parietal-occipital association cortex becomes affected, it has many consequences such as aphasia, apraxia and agnostia, all of which will now be considered in more detail. </s><s n="s2.11;p43.51">Aphasia can be divided into 2 categories, receptive and expressive. </s><s n="s3.11;p43.51">Benson (1994) describes receptive aphasia as an inability to understand language, so although the individual receives sound in the same way, they can not interpret what it means. </s><s n="s4.11;p43.51">It is important as a practitioner to be sensitive to this when caring for someone with Alzheimer's disease since they may have huge difficulties understanding verbal instructions and it is sometimes better to demonstrate with an action. </s><s n="s5.11;p43.51">Expressive aphasia means that there is difficulty in using language. </s><s n="s6.11;p43.51">Deterioration to Broca's area is common, meaning that finding the words that you want to say and putting them into the appropriate order becomes very hard. </s><s n="s7.11;p43.51">Naming things becomes particularly difficult, to the point where, eventually, the speech of someone with Alzheimer's becomes devoid of specific nouns. </s><s n="s8.11;p43.51">In the middle and later stages, problems in the temporal lobe might also cause some patients to experience auditory and visual hallucinations. </s><s n="s9.11;p43.51">The occipital lobe is also responsible for visual interpretation, most of which is spared during Alzheimer's. </s><s n="s10.11;p43.51">However, some visual association areas are affected, making it difficult to process subtle visual cues. </s><s n="s11.11;p43.51">People's faces are one example of a visual cue that becomes difficult to recognize, probably because age and emotion cause facial expressions to change constantly, requiring a lot of interpretation (The brain and Alzheimer's). </s></p><p n="p44.51"><s n="s1.4;p44.51">Apraxia can be explained as losing the ability to carry out particular motor tasks that were already known to the individual. </s><s n="s2.4;p44.51">Benson (1994) identifies 3 main types: -<hi rend="italic">feeding</hi>: no longer having the skills to use cutlery or eat in an appropriate manner; <hi rend="italic">daily living</hi>: no longer being able to wash and dress oneself and <hi rend="italic">gait:</hi> damage to the frontal and parietal lobes which eventually results in difficulties walking. </s><s n="s3.4;p44.51">Agnostia is similar to receptive aphasia but in this case it is vision and not sound which is affected. </s><s n="s4.4;p44.51">An individual may perceive things perfectly but have no recognition of what they are perceiving, even if it is a member of the family, or in extreme situations, they may not even recognise themselves. </s></p><p n="p45.51"><s n="s1.4;p45.51">The thalamus is another area that is affected, this regulates hunger and thirst - the sufferer will still have the feelings of thirst and hunger although they may not have the ability to be able to be able to feed or stop their self from being thirsty by helping themselves to a drink. </s><s n="s2.4;p45.51">Some areas of the cortex are spared, such as the limbic system which remains completely intact, explaining why we sometimes see emotional or violent outbursts by the individual suffering from Alzheimer's disease whose emotions are not inhibited by the frontal lobe. </s><s n="s3.4;p45.51">When Alzheimer's begins destroying the parietal lobe, sufferers become lost and disoriented, even in familiar settings. </s><s n="s4.4;p45.51">They may also begin mixing up objects, thinking that a computer is a television or that a mixing bowl is a soup pot. </s></p><p n="p46.51"><s n="s1.15;p46.51">The hippocampus takes our immediate thoughts and impressions and turns them into memories. </s><s n="s2.15;p46.51">Alzheimer's attacks the hippocampus first, so short-term memory is the first thing to fail. </s><s n="s3.15;p46.51">Eventually, new memories become impossible to make and learning is a thing of the past. </s><s n="s4.15;p46.51">Without knowing what just happened, it's difficult for people to judge things like time, place and what's going on around them. </s><s n="s5.15;p46.51">This confusion can accentuate the paranoia caused by an Alzheimer's-stricken amygdala. </s><s n="s6.15;p46.51">A common problem that occurs in the Alzheimer's sufferer is urinary incontinence, this happens as the frontal lobe becomes atrophied which would normally generate impulses to inhibit the emptying of the bladder until a convenient time. </s><s n="s7.15;p46.51">The frontal lobe helps carry out purposeful behaviours and complex reasoning. </s><s n="s8.15;p46.51">When Alzheimer's strikes the frontal lobe, victims lose the ability to plan and initiate complicated activities like balancing a checkbook. </s><s n="s9.15;p46.51">That's why it becomes important to break processes into simple steps. </s><s n="s10.15;p46.51">This loss of processing skills makes reasoning with people who have Alzheimer's virtually impossible. </s><s n="s11.15;p46.51">People with Alzheimer's are not being stubborn; their brains just aren't healthy enough to carry out the complex processes that logic demands. </s><s n="s12.15;p46.51">Frontal dysfunction (combined with amygdala problems) also leads to a loss of inhibition, which may cause behaviours such as undressing in public, swearing and making inappropriate statements. </s><s n="s13.15;p46.51">The amygdala regulates basic emotions such as fear, anger and craving and is affected quite early in Alzheimer's. </s><s n="s14.15;p46.51">Once Alzheimer's disrupts the brain's emotional centre, a person may display surprising behaviours such as apathy, paranoia, emotional outbursts and inappropriate sexual advances. </s><s n="s15.15;p46.51">Unprovoked hostility and anxiousness might appear completely out-of-the-blue. </s></p><p n="p47.51"><s n="s1.4;p47.51">Early in Alzheimer's disease, changes to the brain stem begin disrupting sleep patterns. </s><s n="s2.4;p47.51">Very late in the disease, the brain stem's deterioration can also affect vital processes like breathing, blinking, blood pressure and heart rate. </s><s n="s3.4;p47.51">However, other complications usually intervene before this happens. </s><s n="s4.4;p47.51">For instance, difficulties swallowing often make someone vulnerable to pneumonia before the brain stem truly degenerates. </s></p><p n="p48.51"><s n="s1.16;p48.51">One theory is a genetic theory which suggests that there is a higher incidence of Alzheimer's in some families than others. </s><s n="s2.16;p48.51">Although this accounts for only around 25% of all cases and this tends to be in early onset Alzheimer's (Cutler and Sramek 1996). </s><s n="s3.16;p48.51">If siblings had the disease, there is a 3.8% risk and if a parent had the disease there is a 10% risk. </s><s n="s4.16;p48.51">There have been no specific genes identified but recently, research has focussed on a gene which makes a protein called apolipoprotein E (ApoE). </s><s n="s5.16;p48.51">There are three types of ApoE - E2, E3, E4. </s><s n="s6.16;p48.51">Each person inherits an ApoE gene from each parent. </s><s n="s7.16;p48.51">It seems that people who inherit an ApoE-E4 gene have a higher risk of developing Alzheimer's disease. </s><s n="s8.16;p48.51">Abnormalities on three other genes - PS1 (presenilin type 1), PS2 and APP (amyloid precursor protein) - have been identified as a cause of the rare inherited form of the disease, but the mechanism is not clear. </s><s n="s9.16;p48.51">(Caton et Al 2002). </s><s n="s10.16;p48.51">Researchers are still very interested in links between Alzheimer's disease and Down's syndrome, research into this began when physicians noticed that the majority of people with Down's who lived into their 30s developed degenerative brain disease remarkable similar to Alzheimer's . </s><s n="s11.16;p48.51">People with Down syndrome always have an extra chromosome 21. </s><s n="s12.16;p48.51">One gene on chromosome 21 creates amyloid precursor protein (APP). </s><s n="s13.16;p48.51">Abnormal deposition of amyloid in the brain occurs in Alzheimer's disease. </s><s n="s14.16;p48.51">It seems the extra gene results in an excess of amyloid. </s><s n="s15.16;p48.51">Consequently, almost all people with Down's syndrome over age forty develop Alzheimer's disease (Cutler N &amp; Sramek 1996). </s><s n="s16.16;p48.51">There are also some common environmental factors that are responsible for a familial frequency such as a higher risk in people who live in high background radiation areas such as Edinburgh which is built on radioactive granite. </s></p><p n="p49.51"><s n="s1.5;p49.51">Trace metal contamination is another theory proposed to explain the development of the disease. </s><s n="s2.5;p49.51">Animal studies (Toates 2001) have identified degenerative neurofibulatory tangles similar to those found in Alzheimer's disease after rats were given aluminium salts. </s><s n="s3.5;p49.51">Post mortems have found that there is a 10-30% increase in aluminium deposits in brains of Alzheimer's sufferers. </s><s n="s4.5;p49.51">It is not yet known if a reduction in aluminium could be of benefit to patients. </s><s n="s5.5;p49.51">Most aluminium contamination is found around the amyloid proteins. </s></p><p n="p50.51"><s n="s1.9;p50.51">Some researchers think that there could be a link between Alzheimer's and <hi rend="italic">immune reaction</hi>. </s><s n="s2.9;p50.51">They believe that as we age, the immune system may lose the ability to recognise the individuals own body and begin to attack it. </s><s n="s3.9;p50.51">As a result, we develop "anti-brain" antibodies which cause neural degeneration. </s><s n="s4.9;p50.51">There is to date little evidence to support such a theory. </s><s n="s5.9;p50.51">The link with multiple sclerosis is the main reason that this is being investigated as since with MS the brain becomes visible to the rest of the body and it begins to attack it. </s><s n="s6.9;p50.51">Another theory is that it may be a slow virus. </s><s n="s7.9;p50.51">This idea comes from a study of tribes in Papua New Gineau who transmitted Kuru (Alzheimer's disease society 1997) after eating the brains of their deceased tribesmen who had died from it. </s><s n="s8.9;p50.51">Another area being investigated is that of neurochemical disturbances. </s><s n="s9.9;p50.51">Enzymes related to the neurotransmitter aceytocholine are greatly reduced in the brains of individuals suffering from Alzheimer's disease, especially in the hippocampus. </s></p></div2><div2><head>Conclusion</head><p n="p51.51"><s n="s1.7;p51.51">In this essay I have discussed the pathology and neurological correlation of Alzheimer's disease and how this has informed practice. </s><s n="s2.7;p51.51">With an aging population and a climbing incidence of the disease, it is more important than ever for healthcare professionals to understand the treatment needs of this group of individuals. </s><s n="s3.7;p51.51">Alzheimer's disease has a lot of similarities to the normal aged brain; it seems that the aging process is just accelerated. </s><s n="s4.7;p51.51">A key area in practical patient care over the last few years has been the education of carers in different ways to communicate, whereas people in the past may have assumed that elderly people become deaf, it is now understood that Alzheimer's patients have not lost the ability to hear, but the ability to process the audio information and so it must be presented in a way that they will understand. </s><s n="s5.7;p51.51">As a mental health nurse, this greatly changes the way therapeutic relationships are established. </s><s n="s6.7;p51.51">By understanding that normal ways of communicating may not be effective, greater emphasis can be placed on skills such as non verbal communication - essential when dealing with individuals who can not vocalise when they are in pain or discomfort. </s><s n="s7.7;p51.51">As care of the elderly moves away from its "Cinderella" status, more money is becoming available for research into diseases such as Alzheimer's which can only be positive in terms of informing healthcare practice. </s></p></div2></div1></body><back/></text></TEI.2>
