<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_3038a" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Using empirical data that has been gathered on your chosen leisure sector and theoretical models of either social class, or gender, or the life cycle, evaluate the extent .</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">Language used in quote: <foreign id="English">English</foreign></note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">
Student name and number and date in doc header. Module name and short assignemnt title in doc footer.
</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">3</p><p n="date">2005-12</p><p n="module title">Understanding Leisure</p><p n="module code">U54066</p><p n="genre family">Essay</p><p n="discipline">Hospitality, Leisure &amp; Tourism Management</p><p n="disciplinary group">SS</p><p n="grade">M</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">2479</p><p n="number of s-units">86</p><p n="number of p">29</p><p n="number of tables">0</p><p n="number of figures">0</p><p n="number of block quotes">3</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">0</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">0</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">28.8</p><p n="average s-units per p">3.0</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">f</p><p n="year of birth">1983</p><p n="first language">English</p><p n="education">UKa</p><p n="course">International Tourism Management</p><p n="student ID">3038</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><docTitle><titlePart rend="bold">Using empirical data that has been gathered on your chosen leisure sector and theoretical models of either social class, or gender, or the life cycle, evaluate the extent to which traditional paradigms of the sources of inequality in leisure remain relevant to an understanding of differences in participation in leisure activities. </titlePart></docTitle></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold italic">Introduction</head><p n="p1.29"><s n="s1.1;p1.29">The aim of this research piece is to attempt to highlight the differences amongst those who visit bars and clubs by looking at life cycle as a traditional paradigm. </s></p><p n="p2.29"><s n="s1.2;p2.29">The objective of this research piece is to look at four stages of the life cycle. </s><s n="s2.2;p2.29">The four stages that will be referred to throughout the statistical analysis are: pre-family/no family (those that are aged under 45 who are not parents), family (those that are of any age with a least one child under the age of 16 still living at home), third age (those that are aged 45-64 with no children aged under 16) and retired (aged over 65 with no children aged under 16) (Mintel, 2004b). </s></p><p n="p3.29"><s n="s1.1;p3.29">In academic literature Rapoport and Rapoport (1975) broke the life cycle down into four different stages: adolescence (search for personal identity), young adulthood (search for social identity), establishment (creating life investments) and retirement (searching for the meaning of life). </s></p><p n="p4.29"><s n="s1.2;p4.29">Unfortunately the stages that Rapoport and Rapoport refer to are unable to support statistical research that has been carried out. </s><s n="s2.2;p4.29">The main discretion between market analysers and Rapoport and Rapoport is that of adolescence. </s></p><p n="p5.29"><s n="s1.1;p5.29">Nevertheless, it could be argued that due to the nature of the research being carried out market analysers refrained from including adolescents within their research, as it is illegal for those under 18 to drink alcohol within the U.K. </s></p><p n="p6.29"><s n="s1.2;p6.29">Although this doesn't mean that those under the age of 18 don't drink research that might be carried out amongst adolescents is highly likely to prove to be insufficient and inaccurate. </s><s n="s2.2;p6.29">This is due to the possibility of adolescents claiming that they drink when they don't due to peer pressure or the possibility that those that do drink don't tell the truth in fear of being reprimanded. </s></p><p n="p7.29"><s n="s1.2;p7.29">In terms of the leisure sector that has been chosen pubs will be the main area concentrated on however themed pubs and bars and nightclubs will also be considered within the statistical analysis. </s><s n="s2.2;p7.29">Unfortunately there is limited data available on alcohol outlets outside of the traditional pub therefore resulting in less in-depth data analysis. </s></p><p n="p8.29"><s n="s1.6;p8.29">Over the last 100 years acceptance in pubs has changed. </s><s n="s2.6;p8.29">The pub used to be very much a workingman's place where they could go and socialise together after a day of backbreaking work. </s><s n="s3.6;p8.29">The woman was never seen there, they were expected be at home cooking for when her husband comes home and looking after their children. </s><s n="s4.6;p8.29">Over time this slowly changed. </s><s n="s5.6;p8.29">At first women were not allowed in alone but were allowed in relying they were accompanied by a member of the male sex, mainly their husband. </s><s n="s6.6;p8.29">However time has progressed rapidly and the woman has become more dominant and with the introduction of feminism, pubs are no longer just for the man but for woman too, no matter what life stage they may be in. </s></p><p n="p9.29"><s n="s1.5;p9.29">It is important to look at life cycle and bars and clubs in order to be able to gain a look at how times will change throughout our lives. </s><s n="s2.5;p9.29">In general people's situation and circumstances change on a quick and constant basis between 20 and 35 years old. </s><s n="s3.5;p9.29">Many pubs are often seen as a younger persons place and those who are settled in the later stages of the life cycle are often thought to be at home, due to family and less available expenditure. </s><s n="s4.5;p9.29">As Mintel (2002) suggests, "among the family-building age groups, drinking is -more of a home-centred leisure activity" (Market Drivers, Demographics). </s><s n="s5.5;p9.29">By studying the statistical data available and using the life stages it will be possible to obtain a clearer picture as to the changes that have occurred over the past couple of years and how this may evolve into the future. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold italic">Discussion</head><p n="p10.29"><s n="s1.4;p10.29">Within the leisure industry there are numerous paradigms that can be looked at in order to help understand why people choose the leisure activities that they select. </s><s n="s2.4;p10.29">Gender and social class are the main two paradigms that had been looked at over time in order to asses leisure activities. </s><s n="s3.4;p10.29">However, family life cycle is just an important factor when it comes to leisure although is often overlooked. </s><s n="s4.4;p10.29">There is limited academic written knowledge on this particular paradigm however Rapoport and Rapoport (1975) have studied the life cycle in depth and they feel that class and gender are less important paradigms when researching within the leisure sector. </s></p><p n="p11.29"><s n="s1.3;p11.29">However when looking at market analysis it is often found that the statistics that are produced for leisure activities are often defined by age rather than by the stage as to which a person is in within the life cycle. </s><s n="s2.3;p11.29">Academic writers more often refer to the life cycle of people rather than their age and this provides a much deeper insight into their lives. </s><s n="s3.3;p11.29">It allows more variables to be assessed such as space, time and money which are significant factors when discussing leisure. </s></p><p n="p12.29"><s n="s1.2;p12.29">Rapoport and Rapoport (1975) have argued that there are three dimensions (work, family and leisure) that interrelate together in order for social life to be fully understood. </s><s n="s2.2;p12.29">They believe that it is in the way in which these three factors interact together and the importance that each part has on the next that influences our leisure choices and that during our life cycle these factors will change over time. </s></p><p n="p13.29"><s n="s1.4;p13.29">Nevertheless one of the most popular leisure activities for adults is to visit a pub or bar of some sort. </s><s n="s2.4;p13.29">The reason that most decide to visit is because it is an opportunity to have a break from their every day life and a social place to meet up with their partners and friends in an evening. </s><s n="s3.4;p13.29">In 2002 it was estimated that £20.69 billion would be spent on beer/cider, wine and spirits outside of the home (Mintel, 2003a). </s><s n="s4.4;p13.29">In 2003 it was found that 48% of all leisure expenditure is spent on drinks within pubs (Mintel, 2003c). </s></p><p n="p14.29"><s n="s1.1;p14.29">Mintel (2002) reported that, </s></p><quote lang="English">The pub of course is an important meeting place for the young, often before going on to a nightclub. Many in the 18-24 age group will still be living at home with parents, or in rented accommodation, and lack the space to entertain there. The youngest 18-24 group will also include students who are highly likely to enjoy a drink at the pub. Beyond the 25-34 age group, propensity to have drunk alcohol in a pub with friends tails off first steadily before plummeting among those aged 65+. (Market Drivers, Introduction.)</quote><p n="p15.29"><s n="s1.3;p15.29">A survey carried out in November-December in 2001 based on 1,189 adults, aged 18 upwards showed that 92% of adults drink in a pub or a club, whether it be with friends, family, during the day or during the evening. </s><s n="s2.3;p15.29">Out of that 92% it was then found that 75% of those that drink in the pub with their friends were in the pre-family stage of the life cycle (Mintel, 2002). </s><s n="s3.3;p15.29">The life cycle stage that appeared to produce the lowest percentage of drinking in pubs with friends are those that have retired although appeared to have the highest result for those that drank at home with friends. </s></p><p n="p16.29"><s n="s1.7;p16.29">In a survey carried out by Mintel in 2003(b) looking at four different types of alcoholic beverages served in a pub (white wine, red wine, lager and bitter/ale) produced a varied result as to which life-stage drank what. </s><s n="s2.7;p16.29">It was found that majority of those who drank red wine were of the family and third age life stage. </s><s n="s3.7;p16.29">White wine produced a similar result throughout all the life stages however the third age had the highest percentage. </s><s n="s4.7;p16.29">In terms of lager the highest threshold was those that were pre-family or no family and there was a significant drop amount the third age and retired life stage. </s><s n="s5.7;p16.29">The bitter/ale market produced a not so surprising result in that the highest stages to drink this was those of the third age and those that are retired, as this is seen more commonly as an older mans drink. </s><s n="s6.7;p16.29">The results from the survey though neglected a very important drinks category that may have produced significant results; spirits. </s><s n="s7.7;p16.29">Overall though the result totals were of a similar nature apart from those that are of the retired life stage. </s></p><p n="p17.29"><s n="s1.2;p17.29">Traditional pubs are not the only available outlets of alcohol available any longer. </s><s n="s2.2;p17.29">Mintel (2003d) state that, </s></p><quote lang="English">The concept of the themed pub was exploited in the 1990s, but market trends have been against this type of pub concept in the early 21 <hi rend="sup">st</hi> Century. The themed pub...now occupies a smaller niche market, offering a different experience in pub visiting for the occasional users. (Summary of Key Report Findings, One Niche in an Evolving Market.)</quote><p n="p18.29"><s n="s1.4;p18.29">Although themed pubs in 2000 only took 1.7% of the total spending within pubs it was estimated to be worth £382 million. </s><s n="s2.4;p18.29">This is still a significantly large amount of money for approximately 425 themed pubs to accumulate throughout the year (Mintel, 2003d). </s><s n="s3.4;p18.29">However majority of those that visit a themed pub are those aged between 18-24, the pre-family life stage. </s><s n="s4.4;p18.29">This is largely due to the fact that themed pubs market themselves towards this life stage as it is seen that they are more willing and likely to visit in order to try something new and different (Mintel, 2003d). </s></p><p n="p19.29"><s n="s1.3;p19.29">It appears that visiting a nightclub is a less popular choice from those that wish to drink then visiting a pub. </s><s n="s2.3;p19.29">In an interview carried out by Mintel (2003c) it was found that only 32% of those questioned had visited a nightclub within the previous 12 months, the leisure sector resulting in the lowest percentage. </s><s n="s3.3;p19.29">As previously mentioned it was ascertained that 48% of leisure spending in 2003 was spent on drinks within the pub where as only 28% of leisure spending was spent on an array of entertainment and sporting activities that included nightclubs within it's sector. </s></p><p n="p20.29"><s n="s1.3;p20.29">Mintel (2005) compared expenditure between pubs and nightclubs in 2004. </s><s n="s2.3;p20.29">It showed how £23.4 billion was spent within pubs and that only £1, 798 million was spent within the nightclub market. </s><s n="s3.3;p20.29">This was a decrease in nearly a third since 1999 and Mintel (2005) stated, </s></p><quote lang="English">The nightclub sector has struggled recently due to increased competition from other leisure sectors, such as late-night bars, and will face the same legislative challenges as the pub sector over the next couple of years. (Summary of Key Report Findings, Individual Leisure Sectors, Nightclubs.)</quote><p n="p21.29"><s n="s1.2;p21.29">Mintel (2004a) report that 67% of those in the pre/no family life stage attend nightclubs on a regular basis (at least once a month). </s><s n="s2.2;p21.29">If was found that only 28% of those who are parents aged under 35 go clubbing and then that was only on an occasional basis. </s></p><p n="p22.29"><s n="s1.2;p22.29">Mintel (2004a) found that only 74% of those in the pre/no family life stage visit late night bars with 52% of them visiting at least once a month. </s><s n="s2.2;p22.29">Mintel also found that late night bars are more popular than nightclubs amongst all life stages. </s></p><p n="p23.29"><s n="s1.7;p23.29">Although the general theory in what Rapoport and Rapoport say is still valid in today's day and age there are room for improvements in modern day society. </s><s n="s2.7;p23.29">Unfortunately nowadays families do not stay together as they once did. </s><s n="s3.7;p23.29">Divorce is frequent (in 2000 over half the marriages ended in divorce (Benson, 2003)) and remarriage occurs often (41% of marriages in 2000 were re-marriages (Benson, 2003)). </s><s n="s4.7;p23.29">Single parent families are on the increase whether the result is through divorce or through death (the death rate for males aged between 40-59 is rapidly increasing (National Statistics, 2005). </s><s n="s5.7;p23.29">Fifty years ago it was common for men and women to marry at an early age and have children whilst in their mid-20s. </s><s n="s6.7;p23.29">However as time has progressed society has changed and those in the pre-family/no family life stage no longer feel the pressure to settle down until later on in their lives. </s><s n="s7.7;p23.29">It is now common for people to spend their 20s and possibly their early 30s travelling and living a single life within groups of friends. </s></p><p n="p24.29"><s n="s1.2;p24.29">Those who are in older age groups no longer feel unaccepted in a younger environment and through mass media it has allowed them to be accepted into the young market. </s><s n="s2.2;p24.29">Postmodernism suggests that drinking is increasing in social approval and it allows for the opportunity to network amongst others and to allow alcohol to act as a confidence booster. </s></p><p n="p25.29"><s n="s1.4;p25.29">The wide range of drinks that are found in pubs nowadays allow for older people to feel young. </s><s n="s2.4;p25.29">With the introduction of 'alcohpops' into the drinks market it is a recognisable trendy and young persons drink. </s><s n="s3.4;p25.29">Therefore those who are not within the 18-24 year old age group and who drink the 'alcohpops' may feel that they are creating that bond with those who are younger through the drink that they have. </s><s n="s4.4;p25.29">The older person looks and feels young in themselves and therefore have created an illusion that fails to meet the expectations of Rapoport and Rapoport's theory. </s></p><p n="p26.29"><s n="s1.4;p26.29">With the added opportunities that television programmes also create this allows for both young and older people to connect with each other. </s><s n="s2.4;p26.29">There are television programmes that all generations may watch and it is highly likely that there may be an alcohol related type of sponsorship (e.g. </s><s n="s3.4;p26.29">Sex and the City and Baileys, Friends and Jacobs Creek, Channel 4 films and Stella Artois). </s><s n="s4.4;p26.29">Through mass media this may therefore create an added bond between those in different life stages when in the pub through the sponsored drink. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold italic">Conclusion</head><p n="p27.29"><s n="s1.2;p27.29">Postmodernism and mass media have led to a less distinctive gap between those in different life stages when drinking in a pub. </s><s n="s2.2;p27.29">There are few distinctions in the type of drinks that all life stages consume and the gaps between the frequencies of visits to a pub are becoming smaller and less noticeable. </s></p><p n="p28.29"><s n="s1.4;p28.29">The life stages suggest that those who are in the pre/no family life stage and possibly those that are in the third age should be the life stages that visit the pub more frequently. </s><s n="s2.4;p28.29">It is clear to agree that those in the pre/no family life stage are undoubtedly the largest market for pubs it does not mean that the other life stages can be ruled out. </s><s n="s3.4;p28.29">Increasing numbers of those in the family life stage are visiting the pub and this may be due to the increased expenditure that people have nowadays. </s><s n="s4.4;p28.29">Different pubs do appear to attract different markets (e.g. themed pubs and nightclubs) but overall the boundaries at the traditional pub are narrowing greatly each year. </s></p><p n="p29.29"><s n="s1.1;p29.29">As time has progressed and continues to develop the life stages will need to be developed into more groups in order to be able to incorporate all backgrounds, periods and people and not just those that are the typical characteristics from fifty years ago. </s></p></div1></body><back><div1 type="bibliography"><head rend="bold">References</head><p>Benson, H., (2005). <hi rend="italic">UK Marriage Statistics.</hi> Retrieved on 29<hi rend="sup">th</hi> November 205 at 10.15 from <seg type="URL" n="http://www.2-in-2-1.co.uk/ukstats.html"/></p><p>Mintel International Group Ltd., (2003a). <hi rend="italic">British Lifestyles 2003.</hi></p><p>Mintel International Group Ltd., (2003b). <hi rend="italic">Drinks Market - U.K. - November 2003.</hi></p><p>Mintel International Group Ltd., (2002). <hi rend="italic">Is Britain A Nation Of Drinkers? - U.K. - February 2002.</hi></p><p>Mintel International Group Ltd., (2003c). <hi rend="italic">Leisure Business (The) - U.K. - August 2003.</hi></p><p>Mintel International Group Ltd., (2005). <hi rend="italic">Leisure Review - U.K. - June 2005.</hi></p><p>Mintel International Group Ltd., (2004a). <hi rend="italic">Nightclubs - U.K. - December 2004.</hi></p><p>Mintel International Group Ltd., (2004b). <hi rend="italic">Pub Visiting - U.K. - August 2004.</hi></p><p>Mintel International Group Ltd., (2003d). <hi rend="italic">Themed Pubs and Bars - U.K. - April 2003.</hi></p><p>National Statistics. <hi rend="italic">Death Rates (registrations), by sex and age: 2002-2004</hi>. Retrieved on 29<hi rend="sup">th</hi> November 2005 at 10.34 from <seg type="URL" n="http://www.statistics.gov.uk/STATBASE/ssdataset.asp?vlnk=8983&amp;More=Y"/></p><p>Rapoport, R. N., &amp; Rapoport, R., (1975). <hi rend="italic">Leisure and the Family Life Cycle.</hi> London: Routledge.</p></div1><div1 type="bibliography"><head>Bibliography</head><p>Aitchson, C., (2003). <hi rend="italic">Gender and Leisure: Social and Cultural Perspectives.</hi> London: Routledge.</p><p>Bodie, Z. <hi rend="italic">Life-Cycle Investing in Theory and Practice.</hi> Retrieved on 25<hi rend="sup">th</hi> November 2005 at 12.40 from <seg type="URL" n="http://66.102.9.104/search?q=cache"/>:CabHac2r2GYJ:fmg.lse.ac.uk/upload_file/253_z_bodie_paper.PDF+life+cycle+and+leisure&amp;hl=en</p><p>Clarke, J. &amp; Critcher, C., (1985). <hi rend="italic">The Devil Makes Work.</hi> Basingstoke: MacMillan.</p><p>Critcher, C., Braham, P. &amp; Tomlinson, A., (1995). <hi rend="italic">Sociology of Leisure: A Reader.</hi> London: E &amp; F N Spon.</p><p>Hey, V., (1986). <hi rend="italic">Patriarchy and Pub Culture.</hi> London: Tavistock Publications Ltd.</p><p>Leonard-Barker, D. &amp; Allen, S., (1976). <hi rend="italic">Dependence and Exploitation in Work and Marriage.</hi> London: Longman.</p><p>Lyon, D., (1999). <hi rend="italic">Postmodernity</hi>. (2<hi rend="sup">nd</hi> ed.). Buckingham: Open University Press.</p><p>MADD Online. <hi rend="italic">Underage Drinking Research.</hi> Retrieved on 21<hi rend="sup">st</hi> November 2005 at 19.07 from <seg type="URL" n="http://www.madd.org/stats/0,1056,1114,00.html"/></p><p>Mintel International Group Ltd., (2004). <hi rend="italic">British Lifestyles 2004.</hi></p><p>Mintel International Group Ltd., (2004). <hi rend="italic">High Street Pubs and Bars - U.K.- April 2004.</hi></p><p>Mintel International Group Ltd., (2004). <hi rend="italic">Pub Catering - U.K. - August 2004.</hi></p><p>National Statistics. <hi rend="italic">Population Estimates: UK Population Approaches 60 Million.</hi> Retrieved on 29<hi rend="sup">th</hi> November 2005 at 10.17 from <seg type="URL" n="http://www.statistics.gov.uk/CCI/nugget.asp?ID=6"/></p><p>Social Issues Research Centre. <hi rend="italic">Social and Cultural Aspects of Drinking.</hi> Retrieved on 25<hi rend="sup">th</hi> November 2005 at 12.44 from <seg type="URL" n="http://www.sirc.org/publik/drinking3.html"/></p></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
