<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_3042d" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>The impacts of indigenous culture based tourism in New Zealand: Ethnocentrism and its implications with regard to the commoditisation of Maori images &amp; symbols</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">The document has a title page which contains:
document title
title part</note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">Language used in quote: <foreign id="English">English</foreign></note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">
Student name and number and date in doc header. Module name and number in doc footer.
</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">2</p><p n="date">2005-03</p><p n="module title">Tourism Impact Analysis</p><p n="module code">U57266</p><p n="genre family">Essay</p><p n="discipline">Hospitality, Leisure &amp; Tourism Management</p><p n="disciplinary group">SS</p><p n="grade">D</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">2540</p><p n="number of s-units">74</p><p n="number of p">22</p><p n="number of tables">0</p><p n="number of figures">2</p><p n="number of block quotes">3</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">0</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">0</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">34.3</p><p n="average s-units per p">3.4</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">m</p><p n="year of birth">1983</p><p n="first language">English</p><p n="education">UKa</p><p n="course">Tourism Management / Spanish Studies</p><p n="student ID">3042</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><titlePart>TOURISM IMPACT ANALYSIS, U57266 <hi rend="italic"> Module leader: <name type="tutor name"/> Thematic Essay</hi><hi rend="italic"> (2,500 words)</hi></titlePart><docTitle><titlePart>The impacts of indigenous culture based tourism in New Zealand: Ethnocentrism and its implications with regard to the commoditisation of Maori images &amp; symbols.</titlePart></docTitle><titlePart rend="italic"><name type="student name"/><name type="student ID"/></titlePart><titlePart rend="italic">March - April 2005</titlePart><docTitle><titlePart rend="underlined bold">The impacts of indigenous culture based tourism in New Zealand: Ethnocentrism and its implications with regard to the commoditisation of Maori images &amp; symbols. </titlePart></docTitle></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">Introduction. </head><p n="p1.22"><s n="s1.3;p1.22">Any form of tourism has both positive and negative impacts on the society in which it operates, but the impacts of indigenous culture based tourism, while undoubtedly far-reaching, are particularly hard to measure. </s><s n="s2.3;p1.22">The use of indigenous culture as an asset for tourism is by no means a new phenomenon, but the study of the associated impacts is an area which has only in the last few decades attracted any significant attention. </s><s n="s3.3;p1.22">The interdependence of social, cultural, historical, spiritual, political, anthropological, economic and management factors makes indigenous tourism a complex and interesting field, and one worthy of further study. </s></p><p n="p2.22"><s n="s1.2;p2.22">This essay will therefore examine some of the impacts of indigenous culture based tourism in New Zealand, where the Maori have a significant role to play in a highly developed tourism industry. </s><s n="s2.2;p2.22">A review of existing literature reveals two main schools of thought, one which accepts and even promotes the use of Maori culture as a tool in tourism marketing: </s></p><quote lang="English">"The strong culture of the Maori - unique to New Zealand - is a major aspect of our national heritage which enhances New Zealand's appeal to the world's travellers." (New Zealand Tourist Board, 1993: <hi rend="italic">4</hi>, cited by Hall in Butler &amp; Hinch, 1996: <hi rend="italic">156</hi>)</quote><p n="p3.22"><s n="s1.1;p3.22">And the other which views such use of the culture as disrespectful and exploitative: </s></p><quote lang="English">"Pakeha<ref target="BAWE_3042d-ftnote.001"/> New Zealanders have never been slow to exploit this indigenous culture in promotion and advertising - often in ways that drew Maori disapproval." (Barber, 1992: <hi rend="italic">19</hi>, cited by Hall in Butler &amp; Hinch, 1996: <hi rend="italic">157</hi>)</quote><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3042d-ftnote.001"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1"><hi rend="italic">Pakeha</hi>: <hi rend="italic">A New Zealander of non-Maori, European extraction.</hi> </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">(<hi rend="italic">Ryan, 1997)</hi> </s></p></note><p n="p4.22"><s n="s1.1;p4.22">The essay will address each point of view with reference to recent studies (Hall, 1996; Ryan, 1997; OTSP &amp; TPK, 2000; Ryan, 2002; McIntosh, 2004), while supporting evidence will be drawn from texts on other indigenous groups involved in tourism. </s></p><p n="p5.22"><s n="s1.1;p5.22">It will also attempt to show that Hinch &amp; Butler's (1996: <hi rend="italic">5</hi>) assessment that 'cultural survival will contribute to economic success and economic success will contribute to cultural survival' is simplistic and that a more thorough, multidisciplinary approach is needed to fully understand the issues and conflicts between indigenous peoples and tourism. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">Ethnocentrism. </head><p n="p6.22"><s n="s1.4;p6.22">Ethnocentrism is at the root of many conflicts between indigenous peoples and tourism. </s><s n="s2.4;p6.22">It is concerned with the tendency to see the world from a specific perspective, influenced by cultural factors. </s><s n="s3.4;p6.22">Quite simply, tourism providers and tourists often have a significantly different world view from that of the "fourth world communities" (Evans, 2004: <hi rend="italic">315</hi>) whose culture they gaze upon. </s><s n="s4.4;p6.22">Tourism managers and policy makers are therefore unable to understand the true meaning of indigenous symbols, imagery, practices and beliefs, making sensitive management of that cultural heritage a near impossible task; indigenous communities are often equally restricted in understanding the first world priorities of economic viability and consumerism, leading to disenchantment with tourism. </s></p><p n="p7.22"><s n="s1.5;p7.22">The Maori are more integrated with <hi rend="italic">pakeha</hi> society than many indigenous peoples are with their surrounding communities, but ethnocentrism remains an issue. </s><s n="s2.5;p7.22">"Maori possess a holistic world view" (Ryan, 1997: <hi rend="italic">270</hi>) in which the people and the land (and everything else) are closely spiritually linked. </s><s n="s3.5;p7.22">Additionally, common to many indigenous groups around the world, family and tribal values are hugely significant, decision is traditionally by consensus, and individual entrepreneurship is frowned upon. </s><s n="s4.5;p7.22">In contrast, first world values of enterprise and "economic rationalism" (Whitford, Bell &amp; Watkins, 2001) dominate tourism development and must be reconciled as far as possible with the aforementioned traditional values. </s><s n="s5.5;p7.22">However, as a New Zealand Government tourism report highlighted: </s></p><quote lang="English">"There is perceived, among Maori, to be a lack of understanding of Maori values, culture and issues by non-Maori (including tourists and tour operators). [...]. That perceived lack of understanding [...] has also led, arguably, to an overly simplistic dependency on a marketing-led ideology of tourism rather than a concern and understanding of Maori cultural issues." (OTSP &amp; TPK, 2000: <hi rend="italic">7</hi>)</quote><p n="p8.22"><s n="s1.2;p8.22">Given that the key decision makers in the politics and management of tourism are predominantly non-indigenous - and above all businessmen, not anthropologists - it is not surprising that the worth of tourism projects is generally judged "by the bottom line of the balance sheet rather than the well-being of people who contribute to the balance sheet" (Whitford, Bell &amp; Watkins, 2001). </s><s n="s2.2;p8.22">First world priorities often override the cultural sensibility of indigenous communities, including the Maori. </s></p><p n="p9.22"><s n="s1.1;p9.22">So, while the New Zealand Tourist Board (1993) and Hinch &amp; Butler's introduction (1996) would have us believe in an ideal, mutually beneficial relationship between indigenous culture and tourism, in reality there are deep-rooted interests and principles on both sides which come into direct conflict; the very compatibility of indigenous culture and tourism is called into question. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">Overcoming ethnocentrism. </head><p n="p10.22"><s n="s1.4;p10.22">Despite the obvious issues related to cross-cultural understanding and communication, there are strategies which can be employed in order to minimise any problems. </s><s n="s2.4;p10.22">The Maori have political representation (Te Puni Kōkiri - Ministry of Maori Development) as well as various groups that have shared responsibility for protecting Maori rights (Ministry of Cultural Affairs; Maori Tourism Task Force, later the Aotearoa Maori Tourist Federation) and concerted efforts have been made to highlight the needs of the Maori so that cultural sensibilities are respected by tourism development. </s><s n="s3.4;p10.22">The importance of meaningful dialogue between the industry and indigenous groups should not be understated. </s><s n="s4.4;p10.22">Traditionally "there has been minimal consultation with Maori over the promotion of Maori culture in the tourism industry" (OTSP &amp; TPK, 2000: <hi rend="italic">6</hi>) and various reports (Ryan, 1997; OTSP &amp; TPK, 2000, 2001; WTO/UNEP, 2002; Dyer, Aberdeen &amp; Schuler, 2003; Evans, 2004) highlight the lack of culturally appropriate communication with indigenous groups, who may (as in the case of the Maori) favour a process of full partnership and consensus rather than merely being consulted (OTSP &amp; TPK, 2000: <hi rend="italic">9</hi>), or may (as with Australian aborigines) have an oral tradition, rendering letters to elders inappropriate as the predominant means of communication. </s></p><p n="p11.22"><s n="s1.4;p11.22">McClean <hi rend="italic">et al</hi> (1997: <hi rend="italic">9</hi>, cited in Dyer, Aberdeen &amp; Schuler, 2003: <hi rend="italic">85</hi>) refers to the 'spirit of partnership' when working with indigenous peoples, a concept which is echoed in much of the existing literature studied on Maori based tourism. </s><s n="s2.4;p11.22">This is more than simply involving indigenous peoples in planning and consulting them on the appropriateness of an attraction; a real partnership includes "development that is culturally sustainable, that is, owned, controlled, acceptable and desired by the indigenous communities affected, as well as economically sustainable" (McIntosh, 2004: <hi rend="italic">1</hi>). </s><s n="s3.4;p11.22">The community must ideally be involved in all levels of tourism, including, crucially, the interpretation and management of it, for they are the people who best understand sensitive cultural issues and are best placed to manage them. </s><s n="s4.4;p11.22">The lack of indigenous involvement in tourism planning, development and management accentuates the problems caused by ethnocentrism and raises related issues regarding Maori custodianship of their own culture and gaining access to the economic benefits of indigenous culture based tourism. </s></p><p n="p12.22"><s n="s1.5;p12.22">Although the need for tourism industry-Maori partnerships is clear, there are obstacles to indigenous involvement. </s><s n="s2.5;p12.22">Dyer, Aberdeen &amp; Schuler (2003) identify several key factors, including limited business knowledge, poor education and inability to secure capital loans. </s><s n="s3.5;p12.22">Indigenous communities have valuable insights to offer in the interpretation of their culture, but often members of those communities experience a 'glass ceiling' effect whereby they can become involved in low-level activities like guiding (official or otherwise) or arts and crafts, but wield little influence over large tour operators, large attractions or policy makers, and find it hard to access higher levels of management. </s><s n="s4.5;p12.22">Evans (2004: <hi rend="italic">325</hi>) notes, "ethnic groups have secured, at least theoretically, international support in their jockeying for cultural recognition and political influence", but case studies (Ryan, 1997; OTSP &amp; TPK, 2000; Whitford, Bell &amp; Watkins, 2001; Dyer, Aberdeen &amp; Schuler, 2003; Evans 2004; McGrath, 2004; McIntosh, 2004) suggest that in reality, many minority ethno-cultural groups lack any real influence and as such are excluded from the custodianship of their own culture. </s><s n="s5.5;p12.22">Furthermore, given the overwhelming dominance of 'outsiders' in management positions, indigenous people are also denied access to a significant portion of the economic benefit. </s></p><p n="p13.22"><s n="s1.1;p13.22">Although in New Zealand the segregation of indigenous and non-indigenous people is not as severe as in other countries, Maori face several of the same key issues as other indigenous peoples around the world; If they are not involved in the management and interpretation of their own culture, negative impacts are likely to be greater, and the potential benefits to them, smaller. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">The use and abuse of Maori images &amp; symbols. </head><p n="p14.22"><s n="s1.5;p14.22">The potential negative impacts of indigenous culture based tourism are numerous and varied. </s><s n="s2.5;p14.22">"Poverty, displacement of communities and the erosion of cultural traditions" (WTO/UNEP, 2002), "rejection of traditional culture itself" (Dyer, Aberdeen &amp; Schuler, 2003), intrusion into sacred sites (OTSP &amp; TPK, 2000), 'dispossession' of culture (Hinch &amp; Butler, 1996: <hi rend="italic">10</hi>) and "clashes of values" (Reisinger, in Seaton, 1994) are just some of the issues faced. </s><s n="s3.5;p14.22">However, many of the most serious issues in New Zealand are related to the use and abuse of symbols and images which are sacred to the Maori, but which have become commonplace in tourism marketing, literature and souvenirs. </s><s n="s4.5;p14.22">At its extreme, "treating culture as a natural resource or a commodity over which tourists have rights is not simply perverse, it is a violation of the people's cultural rights" (Greenwood, 1978, in Smith, 1989: <hi rend="italic">179</hi>) and is a profoundly negative impact of tourism which arises from an ethnocentric attitude to management; a refusal to consider that perhaps what to us seems a simple design, may, for someone else, have a much deeper spiritual meaning. </s><s n="s5.5;p14.22">The ethical dimension of commercially using indigenous images is rarely fully considered. </s></p><p n="p15.22"><s n="s1.2;p15.22">The value of Maori imagery to tourism has long been recognised so has often been exploited. </s><s n="s2.2;p15.22">In 1987 the Maori Tourism Task Force highlighted the issue: </s></p><p n="p16.22"><s n="s1.3;p16.22">"It has been of deep concern to the Maori that the Maori image has been used as a marketing tool in the promotion of the tourist industry for over a hundred years [...] It is clear that the Maori image has commercial value. </s><s n="s2.3;p16.22">The expressed desire of the Maori people is that they should control their image..." </s><s n="s3.3;p16.22">(Maori Tourism Task Force, 1986: <hi rend="italic">25</hi>, cited by Hall in Butler &amp; Hinch, 1996: <hi rend="italic">170</hi>). </s></p><p n="p17.22"><s n="s1.2;p17.22">However, nothing changed and in 1994 the Aotearoa Maori Tourism Federation identified the "misuse of Taonga<ref target="BAWE_3042d-ftnote.002"/>. </s><s n="s2.2;p17.22">This involves the misuse of names and language, mispronunciation, inappropriate use of images on souvenirs and photographs, and the incorrect and inappropriate communication of histories and tribal lore" (cited by Ryan, 1997: <hi rend="italic">265</hi>). </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3042d-ftnote.002"><p n="pn1.1"><s rend="italic" n="s1.3;pn1.1">Taonga: Property, treasure. </s><s rend="italic" n="s2.3;pn1.1">Used more widely to mean culture as well as tangible items. </s><s rend="italic" n="s3.3;pn1.1">(Ryan, 1997) </s></p></note><p n="p18.22"><s n="s1.3;p18.22">There is still significant stereotyping, misuse of images and symbols, exploitation, misrepresentation, commoditisation and/or bastardisation of Maori culture. </s><s n="s2.3;p18.22">Modern indigenous culture is often neglected in favour of meeting overseas tourist expectations, so a rose-tinted view of a more primitive, bygone age is presented (see for example right - Discover the World, 2004: <hi rend="italic">24</hi>). </s><s n="s3.3;p18.22">It is important to recognise that any culture is "dynamic and emergent" (Kroshus Medina, 2003: <hi rend="italic">354</hi>) rather than static, so to present a complex and continually evolving culture simply as a centuries-old tradition may be considered misleading. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_3042d-pic.001"/><p n="p19.22"><s n="s1.3;p19.22">The misrepresentation of indigenous culture and misuse of symbols, due at least in part to <hi rend="italic">pakeha</hi> dominance of the industry, highlights the need for indigenous involvement in tourism management as a means of ensuring ethical practices. </s><s n="s2.3;p19.22">Furthermore, a lack of legislation leads to problems securing intellectual property rights (OTSP &amp; TPK, 2001: <hi rend="italic">82-84</hi>), meaning that Maori, just like indigenous communities in less developed countries, have to an extent lost control over their heritage. </s><s n="s3.3;p19.22">While for the Maori it is an important, respected and valued part of life, in the tourism industry, Maori heritage is largely viewed as an asset; a tool for attracting visitors to New Zealand. </s></p><p n="p20.22"><s n="s1.2;p20.22">The use of indigenous people and culture as a marketing tool is by no means restricted to New Zealand. </s><s n="s2.2;p20.22">There are abundant examples in a wide variety of brochures and tourist board promotional materials (Audley Travel, 2005a; Audley Travel , 2005b; Discover The World, 2004; Last Frontiers, 2005; Tourism Australia, 2005; Wanderlust/Journey Latin America, 2005) as well as in company logos (see right - Air New Zealand aircraft livery, in Audley Travel, 2005a: <hi rend="italic">5</hi>). </s></p><figure id="BAWE_3042d-pic.002"/><p n="p21.22"><s n="s1.9;p21.22">Easily identifiable images which tourists immediately relate to a particular country or destination are obviously immensely valuable for tourism promotion. </s><s n="s2.9;p21.22">There is little problem when those images are buildings (e.g. </s><s n="s3.9;p21.22">Sydney Opera House), monuments (e.g. </s><s n="s4.9;p21.22">Eiffel Tower) or other features of the built environment (e.g. </s><s n="s5.9;p21.22">Golden Gate Bridge), but when those images are of deep social, cultural or spiritual significance to a community then an assessment must be made regarding their suitability for commoditisation. </s><s n="s6.9;p21.22">Maori culture is undeniably valuable to New Zealand tourism and there are notable successes of Maori communities involved in the industry (e.g. </s><s n="s7.9;p21.22">The <hi rend="italic">Ngati Wahiao</hi> at Whakarewarewa Thermal Village, Rotorua and <hi rend="italic">Ngāi Tahu</hi> affiliated to Whale Watch Kaikoura), but they are successful partly because their ethos reflects an understanding of indigenous culture, values and practices which is written into company mission statements (e.g. </s><s n="s8.9;p21.22">Ngāi Tahu Holdings Group, 2005). </s><s n="s9.9;p21.22">Other, <hi rend="italic">pakeha</hi> dominated, companies do not always take such a respectful approach. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">Conclusions. </head><p n="p22.22"><s n="s1.11;p22.22">The New Zealand Tourist Board is right to emphasise the importance of Maori heritage for New Zealand tourism and there are undeniably some positive economic and social impacts of tourism for the Maori, e.g. preservation of cultural heritage. </s><s n="s2.11;p22.22">This is, however, a superficial view and a more thorough examination reveals deep-rooted problems with the management - or rather, mismanagement - of Maori culture based tourism products. </s><s n="s3.11;p22.22">Beyond specifically Maori products, Maori heritage is used inappropriately in the wider New Zealand tourism industry, particularly in marketing. </s><s n="s4.11;p22.22">It seems an unequal relationship in which sacred Maori heritage is exploited for commercial ends and the Maori have little or no political or legal recourse, while, as with other indigenous communities around the world, the economic and social benefits are minimal. </s><s n="s5.11;p22.22">The industry is dominated by economic rationalism with a near total disregard for anthropological issues, which are left to academics. </s><s n="s6.11;p22.22">As Ryan (1997: 257) highlights, "The Ministry of Cultural Affairs [...] notes the need for more attention to environmental, social and cultural effects of tourism and that "<hi rend="bold italic">greater resources need to be devoted to thinking and a little less to selling</hi>" (Parliamentary Commissioner for the Environment, 1997: 14)" [emphasis added]. </s><s n="s7.11;p22.22">The issues associated with indigenous peoples and tourism go far beyond balancing cultural survival and economic success, but non-indigenous tourism professionals are often not in a position to fully understand all the related social, cultural, historical, spiritual and political issues. </s><s n="s8.11;p22.22">The sharing of any indigenous culture is a gift, and demands an appropriately sensitive response from tourists and the tourism industry. </s><s n="s9.11;p22.22">Without cooperation and knowledge from other disciplines and above all indigenous people themselves, tourism can become highly intrusive and exploitative. </s><s n="s10.11;p22.22">Preventing this requires an "acknowledgement of the limitations of Western thinking and assumptions in applying value-judgements" (Evans, 1994b, in Seaton, 1994: 836) and a departure from the ethnocentric, economic rationalist viewpoint discussed by Whitford, Bell &amp; Watkins (2001) which is still so dominant. </s><s n="s11.11;p22.22">If this is not possible, then the use of cultural symbols and imagery is perhaps best left to the legitimate custodians of that culture rather than allow it to be appropriated by those who do not fully appreciate its significance. </s></p></div1></body><back><div1 type="bibliography"><head rend="underlined bold">RESOURCES</head><p>AUDLEY TRAVEL (2005a), <hi rend="italic">New Zealand &amp; The South Pacific</hi>. [brochure]</p><p>AUDLEY TRAVEL (2005b), <hi rend="italic">South America</hi>. [brochure]</p><p>COOPER et al (1998), <hi rend="underlined">Tourism: Principles and Practice</hi> (2<hi rend="sup">nd</hi> Ed.), Prentice Hall, Harlow.</p><p>DISCOVER THE WORLD (2004), <hi rend="italic">Discover the World: New Zealand</hi>. [brochure]</p><p>DYER, P., ABERDEEN, L. &amp; SCHULER, S (2003), 'Tourism Impacts on an Australian indigenous community: a Djabugay case study', <hi rend="italic">Tourism Management</hi>, Vol.24, No.1: <hi rend="italic">83-95</hi>.</p><p>EVANS, G. (1994a), <hi rend="italic">'Fair trade: cultural tourism and craft production in the third world'</hi>.</p><p><hi rend="italic">In</hi>: SEATON, A.V et al (1994), <hi rend="underlined">Tourism: The State of the Art</hi>, John Wiley &amp; Sons, Chichester [p.783-791]</p><p>EVANS, G. (1994b), <hi rend="italic">'Whose culture is it anyway? Tourism in Greater Mexico and the Indigena'</hi>.</p><p><hi rend="italic">In</hi>: SEATON, A.V et al (1994), <hi rend="underlined">Tourism: The State of the Art</hi>, John Wiley &amp; Sons, Chichester [p.836-847]</p><p>EVANS, G. (2004), 'Mundo Maya: From Cancún to City of Culture. World Heritage in Post-colonial Mesoamerica', <hi rend="italic">Current Issues in Tourism</hi>, Vol.7, Nos.4-5: <hi rend="italic">315-329</hi>.</p><p>GREENWOOD, D.J. (1978), <hi rend="italic">'Culture by the Pound: An Anthropological Perspective on Tourism as Cultural Commoditization'</hi>.</p><p><hi rend="italic">In</hi>: SMITH, V.L (<hi rend="italic">Ed</hi>.) (1989), <hi rend="underlined">Hosts and Guests: The Anthropology of Tourism</hi> (2<hi rend="sup">nd</hi> Ed.), University of Pennsylvania Press, Philadelphia [p.171-185]</p><p>HALL, C.M. (1996), <hi rend="italic">'Tourism and the Maori of Aotearoa, New Zealand'</hi>.</p><p><hi rend="italic">In</hi>: BUTLER, R &amp; HINCH, T (<hi rend="italic">Eds</hi>.) (1996), <hi rend="underlined">Tourism and Indigenous Peoples</hi>, International Thomson Business Press, London [p.155-175]</p><p>HINCH, T (1998), 'Ecotourists and Indigenous Hosts: Diverging Views on Their Relationship with Nature', <hi rend="italic">Current Issues in Tourism</hi>, Vol.1, No.1: <hi rend="italic">120-124</hi>.</p><p>HINCH, T. &amp; BUTLER, R. (1996), <hi rend="italic">'Indigenous tourism: a common ground for discussion'</hi>.</p><p><hi rend="italic">In</hi>: BUTLER, R &amp; HINCH, T (<hi rend="italic">Eds</hi>.) (1996), <hi rend="underlined">Tourism and Indigenous Peoples</hi>, International Thomson Business Press, London [p.3-19]</p><p>HOLLINSHEAD, K. (1996), <hi rend="italic">'Marketing and metaphysical realism: the disidentification of Aboriginal life and traditions through tourism'</hi>.</p><p><hi rend="italic">In</hi>: BUTLER, R &amp; HINCH, T (<hi rend="italic">Eds</hi>.) (1996), <hi rend="underlined">Tourism and Indigenous Peoples</hi>, International Thomson Business Press, London [p.308-348]</p><p>KROSHUS MEDINA, L. (2003), 'Commoditizing Culture: Tourism and Maya Identity', <hi rend="italic">Annals of Tourism Research</hi>, Vol.30, No.2: <hi rend="italic">353-368</hi>.</p><p>LAST FRONTIERS (2005), <hi rend="italic">Latin America</hi>. [brochure]</p><p>MADER, R. (2002), 'Latin American ecotourism: What is it?', <hi rend="italic">Current Issues in Tourism</hi>, Vol.5, No.3-4: <hi rend="italic">272-279</hi>.</p><p>MCGRATH, G. (2004), 'Including the outsiders: The Contribution of Guides to Integrated Heritage Tourism Management in Cusco, Southern Peru', <hi rend="italic">Current Issues in Tourism</hi>, Vol.7, No.4-5: <hi rend="italic">426-432</hi>.</p><p>MCINTOSH, A.J. (2004), 'Tourists' appreciation of Maori culture in New Zealand', <hi rend="italic">Tourism Management</hi>, Vol.25, No.1: <hi rend="italic">1-15</hi>.</p><p>NGĀI TAHU HOLDINGS GROUP (2005), 'Core Business', Accessed 29-04-05: <seg type="URL" n="http://www.ngaitahu.iwi.nz/Holdings/Group%20Profile/Core%20Business"/></p><p>OTSP &amp; TPK [New Zealand Office of Tourism and Sport &amp; Te Puni Kōkiri - Ministry of Maori Development] (2000), 'Closing the Gaps - He matai tapoi Maori: barriers and impediments short report', The Stafford Group.</p><p>Accessed 28-03-05: <seg type="URL" n="http://www.tourism.govt.nz/policy/pol-reports/pol-app-maoriapp1.pdf"/></p><p>OTSP &amp; TPK [New Zealand Office of Tourism and Sport &amp; Te Puni Kōkiri - Ministry of Maori Development] (2001), 'A Study of Barriers, Impediments and Opportunities for Maori in Tourism - He Matai Tapoi Maori', The Stafford Group.</p><p>Accessed 26-04-05: <seg type="URL" n="http://www.tpk.govt.nz/publications/docs/MTour_full.pdf"/></p><p>REISINGER, Y. (1989), <hi rend="italic">'Social contact between tourists and hosts of different cultural backgrounds'</hi>.</p><p><hi rend="italic">In</hi>: SEATON, A.V et al (1994), <hi rend="underlined">Tourism: The State of the Art</hi>, John Wiley &amp; Sons, Chichester [p.743-754]</p><p>RYAN, C (1997), 'Maori and Tourism: A Relationship of History, Constitutions and Rites', <hi rend="italic">Journal of Sustainable Tourism</hi>, Vol.5, No.4: <hi rend="italic">257-278</hi>.</p><p>RYAN, C. (2002), 'Tourism and cultural proximity - Examples from New Zealand', <hi rend="italic">Annals of Tourism Research</hi>, Vol.29, No.4: <hi rend="italic">952-971</hi>.</p><p>RYAN, C. &amp; HUYTON J, (2002), 'Tourists and Aboriginal people', <hi rend="italic">Annals of Tourism Research</hi>, Vol.29, No.3: <hi rend="italic">631-647</hi>.</p><p>SMITH, V.L. (1996),<hi rend="italic"> 'Indigenous tourism: the four Hs'</hi>.</p><p><hi rend="italic">In</hi>: BUTLER, R &amp; HINCH, T (<hi rend="italic">Eds</hi>.) (1996), <hi rend="underlined">Tourism and Indigenous Peoples</hi>, International Thomson Business Press, London [p.283-307]</p><p>TOURISM AUSTRALIA (2005), <hi rend="italic">The Official Guide to Australia 2005/2006</hi>.</p><p>WANDERLUST/JOURNEY LATIN AMERICA (2005), <hi rend="italic">Discover the Andes</hi>, Wanderlust Publications Ltd.</p><p>WHAKAREWAREWA THERMAL VILLAGE TOURS (2005), 'Background', Accessed 29-04-05: <seg type="URL" n="http://www.whakarewarewa.com/index2.htm"/></p><p>WHALE WATCH KAIKOURA LTD (2002), Accessed 29-04-05: <seg type="URL" n="http://www.whalewatch.co.nz/"/></p><p>WHITFORD, M., BELL, B. &amp; WATKINS, M. (2001), 'Indigenous Tourism policy in Australia: 25 Years of Rhetoric and Economic Rationalism', <hi rend="italic">Current Issues in Tourism</hi>, Vol.4, No.2-4: <hi rend="italic">151-181</hi>.</p><p>WTO/UNEP (2002), <hi rend="underlined">World Ecotourism Summit - Final Report</hi>, WTO, Madrid.</p><p>Accessed 28-03-05:</p><p><seg type="URL" n="http://www.world-tourism.org/sustainable/IYE/quebec/anglais/Final-Report-QuebecSummit-web.pdf"/></p></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
