<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_3044a" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title></title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">
Assignemnt came in 2 files, put together into 1.
</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">4</p><p n="date">2005-10</p><p n="module title">Primate Conservation - Research Methods</p><p n="module code">P20103</p><p n="genre family">Proposal</p><p n="discipline">Anthropology</p><p n="disciplinary group">SS</p><p n="grade">M</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">671</p><p n="number of s-units">37</p><p n="number of p">25</p><p n="number of tables">1</p><p n="number of figures">0</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">0</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">3</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">18.1</p><p n="average s-units per p">1.5</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">m</p><p n="year of birth">1970</p><p n="first language">Swedish</p><p n="education">OSa</p><p n="course">MSc Primate Conservation</p><p n="student ID">3044</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front/><body><div1 type="section"><p n="p1.25"><s n="s1.6;p1.25">Nocturnal primates of the family Galagidae have recently been under great taxonomic revision due to new discoveries concerning their behavior and morphology. </s><s n="s2.6;p1.25">New species are appearing at such a rapid rate that the important process of scientifically identifying and naming species has been put on the backburner. </s><s n="s3.6;p1.25">Effective conservation work is dependent on an updated taxonomy in order to acknowledge the width of the biodiversity one is trying to save (Grubbal. 2003; Groves, 2001). </s><s n="s4.6;p1.25">The proposed investigation concerns a taxonomic study of one up to four as yet scientifically unnamed primates of the genus <hi rend="italic">Galagoides</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Sciurocheirus</hi>. </s><s n="s5.6;p1.25">The study's main objective will be to compile sufficient amounts of character data, i.e. behavioral, morphological and genetic data, to enable the endorsement of species status independent of species concept (see Groves, 2001, for overview) applied with the specific aim as to publicly name these species in accordance with the International Code of Zoological Nomenclature (ICZN, 1999) regulations. </s><s n="s6.6;p1.25">The data collected will also create the body of a comprehensive database over the known information of the family Galagidae. </s></p><p n="p2.25"><s n="s1.1;p2.25">The research will be carried out in several steps and with different methodologies appropriate for descriptions of new species (ICZN, 1999): </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p3.25"><s n="s1.3;p3.25">An exhaustive literature study where previous descriptions of the target taxa will be researched. </s><s n="s2.3;p3.25">The information gathered will provide important background information vital for both the choice of scientific name and for the species description. </s><s n="s3.3;p3.25">Characters previously used as means for species description for nocturnal, cryptic species such as penile morphology, facial masks and vocal repertoire will be of special interest but general morphological, behavioral and distributional data will also be investigated. </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p4.25"><s n="s1.3;p4.25">Localize museum specimens (if available) for each species to conduct morphological research. </s><s n="s2.3;p4.25">New specimens of primates rarely occur in museums due to export regulations for endangered species (Baillie, 2004), however, the presence of these newly discovered species often exist in museum collections under erroneous names (Bearder, pers. comm.) </s><s n="s3.3;p4.25">This means that valuable material is available for descriptive morphometric analysis and historical distribution. </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p5.25"><s n="s1.3;p5.25">Comparative analysis of recent field data including vocal recordings, behavioral data, distribution, morphology and genetics (i.e. karyotyping). </s><s n="s2.3;p5.25">Special emphasis will be put on vocal analysis and karyotyping since these features have been shown to be highly significant as diagnostic tools for species specification within the Galagidae family (Bearderal. 1995; Masters, 1986). </s><s n="s3.3;p5.25">Vocal recordings and tissue samples from the targeted species are available for analysis (Bearder, pers. comm., 2005). </s></p><table id="BAWE_3044a-tab.001"><row><cell/></row></table></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">Funding agencies</head><div2><head rend="bold">Primate Action Fund</head><p n="p6.25"><s n="s1.1;p6.25">Conservation International </s></p><p n="p7.25"><s n="s1.1;p7.25">Awards of US$ 1000-5000 </s></p><p n="p8.25"><s n="s1.1;p8.25">The principal objective of Conservation International's Primate Action Fund is to contribute to global biodiversity conservation by providing strategically targeted, catalytic support for the conservation of endangered nonhuman primates and their natural habitats. </s></p><p n="p9.25"><s n="s1.1;p9.25">Information about application process is given by Dr Anthony Rylands at a.rylands@conservation.org </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">ASP General Small Grant</head><p n="p10.25"><s n="s1.1;p10.25">American Society of Primatologist </s></p><p n="p11.25"><s n="s1.1;p11.25">Awards amounts range from US$ 500-1500 </s></p><p n="p12.25"><s n="s1.1;p12.25">Grant proposals are invited for general research projects, with preference given to training initiatives, start-up funds, supplementary funding for students, and innovations in animal care and research technology. </s></p><p n="p13.25"><s n="s1.1;p13.25">Information about application process is found on <seg type="URL" n="www.asp.org/grants"/> </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">Awards for Graduate Student Research</head><p n="p14.25"><s n="s1.1;p14.25">Society of Systematic Biologists </s></p><p n="p15.25"><s n="s1.1;p15.25">Awards range between US$ 1000-5000 </s></p><p n="p16.25"><s n="s1.2;p16.25">Systematics is interpreted broadly to include questions below and above the species level, molecular and morphological approaches, and issues of pattern and process. </s><s n="s2.2;p16.25">Funding is not limited to any particular aspect of research, but rather is available for field, museum/herbarium, and/or laboratory work. </s></p><p n="p17.25"><s n="s1.1;p17.25">Information about application process is found on <seg type="URL" n="www.systbio.org"/> </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">The Systematic Research Fund</head><p n="p18.25"><s n="s1.1;p18.25">The Systematics Association and The Linnean Society of London </s></p><p n="p19.25"><s n="s1.1;p19.25">Awards amounts up to a maximum of £ 1500 </s></p><p n="p20.25"><s n="s1.1;p20.25">Provide small grants to support research in the field of systematics. </s></p><p n="p21.25"><s n="s1.1;p21.25">Information about application process is found on <seg type="URL" n="www.linnean.org"/> </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">Grants-in-Aid of Research</head><p n="p22.25"><s n="s1.1;p22.25">The Society for Integrative and Comparative Biology </s></p><p n="p23.25"><s n="s1.1;p23.25">Awards amounts up to a maximum of US$ 1000 </s></p><p n="p24.25"><s n="s1.1;p24.25">The Grants-in-Aid of Research program was established by the SICB in 1996 to provide small awards to graduate students in support of their research in the fields of integrative and comparative biology. </s></p><p n="p25.25"><s n="s1.1;p25.25">Information about application process is found on <seg type="URL" n="www.sicb.org/grants"/> </s></p></div2></div1></body><back/></text></TEI.2>
