<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_3045e" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>The criteria determining a book's potential in foreign countries: a case study</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">Language used in quote: <foreign id="English">English</foreign></note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">Language used in quote: <foreign id="Italian">Italian</foreign></note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">
Student name, student number, module name, module number and date in doc header. Word count at the end of running text (before bibliography).
</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">4</p><p n="date">2006-05</p><p n="module title">Publishing and Language Issues</p><p n="module code">P65026</p><p n="genre family">Case study</p><p n="discipline">Publishing</p><p n="disciplinary group">SS</p><p n="grade">M</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">3525</p><p n="number of s-units">88</p><p n="number of p">64</p><p n="number of tables">2</p><p n="number of figures">1</p><p n="number of block quotes">10</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">1</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">3</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">40.1</p><p n="average s-units per p">1.4</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">f</p><p n="year of birth">1979</p><p n="first language">Italian</p><p n="education">OSa</p><p n="course">MA Publishing</p><p n="student ID">3045</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><docTitle><titlePart rend="bold">The criteria determining a book's potential in foreign countries: a case study. </titlePart></docTitle></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">1. Introduction</head><div2><head rend="bold">1.1. Choosing "Better than Sex" as a case study</head><p n="p1.64"><s n="s1.1;p1.64">I happened upon "Better than Sex" by chance, at a book sale at the Student Union.Beyond the cheekiness of the title, the cover image and subtitle immediately conveyed what the topic and tone would be, in what I thought to be a strikingly well chosen combination. </s></p><p n="p2.64"><s n="s1.1;p2.64">"Better than Sex" was published and promoted by Random House Australia in 2004, but - surprisingly to me, at first - never sold Italian (or any other language) translation rights.After less than two years from a successful publication, because of its current affairs content, it is outdated and realistically impossible to sell: therefore "Better than Sex" makes for an interesting case study on why foreign rights are bought (or not bought), allowing the perspective to analyse what happened in hindsight. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">1.2. Background</head><p n="p3.64"><s n="s1.3;p3.64">"Better than Sex" was published by Random House Australia in paperback, on June 1st 2004; the authors are two Australian journalists, who write about work environment and office organisation for a Financial Times magazine called AFT Boss.One of them, Helen Trinca, was heavily involved in the publicity for the book, which included a well-balanced and well-paced succession of press releases, radio talks<ref target="BAWE_3045e-endnote.001"/>, participation in conferences and seminars<ref target="BAWE_3045e-endnote.002"/>, and reviews<ref target="BAWE_3045e-endnote.003"/>. </s><s n="s2.3;p3.64">However, her popularity doesn't cross borders and couldn't be used to promote the book abroad.The book was fairly successful in its home market, with sales summing up to 1.827 as of April 2006<ref target="BAWE_3045e-endnote.004"/> (see 6.1. </s><s n="s3.3;p3.64">Product life-cycle for graph). </s></p><note place="end" id="BAWE_3045e-endnote.001"><p n="pn1.2"><s n="s1.1;pn1.2">"Is Work Better Than Sex?", June 2nd 2004, radio interview with presenter Richard Glover on 702 ABC Sidney, retrieved on April 29th 2006 from: </s></p><p n="pn2.2"><s n="s1.1;pn2.2"><seg type="URL" n="http://www.abc.net.au/sydney/stories/s1124031.htm"/> </s></p></note><note place="end" id="BAWE_3045e-endnote.002"><p n="pn1.5"><s n="s1.1;pn1.5">"Fair go or anything goes", Sidney, July 13th 2005, conference on the industrial relations reform, transcript of Helen Trinca's speech retrieved on April 29th 2006 from: </s></p><p n="pn2.5"><s n="s1.1;pn2.5"><seg type="URL" n="http://www.iceaustralia.com/ir/pdf/Session%203%20-%20Impact%20on%20the%20Individual.pdf"/> </s></p><p n="pn3.5"><s n="s1.1;pn3.5">and </s></p><p n="pn4.5"><s n="s1.1;pn4.5">"Executive Women and Leadership Congress", Sidney, November 30th to December 2nd 2005, seminar programme and registration form retrieved on April 29th 2006 from: </s></p><p n="pn5.5"><s n="s1.1;pn5.5"><seg type="URL" n="http://www.iir.com.au/user_pages/conf/pdf/L1229.pdf"/> </s></p></note><note place="end" id="BAWE_3045e-endnote.003"><p n="pn1.2"><s n="s1.1;pn1.2">"Work and family life: what we've forgotten", by Suzanne Franzway, April 4th 2005, review in Australian Review of Public Affairs, retrieved on May 1st 2006 from: </s></p><p n="pn2.2"><s n="s1.1;pn2.2"><seg type="URL" n="http://www.australianreview.net/digest/2005/04/franzway.html"/> </s></p></note><note place="end" id="BAWE_3045e-endnote.004"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">data from the Nielsen BookScan database, provided by Richard Knight </s></p></note><p n="p4.64"><s n="s1.2;p4.64">At the 2004 Frankfurt Book Fair, it was promoted in the Random House Australia Rights Catalogue<ref target="BAWE_3045e-endnote.005"/>; however, according to Unesco's Translationum database, there haven't been any translations of "Better than Sex" at all. </s><s n="s2.2;p4.64">Today, the book is still available through minor internet book retailers (Dymocks, Whitcoulls, Bookworld), especially remainders specialists, but not Amazon.Bookstores don't stock it and won't order it, though it can still be found by chance, as I did, at remainder sales.Although the main Italian e-retailers (Books Online, Internet Bookshop) offer a range of foreign books to gain competitive advantage over brick-and-mortar stores, they don't include "Better than Sex" in their lists.A Google research for pages in Italian, French or German containing the title and the word "Trinca" leads to only one relevant result: the list of newly acquired books of the Mannheim University Library. </s></p><note place="end" id="BAWE_3045e-endnote.005"><p n="pn1.2"><s n="s1.1;pn1.2">Random House Australia Rights Catalogue for the Frankfurt Book Fair, 2004, retrieved on March 23rd 2006 from: </s></p><p n="pn2.2"><s n="s1.1;pn2.2"><seg type="URL" n="http://www.randomhouse.com.au/Rights/Random%20House%20Australia%20Rights%20Guide.pdf"/> </s></p></note></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">2. Cultural transferability</head><div2><head rend="bold">2.1. References to Australia</head><p n="p5.64"><s n="s1.1;p5.64">"Better than Sex" is clearly a light-tone sociological study of the developments in the Australian work environment. </s></p><p n="p6.64"><s n="s1.1;p6.64">Although the authors hint at the fact that the discussed trends are international, and typical of the multinational or global companies of our times, </s></p><quote lang="English">In recent years, as journalists, we have had access to the leaders of the biggest companies in Australia and we have spent time talking to people at many levels of organisations across the globe, whose role is to build, manage and mould the workspace(Trinca and Fox, 2004, p. 11),</quote><p n="p7.64"><s n="s1.1;p7.64">focusing on a single country allows them to go more in depth in their investigation, and Australia is their area of expertise: so their sources and examples are always Australian. </s></p><quote lang="English">Professor Amanda Sinclair of the Melbourne Business School says that work may be the only thing that answers the question of why we are here(Trinca and Fox, 2004, p. 9).</quote><p n="p8.64"><s n="s1.1;p8.64">Beyond this understandable degree of self-reference, in my opinion, the authors have needlessly made the book hard to sell to foreign countries.Their subject matter could easily be interesting to readers in the Western countries who are going through similar workplace developments, but the continuous referrals to Australian cities and companies are distracting. </s></p><quote lang="English">We word in a swish high-rise building in central Sidney.It's a far cry from the grimy rabbit warrens of the news-paper offices of our past. Those offices - News Limited, on the edge of the CBD near Central railway station, and Fairfax, a little further along the ugly, frenetic stretch of Sydney that becomes Parramatta Road - were legendary for their lack of gloss and aesthetic appeal(Trinca and Fox, 2004, p. 14).</quote><p n="p9.64"><s n="s1.1;p9.64">It is obvious in certain passages how the authors have Australia, and Australia only, on their minds. </s></p><quote lang="English">As well, many Australians work outside our narrow workspace. [...] In Australia's factories, work is far more regimented, with employees held to strict break times and with little chance to leave work to pick up the dry cleaning or run to the ATM(Trinca and Fox, 2004, p. 16).</quote><p n="p10.64"><s n="s1.1;p10.64">It wouldn't be different in any other country's factories, but foreign readers would have to make that link on their own. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">2.2. Cultural gaps</head><p n="p11.64"><s n="s1.1;p11.64">There are instances in which "Better than Sex" mentions facts, people or companies which readers from many countries, including Italy, would not be familiar with. </s></p><quote lang="English">Take your pick - from the brown-beaten cynicism of <hi rend="italic">Dilbert</hi> to the boosterism of flash mags like <hi rend="italic">Fast Company</hi>, there are plenty of ways to talk about what work is like right now(Trinca and Fox, 2004, p. 3).</quote><p n="p12.64"><s n="s1.1;p12.64">However annoyingly, these instances could be easily explained in simple footnotes, and are not essential to the contents of the book.After all, American children have enjoyed reading "The Lion, the Witch and the Wardrobe" for decades without knowing exactly what Turkish delight is. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">2.3. Employment issues and attitude towards work</head><p n="p13.64"><s n="s1.1;p13.64">There is no doubt about the existence of a market segment in Italy, similar to that of Australian "Better than Sex" target readers, made up of 30-to-45-year-old professionals who are dedicated to their work and identify with their careers.They are the ones reading Capital (a monthly magazine about the lives and lifestyle of successful managers) and business management manuals, of which a new series, e.g., has been launched by the "La Repubblica" newspaper in the first quarter of 2006<ref target="BAWE_3045e-endnote.006"/>.In October 2004, the results of the 5th research on Italians' social capital (about the relationship between Italians and work) were published<ref target="BAWE_3045e-endnote.007"/>, revealing that: </s></p><note place="end" id="BAWE_3045e-endnote.006"><p n="pn1.2"><s n="s1.1;pn1.2">List of volume titles and information retrieved on April 25th from: </s></p><p n="pn2.2"><s n="s1.1;pn2.2"><seg type="URL" n="http://www.servizioclienti.repubblica.it/index.php?page=vpclist&amp;idopera=&amp;idcategoria=46&amp;idcollana=691"/> </s></p></note><note place="end" id="BAWE_3045e-endnote.007"><p n="pn1.2"><s n="s1.1;pn1.2">Diamanti, I., October 2004, "Un posto per sempre", Lapolis working paper, retrieved on April 19th 2006 from: </s></p><p n="pn2.2"><s n="s1.1;pn2.2"><seg type="URL" n="http://www.uniurb.it/lapolis/materiali/edocs/cap_soc_5_testo.pdf"/> </s></p></note><p rend="ordered" n="p14.64"><s n="s1.1;p14.64">- over half of Italians think the ideal job should be a source of self-expression and relations;- 54% would prefer working autonomously, for reasons of personal satisfaction and income;- since 2000 the social importance of work, and time dedicated to it, have increased. </s></p><p n="p15.64"><s n="s1.1;p15.64">Australia's unemployment rate is today only slightly lower than Italy's (5,2%, 2005 estimate, ranking 48th best in the world, against 7,9%, and 75th rank<ref target="BAWE_3045e-endnote.008"/>), and seems to have followed a similar pattern<ref target="BAWE_3045e-endnote.009"/>. </s></p><note place="end" id="BAWE_3045e-endnote.008"><p n="pn1.2"><s n="s1.1;pn1.2">Rank Order - Unemployment rate, table in the CIA World Factbook website, retrieved on May 7th 2006 from: </s></p><p n="pn2.2"><s n="s1.1;pn2.2"><seg type="URL" n="http://www.cia.gov/cia/publications/factbook/rankorder/2129rank.html"/> </s></p></note><note place="end" id="BAWE_3045e-endnote.009"><p n="pn1.5"><s n="s1.1;pn1.5">Dennis, R., July 2003, "The double dividend", retrieved on May 7th 2006 from: </s></p><p n="pn2.5"><s n="s1.1;pn2.5"><seg type="URL" n="http://www.tai.org.au/Publications_Files/Papers&amp;Sub_Files/Double%20Dividend.pdf"/>, p. 2 </s></p><p n="pn3.5"><s n="s1.1;pn3.5">and </s></p><p n="pn4.5"><s n="s1.1;pn4.5">Bertola, G. and Garibaldi, P., November 2002, "The Structure and History of Italian Unemployment", preliminary paper retrieved on May 7th from: </s></p><p n="pn5.5"><s n="s1.1;pn5.5"><seg type="URL" n="http://www.personalweb.unito.it/Giuseppe.Bertola/ItalUnemp.pdf"/>, p. 20 </s></p></note><p n="p16.64"><s n="s1.1;p16.64">However, Italy's situation remains worse and more stagnant than Australia's, and generally there might be a more negative attitude towards the work environment, including careerism. </s></p><p n="p17.64"><s n="s1.1;p17.64">Recently published titles about the employment situation include: </s></p><list type="ordered"><item>- "Cordiali saluti"<ref target="BAWE_3045e-endnote.010"/> ("Kind regards", by Einaudi), a tragicomical novel about a man whose job is to write lay-off letters</item><item>- "Risorsa umana sarà lei" (loosely translatable into "Who are you calling human resource?", by Sperling &amp; Kupfer), a graduate's quest to find her first job</item><item>- "(S)legati (d)al lavoro" ("(Un)tied from/by work"), on the role of work as a socially aggregating force for young adults in Italy.</item></list><note place="end" id="BAWE_3045e-endnote.010"><p n="pn1.2"><s n="s1.1;pn1.2">2005, "Andrea Bajani, Cordiali saluti", title description in Einaudi's website (the book's publisher), retrieved on May 1st 2006 from: </s></p><p n="pn2.2"><s n="s1.1;pn2.2"><seg type="URL" n="http://www.einaudi.it/einaudi/ita/catalogo/scheda.jsp?isbn=978880617297&amp;ed=87"/> </s></p></note></div2><div2><head rend="bold">2.4. Finding an appropriate Italian publisher</head><p n="p18.64"><s n="s1.2;p18.64">At Australia's stand at the London Book Fair in 2006, a diagram of participating exhibitors gave an overview of the genres within which each one works. </s><s n="s2.2;p18.64">Random House Australia was associated with "Biogs and autobiogs", "Adult fiction", "Children's books", "Mind, body and spirit" and "Sport, games and toys" - none of which are appropriate for "Better than Sex". </s></p><p n="p19.64"><s n="s1.1;p19.64">Determining to what genre a book belongs is an important issue when selling its rights, as prospective buyers seek titles which will fit with their current lists and image. </s></p><p n="p20.64"><s n="s1.1;p20.64">A mismatch between publisher and title can lead to confusing positioning not only in the retail market, but also in the rights market. </s></p><p n="p21.64"><s n="s1.1;p21.64">According to Tuvia Fogel of Il Caduceo, a foreign rights agency, there are many publishers in Italy who could take on "Better than Sex" "as long as it's written in a journalistic and fun style, and not as a sociological study. [...] The most famous brands for this genre are probably Sperling &amp; Kupfer, Sonzogno, Piemme and Ponte alle Grazie."<ref target="BAWE_3045e-endnote.011"/> </s></p><note place="end" id="BAWE_3045e-endnote.011"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">e-mail correspondence with Tuvia Fogel, of Il Caduceo foreign rights agency, March 24th 2006 (my own translation) </s></p></note><p n="p22.64"><s n="s1.1;p22.64">After examining these publishing houses' catalogues online, I believe Sperling &amp; Kupfer would be the most appropriate option. </s></p><p n="p23.64"><s n="s1.1;p23.64">In fact, there are two lists the title could fit into: </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p24.64"><s n="s1.1;p24.64">- Capire il presente (Understanding the present), including the new title "Risorsa umana sarà lei" (mentioned in the above paragraph); although not focused on business issues, this list has the right tone for "Better than Sex" </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p25.64"><s n="s1.1;p25.64">- Economia &amp; Management (Economy &amp; Management), spanning from business management manuals to lighter-tone books, such as "Come riconoscere il lupo cattivo e vivere felici (senza la nonna)" ("How to recognise the big bad wolf and live happily (without granny)"), in which classic children stories are re-told to teach women how to survive on the workplace. </s></p><p n="p26.64"><s n="s1.1;p26.64">Sperling &amp; Kupfer also is advantaged by belonging to a bigger publisher, Rizzoli, who has resources to invest in list-building. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">2.5. Type of book</head><p n="p27.64"><s n="s1.1;p27.64">Wondering whether "Better than Sex" had been outshined by the other non-fiction business book in the 2004 Catalogue, I found the rights for "Working with monsters" hadn't been sold either. </s></p><p n="p28.64"><s n="s1.1;p28.64">Do social analysis/business books about work and employment not travel well in general? </s></p><p n="p29.64"><s n="s1.1;p29.64">A few recent examples seem to state the opposite. </s></p><p n="p30.64"><s n="s1.1;p30.64">Recently the French "Bonjour paresse" has been translated successfully in Italy (in fact the Italian cover boasts translations in 20 languages)<ref target="BAWE_3045e-endnote.012"/>. </s></p><note place="end" id="BAWE_3045e-endnote.012"><p n="pn1.2"><s n="s1.1;pn1.2">Casagrande, G., "Buongiorno pigrizia", March 25th 2006, book review in Libri Alice's website, retrieved on May 8th 2006 from: </s></p><p n="pn2.2"><s n="s1.1;pn2.2"><seg type="URL" n="http://www.librialice.it/cafeletterario/367/8845233774.htm"/> </s></p></note><p n="p31.64"><s n="s1.1;p31.64">The book about so called "milleuristi", "Generazione mille euro"<ref target="BAWE_3045e-endnote.013"/>, is Italian, but was inspired by an article in El Pais<ref target="BAWE_3045e-endnote.014"/> regarding the phenomenon in Spain. </s></p><note place="end" id="BAWE_3045e-endnote.013"><p n="pn1.2"><s n="s1.1;pn1.2">Pilati, P., February 10th 2006, "Generazione mille euro", article in L'espresso, retrieved on April 28th 2006 from: </s></p><p n="pn2.2"><s n="s1.1;pn2.2"><seg type="URL" n="http://www.espressonline.it/eol/free/jsp/detail.jsp?m1s=null&amp;m2s=e&amp;idCategory=4799&amp;idContent=1291023"/> </s></p></note><note place="end" id="BAWE_3045e-endnote.014"><p n="pn1.2"><s n="s1.1;pn1.2">Barca, A. J., October 23rd 2005, "La generación de los mil euros", article in El Pais, retrieved on April 28th 2006 from: </s></p><p n="pn2.2"><s n="s1.1;pn2.2"><seg type="URL" n="http://www.elpais.es/articulo/elpdompor/20051023elpdmgpor_1/Tes"/> </s></p></note><p n="p32.64"><s n="s1.1;p32.64">The aforementioned "Risorsa umana sarà lei", is also originally a French book. </s></p><p n="p33.64"><s n="s1.1;p33.64">Permeability amongst Wester-European countries may be fostered by similarity in the attitude with which work-issues are approached (see 2.3.), or by Italy's exposure to publicity coming from closer markets (see 3.). </s></p><p n="p34.64"><s n="s1.2;p34.64">I also think that foreign books transfer more easily to different cultures when they can be clearly identified as foreign. </s><s n="s2.2;p34.64">To do so they must adhere to certain stereotypes, which will be added to their meaning in the new country: e.g., Italian publishing houses buy business manuals and books on macro-economic trends such as globalisation from the US, adding to the product the reference to the stereotypical successful American manager. </s></p><p n="p35.64"><s n="s1.1;p35.64">According to stereotypes Japanese books are short and alienating, Russian books are long and complicated, and Australian books are either about the wildlife or immigration and Maoris: placement in a certain genre is influenced by having the "right" publisher, as much as coming from the "right" country. </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">3. Original success</head><quote lang="English">"All translation is a compromise; there are inevitable losses"<ref target="BAWE_3045e-endnote.015"/>.</quote><note place="end" id="BAWE_3045e-endnote.015"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Steven, K., 2002, translators note to "The Half Brother" by Lars Saabye Christensen, Arcadia </s></p></note><p n="p36.64"><s n="s1.1;p36.64">However there seems to be one paramount factor driving rights sales, which compensates for any loss in cultural and literary value: success in the country of origin. </s></p><p n="p37.64"><s n="s1.1;p37.64">For any book, there's a level of success which creates a buzz so loud it can be heard internationally; this "pulls" demand invaluably, and at the same time can be used in marketing "push" strategies. </s></p><p n="p38.64"><s n="s1.1;p38.64">Once "Bonjour Paresse" sold 300.000 copies in France, even South Korea wanted its edition. </s></p><p n="p39.64"><s n="s1.1;p39.64">"The diary of Bridget Jones" was first a British, and American, and then worldwide hit, although much of the main character's charm lies in her untranslatable use of English and love for Milktray. </s></p><p n="p40.64"><s n="s1.4;p40.64">The Italian translator of "The Series of Unfortunate Events" confessed not realising until book "The 7th" how all evil characters' names where anagrams of Count Olaf, and had to add a footnote to explain that. </s><s n="s2.4;p40.64">The author's trademarks are such clues, play-on-words, building the plot around common expressions in English like "red herring", and exaggerating alliterations or other figures of speech. </s><s n="s3.4;p40.64">Some are lost, others substituted, and although the dark tone of the children's stories is not appreciated in Italy like it was in the US, rights for the entire series were sold to Salani since the launch of book "The 2nd"<ref target="BAWE_3045e-endnote.016"/>. </s><s n="s4.4;p40.64">Soon after, the homonymous film was released as well, adding to the buzz. </s></p><note place="end" id="BAWE_3045e-endnote.016"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">The Translator's Workshop: A Series of Unfortunate Events, meeting with Valentina Daniele at the Bologna Book Fair, March 28th 2006 </s></p></note><p n="p41.64"><s n="s1.2;p41.64">In this escalation of translations for the sake of international fame, I must end on "Eats, Shoots &amp; Leaves", which has been recently published by Piemme in Italian ("Virgole per caso. </s><s n="s2.2;p41.64">Tolleranza zero per gli errori di punteggiarura!") with extensive re-writing, well beyond translation, to fit Italian grammar rules. </s></p><p n="p42.64"><s n="s1.2;p42.64">Was it worth loosing the original text to import the successful "format" of a fun-to-read grammar book? </s><s n="s2.2;p42.64">Sales are nowhere near the UK figures, but the media build-up<ref target="BAWE_3045e-endnote.017"/> meant the book had to be made available to Italian readers. </s></p><note place="end" id="BAWE_3045e-endnote.017"><p n="pn1.2"><s n="s1.1;pn1.2">Franceschini, E., March 3rd 2004, "Perché la punteggiatura torna di moda" ("Why Punctuation is Back in Fashion"), article in Diario di Repubblica, retrieved on March 23rd 2006 from: </s></p><p n="pn2.2"><s n="s1.1;pn2.2"><seg type="URL" n="http://download.repubblica.it/pdf/diario/03032004.pdf"/> </s></p></note><p n="p43.64"><s n="s1.2;p43.64">"Eats, Shoots &amp; Leaves" was translated into German as well, but in its marketing footsteps another book, "Der Dativ ist dem Genitiv sein Tod" ("The Dative is the Death of the Genitive"), has sold over 800.000 copies<ref target="BAWE_3045e-endnote.018"/>. </s><s n="s2.2;p43.64">A case of how international buzz makes translation, transfer, and even cloning, possible. </s></p><note place="end" id="BAWE_3045e-endnote.018"><p n="pn1.2"><s n="s1.1;pn1.2">MacLeod, M., August 14th 2005, "Double-Deutsch has Germans tongue-tied", article on Scotsman website, retrieved on April 15th 2006 from: </s></p><p n="pn2.2"><s n="s1.1;pn2.2"><seg type="URL" n="http://news.scotsman.com/international.cfm?id=1777302005"/> </s></p></note></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">4. The translation itself</head><div2><head rend="bold">4.1. Words and language used</head><p n="p44.64"><s n="s1.2;p44.64">The vocabulary the authors use is simple to translate, with no use of either technical or slang/local terms.The main difficulty would be in the lack, in the Italian language, of different words for "job" and "work".While both can be translated into "lavoro", and "job" can be turned into "occupazione" for clarity's sake, either confusing repetitions or lengthier translations are bound to happen. </s><s n="s2.2;p44.64">The book is laden with expressions that require the use of the word "lavoro" in some form (going to work, work place, working hours, getting the job done, etc.), and Italian is a language in which repetition is minded more than in English. </s></p><quote lang="English">We were increasingly interested in work as a concept, something that was bigger than the job(Trinca and Fox, 2004, p. 5).</quote><quote lang="Italian" rend="italic">Ci interessavamo sempre di più al lavoro come concetto: qualcosa che va oltre la semplice occupazione. </quote><p n="p45.64"><s n="s1.1;p45.64">The few play on words are not essential in the text, while the title bears the fortunate possibility of adding a catchy one: "how a whole generation got hooked on work" can be translated into "come un'intera generazione è passata dal lavoro da dipendente alla dipendenza dal lavoro", playing on the double meaning of the Italian "dipendenza" as either "employment" or "addiction". </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">4.2. Tone</head><p n="p46.64"><s n="s1.3;p46.64">As the authors themselves say in the introduction to the book - in case the title wasn't an obvious clue - they felt "a certain brio" about this project. </s><s n="s2.3;p46.64">They didn't want to write a despairing critique about the oppressive role of work in today's professionals' lives, hence "Better than Sex" is an upbeat and readable book.The tone is informal though not colloquial, closer to that of self-help books than academic ones. </s><s n="s3.3;p46.64">It is in fact the same tone that journalists of AFR Boss magazine use for their articles. </s></p><quote lang="English">Perhaps the biggest paradox is the sense that many of us are on the job even when not physically present at the office. This is one of the big shifts in the way we see work. It's not accidental, of course. Imagine your job is to produce a batch of perfect T-shirts at a factory(Trinca and Fox, 2004, p. 17).</quote><p n="p47.64"><s n="s1.1;p47.64">While making the book enjoyable, this tone is also an important determinant in placing the book: "Better than Sex" is essentially a trade book, and should therefore be promoted to trade publishers. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">4.3. Research grants and funding</head><p n="p48.64"><s n="s1.1;p48.64">"Better than Sex" being neither an academic sociological work, nor a book of significant literary value, it is improbable that it would obtain funding from bodies such as the Australia Council, which promotes national culture in all of its expressions.As of May 2006, there were no grants open for application which would suit the proposed title: of the four available for literature, three relate to creative writing and one was open for publishers only until mid-March<ref target="BAWE_3045e-endnote.019"/>. </s></p><note place="end" id="BAWE_3045e-endnote.019"/></div2><div2><head rend="bold">4.4. Expertise of translator and translation costing</head><p n="p49.64"><s n="s1.2;p49.64">For the same reasons why "Better than Sex" is not eligible for funding, the cost of its translation should be contained.The book is in fact translatable by anyone who has a sound knowledge of the common English language, and doesn't require specific knowledge or skills; the Italian publisher therefore could pay a freelancer, perhaps one who is eager to gain some experience, and pay around € 7-8 per standard page (30 lines of 60 characters, excluding spaces, or 2000 characters including them). </s><s n="s2.2;p49.64">A professional translator would charge around €9.50-10, an established one €12-13.Rates for non-technical translation of English to Italian are particularly low, as the competition is very strong; for specialist topics, the rates are raised to about €10-15-20, depending on the expertise of the translator<ref target="BAWE_3045e-endnote.020"/>. </s></p><note place="end" id="BAWE_3045e-endnote.020"><p n="pn1.2"><s n="s1.1;pn1.2">figures based on those available on Simon Turner's "tariffometro", retrieved on April 28th 2006 from: </s></p><p n="pn2.2"><s n="s1.1;pn2.2"><seg type="URL" n="www.tariffometro.it"/> </s></p></note><table id="BAWE_3045e-tab.001"><row><cell/></row></table></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">5. Profit potential</head><div2><head rend="bold">5.1. Sales expectations and pricing in Italy</head><p n="p50.64"><s n="s1.1;p50.64">The sales potential of a book in a foreign market is something important for both the buyer, who wants to acquire a profitable title, and the seller, who will put the most effort in promoting the title to publishers who can afford to pay more for the translation rights. </s></p><p n="p51.64"><s n="s1.1;p51.64">I suspect that the Italian market is not appealing enough for most books, and that many foreign titles are not translated because the small size of the market makes the venture too risky. </s></p><p n="p52.64"><s n="s1.1;p52.64">Working out the figures for "Better than Sex", it becomes obvious why the book wasn't translated. </s></p><p n="p53.64"><s n="s1.1;p53.64">I'll assume a realistic price would be €12, as similar titles are selling as follows: </s></p><table id="BAWE_3045e-tab.002"><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p54.64"><s n="s1.1;p54.64">I'll suppose the publisher could expect making a 10% profit, and sell as many copies as in the original market (Italy's population is three times that of Australia, but marketing would lack the benefit of Helen Trinca's media-worthiness and the book, as I've discussed in 2.1. and 2.2., is rooted in Australia to some degree). </s></p><p n="p55.64"><s n="s1.1;p55.64">In this optimistic scenario, profit would sum up to about €2.200. </s></p><p n="p56.64"><s n="s1.1;p56.64">More realistic assumptions are quick to bring that figure further down to €840 (7% profit and 1.000 copies sold). </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">5.2. Aggressive marketing because of timing</head><p n="p57.64"><s n="s1.4;p57.64">Marketing would have to compensate for the lack of "international buzz" (see 3. </s><s n="s2.4;p57.64">Original success), and also push sales as fast as possible to beat the product's natural decline (see 6. </s><s n="s3.4;p57.64">Timing). </s><s n="s4.4;p57.64">"Pushing" a book is one of the most expensive sales strategies, and would probably erode profit rates turning them into a loss. </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">6. Timing</head><div2><head rend="bold">6.1. Product life-cycle</head><p n="p58.64"><s n="s1.1;p58.64">Books regarding current affairs topics are intrinsically destined to early aging, meaning sales volumes decline quickly and subsidiary rights become impossible to sell once the title slips into the backlist. </s></p><p n="p59.64"><s n="s1.1;p59.64">In Australia, sales of "Better than Sex" have followed a pronounced "long-tail" pattern. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_3045e-fig.001"><head><hi rend="italic">Week by week sales volumes of "Better than Sex" since publication in June 2004</hi><ref target="BAWE_3045e-endnote.021"/>. <note place="end" id="BAWE_3045e-endnote.021"><p n="pn1.1"> graph based on data from the Nielsen BookScan database</p></note></head></figure><p n="p60.64"><s n="s1.1;p60.64">"Better than Sex", unlike an "instant book" related to a single fact, regards a phenomenon which has evolved through all of the '90s, and is starting to influence the attitudes towards work of a second, younger, generation ("Generation Next"<ref target="BAWE_3045e-endnote.022"/>). </s></p><note place="end" id="BAWE_3045e-endnote.022"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Trinca, H. and Fox, C., 2004, "Better than Sex", Random House Australia, p. 128 </s></p></note><p n="p61.64"><s n="s1.1;p61.64">The topic itself is perhaps more interesting today than it was on publication, but the journalistic style of presentation makes the book feel dated. </s></p><quote lang="English">It's a reality check on what work means now and a glimpse at where it's going (Trinca and Fox, 2004, p. 10).</quote></div2><div2><head rend="bold">6.2. Time to translate</head><p n="p62.64"><s n="s1.5;p62.64">For this type of book, a translator would be able to work through 5 to 10 (standard) pages a day, depending on stamina more than on the terms of the contract. </s><s n="s2.5;p62.64">Including an extra week to read the Italian translation and make sure it flows correctly, "Better than Sex" could be translated in about 40 working days. </s><s n="s3.5;p62.64">That would probably sum up to a couple of months, considering week-ends, holidays, and any delays (bearing in mind the translator is not a professional). </s><s n="s4.5;p62.64">When "Better than Sex" was promoted at the Frankfurt Book Fair (October), it was over 4 months old; rushing rights negotiation, translation, editing, layout, production, promotion and distribution, the Italian edition could probably have been in bookstores by March 2005. </s><s n="s5.5;p62.64">Come June and summer holidays, sales would have died out because of the seasonality of business books: their sales peak in autumn, slumping in the spring and summer (the title was in fact launched in June originally, which in Australia is the beginning month of winter). </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">7. Conclusions</head><p n="p63.64"><s n="s1.1;p63.64">The content of the book could have been translated and transferred into the Italian market with some effort, but the investment would have had to be justified and supported either by a wider success in the original market, or in a closer European country, or by the prospect of a longer life-cycle for the book.I suspect that the light tone and positive attitude towards work were the worst enemies of "Better than Sex": the Italian market is quite interested in the issue, but seems to prefer scandals and protests about the labour conditions to careerism. </s></p><p n="p64.64"><s n="s1.3;p64.64">The economics of the book don't work. </s><s n="s2.3;p64.64">The cost of the translation is not excessive, but the window of opportunity for sales, given the current-journalistic style and the seasonality in sales of business books, is extremely small. </s><s n="s3.3;p64.64">To reach break-even on a print-run that would make production costs low enough to keep the price down, given the light non-academic tone, a disproportionate investment in marketing would have been necessary, throwing the figures off balance. </s></p></div1></body><back><div1 type="bibliography"><head rend="bold">Title analysed for this essay</head><p>Trinca, H. and Fox, C., 2004, "Better than Sex", Random House Australia</p></div1><div1 type="bibliography"><head rend="bold">References</head><p><hi rend="bold">1.</hi> "Is Work Better Than Sex?", June 2nd 2004, radio interview with presenter Richard Glover on 702 ABC Sidney, retrieved on April 29th 2006 from:</p><p> <seg type="URL" n="http://www.abc.net.au/sydney/stories/s1124031.htm"/></p><p><hi rend="bold">2.</hi> "Fair go or anything goes", Sidney, July 13th 2005, conference on the industrial relations reform, transcript of Helen Trinca's speech retrieved on April 29th 2006 from:</p><p><seg type="URL" n="http://www.iceaustralia.com/ir/pdf/Session%203%20-%20Impact%20on%20the%20Individual.pdf"/></p><p>and</p><p> "Executive Women and Leadership Congress", Sidney, November 30th to December 2nd 2005, seminar programme and registration form retrieved on April 29th 2006 from:</p><p><seg type="URL" n="http://www.iir.com.au/user_pages/conf/pdf/L1229.pdf"/></p><p><hi rend="bold">3.</hi> Franzway, S., April 4th 2005, "Work and family life: what we've forgotten", review in Australian Review of Public Affairs, retrieved on May 1st 2006 from:</p><p><seg type="URL" n="http://www.australianreview.net/digest/2005/04/franzway.html"/></p><p><hi rend="bold">4.</hi> data from the Nielsen BookScan database, provided by Richard Knight</p><p><hi rend="bold">5.</hi> Random House Australia Rights Catalogue for the Frankfurt Book Fair, 2004, retrieved on March 23rd 2006 from:</p><p><seg type="URL" n="http://www.randomhouse.com.au/Rights/Random%20House%20Australia%20Rights%20Guide.pdf"/></p><p><hi rend="bold">6.</hi> List of volume titles and information retrieved on April 25th from:</p><p><seg type="URL" n="http://www.servizioclienti.repubblica.it/index.php?page=vpclist&amp;idopera=&amp;idcategoria=46&amp;idcollana=691"/></p><p><hi rend="bold">7.</hi> Diamanti, I., October 2004, "Un posto per sempre", Lapolis working paper, retrieved on April 19th 2006 from:</p><p><seg type="URL" n="http://www.uniurb.it/lapolis/materiali/edocs/cap_soc_5_testo.pdf"/></p><p><hi rend="bold">8.</hi> Rank Order - Unemployment rate, table in the CIA World Factbook website, retrieved on May 7th 2006 from:</p><p><seg type="URL" n="http://www.cia.gov/cia/publications/factbook/rankorder/2129rank.html"/></p><p><hi rend="bold">9.</hi> Dennis, R., July 2003, "The double dividend", retrieved on May 7th 2006 from:</p><p><seg type="URL" n="http://www.tai.org.au/Publications_Files/Papers&amp;Sub_Files/Double%20Dividend.pdf"/>, p. 2</p><p>and</p><p> Bertola, G. and Garibaldi, P., November 2002, "The Structure and History of Italian Unemployment", preliminary paper retrieved on May 7th from:</p><p><seg type="URL" n="http://www.personalweb.unito.it/Giuseppe.Bertola/ItalUnemp.pdf"/>, p. 20</p><p><hi rend="bold">10.</hi> 2005, "Andrea Bajani, Cordiali saluti", title description in Einaudi's website (the book's publisher), retrieved on May 1st 2006 from:</p><p><seg type="URL" n="http://www.einaudi.it/einaudi/ita/catalogo/scheda.jsp?isbn=978880617297&amp;ed=87"/></p><p><hi rend="bold">11.</hi> e-mail correspondence with Tuvia Fogel, of Il Caduceo foreign rights agency, March 24th 2006 (my own translation)</p><p><hi rend="bold">12.</hi> Casagrande, G., "Buongiorno pigrizia", March 25th 2006, book review in Libri Alice's website, retrieved on May 8th 2006 from:</p><p><seg type="URL" n="http://www.librialice.it/cafeletterario/367/8845233774.htm"/></p><p><hi rend="bold">13.</hi> Pilati, P., February 10th 2006, "Generazione mille euro", article in L'espresso, retrieved on April 28th 2006 from:</p><p><seg type="URL" n="http://www.espressonline.it/eol/free/jsp/detail.jsp?m1s=null&amp;m2s=e&amp;idCategory=4799&amp;idContent=1291023"/></p><p><hi rend="bold">14.</hi> Barca, A. J., October 23rd 2005, "La generación de los mil euros", article in El Pais, retrieved on April 28th 2006 from:</p><p><seg type="URL" n="http://www.elpais.es/articulo/elpdompor/20051023elpdmgpor_1/Tes"/></p><p><hi rend="bold">15.</hi> Steven, K., 2002, translators note to "The Half Brother" by Lars Saabye Christensen, Arcadia</p><p><hi rend="bold">16.</hi> The Translator's Workshop: A Series of Unfortunate Events, meeting with Valentina Daniele at the Bologna Book Fair, March 28th 2006</p><p><hi rend="bold">17.</hi> Franceschini, E., March 3rd 2004, "Perché la punteggiatura torna di moda" ("Why Punctuation is Back in Fashion"), article in Diario di Repubblica, retrieved on March 23rd 2006 from:</p><p><seg type="URL" n="http://download.repubblica.it/pdf/diario/03032004.pdf"/></p><p><hi rend="bold">18.</hi> MacLeod, M., August 14th 2005, "Double-Deutsch has Germans tongue-tied", article on Scotsman website, retrieved on April 15th 2006 from:</p><p><seg type="URL" n="http://news.scotsman.com/international.cfm?id=1777302005"/></p><p><hi rend="bold">19.</hi> information taken from the Australia Council website, through the "grand finder" tool, retrieved on April 15th 2006 from:</p><p><seg type="URL" n="http://www.ozco.gov.au/grantFinder.aspx"/></p><p><hi rend="bold">20.</hi> figures based on those available on Simon Turner's "tariffometro", retrieved on April 28th 2006 from:</p><p><seg type="URL" n="www.tariffometro.it"/></p><p><hi rend="bold">21.</hi> graph based on data from the Nielsen BookScan database</p><p><hi rend="bold">22.</hi> Trinca, H. and Fox, C., 2004, "Better than Sex", Random House Australia, p. 128</p></div1><div1 type="bibliography"><head rend="bold">Websites</head><p>Books online: <seg type="URL" n="www.bol.it"/></p><p>Internet Bookshop: <seg type="URL" n="www.internetbookshop.it"/></p><p>Amazon: <seg type="URL" n="www.amazon.com"/></p><p>Amazon (UK): <seg type="URL" n="www.amazon.co.uk"/></p><p>Nielsen BookScan: <seg type="URL" n="www.nielsenbookscan.net"/></p><p>Random House Australia: <seg type="URL" n="www.randomhouse.com.au"/></p><p>Random House: <seg type="URL" n="www.randomhouse.com"/></p><p>UNESCO Translationum: <seg type="URL" n="http://databases.unesco.org/xtrans/xtra-form.html"/></p><p>Generazione mille euro: <seg type="URL" n="www.generazione1000euro.com"/></p></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
