<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_3045b" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Marketing Plan</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">Language used in quote: <foreign id="English">English</foreign></note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">Evaluated as candidate compound assignment. Assigned to S1b: collection of reports: compound.</note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">deleted: header: student name and number, date, course, module and assignment titles; footer: page numbers</note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">deleted: Word count: 1.000</note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">deleted: Word count: 994</note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">Running text contains reference to external or missing appendix.
</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">4</p><p n="date">2005-12</p><p n="module title">Marketing Management for Publishing</p><p n="module code">P65023</p><p n="genre family">Proposal</p><p n="discipline">Publishing</p><p n="disciplinary group">SS</p><p n="grade">D</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">2398</p><p n="number of s-units">70</p><p n="number of p">65</p><p n="number of tables">1</p><p n="number of figures">0</p><p n="number of block quotes">1</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">16</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">3</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">34.3</p><p n="average s-units per p">1.1</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">compound assignment consisting of 0 parts (see notesStmt for details)</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">f</p><p n="year of birth">1979</p><p n="first language">Italian</p><p n="education">OSa</p><p n="course">MA Publishing</p><p n="student ID">3045</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front/><body><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">1. Market conditions</head><p n="p1.65"><s n="s1.1;p1.65">In spite of stringent market conditions, Routledge is expanding its Humanities and Social Science catalogue, having added 5 Media and Communication titles in 2005, and launching <hi rend="bold">Journal of European Media and Communications Studies (EMCS)</hi> and Journal of Intercultural Communication Research in 2006. </s></p><quote lang="English">"A fair few new Media and Communication Studies journals have been launched in the last decade or so, but this is a consequence of an expanding market, not the RAE [Research Assessment Exercise]. Compared to other disciplines, the field is a young and dynamic one. As new sub-fields have emerged over the years - new media, journalism and visual culture - the space has been created for new forums for debate to emerge."<ref target="BAWE_3045b-ftnote.001"/></quote><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3045b-ftnote.001"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Julia Hall (Editor for Media and Communications, SAGE Ltd.), interviewed in MeCCSA's newsletter Three-D, September 2005 </s></p></note></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">2. Marketing objectives</head><p n="p2.65"><s n="s1.1;p2.65">We aim at building market share for EMCS, allowing Routledge to: </s></p><list type="bulleted"><item>Hold its position in the growing field of journal publishing</item><item>Take advantage of the developments in Media and Communication research in Europe.</item></list><p n="p3.65"><s n="s1.1;p3.65">The marketing campaign also supports the advantageous shift towards e-journals, as the adoption of purely electronic publications yields "savings of up to 20% [...] by the elimination of printing."<ref target="BAWE_3045b-ftnote.002"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3045b-ftnote.002"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Learned Journal Publishing in the UK, 2002, <seg type="URL" n="www.alpsp.org"/> </s></p></note><p n="p4.65"><s n="s1.2;p4.65">"[E]lectronic delivery has revolutionized journal publishing. </s><s n="s2.2;p4.65">The emphasis now is on usage, rather than on the absolute number of subscribers." <ref target="BAWE_3045b-ftnote.003"/> </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3045b-ftnote.003"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Julia Hall (Editor for Media and Communications, SAGE Ltd.), interviewed in MeCCSA's newsletter Three-D, September 2005 </s></p></note><p n="p5.65"><s n="s1.1;p5.65">Goals are therefore set at: </s></p><list type="bulleted"><item>Gaining 500 print subscriptions in the first two years after launch</item><item>400 institutional and 100 individual</item><item>Developing "regular online usage", defined as follows:</item><item>50% of subscribers visit the website at least once a month</item><item>70% of subscribers view online at least one article from each issue</item><item>Following-up profitable special sales (single issues, single articles) with promotional packs for subscriptions.</item></list></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">3. Target market</head><p n="p6.65"><s n="s1.1;p6.65">Target readers are academics and researchers, based in the UK and Europe, interested in the development of new means and models of communication in the context of a new European identity overlapping with the national ones. </s></p><div2><head rend="bold">3.1. Academics and researchers in university departments</head><list type="bulleted"><item>Professors in the relevant departments, working in the 20 British universities ranking highest for Communication and Media Studies (see appendix C)</item><item>Participants in the 2000-2004 European Science Foundation initiative "Changing Media-Changing Europe" (EMCS editor Prof. Schrøder was one)</item><item>Contacts from all members of the editorial board (see appendix G).</item></list><p n="p7.65"/></div2><div2><head rend="bold">3.2. Libraries</head><list type="bulleted"><item>UK Library consortia (see appendix D)</item><item>Subject librarians for Media and Communication, contacted personally, starting from the 20 universities in appendix C</item><item>A list of journal and/or subject librarians working in European, American and Asian universities with Media and Communication courses will be built with help from local sales representatives, or bought inexpensively, if the one available in-house is outdated.</item></list><p n="p8.65"/></div2><div2><head rend="bold">3.3. Associations</head><p n="p9.65"><s n="s1.1;p9.65">EMCS is the official title for the <hi rend="bold">European Communication Research and Education Association (ECREA)</hi>, the November 2005 merger of ECA (European Communication Association) and ECCR (European Consortium for Communications Research), now counting over 500 members. </s></p><p n="p10.65"><s n="s1.1;p10.65">Other key associations (all put their members' contact lists online), are: </s></p><list type="bulleted"><item>European Science Foundation (<seg type="URL" n="www.esf.org"/>), Social Sciences section</item><item>International Association for Media and Communications Research (<seg type="URL" n="www.iamcr.net"/>)</item><item>European Institute for Communication and Culture (<seg type="URL" n="www.euricom.si"/>)</item><item>Media, Communication and Cultural Studies Association (<seg type="URL" n="www.meccsa.org.uk"/>).</item></list></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">4. Positioning</head><p n="p11.65"><s n="s1.1;p11.65">Routledge has strong presence, with "Media Student's Handbook" being considered indispensable, in the field of Media and Communication, and is renown for high-quality peer-reviewed journals. </s></p><p n="p12.65"><s n="s1.2;p12.65">EMCS is the official title for ECREA, and is dedicated to the publication of original scholarly articles advancing understanding of human communication in the context of changing national identities. </s><s n="s2.2;p12.65">It provides an academic forum for interpretive approaches to mass-communication theory and research in Europe. </s></p><p n="p13.65"><s n="s1.1;p13.65">Several specialized journals represent particular national traditions, but EMCS enriches the broad debate among them and shapes the parameters of this genre. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">5. Marketing communications mix</head><p n="p14.65"><s n="s1.2;p14.65">EMCS reflects the need of a new European community to develop its cross-national means of communication. </s><s n="s2.2;p14.65">This campaign puts that idea into practice, encouraging and exploiting networks amongst academics and researchers in different countries (presence at international conferences, peer-recommendations). </s></p><p n="p15.65"><s n="s1.1;p15.65">To stand out against competition and make a lasting impression, we prompt involvement: giving feedback, recommending EMCS, visiting the website and subject arenas. </s></p><p n="p16.65"><s n="s1.2;p16.65">Printed material is graphically consistent, establishing a recognisable look. </s><s n="s2.2;p16.65">Messages aren't tailored to national characteristics, as EMCS's target is interested in the common means of communication emerging in the continent as a whole. </s></p><p n="p17.65"><s n="s1.2;p17.65">Subscribing is conveniently made possible through different channels. </s><s n="s2.2;p17.65">Renewing is possible over the phone as well. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">6. Sales channels</head><div2><head rend="bold">6.1. Sales representatives</head><p n="p18.65"><s n="s1.1;p18.65">Market- and product-focused representatives will be briefed at the twice-yearly general meeting in Oxford, in March 2006; they will receive material according to schedule. </s></p><p n="p19.65"><s n="s1.1;p19.65">One person in the central Marketing Department will be identified as main contact for the encouraged feedback and inquiries. </s></p><p n="p20.65"><s n="s1.1;p20.65">For Europe, aiming for a stronger impact, 8 key representatives (see appendix E) will be proactively involved in the marketing campaign; they will participate in bi-monthly conference calls with the main contact in the Marketing Department, from January 2006 to July 2007. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">6.2. Subscription agents</head><p n="p21.65"><s n="s1.1;p21.65">Services offered by international subscription agencies are very similar, but the consolidated partnership with Swets has proved effective in the past for similar titles. </s></p><p n="p22.65"><s n="s1.2;p22.65">On average, about 70% of library subscriptions go through agents. </s><s n="s2.2;p22.65">According to our objectives, this means that about 250 institutional subscriptions will rely on Swets as an intermediary. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">6.3. Online sales</head><p n="p23.65"><s n="s1.1;p23.65">The journal's webpage allows institutions and individuals to subscribe online, paying with credit or debit card, and also links to the library order form (see appendix B). </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">6.4. Subscription forms</head><p n="p24.65"><s n="s1.1;p24.65">Subscription forms, inserted or attached with all marketing material, can be sent directly to the Subscriptions Office. </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">7. Promotional material</head><div2><head rend="bold">7.1. New Titles Catalogue</head><p n="p25.65"><s n="s1.1;p25.65">EMCS will appear in the May-August and September-December 2006 issues of the New Titles Catalogue for Humanities and Social Science. </s></p><p n="p26.65"><s n="s1.1;p26.65">Unless a centralised decision is made to change the current format (all journals blandly described at the end), we suggest at least to add a reference from the "Media and Cultural Studies" section (ideally after books focused on Europe) to the page where EMCS's brief presentation can be found. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">7.2. Blads</head><p n="p27.65"><s n="s1.1;p27.65">Printed on A4 good quality, non glossy paper, in four colours. </s></p><list type="bulleted"><item>Blad #1: before the first issue is ready, presents the journal emphasising the call for papers</item><item>Blad #2 (see appendix F): replicates the cover of the first issue (which has the content list on it), presents the journal, and gives technical information about subscriptions (on last page is, which is a subscription form)</item><item>Blad #3: after one year, content is revised to include information about the publication's success and first page represents the latest issue.</item></list></div2><div2><head rend="bold">7.3. Newsletter</head><p n="p28.65"><s n="s1.1;p28.65">A brief description of the journal, and its webpage's URL, will be included in the "Journal Update" box of the company's June and September newsletters, sent to libraries and associations. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">7.4. Free sample copies</head><p n="p29.65"><s n="s1.2;p29.65">Sample copies of the latest issue will be distributed throughout the two-year plan, always in a promotional pack. </s><s n="s2.2;p29.65">See assumptions in appendix H for quantities. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">7.5. Gadgets</head><list type="bulleted"><item>Pen, branded with Routledge website URL, and journal's title</item><item>Bookmark (7 x 10 cm, maintaining A4 proportions) portraying latest cover (and contents)</item><item>Series of 4 classical music CDs (European composers: Mozart, Beethoven, Tchaikovsky and Vivaldi), in branded case.</item></list><p n="p30.65"/></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">8. Direct marketing</head><div2><head rend="bold">8.1. Librarians</head><p n="p31.65"><s n="s1.1;p31.65">Promotional pack for librarians comes in two versions: </s></p><list type="bulleted"><item rend="bold">Basic</item><item>Sample copy request form</item><item>Subscription form</item><item>Circulation form</item><item>Blad #2 (or 3)</item><item>Routledge newsletter</item><item><hi rend="bold">Extra</hi> (to subject librarians in the 20 universities in appendix C, plus other 30): add</item><item>1 CD</item><item>Feedback form, which must be returned to have the next Extra pack sent after six months (or will receive Basic).</item></list><p n="p32.65"><s n="s1.1;p32.65">For launch, packs include also: </s></p><list type="bulleted"><item>September-December 2006 New Titles Catalogue</item><item>Sample copy (instead of request form) in 100 Basics and all Extras.</item></list></div2><div2><head rend="bold">8.2. Individuals</head><list type="bulleted"><item><hi rend="bold">Basic</hi> (sent to academics on list, and single issue/single article buyers)</item><item>Sample copy request form</item><item>Direct link to an online version of the first issue*</item><item>Library recommendation form</item><item>Subscription form</item><item>Blad #2 (or 3)</item><item>Call for papers and author instructions</item><item>* Explains what the e-journal is like; can't be downloaded, but can be forwarded once with a "Let me draw your attention to..." message; has links to webpage, arenas, online forms.</item><item><hi rend="bold">Extra</hi> (100 sent on launch, to ECREA board members and participants in "Changing Media-Changing Europe"; then sent in reply to sample copy requests): add</item><item>Sample copy (instead of a request form)</item><item>Sample-copy-for-a-peer request form, with space to write a message under the heading "Let me draw your attention to...", allowing us to collect both contacts and feedback.</item></list><p n="p33.65"/></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">9. Publicity</head><div2><head rend="bold">9.1. Conferences</head><list type="bulleted"><item>January 13 <hi rend="sup">th</hi>-15 <hi rend="sup">th</hi> 2006 (Leeds Metropolitan University) Second Joint Annual Conference of MeCCSA and AMPE</item><item>350 blads #1 sent in, and included in the conference's welcome pack</item><item>July 23 <hi rend="sup">rd</hi>-24 <hi rend="sup">th</hi> 2006 (University of Amsterdam) European Science Foundation Conference</item><item>Promotional material distributed from clearly branded tables (e.g., Routledge logo on blue tablecloths): pens, blad #2, call for papers and author instructions, library recommendation form, sample copy request form, June newsletter</item><item>November 2 <hi rend="sup">nd</hi> 2006 (Brussels headquarters) First Annual ECREA Conference</item><item>Official presentation to members, speeches by the President and a Routledge representative</item><item>Clearly branded tables display the first issue and offer refreshments</item><item>Conference pack distributed to all participants (costs split with ECREA): sample copy, blad #2, call for papers and authors instructions, library recommendation form, subscription form.</item></list><p n="p34.65"/></div2><div2><head rend="bold">9.2. Referencing</head><p n="p35.65"><s n="s1.2;p35.65">EMCS will be listed under the ISI subject category "Communication", and aims at increasing its Impact Factor quickly. </s><s n="s2.2;p35.65">Routledge's membership of Cross-ref will help. </s></p><p n="p36.65"><s n="s1.1;p36.65">Being a new journal we don't expected it to gain influence comparable to that of established titles, but marketing material will mention promising improvement. </s></p><p n="p37.65"><s n="s1.1;p37.65">EMCS will be indexed with as many abstracting agencies as possible. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">9.3. Webpage and arenas</head><p n="p38.65"><s n="s1.1;p38.65">Like all Routledge journals, EMCS will have a dedicated webpage (see appendix B), linking to </s></p><list type="bulleted"><item>Online sample issue</item><item>SARA registration</item><item>Call for papers and online submission</item><item>Library recommendation and order forms</item><item>Online subscription</item><item>Subject arenas (Communication, and Media and Cultural Studies, provide an additional forum for EMCS's target readership).</item></list></div2><div2><head rend="bold">9.4. Advertisements</head><p n="p39.65"><s n="s1.1;p39.65">Routledge publishes many journals sold to readers belonging to EMCS's target readership, on which advertising will be both effective and inexpensive (offering similar advertising space should suffice). </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">9.5. Press office</head><p n="p40.65"><s n="s1.1;p40.65">The journal's launch will receive the usual (minimal) coverage; we suggest stressing the connection with ECREA, the association in itself reflecting developments in the journal's field. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">9.6. E-mails</head><p n="p41.65"><s n="s1.1;p41.65">E-mails will be avoided as they are impersonal, overlooked if simple, and problematic to download if elaborate. </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">10. Price promotions</head><p n="p42.65"><s n="s1.1;p42.65">Rates are structured as follows: </s></p><table id="BAWE_3045b-tab.001"><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p43.65"><s n="s1.1;p43.65">Routledge uses a simple rough currency conversion, so rates can be shown freely to all prospective subscribers. </s></p><p n="p44.65"><s n="s1.1;p44.65">Discounts aren't necessary to promote sales in countries which are part of the geographical scope of the journal (unlike, e.g., Asian Journal of Communication): Routledge's presence is already affirmed in Europe (26% of revenue comes from continental Europe and 18% from the UK). </s></p><p n="p45.65"><s n="s1.2;p45.65">Subscriptions include both the print and the digital versions, because, although we aim at increasing online usage, a new journal benefits from the lasting impression of "physical appearance". </s><s n="s2.2;p45.65">Also, print journals are still what readers are used to, and ask for. </s></p><p n="p46.65"><s n="s1.1;p46.65">An online-only rate will be available from the third year. </s></p><p n="p47.65"><s n="s1.1;p47.65">Promotions planned since launch are: </s></p><list type="bulleted"><item>"Big Deal" with library consortia</item><item>5% discount on 2-year subscription (institutional: $399/£247, individual: $114/£70).</item></list><p n="p48.65"><s n="s1.1;p48.65">Should subscriptions lag, special rates will be offered through the subject arenas. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">11. Schedule</head><p n="p49.65"><s n="s1.1;p49.65">Library consortia are contacted in advance to allow for longer bureaucracy. </s></p><p n="p50.65"><s n="s1.2;p50.65">Promotional packs with sample copy request forms are sent out a month before an issue is due for publication, while those including a specimen are sent as soon as the issue is ready. </s><s n="s2.2;p50.65">This means that some librarians will receive packs only in October 2006: back issues are available if they don't order immediately. </s></p><p n="p51.65"><s n="s1.1;p51.65">Basic individual packs can be sent only after the special online version of the first issue is ready to be viewed. </s></p><p n="p52.65"><s n="s1.1;p52.65">See appendix A for whole schedule. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">12. Budget</head><p n="p53.65"><s n="s1.1;p53.65">We aim at reaching objectives quickly, to secure: </s></p><list type="bulleted"><item>Regular cash flow, avoiding loss in the short-term</item><item>Readership necessary to boost relevance in the academic world, key to long-term success and profitability.</item></list><p n="p54.65"><s n="s1.1;p54.65">Therefore, the allocated budget corresponds to 85% of the expected margin after covering production costs. </s></p><p n="p55.65"><s n="s1.1;p55.65">The remaining 15% is a buffer, not a profit objective: in the first two years of publication, investment for long-term success is paramount. </s></p><p n="p56.65"><s n="s1.1;p56.65">Cash flow will be balanced by pooling EMCS with other Routledge projects. </s></p><p n="p57.65"><s n="s1.1;p57.65">See appendix H for assumptions, title and marketing budgets, and cash flow. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">13. Monitoring results</head><p n="p58.65"><s n="s1.1;p58.65">For the first two years, progression towards the campaign's objectives will be measured monthly, and evaluated quarterly after one month from the publication of each issue (possibly identifying articles which boosted sales): </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p59.65"><s n="s1.1;p59.65">Number of subscriptions is checked with reports from the Subscriptions Office (broken down by country and geographical area, and institutional/individual) </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p60.65"><s n="s1.1;p60.65">Online usage is monitored through login (identifying the subscriber) and variables built into PHP webpages (collecting data about navigation sessions, then deposited in a server database and aggregated into statistics) </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p61.65"><s n="s1.1;p61.65">The Sales Department will provide single article and single sales reports, pointing out peaks. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">14. Feedback</head><p n="p62.65"><s n="s1.1;p62.65">Feedback is encouraged with an array of initiatives: </s></p><list type="bulleted"><item>Authors' publicity form</item><item>Feedback form in Extra librarian pack (see par. 8.1)</item><item>Sample-copy-for-a-peer requests (see par. 8.2)</item><item>Follow-up phone calls (see par. 15).</item></list></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">15. Follow-up</head><p n="p63.65"><s n="s1.1;p63.65">The Subscriptions Office will keep track of expiring subscriptions, and a monthly report will break-up numbers by country and type (institutional/individual), to reveal any relevant target for specific marketing actions (special offers, extra communication). </s></p><p n="p64.65"><s n="s1.1;p64.65">Avoid confusing overlap, or annoying repetition, bearing in mind that libraries ordering through subscription agents will be reminded with renewal instructions by the Swets Information Services. </s></p><p n="p65.65"><s n="s1.1;p65.65">Individuals will be prompted to renew with: </s></p><list type="bulleted"><item>2-page A5 card (see appendix I) inserted in second-last issue, reporting the current status of all their Routledge subscriptions - the expiring one highlighted - and suggesting other journals (according to subscription history, and interests registered with SARA)</item><item>Call after one month, under the pretext of a special deal, offering to renew immediately over the phone (tone is professional, briefly describing advantages and asking for feedback about the publication; objective is to remind, and to make it as convenient as possible, to renew)</item><item>2-page A5 card (brighter colours, more pressing copy), inserted in last issue</item><item>Follow-up pack (pen, bookmark, and subscription form), after three months from expiration (new issue appears on bookmark).</item></list></div1></body><back><div1 type="appendix"><head rend="bold">Index of appendixes</head><p/></div1><div1 type="missing or external appendix"><p/></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
