<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_3047b" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title></title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note/></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">1</p><p n="date">2004-04</p><p n="module title">Tourism Concepts</p><p n="module code">M07205</p><p n="genre family">Case study</p><p n="discipline">Hospitality, Leisure &amp; Tourism Management</p><p n="disciplinary group">SS</p><p n="grade">M</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">3189</p><p n="number of s-units">134</p><p n="number of p">40</p><p n="number of tables">2</p><p n="number of figures">13</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">0</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">0</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">23.8</p><p n="average s-units per p">3.4</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">f</p><p n="year of birth">1984</p><p n="first language">Chinese unspecified</p><p n="education">UK8</p><p n="course">MSc International Travel and Tourism Management</p><p n="student ID">3047</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><div1 type="toc" n="2"><head rend="underlined bold">Contents</head><p/></div1></front><body><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">1.0 Introduction</head><p n="p1.40"><s n="s1.4;p1.40">Oxford and Bath are both international tourist destinations in Britain and have the same tourism concepts. </s><s n="s2.4;p1.40">Oxford and Bath are the historical cities with heritages and Georgian architectures. </s><s n="s3.4;p1.40">Oxford has hundreds years university history, which is the main attraction to the tourists. </s><s n="s4.4;p1.40">Similarly, Bath has hundreds years Roman history, which is very well-known with the 'Roman Bath' concept to the tourists. </s></p><p n="p2.40"><s n="s1.2;p2.40">As these two tourism destinations have the similar background tourism concepts, the facilities that they have to offer the tourists; their respective markets and the way they are manages as tourism destinations may be more or less the same. </s><s n="s2.2;p2.40">This report is going to compare and analysis the above aspects of both tourism destinations. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">2.0. The scale and value of tourism</head><div2><head rend="underlined bold">2.1 Visitor origins</head><p n="p3.40"><s n="s1.4;p3.40">Oxford and Bath are popular tourist places for both UK and Overseas residents. </s><s n="s2.4;p3.40">According to Oxford Visitor Study, 61% of visitors staying overnight in the Oxford was from overseas. </s><s n="s3.4;p3.40">Twenty nine percentages of all staying visitors was from Western Europe. </s><s n="s4.4;p3.40">Following that, 12% of that was from North America (1996). </s></p><figure id="BAWE_3047b-fig.001"><head>Fig.1 Staying visitors in Oxford Source: Oxford Visitor Survey</head></figure><figure id="BAWE_3047b-fig.002"><head>Fig.2 Staying visitors in Oxford: Overseas Source: Oxford Visitor Survey</head></figure><p n="p4.40"><s n="s1.2;p4.40">In addition, domestic staying visitors came from throughout the UK such as the Southern, the North West and East Anglia regions. </s><s n="s2.2;p4.40">Among day visitors, 75% were from overseas (40% were from Western Europe and 15% from North America), and the rest of them were from the UK, for instance from Scotland (5%), the Southern region (4%) the North West (4%) and Yorkshire/Humberside (4%) (Southern Tourist Board, n.d.). </s></p><p n="p5.40"><s n="s1.2;p5.40">As for Bath, among UK residents about a quarter of visitors were from South West. </s><s n="s2.2;p5.40">The second largest number of visitors was from South East, and the third largest number of visitors was from West Midlands which were 18% and 13% respectively. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_3047b-fig.003"><head>Fig.3 Visitor origins in Bath - UK residents Source: South West Tourism</head></figure><p n="p6.40"><s n="s1.2;p6.40">From overseas, more than one fifth of visitors were from the United States of America. </s><s n="s2.2;p6.40">Then, 14% of visitors came from France and 13% of them were from German (South West Tourism, 2002). </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined bold">2.2 Length of stay</head><p n="p7.40"><s n="s1.3;p7.40">Tourists stay longer in Oxford than Bath. </s><s n="s2.3;p7.40">The average length of stay in Bath was 1.7 nights (Bath Spa Project, 2004). </s><s n="s3.3;p7.40">However, that of stay in Oxford was 3 nights which did not change from the 1974 survey (Glasson et al, 1992). </s></p><figure id="BAWE_3047b-fig.004"><head>Fig.4 Visitor origins in Bath - Overseas Source: South West Tourism</head></figure></div2><div2><head rend="underlined bold">2.3 Volume of tourists </head><p n="p8.40"><s n="s1.2;p8.40">In Bath, there were 6,174,000 tourists in total in 2001 (743,000 trips were made by staying visitors, and 5,431,000 were day visits) (RRG, 2001). </s><s n="s2.2;p8.40">On the other hand, in the case of Oxford, the total visitors in 2002 were 2,450,000 (1,900,000 trips were made by UK residents and 550,000 trips by overseas residents) (Star UK, 2002). </s></p><figure id="BAWE_3047b-fig.005"><head>Fig.5 Volume of visitors in Bath and Oxford Source: RRG / Star UK</head></figure></div2><div2><head rend="underlined bold">2.4 Value of tourists</head><p n="p9.40"><s n="s1.3;p9.40">Compared with Oxford and Bath, visitors in Oxford spent more than those in Bath. </s><s n="s2.3;p9.40">In 2001, £292,111,000 was used by visitors in Bath (£132,855,000 by staying visitors and £159,256,000 by day visitors) (RRG, 2001). </s><s n="s3.3;p9.40">On the one hand, the total tourists' spending was £496 million in 2002 (£257 million by UK residents and £239 million by overseas residents) (Star UK, 2002). </s></p><figure id="BAWE_3047b-fig.006"><head>Fig.6 Value of tourist in Bath and Oxford Source: RRG / Star UK</head></figure></div2><div2><head rend="underlined bold">2.5 How these meet the aim of the management plans? </head><p n="p10.40"><s n="s1.4;p10.40">Both Bath and Oxford city are trying to let the visitors stay there as long as possible. </s><s n="s2.4;p10.40">In Oxford, although there are up to three quarters of a million staying visitors per year, the number of day visits accounts for the quite high proportion (South East England Regional Assembly, 2003). </s><s n="s3.4;p10.40">Oxford Visitor Study shows that 59.2% of the Oxford total visitors were day visitors while just 40.8% of them made an overnight stay (Glasson at al, 1992). </s><s n="s4.4;p10.40">If Oxford integrates with surrounding cities's tourism such as Cotswolds and the West Country, it can obtain longer stay visitors. </s></p><p n="p11.40"><s n="s1.6;p11.40">Similarly, there are much more day visits than staying visitors in Bath. </s><s n="s2.6;p11.40">About 88% visit Bath as day trips while 12% of all visitors stay overnight (RRG, 2001). </s><s n="s3.6;p11.40">Therefore, Bath has not reached the aim in this moment; however, Bath is planning a project called Bath Spa Project which will open Mowlem and Thermae Bath Spa in 2004. </s><s n="s4.6;p11.40">The project is hoped to let the visitors stay longer in the region. </s><s n="s5.6;p11.40">Bath Spa Project estimates "If the average length of stay were to increase to 1.75 nights on average, this would imply an additional 48,000 'bed-nights' per year and B&amp;NES also receives 2.75 million day visitors every year. </s><s n="s6.6;p11.40">If just 1% of these visitors were to stay for one night, this would add a further 27,000 bed-nights" (Bath Spa Project, 2004). </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">3.0 The range of tourist facilities, attractions, and services available and the role they play in any visit</head><div2><head rend="underlined bold">3.1 Attractions</head><p n="p12.40"><s n="s1.10;p12.40">Attractions play the most important role in tourism in both Oxford and Bath. </s><s n="s2.10;p12.40">The main attractions of Oxford and Bath are the colleges of the University and Roman Bath respectively. </s><s n="s3.10;p12.40">According to Mintel (2002), Roman Bath was the forth most popular paid admission attractions in the UK and the number of tourists has been increasing. </s><s n="s4.10;p12.40">On the other hand, Oxford has many colleges of the University in the city centre and it is one of the main attractions. </s><s n="s5.10;p12.40">Although Oxford and Bath look similar as tourist cities, there are some different aspects about attractions. </s><s n="s6.10;p12.40">The major attractions in Oxford are the University colleges, Botanic Garden, Ashmolean Museum, Bodleian Library, Christ Church Cathedral and The Oxford Story (Oxford City Council, n.d.). </s><s n="s7.10;p12.40">Besides, Oxford is close to other visitor cities, such as Woodstock and Cotswolds. </s><s n="s8.10;p12.40">It takes just within one hour from the city centre. </s><s n="s9.10;p12.40">Tourist can go to the Blenheim Palace and the beautiful village of Cotswolds. </s><s n="s10.10;p12.40">It is one of the advantages that Oxford has many attractions spreading out in Oxford. </s></p><p n="p13.40"><s n="s1.5;p13.40">On the other hand, Bath's attractions are not spreading out and they are relatively concentrated in the centre of the city. </s><s n="s2.5;p13.40">The Roman Bath, Pump Room, Bath Abbey, Royal Crescent, The Circus and some museums are major attractions in Bath (Visit Bath, n.d.) and tourists can walk around the city to get these attractions. </s><s n="s3.5;p13.40">Though it is the one of the problems, there are some advantages which are different from Oxford. </s><s n="s4.5;p13.40">Bath has some seasonal attractions, such as rugby and Christmas Market and they gather many tourists even in winter. </s><s n="s5.5;p13.40">What is more, a new huge attraction, Thermae Bath Spa, is under construction and is expected to gather more tourists in the future. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined bold">3.2 Accommodation</head><p n="p14.40"><s n="s1.5;p14.40">There are some differences on the range of accommodation. </s><s n="s2.5;p14.40">At first, Bath has wide range of accommodation and the number of accommodation is more than Oxford. </s><s n="s3.5;p14.40">Whole accommodation guide (2004) is available from Tourist Information Centre and it indicates there are 193 accommodations in Bath. </s><s n="s4.5;p14.40">On the other hand, the number of the accommodation in Oxford seems not enough. </s><s n="s5.5;p14.40">The number of accommodation in Bath is nearly twice as much as Oxford (Bath &amp; Beyond: The Guide, 2004/Oxford City Council, n.d.). </s></p><figure id="BAWE_3047b-fig.007"><head>Fig 7 - The number of accommodations in Bath and Oxford Source: Bath &amp; Beyond: The Guide (2004) / Oxford City Council (no date)</head></figure><p n="p15.40"><s n="s1.4;p15.40">That is one of the problems of accommodation in Oxford, however, nearly half of the visitors stayed friends' houses who lived in Oxford city or around the city (Oxford Visitor Study, 1996). </s><s n="s2.4;p15.40">Another feature of accommodation in Oxford is the College Owned Accommodations. </s><s n="s3.4;p15.40">The University of Oxford provides some college accommodations for tourists. </s><s n="s4.4;p15.40">It might be one of the attractions in Oxford. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_3047b-fig.008"><head>Fig.8 - Accommodations used on holiday in Oxford Source: Oxford Visitor Study (1996)</head></figure></div2><div2><head rend="underlined bold">3.3 Restaurant</head><p n="p16.40"><s n="s1.1;p16.40">Although the range of accommodations in Bath is wide, one of restaurant is more restricted than Oxford. </s></p><table id="BAWE_3047b-tab.001"><head>The range of restaurant in Oxford Oxford City Council (n.d.)</head><row><cell/></row></table><table id="BAWE_3047b-tab.002"><head>The range of restaurant in Bath Bath.co.uk (n.d.)</head><row><cell/></row></table></div2><div2><head rend="underlined bold">3.4 Guide and Walks</head><p n="p17.40"><s n="s1.6;p17.40">There are guide and walking tours in Oxford and Bath. </s><s n="s2.6;p17.40">Since these cities are relatively small cities, walking tours are popular, especially in Oxford. </s><s n="s3.6;p17.40">Oxford Tourist Information Centre offers bus tour, named City Sightseeing Oxford, walking tours, such as Guild Guide, Inspector Morse Walking Tours, which features famous television drama, and Ghost Tour, which is conducted only in summer. </s><s n="s4.6;p17.40">These tours take around two hours. </s><s n="s5.6;p17.40">Bath has a similar bus tour around the city. </s><s n="s6.6;p17.40">It is useful to go around the city because Bath City Council restricts enter of traffic in the city. </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">4.0 The impact of Tourism on Oxford and Bath</head><div2><head rend="underlined bold">4.1 Economy</head><p n="p18.40"><s n="s1.3;p18.40">Oxford and Bath have high quality natural and built environment with heritage and Georgian architecture. </s><s n="s2.3;p18.40">They are historical cities with an international tourism reputation. </s><s n="s3.3;p18.40">Therefore, Tourism is a key part of the local economy. </s></p><p n="p19.40"><s n="s1.3;p19.40">As Oxford and Bath have a similar tourism background for tourists, the impact of tourism on the local economy may be more or less the same. </s><s n="s2.3;p19.40">From figure 9 (Tourism industry fact pack - Oxford, 2001 / Culture and Leisure Time - Bath, 2002), it shows that although Bath has more visitors and have higher contribution from tourism, but Oxford has more jobs created from the tourism industry. </s><s n="s3.3;p19.40">However, the unemployment levels are low in both destinations; from this point, the capacities in Oxford and Bath are quite high. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_3047b-fig.009"><head>Fig.9 - Impact on Economy comparison table (Oxford &amp; Bath) Source: Tourism industry fact pack - Oxford / Culture and Leisure Time Nov 2002 - Bath</head></figure><p n="p20.40"><s n="s1.3;p20.40">Therefore, from the figures shown above, tourism does act as an important role for Oxford's and Bath's economy. </s><s n="s2.3;p20.40">It does not just create jobs for the local people, but also may increase the local residents' income and improve life style. </s><s n="s3.3;p20.40">Due to low unemployment level in both Oxford and Bath, local residents may have high disposable income and therefore increase life standard and achieve the economy advantage, which is when marginal cost = marginal benefits. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined bold">4.2 Society</head><p n="p21.40"><s n="s1.3;p21.40">According to the Voicebox survey of Bath (Bath and North East Somerset Tourism Structure report, 2001), it shows that most of the local residents believe tourism is important to Bath, only 2% of residents believe the problems of tourism may outweigh any financial benefits. </s><s n="s2.3;p21.40">Figure 10 shows the Bath residents' view about whether the Bath Council should encourage more visitors or not. </s><s n="s3.3;p21.40">Most of the residents think it should encourage more visitors generally, which represents that tourism is favourable to the society. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_3047b-fig.010"><head>Fig.10 Bath's residents view about "Should the bath Council encourage more visitors" Source: Bath and North East Somerset Tourism Structure Report August 2001</head></figure><p n="p22.40"><s n="s1.2;p22.40">Even though, 53% of the local people think tourism has a little effect on their daily life, 40% believe they are not affected by it at all. </s><s n="s2.2;p22.40">Figure 11 below shows the positive impacts that the local people think they gain from tourism. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_3047b-fig.011"><head>Fig.11 The positive impacts of tourism on Bath's local residents Source: Bath and North East Somerset Tourism Structure Report August 2001</head></figure><p n="p23.40"><s n="s1.2;p23.40">In Oxford side of the society, tourism does have a positive aspect on it, figure 12 shows that the Oxford environment is the attractive points to the tourists. </s><s n="s2.2;p23.40">As Oxford is a historical city which gain a traditional culture value, this heritage environment may increase its capacity. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_3047b-fig.012"><head>Fig.12 Visitor's favour about Oxford Source: Oxford Visitor Survey</head></figure><p n="p24.40"><s n="s1.4;p24.40">Figure 13 shows the disliked about Oxford from the visitors. </s><s n="s2.4;p24.40">Most visitors think there are too much traffic in Oxford, followed by over-crowded. </s><s n="s3.4;p24.40">From these points of view means that these factors affect the local society, which brings negative impact to the local people. </s><s n="s4.4;p24.40">Additionally, Oxford seems an academic based environment, tourism may also bring a negative impact to the local students as well. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_3047b-fig.013"><head>Fig.13 Visitor's disliked about Oxford Source: Oxford Visitor Survey</head></figure></div2><div2><head rend="underlined bold">4.3 Politics</head><p n="p25.40"><s n="s1.2;p25.40">The tourism industry in Oxford is controlled by the Oxford City Council, together with coordination with Oxfordshire Chamber of Commerce Tourism Group, Thames and Chilterns Country Steering Group, Oxfordshire Local Authorities Tourism Group, Southern Tourist Board Tourism Officers Liaison Panel and Southern Tourism Board Executive Committee. </s><s n="s2.2;p25.40">For example, this coordination approach to Oxford tourism industry will implement the Visitor Coaches Strategy (Tourism industry fact pack - Oxford, 2001) which includes the provision of a larger coach park and enforcement of on-street regulations. </s></p><p n="p26.40"><s n="s1.5;p26.40">However, in Bath, the tourism industry is mainly controlled by the B&amp;NES council. </s><s n="s2.5;p26.40">Even though, 50% of the tourism industry is under controlled by the private sectors, which has been difficulties raising the private income on a sustained basis. </s><s n="s3.5;p26.40">Nevertheless, the council is the key player in tourism, but in order to achieve its overall economic development objectives, it needs strong support of the private sector to deliver across the full scope of the new strategy. </s><s n="s4.5;p26.40">For example, the Bath council directly provided culture and leisure-related services such as museums and parks. </s><s n="s5.5;p26.40">Also, indirect and external services that the Council influences, such as subsidised museums and sponsored arts activities. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined bold">4.4 Physical Environment</head><p n="p27.40"><s n="s1.4;p27.40">In order to have an economy growth, high quality environment is required for sustainability. </s><s n="s2.4;p27.40">In bath, there is a good range of indoor and outdoor sports facilities, including clubs at recreational and serious competitive level, which benefits to both residents and visitors. </s><s n="s3.4;p27.40">For physical capacity, "Annual average room occupancy in serviced accommodation is 65%" (Bath and North East Somerset Tourism Structure Report August 2001). </s><s n="s4.4;p27.40">Therefore, it has a spare capacity for tourist to be accommodated. </s></p><p n="p28.40"><s n="s1.3;p28.40">In Oxford, some strategies have been used to encourage environmental sustainability. </s><s n="s2.3;p28.40">For example, "promote the use of public transport and park &amp; Ride as a means of traveling to and from Oxford" and "develop liaison with colleges and encourage them to participate in relevant tourism management initiatives". </s><s n="s3.3;p28.40">These may reduce the harmful impacts of tourism and maintain the environmental sustainability. </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">5.0 Management of the City Councils</head><div2><head rend="underlined bold">5.1 Access</head><p n="p29.40"><s n="s1.3;p29.40">In term of access for disable people, the Disability Discrimination Act covers both Councils' policy for disabilities. </s><s n="s2.3;p29.40">For instance, for people with hearing disabilities, they try to show more written information and audio-visual telephones. </s><s n="s3.3;p29.40">Also, for people with limited mobility, they provide portable ramp and encourage having an area of reception counter at a lower level. </s></p><p n="p30.40"><s n="s1.2;p30.40">Bath shopmobility centre provide a loan service of manual or powered wheelchairs and electric scooters to anyone with limited mobility. </s><s n="s2.2;p30.40">This could be one of access managements of disable people. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined bold">5.2 Transport</head><p n="p31.40"><s n="s1.2;p31.40">The City Councils have own Local Transport Plans which identifies the key transport problems in the cities. </s><s n="s2.2;p31.40">For example, the one in Bath contains traffic management (such as how to reduce traffic impacts and improve air quality and safety), public transport, parking management, public involvement and enhance environment. </s></p><p n="p32.40"><s n="s1.7;p32.40">In their Local Transport Plans, both City Councils encourage using public transport in order to reduce traffic inside the cities and improve air quality. </s><s n="s2.7;p32.40">Especially, Park and Ride car parks are key features of transport strategies for both Oxford and Bath recently. </s><s n="s3.7;p32.40">Oxford has four Park and Ride' car parks compared to three in Bath. </s><s n="s4.7;p32.40">These services are operated seven days a week and every 20 minutes. </s><s n="s5.7;p32.40">It can be said that Oxford is more accessible because there are two bus operators with more than 40 routes in and around Oxford; on the other hand, Bath has one operator with only 8 routes. </s><s n="s6.7;p32.40">The City Councils have dialogues frequently with these bus companies because the bus services is one of the most frequent used transport in both cities. </s><s n="s7.7;p32.40">The Oxford City Council operates the Concessionary Fares scheme which gives benefit for buses for residents with less ability and disabilities in and around the city (Accessible Oxford Guide - Transport 2004, <seg type="URL" n="http://www.oxford.gov.uk/"/>). </s></p><p n="p33.40"><s n="s1.4;p33.40">Cycling is a clean and efficient means of transport that allows mobility with minimal impact on the environment (Bath and North East Somerset Local Transport Plan). </s><s n="s2.4;p33.40">This promotion is a key element of the Council's transport strategy in Bath. </s><s n="s3.4;p33.40">They try to develop cycle parking and maintain the high quality of cycling routes. </s><s n="s4.4;p33.40">Also, Oxfordshire County Council promotes cycling in the city website which says that 19% of the population of Oxford cycle to work and there are 1800 public cycle parking places. (<seg type="URL" n="http://www.oxfordshire.gov.uk/cyclemaps"/>, 2004) </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined bold">5.3 Promotion</head><p n="p34.40"><s n="s1.4;p34.40">Advertising and public relations (PR) are two of the most important promotional tools used in the implementation of marketing campaigns (Middleton, Victor T. C). </s><s n="s2.4;p34.40">As one of the promotions, both City Councils offer concessionary bus fares to urge tourists to travel around the cities by bus. </s><s n="s3.4;p34.40">They also promote walking tours, registered sightseeing buses and cycles for exploring the city. </s><s n="s4.4;p34.40">To give information of events and festivals in the cities through poster, leaflets and websites promote the cities all over the world. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined bold">5.4 Interpretation</head><p n="p35.40"><s n="s1.2;p35.40">Oxford is one of the top heritage destinations in the UK. However, The Oxford City Council gives information not only about heritage places such as museums and colleges of University of Oxford but also about sports facilities, shopping areas and restaurants. </s><s n="s2.2;p35.40">Moreover, they explain Oxford as hi-tech community because many businesses are located around Oxford and Oxford business park stands just outside of the city (<seg type="URL" n="http://www.oxfordcity.co.uk"/>, 2004). </s></p><p n="p36.40"><s n="s1.1;p36.40">On the other hand, with the fact of 80% of tourist come to the South West, especially because of the regional environment and heritage, Roman Baths and some historical places are focused on with their promotions. </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">6.0 Conclusion</head><p n="p37.40"><s n="s1.2;p37.40">Sum of all, the main tourists visit Oxford and Bath are overseas visitors, which their respective market would be International rather than domestic. </s><s n="s2.2;p37.40">The average length that tourists stay in Bath is 6 days but only 2.5 days in Oxford, however, the value that the tourists spend in Oxford is more than in Bath. </s></p><p n="p38.40"><s n="s1.3;p38.40">The both tourism destinations have the same sort of facilities offering to the tourists. </s><s n="s2.3;p38.40">The main similarities are the coach tour, the historical cities attractions and the range of accommodations providing. </s><s n="s3.3;p38.40">However, there are more choices of different cultural restaurants in Bath than in Oxford. </s></p><p n="p39.40"><s n="s1.3;p39.40">The tourism industry has positive impacts on Oxford and Bath local economy and society, as the local people gain benefits from it. </s><s n="s2.3;p39.40">Even though, there are some negative influences on the physical environment, such as too much traffic and over-crowed in the cities. </s><s n="s3.3;p39.40">However, the local council of Oxford and Bath did a lot of policies to minimise the harmful impacts of tourism on the local society, such as transport policy to reduce traffic in the cities and promote walking tours to the tourists. </s></p><p n="p40.40"><s n="s1.2;p40.40">Therefore, Oxford and Bath have the similar management concepts and impact of tourism while they both have the similar tourism background to the tourists. </s><s n="s2.2;p40.40">However, the culture of these tourism destinations are difference, as Oxford has the historical university culture concept but Bath has the relaxing Roman culture concept, which are the different attraction points to attract the tourists, so that the effect on tourists expenses in both tourism destinations may be different. </s></p></div1></body><back/></text></TEI.2>
