<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_3047d" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title></title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">
Appendices (1-3) contain graphs and figures.
</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">2</p><p n="date">2005-12</p><p n="module title">Strategic Management in Tourism</p><p n="module code">U57224</p><p n="genre family">Case study</p><p n="discipline">Hospitality, Leisure &amp; Tourism Management</p><p n="disciplinary group">SS</p><p n="grade">M</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">2559</p><p n="number of s-units">113</p><p n="number of p">34</p><p n="number of tables">0</p><p n="number of figures">0</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">0</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">0</p><p n="abstract present">abstract present</p><p n="average words per s-unit">22.6</p><p n="average s-units per p">3.3</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">f</p><p n="year of birth">1984</p><p n="first language">Chinese unspecified</p><p n="education">UK8</p><p n="course">MSc International Travel and Tourism Management</p><p n="student ID">3047</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><div1 type="toc" n="2"><head rend="underlined bold">Content</head><p rend="underlined">1.0 Executive Summary</p><p><hi rend="underlined">2.0 Introduction</hi> 1</p><p><hi rend="underlined">3.0 Stakeholders Map and Power &amp; Interest Matrix</hi> 2</p><p><hi rend="underlined">3.1 Marketing Liverpool's Tourism - A Great Opportunity</hi> 3</p><p><hi rend="underlined">3.2 Liverpool's New Challenge - Attractions</hi> 3</p><p><hi rend="underlined">4.0 The Effectiveness of Liverpool Model</hi> 4</p><p><hi rend="underlined">4.1 Reasons for Choosing Greenwich</hi> 5</p><p><hi rend="underlined">4.2 Benchmarking - Greenwich vs. Liverpool</hi> 5</p><p><hi rend="underlined">5.0 Problems and Strategic Responses</hi> 6</p><p><hi rend="underlined">6.0 Re-imaging and the Sustainable Tourism</hi> 7</p><p><hi rend="underlined">7.0 Conclusion</hi> 8</p><p><hi rend="underlined">8.0 Appendices</hi> 9</p><p><hi rend="underlined">8.1 Appendix 1: Stakeholders Map</hi> 9</p><p><hi rend="underlined">8.2 Appendix 2: Power and Interest Matrix</hi> 9</p><p><hi rend="underlined">8.3 Appendix 3: Power and Interest Matrix of Stakeholders in Liverpool Tourism Industry</hi>10</p><p><hi rend="underlined">9.0 Bibliography</hi> 11</p></div1></front><body><div1 type="abstract"><head rend="underlined bold">1.0 Executive Summary</head><p n="p1.34"><s n="s1.2;p1.34">Liverpool's visitor volume is estimated to increase with the status of the winner of European Capital of Culture 2008 and also through the regeneration projects. </s><s n="s2.2;p1.34">For this reason, it is fundamental to review Liverpool as a tourist destination with the aim of identifying its opportunities to attract more visitors and meet the demand. </s></p><p n="p2.34"><s n="s1.3;p2.34">The stakeholders have different perspectives and interactions in the provision of tourism at Liverpool. </s><s n="s2.3;p2.34">Also, they have different involvement. </s><s n="s3.3;p2.34">As for the local government in Liverpool, it acts as a key player in the tourism industry since the partnerships intend to promote Liverpool to become a well-known city, which leads high interest of the industry's performance. </s></p><p n="p3.34"><s n="s1.4;p3.34">Besides, the local communities and employees including local people and businesses are the other parties that involve in Liverpool tourism industry. </s><s n="s2.4;p3.34">Local businesses need to be kept satisfied because they may also the investors/suppliers or could be employees participating in the tourism industry. </s><s n="s3.4;p3.34">Furthermore, investors are also the key player in the industry. </s><s n="s4.4;p3.34">They act as the suppliers to provide services or product with the tourist. </s></p><p n="p4.34"><s n="s1.5;p4.34">In order to increase the volume and value of tourism to Liverpool, stakeholders in Liverpool should set some objectives. </s><s n="s2.5;p4.34">For example, Liverpool should be open to other foreign countries because the international tourism market offers a number of opportunities for the city to create the huge benefit. </s><s n="s3.5;p4.34">What is more, getting more visitors from overseas, Liverpool is trying to give them special offers such as a wide range of restaurant. </s><s n="s4.5;p4.34">It is also effective that reflects placing in attractions have interpretations for other major languages so that they do not have language problems. </s><s n="s5.5;p4.34">Moreover, investors of the attractions should provide a wide range of facilities and arrangement to every people such as children, the elders, disabled people and family. </s></p><p n="p5.34"><s n="s1.5;p5.34">As Liverpool is a winner of European Capital of Culture 2008, it should possess some competences. </s><s n="s2.5;p5.34">However, those competences are not necessarily making Liverpool to be succeeded, although European Capital of Culture 2008 has created ideal opportunities for enhancing cooperation among its key stakeholders. </s><s n="s3.5;p5.34">In order to analyse the effectiveness of Liverpool model, benchmarking may be a useful tool to compare with Greenwich (because it has a lot of similarities between Liverpool) and identify the opportunities for improvement. </s><s n="s4.5;p5.34">Owing to the failure of the Greenwich's plan, Liverpool has to make sure that the benefits of its designation and status are to be maximised. </s><s n="s5.5;p5.34">It should have a clear scope for developing a more integrated approach by increasing communication and cooperation. </s></p><p n="p6.34"><s n="s1.3;p6.34">With the aim of developing a sustainable tourism in Liverpool, changing the image of Liverpool is a really good idea. </s><s n="s2.3;p6.34">Stakeholders should make full use of their natural advantages such as the beautiful seaside. </s><s n="s3.3;p6.34">Here, there are new projects to create water parks instead of having green public parks followed by floating restaurants, cafe and hotels as Liverpool is a variable marine city. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">2.0 Introduction</head><p n="p7.34"><s n="s1.2;p7.34">With the status of the European City of Culture for 2008 and also through the regeneration projects, Liverpool's visitor volume is estimated to increase. </s><s n="s2.2;p7.34">Therefore it is essential to review Liverpool as a tourist destination with the aim of identifying its opportunities to attract more visitors and meet the demands. </s></p><p n="p8.34"><s n="s1.1;p8.34">This report covers the stakeholders and their interactions in Liverpool using theoretical models and also strategic response to problems which Liverpool has been facing based on observations and experience that we had in Liverpool. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">3.0 Stakeholders Map and Power &amp; Interest Matrix</head><p n="p9.34"><s n="s1.3;p9.34">The stakeholders map (Appendix 1) shows the stakeholders that involve in Liverpool tourism industry, indicating the relationships and interactions between the stakeholders. </s><s n="s2.3;p9.34">In order to identify the effectiveness of Liverpool model, a Power &amp; Matrix Model (Appendix 2) may effectively illustrate the role of the stakeholders undertaken. </s><s n="s3.3;p9.34">Appendix 3 shows the Power &amp; Interest Matrix of the stakeholders of Liverpool tourism industry. </s></p><p n="p10.34"><s n="s1.4;p10.34">There are public-private partnerships cooperating to carry out the regeneration and 'Liverpool 08' project, such as Liverpool Vision, City Focus and Mersey Partnership. </s><s n="s2.4;p10.34">These are all the partners of Liverpool local government. </s><s n="s3.4;p10.34">Local government acts as a key player in the tourism industry since the partnerships intend to promote Liverpool to become a well-known city, which leads high interest of the industry's performance. </s><s n="s4.4;p10.34">Additionally, it has the power to set regulations (such as legal system - disability regulation) and empower other stakeholders to provide services and products with the industry. </s></p><p n="p11.34"><s n="s1.2;p11.34">Other parties that involve in Liverpool tourism industry are the local communities and employees, which include local people and businesses. </s><s n="s2.2;p11.34">Local businesses need to be kept satisfied, because they may also the investors/suppliers or could be employees participating in the tourism industry. </s></p><p n="p12.34"><s n="s1.1;p12.34">If the number of tourists increases, local people are willing to spend money for starting or investing in a business such as restaurants because they can get more profit from the tourists </s></p><div2><head rend="underlined bold">3.1 Marketing Liverpool's Tourism - A Great Opportunity</head><p n="p13.34"><s n="s1.3;p13.34">The fact that Liverpool has chosen for the European City of Culture encourages other government parties and European Union to involve in the Liverpool's tourism industry, such as the European governments and European Funding. </s><s n="s2.3;p13.34">These parties may have minimal effort to Liverpool but need to be kept satisfied. </s><s n="s3.3;p13.34">For instance, European Funding is a major sponsor to develop infrastructure of Liverpool for the 'Liverpool 08' project, and Liverpool needs to advertise itself in the European countries. </s></p><p n="p14.34"><s n="s1.3;p14.34">Moreover, Liverpool also should be open to other foreign countries, because the international tourism market offers a number of opportunities for the city to create the huge benefit. </s><s n="s2.3;p14.34">However, apparently it is less certain that Liverpool has been successful for attracting overseas visitors. </s><s n="s3.3;p14.34">In fact, even though Liverpool was on the list showing top towns visited by overseas tourists, its ranking was quite low <hi rend="bold">(StarUK, 2004)</hi>. </s></p><p n="p15.34"><s n="s1.3;p15.34">As possible ways to get more visitors from overseas, Liverpool is trying to give them special offers. </s><s n="s2.3;p15.34">For instance, a wide range of restaurant such as Chinese and Italian is one example. </s><s n="s3.3;p15.34">It is also effective that reflects placing in attractions have interpretations for other major languages so that they do not have language problems. </s></p><p n="p16.34"><s n="s1.2;p16.34">In terms of economic return per visit, the international tourism market is identified as a profitable market since they simply spend more money by overnight stay than domestic travellers. </s><s n="s2.2;p16.34">Besides, it is recognised that they are less price sensitive and unlikely to have a negative perception to Liverpool. </s></p><p n="p17.34"><s n="s1.1;p17.34">This might be a result of the media parties such as newspapers and TV programs since they have high power to effect tourists' intention. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined bold">3.2 Liverpool's New Challenge - Attractions</head><p n="p18.34"><s n="s1.6;p18.34">As Liverpool undertaking the regeneration project, investors are also the key player in the industry. </s><s n="s2.6;p18.34">They act as the suppliers to provide services or product with the tourist, for example, 'Liverpool 08' project has led to new investments in theatres, concert venues and national museums and galleries. </s><s n="s3.6;p18.34">This includes the transformation of the Museum of Liverpool Life into the world's greatest city history museum <hi rend="bold">(The Mersey Partnership, 2004)</hi> and also the investments in hospitality and transport sectors. </s><s n="s4.6;p18.34">Therefore, they have high interest in the tourism industry and have great power to affect the industry. </s><s n="s5.6;p18.34">Especially, in the Liverpool case, their role can be really important to support the tourism since it has more museums than any other UK city outside of London <hi rend="bold">(The Liverpool Culture Company Ltd, 2004a)</hi>. </s><s n="s6.6;p18.34">Also, Liverpool's cultural importance is represented by its range of traditional and modern galleries <hi rend="bold">(The Liverpool Culture Company Ltd, 2004b).</hi> </s></p><p n="p19.34"><s n="s1.3;p19.34">However, they should make sure that there are sophisticated arrangements and a wide range of facility in the attractions which are suitable to everyone such as children, the elders, disabled people and family. </s><s n="s2.3;p19.34">For example, Liverpool Museum has flat-access exits as well as toilets for the disabled <hi rend="bold">(Field Notebook, 2004)</hi>. </s><s n="s3.3;p19.34">As disabled people cannot move easily, these facilities can make them much easier to visit museums or galleries. </s></p><p n="p20.34"><s n="s1.5;p20.34">Similarly, Liverpool Museum has many facilities and enjoyable activities for children. </s><s n="s2.5;p20.34">One of them is called 'the Big Draw' and it allows kids to develop their creative ideas for drawing <hi rend="bold">(Field Notebook, 2004)</hi>. </s><s n="s3.5;p20.34">These activities can encourage more children to feel like going to museums, galleries or theatres, even if they are unfamiliar with those. </s><s n="s4.5;p20.34">As a result of it, this would increase the number of family who visit to these attractions. </s><s n="s5.5;p20.34">To create the atmosphere where family can spend fun time together might be a key aspect for the future decision. </s></p><p n="p21.34"><s n="s1.4;p21.34">So far, it seems that Liverpool has many advantages and gives tourists the image of well-organised city, but there are also some problems should be considered. </s><s n="s2.4;p21.34">For example, the closing time of the attractions is too early (around 5 to 6 o'clock) <hi rend="bold">(Field Notebook, 2004)</hi>. </s><s n="s3.4;p21.34">Therefore, it is hard for most of the business people to visit these attractions. </s><s n="s4.4;p21.34">In order to deal with it, they can have a special service for busy men such as making particular days when the attractions open until relatively late. </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">4.0 The Effectiveness of Liverpool Model</head><p n="p22.34"><s n="s1.3;p22.34">As Liverpool is a victor in the contest to be named European Capital of Culture 2008, it should possess some competences. </s><s n="s2.3;p22.34">However, those competences are not necessarily making Liverpool to be succeeded, although European Capital of Culture 2008 has created ideal opportunities for enhancing cooperation among its key stakeholders (As stated above). </s><s n="s3.3;p22.34">In order to analyse the effectiveness of Liverpool model, benchmarking may be a useful tool to compare with other tourist destinations and identify the opportunities for improvement. </s></p><div2><head rend="underlined bold">4.1 Reasons for Choosing Greenwich</head><p n="p23.34"><s n="s1.4;p23.34">Greenwich was a tourist destination chosen for the host of the Millennium Dome exhibition in 2000 which is similar event to European Capital of Culture 2008 in Liverpool. </s><s n="s2.4;p23.34">Furthermore, Greenwich and Liverpool both gain the status as a World Heritage Site and maritime tourism destinations. </s><s n="s3.4;p23.34">In the past, they both used to have a poor image due to the recession and the lack of investments <hi rend="bold">(Greenwich Council, 2004)</hi>. </s><s n="s4.4;p23.34">These similarities tell that Greenwich may be a good tourist destination so that Liverpool can produce strategic plans on the basis of its success and failure. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined bold">4.2 Benchmarking - Greenwich vs. Liverpool</head><p n="p24.34"><s n="s1.2;p24.34">Based on the Millennium Dome exhibition in 2000, Greenwich has put huge efforts in developing its tourism industry. </s><s n="s2.2;p24.34">However, it was an completely failure as by February 2000 "the much maligned Dome had failed to meet its visitor targets, attracting only 3% of the 12 million visitors it need to break even"<hi rend="bold">(Arlidge and Wintour, 2000)</hi>, although "it was originally estimated that 12 million visitors would visit the Dome"<hi rend="bold"> (British Tourist Authority, 1999)</hi>. </s></p><p n="p25.34"><s n="s1.4;p25.34">According to Smith (2000), it says that "tourism development in Greenwich has traditionally been piecemeal and lacking in coordination." </s><s n="s2.4;p25.34">Thus, from the failure of the dome, Liverpool has to make sure that the benefits of its designation and status are to be maximised. </s><s n="s3.4;p25.34">It should have a clear scope for developing a more integrated approach by increasing communication and cooperation. </s><s n="s4.4;p25.34">In terms of the service sector, the transportation network in Liverpool has to improve connections by examining the example of Greenwich where transport congestion and the lack of parking area are seen. </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">5.0 Problems and Strategic Responses</head><p n="p26.34"><s n="s1.1;p26.34">As the other important service division, it is critically identified that Liverpool needs to improve accommodation and restaurant sectors which cover the development of human resource management too. </s></p><p n="p27.34"><s n="s1.5;p27.34">First of all, the capacity of the accommodation in Liverpool may need to be developed. </s><s n="s2.5;p27.34">It is believed that Liverpool could attract extra 1.7 million visitors during the 'Liverpool 08 project'<hi rend="bold"> (The Liverpool Culture Company Ltd, 2004c)</hi>. </s><s n="s3.5;p27.34">Nevertheless, The Mersey Partnership shows the full list of accommodation available in Liverpool, but there are only 107 accommodations totally and this figure includes Bed and Breakfasts, hostels, campuses and guest houses. </s><s n="s4.5;p27.34">Actual hotel number in Liverpool is 62 <hi rend="bold">(Visit Liverpool, 2004)</hi>. </s><s n="s5.5;p27.34">However, it is not the ideal figure for the city which has potential to be one of the top tourist destinations with 'Liverpool 08' project. </s></p><p n="p28.34"><s n="s1.2;p28.34">Therefore, Liverpool should be able to increase its capacity to meet the huge demand of customers. </s><s n="s2.2;p28.34">It is also critically identified that Liverpool needs to improve accommodation and restaurant sectors and this covers the development of human resource management too. </s></p><p n="p29.34"><s n="s1.7;p29.34">As regards the service which they offer, the experience from the field trip describes a disaster which is actually happening in Liverpool now. </s><s n="s2.7;p29.34">It critically shows the lack of training and development of employees. </s><s n="s3.7;p29.34">In order to enhance this situation and succeed 'Liverpool 08' project, the human resource management sector has to put more effort. </s><s n="s4.7;p29.34">Employees need to understand working hospitality industry and what is more, practical training should be given. </s><s n="s5.7;p29.34">Practical training aims to increase the commitment of teams to rapid action and appropriate decision-making for customer needs. </s><s n="s6.7;p29.34">It would ensure that the superior quality of facilities and services and thus earn the loyalty of guests. </s><s n="s7.7;p29.34">For this reason, although it has minimal effort to this industry, education system is also important as another stakeholder, because higher education creates skilled employees. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">6.0 Re-imaging and the Sustainable Tourism</head><p n="p30.34"><s n="s1.3;p30.34">As the important aspect which Liverpool should consider is redevelopment the image of Liverpool to achieve the sustainable tourism. </s><s n="s2.3;p30.34">In general, the image of Liverpool is quite negative. </s><s n="s3.3;p30.34">It is likely to describe a dangerous and miserable city due to the decline of the sipping industry which Liverpool used to heavily depend on. </s></p><p n="p31.34"><s n="s1.3;p31.34">However, Liverpool has enough resources to sell the city with a positive image, so it just has to find an effective way to take advantage of those. </s><s n="s2.3;p31.34">The Beatles and Albert Dock are all fantastic and great opportunities. </s><s n="s3.3;p31.34">Here, there are new projects to create water parks instead of having green public parks followed by floating restaurants, cafe and hotels <hi rend="bold">(Liverpool Vision, 2004)</hi> as Liverpool is a variable marine city. </s></p><p n="p32.34"><s n="s1.2;p32.34">In addition, Liverpool has taken other actions to be friendly to visitors by placing sings and maps on the street which show the direction to major attractions. </s><s n="s2.2;p32.34">It is also certain that in order to achieve this, local communities give considerable supports to the city making nice atmosphere. </s></p><p n="p33.34"><s n="s1.5;p33.34">With the purpose of the sustainable tourism, Liverpool should have long term development plans. </s><s n="s2.5;p33.34">According to Liverpool Vision (2004), there is a project of Liverpool city having a large scale conference facility. </s><s n="s3.5;p33.34">It is a great opportunity to demonstrate Liverpool as a new image of popular conference destination. </s><s n="s4.5;p33.34">It possibly encourages Liverpool's tourism to be sustainable. </s><s n="s5.5;p33.34">In other words, this scheme ensures that Liverpool can generate further benefit in long term even after the European City of Culture for 2008. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">7.0 Conclusion</head><p n="p34.34"><s n="s1.7;p34.34">As the UK's next European Capital of Culture, Liverpool will see its profile rise. </s><s n="s2.7;p34.34">It intends to boost the tourism industry by increasing the amount of tourists and adding value of tourism to Liverpool. </s><s n="s3.7;p34.34">Since Liverpool was ever one of Britain's poorest cities, the re-imaging is the prior thing to implement. </s><s n="s4.7;p34.34">By undertaking the regeneration project, understanding the stakeholders within the tourism industry in Liverpool is the crucial factor need to be considered. </s><s n="s5.7;p34.34">The authorities have to put all the stakeholders together and make them cooperate with each other so as to make the industry succeeded. </s><s n="s6.7;p34.34">Subsequently, they have to plan for the redevelopment strategically and thoughtfully in each of the sectors in the tourism industry in Liverpool and response to the problems immediately. </s><s n="s7.7;p34.34">After putting all into action, the tourism industry in Liverpool must have a great opportunity in European Capital of Culture 2008. </s></p></div1></body><back><div1 type="appendix"><head rend="underlined bold">8.0 Appendices</head><p/></div1><div1 type="bibliography"><head rend="underlined bold">9.0 Bibliography</head><p>Arlidge, J. and Wintour, P. (2000), how the Dome Dream Collapsed, <hi rend="italic">The Guardian</hi>, Sunday 6<hi rend="sup">th</hi> February. Cited in Smith, Melaine K (2000) Greenwich 2000: Development sustainable tourism in the shadow of the Dome. In: Robinson, M., ed. <hi rend="italic">Environment Management and Pathways to Sustainable Tourism</hi>, pp.285-301.</p><p>British Tourist Authority (1999), <hi rend="italic">Millennium News - The British Tourist Authority Millennium Campaign</hi>, Vol.1, Issue 2, July. Cited in Smith, Melaine K (2000) Greenwich 2000: Development sustainable tourism in the shadow of the Dome. In: Robinson, M., ed. <hi rend="italic">Environment Management and Pathways to Sustainable Tourism</hi>, pp.285-301.</p><p>Field Notebook (2004).</p><p>Greenwich Council (2004). <hi rend="italic">Promoting SustainableTtourism</hi>. Retrieved on 29<hi rend="sup">th</hi> October 2004 from the World Wide Web:</p><p><seg type="URL" n="http://www.greenwich.gov.uk/NR/rdonlyres/2F4CADF0-D2B4-4B9D-83BC-8DF102965AC7/0/beacon_status_general.pdf"/> </p><p>Liverpool Vision (2004). <hi rend="italic">Strategic Regeneration Framework.</hi> Retrieved on 23<hi rend="sup">rd</hi> October 2004 from the World Wide Web: <seg type="URL" n="http://www.liverpoolvision.com"/></p><p>Smith, Melaine K (2000) Greenwich 2000: Development sustainable tourism in the shadow of the Dome. In: Robinson, M., ed. <hi rend="italic">Environment Management and Pathways to Sustainable Tourism</hi>: Sunderland, pp.285-301.</p><p>StarUK (2004). <hi rend="italic">Toptowns visited by oversea tourists.</hi> Retrieved on 24<hi rend="sup">th</hi> October 2004 from the World Wide Web: <seg type="URL" n="http://www.staruk.org.uk/default.asp?ID=657&amp;parentid=469"/></p><p>The Liverpool Culture Company Ltd (2004a). <hi rend="italic">Museum.</hi> Retrieved on 24<hi rend="sup">th</hi> October 2004 from the World Wide Web: <seg type="URL" n="http://www.liverpool08.com/root/About_Liverpool/Museums/Index.asp"/></p><p>The Liverpool Culture Company Ltd (2004b). <hi rend="italic">Galleries.</hi> Retrieved on 24<hi rend="sup">th</hi> October 2004 from the World Wide Web:</p><p><seg type="URL" n="http://www.liverpool08.com/root/About_Liverpool/Galleries/Index.asp"/></p><p>The Liverpool Culture Company Ltd (2004c). <hi rend="italic">About Liverpool.</hi> Retrieved on 27<hi rend="sup">th</hi> October 2004 from the World Wide Web: <seg type="URL" n="http://www.liverpool08.com/root/About_Liverpool/index.asp"/></p><p>The Mersey Partnership (2004). Retrieved on 27<hi rend="sup">th</hi> October 2004 from the World Wide Web: <seg type="URL" n="http://www.merseyside.org.uk/research/pdfs/vision2003forprint.pdf"/> </p><p>Tribe, John (1997). <hi rend="italic">Corporate strategy for tourism</hi>. London: International Thomson Business Press</p><p>VisitLiverpool (2004). <hi rend="italic">Accommodation.</hi> Retrieved on 24<hi rend="sup">th</hi> October 2004 from the World Wide Web:</p><p><seg type="URL" n="http://www.vistiliverpool.com/accomsearch.asp?resultpage=6"/></p></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
