<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_3049c" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>"Much ado about Models" Using Consumer Behavious Models in Shakespeare's Globe Theatre</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">The document has a title page which contains:
document title
title part</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">4</p><p n="date">2005-12</p><p n="module title">Tourist Consumer Behaviour</p><p n="module code">P58904</p><p n="genre family">Case study</p><p n="discipline">Hospitality, Leisure &amp; Tourism Management</p><p n="disciplinary group">SS</p><p n="grade">M</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">3059</p><p n="number of s-units">133</p><p n="number of p">10</p><p n="number of tables">0</p><p n="number of figures">4</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">0</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">0</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">23.0</p><p n="average s-units per p">13.3</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">m</p><p n="year of birth">1981</p><p n="first language">English</p><p n="education">OSa</p><p n="course">MSc International Hotel and Tourism Management</p><p n="student ID">3049</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><titlePart><hi rend="bold">Business School</hi> <hi rend="bold"> MSc in International Hotel and Tourism Marketing Management</hi></titlePart><docTitle><titlePart rend="underlined"><hi rend="bold italic">"Much ado about models"</hi> Using Consumer Behaviour Models in Shakespeare's Globe Theatre</titlePart></docTitle><titlePart>Module Title: Tourist Consumer Behaviour Module Number: P58904</titlePart><titlePart>Module Leader: <name type="tutor name"/></titlePart><titlePart rend="bold"> Submitted Date: December 7th 2005</titlePart><titlePart rend="bold"> Student Name: <name type="student name"/> Student Number: <name type="student ID"/></titlePart></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="section"><p n="p1.10"><s n="s1.17;p1.10">The marketing catch phrase a picture is worth a thousand words, while in some cases true, presents a paradox related to human behaviour; while products and services may be influential, <hi rend="italic">no</hi> picture truly sums up all possible perceptions (Snehota, 2004). </s><s n="s2.17;p1.10">The study of <hi rend="italic">consumer behaviour</hi> thus follows a growing awareness to <hi rend="italic">acquire</hi> and <hi rend="italic">organize</hi> information on behavioural processes involved in purchasing, using, and disposing of products, services, ideas or experiences (Moutinho, 1987; Solomon <hi rend="italic">et al</hi>., 1999; Goeldner <hi rend="italic">et al.</hi> </s><s n="s3.17;p1.10">, 2000). </s><s n="s4.17;p1.10">Authors agree that improved understanding of consumers' internal, psychological, processes is important for companies to meet the needs of desired target markets (Goeldner <hi rend="italic">et al.</hi> </s><s n="s5.17;p1.10">, 2000; Hudson <hi rend="italic">et al.</hi> </s><s n="s6.17;p1.10">, 2000; Middleton <hi rend="italic">et al.</hi> </s><s n="s7.17;p1.10">, 2001, Usunier <hi rend="italic">et al</hi>., 2005). </s><s n="s8.17;p1.10">Even so the tourism industry presents a unique challenge owing to the intangibility of services, coupled with extensive periods of time travellers invest in planning and purchasing an <hi rend="italic">experience</hi>; an area which in the past has been inadequately viewed as simplistic (Moutinho, 1987; Hudson <hi rend="italic">et al.</hi> </s><s n="s9.17;p1.10">, 2000). </s><s n="s10.17;p1.10">As travellers become more sophisticated the question arises as to why particular groups of travellers seek a certain service X within destination Y (Goeldner <hi rend="italic">et al.</hi> </s><s n="s11.17;p1.10">, 2000; Moutinho, 1987). </s><s n="s12.17;p1.10">Consequently, tourism practitioners need to effectively divide the vacation market into subgroups or <hi rend="italic">segments</hi> according to the destination images held by non-residents; facilitating cost-effective marketing to current and future travellers (Middleton <hi rend="italic">et al</hi>., 2001; Leisen, 2001; Solomon <hi rend="italic">et al</hi>., 1999). </s><s n="s13.17;p1.10">Various authors are in agreement that in formulating such strategies, <hi rend="italic">consumer behaviour models</hi> are useful tools in <hi rend="italic">simplifying</hi> abstract relationships and links between numerous internal and external variables which affect behaviour (Chisnall, 1995; Cooper <hi rend="italic">et</hi> al., 1998, Moutinho, 1987; Swarbrooke <hi rend="italic">et al.</hi> </s><s n="s14.17;p1.10">, 1999). </s><s n="s15.17;p1.10">Models also provide <hi rend="italic">micro-level</hi> insights into travellers' thoughts, choices, and events occurring during actual trips (Woodside <hi rend="italic">et al.</hi> </s><s n="s16.17;p1.10">, 2001). </s><s n="s17.17;p1.10">This essay begins with an introduction to <hi rend="italic">Shakespeare's Globe Theatre</hi> and evaluates the benefits of <hi rend="italic">Woodside &amp; King's</hi> consumer behaviour model in understanding future student travellers' behaviour. </s></p><p n="p2.10"><s n="s1.7;p2.10">Founded by American actor/director Sam Wanamaker, the Globe Theatre offers a unique global and local resource committed to the exploration of Shakespeare's work, and the playhouse for which he wrote, by way of education and performance. </s><s n="s2.7;p2.10">The Globe Theatre is located a short distance from Southwark Bridge in London and is open from May to September. </s><s n="s3.7;p2.10">Accessible from both the <hi rend="italic">Visit-London</hi> (<seg type="URL" n="http://www.visitlondon.com"/>) and, the Globe's interactive website (<seg type="URL" n="http://www.shakespeares-globe.org"/>), the reconstruction of the 1599 open - air playhouse, exposes visitors to the same ambience as that of 400 years ago. </s><s n="s4.7;p2.10">Visitors may attend several performances by booking gallery seating or standing as <hi rend="italic">groundlings</hi> in the yard. </s><s n="s5.7;p2.10">Moreover, guests benefit from formal and informal dining facilities, on - site and online shopping, and exhibition halls of various Shakespearean artefacts. </s><s n="s6.7;p2.10">Yet one of the more intriguing services the Globe Theatre offers is a vast selection of educative programs, taught jointly with King's College London, targeting students of all ages and nations. </s><s n="s7.7;p2.10">It would thus be reasonable to assume that this group of travellers forms a significant segment of the Globe Theatre's visitors; which may consequently be segmented by purpose of travel; namely university students seeking educative events in the performing arts and Shakespearean heritage. </s></p><p n="p3.10"><s n="s1.38;p3.10">In the past decades, progressive changes in education and tourism have seen a convergence of these industries into <hi rend="italic">educational</hi> tourism, an area recognized from both an economical and social perspective (Ritchie <hi rend="italic"> et al.</hi> </s><s n="s2.38;p3.10">, 2003). </s><s n="s3.38;p3.10">Even so, <hi rend="italic">travelling to learn</hi> is not a new concept, dating back to when Greek and Roman elites travelled to increase their understanding of the world (Ritchie <hi rend="italic"> et al.</hi> </s><s n="s4.38;p3.10">, 2003; Swarbrooke <hi rend="italic">et al.</hi> </s><s n="s5.38;p3.10">, 1999). </s><s n="s6.38;p3.10">Today, education and learning are important and recognised components of travel, and to this extent it can be argued all manner of tourism may be educational; thus, research in this broad and complex area remains minimal (Smith <hi rend="italic">et al</hi>., 1997 cited in Ritchie <hi rend="italic">et al.</hi> </s><s n="s7.38;p3.10">, 2003). </s><s n="s8.38;p3.10">Still smaller, more identifiable, market segments exist within this broad tourism field. </s><s n="s9.38;p3.10">University students are one such segment, yet a chronological definition has been a discussion topic owing to changing demographics; the traditionally accepted age limit of 15 - 25 has been replaced by 18 - 30 (Carr, 2003; Seekings, 1998). </s><s n="s10.38;p3.10">This definition has only increased the already considerable number of student travellers in the last decade, which some researchers predict will 'quadruple to 100 million by 2025' (Carr, 2003; Mintel, 2005; Smith <hi rend="italic">et al.</hi> </s><s n="s11.38;p3.10">, 1997, p. 64). </s><s n="s12.38;p3.10">The UK has witnessed increasing numbers of not just the general population entering university, but continues to be one of Europe's most successful educational destinations; owing to the global importance of the English language (Carr, 2003; Smith <hi rend="italic">et al.</hi> </s><s n="s13.38;p3.10">, 1997). </s><s n="s14.38;p3.10">Moreover, a strong correlation is evident between educational visits to-and-within the UK, and theatre attendance in such cities as London; owing to increased search for learning and enlightenment (Gilbert <hi rend="italic">et al.</hi> </s><s n="s15.38;p3.10">, 1998). </s><s n="s16.38;p3.10">In fact, the majority of visited attractions are located in the centre and south bank of London (Virdee <hi rend="italic">et al.</hi> </s><s n="s17.38;p3.10">, 2003). </s><s n="s18.38;p3.10">Even more intriguing is the steadily increasing numbers of students entering higher educations to study history and other related degrees; namely Heritage Studies (English Heritage, 2003). </s><s n="s19.38;p3.10">Despite the considerable size and growth of university students, little research has been conducted to understand this segment's needs, desires, and behaviour (Carr, 2003). </s><s n="s20.38;p3.10">However, what is known is this segment displays a range of similar educational motives as other tourists travelling to learn; subsequently illustrated in the following page (Ritchie <hi rend="italic"> et al.</hi> </s><s n="s21.38;p3.10">, 2003). </s><s n="s22.38;p3.10">Furthermore, studies of this segment have covered the <hi rend="italic">general</hi> student population relative to specific issues including hedonistic behaviour; thus, to an extent distorting the image of university student holidays (Carr, 2003). </s><s n="s23.38;p3.10">One such widely held misconception relates to expenditure, the belief being that students and younger tourists spend less than other market segments (Carr, 2003; Seekings, 1998; Smith <hi rend="italic">et al.</hi> </s><s n="s24.38;p3.10">, 1997). </s><s n="s25.38;p3.10">Arguably, trips abroad are indeed high items on a student's annual budget, and many may be price sensitive; yet they are prepared to pay what is a relatively high price for their trip because they place high value on the <hi rend="italic">experience</hi> (Seekings, 1998). </s><s n="s26.38;p3.10">In some cases a student's parents bear the cost of educational trips, while in other cases, even if rare, students in full-time employ can cover costs (Carr, 2003; Smith <hi rend="italic">et al.</hi> </s><s n="s27.38;p3.10">, 1997). </s><s n="s28.38;p3.10">In a study of British university students, Carr (2003) found that despite living in financial debt, this did not deter students from local and global Travel. </s><s n="s29.38;p3.10">This supports the theory that students are gradually more accustomed to borrowing money, be it form banks, student loans, or relatives (Davies <hi rend="italic">et al.</hi> </s><s n="s30.38;p3.10">, 1995 cited in Carr, 2003). </s><s n="s31.38;p3.10">In fact, 2002 estimates saw an average student debt of £10,000 upon graduation (Anon., 2002a, cited in Carr, 2003). </s><s n="s32.38;p3.10">Nonetheless, students tend to stay longer and have higher total average spending than average adults (Seekings, 1998). </s><s n="s33.38;p3.10">Though preferring independent travel, some students travel as part of a degree or by ERASMUS and other such language exchange programmes (Carr, 2003). </s><s n="s34.38;p3.10">Technology has also impacted the segment by way of <hi rend="italic">virtual</hi> and <hi rend="italic">distance</hi> <hi rend="italic">education</hi>; offering the benefits of travel without the leaving home or the university (Carr, 2003; Holley, 2002). </s><s n="s35.38;p3.10">Studies show however, that while students believe such virtual excursions provide useful learning opportunities they can not, and should not, replace real excursions (Spicer <hi rend="italic">et al.</hi> </s><s n="s36.38;p3.10">2001 cited in Carr, 2003). </s><s n="s37.38;p3.10">In fact, students use formal and informal <hi rend="italic">holiday</hi> <hi rend="italic">information</hi> sources; that is, they rely on friends, family, and personal experience more than the web, travel agencies, and other tourism media (Carr, 2003). </s><s n="s38.38;p3.10">In summary, despite rising monetary issues, the number of university students is increasing and an eventual aim of tourism managers should be to better understand this major segment. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_3049c-fig.001"/><p n="p4.10"><s n="s1.1;p4.10">The model proposed by <hi rend="italic">Woodside &amp; King</hi> (2001) is a depictive sequence of mental and observable sequences which consumers consider when buying and using several interrelated products or services; which in some cases may lead to further purchases. </s></p><p n="p5.10"><s n="s1.12;p5.10">As subsequently shown, the model entails three major boxes, which are further subdivided into nineteen variables related to consumer travel and tourism purchase-consumption frameworks. </s><s n="s2.12;p5.10">The eight variables in Box 1 influence thinking and planning actions prior and during travel; that is influence of family, friends, peers and groups have on a consumer's information gathering, problem solving, and overall decision making (Woodside <hi rend="italic">et al.</hi> </s><s n="s3.12;p5.10">, 2001). </s><s n="s4.12;p5.10">The eight variables within Box 2 relate to specific destinations and/or actions that make up the actual trip; in other words, the readily available choices to travellers including attractions, lodgings, and dining establishments (Woodside <hi rend="italic">et al.</hi> </s><s n="s5.12;p5.10">, 2001). </s><s n="s6.12;p5.10">Box 3 is a vital <hi rend="italic">evaluative</hi> stage of the framework relating to event - specific and global - specific evaluations, and possible implications, expressed upon concluding travel experiences (Woodside <hi rend="italic">et al.</hi> </s><s n="s7.12;p5.10">, 2001). </s><s n="s8.12;p5.10">Indeed such findings form the <hi rend="italic">Feedback Loop</hi> connecting Box 3 to Box 1; an indication of the level of consumer satisfaction and probable intentions to return to the destination (Woodside <hi rend="italic">et al.</hi> </s><s n="s9.12;p5.10">, 2001). </s><s n="s10.12;p5.10">Throughout the model, various direct and indirect predictors have interrelated affects on tourists' choice decisions; hence linking arrows imply <hi rend="italic">direct</hi> influences, with multiple-step linkages implying <hi rend="italic">indirect</hi> influences (Woodside <hi rend="italic">et al.</hi> </s><s n="s11.12;p5.10">, 2001). </s><s n="s12.12;p5.10">Overall, the framework 'shows three stages of pre-trip, during - trip, and after - trip information exposure, comprehension-acceptance, and decision to buy or reject (Woodside <hi rend="italic">et al</hi>., 2001, p.10). </s></p><p n="p6.10"><s n="s1.3;p6.10">The question arises how to use the model to understand desired segments; in this case, how can the Globe improve its understating of university students. </s><s n="s2.3;p6.10">One such area of application includes the ability of the host-country and institution to provide desirable quality of reputation and lifestyle; deemed important incentives, or <hi rend="italic">pull</hi> factors, to university students (Mazzarol <hi rend="italic">et al.</hi> </s><s n="s3.3;p6.10">, 2002) and the subsequent topic of Box 2. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_3049c-fig.002"><head>Framework of Purchase-Consumption System Applied to Leisure Travel Behaviour Woodside, A.G. and King R.I. (2001) 'An Updated Model of Travel and Tourism Purchase-Consumption Systems', <hi rend="italic">Journal of Travel &amp; Tourism Marketing</hi> , Volume 10, Issue No. 1, p.6 </head></figure><p n="p7.10"><s n="s1.17;p7.10">While limited research on university students may complicate the application of a behaviour model, under the assumption that such travellers search for similar motives as other educational tourists, the task is not impossible. </s><s n="s2.17;p7.10">To begin with, the analysis suggests England's reputable and educative characteristics; continue to attract both local and global students. </s><s n="s3.17;p7.10">Furthermore, as mentioned, the city capital of London is considered among the country's major hubs and tourist destinations. </s><s n="s4.17;p7.10">Thus <hi rend="italic">Mode/Route to Destination</hi>, and the Globe Theatre, may be gained by both local and global university students by various methods of transportation; generally speaking London is accessible by land, sea, and air. </s><s n="s5.17;p7.10">Similarly, <hi rend="italic">a</hi> choice of <hi rend="italic"> Mode/Routes in and Around</hi> the city facilitate the means for students to reach the Globe Theatre; which in fact provides web-links to <hi rend="italic">Transport for London</hi> (<seg type="URL" n="http://www.tfl.gov.uk/tfl"/>) allowing students to independently plan their own transportation. </s><s n="s6.17;p7.10">Even so, there is only <hi rend="italic">one</hi> Shakespeare's Globe Theatre which inevitably limits students' <hi rend="italic">Destination Options/Choices</hi>; thus, the segment's propensity of seeking <hi rend="italic">cultural</hi> and <hi rend="italic">social</hi> experiences is restricted. </s><s n="s7.17;p7.10">Still the Globe Theatre offers a variety of educational <hi rend="italic">Activity Choices</hi>. </s><s n="s8.17;p7.10">From interactive lectures and workshops, to fencing classes, to performances and exhibitions; this vast selection can effectively enable the Theatre to meet the <hi rend="italic">social</hi>, <hi rend="italic">cultural</hi>, <hi rend="italic">physical</hi>, and to some extent <hi rend="italic">fantasy</hi> motives earlier mentioned. </s><s n="s9.17;p7.10">The Globe Shop could further add to the experience, albeit minimally, by offering <hi rend="italic">Self-gifts and other Purchases</hi> including Globe music CDs and Performances on DVD or books; thus not only providing a reflective gift with which to remember the trip, but a cultural "proof" of visit as an <hi rend="italic">Ego-enhancer</hi>. </s><s n="s10.17;p7.10">While three classes of on-site dining facilities meet the <hi rend="italic">social</hi> and <hi rend="italic">cultural</hi> motives sought by students, the Globe Theatre's lack of information on <hi rend="italic">Dining Out Choices</hi> available in London impacts the overall experience. </s><s n="s11.17;p7.10">On the one hand students may insight into English cuisine and table-etiquette, yet the cultural dining experience is thus confined. </s><s n="s12.17;p7.10">Ultimately, despite the provision of various activities, this does not mean the Globe Theatre would be the main attraction to students. </s><s n="s13.17;p7.10">Once again the propensity to seek further knowledge through travel would impact the <hi rend="italic">Attraction Choices</hi> available in the destination, possibly making the Globe Theatre one of many stopovers. </s><s n="s14.17;p7.10">In addition, while not as relevant as other variables, the Globe Theatre's lack of <hi rend="italic">Accommodation Choices</hi> could seriously impact the possibility of attracting students; particularly overseas students wishing to enrol in the theatre's one-year MA courses. </s><s n="s15.17;p7.10">Overall it is evident that the application of the proposed consumer behaviour model can generate an increasing awareness of what could motivate potential students to visit the Globe Theatre. </s><s n="s16.17;p7.10">Furthermore, the model indicates possible existing limitations which can positively or negatively impact the student segment. </s><s n="s17.17;p7.10">To some extent it can be argued that in some cases the affects of such limitations are only assumptions, and yet this raises a further issue relative to future trends; that is to say, what behavioural trends can be expected from university students in the next ten years. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_3049c-fig.003"/><p n="p8.10"><s n="s1.15;p8.10">It is widely recognized that the pace of societal change impacts trends, be they economical, social, or lifestyle, and inevitably these trends impact tourism and other businesses (ETC, 2005; Middleton <hi rend="italic">et al.</hi> </s><s n="s2.15;p8.10">, 2001). </s><s n="s3.15;p8.10">Authors agree one trend is consumers becoming better educated and interested in continuing education by way of further schooling or educative tourism (ETC, 2005; Middleton <hi rend="italic">et al.</hi> </s><s n="s4.15;p8.10">, 2001; Ritchie <hi rend="italic"> et al.</hi> </s><s n="s5.15;p8.10">, 2003). </s><s n="s6.15;p8.10">Yet this behavioural trend can be interrelated to other trends thus making it nearly impossible to isolate development into a single element (ETC, 2005). </s><s n="s7.15;p8.10">As suggested, an accurate definition of university students has yet to be formulated due to changing <hi rend="italic">social environments</hi>; and so it is advisable for the Globe Theatre to review its "student" target market (Ritchie <hi rend="italic">et al.</hi> </s><s n="s8.15;p8.10">, 2003). </s><s n="s9.15;p8.10">As depicted in the following table, such changes have broadened the definition of students to include pension-able adults and professionals; thus, targeting "older" generations, empty-nesters, and DINK couples, could increase the appeal of the Globe Theatre to a broader, educational tourism market. </s><s n="s10.15;p8.10">The additional impact of <hi rend="italic">technology</hi> and the web is also expected to grow, increasing demand for travel information, online bookings, and overall computer literacy (ETC, 2005; Middleton <hi rend="italic">et al.</hi> </s><s n="s11.15;p8.10">, 2001; Holley, 2002). </s><s n="s12.15;p8.10">As suggested, students remain unsure on the benefits of virtual seminars and distance learning. </s><s n="s13.15;p8.10">While the Globe Theatre provides such programmes, stressing the <hi rend="italic">social</hi> and <hi rend="italic">cultural</hi> benefits of more dynamic teachings could increase the attractiveness of learning through travel. </s><s n="s14.15;p8.10">Transportation in turn is developing faster, economical, and direct travel to desired destinations; and yet, road congestion and reduced coach travel is expected to be problematic (ETC, 2005). </s><s n="s15.15;p8.10">Although, the Globe Theatre is accessible by various modes, it would thus be suitable for the theatre to facilitate tourists' travel with suggestive comments on preferable modes of transport; namely trains, and the underground. </s></p><p n="p9.10"><s n="s1.13;p9.10">In order to meet the predicted behavioural trend of increased university student enrolment, the Globe Theatre would need to further improve on the Model implications previously indicated. </s><s n="s2.13;p9.10">In tackling the issue of <hi rend="italic">Destination Options/Choices</hi> it would be advisable for the Globe Theatre to cooperatively promote Shakespearean performing arts with other cities, including Plymouth and Stratford-Upon-Avon. </s><s n="s3.13;p9.10">Such a cooperative venture would increase the <hi rend="italic">cultural</hi> and <hi rend="italic">social</hi> elements available to students, while at the same time expanding into other student markets in other cities. </s><s n="s4.13;p9.10">Providing more <hi rend="italic">Dining Out Choices</hi> is also recommendable, as this could increase students' perception of the Globe's efforts to meet the <hi rend="italic">cultural</hi> motives for educational travel. </s><s n="s5.13;p9.10">Moreover, publicising dining locations throughout London could generate increased awareness of the Globe Theatre; that is by way of <hi rend="italic">socializing</hi>, students would spread word of mouth to locals and foreigners. </s><s n="s6.13;p9.10">Similar impacts could be witnessed by way of providing further <hi rend="italic">Attraction Choices</hi>. </s><s n="s7.13;p9.10">A recommendation would therefore be to form a marketing alliance with other <hi rend="italic">cultural</hi> heritage sites in the vicinity such as St. Paul's Cathedral, Tate Modern, and Tower Bridge. </s><s n="s8.13;p9.10">This could increase the perceived educational attractiveness of both the Southwark area and the efforts of the Globe Theatre in facilitating students' learning opportunities. </s><s n="s9.13;p9.10">While it is true the Globe Theatre's main purpose is to provide an educational experience through theatrical performances, the lack of accommodations could quite possibly affect students' perceptions. </s><s n="s10.13;p9.10">A final recommendation would hence be to provide information on neighbouring lodging facilities including hotels, hostels, and guest houses. </s><s n="s11.13;p9.10">This would benefit the Globe Theatre in the long run, assuming the growing number of university students would require somewhere to stay if enrolled in a year-long MA, or short period programme. </s><s n="s12.13;p9.10">Not only would the students gain a <hi rend="italic">social</hi> and <hi rend="italic">cultural</hi> experience by interacting together, they could learn to habituate themselves with living in England, albeit for a short period of time. </s><s n="s13.13;p9.10">An illustrative interpretation of such proposed recommendations is subsequently included on the final page of this essay. </s></p><p n="p10.10"><s n="s1.10;p10.10">As already noted, the study of consumer behaviour ultimately seeks to gain information to enforce the comprehensive understanding of tourists' decision - making processes. </s><s n="s2.10;p10.10">Such information ultimately benefits both the political and tourism aspects of a destination by way of facilitating, and improving, industry planning (Woodside <hi rend="italic">et al.</hi> </s><s n="s3.10;p10.10">, 2001). </s><s n="s4.10;p10.10">Moreover, by way of predictive consumer behaviour models, marketers may study the intricate relationships of consumer behaviour on a micro level; the theory being the relative findings, once overlaid on to a macro level, aid in developing more effective marketing to desired segments (Woodside <hi rend="italic">et al.</hi> </s><s n="s5.10;p10.10">, 2001). </s><s n="s6.10;p10.10">As discussed, the aim of the essay was to provide an evaluative extract as to how the successful use of a consumer behaviour model, could help to enhance a tourism manager's understanding of a particular segment. </s><s n="s7.10;p10.10">In the case of the Shakespeare's Globe Theatre the goal of providing an overall educational experience, can be positively linked to the university student segment. </s><s n="s8.10;p10.10">As indicated however, the lack of <hi rend="italic">specific</hi> behavioural information regarding students may complicate the relevance and overall findings of such a study. </s><s n="s9.10;p10.10">Nevertheless, the findings would suggest that in an effort to better meet the predicted behavioural trends of a growing <hi rend="italic">education</hi> inclined tourism market, the theatre stands to generate considerable profit. </s><s n="s10.10;p10.10">With world tourism predicted to grow to include added elements relating to the arts, culture, and history; the Globe Theatre looks set to gain a significant advantage, by way of effective marketing, and in becoming a component in a complex decision-making process. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_3049c-fig.004"><head>Framework of Purchase-Consumption System Applied to <hi rend="italic">Shakespeare's Globe Theatre</hi> Woodside, A.G. and King R.I. (2001) 'An Updated Model of Travel and Tourism Purchase-Consumption Systems', <hi rend="italic">Journal of Travel &amp; Tourism Marketing</hi> , Volume 10, Issue No. 1, p.6 </head></figure></div1></body><back><div1 type="bibliography"><head rend="bold">Bibliography:</head><p>Anonymous (2002a) Student debt triples in three years. <hi rend="italic">The Guardian (online accessed 16/5/02)</hi></p><p>Carr, N. (2003) 'University and College Students' Tourism'. In: Ritchie, B.W., Carr, N., and Cooper, C. (Eds.) (2003) <hi rend="italic">Managing Educational Tourism</hi>. Clevedon: Channel View Publications, Chapters 5, p. 181-225</p><p>Chisnall, P.M. (1995) <hi rend="italic">Consumer Behaviour</hi> (3<hi rend="sup">rd</hi> Ed.). London: McGraw - Hill.</p><p>Cooper, C., Fletcher, J., Wanhill, S., Gilbert, D., and Shepherd, R. (1998) <hi rend="italic">Tourism: Principles and Practice</hi> (2<hi rend="sup">nd</hi> Ed.). Harlow: Longman.</p><p>Davies, E. and Lea, S. (1995) 'Student attitudes to student debt', <hi rend="italic">Journal of Economic Psychology</hi>, Vol. 16, No.4, pp. 663-679.</p><p>English Heritage (2003) <hi rend="italic">Heritage Counts 2003: The Stage of England's Historic Environment</hi>. London: English Heritage.</p><p>ETC Website (2005). <hi rend="italic">European Travel Commission: Tourism Trends for Europe</hi> [online] Brussels: ETC. Available from: <seg type="URL" n="http://www.etc-corporate.org/modules.php?name=Content&amp;pa=showpage&amp;pid=100&amp;ac=5"/> [Accessed 2<hi rend="sup">nd</hi> December 2005]</p><p>Gilbert, D. and Lizotte, M. (1998) 'Tourism and the Performing Arts', <hi rend="italic">Travel &amp; Tourism Analyst</hi>, No.1, pp. 82-96. </p><p>Goeldner, C.R., Ritchie, J.R.B., and McIntosh, R. (2000) <hi rend="italic">Tourism: Principles, Practices, Philosophies</hi>. New York: John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd.</p><p>Holley, D. (2002) 'Which room is the virtual seminar in please?', <hi rend="italic">Education &amp; Training</hi>, Vol. 44, No.3, pp. 112-121.</p><p>Hudson, S. and Gilbert, D. (2001) 'Tourism Constraints: the Neglected Dimension of Consumer Behaviour Research'. In: Mazanec, J.A., Crouch, G.I., Ritchie, J.R.B., and Woodside, A.G. (Eds.) (2001) <hi rend="italic">Consumer Psychology of Tourism, hospitality and leisure</hi>. Wallingford: CABI, Chapter 8, p.137-154. </p><p>Leisen, B. (2001) 'Image segmentation: the case of a tourism destination', <hi rend="italic">Journal of Services Marketing</hi>, Vol. 15, No.1, pp. 49-66. </p><p>Mazzarol, T. and Soutar, G.N. (2002) 'Push-pull factors influencing international student destination choice', <hi rend="italic">International Journal of Educational Management</hi>, Vol. 16, No.2, pp. 82-90.</p><p>Middleton, V.T.C. and Clarke, J. (2001) <hi rend="italic">Marketing in Travel and Tourism</hi>. (3<hi rend="sup">rd</hi> Ed.) Oxford: Elsevier Butterworth-Heinemann.</p><p>Mintel (2001) 'Overland Expeditions', <hi rend="italic">Mintel International Group Ltd.</hi>, November. Available from: <seg type="URL" n="http://reports.mintel.com/sinatra/reports/search_results/show&amp;&amp;type=RCItem&amp;page=0&amp;noaccess_page=0/display/id=2095"/> [Accessed 6<hi rend="sup">th</hi> November, 2005].</p><p>Moutinho, L. (1987) 'Consumer Behaviour in Tourism', <hi rend="italic">European Journal of Marketing</hi>, Vol. 21, No.10, pp. 5-44. </p><p>Ritchie, B.W., Carr, N., and Cooper, C. (Eds.) (2003) <hi rend="italic">Managing Educational Tourism</hi>. Clevedon: Channel View Publications, Chapters 1, 2, &amp; 5</p><p>Seekings, J. (1998) 'The Youth Travel Market', <hi rend="italic">Travel &amp; Tourism Analyst</hi>, No.5, pp. 35-55.</p><p>Shakespeare's Globe Website (2005). <hi rend="italic">Shakespeare's Globe Theatre</hi> [online]. Available from: <seg type="URL" n="http://www.shakespeares-globe.org/"/> [Accessed 2<hi rend="sup">nd</hi> November 2005]</p><p>Smith, C. and Jerner, P. (1997) 'Educational Tourism', <hi rend="italic">Travel &amp; Tourism Analyst</hi>, No.3, pp. 60-75. </p><p>Snehota, I. (2004) 'Perspectives and theories of market'. In: Håkansson, H., Harrison, D., and Waluszewski, A. (2004) <hi rend="italic">Rethinking Marketing: Developing A New Understanding of Markets</hi>. Chichester: John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd., Chapter 2, p. 15-32 </p><p>Solomon, M., Bamossy, G., and Askegaard, S. (1999) <hi rend="italic">Consumer Behaviour: A European Perspective</hi>. London: Prentice Hall.</p><p>Spicer, J. and Stratford, J. (2001) 'Student perceptions of a virtual field trip to replace a real field trip', <hi rend="italic">Journal of Computer Assisted Learning</hi>, Vol. 17, p.345-354</p><p>Swarbrooke, J. and Horner, S. (1999) <hi rend="italic">Consumer behaviour in tourism</hi>. Oxford: Butterworth - Heinemann.</p><p>Transport for London Website (2005). <hi rend="italic">TfL Homepage</hi> [online] London: Greater London Authority. Available from: <seg type="URL" n="http://www.tfl.gov.uk/tfl/"/> [Accessed 2<hi rend="sup">nd</hi> December 2005]</p><p>Usunier, J.C. and Lee, J.A. (2005) <hi rend="italic">Marketing Across Cultures</hi> (4<hi rend="sup">th</hi> Ed.). Harlow: Prentice Hall.</p><p>Virdee, D. and Williams, T. (2003) <hi rend="italic">Focus on London 2003</hi>. Norwich: HMSO.</p><p>Visit London Website (2005). <hi rend="italic">Directory - Shakespeare's Globe Theatre</hi> [online] London: Visit London Limited. Available from: <seg type="URL" n="http://www.visitlondon.com/directory/details/7X05609K.html"/> [Accessed 2<hi rend="sup">nd</hi> December 2005]</p><p>Woodside, A.G. and King, R.I. (2001) 'An Updated Model of Travel and Tourism Purchase-Consumption Systems', <hi rend="italic">Journal of Travel &amp; Tourism Marketing</hi>, Vol. 10, No.1, pp. 3-26. </p></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
