<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_3052d" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Coursework 1</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">The document has a title page which contains:
document title
title part</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">3</p><p n="date">2005-11</p><p n="module title">Computer Graphics</p><p n="module code">U08181</p><p n="genre family">Design specification</p><p n="discipline">Computer Science</p><p n="disciplinary group">PS</p><p n="grade">D</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">1439</p><p n="number of s-units">74</p><p n="number of p">29</p><p n="number of tables">0</p><p n="number of figures">1</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">1</p><p n="number of lists">0</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">12</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">19.4</p><p n="average s-units per p">2.6</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">m</p><p n="year of birth">1985</p><p n="first language">French</p><p n="education">OSa</p><p n="course">Computing</p><p n="student ID">3052</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><titlePart rend="italic"><name type="student name"/> Student number: <name type="student ID"/></titlePart><titlePart rend="italic">Computer Graphics (U08181)</titlePart><docTitle><titlePart rend="italic">Coursework 1</titlePart></docTitle><titlePart rend="italic">4th November 2005</titlePart></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold italic">Story Board:</head><div2><head rend="italic">Scene description:</head><p n="p1.29"><s n="s1.1;p1.29">The scene is composed by several static elements: the sun, the sky, the mountains, the land, the house, the trees (a forest), the road, the path road (from the road to the house) and the flowers. </s></p><p n="p2.29"><s n="s1.2;p2.29">Several dynamics elements interact together in this scene by using it. </s><s n="s2.2;p2.29">These dynamics elements are: the characters (the postman, the girl and the husband) and the postman's car. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="italic">Story Board:</head><p n="p3.29"><s n="s1.1;p3.29">This story is made by 6 mains steps: </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p4.29"><s n="s1.1;p4.29">First of all, the car arrives from the right of the screen and stops in front of the path road. </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p5.29"><s n="s1.1;p5.29">Then, the postman comes out of the car (the postman is on the profile side) and walks to the house through the path road and stops in front of the house door. </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p6.29"><s n="s1.3;p6.29">Then he pushes down the bell button and waits for someone open the door; a woman opens the door and comes just in front of the postman. </s><s n="s2.3;p6.29">They look for each other in their eyes and they fall in love together (we guess that because red heart is in their eyes). </s><s n="s3.3;p6.29">Then, they enter in the girl's house and close the door. </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p7.29"><s n="s1.1;p7.29">A zoom on the bedroom window is done and some hearts get out from the window. </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p8.29"><s n="s1.1;p8.29">After that, the girl's husband walks to the house through the road and the path road, and then enters in the house (then the hearts which come from the window disappear). </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p9.29"><s n="s1.1;p9.29">In the end, the husband throws the postman through the door (the postman is then on the face side). </s></p><p n="p10.29"><s n="s1.1;p10.29">A graphic story board is drawn down below, </s></p><figure id="BAWE_3052d-fig.001"/></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold italic">How the story board is translated to a SVG animation:</head><p n="p11.29"><s n="s1.7;p11.29">First of all, I have drawn each static element on a paper in order to have a first idea about each shape. </s><s n="s2.7;p11.29">Then I have built these elements on SVG using quadratic curves, line, circle, ellipse, etc...using one svg file per shape. </s><s n="s3.7;p11.29">Each shape was grouped in a <hi rend="italic">&lt;g></hi> element. </s><s n="s4.7;p11.29">When every shape was drawn with SVG, I have assembled them in one svg file. </s><s n="s5.7;p11.29">Each element is defined in a <hi rend="italic">&lt;defs></hi> tag and instanced with the <hi rend="italic">&lt;use></hi> tag in order to use it in the animation. </s><s n="s6.7;p11.29">Finally, when each element is placed in the scene, I can add the different animation in order to produce the same which is described in the story board. </s><s n="s7.7;p11.29">In this part, I will explain how each element is translate in SVG (globally) and how the animation is made, linked together etc... </s></p><div2><head rend="italic">Static element:</head><p n="p12.29"><s n="s1.3;p12.29">The main idea of the architecture of the SVG code is to define each static element (including the postman, girl, husband and the car) in a <hi rend="italic">&lt;defs></hi> tag and then, and then to use the <hi rend="italic">&lt;use></hi> tag to use this element. </s><s n="s2.3;p12.29">The schema below explain globally how is structured the SVG file. </s><s n="s3.3;p12.29">Obviously, each tag in the SVG file is identified by a different id, </s></p><p n="p13.29"><s n="s1.1;p13.29"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_3052d-form.001"/> </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p14.29"><s n="s1.6;p14.29"><hi rend="bold italic">The car:</hi> A <hi rend="italic">&lt;defs></hi> tag is included in the car definition in order to define every linear gradient used in the car. </s><s n="s2.6;p14.29">There is 4 linear gradient: one for the window, one for the car body, one for the 'Royal Mail" text and a last for the wheels. </s><s n="s3.6;p14.29">The wheel is also include in a <hi rend="italic">&lt;defs></hi> tag because there is two wheels for this car and it's useful to define a wheel and instance twice in a different place (different x,y). </s><s n="s4.6;p14.29">The <hi rend="italic">&lt;path></hi> tag is used in order to define the car body, the door etc... </s><s n="s5.6;p14.29">Obviously, some <hi rend="italic">&lt;ellipse>,&lt;circle>,...</hi> </s><s n="s6.6;p14.29">tags is used in order to define the light etc... </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p15.29"><s n="s1.5;p15.29"><hi rend="bold italic">The house: </hi>The global form of the house is defined by a <hi rend="italic">&lt;path></hi> tag. </s><s n="s2.5;p15.29">Several clip path are used to define some area (for example for the window etc...). </s><s n="s3.5;p15.29">Two textures (jpg files) are used in order to fill the wall of the house and the roof. </s><s n="s4.5;p15.29">These textures are define in a <hi rend="italic">&lt;image></hi> tag and the texture area is define in a clip path tag. </s><s n="s5.5;p15.29">If an element is used several times (like the windows), it's define in a <hi rend="italic">&lt;defs></hi> and <hi rend="italic">&lt;g></hi> tags and use with a different scale in order to create different forms. </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p16.29"><s n="s1.5;p16.29"><hi rend="bold italic">The Postman:</hi> In order to draw the postman, some similar methods mentions above are used. </s><s n="s2.5;p16.29">However, two side of the postman is needed: profile and face side. </s><s n="s3.5;p16.29">So, the both are described in two different groups. </s><s n="s4.5;p16.29">Two different postman is made: one which is static, and a second which is walking (the legs are moving). </s><s n="s5.5;p16.29">Each one will be used in different case (when the postman walks or not). </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p17.29"><s n="s1.2;p17.29"><hi rend="bold italic">The girl and the husband:</hi> These forms are very similar than the husband, using different colours. </s><s n="s2.2;p17.29">For some elements (like the arm) which are the same for every character, the definition (described in the postman definition) is used and only the colour is changed. </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p18.29"><s n="s1.5;p18.29"><hi rend="bold italic">The landscape:</hi> Two mains rectangle are defined: one for the sky, a second for the land. </s><s n="s2.5;p18.29">Each element is drawn. </s><s n="s3.5;p18.29">Only one mountain is define and three are instanced using several transformation in order to create three "different" but similar mountains. </s><s n="s4.5;p18.29">The same method is used to create the forest and the flowers (one tree/flower is drawn and several are instanced). </s><s n="s5.5;p18.29">The sun is made with a <hi rend="italic">radialGradient</hi> effect. </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p19.29"><s n="s1.3;p19.29"><hi rend="bold italic">The road:</hi> The road is defined by a rectangle (several rectangle define the white road line). </s><s n="s2.3;p19.29">A path defines the path road. </s><s n="s3.3;p19.29">Some flowers are placed around the path road. </s></p><p n="p20.29"><s n="s1.1;p20.29">Then, each element can be used with the <hi rend="italic">&lt;use></hi> tag and the <hi rend="italic">transform</hi> attribute. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="italic">The animation:</head><p n="p21.29"><s n="s1.2;p21.29">The SVG file can be separated in two parts. </s><s n="s2.2;p21.29">The first part is the definitions parts (which we explain above) and the second part is the one where we instance each element. </s></p><p n="p22.29"><s n="s1.2;p22.29">Each animation concerning the place of an element in the scene (e.g.: x, y, width,...attributes) are made in the second part (so the <hi rend="italic">animate</hi> tag will carry out on the <hi rend="italic">&lt;use></hi> part), whereas when an animation has to change an element which is included in another element (e.g.: a wheel is included in the car), this animation is made in the definition part (the first part). </s><s n="s2.2;p22.29">For example, when the postman is walking, the legs are animated in the first part whereas the postman position (x and y attribute) are animate in the second part. </s></p><p n="p23.29"><s n="s1.6;p23.29">Each animation is defined by duration. </s><s n="s2.6;p23.29">However, the beginning of each animation is not defined by a time (for example: <hi rend="italic">begin="5s"</hi>) but by an event (in general, this event is the end (or the beginning) of another animation (+ n second)). </s><s n="s3.6;p23.29">So, only the first animation is defined by <hi rend="italic">" begin='0s' "</hi> and the others are launched by the end of another. </s><s n="s4.6;p23.29">This method is useful because we can change the duration of one animation (or more) without change all the begin attribute. </s><s n="s5.6;p23.29">Effectively, if we change the duration of an animation, every animation which comes after will be moved in the time. </s><s n="s6.6;p23.29">However, with this method, we don't care about the beginning of the others animations, because they may be launched after the end of the previous (or another). </s></p><p n="p24.29"><s n="s1.1;p24.29">The different animation: </s></p><p n="p25.29"><s n="s1.2;p25.29">The car motion: a simple <hi rend="italic">animate</hi> tag is used which animates the x attribute of the car. </s><s n="s2.2;p25.29">The wheel turn in the same time by using an <hi rend="italic">animateTransform</hi> tag (which is defined in the first part of the file) in order to rotate the wheel. </s></p><p n="p26.29"><s n="s1.5;p26.29">The postman/girl/husband motion: the legs motions (and arms motions) are defined in the first part of the SVG file by an <hi rend="italic">animateTransform</hi> tag (rotate) and the translation of the human (postman/girl/husband) is made is the second part. </s><s n="s2.5;p26.29">The postman/husband translation is made with an <hi rend="italic">animationMotion</hi> tag, so they can follow a path. </s><s n="s3.5;p26.29">These characters can be hidden if they are in the house. </s><s n="s4.5;p26.29">This effect is done with the <hi rend="italic">clip-path</hi> attribute. </s><s n="s5.5;p26.29">When the postman (and the husband) walks on the path road, 3 animation are in the same time: one for move the character, another for move the legs and the last one for scale the character (because the house is far from the road. </s></p><p n="p27.29"><s n="s1.1;p27.29">The heart and eyes animation: these animations are made in the first part of the SVG file, by using <hi rend="italic">animateTransform</hi> (scale) and <hi rend="italic">animate</hi> (CSS attribute, opacity) tags. </s></p><p n="p28.29"><s n="s1.1;p28.29">The beginning and end gradient: A big rectangle has been created and become transparent (or opaque) at the beginning/end of this animation. </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold italic">Critical assessment of this animation:</head><p n="p29.29"><s n="s1.3;p29.29">I think that some elements are not very detailed. </s><s n="s2.3;p29.29">For example, every "human" are the character, with a different colour. </s><s n="s3.3;p29.29">However, I think the different zoom add to the animation "a life", like in a TV animation. </s></p></div1></body><back/></text></TEI.2>
