<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_3052c" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Coursework 4 -Project Title: DirSync</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">The document has a title page which contains:
document title
title part</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">3</p><p n="date">2005-12</p><p n="module title">Systems Programming</p><p n="module code">U08052</p><p n="genre family">Design specification</p><p n="discipline">Computer Science</p><p n="disciplinary group">PS</p><p n="grade">D</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">1930</p><p n="number of s-units">144</p><p n="number of p">73</p><p n="number of tables">0</p><p n="number of figures">1</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">21</p><p n="number of lists">1</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">17</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">13.4</p><p n="average s-units per p">2.0</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">m</p><p n="year of birth">1985</p><p n="first language">French</p><p n="education">OSa</p><p n="course">Computing</p><p n="student ID">3052</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><titlePart rend="italic"><name type="student name"/> Student number: <name type="student ID"/></titlePart><titlePart rend="italic">Systems Programming (U08051) Coursework 4</titlePart><titlePart rend="italic">5th December 2005</titlePart><docTitle><titlePart rend="italic">Project Title: DirSync</titlePart></docTitle></titlePage><div1 type="toc" n="2"><head rend="bold italic">Contents</head><p/></div1></front><body><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold italic">How does the program work ? </head><p n="p1.73"><s n="s1.3;p1.73">The program works like it's explain in the coursework 3. </s><s n="s2.3;p1.73">However, some modifications have been added. </s><s n="s3.3;p1.73">The main idea is that, one (or more) server is running one (or more) distant machine and a client which will manage the synchronisation is running on the local machine (the machine where the user is). </s></p><p n="p2.73"><s n="s1.4;p2.73">The program contains a client side and one (or more) server side. </s><s n="s2.4;p2.73">However, the code is in the same file: <hi rend="italic">dirsync.c</hi>. </s><s n="s3.4;p2.73">So, when we want to launch a server (or daemon) on a machine, we have to add an option in the command line which is called <hi rend="italic">'- d'</hi> which means <hi rend="italic">'daemon'</hi>. </s><s n="s4.4;p2.73">Thus the daemon is running and waits for request from a client. </s></p><p n="p3.73"><s n="s1.3;p3.73">When we want to launch a client, we have to precise if the source and/or the destination directories are distant. </s><s n="s2.3;p3.73">This is done with the option in the command line <hi rend="italic">'-w'</hi>. </s><s n="s3.3;p3.73">Four cases are available: </s></p><p n="p4.73"><s n="s1.1;p4.73"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_3052c-form.001"/> </s></p><p n="p5.73"><s n="s1.1;p5.73">More details about <hi rend="italic">'-w'</hi> option are in the coursework 3 documentation. </s></p><p n="p6.73"><s n="s1.1;p6.73">If the user specifies another case with the option <hi rend="italic"> - w</hi>, he's informed and the program stops. </s></p><p n="p7.73"><s n="s1.1;p7.73">If the option <hi rend="italic"> - d</hi> is specified, then no other option can be added because it's the daemon. </s></p><p n="p8.73"><s n="s1.1;p8.73">The default port number is <hi rend="italic">1985</hi> for the daemon. </s></p><p n="p9.73"><s n="s1.5;p9.73">The communication between the client and the server(s) are done with socket. </s><s n="s2.5;p9.73">When the client (the one who manage the synchronisation) needs information about a directory which is distant, it sends a request to the daemon which is running on this distant machine this information. </s><s n="s3.5;p9.73">This request can be something like <hi rend="italic">"send me this information"</hi> or like <hi rend="italic">"do that please"</hi>. </s><s n="s4.5;p9.73">So, a list of request is defined. </s><s n="s5.5;p9.73">These requests (instruction) can be, </s></p><p n="p10.73"><s n="s1.1;p10.73"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_3052c-form.002"/> </s></p><p n="p11.73"><s n="s1.4;p11.73">Every instruction has to contain 16 characters exactly (16 is defines by the constant <hi rend="italic">INSTRUCTION_SIZE</hi>). </s><s n="s2.4;p11.73">This is I order to simplify the sending with socket. </s><s n="s3.4;p11.73">So, when an instruction contains less than 16 characters, the char '_' is added at the end. </s><s n="s4.4;p11.73">For example, "<hi rend="italic">openfiledest"</hi> is <hi rend="italic">"openfiledest____"</hi>. </s></p><p n="p12.73"><s n="s1.4;p12.73">The daemon knows what to do according to which instruction is received. </s><s n="s2.4;p12.73">Indeed, each case is treated in the <hi rend="italic">dirSyncDaemon()</hi> function. </s><s n="s3.4;p12.73">When an instruction is received, the daemon and the client know and follow the same protocol. </s><s n="s4.4;p12.73">For example, if the instruction <hi rend="italic">"mkdirectory"</hi> is received, this protocol is followed: </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p13.73"><s n="s1.1;p13.73">The client: sends the size of the path name, then send the path name </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p14.73"><s n="s1.1;p14.73">The daemon: receives the size of the path name, then receive the path name, afterward the daemon create the directory. </s></p><p n="p15.73"><s n="s1.1;p15.73">So, each time the client needs information (or want the server to do something), an instruction is sent and is treated by the server like above. </s></p><p n="p16.73"><s n="s1.1;p16.73">So, we have to launch this command in this case: the source is distant (on the 10.10.10.16 machine), the destination is local: </s></p><list type="ordered"><item>On the 10.10.10.16 machine: <hi rend="italic">./dirsync - d</hi></item><item>On the local machine: <hi rend="italic">./dirsync - w s 10.10.10.16:1985:dirSource dirDest</hi></item></list></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold italic">How the modification code has been incorporated in the original code:</head><p n="p17.73"><s n="s1.1;p17.73">First of all, I had to understand exactly how the original program works, how the files are copied, how the file list is created etc... </s></p><p n="p18.73"><s n="s1.6;p18.73">After that, at the beginning of the modification, I have added the code which treat the option <hi rend="italic">'-w'</hi> and <hi rend="italic">'-d'</hi>. </s><s n="s2.6;p18.73">Then, I followed each instruction contained in the synchronisation process and modify it in order to treat the case where a machine (source and/or destination) is distant. </s><s n="s3.6;p18.73">Each time modified a step in the process; this modification contains a message sending to a daemon. </s><s n="s4.6;p18.73">So, I treated the modification in the client side (message sending) and in the server/daemon side (how treat this instruction). </s><s n="s5.6;p18.73">Every time I need to communicate with a daemon, I have to send an instruction. </s><s n="s6.6;p18.73">So, I wrote a function called <hi rend="italic">SendInstruction()</hi> which will send an instruction to a daemon. </s></p><p n="p19.73"><s n="s1.1;p19.73">Here is an example which shows the general case for an instruction sending and the protocol which follows, </s></p><p n="p20.73"><s n="s1.1;p20.73"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_3052c-form.003"/> </s></p><p n="p21.73"><s n="s1.1;p21.73">Where SendInstruction is defined like this, </s></p><p n="p22.73"><s n="s1.1;p22.73">void SendInstruction(srcDestType* Where,char* Instruction); </s></p><p n="p23.73"><s n="s1.2;p23.73">Above is a general example. </s><s n="s2.2;p23.73">The same architecture is used every time with some difference in order to adapt each case. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold italic">Explanation of main system calls used:</head><p rend="ordered" n="p24.73"><s n="s1.2;p24.73">- The system call <hi rend="italic">send</hi> is used to send a buffer <hi rend="italic">buf</hi> which the size is <hi rend="italic">len</hi> via the socket <hi rend="italic">s</hi>. </s><s n="s2.2;p24.73">This function is defined below, </s></p><p n="p25.73"><s n="s1.1;p25.73"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_3052c-form.004"/> </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p26.73"><s n="s1.2;p26.73">- The system call <hi rend="italic">recv</hi> is used to receive a buffer <hi rend="italic">buf</hi> which the size is <hi rend="italic">len</hi> on the socket <hi rend="italic">s</hi>. </s><s n="s2.2;p26.73">This function is defined below, </s></p><p n="p27.73"><s n="s1.1;p27.73"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_3052c-form.005"/> </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p28.73"><s n="s1.3;p28.73">- The system call <hi rend="italic">utime</hi> is used to change the modification date of a file. </s><s n="s2.3;p28.73">This is used to change the date of a new file created in the destination directory in order to have exactly the same properties than the source file. </s><s n="s3.3;p28.73">This function is defined below, </s></p><p n="p29.73"><s n="s1.1;p29.73"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_3052c-form.006"/> </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p30.73"><s n="s1.3;p30.73">- The system call <hi rend="italic"> chmod</hi> is used to change the mode of a file/directory (<hi rend="italic">path</hi>). </s><s n="s2.3;p30.73">The new mode is defined by <hi rend="italic">mod</hi>. </s><s n="s3.3;p30.73">This function is defined below, </s></p><p n="p31.73"><s n="s1.1;p31.73"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_3052c-form.007"/> </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p32.73"><s n="s1.2;p32.73">- The system call <hi rend="italic"> unlink</hi> is used to remove (unlink) a file/directory (<hi rend="italic">path</hi>). </s><s n="s2.2;p32.73">This function is defined below, </s></p><p n="p33.73"><s n="s1.1;p33.73"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_3052c-form.008"/> </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p34.73"><s n="s1.2;p34.73">- The system call <hi rend="italic"> listen</hi> is used to listen for an eventual connection on the socket s. </s><s n="s2.2;p34.73">This function is defined below, </s></p><p n="p35.73"><s n="s1.1;p35.73"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_3052c-form.009"/> </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p36.73"><s n="s1.3;p36.73">- The system call <hi rend="italic">accept</hi> is used to accept a connection on the socket s. </s><s n="s2.3;p36.73">This is used by the daemon. </s><s n="s3.3;p36.73">This function is defined below, </s></p><p n="p37.73"><s n="s1.1;p37.73"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_3052c-form.010"/> </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p38.73"><s n="s1.2;p38.73">- The system call <hi rend="italic"> stat</hi> is used to obtain the <hi rend="italic">stat</hi> of a file/directory (<hi rend="italic">path</hi>). </s><s n="s2.2;p38.73">This function is defined below, </s></p><p n="p39.73"><s n="s1.1;p39.73"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_3052c-form.011"/> </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p40.73"><s n="s1.3;p40.73">- The system call <hi rend="italic">readdir</hi> is used to read the first file in a directory. </s><s n="s2.3;p40.73">This function returns this file structured by the <hi rend="italic"> dirent</hi> structure. </s><s n="s3.3;p40.73">This function is defined below, </s></p><p n="p41.73"><s n="s1.1;p41.73"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_3052c-form.012"/> </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p42.73"><s n="s1.2;p42.73">- The system call <hi rend="italic"> closedir</hi> is used to close the directory <hi rend="italic">dirp</hi> defines by the <hi rend="italic">DIR</hi> structure. </s><s n="s2.2;p42.73">This function is defined below, </s></p><p n="p43.73"><s n="s1.1;p43.73"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_3052c-form.013"/> </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p44.73"><s n="s1.2;p44.73">- The system call <hi rend="italic">rmdir</hi> is used to remove the directory <hi rend="italic">pathname</hi>. </s><s n="s2.2;p44.73">This function is defined below, </s></p><p n="p45.73"><s n="s1.1;p45.73"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_3052c-form.014"/> </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p46.73"><s n="s1.2;p46.73">- The system call <hi rend="italic">mkdir</hi> is used to create a directory which is called <hi rend="italic">pathname</hi>. </s><s n="s2.2;p46.73">This function is defined below, </s></p><p n="p47.73"><s n="s1.1;p47.73"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_3052c-form.015"/> </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold italic">Print out of the compilation:</head><p n="p48.73"><s n="s1.1;p48.73"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_3052c-form.016"/> </s></p><p n="p49.73"><s n="s1.3;p49.73">We can see above that the compilation contains no error. </s><s n="s2.3;p49.73">As I have already specified in the design of the coursework 3, in order to compile it, we have to add the constant definition called __LINUX__. </s><s n="s3.3;p49.73">So the following line has been added at the beginning, </s></p><p n="p50.73"><s n="s1.1;p50.73"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_3052c-form.017"/> </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold italic">Print out of the program execution:</head><p n="p51.73"><s n="s1.1;p51.73">In order to show some execution example, I have created two directories called <hi rend="italic">directoryTestSource</hi> and <hi rend="italic">directoryTestDestination</hi> which contain some test files and directories in order to test the program. </s></p><p n="p52.73"><s n="s1.1;p52.73">Here is shown the content of these directories (initial content) including the content of the sub-directories, where <hi rend="italic">"ll"</hi> an alias of <hi rend="italic">"ls - l",</hi> </s></p><p n="p53.73"><s n="s1.1;p53.73"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_3052c-form.018"/> </s></p><p n="p54.73"><s n="s1.1;p54.73">More clearly, the schema below shown the directories content, </s></p><figure id="BAWE_3052c-fig.001"/><p n="p55.73"><s n="s1.3;p55.73">Above are the initial directories contents. </s><s n="s2.3;p55.73">After the execution of dirSync, we want to have exactly the same content (from source to destination). </s><s n="s3.3;p55.73">So, the following tests execute dirSync in several case: first of all, the case where <hi rend="italic">directoryTestSource</hi> and <hi rend="italic">directoryTestDestination</hi> are both local (we don't specify the <hi rend="italic"> - w</hi> option), then the case where <hi rend="italic">directoryTestSource</hi> is distant, afterward the case where <hi rend="italic">directoryTestDestination</hi> is distant. </s></p><p n="p56.73"><s n="s1.5;p56.73">These tests have been executed on a simple machine (because when I have recorded the execution test, I didn't have an access on a network), but the obtained results are exactly the same on two different machine. </s><s n="s2.5;p56.73">So, the distant address used here is <hi rend="italic">127.0.0.1</hi> and the port number (the default port number) is <hi rend="italic">1985</hi>. </s><s n="s3.5;p56.73">However, the same execution on two different physical machines would be demonstrated during the demonstration time, on Monday 5 <hi rend="sup">th</hi>. </s><s n="s4.5;p56.73">The difference will be the machine address. </s><s n="s5.5;p56.73">Instead of using the address 127.0.0.1, the real address machine will be use. </s></p><p n="p57.73"><s n="s1.2;p57.73">So, three tests follow. </s><s n="s2.2;p57.73">In each case, we show the execution print out, then the content of the directories <hi rend="bold">after</hi> execution, in order to check that the content of the destination directory (it has to be the same than the source directory), </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p58.73"><s n="s1.2;p58.73">Case where the source and the destination directories are in the local machine. </s><s n="s2.2;p58.73">In this test, no dirSync daemon have to be running (because we are in local), </s></p><p n="p59.73"><s n="s1.1;p59.73"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_3052c-form.019"/> </s></p><p n="p60.73"><s n="s1.2;p60.73">We can see above the content of the destination directory is exactly the same than the source directory. </s><s n="s2.2;p60.73">Unnecessary files have been deleted and necessary files have been copied. </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p61.73"><s n="s1.4;p61.73">Case where the source is distant (on 127.0.0.1 machine). </s><s n="s2.4;p61.73">So, a daemon has to be running on this machine. </s><s n="s3.4;p61.73">As it's explains above, if we use 2 different machine, it's exactly the same thing; a daemon has to be running on the distant machine. </s><s n="s4.4;p61.73">We use 127.0.0.1 but the effect is the same, we need to use the socket as well, </s></p><p n="p62.73"><s n="s1.1;p62.73"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_3052c-form.020"/> </s></p><p n="p63.73"><s n="s1.3;p63.73">We can see in this example that the destination directory is the same. </s><s n="s2.3;p63.73">The execution time was a bit longer than the first case because we needed to use the socket and the file was sent through the network (not really here because 127.0.0.1 but in a real network, it's the same. </s><s n="s3.3;p63.73">127.0.0.1 is a simulation). </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p64.73"><s n="s1.2;p64.73">Case where the destination is distant. </s><s n="s2.2;p64.73">Like in the previous example, a daemon has to be running on the distant machine (here 127.0.0.1 again), </s></p><p n="p65.73"><s n="s1.1;p65.73"><formula notation="" id="BAWE_3052c-form.021"/> </s></p><p n="p66.73"><s n="s1.1;p66.73">We can see above that the destination directory is he same than the source directory. </s></p><p n="p67.73"><s n="s1.2;p67.73">A last case is possible, but not shown here (it would be executed during the demonstration on Monday). </s><s n="s2.2;p67.73">This case is where the source and the destination are both distant. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold italic">Discussion about the program:</head><div2><head rend="italic">State of the program:</head><p n="p68.73"><s n="s1.3;p68.73">The program works in every case (4 different cases ('s', 'd', 'l', 'sd')). </s><s n="s2.3;p68.73">The synchronisation is done correctly. </s><s n="s3.3;p68.73">In order to use it in several machine, we only need one file, dirSync and we have to specify the option <hi rend="italic">'-d'</hi> if we want to launch the dirSync daemon. </s></p><p n="p69.73"><s n="s1.1;p69.73">When we launch the daemon, it's better to use '&amp;' to put the process in the background. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="italic">Problem met:</head><p n="p70.73"><s n="s1.6;p70.73">I have met a problem concerning the buffer size. </s><s n="s2.6;p70.73">Indeed, the buffer size which is actually used is very small (512*2 Byte = 1Kb). </s><s n="s3.6;p70.73">The buffer size is used when a file has to be copied from the source to the destination. </s><s n="s4.6;p70.73">This file is read and written in several steps; <hi rend="italic">buffer_size</hi> bytes are read/written every step. </s><s n="s5.6;p70.73">So more the buffer size is small, more the number of steps needed to copy the file is big. </s><s n="s6.6;p70.73">And so, we need more time to copy a file. </s></p><p n="p71.73"><s n="s1.3;p71.73">When the program works in local (127.0.0.1), the socket allows a big buffer size. </s><s n="s2.3;p71.73">However, when the destination and the source are in two different machines, the buffer size is the source of a problem which I didn't manage to solve. </s><s n="s3.3;p71.73">So I have set the buffer size to 512*2, so the program works but is a bit long when a file is big. </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold italic">Discussion about the problem:</head><p n="p72.73"><s n="s1.4;p72.73">This coursework contains two different parts. </s><s n="s2.4;p72.73">First of all, a main part is to understand how a program works. </s><s n="s3.4;p72.73">This part requires an analyse because the program is written by another person and sometimes doesn't contain comments. </s><s n="s4.4;p72.73">So, now, I understand why to comment a code is very useful and important especially when the program is open source (hence a lot a people may read the code). </s></p><p n="p73.73"><s n="s1.3;p73.73">The second main part is to find and write a solution to do the modification. </s><s n="s2.3;p73.73">First of all, I had to think about the architecture of the modification. </s><s n="s3.3;p73.73">After that, I could write the modification and test it on every step. </s></p></div1></body><back/></text></TEI.2>
