<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_3060a" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>There is a growing trend in the zoological, veterinary and laboratory animal community to recognise the value of using operant conditioning as an animal care and</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">
Word count at the end of running text (before bibliography).
</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">4</p><p n="date">2004-06</p><p n="module title">Captive Management and Rehabilitation</p><p n="module code">P20105</p><p n="genre family">Essay</p><p n="discipline">Anthropology</p><p n="disciplinary group">SS</p><p n="grade">M</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">2303</p><p n="number of s-units">128</p><p n="number of p">21</p><p n="number of tables">0</p><p n="number of figures">0</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">0</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">0</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">18.0</p><p n="average s-units per p">6.1</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">f</p><p n="year of birth">1976</p><p n="first language">English</p><p n="education">UKa</p><p n="course">MSc Primate Conservation</p><p n="student ID">3060</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><titlePart>Primate Conservation: Captive Breeding and Rehabilitation (Module 5) <name type="student name"/></titlePart><docTitle><titlePart rend="bold">There is a growing trend in the zoological, veterinary and laboratory animal community to recognise the value of using operant conditioning as an animal care and management tool. Describe how such training can be used to increase the well being of primates in captivity and include in your answer any potential costs of training. </titlePart></docTitle></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="section"><p n="p1.21"><s n="s1.4;p1.21">This essay will start with a history and definition of operant conditioning. </s><s n="s2.4;p1.21">It will outline how this technique can be used as an animal care and management tool for non-human primates within captive environments including: veterinary care, husbandry procedures, maternal care, and behaviour modification. </s><s n="s3.4;p1.21">Specific applications will be outlined, within both laboratory and zoological settings. </s><s n="s4.4;p1.21">The essay will finish with an overview of the value of operant conditioning in terms of a quantitative assessment of its effectiveness and a discussion of any potential costs of training. </s></p><p n="p2.21"><s n="s1.6;p2.21">Operant conditioning has begun to be recognised as a valuable animal management tool to gain the voluntary cooperation of the animals in question (Laule <hi rend="italic">et al</hi>., 2003). </s><s n="s2.6;p2.21">Underlying operant conditioning is the principle that behaviour is determined by consequences (Laule <hi rend="italic">et al</hi>., 2003). </s><s n="s3.6;p2.21">This involves two basic alternatives - positive and negative reinforcement. </s><s n="s4.6;p2.21">In simple terms, positive reinforcement involves rewarding an animal for an appropriate response to a cue (Pryor, 2002; Mellen and Ellis, 1996). </s><s n="s5.6;p2.21">Negative reinforcement involves an animal giving a correct response to avoid something unpleasant (Mellen and Ellis, 1996; Pryor, 2002). </s><s n="s6.6;p2.21">The essay will focus on positive reinforcement training (PRT) as an option that should be exhausted before negative reinforcement is considered (Laule, <hi rend="italic">et al</hi>., 2003). </s></p><p n="p3.21"><s n="s1.4;p3.21">Operant conditioning is far more widely applied in North American as opposed to British Zoos (Prescott, pers. comm.). </s><s n="s2.4;p3.21">PRT is still not used as widely as it could be (Prescott and Buchanan-Smith, 2003). </s><s n="s3.4;p3.21">This may be due to lack of information on how to train (Prescott and Buchanan-Smith, 2003) and a lack of quantitative assessment regarding time investment, costs and benefits of training (McKinley, <hi rend="italic">et al</hi>., 2003; Prescott and Buchanan-Smith, 2003; Schapiro <hi rend="italic">et al.,</hi> 2003). </s><s n="s4.4;p3.21">These issues will be returned to later in the essay. </s></p><p n="p4.21"><s n="s1.2;p4.21">PRT has provided alternatives to invasive veterinary procedures. </s><s n="s2.2;p4.21">Reinhardt (2003) documents its </s></p><p n="p5.21"><s n="s1.3;p5.21">use for the acquisition of blood samples from rhesus macaques (<hi rend="italic">Macaca mulatta</hi>) within a laboratory setting. </s><s n="s2.3;p5.21">Traditional methods involved enforced restraint, which raised normative levels of a range of hormones, enzymes and blood readings (including cortisol, Reinhardt, 2003). </s><s n="s3.3;p5.21">The macaques were therefore trained to cooperate during blood collection and voluntarily offer their leg for the injection, reducing cortisol levels significantly (Reinhardt, 2003). </s></p><p n="p6.21"><s n="s1.5;p6.21">PRT has also been used to acquire urine samples. </s><s n="s2.5;p6.21">This technique may offer an alternative to the blood sampling outlined above, in which the crush cage was still used for the early stages of training (Prescott and Buchanan-Smith, 2003). </s><s n="s3.5;p6.21">McKinley <hi rend="italic">et al</hi>. </s><s n="s4.5;p6.21">(2003) refined, through training, the species-specific behaviour of scent marking in common marmosets (<hi rend="italic">Callithrix jaccus</hi>) in a laboratory to obtain urine samples on demand. </s><s n="s5.5;p6.21">Once they were trained to scent-mark on designated areas within the cage, holes were drilled at these sites to allow for the insertion of collection vials. </s></p><p n="p7.21"><s n="s1.5;p7.21">PRT has also been incorporated into a range of veterinary procedures within zoological settings. </s><s n="s2.5;p7.21">Colahan and Breder (2003) document the use of PRT with primates at Disney's Animal Kingdom (DAS). </s><s n="s3.5;p7.21">Where immobilisation is necessary, primates have been trained to receive injections or to take oral anaesthetics (Colahan and Breder, 2003). </s><s n="s4.5;p7.21">However, training to present body-parts and desensitisation of medical treatments and instruments has negated the need for immobilisation in many cases. </s><s n="s5.5;p7.21">For example, a mandrill was trained to position an injured hand for a portable x-ray, avoiding immobilisation through anaesthesia (Colahan and Breder, 2003). </s></p><p n="p8.21"><s n="s1.5;p8.21">General husbandry techniques have also been improved and modified through the use of PRT. In the past, weighing required immobilisation or capture and separation from conspecifics (McKinley <hi rend="italic">et al</hi>., 2003). </s><s n="s2.5;p8.21">An operant conditioning program at the Bronx zoo trained a variety of Neo-tropical primates to station themselves on scales that were temporarily placed in their enclosure (Savastano <hi rend="italic">et al</hi>. </s><s n="s3.5;p8.21">2003). </s><s n="s4.5;p8.21">McKinley <hi rend="italic">et al</hi>. </s><s n="s5.5;p8.21">(2003) trained common marmosets to climb onto a scale placed in their home cage and remain stationed until their weight was obtained. </s></p><p n="p9.21"><s n="s1.4;p9.21">PRT has also been of value for monitoring pregnancies and other issues regarding maternal care. </s><s n="s2.4;p9.21">Keepers at DAS have trained primates to accept ultrasounds (Colahan and Breder, 2003). </s><s n="s3.4;p9.21">A white-cheeked gibbon at DAS was trained in nipple desensitisation and genital presentation to facilitate the monitoring of her pregnancy (Richards <hi rend="italic">et al</hi>., 2001). </s><s n="s4.4;p9.21">Bonobos at Milwaukee County Zoo accept 45-minute ultrasound examinations and one individual allows the use of a breast pump (cited in Rodgers, 1997). </s></p><p n="p10.21"><s n="s1.7;p10.21">PRT can also reduce the need for hand rearing, even with inexperienced mothers, and aid in early reintroductions in cases where initial hand rearing is necessary. </s><s n="s2.7;p10.21">The white-cheeked gibbon at DAS showed evidence of improvement in her maternal behaviour, but the infant had to be removed after 25 days (Richards <hi rend="italic">et al</hi>., 2001). </s><s n="s3.7;p10.21">However, PRT allowed keepers to train the mother and older sibling to feed cooperatively and ignore the presence of a baby bottle. </s><s n="s4.7;p10.21">PRT was also used to train the infant to come to the mesh for feedings when a bell sounded. </s><s n="s5.7;p10.21">The success of this training allowed the infant to be reintroduced at 4.5 months of age (Richards <hi rend="italic">et al</hi>., 2001). </s><s n="s6.7;p10.21">Infant care training is recognised as a priority at DAS, focusing on mothers who have either a poor history of maternal care, or who are first time mothers (Colahan and Breder, 2003). </s><s n="s7.7;p10.21">Techniques such as training the female to retrieve an object and bring it to the front of the enclosure, can allow an infant to stay within its social group, even when the female is unable to feed her infant (Colahan and Breder, 2003). </s></p><p n="p11.21"><s n="s1.14;p11.21">Many of the examples outlined above involve a technique known as 'refinement' in which a procedure that is already being carried out within animal care institutions is modified (Prescott and Buchanan-Smith, 2003). </s><s n="s2.14;p11.21">However, PRT techniques can also be employed to tackle a range of complex problems that without its use might remain unsolved. </s><s n="s3.14;p11.21">One such example is behaviour modification (Schapiro <hi rend="italic">et al.</hi> </s><s n="s4.14;p11.21">, 2001; Bloomsmith <hi rend="italic">et al.</hi> </s><s n="s5.14;p11.21">, 1994). </s><s n="s6.14;p11.21">This is a particularly relevant term with regard to primates, who often live in complex social groupings. </s><s n="s7.14;p11.21">Social dynamics can be problematic within the confines of a captive situation (Bloomsmith <hi rend="italic">et al.</hi> </s><s n="s8.14;p11.21">, 1994). </s><s n="s9.14;p11.21">Bloomsmith <hi rend="italic">et al</hi>. </s><s n="s10.14;p11.21">(1994) used PRT techniques to tackle the problem of excessive aggression during feeding time in a group of chimpanzees. </s><s n="s11.14;p11.21">The dominant male was very aggressive and often gave chase to subordinate individuals. </s><s n="s12.14;p11.21">For the exclusion/reduction of undesirable behaviours, PRT is used to reinforce a behaviour that is incompatible with the undesired behaviour (Bloomsmith <hi rend="italic">et al.</hi> </s><s n="s13.14;p11.21">, 1994). </s><s n="s14.14;p11.21">In this case, the male chimpanzee was trained to station while the other members of the group were fed (Bloomsmith <hi rend="italic">et al</hi>., 1994). </s></p><p n="p12.21"><s n="s1.4;p12.21">Schapiro <hi rend="italic">et al</hi>. </s><s n="s2.4;p12.21">(2001) demonstrated how affiliative behaviours within socially housed groups of rhesus macaques could be manipulated through the use of PRT. Female rhesus macaques were divided into groups of high and low affiliators. </s><s n="s3.4;p12.21">High affiliators were reinforced for stationing at targets; these targets were set up at increasing distances from other group members. </s><s n="s4.4;p12.21">Low affiliators were reinforced as their targets were moved closer to another monkey (Schapiro <hi rend="italic">et al</hi>., 2001). </s></p><p n="p13.21"><s n="s1.5;p13.21">In response to the previous lack of quantitative assessment regarding the value of operant conditioning, recent work has attempted to document time-investment and effectiveness. </s><s n="s2.5;p13.21">A symposium at the Nineteenth Congress of the International Primatological Society (China, 2002), was organised to bring together individuals involved in operant conditioning in both zoo and laboratory contexts (Prescott and Buchanan-Smith, 2003). </s><s n="s3.5;p13.21">Following the conference, a special issue of the <hi rend="italic">Journal of Applied Animal Welfare Science</hi> was published (Prescott, 2004). </s><s n="s4.5;p13.21">Articles focused on quantifying the costs and benefits of training and providing guidelines for application (Prescott and Buchanan-Smith, 2003; Schapiro <hi rend="italic">et al.</hi> </s><s n="s5.5;p13.21">, 2003). </s></p><p n="p14.21"><s n="s1.5;p14.21">Thus, many of the articles outlined above provided information regarding time investment and level of success. </s><s n="s2.5;p14.21">For example, the number of training sessions required for rhesus macaques to cooperate in blood collection varied from 2-27 sessions; a mean time-investment of 38.5 minutes (Reinhardt, 2003). </s><s n="s3.5;p14.21">Only one member of the animal care staff is needed for this technique, whereas traditional restraint methods required two individuals (Reinhardt, 2003). </s><s n="s4.5;p14.21">Training the chimpanzee to sit during feeding times took one week for him to sit reliably on command; and after three weeks he remained seated even when preferred food items were fed (Bloomsmith <hi rend="italic">et al</hi>., 1994). </s><s n="s5.5;p14.21">Behavioural data showed that antagonistic behaviours (defined as displays, submission, aggression and reconciliation) were significantly lower after the training had been implemented (Bloomsmith <hi rend="italic">et al</hi>., 1994). </s></p><p n="p15.21"><s n="s1.7;p15.21">McKinley <hi rend="italic">et al</hi>. </s><s n="s2.7;p15.21">(2003), document a mean time investment of an hour and four minutes per pair of common marmosets for target training and a mean of 52 minutes per pair for urine training. </s><s n="s3.7;p15.21">No sex differences were observed during McKinley's study. </s><s n="s4.7;p15.21">However, Bloomsmith <hi rend="italic">et al</hi>. </s><s n="s5.7;p15.21">(1998) document significant sex differences regarding training chimpanzees to move from their outdoor to indoor enclosure on request. </s><s n="s6.7;p15.21">A mean of 16.1 training sessions were required for all chimps to reach reliable performance levels (defined by the authors as complying with 90% of requests). </s><s n="s7.7;p15.21">However, the female chimpanzees required significantly fewer training sessions than the males. </s></p><p n="p16.21"><s n="s1.5;p16.21">The training programme at the Bronx Zoo discovered significant species differences in response to a range of training procedures. </s><s n="s2.5;p16.21">Shyness made golden lion tamarins (<hi rend="italic">Leontopithecus rosalia</hi>) slow to respond to training. </s><s n="s3.5;p16.21">Other tamarin species responded more quickly than the marmosets, but required frequent, short sessions, as they tended to lose interest during longer sessions. </s><s n="s4.5;p16.21">Common marmosets were slower to respond to early training sessions - 60 sessions to hand-feed - but subsequent behaviours were learned very quickly, often in less than 10 sessions (Savastano <hi rend="italic">et al</hi>. </s><s n="s5.5;p16.21">2003). </s></p><p n="p17.21"><s n="s1.8;p17.21">One major benefit of PRT is that it negates the need for invasive and stressful techniques, such as darting, capture, restraint and separation from conspecifics (as outlined above). </s><s n="s2.8;p17.21">In addition, PRT also facilitates health monitoring (Schapiro <hi rend="italic">et al.</hi> </s><s n="s3.8;p17.21">, 2003), gives captive animals more choice and control over daily events (Bloomsmith <hi rend="italic">et al.</hi> </s><s n="s4.8;p17.21">, 1998), mitigates social problems (Bloomsmith et al., 1994; Schapiro et al., 2001), and reduces abnormal behaviours (Laule <hi rend="italic">et al.</hi> </s><s n="s5.8;p17.21">, 2003). </s><s n="s6.8;p17.21">Although animal welfare benefits are the priority, there are other notable positive outcomes of PRT. These include: improved reliability and quantity of data collection (McKinley <hi rend="italic">et al.,</hi> 2003; Reinhardt, 2003), positive attitude changes among staff (Savastano <hi rend="italic">et al.</hi> </s><s n="s7.8;p17.21">, 2003) and positive experiences for zoo visitors, who see visible, interactive animals while learning the importance of low-stress animal husbandry (Savastano <hi rend="italic">et al.</hi> </s><s n="s8.8;p17.21">, 2003). </s></p><p n="p18.21"><s n="s1.10;p18.21">Potential costs involved with PRT require exploration. </s><s n="s2.10;p18.21">Many researchers show that the initial cost in terms of time investment is recouped within a short period of time (Prescott and Buchanan-Smith, 2003; Reinhardt, 2003; Colahan and Breder, 2003). </s><s n="s3.10;p18.21">In addition, once the first behaviour is trained, animals respond quickly to subsequent training (Savastano <hi rend="italic">et al.</hi> </s><s n="s4.10;p18.21">, 2003). </s><s n="s5.10;p18.21">Potential animal welfare costs include physical problems from performing tasks too frequently. </s><s n="s6.10;p18.21">For example, excessive scent marking could lead to urinary tract infections in marmosets (Prescott and Buchanan-Smith, 2003). </s><s n="s7.10;p18.21">Moreover, scent marking has been associated with stress in marmosets (Bassett <hi rend="italic">et al.</hi> </s><s n="s8.10;p18.21">, 2003), highlighting the issue of rewarding a stress-related behaviour (McKinley <hi rend="italic">et al</hi>., 2003). </s><s n="s9.10;p18.21">Saliva samples may prove a viable alternative to urine samples in the future, which might solve such issues (McKinley <hi rend="italic">et al</hi>., 2003). </s><s n="s10.10;p18.21">Within laboratory environments, training should not be seen as a substitute for housing of a high standard and enriching environments, as this could compromise welfare (Scott <hi rend="italic">et al</hi>., 2003; Prescott and Buchanan-Smith, 2003). </s></p><p n="p19.21"><s n="s1.7;p19.21">There are also concerns around habituation (Prescott, pers. comm.). </s><s n="s2.7;p19.21">However, exposing primates to positive human interactions may increase welfare, especially when frequent human contact is necessary (Bassett <hi rend="italic">et al.</hi> </s><s n="s3.7;p19.21">, 2003). </s><s n="s4.7;p19.21">O'Sullivan (1999) explores the issue of training in relation to re-introductions. </s><s n="s5.7;p19.21">In this context, PRT can have both positive and negative effects on an animal's behavioural repertoire. </s><s n="s6.7;p19.21">Increased human contact results in animals losing their fear of humans, which could be dangerous in a post-release environment (O'Sullivan, 1999). </s><s n="s7.7;p19.21">However, training can be used to teach skills and appropriate reactions necessary for survival in the wild (O'Sullivan, 1999). </s></p><p n="p20.21"><s n="s1.10;p20.21">Institutions embarking on PRT programmes must plan to equip keepers with the necessary skills (Colahan and Breder, 2003). </s><s n="s2.10;p20.21">Consistency is important; otherwise the wrong behaviours can be accidentally reinforced (Prescott, pers. comm.). </s><s n="s3.10;p20.21">Changes in behaviour can occur outside of training (Prescott, pers. comm.). </s><s n="s4.10;p20.21">Schapiro <hi rend="italic">et al.</hi> </s><s n="s5.10;p20.21">(2003) demonstrated that training altered the overall behavioural repertoire of the low affiliators in their macaque study, which was a positive outcome as affiliation has been linked to psychological well being (Schapiro <hi rend="italic">et al.</hi> </s><s n="s6.10;p20.21">, 2001). </s><s n="s7.10;p20.21">The chimpanzee trained to station during feeding (Bloomsmith <hi rend="italic">et al.</hi> </s><s n="s8.10;p20.21">, 1994) retained normal levels of aggression and dominance outside the training sessions (Bloomsmith <hi rend="italic">et al.</hi> </s><s n="s9.10;p20.21">, 1994), so that the overall hierarchy of the group was not disrupted. </s><s n="s10.10;p20.21">These examples illustrate the importance of quantitative data to ensure that training objectives are carefully monitored and ultimately met. </s></p><p n="p21.21"><s n="s1.8;p21.21">This essay has outlined the various ways in which PRT techniques can play a valuable role in the care and management of primates in captivity. </s><s n="s2.8;p21.21">Recent attempts to quantify its value in terms of time-investment and its successfulness have helped to clarify this. </s><s n="s3.8;p21.21">As demonstrated, some of the more complex potential costs are yet to be properly assessed and the advantages and disadvantages involved deserve more extensive and scientific exploration (Prescott and Buchanan-Smith, 2003). </s><s n="s4.8;p21.21">These may vary between species and even individuals, as some studies show significant differences in responses to training. </s><s n="s5.8;p21.21">However, these factors should not be used as an excuse for institutions not to implement PRT programmes for standard techniques that are tried and tested, as these present viable alternatives to procedures which are necessary but which traditionally involved handling, restraint and solitary confinement - stressful experiences for the primates involved. </s><s n="s6.8;p21.21">There are very few institutions in which PRT would not be useful and beneficial to both the primates and the animal care staff (Schapiro <hi rend="italic">et al.</hi> </s><s n="s7.8;p21.21">, 2003; Prescott and Buchanan-Smith, 2003). </s><s n="s8.8;p21.21">Moreover, institutions that have incorporated PRT into their management practices have found it an indispensable tool (Colahan and Breder, 2003). </s></p></div1></body><back><div1 type="bibliography"><head rend="bold">References</head><p>Bassett, L., Buchanan-Smith, H.M., McKinley, J., Smith, T.E. (2003). Effects of Training on Stress-Related Behaviour of the Common Marmoset (<hi rend="italic">Callithrix jacchus</hi>) in Relation to Coping With Routine Husbandry Procedures. <hi rend="italic">Journal of Applied Animal Welfare Science</hi> 6 (3), pp. 221-233.</p><p>Bloomsmith, M.A., Laule, G.E., Alford, P.L., Thurston, R.H. (1994). Using Training to Moderate Chimpanzee Aggression During Feeding. <hi rend="italic">Zoo Biology</hi> 13, pp. 557-566.</p><p>Bloomsmith, M.A., Stone, A.M., Laule, G.E. (1998). Positive Reinforcement Training to Enhance the Voluntary Movement of Group-Housed Chimpanzees Within Their Enclosures. <hi rend="italic">Zoo Biology</hi> 17, pp. 333-341.</p><p>Colahan, H., Breder, C. (2003). Primate Training at Disney's Animal Kingdom. <hi rend="italic">Journal of Applied Animal Welfare Science</hi> 6 (3), pp. 235-246.</p><p>Laule, G.E., Bloomsmith, M.A., Schapiro, S.J. (2003). The Use of Positive Reinforcement Training Techniques to Enhance the Care, Management, and Welfare of Primates in the Laboratory. <hi rend="italic">Journal of Applied Animal Welfare Science</hi> 6 (3), pp. 163-173. </p><p>McKinley, J., Buchanan-Smith, H.M., Bassett, L., Morris, K. (2003). Training Common Marmosets (<hi rend="italic">Callithrix jacchus</hi>) to Cooperate During Routine Laboratory Procedures: Ease of Training and Time Investment. <hi rend="italic">Journal of Applied Animal Welfare Science</hi> 6 (3), pp. 209-220. </p><p>Mellen, J.D., Ellis, S. (1996). Animal Learning and Husbandry Training. In: Kleiman, D.G., Allen, M.E., Thompson, K.V., Lumpkin, S., eds. <hi rend="italic">Wild Mammals in Captivity: Principles and Techniques</hi>. Chicago and London: The University of Chicago Press, pp.88-99. </p><p>O'Sullivan, C., (1999). The Role of Training in Re-introduction Programmes. <hi rend="italic">Ratel</hi> 26 (3), pp. 90-92. </p><p>Prescott, M.J., Buchanan-Smith, H.M. (2003). Training Nonhuman Primates Using Positive Reinforcement Techniques. <hi rend="italic">Journal of Applied Animal Welfare Science</hi> 6 (3), pp. 157-161.</p><p>Prescott, M.J. (2004). Reducing Primate Suffering Through Positive Reinforcement Training. <hi rend="italic">Primate Eye</hi> 82, pp. 14-15.</p><p>Pryor, K. (2002). <hi rend="italic">Don't Shoot the Dog! The New Art of Teaching and Training.</hi> Gloucestershire: Ringpress Books Limited.</p><p>Reinhardt, V. (2003). Working With Rather Than Against Macaques During Blood Collection. <hi rend="italic">Journal of Applied Animal Welfare Science</hi> 6 (3), pp. 189-197.</p><p>Richards, B., Owen, L., Mullins-Cordier, S., Sellin, R. (2001). The Lesser-Known Ape: Husbandry Training With Gibbons and Siamangs. In: Chicago Zoological Society, ed., <hi rend="italic">The Apes: Challenges for the 21st Century.</hi> Brookfield Zoo, May 10-13, 2000 Conference Proceedings, Chicago Zoological Society, Brookfield, Illinois, U.S.A., pp.107-111. </p><p>Rodgers, G. (1997). Science or Circus? The Role of Operant Conditioning in the Zoo. <hi rend="italic">Ratel</hi> 24 (5), pp. 170-175. </p><p>Savastano, G., Hanson, A., McCann, C. (2003). The Development of an Operant Conditioning Program for New World Primates at the Bronx Zoo. <hi rend="italic">Journal of Applied Animal Welfare Science</hi> 6 (3), pp. 247-261.</p><p>Schapiro, S.J., Perlman, J.E., Boudreau, B.A. (2001). Manipulating the Affiliative Interactions of Group-Housed Rhesus Macaques Using Positive Reinforcement Training Techniques. <hi rend="italic">American Journal of Primatology</hi> 55, pp. 137-149. </p><p>Schapiro, S.J., Bloomsmith, M.A., Laule, G.E. (2003). Positive Reinforcement Training As a Technique to Alter Nonhuman Primate Behaviour: Quantitative Assessments of Effectiveness. <hi rend="italic">Journal of Applied Animal Welfare Science</hi> 6 (3), 175-187.</p><p>Scott, L., Pearce, P., Fairhall, S., Muggleton, N., Smith, J. (2003). Training Nonhuman Primates to Cooperate With Scientific Procedures in Applied Biomedical Research. <hi rend="italic">Journal of Applied Animal Welfare Science</hi> 6 (3), pp. 199-207. </p></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
