<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_3063c" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Research proposal</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">Language used in quote: <foreign id="English">English</foreign></note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">
Manually inserted page numbers and student name deleted throughout. Word count at the end of every section deleted.
</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">4</p><p n="date">2005-12</p><p n="module title">Research methods</p><p n="module code">P20103</p><p n="genre family">Proposal</p><p n="discipline">Anthropology</p><p n="disciplinary group">SS</p><p n="grade">M</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">5640</p><p n="number of s-units">222</p><p n="number of p">60</p><p n="number of tables">2</p><p n="number of figures">2</p><p n="number of block quotes">1</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">0</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">0</p><p n="abstract present">abstract present</p><p n="average words per s-unit">25.4</p><p n="average s-units per p">3.7</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf) </p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">f</p><p n="year of birth">1974</p><p n="first language">English</p><p n="education">UKa</p><p n="course">MSc Primate Conservation</p><p n="student ID">3063</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><docTitle><titlePart rend="underlined bold">RESEARCH PROPOSAL </titlePart></docTitle><titlePart><name type="student ID"/></titlePart></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="abstract"><head rend="underlined bold">Section 1: Summary Information</head><p n="p1.60"><s rend="underlined bold" n="s1.1;p1.60">Project Title </s></p><p n="p2.60"><s rend="bold" n="s1.1;p2.60">Comparison of captive female chimpanzee behaviour in an all-female group with mixed-sex groups in UK zoos. </s></p><p n="p3.60"><s rend="underlined bold" n="s1.1;p3.60">Flagship Species </s></p><p n="p4.60"><s rend="bold" n="s1.1;p4.60">Common chimpanzee (<hi rend="italic">Pan troglodytes</hi>) </s></p><p n="p5.60"><s rend="underlined bold" n="s1.1;p5.60">Country of Planned Project Dates of Project </s></p><p n="p6.60"><s n="s1.1;p6.60">UK May 2006 - September 2006 </s></p><p n="p7.60"><s rend="underlined bold" n="s1.1;p7.60">Project Summary </s></p><p n="p8.60"><s n="s1.7;p8.60">Dudley Zoo houses a group of seven female chimpanzees. </s><s n="s2.7;p8.60">The only male in the group died in 2005 of natural causes, making it the only known all-female group of captive chimpanzees in a UK zoo. </s><s n="s3.7;p8.60">I can find no documentation of current all-female groups of chimpanzees in other captive settings, though there may be some in research laboratories or zoos elsewhere. </s><s n="s4.7;p8.60">It is of interest whether this living arrangement in any way impacts upon the behaviour of the female chimpanzees, when compared to females living in mixed sex groups. </s><s n="s5.7;p8.60">To try to investigate this, I will be comparing the activity budgets and social behaviour of the all-female group with four other groups of zoo chimpanzees of similar size which include adult males. </s><s n="s6.7;p8.60">I will use focal animal instantaneous samples, along with group scans. </s><s n="s7.7;p8.60">With five groups I would have enough samples to undertake statistical analysis. </s></p><p n="p9.60"><s n="s1.7;p9.60">Preliminary observations and anecdotal narratives from keepers at Dudley Zoo suggest that there may be a limited amount of activity among the group of female chimpanzees, and a hypothesis can be stated that the absence of males decreases the amount of activity among females. </s><s n="s2.7;p9.60">As well as making comparisons to four other groups of chimps, I will also address the activity budgets of wild chimpanzees, to see if there is any difference. </s><s n="s3.7;p9.60">Social relationships are crucial to the well-being of chimpanzees (ILAR, 1998). </s><s n="s4.7;p9.60">Anecdotal observations suggest few agonistic exchanges among the all-female group, and again this will be compared to the mixed-sex groups. </s><s n="s5.7;p9.60">If there are behavioural social differences, they may be due to individual personalities, housing conditions, kin relationship, changing social structure, age, reproductive state, season, climate or other factors. </s><s n="s6.7;p9.60">However, it may also be in part because of the absence of males in the group. </s><s n="s7.7;p9.60">If the hypothesis holds and this appears to be the case, this style of social housing has implications for captive chimpanzee management and may raise questions about whether to keep groups stable or make changes. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">Section 2: Applicant's Details</head><div2><head rend="underlined bold">Applicant</head><figure id="BAWE_3063c-pic.001"/><p n="p10.60"><s n="s1.1;p10.60"><name type="student name"/> </s></p><p n="p11.60"><s n="s1.1;p11.60"><name type="other"/> </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined bold">Affiliate Details</head><figure id="BAWE_3063c-pic.002"/><p n="p12.60"><s n="s1.1;p12.60"><name type="tutor name"/> </s></p><p n="p13.60"><s n="s1.1;p13.60"><name type="other"/> </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined bold">What other organisations/groups/individuals will be involved in this project? </head><div3><head rend="underlined bold">Colchester Zoo</head><p n="p14.60"><s n="s1.1;p14.60"><name type="other"/> </s></p></div3><div3><head rend="underlined bold">Dudley Zoo</head><p n="p15.60"><s n="s1.1;p15.60"><name type="other"/> </s></p></div3><div3><head rend="underlined bold">Edinburgh Zoo</head><p n="p16.60"><s n="s1.1;p16.60"><name type="other"/> </s></p></div3><div3><head rend="underlined bold">Twycross Zoo</head><p n="p17.60"><s n="s1.1;p17.60"><name type="other"/> </s></p></div3><div3><head rend="underlined bold">Whipsnade Wild Animal Park</head><p n="p18.60"><s n="s1.1;p18.60"><name type="other"/> </s></p></div3></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">Section 3: Project aims and background</head><div2><head rend="underlined bold">Project Aims</head><p n="p19.60"><s n="s1.5;p19.60">In the wild, female chimpanzees leave their natal groups upon reaching adolescence, so it is unusual to find groups of females together (Lehmann and Boesch, 2004). </s><s n="s2.5;p19.60">Chimpanzees in the Tai Forest appear to be more homosexually bonded than in other communities (Boesch, 1996). </s><s n="s3.5;p19.60">Studies from other sites have reported less sociality among wild chimpanzee females than among males (for an overview see Sugiyama, 1973). </s><s n="s4.5;p19.60">However, in captivity there is no opportunity for emigration, so social structures are different to those found in the wild (de Waal, 1994). </s><s n="s5.5;p19.60">Chimpanzees can be found in captivity in large mixed groups, small mixed groups, same-sex groups, dyads and in isolation (Brent, 2001). </s></p><p n="p20.60"><s n="s1.3;p20.60">It could be important for captive management to compare female behaviour with the presence and absence of males. </s><s n="s2.3;p20.60">The main aims are to investigate whether life is more or less active for females in all-female rather than mixed-sex groups, and to compare agonistic and affiliative behaviours in their social interactions. </s><s n="s3.3;p20.60">The stability of social groupings may be a key factor in the behaviour of the individuals (Jensvoldal. 2005). </s></p><p n="p21.60"><s n="s1.4;p21.60">It is hoped the data will provide caregivers and zoo managers information about the amount of time spent active and inactive, as this may be of concern. </s><s n="s2.4;p21.60">It will also be important to compare these data on activity budgets and social behaviour among female chimpanzees in the wild, where up to 40% of the day is reportedly spent inactive (Doran, 1997). </s><s n="s3.4;p21.60">The project aims to offer these findings to zoo managers for their consideration when planning group structures, and to add to the discussion about how naturalistic zoo housing should aim to be (Baker and Smuts, 1994; Lindberg and Coe, 1995). </s><s n="s4.4;p21.60">It may help in discussions about whether to alter social structures in the future. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined bold">What threatened flagship species (include scientific names) or their habitats are targeted by this project? Include current global IUCN Red List or CITES category. Why do you consider this species to be a flagship? </head><p n="p22.60"><s n="s1.1;p22.60">According to the IUCN Red List (2004), the common chimpanzee (<hi rend="italic">Pan troglodytes)</hi> is ENDANGERED, with a predicted downward trend, based on the criteria of A3cd: </s></p><table id="BAWE_3063c-tab.001"><head>(IUCN, 2004)</head><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p23.60"><s n="s1.1;p23.60"><hi rend="italic">Pan troglodytes</hi> is also listed on Appendix I of CITES (Convention on International Trade in Endangered Species), and has been listed as such since 04/02/1977. </s></p><quote lang="English"><hi rend="italic">Convention on International Trade in Endangered Species of Wild Fauna and Flora</hi> <hi rend="italic"> Signed at Washington, D.C., on 3 March 1973</hi> / <hi rend="italic">Amended at Bonn, on 22 June 1979</hi> <hi rend="italic"> Article II</hi> <hi rend="bold italic"> Fundamental Principles </hi><hi rend="italic"> 1. Appendix I shall include all species threatened with extinction which are or may be affected by trade. Trade in specimens of these species must be subject to particularly strict regulation in order not to endanger further their survival and must only be authorized in exceptional circumstances.</hi> (CITES, 2005)</quote><p n="p24.60"><s n="s1.1;p24.60">Some chimpanzees are moved from one country to another legally, and permission for the transfer of animals listed under Appendix I is granted in Article III of the Convention. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">Why do you consider the species to be a flagship? </head><p n="p25.60"><s n="s1.7;p25.60">The endangered status of chimpanzees makes them particularly important to zoos. </s><s n="s2.7;p25.60">For example, Twycross Zoo states that "In 1972 the zoo became a charitable trust concentrating on conservation and education, and now takes part in many captive breeding programmes for endangered animals (about three quarters of the animals housed at Twycross are officially classed as endangered species)" (Twycross Zoo, 2005). </s><s n="s3.7;p25.60">This year a female chimpanzee at Twycross Zoo; Mukundu, gave birth to a female infant. </s><s n="s4.7;p25.60">With more animals being born into captivity any study which makes observations about zoo chimpanzees may offer suggestions to assist the psychological, physical and reproductive well-being of those animals. </s><s n="s5.7;p25.60">Chimpanzees are characterised by many conservation organisations as "charismatic megafauna" (WCS, 2005), and therefore have a role as a flagship for endangered apes. </s><s n="s6.7;p25.60">It could be argued that chimpanzees are not endangered in captivity, as they are the most widely held captive great apes (Brent, 2001). </s><s n="s7.7;p25.60">However, the fact that there are many of them also means that there are more animals whose lives can be improved by better management, and there are also more educational opportunities for people to see chimpanzees and learn about them. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined bold">What main problem or threat is this project intending to address? </head><p n="p26.60"><s n="s1.10;p26.60">Comparatively little research has been undertaken on the behaviour of female chimpanzees, when compared with the amount of observations made on male behaviour (Baker and Smuts, 1994). </s><s n="s2.10;p26.60">The opportunity to observe an all-female group of chimps offers a unique opportunity to see if the absence or presence of males affects behaviour. </s><s n="s3.10;p26.60">It is an opportunity to focus on females. </s><s n="s4.10;p26.60">Based on anecdotal reports from keepers, and informal observations, a hypothesis could be made that life in an all-female chimpanzee group is less active than in a mixed-group. </s><s n="s5.10;p26.60">The study will provide a comparison between activity and social behaviour among single-sex and mixed-sex groups of chimpanzees, as well as references to literature about social behaviour in wild groups. </s><s n="s6.10;p26.60">The project will examine if the type of social grouping does have an impact on behaviour, or if there is no change, or if other factors play a role. </s><s n="s7.10;p26.60">A reduced level of activity may be something that zoo managers may wish to address, and it may lead to discussions about whether to alter the social structure. </s><s n="s8.10;p26.60">It is an important ongoing issue for animal management to assess how naturalistic a captive environment should be (Baker and Smuts, 1994; Lindberg and Coe, 1995). </s><s n="s9.10;p26.60">This does not just extend to the type of housing used in zoos, but also includes the structure of a social group (Murray, 1998). </s><s n="s10.10;p26.60">However, activity levels and amounts of social behaviour should not be automatically correlated with abnormality or problems with psychological well-being (Dawkins, 2003). </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined bold">How was this problem or threat identified and by whom? </head><p n="p27.60"><s n="s1.4;p27.60">Anecdotal conversations with animal caregivers at various zoos suggest that the social structure of chimpanzee groups in zoos causes some concern, with regards to the well-being of the animals and the stresses caused to both the chimpanzees, and to keepers and visitors if problems arise. </s><s n="s2.4;p27.60">No research has been undertaken on an all-female group of captive chimpanzees in a UK zoo, and the research department at Dudley Zoo is keen for a comparison to be made between this group and mixed-sex groups at other institutions. </s><s n="s3.4;p27.60">It is hoped this can help informed discussions about whether to leave the group as it is or to seek to change the social structure. </s><s n="s4.4;p27.60">Research departments at the other four zoos involved in this project are also interested in an analysis of activity and behaviour in their chimpanzee groups, as this may identify issues to address. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined bold">Is the project a recommendation of an IUCN/SSC Action Plan or national priority activity? </head><p n="p28.60"><s n="s1.7;p28.60">All five zoos are committed to research. </s><s n="s2.7;p28.60">Twycross Zoo hopes to "build up an extensive library of research from which we can continue to improve the animals surroundings" (Twycross Zoo, 2005). </s><s n="s3.7;p28.60">Colchester Zoo believes "studies that have been selected within the behaviour section generally have a value for captive animal management" (Colchester Zoo, 2005). </s><s n="s4.7;p28.60">This project accords with the research priority of "evolution of social behaviour" at the Institute of Zoology (Whipsnade Wild Animal Park, 2005). </s><s n="s5.7;p28.60">Edinburgh Zoo offers "a unique opportunity for studying animals up close, and for conducting research which would be extremely difficult or impossible in the field" (Edinburgh Zoo, 2005). </s><s n="s6.7;p28.60">Managers at Dudley Zoo say the behavioural project "will be useful to the Zoo if the comparison with an alpha male led group is made." </s><s n="s7.7;p28.60">(Beeston, personal communication, 19 October, 2005). </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined bold">How does this project relate to previous work in the area or on the same species? </head><p n="p29.60"><s n="s1.13;p29.60">Many studies have been done on chimpanzee group behaviour. </s><s n="s2.13;p29.60">De Waal (2005) gives an overview of the breadth of chimpanzee research with its beginnings in laboratory studies before shifting to behavioural observations in the wild. </s><s n="s3.13;p29.60">Over four decades of in-situ research in Africa, theories have shifted about group dynamics among chimpanzees. </s><s n="s4.13;p29.60">In an overview of the literature, Stanford (1998) and Sugiyama (1973) describe how in the 1960s it was thought there was no structure to chimpanzee society. </s><s n="s5.13;p29.60">A decade later this idea had shifted to the concept of chimpanzee communities, where chimpanzees form part of a fluid 'unit group' made up of small parties. </s><s n="s6.13;p29.60">Observations were made of inter-community aggression and female emigration, showing that social systems and mating systems are not necessarily the same thing. </s><s n="s7.13;p29.60">Stanford (1998) describes how the 1980s saw field sites in other parts of Africa offering research results, and showed differences in social groupings between locations. </s><s n="s8.13;p29.60">The female chimpanzees of the Tai Forest were found to be more sociable and bisexually-bonded than those at Kibale, Mahale, Bossou, Assirik and Gombe (Boesch, 1996). </s><s n="s9.13;p29.60">Suggestions have been made that female sociality may be connected to the availability of food resources, and indeed Wittig and Boesch (2003) found a linear dominance hierarchy among females when there was competition for food. </s><s n="s10.13;p29.60">It has been suggested that in order to forage for food during periods of scarcity "weak ties facilitate the individual dispersal of animals from the group" (Maryanski, 1987, p210). </s><s n="s11.13;p29.60">De Waal (2005) asserts that cooperation is typical among kin, for example mother and offspring, and among adult males regardless of kinship. </s><s n="s12.13;p29.60">In a study of the bonds between all the different age and sex categories of chimpanzees, Maryanski (1987) describes a fission-fusion society with weak ties among non-kin, apart from adult males who can form strong bonds, and strong ties between mothers and offspring and among siblings. </s><s n="s13.13;p29.60">The weakening of mother and daughter bonds as adolescence approaches is attributed to the likelihood of female chimpanzees to leave their natal group upon sexual maturity in order to join another group. </s></p><p n="p30.60"><s n="s1.6;p30.60">More recent research on DNA analysis seems to suggest kin relationships are less important than previously thought (Mitanial. 2000, Goldberg and Wrangham, 1997) which contradicts earlier presumptions that chimpanzees selected associations with family members (Morinal. 1994). </s><s n="s2.6;p30.60">Research on female sociality and sexuality has sought to expose a 'myth' of the passive female, with claims that females are as capable of males with competition strategies (Wrangham, 1997, Small, 1993). </s><s n="s3.6;p30.60">When within-group competition for resources is strong female dominance hierarchies are found. </s><s n="s4.6;p30.60">When between-group competition is strong but within-group relationships are stable, an egalitarian dominance relationship is expected (Silk, 2002, p 85). </s><s n="s5.6;p30.60">In studies of other primates, expressions of dominance and position in a hierarchy have accounted for differences in behaviour between the sexes. </s><s n="s6.6;p30.60">For example, female macaques began showing more dominant behaviour after the removal of the alpha male and female (Hendricksal. 1975) and newly paired female rhesus monkeys showed affiliative behaviour while all newly paired males started fighting (Angermeiral. 1967). </s></p><p n="p31.60"><s n="s1.4;p31.60">In conjunction with studies of chimpanzees in the wild, there has also been extensive observation of captive chimpanzees. </s><s n="s2.4;p31.60">Indeed, there are more chimpanzees in captivity than any other ape, largely due to the high number of the species in research laboratories in the United States (Brent, 2001). </s><s n="s3.4;p31.60">The current ongoing transfer of hundreds of these animals to sanctuaries gives added impetus to behavioural observations of captive chimpanzees that can inform caregivers of ways to improve the physical and psychological well-being of the animals (Brent, 2001). </s><s n="s4.4;p31.60">In addition to improving understanding and conditions for captive chimpanzees, such observations may also aid comprehension of natural behaviour. </s></p><p n="p32.60"><s n="s1.2;p32.60">Hosey (2005, p 111) claims it is a "myth that worthwhile behavioural research is not possible in zoos because they are such an artificial environment. </s><s n="s2.2;p32.60">In reality not only is a substantial amount of good research undertaken on zoo-housed animals much of it has made important contributions towards developing and testing theory in behavioural biology". </s></p><p n="p33.60"><s n="s1.13;p33.60">Students of captive chimpanzee behaviour recognise that the usual patterns of social behaviour cannot be entirely replicated. </s><s n="s2.13;p33.60">For example, as "individuals are usually unrelated, when adolescents would ordinarily migrate to another group. </s><s n="s3.13;p33.60">It is hard for animals to escape aggressiveness when they are unable to avoid each other, as they would do in the wild" (Poole, 1991, p 369). </s><s n="s4.13;p33.60">Therefore many social interactions may become magnified in a captive situation whereas in the wild avoidance would occur instead. </s><s n="s5.13;p33.60">In numerous studies of zoo chimpanzees, de Waal (2005, 1994, 1982) suggests that in the absence of the need to spend half their daily lives foraging for food, chimpanzee social lives become intensified and they devote much more time to socialising. </s><s n="s6.13;p33.60">He believes that among females, a subordination hierarchy rather than a dominance hierarchy exists, whereby females accept dominance rather than having to prove dominance and that different types of dominance manifest themselves in a chimp colony (Noe et al., 1980). </s><s n="s7.13;p33.60">In contrast to de Waal's (1982) assertion that dominance is relatively unimportant to female chimpanzees, Wrangham (1997) contends that in certain conditions females do exhibit displays of dominance. </s><s n="s8.13;p33.60">There have been incidences of female chimpanzees assuming the role of alpha animal in a group in captivity. </s><s n="s9.13;p33.60">De Waal (1982) recounts the narrative of Mama, a mature female who was the undisputed leader of a mixed group of chimpanzees at Arnhem Zoo for 18 months, until three adult males were introduced and the other members of the group rejected her leadership and followed one of the males. </s><s n="s10.13;p33.60">De Waal anecdotally reflects that dominance ceased to be important to Mama in terms of overall group leadership. </s><s n="s11.13;p33.60">In the laboratory setting Jensvoldal. (2005) place female chimpanzee Washoe at the top of the dominance hierarchy at the Chimpanzee and Human Communication Institute (CHCI) at Central Washington University. </s><s n="s12.13;p33.60">This hierarchical structure of dominance has remained stable for the last 10 years, and it is this stability which is thought to reduce group aggression, as "A stable hierarchy may reduce agonistic interactions due to the absence of attempts to displace the alpha chimpanzee" (Jensvoldal. 2005). </s><s n="s13.13;p33.60">So, the stability of a hierarchy may be an important element, along with individual personality differences, as well as the sex-ratio in the group. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined bold">How will this project address the identified problem and its causes? </head><p n="p34.60"><s n="s1.4;p34.60">There are many different types of social groups found in zoos; large mixed-sex groups, small mixed-sex groups, large bachelor groups, all-female groups, mixed sex triads, mixed-sex dyads, single-sex dyads (Brent, 2001). </s><s n="s2.4;p34.60">By comparing similar sized mixed-sex groups and all-female groups, in similar environmental conditions with matching available space, it may be possible to observe different behaviour patterns or different activity levels that may be attributed to the sex composition of the group, rather than group size or environmental conditions. </s><s n="s3.4;p34.60">However, it must still be recognised that each zoo will inevitably have different husbandry practises and routines, but perhaps the study can help to share information between locations for future consideration. </s><s n="s4.4;p34.60">Of course, individual personalities of chimpanzees will also always play a part in their behaviour, but by comparing zoos with similar group sizes it is hoped the role of sex ratio will be more easily identified. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined bold">List any other important impacts of your project, other than on the flagship species or its habitat? </head><p n="p35.60"><s n="s1.5;p35.60">As I will be visiting several zoos in this study, there will be important benefits of information-sharing between sites. </s><s n="s2.5;p35.60">All of the zoos have different husbandry procedures, and the chimpanzees are housed in different social groupings. </s><s n="s3.5;p35.60">It may be important for keepers and zoo managers to consider social grouping as crucial as other aspects of care-giving. </s><s n="s4.5;p35.60">Any information that can be gleaned about social behaviour of captive chimps may hold clues for the best way to house chimps in zoos, which will be a long-term benefit. </s><s n="s5.5;p35.60">By comparing the social behaviour of five different zoo groups, those five zoos can have access to information about how other institutions care for the same species which may provide suggestions for change. </s></p><p n="p36.60"><s n="s1.6;p36.60">If the hypothesis holds that there are different amounts of activity between chimpanzees in different sex-ratio settings, this might have implications for the visitor experience of those animals in the zoo. </s><s n="s2.6;p36.60">Anecdotal reports from zoo keepers suggest visitors do not spend much time at enclosures with inactive animals, so the exhibits are unlikely to elicit much visitor appreciation and interest. </s><s n="s3.6;p36.60">This may mean that opportunities for education are lost. </s><s n="s4.6;p36.60">If the hypothesis is not validated, and activity levels are normal when compared with those in other zoos and in the wild, that could be an important addition to the educational materials available about chimpanzees, as visitors would realise that the behaviour is not abnormal or an animal welfare issue. </s><s n="s5.6;p36.60">Otherwise this could have a serious implication for the visitor experience of the zoo, their perception of the welfare of the animals, and their appreciation of the animals. </s><s n="s6.6;p36.60">Being able to address anecdotal keeper concerns about the social behaviour patterns would also be a positive impact of the project by involving people who are directly responsible for animal welfare, and bringing their comments to wider attention. </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Section 4: Planned activities and methods</head><div2><head rend="underlined bold">Please list the major activities planned within the project, along with an approximate time-scale for these activities. Explain exactly what you plan to do and why it is needed. </head><div3><head rend="italic">Overview</head><p n="p37.60"><s n="s1.5;p37.60">The chimpanzee group at Dudley Zoo consists of seven individuals. </s><s n="s2.5;p37.60">There are two mother/daughter dyads in the group, with both offspring seven years of age. </s><s n="s3.5;p37.60">Other adolescent females born to other adult females in the group have been removed in the last year because they were displaying aggressive behaviour, and so they could be added to breeding collections of chimpanzees. </s><s n="s4.5;p37.60">Anecdotal evidence from the chimpanzee caregivers suggests there is a hierarchy among the seven females, with one animal assuming the role of alpha. </s><s n="s5.5;p37.60">There is an indoor enclosure and permanent access to a large outdoor space. </s></p><p n="p38.60"><s n="s1.11;p38.60">Twycross Zoo has a group of eight chimpanzees, with two adult males. </s><s n="s2.11;p38.60">One of the males has recently been returned to the group after being removed for aggressive behaviour. </s><s n="s3.11;p38.60">He has now been castrated, and is also receiving hormone supplements to reduce aggression. </s><s n="s4.11;p38.60">There is an indoor enclosure and constant access to an outdoor space equipped with climbing apparatus. </s><s n="s5.11;p38.60">Whipsnade Zoo has a breeding group of seven chimpanzees which includes two adult males. </s><s n="s6.11;p38.60">The chimps have a 0.6 hectare naturalistic outdoor enclosure with trees and a climbing frame, and large indoor quarters. </s><s n="s7.11;p38.60">Edinburgh Zoo has a group of eleven chimpanzees of mixed sexes; three adult males, two juvenile males and six females. </s><s n="s8.11;p38.60">Colchester Zoo has a mixed group of chimpanzees; three males and four females. </s><s n="s9.11;p38.60">In a review of party sizes in different communities of chimpanzees, Boesch (1996) found an average party size of 5.7 individuals (averages ranged from 4.0 to 8.3). </s><s n="s10.11;p38.60">The group sizes in my proposed study range from 7 to 11 (mean 8.6), therefore the average aligns with the top end of the average seen in the wild. </s><s n="s11.11;p38.60">It is hoped that by keeping the range small, the group size will be less of a factor than if comparisons were made with much larger groups. </s></p></div3><div3><head rend="italic">Site visit and pilot study at Dudley Zoo</head><p n="p39.60"><s n="s1.2;p39.60">I will conduct a two-week pilot study at Dudley Zoo in December 2005 to practise using my data check-sheets and ethogram, and make refinements where necessary. </s><s n="s2.2;p39.60">I will also familiarise myself with the process of making observations and establish a relationship with staff. </s></p><p n="p40.60"><s n="s1.10;p40.60">I visited Dudley Zoo during October 2005 for a preliminary investigation of the site. </s><s n="s2.10;p40.60">The chimpanzees have access to the inside and outside areas all day by means of a cage tunnel. </s><s n="s3.10;p40.60">In order for observers to move from the observation area of the outside space to the indoor enclosure it is necessary to walk all the way around the building, which takes around three minutes. </s><s n="s4.10;p40.60">After four hours of observations, and after a conversation with the primary chimpanzee caregiver, it became clear that the outside space was rarely utilised and the chimpanzees preferred to remain indoors. </s><s n="s5.10;p40.60">Indeed this is an issue that the caregivers would like to address. </s><s n="s6.10;p40.60">The observation windows for the outside enclosure are positioned in areas where there are a lot of blind spots. </s><s n="s7.10;p40.60">The windows are either too high or too low for me to see properly. </s><s n="s8.10;p40.60">A second look-out point is situated a long distance away, and I would anticipate difficulties identifying the animals from that location. </s><s n="s9.10;p40.60">I will expect to be based mostly indoors for the duration of my study, though if the animals are outside for longer than five minutes I will cease the observation bout and move outside to begin a new session. </s><s n="s10.10;p40.60">It will be necessary to make careful note of which location I am observing from, as there are different substrates and heights available in the two spaces. </s></p><p n="p41.60"><s n="s1.6;p41.60">In my opinion the chimpanzee exhibit at Dudley Zoo is not very well signposted, and it is also a long way and in the opposite direction from all the other zoo exhibits. </s><s n="s2.6;p41.60">These factors mean that, according to anecdotal evidence, there are comparatively fewer visitors to the chimpanzee area than to other parts of the zoo. </s><s n="s3.6;p41.60">I will make a note of the presence of human visitors in my observations. </s><s n="s4.6;p41.60">I will then be able to give overall numbers of zoo visitors, which may be useful information to the zoo management. </s><s n="s5.6;p41.60">I will also examine if chimpanzee activity increases, decreases or remains the same given the presence of onlookers. </s><s n="s6.6;p41.60">I should then be able to carry out a non-parametric chi-square analysis based on the null hypothesis that the presence of visitors does not impact the amount of activity carried out by the chimpanzees. </s></p></div3><div3><head rend="italic">Preliminary investigations at four other locations</head><p n="p42.60"><s n="s1.10;p42.60">I plan to spend a minimum of three days at each of the other four zoos before beginning my two-week observation period at each location, starting in May 2006. </s><s n="s2.10;p42.60">During preliminary visits to the zoos I will take digital photographs of each of the chimpanzees, and in the presence of the caregivers write down the names, ages and sexes of those individuals. </s><s n="s3.10;p42.60">I will then be able to compile an identification sheet for each chimpanzee, and I will spend the days of my preliminary unrecorded observations recognising the group members. </s><s n="s4.10;p42.60">I have experience of identifying chimpanzees from previous work and I am confident this can be accomplished within the time frame. </s><s n="s5.10;p42.60">I can compile a family tree and group history from zoo records and caregiver narratives. </s><s n="s6.10;p42.60">Zoo keepers will also be able to provide anecdotal evidence of the chimpanzee hierarchy and group relationships, which I can be aware of whilst carrying out quantitative analysis. </s><s n="s7.10;p42.60">During this period of observation I will be able to refine my ethogram to include any additional behaviours or variables not yet encountered. </s><s n="s8.10;p42.60">Throughout the course of the research I will be open to making changes, as long as they do not affect the viability of the study. </s><s n="s9.10;p42.60">During the preliminary phase I will also be able to observe the schedule at the zoo, including the arrival of the keepers, the first feeding session, the opening of cages, the giving of extra feeds, the arrival of the first visitors, visitor numbers throughout the day, any other keeper involvement, later feeds, removal into night cages and sleeping activity. </s><s n="s10.10;p42.60">I plan to stay throughout the entire day and into the evening during these initial stages to understand the schedule. </s></p></div3><div3><head rend="italic">Ethogram</head><table id="BAWE_3063c-tab.002"><head rend="italic">Bettinger (2002), Kingal. (1980), McLennan (2003), McQuitty (1970) and Nishidaal. (1999)</head><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p43.60"/></div3><div3><head rend="italic">Sampling methods</head><p n="p44.60"><s n="s1.1;p44.60">I will be using non-invasive observations in accordance with guidelines on behavioural research (Association for the Study of Animal Behaviour, 2003). </s></p><p n="p45.60"><s n="s1.3;p45.60">I needed to choose between using ad libitum focal sampling and focal animal sampling. </s><s n="s2.3;p45.60">Having used ad libitum sampling during a short experimental study of chimpanzees, I concur with Bernstein (1991) that less noticeable behaviour and less conspicuous individuals tend to be missed out in the ad libitum observations. </s><s n="s3.3;p45.60">However, ad libitum observations could be of more use in a preliminary study to test my ethogram and suggest refinements. </s></p><p n="p46.60"><s n="s1.3;p46.60">I plan to utilise a focal instantaneous sampling method as the main type of date collection. </s><s n="s2.3;p46.60">Having experimented with one-minute intervals and found the recordings to miss some observations, I will use 30 second intervals for 15 minutes at a time. </s><s n="s3.3;p46.60">This follows the recommendation of Martin and Bateson (1993, p90) who suggest "The shorter the sample interval, the more accurate instantaneous sampling is at estimating duration and the more closely it resembles continuous recording". </s></p><p n="p47.60"><s n="s1.2;p47.60">As I am only planning to analyse female chimpanzee behaviour, it is important to bear in mind that more hours of observation time will be needed at Dudley Zoo for seven females than for smaller numbers of females at the other zoos. </s><s n="s2.2;p47.60">I will keep a close watch on how many hours of observation each individual has received to make sure the numbers correlate. </s></p><p n="p48.60"><s n="s1.1;p48.60">Altmann (1974, p213) suggests that focal animal sampling may exclude acts directed at the individual by others, so I also include in the ethogram a column to note the proximity to other individuals, approaches made to and by other individuals and the others involved in active behaviours such as grooming, playing and vocalisations. </s></p><p n="p49.60"><s n="s1.4;p49.60">I plan to choose the focal animal in a rotating random order. </s><s n="s2.4;p49.60">I have experimented using a random number programme such as <seg type="URL" n="www.random.org"/>. </s><s n="s3.4;p49.60">For Dudley Zoo for example, I would attribute each of the seven chimpanzees a number, then on the generator programme use 1 as my lowest number and 7 as my highest. </s><s n="s4.4;p49.60">I would then generate a randomised sequence on the programme, to give me the pattern for observations. </s></p><p n="p50.60"><s n="s1.1;p50.60">I will conduct 15-minute focal samples before changing animal. </s></p><p n="p51.60"><s n="s1.2;p51.60">At the same time I will do five-minute interval scans of the whole group. </s><s n="s2.2;p51.60">Altmann (1974) suggests it is possible to do multiple sampling methods, for example taking instantaneous samples of nearest animals whilst doing focal animal behaviour samples of one individual, or to do all occurrences notations for the whole social group at the same time as focal animal sampling. </s></p><p n="p52.60"><s n="s1.2;p52.60">I plan to spread my observations across the whole day, given reports that chimpanzees are more active in the mornings and evenings, and less active in the middle of the day (Doran, 1997). </s><s n="s2.2;p52.60">I would not wish to bias the findings by only conducting observations at certain times. </s></p></div3><div3><head rend="italic">Statistical analysis</head><p n="p53.60"><s n="s1.4;p53.60">With a sample of five chimpanzee groups it should be possible to make a statistical analysis of the results. </s><s n="s2.4;p53.60">With a chi-square test for example, "many statisticians recommend a certain minimum <hi rend="italic">expected frequency</hi> (fe) per cell. </s><s n="s3.4;p53.60">A very conservative rule of thumb is that fe must always be equal to or greater than 5" (Kranzler and Moursund, 1995, p 103). </s><s n="s4.4;p53.60">I plan to begin the analysis and write-up of results in August 2006. </s></p></div3></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">Section 5: Local involvement</head><div2><head rend="underlined bold">How will local communities/organisations/individuals be involved in the project? </head><p n="p54.60"><s n="s1.7;p54.60">The research departments in each of the five zoos have been involved in approving my proposal, after discussing my ideas with the animal caregivers. </s><s n="s2.7;p54.60">I will maintain regular contact with the research co-ordinators during the preliminary and full undertaking of the project, and use the research departments to obtain information deemed necessary for my work. </s><s n="s3.7;p54.60">They will be able to provide previous research done on the same group of animals, and information on kin relationships, immigration/emigration within the group, contraception and medication histories. </s><s n="s4.7;p54.60">During the preliminary stage of my investigation I have obtained permission to shadow a keeper, so that I can understand the daily schedule of keeper activity involving the chimpanzees. </s><s n="s5.7;p54.60">This will allow me to appreciate the times that the chimpanzees are let in/out of their sleeping quarters, the times for feeding and foraging and other keeper interactions during the day. </s><s n="s6.7;p54.60">In addition, this time of shadowing will provide me the invaluable opportunity to talk to the keepers, and gain considerable knowledge from the primary caregivers. </s><s n="s7.7;p54.60">They will be able to provide useful background knowledge on the life histories, social structure and individual personalities of the chimpanzees. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined bold">In what ways will local communities, organisations or individuals benefit from this project? </head><p n="p55.60"><s n="s1.4;p55.60">I have already had an enthusiastic response from keepers about finding out the activity budget for chimpanzees, as they have expressed informal concern about low levels of activity. </s><s n="s2.4;p55.60">With a viable study, these concerns can either be debunked or validated, and brought to the attention of managers. </s><s n="s3.4;p55.60">Given the relatively few studies on female chimpanzee behaviour, any study that gives dedicated attention to this area of research may have a value. </s><s n="s4.4;p55.60">Studies of social behaviour among zoo chimpanzees may also add to the understanding among zoo keepers and managers about the animals in their care. </s></p><p n="p56.60"><s n="s1.2;p56.60">With five zoos involved in this project, there will be many different animal husbandry practises to compare. </s><s n="s2.2;p56.60">As an exercise in information-sharing all of the zoos will have access to the findings, and may wish to incorporate some of the caregiving methods used by other institutions. </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="underlined bold">Section 6: Evaluation and dissemination</head><div2><head rend="underlined bold">How do you intend to monitor and evaluate progress during the project and how will you determine the eventual success of this project? </head><p n="p57.60"><s n="s1.9;p57.60">During the course of the project I will make detailed observations on the groups of chimpanzees using personally-compiled check sheets and my own ethogram. </s><s n="s2.9;p57.60">I will use the pilot study to monitor that I am able to input data correctly and have an ethogram that covers all the behaviours I wish to capture. </s><s n="s3.9;p57.60">I will make collations of my observations which can then be ordered for input into a computer spreadsheet. </s><s n="s4.9;p57.60">I will be keeping a careful tally of how many hours of observation each chimpanzee has received to make sure that the observation time is even and statistically viable. </s><s n="s5.9;p57.60">I will be happy to share my initial thoughts with the caregivers as I conduct observations, but I will wait until the results have been processed before making any evaluation to managers. </s><s n="s6.9;p57.60">At the end of the project I hope to be able to have an analysis of the activity budgets and behavioural patterns of five groups of chimpanzees. </s><s n="s7.9;p57.60">Using statistical analysis I hope to be able to produce a comparison of female chimpanzees housed in an all-female group and housed in a mixed-sex environment. </s><s n="s8.9;p57.60">I hope to be able to validate or reject the hypothesis that females in the single-sex housing condition are less active than females with a male presence. </s><s n="s9.9;p57.60">I will consider the project successful if I am able to use my results to inform zoo managers about the rates of activity in their captive chimpanzee groups, in order to inform discussions about group structure. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="underlined bold">How do you intend to disseminate your results at the end of the project? In particular, how will you ensure that information from and about this project reaches local communities and/or organisations? </head><p n="p58.60"><s n="s1.5;p58.60">It is my intention to circulate a copy of my completed MSc dissertation to each of the five participating zoos. </s><s n="s2.5;p58.60">As a trained journalist, I also feel comfortable writing a short summary of my report, which I will submit to the MSc Primate Conservation course publication; Canopy. </s><s n="s3.5;p58.60">This summary article will also be offered to each of the five zoos for possible publication in their in-house journals. </s><s n="s4.5;p58.60">As many of the zoos also feature articles about research projects on their websites I would be happy to utilise my journalistic experience to write an article about my project and report my findings. </s><s n="s5.5;p58.60">If required, I would also be happy to meet with each of the research co-ordinators at the zoos to give a presentation on my findings. </s></p><p n="p59.60"><s n="s1.1;p59.60">If my application for funding is successful I will of course provide summaries and completed projects to the funding bodies. </s></p><p n="p60.60"><s n="s1.1;p60.60">I would also offer to give a presentation at the Winter 2006 meeting of the Primate Society of Great Britain, of which I am a student member. </s></p></div2></div1></body><back/></text></TEI.2>
