<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_3064i" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Research Proposal 2: Qualitative study using semi-structured interviews</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">
Student number in doc header. Module name and number in doc footer.
</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">2</p><p n="date">2005-04</p><p n="module title">Research Methods and Analysis</p><p n="module code">U43744</p><p n="genre family">Proposal</p><p n="discipline">Health</p><p n="disciplinary group">LS</p><p n="grade">D</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">2168</p><p n="number of s-units">90</p><p n="number of p">38</p><p n="number of tables">2</p><p n="number of figures">0</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">2</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">12</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">24.1</p><p n="average s-units per p">2.4</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">f</p><p n="year of birth">1984</p><p n="first language">English</p><p n="education">UKa</p><p n="course">BSc Occupational Therapy</p><p n="student ID">3064</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><docTitle><titlePart rend="underlined">Research Proposal 2: Qualitative Study using semi-structured interviews</titlePart></docTitle></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Exploratory research question</head><p n="p1.38"><s n="s1.1;p1.38">How do people with rheumatoid arthritis (RA) of the hand feel about the exercise programme and splinting regime they are currently following? </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Research questions</head><p rend="ordered" n="p2.38"><s n="s1.1;p2.38">1. Why do some patients attend appointments to see the occupational therapist (OT), while some do not? </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p3.38"><s n="s1.1;p3.38">2. Why do some patients follow the exercise programme and splinting regime as prescribed by the OT, while some do not? </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p4.38"><s n="s1.2;p4.38">3. </s><s n="s2.2;p4.38">In what ways do the patients think the regime is useful in helping the symptoms of their RA? </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Method:</head><div2><head rend="bold">Sample</head><p n="p5.38"><s n="s1.3;p5.38">The sample will consist of between 30 and 40 patients with RA of the hand who attend one of three hand clinics in and around a major city, to see the occupational therapist (OT). </s><s n="s2.3;p5.38">The sampling technique will be 'homogenous sampling' which explores a particular subgroup of people (Patton, 1990, cited in Grbich, 1999). </s><s n="s3.3;p5.38">The sample size will be determined once saturation point within the data analysis has been reached, this is when further data collection appears to add no new information to that already gathered (Robson, 2002; Sim and Wright, 2000). </s></p><p n="p6.38"><s n="s1.5;p6.38">The researcher will not be employed at the clinics to minimise bias. </s><s n="s2.5;p6.38">(Sim and Wright, 2000). </s><s n="s3.5;p6.38">Potential participants will be given an information sheet inviting them to participate in the study and explaining the nature of their participation (See 'Data collection'). </s><s n="s4.5;p6.38">Participants will be gathered over a period of 6 months to ensure a large enough number of participants can be obtained, until saturation point is reached (Robson, 2002; Streubert and Rinaldi Carpenter, 1995). </s><s n="s5.5;p6.38">Collecting data over a prolonged period can also ensure a range of participants are involved which will increase credibility (Taylor, 2000). </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Design </head><p n="p7.38"><s n="s1.6;p7.38">Qualitative research is used to 'understand the meanings, experience, and phenomena as they evolve in the natural setting' (Depoy and Gitlin, 1994, cited in Taylor, 2000, p101). </s><s n="s2.6;p7.38">The qualitative research approach to be used for this study is naturalistic, phenomenological research. </s><s n="s3.6;p7.38">This focuses on understanding and interpreting human experience (Depoy and Gitlin, 1998). </s><s n="s4.6;p7.38">Particular phenomena, events or experiences are explored in an attempt to understand an individuals' lived experience (Spiegelberg, 1975, cited in Streubert and Rinaldi Carpenter, 1995; Taylor, 2000). </s><s n="s5.6;p7.38">Crotty (1996, cited in Grbich, 1999) gives 5 steps involved in the phenomenological research process. </s><s n="s6.6;p7.38">(See table 1). </s></p><table id="BAWE_3064i-tab.001"><head><hi rend="italic">Table 1</hi> . The 5 steps involved in the phenomenological research process. (Crotty, 1996, cited in Grbich, 1999)</head><row><cell/></row></table><p n="p8.38"><s n="s1.2;p8.38">Naturalistic inquiry takes a holistic perspective and postulates that those who have the experiences are most knowledgeable about them (Depoy and Gitlin, 1998). </s><s n="s2.2;p8.38">Therefore, semi-structured interviews will be conducted, asking the patients themselves about their experiences. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Data Collection</head><p n="p9.38"><s n="s1.3;p9.38">To increase credibility, data will be collected using a variety of research methods, and from different sources. </s><s n="s2.3;p9.38">This process in know as triangulation and can enhance the rigour of the research (Mays and Pope, 2000; Taylor, 2000; Robson, 2002). </s><s n="s3.3;p9.38">Therefore, three hand clinics are being included in this study rather than one, and in order to answer the research questions, three forms of data collection will be conducted: </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p10.38"><s n="s1.3;p10.38">One to one semi-structured interviews with participants, conducted according to a list of topics to be covered in an interview guide. </s><s n="s2.3;p10.38">(See 'Research questions'). </s><s n="s3.3;p10.38">The interviews will be audio taped with the participants' consent, and subsequently transcribed. </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p11.38"><s n="s1.1;p11.38">Participants will be asked to keep a diary for 4 weeks, to keep a record of when/if they practice the exercise and splinting regime in their own time, and when/if they attend appointments to see the OT. They will also write about their feelings about their treatment related to appointments, the regime and daily life activities throughout the weeks. </s></p><p rend="ordered" n="p12.38"><s n="s1.2;p12.38">A researchers diary will be kept, to enable readers of the research to understand 'how the researcher thinks, acts, interacts with and feels about the participants in the project, and how the researchers concerns and values affect the data' (Grbich, 1999, p89). </s><s n="s2.2;p12.38">The suspension of beliefs, assumptions and biases about the phenomena under investigation is known as 'phenomenological reduction' (Streubert and Rinaldi Carpenter, 1995). </s></p><div2><head rend="italic">Setting</head><p n="p13.38"><s n="s1.1;p13.38">Interviews, and meetings with participants to look at diaries will take place in the particular hand clinic the participant attends, so that the environment is familiar to them (Mays and Pope, 2000; Sim and Wright, 2000). </s></p><div3><head rend="italic">Inclusion and exclusion criteria</head><list type="bulleted"><item>The criteria for the selection of participants are as follows:</item><item>Aged between 25 and 85 years </item><item>Must have a diagnosis of RA of the hand</item><item>Must have been given appointment(s) with an OT at a hand clinic to undertake an exercise and splinting treatment regime to help to manage symptoms of RA</item><item>Must be able to give informed consent </item><item>Must be able to communicate adequately </item><item>Must be willing to keep a diary over 4 weeks. (See 'Data collection')</item><item>Must be willing to talk to a researcher about their appointments and treatment regime, and about their diary for up to an hour on two separate occasions, and for their responses to be audio taped. </item></list><list type="bulleted"><item>Exclusion criteria:</item><item>Serious ill-health or pathology </item><item>Recent surgery</item><item>Pregnancy</item><item>Diagnosis of clinical depression or other psychiatric pathology</item><item>(Buckeldee and McMahon, 1994; Bury and Mead, 1998; Sim and Wright, 2000).</item></list><p n="p14.38"/></div3></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Interviews</head><p n="p15.38"><s n="s1.2;p15.38">Participants will be invited to participate in one to one interviews with the researcher. </s><s n="s2.2;p15.38">The interviewer's appearance should be similar to the interviewee's so as not to come across as too authoritative, and the interviewer should try to make the interviewee comfortable in expressing their true experiences (Robson, 2002; Streubert and Rinaldi Carpenter, 1995). </s></p><p n="p16.38"><s n="s1.4;p16.38">Semi-structured interviews are appropriate where a study focuses on the meaning of particular phenomena to the participants (King, 1994, cited in Grbich, 1999); they are therefore the most appropriate interview design for this study. </s><s n="s2.4;p16.38">Semi-structured interviews have predetermined questions, but the order in which they are asked can be modified based on what the interviewer feels is most appropriate. </s><s n="s3.4;p16.38">The wording, order and explanations of the questions can vary, and questions which seem inappropriate with a particular interviewee can be omitted, or additional ones added (Robson, 2002). </s><s n="s4.4;p16.38">The design of semi-structured interviews enables interviewees to elaborate on their answers, and the interviewer to ask probing questions, so comprehensive data can be obtained (See table 2, 'The 4 Components of Asking'). </s></p><p n="p17.38"><s n="s1.5;p17.38">In the initial interview, participants will be asked open questions about their attending of appointments and whether they follow the exercise and splinting regime, and in what ways they think it helps. </s><s n="s2.5;p17.38">Further and probing questions will be asked, depending on the answers given. </s><s n="s3.5;p17.38">Probes are neutral statements which do not bias the subject to respond in any particular way. </s><s n="s4.5;p17.38">They are used to encourage more information, or elaborations, for example, "tell me more about it" (Depoy and Gitlin, 1998). </s><s n="s5.5;p17.38">Summary questions are also useful at the end of an interview, to enable the interviewer to check they have understood the interviewee correctly (Grbich, 1999). </s></p><p n="p18.38"><s n="s1.4;p18.38">The second interview will provide an opportunity to expand, verify and add descriptions to the phenomena being researched. </s><s n="s2.4;p18.38">The researcher can refer to limited or inadequately described information to gain further descriptions. </s><s n="s3.4;p18.38">Often, the participants will also have additional thoughts about the phenomena, following the initial interview (Streubert and Rinaldi Carpenter, 1995). </s><s n="s4.4;p18.38">The second interview will take place after the 4 weeks that the participant has kept a diary, and will also be an opportunity to discuss what is written in the diary. </s></p><table id="BAWE_3064i-tab.002"><row><cell/></row></table><div2><head rend="italic">Audio taping</head><p n="p19.38"><s n="s1.2;p19.38">Audio taping is a fundamental data-recording strategy in naturalistic inquiry. </s><s n="s2.2;p19.38">Participants must be informed that they are being recorded, so they can give their consent, and they are also to be informed that confidentiality will be maintained, and that they can request the audio-taping to cease at any point (Depoy and Gitlin, 1998). </s></p><p n="p20.38"><s n="s1.4;p20.38">Grbich (1999) notes that there is a tendency for respondents to engage in casual conversation on the topic, once the tape recorder has stopped, commenting reflectively on what they have just said. </s><s n="s2.4;p20.38">The author says that this 'off-the-record' data often allows the interviewer to see what is behind the interviewee's recorded responses, and the researcher should make a mental note of what had been said and write up these observations as soon as possible after the interview. </s><s n="s3.4;p20.38">However, doing this means that information is from the researcher's memory, and not from a reliable source; therefore it could have been misinterpreted and would lead to incorrect data. </s><s n="s4.4;p20.38">For the purpose of this study, this will not be recommended; instead, the interviewer will be encouraged to write about any such events in their diary. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="italic">Transcribing the interviews and field notes</head><p n="p21.38"><s n="s1.3;p21.38">The interviewer will transcribe the interviews verbatim from the audio tapes rather than during the interview. </s><s n="s2.3;p21.38">However, whilst in the interviews, notes will be kept of how the interviewee expresses themselves in other ways in relation to the questions being asked, for example, if they are upset, laughing, or demonstrating with their hands. </s><s n="s3.3;p21.38">Any relevant expressions will subsequently be added to the transcriptions to give further depth (Robson, 2002; Streubert and Rinaldi Carpenter, 1995). </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Ethical issues</head><p n="p22.38"><s n="s1.1;p22.38">Permission has been gained from the hand clinics to invite RA patients to take part in the study, explaining that the purpose of the study is to improve practice for all participants (Winter and Munn-Giddings, 2001). </s></p><p n="p23.38"><s n="s1.2;p23.38">There are a number of issues in phenomenological research due to its personal nature, and consent should be viewed as an ongoing process (Streubert and Rinaldi Carpenter, 1995). </s><s n="s2.2;p23.38">A one page explanatory letter will be sent to all potential participants including the following information: </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p24.38"><s n="s1.1;p24.38">The aims of the study and the nature of their involvement </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p25.38"><s n="s1.1;p25.38">Contact names, addresses and telephone numbers in case of queries or concerns </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p26.38"><s n="s1.1;p26.38">Clarification that the participant is free to leave the study at any time and is not obliged to answer any questions they feel uncomfortable with </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p27.38"><s n="s1.1;p27.38">Information gathered will be confidential and anonymous and measures will be taken to prevent data being linked with a specific participant </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p28.38"><s n="s1.1;p28.38">Any potential harm the participant may suffer </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p29.38"><s n="s1.1;p29.38">Should any of the above change, participants will be contacted and further permission sought </s></p><p n="p30.38"><s n="s1.1;p30.38">A sign-off space will be included for the participant to sign if they have read and agreed to the previous stipulations </s></p><p n="p31.38"><s n="s1.1;p31.38">(Grbich, 1999; Kumar, 1996; Morton-Cooper, 2000; Robson, 2002) </s></p><p n="p32.38"><s n="s1.3;p32.38">Contact details of participants will also be requested. </s><s n="s2.3;p32.38">A copy of the signed consent form will be given to the participants (Robson, 2002). </s><s n="s3.3;p32.38">The researcher will then contact willing and eligible participants by telephone one week after they agree to participate, to arrange a time for the interviews to take place and to answer any questions the participants may have (Sim and Wright, 2000). </s></p><p n="p33.38"><s n="s1.2;p33.38">All tape recordings and diaries will be kept in a secure location within the researcher's university department and archived. </s><s n="s2.2;p33.38">Once data analysis is completed the key findings of the study will be fed back to the relevant staff at the hand clinics, and any participants who wish to know the information (Sim and Wright, 2000). </s></p><p n="p34.38"><s n="s1.1;p34.38">This proposal will be submitted to a Research Ethics Committee to gain approval before it is put into practice (Winter and Munn-Giddings, 2001; Robson, 2002). </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Analysis</head><p n="p35.38"><s n="s1.3;p35.38">Data analysis begins when data collection begins; they are inseparable processes (Streubert and Rinaldi Carpenter, 1995). </s><s n="s2.3;p35.38">Analysis will therefore take place throughout the research as an ongoing process (Taylor, 2000). </s><s n="s3.3;p35.38">Data analysis requires the researcher to become immersed in the data and in the phenomenon under investigation (Streubert and Rinaldi Carpenter, 1995). </s></p><p n="p36.38"><s n="s1.2;p36.38">A strategy to ensure credibility and trustworthiness of the data will be to involve participants in the analysis of the research, by giving them access to the transcribed data, and also the researcher's interpretations of it, and allowing them to comment on the research (Taylor, 2000). </s><s n="s2.2;p36.38">This is known as member checking (Mays and Pope, 2000; Robson, 2002). </s></p><p n="p37.38"><s n="s1.8;p37.38">The data will be analysed using thematic analysis. </s><s n="s2.8;p37.38">The themes to be concentrated on will be those that relate to the participants feelings about the exercise and splinting regime they are currently undertaking. </s><s n="s3.8;p37.38">The researcher will familiarise themselves with the data and listen to the tapes, whilst reading the transcriptions for accuracy. </s><s n="s4.8;p37.38">Significant statements and recurring themes will be identified and extracted (Streubert and Rinaldi Carpenter, 1995). </s><s n="s5.8;p37.38">The initial themes that emerge will be coded, described and categorised into broad 'higher themes' (Taylor, 2000; Streubert and Rinaldi Carpenter, 1995). </s><s n="s6.8;p37.38">There may be some interconnection between categories, and there may also be some data which may not fit neatly into the main themes of the analysis (Taylor, 2000). </s><s n="s7.8;p37.38">The researcher will note this for further analysis. </s><s n="s8.8;p37.38">Clusters of themes will be organised and compared to the original descriptions to validate them and examine discrepancies (Streubert and Rinaldi Carpenter, 1995). </s></p><p n="p38.38"><s n="s1.5;p38.38">A descriptive account of the phenomena under investigation will be produced and a theoretical explanation given (Ritchie, Spencer and O'Connor, 2003). </s><s n="s2.5;p38.38">These results will give an answer to the research question. </s><s n="s3.5;p38.38">Peer evaluation, member checking and audit will be used to review the research process to ensure dependability and validity (Taylor, 2000; Robson, 2002). </s><s n="s4.5;p38.38">This kind of research cannot be generalised. </s><s n="s5.5;p38.38">However, the insights and understandings of individuals' experiences gained from phenomenological research can be used as tools for reflection and evaluation of practice, and to enrich knowledge (Taylor, 2000; Mays and Pope, 2000). </s></p></div1></body><back><div1 type="bibliography"><head rend="bold">References</head><p>Buckeldee, J. and McMahon, R. (1994). <hi rend="italic">The Research Experience in Nursing.</hi> London: Chapman &amp; Hall.</p><p>Bury, T. and Mead, J. (1998). <hi rend="italic">Evidence Based Healthcare, A Practical Guide for Therapists.</hi> Oxford: Butterworth-Heinemann.</p><p>Depoy, E. and Gitlin, L.N. (1998). <hi rend="italic">Introduction to research. Understanding and applying multiple stratergies.</hi> 2<hi rend="sup">nd</hi> ed. London: Mosby.</p><p>Grbich, C. (1999). <hi rend="italic">Qualitative Research in Health. An Introduction.</hi> London: SAGE Publications.</p><p>Kumar, R. (1996). <hi rend="italic"> Research Methodology, A Step by Step Guide for Beginners.</hi> London: SAGE Publications.</p><p>Mays, N. and Pope, C. (2000). Qualitative Research in Health Care: Assessing quality in qualitative research. <hi rend="italic">BMJ. 320</hi>, 50-52.</p><p>Morton-Cooper, A. (2000). <hi rend="italic">Action Research in Health Care.</hi> London: Blackwell Sciences Ltd.</p><p>Ritchie, J., Spencer, L. and O'Connor, W. (2003). Carrying out Qualitative Analysis. In Ritchie, J. and Lewis, J. (Eds.), <hi rend="italic">Qualitative Research Practice: a guide for social science students and researchers.</hi> London: Sage.</p><p>Robson, C. (2002). <hi rend="italic">Real World Research.</hi> 2<hi rend="sup">nd</hi> ed. Oxford: Blackwell Publishing.</p><p>Sim, J. and Wright, C. (2000). <hi rend="italic">Research in health care. Concepts, designs and methods.</hi> Cheltenham: Stanley Thorne Ltd.</p><p>Streubert, H. J. and Rinaldi Carpenter, D. (1995). <hi rend="italic">Qualitative Research in Nursing, Advancing the Humanistic Imperative.</hi> Philadelphia: J. B. Lippincott Company.</p><p>Taylor, M. C. (2000). <hi rend="italic">Evidence-Based Practice for Occupational Therapists.</hi> Oxford: Blackwell Science Ltd.</p><p>Winter, R. and Munn-Giddings, C. (2001). <hi rend="italic">A Handbook for Action Research in Health and Social Care.</hi> London: Routledge.</p></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
