<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_3066a" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An analysis of the formal features of Aphra Behn's 'Song: ~On her lovin two equally'</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note/></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">1</p><p n="date">2006-02</p><p n="module title">Approaching Poetry</p><p n="module code">U67010</p><p n="genre family">Essay</p><p n="discipline">English</p><p n="disciplinary group">AH</p><p n="grade">M</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">516</p><p n="number of s-units">27</p><p n="number of p">6</p><p n="number of tables">0</p><p n="number of figures">0</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">0</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">0</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">19.1</p><p n="average s-units per p">4.5</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">f</p><p n="year of birth">1987</p><p n="first language">English</p><p n="education">UKa</p><p n="course">BA English Studies and Sociology</p><p n="student ID">3066</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><docTitle><titlePart rend="underlined bold">An Analysis of the Formal Features of Aphra Behn's 'Song: On Her Loving Two Equally'</titlePart></docTitle></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="section"><p n="p1.6"><s n="s1.3;p1.6">Aphra Behn begins this poem by relating the narrator's passion to a stream, through the use of metaphorical language. </s><s n="s2.3;p1.6">The second line creates an image of a fork in the stream as it splits into different, but equal courses. </s><s n="s3.3;p1.6">This appropriately summarises the theme of the poem; the narrator has to decide on a course to take, meaning she has to choose either Damon or Alexis. </s></p><p n="p2.6"><s n="s1.3;p2.6">In terms of rhyme scheme, the first and third stanzas consist of three rhyming couplets (aabbcc). </s><s n="s2.3;p2.6">This type of rhyme scheme is sometimes referred to as 'metrically accelerated rhyme' - the rhyme words are as close together as possible, speeding up the pace of the poem. </s><s n="s3.3;p2.6">The fast pace suggests a rapid stream of thought as the narrator, or persona, tries to make sense of her complex situation. </s></p><p n="p3.6"><s n="s1.3;p3.6">The rhyme scheme changes to ababcc in the second stanza, and consequently there is a break from rhyming couplets. </s><s n="s2.3;p3.6">This highlights the unexpected sound of 'mourn' at the end of the second line. </s><s n="s3.3;p3.6">The idea of mourning is central to the poem, as it helps relate a sense of longing and sadness. </s></p><p n="p4.6"><s n="s1.8;p4.6">There is a fairly equal balance of perfect and imperfect rhyme throughout the poem, although most of the imperfect rhyme occurs in the last stanza (god / blood and back / take). </s><s n="s2.8;p4.6">These are examples of pararhyme; the vowel sounds differ, but the consonants remain the same (in this case'd' and 'k'). </s><s n="s3.8;p4.6">Typically half or imperfect rhyme creates a disconcerting feel, and this is true for the last stanza. </s><s n="s4.8;p4.6">The increasing sense of tension and frustration is reinforced further by the question mark at the end of the fourth line. </s><s n="s5.8;p4.6">This is apt for the subject of the poem, as there is no satisfying conclusion. </s><s n="s6.8;p4.6">The narrator cannot choose between her two lovers, so the poem ends on a hopeless and resigned note. </s><s n="s7.8;p4.6">Despite the full rhyme in the final lines of the poem (crost / lost), the words simply reinforce each other and heighten the sense of loss and disillusionment. </s><s n="s8.8;p4.6">'Crost' is a form of 'crossed', and in the phrase "all my hopes are crost" it probably meant 'obliterated'. </s></p><p n="p5.6"><s n="s1.4;p5.6">Another instance of full rhyme that is more disturbing than agreeable is 'heart / part' in the first stanza. </s><s n="s2.4;p5.6">Although the words are acoustically similar, they clash in terms of meaning. </s><s n="s3.4;p5.6">In this context the pairing of 'heart' and 'part' suggests something that should be complete, but is in fact separated. </s><s n="s4.4;p5.6">This could be referred to as 'counter-semantic' rhyme, because the connotations of 'part' question those of 'heart'. </s></p><p n="p6.6"><s n="s1.6;p6.6">Generally the poem is written in iambic tetrameter, with the last line of each stanza in iambic pentameter. </s><s n="s2.6;p6.6">Usually the second syllable of each line is emphasised, but there are some exceptions, such as the first line of the third stanza. </s><s n="s3.6;p6.6">In this case the first syllable 'cure' is stressed. </s><s n="s4.6;p6.6">This is a particularly significant point in the poem as it marks a change in tone. </s><s n="s5.6;p6.6">The third stanza begins commanding Cupid to take action. </s><s n="s6.6;p6.6">It signals a break from the more reflective nature of the preceding stanzas and offers the reader some sort of conclusion. </s></p></div1></body><back/></text></TEI.2>
