<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_3066d" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Discuss the use of time in ­two out of the three major literary genres (poetry, drama and the novel) represented on the course</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">Language used in quote: <foreign id="English">English</foreign></note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">1</p><p n="date">2006-04</p><p n="module title">Reading Narrative</p><p n="module code">U67011</p><p n="genre family">Essay</p><p n="discipline">English</p><p n="disciplinary group">AH</p><p n="grade">M</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">1603</p><p n="number of s-units">78</p><p n="number of p">16</p><p n="number of tables">0</p><p n="number of figures">0</p><p n="number of block quotes">3</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">0</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">0</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">20.6</p><p n="average s-units per p">4.9</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">f</p><p n="year of birth">1987</p><p n="first language">English</p><p n="education">UKa</p><p n="course">BA English Studies and Sociology</p><p n="student ID">3066</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><docTitle><titlePart rend="underlined bold">2. Discuss the use of time in two out of the three major literary genres (poetry, drama and the novel) represented on the course. </titlePart></docTitle></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="section"><p n="p1.16"><s n="s1.7;p1.16">Is the use of time in narrative important? </s><s n="s2.7;p1.16">If so, why? </s><s n="s3.7;p1.16">Before these questions can be discussed in further detail, first it is necessary to clarify what narrative is. </s><s n="s4.7;p1.16">Simply put, a narrative is a story. </s><s n="s5.7;p1.16">How a writer, poet or playwright chooses to use time affects how the story is told, for example the events can be related in a simple, chronological order or with the use of flashbacks. </s><s n="s6.7;p1.16">Time is, in essence, a structural device that can be used to achieve a deliberate affect on a reader or audience. </s><s n="s7.7;p1.16">The concept of 'time' discussed in this essay can be defined as a component of a story, or a structural tool. </s></p><p n="p2.16"><s n="s1.6;p2.16">E. M. </s><s n="s2.6;p2.16">Forster certainly saw time as an important element of narrative. </s><s n="s3.6;p2.16">"In the novel", he says, "the allegiance to time is imperative: no novel could be written without it"<ref target="BAWE_3066d-ftnote.001"/>. </s><s n="s4.6;p2.16">But is the same true for a play? </s><s n="s5.6;p2.16">A time sequence is still present in a plot, although, again using Forster's terminology, "the sense of causality overshadows it"<ref target="BAWE_3066d-ftnote.002"/>. </s><s n="s6.6;p2.16">It is easier to create a precise sense of time in a novel than in a play, simply because there is a narrator throughout. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3066d-ftnote.001"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">E. M. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">Forster, <hi rend="underlined">Aspects of the Novel</hi> (London, Edward Arnold Publishers Ltd, 1974) p.19 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3066d-ftnote.002"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ibid., p.60 </s></p></note><p n="p3.16"><s n="s1.3;p3.16">Perhaps inevitably then, the use of time differs across literary genres. </s><s n="s2.3;p3.16">This essay aims to compare the use of time in Shakespeare's <hi rend="italic">The Winter's Tale</hi> (1611) and Jane Austen's <hi rend="italic">Emma</hi> (1816). </s><s n="s3.3;p3.16">Both have revolutionised the use of time in narrative to some extent, and so provide interesting texts for discussion. </s></p><p n="p4.16"><s n="s1.3;p4.16">Before Shakespeare, Renaissance dramatists were expected to comply with Aristotle's 'Three Unities'. </s><s n="s2.3;p4.16">Aristotle recommended that the events in a play should occur over a time scale of no more than twenty-four hours (the 'unity of time'). </s><s n="s3.3;p4.16">Shakespeare deliberately ridicules the 'unity of time' in <hi rend="italic">The Winter's Tale</hi> - it is referred to with an ironic tone in The Chorus of Time; </s></p><quote lang="English">"Impute it not a crime / To me or my swift passage that I slide / O'er sixteen years...since it is in my power / To o'erthrow law" (IV i 4-8) </quote><p n="p5.16"><s n="s1.6;p5.16">The phrase "impute it not a crime" (IV i 4) tells us that Shakespeare is knowingly breaking the rule of the 'unity of time'. </s><s n="s2.6;p5.16">This is not the first occasion on which Shakespeare refuses to abide by the conventional use of time in Renaissance drama. </s><s n="s3.6;p5.16">Neither is this his only play that has a choric narrator. </s><s n="s4.6;p5.16">Shakespeare also uses choric narrators in <hi rend="italic">Pericles</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Henry V</hi>, but it is the fact that the narrator in <hi rend="italic">The Winter's Tale</hi> is the personification of time itself that has interested critics. </s><s n="s5.6;p5.16">Shakespeare's unique treatment of time in <hi rend="italic">The Winter's Tale</hi> is largely responsible for the play's originality as a whole. </s><s n="s6.6;p5.16">Through disregarding the 'unity of time' and using time to function as a narrator, Shakespeare has more freedom to explore the nature of time and its effects. </s></p><p n="p6.16"><s n="s1.6;p6.16">Far from being controversial, Austen's use of time as a structural factor in <hi rend="italic">Emma</hi> is typical of the early novel. </s><s n="s2.6;p6.16">Though as the term 'novel' means 'new', we would expect the genre itself to be innovative in some way. </s><s n="s3.6;p6.16">The novel was the first literary form that attempted to accurately depict everyday life, a characteristic that Ian Watt coined 'formal realism'. </s><s n="s4.6;p6.16">In terms of 'formal realism', the sense of time generated through a text can potentially add "a new dimension to reality"<ref target="BAWE_3066d-ftnote.003"/>. </s><s n="s5.6;p6.16">M. H. </s><s n="s6.6;p6.16">Abrams describes the aim of realistic fiction as follows; </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3066d-ftnote.003"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ian Watt, <hi rend="underlined">The Rise of the Novel</hi> (Middlesex, Penguin Books Ltd, 1963) p.25 </s></p></note><quote lang="English">"realistic fiction is written to give the effect that it represents life and the social world as it seems to the common reader"<ref target="BAWE_3066d-ftnote.004"/>.</quote><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3066d-ftnote.004"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.3;pn1.1">M. H. </s><s n="s2.3;pn1.1">Abrams, <hi rend="underlined">A Glossary of Literary Terms</hi> 7th ed. </s><s n="s3.3;pn1.1">(Boston, Heinle &amp; Heinle, 1999) p.260 </s></p></note><p n="p7.16"><s n="s1.3;p7.16">Austen uses time to do exactly this. </s><s n="s2.3;p7.16"><hi rend="italic">Emma</hi> is grounded in an ordinary, credible time scheme; the passing of time and the progression of the story are gradual and uninterrupted - just like in real life. </s><s n="s3.3;p7.16">This is effective at creating realism, because the characters in the novel experience time as the reader does. </s></p><p n="p8.16"><s n="s1.5;p8.16">Another structural feature of <hi rend="italic">Emma</hi> is that the reader is often informed of the time period that has passed since the last significant incident, either through dialogue or the narration. </s><s n="s2.5;p8.16">For example; "a week had not passed since Miss Hawkins's name was first mentioned in Highbury" (vol II chapter iv), and "a very few days had passed after this adventure, when..." (vol III chapter iv). </s><s n="s3.5;p8.16">This technique of frequently referring to the passing of time is essential for the progression of the story, because it constantly edges the narrative forward. </s><s n="s4.5;p8.16">This is ultimately the function of Shakespeare's choric narrators, although the major difference is that the progression in time is not gradual and constant as it is in the novel. </s><s n="s5.5;p8.16">Some critics maintain that the time gap of sixteen years gives the play a disjointed feel, perhaps like the 'year and a day' technique in fairytales and nursery rhymes. </s></p><p n="p9.16"><s n="s1.6;p9.16">The use of time can manipulate the interpretation of a text; for example, the world portrayed in it can be realistic or histrionic depending on the time scheme used. </s><s n="s2.6;p9.16">At one extreme, fairytales deliberately escape the notion of time - a classic quote to illustrate this point is the customary opening of 'Once upon a time...'. </s><s n="s3.6;p9.16">Similarly, Shakespeare refuses to be specific in his depiction of time in <hi rend="italic">The Winter's Tale</hi>. </s><s n="s4.6;p9.16">This is not to say that he disregards time as an issue. </s><s n="s5.6;p9.16">Time is referred to throughout the play using figurative language and imagery. </s><s n="s6.6;p9.16">For example, Camillo remarks; </s></p><quote lang="English">"they were trained together in their childhoods; and there rooted betwixt them such an affection which cannot choose but branch now" (I i 22-24) </quote><p n="p10.16"><s n="s1.7;p10.16">Shakespeare's choice of the word 'branch' is ambiguous. </s><s n="s2.7;p10.16">This is significant as it highlights the dual nature of time, both as a creator and a destroyer. </s><s n="s3.7;p10.16">On one hand 'branch' could be interpreted as to flourish or extend. </s><s n="s4.7;p10.16">These meanings have positive connotations and imply that time is a creator. </s><s n="s5.7;p10.16">However, 'branch' can also mean diverge or separate. </s><s n="s6.7;p10.16">This interpretation gives a more negative view of time as a destroyer. </s><s n="s7.7;p10.16">This is equally true for the somewhat paradoxical statement in The Chorus of Time - Shakespeare points out that rules are made in time, but can also be destroyed in time. </s></p><p n="p11.16"><s n="s1.3;p11.16">Although there are references to the passing of time in <hi rend="italic">The Winter's Tale</hi>, these are not particularised. </s><s n="s2.3;p11.16">Locke's 'principle of individuation' is the theory that "ideas become general by separating from them the circumstances of time and place"<ref target="BAWE_3066d-ftnote.005"/>. </s><s n="s3.3;p11.16">Therefore, as the play does not limit itself to a particular time and place, the themes and issues explored have a universal and timeless quality - perhaps more so than those in <hi rend="italic">Emma</hi>. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3066d-ftnote.005"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">cited in Ian Watt, <hi rend="underlined">The Rise of the Novel</hi> (Middlesex, Penguin Books Ltd, 1963) p.22 </s></p></note><p n="p12.16"><s n="s1.5;p12.16">So far, we have seen how the use of time can alter the degree of realism. </s><s n="s2.5;p12.16">Its other main function, which is prominent when comparing these texts, is to limit or enable character development. </s><s n="s3.5;p12.16">Watt observes that "many novelists...have made their subject the exploration of the personality as it is defined in the interpenetration of its past and present self-awareness"<ref target="BAWE_3066d-ftnote.006"/>. </s><s n="s4.5;p12.16">Time is crucial in terms of character development; because characters are elaborated on and disentangled through time. </s><s n="s5.5;p12.16">Usually a longer time scale is needed to do this successfully (the time scale for <hi rend="italic">Emma</hi> is a year for example). </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3066d-ftnote.006"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ian Watt, <hi rend="underlined">The Rise of the Novel</hi> (Middlesex, Penguin Books Ltd, 1963) p.21 </s></p></note><p n="p13.16"><s n="s1.6;p13.16">It would be impossible for the action in <hi rend="italic">The Winter's Tale</hi> to take place over a maximum of twenty-four hours, because the character development of Leontes is fundamental to the plot. </s><s n="s2.6;p13.16">As Howard Felperin acknowledges, <hi rend="italic">The Winter's Tale</hi> "reveals much more of the vital information concerning the principals than is, strictly speaking, required by the plot or usual even in a Shakespearean play"<ref target="BAWE_3066d-ftnote.007"/>. </s><s n="s3.6;p13.16">The characters in <hi rend="italic">The Winter's Tale</hi> have a past, and (we can assume) a future. </s><s n="s4.6;p13.16">This is equally true in <hi rend="italic">Emma</hi>; Austen offers us a brief account of Emma's past and her present situation in the first four paragraphs. </s><s n="s5.6;p13.16">In this respect <hi rend="italic">The Winter's Tale</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Emma</hi> are surprisingly similar - the central character is developed over time. </s><s n="s6.6;p13.16">This is made possible primarily by the length of the time scale employed. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3066d-ftnote.007"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Howard Felperin, <hi rend="underlined">Shakespearean Romance</hi> (New Jersey, Princeton University Press, 1972) p.219 </s></p></note><p n="p14.16"><s n="s1.7;p14.16">In his essay entitled <hi rend="italic">The Structural Pattern</hi> (1964), Ernest Schanzer emphasises how the first half of <hi rend="italic">The Winter's Tale</hi> is replicated again in the second. </s><s n="s2.7;p14.16">The function of the Chorus of Time is not only important to highlight the contrast, but also the structural similarities. </s><s n="s3.7;p14.16">Schanzer argues that "by his gesture of turning the hour-glass Time...creates in us a feeling of repetition"<ref target="BAWE_3066d-ftnote.008"/>. </s><s n="s4.7;p14.16">His point that "both parts of the hour-glass look alike" is a valid and significant one. </s><s n="s5.7;p14.16">Each half of the hour-glass is a mirror image of the other. </s><s n="s6.7;p14.16">In many respects, so is each half of the play. </s><s n="s7.7;p14.16">Therefore in answer to those critics such as Panofsky who believe that "the figure of Father Time is used as a mere device to indicate the lapse of months, years or centuries"<ref target="BAWE_3066d-ftnote.009"/>, the Chorus of Time not only functions as a narrator, but also as a structural device to emphasise the repetition of events in the second half of the play. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3066d-ftnote.008"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">Ernest Schanzer, <hi rend="underlined">The Structural Pattern</hi> (1964) cited in K. Muir, <hi rend="underlined">Shakespeare: The Winter's Tale</hi> (Basingstoke, Macmillan Press Ltd, 1968) p.94 </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3066d-ftnote.009"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">E. Panofsky, <hi rend="underlined">Studies in Iconology</hi> (New York, 1939) p.81 </s></p></note><p n="p15.16"><s n="s1.2;p15.16">It is easy to underestimate the importance of time, as it has a more subtle presence in narrative than, for example, the plot or central characters. </s><s n="s2.2;p15.16">Nonetheless, after a close analysis of a text it is clear that its use of time is fundamental to its interpretation. </s></p><p n="p16.16"><s n="s1.3;p16.16">After all, every writer or dramatist uses time, whether they intend to or not. </s><s n="s2.3;p16.16">I think Johnson had a valuable point when he said "Time is, of all modes of existence, most obsequious to the imagination: a lapse of years is as easily conceived as a passage of hours"<ref target="BAWE_3066d-ftnote.010"/>. </s><s n="s3.3;p16.16">This is a fact that is fundamental to story-telling, for we need to believe and accept the time scheme of the narrative before the story can be told. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3066d-ftnote.010"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">cited in Howard Felperin, <hi rend="underlined">Shakespearean Romance</hi> (New Jersey, Princeton University Press, 1972) p.229 </s></p></note></div1></body><back><div1 type="bibliography"><head rend="underlined">Bibliography</head><p>M. H. Abrams, <hi rend="underlined">A Glossary of Literary Terms</hi> 7<hi rend="sup">th</hi> ed. (Boston, Heinle &amp; Heinle, 1999)</p><p>M. Butler, <hi rend="underlined">Jane Austen and the War of Ideas</hi> (Oxford, Oxford University Press, 1975)</p><p>I. Evans, <hi rend="underlined">A Short History of English Literature</hi> 4<hi rend="sup">th</hi> ed. (London: Penguin Books Ltd, 1976)</p><p>H. Felperin, <hi rend="underlined">Shakespearean Romance</hi> (New Jersey, Princeton University Press, 1972)</p><p>E. M. Forster, <hi rend="underlined">Aspects of the Novel</hi> (London, Edward Arnold Publishers Ltd, 1974)</p><p>S. Johnson, <hi rend="underlined">Johnson on Shakespeare</hi> (New Haven and London, Yale University Press, 1968)</p><p>S. McEvoy, <hi rend="underlined">Shakespeare: The Basics</hi> (London, Routledge, 2000)</p><p>K. Muir, <hi rend="underlined">Shakespeare: The Winter's Tale</hi> (Basingstoke, Macmillan Press Ltd, 1968)</p><p>E. Schanzer, <hi rend="underlined">The Structural Pattern</hi> (1964)</p><p>H. Steeves, <hi rend="underlined">Before Jane Austen</hi> (London, George Allen &amp; Unwin Ltd, 1966)</p><p>I. Watt, <hi rend="underlined">The Rise of the Novel</hi> (Middlesex, Penguin Books Ltd, 1963)</p></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
