<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_3067a" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Discuss the use of form as a means of ordering and/or articulating the experience of modern life in any two or more texts from the course</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">The document has a title page which contains:
document title
title part</note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">Language used in quote: <foreign id="English">English</foreign></note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">
Module name and number in doc footer.
Appendices are external excel sheets. (The appendix heading is found as part of the assignment.)
</note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">Running text contains reference to external or missing appendix.
</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">4</p><p n="date">2005-12</p><p n="module title">Marketing Management for Publishing</p><p n="module code">P65023</p><p n="genre family">Proposal</p><p n="discipline">Publishing</p><p n="disciplinary group">SS</p><p n="grade">D</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">2548</p><p n="number of s-units">139</p><p n="number of p">75</p><p n="number of tables">2</p><p n="number of figures">6</p><p n="number of block quotes">1</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">7</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">38</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">18.3</p><p n="average s-units per p">1.9</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">f</p><p n="year of birth">1964</p><p n="first language">Chinese unspecified</p><p n="education">OSa</p><p n="course">MA Publishing</p><p n="student ID">3067</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><docTitle><titlePart rend="bold">Marketing Plan</titlePart></docTitle><titlePart>for <hi rend="bold"> Journal of European Media and Communications Studies Publisher: Taylor and Francis</hi><hi rend="bold"> First Publishing Date: Oct, 2006 Frequency: Quarterly</hi></titlePart><titlePart>Text Prepared by: <name type="student name"/> Student No. <name type="student ID"/></titlePart><titlePart>Dec. 22, 2005</titlePart></titlePage><div1 type="toc" n="3"><head rend="underlined bold">Content </head><p/></div1></front><body><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Section One: Introduction </head><p n="p1.75"><s n="s1.5;p1.75">The rapid development of media technologies in recent years has produced dramatic changes in Europe Media Industry. </s><s n="s2.5;p1.75">They are featured as not only broadening information channels, but also changing the structure of the European media industry. </s><s n="s3.5;p1.75">Combining merger and acquisition strategies with internationalisation and diversification, the major media players now operate at the European level and define their policies accordingly. </s><s n="s4.5;p1.75">Media program's contents are therefore dominated by major players from a few countries. </s><s n="s5.5;p1.75">These changes are producing effects to social idea, social economy, life style and behaviours etc. and they have created an increasing demand of doing research about development of media industry and its impact to European society. </s></p><p n="p2.75"><s n="s1.2;p2.75">Journal of European Media and Communications Studies, which will be launched in Oct 2006, is catering for this need and will serve as a forum for specialists to publicize research fruits and exchange ideas. </s><s n="s2.2;p2.75">Articles on this journal will assess existing media structures and practices, European media concentration, European media and consumer culture, the role of media in democratic governance and European justice, propaganda, media reception and cultural practice, commercialization of news, European Media industry's structure and future trends, new media technologies, media regulations, regional media, alternative media, and other timely issues. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Section Two: Marketing Objectives and Situation Analysis</head><div2><head rend="bold">Marketing Objectives</head><p rend="bulleted" n="p3.75"><s n="s1.1;p3.75">Publicizing information shortly to European countries and non-European countries; </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p4.75"><s n="s1.1;p4.75">Making this journal highly recognised by core market - Europe in the first two years; </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p5.75"><s n="s1.1;p5.75">Drawing attentions from non-European countries as well; </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p6.75"><s n="s1.1;p6.75">Arranging promotions in 2006 and 2007 </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p7.75"><s n="s1.1;p7.75">Achieving 500 copies of subscription for 2007 and 2008 respectively </s></p><p n="p8.75"><s n="s1.5;p8.75">Due to the feature of subscription, 2 time lines need to be defined. </s><s n="s2.5;p8.75">One is for promoting this journal, i.e. </s><s n="s3.5;p8.75">2006 and 2007. </s><s n="s4.5;p8.75">The other is for subscriptions to issues, i.e. </s><s n="s5.5;p8.75">2007 and 2008. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">External Environment</head><p rend="bulleted" n="p9.75"><s n="s1.2;p9.75">In Europe there are about 45 countries using around 29 official languages. </s><s n="s2.2;p9.75">However, European Union now dominates this continent and aims at European Integration which brought about some anxieties, e.g. how to keep the language and culture identified and economic and politic system independent. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p10.75"><s n="s1.1;p10.75">The enlargement of the European Community and further economic integration in EU, have created a 300 million pan-European mass media consumer market more open to international competition and commercial forces at the expense of protected national broadcasters. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p11.75"><s n="s1.2;p11.75">The application of new media technologies has brought about great changes characterized by concentration of capital and internationalization of market; diversity of information channels; technological convergence etc. </s><s n="s2.2;p11.75">A host of questions, and even controversy, have surrounded these changes ranging from the economic (both macro and micro), to the social (exclusion, cohesion), the socio-economic (the digital divide), the political (e-democracy), the cultural and beyond and created interests regarding their actual and potential impact. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p12.75"><s n="s1.2;p12.75">Broad attention is absorbed from academic circles and policy-makers. </s><s n="s2.2;p12.75">5-year study programme: "Changing Media - Changing Europe" by ESF (European Science Foundation), "Guide to Measuring the Information Society" by OECD (Organisation for Economic Co-operation and Development) and "i2010" (European Information society in 2010) etc are the results of these consideration and discussion. </s></p><p n="p13.75"><s n="s1.3;p13.75">Under this situation, it is necessary to supply a forum for specialists to make a full discussion and communication. </s><s n="s2.3;p13.75">Meanwhile, it is necessary to open a window for policymaker and media players to learn information from academic studies. </s><s n="s3.3;p13.75">So there is a marketing gap for this journal. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">Internal environment</head><p rend="bulleted" n="p14.75"><s n="s1.2;p14.75">Intentionally extending its list on media and communication. </s><s n="s2.2;p14.75">2005's catalogue shows that Taylor has increased 7 journals on communication. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p15.75"><s n="s1.1;p15.75">Launching this journal in order to fill in the vacancy without a journal on European Media and Communication. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">SWOT analysis</head><div3><head rend="bold italic">Strengths</head><p rend="bulleted" n="p16.75"><s n="s1.1;p16.75">Having a long history of publication with the world famed academic brand on social science and humanities. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p17.75"><s n="s1.1;p17.75">Having a good performance in company operation. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p18.75"><s n="s1.3;p18.75">Having a great specialist team. </s><s n="s2.3;p18.75">Over 1300 specialists from 36 countries work for editorial board of communication-related journals. </s><s n="s3.3;p18.75">Among them 73 editors are from 17 European countries. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p19.75"><s n="s1.3;p19.75">Having a good customer basis. </s><s n="s2.3;p19.75">2004 T&amp;F Informa Annual Report shows that subscriptions' contribution to annual revenue is up to 43%. </s><s n="s3.3;p19.75">The revenue from Europe market is up to 50% (United Kingdom -19%, West Europe - 31%). </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p20.75"><s n="s1.1;p20.75">Having priority to grasp the first-hand materials about technology trends and specialists due to acquisition with Informa Telecoms &amp; Media which is the world's largest telecoms event organizer. </s></p></div3><div3><head rend="bold italic">Opportunities</head><p rend="bulleted" n="p21.75"><s n="s1.1;p21.75">An increasing demand on exchanging academic ideas </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p22.75"><s n="s1.1;p22.75">An increasing demand on knowing the trends of change in Media Industry and its impact. </s></p></div3><div3><head rend="bold italic">Weaknesses</head><p n="p23.75"><s n="s1.2;p23.75">Europe has 45 countries in which 29 official languages are used. </s><s n="s2.2;p23.75">English language makes it vulnerable. </s></p></div3><div3><head rend="bold italic">Threats</head><p n="p24.75"><s n="s1.4;p24.75">The original submission possibly goes to various outlets. </s><s n="s2.4;p24.75">Because this subject is related to all aspects, i.e. from technology to policy to investment, from academic research to social activities. </s><s n="s3.4;p24.75">Moreover, communication-related associations are very active and have their own websites or publications. </s><s n="s4.4;p24.75">How to guarantee this journal can collect high quality original submissions became significant. </s></p></div3></div2><div2><head rend="bold">Competition environments</head><p n="p25.75"><s n="s1.6;p25.75">Information from websites, Ulrich International Journal online catalogue and Web of Science show that the publications on Media and communication are mainly published by Taylor and Sage. </s><s n="s2.6;p25.75">Other major academic publishers, e.g. </s><s n="s3.6;p25.75">Elsevier, Springer and Wiley, only publish a very small quantity of relevant books. </s><s n="s4.6;p25.75">They haven't book / journal list under this subject. </s><s n="s5.6;p25.75">Palgrave Macmillan has quite a lot of books on relevant topic but they focus on relationship between cultural theory, politics etc. and media. </s><s n="s6.6;p25.75">So they can hardly create a competition to Taylor. </s></p><p n="p26.75"><s n="s1.4;p26.75">Sage has 488 titles book and 26 journals list on Communication and Media. </s><s n="s2.4;p26.75">One journal is specific to the European Communication. </s><s n="s3.4;p26.75">Somehow, it is a competitor of Taylor and Francis in this field. </s><s n="s4.4;p26.75">However, Sage can't compete with Taylor and Francis on company scale, publishing history, professional experience and specialist team. </s></p><p n="p27.75"><s n="s1.1;p27.75">In general, Taylor and Francis takes a good position in this field. </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Section Three: Identification of Target Market</head><p n="p28.75"><s n="s1.1;p28.75">This analysis is based on the marketing objective which will focus on the European market within the first 2 years. </s></p><div2><head rend="bold">Geography</head><list type="bulleted"><item>Core market: European countries</item><item>Extended market: non-European countries, which are interested in the relevant studies</item></list><p n="p29.75"/></div2><div2><head rend="bold">Readerships </head><list type="bulleted"><item>Scholars, educators and students in the fields of media and communication, sociology and politics</item><item>Policymakers </item><item>Practitioners of media industry</item></list><p n="p30.75"/></div2><div2><head rend="bold">Segment of Core Market </head><p n="p31.75"><s n="s1.1;p31.75">According to research of target institutional subscribers and their size in Europe, Figure 1 is applied to give a direct expression of market structure of this journal. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_3067a-fig.001"><head>Figure 1: segment of target market in Europe </head></figure><p rend="bulleted" n="p32.75"><s n="s1.3;p32.75">European Universities and university level institutions will be the major subscribers. </s><s n="s2.3;p32.75">Online information shows that media and communication related courses are very popular in Europe. </s><s n="s3.3;p32.75">Figure 2 shows the relevant details in UK. It refers that there is a very good need to relevant journals. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_3067a-fig.002"><head>Figure 2: UK 2006 degree courses on Media and Communications Source: <seg type="URL" n="http://www.ucas.com"/> Dated: 4th Dec. 2005 </head></figure><p n="p33.75"><s n="s1.6;p33.75">European higher Education is well developed. </s><s n="s2.6;p33.75">Official statistics e.g. </s><s n="s3.6;p33.75">Eurostat, supply detailed data of university student numbers. </s><s n="s4.6;p33.75">But they aren't applied to support this marketing plan. </s><s n="s5.6;p33.75">This is taking into account of the feature of subscriptions to academic journals, i.e. the main subscribers are institutions. </s><s n="s6.6;p33.75">Figure 3 applied to show that there is a big basis of higher educational institutions and potential market in Europe. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_3067a-fig.003"><head>Figure 3: Worldwide Universities Statistics (Including university level Academic Institutions) Source: <seg type="URL" n="http://www.webometrics.info"/> Dated: 20th Dec. 2005 (Note: European country number listed above contains the former name and current name and disputed area. However, this doesn't affect the statistics of universities' numbers as the latter comes only under the current country names.) </head></figure><p n="p34.75"><s n="s1.1;p34.75">In order to support this campaign and verify market potentiality of European universities, here supplies official statistics of universities in UK, Germany and France as a further supportive materials. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_3067a-fig.004"><head>Figure 4: University / university level institutions in UK, Germany and France Sources: 1. The Office for National Statistics, 2005 The Official Year Book of the United Kingdom and Northern Ireland 2. <seg type="URL" n="http://www.destatis.de/basis/e/biwiku/hochtab1.htm"/> (Dated: 10 <hi rend="sup">th</hi> Dec. 2005) 3. <seg type="URL" n="http://www.frenchculture.org/education/france/system/univ.html"/> (Dated: 10th Dec. 2005)</head></figure><p n="p35.75"><s n="s1.1;p35.75">Over 300 university institutions in the above 3 European countries, plus universities in Spain, Italy, Sweden, Finland, Netherlands, Switzerland, Norway, Austria, Russia etc, there is a market potentiality of 500 university subscribers. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p36.75"><s n="s1.4;p36.75">European National academic institutions will be important contributors and subscribers of this journal. </s><s n="s2.4;p36.75">European Science Foundation has 77 national academic institutions registered from 30 main European countries. </s><s n="s3.4;p36.75">48 of them with programmes on Humanities and Social Science have been undertaking the relevant studies. </s><s n="s4.4;p36.75">They will be the target customers. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p37.75"><s n="s1.1;p37.75">Top 10 European media enterprises can be taken as potential subscribers. </s></p><p n="p38.75"><s n="s1.2;p38.75">European Media Industry in Europe is well developed. </s><s n="s2.2;p38.75">Figure 5 shows the Breakdown of top 50 media companies in Europ. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_3067a-fig.005"><head>Figure 5: top 50 European media companies by nation (based on turnover) Source: <seg type="URL" n="http://www.medialaw.ru/laws/other_laws/european/e-eh.htm"/> dated: 10 <hi rend="sup">th</hi> Dec. 2005 (Origin: Statistical Yearbook, European Audio-visual Observatory 1997)</head></figure><p n="p39.75"><s n="s1.4;p39.75">Top 10 leading media companies account for a revenue ranged from $7.9 billion to $2.4 billion. </s><s n="s2.4;p39.75">They are dominated in Europe, even non-Europe market. </s><s n="s3.4;p39.75">It is necessary for them to know more about scholars' attention to media industry. </s><s n="s4.4;p39.75">So they may be potential customers. </s></p><p n="p40.75"><s rend="italic" n="s1.1;p40.75">Name list of Top 10: Bertelsmann, Havas, ARD, Reed-Elsevier, BBC, Fininvest Matra, Hachette, RAI, CLT and Axel Springer </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">Potentiality of Extended Market</head><p rend="bulleted" n="p41.75"><s n="s1.1;p41.75">2004 Annual report shows that T&amp;F Informa has a good market share in North America which contributes to its revenue about 33% while the rest of the world outside Europe is 17%. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p42.75"><s n="s1.1;p42.75">North America is active at academic research of media and communication and is the base of some important academic associations. </s></p><p n="p43.75"><s n="s1.1;p43.75">So there is possibility to market this journal outside Europe. </s></p><p n="p44.75"><s n="s1.1;p44.75">Sum up the above analysis, a conclusion can be made that there is a tangible and accessible market for this journal within and outside Europe. </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Section Four: Marketing Strategy and Tactics</head><div2><head rend="bold">Marketing Strategy</head><p n="p45.75"><s n="s1.1;p45.75">Marketing strategy for this campaign can be abbreviated as a six-word slogan: </s></p><quote lang="English" rend="bold italic"> Creating customers' awareness; Deploying existing resources </quote><list type="bulleted"><item>Widely send press release by email to universities and academic institutions related to media and communication studies;</item><item>Publicising the publication information on Taylor's communication journals </item><item>Basing on existing customers and taking a 2-year step to marketing this journal </item></list><p n="p46.75"><s n="s1.1;p46.75">Taylor's existing communication journals have achieved good circulations whose subscribers will be the core target customers. </s></p><figure id="BAWE_3067a-fig.006"><head> Figure 7: Subscription Quantity to existing communication journals Source: Ulrich International Journal online Catalogue 2005, Searched through Oxford University Intranet <hi rend="underlined"><seg type="URL" n="www.ulrichsweb.com/ulrichsweb/Search/fullCitation.asp?navPage=1&amp;tab=1&amp;serial_uid=43527&amp;issn=10510974"/> </hi></head></figure><p n="p47.75"><s n="s1.3;p47.75">Besides, Taylor has great subscriptions to other Humanities and Social Science journals. </s><s n="s2.3;p47.75">Deploying the current subscribers could bring about a breakthrough of marketing this journal. </s><s n="s3.3;p47.75">In the first year marketing will focus on European market but give consideration to non-European market; in the second year marketing will put more efforts to non-European market. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">Marketing Mix and Marketing Communications</head><div3><head rend="bold italic">Product</head><p n="p48.75"><s n="s1.3;p48.75">This journal will be developed into the primer source of European media and communication studies. </s><s n="s2.3;p48.75">Its editorial board will consist of specialists from the relevant fields. </s><s n="s3.3;p48.75">The quality and pertinence will be guaranteed. </s></p></div3><div3><head rend="bold italic">Price</head><p n="p49.75"><s n="s1.1;p49.75">Research shows that Taylor's communication journals are priced at the medium to low level. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p50.75"><s n="s1.1;p50.75">Pricing this journal at the same level as other regional communication journals. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p51.75"><s n="s1.1;p51.75">Price options available for Print + online access, Online only and individual in order to meet various demands. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p52.75"><s n="s1.1;p52.75">20% special offer to existing communication journal's subscribers who submit orders before 31 <hi rend="sup">st</hi> Aug 2006. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p53.75"><s n="s1.1;p53.75">Within the first two years the price won't change in order to stabilise subscriptions and absorb new subscriptions. </s></p></div3><div3><head rend="bold italic">Promotion </head><p rend="bulleted" n="p54.75"><s n="s1.2;p54.75">Sending press release and order form together with current subscriptions by email or by post. </s><s n="s2.2;p54.75">Sample issues will be delivered as requested. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p55.75"><s n="s1.1;p55.75">Publishing new journal's information on all communication-related journals. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p56.75"><s n="s1.3;p56.75">Delivering information through editors. </s><s n="s2.3;p56.75">Over 1300 editors work for communication-related journals. </s><s n="s3.3;p56.75">They are from key institutions and can take information to the end-users at the first time. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p57.75"><s n="s1.3;p57.75">Doing promotion on Taylor's website. </s><s n="s2.3;p57.75">Items"New Journal", "Press Release" and "Communication Arena" (<seg type="URL" n="http://www.communicationarena.com/"/>) can be used to deliver information of this new journal. </s><s n="s3.3;p57.75">There through editors' special recommendation and link service the information can be easily distributed. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p58.75"><s n="s1.1;p58.75">Opening free online access to subscribers and guests in order to make this journal to be recognised well in 2007. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p59.75"><s n="s1.5;p59.75">Doing promotion through academic associations. </s><s n="s2.5;p59.75">Taylor publishes lots of communication-related journals on behalf of academic associations, e.g. </s><s n="s3.5;p59.75">AMIC, NCA, ECA, WSCA etc. </s><s n="s4.5;p59.75">National Communication Association (NCA), has 7700 memberships from 20 countries. </s><s n="s5.5;p59.75">Marketing this journal through relevant conventions and website will be an economical, effective and mutually beneficial way. </s></p></div3><div3><head rend="bold italic">Channels </head><p rend="bulleted" n="p60.75"><s n="s1.3;p60.75">Direct sale will be the major way of marketing this journal and collecting orders. </s><s n="s2.3;p60.75">Taylor's in house mailing list will be the first choice. </s><s n="s3.3;p60.75">Other relevant lists can be taken as a supplement. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p61.75"><s n="s1.2;p61.75">Professional agents will be used for areas where Taylor's sales force can't cover. </s><s n="s2.2;p61.75">Swets will be a candidate agent because it owns offices in 12 European Countries and can link between 60,000 providers and 65,000 librarians, purchasers &amp; end users. </s></p></div3><div3><head rend="bold italic">Customer Services </head><p rend="bulleted" n="p62.75"><s n="s1.1;p62.75">Replacing missing issues at the first time of receiving claiming. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p63.75"><s n="s1.1;p63.75">Setting up online access as soon as fulfilment of subscription order. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p64.75"><s n="s1.1;p64.75">Sending questionnaires to subscribers against schedule and processing the feedback in time </s></p></div3></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Section Five: Marketing Planning </head><p n="p65.75"><s n="s1.1;p65.75">"Journal Publishing" shows that the costs of paper, printing and binding for a journal usually account for rather less than 35% of the subscription price. </s></p><div2><head rend="bold italic">Budget and Gross Margin </head><p n="p66.75"><s n="s1.2;p66.75">This marketing plan is based on economical and effective operation. </s><s n="s2.2;p66.75">Since lots of existing resources can be used without extra charges, this budget is made only for the following expenses: </s></p><list type="bulleted"><item>Printing promotion materials, e.g. Press Release and subscription order notice etc </item><item>Postage for developing new customers </item><item>Printing free issues for promotion </item></list><list type="simple"><head>Breakdown of 1000 copies of free issues in the first year: </head><item> 500 copies from initial issues</item><item> 200 copies each for Vol1 No.1</item><item> 100 copies each for Vol1 No.2</item><item> 100 copies each for Vol1 No.3</item><item> 100 copies each for Vol1 No.4</item></list><list type="simple"><head> Breakdown of 500 copies of free issues in the second year</head><item> 150 copies each for Vol1 No.1</item><item> 150 copies each for Vol1 No.2</item><item> 100 copies each for Vol1 No.3</item><item> 100 copies each for Vol1 No.4</item></list><list type="simple"><head>Attachments:</head><item> "1 <hi rend="sup">st</hi> Year Gross Margin and Budget" </item><item> "2 <hi rend="sup">nd</hi> Year Gross Margin and Budget"</item><item> "Schedule for 2006 and 2007" （Separate file）</item></list><table id="BAWE_3067a-tab.001"><head rend="bold italic"> 1st Year Gross Margin and Budget </head><row><cell/></row></table><table id="BAWE_3067a-tab.002"><head rend="bold italic"> 2nd Year Gross Margin and Budget </head><row><cell/></row></table></div2><div2><head rend="bold">Implementation and Monitoring</head><p n="p67.75"><s n="s1.4;p67.75">This marketing plan is based on the overall marketing research and consulting with Editorial Dept, Sales Dept. </s><s n="s2.4;p67.75">Subscription Dept, Customer Service Centre and Distribution Centre etc. </s><s n="s3.4;p67.75">Various processes should be controlled by the relevant developments. </s><s n="s4.4;p67.75">The responsibilities are allocated as follows: </s></p><p n="p68.75"><s n="s1.1;p68.75"><hi rend="bold italic">Marketing Dept:</hi> overall supervision of this plan's implementation and monitoring </s></p><p n="p69.75"><s n="s1.1;p69.75"><hi rend="bold"><hi rend="italic">Editorial Dept</hi>:</hi> compiling blurb, special recommendation for "Commendation Arena" and process the feedback about the contents of this journal </s></p><p n="p70.75"><s n="s1.1;p70.75"><hi rend="bold italic">Sales Dept: </hi>overall promotions, including arrangement of distributing information by email, post and website, contacting liaisons of associations and overseas representatives </s></p><p n="p71.75"><s n="s1.1;p71.75"><hi rend="bold italic">Subscription Dept:</hi> fulfilment of subscription orders and monitoring feedbacks from customers </s></p><p n="p72.75"><s n="s1.1;p72.75"><hi rend="bold italic">Customer Service: </hi>handling various queries and processing claims and monitoring feedbacks </s></p><p n="p73.75"><s n="s1.1;p73.75"><hi rend="bold italic">Distribution Centre: </hi>delivering press release, order forms and sample issues with shipments of current subscriptions </s></p><p n="p74.75"><s n="s1.2;p74.75">In order to guarantee this plan can be well implemented, all above mentioned departments, especially those involved in timely tasks, should have its own schedules in line with this plan. </s><s n="s2.2;p74.75">Relevant departments will have meetings together and analyse the process of promotion, the sources of subscription order and feedback about the service and journal's quality. </s></p><p n="p75.75"><s n="s1.1;p75.75">Any adjustment for a period plan, when it is necessary, will be made after discussion. </s></p></div2></div1></body><back><div1 type="appendix"><head rend="bold">Appendices </head><p/></div1><div1 type="bibliography"><head rend="bold">Bibliography </head><div2 type="bibliography"><head rend="bold italic">Online sources </head><p>EU information Society </p><p> ( available at://europa.eu.int/information_society/eeurope/2005/index_en.htm, 17<hi rend="sup">th</hi> Dec. 2005)</p><p>Viviane Reding, (2005) Better regulation for Europe's media industry: the Commission's approach, Speech, European Commissioner for Information Society and Media </p><p> (available at: <seg type="URL" n="http://europa.eu.int/information_society/index_en.htm"/>, 20<hi rend="sup">th</hi> Dec. 2005)</p><p>Taylor Francis Price list for 2006</p><p>(available at: <seg type="URL" n="http://www.tandf.co.uk/journals/pdf/price.pdf"/>, 17<hi rend="sup">th</hi> Dec. 2005)</p><p>Imforma Media, part of T&amp; F Informa (available at: <seg type="URL" n="http://www.informamedia.com/"/>, 17<hi rend="sup">th</hi> Dec. 2005)</p><p>Reed Elsevier Publications, ( available at: <seg type="URL" n="http://www.elsevier.com"/>, 17<hi rend="sup">th</hi> Dec. 2005)</p><p>Springer Publications, (available at: <seg type="URL" n="http://www.springer.com"/>, 17<hi rend="sup">th</hi> Dec. 2005)</p><p>Palgrave USA Publications (available at: <seg type="URL" n="http://www.palgrave-usa.com"/>, 17<hi rend="sup">th</hi> Dec. 2005)</p><p>Palgrave Macmillan Publications (available at: <seg type="URL" n="http://www.palgrave.com/home/"/>, 17<hi rend="sup">th</hi> Dec. 2005)</p><p>Wiley Publications, (available at: <seg type="URL" n="http://eu.wiley.com"/>, 17<hi rend="sup">th</hi> Dec. 2005)</p><p>Sage Publications, (available at: <seg type="URL" n="http://www.sagepub.co.uk"/>, 17<hi rend="sup">th</hi> Dec. 2005)</p><p>International Association for Media and Communication Research</p><p> (available at: <seg type="URL" n="http://www.iamcr.net"/> 7<hi rend="sup">th</hi> Dec. 2005) </p><p>International Communication Association, (available at: <seg type="URL" n="http://www.icahdq.org"/>, 8<hi rend="sup">th</hi> Dec. 2005)</p><p>The Association for Education in Journalism and Mass Communication</p><p> (available at: <seg type="URL" n="http://aejmc.org/orgs/index.html"/> 6<hi rend="sup">th</hi> Dec. 2005) </p><p>Society of College, National and University Libraries,</p><p> (available at: <seg type="URL" n="http://www.sconul.ac.uk/intro/"/>, 18<hi rend="sup">th</hi> Dec. 2005)</p><p>15. The Community Media Association (available at: <seg type="URL" n="http://www.commedia.org.uk/about-cma/"/>)</p><p>16. World Communication Association </p><p> (Available at: <seg type="URL" n="http://facstaff.uww.edu/wca/History.htm"/> 22<hi rend="sup">nd</hi> Dec. 2005)</p><p>17. The top 100 universities in UK, </p><p> (available at: <seg type="URL" n="http://www.timesonline.co.uk/pdfs/finalunitable2.pdf"/>, 20<hi rend="sup">th</hi> Dec. 2005)</p><p>18. International Federation of Journalists,</p><p>(available at: <seg type="URL" n="http://www.ifj.org/default.asp?Issue=IFJ&amp;Language=EN"/>, 7<hi rend="sup">th</hi> Dec. 2005)</p><p>19. European communication Association (available at : <seg type="URL" n="http://www.ecanet.org/"/>)</p><p>Russian Communication Association </p><p>(available at: <seg type="URL" n="http://www.tedfriedman.com/grads/2005/01/01152006_russia.php"/> 22<hi rend="sup">nd</hi> Dec. 2005)</p><p>French University Information </p><p> (available at: <seg type="URL" n="http://www.frenchculture.org/education/france/system/univ.html"/>, 10<hi rend="sup">th</hi> Dec. 2005)</p><p>French and Europe information </p><p> (available at: <seg type="URL" n="http://www.understandfrance.org/France/Europe.html"/> French and Europe information </p><p> 20<hi rend="sup">th</hi> Dec. 2005)</p><p>German University Statistics </p><p>(available at: <seg type="URL" n="http://www.destatis.de/basis/e/biwiku/hochtab1.htm"/>, 10<hi rend="sup">th</hi> Dec. 2005)</p><p>Worldwide University Information </p><p> (available at: <seg type="URL" n="http://www.webometrics.info/university_by_country.asp-country=it.htm"/>, 20<hi rend="sup">th</hi>Dec. 2005)</p><p>European Country Information </p><p> (available at: <seg type="URL" n="http://europa.eu.int/abc/governments/index_en.htm"/>, 20<hi rend="sup">th</hi> Dec. 2005)</p><p>Ehihibition / Advertising Information, 56th Annual Conference of International communication Association (available at: <seg type="URL" n="http://www.icahdq.org/events/conference/2006/DresdenEXHIBITINGINFO.pdf,15th"/> Dec. 2005)</p><p>Publisher Association information (available at: <seg type="URL" n="http://www.publishers.org.uk"/>, 16<hi rend="sup">th</hi> Dec. 2005)</p><p>Swets, Journal Subscription Agent, (available at: <seg type="URL" n="http://www.swets.com"/>, 22<hi rend="sup">nd</hi> Dec. 2005)</p><p>Ebsco, Journal Subscription Agent (available at : <seg type="URL" n="http://www.ebsco.com/home/"/> , 22<hi rend="sup">nd</hi> Dec. 2005)</p><p>Viviane Reding, Better regulation for Europe's media industry: the Commission's approach, Speech, European Commissioner for Information Society and Media, 2005 (available at:</p><p><seg type="URL" n="http://europa.eu.int/rapid/pressReleasesAction.do?reference=SPEECH/05/532&amp;format=HTML&amp;aged=0&amp;language=EN&amp;guiLanguage=en"/>)</p><p>Alison Harcourt, The European Commission and regulation of the media industry, (available at: <seg type="URL" n="http://www.medialaw.ru/laws/other_laws/european/e-eh.htm"/> dated: 10<hi rend="sup">th</hi> Dec. 2005)</p></div2><div2 type="bibliography"><head rend="underlined bold">Online Database </head><p>(available through Oxford Brookes University website except special annotation)</p><p>Web of Science (accessed on 10<hi rend="sup">th</hi> Dec. 2005)</p><p>Ulrich International Journal Catalogue Online (available through Oxford University Bodleian </p><p> Library at <seg type="URL" n="www.ulrichsweb.com/ulrichsweb/Search/fullCitation.asp?navPage=1&amp;tab=1&amp;serial_uid=43527&amp;issn=10510974"/> 8<hi rend="sup">th</hi></p><p> Dec. 2005 )</p><p>Mintel Report (accessed on 18<hi rend="sup">th</hi> Dec, 2005)</p><p>Book Facts Online (accessed 18<hi rend="sup">th</hi> Dec, 2005)</p><p>Communication and Mass Media Complete (accessed 16<hi rend="sup">th</hi> Dec, 2005)</p><p>Datamonitor, 2003, Media in USA: Industry Profile. (accessed 13<hi rend="sup">th</hi> Dec. 2005)</p><p>Datamonitor, 2003, Media in UK: Industry Profile. (accessed 13<hi rend="sup">th</hi> Dec. 2005</p></div2><div2 type="bibliography"><head rend="underlined bold italic">Statistics and Reports</head><p>Claire Creaser, Sally Maynard and Sonya White, LISU Annual Library Statistics 2005: Featuring Trends Analysis of UK public and academic Libraries </p><p>The Office for National Statistics, 2005 the Official Year Book of the United Kingdom and Northern Ireland</p><p>Education and Training 2010: the success of the Lisbon Strategy Hinges on Urgent Reform, 2003, Commissions of the European Communities.</p><p>Commission of European Communities, (2004), Communication from the Commission to the Council, the European Parliament, the European Economic and Social Committee and the Committee of the Regions: Challenges for the European Information Society beyond 2005, Brussels.</p><p>Gerd Nies, Roberto Pedersinis, (2003), Freelance Journalist in the European Media Industry Report, European Federation of Journalists.</p><p>T &amp; F Inform Annual Report Financial Statement, 2004, Specialist Information for Global Market.</p><p>Informa, Interim Report for the Six Months Ended 30 June 2005, Specialist Information for Global Market.</p><p>Academic and Professional Publishing Market Statistics 2004 (from PA)</p></div2><div2 type="bibliography"><head rend="bold italic">Books and others</head><p>Gillian Page, Robert Campbell and Jack Meadows, Journal Publishing, Cambridge, Cambridge University Press, 1997.</p><p>UNESCO, Book Promotion, Sales and Distribution, London, Book House Training Centre, 1991</p><p>Patrick Forsyth, Marketing in Publishing, London, Routledge, 1997</p><p>Jeremy Swinfen Green, e-media, How to use electronic media for effective marketing communications, Henley-on-Thames, Admap Publications, 2000</p><p>Marian Burk Wood, Marketing Planning, principles into practice, Essex, Pearson Education Ltd., 2004</p><p>John Kremer, 1001 Ways to Market Your Books, 5<hi rend="sup">th</hi> Ed., Fairfield, Open Horizons, 1998</p><p>James Watson and Anne Hill, Dictionary of Media &amp; Communication Studies, Fifth Edition, London, Arnold, 2000</p><p>Bernt Stubbe Ostergarrd, The Media in Western Europe, the Euromedia Handbookd, 2<hi rend="sup">nd</hi> Ed. London, Sage, 1997</p><p>John Hartley, Communication, Cultural and Media Studies, the Key Concepts, 3<hi rend="sup">rd</hi> Ed., London, Routledge, 2002</p><p>Andrew Hart, Understanding the Media, A Practical Guide, London, Routledge, 1994</p><p>Jeremy Tunstall, Howard Tumber, Media Power, Professionals and Politics, London, Routledge, 2000</p><p>Michael Skovmand, Kim Christian Schroder, Media Cultures Reappraising Transnational Media, London, 1992, Routledge</p><p>Chris Newbold, Oliver Boyd-Barrett, Hilde van den Bulck, The Media Book, London, Arnold, 2002</p><p>James Watson, Media Communication, New York, Palgrave, 2003</p><p>Klaus Bruhn Jensen, A Handbook of Media and Communication Research, London, Routledge, 2002</p></div2><div2 type="bibliography"><head rend="bold">Primary Sources</head><p>Liz Ferguson, "Journals Publishing" - Guest Lecture from Blackwell Publishing Ltd., Oxford, Oxford Brookes University, 2005</p><p>Note: the above book reference cited by using British Standard (numeric) system </p><p> ( Available at: <seg type="URL" n="http://www.brookes.ac.uk/services/library/resources/britstan.doc"/> on 22nd Dec.2005)</p></div2></div1><div1 type="missing or external appendix"><p/></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
