<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_3067b" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>What has Google Book Search brought to tInternational Publishing?</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">
Module name and number in doc footer. Word count at the end of running text (before bibliography).
</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">4</p><p n="date">2006-03</p><p n="module title">International Publishing Management</p><p n="module code">P65025</p><p n="genre family">Critique</p><p n="discipline">Publishing</p><p n="disciplinary group">SS</p><p n="grade">D</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">958</p><p n="number of s-units">53</p><p n="number of p">18</p><p n="number of tables">0</p><p n="number of figures">0</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">1</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">10</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">18.1</p><p n="average s-units per p">2.9</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">f</p><p n="year of birth">1964</p><p n="first language">Chinese unspecified</p><p n="education">OSa</p><p n="course">MA Publishing</p><p n="student ID">3067</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><docTitle><titlePart rend="bold">What has <hi rend="italic">Google Book Search</hi> brought to International publishing? </titlePart></docTitle><titlePart>By <name type="student name"/></titlePart></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="section"><p n="p1.18"><s n="s1.3;p1.18">In Oct 2004 Google launched Google Print, currently Google Book Search (GBS), which aims at service of book searching and its excerpts displaying. </s><s n="s2.3;p1.18">Google first works with 5 main USA and UK libraries, e.g. </s><s n="s3.3;p1.18">University of Michigan, Oxford University etc, to digitize books in their collections and make them accessible via GBS. Google plans to digitize and make available through GBS service approximately 15 million volumes within a decade. </s></p><p n="p2.18"><s n="s1.2;p2.18">Up to now this ambitious plan and its actual action have brought about a 6-month long controversial dispute, even lawsuit, involving authors, publishers, librarian, internet users and politicians all over the world. </s><s n="s2.2;p2.18">Copyright and relocation of its related profit, publication security as well as culture identity are the core issues concerned by various interest groups. </s></p><p n="p3.18"><s n="s1.7;p3.18">GBS is a 10-year plan at its first stage. </s><s n="s2.7;p3.18">It is too early and too hard to predict what will happen to it in the late of its first 10-year. </s><s n="s3.7;p3.18">But, GBS and its related debate are displaying a phenomenon, i.e. </s><s n="s4.7;p3.18">Non-publishing companies are expecting to make profit through publication-related business. </s><s n="s5.7;p3.18">They may be the new entities and will change the business model of publishing. </s><s n="s6.7;p3.18">Its uncertainty leads that different interest groups have different attitude to it. </s><s n="s7.7;p3.18">Moreover, in the same interest group, they may have contradictory opinions, while others hold an ambiguous attitude. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p4.18"><s n="s1.6;p4.18">Publishers: After the lawsuit of the Association of American Publishers (AAP) on behalf of five major publisher members, there is a continuation of accusing GBS of copyright violation. </s><s n="s2.6;p4.18">Some publishers, e.g. </s><s n="s3.6;p4.18">Bloomsbury, strongly disagree what GBS has been doing. </s><s n="s4.6;p4.18">They are calling on internet users to boycott Google. </s><s n="s5.6;p4.18">(The Guardian, Mar 4, 06) However, other publishers, e.g. </s><s n="s6.6;p4.18">Blackwell and HarperCollins, have put 5-6000 titles into GBS (Bookseller, LBF Daily, Mar 7, 06). </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p5.18"><s n="s1.3;p5.18">Authors: Authors Guild, representing 8,000 writers, at first joined individual authors in a class-action lawsuit alleging the GBS Library Project violated their copyright. </s><s n="s2.3;p5.18">However some authors, e.g. </s><s n="s3.3;p5.18">Cory Doctorow, expressed their firm support to this project. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p6.18"><s n="s1.6;p6.18">Government: GBS has hit a particular nerve in France. </s><s n="s2.6;p6.18">The French response from leading politicians, technology companies and the book world has as much as do with culture. </s><s n="s3.6;p6.18">They suspect whether GBS, a USA-based company's project, can well manage European culture. </s><s n="s4.6;p6.18">As a result, a move of European Digital Library (EDL) was put forwarded and supported by people, including Mr. Jacques Chirac, French president, who is already backing another Google rival in the form of Quaero - a multimedia search engine. </s><s n="s5.6;p6.18">EDL is planning to make 2m books, films and other files digitising and accessible through the portal by 2008. </s><s n="s6.6;p6.18">"It is clear that the Frenchman's tract, which paints the digitisation debate in terms of Europe fighting American hegemony"(Financial Times, Mar 7 2006 ) </s></p><p n="p7.18"><s n="s1.6;p7.18">GBS is a new thing facing international publishing. </s><s n="s2.6;p7.18">It is not because of digitisation of publications itself (there are some similar projects, e.g. </s><s n="s3.6;p7.18">Gutenbery Book Project, OCLC Bibliography service etc) but the feature of the "practitioner", Google is an internet searching service company whose business is based on money earning through advertisement matched with the relevant searching results. </s><s n="s4.6;p7.18">Its operational idea and business model is totally different from what publishing industry is like. </s><s n="s5.6;p7.18">Moreover, its ambitious plan is so big to not only involve all publishing-related people, but also include some in-copyright books. </s><s n="s6.6;p7.18">So it is difficult to be accepted. </s></p><p n="p8.18"><s n="s1.1;p8.18">However, it contains possibilities to be: </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p9.18"><s n="s1.1;p9.18">a channel for book publicity and promotion and sales </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p10.18"><s n="s1.1;p10.18">a channel for online publication service for publications in public domain </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p11.18"><s n="s1.4;p11.18">a way publishers benefit from the book promotion through GBS. What the publishers gain is not only the increase of sales but also a portion of revenue from advertisement. </s><s n="s2.4;p11.18">Normally, publishing is a business of money-spending on Ad or promotion. </s><s n="s3.4;p11.18">But GBS is a new business model which is based on splitting advertising revenue with publishers. </s><s n="s4.4;p11.18">Possibly, this will be a force pushing publishers to involve in GBS more than before. </s></p><p n="p12.18"><s n="s1.1;p12.18">In digital age, the way of information dissemination is changing the business model of publishing, which avoidably lead to reconsider the following issues: </s></p><list type="bulleted"><item>Copyright and security of publication in digital age</item><item>The permission and the technical standard of digitising of publications</item><item>Who should be the owner and practitioner of digitised publications</item><item>New business model, e.g. the cooperation of publishers and non-publishing partners; selling advertisements next to classic works is good or not etc.</item></list><p n="p13.18"><s n="s1.2;p13.18">Google was found in Sept 1998 and headquartered in USA. Now it has grown up as one of global leading internet searching service companies with over 5000 employees working in about 20 overseas offices in the world. </s><s n="s2.2;p13.18">As a multinational enterprise, Google is featured as: </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p14.18"><s n="s1.1;p14.18">Mission Statement: Organize the world's information and make it universally accessible and useful. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p15.18"><s n="s1.1;p15.18">Expansion of business is based on persistently pursuing innovation of technology and bettering the organisational structure and intercultural. </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p16.18"><s n="s1.3;p16.18">It's business philosophy contains 10 aspects. </s><s n="s2.3;p16.18">"Focus on the user and all else will follow" comes at the first. </s><s n="s3.3;p16.18">Possibly, this is why it can make a quick response to issues aroused GBS and took a effective solution to the relevant issues, e.g. starting to use the name of GBS with more precise business orientation; extending GBS from Book Library Project (BLP) only to including BLP and "Google Books Partner Programme - for publishers' service" </s></p><p rend="bulleted" n="p17.18"><s n="s1.4;p17.18">"Don't be evil" is Google's business ethics. </s><s n="s2.4;p17.18">Basing on this motto, Google respects the local culture and ethics, e.g. </s><s n="s3.4;p17.18">Google enters into some countries (including France, Germany, China) with contents not conflicting the local cultural and governance. </s><s n="s4.4;p17.18">This is why Google can win bigger markets than its competitors. </s></p><p n="p18.18"><s n="s1.1;p18.18">GBS, as a new business model of Internet searching engine, as a new channel of international publications, as a new service for Internet users, is worth of further attentions. </s></p></div1></body><back><div1 type="bibliography"><head rend="bold">Reference Materials:</head><p>Bookseller Magazine</p><p>Economist</p><p>Business Weekly</p><p>Financial Times</p><p>Guardian</p><p>Independent</p><p>Times</p><p>Proquest Newspaper Library Online Database</p><p>Business Source Premier Online Database</p><p>Communication &amp; mass media complete Online Database</p><p>Pira Database</p><p><seg type="URL" n="http://www.google.co.uk/intl/en/about.html"/></p></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
