<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "tei_bawe.dtd"><TEI.2 id="_3073c" n="version 1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Environmental scanning of hotel sectores in north america</title></titleStmt><extent/><publicationStmt><distributor>British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus</distributor><availability><p>The British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes, under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC. Subject to the rights of the these institutions in the BAWE corpus, and pursuant to the ESRC agreement, the BAWE corpus is available to researchers for research purposes PROVIDED THAT the following conditions are met:</p><p>1. The corpus files are not distributed in either their original form or in modified form.</p><p>2. The texts are used for research purposes only; they should not be reproduced in teaching materials.</p><p>3. The texts are not reproduced in full for a wider audience/readership, although researchers are free to quote short passages of text (up to 200 running words from any given text).</p><p>4. The BAWE corpus developers (contact: Hilary Nesi) are informed of all projects, dissertations, theses, presentations or publications arising from analysis of the corpus.</p><p>5. Researchers acknowledge their use of the corpus using the following form of words: "The data in this study come from the British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus, which was developed at the Universities of Warwick, Reading and Oxford Brookes under the directorship of Hilary Nesi and Sheena Gardner (formerly of the Centre for Applied Linguistics [previously called CELTE], Warwick), Paul Thompson (Department of Applied Linguistics, Reading) and Paul Wickens (Westminster Institute of Education, Oxford Brookes), with funding from the ESRC (RES-000-23-0800)."</p></availability></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">XLS appendix submitted</note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">Page header contains: module title; assignment title. 
 </note><note resp="British Academic Written English (BAWE) corpus project">Running text contains reference to external or missing appendix.
</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p n="level">4</p><p n="date">2007-02</p><p n="module title">Strategic management</p><p n="module code">P</p><p n="genre family">Critique</p><p n="discipline">Hospitality, Leisure &amp; Tourism Management</p><p n="disciplinary group">SS</p><p n="grade">unknown</p><p n="number of authors">1</p><p n="number of words">5549</p><p n="number of s-units">176</p><p n="number of p">38</p><p n="number of tables">0</p><p n="number of figures">0</p><p n="number of block quotes">0</p><p n="number of formulae">0</p><p n="number of lists">0</p><p n="number of paragraphs formatted like lists">0</p><p n="abstract present">no abstract</p><p n="average words per s-unit">31.5</p><p n="average s-units per p">4.6</p><p n="macrotype of assignment">simple assignment</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><p>TEI P4 (documented in: BAWE.documentation.pdf)</p></encodingDesc><profileDesc><particDesc><person><p n="gender">f</p><p n="year of birth">1982</p><p n="first language">Chinese unspecified</p><p n="education">OSa</p><p n="course">MSc International Hotel and Tourism Marketing Management</p><p n="student ID">3073</p></person></particDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><front><titlePage><docTitle><titlePart>Hotel Sector in North America <hi rend="bold"> Environmental Scanning--PESTE</hi></titlePart></docTitle></titlePage></front><body><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Political</head><p n="p1.38"><s n="s1.11;p1.38">Both the US and Canada enjoy high government stability (Appendix 1) (World Bank, 2007). </s><s n="s2.11;p1.38">Regarding to the promotion of competition and economic efficiency, US antitrust laws apply equally to both the foreign and domestic corporate sectors, however in Canada these are less specific and involve less industries (AWWA, 2007). </s><s n="s3.11;p1.38">US corporate tax rates are lower compared to those in other industrialised countries (Appendix 1), however, different states and municipalities often assess special taxes on hotel and motel lodging (Country Commerce, 2006). </s><s n="s4.11;p1.38">The same rate is currently higher in Canada (Appendix 1), however government is planning to lower it by 2010 (Country Commerce, 2006), therefore creating favourable conditions for the hotel sector's development (IMF, 2006). </s><s n="s5.11;p1.38">Both governments offer a range of incentives, such as tax exemption or deduction, loan guarantee and employee grants (Appendix 1), though these are mainly industry and regional specific, and exclude the hotel sector (Country Commerce, 2006), giving less support and posing barriers to its development (Appendix 2). </s><s n="s6.11;p1.38">With a liberal trade regime, most industries in the US are open to foreign investors and there are comparatively less barriers for these to enter the market (Country Review, 2007). </s><s n="s7.11;p1.38">However, in comparison, Canada has relatively stricter policies regarding foreign investment with much less foreign-owned companies (Country Review, 2007) (Appendix 1). </s><s n="s8.11;p1.38">Employment and labour legislation, but especially equal opportunity laws, predominate heavily in both the US and Canada, however, in the former there are generally no contracts between the employer and the employee (Country Commerce, 2006), justifying high labour turnover. </s><s n="s9.11;p1.38">This has always posed an issue and a source of conflict in the hotel sector. </s><s n="s10.11;p1.38">Further unrest comes from the threat of terrorism. </s><s n="s11.11;p1.38">Hotels are known targets and with its danger growing every year, this region, and especially the US, remains a prime target of terrorists (Cetron, 2006), which may possibly affect the sector and popularity of the region. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Economical</head><p n="p2.38"><s n="s1.7;p2.38">The North American economy has maintained stable rates of growth over the past two years (IMF, 2006; Appendix 1), mainly due to business non-residential investments, and personal expenditure which, nonetheless, have been counterbalanced with decreased investment in residential construction (BEA, 2007; BBC, 2007). </s><s n="s2.7;p2.38">Personal expenditure was particularly significant in the US with rising GNI levels and per capita also enhancing the strength and power of both economies (Appendix 1). </s><s n="s3.7;p2.38">Rises in services' gross domestic product and personal disposable income prove the demand for accommodation and food services (Appendix 1). </s><s n="s4.7;p2.38">Added proof of the industry's high and economic contribution is the increase in US international tourism arrivals and receipts (UNWTO, 2006) (Appendix 1). </s><s n="s5.7;p2.38">Though inflation has increased (Appendix 1), it is being controlled by both countries and maintained within targets so to ensure price stability, provide opportunities for and reflect economic growth (Bank of Canada, 2007). </s><s n="s6.7;p2.38">This control reassures the hotel sector that prices and wages will not be increased in face of domestic financial pressures. </s><s n="s7.7;p2.38">This confidence reinforces lower inflation, allowing for long-term planning and ensuring that investments will not lose significant value over the years (Bank of Canada, 2007). </s></p><p n="p3.38"><s n="s1.3;p3.38">The Canadian dollar's revaluation may constrain the country's export potential (rising prices for international traders), yet this is counteracted by rising domestic demand and opportunities for hotels to expand domestically (FXCM, 2006). </s><s n="s2.3;p3.38">The combination of controlled inflation, money supply and interest rates align consumer expenditure power and price stability (Bank of Canada, 2007), hence attracting lasting business in a steady economy. </s><s n="s3.3;p3.38">Adding to corporate tax reduction, the ease of starting a business and lack of wage and price controls (Appendix 1) encourage hotel development. </s></p><p n="p4.38"><s n="s1.2;p4.38">Unemployment has remained relatively unchanged and the increase in jobs in the accommodation/food services industries (Statistics Canada, 2007c) has proven one of the main contributors to Canada's record high in employment. </s><s n="s2.2;p4.38">Considerable increases are seen in the same sector in the US (Appendix 1). </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Socio-cultural Environment</head><p n="p5.38"><s n="s1.5;p5.38">Population growth rates in both Canada and the US have declined since the 1950s with relatively low annual averages of about or less than 1% between 2001 to 2006 (Country Profile, 2006). </s><s n="s2.5;p5.38">However, against this backdrop, birth rates in ethnic minority communities are high, thus showing the region's cultural diversity. </s><s n="s3.5;p5.38">The significantly aging population (Appendix 1) is caused by rising numbers of those aged over 65, and longer life expectancy (Country Profile, 2006). </s><s n="s4.5;p5.38">Younger generations (Gen-X and Gen-Y) (Appendix 1) are also exerting their influence on patterns of change, shaping social trends, consumer demands and levels of affluence (ISHC, 2007) as their fast paced lifestyles (Orbitz, 2007) may reveal the shortening of business and leisure travels but the need for more luxurious hotel experiences. </s><s n="s5.5;p5.38">Both trends affect the availability of human resources, concept development, design, the influence and application of technology and the characteristics of the guest experience. </s></p><p n="p6.38"><s n="s1.2;p6.38">Most of the population in this region is concentrated in urban areas in eastern US, adjacent parts of Ontario and Québec and the US Pacific coast (Encarta, 2007). </s><s n="s2.2;p6.38">However, the recent economic boost in western Canada and south-western US indicate a regional shift in population to the sparsely or moderately populated west and south parts, affecting the distribution and location of hotel development. </s></p><p n="p7.38"><s n="s1.2;p7.38">Both countries have high living standards as well as highly developed education and health systems, which prompt the population to have high career expectations (UN, 2006). </s><s n="s2.2;p7.38">Rapid technological development and the expansion of e-commerce have significantly changed lifestyles in North America with online shopping and booking becoming one of the most popular means of purchasing (Country Commerce, 2006). </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Technological Environment</head><p n="p8.38"><s n="s1.4;p8.38">North America has consistently maintained the leading role in the field of technological progress (Eule, 2006) as both the government and industry make great efforts on various types of research and development (Appendix 1). </s><s n="s2.4;p8.38">Comparatively to the US, Canada allocates less of its budget to technological development but places more emphasis on environmental concerns and energy efficiency. </s><s n="s3.4;p8.38">The US also actively takes part in technological development and its energy saving program, encouraging increasing partnerships with the hotel sector (Appendix 1) (Energy Star, 2005). </s><s n="s4.4;p8.38">Given the close relationship between the two countries, the sharing of intelligence and technology between them is positive and prompt, greatly benefiting research and development (Wilsoncenter, 2007), and establishing the region as the hub for technology innovation and contributing to the hotel sector's advancement. </s></p><p n="p9.38"><s n="s1.3;p9.38">The Internet has changed the hotel sector's distribution channels, advertising medium and consumer purchasing habits (Appendix 1), having increased online booking (Hitwise, 2007), and led to a shift in hotel strategies towards direct reservation systems (Hospitality eBusiness Strategies, 2004). </s><s n="s2.3;p9.38">Further, hi-tech in-room features are also a prime focus of hospitality technology development (Hotel Online, 2005) within the phenomenon of modern interior design, aimed at satisfying and impressing customers with the latest developments (Hotel News Resources, 2005). </s><s n="s3.3;p9.38">With regards to room infrastructure, bathroom maintenance and innovation require special attention and action from hoteliers in the U.S and Canada, as it is an area where customer dissatisfaction mostly stems from (Appendix 1). </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Ecological</head><p n="p10.38"><s n="s1.4;p10.38">Canada is an important oil exporter (Appendix 1), and natural gas is significantly used in several industries and sectors, including hotels (EIA, 2004). </s><s n="s2.4;p10.38">The significantly high energy consumption in the region is attributed to geographical vastness, cold climate, high living standards, low cost and high availability of energy (EIA, 2004). </s><s n="s3.4;p10.38">Consequently, Canada is determined to improve its environmental position and thus renewable energy sources are fast gaining pace and currently above the average rate of high income countries (World Bank, 2006)(Appendix 1). </s><s n="s4.4;p10.38">It is highly likely that both governments will soon take a stronger position on climate change (The White House, 2007; EIA, 2004) with significant policies, rules and regulations on waste, pollution and energy, and therefore the hotel sector will be forced to change its ways and adopt more environmentally-friendly approaches to its operations. </s></p><p n="p11.38"><s n="s1.2;p11.38">The sector is also particularly sensitive to natural disasters and human conflicts. </s><s n="s2.2;p11.38">However, through advanced economies of scale and the experience of 9/11, the North American industry has shown its rapid response to crises and the ability to speedily recover, which enforced by local communities' constant eagerness and planning in crisis management (Ernst &amp; Young, 2007), reassure developers, despite increasing threats of disasters, of the sector's efficient coping with volatile conditions. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Five Forces</head><div2><head rend="bold">Threats of new entrants</head><p n="p12.38"><s n="s1.4;p12.38">There is a medium threat and evidence of entrants in the hotel sector in North America (Rosszell, 2006; Beasley, 2007). </s><s n="s2.4;p12.38">This comes as a response to increasing demand (Appendix 1) and still reasonable construction costs (Rosszell, 2006), though the latter is only evidenced in Canada, therefore attracting previously regional companies. </s><s n="s3.4;p12.38">Groups such as Taj Hotels, Shangri-La and Jumeirah have already started their expansion in the west and brands undergoing fast expansion and consolidation in Europe, Africa and Middle East, such as Rotana, Oberoi and Rezidor, may be just a step away from expanding further into other markets including North America, though this may be hindered by Canada's strict policies on foreign investment. </s><s n="s4.4;p12.38">Although a major increase in hotel room supply may suggest negative effects on RevPAR, this is counterbalanced in Canada by the significantly rising demand (Rosszell, 2006), which in turn will further attract, not only new companies to open sites in the country but also existing brands to enter the market with innovative hotel concepts (Appendix 2). </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">Bargaining power of buyers</head><p n="p13.38"><s n="s1.8;p13.38">Buyers have a medium to high bargaining power in the hotel sector in North America. </s><s n="s2.8;p13.38">On one hand, ruinous price competition ultimately leads to low or even non-existent margins, thus consumers no longer expect price increases on a regular basis. </s><s n="s3.8;p13.38">Given the impact of discount booking from travel agencies and internet selling, consumers are more price-sensitive and expect these to fall (Deloitte, 2007). </s><s n="s4.8;p13.38">On the other, the development of hi-tech, internet and telecommunication, enable consumers to access full information on products and services, read reviews, and compare prices (Deloitte, 2007). </s><s n="s5.8;p13.38">The combination of these presents a high bargaining power of buyers. </s><s n="s6.8;p13.38">Nonetheless, this is counterbalanced by the strong growth of RevPAR, room occupancy and total industry revenue in the region (Appendix 2). </s><s n="s7.8;p13.38">Moreover, the new passport requirements for American and Canadian travellers that went into effect in January 2007 (Travel State Gov, 2007) may discourage outbound trips to the Caribbean and Mexico, and encourage domestic getaways, thus additionally increasing room demand (Ernst &amp; Young, 2007). </s><s n="s8.8;p13.38">An added indication of strong hotel demand is the region's significant share in the international tourism receipts and business travel (AH&amp;LA, 2007) which further decrease buyer's bargaining power. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">Threat of potential substitute products and services</head><p n="p14.38"><s n="s1.5;p14.38">Given the recent high and favourable conditions of the hotel sector, there is a substantial threat of potential substitute products and services (Ernst &amp; Young, 2007; Hotel Executive Insider, 2006). </s><s n="s2.5;p14.38">The strong possibility of rising construction costs in Canada (HVS Intl, 2006), given the trend in the US, suggests and strengthens the probability of alternative sources of accommodation entering the sector and therefore posing significant threats. </s><s n="s3.5;p14.38">North American tourists, who account for the most lucrative segment (Reuters, 2007a), are increasingly seeking online information about other forms of accommodation, e.g. self-service camping, fully- and partly- owned holiday accommodation, timeshare arrangement, and holiday rentals (Hitwise, 2007). </s><s n="s4.5;p14.38">Already there is evidence in the industry of emerging alternatives with booming condominium hotels in North America and major players emerging with their own brands of mixed concepts (Lodging Hospitality, 2006). </s><s n="s5.5;p14.38">With recent developments and popularity of the 'green travel' concept, the usage of advanced video conference service appears to be another potential substitute for the sector, saving companies' time and costs as well as preserving the environment (Hotel News Resources, 2007), therefore intensifying the bargaining power of substitute accommodation and services (Reuters, 2007a). </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">Bargaining power of suppliers</head><p n="p15.38"><s n="s1.7;p15.38">Suppliers have a medium bargaining power in the North American hotel sector. </s><s n="s2.7;p15.38">Given the industry's successful performance in 2006, its current high (Baird, 2007; Ernst &amp;Young, 2007; Deloitte, 2007) and the overwhelming amount of private investment over the past decade, in addition to its cash flow generating ability and significant real estate value, the hotel sector will continue to attract relatively substantial project funding, which in turn suggests a low supplier bargaining power. </s><s n="s3.7;p15.38">However, this is counterbalanced by the double-digit increase in recent operational and energy costs due to rising environmental concern, property tax increase (Appendix 1) and escalating insurance costs (Ernst &amp; Young, 2007). </s><s n="s4.7;p15.38">High unionization (Rushmore, 2006), especially in North America, is a source of increased supplier bargaining power, where in 2004, UNITE<ref target="BAWE_3073c-ftnote.001"/> and HERE<ref target="BAWE_3073c-ftnote.002"/> merged to form UNITE HERE, currently representing more than 100,000 hotel workers in the region and pressing to consolidate labour contracts (Ernst&amp;Young, 2005). </s><s n="s5.7;p15.38">Consequently, this will greatly contribute to wage negotiation, compensation, employee welfare and have an impact on hotels' operating margin. </s><s n="s6.7;p15.38">In addition, an aging population, long working hours with lower pay than other industries and the lack of emphasis on staff training (ISHC, 2007), make the hotel industry less attractive to the labour force and suggest a high bargaining power of employees. </s><s n="s7.7;p15.38">Nonetheless, this is counterbalanced with the increase of outsourcing companies in technology, engineering and catering services (Imam, 2007) which increase the sector's choice of outsourcing organizations and lower the bargaining power of the suppliers. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3073c-ftnote.001"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">UNITE is formerly the Union of Needle trades, Textiles and Industrial Employees. </s></p></note><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3073c-ftnote.002"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">HERE is Hotel Employees and Restaurant Employees International Union. </s></p></note></div2><div2><head rend="bold">Industry Rivalry between Competitors</head><p n="p16.38"><s n="s1.5;p16.38">There are several elements influencing the level of competition in the sector. </s><s n="s2.5;p16.38">Considering the forces above, it seems there is high competition between the sector's players. </s><s n="s3.5;p16.38">However, when taking into account that the industry's ecocycle is currently at its stage of maturity (Hotel Executive Insider, 2006; Higley, 2007) it appears that competition is based more on perfecting effectiveness, reorganizing operations and distributing resources so to help guarantee more certain and lasting results. </s><s n="s4.5;p16.38">Given that most groups operating in North America have firmly established themselves in the industry with extended portfolios and significant economies of scale, focus moves to differentiating within the sector and through constant product and service diversification. </s><s n="s5.5;p16.38">Therefore, though there is competition between the main players, there is also co-existence between hotel groups and cooperation between brands within the same group. </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Conclusion</head><p n="p17.38"><s n="s1.6;p17.38">The region's economic stability is counterbalanced by a mature stage of its ecocyle which suggests a possible decline in coming years. </s><s n="s2.6;p17.38">Also, the threat of terrorism is ever-present and in addition to new passport requirements, generates some political instability, which together with Canada's restrictions on foreign investment may negatively affect stakeholders. </s><s n="s3.6;p17.38">Nonetheless, the region's free market economy, high levels of diversity, changing demographics and lifestyles, significant investment in technological research and development of renewable sources of energy make it attractive to investors. </s><s n="s4.6;p17.38">Further, increased outsourcing and interest by private investors help counterbalance mounting costs of suppliers and high levels of unionization. </s><s n="s5.6;p17.38">Changing demographics, lifestyles and rising demand from consumers who are increasingly price-sensitive and knowledgeable about products and services, as well as the threat of stricter environmental policies, also pose a danger of emerging substitute products and services. </s><s n="s6.6;p17.38">The combination of opportunities and threats in addition to evident co-existence and cooperation between companies themselves and the sector and other industries indicate its current high and make it favourable for further growth and development. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head><hi rend="bold">Critical Success Factors</hi><ref target="BAWE_3073c-ftnote.003"/><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3073c-ftnote.003"><p n="pn1.1"> Given the interdependence and connectivity between the 3 C's some elements, though included in a particular C may indeed overlap into another</p></note></head><div2><head rend="bold">Corporation</head><p n="p18.38"><s n="s1.7;p18.38">The inclusion of technology is an essential requirement in operations, infrastructures, facilities and services. </s><s n="s2.7;p18.38">It is also crucial for online reservations systems to compete with and eliminate intermediaries and assists in establishing networks with stakeholders in macro and task environments to get a sense of the landscape, explore and exploit change indicators and respond efficiently. </s><s n="s3.7;p18.38">Further, and given modern turbulent business environments, a flexible business approach is key, enabling an awareness of external and internal indicators of change and a continuous and efficient cost benefit analysis, which will ultimately make adaptation to and co-evolution with changes easier, thus enhancing the probability of success (Ohmae, 1982). </s><s n="s4.7;p18.38">Precise timing in applying change is also crucial, as lack of it reveals the inability to tap into ongoing trends. </s><s n="s5.7;p18.38">As for company culture and values, a new approach contributing to community development and environmental causes yet placing customers first, is key. </s><s n="s6.7;p18.38">Integrity, ethics, respect and cooperation add to a strong company culture, concur with ideals held by guests and build strong relations with local communities. </s><s n="s7.7;p18.38">Also vital are economies of scale and knowledge as they reduce costs and tackle all operational features of both consumer and competitors' needs (Ohmae, 1982). </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">Competitors </head><p n="p19.38"><s n="s1.3;p19.38">Competitors must be regarded holistically but also in detail, analysing their alternative sources of profit, capabilities and resources, which may trigger changes in customer and corporation elements (Ohmae, 1982). </s><s n="s2.3;p19.38">Marketing strategies and sound brand image/recognition, loyalty programmes including unique features and strategic alliances with other companies are crucial to differentiate companies in the same sector; currently, web design has become fundamental to portray the right image and impressions, and efficient market research a vital tool to achieve it. </s><s n="s3.3;p19.38">Further, increasing mobility of loyal consumers, fierce competition and rapid expansion make it fundamental to be globally present and have properties in key locations. </s></p></div2><div2><head rend="bold">Customers</head><p n="p20.38"><s n="s1.1;p20.38">Though Ohmae (1982) states it is crucial to reach as many target segments as possible, the importance may not necessarily lie in targeting different markets (luxury, mid-market, budget) but in pursuing as many sub-segments in one market as possible through a range of diversified services and products that meet everyone's needs<ref target="BAWE_3073c-ftnote.004"/>. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3073c-ftnote.004"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.2;pn1.1">Several companies aiming solely at one market (especially luxury) with only one brand (e.g. </s><s n="s2.2;pn1.1">Four Seasons), are now developing luxury serviced-residences and vacation ownership as a result of changing needs and trends, therefore maximizing the potential latent in different segments within the same market. </s></p></note><p n="p21.38"><s n="s1.4;p21.38">Globalization has brought some convergence in tastes, needs and wants, to which global companies respond similarly, thus enabling "functional differentiation" (Ohmae, 1982: p.97) which is achievable once a relatively dependable set of customers and competitors with comparable requirements is formed. </s><s n="s2.4;p21.38">Concurrently, global consumer segments are emerging, competitors are focused on global presence, responding to the needs of as many customers as possible, and developing their strengths primarily around comparable elements (e.g. superior service, prime locations, customization, diversified portfolios of products and services). </s><s n="s3.4;p21.38">Therefore, competitive advantage and differentiation through the use of technology or further distribution becomes a reality. </s><s n="s4.4;p21.38">The key is the ability to view customers, competitors and the organization holistically, interconnected and interdependent, whilst trying to affect the relationships thereof so to increase the company's differentiation and advantage over competition (Ohmae, 1982). </s></p></div2></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Innovation</head><p n="p22.38"><s n="s1.2;p22.38">Innovation in the hotel sector appears to be heavily based on new concepts from other industries (e.g technology, fashion, design, manufacturing and textile) which are then transferred and adapted to the sector. </s><s n="s2.2;p22.38">Given its high dependence on the transformations of other industries, the hotel sector therefore primarily reflects emerging trends, e.g. new food design and composition (trends in organic ingredients, healthy eating), communication facilities in rooms (Appendix 3) and changes in the economy (reflected in price shifts and cost control). </s></p><p n="p23.38"><s n="s1.7;p23.38">The mature stage of the sector's ecocycle signifies that companies are now focusing on improving efficiency levels, restructuring procedures and re-allocating resources in order to ensure predictable outcomes, therefore leading to the continuous diversification of products and services, and a possible slowdown in innovation. </s><s n="s2.7;p23.38">Nonetheless, with the sector's ecocycle in account, innovation can also be viewed as a process by which small improvements in diverse areas of functioning-"functional differentiation" (Ohmae, 1982; p. 97)-can indeed assist hotels to maximize their strengths, minimise weaknesses, improve their competence and potential as well as create new opportunities for growth (see CSF). </s><s n="s3.7;p23.38">Most well-established hotel companies' have vast portfolios, with significant presence in key locations, considerable and comparable economies of scale as well as substantial congruence and profitable management of critical success factors (Appendix 1 and CSF). </s><s n="s4.7;p23.38">Those who pioneer the developments tend to be the main players themselves and this may again be justified by their significant power generated from economies of knowledge and scale. </s><s n="s5.7;p23.38">The combination of the stage of the ecocycle, economies of knowledge and the source of the main developments being from other industries, all contribute to the availability of innovation to all, and a significant degree of imitation. </s><s n="s6.7;p23.38">Also, given that the innovations are mainly from other industries, and therefore extensively accessible to all companies, consumers are not as impressed as they would be if a development stemmed from within the sector and an organization in particular. </s><s n="s7.7;p23.38">The high level of similarity between brands, their products and services indeed confuses guests (Brandimension, 2006; Ohmae, 1982), especially those who are not loyal to any specific hotel organization, and should be a cause for companies to dare to go beyond improvement, development and imitation and challenge existing practices, products and services (Brandimension, 2006). </s></p><p n="p24.38"><s n="s1.6;p24.38">A reflection of critical success factors and their importance is the development of technology and its diffusion in the sector. </s><s n="s2.6;p24.38">Innovations in this area revolve mainly around deals between global hotel brands and development companies, focused primarily on improving internet access for guests, the introduction of VoIP in rooms, and enhanced in-room facilities (Appendix 3). </s><s n="s3.6;p24.38">Technology has spread into the different departments and innovations such as hand held POS systems for food and beverage operations and mobile wireless check-in systems for the convenience of guests. </s><s n="s4.6;p24.38">In addition, kiosks with boarding pass printing, the guarantee of the cheapest online booking rates through constant monitoring of internet prices and the improvement of central reservations' systems which have enabled cutting out intermediaries, are becoming the norm (Appendix 3). </s><s n="s5.6;p24.38">Technology has also found its way into intensely personalising the guest experience, through the emergence of an interactive suite selection tool, where extended-stay guests can choose their suites, upon reservation, according to their preferences. </s><s n="s6.6;p24.38">The iPod innovation has been integrated in staff training, where mobile learning will be provided through specifically developed programs for the software and be made widely available (Appendix 3). </s></p><p n="p25.38"><s n="s1.6;p25.38">The emergence of new hotel concepts mirrors not only trends in various industries but also changes in society. </s><s n="s2.6;p25.38">Designer, lifestyle and extended stay hotels, serviced apartments, vacation ownership or partly owned residences, though a potential substitute threat, represent inevitable adaptations to ever-changing needs. </s><s n="s3.6;p25.38">They may therefore be regarded as innovations, though their impact on the sector and society is highly restricted, as these transformations show high levels of adaptation, limited co-evolution, and minimal influence and persuasion of ground-breaking change. </s><s n="s4.6;p25.38">These new concepts (Appendix 2 &amp; 3), apart from changing the guest experience, may also bring about modifications to previously established rules and regulations (e.g. the possibility of keeping pets in rooms and its probable relation to extended stays by W hotels). </s><s n="s5.6;p25.38">Further developments include the use of alternative and renewable sources of energy, recycling and composting of waste. </s><s n="s6.6;p25.38">Apart from reflecting a recent trend, these actions certainly have an ecological value attributed to them as well as reducing costs and most improving performance (Appendix 3). </s></p><p n="p26.38"><s n="s1.2;p26.38">It may therefore appear that given the hotel sector's dependence on innovation from other industries, it is merely affected by their ripple effects. </s><s n="s2.2;p26.38">However, the consequences felt by the hotel sector may pose as catalysers for increased developments in those and other industries and sectors. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Levels of Exploration and Exploitation</head><p n="p27.38"><s n="s1.3;p27.38">Competition in the hotel sector has shifted from directly competing with each other on price and occupancy to implicitly competing through diversifying products and services, perfecting performance, proficiently relocating resources and achieving customer satisfaction, so to gain competitive advantage, increase profitability and achieve corporate goals. </s><s n="s2.3;p27.38">Further, the consolidation and stabilization in the hotel industry since the late 1990s, expected to accelerate and result in 10 to 20 major hotel chains worldwide (Mathews, 1995), indicates a trend towards mergers and acquisitions as opposed to direct competition, and a consequent co-existence and co-evolution of the major players. </s><s n="s3.3;p27.38">The major internal driver for this change is the sector's mature ecocycle stage, which in general requires improving performance rather than fierce price competition, namely severe discounts, which result in zero margins and the decrease of quality and customer satisfaction. </s></p><p n="p28.38"><s n="s1.6;p28.38">The change in competition is also driven by several external factors. </s><s n="s2.6;p28.38">The development of the sector is highly dependent on the improvement of other industries, thus technological advances, the enhancement of daily products and developments in construction combine to affect the hotel sector and impel organizations to compete on the basis of adapting to innovations from other industries. </s><s n="s3.6;p28.38">Secondly, the hotel sector is substantially affected by social-cultural trends. </s><s n="s4.6;p28.38">Changing demographic characteristics of aging population, needs and demands of X &amp; Y generations, shifting lifestyles and purchasing behaviour and power, add to increased personalisation and growing concerns for the environment (Appendix 4) urging the hotel sector to compete through diversifying products and services to meet different customer needs. </s><s n="s5.6;p28.38">Further, the hotel sector is particularly sensitive to natural disasters, terrorism and political conflict. </s><s n="s6.6;p28.38">This to an extent also drives hotel groups to co-exist and co-evolve through mergers and acquisitions, in a quest to increase their economies of scale and extensive presence worldwide, as well as providing competitive advantage and a safety net for organizations when these unexpected, high-impact events occur in specific areas, and therefore maintain stability at a corporate level. </s></p><p n="p29.38"><s n="s1.4;p29.38">Considering the idiosyncratic characteristics of the sector (e.g. high unpredictability, dependence on other industries and disposable income), high levels of imitation and limited innovation, gaining temporary competitive advantage and continuously anticipating needs, identifying new trends, creating new customers and furthering relationships with existing ones is vital. </s><s n="s2.4;p29.38">Hyatt's Board EZ kiosk (Appendix 3) is an example of the first two S's where the organization partnered with a technology company and following specific market research, developed a service which anticipated guests' needs, accompanied recent socio-cultural trends and possibly attracted new customers. </s><s n="s3.4;p29.38">Hyatt recognized that guests arrive tired to hotels and want to rest (need and want), and appreciated the need for technological advancement to materialize it (identifying new ways to serve customers-existing and new-better). </s><s n="s4.4;p29.38">Customers also prevailed over other stakeholders, e.g. excessive staff may have to be redistributed or laid off, porters trained to understand the kiosks, new partnerships and contracts with technology companies and energy suppliers may be needed. </s></p><p n="p30.38"><s n="s1.3;p30.38">The lack of speed and surprise in the kiosk innovation may be justified by its adaptation from self check-ins prevalent in the airline industry (dependence on other industries) and the lengthy pursuit of its development (significant publicity before implementation). </s><s n="s2.3;p30.38">Surprise and speed disability and the introduction of innovations from other industries make novelties available for competitors to almost catch up when an innovation is just launched<ref target="BAWE_3073c-ftnote.005"/>, thus hardly disturbing the market's status quo. </s><s n="s3.3;p30.38">Hospitality organizations have the vision, but lack the capabilities. </s></p><note place="foot" id="BAWE_3073c-ftnote.005"><p n="pn1.1"><s n="s1.1;pn1.1">It can be said there is significant speed, but only in responding to developments </s></p></note><p n="p31.38"><s n="s1.8;p31.38">The kiosk innovation is too recent a development to realise how much of the three tactics it includes for market disruption. </s><s n="s2.8;p31.38">Self check-in may cause significant changes in hotel lay-outs, the use of labour force, training, job descriptions and labour costs, therefore changing how business rules. </s><s n="s3.8;p31.38">It may also suggest the need for mergers and acquisitions between hotel organizations and technology development companies, triggering competitors into binding contracts. </s><s n="s4.8;p31.38">Therefore, if its potential is fully exhausted and developed (e.g. the progression to and beyond mobile wireless check-in systems) it may disrupt the market. </s><s n="s5.8;p31.38">Signalling was present throughout the process, though it may have played in detriment to Hyatt. </s><s n="s6.8;p31.38">The implementation of kiosks in hotels was lengthy (there was a need to prepare customers), it was brought in from other industries and its development was continuously followed by the media. </s><s n="s7.8;p31.38">All this contributed to its predictability and allowed competitors to work on the process themselves, hence reducing surprise. </s><s n="s8.8;p31.38">It seems there was no effort to win over the main suppliers so to prevent competitors from catching up, appearing almost like a joint movement to introduce self check-in kioks in hotels. </s></p><p n="p32.38"><s n="s1.9;p32.38">The development of mobile wireless check-ins and boarding pass printing kiosks could be viewed as a succession of self check-in kiosks; however these are mere developments, lacking surprise and speed, involving significant signalling and therefore negatively impacting simultaneous and sequential strategic thrusts (D'Aveni, 1995). </s><s n="s2.9;p32.38">Evidence of these tactics is characteristic of hypercompetitive industries, where companies send blows almost immediately and in sequence so to disrupt the market (D'Aveni, 1995). </s><s n="s3.9;p32.38">Comparing hypercompetitive environments to that above suggests perfect competition in the North American hotel sector, as the major players all seem to be in equal advantage, there is no evidence of unusual profits for any particular company, all have access to technological development, compete relatively equally on price and quality within their markets, are globally present, have the capacity to carry-out organizational reforms as needed and break down entry barriers with economies of scale and knowledge. </s><s n="s4.9;p32.38">These in turn, relate to and support the presence of co-existence in the hotel sector and North America. </s><s n="s5.9;p32.38">Though seeming ideal, perfect competition and co-existence may pose threats to long term survival and growth, as profit margins are very limited and ultimately create an environment where markets are almost 'static' and one small disruption may have heavily detrimental ripple effects. </s><s n="s6.9;p32.38">It is therefore vital to prioritize and quickly move between priorities whilst transforming trade-offs into capabilities and tactics. </s><s n="s7.9;p32.38">This will assist hotel companies in identifying and exploring competitors' weaknesses, maximizing strengths, hence generating new opportunities. </s><s n="s8.9;p32.38">If the above concept is fully exploited, Hyatt will be in a position to temporarily gain competitive advantage. </s><s n="s9.9;p32.38">The key then becomes to make this process systematic where the company is always, temporarily, in advantage. </s></p></div1><div1 type="section"><head rend="bold">Space of Possibilities</head><p n="p33.38"><s n="s1.6;p33.38">The main patterns of change suggest developments in security, environment and socio-cultural trends as well as the increased involvement of technology in all advancements. </s><s n="s2.6;p33.38">A significant determinant of the future of the sector is its mature stage. </s><s n="s3.6;p33.38">Indications of a peak of the North American hotel sector in the next 2-3 years (Hotel Executive Insider, 2006; Higley, 2007), suggest a possible decline within the coming 5-10 years. </s><s n="s4.6;p33.38">For the next few years the main players will focus on scanning and monitoring the environment so to improve performance, though soon enough, the sector may experience essential changes. </s><s n="s5.6;p33.38">The uncertainty of who will take the initiative to disrupt the market and lead the industry, what the potential change will be and how it will affect the sector and hotel groups, generates both a high level of anticipation and latent instability at present time, and a significant threat to long-term sustainability and stability (if these indeed exist). </s><s n="s6.6;p33.38">All is left is for one company to take the step and make an innovation, the industry standard. </s></p><p n="p34.38"><s n="s1.3;p34.38">Increased terrorism fears, the dependence of the hotel sector on innovations from other industries, and the inclusion of technology support the possible incorporation of nanotechnology, biometric security and robotics in the sector (Valhouli, 2004). </s><s n="s2.3;p34.38">The hotel entrance will remain a welcoming and open space though subtly including high-tech security, e.g. cameras identifying guests through retina scans or the use of finger-print recognition to open bedroom doors. </s><s n="s3.3;p34.38">Nonetheless, technology is available to all, including terrorists, and the sector will need to further develop its tactics (e.g. different hotel layouts and construction material) if it is to protect itself. </s></p><p n="p35.38"><s n="s1.7;p35.38">At a corporate level, the inclusion of technology may lead to strategic alliances and mergers and acquisitions between hotel organizations and technology-development companies, disrupting the market, shifting the rules of the game and creating hypercompetition-no longer between hotel companies but also amongst technology-development organizations operating with the hotels. </s><s n="s2.7;p35.38">Bill Gates' acquisition of a major share of Four Seasons and ownership of Microsoft make credible a merger between the two and the creation of a seminal operating system, which could shape the market and change competition rules. </s><s n="s3.7;p35.38">Key players are ever more incorporating technological advances in their corporations, leading to cost reductions, especially labour related, and an improvement of facilities and structures. </s><s n="s4.7;p35.38">The most significant development appears to be not that of technological advancements in facilities and equipments but that of manpower replacement with technology. </s><s n="s5.7;p35.38">Though seeming progress, this trend may pose significant threats to the industry as evidence suggests a growing demand for human relations, interaction in hotels and a personalised experience, not one technology dominated (Ferry, 2005). </s><s n="s6.7;p35.38">Therefore, though the influence and presence of technology is imperative in the improvement of work processes and functioning, a balance should be found between the latter and the extent to which human interactions are affected. </s><s n="s7.7;p35.38">The hotel sector is characterised by the interaction of people and to remove this could be heavily detrimental to the success of organizations. </s></p><p n="p36.38"><s n="s1.6;p36.38">Climate change and the resulting adjustments in government policy already show their effects on the hotel sector. </s><s n="s2.6;p36.38">Not only are North American governments taking significant measures towards recycling, the use of renewable sources of energy, composting of waste and supporting hotels to go "green", but these developments are accompanying a wider trend that being ecologically-friendly is not only necessary but also fashionable. </s><s n="s3.6;p36.38">This presents the possibility of major players becoming environmentally friendly and adopting measures such as self-generation of energy or inclusion of a waste composing area which could be used to develop and supply part of the hotels' energy. </s><s n="s4.6;p36.38">Further, the constant erosion of coastlines could trigger the emergence of destinations and hotel sites in unexpected locations. </s><s n="s5.6;p36.38">The combination of technology with environmental and economic concerns could lead to the exploitation of unthought-of locations. </s><s n="s6.6;p36.38">In-land deserted regions, plains, mountain sites and deserts could all be maximized to reproduce or create new destinations. </s></p><p n="p37.38"><s n="s1.2;p37.38">Adapting to social trends is a key characteristic of the hotel sector and the emergence of designer hotels due to increasing demands of younger and educated generations could imply the creation of hotels for senior segments (Appendix 1), created under different brands, according to the financial possibilities of the segments. </s><s n="s2.2;p37.38">Changes would include innovative hotel structures (i.e. less floors), room lay-outs featuring visible indications and health monitoring devices, more space, the inclusion of transportation (e.g. in resorts, one buggy per room), more and differently distributed multi-skilled staff (e.g. knowledge of healthcare and tertiary needs). </s></p><p n="p38.38"><s n="s1.1;p38.38">This scenario proves the North American hotel sector's interconnectedness with other industries and its dependent co-evolution therewith for increasing progress and development. </s></p></div1></body><back><div1 type="bibliography"><head rend="bold">References </head><p>4hoteliers (2005). 'Fairmont check-in with kiosks'. 17 June. Available from: <seg type="URL" n="http://www.4hoteliers.com/4hots_nshw.php?mwi=1991"/> [Accessed 12<hi rend="sup">th</hi> Feb 2007]</p><p>AH&amp;LA. (2007). '2006 Lodging Industry Profile'/ American Hotel and Lodging Association. </p><p>Available from: <seg type="URL" n="http://www.ahma.com/pdf/Annual-Report-2006.pdf"/> [Accessed 24th Feb 2007]</p><p>Andrews, E.D. (2007). 'Federal Reserve Keeps Interest Rates Unchanged'. <hi rend="italic">International Herald Tribune.</hi> 31 Jan. Available from: <seg type="URL" n="http://www.iht.com/articles/2007/01/31/business/fed.php"/> [Accessed 14th Feb 2007]</p><p>AWWA. (2007). Antitrust Law/ American Water Works Association. Available from: <seg type="URL" n="http://www.awwa.org/Sections/Sectionlibrary/Antitrust.cfm"/> [Accessed 26th Feb 2007]</p><p>Baird. (2006). <hi rend="italic">Hotel Industry Trends Remain Positive</hi>. Milwaukee: Robert W. Baird &amp; Co. Incorporated</p><p>Bank of Canada. (2007). 'Canada's Money Supply'/Publications and Research. Available from: <seg type="URL" n="http://www.bankofcanada.ca/en/backgrounders/bg-m2.html"/> [Accessed 15th Feb 2007]</p><p>Bank of Canada. (2006). Monetary Policy. Available from: <seg type="URL" n="http://www.bankofcanada.ca/en/cpi.html"/> [Accessed 13th Feb 2007]</p><p>BBC. (2007). 'US interest Rates held at 5.25%'. 31st Jan. Available from: <seg type="URL" n="http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/business/6318671.stm"/> [Accessed 10th Feb 2007]</p><p>BEA. (2007). Gross Domestic Product: Fourth Quarter 2006 (Advance)/Bureau of Economic Analysis/US Department of Commerce. 31 Jan. Available from: <seg type="URL" n="http://www.bea.gov/newsreleases/national/gdp/2007/pdf/gdp406a.pdf"/> </p><p>[Accessed 14th Feb 2007]</p><p>Beasley, D. (2007). 'Hotel Sector Stable: Ernst &amp; Young'/ Reuters. 12 Feb. Available from: <seg type="URL" n="http://www.reuters.com/article/HotelsandCasinos07/idUSN0628811720070212?pageNumber=2"/> [Accessed 22nd Feb 2007]</p><p>Benchmark Capital (2003). 'High-tech Devices Put More Options on Diners' Plates'. 3<hi rend="sup">rd</hi> Sep. Available from: <seg type="URL" n="http://www.benchmark.com/news/sv/2003/09_03_2003.php"/> [Accessed 27th Feb 2007]</p><p>Brandimensions. (2006). 'Hotel branding: Using online research to drive innovation'. Available from: <seg type="URL" n="http://www.hotelmarketing.com/images/brandimensions_0106.pdf"/>. [Accessed 4th Mar 2007]</p><p>BTMM. (2007). 'Personal Disposable Income per Capita'/ Board of Trade of Metropolitan Montreal. Available from: <seg type="URL" n="http://www.tableaudebordmontreal.com/indicateurs/activiteeconomique/revenuedispo.en.html"/> </p><p>[Accessed 14th Feb 2007]</p><p>Bureau of Labor Statistics. (2007). Consumer Price Index: December 2006/ News/ United States Department of Labor.18 January. </p><p>Available from: <seg type="URL" n="http://www.bls.gov/news.release/pdf/cpi.pdf"/> </p><p>[Accessed 14th Feb 2007]</p><p>Bureau of Labor Statistics. (2007a). Employment Situation Summary/ News/ Department of Labor. 2 February.</p><p>Available from: <seg type="URL" n="http://www.bls.gov/news.release/empsit.nr0.htm"/> </p><p>[Accessed 15th Feb 2007] </p><p>CBC. (2006). 'Indepth Economy: Inflation FAQ's'. <hi rend="italic">CBC News.</hi>19 October. Available from: <seg type="URL" n="http://www.cbc.ca/news/background/economy/inflation.html"/> </p><p>[Accessed 15<hi rend="sup">th</hi> Feb 2007]</p><p>Cetron, M. (2006). 'How to protect you hotel in an era of terrorism'. <hi rend="italic">HSMAI Marketing Review</hi>. Summer 2006. Available from: <seg type="URL" n="http://www.hospitalitynet.org/file/152002734.pdf"/> [Accessed 10th Mar 2007]</p><p>Choice Hotel International. (2003). 'Choice Hotels Offers Best E-Rate Guarantee; ChoiceHotels.com offers 10 percent Less Than Other Online Rates'. 12<hi rend="sup">th</hi> Mar. </p><p>Available from: <seg type="URL" n="http://investor.choicehotels.com/phoenix.zhtml?c=99348&amp;p=irol-newsArticle&amp;t=Regular&amp;id=39500"/>&amp; [Accessed 27<hi rend="sup">th</hi> Feb 2007]</p><p>CIA. (2007). CIA World Factbook. Available from: <seg type="URL" n="https://www.cia.gov/"/> </p><p>[Accessed 12<hi rend="sup">th</hi> Feb 2007]</p><p>CNN. (2005). 'Hotels get more eco-friendly'. Available from:</p><p> <seg type="URL" n="www.cnn.com/2005/TRAVEL/09/14/eco.hotels/index.htmL"/> [Accessed 9th Mar 2007]</p><p>CNN.com. (2003). 'Vegas Hotel to Pilot Wireless Guest Check-in'. Available from: <seg type="URL" n="http://edition.cnn.com/2001/TECH/ptech/05/28/venetian.checkin.idg/index.html"/> [Accessed 4th Mar 2007]</p><p><hi rend="italic">Country Commerce</hi>, <hi rend="italic">the United States</hi> (2006). The Economist Intelligence Unit Limited.</p><p><hi rend="italic">Country Commerce</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Canada</hi> (2006). The Economist Intelligence Unit Limited.</p><p><hi rend="italic">Country Profile, the United States</hi>. (2006). The Economist Intelligence Unit Limited.</p><p><hi rend="italic">Country Profile, Canada</hi>. (2006). The Economist Intelligence Unit Limited.</p><p><hi rend="italic">Country Review, the United States</hi>. (2007). The Economic Intelligence Unit Limited.</p><p><hi rend="italic">Country Review, Canada</hi>. (2007). The Economic Intelligence Unit Limited.</p><p>The Daily. (2007). 'Canadian Economic Accounts'. 30 Nov. Available from: <seg type="URL" n="http://www.statcan.ca/Daily/English/061130/d061130a.htm"/> </p><p>[Accessed 14th Feb 2007]</p><p>D'Aveni, R. A. (1995). 'Coping with Hypercompetition: Utilizing the new 7S's Framework'. <hi rend="italic">Academy of Management Executive</hi>, Vol. 9, No.3, pp. 45-57. </p><p>Deloitte. (2007). 'Executive Report: the magazine for the tourism, hospitality and leisure industry'. January. Available from: <seg type="URL" n="http://www.hotelbenchmark.com/pdf/execrepjan07.pdf"/> [Accessed 19th Feb 2007] </p><p>EIA. (2006). International/Country Analysis Briefs/Canada/ Energy Information Administration/USA Government. April. Available from: <seg type="URL" n="http://www.eia.doe.gov/emeu/cabs/Canada/Background.html"/> </p><p>[Accessed 18<hi rend="sup">th</hi> Feb 2007]</p><p>EIA. (2004). 'Canada Environmental Issues'/Country Analysis Briefs/Energy Information Administration/USA Government. February. Available from: <seg type="URL" n="http://www.eia.doe.gov/emeu/cabs/canenv.pdf"/> [Accessed 16th Feb 2007]</p><p>Ember Press (2006). 'ZigBee Slashes Hotel Energy Costs by Up to 40 Percent'. 17 Oct. Available from: <seg type="URL" n="http://www.ember.com/press_release.html?id=94"/> [Accessed 13<hi rend="sup">th</hi> Feb 2007]</p><p>Encarta Encyclopedia (2007). Available from: <seg type="URL" n="http://encarta.msn.com/encyclopedia_761562468_1/North_America.html"/> [Accessed 10th Feb 2007] </p><p>Energy Efficiency and Renewable Energy (2006). 'Lowering Energy Use in Lodging's. 27<hi rend="sup">th</hi> Jan. Available from: <seg type="URL" n="http://www.eere.energy.gov/buildings/info/lodging/"/> [Accessed 15<hi rend="sup">th</hi> Feb 2007]</p><p>Energy Star (2005). '2005 Energy Star Program'. Available from: <seg type="URL" n="http://www.energystar.gov/ia/partners/pt_awards/2005_winners.pdf"/> [Accessed 15th Feb 2007]</p><p>Ernst&amp;Young. (2007). 'Hospitality Industry's Top 10 Thoughts for 200'7. 7 Feb. Available from: <seg type="URL" n="http://www.ey.com/Global/download.nsf/US/Industry_Real_Estate_Hospitality_Top_Ten_Thoughts_2007/$file/Industry_RealEstate_Top%20Ten_Final.pdf"/> [Accessed 25th Feb 2007]</p><p>Eule, S. D. (2006). Testimony bifore the Committee on Government Reform, U.S. House of Representatives, Hearing on "Climate Change Technology". 21<hi rend="sup">st</hi> Sep. Available from: <seg type="URL" n="http://www.climatetechnology.gov/library/2006/testimony21sep2006.htm"/> [Accessed 12th Feb 2007]</p><p>Ernst&amp;Young. (2005). 'Hospitality Industry's Top 10 Thoughts for 2005'. 5 Jan. Available from: <seg type="URL" n="http://www.hotel-online.com/News/PR2005_1st/Jan05_EYThoughts.html"/> [Accessed 25th Feb 2007]</p><p>Ferry, S. (2005). 'The Future Hospitality Professional'. October. Available from: <seg type="URL" n="http://www.hotel-online.com/News/PR2005_4th/Oct05_FuturePro.html"/> [Accessed 8th Mar 2007]</p><p>Forbes Traveler (2006). '10 Pet-Friendly Luxury Hotels'. 15<hi rend="sup">th</hi> Dec. Available from: <seg type="URL" n="http://www.forbestraveler.com/2006/12/06121502_story.html"/> [Accessed 28th Feb 2007]</p><p>FRB. (2007). 'FRB: H.15 Statistical Release-Selected Interest Rates'/ Federal Reserve Board.13 Feb. Available from <seg type="URL" n="http://www.federalreserve.gov/releases/h15/data.htm"/> [Accessed 14<hi rend="sup">th</hi> Feb 2007]</p><p>FRB. (2007a). 'FRB: H.6 Release- Money Stock and Debt Measures'/ Federal Reserve Board. 8 Feb. Available from: <seg type="URL" n="http://www.federalreserve.gov/releases/h6/current/"/> [Accessed 14<hi rend="sup">th</hi> Feb 2007]</p><p>FXCM. (2006). 'News and Charts: Currency Forecast-USD/CAD'/ Forex Capital Markets. Available from: </p><p><seg type="URL" n="http://www.fxcmtr.com/news-and-charts/currency-forecast/forecast-usd-cad.html"/> [Accessed 15th Feb 2007]</p><p>Higley, J. (ed) (2007).'State of the Industry: where are we in the cycle?' <hi rend="italic">Hotel &amp; Motel Management.</hi> Vol. 222, No. 4, pp52-53 </p><p>Hitwise. (2007). 'Hitwise Monthly Travel Category Report: Based on US Internet Usage for the month of January, 2007'. Available from: <seg type="URL" n="http://www.hospitalitynet.org/file/152002916.pdf"/> [Accessed 20th Feb 2007]</p><p>Holiday Inn Express (2005). SimplySmart by Holiday Inn Express. Available from: <seg type="URL" n="http://www.hisuitestampa.com/facilities/bath-amenities.php"/> [Accessed 15th Feb 2007]</p><p>Hospitality eBusiness Strategies (2004). 'Direct Online Distribution Has Become a Top Priority'. Available from: <seg type="URL" n="http://www.hospitalityebusiness.com/hr081903133744.html"/> [Accessed 13th Feb 2007]</p><p>Hospitality Finance &amp; Technology Professionals (2007). 'New and Upcoming Technologies Needed for GUESTROOM 2010'. 26<hi rend="sup">th</hi> Feb. Available from: <seg type="URL" n="http://www.hftp.org/content.cfm?pgid=4408"/> [Accessed 14<hi rend="sup">th</hi> Feb 2007]</p><p>Hospitality Net (2007). 'Jumeirah Announces New Global SPA Brand 'Talise''. 9<hi rend="sup">th</hi> Feb. Available from: <seg type="URL" n="http://www.hospitalitynet.org/news/154000437/4030256.search?query=jumeirah+talise+spa"/> [Accessed 27<hi rend="sup">th</hi> Feb 2007]</p><p>Hotel &amp; Motel Management (2005). 'Energy Efficiency Improves Hotel Bottom Line, Environment'. 7<hi rend="sup">th</hi> Feb. Available from: <seg type="URL" n="http://www.hotelmotel.com/hotelmotel/article/articleDetail.jsp?id=145918"/> [Accessed 13<hi rend="sup">th</hi> Feb]</p><p>Hotelbusiness.com (2006). 'Studio 6 Completes WI-FI Installation at All Properties'. 11 Dec. Available from: <seg type="URL" n="http://www.hotelbusiness.com/links/news/news_brief.asp?ID=29405"/> [Accessed 16<hi rend="sup">th</hi> Feb 2007]</p><p>Hotel Executive Insider. (2006). 'Insider: 2007 U.S. Hotel Industry Outlook: An Optimistic but Cautionary Tale'. Available from: <seg type="URL" n="http://www.hotelexecutive.com/bus_rev/pub/002/739.asp"/> [Accessed 21st Feb 2007] </p><p>Hotel Industry News (2006). 'Guestroom Energy Managament System Vendors Build on Technology Success'. 29<hi rend="sup">th</hi> Nov. </p><p>Available from: <seg type="URL" n="http://www.hotelnewsresource.com/article25337-Guestroom_Energy_Management_System_Vendors_Build_on_Technology_Success___By_Glenn_Hasek.html"/> [Accessed 15th Feb 2007]</p><p>Hotel Industry News (2006). 'New Openings for Condo Hotels, Hotel with Private Residences and Timeshares set to accelerate as the pipeline unfolds'. 14 Aug. Available from: <seg type="URL" n="http://www.hotelnewsresource.com/HNR-detail-sid-2361.html"/> [Accessed 18th Feb 2007]</p><p>Hotel Industry News (2006). 'Palms Casino Resort Unveils Plans for State-of the Art Concert Theater the Pearl'. 17 Nov. Available from: <seg type="URL" n="http://www.hotelnewsresource.com/article25205-Palms_Casino_Resort_Unveils_Plans_for_State_of_the_Art_Concert_Theater_The_Pearl.html"/> [Accessed 21st Feb 2007]</p><p>Hotel Industry News (2006). 'Wyndham to Build First Condo Hotel with Buena Vista Corporation in Orlando, Florida'. 22 Nov. Available from: <seg type="URL" n="http://www.hotelnewsresource.com/article25259-Wyndham_to_Build_First_Condo_Hotel_with_Buena_Vista_Corporation_in_Orlando__FL.html"/> [Accessed 19th Feb 2007]</p><p>Hotel Interactive (2006). 'Westin's Smoke-Free Switch on Schedule'. 13 Jan. Available from: <seg type="URL" n="http://www.hotelinteractive.com/index.asp?page_id=5000&amp;article_id=5471"/> </p><p>[Accessed 3<hi rend="sup">rd</hi> Mar 2007]</p><p>Hotel Management Network (2006). 'Does the Hotel Telephone Have a Future?'. 1 Sep. Available from: <seg type="URL" n="http://www.hotelmanagement-network.com/features/feature465/"/> [Accessed 15<hi rend="sup">th</hi> Feb 2007]</p><p>Hotel News Resource (2005). 'Hilton Hotels Corporation Launches New 'Hilton Technology Room' to Explore Next-Generation Guestroom Technology'. 2 May. Available from: <seg type="URL" n="http://www.hotelnewsresource.com/article16262.html"/> [Accessed 13th Feb 2007]</p><p>Hotel News Resources (2007). 'Portland's Doubletree Hotel &amp; Executive Meeting Center Takes Giant Step toward Sustainability'. 21 Feb. Available from: <seg type="URL" n="http://www.hotelnewsresource.com/article26375-Portland_s_Doubletree_Hotel__amp__Executive_Meeting_Center_Takes_Giant_Steps_Toward_Sustainability___By_Glenn_Hasek.html"/> [Accessed 28th Feb]</p><p>Hotel Online (2007). 'Homewood Suites by Hilton Details Core Initiatives for 2007, Includes Employee Training with Video iPods'. 23 Jan. Available from: <seg type="URL" n="http://www.hotel-online.com/News/PR2007_1st/Jan07_HomewoodEvolution.html"/> [Accessed 27th Feb 2007]</p><p>Hotel Online (2005). 'Hotel Technology Next Generation (HTNG) Making Significant Progress Towards its Objectives of Improving Systems Interoperability in the Hospitality Industry'. 21 Jun. Available from: <seg type="URL" n="http://www.hotel-online.com/News/PR2005_2nd/Jun05_HTNGrelease.html"/> </p><p>[Accessed 12th Feb 2007]</p><p>Hotel Online (2005). 'The Holiday Inn Express Brand Completing Rollout of Shower Initiative; $20 million Bathroom Upgrade at 1,300 North America Properties'. 23 Mar. Available from: <seg type="URL" n="http://www.hotel-online.com/News/PR2005_1st/Mar05_SimplySmart.html"/> [Accessed 13th Feb 2007]</p><p>HVS International. (2006). 'The Low-down on Canada's Hotel Construction High'. Dec. Available from: <seg type="URL" n="http://www.hospitalitynet.org/file/152002915.pdf"/> [Accessed 24 Feb 2007]</p><p>Hummingbird (2006). 'Fairmont Groups "Green Travel Tips" Worth repeating'. 13 Oct. Available from: <seg type="URL" n="http://hummingbird.typepad.com/hummingbird/2006/10/fairmont_groups.html"/> [Accessed 20th Feb 2007]</p><p>The Hyatt Edge (2005). 'Touch &amp; Go Kiosks: Hyatt Express Kiosks Will Help Get Business Travelers, Meeting Attendants to Their Rooms Quicker'. Summer. Available from: <seg type="URL" n="http://www.hyattedge.com/articles/2005_summer/HGM836901.html"/> [Accessed 13th Feb 2007]</p><p>Imam, F. (2007). 'Outsourcing Business in the 21st Century'. Available from: <seg type="URL" n="http://ezinearticles.com/?Outsourcing"/>:-Business-in-the-21st-Century&amp;id=119933 [Accessed 10<hi rend="sup">th</hi> Mar 2007]</p><p>IMF. (2006). 'World Economic Outlook-Financial Systems and Economic Outlooks'/International Monetary Fund. September. Available from: <seg type="URL" n="http://www.imf.org/external/pubs/ft/weo/2006/02/"/> [Accessed 15<hi rend="sup">th</hi> Feb 2007]</p><p>Irbitz, (2007). 'Do Americans Take 5 to Travel?'. 20 Jul. Available from: <seg type="URL" n="http://www.hospitalitynet.org/news/4028239.html"/> [Accessed 10th Mar, 2007]</p><p>ISHC. (2007). 'Top Ten Issues in the Hospitality Industry for 2007'/ International Society of Hospitality Consultants. 29 Nov. Available from: <seg type="URL" n="http://www.hospitalitynet.org/news/4029554.html"/> [Accessed 24th Feb 2007]</p><p>Loding Hospitality. (2006). 'Surf's Up'. November. Available from: <seg type="URL" n="http://web.ebscohost.com/ehost/pdf?vid=5&amp;hid=119&amp;sid=5b9c77dc-6d70-46c2-b28e-3a26d068a08f%40sessionmgr108"/> [Accessed 24<hi rend="sup">th</hi> Feb 2007]</p><p>Mathew, V. (2000). 'Competition in the international hotel industry'. <hi rend="italic">International Journal of Contemporary Hospitality Management</hi>. Vol. 12, No. 2, pp. 114-118. </p><p>Mintel (2005). <hi rend="italic">Hotel Technology- International, Travel &amp; Tourism Analyst</hi>. No. 11, July 2005. Mintel International Group Ltd. London. </p><p>National Research Council Canada (2005). 'New Directions and Commitments for NRC- 2006-2011'. 2 Oct. Available from: <seg type="URL" n="http://www.nrc-cnrc.gc.ca/aboutUs/corporatereports/annual_report206/index_e.html#3"/> [Accessed 13<hi rend="sup">th</hi> Feb 2007]</p><p>National Science Foundation (2006). 'US R&amp;D Continues to Rebound in 2004'. January. Available from: <seg type="URL" n="http://www.nsf.gov/statistics/infbrief/nsf06306/"/> [Accessed 12<hi rend="sup">th</hi> Feb 2007]</p><p>National Science Foundation (2006). NSF-Wide Investments. 6 Jun. Available from: <seg type="URL" n="http://www.nsf.gov/news/priority_areas/index.jsp"/> [Accessed 13th Feb 2007]</p><p>OECD. (2006). Country Profiles: Canada. Available from: <seg type="URL" n="http://stats.oecd.org/WBOS/ViewHTML.aspx?QueryName=177&amp;QueryType=View&amp;Lang=en"/> [Accessed 16<hi rend="sup">th</hi> Feb 2007]</p><p>OECD. (2006a). Country Profiles: United States. Available from: <seg type="URL" n="http://stats.oecd.org/WBOS/ViewHTML.aspx?QueryName=203&amp;QueryType=View&amp;Lang=en"/> [Accessed 16<hi rend="sup">th</hi> Feb 2007]</p><p>Ohmae, K. (1982). <hi rend="italic">The Mind of the Strategist: Business Planning for Competitive Advantage</hi>. London: Penguin Books</p><p>PKF Consulting. (2007).' 2006 Accommodation Industry Outlook'. Available from: <seg type="URL" n="http://www.pkfcanada.com/docs/pkf_brochure_2005.pdf"/> [Accessed 18th Feb 2007] </p><p>Reuters. (2007). 'UPDATE 1-SF Fed sees U.S. inflation over 2 pct far into '08'. <hi rend="italic">Reuters</hi>. 13 Feb. Available from: <seg type="URL" n="http://www.reuters.com/article/bondsNews/idUSN1317981120070213?pageNumber=1"/> [Accessed 14th Feb 2007]</p><p>Reuters. (2007a). 'Hotels &amp; Motels: Overview'. 22 Feb. Available from: <seg type="URL" n="http://www.investor.reuters.com/business/IndustryDmDescr.aspx?industry=HOTELS&amp;target=%2fbusiness%2fbussecindustry%2fbussecindfake%2fbussecindoverview&amp;page=dmdescr"/> [Accessed 22<hi rend="sup">nd</hi> Feb 2007]</p><p>Rosszell, M. (2006). 'Canadian Lodging Outlook'/HVS. December. Available from: <seg type="URL" n="http://www.hospitalitynet.org/file/152002915.pdf"/> </p><p>[Accessed 22nd Feb 2007]</p><p>Rushmore, S. (2006). 'Some Long-Term Trends that might be adverse to the Future of the Hotel Industry'. Available from: <seg type="URL" n="www.hotel-online.com/news/pr2006_2nd/June06_Longtermtrends.html"/> </p><p>[Accessed 27th Feb 2007]</p><p>Slashphone.(2006). 'Marriott Hotel Working on Mobile Wireless Check-In'. 17<hi rend="sup">th</hi> Aug. Available from: <seg type="URL" n="http://www.slashphone.com/70/5026.html"/> [Accessed 27th Feb 2007]</p><p>Statistics Canada. (2007a). Exchange Rates, Interest Rates, Money Supply and Stock Prices. Available from: <seg type="URL" n="http://www40.statcan.ca/l01/cst01/econ07.htm"/> [Accessed 13th Feb 2007]</p><p>Statistics Canada. (2007b). Gross domestic product at basic prices by industry (monthly). Available from: <seg type="URL" n="http://www40.statcan.ca/l01/cst01/gdps04a.htm"/> </p><p>[Accessed 13th Feb 2007]</p><p>Statistics Canada. (2007c). Latest Release form the Labour Force Survey. 9 Feb. Available from: <seg type="URL" n="http://www.statcan.ca/english/Subjects/Labour/LFS/lfs-en.htm"/> </p><p>[Accessed 15<hi rend="sup">th</hi> Feb 2007]</p><p>Statistics Canada. (2007). Consumer Price Index, by Province (monthly). Available from: <seg type="URL" n="http://www40.statcan.ca/l01/cst01/cpis01a.htm"/> [Accessed 13th Feb 2007]</p><p>Statistics Canada (2007). Federal Government Spending on Science and Technology. 7 Mar. Available from: <seg type="URL" n="http://www40.statcan.ca/l01/cst01/scte01a.htm"/> [Accessed 11th Mar 2007]</p><p>Travel Green (2005). 'Carbon Neutral Accommodation'. Available from: <seg type="URL" n="http://www.travel-green.org/"/> [Accessed 16<hi rend="sup">th</hi> Feb 2007]</p><p>Travel State Gov. (2007). 'New Requirements for Travellers'. Available from: <seg type="URL" n="http://travel.state.gov/travel/cbpmc/cbpmc_2223.html"/> [Accessed 20th Feb 2007]</p><p>United States Patent and Trademark Office (2007). 'Deputy Under Secretary of Commerce Announces FY 2008 Budget Proposal for USPTO- President's request provides full access to fees'. 5 Feb. Available from: <seg type="URL" n="http://www.uspto.gov/web/offices/com/speeches/07-09.htm"/> [Accessed 14<hi rend="sup">th</hi> Feb 2007]</p><p>UN (United Nations). (2006). Available from: <seg type="URL" n="www.un.org"/> [Accessed 12<hi rend="sup">th</hi> Feb 2007]</p><p>UNWTO. (2006). 'Tourism Highlights 2006 Edition'. Available from: <seg type="URL" n="http://www.world-tourism.org/facts/menu.html"/> [Accessed 13<hi rend="sup">th</hi> Feb 2007]</p><p>Valhouli, C. (2004). 'Hotels of the Future'/Travel Feature'. 27 May. Available from: <seg type="URL" n="http://www.forbes.com/travel/2004/05/27/cx_cv_0527feat.html"/> [Accessed 9th Mar 2007]</p><p>The White House. (2007). 'Open Letter on the President's Position on Climate Change'/News &amp; Policies. 7 February. Available from: <seg type="URL" n="http://www.whitehouse.gov/news/releases/2007/02/20070207-5.html"/> [ Accessed 18th Feb 2007]</p><p>World Bank,(2007). Governance Indicator. Available from: <seg type="URL" n="http://siteresources.worldbank.org/INTWBIGOVANTCOR/Resources/Governance_Indicators_eng.pdf"/> [Accessed 25th Feb 2007] </p><p>World Bank (2006). Canada Data Profile. Available from: <seg type="URL" n="http://devdata.worldbank.org/external/CPProfile.asp?PTYPE=CP&amp;CCODE=CAN"/></p><p>[Accessed 12<hi rend="sup">th</hi> Feb 2007]</p><p>World Bank (2006a). United States Data Profile. Available from: <seg type="URL" n="http://devdata.worldbank.org/external/CPProfile.asp?PTYPE=CP&amp;CCODE=USA"/> [Accessed 12<hi rend="sup">th</hi> Feb 2007]</p><p>World Bank. (2006b). Little Green Databook. Available from: <seg type="URL" n="http://siteresources.worldbank.org/INTEEI/936214-1146251511077/20916989/LGDB2006.pdf"/> </p><p>[Accessed 16th Feb 2007]</p><p>Woodrow Wilson International Centre (2007). 'Intelligence Sharing Between the United States and Canada'. 29 Jan. Available from: <seg type="URL" n="http://www.wilsoncenter.org/index.cfm?topic_id=1420&amp;fuseaction=topics.event_summary&amp;event_id=214721"/> [Accessed 15<hi rend="sup">th</hi> Feb 2007]</p></div1><div1 type="missing or external appendix"><p/></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
